<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Analyzing the green hydrogen value chain against the sustainable development goals</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Drielli</forename>
            <surname>Peyerl</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Bob</forename>
            <surname>van der Zwaan</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-27T10:09:00.084272Z">27.10.2025 10:09:00</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1007$1$s43621-024-00374-4</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1007/s43621-024-00374-4</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Drielli Peyerl, Bob van der Zwaan. (2024). Analyzing the green hydrogen value chain against the sustainable development goals. Discover Sustainability, 5(1), None. DOI: 10.1007/s43621-024-00374-4</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-27T10:09:00.084272Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-27T10:09:00.084272Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>ORIGINAL RESEARCH <lb/>Triple Combination Clindamycin Phosphate 1.2%/ <lb/>Adapalene 0.15%/Benzoyl Peroxide 3.1% for Acne: <lb/>Efficacy and Safety from a Pooled Phase 3 Analysis <lb/>Leon H. Kircik . Linda Stein Gold . Michael Gold . Jonathan S. Weiss . <lb/>Julie C. Harper . James Q. Del Rosso . Christopher G. Bunick . <lb/>Neal Bhatia . Emil A. Tanghetti . Lawrence F. Eichenfield . <lb/>Hilary Baldwin . Zoe D. Draelos . Valerie D. Callender . <lb/>George Han . Melinda J. Gooderham . Neil Sadick . Mary P. Lupo . <lb/>Edward (Ted) Lain . William Philip Werschler <lb/>Received: February 7, 2024 / Accepted: April 2, 2024 / Published online: May 9, 2024 <lb/>Ó The Author(s) 2024 <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Introduction: A three-pronged approach to <lb/>acne treatment combining an antibiotic, <lb/>antimicrobial, and retinoid may be more effi-<lb/>cacious than single/double treatments while <lb/>potentially reducing antibiotic resistance. This <lb/>study evaluated the efficacy and safety of the <lb/>first fixed-dose, triple-combination topical acne <lb/>product, clindamycin 1.2%/adapalene 0.15%/ <lb/>benzoyl peroxide (BPO) 3.1% gel (CAB) using <lb/>pooled phase 3 data. <lb/>Methods: In two identical phase 3 (N = 183; <lb/>N = 180), double-blind, 12-week studies, par-<lb/>ticipants aged C 9 years with moderate-to-sev-<lb/>ere acne were randomized 2:1 to receive once-<lb/>daily CAB or vehicle gel. Endpoints included <lb/>C 2-grade reduction from baseline in Evalua-<lb/>tor&apos;s Global Severity Score and clear/almost <lb/>clear skin (treatment success) and least-squares <lb/>mean percent change from baseline in acne <lb/>lesion counts. Treatment-emergent adverse <lb/>events (TEAEs) and cutaneous safety/tolerability <lb/>Prior Presentation: Efficacy and safety data from this <lb/>analysis were previously presented at the following <lb/>congresses: Maui Derm for Dermatologists 2023, Elevate-<lb/>Derm PA NP Conference 2023, SDPA Annual Fall <lb/>Dermatology Conference 2023, Fall Clinical 2023, <lb/>ODAC Dermatology, Aesthetic &amp; Surgical Conference <lb/>2024. <lb/>Supplementary Information The online version <lb/>contains supplementary material available at https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1007/s13555-024-01155-7. <lb/>L. H. Kircik (&amp;) <lb/>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, New York, <lb/>NY, USA <lb/>e-mail: wedoderm@yahoo.com <lb/>L. H. Kircik <lb/>Indiana University School of Medicine, <lb/>Indianapolis, IN, USA <lb/>L. H. Kircik <lb/>Physicians Skin Care, PLLC, 1169 Eastern Pkwy <lb/>#2310, Louisville, KY 40217, USA <lb/>L. H. Kircik <lb/>DermResearch, PLLC, Louisville, KY, USA <lb/>L. H. Kircik <lb/>Skin Sciences, PLLC, Louisville, KY, USA <lb/>L. Stein Gold <lb/>Henry Ford Hospital, Detroit, MI, USA <lb/>M. Gold <lb/>Tennessee Clinical Research Center, Nashville, TN, <lb/>USA <lb/>J. S. Weiss <lb/>Georgia Dermatology Partners, Snellville, GA, USA <lb/>J. S. Weiss <lb/>Gwinnett Clinical Research Center, Inc., Snellville, <lb/>GA, USA <lb/>Dermatol Ther (Heidelb) (2024) 14:1211-1227 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s13555-024-01155-7 <lb/>were evaluated. <lb/>Results: At week 12, 50.0% of participants <lb/>achieved treatment success with CAB versus <lb/>22.6% with vehicle gel (P \ 0.001). CAB resul-<lb/>ted in [ 70% reductions in inflammatory and <lb/>noninflammatory lesions at week 12 (77.9% <lb/>and 73.0%, respectively), which were signifi-<lb/>cantly greater than vehicle (57.9% and 48.2%; <lb/>P \ 0.001, both). Most TEAEs were of mild-<lb/>moderate severity, and \ 3% of CAB-treated <lb/>participants <lb/>discontinued <lb/>study/treatment <lb/>because of AEs. Transient increases from base-<lb/>line in scaling, erythema, itching, burning, and <lb/>stinging were observed with CAB, but resolved <lb/>back to or near baseline values by week 12. <lb/>Conclusions: The innovative fixed-dose, triple-<lb/>combination clindamycin phosphate 1.2%/ <lb/>adapalene 0.15%/BPO 3.1% gel was efficacious <lb/>and well tolerated in children, adolescents, and <lb/>adults with moderate-to-severe acne. Half of <lb/>participants achieved clear/almost clear skin by <lb/>12 weeks, rates not previously seen in clinical <lb/>studies of other topical acne products. <lb/>Trial Registration: ClinicalTrials.gov identifier <lb/>NCT04214639 and NCT04214652. <lb/>Keywords: Acne; Antibiotic; Antimicrobial; <lb/>Clinical <lb/>trial; <lb/>Combination <lb/>treatment; <lb/>Retinoid; Topical <lb/>J. C. Harper <lb/>Dermatology &amp; Skin Care Center of Birmingham, <lb/>Birmingham, AL, USA <lb/>J. Q. Del Rosso <lb/>JDR Dermatology Research/Thomas Dermatology, <lb/>Las Vegas, NV, USA <lb/>J. Q. Del Rosso <lb/>Advanced Dermatology and Cosmetic Surgery, <lb/>Maitland, FL, USA <lb/>J. Q. Del Rosso <lb/>Touro University Nevada, Henderson, NV, USA <lb/>C. G. Bunick <lb/>Department of Dermatology and Program in <lb/>Translational Biomedicine, Yale University, New <lb/>Haven, CT, USA <lb/>N. Bhatia <lb/>Therapeutics Clinical Research, San Diego, CA, USA <lb/>E. A. Tanghetti <lb/>Center for Dermatology and Laser Surgery, <lb/>Sacramento, CA, USA <lb/>L. F. Eichenfield <lb/>School of Medicine, University of California, San <lb/>Diego, CA, USA <lb/>L. F. Eichenfield <lb/>Rady Children&apos;s Hospital, San Diego, CA, USA <lb/>H. Baldwin <lb/>The Acne Treatment and Research Center, Brooklyn, <lb/>NY, USA <lb/>H. Baldwin <lb/>Robert Wood Johnson University Hospital, New <lb/>Brunswick, NJ, USA <lb/>Z. D. Draelos <lb/>Dermatology Consulting Services, PLLC, High <lb/>Point, NC, USA <lb/>V. D. Callender <lb/>Callender Dermatology and Cosmetic Center, <lb/>Glenn Dale, MD, USA <lb/>V. D. Callender <lb/>Howard University College of Medicine, <lb/>Washington, DC, USA <lb/></front>

			<page>1212 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Dermatol Ther (Heidelb) (2024) 14:1211-1227 <lb/></note>

			<front>Key Summary Points <lb/>Why carry out this study? <lb/>A three-pronged approach to acne <lb/>treatment using an antibiotic, <lb/>antimicrobial, and a retinoid within an <lb/>easy-to-use topical formulation could <lb/>improve efficacy and treatment <lb/>adherence. <lb/>CAB polymeric mesh gel (clindamycin <lb/>phosphate 1.2%/adapalene 0.15%/ <lb/>benzoyl peroxide 3.1%)-the first fixed-<lb/>dose triple-combination acne topical <lb/>product-demonstrated superior efficacy <lb/>to vehicle and component dyads, with <lb/>good safety/tolerability in a phase 2 and <lb/>two phase 3 studies of moderate-to-severe <lb/>acne. <lb/>This post hoc analysis further evaluated <lb/>the efficacy and safety of CAB gel using <lb/>pooled phase 3 data. <lb/>What was learned from the study? <lb/>Results from this post hoc analysis of two <lb/>pooled randomized, double-blind, <lb/>vehicle-controlled clinical studies in <lb/>participants with moderate-to-severe acne <lb/>showed that half of participants treated <lb/>with CAB gel achieved treatment success <lb/>by week 12, with [ 70% reductions in <lb/>inflammatory and noninflammatory <lb/>lesions. <lb/>To our knowledge, observed acne <lb/>improvements in these studies with CAB <lb/>were greater than any FDA-approved <lb/>topical acne treatment to date, making <lb/>CAB an effective treatment option for <lb/>children, adolescents, and adults with <lb/>moderate-to-severe acne. <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Acne vulgaris is the most common dermato-<lb/>logic disorder, affecting up to 50 million people <lb/>in the USA annually [1]. Acne pathogenesis is <lb/>multifactorial, and includes increased inflam-<lb/>mation and sebum production, follicular pro-<lb/>liferation of Cutibacterium acnes (formerly <lb/>Propionibacterium acnes), and abnormal kera-<lb/>tinization [2, 3]. As such, combination treat-<lb/>ments that simultaneously target multiple <lb/>pathological mechanisms may provide better <lb/>efficacy compared to monotherapy [4]. Fur-<lb/>thermore, combination treatments that are <lb/>delivered in a fixed-dose formulation may <lb/>improve patient adherence, and thereby treat-<lb/>ment success, by reducing treatment complex-<lb/>ity [5]. <lb/>The most recently published acne treatment <lb/>guidelines in the USA and the EU recommend <lb/>combination treatment for most patients [2, 6]. <lb/>Several topical dual-combination prescription <lb/>products currently approved in the USA contain <lb/>an antibiotic or a retinoid in combination with <lb/>benzoyl peroxide (BPO). Clindamycin phos-<lb/>phate 1.2%/adapalene 0.15%/BPO 3.1% gel <lb/>(CAB; Cabtreo Ò ; Ortho Dermatologics) is the <lb/></body>

			<front>G. Han <lb/>Department of Dermatology, Donald and Barbara <lb/>Zucker School of Medicine at Hofstra/Northwell, <lb/>New Hyde Park, New York, NY, USA <lb/>M. J. Gooderham <lb/>Queens University, Peterborough, ON, Canada <lb/>M. J. Gooderham <lb/>SKiN Centre for Dermatology and Probity Medical <lb/>Research, Peterborough, ON, Canada <lb/>N. Sadick <lb/>Weill Cornell Medical College, New York, NY, USA <lb/>N. Sadick <lb/>Sadick Dermatology, New York, NY, USA <lb/>M. P. Lupo <lb/>Lupo Center for Aesthetic and General <lb/>Dermatology, New Orleans, LA, USA <lb/>Edward (Ted)Lain <lb/>Austin Institute for Clinical Research, Austin, TX, <lb/>USA <lb/>W. P. Werschler <lb/>Elson S. Floyd College of Medicine, Washington <lb/>State University, Spokane, WA, USA <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Dermatol Ther (Heidelb) (2024) 14:1211-1227 <lb/></note>

			<page>1213 <lb/></page>

			<body>first triple-combination, fixed-dose topical acne <lb/>treatment approved by the US Food and Drug <lb/>Administration (FDA), and is indicated for use <lb/>in patients 12 years of age and older [7]. In <lb/>addition to being an antibiotic, clindamycin <lb/>phosphate has anti-inflammatory effects on the <lb/>skin [8, 9] while adapalene, a third-generation <lb/>synthetic retinoid, modulates cellular prolifera-<lb/>tion, <lb/>differentiation, <lb/>and <lb/>keratinization <lb/>[10, 11]. BPO, a mainstay of topical acne prod-<lb/>ucts, is an antimicrobial agent with mild <lb/>comedolytic and keratolytic activity [12, 13]. <lb/>Importantly, combining an antibiotic such as <lb/>clindamycin with BPO has the benefit of <lb/>reducing the risk of antibiotic resistance, espe-<lb/>cially during prolonged use [2], which is a core <lb/>goal of antibiotic stewardship recommended by <lb/>the Centers for Disease Control and by the Sci-<lb/>entific Panel on Antibiotic Use in Dermatology <lb/>of the American Acne and Rosacea Society <lb/>[14-16]. Overall, efficacy of CAB may be <lb/>enhanced by its delivery of three active ingre-<lb/>dients with overlapping mechanisms of action <lb/>that simultaneously converge on multiple acne <lb/>pathophysiological pathways (Fig. 1). <lb/>In a phase 2 study of participants with <lb/>moderate-to-severe acne, once-daily treatment <lb/>with CAB was well tolerated and led to signifi-<lb/>cantly greater acne improvements versus vehi-<lb/>cle gel and three dyad component gels (BPO/ <lb/>adapalene, clindamycin phosphate/BPO, and <lb/>clindamycin phosphate/adapalene) [17]. In two <lb/>identical phase 3, randomized, double-blind, <lb/>vehicle-controlled trials, 12 weeks of CAB <lb/>treatment led to a significantly greater per-<lb/>centage of patients achieving treatment success <lb/>and significantly greater reductions in inflam-<lb/>matory and noninflammatory lesions compared <lb/>with vehicle [18]. Across all three clinical stud-<lb/>ies, acne lesions were reduced by [ 70% and <lb/>approximately 50% of CAB-treated participants <lb/>achieved treatment success. In this manuscript, <lb/>data from the phase 3 studies were pooled to <lb/>more robustly examine the efficacy, quality of <lb/>life impacts, safety, and tolerability of CAB gel <lb/>in participants with moderate-to-severe acne. <lb/>METHODS <lb/>Study Design and Participants <lb/>A detailed description of the study designs and <lb/>methods of the two phase 3 studies <lb/>(NCT04214639 and NCT04214652) has been <lb/>published previously [18]. In brief, eligible par-<lb/>ticipants were aged 9 years or older with mod-<lb/>erate or severe facial acne (Evaluator&apos;s Global <lb/>Severity Score [EGSS] 3 or 4, see Table S1 in the <lb/>Electronic Supplementary Material), C 30 to <lb/>B 100 <lb/>inflammatory <lb/>facial <lb/>lesions <lb/>(papules/pustules/nodules), C 35 to B 150 <lb/>noninflammatory facial lesions (closed/open <lb/>comedones), and B 2 facial nodules. Partici-<lb/>pants were randomized 2:1 to receive 12 weeks <lb/>of once-daily CAB or vehicle gel. For optimal <lb/>skin moisturization, cleaning, and protection, <lb/>CeraVeÒ hydrating cleanser (L&apos;Ore ´al, New York, <lb/>NY), CeraVeÒ moisturizing lotion, and sun-<lb/>screen were provided as needed. <lb/>These studies were carried out in accordance <lb/>with principles of Good Clinical Practice (GCP) <lb/>and the Declaration of Helsinki. Study protocols <lb/>across all study centers were approved by the <lb/>same central Institutional Review Board <lb/>(Advarra IRB, Columbus, MD, USA). All partici-<lb/>pants or their legal guardians provided written <lb/>informed consent before entering the clinical <lb/>trial from which the data were derived. Addi-<lb/>tional informed consent was obtained from all <lb/>individual participants for whom identifying <lb/>information/photographs are included in this <lb/>article. <lb/>Efficacy and Safety Evaluations <lb/>Participants were assessed at screening, baseline, <lb/>and weeks 2, 4, 8, and 12. Efficacy assessments <lb/>included facial inflammatory and noninflam-<lb/>matory lesion counts and treatment success, <lb/>defined as the proportion of participants <lb/>achieving a C 2-grade reduction from baseline <lb/>in facial EGSS and a score of 0 or 1 (clear or <lb/>almost clear, see Table S1 in the Electronic <lb/>Supplementary Material). At baseline and <lb/>week 12, participants completed the Acne-<lb/>Specific <lb/>Quality <lb/>of <lb/>Life <lb/>(Acne-QoL) <lb/></body>

			<page>1214 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Dermatol Ther (Heidelb) (2024) 14:1211-1227 <lb/></note>

			<body>questionnaire, which covers four domains: self-<lb/>perception, role-emotional, role-social, and <lb/>acne symptoms. Questions within each domain <lb/>are scored from 0 (extremely) to 6 (not at all); an <lb/>increase in score relative to baseline equates to <lb/>an improvement in health-related quality of life <lb/>[19]. <lb/>Investigator assessments of cutaneous safety <lb/>(scaling, erythema, hypopigmentation, hyper-<lb/>pigmentation) and participant assessments of <lb/>tolerability (itching, burning, stinging) for the <lb/>face were each scored at all post-screening visits <lb/>using a 4-point scale (0 = none, 1 = mild, <lb/>2 = moderate, 3 = severe). Adverse events (AEs) <lb/>were monitored throughout the studies. <lb/>Statistical Analysis <lb/>The intent-to-treat (ITT) population included all <lb/>randomized participants in both studies. Those <lb/>participants who were confirmed to have used <lb/>the study drug at least once were included in <lb/>the safety population. For both studies, co-pri-<lb/>mary endpoints consisted of the percentage of <lb/>participants achieving treatment success at <lb/>week 12 and absolute changes from baseline at <lb/>week 12 in inflammatory and noninflammatory <lb/>lesion counts. Secondary endpoints included <lb/>least-squares mean percent changes in lesion <lb/>counts from baseline at weeks 4, 8, and 12, and <lb/>the percentage of participants achieving C 2-<lb/>grade reduction from baseline in EGSS at <lb/>week 12. <lb/>Percent change from baseline in inflamma-<lb/>tory and noninflammatory lesion counts was <lb/>analyzed <lb/>using <lb/>analysis <lb/>of <lb/>covariance <lb/>(ANCOVA), with factors of treatment group and <lb/>analysis center and the respective baseline <lb/>lesion count as a covariate; when significant <lb/>skewness was observed, a nonparametric <lb/>method was utilized in which data were rank <lb/>transformed prior to analysis. Treatment success <lb/>was analyzed using a logistic regression test <lb/>(using Firth&apos;s penalized likelihood) with factors <lb/>of treatment group and analysis center. For <lb/>Acne-QoL questionnaire responses, domain <lb/>scores were transformed from 0-6 to 1-7 prior <lb/>to ANCOVA with factors of treatment group <lb/>and analysis center, and the respective baseline <lb/>domain score as a covariate. For all efficacy <lb/>assessments except Acne-QoL, multiple impu-<lb/>tation was used to impute missing values using <lb/>the Markov Chain Monte Carlo method. All <lb/>statistical analyses were performed using SASÒ <lb/>version 9.4 or later. Statistical significance was <lb/>based on two-tailed tests of the null hypothesis <lb/>resulting in P B 0.05. <lb/>Fig. 1 Pathogenesis of acne and treatment with triple-<lb/>combination CAB gel. Active ingredients in CAB gel <lb/>address three of the four pathogenic factors in acne: <lb/>adapalene normalizes epithelial hyperproliferation; clin-<lb/>damycin and benzoyl peroxide reduce C. acnes viability; all <lb/>three active ingredients have anti-inflammatory properties. <lb/>Image Ó2023. Courtesy of Ortho Dermatologics. BPO <lb/>benzoyl peroxide, CAB clindamycin phosphate 1.2%/ <lb/>adapalene 0.15%/benzoyl peroxide 3.1% <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Dermatol Ther (Heidelb) (2024) 14:1211-1227 <lb/></note>

			<page>1215 <lb/></page>

			<body>Additionally, co-primary and select sec-<lb/>ondary endpoints (percent change in inflam-<lb/>matory and noninflammatory lesions; EGSS <lb/>reduction of C 2 grade from baseline) at <lb/>week 12 were analyzed for the subgroup of <lb/>participants aged 9-25 years. This age cutoff was <lb/>chosen to assess efficacy in pediatric and ado-<lb/>lescent participants, as acne in patients older <lb/>than 25 years is typically considered &apos;&apos;adult&apos;&apos; <lb/>acne [20, 21]. <lb/>Cutaneous safety and tolerability assess-<lb/>ments and AEs were summarized using <lb/>descriptive statistics. Medical Dictionary for <lb/>Regulatory Activities (MeDRA) terminology was <lb/>used to classify AEs. No imputations were made <lb/>for missing safety data. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Participant Disposition and Demographics <lb/>A total of 363 participants were randomized to <lb/>CAB or vehicle gel in the two trials (Fig. 2); all <lb/>participants were included in both the ITT and <lb/>safety populations. The most common reasons <lb/>for study discontinuation were participant <lb/>request and lost to follow-up. <lb/>Demographics and baseline disease charac-<lb/>teristics are shown in Table 1. The mean age was <lb/>similar for the CAB and vehicle gel groups (ap-<lb/>proximately 20 years), with five participants <lb/>aged \ 12 years. Most participants were female <lb/>(58.4%), White (73.6%), and had moderate acne <lb/>at baseline (91.2%). <lb/>Fig. 2 Pooled participant disposition. A total of 363 <lb/>participants were randomized to CAB or vehicle gel in the <lb/>two trials; all participants were included in both the ITT <lb/>and safety populations. a Withdrawal by a parent/guardian. <lb/>b <lb/>Includes discontinuation due to COVID-19 disruption, <lb/>lack of efficacy, and progressive disease. CAB clindamycin <lb/>phosphate 1.2%/adapalene 0.15%/benzoyl peroxide 3.1%, <lb/>ITT intent to treat <lb/></body>

			<page>1216 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Dermatol Ther (Heidelb) (2024) 14:1211-1227 <lb/></note>

			<body>Efficacy and Quality of Life <lb/>At week 12, CAB was superior to vehicle gel on <lb/>all efficacy assessments (Fig. 3, see Table S2 in <lb/>the Electronic Supplementary Material). Half of <lb/>participants treated with CAB achieved treat-<lb/>ment success by week 12, compared with 22.6% <lb/>of participants treated with vehicle (P \ 0.001). <lb/>Mean absolute reductions in inflammatory and <lb/>noninflammatory lesions from baseline were <lb/>significantly greater with CAB versus vehicle <lb/>(inflammatory, 29.0 vs 21.0; noninflammatory, <lb/>35.3 vs 22.7; P \ 0.001, each). Least-squares <lb/>mean percent changes from baseline in inflam-<lb/>matory and noninflammatory lesion counts <lb/>were also significantly greater with CAB versus <lb/>vehicle gel as early as week 4 (P \ 0.001, all), <lb/>with reductions of [ 70% achieved with CAB <lb/>treatment by week 12 (Fig. 4). For participants <lb/>in the 9-25 years subgroup, treatment success <lb/>rates and lesion count reductions were similar <lb/>to the overall participant population (see <lb/>Table S3 in the Electronic Supplementary <lb/>Material). Representative images showing acne <lb/>improvements in participants treated with CAB <lb/>are shown in Fig. 5. <lb/>For all four Acne-QoL domain scores, least-<lb/>squares mean increases (improvements) from <lb/>baseline at week 12 were significantly greater <lb/>with CAB than with vehicle (range, CAB <lb/>5.2-8.9, vehicle 3.2-5.1; P \ 0.001, all; Fig. 6, <lb/>see Table S4 in the Electronic Supplementary <lb/>Material). <lb/>Safety and Tolerability <lb/>Treatment-emergent adverse events (TEAEs) <lb/>were generally mild or moderate and more <lb/>common among participants treated with CAB <lb/>(Table 2). The most common treatment-related <lb/>TEAEs (C 2% of participants in any group) were <lb/>erythema and application site pain, dryness, <lb/>and irritation (see Table S5 in the Electronic <lb/>Supplementary Material). No serious AEs were <lb/>reported in either treatment arm. Discontinua-<lb/>tions due to TEAEs were low among CAB-treated <lb/>participants (\ 3%). <lb/>Transient increases from baseline in investi-<lb/>gator-assessed scaling and erythema and par-<lb/>ticipant-assessed itching, burning, and stinging <lb/>occurred with CAB treatment. Mean scores for <lb/>these measures were highest at week 2 (Fig. 7), <lb/>with substantial decreases at week 4, and reso-<lb/>lution back to or near baseline values by week 8. <lb/>Additionally, erythema decreased to below-<lb/>baseline levels by week 4 (mean scores: baseline, <lb/>0.57; week 4, 0.55). No trends in investigator-<lb/>assessed hyperpigmentation and hypopigmen-<lb/>tation were observed in either treatment arm. <lb/>Table 1 Baseline demographics and characteristics <lb/>(ITT population) <lb/>CAB gel <lb/>(n = 242) <lb/>Vehicle gel <lb/>(n = 121) <lb/>Age, mean (SD), years <lb/>20.2 (7.29) 20.6 (6.93) <lb/>Age, median (range), years 17 (10-48) 19 (11-44) <lb/>Female, n (%) <lb/>144 (59.5) <lb/>68 (56.2) <lb/>Ethnicity, <lb/>Hispanic/Latino, n (%) <lb/>57 (23.6) <lb/>23 (19.0) <lb/>Race, n (%) <lb/>White <lb/>169 (69.8) <lb/>98 (81.0) <lb/>Black <lb/>40 (16.5) <lb/>14 (11.6) <lb/>Asian <lb/>21 (8.7) <lb/>5 (4.1) <lb/>Other a <lb/>12 (5.0) <lb/>4 (3.3) <lb/>Inflammatory lesion count, <lb/>mean (SD) <lb/>36.9 (7.73) 37.4 (9.29) <lb/>Noninflammatory lesion <lb/>count, mean (SD) <lb/>49.4 (17.32) 47.6 (15.41) <lb/>Evaluator&apos;s Global Severity Score, n (%) <lb/>3, moderate <lb/>216 (89.3) <lb/>115 (95.0) <lb/>4, severe <lb/>26 (10.7) <lb/>6 (5.0) <lb/>CAB clindamycin phosphate 1.2%/adapalene 0.15%/ben-<lb/>zoyl peroxide 3.1%, ITT intent to treat, SD standard <lb/>deviation <lb/>a <lb/>Includes race not reported/multiple, Native Hawaiian or <lb/>Other Pacific Islander, and American Indian or Alaska <lb/>Native <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Dermatol Ther (Heidelb) (2024) 14:1211-1227 <lb/></note>

			<page>1217 <lb/></page>

			<body>DISCUSSION <lb/>This post hoc analysis of data pooled from two <lb/>identical phase 3 studies evaluated the efficacy, <lb/>safety, and tolerability of CAB-a recently <lb/>approved, innovative fixed-dose, triple-combi-<lb/>nation clindamycin phosphate 1.2%/adapalene <lb/>0.15%/BPO 3.1% gel-in participants with <lb/>moderate-to-severe acne. Compared with <lb/>vehicle gel, CAB demonstrated superior efficacy <lb/>on all three co-primary endpoints and was well <lb/>tolerated. Half of CAB-treated participants <lb/>achieved treatment success by week 12. In <lb/>addition, CAB yielded [ 50% reductions in <lb/>inflammatory lesions as early as week 4, and <lb/>[ 70% reductions in inflammatory and nonin-<lb/>flammatory lesions by week 12. <lb/>Fig. 3 Primary efficacy endpoints at week 12 (ITT pop-<lb/>ulation; pooled). At week 12, treatment success rates and <lb/>mean absolute reductions in inflammatory and nonin-<lb/>flammatory lesions from baseline were significantly greater <lb/>with CAB versus vehicle gel. ***P \ 0.001 vs vehicle. <lb/>a <lb/>Treatment success was defined as C 2-grade reduction <lb/>from baseline in Evaluator&apos;s Global Severity Score and a <lb/>score of 0 (clear) or 1 (almost clear). Multiple imputation <lb/>with the Markov Chain Monte Carlo method used to <lb/>impute missing values. CAB clindamycin phosphate 1.2%/ <lb/>adapalene 0.15%/benzoyl peroxide 3.1%, ITT intent to <lb/>treat, LS least squares <lb/>Fig. 4 Percent changes from baseline in inflammatory and <lb/>noninflammatory lesion counts by visit (ITT population; <lb/>pooled). Least-squares mean percent changes from baseline <lb/>in inflammatory and noninflammatory lesion counts were <lb/>significantly greater with CAB versus vehicle gel. <lb/>***P \ 0.001 vs vehicle. Multiple imputation with the <lb/>Markov Chain Monte Carlo method used to impute <lb/>missing values. CAB clindamycin phosphate 1.2%/ada-<lb/>palene 0.15%/benzoyl peroxide 3.1% gel, ITT intent to <lb/>treat, LS least squares <lb/></body>

			<page>1218 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Dermatol Ther (Heidelb) (2024) 14:1211-1227 <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 5 Acne improvements with CAB gel. Participant <lb/>photos showing acne improvement with CAB gel; <lb/>individual results may vary. Photographic images Ó <lb/>2023. Courtesy of Ortho Dermatologics Study Investiga-<lb/>tors. Part of this figure was previously published in Stein <lb/>Gold LS et al., 2023 [18]. EGSS Evaluator&apos;s Global <lb/>Severity Score, CAB clindamycin phosphate 1.2%/ada-<lb/>palene 0.15%/benzoyl peroxide 3.1% gel, IL inflammatory <lb/>lesions, NIL noninflammatory lesions <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Dermatol Ther (Heidelb) (2024) 14:1211-1227 <lb/></note>

			<page>1219 <lb/></page>

			<body>To our knowledge, observed acne improve-<lb/>ments in these CAB studies were greater than <lb/>any other FDA-approved topical acne treatment <lb/>or systemic antibiotic to date, though patient <lb/>populations and design may differ across stud-<lb/>ies. Specifically, percent reductions in facial <lb/>acne lesions were greater with CAB gel ([ 70%) <lb/>compared with other topical monotherapies <lb/>(range 25-66.2%) [22-29], topical dyads <lb/>(21.9-68.7%) [30-37], or oral tetracyclines <lb/>(43.1-52.2%) [38]. Further, when compared <lb/>with other FDA-approved combination topical <lb/>acne treatments with phase 3 studies that report <lb/>treatment success at week 12, CAB was associ-<lb/>ated with treatment success in a greater per-<lb/>centage of participants (50% vs 21.5-39.9%) <lb/>[39]. <lb/>The results from this pooled analysis are <lb/>consistent with a phase 2 study [17] (Fig. 8), and <lb/>with a previous side-by-side analysis of these <lb/>phase 3 trials [18], in which CAB treatment was <lb/>superior to vehicle, and was associated with <lb/>treatment success in around half of participants <lb/>(range 49.6-52.5%) and with [ 70% reductions <lb/>in inflammatory and noninflammatory lesions <lb/>(range 71.0-80.1%). In the phase 2 study, <lb/>treatment efficacy with CAB was also superior to <lb/>component dyads [17] (Fig. 8). In keeping with <lb/>these findings, a meta-analysis of acne treat-<lb/>ments found that triple-combination therapies <lb/>like CAB that include an antibiotic (oral or <lb/>topical), retinoid (topical), and BPO were <lb/>among the top two most efficacious of all <lb/>treatments assessed for both treatment success <lb/>and total lesion count reductions, only second <lb/>to oral isotretinoin [30]. <lb/>Acne onset often follows hormonal changes <lb/>during puberty, with trends toward earlier <lb/>puberty associated with increasing acne preva-<lb/>lence among preteen children [40, 41]. In ado-<lb/>lescents, acne can develop rapidly and present <lb/>as more severe disease compared with adults <lb/>[42]. Further, while patients aged [ 18 years <lb/>may be considered adults, the pathogenesis, <lb/>Fig. 6 Acne-Specific Quality of Life questionnaire at <lb/>week 12 (ITT population; pooled). For all four Acne-<lb/>QoL domain scores, least-squares mean increases (im-<lb/>provements) from baseline at week 12 were significantly <lb/>greater with CAB than with vehicle. ***P \ 0.001 vs <lb/>vehicle. No imputation of missing values. Horizontal black <lb/>lines indicate domain scores at baseline and arrows indicate <lb/>changes from baseline. Range of possible scores are 5-35 <lb/>for self-perception, role-emotional, and acne symptoms <lb/>and 4-28 for role-social. Acne-QoL Acne-Specific Quality <lb/>of Life questionnaire, CAB clindamycin phosphate 1.2%/ <lb/>adapalene 0.15%/benzoyl peroxide 3.1%, ITT intent to <lb/>treat, LS least squares <lb/></body>

			<page>1220 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Dermatol Ther (Heidelb) (2024) 14:1211-1227 <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 2 Treatment-emergent adverse events through <lb/>week 12 (safety population) <lb/>Participants, n (%) <lb/>CAB gel <lb/>(n = 242) <lb/>Vehicle gel <lb/>(n = 121) <lb/>Reporting any TEAE <lb/>66 (27.3) <lb/>10 (8.3) <lb/>Reporting any SAE <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>Discontinued study drug <lb/>because of TEAE a <lb/>7 (2.9) <lb/>0 <lb/>Severity of TEAEs <lb/>Mild <lb/>40 (16.5) <lb/>8 (6.6) <lb/>Moderate <lb/>23 (9.5) <lb/>2 (1.7) <lb/>Severe b <lb/>3 (1.2) <lb/>0 <lb/>Relationship to study drug <lb/>Related <lb/>48 (19.8) <lb/>2 (1.7) <lb/>Unrelated <lb/>18 (7.4) <lb/>8 (6.6) <lb/>Related TEAEs reported in C 2% of participants in any <lb/>treatment group c <lb/>Application site pain <lb/>31 (12.8) <lb/>1 <lb/>Application site dryness <lb/>7 (2.9) <lb/>0 <lb/>Erythema <lb/>6 (2.5) <lb/>0 <lb/>Application site irritation 5 (2.1) <lb/>0 <lb/>CAB clindamycin phosphate 1.2%/adapalene 0.15%/ben-<lb/>zoyl peroxide 3.1%, SAE serious adverse event, TEAE <lb/>treatment-emergent adverse event <lb/>a <lb/>Prematurely discontinued study drug or study because of <lb/>an adverse event (n = 1 each): mild erythema (related to <lb/>study drug); severe application site burn (related); mod-<lb/>erate swelling face, moderate application site pain, mod-<lb/>erate erythema, and mild application site exfoliation <lb/>(related); moderate application site pain (related); mod-<lb/>erate application site dermatitis (related); moderate appli-<lb/>cation site irritation (related); and influenza like illness <lb/>(unrelated) <lb/>b <lb/>All were related to study drug (n = 1 each): application <lb/>site burn (led to study withdrawal); application site pain <lb/>and application site dryness; application site pain <lb/>c All related TEAEs are reported in Supplemental Table 5 <lb/>Fig. 7 Cutaneous safety and tolerability (safety popula-<lb/>tion; pooled). Mean increases from baseline in scaling, <lb/>erythema, itching, burning, and stinging with CAB <lb/>treatment were highest at week 2, with substantial <lb/>decreases at week 4 and resolution back to or near baseline <lb/>values by week 8. No imputation of missing values <lb/>(N values shown for baseline only). Data not shown for <lb/>hyperpigmentation and hypopigmentation as there were <lb/>no trends in transient increases over time. BL baseline, <lb/>CAB clindamycin phosphate 1.2%/adapalene 0.15%/ben-<lb/>zoyl peroxide 3.1% gel, VEH vehicle <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Dermatol Ther (Heidelb) (2024) 14:1211-1227 <lb/></note>

			<page>1221 <lb/></page>

			<body>presentation, and response to treatment may be <lb/>distinct for those aged 18-24 years compared <lb/>with those aged C 25 years (&apos;&apos;adult acne&apos;&apos;) [43]. <lb/>Pooling data from participants 9-25 years of age <lb/>in the phase 3 studies of CAB enabled an anal-<lb/>ysis of efficacy in this subpopulation, which was <lb/>similar to the overall population. When multi-<lb/>ple imputation analyses were used, CAB treat-<lb/>ment at week 12 was associated with 77.9% and <lb/>72.9% reductions in inflammatory and nonin-<lb/>flammatory lesions in these younger patients, <lb/>respectively (overall population 77.9% and <lb/>73.0%), and treatment success in 48.2% of <lb/>participants (overall 50.0%). This suggests that <lb/>CAB is highly efficacious regardless of any age-<lb/>related acne differences. Moreover, delivering <lb/>three ingredients in a simple, fixed-dose treat-<lb/>ment regimen with once-daily application may <lb/>additionally benefit treatment adherence, <lb/>which has been shown to be significantly <lb/>improved when patients are prescribed only one <lb/>product versus two or three acne treatments <lb/>[44]. This is especially compelling for patients <lb/>aged \ 25 years, among whom adherence is <lb/>particularly low [45]. Notably, CAB gel is indi-<lb/>cated for use in patients aged 12 years and older <lb/>Fig. 8 Treatment success a and lesion reductions at <lb/>week 12 across CAB phase 2 and phase 3 clinical studies <lb/>(ITT populations). In a phase 2 study [17] and in this <lb/>pooled analysis of the phase 3 trials, CAB treatment was <lb/>superior to vehicle, with treatment success in around half <lb/>of participants, and [ 70% reductions in inflammatory <lb/>and noninflammatory lesions. ***P B 0.001 vs vehicle; ## <lb/>P \ 0.01, ### P B 0.001 vs CAB gel. Values have been <lb/>adjusted for multiple imputation. a Defined as percentage of <lb/>participants achieving C 2-grade reduction from baseline <lb/>in Evaluator&apos;s Global Severity Score and a score of 0 (clear) <lb/>or 1 (almost clear). ADAP adapalene 0.15%, BPO benzoyl <lb/>peroxide 3.1%, CLIN clindamycin phosphate 1.2%, CAB <lb/>clindamycin phosphate 1.2%/adapalene 0.15%/benzoyl <lb/>peroxide 3.1% gel, ITT intent to treat, LS least squares, <lb/>VEH vehicle gel <lb/></body>

			<page>1222 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Dermatol Ther (Heidelb) (2024) 14:1211-1227 <lb/></note>

			<body>as a result of the limited number of participants <lb/>aged \ 12 years enrolled in these studies. <lb/>Combination treatment with multiple active <lb/>ingredients carries the risk of increased tolera-<lb/>bility concerns. However, in this analysis, CAB <lb/>gel was found to be safe and well tolerated, <lb/>consistent with previously published findings <lb/>from the phase 2 and phase 3 studies [17, 18]. <lb/>Further, in the phase 2 studies, cutaneous safety <lb/>and tolerability assessments with CAB were <lb/>better than BPO/adapalene and generally simi-<lb/>lar to clindamycin phosphate/adapalene, indi-<lb/>cating that the additional product in the triple <lb/>combination did not worsen tolerability [17]. In <lb/>the phase 3 studies, mean tolerability scores <lb/>with CAB treatment were all \ 0.7 (1 = mild). <lb/>Most TEAEs were of mild-to-moderate severity, <lb/>and the rate of discontinuation due to AEs was <lb/>low in the CAB group (\ 3%). Several factors <lb/>may contribute to CAB gel&apos;s safety and tolera-<lb/>bility profile. BPO and adapalene in this poly-<lb/>meric formulation have been micronized to <lb/>allow for even distribution over the skin. This <lb/>improves penetration into the pilosebaceous <lb/>unit, which serves the dual function of <lb/>enhancing tolerability and improving efficacy <lb/>[10, 46]. Moisturizing agents within the gel <lb/>vehicle may help reduce irritation common <lb/>with many acne treatments containing BPO <lb/>and/or retinoids. The anti-inflammatory prop-<lb/>erties of clindamycin may also provide a mod-<lb/>erating effect on cutaneous irritation with BPO <lb/>and adapalene [8]. Finally, the active ingredi-<lb/>ents are delivered in a pH-balanced, aqueous gel <lb/>that contains the humectant propylene glycol <lb/>and is free from preservatives, alcohol, occlusive <lb/>agents, and surfactants. <lb/>Acne can negatively impact self-esteem, <lb/>social relationships, and psychological well-be-<lb/>ing, resulting in a deleterious effect on patients&apos; <lb/>quality of life [47]. Therefore, there is a need for <lb/>treatments that are not only efficacious and safe <lb/>but also improve quality of life. In the present <lb/>analysis, CAB-treated participants had signifi-<lb/>cantly greater increases from baseline at <lb/>week 12 in all Acne-QoL domain scores com-<lb/>pared with vehicle-treated participants, indi-<lb/>cating greater improvement in quality of life. <lb/>Some limitations must be considered in the <lb/>interpretation of these data. The 12-week <lb/>treatment time course in these studies is short <lb/>compared with treatment in the real world, <lb/>which may require 6 months for maximum <lb/>benefits to be seen [48]. However, the rapid and <lb/>sustained effects of CAB on moderate-to-severe <lb/>acne within the 12-week timeframe [49] sug-<lb/>gests further improvements could occur with <lb/>continued treatment, especially as both <lb/>inflammatory and noninflammatory lesion <lb/>counts continued to improve in the 4 weeks <lb/>preceding the end of the study without evi-<lb/>dence of plateauing efficacy. This pooled anal-<lb/>ysis also does not account for the fact that acne <lb/>presentation and associated sequelae can vary <lb/>across demographic factors such as skin type, <lb/>age, and sex; this may be addressed by future <lb/>post hoc analyses in subpopulations of interest. <lb/>Additionally, interobserver bias and variation <lb/>can be associated with global acne severity <lb/>assessments such as the EGSS [31]. Finally, these <lb/>phase 3 studies assessed safety and efficacy of <lb/>CAB in participants with moderate-to-severe <lb/>facial acne; this might limit the generalizability <lb/>of these findings to patients with milder forms <lb/>of acne or those with non-facial acne. Though <lb/>the study monitored truncal acne, data on the <lb/>trunk are not shown here as few patients chose <lb/>to apply study drug to these areas (neck, upper <lb/>chest, upper back, and shoulders). <lb/>CONCLUSION <lb/>In two pooled randomized, double-blind, vehi-<lb/>cle-controlled clinical studies of participants <lb/>with moderate-to-severe facial acne, CAB gel <lb/>(clindamycin <lb/>phosphate <lb/>1.2%/adapalene <lb/>0.15%/BPO 3.1%) demonstrated superior effi-<lb/>cacy to vehicle after 12 weeks of once-daily <lb/>treatment. CAB was associated with [ 70% <lb/>reductions from baseline in inflammatory and <lb/>noninflammatory lesions, treatment success in <lb/>50% of participants, and a favorable safety and <lb/>tolerability profile. These data demonstrate that <lb/>CAB gel-the first fixed-dose, triple-combina-<lb/>tion topical treatment for acne-may be an <lb/>effective treatment option for children, adoles-<lb/>cents, and adults with moderate-to-severe acne. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Dermatol Ther (Heidelb) (2024) 14:1211-1227 <lb/></note>

			<page>1223 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>We thank the participants of the studies. <lb/></div>
              
              <div type="annex">Medical Writing/Editorial Assistance. Med-<lb/>ical writing support was provided by Phillip <lb/>Lewis, PhD and Kavitha Abiraman, PhD of Pre-<lb/>scott Medical Communications Group, a Citrus <lb/>Health Group, Inc. company (Chicago, IL), with <lb/>financial support from Ortho Dermatologics. <lb/>Ortho Dermatologics is a division of Bausch <lb/>Health US, LLC. <lb/></div>
              
              <div type="contribution">Author Contributions. Leon H. Kircik, <lb/>Linda Stein Gold, Michael Gold, Jonathan S. <lb/>Weiss, Julie C. Harper, James Q. Del Rosso, <lb/>Christopher G. Bunick, Neal Bhatia, Emil A. <lb/>Tanghetti, Lawrence F. Eichenfield, Hilary <lb/>Baldwin, Zoe D. Draelos, Valerie D. Callender, <lb/>George Han, Melinda J. Gooderham, Neil <lb/>Sadick, Mary P. Lupo, Edward (Ted) Lain, and <lb/>Wiliam Philip Werschler made substantial con-<lb/>tributions to the conception or design of the <lb/>work; drafted the work/revised it critically; <lb/>approved the version to be published; and agree <lb/>to be accountable for all aspects of this work. <lb/></div>
                
                <div type="funding">Funding. The study and the Rapid Service <lb/>Fee were funded by Ortho Dermatologics. Ortho <lb/>Dermatologics is a division of Bausch Health <lb/>US, LLC. <lb/></div>
                
                <div type="availability">Data Availability. The datasets generated <lb/>during and/or analyzed during the current <lb/>study are available upon reasonable request. <lb/></div>
                  
              <div type="annex">Declarations <lb/></div>
                
                <div type="conflict">Conflict of Interest. Leon H. Kircik has <lb/>served as either a consultant, speaker, advisor or <lb/>an investigator for Allergan, Almirall, Epi <lb/>Health, Galderma, Novartis, Ortho Dermato-<lb/>logics, and Sun Pharma. Linda Stein Gold has <lb/>served as investigator/consultant or speaker for <lb/>Ortho Dermatologics, LEO Pharma, Dermavant, <lb/>Incyte, Novartis, AbbVie, Pfizer, Sun Pharma, <lb/>UCB, Arcutis, and Lilly. Michael Gold has acted <lb/>as an investigator, advisor, speaker, and con-<lb/>sultant for Ortho Dermatologics. Jonathan S. <lb/>Weiss is a consultant, speaker, advisor, and/or <lb/>researcher for AbbVie, Ortho Dermatologics, <lb/>Janssen Biotech, Dermira, Almirall, Brickell <lb/>Biotech, DermTech, and Scynexis. Julie C. Har-<lb/>per has received honoraria from Aclaris, Almi-<lb/>rall, BioPharmX, Cassiopea, Cutanea, Dermira, <lb/>Foamix, Galderma, LaRoche-Posay, Ortho Der-<lb/>matologics, and Sun Pharma. James Q. Del <lb/>Rosso has served as a consultant, investigator, <lb/>and/or speaker for Ortho Dermatologics, Abb-<lb/>Vie, Amgen, Arcutis, Cutera, Dermavant, EPI <lb/>Heath, Galderma, Incyte, JEM Health, La Roche-<lb/>Posay, LEO Pharma, Lilly, L&apos;Oreal, MC2 Thera-<lb/>peutics, Pfizer, Strata, Sun Pharma, and UCB. <lb/>Christopher G. Bunick has served as an inves-<lb/>tigator for AbbVie, Almirall, Timber, and Pal-<lb/>vella; a consultant for AbbVie, Almirall, Apogee, <lb/>Arcutis, Eli Lilly, EPI Health/Novan, LEO <lb/>Pharma, Novartis, Ortho Dermatologics, Pfizer, <lb/>Sanofi-Regeneron, and UCB; and a speaker for <lb/>and received honoraria from Allergan, Almirall, <lb/>LEO Pharma, and UCB. Neal Bhatia has served <lb/>as advisor, consultant, and investigator for <lb/>AbbVie, Almirall, Biofrontera, BI, Brickell, BMS, <lb/>EPI Health, Ferndale, Galderma, InCyte, ISDIN, <lb/>J&amp;J, LaRoche-Posay, LEO Pharma, Ortho Der-<lb/>matologics, Regeneron, Sanofi, Sun Pharma, <lb/>Verrica, and Vyne. Emil A. Tanghetti has served <lb/>as speaker for Novartis, Ortho Dermatologics, <lb/>Sun Pharma, Lilly, Galderma, AbbVie, and <lb/>Dermira; served as a consultant/clinical studies <lb/>for Hologic, Ortho Dermatologics, and Gal-<lb/>derma; and is a stockholder for Accure. Lawr-<lb/>ence F. Eichenfield has received honoraria for <lb/>consulting services from AbbVie, BMS, Dermata, <lb/>Dermira, Dermavant, Eli Lilly, Forte Pharma, <lb/>Galderma, Incyte, J&amp;J, Otsuka, Novartis, Pfizer, <lb/>Regeneron Pharmaceuticals, Inc., Sanofi Gen-<lb/>zyme, and Ortho Dermatologics; and study <lb/>support (to institution) from AbbVie, Bausch <lb/>Health, Dermira, Eli Lilly and Company, Gal-<lb/>derma, Incyte, Pfizer, Regeneron Pharmaceuti-<lb/>cals, Inc. and Sanofi Genzyme. Hilary Baldwin <lb/>has served as advisor, investigator, and on <lb/>speakers&apos; bureaus for Almirall, Cassiopea, Foa-<lb/>mix, Galderma, Ortho Dermatologics, Sol Gel, <lb/>and Sun Pharma. Zoe D. Draelos received <lb/>funding from Ortho Dermatologics. Valerie D. <lb/>Callender has served as an investigator, con-<lb/>sultant, or speaker for Acne Store, Almirall, <lb/>Aerolase, AbbVie, Allergan Aesthetics, Avava, <lb/></div>

			    <page>1224 <lb/></page>

			    <note place="headnote">Dermatol Ther (Heidelb) (2024) 14:1211-1227 <lb/></note>

			    <div type="conflict">Avita Medical, Beiersdorf, Cutera, Dermavant, <lb/>Eli Lilly, Epi Health, Galderma, Janssen, Jeune <lb/>Aesthetics, L&apos;Ore ´al, Ortho Dermatologics, Pfi-<lb/>zer, Prollineum, Regeneron, Scientis, Sente, <lb/>SkinBetter science, SkinCeuticals, Symatese, <lb/>UCB, and UpToDate. George Han is or has been <lb/>an investigator, consultant/advisor, or speaker <lb/>for AbbVie, Athenex, Boehringer Ingelheim, <lb/>Bond Avillion, Bristol-Myers Squibb, Celgene, <lb/>Eli Lilly, Novartis, Janssen, LEO Pharma, MC2, <lb/>Ortho Dermatologics, PellePharm, Pfizer, <lb/>Regeneron, Sanofi Genzyme, Sun Pharma, and <lb/>UCB. Melinda J. Gooderham has served as <lb/>investigator/consultant or speaker for AbbVie, <lb/>Akros Pharma, Amgen, Arcutis Biotherapeutics, <lb/>Aslan, Aristea, AnaptysBio, Bausch, BMS, Boeh-<lb/>ringer Ingelheim, Coherus BioSciences, Der-<lb/>mira, Dermavant, Eli Lilly, Galderma, GSK, <lb/>Incyte, Inmagene, Janssen, Kyowa Kirin, LEO <lb/>Pharma, MedImmune, Meiji, Merck, Moonlake, <lb/>Nimbus, Novartis, Pfizer, Regeneron Pharma-<lb/>ceuticals, Inc., Reistone, Roche, Sanofi, Sun <lb/>Pharma, Takeda, Tarsus, Union, UCB and Ven-<lb/>tyx. Neil Sadick has served on advisory boards, <lb/>as a consultant, investigator, speaker, and/or <lb/>other and has received honoraria and/or grants/ <lb/>research funding from Almirall, Actavis, Aller-<lb/>gan, Anacor Pharmaceuticals, Auxilium Phar-<lb/>maceuticals, Bausch Health, Bayer, Biorasi, BTG, <lb/>Carma Laboratories, Cassiopea, Celgene Cor-<lb/>poration, Cutera, Cynosure, DUSA Pharmaceu-<lb/>ticals, Eclipse Medical, Eli Lilly and Company, <lb/>Endo International, EndyMed Medical, Ferndale <lb/>Laboratories, Galderma, Gerson Lehrman <lb/>Group, Hydropeptide, Merz Aesthetics, Neos-<lb/>trata, Novartis, Nutraceutical Wellness, Palomar <lb/>Medical Technologies, Prescriber&apos;s Choice, <lb/>Regeneron, Roche Laboratories, Samumed, <lb/>Solta Medical, Storz Medical AG, Suneva Medi-<lb/>cal, Vanda Pharmaceuticals, and Venus Con-<lb/>cept. Mary P. Lupo has served as a speaker, <lb/>investigator, and/or on advisory boards for <lb/>Ortho Dermatologics, Bausch Health US, Evo-<lb/>lus, Revance, Eirion, Prolennium, Chemocen-<lb/>tryx, Therapeutics Incorporated, Brickell, Endo, <lb/>Cutera, In Mode, Revision, and Merz. <lb/>Edward (Ted) Lain has served as investigator, <lb/>consultant and/or speaker for Ortho Dermato-<lb/>logics, AbbVie, Almirall, Amgen, Arcutis, Der-<lb/>mavant, EPI Health, Galderma, Incyte, LEO <lb/>Pharma, Novartis, Eli Lilly, Pfizer, Sun Pharma, <lb/>UCB, Endo International, ChemoCentryx, Bio-<lb/>rasi, Sirnaomics, Evelo Biosciences, Concert <lb/>Pharmaceuticals, Cara Therapeutics, Castle <lb/>Biosciences, Mindera, Biofrontera, Alfasigma, <lb/>AiViva Biopharma, Anaptys Bio, Bausch Health, <lb/>Dr Reddy&apos;s, Trevi Therapeutics. William Philip <lb/>Werschler has served as an investigator for <lb/>Ortho Dermatologics. <lb/></div>
                
			    <div type="annex">Ethical Approval. These studies were car-<lb/>ried out in accordance with principles of Good <lb/>Clinical Practice (GCP) and the Declaration of <lb/>Helsinki. Study protocols across all study cen-<lb/>ters were approved by the same central institu-<lb/>tional review board (Advarra IRB, Columbus, <lb/>MD, USA). All participants or their legal guar-<lb/>dians provided written informed consent before <lb/>entering the clinical trial from which the data <lb/>were derived. Additional informed consent was <lb/>obtained from all individual participants for <lb/>whom identifying information/photographs are <lb/>included in this article. <lb/></div>
              
                <front>Open Access. This article is licensed under <lb/>a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCom-<lb/>mercial 4.0 International License, which per-<lb/>mits any non-commercial use, sharing, <lb/>adaptation, distribution and reproduction in <lb/>any medium or format, as long as you give <lb/>appropriate credit to the original author(s) and <lb/>the source, provide a link to the Creative <lb/>Commons licence, and indicate if changes were <lb/>made. The images or other third party material <lb/>in this article are included in the article&apos;s <lb/>Creative Commons licence, unless indicated <lb/>otherwise in a credit line to the material. If <lb/>material is not included in the article&apos;s Creative <lb/>Commons licence and your intended use is not <lb/>permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the <lb/>permitted use, you will need to obtain permis-<lb/>sion directly from the copyright holder. To view <lb/>a copy of this licence, visit http:// <lb/>creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/. <lb/></front>

			    <listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Bickers DR, Lim HW, Margolis D, et al. The burden <lb/>of skin diseases: 2004 a joint project of the Ameri-<lb/>can Academy of Dermatology Association and the <lb/></listBibl>

			    <note place="headnote">Dermatol Ther (Heidelb) (2024) 14:1211-1227 <lb/></note>

			<page>1225 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Society for Investigative Dermatology. J Am Acad <lb/>Dermatol. 2006;55(3):490-500. <lb/>2. Zaenglein AL, Pathy AL, Schlosser BJ, et al. Guide-<lb/>lines of care for the management of acne vulgaris. <lb/>J Am Acad Dermatol. 2016;74(5):945-73.e33. <lb/>3. Gollnick HP, Zouboulis CC, Akamatsu H, et al. <lb/>Pathogenesis and pathogenesis related treatment of <lb/>acne. J Dermatol. 1991;18(9):489-99. <lb/>4. Kircik LH. Synergy and its clinical relevance in <lb/>topical ance therapy. J Clin Aesth Dermaol. <lb/>2011;4(11):30-3. <lb/>5. Moradi Tuchayi S, Alexander TM, Nadkarni A, Feld-<lb/>man SR. Interventions to increase adherence to acne <lb/>treatment. Patient Prefer Adherence. 2016;10:2091-6. <lb/>6. Nast A, Dre ´no B, Bettoli V, et al. European evidence-<lb/>based (S3) guideline for the treatment of acne -<lb/>update 2016 -short version. J Eur Acad Dermatol <lb/>Venereol. 2016;30(8):1261-8. <lb/>7. FDA approves Cabtreo TM (clindamycin phosphate, <lb/>adapalene and benzoyl peroxide) topical gel for the <lb/>treatment of acne vulgaris in patients twelve years <lb/>of age and older. Bausch Health. Updated October <lb/>20, <lb/>2023. <lb/>https://ir.bauschhealth.com/news-<lb/>releases/2023/10-20-2023. Accessed 26 Oct 2023. <lb/>8. Del Rosso JQ, Schmidt NF. A review of the anti-<lb/>inflammatory properties of clindamycin in the <lb/>treatment of acne vulgaris. Cutis. 2010;85(1):15-24. <lb/>9. Armillei MK, Lomakin IB, Del Rosso JQ, et al. Sci-<lb/>entific rationale and clinical basis for clindamycin <lb/>use in the treatment of dermatologic disease. <lb/>Antibiotics. 2024;13(3):270. <lb/>10. Baldwin H, Webster G, Stein Gold L, et al. 50 years <lb/>of topical retinoids for acne: evolution of treat-<lb/>ment. Am J Clin Dermatol. 2021;22(3):315-27. <lb/>11. Shroot B, Michel S. Pharmacology and chemistry of <lb/>adapalene. J Am Acad Dermatol. 1997;36(6 Pt 2): <lb/>S96-103. <lb/>12. Dutil M. Benzoyl peroxide: enhancing antibiotic <lb/>efficacy in acne management. Skin Therapy Lett. <lb/>2010;15(10):5-7. <lb/>13. Waller JM, Dreher F, Behnam S, et al. &apos;&apos;Keratolytic&apos;&apos; <lb/>properties of benzoyl peroxide and retinoic acid <lb/>resemble salicylic acid in man. Skin Pharmacol <lb/>Physiol. 2006;19(5):283-9. <lb/>14. Antibiotic stewardship statement for antibiotic <lb/>guidelines -recommendations of the HICPAC. <lb/>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Upda-<lb/>ted December 28, 2018. https://www.cdc.gov/ <lb/>hicpac/recommendations/antibiotic-stewardship-<lb/>statement.html. Accessed 26 Oct 2023. <lb/>15. Del Rosso JQ, Rosen T, Thiboutot D, et al. Status <lb/>report from the Scientific Panel on Antibiotic Use in <lb/>Dermatology of the American Acne and Rosacea <lb/>Society: Part 3: current perspectives on skin and soft <lb/>tissue infections with emphasis on methicillin-re-<lb/>sistant Staphylococcus aureus, commonly encoun-<lb/>tered scenarios when antibiotic use may not be <lb/>needed, and concluding remarks on rational use of <lb/>antibiotics in dermatology. J Clin Aesthet Derma-<lb/>tol. 2016;9(6):17-24. <lb/>16. Del Rosso JQ, Webster GF, Rosen T, et al. Status <lb/>report from the Scientific Panel on Antibiotic Use in <lb/>Dermatology of the American Acne and Rosacea <lb/>Society: Part 1: antibiotic prescribing patterns, <lb/>sources of antibiotic exposure, antibiotic con-<lb/>sumption and emergence of antibiotic resistance, <lb/>impact of alterations in antibiotic prescribing, and <lb/>clinical sequelae of antibiotic use. J Clin Aesthet <lb/>Dermatol. 2016;9(4):18-24. <lb/>17. Stein Gold L, Baldwin H, Kircik LH, et al. Efficacy <lb/>and safety of a fixed-dose clindamycin phosphate 1. <lb/>2%, benzoyl peroxide 3.1%, and adapalene 0.15% <lb/>gel for moderate-to-severe acne: a randomized <lb/>phase II study of the first triple-combination drug. <lb/>Am J Clin Dermatol. 2022;23(1):93-104. <lb/>18. Stein Gold L, Lain E, Del Rosso JQ, et al. Clindamycin <lb/>phosphate 1.2%/adapalene 0.15%/benzoyl peroxide <lb/>3.1% gel for moderate-to-severe acne: efficacy and <lb/>safety results from two randomized phase 3 trials. <lb/>J Am Acad Dermatol. 2023;89(5):927-35. <lb/>19. Martin AR, Lookingbill DP, Botek A, et al. Health-<lb/>related quality of life among patients with facial <lb/>acne-assessment of a new acne-specific question-<lb/>naire. Clin Exp Dermatol. 2001;26(5):380-5. <lb/>20. Dreno B, Thiboutot D, Layton AM, et al. Large-scale <lb/>international study enhances understanding of an <lb/>emerging acne population: adult females. J Eur <lb/>Acad Dermatol Venereol. 2015;29(6):1096-106. <lb/>21. Skroza N, Tolino E, Mambrin A, et al. Adult acne <lb/>versus adolescent acne: a retrospective study of 1,167 <lb/>patients. J Clin Aesth Dermaol. 2018;11(1):21-5. <lb/>22. ClindagelÒ (clindamycin phosphate) Gel 1% <lb/>[package insert]. Valeant, Bridgewater, NJ; 2017. <lb/>23. TazoracÒ [package insert]. Allergan, Inc., Madison, <lb/>NJ; 2018. <lb/>24. AltrenoÒ [package insert]. Bausch Health Compa-<lb/>nies, Inc., Bridgewater, NJ; 1973. <lb/>25. AkliefÒ [package insert]. Galderma Laboratories, L. <lb/>P., Fort Worth, TX; 2019. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>1226 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Dermatol Ther (Heidelb) (2024) 14:1211-1227 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>26. AmzeeqÒ [package insert]. Vyne Pharmaceuticals, <lb/>Inc., Bridgewater, NJ; 1971. <lb/>27. ArazloÒ [package insert]. Bausch Health Compa-<lb/>nies, Inc., Bridgewater, NJ; 1997. <lb/>28. WinleviÒ [package insert]. Cassiopea, Inc., Milan, <lb/>Italy; 2020. <lb/>29. DifferinÒ [package insert]. Galderma Laboratories, <lb/>L.P., Fort Worth, TX; 1996. <lb/>30. Huang CY, Chang IJ, Bolick N, et al. Comparative <lb/>efficacy of pharmacological treatments for acne <lb/>vulgaris: a network meta-analysis of 221 randomized <lb/>controlled trials. Ann Fam Med. 2023;21(4):358-69. <lb/>31. Tan JK, Fung K, Bulger L. Reliability of dermatolo-<lb/>gists in acne lesion counts and global assessments. <lb/>J Cutan Med Surg. 2006;10(4):160-5. <lb/>32. Gold LS, Tan J, Cruz-Santana A, et al. A North <lb/>American study of adapalene-benzoyl peroxide <lb/>combination gel in the treatment of acne. Cutis. <lb/>2009;84(2):110-6. <lb/>33. Leyden JJ, Berger RS, Dunlap FE, et al. Comparison <lb/>of the efficacy and safety of a combination topical <lb/>gel formulation of benzoyl peroxide and clin-<lb/>damycin with benzoyl peroxide, clindamycin and <lb/>vehicle gel in the treatments of acne vulgaris. Am J <lb/>Clin Dermatol. 2001;2(1):33-9. <lb/>34. Pariser DM, Rich P, Cook-Bolden FE, Korotzer A. An <lb/>aqueous gel fixed combination of clindamycin <lb/>phosphate 1.2% and benzoyl peroxide 3.75% for <lb/>the once-daily treatment of moderate to severe acne <lb/>vulgaris. J Drugs Dermatol. 2014;13(9):1083-9. <lb/>35. Stein Gold L, Weiss J, Rueda MJ, et al. Moderate and <lb/>severe inflammatory acne vulgaris effectively treated <lb/>with single-agent therapy by a new fixed-dose combi-<lb/>nation adapalene 0.3 %/benzoyl peroxide 2.5 % gel: a <lb/>randomized, double-blind, parallel-group, controlled <lb/>study. Am J Clin Dermatol. 2016;17(3):293-303. <lb/>36. Thiboutot D, Zaenglein A, Weiss J, et al. An aqueous <lb/>gel fixed combination of clindamycin phosphate 1. <lb/>2% and benzoyl peroxide 2.5% for the once-daily <lb/>treatment of moderate to severe acne vulgaris: <lb/>assessment of efficacy and safety in 2813 patients. <lb/>J Am Acad Dermatol. 2008;59(5):792-800. <lb/>37. Tschen EH, Katz HI, Jones TM, et al. A combination <lb/>benzoyl peroxide and clindamycin topical gel <lb/>compared with benzoyl peroxide, clindamycin <lb/>phosphate, and vehicle in the treatment of acne <lb/>vulgaris. Cutis. 2001;67(2):165-9. <lb/>38. Graber EM. Treating acne with the tetracycline class <lb/>of antibiotics: a review. Dermatol Rev. 2021;2(6): <lb/>321-30. <lb/>39. Feldman SR, Han G, Callender VD, et al. Benefit of <lb/>topical combination therapy for acne: analyzing <lb/>effect size using number needed to treat. J Drugs <lb/>Dermatol. 2024;23(2):42-9. <lb/>40. Goldberg JL, Dabade TS, Davis SA, et al. Changing <lb/>age of acne vulgaris visits: another sign of earlier <lb/>puberty? Pediatr Dermatol. 2011;28(6):645-8. <lb/>41. Kumtornrut C, Yamauchi T, Koike S, et al. Andro-<lb/>gens modulate keratinocyte differentiation indi-<lb/>rectly through enhancing growth factor production <lb/>from dermal fibroblasts. J Dermatol Sci. 2019;93(3): <lb/>150-8. <lb/>42. Dre ´no B. Treatment of adult female acne: a new <lb/>challenge. J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol. <lb/>2015;29(Suppl 5):14-9. <lb/>43. Stein Gold L, Kircik L, Baldwin H, et al. Tazarotene <lb/>0.045% lotion for females with acne: analysis of two <lb/>adult age groups. J Drugs Dermatol. 2022;21(6): <lb/>587-95. <lb/>44. Anderson KL, Dothard EH, Huang KE, Feldman SR. <lb/>Frequency of primary nonadherence to acne treat-<lb/>ment. JAMA Dermatol. 2015;151(6):623-6. <lb/>45. Dre ´no B, Thiboutot D, Gollnick H, et al. Large-scale <lb/>worldwide observational study of adherence with <lb/>acne therapy. Int J Dermatol. 2010;49(4):448-56. <lb/>46. Kircik LH, Draelos ZD, Berson DS. Polymeric emul-<lb/>sion technology applied to tretinoin. J Drugs Der-<lb/>matol. 2019;18(4):s148-54. <lb/>47. Tanghetti EA, Kawata AK, Daniels SR, et al. Under-<lb/>standing the burden of adult female acne. J Clin <lb/>Aesthet Dermatol. 2014;7(2):22-30. <lb/>48. Eichenfield DZ, Sprague J, Eichenfield LF. Manage-<lb/>ment of acne vulgaris: a review. JAMA. <lb/>2021;326(20):2055-67. <lb/>49. Harper JC, Kircik LH, Gold M, et al. Early and sus-<lb/>tained acne lesion reductions with fixed-dose clin-<lb/>damycin phosphate 1.2%/adapalene 0.15%/ <lb/>benzoyl peroxide 3.1% gel. J Drugs Dermatol. <lb/>2024;23(3):125-31. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Dermatol Ther (Heidelb) (2024) 14:1211-1227 <lb/></note>

			<page>1227 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>