<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>PLOS ONE 2017 Reviewer and Editorial Board <lb/>Thank You <lb/></front>

			<body>PLOS and the PLOS ONE team would like to express our appreciation for our academic edi-<lb/>tors, guest editors, and reviewers who contributed to the peer-review process this past year. <lb/>We are indebted to volunteers who generously give their time and expertise to thoroughly <lb/>review research and advance Open Access. In 2017, PLOS ONE received the help of over 4,400 <lb/>Editorial Board members and 500 guest editors to curate nearly 45,000 submissions. Along <lb/>with the participation of 63,000 reviewers, we were able to publish more than 20,000 articles <lb/>with meaningful and impactful results. <lb/>The names of our 2017 editors that handled submitted manuscripts appear in the Support-<lb/>ing Information as S1 Editor List and as S1 Guest Editor List. Our reviewers appear in the Sup-<lb/>porting Information as S1-S5 Reviewer List. With genuine gratitude, we thank you all for your <lb/>dedicated support of PLOS ONE and our efforts to promote Open Science, thereby contribut-<lb/>ing to the scientific community as a whole. Thank you all. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Editor List. Alphabetical list of 2017 PLOS ONE Editorial Board Members. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S1 Guest Editor List. Alphabetical list of 2017 PLOS ONE Guest Editors. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S1 Reviewer List. Alphabetical list of 2017 PLOS ONE peer reviewers (A-D). <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S2 Reviewer List. Alphabetical list of 2017 PLOS ONE peer reviewers (E-J). <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S3 Reviewer List. Alphabetical list of 2017 PLOS ONE peer reviewers (K-N). <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S4 Reviewer List. Alphabetical list of 2017 PLOS ONE peer reviewers (O-S). <lb/>(PDF) <lb/>S5 Reviewer List. Alphabetical list of 2017 PLOS ONE peer reviewers (T-Z). <lb/>(PDF) <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. (2017) PLOS ONE 2016 Reviewer and Editorial Board Thank You. PLoS ONE 12(3): e0174259. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0174259 <lb/>2. (2016) PLOS ONE 2015 Reviewer Thank You. PLoS ONE 11(2): e0150341. https://doi.org/10.1371/ <lb/>journal.pone.0150341 <lb/></listBibl>

			<front>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0194158 March 15, 2018 <lb/>1 / 2 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: (2018) PLOS ONE 2017 Reviewer and <lb/>Editorial Board Thank You. PLoS ONE 13(3): <lb/>e0194158. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0194158 <lb/>Received: February 27, 2018 <lb/>Published: March 15, 2018 <lb/>Copyright: © 2018 The PLOS ONE Staff. This is an <lb/>open access article distributed under the terms of <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are <lb/>within the paper and its supporting information <lb/>files. <lb/>Funding: The author(s) received no specific <lb/>funding for this work. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>3. (2015) PLOS ONE 2014 Reviewer Thank You. PLoS ONE 10(2): e0121093. https://doi.org/10.1371/ <lb/>journal.pone.0121093 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS ONE 2017 Reviewer and Editorial Board Thank You <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0194158 March 15, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 2 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
