<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32729 <lb/>Available online 10 June 2024 <lb/>2405-8440/© 2024 The Authors. <lb/>Published by Elsevier Ltd. <lb/>This is an open access article under the CC BY license <lb/>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/>Research article <lb/>Structural screening and molecular simulation identify potential <lb/>ligands against the K700E hot spot variant and functional pockets <lb/>of SF3B1 to modulate splicing in myelodysplastic syndrome <lb/>Rolando García a, * , Murat Atis b , Andrew Cox b , Prasad Koduru a <lb/>a Department of Pathology, UT Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, TX, USA <lb/>b Lyda Hill Department of Bioinformatics, UT Southwestern Medical Center, Dallas, TX, USA <lb/>A B S T R A C T <lb/>Myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS), a blood disorder with ineffective hematopoiesis and risk of transformation to acute myeloid leukemia, is char-<lb/>acterized by recurring cytogenetic and molecular alterations. By chromosome analysis, approximately 60% of patients, carry chromosome 5 and 7 <lb/>alterations, trisomy of chromosome 8 and may also present with increasingly complex karyotypes, especially in higher grade MDS (MDS with <lb/>refractory anemia and increased blasts type 1 and 2). Moreover, somatic pathogenic variants in genes associated with aberrant mRNA splicing are <lb/>frequently mutated with SF3B1 the most frequently mutated. In the setting of SF3B1, the K700E hot-spot mutation is present in approximately 50% <lb/>of cases. Since recent studies have highlighted modulation of functional dynamics in SF3B1 by mutant splicing factors, the objective of the study was <lb/>to identify potential small molecule modulators against the frequently mutated RNA splicing factor SF3B1(K700E) and functional allosteric sites by <lb/>using a molecular structure-based approach and a molecular dynamic simulation. To identify potential SF3B1 modulators, we collected a series of <lb/>chemical compounds from the Zinc and Enamine database. An initial screen followed by further molecular analysis and simulation using the <lb/>Schrödinger suite was performed. Parameters used to monitor the stability and binding of the protein-ligand complex included: RMSF, protein-<lb/>ligand contacts, electrostatic, Van Der Waals forces and binding energies (MMGBSA). A 100-nanosecond simulation showed strong binding be-<lb/>tween selected compounds and key amino acid residues, including the mutation hot-spot K700E and functional allosteric amino acid residue R630. <lb/>Ligand binding energies between compounds and key amino acid residues ranged from -50.67 to -58.04 kcal/mol. In brief, small molecule <lb/>modulators show strong binding to SF3B1 suggesting these compounds may be used against cells harboring the K700E variant or to modulate <lb/>splicing by targeting functional allosteric sites. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>Myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS) is a blood disorder characterized by cytopenia, ineffective hematopoiesis, future risk of acute <lb/>myeloid leukemia, and genetic aberrations for structural-functional abnormalities of hematopoietic stem cells. It is clinically and <lb/>genetically heterogeneous disease, primarily affecting the elderly population with a median age of presentation at 70-71 years. The <lb/>categorized morphological features seen are dysplastic features in one or more cell lines of the myeloid lineage and contain an <lb/>increased number of blasts; however, the number of blasts is less than 20 % in the bone marrow or peripheral blood. In terms of genetic <lb/>defects, chromosome aberrations are detected in up to 60 % of patients, notably chromosome 5 and 7 alterations, trisomy of chro-<lb/>mosome 8 and presentation of complex karyotypes. With the advent of newer genetic technologies, recurrent somatic variants in a <lb/>number of genes have been reported in up to 90 % of MDS patients [1]. Sequence variants in genes associated with aberrant mRNA <lb/>splicing (e.g., SF3B1, U2AF1, SRSF2, ZRSR2, DDX41, LUC7L2) are frequently mutated (50-89 %) and are associated with early clonal <lb/></body>

			<front>* Corresponding author. <lb/>E-mail address: rolando.garcia@utsouthwestern.edu (R. García). <lb/>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect <lb/>Heliyon <lb/>journal homepage: www.cell.com/heliyon <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e32729 <lb/>Received 28 May 2024; Received in revised form 4 June 2024; Accepted 7 June 2024 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Heliyon 10 (2024) e32729 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>events and disease development [2-4]. Of these, SF3B1 is by far the most frequently mutated comprising 20-30 % of cases [1,5] and <lb/>the K700E substitution variant accounts for the majority of SF3B1 pathogenic sequence variants in MDS, refractory anemia with ring <lb/>sideroblasts, acute myeloid leukemia (AML), chronic myelomonocytic leukemia, breast and pancreatic cancer, as well as, uveal <lb/>melanoma [3,6-9]. Other commonly mutated genes include histone modification and DNA methylation genes (ASXL1, EZH2, TET2, <lb/>DNMT3A, IDH1 and IDH2) [10,11]. Current therapies of MDS involve lenalidomide for deletion (5q), hypomethylating agents and <lb/>regenerative hematopoietic stem cells to deter the drastic effects of blood cytopenia. More recently, potential new agents for both low <lb/>and high-risk MDS are under investigation. However, despite these efforts, there is a need to develop novel therapies that target <lb/>splicing factor alterations, since these are the most frequently mutated. Currently, small molecule modulators such as FR901464, <lb/>herboxidiene, pladienolide B and analogues are documented. One analogue of pladienolide B (E7107) showed high affinity to SF3B1 <lb/>and exhibited potent cytotoxicity activity against tumor cells, however, failed clinical activity in a clinical trial [12,13]. Likewise, <lb/>H3B-8800, another derivative of pladienolide B undergoing clinical trial (NCT02841540), demonstrated dose dependent modulation <lb/>of SF3B1 [14]. However, in this instance, only a small percentage of patients (14 %) obtained hematologic improvement, and complete <lb/>remission was not observed in these patients [4]. Despite the potential therapeutic effect of H3B-8800, it is unclear at the molecular <lb/>level how it modulates SF3B1 since the amino acid residues contributing to the binding site are far from the K700E hot-spot [15]. <lb/>Nonetheless, HB3-8800 seems to have preferentially lethality against cancer cells harboring the K700E variant [15]. In a similar <lb/>manner, other potential allosteric pockets near the K700E have been identified that may be targeted to modulate SF3B1 [15]. <lb/>Nonetheless, despite a clear understanding of the molecular mechanism, recent studies have highlighted the functional dynamics of <lb/>SF3B1 influenced by small splicing factor modulators or oncogenic mutations [16,17]. Both crystal structures of SF3B1 and cryo-EM <lb/>studies have described its remarkable structural flexibility taking both open and closed conformations. This open or close structural <lb/>flexibility allows SF3B1 to recognize unique intron sequences, specifically the branch point sequences (BPS) within an intron. Like-<lb/>wise, pathogenic mutations located far from the BPS recognition sites can engage in &quot;crosstalk signaling&quot; and exert an influence on the <lb/>functional dynamics of spliceosome activity [18]. Indeed, molecular simulation studies have shown mutations disrupt SF3B1 and <lb/>mRNA interactions [19,20]. Therefore, we explored potential small molecule modulators against the often-mutated K700E and other <lb/>potential SF3B1functional allosteric sites [15,21], by a molecular structure-based approach and molecular dynamic analyses. <lb/>2. Materials and methods <lb/>To identify potential SF3B1 modulators, we curated a selection of chemical compounds from the Zinc database, which is accessible <lb/>at https://zinc.docking.org/. Given the extensive range of compounds in the database and the significant role molecular weight and <lb/>the compound hydrophobicity or lipophilicity (LogP) play in drug development (where compounds exceeding a molecular weight of <lb/>500 Da and LogP greater than 5 exhibit poor absorption or permeation), we concentrated our efforts on a subset of compounds <lb/>categorized as &quot;Goldilocks -druglike compounds&quot; with a molecular weight up to 350 Da and a logP of 2. In addition, a list of FDA <lb/>approved compounds from the Enamine database was also used for analysis. The H3B-8800 compound in phase-1 clinical trials for <lb/>SF3B1 modulation was used as a control. All compounds were converted to single pdbqt file formats for molecular screening and <lb/>docking using Vina and MGL tools (available at https://vina.scripps.edu/). The SF3B1 protein was obtained from the Protein Data <lb/>Bank (PDB: 5ZYA), and docking sites were selected, including H572, L575, V576, E579, T612, M613, D616, N619, Y623, V624, T627, <lb/>R630, A631, and K700E, [15,21]. The K700E hot spot variant in SF3B1was prioritized due to its most frequent mutation occurrence. <lb/>Additionally, other amino acid residues selected for docking demonstrate high druggability and scoring potential for modulating <lb/>SF3B1 [6,15]. For the control, the amino acid residues for docking included Y36, V37, R38, R1074, V1078, Y1157, V1114, R1075, and <lb/>V1110. Binding affinity scores generated by Vina of less than -7.0 kcal/mol were selected for further analysis. The binding affinity <lb/>between SF3B1 and small molecule modulators was later described by pKd values (&gt;5 were considered strong binding affinity). The <lb/>KDEEP package in PlayMolecule (available at: https://playmolecule.com) was used for generating pKd values. Following the initial <lb/>screening, a second docking iteration was conducted, which involved generating an additional library comprising of potential com-<lb/>pounds previously identified along with their stereoisomers. A total of 1000 copies of each compound was attempted. The second <lb/>library was docked using glide Schrödinger module (Schrödinger, LLC, New York, NY). The clusters generated from stereoisomers were <lb/>evaluated using matrix distance plots, contacts to desired amino acid residues, and binding energies generated of the clusters for <lb/>further molecular analyses. To validate the interactions of compounds with the SF3B1 protein, we proceeded with additional mo-<lb/>lecular dynamics (MD) simulations using the Schrödinger Desmond module. Molecular simulations, which typically involve <lb/>high-performance computers calculating how molecules move and interact over time, were prepared, and set up using established <lb/>methods. At first, simulations were carried out for 300 ns (ns). However, if compounds didn&apos;t exhibit convergence (i.e., alignment of <lb/>ligand and the protein) by the end of the simulation, as indicated by the RMSD plots, an extended simulation of 500 ns was conducted. <lb/>The protein-ligand structures were placed in water molecules to mimic their natural environment. The water box used was about 132 <lb/>× 132 × 132 cubic angstroms in size. Sodium and chloride ions were added to balance the charge and create a salt concentration like <lb/>that found in biological systems, around 0.15 mol/L. To simulate how the protein and ligand behave, a mathematical model called the <lb/>OPLS_2005 force field was used. This model helps predict the movements and interactions of the molecules. The simulation started by <lb/>heating the system to a temperature of 300 K to mimic the conditions inside a living organism. Then, a type of simulation called the <lb/>NPT ensemble was used, which maintains constant temperature and pressure. The pressure was controlled at 1.01325 bars, and the <lb/>simulation ran for either 300 or 500 ns. Free energies of non-bonded interactions (electrostatic and van der Waals forces) to evaluate <lb/>stability of protein-ligand complex were determined by using the Desmond package. To estimate the ligand-binding affinities based on <lb/>free energy calculations, the molecular mechanics energies combined with the Poisson-Boltzmann or generalized Born and surface area <lb/>continuum solvation (MM/GBSA) was used [22]. The QuikPro within the Schrödinger suite was employed to evaluate the physically <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">R. García et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32729 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>relevant descriptors and pharmaceutical features of the prospective compounds targeting the K700E and functional pockets of SF3B1 <lb/>[23]. In addition, a toxicity profile of the compounds was generated by the Pro-Tox-II server [24]. <lb/>3. Results <lb/>3.1. Initial virtual screen <lb/>A total of 230,000 compounds from the Zinc database and 1040 FDA approved compounds were collected for analysis. The initial <lb/>virtual screen performed identified 15 potential compounds with affinity to SF3B1 hot-spots and functional amino acid residues in <lb/>SF3B1 with docking scores less than -7 kcal/mol and binding affinity scores (pKd values) greater than or equal to 5. Table 1 shows the <lb/>list of small molecules with potential to modulate SF3B1. <lb/>3.2. Second screen of identified stereoisomer compounds <lb/>Following the initial screening, a second docking iteration was conducted of stereoisomers of the 15 compounds. A grand total of <lb/>6167 stereoisomers were produced and then docked at various potential sites, mainly the K700E substitution and amino acid residues <lb/>with druggability potential [15] to pinpoint ligand docking locations based on clusters. Not all compounds were replicated to the <lb/>desired extent of 1000 stereoisomers. Only Goserelin, Icatibant, ZN299817872, ZN252480685, ZN263583855, and ZN261492935 <lb/>generated 1000 copies. The rest of the compounds collectively generated a total of 169 copies. Selected poses for further molecular <lb/>analysis were determined by evaluating distance matrix plots of compounds in clusters, the contacts to desired amino acid residues and <lb/>their binding energy (only those compound poses with 7 kcal/mol or greater were selected for further molecular evaluation). Priority <lb/>was given to binding energy and amino acid contacts when evaluating stereoisomer clusters. <lb/>Supplementary Fig. 1 illustrates the distance matrix plots of selected compounds, with the exception of ZN8551963-Diquafosol <lb/>because only one stereoisomer copy was generated. Four compounds (Goserelin, Icatibant, ZN263583855 and ZN8551963-Diqua-<lb/>fosol) were identified for subsequent molecular simulation analyses. Likewise, a simulation of the control compound (H3B-8800) was <lb/>also performed. Fig. 1 illustrates the 2-D structures, while Table 2 describes the SMILE notation of compounds selected for molecular <lb/>simulation. <lb/>3.3. Molecular simulation: ligand and protein RMSD <lb/>A molecular simulation was initially conducted for a duration of 300 ns using the Schrödinger&apos;s Desmond package for the above-<lb/>mentioned compounds, including the H3B-8800 control. Not surprisingly, the control attached to the same deep pocket as compound <lb/>E7107 (both derivatives of pladienolide B), a pocket formed by amino acid residues Y36, V37, R38, R1074, R1075, V1078, V1110, <lb/>V1114, V1078, and Y1157. Fig. 2 compares the binding of the control H3B-8800 and the top two compounds at different time intervals. <lb/>The top two compounds (goserelin and icatibant) were selected based on the frequency of interactions with K700E, hydrogen bond <lb/>contacts and energy binding energies to K700E. <lb/>The evolution of both the ligand and the protein were tracked by monitoring the Root-mean-square deviation (RMSD) of the C-<lb/>alpha atoms of the SF3B1 protein and ligand throughout the simulation. To assess the stability and binding of the protein-ligand <lb/>complex, additional parameters such as Root-mean-square fluctuation (RMSF), protein-ligand contacts, electrostatic and van der <lb/>Waals forces, and binding energies (evaluated using MM-GBSA) were also considered. The RMSD of the protein serves as a valuable <lb/>indicator of structural conformation changes during the simulation (i.e., the structural stability of SF3B1 in the presence of the ligand), <lb/>Table 1 <lb/>Docking scores and binding affinities of potential small molecule modulators against hot-spot amino acid residues in SF3B1. <lb/>Compound <lb/>Docking Score (kcal/mol) <lb/>Binding Affinity(Pkd) <lb/>Amino Acid <lb/>H3B-8800 (Control) <lb/>-7.43 <lb/>5.50 <lb/>E622, H662, Y36 <lb/>Icatibant <lb/>-7.7 <lb/>12.9 <lb/>K700E <lb/>Thymopentin <lb/>-8.3 <lb/>7.9 <lb/>K700E <lb/>Goserelin <lb/>-8.3 <lb/>12.3 <lb/>K700E <lb/>Entrectinib <lb/>-10.1 <lb/>7.5 <lb/>K700E <lb/>ZN 630123660 <lb/>-7.7 <lb/>6.2 <lb/>R630 <lb/>K700E <lb/>ZN253530914 <lb/>-11.9 <lb/>8.9 <lb/>K700E <lb/>ZN299817872 <lb/>-9.3 <lb/>9.9 <lb/>K700E <lb/>ZN253530915 <lb/>-9.1 <lb/>8.8 <lb/>K700E <lb/>ZN252480685 <lb/>-10.7 <lb/>9.6 <lb/>K700E <lb/>ZN263583855 <lb/>-8.9 <lb/>8.41 <lb/>K700E <lb/>ZN100045486 <lb/>-9.4 <lb/>6.7 <lb/>K700E <lb/>ZN261492935 <lb/>-9.9 <lb/>5.06 <lb/>K700E <lb/>ZN95353169 <lb/>-7.2 <lb/>6.4 <lb/>R630, K700E <lb/>ZN8551963 (Diquafosol) <lb/>-8.9 <lb/>8.5 <lb/>R630, K700E <lb/>ZN708900121 <lb/>-9.5 <lb/>9.21 <lb/>ASP 616, THR 627 <lb/>R. García et al. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Heliyon 10 (2024) e32729 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>providing insights into equilibration status, while the ligand RMSD reflects the stability of the ligand with respect to the protein and <lb/>binding pockets [25]. The convergence of ligand and compound indicates enhanced conformational stability of the protein-ligand <lb/>complex. These implies that the system has reached a more stable state [26]. Moreover, conformational stability may also be noted <lb/>with a stable behavior in RMSD supported by bonding to the same amino acid residues and binding energy calculations. Initially, a <lb/>300-ns molecular simulation of selected compounds was performed. If the compound and the protein did not converge at the end of <lb/>this simulation, an extended time of 500-ns was performed (Fig. 3). <lb/>Despite the lack of convergence between ZN8551963-Diquafosol and SF3B1, the consistent binding pattern observed throughout <lb/>the 300 and 500-ns simulations, particularly involving residues R630, K786, K748, and R590, suggests enduring and robust nature of <lb/>these interactions. This underscores the strength and specificity of the bonds formed between the ligand and the protein (Fig. 4). <lb/>3.4. RMSF of ligand and protein <lb/>The RMSF (root-mean square function) can be used to assess the molecular flexibility of protein binding pockets and ligand; it <lb/>quantifies the movement of atoms and residues within a molecular structure. The lower the RMSF, the lower mobility of the binding <lb/>site and the ligand, indicating a more favorable interaction and facilitating in the selection of potential drug candidates [27]. The RMSF <lb/>values ranged from 1.65 to 3.65 A <lb/>̊. <lb/>Amino acid residues with the most favorable interactions with the ligands (those with RMSF values <lb/>in the range of 1-2 A <lb/>̊) <lb/>included V1078, V1114, Y1157 in the control-H3B-8800; E622, R625, R630, H662, K666, K700E in goserelin <lb/>and icatibant (Table 3). While ZN263583855-Diquafosol displayed slightly elevated RMSF values for certain amino acid residues, it is <lb/>notable that specific atom numbers within the ligand, particularly oxygen 12 and 20, formed hydrogen bonds with the SF3B1 protein at <lb/>R630, with distances of 2.40 Å and 2.12 Å, respectively. <lb/>3.5. Contacts between SB3B1 protein and ligands <lb/>Protein interactions with the various ligands were monitored during the simulation (Table 4). The protein-ligand interactions were <lb/>divided into four categories: hydrogen bonds, hydrophobic interactions, ionic interactions, and water bridges (i.e., hydrogen bonded <lb/>Fig. 1. 2-D Structures of the molecules selected for further molecular dynamic simulation. <lb/>Table 2 <lb/>SMILE notation of ligands used for molecular simulation. <lb/>Compound <lb/>SMILE Notation <lb/>Control: H3B-8800 <lb/>n1ccccc1[C@H](C)/C --C/C --C(\C)[C@@H](OC(=O)C[C@H](O)CC2)[C@@H](C)/C --C/[C@@H]([C@]2(C)O)OC(=O)N3CC <lb/>[NH+](C)CC3 <lb/>Goserelin <lb/>NC(=O)NNC(=O)[C@@H]1CCCN1C(=O)[C@H](CCCNC(N) = [NH2+])NC(=O)[C@H](CC(C)C)NC(=O)[C@@H](COC(C)(C)C) <lb/>NC(=O)[C@H](Cc2ccc(O)cc2)NC(=O)[C@H](CO)NC(=O)[C@H](Cc3c[nH]c(c34)cccc4)NC(=O)[C@H](C[C@@H]5C[NH+] = <lb/>CN5)NC(=O)[C@@H](N6)CCC6 --O <lb/>Icatibant <lb/>CCNC(=O)[C@@H]1CCCN1C(=O)[C@H](CCCNC(N) = [NH2+])NC(=O)[C@H](CC(C)C)NC(=O)[C@@H](Cc2cn(c[nH+]2) <lb/>Cc3ccccc3)NC(=O)[C@H](Cc4ccc(O)cc4)NC(=O)[C@H](CO)NC(=O)[C@H](Cc5c[nH]c(c56)cccc6)NC(=O)[C@H](Cc7c[nH+]c <lb/>[nH]7)NC(=O)[C@@H](N8)CCC8 --O <lb/>ZN263583855 <lb/>C --C1C[C@]23CC[C@H]4[C@@](C)(CCC[C@@]4(C)C(=O)O[C@@H]4O[C@H](CO)[C@@H](O)[C@H](O)[C@H]4O)[C@@H] <lb/>2CC[C@@]1(O[C@@, H]1O[C@H](CO)[C@@H](O)[C@H](O[C@@H]2O[C@H](CO)[C@@H](O)[C@H](O)[C@H]2O[C@@H] <lb/>2O[C@@H](C)[C@H](O)[C@@H](O)[C@H]2O)[C@H]1O)C3 <lb/>ZINC008551963 <lb/>(Diquafosol) <lb/>O = c1ccn(c(=O)[nH]1)[C@H](O2)[C@H](O)[C@H](O)[C@H]2COP([O-])(=O)OP([O-])(=O)OP([O-])(=O)OP([O-])(=O)OC <lb/>[C@@H]3[C@@H](O)[C@@H](O)[C@@H](O3)n(c(=O)[nH]4)ccc4 = O <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">R. García et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32729 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>protein and ligand interactions mediated by water molecules that are slightly more relaxed that the standard hydrogen bond defi-<lb/>nition). Note that interaction values greater than 100 % (1.0) can occur when certain protein residues engage in multiple contacts with <lb/>the ligand. For example, goserelin formed two hydrogen bonds with K700E; ZN263583855-Diquafosol and ZN008551963 formed two <lb/>hydrogen bonds each with R630. Among the selected ligands with the highest frequency of contacts to K700E (greater than 100 %) <lb/>included goserelin (1.85) and icatibant (1.13). Fig. 5 shows the close interaction of goserelin and icatibant with SF3B1 amino acid <lb/>residues, especially the K700E and R630 residue hot spots. <lb/>3.6. Free energy calculations <lb/>We also conducted free energy calculations (non-bonded interactions: electrostatic and van der Waals forces) to assess confor-<lb/>mation stability of protein-ligand complex throughout the trajectory. Calculations derived from MM-GBSA were also used to assess the <lb/>strength of the ligand-receptor interactions [28]. Indeed, the higher the free energy, the more stable and higher affinity, this means that <lb/>protein-ligand interactions occur spontaneously and release of more energy. Table 5 displays the cumulative energy, electrostatic and <lb/>van der Waals forces, calculated for protein-ligand complex for the different compounds (control H3B-8800, goserelin, Icatibant, <lb/>ZN26358385 and ZN008551963-Diquafosol at four distinct time intervals (0, 100, 200, and 300 ns). The free energies of compounds <lb/>extended to 500 ns are also included. Moreover, MM-GBSA free energy calculation of ligands and SF3B1 amino acid residues was <lb/>performed(see Table 6). <lb/>Note that MM-GBSA calculations demand substantial time and computational resources, especially when handling complete <lb/>simulations. It&apos;s important to recognize that the resulting binding energy from MM-GBSA reflect calculations observed at the end of the <lb/>simulation. This typically occurs when both the ligand and protein RSMD have converged, or a noted behavior stability in their <lb/>interaction is observed, such in the case of ZN8551963-Diquafosol and SF3B1. In contrast, metrics like RMSD (refer to Fig. 2), protein-<lb/>ligand contacts (see Table 4), and total non-bonded energy calculations (detailed in Table 5) offer insights spanning the entirety of the <lb/>simulated trajectory. <lb/>Considering the above molecular analyses and binding energies, the four selected compounds demonstrated affinity interactions <lb/>and free energy binding to the hot spot variant K700E and functional hotspots. Specifically, goserelin exhibited both an increased <lb/>number of interactions and stronger binding affinity to K700E compared to other functional hotspots. Meanwhile, ZN008551963-<lb/>Diquafosol showed a preference for binding functional pockets, particularly R630. <lb/>Fig. 2. Molecular simulation of the H3B-8800 control and the two top compounds (painted in blue) bound to SF3B1 (highlighted in gray). The first <lb/>4 panels of each compound show the simulated trajectory (0-300 ns in 100 ns intervals). (For interpretation of the references to color in this figure <lb/>legend, the reader is referred to the Web version of this article.) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">R. García et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32729 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 3. RMSD plots between SF3B1 and selected ligands. Panel A shows the control-H3B-8800 converged at approximately 350-ns. Panel B shows <lb/>RMSD analysis of goserelin demonstrated a consistent superposition with the protein structure across the entire trajectory of 300-ns. This indicates <lb/>goserelin maintained a stable binding conformation with the protein throughout the simulation. Panel C illustrates RMSD of the protein and ica-<lb/>tibant over the course of 500 ns. Both the ligand and protein exhibited consistent stability throughout the simulation. However, some noticeable <lb/>conformational changes occurred around 380 ns, although stability was restored shortly after 400 ns and persisted until the end of the simulation. <lb/>Panel D illustrates RSMD convergence between ZN263583855 and SF3B1 at approximately 180-ns, but a more stable conformation of the protein <lb/>and compound was reached approximately from 190 to 300-ns. Panels E and D depict RMSD plots for ZN8551963-Diquafosol and the protein at 300 <lb/>and 500 ns, respectively. In this case, the protein and compound system did not achieve convergence. Nonetheless, they exhibited stable behavior <lb/>throughout both simulation durations. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">R. García et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32729 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>3.7. Drug-like properties and toxicity assessment of ligands <lb/>Predictions of drug-like properties (properties found in 95 % of pharmaceutical compounds) of the selected ligands were derived <lb/>from the QuikPro property predictions module in Schrödinger. Our analysis included the following properties: molecular weight, <lb/>dipole moment, total SASA (total solvent accessible surface area), hydrophilic and hydrophobic SASA, number of donor and acceptor <lb/>hydrogen bonds, molecular volume, globularity, solute ionization potential, QP polarizability, QP log P for hexadecane/gas, QP log S <lb/>for aqueous solubility, QP log BB (brain-blood partition coefficient), QPlogKhsa (human serum albumin binding) number of primary <lb/>metabolites, Apparent Caco-2 Permeability, apparent MDCK cell permeability, Lipinski violation (rule of 5), and the Jorgensen&apos;s rule <lb/>of three. The predictions of these features are documented in the Supplementary Table 1. Based on QuikPro property prediction <lb/>calculations, the larger molecular weight FDA approved compounds (&gt;725 atomic mass units) icatibant and goserelin, along with Zinc <lb/>compounds, ZN263583855, and ZN008551963-Diquafosol, had more unsatisfactory ranges, while the smaller molecular weight <lb/>control H3B-8800 (molecular weight of 555) exhibited more acceptable ranges. It&apos;s important to note that QuikPro property pre-<lb/>dictions, which encompass properties observed in 95 % of therapeutic compounds, are valuable but not absolute determinants. <lb/>Fig. 3. (continued). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">R. García et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32729 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Comprehensive evaluation of compounds as effective therapeutics should also take into consideration additional factors such as <lb/>clinical data, risk-benefit analysis, and therapeutic necessity. In addition to evaluating properties frequently observed in 95 % of <lb/>therapeutic compounds, we conducted a toxicity assessment using probability derived calculations from the Pro-Tox-II server. Here, 12 <lb/>toxicity metrics were evaluated: Predicted LD50 (Dose value), hepatotoxicity, neurotoxicity, respiratory toxicity, cardiotoxicity, <lb/>immunotoxicity, cytotoxicity, blood brain barrier, ecotoxicity, clinical toxicity, mutagenicity, and cytotoxicity. Although all the <lb/>compounds, including the control showed some degree of predicted toxicity (painted circles in red, see Table 7), all were classified as <lb/>either moderate or non-toxic based on predicted toxicity classification. However, note that further assessment and validation studies, <lb/>including in-vitro and in-vivo studies, are needed to confirm the toxicity potential predicted by computational methods. These studies <lb/>can provide better information into the effects of these compounds. <lb/>Fig. 4. 2-D structure of ZN8551963-Diquafosol bound to SF3B1 amino acid residues (colored circles) at two different time intervals (300 and 500-<lb/>ns). The contact frequency for each of the amino acids with the ligand is given by the colored arrows. <lb/>Table 3 <lb/>RMSF value measurements of ligand and amino acid residues. <lb/>Ligand/Amino acid residue <lb/>C-alpha/RMSF value -(A <lb/>̊) <lb/>Control: H3B-8800 <lb/>R1074 <lb/>3.08 <lb/>R1075 <lb/>3.28 <lb/>V1078 <lb/>2.66 <lb/>V1110 <lb/>3.62 <lb/>V1114 <lb/>2.58 <lb/>Y1157 <lb/>2.69 <lb/>Goserelin <lb/>R630 <lb/>2.12 <lb/>K700E <lb/>2.16 <lb/>Icatibant <lb/>R630 <lb/>2.72 <lb/>K700E <lb/>3.02 <lb/>ZN263583855 -Diquafosol <lb/>R630 <lb/>2.20 <lb/>K700E <lb/>2.71 <lb/>ZN008551963 <lb/>Y623 <lb/>3.39 <lb/>T627 <lb/>3.41 <lb/>R630 <lb/>3.17 <lb/>K700E <lb/>3.61 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">R. García et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32729 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>4. Discussion <lb/>In this structure-based approach, combined with molecular dynamics, we have introduced four potential compounds (Goserelin, <lb/>Icatibant, ZN263583855 and ZN008551963-Diquafosol) designed to target the K700E hot spot variant and functional pockets, mainly <lb/>R630 within SF3B1. <lb/>The observed characteristics of these compounds in molecular dynamics simulations indicate their promising potential to selec-<lb/>tively modulate or remove the aberrant splicing activity of K700E mutated SF3B1. This suggests that they could have a notable impact <lb/>on the treatment of MDS, but also extends to a broader spectrum of clinical implications in other cancer types associated with the <lb/>SF3B1 K700E mutation, underscoring the significance and widespread applicability of our findings. Other conditions with SF3B1 <lb/>K700E include acute myeloid leukemia (AML), occurring in 2-5% of AML cases, chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) observed in 15 % <lb/>with poor prognosis, uveal melanoma in 15 %, pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC) in 4 % where K700E is an oncogenic driver, <lb/>and 16 % in papillary breast cancers [9,29-31]. These conditions present opportunities for exploration and potential therapeutic <lb/>avenues, by addressing the underlying K700E abnormality and modulating SF3B1 activity. In patients with MDS, SF3B1 mutations are <lb/>prevalent (approximately 25 % in all MDS cases) and occurring in approximately 85 % of cases in a form of MDS (refractory anemia <lb/>with ringed sideroblasts) [32], with K700E the most frequently observed mutation. The presence of K700E in myeloid progenitors <lb/>induces abnormal splicing patterns, reflecting the phenotype observed in MDS. This suggests that targeting this aberration could hold <lb/>promise as a potential therapeutic strategy for MDS. The strong affinities of Goserelin, Icatibant and ZN26358385 for the K700E hot <lb/>spot suggest that these compounds may be suitable for targeted therapies in these neoplasms. In addition, these compounds may be <lb/>used in combination therapies, potentially enhancing their therapeutic effects, and overcoming resistance mechanisms. Similarly, the <lb/>identification of strong binding to the functional allosteric residue R630, mainly ZN008551963-Diquafosol, indicates that the com-<lb/>pounds may exert effects through allosteric modulation of protein function [15]. This could open new avenues for therapeutic <lb/>intervention, particularly if targeting this residue can disrupt aberrant splicing and signaling pathways or enhance the efficacy of <lb/>existing therapies in MDS or other cancer types with this mutation. Nevertheless, further research, including in-vitro and in-vivo <lb/>validation into the therapeutic potential of these compounds is needed to fully assess the therapeutic potential of these compounds <lb/>and determine their applicability in clinical settings. <lb/>Currently, the predominant method of manipulating SF3B1 in tumor cells relies on small molecules [33], a strategy that has shown <lb/>promise in various diseases, including cancer. Computational methods have emerged as invaluable tools in this pursuit, streamlining <lb/>the process of identifying lead compounds and accelerating their path to market. A vast number of compounds identified through these <lb/>methods have already made significant strides in treating diseases such as viral infections and cancer, including HIV inhibitors, <lb/>tyrosine kinase inhibitors for chronic myeloid leukemia, and ALK inhibitors for pancreatic cancer, among others [34-37]. In terms of <lb/>SF3B1, a list of potential SF3B1 modulators is reported in the literature, with compounds like H3B-8800, spliceostatin A, and E7107 <lb/>demonstrating promising outcomes in preclinical studies [38-40]. These compounds exhibit efficacy across a spectrum of solid tumors <lb/>and hematological neoplasms, offering hope for patients with MYC-driven cancers, metastatic neuroblastoma, glioblastoma multi-<lb/>forme, and various others [38,39,41,42]. However, challenges have surfaced during clinical trials, as seen with E7107, which was <lb/>discontinued due to vision impairment concerns [43]. H3B8800, a splicing modulator and synthetic derivative of pladienolide, enter <lb/>clinical trials (NCT02841540) for patients with MDS, acute myeloid leukemia and chronic myelomonocytic leukemia. Despite splicing <lb/>modulation activity and reduced transfusions in patients, H3B-8800 did not show any clinical response [14,44]. Therefore, additional <lb/>Table 4 <lb/>Protein-Ligand Contacts (hydrogen bonds, hydrophobic bonds, ionic and water bridge bonds) to amino acid residue hot spots expressed as a <lb/>percentage. <lb/>Compound/Amino Acid Residue <lb/>Hydrogen <lb/>Hydrophobic <lb/>Ionic <lb/>Water Bridge <lb/>Total <lb/>Control H3B-8800 <lb/>R1074 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>R1075 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>V1078 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>V1110 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>V1114 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>Y1157 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>0.62 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.83 <lb/>Goserelin <lb/>R630 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>K700E <lb/>1.63 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>1.85 <lb/>Icatibant <lb/>R630 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>K700E <lb/>0.70 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.39 <lb/>1.13 <lb/>ZN263583855 <lb/>R630 <lb/>1.20 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>1.42 <lb/>K700E <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.37 <lb/>0.40 <lb/>ZN008551963 <lb/>Y623 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>T627 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.42 <lb/>0.43 <lb/>R630 <lb/>2.08 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>1.89 <lb/>4.13 <lb/>K700E <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.07 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">R. García et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32729 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>efforts are needed to identify and to test additional compounds to modulate the splicing activity of SF3B1. Recent studies have shed <lb/>light on potential mechanisms underlying the cytotoxic effects of these compounds, including cell cycle regulation, apoptosis in-<lb/>duction, and DNA double-stranded break induction [45,46]. However, further research is needed to obtain a better understanding of <lb/>the mechanisms through which SF3B1 modulators induce anti-proliferative effects in tumor cells. Considering the advantages and <lb/>benefits associated with conducting small molecule screens and their potential in identifying possible SF3B1 modulators targeting <lb/>tumor cells, we conducted a review of the literature of the four compounds identified as potential modulators in this study. To the best <lb/>of knowledge, there is limited available data for ZN263583855 (searchable under the Zinc database as ZINC00263583855). The <lb/>remaining three compounds are FDA approved, with ZN008551963-Diquafosol used as a dry eye treatment, Icatibant used in he-<lb/>reditary angioedema, viral infections, and sweating induced dermal pain, and Goserelin, use to treat breast and prostate cancer <lb/>[47-51]. The latter compounds hold a promise for the repurposing as SF3B1 modulators. <lb/>4.1. Limitations and future work <lb/>Although these results show promising results, our molecular structure-based approach may face limitations. For instance, certain <lb/>biological or physical processes may extend beyond the duration of 300 or 500 ns, restricting our understanding of system behavior <lb/>and requiring additional computational resources such as time and computational power. However, our observations of the time scales <lb/>spanning 300 and 500 ns suggested both protein and ligand reached a state of equilibrium within the system for three of the four <lb/>Fig. 5. In Panels A &amp; B, the illustrations demonstrate the intimate interactions and the specific amino acids engaged in the interactions between the <lb/>selected ligands and SF3B1, notably the K700E and R630 hot spots. Hydrogen bonds at green arrows interact with amino acid residues (highlighted <lb/>in orange), along with the corresponding distances between the ligand atoms and the amino acid residue. (For interpretation of the references to <lb/>color in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the Web version of this article.) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">R. García et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32729 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>compounds. One compound, ZN008551963-Diquafosol did not achieve equilibrium but did exhibit consistent stability throughout the <lb/>trajectory of 300 and 500 ns. Despite limitations in long timescale dynamics, the use of molecular simulations offers valuable insights <lb/>into the behavior of compounds at the molecular level, aiding in the discovery and development of novel therapeutics. Moving for-<lb/>ward, several avenues of future research include in-vitro and in-vivo validation studies, exploring molecular mechanisms underlying <lb/>the interaction between the ligands and SF3B1 through mechanistic investigations to better understand their mode of action and <lb/>potential therapeutic targets, optimization of the identified ligands through chemistry approaches that may improve their potency, <lb/>selectivity, and pharmacokinetic properties, and structure-activity relationship studies with analog synthesis that may lead to the <lb/>development of more effective SF3B1 modulators with enhanced therapeutic potential. <lb/>5. Conclusion <lb/>Our research study has identified four ligands exhibiting molecular features that hold promise in regulating SF3B1 activity within <lb/>MDS and potentially other neoplasms associated with the SF3B1 K700E mutation. These ligands target the mutant hot-spot K700E as <lb/>Table 5 <lb/>Energies of protein-ligand at various time intervals. <lb/>H3B-8800 (control) <lb/>Time (ns) <lb/>Elec <lb/>VdW <lb/>Nonbond <lb/>Total (kcal/mol) <lb/>0 <lb/>-80.39 <lb/>-34.07 <lb/>-114.46 <lb/>-114.46 <lb/>100 <lb/>-23.50 <lb/>-29.45 <lb/>-52.95 <lb/>-52.95 <lb/>200 <lb/>-70.86 <lb/>-32.35 <lb/>-103.21 <lb/>-103.21 <lb/>300 <lb/>-110.15 <lb/>-41.12 <lb/>-151.27 <lb/>-151.27 <lb/>500 <lb/>-96.21 <lb/>-21.83 <lb/>-118.04 <lb/>-118.04 <lb/>Goserelin <lb/>0 <lb/>-118.84 <lb/>-48.40 <lb/>-167.24 <lb/>-167.24 <lb/>100 <lb/>-297.67 <lb/>-35.96 <lb/>-333.63 <lb/>-333.63 <lb/>200 <lb/>-279.27 <lb/>-23.34 <lb/>-302.61 <lb/>-302.61 <lb/>300 <lb/>-249.27 <lb/>-43.58 <lb/>-292.85 <lb/>-292.85 <lb/>Icatibant <lb/>0 <lb/>-228.58 <lb/>-35.38 <lb/>-263.96 <lb/>-263.96 <lb/>100 <lb/>12.88 <lb/>-37.06 <lb/>-24.18 <lb/>-24.18 <lb/>200 <lb/>-68.31 <lb/>-28.14 <lb/>-96.45 <lb/>-96.45 <lb/>300 <lb/>-93.84 <lb/>-27.59 <lb/>-121.43 <lb/>-121.43 <lb/>500 <lb/>-221.88 <lb/>-44.51 <lb/>-266.39 <lb/>-266.39 <lb/>ZN263583855 <lb/>0 <lb/>-139.01 <lb/>-48.36 <lb/>-187.37 <lb/>-187.37 <lb/>100 <lb/>-55.89 <lb/>-35.84 <lb/>-91.73 <lb/>-91.73 <lb/>200 <lb/>-24.72 <lb/>-19.16 <lb/>-43.88 <lb/>-43.88 <lb/>300 <lb/>-50.88 <lb/>-37.28 <lb/>-88.16 <lb/>-88.16 <lb/>ZN008551963-Diquafosol <lb/>0 <lb/>-373.01 <lb/>-22.55 <lb/>-395.56 <lb/>-395.56 <lb/>100 <lb/>-683.65 <lb/>-25.26 <lb/>-708.91 <lb/>-708.91 <lb/>200 <lb/>-732.04 <lb/>-23.83 <lb/>-755.87 <lb/>-755.87 <lb/>300 <lb/>-746.82 <lb/>-15.02 <lb/>-761.84 <lb/>-761.84 <lb/>Key: ns, nanoseconds, Elec, electrostatic interactions; VdW, van der Waals interactions; Nonbond, nonbonded. <lb/>Table 6 <lb/>Ligand binding energies to SF3B1 amino acid hot spot residues at convergence or noted behavior stability. <lb/>Compound <lb/>Amino acid Residue <lb/>Binding Energy (Kcal/mol) MM-GBSA <lb/>Goserelin <lb/>R630 <lb/>-76.08 <lb/>K700E <lb/>-183.71 <lb/>Icatibant <lb/>R630 <lb/>34.99 <lb/>K700E <lb/>-161.91 <lb/>ZN263583855 <lb/>R630 <lb/>-57.75 <lb/>K700E <lb/>-164.28 <lb/>ZN008551963-Diquafosol <lb/>Y623 <lb/>-41.35 <lb/>T627 <lb/>-34.49 <lb/>R630 <lb/>-110.78 <lb/>K700E <lb/>-96.31 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">R. García et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32729 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 7 <lb/>Toxicity Profile of selected compounds. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">R. García et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32729 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">R. García et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32729 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>well as the allosteric functional site R630. These findings represent a step forward in the development of potential therapeutic in-<lb/>terventions in these patients. While further research and validation is needed, identification of these compounds may open new av-<lb/>enues for targeted therapies that may ultimately improve the quality of life of individuals affected by MDS and beyond. <lb/></body>

            <div type="annex">Institutional review board statement <lb/>Not applicable. <lb/></div>

            <div type="availability">Data and availability statement <lb/>Data included in article/supplementary material/referenced in article. <lb/></div>

            <div type="contribution">CRediT authorship contribution statement <lb/>Rolando García: Writing -original draft, Visualization, Software, Project administration, Methodology, Investigation, Formal <lb/>analysis, Data curation, Conceptualization. Murat Atis: Formal analysis, Data curation. Andrew Cox: Formal analysis. Prasad <lb/>Koduru: Writing -review &amp; editing, Supervision. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">R. García et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32729 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<div type="conflict">Declaration of competing interest <lb/>The authors document no competing interests or personal relationships that may have influenced the work of this study. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Appendix A. Supplementary data <lb/>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e32729. <lb/>References <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>[1] N. Hosono, Genetic abnormalities and pathophysiology of MDS, Int. J. Clin. Oncol. 24 (8) (2019) 885-892, https://doi.org/10.1007/s10147-019-01462-6. <lb/>[2] A. Jerez, L.P. Gondek, A.M. Jankowska, H. Makishima, B. Przychodzen, R.V. Tiu, C.L. O&apos;Keefe, A.M. Mohamedali, D. Batista, M.A. Sekeres, et al., Topography, <lb/>clinical, and genomic correlates of 5q myeloid malignancies revisited, J. Clin. Oncol. 30 (12) (2012) 1343-1349, https://doi.org/10.1200/JCO.2011.36.1824. <lb/>[3] K. Yoshida, M. Sanada, Y. Shiraishi, D. Nowak, Y. Nagata, R. Yamamoto, Y. Sato, A. Sato-Otsubo, A. Kon, M. Nagasaki, et al., Frequent pathway mutations of <lb/>splicing machinery in myelodysplasia, Nature 478 (7367) (2011) 64-69, https://doi.org/10.1038/nature10496. <lb/>[4] C. Saygin, H.E. Carraway, Current and emerging strategies for management of myelodysplastic syndromes, Blood Rev. 48 (2021) 100791, https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/j.blre.2020.100791. <lb/>[5] M.C. Wahl, C.L. Will, R. Luhrmann, The spliceosome: design principles of a dynamic RNP machine, Cell 136 (4) (2009) 701-718, https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>cell.2009.02.009. <lb/>[6] E. Papaemmanuil, M. Cazzola, J. Boultwood, L. Malcovati, P. Vyas, D. Bowen, A. Pellagatti, J.S. Wainscoat, E. Hellstrom-Lindberg, C. Gambacorti-Passerini, et <lb/>al., Somatic SF3B1 mutation in myelodysplasia with ring sideroblasts, N. Engl. J. Med. 365 (15) (2011) 1384-1395, https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa1103283. <lb/>[7] L. Wang, M.S. Lawrence, Y. Wan, P. Stojanov, C. Sougnez, K. Stevenson, L. Werner, A. Sivachenko, D.S. DeLuca, L. Zhang, et al., SF3B1 and other novel cancer <lb/>genes in chronic lymphocytic leukemia, N. Engl. J. Med. 365 (26) (2011) 2497-2506, https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa1109016. <lb/>[8] M.J. Ellis, L. Ding, D. Shen, J. Luo, V.J. Suman, J.W. Wallis, B.A. Van Tine, J. Hoog, R.J. Goiffon, T.C. Goldstein, et al., Whole-genome analysis informs breast <lb/>cancer response to aromatase inhibition, Nature 486 (7403) (2012) 353-360, https://doi.org/10.1038/nature11143. <lb/>[9] S.J. Furney, M. Pedersen, D. Gentien, A.G. Dumont, A. Rapinat, L. Desjardins, S. Turajlic, S. Piperno-Neumann, P. de la Grange, S. Roman-Roman, et al., SF3B1 <lb/>mutations are associated with alternative splicing in uveal melanoma, Cancer Discov. 3 (10) (2013) 1122-1129, https://doi.org/10.1158/2159-8290.CD-13-<lb/>0330. <lb/>[10] G. Nikoloski, S.M. Langemeijer, R.P. Kuiper, R. Knops, M. Massop, E.R. Tonnissen, A. van der Heijden, T.N. Scheele, P. Vandenberghe, T. de Witte, et al., Somatic <lb/>mutations of the histone methyltransferase gene EZH2 in myelodysplastic syndromes, Nat. Genet. 42 (8) (2010) 665-667, https://doi.org/10.1038/ng.620. <lb/>[11] H. Yang, S. Kurtenbach, Y. Guo, I. Lohse, M.A. Durante, J. Li, Z. Li, H. Al-Ali, L. Li, Z. Chen, et al., Gain of function of ASXL1 truncating protein in the <lb/>pathogenesis of myeloid malignancies, Blood 131 (3) (2018) 328-341, https://doi.org/10.1182/blood-2017-06-789669. <lb/>[12] M. Sato, N. Muguruma, T. Nakagawa, K. Okamoto, T. Kimura, S. Kitamura, H. Yano, K. Sannomiya, T. Goji, H. Miyamoto, et al., High antitumor activity of <lb/>pladienolide B and its derivative in gastric cancer, Cancer Sci. 105 (1) (2014) 110-116, https://doi.org/10.1111/cas.12317. <lb/>[13] D. Zhang, F. Meng, A Comprehensive overview of structure-activity relationships of small-molecule splicing modulators targeting SF3B1 as anticancer agents, <lb/>ChemMedChem 15 (22) (2020) 2098-2120, https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.nanolett.0c01757. <lb/>[14] D.P. Steensma, M. Wermke, V.M. Klimek, P.L. Greenberg, P. Font, R.S. Komrokji, J. Yang, A.M. Brunner, H.E. Carraway, L. Ades, et al., Phase I first-in-human <lb/>dose escalation study of the oral SF3B1 modulator H3B-8800 in myeloid neoplasms, Leukemia 35 (12) (2021) 3542-3550, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41375-<lb/>021-01328-9. <lb/>[15] A. Spinello, J. Borisek, L. Malcovati, A. Magistrato, Investigating the molecular mechanism of H3B-8800: a splicing modulator inducing preferential lethality in <lb/>spliceosome-mutant cancers, Int. J. Mol. Sci. 22 (20) (2021), https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms222011222. <lb/>[16] J. Borisek, A. Saltalamacchia, A. Galli, G. Palermo, E. Molteni, L. Malcovati, A. Magistrato, Disclosing the impact of carcinogenic SF3b mutations on pre-mRNA <lb/>recognition via all-atom simulations, Biomolecules 9 (10) (2019), https://doi.org/10.3390/biom9100633. <lb/>[17] J. Borisek, A. Saltalamacchia, A. Spinello, A. Magistrato, Exploiting cryo-EM structural information and all-atom simulations to decrypt the molecular <lb/>mechanism of splicing modulators, J. Chem. Inf. Model. 60 (5) (2020) 2510-2521, https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jcim.9b00635. <lb/>[18] T.J. Carrocci, D.M. Zoerner, J.C. Paulson, A.A. Hoskins, SF3b1 mutations associated with myelodysplastic syndromes alter the fidelity of branchsite selection in <lb/>yeast, Nucleic Acids Res. 45 (8) (2017) 4837-4852, https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkw1349. <lb/>[19] A.K. Kesarwani, O. Ramirez, A.K. Gupta, X. Yang, T. Murthy, A.C. Minella, M.M. Pillai, Cancer-associated SF3B1 mutants recognize otherwise inaccessible <lb/>cryptic 3&apos; splice sites within RNA secondary structures, Oncogene 36 (8) (2017) 1123-1133, https://doi.org/10.1038/onc.2016.279. <lb/>[20] A. Samy, B.E. Suzek, M.K. Ozdemir, O. Sensoy, In silico analysis of a highly mutated gene in cancer provides insight into abnormal mRNA splicing: splicing <lb/>factor 3B subunit 1(K700E) mutant, Biomolecules 10 (5) (2020), https://doi.org/10.3390/biom10050680. <lb/>[21] D. Maji, A. Grossfield, C.L. Kielkopf, Structures of SF3b1 reveal a dynamic Achilles heel of spliceosome assembly: implications for cancer-associated <lb/>abnormalities and drug discovery, Biochim Biophys Acta Gene Regul Mech 1862 (11-12) (2019) 194440, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbagrm.2019.194440. <lb/>[22] S. Genheden, U. Ryde, The MM/PBSA and MM/GBSA methods to estimate ligand-binding affinities, Expet Opin. Drug Discov. 10 (5) (2015) 449-461, https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1517/17460441.2015.1032936. <lb/>[23] S. Release, QuickProp, LLC, New York, NY, 2018-2, Schrodinger. <lb/>[24] P. Banerjee, A.O. Eckert, A.K. Schrey, R. Preissner, ProTox-II: a webserver for the prediction of toxicity of chemicals, Nucleic Acids Res. 46 (W1) (2018) <lb/>W257-W263, https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gky318. <lb/>[25] F. Opo, M.M. Rahman, F. Ahammad, I. Ahmed, M.A. Bhuiyan, A.M. Asiri, Structure based pharmacophore modeling, virtual screening, molecular docking and <lb/>ADMET approaches for identification of natural anti-cancer agents targeting XIAP protein, Sci. Rep. 11 (1) (2021) 4049, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-021-<lb/>83626-x. <lb/>[26] I. Sarkar As, In silico screening predicts common cold drug Dextromethorphan along with Prednisolone and Dexamethasone can be effective against novel <lb/>Coronavirus disease (COVID-19), J. Biomol. Struct. Dyn. 40 (8) (2020) 3706-3710. <lb/>[27] N.N. Cob-Calan, L.A. Chi-Uluac, F. Ortiz-Chi, D. Cerqueda-Garcia, G. Navarrete-Vazquez, E. Ruiz-Sanchez, E. Hernandez-Nunez, Molecular docking and <lb/>dynamics simulation of protein beta-tubulin and antifungal cyclic lipopeptides, Molecules 24 (18) (2019), https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules24183387. <lb/>[28] K.H. Chowdhury Mrc, S. Mahmud, A.M. Tareq, N.B. Hanif, N. Banu, et al., Drug repurposing approach against novel coronavirus disease (COVID-19) through <lb/>virtual screening targeting SARS-CoV-2 main protease, Biology 10 (2) (2021) 2021. <lb/>[29] L.M. Scott, V.I. Rebel, Acquired mutations that affect pre-mRNA splicing in hematologic malignancies and solid tumors, J. Natl. Cancer Inst. 105 (20) (2013) <lb/>1540-1549, https://doi.org/10.1093/jnci/djt257. <lb/>[30] I. Lopez-Oreja, A. Gohr, H. Playa-Albinyana, A. Giro, F. Arenas, M. Higashi, R. Tripathi, M. Lopez-Guerra, M. Irimia, M. Aymerich, et al., SF3B1 mutation-<lb/>mediated sensitization to H3B-8800 splicing inhibitor in chronic lymphocytic leukemia, Life Sci. Alliance 6 (11) (2023), https://doi.org/10.26508/ <lb/>lsa.202301955. <lb/>[31] D. Cilloni, F. Itri, V. Bonuomo, J. Petiti, SF3B1 mutations in hematological malignancies, Cancers 14 (19) (2022), https://doi.org/10.3390/cancers14194927. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">R. García et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e32729 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[32] G. Garcia-Manero, Myelodysplastic syndromes: 2012 update on diagnosis, risk-stratification, and management, Am. J. Hematol. 87 (7) (2012) 692-701, https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1002/ajh.23264. <lb/>[33] D. Kaida, H. Motoyoshi, E. Tashiro, T. Nojima, M. Hagiwara, K. Ishigami, H. Watanabe, T. Kitahara, T. Yoshida, H. Nakajima, et al., Spliceostatin A targets SF3b <lb/>and inhibits both splicing and nuclear retention of pre-mRNA, Nat. Chem. Biol. 3 (9) (2007) 576-583, https://doi.org/10.1038/nchembio.2007.18. <lb/>[34] J. Yan, Y. Yao, S. Yan, R. Gao, W. Lu, W. He, Chiral protein supraparticles for tumor suppression and synergistic immunotherapy: an enabling strategy for <lb/>bioactive supramolecular chirality construction, Nano Lett. 20 (8) (2020) 5844-5852, https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.nanolett.0c01757. <lb/>[35] E. Buchdunger, J. Zimmermann, H. Mett, T. Meyer, M. Muller, B.J. Druker, N.B. Lydon, Inhibition of the Abl protein-tyrosine kinase in vitro and in vivo by a 2-<lb/>phenylaminopyrimidine derivative, Cancer Res. 56 (1) (1996) 100-104. <lb/>[36] Z.T. Al-Salama, Apalutamide: a review in non-metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer, Drugs 79 (14) (2019) 1591-1598, https://doi.org/10.1007/ <lb/>s40265-019-01194-x. <lb/>[37] B. Shaker, S. Ahmad, J. Lee, C. Jung, D. Na, In silico methods and tools for drug discovery, Comput. Biol. Med. 137 (2021) 104851, https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>compbiomed.2021.104851. <lb/>[38] R. Sciarrillo, A. Wojtuszkiewicz, Y.G. Assaraf, G. Jansen, G.J.L. Kaspers, E. Giovannetti, J. Cloos, The role of alternative splicing in cancer: from oncogenesis to <lb/>drug resistance, Drug Resist. Updates 53 (2020) 100728, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.drup.2020.100728. <lb/>[39] L.A. Crews, L. Balaian, N.P. Delos Santos, H.S. Leu, A.C. Court, E. Lazzari, A. Sadarangani, M.A. Zipeto, J.J. La Clair, R. Villa, et al., RNA splicing modulation <lb/>selectively impairs leukemia stem cell maintenance in secondary human AML, Cell Stem Cell 19 (5) (2016) 599-612, https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>stem.2016.08.003. <lb/>[40] H. Nakajima, B. Sato, T. Fujita, S. Takase, H. Terano, M. Okuhara, New antitumor substances, FR901463, FR901464 and FR901465. I. Taxonomy, fermentation, <lb/>isolation, physico-chemical properties and biological activities, J. Antibiot. (Tokyo) 49 (12) (1996) 1196-1203, https://doi.org/10.7164/antibiotics.49.1196. <lb/>[41] C. Lagisetti, G. Palacios, T. Goronga, B. Freeman, W. Caufield, T.R. Webb, Optimization of antitumor modulators of pre-mRNA splicing, J. Med. Chem. 56 (24) <lb/>(2013) 10033-10044, https://doi.org/10.1021/jm401370h. <lb/>[42] S. Xargay-Torrent, M. Lopez-Guerra, L. Rosich, A. Montraveta, J. Roldan, V. Rodriguez, N. Villamor, M. Aymerich, C. Lagisetti, T.R. Webb, et al., The splicing <lb/>modulator sudemycin induces a specific antitumor response and cooperates with ibrutinib in chronic lymphocytic leukemia, Oncotarget 6 (26) (2015) <lb/>22734-22749, https://doi.org/10.18632/oncotarget.4212. <lb/>[43] D.S. Hong, R. Kurzrock, A. Naing, J.J. Wheler, G.S. Falchook, J.S. Schiffman, N. Faulkner, M.J. Pilat, J. O&apos;Brien, P. LoRusso, A phase I, open-label, single-arm, <lb/>dose-escalation study of E7107, a precursor messenger ribonucleic acid (pre-mRNA) splicesome inhibitor administered intravenously on days 1 and 8 every 21 <lb/>days to patients with solid tumors, Invest. N. Drugs 32 (3) (2014) 436-444, https://doi.org/10.1007/s10637-013-0046-5. <lb/>[44] M. Steensma Dpw, V.M. Klimek, P.L. Greenberg, P. Font, R.S. Komrokji, J. Yang, A.M. Brunner, H.E. Carraway, Ades lea: results of a clinical trial of H3B-8800, a <lb/>splicing modulator, in patients with myelodysplastic syndromes (MDS), acute myeloid leukemia (AML) or chronic myelomonocytic leukemia (CMML), Blood <lb/>134 (2019) 673. <lb/>[45] R. Prados-Carvajal, A. Lopez-Saavedra, C. Cepeda-Garcia, S. Jimeno, P. Huertas, Multiple roles of the splicing complex SF3B in DNA end resection and <lb/>homologous recombination, DNA Repair 66-67 (2018) 11-23, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.dnarep.2018.04.003. <lb/>[46] S. Sankar, M. Guillen-Navarro, F. Ponthan, S. Bomken, S. Nakjang, V. Grinev, et al., The SF3b splicing complex regulates DNA damage response in acute <lb/>lymphoblastic leukemia, Blood 134 (1) (2019) 1237. <lb/>[47] D.V. Simac, T. Stimac, S. Novak, Is icatibant safe for the treatment of hereditary angioedema during pregnancy? Curr. Allergy Asthma Rep. 22 (10) (2022) <lb/>135-140. <lb/>[48] J. Mustonen, J. Antonen, A. Vaheri, Icatibant in viral infections, Inf. Disp. 55 (6) (2023) 444-445, https://doi.org/10.1080/23744235.2023.2200563. <lb/>[49] LiverTox: Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury [Internet]. Bethesda (MD): National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney <lb/>Diseases, 2012 NBK548740, 2023 May 28. <lb/>[50] S.M. Cheer, G.L. Plosker, D. Simpson, A.J. Wagstaff, Goserelin: a review of its use in the treatment of early breast cancer in premenopausal and perimenopausal <lb/>women, Drugs 65 (18) (2005) 2639-2655, https://doi.org/10.2165/00003495-200565180-00011. <lb/>[51] G.M. Keating, Diquafosol ophthalmic solution 3 %: a review of its use in dry eye, Drugs 75 (8) (2015) 911-922, https://doi.org/10.1007/s40265-015-0409-7. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">R. García et al. </note>


	</text>
</tei>
