<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Review of codelists used to define hypertension in electronic health records and development of a codelist for research</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Georgie May</forename>
            <surname>Massen</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Philip W</forename>
            <surname>Stone</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Harley H Y</forename>
            <surname>Kwok</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Gisli</forename>
            <surname>Jenkins</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Richard J</forename>
            <surname>Allen</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Louise V</forename>
            <surname>Wain</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Iain</forename>
            <surname>Stewart</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Jennifer Kathleen</forename>
            <surname>Quint</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-29T13:01:50.542421Z">29.10.2025 13:01:50</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1136$1$openhrt-2024-002640</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>BMJ</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1136/openhrt-2024-002640</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Georgie May Massen, Philip W Stone, Harley H Y Kwok, Gisli Jenkins, Richard J Allen, Louise V Wain, Iain Stewart, Jennifer Kathleen Quint. (2024). Review of codelists used to define hypertension in electronic health records and development of a codelist for research. Open Heart, 11(1), e002640. DOI: 10.1136/openhrt-2024-002640</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-29T13:01:50.542421Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-29T13:01:50.542421Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<front>Muhia J, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2024;9:e014498. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2023-014498 <lb/>Health journal coverage of climate <lb/>change and health: a bibliometric study <lb/>Joy Muhia <lb/>, 1 Melissa L Rethlefsen, 2 Ben Rossington, 3,4 Florence Wedmore, 5 <lb/>Anandita Pattnaik, 6 Richard Smith, 6 Sara Schroter 7,8 <lb/>Original research <lb/>To cite: Muhia J, Rethlefsen ML, <lb/>Rossington B, et al. <lb/>Health journal coverage <lb/>of climate change and <lb/>health: a bibliometric <lb/>study. BMJ Glob Health <lb/>2024;9:e014498. doi:10.1136/ <lb/>bmjgh-2023-014498 <lb/>Handling editor Seye Abimbola <lb/>► Additional supplemental <lb/>material is published online only. <lb/>To view, please visit the journal <lb/>online (https:// doi. org/ 10. 1136/ <lb/>bmjgh-2023-014498). <lb/>Received 9 November 2023 <lb/>Accepted 4 February 2024 <lb/>1 <lb/>Centre for Global Mental Health, <lb/>London School of Hygiene &amp; <lb/>Tropical Medicine, London, UK <lb/>2 <lb/>University of New Mexico <lb/>Health Sciences Library and <lb/>Informatics Center, Albuquerque, <lb/>New Mexico, USA <lb/>3 <lb/>Thrive LDN, Transformation <lb/>Partners in Health and Care, <lb/>London, UK <lb/>4 <lb/>Public Representative, London, <lb/>UK <lb/>5 <lb/>Barts Health NHS Trust, London, <lb/>UK <lb/>6 <lb/>UK Health Alliance on Climate <lb/>Change, London, UK <lb/>7 <lb/>BMJ, London, UK <lb/>8 <lb/>Faculty of Public Health <lb/>and Policy, London School of <lb/>Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine, <lb/>London, UK <lb/>Correspondence to <lb/>Joy Muhia; <lb/>jjmuhiam7@ yahoo. com <lb/>© Author(s) (or their <lb/>employer(s)) 2024. Re-use <lb/>permitted under CC BY-NC. No <lb/>commercial re-use. See rights <lb/>and permissions. Published by <lb/>BMJ. <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Objectives To find what proportion of a broad set of <lb/>health journals have published on climate change and <lb/>health, how many articles they have published, and when <lb/>they first published on the subject. <lb/>Design Bibliometric study. <lb/>Setting and participants We conducted electronic <lb/>searches in Ovid MEDLINE ALL for articles about climate <lb/>change and human health published from 1860 to 31 <lb/>December 2022 in 330 health journals. There were no <lb/>limits by language or publication type. Results were <lb/>independently screened by two raters for article eligibility. <lb/>Results After screening there were 2932 eligible articles <lb/>published across 253 of the 330 journals between 1947 <lb/>and 2022; most (2795/2932; 95%) were published in <lb/>English. A few journals published articles in the early 90s, <lb/>but there has been a rapid increase since about 2006. <lb/>We were unable to categorise the types of publication <lb/>but estimate that fewer than half are research papers. <lb/>While articles were published in journals in 39 countries, <lb/>two-thirds (1929/2932; 66%) were published in a journal <lb/>published in the UK or the USA. Almost a quarter (77/330; <lb/>23%) of the journals published no eligible articles, and <lb/>almost three-quarters (241/330; 73%) published five <lb/>articles or fewer. The publication of joint editorials in over <lb/>200 journals in 2021 and 2022 boosted the number of <lb/>journals publishing something on climate change and <lb/>health. A third of the (112/330; 34%) journals in our <lb/>sample published at least one of the joint editorials, and <lb/>almost a third of those (32/112; 29%) were publishing on <lb/>climate change and health for the first time. <lb/>Conclusions Health journals are rapidly increasing the <lb/>amount they publish on climate change and health, but <lb/>despite climate change being the major threat to global <lb/>health many journals had until recently published little <lb/>or nothing. A joint editorial published in multiple journals <lb/>increased coverage, and for many journals it was the first <lb/>thing they published on climate change and health. <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>&apos;Climate change is the biggest global health <lb/>threat of the 21st century&apos;, concluded the <lb/>Lancet Commission on Climate Change in <lb/>2009. 1 Harm arises from heatwaves, storms, <lb/>fires, floods, shortages of water, food, and <lb/>shelter, changing patterns of disease, forced <lb/>migration, and conflict. 1 Yet if the world were <lb/>to make the changes necessary to respond to <lb/>climate change-for example, ending the use <lb/>of fossil fuels, shifting diets to being largely <lb/>plant-based and encouraging active transport, <lb/>then the change could also be &apos;the greatest <lb/>opportunity for global health&apos;. 2 <lb/>A series of reports by the Lancet Count-<lb/>down on Health and Climate Change, the <lb/>latest in 2022, show that the global tempera-<lb/>ture and emissions continue to rise, and <lb/>the global response is inadequate. 3 Health <lb/>systems, like all other human activities, emit <lb/>greenhouse gases, and if health systems were <lb/></body>
    
    <front>WHAT IS ALREADY KNOWN ON THIS TOPIC <lb/>⇒ The World Health Organisation has declared climate <lb/>change to be the major threat to global health. <lb/>⇒ Previous studies have shown that articles on cli-<lb/>mate change and health began to appear in the ear-<lb/>ly 1990s and then began to increase rapidly from <lb/>around 2006. <lb/>WHAT THIS STUDY ADDS <lb/>⇒ This study provides the first information on journals <lb/>rather than simply articles and shows that many <lb/>health journals had published little or nothing on cli-<lb/>mate change and health until recently. Some have <lb/>still not published anything. <lb/>⇒ A few journals have published most of the articles. <lb/>⇒ For many journals the first article they published on <lb/>climate change and health was an editorial pub-<lb/>lished simultaneously in more than 200 journals. <lb/>HOW THIS STUDY MIGHT AFFECT RESEARCH, <lb/>PRACTICE OR POLICY <lb/>⇒ A next study might be to explore why many health <lb/>journals have published so little on climate change <lb/>and health and how they might be supported to pub-<lb/>lish more. <lb/>⇒ A preliminary investigation has shown that many <lb/>journals would be interested to publish more, and a <lb/>consortium of journals and publishers may be estab-<lb/>lished to continue the publishing of the joint editorial <lb/>each year. The consortium might also provide mate-<lb/>rial for journals with limited resources and contacts <lb/>and publish editorials on other topics threatening the <lb/>world-for example, nuclear war. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">BMJ Global Health: first published as 10.1136/bmjgh-2023-014498 on 22 February 2024. Downloaded from https://gh.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Muhia J, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2024;9:e014498. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2023-014498 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">BMJ Global Health <lb/></note>
    
    <body>a country they would be the fifth biggest emitter. 4 Most <lb/>health systems have rising emissions of greenhouse <lb/>gases. 3 The NHS in England is responsible for between <lb/>4% and 5% of UK global emissions and is committed to <lb/>achieving carbon net zero by 2040 on all that it controls <lb/>directly and by all that it consumes by 2045. 5 All other <lb/>health systems will also have to achieve net zero by 2050 <lb/>if the world is to respond adequately to climate change, <lb/>and the changes will have to be radical, affecting all parts <lb/>of the system including all medical specialties. Indeed, <lb/>nobody knows exactly how health systems can achieve <lb/>net zero, and much research will be needed. In addi-<lb/>tion, health systems must adapt to the climate changes <lb/>that have already occurred and will continue to worsen <lb/>for a while even if global emissions are cut. This includes <lb/>both the impacts on patients and changing patterns of <lb/>diseases, and the direct threat of changing climates to the <lb/>health system. <lb/>The seriousness of the threat to health and the necessity <lb/>for health systems and medical practice to change mean <lb/>that climate change should receive extensive coverage in <lb/>health journals. Health professionals need to be aware <lb/>of all aspects of climate change and health because they <lb/>will need to change as individuals and professionals. In <lb/>addition, health systems and the organisations of health <lb/>professionals will have to change. There will also have to <lb/>be political changes and informed health professionals <lb/>can be trusted advocates for change. All health profes-<lb/>sionals receive or access different journals, and all jour-<lb/>nals, not just a few, should be covering climate change <lb/>and health. Each medical specialty will need to find <lb/>a route to net zero, and specialist journals will have an <lb/>important role in helping their specialty find the route. <lb/>Climate change from rising carbon dioxide levels was <lb/>predicted as long ago as the late 19th century. In 1988, the <lb/>head of the NASA Goddard Institute for Space Studies <lb/>told a US Senate Committee: &apos;The greenhouse effect has <lb/>been detected, and it is changing our climate now&apos;. 6 The <lb/>first Earth Summit was held in Rio de Janeiro in 1992. <lb/>Health journals could have been covering climate <lb/>change and health for many decades. The Lancet Count-<lb/>down on Climate Change conducted a bibliometric study <lb/>of climate change and health and showed a near expo-<lb/>nential growth in the number of peer-reviewed articles <lb/>between 1985 and 2022, with fewer than 100 in 2000 and <lb/>over 3200 in 2021. 3 There was a 22% increase between <lb/>2020 and 2021. 3 A supporting study of reports between <lb/>2013 and 2020 showed that more than four-fifths of the <lb/>articles (86%) covered the implications for health of <lb/>climate change rather than mitigation or adaptation. 7 <lb/>The authors used supervised machine learning and other <lb/>natural language processing methods without checking <lb/>the relevance of the individual articles identified by the <lb/>search, and did not conduct an analysis by journal. 7 <lb/>Authors of a study published in 2016 searched in PubMed <lb/>and Science Direct for publications from 1990 to 2014 for <lb/>articles that contained one climate term and one health <lb/>term in either the title, abstract or as a Medical Subject <lb/>Heading (MeSH) term. 8 The authors found few articles <lb/>until 2006 and then an exponential increase, but papers <lb/>dealing with health and climate were about half that of <lb/>climate related articles in other sectors. <lb/>Another group searched the National Institute of <lb/>Environmental Health Sciences Climate Change and <lb/>Human Health Literature Portal, which includes global <lb/>peer-reviewed research and grey literature conducted in <lb/>North America (USA, Mexico and Canada). 9 10 The data-<lb/>base was compiled by searching PubMed, Web of Science <lb/>and Google Scholar for research on climate change and <lb/>health published from 2012 to 2019. The group reviewed <lb/>individual articles and identified 7082 original research <lb/>articles published between 2012 and 2019 with an average <lb/>annual increase of 23%. <lb/>These previous bibliometric studies dealt with articles <lb/>not journals, and only one study reviewed individual arti-<lb/>cles to ensure that they did cover climate change and <lb/>health-and that study covered only the years after 2012 <lb/>and research conducted in North America. 9 10 Termi-<lb/>nology for this topic has changed over the years and <lb/>simply mentioning climate change does not mean that <lb/>the article is addressing the topic. We set out to find the <lb/>extent of the coverage of climate change in health jour-<lb/>nals over time in a broad set of health journals, using a <lb/>broad search strategy with two raters screening the eligi-<lb/>bility of the search results. We were particularly interested <lb/>to know when and which health journals first published <lb/>on climate change and health and how many had not <lb/>published anything on the subject. <lb/>We were prompted to do this by a programme devel-<lb/>oped by the UK Health Alliance on Climate Change to <lb/>encourage over 200 health journals around the world to <lb/>publish the same editorials on climate change and health <lb/>before COP26 and COP27, the United Nations annual <lb/>meetings on climate change, in 2021 and 2022. 11 12 The <lb/>aim of the editorials was to encourage more action by <lb/>governments and to reach more health professionals <lb/>with information on the importance for health of acting <lb/>on climate change. Before conducting our study, we had <lb/>the impression that many of the journals had published <lb/>little or nothing on climate change until they published <lb/>these editorials. <lb/>METHODS <lb/>Data sources and searches <lb/>We conducted electronic searches in Ovid MEDLINE <lb/>ALL for articles about climate change published from <lb/>1860 to 31 December 2022. <lb/>Search: identification of journals <lb/>To identify a broad range of health journals to include <lb/>in the search and to avoid retrieving articles in journals <lb/>that focus on environmental health rather than climate <lb/>change, we took three purposive journal samples and <lb/>pooled the results. We identified the top 50 most highly <lb/>cited clinical medicine journals based on impact factor <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">BMJ Global Health: first published as 10.1136/bmjgh-2023-014498 on 22 February 2024. Downloaded from https://gh.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="footnote">Muhia J, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2024;9:e014498. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2023-014498 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">BMJ Global Health <lb/></note>
    
    <body>from Clarivate&apos;s Journal Citation Reports Database <lb/>(JCR 2021); all journals listed in the JCR 2021 category <lb/>of &apos;Medicine, General &amp; Internal&apos;; and all journals that <lb/>published the joint editorial coordinated by UKHACC, <lb/>titled &apos;Call for emergency action to limit global temper-<lb/>ature increases, restore biodiversity, and protect health&apos; <lb/>in 2021. After pooling the three samples, we removed <lb/>duplicated journals and excluded journals that were not <lb/>indexed in MEDLINE in January 2023. <lb/>To ensure a comprehensive list of journals meeting <lb/>inclusion criteria, each journal was individually reviewed <lb/>in the NLM Journals Database (https://www.ncbi.nlm. <lb/>nih.gov/nlmcatalog/journals/). Each included journal <lb/>was reviewed for title changes since being indexed in <lb/>MEDLINE. When title changes were identified, each <lb/>previous and current journal title was reviewed to see <lb/>whether it was indexed in MEDLINE. Published journals <lb/>that were not labelled &apos;Currently indexed by MEDLINE&apos; <lb/>were excluded. For currently published titles indexed <lb/>in MEDLINE, all journal titles for the same publication <lb/>were included in the search to ensure maximum coverage <lb/>of each journal if they were or had been indexed in <lb/>MEDLINE. To be considered the same publication, <lb/>volume numbering needed to continue across the title <lb/>changes (eg, British Medical Journal (Clinical Research <lb/>Edition) ceased with volume 296, number 6639 and <lb/>BMJ (Clinical Research Edition) began with volume 297, <lb/>number 6640). <lb/>Search: identification of articles on climate change and <lb/>human health <lb/>MeSHs have not been available for the topic of climate <lb/>change until 2010 and an array of terms have been used <lb/>to describe the topic. We created a list of keywords based <lb/>on those used in previous studies 13-18 and supplemented <lb/>this with additional keywords we thought should also <lb/>be included following discussions as a team and exper-<lb/>imenting with different keywords. We tested the initial <lb/>search strategy on a single journal (The BMJ) and the <lb/>research team reviewed the results to help decide whether <lb/>the search should be more or less specific. <lb/>We found the inclusion of keywords for extreme <lb/>weather conditions led to the inclusion of some ineligible <lb/>articles but their exclusion from the search would lead to <lb/>the exclusion of some relevant articles. Based on the pilot <lb/>results and to estimate the magnitude of the problem in <lb/>the full set of articles from all journals we decided to <lb/>conduct two separate literature searches: (1) the &apos;main <lb/>search&apos; with the extreme weather-related terms excluded <lb/>(see online supplemental appendix 1, line 409) and (2) <lb/>the &apos;extreme weather conditions search&apos; with additional <lb/>weather-related terms that were not included in the main <lb/>search (see online supplemental appendix 1, line 410). <lb/>Data extraction and synthesis <lb/>The main literature search was conducted in Ovid <lb/>MEDLINE ALL on 26 January 2023 and updated on <lb/>31 March 2023. Results were exported to Covidence <lb/>systematic review software (Veritas Health Innovation, <lb/>Melbourne, Australia. Available at www.covidence.org) <lb/>and Microsoft Excel. For every article identified by the <lb/>main search, two independent raters screened articles for <lb/>eligibility (using the inclusion and exclusion criteria in <lb/>online supplemental appendix 2) based on article title <lb/>and abstract only. For four non-English articles where <lb/>no title or abstract were included from the export from <lb/>MEDLINE, raters used the full text article link available in <lb/>Covidence to access the full text of the article to assess the <lb/>article title and or abstract for eligibility. All conflicting <lb/>ratings were resolved independently by a third rater on <lb/>Covidence. Ineligible articles were then removed from <lb/>the Excel file which was exported from the search results <lb/>in MEDLINE. For the &apos;extreme weather conditions&apos; <lb/>search, the search was conducted on 28 January 2023. <lb/>We took a random sample of 5% articles from the search <lb/>results and screened them for eligibility in the same way <lb/>as for the main search. <lb/>Exclusion and inclusion criteria <lb/>For the search, all articles in the included journals <lb/>available in MEDLINE and published 1860-2022 were <lb/>eligible; there were no limits by language or publication <lb/>type. Online supplemental appendix 2 gives details of the <lb/>inclusion/exclusion criteria applied by raters. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>Descriptive statistics were used to describe the article <lb/>language, year of publication, journal name and journal <lb/>country of publication. <lb/>Patient and public involvement <lb/>BR, who completed a placement at the UK Health Alli-<lb/>ance on Climate Change in autumn 2022 as part of the <lb/>NHS Graduate Management Training Scheme, is our <lb/>public representative and has been involved from the <lb/>start of the study and at every stage of the study and in <lb/>the writing of the manuscript. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Sample <lb/>We included a sample of 330 journals from across the <lb/>three sources (figure 1). The main search strategy iden-<lb/>tified a total of 3571 articles published. Five duplicates <lb/>were removed after identification in Covidence and <lb/>two during data analysis. After screening by raters 2932 <lb/>(82%) of the remaining 3564 articles were considered <lb/>eligible for inclusion. <lb/>The extreme weather conditions search identified <lb/>5202 articles. Screening of a random sample of 260 (5%) <lb/>of these identified that only 6 (2%) were eligible for <lb/>inclusion so we decided not to screen the results from <lb/>the entire extreme weather conditions search and not <lb/>to include any articles from this search in the final data <lb/>analysis. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">BMJ Global Health: first published as 10.1136/bmjgh-2023-014498 on 22 February 2024. Downloaded from https://gh.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Muhia J, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2024;9:e014498. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2023-014498 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">BMJ Global Health <lb/></note>
    
    <body>Distribution over time <lb/>Figure 2 shows the number of articles on climate change <lb/>and health published each year between 1947, the earliest <lb/>year of publication we identified, and 2022. We did not <lb/>identify any articles published before 1947. Figure 3 <lb/>shows the cumulative frequency of articles published <lb/>between 1947 and 2022. There were occasional articles <lb/>published in the 1990s, but the increase in the number of <lb/>articles began in the early 2000s. Fewer than 100 articles <lb/>had been published before 2000, slightly more than 600 <lb/>by 2010, around 2000 by 2020 and almost 3000 by 2022. <lb/>The figures for 2021 and 2022 were inflated by the <lb/>publication of the two joint editorials 11 12 across multiple <lb/>journals. A total of 43 journals in our sample published <lb/>the first editorial, 92 the second and 23 both. Figure 4 <lb/>shows the number of journals publishing articles on <lb/>climate change for the first time; there was a big increase <lb/>between 2017 and 2022. <lb/>Figure 1 Flow chart of included articles. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">BMJ Global Health: first published as 10.1136/bmjgh-2023-014498 on 22 February 2024. Downloaded from https://gh.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="footnote">Muhia J, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2024;9:e014498. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2023-014498 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">BMJ Global Health <lb/></note>

			<body>Distribution across journals <lb/>The 2932 eligible articles were published in 253 of the <lb/>330 included journals between 1947 and 2022. While <lb/>the articles were published in journals in 39 countries, <lb/>two-thirds (1929; 66%) of the articles were published in <lb/>a journal published in the UK or the USA (online supple-<lb/>mental table 1). Figure 5 shows the distribution of arti-<lb/>cles across these 330 journals. Almost a quarter (77/330; <lb/>23%) of the journals published no articles on climate <lb/>change and health, and almost three quarters (241/330; <lb/>73%) published five or fewer articles. Nine of the top 48 <lb/>most highly cited clinical medicine journals (based on <lb/>JCR 2021 and indexed in MEDLINE) published no arti-<lb/>cles; 58 of the 77 journals that published no articles were <lb/>indexed in the JCR 2021 category of &apos;Medicine, General <lb/>&amp; Internal&apos;. <lb/>Figure 2 Number of articles published each year between 1947 and 2022 (n=2932). <lb/>Figure 3 Cumulative frequency of articles published between 1947 and 2022 (n=2932). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">BMJ Global Health: first published as 10.1136/bmjgh-2023-014498 on 22 February 2024. Downloaded from https://gh.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Muhia J, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2024;9:e014498. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2023-014498 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">BMJ Global Health <lb/></note>
    
    <body>The 10 journals publishing the most articles were The <lb/>BMJ (343), Lancet Planetary Health (324), the Lancet (262), <lb/>Global Health Action (92), the Medical Journal of Australia <lb/>(82), mBio (67), Bulletin of the World Health Organization <lb/>(55), BMJ Open (49), JAMA (44) and CMAJ (42). These <lb/>10 journals published 1360 (46%) of the 2932 articles. <lb/>Online supplemental table 2 shows the 59 journals <lb/>publishing at least 10 articles between 1947 and 2022. <lb/>Online supplemental figure 1 shows the number of arti-<lb/>cles published each year over time for the 10 journals <lb/>publishing the most content between 1947 and 2022 <lb/>(1360 articles). Since 2018 the specialist journal Lancet <lb/>Planetary Health has published the most per year and in <lb/>2021-2022 it published 153 (17%) of all the 895 articles <lb/>published; The BMJ published 98 (11%) and the Lancet <lb/>37 (4%). <lb/>Figure 4 Number of journals publishing an article on climate change in human health for the first time (n=253 journals). <lb/>Figure 5 Distribution of articles across the 330 sampled journals between 1947 and 2022 (n=2932). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">BMJ Global Health: first published as 10.1136/bmjgh-2023-014498 on 22 February 2024. Downloaded from https://gh.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="footnote">Muhia J, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2024;9:e014498. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2023-014498 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">BMJ Global Health <lb/></note>
    
    <body>Online supplemental figure 2 shows the number of <lb/>journals that published at least one article on climate <lb/>change in human health between 1947 and 2022. In 2000 <lb/>fewer than 10 journals had published at least one article <lb/>during the year; in 2010 it was slightly fewer than 40, in <lb/>2020 it was almost 100 and in 2022 it was 161 journals. <lb/>Article characteristics <lb/>Language of publication <lb/>The 2932 articles were published in 10 languages (English <lb/>2795, Spanish 41, Norwegian 41, French 31, German <lb/>22, Portuguese 19, Russian 6, Hungarian 5, Icelandic 3 <lb/>and Chinese 1). 2795/2932 (95%) of the articles were <lb/>published in English. <lb/>Article type <lb/>The publication type variable gave 134 different article <lb/>types and we were not able to distinguish research from <lb/>editorial and news type content without access to the full <lb/>text of all articles. However, 1345/2932 (46%) articles <lb/>had an abstract (abstracts were introduced to MEDLINE <lb/>in the 1960s) so it is likely that fewer than half were <lb/>research papers. <lb/>Impact of the first joint editorial <lb/>The aim of the joint editorials published in multiple jour-<lb/>nals is to push governments to be more active in acting on <lb/>climate change and to reach more health professionals <lb/>with information on the importance of acting on climate <lb/>change for the benefit of health. The first joint edito-<lb/>rial 11 was published in September 2021 and the second 12 <lb/>in October 2022, and these boosted the number of arti-<lb/>cles published on the topic and the number of journals <lb/>publishing on the topic in those years. If we exclude the <lb/>publications of both these joint editorials there were 2796 <lb/>articles published across 224 journals; 106/330 (32%) <lb/>journals would have published no articles on climate <lb/>change between 1860 and 2022. <lb/>Of the 330 journals, 112 (34%) published at least <lb/>one of the joint editorials and 32 (29%) of these <lb/>112 were publishing on the topic for the first time. <lb/>29 (26%) of the 112 publishing at least one of the <lb/>editorials did not publish anything else on the topic <lb/>between 1947 and 2022. Of the 23 journals that <lb/>published both of the editorials, 5 (22%) did not <lb/>publish anything else on the topic between 1947 and <lb/>2022. <lb/>A total of 43 (13%) of the 330 journals published <lb/>the first joint editorial. While 30 (70%) of these 43 <lb/>journals published at least one article on climate <lb/>change after this first joint editorial, for 10/30 (33%) <lb/>this was just the second joint editorial. <lb/>18 (42%) of the 43 journals that published the first <lb/>joint editorial had not previously published any arti-<lb/>cles on climate change in human health; 8/18 (44%) <lb/>journals went on to publish at least one more article <lb/>on the topic but 6 of these 8 just published the second <lb/>joint editorial. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>Main findings <lb/>Our study confirms that there were occasional articles <lb/>published on climate change and human health in the <lb/>1990s, but the increase in the number of articles began <lb/>in the early 2000s. <lb/>Our study looked at journals as well as articles, and <lb/>the main finding that our study adds to previous studies <lb/>is that despite climate change being recognised as the <lb/>major threat to global health, roughly a quarter of health <lb/>journals (77/330; 23%) had by 2022 published nothing <lb/>on the topic and almost three quarters (241/330; 73%) <lb/>had published five or fewer articles. If the joint editorials <lb/>published in multiple journals are excluded from the <lb/>analysis then almost a third (106/330; 32%) of the jour-<lb/>nals would have published no articles on climate change <lb/>between 1860 and 2022. <lb/>Three journals (The BMJ, Lancet Planetary Health and <lb/>Lancet), all based in Britain, published almost a third <lb/>of the articles (32%), and 10 journals, all in English, <lb/>published almost half (46%). The two leading general <lb/>journals based in Britain (Lancet and The BMJ) published <lb/>605 (21%) articles between 1860 and 2022, while the two <lb/>leading general journals based in the USA (NEJM and <lb/>JAMA) published 83 (3%). <lb/>Another new finding is that the joint editorials <lb/>published in multiple journals in 2021 and 2022 were <lb/>often the first article on climate change and health that <lb/>the journals published: 112 of the 330 journals published <lb/>at least one of the joint editorials and 32 (29%) were <lb/>publishing on the topic for the first time. <lb/>Publishing the joint editorial as their first article on <lb/>climate change has so far had little impact on encour-<lb/>aging the journals to publish more: of the 18 journals <lb/>that published the first joint editorial as their first article <lb/>on climate change, fewer than half (8, 44%) published at <lb/>least one more article on the topic and six of these eight <lb/>just published the second joint editorial. <lb/>Our results in comparison to other studies <lb/>Studies that have examined articles published on climate <lb/>change and health have shown that articles first appeared <lb/>in the early 1990s and then rapidly increased from the <lb/>early 2000s. 3 7 8 10 13 15 16 18 One study found, however, that <lb/>papers concerned with climate change are published at <lb/>about two times the rate in other sectors, when compared <lb/>with health. 8 <lb/>The only study that gives information on journals is <lb/>that by Sangam and Savitha, which looked at all arti-<lb/>cles on climate change in Web of Science between 2001 <lb/>and 2016. 15 The study includes data on the 20 journals <lb/>publishing the most publications: Science is at the top <lb/>(1523 publications). None of the 20 were health journals. <lb/>Other studies found that most articles on climate <lb/>change and health came from high-income countries. <lb/>We did not look at the country of origin of the articles, <lb/>but we did find that most articles were published in jour-<lb/>nals from high income countries. Verner et al found that <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">BMJ Global Health: first published as 10.1136/bmjgh-2023-014498 on 22 February 2024. Downloaded from https://gh.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Muhia J, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2024;9:e014498. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2023-014498 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">BMJ Global Health <lb/></note>
    
    <body>about two-thirds of all published studies were carried out <lb/>in Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Devel-<lb/>opment countries, predominantly in Europe and North <lb/>America. 8 Berrang-Ford et al looked at 15 963 studies <lb/>published between 2013 and 2019 and found the studies <lb/>came mostly from high-income countries and China. <lb/>There were few studies from low-income countries despite <lb/>them suffering most from the health consequences of <lb/>climate change. 7 Bartlett et al studied research articles <lb/>between 2012 and 2019, took a random sample of 348, <lb/>and found that fewer than a third had first authors from <lb/>the Global South. 10 The Lancet Countdown looked at <lb/>scientific studies and the majority of studies were located <lb/>in, and led by, authors in WHO regions of Western Pacific <lb/>and the Americas. 3 <lb/>We did not analyse the subject matter of the articles <lb/>that we studied, but others have. Articles on the health <lb/>impacts of climate change far outnumbered those on <lb/>mitigation and adaptation, with little or nothing on <lb/>decarbonising health systems. 3 Berrang-Ford et al found <lb/>that air quality and heat stress were the most frequently <lb/>studied exposures, with major gaps in evidence on the <lb/>impact of climate change on mental health, undernutri-<lb/>tion, and maternal and child health. 7 Bartlett et al found <lb/>a lack of research on vulnerable populations, particularly <lb/>the elderly and those in the Global South. 10 Verner et al <lb/>found that the effects of climate change on malnutrition <lb/>and non-communicable diseases is understudied. 8 <lb/>Study strengths and limitations <lb/>A strength of our study is that we have looked at jour-<lb/>nals not just articles. We could not find any other studies <lb/>that had looked at journals rather than articles, although <lb/>Sangam and Savitha gave data on the top 20 journals <lb/>covering all aspects of the science of climate not just <lb/>health. 15 We were able to examine the distribution of <lb/>articles in journals and how many had published little or <lb/>nothing on climate change and health. <lb/>We chose to use Ovid MEDLINE as the database to <lb/>search in order to use complex adjacent word searching, <lb/>which was not possible in PubMed. We may have missed <lb/>some articles, but were able to design a more specific <lb/>search using this technique. In addition to keyword <lb/>searches, we also used MeSHs, however, the MeSH <lb/>&apos;Climate Change&apos; is relatively new and terminology <lb/>has changed over time. Thus, we used combinations of <lb/>specific MeSHs (eg, Climate Change, Global Warming) <lb/>that were directly related to our topic and MeSHs that <lb/>were more generic (eg, Public Health, Global Health) in <lb/>combination with keyword searches. <lb/>Our use of search terms and adjacent word searching <lb/>to try to capture all relevant papers will inevitably have <lb/>resulted in the inclusion of some articles that may not <lb/>be devoted to climate change&apos;s impact on human health <lb/>and may just have mentioned it. There is also an element <lb/>of subjectivity when determining if an article is about <lb/>climate change and human health or just mentioning it. <lb/>Therefore, to improve the accuracy of the search results, <lb/>two independent raters screened the articles&apos; title and <lb/>abstract (where available) for article eligibility. Checking <lb/>the full text of the included articles for relevance was not <lb/>feasible as we were unable to access a large number of <lb/>articles due to subscription and language barriers. <lb/>This independent screening of the MEDLINE search <lb/>results is a strength in our approach, as other studies did <lb/>not include this step, with the exception of Bartlett et <lb/>al, 10 and they studied only articles from North America <lb/>published after 2012. However, even screening did not <lb/>remove all ineligible articles. For example, we included <lb/>all articles that had &apos;climate change&apos; in the title but closer <lb/>inspection of the earliest article, &apos;Dangers of climate <lb/>change&apos;, published in German in Schweizerische Mediz-<lb/>inische Wochenschrift in 1947 19 showed that it was about <lb/>high altitude acclimatisation. A further two articles were <lb/>published before 1989 (both in the 1960s) and were <lb/>published in Spanish 20 and French 21 with no abstract. <lb/>These articles may also not have been on the topic of <lb/>climate change as they were published before the adop-<lb/>tion of the use of the term climate change as we use it <lb/>today. We expect that these errors will only have impacted <lb/>the very early publications, but for reasons of consistency <lb/>have not excluded them from the analysis as we did not <lb/>apply full text screening across the whole sample. <lb/>Extreme weather events-heatwaves, floods, wildfires <lb/>and extreme storms-have become more common with <lb/>climate change, but existed before climate change and <lb/>are not always linked to climate change. We reviewed a <lb/>sample of articles on extreme weather events and found <lb/>that only 2% mentioned these events being linked to <lb/>climate change. Other search strategies might lead to <lb/>these articles being included. <lb/>Our study includes the intervention of a group organ-<lb/>ising a joint editorial on climate change and health, <lb/>which was published in multiple journals in 2021 and <lb/>2022. We were able to examine whether journals that <lb/>published the first editorial, not having published before <lb/>on climate change and health, were prompted to publish <lb/>more articles on climate change and health. <lb/>We must be cautious in generalising to all health jour-<lb/>nals from our study. It was difficult to identify a represen-<lb/>tative list of health journals to include and our sampling <lb/>will inevitably have influenced the results. We did include <lb/>the most highly cited clinical journals and the top jour-<lb/>nals in general and internal medicine, which means that <lb/>we have a bias towards bigger journals and medical as <lb/>opposed to health journals. These journals are better <lb/>resourced than most health journals, which makes it likely <lb/>that we probably underestimated the number of health <lb/>journals that have never mentioned climate change. <lb/>We may also have excluded some relevant articles. For <lb/>example, by including only journals that are currently <lb/>indexed in MEDLINE, we excluded many journals that <lb/>published the joint editorials on climate change. 11 12 <lb/>However, we needed to do the article searches electroni-<lb/>cally as hand searching of the entire back archive of 330 <lb/>journals was not feasible. Not all articles in a journal are <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">BMJ Global Health: first published as 10.1136/bmjgh-2023-014498 on 22 February 2024. Downloaded from https://gh.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="footnote">Muhia J, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2024;9:e014498. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2023-014498 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">BMJ Global Health <lb/></note>
    
    <body>always indexed in MEDLINE even if the journal itself is <lb/>indexed. Some journals are indexed with multiple titles <lb/>in MEDLINE and there is no systematic way of identifying <lb/>these, so some journal names may have been omitted. <lb/>We excluded all the results from our extreme weather-<lb/>related search, as our assessment of a random sample of <lb/>5% of these articles indicated that only 2% were poten-<lb/>tially eligible for inclusion. However, we know that we <lb/>missed a very small proportion of articles by excluding <lb/>these results. <lb/>A limitation of our study is that we have not been able <lb/>to examine the types of articles published, so our study <lb/>does not differentiate between research articles and <lb/>editorials, comments, news, letters and other types of arti-<lb/>cles. We know that only 46% of the articles had abstracts, <lb/>which suggests that fewer than half of the articles were <lb/>research studies. We know too that funding for research <lb/>on climate change and health has been slow to become <lb/>available, 22 meaning that early articles-those before <lb/>2010-were likely to be editorials and comments rather <lb/>than research. This may also explain why particular jour-<lb/>nals have published more-for instance, both the Lancet <lb/>and The BMJ publish news. <lb/>Nor do we know the themes of the articles, but we know <lb/>from the Lancet Countdown 3 that the majority of articles <lb/>published have been about the impact of climate change <lb/>on health, far fewer on mitigating the effects of climate <lb/>change, and fewer still on adapting to the changes that <lb/>have already happened. Almost no articles so far have <lb/>been on decarbonising health systems. <lb/>Another limitation of the study may have been uncon-<lb/>scious bias as several of the authors were linked with the <lb/>BMJ and the UK Health Alliance on Climate Change (see <lb/>the Competing interest section). <lb/>Study implications <lb/>Why have most health journals published little or nothing on <lb/>climate change and health? <lb/>Despite climate change being predicted in the 19th <lb/>century, detectable effects occurring by the 80s, and the <lb/>first Earth Summit being held in 1992, few articles on <lb/>climate change and health appeared in health journals <lb/>until the 2000s. Indeed, despite climate change being <lb/>identified as the major threat to global health, by 2022 <lb/>about a quarter of health journals in our sample had <lb/>published nothing on climate change and health and <lb/>almost three quarters had published five or fewer articles. <lb/>Why have health journals been so slow? There are <lb/>almost certainly multiple reasons. <lb/>One answer might be that almost everybody has been <lb/>slow. Although the serious threat of climate change has <lb/>long been identified, emissions of greenhouse gases are <lb/>still rising. 3 The annual UN meeting on climate change, <lb/>COP, featured health in the main agenda for the first <lb/>time only in 2023. Of course, the policymakers may have <lb/>been slow because health scientists have been slow. <lb/>Another reason may be that journals found the subject <lb/>of climate change &apos;too political&apos;. 23 Although scientists <lb/>have been clear since the 90s that climate change is <lb/>damaging health, many politicians denied the existence <lb/>of climate change, that it is caused by human activity, and <lb/>that it matters. Some still do. This may have made editors <lb/>of health journals nervous about covering the subject. <lb/>That journals based in the USA, where climate change <lb/>has been a party political issue, have been slower than <lb/>journals based in Britain, where there has been consensus <lb/>on the importance of climate change, offers support for <lb/>this possible reason. <lb/>Although general, public and global health, and epide-<lb/>miology journals could feel comfortable covering climate <lb/>change and health, specialist journals may have worried <lb/>that the topic was not relevant to their readers. The health <lb/>community has now recognised that health systems have <lb/>to decarbonise, which means that every specialty will have <lb/>to explore how it can do so, making the subject directly <lb/>relevant to all parts of healthcare. <lb/>More than half of the articles we identified are not <lb/>research articles but editorials, news, letters, comments <lb/>and educational articles. Many health journals publish <lb/>little but research articles, and, as we and others have <lb/>shown, there has been little research on climate change <lb/>and health until recently. <lb/>One important reason for the slow and limited coverage <lb/>of climate change and health is that many journals <lb/>commission few articles. They wait for material, usually <lb/>research papers, to be submitted. A related reason is that <lb/>even if they do commission material, many health editors <lb/>would not know whom to ask to write on the subject: <lb/>there have been, and still are, few authorities on climate <lb/>change and health. <lb/>Increasing coverage of climate change and health in health <lb/>journals? <lb/>As health journals are a major source of information <lb/>to health professionals, we think it important that all <lb/>health journals include material on all aspects of this <lb/>subject. Specialist journals will need to cover the impact <lb/>on their specialty and explore how the specialty can <lb/>progress to net zero. Coverage of climate change and <lb/>health is increasing in health journals and is likely to <lb/>continue to increase because of growing global concern <lb/>about the seriousness of the climate crisis, and because <lb/>of the recognition of the need for decarbonising health-<lb/>care. <lb/>It seems that many journals are willing to publish <lb/>further articles on climate change and health but lack <lb/>the capacity to commission such articles. This finding <lb/>supports a proposal to establish a consortium that would <lb/>lead the publishing of joint editorials on the subject, <lb/>perhaps more than once a year, and commission and <lb/>share articles with the many journals that lack the capacity <lb/>to commission articles themselves. In this way, material <lb/>on climate change and health could reach many more <lb/>health professionals. <lb/></body>
    
    <div type="annex">Twitter Joy Muhia @muhiajoy and Ben Rossington @BenRossington1 <lb/></div>
    
    <note place="headnote">BMJ Global Health: first published as 10.1136/bmjgh-2023-014498 on 22 February 2024. Downloaded from https://gh.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Muhia J, et al. BMJ Glob Health 2024;9:e014498. doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2023-014498 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">BMJ Global Health <lb/></note>
    
    <div type="contribution">Contributors SS, JM, MLR, BR, RS designed the study and developed the search <lb/>strategy. MLR wrote the search strategy and conducted the literature searches. <lb/>SS, MLR and JM extracted data. RS, BR, JM, FW, AP, MLR screened the articles for <lb/>eligibility. SS analysed the data with JM. SS is the study guarantor. All authors had <lb/>direct access to the data, interpreted the findings and contributed to the writing <lb/>of the manuscript. The corresponding author attests that all listed authors meet <lb/>authorship criteria and that no others meeting the criteria have been omitted. <lb/></div>
    
    <div type="funding">Funding The authors have not declared a specific grant for this research from any <lb/>funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors. <lb/></div>
    
    <div type="conflict">Competing interests All authors have completed the ICMJE uniform disclosure <lb/>form at www. icmje. org/ disclosure-of-interest/ and declare: no support from any <lb/>organisation for the submitted work; SS is a full time employee of BMJ Publishing <lb/>Group which published many of the articles included in this study. MLR is working <lb/>on a self-funded PhD in conjunction with BMJ Publishing Group and Maastricht <lb/>University. AP is working as a policy officer with the UK Health Alliance on Climate <lb/>Change (UKHACC). RS was the editor of The BMJ from 1991 to 2004, an assistant <lb/>editor before that from 1979, and is now chair of the UK Health Alliance on Climate <lb/>Change, which organised and funded the joint editorial that has appeared in <lb/>multiple journals. RS has long been concerned about environmental issues. FW <lb/>recently completed a year as a sustainability fellowship at The BMJ, and she <lb/>remains a freelance clinical editor at The BMJ. BR worked at UKHACC for 2 months <lb/>in autumn 2022 and supported work on the second joint editorial. JM helped with <lb/>the second joint editorial. <lb/></div>
    
    <div type="annex">Patient and public involvement Patients and/or the public were involved in the <lb/>design, or conduct, or reporting, or dissemination plans of this research. Refer to <lb/>the Methods section for further details. <lb/>Patient consent for publication Not applicable. <lb/>Ethics approval Not applicable. <lb/>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. <lb/></div>
    
    <div type="availability">Data availability statement Data are available in a public, open access <lb/>repository. The data that support the findings of this study are available on <lb/>OSF:https://doi.org/10.17605/OSF.IO/GSFYQ <lb/></div>
    
    <div type="annex">Supplemental material This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has <lb/>not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been <lb/>peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those <lb/>of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and <lb/>responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content <lb/>includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability <lb/>of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, <lb/>terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error <lb/>and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise. <lb/></div>

			<front>Open access This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which <lb/>permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, <lb/>and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is <lb/>properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the <lb/>use is non-commercial. See: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/. <lb/>ORCID iD <lb/>Joy Muhia http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8788-6956 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1 Costello A, Abbas M, Allen A, et al. Managing the health effects of <lb/>climate change. Lancet 2009;373:1693-733. <lb/>2 Wang H, Horton R. Tackling climate change: the greatest opportunity <lb/>for global health. Lancet 2015;386:1798-9. <lb/>3 Romanello M, Di Napoli C, Drummond P, et al. The 2022 report of <lb/>the lancet countdown on health and climate change: health at the <lb/>mercy of fossil fuels. Lancet 2022;400:1619-54. <lb/>4 Health Care Without Harm and Arup. Health care&apos;s climate footprint: <lb/>how the health sector contributes to the global climate crisis and <lb/>opportunities for action. 2019. Available: https://noharm-global. <lb/>org/sites/default/files/documents-files/5961/HealthCaresClimateFo <lb/>otprint_092319.pdf [Accessed 18 Oct 2023]. <lb/>5 NHS England. Delivering a &apos;net zero&apos; national health service. London <lb/>NHS England; 2019. Available: https://www.england.nhs.uk/ <lb/>greenernhs/wp-content/uploads/sites/51/2022/07/B1728-delivering-<lb/>a-net-zero-nhs-july-2022.pdf [Accessed 18 Oct 2023]. <lb/>6 Krajick K. James hansen&apos;s climate warning, 30 years later. Columbia <lb/>Climate School; 2018. Available: https://news.climate.columbia. <lb/>edu/2018/06/26/james-hansens-climate-warning-30-years-later/ <lb/>[Accessed 18 Oct 2023]. <lb/>7 Berrang-Ford L, Sietsma AJ, Callaghan M, et al. Systematic mapping <lb/>of global research on climate and health: a machine learning review. <lb/>Lancet Planet Health 2021;5:e514-25. <lb/>8 Verner G, Schütte S, Knop J, et al. Health in climate change research <lb/>from 1990 to 2014: positive trend, but still underperforming. Glob <lb/>Health Action 2016;9:30723. <lb/>9 Harper SL, Cunsolo A, Babujee A, et al. Climate change and <lb/>health in North America: literature review protocol. Syst Rev <lb/>2021;10:3. <lb/>10 Bartlett VL, Gupta R, Wallach J, et al. Published research on the <lb/>human health implications of climate change from 2012-2019: a <lb/>cross-sectional study. MedRxiv [Preprint] 2022. <lb/>11 Atwoli L, Baqui AH, Benfield T, et al. Call for emergency action to <lb/>limit global temperature increases, restore biodiversity, and protect <lb/>health. BMJ 2021;374:n1734. <lb/>12 Atwoli L, Erhabor GE, Gbakima AA, et al. COP27 climate change <lb/>conference: urgent action needed for Africa and the world. BMJ <lb/>2022;379:o2459. <lb/>13 Einecker R, Kirby A. Climate change: a bibliometric study <lb/>of adaptation, mitigation and resilience. Sustainability <lb/>2020;12:6935. <lb/>14 Fu HZ, Waltman L. A large-scale bibliometric analysis of global <lb/>climate change research between 2001 and 2018. Clim Change <lb/>2022;170:36. <lb/>15 Sangam SL, Savitha KS. Climate change and global warming: a <lb/>scientometric study. CJSIM 2019;13:199-212. <lb/>16 Sweileh WM. Bibliometric analysis of peer-reviewed literature on <lb/>climate change and human health with an emphasis on infectious <lb/>diseases. Global Health 2020;16:44. <lb/>17 Sweileh WM. Bibliometric analysis of peer-reviewed literature on <lb/>food security in the context of climate change from 1980 to 2019. <lb/>Agric Food Secur 2020;9:9. <lb/>18 Li F, Zhou H, Huang D-S, et al. Global research output and theme <lb/>trends on climate change and infectious diseases: a retrospective <lb/>bibliometric and co-word biclustering investigation of papers <lb/>indexed in PubMed (1999-2018). Int J Environ Res Public Health <lb/>2020;17:5228. <lb/>19 Neergaard KV. Dangers of climate change [in German]. Schweiz Med <lb/>Wochenschr 1947;77:1160. <lb/>20 Hollander JL. The effect of climate changes upon the evolution of <lb/>rheumatoid arthritis [in Spanish]. Rev Med Chil 1964;92:180-3. <lb/>21 Cuenot A. [Psychism and change of climate]. Presse Med <lb/>1961;69:35-8. <lb/>22 Ebi KL, Semenza JC, Rocklöv J. Current medical research funding <lb/>and frameworks are insufficient to address the health risks of global <lb/>environmental change. Environ Health 2016;15:108. <lb/>23 Hai Z, Perlman RL. Extreme weather events and the politics of <lb/>climate change attribution. Sci Adv 2022;8:eabo2190. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">BMJ Global Health: first published as 10.1136/bmjgh-2023-014498 on 22 February 2024. Downloaded from https://gh.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. </note>


	</text>

</TEI>