<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Mouse blood cells types and aging prediction using penalized Latent Dirichlet Allocation</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Xiaotian</forename>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Yee Voan</forename>
            <surname>Teo</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Nicola</forename>
            <surname>Neretti</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Zhijin</forename>
            <surname>Wu</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-31T11:14:50.757261Z">31.10.2025 11:14:50</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1186$1$s12864-024-10763-8</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Springer Science and Business Media LLC</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1186/s12864-024-10763-8</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Xiaotian Wu, Yee Voan Teo, Nicola Neretti, Zhijin Wu. (2024). Mouse blood cells types and aging prediction using penalized Latent Dirichlet Allocation. BMC Genomics, 23(S4), None. DOI: 10.1186/s12864-024-10763-8</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-31T11:14:50.757261Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-31T11:14:50.757261Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>Eur. Phys. J. C (2024) 84:91 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1140/epjc/s10052-024-12462-w <lb/>Regular Article -Theoretical Physics <lb/>T-duality constraint on effective Lagrangians <lb/>Mohammad R. Garousi a <lb/>Department of Physics, Faculty of Science, Ferdowsi University of Mashhad, P.O. Box 1436, Mashhad, Iran <lb/>Received: 29 November 2023 / Accepted: 18 January 2024 / Published online: 28 January 2024 <lb/>© The Author(s) 2024 <lb/>Abstract Recent studies have highlighted the significant <lb/>role of utilizing O(1, 1) symmetry in the circular reduction <lb/>of effective actions to determine NS-NS couplings in the <lb/>effective action of string theory. However, these calculations <lb/>often result in residual terms as total derivatives that do not <lb/>conform to O(1, 1) transformations. In this paper, we present <lb/>explicit calculations at α order, demonstrating the enforce-<lb/>ability of this symmetry on effective Lagrangians to establish <lb/>the parameters governing covariant couplings in any scheme. <lb/>Notably, we discover the O(1, 1)-invariant Lagrangians cor-<lb/>responding to the Metsaev-Tseytlin action and the Meissner <lb/>action. <lb/></front>

    <body>1 Introduction <lb/>It is well-known that the classical effective action of string <lb/>theory, when dimensionally reduced on a torus T (d) , exhibits <lb/>a global symmetry called O(d, d) [1,2]. By assuming that <lb/>the effective action of string theory at the critical dimen-<lb/>sion is background independent, one can consider a back-<lb/>ground with toroidal compactification T (d) and impose the <lb/>non-geometric subgroup of the O(d, d) symmetry on the <lb/>reduction of the most general covariant and gauge-invariant <lb/>couplings. Each coupling has its own arbitrary coefficients, <lb/>and this allows for determining the connections between the <lb/>coefficients of the independent couplings. <lb/>This approach has been applied in previous works [3-<lb/>5] for the case of d = 1, where connections between the <lb/>NS-NS couplings at order α 2 in bosonic and heterotic theo-<lb/>ries, as well as the couplings at order α 3 in superstring the-<lb/>ory, were established. In these calculations, the initial steps <lb/>involve employing the Bianchi identities, the most general <lb/>higher-derivative field redefinitions, and eliminating total <lb/>derivative terms from the most general covariant action to <lb/>a e-mail: garousi@um.ac.ir (corresponding author) <lb/>obtain the minimal independent couplings in the action in <lb/>a particular scheme [6]. The subsequent application of the <lb/>non-geometric part of the O(1, 1) symmetry, known as the <lb/>Buscher rules [7,8], determines the independent couplings <lb/>up to only one unambiguous parameter, which can be fixed <lb/>by other means such as the S-matrix method. Furthermore, <lb/>these calculations extended the Buscher rules to incorporate <lb/>higher-derivative corrections that depend on the scheme of <lb/>the covariant couplings [9]. However, the circular reduction <lb/>of the couplings obtained in [3-5] is O(1, 1) invariant, except <lb/>for some anomalous terms in the form of total derivative <lb/>terms in the base space. In closed spacetime manifolds, the <lb/>anomalous total derivative terms are negligible, leading to <lb/>effective actions that exhibit invariance under O(1, 1) trans-<lb/>formations. The background independence assumption of the <lb/>effective action suggests that this symmetry should also hold <lb/>in open spacetime manifolds. However, in these manifolds, <lb/>the total derivative terms cannot be ignored. Therefore, one <lb/>can approach the problem in two ways. <lb/>The first approach involves utilizing Stokes&apos; theorem to <lb/>transfer the anomalous total derivative terms to the bound-<lb/>ary. By introducing appropriate boundary terms that undergo <lb/>O(1, 1) transformations and possess anomalies under these <lb/>transformations, it is possible to cancel out the aforemen-<lb/>tioned anomalous terms on the boundary. In this way, one <lb/>may be able to find the Gibbons-Hawking-like boundary <lb/>terms [10-13]. <lb/>Alternatively, there is a Lagrangian corresponding to each <lb/>effective action. This Lagrangian may maintain invariance <lb/>under O(1, 1) transformations without any anomaly. This <lb/>paper focuses on exploring this latter possibility, highlighting <lb/>the existence of Lagrangians for the effective actions in each <lb/>scheme that satisfy O(1, 1) symmetry. <lb/>The most general covariant and gauge-invariant <lb/>Lagrangians in the bulk, at order α m , can contain terms <lb/>with up to 2m + 2 derivatives. The coefficients of these cou-<lb/>plings are interconnected only through the Bianchi identi-<lb/></body>

    123 <lb/>

    91 <page>Page 2 of 11 <lb/></page>

    <note place="headnote">Eur. Phys. J. C (2024) 84 :91 <lb/></note>

    <body>ties and field redefinitions. By exploiting the Bianchi iden-<lb/>tities, one can reduce the couplings that are solely related <lb/>to each other by these identities to a set of independent <lb/>couplings. However, the coefficients of the resulting cou-<lb/>plings are either unambiguous, meaning they are invariant <lb/>under field redefinitions, or they are ambiguous, meaning <lb/>they change under field redefinitions. Moreover, under field <lb/>redefinitions, the ambiguous parameters are further divided <lb/>into essential parameters and arbitrary parameters. The num-<lb/>ber of essential parameters at each order of α is fixed. The <lb/>choice of which set of ambiguous parameters is selected as <lb/>essential parameters specifies the scheme of the Lagrangian. <lb/>If one sets all arbitrary parameters to zero, the unambigu-<lb/>ous and essential couplings in the Lagrangian then appear <lb/>in the minimal scheme. The other choices for the arbitrary <lb/>parameters correspond to other schemes that are related to <lb/>the minimal scheme by field redefinitions. Note that the num-<lb/>ber of couplings in the Lagrangian in the minimal scheme is <lb/>greater than the number of couplings in the action in the min-<lb/>imal scheme [6], in which the total derivative terms are also <lb/>removed by using integration by parts. <lb/>In the case where field redefinitions are used, the O(1, 1) <lb/>symmetry can determine all parameters in the Lagrangian in <lb/>the minimal scheme and all parameters in the generalized <lb/>Buscher rules in terms of one unambiguous parameter and <lb/>some arbitrary parameters at each order of α . The presence <lb/>of these arbitrary parameters reflects the fact that the total <lb/>derivative terms in the Lagrangian are not removed. However, <lb/>when working with an effective action that incorporates the <lb/>Bianchi identities, field redefinitions, and the removal of total <lb/>derivative terms to obtain the action in the minimal scheme <lb/>[6], then the O(1, 1) symmetry can determine the couplings <lb/>in the minimal scheme in terms of only one unambiguous <lb/>parameter at each order of α [3-5]. <lb/>On the other hand, in the case where field redefinitions are <lb/>not employed in the Lagrangian at all, the O(1, 1) symmetry <lb/>can determine the independent couplings in the Lagrangian <lb/>and all parameters in the generalized Buscher rules in terms <lb/>of one unambiguous parameter and some additional arbitrary <lb/>parameters compared to the previous case. These arbitrary <lb/>parameters reflect the fact that no field redefinition and no <lb/>integration by parts have been used to reduce the independent <lb/>couplings in the Lagrangian. In other words, if one uses field <lb/>redefinitions and integration by parts on the resulting action, <lb/>then all arbitrary parameters can be shifted to zero or any <lb/>other values. In this paper, we specifically focus on this latter <lb/>scenario. <lb/>In this scenario, it becomes straightforward to find the <lb/>T-duality invariant Lagrangian corresponding to the effec-<lb/>tive action in a particular scheme that is invariant under T-<lb/>duality [9,14], up to some anomalous total derivative terms in <lb/>the base space. The determination of this T-duality invariant <lb/>Lagrangian is based on the same generalized Buscher rules <lb/>as the T-duality invariant action in that specific scheme. By <lb/>understanding the generalized Buscher rules of the effective <lb/>action in a specific scheme, we can determine the major-<lb/>ity of the arbitrary parameters in the T-duality invariant <lb/>Lagrangian. Consequently, we are able to identify the T-<lb/>duality invariant Lagrangian that corresponds to the effective <lb/>action in that scheme. <lb/>To utilize T-duality, one needs to dimensionally reduce the <lb/>couplings in the Lagrangians on a circle. To perform circular <lb/>reduction, we adopt the circular reduction scheme specifi-<lb/>cally designed for the massless NS-NS fields, as introduced <lb/>by Maharana and Schwarz [15], i.e., <lb/>G μν = ḡab + e ϕ g a g b e ϕ g a <lb/>e ϕ g b <lb/>e ϕ <lb/>, <lb/>B μν = bab + 1 <lb/>2 b a g b -1 <lb/>2 b b g a b a <lb/>-b b <lb/>0 <lb/>, <lb/>= φ + ϕ/4. <lb/>(1) <lb/>The Buscher rules in this reduction represent the following <lb/>transformations: <lb/>ϕ = -ϕ , g a = b a , b a = g a , ḡ ab = ḡab , b ab = bab <lb/>φ = φ. <lb/>(2) <lb/>Here, ḡab represents the base space metric, φ is the base space <lb/>dilaton, bab is the base space B-field, and g a and b b are two <lb/>vectors, while ϕ is a scalar in this space. The transformations <lb/>mentioned above obviously form the Z 2 -group O(1, 1, Z), <lb/>meaning that (ψ ) = ψ, where ψ represents any field in the <lb/>base space. The generalized Buscher rules can have defor-<lb/>mations involving derivatives of the base space fields such <lb/>that they satisfy the same constraint (ψ ) = ψ. <lb/>The covariant effective Lagrangian at the leading order of <lb/>α in the bulk contains terms with up to second derivatives, <lb/>as follows: <lb/>L (0) = -<lb/>2 <lb/>κ 2 e -2 √ <lb/>-G a 1 R + a 2 ∇ μ ∇ μ <lb/>+a 3 H 2 + a 4 ∇ μ ∇ μ <lb/>. <lb/>(3) <lb/>where κ is related to the D-dimensional Newton&apos;s constant. <lb/>The invariance of these background independent couplings <lb/>under the Buscher rules (2) fixes the Lagrangian, up to an <lb/>overall factor, to be [16]: <lb/>L (0) = -<lb/>2a 1 <lb/>κ 2 e -2 √ <lb/>-G R -4∇ μ ∇ μ <lb/>-<lb/>1 <lb/>12 <lb/>H 2 + 4∇ μ ∇ μ <lb/>. <lb/>(4) <lb/>For a 1 = 1, the first term corresponds to the Einstein term. <lb/>The aforementioned T-duality invariant Lagrangian is essen-<lb/>tially equivalent to the standard leading-order Lagrangian, <lb/></body>

    123 <lb/>

    <note place="headnote">Eur. Phys. J. C (2024) 84 :91 <lb/></note>

    <page>Page 3 of 11</page> 91 <lb/>

    <body>except for a total derivative term. As we consider higher <lb/>orders of α , we anticipate that the Lagrangian will con-<lb/>tinue to exhibit invariance under O(1, 1, Z) transformations. <lb/>This invariance will determine both the Lagrangian itself and <lb/>the α -deformations of the Buscher rules. Additionally, we <lb/>expect the existence of T-duality invariant Lagrangians that <lb/>correspond to any known covariant effective action in the <lb/>literature. <lb/>The rest of the paper is structured as follows: In the next <lb/>section (Sect. 2), we employ the Bianchi identities to deter-<lb/>mine 31 even-parity independent covariant couplings with <lb/>arbitrary coefficients in the Lagrangian at order α . In the <lb/>heterotic theory at this order, there is only one odd-parity <lb/>coupling with a fixed coefficient. In Sect. 3, we perform a <lb/>reduction on a circle and impose constraints to ensure invari-<lb/>ance under the generalized Buscher rules. We explore all <lb/>possible deformations of the Buscher rules at order α for the <lb/>base space fields that satisfy the Z 2 -constraint (ψ ) = ψ. <lb/>In Sect. 3.1, our focus lies on the even-parity couplings, <lb/>and we conduct the necessary calculations. Our findings <lb/>reveal that the O(1, 1, Z) symmetry establishes 16 relations <lb/>among the 31 parameters of the Lagrangian. Consequently, <lb/>the T-duality invariant Lagrangian and the corresponding <lb/>generalized Buscher rules involve only one unambiguous <lb/>parameter and 14 arbitrary parameters. In Sect. 3.1.1, by <lb/>selecting specific relations between these arbitrary parame-<lb/>ters and the unambiguous parameter to align the generalized <lb/>Buscher rules with those of the Metsaev-Tseytlin and Meiss-<lb/>ner actions discovered in [9,14], we find that the correspond-<lb/>ing Lagrangians possess one unambiguous parameter and <lb/>three arbitrary parameters. Furthermore, by assigning spe-<lb/>cific values to these arbitrary parameters, we demonstrate that <lb/>the resulting Lagrangians become identical to the Metsaev-<lb/>Tseytlin and Meissner Lagrangians, albeit with some total <lb/>derivative terms. Sect. 3.2 is dedicated to examining the <lb/>O(1, 1, Z) symmetry of the odd-parity Lagrangian in the <lb/>heterotic theory. In Sect. 4, we provide a brief discussion of <lb/>our results. We have used the package &quot;xAct&quot; [17] for per-<lb/>forming the calculations in this paper. <lb/>2 Independent couplings <lb/>Using the package &quot;xAct,&quot; one finds that there are 41 covari-<lb/>ant and gauge-invariant couplings of the massless NS-NS <lb/>fields at order α . However, some of these couplings are inter-<lb/>connected through the Bianchi identities, resulting in redun-<lb/>dant terms. By eliminating these redundancies, we identify 31 <lb/>independent geometrical couplings. There are different sets <lb/>for choosing these 31 couplings. All these sets are related to <lb/>each other by using the Bianchi identities. The couplings in <lb/>a particular set are: <lb/>L (1) <lb/>e = -<lb/>2α <lb/>κ 2 e -2 √ <lb/>-G a 1 H α <lb/>δ H αβγ H βδ <lb/>ε H γ ε <lb/>+ a 2 H αβ <lb/>δ H αβγ H γ <lb/>ε H δ ε + a 3 H αβγ H αβγ H δ ε H δ ε <lb/>+ a 4 H α <lb/>γ δ H βγ δ R αβ + a 5 R αβ R αβ <lb/>+ a 6 H αβγ H αβγ R + a 7 R 2 + a 8 R αβγ δ R αβγ δ <lb/>+ a 9 H βγ δ H βγ δ ∇ α ∇ α + a 10 R∇ α ∇ α <lb/>+ a 11 H βγ δ H βγ δ ∇ α ∇ α + a 12 R∇ α ∇ α <lb/>+ a 13 ∇ α ∇ β ∇ β ∇ α + a 14 ∇ α ∇ β R α <lb/>β <lb/>+ a 15 ∇ β ∇ α R αβ + a 16 R αβ ∇ β ∇ α <lb/>+ a 17 ∇ α ∇ α ∇ β ∇ β + a 18 ∇ α ∇ α ∇ β ∇ β <lb/>+ a 19 ∇ α ∇ β ∇ β ∇ α + a 20 ∇ β ∇ β ∇ α ∇ α <lb/>+ a 21 H α <lb/>γ δ H βγ δ ∇ α ∇ β + a 22 ∇ α ∇ α ∇ β ∇ β <lb/>+ a 23 ∇ α ∇ β ∇ α ∇ β + a 24 H α <lb/>γ δ H βγ δ ∇ β ∇ α <lb/>+ a 25 ∇ β ∇ α ∇ β ∇ α + a 26 H αβγ ∇ γ ∇ δ H αβ <lb/>δ <lb/>+ a 27 H βγ δ ∇ α ∇ δ H αβγ + a 28 ∇ α H αβγ ∇ δ H βγ <lb/>δ <lb/>+ a 29 H α <lb/>βγ ∇ α ∇ δ H βγ <lb/>δ + a 30 H αβγ ∇ δ ∇ δ H αβγ <lb/>+ a 31 ∇ δ H αβγ ∇ δ H αβγ . <lb/>(5) <lb/>The parameters a 1 , . . . , a 31 are independent of the back-<lb/>ground and cannot be determined by gauge symmetry. <lb/>Among these parameters, a 1 and a 8 are unambiguous, while <lb/>the remaining parameters are ambiguous as they are related <lb/>by field redefinitions. Some of the ambiguous terms are also <lb/>interconnected through total derivative terms. In fact, if we <lb/>were to remove those terms that are related by integration by <lb/>parts, we would be left with only 20 independent terms [6]. <lb/>However, as mentioned in the previous section, in such a case, <lb/>T-duality is only free from anomalies if we consider the com-<lb/>bination of bulk and boundary actions to be invariant under <lb/>T-duality transformations [12]. However, in this paper, our <lb/>specific focus is on constraining the bulk Lagrangian alone <lb/>to be invariant under T-duality transformations. Therefore, <lb/>we are not permitted to eliminate the total derivative terms <lb/>in Eq. (5). Additionally, if we were to utilize the freedom <lb/>of field redefinitions, we would be left with a Lagrangian in <lb/>the minimal scheme, which has 17 independent terms. How-<lb/>ever, since our objective is to discover the T-duality invariant <lb/>Lagrangian for an arbitrary scheme, we do not employ the <lb/>freedom of field redefinitions. <lb/>The aforementioned couplings apply to both bosonic and <lb/>heterotic effective actions. However, the heterotic string the-<lb/>ory exhibits a gauge symmetry anomaly that can be canceled <lb/>by assuming the gauge group to be SO(32) or E 8 × E 8 , and <lb/>by introducing non-standard gauge transformations and local <lb/>Lorentz transformations for the B-field [18]. In this paper, we <lb/>focus on the case of zero gauge field. Under this assumption, <lb/>the non-standard local Lorentz transformation for the B-field <lb/>requires the field strength of the B-field to be the following <lb/>[18]: <lb/></body>

    123 <lb/>

    91 <page>Page 4 of 11 <lb/></page>

    <note place="headnote">Eur. Phys. J. C (2024) 84 :91 <lb/></note>

    <body>Ĥμνα (ω) = H μνα + <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>α O μνα (ω), <lb/>(6) <lb/>where the Chern-Simons three-form O is <lb/>O μνα (ω) = ω [μi <lb/>j ∂ ν ω α] j <lb/>i + <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>ω [μi <lb/>j ω ν j <lb/>k ω α]k <lb/>i ; <lb/>ω μi <lb/>j = ∂ μ e ν <lb/>j e ν <lb/>i -μν <lb/>ρ e α <lb/>j e ν <lb/>i , <lb/>(7) <lb/>where e μ <lb/>i e ν <lb/>j η i j = G μν . By substituting Eq. (6) into Eq. (4), <lb/>the gauge symmetry of the B-field yields the following bulk <lb/>coupling at order α : <lb/>L (1) <lb/>o = -<lb/>2α <lb/>κ 2 <lb/>√ <lb/>-G e -2 -<lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>H μνα O μνα (ω) . <lb/>(8) <lb/>This coupling is odd under parity. It is worth noting that the <lb/>Bianchi identities imply that there are no other odd-parity <lb/>couplings at this order. In the following, we will thoroughly <lb/>investigate the invariance of the couplings given by Eqs. (5) <lb/>and (8) under O(1, 1, Z) transformations after employing <lb/>circular reduction. <lb/>3 T-duality constraint <lb/>We now impose the constraint that the bulk effective <lb/>Lagrangians are fully invariant under the O(1, 1, Z) trans-<lb/>formations. In order to achieve this, we perform a reduction <lb/>of the D-dimensional theory on a circle with a U (1) isome-<lb/>try, resulting in a (D -1)-dimensional effective Lagrangian <lb/>L eff (ψ). We then subject L eff (ψ) to O(1, 1, Z) transforma-<lb/>tions, yielding L eff (ψ ). The O(1, 1, Z) invariance of the <lb/>Lagrangian can be expressed as follows: <lb/>L eff (ψ) -L eff (ψ ) = 0. <lb/>(9) <lb/>If the effective Lagrangian and its circular reduction have the <lb/>following expansions in terms of α : <lb/>L eff = <lb/>∞ <lb/>n=0 <lb/>α n <lb/>n! <lb/>L (n) , L eff = <lb/>∞ <lb/>n=0 <lb/>α n <lb/>n! <lb/>L (n) , <lb/>(10) <lb/>then the constraint in Eq. (9) can be expressed as <lb/>∞ <lb/>n=0 <lb/>α n <lb/>n! <lb/>L (n) (ψ) -<lb/>∞ <lb/>n=0 <lb/>α n <lb/>n! <lb/>L (n) (ψ ) = 0. <lb/>(11) <lb/>Assuming the following generalized Buscher rules: <lb/>ψ = ψ 0 + <lb/>∞ <lb/>n=1 <lb/>α n <lb/>n! <lb/>ψ n , <lb/>(12) <lb/>where ψ 0 represents the Buscher rules as given in (2), and ψ n <lb/>denotes the corrections at order α n . Expanding the second <lb/>term in (11) around the Buscher transformations ψ 0 , that is, <lb/>L (n) (ψ ) = L (n) (ψ 0 ) + <lb/>∞ <lb/>m=1 <lb/>α m <lb/>m! <lb/>L (n,m) (ψ 0 ), <lb/>(13) <lb/>we obtain the following constraint: <lb/>∞ <lb/>n=0 <lb/>α n <lb/>n! <lb/>L (n) (ψ) -<lb/>∞ <lb/>n=0 <lb/>α n <lb/>n! <lb/>L (n) (ψ 0 ) <lb/>-<lb/>∞ <lb/>n=0,m=1 <lb/>α n+m <lb/>n!m! <lb/>L (n,m) (ψ 0 ) = 0. <lb/>(14) <lb/>To determine the appropriate constraints on the effective <lb/>Lagrangians, each term at every order of α must be set to <lb/>zero. <lb/>The constraint given by (14) at the leading order is: <lb/>L (0) (ψ) -L (0) (ψ 0 ) = 0, <lb/>(15) <lb/>where L (0) (ψ) represents the circular reduction of the <lb/>leading-order Lagrangian, and L (0) (ψ 0 ) is its transformation <lb/>under the Buscher rules given by (2). The reduction of the <lb/>leading-order Lagrangian, as expressed in (4), is [19] <lb/>L (0) (ψ) = -<lb/>2 <lb/>κ 2 e -2 φ -ḡ R -4∇ a φ∇ a φ -<lb/>1 <lb/>12 <lb/>H 2 <lb/>+4∇ a ∇ a φ -<lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>(e ϕ V 2 + e -ϕ W 2 ) -<lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>∇ a ϕ∇ a ϕ . <lb/>(16) <lb/>where κ is related to the (D-1)-dimensional Newton&apos;s con-<lb/>stant. In the given equation, the curvature and covariant <lb/>derivatives on the right-hand side are constructed using the <lb/>metric of the base space. As for the variables V , W , and H , <lb/>they are defined as follows: <lb/>V ab = ∂ a g b -∂ b g a , <lb/>W ab = ∂ a b b -∂ b b a , <lb/>Habc = 3∂ [a bbc] -<lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>g [a W bc] -<lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>b [a V bc] . <lb/>(17) <lb/>Since H is not the exterior derivative of a two-form, it satisfies <lb/>the following anomalous Bianchi identity [19]: <lb/>∂ [a Hbcd] = -<lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>V [ab W cd] . <lb/>(18) <lb/>Our notation for antisymmetry is such that, for example, <lb/>g [a W bc] = 1 <lb/>3 (g a W bc -g b W ac -g c W ba ). It is evident that the <lb/>reduction given by Eq. (16) satisfies the T-duality constraint <lb/>in Eq. (15). <lb/>The constraint (14) at order α is <lb/>L (1) (ψ) -L (1) (ψ 0 ) -L (0,1) (ψ 0 ) = 0, <lb/>(19) <lb/>where L (0,1) (ψ 0 ) is the Taylor expansion of the reduction <lb/>(16) at first order. Writing the first order corrections to the <lb/>Buscher rules as <lb/>ϕ = -ϕ + α ϕ, g a = b a + α e ϕ/2 g a , <lb/>b a = g a + α e -ϕ/2 b a , <lb/>H abc = Habc + α Habc , <lb/>φ = φ + α φ, ḡ ab = ḡab + α ḡab , <lb/>(20) <lb/></body>

    123 <lb/>

    <note place="headnote">Eur. Phys. J. C (2024) 84 :91 <lb/></note>

    <page>Page 5 of 11</page> 91 <lb/>

    <body>one finds L (0,1) (ψ 0 ) to be <lb/>L = -<lb/>2α <lb/>κ 2 e -2 φ -ḡ <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>e ϕ V 2 -e -ϕ W 2 ϕ <lb/>+ <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>∇ a ϕ∇ a ( ϕ) -<lb/>1 <lb/>6 <lb/>H abc <lb/>Habc <lb/>+e -ϕ W ab ∇ b (e ϕ/2 g a ) + e ϕ V ab ∇ b (e ϕ/2 b a ) <lb/>-8∇ a φ∇ a ( φ) + 4∇ a ∇ a ( φ) <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>ḡa <lb/>a -2 φ <lb/>R -4∇ a φ∇ a φ -<lb/>1 <lb/>12 <lb/>H 2 <lb/>+4∇ a ∇ a φ -<lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>(e ϕ V 2 + e -ϕ W 2 ) -<lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>∇ a ϕ∇ a ϕ <lb/>-ḡab <lb/>Rab -<lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>H 2 <lb/>ab -<lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(e ϕ V 2 <lb/>ab + e -ϕ W 2 <lb/>ab ) <lb/>+4∇ b ∇ a φ -4∇ a φ∇ b φ -<lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>∇ a ϕ∇ b ϕ <lb/>+2∇ a φ∇ a ( ḡb <lb/>b ) -4∇ a φ∇ b ( ḡa <lb/>b ) <lb/>+∇ b ∇ a ( ḡab ) -∇ b ∇ b ( ḡa <lb/>a ) . <lb/>(21) <lb/>As the generalized Buscher rules are required to form the <lb/>Z 2 -group, the corrections must satisfy the following relations <lb/>[9]: <lb/>φ(ψ) + φ(ψ 0 ) = 0, <lb/>ḡab (ψ) + ḡab (ψ 0 ) = 0, <lb/>-ϕ(ψ) + ϕ(ψ 0 ) = 0, <lb/>b a (ψ) + g a (ψ 0 ) = 0, <lb/>g a (ψ) + b a (ψ 0 ) = 0, <lb/>Habc (ψ) + Habc (ψ 0 ) = 0. <lb/>(22) <lb/>The correction Habc is related to the corrections g a and <lb/>b a through the following relation, which arises from the <lb/>Bianchi identity in Eq. (18): <lb/>Habc = Habc -3e -ϕ/2 W [ab b c] -3e ϕ/2 g [a V bc] . (23) <lb/>Here, Habc represents a U (1) × U (1) gauge invariant exact <lb/>3-form, meaning H = d B, where B is a U (1) × U (1) gauge <lb/>invariant 2-form at order α [4,19]. This 2-form, along with <lb/>the corrections φ, ḡab , ϕ, g a , and b a , contains con-<lb/>tractions involving the base space fields at order α . <lb/>While in the bosonic theory, L (1) consists only of even-<lb/>parity terms, in the heterotic theory, L (1) includes both even <lb/>and odd parity terms. Consequently, L (1) and the corrections <lb/>to the Buscher rules appearing in L (0,1) (ψ 0 ) contain both <lb/>even and odd parity terms. In the next subsection, we will <lb/>analyze the even-parity terms. <lb/>3.1 Even-parity couplings <lb/>By utilizing the reductions given in Eq. (1), it is straightfor-<lb/>ward to determine the circular reduction of Eq. (5) and obtain <lb/>L (1) (ψ). We can then transform L (1) (ψ) under the Buscher <lb/>rules in Eq. (2) to obtain L (1) (ψ 0 ). <lb/>To calculate the corresponding even-parity contribution <lb/>from L (0,1) (ψ 0 ), we need to write φ, ḡab , ϕ, g a , b a , <lb/>and B in (21) as all possible contractions of the base space <lb/>fields R, H , W , V , ∇ϕ, and ∇ φ at order α , which satisfy <lb/>the constraint (22). The corrections φ, ḡab , ϕ, and b a <lb/>must have even-parity terms, while the corrections g a and <lb/>B must have odd-parity terms. In other words, one should <lb/>take into account the following corrections to the Buscher <lb/>rules: <lb/>φ = f 3 (e ϕ V 2 -e -ϕ W 2 ) + f 9 ∇ a ∇ a ϕ + f 6 ∇ a ϕ∇ a ϕ, <lb/>ϕ = e 1 <lb/>H 2 + e 2 R + e 3 (e ϕ V 2 + e -ϕ W 2 ) <lb/>+e 8 ∇ a ∇ a φ + e 5 ∇ a φ∇ a φ + e 7 ∇ a ϕ∇ a ϕ, <lb/>ḡab = d 5 (e ϕ V 2 <lb/>ab -e -ϕ W 2 <lb/>ab ) + d 6 ḡab (e ϕ V 2 -e -ϕ W 2 ) <lb/>+d 11 (∇ a ϕ∇ b φ + ∇ b ϕ∇ a φ) <lb/>+d 12 ḡab ∇ a ϕ∇ c φ + d 17 ∇ b ∇ a ϕ + d 18 ḡab ∇ c ∇ c ϕ, <lb/>g a = b 1 e ϕ/2 <lb/>Habc V bc + b 3 ∇ b (e -ϕ/2 W a <lb/>b ) <lb/>+b 2 e -ϕ/2 W ab ∇ b φ + b 4 e -ϕ/2 W ab ∇ b ϕ, <lb/>b a = -b 1 e -ϕ/2 <lb/>Habc W bc -b 3 ∇ b (e ϕ/2 V a <lb/>b ) <lb/>-b 2 e ϕ/2 V ab ∇ b φ + b 4 e ϕ/2 V ab ∇ b ϕ, <lb/>Bab = aa 1 (W a <lb/>c V bc -W b <lb/>c V ac ) + aa 4 Habc ∇ c ϕ. <lb/>(24) <lb/>Here, f 3 , . . . , aa 4 are 21 parameters that can be determined <lb/>by the constraint given in Eq. (19). It should be noted that the <lb/>mentioned deformations satisfy the Z 2 -constraint in Eq. (22). <lb/>When these deformations are inserted into Eq. (21), it can be <lb/>observed that L (0,1) (ψ 0 ) yields even-parity terms. <lb/>The constraint given by Eq. (19) then produces 37 rela-<lb/>tions between the parameters in the deformations and the <lb/>parameters in the Lagrangian (5) as follows: <lb/>a 20 = 2a 15 , a 21 = -48a 1 + 16a 2 <lb/>+a 10 /2 + a 12 /2 -a 17 /4 -a 18 /8, <lb/>a 22 = 2a 10 + 2a 12 -2a 17 -(3a 18 )/2, <lb/>a 23 = -8a 10 -4a 13 + 4a 14 + 8a 17 + 2a 18 , <lb/>a 25 = 2a 10 + 2a 12 + a 16 -a 17 -a 18 /2 + a 19 , <lb/>a 27 = -6a 11 -(9a 12 )/2 + (3a 13 )/2 -(9a 14 )/4 <lb/>+a 16 /4 -a 17 + a 18 /2 -a 19 /2 + a 24 , <lb/>a 28 = -12a 1 + 4a 2 , a 29 = 48a 1 -16a 2 , <lb/>a 30 = 8a 1 + (4a 2 )/3 -12a 3 + (11a 10 )/96 + (5a 11 )/4 <lb/>+(91a 12 )/96 -(7a 13 )/24 + (5a 14 )/12 <lb/>-a 16 /48 + (5a 17 )/32 -(41a 18 )/384 + (5a 19 )/48, <lb/>a 31 = 4a 1 + (4a 2 )/3 -12a 3 + (11a 10 )/96 <lb/>+(5a 11 )/4+(91a 12 )/96-(7a 13 )/24+(5a 14 )/12-a 16 /48 <lb/>+(5a 17 )/32-(41a 18 )/384+(5a 19 )/48, <lb/>a 4 = -24a 1 -4a 2 -a 16 /16, a 5 = a 16 /4, <lb/>a 6 = -((7a 10 )/48) -a 11 /4 -(5a 12 )/24 + a 13 /24 <lb/>-a 14 /12 -a 15 /12 + a 17 /48 + (5a 18 )/192 -a 19 /48, <lb/></body>

    123 <lb/>

    91 <page>Page 6 of 11 <lb/></page>

    <note place="headnote">Eur. Phys. J. C (2024) 84 :91 <lb/></note>

    <body>a 7 = (3a 10 )/8 + a 12 /8 -a 17 /8 -a 18 /32, <lb/>a 8 = 24a 1 , 9 = -(a 10 /12) -a 11 -(5a 12 )/12 + a 13 /12 <lb/>-a 14 /6 -a 15 /3 -a 17 /6 -a 19 /12, <lb/>aa 1 = -144a 1 , aa 4 = -144a 1 -24a 2 -(3a 10 )/2 <lb/>-(3a 13 )/8 + (3a 14 )/4 -(3a 16 )/8 + (3a 17 )/4 <lb/>-3a 24 -6a 26 , <lb/>b 1 = -12a 1 -a 26 , <lb/>b 2 = -96a 1 + 32a 2 + 2a 24 , <lb/>b 3 = 96a 1 -8a 2 + a 16 /8 + 2a 26 , <lb/>b 4 = 24a 1 + 8a 2 + a 10 /2 + a 13 /8 <lb/>-a 14 /4 -a 17 /4 + a 24 /2, <lb/>d 11 = a 10 + a 12 -a 17 /2 -a 18 /4, <lb/>d 12 = -2a 12 + a 13 /2 -a 14 -2a 15 -a 17 -a 19 /2, <lb/>d 17 = -a 10 -a 13 /4 + a 14 /2 + a 17 /2, <lb/>d 18 = a 10 + a 12 -a 13 /4 + a 14 /2 -a 17 /2 -a 18 /4, <lb/>d 5 = 24a 1 -8a 2 + a 16 /8, <lb/>d 6 = -18a 3 + (11a 10 )/64 + (3a 11 )/8 + (19a 12 )/64 <lb/>-a 13 /16 + a 14 /8 + a 15 /8 -a 17 /64 <lb/>-(9a 18 )/256 + a 19 /32, <lb/>e 1 = -12a 3 + a 10 /32 + a 11 /4 <lb/>+(19a 12 )/96 -a 13 /16 + a 14 /12 + a 17 /32 <lb/>-(3a 18 )/128 + a 19 /48, <lb/>e 2 = a 10 + a 13 /4 + a 15 -a 17 /2, <lb/>e 3 = 36a 1 -4a 2 -18a 3 -(5a 10 )/64 <lb/>+(3a 11 )/8 + (19a 12 )/64 -a 13 /8 + a 14 /8 -a 15 /8 <lb/>+a 16 /16 + (7a 17 )/64 -(9a 18 )/256 + a 19 /32, <lb/>e 5 = 8a 12 -3a 13 +4a 14 +2a 17 -a 18 +a 19 , <lb/>e 7 = 48a 1 +a 13 /16-a 14 /4+a 17 /8+a 18 /16+a 19 /16, <lb/>e 8 = -4a 12 + 2a 13 -2a 14 + 4a 15 + a 18 , <lb/>f 3 = 6a 1 -2a 2 -(207a 3 )/2 + (253a 10 )/256 <lb/>+(57a 11 )/32 + (365a 12 )/256 -(17a 13 )/64 + (19a 14 )/32 <lb/>+(23a 15 )/32 + a 16 /32 -(39a 17 )/256 <lb/>-(175a 18 )/1024 + (19a 19 )/128, <lb/>f 6 = -((23a 12 )/2) + (23a 13 )/8 -(23a 14 )/4 -(23a 15 )/2 <lb/>-6a 17 -a 18 /8 -(23a 19 )/8, <lb/>f 9 = 6a 10 + 6a 12 -(3a 13 )/2 + 3a 14 -3a 17 -(3a 18 )/2. (25) <lb/>By inserting the aforementioned relations into the Lagrangian <lb/>(5) and the α -correction of the Buscher rules (24), one can <lb/>derive the Lagrangian and the corresponding generalized <lb/>Buscher rules in terms of one unambiguous parameter, a 1 , as <lb/>well as 14 arbitrary parameters: <lb/>a 10 , a 11 , a 12 , a 13 , a 14 , a 15 , a 16 , a 17 , <lb/>a 18 , a 19 , a 2 , a 24 , a 26 , a 3 . <lb/>(26) <lb/>For any choice of these arbitrary parameters in terms of the <lb/>unambiguous parameter a 1 , one can find the T-duality invari-<lb/>ant Lagrangian and its corresponding generalized Buscher <lb/>rules within a specific scheme. It is evident that the coefficient <lb/>of the first term in Bab serves as the unambiguous parameter, <lb/>which cannot be set to zero. Furthermore, for any selection of <lb/>the arbitrary parameters, it is not possible to simultaneously <lb/>set all deformations ϕ, φ, ḡab , g a , and b a to zero. <lb/>However, it is feasible to choose certain arbitrary parame-<lb/>ters such that some of them are set to zero. For example, by <lb/>setting the following values for the arbitrary parameters: <lb/>a 11 = -32a 1 + <lb/>a 10 <lb/>12 <lb/>, a 12 = -a 10 , a 14 = <lb/>a 13 <lb/>2 <lb/>, <lb/>a 15 = 96a 1 -<lb/>a 13 <lb/>4 <lb/>, a 17 = 2(96a 1 + a 10 ), <lb/>a 18 = -4(96a 1 + a 10 ), a 19 = -768a 1 + a 13 , <lb/>a 2 = 9a 1 + <lb/>a 16 <lb/>64 <lb/>, a 24 = -96a 1 -<lb/>a 16 <lb/>4 <lb/>, <lb/>a 26 = -12a 1 , a 3 = <lb/>a 10 -864a 1 <lb/>1152 <lb/>, <lb/>(27) <lb/>one finds ϕ = φ = g a = b a = 0 and <lb/>ḡab = -48a 1 (e ϕ V 2 <lb/>ab -e -ϕ W 2 <lb/>ab -2∇ b ∇ a ϕ), <lb/>Bab = -144a 1 (W a <lb/>c V bc -V a <lb/>c W bc -Habc ∇ c ϕ). <lb/>(28) <lb/>By inserting the values (27) into (5), one can find its cor-<lb/>responding T-duality invariant Lagrangian in terms of the <lb/>unambiguous parameter a 1 and three arbitrary parameters <lb/>a 10 , a 13 , and a 16 . <lb/>A connection can be established between the arbitrary <lb/>parameters (26) and the unambiguous parameter a 1 by com-<lb/>paring the generalized Buscher rules with existing ones in <lb/>the literature. By imposing these relationships between the <lb/>arbitrary parameters, the T-duality invariant Lagrangian cor-<lb/>responding to those generalized Buscher rules can be derived. <lb/>However, it turns out that the number of these relationships is <lb/>less than 14, which means that the resulting T-duality invari-<lb/>ant Lagrangian will still have some arbitrary parameters. <lb/>Since there are generalized Buscher rules in the literature <lb/>associated with the Metsaev-Tseytlin action and the Meiss-<lb/>ner action, we will further investigate this in the subsequent <lb/>subsection. <lb/>3.1.1 Comparing with the Metsaev-Tseytlin action <lb/>It has been shown in [9] that the effective action at order <lb/>α in the Metsaev-Tseytlin scheme is invariant under the <lb/>O(1, 1, Z) transformation, except for some anomalous total <lb/>derivative terms in the base space. The corresponding gener-<lb/>alized Buscher rules are as follows: <lb/>ḡab = 48a 1 e ϕ V a <lb/>c V bc -e -ϕ W a <lb/>c W bc , <lb/>φ = 12a 1 e ϕ V 2 -e -ϕ W 2 , <lb/>ϕ = 48a 1 ∇ a ϕ∇ a ϕ + e ϕ V 2 + e -ϕ W 2 , <lb/></body>

    123 <lb/>

    <note place="headnote">Eur. Phys. J. C (2024) 84 :91 <lb/></note>

    <page>Page 7 of 11</page> 91 <lb/>

    <body>g a = 24a 1 2e -ϕ/2 ∇ b W ab + e ϕ/2 <lb/>Habc V bc <lb/>-4e -ϕ/2 ∇ b ab , <lb/>b a = -24a 1 2e ϕ/2 ∇ b V ab + e -ϕ/2 <lb/>Habc W bc <lb/>-4e ϕ/2 ∇ b φV ab , <lb/>Bab = -144a 1 (W a <lb/>c V bc -W b <lb/>c V ac ). <lb/>(29) <lb/>Comparing the generalized Buscher rules (24) in which the <lb/>relations (25) are inserted, with the above deformations, one <lb/>finds the following relation for the 14 arbitrary parameters: <lb/>a 12 = -a 10 , a 14 = a 13 /2, a 15 = -a 13 /4, <lb/>a 17 = 2a 10 , a 18 = -4a 10 , a 19 = a 13 , <lb/>a 2 = -3a 1 + a 16 /64, a 24 = 48a 1 -a 16 /4, <lb/>a 26 = -36a 1 , a 3 = (24a 11 -a 10 )/1152. <lb/>(30) <lb/>There are still four arbitrary parameters a 10 , a 11 , a 13 , and a 16 . <lb/>If one chooses these parameters to be zero, then the T-duality <lb/>invariant Lagrangian becomes <lb/>L (1) <lb/>e = -<lb/>48a 1 α <lb/>κ 2 e -2 √ <lb/>-G <lb/>1 <lb/>24 <lb/>H α <lb/>δ H αβγ H βδ <lb/>ε H γ ε <lb/>-<lb/>1 <lb/>8 <lb/>H αβ <lb/>δ H αβγ H γ <lb/>ε H δ ε -<lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>H α <lb/>γ δ H βγ δ R αβ <lb/>+R αβγ δ R αβγ δ -4H α <lb/>γ δ H βγ δ ∇ α ∇ β <lb/>+2H α <lb/>γ δ H βγ δ ∇ β ∇ α -<lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>H αβγ ∇ γ δ H αβ <lb/>δ <lb/>+2H βγ δ ∇ α ∇ δ H αβγ -∇ α H αβγ ∇ δ H βγ <lb/>δ <lb/>+4H α <lb/>βγ ∇ α ∇ δ H βγ <lb/>δ + <lb/>1 <lb/>6 <lb/>H αβγ ∇ δ ∇ δ H αβγ . (31) <lb/>If one chooses the unambiguous parameters to be 24a 1 = <lb/>-λ 0 , and uses the following identity: <lb/>H α <lb/>γ δ H βγ δ R αβ -H α <lb/>δ H αβγ R βγ δ <lb/>+H αβγ ∇ γ ∇ δ H αβ <lb/>δ -<lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>H αβγ ∇ δ ∇ δ H αβγ = 0. <lb/>(32) <lb/>Then, up to some total derivative terms, the Lagrangian <lb/>becomes the one in the Metsaev-Tseytlin action [6]. In fact, <lb/>one can write the above Lagrangian as <lb/>L (1) <lb/>e = L <lb/>(1) <lb/>MT + <lb/>2λ 0 α <lb/>κ 2 ∇ α (e -2 J α ), <lb/>(33) <lb/>where the current in the total derivative is given by <lb/>J α = 2H αγ δ H βγ δ ∇ β -H αβγ ∇ δ H βγ <lb/>δ , <lb/>(34) <lb/>and the Metsaev-Tseytlin Lagrangian is <lb/>L <lb/>(1) <lb/>MT = <lb/>2λ 0 α <lb/>κ 2 e -2 √ <lb/>-G R αβγ δ R αβγ δ <lb/>-<lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>H α <lb/>δ H αβγ R βγ δ + <lb/>1 <lb/>24 <lb/>H α <lb/>δ H αβγ H βδ <lb/>ε H γ ε <lb/>-<lb/>1 <lb/>8 <lb/>H αβ <lb/>δ H αβγ H γ <lb/>ε H δ ε . <lb/>(35) <lb/>It is important to note that the Metsaev-Tseytlin Lagrangian <lb/>is derived from the S-matrix elements, and the total derivative <lb/>terms cannot be fixed by the S-matrix method. The above <lb/>calculation indicates that, up to certain total derivative terms, <lb/>the Metsaev-Tseytlin Lagrangian is indeed invariant under T-<lb/>duality transformations. The unambiguous parameter in the <lb/>Lagrangian and the generalized Buscher rules is λ 0 = -1 <lb/>4 for <lb/>bosonic string theory and λ 0 = -1 <lb/>8 for the heterotic theory. <lb/>3.1.2 Comparing with the Meissner action <lb/>It has been shown in [14] that using field redefinitions and <lb/>adding total derivative terms to the Metsaev-Tseytlin action, <lb/>one can write this action in another scheme that its cosmolog-<lb/>ical reduction has only first time derivative. The Lagrangian <lb/>in the Meissner scheme is [14] <lb/>L <lb/>(1) <lb/>M = <lb/>2λ 0 α <lb/>κ 2 <lb/>√ <lb/>-Ge -2 R 2 <lb/>G B + <lb/>1 <lb/>24 <lb/>H α <lb/>δ H αβγ H βδ <lb/>ε H γ ε <lb/>-<lb/>1 <lb/>8 <lb/>H αβ <lb/>δ H αβγ H γ <lb/>ε H δ ε <lb/>+ <lb/>1 <lb/>144 <lb/>H αβγ H αβγ H δ ε H δ ε + H α <lb/>γ δ H βγ δ R αβ <lb/>-<lb/>1 <lb/>6 <lb/>H αβγ H αβγ R -<lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>H α <lb/>δ H αβγ R βγ δ <lb/>-<lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>H βγ δ H βγ δ ∇ α ∇ α + <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>H βγ δ H βγ δ ∇ α ∇ α <lb/>+8R∇ α ∇ α + 16∇ α ∇ α ∇ β ∇ β <lb/>-16R αβ ∇ α ∇ β -16∇ α ∇ α ∇ β ∇ β <lb/>+2H α <lb/>γ δ H βγ δ ∇ β ∇ α , <lb/>(36) <lb/>where R 2 <lb/>G B = R αβμν R αβμν -4R αβ R αβ + R 2 is the Gauss-<lb/>Bonnet couplings. It has been observed in [19] that the cir-<lb/>cular reduction of the above action is invariant under the <lb/>O(1, 1, Z) transformations with the following α -correction <lb/>to the Buscher rules: <lb/>ḡab = 0, <lb/>φ = 0, <lb/>ϕ = -λ 0 2∇ a ϕ∇ a ϕ + e ϕ V 2 + e -ϕ W 2 , <lb/>g a = -λ 0 2e -ϕ/2 ∇ b ϕW ab + e ϕ/2 <lb/>Habc V bc , <lb/>b a = -λ 0 2e ϕ/2 ∇ b ϕV ab -e -ϕ/2 <lb/>Habc W bc , <lb/>Bab = 12λ 0 W [a <lb/>c V b]c . <lb/>(37) <lb/>Comparing the generalized Buscher rules (24) in which the <lb/>relations (25) are inserted, with the above deformations for <lb/></body>

    123 <lb/>

    91 <page>Page 8 of 11 <lb/></page>

    <note place="headnote">Eur. Phys. J. C (2024) 84 :91 <lb/></note>

    <body>24a 1 = -λ 0 , one finds the following relations for the 14 <lb/>arbitrary parameters: <lb/>a 11 = a 10 /12, a 12 = -a 10 , a 14 = 13 /2, a 15 = -a 13 /4, <lb/>a 17 = 2a 10 , a 18 = -4a 10 , a 19 = a 13 , <lb/>a 2 = 3a 1 + a 16 /64, a 24 = -a 16 /4, <lb/>a 26 = -36a 1 , a 3 = a 10 /1152. <lb/>(38) <lb/>There are still three arbitrary parameters a 10 , a 13 , and a 16 . If <lb/>one chooses these parameters to be the following <lb/>a 10 = 192a 1 , a 13 = 0, a 16 = -384a 1 , <lb/>(39) <lb/>then the T-duality invariant Lagrangian becomes <lb/>L (1) <lb/>e = <lb/>2λ 0 α <lb/>κ 2 e -2 √ <lb/>-G <lb/>1 <lb/>24 <lb/>H α <lb/>δ H αβγ H βδ <lb/>ε H γ ε <lb/>-<lb/>1 <lb/>8 <lb/>H αβ <lb/>δ H αβγ H γ <lb/>ε H δ ε + <lb/>1 <lb/>144 <lb/>H αβγ H αβγ H δ ε H δ ε <lb/>+ <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>H α <lb/>γ δ H βγ δ R αβ -4R αβ R αβ -<lb/>1 <lb/>6 <lb/>H αβγ H αβγ R <lb/>+R 2 + R αβγ δ R αβγ δ -<lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>H βγ δ H βγ δ ∇ α ∇ α <lb/>+8R∇ α ∇ α + <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>H βγ δ H βγ δ ∇ α ∇ α <lb/>-8R∇ α ∇ α -16R αβ ∇ β ∇ α +16∇ α ∇ ∇ β ∇ β <lb/>-32∇ α ∇ α ∇ β -4H α <lb/>γ δ H βγ δ ∇ α ∇ β <lb/>+16∇ α ∇ α ∇ β ∇ β +4H α <lb/>γ δ H βγ δ ∇ β ∇ α <lb/>-16∇ β ∇ α ∇ β ∇ α -<lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>H αβγ ∇ γ ∇ δ H αβ <lb/>δ <lb/>-∇ α H αβγ ∇ δ H βγ <lb/>δ + 4H α <lb/>βγ ∇ α ∇ δ H βγ <lb/>δ <lb/>+ <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>H αβγ ∇ δ ∇ δ H αβγ + <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>∇ δ H αβγ ∇ δ H αβγ . <lb/>(40) <lb/>One can write the above Lagrangian as <lb/>L (1) <lb/>e = L <lb/>(1) <lb/>M + <lb/>2λ 0 α <lb/>κ 2 ∇ α (e -2 J α ), <lb/>(41) <lb/>where L <lb/>(1) <lb/>M is the Meissner Lagrangian and the current in the <lb/>total derivative term is <lb/>J α = 8R∇ α + 16∇ α ∇ β ∇ β <lb/>+2H αγ δ H βγ δ ∇ β -16R α β ∇ β <lb/>-16∇ α ∇ β ∇ β -16∇ β ∇ α ∇ β <lb/>+H βγ δ ∇ δ H α βγ -H αβγ ∇ δ H βγ <lb/>δ . <lb/>(42) <lb/>Note that neither the Lagrangian in the Meissner scheme nor <lb/>the total derivative terms are individually invariant under T-<lb/>duality. However, their combinations are invariant. Addition-<lb/>ally, it is worth noting that while the Lagrangians (35) and <lb/>(36) are equivalent up to field redefinitions and total deriva-<lb/>tive terms, it can be demonstrated that the Lagrangians (31) <lb/>and (40) are equivalent solely up to field redefinitions. <lb/>3.2 Odd-parity coupling <lb/>The T-duality of the odd-parity coupling in Eq. (8) has been <lb/>investigated in [20] using the standard leading-order bulk and <lb/>boundary actions, which are given as <lb/>S (0) + ∂S (0) = -<lb/>2 <lb/>κ 2 <lb/>d D x <lb/>√ <lb/>-Ge -2 R +4∇ μ ∇ μ -<lb/>1 <lb/>12 <lb/>H 2 <lb/>+2 d D-1 σ |g|e -2 K , <lb/>(43) <lb/>The last term above represents the Gibbons-Hawking bound-<lb/>ary term [10]. In this case, the O(1, 1, Z) symmetry of <lb/>the bulk coupling in Eq. (8) necessitates the following α -<lb/>corrections of the Buscher rules 1 : <lb/>ḡab = 0, <lb/>φ = 0, <lb/>ϕ = <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>V ab W ab , <lb/>g a = -<lb/>1 <lb/>16 <lb/>2e ϕ/2 ∇ b ϕV ab + 2e ϕ/2 ωabc V bc -e -ϕ/2 Habc W bc , <lb/>b a = -<lb/>1 <lb/>16 <lb/>2e -ϕ/2 ∇ b ϕW ab -2e -ϕ/2 ωabc W bc + e ϕ/2 Habc V bc , <lb/>Bab = 0. <lb/>(44) <lb/>as well as the presence of certain total derivative terms at <lb/>order α in the base space. These terms are canceled out by <lb/>the transformation of the boundary term in Eq. (43) under <lb/>the aforementioned generalized Buscher rules. However, in <lb/>this section, we will be employing the leading-order bulk <lb/>Lagrangian described by Eq. (4). The difference between <lb/>the reduction of the bulk Lagrangian in Eq. (43) and the <lb/>Lagrangian in Eq. (4) lies in the presence of the following <lb/>total derivative term in the base space: <lb/>-<lb/>2 <lb/>κ 2 -ḡ ∇ a -e -2 φ ∇ a ϕ . <lb/>(45) <lb/>Using Stokes&apos; theorem in the corresponding action, it pro-<lb/>duces the following boundary term in the base space: <lb/>2 <lb/>κ 2 e -2 φ -ḡ n a ∇ a ϕ. <lb/>(46) <lb/>This term is precisely canceled out by the reduction of the <lb/>boundary Lagrangian in Eq. (43). Therefore, if one utilizes <lb/>the reduction of the leading-order bulk Lagrangian in Eq. (4), <lb/>the calculations of the T-duality invariance of the coupling <lb/>in Eq. (8) yield no residual total derivative term at order α <lb/>at all. That is, the coupling in Eq. (8) is invariant under T-<lb/>duality with the same corrections to the Buscher rules as in <lb/>Eq. (44). Therefore, the circular reduction of the odd-parity <lb/>Lagrangian in Eq. (8) remains invariant under the O(1, 1, Z) <lb/></body>

    <note place="footnote">1 Note that the sign of the Taylor expansion of the leading-order action <lb/>in [20] is opposite to the sign in Eq. (19). Moreover, the normalization <lb/>of the Chern-Simons term in the field strength H in Eq. (6) is 3/2 <lb/>compared to the one considered in [20]. <lb/></note>

    123 <lb/>

    <note place="headnote">Eur. Phys. J. C (2024) 84 :91 <lb/></note>

    <page>Page 9 of 11</page> 91 <lb/>

    <body>transformations with no anomalous term, as for the even-<lb/>parity Lagrangian in Eq. (31) or Eq. (40). <lb/>4 Discussion <lb/>In this paper, we demonstrate that by imposing the O(1, 1, Z) <lb/>symmetry on the circular reduction of the most general <lb/>covariant Lagrangian at order , both the Lagrangian itself <lb/>and the α -corrections to the Buscher rules can be determined. <lb/>The fixing process involves one unambiguous parameter and <lb/>14 arbitrary parameters. The selection of these additional <lb/>arbitrary parameters corresponds to different Lagrangian for-<lb/>mulations in various schemes. Specifically, we have success-<lb/>fully identified T-duality invariant Lagrangians that corre-<lb/>spond to the Metsaev-Tseytlin and Meissner Lagrangians. <lb/>The difference between these Lagrangians and the T-duality <lb/>invariant Lagrangians arises solely from specific total deriva-<lb/>tive terms. We anticipate that this observation holds true for <lb/>effective Lagrangians at higher orders of α as well. <lb/>In practice, dealing with higher orders of α presents <lb/>challenges when working with covariant couplings, where <lb/>only the redundancy resulting from the Bianchi identities is <lb/>removed. The sheer number of couplings involved makes <lb/>it difficult to handle. As a solution, field redefinitions can <lb/>be employed within the Lagrangian to eliminate the redun-<lb/>dancy resulting from these field redefinitions as well. This <lb/>effectively reduces the number of independent couplings. <lb/>For example, at order α , instead of the 31 couplings con-<lb/>sidered in this paper, there are only 17 independent cou-<lb/>plings. In this reduced scenario, T-duality can determine all <lb/>parameters except for one unambiguous parameter and sev-<lb/>eral arbitrary parameters, which can be set to zero to deter-<lb/>mine the couplings within a specific minimal scheme. Fur-<lb/>thermore, after fixing the couplings in a specific minimal <lb/>scheme, field redefinitions can still be utilized to express the <lb/>effective Lagrangian in alternative schemes. Moreover, field <lb/>redefinitions can be employed along with the removal of total <lb/>derivative terms to express the effective action in particular <lb/>schemes. <lb/>The T-duality constraint has been utilized in [3-5] to deter-<lb/>mine the effective actions up to order α 3 . In these calcula-<lb/>tions, one starts with the independent couplings where redun-<lb/>dancy arising from the Bianchi identities, field redefinitions, <lb/>and total derivative terms has been eliminated. As a result, <lb/>the number of independent couplings is reduced compared to <lb/>the effective Lagrangians where the total derivative terms are <lb/>not removed. However, when applying T-duality to the effec-<lb/>tive actions, it becomes necessary to include all possible total <lb/>derivative terms in the base space. Since the massless fields in <lb/>the base space are more numerous than those in the original <lb/>spacetime, the sheer number of total derivative terms in the <lb/>base space becomes overwhelming to consider. Therefore, <lb/>we anticipate that at higher orders of α , the T-duality calcu-<lb/>lations involved in determining the effective Lagrangian will <lb/>be significantly less complicated compared to those required <lb/>for finding the effective actions. <lb/>We have observed that the O(1, 1, Z) symmetry can gen-<lb/>erate T-duality invariant Lagrangians and their corresponding <lb/>generalized Buscher rules in various schemes. One can fix the <lb/>scheme by specifying a particular form for the generalized <lb/>Buscher rules. However, these specifications are subject to a <lb/>constraint that requires the unambiguous parameter to remain <lb/>non-zero. This logic can be employed to reduce the number <lb/>of covariant couplings, as exemplified in Eq. (5), and the gen-<lb/>eralized Buscher rules, as seen in Eq. (24), before imposing <lb/>the O(1, 1, Z) constraint. To decrease the number of cou-<lb/>plings in the original Lagrangian at order α , one can first <lb/>eliminate each term that involves three or four derivatives <lb/>and then impose the Bianchi identities. This procedure leads <lb/>to the identification of 26 independent couplings. The elimi-<lb/>nated terms can indeed be transformed into other terms using <lb/>integration by parts, which does not affect the unambigu-<lb/>ous couplings in the Lagrangian. Consequently, the result-<lb/>ing Lagrangian and its circular reduction will only contain <lb/>terms with up to two derivatives. Therefore, the generalized <lb/>Buscher rules should not produce terms with more than two <lb/>derivatives. By considering the fact that the second deriva-<lb/>tives of the deformations φ and ḡab appear in Eq. (21), we <lb/>find that these deformations generate terms with more than <lb/>two derivatives. Hence, they should be set to zero in the corre-<lb/>sponding generalized Buscher rules. Moreover, since the first <lb/>derivative of all other deformations appears in Eq. (21), they <lb/>should involve only terms with first derivatives. By applying <lb/>this specific scheme, we find that the O(1, 1, Z) constraint <lb/>fixes the generalized Buscher rules to be (29), and the cor-<lb/>responding Lagrangian includes the unambiguous parameter <lb/>a 1 and two other arbitrary parameters. By choosing specific <lb/>values for these parameters, such that the pure gravity cou-<lb/>plings become the Gauss-Bonnet couplings, we obtain <lb/>L (1) <lb/>e = -<lb/>2α a 1 <lb/>κ 2 e -2 √ <lb/>-G H α <lb/>δ H αβγ H βδ <lb/>ε H γ ε <lb/>-3H αβ <lb/>δ H αβγ H γ <lb/>ε H δ ε + <lb/>1 <lb/>6 <lb/>H αβγ H αβγ H δ ε H δ ε <lb/>+48H α <lb/>γ δ H βγ δ R αβ -96R αβ R αβ -4H αβγ H αβγ R <lb/>+24R 2 + 24R αβγ δ R αβγ δ -144H α <lb/>δ H αβγ R βγ δ <lb/>-16H βγ δ H βγ δ ∇ α ∇ α + 192R∇ α ∇ α <lb/>+16H βγ δ H βγ δ ∇ α ∇ α -192R∇ α ∇ α <lb/>-384R αβ ∇ β ∇ α + 384∇ α ∇ α ∇ β ∇ β <lb/>-768∇ α ∇ α ∇ β ∇ β -96H α <lb/>γ δ H βγ δ ∇ α ∇ β <lb/>+384∇ α ∇ α ∇ β ∇ β + 96H α <lb/>γ δ H βγ δ ∇ β ∇ α <lb/>-384∇ β ∇ α ∇ β ∇ α -24∇ α H αβγ ∇ δ H βγ <lb/>δ <lb/></body>

    123 <lb/>

    91 <page>Page 10 of 11 <lb/></page>

    <note place="headnote">Eur. Phys. J. C (2024) 84 :91 <lb/></note>

    <body>+96H α <lb/>βγ ∇ α ∇ δ H βγ <lb/>δ + 8∇ δ H αβγ ∇ δ H αβγ . <lb/>(47) <lb/>The Lagrangian (40) is equivalent to this Lagrangian, up to <lb/>the utilization of the Bianchi identities. <lb/>We have seen that the O(1, 1, Z) constraint can be used <lb/>to the T-duality invariant bulk Lagrangian up to one <lb/>unambiguous parameter. One may expect that this constraint <lb/>can also fix the covariant boundary Lagrangian. It has been <lb/>shown in [11] that the following boundary couplings at the <lb/>leading order of α are invariant under the Buscher rules: <lb/>∂L (0) = -<lb/>2a 5 <lb/>κ 2 e -2 |g| -<lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>K + n μ ∇ μ <lb/>, <lb/>(48) <lb/>where K represents the extrinsic curvature of the boundary. <lb/>The sum of the bulk Lagrangian (4) and the aforementioned <lb/>boundary Lagrangian, with a 5 = -4a 1 , yields the standard <lb/>Lagrangians in (43) after applying Stokes&apos; theorem. <lb/>We have observed that by imposing the requirement for <lb/>the most general covariant and gauge-invariant couplings in <lb/>the effective Lagrangian at order α to be compatible with <lb/>T-duality, it is possible to determine the corrections to the <lb/>Buscher rules and the effective Lagrangian up to one unam-<lb/>biguous parameter and 14 arbitrary parameters. However, <lb/>if the covariance of the couplings is not enforced, alterna-<lb/>tive couplings may exist that still maintain consistency with <lb/>the aforementioned T-duality. In the context of the heterotic <lb/>theory, the Lorentz-Chern-Simons form has been supersym-<lb/>metrized, leading to the discovery of the following couplings <lb/>in [21,22]: <lb/>L B R = -<lb/>2 <lb/>κ 2 e -2 √ <lb/>-G R -4∇ μ ∇ μ -<lb/>1 <lb/>12 <lb/>Ĥ 2 <lb/>+4∇ μ ∇ μ + <lb/>α <lb/>8 <lb/>R μνi j ( )R μνi j ( ) , <lb/>(49) <lb/>where μ <lb/>i j = ω μ <lb/>i j -1 <lb/>2 Ĥμ <lb/>i j ( ), and R μν <lb/>i j ( ) = ∂ μ ν <lb/>i j -<lb/>∂ ν μ <lb/>i j + μ <lb/>ik νk <lb/>j -ν <lb/>ik μk <lb/>j . This curvature can be <lb/>expressed in terms of the standard curvature R μν <lb/>i j (ω), the <lb/>Ĥ 2 -terms, and a non-covariant but locally Lorentz-covariant <lb/>derivative of Ĥ . The presence of Ĥ ( ) in the Lagrangian <lb/>indicates that it has couplings at all orders of α . It has been <lb/>demonstrated in [21,22] that the aforementioned Lagrangian, <lb/>at order α , is invariant under supersymmetry transforma-<lb/>tions. Additionally, it has been observed that these cou-<lb/>plings also remain invariant under T-duality [23]. Further-<lb/>more, it has been shown in [24] that the aforementioned <lb/>Lagrangian at order α and the Metsaev-Tseytlin Lagrangian <lb/>(35) are equivalent up to certain total derivative terms and <lb/>non-covariant field redefinitions. We have explicitly demon-<lb/>strated the invariance of the above couplings at order α under <lb/>the Buscher rules in the reduction scheme (1). The correc-<lb/>tions to the Buscher rules have been found to exclude any <lb/>2-form B, as well as corrections to the base space metric and <lb/>dilaton. For a flat base space, the corrections are given by: <lb/>ϕ = <lb/>1 <lb/>8 <lb/>2∂ a ϕ∂ a ϕ + e ϕ V 2 + e -ϕ W 2 + 2V ab W ab , <lb/>g a = <lb/>1 <lb/>8 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>e -ϕ/2 <lb/>Habc W bc -e ϕ/2 V ab ∂ b ϕ <lb/>+ <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>e ϕ/2 <lb/>Habc V bc + e -ϕ/2 W ab ∂ b ϕ , <lb/>b a = -g a . <lb/>(50) <lb/>We have examined the invariance of the couplings at order <lb/>α 2 under T-duality and have not observed their preserva-<lb/>tion. This observation may suggest the potential existence <lb/>of additional couplings at this order in the aforementioned <lb/>Lagrangian. Uncovering such couplings would be intriguing, <lb/>and one approach to achieve this is by imposing the constraint <lb/>that the circular reduction of the Lagrangian remains invari-<lb/>ant under O(1, 1, Z) transformations. The newly introduced <lb/>couplings should also be consistent with supersymmetric <lb/>transformations at the order of α 2 . According to supersym-<lb/>metry, the new terms should not include Riemann cubed <lb/>terms [21]. <lb/></body>

    <div type="availability">Data availability This manuscript has no associated data or the data <lb/>will not be deposited. [Authors&apos; comment: The results in this paper are <lb/>obtained analytically, hence, it does not use any data.] <lb/></div>

    <front>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attri-<lb/>bution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, <lb/>distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you <lb/>give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, pro-<lb/>vide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes <lb/>were made. The images or other third party material in this article <lb/>are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons licence, unless indi-<lb/>cated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not <lb/>included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons licence and your intended <lb/>use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permit-<lb/>ted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copy-<lb/>right holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit http://creativecomm <lb/>ons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. <lb/>Funded by SCOAP 3 . <lb/></front>

    <listBibl>References <lb/>1. A. Sen, Phys. Lett. B 271, 295-300 (1991). https://doi.org/10.1016/ <lb/>0370-2693(91)90090-D <lb/>2. O. Hohm, A. Sen, B. Zwiebach, JHEP 02, 079 (2015). https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1007/JHEP02(2015)079. arXiv:1411.5696 [hep-th] <lb/>3. M.R. Garousi, Eur. Phys. J. C 79(10), 827 (2019). https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1140/epjc/s10052-019-7357-4. arXiv:1907.06500 [hep-th] <lb/>4. M.R. Garousi, JHEP 09, 020 (2023). https://doi.org/10.1007/ <lb/>JHEP09(2023)020. arXiv:2307.00544 [hep-th] <lb/>5. M.R. Garousi, JHEP 02, 157 (2021). https://doi.org/10.1007/ <lb/>JHEP02(2021)157. arXiv:2011.02753 [hep-th] <lb/>6. R.R. Metsaev, A.A. Tseytlin, Nucl. Phys. B 293, 385 (1987). https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/0550-3213(87)90077-0 <lb/></listBibl>

    123 <lb/>

    <note place="headnote">Eur. Phys. J. C (2024) 84 :91 <lb/></note>

    <page>Page 11 of 11</page> 91 <lb/>

    <listBibl>7. T.H. Buscher, Phys. Lett. B 194, 59 (1987). https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/0370-2693(87)90769-6 <lb/>8. T.H. Buscher, Phys. Lett. B 201, 466 (1988). https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/0370-2693(88)90602-8 <lb/>9. M.R. Garousi, Phys. Rev. D 99(12), 126005 (2019). https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1103/PhysRevD.99.126005. arXiv:1904.11282 [hep-th] <lb/>10. G.W. Gibbons, S.W. Hawking, Phys. Rev. D 15, 2752 (1977). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevD.15.2752 <lb/>11. M.R. Garousi, Phys. Lett. B 809, 135733 (2020). https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/j.physletb.2020.135733. arXiv:1907.09168 [hep-th] <lb/>12. M.R. Garousi, Eur. Phys. J. C 81(12), 1149 (2021). https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1140/epjc/s10052-021-09952-6. arXiv:2103.13682 [hep-th] <lb/>13. M.R. Garousi, Eur. Phys. J. C 82(7), 645 (2022). https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1140/epjc/s10052-022-10611-7. arXiv:2111.10987 [hep-th] <lb/>14. K.A. Meissner, Phys. Lett. B 392, 298 (1997). https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/S0370-2693(96)01556-0. arXiv:hep-th/9610131 <lb/>15. J. Maharana, J.H. Schwarz, Nucl. Phys. B 390, 3-32 (1993). https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/0550-3213(93)90387-5. arXiv:hep-th/9207016 <lb/>[hep-th] <lb/>16. K. Becker, G. Guo, D. Robbins, JHEP 09, 029 (2010). https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1007/JHEP09(2010)029. arXiv:1007.0441 [hep-th] <lb/>17. T. Nutma, Comput. Phys. Commun. 185, 1719 (2014). https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.cpc.2014.02.006. arXiv:1308.3493 [cs.SC] <lb/>18. M.B. Green, J.H. Schwarz, Phys. Lett. 149B, 117 (1984). https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/0370-2693(84)91565-X <lb/>19. N. Kaloper, K.A. Meissner, Phys. Rev. D 56, 7940 (1997). https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevD.56.7940. arXiv:hep-th/9705193 <lb/>20. M.R. Garousi, Eur. Phys. J. C 83(6), 534 (2023). https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1140/epjc/s10052-023-11728-z. arXiv:2305.04527 [hep-th] <lb/>21. E. Bergshoeff, M. de Roo, Phys. Lett. B 218, 210-215 (1989). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/0370-2693(89)91420-2 <lb/>22. E.A. Bergshoeff, M. de Roo, Nucl. Phys. B 328, 439-468 (1989). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/0550-3213(89)90336-2 <lb/>23. E. Bergshoeff, B. Janssen, T. Ortin, Class. Quantum Gravity <lb/>13, 321-343 (1996). https://doi.org/10.1088/0264-9381/13/3/002. <lb/>arXiv:hep-th/9506156 [hep-th] <lb/>24. W.A. Chemissany, M. de Roo, S. Panda, JHEP 08, 037 <lb/>(2007). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1088/1126-6708/2007/08/037. <lb/>arXiv:0706.3636 [hep-th] <lb/></listBibl>

    123


	</text>

</TEI>