<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">High-resolution non-line-of-sight imaging based on liquid crystal planar optical elements</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Zhibin</forename>
            <surname>Zhao</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Qi</forename>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Xiaoyin</forename>
            <surname>Li</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Yinghui</forename>
            <surname>Guo</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Mingbo</forename>
            <surname>Pu</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Fei</forename>
            <surname>Zhang</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Hengshuo</forename>
            <surname>Guo</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Zewei</forename>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Yulong</forename>
            <surname>Fan</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Mingfeng</forename>
            <surname>Xu</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Xiangang</forename>
            <surname>Luo</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-11-03T17:25:12.584535Z">03.11.2025 17:25:12</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1515$1$nanoph-2023-0655</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Walter de Gruyter GmbH</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1515/nanoph-2023-0655</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Zhibin Zhao, Qi Zhang, Xiaoyin Li, Yinghui Guo, Mingbo Pu, Fei Zhang, Hengshuo Guo, Zewei Wang, Yulong Fan, Mingfeng Xu, Xiangang Luo. (2024). High-resolution non-line-of-sight imaging based on liquid crystal planar optical elements. Nanophotonics, 13(12), 2161-2172. DOI: 10.1515/nanoph-2023-0655</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-03T17:25:12.584535Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-11-03T17:25:12.584535Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>Miquel Llompart*, Sara Fernández Santos and Ewa Dąbrowska <lb/>Comprehension of object relatives in <lb/>Spanish: the role of frequency and <lb/>transparency in acquisition and adult <lb/>grammar <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1515/cog-2024-0016 <lb/>Received February 14, 2024; accepted September 23, 2024; published online October 10, 2024 <lb/>Abstract: This study investigates the relative roles of frequency and transparency in <lb/>native speakers&apos; comprehension of Spanish object relative sentences by comparing <lb/>performance with two variants of the construction that differ in these properties. <lb/>Experiment 1 suggests that seven-to eight-year-old children&apos;s processing of object <lb/>relative sentences is consistently facilitated by variant frequency and likely relies on <lb/>separate representations for each variant as two different, although related con-<lb/>structions. Experiment 2 turns to adult comprehension of the two variants, showing <lb/>similar accuracy and reaction time patterns for both variants for this population. <lb/>This second outcome could be interpreted as a decrease in frequency effects over <lb/>time, in line with the power law of practice, as an experience-based increase in the <lb/>ability to make use of redundant markers, or both. <lb/>Keywords: relative clauses; Spanish; first language acquisition; object relatives; <lb/>Construction Grammar <lb/></front>

        <body>1 Introduction <lb/>A central question for usage-based models of Construction Grammar (CxG) theory is <lb/>what properties of the input facilitate or hinder the acquisition of constructions. <lb/>Frequency is often highlighted, since constructions that are experienced more <lb/></body>

        <front>*Corresponding author: Miquel Llompart, Department of Translation and Language Sciences, <lb/>Universitat Pompeu Fabra, Roc Boronat 138, 08018, Barcelona, Office/Despatx: 53.618, Spain; Friedrich <lb/>Alexander University Erlangen-Nuremberg, Bismarckstraße 1, 91054 Erlangen, Germany, <lb/>E-mail: miguel.llompart@upf.edu. https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2002-8778 <lb/>Sara Fernández Santos, Friedrich Alexander University Erlangen-Nuremberg, Bismarckstraße 1, 91054 <lb/>Erlangen, Germany, E-mail: sara.fernandez@fau.de <lb/>Ewa Dąbrowska, Friedrich Alexander University Erlangen-Nuremberg, Bismarckstraße 1, 91054 Erlangen, <lb/>Germany; and University of Birmingham, Edgbaston, Birmingham, B15 2TT, UK, <lb/>E-mail: ewa.dabrowska@fau.de <lb/>Cognitive Linguistics 2025; 36(1): 31-57 <lb/>Open Access. © 2024 the author(s), published by De Gruyter. <lb/>This work is licensed under the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. <lb/></front>

        <body>frequently are learned faster and processed more easily (Ambridge et al. 2015; Bybee <lb/>2017; Divjak 2019; Ellis 2002). The present study investigates frequency at a schematic, <lb/>coarse level of granularity (Lieven 2010) by exploring whether higher frequency of <lb/>specific schematic variations of a structure can have a facilitating effect on compre-<lb/>hension and acquisition. <lb/>While other input properties may have received considerably less attention than <lb/>frequency, some have also been identified as factors facilitating acquisition. A case in <lb/>point is transparency. Widely understood as the degree to which the meaning of the <lb/>whole structure can be inferred from the meaning of its parts, transparency has been <lb/>shown to facilitate the processing of noun compounds (El-Bialy et al. 2013; Marelli <lb/>and Luzzatti 2012), verb-noun pairs (Gyllstad and Wolter 2016) and idioms (Liu and <lb/>Su 2021). In this study, we explore a particular aspect of transparency, namely how <lb/>clearly semantic roles such as agent and patient can be identified in a sentence. Many <lb/>unambiguous sentences contain local ambiguities which may lead to processing <lb/>difficulty (Dąbrowska 2004). However, languages often offer speakers means of <lb/>adding extra cues to help identify semantic roles. Such extra cues make sentence <lb/>meaning more transparent, which may be useful in the acquisition and processing of <lb/>complex structures. <lb/>In the present study, we attempt to shed light on the relative roles of frequency <lb/>and transparency on the comprehension and representation of Spanish subject and <lb/>object relatives by seven-to eight-year-old children and by adult native speakers of <lb/>Spanish. In the three sub-sections that follow, we first introduce Spanish relatives, <lb/>and then subsequently discuss the potential effects of frequency and transparency <lb/>on the comprehension of this type of structures. Finally, we reflect on how the <lb/>outcome of this study may inform CxG theory regarding the issue of identifying <lb/>individual constructions when dealing with highly similar structures. <lb/>1.1 Spanish relatives <lb/>Relative clauses are subordinate structures that modify a noun. These include subject <lb/>relatives (SRs), in which the head noun is understood to be the subject of the verb in <lb/>the subordinate clause (e.g., the man that saw my friend). In object relatives (ORs), by <lb/>contrast, the head noun is the object of the verb in the subordinate clause (e.g., the <lb/>man that my friend saw). In these sentences, when the verb is in the active voice, the <lb/>subject corresponds to the role of agent and the object corresponds to the role of <lb/>patient. ORs in languages like English, Italian and Spanish are known to be acquired <lb/>late (e.g., Arosio et al. 2009; Kidd and Arciuli 2016) and are relatively difficult to <lb/>process even for adults (e.g., del Río et al. 2012; Holmes and O&apos;Regan 1981; Street 2017). <lb/>The relative difficulty of ORs (vs. SRs) has been attributed to several different yet <lb/></body>

        <page>32 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Llompart et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>non-exclusive factors, such as (i) the presence of syntactic gaps in the object position <lb/>(e.g., Miyamoto and Nakamura 2003), (ii) the heightened working-memory demands <lb/>they impose (e.g., Gibson 1998), and (iii) their less prototypical syntactic structure <lb/>(e.g., Kidd et al. 2007; Reali 2014; Reali and Christiansen 2007). <lb/>In Spanish, the first relatives emerge in children&apos;s speech relatively early, <lb/>approximately around age 3 (Montrul 2004). However, ORs are rare at this stage and, <lb/>in experimental settings, even older children often replace them with SRs (Pérez-<lb/>Leroux 1993). In fact, a recent study on the comprehension of Spanish SRs and ORs by <lb/>children aged 6 and 7 using a simple picture-selection task showed that children <lb/>performed well below chance (27 % correct) on ORs, whereas performance on SRs <lb/>was at ceiling (Llompart and Dąbrowska 2024). <lb/>Relative clauses in Spanish are normally introduced by the complementizer que. <lb/>SRs mainly have an SVO word order (1), just like simple transitive clauses. <lb/>(1) <lb/>el niño que abraza al abuelo <lb/>the boy that hug:3s to:the grandpa <lb/>&apos;the boy that hugs the grandpa&apos; <lb/>In ORs, the subject can come either before (as in 2a) or after the verb (as in 2b). Note <lb/>that when the subject is post-posed the only difference between (1) and (2b) is the <lb/>presence of the preposition a &apos;to&apos; 1 in the subject relative (1). <lb/>(2) a. el niño que el abuelo abraza <lb/>the boy that the grandpa hug:3s <lb/>&apos;the boy that the grandpa is hugging&apos; <lb/>b. el niño que abraza el abuelo <lb/>the boy that hug:3s the grandpa <lb/>&apos;the boy that the grandpa is hugging&apos; <lb/>The preposition a is obligatory on direct objects when these are human and specific. <lb/>In ORs, it can also be used before the complementizer when the head noun (in this <lb/>case el niño &apos;the boy&apos;) is human and specific, as in (3a) and (3b); in this case it must be <lb/>followed by the definite article. 2 <lb/>(3) a. el niño al que el abuelo abraza <lb/>the boy to:the that the grandpa hug:3s <lb/>&apos;the boy that the grandpa is hugging&apos; <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">1 When the preposition a is followed by the definite masculine singular article el, the two are <lb/>contracted into al. This is not the case with the remaining definite articles (i.e., a la, a los, a las). <lb/>2 Note that in non-restrictive RCs, other, less common variants with the pronouns cual &apos;which&apos; and <lb/>quien &apos;who&apos; are also possible when preceded by the preposition a. <lb/></note>
		<note place="headnote">Comprehension of object relatives <lb/></note>

        <page>33 <lb/></page>

        <body>b. el niño al que abraza el abuelo <lb/>the boy to:the that hug:3s the grandpa <lb/>&apos;the boy that the grandpa is hugging&apos; <lb/>The two variants of Spanish ORs, henceforth referred to as the plain-variant 3 (i.e., no <lb/>preposition) in (2) and the a-variant in (3), exhibit crucial differences in frequency <lb/>and transparency, making them a suitable testing ground for how these properties <lb/>facilitate or hinder the comprehension and perhaps even the acquisition of these <lb/>structures. In this study, we focus on the OSV word order, as in (2a) and (3a), to avoid <lb/>potential confusion of spoken OR sentences like (2b) with SRs like (1), especially with <lb/>children, who are less familiar with the ORs (see Llompart and Dąbrowska 2024, for a <lb/>more detailed discussion of this). In the following section, we outline the differences <lb/>between the two variants, explore the possible influences of frequency and trans-<lb/>parency at different stages of acquisition, and introduce the design we used to test <lb/>our predictions. <lb/>1.2 Spanish relatives: frequency and transparency <lb/>In the present study, we used a picture selection task to examine the comprehension <lb/>of SRs and both the plain-variant and the a-variant ORs with the verb in clause-final <lb/>position (e.g., el niño (al) que el abuelo abraza &apos;the boy that the grandpa is hugging&apos;) in <lb/>seven-to eight-year-old children (Experiment 1) and adults (Experiment 2). The aim <lb/>of this design is to explore the relative role of frequency in relation to that of <lb/>transparency in facilitating the comprehension of these structures at two different <lb/>stages of development. <lb/>Regarding frequency, the plain-variant is much more frequent than the a-variant <lb/>in Spanish, especially in spoken language. According to Butler (1992), the mean fre-<lb/>quency of plain ORs in a corpus of educated spoken Spanish is 5696 per million words, <lb/>while prepositional ORs only occur, on average, 351 times per million words, making <lb/>the plain variant about 16 times more frequent. According to usage-based models of <lb/>acquisition, all else being equal, more frequent forms are acquired earlier than less <lb/>frequent ones (Abbot-Smith and Tomasello 2006; Bybee 2010; Dąbrowska and <lb/>Szczerbiński 2006; Rubino and Pine 1998). Therefore, it is sensible to expect that <lb/>Spanish children, likely having had much more exposure to plain ORs, have acquired <lb/>them to a larger extent and are better at comprehending them than the less frequent <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">3 Note that we are using &quot;variant&quot; in as neutral a way as possible with regard to our research <lb/>question. With the use of &quot;variant&quot; we do not mean to assume that they are indeed variants of the <lb/>same construction. <lb/></note>

        <page>34 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Llompart et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>prepositional variant. Note, however, that here we focus on overall variant fre-<lb/>quency differences, and it should be noted that such differences might be driven by <lb/>the animacy of the head NP, i.e., the a-variant can only occur in ORs with animate <lb/>heads, where the use of this variant might be almost categorical (see Llompart and <lb/>Dąbrowska 2024). Similarly, there are frequency differences between the two <lb/>possible word orders, with OVS being more frequent than OSV (Reali 2014). While this <lb/>may affect the ratio of frequency differences between the two variants, there are no <lb/>fine-grained analyses, to our knowledge, that allow us to quantify these. Given the <lb/>large size of the overall variant frequency differences, however, we still expect the <lb/>plain-variant to be more frequent than the a-variant for the word order presently <lb/>investigated (OSV). Moreover, the corpus used by Butler (1992) is limited to the <lb/>Madrid region and the frequency difference might be subject to some degree of <lb/>dialectal variation. Hence, the 16:1 ratio of frequency for plain-versus a-variant ORs <lb/>(Butler 1992) should be understood as an estimate. <lb/>Frequency effects have been shown to be most facilitative during early acqui-<lb/>sition and eventually reach asymptote, a trend that is commonly referred to as the <lb/>power law of practice (Ellis and Schmidt 1998; Ellis 2002). In line with this, the <lb/>Competition Model (Bates and MacWhinney 1989) proposes a specific way in which <lb/>cue properties hold different relevance throughout acquisition whereby cue validity, <lb/>entailing both frequency and reliability of the cue, is expected to be the most <lb/>important factor in the earliest stages of acquisition. Experimental evidence has <lb/>shown that in both Hebrew (Sokolov 1988) and German (Dittmar et al. 2008), <lb/>frequency alone accounted for the earliest acquisition of L1 structures. Based on this, <lb/>in our case, we expect the frequent plain-variant to show a larger advantage in <lb/>children&apos;s OR comprehension at the age of acquisition of ORs (Experiment 1) than in <lb/>automatized adult processing (Experiment 2). <lb/>As hinted above, transparency has been mostly researched with reference to the <lb/>extent to which the semantics of the components of a structure are predictive of the <lb/>meaning of the structure as a whole (El-Bialy et al. 2013; Gyllstad and Wolter 2016; <lb/>Kjaerbaek and Basboll 2016; Liu and Su 2021; Marelli and Luzzatti 2012). In this sense, <lb/>&apos;blueberry&apos; would be considered more transparent than &apos;catwalk&apos; because the <lb/>meaning of the compound can be more easily inferred from the meaning of the single <lb/>words within, i.e., &apos;blue&apos; and &apos;berry&apos; versus &apos;cat&apos; and &apos;walk&apos; (El-Bialy et al. 2013). In <lb/>contrast, we use the term to refer to the syntactic transparency of a sentence in <lb/>relation to the clarity of the functional grammatical roles within it. This formulation <lb/>ties in nicely with Slobin&apos;s Operating Principle E, which states that &quot;underlying <lb/>semantic relationships should be marked overtly and clearly&quot; (Slobin 1973, p. 202). In <lb/>language acquisition, Principle E has been used to explain why some constructions or <lb/>systems are acquired earlier than others. For example, Aksu-Koç and Slobin (1986) <lb/>argue that Turkish children learn the nominal and verbal morphology of their <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Comprehension of object relatives <lb/></note>

        <page>35 <lb/></page>

        <body>language early and efficiently because the relevant morphemes are highly salient, <lb/>obligatory and generally associated with one single function. Similarly, Kupisch, <lb/>Müller and Cantone (2002) argue that the Italian gender system is easier to acquire <lb/>than the French one because it is more transparent. In the case of Spanish relatives, <lb/>the a-variant can be considered more transparent because the preposition a <lb/>unambiguously rules out the possibility that the following relative clause is a SR. In <lb/>other words, the functional grammatical role of the first NP is marked as an object <lb/>immediately prior to the relative clause. <lb/>The redundant marker in the a-variant also holds a high value in terms of <lb/>predictive online processing. The initial element of a structure is typically the sub-<lb/>ject, which in many cases corresponds to the agent, and note that the basic and <lb/>arguably most frequent word order in Spanish is SVO (Leonetti 2017). Therefore, <lb/>sentences with that order can be interpreted following the basic processing heuristic <lb/>that the first NP in a sentence corresponds to the agent, and hence, is taken as the <lb/>functional subject. According to predictive processing approaches, basic heuristics <lb/>can drive syntactic analysis decisions, such as role assignment, in the temporary <lb/>absence of disambiguating cues, which makes the processing of non-canonical <lb/>structures more costly given the need for re-interpretation (Ferreira and Lowder <lb/>2016). Hence, adult&apos;s slower processing of ORs (vs. SRs) has been argued to arise <lb/>because of an erroneous initial interpretation of the sentence as an SR following <lb/>the first NP = agent heuristic, which gives rise to difficulties at the point of <lb/>re-interpretation, i.e., the point at which the participant realizes that the initial <lb/>interpretation was incorrect (Betancort et al. 2009; del Río et al. 2012; Reali 2014). The <lb/>cost of re-interpretation, measured in grammaticality judgements and response <lb/>times, increases along with the distance between the head and the disambiguating <lb/>word (Ferreira and Henderson 1991), hence earlier disambiguation should facilitate <lb/>processing. Spanish SRs show differential object marking (DOM), i.e., when both NPs <lb/>are animate and specific, the preposition a must precede the last NP indicating that it <lb/>functions as an object. Hence, the absence of this marking at the onset of the last NP of <lb/>ORs is the only cue to an OR interpretation in the plain-variant, and this makes it the <lb/>point of re-interpretation if one has been following the first NP = agent heuristic. <lb/>Because of this, an earlier and redundant marker for the first NP as an object, as that <lb/>found in the a-variant, i.e., a + article after the first NP (e.g., el abuelo al que el niño <lb/>abraza; cues signaling OR interpretation in bold), should facilitate processing in <lb/>comparison to the plain-variant, because it signals that the first NP has to be an object <lb/>before the onset of the relative clause, potentially ruling out the SR interpretation <lb/>earlier in the sentence. <lb/>Accordingly, transparency of grammatical relations predicts that the a-variant, <lb/>once acquired, should be easier to process. Nonetheless, note that this facilitation <lb/>effect is fully dependent on the correct interpretation of the specific syntactic-<lb/></body>

        <page>36 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Llompart et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>semantic information carried by a + article. Simple transitives and SRs follow DOM <lb/>rules, whereby specific animate direct objects must be marked. In these cases, a + <lb/>article is simply used to designate the following element as a direct object. 4 However, <lb/>when a + article occurs followed by the relativizer que in ORs, it signals that the <lb/>relativized element functions as a direct or a prepositional object (and hence not <lb/>subject) in the following the relative clause. In ORs, as we have seen, this marker is <lb/>optional and can be omitted. Therefore, it is unclear whether young children have <lb/>been exposed to enough exemplars of a-variant ORs to be able to use this informa-<lb/>tion, especially given that function words are not particularly salient. Indeed, it <lb/>might be the case that a lack of experience with a + article in this position introduces <lb/>confusion during the early acquisition of ORs. This ties in with the notion of &apos;func-<lb/>tional readiness&apos; introduced by Bates and MacWhinney (1989, p. 55), who proposed <lb/>that functional unavailability of a linguistic form will inevitably result in a failure to <lb/>create a mental representation of a form-meaning pair. <lb/>In sum, facilitation for the a-variant could be predicted on the grounds of <lb/>transparency and a reduced load during predictive processing. Due to the limited <lb/>experience that children likely have with this variant, however, it could be that these <lb/>facilitation effects only develop at later stages of acquisition. On the other hand, <lb/>frequency facilitation would point towards an advantage for the plain-variant, which <lb/>is likely to impact earlier stages of acquisition to a greater extent than adult pro-<lb/>cessing. However, these differences in comprehension between the two variants <lb/>would only be expected in case that they are not acquired simultaneously as the same <lb/>construction, which raises an important question that will be considered in the next <lb/>section. <lb/>1.3 One or two constructions? <lb/>Given the similarities between the two variants of Spanish ORs, the potential <lb/>asymmetries in processing and comprehension proposed in the previous section <lb/>could also inform another interesting question, namely whether the two structures <lb/>can be subsumed as the same construction or are better characterized as two <lb/>separate constructions. This would be of particular interest for CxG, given that one of <lb/>the recurring questions within this tradition is how to define which structures <lb/>fall under the same construction and which constitute different constructions <lb/>(Hilpert 2014). <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">4 While there is some research documenting the production of DOM in Spanish children (e.g., <lb/>Rodríguez-Mondoñedo 2008), no studies, to our knowledge, have previously investigated children&apos;s <lb/>comprehension of a + article in the context of DOM. <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">Comprehension of object relatives <lb/></note>

        <page>37 <lb/></page>

        <body>To our knowledge, it is not clear whether these two structures should be treated <lb/>within a CxG theory of language acquisition as two entirely independent construc-<lb/>tions, two closely related constructions or the same construction with/without an <lb/>optional element (i.e., a + article). In support of the latter interpretation is the fact <lb/>that the form of the two variants is exactly the same except for the optional element, <lb/>whose use is motivated by (though not fully predictable from) general rules dictating <lb/>obligatory marking of animate and specific direct objects, i.e., DOM. Besides, the <lb/>meaning conveyed is also essentially identical. Building on that, it is more economic <lb/>for any grammar to treat them as the same construction -and indeed, most refer-<lb/>ence grammars of Spanish state that que alternates with al que and a la que in non-<lb/>restrictive ORs (see, for example, Alarcos-Llorach 2000; RAE-ASALE 2009), thus <lb/>implying that they should be considered variants of the same construction. In this <lb/>respect, Spanish ORs could be regarded as similar to English complement clauses <lb/>introduced by that, as in (4), where the complementizer can be omitted with little <lb/>difference to the meaning. Consequently, the sentences in (4a) and (4b) are usually <lb/>described as different realizations of the same construction rather than two different <lb/>constructions. <lb/>(4) a. She thinks that he will come. <lb/>b. She thinks he will come. <lb/>On the other hand, one could argue that the two variants of the Spanish object <lb/>relative are, in fact, different (though related) constructions. The two variants differ <lb/>in formality/register: the a-variant is associated with more formal styles and also <lb/>with written language, whilst the plain variant is more common in spoken language <lb/>in general (Butler 1992; Reali 2014). In addition to this, while the use of a is motivated <lb/>by a general principle of Spanish grammar, the fact that DOM is obligatory with <lb/>animate and specific NPs in canonical transitive sentences, yet optional in ORs, <lb/>indicates that the properties of the prepositional variant are not entirely predictable <lb/>from general principles of Spanish grammar, and hence the two variants could be <lb/>regarded as different constructions. <lb/>While it is not really possible to decide between the possibilities listed above on <lb/>the sole basis of linguistic data (e.g., corpus studies), psycholinguistic experiments <lb/>such as the one conducted here allow us to test predictions linked to each of them. In <lb/>Experiment 1, we used a pre-test -training -post-test design whereby the seven-and <lb/>eight-year-olds were tested on the two variants at pre-test and post-test but were only <lb/>trained on the distinction between SRs and ORs with one of the two variants. <lb/>With such a design, we focused on (i) the ease of comprehension of the two OR <lb/>variants at pre-test, and (ii) post-test performance with the two variants, as the two <lb/>key metrics to gauge whether the two structures belong to one or two separate <lb/>categories. If the plain-variant and the a-variant were cognitively represented as two <lb/></body>

        <page>38 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Llompart et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>entirely independent constructions, one would predict that children may show <lb/>differences in how accurately the two variants are comprehended and, crucially, <lb/>transfer of learning from the trained variant to the untrained variant would not be <lb/>expected. If, by contrast, we hypothesize that they are represented as the same <lb/>construction but one of the variants has an additional optional element, we would <lb/>expect either similar performance for both or better performance for the variant <lb/>with the additional element (a-variant), as well as an equal amount of improvement <lb/>for the trained and the untrained variant. Finally, if their mental representations <lb/>constituted two different yet closely related constructions, the most likely scenario <lb/>would be one in which performances at pre-test differ and there is improvement on <lb/>both variants but more on the trained one than the untrained one. For the adults in <lb/>Experiment 2, we decided against conducting a training study because we expected <lb/>them to have acquired both variants and to be able to comprehend them quite well <lb/>prior to any training. <lb/>2 Experiment 1 <lb/>The aim of Experiment 1 is to explore the early acquisition stage of Spanish plain-and <lb/>a-variant ORs. For this, we tested seven-to eight-year-old children&apos;s comprehension <lb/>of the structures before and after receiving training on one of the variants. We do not <lb/>expect children of these ages to have fully acquired these structures, and based on <lb/>previous results (Llompart and Dąbrowska 2024), we expect explicit training to <lb/>significantly improve performance. As discussed above, the questions that we aim to <lb/>answer with this design are whether children&apos;s comprehension rates are different <lb/>for the two variants, and to what extent training with one variant may benefit <lb/>comprehension of the other variant. These enquiries will shed light on the ques-<lb/>tions of the relative role of higher frequency in relation to greater transparency, as <lb/>well as of whether these structures appear to be acquired as one or two separate <lb/>constructions. <lb/>2.1 Methods Experiment 1 <lb/>2.1.1 Participants <lb/>46 children (21 females) aged from 7;1 to 8;2 (mean 7;8) took part in this study. All <lb/>children were native speakers of Spanish and were recruited from a school located in <lb/>the Seville area (i.e., Colegio San Antonio María Claret). Participants were randomly <lb/>assigned to one of two groups so that 23 children were included in Group A and 23 in <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Comprehension of object relatives <lb/></note>

        <page>39 <lb/></page>

        <body>Group B. As it will be further discussed below, the only difference between Group A <lb/>and Group B is the type of ORs on which participants were trained during the <lb/>training phase of the picture selection task. Informed consent was obtained from the <lb/>parents and the study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. <lb/>Ethics approval was obtained from the Ethics Committee of the Friedrich Alexander <lb/>University Erlangen-Nuremberg. <lb/>2.1.2 Materials and procedure <lb/>The children were tested individually by an experimenter who was a native speaker <lb/>of Spanish in a quiet room at the school. The experiment consisted of three parts: a <lb/>pre-test, a training phase and a post-test, with short breaks between the parts. The <lb/>children completed all three phases in a single experimental session that lasted <lb/>approximately 50 min. <lb/>The picture selection task was modeled after that used by Llompart and <lb/>Dąbrowska (2024). The materials were 16 pairs of pictures (32 pictures in total) and 96 <lb/>Spanish sentences. The pairs of pictures depicted transitive actions with two animate <lb/>participants (e.g., a boy and a grandpa) and they differed in who carried out the <lb/>action described by the verb (e.g., a boy hugging a grandpa vs. a grandpa hugging a <lb/>boy). There were four different pairs of participants in the pictures: (i) a boy and a <lb/>grandpa, (ii) a girl and a grandma, (iii) a teenage boy and a man and (iv) a teenage girl <lb/>and a woman. Each pair was depicted performing four different actions, amounting <lb/>to a total of 16 different actions. <lb/>For each of the 32 pictures, we constructed (i) an SR (el niño que abraza al abuelo <lb/>&apos;the boy that is hugging the grandpa&apos;), (ii) a plain-variant OR (el abuelo que el niño <lb/>abraza &apos;the boy that the grandpa is hugging&apos;) and (iii) an a-variant OR (el abuelo al que <lb/>el niño abraza &apos;the boy that the grandpa is hugging&apos;). All the content words used in the <lb/>sentences were high-frequency items which were expected to be easily compre-<lb/>hended by our participant group (e.g., niño &apos;boy&apos;, abuela &apos;grandma&apos;, abrazar &apos;to hug&apos;, <lb/>tocar &apos;to touch&apos;). <lb/>Two lists of 48 sentences were created, each containing 16 SRs, 16 plain-variant <lb/>ORs and 16 a-variant ORs. Each sentence consisted of the imperative form Señala… <lb/>&apos;Point to … &apos; followed by a relative clause. In version 1, the three sentence types <lb/>corresponding to each picture pair required pointing to the same participant (e.g., <lb/>the boy) and in version 2, they required pointing to the other participant (e.g., the <lb/>grandpa). Version 1 was used for the pre-test and training and version 2 was used in <lb/>the post-test. This way, the children saw the same picture pairs in the post-test as in <lb/>the pre-test and training, but they heard a prompt with the roles reversed. This <lb/>allows us to rule out simple memorization effects from any improvements we may <lb/>find after training. That is, if the children simply learned to associate particular <lb/></body>

        <page>40 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Llompart et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>pictures with particular sentences during training, this would not help them in the <lb/>post-test. <lb/>The pre-test and post-test consisted of 48 trials, each encompassing one of the <lb/>lists of 48 sentences as described above, with 16 SRs, 16 plain-variant ORs and 16 <lb/>a-variant ORs. The sentences were presented in a pseudorandom order with the <lb/>constraints that there could be no more than two sentences of the same type or with <lb/>the same pair of participants in a row and that sentences involving the same action <lb/>had to be at least two trials apart. On each trial, the children were shown a pair of <lb/>pictures and were orally instructed to point to one specific referent which appeared <lb/>in one of the pictures. Participants could answer either by directly pointing to the <lb/>pictures or by saying &quot;1&quot; or &quot;2&quot;, as the pictures were labelled 1 and 2 as shown in <lb/>Figure 1. Once an answer had been provided, the experimenter moved on to the next <lb/>trial. Participants received no feedback on their responses. The pre-test and post-test <lb/>parts of the task were the same for all participants regardless of the group to which <lb/>they were assigned. <lb/>The training part of the task had 32 trials because all participants only completed <lb/>training with one of the OR variants. The training trials for participants in Group A <lb/>included 16 trials in which the target sentences were SRs and 16 in which they were <lb/>a-variant ORs. For Group B, 16 SRs were presented as well as 16 plain-variant ORs. The <lb/>training was divided into two blocks of 16 trials, with 8 SRs and 8 a-or plain-variant <lb/>ORs in each. In the first block, the children were shown pairs of pictures and the <lb/>experimenter described each picture in turn using an SR and an OR with the same <lb/>head noun (Éste es el niño que abraza al abuelo y éste es el niño (al) que el abuelo <lb/>abraza &apos;This is the boy that is hugging the grandpa, and this is the boy that the <lb/>grandpa is hugging&apos;) while pointing to the relevant referent. Immediately <lb/>Figure 1: Example of a test item. The corresponding prompt was either &apos;Señala el niño que abraza al <lb/>abuelo&apos; (point to the boy that is hugging the grandpa) or &apos;Señala el niño (al) que el abuelo abraza&apos; (point to <lb/>the boy that the grandpa is hugging). <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Comprehension of object relatives <lb/></note>

        <page>41 <lb/></page>

        <body>afterwards, they were asked to repeat the two sentences while pointing to the <lb/>matching pictures. <lb/>In the second training block of 16 trials, the procedure was the same as in the <lb/>preceding pre-test, except for the fact that children were given feedback on their <lb/>responses. Thus, they were shown the pairs of pictures and asked to point to the <lb/>correct referent (e.g. Señala el niño (al) que el abuelo abraza &apos;Point to the boy that the <lb/>grandpa is hugging&apos;). If they selected the matching picture, the experimenter <lb/>confirmed their choice as correct (e.g., Sí, éste es el niño (al) que el abuelo abraza &apos;Yes, <lb/>this is the boy that the grandpa is hugging&apos;). If they selected the wrong picture, the <lb/>experimenter provided negative feedback (e.g., No, éste es el niño que abraza al <lb/>abuelo &apos;No, this is the boy that is hugging the grandpa&apos;) and then pointed to the target <lb/>picture and repeated the correct description (e.g., Éste de aquí es el niño (al) que el <lb/>abuelo abraza &apos;This one here is the boy that the grandpa is hugging&apos;). <lb/>2.2 Results Experiment 1 <lb/>The datasets and code used in all analyses are available at https://osf.io/f7ymg/ (Open <lb/>Science Framework). Figure 2 provides a visualization of response accuracy during <lb/>the pre-test and post-test for the two groups (A and B) and the three sentence types <lb/>(SRs, plain-variant ORs and a-variant ORs). An inspection of Figure 2 suggests that <lb/>children were at ceiling for the SRs throughout the study and they also appear to be <lb/>consistently more accurate with the plain-variant ORs than with the a-variant ORs. <lb/>Figure 2: Percentage of correct responses by sentence type (a-variant OR, plain-variant OR, SR) and <lb/>group (A, B) at each time of testing (pre-test, post-test) in Experiment 1. <lb/></body>

        <page>42 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Llompart et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>Moreover, when pre-test and post-test scores are compared, they seem to be higher <lb/>for the latter for both plain-variant ORs and a-variant ORs. <lb/>In order to test these impressions, we submitted the trial-by-trial data for all OR <lb/>trials to a generalized linear mixed-effects model with a logit linking function (lme4 <lb/>package 1.1-23, Bates et al. 2015) in R (R Core Team 2017; Version 4.2.2). Note that SRs <lb/>were not included because of the clear ceiling effects observed. The dependent <lb/>variable of the model was Response (coded 1 for correct and 0 for incorrect) and the <lb/>predictors of interest were Time (pre-test/post-test), OR variant (a/plain) and their <lb/>interaction. Both predictors were contrast coded so that pre-test and a-variant were <lb/>coded as -0.5 and post-test and plain-variant were coded as 0.5 (see Brehm and Alday <lb/>2022, for a discussion of the importance of providing the numeric values of contrast-<lb/>coding procedures in psycholinguistic research). The random-effects structure of the <lb/>model included random intercepts by Participant and Item and random slopes for <lb/>Time and OR variant over Participant, since these were found to improve the model&apos;s <lb/>fit as assessed through a log-likelihood ratio test (time: χ 2 (3) = 61.26, p &lt; 0.001; OR <lb/>variant: χ 2 (3) = 9.97, p &lt; 0.05). The model was run using the &quot;bobyqa&quot; optimizer in the <lb/>glmer control options. The results are provided in Table 1. <lb/>The results of the model revealed that overall, participants were more accurate <lb/>in the post-test than in the pre-test (i.e., effect of time; pre-test: mean correct <lb/>responses = 5.90 out of 16 (SD = 4.90), mean % correct = 36.89 % (SD = 28.95); post-<lb/>test: mean correct responses = 9.83 (SD = 4.75), mean % correct = 61.41 % (SD = 26.46)) <lb/>and that they were more accurate with the plain-variant than the a-variant across <lb/>the board (i.e., effect of OR variant; a-variant: mean correct responses = 6.62 out of 16 <lb/>(SD = 5.01), mean % correct = 41.37 % (SD = 26.40); plain-variant: mean correct <lb/>responses = 9.11 out of 16 (SD = 5.11), mean % correct = 56.93 % (SD = 26.77)). The lack of <lb/>a significant interaction suggests that accuracy differences between the two OR <lb/>variants did not change dramatically from pre-test to post-test. <lb/>A second critical question in Experiment 1 concerned the effects that training <lb/>had on the comprehension of the two OR variants. More specifically, we were <lb/>interested in whether participants exhibited higher accuracies in the post-test with the <lb/>Table : Results of the generalized linear mixed-effects model on the effects of time, OR variant and their <lb/>interaction on accuracy in picture selection for ORs. <lb/>Predictor <lb/>b <lb/>Std. error <lb/>z <lb/>p <lb/>Intercept <lb/>-. <lb/>. <lb/>-. <lb/>. <lb/>Time <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>&lt;. <lb/>OR variant <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>&lt;. <lb/>Time × OR variant <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Comprehension of object relatives <lb/></note>

        <page>43 <lb/></page>

        <body>variants of ORs that were trained than with those that were not, as is suggested by <lb/>Figure 3. Note again here that the trained variant differed by group, such that, for Group <lb/>A, this was the a-variant and for Group B it was the plain-variant. In Figure 3, however, <lb/>the groups are pooled together to highlight the trained versus untrained comparison. <lb/>Training effects were addressed by means of a second generalized linear mixed-<lb/>effects model, which this time included post-test OR data only. Response was again <lb/>the dependent variable and OR variant, Training and their interaction were the <lb/>predictors of interest. In addition, in an attempt to make our analysis as conservative <lb/>as possible, we added the individual pre-test scores by participant by variant as a <lb/>covariate. 5 The model included random intercepts by Participant and Item. Addi-<lb/>tional random slopes did not improve the model&apos;s fit (p &gt; 0.2). The model revealed <lb/>significant effects of OR variant (b = 0.53; Std. Err = 0.19, z = 2.79; p &lt; 0.01) and, <lb/>critically, Training (b = 0.35; Std. Err = 0.13, z = 2.62; p &lt; 0.01), as well as the expected <lb/>sizable effect of the pre-test scores (b = 0.21; Std. Err = 0.03, z = 6.60; p &lt; 0.001). The <lb/>interaction between OR variant and Training was not significant (b = -0.01; Std. <lb/>Err = 0.67, z = 0.008; p &lt; 0.99). In line with the first analysis, these results confirm that <lb/>the children were more accurate responding to the plain variant than the a-variant <lb/>Figure 3: Percentage of correct responses by OR training status (untrained, trained) and time of testing <lb/>(pre-test, post-test) in Experiment 1. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">5 An additional model run exclusively on pre-test data revealed that there was no significant dif-<lb/>ference between the trained and the untrained variants in the pre-test (b = 0.15; Std. Err = 0.14, z = 1.12; <lb/>p = 0.26). <lb/></note>

        <page>44 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Llompart et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>in the post-test (a-variant: mean correct responses = 8.48 out of 16 (SD = 4.86), mean % <lb/>correct = 52.99 % (SD = 30.38); plain-variant: mean correct responses = 11.17 out of 16 <lb/>(SD = 4.27), mean % correct = 69.84 % (SD = 26.72)). Secondly, and most importantly, <lb/>participants were also significantly more accurate with the variant on which they <lb/>were trained than with the other variant (untrained: mean correct responses = 9.22 <lb/>out of 16 (SD = 5.08), mean % correct = 57.61 % (SD = 31.76); trained: mean correct <lb/>responses = 10.43 out of 16 (SD = 4.36), mean % correct = 65.22 % (SD = 27.28)) and this <lb/>effect was not found to interact with OR variant. <lb/>2.3 Discussion Experiment 1 <lb/>Experiment 1 assessed Spanish 7-and-8-year-old children&apos;s comprehension of SRs <lb/>and two different forms of ORs (plain-variant vs. a-variant). Using an intervention <lb/>design, we measured accuracy in a pre-test as well as in a post-test that followed a <lb/>short training procedure which, crucially, only involved one of the two OR forms. <lb/>Our main aim was to shed light on (i) the potential effects of frequency and trans-<lb/>parency on the children&apos;s comprehension and potential learning through training, <lb/>and (ii) whether, based on our results, the two variants of the Spanish ORs tested here <lb/>are better characterized as belonging to the same construction or as two separate <lb/>constructions during the early stages of acquisition. <lb/>Our results show a consistent advantage in children&apos;s performance with the <lb/>more frequent, although less transparent plain-variant, which allows for two non-<lb/>exclusive explanations. Firstly, and in line with previous research (Ambridge et al. <lb/>2015; Dittmar et al. 2008; Lieven 2010; Sokolov 1988), the higher frequency of this <lb/>variant could have facilitated its acquisition. Secondly, as argued in the introduction, <lb/>children might have lacked sufficient experience with the a-variant to benefit from <lb/>its higher transparency. In this sense, if the specific semantics of the additional <lb/>marker a + article were not easily accessible, these additional elements would not <lb/>facilitate and could even hinder comprehension. Additionally, we observed that our <lb/>training led to an improvement in the comprehension of the two OR variants (both <lb/>trained and untrained) but, crucially, the trained variants were comprehended with <lb/>greater ease after training. Considered together with the better overall performance <lb/>with the plain-variant and the clear-cut predictions outlined in Section 1.3, this <lb/>suggests that the two variants may be learned and stored as two different, although <lb/>related, constructions during their early stages of acquisition. Motivated by these <lb/>results, we conducted a second experiment with adult participants to assess whether <lb/>the advantage for the more frequent variant would persist in Spanish speakers&apos; <lb/>ultimate attainment. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Comprehension of object relatives <lb/></note>

        <page>45 <lb/></page>

        <body>3 Experiment 2 <lb/>Experiment 2 tested adult comprehension of plain-and a-variant ORs to compare it <lb/>with children&apos;s comprehension in the first experiment. In order to do so, we repli-<lb/>cated the pre-test phase of Experiment 1 in a population of adult native Spanish <lb/>speakers. Given that, in contrast to the children in the previous experiment, we <lb/>expected adults to have fully acquired the Spanish relatives and show high accu-<lb/>racies in comprehension, we examined both accuracy scores and reaction time data <lb/>for this population. <lb/>Experiment 1 showed that children&apos;s comprehension of ORs was asymmetric in <lb/>that they were more accurate with the plain-variant than the a-variant. However, <lb/>there are two non-exclusive reasons to expect that adults&apos; comprehension of the two <lb/>variants may be more balanced. Firstly, frequency effects follow the power law of <lb/>practice, whereby they stabilize and plateau over time, hence becoming less relevant <lb/>with development (Ellis 2002). Secondly, given that adults are likely to have had more <lb/>experience with a + article in the context of ORs, they might show greater sensitivity <lb/>to the transparency of the a-variant and its associated reduction in predictive pro-<lb/>cessing load. <lb/>3.1 Methods Experiment 2 <lb/>3.1.1 Participants <lb/>A total of twenty adults took part in Experiment 2 (9 females), with a mean age of 36.4 <lb/>(SD = 10.2). Participants spent a mean of 19 years in formal education (SD = 4.78), with <lb/>master&apos;s degree being the highest educational achievement (N = 8), followed by <lb/>university graduation (N = 6), vocational training (N = 5) and high school (N = 1). Our <lb/>sample was recruited using an online recruitment platform, i.e., Prolific (www. <lb/>prolific.co), where access to the experiment was limited to adult native speakers of <lb/>Spanish born in Spain. All participants received financial compensation for their <lb/>time and provided informed consent before completing the study. <lb/>3.1.2 Materials and procedure <lb/>Participants completed a picture selection task that was almost identical to the pre-<lb/>test in Experiment 1 but was in this case completed online through Gorilla Experi-<lb/>ment Builder (www.gorilla.sc), an online experimental platform. The 32 pictures <lb/>used in this task were the same as those used in Experiment 1 (see Figure 1). Audio <lb/></body>

        <page>46 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Llompart et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>recordings by a female native speaker of Spanish were produced of the 48 relative <lb/>clauses used in the pre-test of Experiment 1: 16 SRs, 16 plain-variant ORs and 16 <lb/>a-variant ORs, but in this case without the imperative form Señala… &apos;Point to … &apos;. <lb/>Participants were given instructions before the task and were also asked to complete <lb/>two practice trials, in which they heard simple transitive sentences, before they were <lb/>presented with the test items. <lb/>Each trial consisted of a 500 ms fixation screen followed by a 1 s picture preview <lb/>aimed at eliminating any visual processing delay in reaction time measures. After <lb/>this, participants automatically heard a sentence recording and were asked to select <lb/>the picture that matched the spoken sentence. The pictures remained on the screen <lb/>from preview until a response was recorded via a click on either of the pictures. The <lb/>order of trials and the position of the correct picture also followed those of the pre-<lb/>test of Experiment 1 (see Section 2.1.2). The stimuli and task used in Experiment 2, <lb/>including the practice trials, can be found at https://app.gorilla.sc/openmaterials/ <lb/>630345. The total duration of the task was approximately 5 min. Participants also <lb/>completed two unrelated tasks for a different study in the same session. <lb/>3.2 Results Experiment 2 <lb/>The number of correct responses to a-variant ORs (mean correct responses = 13.95 out <lb/>of 16 (SD = 2.89); mean % correct = 87.19 (SD = 22.07)) was very close to the number of <lb/>correct responses to plain-variant ORs (mean correct responses = 14.30 out of 16 <lb/>(SD = 1.95); mean % correct = 89.37 (SD = 22.03)), as illustrated in Figure 4. Moreover, as <lb/>shown in Figure 5, response times for correct responses (measured from audio onset) <lb/>were also remarkably close for a-variant (M = 2,872.64, SD = 819.15) and plain-variant <lb/>ORs (M = 2,896.34, SD = 829.46). In contrast, subject relative sentences show clear <lb/>ceiling effects in Figure 4 (mean correct responses = 15.60 out of 16 (SD = 0.88); <lb/>mean % correct = 97.5 (SD = 6.68)) and substantially shorter reaction times in Figure 5 <lb/>(M = 2,472.75, SD = 730.93). <lb/>We performed mixed-effects modeling on trial-by-trial data for both outcome <lb/>variables. As in Experiment 1, all analyses were conducted on OR data only, since <lb/>participants were at ceiling with subject relatives. In the first place, a generalized <lb/>linear mixed-effects model with a logit linking function was run with Response as <lb/>binary dependent variable (1 = correct, 0 = incorrect) and OR variant as the predictor. <lb/>OR variant was contrast-coded with the a-variant as -0.5 and the plain-variant as 0.5. <lb/>The random-effects structure of the model included random intercepts by Partici-<lb/>pant and by Item. Random slopes for OR variant by Participant were left out because <lb/>they did not improve the fit of the model (χ 2 (2) = 2.66, p = 0.26). The effect of <lb/>OR-variant was not significant (b = 0.25, Std. Err = 0.26, z = 0.95, p = 0.34). <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Comprehension of object relatives <lb/></note>

        <page>47 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 4: Percentage of correct responses by sentence type (a-variant OR, plain-variant OR, SR) in <lb/>Experiment 2. <lb/>Figure 5: Mean reaction time in milliseconds by sentence type (a-variant OR, plain-variant OR, SR) in <lb/>Experiment 2. <lb/></body>

        <page>48 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Llompart et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>Secondly, a linear mixed-effects regression model was run using Reaction Time <lb/>(RT) as numeric dependent variable and OR-variant as predictor. Before running any <lb/>model, for each participant, RTs that were above or below 3 absolute deviations from <lb/>their individual median were eliminated as outliers (Leys et al. 2013), which removed <lb/>a total of 46 trials (4.79 %). For this analysis, only trials in which participants provided <lb/>the correct response (92 % of OR remaining trials) were included. OR-variant was <lb/>contrast-coded in the same way as in the previous model and subject relatives were <lb/>again excluded from the analysis. The random-effects structure of this model <lb/>included random intercepts by Item and by Participant. Random slopes for OR <lb/>variant by Participant were not included because they did not improve the fit of the <lb/>model (χ 2 (3) = 0.82, p = 0.84). The model was run using the &quot;bobyqa&quot; optimizer in the <lb/>lmer control options. Significance was tested using Satterthwaite approximated <lb/>p-values obtained through the &apos;lmerTest&apos; package (Kuznetsova et al. 2015). This first <lb/>model was run on raw RTs, however, after visual inspection of residual distribution <lb/>plots showing a possible violation of homoscedasticity, the data was transformed <lb/>with a logarithm function and 4 datapoints with RTs over 6,000 ms were deleted after <lb/>being identified as outliers. The model was run again with the same fixed effects and <lb/>random effects structure but using the log-transformed RT as dependent variable. <lb/>The model rendered a non-significant effect of OR-variant in reaction time (b = 0.02, <lb/>Std. Err = 0.03, t = 0.51, p = 0.61). <lb/>3.3 Discussion Experiment 2 <lb/>Experiment 2 assessed the comprehension of the same structures in Experiment 1 by <lb/>adult Spanish speakers. The main aim of this second experiment was to inform the <lb/>question of whether frequency and transparency may affect comprehension <lb/>differently in adults and children, particularly in relation to the different stages of <lb/>acquisition represented by these populations. <lb/>Our findings show that adult accuracy for the ORs used in this study was not at <lb/>ceiling, in line with previous studies (Dąbrowska et al. 2022), and interestingly, that <lb/>adults showed almost identical accuracies and reaction times for the two OR vari-<lb/>ants. We argue that this may be explained by a balancing out of frequency and <lb/>transparency effects. According to the power law of practice, frequency facilitation is <lb/>likely to decrease in strength over the lifespan. As Ellis (2002: 152) puts it: &quot;the effects <lb/>of practice are greatest at early stages of learning, but they eventually reach <lb/>asymptote&quot;. This could be taken to suggest that the differences between construc-<lb/>tions decrease as the less frequent variant becomes more entrenched. In other <lb/>words, as speakers accumulate experience with ORs, the frequency-based advantage <lb/>for the plain variant might decrease. Additionally, the fact that adults perform <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Comprehension of object relatives <lb/></note>

        <page>49 <lb/></page>

        <body>equally well with the two variants may indicate that adults are more likely than <lb/>children to benefit from the higher transparency of the a-variant, despite its lower <lb/>frequency. That is, it is possible that, as the role of a + article in these structures is <lb/>clarified with increased exposure, and thus, presumably, with increased age, the <lb/>transparency provided by these additional elements might become more beneficial. <lb/>4 General discussion <lb/>In the following sub-sections we discuss (i) the effects of our training procedure in <lb/>Experiment 1, (ii) the constructional status of the two variants of OR during acqui-<lb/>sition, and (iii) the possible &apos;balancing out&apos; of frequency and transparency effects in <lb/>L1 acquisition. <lb/>4.1 Training effects <lb/>The first relevant finding of Experiment 1 was that accuracy with the two types of ORs <lb/>was significantly higher in the post-test (61 % correct) than in the pre-test (37 % <lb/>correct). This indicates that the comprehension of ORs by our participants improved <lb/>once they had completed the training phase. These results replicate the findings of <lb/>Llompart and Dąbrowska (2024), who report an improvement in accuracy from 27 % <lb/>to 60 % using a very similar training procedure but with children who were about <lb/>one year younger and targeting only the a-variant. <lb/>These improvements are noteworthy considering that the number of exemplars <lb/>of the target structure to which the children were exposed during training is very <lb/>small (16) in comparison to the number of ORs they were expected to have heard <lb/>before testing. In a corpus of adult spoken Spanish, Butler (1992) reports that the two <lb/>variants of ORs combined appear with a frequency of about 6,000 instances per <lb/>million words. Using a much smaller corpus of child speech, Llompart and Dąb-<lb/>rowska (2024) estimate that the frequency of ORs in child-directed speech in Spanish <lb/>is of about 4 per hour, which means that, by age 7, children will have heard more than <lb/>80,000 ORs. Note, however, that ORs which occur in spontaneous conversation are <lb/>often quite stereotypical and few of them contain two full NPs (see Reali 2014; <lb/>Llompart and Dąbrowska 2024). <lb/>Following Llompart and Dąbrowska (2024), we argue that the improvement we <lb/>observe is so dramatic because, during training, children were exposed to the target <lb/>structure in ideal conditions: the relevant exemplars occurred in the presence of a <lb/>picture that made it clear what the referent was and ORs were explicitly contrasted <lb/></body>

        <page>50 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Llompart et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>with SRs. Hence, frequency of exposure might be most facilitative when linked to <lb/>high-quality exemplars coupled with explicit attention. <lb/>4.2 The constructional status of the two variants of OR during <lb/>acquisition <lb/>To address the issue of whether the two OR variants belong to the same construction <lb/>or are separate categories, two accuracy metrics in Experiment 1 are of particular <lb/>interest. The first is the ease of comprehension of the two variants at pre-test (and <lb/>potentially at post-test). The second is post-test performance with the trained variant <lb/>versus the untrained variant (remember that the training only included 1 OR variant <lb/>for each group). Regarding the former, results revealed that children were more <lb/>accurate with the plain-variant than the a-variant in the pre-test, and this difference <lb/>also held in the subsequent post-test (see Figure 2). Concerning the second metric, <lb/>post-test data showed an improvement in performance compared to the pre-test for <lb/>both variants even though participants where only exposed to one variant during <lb/>training. This was a clear indication that there was transfer of learning from the <lb/>trained to the untrained variant regardless of which variant was trained. However, <lb/>performance with the trained variant was better than performance with the <lb/>untrained variant in the post-test (see Figure 3). Crucially, this was the case even <lb/>when the pre-test scores were accounted for by including them as a covariate in the <lb/>model in order to account for participants&apos; prior knowledge. <lb/>Taken together, these findings suggest that, in early stages of acquisition, the <lb/>plain-variant and the a-variant of Spanish OR clauses seem to be cognitively repre-<lb/>sented as two different but related constructions, rather than as the same con-<lb/>struction or as two fully independent constructions. If the two variants were the <lb/>same construction, we would not expect to find a consistent advantage for the plain <lb/>variant. Additionally, this scenario implies that improvement from pre-to post-test <lb/>should be the same with both variants regardless of which of the two was used in the <lb/>training, yet we observed that the untrained variant did not improve to the same <lb/>extent as the trained variant. Conversely, an account of the variants as two inde-<lb/>pendent constructions would not predict any transfer of learning across variants. <lb/>This second interpretation would thus not be able to explain why accuracy with the <lb/>untrained structure also improved from pre-test to post-test. A characterization of <lb/>the variants as two different yet related constructions, by contrast, can account for <lb/>the advantage of the plain variant over the a-variant as well as for the existence of a <lb/>limited transfer of learning between variants. <lb/>In contrast, the fact that adults showed comparable performance on the two <lb/>variants is consistent with the idea of a gradual entrenchment of a single, more <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Comprehension of object relatives <lb/></note>

        <page>51 <lb/></page>

        <body>abstract OR construction with an optional element. Of course, such an interpretation <lb/>is speculative in nature, as accuracy data alone do not allow us to make strong claims <lb/>about the adults&apos; exact mental representations for ORs because similar accuracies in <lb/>comprehension could in principle be observed even for unrelated constructions. <lb/>Still, considering our results, it is conceivable that adults, having had more experi-<lb/>ence with the a-variant, have developed a more fully-fledged understanding of the <lb/>contribution of a + article in ORs in relation to other uses of this marker, thus <lb/>increasing the compositionality of its representation, i.e., a-variant = plain-<lb/>variant + a + article. This would in turn gradually increase the entrenchment, and <lb/>hence accessibility of a more abstract higher-level schema encompassing both <lb/>variants (Langacker 2010). <lb/>4.3 The possible &apos;balancing out&apos; of frequency and transparency <lb/>effects in L1 acquisition <lb/>The present results allowed us to gain insights on whether the comprehension of ORs <lb/>in Spanish, both at the initial stages of their acquisition and in what can be consid-<lb/>ered ultimate attainment, is more strongly facilitated by frequency of occurrence, on <lb/>the one hand, or transparency on the other hand. Results from the first experiment <lb/>showed that Spanish seven-and eight-year-olds were more likely to correctly <lb/>comprehend ORs when they heard the plain-variant than the a-variant across the <lb/>board. In short, children performed better with the variant they had presumably <lb/>heard more prior to the study, which fits well with the assumption of usage-based <lb/>models of language acquisition that more frequent forms are likely to be acquired <lb/>earlier (Abbot-Smith and Tomasello 2006; Bybee 2010; Dąbrowska and Szczerbiński <lb/>2006; Rubino and Pine 1998). <lb/>Nonetheless, it is worth noting that the difference is fairly small if one considers <lb/>the extent to which the plain-variant is estimated to be more frequent than the <lb/>a-variant in spoken Spanish. As discussed in the introduction, the corpus data in <lb/>Butler (1992) show that the plain variant is about 16 times more frequent than the <lb/>a-variant in the speech of adult Spanish speakers. Therefore, based on sheer fre-<lb/>quency of occurrence, one would expect a larger difference between the two variants <lb/>at least in the pre-test (i.e., prior to any training). This suggests that the higher <lb/>transparency (Slobin 1973) of the a-variant could actually have facilitated the <lb/>acquisition of this infrequent variant to some extent. Accordingly, this could be taken <lb/>to suggest that frequency does trump transparency in absolute terms when the <lb/>difference in frequency is very large, but it is unknown whether this is still the case <lb/>with differences that are less pronounced. <lb/></body>

        <page>52 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Llompart et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>Considering the consistently higher comprehension accuracy in children for the <lb/>more frequent OR variant in Experiment 1, the absence of a difference in accuracy <lb/>and processing speed between the two variants in the adult population is in line with <lb/>the power law of practice: the processing advantage found for more frequent ele-<lb/>ments is stronger during the early stages of acquisition (Ellis 2002). Moreover, our <lb/>findings might be explained by a combination of such decrease in the facilitative <lb/>strength of frequency over time (Ellis 2002), and the emergence of other facilitative <lb/>factors (see Dittmar et al. 2008 for similar results). In this case, adults could be better <lb/>able to use the information encoded in a + article in the a-variant, which could thus <lb/>facilitate its comprehension by increasing transparency and guiding predictive <lb/>processing. Children master the common uses of direct object marking in Spanish, <lb/>where a + article designates the following NP as an object, before age 3 (Rodríguez-<lb/>Mondoñedo 2008). However, in the case of a-variant ORs, this marker designates the <lb/>preceding NP as an object and is overall more often absent than present (Butler 1992), <lb/>limiting thus the learner&apos;s exposure to the specific uses of this marker within ORs. As <lb/>explained in Section 1.2, once acquired, the information carried by a + article in ORs <lb/>could override the basic first NP = agent heuristic that works against the compre-<lb/>hension of ORs, thus reducing the likelihood of listeners going down the garden-path. <lb/>Therefore, an experience-dependent emergence of a transparency-based facilitation <lb/>of the a-variant could explain how the lower comprehension rates for the a-variant <lb/>in children eventually level out in adulthood, although this remains speculative, <lb/>since our data do not allow us to tease the two aforementioned possibilities apart. <lb/>5 Conclusion and future directions <lb/>The present study assessed the comprehension of two very similar structures that <lb/>are known to be challenging in L1 acquisition and adult processing; that is, two <lb/>different forms or variants of Spanish ORs. In Experiment 1, the effects of a short <lb/>training session on children&apos;s comprehension were used as a probe into (i) the <lb/>facilitating factors for the acquisition of these structures and (ii) their constructional <lb/>status, while Experiment 2 focused on whether facilitating factors are weighted <lb/>differently in comprehension by adult native speakers. The main findings of this <lb/>study point towards a stronger facilitative effect of frequency in children compared <lb/>to adults, in line with the power law of practice (Ellis 2002). It is also possible, <lb/>however, that adults become more sensitive to transparency. <lb/>Crucially, our first experiment presents a novel approach to delineating con-<lb/>structions in CxG using psycholinguistic data and training paradigms. With this we <lb/>aim to bridge the gap between CxG theory and language processing by providing <lb/>linguistic insights rooted in the examination of language use as an online process, a <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Comprehension of object relatives <lb/></note>

        <page>53 <lb/></page>

        <body>route that has not been extensively explored within cognitive linguistics. While <lb/>further experimentation will be needed to assess the promise and effectiveness of <lb/>our approach, we believe that it can be particularly suitable for cases in which <lb/>constructional status cannot simply be derived from linguistic usage data. In addi-<lb/>tion, the results presented here contribute to our understanding of L1 acquisition by <lb/>providing further supporting evidence for the proposed differential role of fre-<lb/>quency at different stages of acquisition (Ellis 2002) in non-canonical structures, and <lb/>prompt a series of interesting questions to be investigated in future research, <lb/>especially as far as the balance between frequency and transparency in OR <lb/>comprehension is concerned. In the first place, an assessment of how children&apos;s data <lb/>compare to those of illiterate or semi-literate adult speakers could be crucial to tease <lb/>apart the influences of age and literacy on the acquisition of ORs (see Dąbrowska <lb/>et al. 2022). Secondly, our data call for further studies that directly assess the <lb/>constructional status of plain-and a-variant Spanish ORs in adults, possibly using <lb/>priming paradigms. Lastly, our findings are indeed suggestive of a differential role of <lb/>frequency and transparency at different stages of constructional acquisition. How-<lb/>ever, in order to be able to investigate this matter systematically, it is necessary that <lb/>the input provided is carefully controlled, so that the magnitude of the frequency <lb/>differences can be precisely quantified. A suitable as well as timely way to exert such <lb/>control would be to resort to artificial language learning paradigms with precise <lb/>input manipulations (e.g., Kenanidis et al. 2023, 2024). <lb/></body>

        <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments: This project was funded by the Alexander von Humboldt <lb/>Foundation (Alexander von Humboldt Professorship awarded to Ewa Dąbrowska <lb/>(ID-1195918)) and by the German Research Foundation (Research Training Group: <lb/>Dimensions of Constructional Space (GRK2839/1)). We would like to thank Colegio San <lb/>Antonio María Claret for their willingness to collaborate with us, Ashley Blake for <lb/>drawing the set of visual stimuli, Balma Laseo for her help with in-person testing, and <lb/>all participating children and adults for their interest and for contributing to <lb/>research in language acquisition. <lb/></div>

        <div type="availability">Data availability: The datasets and code used in all analyses are available at https:// <lb/>osf.io/f7ymg/ (Open Science Framework). <lb/></div>

        <div type="conflict">Declarations of interest: The authors declare none. <lb/></div>

        <listBibl>References <lb/>Abbot-Smith, Kirsten &amp; Michael Tomasello. 2006. Exemplar-learning and schematization in a usage-based <lb/>account of syntactic acquisition. The Linguistic Review 23(3). 275-290. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>54 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Llompart et al. <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>Aksu-Koç, Ayhan &amp; Dan I. Slobin. 1986. A psychological account of the development and use of evidentials <lb/>in Turkish. In Wallace L. Chafe &amp; Johanna Nichols (eds.), Evidentiality: The linguistic coding of <lb/>epistemology, 159-167. Norwood: Ablex Publishing Corporation. <lb/>Alarcos Llorach, Emilio. 2000. Gramática de la lengua española. Madrid: Espasa Calpe. <lb/>Ambridge, Ben, Evan Kidd, Caroline F. Rowland &amp; Anna L. Theakston. 2015. The ubiquity of frequency <lb/>effects in first language acquisition. Journal of Child Language 42(2). 239-273. <lb/>Arosio, Fabrizio, Flavia Adani &amp; Maria Teresa Guasti. 2009. Grammatical features in the comprehension of <lb/>Italian relative clauses by children. In José M. Brucart, Anna Gavarró &amp; Jaume Solà (eds.), Merging <lb/>features: Computation, interpretation, and acquisition. Oxford: Oxford University Press. <lb/>Bates, Douglas, Martin Mächler, Ben Bolker &amp; Steve Walker. 2015. Fitting linear mixed-effects models <lb/>using lme4. Journal of Statistical Software 67(1). 1-48. <lb/>Bates, Elizabeth &amp; Brian MacWhinney. 1989. Functionalism and the competition model. The Crosslinguistic <lb/>Study of Sentence Processing 3. 73-112. <lb/>Betancort, Moisés, Manuel Carreiras &amp; Patrick Sturt. 2009. The processing of subject and object relative <lb/>clauses in Spanish: An eye-tracking study. Quarterly Journal of Experimental Psychology 62(10). <lb/>1915-1929. <lb/>Brehm, Laurel &amp; Phillip M. Alday. 2022. Contrast coding choices in a decade of mixed models. Journal of <lb/>Memory and Language 125. 104334. <lb/>Butler, Christopher S. 1992. A corpus-based approach to relative clauses in the spoken Spanish of Madrid. <lb/>Hispanic Linguistics 5(1-2). 1-42. <lb/>Bybee, Joan L. 2017. Mechanisms of change in grammaticization: The role of frequency. The handbook of <lb/>historical linguistics, 602-623. Hoboken: John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. <lb/>Bybee, Joan L. 2010. Markedness: Iconicity, economy, and frequency. In Jae Jung Song (ed.), The Oxford <lb/>handbook of linguistic typology. Oxford: Oxford University Press. <lb/>Dąbrowska, Ewa. 2004. Language, mind and brain: Some psychological and neurological constraints on <lb/>theories of grammar. Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press. <lb/>Dąbrowska, Ewa, Esther Pascual &amp; Beatriz Macías Gómez-Estern. 2022. Literacy improves the <lb/>comprehension of object relatives. Cognition 224. 104958. <lb/>Dąbrowska, Ewa &amp; Marcin Szczerbiński. 2006. Polish children&apos;s productivity with case marking: The role of <lb/>regularity, type frequency, and phonological diversity. Journal of Child Language 33(3). 559-597. <lb/>Dittmar, Miriam, Kirsten Abbot-Smith, Elena Lieven &amp; Michael Tomasello. 2008. German children&apos;s <lb/>comprehension of word order and case marking in causative sentences. Child Development 79(4). <lb/>1152-1167. <lb/>Divjak, Dagmar. 2019. Frequency in language: Memory, attention and learning. Cambridge: Cambridge <lb/>University Press. <lb/>El-Bialy, Rowan, Christina L. Gagné &amp; Thomas L. Spalding. 2013. Processing of English compounds is <lb/>sensitive to the constituents&apos; semantic transparency. The Mental Lexicon 8(1). 75-95. <lb/>Ellis, Nick C. 2002. Frequency effects in language processing: A review with implications for theories of <lb/>implicit and explicit language acquisition. Studies in Second Language Acquisition 24(2). 143-188. <lb/>Ellis, Nick C. &amp; Richard Schmidt. 1998. Rules or associations in the acquisition of morphology? The <lb/>frequency by regularity interaction in human and PDP learning of morphosyntax. Language &amp; <lb/>Cognitive Processes 13(2-3). 307-336. <lb/>Ferreira, Fernanda &amp; John M. Henderson. 1991. Recovery from misanalyses of garden-path sentences. <lb/>Journal of Memory and Language 30(6). 725-745. <lb/>Ferreira, Fernanda &amp; Matthew W. Lowder. 2016. Chapter six -prediction, information structure, and good-<lb/>enough language processing. In Brian H. Ross (ed.), Psychology of learning and motivation, 65, <lb/>217-247. Amsterdam: Elsevier Academic Press. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="headnote">Comprehension of object relatives <lb/></note>

        <page>55 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>Gibson, Edward. 1998. Linguistic complexity: Locality of syntactic dependencies. Cognition 68(1). 1-76. <lb/>Gyllstad, Henrik &amp; Brent Wolter. 2016. Collocational processing in light of the phraseological continuum <lb/>model: Does semantic transparency matter? Language Learning 66(2). 296-323. <lb/>Hilpert, Martin. 2014. Construction grammar and its application to English. Edinburgh: Edinburgh University <lb/>Press. <lb/>Holmes, V. M. &amp; J. K. O&apos;Regan. 1981. Eye fixation patterns during the reading of relative-clause sentences. <lb/>Journal of Verbal Learning and Verbal Behavior 20(4). 417-430. <lb/>Kenanidis, Panagiotis, Ewa Dąbrowska, Miquel Llompart &amp; Diana Pili-Moss. 2023. Can adults learn L2 <lb/>grammar after prolonged exposure under incidental conditions? PLoS One 18(7). e0288989. <lb/>Kenanidis, Panagiotis, Miquel Llompart, Sara Fernández Santos &amp; Ewa Dąbrowska. 2024. Redundancy can <lb/>hinder adult L2 grammar learning: Evidence from case markers of varying salience levels. Frontiers in <lb/>Psychology 15. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2024.1368080. <lb/>Kidd, Evan &amp; Joanne Arciuli. 2016. Individual differences in statistical learning predict children&apos;s <lb/>comprehension of syntax. Child Development 87(1). 184-193. <lb/>Kidd, Evan, Silke Brandt, Elena Lieven &amp; Michael Tomasello. 2007. Object relatives made easy: A cross-<lb/>linguistic comparison of the constraints influencing young children&apos;s processing of relative clauses. <lb/>Language &amp; Cognitive Processes 22(6). 860-897. <lb/>Kjaerbaek, Laila &amp; Hans Basbøll. 2016. Interaction between input frequency, transparency and productivity <lb/>in acquisition of noun plural inflection in Danish. Poznań Studies in Contemporary Linguistics 52(4). <lb/>663-686. <lb/>Kupisch, Tanja, Natascha Müller &amp; Katja Francesca Cantone. 2002. Gender in monolingual and bilingual <lb/>first language acquisition: Comparing Italian and French. Lingue e Linguaggio 1(1). 107-149. <lb/>Kuznetsova, Alexandra, Per Bruun Brockhoff &amp; Rune Haubo Bojesen Christensen. 2015. Package &apos;lmertest. <lb/>R Package Version 2. 734. <lb/>Langacker, Ronald Wayne. 2010. How not to disagree: The emergence of structure from usage. In <lb/>Kasper Boye &amp; Elisabeth Engberg-Pedersen (eds.), Language Usage and Language structure, 107-144. <lb/>Berlin: De Gruyter Mouton. <lb/>Leonetti, Manuel. 2017. 24. Basic constituent orders. In Andreas Dufter &amp; Elisabeth Stark (eds.), Manual of <lb/>romance morphosyntax and syntax, 887-932. Berlin: De Gruyter. <lb/>Leys, Christophe, Christophe Ley, Olivier Klein, Philippe Bernard &amp; Licata Laurent. 2013. Detecting outliers: <lb/>Do not use standard deviation around the mean, use absolute deviation around the median. Journal <lb/>of Experimental Social Psychology 49(4). 764-766. <lb/>Lieven, Elena. 2010. Input and first language acquisition: Evaluating the role of frequency. Lingua 120(11). <lb/>2546-2556. <lb/>Liu, Te-hsin &amp; Lily I.-Wen Su. 2021. Chinese idioms as constructions: Frequency, semantic transparency and <lb/>their processing. Language and Linguistics 22(4). 558-592. <lb/>Llompart, Miquel &amp; Ewa Dąbrowska. 2024. Explicit instruction improves the comprehension of Spanish <lb/>object relatives by young monolingual children. Language and Cognition. 1-21. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1017/langcog.2023.69. <lb/>Marelli, Marco &amp; Claudio Luzzatti. 2012. Frequency effects in the processing of Italian nominal compounds: <lb/>Modulation of headedness and semantic transparency. Journal of Memory and Language 66(4). <lb/>644-664. <lb/>Miyamoto, Edson. T. &amp; Michiko Nakamura. 2003. Subject/Object asymmetries in the processing of relative <lb/>clauses in Japanese. In Gina Garding &amp; Mimu Tsujimura (eds.), Proceedings of the 22nd West Coast <lb/>conference on formal linguistics, 342-355. Sommerville: Cascadilla Press. <lb/>Montrul, Silvina. 2004. The acquisition of Spanish: Morphosyntactic development in monolingual and bilingual <lb/>L1 acquisition and adult L2 acquisition. Amsterdam: John Benjamins Publishing. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>56 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Llompart et al. <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>Pérez-Leroux, Ana Teresa. 1993. Empty categories and the acquisition of wh-movement. Amherst: University <lb/>of Massachusetts. <lb/>R Core Team. 2017. R: A language and environment for statistical computing. Vienna: R Foundation for <lb/>Statistical Computing. <lb/>RAE-ASALE. 2009. Nueva gramática de la lengua española. Madrid: Espasa. <lb/>Reali, Florencia. 2014. Frequency affects object relative clause processing: Some evidence in favor of <lb/>usage-based accounts. Language Learning 64(3). 685-714. <lb/>Reali, Florencia &amp; Morten H. Christiansen. 2007. Processing of relative clauses is made easier by frequency <lb/>of occurrence. Journal of Memory and Language 57(1). 1-23. <lb/>Río, David del, Ramón López-Higes &amp; María Teresa Martín-Aragoneses. 2012. Canonical word order and <lb/>interference-based integration costs during sentence comprehension: The case of Spanish subject-<lb/>and object-relative clauses. Quarterly Journal of Experimental Psychology 65(11). 2108-2128. <lb/>Rodríguez-Mondoñedo, Miguel. 2008. The acquisition of differential object marking in Spanish. Probus <lb/>20(1). 111-145. <lb/>Rubino, Rejane B. &amp; Julian M. Pine. 1998. Subject-verb agreement in Brazilian Portuguese: What low error <lb/>rates hide. Journal of Child Language 25(1). 35-59. <lb/>Slobin, Dan I. 1973. Cognitive prerequisites for the development of grammar. In Charles A. Ferguson &amp; <lb/>Dan I. Slobin (eds.), Studies of child language development, 175-208. New York: Holt, Rinehart, &amp; <lb/>Winston. <lb/>Sokolov, Jeffrey L. 1988. Cue validity in Hebrew sentence comprehension. Journal of Child Language 15(1). <lb/>129-155. <lb/>Street, James A. 2017. This is the native speaker that the non-native speaker outperformed: Individual, <lb/>education-related differences in the processing and interpretation of Object Relative Clauses by <lb/>native and non-native speakers of English. Language Sciences 59. 192-203. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="headnote">Comprehension of object relatives <lb/></note>

        <page>57 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>