<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:452 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01497-x <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>Datasets of fingertip forces while <lb/>grasping a handle with unsteady <lb/>thumb platform <lb/>Banuvathy Rajakumar &amp; Varadhan SKM ✉ <lb/>This article presents the fingertip forces and moments data of the individual fingers and thumb when <lb/>the thumb was placed on an unsteady platform, when the mass of the handle was systematically <lb/>increased and when the thumb normal force was restricted while grasping a handle. Further, this <lb/>article also includes a dataset while the thumb makes vertical movements such as extension (or <lb/>upward motion) and flexion movement (or downward motion) during the static holding of a handle. <lb/>An instrumented five-finger prehension handle was designed with a vertical railing on the thumb <lb/>side. A slider platform was placed over the railing to mount the thumb force sensor. Further, a <lb/>laser displacement sensor was mounted on top of the handle towards the thumb side to record the <lb/>displacement of the thumb platform. The dataset includes fingertip forces, orientation of the handle, <lb/>and the displacement data of thumb platform. This data helps therapists assess the degree of thumb <lb/>disability, the contribution of ulnar fingers in establishing static equilibrium of a handheld object. <lb/></front>

			<body>Background &amp; Summary <lb/>Grasping objects using hands is a common daily life activity. In the past, studies were performed to investi-<lb/>gate individual fingertip force contribution when the grasped object undergoes systematic variations such as <lb/>change in the mass 1,2 , external torques 3-5 , surface friction 6-8 , grip width 9 , individual digit width 10 and fingertip <lb/>position 4,11 . However, from the handles used in the current research, individual fingers force contribution was <lb/>examined, especially ulnar fingers (ring and little), when the load contribution of the thumb was artificially <lb/>reduced by placing the thumb on a slider platform. The platform was mounted over the vertical railing that was <lb/>fitted on the thumb side of the grasping handle. None of the handles utilized in previous studies involved in <lb/>understanding ulnar fingers contribution in stabilizing handle equilibrium when the load contribution of thumb <lb/>was artificially reduced to a constant minimal magnitude. <lb/>In the current study, since the load contribution by the thumb was artificially reduced, it becomes the duty <lb/>of the ring and little (ulnar) fingers normal forces to increase in order to compensate the role of thumb and <lb/>sustain the vertical equilibrium of the handle 12 . Among the ulnar fingers, although little finger has a mechanical <lb/>advantage (longer moment arm) than ring finger with respect to thumb as pivot point, it is smaller in structure <lb/>compared to the ring finger. Therefore, in this research, we were curious to investigate the individual contri-<lb/>bution of ulnar fingers in compensating the role of thumb. Whether the ring and little finger shares equally or <lb/>little finger contributes greater than ring finger or vice versa at various conditions (or situations) was the general <lb/>purpose of these experiments. <lb/>This article presents the dataset from four experiments. All the experiments were performed with the <lb/>five-finger prehensile handle having an unsteady slider platform for the thumb. The first experiment was con-<lb/>ducted as a preliminary study to gain basic understanding of how the ulnar fingers contribute in establishing <lb/>the static equilibrium of the handle when the thumb was placed on a slider platform 12 . The second experiment <lb/>involved in tracing patterns by displacing the thumb platform in the vertical direction 13 . The fingertip force data <lb/>collected during this experiment helps to reveal the biomechanical relationship between thumb and peripheral <lb/>fingers (index and little). The thumb displacement data collected during the upward (extension 14 ) and down-<lb/>ward (flexion) movement of the carpometacarpal joint of the thumb was fed to trace the pattern displayed on <lb/>the monitor. The visual feedback of the thumb movement to the participant helps to regulate the movement <lb/>efficiently. Thereby, it would result in speedy recovery of patients during the rehabilitation practice. Further, the <lb/>third experiment was performed to investigate whether systematic variation in the mass of the handle influence <lb/></body>
			
			<front>Department of Applied Mechanics, indian institute of technology Madras, chennai, india. ✉ e-mail: skm@iitm.ac.in <lb/>DATA DeScRipToR <lb/>opeN <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:452 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01497-x <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>the ulnar fingers force contribution. The fourth experiment was conducted to confirm whether task difficulty <lb/>could influence the behaviour of the ring and little finger forces. The position and orientation data of the handle <lb/>recorded during all the four experiments provided tilt feedback to the experimenter so as to validate whether the <lb/>participant had performed the trial as per instruction. <lb/>This dataset enables us to understand finger mechanics by answering the following questions: <lb/>a) how handle stabilization is achieved in the presence and absence of a mechanical constraint to fix the plat-<lb/>form? (first experiment) <lb/>b) how the contribution of individual fingers and thumb varies to achieve handle stabilization when there is <lb/>any displacement of the thumb? (second experiment) <lb/>c) how the finger force distribution pattern varies to maintain equilibrium when the mass of the handle is <lb/>systematically increased with load force contribution of the thumb restricted to a constant minimal magni-<lb/>tude by placing on a slider platform? (third experiment) <lb/>d) how handle stabilization is achieved when the thumb&apos;s normal force is restricted to trace a solid horizontal <lb/>target line that corresponds to a minimal normal force? (fourth experiment) <lb/>For all the trials of all the experiments, the participants were instructed to maintain the handle in static <lb/>equilibrium. With a systematic variation in the mass of the handle or position of the thumb platform, residual <lb/>pronation moment (anti-clockwise direction) would be noticed. In order to sustain the static equilibrium of <lb/>the handle, participants had to voluntarily increase their normal forces of the ring and little fingers, producing <lb/>a compensatory supination moment (clockwise direction) but not varying the tangential force of the thumb, as <lb/>the thumb was placed on a slider platform. <lb/>The dataset collected from these experiments can be used as a baseline reference guide by the therapists <lb/>in treating patients with ulnar nerve injury (especially male athletes) as a late phase rehabilitation therapy. By <lb/>recording the forces exerted by the individual fingers of the patients while performing the grasping task, it is <lb/>possible to quantitatively assess the functional recovery of the ring and little fingers strength. Compared to other <lb/>studies, the dataset collected during these experiments helps to understand significant contribution of ulnar fin-<lb/>gers in object stabilization when the load contribution of the thumb was artificially reduced. Also, the force data <lb/>collected during the thumb movements helps researchers in designing ergonomic hand tool 15-17 . <lb/>Methods <lb/>participants. Fifteen young healthy right-handed male volunteers in Experiment-1. Twelve right-handed <lb/>males participated in Experiment-2. In Experiment-3, twelve young, healthy right-handed male volunteers par-<lb/>ticipated. Twelve young healthy right-handed male participants volunteered to participate in the Experiment-4 <lb/>(refer Table 1). All participants had no history of neurological disorders or trauma in the upper limb. All the par-<lb/>ticipants signed the informed consent forms before the start of all the experiments. The experimental procedures <lb/>were approved by the Institutional Ethics committee of the Indian Institute of Technology Madras (Approval <lb/>number for Experiment 1: IEC/2016/02/VSK-2/12, Experiment 2: IEC/2018-03/SKM-2/05, Experiment 3 and 4: <lb/>IEC/2021-01/SKM/02/05). <lb/></body>

			<body>experimental setup. Two five-finger instrumented prehensile handles made of aluminum were designed <lb/>and built by us for performing the experiments (refer Fig. 1). An experimental handle with counterweight was <lb/>utilized for the first (simple grasping) and second (pattern tracing) experiments. Whereas a separate experimen-<lb/>tal handle without counterweight was used for the third (systematic variation of mass) and fourth (weak grasp) <lb/>experiment. The entire mass of the handle (including the counterweight) utilized for experiments 1 and 2 was <lb/>0.535Kg. The total mass of the handle (excluding the external loads) used for experiment-3 was 0.450 kg. The han-<lb/>dles were suspended from a wooden frame using nylon rope housed within the PVC pipe to restrict unnecessary <lb/>movements of the handle (refer Fig. 2). Towards the thumb side of both the handles, a vertical railing was pro-<lb/>vided over which a slider platform of mass 0.101Kg was placed. The slider platform could translate on the entire <lb/>length of the railing as the friction between the platform and railing was kept minimal by regularly cleaning and <lb/>lubricating the ball bearings in the slider. Five six-component force/torque sensors (Nano 17, Force resolution: <lb/>Tangential: 0.0125 N, Normal: 0.0125 N, ATI Industrial Automation, NC, USA) were mounted on the grasping <lb/>handle to measure the forces and moments of individual fingers and thumb. The force sensor to measure the <lb/>thumb&apos;s force was mounted on the slider platform, while the other force sensors were placed on the side opposite <lb/>to the railing. <lb/>Age (years) <lb/>Height (cm) <lb/>Weight (kg) <lb/>Hand-length (cm) Hand-width (cm) <lb/>Experiment 1 <lb/>25.6 ± 2.7 <lb/>172.6 ± 3.9 <lb/>73.3 ± 9.6 <lb/>18.6 ± 0.9 <lb/>8.7 ± 0.3 <lb/>Experiment 2 <lb/>22.6 ± 2.4 <lb/>173.4 ± 6.4 <lb/>70.5.3 ± 9.7 <lb/>19 ± 0.6 <lb/>9.5 ± 0.6 <lb/>Experiment 3 <lb/>26.75 ± 3.9 <lb/>172.02 ± 5.7 <lb/>75.21 ± 17.7 <lb/>18.93 ± 1.1 <lb/>8.92 ± 0.7 <lb/>Experiment 4 <lb/>26.66 ± 3.22 <lb/>171.33 ± 7.54 <lb/>76 ± 13.17 <lb/>19.31 ± 0.70 <lb/>9.02 ± 0.42 <lb/>Table 1. Participant demographic details. The table includes average age, height, weight, hand length and hand <lb/>width of the participants with respective units. volunteered for all four experiments. The mean and standard <lb/>deviation of the data are presented. <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:452 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01497-x <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>An acrylic block was placed in the anterior-posterior direction on the top of the handle to mount the elec-<lb/>tromagnetic tracking sensor (Resolution 1.27 microns, Static position accuracy 0.76 mm, Static angular orien-<lb/>tation accuracy 0.15°, Model: Liberty Standard sensor, Polhemus Inc., USA) for experiments 1 and 2. It gives <lb/>the position and orientation data of the handle with respect to the transmitter. For experiment 3 and 4, an IMU <lb/>(Inertial measurement unit) sensor (Resolution: 16bits, Range: 2000°/s, Model: BNO055, BOSCH, Germany) <lb/>was mounted on the acrylic block to measure the orientation of the handle after appropriate pre-processing of <lb/>the raw data. On the participant&apos;s side of the acrylic block of both the handles, a spirit level with the bull&apos;s eye was <lb/>placed for the participant to monitor the tilt caused in the handle. <lb/>For both the handles, the laser displacement sensor (resolution, 5μm; OADM 12U6460, Baumer, India) was <lb/>mounted over the flat acrylic protrusion placed on the thumb side of the handle to measure the displacement of <lb/>the thumb in the vertical direction. The same experimental handle with counterweight was used for both exper-<lb/>iments 1 and 2. An aluminum counterweight of mass 0.035Kg was attached at the bottom of the handle towards <lb/>the thumb side in order to shift the center of mass close to the geometric center of the handle. However, in the <lb/>case of the handle used for experiment 3, counterweight was not used. Instead, external loads of masses 0.150 kg, <lb/>0.250 kg, 0.350 kg, and 0.450 kg were used at the bottom of the handle. For the fourth experiment, an external <lb/>load of 0.250 kg was attached at the bottom of the handle of mass 0.450 kg. <lb/>For fingertip friction measurement, a separate device was built with the provision to mount a six-component <lb/>force/torque sensor (Nano 25, ATI Industrial Automation, Garner, N.C) on the top of the aluminum platform, <lb/>which moved in the horizontal direction over a railing fitted on rectangular metallic support (shown in Fig. 3). <lb/>The platform moved linearly with the help of a timing belt-pulley system powered by a servomotor 18,19 . A cus-<lb/>tomized LabVIEW program was written for the force/torque data collection and to control the operation of the <lb/>motor. Velcro straps arrested the forearm and wrist movements of the participants while a wooden block was <lb/>placed underneath the participant&apos;s palm for the steady hand and finger configuration. <lb/>experimental procedure. The participants were instructed to lift the handle (approximately 2 cm) upwards <lb/>from the suspended position before the start of the trial of all the prehension experiments in order to have zero <lb/>force in the suspension cable. <lb/>Fig. 1 Schematic diagram of the experimental handles used for the prehension experiment. (a) Experimental <lb/>handle utilized for experiments 1 and 2. The mass of the handle, including the counter-weight, was 0.535 kg. In <lb/>the case of experiment 1, only two horizontal lines were drawn: one at the center of the thumb platform and the <lb/>other at the midway between middle and ring fingers (HOME position). For experiment 2, in addition to the <lb/>two horizontal lines, two more lines were drawn (1.5 cm above from HOME and 1.5 cm below from HOME). <lb/>The dimensions of the handle frame of the handle used for the first and second experiment is (20 × 1 × 3) cm <lb/>(b) Experimental handle utilized for experiment 3 and 4. The total mass of the handle, excluding the external <lb/>load, was 0.450 kg. An external load of any of the mass 0.150 kg, 0.250 kg, 0.350 kg, and 0.450 kg was attached at <lb/>the bottom of the handle below the center of mass of the handle (represented with symbol &apos;X&apos;) depending on the <lb/>condition in the case of experiment 3. For both the conditions of experiment 4, an external load of mass 0.250 kg <lb/>was attached at the bottom of the handle. The dimensions of the handle frame of the handle used for the third <lb/>experiment are (21 × 1 × 3) cm. I, M, R, L, T represents index, middle, ring, little, and thumb. <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:452 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01497-x <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>
			
			<body>prehension experiment-1. The first experiment consisted of two conditions: &apos;fixed&apos; and &apos;free&apos; condition. In <lb/>the fixed condition, a mechanical constraint (see Fig. 4a) was used to arrest the movement of the slider platform. <lb/>On the participant&apos;s side of the handle, two horizontal lines were drawn. One horizontal line was drawn at the <lb/>center of the slider platform, and another line was drawn on the handle frame at the midway of the middle and <lb/>ring finger&apos;s sensor center (referred as HOME position). Before the beginning of the trials in the fixed condition, <lb/>the two horizontal lines were matched and the movement of the slider platform was arrested using the mechanical <lb/> Fig. 2 Schematic diagram of the experimental setup for the prehension experiment (a) The participant was <lb/>holding the handle that was suspended from a wooden frame through a nylon wire which was housed within <lb/>the hollow PVC pipe. An orientation sensor was placed a few cms above the forearm of the participant. For <lb/>experiment 2, the computer monitor displayed the either a trapezoid or inverted trapezoid pattern depending <lb/>on the condition. In the case of experiment 3, the computer monitor displayed solid horizontal target line with <lb/>two dashed lines as acceptable error margins. In the fourth experiment, the participant&apos;s monitor displayed <lb/>solid horizontal target line that correspond to the normal force that need to be produced by the thumb. <lb/>Depending on the experiment performed, handle was varied. For experiments 1 and 2, experimental handle <lb/>with counterweight was used. Whereas for experiment 3 and 4, the handle with provision to suspend external <lb/>load was used. <lb/>Fig. 3 Side view of the friction setup showing force sensor, timing pulleys, and belt. A force sensor is mounted <lb/>on top of the slider platform that translates in the vertical direction. In this figure, the slider platform is at its <lb/>start position. <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/> (2022) 9:452 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01497-x <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>
			
			<body>constraint. Although the fixed condition was a simple grasping of a handle similar to other studies, it was per-<lb/>formed so as to compare with fingertip forces data collected from the free condition. <lb/>In the free condition, the mechanical constraint was removed and therefore the platform could be translated <lb/>in the vertical direction using the thumb. However, the instruction was to hold the slider platform steady by <lb/>aligning the horizontal line drawn on the platform to the line drawn midway between the middle and ring fin-<lb/>gers with the help of the thumb (refer Fig. 4b). <lb/>During both the conditions, the task was to maintain the handle in static equilibrium throughout the trial. It <lb/>was ensured by the participants by placing the bubble at the center of the bull&apos;s eye. <lb/>prehension experiment-2. The second experiment was a tracing task and consisted of two conditions: <lb/>&apos;trapezoid&apos; and &apos;inverted trapezoid&apos; condition. The same experimental handle (see Figs. 1a and 5) that was used for <lb/>the first experiment was used for the second experiment. However, there was no mechanical constraint used to fix <lb/>the slider platform for both the conditions of the second experiment. Therefore, the slider platform could trans-<lb/>late freely in the vertical direction using thumb. The thumb displacement data was shown as a visual feedback <lb/>Fig. 4 The experimental handle with counterweight utilized for first and second experiment (a) Left panel: The <lb/>experimental handle when used for the &apos;fixed&apos; condition of the first experiment. The mechanical constraint was <lb/>fitted to arrest the movement of slider platform. (b) Right panel: The same experimental handle used for the <lb/>&apos;free&apos; condition of the first experiment. The mechanical constraint was removed and therefore, the slider could <lb/>translate in the vertical railing using thumb. For the first experiment, two horizontal lines were drawn on the <lb/>participant&apos;s side of the handle: one at the center of slider platform and another line drawn midway between <lb/>middle and ring finger&apos;s sensor center on the handle frame. For the sake of visualizing, the horizontal lines <lb/>were drawn on the other side of the participant. Since the force sensors were mounted on a different handle for <lb/>a different experiment, dummy force sensors were mounted. The photograph was captured by the first author <lb/>Banuvathy Rajakumar and the participant is the other author Dr Varadhan SKM. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:452 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01497-x <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>
			
			<body>line to trace the pattern displayed. During both the conditions, the task was to trace the pattern displayed on the <lb/>monitor by displacing the slider platform using the thumb in the vertical direction. The thumb displacement data <lb/>was shown as a visual feedback line to the participant to trace the pattern shown on the monitor 13 . <lb/>In a trial of trapezoid condition, three trapezoid patterns were arranged consecutively with a static &apos;flat&apos; por-<lb/>tion of two seconds between two trapezoids (see Fig. 6). For the first five seconds of the trial, the participants <lb/>were instructed to place the slider platform at the HOME position (matching the horizontal line on the platform <lb/>to the line drawn midway between middle and ring fingers). Thereby, tracing the initial static &apos;flat&apos; portion <lb/>before starting the first trapezoid pattern (refer Fig. 6). Then, the slider platform was gradually translated 1.5 cm <lb/>upwards by tracing the &apos;ramp&apos; portion of the first trapezoid. At the new TOP position (indicated by horizontal <lb/>line drawn at 1.5 cm above HOME position on the participant&apos;s side of the handle frame), the slider was held <lb/>steady for the next two seconds by aligning the line on the thumb platform to the horizontal line drawn 1.5 cm <lb/>above the HOME position. This was then be followed by tracing the second &apos;ramp&apos; portion of the same trapezoid <lb/>pattern. Likewise, the participants traced the remaining two trapezoid patterns to complete the trial. The static <lb/>HOME position when reached by translating slider platform from TOP position during trapezoid condition was <lb/>referred as HOME-TOP position (refer Fig. 6). <lb/>In the inverted trapezoid condition, within a trial, three inverted trapezoid patterns were arranged consec-<lb/>utively with a static &apos;flat&apos; portion of two seconds between two successive patterns. For the first five seconds, the <lb/>initial static &apos;flat&apos; portion of the trial in the inverted trapezoid condition was traced by aligning the horizontal <lb/>line at the center of the thumb platform to the line drawn midway between middle and ring fingers on the <lb/>handle frame. The participants were then required to translate the slider platform 1.5 cm downwards by tracing <lb/>the &apos;ramp&apos; portion of the inverted trapezoid pattern (refer Fig. 6). At the new BOTTOM position (indicated by <lb/>horizontal line drawn at 1.5 cm below HOME position on the participant&apos;s side of the handle frame), the slider <lb/>was held steady for the next two seconds. This was ensured by matching the line on the thumb platform to the <lb/>horizontal line drawn 1.5 cm below the HOME position. Thus, this was then be followed by tracing the second <lb/>&apos;ramp&apos; portion of the same inverted trapezoid pattern. Similarly, the participants had to trace the remaining two <lb/>inverted trapezoid patterns to complete the trial. The static HOME position when reached by translating slider <lb/>platform from BOTTOM position during inverted trapezoid condition was referred as HOME-BOTTOM posi-<lb/>tion (refer Fig. 6). <lb/>At the end of the ramp portion of the third pattern of each trial in both the conditions, the slider platform <lb/>was held steady at the HOME position by tracing the final static &apos;flat&apos; portion for three seconds. This was accom-<lb/>plished by aligning the thumb platform line to the line on the handle frame (HOME position). And thus, the end <lb/>of the trial would be reached. <lb/>Fig. 5 Experimental handle used for the second experiment with mechanical constraint removed. In addition <lb/>to the two horizontal lines (one on the platform and another on the handle frame), two additional horizontal <lb/>lines were drawn on the handle frame. At 1.5 cm above and below the line drawn at the HOME position, two <lb/>additional horizontal lines were drawn signifying TOP and BOTTOM position. The mechanical constraint <lb/>was removed so that the slider could translate over the railing and complete performing the tracing task. The <lb/>photograph was captured by the first author Banuvathy Rajakumar and the participant was the other author <lb/>Dr Varadhan SKM. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/> (2022) 9:452 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01497-x <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>
			
			<body>While tracing the pattern displayed on the monitor, i.e, during the entire trial of both the conditions (trap-<lb/>ezoid and inverted trapezoid), the handle had to be maintained in static equilibrium. The static equilibrium of <lb/>the handle was ensured by the participants by placing the bubble at the center of the bull&apos;s eye during the trial. <lb/>prehension experiment-3. The third experiment was comprised of four conditions. The other experimen-<lb/>tal handle (see Figs. 1b and 7) without counterweight was used for the third experiment. Similar to the exper-<lb/>imental handle used for the first experiment, two horizontal lines were drawn on the participant&apos;s side of the <lb/>other handle also. And mechanical constraint was not provided with the handle used for the third experiment. <lb/>Therefore, the platform could translate over the vertical railing using thumb. <lb/>In each condition of the third experiment, the external load of mass 0.150 kg, 0.250 kg, 0.350 kg, and 0.450 kg <lb/>was added at the bottom of the handle below the center of mass 20 . The instruction was to hold the thumb plat-<lb/>form steady at the HOME position by aligning the two horizontal lines closely. Thumb displacement data was <lb/>shown as visual feedback line from the beginning of the trial to trace the solid horizontal target line displayed on <lb/>the monitor (see Video 8 at Figshare). The target line displayed on the monitor corresponds to thumb&apos;s HOME <lb/>position. Two dashed lines drawn at 0.2 cm above and below the solid target line on the monitor was the error <lb/>margins. A successful trial was ensured by matching the thumb displacement feedback line to the target line <lb/>within the acceptable error margin of ±0.2 cm. Further, the participants were instructed to maintain the static <lb/>equilibrium of the handle by positioning the bubble at the center of the spirit level throughout the trial when an <lb/>external load was attached at the bottom of the handle during each condition. <lb/>prehension experiment-4. The fourth experiment consisted of two conditions: simple grasp and weak <lb/>grasp condition. The experimental handle (see Figs. 1b and 7) utilized for third experiment was used for the <lb/>fourth experiment also. For both simple and weak grasp conditions, an external load of 0.250 kg was attached at <lb/>the bottom of the handle. <lb/>The computer monitor displayed a solid horizontal target line that corresponds to thumb normal force (i.e,) <lb/>14 N (in the case of simple grasp condition) or 7 N (in the case of weak grasp condition). The normal force <lb/>produced by the thumb was shown as visual feedback line to trace the target line (see Video 9at Figshare). The <lb/>task was to produce thumb normal force matching to the solid horizontal target line within the acceptable <lb/>error margin of ±0.5 N which were represented in the form of dashed lines above and below the target line. <lb/>The mechanical constraint to arrest the movement of slider platform was not provided for the handle used for <lb/>the fourth experiment. Therefore, the slider platform could translate in the vertical direction using the thumb. <lb/>However, an instructed amount of thumb normal force had to be produced by holding the platform steady <lb/>at the HOME position. This was ensured by aligning the horizontal line drawn at the center of the platform to <lb/>the horizontal line drawn midway between middle and ring fingers on the handle frame by the participants. <lb/>Throughout the trial, during both the conditions, static equilibrium of the handle had to be maintained by posi-<lb/>tioning the bubble at the center of bull&apos;s eye. An acceptable error margin for the thumb displacement data was <lb/>Fig. 6 Diagram shows four static positions of the thumb and the patterns displayed on the computer monitor <lb/>during each condition. The figure shows the static TOP (dark shaded) and HOME-TOP (light shaded) positions <lb/>of the thumb during the trapezoid condition (top panel). Also, the static BOTTOM (dark shaded) and HOME-<lb/>BOTTOM (light shaded) positions of the thumb during inverted trapezoid condition (bottom panel) were <lb/>shown. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:452 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01497-x <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>±0.2 cm. The experimenter could view the thumb displacement data, net tilt angle, normal and tangential forces <lb/>of all fingers and thumb during the trial in a separate monitor. <lb/>Friction experiment. Friction experiments were conducted at the beginning of all four prehension exper-<lb/>iments. It involved one trial per finger (experiment 1) and two trials per finger (experiment 2, 3 and 4), with <lb/>a one-minute break provided between the trials. The force/torque data from the thumb and index finger were <lb/>collected. With the tangential and normal force data collected from the instructed finger, friction coefficient <lb/>was computed. By using the friction coefficient values of the finger and thumb, safety margin analysis can be <lb/>performed. <lb/>During the friction experiment, the participants were instructed to produce a constant downward normal <lb/>force of 6 N for 3 s to initiate movement of the servomotor. Visual feedback of the normal force produced by the <lb/>instructed finger was shown on the computer monitor for the participant. The platform moved at a speed of <lb/>6 mm/s away from the participant. <lb/>experimental protocol. For the current research, repeated measures design has been adopted in designing <lb/>all four experiments. According to this design method, multiple measures were taken for the same variable, and <lb/>same set of participants under different conditions. By having a greater number of trials (repeated measures) with <lb/>limited number of participants, a better statistical power can be achieved. As a result, if there exists any effect, the <lb/>statistical test that we employ can detect the effect accurately. <lb/>Since our first experiment was conducted as a preliminary study, we considered having a maximum number <lb/>of 30 trials for each condition, in order to attain a high statistical power and to ensure if the participants were <lb/>able to perform the trials without experiencing any fatigue. From the results on the analysis performed with <lb/>the pilot data collected, we could find that the high statistical power with no fatigue can be achieved with max-<lb/>imum of 30 trials for each condition of the first experiment. Therefore, each condition of the first experiment <lb/>Fig. 7 Experimental handle utilized for the third and fourth experiments. Instead of a counterweight, a <lb/>provision was provided at the bottom of the handle to attach external loads of varying masses. In the case of the <lb/>third experiment, external loads of different masses (0.150 kg, 0.250 kg, 0.350 kg, 0.450 kg) was attached. For <lb/>both the conditions of the fourth experiment, same external load of 0.250 kg was attached. The photograph was <lb/>captured by the first author Banuvathy Rajakumar and the participant was the other author Dr Varadhan SKM. <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/> (2022) 9:452 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01497-x <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>consisted of thirty trials. The trial duration was 10 seconds (as it was a preliminary grasping study with only two <lb/>conditions). A one-hour rest period was provided between conditions. Eight participants performed the free <lb/>condition first, followed by the fixed condition, while seven participants performed the fixed condition first, <lb/>followed by the free condition. <lb/>In the case of second experiment, each trial lasted for 30 seconds. The second experiment involved two condi-<lb/>tions: trapezoid and inverted trapezoid condition. In each condition, there were twelve trials. Since our focus was <lb/>to analyse the individual fingers force data at different static positions (TOP, HOME-TOP, HOME-BOTTOM, <lb/>BOTTOM) of the thumb, three trapezoid patterns or inverted patterns were accommodated for single trial. <lb/>Therefore, in each trial of trapezoid condition, three static TOP and HOME-TOP positions were seen. While, in <lb/>case of inverted trapezoid condition, three static HOME-BOTTOM and BOTTOM positions were present. With <lb/>twelve trials in each condition, totally 36 &apos;flat&apos; segments for each static position were considered for analysis. The <lb/>time duration of each segment was two seconds. Thus, to accommodate three consecutive trapezoid patterns in <lb/>a trial, total trial duration was set to 30 seconds. Although ten trials are enough to have maximum of 30 segments <lb/>for each static position, 12 trials were collected from each participant to have a better statistical power. A rest <lb/>period of at least one-minute was provided between the trials. Six participants performed trapezoid condition <lb/>first, followed by an inverted trapezoid condition. The other six participants performed inverted trapezoid con-<lb/>dition first, followed by trapezoid condition. A break of 30 minutes was provided between the conditions. The <lb/>entire experiment was completed within two hours. <lb/>The third experiment was conducted as two separate sessions. In each session, two external loads were <lb/>included with thirty minutes of break between conditions. For each external load condition, 25 trials were <lb/>provided. Since there exist four different conditions with the addition of an external load for each condition, <lb/>number of trials were reduced to 25 in order to avoid the effect of fatigue and to balance the trials across the con-<lb/>ditions. For the same reason, the duration of each trial was also brought down to six seconds. One minute break <lb/>was provided between trials. After every twelve trials of each condition, ten minutes break was provided. The <lb/>order of presentation of these sessions was counterbalanced across all participants. Six participants performed <lb/>the external load condition of 0.150 kg followed by 0.350 kg in their first session. The other six participants per-<lb/>formed the external load condition of 0.450 kg followed by 0.250 kg in their first session. <lb/>Although the fourth prehension experiment consisted of only two conditions (simple and weak), the task <lb/>of exerting minimal amount of thumb normal force (weak grasp condition) while holding the slider steady at <lb/>HOME position was quiet challenging. Therefore, to complete the challenging task successfully and to avoid the <lb/>effect fatigue while performing the task, only 25 trials were provided for each condition. In addition to this, since <lb/>the task of producing required amount of thumb normal force exactly matching to the target line takes time with <lb/>different participants and trials, the trial duration was extended to 10 s. One minute rest was provided between <lb/>the trials and half an hour break was provided between the conditions. Six participants performed weak grasp <lb/>first, followed by the simple grasp condition. The other six participants performed simple grasp condition first, <lb/>followed by weak grasp condition. <lb/>The experimental protocol details of all four experiments are shown in Table 2. <lb/>experimental preparation. The participants washed their hands and towel-dried once after entering the <lb/>experimental room. After the completion of the experiment by each participant, a new set of sandpaper (100 <lb/>grit sandpaper) was used on the force sensors surface of the handle and friction setup. Before initiating the data <lb/>collection process, the instructions to perform the task was explained verbally by the experimenter to the par-<lb/>ticipant. After explaining the procedure to perform the task, the experimenter demonstrated a trial from each <lb/>condition for the participant. The participants were also provided with a few familiarization trials to make them <lb/>feel comfortable before performing the main experiment. These trials were not recorded. <lb/>Following were the instructions read out to the participants by the experimenter before commencing the <lb/>experiment. <lb/>a) Please do not overgrip the sensors. <lb/>b) Please place the center of the fingerpad of each finger to the force sensor&apos;s center and then lift the handle <lb/>approximately 2cms from the suspended position. <lb/>c) Before starting each trial, hold the handle vertical to maintain the bubble in the center of the bull&apos;s eye. <lb/>d) Inform the experimenter once after positioning the bubble at the center of the bull&apos;s eye. <lb/>e) Please maintain the handle in static equilibrium throughout the trial during all conditions by keeping the <lb/>bubble at the center of the bull&apos;s eye. <lb/>Experiment <lb/>No. <lb/>No. of <lb/>participants <lb/>No. of <lb/>conditions <lb/>No. of trials <lb/>per condition <lb/>Duration of each <lb/>trial (seconds) <lb/>Experiment 1 15 <lb/>2 <lb/>30 <lb/>10 <lb/>Experiment 2 12 <lb/>2 <lb/>12 <lb/>30 <lb/>Experiment 3 12 <lb/>4 <lb/>25 <lb/>6 <lb/>Experiment 4 12 <lb/>2 <lb/>25 <lb/>10 <lb/>Table 2. Experimental protocol details of all four experiments. Table shows the number of the participants <lb/>participated and number of conditions in each experiment. Also, the number of trials per condition also shown <lb/>with duration of each trial. <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/> (2022) 9:452 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01497-x <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>
			
			<body>f) Please ensure whether the thumb platform is positioned comfortably at the HOME position by matching <lb/>the horizontal line on the thumb platform to the horizontal line drawn between the middle and ring finger <lb/>sensor of the handle (which was considered as HOME position) before the start of the trial. <lb/>g) For the second experiment: Please trace the patterns within the acceptable error margin of ± 0.5 cm by <lb/>displacing the thumb from the HOME position to 1.5cms upwards and then back to the HOME position <lb/>during trapezoid condition. Similarly, during the inverted trapezoid condition, move the thumb platform <lb/>from the HOME position to 1.5 cms downward and then back to the initial position. In the case of the <lb/>third experiment: Please trace the solid horizontal target line shown on the monitor with the thumb dis-<lb/>placement feedback line by aligning the two horizontal lines on the thumb platform and handle frame. <lb/>h) For the fourth experiment, during weak grasp condition, please grasp the handle with minimal grip force <lb/>so that the feedback line of the thumb normal force matches the solid horizontal target force line shown on <lb/>the participant&apos;s monitor. simple grasp condition, please produce thumb normal force matching to <lb/>the solid target line displayed on the participant&apos;s monitor. <lb/>i) Please inform the experimenter when you feel any discomfort. You will be provided rest as needed. <lb/>Data processing. Thirty analog signals from the force/torque sensors (5 sensors x 6 components) and <lb/>single-channel analog laser displacement data were digitized using NI USB 6225 and 6002 at 16-bit resolution <lb/>(National Instruments, Austin, TX, USA). Force/torque and displacement data were synchronized with six chan-<lb/>nels of processed, digital data from the electromagnetic tracker for experiments 1 &amp; 2 and four channels of pro-<lb/>cessed quaternion data from experiment-3 &amp; 4. The force signals from the force sensors and orientation signals <lb/>from polhemus sensors were synchronized in LabVIEW software using predefined library files within a same data <lb/>collection loop. In particular, both the signals were collected at same sampling frequency within a same data col-<lb/>lection loop. The dataset was collected at a sampling frequency of 100 Hz. The raw data were imported to Matlab <lb/>for further processing. The data were filtered in Matlab through the second-order zero phase lag Butterworth low <lb/>pass filter (cut off frequency, 15 Hz) for the prehension and friction experiments. In each experiment, data was <lb/>selected from specific time interval for the computation of the below mentioned forces and moments. In the case <lb/>of the first experiment, data from 2.5 s to 7.5 s of each trial were selected. While, for the second experiment, the <lb/>first one second data from the static positions (TOP, HOME-TOP, HOME-BOTTOM, BOTTOM) were consid-<lb/>ered. With regard to the third experiment, data from 2 s to 5 s of each trial was taken. In the case of fourth exper-<lb/>iment, data from 3 s to 7 s of each trial was taken for forces, and other computations. <lb/>The main reason for performing computation using the datapoints within the particular time window in the <lb/>experiments was to eliminate start and end effects of a trial. With regard to the second experiment, since the <lb/>main focus was to analyse the individual fingers force data when the thumb was held at different static positions <lb/>(TOP, HOME, BOTTOM), only the first one second data (100 datapoints) was chosen from the three static posi-<lb/>tions of the thumb for analysis. Perhaps, even if an entire two seconds data at the three different static positions <lb/>of the thumb was considered for analysis, the results would not be significantly different. <lb/>code description. forceanddisp_dataplots.m. This Matlab code consists of four sections. Each section corre-<lb/>sponds to an experiment. Each section obtains data from the respective folder and filters the individual fingertip forces <lb/>and displacement data. After filtering, the normal (grip) and tangential (load) forces of all the fingers would be averaged <lb/>across trials and participants. The averaged time series plot of the individual finger&apos;s normal forces, tangential forces, <lb/>and thumb displacement data of all the conditions of all the experiments would be displayed separately as figures. <lb/>momentcomputation.m. This Matlab code is a sample code to compute moments exerted by individual fingers <lb/>and thumb during the fixed and free conditions of the first experiment. The center of pressure of all the fingers <lb/>and thumb were computed and accounted for the computation of moment arms of the normal forces. <lb/>filter_code.m. This Matlab code is responsible for filtering the forces and thumb displacement data. After fetch-<lb/>ing the data, this code involves in the filtering of the data. <lb/>Data Records <lb/>The raw data along with the code can be found at figshare 21 . <lb/>Figshare link: https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.19207875. <lb/>The first experiment on a simple five-finger grasping task was collected from fifteen participants. The data <lb/>from each participant was stored in fifteen separate folders. Within each participant folder, there exist two sub-<lb/>folders: fixed condition and free condition. Within the condition subfolder, thirty data files in .csv format would <lb/>be present. Each column contains 1001 rows (sampling frequency = 100 Hz, single-trial duration = 10 seconds). <lb/>The second experiment on the five-finger grasping task that involves tracing the pattern by displacing the <lb/>thumb was collected from twelve participants. The data from each participant were stored in twelve separate <lb/>folders. Within each folder, two subfolders were created for two different conditions, which were named trap-<lb/>ezoid and inverted trapezoid conditions. Twelve data files (in .csv format) are present in each subfolder. Each <lb/>column of the data file contains 3001 rows. <lb/>The data of the third experiment on the five-finger grasping task that involves a systematic increase in the <lb/>mass of the handle of twelve participants were stored in twelve separate folders. Within each folder, four sub-<lb/>folders were created for four different conditions, which were named as onefifty, twofifty, threefifty, and fourfifty. <lb/>Twenty-five data files (in .csv format) are present in each subfolder. Each column of the data file contains 601 <lb/>rows. <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:452 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01497-x <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>The fourth experiment data was stored in twelve separate folders. Within each folder, four subfolders were <lb/>created for two different conditions, which were named as simplegrasp and weakgrasp. Similar to the third <lb/>experiment, twenty-five data files (in .csv format) are present in each subfolder. Each column of the data file <lb/>contains 1001 rows. <lb/>Each data file contains data from a single trial. For experiments 1 and 2, thirty-eight columns of data were <lb/>present for each trial (refer to Table 3). The first thirty columns indicate force and torque data from index, mid-<lb/>dle, ring, little, and thumb. They were followed by six columns of position (X, Y, Z) and orientation (Azimuth <lb/>(A), Elevation (E), Roll (R)) data of the handle. The thirty-seventh column indicates the thumb displacement <lb/>data. The last column signifies the Polhemus data availability flag. <lb/>Whereas, for experiment 3 and 4, thirty-six columns of data were present for each trial (refer to Table 4). <lb/>The first thirty columns indicate force and torque data from index, middle, ring, little, and thumb. They were <lb/>followed by four columns of orientation data of the handle in the form of quaternions (w, x, y, z). The thirty-fifth <lb/>column indicates the net tilt angle data computed directly from the raw quaternion data. The last column signi-<lb/>fies the thumb displacement data. <lb/>Description of the data columns from 1 to 30 of all four experiments. First six columns (col-<lb/>umn number: 1,2,3,4,5,6) includes forces (N) and moments (Nmm) data of Index finger: Fx(horizontal tan-<lb/>gential force), Fy (vertical tangential force), Fz (normal force), Mx(Moment about horizontal tangential force), <lb/>My(Moment about the vertical tangential force), Mz(Moment about the normal force) <lb/>The second set of six columns (column number: 7,8,9,10,11,12) includes forces (N) and moments (Nmm) <lb/>data of the Middle finger: Fx, Fy, Fz, Mx, My, Mz. <lb/>The third set of six columns (column number: 13,14,15,16,17,18) includes forces (N) and moments (Nmm) <lb/>data of Ring finger: Fx, Fy, Fz, Mx, My, Mz. <lb/>Fourth set of six columns (column number: 19,20,21,22,23,24) includes forces (in N) and moments (in <lb/>Nmm) data of Little finger: Fx, Fy, Fz, Mx, My, Mz. <lb/>Fifth set of six columns (column number: 25,26,27,28,29,30) includes forces (in N) and moments (in Nmm) <lb/>data of Thumb: Fy (vertical tangential force), Fx (horizontal tangential force), Fz (normal force), My, Mx, Mz. <lb/>Note: Here, the vertical tangential force of thumb belongs to 25 th column of data due to the change in the orien-<lb/>tation of the force sensor of the thumb <lb/>Description of the columns from 31 to 38 of the first two experiments. The sixth set of six columns <lb/>(column number: 31,32,33,34,35,36) includes position (cm) and orientation (degrees) data of the handle: X (verti-<lb/>cal distance between the origin of the source and the sensor at the handle), Y(horizontal distance between the ori-<lb/>gin of the source and the sensor at the handle in front-back direction), Z (horizontal distance between the origin <lb/>of the source and the sensor at the handle in the left-right direction), Azimuth (Ѳx), Elevation (Ѳy), and Roll (Ѳz). <lb/>The thirty-seventh column of the dataset consists of the thumb displacement data measured from the laser <lb/>displacement sensor. For the first experiment, the unit of thumb displacement data was in millimeters (mm). <lb/>Whereas, for the second experiment, the unit of thumb displacement data was in centimeters (cm). <lb/>The last column of data is the &apos;Polhemus data availability flag&apos; . It would be either 1 or 0. In the absence of <lb/>position data at any particular instance during the trial will have 0. <lb/>Column 1 to 30 <lb/>Column 31 to 36 <lb/>Column 37 <lb/>Column 38 <lb/>Index <lb/>Middle <lb/>Ring <lb/>Little <lb/>Thumb <lb/>Position (cm) and <lb/>orientation (°) <lb/>data of handle <lb/>Thumb <lb/>displacement data <lb/>(Experiment 1 in <lb/>mm, Experiment <lb/>2 in cm) <lb/>Polhemus <lb/>data <lb/>availability <lb/>flag <lb/>Force (Fx, Fy, <lb/>Fz) &amp; torque <lb/>(Mx, My, Mz) <lb/>Force (Fx, Fy, <lb/>Fz) &amp; torque <lb/>(Mx, My, Mz) <lb/>Force (Fx, Fy, <lb/>Fz) &amp; torque <lb/>(Mx, My, Mz) <lb/>Force (Fx, Fy, <lb/>Fz) &amp; torque <lb/>(Mx, My, Mz) <lb/>Force (Fy, Fx, <lb/>Fz) &amp; torque <lb/>(My, Mx, Mz) <lb/>X, Y, Z, A, E, R <lb/>0 or 1 <lb/>Table 3. Data in each column of experiments 1 and 2 are shown in this table. The table shows the column-wise <lb/>data arrangement of forces (N), torques (Nmm) in all three directions of each finger, position and orientation <lb/>data of the handle and thumb displacement data in the datafile. <lb/>Column 1 to 30 <lb/>Column 31 to 34 Column 35 <lb/>Column 36 <lb/>Index <lb/>Middle <lb/>Ring <lb/>Little <lb/>Thumb <lb/>Orientation <lb/>data of handle <lb/>(Quaternions) <lb/>Net tilt <lb/>angle <lb/>(degrees) <lb/>Thumb <lb/>displacement <lb/>data (cm) <lb/>Force (Fx, Fy, <lb/>Fz) &amp; torque <lb/>(Mx, My, Mz) <lb/>Force (Fx, Fy, <lb/>Fz) &amp; torque <lb/>(Mx, My, Mz) <lb/>Force (Fx, Fy, <lb/>Fz) &amp; torque <lb/>(Mx, My, Mz) <lb/>Force (Fx, Fy, <lb/>Fz) &amp; torque <lb/>(Mx, My, Mz) <lb/>Force (Fy, Fx, <lb/>Fz) &amp; torque <lb/>(My, Mx, Mz) <lb/>w, x, y, z <lb/>Ѳ <lb/>Table 4. Data in each column of experiment 3 and 4 are shown in this table. The table shows the column-wise <lb/>data arrangement of forces (N), torques (Nmm) in all three directions of each finger, orientation data of the <lb/>handle, net tilt angle, thumb displacement data in the datafile. <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:452 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01497-x <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>Description of the columns from 31 to 36 of the third and fourth experiment. The sixth set of four <lb/>columns (column number: 31, 32, 33, 34) includes orientation data of the handle in the form of quaternions (w, x, y, z). <lb/>The thirty-fifth column of the dataset consists of the net tilt angle data computed directly from the raw qua-<lb/>ternions data. <lb/>The last column of data is the thumb displacement data (cm) measured from the laser displacement sensor. <lb/>Depending on the experiment, each CSV file was named in the following nomenclature: &apos;(Participant ID)_ <lb/>trial_(trial no)_(condition name).csv. &apos; <lb/>Description of the data columns of the Friction experiment. First six columns (column num-<lb/>ber: 1,2,3,4,5,6) includes forces (in N) and moments (in Nmm) data of the finger (either index or thumb): <lb/>Fx(horizontal tangential force), Fy (vertical tangential force), Fz (normal force), Mx(Moment about horizontal <lb/>tangential force), My(Moment about the vertical tangential force), Mz(Moment about the normal force) <lb/>Technical Validation <lb/>a) Position and Orientation data validation <lb/>The entire experimental handle, counter-weight, and the experimental table were made from material <lb/>like aluminum and wood in order to get rid of the magnetic interference caused due to the usage of the <lb/>electromagnetic tracker. Further, the electromagnetic tracking sensors were properly calibrated prior to the <lb/>data collection. Besides all this, before the start of the trial, a command called Boresight (ctrl + B) was used <lb/>to set the initial position and orientation of Polhemus data as zero with reference to the electromagnetic <lb/>transmitter. Therefore, during the trial, at any instance, a change in the position or orientation of the han-<lb/>dle from its initial configuration would be measured accurately. From the orientation data such as azimuth, <lb/>elevation, and roll data (in degrees), the net tilt angle was computed for the first and second experiments. <lb/>As a preliminary step, the orientation data were low pass filtered with a cut-off frequency of 25 Hz and con-<lb/>verted to radians. Next, the filtered angular data was used to construct direction cosine matrix (or rotation <lb/>matrix). For each rotation matrix, the trace (sum of the diagonal elements) of the matrix was calculated. <lb/>Finally, the net tilt angle data (Ѳ) was computed using the following Eq. (1) and displayed in the experi-<lb/>menter monitor. Net tilt angle in the form of time series was computed for each trial. <lb/>θ = <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>−  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>− trace <lb/>cos <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(1) <lb/>1 <lb/>In the case of the third and fourth experiment, the net tilt angle was directly computed from the raw qua-<lb/>ternions and stored separately in the 35 th column of the data file. <lb/>Finally, the net tilt angle was then averaged across the trials, samples, and participants. Table 5 shows the <lb/>average net tilt angle during the four different experiments. The first 2 s data were averaged and then sub-<lb/>tracted from each sample of Ѳ of the trial to remove any baseline shift. <lb/>b) Force data validation <lb/>The instruction to the participants was to maintain the handle in static equilibrium throughout the trial. To <lb/>achieve static equilibrium, the following criteria have to be satisfied. <lb/>• The sum of the normal forces of the index, middle, ring, and little fingers should be equal to the normal force <lb/>of the thumb. Table 6 shows the average normal force produced by each finger and thumb during the handle <lb/>stabilization during all four experiments. It was found that the sum of normal forces produced by the index, <lb/>middle, ring, and little fingers was close to the normal force produced by the thumb. <lb/>• The sum of the tangential forces of the index, middle, ring, little, and thumb should be equal to the weight <lb/>of the handle. Table 7 shows the average tangential force produced by each finger and thumb during all con-<lb/>ditions of the four experiments. The sum of the tangential forces produced by all the fingers and thumb was <lb/>almost equal to the weight of the handle. <lb/>• The sum of the moment due to the normal and tangential force of the individual fingers and thumb should be <lb/>equal to zero. Table 8 shows the moment due to normal force (Mn) and tangential force (Mt) produced by each <lb/>finger and thumb and the total moment at each thumb position during all conditions of the four experiments. <lb/>experiment-4: Thumb normal force data validation. Since, in the fourth experiment, the thumb nor-<lb/>mal force data was shown as visual feedback to the participants for tracing the target force line, the root mean <lb/>square error of the thumb normal force with reference to the target line was computed. The average root mean <lb/>square error of the thumb normal force and standard deviation for the simple and weak grasp are 0.24 ± 0.05 N <lb/>and 0.36 ± 0.07 N. <lb/>c) Thumb displacement data validation <lb/>Since the thumb displacement data collected during the experiments 2 and 3 was shown as visual feedback <lb/>on the participant monitor to trace the pattern (in experiment 2) and target horizontal line (in experi-<lb/>ment 3), root mean squared error was computed only for the displacement data of the second and third <lb/>experiment. <lb/>Experiment 2. The root mean square error of the thumb displacement data with reference to the tem-<lb/>plate pattern was computed for the first 100 datapoints of the static thumb positions (TOP, HOME-TOP, <lb/>HOME-BOTTOM, BOTTOM). The average root mean square error of the thumb displacement data and stand-<lb/>ard deviation at four different thumb positions are 0.055 ± 0.016, 0.059 ± 0.023, 0.050 ± 0.008, 0.112 ± 0.033 cm. <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:452 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01497-x <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>
			
			<body>Experiment 3. The root mean square error of the thumb displacement data with reference to the target line was <lb/>computed. The average root mean square error of the thumb displacement data and standard deviation for the <lb/>external loads of masses 0.150 kg, 0.250 kg, 0.350 kg and 0.450 kg was 0.021 ± 0.005, 0.024 ± 0.006, 0.024 ± 0.007 <lb/>and 0.032 ± 0.018 cm. <lb/>Behavioural validation. Only the right-hand dominant male volunteers were recruited for participation. <lb/>Usage Notes <lb/>Grip width of the experimental handle used in experiments 1 and 2 = 6.6 cm <lb/>Grip width of the experimental handle used in experiment 3 and 4 = 6.2 cm <lb/>For all the experiments, the distance between the centers of individual finger sensors (excluding the <lb/>thumb) = 2 cm <lb/>At the HOME position, the center of the thumb sensor was aligned midway between the middle and ring <lb/>finger sensor centers for all the experiments <lb/>The thumb displacement data stored in the data file was obtained from the laser displacement sensor after <lb/>calibration. <lb/>For experiment 1, the calibrated HOME position = 3.48 cm. <lb/>For experiment 2, the calibrated HOME position = 7 cm. Moving the thumb platform upwards by 1.5 cm <lb/>would show a calibrated value of 5.5 cm. While translating the thumb platform downwards by 1.5 cm would <lb/>show a calibrated value of 8.5 cm. <lb/>For experiment 3, the calibrated HOME position = 6.17 cm. <lb/>For experiment 4, the calibrated HOME position = 6.21 cm. <lb/>Moments for all the experiments were calculated with respect to the center of mass (COM) of the handle <lb/>(represented as &apos;X&apos;). For the experimental handle of experiments 1 and 2, the center of the thumb sensor at <lb/>HOME position lies at 0.6 cm below COM. In the case of the experimental handle used for the third and fourth <lb/>experiment, the center of the thumb sensor at the HOME position lies 1 cm below COM. <lb/>The friction coefficient was computed by dividing the horizontal tangential force and normal force from <lb/>when the platform translated until the finger slipped from the finger. <lb/>Outcome variable Experiment <lb/>Condition <lb/>Thumb position <lb/>Mean (°) SD <lb/>Net tilt angle <lb/>Experiment 1 <lb/>Fixed <lb/>Home <lb/>4.13 <lb/>2.31 <lb/>Free <lb/>Home <lb/>3.83 <lb/>1.82 <lb/>Experiment 2 <lb/>Trapezoid <lb/>Top <lb/>1.29 <lb/>0.47 <lb/>Home-Top <lb/>1.40 <lb/>0.44 <lb/>Inverted Trapezoid <lb/>Home-Bottom <lb/>2.13 <lb/>1.05 <lb/>Bottom <lb/>2.06 <lb/>0.83 <lb/>Experiment 3 <lb/>0.150 kg <lb/>Home <lb/>0.58 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>0.250 kg <lb/>Home <lb/>0.73 <lb/>0.19 <lb/>0.350 kg <lb/>Home <lb/>0.70 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.450 kg <lb/>Home <lb/>0.81 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>Experiment 4 <lb/>simple grasp <lb/>Home <lb/>0.72 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>weak grasp <lb/>Home <lb/>0.78 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>Table 5. Average Net tilt angle with the standard deviation of all the conditions during the four experiments are <lb/>shown. SD represents standard deviation. <lb/>Outcome variable Condition <lb/>Thumb position Index Middle Ring Little <lb/>Thumb <lb/>I + M + R + L <lb/>Normal force <lb/>Fixed <lb/>Home <lb/>1.63 <lb/>1.33 <lb/>1.21 <lb/>1.09 <lb/>5.36 <lb/>5.26 <lb/>Free <lb/>Home <lb/>1.65 <lb/>1.84 <lb/>2.69 <lb/>2.86 <lb/>9.16 <lb/>9.04 <lb/>Trapezoid <lb/>Top <lb/>3.51 <lb/>1.96 <lb/>1.89 <lb/>1.22 <lb/>8.70 <lb/>8.58 <lb/>Home-Top <lb/>1.64 <lb/>1.79 <lb/>2.59 <lb/>3.43 <lb/>9.58 <lb/>9.45 <lb/>Inverted Trapezoid <lb/>Home-Bottom <lb/>2.15 <lb/>1.86 <lb/>2.90 <lb/>2.78 <lb/>9.79 <lb/>9.69 <lb/>Bottom <lb/>0.80 <lb/>0.94 <lb/>3.02 <lb/>7.25 <lb/>12.13 <lb/>12.01 <lb/>0.150 kg <lb/>Home <lb/>1.79 <lb/>2.58 <lb/>4.55 <lb/>4.75 <lb/>13.73 <lb/>13.67 <lb/>0.250 kg <lb/>Home <lb/>1.54 <lb/>2.46 <lb/>4.84 <lb/>5.07 <lb/>13.97 <lb/>13.91 <lb/>0.350 kg <lb/>Home <lb/>1.55 <lb/>2.81 <lb/>5.29 <lb/>5.70 <lb/>15.44 <lb/>15.35 <lb/>0.450 kg <lb/>Home <lb/>1.68 <lb/>2.79 <lb/>5.03 <lb/>6.94 <lb/>16.50 <lb/>16.44 <lb/>Simple <lb/>Home <lb/>1.88 <lb/>2.76 <lb/>4.61 <lb/>4.49 <lb/>13.89 <lb/>13.74 <lb/>Weak <lb/>Home <lb/>0.65 <lb/>1.01 <lb/>2.13 <lb/>3.36 <lb/>7.28 <lb/>7.15 <lb/>Table 6. Average normal force data of the individual fingers and thumb during different conditions of the four <lb/>experiments are shown. The unit of normal force data is in Newton. <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:452 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01497-x <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<div type="availability">code availability <lb/>The Matlab code provided with this article includes the code for fetching the fingertip force data of all the fingers <lb/>and thumb displacement data from the dataset file. The nomenclature of the Matlab file is forceanddisp_dataplots.m. <lb/>This code helps to average the normal forces, tangential forces of individual fingers separately and thumb <lb/>displacement data across the trials and participants. Further, the code plots the averaged normal and tangential force <lb/>data of the individual fingers and thumb. The Matlab software version used for this code was MATLABR2016b. We <lb/>had also provided the code for preprocessing the dataset and it is named as filter_code.m. The Matlab code for the <lb/>moment computation of the data collected from experimental handle-1 of the first experiment is given separately <lb/>and it is named as momentcomputation.m. Matlab codes are available in figshare along with the raw dataset 21 . <lb/></div>

			<front>Received: 7 March 2022; Accepted: 28 June 2022; <lb/>Published: xx xx xxxx <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Johansson, R. S. &amp; Westling, G. Roles of glabrous skin receptors and sensorimotor memory in automatic control of precision grip <lb/>when lifting rougher or more slippery objects. Exp Brain Res 56, 550-564 (1984). <lb/>2. Winstein, C. J., Abbs, J. H. &amp; Petashnick, D. Influences of object weight and instruction on grip force adjustments. Exp Brain Res 87, <lb/>465-469 (1991). <lb/>3. Zatsiorsky, V. M., Gao, F. &amp; Latash, M. L. Finger force vectors in multi-finger prehension. J Biomech 36, 1745-1749 (2003). <lb/>4. Zatsiorsky, V. M., Gao, F. &amp; Latash, M. L. Prehension synergies: Effects of object geometry and prescribed torques. Exp Brain Res <lb/>148, 77-87 (2003). <lb/>5. Santello, M. &amp; Soechting, J. F. Force synergies for multifingered grasping. Exp Brain Res 133, 457-467 (2000). <lb/>6. Aoki, T., Latash, M. L. &amp; Zatsiorsky, V. M. Adjustments to Local Friction in Multifinger Prehension. J Mot Behav 39, 276-290 (2007). <lb/>7. Cole, K. J. &amp; Johansson, R. S. Friction at the digit-object interface scales the sensorimotor transformation for grip responses to <lb/>pulling loads. Exp Brain Res 95, 523-532 (1993). <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Outcome variable <lb/>Condition <lb/>Thumb position <lb/>Index <lb/>Middle <lb/>Ring <lb/>Little <lb/>Thumb <lb/>I + M + R + L + T <lb/>Mass of the <lb/>handle (N) <lb/>% of <lb/>error <lb/>Tangential force <lb/>Fixed <lb/>Home <lb/>0.85 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.74 <lb/>0.41 <lb/>2.70 <lb/>5.70 <lb/>5.24 <lb/>8.77 <lb/>Free <lb/>Home <lb/>0.77 <lb/>1.08 <lb/>1.25 <lb/>1.14 <lb/>1.09 <lb/>5.33 <lb/>5.24 <lb/>1.71 <lb/>Trapezoid <lb/>Top <lb/>0.92 <lb/>1.54 <lb/>1.34 <lb/>0.80 <lb/>1.23 <lb/>5.83 <lb/>5.24 <lb/>11.25 <lb/>Home-Top <lb/>0.82 <lb/>1.30 <lb/>1.28 <lb/>1.45 <lb/>1 <lb/>5.85 <lb/>5.24 <lb/>11.64 <lb/>Inverted Trapezoid <lb/>Home-Bottom <lb/>0.62 <lb/>1.19 <lb/>1.50 <lb/>1.31 <lb/>1.15 <lb/>5.77 <lb/>5.24 <lb/>10.11 <lb/>Bottom <lb/>0.43 <lb/>0.70 <lb/>1.13 <lb/>2.66 <lb/>0.93 <lb/>5.85 <lb/>5.24 <lb/>11.64 <lb/>0.150 kg <lb/>Home <lb/>0.77 <lb/>1.10 <lb/>1.64 <lb/>2.03 <lb/>1.15 <lb/>6.69 <lb/>5.88 <lb/>13.77 <lb/>0.250 kg <lb/>Home <lb/>0.82 <lb/>1.31 <lb/>1.92 <lb/>2.54 <lb/>1.19 <lb/>7.78 <lb/>6.86 <lb/>13.41 <lb/>0.350 kg <lb/>Home <lb/>0.89 <lb/>1.50 <lb/>2.26 <lb/>2.80 <lb/>1.15 <lb/>8.60 <lb/>7.84 <lb/>9.69 <lb/>0.450 kg <lb/>Home <lb/>1.04 <lb/>1.73 <lb/>2.52 <lb/>3.22 <lb/>1.15 <lb/>9.66 <lb/>8.82 <lb/>9.52 <lb/>Simple <lb/>Home <lb/>0.79 <lb/>1.54 <lb/>1.99 <lb/>2.06 <lb/>1.22 <lb/>7.62 <lb/>6.86 <lb/>11.07 <lb/>Weak <lb/>Home <lb/>0.68 <lb/>1.16 <lb/>1.74 <lb/>2.32 <lb/>1.22 <lb/>7.14 <lb/>6.86 <lb/>4.08 <lb/>Table 7. Average tangential force data of the individual fingers and thumb during different conditions of the <lb/>four experiments are shown. The unit of tangential force data is in Newton. <lb/>Condition <lb/>Index <lb/>Middle <lb/>Ring <lb/>Little <lb/>Thumb <lb/>Total <lb/>Mn <lb/>Mt <lb/>Mn <lb/>Mt <lb/>Mn (−) Mt <lb/>Mn (−) Mt <lb/>Mn <lb/>Mt (−) (Mn + Mt) <lb/>Fixed <lb/>44.61 <lb/>28.27 <lb/>7.29 <lb/>33 <lb/>17.20 <lb/>24.68 <lb/>39.50 <lb/>13.84 <lb/>23.24 <lb/>89.24 <lb/>29 <lb/>Free <lb/>43.59 <lb/>25.51 <lb/>8.18 <lb/>35.65 <lb/>40.89 <lb/>41.39 <lb/>103.15 <lb/>37.70 <lb/>28.16 <lb/>36.09 <lb/>40.06 <lb/>Trapezoid <lb/>94.87 <lb/>30.42 <lb/>12.43 <lb/>51.14 <lb/>28.23 <lb/>44.27 <lb/>44.94 <lb/>26.42 <lb/>−110.88 40.82 <lb/>34.67 <lb/>43.25 <lb/>27.17 <lb/>10.67 <lb/>43.20 <lb/>40.28 <lb/>42.36 <lb/>124.23 <lb/>47.96 <lb/>16.55 <lb/>33.01 <lb/>33.66 <lb/>

			Inverted Trapezoid <lb/>54.95 <lb/>20.61 <lb/>9.58 <lb/>39.56 <lb/>46.91 <lb/>49.69 <lb/>103.57 <lb/>43.49 <lb/>31.69 <lb/>37.98 <lb/>61.13 <lb/>20.55 <lb/>14.47 <lb/>4.17 <lb/>23.21 <lb/>51.21 <lb/>37.54 <lb/>263.94 <lb/>87.92 <lb/>206.04 <lb/>30.73 <lb/>48.03 <lb/>0.150 kg <lb/>40.71 <lb/>23.98 <lb/>2.18 <lb/>34.17 <lb/>85.87 <lb/>50.99 <lb/>187.22 <lb/>63.11 <lb/>115.17 <lb/>35.95 <lb/>21.29 <lb/>0.250 kg <lb/>34.72 <lb/>25.65 <lb/>2.97 <lb/>40.85 <lb/>91.74 <lb/>59.68 <lb/>199.20 <lb/>79 <lb/>114.51 <lb/>36.99 <lb/>29.47 <lb/>0.350 kg <lb/>35.20 <lb/>27.63 <lb/>4.19 <lb/>46.60 <lb/>100.55 <lb/>70.08 <lb/>225.03 <lb/>86.94 <lb/>125.57 <lb/>35.78 <lb/>34.89 <lb/>0.450 kg <lb/>40.01 <lb/>32.52 <lb/>3.55 <lb/>53.70 <lb/>91.86 <lb/>78.30 <lb/>270.27 <lb/>100 <lb/>139.50 <lb/>35.86 <lb/>49.69 <lb/>Simple <lb/>43.33 <lb/>24.64 <lb/>1.02 <lb/>47.74 <lb/>92.68 <lb/>61.98 <lb/>180.55 <lb/>64.09 <lb/>115.37 <lb/>38.04 <lb/>46.90 <lb/>Weak <lb/>15.72 <lb/>21.23 <lb/>1.47 <lb/>36.04 <lb/>42.42 <lb/>54.14 <lb/>135.95 <lb/>71.95 <lb/>55.29 <lb/>38.10 <lb/>39.37 <lb/>Table 8. Average moment due to normal and tangential force data of the individual fingers and thumb and total <lb/>moment during different conditions of the four experiments are shown. Negative sign (&apos;−&apos;) indicates clockwise <lb/>moment. Mn represents moment due to normal force. Mn was computed by considering the center of pressure <lb/>of the individual fingers. Mt represents moment due to tangential force. The unit of the Moment due to normal <lb/>and tangential force data is in Newton millimetre. <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/> (2022) 9:452 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01497-x <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>8. Cadoret, G. &amp; Smith, A. M. Friction, not texture, dictates grip forces used during object manipulation. J Neurophysiol 75, 1963-1969 (1996). <lb/>9. Zatsiorsky, V. M., Gao, F. &amp; Latash, M. L. Prehension Stability: Experiments With Expanding and Contracting Handle. J Neurophysiol <lb/>95, 2513-2529 (2006). <lb/>10. Slota, G. P., Latash, M. L. &amp; Zatsiorsky, V. M. Tangential Finger Forces Use Mechanical Advantage during Static Grasping. Journal of <lb/>Applied Biomechanics 28, 78-84 (2012). <lb/>11. Solnik, S., Zatsiorsky, V. M. &amp; Latash, M. L. Internal Forces during Static Prehension: Effects of Age and Grasp Configuration. J Mot <lb/>Behav 46, 211-222 (2014). <lb/>12. Rajakumar, B. &amp; Skm, V. Comparable behaviour of ring and little fingers due to an artificial reduction in thumb contribution to hold <lb/>objects. PeerJ, https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.9962 (2020). <lb/>13. Banuvathy, R. &amp; Varadhan, S. K. M. Distinct behavior of the little finger during the vertical translation of an unsteady thumb <lb/>platform while grasping. Sci Rep 11, 21064 (2021). <lb/>14. Marshall, V. C. &amp; Marshall, R. D. Movements of the Thumb in Relation to Peripheral Nerve Injuries. Postgrad Med J 39, 518-525 (1963). <lb/>15. Kwakkel, G. et al. Standardized measurement of sensorimotor recovery in stroke trials: Consensus-based core recommendations <lb/>from the Stroke Recovery and Rehabilitation Roundtable. Int J Stroke 12, 451-461 (2017). <lb/>16. Eschmann, H., Héroux, M. E., Cheetham, J. H., Potts, S. &amp; Diong, J. Thumb and finger movement is reduced after stroke: An <lb/>observational study. PLOS ONE 14, e0217969 (2019). <lb/>17. Nowak, D. A. The impact of stroke on the performance of grasping: usefulness of kinetic and kinematic motion analysis. Neurosci <lb/>Biobehav Rev 32, 1439-1450 (2008). <lb/>18. Savescu, A. V., Latash, M. L. &amp; Zatsiorsky, V. M. A technique to determine friction at the finger tips. J Appl Biomech 24, 43-50 (2008). <lb/>19. Park, J., Pažin, N., Friedman, J., Zatsiorsky, V. M. &amp; Latash, M. L. Mechanical properties of the human hand digits: Age-related <lb/>differences. Clinical Biomechanics 29, 129-137 (2014). <lb/>20. Rajakumar, B., Dutta, S. &amp; Varadhan, S. K. M. Support for mechanical advantage hypothesis of grasping cannot be explained only by <lb/>task mechanics. Sci Rep 12, 10242 (2022). <lb/>21. Rajakumar, B. &amp; Varadhan, S. K. M. Datasets of fingertip forces while grasping a handle with unsteady thumb platform. figshare <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.19207875.v4 (2022). <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We like to thank Niraj Kumar and Archana MS for their contribution to the data collection of the Experiment-1. <lb/>Also, we thank Swarnab Dutta, Thomas Jacob and Eswari Balasubramanian for their contribution to the <lb/>data collection of the Experiment-3 and 4. We would like to extend our thanks to Department of Science &amp; <lb/>Technology, Government of India, for supporting this work, vide Reference Nos SR/CSRI/97/2014 &amp; DST/ <lb/>CSRI/2017/87 under Cognitive Science Research Initiative (CSRI) (awarded to Varadhan SKM), American <lb/>Express (funding awarded to DART lab, IIT Madras) and &quot;Women leading IIT Madras (WLI)&quot; Grant (awarded to <lb/>Banuvathy Rajakumar). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, <lb/>or preparation of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions <lb/>Data Collection -B.R., V.S.K.M.; Methodology -B.R., V.S.K.M.; Formal Analysis -B.R.; Writing Original Draft -<lb/>B.R.; Writing, Review, and Editing -B.R., V.S.K.M. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">competing interests <lb/>The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<front>Additional information <lb/>Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to V.S. <lb/>Reprints and permissions information is available at www.nature.com/reprints. <lb/>Publisher&apos;s note Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and <lb/>institutional affiliations. <lb/> Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International <lb/>License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or <lb/>format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Cre-<lb/>ative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this <lb/>article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the <lb/>material. If material is not included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not per-<lb/>mitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the <lb/>copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. <lb/>© The Author(s) 2022 </front>

	</text>
</tei>
