<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>MMP-9 release into collateral blood vessels before <lb/>endovascular thrombectomy to assess the risk of major <lb/>intracerebral haemorrhages and poor outcome for acute <lb/>ischaemic stroke: a proof-of-concept study <lb/>Alexander M. Kollikowski, a, * Mirko Pham, a Alexander G. März, a Jörn Feick, a,b Marius L. Vogt, a Yanyan Xiong, a Marc Strinitz, a,c Christoph Vollmuth, d <lb/>Fabian Essig, d Hermann Neugebauer, d Karl Georg Haeusler, d Christian Hametner, d Lena Zimmermann, d Guido Stoll, d,e and <lb/>Michael K. Schuhmann d, * * <lb/>a <lb/>Department of Neuroradiology, University Hospital Würzburg, Würzburg, Germany <lb/>b <lb/>Department of Radiology, University Hospital Würzburg, Würzburg, Germany <lb/>c <lb/>Department of Neuroradiology, Rechts der Isar Hospital, Technical University Munich, Munich, Germany <lb/>d <lb/>Department of Neurology, University Hospital Würzburg, Würzburg, Germany <lb/>e <lb/>Institute of Experimental Biomedicine, University Hospital Würzburg, Würzburg, Germany <lb/>Summary <lb/>Background Matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs) are implied in blood-brain barrier degradation and haemorrhagic <lb/>transformation following ischaemic stroke, but their local relevance in the hyperacute disease phase is unknown. <lb/>We aimed to examine ultra-early MMP-9 and MMP-2 release into collateral blood vessels, and to assess its <lb/>prognostic value before therapeutic recanalisation by endovascular thrombectomy (EVT). <lb/>Methods We report a cross-sectional proof-of-concept study including patients undergoing EVT for large-vessel <lb/>ischaemic stroke at the University Hospital Würzburg, Germany. We obtained liquid biopsies from the collateral <lb/>circulation before recanalisation, and systemic control samples. Laboratory workup included quantification of <lb/>MMP-9 and MMP-2 plasma concentrations by cytometric bead array, immunohistochemical analyses of cellular <lb/>MMP-9 and MMP-2 expression, and detection of proteolytic activity by gelatine zymography. The clinical impact <lb/>of MMP concentrations was assessed by stratification according to intracranial haemorrhagic lesions on <lb/>postinterventional computed tomography (Heidelberg Bleeding Classification, HBC) and early functional outcome <lb/>(modified Rankin Scale, mRS). We used multivariable logistic regression, receiver-operating-characteristic (ROC) <lb/>curves, and fixed-level estimates of test accuracy measures to study the prognostic value of MMP-9 concentrations. <lb/>Findings Between August 3, 2018, and September 16, 2021, 264 matched samples from 132 patients (86 [65.2%] <lb/>women, 46 [34.8%] men, aged 40-94 years) were obtained. Median (interquartile range, IQR) MMP-9 (279.7 [IQR <lb/>126.4-569.6] vs 441 [IQR 223.4-731.5] ng/ml, p &lt; 0.0001) but not MMP-2 concentrations were increased within <lb/>collateral blood vessels. The median MMP-9 expression level of invading neutrophils was elevated (fluorescence <lb/>intensity, arbitrary unit: 2276 [IQR 1007-5086] vs 3078 [IQR 1108-7963], p = 0.0018). Gelatine zymography <lb/>experiments indicated the locally confined proteolytic activity of MMP-9 but not of MMP-2. Pretherapeutic MMP-9 <lb/>release into stroke-affected brain regions predicted the degree of intracerebral haemorrhages and clinical stroke <lb/>severity after recanalisation, and independently increased the odds of space-occupying parenchymal haematomas <lb/>(HBC1c-3a) by 1.54 times, and the odds of severe disability or death (mRS ≥5 at hospital discharge) by 2.33 <lb/>times per 1000 ng/ml increase. Excessive concentrations of MMP-9 indicated impending parenchymal <lb/>haematomas and severe disability or death with high specificity. <lb/>Interpretation Measurement of MMP-9 within collateral blood vessels is feasible and identifies patients with stroke at <lb/>risk of major intracerebral haemorrhages and poor outcome before therapeutic recanalisation by EVT, thereby <lb/>providing evidence of the concept validity of ultra-early local stroke biomarkers. <lb/>*Corresponding author. Department of Neuroradiology, University Hospital Würzburg, Josef-Schneider-Str.11, 97080, Würzburg, Germany. <lb/>**Corresponding author. Department of Neurology, University Hospital Würzburg, Josef-Schneider-Str.11, 97080, Würzburg, Germany. <lb/>E-mail addresses: Kollikowsk_A@ukw.de (A.M. Kollikowski), Schuhmann_M@ukw.de (M.K. Schuhmann), Pham_M@ukw.de (M. Pham), Maerz_ <lb/>A@ukw.de (A.G. März), Feick_J@ukw.de (J. Feick), Vogt_M2@ukw.de (M.L. Vogt), Xiong_Y@ukw.de (Y. Xiong), Marc.Strinitz@tum.de (M. Stri-<lb/>nitz), Vollmuth_C1@ukw.de (C. Vollmuth), Essig_F@ukw.de (F. Essig), Neugebauer_H@ukw.de (H. Neugebauer), Haeusler_K@ukw.de (K.G. <lb/>Haeusler), Hametner_C@ukw.de (C. Hametner), Papp_L@ukw.de (L. Zimmermann), Stoll_G@ukw.de (G. Stoll). <lb/>eBioMedicine <lb/>2024;103: 105095 <lb/>Published Online 4 April <lb/>2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.ebiom.2024. <lb/>105095 <lb/>www.thelancet.com Vol 103 May, 2024 <lb/>1 <lb/>Articles <lb/>Funding This work was funded by the German Research Foundation (Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft, DFG) and <lb/>the Interdisciplinary Centre for Clinical Research (IZKF) at the University of Würzburg. <lb/>Copyright © 2024 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier B.V. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC <lb/>license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/). <lb/>Keywords: Stroke; Ischaemic stroke; Large-vessel occlusion; Matrix metalloproteinases; MMP-9; MMP-2; Biomarker; <lb/>Haemorrhage; Outcome; Mechanical thrombectomy; Endovascular therapy <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Endovascular thrombectomy (EVT) represents the most <lb/>effective treatment for large-vessel ischaemic stroke, <lb/>achieving complete independence in activities of daily <lb/>living in a large proportion of patients. 1-5 Yet there is a <lb/>trade-off between the indisputable overall benefit <lb/>conferred by EVT, and the subgroup of patients which <lb/>presents with poorer prognosis due to critical infarct <lb/>progression either before or after clot removal. 6 In these <lb/>patients, the clinical consequences may comprise <lb/>intracranial haemorrhagic complications and neurolog-<lb/>ical impairment in a wide variety of manifestations. 4,7,8 <lb/>Although overall factors associated with such out-<lb/>comes have been well-delineated in post-hoc analyses of <lb/>randomised controlled trials (RCTs) of EVT, 7,8 <lb/>individual-level factors to accurately identify patients at <lb/>risk for the most severe ends of the spectra still remain <lb/>to be elucidated to establish the best practice for clinical <lb/>management. 9,10 Hence, identifying distinct risk bio-<lb/>markers and implementing non-traditional clinical trial <lb/>designs in large-vessel ischaemic stroke (e.g., <lb/>biomarker-adaptive) could allow for adjustment of in-<lb/>dividual treatment decisions in high-risk groups. <lb/>Disintegration of the neurovascular unit (NVU) <lb/>including degradation of the endothelial and <lb/>parenchymal basal lamina is a major pathophysiological <lb/>substrate of cerebral infarction, its clinical course, and <lb/>haemorrhagic events. 11,12 Principal effector molecules <lb/>comprise matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs), a group of <lb/>endopeptidases which, when activated upon cleavage, <lb/>are capable of destructing all components of the extra-<lb/>cellular matrix. 11 Among 24 mammalian MMPs, MMP-9 <lb/>and MMP-2 stand out due to their implication in stroke-<lb/>induced blood-brain barrier (BBB) breakdown, vaso-<lb/>genic oedema, and haemorrhagic transformation. 11,13 <lb/>However, conflicting clinical data exist addressing the <lb/>association of MMPs with stroke treatment and <lb/>prognosis. 14-17 These variations in prognostic value can <lb/>be explained by the fact that sample material was <lb/>restricted to systemic sites, which are prone to dilution <lb/>effects, 18,19 and largely obtained at late time points at <lb/>which infarct progression and MMP release by various <lb/>resident brain cells have already occurred. 11 <lb/>Recent evidence suggests that large-vessel ischaemic <lb/>stroke elicits a rapidly evolving intravascular inflamma-<lb/>tory response, which is carried into the ischaemic ter-<lb/>ritory by retrograde collateral supply through pial <lb/>anastomoses, and dominated by neutrophils. 18-20 Retro-<lb/>gradely invading immune cells such as neutrophils <lb/>represent a potential source of MMPs. 11 We therefore <lb/>Research in context <lb/>Evidence before this study <lb/>Matrix metalloproteinase (MMP)-9 and MMP-2 have long <lb/>been implicated in haemorrhagic transformation and <lb/>neurological impairment following ischaemic stroke, but no <lb/>human studies exist on hyperacute release into stroke-<lb/>affected brain regions and its prognostic significance in a <lb/>therapeutic context. <lb/>Added value of this study <lb/>This study investigates MMP-9 and MMP-2, and their <lb/>prognostic relevance in cerebral liquid biopsies from collateral <lb/>blood vessels of patients with large-vessel ischaemic stroke <lb/>before therapeutic recanalisation by endovascular <lb/>thrombectomy (EVT). We analysed 264 samples of 132 <lb/>consecutive patients, indicating the locally confined release of <lb/>enzymatically active MMP-9 but not of MMP-2 into an <lb/>occluded arterial territory. On single-cell level, invading <lb/>neutrophils were identified as intravascular source of MMP-9. <lb/>Local MMP-9 release independently increased the odds of <lb/>space-occupying parenchymal haematomas, and severe <lb/>disability or death in the early clinical course after therapeutic <lb/>recanalisation by EVT. Additionally, our data suggest that <lb/>excessive local MMP-9 concentrations may add considerable <lb/>value for predicting these events. <lb/>Implications of all the available evidence <lb/>Our results posit MMP-9 within collateral blood vessels as <lb/>pathophysiologically relevant biomarker to identify the <lb/>clinically most relevant high-risk groups for deleterious <lb/>outcome among EVT candidates, i.e., before recanalisation of <lb/>the occluded vessel and reperfusion of the target territory. <lb/>Although further external validation is warranted, these <lb/>findings have far-reaching implications for future preclinical <lb/>and clinical stroke research including trial design and clinical <lb/>management as they provide the proof-of-concept for the <lb/>potential prognostic utility of an ultra-early local biomarker <lb/>before therapeutic recanalisation. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 103 May, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<body>aimed to investigate whether MMP-9 and/or MMP-2 are <lb/>released into collateral blood vessels at ultra-early time <lb/>points and predict the formation of space-occupying <lb/>parenchymal haematomas, and severe disability or <lb/>death before therapeutic recanalisation by EVT. For this <lb/>purpose, we took advantage of timed and systematic <lb/>endovascular sampling of liquid biopsies from the <lb/>occluded cerebral vasculature before the final decision <lb/>of recanalisation by clot retrieval was made. 18,19,21 <lb/>Methods <lb/>Study design and participants <lb/>Standardised sampling of liquid biopsies from the hu-<lb/>man collateral circulation was attempted during EVT for <lb/>cerebral large-vessel occlusion in a prospective cross-<lb/>sectional proof-of-concept study of consecutive patients <lb/>with stroke presenting at the Departments of Neurora-<lb/>diology and Neurology, University Hospital Würzburg <lb/>(Würzburg, Germany) between August 3, 2018, and <lb/>September 16, 2021. 18,19 Indication for EVT was given by <lb/>disabling acute stroke and non-invasive imaging quali-<lb/>fying for stroke intervention according to current <lb/>guidelines and consensus recommendations. 9 Patients <lb/>with occlusion locations homologous to standard <lb/>experimental middle cerebral artery (MCA) occlusion <lb/>models were included (i.e., terminal internal carotid <lb/>artery (ICA), MCA-M1, and proximal MCA-M2 <lb/>segment, respectively). 6,22 The final target population <lb/>comprised all patients undergoing EVT for invasively <lb/>confirmed total vascular occlusion in whom intra-<lb/>procedural aspiration and processing of 1 ml of citrate-<lb/>phosphate-dextrose-adenine <lb/>(CPDA)-anticoagulated <lb/>local ischaemic and systemic arterial whole blood was <lb/>successfully performed according to the protocol previ-<lb/>ously published by our group. 18,19 Key exclusion criteria <lb/>were proven bilateral or multifocal large-vessel occlu-<lb/>sion; occlusion locations other than terminal ICA, <lb/>MCA-M1, and MCA-M2 segment; antegrade cerebral <lb/>blood flow; large-vessel occlusion in conjunction with <lb/>either ≥50% cervical ICA stenosis or ICA dissection <lb/>with or without necessitating intraprocedural cervical <lb/>ICA percutaneous transluminal angioplasty (PTA) or <lb/>stent implantation 19 ; and any deviation from the endo-<lb/>vascular, sampling or sample pre-processing procedures <lb/>(see below). The complete flow of patients without <lb/>missing cases is presented in Fig. 1. <lb/>Sex, reported as male or female, was determined by <lb/>checking the patients&apos; identification data and through <lb/>observation of physiological characteristics; current <lb/>gender identity was not recorded. <lb/>Informed consent was obtained from patients or <lb/>their legal representatives. Ethical approval was pro-<lb/>vided by the Ethics Committee of the University of <lb/>Würzburg (approval number 135/17-me). The study <lb/>was conducted in conformity with the Declaration <lb/>of Helsinki, and followed the Strengthening the <lb/>Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology <lb/>(STROBE) reporting guideline. 23 <lb/>Procedures <lb/>In brief, endovascular procedures were carried out by <lb/>certified neurointerventionalists or supervised neuro-<lb/>interventional fellows on biplane angiographic systems <lb/>(Artis icono or ArtisQ, Siemens Healthineers, Erlangen, <lb/>Germany). All patients underwent EVT under general <lb/>anaesthesia according to in-house standard operating <lb/>procedures. Recanalisation of the predefined target oc-<lb/>clusion by stent-embolus retrieval was preceded by <lb/>microcatheter navigation into the MCA-M2 segment to <lb/>obtain samples from within the collateral circulation <lb/>during persistent large-vessel occlusion. After micro-<lb/>catheter (NeuroSlider 27 or 21; Acandis, Pforzheim, <lb/>Germany) navigation to the target sampling location and <lb/>discarding the microcatheter-specific dead space vol-<lb/>ume, sampling of 1 ml ischaemic blood was attempted <lb/>in every consecutive case. These cerebral target samples <lb/>were compared to intraindividual control samples taken <lb/>from the ipsilateral cervical ICA immediately after EVT <lb/>(physiological forward-flow condition). <lb/>All samples were transferred into CPDA monovettes <lb/>(#04.1938.001, Sarstedt, Nümbrecht, Germany) and <lb/>further processed. Slides stained with May-Grünwald-<lb/>Giemsa were used for neutrophil and monocyte quan-<lb/>tification. Samples were centrifuged (1000 ×g, 10 min) <lb/>and plasma was aliquoted, and frozen at -20 • C until <lb/>analysis. 18,19 <lb/>Plasma concentrations of MMP-9 and MMP-2 were <lb/>quantified by flow cytometric analysis (BD FACSLyric™ <lb/>Flow Cytometer, BD Biosciences, RRID:SCR_013311) <lb/>using fluorescent bead immunoassays according to the <lb/>manufacturers&apos; instructions (#740565 and #740559, <lb/>BioLegend, RRID:SCR_001134). <lb/>For immunofluorescent staining of MMP-9 and <lb/>MMP-2, we used 96 available air-dried cell smear slides, <lb/>comprising 48 matched pairs of systemic vs ischaemic <lb/>samples, with 24 subjects for each MMP-9 and MMP-2 <lb/>analysis. All slides were fixed with acetone for 10 min <lb/>at -20 • C and blocked for 1 h at room temperature with <lb/>phosphate-buffered saline (PBS; 1.0 M, pH 7.4) con-<lb/>taining 0.2% Triton X-100 (#T8787, Sigma-Aldrich, <lb/>RRID:SCR_008988), and 5% bovine serum albumin <lb/>(BSA; #SC-2323, Santa Cruz Biotechnology, RRID:SCR_ <lb/>008987). The slides were incubated over night at 4 • C <lb/>with a mouse monoclonal MMP-9 antibody (#819701, <lb/>BioLegend, RRID:AB_2564833; isotype IgG2a, dilution <lb/>1:100) or a mouse monoclonal MMP-2 antibody <lb/>(#436000, Thermo Fisher Scientific, RRID:AB_2532214; <lb/>isotype IgG1, dilution 1:100) in PBS containing 1% <lb/>BSA. For MMP-9, an Alexa 647-labelled secondary <lb/>polyclonal goat anti-mouse antibody (#115-605-003, <lb/>Jackson ImmunoResearch, RRID:AB_2338902; whole <lb/>IgG, dilution 1:100) and, for MMP-2, an Alexa 555-<lb/>labelled secondary polyclonal goat anti-mouse antibody <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 103 May, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Assessed for eligibility between August 2018 and September 2021 <lb/>n=684 <lb/>Exclusion: <lb/>Failed to meet non-invasive imaging inclusion criteria, n=116 <lb/>• <lb/>Vertebrobasilar stroke, n=78 <lb/>• <lb/>Bilateral or multifocal LVO, n=38 <lb/>Intraprocedural sampling before recanalisation <lb/>n=259 <lb/>Exclusion: <lb/>Failed to meet invasive imaging inclusion criteria, n=99 <lb/>• <lb/>Angiographically confirmed recanalisation or subocclusion, n=99 <lb/>Exclusion: <lb/>Violation of the sampling protocol, n=38 <lb/>• <lb/>Reversed sampling sequence and use of an incorrect catheter, n=1 <lb/>• <lb/>Non-standard EVT technique, n=8 <lb/>• <lb/>Microcatheter-specific dead space volume not discarded, n=14 <lb/>• <lb/>Non-insular sampling, n=7 <lb/>• <lb/>Use of improper monovettes, n=1 <lb/>• <lb/>No systemic sampling or samples intraprocedurally discarded, n=7 <lb/>Exclusion: <lb/>Failed to meet interventional inclusion criteria, n=43 <lb/>• <lb/>Cervical ICA stenosis (treated by PTA or stenting), n=35 <lb/>• <lb/>Cervical ICA dissection, n=8 <lb/>Analysed <lb/>n=132 <lb/>Exclusion: <lb/>Poor sample quality, n=44 <lb/>• <lb/>Insufficient sample volume, n=6 <lb/>• <lb/>Laboratory receipt of samples ≥12h after initial sampling, n=38 <lb/>Infectious sample material, n=1 <lb/>Exclusion: <lb/>Empty aspiration, n=210 <lb/>Eligibility <lb/>Inclusion <lb/>l <lb/>l <lb/>u <lb/>f <lb/>n <lb/>i <lb/>t <lb/>e <lb/>m <lb/>e <lb/>b <lb/>o <lb/>t <lb/>a <lb/>i <lb/>r <lb/>e <lb/>t <lb/>i <lb/>r <lb/>c <lb/>f <lb/>o <lb/>e <lb/>c <lb/>n <lb/>e <lb/>u <lb/>q <lb/>e <lb/>S <lb/>Exclusion: <lb/>Consent denied by legal representative, n=1 <lb/>Fig. 1: Study population. EVT, endovascular thrombectomy; ICA, internal carotid artery; LVO, large-vessel occlusion; PTA, percutaneous <lb/>transluminal angioplasty. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 103 May, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<body>(#A-21422, Thermo Fisher Scientific, RRID: AB_ <lb/>2535844; whole IgG, dilution 1:200) was applied for <lb/>1 h at room temperature in PBS containing 1% BSA. <lb/>Finally, slides were embedded in Gold Antifade <lb/>Mountant with DAPI (4,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole <lb/>dihydrochloride) dye for counterstaining of cell nuclei <lb/>(#P36931, Thermo Fisher Scientific, RRID:SCR_ <lb/>008452). <lb/>For single-plane images, the slides were examined at <lb/>40× magnification on an inverted Leica DMi8 (Leica <lb/>Microsystems, RRID:SCR_008960) epifluorescence <lb/>microscope equipped with a DFC 3000 G camera <lb/>(exposure time 12.2 ms, gain 1.0). Quantification of <lb/>MMP-9 and MMP-2 fluorescence intensity at single-<lb/>neutrophil level was performed using the Fiji 24 distri-<lb/>bution (Fiji, RRID:SCR_002285) of ImageJ software. <lb/>The corrected total cellular fluorescence (CTCF) 25 was <lb/>calculated (arbitrary unit) for ten consecutive neutro-<lb/>phils present within at least three fields of view per <lb/>slide, and for 960 neutrophils in total. The integrated <lb/>fluorescence density, area, and mean grey value of <lb/>nuclei were assessed for each cell applying the <lb/>following formula: CTCF = integrated fluorescence <lb/>density of the area of the neutrophil-(the area of the <lb/>neutrophil × mean fluorescence of three background <lb/>readings). <lb/>The residual plasma volumes were retained for <lb/>further analysis of MMP isoenzymes by gelatine <lb/>zymography as described previously. 26 <lb/>Non-contrast computed tomography (CT; Somatom <lb/>Definition AS+, Siemens Healthineers, Erlangen, Ger-<lb/>many) images revealing the greatest lesion extent within <lb/>two to seven days following EVT were employed for <lb/>radiological assessment of structural tissue damage, with <lb/>presumed 100% specificity for the presence of bleeding <lb/>in areas of postinterventional cerebral hyperintensity. 27-30 <lb/>The Alberta Stroke Program Early CT Score (ASPECTS) <lb/>was used for assessing structural tissue damage in the <lb/>absence of bleeding events. 27 Intracranial bleeding events <lb/>were categorized anatomically using the Heidelberg <lb/>Bleeding Classification (HBC): HBC1a, haemorrhagic <lb/>infarction (HI1)-scattered small petechiae; HBC1b, <lb/>HI2-confluent petechiae; HBC1c, parenchymal hae-<lb/>matoma (PH1)-haematoma within infarcted tissue, <lb/>occupying &lt;30%; HBC 2, PH2-haematoma occupying <lb/>≥30% of the infarcted tissue; HBC 3a-PH remote from <lb/>infarcted brain tissue; HBC 3b-intraventricular hae-<lb/>morrhage; HBC 3c-subarachnoid haemorrhage; and <lb/>HBC 3d-subdural haemorrhage. 28,29 These events were <lb/>further stratified as absent, minor (petechial) intracere-<lb/>bral haemorrhage (combined HBC classes 1a and 1b), <lb/>major intracerebral haemorrhage (parenchymal haema-<lb/>tomas: combined HBC classes 1c, 2, and 3a), and <lb/>intracranial-extracerebral haemorrhage (combined HBC <lb/>classes 3b, 3c, and 3d). 29,31 All CT images were <lb/>consensus-read by two neuroradiologists who were <lb/>blinded to laboratory and clinical data (AGM and MS). <lb/>Early functional outcome was assessed by the <lb/>modified Rankin Scale (mRS) at hospital discharge by <lb/>certified stroke neurologists (CV and FE) who were <lb/>blinded to laboratory data and image analyses. 32 <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>Gaussian distribution was tested by the D&apos;Agostino-<lb/>Pearson normality test. 33 Data were summarized using <lb/>frequency (percentage) for categorical variables and <lb/>median (interquartile range, IQR) for continuous vari-<lb/>ables. The χ 2 , the Wilcoxon matched-pairs signed rank <lb/>test, the Mann-Whitney test, and the Kruskal-Wallis <lb/>test with Benjamini, Krieger and Yekutieli correction <lb/>(false discovery rate of 5%) 34 were used for group com-<lb/>parisons, as appropriate. Spearman&apos;s rank correlation <lb/>coefficient was applied to determine associations be-<lb/>tween MMP concentrations and leukocyte numbers. <lb/>Crude univariate (unadjusted) and multivariable-<lb/>adjusted logistic regression using stepwise-backwards <lb/>selection with a cut-off point of p &gt; 0.1 were applied <lb/>to analyse the association of MMP concentrations with <lb/>major intracerebral bleedings (combined HBC classes <lb/>1c-3a) and severe disability or death at hospital <lb/>discharge (mRS ≥5). Covariate selection (i.e., age, sex, <lb/>baseline antiplatelet treatment and anticoagulant use, <lb/>baseline National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale <lb/>(NIHSS) score, baseline ASPECTS, systolic and diastolic <lb/>blood pressure before recanalisation, alteplase admin-<lb/>istration, onset-to-puncture time, occlusion location, <lb/>number of stent-retrieval manoeuvres, reperfusion sta-<lb/>tus, onset-to-final-recanalisation time, and sampling-to-<lb/>sampling time) was based on χ 2 procedures of clinical <lb/>characteristics (p ≈ 0.1), literature review of reported <lb/>risk factors, and methodological considerations <lb/>regarding sequential intraprocedural sampling. 11,35 <lb/>Multicollinearity was assessed by examination of the <lb/>correlation matrix and variables with associations ≥0.8 <lb/>were omitted (Figure S1). 36,37 Results from logistic <lb/>regression are given as adjusted Odds ratios (OR) with <lb/>95% confidence interval (CI). Receiver-operating-<lb/>characteristic (ROC) analysis was performed to further <lb/>evaluate the logistic models and the diagnostic perfor-<lb/>mance of systemic vs ischaemic MMP-9 concentrations <lb/>as potential biomarker of major intracerebral haemor-<lb/>rhages and severe disability or death. We calculated and <lb/>compared the respective areas under the curve (AUC), 38 <lb/>and used the maximized Youden J index (overall correct <lb/>classification rate minus one) to provide a summary <lb/>measure of cut-off values. Fixed-level estimates of test <lb/>accuracy measures including sensitivity, specificity, <lb/>positive predictive value (PPV), and negative predictive <lb/>value (NPV) with 95% CI were calculated for 80%, 90%, <lb/>95%, 97.5%, and 99% sensitivity and specificity, <lb/>respectively, to provide further thresholds for potential <lb/>clinical decision making on individual patient-level. All <lb/>estimates were given along with corresponding MMP-9 <lb/>concentrations. Subgroup analyses were based on <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 103 May, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>specified research questions. Analyses used GraphPad <lb/>Prism (version 10.1.0, GraphPad Software, RRID:SCR_ <lb/>002798) and MedCalc (version 22.013, MedCalc Soft-<lb/>ware, RRID:SCR_015044). <lb/>Role of the funding source <lb/>The funders of the study had no role in study design, <lb/>data collection, data analysis, data interpretation, writing <lb/>of the manuscript, or the decision to submit it for <lb/>publication. <lb/>Results <lb/>Between August 3, 2018, and September 16, 2021, 684 <lb/>patients with large-vessel ischaemic stroke requiring <lb/>emergency EVT were screened for eligibility (Fig. 1). Of <lb/>132 consecutive patients included in the study, 86 <lb/>(65.2%) were women, and the median age was 79 (IQR <lb/>70-83) years. Table 1 shows demographic, clinical, and <lb/>radiological characteristics at presentation and over the <lb/>course of treatment. According to imaging after EVT, 67 <lb/>(50.8%) subjects were classified as having no intracra-<lb/>nial bleeding event (absent), 40 (30.3%) subjects were <lb/>classified as having a minor intracerebral haemorrhage <lb/>(HBC1a + b), 18 (13.6%) subjects were classified as <lb/>having a major intracerebral haemorrhage (HBC1c-3a), <lb/>and 7 (5.3%) subjects were classified as having an <lb/>intracranial-extracerebral haemorrhage (HBC3b-d; full <lb/>listing provided in Table S1). The median NIHSS score <lb/>at admission was highest in patients developing intra-<lb/>cerebral haemorrhagic lesions (HBC1a + b: 15 [IQR <lb/>12-18], HBC1c-3a: 16.5 [IQR 13-20.5], Kruskal-Wallis <lb/>test p = 0.0025), with no significant difference be-<lb/>tween patients with minor and major intracerebral <lb/>haemorrhages (two-stage linear step-up procedure of <lb/>Benjamini, Krieger and Yekutieli p = 0.33). Median <lb/>infarct extent on ASPECTS at admission was low in <lb/>patients without intracranial bleeding events and mod-<lb/>erate in patients with any type of subsequent intracere-<lb/>bral haemorrhage (absent: 9 [IQR 8-9] vs HBC1a + b: 7 <lb/>[IQR 6-8] vs HBC1c-3a: 7 [IQR 6-8], Kruskal-Wallis <lb/>test p &lt; 0.0001), again with no significant difference <lb/>regarding bleeding severity (two-stage linear step-up <lb/>procedure of Benjamini, Krieger and Yekutieli <lb/>p = 0.98). MCA-M2 occlusions were seen less <lb/>frequently (absent: 32.8% [22 of 67] vs HBC1a + b: 7.5% <lb/>[3 of 40] vs HBC1c-3a: 16.7% [3 of 18], χ 2 test p = 0.008) <lb/>in patients who later developed haemorrhagic lesions. <lb/>Functional outcome was significantly worse for patients <lb/>with haemorrhagic lesions when compared to absence <lb/>of bleeding events (median mRS; absent: 2 [IQR 1-5] vs <lb/>HBC1a + b: 5 [IQR 3-5] vs HBC1c-3a: 6 [IQR 5-6], <lb/>Kruskal-Wallis test p &lt; 0.0001), with major intracerebral <lb/>haemorrhages resulting in high death rates during <lb/>hospitalisation (55.6% [10 of 18]). All other de-<lb/>mographic, clinical, or treatment-related characteristics <lb/>including procedural measures were balanced and did <lb/>not show any significant difference between groups. <lb/>Freezing and storage had no impact on MMP sta-<lb/>bility, as group-stratified plasma levels (see below) were <lb/>consistent for different storage times. <lb/>The overall median MMP-9 concentration within <lb/>collateral blood vessels was increased by 57.7% as <lb/>compared to systemic control level (279.7 [IQR <lb/>126.4-569.6] vs 441 [IQR 223.4-731.5] ng/ml, Wilcoxon <lb/>matched-pairs signed rank test p &lt; 0.0001; Fig. 2a). By <lb/>contrast, no significant differences were observed for <lb/>overall median MMP-2 concentrations (Figure S2a). <lb/>Gelatine zymography of pooled plasma samples detec-<lb/>ted higher local MMP-9 but no MMP-2 activity (Fig. 2c). <lb/>To assess which cell type might represent the dominant <lb/>intravascular source of MMP-9, we conducted both <lb/>correlation analyses with corresponding numbers of <lb/>neutrophils and monocytes, and analysed MMP-9 and <lb/>MMP-2 on cellular level by immunohistochemistry. <lb/>Local overall MMP-9 concentrations were best correlated <lb/>with the number of invading neutrophils (Spearman <lb/>r = 0.35, p &lt; 0.0001; Figure S3a and c), whereas no <lb/>correlation with monocyte numbers was found <lb/>(Figure S3b and d). Consistently, fluorescence micro-<lb/>scopy of individual cells showed that large-vessel oc-<lb/>clusion induced a 1.35-fold increase of MMP-9 <lb/>expression in neutrophils in affected brain regions <lb/>(CTCF: 2276 [IQR 1007-5086] vs 3078 [IQR 1108-7963], <lb/>Wilcoxon matched-pairs signed rank test p = 0.0018; <lb/>Fig. 2b). There were no significant differences in <lb/>cellular MMP-2 expression among neutrophils sampled <lb/>from the different sites (Figure S2b). <lb/>After stratifying for intracranial bleeding events, an <lb/>association between median MMP-9 concentrations <lb/>within collateral blood vessels and type of intracerebral <lb/>bleeding was observed, with highest levels in patients <lb/>with parenchymal haematomas (HBC1a + b: 368.3 [IQR <lb/>238-731.5] vs HBC1c-3a: 643 [IQR 434.8-1873] ng/ml, <lb/>two-stage linear step-up procedure of Benjamini, <lb/>Krieger and Yekutieli p = 0.036; Fig. 2d). Equally strat-<lb/>ified systemic MMP-9 concentrations were similar in <lb/>pattern but did not significantly differ between groups. <lb/>Stratification of MMP-9 but not MMP-2 plasma levels by <lb/>neurological outcome category (i.e., mRS &lt;5 vs ≥ 5) and <lb/>sampling location revealed higher ischaemic MMP-9 <lb/>concentrations in patients with early poor neurological <lb/>outcome (mRS &lt;5: 347.6 [IQR 152.7-654.5] vs mRS ≥5: <lb/>552.2 [IQR 360.2-872.5] ng/ml, Mann-Whitney test <lb/>p = 0.0027; Fig. 2e). There was no association of MMP-2 <lb/>concentrations with occurrence and type of bleeding, or <lb/>clinical outcome (Figure S2c and d). <lb/>Further analysis of the subgroup of patients with no <lb/>haemorrhagic event showed no significant difference in <lb/>MMP-9 concentrations between patients with and <lb/>without excellent ASPECTS (≥8) values (Figure S4). <lb/>Median ischaemic MMP-9 levels were increased by <lb/>20.5% among alteplase-treated patients (401.2 [IQR <lb/>216.1-691] vs 483.6 [IQR 268.1-762.1] ng/ml, Mann-<lb/>Whitney test p = 0.32; Figure S5). There was no <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 103 May, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<body>Absent a <lb/>(n = 67) <lb/>HBC class 1a + b a <lb/>(n = 40) <lb/>HBC class 1c-3a a <lb/>(n = 18) <lb/>HBC class 3b-d a <lb/>(n = 7) <lb/>p b value <lb/>Overall <lb/>(n = 132) <lb/>Demographic <lb/>Age, median (IQR), y <lb/>79 (68-83) <lb/>80 (66.5-84) <lb/>76.5 (71.5-85.3) <lb/>71 (70-81) <lb/>0.7 <lb/>79 (70-83) <lb/>Sex <lb/>Male, n (%) <lb/>22 (32.8) <lb/>14 (35) <lb/>6 (33.3) <lb/>4 (57.1) <lb/>0.97 <lb/>46 (34.8) <lb/>Female, n (%) <lb/>45 (67.2) <lb/>26 (65) <lb/>12 (66.7) <lb/>3 (42.9) <lb/>0.97 <lb/>86 (65.2) <lb/>Medical <lb/>Hypertension, n (%) <lb/>57 (85.1) <lb/>36 (90) <lb/>14 (77.8) <lb/>7 (100) <lb/>0.46 <lb/>114 (86.4) <lb/>Diabetes mellitus, n (%) <lb/>15 (22.4) <lb/>8 (20) <lb/>3 (16.7) <lb/>1 (14.3) <lb/>0.86 <lb/>27 (20.5) <lb/>Hyperlipidemia, n (%) <lb/>22 (32.8) <lb/>16 (40) <lb/>8 (44.4) <lb/>1 (14.3) <lb/>0.58 <lb/>47 (35.6) <lb/>Atrial fibrillation, n (%) <lb/>38 (56.7) <lb/>23 (57.5) <lb/>8 (44.4) <lb/>4 (57.1) <lb/>0.61 <lb/>73 (55.3) <lb/>Smoking history, n (%) <lb/>16 (23.9) <lb/>10 (25) <lb/>2 (11.1) <lb/>2 (28.6) <lb/>0.46 <lb/>31 (23.5) <lb/>Baseline medication <lb/>Antithrombotic medication, n (%) <lb/>37 (55.2) <lb/>23 (57.5) <lb/>14 (77.8) <lb/>3 (42.9) <lb/>0.21 <lb/>77 (58.3) <lb/>Antiplatelet drugs, n (%) <lb/>18 (26.9) <lb/>12 (30) <lb/>10 (55.6) <lb/>0 (0) <lb/>0.06 <lb/>40 (30.3) <lb/>Anticoagulants, n (%) <lb/>21 (31.3) <lb/>11 (27.5) <lb/>5 (27.8) <lb/>3 (42.9) <lb/>0.9 <lb/>40 (30.3) <lb/>Antihypertensive drugs, n (%) <lb/>56 (83.6) <lb/>30 (75) <lb/>12 (66.7) <lb/>4 (57.1) <lb/>0.25 <lb/>102 (77.3) <lb/>Clinical <lb/>NIHSS at presentation, median (IQR) <lb/>12 (8-16) <lb/>15 (12-18) <lb/>16.5 (13-20.5) <lb/>9 (6-15) <lb/>0.0025 <lb/>14 (9.3-17) <lb/>Unknown onset, n (%) <lb/>20 (29.9) <lb/>15 (37.5) <lb/>7 (38.9) <lb/>3 (42.9) <lb/>0.63 <lb/>45 (34.1) <lb/>ASPECTS at presentation, median (IQR) <lb/>9 (8-9) <lb/>7 (6-8) <lb/>7 (6-8) <lb/>9 (8-10) <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>8 (7-9) <lb/>Systolic blood pressure, median (IQR), mmHg <lb/>157 (136-180) <lb/>160 (144.5-186) <lb/>160 (155-183.8) <lb/>157 (97.5-164) <lb/>0.31 <lb/>159 (141-180) <lb/>Diastolic blood pressure, median (IQR), mmHg <lb/>86 (69-96) <lb/>80 (73-98) <lb/>89 (78-102.3) <lb/>65 (57.5-76.5) <lb/>0.11 <lb/>85 (72-98) <lb/>Heart rate, median (IQR), min -1 <lb/>81 (70-98) <lb/>78 (69.8-89.8) <lb/>82.5 (70.5-102.3) <lb/>77 (61-98) <lb/>0.75 <lb/>80 (70-97.8) <lb/>Treatment <lb/>Thrombolysis <lb/>Intravenous alteplase treatment, n (%) <lb/>26 (38.8) <lb/>15 (37.5) <lb/>9 (50) <lb/>2 (28.6) <lb/>0.64 <lb/>52 (39.4) <lb/>Intervention <lb/>Onset-to-puncture, median (IQR), min <lb/>235 (153-325) <lb/>230 (156-280) <lb/>257 (195-322) <lb/>291.5 (147.8-355.8) <lb/>0.82 <lb/>237 (165-316) <lb/>Angiographic occlusion location c <lb/>M1, n (%) <lb/>40 (59.7) <lb/>29 (72.5) <lb/>11 (61.1) <lb/>4 (57.1) <lb/>0.4 <lb/>84 (63.6) <lb/>M2, n (%) <lb/>22 (32.8) <lb/>3 (7.5) <lb/>3 (16.7) <lb/>3 (42.9) <lb/>0.008 <lb/>31 (23.5) <lb/>ICA, n (%) <lb/>8 (11.9) <lb/>10 (25) <lb/>4 (22.2) <lb/>0 (0) <lb/>0.2 <lb/>22 (16.7) <lb/>Puncture-to-first-pass, median (IQR), min <lb/>42.5 (30-51) <lb/>38.5 (29-57) <lb/>42 (29.5-53.8) <lb/>40.5 (35.8-58) <lb/>0.92 <lb/>41 (30-53.3) <lb/>Stent-retrieval manoeuvres, n (IQR) <lb/>1 (1-3) <lb/>2 (1-3) <lb/>1 (1-3.5) <lb/>2.5 (1-4) <lb/>0.49 <lb/>2 (1-3) <lb/>Successful recanalisation d , n (%) <lb/>58 (86.6) <lb/>34 (85) <lb/>14 (77.8) <lb/>6 (85.7) <lb/>0.65 <lb/>112 (84.9) <lb/>Duration of MT procedure, median (IQR), min <lb/>70 (52-104) <lb/>89 (62.8-138.3) <lb/>74 (53.5-119) <lb/>98 (56-154.8) <lb/>0.23 <lb/>75 (56-118) <lb/>Onset-to-final-recanalisation, median (IQR), min <lb/>307 (244-425) <lb/>325 (264.5-379.5) <lb/>319 (280-449) <lb/>419 (250-460) <lb/>0.74 <lb/>325 (251.5-408) <lb/>Sampling <lb/>Onset-to-cerebral sampling, median (IQR), min <lb/>274 (191-375) <lb/>285 (192.5-356) <lb/>303 (242-442) <lb/>243.5 (158.3-355) <lb/>0.79 <lb/>285 (198-367) <lb/>Onset-to-carotid sampling, median (IQR), min <lb/>319 (211-405) <lb/>342 (277.5-390) <lb/>338 (297-460) <lb/>366.5 (245.8-475.3) <lb/>0.78 <lb/>336 (263-405) <lb/>Outcome <lb/>mRS at discharge, median (IQR) <lb/>2 (1-5) <lb/>5 (3-5) <lb/>6 (5-6) <lb/>3 (1-5) <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>4 (1-5) <lb/>Death during hospital stay, n (%) <lb/>3 (4.5) <lb/>6 (15) <lb/>10 (55.6) <lb/>1 (14.3) <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>20 (15.2) <lb/>ASPECTS, Alberta Stroke Program Early CT Score; EVT, endovascular thrombectomy; HBC, Heidelberg Bleeding Classification; ICA, internal carotid artery; IQR, interquartile range; M1/M2, middle cerebral artery <lb/>segment; mmHg, millimetres of mercury; mRS, modified Rankin Scale; NIHSS, National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale; SD; standard deviation; y, years. a Intracranial haemorrhages were anatomically categorised <lb/>according to the Heidelberg Bleeding Classification (HBC: 1a, haemorrhagic infarction (HI1)-scattered small petechiae; 1b, HI2-confluent petechiae; 1c, parenchymal haematoma (PH1)-haematoma within infarcted <lb/>tissue, occupying &lt;30%; 2, PH2-haematoma occupying ≥30% of the infarcted tissue; 3a-PH remote from infarcted brain tissue; 3b-intraventricular haemorrhage; 3c-subarachnoid haemorrhage; 3d-subdural <lb/>haemorrhage) and grouped with respect to the type of bleeding (HBC classes 1a + b, minor [petechial] intracerebral haemorrhage; HBC classes 1c-3a, major intracerebral haemorrhage [parenchymal haematoma]; HBC <lb/>classes 3b-d, intracranial-extracerebral haemorrhage). b The p values for binary variables are based on χ 2 test (data for analysis included the following groups: absent, HBC1a + b, and HBC1c-3a). The p values of all <lb/>other variables are based on Kruskal-Wallis test or one-way ANOVA, as appropriate. c Including multiple sites in the target downstream territory. d Defined as eTICI ≥ 2b50. <lb/>Table 1: Patient characteristics by occurrence and type of intracranial bleeding event after EVT. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 103 May, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>Fig. 2: Regional MMP-9 plasma concentrations, neutrophil MMP-9 expression, and MMP activity with plasma concentrations stratified <lb/>by type of intracranial bleeding and functional outcome category. Semi-log plots of MMP-9 plasma concentrations (a, d, and e), fluo-<lb/>rescence intensity of neutrophils stained for MMP-9 (b; presented with examples at single-cell level, scale bar in white = 10 μm), and gelatine <lb/>zymography experiments (c) in arterial non-occlusive control samples at cervical level of the internal carotid artery (systemic) vs samples from <lb/>centrally within the cerebral collateral circulation (ischaemic) in human large-vessel ischaemic stroke. Zymography bands (c) were obtained from <lb/>n = 10 pooled plasma samples. Zymographic intensity of 86 kDa MMP-9 and 72 kDa MMP-2, respectively. Intracranial bleedings (d) were <lb/>anatomically categorized according to the Heidelberg Bleeding Classification (HBC: 1a, haemorrhagic infarction (HI1)-scattered small petechiae; <lb/>1b, HI2-confluent petechiae; 1c, parenchymal haematoma (PH1)-haematoma within infarcted tissue, occupying &lt;30%; 2, PH2-haematoma <lb/>occupying ≥30% of the infarcted tissue; 3a-PH remote from infarcted brain tissue; 3b-intraventricular haemorrhage; 3c-subarachnoid <lb/>haemorrhage; 3d-subdural haemorrhage) and grouped with respect to the type of bleeding (HBC classes 1a + b, minor [petechial] intracerebral <lb/>haemorrhage; HBC classes 1c-3a, major intracerebral haemorrhage [parenchymal haematoma]; HBC classes 3b-d, intracranial-extracerebral <lb/>haemorrhage). Functional outcome (e) was assessed by the modified Rankin Scale (mRS: mRS≥5, severe disability or death at hospital <lb/>discharge). The long horizontal bar shows the median value, and the short error bar shows the interquartile range. Data were analysed using <lb/>Wilcoxon matched-pairs signed rank test (a, b, d, and e), Kruskal-Wallis test with Benjamini, Krieger and Yekutieli post hoc analysis (d), and <lb/>Mann-Whitney test (e). Individual p values are given for p &lt; 0.05. CTCF, corrected total cellular fluorescence; HBC, Heidelberg Bleeding <lb/>Classification; kDa, kilo Dalton; MMP-9/-2, Matrix Metalloproteinase-9/2; mRS, modified Rankin Scale; ng/ml, nanograms per millilitre; ns, not <lb/>significant. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 103 May, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<body>evidence of any sex-specific differences in systemic or <lb/>ischaemic MMP-9 and MMP-2 concentrations <lb/>(Figure S6). <lb/>In multivariable-adjusted logistic regression analysis, <lb/>local MMP-9 concentrations, baseline antiplatelet <lb/>medication, baseline NIHSS, and baseline ASPECTS <lb/>were predictive of HBC classes 1c, 2, and 3a haemor-<lb/>rhages (overall model fit: Nagelkerke R 2 = 0.32, -2 log <lb/>likelihood ratio χ 2 test p = 0.0004; AUC = 0.84 [95% CI <lb/>0.76-0.9]; Table 2; univariate data given in Table S2). <lb/>Using the same model, MMP-9 concentrations within <lb/>collateral blood vessels, systolic blood pressure at <lb/>admission, baseline NIHSS, baseline ASPECTS, and <lb/>non-successful reperfusion were associated with early <lb/>poor neurological outcome following EVT (overall <lb/>model fit: Nagelkerke R 2 = 0.35, -2 log likelihood ratio <lb/>χ 2 test p &lt; 0.0001; AUC = 0.8 [95% CI 0.71-0.87]; <lb/>Table 2). MMP-9 concentrations in collateral blood <lb/>vessels yielded a significantly larger AUC than the sys-<lb/>temic values to discriminate between occurrence or non-<lb/>occurrence of both major intracerebral haemorrhages <lb/>(AUC = 0.57 [95% CI 0.42-0.72]; AUC = 0.67 [95% CI <lb/>0.53-0.82]; ΔAUC = 0.1 [95% CI 0.0035-0.2], DeLong <lb/>test p = 0.042; Fig. 3a), and severe disability or death <lb/>(AUC = 0.6 [95% CI 0.5-0.69]; AUC = 0.65 [95% CI <lb/>0.56-0.74]; ΔAUC = 0.056 [95% CI 0.0018-0.11], <lb/>DeLong test p = 0.045; Fig. 3b). Accordingly, paren-<lb/>chymal haematomas were indicated with 72.2% sensi-<lb/>tivity and 66.7% specificity (PPV 25.5%; NPV 93.8%) at <lb/>a cut-off value (Youden J index) of 552.9 ng/ml <lb/>(p = 0.018), and mRS scores of 5-6 were indicated with <lb/>75.9% sensitivity and 54.1% specificity (PPV 56.4%; <lb/>NPV 74.1%) at a cut-off value of 363.3 ng/ml <lb/>(p = 0.0028). A comprehensive set fixed-level estimates <lb/>of test accuracy measures including sensitivity, speci-<lb/>ficity, PPV, and NPV derived from MMP-9 ROC ana-<lb/>lyses is given in Table 3. Excessive local MMP-9 release <lb/>predicted space-occupying parenchymal haematomas as <lb/>well as severe disability or death with 99% specificity <lb/>(HBC1c-3a: PPV of 72.5% for 2928 ng/ml; mRS ≥5: <lb/>PPV of 84.4% for 2826.9 ng/ml). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Our most important finding is that MMP-9 but not <lb/>MMP-2 was strongly increased within the collateral <lb/>circulation during large-vessel ischaemic stroke. More-<lb/>over, we show that the extent of MMP-9 release into <lb/>collateral blood vessels reflected the degree of intrace-<lb/>rebral haemorrhages and clinical stroke severity after <lb/>recanalisation, and independently predicted poorest <lb/>outcome of either endpoint. These data provide the <lb/>proof-of-concept for the potential prognostic utility of an <lb/>ultra-early local biomarker before the final decision of <lb/>recanalisation by EVT is made. <lb/>The most likely explanation for these findings lies in <lb/>the fact that cerebral ischaemia, both in clinical and <lb/>experimental context, elicits an immediate intravascular <lb/>inflammatory response, which is dominated by neutro-<lb/>phils, 18,20 and known to contribute to infarct progression <lb/>under vascular occlusion, as well as during ischaemia/ <lb/>reperfusion injury. 6,39 Recently, high quantities of the <lb/>platelet-derived neutrophil-activating chemokine CXC <lb/>motif ligand (CXCL) 4, and the neutrophil attractant <lb/>CXCL7 have been detected in human pial blood. 40 <lb/>Therefore, our current findings support a sequence of <lb/>intravascular events by which platelet activation and <lb/>alpha-granule release drives neutrophil degranulation <lb/>and release of MMP-9 with ensuing disturbance of the <lb/>BBB. 11,12,20 These inflammatory processes may perpet-<lb/>uate into the recanalisation phase, thereby explaining <lb/>the potential prognostic utility of ultra-early local MMP-<lb/>9 concentrations. This may have multiple implications <lb/>for research in acute ischaemic stroke. <lb/>For decades, researchers have aimed for diagnosis, <lb/>etiological differentiation, and prognostication of stroke <lb/>HBC class 1c-3a <lb/>mRS ≥5 <lb/>Predictor variable a <lb/>Coefficient SE <lb/>Odds ratio b 95% CI <lb/>p value Predictor variable a <lb/>Coefficient SE <lb/>Odds ratio c 95% CI <lb/>p value <lb/>Constant <lb/>-2.52 <lb/>1.62 NA <lb/>NA <lb/>0.12 <lb/>Constant <lb/>-3.63 <lb/>2.1 <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>0.083 <lb/>MMP-9 ischaemic <lb/>0.43 <lb/>0.18 1.54 <lb/>1.073-2.2 <lb/>0.019 <lb/>MMP-9 ischaemic <lb/>0.85 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>2.33 <lb/>1.068-5.1 <lb/>0.034 <lb/>Baseline NIHSS score <lb/>0.14 <lb/>0.048 1.15 <lb/>1.045-1.26 <lb/>0.0042 Baseline NIHSS score <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.038 1.11 <lb/>1.028-1.19 <lb/>0.0072 <lb/>Baseline ASPECTS <lb/>-0.37 <lb/>0.19 0.69 <lb/>0.47-1.0065 0.054 <lb/>Baseline ASPECTS <lb/>-0.27 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>0.77 <lb/>0.58-1.015 <lb/>0.064 <lb/>Baseline antiplatelet treatment 1.32 <lb/>0.68 3.76 <lb/>1.0024-14.13 0.049 <lb/>Systolic blood pressure at <lb/>admission <lb/>0.019 <lb/>0.0083 1.019 <lb/>1.0028-1.036 0.022 <lb/>No reperfusion <lb/>1.75 <lb/>0.63 <lb/>5.75 <lb/>1.66-19.86 <lb/>0.0058 <lb/>Abbreviations: ASPECTS, Alberta Stroke Program Early CT Score; AUC, area under curve; CI, Confidence interval; HBC, Heidelberg Bleeding Classification; MMP-9, Matrix Metalloproteinase-9; mmHg, <lb/>millimetres of mercury; mRS, modified Rankin Scale; ng/ml, nanograms per millilitre; NIHSS, National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale; NA, not applicable; SE, standard error. a Odds ratios for continuous <lb/>variables are reported per unit of increment: MMP-9 ischaemic [1000 ng/ml]; baseline NIHSS score [1-point NIHSS score increase]; baseline ASPECTS [1-point ASPECTS decrease]; systolic blood pressure at <lb/>admission [1 mmHg]. b Data represent adjusted odds ratios with 95% CI for major intracerebral bleeding events equivalent to the combined Heidelberg Bleeding Classification (HBC) classes 1c, 2, and 3a <lb/>(categorisation corresponding to Table 1). Overall model fit: Nagelkerke R 2 = 0.32, -2 log likelihood ratio χ 2 test p = 0.0004; AUC = 0.84 [95% CI 0.76-0.9]. c Data represent adjusted odds ratios with 95% <lb/>CI for severe disability or death as defined by a modified Rankin Scale (mRS) ≥5 at hospital discharge. Overall model fit: Nagelkerke R 2 = 0.35, -2 log likelihood ratio χ 2 test p &lt; 0.0001; AUC = 0.8 [95% CI <lb/>0.71-0.87]. <lb/>Table 2: Multivariable logistic regression model of predictors of major intracerebral haemorrhages and severe disability or death. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 103 May, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>gleaned from blood-based biomarkers which are typi-<lb/>cally measured in venous samples and often lack tem-<lb/>poral, spatial, or functional relevance in ischaemia-<lb/>induced structural brain damage. 11,12,41 Nowadays, as <lb/>evidence for streamlined decision-making for EVT <lb/>based on widely available non-invasive imaging tech-<lb/>niques grows, 3-5,42 it is reasonable to assume that the <lb/>near-future use of blood-based biomarkers in the setting <lb/>of large-vessel occlusion may serve the identification of <lb/>patients which will likely benefit from timely <lb/>adjustment of endovascular treatment or medical care <lb/>thereafter. 9,10 Hence, the conceptually new approach of <lb/>ultra-early local biomarkers prior to EVT appears <lb/>promising to realise a more tailored stroke care. 21 When <lb/>choosing biomarker candidates, MMPs inherently <lb/>possess prognostic value as their production is tempo-<lb/>rally limited, spatially confined through specific regula-<lb/>tion at transcriptional level, and causative for a <lb/>deleterious pathophysiological phenotype. 11,13,43 <lb/>However, available literature on the prognostic signif-<lb/>icance of MMPs in human stroke is inconsistent. A pro-<lb/>spective single-centre study of 255 patients with stroke <lb/>recruited within 48 h of symptom onset found no <lb/>association of venous MMP-9 concentrations with either <lb/>haemorrhagic transformation or functional outcome at <lb/>three months. 16 Several explanations addressing these <lb/>discrepancies might be discussed. First, we utilised a <lb/>microcatheter-based technique for direct probing from <lb/>within the centre of an occluded cerebral vascular territory <lb/>which previously revealed that non-local sample material <lb/>does not accurately reflect absolute concentrations, cellular <lb/>composition, or the degree of activation of blood compo-<lb/>nents in the ischaemic brain region. 18,19,44,45 Second, local <lb/>sample material was obtained within a median time in-<lb/>terval of 4 h and 45 min after symptom onset, which is <lb/>expected to have a beneficial effect on temporal homoge-<lb/>neity in that an early peak of MMP-9 expression may not <lb/>have been missed. 11,15,17 Third, a set of strict protocol re-<lb/>quirements were in place to avoid observational biases <lb/>which might result from efforts not requiring, e.g., <lb/>mandatory vascular imaging or uniform methods to <lb/>obtain representative sample material of a sufficiently <lb/>narrow defined target patient population. 18,19 Fourth, <lb/>outcome variables were chosen to reflect a relevant pro-<lb/>portion of patients who are in greater need and capacity <lb/>for optimisation of treatment at the same time. 9,16 <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>Fig. 3: ROC analysis of MMP-9 plasma concentrations for discrimination between patients at low and high risk of major intracerebral <lb/>haemorrhages, and severe disability or death. ROC curves of regional ischaemic (blue) and systemic (red) MMP-9 plasma concentrations in <lb/>prediction of HBC1c-3a bleedings (a), and mRS ≥5 at hospital discharge (b) in large-vessel ischaemic stroke; categorisation corresponding to <lb/>Fig. 2. Green dots represent values of maximised balances between sensitivity and specificity. Reported p values for the differences in AUCs were <lb/>derived from DeLong&apos;s test. Youden index, HBC1c-3a: MMP-9 ischaemic 552.9 ng/ml, 72.2% sensitivity (95% CI 46.5-90.3%), 66.7% specificity <lb/>(95% CI 57.2-75.2%); MMP-9 systemic 448.9 ng/ml, 55.6% sensitivity (95% CI 30.8-78.5%), 68.4% specificity (95% CI 59.1-76.8%); Youden index, <lb/>mRS ≥5: MMP-9 ischaemic 363.3 ng/ml, 75.9% sensitivity (95% CI 62.8-86.1%), 54.1% specificity (95% CI 42.1-65.7%); MMP-9 systemic 235.5 ng/ <lb/>ml, 70.7% sensitivity (95% CI 57.3-81.9), 51.4% specificity (95% CI 39.4-63.1). AUC, area under curve; HBC, Heidelberg Bleeding Classification; <lb/>MMP-9, Matrix Metalloproteinase-9; ng/ml, nanograms per millilitre; mRS, modified Rankin Scale; ROC, receiver operating characteristic. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 103 May, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<body>HBC class 1c-3a <lb/>mRS ≥5 <lb/>Sensitivity (%) Specificity (%) 95% CI PPV (%) 95% CI NPV (%) 95% CI MMP-9 ischaemic [ng/ml] Sensitivity (%) Specificity (%) 95% CI PPV (%) 95% CI NPV (%) 95% CI MMP-9 ischaemic [ng/ml] <lb/>80 <lb/>52.6 <lb/>4.4-73.9 21.1 <lb/>16.5-26.5 94.3 <lb/>86.7-97.7 &gt;405.1 <lb/>80 <lb/>41.9 <lb/>21.6-60.8 51.9 <lb/>46.1-57.7 72.8 <lb/>59.9-82.7 &gt;284.7 <lb/>90 <lb/>6.1 <lb/>0.9-52.6 13.2 <lb/>11.4-15.1 79.5 <lb/>45-94.9 &gt;85.6 <lb/>90 <lb/>31.1 <lb/>0-54.2 <lb/>50.6 <lb/>46.2-55 79.9 <lb/>63.1-90.2 &gt;207.4 <lb/>95 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>0.9-1.8 13.1 <lb/>12-14.4 52.7 <lb/>6.3-94.8 &gt;3 <lb/>95 <lb/>0 <lb/>0-14.9 <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>&gt;9.3 <lb/>97.5 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>0.9-1.8 13.4 <lb/>12.6-14.4 69 <lb/>6.4-98.6 &gt;2.5 <lb/>97.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0-17.6 <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>&gt;2.5 <lb/>99 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>0.9-1.8 13.6 <lb/>13.1-14.2 84.8 <lb/>3.7-99.9 &gt;2.2 <lb/>99 <lb/>0 <lb/>0-8.1 <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>&gt;2 <lb/>Specificity (%) Sensitivity (%) <lb/>Specificity (%) Sensitivity (%) <lb/>80 <lb/>38.9 <lb/>11.1-66.7 23.5 <lb/>13.4-37.9 89.2 <lb/>85-92.4 &gt;776.3 <lb/>80 <lb/>27.6 <lb/>12.1-44.8 52 <lb/>36.8-66.7 58.5 <lb/>53.7-63.2 &gt;768.1 <lb/>90 <lb/>27.8 <lb/>11.1-50 30.5 <lb/>14.8-52.6 88.8 <lb/>85.5-91.4 &gt;1246.4 <lb/>90 <lb/>20.7 <lb/>8.6-32.8 61.7 <lb/>41-79.1 59.2 <lb/>55.4-62.8 &gt;1064.5 <lb/>95 <lb/>27.8 <lb/>11.1-61.1 46.7 <lb/>22.7-72.4 89.3 <lb/>86.2-91.8 &gt;1496.9 <lb/>95 <lb/>15.5 <lb/>5.2-27.6 70.9 <lb/>43.3-88.6 58.9 <lb/>55.9-61.9 &gt;1345.7 <lb/>97.5 <lb/>16.7 <lb/>0-0 <lb/>51.3 <lb/>18.4-83.1 88.1 <lb/>85.7-90.1 &gt;2682.8 <lb/>97.5 <lb/>10.3 <lb/>0-0 <lb/>76.4 <lb/>39.3-942 58.1 <lb/>55.8-60.4 &gt;2274 <lb/>99 <lb/>16.7 <lb/>0-0 <lb/>72.5 <lb/>24.4-95.6 88.3 <lb/>85.9-90.3 &gt;2928 <lb/>99 <lb/>6.9 <lb/>0-0 <lb/>84.4 <lb/>31.7-98.4 57.6 <lb/>55.8-59.4 &gt;2826.9 <lb/>Sensitivity (%) Specificity (%) 95% CI PPV (%) 95% CI NPV (%) 95% CI MMP-9 systemic [ng/ml] Sensitivity (%) Specificity (%) 95% CI PPV (%) 95% CI NPV (%) 95% CI MMP-9 systemic [ng/ml] <lb/>80 <lb/>20.2 <lb/>7-36 <lb/>13.7 <lb/>11-16.9 86.5 <lb/>70.3-94.5 &gt;102.6 <lb/>80 <lb/>36.5 <lb/>16.3-50 49.7 <lb/>44.3-55.1 67 <lb/>56.2-80.9 &gt;168.3 <lb/>90 <lb/>13.2 <lb/>4.4-20.2 14.1 <lb/>12.1-16.2 89.3 <lb/>65.9-97.3 &gt;76.3 <lb/>90 <lb/>17.6 <lb/>0-36.5 <lb/>46.1 <lb/>42.8-49.5 69.2 <lb/>47.3-84.9 &gt;83.5 <lb/>95 <lb/>0 <lb/>4.4-4.4 NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>&gt;0.7 <lb/>95 <lb/>5.4 <lb/>0-20.3 <lb/>44.1 <lb/>42.1-46 58 <lb/>24.1-85.7 &gt;22.2 <lb/>97.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>36-36 <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>&gt;0.7 <lb/>97.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0-5.4 <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>&gt;4.1 <lb/>99 <lb/>0 <lb/>4.4-4.4 NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>&gt;0.7 <lb/>99 <lb/>0 <lb/>0-0 <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>&gt;0.7 <lb/>Specificity (%) Sensitivity (%) <lb/>Specificity (%) Sensitivity (%) <lb/>80 <lb/>27.8 <lb/>11.1-55.6 18 <lb/>8.7-33.5 87.5 <lb/>83.9-90.5 &gt;634.3 <lb/>80 <lb/>22.4 <lb/>12.1-41.4 46.8 <lb/>31.2-63 56.8 <lb/>52.4-61.1 &gt;634.3 <lb/>90 <lb/>16.7 <lb/>0-33.3 <lb/>20.8 <lb/>7.6-45.9 87.3 <lb/>84.7-89.5 &gt;1122.1 <lb/>90 <lb/>19 <lb/>10.3-32.8 59.8 <lb/>38.5-78 58.6 <lb/>55.1-62.1 &gt;929.8 <lb/>95 <lb/>11.1 <lb/>0-45.6 26 <lb/>7.1-61.9 87.1 <lb/>85.1-88.9 &gt;1763.4 <lb/>95 <lb/>12.1 <lb/>5.2-27 <lb/>65.4 <lb/>36-86.4 58 <lb/>55.3-60.6 &gt;1363.9 <lb/>97.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0-0 <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>&gt;3034.2 <lb/>97.5 <lb/>6.9 <lb/>0-0 <lb/>68.4 <lb/>28.2-92.3 57.2 <lb/>55.3-59.1 &gt;2444.4 <lb/>99 <lb/>0 <lb/>0-0 <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>&gt;3289.7 <lb/>99 <lb/>1.7 <lb/>0-0 <lb/>44.1 <lb/>43.1-45.1 68.7 <lb/>9.1-98 <lb/>&gt;3251.9 <lb/>Major intracerebral haemorrhages (combined Heidelberg Bleeding Classification [HBC] classes 1c, 2, and 3a), as per Table 1 categorisation. Functional outcome as assessed by the modified Rankin Scale at hospital discharge (mRS: mRS ≥5, severe <lb/>disability or death). CI, Confidence interval; HBC, Heidelberg Bleeding Classification; MMP-9, Matrix Metalloproteinase-9; mRS, modified Rankin Scale; ng/ml, nanograms per millilitre; NPV, negative predictive value; NA, not applicable; PPV, positive <lb/>predictive value. <lb/>Table 3: Fixed-level estimates of diagnostic test accuracy measures for MMP-9 cut-off concentrations in prediction of major intracerebral haemorrhages and severe disability or death. <lb/></body>

            <note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 103 May, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>Other studies utilising peripheral blood samples <lb/>have reported an association between MMP-9 concen-<lb/>trations and prognosis of stroke. 14,15,17 Two prospective <lb/>studies strongly suggested that MMP-9 levels in sample <lb/>material obtained within 3 h of stroke onset predict the <lb/>occurrence of space-occupying parenchymal haemato-<lb/>mas after alteplase treatment. 15,17 Consistently, a dose-<lb/>response association of MMP-9 concentrations and <lb/>major disability or death at 3 months was reported for <lb/>samples obtained within 24 h of hospital admission. 14 <lb/>At present, uncertainty exists concerning the cellular <lb/>origin of MMPs, and the time point at which they exert <lb/>their effect. Our study now permitted the testing of <lb/>previously inaccessible sample material, revealing that <lb/>MMP-9 was locally cleaved into its active form during <lb/>vascular occlusion. 13 Using direct immunofluorescence <lb/>microscopy, we identified invading neutrophils as <lb/>intravascular source of MMP-9 (+35.2% expression). <lb/>Our data accord with experimental findings indicating <lb/>that leukocytes recruited to the brain serve as a signifi-<lb/>cant cellular source of MMP-9 following transient focal <lb/>stroke, 46 and are further supported through analyses of <lb/>human ex-vivo specimens revealing that MMP-9-<lb/>positive neutrophil infiltration surrounding the brain <lb/>microvasculature is related to BBB breakdown. 43 It has <lb/>been shown that circulating neutrophils from patients <lb/>treated with alteplase release more MMP-9 after ex-vivo <lb/>stimulation, 16 and that alteplase enters the collateral <lb/>circulation in-vivo. 35 Together, these findings challenge <lb/>the concept that mainly brain-derived MMP-9 is <lb/>involved in massive BBB opening and drive attention to <lb/>regional neutrophil heterogeneity, and an early mode of <lb/>action from the luminal side of the occluded vascular <lb/>territory. 11,20 <lb/>Analyses by multivariable logistic regression revealed <lb/>that regional MMP-9 release prior to EVT independently <lb/>increased the odds of parenchymal haematomas by 1.54 <lb/>times, and the odds of severe disability or death by 2.33 <lb/>times per 1000 ng/ml increase, respectively. Consis-<lb/>tently, AUC values indicated no effective discriminatory <lb/>ability for systemic MMP-9 concentrations in identifying <lb/>at-risk patients (parenchymal haematomas: AUC = 0.57; <lb/>severe disability or death: AUC = 0.6) who showed non-<lb/>distinct demographic, clinical, or treatment-related fea-<lb/>tures, while ischaemic MMP-9 concentrations achieved <lb/>a significantly higher, albeit moderate, AUC for <lb/>outcome prognostication across all thresholds (paren-<lb/>chymal haematomas: AUC = 0.67; severe disability or <lb/>death: AUC = 0.65). ROC analyses were further con-<lb/>ducted to provide a more detailed evaluation of predic-<lb/>tive thresholds at various MMP-9 concentration levels. <lb/>Due to the lack of comparability with previously pub-<lb/>lished data on MMP-9 concentrations, we employed the <lb/>Youden J index to derive potential data-driven cut-off <lb/>concentrations, which, however, may result in overly <lb/>optimistic estimates of sensitivity and specificity. 47 <lb/>While this approach yielded lower sensitivity and spec-<lb/>ificity than expected, it also prioritised a balance be-<lb/>tween these test measures, potentially neglecting <lb/>relevant clinical factors such as disease severity and the <lb/>implications of false results on patient management. 47 <lb/>Therefore, we additionally assessed a range of fixed-<lb/>level estimates of test accuracy measures, ranging <lb/>from 80% to 99% sensitivity and specificity, respectively. <lb/>These analyses aimed to identify candidate diagnostic <lb/>target concentrations for clinical decision-making, <lb/>indicating that excessive release occurring in a partic-<lb/>ular group of patients is specific to deleterious outcome. <lb/>The major strength of the study is its standardised <lb/>and biologically plausible approach which resulted in <lb/>the definition of a local blood-based biomarker to iden-<lb/>tify the clinically most relevant high-risk groups among <lb/>EVT candidates. However, our study is limited by its <lb/>single-centre design reflecting in-house interventional <lb/>and intensive care standards, and the small number of <lb/>patients who developed space-occupying parenchymal <lb/>haematomas after EVT. Thus, our findings will require <lb/>verification in a larger multi-centre population to in-<lb/>crease generalizability. Furthermore, the measured <lb/>plasma concentrations and immunofluorescence in-<lb/>tensity of MMP-9 do not necessarily indicate activated <lb/>MMP-9. Nevertheless, zymography experiments pro-<lb/>vided evidence for the locally confined proteolytic ac-<lb/>tivity of MMP-9. Finally, we recruited patients in whom <lb/>aspiration of cerebral liquid biopsies succeeded, mean-<lb/>ing that we did not have access to outcome prognosti-<lb/>cation in patients in whom aspiration was attempted but <lb/>failed. <lb/>In conclusion, this study posits MMP-9 concentra-<lb/>tions within collateral blood vessels as local biomarker to <lb/>identify patients at high risk for space-occupying <lb/>parenchymal haematomas and severe disability or <lb/>death before therapeutic recanalisation by EVT is ach-<lb/>ieved. Hence, we hypothesise that the use of point-of-<lb/>care assays for sample material from the collateral <lb/>circulation might be an effective addition to future trial <lb/>designs of EVT to address, e.g., the extensiveness of <lb/>endovascular treatment, adjunct MMP inhibition, con-<lb/>cepts of blood pressure management, and different an-<lb/>tiplatelet, and/or antiinflammatory regimens in <lb/>herewith identified groups of interest. <lb/></body>

            <div type="contribution">Contributors <lb/>Conceptualization: AMK, MP, GS, and MKS; Data Curation: AMK, <lb/>AGM, JF, MLV, MS, CV, FE, LZ, and MKS; Formal Analysis: AMK and <lb/>MKS; Funding Acquisition: AMK, MP, CV, FE, HN, GS, and MKS; <lb/>Investigation: AMK, MP, AGM, JF, MLV, YX, MS, CV, FE, HN, LZ, and <lb/>MKS; Methodology: AMK, MP, and MKS; Project Administration: AMK <lb/>and MKS; Resources: AMK, MP, GS, and MKS; Software: AMK and <lb/>AGM; Supervision: AMK and MKS; Visualization: AMK and MKS; <lb/>Writing-original draft: AMK; Writing-review and editing: AMK, MP, <lb/>AGM, HN, KGH, CH, LZ, GS, and MKS. AMK and MKS have directly <lb/>accessed and verified the underlying data reported in the manuscript. <lb/>All authors confirm that they read and approved the final version of the <lb/>manuscript. <lb/></div>

            <note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 103 May, 2024 <lb/></note>

            <div type="availability">Data sharing statement <lb/>Data collected for the study and data from sample analyses will be made <lb/>available upon reasonable request to the corresponding authors. <lb/></div>

            <div type="conflict">Declaration of interests <lb/>MP has received speaker honoraria from Bayer and Merck Serono; <lb/>unrelated to the present study. KGH has received honoraria for acting as <lb/>an advisor/speaker for Boehringer Ingelheim; unrelated to the present <lb/>study. MKS declares a grant from CSL Behring, funding from the <lb/>German Research Foundation (Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft, <lb/>DFG) project No. 424778381-CRC/TR 295, and is a co-holder of patent <lb/>PCT/EP2020/068464; all unrelated to the present study. All other au-<lb/>thors have nothing to disclose. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>This study was funded by the German Research Foundation (Deutsche <lb/>Forschungsgemeinschaft, DFG) project No. 374031971-CRC/TR 240 <lb/>(MP, HN, GS, and MKS; Gerok position held by AMK), DFG project No. <lb/>413657723-Clinician Scientist programme UNION CVD (AMK, CV, <lb/>and FE), and the Interdisciplinary Centre for Clinical Research (IZKF) at <lb/>the University of Würzburg project No. T-516 (AMK and MKS). We <lb/>thank Julian Kunz and all neurointerventionalists, and radiology tech-<lb/>nicians of the Department of Neuroradiology for their support in data <lb/>acquisition and patient handling. We also thank the CSF-laboratory <lb/>team of the Department of Neurology for excellent technical support. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Appendix A. Supplementary data <lb/>Supplementary data related to this article can be found at https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.ebiom.2024.105095. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1 Goyal M, Menon BK, van Zwam WH, et al. Endovascular throm-<lb/>bectomy after large-vessel ischaemic stroke: a meta-analysis of in-<lb/>dividual patient data from five randomised trials. Lancet. <lb/>2016;387:1723-1731. <lb/>2 Jovin TG, Nogueira RG, Lansberg MG, et al. Thrombectomy for <lb/>anterior circulation stroke beyond 6 h from time last known well <lb/>(AURORA): a systematic review and individual patient data meta-<lb/>analysis. Lancet. 2022;399:249-258. <lb/>3 Sarraj A, Hassan AE, Abraham MG, et al. Trial of endovascular <lb/>thrombectomy for large ischemic strokes. N Engl J Med. <lb/>2023;388:1259-1271. <lb/>4 Huo X, Ma G, Tong X, et al. Trial of endovascular therapy for acute <lb/>ischemic stroke with large infarct. N Engl J Med. 2023;388:1272-<lb/>1283. <lb/>5 Bendszus M, Fiehler J, Subtil F, et al. Endovascular thrombectomy <lb/>for acute ischaemic stroke with established large infarct: multi-<lb/>centre, open-label, randomised trial. Lancet. 2023;402:1753-1763. <lb/>6 Stoll G, Pham M. Beyond recanalization -a call for action in acute <lb/>stroke. Nat Rev Neurol. 2020;16:591-592. <lb/>7 van Kranendonk KR, Treurniet KM, Boers AMM, et al. Hemor-<lb/>rhagic transformation is associated with poor functional outcome <lb/>in patients with acute ischemic stroke due to a large vessel occlu-<lb/>sion. J Neurointerv Surg. 2019;11:464-468. <lb/>8 Ospel JM, Qiu W, Menon BK, et al. Radiologic patterns of intra-<lb/>cranial hemorrhage and clinical outcome after endovascular treat-<lb/>ment in acute ischemic stroke: results from the ESCAPE-NA1 trial. <lb/>Radiology. 2021;300:402-409. <lb/>9 Powers WJ, Rabinstein AA, Ackerson T, et al. Guidelines for the <lb/>early management of patients with acute ischemic stroke: 2019 <lb/>update to the 2018 guidelines for the early management of acute <lb/>ischemic stroke: a guideline for healthcare professionals from the <lb/>American <lb/>heart <lb/>association/American <lb/>stroke. <lb/>Stroke. <lb/>2019;50:E344-E418. <lb/>10 Mazighi M, Richard S, Lapergue B, et al. Safety and efficacy of <lb/>intensive blood pressure lowering after successful endovascular <lb/>therapy in acute ischaemic stroke (BP-TARGET): a multicentre, <lb/>open-label, randomised controlled trial. Lancet Neurol. 2021;20:265-<lb/>274. <lb/>11 Jickling GC, Liu D, Stamova B, et al. Hemorrhagic transformation <lb/>after ischemic stroke in animals and humans. J Cereb Blood Flow <lb/>Metab. 2014;34:185-199. <lb/>12 Obermeier B, Daneman R, Ransohoff RM. Development, mainte-<lb/>nance and disruption of the blood-brain barrier. Nat Med. <lb/>2013;19:1584-1596. <lb/>13 Ra H-J, Parks WC. Control of matrix metalloproteinase catalytic <lb/>activity. Matrix Biol. 2007;26:587-596. <lb/>14 Zhong C, Yang J, Xu T, et al. Serum matrix metalloproteinase-9 <lb/>levels and prognosis of acute ischemic stroke. Neurology. <lb/>2017;89:805-812. <lb/>15 Montaner J, Molina CA, Monasterio J, et al. Matrix <lb/>metalloproteinase-9 pretreatment level predicts intracranial hem-<lb/>orrhagic complications after thrombolysis in human stroke. Cir-<lb/>culation. 2003;107:598-603. <lb/>16 Maestrini I, Tagzirt M, Gautier S, et al. Analysis of the association <lb/>of MPO and MMP-9 with stroke severity and outcome: cohort <lb/>study. Neurology. 2020;95:e97-e108. <lb/>17 Castellanos M, Sobrino T, Millán M, et al. Serum cellular fibro-<lb/>nectin and matrix metalloproteinase-9 as screening biomarkers for <lb/>the prediction of parenchymal hematoma after thrombolytic ther-<lb/>apy in acute ischemic stroke: a multicenter confirmatory study. <lb/>Stroke. 2007;38:1855-1859. <lb/>18 Kollikowski AM, Schuhmann MK, Nieswandt B, Müllges W, <lb/>Stoll G, Pham M. Local leukocyte invasion during hyperacute hu-<lb/>man ischemic stroke. Ann Neurol. 2020;87:466-479. <lb/>19 Strinitz M, Pham M, März AG, et al. Immune cells invade the <lb/>collateral circulation during human stroke: prospective replication <lb/>and extension. Int J Mol Sci. 2021;22:9161. <lb/>20 Stoll G, Schuhmann MK, Nieswandt B, Kollikowski AM, Pham M. <lb/>An intravascular perspective on hyper-acute neutrophil, T-cell and <lb/>platelet responses: similarities between human and experimental <lb/>stroke. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab. 2022;42:1561-1567. <lb/>21 Dagonnier M, Donnan GA, Davis SM, Dewey HM, Howells DW. <lb/>Acute stroke biomarkers: are we there yet? Front Neurol. 2021;12: <lb/>619721. <lb/>22 Sommer CJ. Ischemic stroke: experimental models and reality. Acta <lb/>Neuropathol. 2017;133:245-261. <lb/>23 von Elm E, Altman DG, Egger M, et al. The strengthening the <lb/>reporting of observational studies in epidemiology (STROBE) <lb/>statement: guidelines for reporting observational studies. Lancet. <lb/>2007;370:1453-1457. <lb/>24 Schindelin J, Arganda-Carreras I, Frise E, et al. Fiji: an open-source <lb/>platform for biological-image analysis. Nat Methods. 2012;9:676-<lb/>682. <lb/>25 Ives A, Nomura J, Martinon F, et al. Xanthine oxidoreductase <lb/>regulates macrophage IL1β secretion upon NLRP3 inflammasome <lb/>activation. Nat Commun. 2015;6:6555. <lb/>26 Schuhmann MK, Bittner S, Meuth SG, Kleinschnitz C, Fluri F. <lb/>Fingolimod (FTY720-P) does not stabilize the blood-brain barrier <lb/>under inflammatory conditions in an in vitro model. Int J Mol Sci. <lb/>2015;16:29454-29466. <lb/>27 Kollikowski AM, Cattus F, Haag J, et al. Progression of cerebral <lb/>infarction before and after thrombectomy is modified by pre-<lb/>hospital pathways. J Neurointerv Surg. 2022;14:485-489. <lb/>28 Hacke W, Kaste M, Bluhmki E, et al. Thrombolysis with Alteplase 3 <lb/>to 4.5 hours after acute ischemic stroke. N Engl J Med. <lb/>2008;359:1317-1329. <lb/>29 von Kummer R, Broderick JP, Campbell BCV, et al. The Heidelberg <lb/>bleeding classification: classification of bleeding events after <lb/>ischemic stroke and reperfusion therapy. Stroke. 2015;46:2981-<lb/>2986. <lb/>30 Dekeyzer S, Nikoubashman O, Lutin B, et al. Distinction between <lb/>contrast staining and hemorrhage after endovascular stroke <lb/>treatment: one CT is not enough. J Neurointerv Surg. 2017;9:394-<lb/>398. <lb/>31 Mazya MV, Ahmed N, Ford GA, et al. Remote or extraischemic <lb/>intracerebral hemorrhage-an uncommon complication of stroke <lb/>thrombolysis: results from the safe implementation of treatments <lb/>in stroke-international stroke thrombolysis register. Stroke. <lb/>2014;45:1657-1663. <lb/>32 Ovbiagele B, Saver JL. Day-90 acute ischemic stroke outcomes can <lb/>be derived from early functional activity level. Cerebrovasc Dis. <lb/>2010;29:50-56. <lb/>33 D&apos;Agostino RB, Pearson ES. Tests for departure from normality. <lb/>Empirical results for the distributions of b2 and √b1. Biometrika. <lb/>1973;60:613-622. <lb/>34 Benjamini Y, Krieger AM, Yekutieli D. Adaptive linear step-up <lb/>procedures that control the false discovery rate. Biometrika. <lb/>2006;93:491-507. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 103 May, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>35 Essig F, Kollikowski AM, Müllges W, et al. Local cerebral recom-<lb/>binant tissue plasminogen activator concentrations during acute <lb/>stroke. JAMA Neurol. 2021;78:615-617. <lb/>36 Shrestha N. Detecting multicollinearity in regression analysis. Am J <lb/>Appl Math Stat. 2020;8:39-42. <lb/>37 May RB, Masson MEJ, Hunter MA. Application of statistics in <lb/>behavioral research. New Jork: Harper &amp; Row. 1990. <lb/>38 DeLong ER, DeLong DM, Clarke-Pearson DL. Comparing the areas <lb/>under two or more correlated receiver operating characteristic <lb/>curves: a nonparametric approach. Biometrics. 1988;44:837-845. <lb/>39 Schuhmann MK, Bieber M, Franke M, et al. Platelets and lym-<lb/>phocytes drive progressive penumbral tissue loss during middle <lb/>cerebral artery occlusion in mice. J Neuroinflammation. 2021;18:46. <lb/>40 Kollikowski AM, Pham M, März AG, et al. Platelet activation and <lb/>chemokine release are related to local neutrophil-dominant <lb/>inflammation during hyperacute human stroke. Transl Stroke Res. <lb/>2022;13:364-369. <lb/>41 Montellano FA, Ungethüm K, Ramiro L, et al. Role of blood-based <lb/>biomarkers in ischemic stroke prognosis: a systematic review. <lb/>Stroke. 2021;52:543-551. <lb/>42 Nguyen TN, Abdalkader M, Nagel S, et al. Noncontrast computed <lb/>tomography vs computed tomography perfusion or magnetic <lb/>resonance imaging selection in late presentation of stroke with <lb/>large-vessel occlusion. JAMA Neurol. 2022;79:22-31. <lb/>43 Rosell A, Cuadrado E, Ortega-Aznar A, Hernández-Guillamon M, <lb/>Lo EH, Montaner J. MMP-9-positive neutrophil infiltration is <lb/>associated to blood-brain barrier breakdown basal lamina type <lb/>IV collagen degradation during hemorrhagic transformation after <lb/>human ischemic stroke. Stroke. 2008;39:1121-1126. <lb/>44 Zimmermann L, Pham M, März AG, Kollikowski AM, Stoll G, <lb/>Schuhmann MK. Defining cerebral leukocyte populations in local <lb/>ischemic blood samples from patients with hyperacute stroke. <lb/>J Cereb Blood Flow Metab. 2022;42:901-904. <lb/>45 Feick J, Pham M, März AG, et al. Distinct alterations in oxygena-<lb/>tion, ion composition and acid-base balance in cerebral collaterals <lb/>during large-vessel occlusion stroke. Clin Neuroradiol. 2023;33:973-<lb/>984. <lb/>46 Gidday JM, Gasche YG, Copin J-C, et al. Leukocyte-derived matrix <lb/>metalloproteinase-9 mediates blood-brain barrier breakdown and is <lb/>proinflammatory after transient focal cerebral ischemia. Am J <lb/>Physiol Heart Circ Physiol. 2005;289:H558-H568. <lb/>47 Janssens ACJW, Martens FK. Reflection on modern methods: <lb/>revisiting the area under the ROC curve. Int J Epidemiol. 2020; <lb/>49:1397-1403. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Articles <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">www.thelancet.com Vol 103 May, 2024 </note>


	</text>
</tei>
