<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Acceptability and utility of, and preference for <lb/>wearable activity trackers amongst non-<lb/>metropolitan cancer survivors <lb/>Sarah J. Hardcastle ID <lb/>1,2 <lb/>*, Maddison Galliott 1 , Brigid M. Lynch 3 , Nga H. Nguyen 3 , Paul <lb/>A. CohenID 2,4 , Ganendra Raj Mohan 5 , Niloufer J. Johansen 5 , Christobel Saunders 2,5 <lb/>1 School of Psychology, Curtin University, Perth, WA, Australia, 2 School of Medicine, University of Western <lb/>Australia, Crawley, WA, Australia, 3 Cancer Council Victoria, Melbourne, VIC, Australia, 4 St John of God <lb/>Hospital, Subiaco, WA, Australia, 5 Hollywood Private Hospital, Nedlands, WA, Australia <lb/>* sarah.hardcastle@curtin.edu.au <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Purpose <lb/>The study purpose was to investigate the acceptability and utility of, and preference for, <lb/>wearable activity trackers (WATs) amongst cancer survivors living in regional and remote <lb/>areas of Western Australia. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Twenty participants were recruited (Mean age = 63 years, SD = 13) to test two to three track-<lb/>ers from five available models (Fitbit Alta, Garmin Vivofit 2, Garmin Vivosmart, Polar loop 2 <lb/>and Polar A300). Participants wore each device for two weeks, followed by a one-week <lb/>washout period between devices. Interviews were conducted with participants to explore <lb/>user perceptions and experiences. Interview transcripts were analysed using thematic <lb/>analysis. <lb/>Results <lb/>Four main themes emerged: (i) Consciousness raising; (ii) Prompts and Feedback; (iii) <lb/>Accuracy and registry of activities; and, (iv) WAT preferences and features. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>WATs were acceptable and useful to cancer survivors. WATs increased self-awareness of <lb/>physical activity, provided real time feedback in relation to step goals, and reinforced prog-<lb/>ress and efforts towards goals. The aesthetics of the WATs were deemed crucial in deter-<lb/>mining preference and likelihood of use. <lb/>Implications for cancer survivors <lb/>Future interventions may do well to have two different WATs available for participants to <lb/>choose from, according to activity preferences, aesthetic preferences, and display size. <lb/>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210039 December 31, 2018 <lb/>1 / 13 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Hardcastle SJ, Galliott M, Lynch BM, <lb/>Nguyen NH, Cohen PA, Mohan GR, et al. (2018) <lb/>Acceptability and utility of, and preference for <lb/>wearable activity trackers amongst non-<lb/>metropolitan cancer survivors. PLoS ONE 13(12): <lb/>e0210039. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0210039 <lb/>Editor: Barbara Schouten, Universiteit van <lb/>Amsterdam, NETHERLANDS <lb/>Received: October 15, 2018 <lb/>Accepted: December 14, 2018 <lb/>Published: December 31, 2018 <lb/>Copyright: © 2018 Hardcastle et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: Data cannot be <lb/>shared publicly to protect patient and clinician <lb/>anonymity. Data are available from the St John of <lb/>God Human Research Ethics Committee (contact <lb/>via ethics@sjog.org.au) for researchers who meet <lb/>the criteria for access to confidential data. <lb/>Funding: The authors received no specific funding <lb/>for this work. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Cancer is a leading cause of disease burden worldwide [1]. Effective physical activity (PA) <lb/>interventions to curb the growth in inactivity and prevent chronic illness in cancer survivors <lb/>are essential [2-3]. PA prevents cardiovascular disease (CVD) [4-5] and can reduce the risk of <lb/>cancer recurrence [6-9] and improve overall survival, yet few survivors meet current PA <lb/>guidelines of at least 150-minutes per week of moderate-intensity exercise [10]. Furthermore, <lb/>there are significant geographic inequalities in cancer survival, which need to be addressed <lb/>[11]. Effective, distance-based PA interventions are essential in order to reduce such geo-<lb/>graphic inequalities in survival. <lb/>Evidence from trials support the efficacy of PA interventions in producing short-term, but <lb/>not long-term change in cancer survivors [12,13]. Most interventions tend be supervised and/ <lb/>or facility-based, and subsequently resource-intensive. Home-based and distance-based inter-<lb/>ventions (such as those using wearable activity technology) may mitigate access and transport <lb/>issues, and are less expensive than supervised, facility-based programs requiring participants <lb/>to attend classes or maintain a health club membership [14]. There is a current gap in the liter-<lb/>ature on less intensive home-based interventions that could be cost-effective, and more <lb/>scalable. <lb/>Interventions that offer opportunities for self-monitoring have successfully increased PA in <lb/>cancer survivors [13], and survivors report that self-monitoring is a helpful tool for improving <lb/>PA [15,16]. Wearable activity trackers (WATs) hold great potential as a low-cost self-monitor-<lb/>ing tool to increase PA. Lyons et al [17] reviewed 13 different WATs and their associated apps, <lb/>and concluded that they use many behavior change techniques employed in typical PA inter-<lb/>ventions (i.e. self-monitoring, feedback, goal-setting). WATs are perceived as useful and <lb/>acceptable to individuals with chronic conditions [18]. Thus, WATs may represent a relatively <lb/>low-cost, feasible and scalable approach for widespread PA promotion in cancer survivors. <lb/>To date, only a few studies have examined the acceptability and usefulness of WATs to pro-<lb/>mote physical activity amongst older adults or those with chronic diseases, [18-21] and only <lb/>one study has explored acceptability in breast cancer survivors [22]. This found participants <lb/>mostly increased their awareness of the amount of time spent active or number of steps <lb/>achieved. However, the study recruited only metropolitan breast cancer survivors, and half <lb/>were already active. <lb/>Little is known about the feasibility of using WATs in interventions with survivors, and in <lb/>particular, to promote PA to regional and remote survivors. In order to design and develop <lb/>effective interventions, it is essential to first understand the utility of, and preference for <lb/>WATs, and WAT features amongst such survivors. The aim of this study is to explore the <lb/>acceptability and utility of, and preference for WATs in cancer survivors living in regional and <lb/>remote areas of Western Australia, in order to develop more effective interventions. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Participant recruitment <lb/>Following hospital HREC approval (St John of God Healthcare # 1157) participants were iden-<lb/>tified from the databases of breast and gynaecologic oncologists in Perth, Australia and from a <lb/>list of patients who expressed their interest in future research from previous studies (colorectal <lb/>and endometrial). Patients were eligible to participate if they: (i) had completed active treat-<lb/>ment for cancer within the preceding five years and deemed to be in remission; (ii) were insuf-<lb/>ficiently physically active (i.e., not meeting the recommended 150-minutes of moderate-<lb/>intensity PA per week [10]; (iii) resided in a regional and remote areas of WA [23] (i.e., with a <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Acceptability and utility of, and preference for wearable trackers amongst non-metropolitan cancer survivors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210039 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>postcode of 6200+); and, (iv) had daily access to a handheld device or personal computer and <lb/>internet. Exclusion criteria were: (i) age &lt;25 and &gt;90 years; (ii) already sufficiently physically <lb/>active; (iii) currently using a wearable tracker; (iv) inability to comprehend English. <lb/>Patients meeting the inclusion criteria (N = 77) were invited to participate by their treating <lb/>oncologist via mail. Patients registered their interest in participating in the study via email or <lb/>telephone, and subsequently received a telephone call from a research assistant (RA) to arrange <lb/>a convenient time to conduct a telephone screening questionnaire to determine PA status and <lb/>eligibility using the Active Australia questionnaire [24]. Participants provided written consent <lb/>and gave permission for the interviews to be audio-recorded. They were informed that pseudo-<lb/>nyms would be used in reporting of data. <lb/>Procedure <lb/>The procedure was based on a previous study by co-authors [22] and involved using five com-<lb/>mercially available WATs to assess acceptability and feasibility of wearable technology to <lb/>increase PA. The selected devices were chosen on the basis that they: (i) included a step-count <lb/>function; (ii) included a non-movement notification; (iii) had an associated app; and, (iv) were <lb/>affordable (less than $300AUD). Based on these criteria, five devices were selected for testing: <lb/>Fitbit Alta, Garmin Vivofit2, Garmin Vivosmart, Polar Loop2 and Polar A300. The selected <lb/>devices had a range of different features. For example, the Garmin Vivofit 2 used a long life <lb/>battery rather than needing to be charged; the Garmin Vivosmart measured stairs climbed and <lb/>the Fitbit had a fixed goal of 10,000 steps. <lb/>Participants were assigned two of the five WATs to wear for a minimum of four weeks, two <lb/>weeks per device. A one-week non-wear &apos;wash out&apos; period took place between trackers. Some <lb/>participants wore a third device, if time permitted and they were interested in trialling a third <lb/>device. The expectation was that two wearable trackers would be trialled. A RA mailed written <lb/>instructions, alongside the tracker concerning how to initialise their tracker and install the app <lb/>on their smartphone. Participants were also given brief information on how to operate the <lb/>tracker, its basic features and its app. Tracker features are found in Table 1. <lb/>Table 1. Specific features of wearable activity trackers selected for testing in the study. <lb/>Specific features <lb/>Fitbit Alta <lb/>Garmin Vivofit 2 <lb/>Garmin Vivosmart Polar Loop 2 <lb/>Polar A300 <lb/>Non-movement notification <lb/>Visual/vibration <lb/>visual/ audio <lb/>visual/ vibration <lb/>Sound/vibration <lb/>Sound/vibration <lb/>Display steps <lb/>✓ <lb/>✓ <lb/>✓ <lb/>✓ <lb/>✓ <lb/>Display proportion of steps taken and target goal <lb/>✓ <lb/>✓ <lb/>✓ <lb/>✓ <lb/>✓ <lb/>Default or auto goal a <lb/>Default <lb/>Auto <lb/>Auto <lb/>Auto <lb/>Default <lb/>Altimeter (stairs) <lb/>✓ <lb/>Heart Rate <lb/>✓ <lb/>Water resistant (up to 30 metres) <lb/>✓ <lb/>✓ <lb/>✓ <lb/>✓ <lb/>Sleep monitor <lb/>✓ <lb/>✓ <lb/>✓ <lb/>✓ <lb/>✓ <lb/>Display Size (mm) <lb/>25.5 x 10 <lb/>25.5 x 10.0 <lb/>25.3 x 10.7 <lb/>5 x 17 <lb/>27.5 x 27.5 <lb/>Cost (AUD) <lb/>150 <lb/>80 <lb/>189 <lb/>119 <lb/>149 <lb/>Battery life <lb/>7 days <lb/>1 year <lb/>7 days <lb/>21 days <lb/>4 weeks <lb/>Number of participants testing the device <lb/>12 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>6 <lb/>5 <lb/>a Default or auto-goal: &quot;Default&quot; indicates that devices have default step goals of 10,000 steps per day. <lb/>&quot;Auto goal&quot; indicates that devices will create a daily step goal automatically based on user&apos;s previous activity levels, i.e., if user achieved only 5000 steps under the goal of <lb/>7,500 steps, the step goal will reduce to 6,500 steps on the next day to make the goal more achievable. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210039.t001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Acceptability and utility of, and preference for wearable trackers amongst non-metropolitan cancer survivors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210039 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Data collection. Semi-structured interviews lasting up to 60-minutes were conducted. <lb/>Interviews took place either at the participant&apos;s home, cafe, or via telephone. S1 Fig provides <lb/>an overview of the interview guide used with questions concerning experiences, acceptability <lb/>and preferences of WATs. Questions also explored the utility of devices to increase PA and/or <lb/>reduce sedentary behaviour (SB) and comfort with technology. Interviews were digitally <lb/>recorded and transcribed verbatim. Data collection ceased at the point when no new informa-<lb/>tion was gained and data saturation was reached [25]. The study adhered to the consolidated <lb/>criteria for the reporting of qualitative research (COREQ) [26]. <lb/>Data analysis <lb/>Data were analyzed using thematic analysis [27]. Thematic analysis involved several steps. The <lb/>first step involved immersion and involved carefully reading transcripts several times to iden-<lb/>tify participants&apos; meanings. The second step involved attaching codes to salient text segments. <lb/>The third step involved the identification of themes at a broader level and examining whether <lb/>codes may be combined to form an overarching theme. The final step involved reviewing <lb/>themes, cross-checking for overlap and differences and finally defining and classifying themes. <lb/>To broaden data interpretation, a second researcher read and coded all transcripts and met <lb/>with the first researcher to agree on coding and finalise themes. The analysis offered is one <lb/>interpretation of the interviewees&apos; experiences and we acknowledge that other interpretations <lb/>are possible. Nevertheless, we aim to offer a credible and trustworthy interpretation that cap-<lb/>tures participants&apos; perceptions and experiences. For example, we provide &apos;thick description&apos; <lb/>via the use of extensive and direct quotations so that the reader can evaluate the interpretation <lb/>[28]. <lb/>Results <lb/>Seventy-seven cancer survivors were invited to participate. Of these seven (9%) expressed <lb/>interest but were ineligible. Twenty survivors participated in the trial (26%). Sixteen (14 female <lb/>and 2 male) completed the study with a mean age of 63 (SD 13) years. There were no signifi-<lb/>cant differences in age (t (73) = 1.29, p = 0.20) and months since diagnosis (t (73) = -0.43, <lb/>p = 0.67) of participants that completed the study compared to those who declined participa-<lb/>tion or dropped out. Participant demographics and study tracker allocation are summarized in <lb/>Table 2 and Table 3 respectively. <lb/>Analysis of the data identified four main themes: Increasing Self-Awareness of PA and SB; <lb/>Prompts and Feedback; Accuracy and registry of activities; WAT preferences and features. Sev-<lb/>eral participants purchased (n = 5) their own WAT following participation in the study and <lb/>several others (n = 8) were considering purchasing one. Pseudonyms are used throughout the <lb/>manuscript. A summary of the themes and illustrative quotes can be found in Table 4. <lb/>Increasing self-awareness of PA and SB <lb/>Most participants reported that the trackers made them more conscious of their PA and SB: <lb/>&quot;they motivated me. . .made me very aware of how much I&apos;m moving and that I need to move <lb/>more&quot; (Lisa, aged 49). Self-awareness of PA was viewed as important and the WATs provided <lb/>this awareness: &quot;I think it helps to know how much you&apos;re doing, what you&apos;re doing&quot; (Emma, <lb/>aged 50) and &quot;It certainly prompts my mind to think you&apos;re not doing enough&quot; (Sandra, aged <lb/>68). Several participants expressed surprised at the effort needed to reach the recommended <lb/>steps: &quot;If you&apos;re doing something very stationery I was surprised that you didn&apos;t get much of a <lb/>count&quot; (Paul, aged 52) and &quot;makes you more aware because I have an office job . . .you don&apos;t <lb/>take as many steps during those days&quot; (Anna, aged 35). Awareness of SB was also identified: <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Acceptability and utility of, and preference for wearable trackers amongst non-metropolitan cancer survivors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210039 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>&quot;just look at how much time you spent sitting&quot; (Diane, aged 67) and &quot;I&apos;ve got to move because <lb/>this thing&apos;s telling me I&apos;ve been sitting too long&quot; (Elsa, aged 78). In recognition of negative <lb/>cases, only one participant did not enjoy using the WATs: &quot;I was always worried about steps, <lb/>steps, steps. . .you&apos;ve got to do steps. It&apos;s intrusive on my life&quot; (Miriam, aged 67). <lb/>Prompts and feedback <lb/>The provision of prompts and feedback were the most motivational aspects of the WATs. The <lb/>WATs acted as a prompt: &quot;yeah it prompted me to go. . .like I could have gone up the escalator <lb/>but I elected to go up the stairs. . .and then I was cross because it didn&apos;t show (record stairs <lb/>climbed)&quot; (Carol, aged 68) and for Paul &quot;it prompted me to do it. . .I knew that if I went for a <lb/>decent walk then I&apos;d always get the 10000&quot; (Paul, aged 52). Real time feedback was important <lb/>to nudge behaviour and meet goals: &quot;Geez I haven&apos;t done enough sometimes at night I&apos;m 500 <lb/>short so I go outside in the dark and check on the animals to get my 10000&quot; (Karen, aged 51). <lb/>Participants also found the automated prompts to move motivating: &quot;every time it buzzed, <lb/>you got up and moved so you feel great success&quot; (Diane, aged 67) and &quot;last night I looked-<lb/>ahh that&apos;s the red mark!, so I jumped off the chair and round I went. . .if I didn&apos;t have that on I <lb/>wouldn&apos;t keep doing it&quot; (Elsa, aged 79). However, several participants found these reminders <lb/>too simplistic and in the case of the Garmin&apos;s &apos;MOVE!&apos; prompt, rude: &quot;It buzzed at you and <lb/>went MOVE . . . even had an exclamation mark, it&apos;s like &apos;seriously&apos; you get slightly offended&quot; <lb/>Table 2. Participant characteristics. <lb/>Age (years) <lb/>Mean <lb/>62.58 <lb/>SD <lb/>12.92 <lb/>Range <lb/>35-78 <lb/>Marital Status <lb/>Married/living together <lb/>13 <lb/>Separated <lb/>2 <lb/>Not married <lb/>1 <lb/>Highest completed education <lb/>Primary <lb/>1 <lb/>Secondary/high school <lb/>1 <lb/>Post-school vocational <lb/>6 <lb/>University <lb/>Not reported <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>Annual household income <lb/>&lt;AUS$ 20,000 <lb/>1 <lb/>AUS$ 20,001-$ 39,999 <lb/>2 <lb/>AUS$ 40,000-$ 59,999 <lb/>4 <lb/>AUS$ 60,000-$ 79,999 <lb/>1 <lb/>AUS$ 80,000 + <lb/>3 <lb/>Not reported <lb/>5 <lb/>Employment <lb/>Full-time <lb/>6 <lb/>Part-time <lb/>3 <lb/>Retired <lb/>6 <lb/>Homemaker <lb/>1 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210039.t002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Acceptability and utility of, and preference for wearable trackers amongst non-metropolitan cancer survivors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210039 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>(Emma, aged 50). For Paul, these prompts were rather &apos;Pavlovian&apos;; he offered his thoughts on <lb/>what may work: <lb/>&quot;Quantitative data are good because you&apos;re reminded that you&apos;re not meeting your targets. . .if <lb/>set at 10,000 and you get 7,000 for a couple of days then maybe you could get direct mes-<lb/>sages, bit of a psych talk. . .automated but make it personalised, you missed your target for a <lb/>few days rather than saying Move!&quot; <lb/>Several participants also referred to the feedback and praise concerning achievements as <lb/>important and motivational: &quot;very motivational feedback. . .computer graphics, gave you your <lb/>percentage ranking for the day so you could see how you were getting better&quot; (Diane, aged 67, <lb/>referring to Polar A300) and &quot;all of them had a goal for the day. . .the step goal was good. . .it <lb/>said you&apos;d done over 200% of your step goal&quot; (Maureen, aged 65). <lb/>Accuracy and registry of activities <lb/>The accuracy of statistics was identified as a theme and related predominantly to the accuracy <lb/>of the Fitbit which had a tendency to count arm movements as steps: &quot;Watch this (shakes arm) <lb/>I said what&apos;s the number and I went like this (shakes arm) and she went oh. . .it can be tricked&quot; <lb/>(Maureen, aged 65) and &quot;I&apos;m not sure I believe them, it&apos;s quite easy to get the steps in. . ..wash-<lb/>ing dishes or sanding something down, I tended to get the 10,000 steps pretty easy&quot; (John, <lb/>aged 69). The Polar A300 also misreported activity: &quot;My hand was moving for a couple of min-<lb/>utes, it thought I was running&quot; (Diane, aged 67). <lb/>The inaccuracy of the Fitbit led to a false sense of achievement for some. For example, <lb/>Linda found that it was relatively easy to accumulate steps: &quot;I cleaned the house on Saturday <lb/>and I did 9,800 steps just cleaning. . .it doesn&apos;t take much at all (Linda, aged 51). For others, <lb/>there was disappointment because the WATs didn&apos;t record other activities such as swimming: <lb/>&quot;it doesn&apos;t take into account other exercise like swimming&quot; (Miriam, aged 67), cycling: &quot;I <lb/>found (cycling) a bit tricky to track so I put in the kilometers in an area of the App&quot; (Lisa, aged <lb/>49) or gardening: &quot;It doesn&apos;t record gardening at all&quot; (Maureen, aged 65). <lb/>Table 3. Overview of participants and wearable activity trackers trialed. <lb/>Participant <lb/>Age <lb/>Cancer Type <lb/>Treatment <lb/>1 st tracker <lb/>2 nd tracker <lb/>3 rd tracker <lb/>1 <lb/>50-59 <lb/>Uterine <lb/>SU+CH+RA <lb/>Garmin Vivofit 2 <lb/>Polar Loop 2 <lb/>Garmin VivoSmart <lb/>2 <lb/>50-59 <lb/>Colorectal <lb/>SU+CH <lb/>Garmin VivoSmart <lb/>Polar A300 <lb/>Fitbit Alta <lb/>3 <lb/>60-69 <lb/>Colorectal <lb/>SU+CH <lb/>Garmin VivoSmart <lb/>Polar Loop 2 <lb/>N/A <lb/>4 <lb/>60-69 <lb/>Breast <lb/>SU+CH+RA <lb/>Garmin VivoFit 2 <lb/>Polar Loop 2 <lb/>Garmin VivoSmart <lb/>5 <lb/>60-69 <lb/>Colorectal <lb/>SU <lb/>Garmin VivoSmart <lb/>Fitbit Alta <lb/>Polar A300 <lb/>6 <lb/>50-59 <lb/>Ovarian <lb/>SU+CH <lb/>Fitbit Alta <lb/>Garmin VivoFit 2 <lb/>N/A <lb/>7 <lb/>40-49 <lb/>Breast <lb/>SU+CH+RA <lb/>Fitbit Alta <lb/>Garmin VivoSmart <lb/>N/A <lb/>8 <lb/>60-69 <lb/>Breast <lb/>SU+CH <lb/>Garmin VivoFit 2 <lb/>Fitbit Alta <lb/>Polar Loop 2 <lb/>9 <lb/>70-79 <lb/>Breast <lb/>SU+CH+RA <lb/>Garmin VivoSmart <lb/>Polar A300 <lb/>N/A <lb/>10 <lb/>50-59 <lb/>Breast <lb/>SU+CH+RA <lb/>Fitbit Alta <lb/>Polar Loop 2 <lb/>N/A <lb/>11 <lb/>70-79 <lb/>Breast <lb/>SU+RA+HR <lb/>Polar Loop 2 <lb/>Fitbit Alta <lb/>Garmin VivoFit 2 <lb/>12 <lb/>60-69 <lb/>Colorectal <lb/>SU <lb/>Fitbit Alta <lb/>Polar A300 <lb/>N/A <lb/>13 <lb/>30-39 <lb/>Breast <lb/>SU+CH <lb/>Fitbit Alta <lb/>Polar Loop 2 <lb/>Garmin VivoFit 2 <lb/>14 <lb/>50-59 <lb/>Breast <lb/>SU+CH <lb/>Fitbit Alta <lb/>Garmin VivoFit 2 <lb/>N/A <lb/>15 <lb/>50-59 <lb/>Endometrial <lb/>SU+CH+RA <lb/>Fitbit Alta <lb/>Polar A300 <lb/>N/A <lb/>16 <lb/>60-69 <lb/>Endometrial <lb/>SU+RA <lb/>Garmin VivoSmart <lb/>Fitbit Alta <lb/>N/A <lb/>Note. SU = Surgery; CH = Chemotherapy; RA = Radiotherapy; HR = Hormone Therapy <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210039.t003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Acceptability and utility of, and preference for wearable trackers amongst non-metropolitan cancer survivors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210039 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>WAT preferences and features <lb/>WAT preferences and features contain two sub-themes: appearance and functionality, and <lb/>preferred features. <lb/>Appearance and functionality. Appearance was a commonly cited factor in relation to <lb/>acceptability. The most aesthetically pleasing WAT was the Fitbit because of its slim band and <lb/>small face: &quot;I thought that one was quite sleek. . . not overbearing or overstated&quot; (Paul, aged <lb/>52) and &quot;from an aesthetic point of view it&apos;s more stylish&quot; (Fiona, aged 50). Participants also <lb/>liked the appearance of the Garmin VivoSmart (&quot;I like this watch. . .the face stays on&quot; (Lisa, <lb/>Table 4. Overview of themes and illustrative quotes. <lb/>Theme <lb/>Brief description <lb/>Illustrative quotes <lb/>Increasing self-awareness <lb/>of PA and SB <lb/>WATs increased participant self-awareness of their SB and PA. <lb/>&quot;It made me get out. . .take the dog for a walk. . .walk around the yard <lb/>(to) get my steps up&quot; (P6, aged 50-59) <lb/>&quot;Knowledge is power, so it&apos;s the reality of it that you might think <lb/>you&apos;re doing a certain amount of activity but having it written down <lb/>helps&quot; (P1, aged 50-59) <lb/>&quot;The main benefit was it tells you how many steps you&apos;ve done so it&apos;s <lb/>like quantifying how much exercise that we&apos;re getting on a daily <lb/>basis&quot; (P2, aged 50-59) <lb/>&quot;I get home and I&apos;ve only done 3000 steps for the whole day which <lb/>obviously isn&apos;t enough so it makes you more conscious to keep <lb/>moving and try move a bit more&quot; (P10, aged 50-59) <lb/>Prompts and Feedback <lb/>The most motivational dimensions of the WATs was the provision <lb/>of prompts and feedback. <lb/>&quot;The beep makes you look at the watch and then it tells you it&apos;s time <lb/>to move. . .I thought ok I&apos;ll go get a drink of water or something&quot; (P5, <lb/>aged 60-69) <lb/>&quot;If I&apos;m watching telly and the ads come on I get up off the chair <lb/>around the lounge, down the passage through the kitchen to increase <lb/>my steps, if I didn&apos;t have that on I wouldn&apos;t keep doing it&quot; (P11, aged <lb/>70-79) <lb/>&quot;It prompted me to go for a bit extra walking&quot; (P16, aged 60-69) <lb/>&quot;Fitbit sends you a weekly report. . .fireworks on the screen when you <lb/>reached your target&quot; (P15, aged 50-59) <lb/>Accuracy and Registry of <lb/>Activities <lb/>The accuracy of statistics (primarily step count) was questioned by <lb/>several participants, mainly with reference to the Fitbit which had a <lb/>tendency to over count steps during sedentary or light activity. <lb/>Others expressed disappointment because the WATs did not <lb/>record other activities such as stair climbing, swimming, gardening <lb/>or cycling. <lb/>&quot;The Fitbit needs to be made more accurate, it&apos;s giving people a false <lb/>sense of achievement&quot; (P14, aged 50-59) <lb/>&quot;I did an hour of yoga but it didn&apos;t register that&quot; (P8, aged 60-69) <lb/>&quot;The first one was really nice except, that I climbed up all these stairs <lb/>deliberately because I wanted it recorded. And I did four flights of, <lb/>five flights of stairs and it recorded one (Garmin Vivosmart) (P3, <lb/>aged 60-69) <lb/>&quot;Digging up a hole, large tree stump shurbs. . .didn&apos;t record as an <lb/>activity. . .you might get a little disillusioned, what have I got to do to <lb/>get an activity recorded&quot; (P4, aged 60-69) <lb/>WAT Preferences: <lb/>Appearance &amp; <lb/>Functionality <lb/>Appearance and functionality were commonly cited in relation to <lb/>acceptability and usability. Most participants preferred WATS with <lb/>a slim band. <lb/>&quot;The Fitbit is quite difficult to put on&quot; (Miriam, aged 67); &quot;I much <lb/>preferred the Fitbit because it was smaller and easier to work with&quot; <lb/>(P12, aged 60-69). <lb/>&quot;This one (Fitbit) was smaller, less bulky and easier to see&quot; (P10, aged <lb/>50-59) <lb/>&quot;This is a cute little one (Garmin Vivofit), it fits my wrist <lb/>perfectly. . .you don&apos;t even have to charge it&quot; (P11, aged 70-79) <lb/>WAT Preferences and <lb/>Features: Preferred <lb/>Features <lb/>The most popular feature was step counting. Several wanted the <lb/>WAT to have a heart rate monitor. WATs that were easy to sync <lb/>were also viewed favourably. <lb/>&quot;All I ever focused on was the step count&quot; (P5, aged 60-69); &quot;I used <lb/>them for steps mainly&quot; (P15, aged 50-59) <lb/>&quot;But I like the heart rate monitor on that one [Garmin] which I <lb/>thought was good&quot; (P2, aged 50-59); &quot;The syncing was a pain on that <lb/>one (Garmin Vivosmart) but the tapping (Fitbit) was also a pain&quot; (P6, <lb/>aged 50-59) <lb/>&quot;With the Garmin, I didn&apos;t get on that well with it, couldn&apos;t work out <lb/>a lot of things to do with it, with the Fitbit I was able to download the <lb/>app and follow it a bit more. . .it records the calories and steps&quot; (P16, <lb/>aged 60-67) <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210039.t004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Acceptability and utility of, and preference for wearable trackers amongst non-metropolitan cancer survivors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210039 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>aged 49) and VivoFit, as they were both slim in appearance. The Polar Loop was also popular <lb/>in appearance but perceived as uncomfortable since it&apos;s more like a bangle and would slide <lb/>around. The Polar A300 was not visually appealing and often described as bulky and clunky: <lb/>&quot;The polar was too big on, too clunky so I took it off&quot; (John, aged 69). <lb/>The most common complaint regarding useability concerned the Fitbit. Participants often <lb/>spoke about experiencing difficulties putting the band on: &quot;I physically could not press those <lb/>metal things through so I had to have my husband put it on&quot; (Carol, aged 68) and problems <lb/>looking at the statistics: &quot;I kept tapping and tapping and nothing would happen&quot; (Miriam, <lb/>aged 67) and &quot;you had to find x marks the spot&quot; (Elsa, aged 78). The Garmin VivoFit was <lb/>described with differing opinions. Some participants liked the security of the clip to lock in the <lb/>band, whilst others found it awkward and annoying: &quot;that was far too hard to do it your-<lb/>self. . .that was one that was two little hooks in&quot; (Maureen, aged 65). The Garmin Vivosmart <lb/>was popular because it had a normal watch strap: &quot;I&apos;m seriously thinking of getting a Garmin <lb/>(vivosmart). . .I like the fact it had a proper strap&quot; (Carol, aged 68), and displayed clear text: <lb/>&quot;For an older person, I would give them the Garmin because of its bigger writing and more <lb/>accurate&quot; (Karen, aged 51). <lb/>There were few issues reported concerning limited tech-knowledge even amongst the older <lb/>participants: &quot;pretty straight forward. . .for a techo nerd&quot; (Carol, aged 68) and &quot;I&apos;ve got the <lb/>piece of paper sat down, got my phone out, had to press the button, hang onto it until the <lb/>word came up, perfect&quot; (Elsa, aged 78). Only one participant did not understand how to use <lb/>them: &quot;I&apos;m not very computer literate. . .I couldn&apos;t get it to work&quot; (Sue, aged 78). All partici-<lb/>pants engaged with the Apps apart from Elsa and Sue. Elsa was content using solely the device <lb/>to self-monitor her activity and Sue was unable to set up either device. <lb/>Preferred features. The most popular feature across all WATs was the step counting <lb/>which promoted self-awareness. Most participants&apos; desired simple features as summarised <lb/>by Elsa &quot;What time it is, how many steps I&apos;ve done, how far I&apos;ve gone, that&apos;s all I wanted&quot; <lb/>(aged 78). Most participants found the automated prompts to increase step count as motiva-<lb/>tional, however the tone of the prompt was important. The tone of the Garmin was perceived <lb/>as abrupt and rude whereas the tone of the Fitbit was experienced as more polite: &quot;I&apos;d get a lit-<lb/>tle vibration to say let&apos;s go do 250 steps, it was much more polite than MOVE&quot; (Fiona, aged <lb/>50). <lb/>Trackers that were easy to sync (i.e., Fitbit) were also viewed favorably. There was also a <lb/>preference for the Fitbit app: &quot;Fitbit was superior for quick syncing and notifications associ-<lb/>ated with the App. . .had a lot more versatility. . .it was on autosync. . .the Garmin you had to <lb/>force sync&quot; (Fiona, aged 50), and, &quot;Garmin was a bit more complex to set up. . .even with the <lb/>food/ drinking you had to get a different app called Myfitnesspal&quot; (Lisa, aged 49). <lb/>The less preferred features have been highlighted and include issues relating to the accuracy <lb/>of trackers and disappointment that WATs did not effectively capture all activities. For some, <lb/>the auto-goal function on some trackers caused confusion: &quot;it wasn&apos;t clear like now the goal, <lb/>does that mean I have to do 5000 steps, why have they got that I&apos;ve been doing over 10000&quot; <lb/>(Elsa, aged 78). Despite the study recruiting regional and remote survivors, there were very <lb/>few concerns regarding internet availability. Only Anna mentioned this: &quot;The internet and <lb/>phone coverage is bad. . .that is a barrier if you want to download apps. . .sometimes you have <lb/>to use mobile data to look at your statistics&quot;. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>This is the first study to explore the experiences, acceptability and usability of WATs amongst <lb/>rural cancer survivors. Despite the evidence of the importance of PA for healthy survivorship <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Acceptability and utility of, and preference for wearable trackers amongst non-metropolitan cancer survivors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210039 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>[4-9], few survivors meet the PA guidelines [10]. As a powerful self-monitoring tool, WATs <lb/>present a potential opportunity for PA promotion and in particular, to reach survivors living <lb/>in rural communities. WATs may also play a role in objectively monitoring patient PA <lb/>remotely and used to predict important clinical outcomes such as readmission. A recent study <lb/>found that a higher mean daily step count, derived from the Fitbit, predicted lower risk of <lb/>readmission following metastatic peritoneal cancer [29]. In addition to the use of WATs to <lb/>promote PA to survivors following active treatment to prevent CVD, WATs could also play an <lb/>important role in identifying opportunities for real-time adaptive interventions during cancer <lb/>treatment to improve clinical outcome [29, 30]. <lb/>We found that WATs increased self-awareness of their PA and SB consistent with previous <lb/>research [18,20]. The provision of prompts and feedback were the most motivational aspects <lb/>of the WATs. The trackers provided continuous self-monitoring and real time feedback in <lb/>relation to step goals and appeared to reinforce progress or nudge behaviour towards goals. <lb/>Recognition of achievements (either from the device or through the App) were also enjoyed by <lb/>participants. The motivational nature from immediate feedback on step count and progress <lb/>towards step goals has been reported previously [20]. The features of WATs that most moti-<lb/>vated participants (i.e., monitoring behavior, prompts, setting goals, receiving feedback) are <lb/>also behavior change techniques known to be effective for promoting PA [31,32]. For example, <lb/>&apos;provide instruction&apos; and &apos;reinforcing efforts towards behavior&apos; are techniques associated with <lb/>a significant increase in PA [32]. Interventions that employ self-monitoring and at least one <lb/>other self-regulatory technique (i.e., goal setting, receiving feedback on performance, review of <lb/>goals) are significantly more effective in promoting PA [31]. <lb/>The majority of participants found the WATs to be highly acceptable and useful consistent <lb/>with previous research in older populations, [19,21] chronic disease [18,20] and breast cancer <lb/>survivors [22]. This is the first study to indicate that the provision of written instructions and/ <lb/>or telephone technical support in conjunction with WATs may be sufficient in rural survivors <lb/>and that such interventions do not require face-to-face contact. Only one participant reported <lb/>finding the devices intrusive and one other who was unable to use the technology. <lb/>Some were sceptical of the authenticity of the Fitbit-recorded data, noting that it tended to <lb/>over-count steps. Others failed to notice the devices misclassifying steps during SB or light <lb/>activity leading to a false sense of achievement. However, research supports the accuracy of <lb/>WATs, including the Fitbit for counting steps [33,34]. The reliability and validity of two Fitbit <lb/>models (Flex and ChargeHR) has shown to be good in older adults (aged over 65), with high <lb/>intra class correlations of the WATs with direct observation of steps [35]. Good strength of <lb/>agreement was also found for total distance and moderate-to-vigorous physical activity in the <lb/>free-living environment compared to an accelerometer [35]. A further study in older adults <lb/>also found excellent agreement between the Fitbit (One and Zip) and direct observation for <lb/>step count, and also between the Fitbit and Actigraph for average step count/per day over <lb/>7days [36]. It would appear that Fitbit trackers are sufficiently accurate to be used in commu-<lb/>nity-dwelling older adults to increase physical activity. The over-count of steps found in the <lb/>present study appears to occur only during light household activities. Therefore, future trials <lb/>should ensure the device is worn on the non-dominant wrist or taken off when performing sta-<lb/>tionery activities involving much arm movement. Some participants were disappointed that <lb/>activities such as swimming and cycling were not recorded by the device. Such frustration that <lb/>WATs fail to register activities has been noted elsewhere [20]. This is a limitation with some <lb/>models which are not waterproof and/or do not have more sophisticated features. <lb/>In relation to preferences, the aesthetics of the WATs were deemed crucial in determining <lb/>preference and likelihood of use, consistent with previous research [18, 21,22]. The smaller <lb/>trackers were mostly preferred with the Fitbit Alta being considered the most stylish. The <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Acceptability and utility of, and preference for wearable trackers amongst non-metropolitan cancer survivors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210039 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Garmin models were also favourable due to their slim in appearance and because the screen <lb/>was bigger and the display stayed on. The most common complaint regarding useability con-<lb/>cerned the Fitbit Alta and difficulties tapping to view the statistics. The acceptability of WATs <lb/>is highly influenced by device characteristics such as display, comfort and most of all <lb/>aesthetics. <lb/>The most preferred feature across WATs was step counting and this is consistent with the <lb/>previous study in breast cancer survivors [22]. The prompts were deemed helpful although the <lb/>tone of the prompt was considered important. The Fitbit appeared to be the preferred App; <lb/>participants found it more intuitive and some were interested in self-monitoring food intake, <lb/>which were not available on other Apps. <lb/>Clinical implications <lb/>The WATs provided self-monitoring and real time feedback in relation to step goals and rein-<lb/>forced progress and efforts towards goals. Future interventions may do well to have two differ-<lb/>ent WATs available for participants to choose from, according to activity preferences, aesthetic <lb/>preferences, and display size. <lb/>Strengths and limitations <lb/>Our study has certain limitations including a low response rate, which may have introduced <lb/>response bias. Additionally, our sample is predominantly female (87.5%) (since patient enrol-<lb/>ment was limited to databases with a heavy preponderance of female malignancies including <lb/>breast and gynecologic). Therefore we cannot assume that our findings are transferable to <lb/>male cancer survivors, particularly the findings in relation to aesthetic preferences. Further, <lb/>extended-term acceptance could not be explored. A study strength is the recruitment of under-<lb/>served survivors living in rural areas, and the first feasibility testing of providing WATs with <lb/>written instructions and/or telephone technical support. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>WATs appear to be acceptable to cancer survivors living in rural locations and may represent <lb/>a low-cost, feasible and scalable approach for PA promotion. WATs increased self-awareness <lb/>of physical activity, provided real time feedback in relation to goals, and reinforced progress <lb/>and efforts toward goals. The aesthetics of the WATs were deemed crucial in determining like-<lb/>lihood of use. Future interventions may do well to have two different WATs available for par-<lb/>ticipants to select from, according to activity preferences, aesthetic preferences and display <lb/>size. Future research should explore whether WAT use and increased PA is sustained over <lb/>time. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Fig. Interview guide. The interview guide provides examples of questions used during <lb/>interviews concerning experiences, acceptability and preferences of WATs. <lb/>(PDF) <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>The research team would like to thank the participants who generously shared their time and <lb/>experiences for the purposes of this project. We also thank Tracie Barbour for her kind assis-<lb/>tance in recruiting gynaecologic survivors. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Acceptability and utility of, and preference for wearable trackers amongst non-metropolitan cancer survivors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210039 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 13 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Sarah J. Hardcastle, Brigid M. Lynch. <lb/>Data curation: Sarah J. Hardcastle, Maddison Galliott, Niloufer J. Johansen. <lb/>Formal analysis: Sarah J. Hardcastle. <lb/>Methodology: Sarah J. Hardcastle, Brigid M. Lynch, Nga H. Nguyen. <lb/>Project administration: Niloufer J. Johansen, Christobel Saunders. <lb/>Resources: Sarah J. Hardcastle, Brigid M. Lynch, Nga H. Nguyen, Paul A. Cohen, Ganendra <lb/>Raj Mohan, Christobel Saunders. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Sarah J. Hardcastle. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Sarah J. Hardcastle, Maddison Galliott, Brigid M. Lynch, Nga H. <lb/>Nguyen, Paul A. Cohen, Ganendra Raj Mohan, Niloufer J. Johansen, Christobel Saunders. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. International Agency for Research on Cancer:World Cancer Report 2014. http://publications.iarc.fr/ <lb/>Non-Series-Publications/World-Cancer-Reports/World-Cancer-Report-2014. <lb/>2. Friedenreich CM, Neilson HK, Farris MS, &amp; Courneya KS. Physical activity and cancer outcomes: A pre-<lb/>cision medicine approach. Clin Cancer Res. 2016; 22: 4766-4775. https://doi.org/10.1158/1078-0432. <lb/>CCR-16-0067 PMID: 27407093 <lb/>3. Keats MR, Cui Y, Grandy SA, Parker L. Cardiovascular disease and physical activity in adult cancer sur-<lb/>vivors: A nested, retrospective study from the Atlantic PATH cohort. J Cancer Surviv. 2017; 264-273. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11764-016-0584-x PMID: 27854007 <lb/>4. Stewart J, Manmathan G, Wilkinson P. Primary prevention of cardiovascular disease: A review of con-<lb/>temporary guidance and literature. JRSM Cardiovasc Dis. 2017; 6:2048004016687211. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1177/2048004016687211 PMID: 28286646 <lb/>5. Sattelmair J, Pertman J, Ding EL, Kohl HW, Haskell W, &amp; Lee IM. Dose response between physical <lb/>activity and risk of coronary heart disease: A meta-analysis. Circulation. 2011; 124: 789-795. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.110.010710 PMID: 21810663 <lb/>6. Meyerhardt JA, Heseltine D, Niedzwiecki D, Hollis D, Saltz LB, Mayer RJ et al. Impact of physical activ-<lb/>ity on cancer recurrence and survival in patients with stage III colon cancer: Findings from CALGB <lb/>89803. J Clin Oncol. 2006; 24: 3535-3541. https://doi.org/10.1200/JCO.2006.06.0863 PMID: <lb/>16822843 <lb/>7. Friedenreich CM, Wang Q, Neilson HK, Kopciuk KA, McGregor SE, Courneya KS. Physical activity and <lb/>survival after prostate cancer. Eur Urol. 2016; 70: 576-585. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eururo.2015.12. <lb/>032 PMID: 26774959 <lb/>8. Dieli-Conwright CM, Lee K, Kiwata JL. Reducing the risk of breast cancer recurrence: An evaluation of <lb/>the effects and mechanisms of diet and exercise. Curr Breast Cancer Rep. 2016; 8: 139-150. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1007/s12609-016-0218-3 PMID: 27909546 <lb/>9. Hamer J, Warner E. Lifestyle modifications for patients with breast cancer to improve prognosis and <lb/>optimize overall health. CMAJ. 2017; 189: E268-E274. https://doi.org/10.1503/cmaj.160464 PMID: <lb/>28246240 <lb/>10. Rock CL, Doyle C, Demark-Wahnefried W, Meyerhardt J, Courneya KS, Schwartz AL, et al. Nutrition <lb/>and physical activity guidelines for cancer survivors. CA Cancer J Clin. 2012; 62: 243-274. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.3322/caac.21142 PMID: 22539238 <lb/>11. Tervonen HE, Aranda S, Roder D, You H, Walton R, Morrell S, et al. Cancer survival disparities worsen-<lb/>ing by socio-economic disadvantage over the last three decades in New South Wales, Australia. BMC <lb/>Public Health. 2017; 17: 691-696. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889-017-4692-y PMID: 28903750 <lb/>12. Goode AD, Lawler SP, Brakenridge CC, Reeves MM, &amp; Eakin EG. Phone, print and web-based inter-<lb/>ventions for physical activity, diet and weight control among cancer survivors: a systematic review. Jour-<lb/>nal Cancer Surviv. 2015; 9: 660-82. <lb/>13. Bluethmann SM, Vernon SW, Gabriel KP, Murphy CC, Bartholomew LK. Taking the next step: a sys-<lb/>tematic review and meta-analysis of physical activity and behavior change interventions in recent post-<lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Acceptability and utility of, and preference for wearable trackers amongst non-metropolitan cancer survivors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210039 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 13 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>treatment breast cancer survivors. Breast cancer research and treatment. 2015; 149: 331-342. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1007/s10549-014-3255-5 PMID: 25555831 <lb/>14. Hardcastle SJ, &amp; Cohen PA. Effective Physical Activity Promotion to Survivors of Cancer Is Likely to Be <lb/>Home Based and to Require Oncologist Participation. J Clin Oncol. 2017; 35: 3635-3637. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1200/JCO.2017.74.6032 PMID: 28915086 <lb/>15. Hardcastle SJ, Glassey R, Salfinger S, Tan J, Cohen PA. Factors Influencing Participation in Health <lb/>Behaviours in Endometrial Cancer Survivors. Psycho-Oncology. 2017; 26: 1099-1104. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1002/pon.4288 PMID: 27665487 <lb/>16. Hardcastle SJ, Maxwell-Smith C, Zeps N, Platell C, O&apos;Connor M, &amp; Hagger MS. A Qualitative Study <lb/>Exploring Health Perceptions and Factors Influencing Participation in Health Behaviors in Colorectal <lb/>Cancer Survivors. Psycho-Oncology. 2017; 26: 199-2015. https://doi.org/10.1002/pon.4111 PMID: <lb/>26935994 <lb/>17. Lyons EJ, Lewis ZH, Mayrsohn BG, &amp; Rowland JL. Behavior change techniques implemented in elec-<lb/>tronic lifestyle activity monitors: A systematic content analysis. Journal of Medical Internet Research. <lb/>2014; 16: e192. https://doi.org/10.2196/jmir.3469 PMID: 25131661 <lb/>18. Mercer K, Giangregorio L, Schneider E, Chilana P, Li M, Grindrod K. Acceptance of commercially avail-<lb/>able wearable activity trackers among adults aged over 50 and with chronic illness: a mixed-methods <lb/>evaluation. JMIR mHealth and uHealth. 2016; 4:1. <lb/>19. McMahon SK, Lewis B, Oakes M, Guan W, Wyman JF, Rothman AJ. Older Adults&apos; Experiences Using <lb/>a Commercially Available Monitor to Self-Track Their Physical Activity. JMIR mHealth and uHealth. <lb/>2016; 4:2. <lb/>20. Gualtieri L, Rosenbluth S, Phillips J. Can a free wearable activity tracker change behaviour? The impact <lb/>of trackers on adults in a physican-led wellness group. JMIR Res Protoc. 2016; 5(4):e237. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.2196/resprot.6534 PMID: 27903490 <lb/>21. Puri A, Kim B, Nguyen O, Stolee P, Tung J, Lee J. User acceptance of wrist-worn activity tracker among <lb/>community-dwelling older adults: Mixed method study. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth. 2017; 5:e173. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.2196/mhealth.8211 PMID: 29141837 <lb/>22. Nguyen NH, Hadgraft NT, Moore MM, Rosenberg DE, Lynch C, Reeves MM, et al. A qualitative evalua-<lb/>tion of breast cancer survivors&apos; acceptance of and preferences for consumer wearable technology activ-<lb/>ity trackers. Supportive Care in Cancer. 2017; 25: 3375-3384. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00520-017-<lb/>3756-y PMID: 28540402 <lb/>23. ASGS 2011. Australian Statistical Geography Standard, Remote areas. Canberra, AIHW. <lb/>24. Brown WJ, Burton NW, Marshall AL, &amp; Miller YD. Reliability and validity of a modified self-administered <lb/>version of the Active Australia physical activity survey in a sample of mid-age women. Australia and <lb/>New Zealand Journal of Public Health. 2008; 32: 535-41. http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1753-6405.2008. <lb/>00305. <lb/>25. Sparkes AC, Smith B. Qualitative research methods in sport, exercise and health. Routledge: London, <lb/>2014. <lb/>26. Tong A, Sainsbury P, Craig J. Consolidated criteria for reporting qualitative research (COREQ): a 32-<lb/>item checklist for interviews and focus groups. International Journal for Quality in Health Care. 2007; <lb/>19: 349-357. https://doi.org/10.1093/intqhc/mzm042 PMID: 17872937 <lb/>27. Braun V, Clarke V. Using thematic analysis in psychology. Qual Res Psychol. 2006; 3: 77-101. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1191/1478088706qp063oa <lb/>28. Hardcastle SJ, &amp; Hagger MS. &quot;You can&apos;t do it on your own&quot;: Experiences of a motivational interviewing <lb/>intervention on physical activity and dietary behaviour. Psychology of Sport and Exercise. 2011; 12: <lb/>314-323. <lb/>29. Low CA, Bovbjerg DH, Ahrendt S, Choudry H, Holtzman M, Jones HL, Pingpank JF, Ramalingam L, <lb/>Zeh HJ, Zureikat AH, Bartlett DL. Fitbit stepcounts during inpatient recovery for cancer surgery as a pre-<lb/>dictor of readmission. Ann Behav Med. 2018; 52: 88-92. https://doi.org/10.1093/abm/kax022 PMID: <lb/>29538623 <lb/>30. Low CA, Dey AK, Ferreira D, Kamarck T, Sun T, Bae S, Doryab A. Estimation of symptom severity dur-<lb/>ing chemotherapy from passively sensed data: Exploratory study. J Med Internet Res. 2017; 19:e420. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.2196/jmir.9046 PMID: 29258977 <lb/>31. Michie S, Abraham C, Whittington C, McAteer J, Gupta S. Effective techniques in healthy eating and <lb/>physical activity interventions: a meta-regression. Health Psychology. 2009; 28: 690. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1037/a0016136 PMID: 19916637 <lb/>32. Williams SL, French DP. What are the most effective intervention techniques for changing physical <lb/>activity self-effifacy and physical activity behaviour-and are they the same? Health Education <lb/>Research. 2011; 26: 308-322. https://doi.org/10.1093/her/cyr005 PMID: 21321008 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Acceptability and utility of, and preference for wearable trackers amongst non-metropolitan cancer survivors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210039 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 / 13 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>33. Stockpool C, Porcari J, Gillette C, Foster C. The accuracy of various activity trackers in estimating steps <lb/>taken and energy expenditure. J Fitness Res. 2014; 3: 32-48. <lb/>34. Nelson MD, Kaminsky LA, Dickin DC, Montoye AH. Validity of consumer-based physical activity moni-<lb/>tors for specific activity types. Med Sci Sports Exer. 2016; 48: 1619-1628. <lb/>35. Burton E, Hill KD, Lautenschlager NT, Thogerson-Ntoumani C, Lewin G, Boyle E, Howie E. Reliability <lb/>and validity of two fitness tracker devices in the laboratory and home environment for older community-<lb/>dwelling adults. BMC Geriatrics. 2018; 18:103. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12877-018-0793-4 PMID: <lb/>29724191 <lb/>36. Paul SS, Tiedmann A, Hassett LM, Ramsay E, Kirkham C, Chagpar S, Sherrington C. Validity of the Fit-<lb/>bit activity tracker for measuring steps in community-dwelling older adults. BMJ Open Sport Exerc Med. <lb/>2015; 0:e000013. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjsem-2015-000013 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Acceptability and utility of, and preference for wearable trackers amongst non-metropolitan cancer survivors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0210039 December 31, 2018 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 / 13 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
