<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>C L I N I C A L C O R R E S P O N D E N C E <lb/>Loneliness and belonging: Exploring experiences with the <lb/>COVID-19 pandemic in psycho-oncology <lb/>Melanie P. J. Schellekens 1 <lb/>| Marije L. van der Lee 1,2 <lb/>1 Scientific Research Department, Helen Dowling Institute, Centre for Psycho-Oncology, Bilthoven, The Netherlands <lb/>2 Department of Medical and Clinical Psychology, Tilburg University, Tilburg, The Netherlands <lb/>Correspondence <lb/>Marije L. van der Lee, Department of Medical and Clinical Psychology, Tilburg University, Tilburg, The Netherlands. <lb/>Email: mvanderlee@hdi.nl <lb/>K E Y W O R D S : anxiety, belonging, COVID-19, cancer, loneliness, oncology, Psycho-Oncology, qualitative research, survey <lb/> Keypoints <lb/>1. Patients (45.5% of n = 233) and family members (41.5% <lb/>of n = 41) experience more peace, as lockdown slowed <lb/>down the pace of life. <lb/>2. Some patients described feeling part of society again as <lb/>everyone is advised to stay home. <lb/>3. Patients worry about getting infected (50.5%) and need-<lb/>ing treatment on the intensive care unit (58%). <lb/>4. Family members mainly worry about infecting the <lb/>patient (65.9%). <lb/>5. Patients (36.3%) and their family (41.4%) feel lonelier <lb/>because of lockdown regulations. <lb/></front>

			<body>1 | INTRODUCTION <lb/>The COVID-19 pandemic affects people across the world. While the <lb/>virus appears to infect people of all ages and health status, those with <lb/>cancer, may be at higher risk for developing critical illness and death <lb/>(1,2). Besides physical implications, the psychosocial burden that the <lb/>pandemic puts on people may be especially high for those whose lives <lb/>have already been affected by cancer. Although people confronted <lb/>with cancer can be surprisingly resilient, half of cancer patients suffer <lb/>from significant psychological distress (3). Almost one-third of patients <lb/>develop a psychiatric disorder, such as anxiety and depression (4). <lb/>Family members, in particular life partners of cancer patients, also <lb/>experience psychological problems due to the cancer (5). The addi-<lb/>tional worries caused by COVID-19 and the social distancing regula-<lb/>tions can be detrimental for their wellbeing. To address their needs, <lb/>we explored experiences with the COVID-19 pandemic in patients or <lb/>family members who sought help at a mental health care institute for <lb/>psycho-oncology. Note that family members sought help for them-<lb/>selves, sometimes independently from the cancer patient. <lb/>2 | SETTING AND SURVEY <lb/>On March 12, the Netherlands went into lockdown. At the Helen <lb/>Dowling Institute, a mental health care institute specialized in psycho-<lb/>oncology care, psychological care was continued via video-consults <lb/>and online therapy. Seven weeks after the lockdown, clients (out-<lb/>patients and family members) were invited to participate in a survey <lb/>on the psychosocial burden of the COVID-19 pandemic. The study <lb/>was approved by the ethical board of the Helen Dowling Institute. Of <lb/>the 871 invited clients, 274 clients (233 patients and 41 family mem-<lb/>bers) responded within 2 weeks. Clients were mainly diagnosed with <lb/>an anxiety disorder (including post-traumatic stress), somatic symptom <lb/>disorder or depressive disorder (see Table 1 for demographic <lb/>characteristics). <lb/>The 12-item survey included questions regarding loneliness, <lb/>fear of infection and dying from COVID-19. For example: &quot;I worry <lb/>about getting infected with the coronavirus&quot;. Answers ranged from <lb/>0 = &apos;do not agree al all&apos; to 5 = &apos;totally agree&apos;. Scores ≥4 were coun-<lb/>ted as positive. The last question was open-ended: &quot;What impact <lb/></body>

			<front>Received: 26 May 2020 <lb/>Revised: 17 June 2020 <lb/>Accepted: 18 June 2020 <lb/>DOI: 10.1002/pon.5459 <lb/>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits use and distribution in any <lb/>medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non-commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made. <lb/>© 2020 The Authors. Psycho-Oncology published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. <lb/>Psycho-Oncology. 2020;29:1399-1401. <lb/>wileyonlinelibrary.com/journal/pon <lb/>1399 <lb/></front>

			<body>does the coronacrisis have on your life? Please describe in a few <lb/>sentences how your live has been changed.&quot; Using the thematic <lb/>analysis approach, the first author (in discussion with the second <lb/>author) coded the open-ended answers and grouped the codes into <lb/>the following themes: fear and loneliness, feelings of peace and <lb/>belonging. <lb/>3 | FEAR AND LONELINESS <lb/>The pandemic adds uncertainty for many patients, leading to addi-<lb/>tional worries. Their fears mainly concerned getting infected with <lb/>COVID-19 (50.5%) and requiring treatment on the intensive care unit <lb/>(58.0%). Many patients worried about being alone in the hospital <lb/>(45.6%) and not being able to say farewell to family and friends in case <lb/>of dying from COVID-19 (44.5%). Family members are mainly worried <lb/>about infecting the patient (65.9%). <lb/>Next to fear, loneliness appeared to be a main concern of many <lb/>clients: 36.3% of patients and 41.4% of family members reported feel-<lb/>ing lonelier than before the pandemic. Many patients described how <lb/>isolated they now feel. They miss contact with family and friends, <lb/>which cannot be replaced by a phone call. <lb/>Female patient (≥70): &quot;As someone of age who lives alone with can-<lb/>cer this is a very lonely process. I usually get by very well all by myself. <lb/>But now that all activities outside my home have been cancelled, this is <lb/>very difficult. My skin craves to be touched. No hugs…&quot;. <lb/>These feelings of loneliness seemed to fuel their worries regard-<lb/>ing the cancer. Social outings offered a welcome distraction, leading <lb/>their thoughts away from cancer. With that gone, their life is <lb/>completely focused on cancer again. <lb/>Male partner (50-59): &quot;Being in isolation with my partner who has <lb/>cancer, I miss those moments of recharging by going out with my friends <lb/>and being able to put the cancer on pause. Life is continuously focused on <lb/>only one thing: cancer. How do we keep going? There is no football <lb/>match, no festival, no street fair to get your mind of things. Life has <lb/>become empty. Even the contact with the physician is very limited. There <lb/>is not much left to be happy about.&quot; <lb/>4 | ON THE POSITIVE SIDE: FEELINGS OF <lb/>PEACE AND BELONGING <lb/>For those who have their whole family at home during the lockdown, it <lb/>was busy, often creating extra tension. However, a large group of <lb/>patients (45.5%) and family members (41.5%) felt more at ease because <lb/>of the lockdown. The overload of the external stimuli of daily life had <lb/>fallen away. This created a sense of peace and seems to ease their <lb/>worries. <lb/>The lockdown offered people time to reflect positively on their <lb/>lives: 39.8% of patients and 36.6% of family members expressed they <lb/>were now able to focus more on things that are really important <lb/>to them. <lb/>Female patient (50-59): &quot;This situation has thrown me back onto <lb/>myself instead of reaching out to others. Surprisingly, this stimulated my <lb/>self-reliance which suits me well. I am more in contact with what is truly <lb/>important/valuable to me. Of course I am bored at times, or think it sucks <lb/>that contact with others is so limited. But in the end I feel good, less of a <lb/>victim.&quot; <lb/>Several patients described how they were already used to staying <lb/>at home. Now that everyone stays indoors, they do not feel left out <lb/>anymore, which reinstates a sense of belonging. <lb/>Female patient (50-59): &quot;Currently, also all of my colleagues are <lb/>working from home. Now I am not the only one anymore who dials in (per <lb/>phone/video) at meetings, and I see that as an advantage.&quot; <lb/>5 | IMPLICATIONS <lb/>For many clients, who already suffered from mental problems due to <lb/>cancer, the COVID-19 pandemic caused additional fears The loneli-<lb/>ness they feel because of the lockdown regulations, seems to increase <lb/>their worries. For others, the pandemic created a sense of peace. It <lb/>gave them time to reflect on things that are truly important to them. <lb/>Moreover, they felt being part of society again, as everyone has to <lb/>stay home and limit their social contacts. <lb/>T A B L E 1 Demographic characteristics of the 274 survey <lb/>respondents <lb/>233 patients <lb/>n (%) <lb/>41 family <lb/>members n (%) <lb/>Sex, female <lb/>172 (73.8) <lb/>28 (68.3) <lb/>Age <lb/>&lt; 30 <lb/>8 (3.4) <lb/>1 (2.4) <lb/>30-39 <lb/>25 (10.7) <lb/>8 (19.5) <lb/>40-49 <lb/>40 (17.2) <lb/>8 (19.5) <lb/>50-59 <lb/>77 (33.0) <lb/>12 (29.3) <lb/>60-69 <lb/>62 (26.6) <lb/>10 (24.4) <lb/>≥ 70 <lb/>21 (9.0) <lb/>2 (4.9) <lb/>Living situation <lb/>Alone <lb/>45 (19.3) <lb/>11 (26.8) <lb/>With partner <lb/>76 (32.6) <lb/>11 (26.8) <lb/>With partner and children <lb/>98 (42.1) <lb/>14 (34.1) <lb/>With children <lb/>12 (5.2) <lb/>4 (9.8) <lb/>With parents <lb/>1 (0.4) <lb/>1 (2.4) <lb/>Education <lb/>Primary/lower secondary <lb/>12 (5.2) <lb/>3 (7.3) <lb/>Upper secondary <lb/>90 (39.1) <lb/>12 (29.3) <lb/>Higher vocational training/university 124 (53.3) <lb/>25 (61.0) <lb/>Start psychological treatment <lb/>Prior 2019 <lb/>52 (22.3) <lb/>15 (36.6) <lb/>Since 2019 <lb/>94 (40.3) <lb/>15 (36.6) <lb/>Since 2020 <lb/>87 (37.3) <lb/>11 (26.8) <lb/></body>

			<page>1400 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SCHELLEKENS AND van der LEE <lb/></note>

			<body>These positive experiences can provide input for helping patients <lb/>and family members to cultivate resilience. For example, therapists <lb/>can help clients to explore what values are important to them and <lb/>how they can live by these values, also in case their activities are lim-<lb/>ited due to cancer and lockdown. Acceptance and commitment ther-<lb/>apy includes exercises for living a meaningful life, that can inspire <lb/>therapists and clients (6). The sense of peace and belonging that peo-<lb/>ple felt, may be maintained if the stories of these patients become <lb/>known to the general public. Remembering the restrictions of isolation <lb/>and knowing that cancer patients and family members are living unre-<lb/>mittingly this way, increases understanding, which might mitigate the <lb/>feeling of being left-out. <lb/>To be prepared for a future lockdown, it may be helpful to urge <lb/>clients to seek safe forms of social contact. For example, people liv-<lb/>ing alone could choose one or two friends or family members that <lb/>they keep in (physical) contact with, with the precaution that these <lb/>contacts isolate themselves apart from the contact with the patient. <lb/>Also (online) contact with people in the same boat, that does not <lb/>focus on cancer, but rather on the consoling things in life, might be <lb/>helpful. <lb/>These findings might facilitate communication between clients <lb/>and health care professionals. When fear and feelings of loneliness <lb/>are addressed and normalized, it often relieves accompanying distress. <lb/>Importantly, addressing these feelings might also help to take the step <lb/>to seek psychological care if needed. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">DATA ACCESSIBILITY <lb/>The data that support the findings of this study are available from the <lb/>corresponding author upon reasonable request. The data are not pub-<lb/>licly available due to privacy or ethical restrictions. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">DATA AVAILABILITY STATEMENT <lb/>The data that support the findings of this study are available from the <lb/>corresponding author upon reasonable request. The data are not pub-<lb/>licly available due to privacy or ethical restrictions. <lb/></div>
			
			<front>ORCID <lb/>Melanie P. J. Schellekens <lb/>https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8397-7674 <lb/>Marije L. van der Lee <lb/>https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1316-7008 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Zheng Z, Peng F, Xu B, et al. Risk factors of critical &amp; mortal COVID-19 <lb/>cases: a systematic literature review and meta-analysis. J Infect. 2020; <lb/>23;S0163-4453(20)30234-6. Available from: https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm. <lb/>nih.gov/32335169. <lb/>2. Yang F, Shi S, Zhu J, Shi J, Dai K, Chen X. Clinical characteristics and <lb/>outcomes of cancer patients with COVID-19. J Med Virol. 2020. <lb/>3. Mehnert A, Hartung TJ, Friedrich M, et al. One in two cancer patients <lb/>is significantly distressed: prevalence and indicators of distress. <lb/>Psychooncology. 2018;27(1):75-82. <lb/>4. Mehnert A, Brähler E, Faller H, et al. Four-week prevalence of mental <lb/>disorders in patients with cancer across major tumor entities. J Clin <lb/>Oncol. 2014;32(31):3540-3546. <lb/>5. Moser MT, Künzler A, Nussbeck F, Bargetzi M, Znoj HJ. Higher emo-<lb/>tional distress in female partners of cancer patients: prevalence and <lb/>patient-partner interdependencies in a 3-year cohort. Psychooncology. <lb/>2013;22(12):2693-2701. <lb/>6. González-Fernández S, Fernández-Rodríguez C. Acceptance and com-<lb/>mitment therapy in cancer: review of applications and findings. Behav <lb/>Med. 2019;45(3):255-269. <lb/></listBibl>

			<front>How to cite this article: Schellekens MPJ, van der Lee ML. <lb/>Loneliness and belonging: Exploring experiences with the <lb/>COVID-19 pandemic in psycho-oncology. Psycho-Oncology. <lb/>2020;29:1399-1401. https://doi.org/10.1002/pon.5459 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">SCHELLEKENS AND van der LEE <lb/></note>

			<page>1401 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
