<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">How does using an AR learning environment affect student learning of a radical substitution mechanism?</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Martin</forename>
            <surname>Bullock</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Johannes</forename>
            <surname>Huwer</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Nicole</forename>
            <surname>Graulich</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-11-03T15:35:01.689565Z">03.11.2025 15:35:01</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1515$1$cti-2024-0024</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Walter de Gruyter GmbH</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1515/cti-2024-0024</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Martin Bullock, Johannes Huwer, Nicole Graulich. (2024). How does using an AR learning environment affect student learning of a radical substitution mechanism?. Chemistry Teacher International, 7(1), 91-105. DOI: 10.1515/cti-2024-0024</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-03T15:35:01.689565Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-11-03T15:35:01.689565Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>Dorota Krajewska* <lb/>The diachrony of the Basque marker bait-: <lb/>from a manner expression to subordinator <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1515/ling-2021-0198 <lb/>Received October 30, 2021; accepted December 28, 2022; published online March 20, 2024 <lb/>Abstract: This article analyzes the diachrony of the Basque marker bait-, which is a <lb/>verbal prefix in subordinate clauses, but also has other functions: for example, it <lb/>appears in independent clauses and indefinite pronouns. In subordinate clauses, it is <lb/>used in two ways. First, it co-occurs with clause-initial conjunctions in reason, <lb/>manner or result clauses or with pronouns in relative clauses. Secondly, it is used on <lb/>its own, in relative, reason, result and complement clauses (with a limited group of <lb/>verbs, such as emotive factive predicates or predicates of happening). The article <lb/>combines evidence from a corpus study (6822 examples from 16th-to 20th-century <lb/>texts) and internal reconstruction to (1) determine if and in what way the subordi-<lb/>nator bait-and the affirmative bai &apos;yes&apos; can be diachronically related, and (2) try to <lb/>establish diachronic relations between the functions of bait-. It is proposed that the <lb/>missing link between the subordinator and the affirmative particle might be a <lb/>manner expression bai which had anaphoric functions. The marker bait-emerged as <lb/>a reanalyzed form of the manner expression, which then gradually and through <lb/>various pathways spread to different types of subordinate clauses and was rean-<lb/>alyzed as a subordinator. <lb/>Keywords: adverbial clauses; Basque; complement clauses; diachrony; relative <lb/>clauses <lb/></front>

        <body>1 Introduction <lb/>According to Lafon (1999 [1966]: 667), the particle bait-is one of the most remarkable <lb/>aspects of the Basque grammar. It is used primarily as a subordinator but is also <lb/>found in independent clauses as well as in a series of indefinite pronouns (e.g., <lb/>zerbait &apos;something&apos;). It is also one of the very few grammatical prefixes in Basque. <lb/>One of the issues related to the marker&apos;s diachrony is whether and how it is <lb/>related to the affirmative adverb bai &apos;yes&apos;. While this idea is commonly accepted by <lb/></body>

        <front>*Corresponding author: Dorota Krajewska, Linguistics and Basque Studies, University of the Basque <lb/>Country (UPV/EHU), Vitoria-Gasteiz, Spain, E-mail: dorota.krajewska@ehu.eus. https://orcid.org/0000-<lb/>0002-6909-985X <lb/>Linguistics 2024; 62(3): 653-689 <lb/>Open Access. © 2023 the author(s), published by De Gruyter. <lb/>This work is licensed under the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. <lb/></front>

        <body>scholars (e.g., Lafon 1999 [1966]; Oyharçabal 1987), so far no satisfactory explanation <lb/>has been proposed for the nature of this connection. In this article, I take up this issue <lb/>to answer the following questions: <lb/>-What could be the connection between bai &apos;yes&apos; and the subordinator bait-? <lb/>-Is it possible to establish diachronic relations between the different functions of <lb/>bait-? In particular, what is the place of complement clauses with bait-? <lb/>I will argue that the missing link between the subordinator and the affirmative <lb/>adverb might be a manner expression that had anaphoric functions. The subordi-<lb/>nator could have grammaticalized from this manner expression and extended to <lb/>various subordinate structures in a stepwise way. Even though many of the changes <lb/>occurred before the first written records of the language, this article attempts to <lb/>gather textual evidence of those processes and reconstruct the main stages of the <lb/>grammaticalization processes involved. This is possible due to the phenomenon of <lb/>persistence (Hopper 1991), i.e., the tendency of the traces of the original lexical <lb/>meaning to remain in the grammaticalized item and to influence its grammatical <lb/>distribution. <lb/>As regards the methodology, the study combines corpus analysis, internal <lb/>reconstruction and insights from cross-linguistically common processes in the <lb/>diachrony of subordinate structures. The main corpus, used especially to analyze the <lb/>functions of bait-, consists of 37 16th-to 20th-century texts (listed in the Appendix), <lb/>which cover the eastern and northern regions of the Basque Country: Navarre, <lb/>Labourd, Lower Navarre and Soule (i.e., the areas where the prefix is extensively <lb/>used). 6822 tokens of bait-were extracted from the corpus. R statistical tools (R Core <lb/>Team 2022) were used for the quantitative part of the study. <lb/>The article is structured as follows. Section 2 presents the functions of bait-. <lb/>Section 3 describes changes observed in the history of the language. Section 4 argues <lb/>that the affirmative adverb bai can be seen as a manner expression and presents <lb/>several hypotheses on how the subordinator developed from it and attempts to <lb/>reconstruct how the marker extended to different types of clauses. <lb/>2 Functions of bait-<lb/>2.1 Overview <lb/>The morpheme bait-is usually described as a subordinator (see e.g., Artiagoitia et al. <lb/>2003: 711; Euskaltzaindia 1999: 12; Oyharçabal 1987). The main arguments in favor of <lb/>the subordinate status of clauses with bait-are the following (Oyharçabal 1987: 263): <lb/>(a) it is incompatible with other markers of subordination (relative -en or completive <lb/></body>

        <page>654 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Krajewska <lb/></note>

        <body>-la) or with the conditional prefix ba-, (b) the verbal forms with bait-cannot have <lb/>allocutive forms (which are only possible in independent clauses). However, the <lb/>degree of integration of the subordinate clause varies, as will be shown. Moreover, <lb/>bait-is occasionally found in independent clauses. <lb/>Nowadays, it is used in eastern and northern dialects of Basque. However, old <lb/>western and central texts contain a few examples of bait-, which suggests that the <lb/>morpheme was once common to all varieties (Azkue 1923: Section 529; Lafon 1999 <lb/>[1966]: 681; Lakarra 1986; Lakarra 1996: 191; Mitxelena 2011 [1981]: 530-531). <lb/>The marker behaves like a proclitic (Oyharçabal 1987: 257). No other morpheme <lb/>can go between bait-and the verb. If a verbal particle is used, it has to be placed <lb/>before it (Oyharçabal 1987: 259). The negative particle ez also precedes bait-and, since <lb/>it ends in a voiceless sibilant, it causes devoicing of the initial consonant of the <lb/>marker, which is sometimes reflected in writing, e.g., ezpaikara = ez &apos;no&apos; + bait-<lb/>+ gara &apos;we are&apos;. It can attach to any independent finite verb: it cannot appear on <lb/>imperatives, allocutive forms, verbs carrying the interrogative suffix or hypothetical <lb/>verb forms (Oyharçabal 1987: 257). Several phonological changes occur between the <lb/>final occlusive of the marker and the first consonant of the verb: -t + d-/g-= -t-/-k-<lb/>(baitira, baikara), -t + z-= -tz-(baitzen), -t + n-/l-/h-= -n-/-l-/-h-(bainaiz, bailira, <lb/>baihaiz). Additionally, Souletin has the form beit-, sometimes reduced to be-before n, <lb/>h and l. <lb/>In subordinate clauses the marker is used as relativizer, complementizer and <lb/>adverbializer. Its major uses can be divided into two classes (Figure 1). The classi-<lb/>fication I present here is roughly based on Oyharçabal (1987: 248). <lb/>Figure 1: Functions of bait-. <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">The diachrony of the Basque marker bait-<lb/></note>

        <page>655 <lb/></page>

        <body>First, bait-is employed together with several clause-initial elements: <lb/>-conjunctions in adverbial clauses (reason (1), manner (2), concessive and result <lb/>clauses are the main types) <lb/>-interrogative pronouns in headed relatives (3), correlatives (4) and free rela-<lb/>tives (5) <lb/>(1) <lb/>Erra-ten da <lb/>mortale-a zeren <lb/>ill-zen baitu <lb/>arima <lb/>say-IPFV AUX.3SG mortal-DEF because kill-IPFV bait.AUX.3SG&gt;3SG soul <lb/>&apos;It is called mortal because it kills the soul.&apos; <lb/>(BeriainDotrina, 1626) 1 <lb/>(2) <lb/>Eta kita <lb/>ietzaguk <lb/>gure zorr-ak, <lb/>nola gu-k <lb/>ere <lb/>and forgive AUX.IMP.2SG&gt;3PL&lt;1PL our debt-DEF.PL how we-ERG also <lb/>gure zordun-ei <lb/>kita-tzen <lb/>baitrauegu. <lb/>our debtor-DAT.PL forgive-IPFV bait.AUX.1PL&gt;2SG&lt;3PL <lb/>&apos;And forgive us our debts, as we forgive our debtors.&apos; <lb/>(LeizarragaTest, Matt 6: 12, 1571) 2 <lb/>(3) <lb/>aitafamilia bat, zein-ek <lb/>landa <lb/>baitzezan <lb/>mahasti bat <lb/>landowner one which-ERG plant.RAD bait.AUX.AOR.3SG&gt;3SG vineyard one <lb/>&apos;a landowner who planted a vineyard&apos; <lb/>(LeizarragaTest, Matt 21: 33, 1571) 3 <lb/>(4) <lb/>Nor-i <lb/>ere pot egin-en <lb/>baitraukat, <lb/>hura da <lb/>who-DAT PTCL kiss make-FUT bait.AUX.1SG&gt;3SG&lt;3SG that be.3SG <lb/>&apos;Whomever I will kiss, he is the one.&apos; <lb/>(LeizarragaTest, Matt 26: 48, 1571) 4 <lb/>(5) <lb/>Eta eman-en daraie-la <lb/>[zer bai-tute <lb/>merezi] <lb/>and give-FUT AUX.3SG&gt;3SG&lt;3PL-COMP what bait-AUX.3PL&gt;3SG deserve <lb/>&apos;And that he will give them what they deserve.&apos; <lb/>(Etxepare, 1545) <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">1 Unless stated otherwise, the texts come from the Euskal Klasikoen Corpusa corpus (Euskara <lb/>Institutua 2013). Note that the Basque examples, depending on the source, are mostly given in <lb/>modernized orthography. <lb/>2 Since Leizarraga translated the Bible from French, it might be interesting to compare the Basque <lb/>examples to the original (Le Nouveau Testament 1563). For (2), the French text reads: &quot;Et nous remets <lb/>nos dettes, comme aussi nous les remettons à nos detteurs&quot;. <lb/>3 The French source: &quot;It y avoit un pere de famile, qui planta une vigne&quot;. <lb/>4 The French source: &quot;Celuy que ie baiseray, c&apos;est luy&quot;. <lb/></note>

        <page>656 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Krajewska <lb/></note>

        <body>These kind of bait-clauses can be called &apos;doubly-marked&apos; subordinate clauses, as <lb/>there are two subordinating elements: bait-on the verb and a clause-initial <lb/>conjunction or pronoun. <lb/>As regards the syntactic status of doubly-marked bait-clauses, 5 except for free <lb/>relatives, they are adjoined to the main clause, i.e., they are not embedded and <lb/>cannot function as a constituent in the main clause. They occupy a marginal position <lb/>with regard to the main clause (they can appear before or after it, depending on the <lb/>clause type). Relative clauses can be extraposed (they do not have to appear imme-<lb/>diately to the right of the head noun) and they can also appear as parentheticals in <lb/>the middle of the main clause. In correlatives the degree of integration with the main <lb/>clause might be considered higher (though they are not embedded), as the clause <lb/>with bait-(which always precedes the main clause) is not easily omittable, and in the <lb/>second clause there is usually a pronoun referring back to the clause with bait-. <lb/>Finally, free relatives are embedded and function as a constituent in the main clause. <lb/>The prefix bait-is also used together with the conjunction ala in exclamatives <lb/>(see Rebuschi [2008] for an analysis of their syntax): <lb/>(6) <lb/>Ala ni dohacabe handi-a bainaiz! <lb/>ala I unlucky big-DEF bait.be.1SG <lb/>&apos;I am so unlucky!&apos; <lb/>(Materra, 1623) <lb/>In the second class (&apos;bait-only clauses&apos;), there is no conjunction or any other element <lb/>that determines the meaning. Thus, the interpretation depends on the context and <lb/>often more than one reading is possible. Based on the function that the bait-clause <lb/>fulfills, we can distinguish relative clauses (7)-(8), 6 reason clauses (9)-(10), result <lb/>clauses (which sometimes can be interpreted as expressing manner (11)) and com-<lb/>plement clauses (discussed in Section 2.2). When the clause with bait-is placed before <lb/>the main clause, the marker expresses reason, background information or topic (12). <lb/>(7) <lb/>Anaya, igori-co darauat <lb/>goutum-bat, [jaun-a-c <lb/>eman <lb/>brother send-FUT AUX.1SG&gt;3SG&lt;2SG letter-one <lb/>lord-DEF-ERG give <lb/>baytaraut <lb/>galcerdy ceta-z-ko bat-en barnean]. <lb/>bait.AUX.3SG&gt;3SG&lt;1SG sock <lb/>silk-INS-RM one-GEN inside <lb/>&apos;Brother, I will send you a letter which the lord gave to me inside a silk sock.&apos; <lb/>(15th cent., Mitxelena 2011 [1964]: 3.2.8) <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">5 I will follow Lehmann&apos;s (1988) distinctions when describing the syntax of subordination, especially <lb/>with respect to the level of integration of the main and subordinate clauses. <lb/>6 A prenominal construction (typical of head-final languages) is the least marked relative con-<lb/>struction in Basque since the oldest texts, even though several postnominal constructions have also <lb/>emerged at different stages of the language. <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">The diachrony of the Basque marker bait-<lb/></note>

        <page>657 <lb/></page>

        <body>(8) <lb/>Ethorri da <lb/>ordu-a <lb/>[gizon-a-ren Seme-a glorifikatu-ren <lb/>come <lb/>AUX.3SG <lb/>hour-DEF man-DEF-GEN son-DEF glorify-FUT <lb/>baita]. <lb/>bait.AUX.3SG <lb/>&apos;The hour has come that the son of the man will be covered in glory.&apos; <lb/>(LeizarragaTest, John 12: 23, 1571) 7 <lb/>(9) <lb/>Erran-en dautzuet, <lb/>gero ere jakin-en baituzue. <lb/>say-FUT AUX.1SG&gt;3SG&lt;2PL later also know-FUT bait.AUX.2PL&gt;3SG <lb/>&apos;I will tell you, because you will know later anyway.&apos; <lb/>(Larzabal, 20th c.) <lb/>(10) <lb/>Ordea nolatan ez-tuzue <lb/>egi-ten? Ezin <lb/>baitaidikezue. <lb/>so <lb/>why <lb/>NEG-AUX.2PL&gt;3SG do-IPFV cannot bait.AUX.POT.2PL&gt;3SG <lb/>&apos;So why you don&apos;t do that? Because you can&apos;t.&apos; <lb/>(Axular, 1643) <lb/>(11) <lb/>Gau-a <lb/>jin <lb/>da <lb/>betbetan, bi <lb/>urrats-etan ez baitzen <lb/>night-DEF come AUX.3SG suddenly two step-INES.PL NEG bait.be.PST.3SG <lb/>fits-ik <lb/>ageri. <lb/>nothing-PART visible <lb/>&apos;The night came suddenly, so that one couldn&apos;t see anything two steps ahead.&apos; <lb/>(Etxepare Buruxkak, 1910) <lb/>(12) <lb/>Eta erran baituçu <lb/>Iesu Christo-ren fede-a <lb/>and say <lb/>bait.AUX.2SG&gt;3SG Jesus Christ-GEN faith-DEF <lb/>du-en-a <lb/>de-la <lb/>guiristino, cer-tan <lb/>dago <lb/>have.3SG&gt;3SG-SUB-DEF be-COMP Christian what-INDEF.INES be.3SG <lb/>principalqui Iesu Christo-ren fede-a? <lb/>mainly <lb/>Jesus Christ-GEN faith-DEF <lb/>&apos;So you have said that the one who has the faith of Jesus Christ is Christian, <lb/>what does the faith of Jesus Christ mainly consist of?&apos; <lb/>(Materra, 1623) <lb/>Leaving aside complement clauses, the clauses with bait-illustrated above are <lb/>adjoined and not embedded, similar to their doubly-marked equivalents. This also <lb/>applies to examples interpreted as relative: the head noun and the relative clause do <lb/>not form a single constituent and the bait-clause does not necessarily appear <lb/>immediately after the noun it modifies. The only syntactic difference between <lb/>relative and other bait-only clauses is that in the former there must be a participant <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">7 The French source: &quot;L&apos;heure est venue, que le Fils de l&apos;homme doit estre glorifié&quot;. <lb/></note>

        <page>658 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Krajewska <lb/></note>

        <body>shared between the main and the subordinate clause, while in the latter there is no <lb/>such restriction. <lb/>Moreover, bait-can have a discourse function, expressing shades of conse-<lb/>quence, result, contrast or emphasis (13)-(14). In the oldest texts, the verb marked <lb/>with bait-can appear in the last clause of a sequence, and the clause with bait-can be <lb/>linked with the preceding one using the conjunction eta &apos;and&apos;, as in (13). <lb/>(13) <lb/>baina erra-k <lb/>solament hitz-a, <lb/>eta sendatu-ren baita <lb/>but <lb/>say-IMP.2SG just <lb/>word-DEF and heal-FUT <lb/>bait.AUX.3SG <lb/>ene <lb/>muthill-a. <lb/>my <lb/>boy-DEF <lb/>&apos;but say just a word and my boy will be healed&apos; <lb/>(LeizarragaTest, Matt 8: 8, 1571) 8 <lb/>(14) <lb/>Zoin laster eta aise <lb/>juja-tzen duzu-n, <lb/>zu-k, <lb/>how fast <lb/>and easily judge-IPFV AUX.2SG&gt;3SG-SUB you-ERG <lb/>jende-a! <lb/>Baititut <lb/>ene arrazoin-ak! <lb/>people-DEF bait.have.1SG&gt;3PL my reason-DEF.PL <lb/>&apos;-How fast and easily you judge people! -I (bait-) have my reasons!&apos; <lb/>(Larzabal, 20th c.) <lb/>Finally, the marker shows up in a few other areas of grammar: in place names, <lb/>possibly in the animate locative postposition baita-, in the archaic prefix albait-, in <lb/>indefinite pronouns and as a temporal conjunction. <lb/>Toponyms with bait-are found in some northern regions of the Basque Country, <lb/>for example, Espela bayta &apos;(the place) where the box tree is&apos; (1591) (Salaberri Zaratiegi <lb/>1996: 226). According to Salaberri Zaratiegi (1996: 226), they are Satznamen, which <lb/>developed from bait-relative clauses. We can reconstruct (15) as the source con-<lb/>struction with the subsequent ellipsis of the head noun. <lb/>(15) <lb/>(leku-a) <lb/>[espel-a baita] <lb/>place-DEF <lb/>box-DEF bait.be.3SG <lb/>&apos;(the place) where the box tree is&apos; <lb/>The locative postposition baita-used with animate referents should also be <lb/>mentioned here. <lb/>(16) <lb/>ni-re baita-n <lb/>I-GEN ANIM-INES <lb/>&apos;in me&apos; <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">8 The French source: &quot;mais seulement di le mot, et mon garson sera guari&quot;. <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">The diachrony of the Basque marker bait-<lb/></note>

        <page>659 <lb/></page>

        <body>(17) <lb/>anaia <lb/>baita-ra <lb/>brother <lb/>ANIM-ADL <lb/>&apos;to the brother&apos;s place&apos; <lb/>Mitxelena (2011 [1970]: 264) and Creissels and Mounole (2011: 179) mention the pos-<lb/>sibility that baita-could have developed from a subordinate clause (most probably a <lb/>relative clause) with the verbal prefix bait-. According to Creissels and Mounole <lb/>(2011) a change from &apos;at the place where N is&apos; to &apos;at N&apos;s place&apos; could have taken place. <lb/>From there it could develop into the locative postposition (see also Krajewska 2022), <lb/>cf. &apos;house/home&apos; &gt; locative grammaticalization path (Kuteva et al. 2019: 233, 235-236). 9 <lb/>Albait-, called prescriptif by Lafon (1980 [1944]), is an archaic verbal prefix no <lb/>longer employed in Basque, found only in 16th-and 17th-century northeastern texts <lb/>(Oyharçabal 1997: 61). As for al-, Lafon (1999 [1966]: 692) proposed that it is the particle <lb/>of possibility ahal, as in ahal izan &apos;can&apos;. Albait-appears in second and third-person <lb/>hypothetical verb forms and expresses an imperative that is to be executed in the <lb/>future or if a condition is met (18) (Lafon 1980 [1944]: 491). <lb/>(18) <lb/>Eta orduan baldin nehor-c <lb/>ba-darraçue, <lb/>Huna hemen <lb/>and so <lb/>if <lb/>someone-ERG COND-say.3SG&gt;3SG&lt;2PL Here here <lb/>Christ edo Hara han: ez-albeitzineçate <lb/>sinhets. <lb/>Christ or <lb/>there there NEG-albait.AUX.HYP.2PL&gt;3SG believe <lb/>&apos;And if someone tells you &apos;Christ is here!&apos; or &apos;There!&apos;, do not believe.&apos; <lb/>(LeizarragaTest, Matt 24: 23, 1571) 10 <lb/>Furthermore, we find -bait as a suffix on a series of indefinite pronouns: for example, <lb/>norbait &apos;somebody&apos;, zerbait &apos;something&apos; or nonbait &apos;somewhere&apos;. Azkue (1923: 357) <lb/>was first to realize that the subordinator and the suffix that attaches to interrogative <lb/>pronouns are one and the same and that the particular variant used in subordinate <lb/>clauses is also found in pronouns. Thus, in Soule the verbal marker became beit-(the <lb/>first examples appear in the 17th century, but it became frequent in the 18th [Padilla-<lb/>Moyano 2017: 703]), and the same form appears in pronouns too. In Biscay, the <lb/>variant baist-is found as a prefix in a handful of examples in the anonymous <lb/>collection of proverbs known as Refranes y sentencias (1596) and also occasionally in <lb/>pronouns. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">9 Creissels and Mounole (2011) conclude that this explanation is problematic, because, if it were true, <lb/>we would not expect genitive marking on the noun (as in (16)). However, this might not be a problem <lb/>since, as explained in Krajewska (2022: 249), in the earliest texts the absolutive (17) actually pre-<lb/>dominates and it is possible that the genitive was added later in analogy to other nominal forms <lb/>which are built on the genitive. <lb/>10 The French source: &quot;Lors si quelqu&apos;un vous dit, Voici le Christ, ici ou là, ne le croyez pas&quot;. <lb/></note>

        <page>660 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Krajewska <lb/></note>

        <body>Finally, in some areas, especially in Soule, bait can be used as a temporal <lb/>conjunction in non-finite clauses with the meaning &apos;by the time&apos; (19). The affirmative <lb/>adverb bai or forms built upon it -baiko or baikoz -are employed in some other <lb/>dialects (Lafon 1999 [1973]: 44). <lb/>(19) <lb/>zü jin <lb/>bait, egin-ik düket <lb/>you come bait do-PART have.FUT.1SG&gt;3SG <lb/>&apos;I will have done this before by the time you have arrived.&apos; <lb/>(Gèze 2010) <lb/>2.2 Complement clauses with bait-<lb/>The most common complementizer in Basque is -ela (Artiagoitia 2003; Artiagoitia and <lb/>Elordieta 2016), which is used in indicative complements as well as in some sub-<lb/>junctive complements (-ela contrasts with -en, employed in indirect questions and <lb/>some subjunctive complements). The range of use of bait-is more limited than that of <lb/>-ela as only few verbs take complements with bait-apart from the more usual -ela <lb/>complements. <lb/>The first class of verbs are factive predicates. As put by Kiparsky and Kiparsky <lb/>(1970: 147), with factive predicates &quot;[t]he speaker presupposes that the embedded <lb/>clause expresses a true proposition, and makes some assertion about that proposi-<lb/>tion&quot;. For instance, whichever sentence in (2) the speaker utters, he or she pre-<lb/>supposes what is said in (21). <lb/>(20) a. Bill regrets that Sheila is no longer young. <lb/>b. Bill doesn&apos;t regret that Sheila is no longer young. <lb/>c. Does Bill regret that Sheila is no longer young? <lb/>(21) <lb/>Sheila is no longer young. <lb/>(Karttunen 1971b: 55) <lb/>Predicates which can take bait-complements are mostly affective factive verbal <lb/>and non-verbal predicates, e.g., pena/domaia da &apos;it&apos;s pity&apos; (22), harritzeko da &apos;it&apos;s <lb/>surprising&apos;, ez da dudarik &apos;there is no doubt&apos;, kontent izan &apos;be happy&apos;, xantza izan <lb/>&apos;be lucky&apos; (23). Epistemic factive verbs like &apos;know&apos;, &apos;see&apos; or &apos;realize&apos; never take bait-<lb/>complements. Neither verbs of saying nor verbs of desire are attested with bait-. <lb/>The marker also often surfaces with adverbs such as beharrik &apos;luckily&apos;, though <lb/>examples without the subordinator on the verb are also possible (OEH, 11 s.v. <lb/>beharrik). <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">11 OEH: Orotariko euskal hiztegia -General Basque dictionary (Euskaltzaindia 2019). <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">The diachrony of the Basque marker bait-<lb/></note>

        <page>661 <lb/></page>

        <body>(22) <lb/>Pena da <lb/>egiazko hobendun-ek ez baitute <lb/>hain laster <lb/>pity be.3SG true <lb/>culprit-ERG.PL NEG bait.AUX.3PL&gt;3SG so <lb/>fast <lb/>aitor-tzen. <lb/>confess-IPFV <lb/>&apos;It&apos;s pity that real culprits do not confess so fast.&apos; <lb/>(Larzabal, 20th c.) <lb/>(23) <lb/>Xantza duzue <lb/>gizon-a itsaso-an baitut. <lb/>luck <lb/>have.2PL&gt;3SG man-DEF sea-INES <lb/>bait.have.1SG&gt;3SG <lb/>&apos;You&apos;re lucky that my man is at sea.&apos; <lb/>(Larzabal, 20th c.) <lb/>(24) <lb/>Plazer <lb/>dut <lb/>erran baituzu <lb/>ongi. <lb/>pleasure have.1SG&gt;3G say <lb/>bait.AUX.2SG&gt;3SG well <lb/>&apos;I&apos;m pleased because/that you have said it well.&apos; <lb/>(BerianDotrina, 1626) <lb/>The predicates mentioned above are not uncommon in modern texts (22)-(23), but <lb/>they are scarce in older sources. Before the 18th century, only a few examples are <lb/>found, and they are usually ambiguous between reason and complement as in (24). <lb/>This difference might be partially due to the type of sources available for earlier <lb/>stages of the language (i.e., mostly religious texts), which probably did not favor the <lb/>use of such predicates. Nevertheless, it seems that factive predicates tend to appear <lb/>with non-finite complements in older texts (something still possible nowadays), as <lb/>in (25). <lb/>(25) <lb/>Dolu dizit <lb/>eta damu <lb/>zure <lb/>kontra egin-a-z. <lb/>pain have.1SG&gt;2SG.ALLOC&gt;3SG and remorse you.GEN against do-DEF-INS <lb/>&apos;I feel pain and remorse that I have acted against you.&apos; <lb/>(Etxepare, 1545) <lb/>Another class, quite different from factive predicates, consists of predicates such as <lb/>gutitarik egin du or doi doiak egin du that expresses that something was very close to <lb/>happening but eventually did not (26). <lb/>(26) <lb/>Gutitarik egin zuen, <lb/>ez baitzioten <lb/>nearly <lb/>do <lb/>AUX.PST.3SG&gt;3SG NEG bait.AUX.PST.3PL&gt;3SG&lt;3SG <lb/>bertze-a-ri <lb/>zango-a moztu izan behar. <lb/>other-DEF-DAT leg-DEF cut <lb/>AUX <lb/>must <lb/>&apos;They almost had to cut his leg.&apos; <lb/>(Hiriart-Urruti, 1891-1914) <lb/></body>

        <page>662 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Krajewska <lb/></note>

        <body>Furthermore, in some texts, the bait-clause appears to be the complement of a noun, <lb/>e.g., of kausa &apos;reason&apos; (27). <lb/>(27) <lb/>baina bekatu-a izan da <lb/>kausa, gizon-a bothere hunez <lb/>but <lb/>sin-DEF <lb/>be <lb/>AUX.3SG reason man-DEF power DEM.INS <lb/>gabetu izan baita <lb/>deprive AUX bait.AUX.3SG <lb/>&apos;But the sin was the reason that the man was deprived of this power&apos; <lb/>(LeizarragaABC, 1571) <lb/>This appears to be a special case of a more general structure briefly described by <lb/>Lafitte (1991 [1944]: Section 770), who suggests that any verb can take complement <lb/>with bait-and the marker adds the sense of &apos;the fact that&apos;. In such cases, the sub-<lb/>ordinate clause is sometimes anticipated in the main clause by a demonstrative. In <lb/>(28), for example, we have the demonstrative haur &apos;this&apos;. In (29), on the other hand, <lb/>the main clause in the answer is elided. Such complements are also factive: as argued <lb/>by Kiparsky and Kiparsky (1970), factive predicates can be paraphrased with the fact <lb/>that (e.g., It&apos;s surprising that … → The fact that … is surprising). <lb/>(28) <lb/>Zer erhokeria da <lb/>haur, uste baitu <lb/>gizon hun-ek, <lb/>what madness be.3SG this think bait.AUX.3SG&gt;3SG man this-ERG <lb/>berretu-z <lb/>karga arindu-ko <lb/>zeikala? <lb/>increase-INS load <lb/>decrease-FUT AUX.COMP.3SG&lt;3SG <lb/>&apos;What is this madness, (the fact) that this man thinks that the load will <lb/>become lighter by increasing it?&apos; <lb/>(Axular, 1643) <lb/>(29) <lb/>Hon-en sortzi-a-k <lb/>zer <lb/>dü <lb/>bereberik? Grazia-n <lb/>DEM-GEN <lb/>birth-DEF-ERG <lb/>what AUX.3SG&gt;3SG special <lb/>grace.DEF-INES <lb/>sorthü baita. <lb/>be.born bait.AUX.PST.3SG <lb/>&apos;What is special about his birth? (The fact) that he was born in grace.&apos; <lb/>(Belapeire, 1696) <lb/>The final class are predicates of happening, such as gertatu or heldu &apos;happen&apos;. Con-<lb/>trary to emotive verbs, they appear already in the oldest texts (30). From the point of <lb/>view of semantics, when such predicates are used the formally subordinate clause <lb/>contains the foreground information (&apos;focal clause&apos; in terms of Dixon and Aikhenvald <lb/>[2009]) and the main clause only emphasizes the statement. They can be classified as <lb/>implicative verbs in the sense of Karttunen (1971a), that is, they imply the factivity of <lb/>the subordinate clause. Factive predicates also have this property: the difference is <lb/>that negated implicative verbs imply the negation of the complement (e.g., It <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">The diachrony of the Basque marker bait-<lb/></note>

        <page>663 <lb/></page>

        <body>happened that the poor one died → he died, but It did not happen that the poor one died <lb/>→ he did not die). <lb/>(30) <lb/>Gertha <lb/>zedin <lb/>bada hil baitzedin <lb/>paubre-a <lb/>happen.RAD AUX.AOR.3SG so <lb/>die bait.AUX.PST.3SG poor-DEF <lb/>&apos;So it happened that the poor one died&apos; <lb/>(LeizarragaTest, Luke 16: 22, 1571) 12 <lb/>Thus, complement clauses with bait-tend to express facts or attitude towards them <lb/>(Euskaltzaindia 1999: 1.3.6). This concords well with other uses of the marker. For <lb/>example, reason and result clauses are factually oriented, i.e., they typically express <lb/>something that has happened, as opposed to purpose clauses which express unre-<lb/>alized events (Hetterle 2015: 50-53; Thompson et al. 2007: 250-251). With regards <lb/>to reason clauses, Pérez Saldanya (2020: 591) observes that bait-is used in clauses <lb/>which are assertive or presupposed. Also, exclamatives can be seen as factive (see <lb/>Grimshaw 1979), as they can be paraphrased with a factive predicate (&quot;It&apos;s amazing <lb/>that …&quot;, &quot;I&apos;m surprised that&quot;). <lb/>Crosslinguistically, complement clauses tend to be embedded in the main <lb/>clause and thus occupy a grammatical slot in it. In Basque, it is the case with <lb/>complements with -ela. The situation is more complicated with bait-comple-<lb/>ments. Clearly, bait-complements are not easily omissible, which suggests tighter <lb/>integration with the main clause (as compared to, for example, reason clauses). <lb/>The order of clauses is fixed: -ela complements can precede or follow the <lb/>main clause, but complements with bait-can only occupy the second position <lb/>(Oyharçabal 1987: 249). In many cases, the clause with bait-is at the margin of the <lb/>main clause: in (28) the link between the clauses is established with the demon-<lb/>strative placed in the main clause which refers to the content of the subordinate <lb/>clause. However, in examples such as (22) the subordinate clause might be <lb/>analyzed as occupying the subject slot. Modern data (gathered in Norantz corpus <lb/>[Oyharçabal et al. 2009]) add interesting details to the issue: some speakers put <lb/>both clauses in single intonational phrase, but others place a break between the <lb/>two clauses (31), suggesting that bait-complements are not always embedded <lb/>even nowadays. <lb/>(31) <lb/>Domaia da / euri i-ten <lb/>baitu. <lb/>pity <lb/>is.3SG rain do-IPFV bait.AUX.3SG&gt;3SG <lb/>&apos;It&apos;s a pity that it is rainig.&apos; <lb/>(Norantz, C161-XLEAHA) <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">12 The French source: &quot;Or advint que le povre mourut&quot;. <lb/></note>

        <page>664 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Krajewska <lb/></note>

        <body>3 Diachronic changes in the use of bait-<lb/>Changes in the use of bait-were analyzed in the corpus described in Section 1. The <lb/>corpus was divided into four periods: (i) 1500-1600, (ii) 1600-1750, (iii) 1750-1900 and <lb/>(iv) 1900-1970. 13 <lb/>Since the earliest texts, i.e., the 16th century, the patterns of use of bait-have <lb/>changed: in the oldest texts bait-clauses are typically doubly marked, and bait-only <lb/>clauses are infrequent. In modern texts, the proportions are the opposite (Figure 2). 14 <lb/>At first sight, this could appear as a major change in subordination strategy. <lb/>However, it rather represents the preference of early Basque writers -and even <lb/>more so of translators -for the more explicit and more Romance-like constructions <lb/>(regardless of whether they were indeed borrowed from Romance, as argued by, e.g., <lb/>Figure 2: The proportions of the two kinds of clauses with bait-in the corpus. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">13 This classification follows the most widely accepted periodization of the language (see, e.g., <lb/>Lakarra et al. 2019), which is based on criteria related to language-internal factors and the most <lb/>influential landmarks in the history of the Basque literature. <lb/>14 A logistic regression analysis was performed with the kind of marking as the dependent variable <lb/>and the period as the independent variable (and text as random effect). The effect of period is <lb/>significant (χ 2 = 32, df = 3, p &lt; 0.001). Pairwise comparisons between the periods confirm that the <lb/>differences between the 2nd and 3rd and 3rd and 4th periods are significant. The details of all <lb/>statistical analyses can be found in the supplementary materials. <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">The diachrony of the Basque marker bait-<lb/></note>

        <page>665 <lb/></page>

        <body>Lafon 1999 [1973]). In fact, in the few early texts which are not translations, the <lb/>proportion of bait-only clauses tends to be higher, as shown in Figure 3, which plots <lb/>the proportion of bait-only clauses for all texts in the corpus. In general (Figure 4), <lb/>the proportion of clauses with a conjunction is systematically higher in translations <lb/>and doctrines than in original texts in all periods. 15 <lb/>Figure 3: The proportion of bait-only clauses in the texts in the corpus (the texts are ordered <lb/>chronologically, from the oldest on the left). <lb/>Figure 4: Clauses with bait-in original versus non-original texts. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">15 A logistic regression analysis was performed with the kind of marking as the dependent variable <lb/>and the period and text genre as the independent variables (and text as random effect). The effect of <lb/>genre is significant (χ 2 = 16.7, df = 1, p &lt; 0.001). <lb/></note>

        <page>666 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Krajewska <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 5 plots relative frequencies (per 1,000 words) of all examples with bait-<lb/>and separately for the two types of clauses, bait-only and bait-with an additional <lb/>element. It can be seen that the relative frequency of the marker is much lower in <lb/>modern texts. This is caused by a sharp decrease in the use of clauses where bait-<lb/>appears with a conjunction or a relative pronoun. However, the relative frequency of <lb/>bait-only clauses increased in the late 19th century. 16 <lb/>As regards bait-only clauses, nowadays the most common type is reason. <lb/>However, in historical sources the situation is different. Table 1 presents the pro-<lb/>portions of the following types of clauses: complement, relative, result, reason, <lb/>clauses ambiguous between relative and reason and all other clauses (i.e., bait-in <lb/>independent clauses). The number of examples for the 16th century is low, but <lb/>complement clauses in this period are very frequent. However, this is caused by the <lb/>high incidence of &apos;happen&apos; verbs with bait-complements in the translation of the <lb/>New Testament, which is the most extensive source for this period. In the second <lb/>period, for which we have much more data, the most prominent functions of bait-are <lb/>relative and reason, but other functions are also quite common (except for the result, <lb/>Figure 5: The relative frequency (per 1,000 words) of all types of bait-clauses together, and bait-only <lb/>clauses and those with a conjunction separately. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">16 Three negative binomial regression models were fitted with the period as the independent <lb/>variable and the count of (a) all bait-clause, (b) bait-only clauses and (c) clauses with conjunction or <lb/>pronoun (controlling for the length of the text in each case). The results show that the effect of period <lb/>is significant in all models. <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">The diachrony of the Basque marker bait-<lb/></note>

        <page>667 <lb/></page>

        <body>which is, generally speaking, infrequent). An interesting detail is that clauses <lb/>ambiguous between relative and reason are particularly frequent in this period. The <lb/>reason reading starts to be dominant in the third period (with around half of the <lb/>examples expressing reason). This tendency becomes even more pronounced in the <lb/>most recent texts, where 64 % of all bait-only clauses are of that type. <lb/>Turning to complement clauses, they are not very frequent overall. Neverthe-<lb/>less, as regards the types of predicates, we can tentatively say that a change in <lb/>preference occurred between the earliest and the newest sources. Table 2 provides <lb/>the proportions of verbs of happening, complements of nouns (together with &apos;the fact <lb/>that&apos; constructions) and factive emotive verbs. The latter type is not attested with <lb/>bait-in the earliest sources, but they predominate since the 19th century. <lb/>4 The hypothetical link between bait-and bai &apos;yes&apos; <lb/>Lafon (1999 [1966]) mentions several times that there is a relationship between bai <lb/>and bait and he suggests that the initial function of bait-was to emphasize affir-<lb/>mation (1999 [1966]: 667, 683). However, the exact nature of this connection is never <lb/>clearly spelled out. The question is if and how an affirmative adverb can turn into a <lb/>marker of subordination. Cross-linguistically, some classes of words tend to gram-<lb/>maticalize as markers of subordination (e.g., demonstratives or pronouns), but <lb/>affirmative adverbs are not among them (Givón 2009: chap. 5; Heine and Kuteva 2002: <lb/>Table : Proportions of the various types of bait-only clauses. <lb/>Period <lb/>Tokens <lb/>Comp. <lb/>Rel. <lb/>Result <lb/>Reason <lb/>Rel./reason <lb/>Other <lb/>- <lb/> <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/> . <lb/>  . <lb/> . <lb/>  . <lb/>- <lb/> <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/> . <lb/>  . <lb/>  . <lb/>  . <lb/>- <lb/> <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/> . <lb/>  . <lb/> . <lb/> . <lb/>- <lb/> <lb/>. <lb/> . <lb/> . <lb/>  . <lb/> . <lb/>  . <lb/>Table : Frequencies of different types of predicates taking bait-complements (in percentages). <lb/>Period <lb/>Tokens <lb/>&apos;happen&apos; <lb/>Noun compl. <lb/>Emotive <lb/>- <lb/> <lb/>. <lb/>  . <lb/> . <lb/>- <lb/> <lb/>. <lb/>  . <lb/>  . <lb/>- <lb/> <lb/>. <lb/>  . <lb/>  . <lb/>- <lb/> <lb/>. <lb/> . <lb/>  . <lb/></body>

        <page>668 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Krajewska <lb/></note>

        <body>113-114, 335; Heine and Kuteva 2007: sec. 5.3.1; Hendery 2012: 2.2; Kuteva et al. 2019: <lb/>476-477), though Hendery (2012: 66-71) discusses several discourse markers which <lb/>were source of a relative clause marker (including the Basque bait-). An interesting <lb/>parallel is that of South Slavic languages which use the complementizer da, which is <lb/>also the affirmative particle &apos;yes&apos; in many Slavic languages (Wiemer 2019). The <lb/>particle da was used first with optative or hortative function (Wiemer 2019: 120), and <lb/>in Old Church Slavonic it was already employed as a clause-initial particle in a wide <lb/>range of clauses, and &quot;its function was associated with unrealized states of affairs&quot; <lb/>(Wiemer 2019: 121). Wiemer (2019) argues that the in first stage of the development of <lb/>the complementizer there were two juxtaposed clauses, with da in the second. In this <lb/>context, the function of the particle was reanalyzed as a subordinator, and the <lb/>relation between the clauses became asymmetrical. The reconstruction of de-<lb/>velopments in Basque presented here differs in semantic details but implies a similar <lb/>process of increasing clausal integration. More generally, as shown by Hopper and <lb/>Traugott (2003: Ch. 7), many subordinate structures grammaticalize along the path <lb/>from parataxis (independent clauses) to hypotaxis (interdependency) to subordi-<lb/>nation (understood as embedding). <lb/>The process of which the endpoint is the subordinator bait-as used in the <lb/>modern language can be seen as an example of grammaticalization. First, the <lb/>affirmative bai emerged from its lexical source and acquired various grammatical <lb/>functions. Then the marker bait-developed from bai and underwent further changes <lb/>in which it acquired even more grammatical function (&apos;secondary grammaticaliza-<lb/>tion&apos;). Since the oldest texts, bait-functions as a subordinator with a wide range of <lb/>functions, but it has been proposed for various languages that this situation is the <lb/>endpoint of a series of extensions from one clause type to another (see examples in <lb/>Hendery [2012: Section 2.2.8]). <lb/>The goal of the remainder of this article is to try to reconstruct the details of the <lb/>process. The discussion is going to be speculative in part, as most of the processes in <lb/>question took place before the earliest texts. Nevertheless, a careful analysis of <lb/>textual evidence is crucial. One of the most prominent features of grammaticaliza-<lb/>tion is &apos;persistence&apos; (or &apos;source determination&apos; in Bybee et al. [1994: 15]), or the <lb/>adherence of the original lexical meaning, which might determine the grammatical <lb/>distribution of the grammaticalized element (Hopper 1991). As put by Bybee et al. <lb/>(1994: 18), &quot;we find that multiple uses and the retention of lexical specificities can be <lb/>employed as diagnostics of the earlier history of grammatical material, even in <lb/>languages for which historical attestation is sparse or nonexistent&quot;. <lb/>The view presented here is not completely different from Lafon&apos;s (1999 [1966]) <lb/>explanations of the various uses of bait-. The main difference is that Lafon tried to <lb/>link all of the functions of the prefix to the affirmative meaning of bai. What I propose <lb/>here is that the subordinator cannot go back to an affirmative adverb, but rather to <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">The diachrony of the Basque marker bait-<lb/></note>

        <page>669 <lb/></page>

        <body>the anaphoric function of bai. Thus, bai &apos;yes&apos; and bait-are related to each other, not <lb/>because the latter developed from the former, but because both share a common <lb/>source. Based on textual evidence, I will show that bai can be considered a manner <lb/>expression with anaphoric functions. 17 There are two arguments in favor of this idea, <lb/>which I discuss in Section 4.1: (1) the etymology of bai is compatible with this pro-<lb/>posal, and (2) bai has or had functions typical of grammaticalization paths of manner <lb/>deictics. Then, in Section 4.2, I will focus on the development of bait-and the further <lb/>stages of its grammaticalization: introduction in subordinate clauses, extension and <lb/>generalization to more types of clauses and appearance of more tightly integrated <lb/>structures. <lb/>4.1 Etymology and functions of bai <lb/>According to Trask (1997: 209), &quot;The word bai &apos;yes&apos; is doubtless related to the affir-<lb/>mative morph ba-, as in badator &apos;he/she&apos;s coming&apos;, formerly &apos;he/she is coming&apos;; bai <lb/>may well be an ancient verb-form, along the lines of &apos;it is so&apos;, possibly involving the <lb/>root -di-of the archaic verb *edin&quot;. Lakarra (2018: 158) elaborated on this idea sug-<lb/>gesting that the underlying verb form is *badadi, a form of the participle *edin <lb/>&apos;become&apos; and copular verb (subjunctive of &apos;be&apos; in the modern language). It would <lb/>mean something like &apos;it is (so)&apos; or &apos;let it be&apos;. The prefix ba-could have functions similar <lb/>to those it performs in the modern language: reinforcing finite verbs in clause initial <lb/>positions and emphasizing affirmation. The affirmative function of bai might have <lb/>appeared very early, but it is not the only function the particle has had. It seems <lb/>possible that it came to be used as a kind of a manner expression, with the meaning of <lb/>&apos;so, as, thus, this way&apos;. <lb/>This explanation has parallels in other languages: items with discourse functions <lb/>frequently derive from verb forms. For instance, Bourdin (2008) analyzes gram-<lb/>maticalization of &apos;go&apos; and &apos;come&apos; into textual connectives and, in particular, devices <lb/>expressing consequence of the previous discourse, or to the contrary, expressing <lb/>something unexpected. Also several emphatic affirmative expressions similar to the <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">17 More recently, the idea that bait-is grammaticalized from a manner deictic is presented in Pérez <lb/>Saldanya (2020), who, as regards the development of bait-, accepts the ideas discussed in Krajewska <lb/>(2017). Pérez Saldanya focuses on causal clauses with bait-and shows interesting parallels with <lb/>grammaticalization processes that occurred in Romance and Latin, which provide additional support <lb/>for the hypothesis linking bait-with the manner expression. Additionally, Pérez Saldanya (2020) <lb/>points out to the fact that the grammaticalization of si proceeded further in Occitan than in Spanish. <lb/>Thus, as he suggests, the differences between Basque dialects might be related to different contact <lb/>situations: Eastern varieties, traditionally in contact with Occitan varieties retained and extended the <lb/>use of bait-, while the Western varieties lost the marker. <lb/></note>

        <page>670 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Krajewska <lb/></note>

        <body>reconstructed Basque phrase can be mentioned: Spanish (que) así sea &apos;let it be so&apos;, así <lb/>es &apos;it is so&apos; or French ainsi soit-il &apos;let it be so&apos;. Pérez Saldanya (2020) provides inter-<lb/>esting parallels between bai, bait-and the prefix ba-and Latin and Occitan-Catalan <lb/>forms. In Latin, the conditional si comes from the manner expression sīc (which in <lb/>turn was reinforced as acsīc, which gave way to manner deictics in some modern <lb/>Romance languages, e.g., Spanish así &apos;this way&apos;). <lb/>Moreover, other grammatical words in Basque can be explained through a <lb/>grammaticalization of the verb *edin, e.g., baino &apos;than&apos; or baina &apos;but&apos; (Lakarra 2018: <lb/>109). Another particle, in a way more closely related to bai, is bada &apos;so, thus&apos;. The <lb/>source of this particle could well be ba-da with the emphatic-affirmative ba and 3sg <lb/>form of izan &apos;be&apos;. It would, thus, initially mean something like &apos;it is so (indeed)&apos;. If the <lb/>source of bai was indeed a form or the verb *edin, such as *ba-dadi, bai and bada <lb/>would have very similar sources (though probably different chronologies, bada being <lb/>more recent). <lb/>König (2015: 41) examines manner deictic elements (such as so, this way, like) and <lb/>various grammaticalization paths they typically move along and argues that renewal <lb/>of manner deictic elements is very common. In many languages, the exophoric <lb/>function is often lost: in English, for example, so, such or thus are rarely used <lb/>exophorically, and this way or like this are employed instead. Partial renewal also <lb/>took place, for instance, in Italian (ecco + si became così). <lb/>Anaphoric and cataphoric use develop from exophoric use: instead of pointing <lb/>to the external world, deictic elements start to indicate parts of the discourse. As <lb/>explained by König (2015: 43), manner deictics may develop into propositional <lb/>anaphors and have whole clauses as antecedents, e.g., The meeting has been post-<lb/>poned? I suppose so. Anaphoric deictics can also turn into connectives expressing <lb/>different circumstantial relations, e.g., causal (I didn&apos;t like it, so I wrote to him.), <lb/>concessive (John is very sick. Even so he goes to work) or conditional. Another well-<lb/>documented change involving cataphoric demonstratives is the development of <lb/>quotative markers (Güldemann 2008). Manner deictics are also frequently found in <lb/>other grammatical markers, which are especially relevant for the discussion of <lb/>Basque data: affirmative particles, additive markers, comparative markers and <lb/>subordinators. <lb/>As regards affirmative particles, according to König (2015), <lb/>Affirmative particles typically derive from manner deictics. In the languages under discussion <lb/>Italian si and French si (after negative questions) derive straightforwardly from the Latin <lb/>manner deictic sic. English yes is the result of a fusion between yeah and swa and Polish tak <lb/>means both &apos;so&apos; and &apos;yes&apos;. Moreover, narratives can be confirmed by expressions like So ist es <lb/>(German) or It must have been so and prayers, wishes and plans for the future by phrases like So <lb/>be it or Ainsi soit-il (French) in a wide variety of languages (König 2015: 44). <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">The diachrony of the Basque marker bait-<lb/></note>

        <page>671 <lb/></page>

        <body>The Basque bai has been used as an affirmative adverb &apos;yes&apos; in answer to a question <lb/>since the earliest texts. It can also reinforce affirmation (32), emphasize an opposition <lb/>to a previous negation (33) or function as an adversative conjunction (34) (OEH s.v. <lb/>bai). <lb/>(32) <lb/>Eta harekin ioai-ten ziraden <lb/>gizon-ak, geldi <lb/>zitezen <lb/>and he.COM go-IPFV AUX.PST.3PL man-DEF.PL stay-RAD AUX.AOR.3PL <lb/>izitu-rik, <lb/>haren boza bai enzu-ten, baina nehor <lb/>ikus-ten <lb/>frighten-PART his <lb/>voice yes hear-IPFV but <lb/>nobody see-IPFV <lb/>e-tzute-la. <lb/>NEG-AUX.PST.3PL&gt;3SG-COMP <lb/>&apos;And the men who were going with him got frightened, they did hear his <lb/>voice, but they saw nobody.&apos; <lb/>(LeizarragaTest, Acts 9: 7, 1571) 18 <lb/>(33) <lb/>Bada baldin adultera-tzen <lb/>ez-pa-duk, <lb/>baina <lb/>So <lb/>if <lb/>commit.adultery-IPFV NEG-COND-AUX.2SG&gt;3SG but <lb/>hil-tzen bai, Lege-a-ren transgredizale egin aiz. <lb/>kill-IPFV yes law-DEF-GEN transgressor <lb/>make AUX.2SG <lb/>&apos;For, if you do not commit adultery, but you do kill, you have thus become a <lb/>transgressor of the Law.&apos; <lb/>(LeizarragaTest, James 2: 11, 1571) 19 <lb/>(34) <lb/>zuiek <lb/>ukhen baituzuie <lb/>hezaz guti ansia. / Bai erhoki <lb/>you.ERG have bait.AUX.2PL&gt;3SG DEM.INS little care <lb/>but madly <lb/>konplazitu ene kontra etsai-a <lb/>please <lb/>my against enemy-DEF <lb/>&apos;you did not care too much for him at all, but instead you madly pleased <lb/>against me the enemy&apos; <lb/>(Etxepare, 1545) <lb/>The Basque bai can also be used in various coordinating-additive constructions. <lb/>According to König (2015: 45), &quot;(…) anaphorically used manner demonstratives <lb/>develop into additive focus markers (Engl. also, Fr. aussi, Germ. ebenso, Swed. også, <lb/>Russ. takže) and further into coordinating conjunctions&quot;. Moreover, bai also signals <lb/>ellipsis, usually of the verbal phrase. This is similar to the behavior of the English so <lb/>(John is writing a book and so is MARY) or the French aussi (König 2015: 45). <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">18 The French source: &quot;Or les hommes que cheminoyent avec luy, s&apos;arresterent estonnez, oyans bien la <lb/>voiz d&apos;iceluy, mais ne voyans personne&quot;. <lb/>19 The French source: &quot;Si donc tu n&apos;es point adultere, mais tu tues, tu es transgresseur de la Loy&quot;. <lb/></note>

        <page>672 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Krajewska <lb/></note>

        <body>While it is not very common, the particle bai on its own can be used as a <lb/>conjunction meaning &apos;as well as, and also&apos;: <lb/>(35) <lb/>Cec <lb/>ecarri çaitu <lb/>orain decreto-a egui-te-ra, <lb/>bay <lb/>what.ERG bring AUX.3SG&gt;2SG now order-DEF make-NMLZ-ADL yes <lb/>Vizcaya yl-te-ra? <lb/>Biscay kill-NMLZ-ADL <lb/>&apos;What has brought you now to give orders and kill Biscay?&apos; <lb/>(1688, Lakarra 1984) <lb/>Another group of constructions involves eta &apos;and&apos; and ere &apos;also&apos; apart from bai. For <lb/>example, bai is used in elliptical affirmative clauses together with the additive par-<lb/>ticle ere &apos;also&apos;. Bai is not obligatory, but there is a tendency to use it: <lb/>(36) <lb/>Zuk <lb/>badakizu <lb/>eta ni-k ere (bai) <lb/>you-ERG know.2SG&gt;3SG and I-ERG also yes <lb/>&apos;You know and I do too&apos; (Hualde 2003: 327) <lb/>Importantly, bai cannot be used when there is no verbal ellipsis. This suggests that <lb/>rather than expressing addition, bai signals that a part of the verb phrase was elided: <lb/>(37) <lb/>joan-go da <lb/>eta ni ere bai <lb/>go-FUT <lb/>AUX.3SG and I also yes <lb/>&apos;She will go, and me too&apos; <lb/>(38) <lb/>*joan-go da <lb/>eta ni ere bai joan-go naiz <lb/>go-FUT <lb/>AUX.3SG and I also yes go-FUT <lb/>AUX.1SG <lb/>&apos;She will go, and I will go too&apos; <lb/>Interestingly, verbal ellipsis is also frequent in the emphatic use of bai discussed <lb/>earlier (as in Examples (32), (33) and (34)). <lb/>Furthermore, there is bai eta, which means &apos;and also&apos; (39). It is frequently con-<lb/>tracted to baita, but it is attested in its full form (e.g., baieta ere in Etxepare). In <lb/>modern Basque it is usually reinforced with the particle ere (OEH s.v. baita). How-<lb/>ever, there are numerous examples in texts without it. <lb/>(39) <lb/>Iainko-a <lb/>bera <lb/>ere Saindu dei-tzen da <lb/>baieta <lb/>haren <lb/>god-DEF <lb/>himself also saint <lb/>call-IPFV AUX.3SG and.also his <lb/>Aingeru-ak <lb/>angels-DEF.PL <lb/>&apos;God himself is also called saint, and also his angels&apos; <lb/>(LeizarragaTest, Dictionary, 1571) <lb/>Finally, in the oldest texts we find bai as standard marker in equative constructions <lb/>(Lafon 1999 [1957]: 651-652). Equatives express equal extent and often consist of the <lb/>following elements (Haspelmath and Buchholz 1998: 279): <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">The diachrony of the Basque marker bait-<lb/></note>

        <page>673 <lb/></page>

        <body>(40) <lb/>My sister is as <lb/>tall <lb/>as <lb/>you <lb/>CMP <lb/>PAM PARA STM STAN <lb/>CMP -comparee, PAM -parameter marker, PARA -parameter, STM -<lb/>standard marker, STAN -standard <lb/>In many languages equatives are similar to similative constructions, which express <lb/>equal manner, e.g., He sings like a nightingale (Haspelmath and Buchholz 1998: 313). <lb/>According to König (2015: 50), manner (or, more precisely, degree) demonstratives <lb/>are used frequently as degree markers (German so gross wie Karl &apos;as tall as Karl&apos;), but <lb/>sometimes also as standard markers (or both: as tall as Charles; as &lt; alswa &apos;quite so&apos;). <lb/>In 16th-century Basque texts, bai is occasionally encountered as a standard <lb/>marker in equative (41) and similative constructions (42). According to OEH, this use <lb/>is not attested in any other text afterward. <lb/>(41) <lb/>Egundano izan daia <lb/>ni bai ditxa-tako-rik? <lb/>till.today be <lb/>AUX.3SG.QUEST I bai luck-RM-PART <lb/>&apos;Has there been anyone as unlucky as I am?&apos; <lb/>(Etxepare, 1545) <lb/>(42) <lb/>Elias zen <lb/>gu bai pasion-en <lb/>suiektione-tako gizon-a <lb/>Elias be.PST.3SG we as passion-GEN.PL subject-RM <lb/>man-DEF <lb/>&apos;Elias was a man subject to passions as we are&apos; <lb/>(LeizarragaTest, James 5: 17, 1571) 20 <lb/>To conclude the discussion of the functions of bai, we can say that it appears or <lb/>appeared in several contexts in which manner deictic elements tend to be found <lb/>according to König (2015): as affirmative particle, additive marker and standard <lb/>marker. Though bai is not morphologically related to demonstratives (hau &apos;this&apos;, hori <lb/>&apos;that&apos;, etc.), taking into account its etymology -*badadi &apos;it is (so)&apos;, &apos;let it be (so)&apos; -it <lb/>does not seem impossible that in the process of grammaticalization, it acquired <lb/>anaphoric functions. This could happen because *badadi, uttered in response to a <lb/>question, refers back to the content of that utterance, and even though there is no <lb/>overt deictic element, it contains a zero anaphor. <lb/>4.2 From bai to bait-<lb/>In this section, I will put forward several hypotheses on how the marker bait-<lb/>emerged and became a subordinator. The reconstruction proposed here for Basque <lb/>can be divided in various stages, which are represented in Figure 6. In what follows, I <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">20 The French source: &quot;Elie estoit homme suiet à semblables passions que nous&quot;. <lb/></note>

        <page>674 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Krajewska <lb/></note>

        <body>will first focus on the development of the marker from the manner expression. Then I <lb/>will try to explain how bait-started to be used in complex constructions and was <lb/>eventually reanalyzed as a subordinator. <lb/>4.2.1 Development of bait-<lb/>The first question is how bait-developed from bai. Concerning the morphology of <lb/>bait-, voiceless stops in final position are secondary in Basque and typically result <lb/>from the apocope of the final vowel, which then triggers the devoicing of the final <lb/>consonant if it is voiced (Mitxelena 2011 [1977]: 6.1, 6.4, 12.10). This suggests that the <lb/>marker had some additional material. <lb/>The first possibility could be the following: bait-&lt; *baita &lt; bai &apos;yes, thus&apos; + eta <lb/>&apos;and&apos;. This possibility is supported by the existence of a few conjunctions with eta, for <lb/>example, zein eta &apos;which, that, as&apos; or zeren eta &apos;because&apos;. The addition of eta, at least in <lb/>historical sources, does not seem to alter the meaning of the conjunction. An argu-<lb/>ment possibly against this idea is related to the existence of the particle baita &apos;and <lb/>also&apos; (attested as bai eta as well), mentioned earlier. As pointed out by Etxepare (2001, <lb/>2021) bait-and baita are different in that baita &apos;and also&apos; does not have baist-or beit-<lb/>variants. However, as shown by Padilla-Moyano (2017: 703), the Souletin variant beit-<lb/>Figure 6: Map of proposed extensions of bai and bait-. Subordinate clauses are marked with light gray <lb/>color. <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">The diachrony of the Basque marker bait-<lb/></note>

        <page>675 <lb/></page>

        <body>is rather recent. The lack of form with the sibilant could mean that the particle baita <lb/>is more recent than the subordination prefix. Nevertheless, given that the renewal of <lb/>such markers is a common process, this is not necessarily a reason to reject this <lb/>hypothesis. <lb/>Another possibility is that bait-comes from bai and that -t-is simply an effect of <lb/>being placed frequently before d-and z-starting verbs. Such an explanation was put <lb/>forward by Lafitte (1991 [1944]), according to whom the consonant -t-can be <lb/>explained through reinforcement of -d-and -z-after diphthongs (Lafitte 1991 [1944]: <lb/>Section 405), but the parallels he gave are rather marginal, and the explanation does <lb/>not appear very likely. Nevertheless, there are varieties (e.g., the now extinct <lb/>Roncalese), where the prefix appears to be bai, rather than bait-(Mitxelena 2011 <lb/>[1954]: 643), but it is unclear whether it is secondary (reinterpreting the marker as <lb/>bai-) or is an archaism. <lb/>Finally, the final consonant might come from the copula: bait-&lt; *baida &lt; bai + da <lb/>3sg of izan &apos;be&apos;. As mentioned, manner deictics show a tendency for renewal (König <lb/>2015: 41-42). Adding another finite copular verb form to bai would be an example of <lb/>partial renewal. <lb/>Tentatively we can say that the last explanation appears the least problematic. <lb/>Pérez Saldanya (2020) mentions the first and the second hypotheses and concludes <lb/>that both are possible, but the first appears simpler because it allows explaining the <lb/>development of bait-starting directly from bai. However, if bait-emerged through <lb/>partial renewal, the explanation can also be based on what we know about bai, <lb/>because we might assume that the newer form would inherit functions and prop-<lb/>erties of the older form. In any case, the starting point would be bai, a manner <lb/>expression, which functioned as an affirmation marker and as a focus particle (at <lb/>least as an additive focus particle and standard marker). Then, its reinforced form <lb/>emerged: bait. Initially, it would have functions similar to the older variant, <lb/>i.e., manner deictic and focus particle. <lb/>4.2.2 Indefinite pronouns and bait-plus conjunction/pronoun clauses <lb/>In a subsequent stage, the particle bait-started to appear in complex constructions, <lb/>initially as a focus particle, not a marker of subordination. It was placed in the second <lb/>position of the clause, similarly to the particles ere and eta (as in the already <lb/>mentioned conjunction zeren eta &apos;because&apos;). An early construction with bait could be <lb/>the one that brought the emergence of indefinite pronouns in -bait. As explained, the <lb/>subordinating bait-is found in the northern and eastern varieties of Basque (with a <lb/>few exceptions), but the series of pronouns in -bait is general. Thus, we can hy-<lb/>pothesize that pronouns developed earlier than the subordinator. Etxepare (2001) <lb/></body>

        <page>676 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Krajewska <lb/></note>

        <body>proposed that the source of the pronouns was a free relative clause (the &quot;it may be&quot; <lb/>type in Haspelmath [1997]): <lb/>(43) <lb/>nor baita &gt; norbaita &gt; norbait <lb/>who bait.be.3SG <lb/>&apos;who is&apos; &gt; &apos;someone&apos; <lb/>Forms with the final -a, which provide evidence for this idea, are attested, as noted by <lb/>Etxepare (2001): e.g., we find cerbayta &apos;something&apos; in 1537. Additionally, there are <lb/>very few instances where bait-remains an independent particle, e.g., nork bait in the <lb/>poems by the 16th-century author Bernard Etxepare with the interrogative pronoun <lb/>in the ergative case (it later became norbaitek, externalizing the inflection). <lb/>Alternatively, also building on Haspelmath (1997), we could start from the so-<lb/>called &apos;parametric concessive conditional clause&apos;, illustrated in (44). The concessive <lb/>clause might then be grammaticalized into an indefinite pronoun, (e.g., in French qui <lb/>que ce soit &apos;anyone&apos;). Haspelmath (1997: 137) lists the following characteristics of this <lb/>type of clause: (a) the verb is typically in some kind of subjunctive, (b) focus particles <lb/>such as &apos;also, even&apos; are often present, (c) there might be a conditional marker, (d) a <lb/>pleonastic negator, (e) additional general subordinator, or (f) an emphatic particle. <lb/>(44) <lb/>You can take something, whatever it may be (concessive conditional) <lb/>The concessive clause which could be the source of indefinite pronouns (45) is <lb/>attested in texts (47), though typically with the particle ere. This scenario also allows <lb/>the inclusion of the baista variant in the argument (46). Etxepare (2001) mentions <lb/>that the fricative could be a reflex of ez &apos;no&apos; (the laminal sibilant, &lt;z&gt;, is likely to <lb/>become apical, &lt;s&gt;, before /t/), 21 but does not find an explanation for it. However, as <lb/>argued by Haspelmath, pleonastic negators are common in that kind of clause. <lb/>(45) <lb/>zer <lb/>bait da &gt; zerbait(a) <lb/>what bait is <lb/>&apos;whatever is&apos; &gt; &apos;something&apos; <lb/>(46) <lb/>zer <lb/>bait ez da &gt; zerbaist(a) <lb/>what bait NEG is <lb/>&apos;whatever is (not)&apos; &gt; &apos;something&apos; <lb/>(47) <lb/>Zer e[re] baita, <lb/>eduki-ko-ren dut <lb/>kontu jaki-te-ra. <lb/>what PTCL bait.be.3SG have-FUT-FUT AUX.1SG&gt;3SG care know-NMLZ-ADL <lb/>&apos;Whatever it might be, I will take care to find out.&apos; <lb/>(1595, Orpustan 2010) <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">21 An alternative solution, proposed by Lafon (1999 [1966]: 683), is to link the sibilant to the <lb/>instrumental case. <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">The diachrony of the Basque marker bait-<lb/></note>

        <page>677 <lb/></page>

        <body>Moreover, if -s-in baist goes back to the negative marker, it must have been added <lb/>before bait-became a verbal prefix, because it is placed between bait-and the verb <lb/>(the modern order would be negation-bait-verb and not bait-negation-verb). This <lb/>order would be possible if bait was a particle linked to the interrogative pronoun. <lb/>Thus, we can propose that initially in these concessive clauses bait-was not a fully-<lb/>fledged subordinator, but rather a particle with a focus function. This is convenient: <lb/>it is simpler to think that the subordinator did not fully develop in Western varieties <lb/>than to think it was lost there and was only maintained elsewhere. <lb/>It is difficult to decide whether the departure point for the grammaticalization of <lb/>indefinite pronouns was a relative or a concessive construction. As pointed out by <lb/>Haspelmath and König (1998: 577), in many languages both exhibit similar structure <lb/>and change from one to another can occur (the change from concessive to relative <lb/>implies, among others, a tighter integration: contrary to concessive clauses, free <lb/>relatives occupy a slot in the main clause). <lb/>The use of the focus particle also extended to other kinds of clauses: it appeared <lb/>after a conjunction or an interrogative pronoun in the second position of the clause. <lb/>It did not mark subordination, but frequent usage turned it into the unmarked option <lb/>and, since it often happened to be placed before the finite verb, it cliticized to the verb <lb/>and was eventually reinterpreted as a subordinator. This process proceeded only to a <lb/>limited extent in the western dialects, where bait-/baist-is attested only a few times <lb/>in correlative structures (48) In eastern/northern varieties, we find a broader range <lb/>of clauses: relative and adverbial. In such clauses, a subordinator (-en or bait-) 22 is <lb/>obligatory in the modern language, though in the older texts some types of clauses, <lb/>e.g., those with zeren &apos;because&apos; appear sometimes without any subordinator. <lb/>(48) <lb/>Zelan-go-a baista <lb/>ame-a <lb/>alan-go-a <lb/>oi <lb/>da <lb/>how-RM-DEF bait.be.3SG mother-DEF such-RM-DEF usually be.3SG <lb/>alabe-a <lb/>daughter-DEF <lb/>&apos;Such mother, such daughter&apos; <lb/>(1596, Lakarra 1996) <lb/>4.2.3 Discourse function and bait-only clauses <lb/>Parallel to these developments, but probably only in the northern/eastern varieties, <lb/>bait-acquired the function of a clause-level discourse particle, along the lines of <lb/>Fraser&apos;s (1988: 21-22) definition: discourse particles &quot;signal a comment specifying the <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">22 It is impossible to know which of them, bait-or -en, is older. If it is -en (which is used in all dialects), <lb/>then bait-could replace it in some contexts. <lb/></note>

        <page>678 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Krajewska <lb/></note>

        <body>type of sequential discourse relationship that holds between the current utterance -<lb/>the utterance of which the discourse marker is a part -and the prior discourse&quot;. The <lb/>particle, which did not necessarily appear in subordinate clauses, would express <lb/>meanings related to consequence, contrast and emphasis. It was placed before the <lb/>finite verb, as it is the typical position for particles in Basque, such as the modal <lb/>particles omen &apos;hearsay information&apos; or bide &apos;apparently&apos; (Hualde and Ortiz de <lb/>Urbina 2003: 316). The use of bait-in independent clauses is attested since the oldest <lb/>texts (see Examples (13) and (14)) and its reflex is also found in the archaic al-bait-<lb/>prefix (see (18)). The presence of bait-in exclamatives might also be related to this <lb/>function. 23 <lb/>Finally, we have bait-only subordinate clauses (relative, reason, result or <lb/>complement). The presence of bait-in these constructions can be linked to the <lb/>manner deictic, but the discourse marker function of bait-could also influence the <lb/>use of bait-in such clauses. <lb/>In the oldest texts, as shown earlier, bait-only clauses perform already very <lb/>diverse functions, but relatives appear to be the most frequent type. Furthermore, <lb/>relative clauses are the basis of old place names with bait-(Salaberri Zaratiegi 1996), <lb/>which suggests that the use of the marker in such clauses is quite old, and it could be a <lb/>candidate for the initial stage of the extension of the marker. Deictic elements, such as <lb/>demonstratives, are suitable as markers of relative constructions because of their <lb/>capability to refer back to a referent in the previous discourse (Heine and Kuteva 2002, <lb/>2007; Hendery 2012; Kuteva et al. 2019). Also, manner deictics can appear in relative <lb/>clauses, as shown by König (2015: 52). The particle bai has anaphoric functions, and, <lb/>thus, if bait-developed from it, its use in relative constructions is not surprising. <lb/>Turning to adverbial clauses, cross-linguistically, manner words can be found in <lb/>consequence clauses or reason clauses. According to Kortmann (1998) in European <lb/>languages, the most common source construction for the expression of cause is <lb/>temporal followed by manner. König (2015; 2020) lists various adverbial relations as <lb/>possible extensions of manner deictics. <lb/>As regards Basque, reason clauses appear already in the oldest texts, but they <lb/>became the most prominent function of the marker only later. The presence of bait-<lb/>in these clauses can be explained in two ways and both possibly contributed to the <lb/>increase of their frequency. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">23 As noted by a reviewer, independent uses of bait-could emerge via insubordination. This <lb/>explanation cannot be ruled out completely as both independent and subordinate uses of the marker <lb/>are attested already in the oldest texts. However, the insubordination analysis appears problematic <lb/>because it is not clear what kind of construction(s) could be the source. For exclamatives, factive <lb/>complements could be suitable, but texts suggest that such complements are rather recent. <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">The diachrony of the Basque marker bait-<lb/></note>

        <page>679 <lb/></page>

        <body>The first one starts from accord/comment clauses like (12), with bait-in the first <lb/>clause, which refers to the background information or, more generally, links what is <lb/>to be said in the main clause to the previous discourse (compare English as in e.g., As I <lb/>have mentioned …). It is possible to strengthen this meaning to reason: from <lb/>something like &apos;so you have said that … &apos; to &apos;since you have said … &apos;. The gramma-<lb/>ticalization of manner expressions (such as the Romance conjunctions derived from <lb/>the Latin quōmodo or the English as) into causal conjunctions tends to start precisely <lb/>in such a context, where the clause containing the manner expression appears as the <lb/>topic at the margin of the main clause (Pérez Saldanya 2020: 594; Pérez-Saldanya and <lb/>Hualde 2017). <lb/>The second route goes from relative clauses to reason. 24 Many examples with <lb/>bait-are ambiguous between these two meanings, especially in the 17th-18th cen-<lb/>turies, just before the sharp increase in the proportion of reason clauses. The am-<lb/>biguity happens when a participant appears both in the subordinate and the main <lb/>clause, as in (49). Taking into account relative and reason clauses (including <lb/>ambiguous ones), 26 out of 27 clauses in the 16th century and 83 % in the second <lb/>period have co-referential participants in the main and subordinate clauses. This <lb/>proportion is 77 % in the third period and 60 % in the most recent data. 25 Thus, the <lb/>ambiguous clauses may provide a bridging context for the change from relative to <lb/>reason. <lb/>(49) <lb/>E-tzaye <lb/>eman behar aza <lb/>osto-ric, ema-iten <lb/>NEG-AUX.3SG&lt;3PL give must cabbage leaf-PART give-IPFV <lb/>bei-teyo <lb/>aragui-a-ri khiño gaisto bat. <lb/>bait-AUX.3SG&lt;3SG meat-DEF-DAT smell bad <lb/>one <lb/>&apos;They should not be given cabbage leaves because they / which give the meat <lb/>bad smell.&apos; <lb/>(IntxauspeSolast, 1857) <lb/>Finally, we have complement clauses. The use of bait-in them be explained differ-<lb/>ently depending on the subtype of complements: verbs of happening, nominal <lb/>complements and factive complements. <lb/>In the oldest texts bait-complements appear with verbs of happening and in <lb/>complements of nouns. Manner deictics can be grammaticalized into quotation <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">24 Such process was proposed for several languages (see examples in Disterheft and Viti 2010: 244-<lb/>245; Hendery 2012: sec. 2.2.6), though the opposite direction, i.e., from adverbial to relative is also <lb/>possible. <lb/>25 Using a subset of the data (bait-only clauses that can be interpreted as relative or reason), a <lb/>regression analysis was performed with the co-referentiality as the dependent variable and the <lb/>period as the independent variable (and text as a random effect). The effect of the period is significant <lb/>(χ 2 = 13, df = 3, p = 0.004). See details in the supplementary materials. <lb/></note>

        <page>680 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Krajewska <lb/></note>

        <body>markers and from there into complement clause markers (from &apos;he said so: &quot; …&quot;&apos; to <lb/>&apos;he said that … &apos; [Güldemann 2008; König 2015]). Nevertheless, bai or bait are not <lb/>attested as cataphors. Alternatively, the particle could initially have discourse <lb/>function (50) (cf. Example (30)). This scenario explains well the presence of bait-in <lb/>complements of &apos;happen&apos; verbs. <lb/>(50) <lb/>gertha <lb/>zedin hil bait zen <lb/>happen AUX <lb/>die bait AUX <lb/>&apos;it happened: he (indeed) died&apos; <lb/>(LeizarragaTest, Luke 16: 22, 1571) <lb/>Another possible route would go from relative to complement clauses. As mentioned, <lb/>nouns take bait-complements in early texts. Relative clauses are typical modifiers of <lb/>nouns, and because of that, their use could be extended to other types of nominal <lb/>structures. This grammaticalization path is attested in various languages (rela-<lb/>tive &gt; complementizer grammaticalization path in Kuteva et al. [2019: 367]). <lb/>Finally, bait-complements of factive verbs could emerge via reanalysis of reason <lb/>clauses: from something like I am surprised because … it is easy to arrive at I am <lb/>surprised that …, and in Basque texts there are examples -though not numerous -<lb/>ambiguous between reason and complement. This may explain the use of bait-with <lb/>factive emotive verbs: it is possible to express a reason for an attitude towards a fact <lb/>(I am surprised because …), but not with many other kinds of complement-taking <lb/>verbs (e.g., say). Also, this path has crosslinguistic parallels. Kortmann (1997: 64) <lb/>shows that markers of adverbial clauses can be placed in the middle of the <lb/>complementizer -adverbial subordinator -relativizer -relativizer continuum. <lb/>López-Couso and Méndez-Naya (2015) analyze various &apos;minor complementizers&apos; in <lb/>English, which are grammaticalized from adverbial clause markers such as but, as if, <lb/>if or like. They argue that the adverbial subordinators in complement clauses show a <lb/>higher degree of integration: the subordinate clause becomes an argument in the <lb/>main clause. The grammaticalization process also results in partial loss of the orig-<lb/>inal adverbial meaning, even though its traces continue to constrain the range of <lb/>predicates with which such complements are possible. The Basque case happened in <lb/>a different domain of adverbial subordination (the various English markers do not <lb/>include causal conjunctions), but the grammaticalization operated similarly. The <lb/>subordinate clause became increasingly integrated into the main clause (cf. hypo-<lb/>taxis &gt; subordination cline as described by Hopper and Traugott [2003]), even though <lb/>in the modern language the two clauses need not (yet) be in a single intonational <lb/>phrase. The meaning of cause undergoes bleaching, but it continues to influence the <lb/>use of bait-complements by restricting it to predicates with semantics compatible <lb/>with it. <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">The diachrony of the Basque marker bait-<lb/></note>

        <page>681 <lb/></page>

        <body>5 Conclusions <lb/>The main goal of this article was to explain in what way the Basque subordinator <lb/>bait-might be related to the affirmative adverb bai &apos;yes&apos;. I have argued that the <lb/>missing link could be a manner expression from which both the affirmative adverb <lb/>and the subordinator developed. Earliest texts provide some support for the idea, as <lb/>bai is used there in a range of functions typical of grammaticalization pathways of <lb/>manner deictic expressions. The etymology proposed by Trask (1997) and Lakarra <lb/>(2018) for the adverb (*badadi &apos;it is (so)&apos;) is also compatible with the idea. The marker <lb/>bait-could come from bai plus either the conjunction eta &apos;and&apos; or the verb form da &apos;is&apos;. <lb/>In either case, given the tendency of manner deictics to renew, such developments <lb/>are not surprising. <lb/>The exact stages of the development of the subordinator are difficult to recon-<lb/>struct, as practically all of its functions are already attested in the earliest Basque <lb/>texts. However, it appears plausible that initially, the particle had focus or discourse <lb/>functions. A reflex of this is found in different areas of Basque grammar (e.g., in <lb/>indefinite pronouns). Due to the frequent use in subordinate clauses, it was even-<lb/>tually recategorized as a subordinator. It seems that the extension of the marker bait-<lb/>to the different types of subordinate clauses (and to other areas of grammar) <lb/>happened in a piecemeal fashion, from one construction to another. In the modern <lb/>language bait-is a subordinator with a wide range of functions, but it retains certain <lb/>semantic features related to the earlier stages. <lb/>As shown throughout the article, the changes that brought the emergence of the <lb/>subordinator as well as the subsequent developments can be described as a gram-<lb/>maticalization process. In particular, the following features of grammaticalization <lb/>are prominent: <lb/>(a) Phonetic erosion: in bait-the -t must be secondary and is probably the result of <lb/>the apocope of the final vowel. Additionally, the particle lost its independence <lb/>and cliticized to the verb. <lb/>(b) Decategorialization: a change in the categorical status occurred when a particle <lb/>was reinterpreted as a subordinator. <lb/>(c) Bleaching: the marker partially lost its original lexical meaning, especially in <lb/>contexts where it is used with another element which determines the type of <lb/>clause. <lb/>(d) Persistence: at the same time, however, the influence of the older lexical <lb/>meaning can also be seen, e.g., in the range of predicates which take bait-<lb/>complements. <lb/>(e) Layering: the newer uses of the marker add to the older ones. <lb/></body>

        <page>682 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Krajewska <lb/></note>

        <body>(f) Extension and obligatorification: throughout the process, the subordinator <lb/>extended to new contexts: via the emergence of new constructions (such as <lb/>[conjunction + bait-verb]) and also through the reanalysis of certain structures <lb/>(e.g., reason to complement). In certain constructions the subordinator became <lb/>obligatory. <lb/>Additionally, increased clausal integration can also be mentioned as a feature of <lb/>grammaticalization processes across clauses (Hopper and Traugott 2003): in some <lb/>clause types a change towards embedding has happened (or is still underway). This is <lb/>especially clear in complement clauses, which, according to the arguments presented <lb/>here, are a late addition to the family of bait-clauses and emerged from more loosely <lb/>connected structures (e.g., reason clauses). <lb/></body>

        <div type="annex">Abbreviations <lb/>ADL <lb/>adlative <lb/>AFF <lb/>affirmative <lb/>ANIM <lb/>animate <lb/>AOR <lb/>aorist <lb/>AUX <lb/>auxiliary <lb/>COND <lb/>conditional <lb/>COM <lb/>comitative <lb/>COMP <lb/>complementation <lb/>DAT <lb/>dative <lb/>DEF <lb/>definitive <lb/>DEM <lb/>demonstrative <lb/>DEST <lb/>destinative <lb/>ERG <lb/>ergative <lb/>FUT <lb/>future <lb/>GEN <lb/>genitive <lb/>HYP <lb/>hypothetical <lb/>IMP <lb/>imperative <lb/>INDEF <lb/>indefinite <lb/>INES <lb/>inessive <lb/>INS <lb/>instrumental <lb/>IPFV <lb/>imperfective <lb/>NEG <lb/>negation <lb/>NMLZ <lb/>nominalization <lb/>PART <lb/>partitive <lb/>PL <lb/>plural <lb/>POT <lb/>potential <lb/>PST <lb/>past <lb/>PTCL <lb/>particle <lb/></div>

		<note place="headnote">The diachrony of the Basque marker bait-<lb/></note>

        <page>683 <lb/></page>

        <div type="annex">QUEST <lb/>question particle <lb/>RAD <lb/>radical <lb/>RM <lb/>relational marker <lb/>SG <lb/>singular <lb/>SUB <lb/>subordinator <lb/>In glosses of finite verbs the sign &quot;&gt;&quot; distinguishes ergative and absolutive arguments <lb/>and &quot;&lt;&quot; distinguishes dative ones. <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">Research funding: The research for the article was made possible by the grants from <lb/>the Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation (PGC2018-098995-B-I00, PID2021-<lb/>124769NB-I0 and PID2020-118445GB-I00). Support given by the Diachronic <lb/>Linguistics, Typology, and the History of Basque Research Group (IT1534-22) <lb/>funded by the Basque Government is also acknowledged. <lb/></div>

        <div type="availability">Data availability: Supplementary materials for this article (data and code used for <lb/>the quantitative part of the study) can be accessed at https://osf.io/uqcf5/. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Appendix: Corpora used in the study <lb/>The quantitative part of the article is based on a corpus consisting of texts listed in the <lb/>following table. Unless stated otherwise, the texts come from the Euskal Klasikoen <lb/>Corpusa corpus (Euskara Institutua 2013). The spelling of the texts included in this <lb/>corpus was modernized. <lb/>Abbreviation <lb/>Author and title <lb/>Period  (-) <lb/>Etxepare <lb/>Etxepare, Linguae Vasconum Primitiae () <lb/>LeizarragaAbc <lb/>Leizarraga, ABC edo Kristinoen instrukzionea () <lb/>LeizarragaKat <lb/>Leizarraga, Katexismea () <lb/>LeizarragaTest, Matt <lb/>Leizarraga, Iesus Krist Gure Iaunaren Testamentu Berria (), The Gospel of <lb/>Matthew <lb/>Period  (-) <lb/>Materra <lb/>Materra, Dotrina kristiana () <lb/>BeriainDotrina <lb/>Beriain, Dotrina kristioarena euskaras () <lb/>EtxeberriZiburukoa <lb/>Etxeberri Ziburukoa, Manual debozionezkoa (, ), Noelak (, ) <lb/>Haranburu <lb/>Haranburu, Debozino eskuarra () <lb/>Axular <lb/>Axular, Gero (), chapters I-XV <lb/>Oihenart <lb/>Oihenart, O.ten gaztaroa neurtitzetan () <lb/>Harizmendi <lb/>Harizmendi, Ama birjinaren ofizioa () <lb/>Pouvreau <lb/>Pouvreau, Filotea (), chapters - and Iesusen imitazionea (), <lb/>chapters - <lb/>Argainaratz <lb/>Argainaratz, Deboten brebiarioa () <lb/></div>

        <page>684 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Krajewska <lb/></note>

        <div type="annex">(continued) <lb/>Abbreviation <lb/>Author and title <lb/>TartasOnsa <lb/>Tartas, Onsa hilzeko bidia () <lb/>Aranbillaga <lb/>Aranbillaga, Jesu Kristoren Imitazionea () <lb/>Gazteluzar <lb/>Gasteluzar, Egia katholikak () <lb/>Belapeire <lb/>Belapeire, Katexima labürra () <lb/>Oloroeko kat. <lb/>Oloroeko katixima () (Padilla-Moyano ) <lb/>EtxeberriSarakoa <lb/>Etxeberri Sarakoa, Eskual-Herriko gazteriari (c. ) and Lau-Urduri gomen-<lb/>diozko karta, edo guthuna () <lb/>Xurio <lb/>Xurio, Jesu-Kristoren imitazionea () <lb/>Haraneder <lb/>Haraneder, Jesu Kristoren ebanjelio saindua: San Mateo () <lb/>Period  (-) <lb/>Maister <lb/>Maister, Jesü-Kristen imitazionia (), the st and rd books <lb/>Larregi <lb/>Larregi, Testamen berriko historioa () <lb/>Lizarraga <lb/>Lizarraga, Zenbait sanduen biziak asteaz datozinak (-), first  <lb/>chapters <lb/>Mihura <lb/>Mihura, Andredena Mariaren imitazionea () <lb/>IntxauspeApokalipsia <lb/>Intxauspe, Apokalipsia () (Pagola et al. ) <lb/>IntxauspeSolast <lb/>Intxauspe, Iturriagaren Solastaldiak () (Pagola et al. ) <lb/>Duvoisin <lb/>Duvoisin, Laborantzako liburua () and Solastaldiak () <lb/>Laphitz <lb/>Laphitz, Bi Saindu Heskualdunen Bizia () <lb/>Webster <lb/>Webster, Euskal ipuinak () <lb/>Adema <lb/>Adema, Eskualdun pelegrinaren bidaltzailea () <lb/>Arbelbide <lb/>Arbelbide, Igandea edo Jaunaren eguna () <lb/>Hiriart-Urruti <lb/>Hiriart-Urruti, Gontzetarik jalgiaraziak (-) <lb/>Elizanburu <lb/>Elizanburu, Lehenagoko Eskualdunak zer ziren () <lb/>Period  (-) <lb/>EtxepareBuruxkak <lb/>Etxepare Bidegorri, Buruxkak () <lb/>Barbier <lb/>Barbier, Piarres I () <lb/>LeonImitazionea <lb/>Leon, Jesu-Kristoren imitazionea () <lb/>EtxepareMendekoste <lb/>Etxepare Landerretxe, Mendekoste gereziak () <lb/>Larzabal <lb/>Larzabal, Roxali (), Matalas (), Antzerki laburrak (-) <lb/></div>

        <listBibl>References <lb/>Artiagoitia, Xabier. 2003. Complementation (noun clauses). In José Ignacio Hualde &amp; Jon Ortiz de Urbina <lb/>(eds.), A grammar of Basque, 634-709. Berlin &amp; New York: Mouton de Gruyter. <lb/>Artiagoitia, Xabier &amp; Arantzazu Elordieta. 2016. On the semantic function and selection of Basque finite <lb/>complementizers. In Kasper Boye &amp; Petar Kehayov (eds.), Complementizer semantics in European <lb/>languages, 379-411. Berlin &amp; Boston: De Gruyter Mouton. <lb/></listBibl>

		<note place="headnote">The diachrony of the Basque marker bait-<lb/></note>

        <page>685 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>Artiagoitia, Xabier, Bernard Oyharçabal, José Ignacio Hualde &amp; Jon Ortiz de Urbina. 2003. Subordination. In <lb/>José Ignacio Hualde &amp; Jon Ortiz de Urbina (eds.), A grammar of Basque, 632-762. Berlin &amp; New York: <lb/>Mouton de Gruyter. <lb/>Azkue, Resurrección María. 1923. Morfología vasca. Bilbao: Editorial Vasca. <lb/>Bourdin, Philippe. 2008. On the grammaticalization of &apos;come&apos; and &apos;go&apos; into markers of textual connectivity. <lb/>In María José López-Couso &amp; Elena Seoane (eds.), Rethinking grammaticalization: New perspectives, <lb/>37-59. Amsterdam &amp; Philadelphia: John Benjamins. <lb/>Bybee, Joan L., Revere D. Perkins &amp; William Pagliuca. 1994. The evolution of grammar: Tense, aspect, and <lb/>modality in the languages of the world. Chicago, IL: University of Chicago Press. <lb/>Creissels, Denis &amp; Céline Mounole. 2011. Animacy and spatial cases: Typological tendencies, and the case <lb/>of Basque. In Seppo Kittilä, Katja Västi &amp; Jussi Ylikoski (eds.), Case, animacy and semantic roles, <lb/>157-182. Amsterdam &amp; Philadelphia: John Benjamins. <lb/>Disterheft, Dorothy &amp; Carlotta Viti. 2010. Subordination. In Silvia Luraghi &amp; Vit Bubenik (eds.), Continuum <lb/>companion to historical linguistics, 230-249. New York: Continuum. <lb/>Dixon, Robert M. W. &amp; Alexandra Y. Aikhenvald. 2009. The semantics of clause linking: A cross-linguistic <lb/>typology. Oxford: Oxford University Press. <lb/>Etxepare, Ricardo. 2001. Nz-bait izenordain zehaztugabeen jatorriaz [On the source of wh-bait indefinite <lb/>pronouns]. Lapurdum 6. 93-117. <lb/>Etxepare, Ricardo. 2021. From free relatives to indefinite pronouns in Basque, or how can anyone end up <lb/>being someone. Available at: https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-03505652/. <lb/>Euskaltzaindia. 1999. Euskal gramatika: Lehen urratsak [Basque grammar: First steps], vol. 5-1. Bilbao: <lb/>Euskaltzaindia. <lb/>Euskaltzaindia. 2019. Orotariko Euskal Hiztegia [General Basque Dictionary], 6th edn. Bilbao: <lb/>Euskaltzaindia. <lb/>Euskara Institutua. 2013. Euskal Klasikoen Corpusa (EKC) [Corpus of Basque classics (EKC)]. UPV/EHU. <lb/>Available at: https://www.ehu.eus/ehg/kc/. <lb/>Fraser, Bruce. 1988. Types of English discourse markers. Acta Linguistica Hungarica 38(1-4). 19-33. <lb/>Gèze, Louis. 2010. Éléments de grammaire basque: Dialecte souletin, suivis d&apos;un vocabulaire basque-français &amp; <lb/>français-basque. Munich: LINCOM Europa. <lb/>Givón, Talmy. 2009. The genesis of syntactic complexity: Diachrony, ontogeny, neuro-cognition, evolution. <lb/>Amsterdam &amp; Philadelphia: John Benjamins. <lb/>Grimshaw, Jane. 1979. Complement selection and the lexicon. Linguistic Inquiry 10(2). 279-326. <lb/>Güldemann, Tom. 2008. Quotative indexes in African languages: A synchronic and diachronic survey. Berlin &amp; <lb/>New York: Mouton De Gruyter. <lb/>Haspelmath, Martin. 1997. Indefinite pronouns. Oxford: Oxford University Press. <lb/>Haspelmath, Martin &amp; Oda Buchholz. 1998. Equative and similative constructions in the languages of <lb/>Europe. In Johan van der Auwera (ed.), Adverbial constructions in the languages of Europe, 277-334. <lb/>Berlin &amp; New York: Walter de Gruyter. <lb/>Haspelmath, Martin &amp; Ekkehard König. 1998. Concessive conditionals in the languages of Europe. In <lb/>Johan van der Auwera (ed.), Adverbial constructions in the languages of Europe, 563-640. Berlin &amp; New <lb/>York: Mouton de Gruyter. <lb/>Heine, Bernd &amp; Tania Kuteva. 2002. World lexicon of grammaticalization. Cambridge: Cambridge University <lb/>Press. <lb/>Heine, Bernd &amp; Tania Kuteva. 2007. The genesis of grammar: A reconstruction. Oxford: Oxford University <lb/>Press. <lb/>Hendery, Rachel. 2012. Relative clauses in time and space: A case study in the methods of diachronic typology. <lb/>Amsterdam &amp; Philadelphia: John Benjamins. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>686 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Krajewska <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>Hetterle, Katja. 2015. Adverbial clauses in cross-linguistic perspective. Berlin &amp; Boston: De Gruyter Mouton. <lb/>Hopper, Paul. 1991. On some principles of grammaticalization. In Elizabeth Closs Traugott &amp; Bernd Heine <lb/>(eds.), Approaches to grammaticalization, vol. 1, 17-35. Amsterdam &amp; Philadelphia: John Benjamins. <lb/>Hopper, Paul &amp; Elizabeth Closs Traugott. 2003. Grammaticalization. Cambridge: Cambridge University <lb/>Press. <lb/>Hualde, José Ignacio. 2003. Conjunctions and connectors. In José Ignacio Hualde &amp; Jon Ortiz de Urbina <lb/>(eds.), A grammar of Basque, 323-327. Berlin &amp; New York: Mouton de Gruyter. <lb/>Hualde, José Ignacio &amp; Jon Ortiz de Urbina (eds.). 2003. A grammar of Basque. Berlin &amp; New York: Mouton <lb/>de Gruyter. <lb/>Karttunen, Lauri. 1971a. Implicative verbs. Language 47(2). 340-358. <lb/>Karttunen, Lauri. 1971b. Some observations on factivity. Paper in Linguistics 4(1). 55-69. <lb/>Kiparsky, Paul &amp; Carol Kiparsky. 1970. Fact. In Manfred Bierwisch &amp; Karl Erich Heidolph (eds.), Progress in <lb/>linguistics, 143-173. Berlin: Walter de Gruyter. <lb/>König, Ekkehard. 2015. Manner deixis as source of grammatical markers in Indo-European languages. In <lb/>Carlotta Viti (ed.), Perspectives on historical syntax, 35-60. Amsterdam &amp; Philadelphia: John <lb/>Benjamins. <lb/>König, Ekkehard. 2020. Establishing transphrastic relations: On the grammaticalization of demonstratives. <lb/>In Janet Zhiqun Xing (ed.), A typological approach to grammaticalization and lexicalization: East meets <lb/>West, 55-74. Berlin &amp; Boston: De Gruyter Mouton. <lb/>Kortmann, Bernd. 1997. Adverbial subordination: A typology and history of adverbial subordinators based on <lb/>European languages. Berlin &amp; New York: Mouton de Gruyter. <lb/>Kortmann, Bernd. 1998. Adverbial subordinators in the languages of Europe. In Johan van der Auwera (ed.), <lb/>Adverbial constructions in the languages of Europe, 457-562. Berlin New York: Mouton de Gruyter. <lb/>Krajewska, Dorota. 2017. Euskararen sintaxi diakronikorantz: Egitura konplexuak/towards a historical syntax <lb/>of Basque: Complex constructions. Vitoria-Gasteiz: UPV/EHU dissertation. Available at: http://hdl. <lb/>handle.net/10810/26877. <lb/>Krajewska, Dorota. 2022. The marking of spatial relations on animate nouns in Basque: A diachronic <lb/>quantitative corpus study. Journal of Historical Linguistics 12(2). 241-281. <lb/>Kuteva, Tania, Bernd Heine, Bo Hong, Haiping Long, Heiko Narrog &amp; Seongha Rhee. 2019. World lexicon of <lb/>grammaticalization, 2nd edn. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. <lb/>Lafitte, Pierre. 1991. Grammaire basque: Navarro-labourdin littéraire. Donostia: Elkar. <lb/>Lafon, René. 1980. Le système du verbe basque au XVIe siècle. Donostia: Elkar. <lb/>Lafon, René. 1999 [1957]. L&apos;expression de la comparaison en basque. In Jean Haritschelhar &amp; <lb/>Pierre Charritton (eds.), Vasconiana, 649-666. Bilbao: Euskaltzaindia. <lb/>Lafon, René. 1999 [1966]. La particule bait en basque : Ses emplois morphologiques et syntactiques. In <lb/>Jean Haritschelhar &amp; Pierre Charritton (eds.), Vasconiana, 667-687. Bilbao: Euskaltzaindia. <lb/>Lafon, René. 1999 [1973]. La langue basque. In Jean Haritschelhar &amp; Pierre Charritton (eds.), Vasconiana, <lb/>3-55. Bilbao: Euskaltzaindia. <lb/>Lakarra, Joseba A. 1984. Bertso Bizkaitarrak (1688) [The Biscayan verses (1688)]. Anuario del Seminario de <lb/>Filología Vasca &quot;Julio de Urquijo&quot; 18(2). 89-183. <lb/>Lakarra, Joseba A. 1986. Bizkaiera zaharra euskalkien artean [Old Biscayan among the Basque dialects]. <lb/>Anuario del Seminario de Filología Vasca &quot;Julio de Urquijo&quot; 20(3). 639-681. <lb/>Lakarra, Joseba A. 1996. Refranes y sentencias (1596): Ikerketak eta edizioa [Refranes y sentencias (1596): <lb/>Analysis and edition]. Bilbao: Euskaltzaindia. <lb/>Lakarra, Joseba A. 2018. Euskararen historiaurrea [The prehistory of Basque]. In Joaquín Gorrochategui, <lb/>Iván Igartua &amp; Joseba A. Lakarra (eds.), Euskararen historia [The history of Basque], 23-229. Vitoria-<lb/>Gasteiz: Eusko Jaurlaritza. <lb/></listBibl>

		<note place="headnote">The diachrony of the Basque marker bait-<lb/></note>

        <page>687 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>Lakarra, Joseba A., Julen Manterola &amp; Iñaki Segurola. 2019. Euskal hiztegi historiko-etimologikoa (EHHE-200) <lb/>[The Basque historical and etymological dictionary]. Bilbao: Euskaltzaindia. Available at: https:// <lb/>www.euskaltzaindia.eus/index.php?option=com_ehhe&amp;task=home&amp;Itemid=1193&amp;lang=eu. <lb/>Le Nouveau Testament. 1563. Le Nouveau Testament, c&apos;est à dire, la Nouvelle Alliance de Nostre Seigneur Jesus <lb/>Christ. Genève: Jean Bonne-Foy. ark:/12148/bpt6k314602j. <lb/>Lehmann, Christian. 1988. Towards a typology of clause linkage. In John Haiman &amp; Sandra A. Thompson <lb/>(eds.), Clause combining in grammar and discourse, 181-225. Amsterdam &amp; Philadelphia: John <lb/>Benjamins. <lb/>López-Couso, María José &amp; Belén Méndez-Naya. 2015. Secondary grammaticalization in clause combining: <lb/>From adverbial subordination to complementation in English. Language Sciences 47. 188-198. <lb/>Mitxelena, Koldo. 2011 [1954]. La posición fonética del dialecto vasco del Roncal. In Joseba A. Lakarra &amp; <lb/>Iñigo Ruiz Arzalluz (eds.), Obras completas, vol. VII, 611-647. Bilbao: UPV/EHU. <lb/>Mitxelena, Koldo. 2011 [1964]. Textos arcaicos vascos. In Joseba A. Lakarra &amp; Iñigo Ruiz Arzalluz (eds.), <lb/>Obras completas, vol. XII, 1-171. Bilbao: UPV/EHU. <lb/>Mitxelena, Koldo. 2011 [1970]. Nombre y verbo en la etimología vasca. In Joseba A. Lakarra &amp; <lb/>Iñigo Ruiz Arzalluz (eds.), Obras completas, vol. VII, 235-267. Bilbao: UPV/EHU. <lb/>Mitxelena, Koldo. 2011 [1977]. Fonética histórica vasca. In Joseba A. Lakarra &amp; Iñigo Ruiz Arzalluz (eds.), <lb/>Obras completas, vol. VI. Bilbao: UPV/EHU. <lb/>Mitxelena, Koldo. 2011 [1981]. Lengua común y dialectos vascos. In Joseba A. Lakarra &amp; Iñigo Ruiz Arzalluz <lb/>(eds.), Obras completas, vol. VII, 517-344. Bilbao: UPV/EHU. <lb/>Orpustan, Jean-Baptiste. 2010. Correspondance basque à la fin du XVIe siècle (1595-1598): 20 lettres de <lb/>renseignements sur la politique de Henri IV et la fin des guerres contre la Ligue. Lapurdum 14. <lb/>137-162. <lb/>Oyharçabal, Beñat. 1987. Etude descriptive de constructions complexes en basque, propositions relatives, <lb/>temporelles, conditionelles et consessives. Paris: Université de Paris VII dissertation. <lb/>Oyharçabal, Beñat. 1997. Hiru aditz aurrizki zahar XVI. mendeko testuetan [Three old verbal prefixes in <lb/>16th century texts]. Lapurdum 2. 45-62. <lb/>Oyharçabal, Beñat, Irantzu Epelde &amp; Jasone Salaberria. 2009. Norantz proiektua. Available at: http://www. <lb/>norantz.org/. <lb/>Padilla-Moyano, Manuel. 2015. Oloroeko katixima: Edizioa eta azterketa [The catechisms from Oloroe: <lb/>edition and analysis]. Unpublished manuscript. <lb/>Padilla-Moyano, Manuel. 2017. Zuberoako euskararen azterketa diakronikoa: XVI-XIX. mendeak/Analyse <lb/>diachronique du dialecte souletin: XVI-XIX siècles. Bordeaux: UPV/EHU &amp; Université Bordeaux <lb/>Montaigne dissertation. Available at: http://hdl.handle.net/10810/26535. <lb/>Pagola, Rosa Miren, Juan Jose Iribar &amp; Itziar Iribar (eds.). 1997. Bonaparte ondareko eskuizkribuak: Zuberera <lb/>[Manuscripts from the Bonaparte&apos;s archive: Souletin Basque]. Bilbao: Universidad de Deusto. <lb/>Pérez Saldanya, Manuel. 2020. El prefijo subordinante bait-y sus paralelos en el dominio occitano-catalán. <lb/>In Iñaki Camino, Xabier Artiagoitia, Irantzu Epelde &amp; Koldo Ulibarri (eds.), Eibartik Zuberoara <lb/>euskalkietan barrena. Koldo Zuazori gorazarre, 581-599. Bilbao: UPV/EHU. <lb/>Pérez-Saldanya, Manuel &amp; José Ignacio Hualde. 2017. From theme to rheme: The evolution of causal <lb/>conjunctions of temporal origin in Catalan. Studies in Hispanic and Lusophone Linguistics 10(2). <lb/>319-348. <lb/>R Core Team. 2022. R: A language and environment for statistical computing. Vienna: R Foundation for <lb/>Statistical Computing. Available at: https://www.R-project.org/. <lb/>Rebuschi, Georges. 2008. On older northern Basque exclamatives in ala. In Xabier Artiagoitia &amp; <lb/>Joseba A. Lakarra (eds.), Gramatika jaietan: Patxi Goenagaren omenez, 691-708. Donostia: Gipuzkoako <lb/>Foru Aldundia and UPV/EHU. <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>688 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Krajewska <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>Salaberri Zaratiegi, Patxi. 1996. Toponimia eta dialektologiaren arteko harremanen inguruan: Artaxonako <lb/>jabego genitiboaz eta bestez [On the relation between the toponymy and dialectology: The genitive <lb/>in Artaxona and other issues]. Fontes Linguae Vasconum 72. 223-234. <lb/>Thompson, Sandra A., Robert E. Longacre &amp; Shin Ja J. Hwang. 2007. Adverbial clauses. In Timothy Shopen <lb/>(ed.), Language typology and syntactic description, vol. 2, 237-269. Cambridge: Cambridge University <lb/>Press. <lb/>Trask, Robert L. 1997. The history of Basque. London &amp; New York: Routledge. <lb/>Wiemer, Björn. 2019. On illusory insubordination and semiinsubordination in Slavic: Independent <lb/>infinitives, clause-initial particles and predicatives put to the test. In Karin Beijering, <lb/>Gunther Kaltenböck &amp; María Sol Sansiñena (eds.), Insubordination, 107-166. Berlin &amp; Boston: De <lb/>Gruyter Mouton. <lb/></listBibl>

		<note place="headnote">The diachrony of the Basque marker bait-<lb/></note>

        <page>689 </page>


	</text>

</TEI>