<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage>iScience <lb/>Article <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 Receptors and Entry Genes Are <lb/>Expressed in the Human Olfactory <lb/>Neuroepithelium and Brain <lb/>TMPRSS2 <lb/>ACE2 <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>respiratory <lb/>olfactory <lb/>brain <lb/>sensory <lb/>neurons <lb/>sustentacular <lb/>cells <lb/>Leon Fodoulian, <lb/>Joe ¨l Tuberosa, <lb/>Daniel Rossier, ..., <lb/>Basile N. Landis, <lb/>Alan Carleton, <lb/>Ivan Rodriguez <lb/>alan.carleton@unige.ch (A.C.) <lb/>ivan.rodriguez@unige.ch (I.R.) <lb/>HIGHLIGHTS <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 receptors <lb/>ACE2 and TMPRSS2 are <lb/>expressed in olfactory <lb/>neuroepithelia <lb/>ACE2 and TMPRSS2 are <lb/>coexpressed in <lb/>supporting sustentacular <lb/>cells <lb/>A subset of neuronal and <lb/>non-neuronal cells in the <lb/>brain transcribe ACE2 <lb/>Fodoulian et al., iScience 23, <lb/>101839 <lb/>December 18, 2020 ª 2020 <lb/>The Author(s). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/ <lb/>j.isci.2020.101839 <lb/></titlePage>
			
			<front>ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>iScience <lb/>Article <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 Receptors and Entry Genes <lb/>Are Expressed in the Human Olfactory <lb/>Neuroepithelium and Brain <lb/>Leon Fodoulian, 1,2,6 Joe ¨l Tuberosa, 1,6 Daniel Rossier, 1,6 Madlaina Boillat, 1,6 Chenda Kan, 1 Ve ´ronique Pauli, 1 <lb/>Kristof Egervari, 3,4 Johannes A. Lobrinus, 3 Basile N. Landis, 5 Alan Carleton, 2, * and Ivan Rodriguez 1,7, * <lb/>SUMMARY <lb/>Reports indicate an association between COVID-19 and anosmia, as well as the <lb/>presence of SARS-CoV-2 virions in the olfactory bulb. To test whether the olfac-<lb/>tory neuroepithelium may represent a target of the virus, we generated RNA-<lb/>seq libraries from human olfactory neuroepithelia, in which we found substantial <lb/>expression of the genes coding for the virus receptor angiotensin-converting <lb/>enzyme-2 (ACE2) and for the virus internalization enhancer TMPRSS2. We <lb/>analyzed a human olfactory single-cell RNA-seq dataset and determined that sus-<lb/>tentacular cells, which maintain the integrity of olfactory sensory neurons, ex-<lb/>press ACE2 and TMPRSS2. ACE2 protein was highly expressed in a subset of <lb/>sustentacular cells in human and mouse olfactory tissues. Finally, we found <lb/>ACE2 transcripts in specific brain cell types, both in mice and humans. Sustentac-<lb/>ular cells thus represent a potential entry door for SARS-CoV-2 in a neuronal sen-<lb/>sory system that is in direct connection with the brain. <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>A novel virus from the Coronaviridae family, termed SARS-CoV-2, which emerged in December 2019 in East <lb/>Asia, is currently expanding on the planet. Its exact history is unknown, but its genomic sequence suggests <lb/>that it was transmitted from bats to humans via an intermediate animal host (Zhou et al., 2020). It is now <lb/>transmitted from human to human (Chan et al., 2020) and from human to cat (Shi et al., 2020). Infection <lb/>by SARS-CoV-2 is associated in our species with a severe respiratory syndrome called COVID-19 and is <lb/>characterized by a substantial mortality rate (Huang et al., 2020; Wang et al., 2020a; Zhou et al., 2020). <lb/>Entry of SARS-CoV-2 into target cells depends on the Spike protein (S), which is present on the virus capsid <lb/>(Letko et al., 2020; Walls et al., 2020). Viral attachment involves an interaction between S and the angio-<lb/>tensin-converting enzyme-2 (ACE2), located on the surface of the target cell. One reported mechanism <lb/>facilitating virus entry consists, in association with ACE2, in the priming of S by the cellular serine protease <lb/>TMPRSS2, also attached to the cellular membrane, which eventually leads to the fusion between the cellular <lb/>and the viral membranes (Hoffmann et al., 2020; Zhou et al., 2020). Expectedly, the main targets of SARS-<lb/>CoV-2, respiratory cells that line the respiratory airways, coexpress ACE2 and TMPRSS2 (Bertram et al., <lb/>2012). Other proteins have been proposed to mediate SARS-CoV-2 internalization, in particular CD147 <lb/>(Wang et al., 2020c) as an alternative receptor, and cathepsin (Ou et al., 2020) and furin-like proteases <lb/>(Shang et al., 2020; Walls et al., 2020) as internalization activators. <lb/>Starting with anecdotal reports, both from SARS-CoV-2-infected patients and medical staff that suggested <lb/>an association between viral infection and alterations of olfactory perception (Giacomelli et al., 2020; Per-<lb/>rigo, 2020) (and also taste sensitivity), the link between SARS-CoV-2 infection and olfactory dysfunction is <lb/>today clearly established (Heidari et al., 2020; Hopkins et al., 2020; Luers et al., 2020; Moein et al., 2020; <lb/>Spinato et al., 2020; Xydakis et al., 2020). A smartphone app recording self-reported olfactory symptoms <lb/>is even used to predict potential COVID-19 (Menni et al., 2020). The olfactory perturbations, which range <lb/>from mild to more severe, are usually reversible and affect up to 95% of patients with COVID-19 depending <lb/>on the report. Whether this olfactory perturbation results from a deterioration of the nasal sensor or of a <lb/>more central perturbation is unclear, but the second hypothesis is not to be discarded since neurological <lb/>manifestations of brain origin also appear to be associated with COVID-19 infection (Gutierrez-Ortiz et al., <lb/></body>

			<front>1 Department of Genetics and <lb/>Evolution, Faculty of <lb/>Sciences, University of <lb/>Geneva, quai <lb/>Ernest-Ansermet 30, 1211 <lb/>Geneva, Switzerland <lb/>2 Department of Basic <lb/>Neurosciences, Faculty of <lb/>Medicine, University of <lb/>Geneva, 1 rue Michel-Servet, <lb/>1211 Geneva, Switzerland <lb/>3 Service of Clinical Pathology, <lb/>Department of Genetic <lb/>Medicine, Geneva University <lb/>Hospitals, Geneva, <lb/>Switzerland <lb/>4 Department of Pathology <lb/>and Immunology, Faculty of <lb/>Medicine, University of <lb/>Geneva, 1 rue Michel-Servet, <lb/>1211 Geneva, Switzerland <lb/>5 Rhinology-Olfactology Unit, <lb/>Department of <lb/>Otorhinolaryngology, Head <lb/>and Neck Surgery, Geneva <lb/>University Hospitals, Geneva, <lb/>Switzerland <lb/>6 These authors contributed <lb/>equally <lb/>7 Lead Contact <lb/>*Correspondence: <lb/>alan.carleton@unige.ch <lb/>(A.C.), <lb/>ivan.rodriguez@unige.ch <lb/>(I.R.) <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.isci. <lb/>2020.101839 <lb/>iScience 23, 101839, December 18, 2020 ª 2020 The Author(s). <lb/>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). <lb/>1 <lb/></front>
			
			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note> 
			
			<body>2020; Moriguchi et al., 2020; Paterson et al., 2020; Poyiadji et al., 2020; Wang et al., 2020b), and since SARS-<lb/>CoV-2 virions have been found in the olfactory bulb (Nampoothiri et al., 2020). <lb/> The mammalian nasal cavity can be divided into two areas: the respiratory and the olfactory areas, which <lb/>are anatomically, cellularly, and functionally different (Smith and Bhatnagar, 2019) (Figure 1A). In humans, <lb/>the respiratory part covers the major part of the nasal cavity. It includes the turbinates and is lined with a <lb/>ciliated pseudostratified columnar epithelium. Its function is to humidify, cool, or warm the incoming air, <lb/>and to trap small particles before they get into the lungs. The second nasal area corresponds to the olfac-<lb/>tory neuroepithelium. In our species, it is located in the very dorsal part of the cavity. There, it contacts vol-<lb/>atile chemicals entering the nose, an interaction that represents the first step in the process that leads to <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>F <lb/>G <lb/>Figure 1. ACE2 and TMPRSS2 Expression in Olfactory and Respiratory Nasal Epithelia <lb/>(A) Schematic of the human nasal respiratory and olfactory epithelia, with their respective cell types. <lb/>(B) Design of the bulk tissue transcriptome analysis. OE biopsies: n = 3, RE biopsies: n = 3. <lb/>(C) Volcano plot corresponding to the differential expression analysis, displaying the expression fold change and the <lb/>associated adjusted p value (****: p value % 0.0001; *: 0.01 &lt; p value % 0.05; ns: non-significant, p value &gt; 0.05) between <lb/>olfactory and respiratory epithelia for each gene. OR genes, olfactory transduction cascade specific genes, and SARS-<lb/>CoV-2 entry genes ACE2 and TMPRSS2 are highlighted with a color code. <lb/>(D-G) Transcript quantifications corresponding to (D) OR genes, (E) olfactory sensory epithelium markers and (F and G) <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 entry proteins in olfactory and respiratory biopsies. A different color was attributed to the data of each <lb/>patient (n = 4). Olfactory and respiratory epithelium sample data points are shown on a white and gray background, <lb/>respectively. OE, olfactory epithelium; RE, respiratory epithelium. <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">iScience 23, 101839, December 18, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">iScience <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<body>the identification of a given smell. This epithelium is pseudostratified and includes Bowman&apos;s glands, ol-<lb/>factory sensory neurons, sustentacular cells, microvillar cells, globose, and horizontal basal cells (cells <lb/>that keep dividing during adult life and replenish the pool of sensory neurons) (Moulton and Beidler, <lb/>1967). Each sensory neuron extends a single axon toward the olfactory bulb, which crosses the cribriform <lb/>plate before reaching the olfactory bulb in the brain. On its apical side, the olfactory neuron extends a <lb/>dendrite, which ends in multiple and long specialized cilia in contact with the outside world. These are <lb/>covered with odorant receptors and bath in the mucus that lines the nasal cavity. Olfactory sensory neuron <lb/>dendrites are enwrapped inside specialized cells, termed sustentacular cells (Liang, 2018), whose nuclei <lb/>and cell bodies line the external layer of the thick neuroepithelium (although they remain attached to <lb/>the basal lamina). The role played by the latter in maintaining the integrity and function of the neuroepi-<lb/>thelium is critical, in a very similar way that Sertoli cells support germ cell development and survival. Indeed, <lb/>contact of the olfactory mucosa with various drugs (such as 3-methylindole [Miller and O&apos;Bryan, 2003], the <lb/>anti-thyroid drug methimazole [Bergstrom et al., 2003], or nickel sulfate [Jia et al., 2010]) to which susten-<lb/>tacular cells are very sensitive leads to transient anosmia. <lb/>Whether the apparent olfactory dysfunction associated with SARS-CoV-2 infection results from a general <lb/>inflammation of the nasal cavity or from a more direct perturbation of the olfactory neuroepithelium (or ol-<lb/>factory bulb) is unclear (Cooper et al., 2020). In any case, it is critical to determine whether this virus dis-<lb/>poses of a niche to replicate just under the cribriform plate of the ethmoid bone, a structure with large holes <lb/>through which olfactory neuron axonal projections directly contact the olfactory bulb and offer a potential <lb/>gateway to the brain. This latter, if expressing SARS-CoV2 receptors, could in turn become infected. <lb/>We asked whether specific cells present in the human olfactory neuroepithelium as well as cells in the brain <lb/>may represent targets to SARS-CoV-2, by looking at the molecular players involved in infection, both at the <lb/>RNA and protein levels. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Expression of ACE2 and TMPRSS2 Human Sustentacular and Respiratory Ciliated Cells <lb/>We collected biopsies via nasal endoscopic surgery from four adult patients and explored the potential <lb/>expression of ACE2 and TMPRSS2. Samples of both nasal respiratory and olfactory sensory epithelia <lb/>were harvested. Bulk tissue RNA was extracted and libraries were generated and sequenced (Figure 1B). <lb/>To assess the specificity of our dissection, we performed a differential expression analysis between the res-<lb/>piratory and olfactory epithelia datasets (Figure 1B). As expected, olfactory-specific genes, including olfac-<lb/>tory receptor genes, CNGA2 and ANO2, OMP, and ERMN (encoding critical elements of the olfactory <lb/>transduction cascade, a specific marker of mature olfactory sensory neurons and a marker of sustentacular <lb/>cells, respectively), were significantly enriched in olfactory samples (Figures 1C-1E). The presence of ACE2 <lb/>and TMPRSS2 transcripts was then evaluated. We observed a mean of 7.1 and 63.7 TPMs in the respiratory <lb/>epithelium samples for ACE2 and TMPRSS2, respectively (Figures 1F and 1G), reflecting the presence of <lb/>ciliated cells, which represent targets of SARS-CoV-2. We found a mean of 4.6 and 76.1 TPMs in the sensory <lb/>neuroepithelium samples for ACE2 and TMPRSS2, respectively (Figures 1F and 1G), indicating the pres-<lb/>ence in this tissue of cells that may express both genes, or of a mix of cells that express either TMPRSS2 <lb/>or ACE2. <lb/>To identify putative viral targets transcribing both ACE2 and TMPRSS2 in the neuroepithelium, we took <lb/>advantage of a very recently published dataset reported by Durante et al. (2020). This dataset contains <lb/>the transcriptome of 28,726 single cells, collected during nasal endoscopic surgery of four adult patients. <lb/>Prior to any cell type analysis, we monitored the existence of cells that would transcribe both ACE2 and <lb/>TMPRSS2 (Figure 2A). We then performed an aggregate analysis of the 28,726 single cells and generated <lb/>a UMAP dimensionality reduction plot, which allowed to display the clustering of the 26 different cell types <lb/>reported in the original publication (Durante et al., 2020), including olfactory, respiratory, and immune cells <lb/>(Figure 2B). We then identified all cells expressing ACE2, TMPRSS2, ERMN (an olfactory sustentacular cell <lb/>marker) and GSTA2 (a marker of respiratory ciliated and epithelial cells) (Figures 2C, 2E, 2H, and 2I), and <lb/>those coexpressing both ACE2 and TMPRSS2, respectively (Figures 2D, 2H, and 2I). Olfactory sensory neu-<lb/>rons showed little or no expression of TMPRSS2 and ACE2, respectively (Figure 2C). In contrast, different <lb/>types of respiratory cells, and also olfactory sustentacular cells, expressed ACE2. Many of these cells also <lb/>coexpressed TMPRSS2. To better evaluate the coexpression levels of ACE2 and TMPRSS2 in the different <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note> 
			
			<note place="footnote">iScience 23, 101839, December 18, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">iScience <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<body>A <lb/>ACE2 negative ACE2 positive <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>30 <lb/>Normalized counts (log <lb/>10 scale) <lb/>All cells <lb/>ACE2 <lb/>TMPRSS2 <lb/>Resp. ciliated <lb/>Resp. <lb/>early <lb/>secretory <lb/>Resp. <lb/>HBC <lb/>Sustentacular <lb/>UMAP 1 (a.u.) <lb/>UMAP 2 (a.u.) <lb/>B <lb/>Cluster IDs (# cells) <lb/>B cells (265) <lb/>Bowman&apos;s gland (2577) <lb/>Dendritic cells (366) <lb/>Fibroblasts/Stromal cells (3656) <lb/>Globose basal cells (115) <lb/>Immature neurons (357) <lb/>Macrophages (1138) <lb/>Mast cells (160) <lb/>Mature neurons (222) <lb/>Monocytes (35) <lb/>NK cells (363) <lb/>Olfactory ensheathing glia (251) <lb/>Olfactory horizontal basal <lb/>cells (2182) <lb/>Olfactory microvillar cells (116) <lb/>Pericytes (3052) <lb/>Plasma cells (1405) <lb/>Respiratory ciliated cells (586) <lb/>Respiratory early secretory cells (663) <lb/>Respiratory epithelial cells (164) <lb/>Respiratory horizontal basal cells (1532) <lb/>Respiratory secretory cells (1035) <lb/>Sustentacular cells (3082) <lb/>T cells, CD4+ (1215) <lb/>T cells, CD8+ (2111) <lb/>Unspecified (376) <lb/>Vascular smooth muscle cells (1702) <lb/>C <lb/>ACE2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 1 <lb/>norm. UMI <lb/>TMPRSS2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 5 <lb/>norm. UMI <lb/>ERMN <lb/>0 <lb/>5 2 <lb/>norm. UMI <lb/>0 <lb/>193 <lb/>norm. UMI <lb/>GSTA2 <lb/>D <lb/>ACE2/TMPRSS2 <lb/>E <lb/>Respiratory ciliated cells <lb/>Respiratory early secretory cells <lb/>Respiratory horizontal basal cells <lb/>Sustentacular cells <lb/>0 <lb/>0.36 <lb/>0.72 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.021 <lb/>ACE2 (mean expression) <lb/>TMPRSS2 (mean expression) <lb/>n = 26 clusters <lb/>F <lb/>ACE2 negative ACE2 positive <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>30 <lb/>Normalized counts (log <lb/>10 scale) <lb/>Sustentacular cells <lb/>G <lb/>ACE2 negative ACE2 positive <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>30 <lb/>Respiratory ciliated cells <lb/>ACE2 <lb/>TMPRSS2 <lb/>H <lb/>0 <lb/>80 <lb/>ACE2 <lb/>0 <lb/>1300 <lb/>Expressing cells (#) <lb/>TMPRSS2 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>B <lb/>c e ll s <lb/>B o w <lb/>m <lb/>. g la <lb/>n d <lb/>D <lb/>e n d r . c e ll s <lb/>F ib <lb/>r o . / S t r o . c e ll s <lb/>G <lb/>B C <lb/>I m <lb/>m <lb/>. n e u r . <lb/>M <lb/>a c r o p h a g e s <lb/>M <lb/>a s t c e ll s <lb/>M <lb/>a t u r e <lb/>n e u r . <lb/>M <lb/>o n o c y t e s <lb/>N <lb/>K <lb/>c e ll s <lb/>O <lb/>lf . e n s h . g li a <lb/>O <lb/>lf . H <lb/>B C <lb/>O <lb/>lf . m <lb/>ic <lb/>r o v . <lb/>P e r ic <lb/>y t e s <lb/>P la <lb/>s m <lb/>a <lb/>c e ll s <lb/>R <lb/>e s p . c il . <lb/>R <lb/>e s p . e a r ly <lb/>s e c r . <lb/>R <lb/>e s p . e p it h . <lb/>R <lb/>e s p . H <lb/>B C <lb/>R <lb/>e s p . s e c r . <lb/>S u s t . c e ll s <lb/>T <lb/>c e ll s , C <lb/>D <lb/>4 + <lb/>T <lb/>c e ll s , C <lb/>D <lb/>8 + <lb/>U <lb/>n s p e c if ie <lb/>d <lb/>V a s c . s . m <lb/>u s c . <lb/>ACE2/TMPRSS2 <lb/>I <lb/>0 <lb/>4 <lb/>ACE2 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>Expressing cells (%) <lb/>TMPRSS2 <lb/>0 <lb/>3 <lb/>B o w <lb/>m <lb/>. g la <lb/>n d <lb/>O <lb/>lf . H <lb/>B C <lb/>O <lb/>lf . m <lb/>ic <lb/>r o v . <lb/>R <lb/>e s p . c il . <lb/>R <lb/>e s p . e a r ly <lb/>s e c r . <lb/>R <lb/>e s p . H <lb/>B C <lb/>S u s t . c e ll s <lb/>U <lb/>n s p e c if ie <lb/>d <lb/>ACE2/TMPRSS2 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">iScience 23, 101839, December 18, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">iScience <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<body>cellular populations, we plotted the mean normalized expression levels of ACE2 and TMPRSS2 corre-<lb/>sponding to each of these subpopulations (Figure 2E). Sustentacular cells and ciliated respiratory cells ex-<lb/>hibited the highest levels of expression of both genes. Populations containing olfactory horizontal cells, <lb/>microvillar cells, and Bowman&apos;s glands also showed transcription of both genes, although at lower levels. <lb/>To better evaluate the different expression levels inside the two cell types expressing the highest levels of <lb/>both ACE2 and TMPRSS2, we plotted the distribution of normalized transcript levels across all cells of both <lb/>cell types (Figures 2F and 2G). Finally, the number (Figure 2H) and percentage (Figure 2I) of cells expressing <lb/>ACE2, TMPRSS, or both genes were evaluated. <lb/>Respiratory cells are thus not the only cells in contact with the outside world that exhibit the molecular keys <lb/>involved in SARS-CoV-2 entry in the nose. Sustentacular cells, which lie at the interface between the central <lb/>nervous system and the olfactory cavity, share the same characteristics. <lb/>ACE2 and TMPRSS2 Protein Expression in the Olfactory Neuroepithelium <lb/>Quantification of gene transcripts at the single cell level, a commonly used proxy of protein abundance, <lb/>often leads to very inaccurate predictions, up to a complete discordance between real transcript and pro-<lb/>tein levels (Bauernfeind and Babbitt, 2017; Liu et al., 2016). Since it is the protein that matters here, and at <lb/>the individual cell level, we investigated the expression of ACE2 and TMPRSS2 in tissues by immunohisto-<lb/>chemistry. Given that ortholog tissue specificity is highly conserved between tetrapod species (Kryuchkova-<lb/>Mostacci and Robinson-Rechavi, 2016), and in particular between mouse and humans (Liao and Zhang, <lb/>2006), we analyzed mouse tissues in parallel to human ones. <lb/>We first evaluated the potential ACE2 immunoreactivity of the mouse olfactory epithelium (Figures 3A and <lb/>3B). To assess antibody specificity, we used independently three different anti-ACE2 antibodies, which <lb/>were raised against the extracellular part (Ab1 and Ab3 developed in goat and rabbit, respectively) or <lb/>the intracellular part of ACE2 (Ab2, developed in rabbit). These antibodies were first evaluated to label co-<lb/>lon and kidney tissues, which contain previously described ACE2-expressing cell types (Figures S1A-S1J). <lb/>In the olfactory cavity, a strong and defined labeling was observed in the respiratory epithelium in the nasal <lb/>cavity and nasopharyngeal duct (Figures S3A-S3H), and in a subset of sustentacular cells lining the nasal <lb/>cavity (Figures 3C-3G and S3B). These were almost exclusively located in the dorsal part of the epithelium, <lb/>with a relatively abrupt transition area (Figures 3H and 3I). All antibodies showed a labeling of the apical <lb/>portion of sustentacular cells, except for a slight labeling of their somata with Ab2 (Figure 3D). To clearly <lb/>differentiate olfactory sensory neurons from sustentacular cells, we colabeled the sections with TUJ1 (a <lb/>marker of neurons), OMP (a marker of mature sensory neurons),and ERMN (a marker of sustentacular cells) <lb/>(Figures 3J-3M, 3O, 3Q, and 3R). The localization of ACE2 was at the very luminal border of the sustentac-<lb/>ular cells, sandwiched between the sensory neurons TUJ1-expressing cilia and ERMN, which labels the api-<lb/>cal part of sustentacular cells (Figures 3J-3S). We also evaluated TMPRSS2 immunoreactivity in the mouse <lb/>olfactory epithelium (Figures 3N and 3P). We tested two different antibodies, which were first evaluated on <lb/>kidney tissue (Figure S2). In the mouse main olfactory epithelium, sustentacular cells were positive for <lb/>TMPRSS2, and several other cell types showed weak expression (Figures 3N, S2A, S2B, S2E, and S2F). <lb/>We then evaluated the expression of ACE2 in the human nasal cavity by immunohistochemistry. Similarly to <lb/>what is observed in the mouse, the human neuroepithelium can be discriminated from the respiratory <lb/>epithelium by the presence of TUJ1-positive olfactory sensory neurons (Figure 4A), ERMN-positive <lb/>Figure 2. Coexpression of ACE2 and TMPRSS2 in Human Sustentacular and Respiratory Ciliated Cells <lb/>(A) Violin plots displaying ACE2 and TMPRSS2 normalized expression levels in all ACE2-positive (n = 169) and ACE2-negative (n = 28,557) cells. <lb/>(B) Visualization of the clustering results reported in Durante et al.(2020) on a uniform manifold approximation and projection (UMAP) plot. &apos;&apos;Respiratory <lb/>columnar cells&apos;&apos; was renamed as &apos;&apos;Respiratory early secretory cells&apos;&apos; based on the expression of SERPINB3. a.u., arbitrary units. <lb/>(C) Normalized expression levels of ACE2, TMPRSS2, ERMN (a sustentacular cell gene marker), and GSTA2 (a respiratory ciliated cell gene marker), shown on <lb/>the UMAP plot. norm. UMI, normalized unique molecular identifier counts. <lb/>(D) ACE2 and TMPRSS2 coexpressing cells, highlighted in black on the UMAP plot. <lb/>(E) Coexpression of ACE2 and TMPRSS2 in the different cell clusters (n = 26 clusters). Means of ACE2 and TMPRSS2 normalized expression levels are plotted. <lb/>(F and G) Violin plots displaying ACE2 and TMPRSS2 normalized expression levels in (F) ACE2-positive (n = 71) and ACE2-negative (n = 3,011) sustentacular <lb/>cells, and in (G) ACE2 positive (n = 19) and ACE2 negative (n = 567) respiratory ciliated cells. <lb/>(H) Number of cells per cluster expressing ACE2 and/or TMPRSS2. <lb/>(I) Percentage of cells per cluster expressing ACE2 and/or TMPRSS2 in all coexpressing clusters (i.e., clusters with double-positive cells). Color gradient <lb/>scales in (C) and y axis scales in (A), (F) and (G) are in log 10 . <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note> 
			
			<note place="footnote">iScience 23, 101839, December 18, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">iScience <lb/>Article <lb/></note>
			
			<body>ACE2 <lb/>ACE2 (Ab1) <lb/>ACE2 (Ab2) <lb/>ACE2 (Ab3) <lb/>ACE2 neg. ctrl <lb/>ACE2 OMP <lb/>G <lb/>H <lb/>C <lb/>H <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>F <lb/>OMP ERMN <lb/>TUJ1 ERMN <lb/>ACE2 ERMN <lb/>ACE2 TMPRSS2 <lb/>Q <lb/>R <lb/>L <lb/>N <lb/>ACE2 TUJ1 <lb/>ACE2 TUJ1 <lb/>J <lb/>K <lb/>S <lb/>M <lb/>ACE2 <lb/>ACE2 <lb/>TUJ1 <lb/>ACE2 <lb/>ERMN <lb/>OMP <lb/>TUJ1 <lb/>sustentacular <lb/>cells <lb/>immature/ <lb/>mature OSNs <lb/>ACE2/TMPRSS2 <lb/>neg. ctrl <lb/>ACE2/ERMN <lb/>neg. ctrl <lb/>OB <lb/>OE <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>P <lb/>O <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">iScience 23, 101839, December 18, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">iScience <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<body>sustentacular cells along the apical border of the tissue (Figures 4A and S4C-S4E), as well as the absence of <lb/>Alcian blue-labeled goblet cells (Figure 4B). In accordance with the single-cell data, a strong labeling of <lb/>ACE2 was observed in some sustentacular cells of the sensory epithelium (Figures 4C-4G). However, the <lb/>very apical localization of ACE2 observed in the mouse neuroepithelium was not recapitulated in humans, <lb/>but ACE2 was rather enriched in the apical half of the cells. A similar somatic staining was also observed, <lb/>with the same antibody, in proximal tubule cells of the mouse kidney (Figure S1D). Congruently with its <lb/>pervasiveness in the single-cell transcriptomes, TMPRSS2 labeling was observed in many constituents of <lb/>the nasal epithelium (Figures 4H, S4F, and S4G). <lb/>We sought to investigate whether the SARS-CoV-2 virus was present in sustentacular cells of patients in-<lb/>fected with the virus. The olfactory sensory epithelium of two deceased SARS-CoV-2-infected individuals <lb/>was analyzed. It was found to be highly damaged and largely detached from the basal lamina (Figure S5), <lb/>hindering the potential identification of viral particles in sustentacular cells. Whether this damage was <lb/>caused by the virus cannot be determined based on the few samples analyzed. However, a study of <lb/>SARS-CoV-2-infected Syrian hamsters showed infection of sustentacular cells and a massive desquamation <lb/>of the olfactory epithelium (Bryche et al., 2020). <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 Receptor Expression in the Brain <lb/>SARS-CoV (i.e., the virus responsible for the previous SARS epidemic in 2002), the genome of which is <lb/>closely related to the one of SARS-CoV-2 and whose effects on human tissues appear similar to those <lb/>observed with SARS-CoV-2, has been observed in human brains (Ding et al., 2004; Gu et al., 2005; Xu <lb/>et al., 2005). Could SARS-CoV-2 replicate in the olfactory epithelium and could the infection spread to <lb/>the brain? To explore the potential receptivity to SARS-CoV-2 infection of the various cell types in the brain, <lb/>we evaluated, again, the potential coexpression of ACE2 and TMPRSS2 in neuronal and non-neuronal cell <lb/>types in the central nervous system of both mice and humans. <lb/>For the mouse, we took advantage of two available single-cell RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) datasets (Saun-<lb/>ders et al., 2018; Zeisel et al., 2018), consisting in two broad collections of mouse brain cell types. In the first <lb/>collection, published by Zeisel et al. (2018), which includes non-neuronal cells, we found a very limited num-<lb/>ber of cell types that expressed Ace2 (Figure 5A). These cells are related to pericytes and coexpress the <lb/>mural cell marker Rgs5 (Figure 5B). Tmprss2, whose transcripts were barely detected, was expressed by <lb/>even fewer cell types (Figure 5A), with Purkinje cells displaying the highest expression level. These obser-<lb/>vations were confirmed by the second mouse dataset (Saunders et al., 2018), in which mural cells were the <lb/>main cell type that expressed Ace2 (Figure 5C). None of these cell populations coexpressed Tmprss2. <lb/>Although our data showed substantial expression of ACE2 in the mouse brain, they did not replicate the <lb/>widespread expression of ACE2 in the central nervous system previously reported by others, which found <lb/>ACE2 in the motor cortex, raphe, and nuclei involved in the regulation of cardiovascular function (Doobay <lb/>Figure 3. ACE2 expression in the Mouse Olfactory Neuroepithelium <lb/>(A) Schematic representation of the mouse olfactory system. The sensory tissue and the brain are highlighted in green. The blue frame indicates the coronal <lb/>section level corresponding to the next panels. OB, olfactory bulb; OE, olfactory epithelium. <lb/>(B) Schematic representation of a coronal section of the mouse olfactory system. The OE is highlighted in green, and the brain, including the olfactory bulb, <lb/>in light green. <lb/>(C-F) Immunostainings on coronal sections of mouse olfactory neuroepithelium with three different anti-ACE2 antibodies (red) and a negative control. (C) <lb/>ACE2 Ab1, polyclonal antibody against the extracellular domain of mouse ACE2. (D) ACE2 Ab2, polyclonal antibody against the intracellular domain of <lb/>human ACE2 (that cross reacts with mouse ACE2). (E) ACE2 Ab3, monoclonal antibody against the extracellular domain of human ACE2 (that cross reacts <lb/>with mouse ACE2). (F) Negative control immunostaining without primary antibody against ACE2. <lb/>(G) Immunostaining for ACE2 (red) on a coronal section of the mouse olfactory neuroepithelium. Scale bar, 0.2 mm. Squares indicate zones magnified in (H) <lb/>and (I). The schematic on the lower left indicates that ACE2 expression is observed in the dorsal (H), but not in the ventral part (I) of the olfactory epithelium. <lb/>(J) Double immunostaining for ACE2 (red) and the neuronal marker TUJ1 (green) in the ACE2-positive part of the mouse olfactory neuroepithelium. The <lb/>square indicates the portion of the MOE that is magnified in (K)-(R). Scale bar, 20 mm. <lb/>(K-N) Double immunostaining for ACE2 (red) together with (K) the neuronal marker TUJ1 (green), (L) the marker of mature olfactory sensory neurons OMP <lb/>(green), (M) the marker for sustentacular cells ERMN (green) and (N) TMPRSS2 (green). <lb/>(O and P) Negative control immunostaining without primary antibody against (O) ERMN and (P) TMPRSS2. <lb/>(Q and R) Double immunostaining for the sustentacular cell marker ERMN (red) together with (Q) OMP and (R) TUJ1. <lb/>(S) Schematic of the external part of the olfactory epithelium, highlighting the relative positions of ACE2, TUJ1, ERMN, and OMP according to the <lb/>immunostainings shown in (K)-(R). TUJ1 is present in the dendrites, axons, and somata of olfactory sensory neurons, OMP more concentrated in the cell body <lb/>of olfactory sensory neurons, and ACE2 and ERMN in the apical portion of sustentacular cells. All sections with immunostaining were counterstained with <lb/>DAPI (blue). When not indicated, scale bars are 10 mm. See also Figures S1-S3. <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note> 
			
			<note place="footnote">iScience 23, 101839, December 18, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">iScience <lb/>Article <lb/></note>
			
			<body>et al., 2007). To precisely evaluate the expression of ACE2 in the mouse brain, and in particular at the inter-<lb/>face with the olfactory sensory neuroepithelium, we performed an immunostaining of mouse olfactory bulb <lb/>sections with the three different anti-ACE2 antibodies. A strong labeling of capillary-associated cells was <lb/>observed through the different layers of the olfactory bulb (Figures 5D-5H), in agreement with the single-<lb/>cell RNA-seq observations. <lb/>Finally, we explored two single-nucleus RNA-seq datasets to evaluate ACE2 expression in the human brain. <lb/>In the first dataset (Lake et al. (2018)), we found neuronal and glial cell types, in particular Purkinje neurons <lb/>and cerebellar astrocytes, that expressed ACE2 or TMPRSS2 (Figures S6A-S6E). In the second dataset, <lb/>publicly available in the Allen Brain Map cell types database, we found expression of ACE2 (although at <lb/>relatively limited levels) in various non-neuronal and neuronal types, in particular astrocytes, oligodendro-<lb/>cytes, and neurons from the cortical layer 5 (Figures 6A-6G), a portion of which coexpressed TMPRSS2 (Fig-<lb/>ures 6C-6E). ACE2 and TMPRSS2 are therefore expressed in a number of cell types in the human brain. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>Facing the current pandemic, worldwide efforts have been made to better understand the molecular bases <lb/>of SARS-CoV-2 infection. Here, we aimed at investigating the distribution of the SARS-CoV-2 receptor <lb/>ACE-2 in the human olfactory neuroepithelium and in the brain. Other groups, whose results are mostly <lb/>in line with our findings, have also addressed parallel questions (Bilinska et al., 2020; Brann et al., 2020a, <lb/>2020b; Sungnak et al., 2020). <lb/>Taking a multidisciplinary approach, based both on our own and publicly available RNA-seq datasets, and <lb/>on immunohistochemical staining of mouse and human tissues, we demonstrate here that a subset of ol-<lb/>factory sustentacular cells in the olfactory neuroepithelium, but not olfactory sensory neurons, expresses <lb/>B <lb/>ACE2 TUJ1 <lb/>G <lb/>F <lb/>ACE2 <lb/>ACE2 TUJ1 <lb/>C <lb/>alcian blue <lb/>ERMN TUJ1 <lb/>A <lb/>TMPRSS2 TUJ1 <lb/>B <lb/>alcian blue <lb/>D <lb/>C <lb/>E <lb/>H <lb/>ACE2 TUJ1 <lb/>Figure 4. ACE2 Expression in the Human Olfactory Neuroepithelium <lb/>(A and B) Section of human respiratory epithelium with (A) immunostaining for ERMN (red) and the neuronal marker TUJ1 <lb/>(green), and (B) the same section stained with Alcian blue and counterstained with nuclear fast red, highlighting a <lb/>transition between sensory (left) and respiratory (right, note the goblet cells) epithelium. ERMN is expressed in the apical <lb/>part of sustentacular cells within the olfactory neuroepithelium (arrowheads). <lb/>(C, E) A portion of human olfactory neuroepithelium immunostained for ACE2 (red) and the neuronal marker TUJ1 (green), <lb/>and (D) with Alcian blue (note the absence of goblet cells). <lb/>(F, G) Higher magnification of the external border of the human olfactory neuroepithelium. The same region is shown with <lb/>(F) and without (G) TUJ1 staining. Nuclei were counterstained with DAPI (blue) or FastRed (red). Scale bars, 10 mm. See <lb/>also Figures S4 and S5. <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">iScience 23, 101839, December 18, 2020 <lb/></note> 
			
			<note place="headnote">iScience <lb/>Article <lb/></note>
			
			<body>Ace2 <lb/>Tmprss2 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>Fibroblast−Like (STR) <lb/>Mural_Fibroblast−Like (ENT) <lb/>Mural (SN) <lb/>Mural (TH) <lb/>Fibroblast−Like (CB) <lb/>Mural (GP) <lb/>Mural (FC) <lb/>Mural (PC) <lb/>Mural (HC) <lb/>Mural (STR) <lb/>TPM <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>Mouse brain cell types <lb/>Top 10 Ace2 expressing cell pop. <lb/>rel. expr. <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>B <lb/>Ace2 <lb/>Tmprss2 <lb/>PNS neurons <lb/>Immune <lb/>Vascular <lb/>Sensory <lb/>Astro-<lb/>ependymal <lb/>Cortex/HC <lb/>Cortex/HC <lb/>thalamus <lb/>GC <lb/>OB <lb/>CB <lb/>NBL <lb/>NBL <lb/>MSN <lb/>Symp. <lb/>Enteric <lb/>Cholinergic <lb/>Monoaminergic <lb/>Telencephalon <lb/>projecting <lb/>Telencephalon <lb/>inhibitory <lb/>Peptidergic <lb/>Spinal <lb/>cord <lb/>Di-/mesencephalon <lb/>Hindbrain <lb/>CNS neurons <lb/>Neurons <lb/>Non-neurons <lb/>Oligo-<lb/>dendrocyte <lb/>Rbfox3 <lb/>relative expr. <lb/>Vascular leptomeningeal cells <lb/>Vascular leptomeningeal cells <lb/>Vascular leptomeningeal cells <lb/>Vascular endothelial cells, arterial <lb/>Pericytes <lb/>Vascular smooth muscle cells, arterial <lb/>Pericytes <lb/>Pericytes, possibly mixed with VENC <lb/>Vascular endothelial cells, capillary <lb/>Vascular endothelial cells, venous <lb/>R b fo x 3 <lb/>R g s 5 <lb/>A c e 2 <lb/>T m p rs s 2 <lb/>24.1 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>ABC <lb/>VLMC2 <lb/>VLMC1 <lb/>VECA <lb/>PER3 <lb/>VSMCA <lb/>PER1 <lb/>PER2 <lb/>VECC <lb/>VECV <lb/>D <lb/>nl <lb/>gl <lb/>ml <lb/>gr <lb/>ACE2 (ab2) TUJ1 <lb/>E <lb/>OB <lb/>OE <lb/>OB <lb/>OE <lb/>gl <lb/>ml <lb/>gr <lb/>nl <lb/>ACE2 (ab3) OMP <lb/>F <lb/>G <lb/>H <lb/>ACE2 (ab1) TUJ1 <lb/>ACE2 (ab2) <lb/>Figure 5. Ace2 and Tmprss2 Expression in the Mouse Brain <lb/>(A) Mouse brain cell type classification from Zeisel et al. (2018) was visualized via http://mousebrain.org/. Rows with <lb/>shaded boxes below the tree indicate the gene mean expression levels for each cell type, relative to its maximum. Rbfox3, <lb/>encoding the neuronal marker NEUN, and Rgs5, a marker of pericytes, are shown in comparison with Ace2 and Tmprss2. <lb/>(B) Details of the gene expression levels in pericytes (blue edges clade of the classification dendrogram in (A)). Discs <lb/>represent mean relative expression levels. Maximum values of mean normalized expression levels for Rgs5 and Ace2 are <lb/>connected to the corresponding circles. <lb/>(C) Ace2 and Tmprss2 expression levels in the top 10 Ace2-expressing cell populations from the http://dropviz.org/ <lb/>dataset (Saunders et al., 2018). Abbreviations in parentheses denote the origin brain structure. STR, striatum; HC, <lb/>hippocampus; PC, posterior cortex; FC, frontal cortex; GP, globus pallidus; CB, cerebellum; TH, thalamus; SN, substantia <lb/>nigra; ENT, entopeduncular. <lb/>(D) Similar to Figure 3, subsequent panels show coronal sections (blue area) crossing the nasal cavity and the olfactory <lb/>bulb. As represented in this schematic, olfactory sensory neurons from the olfactory epithelium send axonal projections to <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">iScience 23, 101839, December 18, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">iScience <lb/>Article <lb/></note>
			
			<body>ACE2, the main player in the binding and entry of the SARS-CoV-2 into human cells. These cells were found <lb/>to coexpress TMPRSS2, a serine protease known to facilitate viral entry. We also found ACE2 expression in <lb/>specific cell types of the brain, including neuronal and non-neuronal cell types. <lb/>We first determined, using transcriptomic analyses of whole tissue and single cells from human olfactory <lb/>epithelia, that a subset of sustentacular cells expresses ACE2. We recently reported this finding as a pre-<lb/>print on BioRxiv (Fodoulian et al., 2020), which is in agreement with another preprint on the same server <lb/>(Brann et al., 2020a). We then confirmed this finding in mouse and human tissues by immunohistochemistry. <lb/>In the mouse, in which the olfactory mucosa is particularly well organized both in terms of pseudostratified <lb/>layers and in terms of its very strict separation from the respiratory epithelium, we observed (similarly to <lb/>humans) a clear expression of ACE2 in the apical border of sustentacular cells (in agreement with a very <lb/>recent report citing our BioRxiv article [Bilinska et al., 2020]). This distribution was, however, non-homog-<lb/>enous, since ACE2 was present in the most dorsally located sustentacular cells, but was entirely absent from <lb/>more ventrally located ones. Such dichotomy between the dorsal and the ventral neuroepithelium is remi-<lb/>niscent, in the mouse, of the dorsally located olfactory neurons, which are known to share molecular <lb/>markers that are dissimilar from those present in more ventral neurons (Gussing and Bohm, 2004). This <lb/>known contrast is not limited to the neuronal identities, since the function and response to stress of these <lb/>dorsally located neurons also appear to be different (Kobayakawa et al., 2007; Tuerdi et al., 2018). We now <lb/>add a non-neuronal cell type to this dorsoventral neural dichotomy. In the human olfactory neuroepithe-<lb/>lium, a similar labeling of ACE2 was observed in sustentacular cells, although the staining was mainly pre-<lb/>sent in the somata. Again, as observed in the mouse, some of these cells were positive and others were <lb/>negative for ACE2. These human ACE2-expressing sustentacular cells were found isolated or in small clus-<lb/>ters, intermingled with sustentacular cells negative for ACE2, or even sometimes intermingled with respi-<lb/>ratory epithelium, an expected observation given the relatively poor organization of the human olfactory <lb/>neuroepithelium, in particular in aged individuals. <lb/>How likely is it that the coexpression of ACE2 in olfactory sustentacular cells is involved in the SARS-CoV-2-<lb/>induced anosmia? And why are horizontal basal cells that also express ACE2 not prime candidates? First, <lb/>given the slow rate of neuronal renewal in the main olfactory epithelium (a few months) and the apparent <lb/>rapid development of SARS-CoV-2-triggered anosmia, a perturbation of the stem cell pool constituted by <lb/>the horizontal basal cells appears unlikely to represent an immediate disturbance to the system. Second, <lb/>the amounts of ACE2 transcripts as well as the intensity of the immunohistological staining we observed in <lb/>sustentacular cells are in the same range as the ones observed in respiratory ciliated cells, suggesting at <lb/>least that sustentacular cells play in the same league in terms of SARS-CoV-2 receptors. Third, sustentacular <lb/>cells are in direct contact with the olfactory cavity and thus interact with everything that enters the nose. <lb/>Fourth, sustentacular cells play a critical role in the maintenance of the olfactory neuroepithelium integrity: <lb/>their loss or suffering would cause disaggregation or malfunctioning of the neuroepithelium, respectively, <lb/>leading to anosmia. Supporting this, SARS-CoV-2 infection of golden hamsters via the nasal route leads to <lb/>massive damage of the olfactory neuroepithelium (Bryche et al., 2020). Finally, given that the role played by <lb/>ACE2 in sustentacular cells is unknown, the hijack of this receptor by SARS-CoV-2 may by itself perturb the <lb/>functioning of the olfactory sensor. Taken together, and despite the fact that one cannot exclude inflam-<lb/>mation and the infection of other non-neuronal cell types in the olfactory neuroepithelium as an origin <lb/>of the SARS-CoV-2-induced anosmia, the link between the viral molecular entry tools expressed by olfac-<lb/>tory sustentacular cells and the SARS-CoV-2-induced chemosensory alteration appears quite credible. <lb/>The idea that viruses may affect directly or indirectly the integrity and function of the sensory part of the olfac-<lb/>tory system is not new. Some viruses indeed disturb the neuroepithelium in different ways, and often alter spe-<lb/>cific cell types, including neurons. For example, and among many others, olfactory sensory neurons and sus-<lb/>tentacular cells were shown to be major portals of host entry of the Murid Herpesvirus-4 (MuHV-4) (Milho et al., <lb/>2012). Again, the direct contact of this latter cell type with the respiratory tract, as well as its phagocytic activity, <lb/>Figure 5. Continued <lb/>the olfactory bulb through the cribriform plate of the ethmoid bone, along the nerve layer. OB, olfactory bulb; OE, <lb/>olfactory epithelium; nl, nerve layer; gl, glomerular layer; ml, mitral cell layer; gr, granule cell layer. <lb/>(E-G) Immunostaining for ACE2 (red) and for the neuronal marker TUJ1 (green) on sections of the mouse olfactory bulb. <lb/>White arrowheads indicate the presence of ACE2 in the pericytes of capillaries. Scale bars, 20 mm. <lb/>(H) Magnification of capillary ACE2 immunostaining (red). Scale bar, 5 mm. All sections were counterstained with DAPI <lb/>(blue). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">iScience 23, 101839, December 18, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">iScience <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<body>Cluster IDs (# cells) <lb/>L4 IT (3725) <lb/>IT (21841) <lb/>L5/6 IT Car3 (1053) <lb/>L6 CT (2556) <lb/>L6b (1080) <lb/>L5 ET (158) <lb/>L5/6 NP (816) <lb/>Excitatory neurons <lb/>LAMP5 (2434) <lb/>PAX6 (325) <lb/>VIP (3533) <lb/>SST (2358) <lb/>PVALB (2800) <lb/>Inhibitory neurons <lb/>Astrocyte (1187) <lb/>OPC (773) <lb/>Oligodendrocyte (1930) <lb/>Endothelial (70) <lb/>VLMC (11) <lb/>Pericyte (32) <lb/>Microglia (750) <lb/>Non-neuronal <lb/>t−SNE 1 (a.u.) <lb/>t−SNE <lb/>2 (a.u.) <lb/>A <lb/>0 <lb/>5 9 <lb/>norm. expr <lb/>RBFOX3 <lb/>B <lb/>0 <lb/>1 5 <lb/>norm. expr <lb/>ACE2 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>norm. expr <lb/>TMPRSS2 <lb/>C <lb/>ACE2/TMPRSS2 <lb/>D <lb/>Astrocyte <lb/>Endothelial <lb/>L4 IT <lb/>L5 ET <lb/>L5/6 NP <lb/>Microglia <lb/>Oligodendrocyte <lb/>OPC <lb/>0 <lb/>0.005 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.016 <lb/>0.031 <lb/>ACE2 (mean expression) <lb/>TMPRSS2 (mean expression) <lb/>E <lb/>F <lb/>0 <lb/>1300 <lb/>ACE2 <lb/>0 <lb/>1200 <lb/>Expressing cells (#) <lb/>TMPRSS2 <lb/>0 <lb/>90 <lb/>L 4 <lb/>I T <lb/>I T <lb/>L 5 / 6 <lb/>I T <lb/>C <lb/>a r 3 <lb/>L 6 <lb/>C <lb/>T <lb/>L 6 b <lb/>L 5 <lb/>E T <lb/>L 5 / 6 <lb/>N <lb/>P <lb/>L A M <lb/>P 5 <lb/>P A X 6 <lb/>V I P <lb/>S S T <lb/>P V A L B <lb/>A s t r o c y t e <lb/>O <lb/>P C <lb/>O <lb/>li g o d e n d r o c y t e <lb/>E n d o t h e li a l <lb/>V L M <lb/>C <lb/>P e r ic <lb/>y t e <lb/>M <lb/>ic <lb/>r o g li a <lb/>ACE2/TMPRSS2 <lb/>G <lb/>0 <lb/>8 <lb/>ACE2 <lb/>0 <lb/>8 <lb/>Expressing cells (%) <lb/>TMPRSS2 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>L 4 <lb/>I T <lb/>I T <lb/>L 5 / 6 <lb/>I T <lb/>C <lb/>a r 3 <lb/>L 6 <lb/>C <lb/>T <lb/>L 6 b <lb/>L 5 / 6 <lb/>N <lb/>P <lb/>L A M <lb/>P 5 <lb/>V I P <lb/>S S T <lb/>P V A L B <lb/>A s t r o c y t e <lb/>O <lb/>P C <lb/>O <lb/>li g o d e n d r o c y t e <lb/>M <lb/>ic <lb/>r o g li a <lb/>ACE2/TMPRSS2 <lb/>Figure 6. Coexpression of ACE2 and TMPRSS2 in the Human Brain <lb/>(A) Visualization of the human brain cell-type subclasses on a t-distributed stochastic neighbor embedding (t-SNE) plot. a.u., arbitrary units. <lb/>(B and C) Normalized expression levels of (B) RBFOX3 (which encodes for the neuronal marker NEUN), (C) ACE2 and TMPRSS2, shown on the t-SNE plot. <lb/>norm. expr, normalized expression levels. <lb/>(D) ACE2 and TMPRSS2 coexpressing cells, highlighted in black on the t-SNE plot. <lb/>(E) Coexpression of ACE2 and TMPRSS2 in the different subclasses (n = 19 subclasses). Means of ACE2 and TMPRSS2 normalized expression levels are <lb/>plotted. <lb/>(F) Number of cells per subclass expressing ACE2 and/or TMPRSS2. <lb/>(G) Percentage of cells per subclass expressing ACE2 and/or TMPRSS2 in all coexpressing subclasses (i.e., subclasses with double-positive cells). Color <lb/>gradient scales in (B) and (C) are in log 10 . L, cortical layer; IT, intratelencephalic; CT, corticothalamic; ET, extratelencephalic; NP, near-projecting; LAMP5, <lb/>lysosomal-associated membrane protein family member 5; PAX6, paired box 6; VIP, vasoactive intestinal polypeptide; SST, somatostatin; PVALB, <lb/>parvalbumin; OPC, oligodendrocyte precursor cell; VLMC, vascular leptomeningeal cell. See also Figure S6. <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">iScience <lb/>Article <lb/>iScience 23, 101839, December 18, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">iScience <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<body>may explain its particular sensitivity to viral infection. The cell type targeted by viruses matters, in particular to <lb/>fight infection using drugs. For instance, in the case of a MuHV-4 challenge, olfactory sensory neurons are not <lb/>responsive to interferon treatment (IFNg), whereas sustentacular cells are (Jacobs et al., 2019). <lb/>SARS-CoV-2-infection has not only been linked to the loss of a single chemosensory ability. Indeed, in addition <lb/>to anosmia, ageusia has also been reported (Cooper et al., 2020; Giacomelli et al., 2020). Whether these re-<lb/>ports truly reflect taste anomalies or rather olfactory perturbations that may drastically affect the flavor of <lb/>food is unclear. However, this potential double effect on two chemosensory systems that share nothing at <lb/>the periphery may suggest a more central alteration, involving, for example, a direct infection of the brain <lb/>by SARS-CoV-2. But this would require potential targets. We identified various cell types in the brain that ex-<lb/>press ACE2, although at relatively low levels in humans. In the mouse, we detected ACE2 expression in brain <lb/>vascular endothelial cells and pericytes, but not in neurons. In humans, we found ACE2 transcripts in non-<lb/>neuronal cell types such as astrocytes and microglia, and also in neurons, in particular Purkinje and cortical <lb/>layer 5 neurons. Whether these different cell types reflect differences in tissue specificity between the two <lb/>mammalian species is unclear, since RNA-seq discordances may result from differences in the sequencing <lb/>depth, sequencing protocols (single-nucleus versus single-cell RNA-seq), dissimilar mRNA half-lives, or vari-<lb/>able cell type selection strategies between the different studies. But whatever the reason for the discordances, <lb/>these data point to potential targets for SARS-CoV-2 infection in brain cells. <lb/>Similar to the infection of the olfactory neuroepithelium by SARS-CoV-2, the transport of viral particles from <lb/>the olfactory mucosa to the brain would not be a first. In 1935 already, the olfactory route was hypothesized <lb/>(because of its direct connection with the brain) to represent a portal for entry of viruses into the central <lb/>nervous system (Flexner, 1936). We know today that the olfactory nerve route is indeed used by various vi-<lb/>ruses to reach the brain, including HSV1, poliovirus, MHV (a coronavirus), paramyxoviruses, Hendra virus, <lb/>Nipah virus, influenza virus, adenoviruses, bunyaviruses, and VSV (Durrant et al., 2016). <lb/>Although most pathogenic microorganisms appear to access the CNS via the axons of olfactory sensory <lb/>neurons, other routes of entry through the cribriform plate have been described. For instance, the ameba <lb/>Naegleria fowleri penetrates the olfactory epithelium either via sustentacular cells or in a paracellular way <lb/>and then travels along the nerve bundle through the cribriform plate (Jarolim et al., 2000). Moreover, the <lb/>bacterium Burkholderia pseudomallei causes a widespread loss of OSNs, which leads to the degeneration <lb/>of the olfactory nerves (St John et al., 2014). B. pseudomallei then migrates along the empty conduits of <lb/>olfactory nerves toward the CNS. An even more convincing example may be the neurotropic MHV virus, <lb/>which is found in high concentrations within the perineurium of the olfactory nerve and in the brain after <lb/>nasal infection (Barthold, 1988) (olfactory sensory neurons lack the main MHV virus receptor CEACAM1 <lb/>[Brann et al., 2020b; Miura et al., 2008). <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 virions have in fact been observed in the human olfactory bulb (Nampoothiri et al., 2020). <lb/>SARS-CoV particles have also been found in the human brain (Ding et al., 2004; Gu et al., 2005; Xu et al., <lb/>2005). Adding to these observations, brain lesions were observed in a transgenic mouse model expressing <lb/>the human ACE2 in the nose and infected intranasally with SARS-CoV (Netland et al., 2008). Moreover, a <lb/>retrospective case study on 214 patients with COVID-19 reported neurological manifestations possibly <lb/>correlated with the severity of the disease (Mao et al., 2020) (with the confounding factor that old people <lb/>are more likely to develop severe disease). As worrying are suggestions that a subset of patients infected <lb/>with the virus but lacking respiratory symptoms may exhibit neurologic symptoms (Wang et al., 2020b) and <lb/>that they may be associated with encephalitis (Moriguchi et al., 2020; Poyiadji et al., 2020), Miller Fisher syn-<lb/>drome, and polyneuritis cranialis (Gutierrez-Ortiz et al., 2020). Given, as we showed here, the presence in <lb/>the human brain of various neuronal and non-neuronal cell populations expressing ACE2, this certainly ap-<lb/>pears to be a line of investigation worth pursuing. <lb/>Limitations of the Study <lb/>We investigated whether the SARS-CoV-2 virus was present in sustentacular cells of patients infected with <lb/>the virus. We analyzed the olfactory sensory epithelium of two deceased SARS-CoV-2-infected individuals. <lb/>However, the epithelium was found to be highly damaged and largely detached from the basal lamina, hin-<lb/>dering the potential identification of viral particles in sustentacular cells. Hence, we could not determine <lb/>whether the SARS-CoV-2 virus is indeed present in sustentacular cells of infected patients. Whether the his-<lb/>tological damage was caused by the virus cannot be determined based on the few samples analyzed. <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>
			
			<page>12 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">iScience 23, 101839, December 18, 2020 <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="headnote">iScience <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<div type="availability">Resource Availability <lb/>Lead Contact <lb/> Further information and requests for resources and reagents should be directed to and will be fulfilled by <lb/>the Lead Contact, Ivan Rodriguez (ivan.rodriguez@unige.ch). <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Materials Availability <lb/>This study did not generate new unique reagents. <lb/></div>
			
			<div type="availability">Data and Code Availability <lb/>All datasets generated during and/or analyzed during the current study have been deposited in Mendeley <lb/>Data (https://doi.org/10.17632/4cynjrymgf.1) and NCBI GEO: GSE151973. All codes used for the analyses <lb/>of the data reported in this manuscript are provided at the GitHub repository https://github.com/ <lb/>leonfodoulian/SARS_CoV_2_anosmia. <lb/></div>
			
			<div type="annex">METHODS <lb/>All methods can be found in the accompanying Transparent Methods supplemental file. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">SUPPLEMENTAL INFORMATION <lb/>Supplemental Information can be found online at https://doi.org/10.1016/j.isci.2020.101839. <lb/></div>
			
			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>We thank the iGE3 Genomics Platform at the University of Geneva for expert technical assistance during <lb/>RNA-seq experiments. This research was supported by the University of Geneva and the Swiss National Sci-<lb/>ence Foundation (grant numbers 31003A_172878 to A.C. and 310030_189153 to I.R.). <lb/></div>
			
			<div type="annex">AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS <lb/>L.F., J.T., M.B., D.R., C.K., and V.P. acquired and analyzed data. L.F. performed bulk, single-cell, and single-<lb/>nucleus RNA-seq data analysis. J.T. performed bulk RNA-seq data analysis, mouse brain cell database <lb/>mining, and confocal microscopy. D.R. generated the human bulk RNA-seq dataset. M.B. performed <lb/>immunohistochemical staining and epifluorescence microscopy with help from C.K. and V.P. K.E., J.A.L., <lb/>and B.N.L. collected human biopsies. L.F., J.T., M.B., D.R., A.C., and I.R. carried out the conceptualization <lb/>and experimental design. A.C. and I.R. wrote the manuscript with comments from all the other authors. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">DECLARATION OF INTERESTS <lb/>The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<front>Received: August 7, 2020 <lb/>Revised: September 25, 2020 <lb/>Accepted: November 18, 2020 <lb/>Published: December 18, 2020 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>Barthold, S.W. (1988). Olfactory neural pathway in <lb/>mouse hepatitis virus nasoencephalitis. Acta <lb/>Neuropathol. 76, 502-506. <lb/>Bauernfeind, A.L., and Babbitt, C.C. (2017). The <lb/>predictive nature of transcript expression levels <lb/>on protein expression in adult human brain. BMC <lb/>Genomics 18, 322. <lb/>Bergstrom, U., Giovanetti, A., Piras, E., and <lb/>Brittebo, E.B. (2003). Methimazole-induced <lb/>damage in the olfactory mucosa: effects on <lb/>ultrastructure and glutathione levels. Toxicol. <lb/>Pathol. 31, 379-387. <lb/>Bertram, S., Heurich, A., Lavender, H., <lb/>Gierer, S., Danisch, S., Perin, P., Lucas, J.M., <lb/>Nelson, P.S., Pohlmann, S., and Soilleux, E.J. <lb/>(2012). Influenza and SARS-coronavirus <lb/>activating proteases TMPRSS2 and HAT are <lb/>expressed at multiple sites in human <lb/>respiratory and gastrointestinal tracts. PLoS <lb/>One 7, e35876. <lb/>Bilinska, K., Jakubowska, P., Von Bartheld, C.S., <lb/>and Butowt, R. (2020). Expression of the SARS-<lb/>CoV-2 entry proteins, ACE2 and TMPRSS2, in <lb/>cells of the olfactory epithelium: identification of <lb/>cell types and trends with age. ACS Chem. <lb/>Neurosci. 11, 1555-1562. <lb/>Brann, D., Tsukahara, T., Weinreb, C., Logan, <lb/>D., and Datta, S. (2020a). Non-neural <lb/>expression of SARS-CoV-2 entry genes in the <lb/>olfactory epithelium suggests mechanisms <lb/>underlying anosmia in COVID-19 patients. <lb/>bioRxiv. https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.03.25. <lb/>009084. <lb/>Brann, D.H., Tsukahara, T., Weinreb, C., Lipovsek, <lb/>M., Van den Berge, K., Gong, B., Chance, R., <lb/>Macaulay, I.C., Chou, H.J., Fletcher, R.B., et al. <lb/>(2020b). Non-neuronal expression of SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>entry genes in the olfactory system suggests <lb/>mechanisms underlying COVID-19-associated <lb/>anosmia. Sci. Adv. 6, eabc5801. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">iScience 23, 101839, December 18, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">iScience <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Bryche, B., St Albin, A., Murri, S., Laco ˆte, S., <lb/>Pulido, C., Ar Gouilh, M., Lesellier, S., Servat, A., <lb/>Wasniewski, M., Picard-Meyer, E., et al. (2020). <lb/>Massive transient damage of the olfactory <lb/>epithelium associated with infection of <lb/>sustentacular cells by SARS-CoV-2 in golden <lb/>Syrian hamsters. Brain Behav. Immun. 89, <lb/>579-586. <lb/>Chan, J.F.-W., Yuan, S., Kok, K.-H., To, K.K.-W., <lb/>Chu, H., Yang, J., Xing, F., Liu, J., Yip, C.C.-Y., <lb/>Poon, R.W.-S., et al. (2020). A familial cluster of <lb/>pneumonia associated with the 2019 novel <lb/>coronavirus indicating person-to-person <lb/>transmission: a study of a family cluster. Lancet <lb/>395, 514-523. <lb/>Cooper, K.W., Brann, D.H., Farruggia, M.C., <lb/>Bhutani, S., Pellegrino, R., Tsukahara, T., Weinreb, <lb/>C., Joseph, P.V., Larson, E.D., Parma, V., et al. <lb/>(2020). COVID-19 and the chemical senses: <lb/>supporting players take center stage. Neuron <lb/>107, 219-233. <lb/>Ding, Y., He, L., Zhang, Q., Huang, Z., Che, X., <lb/>Hou, J., Wang, H., Shen, H., Qiu, L., Li, Z., et al. <lb/>(2004). Organ distribution of severe acute <lb/>respiratory syndrome (SARS) associated <lb/>coronavirus (SARS-CoV) in SARS patients: <lb/>implications for pathogenesis and virus <lb/>transmission pathways. J. Pathol. 203, 622-630. <lb/>Doobay, M.F., Talman, L.S., Obr, T.D., Tian, X., <lb/>Davisson, R.L., and Lazartigues, E. (2007). <lb/>Differential expression of neuronal ACE2 in <lb/>transgenic mice with overexpression of the brain <lb/>renin-angiotensin system. Am. J. Physiol. Regul. <lb/>Integr. Comp. Physiol. 292, R373-R381. <lb/>Durante, M.A., Kurtenbach, S., Sargi, Z.B., <lb/>Harbour, J.W., Choi, R., Kurtenbach, S., Goss, <lb/>G.M., Matsunami, H., and Goldstein, B.J. (2020). <lb/>Single-cell analysis of olfactory neurogenesis and <lb/>differentiation in adult humans. Nat. Neurosci. 23, <lb/>323-326. <lb/>Durrant, D.M., Ghosh, S., and Klein, R.S. (2016). <lb/>The olfactory bulb: an immunosensory effector <lb/>organ during neurotropic viral infections. ACS <lb/>Chem. Neurosci. 7, 464-469. <lb/>Flexner, S. (1936). Respiratory versus gastro-<lb/>intestinal infection in poliomyelitis. J. Exp. Med. <lb/>63, 209-226. <lb/>Fodoulian, L., Tuberosa, J., Rossier, D., Boillat, <lb/>M., Kan, C., Pauli, V., Egervari, K., Lobrinus, J.A., <lb/>Landis, B.N., Carleton, A., et al. (2020). SARS-<lb/>CoV-2 receptor and entry genes are expressed by <lb/>sustentacular cells in the human olfactory <lb/>neuroepithelium. bioRxiv. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1101/2020.03.31.013268. <lb/>Giacomelli, A., Pezzati, L., Conti, F., Bernacchia, <lb/>D., Siano, M., Oreni, L., Rusconi, S., Gervasoni, C., <lb/>Ridolfo, A., Rizzardini, G., et al. (2020). Self-<lb/>reported olfactory and taste disorders in SARS-<lb/>CoV-2 patients: a cross-sectional study. Clin. <lb/>Infect. Dis. 71, 889-890. <lb/>Gu, J., Gong, E., Zhang, B., Zheng, J., Gao, Z., <lb/>Zhong, Y., Zou, W., Zhan, J., Wang, S., Xie, Z., <lb/>et al. (2005). Multiple organ infection and the <lb/>pathogenesis of SARS. J. Exp. Med. 202, 415-424. <lb/>Gussing, F., and Bohm, S. (2004). NQO1 activity in <lb/>the main and the accessory olfactory systems <lb/>correlates with the zonal topography of <lb/>projection maps. Eur. J. Neurosci. 19, 2511-2518. <lb/>Gutierrez-Ortiz, C., Mendez, A., Rodrigo-Rey, S., <lb/>San Pedro-Murillo, E., Bermejo-Guerrero, L., <lb/>Gordo-Manas, R., de Aragon-Gomez, F., and <lb/>Benito-Leon, J. (2020). Miller Fisher Syndrome <lb/>and polyneuritis cranialis in COVID-19. <lb/>Neurology 95, e601-e605. <lb/>Heidari, F., Karimi, E., Firouzifar, M., Khamushian, <lb/>P., Ansari, R., Mohammadi Ardehali, M., and <lb/>Heidari, F. (2020). Anosmia as a prominent <lb/>symptom of COVID-19 infection. Rhinology 58, <lb/>302-303. <lb/>Hoffmann, M., Kleine-Weber, H., Schroeder, S., <lb/>Kruger, N., Herrler, T., Erichsen, S., Schiergens, <lb/>T.S., Herrler, G., Wu, N.-H., Nitsche, A., et al. <lb/>(2020). SARS-CoV-2 cell entry depends on ACE2 <lb/>and TMPRSS2 and is blocked by a clinically <lb/>proven protease inhibitor. Cell 181, 271-280.e8. <lb/>Hopkins, C., Surda, P., and Kumar, N. (2020). <lb/>Presentation of new onset anosmia during the <lb/>COVID-19 pandemic. Rhinology 58, 295-298. <lb/>Huang, C., Wang, Y., Li, X., Ren, L., Zhao, J., Hu, <lb/>Y., Zhang, L., Fan, G., Xu, J., Gu, X., et al. (2020). <lb/>Clinical features of patients infected with 2019 <lb/>novel coronavirus in Wuhan, China. Lancet 395, <lb/>497-506. <lb/>Jacobs, S., Zeippen, C., Wavreil, F., Gillet, L., and <lb/>Michiels, T. (2019). IFN-lambda decreases murid <lb/>herpesvirus-4 infection of the olfactory epithelium <lb/>but fails to prevent virus reactivation in the vaginal <lb/>mucosa. Viruses 11, 757. <lb/>Jarolim, K.L., McCosh, J.K., Howard, M.J., and <lb/>John, D.T. (2000). A light microscopy study of the <lb/>migration of Naegleria fowleri from the nasal <lb/>submucosa to the central nervous system during <lb/>the early stage of primary amebic <lb/>meningoencephalitis in mice. J. Parasitol. 86, <lb/>50-55. <lb/>Jia, C., Roman, C., and Hegg, C.C. (2010). Nickel <lb/>sulfate induces location-dependent atrophy of <lb/>mouse olfactory epithelium: protective and <lb/>proliferative role of purinergic receptor <lb/>activation. Toxicol. Sci. 115, 547-556. <lb/>Kobayakawa, K., Kobayakawa, R., Matsumoto, H., <lb/>Oka, Y., Imai, T., Ikawa, M., Okabe, M., Ikeda, T., <lb/>Itohara, S., Kikusui, T., et al. (2007). Innate versus <lb/>learned odour processing in the mouse olfactory <lb/>bulb. Nature 450, 503-508. <lb/>Kryuchkova-Mostacci, N., and Robinson-Rechavi, <lb/>M. (2016). Tissue-specificity of gene expression <lb/>diverges slowly between orthologs, and rapidly <lb/>between paralogs. PLoS Comput. Biol. 12, <lb/>e1005274. <lb/>Lake, B.B., Chen, S., Sos, B.C., Fan, J., Kaeser, <lb/>G.E., Yung, Y.C., Duong, T.E., Gao, D., Chun, J., <lb/>Kharchenko, P.V., et al. (2018). Integrative single-<lb/>cell analysis of transcriptional and epigenetic <lb/>states in the human adult brain. Nat. Biotechnol. <lb/>36, 70-80. <lb/>Letko, M., Marzi, A., and Munster, V. (2020). <lb/>Functional assessment of cell entry and receptor <lb/>usage for SARS-CoV-2 and other lineage B <lb/>betacoronaviruses. Nat. Microbiol. 5, 562-569. <lb/>Liang, F. (2018). Olfactory receptor neuronal <lb/>dendrites become mostly intra-sustentacularly <lb/>enwrapped upon maturity. J. Anat. 232, 674-685. <lb/>Liao, B.-Y., and Zhang, J. (2006). Evolutionary <lb/>conservation of expression profiles between <lb/>human and mouse orthologous genes. Mol. Biol. <lb/>Evol. 23, 530-540. <lb/>Liu, Y., Beyer, A., and Aebersold, R. (2016). On the <lb/>dependency of cellular protein levels on mRNA <lb/>abundance. Cell 165, 535-550. <lb/>Luers, J.C., Rokohl, A.C., Loreck, N., Wawer <lb/>Matos, P.A., Augustin, M., Dewald, F., Klein, F., <lb/>Lehmann, C., and Heindl, L.M. (2020). Olfactory <lb/>and gustatory dysfunction in coronavirus disease <lb/>2019 (COVID-19). Clin. Infect. Dis. 71, 2262-2264. <lb/>Mao, L., Wang, M., Chen, S., He, Q., Chang, J., <lb/>Hong, C., Zhou, Y., Wang, D., Li, Y., Jin, H., et al. <lb/>(2020). Neurological manifestations of <lb/>hospitalized patients with COVID-19 in Wuhan, <lb/>China: a retrospective case series study. medRxiv. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.22.20026500. <lb/>Menni, C., Valdes, A.M., Freidin, M.B., Sudre, <lb/>C.H., Nguyen, L.H., Drew, D.A., Ganesh, S., <lb/>Varsavsky, T., Cardoso, M.J., El-Sayed Moustafa, <lb/>J.S., et al. (2020). Real-time tracking of self-<lb/>reported symptoms to predict potential COVID-<lb/>19. Nat. Med. 26, 1037-1040. <lb/>Milho, R., Frederico, B., Efstathiou, S., and <lb/>Stevenson, P.G. (2012). A heparan-dependent <lb/>herpesvirus targets the olfactory neuroepithelium <lb/>for host entry. PLoS Pathog. 8, e1002986. <lb/>Miller, M.A., and O&apos;Bryan, M.A. (2003). <lb/>Ultrastructural changes and olfactory deficits <lb/>during 3-methylindole-induced olfactory mucosal <lb/>necrosis and repair in mice. Ultrastruct. Pathol. 27, <lb/>13-21. <lb/>Miura, T.A., Travanty, E.A., Oko, L., Bielefeldt-<lb/>Ohmann, H., Weiss, S.R., Beauchemin, N., and <lb/>Holmes, K.V. (2008). The spike glycoprotein of <lb/>murine coronavirus MHV-JHM mediates <lb/>receptor-independent infection and spread in <lb/>the central nervous systems of Ceacam1a-/-Mice. <lb/>J. Virol. 82, 755-763. <lb/>Moein, S.T., Hashemian, S.M.R., Mansourafshar, <lb/>B., Khorram-Tousi, A., Tabarsi, P., and Doty, R.L. <lb/>(2020). Smell dysfunction: a biomarker for COVID-<lb/>19. Int. Forum Allergy Rhinol. 10, 944-950. <lb/>Moriguchi, T., Harii, N., Goto, J., Harada, D., <lb/>Sugawara, H., Takamino, J., Ueno, M., Sakata, H., <lb/>Kondo, K., Myose, N., et al. (2020). A first case of <lb/>meningitis/encephalitis associated with SARS-<lb/>coronavirus-2. Int. J. Infect. Dis. 94, 55-58. <lb/>Moulton, D.G., and Beidler, L.M. (1967). Structure <lb/>and function in the peripheral olfactory system. <lb/>Physiol. Rev. 47, 1-52. <lb/>Nampoothiri, S., Sauve, F., Ternier, G., <lb/>Fernandois, D., Coelho, C., Imbernon, M., <lb/>Deligia, E., Perbet, R., Florent, V., Baroncini, M., <lb/>et al. (2020). The hypothalamus as a hub for SARS-<lb/>CoV-2 brain infection and pathogenesis. bioRxiv. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.06.08.139329. <lb/>Netland, J., Meyerholz, D.K., Moore, S., Cassell, <lb/>M., and Perlman, S. (2008). Severe acute <lb/>respiratory syndrome coronavirus infection <lb/>causes neuronal death in the absence of <lb/>encephalitis in mice transgenic for human ACE2. <lb/>J. Virol. 82, 7264-7275. <lb/>Ou, X., Liu, Y., Lei, X., Li, P., Mi, D., Ren, L., Guo, L., <lb/>Guo, R., Chen, T., Hu, J., et al. (2020). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">iScience 23, 101839, December 18, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">iScience <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Characterization of spike glycoprotein of SARS-<lb/>CoV-2 on virus entry and its immune cross-<lb/>reactivity with SARS-CoV. Nat. Commun. 11, <lb/>1620. <lb/>Paterson, R.W., Brown, R.L., Benjamin, L., Nortley, <lb/>R., Wiethoff, S., Bharucha, T., Jayaseelan, D.L., <lb/>Kumar, G., Raftopoulos, R.E., Zambreanu, L., et al. <lb/>(2020). The emerging spectrum of COVID-19 <lb/>neurology: clinical, radiological and laboratory <lb/>findings. Brain 143, 3104-3120. <lb/>Perrigo, B. (2020). Why Losing Your Sense of <lb/>Smell Could Be a Symptom of COVID-19 (Time). <lb/>Poyiadji, N., Shahin, G., Noujaim, D., Stone, M., <lb/>Patel, S., and Griffith, B. (2020). COVID-19-<lb/>associated acute hemorrhagic necrotizing <lb/>encephalopathy: CT and MRI features. Radiology <lb/>296, E119-E120. <lb/>Saunders, A., Macosko, E.Z., Wysoker, A., <lb/>Goldman, M., Krienen, F.M., de Rivera, H., Bien, <lb/>E., Baum, M., Bortolin, L., Wang, S., et al. (2018). <lb/>Molecular diversity and specializations among <lb/>the cells of the adult mouse brain. Cell 174, 1015-<lb/>1030.e16. <lb/>Shang, J., Wan, Y., Luo, C., Ye, G., Geng, Q., <lb/>Auerbach, A., and Li, F. (2020). Cell entry <lb/>mechanisms of SARS-CoV-2. Proceedings of the <lb/>National Academy of Sciences of the United <lb/>States of America. <lb/>Shi, J., Wen, Z., Zhong, G., Yang, H., Wang, C., <lb/>Huang, B., Liu, R., He, X., Shuai, L., Sun, Z., et al. <lb/>(2020). Susceptibility of Ferrets, Cats, Dogs, and <lb/>Other Domesticated Animals to SARS-<lb/>Coronavirus 2 (Science). <lb/>Smith, T.D., and Bhatnagar, K.P. (2019). Anatomy <lb/>of the olfactory system. Handb. Clin. Neurol. 164, <lb/>17-28. <lb/>Spinato, G., Fabbris, C., Polesel, J., Cazzador, D., <lb/>Borsetto, D., Hopkins, C., and Boscolo-Rizzo, P. <lb/>(2020). Alterations in smell or taste in mildly <lb/>symptomatic outpatients with SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>infection. JAMA 323, 2089-2090. <lb/>St John, J.A., Ekberg, J.A., Dando, S.J., <lb/>Meedeniya, A.C., Horton, R.E., Batzloff, M., <lb/>Owen, S.J., Holt, S., Peak, I.R., Ulett, G.C., et al. <lb/>(2014). Burkholderia pseudomallei penetrates the <lb/>brain via destruction of the olfactory and <lb/>trigeminal nerves: implications for the <lb/>pathogenesis of neurological melioidosis. mBio <lb/>5, e00025. <lb/>Sungnak, W., Huang, N., Becavin, C., Berg, M., <lb/>Queen, R., Litvinukova, M., Talavera-Lopez, C., <lb/>Maatz, H., Reichart, D., Sampaziotis, F., et al. <lb/>(2020). SARS-CoV-2 entry factors are highly <lb/>expressed in nasal epithelial cells together with <lb/>innate immune genes. Nat. Med. 26, 681-687. <lb/>Tuerdi, A., Kikuta, S., Kinoshita, M., Kamogashira, <lb/>T., Kondo, K., Iwasaki, S., and Yamasoba, T. <lb/>(2018). Dorsal-zone-specific reduction of sensory <lb/>neuron density in the olfactory epithelium <lb/>following long-term exercise or caloric restriction. <lb/>Sci. Rep. 8, 17300. <lb/>Walls, A.C., Park, Y.-J., Tortorici, M.A., Wall, A., <lb/>McGuire, A.T., and Veesler, D. (2020). Structure, <lb/>function, and antigenicity of the SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>spike glycoprotein. Cell 181, 281-292.e6. <lb/>Wang, C., Horby, P.W., Hayden, F.G., and Gao, <lb/>G.F. (2020a). A novel coronavirus outbreak of <lb/>global health concern. Lancet 395, 470-473. <lb/>Wang, H.-Y., Li, X.-L., Yan, Z.-R., Sun, X.-P., Han, <lb/>J., and Zhang, B.-W. (2020b). Potential <lb/>neurological symptoms of COVID-19. Ther. Adv. <lb/>Neurol. Disord. 13, 1756286420917830. <lb/>Wang, K., Chen, W., Zhou, Y.-S., Lian, J.-Q., <lb/>Zhang, Z., Du, P., Gong, L., Zhang, Y., Cui, H.-Y., <lb/>Geng, J.-J., et al. (2020c). SARS-CoV-2 invades <lb/>host cells via a novel route: CD147-spike protein. <lb/>bioRxiv. https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.03.14. <lb/>988345. <lb/>Xu, J., Zhong, S., Liu, J., Li, L., Li, Y., Wu, X., Li, Z., <lb/>Deng, P., Zhang, J., Zhong, N., et al. (2005). <lb/>Detection of severe acute respiratory syndrome <lb/>coronavirus in the brain: potential role of the <lb/>chemokine mig in pathogenesis. Clin. Infect. Dis. <lb/>41, 1089-1096. <lb/>Xydakis, M.S., Dehgani-Mobaraki, P., Holbrook, <lb/>E.H., Geisthoff, U.W., Bauer, C., Hautefort, C., <lb/>Herman, P., Manley, G.T., Lyon, D.M., and <lb/>Hopkins, C. (2020). Smell and taste dysfunction in <lb/>patients with COVID-19. Lancet Infect. Dis. 20, <lb/>1015-1016. <lb/>Zeisel, A., Hochgerner, H., Lonnerberg, P., <lb/>Johnsson, A., Memic, F., van der Zwan, J., <lb/>Haring, M., Braun, E., Borm, L.E., La Manno, <lb/>G., et al. (2018). Molecular architecture of the <lb/>mouse nervous system. Cell 174, 999-<lb/>1014.e22. <lb/>Zhou, P., Yang, X.-L., Wang, X.-G., Hu, B., Zhang, <lb/>L., Zhang, W., Si, H.-R., Zhu, Y., Li, B., Huang, C.-L., <lb/>et al. (2020). A pneumonia outbreak associated <lb/>with a new coronavirus of probable bat origin. <lb/>Nature 579, 270-273. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">ll <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">iScience 23, 101839, December 18, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">iScience <lb/>Article <lb/></note> 
			
			<note place="headnote">iScience, Volume 23 <lb/></note>
			
			<div type="annex">Supplemental Information <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 Receptors and Entry Genes <lb/>Are Expressed in the Human Olfactory <lb/>Neuroepithelium and Brain <lb/>Leon Fodoulian, Joël Tuberosa, Daniel Rossier, Madlaina Boillat, Chenda Kan, Véronique <lb/>Pauli, Kristof Egervari, Johannes A. Lobrinus, Basile N. Landis, Alan Carleton, and Ivan <lb/>Rodriguez <lb/> 

			Supplementary Figures <lb/>Figure S1. ACE2 expression in the mouse kidney and colon (related to Figure 3). (A-H) Evaluation of <lb/>the three different anti-ACE2 antibodies. Immunostaining for ACE2 (red) on sections of mouse colon (left <lb/>panels) and kidney (right panels). (A,B) ACE2 Ab1, polyclonal antibody against the extracellular domain of <lb/>mouse ACE2. (C,D) ACE2 Ab2, polyclonal antibody against the intracellular domain of human ACE2. (E,F) <lb/>ACE2 Ab3, monoclonal antibody against the extracellular domain of human ACE2. Counterstaining with <lb/>DAPI (blue). Scale bar: 40 µm. (G,H) Higher magnification of mouse colon (G) and kidney (H) sections <lb/>immunostained for ACE2 (red). Scale bar: 20 µm. (I,J) Negative control immunostainings on colon and <lb/>kidney without primary antibody for ACE2. Scale bar: 40 µm. <lb/>Figure S2. TMPRSS2 expression in the mouse olfactory epithelium and kidney (related to Figure 3). <lb/>(A-H) Evaluation of the two different anti-ACE2 antibodies. Immunostaining for ACE2 (red) on sections of <lb/>mouse olfactory epithelium (left panels) and kidney (right panels). For each staining, the same image is <lb/>shown with and without DAPI staining (blue). (A,B,C,D) TMPRSS2 Ab1, monoclonal antibody against <lb/>human TMPRSS2. (E,F,G,H) TMPRSS2 Ab2, monoclonal antibody against the C-terminus domain of <lb/>human TMPRSS2. (I,J,K,L) Negative control immunostainings on main olfactory epithelium and kidney <lb/>without primary antibody for TMPRSS2. Scale bars: 20 µm. <lb/> Figure S3. ACE2 expression in the mouse olfactory and respiratory epithelium (related to Figure 3). <lb/>(A) Alcian blue staining on a coronal section of the mouse olfactory neuroepithelium. The entire sensory <lb/>epithelium is devoid of goblet cells. Scale bar: 0.2 mm. (B) Immunostaining for ACE2 (red) and the neuronal <lb/>marker TUJ1 (green) on a section of mouse nasal cavity and nasopharyngeal duct. White arrowheads <lb/>indicate transitions from ACE2-positive to ACE2-negative zones. Colored bars on the right show expression <lb/>zones of ACE2 (red) and TUJ1 (green). ACE2 is expressed in the dorsal olfactory epithelium and in the <lb/>ventral respiratory epithelium. SE: sensory epithelium, RE: respiratory epithelium. Scale bar: 0.2 mm. (C-<lb/>H) Evaluation of ACE2 expression in the mouse respiratory epithelium. (C,E) Immunostaining for ACE2 <lb/>(red) and the neuronal marker TUJ1 (green) on sections of respiratory epithelium in the nasopharyngeal <lb/>duct. (D) The same section with alcian blue staining, showing the presence of goblet cells. (F) Negative <lb/>control immunostaining without primary antibodies. (G,H) Immunostaining for ACE2 (red) and the neuronal <lb/>marker TUJ1 (green) on the ventral part of the nasal cavity, showing the transition from olfactory to <lb/>respiratory epithelium (white arrowhead). Scale bar: 40 µm. (H) Higher magnification of the transition zone <lb/>shown in (G). When not indicated, scale bars are 20 µm. All sections with immunostaining were <lb/>counterstained with DAPI (blue). <lb/>Figure S4. ACE2 expression in the human olfactory neuroepithelium (related to Figure 4). (A) Section <lb/>of human olfactory neuroepithelium immunostained for ACE2 (red) and for the neuronal marker TUJ1 <lb/>(green). (B) Same region as in (A), immunostained without primary antibodies. (C, D, E) Section of human <lb/>olfactory neuroepithelium immunostained for the sustentacular cell marker ERMN (red) and the neuronal <lb/>marker TUJ1 (green). The white square in (C) highlights the region magnified in (D). ERMN is expressed <lb/>in the apical portion of sustentacular cells (white arrowheads). (E) Same region as in (D), but without primary <lb/>antibodies. (F) Section of human olfactory neuroepithelium immunostained for TMPRSS2 (red). (G) Same <lb/>region as in (F), immunostained without primary antibody. All sections with immunostaining were <lb/>counterstained with DAPI (blue). Scale bars: 10 µm. <lb/>Figure S5. Damaged olfactory epithelium of deceased patients infected with SARS-CoV-2 (related <lb/>to Figure 4). (A) Sections of uninfected human olfactory neuroepithelium (upper panel) and respiratory <lb/>epithelium (lower panel) stained with alcian blue. (B) and (C) Sections of human olfactory neuroepithelium <lb/>from patients infected by SARS-CoV-2 stained with alcian blue. Scale bars: 10 µm. <lb/>Figure S6. ACE2 and TMPRSS2 expression in the human brain (related to Figure 6). (A) Visualization <lb/>of the clustering results reported in Lake et al.(Lake et al., 2018) on a UMAP plot. a.u.: arbitrary units. (B) <lb/>Normalized expression levels of ACE2 and TMPRSS2 shown on the UMAP plot. Color gradient scales are <lb/>in log10. norm. UMI: normalized unique molecular identifier counts. (C) Absence of ACE2 and TMPRSS2 <lb/>coexpressing cells highlighted on the UMAP plot. (D,E) Number (D) and percentage (E) of cells per cluster <lb/>expressing ACE2 or TMPRSS2. Combined results are shown for clusters with subdivisions (excitatory, <lb/>inhibitory or Purkinje neuron clusters). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Transparent Methods <lb/>Human biopsies and bulk RNA sequencing <lb/>After authorization from the University of Geneva ethics commission (authorization CE-<lb/>13-115) and the informed consent from all subjects, human biopsies were collected at the <lb/>Geneva University Hospital. For whole tissue RNA-seq, samples of 4 individuals (3 males <lb/>and 1 females, age between 45-55 years) were resected during nasal cavity surgeries <lb/>under general anesthesia. Biopsies consisted in small pieces of tissue of approximately <lb/>3 mm in diameter, from the respiratory or the sensory epithelia. Biopsies were snap frozen <lb/>in liquid nitrogen immediately upon collection. One patient had only an OE biopsy and <lb/>another only a RE biopsy. For RNA extraction, tissues were placed in RLT Buffer (Qiagen) <lb/>with beta-mercaptoethanol and lysed with stainless steel balls (5mm diameter, Schieritz <lb/>and Huenstein AG) using a homogenizer (Big Prep, MB Biomedicals). Total RNA was <lb/>isolated using RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen) following the manufacturer protocol. The quality <lb/>and quantity of total RNA were evaluated with a Bioanalyzer (Agilent). Stranded cDNA <lb/>libraries with suitable adapters for multiplexing were generated with Truseq RNA and <lb/>DNA sample preparation kits (Illumina) following ribodepletion of the total RNA (200ng of <lb/>total RNA per sample). Samples were multiplexed for sequencing in a HiSeq®2500 <lb/>Sequencing system, generating 100bp single-end reads. Each patient represented an <lb/>independent biological replicate. <lb/>Bulk RNA sequencing data analysis <lb/>RNA-seq reads were mapped onto the GRCh38 human genome assembly with STAR <lb/>(Dobin et al., 2013) version 2.7.0a using the Ensembl v99 gene annotation file (GTF). <lb/>Mutlimapped reads were filtered out with the option --outFilterMultimapNmax set to 1. <lb/>Reversely stranded gene expression quantification was carried using featureCounts (Liao <lb/>et al., 2014) version 1.6.3 and a modified version of the aforementioned GTF file. The <lb/>records corresponding to AC097625.2, a newly annotated long non-coding RNA that <lb/>spans and shares most exons of ACE2, were removed from the GTF file as they <lb/>hampered ACE2 quantification (due to ambiguous read counting). This gene had a total <lb/>of 3 detected counts in two samples and its removal from the GTF file led on average to <lb/>a 9-fold increase in ACE2 counts. Note that this annotation was absent from and did not <lb/>affect the single-cell RNA-sequencing datasets as it first appeared in the GENCODE <lb/>release 30 and the Ensembl release 96 of the GRCh38 GTF files. Differential gene <lb/>expression analysis between olfactory epithelial (OE) biopsies and respiratory epithelial <lb/>(RE) biopsies was performed using the DESeq2 (Love et al., 2014) Bioconductor package <lb/>version 1.22.2 in R version 3.5.0. After fitting a negative binomial generalized linear model <lb/>(GLM), the Wald test (two-tailed) was used to test for significance of gene expression <lb/>differences as a function of biopsies at a log2 fold change threshold of 0. To control the <lb/>false discovery rate, the Wald test p-values were adjusted for multiple comparisons using <lb/>the Benjamini-Hochberg procedure (Benjamini and Hochberg, 1995). Patient <lb/>identifications were not added to the model to control for potential differences in gene <lb/>expression between individuals (i.e. batch effects) due to the underpowered experimental <lb/>design highlighted by the 3 samples per condition. The Approximate Posterior Estimation <lb/>for GLM coefficients (an adaptive Bayesian shrinkage estimator) implemented in the <lb/>apeglm (Zhu et al., 2019) Bioconductor package version 1.4.2 was used to shrink log2 <lb/>fold changes. During shrinkage, the maximum likelihood estimates (i.e. log2 fold changes) <lb/>and their associated standard errors (both in log scale) were used to adapt the scale of <lb/>the prior. The results of this analysis are represented as a volcano plot in Figure 1C. To <lb/>display the expression levels of selected genes in individual samples (Figure 1D-1G), <lb/>TPM values were calculated for each gene within each sample to normalize for <lb/>sequencing depth differences. Olfactory cascade genes (i.e. OMP, CNGA2 and ANO2) <lb/>and the top 4 most differentially expressed OR genes (with the lowest adjusted p-values) <lb/>were selected as markers of the olfactory neurosensory epithelium. ERMN was selected <lb/>as a marker of sustentacular cells (Liang, 2018; Tang et al., 2009). <lb/>Droplet-based single-cell RNA sequencing data analysis of human olfactory epithelial <lb/>cells <lb/>Data download: The processed 10X Genomics output files of all four patients of the single-<lb/>cell RNA-seq dataset reported in Durante et al. (Durante et al., 2020) were downloaded <lb/>from NCBI GEO: GSE139522. This dataset consists in human olfactory and respiratory <lb/>epithelial cells collected from four patients aged between 41 and 52 years. The data was <lb/>analyzed in R version 3.5.0 using the Seurat (Butler et al., 2018; Satija et al., 2015; Stuart <lb/>et al., 2019) R package version 3.1.4 following the indications described in Durante et al. <lb/>(Durante et al., 2020) and using custom scripts. <lb/>Cell and gene filtering: The 10X files were loaded into R using the Read10X function of <lb/>Seurat. A single Seurat object for all four patients was created using the <lb/>CreateSeuratObject function of Seurat. At this step, genes not expressed in at least 3 <lb/>cells at a threshold of a minimum of 1 UMI count were excluded from the analysis <lb/>(min.cells = 3). The percentage of mitochondrial counts was then calculated for each cell <lb/>using the PercentageFeatureSet function of Seurat. Cells were removed from the analysis <lb/>if they had less than 400 detected UMI counts, expressed less than 100 or more than <lb/>6000 genes, and if their mitochondrial counts exceeded 10% of their total counts. This <lb/>filtering resulted in retaining 28,726 cells and 26,439 genes. <lb/>Dataset integration: The standard Seurat version 3 (Stuart et al., 2019) integration <lb/>workflow was used to integrate the data from all patients, as described in Durante et al. <lb/>(Durante et al., 2020) First, the data from each patient was separated using the <lb/>SplitObject function of Seurat. The raw UMI counts of each gene within each cell were <lb/>normalized by the total number of UMI counts per cell, scaled to 10 4 and natural-log-<lb/>transformed after adding a pseudocount of 1 using the NormalizeData function of Seurat <lb/>(normalization.method = &quot;LogNormalize&quot;; scale.factor = 10000). The top 5000 variable <lb/>genes were then determined in each dataset using the variance-stabilizing transformation <lb/>(Stuart et al., 2019) method of the FindVariableFeatures function of Seurat <lb/>(selection.method = &quot;vst&quot;; nfeatures = 5000). To assemble all datasets, integration <lb/>anchors (i.e. mutual nearest neighbors) across the four datasets were identified with the <lb/>FindIntegrationAnchors function of Seurat after computing the first 30 dimensions of the <lb/>canonical correlation analysis(Butler et al., 2018) between each pair of datasets using the <lb/>top 5000 variable genes shared between most datasets (reduction = &quot;cca&quot;; dims = 1:30; <lb/>anchor.features = 5000; l2.norm = TRUE). The IntegrateData function of Seurat was then <lb/>used to integrate all four datasets into a single Seurat object. <lb/>UMAP plot generation: To generate a UMAP (Becht et al., 2018; McInnes et al., 2018) <lb/>plot, the integrated data was scaled and centered using the ScaleData function of Seurat <lb/>and the first 30 principle components were computed using the RunPCA function of <lb/>Seurat. These 30 principle components were then used as input to the RunUMAP function <lb/>of Seurat (dims = 1:30). The UMAP plot was generated with the uwot R package version <lb/>0.1.8 implementation. The cosine metric was used to measure distance and find the <lb/>nearest neighbors (metric = &quot;cosine&quot;), the number of neighbors used for the <lb/>approximation of the manifold structure was set to 30 (n.neighbors = 30) and the effective <lb/>minimum distance between embedded points was set to 0.3 (spread = 1; min.dist = 0.3). <lb/>The clusters identified by Durante et al.(Durante et al., 2020) were displayed on the UMAP <lb/>plot (Figure 2B) and were used for subsequent analyses. The cluster corresponding to <lb/>&quot;Respiratory columnar cells&quot; was renamed as &quot;Respiratory early secretory cells&quot; based <lb/>on its expression of SERPINB3 (see Supplementary Table 3 from Durante et al. (Durante <lb/>et al., 2020)). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Gene expression analysis and plotting: All gene expression analyses were performed <lb/>using the actual normalized UMI counts (not log-transformed) from the non-integrated <lb/>assay of the Seurat object. However, the scales of the axes in the violin plots (Figure 2A, <lb/>F and G) and the color gradient scales in the heatmap plots (Figure 2C) are in log10 after <lb/>adding a pseudocount of 1 to the normalized UMI counts. The axes in Figure 2E, 2H and <lb/>2I are not in log scale. ACE2 and TMPRSS2 coexpressing cells were identified as <lb/>expressing at least 1 UMI count of both genes (Figure 2D). All violins in each violin plot <lb/>have the same maximum width. <lb/>Droplet-based single-nucleus RNA sequencing data analysis of human brain cells <lb/>Data download: The digital gene expression matrices of the single-nucleus Drop-seq <lb/>dataset reported in Lake et al. (Lake et al., 2018) were downloaded from NCBI GEO: <lb/>GSE97930. This dataset consists in human brain nuclei collected from the frontal cortex, <lb/>visual cortex and lateral cerebellar hemisphere from six individuals aged between 20 and <lb/>49 years (for more information, see Supplementary Table 1 from Lake et al. (Lake et al., <lb/>2018)). The data was analyzed in R version 3.5.0 using the pagoda2 R package <lb/>(https://github.com/hms-dbmi/pagoda2) version 0.1.1 following the indications described <lb/>in Lake et al. (Lake et al., 2018) and using custom scripts. For simplification, the word <lb/>&quot;cells&quot; will be used instead of &quot;nuclei&quot; in the following paragraphs. <lb/>Cell and gene filtering: All cells from the downloaded matrices had a cell type annotation <lb/>and were therefore retained for further analysis. Genes shared between all 3 datasets <lb/>(i.e. frontal cortex, visual cortex and lateral cerebellar hemisphere) were selected for <lb/>downstream analysis. The final UMI count matrix, after combining all datasets, contained <lb/>35,289 cells and 31,302 genes. <lb/>Batch correction and data preparation: A new Pagoda2 object was created and the library <lb/>identification of each cell was defined for batch correction using the plain model (see <lb/>Supplementary Table 2 from Lake et al. (Lake et al., 2018)). Winsorization was used to <lb/>clip the expression levels of each gene at the eleventh most extreme value (i.e. <lb/>winsorizing the ten most extreme values; trim = 10). Batch-corrected gene expression <lb/>levels were then normalized by the total number of counts per cell, scaled to 10 3 and <lb/>natural-log-transformed after adding a pseudocount of 1. <lb/>UMAP plot generation: The variance of genes were calculated and adjusted using the <lb/>adjustVariance function of pagoda2, as described in Lake et al. (Lake et al., 2018) (the <lb/>smoothing term of the generalized additive model was set to gam.k = 10). The 2,000 <lb/>overdispersed genes were then selected from the variance adjusted matrix and the 150 <lb/>principle components were computed using the calculatePcaReduction function of <lb/>pagoda2 (n.odgenes = 2000; nPcs = 150). These 150 principle components were then <lb/>used to generate a UMAP plot with the getEmbedding function of pagoda2 (type = &quot;PCA&quot;; <lb/>embeddingType = &quot;UMAP&quot;). As for the analysis of human olfactory epithelial cells, the <lb/>uwot R package version 0.1.8 implementation was used to generate the UMAP plot. Also, <lb/>the cosine metric was used to measure distance and find the nearest neighbors (distance <lb/>= &quot;cosine&quot;), the number of neighbors used for the approximation of the manifold structure <lb/>was set to 15 (n_neighbors = 15) and the effective minimum distance between embedded <lb/>points was set to 0.1 (spread = 1; min_dist = 0.1). <lb/>Gene expression analysis and plotting: To plot the expression levels of ACE2 and <lb/>TMPRSS2 on the UMAP projection in the form of a heatmap, the raw UMI counts of each <lb/>gene within each cell were normalized by the total number of UMI counts per cell and <lb/>scaled to 10 4 . Similar to Figure 2C, the color gradient scales in the heatmap plots <lb/>(Supplementary Figure 6B) are in log10 after adding a pseudocount of 1 to the normalized <lb/>UMI counts. In Supplementary Figure 6D and 6E, broader clusters were defined by <lb/>separately grouping all excitatory neuron clusters, all inhibitory neuron clusters and all <lb/>Purkinje neuron clusters. <lb/>SMART-Seq v4 single-nucleus RNA sequencing data analysis of human brain cells <lb/>Data download: The digital gene expression matrix (matrix.csv), the t-SNE coordinates <lb/>for each cell (tsne.csv) and the metadata table corresponding to the cells (metadata.csv) <lb/>were downloaded from the Allen Brain Map cell types database, available online at <lb/>https://portal.brain-map.org/atlases-and-data/rnaseq/human-multiple-cortical-areas-<lb/>smart-seq. This dataset consists in human brain nuclei collected from three individuals <lb/>and from eight brain regions: middle temporal gyrus (MTG), cingulate gyrus (CgG), <lb/>primary visual cortex (V1C), primary auditory cortex (A1C), upper limb (ul) and lower limb <lb/>(lm) regions of both primary motor cortex (M1) and primary somatosensory cortex (S1) <lb/>(for more information, see metadata.csv from the website above). The data was analyzed <lb/>in R version 3.5.0 using custom scripts. Like in the above paragraphs, the word &quot;cells&quot; will <lb/>be used instead of &quot;nuclei&quot; in the following paragraphs. <lb/>Cell and gene filtering: Cells lacking a brain cell-type subclass annotation (subclass_label <lb/>column from metadata.csv) and a t-SNE embedding were removed from the analysis, and <lb/>all genes were retained for data normalization. The final expression matrix contained <lb/>47,432 cells and 50,281 genes. <lb/>Gene expression analysis and plotting: Prior to any gene expression plotting or analysis, <lb/>the raw counts of each gene within each cell were normalized by the total number of <lb/>counts per cell and scaled to 10 4 . Similar to Figure 2C, the color gradient scales in the <lb/>heatmap plots (Figure 6B and 6C) are in log10 after adding a pseudocount of 1 to the <lb/>normalized counts. However, the axes in Figure 6E, F and G are not in log scale. Also, <lb/>as described above, ACE2 and TMPRSS2 coexpressing cells were identified as <lb/>expressing at least 1 raw count of both genes (Figure 6D). <lb/>Data visualization and programming tools <lb/>All plots in Figures 1, 2 and 6, as well as in Figure S6, were generated using ggplot2 <lb/>version 3.3.0. Other R and Bioconductor packages used for data analysis and plotting <lb/>include rtracklayer(Lawrence et al., 2009) version 1.46.0, Matrix version 1.2.18, reshape2 <lb/>version 1.4.3, data.table version 1.12.8, dplyr version 0.8.5, stringr version 1.4.0, ggrepel <lb/>version 0.9.0, lemon version 0.4.4, extrafont version 0.17, viridis version 0.5.1, <lb/>RColorBrewer version 1.1.2, patchwork version 1.0.0 and grid version 3.5.0. <lb/>Mouse brain cell database mining <lb/>For mouse brain single-cell transcriptomes, the datasets of Zeisel et al. (Zeisel et al., <lb/>2018) (Figure 5A and 5B) and Sauders et al. (Saunders et al., 2018) (Figure 5C) were <lb/>analyzed from their respective websites: http://mousebrain.org/ and http://dropviz.org/. <lb/>Immunohistochemistry and histology <lb/>Tissue fixation and preparation: All animal procedures were performed in accordance with <lb/>the guidelines and regulations of the institution and of the state of Geneva. Mice (C57BL6, <lb/>Charles River Laboratories, France) were deeply anesthetized with Pentobarbitalum <lb/>natricum at 150mg/kg (Streuli Pharma) and perfused transcardially with 1x phosphate-<lb/>buffered saline (PBS)-heparine 20&apos;000 UI/l (Bichsel), pH 7.4. After flushing, mice were <lb/>perfused with 10% neutral buffered Formalin. Tissues were extracted and fixed over night <lb/>at 4°C and cryoprotected in 15% sucrose, 1x PBS over night at 4 °C followed by 30 % <lb/>sucrose, 1x PBS over night at 4 °C. Tissues were embedded in optimal cutting <lb/>temperature compound (OCT) (Carl Roth, ref. 6478.1) and cut on a cryostat in 16 µm <lb/>sections that were mounted on Superfrost+ slides. Sections were conserved at -80°C until <lb/>use. For human post-mortem samples a written consent for the anonymized research use <lb/>of biological material was obtained from relatives, in accordance with the guidelines and <lb/>regulations of the institution and of the state of Geneva. Human olfactory and respiratory <lb/>epithelia were sampled from autopsies (individual 1: female, 90 years, uninfected with <lb/>SARS-CoV-2; individual 2: male, 54 years, infected with SARS-CoV-2, individual 3: male, <lb/>86 years, infected with SARS-CoV-2. By transcranial access, the cribriform plate with the <lb/>superior part of the nasal cavities and the septum nasi were removed. The postero-lateral <lb/>and postero-medial parts of the nasal mucosa were carefully dissected and fixed in 10% <lb/>neutral buffered Formalin for 48 hours and bony particles were decalcified in EDTA for 24 <lb/>hours. Paraffin embedding was done using a standard protocol using a LOGOS <lb/>Microwave Hybrid Tissue Processor (Milestone). Paraffin blocks were cut at 3 µm <lb/>thickness with a microtome and mounted on Superfrost slides. Before staining, <lb/>cryosections were thawed and dried for 30 min under a ventilated hood. Sections were <lb/>re-hydrated with 1x PBS for 5 min. Paraffin sections were deparaffinized by placing them <lb/>for 10 min in xylene (Fluka), and then successively for 1 min each in ethanol 100%, 90%, <lb/>80%, 70% and H2O. <lb/>Alcian blue staining: For alcian blue staining, hydrated sections were stained for 30 min <lb/>in alcian blue (Sigma, ref. 1.01647), acetic acid 3%, pH 2.5. Sections were washed for 2 <lb/>min in running tap water and rinsed in distilled water. Sections were counterstained with <lb/>0.1% nuclear fast red, 5% aluminum sulfate solution (Merck Millipore, ref. 1.00121) for 5 <lb/>min. Sections were washed for 1 min in running tap water and dehydrated. Sections were <lb/>cleared in xylene and mounted with Eukitt (Sigma, ref. 03989) mounting medium. <lb/>Immunohistochemistry: For antigen retrieval, sections were immersed in 10mM Citric <lb/>Acid, 0.05% Tween 20, pH 6.0 buffer previously heated to 95-100 °C, and incubated for <lb/>20 min. Sections were then cooled down to room temperature in 1x PBS. Section were <lb/>pre-incubated for 30 min with 1x PBS containing 0.5% Triton X-100 and 5% FCS. <lb/>Sections were incubated with primary antibodies (see details in Table S1) diluted in 1x <lb/>PBS containing 0.5% Triton X-100 and 5% FCS over night at 4°C. Sections were washed <lb/>3x15 min with 1x PBS containing 0.5% Triton X-100. Sections were incubated with <lb/>secondary antibodies diluted 1:800 in 1x PBS with 0.5% Triton X-100 and 5% FCS for 90 <lb/>min at room temperature (see details in Table S2). Sections were again washed 3x 15 <lb/>min with 1x PBS containing 0.5% Triton X-100. Sections were counterstained with DAPI <lb/>(1:5000) for 5 min, rinsed with 1x PBS and mounted with DABCO (Sigma) in glycerol. For <lb/>all tissue samples and all conditions, control samples were processed simultaneously <lb/>without applying primary antibodies. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Microscope imaging: Confocal imaging was performed with a Leica TCS SP8 using a <lb/>PMT detector for DAPI fluorescence and HyD 5 detectors for Alexa488, Alexa555 and <lb/>Cy3 fluorescence. Epifluorescence imaging was performed with a Leica DM5500 <lb/>equipped with a DFC9000 GT monochrome camera. For both fluorescence microscopy <lb/>techniques, illumination and detection was manually adjusted to optimize signal-to-noise <lb/>ratio and minimize over-exposure, bleaching and light scattering. Brightfield was <lb/>performed with a Leica DM5500 equipped with a DMC2900 camera. Microscope <lb/>automated control and image encoding was performed with the LAS X software version <lb/>3.4.2. Acquisition settings were matched in negative controls. <lb/>Microscope image editing: Maximum intensity projection were computed on the LAS X <lb/>software for z-stack imaging. The following images are z-stack maximum intensity <lb/>projections: Figure 3G, 3K, 3M, 3O, 3Q, Figure 4E-4G, Supplementary Figure 1A, 1B, <lb/>Figure S2. All images were exported as TIF files. For clarity, cropping and linear exposure <lb/>adjustments were performed on Adobe Photoshop. Again, settings were matched in <lb/>negative controls. <lb/>Table S1. Primary antibodies, related to Figures 3, 4, 5, S1, S2, S3, S4 and S5. <lb/>antibody <lb/>species conc. antigen <lb/>company <lb/>reference LOT <lb/>secondary <lb/>antibody <lb/>ACE2 <lb/>(Ab1) <lb/>goat <lb/>15 <lb/>µg/ml <lb/>Mouse <lb/>ACE2 <lb/>extracellular <lb/>domain, <lb/>Gln18-<lb/>Thr740 <lb/>Invitrogen <lb/>PA5-<lb/>47488 <lb/>VD2973776 <lb/>#1, #2 <lb/>ACE2 <lb/>(Ab2) <lb/>rabbit <lb/>1:200 Human <lb/>ACE2 C-<lb/>terminal <lb/>domain, aa <lb/>788-805 <lb/>Abcam <lb/>ab15348 <lb/>GR3333640-<lb/>4 <lb/>#3, #5 <lb/>ACE2 <lb/>(Ab3) <lb/>rabbit <lb/>1:200 Human <lb/>ACE2, <lb/>extracellular <lb/>domain, aa <lb/>200-300 <lb/>Abcam <lb/>ab108252 GR3338009-<lb/>3 <lb/>#3, #5 <lb/>OMP <lb/>goat <lb/>1:700 Rodent <lb/>olfactory <lb/>marker <lb/>protein <lb/>FUJIFILM <lb/>Wako <lb/>WA3 019-<lb/>22291 <lb/>CAG6625 <lb/>#1 #2 <lb/>OMP <lb/>mouse <lb/>1:100 Human <lb/>olfactory <lb/>marker <lb/>protein, aa <lb/>1-163 <lb/>Santa Cruz <lb/>Biotechnology <lb/>sc-<lb/>365818 <lb/>E1117 <lb/>#6, #7 <lb/>TUJ1 <lb/>mouse <lb/>1:200 Rat brain <lb/>Tubulin <lb/>beta 3 <lb/>Biolegend <lb/>801201 <lb/>B264428 <lb/>#6, #7 <lb/>ERMN <lb/>rabbit <lb/>1:200 Human <lb/>ERMN <lb/>Invitrogen <lb/>PA5-<lb/>58327 <lb/>R35628 <lb/>#3, #4, #5 <lb/>TMPRSS2 <lb/>(Ab1) <lb/>rabbit <lb/>1:100 Human <lb/>TMPRSS2, <lb/>within aa 1-<lb/>100 <lb/>Abcam <lb/>ab92323 <lb/>GR246521-9 #3 <lb/>TMPRSS2 <lb/>(Ab2) <lb/>rabbit <lb/>1:200 Human <lb/>TMPRSS2, <lb/>aa 450 to <lb/>the C-<lb/>terminus <lb/>Abcam <lb/>ab109131 GR3248440-<lb/>2 <lb/>#3, #4, #5 <lb/>Table S2. Secondary antibodies, related to related to Figures 3, 4, 5, S1, S2, S3, S4 <lb/>and S5.. <lb/># <lb/>antibody <lb/>species <lb/>company <lb/>reference <lb/>1 <lb/>anti-goat Alexa 555 <lb/>donkey <lb/>Invitrogen <lb/>A21432 <lb/>2 <lb/>anti-goat Alexa 488 <lb/>donkey <lb/>Abcam <lb/>ab150133 <lb/>3 <lb/>anti-rabbit Alexa 555 <lb/>donkey <lb/>Abcam <lb/>ab150074 <lb/>4 <lb/>anti-rabbit Alexa 488 <lb/>donkey <lb/>Abcam <lb/>ab150073 <lb/>5 <lb/>anti-rabbit Alexa 488 <lb/>goat <lb/>Life Technologies A11034 <lb/>6 <lb/>anti-mouse Alexa 488 donkey <lb/>Abcam <lb/>ab150105 <lb/>7 <lb/>anti-mouse Cy3 <lb/>goat <lb/>Life Technologies A10521 <lb/></div>

			<!-- check if this is to be correctly placed here or under <div type=annex -->
			<listBibl>Supplemental References <lb/>Becht, E., McInnes, L., Healy, J., Dutertre, C.-A., Kwok, I.W.H., Ng, L.G., Ginhoux, F., <lb/>and Newell, E.W. (2018). Dimensionality reduction for visualizing single-cell data using <lb/>UMAP. Nature biotechnology. <lb/>Benjamini, Y., and Hochberg, Y. (1995). Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical <lb/>and powerful approach to multiple testing. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society Series <lb/>B series B, 289-300. <lb/>Butler, A., Hoffman, P., Smibert, P., Papalexi, E., and Satija, R. (2018). Integrating <lb/>single-cell transcriptomic data across different conditions, technologies, and species. <lb/>Nature biotechnology 36, 411-420. <lb/>Dobin, A., Davis, C.A., Schlesinger, F., Drenkow, J., Zaleski, C., Jha, S., Batut, P., <lb/>Chaisson, M., and Gingeras, T.R. (2013). STAR: ultrafast universal RNA-seq aligner. <lb/>Bioinformatics 29, 15-21. <lb/>Durante, M.A., Kurtenbach, S., Sargi, Z.B., Harbour, J.W., Choi, R., Kurtenbach, S., <lb/>Goss, G.M., Matsunami, H., and Goldstein, B.J. (2020). Single-cell analysis of olfactory <lb/>neurogenesis and differentiation in adult humans. Nature neuroscience 23, 323-326. <lb/>Lake, B.B., Chen, Sos, B.C., Fan, J., Kaeser, G.E., Yung, Y.C., Duong, T.E., Gao, <lb/>D., Chun, J., Kharchenko, P.V., et al. (2018). Integrative single-cell analysis of <lb/>transcriptional and epigenetic states in the human adult brain. Nature biotechnology 36, <lb/>70-80. <lb/>Lawrence, M., Gentleman, R., and Carey, V. (2009). rtracklayer: an R package for <lb/>interfacing with genome browsers. Bioinformatics 25, 1841-1842. <lb/>Liang, F. (2018). Olfactory receptor neuronal dendrites become mostly intra-<lb/>sustentacularly enwrapped upon maturity. Journal of Anatomy 232, 674-685. <lb/>Liao, Y., Smyth, G.K., and Shi, W. (2014). featureCounts: an efficient general purpose <lb/>program for assigning sequence reads to genomic features. Bioinformatics 30, 923-930. <lb/>Love, M.I., Huber, W., and Anders, S. (2014). Moderated estimation of fold change and <lb/>dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2. Genome biology 15, 550. <lb/>McInnes, L., Healy, J., and Melville, J. (2018). UMAP: Uniform Manifold Approximation <lb/>and Projection for Dimension Reduction. arXiv. <lb/>Satija, R., Farrell, J.A., Gennert, D., Schier, A.F., and Regev, A. (2015). Spatial <lb/>reconstruction of single-cell gene expression data. Nature biotechnology 33, 495-502. <lb/>Saunders, A., Macosko, E.Z., Wysoker, A., Goldman, M., Krienen, F.M., de Rivera, H., <lb/>Bien, E., Baum, M., Bortolin, L., Wang, S., et al. (2018). Molecular Diversity and <lb/>Specializations among the Cells of the Adult Mouse Brain. Cell 174, 1015-1030.e1016. <lb/>Stuart, T., Butler, A., Hoffman, P., Hafemeister, C., Papalexi, E., Mauck, W.M., 3rd, <lb/>Hao, Y., Stoeckius, M., Smibert, P., and Satija, R. (2019). Comprehensive Integration of <lb/>Single-Cell Data. Cell 177, 1888-1902.e1821. <lb/>Tang, J., Tang, J., Ling, E.A., Wu, Y., and Liang, F. (2009). Juxtanodin in the rat <lb/>olfactory epithelium: specific expression in sustentacular cells and preferential <lb/>subcellular at the apical junctional belt. Neuroscience 161, 249-258. <lb/>Zeisel, A., Hochgerner, H., Lonnerberg, P., Johnsson, A., Memic, F., van der Zwan, J., <lb/>Haring, M., Braun, E., Borm, L.E., La Manno, G., et al. (2018). Molecular Architecture of <lb/>the Mouse Nervous System. Cell 174, 999-1014.e1022. <lb/>Zhu, A., Ibrahim, J.G., and Love, M.I. (2019). Heavy-tailed prior distributions for <lb/>sequence count data: removing the noise and preserving large differences. <lb/>Bioinformatics 35, 2084-2092. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
