<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Slow blood-to-brain transport underlies <lb/>enduring barrier dysfunction in American <lb/>football players <lb/>Ronel Veksler, 1 Udi Vazana, 1 Yonatan Serlin, 1,2 Ofer Prager, 1 Jonathan Ofer, 1 <lb/>Nofar Shemen, 1 Andrew M. Fisher, 3 Olga Minaeva, 3 Ning Hua, 3 Rotem Saar-Ashkenazy, 1,4 <lb/>Itay Benou, 5 Tammy Riklin-Raviv, 5 Ellen Parker, 6 Griffin Mumby, 6 Lyna Kamintsky, 6 <lb/>Steven Beyea, 7 Chris V. Bowen, 7 Ilan Shelef, 8 Eoin O&apos;Keeffe, 9 Matthew Campbell, 9 <lb/>Daniela Kaufer, 10 Lee E. Goldstein 3 and Alon Friedman 1,6 <lb/>See Ware et al. (doi:10.1093/brain/awaa166) for a scientific commentary on this article. <lb/>Repetitive mild traumatic brain injury in American football players has garnered increasing public attention following reports of <lb/>chronic traumatic encephalopathy, a progressive tauopathy. While the mechanisms underlying repetitive mild traumatic brain injury-<lb/>induced neurodegeneration are unknown and antemortem diagnostic tests are not available, neuropathology studies suggest a patho-<lb/>genic role for microvascular injury, specifically blood-brain barrier dysfunction. Thus, our main objective was to demonstrate the ef-<lb/>fectiveness of a modified dynamic contrast-enhanced MRI approach we have developed to detect impairments in brain microvascular <lb/>function. To this end, we scanned 42 adult male amateur American football players and a control group comprising 27 athletes prac-<lb/>ticing a non-contact sport and 26 non-athletes. MRI scans were also performed in 51 patients with brain pathologies involving the <lb/>blood-brain barrier, namely malignant brain tumours, ischaemic stroke and haemorrhagic traumatic contusion. Based on data from <lb/>prolonged scans, we generated maps that visualized the permeability value for each brain voxel. Our permeability maps revealed an <lb/>increase in slow blood-to-brain transport in a subset of amateur American football players, but not in sex-and age-matched controls. <lb/>The increase in permeability was region specific (white matter, midbrain peduncles, red nucleus, temporal cortex) and correlated with <lb/>changes in white matter, which were confirmed by diffusion tensor imaging. Additionally, increased permeability persisted for months, <lb/>as seen in players who were scanned both on-and off-season. Examination of patients with brain pathologies revealed that slow <lb/>tracer accumulation characterizes areas surrounding the core of injury, which frequently shows fast blood-to-brain transport. Next, <lb/>we verified our method in two rodent models: rats and mice subjected to repeated mild closed-head impact injury, and rats with vas-<lb/>cular injury inflicted by photothrombosis. In both models, slow blood-to-brain transport was observed, which correlated with neuro-<lb/>pathological changes. Lastly, computational simulations and direct imaging of the transport of Evans blue-albumin complex in brains <lb/>of rats subjected to recurrent seizures or focal cerebrovascular injury suggest that increased cellular transport underlies the observed <lb/>slow blood-to-brain transport. Taken together, our findings suggest dynamic contrast-enhanced-MRI can be used to diagnose specific <lb/>microvascular pathology after traumatic brain injury and other brain pathologies. <lb/>1 Departments of Physiology and Cell Biology, Brain and Cognitive Sciences, The Zlotowski Center for Neuroscience, Ben-Gurion <lb/>University of the Negev, Beer-Sheva, Israel <lb/>2 Neurology Residency Training Program, McGill University, Montreal, QC, Canada <lb/>3 Molecular Aging and Development Laboratory, Boston University School of Medicine, College of Engineering, Alzheimer&apos;s Disease <lb/>and CTE Center, and Photonics Center, Boston University, Boston, MA, USA <lb/>4 Department of Psychology and the School of Social-work, Ashkelon Academic College, Israel <lb/>5 Department of Electrical Engineering, Ben-Gurion University of the Negev, Beer-Sheva, Israel <lb/>Received July 25, 2019. Revised February 27, 2020. Accepted March 11, 2020. Advance access publication May 28, 2020 <lb/>V C The Author(s) (2020). Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Guarantors of Brain. <lb/>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which <lb/>permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact <lb/>journals.permissions@oup.com <lb/>doi:10.1093/brain/awaa140 <lb/>BRAIN 2020: 143; 1826-1842 | 1826 <lb/>Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/brain/article/143/6/1826/5848368 by guest on 02 August 2022 <lb/>6 Department of Medical Neuroscience, Dalhousie University, Faculty of Medicine, Halifax, NS, Canada <lb/>7 Biomedical Translational Imaging Centre (BIOTIC), IWK Health Centre and QEII Health Sciences Center, Dalhousie University, <lb/>Halifax, NS, Canada <lb/>8 Department of Medical Imaging, Soroka University Medical Center, Beer-Sheva, Israel <lb/>9 Smurfit Institute of Genetics, Trinity College Dublin, Dublin, Ireland <lb/>10 Department of Integrative Biology and the Helen Wills Neuroscience Institute, University of California, Berkeley, CA, USA <lb/>Correspondence to: Dr Alon Friedman <lb/>Ben-Gurion University of the Negev, P.O.B. 653 Beer-Sheva, 8410501 Israel <lb/>E-mail: alonf@bgu.ac.il <lb/>Keywords: blood-brain barrier; repetitive mild traumatic brain injury; dynamic contrast-enhanced magnetic resonance imaging; <lb/>American football; transcellular transport <lb/>Abbreviations: BBBD = blood-brain barrier dysfunction; CTE = chronic traumatic encephalopathy; DCE = dynamic contrast-<lb/>enhanced; DTI = diffusion tensor imaging; FFDE = fibre-flux diffusion density; IFOF = inferior fronto-occipital fasciculus; NPI = <lb/>normalized permeability index; rmTBI = repetitive mild TBI; TBI = traumatic brain injury <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Traumatic brain injury (TBI) is a leading cause of death and <lb/>disability, and is associated with significant secondary mor-<lb/>bidity, including late-life increased risk of neurodegenerative <lb/>diseases such as chronic traumatic encephalopathy (CTE) <lb/>(Critchley, 1957; Omalu et al., 2006; Gavett et al., 2011; <lb/>Ling et al., 2017; Mez et al., 2017; Tagge et al., 2018). <lb/>Human neuropathological studies have demonstrated that <lb/>traumatic microvascular injury is common after brain injury <lb/>and may persist for years after the insult (Hay et al., 2015; <lb/>Salehi et al., 2017). Specifically, blood-brain barrier dysfunc-<lb/>tion (BBBD), and extravasation of serum proteins into the <lb/>brain neuropil have been shown to facilitate delayed compli-<lb/>cations following TBI (Doherty et al., 2016). BBBD is also a <lb/>hallmark of other brain disorders, including ischaemic inju-<lb/>ries [e.g. stroke (Kassner and Merali, 2015; Villringer et al., <lb/>2016; Serlin et al., 2019), subarachnoid haemorrhage <lb/>(Lublinsky et al., 2019), and epilepsy (Ru ¨ber et al., 2018)], <lb/>and has been recently suggested as a potential biomarker pre-<lb/>dicting outcome (Bar-Klein et al., 2017; Lublinsky et al., <lb/>2019; Kamintsky et al., 2019; Serlin et al., 2019). While the <lb/>detailed mechanisms underlying BBBD are poorly under-<lb/>stood, both paracellular leakage, resulting from dysfunction <lb/>or downregulation of tight-junction proteins, and enhanced <lb/>transcellular transport across the endothelial barrier have <lb/>been proposed as pathogenic contributors (Knowland et al., <lb/>2014; De Bock et al., 2016; Haley and Lawrence, 2016; <lb/>Nahirney et al., 2016; Andreone et al., 2017; Zhang et al., <lb/>2017). At present, there is neither a clinically standardized <lb/>method for objective assessment of microvascular permeabil-<lb/>ity changes in vivo, nor data revealing the nature and course <lb/>of BBB permeability changes in individuals affected by repeti-<lb/>tive mild TBI (rmTBI). <lb/>Dynamic contrast-enhanced (DCE) MRI is being used to <lb/>evaluate brain vascular permeability in a growing number of <lb/>neurological diseases (Sweeney et al., 2019). Widely used <lb/>DCE-MRI methods are based on extended Tofts or Patlak <lb/>models (Patlak and Blasberg, 1985; Tofts and Kermode, 1991; <lb/>Sourbron and Buckley, 2013). To date, DCE-MRI studies <lb/>were either primarily used to evaluate conditions defined by <lb/>robust and rapid (45 min) leakage of contrast agent, or only <lb/>rarely distinguished between different blood-to-brain transport <lb/>mechanisms (Zlokovic, 2008; Heye et al., 2014; Montagne <lb/>et al., 2015; Artzi et al., 2016; Nation et al., 2019). We have <lb/>recently implemented a modified DCE-MRI approach to de-<lb/>tect, localize, and track subtle BBBD in a cohort of American <lb/>football players (Weissberg et al., 2014), patients with transi-<lb/>ent ischaemic attack (Serlin et al., 2019) and bipolar depres-<lb/>sion (Kamintsky et al., 2019). In the present study, by <lb/>combining human data, animal studies and computational <lb/>modelling, we show that an increase in slow blood-to-brain <lb/>transport is the hallmark of microvascular pathology follow-<lb/>ing injury. We propose a mechanism-based diagnostic ap-<lb/>proach to detect and track traumatic microvascular pathology <lb/>and BBBD after these common brain injuries. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Human subjects <lb/>The study was approved by the Soroka University Medical <lb/>Center institutional review board; written informed consent was <lb/>given by all participants. The study population included 42 <lb/>Israeli amateur American football players playing in the Israeli <lb/>Football League (IFL), and a control group comprising 27 ath-<lb/>letes practicing a non-contact sport and 26 non-athletes. <lb/>Magnetic resonance scans were also performed in 51 patients <lb/>with malignant brain tumours, ischaemic stroke or traumatic <lb/>brain injury. The NFL sideline concussion assessment tool was <lb/>used to document history of previous head injuries, including <lb/>concussions, as well as symptoms assessment and Standardized <lb/>Assessment of Concussion (SAC) tests. <lb/>MRI <lb/>All subjects were scanned on a 3 T Philips Ingenia MRI scanner. <lb/>Image acquisition protocol was performed as described previ-<lb/>ously (Weissberg et al., 2014; Serlin et al., 2019). Briefly, T 1 -<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Leaky BBB in American football players <lb/>BRAIN 2020: 143; 1826-1842 | </note>
			
			<page>1827 <lb/></page>
			
			Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/brain/article/143/6/1826/5848368 by guest on 02 August 2022 <lb/>

			<body>and T 2 -weighted imaging, FLAIR, diffusion, and susceptibility-<lb/>weighted imaging (SWI) data were acquired, followed by a DCE <lb/>sequence. After five dynamic scans, the contrast agent gadoter-<lb/>ate meglumine (Gd-DOTA, Dotarem V R , 0.1 mmol/kg, 0.5 M, 1.5 <lb/>ml/s) was administered intravenously. <lb/>Blood sampling and analysis <lb/>Immediately prior to MRI, 5 ml of whole blood was withdrawn <lb/>in SST II advance Vacutainer tubes. Samples were centrifuged at <lb/>2000g for 15 min. Serum fraction was stored at -80 C until <lb/>use. Serum levels of inflammation, neuronal or glial injury <lb/>markers were measured using the Xmap (Luminex) method <lb/>(R&amp;D Systems) and ELISA (R&amp;D Systems) as per manufac-<lb/>turer&apos;s instructions. In brief, diluted samples (50 ml) were incu-<lb/>bated in a 96-well plate containing antibody-coated magnetic <lb/>beads for 2 h at room temperature under gentle orbital agita-<lb/>tion. Then, beads were washed with the provided wash buffer <lb/>and signal was developed using the provided biotin antibody <lb/>cocktail and streptavidin-peroxidase. Signal was determined <lb/>using a Luminex 200 plate reader. Levels were calculated by a <lb/>standard curve for each analyte. <lb/>Animals <lb/>Animal housing and experiments were conducted in accordance <lb/>with guidelines of the Association for Assessment and <lb/>Accreditation of Laboratory Animal Care and National <lb/>Research Council Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory <lb/>Animals. All experiments involving animals adhered to provi-<lb/>sions in the Animal Welfare Act and were approved by <lb/>Institutional Animal Care and Use Committees (IACUC) at Ben-<lb/>Gurion University of the Negev and Boston University School <lb/>of Medicine. Animals were provided with food and water ad <lb/>libitum. Ambient temperature was controlled at 20-22 C with <lb/>12 h light-dark cycles. <lb/>Traumatic brain injury models <lb/>We used two models for rmTBI: (i) a modified weight-drop <lb/>model, in which substantial rotation of the head and neck <lb/>occurs following impact (Marmarou et al., 1994; Kane et al., <lb/>2012; Mychasiuk et al., 2014). Briefly, young adult (8-10 <lb/>weeks) male Sprague Dawley rats were sedated using an induc-<lb/>tion chamber (3% isoflurane, 2 l/min O 2 ), until the toe-pinch <lb/>reflex was absent. Rats were then placed in the prone position <lb/>on a sheet of aluminium foil taped to the top of a plastic box <lb/>(30 Â 30 Â 20 cm in depth). A metal bolt (1 cm diameter Â <lb/>10 cm length) was placed on the scalp (midline, frontal bone). <lb/>TBI was induced using a weight (600 g) travelling vertically <lb/>(1.2 m) along a metal guide rail. Following the impact, animals <lb/>fell onto a foam pad placed at the bottom of the box. Sham <lb/>controls underwent the same procedures but without injury. <lb/>(ii) Unilateral (left-lateral) closed-head impact injury was con-<lb/>ducted in adult (10-12 weeks of age) male C57BL/6 mice <lb/>(Charles River Laboratories), as established at the Laboratory <lb/>Animal Science Center, Boston University School of Medicine <lb/>(Tagge et al., 2018). Briefly, mice were injected intraperito-<lb/>neally with buprenorphine (0.2 mg/kg) and secured in the <lb/>prone position via modified DecapiCones (Braintree Scientific <lb/>Inc.). The restrained mice were then positioned on the impact-<lb/>or such that the inner pad of the sled contacted the left <lb/>temporal-zygomatic region of the head. The head and neck <lb/>were free to allow flexion, extension, and rotation of the cer-<lb/>vical spine in the horizontal and sagittal planes to model con-<lb/>ditions relevant to human head impact exposure. Linear <lb/>translation of the sled resulted in left-lateral impact and trau-<lb/>matic head acceleration. Mice were exposed to two impacts 15 <lb/>min apart at a target sled speed of 5.0 m/s. Age-matched naı ¨ve <lb/>C57BL/6 mice were used as controls. MRI was performed 3 h, <lb/>1 day, 3 days and 1 week after injury using 11.7 T MRI <lb/>(Bruker) at the Boston University School of Medicine High-<lb/>Field NMR Core Facility as described (Tagge et al., 2018). For <lb/>additional details see the Supplementary material. <lb/>Vascular injury model <lb/>Experiments were performed in male Sprague-Dawley rats <lb/>(200-380 g, Harlan) as reported (Vazana et al., 2016). For add-<lb/>itional details see the Supplementary material. <lb/>Recurrent seizure model <lb/>Experiments were performed in male Sprague-Dawley rats using <lb/>the open window method as reported (Vazana et al., 2016). For <lb/>additional details see the Supplementary material. <lb/>BBB permeability quantification in <lb/>humans <lb/>Analysis was performed as reported (Chassidim et al., 2013; <lb/>Veksler et al., 2014; Weissberg et al., 2014; Serlin et al., 2019). <lb/>Briefly, preprocessing included image registration and normal-<lb/>ization to MNI coordinates using SPM12 (http://www.fil.ion. <lb/>ucl.ac.uk/spm). BBB permeability was calculated using in-house <lb/>MATLAB script, implementing previously described method <lb/>(Veksler et al., 2014). For rapid contrast accumulation, the <lb/>modified Tofts method was implemented, where middle cerebral <lb/>artery (MCA) was used as the arterial input function (AIF) <lb/>(Tofts, 1997). For slow accumulation, a linear fit is applied to <lb/>the later part [6-17 min, s(t)] of the concentration curve of each <lb/>voxel [Ct(t)]: <lb/>s t <lb/>ð Þ ¼ Ct t <lb/>ð Þ; 8t start 5t5t end <lb/>(1) <lb/>s t <lb/>ð Þ ¼ A Á t þ B <lb/>(2) <lb/>Where A and B are the slope and intercept of the linear re-<lb/>gression, respectively. <lb/>To compensate for physiological (e.g. heart rate, blood flow) <lb/>and technical (e.g. injection rate) variability between scans, a <lb/>normalized permeability index (NPI) is introduced: <lb/>NPI ¼ <lb/>A <lb/>A VIF <lb/>(3) <lb/>where A VIF is the slope at the superior sagittal sinus, which is <lb/>characterized by a larger diameter and a higher signal-to-noise <lb/>ratio, compared to the MCA. <lb/>For regional analysis of BBBD, brains were segmented into <lb/>126 anatomically defined regions (MNI brain atlas: https:// <lb/>github.com/neurodebian/spm12/tree/master/tpm). The number <lb/>of voxels with abnormally high BBB permeability (contrast ac-<lb/>cumulation rates exceeding the above-mentioned intensity <lb/></body>

			<page>1828</page>
			
			<note place="headnote"> | BRAIN 2020: 143; 1826-1842 <lb/>R. Veksler et al. <lb/></note>
			
			Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/brain/article/143/6/1826/5848368 by guest on 02 August 2022 <lb/>

			<body>threshold) was quantified within each region and divided by the <lb/>total number of voxels comprising the region. This ratio was <lb/>defined as the per cent of region volume with BBBD. <lb/>Diffusion tensor imaging analysis <lb/>Diffuse tensor imaging (DTI)-based fibre tracking was per-<lb/>formed using mrDiffusion, an open-source software written by <lb/>the Vision, Imaging Science and Technology Activities (VISTA) <lb/>lab at Stanford University (https://github.com/vistalab/vistasoft, <lb/>CA, USA), and in-house MATLAB scripts. For additional details <lb/>see the Supplementary material. <lb/>Repeated scans comparison <lb/>To measure reproducibility of results, we calculated the similar-<lb/>ity index between two scans (S1 and S2) of the players who <lb/>were scanned twice: <lb/>Similarity index ¼ <lb/>P <lb/>S1S2 <lb/>B <lb/>j j <lb/>j j <lb/>(4) <lb/>where S1 and S2 are binary images in which voxels with abnor-<lb/>mally high NPI = 1, and B <lb/>j j <lb/>j j is the number of voxels within <lb/>the brain. Hence, the similarity index is valued between 0 and <lb/>1. Similarity indices were calculated for the whole brain, as well <lb/>as for white and grey matter. <lb/>BBB permeability analysis using <lb/>MRI in rodents <lb/>DCE-MRI was analysed as reported (Tagge et al., 2018). An ex-<lb/>ternal standard of diluted gadopentetate dimeglumine (1:2000 <lb/>dilution of MagnevistV R , 0.5 mmol/ml, Bayer) was used for nor-<lb/>malization of the T 1 -weighted signal. A linear fit was calculated <lb/>for the final 900 s of the DCE curve, beginning $16 min follow-<lb/>ing contrast injection. The slope of the linear fit, referred to as <lb/>permeability index (PI), reflects brain accumulation of the con-<lb/>trast agent and serves as a measure of BBB permeability. The PI <lb/>map was generated by averaging data from three windows with <lb/>a 1 min shift. The mean ipsilateral and contralateral PIs were <lb/>calculated using a custom MATLAB script developed to select <lb/>region of interest (75 pixels) in both hemispheres. For visualiza-<lb/>tion, PI maps were superimposed on the post-contrast T 1 -<lb/>weighted image. A permeability threshold was defined as the <lb/>mean PI value plus two standard deviations in the region of <lb/>interest contralateral to the injured region. Voxels with supra-<lb/>threshold PI were displayed in 8-bit colour scale on top of the <lb/>grayscale T 1 -weighted image. <lb/>Animal BBB permeability analysis <lb/>using intravital fluorescence imaging <lb/>Data analysis was performed as reported (Vazana et al., 2016) <lb/>using in-house MATLAB scripts and included subpixel image <lb/>registration, segmentation using noise filtration, hole-filling and <lb/>adaptive threshold to produce a binary image, separating blood <lb/>vessels from extravascular regions. For additional details see the <lb/>Supplementary material. <lb/>Ex vivo assessment of BBB <lb/>permeability <lb/>Ex vivo assessment of BBB permeability was performed as <lb/>reported previously (Bar-Klein et al., 2017) (Supplementary ma-<lb/>terial). Briefly, under deep isoflurane anaesthesia, Evans blue <lb/>(48 mg/kg) was injected into the tail vein, followed 30 min later <lb/>with intracardial perfusion (4% paraformaldehyde in phos-<lb/>phate-buffered saline). Immunohistochemistry was performed <lb/>using standard techniques on 30-mm thick coronal sections, <lb/>using primary anti-GFAP antibody (Dako Z0334), followed by <lb/>secondary antibody donkey anti-rabbit IgG-Alexa Fluor V R 488 <lb/>(ThermoFisher Scientific, A21206, 1:500 dilution). Sections <lb/>were visualized using a Zeiss Axioplan 2 microscope. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>To compare between control and players groups, two-sided <lb/>Mann-Whitney U-test was used. For voxel-wise analysis of areas <lb/>with BBBD in players versus controls, each voxel in the statistic-<lb/>al image is the result of a comparison of 2 Â 2 neighbours for <lb/>every subject, without overlaps. For multiple comparisons, two-<lb/>sided Mann-Whitney U-test with false discovery rate (FDR) cor-<lb/>rection was used. For segment-wise analysis on fibre-flux diffu-<lb/>sion density (FFDD) data of specific fibres, two-sided Mann-<lb/>Whitney U-test was used with FDR correction for multiple com-<lb/>parisons. For correlation analysis of serum biomarkers and NPI <lb/>values, either Pearson or Spearman methods were used, as <lb/>denoted. Pearson method was used for correlation analysis of <lb/>model-derived values. <lb/></body>
			
			<div type="annex">Data availability <lb/>The data that support the findings of this study are available <lb/>from the corresponding author, upon reasonable request. <lb/></div>
			
			<body>Results <lb/>Repeated mild TBI is associated <lb/>with persistent BBBD <lb/>We previously reported the use of DCE-MRI to detect a <lb/>leaky BBB in a small cohort of American football players <lb/>(Weissberg et al., 2014). In the present study, we used a <lb/>modified DCE-MRI protocol in a larger cohort of amateur <lb/>American football players (n = 42 males; age range, 18-39 <lb/>years; median, 25 years) scanned during (on-season) and <lb/>after (off-season) two consecutive seasons of play and prac-<lb/>tice. To obtain permeability values in healthy individuals, we <lb/>first scanned a cohort of age-and sex-matched non-contact <lb/>sport athletes (n = 27). Each registered brain voxel was <lb/>assigned a value corresponding to an NPI (Fig. 1A). Based <lb/>on a cumulative distribution function (CDF) of NPI values <lb/>(the entire brain volume) in young healthy individuals, we <lb/>defined an upper limit for &apos;normal&apos; NPI as the 95th percent-<lb/>ile of the mean CDF (Fig. 1B). Brain voxels with higher val-<lb/>ues were considered as &apos;abnormally high NPI&apos;. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Leaky BBB in American football players <lb/>BRAIN 2020: 143; 1826-1842 | </note>

			<page>1829 <lb/></page>
			
			Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/brain/article/143/6/1826/5848368 by guest on 02 August 2022 <lb/>

			<body>In healthy controls, voxels with above-threshold NPI <lb/>were sparsely distributed throughout the brain with <lb/>greater density in white matter compared to grey matter <lb/>(Fig. 1A and C). In contrast, brain permeability maps <lb/>from American football players often demonstrated clus-<lb/>ters of brain voxels with high NPI values (Fig. 1D), sug-<lb/>gesting accumulation of contrast agent in distinct brain <lb/>regions (see below). <lb/>In all players, SWI excluded microhaemorrhagic lesions. <lb/>Twenty players were scanned twice (on-and off-season) in a <lb/>random order, with an inter-scan interval of 3.67-11 <lb/>months (median, 6 months). Importantly, while in different <lb/>individuals different brain regions displayed high NPI values, <lb/>their spatial distribution was consistent in repeated scans of <lb/>the same individual (Fig. 1E and F). Similarity index for <lb/>repeated scans (Fig. 1F, n = 20, see &apos;Materials and methods&apos; <lb/>section) was found to be consistently high in whole brain <lb/>analysis (mean ± SD, 0.87 ± 0.12), as well as segmentation <lb/>to grey matter (0.88 ± 0.11) and white matter (0.84 ± 0.14). <lb/>This finding suggests that localized post-traumatic micro-<lb/>vascular pathology may persist for months in a subset of <lb/>players. <lb/>Next, an additional control group of age-matched healthy <lb/>non-athletes (n = 26; age range, 18-40 years; median, 30 <lb/>years) were scanned. Because no statistical differences in NPI <lb/>maps were found, the two control groups were merged. In <lb/>total, 62 scans of players and 53 scans of control subjects <lb/>were acquired. Players showed higher percentage of brain <lb/>volume with high NPI values compared to controls (Fig. 1G, <lb/>P = 0.006; following exclusion of one player, who had <lb/>450% of brain voxels with high NPI value and was consid-<lb/>ered an outlier, P = 0.01). Players showed higher percentage <lb/>of brain volume with high NPI following repeating the ana-<lb/>lysis with a minimum cluster threshold of 10 voxels <lb/>(P = 0.04), suggesting that BBBD tends to occur in distinct <lb/>brain regions (see below and Supplementary Fig. 1). Using <lb/>k-means clustering, a threshold was calculated defining an <lb/>&apos;intact BBB&apos; group (58.4% of brain voxels with high NPI), <lb/>and a &apos;leaky&apos; (or pathological) BBB group (58.4% of voxels <lb/>with high NPI, Fig. 1H). Players were three times more likely <lb/>to be clustered in the pathological group (9.4% versus <lb/>27.4%, chi square, P = 0.01). In players with repeated scans, <lb/>47.4% (9/19) displayed a gradual resolution of the focal <lb/>pathology, as indicated by a decreasing volume with high <lb/>Figure 1 DCE-MRI reveals persistent BBBD in American <lb/>football players. (A) Maps of NPI were created to measure <lb/>changes in BBB permeability. (B) A cumulative distribution function <lb/>(CDF) plot shows similar NPI values in controls (n = 27). (C and D) <lb/>High NPI values (40.04) are superimposed on anatomical scan of <lb/>control (C) and a representative player with BBBD (D). <lb/>(E) Repeated scans (8-month interval) revealed local increase in the <lb/>number of voxels with high NPI. (F) Similarity analysis showed con-<lb/>sistent results between repeated scans (n = 20), for whole brain, <lb/>grey matter (GM) and white matter (WM). Bars represent mean <lb/>similarity index ± SD. (G) Graph showing percentage of brain vol-<lb/>ume with above-threshold NPI in controls (n = 53) versus players <lb/>(n = 41; for players that were scanned twice, the averaged value is <lb/>shown) demonstrates statistically significant increase in players <lb/>(P = 0.01, Mann-Whitney U-test). (H) K-means clustering of the en-<lb/>tire dataset into &apos;healthy&apos; (blue) and &apos;pathological&apos; (red) BBB groups. <lb/>(I) Comparison of percentage of brain volume with high NPI in play-<lb/>ers who were scanned twice; grey box represents the &apos;healthy&apos; <lb/>group. (J) Probabilistic map representing brain voxels with high <lb/>probability to display high (pathological) NPI values in players <lb/>(upper row) and controls (lower row). (K) Voxel-wise statistical <lb/>comparison of NPI values in players with BBBD versus healthy con-<lb/>trols. Areas where P 5 0.01 (Mann-Whitney U-test with FDR cor-<lb/>rection for multiple comparisons) are superimposed over <lb/>anatomical scan. <lb/></body>

			<page>1830</page>

			<note place="headnote"> | BRAIN 2020: 143; 1826-1842 <lb/>R. Veksler et al. <lb/>Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/brain/article/143/6/1826/5848368 by guest on 02 August 2022 <lb/></note>

			<body>NPI, whereas in 52.6% (10/19), the number of high NPI <lb/>voxels increased (Fig. 1I). <lb/>We found weak positive correlation between the per cent <lb/>brain volume with BBBD and player age (r = 0.26, <lb/>P = 0.044, Spearman), not observed in age-matched controls <lb/>(see &apos;Discussion&apos; section). No correlation was found between <lb/>changes in permeability over time and likelihood of being <lb/>concussed at the time of scanning (on-or off-season), inter-<lb/>scan interval, number of reported concussions, age at start <lb/>of football play or cumulative years of play. No differences <lb/>were found between players with or without BBB pathology <lb/>in number of years playing, number of reported concussions, <lb/>symptoms number or score on a standardized concussion as-<lb/>sessment test (Supplementary Tables 1 and 2). No correl-<lb/>ation was found between the time since last reported <lb/>concussion prior to imaging (range, 0.25-272 months; me-<lb/>dian, 12 months; n = 18 versus 12-228 months; median, 96 <lb/>months; n = 5 in players versus controls, respectively) to the <lb/>extent of BBB pathology. Yet, players with BBBD were sig-<lb/>nificantly older than those with intact BBB (median age, 29 <lb/>versus 25 years, P = 0.028) and started playing at an older <lb/>age (median, 25 versus 21.5 years, P = 0.008). <lb/>In a search for susceptible brain structures, we created <lb/>probabilistic BBB permeability maps in which the probability <lb/>of each voxel to display above-threshold NPI was calculated <lb/>(Fig. 1J). Brain regions that were found to be more suscep-<lb/>tible to BBB pathology in players, but not in controls, <lb/>included the left temporal lobe, thalamus, cerebral <lb/>peduncles, and red nucleus as well as white matter tracts <lb/>(see below). Voxel-wise statistical analysis comparing the <lb/>two groups showed significant differences in permeability in <lb/>the left temporal and left occipital lobes, as well as in white <lb/>matter regions and basal ganglia (Fig. 1K). Regional analysis <lb/>of BBBD was in-line with voxel-based statistics: upon brain <lb/>clustering to 126 anatomical subregions (BBBD was defined <lb/>if the percentage of voxels with high NPI was 42 SD of <lb/>averaged percentage in controls within a region), most foot-<lb/>ball players showed regional BBBD, confirming region-wise <lb/>susceptibility in players (Supplementary Fig. 1). <lb/>Persistent BBBD co-localizes with <lb/>white matter abnormalities <lb/>To examine white matter integrity in our cohort, we used <lb/>DTI (Supplementary Table 3). Fractional anisotropy meas-<lb/>urements significantly decreased in players compared to con-<lb/>trols in the following tracts: left-thalamic radiation, corpus <lb/>callosum, left inferior fronto-occipital fasciculus (IFOF) and <lb/>left inferior longitudinal fasciculus (ILF). Mean diffusivity <lb/>values significantly increased in the right arcuate fasciculus. <lb/>Given the focal nature of BBB abnormalities within long <lb/>white matter tracts (Fig. 1K) and high variability of diffusion <lb/>parameters within tracts, we produced a metric of local <lb/>changes in tract diffusion characteristics using FFDD, a re-<lb/>cently developed measure that combines diffusion parame-<lb/>ters with geometric properties (Benou et al., 2019). The <lb/>FFDD tract profile of the IFOF is shown in Fig. 2A for both <lb/>fractional anisotropy and mean diffusivity, demonstrating <lb/>the variability along the tract in healthy individuals (n = 17). <lb/>In players (n = 13) we found a significant decrease in frac-<lb/>tional anisotropy and increase in mean diffusivity in specific <lb/>regions within the IFOF and the forceps minor of the corpus <lb/>callosum (Fig. 2B, C, E and F). Specifically, an increase in <lb/>mean diffusivity was found in caudal portion of the left <lb/>IFOF towards the occipital lobe, as in the central region of <lb/>the forceps minor (genu of the corpus callosum). <lb/>Interestingly, these white matter changes were consistent <lb/>with permeability changes as observed above: NPI values in <lb/>the left posterior segment of the IFOF were significantly <lb/>higher compared to those in the anterior segment <lb/>(0.025 ± 0.084 versus -0.027 ± 0.074, P = 0.038, Wilcoxon <lb/>signed-ranks test). Similarly, and consistent with FFDD data <lb/>of the forceps minor (Fig. 2F), NPI values within the midline <lb/>region of the tract (genu of corpus callosum) were signifi-<lb/>cantly higher compared to those in the left anterior segment <lb/>of the tract (-0.035 ± 0.16 versus -0.065 ± 0.11, P = 0.021, <lb/>Wilcoxon signed-ranks test). No significant differences be-<lb/>tween the groups were found along the corticospinal tract in <lb/>FFDD or NPI values (Fig. 2D and G). <lb/>Finally, analysis of serum samples collected at the time of <lb/>scanning revealed no significant differences in levels of <lb/>blood-based biomarkers of glial injury (S100B, GFAP), neur-<lb/>onal injury (neurogranin, SNCB, Tau, BDNF) or neuroin-<lb/>flammation (IL6, IL33, IL17, IL23, IL18, IFN) between <lb/>players and healthy controls, or between players with or <lb/>without high brain volume with BBB pathology (data not <lb/>shown). <lb/>BBBD is associated with slow <lb/>contrast agent accumulation <lb/>To validate the modified DCE-MRI approach, we examined <lb/>patients with brain pathologies known to be associated with <lb/>BBBD including malignant brain tumours (n = 4), ischaemic <lb/>stroke (n = 46) and haemorrhagic traumatic contusion <lb/>(n = 1). In all three conditions, a clearly defined brain lesion <lb/>was associated with BBBD within the lesion and/or in the <lb/>surrounding tissue. In patients with grade IV malignant glial <lb/>tumours, T 1 -weighted MRI scan after injection of gadolin-<lb/>ium (Gd)-based contrast agent showed an enhanced tumour <lb/>surrounded by peritumoral oedema (Fig. 3A and B). <lb/>Relative concentration-time curves showed rapid accumula-<lb/>tion of the tracer in the tumour within the first 5 min after <lb/>injection (Fig. 3C). In contrast, peritumoral brain regions <lb/>showed a delayed and slower accumulation that was detect-<lb/>able only 6-15 min post-injection. In the tumour-free contra-<lb/>lateral hemisphere, contrast agent washout was similar to <lb/>that observed in large blood vessels (not shown). SWI <lb/>revealed abnormal signal consistent with haemorrhage at the <lb/>tumour core, but not in the surrounding brain, thus preclud-<lb/>ing active bleeding as the cause of contrast accumulation <lb/>(Fig. 3D). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Leaky BBB in American football players <lb/>BRAIN 2020: 143; 1826-1842 | </note>

			<page>1831 <lb/></page>

			Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/brain/article/143/6/1826/5848368 by guest on 02 August 2022 <lb/>

			<body>We next compared vascular permeability calculated using <lb/>the extended Tofts model (Tofts et al., 1999) and the <lb/>delayed linear approximation method to evaluate fast and <lb/>slow enhancement dynamics (NPI), respectively. A merged <lb/>permeability map shows that while both methods detected <lb/>high permeability at the tumour core (Fig. 3G, yellow), peri-<lb/>tumoral BBB pathology was only detected when slow <lb/>changes in contrast dynamics were measured (Fig. 3E and F, <lb/>green). Similarly, a clear BBB lesion with both fast (K trans ) <lb/>and slow (NPI) contrast agent accumulation is seen in the is-<lb/>chaemic core, whereas in the surrounding brain tissue only a <lb/>slow contrast accumulation is seen (Fig. 3H). Analysis of a <lb/>cohort of patients with a subacute stroke (n = 46, 24 h to 7 <lb/>days after the acute event) shows that while both K trans and <lb/>NPI values are higher in patients compared to age-matched <lb/>(n = 23) or young (n = 27) healthy controls, the distribution <lb/>of values is strikingly different (Fig. 3K, age-matched <lb/>controls versus patients: P = 0.008 for NPI, P 5 0.0001 for <lb/>K trans , Kruskal-Wallis, young controls versus patients: <lb/>P 5 0.0001 for NPI, P = 0.0001 for K trans , Kruskal-Wallis) <lb/>Importantly, while the fast accumulation and the typical <lb/>early changes in diffusion-weighted imaging (DWI) and fluid <lb/>attenuation inversion recovery (FLAIR) had resolved in fol-<lb/>low-up scans, high NPI values were persistent months after <lb/>the acute ischaemic events (Fig. 3I-K). Figure 3L shows <lb/>images from a patient with a haemorrhagic contusion at the <lb/>base of the right frontal lobe resulting from contrecoup in-<lb/>jury secondary to occipital trauma. The posterior injury <lb/>resulted in a persistent left visual field defect. MRI revealed <lb/>bleeding at the base of the frontal lobe with peri-contusional <lb/>oedema and no other apparent brain pathology. However, <lb/>BBB maps revealed high NPI in both frontal and occipital <lb/>lobes, consistent with the injury mechanism and clinical <lb/>sequelae. Finally, in our football players cohort (Fig. 1), no <lb/>Figure 2 White matter changes correlate with persistent BBB pathology in American football players. (A) Local differences in <lb/>diffusion were analysed by FFDD of fractional anisotropy (FA; left) and mean diffusivity (MD; right). Values were averaged along the IFOF white <lb/>matter tracts in controls (n = 17) and players (n = 13). (B-D) Difference between players and control (DFFDD) in three fibres, namely inferior <lb/>fronto-occipital fasciculus (IFOF, B), forceps minor (C) and corticospinal tract (D), are presented in units of standard deviation of FFDD. (E-<lb/>G) Statistical comparison (Mann-Whitney U-test with FDR correction for multiple comparisons) was performed on 50 segments along each <lb/>fibre, revealing significantly differences in IFOF and forceps minor, but not in corticospinal tracts. <lb/></body>

			<page>1832</page>

			<note place="headnote"> | BRAIN 2020: 143; 1826-1842 <lb/>R. Veksler et al. <lb/>Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/brain/article/143/6/1826/5848368 by guest on 02 August 2022 <lb/></note>

			<body>differences in K trans values, or brain volume with high K trans , <lb/>were found between players and controls (cf. Fig. 1G and <lb/>Supplementary Fig. 2). <lb/>Slow contrast enhancement <lb/>characterizes focal BBBD in a <lb/>rodent model of repeated mild <lb/>closed-head injury <lb/>As we found indirect evidence for a slow extravasation of <lb/>Gd-based contrast agent in DCE-MRI of patients with dif-<lb/>ferent brain pathology, we next aimed to confirm that this <lb/>&apos;slow enhancement&apos; indeed reflects a leaky BBB. We used <lb/>two established rodent models for rmTBI. Consistent with <lb/>the results obtained in football players (Fig. 1G), DCE-MRI <lb/>in rats exposed to five repeated impacts (weight-drop model) <lb/>revealed a large variability between animals with a higher <lb/>brain volume with high NPI in injured rats (n = 19) com-<lb/>pared to sham controls (n = 15, P = 0.01, Fig. 4A). To con-<lb/>firm a leaky BBB we performed fluorescent angiography <lb/>using intravital microscopy. This directly revealed the leak-<lb/>age of fluorescent tracer in the cortex of injured rats (n = 3) <lb/>compared to sham-controls (n = 5, P = 0.035, Fig. 4A and <lb/>see below). We next scanned mice subjected to repeated <lb/>mild closed-head impact injury (two impacts, 15-min inter-<lb/>val; n = 3 mice) at different time points after injury (3 h, 1 <lb/>day, 3 days, 1 week). We calculated changes of T 1 -weighted <lb/>Figure 3 BBBD is characterized by fast and slow accumu-<lb/>lation of contrast agent. (A-G) Images from a patient with ma-<lb/>lignant glial tumour. (A) T 1 -weighted image following Gd injection <lb/>showing the enhanced tumour mass (arrow). (B) FLAIR image: note <lb/>the bright right frontal region indicating peritumoral oedema. (C) <lb/>Relative Gd concentration-time curve in tumour (blue), peritumoral <lb/>oedema (red) and contralateral, apparently healthy brain (intact, <lb/>green). (D) Susceptibility-weighted imaging (SWI) reveals blood <lb/>products at the tumour site (arrow) but not in the surrounding <lb/>brain. BBB permeability maps showing the fast (K trans using the <lb/>Tofts model, E) and slow (NPI, F) contrast accumulation. (G) A <lb/>merged image showing both fast and slow contrast accumulation. <lb/>(H) Images from a patient 1 week after a stroke. The ischaemic le-<lb/>sion is visible on the right (FLAIR), with no haemorrhage (SWI). <lb/>Merged maps of fast (K trans ) and slow (NPI) contrast accumulation <lb/>are shown. (I and J) Images from a patient 2 and 21 months after <lb/>acute ischaemic stroke. Clinical imaging techniques (DWI, FLAIR) <lb/>show the ischaemic region at 2 months with no sign of abnormality <lb/>in the later scan. BBBD is more clearly shown when slow (com-<lb/>pared to fast) Gd accumulation is calculated. Note the partial reso-<lb/>lution of the peri-ischaemic BBBD in the later scan. (K) Left: <lb/>Percentage of brain volume with abnormally high permeability (fast, <lb/>i.e K trans and slow, i.e. NPI) in patients with subacute stroke (Pat.; <lb/>n = 46) compared with young controls (Yng; n = 27) and age-<lb/>matched controls (Age m.; n = 27). Middle and right: Slow and fast <lb/>blood-to-brain permeability were calculated in the brain of the pa-<lb/>tient shown in I and J, 2 and 21 months following an acute stroke. <lb/>The hemisphere ipsilateral to the ischaemic lesion and in the <lb/>contralateral (Contra) (2 months: P 5 0.0001 for NPI, P = 0.018 for <lb/>K trans ; 21 months: P 5 0.0001 for NPI, P = 0.76 for K trans , t-test). <lb/>(L) Images obtained 9 days after mild TBI due to occipital impact. <lb/>Haemorrhagic contusion with oedema is observed at the base of <lb/>the frontal lobe, with no occipital pathology in clinically routine <lb/>sequences. Yet, abnormal increase in slow Gd accumulation (NPI) is <lb/>found in both occipital and frontal regions. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Leaky BBB in American football players <lb/>BRAIN 2020: 143; 1826-1842 | </note>
			
			<page>1833 <lb/></page>

			Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/brain/article/143/6/1826/5848368 by guest on 02 August 2022 <lb/>

			<body>signal in initial and delayed phases (1-3 min and 16-30 min <lb/>after contrast injection, respectively). No evidence for a <lb/>BBBD was detected in controls (Fig. 4A) and none of the <lb/>mice showed contrast accumulation during the initial early <lb/>phase. In contrast, all TBI mice exhibited focal regions of en-<lb/>hancement during the delayed phase, localized predominant-<lb/>ly in the left perirhinal cortex ipsilateral to the impact site. <lb/>The lesions exhibited varying patterns of temporal evolution <lb/>of BBBD, including a peak at Day 3 post-injury followed by <lb/>partial resolution at 3 weeks (TBI1, Fig. 4B), slow progres-<lb/>sion during the 3-week evaluation period (TBI2, Fig. 4C), <lb/>and subtle abnormalities in left lateral cortex and midline <lb/>structures (TBI3, Fig. 4D). None of the injured mice dis-<lb/>played DCE-MRI evidence of right-sided BBBD. Post-mor-<lb/>tem examination showed no macroscopic evidence of <lb/>contusion, necrosis, haematoma, haemorrhage, or focal tis-<lb/>sue damage in any of the injured mice (Fig. 4E). Metallomic <lb/>imaging mass spectrometry (MIMS) confirmed the presence <lb/>and localization of gadolinium in the brain 1-week post-in-<lb/>jury (Fig. 4F). Extravasated gadolinium was detected in the <lb/>left-lateral perirhinal cortex in a pattern similar to the corre-<lb/>sponding DCE-MRI-derived permeability map (Fig. 4B). <lb/>Histopathology examination revealed neuronal dropout and <lb/>parenchymal rarefaction (spongiform changes, asterisk), con-<lb/>sistent with cellular injury and neurodegeneration, in the <lb/>superficial layers of the left perirhinal cortex ipsilateral and <lb/>subjacent to impact site (Fig. 4G, region 1). Middle cortical <lb/>layers also exhibited neurodegenerative changes marked by <lb/>clusters of pyknotic, intensely eosinophilic neurons (region <lb/>2). Deep cortical layers showed evidence of neuronal drop-<lb/>out (lower half, region 3); adjacent deeper areas contained <lb/>normal-appearing neurons (Fig. 4G, white arrows) and small <lb/>blood vessels (Fig. 4G, black arrowheads). No evidence of <lb/>red blood cells or haemosiderin-laden macrophages, indica-<lb/>tive of active or prior microhaemorrhage, was observed. The <lb/>contralateral right perirhinal cortex did not reveal observ-<lb/>able pathology (Fig. 4H). Transmission electron microscopy <lb/>confirmed traumatic microvascular injury in the ipsilateral <lb/>perirhinal cortex 1 week after injury induction, showing <lb/>involuting capillary, grossly thickened and tortuous basal <lb/>lamina, degenerating pericytes and oedematous astrocyte <lb/>endfeet and nearby degenerating neurons (Fig. 4I and J). <lb/>Slow contrast enhancement <lb/>characterizes the peri-ischaemic <lb/>brain in a rodent model of vascular <lb/>injury <lb/>As slow BBBD was also found in patients with subacute <lb/>stroke, suggesting it is not specific to traumatic injury, we <lb/>next tested an ischaemic vascular injury model in the rat <lb/>cerebral cortex, by using Rose bengal-induced photothrom-<lb/>bosis (Schoknecht et al., 2014). T 1 -weighted, T 2 -weighted, <lb/>and DWI MRIs acquired 24 h after injury showed the lesion <lb/>core, with high T 2 -weighted and DWI signals and low T 1 -<lb/>weighted signals consistent with cytotoxic oedema. The <lb/>surrounding region exhibited high T 2 -weighted and low <lb/>DWI signals as well as slow accumulation of gadolinium <lb/>during the 30 min post-injection scan. These results are con-<lb/>sistent with BBBD and vasogenic oedema in the peri-injured <lb/>brain, similar to the changes observed in the injured human <lb/>cortex (Fig. 5C and D). Using intravital microscopy and the <lb/>open window technique we measured directly cortical micro-<lb/>vascular permeability and excluded microhaemorrhages as a <lb/>cause for contrast accumulation. Fluorescent angiography <lb/>(Fig. 5E) confirmed the hypoperfused ischaemic core <lb/>(Fig. 5F, asterisks) surrounded by a region of hyperintense <lb/>extravascular signal in adjacent cortex, indicating leakage of <lb/>tracer (Fig. 5G). A linear fit model applied to each pixel <lb/>using a variable starting point (0-24 min) showed that as <lb/>the starting point progressed, the number of pixels with <lb/>positive slope increased, while the slope within the vessels <lb/>remained negative, indicating that while the vascular signal <lb/>decays (due to tracer washout), the tracer continues to accu-<lb/>mulate in the extravascular compartment (Fig. 5H-J). <lb/>Modelling predicts that slow tracer <lb/>accumulation is due to increased <lb/>cellular transport <lb/>The fast accumulation of gadolinium in malignant brain <lb/>tumours (Fig. 3C) likely reflects dysfunctional tight junctions <lb/>and increased paracellular diffusion. This is supported by <lb/>simulating changes in enhancement using a general tissue <lb/>model for exchange of contrast agent between blood and the <lb/>extravascular extracellular space. An important physiologic-<lb/>al parameter that is widely reported in DCE-MRI studies is <lb/>the volume-transfer constant K trans , which is the rate at <lb/>which contrast agent is delivered to the extravascular extra-<lb/>cellular space per volume of tissue and contrast agent con-<lb/>centration in the arterial blood plasma (Heye et al., 2014). <lb/>While increase in K trans models the fast enhancement <lb/>observed in DCE-MRI within (for example) malignant <lb/>tumours (e.g. Fig. 3), no increase in permeability was found <lb/>in the peritumoral brain, where contrast accumulation was <lb/>slow. <lb/>Recent animal studies point to transcellular transport <lb/>across the BBB that is independent of paracellular diffusion <lb/>(Kang et al., 2013; Knowland et al., 2014; De Bock et al., <lb/>2016; Haley and Lawrence, 2016; Zhang et al., 2017). We <lb/>thus hypothesized that the slow increase in contrast accumu-<lb/>lation was due to cellular transport. To model this hypoth-<lb/>esis, we introduced a third compartment representing a <lb/>unidirectional transfer from vessels to cells, reflecting trans-<lb/>cellular transport across the BBB (De Bock et al., 2016) <lb/>(Fig. 6A). Simulations over a wide range of parameters <lb/>revealed a strong linear correlation between the unidirection-<lb/>al (and not bi-directional) transfer constant to the additional <lb/>(cellular) compartment (i.e. K b,c ) and a slow increase in con-<lb/>trast concentrations (Fig. 6B Model 1; r = 0.959, P 5 10 -6 ), <lb/>consistent with the increased NPI values that were detected <lb/>by DCE-MRI (Figs 1, 3 and 5). <lb/></body>

			<page>1834</page>
			<note place="headnote"> | BRAIN 2020: 143; 1826-1842 <lb/>R. Veksler et al. <lb/></note>
			
			Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/brain/article/143/6/1826/5848368 by guest on 02 August 2022 <lb/>

			<body>Figure 4 In vivo DCE-MRI reveals distinct patterns focal neuropathology in rodents following head injury. (A) Left: Above-thresh-<lb/>old permeability index values overlaid on T 1 -weighted MRI scans from rats before and 1 week following repeated mild TBI. Middle: Percentage of <lb/>brain volume with high permeability index (P.I) in injured (n = 19) compared to sham-controls (n = 19, n = 15, respectively, P = 0.01); Right: <lb/>Colour-coded permeability maps of cortical surface vessels (see &apos;Materials and methods&apos; section). Higher permeability is shown in rmTBI rats <lb/>(n = 3) compared with sham controls (n = 5) in the presence of grossly normal brain. (B-E) Above-threshold DCE pixels overlaid on T 1 -<lb/>weighted MRI scans from mice subjected to sham procedure (B) or to lateral (left) closed-head impact injury (C and D) at 3 h, 1 day, 3 days, and <lb/>1 week following intervention. Despite comparable levels of transient neurobehavioural impairment, BBBD displayed in injured mice was variable. <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="headnote">Leaky BBB in American football players <lb/>BRAIN 2020: 143; 1826-1842 | </note>

			<page>1835 <lb/></page>

			<body>(continued) <lb/></body>

			Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/brain/article/143/6/1826/5848368 by guest on 02 August 2022 <lb/>

			<body>We next used confocal imaging to examine the transport <lb/>of Evans blue-albumin complex before and after BBBD ex-<lb/>perimentally-induced using the K + channel blocker 4-amino-<lb/>pyridine (4-AP) (Vazana et al., 2016). High-resolution <lb/>analysis of changes in fluorescent intensity revealed that fol-<lb/>lowing 4-AP application, Evans blue-albumin first transfers <lb/>from the vessel lumen to the vessel wall (520 min post-4-<lb/>AP; Fig. 6C and D), while Evans blue-albumin transit to the <lb/>extravascular space was delayed (420 min post-4-AP). <lb/>Repeating the experiment in the presence of the endocytosis <lb/>inhibitor MbCD, blocked Evans blue-albumin accumulation <lb/>in the vessel wall (Fig. 6C). Histological analysis of brain <lb/>sections from rats subjected to focal cerebrovascular injury <lb/>(Fig. 5) and injected with Evans blue-albumin further con-<lb/>firmed Evans blue-albumin accumulation within the walls of <lb/>small blood vessels in the peri-ischaemic core (Fig. 6C) and <lb/>within cellular structures, mainly astrocytes (Fig. 6F). <lb/>Together, these results support the notion that slow tracer <lb/>accumulation occurred via transcellular transport. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>We developed a modified DCE-MRI protocol and analytical <lb/>methods to investigate microvascular pathology and BBBD <lb/>associated with rmTBI in amateur American football play-<lb/>ers. For the first time, using human brain imaging, we distin-<lb/>guish between fast and slow leakage through the <lb/>pathological BBB. Together with recent studies from our <lb/>group (Kamintsky et al., 2019; Serlin et al., 2019) this is one <lb/>of a few studies using BBB imaging in healthy controls, <lb/>allowing one to set threshold values for pathological perme-<lb/>ability. These threshold values allow, for the first time, the <lb/>identification of a subset of players showing evidence of <lb/>focal brain microvascular pathology that persisted for many <lb/>months (up to 10 months, the longest time point measured). <lb/>Affected brain regions included temporal cortex, several <lb/>long white matter tracts (e.g. left IFOF and left ILF), cerebral <lb/>peduncles, and red nucleus of the midbrain. We further <lb/>bring evidence to suggest that slow accumulation of <lb/>peripherally-injected contrast agent reflects transcellular <lb/>endothelial transport mechanisms that underlie BBBD <lb/>detected in the American football players. <lb/>Widely used DCE-MRI methods are based on extended <lb/>Tofts or Patlak models (Patlak and Blasberg, 1985; Tofts <lb/>and Kermode, 1991; Sourbron and Buckley, 2013), primar-<lb/>ily used to evaluate conditions defined by robust and rapid <lb/>(45 min) leakage of contrast agent. Here, we demonstrate <lb/>that measuring the slow signal changes following contrast <lb/>agent injection enables the detection of a previously over-<lb/>looked pathology, namely post-injury BBBD. The proposed <lb/>analysis approach has the advantage over the classical Tofts <lb/>models by detecting a slow signal change, and over the <lb/>Patlak model by isolating the slow from the fast enhance-<lb/>ment. We thus show that: (i) a fast leak occurred during the <lb/>first $3 min after injection in the core of tumours, ischaemic <lb/>stroke and haemorrhage; and (ii) a far slower leak can be <lb/>found in perfused brain tissue surrounding tumours and the <lb/>ischaemic core, as well as in non-haemorrhagic traumatic in-<lb/>jury. Importantly, this slow subtle pathology may persist for <lb/>months and be detected even in the presence of apparently <lb/>normal brain tissue, as observed in routine clinical magnetic <lb/>resonance sequences (T 1 , T 2 , FLAIR, DWI, SWI) (Fig. 3). <lb/>We confirmed that a modified DCE-MRI protocol detects <lb/>slow BBB leakage in animal models of rmTBI and vascular <lb/>injury. Moreover, direct high-resolution imaging, histological <lb/>analysis and computational modelling support the slow ac-<lb/>cumulation of systemically injected contrast agents even in <lb/>the absence of fast leakage. Taken together, these results are <lb/>consistent with microvascular pathology, likely due to <lb/>increased cellular transport. <lb/>We implemented a modified DCE-MRI approach with a <lb/>longer (16.7 min) acquisition time than usually applied <lb/>(Vidarsson et al., 2009; Heye et al., 2014) to allow the de-<lb/>tection of a slow biological process, which we found below <lb/>the signal-to-noise detection levels with shorter acquisition <lb/>(Supplementary Fig. 3). We used the commonly used gado-<lb/>terate meglumine (Dotarem V R ) as a contrast agent. While test-<lb/>ing different contrast agents and protocols (e.g. injection <lb/>rate) was beyond the scope of the present study, our animal <lb/>Figure 4 Continued <lb/>(E) Gross brain pathology showing left lateral surface of the brain ipsilateral to impact. Arrow indicates approximate impact area. (F-H) <lb/>Confirmation of focal BBBD and corresponding neuropathology in impact-injured mouse TBI1 at 1 week post-injury. (F) MIMS brain map for <lb/>gadolinium (157Gd, coloured areas) overlaid on corresponding MIMS map for phosphorus (31P, black and white) showing accumulation of <lb/>extravasated Gd in the left perirhinal cortex (PRC) ipsilateral and to head impact. (G and H) Hematoxylin and eosin staining of an adjacent brain <lb/>section shows pathological changes in the left PRC (G), but not in the contralateral right PRC (H). Left PRC displays paucity of blood vessels, <lb/>neuronal dropout, and spongiform changes (asterisk) in the superficial cortical layers (region 1), clusters of pyknotic degenerating neurons (re-<lb/>gion 2) and neuronal dropout (lower half, region 3, see text for details) as well as adjacent areas with normal-appearing neurons (white arrows) <lb/>and small blood vessels (black arrowheads). The right PRC exhibits normal cellular and tissue structure, including highly-branched blood vessels <lb/>(black arrowheads). (I-L) Ultrastructural evidence of persistent traumatic microvascular injury in the left PRC. (I) Longitudinal section of a capil-<lb/>lary (asterisk marks lumen). Note pale oedematous (hydropic) cytoplasm in astrocyte endfeet (ae). as = astrocyte soma; e = endothelial cell; p = <lb/>pericyte; magnification = Â 800. (J) Degenerating neuron (nx) and nearby normal-appearing neurons (n). ap = astrocyte process; magnification <lb/>= Â 800. (K) Involuting capillary (asterisk). d = passing dendrite; magnification = Â1200. (L) Higher magnification of the same involuting capil-<lb/>lary (asterisk) shows thickened, tortuous basal lamina (arrowheads). Note hydropic cytoplasm and degenerating mitochondria (m) in the <lb/>ensheathing astrocyte endfeet (ae). p = degenerating pericyte; magnification = Â 3000. Scale bars = 5 mm (I-K), 2 mm (L). <lb/></body>

			<page>1836</page>

			<note place="headnote"> | BRAIN 2020: 143; 1826-1842 <lb/>R. Veksler et al. <lb/></note>

			Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/brain/article/143/6/1826/5848368 by guest on 02 August 2022 <lb/>

			<body>Figure 5 Slow contrast enhancement can be measured in a rodent model of vascular injury. BBB integrity was assessed 24 h after <lb/>induction of vascular injury using the photothrombosis model. (A) T 1 -weighted (T1w) scan following Gd injection reveals a hypo-perfused core <lb/>(asterisk) and a surrounding cortical region with contrast enhancement (blue line). (B) T 2 -weighted image demonstrates high signal in both hypo-<lb/>perfused core and contrast-enhanced surrounding region. (C and D) Permeability map (C, measured in units of intensity/time) was calculated <lb/>based on a linear fit of the slow (30 min) change of T 1 signal after contrast agent injection (D). (E-G) In vivo direct imaging after injection of the <lb/>fluorescent tracer sodium fluorescein demonstrates the hypo-perfused core (F, asterisk). (H-J) Conversely, in the surrounding cortex gradual <lb/>enhancement is seen during 20 min from injection, suggesting a slow leakage of the tracer. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Leaky BBB in American football players <lb/>BRAIN 2020: 143; 1826-1842 | </note>

			<page>1837 <lb/></page>

			Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/brain/article/143/6/1826/5848368 by guest on 02 August 2022 <lb/>

			<body>experiments using a different gadolinium-based, albumin-<lb/>binding gadofosveset trisodium (Ablavar V R ), a fluorescent-<lb/>tagged small molecule (sodium fluorescein) and the albumin-<lb/>bound Evans blue, suggest a relatively non-specific transport <lb/>mechanism. <lb/>Microvascular pathology is a prominent feature in all TBI <lb/>animal models (DeWitt and Prough, 2003; Sashindranath <lb/>et al., 2012; Boyd et al., 2015) and its role in neuroinflam-<lb/>mation, neuronal dysfunction, and neurodegeneration has <lb/>been documented (for reviews see Zlokovic, 2008; Abbott <lb/>et al., 2010; Shlosberg et al., 2010). In humans, while imag-<lb/>ing evidence for persistent BBB pathology after TBI is scarce <lb/>(Tomkins et al., 2008; Li et al., 2016), post-mortem neuro-<lb/>pathological studies confirm that microvascular changes and <lb/>increased barrier permeability are common in TBI patients, <lb/>even years after the acute insult (Rodrı ´guez-Baeza et al., <lb/>2003; Hay et al., 2015; Doherty et al., 2016; Tagge et al., <lb/>2018). Moreover, recent studies have identified perivascular <lb/>p-Tau pathology in post-mortem brains years after neuro-<lb/>trauma (Omalu et al., 2006; McKee et al., 2009, 2013; Mez <lb/>et al., 2017; Tagge et al., 2018) and perivascular tauopathy <lb/>as the uniquely defining brain lesion of early CTE (McKee <lb/>et al., 2016). Our data showing persistent leaky BBB in <lb/>young, active American football players, suggest that this <lb/>early pathology may could serve for early diagnosis and <lb/>monitoring of players at high-risk of developing delayed <lb/>complications. Notably, we observed that in some players, <lb/>BBB pathology continued to progress during the off-season, <lb/>despite reported reduction in exposure to head trauma. No <lb/>relations were found between the extent of BBBD and <lb/>reported concussion symptoms, nor the time from last con-<lb/>cussion. Interestingly, we found a weak positive correlation <lb/>between BBBD and players age, not found in age-matched <lb/>controls. In light of recent studies on age-related BBBD <lb/>(Senatorov et al., 2019) this finding suggest trauma may <lb/>underlie facilitated brain ageing and a long-lasting endothe-<lb/>lial damage, and may not truthfully reflect brain response to <lb/>an acute concussion. This seems to be consistent with emerg-<lb/>ing evidence from preclinical and clinical studies pointing to <lb/>the cumulative effect of head injury exposure, rather than <lb/>concussion per se, as the clinically relevant metric of risk for <lb/>post-traumatic sequel, including CTE (Stamm et al., 2015; <lb/>Huber et al., 2016; McAllister and McCrea, 2017; <lb/>Montenigro et al., 2017; Tagge et al., 2018). While CTE is <lb/>invariably associated with history of rmTBI, in a subset of <lb/>Figure 6 Slow tracer accumulation is consistent with <lb/>increased cellular transport. (A) Modelling contrast accumula-<lb/>tion rate using a three-compartment model, with a either a unidir-<lb/>ectional (model 1) or bi-directional (model 2) volume-transfer <lb/>constant (K b,c ). (B) Simulations over a wide range of parameters <lb/>reveal a clear correlation between K b,c and NPI values in the <lb/>unidirectional model (model 1, r = 0.959, P 5 10 -6 , Pearson cor-<lb/>relation). No correlation was found using the bi-directional model <lb/>(model 2, r = 0.069, P = 0.03, Pearson correlation). (C) In vivo <lb/>direct confocal imaging of capillaries in the rat cerebral cortex <lb/>($50 mm depth) shows leakage of Evans blue-albumin complex <lb/>(red fluorescent) from the lumen to the vessel wall following 4-AP <lb/>application. (D) The endocytosis inhibitor, methyl-b-cyclodextrin <lb/>(MbCD), inhibits vessel wall, but not extravascular enhancement. <lb/>(E and F) Histological analysis of the peri-injured cortex from <lb/>similar experiments to that shown in Fig. 3 confirms the accumula-<lb/>tion of Evans blue-albumin within blood vessel walls (dashed <lb/>lines) in the cortical region with BBBD (E) and within cellular <lb/>structures, mostly identified as GFAP-positive astrocytes (F). <lb/>Scale bars = 20 mm (E), 50 mm (F). ASCF = artificial CSF; <lb/>EES = extravascular extracellular space. <lb/></body>

			<page>1838</page>

			<note place="headnote"> | BRAIN 2020: 143; 1826-1842 <lb/>R. Veksler et al. <lb/></note>

			Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/brain/article/143/6/1826/5848368 by guest on 02 August 2022 <lb/>

			<body>cases, including those involving young adult amateur <lb/>American football players, a history of frank concussion is <lb/>frequently absent (McKee et al., 2014; Bieniek et al., 2015; <lb/>Stein et al., 2015). While the present study was performed in <lb/>otherwise-healthy amateur players, future studies are <lb/>deserved to determine the prevalence and spatial-temporal <lb/>characteristics of BBBD in professional players. Differences, <lb/>if found, may improve the understanding the effects of <lb/>impacts power and frequency, players age of onset and skills <lb/>on the extent of vascular injury. <lb/>Although football players were three times more likely <lb/>to display a leaky BBB than controls, imaging evidence of <lb/>BBBD was detected in a subgroup (27.4%) of players, <lb/>with variable anatomical location, extent, and temporal <lb/>course. This inter-individual variability may explain the <lb/>wide range of cognitive deficits and neuropsychiatric <lb/>impairments observed in players, likely reflecting differen-<lb/>ces in affected brain networks. While the causes for the in-<lb/>ter-player differences are unknown, it was interesting to <lb/>find a similar variability in both rodent models of <lb/>repeated mild TBI, despite a similar impact in each group. <lb/>The differences found in controlled animal experiments <lb/>suggest that variations in location, extent, timing, fre-<lb/>quency, and cumulative exposure of head injuries may not <lb/>be the only explanation for inter-individual variability. <lb/>Genetic differences in response to trauma should be inves-<lb/>tigated in future studies. Despite this variability, specific <lb/>brain regions were found more susceptible to BBBD in <lb/>players. Of note, the observed susceptibility of long white <lb/>matter tracts, midbrain regions and the temporal lobes is <lb/>consistent with previous predictions based on imaging <lb/>data and computational modelling (Ghajari et al., 2017). <lb/>White matter damage following mild TBI has been <lb/>reported in experimental models (Hutchinson et al., 2016; <lb/>Robinson et al., 2017), with high variability among indi-<lb/>vidual animals (Tu et al., 2017). In humans, several DTI-<lb/>based studies that showed TBI-associated white matter <lb/>damage consistently pointed to susceptible fibre bundles, <lb/>including association (e.g. ILF, IFOF), commissural (e.g. <lb/>forceps minor and major) and, to a lesser degree, projec-<lb/>tion fibres (Bendlin et al., 2008; Rutgers et al., 2008; <lb/>Matsushita et al., 2011; Aoki et al., 2012; Shenton et al., <lb/>2012; Gajawelli et al., 2013; Bahrami et al., 2016; Strain <lb/>et al., 2017). Our data showing high mean diffusivity and <lb/>low fractional anisotropy in specific segments of the IFOF <lb/>and forceps minor (Fig. 2) are consistent with these stud-<lb/>ies. Of note is the prominent asymmetry we found with <lb/>higher sensitivity of the left hemisphere to BBBD, consist-<lb/>ent with the left-side DTI pathology reported in football <lb/>players (Bahrami et al., 2016). <lb/>Our observations of focal changes in BBB integrity high-<lb/>lighted the necessity of quantifying local changes in diffusion <lb/>along white matter fibre tracts, by integrating local geomet-<lb/>ric properties with diffusion parameters. The co-occurrence <lb/>of BBBD and white matter abnormalities may indicate a <lb/>contribution of the microvascular damage to white matter <lb/>changes post-injury. Notably, however, abnormal DTI was <lb/>also observed in players without clear BBB pathology in <lb/>imaging. This finding may indicate a longer-lasting effect of <lb/>BBB on white matter fibres, subtle BBBD below our detec-<lb/>tion level or unrelated pathogenic processes. Primary func-<lb/>tional changes in neuronal activity and/or metabolic state <lb/>that directly or indirectly change microvascular permeability <lb/>(Vazana et al., 2016; Ru ¨ber et al., 2018) should also be <lb/>considered. <lb/>The search for serum biomarkers for mild TBI or associ-<lb/>ated brain damage has been the subject of intensive research. <lb/>However, to date there is no single, validated serum bio-<lb/>marker of trauma-related neurodegeneration. We found no <lb/>correlation between the extent of slow contrast accumula-<lb/>tion in players imaging data and the levels of neuronal, <lb/>astrocytic or inflammatory markers, and no significant dif-<lb/>ferences between players and healthy controls. This negative <lb/>result may reflect the large variability between players in the <lb/>extent and localization of BBBD, duration of damage, or <lb/>small sample size. Alternatively, our results may indicate <lb/>that BBBD detected by DCE-MRI reflects greater sensitivity <lb/>or different pathophysiology with regard to blood-based bio-<lb/>markers of this type of mild neurotrauma. <lb/>Our results agree with a previous study showing that lon-<lb/>ger scans detect low permeability values more accurately <lb/>(Cramer and Larsson, 2014). Similarly, analysis of contrast <lb/>enhancement in delayed scans (75 min after contrast injec-<lb/>tion) was reported to reveal contrast accumulation that was <lb/>undetected during the first 2 min (Zach et al., 2012). We <lb/>found only partial overlap between regions of high perme-<lb/>ability (NPI) values and those showing leakage using existing <lb/>two-compartment models, e.g. extended Tofts, and no cor-<lb/>relation between NPI values and Tofts model parameters <lb/>(K trans , v e , K ep ). Based on imaging of human patients with <lb/>different neuropathologies, similar enhancement patterns in <lb/>rats following focal vascular injury and in mice subjected to <lb/>rmTBI, and Gd-MIMS brain mapping confirming the pres-<lb/>ence of gadolinium in regions where slow enhancement was <lb/>detected by in vivo DCE-MRI, we suggest that the slow en-<lb/>hancement represents a true slow leak of contrast agent. <lb/>Since magnetic resonance experiments inherently suffer from <lb/>low resolution and low signal-to-noise ratio, we demonstrate <lb/>slow leaky BBB using high resolution direct imaging of small <lb/>cortical vessels (intravital fluorescent microscopy). These <lb/>experiments, showing a slow accumulation of the injected <lb/>fluorescent tracer following recurrent seizures, support a <lb/>slow biological process underlying the enhancement. These <lb/>results are consistent with previous data showing seizure-<lb/>induced BBB opening (Vazana et al., 2016), and may further <lb/>suggest that neuronal hyperexcitability underlies BBBD fol-<lb/>lowing TBI (McCrory et al., 1997; D&apos;Ambrosio et al., 2009; <lb/>Kuhl et al., 2018). An alternative explanation is a diffusion <lb/>of the contrast agent from the fast-enhanced, BBB-disrupted <lb/>core. While such diffusion may underlie part of the enhance-<lb/>ment in some patients, it is less likely explaining most slow-<lb/>ly-enhanced lesions because: (i) we found no correlation <lb/>between the extent of slow enhancement and the distance <lb/>from the core; and (ii) even in regions with identified <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Leaky BBB in American football players <lb/>BRAIN 2020: 143; 1826-1842 | </note>

			<page>1839 <lb/></page>

			Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/brain/article/143/6/1826/5848368 by guest on 02 August 2022 <lb/>

			<body>ischaemic lesion, slow enhancement was often found in the <lb/>absence of rapid contrast accumulation. <lb/>Following recent studies showing that increased transcellu-<lb/>lar transport is a key mechanism underlying BBBD in neuro-<lb/>pathologies (Kang et al., 2013; De Bock et al., 2016; Haley <lb/>and Lawrence, 2016; Andreone et al., 2017; Yang et al., <lb/>2017; Zhang et al., 2017), we added a cellular compartment <lb/>to traditional imaging models. The additional volume-trans-<lb/>fer constant was highly correlated to NPI values, supporting <lb/>the role of transcellular transport as an underlying pathology <lb/>in rmTBI. Future studies are required to uncover specific <lb/>mechanisms regulating brain microvascular transcellular <lb/>transport, its role in neuropsychiatric sequelae after TBI and <lb/>potential as diagnostic and therapeutic targets. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We gratefully acknowledge the individuals whose participa-<lb/>tion and contributions made this work possible. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>This study was supported by the European Union&apos;s Seventh <lb/>Framework Program (FP7/2007-2013; grant #602102, <lb/>A.F.), the Israel Science Foundation (A.F.), the Israel-USA bi-<lb/>national Science Foundation (A.F. and D.K.), the Nova <lb/>Scotia Health Research Foundation and Canada Institute for <lb/>Health Research (CIHR), Crown Family Foundation (L.E.G. <lb/>and A.F.), NIH-NIA Boston University Alzheimer&apos;s Disease <lb/>Center (P30 AG013846, L.E.G.), Thermo Scientific (in kind <lb/>support; L.E.G.), Office of the Dean, Boston University <lb/>School of Medicine (L.E.G.). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests <lb/>The authors report no competing interests. <lb/>Supplementary material <lb/>Supplementary material is available at Brain online. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Abbott NJ, Patabendige AAK, Dolman DEM, Yusof SR, Begley DJ. <lb/>Structure and function of the blood-brain barrier. Neurobiol Dis <lb/>2010; 37: 13-25. <lb/>Andreone BJ, Chow BW, Tata A, Lacoste B, Ben-Zvi A, Bullock K, <lb/>et al. Blood-brain barrier permeability is regulated by lipid trans-<lb/>port-dependent suppression of caveolae-mediated transcytosis. <lb/>Neuron 2017; 94: 581-94.e5. <lb/>Aoki Y, Inokuchi R, Gunshin M, Yahagi N, Suwa H. Diffusion tensor <lb/>imaging studies of mild traumatic brain injury: a meta-analysis. <lb/>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry 2012; 83: 870-6. <lb/>Artzi M, Liberman G, Nadav G, Blumenthal DT, Bokstein F, <lb/>Aizenstein O, et al. Optimization of DCE-MRI protocol for the <lb/>assessment of patients with brain tumors. Magn Reson Imaging <lb/>2016; 34: 1242-47. <lb/>Bahrami N, Sharma D, Rosenthal S, Davenport EM, Urban JE, <lb/>Wagner B, et al. Subconcussive head impact exposure and white <lb/>matter tract changes over a single season of youth football. <lb/>Radiology 2016; 281: 919-26. <lb/>Bar-Klein G, Lublinsky S, Kamintsky L, Noyman I, Veksler R, Dalipaj <lb/>H, et al. Imaging blood-brain barrier dysfunction as a biomarker <lb/>for epileptogenesis. Brain 2017; 140: 1-14. <lb/>Bendlin BB, Ries ML, Lazar M, Alexander AL, Dempsey RJ, Rowley <lb/>HA, et al. Longitudinal changes in patients with traumatic brain in-<lb/>jury assessed with diffusion-tensor and volumetric imaging. <lb/>Neuroimage 2008; 42: 503-14. <lb/>Benou I, Veksler R, Friedman A, Raviv TR. Combining white matter <lb/>diffusion and geometry for tract-specific alignment and variability <lb/>analysis. Neuroimage 2019; 200: 674-89. <lb/>Bieniek KF, Ross OA, Cormier KA, Walton RL, Soto-Ortolaza A, <lb/>Johnston AE, et al. Chronic traumatic encephalopathy pathology in <lb/>a neurodegenerative disorders brain bank. Acta Neuropathol 2015; <lb/>130: 877-89. <lb/>De Bock M, Van Haver V, Vandenbroucke RE, Decrock E, Wang N, <lb/>Leybaert L. Into rather unexplored terrain-transcellular transport <lb/>across the blood-brain barrier. Glia 2016; 64: 1097-123. <lb/>Boyd BJ, Galle A, Daglas M, Rosenfeld JV, Medcalf R. Traumatic <lb/>brain injury opens blood-brain barrier to stealth liposomes via an <lb/>enhanced permeability and retention (EPR)-like effect. J Drug Target <lb/>2015; 23: 847-53. <lb/>Chassidim Y, Veksler R, Lublinsky S, Pell G, Friedman A, Shelef I. <lb/>Quantitative imaging assessment of blood-brain barrier permeability <lb/>in humans. Fluids Barriers CNS 2013; 10: 9. <lb/>Cramer SP, Larsson HB. Accurate determination of blood-brain bar-<lb/>rier permeability using dynamic contrast-enhanced T1-weighted <lb/>MRI: a simulation and in vivo study on healthy subjects and mul-<lb/>tiple sclerosis patients. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab 2014; 34: <lb/>1655-65. <lb/>Critchley M. Medical aspects of boxing, particularly from a neuro-<lb/>logical standpoint. Br Med J 1957; 1: 357-62. <lb/>D&apos;Ambrosio R, Hakimian S, Stewart T, Verley DR, Fender JS, <lb/>Eastman CL, et al. Functional definition of seizure provides new in-<lb/>sight into post-traumatic epileptogenesis. Brain 2009; 132: 2805-21. <lb/>DeWitt DS, Prough DS. Traumatic cerebral vascular injury: the effects <lb/>of concussive brain injury on the cerebral vasculature. <lb/>J Neurotrauma 2003; 20: 795-825. <lb/>Doherty CP, O&apos;Keefe E, Wallace E, Loftus T, Keaney J, Kealy J, et al. <lb/>Blood-brain barrier dysfunction as a hallmark pathology in chronic <lb/>traumatic encephalopathy. J Neuropathol Exp Neurol 2016; 75: <lb/>656-62. <lb/>Gajawelli N, Lao Y, Apuzzo MLJ, Romano R, Liu C, Tsao S, et al. <lb/>Neuroimaging changes in the brain in contact versus noncontact <lb/>sport athletes using diffusion tensor imaging. World Neurosurg <lb/>2013; 80: 824-8. <lb/>Gavett BE, Stern RA, Mckee AC.Chronic traumatic encephalopathy: a <lb/>potential late effect of sport-related concussive and subconcussive <lb/>head trauma. Clinics in Sports Medicine 2011; 30: 179-88. <lb/>Ghajari M, Hellyer PJ, Sharp DJ. Computational modelling of trau-<lb/>matic brain injury predicts the location of chronic traumatic enceph-<lb/>alopathy pathology. Brain 2017; 140: 333-43. <lb/>Haley MJ, Lawrence CB. The blood-brain barrier after stroke: struc-<lb/>tural studies and the role of transcytotic vesicles. J Cereb Blood <lb/>Flow Metab 2016; 37: 456-70. <lb/>Hay JR, Johnson VE, Young AMH, Smith DH, Stewart W. Blood-<lb/>brain barrier disruption is an early event that may persist for many <lb/>years after traumatic brain injury in humans. J Neuropathol Exp <lb/>Neurol 2015; 74: 1147-57. <lb/>Heye AK, Culling RD, Valdes Hernandez MDC, Thrippleton MJ, <lb/>Wardlaw JM. Assessment of blood-brain barrier disruption using <lb/>dynamic contrast-enhanced MRI. A systematic review. NeuroImage <lb/>Clin 2014; 6: 262-74. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>1840</page>

			<note place="headnote"> | BRAIN 2020: 143; 1826-1842 <lb/>R. Veksler et al. <lb/></note>

			Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/brain/article/143/6/1826/5848368 by guest on 02 August 2022 <lb/>

			<listBibl>Huber BR, Alosco ML, Stein TD, McKee AC. Potential long-term con-<lb/>sequences of concussive and subconcussive injury. Phys Med <lb/>Rehabil Clin N Am 2016; 27: 503-11. <lb/>Hutchinson EB, Schwerin SC, Radomski KL, Irfanoglu MO, Juliano <lb/>SL, Pierpaoli CM. Quantitative MRI and DTI abnormalities during <lb/>the acute period following CCI in the Ferret. Shock 2016; 46: <lb/>167-76. <lb/>Kamintsky L, Cairns KA, Veksler R, Bowen C, Beyea SD, Friedman A, <lb/>et al. Blood-brain barrier imaging as a potential biomarker for bipo-<lb/>lar disorder progression. NeuroImage Clin 2019; 102049. <lb/>Kane MJ, Angoa-Pe ´rez M, Briggs DI, Viano DC, Kreipke CW, Kuhn <lb/>DM. A mouse model of human repetitive mild traumatic brain in-<lb/>jury. J Neurosci Methods 2012; 203: 41-9. <lb/>Kang EJ, Major S, Jorks D, Reiffurth C, Offenhauser N, Friedman A, <lb/>et al. Blood-brain barrier opening to large molecules does not imply <lb/>blood-brain barrier opening to small ions. Neurobiol Dis 2013; 52: <lb/>204-18. <lb/>Kassner A, Merali Z. Assessment of blood-brain barrier disruption in <lb/>stroke. Stroke 2015; 46: 3310-5. <lb/>Knowland D, Arac A, Sekiguchi KJJ, Hsu M, Lutz SEE, Perrino J, <lb/>et al. Stepwise recruitment of transcellular and paracellular path-<lb/>ways underlies blood-brain barrier breakdown in stroke. Neuron <lb/>2014; 82: 603-17. <lb/>Kuhl NO, Yengo-Kahn AM, Burnette H, Solomon GS, Zuckerman <lb/>Sport-related concussive convulsions: a systematic review. Phys <lb/>Sportsmed 2018; 46: 1-7. <lb/>Li W, Watts L, Long J, Zhou W, Shen Q, Jiang Z, et al. <lb/>Spatiotemporal changes in blood-brain barrier permeability, cerebral <lb/>blood flow, T2 and diffusion following mild traumatic brain injury. <lb/>Brain Res 2016; 1646: 53-61. <lb/>Ling H, Morris HR, Neal JW, Lees AJ, Hardy J, Holton JL, et alet al. <lb/>Mixed pathologies including chronic traumatic encephalopathy ac-<lb/>count for dementia in retired association football (soccer) players. <lb/>Acta Neuropathol 2017; 133: 337-52. <lb/>Lublinsky S, Major S, Kola V, Horst V, Santos E, Platz J, et al. Early <lb/>blood-brain barrier dysfunction predicts neurological outcome fol-<lb/>lowing aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage. EBioMedicine 2019; <lb/>43: 460-72. <lb/>Marmarou A, Foda MA, van den Brink W, Campbell J, Kita H, <lb/>Demetriadou K. A new model of diffuse brain injury in rats. Part I: <lb/>pathophysiology and biomechanics. J Neurosurg 1994; 80: <lb/>291-300. <lb/>Matsushita M, Hosoda K, Naitoh Y, Yamashita H, Kohmura E. <lb/>Utility of diffusion tensor imaging in the acute stage of mild to mod-<lb/>erate traumatic brain injury for detecting white matter lesions and <lb/>predicting long-term cognitive function in adults. J Neurosurg 2011; <lb/>115: 130-9. <lb/>McAllister T, McCrea M. Long-term cognitive and neuropsychiatric <lb/>consequences of repetitive concussion and head-impact exposure. J <lb/>Athl Train 2017; 52: 309-17. <lb/>McCrory PR, Bladin PF, Berkovic SF. Retrospective study of concus-<lb/>sive convulsions in elite Australian rules and rugby league footbal-<lb/>lers: phenomenology, aetiology, and outcome. BMJ 1997; 314: <lb/>171-4. <lb/>McKee AC, Cairns NJ, Dickson DW, Folkerth RD, Dirk Keene C, <lb/>Litvan I, et al. The first NINDS/NIBIB consensus meeting to define <lb/>neuropathological criteria for the diagnosis of chronic traumatic en-<lb/>cephalopathy. Acta Neuropathol 2016; 131: 75-86. <lb/>McKee AC, Cantu RC, Nowinski CJ, Hedley-Whyte ET, Gavett BE, <lb/>Budson AE, et al. Chronic traumatic encephalopathy in athletes: <lb/>progressive tauopathy after repetitive head injury. J Neuropathol <lb/>Exp Neurol 2009; 68: 709-35. <lb/>McKee AC, Daneshvar DH, Alvarez VE, Stein TD. The neuropathol-<lb/>ogy of sport. Acta Neuropathol 2014; 127: 29-51. <lb/>McKee AC, Stein TD, Nowinski CJ, Stern RA, Daneshvar DH, <lb/>Alvarez VE, et al. The spectrum of disease in chronic traumatic en-<lb/>cephalopathy. Brain 2013; 136: 43-64. <lb/>Mez J, Daneshvar DH, Kiernan PT, Abdolmohammadi B, Alvarez VE, <lb/>Huber BR, et al. Clinicopathological evaluation of chronic traumatic <lb/>encephalopathy in players of American football. JAMA 2017; 318: <lb/>360-70. <lb/>Montagne A, Barnes SR, Law M, Zlokovic BV, Montagne A, Barnes <lb/>SR, et al. Blood-brain barrier breakdown in the aging human report <lb/>blood-brain barrier breakdown in the aging human hippocampus. <lb/>Neuron 2015; 85: 296-302. <lb/>Montenigro PH, Alosco ML, Martin BM, Daneshvar DH, Mez J, <lb/>Chaisson CE, et al. Cumulative head impact exposure predicts later-<lb/>life depression, apathy, executive dysfunction, and cognitive impair-<lb/>ment in Former High School and College Football Players. J <lb/>Neurotrauma 2017; 34: 328-40. <lb/>Mychasiuk R, Farran A, Esser MJ. Assessment of an experimental ro-<lb/>dent model of pediatric mild traumatic brain injury. J Neurotrauma <lb/>2014; 31: 749-57. <lb/>Nahirney PC, Reeson P, Brown CE. Ultrastructural analysis of blood-<lb/>brain barrier breakdown in the peri-infarct zone in young adult and <lb/>aged mice. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab 2016; 36: 413-25. <lb/>Nation DA, Sweeney MD, Montagne A, Sagare AP, D&apos;Orazio LM, <lb/>Pachicano M, et al. Blood-brain barrier breakdown is an early <lb/>biomarker of human cognitive dysfunction. Nat Med 2019; 25: <lb/>270-6. <lb/>Omalu BI, DeKosky ST, Hamilton RL, Minster RL, Kamboh MI, <lb/>Shakir AM, et al. Chronic traumatic encephalopathy in a National <lb/>Football League player: part II. Neurosurgery 2006; 59: 1086-92. <lb/>Patlak CS, Blasberg RG. Graphical evaluation of blood-to-brain trans-<lb/>fer constants from multiple-time Uptake Data. J Cereb Blood Flow <lb/>Metab 1985; 5: 584-90. <lb/>Robinson S, Berglass JB, Denson JL, Berkner J, Anstine CV, Winer JL, <lb/>et al. Microstructural and microglial changes after repetitive mild <lb/>traumatic brain injury in mice. J Neurosci Res 2017; 95: 1025-35. <lb/>Rodrı ´guez-Baeza A, Reina-de la Torre F, Poca A, Martı ´M, Garnacho <lb/>A. Morphological features in human cortical brain microvessels after <lb/>head injury: a three-dimensional and immunocytochemical study. <lb/>Anat Rec A Rec 2003; 273: 583-93. <lb/>Ru ¨ber T, David B, Lu ¨chters G, Nass RD, Friedman A, Surges R, et al. <lb/>Evidence for peri-ictal blood-brain barrier dysfunction in patients <lb/>with epilepsy. Brain 2018; 141: 2952-65. <lb/>Rutgers DR, Toulgoat F, Cazejust J, Fillard P, Lasjaunias P, Ducreux <lb/>D. White matter abnormalities in mild traumatic brain injury: a dif-<lb/>fusion tensor imaging study. AJNR Am J Neuroradiol 2008; 29: <lb/>514-9. <lb/>Salehi A, Zhang JH, Obenaus A. Response of the cerebral vasculature <lb/>following traumatic brain injury. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab 2017; <lb/>37: 0271678X1770146. <lb/>Sashindranath M, Sales E, Daglas M, Freeman R, Samson AL, Cops <lb/>EJ, et al. The tissue-type plasminogen activator-plasminogen activa-<lb/>tor inhibitor 1 complex promotes neurovascular injury in brain <lb/>trauma: evidence from mice and humans. Brain 2012; 135: <lb/>3251-64. <lb/>Schoknecht K, Prager O, Vazana U, Kamintsky L, Harhausen D, Zille <lb/>M, et al. Monitoring stroke progression: in vivo imaging of cortical <lb/>perfusion, blood-brain barrier permeability and cellular damage in <lb/>the rat photothrombosis model. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab 2014; <lb/>34: 1791-801. <lb/>Senatorov VV, Friedman AR, Milikovsky DZ, Ofer J, Saar-Ashkenazy <lb/>R, Charbash A, et al. Blood-brain barrier dysfunction in aging indu-<lb/>ces hyperactivation of TGFb signaling and chronic yet reversible <lb/>neural dysfunction. Sci Transl Med 2019; 11: 1946-6234. <lb/>Serlin Y, Ofer J, Ben-Arie G, Veksler R, Ifergane G, Shelef I, et al. <lb/>Blood-brain barrier leakage: a new biomarker in transient ischemic <lb/>attacks. Stroke 2019; 50: 1266-1269. <lb/>Shenton MEE, Hamoda HMM, Schneiderman JSS, Bouix S, Pasternak <lb/>O, Rathi Y, et al. A review of magnetic resonance imaging and diffu-<lb/>sion tensor imaging findings in mild traumatic brain injury. Brain <lb/>Imaging Behav 2012; 6: 137-92. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Leaky BBB in American football players <lb/> BRAIN 2020: 143; 1826-1842 | </note>

			<page>1841 <lb/></page>

			Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/brain/article/143/6/1826/5848368 by guest on 02 August 2022 <lb/>

			<listBibl>Shlosberg D, Benifla M, Kaufer D, Friedman A. Blood-brain barrier <lb/>breakdown as a therapeutic target in traumatic brain injury. Nat <lb/>Rev Neurol 2010; 6: 1-23. <lb/>Sourbron SP, Buckley DL. Classic models for dynamic contrast-<lb/>enhanced MRI. NMR Biomed 2013; 26: 1004-27. <lb/>Stamm JM, Bourlas AP, Baugh CM, Fritts NG, Daneshvar DH, <lb/>Martin BM, et al. Age of first exposure to football and later-life cog-<lb/>nitive impairment in former NFL players. Neurology 2015; 84: <lb/>1114-20. <lb/>Stein TD, Alvarez VE, McKee AC. Concussion in chronic traumatic <lb/>encephalopathy. Curr Pain Headache Rep 2015; 19. <lb/>Strain JF, Didehbani N, Spence J, Conover H, Bartz EK, Mansinghani <lb/>S, et al. White matter changes and confrontation naming in retired <lb/>aging National Football League Athletes. J Neurotrauma 2017; 34: <lb/>372-9. <lb/>Sweeney MD, Zhao Z, Montagne A, Nelson AR, Zlokovic BV. Blood-<lb/>brain barrier: from physiology to disease and back. Physiol Rev <lb/>2019; 99: 21-78. <lb/>Tagge CA, Fisher AM, Minaeva OV, Gaudreau-Balderrama A, <lb/>Moncaster JA, Zhang XL, et al. Concussion, microvascular injury, <lb/>and early tauopathy in young athletes after impact head injury and <lb/>an impact concussion mouse model. Brain 2018; 141: 422-58. <lb/>Tofts PS. Modeling tracer kinetics in dynamic Gd-DTPA MR imaging. <lb/>J Magn Reson Imaging 1997; 7: 91-101. <lb/>Tofts PS, Brix G, Buckley DL, Evelhoch JL, Henderson E, Knopp MV, <lb/>et al. Estimating kinetic parameters from dynamic contrast-enhanced <lb/>T1-weighted MRI of a diffusable tracer: standardized quantities <lb/>and symbols. J Magn Reson Imaging 1999; 10: 223-32. <lb/>Tofts PS, Kermode AG. Measurement of the blood-brain barrier per-<lb/>meability and leakage space using dynamic MR imaging. 1. <lb/>Fundamental concepts. Magn Reson Med 1991; 17: 357-67. <lb/>Tomkins O, Shelef I, Kaizerman I, Eliushin A, Afawi Z, Misk A, et al. <lb/>Blood -brain barrier disruption in post-traumatic epilepsy. J Neurol <lb/>Neurosurg Psychiatry 2008; 79: 774-7. <lb/>Tu T-W, Lescher JD, Williams RA, Jikaria N, Turtzo LC, Frank JA. <lb/>Abnormal injury response in spontaneous mild ventriculomegaly <lb/>Wistar rat brains: a pathological correlation study of diffusion ten-<lb/>sor and magnetization transfer imaging in mild traumatic brain in-<lb/>jury. J Neurotrauma 2017; 34: 248-56. <lb/>Vazana U, Veksler R, Pell G, Prager O, Fassler M, Chassidim Y, et al. <lb/>Glutamate-mediated blood-brain barrier opening: implications for <lb/>neuroprotection and drug delivery. J Neurosci 2016; 36: 7727-39. <lb/>Veksler R, Shelef I, Friedman A. Blood-brain barrier imaging in human <lb/>neuropathologies. Arch Med Res 2014; 45: 646-52. <lb/>Vidarsson L, Thornhill RE, Liu F, Mikulis DJ, Kassner A. Quantitative <lb/>permeability magnetic resonance imaging in acute ischemic stroke: how <lb/>long do we need to scan?. Magn Reson Imaging 2009; 27: 1216-22. <lb/>Villringer K, Sanz Cuesta BE, Ostwaldt A-C, Grittner U, Brunecker P, <lb/>Khalil AA, et al. DCE-MRI blood-brain barrier assessment in acute <lb/>ischemic stroke. Neurology 2016; 88: 433-40. <lb/>Weissberg I, Veksler R, Kamintsky L, Saar-Ashkenazy R, Milikovsky <lb/>DZ, Shelef I, et al. Imaging blood-brain barrier dysfunction in foot-<lb/>ball players. JAMA Neurol 2014; 71: 1453-5. <lb/>Yang Y, Xiong X, Liu J, Wu L, Zhong Q, Zhou K, et al. Mfsd2a <lb/>(Major facilitator superfamily domain containing 2a) attenuates <lb/>intracerebral hemorrhage-induced blood-brain barrier disruption by <lb/>inhibiting vesicular transcytosis. J Am Heart Assoc 2017; 6. <lb/>Available from: http://jaha.ahajournals.org/content/6/7/e005811 <lb/>Zach L, Guez D, Last D, Daniels D, Grober Y, Nissim O, et al. <lb/>Delayed contrast extravasation MRI for depicting tumor and non-<lb/>tumoral tissues in primary and metastatic brain tumors. PLoS One <lb/>2012; 7: e52008. <lb/>Zhang J, Liu H, Du X, Guo Y, Chen X, Wang S, et al. Increasing of <lb/>blood-brain tumor barrier permeability through transcellular and <lb/>paracellular pathways by microbubble-enhanced diagnostic ultra-<lb/>sound in a C6 glioma model. Front Neurosci 2017; 11: 86. <lb/>Zlokovic BV. The blood-brain barrier in health and chronic neurode-<lb/>generative disorders. Neuron 2008; 57: 178-201. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>1842</page>

			<note place="headnote"> | BRAIN 2020: 143; 1826-1842 <lb/>R. Veksler et al. <lb/></note>

			Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/brain/article/143/6/1826/5848368 by guest on 02 August 2022 


	</text>
</tei>
