<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>RESEARCH <lb/>Dynamics of Rural <lb/>Settlement Patterns in <lb/>the Yellow River Delta in <lb/>Response to River Diversion <lb/>and Avulsion Since 1855 <lb/>YUTING LIU <lb/>YU YE <lb/>CHANG JIANG <lb/>JINFENG JIANG <lb/>FAHAO WANG <lb/>JUN LI <lb/>XIANGPING ZHANG <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>To explore the unique human-water interaction patterns in the Yellow River Delta since <lb/>1855, based on historical river channel data and historical village data, the patterns of <lb/>villages in the Yellow River Delta and their responses to river channels were analysed. <lb/>The number of new villages in the Yellow River Delta showed an &apos;inverted V&apos;-shaped <lb/>curve after 1855, and the cumulative number of villages showed an &apos;S&apos;-shaped curve. <lb/>The pattern change of villages was influenced by the change in the river system, which <lb/>expanded to the northwest and southeast directions with the old Tiemenguan River <lb/>Course as the axis. During this period, differences in riverbed morphology and fluvial <lb/>areas, the natural evolution of soil in the river delta, and even the guidance of official <lb/>policies were the key controls of the developing settlement pattern in the delta. Flooding <lb/>often leads to the formation of new river channels and the abandonment and silting <lb/>of old river channels. For the dried-up old courses and former flood basin, because the <lb/>Yellow River sediment has the effect of improving soil structure and fertilizing land, the <lb/>soil in these areas becomes suitable for farming and settlement. For the active new <lb/>course, the freshwater from the river can replenish the groundwater and reduce the <lb/>degree of soil salinization in the surrounding area, thus attracting people to settle. In <lb/>general, although the Yellow River causes harm from a course change, it also benefits <lb/>from silted land. <lb/>CORRESPONDING AUTHOR: <lb/>Yu Ye <lb/>Associate Professor, Faculty of <lb/>Geographical Sciences, Beijing <lb/>Normal University, Beijing <lb/>100875, China <lb/>Key Laboratory of Environment <lb/>Change and Natural Disaster, <lb/>Ministry of Education, Beijing <lb/>Normal University, Beijing <lb/>100875, China <lb/>yeyuleaffish@bnu.edu.cn <lb/>KEYWORDS: <lb/>environmental change; historic <lb/>settlements; rural living <lb/>environment; diversion of the <lb/>Yellow River <lb/>TO CITE THIS ARTICLE: <lb/>Liu, Y., Ye, Y., Jiang, C., Jiang, <lb/>J., Wang, F., Li, J., &amp; Zhang, <lb/>X. (2024). Dynamics of Rural <lb/>Settlement Patterns in the <lb/>Yellow River Delta in Response <lb/>to River Diversion and Avulsion <lb/>Since 1855. Rural Landscapes: <lb/>Society, Environment, History, <lb/>11(1): 2, 1-15. DOI: https://doi. <lb/>org/10.16993/rl.100 <lb/>*Author affiliations can be found in the back matter of this article <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Liu et al. Rural Landscapes: Society, Environment, History DOI: 10.16993/rl.100 <lb/></note>

			<body>1 INTRODUCTION <lb/>Water resources are a daily necessity for humans, and <lb/>large rivers were once the original cradle of human <lb/>civilization. Today, most human settlements have <lb/>been built near rivers, as humans rely on rivers to <lb/>provide irrigation and residential water or to facilitate <lb/>transportation and trade. Rivers played an important role <lb/>in the location and layout of new settlements in historic <lb/>times. For the Yellow River Delta, where river systems <lb/>are constantly changing, rural settlement patterns in <lb/>response to river diversion and avulsion are well worth <lb/>exploring. <lb/>In prehistoric times, the survival modes of hunting, <lb/>gathering and farming depended on the natural <lb/>environment (Stavrianos, 2005; Wang, 2019; Wells <lb/>and Postgate, 2010; Zhao, 2018). The rich natural <lb/>environment along rivers and river valleys provided <lb/>abundant animal and plant resources and broad living <lb/>space for ancient humans (Jin, 2018; Lu et al., 2017, <lb/>2019), but the adverse effects of floods could not be <lb/>ignored. For example, Ollivier et al. (2016) revealed <lb/>that Holocene human settlements in the Caspian Sea <lb/>region were mostly located on river tributary terraces <lb/>and silty fans. This was probably linked to water supply <lb/>requirements and agricultural development availability, <lb/>whereas these settlements were still far enough from <lb/>rivers to prevent flooding. Moreover, Shi (2013) found <lb/>that Neolithic settlement sites in the Jiaodong Peninsula, <lb/>Shandong Province, China, were mostly distributed in the <lb/>middle and upper reaches of rivers, while they were less <lb/>distributed in the alluvial plains of the lower reaches of <lb/>large rivers and in intermountain basins in the middle <lb/>reaches of large rivers, which reflects that the prehistoric <lb/>people not only needed rivers as a source of water for <lb/>living but also actively avoided the harm caused by floods <lb/>and debris flows. The human occupation pattern of the <lb/>Danube Delta at the same time has also been shown to <lb/>be heavily determined by flooding (Bonsall et al., 2015; <lb/>Carozza et al., 2012). <lb/>Since then, humans have increasingly adapted and <lb/>improved their ability to use natural resources. The <lb/>construction of irrigation channels, dams and other <lb/>water conservancy facilities has enabled people to better <lb/>utilize the resources brought by rivers and to reduce the <lb/>harm of river avulsion and flooding (Stavrianos, 2005; <lb/>Wells and Postgate, 2010; Zhao, 2018). As a result, the <lb/>proximity of settlements to water sources increased <lb/>significantly, which has been confirmed by numerous <lb/>archaeological studies of the world&apos;s great river basins. <lb/>The Sumerians settled on the floodplains of the Euphrates <lb/>and Tigris Rivers around the 4th millennium BC, relying on <lb/>irrigation facilitated by rivers and man-made canals to <lb/>develop agriculture and to build some of the world&apos;s first <lb/>cities (Bagg, 2000; Ur, 2014). From the Ptolemaic period <lb/>to the Roman period (4th century BC to 7th century <lb/>AD), the number of settlements in the Nile Delta on <lb/>highly elevated levees along channels increased (Ginau, <lb/>2018; Schiestl, 2012; Wilson, 2015). However, these <lb/>high levees were not sufficient to curb the diversion of <lb/>rivers and flooding, which led to the abandonment and <lb/>construction of settlements (Ginau, 2018). <lb/>Historically, with the expansion of farming and <lb/>the continuous development of water conservancy <lb/>technology, the relationships between human production <lb/>and life and water sources (especially rivers) became <lb/>increasingly closer. Since ancient times, the Danube <lb/>and lower Rhine Rivers have nurtured countries along <lb/>their banks (Dobrescu &amp; Grigorescu, 2011; Preoteasa <lb/>et al., 2019; Mako &amp; Galieriková, 2021; Uehlinger et al., <lb/>2009). The Mississippi River is the political, economic <lb/>and shipping lifeblood of North America (Batker et al., <lb/>2010; Stearns, 2011). Between 1687 and 1702, the <lb/>course changes in the Euphrates River jeopardized the <lb/>stability of the eastern Ottoman Empire and left behind <lb/>a profoundly altered ecological and political landscape <lb/>in a rural region southwest of Baghdad (Husain, 2016). <lb/>Floods and changing rivers played a highly important <lb/>role in the East India Company&apos;s control, management <lb/>and trade of colonial Bengal from the late 18th century <lb/>to the mid-19th century (Bhattacharya, 2022; Cederlöf, <lb/>2014). In China, the Yangtze River and the Yellow River <lb/>are called the &apos;mother rivers&apos; of the Chinese nation, <lb/>with many dynasties arising and developing along <lb/>their banks (Zhang, 2001). In some specific areas, such <lb/>as mountainous areas, plains, karst areas, and humid <lb/>and arid areas of China, settlements also show obvious <lb/>distribution patterns near rivers (Ma et al., 2018; Ma et al., <lb/>2022; Wei et al., 2022; Xiang et al., 2023; Xie et al., 2013; <lb/>Zeng et al., 2020). <lb/>The vast majority of studies on river-related settlement <lb/>patterns have considered only established patterns but <lb/>not occupation over time in relation to river dynamics. <lb/>There is still a lack of research examples on the impact of <lb/>river avulsion on settlements in delta areas in China with <lb/>continuously changing river systems. At the same time, <lb/>archaeological studies on occupation patterns along <lb/>dynamic rivers mostly rely on complex environmental <lb/>archaeological methods and are costly. <lb/>The Yellow River Delta offers a unique opportunity to <lb/>study the development of settling patterns in response <lb/>to river dynamics and avulsion. The delta has gradually <lb/>expanded since 1855 when the Yellow River debouched <lb/>in the sea in Shandong Province. The changes in river <lb/>diversion and in avulsion and settling and changes in <lb/>the number and location of settlements in this region <lb/>over the last 150 years have been well documented in <lb/>the form of documents and digital maps, which makes <lb/>studying the Yellow River Delta relatively convenient. <lb/>On the other hand, the Yellow River Delta is one of the <lb/>estuarine deltas with the fastest land growth in China <lb/>and even in the world. Affected by many factors, such <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Liu et al. Rural Landscapes: Society, Environment, History DOI: 10.16993/rl.100 <lb/></note>

			<body>as siltation and changes in river channels, the natural <lb/>environment is experiencing constant and rapid changes <lb/>(Han et al., 2006; Lu, 2019), which often creates a unique <lb/>spatiotemporal pattern of settlements and alters the <lb/>relationship between humans and water. <lb/>With the Yellow River Delta as the research area and <lb/>based on historical river channel and historical village data <lb/>from 1855 to 2000, this study aims to reveal the response <lb/>of the spatial distribution of settlements in this region to <lb/>the diversion and avulsion process of the Yellow River and <lb/>intends to answer the following two questions: (1) What <lb/>are the quantitative and spatial variation characteristics <lb/>of rural settlements in the delta against the background <lb/>of avulsion and settling of the Yellow River tail? (2) What <lb/>is the spatial relationship between rural settlements and <lb/>the old and new channels of the Yellow River, especially <lb/>the inertia of rural settlement distribution to the old <lb/>channels? It is hoped that this research can provide <lb/>information about the characteristics of rural living <lb/>settlements and human-water patterns in deltas. <lb/>2 REGIONAL BACKGROUND <lb/>This study focuses on the modern Yellow River Delta area <lb/>(Figure 1, Figure 2), in particular on Ninghai in the Kenli <lb/>District, Shandong Province, as the focal point, starting <lb/>from the Tao&apos;er River Estuary in the north and ending at <lb/>the Zhimai River Estuary in the south, bordering Bohai Bay <lb/>in the north and adjacent to Laizhou Bay in the east, with <lb/>a total area of approximately 5400 square kilometres. <lb/>The Yellow River Delta is a typical low-elevation <lb/>flat delta plain with an average elevation of 5-6 m. It <lb/>comprises some microtopography features, such as hills, <lb/>sloping fields, river fluvial plains, low-lying lands, and <lb/>hillocks caused by dike breaching and diversion of the <lb/>Yellow River (Lu, 2018). The Yellow River Delta is located in <lb/>the temperate subhumid continental monsoon climate <lb/>zone, with an annual average temperature between <lb/>Figure 1 Settlements, farmland and a levee in the Yellow River <lb/>Delta. (a) the photo taken on the pontoon bridge near Ningjia <lb/>village, Kenli District, Dongying City; (b) the photo taken on the <lb/>Dongying Yellow River Bridge in Kenli District, Dongying City; <lb/>(c) the photo taken near the Lijin Hydrological Station, in Lijin <lb/>District, Dongying City. <lb/>Figure 2 Yellow River Delta. <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Liu et al. Rural Landscapes: Society, Environment, History DOI: 10.16993/rl.100 <lb/></note>

			<body>11.7 and 12.6 °C and an annual average precipitation <lb/>of 530-630 mm. The annual precipitation is uneven and <lb/>concentrated from July to September. The Yellow River <lb/>is the longest, most profound and most extensive river <lb/>flowing through the delta. In addition, there are several <lb/>secondary rivers and artificial canals for flood control, <lb/>flood discharge and drainage (Administration Bureau of <lb/>the Yellow River Estuary, the Yellow River Conservancy <lb/>Commission, 1995). Fresh groundwater resources are <lb/>scarce in this area, while brackish and brine water are <lb/>widely distributed (Wang, 2012). The main types of <lb/>soil are aquatic soil, saline flavo-aquic soil and alluvial-<lb/>salt soil (Liu et al., 2017). The natural vegetation of the <lb/>whole Yellow River Delta is mainly composed of saline <lb/>meadows, with fewer woody plant species (Lu, 2019). <lb/>However, many inland areas have been reclaimed for <lb/>farmland and small-scale plantations. <lb/>The Yellow River has a very large sediment flux with <lb/>monsoon-driven seasonal variations in river discharge <lb/>and sediment load. At a decennial time scale, it has <lb/>experienced regular avulsion and diversion, resulting <lb/>in channel siltation, sediment rerouting and delta <lb/>extension (Zou et al., 2013). Since the Yellow River <lb/>diverted to the sea in Shandong Province in 1855, there <lb/>have been three cycles of north-south swings in the river <lb/>course of the Yellow River, forming 11 channels (except <lb/>for the Freshwater Ditch Channel from 1976 to 1996 <lb/>and the Diaokou River Channel from 1964 to 1976; the <lb/>other channels have dried up) (Table 1). With continuous <lb/>silt accumulation and the extension of delta lobes, the <lb/>present-day Yellow River Delta eventually formed. <lb/>With <lb/>progressive <lb/>agricultural <lb/>development, <lb/>population growth and intensification of human-land <lb/>conflicts in the Qing Dynasty, the new land in the Yellow <lb/>River Delta became the first choice for reclamation <lb/>and gradually transformed from an untrodden delta <lb/>plain into a thriving landscape with villages and arable <lb/>land. During this period, farming was the main type of <lb/>livelihood for residents of the Yellow River Delta. Salt <lb/>(such as high-salinity groundwater and salinized soil) <lb/>and flooding (caused by the Yellow River breach) are <lb/>major constraints on agricultural production in the <lb/>Yellow River Delta, while the water and sand delivered <lb/>by the Yellow River serve as sources of fresh water supply <lb/>and natural fertility, respectively, to sustain agricultural <lb/>production. Balances between salt and fresh water and <lb/>Figure 3 Course changes in the Yellow River Delta. <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Liu et al. Rural Landscapes: Society, Environment, History DOI: 10.16993/rl.100 <lb/></note>

			<body>between flooding and silting are the most critical factors <lb/>affecting land development and village construction in <lb/>the Yellow River Delta, and they even have special spatial <lb/>implications. <lb/>3 MATERIALS AND METHODS <lb/>3.1 DATA SOURCES <lb/>3.1.1 Channel vector data of the lower Yellow River <lb/>since 1855 <lb/>The data for the lower Yellow River since 1855 were <lb/>obtained from the 1:1,000,000 Main River Changes <lb/>Database of the lower Yellow River (1855-2005) released <lb/>by the National Earth System Science Data Center of <lb/>China (http://www.geodata.cn), a national platform for <lb/>basic conditions of science and technology. The data <lb/>contain the changes in the Yellow River course in 11 <lb/>periods between 1855 and 2000 (Figure 3, Table 1). The <lb/>dataset was produced by the College of Environment <lb/>and Planning of Henan University. The researchers <lb/>consulted historical documents and combined the field <lb/>archaeological results to construct a simulation map of <lb/>the river course changes in the lower Yellow River from <lb/>1855 to 2000. After scanning, the map was input into <lb/>the computer, and the screen tracking vectorization <lb/>method was adopted to digitize the dataset. In the <lb/>process of manual sorting, proofreading and input, the <lb/>quality of the data was strictly controlled, and there was <lb/>a special person for data sampling and proofreading. <lb/>The data quality is high, and the source is real and <lb/>reliable. <lb/>3.1.2 Coastline data of the Yellow River Delta <lb/>The coastline data for 1820 were obtained from the <lb/>Chinese historical geographic information system <lb/>(CHGIS) (https://sites.fas.harvard.edu/~chgis/), which is <lb/>directly digitized based on the map of the eighth volume <lb/>of the Historical Atlas of China (Tan, 1982). For 1954, the <lb/>coastline was obtained by the registration and vectoring <lb/>of the Map of Channel Changes of the Yellow River Estuary <lb/>Delta since 1855 in the book of Chinese Historical Physical <lb/>Geography (Zou et al., 2013). Modern coastline data were <lb/>extracted from the 1:400,000 Chinese Administrative <lb/>Zoning Map of the National Center for Basic Geographic <lb/>Information (https://www.webmap.cn). <lb/>NO. <lb/>AVULSION <lb/>YEAR <lb/>AVULSION <lb/>LOCATION <lb/>LOCATION OF <lb/>CHANNEL MOUTH <lb/>CAUSE OF <lb/>AVULSION <lb/>TIME INTERVAL <lb/>TO THE NEXT <lb/>AVULSION <lb/>ACTIVE TIME <lb/>1 <lb/>June 1855 <lb/>Tongwaxiang <lb/>Xiaoshenmiao Village <lb/>and Oyster Mouth <lb/>The first active river <lb/>since Tongwaxiang <lb/>crevasse <lb/>33 years and 9 <lb/>months <lb/>19 years <lb/>2 <lb/>March 1889 <lb/>Hanjiayuan <lb/>Maosituo <lb/>The breaching due to <lb/>ice jam in winter <lb/>8 years and 2 <lb/>months <lb/>5 years and 10 <lb/>months <lb/>3 <lb/>May 1897 <lb/>Beilingzi <lb/>Siwangkou <lb/>The dyke breaching <lb/>due to flood <lb/>7 years and 1 <lb/>month <lb/>5 years and 9 <lb/>months <lb/>4 <lb/>June 1904 <lb/>Yanwo <lb/>Lao Hu Mouth, Car <lb/>Ditch, Noodle Ditch, <lb/>Tao &apos;er River <lb/>Crevasse caused by <lb/>summer flood <lb/>22 years <lb/>17 years and 9 <lb/>months <lb/>5 <lb/>June 1926 <lb/>Balizhuang <lb/>Old Diaokou <lb/>Crevasse caused by <lb/>summer flood <lb/>3 years and 2 <lb/>months <lb/>2 years and 11 <lb/>months <lb/>6 <lb/>August 1929 <lb/>Jijiazhuang <lb/>Nanwang River; <lb/>Siwangkou old River <lb/>Course; Song Chunrong <lb/>Ditch; Qingtuozi <lb/>Artificial breaking <lb/>diversion <lb/>5 years <lb/>3 years and 4 <lb/>months <lb/>7 <lb/>August 1934 <lb/>No. 1 Dam in <lb/>closure <lb/>Sweet Water Ditch, <lb/>Fairy Ditch, Song <lb/>Chunrong Ditch <lb/>Crevasse caused by <lb/>summer flood <lb/>19 years <lb/>9 years and 2 <lb/>months <lb/>8 <lb/>July 1953 <lb/>Xiaokouzi <lb/>Fairy Ditch <lb/>The artificial course <lb/>diversion <lb/>10 years and 5 <lb/>months <lb/>10 years and 5 <lb/>months <lb/>9 <lb/>January 1964 <lb/>Luojiawuzi <lb/>Diaokou River <lb/>Artificial diversion <lb/>12 years and 5 <lb/>months <lb/>12 years and 5 <lb/>months <lb/>10 <lb/>May 1976 <lb/>West river <lb/>mouth <lb/>Fresh Water Ditch <lb/>Artificial diversion <lb/>20 years and 2 <lb/>months <lb/>20 years and 2 <lb/>months <lb/>11 <lb/>July 1996 <lb/>Qing 8 Route <lb/>Artificial diversion <lb/>To date <lb/>Table 1 History of the YRD distributary channels and avulsions since 1855 (Administration Bureau of the Yellow River Estuary, the <lb/>Yellow River Conservancy Commission, 1995). <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

            <note place="headnote">Liu et al. Rural Landscapes: Society, Environment, History DOI: 10.16993/rl.100 <lb/></note>

			<body>3.1.3 Rural settlement data <lb/>The data sources of the place names, establishment <lb/>times, and coordinates of the rural settlements in the <lb/>Yellow River are shown in Table 2. Village coordinate data <lb/>were extracted from the Baidu map using the coordinate <lb/>system on the website (http://api.map.baidu.com/lbsapi/ <lb/>getpoint/index.html). <lb/>3.2 RESEARCH METHODS <lb/>The kernel density estimation (KDE) method was used to <lb/>analyse the spatial distribution characteristics of villages <lb/>in the Yellow River Delta. KDE fully reflects the law of <lb/>distance attenuation in geography. The spatial change <lb/>is continuous, and the &apos;crest&apos; and &apos;trough&apos; strengthen <lb/>the spatial distribution pattern displayed. Therefore, the <lb/>spatial distribution of place names can be objectively and <lb/>accurately expressed (Wang, 2006). <lb/>The kernel density equation is shown in Equation (1) <lb/>below. In this equation, f(x) is the normal kernel density, <lb/>K( ) is the kernel density, h is a smoothing parameter <lb/>(also known as the bandwidth), n is the number of points <lb/>within the threshold range, and d is the dimension of the <lb/>data. The density distribution is highest at the centre of <lb/>each point and continuously decreases with increasing <lb/>distance. The geometric meaning of the kernel density <lb/>equation is that when the distance from the centre <lb/>reaches a certain threshold range, the density is 0. <lb/>( ) <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>n <lb/>i <lb/>d <lb/>i <lb/>x x <lb/>f x <lb/>K <lb/>h <lb/>nh <lb/>= <lb/>ae <lb/>ö <lb/>-÷ <lb/>ç <lb/>= <lb/>÷ <lb/>ç <lb/>÷ ÷ <lb/>ç <lb/>è <lb/>ø <lb/>å <lb/>Equation (1) <lb/>We regard the study area as a two-dimensional space, so <lb/>in our study, d = 2; at the same time, we regard villages <lb/>as point data. The normal kernel density is calculated as <lb/>follows (Equation (2)): <lb/>( ) <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>( <lb/>) ( <lb/>) <lb/>1 <lb/>n <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>x x <lb/>y y <lb/>f x <lb/>nh <lb/>h <lb/>p <lb/>= <lb/>é <lb/>ù <lb/>-<lb/>+ -<lb/>ê <lb/>ú <lb/>= <lb/>-<lb/>ê <lb/>ú <lb/>ê <lb/>ú <lb/>ë <lb/>û <lb/>å <lb/>Equation (2) <lb/>In Equation (2), i represents a village, (x i ,y i ) represents the <lb/>coordinates of village i in a two-dimensional coordinate <lb/>system, and (x,y) represents any point within the search <lb/>radius h, so (x-x i ) 2 + (y-y i ) 2 is the distance between (x i ,y i ) <lb/>and (x,y). Here, 1 km, 3 km, and 5 km were taken as the <lb/>search radii h for the operation of kernel density analysis <lb/>in ArcGIS10.2, among which 5 km was the best because <lb/>of its best cartographic effect, so the search radius was <lb/>set to 5 km, and the value outputs of pixel size were <lb/>assumed to be the default value of ArcGIS, which was <lb/>approximately 2′ × 2′. <lb/>Referring to the data of place names and county <lb/>records, the village establishment times of 714 villages in <lb/>the Yellow River Delta region were obtained. Geographic <lb/>coordinate information and ArcGIS kernel density analysis <lb/>were used to generate a map of the kernel density <lb/>distribution of the delta villages. From the perspective <lb/>of spatial visualization, this study analysed the temporal <lb/>and spatial distribution characteristics of villages and <lb/>their responses to Yellow River diversions since 1855. <lb/>4 RESULTS <lb/>4.1 NUMBER OF VILLAGES IN THE YELLOW <lb/>RIVER DELTA <lb/>The total number of villages in the Yellow River Delta <lb/>is 714, of which 92 existed before 1855, and 622 were <lb/>newly added after 1855. <lb/>Taking 10 years as a statistical period, the number of <lb/>newly added villages in the Yellow River Delta during each <lb/>period from 1855 to 2000 showed an &apos;inverted V&apos; pattern <lb/>of change, which first increased and then decreased <lb/>(Figure 4). Corresponding to the number of newly added <lb/>villages in each period, the total number of villages in the <lb/>Yellow River Delta continued to increase and could be <lb/>divided into three stages according to the growth rate: <lb/>REGIONS <lb/>DATA SOURCE (PLACE NAME AND ESTABLISHMENT YEAR OF RURAL SETTLEMENTS) <lb/>Dongying City <lb/>Gazetteer of Dongying City of Shandong Province (Place Name Committee Office of Dongying, 1992), <lb/>Annals of Dongying District (Compilation Committee of Local Historical Records of Dongying District, <lb/>Dongying City, 2000). <lb/>Kenli County <lb/>Annals of Kenli County (Compilation Committee of Local Historical Records of Kenli County, 1997), <lb/>Annals of Kenli County (1986~2002) (Compilation Committee of Local Historical Records of Kenli <lb/>County, 2004). <lb/>Lijin County <lb/>Annals of Lijin (Compilation Committee of Local Historical Records of Lijin County, Shandong Province, <lb/>1990). <lb/>Hekou District <lb/>Annals of Hekou District (Compilation Committee of Local Historical Records of Hekou District, <lb/>Dongying City, 2002). <lb/>Zhanhua County <lb/>Toponymy of Zhanhua County, Shandong Province (Geographical Names Committee Office of Zhanhua <lb/>County, 1988), <lb/>Annals of Zhanhua County (Compilation Committee of Local Historical Records of Zhanhua County, <lb/>Shandong Province, 1995). <lb/>Table 2 Data sources of rural settlements in the Yellow River. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Liu et al. Rural Landscapes: Society, Environment, History DOI: 10.16993/rl.100 <lb/></note>

			<body> The steady growth stage of villages occurred from <lb/>1855 to 1920, with a growth rate of approximately <lb/>2.7 villages per year. In this stage, the continuous <lb/>increase in population in Shandong became the <lb/>key driving force for land reclamation and village <lb/>establishment (Yan, 2010). This stage corresponds <lb/>to the active time of the first, second, and third river <lb/>courses of the Yellow River. <lb/> During 1921-1970, the number of villages increased <lb/>significantly, exceeding 10 villages per year. In <lb/>1931-1940, 126 villages were built, more than the <lb/>total added villages during 1855-1900. This stage <lb/>corresponds to the active time of River Courses 4, 5, <lb/>6, 7, and 8 of the Yellow River. A large area of fertile <lb/>land was silted up by the frequent diversion of the tail <lb/>of the Yellow River, which attracted indigenous and <lb/>foreign settlers who reclaimed the land, and many <lb/>villages were established as a result. <lb/> During 1971-2000, the growth rate of villages was <lb/>only 0.6 per year. Perhaps the low growth rate was <lb/>related to the influence of oil field construction and <lb/>wetland protection policies; some villages declined in <lb/>size, were relocated, or even disappeared. <lb/>4.2 SPATIAL PATTERN OF VILLAGES IN THE <lb/>YELLOW RIVER DELTA <lb/>Before the Yellow River diverted to Shandong in 1855, the <lb/>villages in the Yellow River Delta were mainly concentrated <lb/>along the Daqing River (Figure 5). The high-value area of the <lb/>kernel density presented a banded distribution along the <lb/>Daqing River, and the kernel density decreased gradually <lb/>with increasing density shifting to the sea. Moreover, a few <lb/>Figure 4 Changes in the number of villages in the Yellow River Delta. <lb/>Figure 5 Spatial pattern of villages in the Yellow River Delta. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Liu et al. Rural Landscapes: Society, Environment, History DOI: 10.16993/rl.100 <lb/></note>

			<body>villages were scattered in the inland area of the Yellow <lb/>River Delta. With the Daqing River as the axis, two small <lb/>densely populated areas of villages formed. Many villages <lb/>are still established and developed in these areas. <lb/>In August 1855, the Yellow River broke at Tongwaxiang <lb/>in Henan Province, and then seized the Daqing River <lb/>into the sea in Shandong Province. Since 1855, the <lb/>distribution range of villages and the range of high <lb/>nuclear density areas in the Yellow River Delta have <lb/>expanded significantly, but the nuclear density is still <lb/>significantly greater in inland areas than in coastal areas. <lb/>Specifically, the Tiemenguan River Course (River Course 1) <lb/>of the Yellow River was considered the axis; it expanded <lb/>to the northeast and southeast, and it further extended <lb/>to the sea. In this stage, three zones with high nuclear <lb/>density appeared, and they were distributed along the <lb/>Tiemenguan Channel (1855-1889), Hutanzui Channel <lb/>(1904-1926), Sweet Water Ditch and Song Chunrong <lb/>Ditch Channel (1934-1953). The kernel density was 2-7 <lb/>times that of other areas. <lb/>4.3 CHARACTERISTICS OF THE SPATIAL <lb/>DISTRIBUTION OF NEWLY ADDED VILLAGES <lb/>AND THEIR RESPONSES TO EACH CHANNEL <lb/>To explore the spatial distribution characteristics of <lb/>newly added villages in the Yellow River Delta and the <lb/>response relationship between the number of newly <lb/>added villages and the active time of each channel of the <lb/>Yellow River, the number of newly added villages during <lb/>the active time of each channel was calculated, and the <lb/>spatial distribution of newly added villages was analysed <lb/>via the kernel density estimation method. <lb/>The newly added villages during the active period of <lb/>each course in the Yellow River Delta were concentrated <lb/>along the active channel and near the silted-up <lb/>abandoned channel (Table 3; Figure 6). According to the <lb/>distribution characteristics of villages and their responses <lb/>to the Yellow River rerouting since 1855, the avulsion and <lb/>settling history could be divided into three stages. <lb/>Stage 1: From 1855 to 1926, the Yellow River <lb/>experienced three avulsions caused by floods. After each <lb/>avulsion, approximately 70% of the total new villages <lb/>were built along the active new course and the dried-up <lb/>old courses. The number of villages involved in the active <lb/>course was greater than that involved in the old course. <lb/>During the period from 1855 to 1889, most new <lb/>villages in the Yellow River Delta were located along the <lb/>river, forming a high-density belt along River Course 1. <lb/>During the active time of River Course 2 from 1889 to <lb/>1897, most of the newly added villages in the delta were <lb/>distributed in a V-shaped pattern along River Course 1 <lb/>and the active river channel (River Course 2) with the <lb/>Hanjiayuan crevasse site as the vertex; the number <lb/>of villages along the two rivers was similar. During the <lb/>active time of River Course 3 from 1897 to 1904, the <lb/>newly added villages were distributed in a scattered <lb/>manner along the three river channels (River Courses 1, <lb/>2 and 3). During the period from 1904-1926, the number <lb/>of newly added villages was greater than that in the <lb/>previous three periods. Among them, more than half of <lb/>the new villages developed along River Course 4, forming <lb/>the core area of village distribution. The number of new <lb/>villages along River Courses 2 and 3 was also large. <lb/>Stage 2: During the period from 1926-1964, the Yellow <lb/>River experienced three avulsions: one developed from <lb/>a crevasse caused by a summer flood, and the other <lb/>two were artificial channel diversions. Different from <lb/>the previous stage, after each avulsion, few village was <lb/>built along the new river branch, and the new villages <lb/>were mainly concentrated along the old courses that <lb/>had dried up, accounting for 50-70% of the total new <lb/>settlements. During this period, there was much silted <lb/>land reclamation and village construction in the old <lb/>channel, which was due to river diversion and the range <lb/>of silted land, as well as the Yellow River flood and the <lb/>official immigration policy. <lb/>The distribution of villages in this stage was more <lb/>complex than that in the previous stage. From 1926 <lb/>to 1953, during the active periods of River Course 5, <lb/>River Course 6, and River Course 7, the number of new <lb/>villages along River Course 4 was the largest, and the <lb/>proportion reached approximately half. River Course 4 <lb/>had &apos;the benefit of silting land&apos; and was very attractive for <lb/>reclamation. As a result, many villages were established <lb/>between 1926 and 1953 along River Course 4. Similarly, <lb/>during the period from 1934-1953, many villages were <lb/>established on fertile land that was silted up by River <lb/>Course 6. Together with those along River Course 4, <lb/>these accounted for approximately two-thirds of the <lb/>total number of new villages established during the <lb/>active period of River Course 7. During the period from <lb/>1934-1953, two high-density areas with different levels <lb/>and patterns of villages formed in the northwestern and <lb/>southeastern regions of the delta. The villages around <lb/>River Course 6, such as the Fifth Village, Sixth Village, <lb/>and Ninety-six Households Village in Yongan Town, Kenli <lb/>County, were formed during the active period of River <lb/>Course 7 (1934-1953). From 1953 to 1964, during the <lb/>active period of River Course 8, more new villages were <lb/>significantly more common near River Course 7 than <lb/>along other old routes, such as Fulin Village, Lilin Village, <lb/>and Zhouliu Village in Huanghekou Town, Kenli County, <lb/>which formed a dense distribution area in the triangular <lb/>area surrounded by branches of Sweet Water Ditch and <lb/>Song Chunrong Ditch, accounting for approximately <lb/>three-quarters of the total number of new villages during <lb/>the active period of River Course 8. <lb/>The different distribution characteristics of villages in <lb/>stage 1 and stage 2 may be attributed to the following <lb/>two factors. On the one hand, there were differences in <lb/>the patterns of each channel and the extent of silted <lb/>land. River Courses 1, 2, and 3 were single channels, so <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Liu et al. Rural Landscapes: Society, Environment, History DOI: 10.16993/rl.100 <lb/></note>

			<body>RIVER <lb/>COURSE <lb/>1 <lb/>RIVER <lb/>COURSE <lb/>2 <lb/>RIVER <lb/>COURSE <lb/>3 <lb/>RIVER <lb/>COURSE <lb/>4 <lb/>RIVER <lb/>COURSE <lb/>5 <lb/>RIVER <lb/>COURSE <lb/>6 <lb/>RIVER <lb/>COURSE <lb/>7 <lb/>RIVER <lb/>COURSE <lb/>8 <lb/>RIVER <lb/>COURSE <lb/>9 <lb/>RIVER <lb/>COURSE <lb/>10 <lb/>THE NUMBER OF <lb/>NEW VILLAGES <lb/>ALONG THE <lb/>COURSES IN EACH <lb/>PERIOD <lb/>THE TOTAL <lb/>NUMBER OF NEW <lb/>VILLAGES IN <lb/>EACH PERIOD <lb/>1855-1889 <lb/>N ** <lb/>38 <lb/>38 <lb/>48 <lb/>P *** <lb/>79% <lb/>79% <lb/>1889-1897 <lb/>N <lb/>12 <lb/>15 <lb/>27 <lb/>32 <lb/>P <lb/>37% <lb/>47% <lb/>84% <lb/>1897-1904 <lb/>N <lb/>6 <lb/>10 <lb/>10 <lb/>26 <lb/>36 <lb/>P <lb/>16% <lb/>28% <lb/>28% <lb/>72% <lb/>1904-1926 <lb/>N <lb/>5 <lb/>13 <lb/>11 <lb/>64 <lb/>93 <lb/>107 <lb/>P <lb/>5% <lb/>12% <lb/>10% <lb/>60% <lb/>87% <lb/>1926-1929 <lb/>N <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>3 <lb/>9 <lb/>0 <lb/>13 <lb/>17 <lb/>P <lb/>6% <lb/>0% <lb/>18% <lb/>53% <lb/>0% <lb/>77% <lb/>1929-1934 <lb/>N <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>31 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>44 <lb/>51 <lb/>P <lb/>2% <lb/>4% <lb/>8% <lb/>60% <lb/>4% <lb/>8% <lb/>86% <lb/>1934-1953 <lb/>N <lb/>7 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>87 <lb/>15 <lb/>56 <lb/>27 <lb/>207 <lb/>217 <lb/>P <lb/>3% <lb/>2% <lb/>5% <lb/>40% <lb/>7% <lb/>26% <lb/>12% <lb/>95% <lb/>1953-1964 <lb/>N <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>4 <lb/>11 <lb/>1 <lb/>59 <lb/>3 <lb/>81 <lb/>82 <lb/>P <lb/>2% <lb/>1% <lb/>0% <lb/>5% <lb/>14% <lb/>1% <lb/>72% <lb/>4% <lb/>99% <lb/>1964-1976 <lb/>N <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>6 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>18 <lb/>18 <lb/>P <lb/>16% <lb/>6% <lb/>0% <lb/>22% <lb/>11% <lb/>6% <lb/>33% <lb/>6% <lb/>0% <lb/>100% <lb/>1976-1996 <lb/>N <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>7 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>12 <lb/>13 <lb/>P <lb/>8% <lb/>0% <lb/>0% <lb/>8% <lb/>0% <lb/>8% <lb/>54% <lb/>15% <lb/>0% <lb/>0% <lb/>93% <lb/>The total number of new <lb/>villages along each channel <lb/>76 <lb/>47 <lb/>38 <lb/>200 <lb/>30 <lb/>63 <lb/>99 <lb/>6 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>Table 3 The number and proportion of newly added villages along the Yellow River during each flow period *. <lb/>* Villages within 5 km of each river course are counted as coastal villages of each old route <lb/>** The number of newly added villages along each course. <lb/>*** The proportion of newly added villages along courses to the total number of new villages in the period. <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Liu et al. Rural Landscapes: Society, Environment, History DOI: 10.16993/rl.100 <lb/></note>

            <body>Figure 6 Density distribution of newly added villages in the Yellow River Delta during different periods after 1855. <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Liu et al. Rural Landscapes: Society, Environment, History DOI: 10.16993/rl.100 <lb/></note>

			<body>after abandonment, the area of the silted-up channel <lb/>was relatively narrow. During the active period of River <lb/>Courses 1, 2 and 3, the attraction of silted land by old <lb/>river courses was not much different, and even the <lb/>former was stronger. River Courses 4, 6, and 7 had at <lb/>least three river branches and flowed through a wide <lb/>area; &apos;the benefit of silting&apos; was very significant. Among <lb/>them, River Course 4 had the largest impact area. In its <lb/>active period and the active periods of River Courses 5, 6, <lb/>and 7, the proportion of newly added villages along the <lb/>river was the highest. On the other hand, in the second <lb/>stage, the official immigration policy stimulated the <lb/>growth of the number of villages. In August 1933, the <lb/>Yellow River flooded 30 counties in Henan, Shandong, <lb/>Hebei, and Jiangsu Provinces. On July 10th, 1935, the <lb/>Yellow River breached its banks at Dongzhuang Village, <lb/>Juancheng County (located in the upper reaches of the <lb/>Yellow River delta, approximately 400 km from the Yellow <lb/>River delta), and western Shandong was inundated again <lb/>in an &apos;especially unprecedented catastrophe&apos; (Shandong <lb/>Yellow River Flood Relief Committee, 1935). Faced with <lb/>a large number of victims caused by two Yellow River <lb/>floods, the government implemented a reclamation plan <lb/>to migrate them to the Yellow River Delta (Zhang, 2019). <lb/>At this time, the old, silted land in the Yellow River Delta, <lb/>especially that of River Course 4, naturally became the <lb/>best choice for resettlement, and villages continued to <lb/>be established. <lb/>Stage 3: From 1964 to the present, the Yellow River has <lb/>undergone two artificial diversions. After each diversion, <lb/>the number of newly added villages decreased sharply <lb/>compared to that in the first two stages, and they were <lb/>scattered along the banks of several old river courses. <lb/>From 1964 to 1976, during the active period of River <lb/>Course 9, villages were built along the Yellow River <lb/>courses except for the active river course and River Course <lb/>3, and villages in River Course 7 were the most common, <lb/>while villages in River Course 2, 6, and 8 were the least <lb/>common. From 1976 to 1996, during the active period <lb/>of River Course 10, more than half of the new villages in <lb/>the delta were concentrated along River Course 7, and <lb/>the rest were scattered in River Courses 1, 4, 6, and 8. <lb/>Since 1996, only one new village has been added, and it <lb/>is located at the old river mouth of River Course 8. <lb/>In this stage, after a long period of desalinization and <lb/>dealkalization, the difference in soil quality between the <lb/>old river courses of the Yellow River Delta decreased, which <lb/>might be the main reason for the scattered distribution <lb/>of new villages. In addition, it was influenced by the <lb/>development of oil fields and wetland conservation. <lb/>For example, there were oil fields and their associated <lb/>factories near River Courses 8, 9, 10 and 11, which might <lb/>occupy areas of living places and farmland. Therefore, <lb/>new villages were not gathering along these channels. <lb/>On the other hand, wetland conservation could force <lb/>some coastal villages to return farmland to wetlands so <lb/>that the villagers had to move to other places to make <lb/>a living. <lb/>From 1855 to the present, the Yellow River breached its <lb/>banks and changed its course several times. Progressive <lb/>sedimentation caused the Yellow River Delta to further <lb/>expand, and the area of land available for reclamation <lb/>continued to increase. Additionally, benefiting from the <lb/>sediment fertility of the Yellow River and the effects <lb/>of salt and alkali reduction, the dried-up riverbed and <lb/>surrounding silted land after the Yellow River avulsion <lb/>were suitable for crop cultivation. Therefore, the constant <lb/>increase in land suitability for reclamation has provided <lb/>the material basis for agricultural development, attracting <lb/>villagers to reclaim and settle. As a result, many villages <lb/>have emerged, and their distribution pattern has shown <lb/>great changes. <lb/>5 DISCUSSION <lb/>Agriculture (especially crop farming) is the most <lb/>fundamental and important economic activity in <lb/>many river deltas. The location of the associated delta <lb/>settlements reflects the spatial path of land reclamation, <lb/>which should be a process of seeking benefits and <lb/>avoiding disadvantages. The unique geographical <lb/>environment of deltas is both beneficial and harmful to <lb/>agricultural development and human settlement. <lb/>There are two adverse effects of natural processes on <lb/>new settling patterns: flooding and soil salinization. First, <lb/>the flooding of large rivers would undoubtedly destroy <lb/>arable land and villages, and archaeological sites also <lb/>show traces of villages being washed and drowned by <lb/>floods (Ginau, 2018; He et al., 2021; Zhu, 2003). Second, <lb/>because deltas are close to the sea and affected by tides, <lb/>the groundwater salinity rate is high, coupled with the <lb/>low and flat terrain, the soil water release ability is weak, <lb/>and soil salinization is widespread, which has become <lb/>the greatest limiting factor for the development of <lb/>agriculture in deltas. Moreover, impractical irrigation will <lb/>also cause and aggravate secondary salinization of soil <lb/>(Altaweel &amp; Watanabe, 2012; Hammam &amp; Mohamed, <lb/>2020; Kotb et al., 2000; Shahid et al., 2018; Tamburrino, <lb/>1970; Yu J et al., 2014; Zhang et al., 2011). <lb/>There are also two benefits: easy access to water and <lb/>fertile soil from floods. First, large rivers provide deltas <lb/>with easy access to water for irrigation and domestic use. <lb/>The role of water is especially important in the Nile Delta, <lb/>Mesopotamia Plain and other arid climate areas (Bagg, <lb/>2000; Ginau, 2018; Wang, 2019). Second, flooding often <lb/>causes the soil from the upper and middle reaches to <lb/>silt over large areas along the coast, which is fertile and <lb/>can provide nutrients for a new round of crop cultivation. <lb/>For example, Egyptians were able to grow cotton in the <lb/>Nile Valley as early as 4000-5000 years ago, taking <lb/>advantage of the regular flooding of the Nile caused by <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Liu et al. Rural Landscapes: Society, Environment, History DOI: 10.16993/rl.100 <lb/></note>

            <body>seasonal heavy rains on the Ethiopian Plateau (Craig, <lb/>1993; Liu, 2000). <lb/>From this point of view, the influence of large rivers <lb/>on deltas is not unidirectional but rather has dual effects <lb/>-flooding and siltation. The Yellow River has a very <lb/>high sediment content and is good at sedimentation <lb/>and migration. The extremely high sediment content <lb/>significantly amplifies both the beneficial and adverse <lb/>effects of Yellow River flooding. <lb/>Similar to other deltas, soil salinization is a key limiting <lb/>factor for reclamation in the Yellow River Delta, and <lb/>the land reclamation process in the Yellow River Delta <lb/>is a continuous search for low-salinization land that <lb/>can be developed. The best option for combating soil <lb/>salinization is Yellow River sediment. The Yellow River <lb/>has excellent sediment and fertilizer efficiency and has <lb/>multiple effects, such as land levelling, desalination <lb/>and alkalization, and improving the soil structure. When <lb/>the silting reaches a certain height, which causes large <lb/>depressions around the old river, the old course after the <lb/>diversion turns into a good field. A large area of silted <lb/>land suitable for cultivation attracts many reclamation <lb/>households. In the Republic of China, the silted land <lb/>in Xinhu of Hekou District was extensive, and the soil <lb/>quality was &apos;suitable for all kinds of plants to be planted&apos;; <lb/>moreover, &apos;nearby residents were striving to be the first to <lb/>reclaim the land&apos;, and &apos;foreign reclamation families also <lb/>came&apos; (Zhanhua County Chronicle, 1935). The areas of <lb/>Yihe Village and Taiping Village have become prosperous <lb/>(Dong, 1996; Zhanhua County Records, 1935). The land <lb/>silted by the Yellow River gradually became a region <lb/>with a concentrated distribution of villages. For the <lb/>Yellow River Delta region, the changes in the Yellow River <lb/>provided a driving force for the increase and development <lb/>of settlements. On the other hand, the supply of fresh <lb/>water from the Yellow River to the soil moisture and <lb/>groundwater along the coast will also reduce the degree <lb/>of soil salinization. Therefore, although a small number <lb/>of residents are aware of the dangers of Yellow River <lb/>flooding, they are forced to make a living (to cultivate on <lb/>low-salinity soil) and still establish their villages near the <lb/>channels of the active river. <lb/>Floods are another limiting factor for reclamation and <lb/>settlement in the Yellow River Delta. In contrast to land <lb/>salinization, flood destruction is extremely strong and <lb/>sudden. Although it can indeed bring silting benefits in <lb/>the long term, it is more harmful in the short term. Due to <lb/>the extremely high sand content of the Yellow River, the <lb/>frequency of its breach and diversion is increasingly more <lb/>irregular than that of other large rivers in the world, and <lb/>the destructive force is also stronger. Since 1855, when <lb/>the river was diverted to Shandong, the Yellow River has <lb/>flooded nearly 100 times, causing profound disasters <lb/>in the delta (Administration Bureau of the Yellow River <lb/>Estuary, the Yellow River Conservancy Commission, <lb/>1995). The reclamation of cultivated land and the <lb/>establishment of villages along the Yellow River are often <lb/>at risk; for example, extreme floods of the ninth year of <lb/>Guangxu&apos;s reign (1883) and the 26th year of the Republic <lb/>of China (1937) damaged hundreds of villages. <lb/>In summary, although the Yellow River has the <lb/>drawback of migration, it also has the benefit of <lb/>silting up the land, which is a double-edged sword for <lb/>village development and agricultural reclamation. The <lb/>livelihood of local residents and their dependence on the <lb/>Yellow River, as well as the changes in the Yellow River, <lb/>together create the distribution of villages in the Yellow <lb/>River delta. <lb/>6 CONCLUSION <lb/>Combining historical data and field investigations, this <lb/>study focused on the 150 years since the Yellow River <lb/>diverted from Shandong to the sea and analysed the <lb/>response of villages to dynamic changes in the natural <lb/>environment in the Yellow River Delta using records of <lb/>avulsion and settling and village information since 1855. <lb/>A significant tendency was identified of establishment <lb/>of new villages towards an active Yellow River course as <lb/>well as along an abandoned and silted-up Yellow River <lb/>course. <lb/>The Yellow River Delta is seriously salinized because of <lb/>its topography and sea-land position. For settlement and <lb/>agricultural production, residents must avoid the harm <lb/>of soil salinization and constantly search for land with <lb/>low salinization, which is a typical adaptive settlement <lb/>pattern in the Yellow River Delta. The replenishment of <lb/>fresh water from the Yellow River to the groundwater in <lb/>the surrounding area, the improvement of soil structure <lb/>and even the accumulation of the silted area by Yellow <lb/>River sediment have significantly weakened the degree <lb/>of soil salinization. The spatial pattern of active and dry <lb/>channels has determined the settling pattern of residents <lb/>of the delta. <lb/>Moreover, when the Yellow River is diverted and the <lb/>water system changes, the spatial pattern of the village <lb/>will also change accordingly. It Indicates that these <lb/>past shifts and relations to channel avulsion may be still <lb/>valid, and other great river deltas also face the crisis and <lb/>limitation of river damage and salinization, which should <lb/>be considered in delta planning for the future. <lb/></body>

            <div type="availability">DATA ACCESSIBILITY STATEMENT <lb/>The data that support the findings of this study are <lb/>available on request from the corresponding author, <lb/>upon reasonable request. <lb/>This paper does not involve ethical and academic <lb/>misconduct. This paper does not involve other <lb/>competitive interests. <lb/></div>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Liu et al. Rural Landscapes: Society, Environment, History DOI: 10.16993/rl.100 <lb/></note>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>The authors appreciate the editor and reviewers for their <lb/>valuable comments, as well as the efforts and concern <lb/>for this article. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">FUNDING INFORMATION <lb/>Supported by the National Natural Science Foundation <lb/>of China (42041006); Research Startup Fund for <lb/>Academician Team from Zhengzhou University <lb/>(13432340370); the Excellent Young Talents Project <lb/>of Yellow River Conservancy Commission (HQK-<lb/>202313). <lb/></div>

            <div type="conflict">COMPETING INTERESTS <lb/>The authors have no competing interests to declare. <lb/></div>

            <div type="contribution">AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS <lb/>Yu Ye organized the field expedition and concepted the <lb/>outline of this paper; Yuting Liu and Yu Ye wrote and <lb/>edited the manuscript; Jinfeng Jiang translated the <lb/>manuscript into English; all authors, except for Jinfeng <lb/>Jiang, took part in the field expedition and the discussion <lb/>of editing this paper. <lb/></div>

            <front>AUTHOR AFILIATIONS <lb/>Yuting Liu <lb/>Faculty of Geographical Sciences, Beijing Normal University, <lb/>Beijing 100875, China <lb/>Yu Ye <lb/>Faculty of Geographical Sciences, Beijing Normal University, <lb/>Beijing 100875, China; Key Laboratory of Environment Change <lb/>and Natural Disaster, Ministry of Education, Beijing Normal <lb/>University, Beijing 100875, China <lb/>Chang Jiang <lb/>Faculty of Geographical Sciences, Beijing Normal University, <lb/>Beijing 100875, China <lb/>Jinfeng Jiang <lb/>Faculty of Geographical Sciences, Beijing Normal University, <lb/>Beijing 100875, China <lb/>Fahao Wang <lb/>Faculty of Geographical Sciences, Beijing Normal University, <lb/>Beijing 100875, China <lb/>Jun Li <lb/>Faculty of Geographical Sciences, Beijing Normal University, <lb/>Beijing 100875, China <lb/>Xiangping Zhang <lb/>Yellow River Institute of Hydraulic Research, Zhengzhou <lb/>450003, China; Key Laboratory of Lower Yellow River Channel <lb/>and Estuary Regulation, MWR, Zhengzhou 450003, China <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>Administration Bureau of the Yellow River Estuary, the <lb/>Yellow River Conservancy Commission. (1995). Annals of <lb/>the Yellow River in Dongying City. Qilu Publishing House. <lb/>Altaweel, M., &amp; Watanabe, C. (2012). Assessing the resilience <lb/>of irrigation agriculture: Applying a social-ecological model <lb/>for understanding the mitigation of salinization. Journal of <lb/>Archaeological Science, 39(4), 1160-1171. DOI: https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.jas.2011.12.020 <lb/>Bagg, A. M. (2000). Irrigation in Northern Mesopotamia: Water <lb/>for the Assyrian Capitals (12th-7th centuries BC). Irrigation <lb/>&amp; Drainage Systems, 14(4), 301-324. DOI: https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1023/A:1006421000423 <lb/>Batker, D., Torre, I. D. L., Costanza, R., Swedeen, P., Boumans, <lb/>R., &amp; Bagstad, K. (2010). Gaining ground: Wetlands, <lb/>hurricanes, and the economy: The value of restoring the <lb/>Mississippi River Delta. The environmental law reporter, <lb/>40(11), 11106-11110. DOI: https://doi.org/10.3411/ <lb/>col.08230102 <lb/>Bhattacharya, U. (2022). Floods, aridity and rivers: An <lb/>environmental history of pargana Mandalghat in <lb/>eighteenth-century Bengal. The Indian Economic &amp; <lb/>Social History Review, 59(3), 335-371. DOI: https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1177/00194646221109299 <lb/>Bonsall, C., Macklin, M. G., Boroneant, A., Pickard, C., <lb/>Bartosiewicz, L., Cook, G. T., &amp; Higham, T. F. G. (2015). <lb/>Holocene climate change and prehistoric settlement <lb/>in the lower Danube valley. Quaternary International, <lb/>378(Aug. 18), 14-21. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>quaint.2014.09.031 <lb/>Carozza, J. M., Micu, C., Mihail, F., &amp; Carozza, L. (2012). <lb/>Landscape change and archaeological settlements in <lb/>the lower Danube valley and delta from early Neolithic <lb/>to Chalcolithic time: A review. Quaternary International, <lb/>261(May 30), 21-31. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>quaint.2010.07.017 <lb/>Cederlöf, G. (2014). Founding an empire on India&apos;s north-<lb/>eastern frontiers, 1790-1840: Climate, commerce, polity. <lb/>Oxford University Press. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1093/acpro <lb/>f:oso/9780198090571.001.0001 <lb/>Compilation Committee of Local Historical Records of <lb/>Dongying District, Dongying City. (2000). Annals of <lb/>Dongying District. Zhonghua Book Company. <lb/>Compilation Committee of Local Historical Records of Hekou <lb/>District, Dongying City. (2002). Annals of Hekou District. <lb/>Zhonghua Book Company. <lb/>Compilation Committee of Local Historical Records of Kenli <lb/>County. (1997). Annals of Kenli County. Shandong People&apos;s <lb/>Publishing House. <lb/>Compilation Committee of Local Historical Records of Kenli <lb/>County. (2004). Annals of Kenli County (1986~2002). <lb/>Zhonghua Book Company. <lb/>Compilation Committee of Local Historical Records of Lijin <lb/>County, Shandong Province. (1990). Annals of Lijin County. <lb/>Oriental Publishing House. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Liu et al. Rural Landscapes: Society, Environment, History DOI: 10.16993/rl.100 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Compilation Committee of Local Historical Records of <lb/>Zhanhua County, Shandong Province. (1995). Annals of <lb/>Zhanhua County. Qilu Publishing House. <lb/>Craig, G. M. (1993). Agriculture of Egypt, 383-394. Oxford <lb/>University Press. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1093/ <lb/>oso/9780198592037.001.0001 <lb/>Dobrescu, E. M., &amp; Grigorescu, A. (2011). The European Union <lb/>strategy for the Danube -Preliminaries, mechanisms, <lb/>positions, priorities and effects. Romanian Journal of <lb/>Economics, 32(1), 169-190. <lb/>Dong, L. K. (1996). Development and migration of the Yellow <lb/>River Delta in modern times. Journal of Chinese Historical <lb/>Geography, 1, 39-61. <lb/>Geographical Names Committee Office of Zhanhua County. <lb/>(1988). Toponymy of Zhanhua County, Shandong Province. <lb/>China Ocean Press. <lb/>Ginau, A., Schiestl, R., &amp; Wunderlich, J. (2018). Integrative <lb/>geoarchaeological research on settlement patterns in <lb/>the dynamic landscape of the northwestern Nile delta. <lb/>Quaternary International, 511, 51-67. DOI: https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.quaint.2018.04.047 <lb/>Hammam, A. A. A., &amp; Mohamed, B. E. S. (2020). Mapping soil <lb/>salinity in the East Nile Delta using several methodological <lb/>approaches of salinity assessment. The Egyptian Journal of <lb/>Remote Sensing and Space Science, 23(2), 125-131. DOI: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejrs.2018.11.002 <lb/>Han, M., Zhang, X., &amp; Liu, L. (2006). Research progress of Yellow <lb/>River Delta wetland. Ecological Environment, 872-875. <lb/>He, K., Lu, H., Sun, G., Ji, X., Wang, Y., Yan, K., Zuo, X., Zhang, <lb/>J., Liu, B., &amp; Wang, N. (2021). Multi-proxy evidence of <lb/>environmental change related to collapse of the Liangzhu <lb/>Culture in the Yangtze Delta, China. Science China Earth <lb/>Sciences, 64(6), 890-905. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1007/ <lb/>s11430-020-9767-5 <lb/>Husain, F. H. (2016). Changes in the Euphrates River: Ecology <lb/>and politics in a rural Ottoman periphery, 1687-1702. <lb/>The Journal of Interdisciplinary History, 47(1), 1-25. DOI: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1162/JINH_a_00939 <lb/>Jin, T. (2018). Study on the human and land relationship <lb/>in Liangzhu period based on GIS. China University of <lb/>Geosciences (Beijing). <lb/>Kotb, T. H. S., Watanabe, T., Ogino, Y., &amp; Tanji, K. (2000). Soil <lb/>salinization in the Nile Delta and related policy issues in <lb/>Egypt. Agricultural Water Management, 43(2), 239-261. <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.1016/S0378-3774(99)00052-9 <lb/>Liu, W. P. (2000). History of ancient Egypt. The Commercial <lb/>Press. <lb/>Liu, Y., Han, M., Pan, B., &amp; Liu, Y. (2017). Spatial distribution of <lb/>plant biomass and soil salt content in the newborn wetland <lb/>in Yellow River Delta. Wetland Science, 15, 364-368. <lb/>Lu, G. (2018). Analysis on spatiotemporal changes of net <lb/>primary productivity in the Yellow River Delta in modern <lb/>times. Shandong Normal University. <lb/>Lu, J. F. (2019). Study on the change of landscape pattern and its <lb/>response to major environmental factors in the Yellow River <lb/>Delta in recent 30 years. Qingdao Technological University. <lb/>Lu, P., Mo, D., Wang, H., Yang, R., Tian, Y., Chen, P., <lb/>Lasaponara, R., &amp; Masini, N. (2017). On the relationship <lb/>between Holocene geomorphic evolution of rivers and <lb/>prehistoric settlements distribution in the Songshan <lb/>Mountain Region of China. Sustainability, 9, 114. DOI: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/su9010114 <lb/>Lu, P., Wang, H., Chen, P., Storozum, M., Xu, J., Tian, Y., Mo, <lb/>D., Wang, S., He, Y., &amp; Yan, L. (2019). The impact of <lb/>Holocene alluvial landscape evolution on an ancient <lb/>settlement in the southeastern piedmont of Songshan <lb/>Mountain, Central China: A study from the Shiyuan site. <lb/>Catena, 183(1), 104232. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>catena.2019.104232 <lb/>Ma, C., Wang, H., Tan, B., Zhou, J., Dai, X., &amp; Wang, X. (2022). <lb/>Characteristics and spatial reconstruction of an urban-<lb/>rural settlement scale system in a typical oasis in Xinjiang: <lb/>A case study of the Ugan-Kuqa River Delta Oasis. Acta <lb/>Geographica Sinica, 77(04), 852-868. <lb/>Ma, X., Bai, Y., Ji, X., Qiao, F., &amp; Zhang, N. (2018). Spatial <lb/>pattern and differentiation of rural settlements in inland <lb/>river basin of arid area. Research of Soil and Water <lb/>Conservation, 25(02), 281-287. <lb/>Mako, P., &amp; Galileriková, A. (2021). Inland navigation on the <lb/>Danube and the Rhine waterways. Transportation Research <lb/>Procedia, 55, 10-17. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>trpro.2021.06.002 <lb/>Ollivier, V., Fontugne, M., Lyonnet, B., &amp; Chataigner, C. (2016). <lb/>Base level changes, river avulsions, and Holocene human <lb/>settlement dynamics in the Caspian Sea area (middle Kura <lb/>valley, South Caucasus). Quaternary International, 395, <lb/>79-94. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quaint.2015.03.017 <lb/>Place Name Committee Office of Dongying. Gazetteer <lb/>of Dongying City of Shandong Province. 1992. Jinan: <lb/>Cartographic Publishing House. <lb/>Preoteasa, L., Vespremeanu-Stroe, A., Panaiotu, C., Rotaru, <lb/>S., Tutuianu, L., Sava, T., Bîrzescu, I., Dimofte, D., Sava, <lb/>G., Mirea, D., &amp; Ailincai, S. (2019). Neolithic to modern <lb/>period palaeogeographic transformations in southern <lb/>Danube delta and their impact on human settlements in <lb/>the Enisala-Babadag region. Quaternary International, 504. <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.quaint.2018.09.010 <lb/>Schiestl, R. (2012). Field boundaries and ancient settlement <lb/>sites: Observations from the regional survey around <lb/>Buto, Western Delta. Mitteilungen des Deutschen <lb/>Archäologischen Instituts, Abteilung Kairo, 68(1): 175-190. <lb/>https://epub.ub.uni-muenchen.de/28072/ <lb/>Shahid, S. A., Zaman, M., &amp; Heng, L. (2018). Soil salinity: <lb/>Historical perspectives and a world overview of the <lb/>problem. Guideline for Salinity Assessment, Mitigation and <lb/>Adaptation Using Nuclear and Related Techniques, 11, <lb/>43-53. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-96190-3_2 <lb/>Shandong Yellow River Flood Relief Committee (Eds.). (1935). <lb/>Shandong Yellow River Flood Relief Report, 1, 1. <lb/>Shi, B. (2013). Hydrological and geomorphic conditions on <lb/>the influence of Jiaodong peninsula settlement location. <lb/>Journal of Chinese Archaeology, 34 and 45. <lb/></div>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Liu et al. Rural Landscapes: Society, Environment, History DOI: 10.16993/rl.100 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Stavrianos, L. S. (2005). A global history: From prehistory to the <lb/>21st century (7th ed.). Peking University Press. <lb/>Stearns, S. G. (2011). Streams of interest: The Mississippi River <lb/>and the political economy of the Early Republic, 1783-1803. <lb/>The University of Chicago. <lb/>Tamburrino, A. (1970). Water technology in ancient <lb/>Mesopotamia. Springer Netherlands. <lb/>Tan, Q. (1982). The historical atlas of China. SinoMaps Press. <lb/>Uehlinger, U., Arndt, H., Wantzen, K. M., &amp; Leuven, R. S. (2009). <lb/>Chapter 6 -The Rhine River Basin. Rivers of Europe, 199-245. <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-369449-2.00006-0 <lb/>Ur, J. (2014). Households and the emergence of cities in <lb/>ancient Mesopotamia. Cambridge Archaeological Journal, <lb/>24(02, June), 249-268. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1017/ <lb/>S095977431400047X <lb/>Wang, F. (2006). Quantitative methods and applications based <lb/>on GIS. CRC Press. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1201/978142000 <lb/>4281 <lb/>Wang, J. (2012). Study on the characteristics and formation <lb/>mechanism of groundwater chemical composition in the <lb/>Yellow River Delta. Ocean University of China. <lb/>Wang, S. (2019). The history of world agricultural civilization. <lb/>China Agricultural Press. <lb/>Wei, J., Cheng, W., Wang, Y., Di, W., &amp; Xiong, Y. (2022). Spatial <lb/>distribution characteristics and influencing factors of rural <lb/>settlements in Bazhong City. Research of Soil and Water <lb/>Conservation, 29(04), 285-291. <lb/>Wells, H. G., &amp; Postgate, R. (2010). The outline of history. World <lb/>Book Inc. <lb/>Wilson, P. (2015). Baltim, Parallos and Mutubis: Late Period <lb/>and Ptolemaic antecedents for Late antique ports and <lb/>settlements in northern Egypt. Oxford Centre for Maritime <lb/>Archaeology. <lb/>Xiang, Q., Yu, H., Kan, A., Huang, H., &amp; He, J. (2023). The <lb/>influence characteristics of river system on the distribution <lb/>of rural settlements in Hengduan Mountains-Taking the <lb/>upper reaches of Minjiang River as an example. Resources <lb/>and Environment in the Yangtze Basin, 32(07), 1510-1520. <lb/>Xie, X., Gan, S., Yu, L., Ren, P., &amp; Chen, Y. (2013). Spatial pattern <lb/>analysis of rural settlements in Karst Mountains: An <lb/>example from Guangnan. Earth Science-Journal of China <lb/>University of Geosciences, 38(S1), 183-190. <lb/>Yan, N. (2010). Study on population of Shandong counties in <lb/>Qing Dynasty. Qufu Normal University. <lb/>Yu, J., Li, Y., Han, G., Zhou, D., Fu, Y., Guan, B., Wang, G., Ning, <lb/>K.; Wu, H., &amp; Wang, J. (2014). The spatial distribution <lb/>characteristics of soil salinity in coastal zone of the Yellow <lb/>River Delta. Environmental Earth Science, 72, 589-599. DOI: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s12665-013-2980-0 <lb/>Zeng, H. Z., Zhang, C., &amp; Zhao, M. (2020). The research on site <lb/>selection and morphological characteristics of traditional <lb/>settlements under the influence of water of Yuanshui River <lb/>in Hunan. Modern Urban Research, 2020(03), 54-59. DOI: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3969/j.issn.1009-6000.2004.01.006 <lb/>Zhang, K. Z. (2001). Chinese history. Higher Education Press. <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1004151226395 <lb/>Zhang, S. (2019). Interaction between natural disasters and <lb/>migration: A case study of the Yellow River Delta and Luxi <lb/>Region from 1930 to 1937. Guangxi Normal University. <lb/>Zhang, T., Zeng, S., Gao, Y., Ouyang, Z., Li, B., Fang, C., &amp; Zhao, B. <lb/>(2011). Assessing impact of land uses on land salinization in <lb/>the Yellow River Delta, China using an integrated and spatial <lb/>statistical model. Land Use Policy, 28(4), 857-866. DOI: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landusepol.2011.03.002 <lb/>Zhanhua County Chronicle. (1935). 24 years of the Republic of <lb/>China, Volume 6, Construction Annals. <lb/>Zhanhua County Records. (1935). 24 years of the Republic of <lb/>China, Volume 1, Territory Records. <lb/>Zhao, Y. Y. (2018). The reacher of primitive agricultural types <lb/>and early Chinese civilization. Northwest A&amp;F University. <lb/>Zhu, C., Zhang, Q., Zhang, Y., Zhang, Z., &amp; Shen, M. (2003). <lb/>Relationship between human and nature in the north <lb/>part of the Yangtze Delta since the Holocene. Scientia <lb/>Geographica Sinica, 2003(06), 705-712. <lb/>Zou, Y., Zhang, X., &amp; Wang, S. (2013). Historical and physical <lb/>geography of China. Science Press. <lb/></listBibl>

			<front>TO CITE THIS ARTICLE: <lb/>Liu, Y., Ye, Y., Jiang, C., Jiang, J., Wang, F., Li, J., &amp; Zhang, X. (2024). Dynamics of Rural Settlement Patterns in the Yellow River Delta in <lb/>Response to River Diversion and Avulsion Since 1855. Rural Landscapes: Society, Environment, History, 11(1): 2, 1-15. DOI: https://doi. <lb/>org/10.16993/rl.100 <lb/>Submitted: 14 June 2023 Accepted: 26 June 2024 Published: 16 July 2024 <lb/>COPYRIGHT: <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 <lb/>International License (CC-BY 4.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. <lb/>Rural Landscapes: Society, Environment, History is a peer-reviewed open access journal published by Stockholm University Press. </front>


	</text>
</tei>
