<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Heliyon 10 (2024) e27580 <lb/>Available online 4 March 2024 <lb/>2405-8440/© 2024 The Authors. <lb/>Published by Elsevier Ltd. <lb/>This is an open access article under the CC BY license <lb/>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/>Research article <lb/>Preparation and performance of alumina/epoxy-siloxane <lb/>composites: A comparative study on thermal-and <lb/>photo-curing process <lb/>Chan Soo Kim a,b,1 , Junho Jang a, 1 , Hyeon-Gyun Im a , Seogyoung Yoon b,** , Dong <lb/>Jun Kang a, * <lb/>a Insulation Materials Research Center, Electrical Materials Research Division, Korea Electrotechnology Research Institute (KERI), Changwon-si, <lb/>51543, Republic of Korea <lb/>b School of Materials Science and Engineering, Pusan National University, Busan, 46241, Republic of Korea <lb/>A R T I C L E I N F O <lb/>Keywords: <lb/>Epoxy-siloxane composites <lb/>Alumina particle <lb/>Thermal conductivity <lb/>Electronic packaging <lb/>A B S T R A C T <lb/>Although epoxy-based composites that consist of inorganic fillers and matrixes are widely used in <lb/>&quot;conventional&quot; electronic packaging applications due to their excellent insulation and robust <lb/>properties, they limit their uses in &quot;advanced electronic packaging&quot; which requires enhanced <lb/>thermal conductivity. However, conventional thermal curing methods for fabrication of epoxy-<lb/>based composites do not fulfill sufficient thermal conductivity. Herein, we apply photo-induced <lb/>curing strategy for fabricating alumina-incorporated epoxy-siloxane composites that consist of <lb/>sol-gel derived siloxane matrix and bimodal sized alumina particles as a thermally conductive <lb/>filler. We investigate how curing mechanism (thermal-or UV-curing) and varying the ratios of the <lb/>alumina particles of two different sizes affect the various physical properties. It is found that <lb/>photo-curing process makes greatly enhanced thermal conductivity, low thermal expansion, and <lb/>high mechanical robustness compared to thermally-cured composites. As the results, we can <lb/>achieve significantly enhanced thermal conductivity (&gt;11 W/m K) with high thermal stability <lb/>and mechanical robustness. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>Epoxy-based polymeric materials have been extensively applied to a wide range of fields, for example paints, coatings, adhesives, <lb/>aerospace industry and electronics materials because of their high mechanical properties, good thermal/chemical resistances, and high <lb/>adhesiveness to versatile substrates [1-3]. Although they are widely used as electronics packaging materials, the properties of con-<lb/>ventional epoxy-based materials (e.g., bisphenol A type diglycidyl ether) do not meet the requirements of advanced electronics ma-<lb/>terials, which include high thermal conductivity, stability, mechanical properties, and electrical performance [4-6]. A high thermal <lb/>conductivity is critical for decreasing internal overheating, which can generate cracks or deformations in the microlevel structure of <lb/>high-efficiency electronics devices [7]. These cracks and deformations can cause system failures, human health and safety problems, <lb/></body>

			<front>* Corresponding author. <lb/>** Corresponding author. <lb/>E-mail addresses: syy3@pusan.ac.kr (S. Yoon), kangdj@keri.re.kr (D.J. Kang). <lb/>1 These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect <lb/>Heliyon <lb/>journal homepage: www.cell.com/heliyon <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e27580 <lb/>Received 25 February 2024; Accepted 1 March 2024 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Heliyon 10 (2024) e27580 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>and assembly loss in the electronics components [8,9]. <lb/>Incorporating filler materials with high thermal conductivity into an epoxy-based polymeric matrix to form composites is an <lb/>effective method to improve thermal performance in cases where the thermal conductivity of epoxy-based materials is too low for <lb/>removing the heat generated by electronics devices. Typical thermally conductive filler materials include metallic, ceramic particles, <lb/>and carbon-based materials (e.g., carbon nanotubes and graphene) [7,8,10,11]. Among various thermally conductive fillers, alumina <lb/>particles (APs) have utilized as filler materials for the thermal management of electronics because of their high thermal conductivity <lb/>(30 W/m K), and cost effectiveness [10,12-15]. However, the traditional strategy for fabricating AP-incorporated epoxy-based <lb/>composites limits to enhancing the thermal performance of composites because of the issues of the uniform distribution of AP in <lb/>matrix. Moreover, conventional epoxy-based polymeric materials show low thermal stability and other physical properties, which <lb/>hinder uses in advanced electronic devices [5]. <lb/>Improving thermal conductivity of composites consisting of inorganic fillers and polymer matrices can be achieved by percolation <lb/>of inorganic fillers; the effective thermal pathway that can be generated by proper contact of inorganic fillers makes enhanced thermal <lb/>conductivity of the composites. Thus, uniform distribution of inorganic fillers in the composites is crucial for effective percolation; <lb/>aggregated and/or isolated fillers cannot contribute to the thermal pathway. To attain uniform dispersion of inorganic fillers, optimal <lb/>fabrication methods can be considered because typical fabrication methods of composites suffer from sedimentation of inorganic fillers <lb/>which may hinder thermal percolation while curing process of organic matrices. Thus, preventing particle&apos;s sedimentation should be <lb/>guaranteed while fabrication process. <lb/>Photo-curing process by ultraviolet (UV) irradiation (UV-curing) is often used for fabricating various composites due to its fast <lb/>curing time and low shrinkage [16,17]. Photo-cured composites can ensure uniform composite structure compared to thermal cured; <lb/>inorganic fillers can be uniformly distributed due to UV-induced fast curing of organic matrices, so particle&apos;s sedimentation can be <lb/>prevented. For fabricating electronic packaging composites, however, photo-curing has been rarely utilized because typical <lb/>epoxy-based polymer matrices in electronic packaging require sufficient thermal energies to be completely cured. <lb/>Organic-inorganic siloxane hybrid materials derived from sol-gel hydrolysis and condensation have been utilized widely in the past <lb/>few decades because of their various advantages including high optical properties and excellent thermo-mechanical characteristics <lb/>[16,18,19]. Given these high performances, siloxane hybrid materials have been used in a wide range of applications, for example, <lb/>flexible substrates [20], functional coatings [21], encapsulation of nanocrystals [22,23], dielectrics [24], and electronics packaging [3, <lb/>5]. In particular, thermal stability of siloxane hybrid materials is considerably higher than that of conventional polymers containing <lb/>epoxy-based materials because they have robust inorganic siloxane networks (composed of Si-O-Si bonds) that have a higher bond <lb/>energy than the carbon bond (bond energy: Si-O = 452 kJ/mol, and C-C = 346 kJ/mol) [25]. Furthermore, other physicochemical <lb/>properties, such as chemical inertness and mechanical durability, can also be obtained with thermal stability. In addition, some <lb/>organo-siloxane matrices, such as cycloaliphatic epoxy-based siloxane, can be applied to UV-curing process [17]. <lb/>Based on the above considerations, we developed UV-curable and robust alumina-incorporated cycloaliphatic epoxy-based com-<lb/>posites (AP-EPSH) with superior thermal conductivity (&gt;11 W/m K) for electronic packaging. The composites consist of bimodal sized <lb/>micro-alumina particles (APs) (average size of 2 μm (SAP) and 45 μm (LAP)) with fillers and UV-curable cycloaliphatic-epoxy-siloxane <lb/>(EPSH) matrix with high thermal stability. For uniform distribution of the AP fillers in the composites, the size and composition of AP <lb/>fillers are optimized based on the theoretical packing density rule. For robustness and photo-curability of the composites, <lb/>cycloaliphatic-epoxy-siloxane matrix is utilized owing to its capability of cationic curing. We investigated the changes in thermal, <lb/>mechanical, and electrical performances by varying size and composition of bimodal sized APs in the siloxane matrix. In addition, <lb/>different curing mechanisms (UV-and thermal-curing) are implemented for fabrication of the composites to assess the effects on <lb/>subsequent thermal, mechanical, and electrical properties. <lb/>2. Materials and methods <lb/>2.1. Materials <lb/>Diphenylsilanediol (DPSD, Gelest, USA), 2-(3,4-epoxycyclohexyl)ethyltrimethoxysilane (ECTS, Gelest, U.S.A.), 3-ethyl-3 [(3-<lb/>ethyloxetane-3-yl)methoxy]methyl oxetane (DOX, Toagosei, Japan), APs (SAP and LAP) (AnHui Estone Material Technology Co., <lb/>Ltd., China), triarylsulfonium hexafluoroantimonate salt (Sigma-Aldrich, U.S.A.), 2-methylimidazole (Sigma Aldrich, USA), and <lb/>barium hydroxide monohydrate (Ba(OH) 2 ⋅H 2 O, Sigma Aldrich, USA) were used without any further purification. <lb/>2.2. Synthesis of cycloaliphatic epoxy-phenyl-based siloxane hybrid resin (EPSR) <lb/>A Cycloaliphatic epoxy-phenyl siloxane matrix resin (EPSR) was synthesized by a nonhydrolytic sol-gel condensation reaction <lb/>following previously reported methods [5,16]. ECTS and DPSD (molar ratio of 1:1) were blended in a two-neck flask using a magnetic <lb/>(or mechanical) stirrer for a few minutes. Next, 0.2 mol% Ba(OH) 2 ⋅H 2 O of total silane precursors was added to promote a <lb/>base-catalyzed sol-gel reaction between the ECTS and DPSD. The blended solution was mixed at 80 • C under nitrogen purging for a few <lb/>hours. After mixing, a viscous siloxane resin was obtained. <lb/>2.3. Fabrication of alumina-incorporated epoxy-based siloxane composites (AP-EPSH) <lb/>The DOX as an epoxy crosslinker was added to EPSR at a 2:3 M ratio of the epoxy molecule. Triarylsulfonium hexafluoroantimonate <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">C.S. Kim et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e27580 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>salt (for UV-curing) or 2-methylimidazole (for thermal-curing) was added to induce the epoxy ring-opening polymerization at 1 wt% of <lb/>total resin content. Further, APs (SAP and LAP) were added to the mixed resin at a certain concentration (90% of matrix) (the ratio of <lb/>SAP to LAP is varied from 0:10 to 10:0). The final mixed resin was exposed to UV-lamp (240 mJ/s, 10 min) for UV-curing or was stored <lb/>at 120 • C for 5 h for thermal-curing to obtain the cured product (UV-or thermal-cured AP-EPSH) was obtained. <lb/>2.4. Characterization <lb/>Thermal properties were examined by thermogravimetric analysis (TGA, Q50, TA Instruments, Inc.) at a heating rate of 10 • C/min <lb/>under N 2 atmosphere. Thermomechanical properties were measured by thermomechanical analysis (TMA, EXTAR TMA/SS 6100, <lb/>Seiko Instrument, Inc.) at a heating rate of 10 • C/min. Fourier-transform infrared (FT-IR) spectra were recorded with on an FT-IR 680 <lb/>plus instrument (JASCO, U.S.A.). 29 Si nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectra were obtained using a DMX600 FT 600-MHz <lb/>spectrometer (Bruker Biospin, Australia). Mechanical properties were measured using a universal testing machine (AGS-X STD, Shi-<lb/>madzu, Japan). The dielectric properties of the composites (at 5 Hz) were measured using a microdielectrometer (AET, Japan). The <lb/>surface resistivity of the composites was obtained using an electrometer (6517 B, Keithley, USA) and a resistivity test fixture (8009, <lb/>Keithley, USA). The breakdown strengths of the composites were recorded using a breakdown strength tester (SKY-HAV-1010, SKY <lb/>Innotek, Republic of Korea). The thermal conductivity was determined using a thermal conductivity analyzer (LAF 6720, C-Therm <lb/>Technologies, Canada). The SEM images were obtained using scanning electron microscopy (S-4800, Hitachi, Japan) <lb/>3. Results and discussion <lb/>3.1. Fabrication of AP-incorporated epoxy-based siloxane composites <lb/>Fig. 1a presents the procedure for synthesizing cycloaliphatic epoxy-phenyl-based siloxane hybrid resin (EPSR) via a non-<lb/>hydrolytic sol-gel reaction between the methoxy group of ECTS and the hydroxyl group of DPSD. Unlike a conventional hydrolytic <lb/>sol-gel reaction, non-hydrolytic sol-gel reactions do not require water for hydrolysis of silane precursors prior to condensation; <lb/>however, siloxane networks can be formed because of the existence of the hydroxyl group (silanol) in DPSD [26]. The FT-IR spectra <lb/>(Fig. 1b) shows that the band corresponding to the stretching of the siloxane bond (Si-O-Si) at 1100-1100 cm -1 is considerably <lb/>broadened after the non-hydrolytic sol-gel reaction, indicating the successful formation of siloxane networks, which can be further <lb/>Fig. 1. a) Synthesis scheme of EPSR and b) comparison of FT-IR spectra before (ECTS, DPSD and mixture) and after sol-gel reaction. c) Fabrication <lb/>scheme of AP-EPSH and d) comparison of FT-IR spectra before and after thermal curing. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">C.S. Kim et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e27580 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>confirmed by comparing FT-IR spectra of ECTS, DPSD and EPSR. In addition, the organic groups present in the two types of silane <lb/>precursors (epoxy group peak at 882 cm -1 ; and phenyl group peak at 1430 cm -1 ) remained after the sol-gel reaction, indicating that <lb/>they did not decompose during the non-hydrolytic sol-gel reaction. In the sol-gel reaction between ECTS and DPSD, there are two <lb/>reactive functional groups to form siloxane networks in which three methoxy groups and two hydroxyl groups present in ECTS and <lb/>DPSD, respectively, thereby randomly formed siloxane bonds with branched structure can be generated. These can be confirmed in <lb/>FT-IR spectra, where the absorbance intensity at the peak region in 1000-1100 cm -1 is much broaden and no distinct peaks in the <lb/>siloxane bond region. Moreover, synthesized EPSR showed a high degree of siloxane bond formation (~85%) that can be observed in <lb/>the 29 Si-NMR results, supporting the random and branched siloxane bond formation (Fig. S1). <lb/>Using EPSR, we fabricated AP-incorporated siloxane hybrid-based composites (AP-EPSH) by combining LAPs and SAPs (Fig. 1c) <lb/>having average sizes of 2 and 45 μm, respectively (Fig. S2). The weight ratio of AP to EPSH is 90:10. Keeping the total weight con-<lb/>centration of AP constant, we changed the ratio of LAP to SAP (from 0:10 to 10:0). For complete epoxy curing, the di-oxetane monomer <lb/>(DOX) that acts as an epoxy crosslinker as well as a hardener, was used as the curing agent. Subsequently, after mixing crosslinker <lb/>(DOX) and bimodal sized APs (LAP and SAP) with the matrix, AP-EPSH was fabricated via thermal-or UV-induced cationic epoxy ring-<lb/>opening polymerization [5,16]. In this process, there are two chemical crosslinking reaction: (I) a chemical reaction between <lb/>epoxy-functional groups in siloxane matrix and (II) a chemical reaction between epoxy-functional group in siloxane matrix and <lb/>oxetane group in DOX. These two chemical crosslinking reactions induce the formation of alumina/epoxy-based siloxane composites <lb/>Fig. 2. (Revised). Cross-sectional SEM images of a) thermal-and b) UV-cured AP-EPSH according to changing the ratio of LAP to SAP. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">C.S. Kim et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e27580 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>with rigid and high crosslinking density [5,22,25]. Fig. 1d presents the FT-IR spectra before and after the thermal-and UV-induced <lb/>epoxy curing process; the peaks correspond to the epoxy ring at 882 cm -1 was removed completely, indicating that APs did not <lb/>interrupt the epoxy ring-opening process. Therefore, we fabricated successfully cured AP (with two different size)-incorporated <lb/>cycloaliphatic epoxy-phenyl-based siloxane composites. <lb/>3.2. Morphology and packing density of AP-EPSH <lb/>The photographs of AP-EPSH for different ratios of SAP to LAP are shown in Fig. S3, which shows the increased optical haze causes <lb/>by APs incorporation. Fig. 2 shows cross-sectional SEM images of thermal-cured (Fig. 2a) and UV-cured (Fig. 2b) AP-EPSH by varying <lb/>the ratio of LAP to SAP, in which all samples according to two different curing mechanism and varying the ratio of LAP to SAP exhibited <lb/>distribution of APs surrounded by the EPSH matrix was confirmed. Especially, UV-cured composites showed more homogeneous <lb/>distribution of APs in EPSH matrix than that of thermal-cured samples. <lb/>Before the investigation of various physical properties, we confirmed the packing density of composites with two different sized <lb/>filler particles. In conventional particle packing theories, loosening (large particle dominant case) and wall (small particle dominant <lb/>case) effects are considered to obtain the theoretical calculation values of the packing density of power, which exhibit highly reliable <lb/>prediction [27-32]. The packing density of powder after mixture can be expressed by <lb/>ρ = <lb/>∑ n <lb/>i=1 <lb/>∅ i (i = 1 for small particle, and 2 for large particle) <lb/>(1) <lb/>where ρ and φ i represent the packing density using two different size particles and partial volume fraction of given particles (small or <lb/>large particles), respectively. The fractions of large or small particles are denoted by <lb/>ω i = <lb/>∅ i <lb/>ρ <lb/>, <lb/>(2) <lb/>∑ n <lb/>i=1 <lb/>ω i = 1. <lb/>(3) <lb/>When small particles in the matrix are dominant, the space occupied by large particles can be defined as φ 2 ; therefore, the space <lb/>occupied by small particles is 1 -φ 2 . If there are no interactions between large and small particles, ρ is expressed by <lb/>ρ = ∅ 2 + α(1 -∅ 2 ), <lb/>(4) <lb/>where α represents the packing density of both particles. When small particles in the matrix are dominant, the ρ of power (denoted by <lb/>ρ 1 ) considering the wall effect is obtained by [29]: <lb/>ρ 1 = α 1 + (1 -α 1 )g∅ 2 , <lb/>(5) <lb/>where g represents the wall effect related to the constant determined by g = 1 -r 1 /r 2 , and α 1 represents the packing density of small <lb/>particles [29]. When r 1 /r 2 is closed to zero, small particles are too small to consider the wall effect. To make Eqs. (4) and (5) consistent, <lb/>g equals to 1. When the size of large particles is the same with that of small particles (i.e., r 1 /r 2 = 1), ρ 1 is equal to α 1 because only small <lb/>particles are considered, the g value is zero. When large particles in the matrix are dominant, ρ without the interaction is expressed as <lb/>Fig. 3. Changes of packing density of AP-EPSH according to the ratios of LAP to SAP. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">C.S. Kim et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e27580 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>ρ = α 2 + ∅ 1 <lb/>(6) <lb/>where α 2 represent the packing density of large particles. Considering the loosening effect, the ρ of binary particle system (denoted by <lb/>ρ 2 ) can be obtained from [29]: <lb/>ρ 2 = α 2 + f ∅ 1 , <lb/>(7) <lb/>where f represents the loosening effect-related constant. Parameter f is similar to g in which f = 1 when r 1 /r 2 = 0 and f = 0 when r 1 /r 2 = <lb/>1. <lb/>Based on packing theories, we calculated the packing density using the various physical parameters of LAP and SAP (Fig. 3). We <lb/>used specification values from manufacturers and calculated the volumes of two different APs using their average diameters. <lb/>Therefore, the highest packing density of AP-EPSH was obtained when the ratio of LAP to SAP was 8:2. <lb/>3.3. Thermal properties of AP-EPSH <lb/>We investigated changes in the thermal conductivity of AP-EPSH by thermal-and UV-curing processes for different ratios of LAP to <lb/>SAP following the incorporation of AP with a high-thermal conductivity filler (Fig. 4a). By increasing the LAP concentration until 80% <lb/>(LAP:SAP = 8:2), the thermal conductivity of UV-cured AP-EPSH was increased dramatically (from 4.26 to 11.45 W/m K) that is much <lb/>higher than those of thermal-cured composites (from 1.66 to 2.97 W/m K). This is because UV-cured composite retains uniform <lb/>distribution of LAPs and SAPs compared to thermal-cured sample, which induces effective thermal conductive pathways making high <lb/>thermal conductivity. Fig. S4 represents schematic illustration of difference of thermal conduction of between thermal-and UV-cured <lb/>composites. On the other hands, thermal-cured composites have large portion of sedimented particle in matrix because the thermal-<lb/>curing process can cause aggregation and/or agglomeration of particles, which inhibits thermal conduction that cause low thermal <lb/>conductivity. This can be also confirmed by previous cross-sectional SEM images of UV-or thermal-cured AP-EPSH (Fig. 2). The <lb/>thermal conductivity values of all AP-EPSH were higher than that of the previous reported epoxy-based siloxane/silica composites <lb/>because of the higher thermal conductivity of AP than that of silica (AP = 30 W/m K, silica = 12-20 W/m K) [5]. When LAPs were <lb/>Fig. 4. Thermal properties of AP-EPSH according to the ratios of LAP to SAP. a) thermal conductivity, b) coefficient of thermal expansion, TGA <lb/>results of AP-EPSH using c) thermal-curing and d) UV-curing. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">C.S. Kim et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e27580 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>further added in AP-EPSH (i.e., LAP:SAP = 10:0), the thermal conductivity values of UV-and thermal-cured AP-EPSH were reduced <lb/>due to decreasing packing density. Although the decreasing thermal conductivity of composites by further added LAPs, UV-cured <lb/>AP-EPSH still exhibited higher than thermal-cured EPSH. <lb/>We compared the thermomechanical properties of UV-and thermal-cured AP-EPSH by varying the ratio of LAP to SAP (Fig. 4b and <lb/>S5). The coefficient of thermal expansion (CTE) values of AP-EPSH gradually decreased on increasing the LAP portion until the ratio of <lb/>LAP to SAP is 8:2 because of the increasing packing density. The CTE values of UV-and thermal-cured AP-EPSH were increasing when <lb/>LAP was added to 100%, caused by decreasing the packing density. All CTE values of UV-cured AP-EPSH according to varying the ratio <lb/>of LAP to SAP were higher than those of thermal-cured samples because UV-curing process induces uniform distribution of APs making <lb/>effective preventing thermal expansion of composites. We investigated thermal stability by confirming thermal decomposition <lb/>behavior using TGA, which exhibited high five weight percent loss temperature (T d5wt% ) (~380 • C) and residual weight (~90%) that is <lb/>higher than those of bare siloxane matrix and commercial epoxy-based matrix, which are attributed to robust siloxane matrix and <lb/>highly concentrated inorganic fillers [5] (Fig. 4c and d and Table S1). Therefore, we attributed that incorporating APs induces greatly <lb/>enhanced thermal stability and the packing density affected the thermal expansion property. In addition, UV-cured composites <lb/>exhibited much higher thermal conductivity (&gt;11 W/m K) than that of thermal-cured AP-EPSH (~3 W/m K). <lb/>3.4. Mechanical properties of AP-EPSH <lb/>We conducted tensile tests for investigating the change in the mechanical properties of thermal-and UV-cured AP-EPSH with <lb/>varying the ratio of LAP to SAP (Fig. 5 and S6). In thermal-cured AP-EPSH, with an increase in the concentration of LAP until 80% <lb/>(LAP:SAP = 8:2), the tensile strength value (or facture strength) of AP-EPSH exhibited decreases (from 17.9 MPa to ~10 MPa), while <lb/>elastic modulus of AP-EPSH was gradually increased (from 2.44 GPa to 3.92 GPa) because of mechanical reinforcement by the <lb/>increased packing density and effective reinforcement by small particles (i.e., SAPs) (Fig. 5a and Table 1) [32,33]. The tensile strength <lb/>values increased when LAPs were further increased to 100% (LAP:SAP = 10:0) due to weakening mechanical reinforcement. This can <lb/>be also confirmed by decreased elastic modulus to 3.24 GPa. In case of UV-cured AP-EPSH, tensile strength and elastic modulus were <lb/>significantly increased (tensile strength: from 19.7 MPa to 24.2 MPa; elastic modulus: from 2.99 GPa to 6.30 GPa), which are much <lb/>Fig. 5. Tensile stress and elastic modulus values of a) thermal-cured and b) UV-cured AP-EPSH according to the ratios of LAP to SAP. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">C.S. Kim et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e27580 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>higher than those of thermal-cured composites because uniform distributed APs by UV-curing processes can make the effective me-<lb/>chanical reinforcement [16] (Fig. 5b). Changes of elongation with varying the ratios of LAP to SAP also exhibited similar trend, which <lb/>are proof of mechanical reinforcement (Fig. S7). Therefore, we can confirm that UV-cured AP-EPSH with uniform distributed APs can <lb/>induce effective mechanical reinforcement compared to thermal-cured AP-EPSH with large sedimented APs. Therefore, we conclude <lb/>that the incorporation of APs with two different sizes enhances the tensile property of composites (i.e., tensile strength and elastic <lb/>modulus) with the decreased elongation. Meanwhile, the UV-cured composites provide effective mechanical reinforcement (i.e., high <lb/>elastic modulus) (Fig. S8). <lb/>3.5. Electrical insulation properties of AP-EPSH <lb/>Electrical insulation properties, such as electrical resistance, breakdown strength, and dielectric properties are crucial factors for <lb/>using the composites as electronic packaging materials. Therefore, we investigated various insulation properties of thermal-and UV-<lb/>cured AP-EPSH with varying ratios of LAP to SAP (Fig. 6). The electrical surface resistivity of thermal-cured AP-EPSH with 100% SAP <lb/>was approximately 10 15 Ω cm, which is relatively lower than that of the previously reported siloxane hybrid matrix and is attributed to <lb/>Table 1 <lb/>Mechanical properties values of thermal-or UV-cured AP-EPSH with varying the ratios of LAP to SAP. <lb/>Methods <lb/>LAP:SAP <lb/>Tensile Strength (MPa) <lb/>Elastic Modulus (GPa) <lb/>Thermal-Curing <lb/>0:10 <lb/>17.9 <lb/>2.44 <lb/>2:8 <lb/>11.3 <lb/>3.42 <lb/>4:6 <lb/>8 <lb/>3.42 <lb/>6:4 <lb/>9.2 <lb/>3.70 <lb/>8:2 <lb/>10.5 <lb/>3.92 <lb/>10:0 <lb/>15.3 <lb/>3.24 <lb/>UV-Curing <lb/>0:10 <lb/>19.7 <lb/>2.99 <lb/>2:8 <lb/>19.7 <lb/>3.10 <lb/>4:6 <lb/>12.1 <lb/>3.42 <lb/>6:4 <lb/>15.8 <lb/>3.51 <lb/>8:2 <lb/>24.2 <lb/>6.30 <lb/>10:0 <lb/>22.3 <lb/>2.60 <lb/>Fig. 6. Electrical properties of thermal-and UV-cured AP-EPSH with varying the ratios of LAP to SAP. a) Surface resistivity, b) breakdown strength, <lb/>and c-d) dielectric constant and dielectric loss. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">C.S. Kim et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e27580 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

            <body>the incorporation of AP with a high concentration in the matrix [5]. By increasing the portion of LAPs, the surface resistivity value (log <lb/>scale) of AP-EPSH was continuously decreased (from 10 14 Ω cm (logscale value: 14.4) to 10 13 Ω cm (logscale value: 13.6) until the 80% <lb/>incorporation of LAP (LAP:SAP = 8:2) caused by the increasing packing density in matrix (Fig. 6a). However, this value increased when <lb/>only LAPs were added in siloxane hybrid matrix (100% of LAP), and it can be attributed to physical disconnection between LAPs with <lb/>inserted SAPs, causing reduction of electrical conducting pathways. In case of UV-cured AP-EPSH, although similar behavior were able <lb/>to be observed, all values were lower than those of thermal-cured AP-EPSH (from 10 14 Ω cm (logscale value: 14.3) (LAP:SAP = 0:10) to <lb/>10 12 Ω cm (logscale value: 12.6) (LAP:SAP = 8:2)), which is same reason in previous explained. The electrical breakdown strength <lb/>values of thermal-cured AP-EPSH were increased continuously (from 10.88 kV/mm to 23.22 kV/mm) with the increasing portion of <lb/>LAP until 80% incorporation of LAP (LAP:SAP = 8:2) (Fig. 6b). Alumina has a relatively low dielectric breakdown strength compared <lb/>to that of siloxane-based hybrid matrix [34]. We can improve the breakdown strength of AP by combining it with the siloxane hybrid <lb/>matrix. The breakdown strength of thermal-cured AP-EPSH was significantly decreased to 5.29 kV/mm, which is lower than that of <lb/>AP-EPSH with 100% of SAP when LAPs were further added. This is due to dense particle accumulation by SAPs. For UV-cured <lb/>AP-EPSH, the relatively higher breakdown strength values could be confirmed (from 16.2 kV/mm to 30.68 kV/mm); this indicate <lb/>that the UV-cured siloxane-based matrix makes the effectively enhanced electrical breakdown strength of APs because of effective <lb/>surrounding of APs with matrix. In addition, the stronger bond energy of the siloxane-based backbone in GPSH than that of the single <lb/>carbon bond-based backbone in conventional polymers can be also effectively improved the breakdown strength [25,35]. Dielectric <lb/>constant values of thermal-cured AP-EPSH were increased continuously (from 5.02 to 6.34) until 80% incorporation of LAP because of <lb/>the high packing characteristics of composite with a high dielectric constant and the generation of continuous interconnection by SAPs <lb/>(Fig. 6c). The dielectric loss property of thermal-cured AP-EPSH exhibited a similar trend to the dielectric constant results (from 0.009 <lb/>to 0.013), which is attributed to the low dielectric loss property of alumina. The dielectric properties of AP-EPSH with 100% of SAP <lb/>were similar to those of AP-EPSH with 100% of LAP because of the existence of high free volumes that can reduce the dielectric <lb/>constant and relatively lower packing density than the other samples (AP-EPSH (LAP 100%): 5.02/0.009 and AP-EPSH (SAP 100%): <lb/>5.10/0.012) [33]. Although a similar tendency of UV-cured AP-EPSH was also shown in which increased dielectric constant until 80% <lb/>(from 5.91 to 6.14) and re-decreased after 100% of LAP was added, the effect by APs was higher than that of thermal-cured AP-EPSH <lb/>(Fig. 6d); higher dielectric constant and lower dielectric loss. This indicates uniform distribution and compact surrounding of APs by <lb/>matrix, which can lead to increase dielectric constant and decrease dielectric loss (Fig. S9). <lb/>By combining various experimental results and packing theory, we concluded that reinforcement with APs of two different sizes <lb/>increase packing density (especially, at a LAP-to-SAP ratio of 8:2); this greatly enhances the mechanical and thermal properties. <lb/>However, these induce low surface resistivity and high dielectric constant because of the electrical properties of APs. Furthermore, we <lb/>found that UV-curing process makes uniform distribution of APs and effective reinforcement compared to thermal-curing process, <lb/>which significantly improved various properties. Our approach for fabricating particle-based composites has a great potential for <lb/>future application to electronics packaging and various insulation materials that require high thermal conductivity and mechanical <lb/>robustness. <lb/>4. Conclusion <lb/>In conclusion, we developed AP-incorporated cycloaliphatic epoxy-phenyl-based siloxane hybrid composite (AP-EPSH) to obtain <lb/>high thermal, mechanical, and insulation properties. The sol-gel derived siloxane hybrid matrix with highly condensed robust inor-<lb/>ganic networks was employed. To maximize the packing density of AP-EPSH, bimodal sized APs with high thermal conductivity were <lb/>introduced. We investigated the effect on the various physical properties of AP-EPSH according to curing mechanism (thermal-or UV-<lb/>curing) and varying the ratio of LAP and SAP. The greatly improved thermal conductivity with high thermal stability, enhanced <lb/>mechanical robustness (i.e., increased elastic modulus and decreased elongation) by incorporating bimodal sized APs in the siloxane <lb/>hybrid matrix were obtained, while increased the dielectric properties (dielectric constant and dielectric loss) and decreased the <lb/>surface resistivity were able to be confirmed. The experimental results indicated that all property changes were maximized when the <lb/>ratio of LAP to SAP was 8:2 because of the packing density of AP-EPSH was the highest among the other ratios. This can be explained <lb/>via calculations using the packing theory of composite with two different size filler particles. Furthermore, UV-curing process exhibited <lb/>more effective than thermal-curing process, which is induced by uniform distribution without sedimented and aggregation APs. <lb/>Following these, we obtained superior thermal conductivity (&gt;11 W/m K), high mechanical strength (tensile strength = 24.2 MPa, <lb/>elastic modulus = 6.30 GPa), electrical breakdown strength (30.68 kV/mm), and enhanced thermal stability (T d5wt% = 380 • C, with <lb/>90% residual weight after test and CTE = 20.23 ppm/K) by using UV-curing process. Therefore, we achieved the trade-off charac-<lb/>teristics of high thermal conductivity with high electrical insulation properties by optimizing composition of composites with high <lb/>packing density. We expect that our approach for fabricating AP-based composite has a significant potential toward high-performance <lb/>electrical packaging and insulation materials that require high thermal conductivity and thermal/mechanical robustness. <lb/></body>

            <div type="contribution">CRediT authorship contribution statement <lb/>Chan Soo Kim: Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Validation. Junho Jang: Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal <lb/>analysis, Investigation, Validation, Visualization, Writing -original draft, Writing -review &amp; editing. Hyeon-Gyun Im: Formal <lb/>analysis, Investigation, Validation, Visualization, Writing -review &amp; editing. Seogyoung Yoon: Funding acquisition, Project <lb/>administration, Supervision, Validation, Writing -review &amp; editing. Dong Jun Kang: Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Funding <lb/>acquisition, Project administration, Supervision, Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">C.S. Kim et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e27580 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<div type="conflict">Declaration of competing interest <lb/>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to <lb/>influence the work reported in this paper. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>This work was supported by the Primary Research Program (24A01021) of the Korea Electrotechnology Research Institute and by <lb/>the National Research Council of Science and Technology (22A02180). This work also supported by the National Research Foundation <lb/>of Korea (NRF) grant by the Korean Government (MSIT) (NRF-2021M3D1A2049846). J. Jang thankfully acknowledges financial <lb/>support by the Sejong Science Fellowship grant by the Korean Government (MSIT) (NRF-2022R1C1C2003017). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Appendix A. Supplementary data <lb/>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e27580. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] F.L. Jin, X. Li, S.J. Park, Synthesis and application of epoxy resins: a review, J. Ind. Eng. Chem. 29 (2015) 1-11. <lb/>[2] V.H. Pham, Y.W. Ha, S.H. Kim, H.T. Jeong, M.Y. Jung, B.S. Ko, Y.J. Hwang, J.S. Chung, Synthesis of epoxy encapsulated organoclay nanocomposite latex via <lb/>phase inversion emulsification and its gas barrier property, J. Ind. Eng. Chem. 20 (2014) 108-112. <lb/>[3] H. Oh, Y. Kim, J. Wie, K. Kim, J. Kim, Tailoring of si-c-n-o ceramic-coated reduced graphene oxide by oil/water-solution process for high thermal conductive <lb/>epoxy composite with electrical insulation, Compos. Sci. Technol. 197 (2020) 108257. <lb/>[4] T. Na, H. Jiang, X. Liu, C. Zhao, Preparation and properties of novel fluorinated epoxy resins cured with 4-trifluoromethyl phenylbenzimidazole for application <lb/>in electronic materials, Eur. Polym. J. 100 (2018) 96-102. <lb/>[5] B.H. Jin, J. Jang, D.J. Kang, S. Yoon, H.-G. Im, Epoxy-based siloxane composites for electronic packaging: effect of composition and molecular structure of <lb/>siloxane matrix on their properties, Compos. Sci. Technol. 224 (2022) 109456. <lb/>[6] Y.J. Wan, G. Li, Y.M. Yao, X.L. Zeng, P.L. Zhu, R. Sun, Recent advances in polymer-based electronic packaging materials, Compos. Commun. 19 (2020) 154-167. <lb/>[7] M.A. Alim, M.Z. Abdullah, M.S.A. Aziz, R. Kamarudin, P. Gunnasegaran, Recent advances on thermally conductive adhesive in electronic packaging: a review, <lb/>Polymers 13 (2021) 3337. <lb/>[8] A.A. Almubarak, The effects of heat on electronic components, Int. J. Eng. Res. Afr. 7 (2017) 52-57. <lb/>[9] X. Xu, J. Chen, J. Zhou, B. Li, Thermal conductivity of polymers and their nanocomposites, Adv. Mater. 30 (2018) 1705544. <lb/>[10] A. Dorigato, A. Pegoretti, The role of alumina nanoparticles in epoxy adhesives, J. Nanoparticle Res. 13 (2011) 2429-2441. <lb/>[11] T. Jiang, Y. Wang, K. Xu, L. Xiang, B. Tang, S. Shi, X. Wu, W. Li, K. Sun, R. Fan, J. Yu, Highly thermally conductive and negative permittivity epoxy composites <lb/>by constructing the carbon fiber/carbon networks, Compos. Commun. 39 (2023) 101560. <lb/>[12] J. Wu, Y. Zhang, Y. Gong, K. Wang, Y. Chen, X. Song, J. Lin, B. Shen, S. He, X. Bian, Analysis of the electrical and thermal properties for magnetic fe3o4-coated <lb/>sic-filled epoxy composites, Polymers 13 (2021) 3028. <lb/>[13] M. Mora, H. Amaveda, L. Porta-Velilla, G.F. de la Fuente, E. Martínez, L.A. Angurel, Improved copper-epoxy adhesion by laser micro-and nano-structuring of <lb/>copper surface for thermal applications, Polymers 13 (2021) 1721. <lb/>[14] K. Naresh, K.A. Khan, R. Umer, Experimental characterization and modeling multifunctional properties of epoxy/graphene oxide nanocomposites, Polymers 13 <lb/>(2021) 2831. <lb/>[15] L. Sim, C. Lee, S. Ramanan, H. Ismail, K. Seetharamu, Cure characteristics, mechanical and thermal properties of al2o3 and zno reinforced silicone rubber, <lb/>Polym.-Plast. Technol. Eng. 45 (2006) 301-307. <lb/>[16] J. Jang, H.-G. Im, D. Lim, B.-S. Bae, Preparation of high-performance transparent glass-fiber reinforced composites based on refractive index-tunable epoxy-<lb/>functionalized siloxane hybrid matrix, Compos. Sci. Technol. 201 (2021) 108527. <lb/>[17] S. Yang, J. Jin, S.Y. Kwak, B.S. Bae, Photocurable transparent cycloaliphatic epoxy hybrid materials crosslinked by oxetane, J. Appl. Polym. Sci. 126 (2012) <lb/>E380-E386. <lb/>[18] Y.-W. Lim, J. Jin, B.-S. Bae, Optically transparent multiscale composite films for flexible and wearable electronics, Adv. Mater. (2020) 1907143. <lb/>[19] M. Sheng, J. Yu, H. Gong, Y. Zhang, Y. Wang, Enhancing the thermal stability and mechanical properties of phenyl silicone rubbers by controlling bn addition <lb/>and phenyl content, Compos. Commun. 35 (2022) 101340. <lb/>[20] Y. Lee, H. Lee, H.-G. Im, W. Jo, G.-M. Choi, T.-S. Kim, J. Jang, B.-S. Bae, Transparent and flexible hybrid cover window film: hard coating/substrate all-in-one <lb/>composite film for reliable foldable display, Composites, Part B 247 (2022) 110336. <lb/>[21] H. Lee, Y. Lee, S.W. Lee, S.-M. Kang, Y.H. Kim, W. Jo, T.-S. Kim, J. Jang, B.-S. Bae, Elongation improvement of transparent and flexible surface protective coating <lb/>using polydimethylsiloxane-anchored epoxy-functionalized siloxane hybrid composite for reliable out-foldable displays, Composites (Part B) (2021) 109313. <lb/>[22] J. Jang, Y.H. Kim, S. Park, D. Yoo, H. Cho, J. Jang, H.B. Jeong, H. Lee, J.M. Yuk, C.B. Park, D.Y. Jeon, Y.-H. Kim, B.-S. Bae, T.-W. Lee, Extremely stable <lb/>luminescent crosslinked perovskite nanoparticles under harsh environments over 1.5 years, Adv. Mater. 33 (2021) 2005255. <lb/>[23] S.K. Kuk, J. Jang, H.J. Han, E. Lee, H. Oh, H.Y. Kim, J. Jang, K.T. Lee, H. Lee, Y.S. Jung, C.B. Park, B.-S. Bae, Siloxane-encapsulated upconversion nanoparticles <lb/>hybrid composite with highly stable photoluminescence against heat and moisture, ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces 11 (2019) 15952-15959. <lb/>[24] F. Mammeri, E. Le Bourhis, L. Rozes, C. Sanchez, Mechanical properties of hybrid organic-inorganic materials, J. Mater. Chem. 15 (2005) 3787-3811. <lb/>[25] H.Y. Kim, D.-E. Yoon, J. Jang, D. Lee, G.-M. Choi, J.H. Chang, J.Y. Lee, D.C. Lee, B.-S. Bae, Quantum dot/siloxane composite film exceptionally stable against <lb/>oxidation under heat and moisture, J. Am. Chem. Soc. 138 (2016) 16478-16485. <lb/>[26] J. Jin, S. Yang, B.-S. Bae, Fabrication of a high thermal-stable methacrylate-silicate hybrid nanocomposite: hydrolytic versus non-hydrolytic sol-gel synthesis of <lb/>methacryl-oligosiloxanes, J. Sol. Gel Sci. Technol. 61 (2012) 321-327. <lb/>[27] A.-B. Yu, R. Zou, N. Standish, Modifying the linear packing model for predicting the porosity of nonspherical particle mixtures, Ind. Eng. Chem. Res. 35 (1996) <lb/>3730-3741. <lb/>[28] P. Goltermann, V. Johansen, L. Palbøl, Packing of aggregates: an alternative tool to determine the optimal aggregate mix, Materials Journal 94 (1997) 435-443. <lb/>[29] T. Stovall, F. De Larrard, M. Buil, Linear packing density model of grain mixtures, Powder Technol. 48 (1986) 1-12. <lb/>[30] M. Jones, L. Zheng, M. Newlands, Comparison of particle packing models for proportioning concrete constitutents for minimum voids ratio, Mater. Struct. 35 <lb/>(2002) 301-309. <lb/>[31] A.K.H. Kwan, K.W. Chan, V. Wong, A 3-parameter particle packing model incorporating the wedging effect, Powder Technol. 237 (2013) 172-179. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">C.S. Kim et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e27580 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[32] X. Ye, Y. Li, Y. Ai, Y. Nie, Novel powder packing theory with bimodal particle size distribution-application in superalloy, Adv. Powder Technol. 29 (2018) <lb/>2280-2287. <lb/>[33] S.-Y. Fu, X.-Q. Feng, B. Lauke, Y.-W. Mai, Effects of particle size, particle/matrix interface adhesion and particle loading on mechanical properties of <lb/>particulate-polymer composites, Composites, Part B 39 (2008) 933-961. <lb/>[34] C. Neusel, H. Jelitto, D. Schmidt, R. Janßen, F. Felten, G.A. Schneider, Dielectric breakdown of alumina single crystals, J. Eur. Ceram. Soc. 32 (2012) <lb/>1053-1057. <lb/>[35] C. Han, H.-G. Im, H.Y. Park, S.-Y. Yoon, D.J. Kang, Fabrication of crystalline silica nanoparticles-embedded nanocomposites and their enhanced mechanical, <lb/>thermal and insulating properties, Ceram. Int. 45 (2019) 16688-16693. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">C.S. Kim et al. </note>


	</text>
</tei>
