<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Social, cultural and political conditions for advancing health equity: examples from eight country case studies (2011–2021)</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Miriam</forename>
            <surname>van den Berg</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Joanne</forename>
            <surname>Flavel</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Ashley</forename>
            <surname>Schram</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Sharon</forename>
            <surname>Friel</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Hailay Abrha</forename>
            <surname>Gesesew</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Fran</forename>
            <surname>Baum</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-28T15:03:23.182274Z">28.10.2025 15:03:23</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1136$1$bmjgh-2024-015694</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>BMJ</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmjgh-2024-015694</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Miriam van den Berg, Joanne Flavel, Ashley Schram, Sharon Friel, Hailay Abrha Gesesew, Fran Baum. (2024). Social, cultural and political conditions for advancing health equity: examples from eight country case studies (2011–2021). BMJ Global Health, 9(Suppl 1), e015694. DOI: 10.1136/bmjgh-2024-015694</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-28T15:03:23.182274Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-28T15:03:23.182274Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>Ambrosio L, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e077978. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077978 <lb/>Open access <lb/>Psychometric properties of the living <lb/>with long term conditions scale in an <lb/>English-speaking population living <lb/>with long term conditions in the UK <lb/>Leire Ambrosio <lb/>, 1,2 Kelly Hislop-Lennie, 3 Nestor Serrano-Fuentes, 1,2 <lb/>Corine Driessens, 2 Mari Carmen Portillo 1,2 <lb/>To cite: Ambrosio L, Hislop-<lb/>Lennie K, Serrano-Fuentes N, <lb/>et al. Psychometric properties <lb/>of the living with long term <lb/>conditions scale in an English-<lb/>speaking population living <lb/>with long term conditions <lb/>in the UK. BMJ Open <lb/>2024;14:e077978. doi:10.1136/ <lb/>bmjopen-2023-077978 <lb/>► Prepublication history and <lb/>additional supplemental material <lb/>for this paper are available <lb/>online. To view these files, <lb/>please visit the journal online <lb/>(http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/ <lb/>bmjopen-2023-077978). <lb/>Received 20 July 2023 <lb/>Accepted 12 December 2023 <lb/>1 <lb/>School of Health Sciences, <lb/>University of Southampton, <lb/>Southampton, UK <lb/>2 <lb/>National Institute for Health <lb/>and Care Research, Applied <lb/>Research Collaboration Wessex, <lb/>Southampton, UK <lb/>3 <lb/>University of Bournemouth, <lb/>Bournemouth, UK <lb/>Correspondence to <lb/>Dr Leire Ambrosio; <lb/>lag1v19@ soton. ac. uk <lb/>Original research <lb/>© Author(s) (or their <lb/>employer(s)) 2024. Re-use <lb/>permitted under CC BY-NC. No <lb/>commercial re-use. See rights <lb/>and permissions. Published by <lb/>BMJ. <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Objective To present the psychometric properties of <lb/>the living with long-term condition (LwLTCs) scale in an <lb/>English-speaking population of people with different LTCs. <lb/>Design An observational and cross-sectional study, with <lb/>retest was conducted. Psychometric properties including <lb/>feasibility, internal consistency, confirmatory factor <lb/>analysis, reproducibility and content validity were tested. <lb/>Setting The study took place across the UK via primary <lb/>care surgeries and voluntary organisations, between <lb/>December 2021 and June 2022. <lb/>Participants The study included 577 patients living with <lb/>different LTCs, as chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, <lb/>arthritis, chronic heart failure, Parkinson&apos;s disease, chronic <lb/>kidney disease and type 2 diabetes mellitus. Inclusion <lb/>criteria included: (a) having been diagnosed with one or <lb/>more of the conditions; (b) being able to read, understand <lb/>and answer written questionnaires; (c) being fluent in <lb/>English and (d) being able to provide written informed <lb/>consent. Patients were involved in the design and pilot <lb/>study of the scale. <lb/>Results A total sample of 577 people with an age <lb/>range of 37-97 years (98±9.65) were recruited. Internal <lb/>consistency of the total 26-item LwLTCs scale score was <lb/>excellent (ordinal alpha=0.90) but confirmatory factor <lb/>analysis showed better fit indices (Normed Fit Index=0.96; <lb/>standardised root mean square residual=0.051; Goodness <lb/>of Fit Index=0.98) for a 20-item LwLTCs scale. <lb/>Conclusions A shorter version of the LwLTCs scale, with <lb/>just 20 items and with excellent psychometric properties, <lb/>is recommended. Having a short scale is key when <lb/>considering the implementation of the scale in clinical <lb/>practice to develop person-centred pathways and more <lb/>comprehensive care plans. <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Approximately 15.4 million people in the UK <lb/>live with one long-term condition (LTC). 1 <lb/>Due to an ageing population and increased <lb/>diagnosis, it is expected to increase to <lb/>18 million by 2025. 1 Currently, the prevalence <lb/>of LTC accounts for 16% of those under 40 <lb/>and 58% of those over 60 years. 2 <lb/>Major contributors to these LTC include <lb/>rheumatoid and osteoarthritis (9.1 million), 3 <lb/>type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) (3.8 million), 4 <lb/>chronic kidney disease (CKD) (3 million), 5 <lb/>chronic obstructive pulmonary disease <lb/>(COPD) (1.2 million), 6 chronic heart failure <lb/>(CHF) (580 000) 7 and Parkinson&apos;s disease <lb/>(PD) (1 27 000 million). 8 With many LTCs <lb/>underdiagnosed, the accurate morbidity rate <lb/>is likely to be somewhat higher. 9 The cost to <lb/>the National Health System is estimated to be <lb/>between £1.4 and £10.2 billion per condition <lb/>per year. 9 <lb/>Living with one or more than one LTCs has <lb/>multiple complex implications, not only due <lb/>to the medical consequences of the condi-<lb/>tions but also to the people&apos;s ability to cope <lb/>with and manage demands of daily living. 10 11 <lb/>Living with multiple LTCs increases mortality <lb/>and reduces quality of life and well-being. 11 12 <lb/>People with LTCs have more difficulties with <lb/>everyday activities, reduced ability to manage <lb/>symptoms effectively and higher risks of <lb/>disability and premature death. 1 9 LTCs involve <lb/>psychosocial, environmental, economic and <lb/>spiritual needs, which require support from <lb/>health and social care services. 9 13 <lb/>In this regard, healthcare and policy is <lb/>shifting focus from the illness to the person&apos;s <lb/>needs and how he/she lives with and responds <lb/></body>

			<front>STRENGTHS AND LIMITATIONS OF THIS STUDY <lb/>⇒ This validation study used an observational and <lb/>cross-sectional design. <lb/>⇒ The sample size is a strength considering the chal-<lb/>lenge of recruiting these populations. <lb/>⇒ The sample represented a heterogeneous popula-<lb/>tion, with patients from different sectors. <lb/>⇒ Most psychometric properties, including confirma-<lb/>tory factor analysis, were analysed. <lb/>⇒ Almost all participants were white British over 40, <lb/>which could limit the generalisability. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>10 January 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077978 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Ambrosio L, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e077978. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077978 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
    
    <body>to the illness. 14 15 More concretely, the phenomena &apos;living <lb/>with an LTC&apos; gains a meaning that goes beyond the <lb/>biomedical management of the condition, integrating <lb/>the whole psychosocial individual experience of the <lb/>process. 10 16 Based on our previous research, 10 17 living <lb/>with an LTC has been defined as a complex, dynamic, <lb/>cyclic and multidimensional process that involves key <lb/>elements, namely acceptance, coping, self-management, <lb/>integration and adjustment. Accepting an LTC implies <lb/>the absence of feelings of denial or anger, where the <lb/>person acknowledges and assumes the fact that they <lb/>have an LTC. 10 Coping refers to the process of learning <lb/>to face the LTC and implementing different strategies to <lb/>deal with the disease. 10 Self-management refers to having <lb/>some knowledge about the LTC itself, adhering to a plan <lb/>and actively participating in the decision-making that <lb/>the illness involves. 10 Finally, integrating the LTC implies <lb/>making changes in lifestyle to search for a new normal <lb/>and adjusting entails a progressive process of the transfor-<lb/>mation of the person&apos;s self-identity, as the LTC also forms <lb/>part of it. 10 Evidence also identified that the experience <lb/>of living with LTCs (LwLTCs) is unique for each person, <lb/>influenced by factors such as previous life experiences, <lb/>personality types, values and beliefs, and coping skills <lb/>for patients and family, affecting their quality of life. 9 13 <lb/>This supports the fact that there are important parallels <lb/>between different LTCs that could result in common care <lb/>pathways and interventions, also applied to the manage-<lb/>ment of multiple LTCs. <lb/>In order to plan individualised, comprehensive and <lb/>targeted interventions to improve the experience of living <lb/>with an LTC, an effective measure of the individual expe-<lb/>rience is needed. 10 17 To cover this need, the LwLTCs scale <lb/>was developed within an international Spanish-speaking <lb/>population. 18 Currently, the scale has been translated and <lb/>piloted in English-speaking population LwLTCs naming <lb/>the scale LwLTCs scale. 19 Preliminary results are waiting <lb/>to confirm the satisfactory and promising results identi-<lb/>fied in the pilot study. 19 Moreover, because LwLTCs scale <lb/>is not limited to an LTC, this study could show the extent <lb/>to which it reflects the experience of living with one or <lb/>more than one LTCs. <lb/>Therefore, the aim of this study is to present the psycho-<lb/>metric properties of the LwLTCs scale in an English-<lb/>speaking population of people living with different LTCs, <lb/>such as arthritis, COPD, CHD, PD, CKD or T2DM, and <lb/>discuss the clinical implications of its use. <lb/>METHODS <lb/>Design <lb/>An observational and cross-sectional study (one point-<lb/>in-time evaluation, with test-retest) was conducted to <lb/>validate the English version of the LwLTCs scale. This <lb/>was the most suitable design for validation studies as the <lb/>researcher was an observer and the data collection took <lb/>place at predetermined points of time. 20 <lb/>Patients <lb/>The following inclusion and exclusion criteria were <lb/>applied during participant recruitment: (a) having been <lb/>diagnosed with one or more of the following conditions <lb/>by a general practitioner (GP) or consultant: arthritis, <lb/>COPD, CHD, PD, CKD, T2DM; (b) any duration of the <lb/>condition; (c) being able to read, understand and answer <lb/>written questionnaires; (d) being fluent in English and <lb/>(e) being able to provide written informed consent. The <lb/>exclusion criteria were to present cognitive deterioration <lb/>and/or psychiatric disorders or any other disorder that <lb/>could interfere with or impede the reliably of the assess-<lb/>ment of LTC manifestations or objectives of the study. <lb/>Sampling and sample size <lb/>Consecutive cases sampling was applied to partici-<lb/>pant identification. 21 The sample size was based on the <lb/>consideration of confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) and <lb/>convergent validity. Based on high communality, 5-6 <lb/>factors and 4-5 variables per factor, 18 a sample size of <lb/>260 per condition would be sufficient to determine an <lb/>excellent-level (&gt;0.98) criterion for the coefficient of <lb/>congruence, aiming at a total 1650 participants. However, <lb/>due to the COVID-19, recruitment was slightly modified <lb/>and adjusted to the pandemic circumstances. Some GP <lb/>services declared a lack of capacity or capability due to the <lb/>further pressure the pandemic put on an already fragile <lb/>primary care system 22 and declined to participate. Also, <lb/>social distance circumstances changed the data collection <lb/>method from an intentioned face to face to email and <lb/>post. There might be other reasons for not taking part in <lb/>the research, such as having perspectives on the potential <lb/>lack of short-term benefits and usefulness of the research <lb/>in the middle of the COVID-19 pandemic, lack of digital <lb/>literacy to complete and send data online, difficulties in <lb/>accessing postservices or experiencing low mood and <lb/>decreasing the motivation to participate. <lb/>For the test-retest reliability, a sample of 60 per condi-<lb/>tion was estimated, to calculate the intraclass correla-<lb/>tion (ICC) to within±0.1 if ICC=0.8 and to within ±0.05 <lb/>if ICC=0.9. Therefore, up to 60 people per condition <lb/>were asked to complete the LwLTCs scale twice to avoid <lb/>drop-out. <lb/>Patient and public involvement <lb/>Prior to this validation study, a group of patient and public <lb/>involvement representatives, living with different LTCs, <lb/>such as osteoarthritis, T2DM, CKD, COPD, CHF and <lb/>PD and multimorbidity, was conducted in order to ask <lb/>them and gather their feedback in relation to the project <lb/>plan and the LwLTC Scale. Members of the PPI group <lb/>were invited to attend a meeting at our research facility. <lb/>Arrangements were made to ensure that all members <lb/>were able to access this location easily. The research team <lb/>was introduced, and a short presentation of the project <lb/>was given. Study documentation was provided to the <lb/>participants and discussion was facilitated by the research <lb/>team. Participants were encouraged to assess the overall <lb/></body>
    
    <note place="footnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>10 January 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077978 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Ambrosio L, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e077978. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077978 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
    
    <body>LwLTCs scale and supporting questions regarding rele-<lb/>vance, usefulness, appropriateness and to ensure that <lb/>there was no misunderstanding. This also provided the <lb/>opportunity to identify any potential barriers due to <lb/>assumed health literacy within the scale. Following this, <lb/>views were collated and adjustments to the scale were <lb/>made, this was then reviewed by randomly selected partic-<lb/>ipants of the PPI group who then approved the changes. <lb/>The PPI event was totally voluntary and without economic <lb/>remuneration. <lb/>Assessments <lb/>Sociodemographic data, such as age, gender, ethnicity <lb/>and educational level, and data related to the age of diag-<lb/>nosis, current treatment and surgery for the LTCs, were <lb/>collected. In addition, considering our previous findings <lb/>of the elements that influence the process of living with an <lb/>LTC 11 23 several validated outcome measures were used. <lb/>It was estimated that the completion of all the outcome <lb/>measures could take an average of 40 min per participant <lb/>(as in the original study). 18 <lb/>The Living with Chronic Illness Scale is the only avail-<lb/>able tool in clinical practice and research to measure <lb/>how people live with an LTC holistically, focusing on the <lb/>person and not the disease. 19 It is a 26-item scale with <lb/>five domains: (1) acceptance (four items), (2) coping <lb/>(seven items), (3) self-management (four items), (4) <lb/>integration (five items) and (5) adjustment (six items). <lb/>All items are answered using a 5-point Likert scale from <lb/>never or nothing (0) to always or a lot (4), except for <lb/>domain 1-acceptance, which is reversely scored from <lb/>never or nothing (4) to always or a lot (0). The scale has a <lb/>total score value from 0 points, indicating negative living <lb/>with the condition, to 104 points, reflecting positive living <lb/>with the condition. 18 The principal variable of the study is <lb/>&apos;living with an LTC&apos; measured through the LwLTCs scale. <lb/>The LwLTCs scale was originally developed for Spanish-<lb/>speaking population (in Spanish: Escala de convivenvia <lb/>con un proceso crónico EC-PC) and was developed <lb/>based on empirical 16 18 and conceptual 10 studies carried <lb/>out by international experts in the field of LTCs. Prior <lb/>to this validation study, the scale was translated and <lb/>cross-culturally adapted from the original LwLTCs scale <lb/>(Spanish-language) to make it suitable for an English-<lb/>speaking population. 19 The translation and cross-cultural <lb/>adaptation process was conducted by a panel of four <lb/>native English speaker experts. In addition, approval of <lb/>the English version was sought from the original author <lb/>of the LwLTC Scale in Spanish language. 19 <lb/>In addition to the LwLTCs scale, the following self-<lb/>reported scales were used: <lb/>Duke-UNC Functional Social Support Questionnaire <lb/>(DUFSS). 23 <lb/>It evaluates the social support of the patient from his/ <lb/>her perspective. It is an eight item that evaluates different <lb/>dimensions of social support as confidant, affective and <lb/>instrumental support. The score for each item varies from <lb/>1 (much less than I would like) to 5 (as much as I would <lb/>like). The Duke-UNC Functional Social Support Ques-<lb/>tionnaire (DUFSS) presented adequate psychometric <lb/>properties, showing a Cronbach&apos;s alpha value of 0.9 and <lb/>strong construct validity. 23 <lb/>Satisfaction with Life Scale (SLS-6) (modified version). 24 <lb/>It measures the degree of overall satisfaction with life <lb/>(one item), regarding other five areas: physical, psycho-<lb/>logical well-being, social relations, leisure and finan-<lb/>cial situation. Each item scores from 0 (unsatisfied) to <lb/>10 (totally satisfied). The SLS-6 presented satisfactory <lb/>psychometric properties, with a Cronbach&apos;s alpha of 0.8 <lb/>and internal validity values ranging from 0.4 to 0.7. 24 <lb/>WHO-Quality of life Scale (WHOQOL-BREF). 25 <lb/>The WHO Quality of Life-BREF (WHOQOL-BREF) <lb/>instrument was created by the WHO and comprises 26 <lb/>items, which measure the following broad domains: phys-<lb/>ical health, psychological health, social relationships and <lb/>environment. The WHOQOL-BREF is a shorter version of <lb/>the original instrument that may be more convenient for <lb/>this study in which several instruments will be completed. <lb/>The WHOQOL-BREF is comprised by 24 items that eval-<lb/>uates physical health, psychological health, social rela-<lb/>tionships and environment. Item response options range <lb/>from 1 (very dissatisfied) to 5 (very satisfied/very good <lb/>quality of life). The WHOQOL-BREF presented adequate <lb/>psychometric properties, showing a Cronbach&apos;s alpha <lb/>value of 0.9. 25 <lb/>Patient Global Impression of Severity (PGIS). 26 <lb/>The Patient Global Impression of Severity (PGIS) is a <lb/>self-reported generic scale that measures the patient&apos;s <lb/>perception of health. It contains one question about the <lb/>perception of the severity of the illness and six possible <lb/>answers rating from 0 (not at all unwell) to 7 (among the <lb/>most extremely unwell). The PGIS has excellent construct <lb/>validity and has been widely used in studies of chronic <lb/>diseases. 26 <lb/>Data collection <lb/>Data collection was carried out between December 2021 <lb/>and June 2022 across the UK via primary care surgeries <lb/>and voluntary organisations, such as Parkinson&apos;s UK, <lb/>Diabetes UK or Asthma UK. Sites were recruited with <lb/>the assistance of local clinical research networks. It is <lb/>important to mention that data collection was conducted <lb/>during the COVID-19 pandemic. Therefore, due to <lb/>COVID-19 lockdown and already-known restrictions, <lb/>face-to-face collection of data was no longer an option. <lb/>Potential participants were identified by members <lb/>of the primary care site using National Health Service <lb/>(NHS) clinical databases (EMIS or SystmOne). These <lb/>databases contain general information regarding the <lb/>patient&apos;s condition. Those who met initial inclusion <lb/>criteria were listed and checked individually by a GP or <lb/>research nurse at the site to ensure that the patient was <lb/>not at the end of life or in cognitive decline; if so, they <lb/>were excluded. A letter of invitation to participate in the <lb/>study was sent to those participants meeting the inclusion <lb/>criteria, via the clinical team using Docmail, which is a <lb/></body>
    
    <note place="footnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>10 January 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077978 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Ambrosio L, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e077978. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077978 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
    
    <body>confidential mass mailing service approved by the NHS. <lb/>Interested participants contacted the research team at <lb/>the (blinded information) by a dedicated email address <lb/>or phone line. Eligibility was checked and a patient <lb/>information sheet was sent by post or email, followed by <lb/>a consent form and questionnaires in accordance with <lb/>ethical approval. Completed documents were returned <lb/>to the research team by post using a freepost address or <lb/>email. Two research team members checked the answers <lb/>and participants were contacted again, via email or tele-<lb/>phone and a maximum of two times, if there were missing <lb/>data to obtain the information. Confidentiality was main-<lb/>tained by assigning participant numbers and storing <lb/>patient identifiable information securely according to <lb/>ethical guidelines. All questionnaires were checked for <lb/>completeness and then a £10 thank you voucher was sent <lb/>to the participants after completion. <lb/>Data analysis <lb/>The data have been cleaned, formatted and analysed <lb/>in SPSS (IBM Corp. Released 2021. IBM SPSS Statis-<lb/>tics for Windows, V.28.0., IBM), SAS V.9.4 (SAS Insti-<lb/>tute). Descriptive analyses (central tendency measures, <lb/>proportions) were used to analyse sociodemographic <lb/>characteristics of the sample and also LTCs-related char-<lb/>acteristics. The Consensus-based Standards for the selec-<lb/>tion of health Measurement INstruments 27 definition of <lb/>the measurement properties was used in the following <lb/>psychometric properties: <lb/>Data quality and acceptability was considered satisfac-<lb/>tory if missing data was &lt;5%. 28 Floor and ceiling effect <lb/>were deemed acceptable if they were &lt;15% 29 and the <lb/>skewness was expected between -1 and +1. 30 <lb/>Internal consistency is the degree of inter-relatedness <lb/>among the times. 27 Polychoric inter-item correlations <lb/>and ordinal alpha measures were used to assess internal <lb/>consistency 31 with alpha values higher than 0.70 consid-<lb/>ered good to excellent internal consistency. 32 <lb/>-CFA tests whether the data fit a priori hypothesised <lb/>factor structure. 33 This was used to corroborate the orig-<lb/>inal five domains structure of the LwLTCs scale. As the <lb/>LwLTCs domains and total scores were not normally <lb/>distributed, the unweighted least square estimation <lb/>approach was used to estimate the parameters for the <lb/>CFA models. 34 35 Fit indices of 0.97≤NFI (=Bentler-Bonett <lb/>Normed Fit Index) ≤1, 0&lt;SRMR (=standardised root <lb/>mean square residual) &lt;0.05, 0.95≤GFI (Goodness of <lb/>Fit Index) ≤1 indicate a perfect fit, while fit indices of <lb/>0.95≤NFI≤0.97, 0.05&lt;SRMR&lt;0.08, 0.90≤GFI≤0.95 indi-<lb/>cates an acceptable fit. 36 <lb/>Reproducibility is defined as the ability of a PROM <lb/>to measure change over time in the construct to be <lb/>measured. 27 This was evaluated through a test-7-day-<lb/>retest approach. To ensure reproducibility, the research <lb/>team facilitated the rationale for and the process of <lb/>conducting the retest by providing clear instructions in <lb/>the participant information sheet and after completing <lb/>the first assessment, and the retest was provided in the <lb/>participant&apos;s preferred administration method. A subset <lb/>of 122 participants completed a second assessment of the <lb/>LwLTCs scale within a timespan of 7-10 days after the base-<lb/>line assessment. Agreement between the two ordinally <lb/>distributed measurements from the same individual was <lb/>explored using the Wilcoxon signed-rank test. Asymptom-<lb/>atic significance (*&lt;0.05, **&lt;0.01, ***&lt;0.001) indicates a <lb/>significant disagreement between the two measurements <lb/>taken 7-10 days apart, and ICC (one way, random effect; <lb/>criterion≥0.70) for domains and total score. <lb/>Construct validity is the degree to which the content <lb/>of the scale is an adequate reflection of the construct <lb/>to be measured. 27 It was assessed with Spearman rank <lb/>correlations by determining (1) convergent validity: a <lb/>moderate (r s ≥0.35-0.50) or strong relationship (r s &gt;0.50) <lb/>was hypothesised between the LwLTCs scale and similar <lb/>constructs measured by DUFSS, SLS-6, and WHOQOL-<lb/>BREF, (2) discriminant validity: a weak (r s &lt;0.30) asso-<lb/>ciation was hypothesised between LwLTCs scale and <lb/>dissimilar constructs such as age, age onset LTC, duration <lb/>of LTC and PGIS. <lb/>Internal validity is understood as the intercorrela-<lb/>tions between domains of the scale. 27 In this study, the <lb/>LwLTCs scale domains (standard, r s =0.30-0.70) 30 36 was <lb/>determined. <lb/>Known-groups validity provides an adequate descrip-<lb/>tion of important characteristics of the subgroups, such as <lb/>disease or demographic characteristics. 27 The following <lb/>subgroups were analysed: gender, comorbidity, lifestyle <lb/>changes, therapy or employment situation. Not signif-<lb/>icant differences were hypothesised between the total <lb/>score of the LwLTCs scale and participants grouped by <lb/>those subgroups. As the LwLTCs scale is not normally <lb/>distributed, Kruskal-Wallis statistic and the Mann-Whitney <lb/>U test were used for groups comparison. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Sample characteristics <lb/>A total of 577 participants living with at least one LTC, <lb/>such as arthritis, COPD, CHD, PD and T2DM were <lb/>recruited. The age range was 37-97 years, with a mean <lb/>age of 98 (SD 9.65 years). 44.7% were female, 71.1% were <lb/>married or in a civil partnership and just over half were <lb/>living with the partner and/or spouse. The sample was <lb/>mainly white British (97.7%) with limited representation <lb/>from other ethnicity groups and retired (76.4%). Further <lb/>sociodemographic information is shown in table 1. <lb/>Regarding LTCs, although participants were recruited <lb/>with the criteria of living with one LTC, more than half of <lb/>the sample (70.1%) had more than one LTCs. The dura-<lb/>tion of the LTCs range was from 6 months to 76 years and <lb/>on average, participants had lived with an LTCs for 11 <lb/>years (SD 10.05 years). 87.7% of the sample were taking <lb/>medication for the LTCs and just over half were experi-<lb/>encing a change in their lifestyle due to the LTCs. Further <lb/>information regarding LTCs characteristics is shown in <lb/>table 1. <lb/></body>
    
    <note place="footnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>10 January 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077978 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Ambrosio L, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e077978. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077978 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
    
    <body>Data quality and acceptability <lb/>Results related to data quality showed that there were <lb/>seven missing data (three in domain 2-coping, one <lb/>in domain 3-self-management and three in domain <lb/>5-adjustment). Twenty-four of the 26-items included in <lb/>the LwLTCs scale showed flooring/ceiling effects and <lb/>were moderately (outside -0.5 to +0.5 range) to highly <lb/>(outside the range -1 to +1) skewed. The participant <lb/>scores for domain 4integration were also skewed. The <lb/>Shapiro-Wilk tests showed that the total, domain and <lb/>item scores of the English version of the LwLTCs were <lb/>not normally distributed. Due to the presence of ceiling/ <lb/>flooring effects, skewness and significant Shapiro-Wilk <lb/>tests, we decided to employ non-parametric statistics to <lb/>test the validity of the LwLTCs scale. <lb/>Internal consistency <lb/>Results related to internal consistency of the LwLTCs <lb/>scale showed that ordinal alpha was 0.90 for the total <lb/>scale and for the domains ranged between 0.68 (domain <lb/>3-self-management) and 0.87 (domain 1-acceptance). <lb/>Table 1 Sociodemographic and LTCs characteristics of the <lb/>sample (n=577) <lb/>N (%) <lb/>Gender <lb/>Male <lb/>310 (53.7) <lb/>Female <lb/>258 (44.7) <lb/>Prefer not to say <lb/>4 (0.7) <lb/>Missing <lb/>5 (0.9) <lb/>Ethnicity <lb/>White <lb/>564 (97.7) <lb/>Mixed or multiple <lb/>ethnic groups <lb/>4 (0.7) <lb/>Asian or Asian British <lb/>4 (0.7) <lb/>Black, African, <lb/>Caribbean or black <lb/>British <lb/>1 (0.2) <lb/>Other ethnic group <lb/>3 (0.5) <lb/>Prefer not to day <lb/>1 (0.2) <lb/>Marital status <lb/>Married <lb/>410 (71.1) <lb/>Widowed <lb/>51 (8.8) <lb/>Living with partner <lb/>29 (5.0) <lb/>Single <lb/>35 (6.1) <lb/>Separated/divorced <lb/>49 (8.5) <lb/>Other <lb/>2 (0.3) <lb/>Household <lb/>composition <lb/>Alone <lb/>127 (22.0) <lb/>With partner/spouse 367 (63.6) <lb/>With partner/ <lb/>spouse+children/ <lb/>grandchildren <lb/>59 (10.2) <lb/>With children/ <lb/>grandchildren <lb/>11 (1.9) <lb/>With partner/spouse <lb/>and hired carer <lb/>1 (0.2) <lb/>Other relatives <lb/>4 (0.7) <lb/>Other <lb/>8 (1.4) <lb/>Education level <lb/>Primary school <lb/>4 (0.7) <lb/>Secondary school <lb/>141 (24.4) <lb/>Apprenticeship <lb/>29 (5.0) <lb/>College <lb/>154 (26.7) <lb/>University degree <lb/>139 (24.1) <lb/>Postgraduate studies 88 (15.3) <lb/>Doctorate <lb/>17 (2.9) <lb/>Employment <lb/>Retired <lb/>441 (76.4) <lb/>Employed (&gt;40 hours) 29 (5.0) <lb/>Employed (&lt;40 hours) 63 (10.9) <lb/>Looking for work <lb/>5 (0.9) <lb/>Not employed and not <lb/>looking for work <lb/>20 (3.5) <lb/>Disabled/not able to <lb/>work <lb/>19 (3.3) <lb/>Continued <lb/>N (%) <lb/>Lifestyle changes Yes <lb/>322 (55.8) <lb/>No <lb/>247 (42.8) <lb/>Therapy <lb/>Yes <lb/>189 (32.8) <lb/>No <lb/>379 (65.7) <lb/>Surgery <lb/>Yes <lb/>123 (21.3) <lb/>No <lb/>448 (77.6) <lb/>Primary LTC <lb/>Arthritis <lb/>126 (21.8) <lb/>Parkinson&apos;s disease <lb/>241 (41.8) <lb/>Diabetes type II <lb/>70 (12.1) <lb/>Chronic heart disease 78 (13.5) <lb/>Chronic obstructive <lb/>pulmonary disease <lb/>60 (10.4) <lb/>Other LTCs <lb/>None <lb/>196 (34.0) <lb/>Arthritis <lb/>262 (45.4) <lb/>Parkinson&apos;s disease <lb/>60 (10.4) <lb/>Diabetes type II <lb/>1 (0.2) <lb/>Chronic heart disease <lb/>1 (0.2) <lb/>Only one LTC <lb/>59 (10.2) <lb/>LTCs characteristics <lb/>Current age <lb/>Mean±SD (range) <lb/>in years <lb/>68.0±9.27 <lb/>(37-97) <lb/>Duration LTC <lb/>Mean+SD, <lb/>median+mode <lb/>(range) <lb/>11.0±10.05, 8.0, <lb/>4.0 (0.5-76) <lb/>.LTC, long term condition. <lb/>Table 1 Continued <lb/></body>
    
    <note place="footnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>10 January 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077978 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Ambrosio L, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e077978. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077978 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
    
    <body>All intercorrelations between the LwLTCs scale domains <lb/>ranged between 0.04 (domain 3-self-management) and <lb/>0.74 (domain 1-acceptance). See table 2 for further <lb/>information. <lb/>Confirmatory factor analysis <lb/>The CFA did not show a good fit for the originally <lb/>proposed 5-domain structure fitted to the 26 items (see <lb/>online supplemental figure 1). The fit of the structure <lb/>improved significantly if items 2, 5, 10, 16, 18 and 23 were <lb/>to be removed and item 24 was reassigned to domain <lb/>4-intergration. This final CFA model (see online supple-<lb/>mental figure 2) with 5 domains and 20 items showed <lb/>good fit indices (NFI=0.96; SRMR=0.051; GFI=0.98). <lb/>Reproducibility <lb/>Reproducibility was determined on the 7-day apart <lb/>consecutive measurements of 122 participants living with <lb/>arthritis (n=27), COPD (n=8), CHD (n=20), PD (n=44), <lb/>CKD (n=20) and T2DM (n=18). The ICC for the total <lb/>scale was 0.86 and for all domains was over 0.75 except <lb/>for domain 4-integration (see table 2). For items, Cohen&apos;s <lb/>kappa ranged between 0.31 (item 8) and 0.58 (item 6). <lb/>As the items, domains and total score of the LwLTCs scale <lb/>are not normally distributed, Wilcoxon signed-rank test <lb/>was applied to determine the level of agreement between <lb/>the baseline LwLTCs measurement and the second <lb/>LwLTCs assessment 7-10 days later. Findings indicate that <lb/>there are no significant differences between baseline and <lb/>second assessment measurement for most of the items, <lb/>except for items 8, 10, 11, 12 and 21. The significant <lb/>differences in these items also affect the reproducibility <lb/>of domain 2-coping, domain 3-self management and the <lb/>LwLTCs total score. <lb/>Construct validity <lb/>In agreement with our hypothesis, the results in table 3 <lb/>showed that the LwLTCs scale strongly correlated with <lb/>SLS-6 (r s =0.58) and WHOQOL-BREF (r s =0.50) and <lb/>moderately correlated with DUFSS (r s =0.43). In addition, <lb/>weak or negligible correlations were identified between <lb/>LwLTCs scale and clinical characteristics such as the <lb/>patient impression of LTCs severity (PGIS) or duration of <lb/>LTCs (see table 3). <lb/>According to internal validity analysis, correlation values <lb/>between LwLTCs domains ranged from 0.31 to 0.51, <lb/>except for domain 1-acceptance that showed low correla-<lb/>tions with domain 2-coping, domain 3-self-management <lb/>and domain 5-adaptation. See table 3 for further detail. <lb/>As shown in table 4, in agreement with our hypothesis, <lb/>the total score of known-group validity analysis showed no <lb/>significant differences were identified for gender, comor-<lb/>bidity, lifestyle changes or therapy. However, significant <lb/>difference was identified for the LwLTCs scale on employ-<lb/>ment situation (p=-0.017). A summary of the key findings <lb/>is shown in table 5. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>This is the first validation study of the LwLTCs scale in an <lb/>English-speaking population living with different LTCs. <lb/>Until now, the LwLTC Scale has only been available in <lb/>Spanish. 19 Hence, this study covers an important gap <lb/>related to reliable and valid person-centred tools to eval-<lb/>uate the process of LwLTCs in English-speaking countries. <lb/>The internal consistency of the LwLTCs scale was excel-<lb/>lent (0.90) both overall and for each domain. However, <lb/>some of the inter-item polychoric correlations indicate <lb/>that it would be better to remove certain items due to <lb/>low correlations (eg, items 5, 12) and overlaps (eg, items <lb/>10/11, 16/17, 23/24) showing redundancy in the content <lb/>of the items. 37 These findings completely aligned with <lb/>the CFA findings of this study. Particularly, the CFA did <lb/>not support the original structure of the scale. 10 Findings <lb/>showed that there is a considerable amount of overlap <lb/>among certain items (items 2/4; 10/11; 16/17; 23/24) <lb/>and certain items do not fit well within the construct <lb/>being measured (items 5 and 18). Hence, a 5-domain <lb/>and 20 item version worked better than the 26-item orig-<lb/>inal version. These findings align with other validation <lb/>results 19 38 conducted in the Spanish version of the scale <lb/>for people living with different LTCs. For instance, the <lb/>CFA conducted in Spanish-speaking population living <lb/>Table 2 Feasibility/acceptability, reliability and precision of the LwLTCs scale <lb/>LwLTCs scale <lb/>Domain 1: <lb/>acceptance <lb/>Domain 2: <lb/>coping <lb/>Domain 3: self-<lb/>management <lb/>Domain 4: <lb/>integration <lb/>Domain 5: <lb/>adjustment <lb/>LwLTCs <lb/>total score <lb/>Data Quality (% fully computable data) 0 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>3 <lb/>7 <lb/>Floor effect (%) <lb/>1.2 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>0 <lb/>Ceiling effect (%) <lb/>9 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>4.9 <lb/>8.5 <lb/>2.1 <lb/>0 <lb/>Skewness <lb/>-0.7 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>-0.6 <lb/>-1 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>-0.3 <lb/>Ordinal alpha <lb/>0.87 <lb/>0.80 <lb/>0.68 <lb/>0.72 <lb/>0.85 <lb/>0.90 <lb/>Inter-item polychoric correlation <lb/>0.49-0.74 <lb/>0.13-0.60 <lb/>0.22-0.45 <lb/>-0.09-0.69 0.19-0.70 <lb/>-<lb/>Reproducibility (ICC) <lb/>0.81 <lb/>0.82 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.73 <lb/>0.77 <lb/>0.86 <lb/>.ICC, intraclass correlation; LwLTCs, living with long term conditions. <lb/></body>
    
    <note place="footnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>10 January 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077978 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Ambrosio L, et al. BMJ Open doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077978 <lb/></note>
    
    <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
    
    <body>with T2DM also showed that a shorter and adjusted <lb/>version of the scale presented better fit indices. 38 <lb/>The reproducibility results showed that some partici-<lb/>pants scored quite different (lower) at the second assess-<lb/>ment for some items and the whole LwLTCs scale. These <lb/>results are in line with the CFA results, indicating the <lb/>removal of certain items will improve the validity and <lb/>reliability of the LwLTCs scale. However, reproducibility <lb/>results from this study should be interpreted with caution <lb/>because it was not assessed during the second data collec-<lb/>tion if personal circumstances (ie, change in economic <lb/>status, medication for the condition or familiar issues) <lb/>had changed for the participants that could justify the <lb/>differences between the data measurements. One of the <lb/>reasons behind these results could be the physical and <lb/>mental health alterations that the COVID-19 pandemic <lb/>might have generated in participants&apos; daily lives. Hence, <lb/>further analyses are recommended to identify if the <lb/>LwLTCs scale captures how the person lives with LTCs <lb/>repeatedly under the same circumstances. <lb/>Regarding convergent validity, as hypothesised, the <lb/>process of living with an LTC presents moderate or strong <lb/>relationship with social support, satisfaction with life and <lb/>quality of life. Similarly, weak or negligible correlations <lb/>were identified between LwLTCs scale and clinical char-<lb/>acteristics, such as patient impression of LTC severity or <lb/>duration of LTCs. These findings were also identified in <lb/>the Spanish-speaking validation study among multiple <lb/>LTCs, 19 such as DM2, 37 PD, 18 COPD, 39 CHF 40 or arthritis. 41 <lb/>Once again, this study corroborates the comprehen-<lb/>sive approach needed when assessing the daily living <lb/>of people with LTCs, focusing on the person and not <lb/>the disease. Therefore, social support, satisfaction with <lb/>life and quality of life assessments should be addressed <lb/>through collaboration between the healthcare and social <lb/>system. Particularly, the LwLTCs scale could be used as <lb/>a complement to conventional generic health-related <lb/>quality of life measures or other existing medical records <lb/>platforms available in the NHS. This could constitute a <lb/>basis for evaluation where interventions may affect both <lb/>health and social care outcomes, including mental health <lb/>and well-being and in comparing outcomes and resource <lb/>allocation across different areas of the public sector. 42 <lb/>The internal validity for LwLTCs scale domains was <lb/>good to excellent, except for domain 1: acceptance, <lb/>with correlation coefficients very low with the rest of the <lb/>domains. This result is consistent with previous validation <lb/>studies 18 19 and conceptual work, 10 showing that accepting <lb/>Table 3 Convergent validity and internal validity of the LwLTCs scale <lb/>LwTLCs scale <lb/>Domain 1: <lb/>acceptance <lb/>Domain 2: <lb/>coping <lb/>Domain 3: self-<lb/>management <lb/>Domain 4: <lb/>integration <lb/>Domain 5: <lb/>adjustment <lb/>Total <lb/>score <lb/>Convergent <lb/>validity <lb/>Age <lb/>0.18*** <lb/>0.04 <lb/>-0.004 <lb/>0.12** <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.09* <lb/>Age-onset LTC <lb/>0.11** <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>Duration LTC <lb/>0.04 <lb/>-0.06 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>WHOQOL-Physical health <lb/>0.56*** <lb/>0.20*** <lb/>0.13** <lb/>0.54*** <lb/>0.32*** <lb/>0.44*** <lb/>WHOQOL-Psychological <lb/>0.57*** <lb/>0.41*** <lb/>0.29*** <lb/>0.65*** <lb/>0.46*** <lb/>0.64*** <lb/>WHOQOL-Social relationships <lb/>0.28*** <lb/>0.35*** <lb/>0.23*** <lb/>0.42*** <lb/>0.36*** <lb/>0.45*** <lb/>WHOQOL-Environment <lb/>0.46*** <lb/>0.33*** <lb/>0.34*** <lb/>0.57*** <lb/>0.35*** <lb/>0.53*** <lb/>WHOQOL-Overall QOL <lb/>0.48*** <lb/>0.31*** <lb/>0.19*** <lb/>0.54*** <lb/>0.38*** <lb/>0.50*** <lb/>DUFSS <lb/>0.37*** <lb/>0.36*** <lb/>0.19*** <lb/>0.42*** <lb/>0.26*** <lb/>0.43*** <lb/>Satisfaction With Life <lb/>0.54*** <lb/>0.36*** <lb/>0.18*** <lb/>0.58*** <lb/>0.48*** <lb/>0.58*** <lb/>Satisfaction-physical health <lb/>0.53*** <lb/>0.30*** <lb/>0.18*** <lb/>0.54*** <lb/>0.43*** <lb/>0.54*** <lb/>Satisfaction-well-being <lb/>0.49*** <lb/>0.31*** <lb/>0.20*** <lb/>0.53*** <lb/>0.37*** <lb/>0.52*** <lb/>Satisfaction-social relations <lb/>0.42*** <lb/>0.34*** <lb/>0.18*** <lb/>0.47*** <lb/>0.32*** <lb/>0.47*** <lb/>Satisfaction-leisure <lb/>0.49*** <lb/>0.31*** <lb/>0.17*** <lb/>0.57*** <lb/>0.41*** <lb/>0.53*** <lb/>Satisfaction-financial situation <lb/>0.29*** <lb/>0.19*** <lb/>0.25*** <lb/>0.35*** <lb/>0.23*** <lb/>0.34*** <lb/>Patient impression illness severity -0.44*** <lb/>-0.10* <lb/>-0.09* <lb/>-0.37*** <lb/>-0.25*** <lb/>-0.32*** <lb/>Internal <lb/>validity <lb/>Coping <lb/>-0.18* <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Self-management <lb/>-0.08* <lb/>0.44*** <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Integration <lb/>0.47*** <lb/>0.43*** <lb/>0.41*** <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Adjustment <lb/>0.28*** <lb/>0.51*** <lb/>0.31*** <lb/>0.48*** <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Spearman rank correlations: *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001. <lb/>DUFSS, Duke-UNC Functional Social Support Questionnaire; LTC, long term condition; LwLTC, living with long term conditions; <lb/>QOL, quality of life; WHOQOL, WHO Quality of Life. <lb/></body>
    
    <note place="footnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>10 January 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077978 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Ambrosio L, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e077978. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077978 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>
    
    <body>the is always the first step to achieve a positive <lb/>living. Hence, only when the person has accepted and <lb/>assumed his/her illness can he or she move on to the <lb/>other domains such as coping or self-management. 10 43 <lb/>Therefore, according to the poor correlation that domain <lb/>1-acceptance showed with other domains of the LwLTCs <lb/>scale and previous validation studies, this finding was <lb/>expected because acceptance is considered an internal, <lb/>illness-independent process through which the person <lb/>recognises and accepts the reality. 42 44 <lb/>LwLTCs scale demonstrated satisfactory know-group <lb/>validity, yielding not significant differences for gender, <lb/>comorbidity, lifestyle changes or therapy. This means that <lb/>the LwLTCs scale equally evaluates the degree of living <lb/>with an LTC in all individuals independently of gender, <lb/>comorbidity, lifestyle changes or therapy. Hence, this <lb/>shows that the LwLTCs scale could be used with a diverse <lb/>LTCs population without discriminating their gender, <lb/>lifestyle or therapy, preventing inequalities. Nevertheless, <lb/>surprisingly significant differences were identified for <lb/>employment situation. This means that the LwLTCs scale <lb/>could capture differences among people with different <lb/>employment situations. However, among the sample very <lb/>few participants were unemployed which does not cover <lb/>other employment situations. Hence, to identify if the <lb/>LwLTCs scale captures the differences among people with <lb/>different employment situations or not, future research is <lb/>recommended. <lb/>Having a short scale, with just 20 items and with excel-<lb/>lent psychometric properties, is key when considering <lb/>the implementation of the scale in clinical practice in <lb/>primary care settings with short time consultations and <lb/>staff shortage. Using the LwLTCs in primary care could <lb/>result in more optimal healthcare utilisation without <lb/>sacrificing quality of life and economic costs because <lb/>it could ensure more effective risk stratification and <lb/>Table 4 Known-group validity <lb/>Categories <lb/>LwLTCs scale total <lb/>P value <lb/>Sex <lb/>0.49 <lb/>Men <lb/>66.6 (15.2) <lb/>Women <lb/>65.4 (15.2) <lb/>Employment <lb/>0.017 <lb/>Employed <lb/>64.3 (14.5) <lb/>Unemployed <lb/>58.2 (17.4) <lb/>Retired/disabled <lb/>66.8 (15) <lb/>Comorbidities <lb/>0.76 <lb/>None <lb/>66.1 (15) <lb/>Arthritis <lb/>66.1 (15.3) <lb/>Parkinson&apos;s disease <lb/>67.5 (15.3) <lb/>Lifestyle changes <lb/>0.85 <lb/>Yes <lb/>66.0 (14.2) <lb/>No <lb/>65.9 (15.9) <lb/>Therapy <lb/>0.12 <lb/>Yes <lb/>64.7 (14.6) <lb/>No <lb/>66.4 (15.3) <lb/>LwLTCs, living with long term conditions. <lb/>Table 5 Summary of the key findings <lb/>Psychometric <lb/>property <lb/>Established criteria <lb/>Findings-LwLTCs scale score <lb/>Data quality and <lb/>acceptability <lb/>► Missing data &lt;5% <lb/>► Floor and ceiling effect &lt;15% <lb/>► Skewness -1 to +1 <lb/>► Missing data 1.2% (n=7) <lb/>► Floor and ceiling effect=0% <lb/>► Skewness=-0.3 <lb/>Internal consistency ► Ordinal alpha≥0.70 <lb/>► Ordinal alpha=0.90 <lb/>Confirmatory factor <lb/>analysis <lb/>► Originally proposed 5-domain structure fitted to the 26 <lb/>items <lb/>► Good fit with 5 domains and 20 items (NFI=0.96; <lb/>SRMR=0.051; GFI=0.98) <lb/>Reproducibility <lb/>► Intraclass correlation coefficient ≥0.70 <lb/>► Intraclass correlation coefficient=0.86 <lb/>Construct validity <lb/>► Strong (rs&gt;0.50) or moderate (r s ≥0.35-0.50) relationship <lb/>was hypothesised between the total score of the <lb/>LwLTCs scale and DUFSS, SLS-6 and WHOQOL-BREF <lb/>► Weak (r s &lt;0.30) relationship was hypothesised between <lb/>the total score of the LwLTCs scale and age of the <lb/>person, age onset LTC, duration of LTC and PGIS <lb/>► Strong correlations were identified with SLS-<lb/>6 (r s =0.58) and WHOQOL-BREF (r s =0.50) and <lb/>moderate correlations with DUFSS (r s =0.43) <lb/>► Weak or negligible correlations were identified <lb/>with PGIS (r s =-0.32), duration of LTC (r s =-0.01), <lb/>age onset LTC (r s =0.06) and age of the person <lb/>(r s =0.09) <lb/>Internal validity <lb/>► r s =0.30-0.70 <lb/>► r s =0.31-0.51 <lb/>Know-group validity ► Not significant differences were hypothesised between <lb/>the total score of the LwLTCs scale and gender, <lb/>comorbidity, lifestyle changes, therapy or employment <lb/>situation <lb/>► Significant differences for employment situation <lb/>(p=-0.017) <lb/>DUFSS, Duke-UNC Functional Social Support Questionnaire; GFI, Goodness of Fit Index; LTC, long term condition; LwLTCs, living with <lb/>long term conditions; NFI, Normed Fit Index; PGIS, Patient Global Impression of Severity; SLS-6, Satisfaction with Life Scale; SRMR, <lb/>standardised root mean square residual; WHOQOL-BREF, WHO Quality of life Scale. <lb/></body>
    
    <note place="footnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>10 January 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077978 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Ambrosio L, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e077978. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077978 <lb/></note>
              
              <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>

			<body>the early identification of people with needs for <lb/>more complex care coordination and high or low risk <lb/>for poor self-management. Specifically, the LwLTCs scale <lb/>could facilitate the implementation of NICE pathways <lb/>and recommendations for LTCs. 45 Particularly, a more <lb/>comprehensive care plan, directed referral to specialists <lb/>or other resources and support groups in the community, <lb/>regular monitoring and points of contact of support 45 <lb/>could be ensured based on the results of the LwLTCs <lb/>scale assessment. Finally, the LwLTCs scale is very rele-<lb/>vant to the quality requirements of the National Services <lb/>framework for LTCs 46 especially when it comes to the <lb/>assessment of personal care and support to tackle phys-<lb/>ical, emotional, spiritual and social needs, improving <lb/>connections between health and social care. <lb/>Strengths and limitations <lb/>This is an innovative and unique validation study of <lb/>the LwLTCs scale among English-speaking population <lb/>LwLTCs. The findings of this study align well with findings <lb/>identified in Spanish-speaking population, leading to a <lb/>recommendation for a shortened version of the scale with <lb/>excellent psychometric properties. Finally, although the <lb/>negative impact of COVID-19, the project kept running <lb/>successfully. <lb/>Regarding the limitations, sample characteristics could <lb/>limit the generalisability of the findings of this study. <lb/>First, of the 577 participants included in this study 241 <lb/>had PD. Second, most participants in the current study <lb/>were over 40 years old. Hence, results are not generalis-<lb/>able to younger adults LwLTCs on working age. Third, <lb/>almost all participants in this study were white British. <lb/>Therefore, in order to overcome this sampling limitation, <lb/>the recruitment efforts of future validation studies of the <lb/>LwLTCs scale should focus on inclusion of young adult <lb/>population, people living with multiple different LTCs, <lb/>and ethnic representative groups, such as black or Asian. <lb/>Finally, we cannot ignore the impact that the COVID-19 <lb/>pandemic had on this project. Recruitment process was <lb/>adapted to social distancing circumstances and data <lb/>collection was conducted smoothly although the impact <lb/>of the change in circumstances for people with LTCs <lb/>could have caused the observed differences between the <lb/>Spanish and the English validation studies. Also, due to <lb/>COVID-19 pandemic, initially calculated sample size was <lb/>not reached, having a smaller sample size. This could <lb/>have interfered with the results of the CFA. <lb/>CONCLUSIONS <lb/>This paper provides the first psychometric analysis of <lb/>the LwLTCs scale in English-speaking population among <lb/>people living with different LTCs. A shorter version of the <lb/>LwLTCs scale, maintaining the 5 domains but just with <lb/>20 items is recommended. This shorter version of the <lb/>scale, with excellent psychometric properties, is ready to <lb/>be used in clinical practice to facilitate the implementa-<lb/>tion of person-centred care pathways and more effective <lb/>referrals. Prior to the full implementation trial, a feasi-<lb/>bility testing using the 20 items version of the scale is <lb/>recommended. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements This study is supported by the National Institute for Health <lb/>and Care Research ARC Wessex. Besides, the authors would like to acknowledge <lb/>the collaboration of people living with long-term conditions that have participated <lb/>in this project. <lb/></div>
    
            <div type="contribution">Contributors LA: principal author of the scale, conception and design of the work, <lb/>interpretation of the findings, drafting the article, critical revision and substantial <lb/>contribution of the article, approval of the final version for publication. KH-L: data <lb/>collection, design of the work and critical revision and substantial contribution of <lb/>the article, approval of the final version for publication. NS-F, data collection, critical <lb/>revision and substantial contribution of the article, approval of the final version for <lb/>publication. CD: data analysis, interpretation of the findings, critical revision and <lb/>substantial contribution of the article, approval of the final version for publication. <lb/>MCP: principal investigator of the project and responsible for funding of the project, <lb/>conception and design of the work, critical revision and substantial contribution of <lb/>the article, approval of the final version for publication. All the authors (LA, KH-L, <lb/>NS-F, CD, MCP) accepts the full responsibility for the work and/or the conduct of the <lb/>study, had access to the data, and controlled the decision to publish. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding This study is funded by the National Institute for Health and Care <lb/>Research ARC Wessex. There is no award/grant number for this study, as the <lb/>National Institute for Health and Care Research ARC does not allocate grant <lb/>numbers to the funded projects. <lb/></div>
    
            <div type="annex">Disclaimer The views expressed in this publication are those of the author(s) and <lb/>not necessarily those of the National Institute for Health and Care Research or the <lb/>Department of Health and Social Care. <lb/></div>
    
            <div type="conflict">Competing interests None declared. <lb/></div>
    
            <div type="annex">Patient and public involvement Patients and/or the public were involved in the <lb/>design, or conduct, or reporting, or dissemination plans of this research. Refer to <lb/>the Methods section for further details. <lb/>Patient consent for publication Consent obtained directly from patient(s). <lb/>Ethics approval This study involves human participants and this validation study <lb/>was ethically approved by the University of Southampton (ERGO 59259), the <lb/>NHS ethics (Rec ref: 20/ES/0084) and the HRA (IRAS: 272646). Participants gave <lb/>informed consent to participate in the study before taking part. <lb/>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. <lb/></div>
      
            <div type="availability">Data availability statement Data are available on reasonable request to the <lb/>corresponding author. All data relevant to the study are included in the article. Only <lb/>members of the research team (ie, corresponding author) have access to the study <lb/>data. The full anonymised data set was shared between the principal investigator of <lb/>the study and the research member involved in the data analysis. <lb/></div>
    
            <div type="annex">Supplemental material This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has <lb/>not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been <lb/>peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those <lb/>of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and <lb/>responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content <lb/>includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability <lb/>of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, <lb/>terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error <lb/>and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise. <lb/></div>

			<front>Open access This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which <lb/>permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, <lb/>and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is <lb/>properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use <lb/>is non-commercial. See: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/. <lb/>ORCID iD <lb/>Leire Ambrosio http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9450-7210 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1 The Richmond Group of Charities. Multimorbidity. In: Understanding <lb/>the challenge. A report for the Richmond Group of Charities, 2018. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>10 January 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077978 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Ambrosio L, et al. BMJ Open 2024;14:e077978. doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077978 <lb/></note>
    
            <note place="headnote">Open access <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Available: https://richmondgroupofcharities.org.uk/sites/default/files/ <lb/>multimorbidity_-_understanding_the_challenge.pdf <lb/>2 Department of Health. Improving Health and Well-Being of <lb/>People with Long Term Conditions. World Class Services for People <lb/>with Long Term Conditions: Information Tool for Commissioners, . <lb/>2010Available: https://www.yearofcare.co.uk/sites/default/files/pdfs/ <lb/>dh_improving/the/wb/of/people/with/ltcs/pdf <lb/>3 Arthritis research UK. Available: https://www.arthritisresearch.org/ <lb/>arthritis-information-data-and-statistics/state-of-muscloskeletal-<lb/>health.aspx <lb/>4 Diabetes UK. Available: https://www.diabetes.org.uk/professionals/ <lb/>position-statements-reports-statistics <lb/>5 Kidney care UK. Available: https://www.kidneycareuk.org <lb/>6 British lung foundation. Available: https://www.statistics.blf.org.uk/ <lb/>copd <lb/>7 British heart foundation. Available: https://www.bhf.org.uk/what-we-<lb/>do/our-research-heart-statistics <lb/>8 National Institute for Care and Health Excellence. Parkinson&apos;s <lb/>disease-everything NICE says in an interactive Flowchart. n.d. <lb/>Available: https://pathways.nice.org.uk/pathways/parkinsons-<lb/>disease/managing-parkinsons-disease#content=view-index&amp;path= <lb/>view%3A/pathways/parkinsons-disease/managing-parkinsons-<lb/>disease.xml <lb/>9 Stafford M, Steventon A, Thorlby R, et al. Briefing: understanding <lb/>the health care needs of people with multiple health conditions. In: <lb/>The Health Foundation. 2018. Available: https://www.health.org. <lb/>uk/sites/default/files/upload/publications/2018/Understanding% <lb/>20the%20health%20care%20needs%20of%20people%20with% <lb/>20multiple%20health%20conditions.pdf <lb/>10 Ambrosio L, Senosiain García JM, Riverol Fernández M, et al. <lb/>Living with chronic illness in adults: a concept analysis. J Clin Nurs <lb/>2015;24:2357-67. <lb/>11 Ambrosio L, Portillo MC, Rodriguez-Blazquez C, et al. Influencing <lb/>factors when living with Parkinson&apos;s disease: A cross-sectional study. <lb/>J Clin Nurs 2019;28:3168-76. <lb/>12 Naylor C, Parsonage M, McDaid D, et al. Long-term conditions <lb/>and mental health. The cost of Co-morbidities. In: The King&apos;s Fund. <lb/>2012. Available: https://www.kingsfund.org.uk/sites/default/files/ <lb/>field/field_publication_file/long-term-conditions-mental-health-cost-<lb/>comorbidities-naylor-feb12.pdf <lb/>13 Dambha-Miller H, Simpson G, Hobson L, et al. Integrating primary <lb/>care and social services for older adults with Multimorbidity: a <lb/>qualitative study. Br J Gen Pract 2021;71:e753-61. <lb/>14 World health Organisation regional office for Europe. In: Action Plan <lb/>for implementation of the European Strategy for the prevention and <lb/>control of noncommunicable diseases 2012-2016. Available: http:// <lb/>www.euro.who.int/__data/assets/pdf_file/0019/170155/e96638.pdf <lb/>15 Rosland A-M, Heisler M, Janevic MR, et al. Current and potential <lb/>support for chronic disease management in the United States: the <lb/>perspective of family and friends of chronically ill adults. Fam Syst <lb/>Health 2013;31:119-31. <lb/>16 Pumar-Méndez MJ, Mujika A, Regaira E, et al. Stakeholders <lb/>in support systems for self-care for chronic illness: the gap <lb/>between expectations and reality regarding their identity, roles <lb/>and relationships. Health Expectations 2017;20:434-47. 10.1111/ <lb/>hex.12471 Available: https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/toc/13697625/ <lb/>20/3 <lb/>17 Navarta-Sánchez MV, Senosiain García JM, Riverol M, et al. Factors <lb/>influencing Psychosocial adjustment and quality of life in Parkinson <lb/>patients and informal Caregivers. Qual Life Res 2016;25:1959-68. <lb/>18 Ambrosio L, Portillo MC, Rodríguez-Blázquez C, et al. Living with <lb/>chronic illness scale: International validation of a new self-report <lb/>measure in Parkinson&apos;s disease. NPJ Parkinsons Dis 2016;2:16022. <lb/>19 Ambrosio L, Hislop-Lennie K, Barker H, et al. Living with long term <lb/>condition scale: A pilot validation study of a new person-centred tool <lb/>in the UK. Nurs Open 2021;8:1909-19. <lb/>20 Bryman A. Social research methods4th ed. Oxford: Oxford University <lb/>Press, 2012. <lb/>21 Bowling A. Research Methods in Health: Investigating Health and <lb/>Health Services4th ed. Maidenhead, UK: University Press, 2014. <lb/>22 Hillman A. COVID-19: explaining the UK&apos;s slow recovery in clinical <lb/>trial activity 2022. Available: https://www.clinicaltrialsarena.com/ <lb/>analysis/uk-clinical-trials-covid-19-2/ <lb/>23 Broadhead WE, Gehlbach SH, de Gruy FV, et al. The Duke-UNC <lb/>functional social support questionnaire, measurement of social <lb/>support in family medicine patients. Med Care 1988;26:709-23. <lb/>24 Mazaheri M, Theuns P. A study of how satisfaction and <lb/>dissatisfaction with life overall relate to satisfaction and <lb/>dissatisfaction in specific life domains. In: . Patient Reported <lb/>Outcomes Newsletter, 2006: 37. 24-7. <lb/>25 The world health organization quality of life (WHOQOL)-BREF world <lb/>health organization 2004. Available: http://www.who.int/substance_ <lb/>abuse/research_tools/en/english_whoqol.pdf <lb/>26 Guy W. ECDEU Assessment Manual for Psychopharmacology-<lb/>Revised. Rockville, MD: National Institute of Mental Health. <lb/>Psychopharmacology Research Branch, n.d.: 1976. <lb/>27 Mokkink LB, Terwee CB, Patrick DL, et al. The COSMIN study <lb/>reached International consensus on Taxonomy, terminology, and <lb/>definitions of measurement properties for health-related patient-<lb/>reported outcomes. J Clin Epidemiol 2010;63:737-45. <lb/>28 Smith SC, Lamping DL, Banerjee S, et al. Measurement of health-<lb/>related quality of life for people with dementia: development of a new <lb/>instrument (DEMQOL) and an evaluation of current methodology. <lb/>Health Technol Assess 2005;9:1-93, <lb/>29 van der Linden FAH, Kragt JJ, Klein M, et al. Psychometric evaluation <lb/>of the multiple sclerosis impact scale (MSIS-29) for proxy use. J <lb/>Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry 2005;76:1677-81. <lb/>30 Kapitula LR. Estimating Ordinal reliability using SAS®. In: SAS global <lb/>forum. <lb/>31 Nunnally B, Bernstein IR. Psychometric Theory. New York: Oxford <lb/>University, 1994. <lb/>32 Forero CG, Maydeu-Olivares A, Gallardo-Pujol D. Factor analysis <lb/>with Ordinal indicators: A Monte Carlo study comparing DWLS and <lb/>ULS estimation. Structural Equation Modeling: A Multidisciplinary <lb/>Journal 2009;16:625-41. <lb/>33 Mokkink LB, Terwee CB, Knol DL, et al. The COSMIN checklist for <lb/>evaluating the methodological quality of studies on measurement <lb/>properties: A clarification of its content. BMC Med Res Methodol <lb/>2010;10:22:1-8.:. <lb/>34 Jöreskog K, Sörbom D. LISREL 9.2. New York: Scientific Software <lb/>International, 2015. <lb/>35 Hobart JC, Riazi A, Lamping DL, et al. Improv-Ing the evaluation <lb/>of therapeutic interventions in multiple sclerosis: development <lb/>of a Patient-Based measure of outcome. Health Technol Assess <lb/>2004;8:iii, <lb/>36 Terwee CB, Bot SDM, de Boer MR, et al. Quality criteria <lb/>were proposed for measurement properties of health status <lb/>questionnaires. J Clin Epidemiol 2007;60:34-42. <lb/>37 Caro-Bautista J, Rodríguez-Blázquez C, Perez-Manchon D, et al. <lb/>Validation of living with chronic illness scale in a type 2 diabetes <lb/>mellitus population. Health Qual Life Outcomes 2021;19:93. <lb/>38 National Institute for Care and Health Excellence. Parkinson&apos;s disease <lb/>in over 20s: diagnosis and management. Available: https://www.nice. <lb/>org.uk/guidance/cg35 <lb/>39 Corchon S, Rodriguez-Blazquez C, Carvajal-Carrascal G, et al. <lb/>International Psychometric validation of the living with chronic <lb/>illness scale in Spanish-speaking patients with chronic obstructive <lb/>pulmonary disease. BMJ Open 2021;11:e039973. <lb/>40 Ambrosio L, Perez-Manchon D, Carvajal-Carrascal G, et al. <lb/>International Psychometric validation of the living with chronic illness <lb/>scale in Spanish speaking population with chronic heart failure. Int J <lb/>Environ Res Public Health 2021;18:572:1-13.:. <lb/>41 Meneses Monroy A, Rodríguez-Blázquez C, Ursúa ME, et al. <lb/>Validación de la Escala de Convivencia con Artrosis en Población <lb/>Española. Atención Primaria 2021;53:102044. <lb/>42 Vassilev I, Rogers A, Kennedy A, et al. Social network type and long-<lb/>term condition management support: a cross-sectional study in six <lb/>European countries. PLOS One 2016;11:e0161027. <lb/>43 Roddis JK, Holloway I, Bond C, et al. Living with a long-<lb/>term condition: understanding well-being for individuals with <lb/>Thrombophilia or asthma. Int J Qual Stud Health Well-Being <lb/>2016;11:31530. <lb/>44 Haahr A, Groos H, Sørensen D. Striving for Normality&apos; when coping <lb/>with Parkinson&apos;s disease in everyday life: A Metasynthesis. Int J Nurs <lb/>Stud 2021;118:103923. <lb/>45 Department of Health. The National Service Framework for Long-<lb/>term Conditions, Available: https://www.gov.uk/government/ <lb/>publications/quality-standards-for-supporting-people-with-long-<lb/>term-conditions <lb/>46 National Institute for Care and Health Excellence. Multimorbidity: <lb/>clinical assessment and management. Available: https://www.nice. <lb/>org.uk/guidance/cg56 <lb/></listBibl>
    
    <note place="footnote">Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/>. <lb/>by guest <lb/>on September 10, 2025 <lb/>http://bmjopen.bmj.com/ <lb/>Downloaded from <lb/>10 January 2024. <lb/>10.1136/bmjopen-2023-077978 on <lb/>BMJ Open: first published as </note>


	</text>

</TEI>