<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:448 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01570-5 <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>a high spatial resolution land <lb/>surface phenology dataset for <lb/>ameriFlux and NEON sites <lb/>Minkyu Moon 1 ✉ , andrew D. Richardson 2,3 , thomas Milliman 4 &amp; Mark a. Friedl 1 <lb/>Vegetation phenology is a key control on water, energy, and carbon fluxes in terrestrial ecosystems. <lb/>Because vegetation canopies are heterogeneous, spatially explicit information related to seasonality in <lb/>vegetation activity provides valuable information for studies that use eddy covariance measurements <lb/>to study ecosystem function and land-atmosphere interactions. Here we present a land surface <lb/>phenology (LSP) dataset derived at 3 m spatial resolution from PlanetScope imagery across a range of <lb/>plant functional types and climates in North america. the dataset provides spatially explicit information <lb/>related to the timing of phenophase changes such as the start, peak, and end of vegetation activity, <lb/>along with vegetation index metrics and associated quality assurance flags for the growing seasons of <lb/>2017-2021 for 10 × 10 km windows centred over 104 eddy covariance towers at AmeriFlux and National <lb/>Ecological Observatory Network (NEON) sites. these LSP data can be used to analyse processes <lb/>controlling the seasonality of ecosystem-scale carbon, water, and energy fluxes, to evaluate predictions <lb/>from land surface models, and to assess satellite-based LSP products. <lb/></front>

			<body>Background &amp; Summary <lb/>The AmeriFlux network 1 , which is part of the global FLUXNET 2 network of eddy covariance towers, is <lb/>an important tool for measuring land-atmosphere exchanges of carbon, energy, and water at local to global <lb/>scales 3,4 . The network uses eddy covariance instruments and standardized data processing techniques to pro-<lb/>vide non-destructive measurements of ecosystem fluxes at high temporal resolution, which makes it a unique <lb/>and powerful tool for studying how ecosystems are influencing and responding to climate change 1-4 . However, <lb/>analysing and interpreting how measured fluxes are affected by local environmental conditions, and particularly <lb/>spatio-temporal variation in local vegetation properties, is challenging. Many eddy covariance towers now have <lb/>PhenoCams 5,6 , which provide valuable information and imagery that can be used to characterize and monitor <lb/>canopy conditions in the vicinity of towers. However, PhenoCams have fixed and limited fields of view that only <lb/>capture local conditions in the camera field of view or region of interest. Given the important role of vegetation <lb/>phenology in controlling fluxes of carbon, water, and energy, spatially explicit information related to vegeta-<lb/>tion phenology has significant utility for studies that use eddy covariance tower data to quantify and interpret <lb/>land-atmosphere interactions and their role in ecosystem function and weather and climate processes 7-10 . <lb/>Remote sensing has been used for several decades to monitor and map the land surface phenology (LSP) <lb/>of terrestrial ecosystems 11-14 and has also been used to estimate models of land-atmosphere fluxes calibrated <lb/>to eddy covariance measurements 15-18 . Until recently, however, the temporal frequency of image acquisitions <lb/>required for this latter application has constrained these studies to using coarse spatial resolution imagery (e.g., <lb/>MODIS at 500 m), which limits their utility for understanding how local variability in landscape properties <lb/>influence fluxes. Bolton et al. 19 recently demonstrated that harmonized Landsat and Sentinel-2 data can provide <lb/>high-quality LSP information at 30 m spatial resolution, but even this resolution fails to capture fine-scale varia-<lb/>tion (i.e., below 30 m) in phenology and vegetation cover (related to, for example, species composition or patchy <lb/>vegetation structure) that can influence land-atmosphere fluxes 20-22 . <lb/>Several recent studies have demonstrated that commercially available PlanetScope imagery can be used to <lb/>monitor and map LSP at fine spatial resolution, thereby providing new opportunities to exploit high spatial <lb/></body>

			<front>1 <lb/>Department of earth and environment, Boston University, Boston, USA. 2 School of informatics, computing &amp; cyber <lb/>Systems, Northern Arizona University, Flagstaff, USA. 3 center for ecosystem Science and Society, northern Arizona <lb/>University, Flagstaff, USA. 4 earth Systems Research center, University of new Hampshire, Durham, USA. ✉ e-mail: <lb/>moon.minkyu@gmail.com <lb/>Data DEScRiPtOR <lb/>OPEN <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:448 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01570-5 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>resolution LSP measurements for studies that require spatially explicit information related to vegetation phe-<lb/>nology 23-26 . PlanetScope imagery is acquired by a constellation of CubeSats (180 + as of 2022), and provides <lb/>daily imagery in four bands spanning the visible and near-infrared wavelengths at a nominal spatial resolution <lb/>of 3 m 27 . Although PlanetScope data do not have the radiometric fidelity and geometric accuracy 28,29 of publicly <lb/>available medium spatial resolution imagery from Landsat 8 and Sentinel-2, the higher spatial and temporal <lb/>resolution of PlanetScope imagery creates new opportunities to investigate a wide array of land surface proper-<lb/>ties and processes. For example, Moon et al. 26 used PlanetScope imagery in association with the LSP algorithm <lb/>developed by Bolton et al. 19 and reported that LSP metrics estimated using PlanetScope imagery show strong <lb/>agreement with LSP metrics derived from high-quality publicly available 30 m satellite imagery (i.e., Landsat <lb/>8 and Sentinel 2) and from PhenoCams. Their results demonstrated that PlanetScope imagery captures useful <lb/>information related to vegetation phenology at 3 m spatial resolution across a range of ecosystem types 26 , and <lb/>that fine-scale variation in landscape properties arising from land use, water bodies, species composition, and <lb/>vegetation structure results in substantial spatial variation in phenology that is not captured at medium spatial <lb/>resolution (i.e., 30 m). <lb/>Building on the proof-of-concept provided by Moon et al. 26 , here we present a new LSP dataset derived from <lb/>3 m spatial resolution PlanetScope imagery covering 104 AmeriFlux and NEON sites that encompass a wide <lb/>range of plant functional types, biomes, and climates regimes in North America (Fig. 1). The dataset includes <lb/>standard LSP metrics that are commonly derived from remote sensing such as the day of year corresponding <lb/>to the start, peak, and end of vegetation greenness, along with metrics that provide the maximum, amplitude, <lb/>and growing season sum of the two-band Enhanced Vegetation Index 30 (EVI2) and associated quality assurance <lb/>flags. Data for the period 2017 to 2021 for areas that encompass the flux footprint and surrounding landscapes <lb/>at each tower site (10 × 10 km = 10 8 m 2 ) are included in the dataset. To document and illustrate the quality of <lb/>these data, we present results from a comprehensive assessment using two independent data sources: (1) LSP <lb/>metrics from the Multisensor Land Surface Phenology dataset, which is derived from Harmonized Landsat 8 <lb/>and Sentinel-2 imagery 31 ; and (2) phenometrics from the PhenoCam V3 Dataset. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Site selection. We selected 104 sites covering a range of ecological, land cover, and climate conditions <lb/>across North America (Table 1). These sites were selected because they are part of either the National Ecological <lb/>Observatory Network (NEON) or AmeriFlux network, all have PhenoCams, and each has at least one year of <lb/>available flux data between 2017 and 2021. Among the included sites, 44 are part of the NEON. <lb/>PlanetScope image database compilation. The LSP metrics included in the dataset are derived from a <lb/>database of daily 3 m PlanetScope imagery. To compile this database, a Python script was created to search, request, <lb/>and download imagery using Planet&apos;s RESTful API interface (https://developers.planet.com/docs/apis/data/). <lb/>For each site, the area of interest (AOI) was defined using a GeoJSON file that prescribed a 10 by 10 km box <lb/>centered over the flux tower at each site. Each GeoJSON was then used to submit search requests to the API. As <lb/>part of the search process, the following filters were applied to ensure that good quality images with adequate <lb/>clear sky views and high-accuracy geolocation were downloaded: (1) quality category identified as &apos;standard&apos;; (2) <lb/>cloud cover less than or equal to 50%; and (3) ground control is &apos;true&apos; . Filtering was performed using all available <lb/>Fig. 1 Geographic distribution of sites included in the PLSP dataset across North America. Each site includes <lb/>data from a 10 × 10 km square centred over one AmeriFlux or NEON site (n = 104). Note that several adjacent <lb/>sites are not distinguishable on the map. The background map shows the IGBP land cover type from the MODIS <lb/>Land Cover Type product 35 . <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:448 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01570-5 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>PlanetScope &apos;PSScene4Band&apos; imagery from 2016 to 2022. Once the API completed the search, the Python script <lb/>read the search results, submitted orders, and the selected imagery was downloaded from Planet&apos;s cloud-based <lb/>system to local storage. During execution of the Python script, a log file was created to keep track of successful <lb/>Site Code <lb/>Site Full Name <lb/>Site Code <lb/>Site Full Name <lb/>PR-xGU <lb/>NEON Guanica Forest <lb/>US-Var <lb/>Vaira Ranch <lb/>PR-xLA <lb/>NEON Lajas Experimental Station <lb/>US-Vcm <lb/>Valles Caldera Mixed Conifer <lb/>US-ALQ <lb/>Allequash Creek Site <lb/>US-Vcp <lb/>Valles Caldera Ponderosa Pine <lb/>US-ARM <lb/>ARM Southern Great Plains site <lb/>US-Vcs <lb/>Valles Caldera Sulphur Springs Mixed Conifer <lb/>US-Bi1 <lb/>Bouldin Island Alfalfa <lb/>US-WCr <lb/>Willow Creek <lb/>US-Bi2 <lb/>Bouldin Island corn <lb/>US-Whs <lb/>Walnut Gulch Lucky Hills Shrub <lb/>US-BMM <lb/>Bangtail Mountain Meadow <lb/>US-Wjs <lb/>Willard Juniper Savannah <lb/>US-BRG <lb/>Bayles Road Grassland Tower <lb/>US-Wkg <lb/>Walnut Gulch Kendall Grasslands <lb/>US-CF1 <lb/>CAF-LTAR Cook East <lb/>US-xAB <lb/>NEON Abby Road <lb/>US-CF2 <lb/>CAF-LTAR Cook West <lb/>US-xAE <lb/>NEON Klemme Range Research Station <lb/>US-CF3 <lb/>CAF-LTAR Boyd North <lb/>US-xBL <lb/>NEON Blandy Experimental Farm <lb/>US-CF4 <lb/>CAF-LTAR Boyd South <lb/>US-xBN <lb/>NEON Caribou Creek -Poker Flats Watershed <lb/>US-Ha1 <lb/>Harvard Forest EMS Tower <lb/>US-xBR <lb/>NEON Bartlett Experimental Forest <lb/>US-Ha2 <lb/>Harvard Forest Hemlock Site <lb/>US-xCL <lb/>NEON LBJ National Grassland <lb/>US-HB1 <lb/>North Inlet Crab Haul Creek <lb/>US-xCP <lb/>NEON Central Plains Experimental Range <lb/>US-HB2 <lb/>Hobcaw Barony Mature Longleaf Pine <lb/>US-xDC <lb/>NEON Dakota Coteau Field School <lb/>US-HB3 <lb/>Hobcaw Barony Longleaf Pine Restoration <lb/>US-xDJ <lb/>NEON Delta Junction <lb/>US-Ho1 <lb/>Howland Forest <lb/>US-xDL <lb/>NEON Dead Lake <lb/>US-ICs <lb/>Imnavait Creek Watershed Wet Sedge Tundra US-xDS <lb/>NEON Disney Wilderness Preserve <lb/>US-KFS <lb/>Kansas Field Station <lb/>US-xGR <lb/>NEON Great Smoky Mountains National Park <lb/>US-Me2 <lb/>Metolius mature ponderosa pine <lb/>US-xHA <lb/>NEON Harvard Forest <lb/>US-Me6 <lb/>Metolius Young Pine Burn <lb/>US-xHE <lb/>NEON Healy <lb/>US-MMS <lb/>Morgan Monroe State Forest <lb/>US-xJE <lb/>NEON Jones Ecological Research Center <lb/>US-Mpj <lb/>Mountainair Pinyon-Juniper Woodland <lb/>US-xJR <lb/>NEON Jornada LTER <lb/>US-Myb <lb/>Mayberry Wetland <lb/>US-xKA <lb/>NEON Konza Prairie Biological Station-Relocatable <lb/>US-NC2 <lb/>NC_Loblolly Plantation <lb/>US-xKZ <lb/>NEON Konza Prairie Biological Station <lb/>US-NC3 <lb/>NC_Clearcut#3 <lb/>US-xLE <lb/>NEON Lenoir Landing <lb/>US-NC4 <lb/>NC_AlligatorRiver <lb/>US-xMB <lb/>NEON Moab <lb/>US-Ne1 <lb/>Mead-irrigated continuous maize site <lb/>US-xML <lb/>NEON Mountain Lake Biological Station <lb/>US-Ne2 <lb/>Mead-irrigated maize-soybean rotation site <lb/>US-xNG <lb/>NEON Northern Great Plains Research Laboratory <lb/>US-Ne3 <lb/>Mead-rainfed maize-soybean rotation site <lb/>US-xNQ <lb/>NEON Onaqui-Ault <lb/>US-NR1 <lb/>Niwot Ridge Forest <lb/>US-xNW <lb/>NEON Niwot Ridge Mountain Research Station <lb/>US-PFa <lb/>Park Falls <lb/>US-xPU <lb/>NEON Pu&apos;u Maka&apos;ala Natural Area Reserve <lb/>US-Rms <lb/>RCEW Mountain Big Sagebrush <lb/>US-xRM <lb/>NEON Rocky Mountain National Park <lb/>US-Ro4 <lb/>Rosemount Prairie <lb/>US-xRN <lb/>NEON Oak Ridge National Lab <lb/>US-Ro5 <lb/>Rosemount I18_South <lb/>US-xSB <lb/>NEON Ordway-Swisher Biological Station <lb/>US-Ro6 <lb/>Rosemount I18_North <lb/>US-xSC <lb/>NEON Smithsonian Conservation Biology Institute <lb/>US-Rws <lb/>Reynolds Creek Wyoming big sagebrush <lb/>US-xSE <lb/>NEON Smithsonian Environmental Research Center <lb/>US-Seg <lb/>Sevilleta grassland <lb/>US-xSJ <lb/>NEON San Joaquin Experimental Range <lb/>US-Ses <lb/>Sevilleta shrubland <lb/>US-xSL <lb/>NEON North Sterling <lb/>US-Sne <lb/>Sherman Island Restored Wetland <lb/>US-xSP <lb/>NEON Soaproot Saddle <lb/>US-Snf <lb/>Sherman Barn <lb/>US-xSR <lb/>NEON Santa Rita Experimental Range <lb/>US-SRG <lb/>Santa Rita Grassland <lb/>US-xST <lb/>NEON Steigerwaldt Land Services <lb/>US-SRM <lb/>Santa Rita Mesquite <lb/>US-xTA <lb/>NEON Talladega National Forest <lb/>US-Syv <lb/>Sylvania Wilderness Area <lb/>US-xTE <lb/>NEON Lower Teakettle <lb/>US-Ton <lb/>Tonzi Ranch <lb/>US-xTL <lb/>NEON Toolik <lb/>US-Tw1 <lb/>Twitchell Wetland West Pond <lb/>US-xTR <lb/>NEON Treehaven <lb/>US-Tw3 <lb/>Twitchell Alfalfa <lb/>US-xUK <lb/>NEON The University of Kansas Field Station <lb/>US-Tw4 <lb/>Twitchell East End Wetland <lb/>US-xUN <lb/>NEON Univ. of Notre Dame Environmental Research Center <lb/>US-Tw5 <lb/>East Pond Wetland <lb/>US-xWD <lb/>NEON Woodworth <lb/>US-UMB <lb/>Univ. of Mich. Biological Station <lb/>US-xWR <lb/>NEON Wind River Experimental Forest <lb/>US-UMd <lb/>UMBS Disturbance <lb/>US-xYE <lb/>NEON Yellowstone Northern Range <lb/>Table 1. List of AmeriFlux and NEON sites included in the dataset. . <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:448 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01570-5 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>and failed orders. If an order failed, the script was run again targeting the specific order that failed. The resulting <lb/>dataset included over 1.8 million unique files with, on average, 3,885 scene images for each site (i.e., the number <lb/>of images, on average, that overlap part of each 10 by 10 km site), and had a total volume of 62.2 TB. <lb/>image processing. To ensure that high-quality image time series were used to generate LSP metrics, we <lb/>used PlanetScope per-pixel quality assurance information to exclude pixels that had low quality in all 4 bands <lb/>(i.e., blue, green, red, and near-infrared). Specifically, we excluded pixels where the Unusable Data Mask (layer <lb/>&apos;umd&apos;) was not 0 (i.e., we retained pixels that were not cloud contaminated or located in non-image areas) and <lb/>pixels where the Usable Data Mask (layer &apos;umd2&apos;) is 0 (i.e., we retained pixels that were not contaminated by <lb/>snow, shadow, haze, or clouds). We then cropped all the images to exclude pixels outside of the 10 by 10 km win-<lb/>dow centered over each tower. We selected this window size based on published results showing that 80% of the <lb/>average monthly footprint at eddy covariance towers ranges from 10 3 to 10 7 square meters 22 . Note that the swath <lb/>for PlanetScope imagery often did not cover entire sites and some sites (e.g., the tall tower at US-Pfa) have larger <lb/>footprints than other sites. Similarly, most sites had multiple PlanetScope image acquisitions on the same day. <lb/>To create image time series, we mosaiced all available imagery at each site on each date, and, under the assump-<lb/>tion that geolocation error was non-systematic and modest, we created a single image for each date using the <lb/>mean surface reflectance for pixels with multiple values on the same day. The resulting database of daily surface <lb/>Layer Name <lb/>Description <lb/>Units <lb/>Scale Factor Valid Range Fill value <lb/>NumCycles <lb/>Number of phenological cycles detected in <lb/>target year <lb/>Number of cycles <lb/>1 <lb/>0-6 <lb/>32767 <lb/>First Vegetation Cycle: Largest EVI2 amplitude cycle Phenology Timing Metrics <lb/>OGI <lb/>Onset Greenness Increase (Date of 15% <lb/>greenness increase) <lb/>Day of year (January 1 of target <lb/>year = 1) <lb/>1 <lb/>−181-548 <lb/>32767 <lb/>50PCGI <lb/>50 Percent Greenness Increase (Date of 50% <lb/>greenness increase) <lb/>Day of year (January 1 of target <lb/>year = 1) <lb/>1 <lb/>−181-548 <lb/>32767 <lb/>OGMx <lb/>Onset Greenness Maximum (Date of 90% <lb/>greenness increase) <lb/>Day of year (January 1 of target <lb/>year = 1) <lb/>1 <lb/>−181-548 <lb/>32767 <lb/>Peak <lb/>Date of Cycle Peak <lb/>Day of year (January 1 of target <lb/>year = 1) <lb/>1 <lb/>1-366 <lb/>32767 <lb/>OGD <lb/>Onset Greenness Decrease (Date of 10% <lb/>greenness decrease) <lb/>Day of year (January 1 of target <lb/>year = 1) <lb/>1 <lb/>−181-548 <lb/>32767 <lb/>50PCGD <lb/>50 Percent Greenness Decrease (Date of 50% <lb/>greenness decrease) <lb/>Day of year (January 1 of target <lb/>year = 1) <lb/>1 <lb/>−181-548 <lb/>32767 <lb/>OGMn <lb/>Onset Greenness Minimum (Date of 85% <lb/>greenness decrease) <lb/>Day of year (January 1 of target <lb/>year = 1) <lb/>1 <lb/>−181-548 <lb/>32767 <lb/>Vegetation Indices <lb/>EVImax <lb/>Maximum EVI2 during vegetation cycle <lb/>-<lb/>0.0001 <lb/>0-10000 <lb/>32767 <lb/>EVIamp <lb/>EVI2 Amplitude during vegetation cycle <lb/>-<lb/>0.0001 <lb/>0-10000 <lb/>32767 <lb/>EVIarea <lb/>Integrated EVI2 during vegetation cycle <lb/>-<lb/>0.01 <lb/>0-32766 <lb/>32767 <lb/>Second Vegetation Cycle: Second Largest EVI2 amplitude cycle Phenology Timing Metrics <lb/>OGI_2 <lb/>Onset Greenness Increase (Date of 15% <lb/>greenness increase) <lb/>Day of year (January 1 of target <lb/>year = 1) <lb/>1 <lb/>−181-548 <lb/>32767 <lb/>50PCGI_2 <lb/>50 Percent Greenness Increase (Date of 50% <lb/>greenness increase) <lb/>Day of year (January 1 of target <lb/>year = 1) <lb/>1 <lb/>−181-548 <lb/>32767 <lb/>OGMx_2 <lb/>Onset Greenness Maximum (Date of 90% <lb/>greenness increase) <lb/>Day of year (January 1 of target <lb/>year = 1) <lb/>1 <lb/>−181-548 <lb/>32767 <lb/>Peak_2 <lb/>Date of Cycle Peak <lb/>Day of year (January 1 of target <lb/>year = 1) <lb/>1 <lb/>1-366 <lb/>32767 <lb/>OGD_2 <lb/>Onset Greenness Decrease (Date of 10% <lb/>greenness decrease) <lb/>Day of year (January 1 of target <lb/>year = 1) <lb/>1 <lb/>−181-548 <lb/>32767 <lb/>50PCGD_2 <lb/>50 Percent Greenness Decrease (Date of 50% <lb/>greenness decrease) <lb/>Day of year (January 1 of target <lb/>year = 1) <lb/>1 <lb/>−181-548 <lb/>32767 <lb/>OGMn_2 <lb/>Onset Greenness Minimum (Date of 85% <lb/>greenness decrease) <lb/>Day of year (January 1 of target <lb/>year = 1) <lb/>1 <lb/>−181-548 <lb/>32767 <lb/>Vegetation Indices <lb/>EVImax_2 <lb/>EVI2 maximum during vegetation cycle <lb/>-<lb/>0.0001 <lb/>0-10000 <lb/>32767 <lb/>EVIamp_2 <lb/>EVI2 Amplitude during vegetation cycle <lb/>-<lb/>0.0001 <lb/>0-10000 <lb/>32767 <lb/>EVIarea_2 <lb/>EVI2 area during vegetation cycle <lb/>-<lb/>0.01 <lb/>0-32766 <lb/>32767 <lb/>Quality Assurance (QA) <lb/>QA <lb/>Quality Assurance for first vegetation cycle <lb/>-<lb/>1 <lb/>1-4 <lb/>-<lb/>QA_2 <lb/>Quality Assurance for second vegetation cycle -<lb/>1 <lb/>1-4 <lb/>-<lb/>numObs <lb/>Number of days with clear observations in <lb/>calendar year <lb/>Days <lb/>1 <lb/>0-366 <lb/>32767 <lb/>Table 2. Product table. <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:448 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01570-5 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>reflectance images were sorted in chronological order, sub-divided into 200 sub-areas at each site (i.e., 0.5 km 2 <lb/>each), and then stored as image stacks to facilitate parallel processing to estimate LSP metrics, where each image <lb/>stack included all images from July 1, 2016 through January 31, 2022. <lb/>Creation of daily EVI2 time series. To estimate LSP metrics we adapted the algorithm described by Bolton <lb/>et al. 19 , which was originally implemented to estimate LSP metrics from harmonized Landsat and Sentinel-2 <lb/>(HLS) imagery, for use with PlanetScope imagery. Prior to LSP estimation, daily images of the two-band <lb/>Enhanced Vegetation Index 30 (EVI2) data were generated from PlanetScope imagery and then interpolated to <lb/>create smooth time series of daily EVI2 values at each pixel in three main steps. First, sources of variation related <lb/>to clouds, atmospheric aerosols, and snow were detected and removed from the EVI2 time series at each pixel <lb/>based on data masks provided with PlanetScope imagery (described above) and outlier detection criteria (i.e., <lb/>de-spiking and removing negative EVI2 values). Second, we identified the &apos;background&apos; EVI2 value (the mini-<lb/>mum EVI2 value outside of the growing season) based on the 10 th percentile of snow-free EVI2 values at each <lb/>pixel. Any dates with EVI2 values below the background value were replaced with the background EVI2. Third, <lb/>penalized cubic smoothing splines were used to gap-fill and smooth the data to create daily EVI2 time series <lb/>across all years of available data. Complete details on these steps are given in Bolton et al. 19 . This approach has <lb/>been tested and shown to yield PlanetScope EVI2 time series that are consistent with both EVI2 time series from <lb/>HLS imagery and time series of the Green Chromatic Coordinate (G CC ) from PhenoCam imagery 26 . We used <lb/>the EVI2 instead of other vegetation indices such as the Enhanced Vegetation Index (EVI) or the Normalized <lb/>Difference Vegetation Index (NDVI) because EVI2 is less sensitive to noise from atmospheric effects relative to <lb/>EVI and is less prone to saturation over dense canopies and noise from variation in soil background reflectance <lb/>over sparse canopies relative to the NDVI 30,32 . Thus, phenological metrics from EVI2 time series tend to have <lb/>better agreement with PhenoCam observations than corresponding metrics from NDVI 33 . <lb/>identifying phenological cycles. Prior to estimating LSP metrics, we first identity unique growth cycles by <lb/>searching the period before and after each local peak in the daily PlanetScope EVI2 time series. To be considered <lb/>a valid growth cycle, the difference in EVI2 between the local minimum and maximum was required to be at <lb/>least 0.1 and greater than 35% of the total range in EVI2 over the 24-month period centered on the target year ± 6 <lb/>Fig. 2 Greenup dates and EVI2 seasonal amplitudes in 2019. Each column represents a different site. Left: US-<lb/>Ro5 (cropland); middle: US-NC2 (pine plantation); and right: US-Tw5 (wetland). The upper row shows the day <lb/>of year corresponding to 50PCGI and the lower row shows the EVI2 amplitude at each 3 m pixel. The spatial <lb/>extent for each image is 10 by 10 km. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:448 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01570-5 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>months. The start of each growth cycle is restricted to occur within 185 days before the peak of the cycle and at <lb/>least 30 days after the previous peak. The same procedure was applied in reverse at the end of the cycle to con-<lb/>strain the range of end dates for each growth cycle. This procedure is applied recursively over the time series until <lb/>each local peak has been assessed and all growth cycles (with associated green-up period, peak greenness, and <lb/>green-down period) are identified in the time series at each pixel. As part of this process, the algorithm provides <lb/>the number of growth cycles identified for each year in the time series. <lb/>Retrieving LSP metrics. LSP metrics are estimated for each pixel in up to two growth cycles in each year. <lb/>If no growth cycles are detected, the algorithm returns fill values for all timing metrics, but does report values for <lb/>the four annual metrics: EVImax, EVIamp, EVIarea, and numObs (see below). If more than two growth cycles are <lb/>detected, which is rare but does occur (e.g., alfalfa, which is harvested and regrows multiple times in a year), the <lb/>algorithm records 7 LSP metrics for each of the two growth cycles with the largest EVI2 amplitudes. The resulting <lb/>dataset includes seven &apos;timing&apos; metrics that identify the timing of greenup onset, mid-greenup, maturity, peak <lb/>EVI2, greendown onset, mid-greendown, and dormancy. These metrics record the day of year (DOY) when the <lb/>EVI2 time series exceeds 15%, 50%, and 90% of EVI2 amplitude during the greenup phase, reaches its maximum, <lb/>and goes below 90%, 50%, and 15% of EVI2 amplitude during the greendown phase. In addition, the algorithm <lb/>records three complementary metrics that characterize the magnitude of seasonality and total &apos;greenness&apos; at each <lb/>pixel in each growth cycle: the EVI2 amplitude, the maximum EVI2, and the growing season integral of EVI2, <lb/>which is calculated as the sum of daily EVI2 values between the growth cycle start-and end-dates (i.e., from <lb/>greenup onset to dormancy). <lb/>Fig. 3 Five years of daily variation in vegetation activity at the Jornada LTER site (US-xJR). Images in the upper <lb/>row show the day of year corresponding to the timing of maximum EVI2 in each PlanetScope pixel in 2017, <lb/>2018, and 2021. The PhenoCam is located at the centre of the site. The second row shows PhenoCam images <lb/>acquired on dates corresponding to the maximum EVI2. The bottom panel shows EVI2 time series from a single <lb/>PlanetScope pixel centred over the PhenoCam (dots: raw data; line: smoothing spline fit to data). Note, grey <lb/>areas in the top row correspond to pixels where the seasonal amplitude of PlanetScope imagery did not exceed <lb/>0.1, which was the case for nearly all pixels in 2018. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:448 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01570-5 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>Quality assurance flags. Quality Assurance (QA) values are estimated at each pixel based on the density of <lb/>observations and the quality of spline fits during each phenophase of the growing season. A QA value of 1 (high <lb/>quality) is assigned if the correlation between observed versus fitted daily EVI2 values is greater than 0.75 and <lb/>the maximum gap during each phase is less than 30 days. A QA value of 2 (moderate quality) is assigned if the <lb/>correlation coefficient is less than 0.75 or the length of the maximum gap over the segment is greater than 30 days. <lb/>A QA value of 3 (low quality) is assigned if the correlation coefficient is less than 0.75 and the length of the maxi-<lb/>mum gap over the segment is greater than 30 days. A QA value of 4 is assigned if no growth cycles were detected <lb/>or insufficient data were available to run the algorithm. <lb/>Data Records <lb/>The PlanetScope Land Surface Phenology (PLSP) dataset 34 consists of 24 data layers (Table 2) and spans 5 years <lb/>(2017-2021) for each site. Each site and year of data is saved in a single Network Common Data Form (netCDF) <lb/>file, and the dataset is permanently and publicly available through the Oak Ridge National Lab Distributed <lb/>Active Archive Centre for Biogeochemical Dynamics (https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/2033). <lb/>The structure of the dataset is as follows: <lb/>&lt;Site Code__Site Full Name&gt; <lb/>└─── PSLP_&lt;Year&gt;.nc <lb/>Here, &quot;Site Code&quot; and &quot;Site Full Name&quot; are the AmeriFlux site code and full site name, respectively, as pre-<lb/>sented in Table 1, and &quot;Year&quot; is the year of the estimated LSP metric from 2017 to 2021. Each netCDF file <lb/>includes all 24 data layers for each year. Note that even though the PlanetScope imagery we use to create this <lb/>Fig. 4 Phenological cycles at the Bouldin Island (Alfalfa) site (US-Bi1) in 2019. Images in the upper row show <lb/>the Cropland Data Layer 36 , the number of phenological cycles, and the day of year corresponding to 50PCGI in <lb/>2019. The PhenoCam is located at the centre of the site. The second row shows PhenoCam images acquired on <lb/>dates corresponding to the points identified by arrows in the bottom panel. The bottom panel shows EVI2 and <lb/>G CC time series from a single PlanetScope pixel centred over the PhenoCam and PhenoCam imagery. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:448 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01570-5 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>dataset starts in 2016, we exclude this year from the PLSP dataset because the density of EVI2 times series is too <lb/>sparse to estimate phenometrics with high confidence. To facilitate access to the location and boundary of each <lb/>site, we include the GeoJSON file for each site as ancillary data. <lb/>technical Validation <lb/>A detailed technical validation of LSP metrics from PlanetScope imagery is presented in Moon et al. 26 . Results <lb/>from that study demonstrated that LSP metrics estimated from PlanetScope image times series show strong <lb/>agreement with LSP records derived from both HLS and PhenoCams, and that LSP metrics from PlanetScope <lb/>capture information related to fine-scale variation in LSP that is not captured in medium or coarse spatial res-<lb/>olution LSP datasets 26 . Below we present additional validation that extends these previous results for the sites <lb/>included in the PLSP dataset. First, we present images showing the mid-greenup date (50PCGI) and the EVI2 <lb/>seasonal amplitude for three representative sites included in the dataset. Second, we present results showing <lb/>the timing of peak EVI2 and associated PhenoCam images at the Jornada LTER site (US-xJR), which does not <lb/>exhibit a clear annual cycle of vegetation activity. Third, we present phenological cycles at the Bouldin Island <lb/>Alfalfa site (US-Bi1) to illustrate how our algorithm handles an extreme case with multiple growth cycles within <lb/>a year. Fourth, we compare mid-greenup and mid-greendown dates (i.e., 50PCGI and 50PCGD, respectively) <lb/>from PlanetScope imagery against an independent LSP dataset derived from HLS time series. Specifically, we <lb/>compare the PLSP dataset against V011 of the MSLSP30NA 31 data product (hereafter, MSLSP), which is pub-<lb/>licly available via NASA&apos;s Land Processes Distributed Active Archive Centre. Fifth, we compare 50PCGI and <lb/>50PCGD from the PLSP dataset against corresponding values estimated from PhenoCam G CC time series. <lb/>Figure 2 shows representative images showing PLSP greenup dates and the seasonal amplitude of EVI2 <lb/>for three sites with different landscapes included in the dataset. Each site has a land cover type (assigned <lb/>by AmeriFlux) that is representative of the flux tower footprint. However, as is evident in these images, the <lb/>10 × 10 km 2 areas surrounding these sites include a range of vegetation and land cover, which are manifested in <lb/>the LSP data. For example, the primary land cover type for the US-Ro5 site (first column in Fig. 2) is cropland <lb/>and greenup dates for most of the area surrounding the tower at the centre of the image occur around DOY 170. <lb/>However, non-cropland areas (particularly in riparian areas) show greenup dates that are several weeks earlier, <lb/>which reflects the impact of land management on vegetation phenology at the site. Further, the high spatial reso-<lb/>lution of PlanetScope imagery captures fine-scale spatial variation in land surface phenology related to fine-scale <lb/>variation in land cover (i.e., vegetated versus non-vegetated areas) associated with buildings, roads, and small <lb/>water bodies. At the US-NC2 site (second column in Fig. 2), pine plantations (green and purple in the top row) <lb/>show earlier greenup dates with low seasonal EVI2 amplitudes, while croplands show later greenup dates with <lb/>large EVI2 amplitudes. The third column in Fig. 2 shows LSP images centred over AmeriFlux site US-Tw5, <lb/>which is located in a wetland and is surrounded by heterogeneous land cover that includes a mix of wetlands, <lb/>Fig. 5 Comparison of PLSP and MSLSP metrics. Each plot compares average values for randomly selected 3 × 3 <lb/>pixel windows in the MSLSP dataset against average values for co-located 30 × 30 pixel windows from the PLSP <lb/>dataset (i.e., 90 by 90 m windows). Acronyms for the various LSP metrics are given in Table 2. <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:448 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01570-5 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>croplands, natural vegetation, and water bodies. Again, the LSP metrics in the PLSP dataset capture fine-scale <lb/>variation in LSP across the site. <lb/>Figure 3 presents PLSP images showing the timing maximum EVI2 at the Jornada LTER site in 2017, 2018, and <lb/>2021 (first row), PhenoCam images on dates corresponding to maximum EVI2 from PlanetScope (second row), and <lb/>EVI2 time series from PlanetScope for 2017-2021 (third row). Phenology at this site shows either weak seasonality or <lb/>no clear annual cycle of vegetation activity over the five-year period. In 2017, only 15% of pixels in the 10 by 10 km site <lb/>exhibited sufficient phenological variation to be detected by the PLSP algorithm (i.e., 15% of pixels exhibited seasonal <lb/>EVI2 amplitudes that exceeded 0.1). In 2018, less than 1% of pixels met this criterion. In contrast, over 75% of pixels <lb/>in the site exhibited a measurable phenological cycle in 2021. This pattern is corroborated by PhenoCam images cor-<lb/>responding to the date of maximum PlanetScope EVI2 that are shown in the second row of Fig. 3, and demonstrates <lb/>how the PLSP dataset is able to capture relatively subtle year-to-year variation in phenology. <lb/>Figure 4 shows PLSP and PhenoCam data from the US-Bi1 site, which is dominated by croplands and includes a <lb/>variety of crop species. The PhenoCam&apos;s field of view faces a field with alfalfa (second row), a crop with short growth <lb/>cycles (generally less than two months) that is harvested multiple times per year. Corn fields occupy most of the land-<lb/>scape, exhibit relatively uniform phenology with one growth cycle, and have 50PCGI dates that range from DOY 150 <lb/>to 190 (first row). PlanetScope EVI2 and PhenoCam G CC time series both capture the short growth cycles of alfalfa <lb/>(i.e., six growth cycles in 2019; third row). However, due to heuristics encoded in our algorithm (among others, that <lb/>the start of each growth cycle is restricted to occur at least 30 days prior to the peak), the algorithm used to create <lb/>the PLSP dataset does not provide a realistic representation of phenology for the alfalfa fields at this site (i.e., most <lb/>pixels assigned as alfalfa are estimated to have three growth cycles, and the dataset provides phenometrics for only <lb/>two growth cycles). That said, PlanetScope EVI2 time series clearly capture phenological dynamics in the field that <lb/>are consistent with ground-based PhenoCam G CC data. Hence, it should be possible to adjust our algorithm in future <lb/>versions of the dataset to account for locations with more than two growing seasons each year. <lb/>Figure 5 provides a comprehensive comparison of DOY phenometrics estimated from the MSLSP and PLSP <lb/>datasets that includes data from 101 sites and six day-of-year phenometrics. Three sites were excluded (in Hawaii <lb/>and Puerto Rico) because they were outside of the geographic coverage of the MSLSP dataset. This comparison <lb/>uses average values from co-located 3 × 3 pixel windows from MSLSP images and 30 × 30 pixel windows from <lb/>PLSP images (i.e., covering 90 by 90 m windows for both datasets) for 100,000 randomly sampled points across <lb/>all sites from 2017 to 2019. Overall, there was strong agreement between LSP metrics from the PLPS and MSLSP <lb/>datasets: the minimum correlation (r) is 0.83; the maximum root-mean-square error (RMSE) is 26 days; and <lb/>the maximum bias (i.e., PLSP -MSLSP) is −7.2 days. Agreement was strongest for LSP metrics corresponding <lb/>to the timing of maximum greenness and 50% greenup and greendown (i.e., OGMx, 50PCGI and 50PCGD, <lb/>respectively), and was weakest for LSP metrics representing the start and end of growing seasons (i.e., OGI and <lb/>OGMn), which showed modestly lower agreement and higher RMSEs. These lower agreements for OGI and <lb/>OGMn can be attributed to the fact that these metrics are most susceptible to artefacts from image processing <lb/>such as screening for snow-and cloud-contaminated pixels and determination of background EVI2 values. <lb/>As a final basis for assessing the PLSLP dataset, we compared phenometrics from PlanetScope to correspond-<lb/>ing phenometrics from PhenoCam G CC time series (Fig. 6). Across 5 years of PLSP measurements and 101 sites, <lb/>the comparison includes PhenoCam imagery from 207 individual cameras (Supplementary Table 1), yielding <lb/>803 and 816 site-years of greenup and geendown dates, respectively. To perform this comparison, we used the <lb/>average value of PLSP metrics for 5 × 5 pixel windows located 30 m north of each PhenoCam camera. We used <lb/>this strategy because over 75% of the PhenoCams we used are oriented to face north. (Supplementary Table 1). <lb/>And, given their proximity, the same PLSP value was used for comparisons of phenometrics from multiple ROIs <lb/>within a single camera scene. Consistent with results comparing LSP metrics from the PLSP dataset against LSP <lb/>metrics from the MSLSP dataset (i.e., Fig. 5), there is strong agreement between PLSP data and phenometrics <lb/>from PhenoCam (r ≥ 0.87; RMSE ≤ 25 days; absolute bias ≤ 4.5 days). Note that even though phenometrics from <lb/>PhenoCam and both PLSP and MSLSP are derived from different vegetation indices (i.e., G CC versus EVI2), <lb/>Fig. 6 Comparison between PLSP and PhenoCam phenometrics. The comparison is based on average values <lb/>for 5 × 5 pixel windows from PLSP images centred over each PhenoCam (i.e., 15 by 15 m). Colors indicate the <lb/>IGBP land cover class assigned to each site by AmeriFlux or NEON. <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:448 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01570-5 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>previous studies have demonstrated that phenological metrics derived from these two data sources show strong <lb/>agreement 19,26 . Hence, once again, these results support the conclusion that LSP metrics included in the PLSLP <lb/>dataset accurately capture the seasonality of vegetation activity at high spatial resolution across the sites included <lb/>in the dataset. <lb/>Usage Notes <lb/>At the time we processed the data (i.e., early 2022), time series of PlanetScope imagery did not cover the first <lb/>six months of 2022. Hence, time series of EVI2 data did not cover the full period required by our algorithm to <lb/>retrieve phenometrics in 2021. To overcome this, we used EVI2 time series data from 2021 in place of data that <lb/>had not yet been acquired (i.e., we filled data from February to June in 2022 using data from 2021). To evaluate <lb/>the impact of this strategy, we performed a sensitivity analysis (results not shown), which indicated that this <lb/>approach had minimal impact on the quality of phenometrics in 2021. Also, unfortunately, our license agree-<lb/>ment prevents us from distributing the quality-controlled and gap-filled EVI2 time series that we generated as <lb/>intermediate products, which might also be useful to the community. As a compromise, all the source code that <lb/>we used to generate these data are publicly available on our GitHub repository (see below), which allows inter-<lb/>ested readers to generate these data themselves. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">code availability <lb/>Python and R source code to download and process the PlanetScope imagery and generate the product can be <lb/>obtained through a public repository at https://github.com/BU-LCSC/PLSP. R source code for generating the <lb/>figures in the Technical Validation section is also available on the same repository. <lb/></div>

			<front>Received: 17 March 2022; Accepted: 19 July 2022; <lb/>Published: xx xx xxxx <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Novick, K. A. et al. The AmeriFlux network: A coalition of the willing. Agr. Forest Meteoro. 249, 444-456 (2018). <lb/>2. Pastorello, G. et al. The FLUXNET2015 dataset and the ONEFlux processing pipeline for eddy covariance data. Sci Data 7, 225 <lb/>(2020). <lb/>3. van Gorsel, E. et al. Preface: OzFlux: a network for the study of ecosystem carbon and water dynamics across Australia and New <lb/>Zealand. Biogeosciences 15, 349-352 (2018). <lb/>4. Baldocchi, D. et al. FLUXNET: A New Tool to Study the Temporal and Spatial Variability of Ecosystem-Scale Carbon Dioxide, Water <lb/>Vapor, and Energy Flux Densities. Bull. Amer. Meteor. Soc. 82, 2415-2434 (2001). <lb/>5. Seyednasrollah, B. et al. Tracking vegetation phenology across diverse biomes using Version 2.0 of the PhenoCam Dataset. Scientific <lb/>Data 6, 222 (2019). <lb/>6. Richardson, A. D. et al. Tracking vegetation phenology across diverse North American biomes using PhenoCam imagery. Scientific <lb/>Data 5, 180028 (2018). <lb/>7. Piao, S. et al. Plant phenology and global climate change: current progresses and challenges. Global Change Biology https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1111/gcb.14619 (2019). <lb/>8. Peano, D. et al. Plant phenology evaluation of CRESCENDO land surface models -Part 1: Start and end of the growing season. <lb/>Biogeosciences 18, 2405-2428 (2021). <lb/>9. Xu, X., Riley, W. J., Koven, C. D., Jia, G. &amp; Zhang, X. Earlier leaf-out warms air in the north. Nat. Clim. Chang. 10, 370-375 (2020). <lb/>10. Moon, M., Li, D., Liao, W., Rigden, A. J. &amp; Friedl, M. A. Modification of surface energy balance during springtime: The relative <lb/>importance of biophysical and meteorological changes. Agricultural and Forest Meteorology 284, 107905 (2020). <lb/>11. Reed, B. C. et al. Measuring phenological variability from satellite imagery. Journal of Vegetation Science 5, 703-714 (1994). <lb/>12. White, M. A. et al. Intercomparison, interpretation, and assessment of spring phenology in North America estimated from remote <lb/>sensing for 1982-2006. Global Change Biology 15, 2335-2359 (2009). <lb/>13. Zhang, X. et al. Monitoring vegetation phenology using MODIS. Remote Sensing of Environment 84, 471-475 (2003). <lb/>14. Jonsson, P. &amp; Eklundh, L. Seasonality extraction by function fitting to time-series of satellite sensor data. IEEE Transactions on <lb/>Geoscience and Remote Sensing 40, 1824-1832 (2002). <lb/>15. Mahadevan, P. et al. A satellite-based biosphere parameterization for net ecosystem CO2 exchange: Vegetation Photosynthesis and <lb/>Respiration Model (VPRM). Global Biogeochemical Cycles 22 (2008). <lb/>16. Verma, M. et al. Remote sensing of annual terrestrial gross primary productivity from MODIS: an assessment using the FLUXNET <lb/>La Thuile data set. Biogeosciences 11, 2185-2200 (2014). <lb/>17. Verma, M. et al. Improving the performance of remote sensing models for capturing intra-and inter-annual variations in daily GPP: <lb/>An analysis using global FLUXNET tower data. Agricultural and Forest Meteorology 214-215, 416-429 (2015). <lb/>18. Xiao, X. Modeling gross primary production of temperate deciduous broadleaf forest using satellite images and climate data. Remote <lb/>Sensing of Environment 91, 256-270 (2004). <lb/>19. Bolton, D. K. et al. Continental-scale land surface phenology from harmonized Landsat 8 and Sentinel-2 imagery. Remote Sensing of <lb/>Environment 240, 111685 (2020). <lb/>20. Bonan, G. B. Forests and Climate Change: Forcings, Feedbacks, and the Climate Benefits of Forests. Science 320, 1444-1449 (2008). <lb/>21. Young, A. M. et al. Seasonality in aerodynamic resistance across a range of North American ecosystems. Agricultural and Forest <lb/>Meteorology 310, 108613 (2021). <lb/>22. Chu, H. et al. Representativeness of Eddy-Covariance flux footprints for areas surrounding AmeriFlux sites. Agricultural and Forest <lb/>Meteorology 301-302, 108350 (2021). <lb/>23. Cheng, Y. et al. Phenology of short vegetation cycles in a Kenyan rangeland from PlanetScope and Sentinel-2. Remote Sensing of <lb/>Environment 248, 112004 (2020). <lb/>24. Dixon, D. J., Callow, J. N., Duncan, J. M. A., Setterfield, S. A. &amp; Pauli, N. Satellite prediction of forest flowering phenology. Remote <lb/>Sensing of Environment 255, 112197 (2021). <lb/>25. Wang, J. et al. Multi-scale integration of satellite remote sensing improves characterization of dry-season green-up in an Amazon <lb/>tropical evergreen forest. Remote Sensing of Environment 246, 111865 (2020). <lb/>26. Moon, M., Richardson, A. D. &amp; Friedl, M. A. Multiscale assessment of land surface phenology from harmonized Landsat 8 and <lb/>Sentinel-2, PlanetScope, and PhenoCam imagery. Remote Sensing of Environment 266, 112716 (2021). <lb/>27. Planet. Satellite Imagery and Archive. Planet https://planet.com/products/planet-imagery/ (2021). <lb/>28. Dash, J. &amp; Ogutu, B. O. Recent advances in space-borne optical remote sensing systems for monitoring global terrestrial ecosystems. <lb/>Progress in Physical Geography: Earth and Environment 40, 322-351 (2016). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2022) 9:448 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-022-01570-5 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>29. Houborg, R. &amp; McCabe, M. F. A Cubesat enabled Spatio-Temporal Enhancement Method (CESTEM) utilizing Planet, Landsat and <lb/>MODIS data. Remote Sensing of Environment 209, 211-226 (2018). <lb/>30. Jiang, Z., Huete, A. R., Didan, K. &amp; Miura, T. Development of a two-band enhanced vegetation index without a blue band. Remote <lb/>Sensing of Environment 112, 3833-3845 (2008). <lb/>31. Friedl, MA. MuSLI Multi-Source Land Surface Phenology Yearly North America 30 m V011, NASA EOSDIS Land Processes DAAC, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5067/Community/MuSLI/MSLSP30NA.011 (2021). <lb/>32. Zhang, X. et al. Generation and evaluation of the VIIRS land surface phenology product. Remote Sensing of Environment 216, <lb/>212-229 (2018). <lb/>33. Klosterman, S. T. et al. Evaluating remote sensing of deciduous forest phenology at multiple spatial scales using PhenoCam imagery. <lb/>Biogeosciences 11, 4305-4320 (2014). <lb/>34. Moon, M., Richardson, AD., Milliman, T. &amp; Friedl, MA. High Resolution Phenology, Eddy Covariance Tower Sites, North America, <lb/>2017-2021, ORNL Distributed Active Archive Center, https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/2033 (2022). <lb/>35. Sulla-Menashe, D., Gray, J. M., Abercrombie, S. P. &amp; Friedl, M. A. Hierarchical mapping of annual global land cover 2001 to present: <lb/>The MODIS Collection 6 Land Cover product. Remote Sensing of Environment 222, 183-194 (2019). <lb/>36. USDA. USDA National Agricultural Statistics Service Cropland Data Layer. crop-specific data layer https://nassgeodata.gmu.edu/ <lb/>CropScape/ (2022). <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="acknowledgement">acknowledgements <lb/> This work was supported by NASA grants #80NSSC18K0334 and #80NSSC21K1974 and by NSF award #1702627. <lb/>We gratefully acknowledge the support and excellent work of the HLS team at NASA GSFC who provided the <lb/>HLS data product, and without whose efforts, this work would not be possible. For use of the PhenoCam data, <lb/>we thank our many collaborators, including site PIs and technicians, for their efforts in support of PhenoCam. <lb/>The development of PhenoCam has been funded by the Northeastern States Research Cooperative, NSF&apos;s <lb/>Macrosystems Biology Program (awards EF-1065029 and EF-1702697), and DOE&apos;s Regional and Global Climate <lb/>Modelling Program (award DE-SC0016011). We also gratefully acknowledge NASA&apos;s Commercial Smallsat <lb/>Data Acquisition (CSDA) Program, which provided access to the PlanetScope imagery used in this study. <lb/>The PlanetScope imagery was provided under contract to Boston University as part of Planet&apos;s Research and <lb/>Education program. The authors gratefully acknowledge the support provided by this program. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">author contributions <lb/>M.M. and M.A.F. conceived and designed the dataset. M.M. developed the source code to process the data and <lb/>was responsible for image processing and dataset development. M.M. and M.A.F. led the efforts to draft this Data <lb/>Descriptor with contributions from A.D.R. and T.M. A.D.R. and T.M. were responsible for the PhenoCam data. <lb/>All authors reviewed and approved this Data Descriptor. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">competing interests <lb/>The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<front>additional information <lb/>Supplementary information The online version contains supplementary material available at https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1038/s41597-022-01570-5. <lb/>Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to M.M. <lb/>Reprints and permissions information is available at www.nature.com/reprints. <lb/>Publisher&apos;s note Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and <lb/>institutional affiliations. <lb/>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International <lb/>License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or <lb/>format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Cre-<lb/>ative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this <lb/>article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the <lb/>material. If material is not included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not per-<lb/>mitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the <lb/>copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. <lb/>© The Author(s) 2022 </front>


	</text>
</tei>
