<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Heliyon 10 (2024) e33389 <lb/>Available online 21 June 2024 <lb/>2405-8440/© 2024 The Authors. <lb/>Published by Elsevier Ltd. <lb/>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC license <lb/>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/). <lb/>Research article <lb/>Development of a conceptual model for an information <lb/>management system in spatial planning projects. Case study of <lb/>making-city project <lb/>Nataliia Yehorchenkova * , Oleksii Yehorchenkov , Maros Finka , <lb/>Vladimir Ondrejicka , Silvia Ondrejickova <lb/>SPECTRA Centre of Excellence EU, Slovak University of Technology in Bratislava, Vazovova 5, 812 43, Bratislava, Slovakia <lb/>A R T I C L E I N F O <lb/>Keywords: <lb/>Information management <lb/>Spatial planning <lb/>MAKING-CITY project <lb/>Conceptual model <lb/>Integration <lb/>Stakeholders <lb/>Decision-making <lb/>Information technology <lb/>A B S T R A C T <lb/>Efficient information management is pivotal for the effective execution of spatial planning pro-<lb/>jects, yet many encounter hurdles stemming from disjointed information systems and processes. <lb/>In this article, authors consider the intricacies of information management within the realm of <lb/>spatial planning, leveraging insights from the multifaceted MAKING-CITY project to elucidate <lb/>common challenges and propose innovative solutions. The proposed conceptual model for an <lb/>integrated information management system offers a holistic approach, aiming to eliminate <lb/>weaknesses inherent in existing information landscapes by seamlessly integrating diverse infor-<lb/>mation components into a unified framework. By facilitating robust communication channels and <lb/>synchronizing the actions of all project participants and stakeholders, this model enhances <lb/>collaboration, streamlines workflows, and fosters informed decision-making. Importantly, the <lb/>adaptability and versatility of developed model ensure its applicability across various spatial <lb/>planning initiatives, offering a scalable solution to address the evolving demands of urban <lb/>development projects. Through a meticulous examination of real-world challenges and practical <lb/>solutions, this article contributes to the advancement of information management practices in <lb/>spatial planning, laying the groundwork for more efficient, sustainable, and inclusive urban <lb/>development processes in today&apos;s dynamic landscape. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>In the times of the Fourth Industrial Revolution, which is characterized by integrating advanced technologies in manufacturing and <lb/>global digital transformation, namely the worldwide adoption of digital technologies to enhance operations and processes, information <lb/>is the main tool and the main weapon of many organizations (businesses, public authorities, academic institutions, etc.) [1,2,3]. <lb/>Numerous studies in the field of management have addressed the significance and standing of information management within or-<lb/>ganizations [4,5,6,7,8,9,10]. But, on the other hand, research shows that without proper information management, any organisation <lb/>begins to lose control over the real state of affairs both in the internal and external environments [4,11,12]. Therefore, for its existence <lb/>and sustainable development, organizations need to receive information promptly and use it to make effective, evidence-based <lb/></body>

			<front>* Corresponding author. <lb/>E-mail addresses: nataliia.yehorchenkova@stuba.sk (N. Yehorchenkova), oleksii.yehorchenkov@stuba.sk (O. Yehorchenkov), maros.finka@ <lb/>stuba.sk (M. Finka), vladimir.ondrejicka@stuba.sk (V. Ondrejicka), silvia.ondrejickova@stuba.sk (S. Ondrejickova). <lb/>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect <lb/>Heliyon <lb/>journal homepage: www.cell.com/heliyon <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e33389 <lb/>Received 7 December 2023; Received in revised form 12 June 2024; Accepted 20 June 2024 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Heliyon 10 (2024) e33389 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>management decisions. <lb/>One of the important areas of activity in the development of modern society, which requires the use of modern approaches of <lb/>information management, is spatial planning projects. Spatial planning is used by public authorities and local governments to in-<lb/>fluence the future location and distribution of territories, population distribution, and the implementation/conduct of various ac-<lb/>tivities in space. Such planning is needed to balance the potentially competing needs of the economy, society, and the preservation of <lb/>the environment [9] Spatial planning project refers to a structured and strategic initiative undertaken by governments, organizations, <lb/>or communities to manage and organize the use of land and resources within a specific geographical area. Spatial planning projects <lb/>primarily focus on organizing physical spaces, emphasizing land use and sustainability, often spanning large areas and years, involving <lb/>government, communities, and interest groups, and requiring adherence to government regulations and environmental standards. It is <lb/>the main difference between this kind of project and other kinds of projects like IT or construction [13]. <lb/>Effective spatial planning project decisions depend on the availability of timely and reliable spatial information. Spatial data has <lb/>become indispensable across various facets of urban development, planning, and management. Its growing significance can be <lb/>attributed to recent advancements in spatial data acquisition, including satellite remote sensing and the Global Navigation Satellite <lb/>System, as well as improved data management through Geographic Information Systems (GIS) and database tools. The challenge lies in <lb/>overcoming information barriers and enabling users both within and outside these domains to discover, access, and utilize this in-<lb/>formation to enhance decision-making, business outcomes, and customer services. Spatially enabled web-based services are opening <lb/>fresh opportunities to engage citizens more closely in consultations and land administration activities [14]. <lb/>The tool that has shown practical effectiveness, that can be used for information management of spatial planning projects is an <lb/>information management system. Information systems are integrated sets of components that collect, process, store, and distribute <lb/>information to support decision-making, coordination, control, analysis, and visualization in an organization [15]. <lb/>To date, scientific research has not presented the study of the problem of creating a unified information management system in <lb/>spatial planning projects. Therefore, the authors propose to consider the creation of such a system through the prism of the inter-<lb/>national project Making City. <lb/>2. Research goal and objectives <lb/>The main goal of the article is to build a conceptual model of an information management system in the spatial planning project. <lb/>The model proposed in the article should help to eliminate weaknesses in the existing information space of the project by integrating <lb/>different information components into a single system that will connect and synchronize the actions of all participants and stake-<lb/>holders of the project. Such a system will accelerate the interaction processes, as well as reduce the degree of uncertainty in the project, <lb/>which will improve the spatial planning processes. The developed model can be adapted and applied to different types of spatial <lb/>planning projects. <lb/>To achieve this goal, the article outlines three main objectives. <lb/>Objective 1. Analyse the existing information management system of the MAKING-CITY project. <lb/>The first objective is to conduct a thorough analysis of the existing information management system used in the MAKING-CITY <lb/>project. This will involve reviewing project documents, conducting interviews with project team members, and gathering feedback <lb/>from stakeholders. The aim is to identify the strengths and weaknesses of the existing system, which will inform the development of the <lb/>conceptual model. <lb/>Objective 2. Analyse previous research materials. <lb/>The second objective is to review the current research on problem-solving available in the field of information management and <lb/>spatial planning. This will involve a thorough literature review and an examination of case studies. The aim is to identify the most <lb/>effective problem-solving decisions that can be integrated into the conceptual model. <lb/>Objective 3. Develop a conceptual model of the information management system. <lb/>The third objective is to develop a conceptual model of the information management system that can be used in spatial planning <lb/>projects. This model will consider the strengths and weaknesses of the existing system, along with the authors&apos; previous experience. <lb/>The aim is to provide a practical solution that can be implemented in real-world projects. <lb/>Following the study&apos;s goals and objectives, the article follows the next structure. <lb/>1. Introduction. This section provides a general overview of the importance of information management and its relevance for business. <lb/>It introduces the research question the study aims to address and outlines the structure of the article. <lb/>2. Research goal and objectives. This section describe the main goal and objectives of the research. <lb/>3. Materials and Methods This section summarizes relevant studies, research, and literature that are conducted on information <lb/>management of spatial planning projects. Also in this section, the authors clarify the issues or challenges that prompted the research <lb/>and provide context for the subsequent research materials. <lb/>4. Results. This part introduces a conceptual model for an information management system in spatial planning projects. It explains the <lb/>key definitions, components, and principles of this model. <lb/>5. Discussion. In this part the article delves into the findings of the study, analyzing and interpreting the application of the conceptual <lb/>model of information management systems for spatial planning projects on the example of the international project MAKING-CITY. <lb/>6. Conclusions. The final section of the article summarizes the key takeaways and conclusions drawn from the study&apos;s findings. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">N. Yehorchenkova et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e33389 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>The research method in this article appears to be conceptual, focusing on the development of a conceptual model based on existing <lb/>knowledge and literature. Conceptual research is characterized by the examination and analysis of pre-existing information about a <lb/>specific subject, without the involvement of practical experimentation. It primarily deals with abstract concepts and ideas. <lb/>The article discusses the development of a conceptual model for an information management system in spatial planning projects, <lb/>using the international project MAKING-CITY as a prominent case study [16]. The study involves the analysis of existing literature and <lb/>research in the fields of information management, spatial planning, and related areas. It also presents a conceptual framework for the <lb/>information management system, including definitions, components, and functionality. <lb/>3. Materials and methods <lb/>3.1. Literature review <lb/>The concept of information management in organizations has garnered significant attention in previous research. For instance, <lb/>White [17] defines information management as the systematic collection and dissemination of information from various sources, with <lb/>a primary focus on organizing, controlling, processing, evaluating, and reporting these activities. This encompasses all forms of <lb/>valuable information, whether originating within or outside the organization. Furthermore, Detlor [18] elaborates on information <lb/>management as encompassing the control over information creation, acquisition, organization, storage, distribution, and utilization, <lb/>emphasizing its role in facilitating efficient and effective information access, processing, and utilization. A comprehensive analysis <lb/>conducted by Altındag and colleagues [4] highlights the diversity of definitions for information management in the organizational <lb/>context. These definitions vary, including one from Ruuska [8], which emphasizes the importance of how information is obtained, and <lb/>efficiently used, and the development of applications for its management. Canbaz [5] and his colleagues, on the other hand, emphasize <lb/>the unity of processes involved in obtaining, transforming, producing, and disseminating information to achieve organizational goals. <lb/>In addition to these definitions, it&apos;s important to acknowledge the significance of information management in the broader context of <lb/>project management. Previous studies (e.g., Refs. [7,9,19]) underline that information management plays a pivotal role in achieving <lb/>organizational purposes and enhancing individual expertise. <lb/>These definitions collectively underline the multifaceted nature of information management, spanning a range of processes, from <lb/>acquisition to utilization. These processes typically comprise stages such as establishment, acquisition, classification, storage, transfer, <lb/>sharing, and evaluation within an integrated information management system [20]. Moreover, the crucial role of information man-<lb/>agement systems, integrating people, processes, and technology, cannot be underestimated in supporting an organization&apos;s operations, <lb/>management, and decision-making functions. Effective use of collected information is central to these systems. <lb/>Opoku and Enu-Kwesi [21] emphasize the importance of establishing policies and strategies for data creation, storage, processing, <lb/>distribution, and use as part of information management practices while highlighting the relationship between information man-<lb/>agement practices and an organization&apos;s innovation, growth, and financial performance. <lb/>The literature also underscores the significance of spatial planning information management. Effective spatial planning projects <lb/>rely heavily on access to quality data and information, which can influence decisions related to land use, development, and ecological <lb/>conservation [22]. An in-depth review of data analysis in spatial planning projects reveals various challenges and opportunities. For <lb/>instance, studies (e.g., Refs. [23,24,25,14,26,27]) have explored issues related to data quality, standardization, and the use of <lb/>Geographic Information Systems (GIS) in spatial planning. These works underscore the importance of robust data analysis for informed <lb/>decision-making. In addition to data analysis, the role of spatial knowledge (including expert, tacit, sectoral, and community <lb/>knowledge) in urban development has gained attention [8]. Research has explored methods for participatory data collection and <lb/>analysis to integrate diverse forms of knowledge into planning processes. Advances in (geo)information technology have expanded <lb/>opportunities for spatial knowledge production, although questions regarding access and inclusivity remain [8]. <lb/>Issues of knowledge management are also prominent in urban development and spatial planning research [28,19]. These studies <lb/>delve into topics such as citizen participation through social networks, ontologies-based approaches to planning, and the integration of <lb/>human knowledge and artificial intelligence in geographic knowledge systems. Document management, a critical aspect of spatial <lb/>planning information management, is examined in a study proposing a spatial document management system [29]. This system <lb/>simplifies the handling of spatial documents and enhances information accessibility. Communication within spatial planning projects <lb/>is another key area of investigation. Improved communication can foster citizen engagement and a deeper understanding of devel-<lb/>opment plans [30]. Effective communication management systems are essential for stakeholder engagement in urban infrastructure <lb/>projects [31]. Furthermore, comparative studies have examined public communication in urban planning practices in different regions <lb/>[32]. <lb/>The enhanced literature review underscores several key insights that not only enrich the understanding of information manage-<lb/>ment in spatial planning projects but also lay the groundwork for research activities. Through a meticulous analysis of previous works, <lb/>it was uncovered a multifaceted landscape where information management encompasses various dimensions, including document <lb/>management, communication management, knowledge management, and data management. This nuanced understanding allows to <lb/>approach research with a holistic perspective, recognizing the intricate interplay of these facets within spatial planning projects. <lb/>3.2. Problem state-of-art review <lb/>Launched in December 2018 and coordinated by the CARTIF Technology Centre, the MAKING-CITY project has undertaken a 60-<lb/>month endeavor to implement advanced methodologies based on the Positive Energy District (PED) concept. In the context of this <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">N. Yehorchenkova et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e33389 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>project, a PED is defined as a district that achieves net zero energy import and net zero carbon emissions annually while working <lb/>towards generating a surplus of renewable energy locally. The primary objectives of the project include demonstrating the PED concept <lb/>in selected Lighthouse cities, Groningen and Oulu, and subsequently developing a validated procedure for its implementation in six <lb/>additional cities. To support this, the project aims to establish business models that integrate PED deployment and stimulate the <lb/>creation of a business ecosystem around the concept. Furthermore, the project will assist in aligning with the City Vision 2050 and mid-<lb/>term goals by providing methodologies and procedures for PED implementation within the 2030 timescale. MAKING-CITY also plans <lb/>to engage in social innovation activities to identify business opportunities related to PED integration, involving industrial players, <lb/>SMEs, and NGOs. A robust communication and dissemination strategy will be employed to promote and raise awareness of the <lb/>developed PED concept, fostering cooperation with related projects and relevant clusters. As a result, the project is expected to have <lb/>significant impacts, including increased use of renewables, reduced greenhouse gas emissions, improved energy efficiency, enhanced <lb/>energy balance, and greater adoption of electric mobility solutions. It will also contribute to improved urban air quality, transform <lb/>local economies, and generate employment, with over 4358 jobs anticipated in the eight cities initially involved. Replicating the PED <lb/>concept in at least 20 other European cities could create an additional 14,500 jobs. MAKING-CITY aims to mobilize public and private <lb/>investments through validated PED replication and innovative business models, paving the way for broader PED implementation, <lb/>supported by technical feasibility, suitable business models, and societal acceptance. The MAKING-CITY consortium comprises 34 <lb/>partners, including city councils, universities, research centers, clusters, housing administrators, SMEs, energy companies, and con-<lb/>struction firms, pooling their expertise for the pro#ject&apos;s success. <lb/>In Fig. 1 Project Stakeholders&apos; Map is presented. <lb/>Given the large number of stakeholders, project participants, and data that are the main resources of a project, the problem of <lb/>information management in a project is a relevant one. <lb/>The success of the MAKING-CITY project directly depends on the quality of the information used to create the urban development <lb/>model of Groningen, Bassano del Grappo, Leon, Trenčin, Oulu, Kadıkoy, Lublin, Vidin. Regarding the specific MAKING-CITY, when it is <lb/>developed as a model of an urban environment with the PED concept, the tasks related to the collection, processing, exchange, <lb/>dissemination, and storage of information are the basic needs of the project. <lb/>So, the information needs of the MAKING-CITY project are [33]. <lb/>-Information collection: city-related, multisource data <lb/>-Information analysis: complex information processing <lb/>-External cooperation -public involvement <lb/>-Internal cooperation between government departments <lb/>-Openness: transparency in urban planning management <lb/>-Fairness: multi-dimensional considerations, the pursuit of equality <lb/>-Adaptability: adjust the planning direction and methods according to recent circumstances <lb/>In the context of spatial planning projects, exemplified by the international project MAKING-CITY, the exchange, dissemination, <lb/>and management of information face substantial challenges. The existing information exchange framework lacks seamless integration, <lb/>leading to fragmented information-sharing processes among project participants and stakeholders. Currently, project information is <lb/>spread across multiple platforms, including a cloud-based document repository, email, MS Teams, and the project website, without <lb/>effective interconnectivity. This fragmentation hampers efficient collaboration and obstructs comprehensive monitoring of project <lb/>Fig. 1. Project stakeholders&apos; Map. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">N. Yehorchenkova et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e33389 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>documentation movement and status. Oversight of project communication lies with the Collaboration Secretariat, as outlined in <lb/>Ref. [34]. <lb/>MAKING-CITY&apos;s Collaboration Secretariat has specific objectives to enhance knowledge information flow, recognizing that <lb/>collaboration hinges on effective information management. These objectives adhere to the following principles. <lb/>a) Ensure that information is: <lb/>-Condensed, given the abundance of data. <lb/>-Interpreted and conveyed appropriately, tailored to the interests of the parties. <lb/>-Geared towards identifying complementarities. <lb/>b) Create opportunities for: <lb/>-Enhancing our work. <lb/>-Enhancing the work of others. <lb/>-Facilitating efficient collaborative efforts. <lb/>In the results of project implementation authors defined a significant level of dissatisfaction with the prevailing information <lb/>management processes and technologies. This discontentment can be attributed to several key factors that collectively underscore the <lb/>urgent need for reform in spatial planning projects like MAKING-CITY. <lb/>Firstly, one of the primary sources of frustration has been the limited collaborative capabilities within the existing information <lb/>management framework. Project participants have expressed concerns regarding the difficulty of working together seamlessly. <lb/>Collaborative efforts often encounter roadblocks due to the disjointed nature of the current information system. This limitation not <lb/>Fig. 2. Information request schema. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">N. Yehorchenkova et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e33389 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>only impedes the fluid exchange of ideas and insights but also hinders the collective effort to achieve project objectives efficiently. <lb/>Secondly, the constraints in disseminating project outcomes have been a focal point of dissatisfaction. The project&apos;s success hinges <lb/>on the effective communication of findings, solutions, and progress to relevant stakeholders. However, the current information <lb/>management setup falls short in this regard. Project outcomes struggle to reach the intended audiences in a timely and comprehensive <lb/>manner, impeding the project&apos;s ability to make a meaningful impact. <lb/>Thirdly, inadequate functionalities for managing document flow have been a recurring issue. In a complex spatial planning project <lb/>like MAKING-CITY, the volume of documentation can be substantial. Without robust document management tools and workflows, <lb/>project participants face challenges in organizing, tracking, and accessing critical information. This deficiency not only increases the <lb/>risk of errors and oversights but also consumes valuable time and resources. <lb/>The complexity and multitude of interactions inherent in such projects underscore the urgency of establishing a unified information <lb/>space to minimize errors, delays, and the potential failure of information to reach its intended recipients in a timely and effective <lb/>manner [35]. <lb/>Let us consider a special case. A project stakeholder needs to obtain information D, which consists of d 1 , d 2 , d 3 , d 4 . To obtain in-<lb/>formation D(d 1 , d 2 , d 3 , d 4 ) it is necessary to influence worker S 1 . Since worker S 1 can only provide information d 1 , he influences <lb/>workers on systems S 2 and S 3 . to obtain information d 2 and d 3 , d 4 respectively. Since there is no information d 4 in the information <lb/>system that S 3 works with, worker S 3 influences worker S 4 to obtain it. Then in reverse order S 4 , S 3 , S 2 , S 1 interact by providing each <lb/>other with information D (Fig. 2). <lb/>With such a form of interaction, the time to acquire information will be equal: <lb/>T 1 = <lb/>∑ n <lb/>i=1 <lb/>t z <lb/>i + <lb/>∑ m <lb/>j=1 <lb/>t 0 <lb/>j <lb/>(1) <lb/>where T 1 -total time of receiving information, t z <lb/>i -the time required to deliver a request for a document d i for information to the <lb/>performer; t 0 <lb/>j -the time required to process a request for a document d j and providing information to the initiator (response); n -a <lb/>number of requests; m -the number of responses (in the general case n∕ =m). <lb/>The risk of producing erroneous information is proportional to the probability of error in understanding at least one request: <lb/>P 1 = 1 -<lb/>∏ n <lb/>i=1 <lb/>∏ mi <lb/>j=1 <lb/>p ij <lb/>(2) <lb/>where P 1 -the probability of an error in understanding at least one request; p ij -the probability of a request for a document d i being <lb/>correctly understood by the performer R j ; n -number of requests; m i -the number of performers in the chain of processing for a <lb/>document request d i ; i -number of document; j -number of performers. <lb/>Consequently, the more people involved in providing the information, the later it will be received by the end-user, and the greater <lb/>the probability of error. <lb/>The influence of the external environment and instability within the environment also has to be taken into account. Factors such as <lb/>a large workload of performers, a large number of influences per performer, and many other factors can significantly increase the time <lb/>T and the probability of error P. However timely information plays an important role in management decision-making. <lb/>It follows from the above that to improve the efficiency of spatial planning projects it is necessary to shorten the path from the <lb/>customer of the information to the specialist who receives it, and in the opposite direction. <lb/>If we are talking about a unified information management system, it is necessary to define what should be the software and in-<lb/>formation technology core, in which the different information components of the project can be combined and can easily exchange <lb/>information. To solve this problem, the information management system of spatial planning projects should be seen as a set of people, <lb/>policies, methods, and tools. <lb/>Table 1 <lb/>The entities of an information management system in spatial planning projects. <lb/>N • <lb/>Element <lb/>Essence <lb/>1 <lb/>Internal Environment <lb/>-spatial planning project <lb/>2 <lb/>Actors <lb/>-project participant (project team, project experts) <lb/>3 <lb/>Information system <lb/>-data management information systems; <lb/>-document management information systems; <lb/>-communication information systems; <lb/>-knowledge management information systems; <lb/>-data and document storage. <lb/>4 <lb/>External Environment <lb/>-regional administration; <lb/>-Internet, telecommunication means; <lb/>-higher education institutions, scientific institutions; <lb/>-other agencies and organizations. <lb/>N. Yehorchenkova et al. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Heliyon 10 (2024) e33389 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>4. Results <lb/>4.1. Conceptual model of the information management system <lb/>Based on the author&apos;s experience, the analyzed articles, and previous studies [36,37,38,39], a conceptual model for an information <lb/>management system of spatial planning projects has been developed. <lb/>First, let&apos;s consider the glossary of the model. <lb/>Definition 1. The Spatial Planning Information Management System (SPIMS) is a comprehensive system designed to facilitate <lb/>the effective planning, collection, storage, processing, dissemination, and control of digital project information within the context of <lb/>spatial planning projects. <lb/>SPIMS will be represented as consisting of the SPIMS entities (Table 1). <lb/>The SPIMS manages any information produced by the project&apos;s information systems and used outside of those systems. Its main <lb/>purpose is to manage the processes of creating and using digital information in the spatial planning project. <lb/>SPIMS functions. <lb/>-planning the receiving of information resources; <lb/>-planning the exchange of information resources; <lb/>-electronic accounting of incoming information resources (including electronic ones produced by the IS); <lb/>-fast searching for required information resources; <lb/>-control of work with information resources (including receipt and execution of orders); <lb/>-control of the flow of information resources. <lb/>SPIMS -is a complex system, and therefore its effective functioning requires the timely and coherent interaction of all its elements, <lb/>which is impossible without good management of information resources. <lb/>Definition 2. Information Resource (IR) -any information that is obtained in the project or from the external environment and <lb/>used to produce a project product or intermediate deliverable. <lb/>The following types of information resources are identified for spatial planning projects. <lb/>-Document -officially approved and recorded in specific form information intended for management of the spatial planning project. <lb/>-Project data -data obtained during the implementation of the project, which is intended to obtain the product of the project. <lb/>-Dissemination information -project information intended to be shared with stakeholders or others to make them aware of the <lb/>project results. <lb/>-Knowledge -useful information directly or indirectly acquired as a result of the project, which may be fully or partially used for <lb/>other processes or projects. <lb/>Fig. 3. Components of SPIMS Consider each plane in more detail. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">N. Yehorchenkova et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e33389 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>-Communication information -information necessary for communication between project participants and stakeholders. <lb/>In essence, the SPIMS is a set of components such as document management, knowledge management, data management, and <lb/>project communication management linked by project information resources. Each component may contain different information <lb/>systems. <lb/>Definition 3. Document management is a systematic process for the creation, storage, organization, retrieval, sharing, and control <lb/>of electronic and physical documents within an organization. Its primary purpose is to efficiently manage documents throughout their <lb/>lifecycle, ensuring they are easily accessible, secure, and compliant with regulatory requirements. <lb/>Definition 4. Knowledge management is the systematic process of identifying, capturing, storing, organizing, retrieving, and <lb/>sharing an organization&apos;s knowledge (employee expertise, product knowledge, customer knowledge, intellectual property, best <lb/>practices, etc.) and information assets to support its objectives and improve decision-making. <lb/>Definition 5. Data management is the process of collecting, storing, organizing, and maintaining data (financial data, website <lb/>analytics, logistics, and transportation data) in a structured and secure manner to ensure its accuracy, availability, and usability for <lb/>various business purposes and decision-making. It encompasses activities such as data collection, data storage, data integration, data <lb/>quality assurance, and data security to maximize the value and reliability of an organization&apos;s data assets. <lb/>Definition 6. Communication management refers to the strategic planning, execution, and coordination of communication ac-<lb/>tivities within an organization or project. It involves the development of communication strategies, messaging, and channels to ensure <lb/>that information is effectively conveyed to the right stakeholders at the right time. <lb/>In addition to the components outlined above, the information management system should be implemented on three planes: <lb/>organisation, methodology, and technology (Fig. 3) <lb/>1. Organisation of the information management system: <lb/>-identification of responsibility for the management, administration, and coordination in the SPIMS; <lb/>-modification of the information interaction processes in the project by the SPIMS procedures. <lb/>2. Information management system methodology: <lb/>-definition and approval of rules and procedures for the collection, processing, storing, transfer, etc. information resources in <lb/>spatial planning projects; <lb/>Fig. 4. Components of SPIMS <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">N. Yehorchenkova et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e33389 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">-development of interaction structures in the information management system. <lb/>3. Information management system technology: <lb/>-development and implementation of a tool (information technology) that technically connects project participants and stake-<lb/>holders with information systems in a unified system for collection, processing, storing, transfer, etc. information resources in <lb/>spatial planning projects. <lb/>Effective information management involves a holistic approach that encompasses three key components: methodology, organi-<lb/>zation, and technology. Methodology refers to the set of processes and procedures that govern how information is collected, processed, <lb/>stored, and disseminated throughout the project lifecycle. This includes defining the rules of information interaction between project <lb/>participants and stakeholders, as well as the responsible persons who will oversee the implementation of these rules. Organization, on <lb/>the other hand, focuses on the structure of the project team and how information is distributed among its members. It involves <lb/>identifying the key stakeholders and defining their roles and responsibilities in the management of project information. This includes <lb/>establishing communication channels and protocols, setting up reporting mechanisms, and defining workflows and decision-making <lb/>processes. Also, technology plays a crucial role in the effective management of project information by providing tools and platforms <lb/>that simplify the processes of collecting, processing, storing, and disseminating data. This includes the use of databases, project <lb/>management software, collaborative platforms, and other digital tools that enable real-time data sharing and analysis. By leveraging <lb/>technology, project teams can streamline their workflows and improve their ability to collaborate and make informed decisions based <lb/>on accurate and up-to-date information. Overall, an effective information management strategy requires the careful integration of <lb/>these three key components to ensure the success of the project. <lb/>Based on the proposed conceptual framework, system components, and implementation planes, a conceptual model of the infor-<lb/>mation management system of spatial planning projects &quot;Hourglass&quot; was developed (Fig. 4). The model is called an hourglass because <lb/>of the property of the information resource to flow from the actor to the information systems and back through the neck of the hub like <lb/>sand is poured in an hourglass. <lb/>The Hourglass model shows the information management system in spatial planning projects through the relationship between <lb/>actors, information systems, and the external environment in the context of SPIMS components. This relationship is the exchange of <lb/>information resources between system elements through the information hub of the SPIMS. An information hub (Info Hub) is an <lb/>information technology that acts as a link between system actors and information systems. In essence, through the use of this hub, an <lb/>actor can. <lb/>-submit an inquiry and obtain the necessary information; <lb/>-upload information to information systems. <lb/>An Information Hub is a centralized platform that serves as a focal point for the aggregation, organization, exchange, and distri-<lb/>bution of data and information within an organization or network. Information Hubs are designed to facilitate seamless communi-<lb/>cation and data flow between various systems, applications, databases, and stakeholders, often acting as intermediaries to ensure that <lb/>information reaches its intended destination efficiently and securely. Instead of necessitating direct connections between all actors and <lb/>project stakeholders, which can be cumbersome and prone to errors, the hub acts as a single node through which all communication <lb/>flows. This streamlines the entire process, significantly reducing the time required for both sending and receiving information within <lb/>the project. Moreover, it plays a crucial role in error reduction, as it minimizes the complexity associated with multiple, potentially <lb/>error-prone connections. In the context of external information resources, the Information Hub plays a dual role in facilitating seamless <lb/>interactions. When external information is submitted to the project, it follows a structured path, beginning with the External <lb/>Table 2 <lb/>Information Hub functionality. <lb/>N • <lb/>Functionality <lb/>Description <lb/>1 <lb/>Information Aggregation <lb/>Collects project data, knowledge, and documents from diverse sources, such as databases, applications, APIs, and external <lb/>feeds. <lb/>2 <lb/>Central Repository <lb/>Provides a centralized location to store structured and unstructured project information. <lb/>3 <lb/>Access Control <lb/>Implements user authentication and authorization mechanisms to control project information access. <lb/>4 <lb/>Security Monitoring <lb/>Monitors project information access and detects and responds to security threats. <lb/>5 <lb/>Information Routing <lb/>Directs project information to the appropriate destination or endpoint based on predefined rules. <lb/>6 <lb/>Workflow Automation <lb/>Coordinate projects information-related tasks and processes through automated workflows. <lb/>7 <lb/>Real-time Messaging <lb/>Facilitates real-time communication between systems, applications, and users. <lb/>8 <lb/>Information <lb/>Management <lb/>Encompasses projects information governance policies and ensures compliance with regulations. <lb/>9 <lb/>Scalability <lb/>Scales both horizontally and vertically to handle increasing information loads. <lb/>10 <lb/>Decision Support <lb/>Empowers decision-making with real-time insights and data-driven recommendations. <lb/>11 <lb/>Audit Trails <lb/>Maintains detailed audit trails and logs of information transactions and user activities. <lb/>12 <lb/>Integration <lb/>Enables seamless third-party integrations and extensions. <lb/>13 <lb/>Adaptability <lb/>Adapts to evolving technology and business requirements. <lb/>14 <lb/>Reporting Tools <lb/>Generates reports, dashboards, and visualizations for in-depth information analysis. <lb/>15 <lb/>Insights <lb/>Offers users actionable insights derived from integrated information. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">N. Yehorchenkova et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e33389 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>Environment. This information flows through the Actor, who acts as the interface between the external source and the Information <lb/>Hub. The Information Hub then serves as the central point for processing and channeling this data into the relevant Information <lb/>Systems within the project. When the project needs to share information with the external environment, such as stakeholders or other <lb/>entities, the process is equally streamlined. The Information System initiates this interaction by sending the information to the In-<lb/>formation Hub, which acts as an intermediary. From there, the Information Hub seamlessly forwards the data to the designated Actor, <lb/>who is responsible for ensuring that the information reaches the intended recipients in the External Environment. This structured <lb/>approach ensures that information flows efficiently in both directions, enhancing the project&apos;s ability to engage with external resources <lb/>while maintaining control and coordination through the Information Hub. Table 2 it is presented part of the Information Hub <lb/>functionality. <lb/>Figs. 5-6 in Business Process Model and Notation shows a conceptual diagram of the processes of Submitting and Uploading In-<lb/>formation Resources through an information hub. <lb/>To evaluate the effectiveness of the system, the authors have proposed a model for estimating the time and risks of error in the <lb/>transfer of information resources. <lb/>When using Information Hub, the time to receive information is defined as <lb/>T 2 = <lb/>∑ m <lb/>j=1 <lb/>( <lb/>t z <lb/>j + t o <lb/>j <lb/>) <lb/>, <lb/>(3) <lb/>where T 2 -the time to receive information when using Info Hub; t j <lb/>z -the time to deliver a request for an information resource d j project <lb/>participant; t j <lb/>z -the time to process a request for an information resource d j and providing a response; m -number of information <lb/>resources. <lb/>As in formula (2), the risk of producing erroneous information is proportional to the probability of error in understanding at least <lb/>one query. But in this case, each query chain consists of a single element: <lb/>P 2 = 1 -<lb/>∏ n <lb/>i=1 <lb/>p i <lb/>(4) <lb/>where P 2 -the probability of an error in understanding at least one query in the Info Hub; p j -the probability of correct understanding <lb/>of a request for an information resource d i ; n -a number of requests. <lb/>If we consider the values obtained in formulas (1), (3) and (2), (4), we can conclude that Info Hub generally reduces the time and <lb/>reduces the risk of erroneous information. Indeed, from (1) and (3) <lb/>T 2 ≤ T 1 . <lb/>And from (2) and (4) <lb/>Р 2 ≤ Р 1 . <lb/>Of course, Information Hub is not a Database Management System that implements queries to databases. Info Hub implements <lb/>queries to actors working with different IS and obtaining a variety of information to perform their functions. On the other hand, Info <lb/>Hub implements an automated technology for obtaining information. When a request for information is an element that falls within the <lb/>scope of information management, it is planned, and sent to the right addressee, its implementation is monitored, all actions with <lb/>information are logged, etc. <lb/>Fig. 5. Submitting processes IR. <lb/>N. Yehorchenkova et al. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Heliyon 10 (2024) e33389 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>4.2. Examination of SPIMS effectiveness <lb/>Let&apos;s consider sources and timing of information resources using Info Hub in MAKING-CITY project (Tabl.3) <lb/>The interaction time for delivering requests for information resources is shown in Table 4. <lb/>Bringing the received information resources to the user is carried out in reverse order. <lb/>The interaction time when providing the IS with the requested information resources is shown in Table 5. <lb/>Of course, this time includes the waiting time for the counterparty, taking into account his busyness with other things. If the in-<lb/>formation resource is delivered by e-mail, then the counterparty may not immediately see the letter, etc. <lb/>The probability of correct understanding of the request during the interaction is estimated by the values presented in Table 6. <lb/>If Info Hub is used, we obtain different interaction characteristics (Table 7, Table 8). <lb/>The probability of a correct understanding of the request in the interaction is estimated by the values presented in Table 8. The <lb/>increase in the probability of correct recognition of a query by Info Hub, in comparison with their recognition in traditional IS, is <lb/>explained by the fact that Info Hub concentrates on information professionals, managers, and specialists, who are engaged in working <lb/>with users in the field of information management. <lb/>Then, by substituting the values from Tables 2-9 into formulae (1) to (4), we obtain. <lb/>T 1 =(2 + 2,5 + 3+1 + 2,5 + 3+1 + 1)+(2 + 2+2 + 2+3 + 2+2 + 1)+(1 + 24+ <lb/>+6 + 1) = 64 h. <lb/>T 2 =(1 + 1+1 + 1+1,5 + 2,5 + 2+1)+(2,5 + 2,5 + 2,5 + 2,5 + 1+1 + 1+1)+(1 + 24+6 + 1)=. <lb/>=57 h. <lb/>P 1 = 1-0,99⋅(0,9⋅0,99)⋅(0,8⋅0,9)⋅(0,98⋅0,95⋅0,99)≈0,415. <lb/>P 2 = 1-0,99⋅0,95⋅0,90⋅0,99 ≈ 0,162. <lb/>As you can see from this case, Info Hub reduces time and the risk of getting information wrong. <lb/>5. Discussion <lb/>The conceptual model of information management systems presented in this study, utilizing the MAKING-CITY project as a case <lb/>study, offers valuable insights into the complexities and challenges of managing information in spatial planning projects. With its <lb/>diverse array of stakeholders and lack of a unified information management system, MAKING-CITY serves as an apt example for <lb/>exploring these issues, which are prevalent in many spatial planning endeavors. <lb/>The proposed conceptual model, termed SPIMS, addresses the need for a centralized information management environment by <lb/>integrating various information systems, project participants, and stakeholders. The main advantages of SPIMS are. <lb/>1. Localisation of IS information management functions in the SPIMS, which allows the entire information environment of the project <lb/>to be easily tailored to the needs of the users. <lb/>2. Created and implemented new IS are not adjusted to the databases and knowledge bases of other IS. Their integration is based on <lb/>the macro-description of the project&apos;s information technology performed in the SPIMS. <lb/>Fig. 6. Uploading processes IR. <lb/>Table 3 <lb/>Sources and timing of information resources using Info Hub. <lb/>IR identification <lb/>IR source identification <lb/>Time to receive IR (hours) <lb/>r 1 <lb/>S 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>r 2 <lb/>S 2 <lb/>24 <lb/>r 3 <lb/>S 3 <lb/>6 <lb/>r 4 <lb/>S 4 <lb/>1 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">N. Yehorchenkova et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e33389 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>3. The user, without knowing what information and where it is located, can form requests for its retrieval in the single functional <lb/>environment of the SPIMS. <lb/>The disadvantages of SPIMS are the additional functionality and hence the additional costs incurred by the project to create and <lb/>implement such systems. <lb/>And of course, this model has limitations. These limitations include potential challenges in generalizing the model to diverse <lb/>projects, dependence on data quality, susceptibility to evolving technology, resource intensity, human factors, adaptability to external <lb/>environment variability, scalability concerns, cultural and organizational differences, and uncertainty in long-term viability. <lb/>Table 4 <lb/>Interaction time (hours) in delivering requests for information resources to traditional IS. <lb/>Recipient/Source <lb/>Project Manager <lb/>S 1 <lb/>S <lb/>S 3 <lb/>S 4 <lb/>Project Manager <lb/>S 1 <lb/>t 1 <lb/>z = 2; <lb/>t 2 <lb/>z = 2,5; <lb/>t 3 <lb/>z = 3; <lb/>t 4 <lb/>z = 1. <lb/>S 2 <lb/>t 2 <lb/>z = 2,5. <lb/>S 3 <lb/>t 3 <lb/>z = 3; <lb/>t 4 <lb/>z = 1. <lb/>S 4 <lb/>t 4 <lb/>z = 1. <lb/>Table 5 <lb/>Interaction time (hours) in providing the IS with the requested information resources. <lb/>Recipient/Source <lb/>Project Manager <lb/>S 1 <lb/>S 2 <lb/>S 3 <lb/>S 4 <lb/>Project Manager <lb/>S 1 <lb/>t 1 <lb/>z = 2; <lb/>t 2 <lb/>z = 2; <lb/>t 3 <lb/>z = 2; <lb/>t 4 <lb/>z = 2. <lb/>S 2 <lb/>t 2 <lb/>z = 3. <lb/>S 3 <lb/>t 3 <lb/>z = 2; <lb/>t 4 <lb/>z = 2. <lb/>S 4 <lb/>t 4 <lb/>o = 1. <lb/>Table 6 <lb/>Probability of correctly understanding a request for an information resource when using traditional IS. <lb/>Recipient/Source <lb/>Project Manager <lb/>S 1 <lb/>S 2 <lb/>S 3 <lb/>S 4 <lb/>Project Manager <lb/>S 1 <lb/>p 1 = 0,99; <lb/>p 2 = 0,90; <lb/>p 3 = 0,80; <lb/>p 4 = 0,98. <lb/>S 2 <lb/>p 2 = 0,99. <lb/>S 3 <lb/>p 3 = 0,90; <lb/>p 4 = 0,95. <lb/>S 4 <lb/>p 4 = 0,99. <lb/>Table 7 <lb/>Interaction time (hours) in delivering requests for information resources to Info Hub. <lb/>Recipient/Source <lb/>Project Manager <lb/>Info Hub <lb/>S 1 <lb/>S 2 <lb/>S 3 <lb/>S 4 <lb/>Project Manager <lb/>Info Hub <lb/>t 1 <lb/>z = 1; <lb/>t 2 <lb/>z = 1; <lb/>t 3 <lb/>z = 1; <lb/>t 4 <lb/>z = 1. <lb/>S 1 <lb/>t 1 <lb/>z = 1,5. <lb/>S 2 <lb/>t 2 <lb/>z = 2,5. <lb/>S 3 <lb/>t 3 <lb/>z = 2. <lb/>S 4 <lb/>t 4 <lb/>z = 1. <lb/>N. Yehorchenkova et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e33389 <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Therefore, its application should be context-specific, considering project characteristics and potential. <lb/>Consequently, the developed conceptual model for information management systems in spatial planning projects holds significant <lb/>importance for both theory and practice. This model offers a structured framework that enhances our understanding of how infor-<lb/>mation resources can be effectively managed in complex spatial planning projects. From a theoretical perspective, it enriches the field <lb/>of information management by providing a tailored framework for spatial planning, addressing the unique challenges in this domain. <lb/>In practice, this model offers several managerial implications. Firstly, it empowers organizations involved in spatial planning <lb/>projects to streamline their information management processes, reducing redundancy, errors, and inefficiencies. It also aids in the <lb/>integration of various information systems, leading to better collaboration among project participants. Moreover, the model em-<lb/>phasizes the importance of data quality, which can significantly improve decision-making in spatial planning projects. For decision-<lb/>makers and policymakers, this study provides valuable insights into optimizing information management in spatial planning. By <lb/>adopting the proposed model, decision-makers can ensure that the right information is available to the right stakeholders at the right <lb/>time, facilitating informed and timely decisions. Additionally, the model&apos;s emphasis on adaptability to external environmental changes <lb/>can help policymakers develop strategies that are more resilient in the face of evolving challenges such as climate change and <lb/>urbanization. <lb/>The proposed conceptual model is an idea that allows the creation of tools that will serve as the technological infrastructure that <lb/>supports the systematic organization, control, and dissemination of information in alignment with the principles of information <lb/>management, thereby ensuring the efficient operation of spatial planning projects. <lb/>6. Conclusions <lb/>This study delineates the crucial aspects of information management systems in spatial planning projects, using the MAKING-CITY <lb/>project as a focal point. It proposes a comprehensive conceptual model, SPIMS, to address information management challenges, <lb/>emphasizing the need for technological, methodological, and organizational solutions. The research underscores the growing <lb/>importance of information management in contemporary spatial planning endeavors and advocates for further exploration into <lb/>emerging technologies, cybersecurity, and user experience. These efforts are vital for advancing urban development processes in an <lb/>increasingly information-driven world. <lb/></body>

            <div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>Data will be made available on request. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">CRediT authorship contribution statement <lb/>Nataliia Yehorchenkova: Writing -original draft, Methodology. Oleksii Yehorchenkov: Visualization, Formal analysis. Maros <lb/>Finka: Supervision. Vladimir Ondrejicka: Project administration, Funding acquisition. Silvia Ondrejickova: Resources, Project <lb/></div>

            <body>Table 8 <lb/>Interaction time (hours) when delivering received information resources via Info Hub. <lb/>Recipient/Source <lb/>Project Manager <lb/>Info Hub <lb/>S 1 <lb/>S 2 <lb/>S 3 <lb/>S 4 <lb/>Project Manager <lb/>Info Hub <lb/>t 1 <lb/>z = 2,5; <lb/>t 2 <lb/>z = 2,5; <lb/>t 3 <lb/>z = 2,5; <lb/>t 4 <lb/>z = 2,5. <lb/>S 1 <lb/>t 1 <lb/>z = 1. <lb/>S 2 <lb/>t 2 <lb/>z = 1. <lb/>S 3 <lb/>t 3 <lb/>z = 1. <lb/>S 4 <lb/>t 4 <lb/>z = 1. <lb/>Table 9 <lb/>Probability of correctly understanding a request for information when using Info Hub. <lb/>Recipient/Source <lb/>Project Manager <lb/>Info Hub <lb/>S 1 <lb/>S 2 <lb/>S 3 <lb/>S 4 <lb/>Project Manager <lb/>Info Hub <lb/>p 1 = 0,99; <lb/>p 2 = 0,90; <lb/>p 3 = 0,80; <lb/>p 4 = 0,98. <lb/>S 1 <lb/>S 2 <lb/>S 3 <lb/>S 4 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">N. Yehorchenkova et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e33389 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">administration. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Declaration of competing interest <lb/>The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing in-<lb/>terests:Nataliia Yehorchenkova reports administrative support, article publishing charges, and writing assistance were provided by <lb/>Slovak University of Technology in Bratislava. Nataliia Yehorchenkova reports a relationship with Slovak University of Technology in <lb/>Bratislava that includes: employment and funding grants. If there are other authors, they declare that they have no known competing <lb/>financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledges <lb/>This article displays the outputs from the project APVV 21-0099 EMINUK and H2020 MAKING-CITY No. 824418 supported by the <lb/>EUand co-funded by the European Union Erasmus Jean Monnet Module project PM4U No.101126659 and the EU NextGenerationEU <lb/>through the Recovery and Resilience Plan for Slovakia under the projects No. 09I03-03-V01-00024 and No. 09I03-03-V01-00025. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] Webster Ferris, A national global change information management strategy, Data For Discovery (January 2023), https://doi.org/10.1615/1-56700-002-9.20. <lb/>[2] Haelim Anderson, Adam Copeland, Information management in times of crisis, J. Monetary Econ. 136 (2023) 35-49, https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>jmoneco.2023.01.008. <lb/>[3] D. Mhlanga, Exploring the evolution of artificial intelligence and the Fourth industrial revolution: an overview, in: FinTech and Artificial Intelligence for <lb/>Sustainable Development. Sustainable Development Goals Series, Palgrave Macmillan, Cham, 2023, pp. 15-39, https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-37776-1_2. <lb/>[4] Ö. Altındag, V. Öngel, Information management, organizational intelligence, and innovation performance triangle: empirical research on Turkish IT firms, Sage <lb/>Open 11 (4) (2021), https://doi.org/10.1177/21582440211052550. <lb/>[5] S. Canbaz, E. Yıldız, A research of management information systems on the strategic planning and decision-making process in enterprises, Akademik Bakıs ¸ <lb/>Dergisi 44 (2014) 21-39. <lb/>[6] E. Costa, A.L. Soares, J.P. de Sousa, G.L. Jamil, in: G.L. Jamil, A.L. Soares, C.R.M. Pessoa (Eds.), Information Management for Network Transformation in <lb/>Industrial Enterprises Associations: the Case of the Internationalization Process, 2020, pp. 589-610, 2020. <lb/>[7] H. Odabas ¸, Knowledge management and institutional open access in higher education institutions [Conference session], Xııı. Türkiye&apos;de İnternet Konferansı, <lb/>Orta Dogu Teknik Üniversitesi, Ankara (2008) 1-7. <lb/>[8] I. Ruuska, Social Structures as Communities for Knowledge Sharing in Project-Based Environments [Doctoral Dissertation Series, 3], Helsinki University of <lb/>Technology, 2005, pp. 1-234. <lb/>[9] R.P. Uit Beijerse, Knowledge management in small and medium-sized companies: knowledge management for entrepreneurs, J. Knowl. Manag. 4 (2) (2000) <lb/>162-179. <lb/>[10] U-learn.org.ua. Spatial planning in the community.Retrieved from https://u-learn.org.ua/p/spatial-planning. <lb/>[11] B. Detlor, Information management, Int. J. Inf. Manag. 30 (2) (2010) 103-108, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2009.12.001. <lb/>[12] O. Haas, P. Markovič, Management information system of the critical path of construction projects by way of example Berlin brandenburg airport (BER), in: <lb/>N. Kryvinska, M. Greguš, S. Fedushko (Eds.), Developments in Information and Knowledge Management Systems for Business Applications, Studies in Systems, <lb/>Decision and Control, 2023, p. 466, https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-27506-7_18. <lb/>[13] M. Finka, Interdisciplinárne Aspekty Vývoja Priestorovej Kvality Systémov Osídlenia, vol.2001, Road, Bratislava, 2001, p. 165. <lb/>[14] B. Murgante, V. Garramone, Web 3.0 and knowledge management: opportunities for spatial planning and decision making. Computational science and its <lb/>applications, Lect. Notes Comput. Sci. 7973 (2013). <lb/>[15] Preston Mwiinga, Management information systems (MIS), Retrieved from: https://www.researchgate.net/publication/372599725_Management_Information_ <lb/>Systems_MIS, 2023. <lb/>[16] M. Martinsuo, M. Huemann, Designing case study research, Int. J. Proj. Manag. 39 (5) (2021) 417-421, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijproman.2021.06.007. <lb/>[17] D. White, Information management, International Journal of Computers &amp; Technology 3 (3) (2012) 424-427. <lb/>[18] B. Detlor, Information management, Int. J. Inf. Manag. 30 (2) (2010) 103-108. <lb/>[19] K. Vıjayakumar, Knowledge management in libraries, Indian Journal of Information Sources and Services 1 (1) (2011) 7-10. <lb/>[20] E.W. Ngirigacha, J. Wasike, D. Gichuhi, Contributions of information management practices on performance among selected counties, J. Arts Humanit. 8 (10) <lb/>(2019) 73-83. <lb/>[21] M.O. Opoku, F. Enu-Kwesi, Evaluation of information management practices in Ghanaian organizations, Net Journal of Business Management 5 (2) (2017) <lb/>19-29. <lb/>[22] European Commission, Seanergy 2020. https://maritime-spatial-planning.ec.europa.eu/sites/default/files/seanergy_2020_6.pdf, 2012. (Accessed 22 May <lb/>2024). Date accessed. <lb/>[23] G. Badea, A. Badea, Considerations regarding the implementation of the technical specifications in the urban information system, ICE Proceedings Municipal <lb/>Engineer 161 (3) (2018) 163-173. <lb/>[24] I. Bulent, Spatial analyst methods for urban planning, Scientific Research and Essay 4 (12) (2009) 1531-1535. <lb/>[25] J. Cheng, I. Masser, Towards a spatial analysis framework: modelling urban development patterns, Geocomputation Conference Brisbane (2001). <lb/>[26] T. Nylén, H. Tolvanen, A. Erkkilä-Välimäki, M. Roose, Guide for Cross-Border Spatial Data Analysis in Maritime Spatial Planning, 2019. <lb/>[27] W. Xin, Urban planning and management information systems analysis and design based on GIS, Phys. Procedia 33 (2012) 1440-1445. <lb/>[28] R. Laurini, A primer of knowledge management for smart city governance, Land Use Pol. 111 (2021) 104832. <lb/>[29] Y. Shiraishi, M. Arikawa, T. Sagara, Y. Asami, Spatial document management system for ubiquitous mapping, International Journal of Urban Sciences 15 (1) <lb/>(2011) 10-23. <lb/>[30] T.R. Kirkhaug, Communication in Urban Planning, Citizen Participation in Urban Planning, vol.2016, 2016, pp. 1-12. <lb/>[31] V. Ahuja, S. Priyadarshini, Effective communication management for urban infrastructure projects, Journal of Infrastructure Development. 7 (1) (2015) 47-60. <lb/>[32] Ł. Dziedzic, Public communication in urban planning: growing role of online applications for citizen participation, in: T. Parycek, N. Edelmann (Eds.), IT in the <lb/>Public Sphere: Applications in Administration, Government, Politics, and Planning, 2014, pp. 33-47. <lb/>[33] A. Badea, G. Badea, Aspects about Spatial Information Management to Optimize Spatial Planning and Sustainable Development, Conference: Workshop Joint <lb/>FIG Commissions 3 and 8 20-21 July 2021, Prato, Italy, 2021. <lb/>[34] MAKING-CITY Collaboration Secretariat, MAKING-CITY D8.1 Collaboration Secretariat Final, 2020. <lb/>[35] Louis albrechts bridge the gap: from spatial planning to strategic projects, Eur. Plann. Stud. 14 (10) (2006) 1487-1500, https://doi.org/10.1080/ <lb/>09654310600852464. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">N. Yehorchenkova et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e33389 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[36] N. Boyko, I. Teslia, I. Khlevna, et al., PrimaDoc -an enterprise information management system: implementation of the development and deployment project, <lb/>in: The 9th IEEE International Conference on Intelligent Data Acquisition and Advanced Computing Systems: Technology and Applications, 2017, pp. 923-929, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1109/IDAACS.2017.8095222. <lb/>[37] Y. Khlevna, L. Kubyavka, O. Ivanova, N.I. Yehorchenkova, Methodology of Implementation of the Technology of Electronic Management of Geological Projects. <lb/>Geoinformatics: Theoretical and Applied Aspects, vol. 9, 2017, pp. 47-52. <lb/>[38] N. Yehorchenkova, I. Teslia, O. Yehorchenkov, et al., Development of principles and method of electronic project management, E. Eur. J. Enterprise Technol. 5 <lb/>(2017) 23-29, https://doi.org/10.15587/1729-4061.2017.109534. <lb/>[39] N. Yehorchenkova, Project Management Methodology in Dynamic Digital Environment [Doctoral Thesis], Kyiv National University of Construction and <lb/>Architecture, 2018, p. 400. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">N. Yehorchenkova et al. </note>


	</text>
</tei>
