<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping in The Crown of Aragon: Torralba’s Company</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>María Dolores</forename>
            <surname>López Pérez</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Sari</forename>
            <surname>Nassar</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-31T14:37:40.897676Z">31.10.2025 14:37:40</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1344$1$jesb.44656</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Edicions de la Universitat de Barcelona</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1344/jesb.44656</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>María Dolores López Pérez, Sari Nassar. (2024). Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping in The Crown of Aragon: Torralba’s Company. Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business, None(None), None. DOI: 10.1344/jesb.44656</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-31T14:37:40.897676Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-31T14:37:40.897676Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping in The <lb/>Crown of Aragon: Torralba&apos;s Company <lb/>How to cite <lb/>--<lb/>lol <lb/>8 .Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/>Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, Universitat de Barcelona (Spain) <lb/>mdlopez@ub.edu <lb/>G) https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6184-5352 <lb/>Sari Nassar, Universitat de Barcelona (Spain) <lb/>sari.nassar@ub.edu <lb/>G) https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5372-7594 <lb/>Lopez Perez, Maria Dolores, and Sari Nassar. 2024. &quot;Late Medieval Administration <lb/>and Bookkeeping in The Crown of Aragon: Torralba&apos;s Company,&quot; Journal of <lb/>Evolutionary Studies in Business. https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656. <lb/>Received: 31 October 2023 I Accepted: 20 February 2024 I Published on line: 31 October 2024 <lb/>Corresponding author: Sari Nassar I sari.nassar@ub.edu. <lb/>(c) University ofBarcelona, 2024. <lb/>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons <lb/>Attribution-Non-Commercial <lb/>License (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/), which permits non-<lb/>commercial re-use and distribution of <lb/>the original work or its derivative works, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/>COPE Committee on Publication Ethics <lb/>Creative Commons License 4.0 <lb/>Online ISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>http:/ /revistes.ub.edu/index.php/JESB <lb/>JESB <lb/>Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping in The Crown of Aragon: Torralba&apos;s Company <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Administración y contabilidad bajomedieval en la Corona de Aragón: la compañía de Joan de <lb/>Torralba <lb/>Resumen <lb/>Administració i comptabilitat baixmedieval a la Corona d&apos;Aragó: la Companyia de Joan de <lb/>Torralba <lb/>Resum <lb/>. . <lb/>Ila <lb/>• <lb/>.Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business JESB <lb/>Early Views I May 20324 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/>The attempt to rebuild the socioeconomic reality of the fifteenth-century Crown of Aragon has brought us to all the <lb/>companies once founded and managed by Joan de Torralba. Linking two main commercial cities of that time -Zaragoza <lb/>and Barcelona-with the forefront financial centres of those days -Italian cities, in particular, Venice, Pisa-Florence, and <lb/>Genoa -set the company in a unique position. This paper studies two primary components of our business: corporate <lb/>and financial management. This analysis intends to demonstrate the complexity of management in late medieval <lb/>companies of the Crown of Aragon, alongside knowledge diffusion and the extent and significance of weaving networks. <lb/>We have in mind to present how the administration was developing, giving the local colour and regional details, making <lb/>much of the proper management and contacts through the Mediterranean, employing management and historical <lb/>analysis. The results reveal that the companies in the Crown of Aragon benefited from their management approach, <lb/>which was comprehensive and advanced, for that era. The position of merchant elites, with the example observed by Joan <lb/>de Torralba as the executive, was prominent. Hence, the weight of the last centuries of the Middle Ages, considering the <lb/>West Mediterranean area, was essential in the transition to build a modern-like economic space. <lb/>Keywords: management history, corporate administration, late medieval business, Crown of Aragon, Joan de Torralba, bookkeeping <lb/>L&apos;intent de reconstruir la realitat socioeconomica de la Corona dArago de! segle XV ens ha portat a analitzar Jes empreses fundades i <lb/>gestionades pel mercader Joan de Torralba. La vinculacio de dues de Jes principals ciutats comercials de! Quatre-cents i seus de la <lb/>companyia -Saragossa i Barcelona-amb els centres financers d&apos;avantguarda de l&apos;epoca -ciutats italianes, en particular Venecia, Pisa-<lb/>Florencia i Genova-va situar l&apos;empresa en una posicio unica. Aquest article estudia dos components fonamentals de la nostra <lb/>companyia, la gestio empresarial i la gestio financera, amb la finalitat de demostrar la complexitat de la gestio de Jes empreses <lb/>baixmedievals de la Corona d&apos;Arago i, alhora, demostrar la difusio de! coneixement i l&apos;extensio i importancia de Jes xarxes dintercanvi. <lb/>El nostre objectiu es presentar com es va desenvolupar l&apos;administracio de la companyia Torralba, considerant para.metres locals i <lb/>regionals, fent especial emfasi en la gestio i els contactes a traves de la Mediterrania i emprant l&apos;analisi historica i de gestio. Els <lb/>resultats revelen que Jes empreses de la Corona d&apos;Arago, de Jes quals Torralba es un estudi de cas, es van beneficiar d&apos;un enfocament de <lb/>gestio integral i avarn;:at, i que, per tant, la posicio de Jes elits mercantils van tenir un lloc destacat en la conformacio de l&apos;espai mercantil <lb/>mediterrani. D&apos;aixo es conclou que el pes dels darrers segles de l&apos;edat mitjana, considerant !&apos;area de la Mediterrania Occidental, <lb/>resultes essencial en la transicio per construir un espai economic de tall modern. <lb/>Paraules clau: historia de gestio, administracio corporativa, negocis baixmedievals, Corona d&apos;Arago, Joan de Torralba, comptabilitat <lb/>El intento de reconstruir la realidad socioeconomica de la Corona de Aragon de! siglo XV nos ha llevado a analizar las empresas <lb/>fundades y gestionades por el mercader Joan de Torralba. La vinculacion de dos de las principales ciudades comerciales de! <lb/>Cuatrocientos y sedes de la compaiifa -Zaragoza y Barcelona-con los centros financieros de vanguardia de la epoca -ciudades italianas, <lb/>en particular, Venecia, Pisa-Florencia y Genova-situo a la empresa en una posicion unica. Este articulo estudia dos componentes <lb/>fundamentales de nuestra compaiifa, la gestion empresarial y la gestion financiera, con la finalidad de demostrar la complejidad de la <lb/>gestion de las empresas bajomedievales de la Corona de Aragon y, al mismo tiempo, demostrar la difusion de! conocimiento y la <lb/>extension e importancia de las redes de intercambio. Nuestro objetivo es presentar como se desarrollo la administracion de la <lb/>compaiifa Torralba, considerando para.metros locales y regionales, haciendo especial hincapie en la gestion yen los contactos a traves <lb/>de! Mediterraneo y empleando el analisis historico y de gestion. Los resultados revelan que las empresas de la Corona de Aragon, de las <lb/>cuales Torralba es un estudio de caso, se beneficiaron de un enfoque de gestion integral y avanzado, y que, por consiguiente, la posicion <lb/>de las elites mercantiles tuvieron un lugar destacado en la conformacion de! espacio mercantil mediterraneo. De ello se concluye que el <lb/>peso de los ultimos siglos de la Edad Media, considerando el area de! Mediterraneo Occidental, resultara esencial en la transicion para <lb/>construir un espacio economico de corte moderno. <lb/>Palabras clave: historia de la gestion, administracion de empresas, negocios bajomedievales, Corona de Aragon, Joan de Torralba, <lb/>tenedurfa de libros <lb/></front>

        <body>Introduction <lb/>The Catalan mercantile companies in his-<lb/>toriography <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Marfa Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping... <lb/></note>

        <page>3 <lb/></page>

        <body>The purpose of the research is an analysis of the <lb/>business techniques actively used by the <lb/>merchants of the Crown of Aragon at the end of <lb/>the Middle Ages through a case study of the <lb/>commercial activities of Joan de Torralba, a <lb/>merchant who operated in fifteenth-century <lb/>Barcelona. We study them to find out the <lb/>pattern of how these companies operated <lb/>during the late medieval ages, giving special <lb/>consideration to the &apos;management&apos; aspects of <lb/>the companies. However, they are almost <lb/>always based on an incomplete picture, since <lb/>there is not much information preserved. It is <lb/>usually sections of the book or parts, but the <lb/>data is still priceless. For most companies of <lb/>merchants from the Crown of Aragon, only one <lb/>accounting book has been preserved. In other <lb/>cases, there is information available from <lb/>notarial or fiscal documentation, but that alone <lb/>is not enough to fully understand the operation <lb/>of these companies. Therefore, the case of <lb/>having twelve completely preserved accounting <lb/>books is unique; on top of that uniqueness, they <lb/>are all in chronological order. They are in the <lb/>National <lb/>Archive <lb/>of <lb/>Catalonia <lb/>and <lb/>corresponding <lb/>to <lb/>Joan <lb/>de <lb/>Torralba. <lb/>Furthermore, in his commercial activity, we <lb/>identify the complexity of business running that <lb/>indicates the advancement of managerial <lb/>techniques among merchants. Hence, the <lb/>central objective is to analyse the mentioned <lb/>company to prove the development of <lb/>management and bookkeeping techniques in <lb/>the late medieval Crown of Aragon. The novelty <lb/>of the study is that such an analysis could be <lb/>made only when there is a complete picture of <lb/>the data necessary to verify our hypothesis, that <lb/>the origin of the modern corporate system can <lb/>be found in the companies established in the <lb/>last medieval centuries. A deduction that we <lb/>have from the partial analyses of these <lb/>companies carried out so far can be verified or <lb/>not by applying -some modern management <lb/>parameters. We acknowledge the risk of <lb/>analysing <lb/>a <lb/>medieval <lb/>company <lb/>with <lb/>contemporary methods but believe it can <lb/>provide valuable insights into similarities and <lb/>differences in operation and management. <lb/>Exactly what we do with our company. <lb/>Meanwhile, we may intuit the similarity with <lb/>other companies, attempting to approximate <lb/>and re-create but not prove it empirically. <lb/>It is important to mention some aspects of why <lb/>this company was chosen. The first one, and <lb/>most straightforward, the presence of all the <lb/>books throughout the whole chronology of <lb/>Joan&apos;s activity. However, there is another <lb/>essential point. Our case is (how we would call <lb/>it today using modern terminology) SMEs -<lb/>Small and Medium-sized Enterprises. 1 Studying <lb/>small-sized companies provides valuable <lb/>insights into a diverse range of business <lb/>aspects, <lb/>including <lb/>innovation, <lb/>entrepreneurship, community impact, and <lb/>resource management. Understanding the <lb/>challenges and strategies of small businesses <lb/>enriches our understanding of the broader <lb/>business ecosystem and contributes to a well-<lb/>rounded <lb/>perspective <lb/>on <lb/>business <lb/>administration. <lb/>The interest in mercantile societies is linked to <lb/>Mediterranean expansion, maritime trade, and <lb/>navigation, aspects that have attracted the <lb/>attention of historians. In the 1970s, two <lb/>magnificent works were translated about the <lb/>world of Barcelona&apos;s merchants -Mario del <lb/>Treppo and Claude Carrere. They both <lb/>approached, from different perspectives, the <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">1 For the international European panorama, notably <lb/>compared to Italians vanguard companies, however, it is <lb/>a reasonably big company within the Crown&apos;s business <lb/>circles. <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <page>4 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping ... <lb/></note>

        <body>issue of the so-called late medieval &quot;crisis&quot; and <lb/>included in their analysis topics such as <lb/>commercial methods (Del Treppo 1976, Carrere <lb/>1977-78). In the 1980s, Josep Maria Madurell <lb/>and Arcadi Garcia published a magnificent <lb/>analysis of Catalan mercantile societies from a <lb/>historical-legal perspective, focusing their <lb/>research on the formation and development of <lb/>the partnership contract and providing a <lb/>selection of documents from the Historical <lb/>Archive of Protocols of Barcelona (Madurell and <lb/>Garcia 1986). Notarial contracts are the <lb/>documentary basis used by Nuria Coll to <lb/>reconstruct the origins of several companies <lb/>that operated in 15th century Barcelona (Coll <lb/>1968, 1981), and by Coral Cuadrada and Marfa <lb/>Dolores Lopez in their analysis of the economic <lb/>characteristics and levels of operation of <lb/>societies in the 14th century (Cuadrada and <lb/>Lopez 1991). <lb/>The notarial sources, on which the research of <lb/>Madurell and Garcia, Coll, and Cuadrada and <lb/>Lopez are based, provide extremely important <lb/>information about the movement of capitals <lb/>and commercial activities in the merchant <lb/>sector by recording not only the establishment <lb/>of companies but also sales, insurances, <lb/>commissions, loans, etc. However, they do not <lb/>record the daily activities of the merchant, <lb/>which are reflected in the accounting books. In <lb/>the Barcelona archives, there are preserved <lb/>accounting records that reflect the activities <lb/>carried out by individual operators or <lb/>mercantile societies, although they are <lb/>extremely rare. The surviving records show <lb/>enormous heterogeneity due to the different <lb/>realities and needs of the companies or <lb/>individual merchants who generated them. The <lb/>management <lb/>systems <lb/>used <lb/>differently <lb/>according to the levels of complexity of their <lb/>businesses and are always adapted to the goal <lb/>of managing commercial data. Medieval <lb/>companies had, according to their size, or even <lb/>more so, according to the complexity of their <lb/>businesses, main books, and subsidiary books. <lb/>In the present day, researchers have primarily <lb/>focused their attention on the accounting books <lb/>deposited in the Archive of the Cathedral of <lb/>Barcelona and the National Archive of <lb/>Catalonia. The Archive of the Cathedral of <lb/>Barcelona houses more than 70 manuscripts, in <lb/>the section known as &quot;Extravagants,&quot; series <lb/>&apos;Comptes <lb/>de <lb/>companyies, <lb/>comerciants, <lb/>navegants, etc. (1268-1864),&apos; which record the <lb/>accounts of companies or merchant voyages. <lb/>Conscious of the importance of making these <lb/>economic sources known, Madurell published <lb/>in the 1960s the accounts of a 14th-century <lb/>Barcelona society, the Mitjavila Company <lb/>(Madurell 1965 and 1966); a research <lb/>endeavour that was later taken up by Victor <lb/>Hurtado (2005, 2007). The archive also has the <lb/>books of the Tarasco Company, transcribed and <lb/>studied by Elisa Varela (1995), and those of the <lb/>merchant Joan Gasull, analyzed by Juanjo <lb/>Caceres (2011). Within the same collection, the <lb/>records of the journeys of Joan Benet to Cyprus <lb/>and Sardinia are preserved, which attracted the <lb/>attention of Maria Vila (1977) and Josep Plana <lb/>(1983), as well as those of Berenguer Benet to <lb/>Romania, studied by Daniel Duran (2002), or <lb/>the ship captained by Arnau Espaer and Romeu <lb/>d&apos;Olzinelles, navigating the Mallorca-Honein-<lb/>Mallorca route, analysed by Jose I. Padilla and <lb/>M.D. Lopez (2013, 2021) and Daniel Duran <lb/>(2009). These works mostly delve into the <lb/>reconstruction and analysis of societies and <lb/>merchants operating in 14th century Barcelona. <lb/>The most important documentary collection on <lb/>medieval Catalan companies, however, is <lb/>located in the National Archive of Catalonia, <lb/>where the patrimonial fund of the Palau <lb/>Requesens is deposited. Among the numerous <lb/>documentation that integrates this patrimonial <lb/>fund, there are the accounting records of two <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <body>The Torralba Company: Ledgers, Journals <lb/>and Economic Characteristics <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Marfa Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping... <lb/></note>

        <page>5 <lb/></page>

        <body>15th century Barcelona merchants, Joan de <lb/>Torralba and Joan Sabastida, as well as parallel <lb/>documentation <lb/>necessary <lb/>for <lb/>the <lb/>reconstruction of the companies in which they <lb/>participated as partners. The documentation of <lb/>the merchant Torralba, our case study, was <lb/>made known in the late 1960s by Mario del <lb/>Treppo, outlining the lines of action of the <lb/>Torralba Company (Del Treppo 1976). In 1985, <lb/>Jose Angel Sesma renewed his interest in this <lb/>company following the discovery of its articles <lb/>of incorporation in the notarial records of <lb/>Zaragoza. Although the importance of this <lb/>company was highlighted by the works of Del <lb/>Treppo and Sesma, it wasn&apos;t until 2013 that <lb/>further studies were conducted. In that year, <lb/>M.D. Lopez published an article on the wool <lb/>business of Torralba with Italy, which marked <lb/>the beginning of the research currently being <lb/>carried out by our research group, GRAMP-Med, <lb/>where one of the primary objectives was to <lb/>analyse the accounting books of Joan de <lb/>Torralba. <lb/>His accounting books are currently the focus of <lb/>several competitive projects of our research <lb/>group, GRAMP-Med, within the framework of <lb/>which the transcription, edition, and study of <lb/>the 12 preserved books are being carried out <lb/>(Lopez et al. 2019, Benavides and Casado 2019, <lb/>Viu 2021, 2022), yielding promising initial <lb/>results with the priority objective of being able <lb/>to generate, for the Crown of Aragon, an <lb/>economic model comparable to that established <lb/>for Tuscan companies, thereby enabling the <lb/>design of parameters that can be handled as <lb/>models of action by economic actors of the <lb/>Crown of Aragon (Abulafia and Lopez 2020, Viu <lb/>2021). <lb/>In this fast-developing world through <lb/>innovation and trade growth, daughters, wives, <lb/>and widows played a decisive role; decisive, <lb/>among other aspects, as sole responsible <lb/>parties in the event of becoming widows, taking <lb/>charge of investments, purchasing goods, being <lb/>partners in companies, and managing <lb/>commercial accounting. While it is true that the <lb/>History of Women is a fruitful and rich research <lb/>pathway in the Spanish Academy, the <lb/>achievements and training of daughters, wives, <lb/>mothers, and widows of merchants are a <lb/>relatively little-known aspect. An exception is <lb/>the work of Gemma Colesanti and Martina del <lb/>Popolo, which focuses on the analysis of the <lb/>four accounting books of Caterina Llull, the <lb/>second wife of Joan Sabastida (Colesanti 2008, <lb/>Colesanti and Del Popolo 2020). The mastery <lb/>with which she managed the inherited <lb/>investments denotes prior learning, as a co-<lb/>participant in the family business and, <lb/>probably, as the sole investor in some of them. <lb/>Torralba was the founder of a company that <lb/>emerged in the first half of the 1400s and was <lb/>initially founded by partners of Aragonese <lb/>origin, Joan de Torralba and Fortuny de <lb/>Manariello, established in Barcelona, and a <lb/>partner from Zaragoza, Juan Feixas. It arose <lb/>with the aim of trading two primary products of <lb/>the Aragonese export to Barcelona and then to <lb/>Italy: wheat and wool. During its more than <lb/>twenty years of operation, from 1425 to 1447, <lb/>the company interwove a network of interests <lb/>in the Italian markets, taking advantage of a <lb/>favourable situation in the wool market and the <lb/>growing demand from Italian textile centres. <lb/>The company&apos;s businesses were only one part <lb/>of our merchant&apos;s investment schemes, possibly <lb/>the one that generated the least profit, <lb/>allocating a considerable percentage of his <lb/>capital to other forms of investment carried out <lb/>individually and beyond the company. Without <lb/>quitting his partners and the wool business, <lb/>Torralba designs new strategies and explores <lb/>different markets, conditioned by the novel <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <page>6 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping ... <lb/></note>

        <body>international situation. He continues to invest <lb/>in strictly commercial activities in Naples, <lb/>Tunis, Mallorca, and Alexandria. At the same <lb/>time, he set up ties with the major Italian banks <lb/>of the Four Hundred (the Bernardi and Garzoni, <lb/>the Soranzi and, strikingly, the Balbi and the <lb/>Medici) while evolving intense business with <lb/>the members of the Tuscan and German <lb/>communities. They traded in the squares of <lb/>Barcelona, Zaragoza and Tortosa. It also <lb/>underlines crucial business concerning public <lb/>debt operations, the arming of corsair vessels, <lb/>the redemption of captives, and the purchase of <lb/>the rural and urban real estate, without the <lb/>purpose of an abandonment of the mercantile <lb/>profession (Abulafia and Lopez 2020, Viu <lb/>2021). The unprecedented nature of this <lb/>company lies not in its operation, comparable <lb/>to most companies in the Crown of Aragon, but <lb/>in the conservation of XII accounting books <lb/>related to the administration of the company <lb/>and the private business of one of the partners, <lb/>Joan of Torralba. These records, currently kept <lb/>in the National Archive of Catalonia, have been <lb/>transcribed and partially published (Lopez et al. <lb/>2019, Benavides and Casado 2019, Viu 2021, <lb/>2022). The companies and the commercial <lb/>activity in general of the Torralba are a key <lb/>element for exploring the processes of <lb/>Europeanisation-internationalisation of trade <lb/>and the formation of a market economy that, <lb/>broadly speaking, is initiating to resemble the <lb/>appearance of the economic system that we <lb/>know today. The study of the matters <lb/>introduced, assuming the businesses of <lb/>Torralba as the subject of analysis, will make it <lb/>feasible to comprehend the economic <lb/>behaviour of the mercantile elite of the Crown <lb/>of Aragon, providing alluring components in the <lb/>debate on the ingenious role of late medieval <lb/>merchants. <lb/>Merchants as actors in the <lb/>economic realm, as well as social, contribute to <lb/>shaping a new European space while cultural <lb/>changes took place in Europe during the <lb/>transition from the Middle Ages to the modern <lb/>age. This space sees intense commercial <lb/>relationships developing at an international <lb/>level, generating for the first time a commercial <lb/>macro space understood in modern terms. This <lb/>integrated economic system would contribute <lb/>to the construction of a European mentality. <lb/>Torralba lived in a world that is emerging from <lb/>a profound restructuration, now understood <lb/>more as a structural alternation and a <lb/>reconversion, more as &apos;creative destruction&apos; <lb/>dynamics than as a unilateral and widespread <lb/>depression. From this perspective, it would <lb/>provoke a dynamic of growth. A positive <lb/>interpretation of the crisis of the 1300s, now <lb/>tendentially prevalent, values the positive <lb/>aspects of the demographic downturn. This <lb/>enabled a more rational use of land, <lb/>abandonment of marginal lands, an increase in <lb/>wages, and a process of productive <lb/>specialization both in the agricultural and <lb/>manufacturing spheres. <lb/>Based on the analysis of accounting data, <lb/>Torralba creates business networks that align <lb/>with the networks formed by the Catalan <lb/>merchant sector during the 14th and 15th <lb/>centuries. These networks consist of centers of <lb/>varying importance that are integrated with <lb/>each other. The main question is how the late <lb/>medieval economic recession affected these <lb/>markets and, as a result, how it may have <lb/>impacted the investments made by Torralba <lb/>and its partners. A sectoral analysis of the <lb/>different markets frequented by the merchants <lb/>of the Crown of Aragon in the Western <lb/>Mediterranean, an area of intervention for the <lb/>Torralba company, appears to confirm recent <lb/>&quot;diagnoses&quot; of historiography regarding the <lb/>non-recession of commercial activities in the <lb/>last medieval centuries. The frequency of <lb/>contacts with the markets of Sardinia, the ports <lb/>of Sicily, southern Italy, Nasrid Granada, or the <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Marfa Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping... <lb/></note>

        <page>7 <lb/></page>

        <body>Maghreb areas etc. -indicates a continuity, even <lb/>an increase in business volumes. Thus, crisis <lb/>parameters do not seem to affect the trade <lb/>developed in the areas of the Western <lb/>Mediterranean. It is therefore in international <lb/>trade where the fastest changes are visible, <lb/>linked to a boom in local economies and <lb/>markets driven by credit and, above all, by an <lb/>increase in demand. The weight of external <lb/>demand, restricted to a few attractive products, <lb/>combined with a growing domestic market <lb/>capable of directing productions. Therefore, <lb/>new routes, new exchanges, new techniques, <lb/>and new goods characterize this &quot;First Global <lb/>Age&quot; (Casado 2011). In this regard, we believe <lb/>that in line with the debates surrounding the <lb/>meaning of globalisation and its possible <lb/>historical <lb/>precedents, <lb/>the <lb/>commercial <lb/>development of Western Europe could <lb/>condition, <lb/>along <lb/>with <lb/>new <lb/>political <lb/>circumstances, a redesign of commercial <lb/>circuits and modifications in economic <lb/>orientations. The profits from this international <lb/>trade, whose transfers were facilitated by the <lb/>creation of a network for settling advances and <lb/>international debts negotiated through bills of <lb/>exchange, enabled the accumulation of capital <lb/>in dynamic centres such as Genoa, Venice, <lb/>Milan, Florence, or Barcelona -profits upon <lb/>which the expansion towards overseas <lb/>territories was founded. This expansion, <lb/>accelerated and reinforced in the 16 th and 17 th <lb/>centuries, allows us to hypothesise about a <lb/>&apos;First Globalisation&apos; already by the late Middle <lb/>Ages. <lb/>What are those modifications? Modifications <lb/>materialise in the routes due to foreign <lb/>competition, as well as setbacks in some <lb/>marketplaces due to political conflicts. There <lb/>are also transformations in the very nature of <lb/>exchanges, in the range of goods being traded. <lb/>The increasing importance of agricultural <lb/>products and raw materials -such as cereals, <lb/>oil, nuts, saffron, wool, etc. -enhances local <lb/>economies in some cases, as they specialise in <lb/>the production of these commodities. The <lb/>integration of luxury items with others of low <lb/>value but of daily use and high demand allows <lb/>for adjustments in freight. The pressure exerted <lb/>by foreign operators drives some of the <lb/>reorientation of crops aimed at meeting <lb/>external demand. Therefore, the effects of the <lb/>crisis must be seen in this sense, as a <lb/>restructuring motivated by the effects of <lb/>demand and an adaptation of the capacities of <lb/>each of the commercial centres. Torralba and <lb/>his partners are skilled merchants who took <lb/>advantage of these changes to intervene in two <lb/>of the most active sectors with the greatest <lb/>growth potential in the second quarter of the <lb/>15th century: the commercialisation of cereal, <lb/>which is always deficient in Mediterranean <lb/>cities, and wool, a product constantly <lb/>demanded by the main Italian textile centres <lb/>(Lopez 2013, Abulafia and Lopez 2020). <lb/>Alongside, the study of our merchant in the <lb/>framework of the trade that he carried out <lb/>suggests access to the panorama of late <lb/>medieval trade and an approximation of the <lb/>evolution of corollary economic thought <lb/>(Schwartz 2001, Navarro 2020). <lb/>The historical evolution of the economic system <lb/>-real practice -i.e., the change like the object of <lb/>economic theory, plays a key role at the end of <lb/>the XIV at the beginning of the XV century. It is <lb/>the logical continuity of scientific knowledge <lb/>and the advancement of its intellectual process. <lb/>Of fundamental importance in the development <lb/>of economic culture are real changes in the <lb/>economic life of society, where the commercial <lb/>activity of Joan de Torralba may serve as an <lb/>excellent example for our geographical area. It <lb/>is the commercial activity and real changes that <lb/>led to the origin of various scientific schools <lb/>and new economic directions. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <body>Data collection and methodology <lb/></body>

        <page>8 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping ... <lb/></note>

        <body>The priority of empirical studies in social <lb/>sciences as a nucleus against theorising has <lb/>been remarkably defended by De Roover. <lb/>Likewise, the words of Robert Lopez may point <lb/>out the relevance of small-sized businesses for <lb/>general awareness in socio-economic research -<lb/>&quot;first gather the facts, explain the smaller <lb/>problems that each of them involves, and finally <lb/>see what general theory, if any, can be built <lb/>upon them&quot; (Lopez 1948, 63). Similarly, it is <lb/>necessary to mention a curious fact that would <lb/>help to understand the pivotal limitation of the <lb/>interpretive process when it comes to medieval <lb/>and temporally distant companies. As <lb/>expressed by Sturdy and Fleming, &quot;mental <lb/>constructs cannot be directly observed, and <lb/>must be put into action -operationally or <lb/>discursively -to be impactful&quot; (Sturdy and <lb/>Fleming 2003) -implies another perspective of <lb/>interpretation that is based on the analysis of <lb/>the techniques, policies, and behaviour but not <lb/>ideas per se, therefore the preserved <lb/>accounting books, Articles of Incorporation, <lb/>private letters and the way and manner of <lb/>conducting the business, provide us with <lb/>valuable information to <lb/>simulate the <lb/>contemporary reality of our merchant (Jones <lb/>2008). Furthermore, the recreation of the <lb/>company of Catalan and Aragonese origin can <lb/>also provide a space for a comparison study <lb/>with the Iberian accounting and management <lb/>model to define the clear differences in the <lb/>entrepreneurship that took place between the <lb/>companies of Crown of Aragon and Italian in <lb/>what refers to the mercantile and accounting <lb/>realm (Hernandez Esteve 2006, Mari and <lb/>Alvaro 2020). <lb/>This chapter outlines the research design, data <lb/>collection methods, and analytical approach <lb/>employed in the study of late medieval <lb/>company management. The goal of this <lb/>research is to gain insights into the <lb/>organisational <lb/>structure, <lb/>decision-making <lb/>processes, and economic practices of late <lb/>medieval companies in the Crown of Aragon. <lb/>This study adopts a historical research <lb/>approach to investigate late medieval company <lb/>management. It involves the examination and <lb/>interpretation of primary and secondary <lb/>historical sources to reconstruct and <lb/>understand the organisational and managerial <lb/>practices prevalent during the late medieval <lb/>period. The selection of case studies is based on <lb/>historical significance, availability of relevant <lb/>sources, and diversity in the types of sources. <lb/>The commercial activity of Joan de Torralba has <lb/>been chosen for analysis. The documental base <lb/>of our research consists of the XIII accounting <lb/>books corresponding to the management of <lb/>Joan de Torralba and preserved in the National <lb/>Archive of Catalonia ( see Annex II). <lb/>All these books are stored at the ANC (Arxiu <lb/>Nacional de Catalunya), under the Requesens <lb/>fund. We have 3 ledgers (llibre major), 3 <lb/>journals (manual), and 8 account books (/fibre <lb/>de comptes) at our disposal. Additionally, there <lb/>are two boxes of loose documentation <lb/>(fragments, letters and notes). <lb/>The documentation referring to the Torralba <lb/>company is found not only in the National <lb/>Archive of Catalonia but also in other archival <lb/>collections. The investigations carried out to <lb/>date have made it possible to locate relevant <lb/>information in the archives of those centres <lb/>linked to the company and its partners, <lb/>enabling the analysis of cases not sufficiently <lb/>explained in the accounting records. In this <lb/>sense, the Articles of Incorporation have been <lb/>crucial, uncovered in the archives of the <lb/>Zaragoza notaries Anton de Aldovera and <lb/>Salvador de la Faz. The latter has provided <lb/>information concerning the partners, the social <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <body>Macro outlook of economic <lb/>climate <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Marfa Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping... <lb/></note>


        <page>9 <lb/></page>

        <body>capital, and the system of operation of <lb/>successive companies. The above-mentioned <lb/>has allowed us to work with two types of data: <lb/>quantitative and qualitative. The reading and <lb/>interpretation of the collected data have made <lb/>it possible to reconstruct the company&apos;s <lb/>organisation chart and forms of activity. <lb/>The considerable volume of data from <lb/>transcribing the eleven accounting books made <lb/>it necessary to design a database. This base <lb/>focuses on the details of the administrative <lb/>structure of the companies, with relevant <lb/>information regarding accounting data. FENIX, <lb/>the name of the dataset, aims to use and <lb/>process the data compiled with analytical and <lb/>statistical criteria to be able to interpret them <lb/>in the double keyway -financial and social -<lb/>(Trave, Lopez, Casado, Alvaro and Mari 2018, <lb/>Travel and Casado 2020). There is a possibility <lb/>to see the interface of the aforesaid integrated <lb/>system for data gathering and management <lb/>FENIX in Annex II. <lb/>The research utilises a case study method to <lb/>focus on selected late medieval companies as <lb/>representative examples of the broader <lb/>management practices of the time. By <lb/>employing in-depth case studies, this research <lb/>aims <lb/>to <lb/>provide <lb/>a <lb/>comprehensive <lb/>understanding <lb/>of <lb/>specific <lb/>companies&apos; <lb/>management structures and operations. <lb/>Economic, social and cultural shifts that took <lb/>place in the transition between the Middle Ages <lb/>and the Modern Age -contributed to the design <lb/>of a new European space in which significant <lb/>commercial ties were developed at a supra-<lb/>national level. Commercial space was generated <lb/>for the first time in a way it is understood in <lb/>modern days, as an integrated economic system <lb/>that would eventually contribute to the building <lb/>of a European mentality. In the XV-XVI <lb/>centuries, in Western Europe, there was a <lb/>period of unconscious attempts to create a <lb/>&apos;single market&apos; within a certain territory as a <lb/>basis. Italian cities were the benchmark of <lb/>economic and commercial expansion in the <lb/>medieval centuries. They were spreading their <lb/>operational pattern to other cities such as <lb/>Barcelona, Valencia, Zaragoza or Mallorca, <lb/>making possible the accumulation of capital <lb/>necessary for the subsequent overseas <lb/>expansion at the time of the Early modern <lb/>period, the theory that was heavily supported <lb/>by M. Del Treppo and Giampiero Nigro. They <lb/>defended the theory that Tuscan companies, <lb/>that were presented in Catalonia, had a <lb/>considerable impact on converting Barcelona <lb/>into the one of the most important financial <lb/>centres of the time. The same as Tuscan <lb/>companies contributed to the spread and the <lb/>wide usage of the bills of exchange and <lb/>promoted the market of marine insurance. <lb/>Cities of the Crown of Aragon were satellite-like <lb/>objects of Italian centres when it came to <lb/>techniques and knowledge diffusion. The latter <lb/>gives a special place to the royal cities of the <lb/>Kingdom in business history. That is why <lb/>commercial history has focused its interest, for <lb/>decades, on the &quot;great trade&quot;, in which these <lb/>and other Italian cities exercised the guiding <lb/>pattern as poles of growth and spread of <lb/>mercantile techniques and economic thought <lb/>(Rothbard 2006, Schumpeter 1954, Melis <lb/>1962). However, nowadays, there is a way new <lb/>view on the matter of the question and paying a <lb/>higher attention to the power of &quot;local market&quot; <lb/>rather than the &apos;great trade&apos; and one of the first <lb/>to indicate that was Jose A. Sesma (Sesma <lb/>2006). <lb/>During this period, an increase in the number of <lb/>consumers should be mentioned. Consequently, <lb/>growth in demand which caused the extension <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <page>10 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping ... <lb/></note>

        <body>of products offered on the market took place. It <lb/>was, however, in the fourteenth and fifteenth <lb/>centuries when a market was determined by <lb/>the search for profit and capital accumulation <lb/>alongside the concept of rationality that tended <lb/>to change the old forms of production (Igual <lb/>2008). It was produced to sell, not in nearby <lb/>markets, but to respond to international <lb/>demand. Simultaneous development of various <lb/>factors such as the spread of checks, <lb/>promissory notes, bills of exchange, double-<lb/>entry accounting, maritime insurance and the <lb/>rise of banking (Palermo 2008) played their <lb/>decisive role. The response lies in those late <lb/>medieval centuries and the operation of the <lb/>major European business companies. <lb/>Late medieval merchants, among which <lb/>Aragonese, Catalan, Valencian and Mallorcan <lb/>tradesmen, were the leading actors in building <lb/>a modern like economy, where multilingualism, <lb/>alongside the growing role of women in the <lb/>management of mercantile companies, played a <lb/>remarkably prominent role. To intervene safely, <lb/>businessmen needed specific knowledge about <lb/>the functioning of the markets and the factors <lb/>that could impact their business, both in <lb/>product transactions and financial transfers. <lb/>The accumulation of knowledge acquired <lb/>through commercial practice was recorded in <lb/>the Ledgers and private notes. In these books, <lb/>the relevant information is reflected -inter <lb/>alia tax systems, currency values -but the <lb/>continuous changes in market conditions <lb/>required immediacy and instantaneous access <lb/>to changing circumstances on which knowledge <lb/>success or failure may have influenced <lb/>commercial performance. In the fast-moving <lb/>reality of innovation, exchange and circulation <lb/>of knowledge and skills, daughters, wives, and <lb/>widows played a decisive role, despite not <lb/>being trained with the same skills as those <lb/>acquired by their brothers or husbands (Lopez, <lb/>Cuadrada and Trave 2023). <lb/>It is no secret that networking is crucial. <lb/>Networks could have gone beyond solely family <lb/>limits. It was about social networks that made <lb/>merchants successful, along with protection <lb/>during their journeys, accompanied by the <lb/>required information for the prosperous <lb/>running of their businesses. The mobility of <lb/>these economic elites, and their installation in <lb/>the main European business centres, even in <lb/>the Maghreb, encouraged the circulation of <lb/>ideas in heterogeneous but deeply permeable <lb/>societies, where these newcomers -privileged <lb/>foreigners-swung between insertion and social <lb/>adaptation. However, there was always osmosis <lb/>between natives and foreigners, along with the <lb/>cultural transmission of commercial techniques. <lb/>The obvious thing was that the cultural level of <lb/>the mercantile sector differed concerning the <lb/>extent of the business carried out and the <lb/>geographical location of its economic interests. <lb/>Knowledge is the nucleus of being successful in <lb/>the undertaken commercial activities. First and <lb/>foremost, the merchant had to know the <lb/>situation on the foreign markets, like the prices <lb/>of the products or the supply levels at a given <lb/>time, and always had to be attentive to a <lb/>political situation, circumstantial, that could <lb/>cause dysfunctions in the normal operation of <lb/>the market (Kohn 1999). We should not bypass <lb/>that the world of information was vivid and <lb/>altering, and the markets tended to fluctuate <lb/>with just the arrival at the port of a merchant <lb/>ship with the most recent information on <lb/>distant places. The most experienced factors <lb/>dealt with obtaining news about prices, the <lb/>acquisition of raw materials or the functioning <lb/>of the markets, and sometimes they could <lb/>synthesise the facts acquired in the so-called <lb/>&apos;merchandise manuals&apos; (Cuadrada 2019). <lb/>Hence, the need to have loyal and reliable <lb/>agents in the most important markets was an <lb/>absolute must (Erikson and Samila 2018). <lb/>When discussing late medieval management, <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <body>Accounting <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Marfa Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping ... <lb/></note>

        <page>11 <lb/></page>

        <body>we are not referring to it in the same way as we <lb/>speak about modern management practices <lb/>today. The concept of &apos;management&apos; as we <lb/>understand it today, with its formal structures, <lb/>theories, and systematic approach to organising <lb/>and leading organisations, did not exist in the <lb/>same form during the late medieval period. In <lb/>the modern context, management involves a set <lb/>of principles, practices, and theories developed <lb/>over the last century or so, with roots in the <lb/>industrial revolution and the rise of large-scale <lb/>organisations. It encompasses concepts such as <lb/>organisational <lb/>hierarchy, <lb/>scientific <lb/>management, human resources, strategic <lb/>planning, quality control, and more. In contrast, <lb/>the late medieval period (the 14th to the 16th <lb/>centuries) predates the development of modern <lb/>management theory. During this time, societies <lb/>were organised differently, and the economy <lb/>was primarily agrarian and feudal. There were <lb/>no formal business corporations or modern <lb/>industries as we know them today. Instead, <lb/>economic activities were often localised, with <lb/>guilds playing a significant role in regulating <lb/>trade and craftsmanship. While some basic <lb/>principles of management, such as leadership, <lb/>communication, and organisation, have always <lb/>been present throughout history, they were not <lb/>approached or defined in the same systematic <lb/>and structured way as in modern management. <lb/>When we talk about &apos;late medieval <lb/>management,&apos; we are usually referring to how <lb/>economic activities and social structures were <lb/>organised during that period. However, it is <lb/>important to recognise that these practices <lb/>were shaped by the historical context and were <lb/>quite different from the sophisticated <lb/>management practices we see today. So, while <lb/>we can study and analyse how economic <lb/>activities were managed during the late <lb/>medieval period, it would be incorrect to apply <lb/>the term &apos;management&apos; in the same sense as we <lb/>do in contemporary discussions of modern <lb/>management practices, hence by management <lb/>we always mean the administration practises <lb/>that we are able to trace and intention to <lb/>&quot;translate&quot; them into modern management <lb/>language, exclusively to facilitate <lb/>the <lb/>comprehension and better visualisation. <lb/>In urban centres, especially during the late <lb/>medieval period, as trade and commerce began <lb/>to develop, some rudimentary forms of <lb/>mercantile accounting emerged. Traders and <lb/>merchants would keep records of their <lb/>inventory, purchases, and sales, often in the <lb/>form of journals or ledgers. In the Middle Ages, <lb/>far more than any public authority, the needs of <lb/>a business required merchants to compile <lb/>account books. Despite the tight relationship <lb/>between accounting and taxation, the <lb/>indifference of the legislator in accounting <lb/>matters is therefore not a topic of current <lb/>interest (Gual 1981). Nevertheless, a riveting <lb/>notion arose in the Middle Ages -merchants <lb/>kept secret books, by the latter should be <lb/>understood documents to which no public had <lb/>access. These were presumably management <lb/>tools, for making an internal assessment. <lb/>Consequently, no legal status was recognised. <lb/>Before the courts, in case of conflict, only the <lb/>ledger was valid. However, it could also be the <lb/>subject of litigation (Mufi.oz 1603). The <lb/>foregoing emphasises the main reason for <lb/>accounting book studies, specifically the <lb/>interpretation <lb/>and <lb/>awareness <lb/>of the <lb/>commercial world of late medieval times to <lb/>build, locate and observe, the line of accounting <lb/>development, and the capitalist world. <lb/>The basic principles and fundamental practices <lb/>in accounting were established between the <lb/>12th and 15th centuries, a period during which <lb/>innovative techniques, such as double-entry <lb/>accounting, emerged, paving the way for the <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <page>12 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping ... <lb/></note>

        <body>improvement and dissemination of modern <lb/>accounting methods. From the 15th to the 21st <lb/>century, significant technological advances and <lb/>changes in accounting methods occurred, the <lb/>foundations of which were established in the <lb/>earlier period. Therefore, it is necessary to <lb/>study accounting practices in pre-modern <lb/>Mediterranean Europe from the current <lb/>understanding and perception of management <lb/>and accounting to understand Torralba&apos;s <lb/>accounting practices. While not our primary <lb/>objective, understanding how our merchant <lb/>records their operations will provide significant <lb/>insights into interpreting the management of <lb/>the company. <lb/>We have evidence of the use of simple forms of <lb/>accounting, which met the financial control <lb/>needs of Mediterranean European merchants, <lb/>as early as the 12th century. Initially, accounts <lb/>were only used to record credits and debts, as <lb/>well as receipts and payments, but it soon <lb/>became clear that this mechanism could be <lb/>useful for many other business objectives. <lb/>These early examples showed that there were <lb/>two different types of variations affecting the <lb/>object of accounting. As a result, the typical <lb/>form of an account was already established. <lb/>This development was a significant step <lb/>forward in the evolution of accounting and <lb/>paved the way for future advances. In parallel, <lb/>companies underwent rapid organisational <lb/>evolution. The most influential innovation was <lb/>the <lb/>establishment <lb/>of <lb/>limited <lb/>liability-commenda-alongside <lb/>unlimited <lb/>liability-company-(Malanima <lb/>2009). <lb/>However, it was not until the 13th century that <lb/>the double-entry accounting system was <lb/>introduced in some Tuscan companies -each <lb/>operation being recorded in opposite sections, <lb/>debit and credit -ensuring complete control <lb/>over the company&apos;s business (Steensgaard <lb/>1982). For some researchers, this system was a <lb/>crucial factor in the success of capitalist <lb/>rationality. It spread across Europe from <lb/>northern Italy, often through Italian merchants <lb/>and their interactions with local traders. <lb/>With the growth of trade, the role of accounting <lb/>expanded, and knowledge of accounting <lb/>methods became increasingly important. Basic <lb/>double-entry accounting was typically learned <lb/>on the job, although the emergence of the <lb/>corporate sector created a demand for trained <lb/>auditors and investigators, leading to the <lb/>formation of the modern profession of <lb/>chartered accountant in 19th century Scotland. <lb/>Today, the accounting profession enjoys great <lb/>prestige and continues to evolve, with <lb/>accountants playing a vital role in ensuring the <lb/>financial success and stability of businesses <lb/>worldwide. Italian merchants and their <lb/>interactions with local traders. <lb/>Prior to the mid-1800s, accounting practices <lb/>did not distinguish between business and <lb/>personal expenses. Attempting to separate the <lb/>two was usually futile, and today it&apos;s <lb/>unnecessary as accounting standards have <lb/>evolved over time due to changing economic, <lb/>social and technological factors. During the late <lb/>medieval period, some merchants, mostly from <lb/>the Mediterranean region, had more structured <lb/>entries, even though it was a single-entry <lb/>bookkeeping <lb/>style. <lb/>However, <lb/>business <lb/>transactions and personal expenses were still <lb/>recorded together, making the analysis of <lb/>accounting books from this time more exigent <lb/>and more complex for researchers. <lb/>The origins of modern accounting practices can <lb/>be traced back to Italy, where Italian merchants <lb/>were pioneers in developing effective ways to <lb/>manage their accounts to meet the demands of <lb/>their trade. The first banks, such as the Bank of <lb/>Venice (1157) and the Bank di San Giorgio in <lb/>Genoa (1407), were also crucial factors in the <lb/>development of accounting practices. These <lb/>banks continued to operate successfully until <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Marfa Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping ... <lb/></note>

        <page>13 <lb/></page>

        <body>the late 18th century. Additionally, several <lb/>merchant bankers, such as the Medici in the <lb/>14th century, established branches throughout <lb/>Europe, leading to the rapid growth of banks <lb/>and a significant boost to bookkeeping. The <lb/>importance of Italian accounting advancements <lb/>lies not only in the invention and use of double-<lb/>entry, but also in two other equally important <lb/>aspects: firstly, the existence of separate <lb/>accounting books for different businesses, and <lb/>secondly, the hierarchy among books. Different <lb/>detailed books, such as giornale (journal), <lb/>ricordanza, entrata e uscita (cash book), <lb/>mercanzia (merchandise book), and other <lb/>specialist books like a ledger, were maintained <lb/>separately for different businesses. This helped <lb/>in the proper management and tracking of <lb/>accounts. (Goldthwaite 2011, 2015). <lb/>The Italian case provides evidence for the <lb/>genuine origin of double-entry accounting. In <lb/>the earliest known example of Florentine <lb/>merchants&apos; accounting books from the 12th <lb/>century, we can see cross-entries. This is a <lb/>method where credit entries are recorded on <lb/>one side and corresponding debt entries are <lb/>recorded on the other side of the page. The <lb/>culture of separately listing the entries was an <lb/>Italian divisible feature, e.g. the accounts book <lb/>of Medici could be clearly distinguished <lb/>between three types: the Stock Book, the Cash <lb/>Book, and the Bill Book. Irrespectively that <lb/>Medici maintained the classical form of <lb/>narrative -income and spendings were written <lb/>down one below the other and oppositely -in <lb/>any case, gives a unique and first tendency into <lb/>forthcoming double entry style. Another vivid <lb/>illustration could be preserved accounting book <lb/>(1305-1308) of the Gallerani in London. As <lb/>argued by C. W. Nobes (1982), this book meets <lb/>a substantial part of the requirements of the <lb/>double entry stated by De Roover (1956), <lb/>Martinelli (1977), and Lee (1973). Thus, the <lb/>book could serve as one of the earliest <lb/>examples of the double entry accounting. <lb/>For additional reading regarding the Florentine <lb/>bankers/merchants consult some sources: <lb/>Peruzzi (Hunt 1990,1994, Vannucci 1993, <lb/>Sapori 1926); Bardi (Hunt and Murray 1999, <lb/>Hunt 1990, Sapori 1926, Renouard 1938); <lb/>Peruzzi (De Roover 1956, Goldthwaite 2011, <lb/>Renouard 1938); Datini (Melis 1950, 1962, <lb/>1991, Michienzi 2013, Jouanique 1996, Orlandi <lb/>2018, Nigro 2010); Salviati (Carlomagno 2009, <lb/>Houssaye Michienzi 2016, Matringe 2016, <lb/>Scherman 2020); Frescobaldi (Sapori 1944, <lb/>Tognetti 2014); Gallerani (Melis 1950, <lb/>Bigwood 1962, Nobes 1982); Medici (De <lb/>Roover 1946, 1963, 194 7, Ghosh 2006, <lb/>Goldthwaite 1985). <lb/>The accounting books used by the Genoese <lb/>merchants and bankers have many similarities <lb/>to those used by the Florentines. However, <lb/>there was a significant improvement in <lb/>bookkeeping among the Genoese, which <lb/>emerged in the late 14th century. This <lb/>improvement involved placing the &quot;income&quot; <lb/>section on the left and the &quot;spending&quot; section <lb/>on the right. As a result, the Genoese merchants <lb/>and bankers were the first to provide clear <lb/>evidence of double-entry accounting in the <lb/>modern sense. However, it is unclear whether <lb/>Genoese <lb/>bankers <lb/>used <lb/>double <lb/>entry <lb/>bookkeeping in the past, but we do know that <lb/>the ledgers of the massari and magistri racionali <lb/>in 1340 were definitely kept in double entry <lb/>bookkeeping. We have no record of any <lb/>changes in accounting methods required by <lb/>statutory laws, so we can assume that the <lb/>ledgers have been kept according to the same <lb/>rules since 1327. Therefore, we can infer that <lb/>Genoese bankers also kept their ledgers in <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">2 Archivio di Stato di Genova, Communis Janue, Massaria <lb/>no. 1 (1340) and no. 2 (1340-1351). Archivio di Stato di <lb/>Genova, Communis Janue, lntroitus et Exitus <lb/>Cartullarium Magistrorum Rationalium, Registro no. 44 <lb/>(1340). circles. <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <page>14 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping ... <lb/></note>

        <body>double entry bookkeeping 2 in 1327. However, <lb/>we cannot prove this, as no ledger from that <lb/>time has survived. The earliest ledger of <lb/>Genoese bankers in the State Archives of Genoa <lb/>is dated 1386, which is more of a manual or <lb/>cashbook than a ledger. <lb/>There are very few surviving account books and <lb/>records from the thirteenth and fourteenth <lb/>centuries in Venice, that does not allow a <lb/>coherent view on the evolution of Venetian <lb/>accounting practice (Besta 1909, Melis 1950, <lb/>Martinelli 1977), and the remaining ones from <lb/>the fifteenth century are relatively scarce <lb/>compared to other Italian cities. Nonetheless, <lb/>these sources provide enough evidence to <lb/>indicate that double-entry bookkeeping was <lb/>widely adopted and perfected among Venetian <lb/>merchants. In the case of Venice, their economy <lb/>was specialised in long-distance maritime <lb/>trade. Therefore, information provided by the <lb/>ledgers of these merchants is crucial in studying <lb/>the macroeconomy of the Late Middle Ages. <lb/>The Soranzo Fraterna, a family partnership <lb/>consisting of brothers Donado, Giacomo, Piero, <lb/>and Lorenzo Soranzo, owned the earliest <lb/>surviving set of Venetian account books. Their <lb/>trading company was active during the first half <lb/>of the 15th century and specialised in importing <lb/>raw cotton from Syria (Lane 1944, Chatfield <lb/>1996). The two accounting registers of the <lb/>Soranzo enterprise are known as the Libra <lb/>Vecchio Real and the Libra Real Novo 3 in <lb/>Venetian. The &apos;old book,&apos; or Libra Vecchio Real, <lb/>covers the period from 1410 to 1416 and <lb/>contains 51 sheets, while Libra Real Novo <lb/>covers the period from 1406 to 1434. Libra <lb/>Real Novo is a compilation of distinct financial <lb/>documents. Based on Sieveking (1901) and <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">3 As suggested by Tommaso Zarbi (1952) and Ryabova <lb/>(2018), we are fully aware that this book was compiled <lb/>from various accounting records to be presented during <lb/>the trial held before the Venetian judicial body (giudici de <lb/>petizion). <lb/></note>

        <body>Ryabova (2018), it is known that the Libra <lb/>Vecchio Real does not have both profit and loss <lb/>accounts and capital accounts; hence, the <lb/>accounting system could be described as <lb/>incomplete. While Libra Real Novo has the full <lb/>set of accounts required to be a double-entry <lb/>ledger: there were debit and credit entries, <lb/>written opposite each other, and a profit and <lb/>loss account and a capital account, indicating <lb/>the advance in the bookkeeping in Venice. <lb/>Concerning bookkeeping of Joan de Torralba, <lb/>we are fortunate to have 13 books in excellent <lb/>condition. Analysing the accounting techniques <lb/>used by our merchant enables us to establish <lb/>guidelines of accounting practices in the <lb/>territories of the Crown of Aragon, by <lb/>comparing with data we already have <lb/>concerning other companies. We would like to <lb/>provide a general overview of bookkeeping <lb/>techniques, without going into too much <lb/>technical detail. Our aim is to focus on <lb/>management research rather than accounting. <lb/>However, it is important to note that accounting <lb/>is a vital source of information for <lb/>understanding a company&apos;s management. As an <lb/>example, we will look at the Account Book <lb/>(Journal) of the Company of Joan de Torralba <lb/>with Joan de Manariello, from Saragossa (ANCl-<lb/>960-T-157). <lb/>o The text opens with a traditional prayer to <lb/>holy figures, including Jesus and Mary, <lb/>seeking their blessings for the endeavours <lb/>documented in the account book. Evidence of <lb/>the merchants&apos; need to seek divine <lb/>protection for the proper development of <lb/>their businesses is also evidenced in the <lb/>donations made to the churches they <lb/>revered. <lb/>o The merchant, Johan de Torralba, is <lb/>introducing himself and his business partner, <lb/>Johan de Manariello de Caragoca (Zaragoza). <lb/>He mentions that they have been partners <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Marfa Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping... <lb/></note>

        <page>15 <lb/></page>

        <body>since the beginning of the year 1436 until the <lb/>end of the year 1437, hence the book <lb/>dedicated to this specific period of their <lb/>partnership. <lb/>o The text includes detailed financial <lb/>transactions conducted by partners: <lb/>• Payments made to various individuals, <lb/>such as Domingo del Vilar, Bernat <lb/>d&apos;Algars, and Lluis Vives, either <lb/>directly or through intermediaries. <lb/>• Purchase of items, including grain from <lb/>Aragon, <lb/>currency <lb/>exchange <lb/>transactions, insurance payments, and <lb/>the acquisition of goods like pine nuts. <lb/>• Sending goods, such as clothing for <lb/>church use, to specific recipients, like <lb/>Pero Cabanyas&apos; wife from Azuara <lb/>[province of Zaragoza]. <lb/>• Receipt of goods, like a silk cord, sent <lb/>for the merchant&apos;s wife, Ursula, as <lb/>mentioned in the &quot;Manual honze&quot; in a <lb/>specific letter. <lb/>o The text contains periodic summaries of <lb/>transactions, showing the total amounts <lb/>involved in various dealings. These <lb/>summaries give an overview of the <lb/>merchant&apos;s financial activities during a <lb/>specific period. <lb/>It records debts and credits with various <lb/>individuals and cities. It lists people from <lb/>Barcelona to whom money is owed, along with <lb/>the amounts owed to each. Additionally, there <lb/>are accounts with individuals from outside <lb/>Barcelona, such as Saragossa, Pisa, Venice, etc., <lb/>with debts expressed in different currencies <lb/>like pounds, sous, florins, ducats, etc. Each debt <lb/>is detailed with the exact amount owed, as well <lb/>as specific details such as the reason for the <lb/>debt, items bought or sold, and other <lb/>commercial transactions. Every entry seems to <lb/>be meticulously recorded, indicating the <lb/>transaction date, debtor details, exact amount, <lb/>and any relevant additional information. The <lb/>accounting is organised into different <lb/>categories and subcategories, such as debts <lb/>located in Barcelona, debts outside Barcelona, <lb/>and old debts with people from Pisa and Venice, <lb/>suggesting clear and structured account <lb/>organisation. <lb/>Regarding the accounting kept by our <lb/>merchant, Joan de Torralba boosts curious <lb/>questions. <lb/>Commence with a remarkably impressive <lb/>clause that should be said <lb/>despite <lb/>widespread use of the double entry in <lb/>accounting across the Mediterranean, mainly in <lb/>Italy, but even in Catalonia, Valencia and <lb/>Aragon -our merchant was in favour of the <lb/>use of &quot;classical accounting&quot;,4 which refers to <lb/>single-entry 5 bookkeeping. Nevertheless, it <lb/>should be stressed that the system, even though <lb/>it was not the double entry of its common form, <lb/>considering assets and liabilities divided and <lb/>calculated in unison with the essential rule of <lb/>accounting, we should necessarily mention how <lb/>advanced it was and accurate in matters to <lb/>carry it out with a proper and progressive form. <lb/>The enormous administrative task posed before <lb/>the accounting was the collection and <lb/>processing of complete and reliable information <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">4 Classical accounting, also known as traditional <lb/>accounting, refers to the historical and foundational <lb/>principles and practices of accounting that have been in <lb/>use for several centuries. It represents the early stages of <lb/>accounting development and lays the groundwork for <lb/>modern accounting systems. Classical accounting <lb/>methods were established before the advent of modern <lb/>technologies and complex financial transactions, and they <lb/>were primarily used during the pre-industrial and <lb/>industrial eras. <lb/>5 Late medieval accounting was primarily based on <lb/>single-entry bookkeeping, which involved recording <lb/>transactions in a simple ledger. Transactions were <lb/>recorded as they occurred, often in a chronological order, <lb/>without the use of debits and credits. <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <page>16 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping ... <lb/></note>

        <body>on the activities of an economic entity, since <lb/>said information was used mainly for two pur-<lb/>poses: <lb/>a. Decision-making based on the economic <lb/>analysis of gathered information. <lb/>b. Implementation of financial control. <lb/>If point a is tricky to prove since no information <lb/>has been kept on the analysis of the current <lb/>accounts by the partners to enable us with the <lb/>support that said point took place in the <lb/>operation of the companies with Joan de <lb/>Torralba. However, keeping in mind all the <lb/>transcribed documentation leaves us with a <lb/>place to possess explicit information, meaning <lb/>that point cannot be eliminated, but with the <lb/>current information, it does not explain that <lb/>there is such documentation. Regarding point b, <lb/>it is corroborated by the information available. <lb/>The presence of eleven meticulously written <lb/>accounting books with final balances of the <lb/>pages and established periods, with details of <lb/>the entries and payments applied by Joan de <lb/>Torralba, translates into complete and inclusive <lb/>financial control. <lb/>In this regard, beyond doubt, the conserved <lb/>accounting of Joan de Torralba&apos;s commercial <lb/>activity performs its function to conduct the <lb/>business satisfactorily. Financial control, being <lb/>an integral part of control in the activities of an <lb/>economic entity, was one of the key <lb/>management tools. It is proof of compliance by <lb/>the entity for the interests of the partners when <lb/>it comes to the context of the fifteenth century. <lb/>One of the main conditions for the <lb/>implementation of financial control functions is <lb/>the availability of objective and updated <lb/>financial information. The carriers of said <lb/>information (in a detailed and generalised <lb/>form) are the accounting documents. <lb/>In the case of the activity of Joan de Torralba <lb/>and its accounting books, the four documents <lb/>have been integrated into consolidated ledgers. <lb/>They are not found separately, which implies a <lb/>detailed examination of the books and their <lb/>systematisation, albeit simplistic, in order not <lb/>to lose the original thread, but to use current <lb/>techniques to carry out an exhaustive and <lb/>coherent interpretation. 6 <lb/>Nonetheless, in case of considering the modern <lb/>formulation it is curious, to consider, for <lb/>TABLE 1. THE PRESENCE OF KEY ACCOUNTING DOCUMENTS IN THE CASE OF JOAN DE TORRALBA <lb/>Key documents <lb/>Its presence in commercial activity of <lb/>Joan de Torralba <lb/>Accounting source documents <lb/>+ <lb/>Register <lb/>+ <lb/>Financial statement <lb/>+ <lb/>Stock-taking <lb/>+ <lb/>Sources: own elaboration. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">6 &quot;Presentation of Financial Statements&quot; Standard IAS 1, International Accounting Standards Board. Accessed 24 June <lb/>2007. <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Marfa Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping... <lb/></note>

        <page>17 <lb/></page>

        <body>example, points such as statement of financial <lb/>position, profit and loss report, statement of <lb/>equity, cash flow statement and comprehensive <lb/>income statement, they are impossible to be <lb/>observed either in its modern sense or the way <lb/>of creating it. First, on the establishment of the <lb/>first company with Joan de Torralba, in 1425, <lb/>the book &quot;Summa de arithmetica, geometria, <lb/>proportioni et proportionalita&quot; by Luca Pacioli, <lb/>which he released in the year 1494, has not yet <lb/>been published. It is known that the work of <lb/>Luca Pacioli is only a record of an explanation <lb/>of the best practices known and used by his <lb/>contemporaries. The aim was to collect a <lb/>complete standardisation and classification of <lb/>existent techniques (Smith 2018). Another <lb/>example is Benedetto Cotrugli&apos;s book &quot;Della <lb/>mercatura e del mercante perfetto&quot;, published <lb/>only in the year 1573, but which had been <lb/>written in 1458 (36 years before Pacioli&apos;s book) <lb/>specifies that the trade conducted by our <lb/>companies with the participation of Joan de <lb/>Torralba coincides in time with what we call the <lb/>official formalisation and establishment of <lb/>double-entry accounting before it was <lb/>empirically used by Italian merchants during <lb/>the 13th-14th century. The earliest extant <lb/>accounting records following the modern <lb/>double-entry system in Europe come from <lb/>Amatino Manucci, a Florentine merchant in the <lb/>late 13th century (Lee 1977). <lb/>Everything, indicated above, provides the first <lb/>of the justifications for the non-use of double <lb/>entry by our merchants, due to the <lb/>comparatively slow process of extension of the <lb/>updated practice. Likewise, it is worth <lb/>emphasising that the first example of said <lb/>double entry is rudimentary and far from <lb/>meeting the <lb/>practically founded <lb/>and <lb/>consolidated rules (de Roover 1937). However, <lb/>after analysing the accounting books of Joan de <lb/>Torralba, and examining his business career, <lb/>another reason emerges that has its rational <lb/>place -opting for single-entry bookkeeping was <lb/>not caused by Joan de Torralba&apos;s ignorance but <lb/>by considering it unnecessary. It is pointless for <lb/>a medium-sized business, and besides the <lb/>absence of an external audit that would force it <lb/>to execute and comply with rigorous regula-<lb/>tions. 7 <lb/>It makes sense to mention the advantages of <lb/>using the Single-Entry System in our bespoke <lb/>case. Firstly, it was more cost-effective. <lb/>Furthermore, in the single-entry system, we <lb/>register only one entry for each transaction, <lb/>therefore this was time savings for the <lb/>business. A more sophisticated system was not <lb/>necessary. It also gave the manager the <lb/>required information about sales and profits, so <lb/>they could make decisions accordingly. And <lb/>eventually, perhaps the most meaningful thing <lb/>was that any written document was used as a <lb/>confirmation or proof. The single-entry account <lb/>book records all transactions; hence it can be <lb/>used as supporting documents. <lb/>Our operational hypotheses begin with this <lb/>initial panorama. The data provided by the <lb/>documentation on which our investigation is <lb/>based -infers that the company founded by <lb/>Torralba was a trading company capable of <lb/>taking advantage of a favourable context and <lb/>international relationship networks that would <lb/>consolidate in the second half of the fifteenth <lb/>century. These far-reaching shifts in the forms <lb/>of economic relationships entail a substantial <lb/>evolution in the articulation of the European <lb/>continent, which witnesses its international <lb/>relations tighten from a novel standpoint, <lb/>which goes beyond political relations, which <lb/>were sometimes tense or conflictive. Indeed, <lb/>the late medieval mercantile world was a <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">7 According to John L. Carey (1969, 17-18), audits were <lb/>required by law in England for the first time only in the <lb/>year 1845. <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <body>Company&apos;s analysis <lb/></body>

        <page>18 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping ... <lb/></note>

        <body>pioneer in transforming European business <lb/>matters in favour of multilingualism, people&apos;s <lb/>mobility, wealth increase, and knowledge <lb/>spread. <lb/>The preservation of the XII accounting books of <lb/>Joan de Torralba makes it achievable to study <lb/>the internal management of his company. In <lb/>consideration of being aware of the <lb/>socioeconomic reality of the time, it is curious <lb/>to deal with the question of the internal <lb/>management of a medieval company, of <lb/>Catalan-Aragonese origin. The process of <lb/>sustaining a business is closely linked to the <lb/>management and its type implemented by the <lb/>equity partners. However, here it is worth <lb/>saying separately the position of the top <lb/>manager of one of the founding partners -Joan <lb/>de Torralba. His private letters, accounting <lb/>books, and notarial documents conserved to <lb/>this day helped us to rebuild his business, <lb/>accentuating the part of decision-making and <lb/>governance. <lb/>Joan de Torralba, Aragonese, settled in <lb/>Barcelona in the early years of the fifteenth <lb/>century, being granted citizenship shortly after. <lb/>The first news regarding the company places us <lb/>in 1425. That year Joan de Torralba and <lb/>Fortuny de Manariello, both citizens of <lb/>Barcelona, although of Aragonese origin, and <lb/>Juan Feixas (Fexas or Flexas), from Zaragoza, <lb/>founded the first company whose duration is <lb/>stipulated in two years, from December 1, 1425, <lb/>to December 1, 1427, and with a constitutive <lb/>capital of 10,000 Barcelona pounds, contributed <lb/>40% by Feixas (4,000 pounds), and 30% by <lb/>each of the Catalan partners (3,000 lbs. each). <lb/>In 1428 the society was renewed. On this <lb/>occasion, the share capital is contributed in <lb/>equal parts by the three partners with a total of <lb/>12,000 pounds (at a rate of 4,000 pounds each). <lb/>After a new biennium, the company was <lb/>renewed in September 1430, with a change in <lb/>terms of capital and partners. The changes in <lb/>partners pointed towards a simplification of the <lb/>organisation chart, as the governing body was <lb/>reduced to only two members. Feixas left the <lb/>company, and the share capital became 10,000 <lb/>pounds of Barcelona currency contributed in <lb/>equal parts by two sole partners, Joan de <lb/>Torralba and Juan de Manariello. The rest <lb/>remains unchanged in terms of the areas of <lb/>commercial intervention -Aragon and Italy-<lb/>and the products object of trade -wheat and <lb/>wool-. The administration, therefore, ventured <lb/>into a short period, renewable according to <lb/>perspectives, a characteristic comparable to <lb/>most companies analysed in Barcelona, <lb/>Valencia, and Mallorca. <lb/>New changes took place in 1438. That year the <lb/>company was renewed for two years (from <lb/>January 1, 1438, to December 31, 1440) 8 new <lb/>partners were incorporated: Domingo Sanz, a <lb/>resident of Zaragoza, and Bernat d&apos;Algars 9 from <lb/>Barcelona. With inferior capital, only 6,000 <lb/>florins (in the previous companies the capital <lb/>was counted in pounds), were invested at the <lb/>rate of 2,000 fl. by Torralba and Manariello <lb/>each, and 1,000 fl. by Sanz and D&apos;Algars. Its <lb/>areas of intervention were specified in Aragon <lb/>and Catalonia without expressly mentioning the <lb/>Italian markets but leaving available the option <lb/>of acting in other territories. Torralba and <lb/>Manariello withdrew from direct management <lb/>and delegated direction to minority partners. <lb/>An aforementioned business structure would <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">8 The chapters in the Historical Archive of Notarial <lb/>Protocols of Zaragoza (hereinafter AHPNZ), Anton de <lb/>Aldovera 2400, loose paper, 1438. <lb/>9 Chapters signed in Alcafiiz, in the absence of Joan de <lb/>Torralba [AHPNZ, Anton de Aldovera, 2400, f.12.v. <lb/>(Alcafiiz. 12, February 1438)]. <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Marfa Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping... <lb/></note>

        <page>19 <lb/></page>

        <body>last until the end of the 1440s. <lb/>Under the data available, it can be deduced that <lb/>Torralba, Feixas &amp; Manariello, with a founding <lb/>capital of 12,000 pounds, later Torralba &amp; <lb/>Manariello, with an initial investment of 10,000 <lb/>pounds, and then Torralba, Manariello, Algars &amp; <lb/>Sanz with 6,000 florins, may have been <lb/>included among the large operating companies <lb/>in the Crown of Aragon in the first half of the <lb/>XV. Del Treppo assessed these skills employing <lb/>the classification made by F. Melis of Florentine <lb/>companies as a comparative index. On a <lb/>classification based on six groups, the first with <lb/>capitals greater than 75,000 florins from <lb/>Florence, and the last companies with less than <lb/>10,000 florins of founding capital (Melis 1962), <lb/>the Italian historian concluded its position <lb/>between the fifth group and the sixth, <lb/>depending on whether we consider the capital <lb/>or the personnel. <lb/>It was a relatively medium-sized company even <lb/>for that time. Being a profit entity dedicated to <lb/>commerce within the Crown of Aragon and <lb/>internationally, it automatically entails a <lb/>comparatively <lb/>solid <lb/>managing <lb/>system. <lb/>Nevertheless, it is necessary to distinguish the <lb/>fact that it was not a very large company of the <lb/>epoch, such as that of the Medici, Datini or <lb/>Casaldaguila. Nonetheless, it is indispensable to <lb/>consider a company of other dimensions to <lb/>ascertain that management was practically <lb/>versatile with the ability to adapt itself to the <lb/>commercial flow and current geographic <lb/>extension. As in the ancient world, medieval <lb/>cultural norms may have made the general <lb/>adoption of legal personality for business seem <lb/>counterintuitive. Theological concerns largely <lb/>dominated economic thought, and we can <lb/>TABLE 2. POSITIVE ASPECTS OF FISCAL POLICY IN THE CROWN OF ARAGON <lb/>A <lb/>clear trade protection after interventions in fiscal policy and social security; <lb/>stimulation of domestic consumption likewise demands (but when it comes <lb/>to distinguishing between private demand and public demand before the <lb/>B <lb/>eighteenth century, it is very complicated or almost impossible) for consumer <lb/>goods; demand for services; demand for capital were treated by the <lb/>government; <lb/>C <lb/>governmental management to reduce transport costs; <lb/>development of urban infrastructure, similarly, converting Zaragoza as a <lb/>D <lb/>priority and Barcelona into opportune and convenient hubs to carry out <lb/>commercial activity; <lb/>well-established connection between Zaragoza and other cities of supply and <lb/>E <lb/>stocking with raw material (the main source of foreign trade) and Barcelona, <lb/>on the other hand, as a valuable port and logistics city when it comes to <lb/>foreign trade with Italy and Venice essentially; <lb/>F <lb/>highly favourable municipal legal framework of the Aragonese capital in <lb/>conjunction with the county capital; <lb/>G <lb/>measures of protectionism (viz. social and fiscal protectionism). <lb/>Sources: own elaboration. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <page>20 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping ... <lb/></note>

        <body>affirm that our company has not been omitted, <lb/>yet with some certainty, it can be admitted that <lb/>the Catalan business circles and its <lb/>administration already in the fifteenth century <lb/>began to perform in a more &quot;modern&quot; way as <lb/>the companies of the XVI-XVII century. <lb/>It is worth underlining that the environment <lb/>created by the Catalan-Aragonese government <lb/>was nothing less than an encouraging reality for <lb/>commercial expansion (Ferrer 2012). It is due <lb/>to a fairly balanced policy and what we <lb/>nowadays call the support system. Certainly, it <lb/>should be mentioned that it is not the same as <lb/>today, there was no public investment fund, for <lb/>instance, or a government credit model, <lb/>however, the Crown of Aragon, ontologically, <lb/>did not experience excessive regulations within <lb/>a fiscal system that apply the risk of impeding <lb/>economic and commercial innovation. Even if <lb/>the Crown of Aragon had severely restricted <lb/>commercial law, merchants would devise <lb/>alternative ways to achieve the same end away <lb/>from public surveillance. A more multifarious <lb/>environment of business forms, including those <lb/>that explicitly prioritise social ends. It deserves <lb/>to highlight a basic definition that took place in <lb/>the medieval world. Capital is one of the <lb/>indispensable factors when we talk about any <lb/>economy. Likewise, it is reasonable to state that <lb/>what it consumes is no longer available for <lb/>investment by merchants, thus the absence of a <lb/>surplus troubled the circulation of capital and, <lb/>therefore, caused an imbalance in constant <lb/>consumption that all pre-industrial European <lb/>regions experienced. However, it is possible to <lb/>facilitate some points of the successful <lb/>Aragonese fiscal policy. <lb/>Some key facts about Zaragoza. The city <lb/>experienced and played a fundamental role at <lb/>the time of the economic expansion, despite not <lb/>having such a strategic geographical location as <lb/>Barcelona. Zaragoza does not have an open and <lb/>direct access to the Mediterranean Sea, which <lb/>was a significant factor during that time, but <lb/>Zaragoza was a redistributive center for raw <lb/>materials. While Barcelona, we may call a <lb/>commercial centre. It is the wide representation <lb/>of the elite of the city, in many cases being <lb/>merchants or bankers, in municipal leadership, <lb/>thereby lighting the way for commerce and <lb/>entrepreneurship (Kadens 2015). Everything <lb/>mentioned above expresses the advantageous <lb/>external governance for the growth of our <lb/>company. They continued to be our main <lb/>partners of Aragonese origin, creating and <lb/>forming their entities before notaries in <lb/>Zaragoza-it allows us to extrapolate the <lb/>Aragonese socio-economic reality to the <lb/>operation of our company and its genesis. On <lb/>the one hand, this company is a tangible <lb/>demonstration of the international projection of <lb/>Aragon&apos;s kingdom and the role Zaragoza played <lb/>in the Mediterranean trade networks. Evidence <lb/>of how the response to the difficulties of the <lb/>14th century meant a reorientation of economic <lb/>activities and intensification of relations <lb/>between operators in Catalonia and Aragon, <lb/>intending to connect the production of the <lb/>inland territories with the coastal commercial <lb/>centres, particularly Barcelona, and achieve a <lb/>notable international expansion, already <lb/>apparent in the first decades of the XV (Sesma <lb/>1982,1985,2005, Viu 2019). <lb/>Among many successful qualities of Joan de <lb/>Torralba that have helped him to become a <lb/>distinguished trader during the first years, 10 <lb/>we would like to start with the principle of <lb/>&apos;staying out of politics&apos;, 11 and the first years of <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">10 After the year 1434, he began to invest in government <lb/>bonds, however, he did not experience the bad luck of <lb/>other banks or merchants of his time going bankrupt <lb/>after dealing with dubious business relationships with <lb/>monarchs. <lb/>11 Chapters signed in Alcafiiz, in the absence of Joan de <lb/>Torralba [AHPNZ, Anton de Aldovera, 2400, f.12.v. <lb/>(Alcafiiz. 12, February 1438)]. <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Marfa Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping... <lb/></note>

        <page>21 <lb/></page>

        <body>our company&apos;s operation the rule was fulfilled, <lb/>which is seen by the stay out of politics and the <lb/>engagement on the business both within the <lb/>country and abroad. Traders should not get <lb/>involved in politics or the courts, &quot;because they <lb/>are dangerous areas&quot;, on the contrary, they <lb/>must possess a series of personal qualities if <lb/>they want to be successful in their businesses. <lb/>The unknown Catalan author of the Llibre de <lb/>conexenses de spf cies, e de drogues e de <lb/>avissaments de pessos, canes e masures de <lb/>diverses terres, written in 1385 (Gual 1981), 12 <lb/>explains what these qualities are. A merchant <lb/>should, in addition to being discreet and wise, <lb/>gather a series of attributes, not only <lb/>commercial but also ethical and moral: <lb/>providence, faith, truthfulness, love, loyalty, <lb/>diligence, temperance, sobriety, religiosity and <lb/>good health, to being able to travel the world <lb/>and attend to their business (Cuadrada 1994, <lb/>110). Aptitudes analogous, on the other hand, <lb/>to those expressed in the well-known trade <lb/>manuals and, are repeated as a decalogue of <lb/>essential virtues to exercise the &quot;Arte de la <lb/>mercaderfa&quot; (Cuadrada 2019). And among them <lb/>is the importance of charity: &quot;the merchant <lb/>must be generous in extending his hand to the <lb/>poor and in giving alms from his property in <lb/>proportion to its extension.&quot; (Cotrugli 1458). <lb/>The anguish for the afterlife, the uncertainty or, <lb/>sometimes, the full security of not meeting the <lb/>requirements to achieve eternal salvation , <lb/>pushed these merchants to make large <lb/>donations, to the churches that were the object <lb/>of their devotion, or to establishing <lb/>testamentary legacies, do not differ so much <lb/>from the creation of current foundations by <lb/>companies and banks or aid to NGOs. Our <lb/>company allocated around 10 pounds a year as <lb/>a donation to the churches of Santa Maria de <lb/>12 Published by Miguel Gual Camarena (1981). <lb/>Montserrat, in Barcelona, and Santa Maria de <lb/>Portillo, in Zaragoza, as stated in the record that <lb/>we reproduce, some amounts, on the other <lb/>hand, scarce if we stick to the company&apos;s <lb/>investments. <lb/>Libro secreto (1430-1432) / Secret book <lb/>(1430-1432) [f.142v] <lb/>Avem data madona Santa Marie de Monserat <lb/>We have donated to Lady Saint Mary <lb/>of Montserrat ............................................................................. V 11. <lb/>Avem data madona Santa Maria de/ Portello, los <lb/>quails dony contants a don Johan de Manariello <lb/>de present <lb/>We have given to the Lady Saint Mary of Portello, <lb/>which I give in payment to Sir Johan <lb/>de Manarie/lo as a present ........................ 1111 II. VI s. VIII <lb/>Applying modern management principles to a <lb/>late medieval company can be challenging due <lb/>to the vast differences in the historical context , <lb/>social structures, technology, and economic <lb/>systems between those times and the present <lb/>day. However, some aspects of modern <lb/>management can potentially be adapted or <lb/>integrated into a late medieval company to <lb/>improve efficiency and effectiveness. It&apos;s <lb/>important to recognise that attempting to <lb/>impose a fully modern management system on <lb/>a late medieval company may not be practical <lb/>or culturally appropriate. Instead, the goal <lb/>should be to identify principles that align with <lb/>the historical context and can be adapted to <lb/>improve the company&apos;s overall performance <lb/>while respecting the limitations of the time. <lb/>Moreover, the specific company&apos;s location, size, <lb/>and nature of business will heavily influence <lb/>the feasibility of implementing certain <lb/>management practices. Using modern concepts <lb/>to study the late medieval period allows us to <lb/>approach the subject with a critical and <lb/>analytical mindset, enabling to gain deeper <lb/>insights into historical events, human <lb/>behaviour, and the dynamics of medieval <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <page>22 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping ... <lb/></note>

        <body>societies. However, it is essential to strike a <lb/>balance between applying relevant modern <lb/>concepts and understanding the unique <lb/>characteristics of the historical era being stud-<lb/>ied. <lb/>Foremost, there is a certain necessity to define <lb/>the methods that can be used when analysing <lb/>management, especially when the discourse is <lb/>about medieval management and the times <lb/>before the formalisation of management <lb/>sciences. As references, works such as Strang <lb/>and Wittorck (2019); Mitev et al. (2018); <lb/>Scandura &amp; Williams (2000); Buchanan and <lb/>Badham (1999); Burrell and Morgan (1979); <lb/>Butler (1986); Eccles and Nohria (1992); <lb/>Alvesson and Willmott (2012); Huber (2019) -<lb/>were used. The modern approach to <lb/>management formulated by H. Fayol (1916), <lb/>founder of the ( classical) administrative school <lb/>of management, is presented below. The <lb/>objective is to apply his ideas and principles to <lb/>our company to create a modern-like vision. <lb/>The table represents the detection or non-<lb/>existence of the xiv principles formulated by H. <lb/>Fayol. 13 The adoption of such a method allows <lb/>us to attempt to visualise a modern estimation <lb/>regarding the management system of this <lb/>Catalan-Aragonese entity to pinpoint its <lb/>coherence. The relevance of such a study is a <lb/>medium-sized company and [simultaneously] a <lb/>company not located in the Italian or English <lb/>territory, where it is possible to go to the <lb/>extensive studies available. The analysis per se <lb/>is achievable after studying the vast collection <lb/>of preserved accounting books, private letters <lb/>13 Fayol&apos;s principles of management were significant in <lb/>shaping modern management practices and continue to <lb/>be influential in organisational management theory. <lb/>However, it&apos;s essential to note that the concepts may <lb/>have their limitations and might need to be adapted to <lb/>suit the specific context and complexities of modern <lb/>organisations, same as they need some &quot;corrections&quot; <lb/>when applied to a medieval entity. <lb/>and articles of incorporation of the company. <lb/>The presumed comprehensive image provides a <lb/>high-quality overview of the late-medieval <lb/>management framework and what the <lb/>corporate structure was like across the Crown <lb/>of Aragon. Even though the relationships <lb/>between partners and employees considering <lb/>the circumstances were built above all on <lb/>fiducia and an interpersonal network, it is <lb/>possible to contemplate a vestige of a certain <lb/>corporate culture. Organisational culture <lb/>influences how people interact, the context <lb/>within which knowledge is formed, and <lb/>ultimately how they share ( or don&apos;t) <lb/>knowledge. Given what has been stated, it is <lb/>worth mentioning the existence of this culture <lb/>in the commercial sphere of Joan de Torralba. <lb/>Certainly, the structure lacks the modern <lb/>complexity introduced by E. H. Schein (1990) <lb/>and E. Jaques (1951, 1956, 1961), who <lb/>proposed a more interdisciplinary approach in <lb/>administrative culture. <lb/>Division of labour had a clear path framed by <lb/>understanding the phenomenon in the fifteenth <lb/>century&apos;s reality. Since our company was small-<lb/>medium in size, a broad hierarchy cannot be <lb/>observed ( due to a lack of personnel), however, <lb/>the division is seen above all: geographical <lb/>specialisation and the distinction of capabilities. <lb/>Since the existence of the learning process in <lb/>carrying out continuous work, in addition to <lb/>devoting all time to a single approach, an <lb/>economic agent would be more likely to master <lb/>the necessary skills or develop more advanced <lb/>technological methods than if he divided his <lb/>time between different types of work increasing <lb/>the performance of the business as a whole. <lb/>Anyway, the late medieval division of labour <lb/>was distinct from modern industrial economies, <lb/>and it shaped the economic and social dynamics <lb/>of the time, yet it could not be fully extrapolated <lb/>by the modern reality. The division of labour <lb/>almost automatically entails clear authority <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Marfa Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping... <lb/></note>

        <page>23 <lb/></page>

        <body>TABLE 3. THE IDENTIFICATION OF THE CONTROL PRINCIPLES EXPRESSED BY H. FAYOL IN THE <lb/>MANAGEMENT SYSTEM OF TORRALBA COMPANY (15TH CENTURY) <lb/>PRINCIPLES OF CONTROL <lb/>Division of labour <lb/>Authority <lb/>Discipline <lb/>Unity of command <lb/>unity of direction {see the note) <lb/>Collective interest over individual interest <lb/>Remuneration <lb/>Centralisation <lb/>Scalar chain <lb/>Order <lb/>Equity <lb/>Stability of tenure of personnel <lb/>Initiative {see the note) <lb/>£spirit de corps <lb/>Sources: own elaboration. <lb/>and responsibility for each member. That builds <lb/>a stronger way of running a business. The <lb/>formulations that support it are the articles of <lb/>incorporation of the companies, where the <lb/>responsibilities and roles of each signatory are <lb/>observed. The discipline that obedience implies <lb/>stands out with the fact of the jove system used <lb/>by the capitalist partners. 14 Each young man in <lb/>its modern interpretation was an employee <lb/>who acted as a first-line manager. <lb/>Item mes, an concordat que la demunt dita <lb/>conpanya tinga quatro jovens, es a saber: hu en <lb/>Tortosa, lo qua[ per salario e misio aga cent <lb/>jlorines; y el altro que estiga ab lo senyor en <lb/>Johan Flexas y qua[ le aga a fer la misio de <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">14 The word &quot;jove&quot; directly translated into English from <lb/>Catalan as &quot;young men&quot;, however in our context it refers <lb/>to apprentice .. <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <body>ITS PRESENCE IN OUR CASE <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>? <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>boca en casa sua y com yra de fora la ciutat <lb/>per la companya, que la dita companya Ii aya a <lb/>dar doze dineros per dia pera misio y mes Ii <lb/>aga a dar la dita companya son salari que Ii <lb/>sera promes; y el altro joven que stigaab Johan <lb/>de Manariello en la manera de! d&apos;en Johan <lb/>Flexas; y el altro jove que stiga ab Johan de <lb/>Torralba en Barcelona y quel la fa~a la misio e <lb/>la companya Ii pach son salarii. <lb/>Also, it has been agreed that the <lb/>aforementioned company will have four <lb/>&apos;young men&apos;, namely: one in Tortosa, who will <lb/>receive a salary and a mission payment of one <lb/>hundred florins; and another who will be <lb/>with Sir Joan Flexas and who will carry out <lb/>the mission of speaking on his behalf at his <lb/>house and when he goes outside the city for <lb/>the company, the company will give him <lb/>twelve diners per day for the mission, and the <lb/></body>

        <page>24 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping ... <lb/></note>

        <body>company will also give him his promised <lb/>salary; and another young man who will be <lb/>with Joan de Manariello in the same way as <lb/>with Joan Flexas; and the other young man <lb/>who will be with Joan de Torralba in <lb/>Barcelona and who will carry out the mission, <lb/>and the company will pay him his salary. <lb/>Unity of command in the case of our company <lb/>exists in its explicit form, that is, each equity <lb/>partner has his team (it used to be just one <lb/>person but not always) of subordinates, <lb/>nonetheless submission to other partners has <lb/>still never been practised but neither can it be <lb/>said that it did not exist. 15 For instance, during <lb/>the first company 1425-1428 there is a clause, <lb/>which clearly expresses the subordination of <lb/>the joves, their salary and the mission carried <lb/>out (The Articles of Incorporation 1425-1428, <lb/>Viu 2019). In the late medieval period, the <lb/>concept of unity of command as formulated by <lb/>Henri Fayol in modern management theory did <lb/>not exist in the same structured form. The late <lb/>medieval period had a very different social and <lb/>organisational structure compared to the <lb/>industrialised and modernised societies where <lb/>Fayol&apos;s principles were developed. During the <lb/>late medieval period, the division of labour and <lb/>management were largely shaped by feudalism, <lb/>a hierarchical system where power and <lb/>authority were concentrated in the hands of <lb/>monarchs, nobles, and feudal lords. The concept <lb/>of a formal management hierarchy with a chain <lb/>of command, as we understand it today, did not <lb/>exist during this time. In medieval societies, <lb/>leadership and decision-making were often <lb/>determined by birthright, social status, and <lb/>tradition. In the late medieval period, <lb/>individuals generally followed the authority of <lb/>their feudal lord or guild master, and there was <lb/>a clear hierarchy of power. However, the idea of <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">15 This principle emphasises the importance of ensuring <lb/>that employees receive orders and directives from only <lb/>one manager or supervisor. <lb/></note>

        <body>a unified and formal chain of command across <lb/>all levels of society, as advocated by Fayol, was <lb/>not a prevalent concept during this historical <lb/>era. <lb/>A direction unit is a point that is sophisticated <lb/>to accept but at the same time exclude. Since <lb/>the management unit and the entity must have <lb/>a clear and defined action plan that is also <lb/>written. Nevertheless, it should be stressed that <lb/>the companies set up by Joan de Torralba <lb/>always had the same objective and the <lb/>responsibility was assumed by the capital <lb/>partners, which does provide the basis for the <lb/>control unit, but given that for now with the <lb/>transcribed documentation it is impossible to <lb/>sustain that the company had the written and <lb/>documented supervision and evaluation of the <lb/>commercial activity. The concept of unity of <lb/>direction is closely related to the idea of <lb/>coordination and harmony within an <lb/>organisation. In the late medieval context, unity <lb/>of direction was more implicit and inherent in <lb/>the hierarchical social structure than it is today. <lb/>The subordination of individual interest to <lb/>the general interest is reflected in any company <lb/>charter, where it is emphatically stated that the <lb/>business strategy is focused on the goals of the <lb/>entity and any activity outside of that is <lb/>restricted. As far as it is said, it seems logical the <lb/>remuneration that must be paid to the <lb/>employees and a fair distribution, which adjusts <lb/>to the part invested, among the capitalist <lb/>partners. All information is always recorded in <lb/>the company&apos;s articles of incorporation, they <lb/>are the main sources concerning salaries. <lb/>Centralisation and decentralisation -the <lb/>natural and socially hierarchical structure of <lb/>late medieval society assumed centralisation, <lb/>although on rare occasions a weak one as in the <lb/>case of the Medici, but it is still centralised, it <lb/>casts an almost non-delegated authority and <lb/>mainly taken among the equity partners in <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Marfa Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping... <lb/></note>

        <page>25 <lb/></page>

        <body>Barcelona and Zaragoza. All in all, it should be <lb/>pointed out again that our companies do not <lb/>have a very large workforce, which certainly <lb/>translates into a reduction in the probability of <lb/>a certain affirmation of the impossibility of an <lb/>undoubted diversification of power. Regarding <lb/>the scalar chain, 16 it is confirmed with an <lb/>infallible example -it is the case of Bernart <lb/>d&apos;Algars. A young man and employee, perhaps <lb/>even an apprentice of Joan de Torralba in the <lb/>year 1438, was part of a company as a partner <lb/>where our merchant Joan de Torralba was also <lb/>present. In addition, during the last company, <lb/>both were part partners-capitalists of the same <lb/>level. The scalar chain did not have this clear <lb/>path that is observed today, but neither is it a <lb/>modern nor alien notion to late medieval <lb/>Aragonese society. It used to be a longer, <lb/>thornier road and did not always lead to a pro-<lb/>motion. <lb/>Order 17 and equity 18 -have a unique spot in <lb/>the commercial activity of Joan de Torralba. <lb/>Order is nothing less than a crucial point for the <lb/>prolific functioning of a business entity. If the <lb/>work is not defined in advance, labour <lb/>16 The Scalar Chain, also known as the Hierarchy <lb/>Principle, is one of the fourteen principles of <lb/>management introduced by Henri Fayol in his book <lb/>&apos;General and Industrial Management&apos; (1916). The Scalar <lb/>Chain emphasises the importance of clear and unbroken <lb/>lines of authority and communication within an <lb/>organisation. According to Fayol, a well-defined <lb/>hierarchy is essential for effective coordination and <lb/>smooth functioning of the organisation. <lb/>17 Order refers to the organisation and arrangement of <lb/>resources and activities within a company to achieve <lb/>efficiency and effectiveness. In the late medieval period, <lb/>businesses and trading ventures were conducted within a <lb/>structured framework. Hence, the principle is fully ap-<lb/>plicable. <lb/>18 Equity in the context of late medieval companies refers <lb/>to fairness and justice in dealing with employees, <lb/>business partners, and customers. Although the medieval <lb/>period had hierarchical and feudal social structures, <lb/>there were efforts to ensure some level of fairness in <lb/>commercial interactions. <lb/>segregation loses its identification, which leads <lb/>to the precariousness of the business. In the <lb/>particular case of Joan de Torralba, due to the <lb/>small-medium sizes of the entities <lb/>management is easier and more tactical. <lb/>Concerning fairness, one fact should be <lb/>mentioned -the companies formed with Joan de <lb/>Torralba always had one thing in common: they <lb/>were all formed by Aragonese, whether they <lb/>were citizens of Barcelona, but always with <lb/>friendly ties from Aragon. What does to mean? <lb/>Since trust (fiducia) played a compulsory role at <lb/>the time of forming a business, it did not seem <lb/>strange to create a company with previously <lb/>known people and equally create an equitable <lb/>environment. <lb/>Stability of tenure of personnel -we do not <lb/>have any source that expresses staff loss. In the <lb/>beginning, it is important to point out that the <lb/>articles of incorporation stated of not being able <lb/>to carry on other businesses apart from the <lb/>formed company. However, after studying the <lb/>acts and accounting books, they highlight the <lb/>prolonged <lb/>permanence <lb/>where <lb/>the <lb/>abandonment of the position was only after <lb/>finishing the biennial period, usually for ageing <lb/>reasons. However, this principle neither would <lb/>be achievable due to the small size of the <lb/>company and luck of clear statements of <lb/>members of all levels. <lb/>Lamentably, when it comes to the initiative, it <lb/>is challenging to give precise answers, since the <lb/>available documentation does not allow it <lb/>because it does not document occasions of this <lb/>type. In the context of the late medieval ages, <lb/>the principle of &apos;Initiative&apos; was not a formal <lb/>concept in the same way it is understood in <lb/>modern management practices. During this <lb/>period, the social and economic systems were <lb/>vastly different from what we have today, and <lb/>the idea of individual initiative, as we know it, <lb/>was not a prominent aspect of the workforce or <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <body>General discussion <lb/></body>

        <page>26 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping ... <lb/></note>

        <body>business practices. May it be argued that it <lb/>never happened? Undoubtedly not, because the <lb/>fact <lb/>of <lb/>unwritten <lb/>conversations <lb/>or <lb/>communication between people reflecting and <lb/>debating suggestions and proposals cannot be <lb/>abolished. Given this, it is not relevant to <lb/>emphatically exclude it, but neither would it be <lb/>scientific to approve it without any clarification. <lb/>The last point is team spirit, which is certainly <lb/>an integral part of any business entity. &quot;Morale <lb/>is the ability of a group of people to persistently <lb/>and consistently unite in pursuit of a common <lb/>purpose&quot; (Leighton 1949) -creates the core of <lb/>business success no matter what time is <lb/>referred to. In the case of Joan de Torralba, <lb/>using the Italian concept of fiducia as a nucleus <lb/>of medieval business implies a decisive link by <lb/>creating a common purpose for the operation of <lb/>the companies created between 1425 and 1458 <lb/>with the participation of Joan de Torralba. Let&apos;s <lb/>apply contradictio in contrarium, that the <lb/>absence of group spirit would cause inefficiency <lb/>and decrease profit margins, thus contributing <lb/>to the cessation of commercial activity, which is <lb/>a falsehood because the documents deduce the <lb/>contrary. <lb/>Analysing a late medieval company&apos;s <lb/>management and administration can provide <lb/>valuable insights into the historical practices <lb/>and organisational structures of businesses <lb/>during that era. While the specifics of each <lb/>company would vary based on its size, industry, <lb/>and location, several specifics and themes can <lb/>be traced. Understanding the administration of <lb/>business in the late medieval period enriches <lb/>our understanding of broader historical trends <lb/>and events. Economic factors often play a role <lb/>in shaping political decisions, conflicts, and <lb/>societal changes. Perhaps, a more significant <lb/>point in studying the late medieval <lb/>administration system is that the era witnessed <lb/>the considerable evolution of financial <lb/>instruments like bills of exchange, promissory <lb/>notes, and rudimentary forms of banking. <lb/>Exploring business administration from this <lb/>period allows us to trace the origins of many <lb/>modern financial practices and institutions. <lb/>We may name the following points as the main <lb/>results. Firstly, by looking at the commercial <lb/>activities of Joan de Torralba, one can see that <lb/>the complexity and diversity of management do <lb/>not always accompany the use of more <lb/>complicated accounting systems. Late medieval <lb/>companies relied on basic record-keeping and <lb/>single-entry bookkeeping to track transactions, <lb/>resources, and obligations. Financial records <lb/>were often simple and focused on essential <lb/>information for managing the company&apos;s <lb/>affairs. Therefore, showing the influence of <lb/>personal qualities and knowledge in the field of <lb/>management. Secondly, accounting books have <lb/>primarily narrative functions, although they <lb/>display the full range of trading (and non-<lb/>trading) activities. Cash accounting, also known <lb/>as a &apos;journal&apos;, is used for both single-entry and <lb/>double-entry bookkeeping. In single-entry, <lb/>however, only income and expenses are <lb/>recorded chronologically, with no revenues and <lb/>costs. Though, in Joan de Torralba&apos;s ledgers, we <lb/>find revenues and costs statements. The income <lb/>statement and balance sheet in a separate <lb/>accounting system cannot be derived directly <lb/>from the journal entries. This requires the <lb/>accounting inventory. In this inventory, all <lb/>expected costs and revenues are collected, so <lb/>that an overview is created of all receivables <lb/>and debts. In addition to these receivables and <lb/>payables, <lb/>the <lb/>expenses <lb/>incurred <lb/>for <lb/>investments (in the costs) are removed from <lb/>the costs, to be capitalised. After that, the <lb/>depreciation can be calculated. Since inventory <lb/>is a cumbersome problem, most companies and <lb/>organisations of any size operate with a double-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <body>Limitations and future research <lb/>directions <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Marfa Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping... <lb/></note>

        <page>27 <lb/></page>

        <body>entry bookkeeping system, tried to avoid it. <lb/>Hence, the path is clear to re-create the <lb/>company&apos;s financial statements, because it is <lb/>viable with accumulated data and accounting <lb/>books of Joan de Torralba. Nonetheless, it <lb/>requires more time and meticulous calculation <lb/>of all the data ( which is available) but not the <lb/>whole range of private documentation of Joan <lb/>de Torralba is transcribed. The latter deterrent <lb/>prevents us from rebuilding a whole chain and <lb/>network crafted by Joan de Torralba. <lb/>Relationships and patronage were crucial in <lb/>late medieval business. Companies relied on <lb/>personal connections and networks for various <lb/>purposes, <lb/>including sourcing materials, <lb/>accessing markets, and securing protection or <lb/>support from powerful figures. Another <lb/>intriguing fact to mention is that the main <lb/>disadvantage of a single-entry accounting <lb/>system is the incomplete control system. <lb/>Though this disadvantage is not met in the <lb/>ledgers of Joan de Torralba. The records and <lb/>entries are highly systematic and well-<lb/>organised. Concerning the control system, we <lb/>do not doubt that the used way of record met <lb/>the needs of the merchant entirely. <lb/>Additionally, and maybe even more significant, <lb/>is the introduction and presentation of the <lb/>management system of Aragonese merchants. <lb/>The historical importance of management in <lb/>small companies lies in their role as engines of <lb/>innovation, local development, and economic <lb/>growth. Effective management practices within <lb/>small companies have shaped economies and <lb/>contributed to the evolution of management <lb/>theories and practices over time (Dieguez-Soto <lb/>et al. 2016). It gives the picture of how <lb/>companies operated and the mercantile way of <lb/>thinking in late medieval Barcelona, Zaragoza <lb/>and other cities of the Crown of Aragon. Such <lb/>information is of value when dealing with the <lb/>essential sector (the second after agriculture, as <lb/>in any other territory of those times) of the <lb/>Aragonese economy, like the commercial one. <lb/>To gather different sectors together and <lb/>interconnect them, would be the only way to re-<lb/>create the socio-economic reality of the late <lb/>medieval Crown of Aragon. We do not have <lb/>enough Aragonese documentation of that exact <lb/>period, and the case of Torralba is distinctive <lb/>since it provides us with Ledgers, acts of <lb/>foundation and notarial documentation. Hence, <lb/>on this solid basis, we may give one more <lb/>instance that the emergence of management <lb/>lies (in the modern sense) in the last centuries <lb/>of the Middle Ages, while society was in <lb/>transition to a Modern Age. Also, it is important <lb/>to highlight that The Crown of Aragon was not <lb/>only a powerful kingdom with considerable <lb/>dominance in the West Mediterranean but also <lb/>a place for the enhancement of managerial <lb/>techniques. <lb/>Regarding the limitations, the principal limiting <lb/>aspect of this study may be called, in the first <lb/>place, incompleteness of deciphered sources. <lb/>Many personal letters might disclose <lb/>confidential and vital information about the <lb/>way of thinking and the decision-making <lb/>process. Undoubtedly, it is an integral part of <lb/>the management and the drive of the <lb/>investigation. The data is the fructus of personal <lb/>musings, and that makes it easier for us to <lb/>change the angle of analysis and perception of <lb/>the analysed information. As we treat a small-<lb/>sized company -it is invaluable to depict the <lb/>whole image of a business functioning in the <lb/>Crown of Aragon. A microdot of that system -<lb/>the company of Joan de Torralba is surely one <lb/>of them -assists in the macro re-creation of <lb/>both commercial and managerial reality of that <lb/>momentous period. Put another way, the <lb/>Torralba company facilitates highlighting the <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <body>Practical implications <lb/></body>

        <div type="acknowledgment">Acknowledgement <lb/>Declarations <lb/></div>

        <div type="availability">Data availability <lb/></div>

        <page>28 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping ... <lb/></note>

        <body>pattern of the Catalano-Aragonese business <lb/>operation style. Further comparative analysis <lb/>with other Aragonese companies -where the <lb/>Ledgers are presented-would open the door to <lb/>formalising the Catalano-Aragonese business <lb/>identity. <lb/>Concerning the potential application of the <lb/>current study, it is nothing less than an <lb/>exhaustive understanding of the evolution and <lb/>development of management. Primarily when <lb/>we look at an entity, not being a bank or a <lb/>company of a large dimension that covers all <lb/>pre-industrial European financial centres such <lb/>as Bruges and London, but a company with <lb/>exclusively Euro-Mediterranean geography <lb/>-notwithstanding the African and Levantine <lb/>coasts as well under cases-, although being of a <lb/>lesser <lb/>extent, <lb/>consequently <lb/>more <lb/>representative. The analysis contributes to <lb/>constructing a complete image of late medieval <lb/>management, recreating the succession of the <lb/>emergence and formation of administration and <lb/>management sciences. <lb/></body>

        <div type="acknowledgment">The responsibility for the content and any <lb/>remammg mistakes or errata remains <lb/>exclusively with the authors of the paper. The <lb/>ideas and opinions defined in this paper are <lb/>those of the authors and do not necessarily <lb/>reflect those of their institutions or employers. <lb/>Furthermore, we would like to mention that <lb/>The Spanish Ministry funded the research <lb/>results contained in this paper with two R+D <lb/>grants for the project entitled FENICE. Markets <lb/>and economic spaces in the Western <lb/>Mediterranean: <lb/>The <lb/>formation <lb/>of an <lb/>international environment for European Trade <lb/>at the beginning of Modernity [HAR2015-<lb/>65285-R MINECO/FEDER, UE] and GENESIS. <lb/>Economic globalisation and new international <lb/>frameworks: European Markets and Late <lb/>Medieval trade <lb/>networks <lb/>in Western <lb/>Mediterranean <lb/>[PID2019-104157GB-IO0/ <lb/>AEI/10.13039/501100011033]. It also received <lb/>funds from the &quot;La Caixa&quot; Foundation (ID <lb/>100010434), under agreement FENIX. The <lb/>formation of an International Trade Network: <lb/>the business of a Catalan merchant at the dawn <lb/>of Modernity [2017 ACUP0l 95]. Research has <lb/>taken place under the Medieval and <lb/>Postmedieval Research Group framework at the <lb/>University <lb/>of <lb/>Barcelona <lb/>GRAMP-Med <lb/>(Generalitat de Catalunya 2021SGR236). Fin-<lb/>ally, also received funds from M&amp;N. Merchants <lb/>and Networks: datificaci6n y transcripci6n <lb/>automatica <lb/>del <lb/>comercio <lb/>mediterraneo <lb/>(Compafiia Torralba, siglo XV) [PID2023-<lb/>150176NB-IO0]. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">We declare that this paper was composed by us, <lb/>that the work contained herein is our own <lb/>except where explicitly stated otherwise in the <lb/>text, and that this work has not been submitted <lb/>for any other reviews. <lb/></div>

        <div type="availability">The eleven conserved Ledgers used throughout <lb/>the research are stored in the National Archive <lb/>of Catalonia. They are coded as follows: ANCl-<lb/>960-T-157, ANCl-960-T-211, ANCl-960-T-<lb/>3000, ANCl-960-T-3003, ANCl-960-T-3004, <lb/>ANCl-960-T-3065, ANCl-960-T-3187, ANCl-<lb/>960-T-3189, ANCl-960-T-3200, ANCl-960-T-<lb/>3274, ANCl-960-T-3277, ANCl-960-T-4240, <lb/>ANCl-960-T-4782, ANCl-960-T-5206. The <lb/>above-mentioned data supporting material is <lb/>available digitally on an official website: <lb/>https:/ /arxiusenlinia.cultura.gencat.cat <lb/></div>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>References <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="headnote">Marfa Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping... <lb/></note>

        <page>29 <lb/></page>

        <div type="availability">ANCl-960-T-4787 -is unavailable and must be <lb/>requested in advance for a personal <lb/>consultation in the Archive. <lb/>Otherwise, the listed material can be accessed <lb/>in transcribed form in the following books: <lb/>i. <lb/>ii. <lb/>iii. <lb/>iv. <lb/>M. Dolores Lopez, Enrico Basso, Gerard <lb/>Mari, Esther Trave, De Aragon a Venecia. El <lb/>«Llibre major de comer&lt;; de Ilana blanca <lb/>amb Italia» de la companyia Torralba (1433-<lb/>1434 ), Barcelona-Torino, Publicaciones <lb/>Universitat de Barcelona, Universita di <lb/>Torino, <lb/>2019. <lb/>http://diposit.ub.edu/ <lb/>dspace/handle/2445 /172050 <lb/>Jesus Benavides, Ivan Casado, La memoria <lb/>del mercader. El «Manual honze» de la <lb/>compafifa Torralba (1434-143 7), Barcelona, <lb/>Publicacions Universitat de Barcelona, 2019. <lb/>http:// <lb/>diposit.ub.edu/ dspace/handle/2445 /17900 <lb/>1 <lb/>Marfa Viu, La contabilidad privada del <lb/>mercader barcelones Joan de Torralba. El <lb/>«Llibre de comtans» (1430-1460) y el <lb/>cuadernillo de deudas con Pere de Sitges <lb/>(1432-1448), <lb/>Barcelona, <lb/>Publicaciones <lb/>Universitat <lb/>de <lb/>Barcelona, <lb/>2019. <lb/>http://diposit.ub.edu/ dspace/handle/2445 <lb/>/179002 <lb/>Maria Viu, Los libros secretos de una <lb/>compafifa comercial de la Corona de Aragon: <lb/>la <lb/>Torralba-Manariello <lb/>(1430-143 7), <lb/>Barcelona, Publicaciones Universitat de <lb/>Barcelona, Universita degli Studi dell&apos;Aquila. <lb/>The dataset FENIX is not available for external <lb/>use. The availability is exclusively internal by <lb/>the members of the investigation group. <lb/></div>

        <listBibl>Abulafia, David, and Marfa Dolores Lopez Perez. <lb/>2020. &quot;El mundo de Joan de Torralba, un <lb/>mercader del siglo XV.&quot; In Mercados y <lb/>espacios econ6micos en el siglo XV: el mundo <lb/>del mercader Joan de Torralba, edited by <lb/>David Baulafia, and Maria Dolores Lopez <lb/>Perez, 9-30. Barcelona: Edicions, Universitat <lb/>de Barcelona. <lb/>Abulafia, David, and Maria Dolores Lopez Perez. <lb/>2020. Mercados y espacios econ6micos en el <lb/>siglo XV El mundo de/ mercader Torralba. <lb/>Barcelona: <lb/>Edicions <lb/>Universitat <lb/>de <lb/>Barcelona. <lb/>http://dipositub.edu/dspacefhandle/2445/185040. <lb/>Allepuz Trave, Ester, and Ivan Casado Novas. 2020. <lb/>&quot;Herramienta para el analisis contable de <lb/>documentacion mercantil bajomedieval: <lb/>perspectiva ontologica y gestion integrada <lb/>de datos.&quot; In Mercadosy espacios econ6micos <lb/>en el siglo XV: el mundo de/ mercader Joan de <lb/>Torralba, 69-110. Barcelona: Edicions, <lb/>Universitat de Barcelona. <lb/>Altisent, Agusti. 196 7-68. &quot;Una societat mercantil a <lb/>Catalunya a darreries del segle XII.&quot; Boletin <lb/>de la Real Academia de Buenas Letras de <lb/>Barcelona XXXII: 45-65. <lb/>Alvesson, Mats, and Hugh Willmott. 2012. Making <lb/>Sense <lb/>of <lb/>Management: <lb/>A <lb/>Critical <lb/>Introduction. Los Angeles (CA).: SAGE. 2. ed. <lb/>Benavides, Jesus, and Ivan Casado Novas. 2019. La <lb/>memoria de/ mercader. El &quot;Manual Honze&quot; de <lb/>la <lb/>Compafi.ia <lb/>Torralba <lb/>(1434-1437). <lb/>Barcelona: <lb/>Edicions, <lb/>Universitat <lb/>de <lb/>Barcelona. <lb/>http://dipositub.edu/dspace/handle/2445/179001 <lb/>Besta, Fabio. 1909. La Ragioneria. Rome: Rirea. <lb/>2nd Edition (In 3 Volumes), Facsimile <lb/>Reprint, 2007. <lb/>Bigwood, Georges. 1962. Les livres des comptes des <lb/>Gallerani. revu, mis au point, Tome II: <lb/>Introduction complete et tables, edited by <lb/>Armand Ouvrage Grunzweig. Memoires in-<lb/>8° de la Commission royale d&apos;histoire. <lb/>Bruxelles, Palais des Academies, 8°, 354 p. <lb/>(Don de la Commission royale d&apos;histoire.) <lb/>Buchanan, David, and Richard Badham. 1999. <lb/>Power, Politics and Organizational Change. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <page>30 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping ... <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>London: Corwin Press. <lb/>Burrell, Gibson, and Gareth Morgan. 2016. <lb/>Sociological Paradigms and Organisational <lb/>Analysis: Elements of the Sociology of <lb/>Corporate Life. Abingdon, Oxon: Routledge. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.4324/9781315242804 <lb/>Butler, Gathorne V. 1986. Organization and <lb/>Management: <lb/>Theory <lb/>and <lb/>Practice. <lb/>Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice Hall. <lb/>Caceres, Juanjo. 2011. &quot;Un analisis de contabilidad <lb/>comercial del siglo XV: el libro de cuentas de <lb/>Joan Gasull, mercader de Barcelona.&quot; <lb/>Studium. Revista de Humanidades 17: 39-63. <lb/>Carey, John Lansing. 1969. The Rise of the <lb/>Accounting Profession: From Technician to <lb/>Professional, 1896-1936. New York: AICPA. <lb/>Carlomagno, Antonio. 2009. II banco Salviati di <lb/>Pisa: commercio e finanza di una compagnia <lb/>fiorentina tra ii 1438 e ii 1489. Universita di <lb/>Pisa. etd-11112009-115303. <lb/>Carrere, Claude. 1977-78. Barcelona, 1380-1482: <lb/>Un centre economic en epoca de crisi. <lb/>Barcelona: Curial. 2 vols. <lb/>Casado, Hilario. 2011. &quot;La formacion del espacio <lb/>economico Atlantico (siglos XV y XVI). Las <lb/>transferencias de mercandas y simbolos en <lb/>la &apos;Primera Edad Global&apos;.&quot; In La apertura de <lb/>Europa al mundo at/6.ntico. Espacios de <lb/>pod er, economf a marf tima y circulaci6n <lb/>cultural, edited by Jose Ramon Diaz de <lb/>Durana and Jose Antonio Munita, 117-142. <lb/>Bilbao: Universidad de Pais Vasco. <lb/>Chatfield, Michael. 1996. &quot;Donaldo Soranzo and <lb/>brothers.&quot; In The History of Accounting: An <lb/>International Encyclopedia, edited by <lb/>Michael <lb/>Chatfield <lb/>and <lb/>Richard <lb/>Vangermeersch, 216. New York: Garland <lb/>Publishing. <lb/>Colesanti, Gemma. 2008. Una mujer de negocios <lb/>catalana en la Sicilia de/ siglo XV: Caterina <lb/>Llull i Sabastida. £studio y edici6n de su libro <lb/>maestro 1472-1472. Barcelona: Consejo <lb/>Superior de Investigaciones Cientfficas. <lb/>Colesanti, Gemma, and Maria Del Popolo. 2020. <lb/>&quot;Caterina Llull i Sabastida, il suo spazio <lb/>economico e familiare tra la Sicilia e la <lb/>Catalogna della fino del XV secolo.&quot; In <lb/>Mercados y espacios econ6micos en el siglo <lb/>XV: el mundo de/ mercader Joan de Torralba, <lb/>edited by David Baulafia, and Maria Dolores <lb/>Lopez Perez, 539-559. Barcelona: Edicions, <lb/>Universitat de Barcelona. <lb/>Coll, Nuria. 1968. &quot;Una compafiia barcelonesa para <lb/>el comercio de pafios (1400-1484).&quot; Anuario <lb/>de £studios Medievales 5: 339-408. <lb/>Coll, Nuria. 1981. &quot;Compafiias mercantiles <lb/>barcelonesas del siglo XV y su estrato <lb/>familiar.&quot; Estudis Histories i Documents dels <lb/>Arxius <lb/>de <lb/>Protocols <lb/>9: <lb/>27-104. <lb/>https://raco.cat/index.php/EHDAP /article/ <lb/>view /287899. <lb/>Casado Quintanilla, Blas, and Jose Ignacio de La <lb/>Iglesia Duarte. 2006. El comercio en la Edad <lb/>Media: XVI semana de estudios medievales, <lb/>Najera y Tricia (1-5 de agosto 2005). <lb/>Logrono: Instituto de Estudios Riojanos. <lb/>Cotrugli, Benedetto. 1458. Libra de Larte de/a <lb/>Mercatura, copy made 1475. In Libr. XV, <lb/>National Library of Malta. Valletta. <lb/>Cuadrada Majo, Coral. 1994. &quot;Valen instroyr e <lb/>informar las mercaders, aquells qui d&apos;aquest <lb/>art de marcaderia volen usar.&quot; Revista <lb/>d&apos;Historia Medieval 5: 107-132. <lb/>Cuadrada Majo, Coral. 2020. &quot;Del juramiento a la <lb/>compafiia: mentalidades feudal es y / o <lb/>mercantiles.&quot; In Mercados y espacios <lb/>econ6micos en el siglo XV: el mundo de/ <lb/>mercader Joan de Torralba, 495-538. <lb/>Barcelona: <lb/>Edicions, <lb/>Universitat <lb/>de <lb/>Barcelona. <lb/>Cuadrada Majo, Coral, and Maria Dolores Lopez <lb/>Perez. 1991. &quot;A la Mediterrania medieval: <lb/>les societats mercantils a la Corona d&apos; Arago <lb/>(s.XIV).&quot; Universitas Tarraconensis. Revista <lb/>de Geografia, Historia i Filosofia X: 67-92. <lb/>De Roover, Raymond. 1937. &quot;Aux origines d&apos;une <lb/>technique intellectuelle. La formation et <lb/>!&apos;expansion de la comptabilite a partie double.&quot; <lb/>Anna/es d&apos;histoire economique et socia/e, t. 9: <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Marfa Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping... <lb/></note>

        <page>31 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>270-288. <lb/>http://www.jstor.org/stable/27574484. <lb/>De Roover, Raymond. 1946. &quot;The Medici Bank <lb/>Organization and Management.&quot; The Journal <lb/>of Economic History, 6(1): 24-52. <lb/>http:/ /www.jstor.org/stable/2112995. <lb/>De Roover, Raymond. 194 7. &quot;The Decline of the <lb/>Medici Bank&quot; The Journal of Economic <lb/>History, <lb/>7(1): <lb/>69-82. <lb/>http://www.jstor.org/stable/2113600. <lb/>De Roover, Raymond. 1956. &quot;The Development of <lb/>Accounting Prior to Luca Pacioli According <lb/>to The Account-books of Medieval <lb/>Merchants.&quot; In Studies in the History of <lb/>Accounting, edited by A. C. Littleton, and B. <lb/>S. Varney, 114-174. Homewood,: Richard D. <lb/>Irwin. <lb/>De Roover, Raymond. 1963. The Rise and Decline of <lb/>the Medici Bank, 1397-1494. Cambridge <lb/>(Massachussetts ), <lb/>University Press. <lb/>London: <lb/>Harvard <lb/>Del Punta, Ignazio. 2004. &quot;Principal Italian Banking <lb/>Companies of the XIIIth and XIVth <lb/>Centuries: A Comparison Between the <lb/>Ricciardi of Lucca and the Bardi, Peruzzi and <lb/>Acciaiuoli of Florence.&quot; Journal of European <lb/>Economic History 3: 647-662. <lb/>Del Treppo, Mario. 1976. Els mercaders catalans i <lb/>l&apos;expansi6 de la corona catalano-aragonesa <lb/>al segle XV. Barcelona: Curial. <lb/>Dieguez-Soto, Julio, Antonio Durendez, Domingo <lb/>Garcia-Perez-de-Lema, and Daniel Ruiz-<lb/>Palomo. 2016. &quot;Technological, management, <lb/>and persistent innovation in small and <lb/>medium family firms: The influence of <lb/>professionalism.&quot; Canadian Journal of <lb/>Administrative Sciences 33( 4): 332-346. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/cjas.1404. <lb/>Duran, Daniel. 2002. Manual def viatge Jet per <lb/>Berenguer Benet a Romania, 1341-1342. <lb/>Estudi i edici6. Barcelona: Consejo Superior <lb/>de Investigaciones Cientificas. <lb/>Duran, Daniel. 2009. &quot;A proposit d&apos;una expedicio <lb/>comercial de Mallorca a Honein el 1339. El <lb/>«Quern de carregar en Malorque per lo <lb/>viatga de Hone de la nau d&apos;en Arnau Spaher <lb/>e d&apos;en Romeu d&apos;Olzineles.&quot; Bolletf de la <lb/>Societat Arqueologica Lul•liana 65: 31-56. <lb/>Eccles, Robert. G., and Nohria Nitin. 1992. Beyond <lb/>the Hype-Rediscovering the Essence of <lb/>Management. Boston: Harvard Business <lb/>School Press. <lb/>Epstein, Stephan. R. 2006. &quot;I caratteri originali. <lb/>L&apos;economia.&quot; In L&apos;Italia alla fine def <lb/>Medioevo: i carateri originali nel quadro <lb/>Europeo, edited by Franciso Salvestrini, 381-<lb/>431. Florence: Firenze University Press. <lb/>Erikson, Emily, and Samila Sampsa. 2018. <lb/>&quot;Networks, Institutions, and Uncertainty: <lb/>Information Exchange in Early-Modern <lb/>Markets.&quot; The Journal of Economic History, <lb/>78(4): <lb/>1034-1067. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017 /S0022050718000566. <lb/>Fayal, Henri. 1916. Administration industrielle et <lb/>generale. Paris: Dunod et Pinat. <lb/>Ferrer, M. Teresa. 2012. &quot;Catalan commerce in the <lb/>late Middle Ages.&quot; Catalan Historical Review 5: <lb/>29-65. <lb/>https://raco.cat/index.php/CatalanHistoricalReview <lb/>/article/view /265172. <lb/>Furio, Antoni. 2010. &quot;La crisis de la Baja Edad <lb/>Media: una revision.&quot; In Las crisis a lo largo <lb/>de la historia, edited by Antoni Furio, 13-45. <lb/>Valladolid: Publicaciones de la Universidad <lb/>de Valladolid. <lb/>Furio, Antoni. 2015. &quot;La crisis de la Baja Edad <lb/>Media en las origenes de una construccion <lb/>historiografica.&quot; <lb/>In <lb/>La <lb/>Historiografia <lb/>medieval davant la crisi -La Historiograffa <lb/>medieval ante la crisis, edited by Elisa Varela <lb/>Rodriguez, 169-206. Girona: Documenta <lb/>Universitaria. <lb/>Ghosh, Dhruba Narayan. 2006. &quot;Genesis of High <lb/>Finance: Case of Medici Bank&quot; Economic and <lb/>Political <lb/>Weekly, <lb/>41(7): <lb/>542-543. <lb/>http://www.jstor.org/stable/4417808. <lb/>Goldthwaite, Richard A. 1985. &quot;Local banking in <lb/>Renaissance Florence.&quot; The Journal of <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <page>32 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping ... <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>European Economic History, 14: 5-55. <lb/>Goldthwaite, Richard A. 1987. &quot;The Medici Bank <lb/>and the World of Florentine Capitalism.&quot; <lb/>Past <lb/>&amp; <lb/>Present, <lb/>114: <lb/>3-31. <lb/>http://www.jstor.org/stable/650959. <lb/>Goldthwaite, Richard A. 2011. The Economy of <lb/>Renaissance Florence. Baltimore: Johns <lb/>Hopkins <lb/>University <lb/>Press. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1353/book.3422. <lb/>Goldthwaite, Richard A. 2013. L&apos;economia de/la <lb/>Firenze rinascimentale. Bolonia: 11 Mulino. <lb/>Goldthwaite, Richard A. 2015. &quot;The Practice and <lb/>Culture of Accounting in Renaissance <lb/>Florence.&quot; Enterprise &amp; Society, 16(3): <lb/>611-647. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017 /eso.2015.17. <lb/>Gual Camarena, Miguel. 1981. El primer manual <lb/>hispanico de mercaderfa (siglo XIV). <lb/>Barcelona: <lb/>Consejo <lb/>Superior <lb/>de <lb/>Investigaciones Cientificas. <lb/>Hernandez-Esteve, Estebab. 2006. &quot;Preliminary <lb/>Accounting Thought in Spain, 13th to 16th <lb/>centuries.&quot; Paper presented at the Xie <lb/>Congres mondial des historiens de la <lb/>comptabilite (11th WCAH), Nantes. <lb/>Houssaye Michienzi, Ingrid. 2013. Datini, Majorque <lb/>et le Maghreb: 14e-15e siecles: reseaux, <lb/>espaces <lb/>mediterraneens et strategies <lb/>marchandes. Leiden-Boston: Brill. <lb/>Houssaye Michienzi, Ingrid. 2016. &quot;Reconstruire <lb/>des reseaux d&apos;affaires a partir de sources <lb/>comptables : des exemples toscans (xive-<lb/>xvie siecles).&quot; In Reseaux politiques et <lb/>economiques, edited by Henri Bresc, 123-34. <lb/>Paris: Editions du Comite des travaux <lb/>historiques <lb/>et <lb/>scientifiques. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.4000/books.cths.2219. <lb/>Huber, Guy. 2019. &quot;Book Review: A new history of <lb/>management.&quot; Management Learning, 50(4): <lb/>511-514. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1177 /1350507618772129. <lb/>Hunt, Edwin. 1990. &quot;Dealings of the Bardi and <lb/>Peruzzi.&quot; Journal of Economic History, 50(1). <lb/>https://www.jstor.org/stable/2123442. <lb/>Hunt, Edwin. 1994. The Medieval Super-Companies: <lb/>A Study of the Peruzzi Company of Florence. <lb/>Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. 1st <lb/>ed. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017 /CBO9780511528798. <lb/>Hunt, Edwin, and Murray, James. 1999. A History of <lb/>Business in Medieval Europe, 1200-1550. <lb/>Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. <lb/>Hurtado, Victor. 2005. Llibre de deutes, trameses i <lb/>rebudes de Jaume de Mitjavila i compafi.ia <lb/>(1345-1370). Edici6, estudi comptable i <lb/>economic. Barcelona: Consejo Superior de <lb/>Investigaciones Cientificas. <lb/>Hurtado, Victor. 2007. Els Mitjavila. Una familia de <lb/>mercaders a la Barcelona de/ segle XIV. <lb/>Barcelona: Publicacions de l&apos; Abadia de <lb/>Montserrat. <lb/>Igual, David. 2002. &quot;La economia europea vista <lb/>desde el siglo XV o las globalizaciones en el <lb/>pasado.&quot; La Musa. Pensamiento, Universidad <lb/>y Red, 1: 105-113. <lb/>Igual, David. 2006-2008. &quot;Operadores econ6micos <lb/>y espacios de comercio en el Mediterraneo <lb/>Occidental (siglos XIII-XV).&quot; Revista de <lb/>Historia Medieval, 15: 189-214. <lb/>Igual, David. 2007. &quot;LCrisis? lQue crisis? El <lb/>comercio internacional en las reinos <lb/>hispanicos de la Baja Edad Media.&quot; Edad <lb/>Media: revista de historia, 8: 203-223. <lb/>Igual, David. 2008. &quot;Economia, mercado y <lb/>comercio en la Peninsula lberica (1350-<lb/>1516).&quot; <lb/>eHumanista, <lb/>10: <lb/>170-200. <lb/>https://www.cervantesvirtual.-<lb/>com/nd/ark:/59851/bmcbz825. <lb/>Jaques, Elliott. 1961. Equitable Payment: A General <lb/>Theory of Work, Differential Payment, and <lb/>Individual Progress. London: Heinemann. <lb/>Jaques, Elliott. 1951. The Changing Culture of a <lb/>Factory: A Study of Authority and <lb/>Participation in an Industrial Setting. <lb/>London: Tavistock. <lb/>Jaques, <lb/>Elliott. <lb/>1956. <lb/>Measurement <lb/>of <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping... <lb/></note>

        <page>33 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>Responsibility: A study of work, payment, and <lb/>individual capacity. Cambridge: Harvard <lb/>University Press. <lb/>Jones, Michael Jones. 2008. &quot;Internal control, <lb/>accountability and corporate governance: <lb/>Medieval and modern Britain compared.&quot; <lb/>Accounting, Auditing &amp; Accountability <lb/>Journal <lb/>21(7): <lb/>1052-1075. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1108/09513570810907474. <lb/>Jouanique, Pierre. 1996. &quot;Three medieval merchants: <lb/>Francesco di Marco Datini, Jacques Coeur and <lb/>Benedetto Cotrugli.&quot; Accounting, Business &amp; <lb/>Financial <lb/>History, <lb/>6(3): <lb/>261-275. <lb/>https:/ / doi.org/10.1080 /09585209600000046. <lb/>Kadens, Emily. 2015. &quot;The Medieval Law <lb/>Merchant: The Tyranny of a Construct.&quot; <lb/>Journal of Legal Analysis, Volume 7(2): <lb/>251-289. <lb/>https://doi-<lb/>org.sire. ub.edu/10.1093 /jla/lav004 <lb/>Kohn, Mier. 1999. &quot;Merchants banking in the <lb/>medieval and early modern economy.&quot; <lb/>Dartmouth <lb/>College, <lb/>Department <lb/>of <lb/>Economics Working Paper No. 99-05. ht-<lb/>tp://dx.doi.org/10.2139 /ssrn.151850. <lb/>Laliena, Carlos. 2012. &quot;Transformacion social y <lb/>revolucion comercial en Aragon: treinta <lb/>afios de investigacion.&quot; In Una economfa <lb/>integrada. <lb/>Comercio, <lb/>instituciones <lb/>y <lb/>mercados <lb/>en <lb/>Aragon, <lb/>1300-1500, <lb/>coordinated by Carlos Laliena Corbera and <lb/>Mario Lafuente Gomez, 13-68. Zaragoza: <lb/>CEMA. <lb/>Lane, Frederic. C. 1944. Andrea Barbarigo, <lb/>Merchant of Venice, 1418-1449. Baltimore, <lb/>MD: The Johns Hopkins University Press. <lb/>Lee, Geoffrky Alan. 1973. &quot;The Development of <lb/>Italian Bookkeeping, 1211-1300.&quot; Abacus <lb/>9(2): 137-155. <lb/>Lee, Geoffrky Alan. 1977. &quot;The Coming of Age of <lb/>Double Entry: The Giovanni Farolfi Ledger <lb/>of 1299-1300.&quot; Accounting Historians <lb/>Journal, <lb/>4(2): <lb/>79-95. <lb/>https: / / egrove.olemiss.edu/ aahjournal/vol4 /iss2 / 6. <lb/>Leighton, Alexander. 1949. Human relations in a <lb/>changing world: Observations on the use of <lb/>the social sciences. New York: E P Dutton and <lb/>Company. <lb/>https://psycnetapa.org/doi/10.1037 /13243-000. <lb/>Lopez, Perez, Maria Dolores. 2001. &quot;Comprar y <lb/>vender en Catalufia: mercados, ferias y <lb/>lonjas (ss.XII-XV)&quot;. In Fiere e mercati nella <lb/>integrazione delle economie europee secco <lb/>XIII-XVIII, edited by Simonetta Cavacciocci, <lb/>309-333. Florence: Le Monnier. <lb/>Lopez, Perez, Maria Dolores. 2013. &quot;La Compafiia <lb/>Torralba y las redes de distribucion de la <lb/>lana en el norte de Italia (1433-1434).&quot; In A <lb/>I&apos;entorn de la Barcelona medieval. Estudis <lb/>dedicats a la doctora Josefina Mutge i Vives, <lb/>edited by Manuel Sanchez Martinez, Ana <lb/>Gomez Rabal, Roser Salicru i Lluch, and Pere <lb/>Vierdes <lb/>Pijuan, 313-332. Barcelona: <lb/>Consejo <lb/>Superior <lb/>de <lb/>Investigaciones <lb/>Cientificas. <lb/>Lopez, Perez, Maria Dolores. 2015. &quot;El comercio <lb/>interno. <lb/>Ferias <lb/>y <lb/>mercados. <lb/>La <lb/>redistribucion a traves de los caminos <lb/>terrestres, fluviales y el trafico de cabotaje&quot;. <lb/>In Mart[ l&apos;Huma. El darrer ref de la dinastfa <lb/>de Barcelona (1396-1410). L&apos;Interregne i el <lb/>Compromfs de Casp, edited by Maria Teresa <lb/>Ferrer, <lb/>501-517. <lb/>Barcelona: <lb/>Institut <lb/>d&apos;Estudis Catalans. <lb/>Lopez, Perez, Maria Dolores. 2017. &quot;Catalan <lb/>maritime expansion in the western <lb/>Mediterranean (12th-15th centuries)&quot;. In <lb/>The sea in history -The Medieval World, <lb/>edited by Michel Balard, 295-305. Suffolk: <lb/>Boydell &amp; Brewer. <lb/>Lopez, Perez, Maria Dolores. 2020. Joan de <lb/>Torralba y la apertura de nuevos mercados: <lb/>el negocio magrebi. In Mercados y espacios <lb/>econ6micos en el siglo XV: el mundo def <lb/>mercader Joan de Torralba, edited by David <lb/>Abulafia, and Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, <lb/>227-256. Barcelona: Edicions, Universitat de <lb/>Barcelona. <lb/>Lopez, Perez, Maria Dolores, Casado Ivan, Mari <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <page>34 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping ... <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>Gerrad, Alvaro, Karen. 2022. &quot;Ragusa <lb/>(Dubrovnik) en las redes comerciales del <lb/>Mediterraneo Occidental: las negocios de la <lb/>compafiia Torralba (s. XV).&quot; Ana/es de la <lb/>Universidad de Alicante. Historia Medieval, 23: <lb/>pp.131-159. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.14198/medieval.21467. <lb/>Lopez, Perez, Maria Dolores, Enrico Basso Enrico, <lb/>Gerard Mari, Ester Trave. 2019. De Aragon a <lb/>Venecia. La Compafi.fa Torralba y el negocio <lb/>de la lana (1433-1434). Barcelona-Torino: <lb/>Edicions <lb/>Universitat <lb/>de <lb/>Barcelona, <lb/>Universita <lb/>di <lb/>Torino. <lb/>http://dipositub.edu/dspace/handle/2445/172050. <lb/>Lopez, Perez, Maria Dolores, Coral Cuadrada, and <lb/>Ester Trave. 2023. &quot;Females also Run <lb/>Business. Merchants&apos; Wives and Female <lb/>Merchants in the Crown of Aragon <lb/>(Fourteenth-Fifteenth Century).&quot; Imago <lb/>temporis: medium Aevum 17: 279-308. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.21001/itma.2023.16.12. <lb/>Lopez, Perez, Maria Dolores, and Jose Padilla. <lb/>2013. &quot;Mallorcan merchants in Medieval <lb/>Maghreb: mercantile strategies in the port <lb/>of Honein in the mid-fourteenth century.&quot; <lb/>Mediterranean Historical Review, 28(2): <lb/>141-165. <lb/>Lopez, Perez, Maria Dolores, and Jose Ignacio <lb/>Padilla. 2021. &quot;Mercaderes mallorquines en <lb/>la ruta de Berberia. Las actividades <lb/>mercantiles de la Liga de Honein (1344)&quot;. In <lb/>Entre el Mediterraneo y el Atlantico: Jose <lb/>Hinojosa Montalvo y el mundo medieval, <lb/>edited by Jose Vicente Cabezuelo, Juan <lb/>Antonio Barrio Barrio, Jua Leonardo Soler, <lb/>357-392. Alicante: Publicaciones de la <lb/>Universidad de Alicante. <lb/>Lopez, Robert. 1948. &quot;Italian Leadership in the <lb/>Medieval Business World.&quot; The Journal of <lb/>Economic <lb/>History, <lb/>8(1): <lb/>63-68. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017 /S0022050700053845. <lb/>Madurell, Jose M. 1965. &quot;Contabilidad de una <lb/>compafiia <lb/>mercantil <lb/>trescentista <lb/>barcelonesa (1334-1342).&quot; Anuario de <lb/>Historia de! Derecho Espafi.ol, XXV: .412-525. <lb/>Madurell, Jose M. 1966. &quot;Contabilidad de una <lb/>compafiia <lb/>mercantil <lb/>trescentista <lb/>barcelonesa (1334-1342).&quot; Anuario de <lb/>Historia de! Derecho Espafi.ol XXXVI: 458-<lb/>546. <lb/>Madurell, Josep M., Garcia, Arcadi. 1986. Societats <lb/>mercantils medievals a Barcelona. Barcelona: <lb/>Fundacio Noguera, 2 vols. <lb/>Malanima, Paolo. 2009. Pre-modern European <lb/>economy: One thousand years (10th-19th <lb/>centuries). Leiden-Boston: Brill. <lb/>Mari, Gerard, and Karen Alvaro. 2020. &quot;Mercaderes <lb/>y hombres de negocios en la documentacion <lb/>pisana: las fondos del notario Scarsi.&quot; In <lb/>Mercados y espacios econ6micos en el siglo <lb/>XV: el mundo de! mercader Joan de Torralba, <lb/>edited by David Abulafia, and Maria Dolores <lb/>Lopez Perez, 445-70. Barcelona: Edicions, <lb/>Universitat de Barcelona. <lb/>Martinelli, Alvaro. 1977. &quot;Notes on the Origin of <lb/>Double Entry Bookkeeping.&quot; Abacus 13(1): <lb/>3-27. <lb/>Matringe, Nadia. 2016. La banque en Renaissance. <lb/>Les Salviati et la place de Lyon au milieu du <lb/>XV/e siecle. Rennes: Presses universitaires <lb/>de Rennes. <lb/>https:/ / doi.org/10.4000 /books.pur.44665. <lb/>Melis, Federigo. 1950. Storia della Ragioneria. <lb/>Conoscenza alla Contributo interpretazione e <lb/>piu delle significativa della storia economica <lb/>Fanti. Bologna: Zuffi. <lb/>Melis, Federigo. 1962. Aspetti della vita economica <lb/>medievale <lb/>{Studt <lb/>di <lb/>Prato <lb/>Datini <lb/>nell&apos;Archivio). Siena: Monte dei Paschi di <lb/>Siena. <lb/>Melis, Federigo. 1962. Aspetti della vita economica <lb/>medievale (Studt nell&apos;Archivio Datini di <lb/>Prato). Firenze: Olschki, IV,7. <lb/>Melis, Federigo. 1991. L&apos;Azienda nel Medioevo. <lb/>Florence: Istituto di Storia Economica <lb/>Francesco di Marco Datini. <lb/>Mitev, Nathalie, Anna Morgan-Thomas, Philippe <lb/>Lorino, Frarn;ois-Xavier De Vaujany, and <lb/>Yesh Nama, editors. 2018. Materiality and <lb/>Managerial Techniques. Cham: Palgrave <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Marfa Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping... <lb/></note>

        <page>35 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>Macmillan. https://doi.org/10.1007 /978-3-<lb/>319-66101-8. <lb/>Mufi.oz de Escobar, Francisco. 1603. De Ratiociniis <lb/>Administratorum <lb/>et <lb/>Aliis <lb/>Variis <lb/>Computationibus Tractatus. Medina del <lb/>Campo. <lb/>Murray, David. 1923. &quot;The Medieval Law and <lb/>Practice in regard to Accounts.&quot; Journal of <lb/>Comparative Legislation and International <lb/>Law 5(1): 63-72. <lb/>Navarro Espinach, German. 2020. &quot;El comercio de <lb/>cereales en Aragon en el siglo XV.&quot; In <lb/>Mercados y espacios econ6micos en el siglo <lb/>XV: el mundo de/ mercader Joan de Torralba, <lb/>edited by David Abulafia and Marfa Dolores <lb/>Lopez, 155-189. Barcelona: Edicions, <lb/>Universitat de Barcelona. <lb/>Nigro, Giampiero, ed. 2010. Francesco di Marco Datini. <lb/>L&apos;uomo ii mercate. Firenze: Firenze University <lb/>Press. <lb/>https:/ / doi.org/10.36253 /978-88-8453-558-0. <lb/>N obes, Christopher. W. 1982. &quot;The Gallerani <lb/>Account Book of 1305-1308.&quot; <lb/>The <lb/>Accounting Review 57(2): 303-310. <lb/>Orlandi, Angela. 2008. Mercaderies i diners: la cor-<lb/>respondencia datiniana entre Valencia i Mal-<lb/>lorca (1395-1398). Valencia: Universidad de <lb/>Valencia. <lb/>Orlandi, Angela. 2020. &quot;Prima della Compagnia <lb/>Torralba. II commercio della lana spagnola <lb/>tra XIV e XV secolo.&quot; In Mercados y espacios <lb/>econ6micos en el siglo XV: el mundo de/ <lb/>mercader Joan de Torralba, edited by David <lb/>Abulafia and Marfa Dolores Lopez, 413-444. <lb/>Barcelona: <lb/>Edicions, <lb/>Universitat <lb/>de <lb/>Barcelona. <lb/>Palermo, Luciano. 2008. La banca e ii credito nel <lb/>Medioevo. Milan: Bruno Mondadori. <lb/>Plana, Josep. 1983. &quot;Els Benet, una familia de <lb/>mercaders barcelonins a la primera meitat <lb/>del segle XIV.&quot; Acta Historica <lb/>et <lb/>Archaeologica Mediaevalia 1: 53-66. <lb/>Renouard, Yves. 1938. &quot;Le compagnie commerciali <lb/>fiorentine del Trecento (Dai documenti <lb/>dell&apos;Archivio Vaticano).&quot; Archivio Storico <lb/>Italiano 96(1): 41-68. <lb/>Rothbard, Murray N. 1995. Economic Thought <lb/>Before Adam Smith: An Austrian Perspective <lb/>on the History of Economic Thought, Volume <lb/>I. Aldershot and Brookfield: Edward Elgar <lb/>Publishing. <lb/>Rothbard, Murray N. 2006. Making Economic Sense. <lb/>Auburn: Ludwig van Mises Institute. 2nd ed. <lb/>Ryabova, Maria. 2018. &quot;The Account Books of the <lb/>Soranzo Fraterna (Venice 1406-1434) and <lb/>Their Place in the History of Bookkeeping.&quot; <lb/>Accounting Historians Journal 45(1): 1-27. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.2308/aahj-10580. <lb/>Sapori, Armando. 1926. La crisi de/le compagnie <lb/>mercantili def Bardi e def Peruzzi. Florence: <lb/>Leo S. Olschki, editore. <lb/>Sapori, Armando. 1944. &quot;La Compagnia dei <lb/>Frescobaldi in Inghilterra.&quot; Archivio Storico <lb/>Italiano 102(389): 3-81. <lb/>Scandura, Terri, and Ethlyn Williams. 2000. <lb/>&quot;Research Methodology in Management: <lb/>Current Practices, Trends, and Implications <lb/>for <lb/>Future <lb/>Research.&quot; <lb/>Academy of <lb/>Management Journal 43: <lb/>1248-1264. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.2307 /1556348. <lb/>Schein, Edgar. 1990. &quot;Organizational culture.&quot; <lb/>American Psychologist 45(2): 109-119. <lb/>Scherman, Matthieu. 2020. &quot;L&apos;insertion d&apos;une <lb/>banque a l&apos;etranger : le cas des Salviati a <lb/>Landres a la mi-xve siecle.&quot; In Mercados y <lb/>espacios econ6micos en el siglo XV: El mundo <lb/>de/ mercader Torralba, edited by David <lb/>Abulafia, and Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, <lb/>383-412. <lb/>Barcelona: <lb/>Universitat <lb/>de <lb/>Barcelona Edicions. <lb/>Schumpeter, Joseph. 1954. History of Economic <lb/>Analysis. New York: Oxford University Press. <lb/>Schwartz, Pedro. 2001. &quot;El comercio internacional <lb/>en la historia del pensamiento economico.&quot; <lb/>IUDEM Documento de Trabajo 2001-3. <lb/>Sesma, Jose Angel. 1982. Transformaci6n social y <lb/>revoluci6n comercial en Aragon durante la <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <page>36 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping ... <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>Baja Edad Media. Madrid: Fundacion Juan <lb/>March. <lb/>Sesma, Jose Angel. 1985. &quot;La participacion <lb/>aragonesa en la economia de la Corona. <lb/>Compafiias de comercio con chapista mixto <lb/>en la baja Edad Media.&quot; Anuario de £studios <lb/>Medievales 15: 331-344. <lb/>Sesma, Jose Angel. 2005. &quot;Centros de produccion y <lb/>redes de distribucion en las espacios <lb/>interiores de la Corona de Aragon: materias <lb/>primas y productos basicos.&quot; In La <lb/>Mediterrimia de la Corona d&apos;Arag6 segles <lb/>XIII-XVI &amp; VII Cantanari de la Sentencia <lb/>Arbitral de Torrellas 1304-2004, edited by <lb/>Rafael Narbona, vol I, 903-938. Valencia: <lb/>Universitat de Valencia. <lb/>Sesma, Jose Angel. 2006. &quot;La participacion <lb/>aragonesa en la economia de la corona. <lb/>Compafiias de comercio con capital mixto en <lb/>la Baja Edad Media.&quot; Anuario de £studios <lb/>Medievales 15: 331-343. <lb/>Sesma, Jose Angel. 2006. &quot;El comercio en la Edad <lb/>Media. Reflexiones para abrir una semana <lb/>de estudios.&quot; In El comercio en la Edad <lb/>Media, coordinated by J. A. Garcia de <lb/>Cortazar, J. I. de la Iglesia, 8. Casado, F. J. <lb/>Garcia Turza, 15-38. Logrono: Instituto de <lb/>Estudios Riojanos. <lb/>Sieveking, <lb/>Heinrich. <lb/>1901-1902. <lb/>&quot;Aus <lb/>venetianischen <lb/>Handlungsbiichern. <lb/>Ein <lb/>Beitrag zur Geschichte des Grosshandels im <lb/>15. Jahrhundert.&quot; Jahrbuch for Gesetzgebung, <lb/>Verwaltung <lb/>und <lb/>Volkswirtschaft <lb/>im <lb/>Deutschen Reich, 25, 1489-1521; ]ahrbuch <lb/>for <lb/>Gesetzgebung, <lb/>Verwaltung <lb/>und <lb/>Volkswirtschaft im Deutschen Reich 26: 189-<lb/>225. <lb/>Smith, Murphy. 2018. &quot;Luca Pacioli: The Father of <lb/>Accounting.&quot; <lb/>SSRN. <lb/>https://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.2320658. <lb/>Steensgaard, Niels. 1982. &quot;The Dutch East India <lb/>Company as an Institutional Innovation.&quot; In <lb/>Dutch Capitalism and World Capitalism, <lb/>edited by M. Aymard, 235-257. Cambridge: <lb/>Cambridge University Press. <lb/>Strang, David, and Wittrock, Christian. 2019. <lb/>&quot;Methods for the Study of Management <lb/>Ideas.&quot; In The Oxford Handbook of <lb/>Management Ideas, edited by Andrew <lb/>Sturdy, Stefan Heusinkveld, Trish Reay, and <lb/>David Strang, 86-103. Oxford: Oxford <lb/>University Press. <lb/>Sturdy, Andrew, and Peter Fleming, Peter. 2003. <lb/>&quot;Talk as Technique: A Critique of the Words <lb/>and Deeds Distinction in the Diffusion of <lb/>Customer Service Cultures.&quot; Journal of <lb/>Management Studies 40: 753-773. <lb/>Tognetti, Sergio. 2014. &quot;Nuovi documenti sul <lb/>fallimento della compagnia Frescobaldi in <lb/>Inghilterra.&quot; In Citta e campagne de/ Basso <lb/>Medioevo: studi sulla societa italiana offerti <lb/>dagli allievi a Giuliano Pinto, 69-110. <lb/>Florence: <lb/>L.S. <lb/>Olschki. <lb/>Biblioteca <lb/>dell&apos;archivio storico italiano; XXXVII. <lb/>Trave, <lb/>Ester, <lb/>and <lb/>Ivan <lb/>Casado. <lb/>2020. <lb/>&quot;Herramientas para el analisis contable de <lb/>documentacion mercantil bajomedieval: <lb/>perspectiva ontologica y gestion integrada <lb/>de datos.&quot; In Mercados y espacios econ6micos <lb/>en el siglo XV. El mundo de/ mercader <lb/>Torralba, edited by David Abulafia, and <lb/>Maria Dolores Lopez, 69-110. Barcelona: <lb/>Edicions, Universitat de Barcelona. <lb/>Trave, Ester, Maria Dolores Lopez, Ivan Casado, <lb/>Karen Alvaro, and Gerard Mari. 2018. <lb/>&quot;Research Information System (RIS): Study <lb/>case for mercantile societies through the <lb/>FENIX database.&quot; Poster presented at the <lb/>Open Science &amp; The Humanities Conference <lb/>2018, University of Barcelona, June 21. <lb/>Yannucci, Marcello. 1993. Le grandi famiglie di <lb/>Firenze: Da mercanti, artigiani, umili <lb/>popolani, da feudatari che hanno lasciato i <lb/>loro castelli, nascono, nella miracolosa <lb/>Firenze, le famiglie che entreranno nella <lb/>storia. Rome: Newton Compton. 1st ed. <lb/>Varela, Elisa. 1995. &quot;El control de las bienes: las <lb/>libros de cuentas de las mercaderes Tarasco <lb/>(1334-1346).&quot; PhD diss., University of <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping... <lb/></note>

        <page>37 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>Barcelona. <lb/>Retrieved <lb/>from <lb/>http://www.tdx.cat/handle/10803/37469. <lb/>Vila, Marsa. Maria. 1977. &quot;Algunos elementos para <lb/>el estudio de las relaciones comerciales <lb/>entre Cagliari y Barcelona en la primera <lb/>mitad del siglo XIV (&quot; Libre de compres i <lb/>vendes de Johan Benet. Caller, 1332-<lb/>1338&quot;).&quot; PhD diss., University of Barcelona. <lb/>Viu, Maria. 2019. &quot;Una gran empresa en el <lb/>Mediterraneo medieval. La compama <lb/>mercantil de Joan de Torralba y Juan de <lb/>Manariello (Barcelona-Zaragoza, 1430-<lb/>143 7) .&quot; PhD diss., University of Zaragoza. <lb/>Viu, Maria. 2020. &quot;Una compafiia, dos sedes. <lb/>Zaragoza y Barcelona en el entramado <lb/>empresarial de las sociedades mercantiles-<lb/>bancarias de Joan de Torralba y Juan de <lb/>Manariello (1425-1448).&quot; In Mercados y <lb/>espacios econ6micos en el siglo XV: el mundo <lb/>de/ mercader Joan de Torralba, edited by <lb/>David Abulafia, and Maria Dolores Lopez, <lb/>113-132. Barcelona: Edicions, Universitat de <lb/>Barcelona. <lb/>Viu, Maria. 2021. Una gran empresa en el <lb/>Mediterraneo <lb/>medieval: <lb/>la <lb/>compama <lb/>mercantil de Joan de Torralba y Juan de <lb/>Manariello <lb/>(Barcelona-Zaragoza, <lb/>1430-<lb/>1437). Madrid: Consejo Superior de <lb/>Investigaciones Cientificas. <lb/>Viu, Maria. 2022. Los libros secretos de la compafifa <lb/>Torralba-Manariel/o {Corona de Aragon, <lb/>1430-1437). Barcelona: Edicions Universitat <lb/>de Barcelona-Universita de L&apos;Aquila. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <page>38 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping ... <lb/></note>

        <div type="annex">ANNEX I. OVERVIEW OF THE COMPANIES <lb/>Headquarters -Zaragoza 19 and Barcelona; 20 <lb/>Items of commerce -mostly wheat and wool, but also to a lesser extent: leather, saffron. <lb/>Geography of operation -Crown of Aragon, Florence -Pisa, Genoa, Venice, Sardinia, South France, <lb/>Ancona, Sicily, uppercase S -Selected cases of Joan de Torralba, as a solo-trader -Tunisia, Maghreb <lb/>and Levant. 21 <lb/>Delegation -Tortosa 22 (Crown of Aragon); <lb/>Trade officers -Domingo Pandetrigo (Tortosa) Antoni Ferruz (Tortosa); <lb/>The typical contract system used by Joan de Torralba -is biennial. <lb/>TABLE Al. BRIEF OF ALL TORRALBA&apos;S COMMERCIAL ACTIVITIES BETWEEN 1425 AND 1458 <lb/>Chronology and composition of Torralba &apos;s commercial activities <lb/>Years <lb/>Membership <lb/>Capiatl <lb/>Owner&apos;s equity <lb/>Operational range <lb/>Notary <lb/>Joan de Torralba; <lb/>JF = 400011. <lb/>Corona de Aragon, Florence, <lb/>Salvador de la Faz <lb/>m5-H2Z <lb/>Fornmy de Manariello; <lb/>10.000 II. <lb/>JT = 300011. <lb/>Juan Feixas <lb/>Flvf. = 300011. <lb/>Genoa, Venice, Ancona. <lb/>{1426), Zaragoza <lb/>f ---<lb/>Joan de T01Talba: <lb/>JT = 4000 II. <lb/>Corona de Aragon, Florence, <lb/>Salvador de la Faz <lb/>1428-1430 <lb/>Fortuny de Manariello; <lb/>12.000 II. <lb/>Flvf. = 4000 II. <lb/>Juan Feixas <lb/>JF = 400011. <lb/>Genoa, Venice, Ancona. <lb/>(I 428), Zaragoza <lb/>1430-1432 <lb/>Joan de Torralba; <lb/>10.000 II. <lb/>JT = 5000 II. <lb/>Corona de Aragon, Florence, <lb/>Salvador de la Faz <lb/>Fortuny de Manariello <lb/>JF = 5000 II. <lb/>Genoa, Venice, Ancona. <lb/>(1430), Zaragoza <lb/>~ <lb/>1432-1434 <lb/>Joan de Torralba: <lb/>10.000 II. <lb/>J T = 500011. <lb/>Corona de Aragon, Florence, <lb/>Salvador de la Faz <lb/>Fortuny de Manariello <lb/>JF = 5000 II. <lb/>Genoa, Venice, Ancona. <lb/>{1432), Zaragoza <lb/>1434-1436 <lb/>Joan de Torralba: <lb/>10.000 II. <lb/>JT = 5000 II. <lb/>Corona de Aragon, Florence, <lb/>Salvador de la Faz <lb/>Fornmy de Manariello <lb/>JF = 500011. <lb/>Genoa, Venice, Ancona. <lb/>(1434), Zaragoza <lb/>~ <lb/>Joan de Torralba; <lb/>JT = 2000fl. <lb/>en Arago yen Catalunya e en <lb/>143!!-1440 <lb/>Juan de Manariello; <lb/>6000 11. <lb/>JF = 2000jl. <lb/>altres parts, si per Jes &lt;lites parts <lb/>Anton de Aldovera <lb/>Domingo Sanz; <lb/>D.S. = 1000 fl. <lb/>concodat serit&apos; <lb/>(I 438), Zaragoza <lb/>~ <lb/>Bernart d&apos; Algars <lb/>B.d&apos;A.= lOOOjl. <lb/>Joan de Torralba: <lb/>JT = 2000fl. <lb/>en Arago yen Catalunya e en <lb/>1440-1447 <lb/>Juan de Manariello; <lb/>6000 11. <lb/>JF = 2000fl. <lb/>altres parts, si per Jes &lt;lites parts <lb/>Anton de Aldovera <lb/>D0111ingo Sanz*: <lb/>D.S. = 1000 fl. <lb/>(I 440), Zaragoza <lb/>Beman d&apos; Algars• <lb/>B. d &apos;A .= 1000 fl. <lb/>concodat serit &apos; <lb/>~ <lb/>1441-1454** <lb/>fl is known rhat commercial acrivity during this period occwred, howeve1; rhere was not any regisrered company, hence rhe activiry was exclusively <lb/>individual (the falter is confirmed by personal books and fellers of Joan de Torralba) <lb/>Joan de Torralba; <lb/>J T = 469 11. 16 s. 6 d. <lb/>Joan Sabastida; <lb/>JS. = 66211. 10 s. <lb/>Sicily, the Adriatic, Munt de <lb/>Bartomeu Costa <lb/>1454-145!! <lb/>Francisco de Junyenr: <lb/>,lHll , £ ~ ,, FJ = 33 111. 5 s. <lb/>Bernart D&apos; Algars ; <lb/>B.d&apos;A. = 331 II. 5 s. <lb/>barques (Libya), Levante. <lb/>(1454), Barcelona <lb/>Joan de Riumany: <lb/>JR. = 33111. 5 s. <lb/>Sources: own elaboration. <lb/>19 We may presume that Zaragoza served as a logistical and stock hub for the company, considering that all the raw <lb/>materials for trade were directly sourced from Aragon, which we refer to as a region. <lb/>20 Barcelona may be presented as the &quot;commercial and financial hub&quot; of a company. <lb/>21 Lopez Marfa Dolores (2020), Joan de Torralba y la apertura de nuevos mercados: el negocio magrebi, Mercados y <lb/>espacios econ6micos en el siglo XV: el mundo del mercader Joan de Torralba, Mediterraneum, Universitat de Barcelona, <lb/>pp. 227-256. <lb/>22 Tortosa is a logistic hub primarily for overseas trade, being as we call it nowadays traffic hub. <lb/></div>

        <note place="footnote">Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Marfa Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping... <lb/></note>

        <page>39 <lb/></page>

        <div type="annex">How to read the table A1: <lb/>• <lb/>Fl. -florins of Aragon. If the currency originally is indicated in florins of Aragon without any <lb/>remarks about the exchange rate into Libra, we leave it unchanged. <lb/>• <lb/>Companies of [1438-1440]; [1440-144 7] operational range translation from Catalan: In Aragon <lb/>and Catalonia and other parts ( of the world), if it is agreed by the parties. <lb/>• <lb/>The company of [1454 -1458]: The original quantity is expressed in carlins de Cicilia <lb/>( currency of Sicily). The amount is -650 car/ins, and it was converted into lliura barcelonina. <lb/>FIGURE AZ. SUMMARY OF ALL TRADE AGENTS RELATED TO TORRALBA&apos;S COMPANY <lb/>TORTOSA <lb/>PISA -FLORENCE <lb/>GENOA <lb/>VENICE <lb/>Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 <lb/>DOMINGO <lb/>PANDETRIGO <lb/>JUAN ESP ARTER <lb/>GABRIEL <lb/>HOMEDES <lb/>FRANCESC <lb/>CASTELLO <lb/>FRANCESC <lb/>ALUART <lb/></div>

        <page>40 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Maria Dolores Lopez Perez, Sari Nassar I Late Medieval Administration and Bookkeeping ... <lb/></note>

        <div type="annex">ANNEX 2. THE INTERFACE OF THE DATABASE, FENIX 23 <lb/>0 :::!.&apos; ,!C:~ (Desord.) <lb/>la <lb/>Ill <lb/>Regtstros <lb/>Nuevo reoistro Elrminar <lb/>Buscar <lb/>Compamr <lb/>Presentaci6n:&apos; Actores <lb/>Ver El § <lb/>Vistaprevla <lb/>N presentaciOfl <lb/>uuy,,., .. ,_ • .., .. ........ ,.. <lb/>Documentacl6n <lb/>Recursos Graflcos <lb/>min/mas <lb/>de lnformac/6n /UM//: <lb/>Transacclones <lb/>Relaclones <lb/>Datos lntegrados <lb/>Actores <lb/>llllI3liJ ma am <lb/>islbQl!Caixa <lb/>&lt; &gt; <lb/>~; {Orn.) <lb/>R1gislto1 <lb/>•-<lb/>!Mhiittfui.P <lb/>Procedencla <lb/>G6nero f• Hombre O <lb/>Rellgl6n l•crtsUano/a O Judlola O MusulmAn/a <lb/>DOCUMENTACl6N Y CIUDADANIA <lb/>Primera aparfcl6n documental <lb/>Topogrtflco Prfnclpal) <lb/>Archtvo Llbro <lb/>FolloAslenro <lb/>ANC <lb/>690-T-721 <lb/>032r 05 <lb/>. <lb/>I• Habllante ANC 690-T-721 072v 02 <lb/>690-T-721 <lb/>083r 02 <lb/>Obtencl6n de la cludadanla <lb/>ANC <lb/>690-T-721 <lb/>108v <lb/>ANC <lb/>690-T-721 <lb/>243v <lb/>ANC <lb/>690-T-721 <lb/>ANC <lb/>690-T-721 <lb/>ACTNIOAO PROFESJONAL <lb/>Fecha Profesl6nldedlcacl6n <lb/>Mercader <lb/>2. ,~-,-4--1/2 _ 8 _ __ Me rca _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ <lb/>3. <lb/>F <lb/>•. , <lb/>PARTICIPACt6N EN SOCIEDADES MERCANTILES <lb/>Compafl/1 I Socledad mercantff <lb/>Vlncu/ac/6n I Poslc/6n <lb/>J. Felxas &amp; J. Torralba &amp; Fortuny <lb/>003 <lb/>Soci <lb/>J. Felxas &amp; J. Torralba &amp; Fortuny <lb/>003 <lb/>Cap <lb/>J. Felxas &amp; J. Torralba &amp; Juan Manarlello 002 <lb/>Soci <lb/>J. Felxas &amp; J. Torralba &amp; Juan Manarlello 002 <lb/>Cap <lb/>J. Torralba &amp; J. Manarlello (1 ) <lb/>001 <lb/>Soci <lb/>J. Torralba &amp; J . Manarlello (1 ) <lb/>001 <lb/>Cap <lb/>Ill <lb/>[ <lb/>R/1&quot;/onN~.,, <lb/>Padre <lb/>Madre <lb/>Mltrfmonfo Nombr• <lb/>ID <lb/>C6nyuge 1 rHu -so -, -. ---------01661 <lb/>I <lb/>C6nyuge 2 I <lb/>C6nyuge3 I <lb/>O.sc•ndencl• Nombr• <lb/>H!Jola 1 ,Agnes (de Torralba) de Sitges <lb/>H!Jola 2 ,Ant6nia Sabastida <lb/>HlJola3 -----------<lb/>Hljo/a4 I <lb/>&quot;ALIAS&quot; Y NOMENCLATURAS ALTERNATIVAS <lb/>Nombr• <lb/>1. <lb/>2. <lb/>3. <lb/>-<lb/>4. <lb/>• . <lb/>Palabras clave: I <lb/>l <lb/>I <lb/>ID <lb/>00276 <lb/>Do&lt;ID <lb/>Obsarvaclones <lb/>-•• Plaza <lb/>1425112/01 <lb/>Barcelona <lb/>1425/12/01 <lb/>Barcelona <lb/>1428/01/01 <lb/>Barcelona <lb/>1428/01/01 <lb/>Barcelona <lb/>1430/01/01 <lb/>Barcelona <lb/>1430/01/01 <lb/>Barcelona <lb/>Nuevo re,g111ro ElimlMr registro <lb/>Buscar <lb/>Ordenu Compamr <lb/>7 <lb/>1438 <lb/>I <lb/>Archlvo Ubro <lb/>l <lb/>Sesn <lb/>Folio As/8j <lb/>Auto <lb/>Travt <lb/>Dom! <lb/>Maur <lb/>Mod <lb/>19/9!. <lb/>f&gt;resentaCIOn: Aclores <lb/>mrormac,on pnmana• <lb/>Documentacl6n <lb/>Ver como: El § liiil <lb/>Vista previ1 <lb/>~ctor 1u <lb/>Nomore <lb/>!MCIMl•I= <lb/>Recursos Grtiflcos <lb/>Procedencla <lb/>G6nero ;:a <lb/>. cc: Hom c=c= br = • =OM &quot;uJe ;=r=========~ <lb/>I &apos; ===Fl ~;:~~l o~r: :••--= -= &quot;&quot; ::::::::::::::::::l[ C: . : =: : : =-=-: -: : -: : l ~. ===A&apos;=l =&quot;=&quot;•~rpresent ad6n <lb/>Ir <lb/>Madre ! <lb/>,c:=-J <lb/>_ <lb/>Unldades mfnlmas <lb/>de lnformaci6n IUMI)• <lb/>Transacclones <lb/>Relaclones laborales <lb/>Datos lnteqrados: <lb/>Actores <lb/>Socledades <lb/>llllI3liJ ma am <lb/>&quot;&quot;&quot;QlbQl!Caixa <lb/>AC:::JP ;!( Ob,,Soa.1i.c.iu• <lb/>Rellgl6n 1 •cr1st1anola O Judlo/a O Musulman/a <lb/>OOCUMENTACl6N Y CIUDADANlA <lb/>Primera apartcl6n documental <lb/>Fech• !1443/02/15 <lb/>ib CiudadaOO b Habltante •7 <lb/>Obtencl6n de la cludadanla <lb/>Fech• ~I -------~ <lb/>ACTIVIDAO PROFESIONAL <lb/>Topogrartco (Actor Prlnclpal) <lb/>PARTICIPACl6N EN SOCIEOADES MERCANTILE$ <lb/>*lrlmonlo Nombr• <lb/>ID <lb/>,=.ct,a <lb/>C6nyuge 1 i&apos;-1 = ~-------~l i ____ l l r = ~--~I <lb/>C6nyuge2 I <lb/>IL. : j1 <lb/>C6nyuge 3 I <lb/>I [ :: __ :_. __ JI <lb/>O.scendenela Nombr• <lb/>ID <lb/>Hljola 1 &apos; <lb/>I ----------~, 1-•-•---•-•--] <lb/>Hljola2 ; <lb/>r-<lb/>1 <lb/>HIJola 3 I <lb/>I r:-~~l <lb/>Hljo/a 4 I <lb/>I C-:::-:::::-] <lb/>&quot;ALIAS&quot; Y NOMENCLATURAS ALTERNATIVAS <lb/>Palabras clave: imlsser <lb/>Observaclones <lb/>Auto <lb/>fMi Ur <lb/>i <lb/>l--, <lb/>Mod <lb/>~/~ <lb/>23 The database is of private use by the Medieval and Post-medieval Archeology Research Group at the University of <lb/>Barcelona (GRAMP-Med) <lb/>Journal of Evolutionary Studies in Business I eISSN: 2385-7137 <lb/>Early Views I October 2024 I https://doi.org/10.1344/jesb.44656 </div>


	</text>

</TEI>