<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>The membrane-cytoplasmic linker defines activity of FtsH <lb/>proteases in Pseudomonas aeruginosa clone C <lb/>Received for publication, August 12, 2023, and in revised form, December 22, 2023 Published, Papers in Press, January 3, 2024, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jbc.2023.105622 <lb/>Gina D. Mawla 1 , Shady M. Kamal 2 , Lian-Ying Cao 2 , Pasi Purhonen 3 , Hans Hebert 3 , Robert T. Sauer 1 , <lb/>Tania A. Baker 1, * , ‡ , and Ute Römling 2, * , ‡ <lb/>From the 1 Department of Biology, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Massachusetts, USA; 2 Department of <lb/>Microbiology, Tumor and Cell Biology, Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden; 3 Department of Biomedical Engineering and <lb/>Health Systems, KTH Royal Institute of Technology, Huddinge, Sweden <lb/>Reviewed by members of the JBC Editorial Board. Edited by Chris Whitfield <lb/>Pandemic Pseudomonas aeruginosa clone C strains encode <lb/>two inner-membrane associated ATP-dependent FtsH pro-<lb/>teases. PaftsH1 is located on the core genome and supports cell <lb/>growth and intrinsic antibiotic resistance, whereas PaftsH2, a <lb/>xenolog acquired through horizontal gene transfer from a <lb/>distantly related species, is unable to functionally replace <lb/>PaftsH1. We show that purified PaFtsH2 degrades fewer sub-<lb/>strates than PaFtsH1. Replacing the 31-amino acid-extended <lb/>linker region of PaFtsH2 spanning from the C-terminal end of <lb/>the transmembrane helix-2 to the first seven highly divergent <lb/>residues of the cytosolic AAA+ ATPase module with the corre-<lb/>sponding region of PaFtsH1 improves hybrid-enzyme substrate <lb/>processing in vitro and enables PaFtsH2 to substitute for <lb/>PaFtsH1 in vivo. Electron microscopy indicates that the identity <lb/>of this linker sequence influences FtsH flexibility. We find <lb/>membrane-cytoplasmic (MC) linker regions of PaFtsH1 char-<lb/>acteristically glycine-rich compared to those from FtsH2. <lb/>Consequently, introducing three glycines into the membrane-<lb/>proximal end of PaFtsH2&apos;s MC linker is sufficient to elevate its <lb/>activity in vitro and in vivo. Our findings establish that the effi-<lb/>ciency of substrate processing by the two PaFtsH isoforms de-<lb/>pends on MC linker identity and suggest that greater linker <lb/>flexibility and/or length allows FtsH to degrade a wider spectrum <lb/>of substrates. As PaFtsH2 homologs occur across bacterial phyla, <lb/>we hypothesize that FtsH2 is a latent enzyme but may recognize <lb/>specific substrates or is activated in specific contexts or biological <lb/>niches. The identity of such linkers might thus play a more <lb/>determinative role in the functionality of and physiological <lb/>impact by FtsH proteases than previously thought. <lb/></front>

			<body>FtsH, a membrane-bound protease and member of the <lb/>AAA+ (ATPases associated with diverse cellular activities) <lb/>superfamily of ATPases, is widespread in prokaryotes and in <lb/>eukaryotic organelles (1-3). Although some bacteria encode <lb/>five distinct classes of AAA+ proteases, FtsH is typically the <lb/>only protease that is biologically essential, is the most phylo-<lb/>genetically conserved, and is the only inner membrane-<lb/>associated AAA+ protease in most Gram-negative bacteria <lb/>(4). FtsH is an essential modulator of lipid metabolism in <lb/>Escherichia coli and is important for growth, virulence, pro-<lb/>duction of secondary metabolites, biofilm formation, and for-<lb/>mation of persister cells in Pseudomonas aeruginosa and many <lb/>other bacteria (5-10). Model bacteria, including P. aeruginosa, <lb/>typically encode just one FtsH enzyme. The pandemic clone C <lb/>group of P. aeruginosa strains, found at high prevalence in <lb/>acute and chronic infections and the aquatic habitat (11, 12), <lb/>however, is an example of a distinct group of organisms that <lb/>have undergone recent &apos;ftsH-gene expansion&apos; as it carries a <lb/>second FtsH proteinase introduced by horizontal transfer (5, <lb/>13). <lb/>Like other AAA+ proteases, FtsH functions as a hexamer <lb/>with an axial channel that serves as a conduit for polypeptide <lb/>translocation into a degradation chamber. A prototypical FtsH <lb/>subunit begins with a short N-terminal cytoplasmic segment, <lb/>followed by a transmembrane helix (TM1), a periplasmic <lb/>domain, another transmembrane helix (TM2), a cytoplasmic <lb/>AAA+ substrate unfolding/translocation module, and a cyto-<lb/>plasmic M41-family peptidase domain (Figs. 1A and S1). A <lb/>cytosolic segment of 25-residues connects TM2 with the <lb/>AAA+ module and hereafter is called the MC or membrane-<lb/>cytosolic linker. As FtsH is membrane-tethered, it has been <lb/>suggested that this linker may help gate substrate entry via the <lb/>conserved FVG pore (3). Together, these distinct regions of <lb/>FtsH are required for its function (14-20). <lb/>FtsH recognizes protein substrates by binding to N-or <lb/>C-terminal degrons, with the amino acid sequences deter-<lb/>mining the degradation rate, and, less commonly, to internal <lb/>disordered regions (10, 14, 21, 22). One group of FtsH sub-<lb/>strates includes incomplete proteins tagged with a C-terminal <lb/>ssrA degron, a short predominantly nonpolar peptide <lb/>sequence attached to nascent chains via its transfer-messenger <lb/>RNA-mediated stalled ribosome rescue (21, 23, 24). FtsH <lb/>participates in membrane-protein quality control by degrading <lb/>misassembled and misfolded inner membrane proteins and <lb/>regulates proteotoxic stress by controlling intracellular levels <lb/>of the RpoH/σ 32 heat-shock transcription factor (5, 25-29). In <lb/>some cases, adaptor proteins influence the degradation effi-<lb/>ciency and specificity of FtsH proteases. For example, in E. coli, <lb/></body>

			<front> ‡ These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/>* For correspondence: Tania A. Baker, tabaker@mit.edu; Ute Römling, Ute. <lb/>Romling@ki.se. <lb/>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>J. Biol. Chem. (2024) 300(2) 105622 1 <lb/>© 2024 THE AUTHORS. Published by Elsevier Inc on behalf of American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology. This is an open access article under the CC <lb/>BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/></front>

			<body>AAA+ Unfoldase <lb/>N <lb/>C <lb/>0 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/>1,000 <lb/>Retention volume (mL) <lb/>ATP hydrolysis <lb/>(min -1 <lb/>FtsH <lb/>6 <lb/>-1 <lb/>) <lb/>β-casein: -<lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>mAU <lb/>mAU <lb/>PaFtsH1-His 6 <lb/>PaFtsH2-His 6 <lb/>A <lb/>50 <lb/>75 <lb/>37 <lb/>25 <lb/>kDa <lb/>Arc-st11-ssrA <lb/>λcI N -ssrA <lb/>β-casein <lb/>Time (hr): <lb/>75 <lb/>50 <lb/>37 <lb/>25 <lb/>20 <lb/>75 <lb/>50 <lb/>37 <lb/>25 <lb/>20 <lb/>50 <lb/>75 <lb/>kDa: <lb/>EcFtsH <lb/>PaFtsH1 PaFtsH2 <lb/>FtsH <lb/>0 1 2 <lb/>0 1 2 <lb/>0 1 2 <lb/>0 1 2 0 1 2 0 1 2 <lb/>Time (hr): <lb/>kDa <lb/>kDa <lb/>Time (min): 0 15 30 <lb/>0 15 30 60 <lb/>PaFtsH1 <lb/>PaFtsH2 <lb/>PaFtsH2 <lb/>EcFtsH <lb/>PaFtsH1 <lb/>PaFtsH2 <lb/>Arc-st11-ssrA <lb/>N <lb/>C <lb/>N <lb/>C <lb/>AAA+ Unfoldase <lb/>Peptidase <lb/>Transmembrane <lb/>Periplasmic <lb/>DNTR <lb/>MC linker <lb/>Cytoplasm <lb/>Periplasm <lb/>B <lb/>660 <lb/>150 <lb/>45 <lb/>MW standard (kDa): <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>60 <lb/>E <lb/>F <lb/>C <lb/>M41 Peptidase <lb/>N <lb/>DNTR <lb/>TM1 <lb/>TM2 <lb/>MC <lb/>Peri <lb/>FtsH 6 <lb/>M <lb/>M <lb/>M <lb/>kDa: <lb/>50 <lb/>75 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 5 <lb/>3 0 <lb/>4 5 <lb/>6 0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>Time (min) <lb/>Percent <lb/>β-casein remaining <lb/>PaFtsH1 <lb/>PaFtsH2 <lb/>PaFtsH1 <lb/>PaFtsH2 <lb/>660 <lb/>150 <lb/>45 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>1.25 <lb/>1.50 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>M <lb/>M <lb/>CK <lb/>CK <lb/>CK <lb/>ftsH2 <lb/>P. aeruginosa SG17M clone C <lb/>Transmissible Locus of Stress Tolerance (tLST) <lb/>Core genome <lb/>1 kb <lb/>ftsH1 <lb/>0 <lb/>25 <lb/>50 <lb/>75 <lb/>100 <lb/>125 <lb/>150 <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>7+ <lb/>MC 7+ <lb/>G <lb/>PaFtsH1 <lb/>FtsH <lb/>15 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>10 <lb/>Figure 1. Purified hexameric PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 have distinct biochemical activities in vitro. A, schematic (top) and linear representation (bottom) of <lb/>a prototypical hexameric FtsH enzyme in a bacterial cell with key regions labeled. The DNTR spans the N-terminus, TM1, periplasmic domain, TM2, MC linker, <lb/>and the first seven amino acids in the AAA+ ATPase module (MC 7+ ). B, schematic of genetic loci of PaftsH genes in Pseudomonas aeruginosa SG17M clone C <lb/>strain. PaFtsH1 is encoded on the core genome of SG17M (blue), and PaFtsH2 (purple) is encoded on a horizontally acquired genomic island termed the <lb/>transmissible locus of stress tolerance (tLST) which is distinctive in SG17M clone C. Names of genes in the vicinity of ftsH1 and ftsH2 are labeled in Fig. S2A. In <lb/>dark gray, P. aeruginosa SG17M specific tLST genes; light gray, additional tLST genes present in other tLST classes. C, molecular weight determination of <lb/>PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 purified from Escherichia coli. Purified PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 were run on an analytical Superdex 200 3.2/3.0 gel filtration column (left) <lb/>and separated by a 4 to 20% gradient SDS-PAGE in a two-fold dilution series (insets). Molecular weights of PaFtsH enzymes were consistent with hexamer <lb/>formation plus 3.5 NP-40 micelles per PaFtsH1-6xHis hexamer (PaFtsH1 6 -6xHis: 743,373 Da; one NP-40 micelle: 90 Da) and 2.7 NP-40 micelles per <lb/>PaFtsH2-6xHis hexamer (PaFtsH2-6xHis: 659,792 Da). Theoretical molecular weights of 6xHis-tagged PaFtsH monomers: PaFtsH1-6xHis: 70,886 Da; PaFtsH2-<lb/>6xHis: 69,521 Da. D, hydrolysis of ATP (5 mM) by PaFtsH1 (blue bars) or PaFtsH2 (purple bars) (0.43 μM) in the presence or absence of the substrate β-casein <lb/>(40 μM) at 40 C. ATP hydrolysis rates by PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 increased in the presence of β-casein (two-tailed Mann-Whitney U test (*p &lt; 0.05)). The rate <lb/>of ATP hydrolysis by β-casein in the absence of enzyme was negligible (0.0032 ± 0.0004 ATP min -1 ). E, Forty micromolar β-casein was incubated at 40 C <lb/>with PaFtsH1 or PaFtsH2 (0.43 μM), and degradation kinetics were monitored by a 4 to 20% gradient SDS-PAGE. Data points are averages of three in-<lb/>dependent replicates ± SD (bottom). M: Molecular weight marker taken from the PaFtsH2 casein degradation gel. F, the N-terminal domain of phage λ <lb/>repressor (λcI N ) with a C-terminal ssrA degron tag (λcI N -ssrA; 15 μM) was incubated at 40 C with EcFtsH, PaFtsH1, or PaFtsH2 (3.04 μM). λcI N -ssrA PDB: 1LM <lb/>(82). M: Molecular weight marker. G, SsrA degron-tagged Arc repressor-(6 x H)KNQHE (Arc-st11-ssrA; 15 μM) was incubated at 40 C with EcFtsH, PaFtsH1, or <lb/>PaFtsH2 (3.53 μM). Arc-st11-ssrA PDB: 1ARR. M: Molecular weight marker. D-G, all reactions used C-terminal 6xHis-tagged proteins. E-G, all reactions <lb/>contained 5 mM ATP and a creatine kinase (CK)-based ATP regeneration system (83). DNTR, diverse N-terminal region; MC, membrane-cytoplasmic; MC 7+ , <lb/>membrane-cytoplasmic linker plus seven C-terminal amino acids into the AAA+ ATPase module boundary; MW, Molecular weight; M, Molecular weight <lb/>marker; mAU, milli-Absorbance Unit; MC 7+ , membrane-cytoplasmic plus next seven C-terminal amino acids; Peri, periplasmic domain; TM1, transmembrane <lb/>helix 1; TM2, transmembrane helix 2. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Divergent FtsH protease functionality <lb/></note>

			<page>2</page>

			<note place="footnote">J. Biol. Chem. (2024) 300(2) 105622 <lb/></note>


			<body>the heat shock transcription factor RpoH requires the co-<lb/>chaperone DnaK and the signal recognition particle to be <lb/>efficiently processed by core genome FtsH (30-32). On the <lb/>other hand, the periplasmic membrane proteins, HflK and <lb/>HflC, interact with FtsH (33) and negatively regulate proteol-<lb/>ysis of the protein translocase subunit SecY (28) and the λ <lb/>transcriptional regulator cII (34). Other adaptor proteins of <lb/>FtsH influence degradation of LpxC, the first committed <lb/>enzyme in lipopolysaccharide biosynthesis, and processing of <lb/>the polypeptide toxin Colicin D (8, 35). <lb/>As all clone C strains, the virulent aquatic isolate of <lb/>P. aeruginosa SG17M carries a transmissible locus of stress <lb/>tolerance (tLST) important for survival under multiple stress <lb/>conditions that encodes a xenolog of FtsH called PaFtsH2 <lb/>((Figs. 1B and S2A); (12, 13)). We previously found that <lb/>deletion of the core genome FtsH copy, PaftsH1, causes a <lb/>substantial growth deficiency and affects multiple other phe-<lb/>notypes including secondary metabolite secretion and anti-<lb/>microbial resistance, whereas PaFtsH2 appears to act primarily <lb/>as a low-level backup enzyme under the growth and stress <lb/>conditions tested (5, 36). Here, we investigate the molecular <lb/>basis of the differential activities and impacts of PaFtsH1 and <lb/>PaFtsH2. In vivo observations indicated that the N-terminal <lb/>region of the PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 homologs, which include <lb/>TM1, TM2, the periplasmic domain, the MC linker, and the <lb/>first seven amino acids of the AAA+ ATPase module, is <lb/>necessary and sufficient to determine function of the two <lb/>distinct PaFtsH enzymes in vivo. Using phenotypic and <lb/>biochemical assays, we identified a 32-amino acid stretch <lb/>composed of the MC linker (25-amino acids long) and first <lb/>seven resides of the AAA+ ATPase module (referred to herein <lb/>as the membrane-cytoplasmic plus next seven C-terminal <lb/>amino acids (MC 7+ ) linker region) as a determinative element <lb/>of PaFtsH function. Even more, inserting just three glycines <lb/>into the PaFtsH2 linker to mimic the glycine-rich feature of the <lb/>PaFtsH1 sequence results in a &apos;gain-of-function&apos; phenotype. <lb/>Notably, purified PaFtsH2 hybrids carrying PaFtsH1-like MC <lb/>linker alterations gain proteolytic activity against model sub-<lb/>strates in vitro. We propose a model that explains how the <lb/>composition, length, and flexibility of the MC linker could <lb/>modulate PaFtsH enzyme function by affecting the position <lb/>and mobility of the cytoplasmic AAA+ protease with respect <lb/>to the plane of the membrane and control the accessibility of <lb/>specific substrates to the AAA+ axial channel during the <lb/>initiation of efficient proteolysis. <lb/>Results <lb/>The N-terminal regions of PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 are highly <lb/>divergent <lb/>To identify the molecular mechanism of the differential <lb/>activity of PaFtsH2 compared to PaFtsH1 observed in vivo (5), <lb/>we first assessed the amino acid sequence conservation of the <lb/>individual domains. The overall sequence identity between <lb/>PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 is 45%, with the most conserved regions <lb/>being the AAA+ module and the Zn 2+ -dependent M41 <lb/>peptidase domain (54% identity). Signature motifs for substrate <lb/>processing: the pore motif FVG for substrate entry and motifs <lb/>required for catalytic activities of the AAA+ module (Walker A <lb/>and Walker B motifs) and the M41 peptidase domain (Zn 2+ -<lb/>binding motif and catalytic base) are completely conserved in <lb/>PaFtsH2 and PaFtsH1 for both domains (Figs. 1A and S1). <lb/>Presence of these and other consensus residues therefore <lb/>suggests that any functional differences between these two <lb/>multidomain enzymes would not be attributed to differences <lb/>in these motifs. We found, however, the N-terminal 150 <lb/>amino acids to be most divergent (24% identity) (Fig. S1). We <lb/>refer to this region from the N terminus through the first β-<lb/>strand of the AAA+ module as the divergent N-terminal re-<lb/>gion (DNTR) (Figs. 1A and S1). <lb/>Purified PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 assemble as hexameric ATPases <lb/>and proteases <lb/>To compare the intrinsic biochemical activities of PaFtsH1 <lb/>and PaFtsH2, we overexpressed each His-tagged enzyme in <lb/>E. coli and purified them from cell membranes according to a <lb/>protocol previously established for E. coli FtsH (24). Each <lb/>enzyme eluted from an analytical size-exclusion column as a <lb/>single peak, with a molecular weight expected for a hexamer <lb/>bound to detergent micelles (Fig. 1C). Both enzymes were <lb/>active ATPases, with ATP hydrolysis by PaFtsH2 being nine-<lb/>fold faster than by PaFtsH1 under standard conditions <lb/>(Figs. 1D and S2B) despite being the &apos;silent&apos; gene product, a <lb/>latent enzyme with no explicit proteolytic activity in vivo and <lb/>in most in vitro instances ((5); and as described below). The <lb/>temperature optimum for ATPase activity was 45 C and 55 C <lb/>for PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2, respectively, which is above the <lb/>standard and maximum growth temperature, 30 C-37 C and <lb/>42 C, respectively, for P. aeruginosa. Addition of β-casein, a <lb/>commonly used protease substrate with a molten-globule <lb/>structure, stimulated the PaFtsH1 ATPase activity about <lb/>two-fold but only marginally stimulated that of PaFtsH2 <lb/>(Fig. 1D). Both enzymes effectively degraded β-casein with <lb/>PaFtsH1 degradation rate being slightly (two-fold) faster <lb/>than PaFtsH2 (Fig. 1E). Thus, purified PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 <lb/>are active as ATPases and proteases in vitro. <lb/>PaFtsH2 fails to degrade ssrA-tagged proteins <lb/>E. coli FtsH degrades protein substrates with C-terminal <lb/>ssrA tags (Fig. 1, F and G; (24, 37)). SsrA is a well-recognized <lb/>autonomous degron that can be added to essentially any <lb/>protein, rendering it a substrate. In the case of SsrA-tagged <lb/>peptides subjected to degradation by FtsH protease, addi-<lb/>tional cofactors that aid processing do not seem to be required. <lb/>Thus, we tested PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 degradation of λcI N -<lb/>ssrA, the N-terminal DNA-binding domain of the phage λ <lb/>repressor cI (λcI N ) with the E. coli 11-amino acid ssrA tag <lb/>(-AANDENYALAA) (38). As assayed by an 4 to 20% SDS-<lb/>PAGE gel, PaFtsH1 degraded this substrate over the course <lb/>of 1 h, whereas PaFtsH2 was essentially inactive in degra-<lb/>dation of this substrate (Fig. 1F). Notably, PaFtsH1 did not <lb/>degrade λcI N lacking the ssrA degron (Fig. S3A). PaFtsH1, but <lb/>not PaFtsH2, also degraded the Podoviridae family phage P22 <lb/>Divergent FtsH protease functionality <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">J. Biol. Chem. (2024) 300(2) 105622</note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>


			<body>Arc repressor model protein substrate Arc-st11 containing a <lb/>P. aeruginosa ssrA tag (AANDDNYALAA; Fig. 1G). Note that <lb/>throughout this work, we found that PaFtsH1 efficiently <lb/>recognized both the P. aeruginosa sequence-specific ssrA-tag <lb/>(-AANDDNYALAA) and the E. coli ssrA sequence (-AAN-<lb/>DENYALAA), which differ by just one amino acid. <lb/>PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 have similar peptide-binding profiles <lb/>As degrons are often unstructured peptide loops exposed on <lb/>a protein surface, measuring binding of an AAA+ M41 pro-<lb/>tease to immobilized peptide arrays can be a useful method for <lb/>identifying and characterizing degron sequences of substrates. <lb/>However, these binding experiments must be followed up by <lb/>functional assays to establish the role of identified sequences in <lb/>protease recognition of the intact protein. To rapidly investi-<lb/>gate if PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 had similar or distinct peptide-<lb/>binding properties, we synthesized arrays of 12-residue pep-<lb/>tides from known or probable FtsH substrates from <lb/>P. aeruginosa. Known PaFtsH1 substrates include RpoH and <lb/>the phenazine biosynthesis enzyme PhzC1/2 (identical), and <lb/>PaFtsH1 or PaFtsH2 candidate substrates include phospho-<lb/>glucosamine mutase GlmM, the septum-site determining <lb/>protein MinD, and the signal peptidase LepB1, respectively (5, <lb/>29). Subsequently, peptide arrays were probed with 35 S-<lb/>PaFtsH1 and 35 S-PaFtsH2 (Figs. 2, A and B, S4, and Table S1). <lb/>Radiolabeled PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 bound to these arrays with <lb/>very similar profiles, indicating that both enzymes interact <lb/>with the immobilized linear peptides in the same manner. <lb/>Note that this approach revealed strong binding of E. coli FtsH <lb/>and both P. aeruginosa enzymes also to a sequence in RpoH <lb/>(region 3, Fig. 2, A and B) that is known to be important for <lb/>degradation in E. coli (39, 40). These findings indicate that at <lb/>least some of the protein-protein interactions identified here <lb/>are involved in substrate recognition by these enzymes and <lb/>that the linear epitopes of the substrates are recognized in an <lb/>identical way by the two enzymes. <lb/>The C-terminal region of the DNTR determines in vivo impact <lb/>We have reported previously that although both PaFtsH1 <lb/>and PaFtsH2 are produced in exponential phase in rich and <lb/>nutrient-poor medium (with PaFtsH2 even showing enhanced <lb/>production in stationary phase, while PaFtsH1 production <lb/>highly diminished), PaFtsH1 plays an almost exclusive role in <lb/>supporting robust growth, as measured by colony size and <lb/>growth rate (5). Figure 2C recalls that leaky expression of <lb/>plasmid-based PaftsH1 but not PaftsH2 under the translational <lb/>control of the PaftsH2 Shine-Dalgarno sequence rescues the <lb/>tiny colony size phenotype of SG17M ΔftsH1ΔftsH2. Of note, <lb/>plasmid-based production of any of the two proteins does not <lb/>affect plating efficiency as equal dilutions starting from the <lb/>same OD 600 yielded the same number of colonies irre-<lb/>spectively of colony size and growth rate (5). We thus used <lb/>colony size as the phenotypic assay to estimate alterations in <lb/>PaFtsH1-linked functionality as neither PaFtsH1 nor PaFtsH2 <lb/>protein production are directly correlated with functionality <lb/>(5). To determine if DNTR, the most distinct region between <lb/>these two proteins, determines functionality under these <lb/>experimental conditions, we expressed constructs containing <lb/>residues 1 to 151 of PaFtsH1 (PaFtsH1 DNTR) appended to <lb/>the &quot;body&quot; of PaFtsH2 (PaFtsH2 NFtsH1 ) or residues 1 to 154 of <lb/>PaFtsH2 (PaFtsH2 DNTR) attached to &quot;body&quot; of PaFtsH1 <lb/>(PaFtsH1 NFtsH2 ) under translational control of an identical <lb/>PaftsH2 Shine-Dalgarno sequence in SG17M ΔftsH1ΔftsH2. <lb/>Notably, PaFtsH2 NFtsH1 rescued the colony size defect whereas <lb/>PaFtsH1 NFtsH2 did not (Fig. 2, C-E), indicating that the DTNR <lb/>of ftsH1 can function with the AAA+ module and M41 <lb/>peptidase of PaftsH2 to support robust growth, while the <lb/>DTNR of PaFtsH2 even in combination with the body of <lb/>PaFtsH1 does not promote functionality. To identify the <lb/>minimal regions of the PaFtsH1 DTNR that contribute most <lb/>strongly to PaFtsH functionality, we constructed and tested <lb/>additional PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 chimeras with iteratively <lb/>swapped DTNR segments informed by the predicted bound-<lb/>aries for the two transmembrane helices and the periplasmic <lb/>domains (Figs. 2, D and E and S1; (5)). We found that for <lb/>PaFtsH2, restoration of colony size was largely determined by <lb/>an amino acid stretch of PaFtsH1 that included the MC linker <lb/>and the N-terminal seven residues of β-strand 1 in the AAA+ <lb/>module (see especially Fig. 2E, construct a compared to <lb/>PaFtsH2 NFtsH1 ). On the other hand, the equivalent amino acid <lb/>stretch from PaFtsH2 abolished the restoration of colony size <lb/>by PaFtsH1 (Fig. 2E, construct d compared to PaFtsH1 NFtsH2 ). <lb/>We subsequently defined the 32-amino acid long sequence of <lb/>PaFtsH1 from Met 120 to Thr 151 and the corresponding 31-<lb/>amino acid long sequence of PaFtsH2 from Phe 124 to Val 154 <lb/>as the MC 7+ linker (Figs. 3A and S1). <lb/>MC 7+ sequences from PaFtsH1 activate degradation by <lb/>PaFtsH2 <lb/>To unambiguously assess the contribution of the MC 7+ to <lb/>functionality, we constructed, expressed, and purified a variant <lb/>called PaFtsH2 H1-link-32 containing the 32-residue MC 7+ region <lb/>from PaFtsH1 with all other amino acid sequences derived from <lb/>PaFtsH2 (Fig. 3, A and B). Strikingly, PaFtsH2 H1-link-32 degraded <lb/>λcI N -ssrA, whereas the parental PaFtsH2 protease did not. <lb/>PaFtsH2 H1-link-32 also degraded the λcI N -ssrA substrate at a rate <lb/>faster than PaFtsH1 in an ATP-and ssrA tag-dependent manner <lb/>(Figs. 3C and S3, A and B). However, PaFtsH2 H1-link-32 , like its <lb/>PaFtsH2 parent, was unable to degrade Arc-st11-ssrA (Fig. 3D), <lb/>suggesting that the MC 7+ region from PaFtsH1 is not directly <lb/>involved in recognition of the ssrA tag or that such recognition <lb/>is highly dependent on features of the attached protein. <lb/>PaFtsH2 H1-link-32 degradation of λcI N -ssrA generated a 5.7 kDa <lb/>product (marked by asterisks in Figs. 3, C and F and S3, A and B) <lb/>that mass spectrometry identified as residues 1 to 51 of λcI N -<lb/>ssrA, as expected if proteolysis initiates from the C-terminal <lb/>ssrA degron of this substrate (Fig. S3C). The presence of this <lb/>degradation product could represent a difference in peptide-<lb/>cleavage specificity within the protease chambers of PaFtsH1 <lb/>and PaFtsH2 or a difference in substrate processing by the <lb/>AAA+ modules of these enzymes. Indeed, it has been observed <lb/>that FtsH can perform limited proteolytic cleavage (35). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Divergent FtsH protease functionality <lb/></note>

			<page>4</page>

			<note place="footnote">J. Biol. Chem. (2024) 300(2) 105622 <lb/></note>


			<body>We continued with the linker dissection approach, con-<lb/>structed hybrid open reading frames, and purified corre-<lb/>sponding enzymes containing a hybrid PaFtsH2 with just 12 or <lb/>10 residues of the MC linker of PaFtsH1 replacing a corre-<lb/>sponding PaFtsH2 linker sequence (Fig. 3B). These amino acid <lb/>sequences encompassed the characteristic glycine-rich part of <lb/>the PaFtsH1 linker from Gly125 to Met134/Phe136, respec-<lb/>tively. Importantly, unlike the parental PaFtsH2, both chimeras <lb/>degraded λcI N -ssrA like PaFtsH2 H1-link-32 with a not substan-<lb/>tially slower initial kinetics but again not to completion <lb/>(Figs. 3, F and G and S3A). The MC 7+ linker of PaFtsH1 is <lb/>predicted by computational methods to be more disordered/ <lb/>SG17M EV <lb/>∆ftsH1∆ftsH2 EV <lb/>10 -1 10 -2 10 -3 10 -4 10 -5 10 -6 <lb/>PaFtsH2 <lb/>PaFtsH1 <lb/>1-24 <lb/>Construct <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>f <lb/>Amino acids <lb/>from PaFtsH1 <lb/>Amino acids <lb/>from PaFtsH2 <lb/>29-626 <lb/>1-97 <lb/>1-118 <lb/>1-151 (DNTR) <lb/>101-626 <lb/>123-626 <lb/>155-626 <lb/>25-639 <lb/>1-28 <lb/>1-100 <lb/>1-122 <lb/>1-154 (DNTR) <lb/>152-639 <lb/>119-639 <lb/>98-639 <lb/>PaFtsH2 NFtsH1 <lb/>PaFtsH1 NFtsH2 <lb/>c <lb/>b <lb/>a <lb/>f <lb/>e <lb/>d <lb/>PaFtsH1 <lb/>PaFtsH2 <lb/>10 -1 10 -2 10 -3 10 -4 10 -5 10 -6 <lb/>10 -1 10 -2 10 -3 10 -4 10 -5 10 -6 <lb/>PaFtsH2 NFtsH1 <lb/>PaFtsH1 NFtsH2 <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>++++ <lb/>+++ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>++ <lb/>+++ <lb/>-<lb/>++ <lb/>++ <lb/>+++ <lb/>+++ <lb/>++ <lb/>++ <lb/>+ <lb/>SG17M ∆ftsH1∆ftsH2 <lb/>SG17M ∆ftsH1∆ftsH2 <lb/>SG17M ∆ftsH1∆ftsH2 <lb/>B <lb/>1 <lb/>31 <lb/>61 <lb/>91 <lb/>121 <lb/>30 <lb/>60 <lb/>90 <lb/>120 <lb/>137 <lb/>1 <lb/>31 <lb/>61 <lb/>91 <lb/>121 <lb/>30 <lb/>60 <lb/>90 <lb/>120 <lb/>137 <lb/>Probe: 35 S-PaFtsH1 <lb/>Probe: 35 S-PaFtsH2 <lb/>A <lb/>Probe: 35 S-EcFtsH <lb/>1 <lb/>31 <lb/>61 <lb/>91 <lb/>121 <lb/>30 <lb/>60 <lb/>90 <lb/>120 <lb/>137 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>N 1 <lb/>C 284 <lb/>C 284 <lb/>180°1 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>N 1 <lb/>AAA+ Unfoldase M41 Peptidase <lb/>N <lb/>C <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>Construct: <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>f <lb/>PaFtsH2 NFtsH1 <lb/>DNTR <lb/>PaFtsH1 NFtsH2 <lb/>2 <lb/>M T <lb/>PaFtsH1 <lb/>PaFtsH2 <lb/>PaFtsH2 <lb/>PaFtsH1 <lb/>1 <lb/>M <lb/>T <lb/>C <lb/>Peri <lb/>C <lb/>M <lb/>+ <lb/>7 <lb/>PaRpoH <lb/>2 <lb/>284 <lb/>MTTSLQPVHALVPGANLEAYVHSVNSIPLLSPEQERELAERLFYQ <lb/>QDLEAARQMVLAHLRFVVHIAKSYSGYGLAQADLIQEGNVGLMKA <lb/>VKRFNPEMGVRLVSFAVHWIKAEIHEFILRNWRIVKVATTKAQRK <lb/>LFFNLRSQKKRLAWLNNEEVHRVAESLGVEPREVREMESRLTGQD <lb/>MAFDPAADADDESAYQSPAHYLEDHRYDPARQLEDADWSDSSSAN <lb/>LHEALEGLDERSRDILQQRWLSEEKATLHDLAEKYNVSAERIRQL <lb/>EKNAMSKLKGRILA <lb/>1 <lb/>46 <lb/>91 <lb/>136 <lb/>181 <lb/>226 <lb/>271 <lb/>45 <lb/>90 <lb/>135 <lb/>180 <lb/>225 <lb/>270 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>Figure 2. PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 have similar in vitro peptide-binding profiles and differentially affect in vivo colony size. A, peptide array of the RpoH <lb/>sequence from Pseudomonas aeruginosa (PaRpoH; P42378|RpoH_PSEAE; 1-284, sliding window of 12 amino acids with a step size of two amino acids <lb/>towards the C-terminus with each spot) probed with 1 μM 35 S-EcFtsH (top), 35 S-PaFtsH1 (middle), or 35 S-PaFtsH2 (bottom) in the presence of 1.25 mM ATPγS. <lb/>Peptide sequences corresponding to each spot are listed in Table S1. Circled spots indicate peptides containing residues A132 and/or K135, which were <lb/>previously shown to be important for in vivo Escherichia coli FtsH (EcFtsH) binding to RpoH (conserved RpoH residues from E. coli are A131 and K134; (39, <lb/>40)). B, amino acid sequence of PaRpoH (top). Residues in red indicate regions bound by 35 S-EcFtsH, 35 S-PaFtsH1, 35 S-PaFtsH2. Residues in blue correspond to <lb/>A132 and K135 (see panel A legend). FtsH-bound sequences identified by peptide blotting are mapped on the predicted PaRpoH structure (bottom; (72)) <lb/>and numbered as on the sequence above. C, colony sizes of wild-type P. aeruginosa SG17M, the SG17M ΔftsH1ΔftsH2 double deletion and SG17M <lb/>ΔftsH1ΔftsH2 strains complemented with either an empty pJN105 expression vector (EV) or pJN105-derived expression of PaFtsH1 or PaFtsH2. PaftsH1 and <lb/>PaftsH2 genes had been cloned into the expression vector pJN105 under the translational regulation of the PaftsH2 Shine Dalgarno (SD) sequence. &quot;+&quot; and <lb/>&quot;-&quot; scoring system relates the qualitative degree of colony growth of a particular strain genotype relative to that of SG17M EV (++++; wild-type colony <lb/>growth) or SG17M ΔftsH1ΔftsH2 (-; very poor colony growth). For (C and E), numbers along the top refer to the serial dilution factor for plating cells. D, <lb/>schematic representation of PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 hybrid protein constructs. Regions corresponding to PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 identity are depicted in gray <lb/>and purple, respectively (top). Designation of protein variants and regions derived from PaFtsH1 and/or PaFtsH2 that make up the respective FtsH hybrid <lb/>variants are indicated in the table (bottom). E, colony size of the P. aeruginosa SG17M ΔftsH1ΔftsH2 double deletion strain complemented with PaftsH1 and <lb/>PaftsH2 hybrid constructs as introduced in panel D. &quot;+&quot; and &quot;-&quot; scoring system is the same as in (C). DNTR, Diverse N-terminal region; MC 7+ , membrane-<lb/>cytoplasmic linker plus seven C-terminal amino acids into the AAA+ ATPase module boundary; TM1, Transmembrane helix 1; TM2, Transmembrane helix 2. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Divergent FtsH protease functionality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">J. Biol. Chem. (2024) 300(2) 105622</note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>


			<body>A <lb/>E <lb/>F <lb/>G <lb/>H <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>Figure 3. The membrane-cytoplasmic MC 7+ linker of PaFtsH1 activates degradation by PaFtsH2 in vitro. A, linear map of a model FtsH enzyme with a <lb/>zoom-in on MC 7+ linker sequences from PaFtsH1 (32 amino acids) and PaFtsH2 (31 amino acids). Bolded residues denote the start (N-terminal side) of the <lb/>respective PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 AAA+ ATPase modules. B, schematic of PaFtsH2 MC 7+ and MC linker chimera constructs: PaFtsH2 H1-link-32 , PaFtsH2 H1-link-12 , <lb/>PaFtsH2 H1-link-10 . Regions in gray represent residues of donor PaFtsH1 identity on an otherwise PaFtsH2 host (purple). The number of amino acids derived <lb/>from PaFtsH1 are indicated in the superscript of the variant name. Black filled rectangles represent TM domains. C, degradation of λcI N -ssrA substrate (15 μM) <lb/>by PaFtsH1, PaFtsH2, and PaFtsH2 H1-link-32 (3.04 μM) as described in Figure 1F. Bands corresponding to full-length λcI N -ssrA substrate and a 5.7 kDa <lb/>intermediate degradation product (denoted by asterisk) are indicated. D, degradation of Arc-st11-ssrA (15 μM) was monitored in the presence of PaFtsH1, <lb/>PaFtsH2, and PaFtsH2 H1-link-32 (3.53 μM) as described in Figure 1G. E, structural disorder prediction profiles of PaFtsH1 (blue) and PaFtsH2 (purple) as <lb/>anticipated by the IUPred algorithm (74). Dotted lines indicate the average disorder scores for residues 1 to 590 of PaFtsH1 (blue, 0.29) and PaFtsH2 (purple, <lb/>0.20). Inset shows a zoom-in of the MC 7+ linker regions. Bottom schematic is a linear model of an FtsH enzyme with relevant structural and functional <lb/>regions noted on the diagram. F, degradation of λcI N -ssrA substrate (15 μM) was monitored in the presence of PaFtsH1, PaFtsH2, and PaFtsH2 H1-link-32 <lb/>(3.04 μM) as described in Figure 1F. G, quantification of full-length substrate remaining over reaction time courses. Error bars represent SD of experiments <lb/>performed in triplicate. Representative degradation kinetics as monitored by SDS-PAGE by PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 are shown in Figure 1, E and F. H, <lb/>3D-reconstructions from negative stain TEM of PaFtsH1, PaFtsH2, and PaFtsH2 H1-link-32 . Scale bar represents 3 nm. Periplasmic, transmembrane (TM), and <lb/>cytoplasmic domains are noted on the figure. MC 7+ , membrane-cytoplasmic plus next seven C-terminal amino acids; Peri, Periplasmic domain; TM1, <lb/>Transmembrane domain 1; TM2, Transmembrane domain 2. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Divergent FtsH protease functionality <lb/></note>

            <page>6</page>

			<note place="footnote">J. Biol. Chem. (2024) 300(2) 105622 <lb/></note>

			<body>flexible than that of PaFtsH2, as are the linker segments <lb/>containing just 12 or 10 PaFtsH1 residues (Figs. 3E, S3D, and <lb/>S5). <lb/>The MC 7+ linker appears to contribute to conformational <lb/>flexibility <lb/>To investigate whether the functional differences we <lb/>observed with the different MC linkers are reflected in differ-<lb/>ences in enzyme structure/dynamics, we imaged detergent-<lb/>solubilized PaFtsH1, PaFtsH2, and the most active hybrid pro-<lb/>tein PaFtsH2 H1-link-32 by electron microscopy and negative <lb/>staining, resulting in fields of particles representing single <lb/>hexamers (Fig. S6A). Reconstructed 3D-maps using six-fold <lb/>symmetry produced distinct 22-Å resolution density maps <lb/>for the three enzymes (Fig. 3H). Each map contained obvious <lb/>density for the large cytoplasmic domains and weaker density <lb/>for the periplasmic domain, whereas the transmembrane helices <lb/>were obscured by detergent and not well-visualized (Fig. S6B). <lb/>Although PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 showed cone-shaped ap-<lb/>pearances, more defined-shape features were visible for <lb/>PaFtsH2, including well-defined domain-like shapes in the <lb/>periplasmic ring and clear delineation between the AAA+ <lb/>ATPase and peptidase segments of the cytoplasmic regions <lb/>(Fig. 3H). We interpret these structural differences as an <lb/>indication of PaFtsH2&apos;s relative conformational homogeneity <lb/>and rigidity, whereas PaFtsH1 may adopt more, slightly <lb/>different, conformations and thus &quot;blur&quot; structural features. <lb/>These observations are consistent with the hypothesis that the <lb/>shorter, stiffer MC 7+ linker in PaFtsH2 confines its move-<lb/>ments, potentially hampering substrate engagement and/or <lb/>unfolding. Interestingly, the structural definition in the <lb/>PaFtsH2 H1-link-32 variant was an intermediate between those of <lb/>PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2. Especially noticeable in PaFtsH2 H1-link-<lb/>32 was the loss of cytoplasmic-ring definition compared to <lb/>parental PaFtsH2. These results also support the notion that <lb/>the PaFtsH1 MC7+ linker imparts greater ability to &quot;explore&quot; <lb/>more conformations than the PaFtsH2 linker. <lb/>The PaFtsH2 structure was more similar to a recent cryo-<lb/>EM structure of hyperthermophilic Aquifex aeolicus FtsH <lb/>((3); EMD-11161) than the other structures, probably because <lb/>it had the most well-defined periplasmic and cytoplasmic do-<lb/>mains. Of note, although phylogenetically more similar to <lb/>PaFtsH1 (46% vs. 42% identity), AaFtsH is predicted to possess <lb/>a more rigid linker than PaFtsH1 with three glycine residues <lb/>(Fig. S1). The crystal structure of the A. aeolicus cytoplasmic <lb/>domain of FtsH (PDB 4WW0; (41)) also fit best with PaFtsH2, <lb/>although the AAA+ modules and peptidase domains could be <lb/>acceptably fit in each of the three density maps (Fig. S6B). <lb/>PaFtsH1 MC 7+ linker length determines complementation <lb/>strength by PaFtsH1-PaFtsH2 chimeras <lb/>PaFtsH2 H1-link-32 <lb/>complementation <lb/>of <lb/>SG17M <lb/>ΔftsH1ΔftsH2 colony size was substantial, but less complete <lb/>than PaFtsH2 NFtsH1 complementation, and far greater than <lb/>complementation by PaFtsH2 alone (Fig. 4A). PaFtsH2 H1-link-12 <lb/>did not rescue colony growth. We also monitored the ability of <lb/>different FtsH linker chimeras to complement tobramycin <lb/>susceptibility and growth in liquid M63-citrate minimal media <lb/>(Figs. 4, B-D and S7). Expression of PaFtsH2 H1-link-32 , but not <lb/>PaFtsH2 H1-link-12 , restored tobramycin tolerance to a level <lb/>similar to that afforded by PaFtsH1 or PaFtsH2 NFtsH1 (Fig. 4B). <lb/>Similarly, while even complementation with PaFtsH1 was <lb/>poor, only PaFtsH2 NFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 H1-link-32 partially <lb/>complemented the slow-growth defect of SG17M <lb/>ΔftsH1ΔftsH2 in M63-citrate medium better than PaFtsH2 <lb/>itself (Fig. 4, C and D). Thus, although in vitro and in vivo <lb/>activities of hybrid proteins are not entirely congruent, as <lb/>distinct substrate(s), adaptor proteins, or protein conforma-<lb/>tions might be determinative for recovery of in vivo pheno-<lb/>types such as colony size, the PaFtsH1-PaFtsH2-linker hybrids <lb/>significantly gained functionality in all or selected assays. <lb/>Membrane-cytoplasmic linker across phylogeny <lb/>Previous phylogenetic analyses of representative homologs <lb/>of PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 with highest sequence similarity in <lb/>different taxonomic groups of bacteria revealed that similarity <lb/>among PaFtsH1-like proteins was largely in line with overall <lb/>phylogenetic relationships (as determined by 16S rRNA), <lb/>whereas PaFtsH2-like protein similarity was not (5). These <lb/>data are consistent with PaftsH2-like genes frequently hori-<lb/>zontally transferred as part of the tLST genomic island into <lb/>distinct genetic backgrounds of diverse bacterial species <lb/>including the occasional pathogens P. aeruginosa, Cronobacter <lb/>sakazakii, Klebsiella pneumoniae, and E. coli (5, 12, 13). <lb/>Given our structure/function data on the impact of the <lb/>MC 7+ linker in PaFtsH1 versus PaFtsH2 activity, we hypothe-<lb/>sized that MC 7+ linker similarity is congruent with the clus-<lb/>tering of FtsH proteins. To this end, we aligned representative <lb/>FtsH proteins from different genera of γ-proteobacteria from <lb/>the NCBI and UniProt databases homologous to PaFtsH1 and <lb/>PaFtsH2 and also included FtsH representatives from all <lb/>established major phyla of the bacterial phylogenetic tree. As <lb/>FtsH proteins are also highly conserved in other major <lb/>evolutionary branches of life including amoeba, fungi, plants, <lb/>and mammals, FtsH representatives from select organisms, <lb/>such as the model plant Arabidopsis thaliana (which possess <lb/>11 FtsH homologs) and Homo sapiens, were also added to this <lb/>analysis. We generated a protein evolutionary tree where <lb/>branch length represents the number of sequence changes <lb/>between entries (Fig. 5A; (5)). As expected, the PaFtsH1 and <lb/>PaFtsH2 representatives each clustered together, but far apart <lb/>from each other. PaFtsH1-like proteins (blue branches; &gt;46% <lb/>identity) and PaFtsH2-like proteins (purple branches; &gt;61% <lb/>identity) were therefore used to generate two sequence align-<lb/>ments, to allow comparison between the MC linkers of the <lb/>representative proteins which originated from different bac-<lb/>terial phyla (Table S2 and Fig. 5B). <lb/>Comparing the amino acid preferences within the MC 7+ <lb/>linker sequences (including the first seven residues of the <lb/>AAA+ modules) shows a strikingly conserved glycine-rich <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Divergent FtsH protease functionality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">J. Biol. Chem. (2024) 300(2) 105622</note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>


			<body>character of the PaFtsH1-type linker in contrast to the <lb/>PaFtsH2-type linker (Fig. 5B). Whereas up to eight clustered <lb/>glycines (seven being common, e.g., GGGGG[K/R]GG) <lb/>occurred in PaFtsH1-type linkers, those of the PaFtsH2-like <lb/>proteases contained fewer glycines and no long Gly-rich <lb/>blocks (e.g. GMGG being common). In addition, the Gly-rich <lb/>sequence tracks in both types of linkers are positioned <lb/>differently with respect to the TM2 transmembrane helix, <lb/>which is extended in length in PaFtsH2, and the AAA+ module <lb/>(Fig. 5B). <lb/>Subsequently, we dissected the more immediate linker <lb/>evolution in more detail. Besides for one protein, the PaFtsH2 <lb/>linker has been conserved in all 287 full-length FtsH2 homo-<lb/>logs with an identity &gt;80% as retrieved from the NCBI and <lb/>UniProt databases (Fig. S8A). This finding indicates that, <lb/>despite horizontal gene transfer into different species, the <lb/>FtsH2 linker sequence had remained stable. Few more <lb/>diverged (longer, more glycine-rich) linkers are observed <lb/>among 252 FtsH2 homologs with an identity larger than 67% <lb/>(UniProt database), suggesting that immediate, but not accel-<lb/>erated, linker evolution of similar proteins can occur in <lb/>different species (Fig. S8B). Equally, only five out of 252 full <lb/>length PaFtsH1 proteins of P. aeruginosa with identity &gt;50% <lb/>and &gt;90% query coverage (BLAST database) showed evolved <lb/>linkers (Fig. S8C). All five evolved linkers displayed reduced <lb/>glycine content suggesting that longer more glycine rich <lb/>linkers are not evolutionary supported in P. aeruginosa. In 248 <lb/>non-P. aeruginosa representative homologs of PaFtsH1 with <lb/>Figure 4. MC 7+ linker identity determines the strength of complementation in Pseudomonas aeruginosa SG17M ΔftsH1ΔftsH2 cells. A, colony <lb/>growth of P. aeruginosa SG17M ΔftsH1ΔftsH2 double deletion strains upon complementation with an empty expression vector control pJN105 (EV), PaFtsH1, <lb/>PaFtsH2, PaFtsH1 NFtsH2 , PaFtsH2 NFtsH1 , PaFtsH2 H1-link-32 , or PaFtsH2 H1-link-12 as indicated. Strains were grown overnight at 37 C on LB plates with 30 μg/ml <lb/>gentamicin. &quot;+&quot; and &quot;-&quot; scoring system relates the qualitative degree of colony growth of a particular strain genotype relative to that of SG17M EV (++++; <lb/>wild-type (WT) colony growth) or SG17M ΔftsH1ΔftsH2 (-; very poor colony growth). B, measurement of zone of inhibition upon exposure to the amino-<lb/>glycoside antibiotic tobramycin. P. aeruginosa SG17M ΔftsH1ΔftsH2 double deletion strains were complemented by expression with PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 <lb/>WT and hybrid constructs as indicated. WT SG17M strain harboring an empty expression vector (EV) is shown for reference. A bacterial suspension of 0.5 <lb/>Farland was distributed onto a Mueller Hinton agar plate containing 30 μg/ml gentamicin. The diameter of the zone of growth inhibition was measured <lb/>after incubation at 37 C for 20 to 24 h in the presence of a 10 μg tobramycin disk. ****p &lt; 0.00002; ***p &lt; 0.0002; **p &lt; 0.002; *p &lt; 0.02; ns: not significant <lb/>(compared to &quot;EV&quot; (teal bar)) as analyzed by an unpaired t test. C and D, growth of P. aeruginosa SG17M WT or ΔftsH1ΔftsH2 double deletion strains <lb/>complemented by plasmid-borne expression of the indicated PaFtsH variants in M63-citrate minimal media. Identical growth curves for P. aeruginosa <lb/>SG17M ΔftsH1ΔftsH2 EV, complemented with PaFtsH1 and complemented with PaFtsH2 are displayed in (C) as reference values. EV, pJN105 empty <lb/>expression vector control. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Divergent FtsH protease functionality <lb/></note>

			<page>8</page>

			<note place="footnote">J. Biol. Chem. (2024) 300(2) 105622 <lb/></note>


			<body>Figure 5. Insertion of triplicate alanine or glycine residues in the membrane-proximal region of the PaFtsH2 MC linker activates PaFtsH2 in vivo <lb/>and in vitro. A, evolutionary tree of full-length FtsH proteins of PaFtsH2 and PaFtsH2 homologs of &gt;50% identity, representative FtsH proteins from major <lb/>bacterial phyla and representative FtsH proteins from the archaeal and eukaryotic kingdoms (see Table S2). Blue branches indicate PaFtsH1-like proteins <lb/>with a PaFtsH1-like linker, and red branches indicate PaFtsH2 proteins with a PaFtsH2-like linker. Green branches indicate Arabidopsis thaliana FtsH proteins. <lb/>Tree scale indicates amino acid substitutions per site. Sequence alignment was performed with ClustalX2 and manually curated. The phylogenetic tree was <lb/>constructed using the maximum likelihood of distance estimation with MEGA 7.0 using standard parameters with 100 bootstrap iterations. B, domain <lb/>structure of a model FtsH enzyme and WebLogos of typical FtsH1 and FtsH2 MC 7+ linker sequences constructed from 149 sequences of PaFtsH1-like <lb/>proteases (blue branches in (A)) and 48 sequences of PaFtsH2-like (red branches in (A)). Extended WebLogo depicts the MC 7+ linker region. Residue <lb/>numbers refer to PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2, respectively. C, a zoom-in on the MC linker sequences of indicated PaFtsH2 triplicate residue insertion variants. <lb/>PaFtsH2 MC linker structural prediction was generated by PEP-FOLD 3.5 (bottom; (71)) where blue and red helices indicate predicted proximal and distal <lb/>helices, respectively, and the course grained energy (sOPEP) is -35.74. Site of proximal insertion is between amino acids 131 and 132, and site of distal <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Divergent FtsH protease functionality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">J. Biol. Chem. (2024) 300(2) 105622</note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>


			<body>identity &gt;74.7% (UniProt database), few linkers with extended <lb/>length and glycine content have been observed, besides one <lb/>reduced linker sequence (Fig. S8D). However, the FtsH linker <lb/>has been subject to evolution already in isolates from deeply <lb/>branching phyla such as Bipolaricaulota, Caldiserica, Dictyo-<lb/>glomota, and Coprothermobacterota (Fig. S9). Although most <lb/>isolates display FtsH proteins with short glycine-poor linker <lb/>sequences, longer glycine-rich linkers have occasionally <lb/>evolved. <lb/>Insertion of Gly-Gly-Gly membrane-proximal into the MC <lb/>linker activates PaFtsH2 <lb/>The MC linker in PaFtsH2 H1-link-12 contains more glycines <lb/>than that of wild-type (WT) PaFtsH2, is longer by one residue, <lb/>and activates proteolysis of λcI N -ssrA (Fig. 3, A, F, and G). To <lb/>probe linker length, flexibility and positional effects of a 3x-<lb/>glycine stretch within the linker, we cloned, overexpressed and <lb/>purified (with the exception of PaFtsH2 AAA-p ), PaFtsH2 vari-<lb/>ants with three glycines or alanines inserted immediately <lb/>membrane-proximal (PaFtsH2 GGG-p and PaFtsH2 AAA-p ) or <lb/>membrane-distal (PaFtsH2 GGG-d and PaFtsH2 AAA-d ) to the WT <lb/>MC linker. These insertions are C-terminal of Gln131 and <lb/>Gly140, respectively, and thereby directly at the sequence <lb/>junctions between predicted structured and unstructured re-<lb/>gions of the PaFtsH2 MC linker peptide fold corresponding also <lb/>to PaFtsH1 (Fig. 5C). PaFtsH2 GGG-p , but not PaFtsH2 GGG-<lb/>d partially degraded λcI N -ssrA over the course of 1 h (Fig. 5, D <lb/>and E). Consistent with this, plasmid-borne expression of both <lb/>PaFtsH2 GGG-p and PaFtsH2 AAA-p partially rescued the colony-<lb/>size defect of SG17M ΔftsH1ΔftsH2, albeit less well than <lb/>PaFtsH1, but better than the PaFtsH2 parent (Fig. 5F). Of note, <lb/>PaFtsH2 GGG-p performed better than PaFtsH2 AAA-p in the <lb/>tobramycin assay (Fig. 5G). Neither PaFtsH2 GGG-d nor PaFt-<lb/>sH2 AAA-d rescued colony growth (Fig. 5F), scored well in the <lb/>tobramycin assay (Figs. 5G and S7), or complemented growth in <lb/>M63-citrate liquid medium (Fig. S10A). However, both linker <lb/>variants had reduced rates of ATP hydrolysis (as measured at 45 <lb/>C, the temperature optimum for PaFtsH1) which might <lb/>partially account for their poor activities (Fig. S10B). In com-<lb/>bination, these results strongly suggest that MC linker length <lb/>and flexibility influence the biological activity of FtsH proteases <lb/>in ways that depend on the position of a flexible segment within <lb/>the linker. <lb/>The fact that PaFtsH2 GGG-p has biological activities that <lb/>PaFtsH2 lacks suggests that the WT MC linker of PaFtsH2 <lb/>lacks flexibility and length (Fig. 6), but this model fails to <lb/>explain why PaFtsH2 H1-link-12 was even less active than <lb/>PaFtsH2 GGG-p in some in vivo assays. We noticed, however, <lb/>that a glutamine at position 131 (Gln 131 ) in PaFtsH2 near the <lb/>membrane-proximal end of the MC 7+ linker (Gln 124 in <lb/>PaFtsH1), is highly conserved in PaFtsH2 sequences and the <lb/>vast majority of PaFtsH1 linkers (Figs. 5B, S1, and S7). As the <lb/>glutamine at this position is absent in the construct <lb/>PaFtsH2 H1-link-12 inactive in vivo (Fig. 3B), we constructed an <lb/>additional PaFtsH2 chimera that preserves Gln 131 and adds the <lb/>glycine-rich region of five residues from PaFtsH1 at the <lb/>respective aligned position, basically replacing Met 133 <lb/>(PaFtsH2 H1-link-5 ; Fig. 6A). Notably, PaFtsH2 H1-link-5 expres-<lb/>sion rescued the colony growth defect of SG17M <lb/>ΔftsH1ΔftsH2 to a similar extent as PaFtsH2 H1-link-32 (which <lb/>also retains Gln 131 ) (Fig. 6B). Combined structural and topo-<lb/>logical predictions from AlphaFold models and trans-<lb/>membrane helix prediction programs place Gln 131 at the base <lb/>of the TM2 helix that ends C-terminally with FRRFAEK 130 (a <lb/>sequence preserved in all PaFtsH2 homologs; Figs. 5B and 6C). <lb/>As Gln 131 is localized to the TM2 C-terminal end, it is possible <lb/>that this amino acid serves a functional role such as in aiding <lb/>the formation of a structural boundary between TM2 and the <lb/>MC linker, thereby influencing the flexibility of the membrane <lb/>tether and in vivo activity. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Bacterial species occupy defined ecological habitats based <lb/>on their physiological and metabolic properties and ability to <lb/>tolerate different environmental stresses. P. aeruginosa is not <lb/>only a successful environmental species (42), but an important <lb/>opportunistic human pathogen that infects immune-<lb/>compromised individuals and contributes substantially to the <lb/>morbidly and mortality of cystic fibrosis patients (43). Of note, <lb/>P. aeruginosa has been recently found to be one of the most <lb/>frequently co-infecting pathogen in COVID-19 patients <lb/>contributing to disease severity (44, 45). Compared to other <lb/>strain clusters, clone C of P. aeruginosa is especially robust and <lb/>abundant in the environment and causes acute and chronic <lb/>human infections. Elucidating the molecular mechanisms that <lb/>contribute to the prevalence of P. aeruginosa clones, groups of <lb/>closely related strains with distinct habitat preferences, is <lb/>therefore an important goal with both ecological and clinical <lb/>impact. We have recently shown that P. aeruginosa clone C <lb/>harbors the tLST genomic island, which includes PaftsH2 and <lb/>provides increased tolerance against elevated temperature and <lb/>other stresses. It is therefore plausible that expression of tLST-<lb/>insertion is between amino acids 140 and 141. Arrows indicate positions of residue insertions (Gly-Gly-Gly or Ala-Ala-Ala) for four PaFtsH2 insertion variants: <lb/>PaFtsH2 GGG-p , PaFtsH2 GGG-d , PaFtsH2 AAA-p , PaFtsH2 AAA-d . D, degradation of λcI N -ssrA (15 μM) was monitored in the presence of PaFtsH2, PaFtsH2 GGG-p , or <lb/>PaFtsH2 GGG-d (3.04 μM hexamer equivalents) as described in Figures 1E and 3C. Bands corresponding to full-length λcI N -ssrA and a 5.7 kDa degradation <lb/>intermediate product (denoted by asterisk) are indicated. M: Molecular weight marker. E, quantification of full-length substrate (λcI N -ssrA and Arc-st11-ssrA) <lb/>remaining over the course of the reaction time. Error bars represent SD of experiments performed in triplicate. Data for degradation reactions containing <lb/>PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 are the same as in Figure 3G. F, colony growth of P. aeruginosa SG17M ΔftsH1ΔftsH2 double deletion strains complemented by the <lb/>expression of the indicated PaFtsH variants. &quot;+&quot; and &quot;-&quot; scoring system relates the qualitative degree of colony growth of a particular strain genotype relative <lb/>to that of SG17M EV (pJN105) (++++; wild type colony growth) or SG17M ΔftsH1ΔftsH2 EV (-; very poor colony growth). G, measurement of zone of inhibition <lb/>upon treatment with the aminoglycoside antibiotic tobramycin. P. aeruginosa SG17M ΔftsH1ΔftsH2 double deletion strains were complemented by <lb/>expression with PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 wild-type and triplicate insertion constructs as indicated. Wild-type SG17M strain harboring an empty pJN105 <lb/>expression vector (EV) is shown for reference. ****p &lt; 0.00002; ***p &lt; 0.0002; **p &lt; 0.002; *p &lt; 0.02; ns: not significant (compared to &quot;EV&quot; (dark teal bar)) as <lb/>analyzed by an unpaired t test. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Divergent FtsH protease functionality <lb/></note>

			<page>10</page>

			<note place="footnote">J. Biol. Chem. (2024) 300(2) 105622 <lb/></note>


			<body>H1-link-5 <lb/>++ <lb/>+ <lb/>++ <lb/>SG17M ftsH1 ftsH2 <lb/>A <lb/>AAA+ Unfoldase M41 Peptidase <lb/>N <lb/>C <lb/>FtsH <lb/>PaFtsH1 <lb/>PaFtsH2 <lb/>120 <lb/>M R Q M Q G G G G G R G G P M SFG KSK A RL L <lb/>144 <lb/>R R F A E K <lb/>F <lb/>-Q G M G G F L SIG KSR A KV F <lb/>124 <lb/>147 <lb/>125 <lb/>134 136 <lb/>131 <lb/>137 139 <lb/>MC linker <lb/>Donor PaFtsH1 region: 126-130 aa <lb/>Region of PaFtsH2 replaced: Met133 <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>Cytoplasm <lb/>Periplasm <lb/>s s rA <lb/>s s r A <lb/>FtsH1 6 <lb/>s s r A <lb/>s s A <lb/>Rp oH <lb/>RpoH <lb/>PaFtsH1 Protomer (1-598) <lb/>PaFtsH2 Protomer (1-600) <lb/>Q131 <lb/>MC linker <lb/>16% glyine <lb/>C <lb/>N <lb/>Membrane <lb/>Putative substrate pool <lb/>Putative substrate pool <lb/>N <lb/>MC linker <lb/>32% glycine <lb/>Q124 <lb/>C <lb/>FtsH2 6 <lb/>P h z C <lb/>s s r A <lb/>Rp oH <lb/>P h z C <lb/>M G <lb/>FtsH2 activation models <lb/>FtsH2-specific <lb/>adaptor-substrate <lb/>vertical motion <lb/>membrane composition/fluidity <lb/>substrate conformation/unfolding <lb/>FtsH1 inhibition model <lb/>FtsH1-specific <lb/>MC linker &apos;brace&apos; <lb/>s s r A <lb/>RpoH <lb/>M G <lb/>MG <lb/>s s rA <lb/>h z C <lb/>MG <lb/>s s rA <lb/>P h z C <lb/>ATP <lb/>ADP <lb/>+ P <lb/>? <lb/>PaFtsH2 <lb/>: <lb/>F R R F A E K <lb/>S I G K S R A K V F <lb/>Q G G G G R G G F L <lb/>N <lb/>PaFtsH2 <lb/>PaFtsH1 (5 aa) <lb/>C <lb/>AAA+ <lb/>M41 <lb/>G <lb/>Figure 6. Membrane-cytoplasmic linker properties are important in determining PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 functionality. A, schematic description of the <lb/>PaFtsH2 H1-link-5 variant. Met 133 of PaFtsH2 was replaced with a stretch of five amino acids from PaFtsH1, GGGGR (residues 126-130). PaFtsH1 Gln 124 and <lb/>PaFtsH2 Gln 131 are denoted in bold and are predicted to localize at the base of TM2 in both enzymes, as referred to in panel C (top). Amino acids labeled in <lb/>purple on the PaFtsH2 H1-link-5 variant schematic are of PaFtsH2 identity (bottom). B, colony growth of Pseudomonas aeruginosa SG17M ΔftsH1ΔftsH2 double <lb/>deletion strains complemented with either empty vector pJN105 (EV), wild-type PaftsH1, PaftsH2, or the hybrid constructs PaFtsH2 H1-link-32 , PaFtsH2 H1-link-12 , <lb/>and PaFtsH2 H1-link-5 , as indicated. The plate in this panel is the same as in Figure 4A for EV, PaFtsH1, and PaFtsH2. &quot;+&quot; and &quot;-&quot; scoring system relates the <lb/>qualitative degree of colony growth of a particular strain genotype relative to that of SG17M EV (++++; wild-type colony growth) or SG17M ΔftsH1ΔftsH2 (-; <lb/>very poor colony growth). C, model of MC linker-dependent functionality of FtsH proteases. The more flexible MC linker of PaFtsH1 compared to that of <lb/>PaFtsH2 (32% and 16% glycine, respectively) allows enhanced motion relative to the inner membrane plane (θ) which may promote access of substrates <lb/>into the FtsH1 axial pore (highly conserved FVG pore loops are indicated by orange-filled circles). The comparatively reduced MC linker flexibility of PaFtsH2 <lb/>restricts its plane of motion and inhibits the productive entry of substrates for proteolysis by PaFtsH2. Green arrows indicate productive substrate <lb/>recognition and subsequent proteolysis and arrows with a black &quot;X&quot; indicate unproductive substrate recognition. PaFtsH2 degrades molten-globule-like <lb/>(MG) substrates in vitro, which may indicate an in vivo prerequisite for the remodeling of folded substrates prior to PaFtsH2-dependent degradation. <lb/>Alternatively, the higher ATPase activity/substrate pulling force of PaFtsH2 may point to a scenario in which PaFtsH2 preferentially proteolyzes integral <lb/>membrane proteins compared to PaFtsH1, a substrate class that we did not test in vitro. As PaftsH2 is found on a tLST genomic island which confers <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Divergent FtsH protease functionality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">J. Biol. Chem. (2024) 300(2) 105622</note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>


			<body>encoded factors may contribute to establishing the observed <lb/>abundant representation of P. aeruginosa clone C (11, 13, 42, <lb/>46-48). The presence of the PaftsH2 xenolog in addition to <lb/>core genome PaftsH1 distinguishes P. aeruginosa clone C and <lb/>clone J from the model P. aeruginosa strains PAO and PA14 <lb/>and most other investigated model bacterial species, which <lb/>encode only a single membrane-bound FtsH enzyme. Evolu-<lb/>tionary analysis reveals that a very similar tLST genomic island <lb/>containing an ftsH2 gene has been transferred into and <lb/>maintained in other bacterial species including in clones of <lb/>occasional pathogens (13). On the other hand, in the same <lb/>tLST context, ftsH2 has also been observed to be frequently <lb/>deleted indicating evolutionary constraints to maintain two <lb/>ftsH genes in some genetic backgrounds. In general, however, <lb/>expansion of FtsH proteases in bacteria is not as uncommon. <lb/>For example, although Burkholderia species harbor a FtsH1 <lb/>homolog that is closely related to PaFtsH1, some organisms <lb/>have acquired additional distinct, distantly-related FtsH pro-<lb/>teases (Fig. S11). It is well known that cyanobacteria harbor up <lb/>to four FtsH paralogs and highly diverse xenologs which <lb/>cluster with FtsH from other bacterial species (Fig. S11). <lb/>Furthermore, phytoplasma, such as the vineyard-grape path-<lb/>ogen Flavescence doree, carry multiple virulence-associated <lb/>and clearly paralogous ftsH genes despite having minimalized <lb/>genomes (Fig. S11) (49, 50). Thus, expansion of FtsH protease <lb/>variants appears to be an adaptive evolutionary strategy that <lb/>has occurred independently in more than one bacterial <lb/>species/sub-species throughout the phylogenetic tree and in <lb/>higher organisms including plants and humans (Figs. S11 and <lb/>5A with reference FtsH proteases indicated). The phylogenetic <lb/>relationships among the FtsH proteases suggest various <lb/>mechanisms such as gene duplication with subsequent diver-<lb/>sification and horizontal gene transfer to contribute to the <lb/>multiplication of ftsH protease genes in genomes. <lb/>Building upon a previous study (5), here we characterized <lb/>the molecular basis of functional differences between the <lb/>PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 proteases of P. aeruginosa clone C. <lb/>Notably, although both enzymes are active ATP-dependent <lb/>proteases, we find that they have common and distinct sub-<lb/>strate specificities as concluded from in vivo and in vitro <lb/>studies ((5) and this work). For example, both enzymes <lb/>degrade the structurally-relaxed protein β-casein, whereas only <lb/>PaFtsH1 degrades λcI N -ssrA and Arc-st11-ssrA. We also <lb/>demonstrate that many of the biochemical and biological ac-<lb/>tivities of these PaFtsH xenologs depend on the identity and <lb/>character of a short region of the linker that connects the TM2 <lb/>transmembrane helix to the cytoplasmic AAA+ module. While <lb/>tilting of the catalytic domains against the membrane plane <lb/>provides substrate access (3), we show in this work that the <lb/>impact of highly divergent MC linker sequences extends <lb/>beyond a solely physical role in providing substrate access to a <lb/>much more determinative and flexible role in substrate pro-<lb/>cessing. Future work will identify natural substrates processed <lb/>by FtsH proteases with distinct linker sequences. <lb/>MC linker flexibility and control of FtsH function <lb/>We initially discovered that a hybrid protein containing the <lb/>TM1 helix, periplasmic domain, TM2 helix, and MC 7+ linker <lb/>region of PaFtsH1 and the AAA+ module and protease <lb/>domain of PaFtsH2 had cellular activities similar to PaFtsH1 <lb/>and vice versa. Further sequence swaps identified a short <lb/>sequence stretch of cytoplasmic MC 7+ linker as being <lb/>substantially responsible for functionality of the PaFtsH2 cat-<lb/>alytic subunits such as PaFtsH1-like substrate degradation <lb/>in vitro and phenotypic recovery in vivo. Indeed, swapping as <lb/>few as five residues from the PaFtsH1 MC linker into PaFtsH2 <lb/>was sufficient to endow the chimeric protease with substantial <lb/>PaFtsH1-like activities (Fig. 6, A and B). <lb/>In the hexameric FtsH enzyme, the MC 7+ linker appears to <lb/>determine the flexibility of the cytoplasmic parts of the pro-<lb/>tease relative to the membrane (Fig. 6C). This model is <lb/>consistent with (i) predictions of the flexibilities of different <lb/>linkers that reinforce or fail to support certain PaFtsH1-<lb/>specific functions; (ii) with the higher glycine content of the <lb/>MC linker of PaFtsH1 relative to PaFtsH2; (iii) with low-<lb/>resolution EM structures of PaFtsH1, PaFtsH2, and an active <lb/>chimeric enzyme; and (iv) with the observation that position-<lb/>specific insertion of just three glycines or alanines into the <lb/>MC linker of PaFtsH2 allowed this chimera to partially restore <lb/>defects caused by an ftsH1 deletion. <lb/>Our results advocate the hypothesis that higher MC linker <lb/>flexibility correlates with PaFtsH1-like biochemical and bio-<lb/>logical functions. Identification of endogenous biological <lb/>substrates of P. aeruginosa PaFtsH2, however, remains to be <lb/>determined, as does addressing the question of how the <lb/>properties of the PaFtsH2 MC linker contribute to its pro-<lb/>teolytic specificity. Intracellular levels of PaFtsH2 increase <lb/>during nutrient deprivation and it represents the predominant <lb/>FtsH species in late-stationary phase (5). Thus, PaFtsH2-<lb/>specific substrates, which may include the gene products of <lb/>the tLST genomic island (46, 51), may be more prevalent in <lb/>late-stationary phase or during biofilm formation, whereby <lb/>differences in substrate specificity may provide a survival <lb/>enhanced tolerance to heat and other stresses to the host organism, it is possible that a higher membrane fluidity characteristic of higher temperatures is <lb/>required for the optimal function of PaFtsH2 or that condition-dependent adaptors or factors are required for the specific delivery of substrates. Although <lb/>PaFtsH2 has a more rigid MC linker than PaFtsH1 and its horizontal movement relative to the membrane plane is constrained, it contains a longer TM2 <lb/>domain which may result in higher vertical &apos;up-and-down&apos; movement within the inner membrane. This vertical movement may be important for the <lb/>degradation of certain substrates or for regulating substrate entry into the PaFtsH2 axial pore. As PaFtsH1 was active against most protein substrates tested <lb/>in our study, models for its inhibition in vivo include those that restrict or &quot;brace&quot; the flexibility of its MC linker such that entry into its axial pore is no longer <lb/>accessible. Monomer structural predictions of PaFtsH1 (top left, Q9HV48_PSEAE) and PaFtsH2 (top right, A0485GIM3_PSEAI) were generated using <lb/>AlphaFold. Although the structures are torsionally inaccurate, they are helpful for viewing the proximity of the MC linkers to the transmembrane (towards <lb/>the N terminus) and cytoplasmic (towards the C terminus) domains. Conserved Gln (Q) residues as mentioned in panel A are located at the base (C-terminal <lb/>end) of TM2 of each protein and labeled with arrows. The UniProt ID used for modeling PaFtsH2 is 99.52% identical to the PaFtsH2 sequence from SG17M <lb/>clone C. The three residues that differed from PaFtsH2 (S127, M447, E524) were changed to residues of PaFtsH2 identity using PyMol (S127R, M447I, E524A). <lb/>Only residues 1-598 of PaFtsH1 and 1-600 of PaFtsH2 are shown in the figure, as the C-terminal regions are predicted to be highly unstructured. <lb/>Divergent FtsH protease functionality <lb/></body>

			<page>12</page>

			<note place="footnote">J. Biol. Chem. (2024) 300(2) 105622 <lb/></note>


			<body>benefit to the organism. For example, the faster rate of ATP <lb/>hydrolysis of PaFtsH2 compared to PaFtsH1 may aid in the <lb/>processing of thermodynamically more stable substrates. ATP-<lb/>hydrolysis activity by PaFtsH2 also has a temperature optimum <lb/>that is higher than that of the PaFtsH1 enzyme (Fig. S2B). This <lb/>fact indicates superior PaFtsH2 functionality at higher tem-<lb/>peratures consistent with glycine-poor linker sequences of <lb/>FtsH proteases in thermophilic organisms such as Thermus <lb/>spp. and even FtsH1-like A. aeolicus (Fig. S1). P. aeruginosa <lb/>skin infections in humans are a frequent issue associated with <lb/>hot tub usage and outbreaks on thermally sterilized endo-<lb/>scopes by sequence type ST17 (clone C) have occurred (52, <lb/>53); these high-temperature environments may favor and/or <lb/>activate PaFtsH2 due to its more rapid ATPase rate. Alterna-<lb/>tively, increased membrane fluidity or change in membrane <lb/>composition could suppress the apparent &apos;negative gating&apos; <lb/>properties of PaFtsH2&apos;s &apos;rigid&apos; MC linker and thus contribute <lb/>to survival of the organism (Fig. 6C). <lb/>Moreover, the presence of protein adaptors able to alter <lb/>PaFtsH1 or PaFtsH2 activity and function (e.g., HflC and HflK) <lb/>may also change depending upon specific growth or environ-<lb/>mental conditions. An interesting and testable hypothesis is <lb/>that some adaptors/regulators exert their influence on FtsH <lb/>activity, at least in part, by or mimicking the effects <lb/>of a flexible versus stiff attachment to the inner membrane. <lb/>Surprisingly, such physiological impact seems to have devel-<lb/>oped gradually as selectively investigated deeply branching <lb/>bacterial phyla contain predominantly, but not exclusively, <lb/>FtsH proteins with short linkers (Fig. S8A). Like the MC linker <lb/>of P. aeruginosa PaFtsH2, MC linkers from well-investigated <lb/>extremophile variants of FtsH (e.g., A. aeolicus and Thermus <lb/>thermophilus) or single-membrane Gram-positive bacteria <lb/>(e.g., M. tuberculosis) also have fewer glycines (Fig. S1). This <lb/>observation emphasizes the need to elucidate molecular <lb/>mechanisms that determine how MC linker flexibility and/or <lb/>properties impact FtsH function and overall cellular physi-<lb/>ology (54). Our work demonstrates the functional importance <lb/>of PaFtsH MC 7+ linkers with implications that potentially <lb/>extend to other membrane-tethered FtsH proteases and even <lb/>membrane proteins in all kingdoms of life. Although linkers <lb/>have previously been identified as mediating signal trans-<lb/>duction (55-58), we have shown that the molecular properties <lb/>of the junction separating transmembrane and cytoplasmic <lb/>domains of a protein can have profound significance on its <lb/>activity and physiological impact. These findings anticipate <lb/>further that molecular hinges found in other membrane-<lb/>bound proteins may be key regulatory elements to a greater <lb/>extent than previously anticipated. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Experimental procedures <lb/>Strains and plasmids <lb/>P. aeruginosa strains used in this study were the <lb/>P. aeruginosa clone C strain SG17M (42) and its derivative <lb/>SG17M053 (SG17M ΔftsH1ΔftsH2) (5). For liquid growth, <lb/>strains were cultivated in LB broth medium (BD Difco) at <lb/>37 C. If needed, 30 μg/ml gentamicin (for pJN105 plasmid <lb/>selection in P. aeruginosa and E. coli) and 50 μg/ml kanamycin <lb/>(for pET-28a(+) (Novagen) expression plasmid selection in <lb/>E. coli) were used. P. aeruginosa SG17M genomic DNA was <lb/>used as a template to amplify native PaftsH1 and PaftsH2 se-<lb/>quences. To generate constructs for protein overexpression, <lb/>standard cloning of the open reading frames with upstream <lb/>Shine-Dalgarno sequences and downstream codons for a <lb/>6xHis-tag into the expression vector pET-28a(+) between the <lb/>NheI/XbaI restriction sites was performed. For cloning and <lb/>expression of WT and variant PaftsH1 and PaftsH2 genes in <lb/>P. aeruginosa SG17M, the L-arabinose inducible broad host-<lb/>range expression vector pJN105 was used (5, 59) combined <lb/>with the PaftsH2 Shine-Dalgarno sequence to normalize pro-<lb/>tein production. For the construction of PaftsH DNTR hybrid <lb/>constructs (PaFtsH1 NFtsH2 , PaFtsH2 NFtsH1 and constructs a-e), <lb/>the desired regions of PaftsH1 and PaftsH2 were selectively <lb/>amplified from P. aeruginosa SG17M genomic DNA, <lb/>isolated, subjected to overlapping PCR to create custom hy-<lb/>brids, and cloned into pJN105. Standard Gibson Assembly <lb/>(New England Biolabs) cloning was used to construct linker <lb/>variants PaFtsH2 H1-link-32 , PaFtsH2 H1-link-12 , and PaFtsH2 H1-link-10 ; <lb/>and site-directed mutagenesis (QuickChange, Agilent) was used <lb/>to create all triplicate insertion MC linker variants in PaFtsH2. <lb/>Some constructs were subcloned into pJN105, while others were <lb/>directly cloned and constructed in pJN105. All constructs were <lb/>confirmed by Sanger sequencing. Plasmids used in this study are <lb/>described in Table S3. <lb/>All primer sequences used in this study are described in <lb/>Table S4. Stable introduction of expression plasmids into <lb/>P. aeruginosa SG17M ΔftsH1ΔftsH2 was achieved by electro-<lb/>poration using Gene Pulser (Bio-Rad) with 0.1 cm gap cuvettes <lb/>operated at 13 kV/cm, 400 Ω and 25 μF. <lb/>Protein expression and purification <lb/>For protein induction, EcFtsH-Myc-6xHis, PaFtsH1-6xHis, <lb/>and PaFtsH2-6xHis variants were expressed from a pET-<lb/>28a(+) plasmid in E. coli strain BL21(DE3) (New England <lb/>Biolabs) grown at 37 C in LB supplemented with 50 μg/ml <lb/>kanamycin. At OD 600 of 0.6, temperature was reduced to 30 <lb/>C, and β-D-1-thiogalactopyranoside was added to a final <lb/>concentration of 0.5 mM in 1 L cultures and cells were har-<lb/>vested after 3 h. FtsH purification was performed as previously <lb/>described with modifications (24, 60). Cell pellets were <lb/>resuspended in Tris Buffered Saline containing protease in-<lb/>hibitor (Pierce Protease Inhibitor Capsules, EDTA-free, <lb/>Thermo Fisher Scientific) and frozen. For protein purifica-<lb/>tion, cell suspensions were pelleted by centrifugation and <lb/>pellets were lysed by repeated freeze thaw cycles (4×) in which <lb/>frozen cell pellets were thawed in a warm water bath and <lb/>frozen in a dry ice and ethanol bath. The lysate was mixed at <lb/>room temperature with 20 ml B-PER (a mild non-ionic <lb/>detergent; Thermo Fisher Scientific) containing 10 mg lyso-<lb/>zyme, 5 μl benzonase (Merck), and EDTA-free protease in-<lb/>hibitor for 20 min. Lysate was then centrifuged for 30 min at <lb/>30,000 RCF at 4 C, and supernatant was discarded. The <lb/>resulting pellet containing inclusion bodies was resuspended <lb/>Divergent FtsH protease functionality <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">J. Biol. Chem. (2024) 300(2) 105622</note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>


			<body>in solubilization buffer (50 mM N-cyclohexyl-3-amino-<lb/>propanesulfonic acid (pH 11.0), 2 mM MgSO 4 , 0.1 mM <lb/>ZnCl 2 ). After manual resuspension, ATP was added to a final <lb/>concentration of 1 mM, followed by a dropwise addition of <lb/>15% N-lauroylsarcosine (Sigma) to a final concentration of <lb/>0.6%. The solution was mixed at room temperature for 30 min <lb/>to allow for the solubilization of inclusion bodies and then <lb/>centrifuged for 30 min at 30,000 RCF. The supernatant was <lb/>applied to a Ni 2+ Sepharose column (5 ml HisTrap HP; Cytiva) <lb/>equilibrated in base buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), 100 mM <lb/>NaCl, 20 mM imidazole, 5 mM MgSO 4 , 2 mM β-mercaptoe-<lb/>thanol, 100 μM ZnCl 2 , 1 mM ATP) containing 0.6% N-laur-<lb/>oylsarcosine. The column was washed with 3 column volumes <lb/>(CV) of the same buffer, and then subjected to a wash with 9 <lb/>CV of buffer made of base buffer plus 0.5% NP-40 (note that <lb/>N-lauroylsarcosine is omitted from this wash buffer to allow <lb/>for protein refolding). The column was washed with 3 CV by a <lb/>third and final solution composed of base buffer plus 10% <lb/>glycerol, 0.1% NP-40, and 80 mM imidazole (the first step of a <lb/>stepwise elution; we find FtsH is still bound to the column at <lb/>this step). Finally, protein was eluted with 280 mM imidazole <lb/>in base buffer containing 10% glycerol, and 0.1% NP-40. <lb/>Fractions containing protein at &gt;95% purity as judged by an <lb/>4 to 20% gradient SDS-PAGE gel (Mini-PROTEAN TGX <lb/>Precast, Bio-Rad) stained with Coomassie brilliant blue R-250 <lb/>(BioRad) were combined, concentrated, and dialyzed overnight <lb/>at 4 C in dialysis buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), 80 mM <lb/>NaCl, 60 mM imidazole, 5 mM MgSO 4 , 2 mM β-mercaptoe-<lb/>thanol, 10 μM ZnCl 2 , 10% glycerol). Precision Plus Protein <lb/>Dual Color Standard (Bio-Rad) was consistently used as mo-<lb/>lecular weight marker. We ruled out the possibility of <lb/>contaminating host E. coli FtsH associating with PaFtsH <lb/>complexes after analyzing the migration patterns of purified <lb/>PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 on 4 to 20% SDS-PAGE gels, as EcFtsH, <lb/>PaFtsH1, and PaFtsH2 possess different sizes (monomer mo-<lb/>lecular weights: EcFtsH-Myc-6xHis: 73,127 Da; PaFtsH1-<lb/>6xHis: 70,886 Da; PaFtsH2-6xHis: 69,521 Da) and run <lb/>distinctly on the SDS-PAGE gels (Fig. 1, F and G). After <lb/>dialysis, purified protein was concentrated, aliquoted, flash <lb/>frozen in liquid nitrogen, and stored at -80 C. <lb/>For purification of radioactive proteins ( 35 S-EcFtsH, 35 S-<lb/>PaFtsH1 and 35 S-PaFtsH2), the same experimental procedure <lb/>as above was followed with the following modifications to the <lb/>protein induction conditions: E. coli BL21(DE3) (New England <lb/>Biolabs) cells harboring a pET-28a(+) expression plasmid <lb/>encoding FtsH-6xHis were grown in 500 ml of M9 minimal <lb/>media lacking methionine and cysteine at 37 C and induced at <lb/>OD 600 0.6 with 0.5 mM β-D-1-thiogalactopyranoside. At the <lb/>time of induction, 20 μCi/ml EasyTag Express 35 S Protein <lb/>Labeling Mix (PerkinElmer) was added to cultures and tem-<lb/>perature was reduced to 30 C. After 3 hours of growth <lb/>post-induction, cells were harvested via centrifugation and <lb/>purification was carried out as described above. <lb/>For determination of the native molecular weights of puri-<lb/>fied FtsH enzymes, calibration curves were calculated by <lb/>running molecular weight standards (BioRad cat. No. 151-<lb/>1901) on a Superdex increase 3.2/3.0 analytical gel filtration <lb/>column equilibrated in Buffer PD (50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), <lb/>80 mM NaCl, 5 μM MgSO 4 , 12.5 μM ZnCl 2 , 10% glycerol, <lb/>2 mM β-mercaptoethanol, and 0.1% NP-40). Purified FtsH <lb/>proteins were applied to the column and native molecular <lb/>weights were calculated by fitting to a one-phase decay model. <lb/>Purification of the ssrA tagged substrates, the P22 Arc <lb/>repressor with the (6 x H)KNQHE (st11) tag (Arc-st11) Arc-<lb/>st11-ssrA and the N-terminal domain of the phage λ repressor <lb/>cI, λcI N , substrates were carried out as described (61, 62). <lb/>Growth assays <lb/>For assessing growth on solid media, WT P. aeruginosa <lb/>SG17M and SG17M ΔftsH1ΔftsH2 mutant harboring pJN105 <lb/>empty vector control and derivatives with cloned PaFtsH WT <lb/>and variants were inoculated from a single colony into 10 ml <lb/>LB medium overnight supplemented with 30 μg/ml genta-<lb/>micin. The OD 600 of the cell suspension was adjusted to 1 in <lb/>LB medium and a 10-fold serial dilution was prepared in a 96-<lb/>well plate. Ten microliters of each suspension was spotted <lb/>onto an LB-agar plate with 30 μg/ml gentamicin and incubated <lb/>at 37 C overnight. Colony size as a semiquantitative assess-<lb/>ment of growth was monitored visually and imaged at different <lb/>time points as described previously (5). For quantifying growth <lb/>in liquid culture, bacteria were grown overnight in LB and <lb/>resuspended to a final OD 600 of 1.0 in PBS. One microliter of <lb/>suspension was added to 200 μl M63 minimal medium with <lb/>the appropriate antibiotics in 96-well plates. Growth condi-<lb/>tions were provided in a SpectraMax i3x (Molecular Devices), <lb/>where the plate was incubated at 37 C under shaking for 24 h <lb/>with OD 600 measured every 30 min. <lb/>Antibiotic susceptibility assays <lb/>P. aeruginosa SG17M and/or respective derivatives grown <lb/>on LB-agar plates overnight were resuspended in PBS to a final <lb/>OD 600 of 0.1. An aliquot of this suspension was streaked out <lb/>evenly on a Mueller Hinton agar plate (containing 30 μg/ml <lb/>gentamicin) to which two tobramycin discs (10 μg, Liofilchem) <lb/>was subsequently placed central on the agar plate. The <lb/>tobramycin-disc-containing plate was incubated at 37 C and <lb/>the diameter of the inhibition zone was measured after 20 to <lb/>24 h. <lb/>Enzymatic assays <lb/>Protein degradation assays were performed at 40 C in <lb/>Buffer PD supplemented with 5 mM ATP and an ATP <lb/>regeneration system consisting of 50 μg/ml creatine kinase <lb/>(Millipore-Sigma) and 5 mM creatine phosphate (Millipore-<lb/>Sigma). Protein substrates were added to degradation reactions <lb/>at the following concentrations: 40 mM β-casein (Sigma), <lb/>15 μM Arc-st11-ssrA, 15 μM λcI N -ssrA, and 15 μM untagged <lb/>λcI N , respectively. For Arc-st11-ssrA degradation reaction, <lb/>PaFtsH1/2 was added at a final concentration of 3.53 μM <lb/>hexamer equivalents, and for reactions containing all other <lb/>protein substrates, 3.04 μM PaFtsH1/2 hexamer equivalents <lb/>were added. Reactions were quenched by the addition of SDS-<lb/>loading buffer and boiled before separation by a 4 to 20% SDS-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Divergent FtsH protease functionality <lb/></note>

			<page>14</page>

			<note place="footnote">J. Biol. Chem. (2024) 300(2) 105622 <lb/></note>


			<body>PAGE (BioRad). Proteins in gels were stained with SYPRO <lb/>orange (Sigma-Aldrich), and gels were imaged with a Typhoon <lb/>FLA9500 scanner (GE Healthcare) and quantified with <lb/>ImageQuant 8.1 software (GE Healthcare). The fraction of <lb/>substrate remaining at each reaction time point was calculated <lb/>by dividing the substrate band intensity by the substrate band <lb/>intensity at time zero. <lb/>ATP hydrolysis assays were performed at 40 C using an <lb/>NADH-coupled assay (63) containing 0.43 μM FtsH hexamer, <lb/>5 mM ATP, and NADH-coupled regeneration system in Buffer <lb/>PD. ATP hydrolysis was assessed by the decrease in absor-<lb/>bance at 340 nm using a SpectraMax M5 plate reader (Mo-<lb/>lecular Devices). In all ATP hydrolysis measurements, the <lb/>background rate of ATP depletion in the absence of protease <lb/>was subtracted from all ATPase reactions for calculation of <lb/>protease-dependent ATPase rates. <lb/>Peptide arrays <lb/>Arrays of 12-mer peptides were synthesized by standard <lb/>Fmoc (9-fluorenylmethoxycarbonyl) solid-phase techniques <lb/>and C-terminally linked to a cellulose membrane using a <lb/>ResPep SL peptide synthesizer (Intavis). Each peptide spot on <lb/>the arrays contained a sliding window of 12 amino acids with a <lb/>step size of two amino acids starting from the N-terminus and <lb/>moving towards the C-terminus corresponding to the se-<lb/>quences of target proteins indicated on the respective figures <lb/>and in the figure legends (PaRpoH, PaGlmM, PaLepB1, <lb/>PaMinD, PaPhzC1/2 (identical)). Each peptide array was pro-<lb/>bed with 1 μM 35 S-EcFtsH, 35 S-PaFtsH1, or 35 S-PaFtsH2 in the <lb/>presence of 1.25 mM ATPγS. Peptide sequences correspond-<lb/>ing to each spot are listed in Table S1. Arrays were incubated <lb/>with gentle agitation in TBST (3 x 5 min) followed by over-<lb/>night blocking in 5% BSA in TBST at 4 C. Blocked arrays were <lb/>washed in TBST (2 × 5 min) followed by Buffer PD containing <lb/>0.03% NP-40 (2 × 5 min) at room temperature, and then with <lb/>fresh Buffer PD containing 0.03% NP-40, 1.25 mM ATPγS, <lb/>0.05% BSA, and 1 μM radioactive FtsH hexamer. After incu-<lb/>bation with agitation for 2 h at room temperature, the array <lb/>was briefly washed with Buffer PD containing 0.03% NP-40 <lb/>and 1 mM ATPγS (2 × 30 s), excess liquid from the blot was <lb/>dried, and the dried blot was exposed to a Storage Phosphor <lb/>Screen (Amersham) overnight at room temperature and <lb/>imaged using a Typhoon FLA9500 scanner (GE Healthcare). <lb/>Bioinformatic analyses <lb/>To computationally search for FtsH proteins across phyla, <lb/>PaFtsH1 (accession number: EWH24232.1) and PaFtsH2 <lb/>(accession number: EWH27927.1) of P. aeruginosa SG17M <lb/>were used as queries to identify homologs in the NCBI and <lb/>UniProt databases by BlastP using standard parameters (64, <lb/>65). Due to the high conservation of FtsH, standard search <lb/>parameters (word size: 5; matrix; BLOSUM62; gap costs: ex-<lb/>istence 11, extension 1) allow the identification of FtsH pro-<lb/>teases in all branches of life including H. sapiens and the plant <lb/>A. thaliana. Selection criteria for searches with PaFtsH1 and <lb/>PaFtsH2 to build the phylogenetic tree were &gt;93% coverage <lb/>over the entire length of the amino acid sequence to account <lb/>for the sequence diversity at the N-and C-termini of the <lb/>protein and to retrieve only full-length proteins combined with <lb/>a identity threshold of &gt; 50%. This threshold was chosen to <lb/>avoid overlap between the PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 groups, while <lb/>different empirical thresholds were chosen for the analysis of <lb/>linker sequences in protein subgroups. Identical protein se-<lb/>quences were subsequently removed. In addition, representa-<lb/>tive FtsH proteins, with the consideration of one representative <lb/>protein per genus and up to three proteins per phylum, from <lb/>all major bacterial phyla; selected FtsH protein sequences from <lb/>UniProt; representative proteins from other branches of the <lb/>phylogenetic tree including plant FtsH representatives from A. <lb/>thaliana and mammalian representatives from H. sapiens were <lb/>included in the assessment of phylogenetic relatedness. Sub-<lb/>sequently, proteins were aligned using ClustalX2 using stan-<lb/>dard parameters and manually curated (66). The aligned <lb/>sequences were subjected to phylogenetic analysis using pre-<lb/>liminary neighbor-joining and conclusively maximum likeli-<lb/>hood in MEGA7.0 or MEGA 10.2.2 (67). The Poisson model <lb/>was used as an amino acid replacement model. The robustness <lb/>of the phylogenetic tree topologies was evaluated by bootstrap <lb/>analysis with 100 replications. The trees were displayed with <lb/>MEGA or iTOL (68). <lb/>To analyze the linker sequences, the protein alignment was <lb/>inspected manually in ClustalX2 (69) and GeneDoc (nrbsc.org/ <lb/>gfx/genedoc). Subsequently, considering the overall protein <lb/>identity, proteins with linker sequences most homologous to <lb/>the PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 linker sequence were selected. Only <lb/>few linkers of PaFtsH1-like proteases were omitted due to <lb/>substantial evolution such as missing the highly conserved R(Q/ <lb/>R/K)MQ motif as in NLA45192.1 (RGVS) and OGN14899.1 <lb/>(RMTT) or missing the linker at all (Fig. 5A, indicated in black). <lb/>WebLogos which display the frequency of amino acid occur-<lb/>rence at one position were created using the resulting linker <lb/>sequence alignments for typical PaFtsH1-like and PaFtsH2-like <lb/>linkers (70). Linker sequences for alternative PaFtsH1 and <lb/>PaFtsH2 related subgroups were retrieved in a similar approach. <lb/>Structural prediction of the MC linker in Figure 5C was <lb/>calculated using PEP-FOLD 3.5 (71). Structural prediction of <lb/>P. aeruginosa RpoH (PaRpoH) was calculated using ROSETTA <lb/>(72). PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 monomer structures were predicted <lb/>by AlphaFold (73) using accession numbers Q9HV38_PSEAE <lb/>for PaFtsH1 and A0485GIM3_PSEI for PaFtsH2. The following <lb/>residue changes were made for A0485GIM3_PSEI to achieve <lb/>100% sequence identity with PaFtsH2: G68S, I447M, and <lb/>A524E in PyMOL 2.5.4 (The PyMOL Molecular Graphics <lb/>System, Version 2.0 Schrödinger, LLC). Estimations of struc-<lb/>tural disorder were calculated by the IUPred algorithm (74). <lb/>Charge versus hydropathy calculations were computed using <lb/>PONDR protein disorder predict (75-77). <lb/>Transmembrane helices in PaFtsH1 and PaFtsH2 were <lb/>evaluated by AlphaFold structural models, TOPCON and ΔG <lb/>prediction server v1.0 (78, 79). Current and previous analysis <lb/>was based on TMHMM 2.0, SOSUI and DAS (5). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Divergent FtsH protease functionality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">J. Biol. Chem. (2024) 300(2) 105622</note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>


            <body>Electron microscopy and image processing <lb/>Samples were diluted to 0.4 mg/ml with storage buffer <lb/>(50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), 10 mM KCl, 5 mM MgSO4, 10 μM <lb/>ZnCl 2 , 60 mM imidazole, 10% glycerol, 0.1% Igepal and 2 mM <lb/>β-mercaptoethanol). 3.0 μl of the dilutions were placed to <lb/>glow-discharged copper grids with continuous carbon support <lb/>film and incubated for 1 min. Excess sample was blotted away <lb/>with filter paper and the grids washed in three drops of Milli-Q <lb/>water before staining 30 s in 2% uranyl acetate (TAAB Labo-<lb/>ratories Equipment Ltd). After most stain was blotted away <lb/>with the filter paper, the grids were let to air-dry. Samples were <lb/>checked in JEM-2100f field emission electron microscope <lb/>(JEOL Ltd) operated at 200 kV. Images were collected at 50kx <lb/>nominal magnification and 0.7 to 1.5 μm defocus with Tvips <lb/>TemCam XF416-camera (Tietz Video and Image Processing <lb/>Systems GmbH) using real-time drift correction. <lb/>All image processing was done in EMAN2 (version 2.2; (80). <lb/>Particles were boxed in e2boxer_old using swarm mode using <lb/>box size of 128 pixels. The extracted particles were corrected <lb/>for the contrast transfer function. 2D classifications were used <lb/>for estimating data quality and resulting 2D classes to create <lb/>initial models both without symmetry and with the proposed <lb/>C6-symmetry. Initial models were further refined during <lb/>following 3D refinement rounds. Final particle sets for 3D-<lb/>reconstructions in e2refine_easy using C6 symmetry and <lb/>defined target resolution 18.0 Å contained 4781 (PaFtsH1), <lb/>2921 (PaFtsH2) and 3510 (PaFtsH2 H1-link-32 ) particles. Docking <lb/>of atomic structures was achieved using UCSF Chimera (81). <lb/>Structures were deposited in wwPDB EMDB database with <lb/>accession numbers EMD-18387 (Deposition ID D_1292133141; <lb/>PaFtsH1), EMD-18388 (Deposition ID D_1292133170; <lb/>PaFtsH2) and EMD-18389 (Deposition ID D_1292133186; <lb/>PaFtsH2 H1-link32 ). <lb/></body>

            <div type="availability">Data availability <lb/>All material, strains, and plasmids are available from either <lb/>Tania A. Baker (tabaker@mit.edu) or Ute Römling (Ute. <lb/>Romling@ki.se). pJN105-and pET-28a(+)-based plasmids <lb/>with cloned PaftsH1, PaftsH2, PaftsH1 NFtsH2 , PaftsH2 NFtsH1 and <lb/>PaftsH2 H1-link-32 have been submitted to Addgene. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Supporting information-This article contains supporting informa-<lb/>tion (82-84). A PDF file with supporting information containing SI <lb/>Figures S1-S11 and an Excel file with SI Tables S1-S4 are provided. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments-We thank Sanjay Hari and Sora Kim for <lb/>generously providing materials and thoughtful discussions, Liam <lb/>Longo for analysis recommendations, and Igor Levchenko for the <lb/>synthesis of peptide arrays. We thank Antonius Koller and Richard <lb/>Schiavoni from Biopolymers &amp; Proteomics Facility at the Koch <lb/>Institute at MIT for conducting mass spectrometry. This work was <lb/>funded by the Swedish Research Council for Medicine and Health <lb/>(2012-56X-22034-01-3). <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Author contributions-G. D. M., S. M. K., T. A. B., and U. R. <lb/>conceptualization; G. D. M., S. M. K., L.-Y. C., P. P., H. H., T. A. B., <lb/>and U. R. investigation; G. D. M., S. M. K., L.-Y. C., P. P., R. T. S., T. <lb/>A. B., and U. R. methodology; G. D. M., S. M. K., L.-Y. C., P. P., H. <lb/>H., T. A. B., and U. R. formal analysis; G. D. M., S. M. K., P. P., R. T. <lb/>S., T. A. B., and U. R. writing-original draft; G. D. M., R. T. S., T. A. <lb/>B., and U. R. writing-review and editing; H. H., T. A. B., and U. R. <lb/>supervision; H. H., R. T. S., T. A. B., and U. R. resources; T. A. B. and <lb/>U. R. funding acquisition; T. A. B. and U. R. project administration; <lb/>U. R. data curation. <lb/></div>

            <div type="funding">Funding and additional information-S. M. K. received a personal <lb/>scholarship from the Future University, Cairo, Egypt partially to <lb/>conduct this work and travel grants from the Swedish Medical <lb/>Association (SSMF) for a research stay at the Department of <lb/>Biology, MIT, Cambridge, USA. Payment of page charges has been <lb/>funded by the Lillian Sagens and Curt Ericssons Research <lb/>Foundation. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Conflicts of interest-The authors declare that they have no conflicts <lb/>of interest with the contents of this article. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Abbreviations-The abbreviations used are: AAA+, ATPases asso-<lb/>ciated with diverse cellular activities; CV, column volume; DNTR, <lb/>divergent N-terminal region; MC, membrane-cytoplasmic; MC 7+ , <lb/>membrane-cytoplasmic plus next seven C-terminal amino acids; <lb/>tLST, transmissible locus of stress tolerance; TM, transmembrane <lb/>helix; WT, wild-type. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Schumann, W. (1999) FtsH-a single-chain charonin? FEMS Microbiol. <lb/>Rev. 23, 1-11 <lb/>2. Ito, K., and Akiyama, Y. (2005) Cellular functions, mechanism of action, <lb/>and regulation of FtsH protease. Annu. Rev. Microbiol. 59, 211-231 <lb/>3. Carvalho, V., Prabudiansyah, I., Kovacik, L., Chami, M., Kieffer, R., van <lb/>der Valk, R., et al. (2021) The cytoplasmic domain of the AAA+ protease <lb/>FtsH is tilted with respect to the membrane to facilitate substrate entry. J. <lb/>Biol. Chem. 296, 100029 <lb/>4. Okuno, T., and Ogura, T. (2013) FtsH protease-mediated regulation of <lb/>various cellular functions. Subcell. Biochem. 66, 53-69 <lb/>5. Kamal, S. M., Rybtke, M. L., Nimtz, M., Sperlein, S., Giske, C., Trcek, <lb/>J., et al. (2019) Two FtsH proteases contribute to fitness and adapta-<lb/>tion of Pseudomonas aeruginosa clone C strains. Front. Microbiol. 10, <lb/>1372 <lb/>6. Basta, D. W., Angeles-Albores, D., Spero, M. A., Ciemniecki, J. A., and <lb/>Newman, D. K. (2020) Heat-shock proteases promote survival of Pseu-<lb/>domonas aeruginosa during growth arrest. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. <lb/>117, 4358-4367 <lb/>7. Basta, D. W., Bergkessel, M., and Newman, D. K. (2017) Identification of <lb/>fitness determinants during energy-limited growth arrest in Pseudomonas <lb/>aeruginosa. mBio 8, e01170-17 <lb/>8. Thomanek, N., Arends, J., Lindemann, C., Barkovits, K., Meyer, H. E., <lb/>Marcus, K., et al. (2018) Intricate crosstalk between lipopolysaccharide, <lb/>phospholipid and fatty acid metabolism in Escherichia coli modulates <lb/>proteolysis of LpxC. Front. Microbiol. 9, 3285 <lb/>9. Ogura, T., Inoue, K., Tatsuta, T., Suzaki, T., Karata, K., Young, K., et al. <lb/>(1999) Balanced biosynthesis of major membrane components through <lb/>regulated degradation of the committed enzyme of lipid A biosynthesis by <lb/>the AAA protease FtsH (HflB) in Escherichia coli. Mol. Microbiol. 31, <lb/>833-844 <lb/>10. Hari, S. B., Morehouse, J. P., Baker, T. A., and Sauer, R. T. (2023) FtsH <lb/>degrades kinetically stable dimers of cyclopropane fatty acid synthase via <lb/>an internal degron. Mol. Microbiol. 119, 101-111 <lb/>11. Römling, U., Kader, A., Sriramulu, D. D., Simm, R., and Kronvall, G. <lb/>(2005) Worldwide distribution of Pseudomonas aeruginosa clone C <lb/>strains in the aquatic environment and cystic fibrosis patients. Environ. <lb/>Microbiol. 7, 1029-1038 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Divergent FtsH protease functionality <lb/></note>

			<page>16</page>

            <note place="footnote"> J. Biol. Chem. (2024) 300(2) 105622 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>12. Lee, C., Klockgether, J., Fischer, S., Trcek, J., Tümmler, B., and Römling, <lb/>U. (2020) Why? -successful Pseudomonas aeruginosa clones with a focus <lb/>on clone C. FEMS Microbiol. Rev. 44, 740-762 <lb/>13. Kamal, S. M., Simpson, D. J., Wang, Z., Gänzle, M., and Römling, U. <lb/>(2021) Horizontal transmission of stress resistance genes shape the <lb/>ecology of beta-and gamma-proteobacteria. Front. Microbiol. 12, 696522 <lb/>14. Asahara, Y., Atsuta, K., Motohashi, K., Taguchi, H., Yohda, M., and Yoshida, <lb/>M. (2000) FtsH recognizes proteins with unfolded structure and hydrolyzes <lb/>the carboxyl side of hydrophobic residues. J. Biochem. 127, 931-937 <lb/>15. Akiyama, Y., Kihara, A., Mori, H., Ogura, T., and Ito, K. (1998) Roles <lb/>of the periplasmic domain of Escherichia coli FtsH (HflB) in protein <lb/>interactions and activity modulation. J. Biol. Chem. 273, <lb/>22326-22333 <lb/>16. Akiyama, Y., Yoshihisa, T., and Ito, K. (1995) FtsH, a membrane-bound <lb/>ATPase, forms a complex in the cytoplasmic membrane of Escherichia <lb/>coli. J. Biol. Chem. 270, 23485-23490 <lb/>17. Niwa, H., Tsuchiya, D., Makyio, H., Yoshida, M., and Morikawa, K. (2002) <lb/>Hexameric ring structure of the ATPase domain of the membrane-<lb/>integrated metalloprotease FtsH from Thermus thermophilus HB8. <lb/>Structure 10, 1415-1423 <lb/>18. Krzywda, S., Brzozowski, A. M., Verma, C., Karata, K., Ogura, T., and <lb/>Wilkinson, A. J. (2002) The crystal structure of the AAA domain of the <lb/>ATP-dependent protease FtsH of Escherichia coli at 1.5 A resolution. <lb/>Structure 10, 1073-1083 <lb/>19. Bieniossek, C., Schalch, T., Bumann, M., Meister, M., Meier, R., and <lb/>Baumann, U. (2006) The molecular architecture of the metalloprotease <lb/>FtsH. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 103, 3066-3071 <lb/>20. Akiyama, Y., and Ito, K. (2001) Roles of homooligomerization and <lb/>membrane association in ATPase and proteolytic activities of FtsH <lb/>in vitro. Biochemistry 40, 7687-7693 <lb/>21. Herman, C., Prakash, S., Lu, C. Z., Matouschek, A., and Gross, C. A. <lb/>(2003) Lack of a robust unfoldase activity confers a unique level of sub-<lb/>strate specificity to the universal AAA protease FtsH. Mol. Cell 11, <lb/>659-669 <lb/>22. Bittner, L. M., Arends, J., and Narberhaus, F. (2017) When, how and why? <lb/>Regulated proteolysis by the essential FtsH protease in Escherichia coli. <lb/>Biol. Chem. 398, 625-635 <lb/>23. Keiler, K. C., Waller, P. R., and Sauer, R. T. (1996) Role of a peptide <lb/>tagging system in degradation of proteins synthesized from damaged <lb/>messenger RNA. Science 271, 990-993 <lb/>24. Hari, S. B., and Sauer, R. T. (2016) The AAA+ FtsH protease degrades an <lb/>ssrA-tagged model protein in the inner membrane of Escherichia coli. <lb/>Biochemistry 55, 5649-5652 <lb/>25. Herman, C., Thevenet, D., D&apos;Ari, R., and Bouloc, P. (1995) Degradation of <lb/>sigma 32, the heat shock regulator in Escherichia coli, is governed by HflB. <lb/>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 92, 3516-3520 <lb/>26. Kihara, A., Akiyama, Y., and Ito, K. (1995) FtsH is required for proteolytic <lb/>elimination of uncomplexed forms of SecY, an essential protein translo-<lb/>case subunit. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 92, 4532-4536 <lb/>27. Akiyama, Y., Kihara, A., and Ito, K. (1996) Subunit a of proton ATPase F0 <lb/>sector is a substrate of the FtsH protease in Escherichia coli. FEBS Lett. <lb/>399, 26-28 <lb/>28. Akiyama, Y., Kihara, A., Tokuda, H., and Ito, K. (1996) FtsH (HflB) is an <lb/>ATP-dependent protease selectively acting on SecY and some other <lb/>membrane proteins. J. Biol. Chem. 271, 31196-31201 <lb/>29. Tomoyasu, T., Gamer, J., Bukau, B., Kanemori, M., Mori, H., Rutman, A. <lb/>J., et al. (1995) Escherichia coli FtsH is a membrane-bound, ATP-<lb/>dependent protease which degrades the heat-shock transcription factor <lb/>sigma 32. EMBO J. 14, 2551-2560 <lb/>30. Arsene, F., Tomoyasu, T., Mogk, A., Schirra, C., Schulze-Specking, A., <lb/>and Bukau, B. (1999) Role of region C in regulation of the heat shock <lb/>gene-specific sigma factor of Escherichia coli, sigma32. J. Bacteriol. 181, <lb/>3552-3561 <lb/>31. Yura, T. (2019) Regulation of the heat shock response in Escherichia coli: <lb/>history and perspectives. Genes Genet. Syst. 94, 103-108 <lb/>32. Tomoyasu, T., Ogura, T., Tatsuta, T., and Bukau, B. (1998) Levels of <lb/>DnaK and DnaJ provide tight control of heat shock gene expression and <lb/>protein repair in Escherichia coli. Mol. Microbiol. 30, 567-581 <lb/>33. Qiao, Z., Yokoyama, T., Yan, X. F., Beh, I. T., Shi, J., Basak, S., et al. (2022) <lb/>Cryo-EM structure of the entire FtsH-HflKC AAA protease complex. <lb/>Cell Rep. 39, 110890 <lb/>34. Kihara, A., Akiyama, Y., and Ito, K. (1997) Host regulation of lysogenic <lb/>decision in bacteriophage lambda: transmembrane modulation of FtsH <lb/>(HflB), the cII degrading protease, by HflKC (HflA). Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. <lb/>U. S. A. 94, 5544-5549 <lb/>35. Chauleau, M., Mora, L., Serba, J., and de Zamaroczy, M. (2011) FtsH-<lb/>dependent processing of RNase colicins D and E3 means that only the <lb/>cytotoxic domains are imported into the cytoplasm. J. Biol. Chem. 286, <lb/>29397-29407 <lb/>36. Hinz, A., Lee, S., Jacoby, K., and Manoil, C. (2011) Membrane proteases <lb/>and aminoglycoside antibiotic resistance. J. Bacteriol. 193, 4790-4797 <lb/>37. Herman, C., Thevenet, D., Bouloc, P., Walker, G. C., and D&apos;Ari, R. (1998) <lb/>Degradation of carboxy-terminal-tagged cytoplasmic proteins by the <lb/>Escherichia coli protease HflB (FtsH). Genes Dev. 12, 1348-1355 <lb/>38. Gottesman, S., Roche, E., Zhou, Y., and Sauer, R. T. (1998) The ClpXP <lb/>and ClpAP proteases degrade proteins with carboxy-terminal peptide tails <lb/>added by the SsrA-tagging system. Genes Dev. 12, 1338-1347 <lb/>39. Obrist, M., and Narberhaus, F. (2005) Identification of a turnover element <lb/>in region 2.1 of Escherichia coli sigma32 by a bacterial one-hybrid <lb/>approach. J. Bacteriol. 187, 3807-3813 <lb/>40. Obrist, M., Langklotz, S., Milek, S., Fuhrer, F., and Narberhaus, F. (2009) <lb/>Region C of the Escherichia coli heat shock sigma factor RpoH (sigma 32) <lb/>contains a turnover element for proteolysis by the FtsH protease. FEMS <lb/>Microbiol. Lett. 290, 199-208 <lb/>41. Vostrukhina, M., Popov, A., Brunstein, E., Lanz, M. A., Baumgartner, R., <lb/>Bieniossek, C., et al. (2015) The structure of Aquifex aeolicus FtsH in the <lb/>ADP-bound state reveals a C2-symmetric hexamer. Acta Crystallogr. D <lb/>Biol. Crystallogr. 71, 1307-1318 <lb/>42. Römling, U., Wingender, J., Muller, H., and Tümmler, B. (1994) A major <lb/>Pseudomonas aeruginosa clone common to patients and aquatic habitats. <lb/>Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 60, 1734-1738 <lb/>43. Kerr, K. G., and Snelling, A. M. (2009) Pseudomonas aeruginosa: a <lb/>formidable and ever-present adversary. J. Hosp. Infect. 73, 338-344 <lb/>44. Lansbury, L., Lim, B., Baskaran, V., and Lim, W. S. (2020) Co-infections in <lb/>people with COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J. Infect. <lb/>81, 266-275 <lb/>45. Qu, J., Cai, Z., Liu, Y., Duan, X., Han, S., Liu, J., et al. (2021) Persistent <lb/>bacterial coinfection of a COVID-19 patient caused by a genetically <lb/>adapted Pseudomonas aeruginosa chronic colonizer. Front. Cell Infect. <lb/>Microbiol. 11, 641920 <lb/>46. Lee, C., Wigren, E., Trcek, J., Peters, V., Kim, J., Hasni, M. S., et al. (2015) <lb/>A novel protein quality control mechanism contributes to heat shock <lb/>resistance of worldwide-distributed Pseudomonas aeruginosa clone C <lb/>strains. Environ. Microbiol. 17, 4511-4526 <lb/>47. Wiehlmann, L., Wagner, G., Cramer, N., Siebert, B., Gudowius, P., Mo-<lb/>rales, G., et al. (2007) Population structure of Pseudomonas aeruginosa. <lb/>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 104, 8101-8106 <lb/>48. Fischer, S., Klockgether, J., Moran Losada, P., Chouvarine, P., Cramer, N., <lb/>Davenport, C. F., et al. (2016) Intraclonal genome diversity of the major <lb/>Pseudomonas aeruginosa clones C and PA14. Environ. Microbiol. Rep. 8, <lb/>227-234 <lb/>49. Seemüller, E., Sule, S., Kube, M., Jelkmann, W., and Schneider, B. (2013) <lb/>The AAA+ ATPases and HflB/FtsH proteases of &apos;Candidatus Phyto-<lb/>plasma Mali&apos;: phylogenetic diversity, membrane topology, and relation-<lb/>ship to strain virulence. Mol. Plant Microbe Interact. 26, 367-376 <lb/>50. Jollard, C., Foissac, X., Desque, D., Razan, F., Garcion, C., Beven, L., et al. <lb/>(2019) Flavescence doree phytoplasma has multiple ftsH genes that are <lb/>differentially expressed in plants and insects. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 21, 150 <lb/>51. Lee, C., Franke, K. B., Kamal, S. M., Kim, H., Lünsdorf, H., Jäger, J., et al. <lb/>(2018) Stand-alone ClpG disaggregase confers superior heat tolerance to <lb/>bacteria. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 115, E273-E282 <lb/>52. Fernandez-Cuenca, F., Lopez-Cerero, L., Cabot, G., Oliver, A., Lopez-<lb/>Mendez, J., Recacha, E., et al. (2020) Nosocomial outbreak linked to a <lb/>flexible gastrointestinal endoscope contaminated with an amikacin-<lb/>resistant ST17 clone of Pseudomonas aeruginosa. Eur. J. Clin. Micro-<lb/>biol. Infect. Dis. 39, 1837-1844 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Divergent FtsH protease functionality <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">J. Biol. Chem. (2024) 300(2) 105622</note>

            <page>17 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>53. Jacob, J. S., and Tschen, J. (2020) Hot tub-associated Pseudomonas <lb/>folliculitis: a case report and review of host risk factors. Cureus 12, <lb/>e10623 <lb/>54. Ruer, M., Krainer, G., Groger, P., and Schlierf, M. (2018) ATPase and <lb/>protease domain movements in the bacterial AAA+ protease FtsH are <lb/>driven by thermal fluctuations. J. Mol. Biol. 430, 4592-4602 <lb/>55. Aravind, L., and Ponting, C. P. (1999) The cytoplasmic helical linker <lb/>domain of receptor histidine kinase and methyl-accepting proteins is <lb/>common to many prokaryotic signalling proteins. FEMS Microbiol. Lett. <lb/>176, 111-116 <lb/>56. Stopp, M., Schubert, C., and Unden, G. (2021) Conversion of the sensor <lb/>kinase DcuS to the fumarate sensitive state by interaction of the <lb/>bifunctional transporter DctA at the TM2/PAS(C)-Linker region. Mi-<lb/>croorganisms 9, 1397 <lb/>57. Buchner, S., Schlundt, A., Lassak, J., Sattler, M., and Jung, K. (2015) <lb/>Structural and functional analysis of the signal-transducing linker in the <lb/>pH-responsive one-component system CadC of Escherichia coli. J. Mol. <lb/>Biol. 427, 2548-2561 <lb/>58. Zhu, Y., and Inouye, M. (2003) Analysis of the role of the EnvZ linker <lb/>region in signal transduction using a chimeric Tar/EnvZ receptor protein, <lb/>Tez1. J. Biol. Chem. 278, 22812-22819 <lb/>59. Newman, J. R., and Fuqua, C. (1999) Broad-host-range expression vectors <lb/>that carry the l-arabinose-inducible Escherichia coli araBAD promoter <lb/>and the araC regulator. Gene 227, 197-203 <lb/>60. Bruckner, R. C., Gunyuzlu, P. L., and Stein, R. L. (2003) Coupled kinetics <lb/>of ATP and peptide hydrolysis by Escherichia coli FtsH protease. <lb/>Biochemistry 42, 10843-10852 <lb/>61. Baytshtok, V., Baker, T. A., and Sauer, R. T. (2015) Assaying the kinetics <lb/>of protein denaturation catalyzed by AAA+ unfolding machines and <lb/>proteases. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 112, 5377-5382 <lb/>62. Sundar, S., McGinness, K. E., Baker, T. A., and Sauer, R. T. (2010) <lb/>Multiple sequence signals direct recognition and degradation of protein <lb/>substrates by the AAA+ protease HslUV. J. Mol. Biol. 403, 420-429 <lb/>63. Martin, A., Baker, T. A., and Sauer, R. T. (2005) Rebuilt AAA + motors <lb/>reveal operating principles for ATP-fuelled machines. Nature 437, <lb/>1115-1120 <lb/>64. Altschul, S. F., Gish, W., Miller, W., Myers, E. W., and Lipman, D. J. <lb/>(1990) Basic local alignment search tool. J. Mol. Biol. 215, 403-410 <lb/>65. Apweiler, R., Bairoch, A., Wu, C. H., Barker, W. C., Boeckmann, B., <lb/>Ferro, S., et al. (2004) UniProt: the universal protein knowledgebase. <lb/>Nucleic Acids Res. 32, D115-119 <lb/>66. Higgins, D. G., and Sharp, P. M. (1988) CLUSTAL: a package for per-<lb/>forming multiple sequence alignment on a microcomputer. Gene 73, <lb/>237-244 <lb/>67. Kumar, S., Stecher, G., Li, M., Knyaz, C., and Tamura, K. (2018) Mega X: <lb/>molecular evolutionary genetics analysis across computing platforms. <lb/>Mol. Biol. Evol. 35, 1547-1549 <lb/>68. Letunic, I., and Bork, P. (2021) Interactive Tree of Life (iTOL) v5: an <lb/>online tool for phylogenetic tree display and annotation. Nucleic Acids <lb/>Res. 49, W293-W296 <lb/>69. Higgins, D. G., Thompson, J. D., and Gibson, T. J. (1996) Using CLUS-<lb/>TAL for multiple sequence alignments. Methods Enzymol. 266, 383-402 <lb/>70. Crooks, G. E., Hon, G., Chandonia, J. M., and Brenner, S. E. (2004) <lb/>WebLogo: a sequence logo generator. Genome Res. 14, 1188-1190 <lb/>71. Lamiable, A., Thevenet, P., Rey, J., Vavrusa, M., Derreumaux, P., and <lb/>Tuffery, P. (2016) PEP-FOLD3: faster de novo structure prediction for linear <lb/>peptides in solution and in complex. Nucleic Acids Res. 44, W449-454 <lb/>72. Raman, S., Vernon, R., Thompson, J., Tyka, M., Sadreyev, R., Pei, J., et al. <lb/>(2009) Structure prediction for CASP8 with all-atom refinement using <lb/>Rosetta. Proteins 77, 89-99 <lb/>73. Jumper, J., Evans, R., Pritzel, A., Green, T., Figurnov, M., Ronneberger, O., <lb/>et al. (2021) Highly accurate protein structure prediction with AlphaFold. <lb/>Nature 596, 583-589 <lb/>74. Dosztanyi, Z., Csizmok, V., Tompa, P., and Simon, I. (2005) IUPred: web <lb/>server for the prediction of intrinsically unstructured regions of proteins <lb/>based on estimated energy content. Bioinformatics 21, 3433-3434 <lb/>75. Romero, P., Obradovic, Z., Li, X., Garner, E. C., Brown, C. J., and Dunker, <lb/>A. K. (2001) Sequence complexity of disordered protein. Proteins 42, 38-48 <lb/>76. Peng, K., Vucetic, S., Radivojac, P., Brown, C. J., Dunker, A. K., and <lb/>Obradovic, Z. (2005) Optimizing long intrinsic disorder predictors with <lb/>protein evolutionary information. J. Bioinform. Comput. Biol. 3, 35-60 <lb/>77. Peng, K., Radivojac, P., Vucetic, S., Dunker, A. K., and Obradovic, Z. <lb/>(2006) Length-dependent prediction of protein intrinsic disorder. BMC <lb/>Bioinform. 7, 208 <lb/>78. Tsirigos, K. D., Peters, C., Shu, N., Kall, L., and Elofsson, A. (2015) The <lb/>TOPCONS web server for consensus prediction of membrane protein <lb/>topology and signal peptides. Nucleic Acids Res. 43, W401-407 <lb/>79. Hessa, T., Meindl-Beinker, N. M., Bernsel, A., Kim, H., Sato, Y., Lerch-<lb/>Bader, M., et al. (2007) Molecular code for transmembrane-helix recog-<lb/>nition by the Sec61 translocon. Nature 450, 1026-1030 <lb/>80. Tang, G., Peng, L., Baldwin, P. R., Mann, D. S., Jiang, W., Rees, I., et al. <lb/>(2007) EMAN2: an extensible image processing suite for electron mi-<lb/>croscopy. J. Struct. Biol. 157, 38-46 <lb/>81. Pettersen, E. F., Goddard, T. D., Huang, C. C., Couch, G. S., Greenblatt, <lb/>D. M., Meng, E. C., et al. (2004) UCSF Chimera-a visualization system <lb/>for exploratory research and analysis. J. Comput. Chem. 25, 1605-1612 <lb/>82. Beamer, L. J., and Pabo, C. O. (1992) Refined 1.8 A crystal structure of the <lb/>lambda repressor-operator complex. J. Mol. Biol. 227, 177-196 <lb/>83. Morehouse, J. P., Baker, T. A., and Sauer, R. T. (2022) FtsH degrades <lb/>dihydrofolate reductase by recognizing a partially folded species. Protein <lb/>Sci. 31, e4410 <lb/>84. Scharfenberg, F., Serek-Heuberger, J., Coles, M., Hartmann, M. D., <lb/>Habeck, M., Martin, J., et al. (2015) Structure and evolution of N-do-<lb/>mains in AAA metalloproteases. J. Mol. Biol. 42, 910-923 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Divergent FtsH protease functionality <lb/></note>

			<page>18</page>

            <note place="footnote">J. Biol. Chem. (2024) 300(2) 105622</note>


	</text>
</tei>
