<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Quantum Monte Carlo study of thin parahydrogen films on graphite <lb/>Jie-Ru Hu 1 , Massimo Boninsegni * <lb/>a Department of Physics, University of Alberta, Edmonton, T6G 2H5, Alberta, Canada <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The low-temperature properties of one and two layers of parahydrogen adsorbed on graphite are investigated the-<lb/>oretically through Quantum Monte Carlo simulations. We adopt a microscopic model that explicitly includes the <lb/>corrugation of the substrate. We study the phase diagram of a monolayer up to second layer promotion, and the pos-<lb/>sible occurrence of superfluidity in the second layer. We obtain results down to a temperature as low as 8 mK. We <lb/>find second-layer promotion to occur at a considerably greater coverage than obtained in previous calculations and <lb/>estimated experimentally; moreover, we find no evidence of a possible finite superfluid response in the second layer, <lb/>disproving recent theoretical predictions. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>The physics of a thin (few layers) film of parahydro-<lb/>gen molecules (p-H 2 ) adsorbed on a strongly attractive <lb/>corrugated substrate like graphite, has been extensively <lb/>studied experimentally [1, 2, 3, 4, 5] and theoretically <lb/>[6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11]. The basic features of the phase di-<lb/>agram of the system at low temperature are well under-<lb/>stood, but there exist specific aspects which still require <lb/>elucidation. <lb/>Adsorption of p-H 2 on essentially any substrate [12] <lb/>occurs through the formation of successive crystalline <lb/>layers. On a strongly attractive substrate such as <lb/>graphite, the first layer is physically distinct, featuring <lb/>an equilibrium phase registered with the underlying car-<lb/>bon lattice, which transitions at higher coverage to a <lb/>compressible, incommensurate crystal through a series <lb/>of domain-wall phases. It is interesting to compare p-<lb/>H 2 with 4 He, i.e., the archetypal (Bose) quantum fluid, <lb/>and it seems fair to state that there is little qualitative <lb/>difference between the phase diagram of the first layer <lb/>of either substance on graphite, as the energetics is in <lb/>both cases dominated by the substrate attraction. On the <lb/>other hand, the second layer displays very different be-<lb/>havior for the two systems, with 4 He forming a liquid <lb/>(superfluid) film while p-H 2 remains solid. <lb/>An outstanding puzzle is represented by the value of <lb/>coverage θ p of a p-H 2 monolayer at which molecular <lb/></body>

			<front> * Corresponding author: m.boninsegni@ualberta.ca <lb/>1 Present address: State Key Laboratory of Precision Spectroscopy, <lb/>East China Normal University, Shanghai 200062, China. <lb/></front>

			<body>promotion to the second layer begins to occur. There <lb/>exists an experimental estimate [3] for θ p ≈ 0.094 Å -2 , <lb/>considerably lower (by about 15%) than the correspond-<lb/>ing coverage for a 4 He monolayer on the same substrate <lb/>[13]. This seems counter-intuitive, as a) one would ex-<lb/>pect a parahydrogen monolayer to be more compress-<lb/>ible than one of helium, which displays much more pro-<lb/>nounced quantum effects [14], and b) the attractive well <lb/>of the effective potential between a p-H 2 molecule and a <lb/>graphite substrate [15] is about three times deeper than <lb/>that for a 4 He atom and the same substrate [16]. <lb/>Microscopic calculations for realistic models of the <lb/>system have yielded conflicting results; specifically, an <lb/>early study [10] making use of Quantum Monte Carlo <lb/>(QMC) simulations predicted second-layer promotion <lb/>at a coverage very close to that reported in Ref. [3], but <lb/>a subsequent study [17] of the same system based on <lb/>a slightly different QMC methodology showed no pro-<lb/>motion to second layer up to a coverage ∼ 0.110 Å -2 , <lb/>i.e., very similar to that observed for a 4 He monolayer. <lb/>Both calculations treated the underlying graphite sub-<lb/>strate as smooth, i.e., ignored its corrugation. While <lb/>the cause of the disagreement between the two cal-<lb/>culations is unclear, it is conceivable that corrugation <lb/>could have a significant effect on θ p . However, in Ref. <lb/>[17] the same calculation was carried out for a p-H 2 <lb/>monolayer on graphene (which is some 10% less attrac-<lb/>tive than graphite), explicitly including substrate corru-<lb/>gation, and the second layer promotion coverage was <lb/>found to be close to 0.11 Å -2 . One certainly expects a <lb/>comparable or even greater value for the more attractive <lb/></body>

			<front>Preprint submitted to Results in Physics <lb/>May 14, 2024 <lb/>arXiv:2403.12637v4 [cond-mat.other] 11 May 2024 <lb/></front>

			<body>graphite. <lb/>A second point of contention has to do with the sec-<lb/>ond (solid) layer, for which the claim of a possible finite <lb/>superfluid response in the ground state has been recently <lb/>made [11]. This seems very similar to other predictions <lb/>of superfluidity (SF) of either solid helium or hydrogen <lb/>in various settings (usually in confinement) arrived at <lb/>using the same ground state methodology, all of which <lb/>have been shown to be incorrect. There is presently no <lb/>experimental evidence of superfluid behavior of p-H 2 , <lb/>except (possibly) in very small clusters (∼ 15 molecules <lb/>or less) [18]; all reliable theoretical studies of parahy-<lb/>drogen, including in reduced dimensions [19], thin films <lb/>[20] and in disordered and/or inhomogeneous environ-<lb/>ments [21, 22, 23] have shown that exchanges of in-<lb/>distinguishable molecules, which are known to under-<lb/>lie SF, are strongly suppressed even at low tempera-<lb/>ture. However, no microscopic calculation for the sec-<lb/>ond layer of p-H 2 on graphite has yet been carried out, <lb/>independent of that of Ref. [11], in which the corru-<lb/>gation of the graphite substrate is taken into account. <lb/>Although a recent study [24] for 4 He provides strong <lb/>evidence that the effect of substrate corrugation on the <lb/>superfluid properties of the second layer is minimal, it <lb/>seems worthwhile to investigate in greater depth the sce-<lb/>nario of a possible superfluid response on the second <lb/>layer of p-H 2 on graphite, taking the corrugation of the <lb/>substrate into account. <lb/>To clarify the above outstanding issues, we have car-<lb/>ried out extensive QMC simulations of a thin (1 and 2 <lb/>layers) film of p-H 2 adsorbed on graphite at low tem-<lb/>perature (as low as 8 mK), making use of the same ab <lb/>initio potential proposed in Ref. [10], describing the in-<lb/>teraction of a p-H 2 molecule with the substrate, specif-<lb/>ically designed to capture the effects of substrate corru-<lb/>gation. We aim to compare directly our results to those <lb/>obtained therein. For the 2-layer system, we focused <lb/>on ascertaining whether there is a significant enhance-<lb/>ment of quantum exchanges of indistinguishable p-H 2 <lb/>molecules at subKelvin temperatures, and with that the <lb/>possible onset of a weak superfluid response as pre-<lb/>dicted in Ref. [11], at the same thermodynamic con-<lb/>ditions. <lb/>Our results yield, for the monolayer system, a <lb/>second-layer promotion coverage close to 0.110 Å -2 , <lb/>i.e., consistent with both that found on graphene as well <lb/>as on a smooth graphite substrate [17], significantly <lb/>above the existing experimental estimate from Ref. [3]. <lb/>While our results are generally qualitatively consistent <lb/>with those of Ref. [10], there are significant numeri-<lb/>cal discrepancies, which we believe may be at the root <lb/>of the difference between the promotion coverage pre-<lb/>dicted therein and in this work. Still, the disaccord of <lb/>our calculation with experiment remains, and at this <lb/>point can only be solved by new, independent experi-<lb/>mental and theoretical studies. <lb/>No evidence of any &quot;supersolid&quot; phase is observed for <lb/>the second layer. Our simulations, carried out down to <lb/>a temperature as low as 8 mK, yield the same paucity <lb/>of quantum-mechanical exchanges of indistinguishable <lb/>molecules observed at temperatures of the order of 1 <lb/>K, down to temperatures more than two orders of mag-<lb/>nitude lower; no discernible difference can be seen in <lb/>the one-body density matrix computed at temperature <lb/>T = 4 K and T =0.03 K, once again confirming that <lb/>this system forms an insulating crystal which does not <lb/>undergo a superfluid transition in the T → 0, which <lb/>is the conclusion reached in many previous theoretical <lb/>studies, consistent with all existing experimental obser-<lb/>vations. It is therefore our submission that the predic-<lb/>tion of Ref. [11] is incorrect. <lb/>The remainder of this paper is organized as follows: <lb/>in section 2 we describe the microscopic model of the <lb/>system; in Sec. 3 we briefly describe our methodology; <lb/>we present and discuss our results in Sec. 4 and finally <lb/>outline our conclusions in Sec. 5. <lb/>2. Model <lb/>We consider an ensemble of N p-H 2 molecules, re-<lb/>garded as point-like spin-zero bosons, moving in the <lb/>presence of a graphite substrate, modeled as described <lb/>below. The system is enclosed in a simulation cell of <lb/>sizes L x × L y × L z , with periodic boundary conditions <lb/>in all directions (but L z is taken large enough to make <lb/>boundary conditions in the z direction irrelevant). The <lb/>graphite substrate lies on the z = 0 plane; in our mono-<lb/>layer simulations, we set L x = 34.08 Å, L y = 36.8927 <lb/>Å; on the other hand, those of a two-layer system were <lb/>carried out for a significantly smaller simulation cell, <lb/>one with L x = 21.3 Å and L y = 19.6761 Å. The reason <lb/>is that our goal in this case is exclusively that of as-<lb/>certaining whether the conditions for SF exist, and the <lb/>superfluid response is typically enhanced in a finite sys-<lb/>tem with periodic boundary conditions. Thus, if no su-<lb/>perfluid signal is observed in a system of small size, a <lb/>fortiori that will be the case in the thermodynamic limit. <lb/>The quantum-mechanical many-body Hamiltonian <lb/>reads as follows: <lb/>Ĥ = -λ <lb/>i <lb/>∇ 2 <lb/>i + <lb/>i&lt; j <lb/>v(r i j ) + <lb/>i <lb/>V(r i ). <lb/>(1) <lb/>The first and third sums run over all the N p-H 2 <lb/>molecules, λ = 12.031 KÅ 2 ; the second sum runs over <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>all pairs of molecules, r i j ≡ |r i -r j |, r i ≡ (x i , y i , z i ) being <lb/>the position of the ith molecule, and v(r) is the accepted <lb/>Silvera-Goldman pair potential [25], which describes <lb/>the interaction between two p-H 2 molecules. V is the <lb/>potential describing the interaction of a p-H 2 molecule <lb/>with the graphite substrate; for consistency with the cal-<lb/>culation of Ref. [10], we use the same potential utilized <lb/>therein, which can be expressed as follows: <lb/>V(r) = V 0 (z) + <lb/>G <lb/>V G (z) exp [i (G x x + G y y)] (2) <lb/>V 0 (z) is a term that only depends on the distance of the <lb/>molecule from the basal plane; it corresponds to the lat-<lb/>erally averaged potential normally utilized to represent <lb/>a flat substrate [15]. The sum in the second term of <lb/>the right-hand side of (2) runs over all reciprocal lattice <lb/>vectors G ≡ (G x , G y , 0) of the graphite substrate. The <lb/>functions V 0 (z), V G (z) are provided in Ref. [10]. We <lb/>come back to the details of the evaluation of (2) in our <lb/>simulations in Sec. 3. <lb/>3. Methodology <lb/>The QMC methodology adopted here is the canoni-<lb/>cal [26, 27] version of the continuous-space Worm Al-<lb/>gorithm [28, 29], a well-established finite temperature <lb/>QMC technique. Details of the simulations carried out <lb/>in this work are standard, and therefore the reader is re-<lb/>ferred to the original references. However, because as <lb/>mentioned above there are numerical discrepancies be-<lb/>tween our results and those reported in Ref. [10], where <lb/>a similar computational technique was utilized, we are <lb/>going to provide here enough technical information to <lb/>enable others to repeat the calculation, in order to inves-<lb/>tigate the possible causes of the disagreement. <lb/>The calculation of the potential energy of interaction <lb/>between a p-H 2 molecule and the graphite substrate (Eq. <lb/>2) has been carried out in the simulation by tabulating <lb/>and interpolating the functions V 0 (z) and V G (z), and by <lb/>performing a direct, on-the-fly summation over terms <lb/>associated to a subset of reciprocal lattice vectors; we <lb/>found that the inclusion of the twelve shortest recipro-<lb/>cal lattice vectors is sufficient to achieve a numerically <lb/>accurate representation of V(r). <lb/>The key physical quantities computed in this work <lb/>are the energetics and the superfluid fraction ρ S (T ) of <lb/>the top layer as a function of temperature, for which we <lb/>use the well-known winding number estimator [30]. We <lb/>also evaluate structural properties, such as the averaged <lb/>molecular density profile along the direction z, perpen-<lb/>dicular to the substrate, in order to investigate the oc-<lb/>currence of promotion to the second layer. Crystalline <lb/>order in both layers may also be monitored through the <lb/>visual inspection of the imaginary time paths. <lb/>Simulations of a two-layer system have been carried <lb/>out by a) considering molecules in the top and bottom <lb/>layer as two distinct species and b) regarding molecules <lb/>in the bottom layer as distinguishable quantum particles <lb/>(i.e., &quot;Boltzmannons&quot;). Both approximations are jus-<lb/>tified by the de facto absence of quantum-mechanical <lb/>exchanges involving molecules in the bottom layer; on <lb/>the other hand, molecules in the top layers are consid-<lb/>ered indistinguishable and their quantum (Bose) statis-<lb/>tics is fully accounted for (as we shall see, even changes <lb/>of molecules in the top layers turn out to be exceed-<lb/>ingly infrequent even at the lowest temperature consid-<lb/>ered here). <lb/>We used the primitive approximation for the short <lb/>imaginary-time (τ) propagator and carried out extrap-<lb/>olation of all the computed physical observable in the <lb/>τ → 0 limit. This point warrants a quantitative discus-<lb/>sion because this is where the first major difference with <lb/>Ref. [10] is noted. <lb/>Figure 1: Energy per molecule at T = 1 K, for coverage θ = 0.0636 <lb/>Å -2 , computed as a function of the time step τ. Dotted line is a <lb/>quadratic fit to the data for τ → 0. It is not possible to include in <lb/>the quadratic fit data points obtained for values of the time step above <lb/>1.5625 × 10 -3 K -1 . <lb/>Fig. 1 show the computed energy per p-H 2 molecule <lb/>at temperature T = 1 K as a function of the time step <lb/>τ, for coverage θ = 0.0636 Å -2 , namely the coverage <lb/>at which a commensurate monolayer crystal forms, as <lb/>will be shown below. Because the primitive approxima-<lb/>tion is used, one expects quadratic behavior as a func-<lb/>tion of τ, in the τ → 0 limit. As shown in the figure, <lb/>the estimate for τ = 1.5625 × 10 -3 K -1 is indistin-<lb/>guishable, within statistical uncertainties, from the ex-<lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>trapolated one, namely -480.3(4) K. This is only a few <lb/>K lower than the value reported in Ref. [10], namely <lb/>-476.9 K, but what is puzzling is that the value of the <lb/>time step used therein was 0.005 K -1 , which in our cal-<lb/>culation yields an energy estimate some ∼ 17 K lower <lb/>than the value reported in Ref. [10]. The reason for <lb/>this disagreement is unknown to us, at this time, as the <lb/>calculations are based on the same potentials; it cannot, <lb/>in our view, be attributed to the different system sizes <lb/>(the calculation of Ref. [10] used N = 60 molecules, <lb/>whereas N = 80 was the number in this work, at this <lb/>coverage), nor to the difference in temperature between <lb/>the two calculations (we come back to this point below), <lb/>nor to a possible, different choice of wave vectors in-<lb/>cluded in the expansion of the potential (2). <lb/>The energy estimates quoted below for the energy <lb/>were all obtained either by carrying out explicitly the <lb/>τ → 0 extrapolation, as shown above, or using a time <lb/>step τ = 1.5625 × 10 -3 K -1 . On the other hand, it has <lb/>been observed in this work, as well as in 4 He studies <lb/>based on the same methodology [24], that convergence <lb/>of the results for structural and superfluid properties is <lb/>achieved with a considerably greater (up to four times) <lb/>time step than that needed for the energy. <lb/>4. Results <lb/>4.1. Monolayer <lb/>We begin by discussing the energetics of a mono-<lb/>layer. In general, we observe that the estimates for the <lb/>energy, as well as for all structural properties, remain <lb/>essentially unchanged (the energy within less than 1%) <lb/>for temperatures below 4 K. In the zero-coverage limit <lb/>(i.e., one particle), we obtain an energy per molecule <lb/>of -454.7(1) K, which is very close to the estimate ob-<lb/>tained by Crowell and Brown for the laterally averaged <lb/>potential [15]. <lb/>In our monolayer calculations, we cut off the pair <lb/>potential at 17 Å, i.e., we set it to zero beyond that <lb/>distance. We estimate the energy contribution arising <lb/>from pairs of molecules at distances greater than that to <lb/>amount to less than 0.01% of the total energy. <lb/>Fig. 2 shows the computed energy per p-H 2 molecule as <lb/>a function of coverage, at the two temperatures T = 1 <lb/>K (filled circles) and T = 4 K (filled boxes). Also <lb/>shown (open circles) are the estimates from Ref. [10]. <lb/>There is an obvious numerical discrepancy between the <lb/>results obtained here, which on the scale of the figure <lb/>are temperature independent, and those offered in Ref. <lb/>[10]. The difference is just a few K at the equilibrium <lb/>coverage θ = 0.0636 Å -2 , which is the same on both <lb/>Figure 2: Energy per p-H 2 molecule on a corrugated graphite substrate <lb/>computed in this work as a function of coverage θ, at the two temper-<lb/>atures T = 1 K (filled circles) and T = 4 K (filled boxes). Dashed <lb/>line is the ground state energy at the equilibrium density, attained for <lb/>coverage θ = 0.0636 Å -2 . Open circles refer to data from Ref. [10] at <lb/>T = 2 K. Statistical errors are smaller than symbol sizes. <lb/>works and corresponds to the formation of a solid mono-<lb/>layer commensurate with the underlying substrate, but <lb/>increases at higher coverage and becomes as large as <lb/>∼ 20 K in the proximity of the coverage estimated in <lb/>Ref. [10] to correspond to second layer promotion. <lb/>The origin of such a large disagreement between <lb/>these two calculations is unclear, especially given that, <lb/>as shown above, the choice of time step made by the <lb/>authors of Ref. [10] should have resulted in an underes-<lb/>timation of the energy. While the overall trend is simi-<lb/>lar in both calculations, the specific physical predictions <lb/>made in Ref. [10] are, in our view, likely to be affected <lb/>by the quantitative inaccuracy of their energy estimates. <lb/>Altogether, the physics of the monolayer is very sim-<lb/>ilar to that observed on graphene; we did not attempt to <lb/>characterize it in detail in this work, focusing instead on <lb/>the issue of second-layer promotion, attempting to elu-<lb/>cidate the outstanding disagreement between some of <lb/>the theoretical calculations and the existing experimen-<lb/>tal estimates. <lb/>Fig. 3 shows the p-H 2 density profile n(z) in the direc-<lb/>tion perpendicular to the substrate, computed at T = 1 <lb/>K for a coverage θ = 0.1098 Å -2 , i.e., well above the <lb/>experimentally estimated second-layer promotion cov-<lb/>erage θ p [3]. In Ref. [10] it was argued that simulations <lb/>based on the many-body Hamiltonian (1) yield a value <lb/>of the second-layer promotion coverage in agreement <lb/>with experiment, based on an analysis of density pro-<lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>o <lb/>Figure 3: Density profile n(z) (in Å -3 ) in the direction perpendicular <lb/>to the graphite substrate for a monolayer p-H 2 film of coverage θ = <lb/>0.1098 Å -2 , computed by simulation at temperature T = 1 K. Dashed <lb/>line shows the corresponding profile for coverage θ = 0.0636 Å -2 . <lb/>files such as that shown in Fig. 3, displaying a &quot;bump&quot; <lb/>at distances ∼ 6.5 Å from the substrate for coverages <lb/>close to, or above the experimentally estimated θ p . Our <lb/>simulations, on the other hand, give no evidence of <lb/>that until a much higher value of coverage is reached, <lb/>slightly above 0.11 Å -2 , which is consistent both with <lb/>the value found on graphene [17] as well as for 4 He on <lb/>graphite [31]. <lb/>Fig. 4 shows an instantaneous configurational snap-<lb/>shot (particle world lines) from a simulation of a p-<lb/>H 2 monolayer at temperature T = 1 K for coverage <lb/>θ = 0.1018 Å -2 . Although the world lines extend far <lb/>out, up to distances considerably greater than the av-<lb/>erage width of the layer, nevertheless all particles re-<lb/>main localized within it, as shown by the positions of <lb/>the path centroids. There is no evidence of the forma-<lb/>tion of an actual second layer. We therefore conclude <lb/>that promotion to the second layer does not take place <lb/>for θ ∼ 0.094 Å -2 as contended in Ref. [10], but at <lb/>considerably higher coverage, ∼ 0.11 Å -2 , value is very <lb/>close to that predicted for 4 He as well, on the same sub-<lb/>strate [31]. <lb/>4.1.1. Bilayer <lb/>We now discuss the results of our simulation of a <lb/>two-layer p-H 2 system, aimed at investigating the pos-<lb/>sible occurrence of a finite superfluid response in the <lb/>top layer, in the low-temperature limit. The possible SF <lb/>of a film of p-H 2 has been investigated and ruled out <lb/>in numerous theoretical calculations, characterized by a <lb/>wide variety of physical settings [20, 21, 22, 23]. Ev-<lb/>Figure 4: Snapshot of instantaneous many-particle world lines for a <lb/>p-H 2 monolayer of coverage θ = 0.1016 Å -2 at temperature T = 1 K, <lb/>projected on the x -z plane. <lb/>ery time the conclusion was arrived at that exchanges <lb/>among identical molecules, which underlie any super-<lb/>fluid response, are too strongly suppressed in this sys-<lb/>tem, mainly due to the large value of the diameter of the <lb/>repulsive core of the potential at short distances. <lb/>Figure 5: Density map of p-H 2 molecules in the bottom (left) and top <lb/>(layer), at temperature T = 8 mK. The total coverage is 0.165 Å -2 , <lb/>the two-dimensional density of the bottom layer is 0.100 Å -2 . <lb/>Nonetheless, it was recently contended that the top <lb/>layer of a two-layer film of coverage 0.165 Å -2 may dis-<lb/>play a small but finite superfluid response in the ground <lb/>state [11]. If confirmed, this would be a remarkable <lb/>finding, as the top layer still displays crystalline long-<lb/>range order, which would render this the first example <lb/>of a supersolid system (there is no indication that the top <lb/>solid layer would be commensurate with the underlying <lb/>one). <lb/>In order to provide an independent theoretical assess-<lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>ment of this intriguing prediction, we carried out simu-<lb/>lations at finite temperature of the same system, based <lb/>on model (1), which is physically equivalent to that uti-<lb/>lized in Ref. [11], as explicitly verified in Ref. [24]. As <lb/>mentioned above, we purposefully utilized a relatively <lb/>small simulation cell and overall number of particles, <lb/>enabling us to explore as wide a range of temperature <lb/>as possible, enabling us to detect any sign of build-up <lb/>of superfluid order. We set the coverage to be the same <lb/>as that of Ref. [11], namely 0.165 Å -2 , with a two-<lb/>dimensional density equal to 0.100 Å -2 in the bottom <lb/>layer [32], and 0.065 in the top one, just as in Ref. [11]. <lb/>It is worth restating that the absence of SF in such a <lb/>small system which comprises 42 p-H 2 molecules <lb/>the bottom layer and 27 on the top one, necessarily im-<lb/>plies no SF in the thermodynamic limit. <lb/>Fig. 5 shows two-dimensional density maps for the <lb/>bottom and top layers of the simulated two-layer sys-<lb/>tem, at a temperature T =8 mK. The first obvious remark <lb/>is that the system forms crystal phases on both layers, <lb/>as expected; p-H 2 molecules are initially given the posi-<lb/>tions shown in the figure for the bottom layer, namely <lb/>a triangular lattice incommensurate with the graphite <lb/>substrate is assumed, consistently with our present ex-<lb/>perimental and theoretical understanding of the system. <lb/>Molecules in the top layer, on the other hand, are ini-<lb/>tially placed at random initial position at a distance <lb/>z = 6 Å from the graphite basal plane, i.e., the regular <lb/>crystalline arrangement shown in the right part of Fig. <lb/>5 forms spontaneously, despite the fact that the cell is <lb/>not designed to accommodate a triangular lattice with <lb/>that number particles; just as observed in other studies, <lb/>if the system cannot form the preferred structure, due to <lb/>geometrical constraints, it will do the &quot;next best thing&quot;, <lb/>namely form whatever triangular crystal can be formed <lb/>inside the cell. <lb/>Another thing that can be noticed is that p-H 2 <lb/>molecules in both layers are highly localized, that there <lb/>is no visible overlap between quantum delocalization <lb/>clouds of adjacent molecules to indicate that exchanges <lb/>among molecules are essentially non-existent, and this <lb/>is precisely what is observed in the simulations, i.e., <lb/>even those carried out at a temperature as low as 8 mK <lb/>show the nearly complete absence of exchanges of p-H 2 <lb/>molecules. Consequently, no evidence of any finite su-<lb/>perfluid response is observed; the superfluid fraction of <lb/>the top layer is zero (within the precision of the com-<lb/>puting machine) even at a temperature as low as T = 8 <lb/>mK. This observation is consistent with all other studies <lb/>of p-H 2 performed by us, though it is worth mentioning <lb/>that, at least to our knowledge 8 mK is the lowest tem-<lb/>perature attained so far in QMC simulations of either <lb/>4 He or p-H 2 . <lb/>Figure 6: Laterally averaged one-particle density matrix for the top <lb/>layer of p-H 2 in a two-layer system of coverage 0.165 Å -2 . Results <lb/>shown are for the two temperature T = 4 K (circles) and T = 0.03 K <lb/>(diamonds). Statistical errors are smaller of symbol sizes. <lb/>Fig. 6 compares the laterally averaged one-body den-<lb/>sity matrix computed for the top layer, at the two tem-<lb/>peratures T = 4 K and T = 0.03 K. The most remark-<lb/>able aspect of this result, to our knowledge, is the virtual <lb/>indistinguishability of the two results, at least within <lb/>the scale of the figure. The absence of any noticeable <lb/>temperature dependence within a temperature range that <lb/>spans over two orders of magnitude constitutes, in our <lb/>view, strong evidence that the system is not superfluid, <lb/>even in the T = 0 limit. One could argue, of course, that <lb/>the temperature that we considered is not low enough to <lb/>observe the onset of SF. We do not believe that to be the <lb/>case, however, as the hypothetical superfluid transition <lb/>should conform to the Bereszinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless <lb/>paradigm, and in particular, fulfill the well-known &quot;uni-<lb/>versal jump&quot; condition [33], based on which one can <lb/>obtain a fairly reliable quantitative estimate [34] of the <lb/>superfluid transition temperature T c . In this case, we <lb/>can expect T c ≈ 10 mK, i.e., simulations of a system <lb/>of size as small as that considered here at T = 8 mK <lb/>should yield clear evidence of quantum-mechanical ex-<lb/>changes of top-layer molecules and/or a finite in-plane <lb/>superfluid response, if the predictions of Ref. [11] were <lb/>correct. <lb/>5. Discussion and Conclusions <lb/>We have carried out extensive QMC simulations <lb/>of monolayer and bilayer p-H 2 films adsorbed on a <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>graphite substrate, making use of a microscopic model <lb/>in which the corrugation of the substrate is fully taken <lb/>into account. For a monolayer, we report important <lb/>numerical differences with respect to prior theoreti-<lb/>cal work [10], the most important being the estimated <lb/>second-layer promotion coverage, which we find to be <lb/>some ∼ 15% higher. The resolution of the discrepancy <lb/>requires additional independent theoretical studies car-<lb/>ried out with the same methodology and microscopic <lb/>model. For the moment, however, we note that signifi-<lb/>cantly greater binding energy of the p-H 2 molecules ob-<lb/>tained in this work, at coverages above the equilibrium <lb/>one. Our estimate is also in disagreement with the only <lb/>(at least to our knowledge) existing experimental de-<lb/>termination of the second-layer promotion coverage for <lb/>this system; while we cannot comment on experimental <lb/>details, it seems counterintuitive that second-layer pro-<lb/>motion should occur at a lower coverage for a system <lb/>such as p-H 2 , which experiences a significantly stronger <lb/>attraction to the graphite substrate and whose behavior <lb/>is considerably less quantum than 4 He. Nonetheless, <lb/>it should be mentioned that our result is also at vari-<lb/>ance with that of a recent ground state calculation [11], <lb/>based on a different model of the substrate, which pre-<lb/>dicts a value of the second layer promotion coverage in <lb/>agreement with the experiment. <lb/>We have also investigated the possible occurrence of <lb/>a finite superfluid response in the top layer of a bilayer <lb/>system, at the same condition of coverage in which <lb/>other authors have maintained that SF could occur in <lb/>the low-temperature limit. Our simulations, reaching a <lb/>temperature as low as 8 mK, confirm the same observa-<lb/>tions consistently and repeatedly made for p-H 2 in all <lb/>physical settings explored so far, namely that this sys-<lb/>tem fails to display SF due to the strong suppression of <lb/>quantum-mechanical exchanges. This parallels the con-<lb/>clusion reached for 4 He monolayers on graphene, for <lb/>which a very similar contention of SF was made, based <lb/>on the same approach [35]. In our submission, our cal-<lb/>culation disproves the contention of Ref. [11], the latest <lb/>of a series of incorrect predictions [19, 22, 23, 36, 37] of <lb/>a finite SF response based on a computational technol-<lb/>ogy (Diffusion Monte Carlo) known to be affected by <lb/>serious limitations, chiefly the bias due to the use of a <lb/>finite population of random walkers [38, 39, 40, 41, 42]. <lb/>In general, all bulk supersolid phases that have been <lb/>established theoretically hinge on some &quot;softening&quot; of <lb/>the repulsive core of the pairwise interaction at short <lb/>distances [43, 44]. <lb/></body>

            <div type="annex">6. Declaration of Competing Interests <lb/>The authors declare no known competing financial <lb/>interests or personal relationships that could appear to <lb/>influence the work reported in this paper. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">7. Acknowledgments <lb/>This work was supported by the Natural Sciences and <lb/>Engineering Research Council of Canada. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] M. Nielsen, J. P. McTague, L. Passell, Neutron scattering studies <lb/>of physisorbed monolayers on graphite, in: J. G. Dash, J. Ru-<lb/>valds (Eds.), Phase Transitions in Surface Films, Vol. 51 of <lb/>NATO ASI Series B: Physics, Springer, New York, NY, 1980, <lb/>pp. 127-163. doi:10.1007/978-1-4613-3057-8. <lb/>[2] H. J. Lauter, H. Godfrin, V. L. P. Frank, P. Leiderer, Neutron <lb/>scattering studies of quantum films, in: H. Taub, G. Torzo, <lb/>H. J. Lauter, S. C. Fain (Eds.), Phase Transitions in Sur-<lb/>face Films 2, Vol. 267 of NATO ASI Series B: Physics, <lb/>Springer, New York, NY, 1990, pp. 135-151. doi:10.1007/ <lb/>978-1-4684-5970-8. <lb/>[3] H. Wiechert, Thermodynamic and neutron-diffraction studies of <lb/>H 2 and D 2 multilayers physisorbed on graphite, in: A. F. G. <lb/>Wyatt, H. J. Lauter (Eds.), Excitations in Two-Dimensional and <lb/>Three-Dimensional Quantum Fluids, Vol. 257 of NATO ASI Se-<lb/>ries B: Physics, Springer, New York, NY, 1991, pp. 499-510. <lb/>doi:10.1007/978-1-4684-5937-1. <lb/>[4] H. Wiechert, Ordering phenomena and phase transitions in <lb/>the physisorbed quantum systems H 2 , HD and D 2 , Physica <lb/>B 169 (1) (1991) 144-152. doi:10.1016/0921-4526(91) <lb/>90221-Y. <lb/>[5] R. S. Morton, D. P. van der Werf, P. C. Rice-Evans, Phase tran-<lb/>sitions in monolayer hydrogen and deuterium on graphite, Phys. <lb/>Rev. B 62 (2000) 17031-17034. doi:10.1103/PhysRevB. <lb/>62.17031. <lb/>[6] S. C. Wang, L. Senbetu, C.-W. Woo, Superlattice of parahydro-<lb/>gen physisorbed on graphite surface, J. Low Temp. Phys. 41 <lb/>(1980) 611-628. doi:10.1007/BF00114368. <lb/>[7] X. Z. Ni, L. W. Bruch, Hartree and Jastrow approximations for <lb/>monolayer solids of Ne, D 2 , H 2 , 4 He, and 3 He, Phys. Rev. B 33 <lb/>(1986) 4584-4595. doi:10.1103/PhysRevB.33.4584. <lb/>[8] A. D. Novaco, Phonon Spectrum and Density of States for the <lb/>√ <lb/>3 × <lb/>√ <lb/>3R30 • Phase of D 2 and H 2 on Graphite, Phys. Rev. <lb/>Lett. 60 (1988) 2058-2061. doi:10.1103/PhysRevLett.60. <lb/>2058. <lb/>[9] J. M. Gottlieb, L. W. Bruch, Calculated properties of the com-<lb/>mensurate monolayers of helium and hydrogen on graphite, <lb/>Phys. Rev. B 41 (1990) 7195-7196. doi:10.1103/PhysRevB. <lb/>41.7195. <lb/>[10] K. Nho, E. Manousakis, Submonolayer molecular hydrogen on <lb/>graphite: A path-integral Monte Carlo study, Phys. Rev. B 65 <lb/>(2002) 115409. doi:10.1103/PhysRevB.65.115409. <lb/>[11] M. C. Gordillo, J. Boronat, Supersolidity in the second layer of <lb/>para-H 2 adsorbed on graphite, Phys. Rev. B 105 (2022) 094501. <lb/>doi:10.1103/PhysRevB.105.094501. <lb/>[12] M. Boninsegni, Melting of a p-H 2 monolayer on a lithium sub-<lb/>strate, Phys. Rev. B 70 (12) (2004) 125405. doi:10.1103/ <lb/>PhysRevB.70.125405. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[13] D. S. Greywall, P. A. Busch, Heat Capacity of Fluid Monolayers <lb/>of 4 He, Phys. Rev. Lett. 67 (25) (1991) 3535-3538. doi:10. <lb/>1103/PhysRevLett.67.3535. <lb/>[14] For example, the equilibrium density of p-H 2 is almost 50% <lb/>greater than that of 4 He in two dimensions. <lb/>[15] A. D. Crowell, J. S. Brown, Laterally averaged interaction <lb/>potentials for 1 H 2 and 2 H 2 on the (0001) graphite surface, <lb/>Surface Science 123 (2-3) (1982) 296-304. doi:10.1016/ <lb/>0039-6028(82)90330-2. <lb/>[16] W. E. Carlos, M. W. Cole, Interaction between a He atom and <lb/>a graphite surface, Surf. Sci. 91 (1) (1980) 339-357. doi:10. <lb/>1016/0039-6028(80)90090-4. <lb/>[17] M. Dusseault, M. Boninsegni, Adsorption of parahydrogen on <lb/>graphene, Phys. Rev. B 97 (2018) 205403. doi:10.1103/ <lb/>PhysRevB.97.205403. <lb/>[18] S. Grebenev, B. Sartakov, J. P. Toennies, A. F. Vilesov, Evidence <lb/>for Superfluidity in Para-Hydrogen Clusters Inside Helium-4 <lb/>Droplets at 0.15 Kelvin, Science 289 (2000) 1532-1535. <lb/>[19] M. Boninsegni, Ground state phase diagram of parahydrogen in <lb/>one dimension, Phys. Rev. Lett. 111 (23) (2013) 235303. doi: <lb/>10.1103/PhysRevLett.111.235303. <lb/>[20] M. Boninsegni, Quasi-2D parahydrogen: On the Verge of Turn-<lb/>ing Superfluid?, J. Low Temp. Phys. 202 (1-2) (2021) 1-10. <lb/>doi:10.1007/s10909-020-02548-6. <lb/>[21] J. Turnbull, M. Boninsegni, Disorder and the elusive superfluid <lb/>phase of para-hydrogen, Phys. Rev. B 78 (14) (2008) 144509-<lb/>144509. doi:10.1103/PhysRevB.78.144509. <lb/>[22] M. Boninsegni, Search for superfluidity in supercooled liquid <lb/>parahydrogen, Phys. Rev. B 97 (2018) 054517. doi:10.1103/ <lb/>PhysRevB.97.054517. <lb/>[23] M. Boninsegni, Absence of superfluidity in a parahydrogen <lb/>film intercalated within a crystal of Na atoms, Phys. Rev. B <lb/>93 (5) (2016) 054507-054507. doi:10.1103/PhysRevB.93. <lb/>054507. <lb/>[24] M. Boninsegni, S. Moroni, Superfluid transition of the second <lb/>layer of 4 He on graphite: Does substrate corrugation matter?, <lb/>Res. in Phys. 44 (2023) 106186. doi:https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.rinp.2022.106186. <lb/>[25] I. F. Silvera, V. V. Goldman, The isotropic intermolecular po-<lb/>tential for H 2 and D 2 in the solid and gas phases, The Journal of <lb/>Chemical Physics 69 (9) (1978) 4209-4213. doi:10.1063/1. <lb/>437103. <lb/>[26] F. Mezzacapo, M. Boninsegni, Superfluidity and quantum melt-<lb/>ing of p-H 2 clusters, Phys. Rev. Lett. 97 (2006) 045301. doi: <lb/>10.1103/PhysRevLett.97.045301. <lb/>[27] F. Mezzacapo, M. Boninsegni, Structure, superfluidity, and <lb/>quantum melting of hydrogen clusters, Phys. Rev. A 75 (2007) <lb/>033201. doi:10.1103/PhysRevA.75.033201. <lb/>[28] M. Boninsegni, N. Prokof&apos;ev, B. Svistunov, Worm algorithm for <lb/>continuous-space path integral monte carlo simulations, Phys. <lb/>Rev. Lett. 96 (2006) 070601. doi:10.1103/PhysRevLett. <lb/>96.070601. <lb/>[29] M. Boninsegni, N. V. Prokof&apos;ev, B. V. Svistunov, Worm al-<lb/>gorithm and diagrammatic monte carlo: A new approach to <lb/>continuous-space path integral monte carlo simulations, Phys. <lb/>Rev. E 74 (2006) 036701. doi:10.1103/PhysRevE.74. <lb/>036701. <lb/>[30] E. L. Pollock, D. M. Ceperley, Path-integral computation of su-<lb/>perfluid densities, Phys. Rev. B 36 (1987) 8343-8352. doi: <lb/>10.1103/PhysRevB.36.8343. <lb/>[31] P. Corboz, M. Boninsegni, L. Pollet, M. Troyer, Phase dia-<lb/>gram of 4 He adsorbed on graphite, Phys. Rev. B 78 (24) (2008) <lb/>245414-245414. doi:10.1103/PhysRevB.78.245414. <lb/>[32] Our calculation points to a significantly greater value of the den-<lb/>sity for the bottom layer, as our estimated second layer promo-<lb/>tion density is well above 0.100 Å -2 , and the bottom layer is <lb/>well-known to undergo compression upon adsorbing a top layer. <lb/>Nonetheless, because the goal of this part of the project is ex-<lb/>clusively to assess the prediction of Ref. [11], we duplicate the <lb/>thermodynamic conditions proposed therein. <lb/>[33] D. R. Nelson, J. M. Kosterlitz, Universal jump in the superfluid <lb/>density of two-dimensional superfluids, Phys. Rev. Lett. 39 (19) <lb/>(1977) 1201-1205. doi:10.1103/PhysRevLett.39.1201. <lb/>[34] C. Zhang, B. Capogrosso-Sansone, M. Boninsegni, N. V. <lb/>Prokof&apos;ev, B. V. Svistunov, Superconducting transition temper-<lb/>ature of the bose one-component plasma, Phys. Rev. Lett. 130 <lb/>(2023) 236001. doi:10.1103/PhysRevLett.130.236001. <lb/>[35] J. Happacher, P. Corboz, M. Boninsegni, L. Pollet, Phase di-<lb/>agram of 4 He on graphene, Phys. Rev. B 87 (2013) 094514. <lb/>doi:10.1103/PhysRevB.87.094514. <lb/>[36] M. Boninsegni, On the existence of supersolid 4 He monolayer <lb/>films, J. Low Temp. Phys. 165 (3-4) (2011) 67-77. doi:10. <lb/>1007/s10909-011-0393-6. <lb/>[37] F. Cinti, M. Boninsegni, Absence of superfluidity in 2d <lb/>dipolar bose striped crystals, Journal of Low Tempera-<lb/>ture Physics 196 (5-6) (2019) 413-422. <lb/>doi:10.1007/ <lb/>s10909-019-02209-3. <lb/>[38] M. Boninsegni, Phase separation in mixtures of hard core <lb/>bosons, Phys. Rev. Lett. 87 (2001) 087201. doi:10.1103/ <lb/>PhysRevLett.87.087201. <lb/>[39] M. Boninsegni, S. Moroni, Population size bias in Diffusion <lb/>Monte Carlo, Phys. Rev. E 86 (2012) 056712. doi:10.1103/ <lb/>PhysRevE.86.056712. <lb/>[40] E. M. Inack, G. Giudici, T. Parolini, G. Santoro, S. Pilati, <lb/>Understanding quantum tunneling using diffusion monte carlo <lb/>simulations, Phys. Rev. A 97 (2018) 032307. doi:10.1103/ <lb/>PhysRevA.97.032307. <lb/>[41] K. Ghanem, N. Liebermann, A. Alavi, Population control bias <lb/>and importance sampling in full configuration interaction quan-<lb/>tum monte carlo, Phys. Rev. B 103 (2021) 155135. doi: <lb/>10.1103/PhysRevB.103.155135. <lb/>[42] J. Brand, M. Yang, E. Pahl, Stochastic differential equation ap-<lb/>proach to understanding the population control bias in full con-<lb/>figuration interaction quantum monte carlo, Phys. Rev. B 105 <lb/>(2022) 235144. doi:10.1103/PhysRevB.105.235144. <lb/>[43] M. Boninsegni, Supersolid phases of cold atom assemblies, J. <lb/>Low Temp. Phys. 168 (3-4) (2012) 137-149. doi:10.1007/ <lb/>s10909-012-0571-1. <lb/>[44] Y. Kora, M. Boninsegni, Patterned supersolids in dipolar bose <lb/>systems, J. Low Temp. Phys. 197 (5-6) (2019) 337-347. doi: <lb/>10.1007/s10909-019-02229-z. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>8 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
