<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Qualitative and quantitative return-to-sport test battery and second anterior cruciate ligament injury risk factors</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Lauren</forename>
            <surname>Butler</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Alexa</forename>
            <surname>Martinez</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Mina</forename>
            <surname>Entessari</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Gabriel</forename>
            <surname>Cardenas</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Margaret</forename>
            <surname>Wright</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Dai</forename>
            <surname>Sugimoto</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-29T11:43:18.962465Z">29.10.2025 11:43:18</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1136$1$bmjsem-2024-002000</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>BMJ</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmjsem-2024-002000</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Lauren Butler, Alexa Martinez, Mina Entessari, Gabriel Cardenas, Margaret Wright, Dai Sugimoto. (2024). Qualitative and quantitative return-to-sport test battery and second anterior cruciate ligament injury risk factors. BMJ Open Sport &amp;amp; Exercise Medicine, 10(3), e002000. DOI: 10.1136/bmjsem-2024-002000</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-29T11:43:18.962465Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-29T11:43:18.962465Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>1 <lb/>Abhishek A, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003980. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003980 <lb/>ORIGINAL RESEARCH <lb/>Risk-stratifiedmonitoringfor <lb/>sulfasalazinetoxicity:prognosticmodel <lb/>developmentandvalidation <lb/>Abhishek Abhishek <lb/>, 1 Matthew Grainge, 2 Tim Card <lb/>, 2 Hywel C Williams, 2,3 <lb/>Maarten W Taal, 4 Guruprasad P Aithal, 4,5 Christopher P Fox, 4 Christian D Mallen, 6 <lb/>Matthew D Stevenson, 7 Georgina Nakafero, 1 Richard Riley 8 <lb/>To cite: Abhishek A, <lb/>Grainge M, Card T, et al. <lb/>Risk-stratified monitoring <lb/>for sulfasalazine toxicity: <lb/>prognostic model development <lb/>and validation. RMD Open <lb/>2024;10:e003980. doi:10.1136/ <lb/>rmdopen-2023-003980 <lb/>► Additional supplemental <lb/>material is published online only. <lb/>To view, please visit the journal <lb/>online (https:// doi. org/ 10. 1136/ <lb/>rmdopen-2023-003980). <lb/>GN and RR contributed equally. <lb/>Received 6 December 2023 <lb/>Accepted 30 January 2024 <lb/>For numbered affiliations see <lb/>end of article. <lb/>Correspondence to <lb/>Dr Abhishek Abhishek; <lb/>Abhishek. Abhishek@ <lb/>nottingham. ac. uk <lb/>Epidemiology <lb/>© Author(s) (or their <lb/>employer(s)) 2024. Re-use <lb/>permitted under CC BY. <lb/>Published by BMJ. <lb/>ABSTRACT: <lb/>Background Sulfasalazine-induced cytopenia, <lb/>nephrotoxicity and hepatotoxicity is uncommon during <lb/>long-term treatment. Some guidelines recommend <lb/>3 monthly monitoring blood tests indefinitely during <lb/>long-term treatment while others recommend stopping <lb/>monitoring after 1 year. To rationalise monitoring, we <lb/>developed and validated a prognostic model for clinically <lb/>significant blood, liver or kidney toxicity during established <lb/>sulfasalazine treatment. <lb/>Design Retrospective cohort study. <lb/>Setting UK primary care. Data from Clinical Practice <lb/>Research Datalink Gold and Aurum formed independent <lb/>development and validation cohorts. <lb/>Participants Age ≥18 years, new diagnosis of an <lb/>inflammatory condition and sulfasalazine prescription. <lb/>Study period 1 January 2007 to 31 December 2019. <lb/>Outcome Sulfasalazine discontinuation with abnormal <lb/>monitoring blood-test result. <lb/>Analysis Patients were followed up from 6 months after <lb/>first primary care prescription to the earliest of outcome, <lb/>drug discontinuation, death, 5 years or 31 December <lb/>2019. Penalised Cox regression was performed to develop <lb/>the risk equation. Multiple imputation handled missing <lb/>predictor data. Model performance was assessed in terms <lb/>of calibration and discrimination. <lb/>Results 8936 participants were included in the <lb/>development cohort (473 events, 23 299 person-years) <lb/>and 5203 participants were included in the validation <lb/>cohort (280 events, 12 867 person-years). Nine candidate <lb/>predictors were included. The optimism adjusted R 2 <lb/>D and <lb/>Royston D statistic in the development data were 0.13 <lb/>and 0.79, respectively. The calibration slope (95% CI) and <lb/>Royston D statistic (95% CI) in validation cohort was 1.19 <lb/>(0.96 to 1.43) and 0.87 (0.67 to 1.07), respectively. <lb/>Conclusion This prognostic model for sulfasalazine <lb/>toxicity uses readily available data and should be used <lb/>to risk-stratify blood-test monitoring during established <lb/>sulfasalazine treatment. <lb/></front>

        <body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Sulfasalazine is commonly used in the treat-<lb/>ment of inflammatory diseases such as rheu-<lb/>matoid arthritis (RA), psoriatic arthritis <lb/>(PsA), axial spondylarthritis, reactive arthritis <lb/>and infrequently in the management of <lb/>inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) (the latter <lb/></body>

        <front>WHAT IS ALREADY KNOWN ON THIS TOPIC <lb/>⇒ Hepatic, haematological and renal toxicity from sul-<lb/>fasalazine occurs uncommonly after the first few <lb/>months of treatment. <lb/>⇒ Nevertheless, the manufacturers and some special-<lb/>ist societies, for example, the American College of <lb/>Rheumatology recommend monitoring blood tests <lb/>at 3 monthly intervals during established treatment. <lb/>⇒ Other guidelines, for example, from the British <lb/>Society of Rheumatology recommend no monitoring <lb/>after the first 2 years of treatment. <lb/>⇒ It is not known whether hepatic, haematological and <lb/>renal toxicities due to sulfasalazine can be predicted <lb/>and monitoring be risk-stratified. <lb/>WHAT THIS STUDY ADDS <lb/>⇒ This study developed a prognostic model that dis-<lb/>criminated patients at varying risk of sulfasalazine <lb/>toxicity during long-term treatment. <lb/>⇒ It had excellent performance characteristics in an <lb/>independent validation cohort. <lb/>⇒ The model performed well across age groups, and <lb/>in people with rheumatoid arthritis and other inflam-<lb/>matory conditions. <lb/>⇒ Any cytopenia or liver enzyme elevation prior to <lb/>start of follow-up, chronic kidney disease stage 3, <lb/>diabetes, methotrexate prescription, leflunomide <lb/>prescription and age were strong predictors of sul-<lb/>fasalazine toxicity. <lb/>HOW THIS STUDY MIGHT AFFECT RESEARCH, <lb/>PRACTICE OR POLICY <lb/>⇒ This prognostic model uses information that can be <lb/>easily ascertained during clinical visits. <lb/>⇒ It can be used to inform decisions on the interval <lb/>between monitoring blood tests. <lb/>⇒ The results of this study ought to be considered by <lb/>national and international rheumatology guideline <lb/>writing groups to rationalise monitoring during long-<lb/>term sulfasalazine treatment. <lb/></front>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003980 on 7 March 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>

        <page>2 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Abhishek A, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003980. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003980 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/></note>

        <body>is mostly treated with 5-aminosalicylates due to a better <lb/>safety profile). 1-3 Although effective, sulfasalazine can <lb/>cause cytopenia and elevated liver enzymes typically in <lb/>the first 3-6 months of treatment, although late-onset <lb/>toxicity is reported. 4-16 Sulfasalazine can also cause cryst-<lb/>alluria and interstitial nephritis, and is not recommended <lb/>in those with severe renal impairment. 17 Cautious use <lb/>is recommended in those with mild-to-moderate renal <lb/>impairment. 17 <lb/>There is considerable inconsistency in guidance on <lb/>how to monitor patients on long-term sulfasalazine treat-<lb/>ment for asymptomatic bone marrow, liver and/or renal <lb/>toxicity. The British Society of Rheumatology (BSR) <lb/>guidelines recommend 2-4 weekly blood tests for full <lb/>blood count (FBC), liver function test (LFT), urea elec-<lb/>trolytes and creatinine (UE&amp;C) for the first 3 months of <lb/>treatment followed by 3 monthly testing in the first year <lb/>and no further monitoring blood tests thereafter. 18 On <lb/>the contrary, the American College of Rheumatology <lb/>(ACR) guidelines recommend close monitoring for the <lb/>first 3 months of treatment, followed by 3 monthly blood <lb/>testing for FBC, UE&amp;C and LFT during the entire dura-<lb/>tion of treatment. 19 The summary of product characteris-<lb/>tics for sulfasalazine recommends monitoring with FBC, <lb/>LFT and UE&amp;C at 3 monthly intervals during long-term <lb/>treatment. 20 However, whether everyone needs a fixed <lb/>monitoring schedule once established on sulfasalazine <lb/>treatment, or whether monitoring can be risk-stratified <lb/>during long-term treatment is not known. <lb/>To predict clinically significant laboratory abnormal-<lb/>ities during established sulfasalazine treatment and to <lb/>inform the frequency of testing, we have developed and <lb/>validated a prognostic model for clinically significant <lb/>myelotoxicity, hepatotoxicity and/or nephrotoxicity due <lb/>to sulfasalazine. <lb/>METHODS <lb/>Data source <lb/>Data from the Clinical Practice Research Datalink <lb/>(CPRD) Aurum and Gold were used for model devel-<lb/>opment and validation, respectively. 21 22 CPRD is an <lb/>anonymised longitudinal database of electronic health <lb/>records originated during clinical care in the National <lb/>Health Service in the UK. With almost universal coverage <lb/>of UK residents, participants that contributed data to the <lb/>CPRD are representative of the UK population. 21 The <lb/>CPRD includes information on demographic details, <lb/>lifestyle factors (eg, smoking, alcohol intake), diagnoses, <lb/>results of blood tests and details of primary care prescrip-<lb/>tions. CPRD Gold and Aurum complement each other in <lb/>terms of coverage of general practices due to their use of <lb/>different software for data capture. Some general prac-<lb/>tices that have contributed data to both databases are <lb/>identifiable using a bridging file provided by the CPRD. <lb/>Study design <lb/>Retrospective cohort study. <lb/>Study period <lb/>1 January 2007 to 31 December 2019. <lb/>Study population <lb/>Participants aged 18 years or older with a new diagnosis <lb/>of inflammatory disease (eg, RA, axial spondyloarthritis, <lb/>PsA and IBD) and prescribed sulfasalazine by their <lb/>general practitioner (GP) for ≥6 months were eligible. <lb/>Patients were required to have ≥1 year disease-free regis-<lb/>tration in their current general practice to be classi-<lb/>fied as having a new diagnosis. 23 Additionally, patients <lb/>were required to have received their first sulfasalazine <lb/>prescription either after the first record of inflammatory <lb/>disease in the CPRD or in the 90 days preceding. This <lb/>90-day period was allowed because recording of diagnosis <lb/>may lag prescriptions. These two requirements mini-<lb/>mised the chance of patients on long-term sulfasalazine <lb/>treatment appearing as new users of sulfasalazine when <lb/>they moved to a different general practice. Patients with <lb/>chronic liver disease, haematological disease and chronic <lb/>kidney disease (CKD) stage 4 or 5 prior to cohort entry <lb/>were excluded as described in a previous manuscript. 24 <lb/>Sulfasalazine prescriptions <lb/>In the UK, sulfasalazine initiation and dose escalation <lb/>occur in hospital outpatient clinics. During this period <lb/>prescriptions are issued by the hospital specialists. They <lb/>also organise monitoring blood tests and acts on any <lb/>abnormalities. Once a patient is established on treatment, <lb/>typically approximately 6 months after initiating on treat-<lb/>ment, the responsibility for prescribing and monitoring, <lb/>including with periodic blood tests is handed to the <lb/>patients&apos; GP as per the National Health Service (NHS) <lb/>shared-care protocols. During shared-care monitoring, <lb/>the GP seeks advice from the hospital specialist if there <lb/>are side effects including abnormal blood-test results, <lb/>and treatment changes are directed by the specialist. <lb/>Start of follow-up <lb/>Patients were followed up from 180 days after their first <lb/>primary care sulfasalazine prescription until the earliest <lb/>of outcome, death, transfer out of practice, 90-day <lb/>prescription gap, last data collection from practice, 31 <lb/>December 2019 or 5 years. <lb/>Outcome <lb/>Sulfasalazine toxicity-associated drug discontinuation was <lb/>the outcome of interest. This was defined as a prescrip-<lb/>tion gap of ≥90 days with either an abnormal blood-test <lb/>result or a diagnostic code for abnormal blood-test result <lb/>within ±60 days of the last prescription date. 25 The blood <lb/>tests were considered abnormal if any of the following <lb/>were present: total leucocyte count &lt;3.5×10 9 /L, neutro-<lb/>phil count &lt;1.6×10 9 /L, platelet count &lt;140×10 9 /L, <lb/>alanine transaminase (ALT) and/or aspartate transami-<lb/>nase (AST) &gt;100 IU/mL and decline in kidney function, <lb/>defined as either progression of CKD based on medical <lb/>codes recorded by the GP or &gt;26 µmol/L increase in <lb/>creatinine concentration, the threshold for consideration <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003980 on 7 March 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>

        <page>3 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Abhishek A, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003980. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003980 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Epidemiology Epidemiology Epidemiology <lb/></note>

        <body>of acute kidney injury (AKI). 18 26 In a previous valida-<lb/>tion study on methotrexate discontinuation, only 5.4% <lb/>of abnormal blood-test results in this time window were <lb/>potentially explained by an alternate illness. 25 <lb/>A random sample of sulfasalazine discontinuation <lb/>with abnormal blood-test results was drawn. Data for all <lb/>diagnostic codes entered during primary care consulta-<lb/>tions within ±60 days of the abnormal blood test result <lb/>were extracted. AA (rheumatology and general medicine <lb/>expertise) screened the list to identify outcomes that <lb/>could potentially be explained by an alternative condi-<lb/>tion or its treatment. <lb/>Predictors <lb/>These were selected by the clinical members of the study <lb/>team based on their clinical expertise and knowledge <lb/>of the published literature. Age, sex, body mass index <lb/>(BMI), alcohol intake and diabetes were included as <lb/>they associate with drug-induced liver injury (DILI). 27 28 <lb/>Individual inflammatory diseases were considered sepa-<lb/>rately because sulfasalazine toxicity is reported to be less <lb/>common in people with IBD than in those with RA. 3 <lb/>CKD stage 3 was included as it reduces sulfasalazine <lb/>clearance. 29 Statins, carbamazepine, valproate and <lb/>paracetamol were included as their use is associated <lb/>with sulfasalazine toxicity as per the British National <lb/>Formulary. Methotrexate, leflunomide, thiopurines <lb/>were included as they can cause cytopenia, elevated liver <lb/>enzymes and AKI. Either cytopenia (neutrophil count <lb/>&lt;2×10 9 /L, total leucocyte count &lt;4×10 9 /L or platelet <lb/>count &lt;150×10 9 /L) or elevated transaminase (ALT and/ <lb/>or AST &gt;35 IU/L) during the first 6 months of primary <lb/>care prescription were included as they predicted cyto-<lb/>penia and/or transaminitis in other studies. 30 31 <lb/>The latest record of demographic and lifestyle factors, <lb/>diseases recorded within 2 years prior to start of follow-up <lb/>and latest primary care prescriptions within 6 months <lb/>prior to start of follow-up were used to define predic-<lb/>tors except for CKD stage 3 that was defined using both <lb/>GP records and/or estimated glomerular filtration rate <lb/>30-59 mL/min. GPs typically review patients with long-<lb/>term conditions annually. A 2-year look-back period was <lb/>used to minimise the risk of missing data from those that <lb/>did not attend in the previous 12-months. <lb/>Patient and public involvement <lb/>Patient and public involvement members were involved <lb/>in selecting and prioritising the research question. They <lb/>advised to use readily available datasets for the study <lb/>rather than conduct an expensive and time-consuming <lb/>clinical trial. <lb/>Sample size <lb/>In a previously published cohort of 1321 patients with <lb/>RA, 85 stopped sulfasalazine with neutropenia, throm-<lb/>bocytopenia or elevated liver enzymes during a mean <lb/>follow-up of 2.39 years. 16 Assuming a similar incidence <lb/>of treatment discontinuation for model development, <lb/>the minimum sample size needed to minimise model <lb/>overfitting (a target shrinkage factor of 0.9) and ensure <lb/>precise estimation of overall risk was 1748 participants <lb/>(113 outcomes) based on a maximum of 25 parame-<lb/>ters, Cox-Snell R 2 value of 0.12, outcome rate of 0.027/ <lb/>person-year, 16 a 5-year time horizon and a mean follow-up <lb/>period of 2.39 years using the formulae of Riley et al. 32 <lb/>The sample size for external model validation was much <lb/>larger than the typically recommended minimum sample <lb/>size of 200 events. 33 <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>Multiple imputation handled missing data on BMI, <lb/>alcohol intake and sulfasalazine dose using chained <lb/>equations. 34 We carried out 10 imputations in the devel-<lb/>opment dataset and 5 imputations in the validation data-<lb/>set-a pragmatic approach considering the larger size <lb/>of CPRD Aurum. The imputation model included all <lb/>candidate predictors, Nelson-Aalen cumulative hazard <lb/>function and outcome variable. The data analysis was <lb/>undertaken using the Stata command &apos;mi estimate&apos; in a <lb/>combined dataset that included all imputations. <lb/>Model development <lb/>Fraction polynomial regression (first-degree) anal-<lb/>ysis was used to model non-linear risk relationships <lb/>with continuous predictors, but these were not better <lb/>than the linear terms (p&gt;0.05), hence were not <lb/>transformed. All 12 candidate predictors (19 param-<lb/>eters) were included in the Cox model and coeffi-<lb/>cients of each parameter estimated and combined <lb/>using Rubin&apos;s rule across the imputed datasets. The <lb/>risk equation for predicting an individual&apos;s risk of <lb/>sulfasalazine discontinuation with abnormal blood-<lb/>test results by 5 years follow-up was formulated in the <lb/>development data. The baseline survival function at <lb/>t=5 years, a non-parametric estimate of survival func-<lb/>tion when all predictor values are set to zero, which <lb/>is equivalent to the Kaplan-Meier product-limit esti-<lb/>mate, was estimated along with the estimated regres-<lb/>sion coefficients (β) and the individual&apos;s predictor <lb/>values (X). This led to the equation for the predicted <lb/>absolute risk over time 35 : <lb/>Predicted risk of sulfasalazine toxicity associated drug <lb/>discontinuation at 5 years=1-S 0 (t=5) exp(βX) , where S 0 (t=5) <lb/>is the baseline survival function at 5 years of follow-up <lb/>and βX is the linear predictor, β 1 x 1 +β 2 x 2 + … + β p x p . <lb/>Model internal validation and shrinkage <lb/>The performance of the model in terms of calibra-<lb/>tion (where 1.00 is the ideal) was assessed by plot-<lb/>ting agreement between predicted and observed <lb/>outcomes. Internal validation was performed to <lb/>correct performance estimates for optimism due to <lb/>overfitting by bootstrapping with replacement of 500 <lb/>samples of the development data. The full model <lb/>was fitted in each bootstrap sample and then its <lb/>performance was quantified in the bootstrap sample <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003980 on 7 March 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>

        <page>4 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Abhishek A, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003980. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003980 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/></note>

        <body>(apparent performance) and the original sample (test <lb/>model performance), and the optimism calculated <lb/>(difference in test performance and apparent perfor-<lb/>mance). A uniform shrinkage factor was estimated as <lb/>the average of calibration slopes from the bootstrap <lb/>samples. This process was repeated for all 10 imputed <lb/>datasets, and the final uniform shrinkage calculated <lb/>by averaging across the estimated shrinkage estimates <lb/>from each imputation. Optimism-adjusted estimates <lb/>of performance for the original model were then <lb/>calculated, as the original apparent performance <lb/>minus the optimism. <lb/>To account for overfitting during model develop-<lb/>ment process, the original β-coefficients were multi-<lb/>plied by the final uniform shrinkage factor and the <lb/>baseline hazards re-estimated conditional on the <lb/>shrunken β-coefficients to ensure that overall calibra-<lb/>tion was maintained, producing a final model. The <lb/>D statistic, a measure of discrimination, interpreted <lb/>as a log HR, the exponential of which gives the HR <lb/>Table 1 Distribution of candidate predictors in development and validation cohorts <lb/>Predictor* <lb/>Development cohort (CPRD Aurum) <lb/>N=8936 <lb/>Validation cohort (CPRD Gold) <lb/>N=5203 <lb/>Age, mean (SD) year <lb/>55.3 (14.8) <lb/>55.5 (14.8) <lb/>Female sex <lb/>5535 (61.9) <lb/>3240 (62.3) <lb/>Body mass index (kg/m 2 ) <lb/>&lt;18.5 <lb/>138 (1.5) <lb/>88 (1.7) <lb/>18.5-24.9 <lb/>2441 (27.3) <lb/>1428 (27.5) <lb/>25.0-29.9 <lb/>2840 (31.8) <lb/>1678 (32.3) <lb/>≥30 <lb/>2714 (30.4) <lb/>1626 (31.3) <lb/>Missing <lb/>803 (9.0) <lb/>383 (7.4) <lb/>Alcohol use <lb/>Non-user <lb/>1705 (19.1) <lb/>805 (15.5) <lb/>Low (1-14 units/week) <lb/>3854 (43.1) <lb/>2859 (55.0) <lb/>Moderate (15-21 units/week) <lb/>535 (6.0) <lb/>251 (4.8) <lb/>Hazardous (&gt;21 units/week) <lb/>667 (7.5) <lb/>273 (5.3) <lb/>Ex-user <lb/>996 (11.2) <lb/>359 ((6.9) <lb/>Missing <lb/>1179 (13.2) <lb/>656 (12.6) <lb/>Inflammatory conditions <lb/>Rheumatoid arthritis <lb/>6945 (77.7) <lb/>4067 (78.2) <lb/>Psoriatic arthritis <lb/>1354 (15.2) <lb/>773 (14.9) <lb/>Inflammatory bowel disease <lb/>319 (3.6) <lb/>173 (3.3) <lb/>Ankylosing spondylitis/reactive arthritis <lb/>318 (3.6) <lb/>190 (3.7) <lb/>Comorbidities <lb/>Diabetes <lb/>982 (11.0) <lb/>519 (10.0) <lb/>Chronic kidney disease stage 3 <lb/>613 (6.9) <lb/>333 (6.4) <lb/>Immunosuppressive drugs <lb/>Methotrexate <lb/>2999 (33.6) <lb/>1785 (34.3) <lb/>Leflunomide <lb/>109 (1.2) <lb/>78 (1.5) <lb/>Azathioprine/Mercaptopurine <lb/>73 (0.8) <lb/>41 (0.8) <lb/>Other drugs <lb/>Statins <lb/>2088 (23.4) <lb/>1130 (21.7) <lb/>Carbamazepine/Valproate <lb/>103 (1.2) <lb/>37 (0.7) <lb/>Paracetamol <lb/>1445 (16.2) <lb/>884 (17.0) <lb/>At least mild cytopenia or liver enzyme elevation in <lb/>6 months preceding start of follow-up <lb/>1264 (14.2) <lb/>753 (14.5) <lb/>*Values are numbers (percentage) unless stated otherwise. <lb/>CPRD, Clinical Practice Research Datalink. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003980 on 7 March 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>

        <page>5 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Abhishek A, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003980. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003980 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Epidemiology Epidemiology Epidemiology <lb/></note>

        <body>comparing two groups defined by above/below the <lb/>median of the linear predictor was calculated. 36 37 R 2 , <lb/>a measure of variation explained by the model was <lb/>calculated. <lb/>Model external validation <lb/>External validation of the final model was performed <lb/>using data from CPRD Gold. The final developed model <lb/>equation was applied to the validation dataset, and cali-<lb/>bration and discrimination were examined using the <lb/>same measures as above. 36 37 Calibration of 5-year risk was <lb/>examined by plotting agreement between estimated risk <lb/>from the model and observed outcome risks. In the cali-<lb/>bration plot, predicted and observed risks were divided <lb/>into 10 equally sized groups. Additionally, pseudo-<lb/>observations were used to construct smooth calibration <lb/>curves across all individuals via a running non-parametric <lb/>smoother. Separate graphs were plotted for each imputa-<lb/>tion of the validation cohort and an example of one plot <lb/>is shown in the results. Subgroup analyses considered <lb/>age group and inflammatory disease type (RA vs others). <lb/>Stata-MP V.16 was used for all statistical analyses. This <lb/>study was reported in line with the transparent reporting <lb/>of a multivariate prediction model for individual predic-<lb/>tion or diagnosis guidelines. 38 <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Study participants <lb/>Data for 8936 and 5203 participants contributing 23 299 <lb/>and 12 867 person-years follow-up were included in the <lb/>derivation and validation cohorts, respectively (online <lb/>supplemental figures S1 and S2). Most participants in <lb/>both cohorts were diagnosed with RA, were female and <lb/>had similar prevalence of lifestyle factors, comorbidities <lb/>and drug treatments (table 1). Nine candidate predictors <lb/>(21 parameters) were included in the model (table 2). <lb/>Table 2 Final model HRs and β-coefficients <lb/>Adjusted HR (95% CI) <lb/>β-Coefficients <lb/>Age, mean (SD) year <lb/>1.01 (1.00 to 1.02) <lb/>0.0076439 <lb/>Female sex <lb/>1.08 (0.88 to 1.31) <lb/>0.0741336 <lb/>Body mass index <lb/>0.98 (0.97 to 1.00) <lb/>-0.0168035 <lb/>Alcohol use <lb/>Non-user <lb/>Reference <lb/>Low (1-14 units/week) <lb/>1.02 (0.80 to 1.29) <lb/>0.0182851 <lb/>Moderate (15-21 units/week) <lb/>0.64 (0.38 to 1.06) <lb/>-0.4507257 <lb/>Hazardous (&gt;21 units/week) <lb/>0.87 (0.58 to 1.33) <lb/>-0.133557 <lb/>Ex-user <lb/>0.94 (0.67 to 1.32) <lb/>-0.0651469 <lb/>Inflammatory conditions <lb/>Rheumatoid arthritis <lb/>Reference <lb/>Psoriatic arthritis <lb/>1.03 (0.78 to 1.36) <lb/>0.0316689 <lb/>Inflammatory bowel disease <lb/>0.74 (0.38 to 1.44) <lb/>-0.305206 <lb/>Ankylosing spondylitis/reactive arthritis <lb/>1.25 (0.74 to 2.12) <lb/>0.2214547 <lb/>Comorbidities <lb/>Diabetes <lb/>1.34 (1.01 to 1.78) <lb/>0.2909969 <lb/>Chronic kidney disease stage 3 <lb/>1.96 (1.47 to 2.62) <lb/>0.671859 <lb/>Immunosuppressive drugs <lb/>Methotrexate <lb/>1.39 (1.15 to 1.68) <lb/>0.3315573 <lb/>Leflunomide <lb/>2.05 (1.09 to 3.86) <lb/>0.7164324 <lb/>Azathioprine/Mercaptopurine <lb/>1.24 (0.37 to 4.17) <lb/>0.2189764 <lb/>Other drugs <lb/>Statins <lb/>0.98 (0.78 to 1.24) <lb/>-0.0181917 <lb/>Carbamazepine/Valproate <lb/>0.74 (0.28 to 2.00) <lb/>-0.2949835 <lb/>Paracetamol <lb/>1.14 (0.90 to 1.43) <lb/>0.1272515 <lb/>Blood-test abnormalities <lb/>At least mild cytopenia or liver enzyme elevation in <lb/>6 months preceding start of follow-up <lb/>2.80 (2.29 to 3.42) <lb/>1.029245 <lb/>*The reported values are before shrinkage. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003980 on 7 March 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>

        <page>6 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Abhishek A, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003980. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003980 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/></note>

        <body>Model development <lb/>In the derivation dataset, 473 outcome events occurred <lb/>during the follow-up period at a rate (95% CI) of 20.30 <lb/>(18.55 to 22.22) per 1000 person-years. Of these, 256, <lb/>131 and 113 patients, respectively stopped treatment due <lb/>to cytopenia, renal function decline and elevated liver <lb/>enzymes. Outcome validation exercise in 178 outcomes <lb/>revealed that only 4.5% outcomes (n=8) could poten-<lb/>tially be explained by another contemporaneous illness <lb/>or its treatments, with a positive predictive value of 95.5% <lb/>(online supplemental table S1). <lb/>Outcome events occurred throughout 5-year follow-up <lb/>period when the entire cohort was considered (online <lb/>supplemental figure S3) and when patients co-prescribed <lb/>either methotrexate or leflunomide or thiopurine with <lb/>sulfasalazine were excluded (online supplemental figure <lb/>S4). CKD stage 3, diabetes (either type 1 or 2), co-pre-<lb/>scription of methotrexate, co-prescription of lefluno-<lb/>mide and either cytopenia or elevated liver enzymes <lb/>during first 6 months of sulfasalazine prescription were <lb/>strong predictors of drug discontinuation with adjusted <lb/>HR (95% CI) 1.96 (1.47 to 2.62), 1.34 (1.01 to 1.78), 1.39 <lb/>(1.15 to 1.68), 2.05 (1.09 to 3.86) and 2.80 (2.29 to 3.42), <lb/>respectively (table 2). From the bootstrap, a uniform <lb/>shrinkage factor of 0.84 was obtained and used to shrink <lb/>predictor coefficients in the final model for optimism <lb/>and after re-estimation, the final model&apos;s cumulative <lb/>baseline survival function (S 0 ) was 0.940 at 5 years of <lb/>follow-up (Box 1). <lb/>Model performance in the development cohort <lb/>As expected, the calibration slope (95% CI) in the devel-<lb/>opment data was 1.00 (0.85 to 1.15). Calibration plot of <lb/>the final (ie, after shrinkage) model at 5 years showed <lb/>that the average model predictions matched the average <lb/>observed outcome probabilities across 10 groups of <lb/>patients, with CIs overlapping the 45-degree line (perfect <lb/>prediction line) (figure 1). As most patients had a low <lb/>risk of outcome (online supplemental figure S5), most <lb/>of the deciles clustered at the bottom left of the calibra-<lb/>tion plot (online supplemental figure S6). The smoothed <lb/>calibration curve at 5 years showed alignment of observed <lb/>risk to the predicted risk with wide CIs at high-risk prob-<lb/>abilities (figure 1). The Royston D statistic was 0.91 (95% <lb/>CI 0.77 to 1.05), corresponding to an HR (95% CI) of <lb/>2.48 (2.16 to 2.86) comparing the risk of participants who <lb/>were above the median of linear predictor to that below <lb/>the median. The optimism adjusted Royston D statistic <lb/>was 0.79, corresponding to an HR of 2.20 (table 3). <lb/>Model performance in the validation cohort <lb/>There were 280 outcomes at a rate (95% CI) of 21.76 <lb/>(19.36 to 24.47)/1000 person-years in the validation <lb/>cohort. The calibration slope (95% CI) across the 5-year <lb/>follow-up period was 1.19 (0.96 to 1.43) (figure 2). The <lb/>calibration plot showed reasonable correspondence <lb/>between observed and predicted risk at 5 years across the <lb/>tenths of risk (online supplemental figure S7). Most of <lb/>the deciles clustered at the bottom left of the calibration <lb/>plot due to a low risk of outcome for most patients (online <lb/>supplemental figures S7 and S8). When individual risks <lb/>were plotted, the smoothed calibration curve showed <lb/>alignment of the predicted risk to the observed risk at low <lb/>risk and wide CIs overlapping the perfect prediction line <lb/>at high-risk probabilities (figure 2). Model performance <lb/>was also tested at years 1, 2, 3 and 4 (online supplemental <lb/>figures S9-S12) and showed a similar pattern except for <lb/>overprediction of risk at 1 year. The Royston D statistic in <lb/>the validation data was 0.87 (0.67 to 1.07), corresponding <lb/>to an HR (95% CI) of 2.39 (1.95 to 2.92). Model discrim-<lb/>ination in the derivation and validation data was broadly <lb/>similar (table 3). The model performed well in those <lb/>younger or older than 60 years, in those with RA or other <lb/>conditions (online supplemental figures S13 and S14). <lb/>Worked examples: ten anonymised patient profiles, <lb/>one from the middle of each of the 10 groups defined <lb/>by deciles of predicted risk were selected from the devel-<lb/>opment cohort, the higher the decile group the higher <lb/>the risk, and the risk equation was applied to each. The <lb/>cumulative probability of outcome over 5 years ranged <lb/>from 5.3% in the middle of the first group to 9.3% in the <lb/>middle of the seventh group, and 19.0% in the middle of <lb/>the 10th group (online supplemental table S2). <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>We have developed and externally validated a prognostic <lb/>model for sulfasalazine discontinuation due to abnormal <lb/>blood-test results. To the best of our knowledge, this is <lb/>the first such risk-prediction model. It performed well in <lb/>predicting outcomes by 5 years and in clinically relevant <lb/>Box 1 Equation to predict the risk of sulfasalazine <lb/>discontinuation after 6 months of primary care prescription and <lb/>within the next 5 years <lb/>Risk score=1-0.940 exp(0.84βX) , where βX=0.0076439×age in <lb/>years at first primary care prescription+0.0741336×female <lb/>sex-0.0168035×BMI+0.0182851×low alcohol <lb/>intake-0.4507257×moderate alcohol intake-0.1335573×hazardous <lb/>alcohol intake-0.0651469×e x-alcohol intake+0.0316689×p <lb/>soriasis-0.305206×IBD+0.2214547× ankylosing spondylitis/ <lb/>reactive arthritis+0.2909969×diabetes+ 0.671859×CKD <lb/>+0.3315573×MTX+0.7164324×LEF+0.2189764× AZA or <lb/>6-MP-0.0181917×statins-0.2949835×carbamazepine/ valproate <lb/>+0.1272515×paracetamol+1.029245×at least mild cytopenia or <lb/>liver enzyme elevation within 6 months of primary care sulfasalazine <lb/>prescription. <lb/>All variables are code 0, and 1 if absent or present, respectively, except for <lb/>BMI and age that were continuous variables. At 5 years, 0.940 is the baseline <lb/>survival function, 0.84 is the shrinkage factor and the other numbers are <lb/>the estimated regression coefficients for the predictors, which indicate their <lb/>mutually adjusted relative contribution to the outcome risk. <lb/>AZA, azathioprine; BMI, body mass index; CKD, chronic kidney disease; <lb/>IBD, inflammatory bowel disease; LEF, leflunomide; MP, mercaptopurine; <lb/>MTX, methotrexate. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003980 on 7 March 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>

        <page>7 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Abhishek A, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003980. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003980 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Epidemiology Epidemiology Epidemiology <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 1 Calibration of a prognostic model for sulfasalazine discontinuation with abnormal monitoring blood-test results at 5 <lb/>years in the development cohort. Data from a single imputed dataset was used; S 0 (t=5) 0.940. <lb/>Table 3 Model diagnostics <lb/>Measure <lb/>Apparent <lb/>performance* Test performance † <lb/>Average <lb/>optimism ‡ <lb/>Optimism corrected <lb/>performance § <lb/>External validation <lb/>(CPRD Aurum) ¶ <lb/>Overall calibration slope <lb/>1.00 (0.85 to <lb/>1.15) <lb/>0.84 (0.70 to 0.98) <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.84 (0.69 to 0.99) <lb/>1.19 (0.96 to 1.43) <lb/>R 2 <lb/>D <lb/>0.17 (0.12 to <lb/>0.21) <lb/>0.15 (0.11 to 0.19) <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.13 (0.08 to 0.17) <lb/>0.15 (0.10 to 0.21) <lb/>Royston D statistic <lb/>0.91 (0.77 to <lb/>1.05) <lb/>0.85 (0.72 to 0.99) <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.79 (0.65 to 0.93) <lb/>0.87 (0.67 to 1.07) <lb/>*Refers to performance (95% CI) estimated directly from the data that were used to develop the model. <lb/> †Determined by executing full model in each bootstrap sample (500 samples with replacement), calculating bootstrap performance and <lb/>applying same model in original sample. <lb/> ‡Average difference between model performance in bootstrap data and test performance in original dataset. <lb/> §Subtracting average optimism from apparent performance. <lb/> ¶Penalised model was externally validated (penalised calibration slope: 1.19; 95% CI 1.01 to 1.37). <lb/>CPRD, Clinical Practice Research Datalink. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003980 on 7 March 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>

        <page>8 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Abhishek A, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003980. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003980 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/></note>

        <body>subgroups defined by age and inflammatory condition. <lb/>Previous studies have variably reported N-acetyltrans-<lb/>ferase 2 (NAT-2) acetylator status to be associated with <lb/>sulfasalazine toxicity. 15 39 However, these studies evalu-<lb/>ated all side effects and did not separately assess either <lb/>myelotoxicity, hepatotoxicity or nephrotoxicity as evalu-<lb/>ated in the current study. <lb/>Our findings suggest that a one-size-fits-all approach <lb/>to monitoring for blood, liver or renal toxicity using <lb/>3 monthly blood tests during long-term sulfasalazine <lb/>treatment as recommended in the summary of product <lb/>characteristics and the ACR guidelines, and not moni-<lb/>toring for these after the first year of treatment as <lb/>recommended in the BSR guidelines are both inappro-<lb/>priate because there is a large interindividual variation <lb/>in the risk of developing these side effects. The large <lb/>variation in risk implies that it may be reasonable to not <lb/>monitor some patients after the first year of sulfasalazine <lb/>treatment, while others at higher risk of side effects are <lb/>monitored frequently, for example, 3 monthly. <lb/>It is important to realise that DILI can be idiosyncratic <lb/>and annual testing is unlikely to detect them early enough <lb/>to improve patient outcome. It is beyond our remit to <lb/>propose threshold at which the frequency of monitoring <lb/>blood tests should be altered. These decisions are best <lb/>taken by guideline writing groups. Thus, our findings <lb/>ought to be considered by guideline writing groups. <lb/>It is important that the results of this study are not <lb/>used to risk-stratify monitoring in patients newly started <lb/>on sulfasalazine because our prognosis model used data <lb/>from patients prescribed sulfasalazine by their GP for <lb/>6 months after initiating treatment and dose-escalation <lb/>in a hospital outpatient. It typically takes 3-6 months to <lb/>stabilise a patient&apos;s sulfasalazine dose before prescription <lb/>and monitoring is handed over to the GP. In healthcare <lb/>systems where such shared care arrangements do not <lb/>Figure 2 Calibration of a prognostic model for sulfasalazine discontinuation with abnormal monitoring blood-test results at 5 <lb/>years in the validation cohort. Data from a single imputed dataset was used; S 0 (t=5) 0.940. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003980 on 7 March 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>

        <page>9 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Abhishek A, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003980. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003980 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Epidemiology Epidemiology Epidemiology <lb/></note>

        <body>exist, this strategy may be applied after 1 year of sulfas-<lb/>alazine treatment. Although generally perceived to be <lb/>safe, sulfasalazine use carries a risk of myelotoxicity and <lb/>nephrotoxicity comparable to that observed with metho-<lb/>trexate in people with RA. 40 <lb/>CKD stage 3, diabetes and concomitant methotrexate <lb/>or leflunomide therapy were associated with sulfasalazine <lb/>discontinuation with abnormal monitoring blood-test <lb/>results in this study. These associations may be due to <lb/>reduced sulfasalazine clearance in CKD and DILI being <lb/>associated with diabetes. 41 Abnormal blood-test results <lb/>during the first 6 months of therapy were associated with <lb/>discontinuing sulfasalazine with abnormal monitoring <lb/>blood-test results, like findings for methotrexate and <lb/>leflunomide. 24 42 Elevated liver enzymes and cytopenia <lb/>before starting treatment have previously been associated <lb/>with abnormal blood-test results in patients treated with <lb/>methotrexate and biologics, respectively. 31 43-48 <lb/>There are several strengths of this study. First, we used a <lb/>large real-world and nationally representative dataset for <lb/>model development and a similar independent dataset <lb/>for external validation. Second, the study population <lb/>included patients with a range of diseases and the results <lb/>have broad generalisability. Third, the prognostic factors <lb/>were selected by an expert multidisciplinary team based <lb/>on clinical experience. Fourth, our outcome required the <lb/>abnormal blood-test result to be associated with sulfasala-<lb/>zine discontinuation, thus, allowing the model to predict <lb/>clinically relevant outcomes. Fifth, the prognostic model <lb/>is easy to use in practice, and can be easily built into GP <lb/>electronic health records. <lb/>However, several limitations of this study ought to <lb/>be considered. First, we did not have access to the date <lb/>when the patient was first prescribed sulfasalazine in the <lb/>hospital clinic. Second, we did not have data on concur-<lb/>rent use of biologics as these are hospital prescribed. <lb/>However, there is no evidence to suggest that biologics <lb/>increase sulfasalazine toxicity. Third, we did not have <lb/>data on disease activity as these are not recorded in the <lb/>CPRD. Fourth, the abnormal blood test could be due to <lb/>a different illness and not due to sulfasalazine. However, <lb/>only 4.5% of the outcomes in the development cohort <lb/>in this study could be potentially explained by an alter-<lb/>nate illness in this study. Similarly, in our previous vali-<lb/>dation studies on methotrexate, only 5.4% of abnormal <lb/>blood-test results could be explained by an alternative <lb/>illness. 25 Fifth, although the external validation dataset <lb/>was distinct from the model development dataset, it also <lb/>originated from UK general practice. We recommend <lb/>therefore that our model be validated in a dataset from <lb/>another country. Sixth, there were 31 (0.3%) patients in <lb/>the highest three risk groups defined according to tenths <lb/>of risk, resulting in uncertainty regarding predictors for <lb/>these groups. Seventh, we did not perform competing <lb/>risk regression. However, this does not limit the validity <lb/>of our findings as there were few deaths (28 (0.3%)) in <lb/>the derivation cohort and 8 (0.2%) deaths in validation <lb/>cohort up to 5-year follow-up period. Finally, this was a <lb/>retrospective analysis using secondary data originated <lb/>during routine care of patients in the NHS and data <lb/>were not prospectively collected for this study. However, <lb/>any bias from this approach was minimised by inclusion <lb/>of all consecutive patients that were prescribed sulfas-<lb/>alazine within the study period that met the eligibility <lb/>criteria. <lb/>In conclusion, we have developed and externally vali-<lb/>dated a prognostic model for sulfasalazine discontinua-<lb/>tion with abnormal monitoring blood-test results. These <lb/>findings need to be considered by national and inter-<lb/>national specialist societies&apos; guideline writing groups to <lb/>decide on risk-stratified frequency of monitoring blood <lb/>tests during long-term sulfasalazine treatment. <lb/></body>

        <front>Author affiliations <lb/>1 <lb/>Academic Rheumatology, University of Nottingham, Nottingham, UK <lb/>2 <lb/>Lifespan and Population Health, University of Nottingham, Nottingham, UK <lb/>3 <lb/>Centre for Evidence Based Dermatology, University of Nottingham, Nottingham, UK <lb/>4 <lb/>Translational Medical Sciences, University of Nottingham, Nottingham, UK <lb/>5 <lb/>Nottingham NIHR BRC, Nottingham, UK <lb/>6 <lb/>School of Meicine, Keele University, Keele, UK <lb/>7 <lb/>School of Medicine and Population Health, University of Sheffield, Sheffield, UK <lb/>8 <lb/>University of Birmingham, Birmingham, UK <lb/></front>

        <div type="contribution">Contributors GN, MG, HCW, TC, MWT, GPA, CPF, CDM, MDS, RR and AA designed <lb/>the study. GN analysed the data supervised by MG, RR and AA. GN, MG, HCW, <lb/>TC, MWT, GPA, CPF, CDM, MDS, RR and AA interpreted the data. AA drafted the <lb/>manuscript. All authors critically evaluated and revised the manuscript. The <lb/>corresponding author attests that all listed authors meet authorship criteria and <lb/>that no others meeting the criteria have been omitted. AA is the guarantor. <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">Funding This research was funded by the National Institute for Health and Care <lb/>Research (NIHR) (grant no. NIHR130580). <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">Disclaimer The funders had no role in conducting and/or reporting this study. <lb/></div>

        <div type="conflict">Competing interests AA has received personal fees from UpToDate (royalty), <lb/>Springer (royalty), Cadilla Pharmaceuticals (lecture fees), NGM Bio (consulting), <lb/>Limbic (consulting) and personal fees from Inflazome (consulting) unrelated <lb/>to the work. GPA has received consulting fees from Abbott, Albereo, Amryth, <lb/>AstraZeneca, Benevolent AI, DNDI, GlaxoSmithKline, NuCANA, Pfizer, Roche <lb/>Diagnostics, Servier Pharmaceuticals, W.L. Gore &amp; Associates paid to the <lb/>University of Nottingham unrelated to the work. CPF has received Consultancy/ <lb/>Advisory board fees from AbbVie, GenMab, Incyte, Morphosys, Roche, Takeda, <lb/>Ono, Kite/Gilead, BMS/Celgene, BTG/Veriton and departmental research funding <lb/>from BeiGene unrelated to the work. The other authors have no conflict of interest <lb/>to declare. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Patient consent for publication Not applicable. <lb/>Ethics approval This study was approved by Independent Scientific Advisory <lb/>Committee of the MHRA (reference: 19_275R, 20_000236R). <lb/>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. <lb/></div>

        <div type="availability">Data availability statement Data may be obtained from a third party and are not <lb/>publicly available. Data used in this study cannot be shared due to CPRD licensing <lb/>requirements. However, CPRD data may be obtained directly from them. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Supplemental material This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has <lb/>not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been <lb/>peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those <lb/>of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and <lb/>responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content <lb/>includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability <lb/>of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, <lb/>terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error <lb/>and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise. <lb/></div>

        <front>Open access This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported (CC BY 4.0) license, which permits <lb/>others to copy, redistribute, remix, transform and build upon this work for any <lb/>purpose, provided the original work is properly cited, a link to the licence is given, <lb/>and indication of whether changes were made. See: https://creativecommons.org/ <lb/>licenses/by/4.0/. <lb/></front>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003980 on 7 March 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>

        <page>10 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Abhishek A, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003980. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003980 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/></note>

        <front>ORCID iDs <lb/>Abhishek Abhishek http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0121-4919 <lb/>Tim Card http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2555-2250 <lb/></front>

        <listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1 Ogdie A, Coates LC, Gladman DD. Treatment guidelines in psoriatic <lb/>arthritis. Rheumatology (Oxford) 2020;59:i37-46. <lb/>2 Singh JA. Treatment guidelines in rheumatoid arthritis. Rheum Dis <lb/>Clin North Am 2022;48:679-89. <lb/>3 Ransford RAJ, Langman MJS. Sulphasalazine and mesalazine: <lb/>serious adverse reactions re-evaluated on the basis of suspected <lb/>adverse reaction reports to the committee on safety of medicines. <lb/>Gut 2002;51:536-9. <lb/>4 Farr M, Tunn EJ, Symmons DP, et al. Sulphasalazine in rheumatoid <lb/>arthritis: haematological problems and changes in haematological <lb/>indices associated with therapy. Br J Rheumatol 1989;28:134-8. <lb/>5 McConkey B. Ten years of sulphasalazine use in rheumatoid arthritis. <lb/>Br J Rheumatol 1989;28:175-6. <lb/>6 van Riel P, van Gestel AM, van de Putte LBA. Long-term usage <lb/>and Side-effect profile of sulphasalazine in rheumatoid arthritis. <lb/>Rheumatology 1995;XXXIV:40-2. <lb/>7 de Abajo FJ, Montero D, Madurga M, et al. Et al. acute and clinically <lb/>relevant drug-induced liver injury: a population based case-control <lb/>study.BR. Br J Clin Pharmacol 2004;58:71-80. <lb/>8 McConkey B, Amos RS, Durham S, et al. Sulphasalazine in <lb/>rheumatoid arthritis. Br Med J 1980;280:442-4. <lb/>9 Farr M, Scott DG, Bacon PA. Side effect profile of 200 patients <lb/>with inflammatory arthritides treated with sulphasalazine. Drugs <lb/>1986;32 Suppl 1:49-53. <lb/>10 Amos RS, Pullar T, Bax DE, et al. Sulphasalazine for rheumatoid <lb/>arthritis: toxicity in 774 patients monitored for one to 11 years. Br <lb/>Med J (Clin Res Ed) 1986;293:420-3. <lb/>11 MacGilchrist AJ, Hunter JA. Sulphasalazine hepatotoxicity: lack of a <lb/>hypersensitivity response. Ann Rheum Dis 1986;45:967-8. <lb/>12 Marabani M, Madhok R, Capell HA, et al. Leucopenia during <lb/>sulphasalazine treatment for rheumatoid arthritis. Ann Rheum Dis <lb/>1989;48:505-7. <lb/>13 Jobanputra P, Amarasena R, Maggs F, et al. Et al.hepatotoxicity <lb/>associated with sulfasalazine in inflammatory arthritis: a case series <lb/>from a local surveillance of serious adverse events.BMC. BMC <lb/>Musculoskelet Disord 2008;9:48. <lb/>14 Keisu M, Ekman E. Sulfasalazine associated agranulocytosis in <lb/>Sweden 1972-1989. Eur J Clin Pharmacol 1992;43:215-8. <lb/>15 Wiese MD, Alotaibi N, O&apos;Doherty C, et al. Pharmacogenomics of <lb/>Nat2 and Abcg2 influence the toxicity and efficacy of sulphasalazine <lb/>containing DMARD regimens in early rheumatoid arthritis. <lb/>Pharmacogenomics J 2014;14:350-5. <lb/>16 Grove ML, Hassell AB, Hay EM, et al. Adverse reactions to <lb/>disease-modifying anti-rheumatic drugs in clinical practice. QJM <lb/>2001;94:309-19. <lb/>17 Committee JF. British national Formulary.[85]. London BMJ Group <lb/>and Pharmaceutical Press; 2023. <lb/>18 Ledingham J, Gullick N, Irving K, et al. BSR and BHPR guideline for <lb/>the prescription and monitoring of non-biologic disease-modifying <lb/>anti-rheumatic drugs. Rheumatology (Oxford) 2017;56:865-8. <lb/>19 Singh JA, Saag KG, Bridges SL, et al. American college of <lb/>rheumatology guideline for the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis. <lb/>Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken) 2016;68:1-25. <lb/>20 Pfizer. Salazopyrin tablets. Healthcare professionals (Smpc) 2021. <lb/>2021. Available: https://www.medicines.org.uk/emc/product/3838/ <lb/>smpc#gref [Accessed 23 Jul 2023]. <lb/>21 Herrett E, Gallagher AM, Bhaskaran K, et al. Data resource <lb/>profile: clinical practice research datalink (CPRD). Int J Epidemiol <lb/>2015;44:827-36. <lb/>22 Wolf A, Dedman D, Campbell J, et al. Et al. data resource profile: <lb/>clinical practice research datalink (CPRD). Int J Epidemiol <lb/>2019;48:1740-1740g. <lb/>23 Abhishek A, Doherty M, Kuo C-F, et al. Rheumatoid arthritis is <lb/>getting less frequent-results of a nationwide population-based <lb/>cohort study. Rheumatology (Oxford) 2017;56:736-44. <lb/>24 Nakafero G, Grainge MJ, Williams HC, et al. Risk stratified <lb/>monitoring for methotrexate toxicity in immune mediated <lb/>inflammatory diseases: prognostic model development <lb/>and validation using primary care data from the UK. BMJ <lb/>2023;381:e074678. <lb/>25 Nakafero G, Grainge MJ, Card T, et al. What is the incidence of <lb/>methotrexate or leflunomide discontinuation related to cytopenia, <lb/>liver enzyme elevation or kidney function decline?. Rheumatology <lb/>(Oxford) 2021;60:5785-94. <lb/>26 Khwaja A. KDIGO clinical practice guidelines for acute kidney injury. <lb/>Nephron Clin Pract 2012;120:c179-84. <lb/>27 Chalasani N, Björnsson E. Risk factors for idiosyncratic drug-<lb/>induced liver injury. Gastroenterology 2010;138:2246-59. <lb/>28 Safy-Khan M, de Hair MJH, Welsing PMJ, et al. Current smoking <lb/>negatively affects the response to methotrexate in rheumatoid <lb/>arthritis in a dose-responsive way, independently of concomitant <lb/>prednisone use. J Rheumatol 2021;48:1504-7. <lb/>29 Klotz U. Clinical pharmacokinetics of sulphasalazine, its metabolites <lb/>and other prodrugs of 5-aminosalicylic acid. Clin Pharmacokinet <lb/>1985;10:285-302. <lb/>30 Meijer B, Wilhelm AJ, Mulder CJJ, et al. Pharmacology of thiopurine <lb/>therapy in inflammatory bowel disease and complete blood <lb/>cell count outcomes: a 5-year database study. Ther Drug Monit <lb/>2017;39:399-405. <lb/>31 Dirven L, Klarenbeek NB, van den Broek M, et al. Risk of alanine <lb/>transferase (ALT) elevation in patients with rheumatoid arthritis <lb/>treated with methotrexate in a DAS-steered strategy. Clin Rheumatol <lb/>2013;32:585-90. <lb/>32 Riley RD, Ensor J, Snell KIE, et al. Calculating the sample <lb/>size required for developing a clinical prediction model. BMJ <lb/>2020;368:m441. <lb/>33 Riley RD, Debray TPA, Collins GS, et al. Minimum sample size <lb/>for external validation of a clinical prediction model with a binary <lb/>outcome. Stat Med 2021;40:4230-51. <lb/>34 Schafer JL. Multiple imputation: a primer. Stat Methods Med Res <lb/>1999;8:3-15. <lb/>35 Steyerberg EW. Clinical prediction models: A practical approach <lb/>to development, validation, and updating. Cham, SWITZERLAND <lb/>Springer International Publishing AG; 2019. <lb/>36 Royston P, Altman DG. External validation of a cox prognostic <lb/>model: principles and methods. BMC Med Res Methodol <lb/>2013;13:33. <lb/>37 Cox DR. Note on grouping. JASA 1957;52:543. <lb/>38 Moons KGM, Altman DG, Reitsma JB, et al. Transparent reporting <lb/>of a multivariable prediction model for individual prognosis or <lb/>diagnosis (TRIPOD): explanation and elaboration. Ann Intern Med <lb/>2015;162:W1-73. <lb/>39 Ricart E, Taylor WR, Loftus EV, et al. N-acetyltransferase 1 and 2 <lb/>genotypes do not predict response or toxicity to treatment with <lb/>mesalamine and sulfasalazine in patients with ulcerative colitis. Am J <lb/>Gastroenterol 2002;97:1763-8. <lb/>40 Mielnik P, Sexton J, Fagerli KM, et al. Discontinuation rate of <lb/>sulfasalazine, leflunomide and methotrexate due to adverse <lb/>events in a real-life setting (NOR-DMARD). Rheumatol Adv Pract <lb/>2023;7:rkad053. <lb/>41 Mori S, Arima N, Ito M, et al. Non-alcoholic Steatohepatitis-like <lb/>pattern in liver biopsy of rheumatoid arthritis patients with persistent <lb/>Transaminitis during low-dose methotrexate treatment. PLoS One <lb/>2018;13:e0203084. <lb/>42 Nakafero G, Grainge MJ, Card T, et al. Development and validation <lb/>of a prognostic model for leflunomide discontinuation with abnormal <lb/>blood tests during long-term treatment: cohort study using data <lb/>from the clinical practice research datalink gold and aurum. <lb/>Rheumatology (Oxford) 2022;61:2783-91. <lb/>43 Cavalli M, Eriksson N, Sundbaum JK, et al. Genome-wide <lb/>association study of liver enzyme elevation in an extended cohort <lb/>of rheumatoid arthritis patients starting low-dose methotrexate. <lb/>Pharmacogenomics 2022;23:813-20. <lb/>44 Sherbini AA, Gwinnutt JM, Hyrich KL, et al. Rates and predictors <lb/>of methotrexate-related adverse events in patients with early <lb/>rheumatoid arthritis: results from a nationwide UK study. <lb/>Rheumatology (Oxford) 2022;61:3930-8. <lb/>45 Suzuki Y, Hirose T, Sugiyama N, et al. Post-marketing surveillance <lb/>of high-dose methotrexate (&gt;8 mg/week) in Japanese patients with <lb/>rheumatoid arthritis: a post hoc sub-analysis of patients according to <lb/>duration of prior methotrexate use. Mod Rheumatol 2021;31:575-86. <lb/>46 Verstappen SMM, Bakker MF, Heurkens AHM, et al. Adverse events <lb/>and factors associated with toxicity in patients with early rheumatoid <lb/>arthritis treated with methotrexate tight control therapy: the <lb/>CAMERA study. Ann Rheum Dis 2010;69:1044-8. <lb/>47 Schmajuk G, Miao Y, Yazdany J, et al. Identification of risk factors for <lb/>elevated transaminases in methotrexate users through an electronic <lb/>health record. Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken) 2014;66:1159-66. <lb/>48 Hastings R, Ding T, Butt S, et al. Neutropenia in patients receiving <lb/>anti-tumor necrosis factor therapy. Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken) <lb/>2010;62:764-9. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003980 on 7 March 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. </note>


	</text>

</TEI>