<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Does proactive care in care homes improve survival? A quality improvement project</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>David</forename>
            <surname>Attwood</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Suzy V</forename>
            <surname>Hope</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Stuart G</forename>
            <surname>Spicer</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Adam L</forename>
            <surname>Gordon</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>James</forename>
            <surname>Boorer</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Wendy</forename>
            <surname>Ellis</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Michelle</forename>
            <surname>Earley</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Jillian</forename>
            <surname>Denovan</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Gerard</forename>
            <surname>Hart</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Maria</forename>
            <surname>Williams</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Nicholas</forename>
            <surname>Burdett</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Melissa</forename>
            <surname>Lemon</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-29T10:21:13.754350Z">29.10.2025 10:21:13</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1136$1$bmjoq-2024-002771</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>BMJ</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmjoq-2024-002771</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>David Attwood, Suzy V Hope, Stuart G Spicer, Adam L Gordon, James Boorer, Wendy Ellis, Michelle Earley, Jillian Denovan, Gerard Hart, Maria Williams, Nicholas Burdett, Melissa Lemon. (2024). Does proactive care in care homes improve survival? A quality improvement project. BMJ Open Quality, 13(2), e002771. DOI: 10.1136/bmjoq-2024-002771</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-29T10:21:13.754350Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-29T10:21:13.754350Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>1 <lb/>Scherbacher PJ, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003956. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003956 <lb/>ORIGINAL RESEARCH <lb/>Prospective study of complications and <lb/>sequelae of glucocorticoid therapy in <lb/>ANCA-associated vasculitis <lb/>Paul J Scherbacher, 1 Bernhard Hellmich <lb/>, 1 You-Shan Feng, 2 <lb/>Christian Löffler <lb/>1,3 <lb/>To cite: Scherbacher PJ, <lb/>Hellmich B, Feng Y-S, <lb/>et al. Prospective study of <lb/>complications and sequelae of <lb/>glucocorticoid therapy in ANCA-<lb/>associated vasculitis. RMD Open <lb/>2024;10:e003956. doi:10.1136/ <lb/>rmdopen-2023-003956 <lb/>► Additional supplemental <lb/>material is published online only. <lb/>To view, please visit the journal <lb/>online (https:// doi. org/ 10. 1136/ <lb/>rmdopen-2023-003956). <lb/>Received 28 November 2023 <lb/>Accepted 12 February 2024 <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Internal <lb/>Medicine, Rheumatology, <lb/>Pneumology, Nephrology and <lb/>Diabetology, Medius Klinik <lb/>Kirchheim/Teck, University of <lb/>Tübingen, Kirchheim unter Teck, <lb/>Germany <lb/>2 <lb/>Institute of Clinical <lb/>Epidemiology and Applied <lb/>Biometrics, University of <lb/>Tübingen, Tubingen, Germany <lb/>3 <lb/>Department of Nephrology, <lb/>Endocrinology, Hypertensiology <lb/>and Rheumatology, <lb/>Universitätsmedizin Mannheim, <lb/>University of Heidelberg, <lb/>Mannheim, Germany <lb/>Correspondence to <lb/>Dr Christian Löffler; <lb/>christianloeffler@ gmx. de <lb/>Vasculitis <lb/>© Author(s) (or their <lb/>employer(s)) 2024. Re-use <lb/>permitted under CC BY-NC. No <lb/>commercial re-use. See rights <lb/>and permissions. Published <lb/>by BMJ. <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Objective Glucocorticoids (GC) are a cornerstone in <lb/>treating antineutrophil cytoplasmic antibodies-associated <lb/>vasculitides (AAV), however, they add to morbidity and <lb/>mortality. To date, GC toxicity in AAV has rarely been <lb/>systematically investigated. <lb/>Methods Patients with a confirmed AAV were <lb/>included in this monocentric prospective study. GC <lb/>toxicity was assessed by structured interviews, clinical <lb/>examination and electronic medical record analysis. <lb/>The Glucocorticoid Toxicity Index (GTI) consisting of <lb/>the Aggregate Improvement Score (GTI-AIS) and the <lb/>Cumulative Worsening Score (GTI-CWS) was assessed at <lb/>two time points (t1 baseline, t2 6 months later). We used <lb/>regression analyses to assess the relationship between <lb/>GTI and GC exposure, toxicity, and disease activity, and a <lb/>receiver operating characteristic analysis to calculate a GC <lb/>threshold dose beyond which toxicity is expected to occur. <lb/>Results We included 138 patients with AAV. The median <lb/>cumulative GC dose was 9014.0 mg. The most frequent <lb/>adverse events were skin atrophy, osteoporosis and <lb/>myopathy. GC exposure and toxicity were significantly <lb/>correlated (p&lt;0.001). GTI-AIS was significantly higher <lb/>in active disease compared with patients in remission <lb/>(p&lt;0.001). GTI-CWS scored significantly higher in long-<lb/>standing diseases (p=0.013) with high cumulative GC <lb/>doses (p=0.003). Patients with a cumulative GC dose of <lb/>935 mg or more showed an 80% likelihood for a clinically <lb/>meaningful change in GTI scoring. <lb/>Conclusion The GTI is capable of capturing GC toxicity in <lb/>AAV and identifies patients at increased risk for GC side <lb/>effects. Our data support efforts to limit GC exposure in <lb/>patients with AAV. <lb/></front>

        <body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Antineutrophil <lb/>cytoplasmic <lb/>antibodies <lb/>(ANCA)-associated <lb/>vasculitides <lb/>(AAV) <lb/>encompass granulomatosis with polyangiitis <lb/>(GPA), microscopic polyangiitis (MPA) and <lb/>eosinophilic granulomatosis with polyangiitis <lb/>(EGPA) according to the revised nomencla-<lb/>ture from the 2012 Chapel Hill Consensus <lb/>Conference. 1 2 Their hallmark is a necrotising <lb/>inflammation preferentially affecting small <lb/>vessels. ANCA specifically directed against <lb/>proteinase-3 or myeloperoxidase are often <lb/>detectable, and immune complex deposits <lb/>are rare. 1 The annual incidence in Germany <lb/>is 34 cases per 1 million for GPA, 13 cases per <lb/>1 million for MPA and 2 cases per 1 million <lb/>the EGPA. 3-5 <lb/>Despite modern immunosuppressants <lb/>such as rituximab, mepolizumab, avacopan <lb/>and others in both induction and mainte-<lb/>nance therapy, glucocorticoids (GC) still <lb/>play a crucial role in the treatment of AAV <lb/>and are part of current guideline recom-<lb/>mendations. 6-8 GC substantially add to the <lb/>significantly higher mortality of AAV patients <lb/>compared with the general population. 9-12 <lb/>Severe courses of disease and frequent <lb/></body>

        <front>WHAT IS ALREADY KNOWN ON THIS TOPIC <lb/>⇒ The Glucocorticoid Toxicity Index (GTI) has been val-<lb/>idated in asthma patients. Its value in antineutrophil <lb/>cytoplasmic antibodies-associated vasculitis (AAV) <lb/>remains to be evaluated. <lb/>WHAT THIS STUDY ADDS <lb/>⇒ We provide prospective data in 138 AAV patients <lb/>evaluating the GTI. The data underline the common-<lb/>ness and severity of glucocorticoids (GC) toxicity <lb/>and the usefulness of the GTI in capturing it. The <lb/>threshold GC dose beyond which toxicity becomes <lb/>likely was calculated as 935 mg prednisolone. The <lb/>GTI scores positively correlate with the domain <lb/>&apos;physical limitation&apos;, but not the &apos;treatment side ef-<lb/>fects&apos; of the AAV-specific patient-reported outcome <lb/>questionnaire. <lb/>HOW THIS STUDY MIGHT AFFECT RESEARCH, <lb/>PRACTICE OR POLICY <lb/>⇒ Since GC toxicity is high and frequent in AAV pa-<lb/>tients, novel therapies should aim at reducing their <lb/>use. In order to achieve this goal, a reliable instru-<lb/>ment to measure and objectively quantify GC toxicity <lb/>in AAV is necessary. Therapy trials should include <lb/>the GTI as an endpoint measurement tool. <lb/>RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003956 on 29 February 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></front>

        <page>2 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Scherbacher PJ, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003956. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003956 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/></note>

        <body>relapses lead to high cumulative GC doses with a consid-<lb/>erable risk for GC-associated side effects. 9 <lb/>GC-associated complications and sequelae in patients <lb/>with AAV have rarely been systematically studied. 13 14 <lb/>Before recently, GC side effects have not been assessable <lb/>in a standardised fashion. The Glucocorticoid Toxicity <lb/>Index (GTI) is a novel clinical outcome measurement <lb/>assessing the impact of GC therapy over time and its <lb/>change between two points in time. It was validated <lb/>in patients with asthma and has recently been used in <lb/>a prospective clinical trial in AAV. 12 In our study, we <lb/>prospectively investigated the impact of GC toxicity using <lb/>the GTI in routine care in a large AAV cohort at two <lb/>points in time. <lb/>PATIENTS AND METHODS <lb/>Study design and subjects <lb/>In this prospective monocentric study, subjects with newly <lb/>diagnosed and prevalent AAV were recruited from our <lb/>department, which is a tertiary referral centre for vascu-<lb/>litis. <lb/>Baseline data were collected for each subject by <lb/>reviewing electronic medical records and interviewing <lb/>and examining subjects in person using a standardised <lb/>form. We recorded AAV subtype, stage and activity state, <lb/>organ manifestations, ANCA subtype, disease duration, <lb/>treatment, GC dose and AAV relapses. <lb/>Disease activity of AAV was assessed using the <lb/>Birmingham Vasculitis Activity Score version 3 (BVAS <lb/>v3), 13 and disease-related and therapy-related damage <lb/>was measured by the Vasculitis Damage Index in patients <lb/>with AAV. 15 <lb/>We collected data on two time points, t1 represented <lb/>baseline, t2 6 months later. <lb/>We defined the &apos;total cumulative GC dose&apos; as the sum <lb/>of applied GC doses (prednisone equivalent) over the <lb/>entirety of the disease. It was calculated by analysing elec-<lb/>tronic medical records over the entire disease duration. <lb/>For any data before t1, acquisition of GC dose was retro-<lb/>spective. Standard of care protocols and medical records <lb/>were used to determine GC exposure throughout the <lb/>entire course of disease. <lb/>We further defined the &apos;current GC exposure&apos; as the <lb/>sum of the applied GC doses during the prospective <lb/>observational period between t1 and t2. <lb/>GC toxicity measurement <lb/>GC-related toxicity was assessed using the GTI 2.0, a vali-<lb/>dated and standardised tool to capture the change in GC <lb/>toxicity over time. The GTI consists of 9 domains and 47 <lb/>items. Each item has an individual weighting according <lb/>to the toxicity depicted. In all domains, there is an option <lb/>to score improvement, worsening or no change. 16 The <lb/>GTI Aggregate Improvement Score (GTI-AIS) captures <lb/>current GC toxicity and can reach values from -346 to <lb/>439. Negative values show improvement and positive <lb/>values show worsening of GC toxicity. In our study, the <lb/>GTI-AIS indicated the change in GC toxicity during the <lb/>6-month period between t1 and t2, t1 reflecting the GTI-<lb/>AIS baseline and t2 being 6 months later. The GTI Cumu-<lb/>lative Worsening Score (GTI-CWS) captures cumulative <lb/>GC toxicity and can only increase or remain on its current <lb/>value over time. Therefore, the GTI-CWS is always ≥0, its <lb/>maximum value is 439. The GTI-CWS was calculated for <lb/>the entire disease duration ranging between the time <lb/>of the initial diagnosis and t2. 16 According to literature, <lb/>we defined the minimal clinically important difference <lb/>(MCID) in change of GC toxicity as a GTI≥10. 17 <lb/>GC-related complications between t1 and t2 were <lb/>assessed by analysing electronic medical records and <lb/>interviewing patients. In addition, each patient under-<lb/>went a physical examination. GC toxicity items were <lb/>based on a defined list of GC-related side effects (online <lb/>supplemental table S1). 11 <lb/>To capture the patients&apos; perspective regarding their <lb/>disease, we used the validated AAV patient reported <lb/>outcomes (AAV-PRO) questionnaire 17 18 and correlated <lb/>questionnaire scores with GTI results. <lb/>Statistical analyses <lb/>Data were analysed by using SPSS V.28 (IBM). Categorical <lb/>variables were expressed in counts and frequencies (n <lb/>(%)). Regarding their distribution, continuous variables <lb/>were expressed as means±SD if distributions were rela-<lb/>tively normal or as medians with IQR in cases of skewed <lb/>distribution. The values represent the conditions at t2. <lb/>For continuous variables, the significance of differ-<lb/>ences across subgroups was analysed according to their <lb/>distribution using t tests or Mann-Whitney U tests. To <lb/>assess the significance of association between categorical <lb/>variables and subgroups, the χ 2 statistic was calculated. <lb/>In the case of low predicted cell counts for categorical <lb/>variables, Fisher&apos;s exact test was applied. <lb/>To visualise the associations between GC exposure and <lb/>GTI scores, we constructed a scatter plot and calculated <lb/>a linear regression model. In addition, Spearman&apos;s r <lb/>correlation coefficient was calculated. <lb/>To calculate a threshold value beyond which GC doses <lb/>will cause any change and a clinically meaningful change <lb/>in the GTI (MCID), receiver operating characteristic <lb/>(ROC) analyses were performed and the Youden index <lb/>was assessed. For the MCID, a GTI-AIS&gt;10 (a suggested <lb/>in Stone et al 19 ) was used as the state variable while the <lb/>current GC exposure between t1 and t2 served as the test <lb/>variable. <lb/>AAV patients with active disease had a BVAS&gt;0 at t1, <lb/>whereas AAV patients in stable remission were defined by <lb/>a BVAS of 0. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Patient characteristics <lb/>For this study, 138 patients with AAV were recruited <lb/>(table 1). AAV patients included 71 patients with GPA <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003956 on 29 February 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>

        <page>3 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Scherbacher PJ, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003956. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003956 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Vasculitis Vasculitis Vasculitis <lb/></note>

        <body>Table 1 GC toxicity according to disease activity <lb/>Active disease at t1 <lb/>Stable remission <lb/>N <lb/>29 <lb/>109 <lb/>Diagnosis type <lb/>GPA <lb/>15 (51.7) <lb/>56 (51.4) <lb/>MPA <lb/>7 (24.1) <lb/>18 (16.5) <lb/>EGPA <lb/>7 (24.1) <lb/>35 (32.1) <lb/>Age (years) <lb/>59.03±15.377 <lb/>56.21±15.234 <lb/>Female <lb/>17 (58.6) <lb/>59 (54.1) <lb/>Cumulative GC dose (mg) <lb/>5700.00 (3205.00-11 036.00) <lb/>10 282.00 (5390.00-18 104.00) <lb/>Average daily GC dose (mg/day) <lb/>11.91 (8.45-24.50) <lb/>7.32 (5.89-10.01) <lb/>Duration of illness (months) <lb/>10.00 (7.00-98.50) <lb/>61.00 (30.50-110.00) <lb/>Vasculitis Damage Index <lb/>1.00 (0.50-3.00) <lb/>1.00 (1.00-2.00) <lb/>Cumulative GC dose in the GTI-AIS calculation period (mg) <lb/>1745.00 (1206.50-2542.00) <lb/>240.00 (0.00-733.00) <lb/>GTI-AIS calculation period (days) <lb/>184.00 (159.50-217.00) <lb/>182.00 (161.00-198.00) <lb/>GTI AIS* (at t2) <lb/>23.00 (0.00-74.00) <lb/>0.00 (0.00-0.00) <lb/>Subjects (N) with GTI-AIS&lt;0 <lb/>2 (6.9) <lb/>25 (22.9) <lb/>Subjects (N) with GTI-AIS=0 <lb/>8 (27.6) <lb/>62 (56.9) <lb/>Subjects (N) with GTI-AIS&gt;0 <lb/>19 (65.5) <lb/>22 (20.2) <lb/>GTI CWS* (at t2) <lb/>57.00 (30.50-92.50) <lb/>59.00 (29.00-105.50) <lb/>Subjects (N) with GTI-CWS=0 <lb/>3 (10.3) <lb/>8 (7.3) <lb/>Subjects (N) with GTI-CWS&gt;0 <lb/>26 (89.7) <lb/>101 (92.7) <lb/>GC-associated complications and sequelae (at t2) <lb/>Metabolism <lb/>Weight gain <lb/>8 (27.6) <lb/>3 (2.8) <lb/>Lipodystrophy <lb/>2 (6.9) <lb/>3 (2.8) <lb/>Diabetes/glucose intolerance <lb/>11 (37.9) <lb/>12 (11.0) <lb/>Adrenal insufficiency <lb/>0 <lb/>2 (1.8) <lb/>Dyslipidaemia <lb/>6 (20.7) <lb/>8 (7.3) <lb/>Musculoskeletal and skin <lb/>Skin atrophy <lb/>3 (10.3) <lb/>42 (38.5) <lb/>Easy bruising <lb/>4 (13.8) <lb/>26 (23.9) <lb/>Osteopenia <lb/>2 (6.9) <lb/>14 (12.8) <lb/>Osteoporosis <lb/>5 (17.2) <lb/>17 (15.6) <lb/>Myopathy/muscle weakness <lb/>4 (13.8) <lb/>13 (11.9) <lb/>Acne <lb/>0 (0.0) <lb/>7 (6.4) <lb/>Striae rubrae <lb/>1 (3.4) <lb/>3 (2.8) <lb/>Infections <lb/>6 (20.7) <lb/>9 (8.3) <lb/>Neuropsychiatric symptoms <lb/>Sleep disturbances <lb/>9 (31.0) <lb/>16 (14.7) <lb/>Mood swings <lb/>3 (10.3) <lb/>13 (11.9) <lb/>Depression <lb/>2 (6.9) <lb/>12 (11.0) <lb/>Dizziness <lb/>3 (10.3) <lb/>6 (5.5) <lb/>Tinnitus <lb/>0 (0.0) <lb/>8 (7.3) <lb/>Headaches <lb/>3 (10.3) <lb/>6 (5.5) <lb/>Irritability <lb/>2 (6.9) <lb/>7 (6.4) <lb/>Nervousness <lb/>0 <lb/>2 (1.8) <lb/>Continued <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003956 on 29 February 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>

        <page>4 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Scherbacher PJ, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003956. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003956 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/></note>

        <body>(51.4%), 25 patients with MPA (18.1%) and 42 patients <lb/>with EGPA (30.4%). The mean age was 56.8 (±15.3) years. <lb/>The majority of patients were women (n=76, 55.1). <lb/>The median current GC exposure was 501.5 mg (IQR <lb/>0.0-993.3). The mean total cumulative dose was <lb/>9014.0 mg (IQR 4974.8-17 389.3). The median disease <lb/>duration was 57.0 months (IQR 25.8-103.5). <lb/>29 patients (21.0%) had active disease (BVAS&gt;0) at <lb/>t1, while 109 patients (79.0%) were in stable remission <lb/>during the same period (BVAS=0). <lb/>During the observational period between t1 and t2, <lb/>an infection was recorded in 10% of patients. Over the <lb/>entire disease duration, 46 (33%) patients developed <lb/>infections, 13.8% of which were severe. <lb/>Active disease at t1 <lb/>Stable remission <lb/>Cardiovascular <lb/>Renal dysfunction <lb/>0 <lb/>1 (0.9) <lb/>Oedema <lb/>5 (17.2) <lb/>9 (8.3) <lb/>Disturbance of electrolyte balance <lb/>1 (3.4) <lb/>1 (0.9) <lb/>Arterial hypertension <lb/>8 (27.6) <lb/>11 (10.1) <lb/>Atherosclerosis <lb/>0 <lb/>1 (0.9) <lb/>Angina pectoris <lb/>1 (3.4) <lb/>0 <lb/>Gastrointestinal <lb/>Gastritis <lb/>0 (0.0) <lb/>1 (0.9) <lb/>Ophthalmological <lb/>Cataract <lb/>2 (6.9) <lb/>16 (14.7) <lb/>Glaucoma <lb/>0 <lb/>2 (1.8) <lb/>Data as n (%), mean ± SD or median (IQR); *GTI scores were given as median (IQR). <lb/>AIS, Aggregate Improvement Score; CWS, Cumulative Worsening Score; EGPA, eosinophilic GPA; GC, glucocorticoids; GPA, granulomatosis <lb/>with polyangiitis; GTI, Glucocorticoid Toxicity Index; MPA, microscopic polyangiitis. <lb/>Table 1 Continued <lb/>Figure 1 Cumulative GC dose and GTI-AIS scoring. Scatter plot showing the relationship between cumulative GC dose in mg <lb/>and GTI-AIS scoring. AIS, Aggregate Improvement Score; GC, glucocorticoids; GTI, Glucocorticoid Toxicity Index. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003956 on 29 February 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>

        <page>5 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Scherbacher PJ, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003956. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003956 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Vasculitis Vasculitis Vasculitis <lb/></note>

        <body>Change in GC toxicity between t1 and t2 <lb/>At the end of the observation period (ie, t2), 50.7% <lb/>of our AAV patients showed no change in recent GC <lb/>toxicity (GTI-AIS=0), in 27 (19.6%) an improvement <lb/>(GIT-AIS&lt;0) and in 41 (29.7%) an increase in GC toxicity <lb/>(GTI-AIS&gt;0) was documented. The current GC exposure <lb/>between t1 and t2 correlated positively with GTI-AIS <lb/>scores (r=0.490; p&lt;0.001) as shown in figure 1, which <lb/>was supported by regression analyses (adjusted R 2 =0.262; <lb/>F(df=1;136)=49.74; p&lt;0.001). <lb/>Of those patients whose GC toxicity worsened during <lb/>t1 and t2 19 (46%) had active AAV. In patients with <lb/>active disease, 65.5% had an increasing GC toxicity <lb/>(GTI-AIS&gt;0) compared with 20.2% in those with stable <lb/>remission (p&lt;0.001). In parallel, the mean current GC <lb/>exposure in active disease versus remission was 1745.0 mg <lb/>(IQR 1206.5-2542.0) vs 240.0 mg (IQR 0.00-733.00), <lb/>respectively (p&lt;0.001). A complete list of features char-<lb/>acterising patients with active disease and remission is <lb/>shown in table 1. <lb/>Overall GC toxicity <lb/>The median GTI-CWS at t2 was 58.5 (IQR 29.0-102.3). <lb/>11 patients (8.0%) had a GTI-CWS of 0, whereas in <lb/>127 (92.0%) the GTI-CWS was&gt;0. In both correlation <lb/>and regression analyses, the GTI-CWS showed a weak <lb/>association with the total cumulative GC dose (Spear-<lb/>man&apos;s r=0.251; p=0.003. Regression: adjusted R 2 =0.262; <lb/>F(df=1;136)=49.74; p&lt;0.001). <lb/>We found a weak relationship between disease dura-<lb/>tion and GTI-CWS (Spearman&apos;s r=0.215, p=0.11). <lb/>Neither the current GC exposure between t1 and <lb/>t2 (r=0.042; p=0.556) nor the disease activity state at <lb/>t1 (p=0.664) exerted any influence on the GTI-CWS <lb/>(figure 2). <lb/>Sex-related and age-related differences in GC toxicity <lb/>The total cumulative GC dose and the current GC expo-<lb/>sure between t1 and t2 showed no significant difference <lb/>between women and men, nor did the acute change in <lb/>GC toxicity (online supplemental table S4). Cumulative <lb/>GC toxicity (CWS) was significantly higher in women <lb/>than in men. Osteoporosis was found more frequently in <lb/>women (p=0.022) while acne was more common in men <lb/>(p=0.022). <lb/>Patients of 65 years and above were more prone to <lb/>cataract (p=0.035), skin atrophy (p=0.005) and diabetes <lb/>(p=0.029). All other items of GC toxicity showed no <lb/>differences when dividing the cohort by sex and age <lb/>(online supplemental tables S3 and S4). <lb/>GC threshold dose for GC-related toxicity <lb/>The ROC analysis with the current GC exposure between <lb/>t1 and t2 and the GTI-AIS (figure 3) showed an area <lb/>under the curve (AUC) of 0.815 (95% CI 0.733 to 0.896) <lb/>with a threshold dose of 733.0 mg for the state variable <lb/>GTI-AIS&gt;0 and a threshold dose of 935 mg considering <lb/>the MCID (GTI-AIS&gt;10) with an AUC of 0.800 (95% CI <lb/>0.713 to 0.877). <lb/>Association of GC toxicity and PROs (AAV-PRO) <lb/>AAV patients with GTI-AIS&gt;10 had a significantly higher score <lb/>in the AAV-PRO domain &apos;physical functioning&apos; compared <lb/>with AAV patients with GTI-AIS&lt;10 (p=0.034). Patients with <lb/>active disease scored significantly higher in the &apos;concerns <lb/>about the future&apos; category compared with AAV patients <lb/>Figure 2 Percentage of patients with GTI-AIS 0, &gt;0 and &lt;0 according to disease activity. In patients with active disease <lb/>changes in current GC toxicity as captured by the AIS (GTI-AIS) are more likely compared with patients in stable remission. AIS, <lb/>Aggregate Improvement Score; GC, glucocorticoids; GTI, Glucocorticoid Toxicity Index. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003956 on 29 February 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>

        <page>6 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Scherbacher PJ, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003956. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003956 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/></note>

        <body>in stable remission (p=0.019). All other dimensions of the <lb/>AAV-PRO did not significantly correlate with GTI results, <lb/>including the domain &apos;treatment side effects&apos;. The complete <lb/>data on AAV-PRO and GTI-AIS are shown in table 2. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>This prospective study investigated GC-associated compli-<lb/>cations and sequelae in a real-world cohort of patients <lb/>with AAV using the GTI as a validated scoring instrument <lb/>for GC toxicity. <lb/>Our data confirm that GC-associated complications <lb/>in AAV patients are very common, reflected by only <lb/>8% of patients with a GTI-CWS of 0. AAV disease dura-<lb/>tion showed only a very weak correlation with GTI-CWS <lb/>scoring. In our cohort, patients with stable remission had <lb/>significantly longer disease durations compared with <lb/>those with active AAV, which might have affected these <lb/>findings. <lb/>In this study, we found relatively low infection rates in <lb/>our cohort, especially between t1 and t2. Published data <lb/>report that 30% of AAV patients develop severe infec-<lb/>tions requiring intravenous antimicrobial treatment <lb/>and/or hospitalisation. 9 20 In general, GC treatment is <lb/>associated with increased rates of infections, 9-11 which <lb/>led to several endeavours to reduce GC exposure in <lb/>AAV patients. However, results of studies investigating <lb/>GC-sparing strategies with regard to the risk of infections <lb/>are heterogeneous: In the PEXIVAS trial, a reduced GC <lb/>protocol was capable of significantly diminishing severe <lb/>infectious events by 31%. 21 In the LOVAS trial, a reduced <lb/>GC protocol was capable of reducing infections by almost <lb/>13%. 22 In contrast, reduction of GC exposure in patients <lb/>receiving avacopan in a phase 3 trial was associated with <lb/>an overall reduction of GC toxicity after 26 weeks but did <lb/>not lead to significantly reduced infection rates. 12 In a <lb/>study with EGPA patients, mepolizumab led to a drastic <lb/>reduction in GC use, but GC toxicity measured by the GTI-<lb/>AIS did not change significantly in the overall cohort. 23 <lb/>Prophylaxis with trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole was <lb/>applied in 29 (21%) of our AAV patients. In patients with <lb/>Figure 3 Determination of GC threshold dose. Receiver operating characteristics (ROC) curves to determine the cumulative <lb/>GC threshold dose between t1 and t2 beyond which any GTI-AIS change (A) and a GIT-AIS&gt;10 (B) representing the minimum <lb/>clinically important difference. (A) AUC 0.815, p&lt;0.001, 95% CI 0.733 to 0.896. (B) AUC 0.800, p&lt;0.001, 95% CI 0.713 to <lb/>0.887. AIS, Aggregate Improvement Score; AUC, area under the curve; GC, glucocorticoids; GTI, Glucocorticoid Toxicity Index. <lb/>Table 2 Comparison between GTI and AAV-PRO questionnaire scoring <lb/>AAV-PRO <lb/>Active disease <lb/>Stable remission <lb/>P value GTI-AIS≥10 <lb/>GTI-AIS&lt;10 <lb/>P value <lb/>Organ-specific symptoms <lb/>27.50 (15.00-40.00) 30.00 (20.00-50.00) 0.297 <lb/>32.5 (20.0-45.0) 30.0 (15.0-45.0) 0.760 <lb/>Systemic symptoms <lb/>43.75 (14.06-60.94) 37.50 (18.75-62.50) 0.930 <lb/>43.8 (18.8-62.5) 37.5 (18.8-56.3) 0.594 <lb/>Treatment side effects <lb/>20.00 (10.00-30.00) 25.00 (15.00-35.00) 0.538 <lb/>22.5 (15.0-35.0) 25.0 (10.0-35.0) 0.743 <lb/>Social and emotional impact 35.42 (13.54-44.88) 25.00 (12.50-45.83) 0.157 <lb/>37.5 (16.7-41.9) 25.0 (8.3-45.8) <lb/>0.163 <lb/>Concerns about the future <lb/>45.00 (26.25-55.00) 25.00 (15.00-50.00) 0.019 <lb/>40.0 (20.0-55.0) 25.0 (15.0-50.0) 0.237 <lb/>Physical functioning <lb/>18.75 (6.25-37.50) <lb/>12.50 (0.00-31.25) <lb/>0.100 <lb/>18.8 (6.3-48.4) <lb/>12.5 (0.0-25.0) <lb/>0.034 <lb/>AAV-PRO, ANCA-associated vasculitis patient-reported outcomes; AIS, Aggregate Improvement Score; ANCA, antineutrophil <lb/>cytoplasmic antibodies; GTI, Glucocorticoid Toxicity Index. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003956 on 29 February 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>

        <page>7 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Scherbacher PJ, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003956. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003956 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Vasculitis Vasculitis Vasculitis <lb/></note>

        <body>a mean daily prednisone dose of &gt;7.5 mg 50% received <lb/>prophylaxis, compared with 16% of those with a predni-<lb/>sone dose of ≤7.5 mg. This might have added to the low <lb/>infection rates observed in our cohort. 24 <lb/>It was to be expected that GC toxicity is dose-dependent, <lb/>which our data confirm. However, correlations between <lb/>GC dose and GTI-CWS were surprisingly weak. EGPA <lb/>patients showing the highest cumulative GC dose in our <lb/>study did not reach higher toxicity scores in the GTI-<lb/>CWS. However, GTI-AIS was significantly influenced by <lb/>disease activity, which is consistent with dose-dependent <lb/>GC toxicity since patients with new onset disease or flares <lb/>usually require higher GC doses. <lb/>Interestingly, 20% of our patients had an increase <lb/>in recent GC toxicity during the observational period <lb/>between t1 and t2 (GTI-AIS&gt;0) despite being in complete <lb/>remission and on a low GC dose (mean cumulative dose of <lb/>240 mg prednisone between t1 and t2). This supports our <lb/>observation that even low daily GC doses cause toxicity <lb/>when applied over a longer period of time. Furthermore, <lb/>this might raise suspicion that other factors leading to <lb/>health states captured by the GTI, especially cardiovas-<lb/>cular diseases, are present. <lb/>We conclude that the relationship between GC use <lb/>and objective measures of toxicity in AAV is complex, <lb/>especially with regard to the MCID. Many GC toxicity <lb/>items, especially the ones associated with cardiovascular <lb/>diseases, are affected by factors beyond vasculitis such <lb/>as behavioural habits, socioeconomic factors, education <lb/>and genetics. For this reason, diseases such as atheroscle-<lb/>rosis, myocardial infarction, stroke or heart failure are <lb/>not captured by the GTI. Still, active AAV and its therapy <lb/>are likely to negatively affect these conditions. According <lb/>to our findings, cumulative GC doses and disease activity <lb/>significantly impact GC toxicity. <lb/>AAV patients with active disease who received higher <lb/>GC doses for induction of remission were more likely <lb/>to exhibit acute GC side effects such as weight gain, <lb/>diabetes, sleep disturbances and arterial hypertension <lb/>than AAV patients in stable remission. In contrast, long-<lb/>term GC toxicities such as skin atrophy were significantly <lb/>more common in patients in stable remission due to the <lb/>high cumulative GC exposure over the entire treatment <lb/>period. <lb/>Using an ROC analysis, we calculated that at a cumula-<lb/>tive GC dose of 935 mg within 180 days is highly predic-<lb/>tive of a clinically meaningful GC toxicity event, which to <lb/>our knowledge, has never been reported thus far. Thus, <lb/>an average dose of just over 5 mg prednisone per day <lb/>applied over 6 months is sufficient to reach this threshold. <lb/>Provided that a patient with life and organ-threatening <lb/>AAV requires a GC pulse therapy with 250 mg prednis-<lb/>olone intravenously over 3 days followed by a GC taper <lb/>regimen according to PEXIVAS protocol, 21 the toxicity <lb/>threshold derived from our data would be reached within <lb/>1 week of therapy. This is underlined by the observation <lb/>that over 90% of AAV patients in our cohort exhibit GC <lb/>toxicity in the GTI-CWS. Of note, this threshold certainly <lb/>does not apply for all GC toxicities. Osteoporosis and <lb/>skin atrophy, for instance, will only occur after a long-<lb/>term GC exposure. <lb/>The data of Flossmann et al point out that older <lb/>adults show a higher vulnerability to GC side effects <lb/>in multiple organ systems, 9 which is supported by <lb/>our findings, especially regarding diabetes and skin <lb/>atrophy. <lb/>It is noteworthy, that the novel AAV-PRO questionnaire <lb/>showed some significant correlations with the GTI results. <lb/>In our cohort, physical limitations were reported signifi-<lb/>cantly higher in patients with high GC toxicity, whereas, <lb/>surprisingly, no significant findings were observed in the <lb/>domain &apos;treatment side effects&apos;. The discrepancy between <lb/>patient and physician reported toxicity and damage is <lb/>well known. 25 26 Other authors describe similar findings <lb/>using the European Quality of Life 5 Dimensions 5 Levels <lb/>(EQ5D5L) instrument. 23 This might be explained by the <lb/>fact that the AAV-PRO purely reports PROs, while the GTI <lb/>is a clinician-facing instrument relying on patient input. 19 <lb/>For instance, elevated blood pressure or hyperlipidemia <lb/>can be detected by the physician but could easily be <lb/>missed by a PRO instrument. Disease-specific PRO instru-<lb/>ments have become a field of interest in rheumatology. <lb/>However, our data suggest, that GC-related toxicity can <lb/>easily be missed when relying solely on PRO, and there-<lb/>fore, argue for the use of the GTI in AAV patients. <lb/>Our study has limitations worth mentioning: It is a <lb/>single-centre study and data were taken from routine <lb/>care. The selection of control patients might have <lb/>been biased. The (in part) retrospective assessment <lb/>of the cumulative GC dose from medical records <lb/>might be erroneous. Only 21% of our patients had <lb/>active disease, which limits the interpretability for <lb/>this subset of patients and might also explain the <lb/>low rate of infections detected in our study. We only <lb/>included established or patient-reported diagnoses <lb/>that accounted for (possible) GC-related toxicities. <lb/>There was no active screening for these conditions. <lb/>Some correlations between GTI items and cumulative <lb/>GC doses are surprisingly weak or non-existent, which <lb/>might be due to the fact that we did not adjust for <lb/>preexisting toxicities before the observational period. <lb/>In summary, AAV patients have a high exposure <lb/>to GC over the course of their disease. Our findings <lb/>show that nearly all AAV patients experience GC-as-<lb/>sociated toxicity. Our data support the urgent need <lb/>to limit GC exposure in AAV patients, which can be <lb/>achieved by developing and establishing efficacious <lb/>immunosuppressive agents allowing the restriction of <lb/>dose and time of GC exposure. <lb/></body>

        <div type="contribution">Contributors PJS: project planning, data acquisition, drafting manuscript, <lb/>statistical analyses. BH: project planning, drafting and revising manuscript. Y-SF: <lb/>statistical analyses, drafting and revising manuscript. CL: data acquisition, drafting <lb/>and revising manuscript, statistical analyses, guarantor. <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">Funding The authors have not declared a specific grant for this research from any <lb/>funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors. <lb/></div>

        <div type="conflict">Competing interests None declared. <lb/></div>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003956 on 29 February 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. <lb/></note>

        <page>8 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Scherbacher PJ, et al. RMD Open 2024;10:e003956. doi:10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003956 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/>RMD Open <lb/></note>

        <div type="annex">Patient consent for publication Not applicable. <lb/>Ethics approval This study involves human participants and we obtained approval <lb/>for the conduction of this study from the Ethics Committee of the Eberhard Karls <lb/>University, Tübingen, Germany (project no. 740/2021BO2). Participants gave <lb/>informed consent to participate in the study before taking part. <lb/>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. <lb/>Data availability statement Data are available on reasonable request. On <lb/>reasonable request to the corresponding author, source data for this work can be <lb/>made available. <lb/>Supplemental material This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has <lb/>not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been <lb/>peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those <lb/>of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and <lb/>responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content <lb/>includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability <lb/>of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, <lb/>terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error <lb/>and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise. <lb/></div>

        <front>Open access This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which <lb/>permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, <lb/>and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is <lb/>properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the <lb/>use is non-commercial. See: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/. <lb/>ORCID iDs <lb/>Bernhard Hellmich http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8014-1801 <lb/>Christian Löffler http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9401-3811 <lb/></front>

        <listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1 Jennette JC, Falk RJ, Bacon PA, et al. 2012 revised international <lb/>chapel hill consensus conference nomenclature of vasculitides. <lb/>Arthritis Rheum 2013;65:1-11. <lb/>2 Robson JC, Dawson J, Cronholm PF, et al. Patient perceptions of <lb/>glucocorticoids in anti-neutrophil cytoplasmatic antibody-associated <lb/>vasculitis. Rheumatol Int 2018;38:675-82. <lb/>3 Hellmich B, Lamprecht P, Spearpoint P, et al. New insights into the <lb/>epidemiology of ANCA-associated vasculitides in Germany: results <lb/>from a claims data study. Rheumatology (Oxford) 2021;60:4868-73. <lb/>4 Herlyn K, Hellmich B, Gross WL, et al. Stable incidence of systemic <lb/>vasculitides in schleswig-holstein, Germany. Dtsch Arztebl Int <lb/>2008;105:355-61. <lb/>5 Ormerod AS, Cook MC. Epidemiology of primary systemic vasculitis <lb/>in the Australian capital territory and South-Eastern New South <lb/>Wales. Intern Med J 2008;38:816-23. <lb/>6 Hellmich B, Sanchez-Alamo B, Schirmer JH, et al. EULAR <lb/>recommendations for the management of ANCA-associated <lb/>vasculitis: 2022 update. Ann Rheum Dis 2024;83:30-47. <lb/>7 Chung SA, Langford CA, Maz M, et al. American college of <lb/>rheumatology/vasculitis foundation guideline for the management of <lb/>antineutrophil cytoplasmic antibody-associated vasculitis. Arthritis <lb/>Rheumatol 2021;73:1366-83. <lb/>8 Rovin BH, Adler SG, Barratt J, et al. Executive summary of the <lb/>KDIGO 2021 guideline for the management of glomerular diseases. <lb/>Kidney Int 2021;100:753-79. <lb/>9 Flossmann O, Berden A, de Groot K, et al. Long-term patient survival <lb/>in ANCA-associated vasculitis. Ann Rheum Dis 2011;70:488-94. <lb/>10 Strehl C, Bijlsma JWJ, de Wit M, et al. Defining conditions where <lb/>long-term glucocorticoid treatment has an acceptably low level of <lb/>harm to facilitate implementation of existing recommendations: <lb/>viewpoints from an EULAR task force. Ann Rheum Dis <lb/>2016;75:952-7. <lb/>11 van der Goes MC, Jacobs JWG, Boers M, et al. Monitoring <lb/>adverse events of low-dose glucocorticoid therapy: EULAR <lb/>recommendations for clinical trials and daily practice. Ann Rheum <lb/>Dis 2010;69:1913-9. <lb/>12 Jayne DRW, Merkel PA, Schall TJ, et al. Avacopan for the treatment <lb/>of ANCA-associated vasculitis. N Engl J Med 2021;384:599-609. <lb/>13 Schirmer JH, Sanchez-Alamo B, Hellmich B, et al. Systematic <lb/>literature review informing the 2022 update of the EULAR <lb/>recommendations for the management of ANCA-associated <lb/>vasculitis (AAV): part 1-treatment of granulomatosis with polyangiitis <lb/>and microscopic polyangiitis. RMD Open 2023;9:e003082. <lb/>14 Sanchez-Alamo B, Schirmer JH, Hellmich B, et al. Systematic <lb/>literature review informing the 2022 update of the EULAR <lb/>recommendations for the management of ANCA-associated <lb/>vasculitis (AAV): part 2 -treatment of eosinophilic granulomatosis <lb/>with polyangiitis and diagnosis and general management of AAV. <lb/>RMD Open 2023;9:e003083. <lb/>15 Exley AR, Bacon PA, Luqmani RA, et al. Development and initial <lb/>validation of the vasculitis damage index for the standardized clinical <lb/>assessment of damage in the systemic vasculitides. Arthritis Rheum <lb/>1997;40:371-80. <lb/>16 Miloslavsky EM, Naden RP, Bijlsma JWJ, et al. Development of <lb/>a glucocorticoid toxicity index (GTI) using multicriteria decision <lb/>analysis. Ann Rheum Dis 2017;76:543-6. <lb/>17 Robson JC, Dawson J, Doll H, et al. Validation of the ANCA-<lb/>associated vasculitis patient-reported outcomes (AAV-PRO) <lb/>questionnarie. Ann Rheum Dis 2018;77:1157-64. <lb/>18 Maunz A, Jacoby J, Henes J, et al. Association of the AAV-<lb/>PRO questionnaire with established outcome measures in AAV. <lb/>Rheumatology (Oxford) 2024;63:174-80. <lb/>19 Stone JH, McDowell PJ, Jayne DRW, et al. The glucocorticoid <lb/>toxicity index: measuring change in glucocorticoid toxicity over time. <lb/>Semin Arthritis Rheum 2022;55:152010. <lb/>20 Flossmann O. Risks of treatments and long-term outcomes of <lb/>systemic ANCA-associated vasculitis. Presse Med 2015;44:e251-7. <lb/>21 Walsh M, Merkel PA, Peh C-A, et al. Plasma exchange and <lb/>glucocorticoids in severe ANCA-associated vasculitis. N Engl J Med <lb/>2020;382:622-31. <lb/>22 Furuta S, Nakagomi D, Kobayashi Y, et al. Effect of reduced-dose vs <lb/>high-dose glucocorticoids added to rituximab on remission induction <lb/>in ANCA-associated vasculitis: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA <lb/>2021;325:2178-87. <lb/>23 McDowell PJ, Stone JH, Zhang Y, et al. Glucocorticoid toxicity <lb/>reduction with mepolizumab using the glucocorticoid toxicity index. <lb/>Eur Respir J 2022;59:2100160. <lb/>24 Kronbichler A, Kerschbaum J, Gopaluni S, et al. Trimethoprim-<lb/>sulfamethoxazole prophylaxis prevents severe/life-threatening <lb/>infections following rituximab in antineutrophil cytoplasm antibody-<lb/>associated vasculitis. Ann Rheum Dis 2018;77:1440-7. <lb/>25 Herlyn K, Hellmich B, Seo P, et al. Patient-reported outcome <lb/>assessment in vasculitis may provide important data and a unique <lb/>perspective. Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken) 2010;62:1639-45. <lb/>26 Seo P, Jayne D, Luqmani R, et al. Assessment of damage in <lb/>vasculitis: expert ratings of damage. Rheumatology (Oxford) <lb/>2009;48:823-7. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="headnote">RMD Open: first published as 10.1136/rmdopen-2023-003956 on 29 February 2024. Downloaded from https://rmdopen.bmj.com on 10 September 2025 by guest. <lb/>Protected by copyright, including for uses related to text and data mining, AI training, and similar technologies. </note>


	</text>

</TEI>