<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">The Impact of Student-Centered Teaching Strategies on Educational Attainment in Econometrics: Evidence From the UK</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Imran Hussain</forename>
            <surname>Shah</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Audrey</forename>
            <surname>Au Yong Lyn</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Guillaume Maxence Augustin</forename>
            <surname>Morlet</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Ladina</forename>
            <surname>Rageth</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-31T10:57:35.536608Z">31.10.2025 10:57:35</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1177$1$21582440241240844</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>SAGE Publications</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1177/21582440241240844</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Imran Hussain Shah, Audrey Au Yong Lyn, Guillaume Maxence Augustin Morlet, Ladina Rageth. (2024). The Impact of Student-Centered Teaching Strategies on Educational Attainment in Econometrics: Evidence From the UK. Sage Open, 14(2), None. DOI: 10.1177/21582440241240844</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-31T10:57:35.536608Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-31T10:57:35.536608Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>271 <lb/>Apollo Medicine Volume 21 Issue 3 September 2024 <lb/>Apollo Medicine <lb/>21(3) 271-274, 2024 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s) <lb/>Article reuse guidelines: <lb/>in.sagepub.com/journals-permissions-india <lb/>DOI: 10.1177/09760016241245254 <lb/>journals.sagepub.com/home/aom <lb/>Creative Commons Non Commercial CC BY-NC: This article is distributed <lb/>under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial <lb/>4.0 License (http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits non-<lb/>Commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission <lb/>provided the original work is attributed as specified on the Sage and Open Access pages <lb/>(https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage). <lb/>Submitted: 18-Sep-2023 <lb/>Revised: 20-Oct-2023 <lb/>Accepted: 26-Oct-2023 <lb/>Published: 30-Mar-2024 <lb/>How to cite this article: Priyadharshan KP, Marappan K, Mathew M, Mani <lb/>AK, Vakamala HR, Jayamoorthy T. Pleuro-spinal hydatid cyst masquerading <lb/>as spinal tuberculosis: A rare case report. Apollo Med 2024;21:271-274. <lb/>Case Report <lb/>Pleuro-spinal Hydatid Cyst Masquerading as Spinal <lb/>Tuberculosis: A Rare Case Report <lb/>K. P. Priyadharshan, Kodeeswaran Marappan, Meghena Mathew, Ashwin Kumar Mani, Haritha Reddy Vakamala, T. Jayamoorthy 1 <lb/>Departments of Neurosurgery and 1 orthopaedics, Apollo First Med Hospital, Chennai, Tamil Nadu, India <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Introduction: Primary hydatid cyst of the spinal cord is exceedingly rare. Diagnosis at the early stages is difficult as they may be asymptomatic <lb/>or have mild vague pain. Patients typically present when there are features of cord/root compression. Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) stands <lb/>as the primary investigative modality, but even then, preoperative diagnosis might not always be possible as it may resemble other pathological <lb/>conditions. Methods: This was a case report of a single case with evidence-based discussion. Informed consent was obtained. Case Report: We <lb/>present a 62-year-old female patient with progressive paraparesis and numbness of bilateral lower limbs. MRI was suggestive of a tubercular <lb/>pleurospinal lesion at the D9-D10 level. However, intraoperatively, it was identified to be a rare case of primary pleurospinal (thoracic) hydatid <lb/>cyst. The patient was managed with complete surgical removal of all the cysts and antihelminthic drug therapy with no evidence of recurrence <lb/>at the 2-year follow-up. Conclusion: Radiological diagnosis might not be accurate and hydatidosis must be kept in mind to avoid intraoperative <lb/>confusion. Timely diagnosis, appropriate surgical planning, and comprehensive follow-up are crucial for achieving optimal outcomes. <lb/>Keywords: Echinococcosis, humans, hydatid, spinal cord compression <lb/>Address for correspondence: Prof. Kodeeswaran Marappan, <lb/>Apollo First Med Hospital, 154, Poonamalee High Road, Kilpauk, <lb/>Chennai -600 010, Tamil Nadu, India. <lb/>E-mail: neurokodee@gmail.com <lb/></front>

        <body>IntroductIon <lb/>Hydatid cyst is caused by the cestode Echinococcus granulosus. <lb/>The incidence of bony hydatid lesions ranges from 0.5% <lb/>to 3% of hydatidosis with half of them occurring in the <lb/>vertebral system. [1,2] The vertebral involvement is commonly <lb/>a direct extension from an adjoining tissue/organ. Direct <lb/>primary involvement of vertebral bone is rare, and contiguous <lb/>intrathoracic involvement is even rarer. [2] Even with the advent <lb/>of advanced magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) techniques, <lb/>it might sometimes be difficult to arrive at a preoperative <lb/>diagnosis as it may resemble other infectious conditions. [3] <lb/>Here, we present the case of a primary pleurospinal (thoracic) <lb/>hydatid cyst with epidural extension causing spinal cord <lb/>compression and paraparesis. <lb/>case report <lb/>Case presentation <lb/>A 62-year-old female patient presented to our hospital with a <lb/>three-month history of progressive weakness, numbness of <lb/>bilateral lower limbs, and difficulty in walking. She also <lb/>complained of vague back pain for the past year. Neurological <lb/>examination revealed paraparesis, with reduced muscle <lb/>strength (MRC grade 3/5 bilaterally) and impaired sensation <lb/>below the D8 level. <lb/>Diagnosis <lb/>MRI imaging showed the presence of a T1 hypo, T2 <lb/>hyperintense dumbbell-shaped pleurospinal multicystic <lb/>lesion located at the D9-D10 vertebral level with <lb/>spinal cord compression [Figure 1]. The radiologist <lb/>provided a differential diagnosis of tuberculous/nonspecific <lb/>abscess. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Priyadharshan, et al.: Rare primary pleurospinal hydatidosis <lb/></note>

        <page>272 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Apollo Medicine Volume 21 Issue 3 September 2024 <lb/></note>

        <body>Intervention <lb/>After a preanesthetic checkup, the patient was taken up <lb/>for surgery. The patient was placed in a prone position under <lb/>general anesthesia. A posterior midline incision was made <lb/>extending from D8 to D11. Bilateral D9-D10 decompressive <lb/>laminectomy relieved the pressure on the cord and the <lb/>cord regained pulsatility. On the left lateral aspect, whitish <lb/>cysts were seen extending along the root and exiting via the <lb/>intervertebral foramina which was widened. A midline <lb/>posterior durotomy was made and no intradural extension <lb/>cysts were present. To gain better access and ensure complete <lb/>removal, an extension into a left posterolateral D10 <lb/>thoracotomy was made [Figure 2]. <lb/>Careful dissection was carried out to identify the cysts, which <lb/>were adherent to the spinal cord and surrounding tissues. <lb/>Due to dense adhesions to the surrounding tissue, some <lb/>cysts ruptured when attempting removal [Figure 2]. <lb/>Contamination was kept to a minimum by continuous suction <lb/>and preemptively covering the lung and surrounding tissue <lb/>with cottonoids. After ensuring complete removal, the cystic <lb/>cavity was thoroughly irrigated with 30% hypertonic saline. <lb/>An intercostal drain was placed. The patient was extubated <lb/>postoperatively, the ICD was removed on day two, and the <lb/>patient was discharged on day four postoperatively. <lb/>Outcome and follow-up <lb/>Postoperatively, the patient showed immediate improvement <lb/>in motor strength and sensation. Histopathological examination <lb/>confirmed the diagnosis of a hydatid cyst. The patient was <lb/>prescribed albendazole for three months postoperatively. As of <lb/>the review done at one-year postoperatively, the patient had no <lb/>Figure 1: (a) T1 sagittal section showing heterogeneously hypointense <lb/>lesion in the posterior aspect of D9-D10 vertebra, (b-d) T2-weighted <lb/>images showing heterogeneously hyperintense dumbbell-shaped lesion <lb/>with surrounding bony erosion and cord compression <lb/>Figure 2: (a) Intraoperative imaging with T-shaped incision -midline <lb/>vertical plus left posterolateral thoracotomy. The Dura (white arrow) was <lb/>opened to ensure no intradural extension. Right lateral thoracotomy for <lb/>extirpation of pleural cavity cysts -Lung parenchyma appeared normal. <lb/>D9-D10 intercostal space (black arrow), (b) Excised hydatid cysts of <lb/>varying sizes <lb/>Figure 3: Postoperative image at 2 years with postoperative changes <lb/>and no recurrence <lb/>neurological deficit, and during the 24-month follow-up <lb/>period, the patient remained asymptomatic, with no evidence <lb/>of recurrence [Figure 3]. [4] <lb/>dIscussIon <lb/>Spinal echinococcosis was first reported in 1807. [5] The <lb/>condition is endemic in countries with large sheep-rearing <lb/>populations. [1] Humans acquire the infection via infected <lb/>dogs or by consumption of contaminated food/water. [2] <lb/>The cysts are carried through the bloodstream from the <lb/>intestinal wall to various organs. Liver is the most common <lb/>site (60-70%), followed by the lungs (10-15%). Spinal <lb/>involvement is seen in 0.2%-1%. [6] <lb/>The occurrence of vertebral hydatidosis is most prevalent in <lb/>individuals aged between 30 and 50 years but can occur <lb/>in children as well. [5] Involvement of the vertebra in hydatid <lb/>disease typically occurs as a result of direct extension <lb/>from the abdomen, chest cavity, or pelvis. Among the various <lb/>regions of the spine, the most commonly affected are the <lb/></body>

        <page>273 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Apollo Medicine Volume 21 Issue 3 September 2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Priyadharshan, et al.: Rare primary pleurospinal hydatidosis <lb/></note>

        <body>recommended and in some patients, due to extensive vertebral <lb/>body erosion, anterior decompression and spinal fusion was <lb/>recommended as a second stage. [15] In our patient, the bony <lb/>erosion was not severe enough to necessitate fusion and the <lb/>decompression and excision alone was sufficient. <lb/>Thorough irrigation of the cavity with cysticidal agent <lb/>(hypertonic saline 30%, cetrimide, and 70%-95% ethanol) is <lb/>suggested for reducing recurrence. [16,17] In our patient, 30% <lb/>hypertonic saline irrigation was utilized. In the postoperative <lb/>period, oral albendazole was administered for 3 months. Our <lb/>literature search did not provide any consensus as to the <lb/>duration of therapy, which varied from study to study from <lb/>4 weeks to 1 year. [15,18] <lb/>conclusIon <lb/>This case report highlights the successful management <lb/>of a rare primary pleural and spinal hydatid cyst located at <lb/>the D9-10 level, leading to paraparesis. MRI findings are <lb/>not pathognomonic and may simulate similar pathological <lb/>conditions. Surgical intervention utilizing a posterior midline <lb/>approach with an extension into a left lateral thoracotomy <lb/>resulted in complete cyst removal and excellent postoperative <lb/>recovery. Timely diagnosis, appropriate surgical planning, <lb/>and comprehensive follow-up are crucial for achieving <lb/>optimal outcomes in cases of pleurospinal hydatid cysts. <lb/></body>

        <div type="conflict">declaratIon of conflIctIng Interests <lb/>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the <lb/>research, authorship and/or publication of this article. <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">fundIng <lb/>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/ <lb/>or publication of this article. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">declaratIon of patIent consent <lb/>The authors certify that he has obtained all appropriate patient consent <lb/>forms. In the form, the patient has given her consent for her images and other <lb/>clinical information to be reported in the journal. The patient understands <lb/>that her name and initials will not be published, and due efforts will be made <lb/>to conceal their identity, but anonymity cannot be guaranteed. <lb/>Informed consent <lb/>Patient consent has been obtained for publication in accordance with the <lb/>journal guidelines and shall be furnished on request. <lb/></div>

        <div type="contribution">credIt author statement <lb/>• Priyadharshan K.P. -Concept and design, draft and revision of intellectual <lb/>content, literature search, discussion and interpretation, manuscript <lb/>preparation, and review. <lb/>• Kodeeswaran M. -Concept, revision of draft, final approval of version to <lb/>be published, and manuscript review. <lb/>• Meghena Mathew -Concept and design of study. <lb/>• Ashwin Kumar Mani -Concept and design of study. <lb/>• Haritha Reddy Vakamala -Concept and design, original draft, discussion, <lb/>and interpretation. <lb/>• Jayamoorthy T. -Concept and design of study. <lb/></div>

        <body>Figure 4: (Reproduced -source added): Classification of spinal cystic <lb/>echinococcosis (CE) according to the Dew/Braithwaite and Lees <lb/>classification (type 1-5) and &apos;dumbbell&apos; formation. [4] Licensing: https:// <lb/>creativecommons.Org/licenses/by/4.0/(unchanged) <lb/>thoracic spine (52%), followed by the lumbar spine (37%), <lb/>cervical spine (5.5%), and sacral spine (5.5%). [7-9] Braithwaite <lb/>and Lees classified spinal hydatid disease based on radio-<lb/>anatomic characteristics. [4,9] Another classification method is <lb/>based on the route of infection, distinguishing between <lb/>primary and secondary spinal hydatid disease [7] [Figure 4]. <lb/>The vertebral body type is often seen as a dumbbell-shaped <lb/>lesion as was present in our patient. <lb/>Our patient presented with vague pain for the past year <lb/>and progressive paraparesis for three months. The duration <lb/>and characteristics of clinical symptoms can vary. Typical <lb/>manifestations often include back pain, paraparesis (weakness <lb/>in the lower limbs), radiculopathy (nerve root pain), sensory <lb/>disturbances, deformity, and involvement of the sphincter <lb/>muscles. Paraplegia, which refers to complete paralysis <lb/>of the lower limbs, is observed in approximately 26% of <lb/>cases. [10-12] <lb/>In our case, the preoperative diagnosis was difficult as the <lb/>lesion closely resembled a tuberculous/nonspecific abscess, a <lb/>diagnosis that has to be considered in an endemic country like <lb/>India. The lesion was completely extrapulmonary and involved <lb/>the vertebral pedicle, facet joints, and the body. MRI may not <lb/>be conclusive in all cases and some other differential diagnoses <lb/>mentioned in the literature that can closely resemble hydatidosis <lb/>are arachnoid cyst, tubercular spondylitis, and chronic <lb/>osteomyelitis. [13,14] <lb/>Surgical intervention remains the primary treatment modality, <lb/>aiming for complete cyst removal when preserving neurological <lb/>function. In this case, the posterior midline approach with <lb/>an extension into a left lateral thoracotomy provided <lb/>adequate exposure for complete cyst removal, resulting in a <lb/>successful outcome. In a similar series by Prabhakar et al., <lb/>wide decompressive laminectomy and debridement was <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Priyadharshan, et al.: Rare primary pleurospinal hydatidosis <lb/></note>

        <page>274 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Apollo Medicine Volume 21 Issue 3 September 2024 <lb/></note>

        <div type="availability">data avaIlabIlIty <lb/>Data available -open access. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">use of artIfIcIal IntellIgence <lb/>Artificial intelligence was not used. <lb/></div>

        <listBibl>references <lb/>1. Pamir MN, Akalan N, Ozgen T, Erbengi A. Spinal hydatid cysts. Surg <lb/>Neurol 1984;21:53-7. <lb/>2. Charles RW, Govender S, Naidoo KS. Echinococcal infection of <lb/>the spine with neural involvement. Spine (Phila Pa 1976) 1988;13: <lb/>47-9. <lb/>3. Doganay S, Kantarci M. Role of conventional and diffusion-weighted <lb/>magnetic resonance imaging of spinal treatment protocol for hydatid <lb/>disease. J Spinal Cord Med 2009;32:574-7. <lb/>4. Neumayr A, Tamarozzi F, Goblirsch S, Blum J, Brunetti E. Spinal <lb/>cystic echinococcosis -A systematic analysis and review of the <lb/>literature: Part 2. Treatment, follow-up and outcome. PLoS Negl Trop <lb/>Dis 2013;7:e2458. <lb/>5. Rayport M, Wisoff HS, Zaiman H. Vertebral echinococcosis: Report <lb/>of case of surgical and biological therapy with review of the literature. <lb/>J Neurosurg 1964;21:647-59. <lb/>6. Gopal N, Chauhan S, Yogesh N. Primary spinal extradural hydatid cyst <lb/>causing spinal cord compression. Indian J Orthop 2007;41:76-8. <lb/>7. Sioutis S, Reppas L, Bekos A, Soulioti E, Saranteas T, Koulalis D, <lb/>et al. Echinococcosis of the spine. EFORT Open Rev 2021;6:288-96. <lb/>8. Sharma A, Kashyap V, Abraham J, Kurian S. Intradural hydatid cysts <lb/>of the spinal cord. Surg Neurol 1981;16:235-7. <lb/>9. Braithwaite PA, Lees RF. Vertebral hydatid disease: Radiological <lb/>assessment. Radiology 1981;140:763-6. <lb/>10. Güneçs M, Akdemir H, Tuğcu B, Günaldi O, Gümüçs E, Akpinar A. <lb/>Multiple intradural spinal hydatid disease: A case report and review of <lb/>literature. Spine (Phila Pa 1976) 2009;34:E346-50. <lb/>11. Ndondo AP, Fieggen G, Wilmshurst JM. Hydatid disease of the spine <lb/>in South African children. J Child Neurol 2003;18:343-6. <lb/>12. Thaler M, Gabl M, Lechner R, Gstöttner M, Bach CM. Severe <lb/>kyphoscoliosis after primary Echinococcus granulosus infection of the <lb/>spine. Eur Spine J 2010;19:1415-22. <lb/>13. Singh N, Anand T, Singh DK. Imaging diagnosis and management of <lb/>primary spinal hydatid disease: A case series. Egypt J Radiol Nucl Med <lb/>2022;53:106. <lb/>14. Secer HI, Anik I, Celik E, Daneyemez MK, Gonul E. Spinal hydatid <lb/>cyst mimicking arachnoid cyst on magnetic resonance imaging. <lb/>J Spinal Cord Med 2008;31:106-8. <lb/>15. Prabhakar MM, Acharya AJ, Modi DR, Jadav B. Spinal hydatid <lb/>disease: A case series. J Spinal Cord Med 2005;28:426-31. <lb/>16. Caglar YS, Ozgural O, Zaimoglu M, Kilinc C, Eroglu U, Dogan I, <lb/>et al. Spinal hydatid cyst disease: Challenging surgery -An institutional <lb/>experience. J Korean Neurosurg Soc 2019;62:209-16. <lb/>17. Paksoy Y, Odev K, Sahin M, Arslan A, Koç O. Percutaneous treatment <lb/>of liver hydatid cysts: Comparison of direct injection of albendazole and <lb/>hypertonic saline solution. AJR Am J Roentgenol 2005;185:727-34. <lb/>18. Baykaner MK, Doğulu F, Oztürk G, Edali N, Tali T. A viable residual <lb/>spinal hydatid cyst cured with albendazole. Case report. J Neurosurg <lb/>2000;93:142-4. </listBibl>


	</text>

</TEI>