<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Evaluation of innovation efficiency of high-tech enterprise based on DEA and Malmquist index under the background of sustainable development</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Liwei</forename>
            <surname>Wang</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Tianbo</forename>
            <surname>Tang</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-28T11:07:53.187010Z">28.10.2025 11:07:53</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1108$1$apjie-10-2023-0190</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Emerald</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1108/apjie-10-2023-0190</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Liwei Wang, Tianbo Tang. (2024). Evaluation of innovation efficiency of high-tech enterprise based on DEA and Malmquist index under the background of sustainable development. Asia Pacific Journal of Innovation and Entrepreneurship, 18(4), 340-354. DOI: 10.1108/apjie-10-2023-0190</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-28T11:07:53.187010Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-28T11:07:53.187010Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
			<front>Exploring lean manufacturing <lb/>drivers for enhancing circular <lb/>economy performance in the <lb/>pharmaceutical industry: <lb/>a Bayesian best-worst approach <lb/>Sheak Salman, Shah Murtoza Morshed, Md. Rezaul Karim, <lb/>Rafat Rahman, Sadia Hasanat and Afia Ahsan <lb/>Department of Mechanical and Production Engineering, <lb/>Ahsanullah University of Science and Technology, Dhaka, Bangladesh <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Purpose -The imperative to conserve resources and minimize operational expenses has spurred a notable <lb/>increase in the adoption of lean manufacturing within the context of the circular economy across diverse <lb/>industries in recent years. However, a notable gap exists in the research landscape, particularly concerning the <lb/>implementation of lean practices within the pharmaceutical industry to enhance circular economy <lb/>performance. Addressing this void, this study endeavors to identify and prioritize the pivotal drivers <lb/>influencing lean manufacturing within the pharmaceutical sector. <lb/>Findings -The outcome of this rigorous examination highlights that &quot;Continuous Monitoring Process for <lb/>Sustainable Lean Implementation,&quot; &quot;Management Involvement for Sustainable Implementation&quot; and <lb/>&quot;Training and Education&quot; emerge as the most consequential drivers. These factors are deemed crucial for <lb/>augmenting circular economy performance, underscoring the significance of management engagement, <lb/>training initiatives and a continuous monitoring process in fostering a closed-loop practice within the <lb/>pharmaceutical industry. <lb/>Research limitations/implications -The findings contribute valuable insights for decision-makers aiming <lb/>to adopt lean practices within a circular economy framework. Specifically, by streamlining the process of <lb/>developing a robust action plan tailored to the unique needs of the pharmaceutical sector, our study provides <lb/>actionable guidance for enhancing overall sustainability in the manufacturing processes. <lb/>Originality/value -This study represents one of the initial efforts to systematically identify and assess the <lb/>drivers to LM implementation within the pharmaceutical industry, contributing to the emerging body of <lb/>knowledge in this area. <lb/>Keywords Drivers of lean manufacturing, Sustainable lean implementation, Best-worst method (BWM), <lb/>Pharmaceutical industry, Circular economy <lb/>Paper type Research paper <lb/>IJIEOM <lb/>7,1 <lb/>68 <lb/>© Sheak Salman, Shah Murtoza Morshed, Md. Rezaul Karim, Rafat Rahman, Sadia Hasanat and Afia <lb/>Ahsan. Published in International Journal of Industrial Engineering and Operations Management. <lb/>Published by Emerald Publishing Limited. This article is published under the Creative Commons <lb/>Attribution (CC BY 4.0) licence. Anyone may reproduce, distribute, translate and create derivative works <lb/>of this article (for both commercial and non-commercial purposes), subject to full attribution to the <lb/>original publication and authors. The full terms of this licence may be seen at http://creativecommons. <lb/>org/licences/by/4.0/legalcode <lb/>Funding acknowledgment: The research received no external funding. <lb/>Conflict of interest statement: No potential conflict of interest was reported by the author(s). <lb/>Data availability statement: Data used are available in this paper. <lb/>The current issue and full text archive of this journal is available on Emerald Insight at: <lb/>https://www.emerald.com/insight/2690-6090.htm <lb/>Received 3 October 2023 <lb/>Revised 31 December 2023 <lb/>Accepted 27 February 2024 <lb/>International Journal of Industrial <lb/>Engineering and Operations <lb/>Management <lb/>Vol. 7 No. 1, 2025 <lb/>pp. 68-96 <lb/>Emerald Publishing Limited <lb/>e-ISSN: 2690-6104 <lb/>p-ISSN: 2690-6090 <lb/>DOI 10.1108/IJIEOM-10-2023-0074 <lb/>Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>In the manufacturing sector, the term &quot;lean&quot; is a word which used to highlight the reduction of <lb/>waste and uncertainty in the production process through scientific management and the core <lb/>idea of lean manufacturing principles is to divide and enhance the manufacturing process (Du <lb/>et al., 2023). The development of manufacturing processes by Henry Ford and other <lb/>manufacturers at the end of the 19th and beginning of the 20th centuries is when the lean <lb/>notion first appeared (Dekier, 2012). In the last years, the concept of lean manufacturing has <lb/>gained immense popularity among the manufacturing industries worldwide. Lean <lb/>manufacturing is a concept focused on reducing waste and uncertainty in the production <lb/>process. It has gained popularity in the manufacturing sector worldwide. Lean <lb/>manufacturing aims to eliminate nonvalue-added items, enhance efficiency and simplify <lb/>processes. The seven categories of waste considered in lean manufacturing are <lb/>overprocessing, overproduction, high inventory, waiting time, unnecessary motion, defects <lb/>and unnecessary transportation. <lb/>In the pharmaceutical industry, the adoption of lean manufacturing principles has led to <lb/>improved product quality, cost reduction and increased productivity. However, <lb/>implementing lean in this industry can be challenging due to regulatory complexities and <lb/>the need for strict adherence to quality standards. Numerous investigations into the use of <lb/>lean principles in pharmaceutical manufacturing have revealed positive results to boost the <lb/>efficiency of their manufacturing process (Sharabati, 2023). One research by Bento and <lb/>Tontini (2019) focused on the implementation of lean principles in production system of small <lb/>and medium pharmaceutical enterprises. The authors include the unique features of small <lb/>and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) in this industry. They noted that the implementation of <lb/>lean principles in the pharmaceutical industry can be challenging due to the complex <lb/>regulatory environment, the need for strict adherence to quality standards, heavy equipment, <lb/>long processing time, etc. To the best of the authors&apos; knowledge, this research is the first to <lb/>evaluate a pharmaceutical firm using these markers both statistically and qualitatively <lb/>(Eskandari et al., 2022). <lb/>The adoption of lean manufacturing principles in the pharmaceutical industry has been <lb/>identified as a potential strategy for improving performance outcomes within a circular <lb/>economy framework (Liu et al., 2023). The circular economy (CE) offers a comprehensive <lb/>framework that promotes resource efficiency, waste reduction and closed-loop systems to <lb/>uncouple economic growth from resource consumption. A study by Arruda et al. (2021) <lb/>reviewed CE adaptation, divided the criteria into three perspectives such as energy and <lb/>material scarcity, environmental effects (solid waste, landfills, emissions or pollution) and <lb/>financial implications (such as cost savings and higher income) are all factors that affect the <lb/>availability of resources and described the industrial advantages. Also, research by Bag and <lb/>Pretorius (2022) stated lean manufacturing and the circular economy can work together to <lb/>create a positive feedback loop that benefits the environment and society at large, hence <lb/>supporting sustainable growth in the manufacturing sector. The circular economy <lb/>framework offers a comprehensive approach to resource efficiency and waste reduction. <lb/>Lean manufacturing practices have been found to positively impact circular economy <lb/>performance outcomes in the pharmaceutical industry. The circular economy prioritizes <lb/>resource reuse and recycling to achieve a more comprehensive sustainability goal. The <lb/>circular economy promotes maximizing the value of products, minimizing waste and <lb/>ensuring sustainability in the pharmaceutical supply chain. Incorporating the concept of <lb/>circular economy with lean manufacturing will help the pharmaceutical industries conserve <lb/>raw materials, machinery, environment, etc. while lessening the operational cost. <lb/>Implementing lean and circular economy practices in emerging economies presents unique <lb/>challenges such as limited resources and infrastructure. However, lean manufacturing can <lb/>help overcome these challenges and achieve long-term profitability. <lb/></body>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">Circular <lb/>economy <lb/>performance <lb/></note>

			<page>69 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>Bangladesh&apos;s pharmaceutical industry is flourishing, with 257 licensed factories, of which <lb/>150 are operational. Implementing the CE in this industry would bring benefits such as <lb/>reduced process time, by-product production and costs as well as ensuring a sustainable <lb/>supply chain (Shi, 2022). However, emerging economies face challenges in adopting CE <lb/>practices due to limited infrastructure, technology for waste management and lack of <lb/>awareness among the consumers and policymakers. Lean manufacturing can help overcome <lb/>these obstacles and achieve long-term profitability by improving efficiency and reducing <lb/>waste (Salman et al., 2023). This integration of lean principles with the circular economy can <lb/>play a crucial role in sustainable development. Lean manufacturing has the potential to have <lb/>a huge influence in emerging economies like Bangladesh, which has a bright future as an <lb/>emerging market (Salman et al., 2023). Due to the country&apos;s fast industrialization and <lb/>urbanization, it is currently experiencing serious environmental and economic problems. The <lb/>circular economy idea is gaining popularity in Bangladesh, according to research by Hussain <lb/>and Malik (2020) because of its capability to support sustainable development. But the <lb/>absence of proper technology and infrastructure for waste management and recycling is one <lb/>of the key challenges (Hussain and Malik, 2020). Bangladesh, as an emerging market, can <lb/>greatly benefit from the implementation of lean manufacturing. The country faces <lb/>environmental and economic issues due to rapid industrialization and urbanization. While <lb/>the circular economy idea is gaining popularity, the lack of waste management infrastructure <lb/>and awareness among the consumers and policymakers pose challenges. <lb/>The adoption of lean manufacturing in the Bangladeshi pharmaceutical industry can lead <lb/>to improved operational and financial performance. Productivity indicators such as reduced <lb/>lead times, lower customer complaint rates, increased units produced per labor hour and <lb/>improved equipment effectiveness can be achieved through lean practices. According to the <lb/>studies of Kamble et al. (2020), Karam et al. (2018), Nenni et al. (2014), use of the lean approach <lb/>is the only option for expanding the economy. <lb/>It provides a new method of measuring the integration of the circular economy with lean <lb/>practices. A few drivers of lean manufacturing such as extension of product life, innovative <lb/>business models, etc. are implemented to achieve the benefits of circular economy in <lb/>pharmaceutical industry. Moreover, the study focuses on examining the extent to which lean <lb/>manufacturing drivers are being implemented in Bangladesh&apos;s pharmaceutical business and <lb/>how the circular economy paradigm is being integrated. Examining the possible synergies <lb/>between lean manufacturing and circular economy concepts becomes imperative research, <lb/>especially in the pharmaceutical industry, where resource efficiency and environmental <lb/>issues are of utmost importance. The objective of this study is to investigate the factors that <lb/>facilitate the improvement of circular economy performance in the pharmaceutical sector by <lb/>utilizing lean manufacturing techniques. The ways to get the best performance outcomes, <lb/>following research questions (RQs) are developed, such as: <lb/>RQ1. What are the specific drivers within lean manufacturing that play a pivotal role in <lb/>improving circular economy performance in the pharmaceutical sector? <lb/>RQ2. How can a Bayesian best-worst approach be utilized to analyze and prioritize lean <lb/>manufacturing drivers with the aim of enhancing circular economy performance in <lb/>the pharmaceutical industry? <lb/>RQ3. Based on the Bayesian best-worst findings, what strategic pathways can be <lb/>identified and recommended for the effective implementation of lean <lb/>manufacturing drivers, fostering circular economy practices within the <lb/>pharmaceutical industry? <lb/>By measuring the integration of the circular economy with lean practices, this study provides <lb/>a new methodological approach and highlights the importance of incorporating circular <lb/></body>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">IJIEOM <lb/>7,1 <lb/></note>

			<page>70 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>economy principles in the pharmaceutical industry&apos;s operations. Aiming to answer the <lb/>research questions, the Bayesian best-worst method (BWM), an optimal barrier mitigation <lb/>route analysis tool, is used to identify the most effective path shapes for promoting lean <lb/>manufacturing. In this study, a multicriteria decision-making model was created to assess the <lb/>success of the circular economy in Bangladesh&apos;s pharmaceutical business. By visualizing and <lb/>simulating the system&apos;s rise to the top of the fitness landscape, the BWM method identifies <lb/>the optimum course of action for removing obstacles to lean implementation. The novelty of <lb/>this work lies in its focus on implementing lean manufacturing drivers in the pharmaceutical <lb/>industry of Bangladesh, which has not been previously explored. The study emphasizes the <lb/>need to incorporate the circular economy paradigm into various aspects of the <lb/>pharmaceutical industry operations, including logistics, procurement, design, production, <lb/>marketing and communication. By measuring the integration of the circular economy with <lb/>lean practices, the study introduces a new methodological approach. <lb/>The following is an outline of the article: Section 2 offers a comprehensive analysis of the <lb/>existing literature on lean manufacturing practices and driver of implementing LM in the <lb/>pharmaceutical sector in the circular economy context. Section 3 portrays the data collection <lb/>procedure and computational phase of the proposed BWM framework. The findings and the <lb/>validation of the study are shown in Section 4. Afterward a discussion of the implications of <lb/>the study, Section 5 highlights the practical implication of the study and the insights gained <lb/>from the investigation. Section 6 concludes the research work by discussing the findings and <lb/>opportunities for future exploration. <lb/>2. Literature review <lb/>2.1 Current scenario of lean manufacturing practices and circular economy <lb/>Lean manufacturing was invented in the 1950s by Toyota in Japan, and many businesses all <lb/>over the world have subsequently adopted it to boost their competitiveness. Numerous papers, <lb/>including research carried out in diverse areas, such as India, provide evidence of lean practices. <lb/>A considerable majority of businesses had incorporated various parts of lean manufacturing, <lb/>according to Patel and Patel (2022), investigation into the extent of lean adoption and its effect on <lb/>operational performance in Indian companies. Lean manufacturing was not commonly used in <lb/>Indian organizations to enhance operational or quality performance, according to research by <lb/>(Chugani et al., 2017). Lean practices are not widely used in all industries in Bangladesh. <lb/>However, research by Habib et al. (2023) in a packaging firm in Bangladesh showed that <lb/>applying lean manufacturing principles helped solve problems with regard to reducing lead <lb/>times. They suggested using lean practices in Bangladesh&apos;s packaging industry. For the ready-<lb/>made garments (RMG) industry in Bangladesh to successfully implement lean, Kumar et al. <lb/>(2022) emphasized the necessity for a comprehensive plan that includes a distinct vision, goals <lb/>and objectives. <lb/>Researchers in several areas have looked into the potential advantages of lean practices in <lb/>the particular sectors. Eskandari et al. (2022) looked into the possibility of giving Jordanian <lb/>pharmaceutical manufacturing firms a competitive edge on the international market. The <lb/>difficulties the Irish pharmaceutical industry had in implementing continuous improvement <lb/>techniques like Lean Six Sigma (LSS) were investigated by McDermott et al. (2022). To ensure <lb/>improved regulatory compliance, Jalundhwala and Londhe (2023) identified a number of <lb/>enablers for operational excellence in the pharmaceutical sector. Some evidence of lean practices <lb/>in different regions can be found in many publications such as (Garza-Reyes et al., 2012; Ghosh, <lb/>2013; Krishnan et al., 2022; Verma et al., 2022; Citybabu and Yamini, 2022; Hasan et al., 2022). <lb/>A systematic review by Lim et al. (2022) stated lean manufacturing and circular economy <lb/>combination can help to the transformation of companies in a positive way. Numerous factors <lb/>for achieving circular economy in the pharmaceutical industry while implementing lean <lb/></body>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">Circular <lb/>economy <lb/>performance <lb/></note>

			<page>71 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>manufacturing for sustainability is absolutely rudimentary. A significant determinant in the <lb/>restricted implementation of lean techniques is the manufacturers&apos; inadequate awareness <lb/>(Singh et al., 2021). Manufacturers are less likely to allocate resources towards the <lb/>technologies when they possess insufficient knowledge and comprehension of them. The <lb/>resulting decline in investment and interest may impede the progress of the multiple booming <lb/>sectors, such as the manufacturing and pharmaceutical industry (Naseemullah, 2022). <lb/>Nonetheless, considerable research has been conducted on the critical factors of lean <lb/>implementation (Osman et al., 2020; Ciliberto et al., 2021; Debnath et al., 2023a, b). Since a <lb/>dearth of material that deals, especially, with Bangladesh&apos;s deployment of lean <lb/>manufacturing in the pharmaceutical sector is existent, exploration in this field would help <lb/>Bangladeshi policymakers and business leaders to better understand the potential <lb/>advantages and difficulties of implementing lean practices in the pharmaceutical industry. <lb/>2.2 Drivers of implementing lean manufacturing in the pharmaceuticals industry to achieve <lb/>circular economy <lb/>The two popular terms that have received the most attention in the manufacturing sector in <lb/>recent years are Lean Manufacturing and Circular Economy (Shashi et al., 2021; Sawe et al., <lb/>2021; Ciliberto et al., 2021; Touriki et al., 2021; Khan and Haleem, 2021). Despite certain <lb/>similarities, they use different underlying concepts and approaches. Waste reduction and <lb/>operational performance have improved as a result of lean implementation (Habib et al., 2023; <lb/>Anwar et al., 2023; Afum et al., 2022). Through resource reuse and recycling, the circular <lb/>economy seeks to reduce waste and improve sustainability (Palange and Dhatrak, 2021). <lb/>According to Dey et al., 2020), integrating lean and circular economy practices can enhance <lb/>operational effectiveness and resource efficiency. <lb/>The pharmaceutical industry&apos;s goals for the circular economy can be achieved with the <lb/>use of lean manufacturing techniques (Kazakova and Lee, 2022). The pharmaceutical sector <lb/>can employ the many criteria listed in this section to accomplish its circular economy aims. <lb/>The pharmaceutical industry can gain a thorough understanding of the components <lb/>necessary for advancement in this discipline through lean integration (Januszek et al., 2023). <lb/>The drivers were found using the extensive literature review conducted for the study. To <lb/>identify the context and drivers that can implement lean manufacturing in the <lb/>pharmaceuticals industry to achieve circular economy, this study has reviewed prior <lb/>studies. The key terms that have been utilized while conducting the literature search are <lb/>&quot;Lean manufacturing in pharmaceuticals industry&quot; OR &quot;Lean implementation to enhance <lb/>circular economy performance&quot; OR &quot;Circular economy in pharmaceutical industry&quot; OR &quot;Lean <lb/>manufacturing effects on circular economy performance&quot; AND &quot;Lean manufacturing drivers&apos; <lb/>assessment for achieving circular economy&quot; OR &quot;Possible driver to implement lean in <lb/>pharmaceuticals industry&quot;. Google Scholar and the Scopus database were utilized for this <lb/>literature search between the years 2016 and 2023. The drivers are presented in Table 1. <lb/>2.2.1 Economical and organizational context. The drivers of the economic and <lb/>organizational setting, such as cost reduction (Nour and Laux, 2021; Nagaich, 2022) and <lb/>quality augmentation (Yadav et al., 2020), play a significant role in the implementation of lean. <lb/>Cost reduction and quality enhancement are the main goals of lean adoption in the <lb/>pharmaceutical sector (Nour and Laux, 2021; Nagaich, 2022). By reducing their negative <lb/>effects on the environment and making the best use of their resources, businesses can <lb/>improve their sustainability (Parmar and Desai, 2020). Implementing a strategic plan, being <lb/>committed to it, allocating resources and standardizing play big roles (Yadav et al., 2020). <lb/>2.2.2 Knowledge and learning context. Sharing of knowledge is essential for the adoption of <lb/>lean successfully (Rana and Kaushik, 2018). Effective strategies include encouraging the <lb/>exchange of best practices, offering chances for training and development and encouraging <lb/></body>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">IJIEOM <lb/>7,1 <lb/></note>

			<page>72 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>Context <lb/>Sl. Drivers <lb/>How does it affect pharmaceutical <lb/>industry <lb/>Sources <lb/>Economical and <lb/>organizational <lb/>1 Cost cutting <lb/>Pharmaceutical firms seek to optimize <lb/>resource utilization, remove waste and <lb/>streamline processes by implementing <lb/>lean concepts. This lean methodology <lb/>supports the larger goals of circular <lb/>economy performance in addition to <lb/>lowering costs <lb/>Nagaich (2022), Hariyani <lb/>and Mishra (2022b), Nour <lb/>and Laux (2021) <lb/>2 Shorter time to <lb/>market <lb/>Pharmaceutical firms can respond to <lb/>market demands more quickly by <lb/>streamlining their supply chain, <lb/>manufacturing and research and <lb/>development operations through the <lb/>adoption of lean concepts. By <lb/>encouraging resource efficiency, this <lb/>quicker time to market not only boosts <lb/>competitiveness but also adheres to the <lb/>circular economy&apos;s tenets <lb/>Nenni et al. (2014) <lb/>3 Adherence to <lb/>regulations <lb/>Lean methodologies, which prioritize <lb/>waste reduction strategies, energy-<lb/>efficient practices and raw material <lb/>optimization, align with the objectives <lb/>of the circular economy. This results <lb/>in a comprehensive and compliant <lb/>approach to pharmaceutical <lb/>manufacturing that strikes a balance <lb/>between regulatory requirements and <lb/>sustainable and circular practices <lb/>Sol ıs-Quinteros et al., <lb/>(2021), McKie et al., (2021) <lb/>4 Top management <lb/>commitment <lb/>Top executives&apos; dedication shapes <lb/>organizational culture and has an <lb/>impact on decision-making <lb/>procedures. Within the framework of <lb/>lean methodologies, it entails <lb/>cultivating an attitude that places <lb/>emphasis on productivity and <lb/>incorporate principles of the circular <lb/>economy into the manufacturing <lb/>cycle of pharmaceuticals <lb/>Hariyani and Mishra <lb/>(2022a, b), Parmar and <lb/>Desai (2020), Elkhairi et al. <lb/>(2019) <lb/>5 Quality <lb/>augmentation <lb/>Pharmaceutical firms may secure the <lb/>manufacturing of high-quality <lb/>medicines, streamline processes and <lb/>eliminate defects by implementing lean <lb/>principles. In addition to meeting legal <lb/>requirements, this dedication to quality <lb/>advances resource efficiency, a <lb/>cornerstone of the circular economy&apos;s <lb/>tenets <lb/>Yadav et al. (2020) <lb/>6 Standardization <lb/>Pharmaceutical businesses may more <lb/>efficiently pinpoint areas for <lb/>improvement because of standardized <lb/>processes, which reduces <lb/>environmental impact and promotes <lb/>continual process optimization. The <lb/>pharmaceutical sector may actively <lb/>support a more circular and <lb/>sustainable approach by incorporating <lb/>lean-driven standardization <lb/>Yadav et al. (2020) <lb/>(continued ) <lb/>Table 1. <lb/>Drivers for <lb/>implementing lean <lb/>manufacturing in the <lb/>pharmaceutical <lb/>industry to enhance <lb/>circular economy <lb/>performance outcomes <lb/></body>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">Circular <lb/>economy <lb/>performance <lb/></note>

			<page>73 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>Context <lb/>Sl. Drivers <lb/>How does it affect pharmaceutical <lb/>industry <lb/>Sources <lb/>7 Innovative business <lb/>models <lb/>Pharmaceutical firms should <lb/>reconsider established procedures <lb/>and integrate lean concepts, which <lb/>prioritize efficiency and waste <lb/>reduction, by adopting innovative <lb/>and creative methods to business. <lb/>A creative business plan can inspire <lb/>the creation of fresh approaches that <lb/>support the objectives of the circular <lb/>economy, such maximizing resource <lb/>utilization and reducing <lb/>environmental effect <lb/>Aloini et al. (2020), Pieroni <lb/>et al. (2019) <lb/>8 Systems with closed <lb/>loops <lb/>Lean principles encourage the <lb/>development of goods and procedures <lb/>that permit material reuse, recycling <lb/>and remanufacturing. This strategy <lb/>makes it easier to develop closed-loop <lb/>systems where resources are <lb/>continually reused, lowering the need <lb/>for virgin materials and fostering a <lb/>more circular and sustainable <lb/>economy <lb/>Achillas and Bochtis <lb/>(2020), Sosnowski and <lb/>Cyplik (2022) <lb/>Knowledge and <lb/>learning <lb/>1 Ongoing <lb/>development <lb/>Lean approaches offer an organized <lb/>framework for continuous <lb/>improvement, encouraging a flexible <lb/>and creative culture. Pharmaceutical <lb/>firms can find opportunities to reduce <lb/>waste, maximize resource utilization <lb/>and improve overall efficiency by <lb/>routinely evaluating and improving <lb/>their operations. The objectives of the <lb/>circular economy are easily aligned <lb/>with this iterative method <lb/>Parmar and Desai (2020), <lb/>Yadav et al. (2020) <lb/>2 Employee <lb/>involvement <lb/>Employee involvement promotes a <lb/>continuous improvement culture and <lb/>gives staff members the ability to <lb/>offer creative solutions for reducing <lb/>resource inefficiencies and optimizing <lb/>procedures. By encouraging <lb/>responsible resource usage and waste <lb/>reduction, this cooperative method <lb/>not only improves the efficiency of <lb/>operations but also adheres to the <lb/>circular economy&apos;s tenets <lb/>Parmar and Desai (2020), <lb/>Osman et al. (2020), Yadav <lb/>et al. (2020) <lb/>3 Training and <lb/>education <lb/>Through the provision of specialized <lb/>expertise and abilities to their <lb/>workforce, pharmaceutical <lb/>businesses may cultivate a lean <lb/>culture and improve their <lb/>performance in the circular economy. <lb/>Employees can be empowered by <lb/>training programs to recognize and <lb/>reduce inefficiencies in production <lb/>processes <lb/>Parmar and Desai (2020), <lb/>Elkhairi et al. (2019) <lb/>Table 1. <lb/>(continued ) <lb/></body>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">IJIEOM <lb/>7,1 <lb/></note>

			<page>74 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>Context <lb/>Sl. Drivers <lb/>How does it affect pharmaceutical <lb/>industry <lb/>Sources <lb/>4 Customer <lb/>contentment <lb/>Pharmaceutical firms can meet <lb/>consumer requests with promptness <lb/>and consistency by implementing <lb/>lean techniques that enhance <lb/>efficiency and reliability. <lb/>Furthermore, there is a growing <lb/>correlation between environmental <lb/>responsibility and customer pleasure <lb/>as society places a higher priority on <lb/>sustainability. Putting circular <lb/>economy principles into practice <lb/>Hariyani and Mishra <lb/>(2022a), Goshime et al. <lb/>(2019) <lb/>5 Collaboration and <lb/>communication <lb/>Good channels of communication <lb/>make it easier to share knowledge and <lb/>best practices, which makes it <lb/>possible to incorporate the concepts of <lb/>the circular economy with ease. <lb/>A harmonious environment for <lb/>adopting lean approaches is created <lb/>when varied stakeholders have <lb/>effective communication and share a <lb/>common understanding <lb/>Osman et al. (2020), <lb/>Elkhairi et al. (2019) <lb/>6 Demand from <lb/>consumers and <lb/>awareness <lb/>Lean can be used to increase consumer <lb/>demand and knowledge of the circular <lb/>economy by highlighting the worth and <lb/>advantages of sustainable practices and <lb/>products. Lean also makes it possible <lb/>for visible supply chains and <lb/>unambiguous labeling, giving <lb/>customers the freedom to make <lb/>educated decisions and advancing the <lb/>circular economy by their buying <lb/>actions <lb/>Hunka et al. (2021), Aloini <lb/>et al. (2020) <lb/>Technological and <lb/>resource <lb/>management <lb/>1 Operational <lb/>efficiency <lb/>Pharmacies may save money, increase <lb/>productivity and guarantee a more <lb/>sustainable use of supplies by reducing <lb/>waste and enhancing overall <lb/>operational efficacy. Lean approaches <lb/>emphasize material reduction, reuse <lb/>and recycling, which supports the <lb/>circular economy and increases <lb/>resource efficiency <lb/>Panigrahi et al. (2023), <lb/>Salonitis and Tsinopoulos <lb/>(2016) <lb/>2 Resource <lb/>optimization <lb/>Just-in-time manufacturing and <lb/>ongoing improvement are two lean <lb/>concepts that help to optimize <lb/>production processes, cut down on <lb/>extra inventory and use less energy. <lb/>By encouraging sustainable resource <lb/>management, this not only improves <lb/>operational efficiency but also <lb/>adheres to the fundamental principles <lb/>of the circular economy <lb/>Salonitis and Tsinopoulos <lb/>(2016) <lb/>(continued ) <lb/>Table 1. <lb/></body>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">Circular <lb/>economy <lb/>performance <lb/></note>

			<page>75 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>Context <lb/>Sl. Drivers <lb/>How does it affect pharmaceutical <lb/>industry <lb/>Sources <lb/>3 Capacity utilization By reducing material and energy <lb/>waste, efficient capacity utilization <lb/>fosters sustainability in the sector. <lb/>Furthermore, the pharmaceutical <lb/>industry is prioritizing environmental <lb/>responsibility more and more; <lb/>therefore, integrating lean principles <lb/>is essential to meeting both ecological <lb/>and circular economy objectives <lb/>Laskowski (2017), Nenni <lb/>et al. (2014) <lb/>4 Process mapping <lb/>One of the most important parts of <lb/>lean techniques is process mapping, <lb/>which helps companies optimize their <lb/>workflows, cut waste and boost <lb/>productivity. Creating a map of the <lb/>manufacturing process makes it <lb/>possible to identify areas where <lb/>sustainable practices, including <lb/>recycling and material reuse, can be <lb/>implemented to support the circular <lb/>economy <lb/>Abusaq et al. (2023), <lb/>Proença et al. (2022), <lb/>Pereira et al. (2019) <lb/>5 Continuous <lb/>monitoring process <lb/>Continuous monitoring process <lb/>distinguished by its capacity to track <lb/>and evaluate in real time, which <lb/>makes it easier to take a complete and <lb/>adaptive approach to managing <lb/>resources and sustainability. It makes <lb/>sure that resource optimization <lb/>measures in the pharmaceutical <lb/>industry, where accuracy and <lb/>compliance are crucial, are in line with <lb/>the circular economy principles <lb/>Swarnakar et al. (2020) <lb/>6 Sustainable supplier <lb/>selection <lb/>Materials from sustainable providers <lb/>frequently have a smaller <lb/>environmental impact. An essential <lb/>component of the circular economy is <lb/>resource efficiency, which is <lb/>enhanced by using these materials <lb/>into lean manufacturing techniques <lb/>Debnath et al. (2023a) <lb/>7 Digitalization <lb/>Lean can help digitalize the circular <lb/>economy by including IoT devices, <lb/>data analytics and automation which <lb/>utilize data and technology to <lb/>streamline processes, boost <lb/>productivity and facilitate better <lb/>resource management. Lean <lb/>principles promote the use of digital <lb/>tools in order to track material flows, <lb/>streamline operations and find areas <lb/>for improvement <lb/>Zu Castell-R€ udenhausen <lb/>et al. (2021), Hedberg and <lb/>Sipka (2021) <lb/>8 Extension of product <lb/>life <lb/>Lean can be used to extend product <lb/>life in the circular economy by putting <lb/>in place tactics that maximize product <lb/>use, maintenance and repair. <lb/>Producers can increase the lifespan of <lb/>their products through remodeling, <lb/>remanufacturing and repair by <lb/>implementing lean practices <lb/>Fontana et al. (2021), <lb/>Milios (2021) <lb/>Source(s): Authors&apos; own contribution <lb/>Table 1. <lb/></body>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">IJIEOM <lb/>7,1 <lb/></note>

			<page>76 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>cross-functional cooperation (Rana and Kaushik, 2018). According to Elkhairi et al. (2019), <lb/>training and education are essential success elements. Employee engagement and <lb/>communication are crucial (Osman et al., 2020). The goal is to foster learning environments <lb/>and invest in training programs. <lb/>2.2.3 Technological and resource management context. For the pharmaceutical business to <lb/>implement lean and the circular economy, effective management of technological resources is <lb/>essential (Laskowski, 2017). Considerations like capacity utilization and operational strategy <lb/>are crucial (Laskowski, 2017). Process mapping enables remedial measures by identifying <lb/>waste, inefficiency and quality issues (Habib et al. , 2023b). Continuous monitoring makes it <lb/>easier to discover waste in real time and improves the performance of the supply chain <lb/>(Swarnakar et al., 2020). <lb/>Organizations should concentrate on organizational and economic issues, encourage <lb/>knowledge exchange and learning and effectively use technical resources if they want to <lb/>successfully adopt lean manufacturing and develop a circular economy in the pharmaceutical <lb/>sector. <lb/>2.3 Existing methods and rationale behind this study <lb/>Numerous lean development strategies have been discovered in previous studies. Several <lb/>academic papers have included an implementation framework diagram. Using a framework, <lb/>Sieckmann et al. (2018) highlighted the aspects that make lean successful as well as its <lb/>obstacles and suggests a method for implementing lean production system that takes into <lb/>consideration the special characteristics of small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) in the <lb/>pharmaceutical sector. Other works have described the lean adoption framework specifically <lb/>for SMEs and not only the frameworks but also the difficulties they encountered (Almanei <lb/>et al., 2017). Although there are many authors who researched lean for all category industry. <lb/>Among them one is Karam et al. (2018) who adopted the lean manufacturing philosophy in a <lb/>Romanian pharmaceutical business. Nagaich (2022) examined the pharmaceutical industry&apos;s <lb/>use of lean methodologies, removal of waste and elimination of nonvalue-added activities. <lb/>Roadmaps have been utilized in other studies for the lean transformation. Seleem et al. (2020) <lb/>developed a path for lean manufacturing for industrial businesses based on the limits of the <lb/>company and the predetermined strategic goals. A positive feedback is presented by <lb/>Cekerevac et al. (2022) where it is shown that lean production affirmatively added value to the <lb/>companies in the post-COVID-19 period with some examples as evidence. Obstacles and <lb/>enablers of circular supply chain management were highlighted by Khan and Ali (2022), <lb/>while Patwa et al. (2021) investigated the implementation of circular economy in emerging <lb/>economies. Research on the dynamic evolution of the industrial circular economy has been <lb/>conducted (Ding et al., 2020). However, there is a gap in examining the adoption of lean <lb/>manufacturing to enhance circular economy performance outcomes in the pharmaceutical <lb/>industry, which our study addresses using the Bayesian BWM. <lb/>The current methods for studying lean implementation drivers in THE pharmaceutical <lb/>industry includes a fuzzy decision-making and evaluation laboratory (DEMATEL) approach <lb/>is used by Parmar and Desai (2020), to identify the enablers of sustainable lean six sigma in <lb/>the manufacturing organization by evaluating the cause and effect enablers. A multi-level <lb/>approach was taken by Schmitt et al. (2021) to recognize the potentials of lean from circular <lb/>perspective. Similar study was found where the author Jaiswal et al. (2021) used a gray <lb/>DEMATEL technique to recognize barriers of lean. An ontological approach was adopted by <lb/>Morseletto (2023) to outline the factors that influence whether an economy is linear or circular. <lb/>Some authors Nagaich (2022) used statistical analysis by SPSS and the drivers and barriers of <lb/>lean manufacturing. As there is no thorough investigation on the drivers of lean <lb/>manufacturing in the pharmaceuticals industry to enhance circular economy performance <lb/></body>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">Circular <lb/>economy <lb/>performance <lb/></note>

			<page>77 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>outcome using the Bayesian BWM method, this study will contribute in this area and will <lb/>provide a guiding about the implications of this study for successfully adopting and <lb/>implementing lean manufacturing in the setting analyzed and assisting decision-makers and <lb/>industry leaders in making strategic and tactical choices on the managerial level. A study by <lb/>Santos et al. (2023) used the graph theory to find the leanness of automotive industry supply <lb/>chain management. However, significant absence of Bayesian BWM for analyzing <lb/>sustainability in the circular economy context clearly depicts the unexplored opportunities <lb/>of study in this field. Comparing sustainability in a circular economy to the contemporary <lb/>methods such as the graph theory or probabilistic graph theory, Bayesian BWM exhibits <lb/>superior performance due to its incorporation of the decision-maker&apos;s preferences and <lb/>subjective evaluations of alternative performance and criterion weights (Ferdoush et al., <lb/>2024). By doing so, the Bayesian BWM offers a more comprehensive analysis that duly <lb/>acknowledges the intrinsic uncertainty associated with the circular economy framework <lb/>(Ferdoush et al., 2024). Since they might not overtly consider subjective assessments or <lb/>uncertainty, by enabling decision-makers to integrate prior information into the analysis and <lb/>update their opinions in light of observed data, the Bayesian framework facilitates the <lb/>formulation of more precise and robust decisions (Ruberg et al., 2023). <lb/>3. Methodological framework <lb/>This study evaluated the key drivers for implementing lean manufacturing using the <lb/>Bayesian BWM framework. The data collection process included three distinct stages of <lb/>gathering feedback from experts. During the first stage, a survey questionnaire was emailed <lb/>to 26 experts using Google Forms with the goal of validating, refining and grouping the <lb/>identified key drivers for subsequent analysis. A total of 19 experts replied, yielding a <lb/>response rate of 73.07%. The purposive sampling method, also known as judgmental or <lb/>selective sampling, was used in this study. It is a nonprobability sampling technique and <lb/>unlike the random sampling methods, purposive sampling involves the deliberate selection of <lb/>participants based on the specific criteria or characteristics relevant to the research objectives <lb/>(Palit et al., 2022; Ali et al., 2022). The chosen participants had direct involvement and active <lb/>engagement within the pharmaceutical industry. The experts were selected based on the <lb/>criteria of possessing in-depth knowledge of lean manufacturing, circular economy practices, <lb/>the pharmaceutical industry, supply chain management, sustainability and a minimum <lb/>experience of seven years in the relevant sector. For this study, professionals from well-<lb/>known companies and organizations were chosen using purposeful sampling. By ensuring a <lb/>wide pool of responders, this technique reduces the possibility of biases and offers a well-<lb/>rounded portrayal of opinions. The selection of experts was based on a range of factors, such <lb/>as professional experience, academic background, expertise in lean and industry <lb/>management and participation in sustainable projects as well as a diversity of opinions <lb/>and pharmaceutical production experiences. A summary of the experts&apos; profiles who <lb/>participated in the study has been provided in (Table S1, see supplementary material). <lb/>Following that, the experts were then asked to complete a BWM survey form to develop <lb/>the &quot;Best to Others&quot; and &quot;Others to Worst&quot; matrices. In the following stage, a BWM survey <lb/>form was created and given to the experts to produce the &quot;Best to Others&quot; and &quot;Others to <lb/>Worst&quot; matrices. About 19 experts who were in the initial group were asked to participate in <lb/>the Bayesian BWM study again. Out of the invited experts, 15 responded, resulting in a <lb/>response rate of 78%. Subsequently, the data obtained through the survey were utilized to <lb/>apply the Bayesian BWM method, enabling the estimation of the final weights of the <lb/>identified drivers along with the credal ranking. The results were then shared with the 15 <lb/>experts who took part in the second stage. A 100% response rate was achieved since all of the <lb/>requested experts responded. Our study is designed to recognize personal decision-making <lb/></body>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">IJIEOM <lb/>7,1 <lb/></note>

			<page>78 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>trends. For this reason, the number of respondents included in this study is adequate to <lb/>capture a variety of viewpoints. The framework of this research methodology is illustrated in <lb/>Figure 1. Following the identification of the drivers, the experts guided the grouping of these <lb/>drivers into three primary clusters: economical and organizational, knowledge and learning <lb/>and technological and resource management. Table 1 summarizes the three key clusters and <lb/>their respective drivers. <lb/>3.1 Bayesian best-worst method (BWM) <lb/>Rezaei (2015) introduced the BWM as a reliable multicriteria decision-making (MCDM) <lb/>technique for pairwise comparisons. The Bayesian BWM is an improved version designed <lb/>for group decision-making, providing accurate rankings with fewer data requirements <lb/>(Debnath. et al., 2023a, b). Compared to other approaches like the analytic hierarchy <lb/>process (AHP), the BWM is simpler and more consistent (Liang et al., 2020). In group <lb/>decision-making, the Bayesian BWM integrates preferences effectively by determining <lb/>aggregate final weights for multiple decision-makers (Mohammadi and Rezaei, 2020). It <lb/>considers the group decision from a probabilistic perspective, ensuring comprehensive <lb/>and unbiased analysis (Yanilmaz et al., 2021). <lb/>The following present the major steps of the Bayesian BWM adopted from Debnath et al. <lb/>(2023a, b): <lb/>Step 1: Identifying the best and worst criterion <lb/>Step 2: Constructing the pairwise comparison of best to others <lb/>Step 3: Constructing a pairwise comparison of others to worst <lb/>Step 4: Calculation of aggregated weight <lb/>The details of the above-mentioned method are presented in the supplementary file (see <lb/>section 3.1 in supplementary file). <lb/>Figure 1. <lb/>Framework of research <lb/>methodology <lb/></body>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">Circular <lb/>economy <lb/>performance <lb/></note>

			<page>79 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>4. Analysis and results <lb/>4.1 Result analysis of the study <lb/>This section displays the drivers&apos; established rankings as determined by the Bayesian BWM. <lb/>For each cluster, the authors have established a weighted directed graph. <lb/>Figure 2 shows the credal ranking of the three clusters. The most significant of the three <lb/>clusters was technological and resource management (0.376), which was followed by <lb/>economic and organizational (0.359) and knowledge and learning (0.263). The technological <lb/>and resource management cluster&apos;s drivers require special attention from managers since <lb/>they are more important than those of the other clusters. However, the economic and <lb/>organizational clusters are close to the technological and resource management cluster in <lb/>terms of weight, which suggests that in order to successfully apply lean practices in <lb/>pharmaceutical supply chain, managers and policymakers must pay attention to both <lb/>clusters. Furthermore, it was discovered that the technological and resource management <lb/>cluster had more implementation than the economical and organizational cluster (0.97 <lb/>confidence-level) and the knowledge and learning cluster (0.6 confidence-level). Once more, <lb/>with 0.95 confidence-level, the economical and organizational clusters were more widely used <lb/>than knowledge and learning. Although it relies on the expert&apos;s perspective, a 0.55 threshold <lb/>has been used in this study to denote substantial confidence in the assessment of the <lb/>confidence values. On the routes of Figure 2 are the determined statistical probability <lb/>confidence scores. Figure 3 displays the local ranking of the drivers in the technological and <lb/>resource management cluster. <lb/>The most important driver is continuous monitoring process for sustainable lean <lb/>implementation (0.263), which is followed by capacity utilization (0.194), resource optimization <lb/>(0.159), operational efficiency (0.148), sustainable supplier selection (0.124) and digitalization <lb/>(0.115), respectively. The continuous monitoring process for sustainable lean implementation <lb/>counted significantly higher than other drivers among those in the technological and resource <lb/>management cluster. Figure 3 uses colored links to illustrate the network between the cluster&apos;s <lb/>drivers in the areas of technology and resource management. Figure 4 shows the relative <lb/>importance of several economic and organizational factors in a given area. <lb/>The most significant drivers are management involvement for sustainable <lb/>implementation (0.209), followed by cost cutting (0.207), standardization (0.167), adherence <lb/>to regulations (0.142), shorter time to market (0.141) and quality augmentation (0.136) in that <lb/>order. Management involvement for sustainable implementation measured greater <lb/>importance than other drivers within the economic and organizational cluster&apos;s drivers. In <lb/>Figure 4, we see how the factors that make up the economical and organizational cluster are <lb/>related to one another through a color-coded network. The knowledge and learning cluster&apos;s <lb/>local ranking of influential factors is shown in Figure 5. <lb/>Figure 2. <lb/>Illustration of ranking <lb/>of major clusters <lb/></body>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">IJIEOM <lb/>7,1 <lb/></note>

			<page>80 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>The three most significant drivers among the cluster&apos;s six drivers are the continuous <lb/>monitoring process for sustainable lean implementation (0.262), capacity utilization (0.193) <lb/>and resource optimization (0.158). In comparison to all other drivers in this cluster, the <lb/>continuous monitoring process for sustained lean implementation is determined to be much <lb/>more influential (with a threshold of 0.55). To determine the relative importance of each of the <lb/>22 drivers, we multiplied their weights at the cluster level by their weights at the local-level. <lb/>Figure 6 shows the drivers&apos; overall standings across the globe. Continuous monitoring <lb/>process for sustainable lean implementation (0.99) is the most significant driver, according to <lb/>the study, whereas demand from consumers and awareness is the least significant driver <lb/>(0.031). In addition, the confidence score matrices for all clusters have been presented in <lb/>Table S2-S5 (see supplementary material). <lb/>Figure 3. <lb/>Ranking of the <lb/>technological and <lb/>resource management-<lb/>related drivers <lb/>Figure 4. <lb/>Ranking of the <lb/>economical and <lb/>organizational-related <lb/>drivers <lb/></body>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">Circular <lb/>economy <lb/>performance <lb/></note>

			<page>81 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>It can be concluded that, technology and resource management is the most significant driver <lb/>among the other ones as one of the main components of the lean methods is careful resource <lb/>management, which guarantees that raw resources are used wisely, and waste is reduced <lb/>throughout the whole manufacturing process. This coherence with the goals of the circular <lb/>economy is essential because it encourages the conservation, reuse and recycling of resources in <lb/>a closed-loop system. Thus, the key to promoting sustainability in the pharmaceutical business <lb/>and moving it in the direction of a more ecologically conscious and circular future is the mutually <lb/>beneficial interaction between lean implementation, technology and resource management. <lb/>4.2 Validation of the result <lb/>In this crucial part of the study, the pharmaceutical sector&apos;s identified drivers for sustainable <lb/>lean manufacturing were thoroughly tested through an organized interaction with the <lb/>0.029 <lb/>0.032 <lb/>0.032 <lb/>0.035 <lb/>0.036 <lb/>0.039 <lb/>0.040 <lb/>0.043 <lb/>0.047 <lb/>0.049 <lb/>0.049 <lb/>0.051 <lb/>0.051 <lb/>0.056 <lb/>0.060 <lb/>0.060 <lb/>0.060 <lb/>0.072739956 <lb/>0.074127934 <lb/>0.074972045 <lb/>0.075119212 <lb/>0.098729414 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>0.020 <lb/>0.040 <lb/>0.060 <lb/>0.080 <lb/>0.100 <lb/>0.120 <lb/>K6:Demand from consumers and Awareness <lb/>E8:System with Closed Loop <lb/>T8:Extension of Product Life <lb/>E7:Innovative Business Model <lb/>T7:Digitalization <lb/>K1:Ongoing development <lb/>K4:Customer contentment <lb/>T4:Process mapping <lb/>T6:Sustainable supplier selection <lb/>E5:Quality augmentation <lb/>K5:Collaboration and Communication <lb/>E2:Shorter time to market <lb/>E3:Adherence to Regulations <lb/>T1:Operational efficiency <lb/>T2:Resource optimization <lb/>E6:Standardization <lb/>K2:Employee involvement <lb/>T3:Capacity utilization <lb/>E1:Cost cutting <lb/>K3:Training and Education <lb/>E4:Management involvement for sustainable implementation <lb/>T5:Continuous monitoring Process for sustainable lean implementation <lb/>Source(s): Authors&apos; own contribution <lb/>Figure 5. <lb/>Ranking of the <lb/>knowledge and <lb/>learning-related <lb/>drivers <lb/>Figure 6. <lb/>Global ranking of the <lb/>drivers related to lean <lb/>implementation in <lb/>pharmaceutical <lb/>industry <lb/></body>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">IJIEOM <lb/>7,1 <lb/></note>

			<page>82 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>industry experts. The research, which employed a three-phase methodology, featured a <lb/>targeted group of 15 seasoned professionals, all of whom had an extensive understanding of <lb/>lean procedures and at least seven years of experience in the pharmaceutical manufacturing <lb/>industry. The specialists were carefully chosen according to their broad experience, current <lb/>positions in the pharmaceutical industry and knowledge of lean manufacturing concepts. <lb/>This criterion guaranteed the relevance and insightfulness of the comments and insights <lb/>received. Following the conversations, all the participants agreed on the significance and <lb/>applicability of these factors, confirming the initial research findings. In the subsequent <lb/>phase, the focus shifted to categorizing these drivers within the framework of a circular <lb/>economy. In order to ensure a complete grasp of each driver&apos;s functions and <lb/>interrelationships, the participants examined how each fit into the larger objective of <lb/>sustainability and resource conservation. Lastly, the study showed the experts an organized <lb/>model that prioritized the drivers according to their significance and influence by utilizing the <lb/>Bayesian BWM. The participants gave this model a critical evaluation, confirming the <lb/>ranking order and providing suggestions for improving the priority for the pharmaceutical <lb/>industry&apos;s real-world application. During these stages, the interaction with professionals in <lb/>the field not only confirmed the study&apos;s conclusions but also added useful insights. The <lb/>suggested drivers for sustained lean adoption in the pharmaceutical business were shown to <lb/>be both theoretically sound and practically feasible through a multifaceted validation <lb/>procedure. This study&apos;s conclusion opens the door for the pharmaceutical sector decision-<lb/>makers to successfully apply lean approaches within a framework of the circular economy, <lb/>promoting a more resource-efficient, economical and sustainable production environment. <lb/>5. Discussion and implications of the study <lb/>5.1 Discussion of the findings <lb/>According to the findings of the Bayesian BWM framework developed in this study, several <lb/>key drivers for implementing lean manufacturing in the pharmaceutical industry to enhance <lb/>circular economy performance outcomes have been identified. <lb/>The &quot;Continuous Monitoring Process for Sustainable Lean Implementation (T5)&quot; is the <lb/>first and most significant driver. This driver places a strong emphasis on the value of <lb/>routinely evaluating how operations are progressing, creating clear goals and targets, <lb/>monitoring results and measuring and analyzing the application of lean manufacturing and <lb/>sustainability efforts. Organizations can remove waste, maximize resource usage and <lb/>gradually increase operational efficiency thanks to continuous monitoring. Key performance <lb/>indicators (KPIs) can help organizations prevent setbacks and work towards continual <lb/>improvement (Henrique et al., 2021). &quot;Management involvement for sustainable <lb/>implementation (E4)&quot; is the second important factor. Leading the sustainable adoption of <lb/>lean manufacturing practices is essential for success. Their participation is crucial for <lb/>integrating sustainability and circular economy principles into the organization&apos;s strategic <lb/>objectives. They support a culture of environmental stewardship and continual <lb/>improvement, offer the resources required and show the organization&apos;s dedication to <lb/>sustainable development. Gaining employee buy-in and guaranteeing the success of lean <lb/>implementation initiatives depend heavily on top management&apos;s active involvement and <lb/>support. Sieckmann et al. (2018) also showed from the existing literature that a lack of <lb/>commitment from management poses a substantial barrier to the implementation of a lean <lb/>production system, particularly in the small and medium-sized pharmaceutical industries. <lb/>The &quot;Training and Education (K3)&quot; driver is the third one. A skilled workforce must be <lb/>created in order to adopt lean manufacturing successfully. Organizations equip workers with <lb/>the knowledge and abilities they need to spot waste, streamline operations and adopt <lb/>sustainable practices. Lean principles, circular economy ideas, waste minimization strategies <lb/></body>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">Circular <lb/>economy <lb/>performance <lb/></note>

			<page>83 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>and sustainable manufacturing methods can all be covered in training programs to help <lb/>employees contribute to improving organizational performance. <lb/>&quot;Cost cutting (E1)&quot; is the fourth driving force. By reducing waste, boosting efficiency, and <lb/>maximizing resource utilization, businesses can cut costs while improving their performance <lb/>in the circular economy. Inefficient processes, excess inventory, and waste disposal costs can <lb/>all be reduced by using lean concepts to help identify and eliminate non-value-added <lb/>operations. Organizations can increase financial sustainability and support the circular <lb/>economy by putting cost-cutting initiatives into place. Lean principles assist in identifying <lb/>and eliminating non-value-added operations, which lowers expenses associated with excess <lb/>inventory, waste disposal, and inefficient processes (Chahal and Narwal, 2017). <lb/>&quot;Capacity utilization (T3)&quot; is the fifth driver. Utilizing capacity effectively is essential for <lb/>effectively satisfying market demand. Organizations can maximize capacity utilization with the <lb/>aid of lean manufacturing techniques including just-in-time production, balanced production <lb/>flow, and efficient inventory management. Organizations can improve operational efficiency <lb/>and support the circular economy by making efficient use of resources and coordinating output <lb/>with market demands (Mankazana and Mukwakungu, 2018). <lb/>The &quot;Employee Involvement (K2)&quot; driver is the sixth driver. Success depends on including <lb/>workers in circular economy and lean manufacturing initiatives. Employees have important <lb/>knowledge about waste production and operational inefficiencies. Organizations can tap into <lb/>employees&apos; knowledge and ideas by developing a culture of continuous improvement and <lb/>involving them in problem-solving, decision-making, and improvement projects, greatly <lb/>enhancing the effectiveness of lean implementation and the circular economy. <lb/>The &quot;Standardization (E6)&quot; driver is the seventh driver. Promoting efficiency and <lb/>reducing errors within the organization requires the establishment of standardized <lb/>procedures and standards. Process variation may result in longer wait times, bottlenecks <lb/>and extra time for material handling (Debnath et al., 2023a, b). Lean manufacturing strives to <lb/>eliminate process variances and waste, and this is made possible through standardized work <lb/>procedures, practices and instructions. Standardization boosts the performance of the <lb/>circular economy, encourages sustainable practices and improves operational efficiency <lb/>(Thanki et al., 2016). <lb/>The &quot;Resource Optimization (T2)&quot; driver is the eighth driver. In the pharmaceutical sector, <lb/>resource optimization is a key factor in improving the performance of the circular economy. <lb/>The pharmaceutical industry is becoming more and more aware of the significance of <lb/>effective resource management in an era where sustainability is a major priority in order to <lb/>minimize environmental damage and maximize economic rewards (Dossou et al., 2022). The <lb/>sector needs to strategically move toward circular economy concepts because of its reliance <lb/>on a variety of raw materials, energy-consuming processes and complex supply chains. <lb/>Pharmaceutical firms may minimize waste generation and their environmental impact by <lb/>optimizing their use of resources, including raw materials, water as well as energy (Aithal and <lb/>Aithal, 2023). <lb/>The remaining factors are &quot;Operational Efficiency (T1),&quot; which aims to increase process <lb/>efficiency, &quot;Adherence to Regulations (E3),&quot; which ensures compliance with legal <lb/>requirements, &quot;Shorter Time to Market (E2),&quot; to remain competitive, &quot;Collaboration and <lb/>Communication (K5),&quot; which fosters collaboration and knowledge sharing, &quot;Quality <lb/>Augmentation (E5),&quot; which emphasizes product quality and &quot;Sustainable Supplier <lb/>Selection (T6)&quot; selecting sustainable-minded vendors. It is crucial to remember that all <lb/>drivers contribute to the implementation of lean manufacturing and raising the performance <lb/>outcomes of the circular economy, even though certain drivers are more significant than <lb/>others. The drivers&apos; relative importance in the context of this study is shown by the ranking. <lb/>There have been a few studies on lean practice to improve circular economy performance <lb/>outcomes in different industries and economic contexts, but this research is very different <lb/></body>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">IJIEOM <lb/>7,1 <lb/></note>

			<page>84 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>from those earlier studies in several key ways. For instance, Yadav et al. (2020) identified and <lb/>quantified the interrelationships between the drivers for implementing lean manufacturing in <lb/>the pump parts manufacturing organization in the context of the Indian economy perspective <lb/>using the hybrid fuzzy analytical hierarchy process (FAHP)-decision-making trial and <lb/>evaluation laboratory (DEMATEL) tools. Their outcome showed that &quot;improved shop-floor <lb/>management,&quot; &quot;quality management,&quot; and &quot;manufacturing strategy&quot; were the most <lb/>significant drivers for adopting lean manufacturing. Again, Dehdasht et al. (2020) used the <lb/>TOPSIS method to identify and rank the most important factors influencing successful and <lb/>long-term adoption of sustainable lean practices in the Malaysia&apos;s construction industry. The <lb/>study found that the top drivers for implementing lean manufacturing in the pharmaceutical <lb/>industry were &quot;continuous monitoring process for sustainable lean implementation,&quot; <lb/>&quot;management involvement for sustainable implementation,&quot; &quot;training and education,&quot; <lb/>&quot;cost cutting&quot; and &quot;capacity utilization.&quot; This study is the first of its kind because no other <lb/>research has focused on identifying the drivers, especially in the pharmaceutical business <lb/>utilizing the Bayesian BWM technique. This study differs from earlier ones in a number of <lb/>ways. A number of industries and economic scenarios have been studied in the past to see <lb/>how lean implementation affects performance outcomes. However, this study is the first to <lb/>clearly define and rank the Bayesian BWM technique&apos;s drivers for lean deployment in the <lb/>pharmaceutical sector. This study offers important insights into how lean manufacturing <lb/>techniques might improve circular economy performance outcomes in the pharmaceutical <lb/>industry by adopting the circular economy approach. <lb/>5.2 Theoretical implications <lb/>The results of this study enhance the comprehension of the elements that lead to the <lb/>performance improvement of the circular economy, as perceived by practitioners. It is <lb/>possible to prioritize the drivers and allocate attention to them in the proper sequence by <lb/>employing our methodologies. The significance of conducting regular assessments of <lb/>operational progress, establishing unambiguous objectives and targets, overseeing outcomes <lb/>and quantifying and analyzing the implementation of lean manufacturing and sustainability <lb/>initiatives -a process known as continuous monitoring -must be underscored. This must be <lb/>completed before the organization commences the lean implementation process. Management <lb/>involvement is an additional critical element that propels the implementation of lean <lb/>principles. The active participation of these personnel is critical for the effective integration of <lb/>sustainability and circular economy principles into the organization&apos;s strategic objectives. <lb/>Furthermore, they exemplify the institution&apos;s dedication to sustainable development through <lb/>the provision of essential resources, cultivation of an environment conscious of <lb/>environmental stewardship and ongoing enhancement and reinforcement of said culture. <lb/>Succeeding in the implementation of lean manufacturing requires the cultivation of a <lb/>proficient workforce. The various firms equip their personnel with the requisite knowledge <lb/>and competencies to identify waste, optimize operations and demonstrate a steadfast <lb/>dedication to environmentally friendly practices. To enable personnel to contribute to the <lb/>enhancement of organizational performance, training programs may encompass a range of <lb/>subjects such as lean principles, circular economy concepts, waste minimization techniques <lb/>and sustainable manufacturing procedures. Consequently, training and education for <lb/>employees are paramount. <lb/>Although the analysis primarily focuses on case studies originating from pharmaceutical <lb/>corporations, the created methodology demonstrates applicability to several other domains <lb/>of endeavor. Due to this, the process of overcoming a variety of substantial obstacles can be <lb/>intricately connected to the structural foundation that this research provides. By optimizing <lb/>production processes while considering their impacts on natural resources, the environment, <lb/></body>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">Circular <lb/>economy <lb/>performance <lb/></note>

			<page>85 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>and the workplace, lean practices can contribute directly to the realization of sustainable <lb/>development goals (SDGs). <lb/>The literature already available on the application of lean gains various theoretical <lb/>insights from this study, including: <lb/>(1) Emphasizing the critical driving factors that will drive the implementation of LM in <lb/>the burgeoning pharmaceutical sector. <lb/>(2) Constructing a unified MCDM framework while utilizing the Bayesian BWM method <lb/>to evaluate and rank the primary drivers. <lb/>(3) To get a comprehensive understanding of the potential effects of LM deployment on <lb/>the pharmaceutical industry productivity and mitigate any adverse environmental <lb/>effects. <lb/>(4) Establishing a framework for more comprehensive investigations that would provide <lb/>decision-makers with a depth of knowledge regarding the factors influencing the <lb/>adoption of lean manufacturing practices across various manufacturing sectors. <lb/>5.3 Managerial and policy implications <lb/>For managers, consultants and industry experts striving to implement lean manufacturing <lb/>and move the pharmaceutical business toward a circular economy, the study&apos;s findings have <lb/>important ramifications. Managers may prioritize their efforts and create action plans in <lb/>accordance with the study&apos;s primary drivers by understanding them. Lean implementation, <lb/>for instance, can be made sustainable by beginning with a focus on the continuous <lb/>monitoring process. For the implementation to be successful, management support and <lb/>involvement are essential and training and education programs can enable staff to contribute <lb/>successfully. Managers may establish responsible and effective plans for implementing lean <lb/>manufacturing in their organizations by matching their strategies with the prioritized <lb/>drivers. The study emphasizes the value of waste reduction and performance enhancement, <lb/>which are important objectives for businesses pursuing profitability. The pharmaceutical <lb/>industry managers should become aware of these drivers and work to embrace lean <lb/>manufacturing practices in order to achieve their objectives. <lb/>The results also have ramifications for those who make policy. According to the study, <lb/>laws should be put in place to encourage capacity utilization and cost-cutting advantages for <lb/>companies that are sustainable. This may encourage additional pharmaceutical-makers to <lb/>embrace lean manufacturing techniques. To improve the performance of the circular <lb/>economy overall, policymakers should concentrate on encouraging the development of <lb/>sustainable technologies in the sector. Policymakers can aid in the accomplishment of circular <lb/>economy objectives by promoting the shift to a low-carbon economy and corporate <lb/>sustainability. In conclusion, this study offers insightful information for managers, <lb/>consultants and decision-makers that will help them comprehend the key elements <lb/>influencing the adoption of lean manufacturing and its fusion with circular economy <lb/>principles in the pharmaceutical business. Improved environmental sustainability, lower <lb/>costs and better performance outcomes can result from putting the drivers in place and <lb/>adjusting policies in accordance with them. <lb/>6. Conclusion, limitations and future directions <lb/>The integration of sustainable lean practices and the circular economy has gained significant <lb/>popularity in recent years due to its potential to reduce adverse environmental impacts in the <lb/>pharmaceutical industry. However, there is a research gap in understanding the implementation <lb/></body>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">IJIEOM <lb/>7,1 <lb/></note>

			<page>86 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<body>of lean practices in the pharmaceutical sector to enhance circular economy outcomes. This study <lb/>aimed to address this gap by utilizing a Bayesian BWM framework to identify the critical <lb/>drivers for lean implementation and their order of importance. The study began by identifying <lb/>relevant drivers through a comprehensive literature search, which were then validated through <lb/>expert feedback. A survey was conducted among the specialists to assess and categorize the <lb/>selected drivers into three groups: economical and organizational, knowledge and learning and <lb/>technological and resource management. The Bayesian BWM method was applied to rank the <lb/>drivers and determine their order in the context of the circular economy. The findings of the <lb/>study highlighted that the drivers &quot;continuous monitoring process for sustainable lean <lb/>implementation (T5)&quot;, &quot;management involvement for sustainable implementation (E4)&quot; and <lb/>&quot;training and education (K3)&quot; were the top three drivers for the lean manufacturing in the <lb/>pharmaceutical industry. These drivers play a crucial role in facilitating the successful adoption <lb/>and implementation of lean practices. Policymakers and industry leaders should prioritize these <lb/>drivers to simplify the integration process and promote sustainable lean implementation. <lb/>It is important to acknowledge the limitations of this study. While the study identified 17 <lb/>drivers of sustainable lean implementation and categorized them into different groups, it does <lb/>not claim to have captured all the drivers that contribute to lean philosophy in the <lb/>pharmaceutical industry. Further research can explore additional drivers and group them <lb/>into logical categories to compare the results with the current study. Additionally, the focus of <lb/>this study was limited to the circular economy perspective in the context of the <lb/>pharmaceutical industry in Bangladesh. Future studies can explore other economic <lb/>contexts and examine the interrelation of these drivers using modeling approaches such <lb/>as interpretive structural modeling (ISM) and fuzzy total interpretive structural modeling <lb/>(fuzzy TISM). To enhance the robustness of the findings, alternative pairwise comparison <lb/>approaches and other MCDM techniques such as fuzzy VIKOR and fuzzy TOPSIS can be <lb/>applied to compare and validate the proposed conceptual framework. Furthermore, the <lb/>outcomes of this study may vary for other service sectors, and researchers can conduct <lb/>further analysis in different industries to assess the generalizability of the findings. <lb/>In summary, this study contributes to the understanding of lean implementation in the <lb/>pharmaceutical industry by providing a framework and identifying the key drivers for <lb/>sustainable lean implementation. The findings offer valuable insights for policymakers and <lb/>industry leaders to improve decision-making and promote the successful adoption of lean <lb/>manufacturing practices. However, further research is needed to explore additional drivers, <lb/>compare different sectors and validate the proposed framework using other MCDM <lb/>techniques. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Abusaq, Z., Zahoor, S., Habib, M.S., Rehman, M., Mahmood, J., Kanan, M. and Mushtaq, R.T. (2023), <lb/>&quot;Improving energy performance in flexographic printing process through lean and ai <lb/>techniques: a case study&quot;, Energies, Vol. 16 No. 4, p. 1972, doi: 10.3390/en16041972. <lb/>Achillas, C. and Bochtis, D. (2020), &quot;Toward a green, closed-loop, circular bioeconomy: boosting the <lb/>performance efficiency of circular business models&quot;, Sustainability (Switzerland), Vol. 12 No. 23, <lb/>pp. 1-6, doi: 10.3390/su122310142. <lb/>Afum, E., Li, Y., Han, P. and Sun, Z. (2022), &quot;Interplay between lean management and circular <lb/>production system: implications for zero-waste performance, green value competitiveness, and <lb/>social reputation&quot;, Journal of Manufacturing Technology Management, Vol. 33 No. 7, <lb/>pp. 1213-1231, doi: 10.1108/jmtm-01-2022-0038. <lb/>Aithal, S. and Aithal, P.S. (2023), &quot;Importance of circular economy for resource optimization in various <lb/>industry sectors -a review-based opportunity analysis&quot;, International Journal of Applied <lb/>Engineering and Management Letters, Vol. 1, pp. 191-215, doi: 10.47992/ijaeml.2581.7000.0182. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">Circular <lb/>economy <lb/>performance <lb/></note>

			<page>87 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Ali, S.M., Ahmed, S., Ahmed, H.N., Sharmin, A. and Rahman, R. (2022), &quot;Reducing plastic pollutants <lb/>through catalyzing consumer roles: a novel application of fuzzy total interpretive structural <lb/>modeling&quot;, Journal of Cleaner Production, Vol. 335 December 2021, 130327, doi: 10.1016/j.jclepro. <lb/>2021.130327. <lb/>Almanei, M., Salonitis, K. and Xu, Y. (2017), &quot;Lean implementation frameworks: the challenges for <lb/>SMEs&quot;, Procedia CIRP, Vol. 63, pp. 750-755, doi: 10.1016/j.procir.2017.03.170. <lb/>Aloini, D., Dulmin, R., Mininno, V., Stefanini, A. and Zerbino, P. (2020), &quot;Driving the transition to a <lb/>circular economic model: a systematic review on drivers and critical success factors in circular <lb/>economy&quot;, Sustainability (Switzerland), Vol. 12 No. 24, pp. 1-14, doi: 10.3390/su122410672. <lb/>Anwar, A., Jamil, K., Idrees, M., Atif, M. and Ali, B. (2023), &quot;An empirical examination of SMEs <lb/>sustainable performance through lean manufacturing&quot;, Knowledge and Process Management, <lb/>Vol. 30 No. 3, pp. 289-299, doi: 10.1002/kpm.1740. <lb/>Arruda, E.H., Melatto, R.A.P.B., Levy, W. and Conti, D.D.M. (2021), &quot;Circular economy: a brief <lb/>literature review (2015-2020)&quot;, Sustainable Operations and Computers, Vol. 2 March, pp. 79-86, <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.susoc.2021.05.001. <lb/>Bag, S. and Pretorius, J.H.C. (2022), &quot;Relationships between industry 4.0, sustainable manufacturing <lb/>and circular economy: proposal of a research framework&quot;, International Journal of <lb/>Organizational Analysis, Vol. 30 No. 4, pp. 864-898, doi: 10.1108/ijoa-04-2020-2120. <lb/>Bento, G.dos S. and Tontini, G. (2019), &quot;Maturity of lean practices in Brazilian manufacturing <lb/>companies&quot;, Total Quality Management &amp; Business Excellence, Vol. 30 Sup1, pp. S114-S128, <lb/>doi: 10.1080/14783363.2019.1665827. <lb/>Cekerevac, Z., Dvorak, Z. and Prigoda, L. (2022), &quot;LEAN MANUFACTURING vs COVID-19&quot;, MEST <lb/>Journal, Vol. 10 No. 1, pp. 1-11, doi: 10.12709/mest.10.10.01.01. <lb/>Chahal, V. and Narwal, M. (2017), &quot;Impact of lean strategies on different industrial lean wastes&quot;, <lb/>International Journal of Theoretical and Applied Mechanics, Vol. 12 No. 2, pp. 275-286. <lb/>Chugani, N., Kumar, V., Garza-Reyes, J.A., Rocha-Lona, L. and Upadhyay, A. (2017), &quot;Investigating the <lb/>green impact of lean, six sigma and lean six sigma: a systematic literature review&quot;, <lb/>International Journal of Lean Six Sigma, Vol. 8 No. 1, pp. 7-32, doi: 10.1108/ijlss-11-2015-0043. <lb/>Ciliberto, C., Szopik-Depczy nska, K., Tarczy nska-Łuniewska, M., Ruggieri, A. and Ioppolo, G. (2021), <lb/>&quot;Enabling the Circular Economy transition: a sustainable lean manufacturing recipe for <lb/>Industry 4.0&quot;, Business Strategy and the Environment, Vol. 30 No. 7, pp. 3255-3272, doi: 10.1002/ <lb/>bse.2801. <lb/>Citybabu, G. and Yamini, S. (2022), &quot;The implementation of Lean Six Sigma framework in the Indian <lb/>context: a review and suggestions for future research&quot;, The TQM Journal, Vol. 34 No. 6, <lb/>pp. 1823-1859, doi: 10.1108/tqm-10-2021-0291. <lb/>Debnath, B., Bari, A.B.M.M., de Jesus Pacheco, D.A. and Karmaker, C.L. (2023a), &quot;An integrated Best-<lb/>Worst Method and Interpretive Structural Modeling approach for assessing the barriers to <lb/>circular economy implementation&quot;, Decision Analytics Journal, Vol. 7, 100250, doi: 10.1016/j. <lb/>dajour.2023.100250. <lb/>Debnath, B., Shakur, M.S., Bari, A.B.M.M. and Karmaker, C.L. (2023b), &quot;A Bayesian Best-Worst <lb/>approach for assessing the critical success factors in sustainable lean manufacturing&quot;, Decision <lb/>Analytics Journal, Vol. 6, 100157, doi: 10.1016/j.dajour.2022.100157. <lb/>Dehdasht, G., Ferwati, M.S., Zin, R.M. and Abidin, N.Z. (2020), &quot;A hybrid approach using entropy and <lb/>TOPSIS to select key drivers for a successful and sustainable lean construction <lb/>implementation&quot;, PLOS ONE, Vol. 15 No. 2, e0228746, doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0228746. <lb/>Dekier, Ł. (2012), &quot;The origins and evolution of Lean Management system&quot;, Journal of International <lb/>Studies, Vol. 5 No. 1, pp. 46-51, doi: 10.14254/2071-8330.2012/5-1/6. <lb/>Dey, P.K., Malesios, C., De, D., Budhwar, P., Chowdhury, S. and Cheffi, W. (2020), &quot;Circular economy to <lb/>enhance sustainability of small and medium-sized enterprises&quot;, Business Strategy and the <lb/>Environment, Vol. 29 No. 6, pp. 2145-2169, doi: 10.1002/bse.2492. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">IJIEOM <lb/>7,1 <lb/></note>

			<page>88 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Ding, L.li, Lei, L., Wang, L. and Zhang, L.fu. (2020), &quot;Assessing industrial circular economy <lb/>performance and its dynamic evolution: an extended Malmquist index based on cooperative <lb/>game network DEA&quot;, Science of the Total Environment, Vol. 731, 139001, doi: 10.1016/j. <lb/>scitotenv.2020.139001. <lb/>Dossou, P.-E., Torregrossa, P. and Martinez, T. (2022), &quot;Industry 4.0 concepts and lean manufacturing <lb/>implementation for optimizing a company logistics flows&quot;, Procedia Computer Science, Vol. 200 <lb/>No. 2019, pp. 358-367, doi: 10.1016/j.procs.2022.01.234. <lb/>Du, J., Zhang, J., Castro-Lacouture, D. and Hu, Y. (2023), &quot;Lean manufacturing applications in <lb/>prefabricated construction projects&quot;, Automation in Construction, Vol. 150, 104790, doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.autcon.2023.104790. <lb/>Elkhairi, A., Fedouaki, F. and El Alami, S. (2019), &quot;Barriers and critical success factors for <lb/>implementing lean manufacturing in SMEs&quot;, IFAC-PapersOnLine, Vol. 52 No. 13, pp. 565-570, <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.ifacol.2019.11.303. <lb/>Eskandari, M., Hamid, M., Masoudian, M. and Rabbani, M. (2022), &quot;An integrated lean production-<lb/>sustainability framework for evaluation and improvement of the performance of pharmaceutical <lb/>factory&quot;, Journal of Cleaner Production, Vol. 376, 134132, doi: 10.1016/j.jclepro.2022.134132. <lb/>Ferdoush, M.R., Al Aziz, R., Karmaker, C.L., Debnath, B., Limon, M.H. and Bari, A.B.M.M. (2024), <lb/>&quot;Unraveling the challenges of waste-to-energy transition in emerging economies: implications for <lb/>sustainability&quot;, Innovation and Green Development, Vol. 3 No. 2, 100121, doi: 10.1016/j.igd.2023.100121. <lb/>Fontana, A., Barni, A., Leone, D., Spirito, M., Tringale, A., Ferraris, M., Reis, J. and Goncalves, G. <lb/>(2021), &quot;Circular economy strategies for equipment lifetime extension: a systematic review&quot;, <lb/>Sustainability (Switzerland), Vol. 13 No. 3, pp. 1-27, doi: 10.3390/su13031117. <lb/>Garza-Reyes, J.A., Parkar, H.S., Oraifige, I., Soriano-Meier, H. and Harmanto, D. (2012), &quot;An empirical-<lb/>exploratory study of the status of lean manufacturing in India&quot;, International Journal of <lb/>Business Excellence, Vol. 5 No. 4, pp. 395-412, doi: 10.1504/IJBEX.2012.047906. <lb/>Ghosh, M. (2013), &quot;Lean manufacturing performance in Indian manufacturing plants&quot;, Journal of <lb/>Manufacturing Technology Management, Vol. 24 No. 1, pp. 113-122, doi: 10.1108/ <lb/>17410381311287517. <lb/>Goshime, Y., Kitaw, D. and Jilcha, K. (2019), &quot;Lean manufacturing as a vehicle for improving <lb/>productivity and customer satisfaction: a literature review on metals and engineering <lb/>industries&quot;, International Journal of Lean Six Sigma, Vol. 10 No. 2, pp. 691-714, doi: 10.1108/ijlss-<lb/>06-2017-0063. <lb/>Habib, M.A., Rizvan, R. and Ahmed, S. (2023), &quot;Implementing lean manufacturing for improvement of <lb/>operational performance in a labeling and packaging plant: a case study in Bangladesh&quot;, <lb/>Results in Engineering, Vol. 17, 100818, doi: 10.1016/j.rineng.2022.100818. <lb/>Hariyani, D. and Mishra, S. (2022a), &quot;Barriers to the adoption of integrated sustainable-green-lean-six <lb/>sigma-agile manufacturing system (ISGLSAMS): a literature review&quot;, Benchmarking: An <lb/>International Journal, Vol. 30 No. 9, pp. 3590-3636, doi: 10.1108/bij-10-2021-0585. <lb/>Hariyani, D. and Mishra, S. (2022b), &quot;Drivers for the adoption of integrated sustainable green lean six <lb/>sigma agile manufacturing system (ISGLSAMS) and research directions&quot;, Cleaner Engineering <lb/>and Technology, Vol. 7, 100449, doi: 10.1016/j.clet.2022.100449. <lb/>Hasan, S., Khan, G., Hoque, M.R., Hassan, F. and Ahmed, N. (2022), &quot;Lean practices in the Bangladeshi <lb/>ready-made garments industry and global significance&quot;, International Journal of Logistics <lb/>Research and Applications, Vol. 25 No. 3, pp. 309-327, doi: 10.1080/13675567.2020.1847262. <lb/>Hedberg, A. and <lb/>Sipka, S. (2021), &quot;Toward a circular economy: the role of digitalization&quot;, One Earth, <lb/>Vol. 4 No. 6, pp. 783-785, doi: 10.1016/j.oneear.2021.05.020. <lb/>Henrique, D.B., Filho, M.G., Marodin, G., Jabbour, A.B.L.D.S. and Chiappetta Jabbour, C.J. (2021), &quot;A <lb/>framework to assess sustaining continuous improvement in lean healthcare&quot;, International <lb/>Journal of Production Research, Vol. 59 No. 10, pp. 2885-2904, doi: 10.1080/00207543.2020. <lb/>1743892. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">Circular <lb/>economy <lb/>performance <lb/></note>

			<page>89 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Hunka, A.D., Linder, M. and Habibi, S. (2021), &quot;Determinants of consumer demand for circular <lb/>economy products. A case for reuse and remanufacturing for sustainable development&quot;, <lb/>Business Strategy and the Environment, Vol. 30 No. 1, pp. 535-550, doi: 10.1002/bse.2636. <lb/>Hussain, M. and Malik, M. (2020), &quot;Organizational enablers for circular economy in the context of <lb/>sustainable supply chain management&quot;, Journal of Cleaner Production, Vol. 256, 120375, doi: 10. <lb/>1016/j.jclepro.2020.120375. <lb/>Jaiswal, P., Singh, A., Misra, S.C. and Kumar, A. (2021), &quot;Barriers in implementing lean manufacturing <lb/>in Indian SMEs: a multi-criteria decision-making approach&quot;, Journal of Modelling in <lb/>Management, Vol. 16 No. 1, pp. 339-356, doi: 10.1108/JM2-12-2019-0276. <lb/>Jalundhwala, F. and Londhe, V. (2023), &quot;A systematic review on implementing operational excellence as a <lb/>strategy to ensure regulatory compliance: a roadmap for Indian pharmaceutical industry&quot;, <lb/>International Journal of Lean Six Sigma, Vol. 14 No. 4, pp. 730-758, doi: 10.1108/ijlss-04-2022-0078. <lb/>Januszek, S., Macuvele, J., Friedli, T. and Netland, T.H. (2023), &quot;The role of management in lean <lb/>implementation: evidence from the pharmaceutical industry&quot;, International Journal of Operations <lb/>&amp; Production Management, Vol. 43 No. 3, pp. 401-427, doi: 10.1108/ijopm-02-2022-0129. <lb/>Kamble, S., Gunasekaran, A. and Dhone, N.C. (2020), &quot;Industry 4.0 and lean manufacturing practices <lb/>for sustainable organisational performance in Indian manufacturing companies&quot;, International <lb/>Journal of Production Research, Vol. 58 No. 5, pp. 1319-1337, doi: 10.1080/00207543.2019. <lb/>1630772. <lb/>Karam, A.A., Liviu, M., Cristina, V. and Radu, H. (2018), &quot;The contribution of lean manufacturing tools <lb/>to changeover time decrease in the pharmaceutical industry. A SMED project&quot;, Procedia <lb/>Manufacturing, Vol. 22, pp. 886-892, doi: 10.1016/j.promfg.2018.03.125. <lb/>Kazakova, E. and Lee, J. (2022), &quot;Sustainable manufacturing for a circular economy&quot;, Sustainability, <lb/>Vol. 14 No. 24, 17010, doi: 10.3390/su142417010. <lb/>Khan, F. and Ali, Y. (2022), &quot;Implementation of the circular supply chain management in the <lb/>pharmaceutical industry&quot;, Environment, Development and Sustainability, Vol. 24 No. 12, <lb/>pp. 13705-13731, doi: 10.1007/s10668-021-02007-6. <lb/>Khan, S. and Haleem, A. (2021), &quot;Investigation of circular economy practices in the context of <lb/>emerging economies: a CoCoSo approach&quot;, International Journal of Sustainable Engineering, <lb/>Vol. 14 No. 3, pp. 357-367, doi: 10.1080/19397038.2020.1871442. <lb/>Krishnan, S., Mathiyazhagan, K. and Appolloni, A. (2022), &quot;Assessing the drivers and challenges to <lb/>deploying lean-green practices the in Indian manufacturing sector&quot;, Lean and Green <lb/>Manufacturing: Towards Eco-Efficiency and Business Performance, pp. 23-43, doi: 10.1007/ <lb/>978-981-16-5551-7_2. <lb/>Kumar, N., Hasan, S.S., Srivastava, K., Akhtar, R., Yadav, R.K. and Choubey, V.K. (2022), &quot;Lean <lb/>manufacturing techniques and its implementation: a review&quot;, Materials Today: Proceedings. <lb/>Laskowski, S.E. (2017), &quot;Capacity utilization and lean manufacturing at a plastic medical device <lb/>components manufacturer&quot;, Vol. 94. <lb/>Liang, F., Brunelli, M. and Rezaei, J. (2020), &quot;Consistency issues in the best worst method: <lb/>measurements and thresholds&quot;, Omega (United Kingdom), Vol. 96, 102175, doi: 10.1016/j.omega. <lb/>2019.102175. <lb/>Lim, M.K., Lai, M., Wang, C. and Lee, Y. (2022), &quot;Circular economy to ensure production operational <lb/>sustainability: a green-lean approach&quot;, Sustainable Production and Consumption, Vol. 30, <lb/>pp. 130-144, doi: 10.1016/j.spc.2021.12.001. <lb/>Liu, L., Song, W. and Liu, Y. (2023), &quot;Leveraging digital capabilities toward a circular economy: <lb/>reinforcing sustainable supply chain management with Industry 4.0 technologies&quot;, Computers <lb/>&amp; Industrial Engineering, Vol. 178, 109113, doi: 10.1016/j.cie.2023.109113. <lb/>Mankazana, S. and Mukwakungu, S.C. (2018), &quot;The impact of just-in-time (JIT) in inventory <lb/>management system and the supplier overall performance of south African&apos;s bed mattress <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">IJIEOM <lb/>7,1 <lb/></note>

			<page>90 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>manufacturing companies&quot;, Proceedings of the International Conference on Industrial <lb/>Engineering and Operations Management, Vol. 2018 November, pp. 239-249. <lb/>McDermott, O., Antony, J., Bhat, S., Jayaraman, R., Rosa, A., Marolla, G. and Parida, R. (2022), &quot;Lean <lb/>six sigma in healthcare: a systematic literature review on motivations and benefits&quot;, Processes, <lb/>Vol. 10 No. 10, p. 1910, doi: 10.3390/pr10101910. <lb/>McKie, M.G., Jones, R., Miles, J. and Jones, I.R. (2021), &quot;Improving lean manufacturing systems and <lb/>tools engagement through the utilisation of industry 4.0, improved communication and a people <lb/>recognition methodology in a UK engine manufacturing centre&quot;, Procedia Manufacturing, <lb/>Vol. 55, pp. 371-382, doi: 10.1016/j.promfg.2021.10.052. <lb/>Milios, L. (2021), &quot;Overarching policy framework for product life extension in a circular economy-a <lb/>bottom-up business perspective&quot;, Environmental Policy and Governance, Vol. 31 No. 4, <lb/>pp. 330-346, doi: 10.1002/eet.1927. <lb/>Mohammadi, M. and Rezaei, J. (2020), &quot;Bayesian best-worst method: a probabilistic group decision <lb/>making model&quot;, Omega (United Kingdom), Vol. 96 June, 102075, doi: 10.1016/j.omega.2019.06.001. <lb/>Morseletto, P. (2023), &quot;Sometimes linear, sometimes circular: states of the economy and transitions to <lb/>the future&quot;, Journal of Cleaner Production, Vol. 390 January, 136138, doi: 10.1016/j.jclepro.2023. <lb/>136138. <lb/>Nagaich, R. (2022), &quot;Lean concept implementation practices in small and medium scale pharmaceutical <lb/>industry-A case study&quot;, International Journal for Research in Applied Science and Engineering <lb/>Technology, Vol. 10 No. 1, pp. 213-220, doi: 10.22214/ijraset.2022.39811. <lb/>Naseemullah, A. (2022), &quot;Dependent development in the twenty-first century&quot;, Third World Quarterly, <lb/>Vol. 43 No. 9, pp. 2225-2243, doi: 10.1080/01436597.2022.2089104. <lb/>Nenni, M.E., Giustiniano, L. and Pirolo, L. (2014), &quot;Improvement of manufacturing operations through <lb/>a lean management approach: a case study in the pharmaceutical industry&quot;, International <lb/>Journal of Engineering Business Management, Vol. 6 No. 1, pp. 1-6, doi: 10.5772/59027. <lb/>Nour, R. and Laux, C. (2021), &quot;Application of lean six sigma to reduce the cost of regulatory <lb/>noncompliance&quot;, International Conference on Lean Six Sigma. <lb/>Osman, A.A., Othman, A.A. and Abdul Rahim, M.K.I. (2020), &quot;Lean manufacturing adoption in <lb/>Malaysia: a systematic literature review&quot;, International Journal of Supply Chain, Operation <lb/>Management and Logistics, Vol. 1 No. 1, pp. 1-35, doi: 10.35631/ijscol.11001. <lb/>Palange, A. and Dhatrak, P. (2021), &quot;Lean manufacturing a vital tool to enhance productivity in <lb/>manufacturing&quot;, Materials Today: Proceedings, Vol. 46, pp. 729-736, doi: 10.1016/j.matpr.2020. <lb/>12.193. <lb/>Palit, T., Bari, A.B.M.M. and Karmaker, C.L. (2022), &quot;An integrated Principal Component Analysis and <lb/>Interpretive Structural Modeling approach for electric vehicle adoption decisions in sustainable <lb/>transportation systems&quot;, Decision Analytics Journal, Vol. 4 September, 100119, doi: 10.1016/j. <lb/>dajour.2022.100119. <lb/>Panigrahi, S., Al Ghafri, K.K., Al Alyani, W.R., Ali Khan, M.W., Al Madhagy, T. and Khan, A. (2023), <lb/>&quot;Lean manufacturing practices for operational and business performance: a PLS-SEM modeling <lb/>analysis&quot;, International Journal of Engineering Business Management, Vol. 15, <lb/>18479790221147864, doi: 10.1177/18479790221147864. <lb/>Parmar, P.S. and Desai, T.N. (2020), &quot;Evaluating Sustainable Lean Six Sigma enablers using fuzzy <lb/>DEMATEL: a case of an Indian manufacturing organization&quot;, Journal of Cleaner Production, <lb/>Vol. 265, 121802, doi: 10.1016/j.jclepro.2020.121802. <lb/>Patel, A.S. and Patel, K.M. (2022), &quot;Status of Lean Six Sigma implementation in Indian industries: <lb/>a cross-sectional national survey&quot;, International Journal of Lean Six Sigma, Vol. 14 No. 4, <lb/>pp. 791-814, doi: 10.1108/ijlss-05-2022-0107. <lb/>Patwa, N., Sivarajah, U., Seetharaman, A., Sarkar, S., Maiti, K. and Hingorani, K. (2021), &quot;Towards a <lb/>circular economy: an emerging economies context&quot;, Journal of Business Research, Vol. 122 <lb/>September 2019, pp. 725-735, doi: 10.1016/j.jbusres.2020.05.015. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">Circular <lb/>economy <lb/>performance <lb/></note>

			<page>91 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Pereira, A.C., Dinis-Carvalho, J., Alves, A.C. and Arezes, P. (2019), &quot;How Industry 4.0 can enhance lean <lb/>practices&quot;, FME Transactions, Vol. 47 No. 4, pp. 810-822, doi: 10.5937/fmet1904810p. <lb/>Pieroni, M.P.P., McAloone, T.C. and Pigosso, D.C.A. (2019), &quot;Business model innovation for circular <lb/>economy and sustainability: a review of approaches&quot;, Journal of Cleaner Production, Vol. 215, <lb/>pp. 198-216, doi: 10.1016/j.jclepro.2019.01.036. <lb/>Proença, A.P., Gaspar, P.D. and Lima, T.M. (2022), &quot;Lean optimization techniques for improvement of <lb/>production flows and logistics management: the case study of a fruits distribution center&quot;, <lb/>Processes, Vol. 10 No. 7, p. 1384, doi: 10.3390/pr10071384. <lb/>Rana, P. and Kaushik, P. (2018), &quot;Initiatives of six-sigma in an automotive ancillary unit: a case study&quot;, <lb/>Management Science Letters, Vol. 8 No. 6, pp. 569-580, doi: 10.5267/j.msl.2018.4.033. <lb/>Rezaei, J. (2015), &quot;Best-worst multi-criteria decision-making method&quot;, Omega, Vol. 53, pp. 49-57, doi: 10. <lb/>1016/j.omega.2014.11.009. <lb/>Ruberg, S.J., Beckers, F., Hemmings, R., Honig, P., Irony, T., LaVange, L., Lieberman, G., Mayne, J. and <lb/>Moscicki, R. (2023), &quot;Application of Bayesian approaches in drug development: starting a <lb/>virtuous cycle&quot;, Nature Reviews Drug Discovery, Vol. 22 No. 3, pp. 235-250, doi: 10.1038/s41573-<lb/>023-00638-0. <lb/>Salman, S., Ahmed, T., Taqi, H.M.M., Frederico, G.F., Dip, A.S. and Ali, S.M. (2023), &quot;An integrated <lb/>approach to explore the barriers to lean manufacturing in the context of the COVID-19 pandemic: <lb/>implications for sustainability&quot;, International Journal of Industrial Engineering and Operations <lb/>Management, Vol. ahead-of-print No. ahead-of-print, doi: 10.1108/IJIEOM-02-2023-0027. <lb/>Salonitis, K. and Tsinopoulos, C. (2016), &quot;Drivers and barriers of lean implementation in the Greek <lb/>manufacturing sector&quot;, Procedia CIRP, Vol. 57, pp. 189-194, doi: 10.1016/j.procir.2016.11.033. <lb/>Santos, L.C., Reul, L.M.A. and Gohr, C.F. (2023), &quot;A graph-theoretic approach for assessing the <lb/>leanness level of supply chains&quot;, Supply Chain Management: An International Journal, Vol. 28 <lb/>No. 1, pp. 74-89, doi: 10.1108/scm-02-2021-0079. <lb/>Sawe, F.B., Kumar, A., Garza-Reyes, J.A. and Agrawal, R. (2021), &quot;Assessing people-driven factors for <lb/>circular economy practices in small and medium-sized enterprise supply chains: business <lb/>strategies and environmental perspectives&quot;, Business Strategy and the Environment, Vol. 30 <lb/>No. 7, pp. 2951-2965, doi: 10.1002/bse.2781. <lb/>Schmitt, T., Wolf, C., Lennerfors, T.T. and Okwir, S. (2021), &quot;Beyond &apos;Leanear&apos; production: a multi-<lb/>level approach for achieving circularity in a lean manufacturing context&quot;, Journal of Cleaner <lb/>Production, Vol. 318 July, 128531, doi: 10.1016/j.jclepro.2021.128531. <lb/>Seleem, S.N., Attia, E.A., Karam, A. and El-Assal, A. (2020), &quot;A lean manufacturing road map using <lb/>fuzzy-DEMATEL with case-based analysis&quot;, International Journal of Lean Six Sigma, Vol. 11 <lb/>No. 5, pp. 917-942, doi: 10.1108/IJLSS-12-2017-0147. <lb/>Sharabati, A.-A.A. (2023), &quot;Lean operations and competitive advantage in the pharmaceutical <lb/>industry&quot;, International Journal of Services and Operations Management, Vol. 44 No. 3, <lb/>pp. 293-316, doi: 10.1504/IJSOM.2023.129463. <lb/>Shashi, Centobelli, P., Cerchione, R. and Mittal, A. (2021), &quot;Managing sustainability in luxury industry <lb/>to pursue circular economy strategies&quot;, Business Strategy and the Environment, Vol. 30 No. 1, <lb/>pp. 432-462, doi: 10.1002/bse.2630. <lb/>Shi, L. (2022), &quot;Industrial symbiosis: context and relevance to the sustainable development goals <lb/>(SDGs)&quot;, in Responsible Consumption and Production, Springer, pp. 381-391. <lb/>Sieckmann, F., Ngoc, H.N., Helm, R. and Kohl, H. (2018), &quot;Implementation of lean production systems <lb/>in small and medium-sized pharmaceutical enterprises&quot;, Procedia Manufacturing, Vol. 21 <lb/>No. 2017, pp. 814-821, doi: 10.1016/j.promfg.2018.02.188. <lb/>Singh, C., Singh, D. and Khamba, J.S. (2021), &quot;Analyzing barriers of Green Lean practices in <lb/>manufacturing industries by DEMATEL approach&quot;, Journal of Manufacturing Technology <lb/>Management, Vol. 32 No. 1, pp. 176-198, doi: 10.1108/JMTM-02-2020-0053. <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">IJIEOM <lb/>7,1 <lb/></note>

			<page>92 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Sol ıs-Quinteros, M.M., Zayas-M arquez, C., <lb/>Avila-L opez, L.A. and Carrillo-Gutirrez, T. (2021), &quot;Lean <lb/>manufacturing as a strategy for continuous improvement in organizations&quot;, Lean <lb/>Manufacturing, pp. 131-144, doi: 10.5772/intechopen.96427. <lb/>Sosnowski, P.C. and Cyplik, P. (2022), &quot;Closed loop supply chains and circular economy -the <lb/>possibilities of interplay&quot;, Logforum, Vol. 18 No. 4, pp. 413-420, doi: 10.17270/J.LOG.2022.784. <lb/>Swarnakar, V., Tiwari, A.K. and Singh, A.R. (2020), &quot;Evaluating critical failure factors for <lb/>implementing sustainable lean six sigma framework in manufacturing organization: a case <lb/>experience&quot;, International Journal of Lean Six Sigma, Vol. 11 No. 6, pp. 1083-1118, doi: 10.1108/ <lb/>IJLSS-05-2019-0050. <lb/>Thanki, S., Govindan, K. and Thakkar, J. (2016), &quot;An investigation on lean-green implementation <lb/>practices in Indian SMEs using analytical hierarchy process (AHP) approach&quot;, Journal of <lb/>Cleaner Production, Vol. 135, pp. 284-298, doi: 10.1016/j.jclepro.2016.06.105. <lb/>Touriki, F.E., Benkhati, I., Kamble, S.S., Belhadi, A. and El fezazi, S. (2021), &quot;An integrated smart, <lb/>green, resilient, and lean manufacturing framework: a literature review and future research <lb/>directions&quot;, Journal of Cleaner Production, Vol. 319 July, 128691, doi: 10.1016/j.jclepro.2021. <lb/>128691. <lb/>Verma, N., Sidhu, S.S., Chatha, J.S. and Bali, S. (2022), &quot;To study the implementation of kaizen in <lb/>northern Indian manufacturing industries&quot;, Recent Advances in Mechanical Engineering: Select <lb/>Proceedings of ICRAMERD 2021, Springer, pp. 465-474. <lb/>Yadav, G., Luthra, S., Huisingh, D., Mangla, S.K., Narkhede, B.E. and Liu, Y. (2020), &quot;Development of a <lb/>lean manufacturing framework to enhance its adoption within manufacturing companies in <lb/>developing economies&quot;, Journal of Cleaner Production, Vol. 245, 118726, doi: 10.1016/j.jclepro. <lb/>2019.118726. <lb/>Yanilmaz, S., Baskak, D., Yucesan, M. and Gul, M. (2021), &quot;Extension of FEMA and SMUG models <lb/>with Bayesian best-worst method for disaster risk reduction&quot;, International Journal of Disaster <lb/>Risk Reduction, Vol. 66, 102631, doi: 10.1016/j.ijdrr.2021.102631. <lb/>Zu Castell-R€ udenhausen, M., Wahlstr€ om, M., Fruergaard Astrup, T., Jensen, C., Oberender, A., <lb/>Johansson, P. and Waerner, E.R. (2021), &quot;Policies as drivers for circular economy in the <lb/>construction sector in the nordics&quot;, Sustainability (Switzerland), Vol. 13 No. 16, pp. 1-19, doi: 10. <lb/>3390/su13169350. <lb/>(The Appendix follows overleaf) <lb/></listBibl>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">Circular <lb/>economy <lb/>performance <lb/></note>

			<page>93 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Supplementary material <lb/>The confidence score matrices for all clusters have been presented in Table S2-S5 (see supplementary <lb/>material). <lb/>For determining and clustering the key driver for implementing lean manufacturing <lb/>Total experts <lb/>Experience <lb/>Designation <lb/>Number of experts <lb/>Percentage <lb/>N 5 19 <lb/>More than 16 years <lb/>Executive Director <lb/>4 <lb/>21.05 <lb/>General Manager <lb/>3 <lb/>15.79 <lb/>Assistant General Manager <lb/>2 <lb/>10.53 <lb/>Manager <lb/>2 <lb/>10.53 <lb/>10-16 years <lb/>Executive Director <lb/>3 <lb/>15.79 <lb/>General Manager <lb/>2 <lb/>10.53 <lb/>Assistant General Manager <lb/>1 <lb/>5.26 <lb/>7-10 years <lb/>Manager <lb/>2 <lb/>10.53 <lb/>For determining the ranking of key drivers using Bayesian BWM <lb/>M 5 15 <lb/>More than 16 years <lb/>Executive Director <lb/>3 <lb/>20.00 <lb/>General Manager <lb/>2 <lb/>13.33 <lb/>Assistant General Manager <lb/>2 <lb/>13.33 <lb/>Manager <lb/>1 <lb/>6.67 <lb/>10-16 years <lb/>General Manager <lb/>3 <lb/>20.00 <lb/>Assistant General Manager <lb/>2 <lb/>13.33 <lb/>Academic (Professor) <lb/>1 <lb/>6.67 <lb/>7-10 years <lb/>Manager <lb/>1 <lb/>6.67 <lb/>Source(s): Authors&apos; own contribution <lb/>Cluster <lb/>C1 <lb/>C2 <lb/>C3 <lb/>C1. Economical and organizational (0.359) <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>0.9493 <lb/>0.3958 <lb/>C2. Knowledge and learning (0.263) <lb/>0.0507 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>0.0301 <lb/>C3. Technological and resource management (0.376) <lb/>0.6042 <lb/>0.9699 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>Source(s): Authors&apos; own contribution <lb/>Economical and organizational <lb/>E1 <lb/>E2 <lb/>E3 <lb/>E4 <lb/>E5 <lb/>E6 <lb/>E1: Cost cutting <lb/>0.0000 0.9885 0.9874 0.4665 0.9937 0.9044 <lb/>E2: Shorter time to market <lb/>0.0115 0.0000 0.4778 0.0089 0.5910 0.1573 <lb/>E3: Adherence to regulations <lb/>0.0126 0.5222 0.0000 0.0102 0.6097 0.1663 <lb/>E4: Management involvement for sustainable <lb/>implementation <lb/>0.5335 0.9911 0.9898 0.0000 0.9957 0.9190 <lb/>E5: Quality augmentation <lb/>0.0063 0.4090 0.3903 0.0043 0.0000 0.1106 <lb/>E6: Standardization <lb/>0.0956 0.8427 0.8337 0.0810 0.8894 0.0000 <lb/>Source(s): Authors&apos; own contribution <lb/>Table S1. <lb/>Summary of the <lb/>participating experts&apos; <lb/>profiles <lb/>Table S2. <lb/>Confidence score of <lb/>cluster level <lb/>Table S3. <lb/>Economical and <lb/>organizational-related <lb/>confidence scores <lb/></div>
	  
	  <note place="headnote">IJIEOM <lb/>7,1 <lb/></note>

			<page>94 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">3.1 Bayesian Best-Worst Method (BWM) <lb/>The following present the major steps of the Bayesian BWM (Debnath et al., 2023): <lb/>1. Identifying the best and worst criterion: Consider a group of criteria, denoted as <lb/>E ¼ fE 1 ; E 2 ; . . . . . . . . . ; E n g, that are being evaluated by k experts. At first, each expert is tasked <lb/>with selecting the best ðE <lb/>k <lb/>C Þ and worst ðE k <lb/>U Þ criterion from the set of criteria E. During this phase, <lb/>experts make these selections without engaging in pairwise comparisons. Expert k considers the best <lb/>criterion to be the most significant, whereas the weakest criterion is considered the least significant. <lb/>It is important to note that different experts may have different perspectives on what they perceive to <lb/>be the best and worst choices depending on their own criteria. <lb/>2. Constructing the pairwise comparison of best to others: Expert k generates a pairwise comparison <lb/>matrix to compare the best criterion ðE k <lb/>C Þ with the other criteria in set E. To indicate their choice for <lb/>the best criterion above the others as chosen in the previous stage, each expert assigns a number <lb/>between one and nine. One implies that the two criteria are equally important, but nine shows that E k <lb/>C <lb/>is much more important. The &quot;Best to Others&quot; vector represents the pairwise comparisons&apos; result of <lb/>expert n, represented by B k <lb/>C as follows: <lb/>B k <lb/>C ¼ b k <lb/>C1 ; b k <lb/>C2 ; . . . . . . . . . ; b k <lb/>Cn ; k ¼ 1; 2; 3; . . . . . . ; K <lb/>(1) <lb/>where the preference of an expert k for the best criteria E k <lb/>C over e i ∈ E is represented by b k <lb/>Ci . <lb/>3. Constructing a pairwise comparison of others to worst: Like before, expert k creates a pairwise <lb/>comparison matrix to compare the worst criterion ðE k <lb/>U Þ with other criteria in set E. The &quot;Others to <lb/>Worst&quot; vector represents the pairwise comparisons&apos; result of expert n, denoted as B k <lb/>U . <lb/>B k <lb/>U ¼ ðb k <lb/>1U ; b k <lb/>2U ; . . . . . . . . . ; b k <lb/>nU <lb/>T <lb/>(2) <lb/>where the preference of an expert k for the worst criteria E k <lb/>U over e i ∈ E is represented by b k <lb/>Ui . <lb/>Knowledge and learning <lb/>K1 <lb/>K2 <lb/>K3 <lb/>K4 <lb/>K5 <lb/>K1: Ongoing development <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>0.0076 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>0.4521 <lb/>0.1038 <lb/>K2: Employee involvement <lb/>0.9924 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>0.0808 <lb/>0.9902 <lb/>0.8872 <lb/>K3: Training and education <lb/>0.9999 <lb/>0.9192 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>0.9997 <lb/>0.9947 <lb/>K4: Customer contentment <lb/>0.5479 <lb/>0.0098 <lb/>0.0003 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>0.1296 <lb/>K5: Collaboration and communication <lb/>0.8961 <lb/>0.1128 <lb/>0.0053 <lb/>0.8704 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>Source(s): Authors&apos; own contribution <lb/>Technological and resource management <lb/>T1 <lb/>T2 <lb/>T3 <lb/>T4 <lb/>T5 <lb/>T6 <lb/>T1: Operational efficiency <lb/>0.0000 0.3157 <lb/>0.0349 0.9567 0.01 <lb/>0.883 <lb/>T2: Resource optimization <lb/>0.6843 0.0000 <lb/>0.0904 0.9846 0.000413 0.951 <lb/>T3: Capacity utilization <lb/>0.9651 0.9096 <lb/>0.0000 0.9997 0.016534 0.998 <lb/>T4: Process mapping <lb/>0.0433 0.0154 <lb/>0.0003 0.0000 0.556 <lb/>0.297 <lb/>T5: Continuous monitoring process for <lb/>sustainable lean implementation <lb/>0.9797 0.99950 0.983 <lb/>0.557 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>0.259 <lb/>T6: Sustainable supplier selection <lb/>0.1172 0.0488 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.703 <lb/>0.3358 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>Source(s): Authors&apos; own contribution <lb/>Table S4. <lb/>Knowledge and <lb/>learning-related <lb/>confidence scores <lb/>Table S5. <lb/>Technological and <lb/>resource management-<lb/>related confidence <lb/>scores <lb/></div>
	  
	 <note place="headnote">Circular <lb/>economy <lb/>performance <lb/></note>

			<page>95 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">4. Calculation of aggregated weight: The Bayesian BWM uses a probabilistic technique to determine <lb/>the combined weights ðu * ¼ u * <lb/>1 ; u * <lb/>2 ; . . . . . . ::u * <lb/>n Þ from all K experts as well as the individual weights <lb/>ðu k Þ; where k ¼ 1; 2; . . . ::K; for each expert. This method calculates aggregated weights using <lb/>probabilistic principles and takes into consideration all expert input to determine the overall <lb/>relevance of the criterion. It also computes the individual weight of each expert, showing their <lb/>contribution to the final outcomes. <lb/>B k <lb/>C <lb/>u k ∼ multinomial <lb/>À <lb/>1 <lb/>u k Á <lb/>; ∀k ¼ 1; 2; . . . ::; K; <lb/>(3) <lb/>B k <lb/>C <lb/>u k ∼ multinomial <lb/>À <lb/>u k Á <lb/>; ∀k ¼ 1; 2; . . . ::; K; <lb/>(4) <lb/>u k <lb/>u * ∼ Dirðγ * u * Þ; ∀k ¼ 1; 2; . . . ::; K; <lb/>(5) <lb/>γ ∼ gammað0:1; 0:1Þ <lb/>(6) <lb/>u * ∼ Dirð1Þ <lb/>(7) <lb/>The probabilistic model defined by equation (7) involves a multinomial distribution denoted as <lb/>multinomial, a Dirichlet distribution denoted as Dir and a gamma distribution denoted as gamma (0.1, <lb/>0.1). Unfortunately, there is no direct mathematical solution available for this model. Markov-chain <lb/>Monte Carlo (MCMC) sampling is used to obtain the result. MCMC sampling involves creating random <lb/>samples from the probability distribution to approximate the solution. It is a computationally intensive <lb/>process but necessary to compute the desired output in this case. <lb/>In the context of MCDM, the weight vector u i ¼ ðu 1 ; u 2 ; u 3 ; . . . . . . . . . ::u n Þ is commonly used. This <lb/>weight vector is subject to the condition <lb/>P n <lb/>i¼1 <lb/>u i ¼ 1, indicating that the weights assigned to each criterion <lb/>should add up to one. Additionally, each u i the value must be greater than or equal to zero ðu i ≥ 0Þ. The <lb/>weighting of each criterion ðe i Þ can be considered a probabilistic or random event, where u i represents <lb/>the likelihood of that event occurring. This formulation aligns with the principles of the probability <lb/>theory, where <lb/>P n <lb/>i¼1 <lb/>u i ¼ 1 and u i ≥ 0 can be mathematically derived as equivalent statements. Thus, the <lb/>constructing probabilistic models is crucial in the context of decision-making (Yang et al., 2020). <lb/></div>
				
				<listBibl>References <lb/>Debnath, B., Shakur, Md S., Mainul Bari, A.B.M. and Karmaker, C.L. (2023c), &quot;A bayesian best-worst <lb/>approach for assessing the critical success factors in sustainable lean manufacturing&quot;, Decision <lb/>Analytics Journal, Vol. 6, 100157, doi: 10.1016/j.dajour.2022.100157. <lb/>Yang, J.J., Lo, H.W., Chao, C.S., Shen, C.C. and Yang, C.C. (2020), &quot;Establishing a sustainable sports <lb/>tourism evaluation framework with a hybrid multi-criteria decision-making model to explore <lb/>potential sports tourism attractions in taiwan&quot;, Sustainability (Switzerland), Vol. 12 No. 4, <lb/>pp. 1-20, doi: 10.3390/su12041673. <lb/></listBibl>

			    <front>Corresponding author <lb/>Sheak Salman can be contacted at: salman.ipe@aust.edu <lb/>For instructions on how to order reprints of this article, please visit our website: <lb/>www.emeraldgrouppublishing.com/licensing/reprints.htm <lb/>Or contact us for further details: permissions@emeraldinsight.com <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">IJIEOM <lb/>7,1 <lb/></note>

			<page>96 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from http://www.emerald.com/ijieom/article-pdf/7/1/68/9674929/ijieom-10-2023-0074.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 </note>


	</text>

</TEI>