<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Heliyon 10 (2024) e24150 <lb/>Available online 8 January 2024 <lb/>2405-8440/© 2024 The Authors. <lb/>Published by Elsevier Ltd. <lb/>This is an open access article under the CC BY license <lb/>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/>Research article <lb/>Finite element simulation of Soret-Dufour and conjugate heating <lb/>effects on mixed convective heat absorbing hydromagnetic Casson <lb/>fluid flow with suction/blowing from flat semi-infinite vertical <lb/>porous plate <lb/>B. Prabhakar Reddy * , Alijen Felician , P.M. Matao <lb/>Department of Mathematics and Statistics, The University of Dodoma, P. O. Box 338, Dodoma, Tanzania <lb/>A R T I C L E I N F O <lb/>Keywords: <lb/>Hydromagnetic <lb/>Suction/blowing <lb/>Porous medium <lb/>Chemical reaction <lb/>Conjugate heating <lb/>Soret-Dufour effect <lb/>A B S T R A C T <lb/>The finite element simulations of the Soret-Dufour and angled magnetic field effects on conjugate <lb/>heat and mass transportation of unsteady heat absorbing hydromagnetic Casson flow across a <lb/>semi-infinite flat oscillatory plate engrafted in a porous medium with suction/blowing, radiation <lb/>and chemical reaction is performed. The dimensionless coupled flow guiding nonlinear PDEs of <lb/>the physical structure is handled numerically by the dynamic Galerkin finite element scheme. The <lb/>demeanor of the velocity, concentration and the temperature profiles due to the alterations in the <lb/>regulating flow parameters are examined graphically whereas the wall-friction, mass and heat <lb/>transfer rates explicated by utilizing the tabular data. The research discovered that radiation; <lb/>conjugate heat transfer and diffusion thermo effects heighten the temperature and velocity dis-<lb/>tributions whereas heat absorption has a reverse effect. Likewise, conjugate mass transfer and <lb/>thermo-diffusion effects intensify the concentration and velocity distributions whereas the <lb/>chemical reaction display overturns aspect. Increased radiation absorption, inclined magnetic <lb/>field and porosity parameter stimulate fluid velocity whereas the Casson and magnetic parame-<lb/>ters exhibit the converse impact. In the instance of suction, the profiles of concentration, velocity <lb/>and temperature displayed a downturn nature but for the case of blowing, it was noticed a <lb/>reversal trend. Further, a comparative analysis between the current findings and existing research <lb/>works in the literature demonstrates our results are exact and accurate. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>The problem of magneto-hydrodynamic (MHD) Casson flow provides the groundwork for understanding the complexion of elec-<lb/>trically guiding non-Newtonian fluids in the incidence of magnetic fields. This particular type of fluid motion is encountered in various <lb/>industry and engineering contexts, such as chemical processing, biomedical engineering, and polymer manufacturing. The investi-<lb/>gation of MHD Casson flow dominance the significant importance in effective industrial processes and devising innovative technol-<lb/>ogies. Nonetheless, the complexity of the fluid dynamics involved makes it a formidable task, necessitating the use of advanced <lb/>mathematical and computational methods for modeling and analysis. The examination of MHD Casson liquid migration has earned <lb/>global attention due to its influential applications in the study of magnetic drug targeting, where magnetic fields are employed to guide <lb/></body>

			<front>* Corresponding author. <lb/>E-mail address: prabhakar.bijjula@gmail.com (B.P. Reddy). <lb/>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect <lb/>Heliyon <lb/>journal homepage: www.cell.com/heliyon <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e24150 <lb/>Received 26 August 2023; Received in revised form 1 January 2024; Accepted 4 January 2024 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Heliyon 10 (2024) e24150 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>drugs to specific areas of the body, and in the designing of magnetic pumps, which can move fluids without the need of physical contact <lb/>between the pump and the fluid, relying solely on magnetic fields. Keeping in mind all these utilizations, Krishna et al. [1] studied <lb/>reactive Casson fluid flow through a stretched porous sheet. Kataria and Patel [2] analyzed the heat and mass characteristics of MHD <lb/>Casson fluid in a porous channel via an oscillating upward plate. Makinde et al. [3] focused on energy transfer on a 2-D Casson fluid <lb/>passage due to the uppermost horizontal plate surface of a thermally stratified paraboloid revolution. An extensive research inves-<lb/>tigation was conducted on MHD Casson fluid transfer under diverse contexts by Refs. [4-9]. Subsequently, Asogwa and Ibe [10] <lb/>developed the MATLAB bvp4c solver to explore the domination of heat and mass transfer by the flow of MHD Casson fluid towards a <lb/>permeable stretching plane surface. Several other research studies [11-14] have specifically focused on the effects of radiation, <lb/>heat-source along with other physical parameters on the flow of MHD Casson fluid via the different porous surfaces. Very recently, <lb/>Investigations [15,16] discussed the behavior of Casson nanofluid under different circumstances through exponentially stretching and <lb/>bidirectional stretching surfaces. <lb/>The dominance of thermal radiation and chemical reactions in flow with MHD can lead to complex dynamics as these two phe-<lb/>nomena interact with each other. The behavior exhibited in such situations is highly dependent on specific conditions and parameters <lb/>of the flow, including the strength of the magnetic force, radiation intensity, and characteristics of the chemical reactions involved. <lb/>However, the flow of MHD radiative and reactive liquid extends to numerous influential appliances in engineering, sciences, and <lb/>industries, such as heat exchangers, irrigation pumps, cooling nuclear reactors, and food processing. Due to the specified significant <lb/>applications, researchers [17-26] elaborately analyzed the repercussions of chemical reaction and thermal radiation on MHD fluid <lb/>momentum by considering various fluids in a porous material under distinctive flow geometrics. Further, Suresh et al. [27] discussed <lb/>radiative and reactive MHD Casson fluid heat and mass transport characteristics via porous substance flowing along an exponentially <lb/>stretching sheet surface. Bejawada et al. [28] marked thermal radiation consequence in reactive MHD Casson liquid streaming over an <lb/>inclined non-linear surface. <lb/>When a fluid flows over a plate surface, frequently results in a temperature disparity between the fluid and the plate for multiple <lb/>reasons, including heat exchange with the surroundings, frictional heating, or chemical reactions. These kinds of temperature dif-<lb/>ferences lead to heat transfer along with the fluid and the plate, influencing both the flow and heat conduction properties of the <lb/>structure. This problem is commonly referred as the conjugate heating effect. This phenomenon finds momentous applications in <lb/>various scientific and engineering fields, including mechanics, aerospace, nuclear engineering, biology, and meteorology. Many <lb/>noteworthy investigations [29-36] scrutinized the aftermath of Newtonian heating (NH) on heat and mass transfer of radiating MHD <lb/>chemically reacting Casson fluid flowing through different porous materials. Mahato and Das [37] purposely examined the re-<lb/>percussions of conjugate heating aspect on unsteady Casson heat captivating and radiating fluid flowing over a semi-infinite flat porous <lb/>surface by considering chemical reaction, suction/blowing, inclined magnetic field. Afterwards, several studies [38-41] focused on an <lb/>exploration of Newtonian heating impact on magneto-hydrodynamic Casson flow by including various surface conditions. <lb/>The relationship between fluxes and driving materials grows more complicated while heat and mass transfer become obvious <lb/>simultaneously via MHD Casson fluid. The diffusion-thermo (Dufour) effect emerges from the concentration gradient and produces an <lb/>energy flux in addition to temperature gradients. Equivalently, the thermal-diffusion (Soret) effect expedites mass flux in response to <lb/>temperature gradients. Although, the Soret-Dufour effects are typically neglected in many heat and mass transfer examinations owing <lb/>to their smaller magnitude related to Fourier and Fick&apos;s laws. However, Soret-Dufour effects can play a decisive role in the fields such <lb/>as petrology, chemical engineering, geosciences, geothermal energy, and nuclear actor research. For instance, the Soret effect is <lb/>practiced in isotope severance between the mixtures with gases of different molecular weights. Several researchers [42-46] checked <lb/>the Soret-Dufour effects with other embedded parameters on the Casson unsteady fluid flowing via the vertical porous plate. Sub-<lb/>sequently, Bejawada and Yanala [47] employed the finite element technique to explore the impact of the Soret-Dufour effect on <lb/>unsteady MHD flow with heat and mass transportation from a quickened inclined vertical plate. The investigators [48,49] have <lb/>purposely investigated Dufour-Soret&apos;s influence on the mixed convection of magneto-hydrodynamic radiating and reacting Casson <lb/>fluid flowing through different media. Reddy et al. [50] investigated the sway of multiple slips, Dufour-Soret and suction/blowing <lb/>effects on MHD unsteady flow throughout a non-isothermal stretched surface. Prabhakar Reddy et al. [51] enforced the finite element <lb/>numerical procedure to highlight the effects of diffusion-thermal on the mixed convection reacting unsteady MHD Casson fluid in the <lb/>direction of an oscillating porous plate. Recently, Reddy et al. [52] utilized a numerical technique to prospect the combined persuade <lb/>of radiation and Soret-Dufour&apos;s parameters on natural convection MHD unsteady flow of Casson fluid via a semi-infinite vertical <lb/>porous surface. <lb/>The above scrupulous literature evaluation exposed that the problem of conjugate heat and mass transmute mixed convective <lb/>radiation absorption oscillatory hydro-magnetic flow of radiating Casson fluid across a flat semi-infinite surface entrenched in a porous <lb/>medium with an angled magnetic field, thermo-diffusion, heat absorption, chemical reaction and diffusion-thermo in the existence of <lb/>suction/blowing, no scientific study is yet conducted. However, this kind of research has significant usages in the chemical industry, <lb/>printing mechanization, polymer, mechanical filtering, pharmaceutical, textile, food manufacturing, drag-reducing agents, and <lb/>medical sciences and in the production of dumping accessories, etc. Because of these listed significant applications and the quintes-<lb/>sence of mixed convective heat absorbing hydro-magnetic oscillatory Casson fluid with conjugate heating effects, the main goal of the <lb/>authors in the ongoing study is to interpret the effects of inclined magnetic field, radiation absorption, thermo-diffusion, radiation and <lb/>diffusion-thermo on mixed convection chemically reacting hydro-magnetic Casson flow of heat absorptive fluid from the flat semi-<lb/>infinite porous oscillating plate with suction/blowing. This model problem has not been previously examined. Hence, our present <lb/>study is unique. The popular Galerkin finite element scheme is utilized to simulate the non-dimensional matched nonlinear PDEs of the <lb/>prospective physical model. This numerical technique coupled through the model which in epitome broadens the past work of Mahato <lb/>and Das [37] by incorporating the radiation absorption, Soret and Dufour effects including its paramount applications encompass the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">B.P. Reddy et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e24150 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>novelty of the current research. <lb/>2. Mathematical description <lb/>Consider a mixed convection 2D hydro-magnetic viscous, radiation absorption incompressible unsteady radiating Casson fluid flow <lb/>of electrically conducting, chemically reactive species through a flat semi-infinite vertical plate implanted in a porous media with <lb/>aspects of thermo-diffusion, heat absorption, diffusion-thermo, and suction/blowing. The characteristics of heat and mass transmit are <lb/>explained by the conjugate heat and mass transfer processes. Let x ′ -axis be aligned vertically with the plate surface, y ′ -axis is <lb/>perpendicular to it and z ′ -axis normal to plane x ′ y ′ as presented in Fig. 1. At t ′ = 0 the plate and fluid both are caught up with constant <lb/>temperature and concentration T ′ <lb/>∞ and C ′ <lb/>∞ , respectively. Subsequently, for t ′ &gt; 0, the plate instigate to oscillate in its own plane with <lb/>the velocity u = u 0 cos(ω&apos;t&apos;) + u 0 sin(ω&apos;t&apos;) oppositely the gravitational force. The Casson fluid&apos;s constitutive equation can be conveyed <lb/>following [10,37] as: <lb/>τ ij = <lb/>⎧ <lb/>⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎨ <lb/>⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎩ <lb/>2 <lb/>( <lb/>μ B + <lb/>p y <lb/>̅̅̅̅̅ <lb/>2π <lb/>√ <lb/>) <lb/>e ij when π &gt; π c , <lb/>2 <lb/>( <lb/>μ B + <lb/>p y <lb/>̅̅̅̅̅̅̅ <lb/>2π c <lb/>√ <lb/>) <lb/>e ij when π &lt; π c . <lb/>(1) <lb/>In the above Eq. (1), π = e ij e ij and e ij -indicates (i, j) th the rate of deformity component, π c -indicate the critical charge grounded on <lb/>the non-Newtonian model, π-indicate product of self deformation rate, and p y -indicate fluid&apos;s yield stress. <lb/>The following assumptions are made in the current inspection: <lb/>(i) A continuous magnetic field B = (B 0 cos γ, B 0 sin γ, 0) is enforced in y ′ -direction with an angle γ with y ′ &gt; 0. <lb/>(ii) The magnetic Reynolds number estimated to be paltry; hence the importance of the magnetic field infused by flow impetus is <lb/>ignored. <lb/>(iii) There is no externally sanctioned electric field, so that the response of polarization is overlooked. <lb/>(iv) The fluid flow is originated by the plate impulsive motion in x ′ -direction and due to the pores in the plate surface there is no <lb/>constant flow in y ′ -direction, hence the velocity vector is given by q = (u ′ , -υ 0 , 0). <lb/>By the foregoing assumptions, in addition to the usual Boussinesq&apos;s approximation, the set of flow regulating coupled PDEs of <lb/>physical phenomena with initial and boundary conditions following [37,47] derived as; <lb/>∂u ′ <lb/>∂t ′ -υ 0 <lb/>∂u ′ <lb/>∂y ′ = ν <lb/>( <lb/>1 <lb/>β <lb/>+ 1 <lb/>) <lb/>∂ 2 u ′ <lb/>∂y ′ 2 -<lb/>σB 2 <lb/>0 cos 2 γ <lb/>ρ <lb/>u ′ -ν <lb/>( <lb/>1 <lb/>β <lb/>+ 1 <lb/>) <lb/>u ′ <lb/>K ′ <lb/>+gβ T ( <lb/>T ′ -T ′ <lb/>∞ <lb/>) <lb/>+ gβ C ( <lb/>C ′ -C ′ <lb/>∞ <lb/>) <lb/>, <lb/>(2) <lb/>∂T ′ <lb/>∂t ′ -υ 0 <lb/>∂T ′ <lb/>∂y ′ = <lb/>k <lb/>ρc p <lb/>∂ 2 T ′ <lb/>∂y ′ 2 -<lb/>Q 0 <lb/>ρc p <lb/>( <lb/>T ′ -T ′ <lb/>∞ <lb/>) <lb/>+ <lb/>Q 1 <lb/>ρc p <lb/>( <lb/>C ′ -C ′ <lb/>∞ <lb/>) <lb/>-<lb/>1 <lb/>ρc p <lb/>∂q r <lb/>∂y ′ + <lb/>D m K T <lb/>c p c s <lb/>( <lb/>∂ 2 C ′ <lb/>∂y ′ 2 <lb/>) <lb/>, <lb/>(3) <lb/>Fig. 1. Flow geometry. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">B.P. Reddy et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e24150 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>∂C ′ <lb/>∂t ′ -υ 0 <lb/>∂C ′ <lb/>∂y ′ = D m <lb/>∂ 2 C ′ <lb/>∂y ′ 2 -k ′ <lb/>c <lb/>( <lb/>C ′ -C ′ <lb/>∞ <lb/>) <lb/>+ <lb/>D m K T <lb/>T m <lb/>( <lb/>∂ 2 T ′ <lb/>∂y ′ 2 <lb/>) <lb/>. <lb/>(4) <lb/>and <lb/>u ′ = 0, T ′ = T ′ <lb/>∞ , C ′ = C ′ <lb/>∞ <lb/>for y ′ ≥ 0 and t ′ ≤ 0, <lb/>u ′ = u 0 cos(ω&apos;t&apos;) + u 0 sin(ω&apos;t&apos;), <lb/>∂T ′ <lb/>∂y ′ = -h 1 T ′ , <lb/>∂C ′ <lb/>∂y ′ = -h 2 C ′ at y ′ = 0 for t ′ &gt; 0, <lb/>u ′ →0, T ′ →T ′ <lb/>∞ , C ′ →C ′ <lb/>∞ <lb/>as y ′ →∞for t ′ &gt; 0. <lb/>⎫ <lb/>⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎬ <lb/>⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎭ <lb/>(5) <lb/>here, ν, β, T ′ , σ, K ′ , g, ρ, β T , u ′ , t ′ , υ 0 , T ′ <lb/>∞ , y ′ , β C , C ′ , C ′ <lb/>∞ , k, u 0 , c p , Q 0 , Q 1 , q r , D m , K T , c s , k ′ <lb/>c , T m , h 1 , ωt, h 2 , and B 0 , respectively indicates the ki-<lb/>nematic viscosity, Casson parameter, fluid temperature, electrical conductivity, medium permeability, gravitational force, fluid <lb/>density, thermal extension coefficient, fluid&apos;s velocity, time, fluid viscosity, fluid temperature distantly from the plate, span-wise <lb/>coordinate, concentration extension coefficient, fluid&apos;s concentration, fluid concentration distantly from the plate, thermal conduc-<lb/>tivity, amplitude of the plate, specific heat at steady pressure, heat absorption, radiation absorption, radiation heat flux, molecular <lb/>diffusivity, thermo-diffusion ratio, concentration susceptibility, chemical reaction constant, mean value temperature, heat transfer <lb/>coefficient, phase angle, mass transfer coefficient and the magnetic field intensity. <lb/>With the assumption that fluid&apos;s temperature is linearly related to thermal conductivity, then the radiation flux vector q r in <lb/>Equation (3) can be written by following Rosseland approximation [53] as: <lb/>q r = -<lb/>4σ s <lb/>3A m <lb/>∂T &apos; 4 <lb/>∂y &apos; <lb/>(6) <lb/>here, A m and σ s are indicate respectively, the mean absorptive and Stephen Boltzmann constants. We presume that the temperature <lb/>changes inside the flow allow us to expand T ′ 4 by engaging the Taylor series expansion about T ′ <lb/>∞ , upon overlooking higher order terms <lb/>(i.e., from 2nd order terms), bring about; <lb/>T ′ 4 <lb/>≅ 4T ′ 3 <lb/>∞ T ′ -3T ′ 4 <lb/>∞ <lb/>(7) <lb/>After using Eqs. (6) and (7) into Eq. (3), results <lb/>∂T ′ <lb/>∂t ′ -υ 0 <lb/>∂T ′ <lb/>∂y ′ = <lb/>k <lb/>ρc p <lb/>∂ 2 T ′ <lb/>∂y ′ 2 -<lb/>Q 0 <lb/>ρc p <lb/>( <lb/>T ′ -T ′ <lb/>∞ <lb/>) <lb/>+ <lb/>Q 1 <lb/>ρc p <lb/>( <lb/>C ′ -C ′ <lb/>∞ <lb/>) <lb/>+ <lb/>16σ s T ′ 3 <lb/>∞ <lb/>3ρc p A m <lb/>( <lb/>∂ 2 T ′ <lb/>∂y ′ 2 <lb/>) <lb/>+ <lb/>D m K T <lb/>c p c s <lb/>( <lb/>∂ 2 C ′ <lb/>∂y ′ 2 <lb/>) <lb/>(8) <lb/>We define the following dimensionless variables and parameters: <lb/>ξ = y &apos; u 0 <lb/>ν <lb/>, u = <lb/>u &apos; <lb/>u 0 <lb/>, t = t &apos; u 2 <lb/>0 <lb/>ν <lb/>, θ = <lb/>T &apos; -T &apos; <lb/>∞ <lb/>T &apos; <lb/>∞ <lb/>, S = <lb/>υ 0 <lb/>u 0 <lb/>, K c = <lb/>k c <lb/>u 2 <lb/>0 <lb/>, γ 1 = <lb/>h 1 ν <lb/>u 0 <lb/>, <lb/>M = <lb/>σB 2 <lb/>1 ν <lb/>ρu 2 <lb/>0 <lb/>, G r = <lb/>ρβ T νT &apos; <lb/>∞ <lb/>u 3 <lb/>0 <lb/>, G m = <lb/>ρβ C νC &apos; <lb/>∞ <lb/>u 3 <lb/>0 <lb/>, P r = <lb/>ρνc p <lb/>k <lb/>, ω = ω &apos; ν <lb/>u 2 <lb/>0 <lb/>, <lb/>K = K &apos; u 2 <lb/>0 <lb/>ν 2 , S c = <lb/>ν <lb/>D m <lb/>, φ 1 = <lb/>νQ 0 <lb/>ρc p u 2 <lb/>0 <lb/>, φ 2 = <lb/>νQ 1 C &apos; <lb/>∞ <lb/>ρc p u 2 <lb/>0 T &apos; <lb/>∞ <lb/>, N r = <lb/>16σ s T &apos; <lb/>∞ <lb/>3kA m <lb/>, <lb/>C = <lb/>C &apos; -C &apos; <lb/>∞ <lb/>C &apos; <lb/>∞ <lb/>, D u = <lb/>K T D m C &apos; <lb/>∞ <lb/>c p c s νT &apos; <lb/>∞ <lb/>, S r = <lb/>K T D m T &apos; <lb/>∞ <lb/>T m νC &apos; <lb/>∞ <lb/>, γ 2 = <lb/>h 2 ν <lb/>u 0 <lb/>. <lb/>⎫ <lb/>⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎬ <lb/>⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎭ <lb/>(9) <lb/>Submitting Eq. (9), into Equations (2), (4), (5) and (8) designate into the following dimensionless nonlinear PDEs of the stated flow <lb/>with initial and boundary specifies: <lb/>∂u <lb/>∂t <lb/>-S <lb/>∂u <lb/>∂ξ <lb/>= <lb/>( <lb/>1 <lb/>β <lb/>+ 1 <lb/>) <lb/>∂ 2 u <lb/>∂ξ 2 -<lb/>[ <lb/>M cos 2 γ + <lb/>( <lb/>1 <lb/>β <lb/>+ 1 <lb/>) <lb/>1 <lb/>K <lb/>] <lb/>u + G r θ + G m C, <lb/>(10) <lb/>∂θ <lb/>∂t <lb/>-S <lb/>∂θ <lb/>∂ξ <lb/>= <lb/>( <lb/>1 + N r <lb/>P r <lb/>) <lb/>∂ 2 θ <lb/>∂ξ 2 -φ 1 θ + φ 2 C + D u <lb/>( <lb/>∂ 2 C <lb/>∂ξ 2 <lb/>) <lb/>, <lb/>(11) <lb/>∂C <lb/>∂t <lb/>-S <lb/>∂C <lb/>∂ξ <lb/>= <lb/>1 <lb/>S c <lb/>∂ 2 C <lb/>∂ξ 2 -K c C + S r <lb/>( <lb/>∂ 2 θ <lb/>∂ξ 2 <lb/>) <lb/>. <lb/>(12) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">B.P. Reddy et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e24150 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>and <lb/>u = 0, θ = 0, C = 0 for all ξ ≥ 0 and t ≤ 0, <lb/>u = cos(ωt) + sin(ωt), <lb/>∂θ <lb/>∂ξ <lb/>= -γ 1 (θ + 1), <lb/>∂C <lb/>∂ξ <lb/>= -γ 2 (C + 1) at ξ = 0 and t &gt; 0, <lb/>u→0, θ→0, C→0 for ξ→∞and t &gt; 0. <lb/>⎫ <lb/>⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎬ <lb/>⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎭ <lb/>(13) <lb/>here, t, S, N r , β, u, M, C, φ 1 , K, G r , S c , ξ, θ, γ, G m , P r , φ 2 , D u , K c and S r respectively, indicates the dimensionless time, suction/blowing, <lb/>radiation parameter, Casson parameter, fluid velocity, magnetic parameter, fluid concentration, heat absorption parameter, porosity <lb/>parameter, thermal Grashof number, Schmidt number, dimensionless space coordinate, fluid temperature, magnetic field inclination <lb/>angle, mass Grashof number, Prandtl number, radiation absorption parameter, Dufour parameter, chemical reaction parameter, and <lb/>the Soret parameter. <lb/>The engineering depiction of quantities of physical significance in the dimensionless form at the plate defined by <lb/>Skin friction τ = -<lb/>( <lb/>1 <lb/>β + 1 <lb/>)( <lb/>∂u <lb/>∂ξ <lb/>) <lb/>ξ=0 <lb/>, <lb/>Heat transfer rate (Nusselt number) N u = -(1 + N r ) <lb/>( <lb/>∂θ <lb/>∂ξ <lb/>) <lb/>ξ=0 <lb/>, <lb/>Table 1 <lb/>In the limiting case, comparison of the skin-friction τ. <lb/>Pr <lb/>Gr <lb/>γ 1 <lb/>wt <lb/>t <lb/>Das et al. [29] <lb/>Mahato and Das [37] <lb/>FEM results <lb/>0.35 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>5.5818 <lb/>5.5812 <lb/>5.581810 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>5.5956 <lb/>5.5956 <lb/>5.595609 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>10 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>5.5218 <lb/>5.5205 <lb/>5.521825 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>5 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>5.5027 <lb/>5.5011 <lb/>5.502510 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 <lb/>π/2 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>4.4819 <lb/>4.4819 <lb/>4.481989 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>3.8620 <lb/>3.8606 <lb/>3.862071 <lb/>Table 2 <lb/>Comparison of the Nusselt number N u . <lb/>Pr <lb/>Nr <lb/>φ 1 <lb/>γ 1 <lb/>t <lb/>Mahato and Das [37] <lb/>FEM results <lb/>Nu (Suction) <lb/>Nu (Blowing) <lb/>Nu (Suction) <lb/>Nu (Blowing) <lb/>0.71 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.72883814 <lb/>0.63247729 <lb/>0.72883814 <lb/>0.63247729 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.84550858 <lb/>0.69516014 <lb/>0.84550858 <lb/>0.69516014 <lb/>0.71 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.62712616 <lb/>0.57424226 <lb/>0.62712616 <lb/>0.57424226 <lb/>0.71 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.73544219 <lb/>0.63686326 <lb/>0.73544219 <lb/>0.63686326 <lb/>0.71 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.82210603 <lb/>0.75708048 <lb/>0.82210603 <lb/>0.75708048 <lb/>0.71 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.78847861 <lb/>0.69038286 <lb/>0.78847861 <lb/>0.69038286 <lb/>Fig. 2. The consequence of N r on velocity distribution vs ξ. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">B.P. Reddy et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e24150 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Mass transfer rate (Sherwood number) S h = -<lb/>( <lb/>∂C <lb/>∂ξ <lb/>) <lb/>ξ=0 <lb/>. <lb/>3. Numerical technique <lb/>This article section discusses the development and implementation of the Galerkin finite element scheme on a non-linear system of <lb/>three linked PDEs (10)-(12), conjointly with initial and boundary conditions Eq. (13) that describes the proposed physical phe-<lb/>nomenon. The numerical method presented here has a broad range of applications and can be effectively implemented to solve various <lb/>complex problems in the fields of biomechanics, metallurgical transport exercises, mixed convection micro-polar heat transfer <lb/>problems, third-grade visco-elastic hydrodynamics, magneto-biofluid dynamics, etc. Implementation of the Galerkin finite element <lb/>scheme on Eqs. (10)-(12) over the two-node linear element (e), (ξ j ≤ ξ ≤ ξ k ) leads to the following equations: <lb/>∫ ξ k <lb/>ξ j <lb/>ψ (e) T <lb/>[( <lb/>1 + <lb/>1 <lb/>β <lb/>) <lb/>∂ 2 u (e) <lb/>∂ξ 2 -<lb/>∂u (e) <lb/>∂t <lb/>+ S <lb/>∂u (e) <lb/>∂ξ <lb/>-Δ 1 u (e) + Δ 2 <lb/>] <lb/>dξ = 0, <lb/>(14) <lb/>∫ ξ k <lb/>ξ j <lb/>ψ (e) T <lb/>[ ( <lb/>1 + N r <lb/>P r <lb/>) <lb/>∂ 2 θ (e) <lb/>∂ξ 2 -<lb/>∂θ (e) <lb/>∂t <lb/>+ S <lb/>∂θ (e) <lb/>∂ξ <lb/>-φ 1 θ (e) + φ 2 C + D u <lb/>( <lb/>∂ 2 C <lb/>∂ξ 2 <lb/>) ] <lb/>dξ = 0, <lb/>(15) <lb/>Fig. 3. The consequence of N r on temperature distribution vs ξ. <lb/>Fig. 4. The consequence of D u on velocity distribution vs ξ. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">B.P. Reddy et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e24150 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>∫ ξ k <lb/>ξ j <lb/>ψ (e) T <lb/>[( <lb/>1 <lb/>S c <lb/>) <lb/>∂ 2 C (e) <lb/>∂ξ 2 -<lb/>∂C (e) <lb/>∂t <lb/>+ S <lb/>∂C (e) <lb/>∂ξ <lb/>-K c C (e) + S r <lb/>( <lb/>∂ 2 θ <lb/>∂ξ 2 <lb/>)] <lb/>dξ = 0, <lb/>(16) <lb/>where Δ 1 = M cos 2 γ + <lb/>( <lb/>1 + 1 <lb/>β <lb/>) ( 1 <lb/>K <lb/>) <lb/>, Δ 2 = G r θ + G m C, and ψ (e) = <lb/>[ <lb/>ψ j ψ k <lb/>] <lb/>. <lb/>In order to lower the order of integration and nonlinearity in above equations; after applying the integration process in Eqs. (14)-<lb/>(16), we obtain the following equations; <lb/>∫ ξ k <lb/>ξ j <lb/>[ ( <lb/>1 + <lb/>1 <lb/>β <lb/>) <lb/>∂ψ (e) T <lb/>∂ξ <lb/>∂u (e) <lb/>∂ξ <lb/>+ ψ (e) T <lb/>( <lb/>∂u (e) <lb/>∂t <lb/>-S <lb/>∂u (e) <lb/>∂ξ <lb/>+ Δ 1 u (e) -Δ 2 <lb/>) ] <lb/>dξ -<lb/>[ ( <lb/>ψ (e) T ) ∂u (e) <lb/>∂ξ <lb/>] ξ k <lb/>ξ j <lb/>= 0, <lb/>(17) <lb/>∫ ξ k <lb/>ξ j <lb/>[ ( <lb/>1 + N r <lb/>P r <lb/>) <lb/>∂ψ (e) T <lb/>∂ξ <lb/>∂θ (e) <lb/>∂ξ <lb/>+ ψ (e) T <lb/>( <lb/>∂θ (e) <lb/>∂t <lb/>-S <lb/>∂θ (e) <lb/>∂η <lb/>+ φ 1 θ (e) -φ 2 C -D u <lb/>( <lb/>∂ 2 C <lb/>∂ξ 2 <lb/>) )] <lb/>dξ -<lb/>[ ( <lb/>ψ (e) T ) ∂θ (e) <lb/>∂ξ <lb/>] ξ k <lb/>ξ j <lb/>= 0, <lb/>(18) <lb/>Fig. 5. The consequence of D u on temperature distribution vs ξ. <lb/>Fig. 6. The consequence of φ 1 on velocity distribution vs ξ. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">B.P. Reddy et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e24150 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 7. The consequence of φ 1 on temperature distribution vs ξ. <lb/>Fig. 8. The consequence of γ 1 on velocity distribution vs ξ. <lb/>Fig. 9. The consequence of γ 1 on temperature distribution vs ξ. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">B.P. Reddy et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e24150 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>∫ ξ k <lb/>ξ j <lb/>[ ( <lb/>1 <lb/>S c <lb/>) <lb/>∂ψ (e) T <lb/>∂ξ <lb/>∂C (e) <lb/>∂ξ <lb/>+ ψ (e) T <lb/>( <lb/>∂C (e) <lb/>∂t <lb/>-S <lb/>∂C (e) <lb/>∂ξ <lb/>+ K c C (e) -S r <lb/>( <lb/>∂ 2 θ <lb/>∂ξ 2 <lb/>)) ] <lb/>dξ -<lb/>[ ( <lb/>ψ (e) T ) ∂C (e) <lb/>∂ξ <lb/>]ξ k <lb/>ξ j <lb/>= 0. <lb/>(19) <lb/>We use finite element approximation to formulate the finite element model from Eqs. (17)-(19) over the typical e th element <lb/>(e), (ξ j ≤ ξ ≤ ξ k ) is of the form; <lb/>u (e) = ψ j u j + ψ k u k , <lb/>(20) <lb/>θ (e) = ψ j θ j + ψ k θ k , <lb/>(21) <lb/>C (e) = ψ j C j + ψ k C k <lb/>(22) <lb/>where u j , u k , θ j , θ k , C j and C k <lb/>′ s indicates, respectively the velocity, temperature and the concentration components at j th and k th nodes of <lb/>the e th element (ξ j ≤ ξ ≤ ξ k ), ψ j and ψ k are the shape functions over the e th element (ξ j ≤ ξ ≤ ξ k ), described as; <lb/>ψ j = <lb/>ξ k -ξ <lb/>ξ k -ξ j <lb/>and ψ k = <lb/>ξ -ξ j <lb/>ξ k -ξ j <lb/>(23) <lb/>Substituting Eqs. (20)-(22) into Eqs. (17)-(19) with the help of Eq. (23) and use of the boundary conditions (13), after gathering <lb/>Fig. 10. The consequence φ 2 on velocity distribution vs ξ. <lb/>Fig. 11. The consequence of φ 2 on temperature distribution vs ξ. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">B.P. Reddy et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e24150 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>element equations for all elements by inter connectivity rule, results in the following tri-diagonal form of matrix system; <lb/>Pu = P ′ <lb/>Qθ = Q ′ <lb/>RC = R ′ <lb/>(24) <lb/>where P, Q and R specify matrices of order n and u, θ, C, P&apos;Q&apos; and R ′ represents column matrices having n components. The above matrix <lb/>system of Eq. (24) can be simplified successfully by the Gauss-Seidel iteration scheme. Our main intention is to get the converged <lb/>solution. For this, care has been taken in selecting mesh dimensions in space ξ-direction and time t-direction. Keeping the mesh <lb/>length fixed at 0.001 in time t-direction, the developed finite element code was run with distinct mesh lengths 0.01, 0.02 and 0.05 in <lb/>space ξ-direction. In this experiment, we do not find any convincing changed values in u, θ and C. This exercise authenticates the <lb/>solutions are mesh independent. Furthermore, the solution is expected to be converges at any time; the comparative deviation amidst <lb/>two successive iterations arrives at a specific value, i.e., the iterative operation is terminated when the condition <lb/>⃒ <lb/>⃒ <lb/>⃒f m+1 <lb/>i <lb/>-f m <lb/>i <lb/>⃒ <lb/>⃒ <lb/>⃒ &lt; 10 -6 is <lb/>satisfied, where f = u, θ, C and m indicates the iterative step. This condition preserves the high accuracy in solving the multi-physical <lb/>coupled boundary layer equations. <lb/>4. Validation <lb/>Tables 1 and 2 revealed the comparison of our results captured by the Galerkin finite element scheme by considering skin friction τ <lb/>Fig. 12. The consequence of γ 2 on velocity distribution vs ξ. <lb/>Fig. 13. The consequence of γ 2 on concentration distribution vs ξ. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">B.P. Reddy et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e24150 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>in the limiting case and Nusselt number N u with available results from the literature. We clearly point out in the limiting case from <lb/>Table 1 that when G m = 0, β→∞, D u = 0, M = 0, φ 2 = 0, S = 0, K→∞ and γ = 0, the numerical values of τ computed by us is precisely <lb/>matched with the results of Das et al. [29] and Mahato and Das [37] computed by the Laplace Transform Technique. Also, it is much <lb/>apparent from Table 2 that the numerical values of N u computed by us when D u = 0 and φ 2 = 0 are exalted matching. Therefore, our <lb/>current results are exactitude and accurate. <lb/>5. Results analysis <lb/>In this section, we have provided the graphical and tabular representations to demonstrate the features of fluid temperature, <lb/>concentration, velocity profiles and skin friction, mass and heat transfer rates for the suction and blowing cases due to the di-<lb/>versifications of the flow predominant parameters acting as the magnetic parameter M, energy absorption parameter φ 1 , Dufour <lb/>parameter D u , conjugate heat transfer parameter γ 1 , radiation absorption parameter φ 2 , magnetic field inclination angle γ, chemical <lb/>reaction parameter K c , porosity parameter K, conjugate mass transfer parameter γ 2 , Soret parameter S r , Casson parameter β, phase <lb/>angle ωt, suction/blowing parameter S, and radiation parameter N r . Numerical computations were executed using definite constant <lb/>values of the pertinent parameters, which apply all graphs and tables except for stated otherwise; N r = 2, M = 2, D u = 0.5, φ 1 = 3, K = <lb/>0.5, γ 1 = 0.5, S r = 2, β = 0.5, P r = 0.71, K c = 2, φ 2 = 1, γ 2 = 0.5, S c = 0.6, ωt = π/3 and γ = π/6. <lb/>The profiles of velocity and temperature due to the dissimilarity of radiation parameter N r are described respectively, in Figs. 2 and <lb/>3. It is clear that rising N r assist to broaden the velocity and temperature distributions. Physically, increasing N r values is the source to <lb/>Fig. 14. The consequence of S r on the velocity distribution vs ξ. <lb/>Fig. 15. The consequence of S r on concentration distribution vs ξ. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">B.P. Reddy et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e24150 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>enlarge temperature boundary layer results in an enrichment of fluid temperature, consequently raise the fluid momentum. Figs. 4 and <lb/>5 plotted to scrutinize the transmutation of the velocity and temperature owing to the Dufour number D u , respectively. It is remarked <lb/>from these plots that, as we enlarge the Dufour number, the fluid velocity and temperature goes up. Physically, the Dufour number D u <lb/>in the energy (heat) conserving equation indicates that the heat flux arising by a concentration gradient. As we increase D u values <lb/>boosts transmission of heat in the boundary layer through the concentration gradient results into maximize the thermal boundary layer <lb/>thickness consequently upsurge the fluid velocity. The alterations of the profiles of velocity and temperature for compounding heat <lb/>absorption parameter φ 1 values are engraved in Figs. 6 and 7, respectively. One can see that the velocity and temperature both de-<lb/>creases by increasing heat absorption parameter. This is fact in virtue of the bigger values of φ 1 lessen the temperature of the plate <lb/>surface indebted to reduce fluid temperature eventually downturn is noted in the fluid velocity. Figs. 8 and 9, respectively exhibits the <lb/>graphical explanation of the effect of conjugate heat transfer parameter γ 1 on the profiles of velocity and temperature. From these <lb/>figures, we observe that both fluid momentum and temperature enlarges with growing values of γ 1 . This fact occurs when increasing <lb/>values of γ 1 implies higher heat transfer rate between the fluid and plate turn into enhance the fluid temperature, consequently hasten <lb/>the fluid motion. The consequence of the radiation absorption parameter φ 2 on the profiles of velocity and temperature is analyzed <lb/>respectively, in Figs. 10 and 11, and increasing effect is noticed in the profiles of the velocity and temperature. The variation of both the <lb/>velocity and concentration against the alteration of conjugate mass transfer γ 2 has been illustrated, respectively in Figs. 12 and 13. <lb/>These figures signify that increased values of γ 2 leads to significantly intensify the fluid velocity and concentration. This is because of <lb/>larger values of γ 2 , there is a greater rate of mass transfer between adjacent layers convert into raise the concentration species ulti-<lb/>mately speed up fluid flow. Figs. 14 and 15 respectively, display the variance of the fluid velocity and concentration due to disparity in <lb/>the Soret parameter S r . We can see that there is an upsurge in both flow velocity and concentration with increment in the values of S r . <lb/>Fig. 16. The consequence of K c on velocity distribution vs ξ. <lb/>Fig. 17. The consequence of K c on concentration distribution vs ξ. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">B.P. Reddy et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e24150 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Physically, the (Soret) thermo-diffusion impact stimulate diffusion of solute in the boundary layer through thermal gradient. There-<lb/>fore, enlarging S r values improve notably the concentration boundary layer thickness results marked improvement in the fluid con-<lb/>centration, ultimately heighten the fluid velocity. The fallout of chemical reaction parameter K c on the profiles of the velocity and <lb/>species concentration is engraved in Figs. 16 and 17, respectively. It is captured from these graphs that there is a down trend in both <lb/>velocity and concentration profiles. Physically, snowballing values of K c , causes more species demolished through the chemical re-<lb/>action results in a decrement of concentration boundary layer, eventually deplete momentum boundary layer thickness. Fig. 18 es-<lb/>tablishes the fluctuation of the profiles of velocity with heightening the Casson parameter β. It is perceived that there is a diminution in <lb/>the fluid velocity as the values of β escalate. This is attributed to the reality that bigger values of β implies that the plasticity of the fluid <lb/>enlarge, finally flow with diminutive velocity. The demesne of magnetic field strength M on the profiles of the velocity is observed in <lb/>Fig. 19. This graph demonstrates that the fluid flowing with a small velocity by accumulating values of M this outcome is physically <lb/>acceptable. Because of the enlarging values of M outgrowth a Lorenz force that works adverse to the flow path, in due time we see a <lb/>deterioration in the fluid flow. The deviation of the profiles of velocity is ascertained in Fig. 20 for diverge permeability parameter K <lb/>values. We can see from this plot that flow velocity is heighten with swelling values of K due to the diminution in the refusal of the <lb/>porous medium. Fig. 21 describes the variation of the velocity profiles for dissimilar angled magnetic field γ This depiction exposed <lb/>that; as we increase in the angled magnetic field γ values, accelerate the flow momentum. This signifies that when imposed magnetic <lb/>force works on the back of the direction of the flow, then the magnitude of the Lorentz&apos;s force become paramount, convincingly get <lb/>better fluid motion. The pattern of the velocity profiles in contrast to the phase angle ωt for the distinct angles is illustrated in Fig. 22. <lb/>This graph indicate that the velocity profiles lowering for increasing ωt Figs. 23-25 are depicted to review the profiles of velocity, <lb/>Fig. 18. The consequence of β on velocity distribution vs ξ. <lb/>Fig. 19. The consequence of M on velocity distribution vs ξ. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">B.P. Reddy et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e24150 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>temperature and concentration due to the alteration in the suction/blowing parameter. We observe from these graphs that the <lb/>functioning of suction scale down the size of velocity, energy and concentration boundary layer related to the lowering profiles of <lb/>momentum, temperature and concentration whereas contrary nature is identified for blowing. Because effective blowing always di-<lb/>minishes the wall shear stress and friction drag. <lb/>5.1. Skin-friction, Nusselt and Sherwood number <lb/>The numerical variance in the skin-friction (τ), Nusselt number (N u ) and the Sherwood number (S h ) on account of variation in the <lb/>flow regulating parameters are showcased, respectively in Tables 3-5. We observe from Table 3 that in the instances of suction and <lb/>blowing, both the skin friction and Nusselt number heighten with advancing φ 1 and γ 1 values whereas there is a downturn is noted with <lb/>increasing values of N r , D u , φ 2 and t. Table 4 exposed that the skin friction and Sherwood number escalates by strengthening values of <lb/>K c and γ 2 whereas deterioration is acclaimed in both skin friction and Sherwood number because of higher S r values for both suction <lb/>and blowing. We noted from Table 5 that for both actions of suction and blowing, the skin friction rises with enlargement of β and M <lb/>values whereas a reversal trend is noted with K, γ, and ωt values. <lb/>6. Conclusion <lb/>In the current study, the inclined magnetic field, thermal radiation, suction/blowing and Soret-Dufour aspects on chemically <lb/>reactive unsteady mixed convection Casson heat absorbing hydro-magnetic oscillatory flow in a flat semi-infinite vertical porous plate <lb/>Fig. 20. The consequence of K on velocity distribution vs ξ. <lb/>Fig. 21. The consequence of γ on velocity distribution vs ξ. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">B.P. Reddy et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e24150 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>considering conjugate heating conditions at the boundary is numerically analyzed. The most important findings of the analysis follow: <lb/>(i) The velocity profiles speed up with increased N r , D u , φ 2 , S r , K and γ values whereas there is a drop in the velocity profiles with <lb/>enlarged φ 1 , K c , β, and M values for suction and blowing cases. At the same time skin friction behaves contrary to the velocity. <lb/>(ii) The fluid velocity and skin-friction both enhanced with increasing γ 1 and γ 2 , whereas we noticed a downturn with increasing ωt. <lb/>(iii) The fluid temperature is heightened while increasing N r , D u , and φ 2 whereas the Nusselt number act upon reversely. <lb/>(iv) An increase in φ 1 entails decrease of fluid temperature whereas Nusselt number shown opposite tendency. <lb/>(v) The fluid temperature and Nusselt number both advance on the rise γ 1 . <lb/>(vi) The species concentration drained with rising K c whereas reverse behavior is noticed with surging S r . At the same time Sher-<lb/>wood number act upon oppositely. <lb/>(vii) The species concentration and Sherwood number both strengthen with increased γ 2 . <lb/></body>

            <div type="availability">Data availability <lb/>The data used to backing the findings of the study are available within the article. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">CRediT authorship contribution statement <lb/>B. Prabhakar Reddy: Writing -review &amp; editing, Writing -original draft, Validation, Software, Methodology, Investigation, <lb/></div>

            <body>Fig. 22. The consequence of ωt on velocity distribution vs ξ. <lb/>Fig. 23. The consequence of S on velocity distribution vs ξ. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">B.P. Reddy et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e24150 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Formal analysis, Data curation, Conceptualization. Alijen Felician: Writing -review &amp; editing, Writing -original draft, Validation, <lb/>Software, Methodology, Investigation, Conceptualization. P.M. Matao: Visualization, Supervision, Software, Methodology, Investi-<lb/>gation, Formal analysis, Data curation, Conceptualization. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Declaration of competing interest <lb/>The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing <lb/></div>

            <body>Fig. 24. The consequence of S on temperature distribution vs ξ. <lb/>Fig. 25. The consequences of S on concentration distribution vs ξ. <lb/>Table 3 <lb/>Numerical computation of τ and N u . <lb/>Du <lb/>φ 1 <lb/>γ 1 <lb/>φ 2 <lb/>t <lb/>Nusselt number (Nu) <lb/>Skin friction (τ) <lb/>Suction <lb/>Blowing <lb/>Suction <lb/>Blowing <lb/>2 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.003890 <lb/>0.952996 <lb/>3.859158 <lb/>4.191651 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.960982 <lb/>0.886865 <lb/>3.683712 <lb/>3.873519 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.903870 <lb/>0.911867 <lb/>3.771378 <lb/>4.059261 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.201208 <lb/>0.984515 <lb/>3.962226 <lb/>4.443930 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.407576 <lb/>1.257315 <lb/>4.595818 <lb/>4.642894 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.955938 <lb/>0.932151 <lb/>3.663168 <lb/>3.740247 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.917408 <lb/>0.835422 <lb/>3.186366 <lb/>4.054095 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">B.P. Reddy et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e24150 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">interests:B. Prabhakar Reddy reports administrative support was provided by The University of Dodoma. B. Prabhakar Reddy reports a <lb/>relationship with The University of Dodoma that includes: employment. The authors declare that they have no known competing <lb/>financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper. If there are other <lb/>authors, they declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to <lb/>influence the work reported in this paper. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] Y. Hari Krishna, G.V.R. Reddy, O.D. Makinde, Chemical reaction effect on MHD flow of Casson fluid with porous stretching sheet, Defect Diffusion Forum 389 <lb/>(2018) 100-109. <lb/>[2] H. Kataria, H. Patel, Heat and mass transfer in magneto-hydrodynamic (MHD) Casson fluid flow past over an oscillating vertical plate embedded in a porous <lb/>medium with ramped wall temperature, Propuls. Power Res. 7 (3) (2018) 257-267. <lb/>[3] O.D. Makinde, N. Sandeep, T.M. Ajayi, I.L. Animasaun, Numerical exploration of heat transfer and Lorentz force effects on the flow of MHD Casson fluid over an <lb/>upper horizontal surface of a thermally stratified melting surface of a paraboloid of revolution, Int. J. Nonlinear Sci. Numer. Stimul. 19 (2) (2018) 93-106. <lb/>[4] K.V. Prasad, K. Vajravelu, H. Vaidya, N.Z. Basha, V. Umesh, Thermal and species concentration of MHD Casson fluid at a vertical sheet in the presence of <lb/>variable fluid properties, Ain Shams Eng. J. 9 (4) (2018) 1763-1779. <lb/>[5] G.S. Seth, R. Kumar, R. Tripathi, A. Bhattacharyya, Double diffusive MHD Casson fluid flow in a non-Darcy porous medium with Newtonian heating and thermo-<lb/>diffusion effects, Int. J. Heat Technol. 36 (4) (2018) 1517-1527. <lb/>[6] G.S. Seth, P.K. Mandal, The hydro-magnetic rotating flow of Casson fluid in Darcy-Forchheimer porous medium, in: MATEC Web of Conferences, vol. 192, 2018 <lb/>02059. <lb/>[7] G.B. Prakash, G.R. Reddy, W. Sridhar, Y.H. Krishna, B. Mahaboob, Thermal radiation and heat source effects on MHD Casson fluid over an oscillating vertical <lb/>porous plate, J. Comp. Mathematic. Sci. 10 (5) (2019) 1021-1031. <lb/>[8] H.R. Kataria, H.R. Patel, Effects of chemical reaction and heat generation/absorption on magneto-hydrodynamic (MHD) Casson fluid flow over an exponentially <lb/>accelerated vertical plate embedded in porous medium with ramped wall temperature and ramped surface concentration, Propuls. Power Res. 8 (1) (2019) <lb/>35-46. <lb/>[9] H.R. Patel, Effects of heat generation, thermal radiation, and hall current on MHD Casson fluid flow past an oscillating plate in porous medium, Multiphas. Sci. <lb/>Technol. 31 (1) (2019) 78-107, https://doi.org/10.1615/MultScienTechn.2019029514. <lb/>[10] K.K. Asogwa, A.A. Ibe, A study of MHD Casson fluid flow over a permeable stretching sheet with heat and mass transfer, J. Eng. Res. Rep. 16 (2) (2020) 10-25. <lb/>[11] R. Mahato, M. Das, P. Sibanda, Hall effect on MHD transient free convection flow of chemically reactive Casson fluid with heat source/sink past an infinite <lb/>vertical cylinder, Phys. Scripta 96 (1) (2020) 015207, https://doi.org/10.1088/1402-4896/abc5eb. <lb/>[12] A.S. Mittal, H.R. Patel, Influence of thermo-phoresis and Brownian motion on mixed convection two dimensional MHD Casson fluid flow with non-linear <lb/>radiation and heat generation, Phys. Stat. Mech. Appl. 537 (2020) 122710. <lb/>[13] S. Das, A.S. Bhanu, R.N. Jana, Delineating impacts of non-uniform wall temperature and concentration on time-dependent radiation-convection of Casson fluid <lb/>under magnetic field and chemical reaction, World J. Eng. 18 (5) (2021) 780-795. <lb/>[14] H.R. Kataria, H.R. Patel, Radiation and chemical reaction effects on MHD Casson fluid flow past an oscillating vertical plate embedded in porous medium, Alex. <lb/>Eng. J. 55 (1) (2016) 583-595. <lb/>[15] M.D. Shamshuddin, S.O. Salawu, K. Ramesh, V.S. Patil, P.H. Pooja, Bio-convective treatment for the reactive Casson hybrid nanofluid flow past an exponentially <lb/>stretching sheet with Ohmic heating and mixed convection, J. Therm. Sci. Calorim. (2023), https://doi.org/10.1007/s10973-023-12465-x. <lb/>[16] M.D. Shamshuddin, K.K. Asogwa, M. Ferdows, Thermo-solutal migrating heat producing and radiative Casson nanofluid flow via bidirectional stretching surface <lb/>in the presence of bilateral reactions, Numer. Heat Tran., Part A: Appl. (2023), https://doi.org/10.1080/10407782.2023.2191873. <lb/>[17] M.C. Raju, S. Reddy, E. Reddy, Radiation absorption and chemical reaction effects on MHD flow of heat generating Casson fluid past oscillating vertical porous <lb/>plate, Front. Heat Mass Transf. (FHMT) 7 (1) (2016), https://doi.org/10.5098/hmt.7.21. <lb/>[18] R. Biswas, M. Mondal, D. Sarkar, S. Ahmmed, Effects of radiation and chemical reaction on MHD unsteady heat and mass transfer of Casson fluid flow past a <lb/>vertical plate, J. Adv. Mathemat. Comp. Sci. 23 (2) (2017) 1-16. <lb/>[19] M.D. Shamshuddin, S.R. Mishra, T. Thumma, Chemically reacting radiative Casson fluid over an inclined porous plate: a numerical study, in: Numerical Heat <lb/>Transfer and Fluid Flow: Select Proceedings of NHTFF, Springer Singapore, Singapore, 2018, pp. 469-479. <lb/>[20] B. Prabhakar Reddy, Effects of chemical reaction on transient MHD flow with mass transfer past an impulsively fixed infinite vertical plate in the presence of <lb/>thermal radiation, Int. J. Appl. Mech. Eng. 24 (4) (2019) 169-182. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Table 4 <lb/>Numerical computation of τ and S h . <lb/>Sr <lb/>Kc <lb/>γ 2 <lb/>t <lb/>Sherwood number (S h ) <lb/>Skin friction (τ) <lb/>Suction <lb/>Blowing <lb/>Suction <lb/>Blowing <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.363794 <lb/>1.244562 <lb/>3.859158 <lb/>4.191651 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.276604 <lb/>1.077904 <lb/>3.748320 <lb/>4.026015 <lb/>2 <lb/>5 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.411770 <lb/>1.283934 <lb/>4.298548 <lb/>4.361193 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.818390 <lb/>1.656534 <lb/>3.771846 <lb/>3.959307 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>1.267160 <lb/>1.049884 <lb/>3.186366 <lb/>4.054095 <lb/>Table 5 <lb/>Numerical computation of τ. <lb/>β <lb/>M <lb/>K <lb/>γ (degree) <lb/>ωt (degree) <lb/>Skin friction (τ) <lb/>(Suction) <lb/>(Blowing) <lb/>0.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>30 <lb/>60 <lb/>3.859158 <lb/>4.191651 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>30 <lb/>60 <lb/>3.958980 <lb/>4.767084 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>30 <lb/>60 <lb/>4.046046 <lb/>4.525335 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>30 <lb/>60 <lb/>3.285141 <lb/>3.695625 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>45 <lb/>60 <lb/>3.724728 <lb/>3.951513 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>30 <lb/>90 <lb/>2.546916 <lb/>2.494971 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">B.P. Reddy et al. <lb/>Heliyon 10 (2024) e24150 <lb/></note>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[21] M.V. Krishna, P.V.S. Anand, A.J. Chamkha, Heat and mass transfer on free convective flow of a micropolar fluid through a porous surface with inclined magnetic <lb/>field and Hall effects, Special Topics and Reviews in Porous Media, An Int. J. 10 (3) (2019) 203-223. <lb/>[22] M.V. Krishna, K. Jyothi, A.J. Chamkha, Heat and mass transfer on MHD flow of second grade fluid through a porous medium over a semi infinite vertical <lb/>stretching sheet, J. Porous Media 23 (8) (2020) 751-765. <lb/>[23] B. Prabhakar Reddy, P. Matao, J.M. Sunzu, Finite element numerical investigation into unsteady MHD radiating and reacting mixed convection past an <lb/>impulsively started oscillating plate, Defect Diffusion Forum 401 (2020) 47-62. <lb/>[24] A. Sandhya, G. Reddy, G.V.S.R. Deekshitulu, Radiation and chemical reaction effects on MHD Casson fluid flow past a semi-infinite vertical moving porous plate, <lb/>Indian J. Pure Appl. Phys. 58 (7) (2020) 548-557. <lb/>[25] S.M. Ibrahim, P.V. Kumar, G. Lorenzini, Analytical modeling of heat and mass transfer of radiative MHD Casson fluid over an exponentially permeable <lb/>stretching sheet with chemical reaction, J. Eng. Thermophys. 29 (2020) 136-155. <lb/>[26] M. Das, G. Mahanta, S. Shaw, Heat and mass transfer effect on an unsteady MHD radiative chemically reactive Casson fluid over a stretching sheet in porous <lb/>medium, Heat Transfer 49 (8) (2020) 4350-4369. <lb/>[27] P. Suresh, Y.H. Krishna, S.H.S. Naik, P.J. Reddy, Heat and mass transfer in MHD Casson fluid flow along exponentially permeable stretching sheet in the <lb/>presence of radiation and chemical reaction, Ann. Romanian Soc. Cell Biol. (2021) 7163-7175. <lb/>[28] S.G. Bejawada, Y.D. Reddy, W. Jamshed, K.S. Nisar, A.N. Alharbi, R. Chouikh, Radiation effect on MHD Casson fluid flow over an inclined non-linear surface <lb/>with chemical reaction in a Forchheimer porous medium, Alex. Eng. J. 61 (10) (2022) 8207-8220. <lb/>[29] M. Das, R. Mahato, R. Nandkeolyar, Newtonian heating effect on unsteady hydro-magnetic Casson fluid flow past a flat plate with heat and mass transfer, Alex. <lb/>Eng. J. 54 (4) (2015) 871-879. <lb/>[30] A. Hussanan, M.Z. Salleh, I. Khan, R.M. Tahar, Heat transfer in magneto-hydrodynamic flow of a Casson fluid with porous medium and Newtonian heating, <lb/>J. Nanofluids 6 (4) (2017) 784-793. <lb/>[31] I. Ullah, S. Shafie, I. Khan, Effects of slip condition and Newtonian heating on MHD flow of Casson fluid over a nonlinearly stretching sheet saturated in a porous <lb/>medium, J. King Saud Univ. Sci. 29 (2) (2017) 250-259. <lb/>[32] K. Ahmad, S.A. Halim, Z. Hanouf, Variable viscosity of Casson fluid flow over a stretching sheet in porous media with Newtonian heating, J. Informat. <lb/>Mathemat. Sci. 10 (1 and 2) (2018) 3359-3370. <lb/>[33] A. Hussanan, M.Z. Salleh, H.T. Alkasasbeh, I. Khan, MHD flow and heat transfer in a Casson fluid over a nonlinearly stretching sheet with Newtonian heating, <lb/>Heat Tran. Res. 49 (12) (2018), https://doi.org/10.1615/HeatTransRes.2018014771. <lb/>[34] I.A. Badruddin, N.J. Salman Ahmed, A.E. Anqi, S. Kamangar, Conjugate heat and mass transfer in a vertical porous cylinder, J. Thermophys. Heat Tran. 33 (2) <lb/>(2019) 548-558. <lb/>[35] G.S. Seth, A. Bhattacharyya, R. Kumar, M.K. Mishra, Modeling and numerical simulation of hydromagnetic natural convection Casson fluid flow with nth-order <lb/>chemical reaction and Newtonian heating in porous medium, J. Porous Media 22 (9) (2019) 1141-1157, https://doi.org/10.1615/JPorMedia.2019025699. <lb/>[36] Z. Abdelmalek, B. Mahanthesh, M.F.M. Basir, M. Imtiaz, J. Mackolil, N.S. Khan, I. Tlili, Mixed convective radiated magneto Casson fluid flow with Arrhenius <lb/>activation energy and Newtonian heating effects: flow and sensitivity analysis, Alex. Eng. J. 59 (5) (2020) 3991-4011. <lb/>[37] R. Mahato, M. Das, Effect of suction/blowing on heat-absorbing unsteady radiative Casson fluid past a semi-infinite flat plate with conjugate heating and <lb/>inclined magnetic field, Pramana 94 (127) (2020), https://doi.org/10.1007/s12043-020-01990-1. <lb/>[38] S.F. Elimefendigil, Y. Akbulut, A. Sengur, H.F. Oztop, MHD conjugate natural convection in a porous cavity involving a curved conductive partition and <lb/>estimations by using Long Short-Term Memory Networks, J. Therm. Anal. Calorim. 140 (3) (2020) 1457-1468. <lb/>[39] K. Gangadhar, T. Kannan, P. Jayalakshmi, G. Sakthivel, Dual solutions for MHD Casson fluid over a shrinking sheet with Newtonian heating, Int. J. Ambient <lb/>Energy 42 (3) (2021) 331-339. <lb/>[40] B. Prabhakar Reddy, O.D. Makinde, Newtonian heating effect on heat absorbing unsteady MHD radiating and chemically reacting free convection flow past an <lb/>oscillating vertical porous plate, Int. J. Appl. Mech. Eng. 27 (1) (2022) 168-187. <lb/>[41] B. Prabhakar Reddy, L.J. Sademaki, A Numerical study on Newtonian heating effect on heat absorbing MHD Casson flow of dissipative fluid past an oscillating <lb/>vertical porous plate, Int. J. Math. Math. Sci. (2022) 7987315, https://doi.org/10.1155/2022/7987315. <lb/>[42] N.A. Reddy, K. Janardhan, Soret and Dufour effects on MHD Casson fluid over a vertical plate in the presence of chemical reaction and radiation, Int. J. Curr. <lb/>Res. Rev. 9 (2017) 55-61. <lb/>[43] T. Hayat, T. Nasir, M.I. Khan, A. Alsaedi, Numerical investigation of MHD flow with Soret and Dufour effect, Results Phys. 8 (2018) 1017-1022. <lb/>[44] M. Das, G. Mahanta, S. Shaw, S.B. Parida, Unsteady MHD chemically reactive double-diffusive Casson fluid past a flat plate in porous medium with heat and <lb/>mass transfer, Heat Tran. Asian Res. 48 (5) (2019) 1761-1777. <lb/>[45] M.V. Krishna, B.V. Swarnalathamma, A.J. Chamkha, Investigation of Soret, Joule and Hall effects on MHD rotating mixed convective flow past an infinite <lb/>vertical porous plate, J. Ocean Eng. Sci. 4 (3) (2019) 263-275. <lb/>[46] K. Vijaya, G.V.R. Reddy, O.D. Makinde, Soret effect on MHD Casson fluid flow past a moving vertical plate in the presence of radiation and chemical reaction, <lb/>Diffus. Found. 26 (2020) 86-103. <lb/>[47] S.G. Bejawada, D.R. Yanala, Finite element Soret Dufour effects on an unsteady MHD heat and mass transfer flow past an accelerated inclined vertical plate, <lb/>Heat Transfer 50 (8) (2021) 8553-8578. <lb/>[48] N. Govindaraj, G. Iyyappan, A.K. Singh, P. Shukla, S. Roy, A computational study on the MHD Casson fluid flow with thermal radiation and variable physical <lb/>properties under the influence of Soret and Dufour effects, Heat Transfer 51 (6) (2022) 5857-5873. <lb/>[49] M.A. Kumar, Y.D. Reddy, B.S. Goud, V.S. Rao, An impact on non-Newtonian free convective MHD Casson fluid flow past a vertical porous plate in the existence <lb/>of Soret, Dufour, and chemical reaction, Int. J. Ambient Energy 43 (1) (2022) 7410-7418. <lb/>[50] N.N. Reddy, Y.D. Reddy, V.S. Rao, B.S. Goud, K.S. Nisar, Multiple slip effects on steady MHD flow past a non-isothermal stretching surface in the presence of <lb/>Soret, Dufour with suction/injection, Int. Commun. Heat Mass Tran. 134 (5) (2022), https://doi.org/10.1016/j.icheatmasstransfer.2022.106024. <lb/>[51] B. Prabhakar Reddy, O.D. Makinde, A. Hugo, A computational study on diffusion-thermo and rotation effects on heat-generated mixed convection flow of MHD <lb/>Casson fluid past an oscillating porous plate, Int. Commun. Heat Mass Tran. 138 (2022), https://doi.org/10.1016/j.icheatmasstransfer.2022.106389. <lb/>[52] K.V. Reddy, G.V. Ramana Reddy, A. Sandhya, Y.H. Krishna, Numerical solution of MHD, Soret, Dufour, and thermal radiation contributions on unsteady free <lb/>convection motion of Casson liquid past a semi-infinite vertical porous plate, Heat Transfer 51 (3) (2022) 2837-2858. <lb/>[53] M.Q. Brewster, Thermal Radiative Transfer and Properties, John Wiley and Sons, 1972. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">B.P. Reddy et al. </note>


	</text>
</tei>
