<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Research Article <lb/>Vaccinomics Approach for Designing Potential <lb/>Peptide Vaccine by Targeting Shigella spp. Serine <lb/>Protease Autotransporter Subfamily Protein SigA <lb/>Arafat Rahman Oany, 1 Tahmina Pervin, 2 Mamun Mia, 1 Motaher Hossain, 3 <lb/>Mohammad Shahnaij, 4 Shahin Mahmud, 1 and K. M. Kaderi Kibria 1 <lb/>1 Department of Biotechnology and Genetic Engineering, Faculty of Life Science, Mawlana Bhashani Science and Technology <lb/>University, Tangail, Bangladesh <lb/>2 Biotechnology and Genetic Engineering Discipline, Life Science School, Khulna University, Khulna, Bangladesh <lb/>3 Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, University of Dhaka, Dhaka, Bangladesh <lb/>4 Enteric and Food Microbiology Laboratory, International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research Bangladesh (icddr,b), <lb/>Dhaka, Bangladesh <lb/>Correspondence should be addressed to K. M. Kaderi Kibria; km_kibria@yahoo.com <lb/>Received 18 March 2017; Revised 28 June 2017; Accepted 24 July 2017; Published 7 September 2017 <lb/>Academic Editor: Pedro A. Reche <lb/>Copyright © 2017 Arafat Rahman Oany et al. This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution <lb/>License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/>Shigellosis, a bacillary dysentery, is closely associated with diarrhoea in human and causes infection of 165 million people <lb/>worldwide per year. Casein-degrading serine protease autotransporter of enterobacteriaceae (SPATE) subfamily protein SigA, an <lb/>outer membrane protein, exerts both cytopathic and enterotoxic effects especially cytopathic to human epithelial cell type-2 <lb/>(HEp-2) and is shown to be highly immunogenic. In the present study, we have tried to impose the vaccinomics approach for <lb/>designing a common peptide vaccine candidate against the immunogenic SigA of Shigella spp. At first, 44 SigA proteins from <lb/>different variants of S. flexneri, S. dysenteriae, S. boydii, and S. sonnei were assessed to find the most antigenic protein. We <lb/>retrieved 12 peptides based on the highest score for human leukocyte antigen (HLA) supertypes analysed by NetCTL. Initially, <lb/>these peptides were assessed for the affinity with MHC class I and class II alleles, and four potential core epitopes <lb/>VTARAGLGY, FHTVTVNTL, HTTWTLTGY, and IELAGTLTL were selected. From these, FHTVTVNTL and IELAGTLTL <lb/>peptides were shown to have 100% conservancy. Finally, IELAGTLTL was shown to have the highest population coverage <lb/>(83.86%) among the whole world population. In vivo study of the proposed epitope might contribute to the development of <lb/>functional and unique widespread vaccine, which might be an operative alleyway to thwart dysentery from the world. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Background <lb/>Shigella is a Gram-negative, facultative anaerobic, nonmotile, <lb/>nonspore forming, and rod-shaped true bacteria closely <lb/>related to Salmonella and Escherichia coli. The resulting <lb/>infection by this organism called shigellosis, also known as <lb/>bacillary dysentery or Marlow syndrome, is most typically <lb/>associated with diarrhoea and other gastrointestinal symp-<lb/>toms in humans. This pathogen is usually found in water that <lb/>is contaminated with human feces within the setting of poor <lb/>hygiene among kids of underneath 5 years old and is trans-<lb/>mitted via the fecal-oral route. The infection will occur even <lb/>if there is just a bodily function of only ten to one hundred <lb/>microorganisms [1]. In each year, 165 million cases of Shi-<lb/>gella infection are accounted worldwide, of that, 163 million <lb/>take place in developing countries and ultimately result in <lb/>millions of death [2]. Bangladesh has got the top rates of shig-<lb/>ellosis according to the recent Global Enteric Multicenter <lb/>Study (GEMS) in Asia. The output of this study has revealed <lb/>that the Shigella is the third leading reason behind diarrhoea <lb/>in children [3, 4]. <lb/>Shigella species are usually classified into four serogroups: <lb/>S. dysenteriae (12 serotypes), S. flexneri (6 serotypes), S. boy-<lb/>dii (18 serotypes), and S. sonnei (one serotype) based on the <lb/></body>

			<front>Hindawi <lb/>Journal of Immunology Research <lb/>Volume 2017, Article ID 6412353, 14 pages <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1155/2017/6412353 <lb/></front>

			<body>biochemical properties and group-specific O antigens <lb/>within the outer portion of the semipermeable membrane. <lb/>S. dysenteriae, S. flexneri, and S. boydii are physiologically <lb/>similar in distinction to S. sonnei. Among them, S. flex-<lb/>neri is the most frequently isolated species globally and <lb/>accounts for 60% of cases in the unindustrialized coun-<lb/>tries; S. sonnei causes 77% of cases in the industrialized <lb/>countries [1]. <lb/>The underlying therapeutic challenge to manage Shigella <lb/>is its accrued resistance to most often used antibiotics like <lb/>ampicillin, tetracycline, streptomycin, nalidixic acid, and <lb/>sulfamethoxazole-trimethoprim [5]. Earlier, ciprofloxacin, <lb/>a third-generation fluoroquinolone antibiotic, has been <lb/>used effectively for the treatment of bacillary dysentery <lb/>[6]. However, this antibiotic is no longer helpful for the <lb/>treatment of bacillary dysentery in south Asian countries <lb/>together with Bangladesh, because of the dissemination <lb/>of fluoroquinolone-resistant variety and its equivalent clones <lb/>across the countries [7, 8]. Hence, it is essential to find a <lb/>sustainable approach like vaccinomics, which can elicit <lb/>long-term and consistent immunological responses to fight <lb/>against Shigella. <lb/>SigA is annotated in the she pathogenicity island of <lb/>Shigella, encoding SigA protein which belongs to the serine <lb/>protease autotransporter of enterobacteriaceae (SPATE) <lb/>subgroup proteins. The autotransporter proteins of Gram-<lb/>negative bacteria exhibit an N-terminal signal sequence, <lb/>required for secretion across the inner membrane, and a C-<lb/>terminal domain that forms an amphipathic β-barrel pore <lb/>that allows passage of the functional domain across the outer <lb/>membrane. This type of exporter proteins either remains <lb/>attached to the cell surface or is released from the cell <lb/>by proteolytic cleavage [9]. SigA is a multifunctional pro-<lb/>tein, able to degrade casein with cytotoxic and enterotoxic <lb/>effects. Moreover, SigA is cytopathic for human epithelial <lb/>type-2 (HEp-2) cells, causing morphological changes and <lb/>loss of integrity of the cell monolayers, important for the <lb/>pathologic process of Shigella [10]. The position of SigA <lb/>in the chromosome made them less vulnerable to loss <lb/>compare to the other virulence factors harbouring within <lb/>the plasmid, and more exposure to the immune cells <lb/>occurred by this secreted toxin [11]. Most importantly, <lb/>this protein has been shown to be immunogenic following <lb/>infection with Shigella [10]. The generalized modules of <lb/>membrane antigen-(GMMA-) based outer membrane <lb/>proteins including SigA were also shown to be highly <lb/>immunogenic [12], which prompted us to target SigA as <lb/>one of the best vaccine candidates and to design potential <lb/>peptide vaccine covering all the Shigella spp. and most of <lb/>the regions of the world. <lb/>Epitope-based immunizing agents are often an inex-<lb/>pensive choice to thwart enteric Shigella infection. The <lb/>identification of specific epitopes derived from infectious <lb/>pathogens has considerably advanced the event of epitope-<lb/>based vaccines (EVs). Higher understanding of the molecular <lb/>basis of substance recognition and human leukocyte antigen-<lb/>(HLA-) binding motifs has resulted in the advancement of <lb/>rationally designed vaccines that solely depends on algo-<lb/>rithms predicting the peptide&apos;s binding to human HLA. <lb/>The traditional process for the development of a vaccine is <lb/>very complex compared to that of the epitope-based vaccine, <lb/>and additionally, it is chemically stable, more specific, and <lb/>free of any infectious or oncogenic potential hazard [13]. <lb/>However, the invention of a wet laboratory-based candidate <lb/>epitope is expensive and laborious that requires varied <lb/>medicine experiments in the laboratory for the ultimate <lb/>choice of epitopes. Hence, the interest for predicting epitopes <lb/>by computational strategies, alternate in silico approaches <lb/>among researchers, is growing bit by bit with reduced efforts. <lb/>Vaccinomics is the application of integrated knowledge <lb/>from different disciplines including immunogenetics and <lb/>immunogenomics to develop candidate next-generation <lb/>vaccine and understand its immune response [14]. Cur-<lb/>rently, various vaccinomics databases are accessible for <lb/>identification of distinctive B lymphocyte epitopes and <lb/>HLA ligands with high sensitivity and specificity [15-17]. <lb/>The vaccinomics approach has already proven its potency <lb/>in identifying the conserved epitope in the case of human <lb/>immunodeficiency virus [18], multiple sclerosis [19], tuber-<lb/>culosis [20], and malaria [21] with desired results. In our <lb/>study, we have applied vaccinomics approaches for the <lb/>screening of potentially conserved epitopes by targeting <lb/>protein SigA. <lb/>2. Methods <lb/>The flow chart summarizing the protocols for the complete <lb/>epitope prediction is illustrated in Figure 1. <lb/>2.1. Sequence Retrieval and Antigenic Protein Determination. <lb/>The SigA protein sequences of different strains of Shigella <lb/>species were retrieved from the NCBI GenBank [22] data-<lb/>base and analysed in the VaxiJen v2.0 [23] server for the <lb/>determination of the most potent antigenic protein. Addi-<lb/>tionally, the target protein was crosschecked against human <lb/>pathogens and other similar pathogens to ensure the ortholo-<lb/>gous entry by using BLAST-P [24] and OrthoMCL [25] <lb/>databases [26]. <lb/>2.2. T-Cell Epitope Prediction and Affinity with MHC. The <lb/>epitope prediction for the respective protein and their affinity <lb/>score with MHC class I and class II allele was measured fol-<lb/>lowing previously used approach [27, 28]. Concisely, the <lb/>NetCTL v1.2 server [29] was used for predicting potential <lb/>cytotoxic T-lymphocyte (CTL) epitopes from the most anti-<lb/>genic protein. A combined algorithms including MHC-I <lb/>binding, transporter of antigenic peptide (TAP) transport effi-<lb/>ciency, and proteasomal C-terminal cleavage prediction were <lb/>employed for the T-cell epitope prediction. The epitope with <lb/>the highest score for 12 MHC class I supertypes was selected. <lb/>T Cell Epitope Prediction Tools from Immune Epitope <lb/>Database and Analysis Resource (IEDB-AR) were used for <lb/>the prediction of affinity with MHC class I [30] and MHC <lb/>class II [31, 32]. The stabilized matrix method (SMM) was <lb/>used to calculate the half-maximal inhibitory concentration <lb/>(IC 50 ) of peptide binding to MHC class I with a preselected <lb/>9.0-mer epitope. The peptides were also assessed for HLA I <lb/>binding affinity by the software, EPISOFT. For the analyses <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Immunology Research <lb/></note>

			<body>of MHC class II binding, the IEDB-recommended method <lb/>was used for the specific HLA-DP, HLA-DQ, and HLA-DR <lb/>loci. Fifteen-mer epitopes were designed for MHC class II <lb/>binding analysis considering the preselected 9-mer epitope <lb/>and its conserved region in the Shigella strains. For the <lb/>MHC class I and MHC class II alleles, the epitopes consisting <lb/>IC 50 &lt; 250 nM and IC 50 &lt; 100 nM, respectively, were selected <lb/>for further analysis. The MHC class II binding prediction <lb/>tool PREDIVAC was also used to assess their affinity with <lb/>HLA_DRB_1. <lb/>2.3. Cluster Analysis of the MHC Restricted Alleles. Further-<lb/>more, the MHCcluster v2.0 server [33] was used for the <lb/>identification of cluster of MHC restricted allele with <lb/>appropriate peptides to further strengthen our prediction. <lb/>This is the additional crosscheck of the predicted MHC <lb/>restricted allele analysis from the IEDB analysis resources. <lb/>The output from this server is a static heat map and a <lb/>graphical tree for describing the functional relationship <lb/>between peptides and HLAs. <lb/>Table 1: T-cell epitopes of SigA protein predicted by the NetCTL <lb/>server on the basis of the combined score. Here, epitopes for all <lb/>the 12 different HLA supertypes have been presented. <lb/>Supertypes <lb/>Epitope <lb/>Start position Combined score <lb/>A1 <lb/>VTARAGLGY <lb/>645 <lb/>2.8475 <lb/>A2 <lb/>SMYNTLWRV <lb/>279 <lb/>1.4558 <lb/>A3 <lb/>KSYMSGNYK <lb/>432 <lb/>1.5812 <lb/>A24 <lb/>NYAWVNGNI <lb/>219 <lb/>1.6813 <lb/>A26 <lb/>HTTWTLTGY <lb/>411 <lb/>2.0947 <lb/>B7 <lb/>APKGSNKEI <lb/>378 <lb/>1.1981 <lb/>B8 <lb/>YMSGNYKAF <lb/>434 <lb/>1.4879 <lb/>B27 <lb/>ARAGLGYQF <lb/>647 <lb/>1.7245 <lb/>B39 <lb/>FHTVTVNTL <lb/>313 <lb/>2.6855 <lb/>B44 <lb/>IELAGTLTL <lb/>178 <lb/>1.9586 <lb/>B58 <lb/>IASFSQPDW <lb/>43 <lb/>1.9421 <lb/>B62 <lb/>YMSGNYKAF <lb/>434 <lb/>1.4814 <lb/>Target selection (Sig A) by searching literature <lb/>Retrieval of SigA protein of different strains of Shigella species <lb/>from NCBI GenBank database <lb/>Antigenic protein determination using VaxiJen <lb/>Orthologous entry search against human pathogens and other <lb/>related pathogens using BLAST-P and OrthoMCL databases <lb/>The most antigenic protein was <lb/>selected for further analyses <lb/>T-cell epitope prediction, using NetCTL, by MHC class I <lb/>binding analysis, TAP transport efficiency, and <lb/>proteasomal C-terminal cleavage <lb/>Top four (4) epitopes were selected <lb/>for further analyses <lb/>MHC class II analysis and cluster analysis <lb/>Crosschecking by predivac score for <lb/>MHC class II <lb/>Epitope conservancy and population coverage analysis <lb/>using IEDB tool <lb/>Allergenicity assessment by AllerHunter <lb/>Homology modelling and structural frustration analysis <lb/>Docking analysis with the selected HLA (HLA-E <lb/>⁎ <lb/>01:01 and HLA-DQA1) with a positive control <lb/>Prediction of the 3D structure of <lb/>the epitope using PEP-FOLD <lb/>Assessment of the potential of <lb/>B-cell epitopes from the IEDB <lb/>tools, including the following: <lb/>Kolasker and Tongaonkar <lb/>antigenicity <lb/>(i) <lb/>Emini surface accessibility <lb/>(ii) <lb/>Parker hydrophilicity <lb/>prediction <lb/>(iii) <lb/>Figure 1: Flow diagram of the methodology. <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Immunology Research <lb/></note>

			<body>2.4. Epitope Conservancy and Population Coverage Analyses. <lb/>Epitope conservancy of the candidate epitopes was exam-<lb/>ined using a web-based epitope conservancy tool available <lb/>in IEDB analysis resource [34]. The conservancy level of <lb/>each potential epitope was calculated by considering iden-<lb/>tities in all SigA protein sequences of different strains <lb/>retrieved from the database. Multiple sequence alignment <lb/>(MSA) was employed to understand the positions of the <lb/>Table 2: Epitopes for CD8 + T-cell along with their interacting MHC class I alleles with affinity &lt; 250 nM. <lb/>Epitope <lb/>Interacting MHC-I allele (IC 50 ) on the nM scale <lb/>VTARAGLGY HLA-A * 29:02 (40.62), HLA-A * 01:01 (224.16), HLA-A * 30:02 (168.45), HLA-B * 15:02 (81.70), HLA-C * 03:03 (103.66) <lb/>FHTVTVNTL <lb/>HLA-B * 39:01 (9.02), HLA-B * 38:01 (62.10), HLA-B * 15:02 (21.84), HLA-C * 03:03 (5.48), HLA-C * 08:02 (211.91), <lb/>HLA-C * 14:02 (92.18), HLA-C * 12:03 (78.92) <lb/>HTTWTLTGY <lb/>HLA-A * 26:01 (162.41), HLA-A * 25:01 (219.32), HLA-B * 15:02 (153.54), HLA-C * 14:02 (122.92), HLA-C * 12:03 (33.90), <lb/>HLA-C * 03:03 (144.75) <lb/>IELAGTLTL <lb/>HLA-E * 01:01 (152.83), HLA-B * 40:01 (35.47), HLA-B * 15:02 (55.75), HLA-C * 03:03 (29.28), HLA-C * 12:03 (109.70) <lb/>IASFSQPDW <lb/>HLA-B * 58:01 (9.34), HLA-B * 57:01 (42.06), HLA-B * 53:01 (61.22), HLA-C * 03:03 (2.35), HLA-C * 08:02 (187.57), <lb/>HLA-C * 15:02 (164.60), HLA-C * 12:03 (11.95), HLA-C * 14:02 (248.10) <lb/>ARAGLGYQF <lb/>HLA-C * 12:03, HLA-C * 03:03 (53.53), HLA-B * 15:02 (107.95), HLA-B * 27:05 (97.18) <lb/>NYAWVNGNI <lb/>HLA-A * 68:02 (188.19), HLA-C * 14:02 (21.26), HLA-C * 03:03 (220.60), HLA-C * 12:03 (60.56) <lb/>KSYMSGNYK <lb/>HLA-C * 15:02 (6.94), HLA-A * 30:01 (9.18), HLA-A * 11:01 (11.28), HLA-A * 03:01 (20.22), HLA-A * 31:01 (54.63), <lb/>HLA-C * 14:02 (40.80), HLA-C * 03:03 (61.75), HLA-C * 12:03 (31.71) <lb/>YMSGNYKAF <lb/>HLA-B * 15:01 (61.09), HLA-B * 35:01 (124.62), HLA-C * 14:02 (17.24), HLA-B * 15:02 (61.69), HLA-C * 03:03 (13.14), <lb/>HLA-C * 12:03 (151.43) <lb/>SMYNTLWRV <lb/>HLA-A * 02:01 (6.70), HLA-A * 02:06 (13.79), HLA-C * 14:02 (105.59), HLA-C * 12:03 (30.21) <lb/>APKGSNKEI <lb/>HLA-B * 07:02 (199.48), HLA-C * 12:03 (7.82), HLA-C * 03:03 (37.81) <lb/>HLA-B15:01 <lb/>HLA-B15:02 <lb/>HLA-A26:01 <lb/>HLA-A25:01 <lb/>HLA-A30:02 <lb/>HLA-A29:02 <lb/>HLA-A01:01 <lb/>HLA-B57:01 <lb/>HLA-B58:01 <lb/>HLA-B53:01 <lb/>HLA-B35:01 <lb/>HLA-B07:02 <lb/>HLA-C08:02 <lb/>HLA-C15:02 <lb/>HLA-C03:03 <lb/>HLA-C12:03 <lb/>HLA-C06:06 <lb/>HLA-C07:01 <lb/>HLA-C14:02 <lb/>HLA-A02:01 <lb/>HLA-A02:06 <lb/>HLA-A68:02 <lb/>HLA-B39:01 <lb/>HLA-B38:01 <lb/>HLA-B40:01 <lb/>HLA-B27:05 <lb/>HLA-A11:01 <lb/>HLA-A03:01 <lb/>HLA-A31:01 <lb/>HLA-A30:01 <lb/>HLA-A31:01 <lb/>HLA-A03:01 <lb/>HLA-A11:01 <lb/>HLA-B27:05 <lb/>HLA-B40:01 <lb/>HLA-B38:01 <lb/>HLA-B39:01 <lb/>HLA-A68:02 <lb/>HLA-A02:06 <lb/>HLA-A02:01 <lb/>HLA-C14:02 <lb/>HLA-C07:01 <lb/>HLA-C06:02 <lb/>HLA-C12:03 <lb/>HLA-C03:03 <lb/>HLA-C15:02 <lb/>HLA-C08:02 <lb/>HLA-B07:02 <lb/>HLA-B35:01 <lb/>HLA-B53:01 <lb/>HLA-B58:01 <lb/>HLA-B57:01 <lb/>HLA-A01:01 <lb/>HLA-A29:02 <lb/>HLA-A30:02 <lb/>HLA-A25:01 <lb/>HLA-A26:01 <lb/>HLA-B15:02 <lb/>HLA-B15:01 <lb/>Color key <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>Value <lb/>(a) <lb/>Color key <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>Value <lb/>DRB1 :0101 <lb/>DRB1 :0901 <lb/>DRB1 :0701 <lb/>DRB1 :0401 <lb/>DRB1 :1302 <lb/>DRB4 :0101 <lb/>DRB3 :0101 <lb/>DRB1 :0301 <lb/>DRB1 :0802 <lb/>DRB1 :0803 <lb/>DRB1 :1501 <lb/>DRB1 :1101 <lb/>DRB1 :1402 <lb/>DRB5 :0101 <lb/>DRB5 :0101 <lb/>DRB1 :1402 <lb/>DRB1 :1101 <lb/>DRB1 :1501 <lb/>DRB1 :0803 <lb/>DRB1 :0802 <lb/>DRB1 :0301 <lb/>DRB3 :0101 <lb/>DRB4 :0101 <lb/>DRB1 :1302 <lb/>DRB1 :0401 <lb/>DRB1 :0701 <lb/>DRB1 :0901 <lb/>DRB1 :0101 <lb/>(b) <lb/>Figure 2: Cluster analysis of the HLA alleles for both MHC molecules through heat map representation. (a) Representing the cluster of the <lb/>MHC-I. (b) Representing the cluster of MHC-II molecules. Epitopes are clustered on the basis of interaction with HLA and shown as red <lb/>colour indicating strong interaction with appropriate annotation. Yellow zone indicates the weaker interaction. Here, all the available <lb/>alleles are shown only. <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Immunology Research <lb/></note>

			<body>epitopes within the sequences. As SPATE family is very <lb/>much specific for the enterobacteria, specifically, E. coli <lb/>and Shigella, we also include two E. coli sequences <lb/>(gi|693049347| and gi|699401135|) along with those of four <lb/>species of Shigella for MSA construction. The Jalview <lb/>(http://www.jalview.org/) tool was used for this analysis. <lb/>The conservancy of the selected peptides was also substan-<lb/>tiated by the Protein Variability Software (PVS) [35]. Pop-<lb/>ulation coverage for the epitope was assessed by the IEDB <lb/>population coverage calculation tool [36]. The combined <lb/>score for MHC classes I and II was assessed for the <lb/>analysis of the population coverage. <lb/>2.5. Homology Modelling and Structural Frustration Analysis. <lb/>A homology model of the conserved region was obtained by <lb/>MODELLER v9 [37], and the predicted model was assessed <lb/>by the PROCHECK [38, 39] server. For the disorder predic-<lb/>tion among the amino acid sequences, DISOPRED v3 [40] <lb/>Table 3: The potential CD4 + T-cell epitopes along with their interacting MHC class II alleles with affinity (IC50) &lt; 100 nM and respective <lb/>predivac scores. <lb/>Epitope <lb/>Interacting MHC-II allele (IC 50 ) on the nM scale <lb/>Number <lb/>of alleles <lb/>Predivac score <lb/>(binding core) <lb/>VTARAGLGYQFDLFA <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 04:01, HLA-DRB1 * 09:01, HLA-DRB1 * 04:05, HLA-DRB3 * 01:01, <lb/>HLA-DQA1 * 05:01 <lb/>5 <lb/>68.76 <lb/>(LGYQFDLFA) <lb/>NSGFHTVTVNTLDAT <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:01 (53), HLA-DRB1 * 01:21 (17.87), HLA-DRB1 * 01:17 (77.94), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:16 (98.93), HLA-DRB1 * 01:13 (61.53), HLA-DRB1 * 01:29 (83.08), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:24 (62.89), HLA-DRB1 * 01:10 (28.18), HLA-DRB1 * 01:11 (45.39), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:19 (39.99), HLA-DRB1 * 01:12 (39.99), HLA-DRB1 * 01:31 (39.99), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:32 (39.99), HLA-DRB1 * 01:08 (39.99), HLA-DRB1 * 01:05 (39.99), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:07 (39.99), HLA-DRB1 * 01:27 (39.99), HLA-DRB1 * 01:25 (39.99), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:22 (39.99), HLA-DRB1 * 01:28 (39.99), HLA-DRB1 * 01:14 (47.44), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:09 (37.12), HLA-DRB1 * 01:15 (71.58), HLA-DRB1 * 01:18 (44.25), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:06 (35.78), HLA-DRB1 * 01:26 (38.4), HLA-DRB1 * 01:20 (41.15), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:23 (48.69), HLA-DRB1 * 01:04 (48.54), HLA-DRB1 * 07:06 (65.25), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 07:05 (65.06), HLA-DRB5 * 02:05 (46.61) <lb/>32 <lb/>71.56 <lb/>(FHTVTVNTL) <lb/>KAIELAGTLTLTGTP <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:01 (82), HLA-DRB1 * 01:21 (23.85), HLA-DRB1 * 01:17 (98.16), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:24 (58.9), HLA-DRB1 * 01:10 (29.05), HLA-DRB1 * 01:11 (49.8), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:19 (44.72), HLA-DRB1 * 01:12 (44.72), HLA-DRB1 * 01:31 (44.72), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:32 (44.72), HLA-DRB1 * 01:08 (44.72), HLA-DRB1 * 01:05 (44.72), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:07 (44.72), HLA-DRB1 * 01:27 (44.72), HLA-DRB1 * 01:25 (44.72), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:22 (44.72), HLA-DRB1 * 01:28 (44.72), HLA-DRB1 * 01:03 (91.98), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:14 (54.39), HLA-DRB1 * 01:09 (31.87), HLA-DRB1 * 01:15 (59.62), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:18 (40.48), HLA-DRB1 * 01:06 (14.26), HLA-DRB1 * 01:26 (18.43), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:20 (17.57), HLA-DRB1 * 01:23 (24.27), HLA-DRB1 * 01:04 (18.63), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:01 (82), HLA-DRB5 * 02:05 (70.95) <lb/>29 <lb/>71.70 <lb/>(IELAGTLTL) <lb/>NNQIASFSQPDWESR <lb/>0 <lb/>55.02 <lb/>(FSQPDWESR) <lb/>VTARAGLGYQFDLFA <lb/>0 <lb/>68.76 <lb/>(LGYQFDLFA) <lb/>AQNYAWVNGNIKSDK HLA-DRB5 * 01:01 (62), HLA-DRB5 * 02:04 (93.07), HLA-DRB5 * 02:05 (24.55) <lb/>3 <lb/>78.78 <lb/>(YAWVNGNIK) <lb/>AAKSYMSGNYKAFLT <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 08:05 (65.65), HLA-DRB1 * 12:03 (94.66), HLA-DRB1 * 01:09 (57.66), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:10 (98.95), HLA-DRB1 * 01:19 (99.23), HLA-DRB1 * 01:12 (99.23), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:31 (99.23), HLA-DRB1 * 01:32 (99.23), HLA-DRB1 * 01:08 (99.23), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:05 (99.23), HLA-DRB1 * 01:07 (99.23), HLA-DRB1 * 01:27 (99.23), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:25 (99.23), HLA-DRB1 * 01:22 (99.23), HLA-DRB1 * 01:28 (99.23), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:21 (73.89), HLA-DRB1 * 01:06 (52.24), HLA-DRB1 * 01:23 (86.01), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:04 (87.14), HLA-DRB1 * 01:26 (83.15), HLA-DRB1 * 01:20 (85.84), <lb/>HLA-DRB5 * 02:05 (12.01), HLA-DRB5 * 02:02 (67.2), HLA-DRB5 * 02:04 (62.02) <lb/>24 <lb/>60.30 <lb/>(KSYMSGNYK) <lb/>SYMSGNYKAFLTEVN <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:21 (56.34), HLA-DRB1 * 01:09 (89.52), HLA-DRB1 * 01:10 (81.52), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:26 (98.98), HLA-DRB1 * 01:06 (88.25), HLA-DRB1 * 04:05 (38), <lb/>HLA-DRB5 * 02:05 (41.74) <lb/>7 <lb/>69.98 <lb/>(YKAFLTEVN) <lb/>ASMYNTLWRVNGQSA <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 08:05 (35.19), HLA-DRB1 * 13:01 (49.45), HLA-DRB1 * 12:05 (52.01), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 12:02 (60.35), HLA-DRB1 * 12:03 (50.74), HLA-DRB1 * 01:23 (62.08), <lb/>HLA-DRB1 * 01:26 (66.37), HLA-DRB1 * 01:20 (74.19), HLA-DRB1 * 01:06 (73.79), <lb/>HLA-DRB5 * 02:05 (44.37), HLA-DRB1 * 11:01 (70) <lb/>11 <lb/>82.45 <lb/>(LWRVNGQSA) <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Immunology Research <lb/></note>

			<body>was used. The protein frustratometer server [41] was <lb/>employed for the detection of the stability and energy differ-<lb/>ences of the 3D structure of the protein. <lb/>2.6. Molecular Docking Analysis and HLA Allele Interaction. <lb/>Docking studies were also performed using the best possible <lb/>epitope following the strategy used in previous studies <lb/>[27, 28]. AutoDock Vina [42] was used for the docking <lb/>analysis. In our study, we have selected the HLA-E * 01:01 <lb/>molecule as a candidate for MHC class I and the HLA-<lb/>DQA1 as a candidate for MHC class II for docking analysis <lb/>because they are the available hits in the Protein Data Bank <lb/>(PDB) database. The PDB structure 2ESV, human cytomeg-<lb/>alovirus complexes with T-cell receptors, VMAPRTLIL <lb/>peptide, and 3PL6-structure of autoimmune TCR <lb/>Hy.1B11 in complex with HLA-DQ1-were retrieved from <lb/>the Research Collaboratory for Structural Bioinformatics <lb/>(RCSB) protein database [43]. Then, the structures were <lb/>simplified by using PyMOL (the PyMOL Molecular Graphics <lb/>System, Version 1.5.0.4, Schrödinger, LLC) for the final <lb/>docking purpose. <lb/>The PEP-FOLD server [44] was used for the conversion <lb/>of the 3D structure of the epitope &quot;IELAGTLTL&quot; for MHC <lb/>I and the epitope &quot;KAIELAGTLTLTGTP&quot; for the MHC II <lb/>molecule in order to analyse the interaction with HLA alleles. <lb/>Finally, molecular docking was performed at the center of <lb/>X: 77.8087, Y: −3.2264, and Z: −9.5769 and the dimensions <lb/>(angstrom) of X: 31.4432, Y: 29.9517, and Z: 19.0455 for <lb/>the MHC I molecules. For the MHC II molecules, docking <lb/>was performed at the center of X: 38.5584, Y: 46.6132, and <lb/>Z: −36.4392 and the dimensions (angstrom) of X: 34.8104, <lb/>Y: 40.4401, and Z: 37.3366. Additionally, we have per-<lb/>formed a control docking with the experimentally known <lb/>peptide-MHC-bound complex. The PDB structure 2ESV, <lb/>human cytomegalovirus complexes with T-cell receptors, <lb/>and VMAPRTLIL peptide were used for this purpose. The <lb/>gridline was used at the center of X: 77.3404, Y: −3.5159, <lb/>and Z: −9.5829. <lb/>2.7. Allergenicity Investigation and B-Cell Epitope Prediction. <lb/>The AllerHunter server [45] was used to predict the <lb/>allergenicity of our proposed epitope for further securing <lb/>the prediction, and the support vector machine (SVM) <lb/>algorithm was used for the prediction within the server <lb/>[46]. The predicted T-cell epitope (15-mer) was screened <lb/>by IEDB-AR using a number of web-based tools for the <lb/>suitability as the B-cell epitope [47-49]. <lb/>3. Results <lb/>3.1. Analysis of the Retrieved Sequences and Their Antigenicity. <lb/>A total of 44 SigA proteins from different variants of S. flex-<lb/>neri, S. dysenteriae, S. boydii, and S. sonnei were retrieved from <lb/>the GenBank database (Table S1 in Supplementary Material <lb/>available online at https://doi.org/10.1155/2017/6412353). <lb/>Thereafter, analyses with the VaxiJen v2.0 server showed the <lb/>protein with the accession number of gi|745767180| to have <lb/>the highest antigenicity of 0.6699 (Table S1). This highly <lb/>antigenic protein was further analysed to detect the highly <lb/>immunogenic epitope. No significant entry was found in the <lb/>orthologous entry search of our targeted protein. <lb/>3.2. T-Cell Epitope Identification. The NetCTLv1.2 server <lb/>identified the T-cell epitopes, where the epitope prediction <lb/>was confined to 12 MHC class I supertypes. Based on the <lb/>combined score, the top twelve epitopes (Table 1) were listed <lb/>for further analysis. <lb/>3.3. MHC Restriction and Cluster Analysis. IEDB analysis <lb/>resource predicted both MHC class I and MHC class II <lb/>restricted allele on the basis of the IC 50 value. All the pre-<lb/>dicted epitopes in Table 1 were assessed for the MHC inter-<lb/>action analysis. Epitopes for the MHC class I alleles are <lb/>presented in Table 2. The peptide IELAGTLTLT was pre-<lb/>dicted to have the highest number of MHC class I binding. <lb/>This peptide was predicted to have the binding affinity with <lb/>five MHC class I alleles including HLA-E * 01:01, HLA-<lb/>B * 40:01, HLA-B * 15:02, HLA-C * 03:03, and HLA-C * 12:03. <lb/>Furthermore, the interacted alleles were reassessed by clus-<lb/>ter analysis and are shown in Figure 2(a), as a heat map, <lb/>and in Figure S1A, as a dynamic tree. The peptides were <lb/>reassessed by the EPISOPT software for the HLA I binding, <lb/>Table 4: Conservancy analysis of all the epitopes with appropriate length. <lb/>Epitope <lb/>Conservancy <lb/>Length <lb/>Epitope <lb/>Conservancy <lb/>Length <lb/>VTARAGLGY <lb/>84.09% <lb/>9 <lb/>VTARAGLGYQFDLFA <lb/>84.09% <lb/>15 <lb/>SMYNTLWRV <lb/>100% <lb/>9 <lb/>ASMYNTLWRVNGQSA <lb/>100% <lb/>15 <lb/>KSYMSGNYK <lb/>97.73% <lb/>9 <lb/>AAKSYMSGNYKAFLT <lb/>97.73% <lb/>15 <lb/>NYAWVNGNI <lb/>100% <lb/>9 <lb/>AQNYAWVNGNIKSDK <lb/>97.73% <lb/>15 <lb/>HTTWTLTGY <lb/>97.73% <lb/>9 <lb/>No prediction <lb/>Undetected <lb/>15 <lb/>APKGSNKEI <lb/>100% <lb/>9 <lb/>No prediction <lb/>Undetected <lb/>15 <lb/>YMSGNYKAF <lb/>97.73% <lb/>9 <lb/>SYMSGNYKAFLTEVN <lb/>97.73% <lb/>15 <lb/>ARAGLGYQF <lb/>84.09% <lb/>9 <lb/>VTARAGLGYQFDLFA <lb/>84.09% <lb/>15 <lb/>FHTVTVNTL <lb/>100% <lb/>9 <lb/>NSGFHTVTVNTLDAT <lb/>100% <lb/>15 <lb/>IELAGTLTL <lb/>100% <lb/>9 <lb/>KAIELAGTLTLTGTP <lb/>100% <lb/>15 <lb/>IASFSQPDW <lb/>97.73% <lb/>9 <lb/>NNQIASFSQPDWESR <lb/>97.73% <lb/>15 <lb/>YMSGNYKAF <lb/>97.73% <lb/>9 <lb/>SYMSGNYKAFLTEVN <lb/>97.73% <lb/>15 <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Immunology Research <lb/></note>

			<body>and IELAGTLTL was found to have affinity with six HLA I <lb/>alleles (Table S3). From this analysis, we selected top four <lb/>peptides VTARAGLGY, FHTVTVNTL, HTTWTLTGY, <lb/>and IELAGTLTL depending on the affinity with most <lb/>MHC class I. <lb/>Epitopes for the MHC class II alleles are presented in <lb/>Table 3. Depending on the IC 50 values as well as on the <lb/>number of MHC class II alleles, three 15-mer peptide candi-<lb/>dates were selected. The peptides NSGFHTVTVNTLDAT, <lb/>KAIELAGTLTLTGTP, and AAKSYMSGNYKAFLT were <lb/>predicted to have high affinity with MHC-II allele, which <lb/>can interact with 32, 29, and 24 MHC class II alleles. The data <lb/>has been validated by another software PREDIVAC. The pre-<lb/>divac scores of the two core peptides FHTVTVNTL and <lb/>IELAGTLTL have been shown to be promising for their <lb/>binding to HLA_DRB_1 (Table 3). Accumulating both <lb/>MHC class I allele-and MHC class II allele-based analyses, <lb/>we showed FHTVTVNTL and IELAGTLTL peptides to have <lb/>the best score to be a vaccine potential. <lb/>3.4. Conservancy Analysis and Position of the Epitopes. Con-<lb/>servancy of all the proposed epitopes was assessed by the <lb/>IEDB conservancy analysis tool and is summarized in <lb/>Table 4. FHTVTVNTL, IELAGTLTL, NYAWVNGNI, and <lb/>SMYNTLWRV were shown to have 100% conserved regions <lb/>across all the SigA proteins. The position of all the predicted <lb/>epitopes is shown in a multiple sequence alignment of SigA <lb/>proteins in Figure 3. Here, we used only our desired <lb/>sequences for the proper annotation. So, from the most <lb/>potential candidates, only two, that is, FHTVTVNTL and <lb/>IELAGTLTL, were found to be fully conserved. The top four <lb/>epitopes were shown within the protein in Figure 4. The <lb/>conservancy of both of these peptides were crosschecked <lb/>by PVS software, and it was found that they were located <lb/>in the conserved region of the SigA protein (Figure S5). <lb/>gi|647302223| Y K S <lb/>600 <lb/>610 <lb/>740 <lb/>750 <lb/>780 <lb/>N NQ I A S F S Q P DW E S R A I E LAG T L T TGTP <lb/>TGTP <lb/>TGTP <lb/>TGTP <lb/>TGTP <lb/>TGTP <lb/>TGTP <lb/>L <lb/>QN Y W V N G NIKAS <lb/>840 <lb/>870 <lb/>880 <lb/>MYNT LW RV E N S <lb/>E NS <lb/>E NS <lb/>E NS <lb/>E NS <lb/>E NS <lb/>E NS <lb/>G F HTVTVNT L <lb/>G F HTVTVNT L <lb/>G F HTVTVNT L <lb/>G F HTVTVNT L <lb/>G F HTVTVNT L <lb/>G F HTVTVNT L <lb/>G F HTVTVNT L <lb/>F HTVTVNT L <lb/>SMYNT LWRV <lb/>SMYNT LWRV <lb/>SMYNT LWRV <lb/>SMYNT LWRV <lb/>SMYNT LWRV <lb/>SMYNT LWRV <lb/>SMYNT LWRV <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>Q NY WVNGN I K <lb/>A <lb/>Q NY WVNGN I K <lb/>A <lb/>Q NY WVNGN I K <lb/>A <lb/>Q NY WVNGN I K <lb/>A <lb/>Q NY WVNGN I K <lb/>A <lb/>Q NY WVNGN I K <lb/>A <lb/>NY WVNGN I <lb/>A <lb/>I E LAGT L T L <lb/>I E LAGT L T L <lb/>I E LAGT L T L <lb/>I E LAGT L T L <lb/>I E LAGT L T L <lb/>I E LAGT L T L <lb/>I E LAGT L T L <lb/>K <lb/>E S R A <lb/>K <lb/>E S R A <lb/>K <lb/>E S R A <lb/>K <lb/>E S R A <lb/>K <lb/>E S R A <lb/>K <lb/>E S R A <lb/>K <lb/>I A S F S Q P DW <lb/>I A S F S Q P DW <lb/>I A S F S Q P DW <lb/>I A S F S Q P DW <lb/>I A S F S Q P DW <lb/>I A S F S Q P DW <lb/>I A S F S Q P DW <lb/>Y K S N NQ <lb/>Y K S N NQ <lb/>Y K S N NQ <lb/>Y K S N NQ <lb/>Y K S N NQ <lb/>Y K S N NQ <lb/>gi|446956855| <lb/>gi|844758686| <lb/>gi|446956853| <lb/>gi|446956854| <lb/>gi|693049347| <lb/>gi|699401135| <lb/>Conservation <lb/>gi|647302223| <lb/>940 <lb/>T A P KGS N K E I F Q E HTTWT L T GYKVA E N T AS S GAA K S YMS GNYK AF L <lb/>VT AR AG L G YQ F D <lb/>VT AR AG L G YQ F D <lb/>VT AR AG L G YQ F D <lb/>VT AR AG L G YQ F D <lb/>VT AR AG L G YQ F D <lb/>VT AR AG L G YQ F D <lb/>VT AR AG L G YQ F <lb/>VT AR AG L G Y <lb/>AR AG L G YQ F <lb/>D <lb/>K S YMS GNYK AF L <lb/>K S YMS GNYK AF L <lb/>K S YMS GNYK AF L <lb/>K S YMS GNYK AF L <lb/>K S YMS GNYK AF L <lb/>K S YMS GNYK AF <lb/>K S YMS GNYK <lb/>YM S GN Y K A F <lb/>L <lb/>Q E HTTWT L T GYKVA E N T AS S GAA <lb/>Q E HTTWT L T GYKVA E N T AS S GAA <lb/>Q E HTTWT L T GYKVA E N T A S S GA A <lb/>Q E HT TWT L T G YKVA E N T AS S GAA <lb/>Q E HTTWT L T G YKVA E N T AS S GAA <lb/>Q E HTTWT L T GY <lb/>HTTWT L T G Y <lb/>KVA E N T A S S GA A <lb/>T A P KGS N K E I F <lb/>T A P KGS N K E I F <lb/>T A P KGS N K E I F <lb/>T A P KGS N K E I F <lb/>T A P KGS N K E I F <lb/>T A P KGS N <lb/>Conservation <lb/>K E I <lb/>A P KGS N K E I <lb/>F <lb/>970 <lb/>980 <lb/>990 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1210 <lb/>gi|446956855| <lb/>gi|844758686| <lb/>gi|446956853| <lb/>gi|446956854| <lb/>gi|693049347| <lb/>gi|699401135| <lb/>Figure 3: MSA-based location identification of the different epitopes within the SPATE proteins of Shigella and their homologue in E. coli. In <lb/>this figure, gi|647302223|, gi|446956855|, gi|844758686|, and gi|446956853| represent the S. flexneri, S. sonnei, S. boydii, and S. dysenteriae, <lb/>respectively. E. coli represented by gi|693049347| and gi|699401135|. <lb/>Figure 4: The three-dimensional model of SPATE subfamily <lb/>protein SigA with the proposed epitopes VTARAGLGY <lb/>(magenta), FHTVTVNTL (yellow), HTTWTLTGY (green), and <lb/>IELAGTLTL (red). The superficial localities of the epitopes <lb/>indicate their surface accessibility. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Journal of Immunology Research <lb/></note>

			<body>The epitopes are precisely positioned on the surface of the <lb/>protein indicating that they would be accessible to the <lb/>immune system, especially by B-cells. <lb/>3.5. Model Validation Structural Frustration Analysis. <lb/>MODELLER modelled the three-dimensional structure of <lb/>the targeted protein through the best multiple template-<lb/>based modelling approach. The validation of the model <lb/>was measured by the PROCHECK server through the <lb/>Ramachandran plot and is depicted in Figure S2, where <lb/>88.8% amino acid residues were found within the favoured <lb/>region. Furthermore, the predicted model was also assessed <lb/>for the frustration analysis and is depicted in Figure 5. The <lb/>DISOPRED server likewise assessed the disorder of the <lb/>protein sequences in order to get an understanding about <lb/>the disorder among the targeted sequences, which is shown <lb/>in Figure S3. <lb/>3.6. Population Coverage Analysis. IEDB analysis resource <lb/>predicted both MHC class I-and MHC class II-based <lb/>coverage of the selected epitopes for the world popula-<lb/>tion to assess the feasibility of being a potential vaccine <lb/>candidate. The combined prediction was also assessed. <lb/>The epitope &quot;IELAGTLTLT&quot; has the highest population <lb/>coverage of 83.86% for the whole world population <lb/>(shown graphically in Figure 6); however, another potential <lb/>epitope &quot;FHTVTVNTL&quot; was shown to have 50.61% popula-<lb/>tion coverage (Table S2). <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>Figure 5: The configurational frustration index of the predicted model of the SigA. (a) This analysis detects the stability and energy <lb/>differences of the 3D structure of the protein. Colours are in accordance with their frustration index. The red colour regions are highly <lb/>frustrated and the green colour regions are not frustrated. The frustrated residues are able to change their identity and also displace the <lb/>location in any favourable conditions. (b) The locations of our proposed epitopes are described by different colours. The epitopes <lb/>HTTWTLTGY (cyan) and IELAGTLTL (blue) are well outside of the frustrated regions and securing their stability. On the other hand, <lb/>the epitopes VTARAGLGY (yellow) and FHTVTVNTL (orange) are in the frustrated regions and unable to secure their stability. <lb/>Cumulative percent of population coverage <lb/>World-Class I and II coverage <lb/>Percent of individuals <lb/>Coumulative percent of population coverage <lb/>65 <lb/>60 <lb/>55 <lb/>50 <lb/>45 <lb/>40 <lb/>35 <lb/>30 <lb/>25 <lb/>20 <lb/>15 <lb/>10 <lb/>5 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>90 <lb/>PC90 <lb/>80 <lb/>70 <lb/>60 <lb/>50 <lb/>40 <lb/>30 <lb/>20 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>Number of epitope hits/HLA combinations recognized <lb/>Figure 6: Population coverage analysis for the top predicted epitope based on the HLA interaction. Here, the whole world populations are <lb/>assessed for the proposed epitope. The combined prediction for both of the MHC has been shown. Here, the number 1 bar for all the <lb/>analyses represents out-predicted epitope. Notes: in the graphs, the line (-o-) represents the cumulative percentage of population coverage <lb/>of the epitopes; the bars represent the population coverage for each epitope. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Immunology Research <lb/></note>

			<body>3.7. Molecular Docking Analysis. The core epitope <lb/>(IELAGTLTL) with 9.0 mer and its 15-mer extension (KAIE-<lb/>LAGTLTLTGTP) were bound in the groove of the HLA-<lb/>E * 01:01 and HLA-DQA1 with an energy of −7.8 and <lb/>−9.7 kcal/mol, respectively. AutoDock Vina generated differ-<lb/>ent poses of the docked peptide, and the best one was picked <lb/>for the final calculation at an RMSD (root-mean-square devi-<lb/>ation) value of 0.0. The docking interface was visualized with <lb/>the PyMOL Molecular Graphics System. The 9.0-mer epitope <lb/>interacted with Arg-61, Asn-62, and Glu-152 through steric <lb/>interaction and formed hydrogen bonding with the Glu-156 <lb/>amino acid residues. On the other hand, the 15-mer epitope <lb/>interacted with Asp-55 through electrostatic interaction and <lb/>Glu-66 through steric interaction and formed hydrogen <lb/>bonding with the Gly-58, Arg-61, Asn-62, and Asn-82 amino <lb/>acid residues. The docking output and the interacted residues <lb/>are shown in Figures 7 and 8 with different orientations. <lb/>Furthermore, the control docking energy was found to be <lb/>−6.8 kcal/mol and is illustrated in Figure S4. <lb/>3.8. Allergenicity Analysis. The AllerHunter web server <lb/>predicted the sequence-based allergenicity calculation very <lb/>precisely. The allergenicity of the queried core epitope <lb/>(IELAGTLTLT) was 0.05 (sensitivity = 98.40%, specific-<lb/>ity = 27.4%), and the allergenicity of the 15-mer epitope <lb/>(KAIELAGTLTLTGTP) was 0.05 (sensitivity = 98.4%, <lb/>specificity = 27.0%). <lb/>3.9. B-Cell Epitope Prediction. B-cell epitope prediction was <lb/>obtained for the peptide KAIELAGTLTLTGTP (15 mer) <lb/>through the sequence-based approaches, and values are <lb/>anticipated with different parameters, ranging from −0.6464 <lb/>to 1.137. These values are the different propensity scores <lb/>and predicted with a threshold ranging from −0.352 to <lb/>1.037 (Figure 9). The Kolaskar and Tongaonkar antigenicity <lb/>scale was employed for evaluating the antigenic property of <lb/>the peptide with a maximum of 1.072. The antigenic plot is <lb/>showed in Figure 9(a). Peptide surface accessibility is another <lb/>important benchmark to meet up the criteria of a potential <lb/>B-cell epitope. Henceforth, Emini surface accessibility pre-<lb/>diction was employed, with a maximum propensity score of <lb/>1.137 (Figure 9(b)). To reinforce our provision for the predic-<lb/>tion of the epitope to elicit B-cell response, the Parker hydro-<lb/>philicity prediction was also employed with a maximum <lb/>score of 1.086 and is depicted in Figure 9(c). <lb/>4. Discussion <lb/>Enteric infections are the foremost cause of sickness and <lb/>impermanence throughout the world, and only the Shigella <lb/>infections resulted in over a million deaths annually [2]. <lb/>The ever rising multidrug-resistant (MDR) strains of the <lb/>Shigella bacteria area unit are another international con-<lb/>cern for the researchers to search out a brand new resolu-<lb/>tion for preventing the deaths [50, 51]. Recently, there are <lb/>several studies that focus on the development of the vac-<lb/>cine against Shigella and continue in the clinical trial. <lb/>Most of them use attenuated and inactivated preparation <lb/>of the bacteria for eliciting immune responses which has <lb/>some potential escape risk [52-54]. In this study, we have <lb/>90°( <lb/>a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>Arg 65 <lb/>Asp 69 <lb/>Glu 152 <lb/>Glu 156 <lb/>(c) <lb/>Figure 7: Docking analysis of the predicted epitope IELAGTLTL and HLA-E allele. (a) Representing the oriented view of the interaction and <lb/>assuring the perfect binding. (b) Representing the cartoon view. (c) Embodying the interacted residues with the peptide. <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Immunology Research <lb/></note>

			<body>tried to find out alternatives to treat this global burden <lb/>through vaccinomics approaches and targeting the immu-<lb/>nogenic and toxic protein SigA. The sequences of different <lb/>strains of Shigella showed that there is a little island of <lb/>conserved sequence throughout the species [55], and we <lb/>have focused on that target for designing the vaccine <lb/>candidate. The orthologous entry search of our targeted <lb/>protein revealed no significant similarity with human <lb/>pathogens and other closely related pathogens. These results <lb/>further strengthen our prediction through confirming no <lb/>cross immunity. <lb/>In recent time, most of the vaccines are grounded on B-<lb/>cell immunity; vaccines based on a T-cell epitope have been <lb/>invigorated lately. This is often as a result of body substance <lb/>response from memory B-cells which may be overawed basi-<lb/>cally by matter drift as time goes on, whereas cell-mediated <lb/>immunity repeatedly long-run immunity [56, 57]. <lb/>As a consequence, a T-lymphocyte epitope elicits a robust <lb/>and distinctive immune response through the cytotoxic <lb/>lymphocyte-(CTL-) mediated pathway and impedes the <lb/>spreading of the infectious agents by the CTL through recog-<lb/>nizing and killing the infected cells or by secreting specific <lb/>cytokines [58]. <lb/>The epitopes VTARAGLGY, FHTVTVNTL, HTTW <lb/>TLTGY, and IELAGTLTL are primarily selected for the <lb/>designing of vaccine from the initial analysis depending on <lb/>the affinity with MHC class I and additionally confirmed <lb/>their presence along with those of the ancestral homologue <lb/>in E. coli (Figure 2). Finally, through substantiation with <lb/>different parameters, the core epitopes IELAGTLTL and <lb/>FHTVTVNTL (in 15.0-mer form, KAIELAGTLTLTGTP <lb/>and NSGFHTVTVNTLDAT, resp.) were found to be the <lb/>most potential and highly interacting HLA candidates for <lb/>MHC class II molecule. Furthermore, we have used <lb/>90°( <lb/>a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>Glu 66 B <lb/>Asn 82 B <lb/>Asp 55 A <lb/>Gly 58 A <lb/>Arg 61 A <lb/>Asn 62 A <lb/>(c) <lb/>Figure 8: Docking analysis of the predicted epitope KAIELAGTLTLTGTP and HLA-DQA1 allele. (a) Representing the oriented view of the <lb/>interaction and assuring the perfect binding. (b) Representing the cartoon view. (c) Embodying the interacted residues with the peptide. <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Immunology Research <lb/></note>

			<body>pSORTb to predict the subcellular localization of SigA and <lb/>found that there is a score of 5.87 for localization in the <lb/>outer membrane and another score of 4.13 for extracellu-<lb/>lar localization. The result was quite similar with that for <lb/>the localization of other SPATE proteins in the bacterial <lb/>cell surface as well as in secreted forms. <lb/>three-dimensional model built through MODEL-<lb/>LER and validated by the Ramachandran plot with an <lb/>acceptable range resulted in the display of the perfect posi-<lb/>tion of the epitope on the surface of the structure. As the <lb/>epitope was found on the surface (Figure 4) of the model, it <lb/>would increase the possibility to interact with the immune <lb/>system earlier. Furthermore, the analysis from the DIS-<lb/>OPRED and frustration analysis servers strengthen our <lb/>prediction, though there are no disorder and energy frustra-<lb/>tion in the epitope region of the sequences and model, <lb/>respectively (Figure 5 and Figure S3). <lb/>To get the acceptability, vaccine candidates must have <lb/>wider population coverage. This is very much important <lb/>before designing. In our analysis, we have found that our <lb/>proposed epitope IELAGTLTL had combined population <lb/>coverage of 83.86%, whereas the other most potential can-<lb/>didate FHTVTVNTL had combined population coverage <lb/>of 50.61%. This output revealed that the proposed epitopes <lb/>would have wider coverage in vitro. <lb/>Molecular docking upkeeps the prediction with a higher <lb/>docking score and the perfectly oriented interactions between <lb/>the both MHC and the predicted 9.0-mer and 15-mer <lb/>epitopes. Additionally, comparative analysis with the experi-<lb/>mentally known peptide-MHC complex-has also revealed <lb/>the precision of our prediction through the similar binding <lb/>energy and interacted residues. Another significant finding <lb/>is the conservancy result. Through analysis of the whole <lb/>retrieved sequences, it was found that our predicted epitopes <lb/>have a 100% conservancy and hopefully they would be <lb/>potential candidates for treating all of the Shigella spp. Our <lb/>proposed epitopes are nonallergenic in nature according to <lb/>the FAO/WHO allergenicity evaluation scheme. <lb/>Finally, the core epitope &quot;IELAGTLTL&quot; was also found to <lb/>be more potential B-cell epitope candidates that were pro-<lb/>posed through the sequence-based approaches including <lb/>the Kolaskar and Tongaonkar antigenicity scale, Emini <lb/>surface accessibility prediction, and Parker hydrophilicity <lb/>prediction. From the overhead analysis, we envisage that <lb/>our suggested epitope would also elicit an immune response <lb/>in vitro. <lb/>Threshold <lb/>1.08 <lb/>1.07 <lb/>1.06 <lb/>1.05 <lb/>1.04 <lb/>1.03 <lb/>1.02 <lb/>1.01 <lb/>20 <lb/>0 <lb/>Position <lb/>Score <lb/>(a) <lb/>20 <lb/>Threshold <lb/>1.15 <lb/>1.10 <lb/>1.05 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.95 <lb/>0.90 <lb/>0 <lb/>Position <lb/>Score <lb/>(b) <lb/>20 <lb/>Threshold <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>-1.0 <lb/>-1.5 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>Position <lb/>Score <lb/>(c) <lb/>Figure 9: B-cell epitope prediction. (a) Kolaskar and Tongaonkar antigenicity prediction of the proposed epitope with a threshold value of <lb/>1.037. (b) Emini surface accessibility prediction of the proposed epitope, with a threshold value of 1.0. (c) Parker hydrophilicity prediction of <lb/>the epitope, with a threshold of −0.352. Notes: the x-axis and y-axis represent the sequence position and antigenic propensity, respectively. <lb/>The regions above the threshold are antigenic (desired), shown in yellow. <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Immunology Research <lb/></note>

			<body>5. Conclusion <lb/>The improved knowledge about antigen recognition at <lb/>molecular level led us to the development of rationally <lb/>designed peptide vaccines. The idea of peptide vaccines is <lb/>based on detecting and chemical synthesis of immunodomi-<lb/>nant B-cell and T-cell epitopes capable of evoking specific <lb/>immune responses. In this study, we used different compu-<lb/>tational tools to identify potential epitope targets against <lb/>Shigella which will help to decrease the cost and time of <lb/>wet lab experiments more successfully. Our bioinformatic <lb/>analyses speculate that the selected part of the outer mem-<lb/>brane and highly immunogenic protein, SigA, is a potential <lb/>candidate for a peptide vaccine. It might also contribute to <lb/>the reduction in the SigA-mediated pathogenicity to the host. <lb/>However, further wet lab validation is necessary to confirm <lb/>the efficiency of our identified peptide sequence as an epitope <lb/>vaccine against Shigella. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Abbreviations <lb/>SPATE: Serine protease autotransporter of enterobacteria <lb/>HEp-2: Human epithelial cell type-2 <lb/>MHC-I: Major histocompatibility complex class I <lb/>MHC-II: Major histocompatibility complex class II <lb/>MSA: <lb/>Multiple sequence alignment <lb/>GMMA: Generalized modules of membrane antigens <lb/>CTL: <lb/>Cytotoxic T-lymphocyte <lb/>TAP: <lb/>Transporter of antigenic peptide <lb/>SMM: <lb/>Stabilized matrix method <lb/>HLA: <lb/>Human leukocyte antigen. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Additional Points <lb/>Availability of Data and Materials. Information about the <lb/>data and their availability is intricately described in Methods. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Ethical Approval <lb/>As samples from human or animals had not been used in this <lb/>study, ethical clearance is not applicable. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Consent <lb/>Patient consent is not applicable. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Conflicts of Interest <lb/>No potential competing interest was reported by the authors. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Authors&apos; Contributions <lb/>Arafat Rahman Oany conceived, designed, and guided the <lb/>study; drafted the manuscript; and analysed the data. <lb/>Tahmina Pervin, Mamun Mia, and Motaher Hossain carried <lb/>out the molecular genetic studies, participated in the sequence <lb/>alignment, and drafted the manuscript. Mohammad Shahnaij <lb/>helped in the design of the study. Shahin Mahmud helped in <lb/>drafting the manuscript. K. M. Kaderi Kibria participated in <lb/>the design and coordination, performed critical revision, <lb/>and helped in drafting the manuscript. All authors read and <lb/>approved the final manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] T. L. Hale and G. T. Keusch, &quot;Shigella,&quot; in Medical Microbiol-<lb/>ogy, S. Baron, Ed., University of Texas Medical Branch at <lb/>Galveston, Galveston (TX), USA, 1996, Chapter 22. <lb/>[2] K. L. Kotloff, J. P. Winickoff, B. Ivanoff et al., &quot;Global burden of <lb/>Shigella infections: implications for vaccine development and <lb/>implementation of control strategies,&quot; Bulletin of the World <lb/>Health Organization, vol. 77, no. 8, p. 651, 1999. <lb/>[3] L. von Seidlein, D. R. Kim, M. Ali et al., &quot;A multicentre <lb/>study of Shigella diarrhoea in six Asian countries: disease <lb/>burden, clinical manifestations, and microbiology,&quot; PLoS Med-<lb/>icine, vol. 3, no. 9, article e353, 2006. <lb/>[4] K. L. Kotloff, J. P. Nataro, W. C. Blackwelder et al., &quot;Burden <lb/>and aetiology of diarrhoeal disease in infants and young chil-<lb/>dren in developing countries (the Global Enteric Multicenter <lb/>Study, GEMS): a prospective, case-control study,&quot; Lancet, <lb/>vol. 382, no. 9888, p. 209, 2003. <lb/>[5] S. Dutta, K. Rajendran, S. Roy et al., &quot;Shifting serotypes, plas-<lb/>mid profile analysis and antimicrobial resistance pattern of <lb/>shigellae strains isolated from Kolkata, India during 1995-<lb/>2000,&quot; Epidemiology and Infection, vol. 129, no. 2, p. 235, 2002. <lb/>[6] M. A. Salam, U. Dhar, W. A. Khan, and M. L. Bennish, &quot;Ran-<lb/>domised comparison of ciprofloxacin suspension and pivme-<lb/>cillinam for childhood shigellosis,&quot; Lancet, vol. 352, no. 9127, <lb/>p. 522, 1998. <lb/>[7] K. A. Talukder, B. K. Khajanchi, M. A. Islam et al., &quot;Genetic <lb/>relatedness of ciprofloxacin-resistant Shigella dysenteriae type <lb/>1 strains isolated in south Asia,&quot; The Journal of Antimicrobial <lb/>Chemotherapy, vol. 54, no. 4, p. 730, 2004. <lb/>[8] K. A. Talukder, B. K. Khajanchi, M. A. Islam et al., &quot;Fluoro-<lb/>quinolone resistance linked to both gyrA and parC mutations <lb/>in the quinolone resistance-determining region of Shigella dys-<lb/>enteriae type 1,&quot; Current Microbiology, vol. 52, no. 2, p. 108, <lb/>2006. <lb/>[9] I. R. Henderson, F. Navarro-Garcia, and J. P. Nataro, &quot;The <lb/>great escape: structure and function of the autotransporter <lb/>proteins,&quot; Trends in Microbiology, vol. 6, no. 9, p. 370, 1998. <lb/>[10] K. Al-Hasani, F. Navarro-Garcia, J. Huerta, H. Sakellaris, and <lb/>B. Adler, &quot;The immunogenic SigA enterotoxin of Shigella flex-<lb/>neri 2a binds to HEp-2 cells and induces fodrin redistribution <lb/>in intoxicated epithelial cells,&quot; PLoS One, vol. 4, no. 12, article <lb/>e8223, 2009. <lb/>[11] K. Al-Hasani, I. R. Henderson, H. Sakellaris et al., &quot;The sigA <lb/>gene which is borne on the shepathogenicity island of Shigella <lb/>flexneri 2a encodes an exported cytopathic protease involved <lb/>in intestinal fluid accumulation,&quot; Infection and Immunity, <lb/>vol. 68, no. 5, p. 2457, 2000. <lb/>[12] F. Berlanda Scorza, A. M. Colucci, L. Maggiore et al., &quot;High <lb/>yield production process for Shigella outer membrane parti-<lb/>cles,&quot; PLoS One, vol. 7, no. 6, article e35616, 2012. <lb/>[13] A. Sette, M. Newman, B. Livingston et al., &quot;Optimizing vaccine <lb/>design for cellular processing, MHC binding and TCR recog-<lb/>nition,&quot; Tissue Antigens, vol. 59, no. 6, p. 443, 2002. <lb/>[14] G. A. Poland, I. G. Ovsyannikova, and R. M. Jacobson, &quot;Appli-<lb/>cation of pharmacogenomics to vaccines,&quot; Pharmacogenomics, <lb/>vol. 10, no. 5, p. 837, 2009. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Immunology Research <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[15] S. P. Singh and B. N. Mishra, &quot;Major histocompatibility com-<lb/>plex linked databases and prediction tools for designing vac-<lb/>cines,&quot; Human Immunology, vol. 77, no. 3, p. 295, 2016. <lb/>[16] V. Brusic, G. Rudy, and L. C. Harrison, &quot;MHCPEP, a database <lb/>of MHC-binding peptides: update 1997,&quot; Nucleic Acids <lb/>Research, vol. 26, no. 1, p. 368, 1998. <lb/>[17] H. Rammensee, J. Bachmann, N. P. Emmerich, O. A. Bachor, <lb/>and S. Stevanovic, &quot;SYFPEITHI: database for MHC ligands <lb/>and peptide motifs,&quot; Immunogenetics, vol. 50, no. 3-4, p. 213, <lb/>1999. <lb/>[18] C. C. Wilson, D. McKinney, M. Anders et al., &quot;Development of <lb/>a DNA vaccine designed to induce cytotoxic T lymphocyte <lb/>responses to multiple conserved epitopes in HIV-1,&quot; Journal <lb/>of Immunology, vol. 171, no. 10, p. 5611, 2003. <lb/>[19] D. N. Bourdette, E. Edmonds, C. Smith et al., &quot;A highly immu-<lb/>nogenic trivalent T cell receptor peptide vaccine for multiple <lb/>sclerosis,&quot; Multiple Sclerosis, vol. 11, no. 5, p. 552, 2005. <lb/>[20] H. L. Robinson and R. R. Amara, &quot;T cell vaccines for <lb/>microbial infections,&quot; Nature Medicine, vol. 11, article S25, <lb/>Supplement 4, 2005. <lb/>[21] J. A. Lopez, C. Weilenman, R. Audran et al., &quot;A synthetic <lb/>malaria vaccine elicits a potent CD8 + and CD4 + T lymphocyte <lb/>immune response in humans. Implications for vaccination <lb/>strategies,&quot; European Journal of Immunology, vol. 31, no. 7, <lb/>p. 1989, 2001. <lb/>[22] D. A. Benson, K. Clark, I. Karsch-Mizrachi, D. J. Lipman, <lb/>J. Ostell, and E. W. Sayers, &quot;GenBank,&quot; Nucleic Acids Research, <lb/>vol. 43, article D30, Database issue, 2008. <lb/>[23] I. A. Doytchinova and D. R. Flower, &quot;VaxiJen: a server for <lb/>prediction of protective antigens, tumour antigens and subunit <lb/>vaccines,&quot; BMC Bioinformatics, vol. 8, p. 4, 2007. <lb/>[24] S. F. Altschul, W. Gish, W. Miller, E. W. Myers, and D. J. <lb/>Lipman, &quot;Basic local alignment search tool,&quot; Journal of Molec-<lb/>ular Biology, vol. 215, no. 3, p. 403, 1990. <lb/>[25] F. Chen, A. J. Mackey, C. J. Stoeckert Jr., and D. S. Roos, <lb/>&quot;OrthoMCL-DB: querying a comprehensive multi-species <lb/>collection of ortholog groups,&quot; Nucleic Acids Research, <lb/>vol. 34, article D363, Database issue, 2006. <lb/>[26] S. P. Singh, K. Roopendra, and B. N. Mishra, &quot;Genome-wide <lb/>prediction of vaccine candidates for Leishmania major: an <lb/>integrated approach,&quot; Journal of Tropical Medicine, vol. 2015, <lb/>Article ID 709216, 14 pages, 2015. <lb/>[27] A. R. Oany, A. A. Emran, and T. P. Jyoti, &quot;Design of an <lb/>epitope-based peptide vaccine against spike protein of human <lb/>coronavirus: an in silico approach,&quot; Drug Design, Development <lb/>and Therapy, vol. 8, p. 1139, 2014. <lb/>[28] A. R. Oany, T. Sharmin, A. S. Chowdhury, T. P. Jyoti, and <lb/>M. A. Hasan, &quot;Highly conserved regions in Ebola virus <lb/>RNA dependent RNA polymerase may be act as a universal <lb/>novel peptide vaccine target: a computational approach,&quot; In <lb/>Silico Pharmacol, vol. 3, no. 1, p. 7, 2015. <lb/>[29] M. V. Larsen, C. Lundegaard, K. Lamberth, S. Buus, O. Lund, <lb/>and M. Nielsen, &quot;Large-scale validation of methods for cyto-<lb/>toxic T-lymphocyte epitope prediction,&quot; BMC Bioinformatics, <lb/>vol. 8, p. 424, 2007. <lb/>[30] S. Buus, S. L. Lauemoller, P. Worning et al., &quot;Sensitive quanti-<lb/>tative predictions of peptide-MHC binding by a &apos;Query by <lb/>Committee&apos; artificial neural network approach,&quot; Tissue Anti-<lb/>gens, vol. 62, no. 5, p. 378, 2003. <lb/>[31] P. Wang, J. Sidney, C. Dow, B. Mothe, A. Sette, and B. <lb/>Peters, &quot;A systematic assessment of MHC class II peptide <lb/>binding predictions and evaluation of a consensus approach,&quot; <lb/>PLoS Computational Biology, vol. 4, no. 4, article e1000048, <lb/>2008. <lb/>[32] P. Wang, J. Sidney, Y. Kim et al., &quot;Peptide binding predictions <lb/>for HLA DR, DP and DQ molecules,&quot; BMC Bioinformatics, <lb/>vol. 11, p. 568, 2010. <lb/>[33] M. Thomsen, C. Lundegaard, S. Buus, O. Lund, and M. <lb/>Nielsen, &quot;MHCcluster, a method for functional clustering of <lb/>MHC molecules,&quot; Immunogenetics, vol. 65, no. 9, p. 655, 2013. <lb/>[34] H. H. Bui, J. Sidney, W. Li, N. Fusseder, and A. Sette, &quot;Devel-<lb/>opment of an epitope conservancy analysis tool to facilitate <lb/>the design of epitope-based diagnostics and vaccines,&quot; BMC <lb/>Bioinformatics, vol. 8, p. 361, 2007. <lb/>[35] M. Garcia-Boronat, C. M. Diez-Rivero, E. L. Reinherz, and <lb/>P. A. Reche, &quot;PVS: a web server for protein sequence variability <lb/>analysis tuned to facilitate conserved epitope discovery,&quot; <lb/>Nucleic Acids Research, vol. 36, article W35, Web Server issue, <lb/>2008. <lb/>[36] H. H. Bui, J. Sidney, K. Dinh, S. Southwood, M. J. Newman, <lb/>and A. Sette, &quot;Predicting population coverage of T-cell <lb/>epitope-based diagnostics and vaccines,&quot; BMC Bioinformatics, <lb/>vol. 7, p. 153, 2006. <lb/>[37] A. Sali, L. Potterton, F. Yuan, H. van Vlijmen, and M. Karplus, <lb/>&quot;Evaluation of comparative protein modeling by MODEL-<lb/>LER,&quot; Proteins, vol. 23, no. 3, p. 318, 1995. <lb/>[38] R. A. Laskowski, J. A. Rullmannn, M. W. MacArthur, R. <lb/>Kaptein, and J. M. Thornton, &quot;AQUA and PROCHECK-<lb/>NMR: programs for checking the quality of protein structures <lb/>solved by NMR,&quot; Journal of Biomolecular NMR, vol. 8, no. 4, <lb/>p. 477, 1996. <lb/>[39] K. Arnold, L. Bordoli, J. Kopp, and T. Schwede, &quot;The SWISS-<lb/>MODEL workspace: a web-based environment for protein <lb/>structure homology modelling,&quot; Bioinformatics, vol. 22, no. 2, <lb/>p. 195, 2006. <lb/>[40] J. J. Ward, L. J. McGuffin, K. Bryson, B. F. Buxton, and D. T. <lb/>Jones, &quot;The DISOPRED server for the prediction of protein <lb/>disorder,&quot; Bioinformatics, vol. 20, no. 13, p. 2138, 2004. <lb/>[41] M. Jenik, R. G. Parra, L. G. Radusky, A. Turjanski, P. G. <lb/>Wolynes, and D. U. Ferreiro, &quot;Protein frustratometer: a tool <lb/>to localize energetic frustration in protein molecules,&quot; <lb/>Nucleic Acids Research, vol. 40, article W348, Web Server <lb/>issue, 2012. <lb/>[42] O. Trott and A. J. Olson, &quot;AutoDock Vina: improving the <lb/>speed and accuracy of docking with a new scoring function, <lb/>efficient optimization, and multithreading,&quot; Journal of Compu-<lb/>tational Chemistry, vol. 31, no. 2, p. 455, 2010. <lb/>[43] H. M. Berman, J. Westbrook, Z. Feng et al., &quot;The Protein Data <lb/>Bank,&quot; Nucleic Acids Research, vol. 28, no. 1, p. 235, 2000. <lb/>[44] P. Thevenet, Y. Shen, J. Maupetit, F. Guyon, P. Derreumaux, <lb/>and P. Tuffery, &quot;PEP-FOLD: an updated de novo structure <lb/>prediction server for both linear and disulfide bonded cyclic <lb/>peptides,&quot; Nucleic Acids Research, vol. 40, article W288, Web <lb/>Server issue, 2012. <lb/>[45] H. C. Muh, J. C. Tong, and M. T. Tammi, &quot;AllerHunter: a <lb/>SVM-pairwise system for assessment of allergenicity and aller-<lb/>gic cross-reactivity in proteins,&quot; PLoS One, vol. 4, no. 6, article <lb/>e5861, 2009. <lb/>[46] L. Liao and W. S. Noble, &quot;Combining pairwise sequence <lb/>similarity and support vector machines for detecting remote <lb/>protein evolutionary and structural relationships,&quot; Journal of <lb/>Computational Biology, vol. 10, no. 6, p. 857, 2003. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Journal of Immunology Research <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[47] A. S. Kolaskar and P. C. Tongaonkar, &quot;A semi-empirical <lb/>method for prediction of antigenic determinants on protein <lb/>antigens,&quot; FEBS Letters, vol. 276, no. 1-2, p. 172, 1990. <lb/>[48] E. A. Emini, J. V. Hughes, D. S. Perlow, and J. Boger, <lb/>&quot;Induction of hepatitis A virus-neutralizing antibody by a <lb/>virus-specific synthetic peptide,&quot; Journal of Virology, vol. 55, <lb/>no. 3, p. 836, 1985. <lb/>[49] J. M. Parker, D. Guo, and R. S. Hodges, &quot;New hydrophilicity <lb/>scale derived from high-performance liquid chromatography <lb/>peptide retention data: correlation of predicted surface resi-<lb/>dues with antigenicity and X-ray-derived accessible sites,&quot; <lb/>Biochemistry, vol. 25, no. 19, p. 5425, 1986. <lb/>[50] D. A. Rowe-Magnus and D. Mazel, &quot;The role of integrons in <lb/>antibiotic resistance gene capture,&quot; International Journal of <lb/>Medical Microbiology, vol. 292, no. 2, p. 115, 2002. <lb/>[51] K. Goh, D. Chua, B. Beck, M. L. McKee, and A. A. Bhagwat, <lb/>&quot;Arginine-dependent acid-resistance pathway in Shigella boy-<lb/>dii,&quot; Archives of Microbiology, vol. 193, no. 3, p. 179, 2011. <lb/>[52] R. Walker, &quot;New possibilities for the development of a com-<lb/>bined vaccine against ETEC and Shigella,&quot; BMJ Global Health, <lb/>vol. 1, no. 2, article A11, Supplement 2, 2017. <lb/>[53] M. S. Riddle, R. W. Kaminski, C. Di Paolo et al., &quot;Safety and <lb/>immunogenicity of a candidate bioconjugate vaccine against <lb/>Shigella flexneri 2a administered to healthy adults: a single-<lb/>blind, randomized phase I study,&quot; Clinical and Vaccine Immu-<lb/>nology, vol. 23, no. 12, p. 908, 2016. <lb/>[54] M. S. Riddle, R. W. Kaminski, C. Williams et al., &quot;Safety and <lb/>immunogenicity of an intranasal Shigella flexneri 2a invaplex <lb/>50 vaccine,&quot; Vaccine, vol. 29, no. 40, p. 7009, 2011. <lb/>[55] Q. Jin, Z. Yuan, J. Xu et al., &quot;Genome sequence of Shigella <lb/>flexneri 2a: insights into pathogenicity through comparison <lb/>with genomes of Escherichia coli K12 and O157,&quot; Nucleic <lb/>Acids Research, vol. 30, no. 20, p. 4432, 2002. <lb/>[56] R. Bacchetta, S. Gregori, and M. G. Roncarolo, &quot;CD4 + regula-<lb/>tory T cells: mechanisms of induction and effector function,&quot; <lb/>Autoimmunity Reviews, vol. 4, no. 8, p. 491, 2005. <lb/>[57] J. U. Igietseme, F. O. Eko, Q. He, and C. M. Black, &quot;Antibody <lb/>regulation of T-cell immunity: implications for vaccine <lb/>strategies against intracellular pathogens,&quot; Expert Review of <lb/>Vaccines, vol. 3, no. 1, p. 23, 2004. <lb/>[58] B. Shrestha and M. S. Diamond, &quot;Role of CD8 + T cells in <lb/>control of West Nile virus infection,&quot; Journal of Virology, <lb/>vol. 78, no. 15, p. 8312, 2004. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Journal of Immunology Research </note>


	</text>
</tei>
