<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Classification accuracy of structural and functional connectomes across different depressive phenotypes</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Hon Wah</forename>
            <surname>Yeung</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Aleks</forename>
            <surname>Stolicyn</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Xueyi</forename>
            <surname>Shen</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Mark J.</forename>
            <surname>Adams</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Liana</forename>
            <surname>Romaniuk</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Gladi</forename>
            <surname>Thng</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Colin R.</forename>
            <surname>Buchanan</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Elliot M.</forename>
            <surname>Tucker-Drob</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Mark E.</forename>
            <surname>Bastin</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Andrew M.</forename>
            <surname>McIntosh</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Simon R.</forename>
            <surname>Cox</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Keith M.</forename>
            <surname>Smith</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Heather C.</forename>
            <surname>Whalley</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-10-31T10:18:17.043048Z">31.10.2025 10:18:17</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.1162$1$imag_a_00064</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.1162/imag_a_00064</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Hon Wah Yeung, Aleks Stolicyn, Xueyi Shen, Mark J. Adams, Liana Romaniuk, Gladi Thng, Colin R. Buchanan, Elliot M. Tucker-Drob, Mark E. Bastin, Andrew M. McIntosh, Simon R. Cox, Keith M. Smith, Heather C. Whalley. (2024). Classification accuracy of structural and functional connectomes across different depressive phenotypes. Imaging Neuroscience, 2(None), None. DOI: 10.1162/imag_a_00064</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-10-31T10:18:17.043048Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-10-31T10:18:17.043048Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>RESEARCH <lb/>A generative model of the connectome with <lb/>dynamic axon growth <lb/>Yuanzhe Liu 1,2 , Caio Seguin 2,3 , Richard F. Betzel 3 , Daniel Han 4 , Danyal Akarca 5,6 , <lb/>Maria A. Di Biase 2,7 , and Andrew Zalesky 1,2 <lb/>1 Department of Biomedical Engineering, Faculty of Engineering and Information Technology, <lb/>The University of Melbourne, Melbourne, VIC, Australia <lb/>2 Melbourne Neuropsychiatry Centre, Department of Psychiatry, The University of Melbourne, Melbourne, VIC, Australia <lb/>3 <lb/>Department of Psychological and Brain Sciences, Indiana University, Bloomington, IN, USA <lb/>4 School of Mathematics and Statistics, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, Australia <lb/>5 MRC Cognition and Brain Sciences Unit, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, UK <lb/>6 <lb/>Department of Electrical and Electronic Engineering, Imperial College London, London, UK <lb/>7 Department of Psychiatry, Brigham and Women&apos;s Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA <lb/>Keywords: Generative model, Connectome, Network neuroscience, Axon simulation <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Connectome generative models, otherwise known as generative network models, provide insight <lb/>into the wiring principles underpinning brain network organization. While these models can <lb/>approximate numerous statistical properties of empirical networks, they typically fail to explicitly <lb/>characterize an important contributor to brain organization-axonal growth. Emulating the <lb/>chemoaffinity-guided axonal growth, we provide a novel generative model in which axons <lb/>dynamically steer the direction of propagation based on distance-dependent chemoattractive <lb/>forces acting on their growth cones. This simple dynamic growth mechanism, despite being solely <lb/>geometry-dependent, is shown to generate axonal fiber bundles with brain-like geometry and <lb/>features of complex network architecture consistent with the human brain, including lognormally <lb/>distributed connectivity weights, scale-free nodal degrees, small-worldness, and modularity. <lb/>We demonstrate that our model parameters can be fitted to individual connectomes, enabling <lb/>connectome dimensionality reduction and comparison of parameters between groups. Our work <lb/>offers an opportunity to bridge studies of axon guidance and connectome development, providing <lb/>new avenues for understanding neural development from a computational perspective. <lb/>AUTHOR SUMMARY <lb/>Generative models of the human connectome provide insight into principles driving brain <lb/>network development. However, current models do not capture axonal outgrowth, which is <lb/>crucial to the formation of neural circuits. We develop a novel generative connectome model <lb/>featuring dynamic axonal outgrowth, revealing the contribution of microscopic axonal guidance <lb/>to the network topology and axonal geometry of macroscopic connectomes. Simple axonal <lb/>outgrowth rules representing continuous chemoaffinity gradients are shown to generate complex, <lb/>brain-like topologies and realistic axonal fascicle architectures. Our model is sufficiently sensitive <lb/>to capture subtle interindividual differences in axonal outgrowth between healthy adults. Our <lb/>results are significant because they reveal core principles that may give rise to both complex brain <lb/>networks and brain-like axonal bundles, unifying neurogenesis across scales. <lb/>a n o p e n a c c e s s <lb/>j o u r n a l <lb/>Citation: Liu, Y., Seguin, C., Betzel, <lb/>R. F., Han, D., Akarca, D., Di Biase, <lb/>M. A., &amp; Zalesky, A. (2024). A generative <lb/>model of the connectome with dynamic <lb/>axon growth. Network Neuroscience, <lb/>8(4), 1192-1211. https://doi.org/10.1162 <lb/>/netn_a_00397 <lb/>DOI: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1162/netn_a_00397 <lb/>Supporting Information: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1162/netn_a_00397 <lb/>Received: 15 February 2024 <lb/>Accepted: 3 June 2024 <lb/>Competing Interests: The authors have <lb/>declared that no competing interests <lb/>exist. <lb/>Corresponding Authors: <lb/>Yuanzhe Liu <lb/>yuanzhel@student.unimelb.edu.au <lb/>Andrew Zalesky <lb/>azalesky@unimelb.edu.au <lb/>Handling Editor: <lb/>Michelle Girvan <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 <lb/>Massachusetts Institute of Technology <lb/>Published under a Creative Commons <lb/>Attribution 4.0 International <lb/>(CC BY 4.0) license <lb/>The MIT Press <lb/>Downloaded from http://direct.mit.edu/netn/article-pdf/8/4/1192/2479295/netn_a_00397.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></front>

        <body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>The network of axonal connections comprising a nervous system is known as the connectome <lb/>(Hagmann, 2005; Sporns et al., 2005). Connectomes display nonrandom topological charac-<lb/>teristics, such as small-worldness (SW) and modularity (Bassett &amp; Bullmore, 2017; Sporns &amp; <lb/>Betzel, 2016) as well as rich diversity in the strength of connections and regions (Buzsáki &amp; <lb/>Mizuseki, 2014). While connectome topological properties are well characterized, the under-<lb/>lying wiring principles that give rise to these properties are poorly understood. <lb/>Generative models offer one avenue to investigate principles governing connectome devel-<lb/>opment. Connectome-like networks have been generated in silico to model the micro-, meso-, <lb/>and macroscale neural connectivity of many organisms, including C. Elegans, Drosophila, <lb/>nonhuman mammals, and humans, through a variety of spatial, topological, and physiological <lb/>wiring rules (Akarca et al., 2023; Betzel et al., 2016; Beul et al., 2018; Ercsey-Ravasz et al., <lb/>2013; Faskowitz et al., 2018; Henriksen et al., 2016; Kaiser &amp; Hilgetag, 2004; Klimm et al., <lb/>2014; Oldham et al., 2022; Pavlovic et al., 2014; Priebe et al., 2017; Simpson et al., 2011; <lb/>Vértes et al., 2012). In each of these models, the extent to which the generative process is <lb/>guided by each wiring rule is determined by a set of tunable parameters. Typically, connec-<lb/>tions are more likely to be generated between regions that are close in spatial proximity to <lb/>each other (Ercsey-Ravasz et al., 2013; Kaiser &amp; Hilgetag, 2004) and/or for which inclusion <lb/>of the proposed connection would enhance a desired topological criterion (Simpson et al., <lb/>2011; Vértes et al., 2012). <lb/>Axonal growth and guidance are important mechanisms that shape brain wiring. Since <lb/>Ramon y Cajal&apos;s discovery of growth cones and Sperry&apos;s pioneering chemoaffinity hypothesis <lb/>(Cajal, 1890; Chilton, 2006; Sperry, 1963; Zang et al., 2021), a variety of guidance molecules, <lb/>such as netrins and slits, were found to contribute to axon pathfinding (Brose et al., 1999; <lb/>Kennedy et al., 1994; Kidd et al., 1999; Serafini et al., 1994). Miswired connectomes are evi-<lb/>dent in model organisms deficient in guidance molecules and receptors; for example, abnor-<lb/>mal optic chiasm development has been found in slit-deficient mice (Dickson, 2002). Given <lb/>the importance of axonal guidance in brain network development and wiring, the modeling of <lb/>pathfinding mechanisms may lead to improved connectome generative models that reflect <lb/>multiple spatial phenomena, compared with preferential generation of connections between <lb/>pairs of regions in close spatial proximity. Connectome generative models that consider axonal <lb/>guidance may provide insight into connectome development, complementing the insight pro-<lb/>vided by current models and shedding light on the mechanisms that generate the characteristic <lb/>geometry and spatial architecture of axonal fiber bundles. <lb/>Explicitly simulating axonal growth also provides an opportunity to generate weighted brain <lb/>networks. Most established connectome generative models are unweighted-a connection is <lb/>either present or absent between a pair of regions. As such, information about diverse connec-<lb/>tivity strengths is overlooked and not modeled. Recent studies have proposed various methods <lb/>to address this issue, such as through connectome community (Faskowitz et al., 2018) and <lb/>communicability redundancy (Akarca et al., 2023). Despite the unique strengths of these <lb/>approaches, axon counts remain a natural and straightforward representation for the strengths <lb/>of physical neural connectivity. In this direction, researchers have established connectome <lb/>generative models that simulate networks by growing axons in predetermined directions (Song <lb/>et al., 2014). In contrast to tuning weights of connections themselves, this work parcellates a <lb/>continuous space into discrete regions that are connected by multiple simulated axons. As a <lb/>result, connection weights naturally arise from the axon counts between pairs of regions. <lb/>Although a nodal correspondence between generated and empirical connectomes is missing, <lb/>Small-worldness: <lb/>Brain regions are densely connected <lb/>locally and can efficiently <lb/>communicate globally. <lb/>Modularity: <lb/>Brain regions are grouped into <lb/>modules such that connections are <lb/>dense within modules and sparse <lb/>between modules. <lb/>Generative model: <lb/>A model that can generate new <lb/>samples of brain networks. <lb/>Chemoaffinity: <lb/>Neurons make connections based on <lb/>the chemical signals that guide them <lb/>to their targets. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Network Neuroscience <lb/></note>

        <page>1193 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A generative model of the connectome with dynamic axon growth <lb/>Downloaded from http://direct.mit.edu/netn/article-pdf/8/4/1192/2479295/netn_a_00397.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>this approach has the advantage of being biologically tractable. The generated networks are <lb/>found to replicate many topological properties of empirical connectomes, including degree, <lb/>clustering, and triad distributions (Song et al., 2014). However, it remains unclear whether <lb/>these attributes persist or new topological characteristics arise in the presence of dynamic <lb/>axon guidance. <lb/>In this study, we establish a new spatially embedded generative model for weighted con-<lb/>nectomes. Our model significantly builds on the seminal models of Kaiser et al. (2009) as well <lb/>as Song et al. (2014), both of which feature axon outgrowth. Dynamic axon growth is a key <lb/>novelty of our model, without which curved axons cannot form. Each brain region exerts a <lb/>distance-dependent attractive force on an extending axon&apos;s tip, steering the direction of axon <lb/>growth. This emulates the process through which axon growth cones react to molecular guid-<lb/>ing cues, whose concentration decays with the distance to chemical release sites. We find that <lb/>our model can recapitulate a diverse array of topological features characteristic of nervous <lb/>systems, at the edge, node, and network levels. We fit the two parameters of our generative <lb/>model to individual connectomes, generating weighted networks that reflect interindividual <lb/>variations in the brain network architecture. Overall, our work enables generation of connec-<lb/>tomes in silico that are weighted, are spatially embedded, and feature axonal trajectories that <lb/>appear biologically realistic. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>We develop a model that generates weighted connectomes through dynamic axon outgrowth, <lb/>an extension of the static generative model proposed by Song et al. (2014). Specifically, the <lb/>direction of axon growth in a static model is governed in a one-shot manner, where fibers are <lb/>generated in a direct, linear trajectory toward their targets. In contrast, axons in a dynamic <lb/>model continuously assess the guidance gradient acting on them and respond accordingly. <lb/>As such, dynamic models have an internal quasitemporal structure such that the position of <lb/>the axon in the past influences its subsequent position over iterations. As a result, axons are <lb/>generated with a richer, fascicle-like geometry. <lb/>For model simplicity and axon visualization purposes, we simplify the cerebral volume to a <lb/>two-dimensional circular construct of radius R. The circumference and the internal space of <lb/>the circle represent brain gray and white matter, respectively (Figure 1A). To discretize the <lb/>circle into regions, we uniformly divide the circumference into N n segments of equal length, <lb/>where each segment represents a distinct brain region, otherwise known as a node. Given that <lb/>brain regions differ in volume and surface area, geometric heterogeneity of nodes is intro-<lb/>duced through a parameter ρ that perturbs node center coordinates (Figure 1B; detailed in <lb/>the Methods section). Node regions are defined using a 1D Voronoi tessellation approach <lb/>along the circumference, such that each point on the circle perimeter is assigned to the region <lb/>of its nearest node center (Figure 1C). Note that perturbed node centers are not necessarily the <lb/>geometric centers of the defined segments; however, we found that substituting perturbed <lb/>node centers with geometric centers did not qualitatively impact our findings (Supporting <lb/>Information Figure S1). <lb/>We use the term axon to denote a unitary connection between a pair of nodes and use the <lb/>term growth cone to refer to an axon&apos;s growing tip. In our model, N a axons are uniformly <lb/>seeded at random from the circular circumference. Each axon is then propagated step by step <lb/>within the circle&apos;s interior until reaching a point on the circumference. Crucially, at each prop-<lb/>agation step, the axon&apos;s direction of propagation is updated based on a combined attractive <lb/>force exerted by each node (Figure 1C). The attractive forces can represent various <lb/>Degree: <lb/>The number of brain regions that a <lb/>region connects to. <lb/>Clustering: <lb/>Three interconnected brain regions <lb/>form a closed triangle. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Network Neuroscience <lb/></note>

        <page>1194 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A generative model of the connectome with dynamic axon growth <lb/>Downloaded from http://direct.mit.edu/netn/article-pdf/8/4/1192/2479295/netn_a_00397.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>environmental and molecular cues (Wadsworth, 2015), decaying as a function of distance <lb/>between the node exerting the force and an axon&apos;s growth cone (Kaiser et al., 2009; Murray, <lb/>2002). Specifically, we assume that the net force exerted at position ⇀ s is given by the following: <lb/>⇀ <lb/>F <lb/>⇀ <lb/>s <lb/>¼ <lb/>X N <lb/>i <lb/>⇀ <lb/>R i -<lb/>⇀ <lb/>s <lb/>⇀ <lb/>R i -<lb/>⇀ <lb/>s <lb/>βþ1 <lb/>(1) <lb/>where R <lb/>⇀ <lb/>i is the coordinate of the ith node center, and jxj describes the vector magnitude of x. <lb/>The parameter β regulates the power-law decay of attractive forces based on the distance <lb/>between the growth cones and node centers. A larger β penalizes the attractive forces from <lb/>distant nodes and promotes the formation of local connectivity. It is one of the two tunable <lb/>parameters of the model. <lb/>A distinguishing feature of the model is the dynamic axonal growth, echoing in vitro and in <lb/>vivo evidence suggesting that axons actively modify growth pathways in response to local <lb/>molecular and mechanical cues (Dickson, 2002; Oliveri &amp; Goriely, 2022). The simulated <lb/>axons grow progressively in a step-by-step manner, based on the attractive forces described <lb/>by <lb/>⇀ <lb/>F ⇀ s <lb/>À Á <lb/>(Figure 1D). For each step, an axon growth cone situated at position ⇀ s i is extended in <lb/>the direction of <lb/>⇀ <lb/>F ⇀ s i <lb/>À Á <lb/>for a constant distance L s . This step length L s is the second tunable <lb/>parameter of the model. We additionally impose weak regularity constraints on growth (see <lb/>the Methods section and Supporting Information Figure S2) to avoid trajectories with biolog-<lb/>ically unrealistic sharp turns (Katz, 1985). <lb/>Figure 1. Illustrative example of the generative process governing axonal growth and network for-<lb/>mation. (A) The model is formulated on a circle of radius R. (B) Coordinates are uniformly posi-<lb/>tioned along the circle&apos;s circumference, each representing a node center (black hexagrams). We <lb/>used 10 nodes in this illustrative example. The coordinates are randomly perturbed on the circum-<lb/>ference (in the direction of black arrows; new node centers are represented with red hexagrams) to <lb/>introduce nodal heterogeneity. (C) Node regions (colored patches) are defined through a 1D <lb/>Voronoi tessellation approach along the perimeter. An axon is seeded on the perimeter. It perceives <lb/>an attractive force from all nodes (blue arrows) and propagates step by step in the direction of the <lb/>net force (red arrow). (D) The net force experienced by the growth cone is updated at each prop-<lb/>agation step to ensure that nodes that become closer to the growth cone exert greater force, while <lb/>nodes further from the growth cone exert less force. (E) The simulated axon forms a connection <lb/>when its growth cone reaches a point on the circular circumference. (F) Multiple axons are gener-<lb/>ated, giving rise to structures resembling axonal fiber bundles. The endpoints of axons are assigned <lb/>to the nearest nodes to construct a network, and the generated network is represented using a <lb/>weighted, undirected connectivity matrix. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Network Neuroscience <lb/></note>

        <page>1195 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A generative model of the connectome with dynamic axon growth <lb/>Downloaded from http://direct.mit.edu/netn/article-pdf/8/4/1192/2479295/netn_a_00397.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>Axon propagation terminates as soon as its growth cone intersects with the circle, forming a <lb/>connection between two points on the circle&apos;s circumference (Figure 1E). Axons that success-<lb/>fully connect two points of the circumference are selected for network construction. Some <lb/>axons fail to navigate to a point on the circumference, and they are excluded from subsequent <lb/>analyses (Methods and Supporting Information Figure S3). <lb/>We construct networks by assigning the endpoints of successful axons to their nearest node <lb/>centers (Figure 1F). The connectivity weight between a pair of nodes is given by the total num-<lb/>ber of axons linking them. Despite the intrinsic directionality of simulated axons, for simplicity, <lb/>we focused on mapping weighted, undirected networks. Within-region connections are <lb/>ignored. As shown in Supporting Information Figure S4, the number of excluded self-<lb/>connections and unsuccessful axons is negligible for parameter combinations generating <lb/>brain-like networks. <lb/>Generating Brain-Like Axonal Fiber Bundles, Hubs, and Connectivity Weights <lb/>In this study, unless otherwise specified, we matched N n to the number of brain regions in the <lb/>Desikan-Killiany atlas (84 nodes) and simulated 2 × 10 5 axons in each network. It should be <lb/>noted that nodes in our generated and empirical connectomes do not have a one-to-one <lb/>correspondence, an intrinsic limitation from using simplified brain geometry (Song et al., <lb/>2014). A complete summary of default parameters used can be found in Methods. We started <lb/>by investigating how simulated networks behaved in response to variations in model param-<lb/>eters. Our model is governed by two key parameters (explained in the Parameter Specification <lb/>section and Supporting Information Figure S5 in the Supporting Information): β-the <lb/>distance-dependent decay of the attractive force, and L s -the length of each extending step. <lb/>Note that β determines the relative contribution of guiding cues exerted by each node, such <lb/>that a larger β emphasizes the guidance from local, adjacent nodes, relative to distant nodes, <lb/>whereas L s governs the extent to which an axon can change its trajectory per unit length. <lb/>We first evaluated the generated networks in terms of the connectivity weight and nodal <lb/>degree distributions. As spatially embedded networks, connectomes exhibit strong and abun-<lb/>dant short-range connections and weak and rare long-range connections across a variety of <lb/>scales and species. This property is typically modeled using an exponential distance rule (EDR) <lb/>of connection weights (Betzel &amp; Bassett, 2018; Ercsey-Ravasz et al., 2013; Gămănuţ et al., <lb/>2018; Horvát et al., 2016; Markov et al., 2014; Oh et al., 2014; Rubinov et al., 2015; Scannell <lb/>et al., 1995). However, a small proportion of strong long-range connections that deviate from <lb/>the expectations of the EDR model are consistently observed in empirical brain networks <lb/>(Deco et al., 2021; Roberts et al., 2016). In addition, connectivity weights are typically lognor-<lb/>mally distributed (Ercsey-Ravasz et al., 2013; Gămănuţ et al., 2018; Song et al., 2005; Wang <lb/>et al., 2012), and nodal degrees are characterized by a scale-free distribution (Broido &amp; <lb/>Clauset, 2019; Eguíluz et al., 2005; Gastner &amp; Ódor, 2016; Giacopelli et al., 2020; Sporns <lb/>et al., 2004; van den Heuvel et al., 2008; Zucca et al., 2019). We examined whether our <lb/>generative model recapitulates these properties. Figures 2 and 3 summarize the key findings <lb/>in terms of variation in β and L s , respectively. <lb/>Figure 2 (also see Supporting Information Figure S6) shows the effects of variations in β. We <lb/>observed that small changes in β had marked effects in the topology of the generated networks, <lb/>especially in terms of the formation of long-range bundles of axonal projections. Specifically, <lb/>when β was either small (β = 0.98) or large (β = 1.02), generated networks lacked distant con-<lb/>nections (Figure 2A-C). This was because local nodal guidance was too weak (strong) to allow <lb/>axon terminations (outgrowths) of long-range connections, as detailed in Supporting <lb/>Scale-free: <lb/>The degree distribution follows a <lb/>power-law function such that a few <lb/>brain regions have many <lb/>connections. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Network Neuroscience <lb/></note>

        <page>1196 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A generative model of the connectome with dynamic axon growth <lb/>Downloaded from http://direct.mit.edu/netn/article-pdf/8/4/1192/2479295/netn_a_00397.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>Information Figure S3. Nevertheless, for moderate β values (β = 0.99, 1 and 1.01; Figure 2A-<lb/>C), strong long-range connections emerged, decreasing in strength with greater β. Remarkably, <lb/>these connections replicated the strong long-range connections observed in empirical connec-<lb/>tomes that cannot be explained by a simple EDR (Deco et al., 2021; Roberts et al., 2016). That <lb/>is, it is not only distance dependence that matters, but the outgrowth of axons depending on <lb/>competing attractive factors also contributes to brain connectivity profiles (Cahalane et al., <lb/>2011), including long-distance connections. <lb/>Compared with null networks generated from a constrained random walk (see the Methods <lb/>section), our model networks featured brain-like axonal projections resembling U-fibers and <lb/>white matter tracts. As shown in Figure 2A (most evident for β = 1), axonal projections were <lb/>organized into bundles at a distance from their origins and defasciculated before reaching their <lb/>targets. This is a natural consequence of axon guidance in the presence of target-released dif-<lb/>fusible chemoattractant (i.e., the node exerted a distance-dependent attractive force) that has <lb/>Figure 2. Characterization of generated connectomes under variation of the force decay parameter (i.e., β). L s was fixed to 1. (A) Circles show <lb/>the generated axons for different values of β (0.98-1.02). The rightmost circle shows generated axons using a random walk null model. Axons <lb/>are color-coded (using a black-red spectrum; see the color bar) by connection weights, such that black (red) curves represent weaker (stronger) <lb/>connections. The color scale is truncated at a connectivity weight of 10 3 . The null network shows 5% of axons generated. (B) Connectivity <lb/>matrices for networks in panel (A). Nodes are ordered such that geometrically adjacent nodes are close to each other. Connectivity weights are <lb/>log-scaled and normalized between 0 and 1. (C) Scatterplots of connection weights (log-scaled) versus distances for networks in panel (A). <lb/>Strong long-range connections that deviate from the EDR are shown as blue dots in β = 0.99 and 1. Distributions of connection weights and <lb/>distances are shown in the marginal histograms. (D) Distributions of connection weights (normalized by nodal strength) for networks in panel <lb/>(A) (red), compared with the fitted lognormal distributions (black), in terms of the cumulative density function (CDF; main figures) and prob-<lb/>ability density function (PDF; insets), respectively. KS described the one-sample Kolmogorov-Smirnov statistics of lognormal fit. (E) Nodal <lb/>degree distributions for the evaluated β values. Results (with median p value among 1,000 simulations; model and null) are compared with <lb/>Erdös-Rényi random networks (ER) and scale-free fits ( y ~k-α ). Scale-free distribution is plausible if p &gt; 0.1. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Network Neuroscience <lb/></note>

        <page>1197 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A generative model of the connectome with dynamic axon growth <lb/>Downloaded from http://direct.mit.edu/netn/article-pdf/8/4/1192/2479295/netn_a_00397.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>been observed in past axon pathfinding studies (Hentschel &amp; van Ooyen, 1999). Adjacent <lb/>nodes were connected via U-shaped fibers that gradually steered according to the dynamically <lb/>changing axon guidance. In contrast, axons generated by the null model failed to form organic <lb/>fiber bundles. Additionally, the proportion of variance in the model generated fiber length <lb/>explained by Euclidean distance is comparable with empirically observed values (Akarca <lb/>et al., 2021), a characteristic missing in the random walk null model (Supporting Information <lb/>Figure S8). <lb/>A negative association between connection weight and the Euclidean distance between <lb/>nodes was evident across the range of β values considered (Figure 2C). Connection weights <lb/>(normalized by the average nodal strength of connected regions; see the Methods section) <lb/>spanned four orders of magnitude and were most parsimoniously modeled by lognormal dis-<lb/>tributions (Figure 2D, Supporting Information Figure S9). In contrast, connection weights for <lb/>the random-walk null model were most accurately described by a gamma distribution <lb/>Figure 3. Characterization of generated networks changed under variation in the step length parameter (i.e., L s ). Results are visualized for <lb/>representative parameter combinations (L s = 0.1-5 and fixed β = 1). (A) Axon organizations of model networks. A higher network density was <lb/>evident with increasing L s (4, 11, 24, 35, and 75% connectivity density, from left to right). (B) Connectivity matrices for networks in panel (A). <lb/>(C) Negative associations between connection weights and distances, with blue dots in L s = 0.5, 1, 2, and 5 representing strong long-range <lb/>connections that deviate from the EDR. Distributions of connection weights and distances are shown in the marginal histograms. (D) Distri-<lb/>butions of connectivity weights (normalized by nodal strength) in model networks (red), compared with fitted log-normal distribution (black). <lb/>The main figure compared CDF, and the insets compared PDF. (E) Degree distributions in generated networks, compared with ER networks and <lb/>scale-free fit. All evaluated L s values showed scale-free behaviors (median p &gt; 0.1). <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Network Neuroscience <lb/></note>

        <page>1198 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A generative model of the connectome with dynamic axon growth <lb/>Downloaded from http://direct.mit.edu/netn/article-pdf/8/4/1192/2479295/netn_a_00397.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>(Supporting Information Figure S9) and exhibited less variability, distinguishing them from <lb/>model networks and empirical connectomes (Figure 2B-D, Supporting Information Figure S10). <lb/>To investigate whether our generated networks showed scale-free degree distributions, we <lb/>adopted the approach developed by Clauset et al. (2009), as detailed in the Methods section. <lb/>In brief, the approach returned a p value describing the goodness of fit, and evidence of a <lb/>scale-free distribution was deemed plausible if more than 50% of the networks in a population <lb/>had a p &gt; 0.1 (Broido &amp; Clauset, 2019). For each representative parameter combination <lb/>considered, we generated 1,000 networks and evaluated evidence for scale-free degree distri-<lb/>butions. Figure 2E shows the networks with the median p value for each parameter combina-<lb/>tion (see Supporting Information Figure S11 for p value distributions). A scale-free behavior <lb/>was evident for β = 0.98 and 1, yet it was missing in networks generated with other β values <lb/>and our null networks. Crucially, β = 1 generated networks that were simultaneously charac-<lb/>terized by all the connectomic properties were evaluated in this section. <lb/>We next characterized the impact of variation in step length, L s , on properties of the <lb/>generated connectomes (Figure 3; also see Supporting Information Figure S7). Greater L s led <lb/>to networks with higher connection density (ranging from 4% to 75% in Figure 3A). This was <lb/>because a larger L s resulted in fewer trajectory updates, and thus, the past guidance an axon <lb/>received had a longer lasting impact on subsequent wiring. As a result, if two axons originated <lb/>from the same node yet different coordinates, with a greater L s , the difference in initial coor-<lb/>dinates made their subsequent trajectories less likely to converge, which led to more diverse <lb/>wiring and denser networks. We also found that the choice of L s impacted connectivity weight <lb/>distributions (Figure 3B-D). Certain values of L s (L s = 1 and 2; Supporting Information Figure <lb/>S9) generated networks with lognormally distributed connectivity weights. Negative associa-<lb/>tions between connection weights and distances were consistently observed, and strong long-<lb/>range connections that deviate from the EDR were found in generated networks except for <lb/>L s = 0.1 (Figure 3C). In addition, all representative L s parameters generated networks with <lb/>scale-free degree distributions (Figure 3E, Supporting Information Figure S11). <lb/>Collectively, these results suggested that combinations of β and L s generate connectomes <lb/>with realistic properties, including scale-free degree distributions, brain-like axonal bundles, <lb/>negatively correlated connection weight and distance, lognormally distributed weights, and <lb/>strong long-range connections that deviate from the EDR. Specifically, comparing the two <lb/>model parameters β and L s , variations in β had a stronger effect on degree distributions, <lb/>whereas changes in L s were more closely related to weight distributions. These observations <lb/>remain robust if generated networks are controlled for network density via thresholding (Sup-<lb/>porting Information Figures S12 and S13). <lb/>Emergence of Complex Network Properties <lb/>So far, we have focused on characterizing the distributions of connection weight and nodal <lb/>degree generated by our model. In this section, we examine whether our generative model <lb/>could give rise to connectomes exhibiting complex topological properties, including SW <lb/>and modularity. We specifically investigated the network average clustering coefficient (CC), <lb/>characteristic path length (CPL), SW, and modularity Q, benchmarked to weight and degree <lb/>preserved null networks (see the Methods section). These topological features are hypothe-<lb/>sized to relate to the functional segregation and integration of brain networks (Bassett &amp; <lb/>Bullmore, 2017; Fornito et al., 2015; Sporns &amp; Betzel, 2016). <lb/>Using an exhaustive grid search (see the Methods section), we investigated how weighted <lb/>topological properties of generated networks changed as a function of β and L s . Figure 4A <lb/>Characteristic path length: <lb/>The average smallest number of <lb/>connections required to travel <lb/>between two brain regions. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Network Neuroscience <lb/></note>

        <page>1199 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A generative model of the connectome with dynamic axon growth <lb/>Downloaded from http://direct.mit.edu/netn/article-pdf/8/4/1192/2479295/netn_a_00397.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>displays the variation of network topology among the parameter space that generated brain-<lb/>like connection weight and nodal degree distributions. Topological properties were evaluated <lb/>at a network density of 10%, yet the patterns of topological variations were insensitive to net-<lb/>work densities (Supporting Information Figure S14). Across the investigated parameter space, <lb/>generated networks consistently displayed small-world and modular structures. A higher CC <lb/>and a longer CPL were evident relative to weight and degree preserved null networks. Varia-<lb/>tions in model parameters impacted the network topology in a continuous manner. Increasing <lb/>β and decreasing L s led to weighted networks with higher clustering, longer CPL, stronger SW, <lb/>and weaker modularity (also see Supporting Information Figures S15 and S16). <lb/>To supplement this analysis, we visualized the axon organizations of example networks <lb/>from different positions of the parameter space. As shown Figure 4B, a decrease in β and <lb/>an increase in L s improved the prevalence and strength of medium-to long-range connections, <lb/>reducing segregation (measured by clustering) while promoting integration (measured by effi-<lb/>ciency, i.e., the inverse of CPL). <lb/>In summary, variations in model parameters shifted network topology by adjusting the balance <lb/>between short-range and long-range connectivity. While the generated networks consistently <lb/>showed small-world and modular organizations, the degrees of these properties vary. Combined <lb/>with the results from Figures 2 and 3 (i.e., analyses on bundle structure, connection weights, and <lb/>degree distributions), certain combinations of model parameters (e.g., β = 1 and L s = 1) were <lb/>capable of generating networks that resembled all the evaluated connectomic features. <lb/>Generating Connectomes for Individuals <lb/>Finally, we focused on fitting the two parameters governing our generative model to individual <lb/>human connectomes. Our motivations here were twofold. First, the results above suggested <lb/>Figure 4. Complex topological organization of the generated connectomes. (A) Contour plots of the weighted network average CC, CPL, SW, <lb/>and modularity Q of generated networks, benchmarked to null networks with preserved weight, degree, and strength distributions. All mea-<lb/>sures were normalized to the null networks. (B) Axon organization of example networks, generated by parameters labeled with a square <lb/>(β = 1.008, L s = 0.678), diamond (β = 1.008, L s = 1.922), triangle (β = 0.992, L s = 1.922), circle (β = 0.992, L s = 0.678), and hexagram <lb/>(β = 0.997, L s = 0.953) in panel (A). (C) Connectivity matrices of example networks in (B). <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Network Neuroscience <lb/></note>

        <page>1200 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A generative model of the connectome with dynamic axon growth <lb/>Downloaded from http://direct.mit.edu/netn/article-pdf/8/4/1192/2479295/netn_a_00397.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>that networks generated by our model exhibited varying degrees of SW and modularity. It was <lb/>unclear if certain parameters gave rise to these properties numerically close to empirical con-<lb/>nectomes and if these parameters resided in the range that generated networks simultaneously <lb/>manifested brain-like connection weights, nodal degrees, and axonal bundles. This question <lb/>could be answered via a parameter optimization approach. Second, model optimization <lb/>enables comparison of individuals in terms of their fitted parameters and can provide insight <lb/>into interindividual variability in the processes guiding connectome development. For exam-<lb/>ple, interindividual variation in parameters of existing generative models is associated with <lb/>various traits, including age, sex, a schizophrenia diagnosis, and social-economic disadvan-<lb/>tage (Akarca et al., 2021; Betzel et al., 2016; Carozza et al., 2023; Faskowitz et al., 2018; <lb/>Simpson et al., 2011; Sinke et al., 2016; Siugzdaite et al., 2022; Zhang et al., 2021). Thus, <lb/>a parameter fitting scheme is a prerequisite for future cohort studies to apply our model. <lb/>Parameters for the current state-of-the-art connectome generative models are typically opti-<lb/>mized by minimizing an energy function that compares the degree, clustering, betweenness <lb/>centrality, and Euclidean space edge lengths between generated and empirical connectomes <lb/>(Betzel et al., 2016). However, our model does not generate networks with nodes that corre-<lb/>spond one-to-one to empirical connectomes; as a result, the discrepancy in Euclidean space <lb/>edge lengths cannot be evaluated and the classical energy cost is not applicable (despite this, <lb/>when evaluated using the degree, clustering, and betweenness centrality, our model achieved <lb/>a better fit relative to the established geometric model; see Supporting Information Figure S17). <lb/>Therefore, we developed a new method to fit the parameters of our generative model to indi-<lb/>vidual connectomes (detailed in the Methods section) and applied it to estimate parameters for <lb/>1,064 participants in the Human Connectome Project (HCP) (Van Essen et al., 2013). <lb/>The parameter estimation method aimed to minimize the dissimilarity between the gener-<lb/>ated network and an individual&apos;s connectome, in terms of CC, CPL, and modularity Q. <lb/>Figure 5A displays the best-fit model parameters for the HCP population, and networks gen-<lb/>erated by the fitted parameters numerically resembled topological features for which they were <lb/>optimized (Supporting Information Figure S18). Individual parameters were found significantly <lb/>Figure 5. Individual parameters for HCP connectomes. (A) Optimized individual parameters (blue dots) overlaid on the contour plots of <lb/>weighted topological measures (CC, CPL, SW, and modularity Q). The black hexagram represents the group average parameters <lb/>(β = 0.9968, L s = 0.9531). (B) Networks simulated with the HCP group average parameters showed organic axon organization (top left), neg-<lb/>atively associated connection weights and distances (top right; blue dots represent strong long-range connections that deviate from the EDR), <lb/>lognormally distributed weights (bottom left), and scale-free degree distributions (bottom right; despite the p value marginally above the thresh-<lb/>old of p = 0.1). <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Network Neuroscience <lb/></note>

        <page>1201 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A generative model of the connectome with dynamic axon growth <lb/>Downloaded from http://direct.mit.edu/netn/article-pdf/8/4/1192/2479295/netn_a_00397.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>different between males and females ( p = 2e -15 ; Supporting Information Figure S19), confirm-<lb/>ing the model&apos;s capability of capturing interindividual variations in connectomes. Using the <lb/>group-averaged model parameters (β = 0.9968, L s = 0.9531), we generated networks and <lb/>investigated their weight, degree, and axonal bundle structures. As shown in Figure 5B, gen-<lb/>erated networks simultaneously manifested brain-like axonal bundles, negatively correlated <lb/>connection weight and distance, lognormally distributed weights, scale-free degree distribu-<lb/>tions, and strong long-range connections that deviate from the EDR. These results suggested <lb/>that a &quot;sweet spot&quot; of parameters can be identified to generate human brain-like connectomes <lb/>possessing a host of empirically observed properties. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>Generative models can provide insight into the wiring principles governing brain network <lb/>organization. Most existing models generate unweighted connectomes in which connections <lb/>are either present or absent (Betzel et al., 2016; Oldham et al., 2022; Simpson et al., 2011; <lb/>Sinke et al., 2016; Vértes et al., 2012). However, it is well-known that connectivity weights <lb/>are diverse and span multiple orders of magnitude (Fornito et al., 2016). In this work, we <lb/>developed a novel model that generates connectomes weighted by axon counts and dem-<lb/>onstrated that our model can recapitulate lognormal connectivity weight distributions. Our <lb/>model is spatially embedded and characterizes the dynamics of axonal outgrowth. We <lb/>demonstrated that our model manifests key topological properties of the connectome and <lb/>yields axonal fiber bundle structures that resemble white matter fascicles. We were also able <lb/>to fit our generative model to individual connectomes, enabling future cohort studies to <lb/>apply the model. <lb/>Our work substantially builds on the seminal generative model developed by Song et al. <lb/>(2014). Whereas this earlier model considered static axon propagation in a fixed direction, we <lb/>established a dynamic axon pathfinding model in which the attractive forces guiding axonal <lb/>outgrowth are continuously updated. With an appropriate selection of β and L s , we observed <lb/>that our model can generate networks with properties that are consistent with empirically <lb/>mapped connectomes. In particular, negative associations between connectivity weights <lb/>and the Euclidean distances between nodes were evident-a property that has been found <lb/>in numerous studies (Betzel &amp; Bassett, 2018; Ercsey-Ravasz et al., 2013; Roberts et al., <lb/>2016). We also found that connectivity weights were lognormally distributed and showed <lb/>scale-free degree distributions. This suggests that a simple axon growth mechanism can gen-<lb/>erate key properties of a connectome&apos;s topological architecture. <lb/>The choice of β and L s determines whether the generated networks show complex topol-<lb/>ogies. As β is increased, distant nodes exert less influence on an axon&apos;s growth and, thus, <lb/>axons are attracted by neighboring nodes, forming short-range connections. This leads to <lb/>the formation of clusters between spatially adjacent nodes and weakens the long-range con-<lb/>nections that are critical to network efficiency. In contrast, a larger step length parameter L s <lb/>enables axons to propagate beyond a local nodal sphere of influence, increasing the preva-<lb/>lence and strength of long-range connectivity and improving network integration. While β and <lb/>L s impact generated axons through mechanisms that are both similar and distinct, their com-<lb/>bined effects lead to generated networks with SW and modularity, akin to empirical <lb/>connectomes. <lb/>Biological plausibility is a key characteristic of our model, where axon outgrowth is deter-<lb/>mined by the summed attractive forces exerted by each node. This is inspired by the observa-<lb/>tion that axons grow by responding to complex and combined effects of multiple guiding cues <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Network Neuroscience <lb/></note>

        <page>1202 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A generative model of the connectome with dynamic axon growth <lb/>Downloaded from http://direct.mit.edu/netn/article-pdf/8/4/1192/2479295/netn_a_00397.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>(Wadsworth, 2015). The two governing parameters also build on empirical observations in <lb/>neural systems. The force decay parameter β determines the distance-dependent decay of <lb/>attractive forces exerted by nodes, modeling the concentration decay of guiding cues with <lb/>distance from releasing sites (Kaiser et al., 2009; Murray, 2002). The step length parameter <lb/>L s governs the extent to which an axon can change its trajectory per unit length, and it can <lb/>represent the combined effects of multiple factors such as a growth cone&apos;s growing speed and <lb/>its sensitivity to molecular guidance (Alberts, 2017). While step length is seldom considered as <lb/>a key parameter in applications such as tractography (Tournier et al., 2002), in vitro evidence <lb/>suggests that it is a vital factor that models axonal growth. For example, variations in growth <lb/>step length have been observed between frog and chick neurons, as well as between normal <lb/>and regenerating frog neurons (Katz et al., 1984). Relating the parameter L s to empirical data <lb/>on neuronal growth rates of different species can help validate the biological interpretability of <lb/>our model. <lb/>Our model generates connection weights by counting axons between nodes, a method dis-<lb/>tinct from other recently proposed models. Different weight inference approaches all have <lb/>their unique strengths. Using a weighted stochastic block model, Faskowitz et al. (2018) <lb/>inferred connection weights from network blocks, highlighting the community architecture <lb/>of connectomes. Based on an unweighted connectome generative model, Akarca et al. <lb/>(2023) introduced connection weights via minimizing the redundancy in network commu-<lb/>nicability, capturing dynamics in the strengthening and weakening of connections. In con-<lb/>trast, axon counts used in our model are intrinsically akin to streamline counts synonymous <lb/>with structural connectomes, emphasizing the physical nature of connections as neural <lb/>pathways. <lb/>Elucidating the mechanisms governing the formation of long-range connections remains a <lb/>pivotal yet unsolved question in connectome generative model research. Early work suggested <lb/>that, in addition to the distance rule, a topological homophily rule is required to promote the <lb/>formation of long-range connections (Betzel et al., 2016; Vértes et al., 2012). Recently, the <lb/>biological plausibility of topological rules was questioned, and homophily in gene expression <lb/>and cytoarchitecture was hypothesized to contribute to long-range wiring (Kerstjens et al., <lb/>2022; Oldham et al., 2022). Nevertheless, existing frameworks failed to explain the specificity <lb/>of long-range connectivity (Betzel &amp; Bassett, 2018). Moreover, it is unclear how brain elements <lb/>can perceive distant pairs without prior global knowledge of topology. Due to the spatial <lb/>embedding of brain networks, a distance component might be required for brain elements <lb/>to search for their wiring pairs. By including a pathfinding component, our model simulated <lb/>long-range connections, including those that deviate from the EDR. Growth cones were <lb/>sequentially guided by the strong local cues of a series of intermediate nodes before reaching <lb/>their distant destinations (despite that weak attractive forces exerted by distant nodes still con-<lb/>tribute). This mechanism is consistent with the hypothesis of intermediate targets in axon guid-<lb/>ance, whose suggestive evidence has been observed in model organisms such as Drosophila <lb/>and mice (Canty &amp; Murphy, 2008; Dickson, 2002). <lb/>We conclude by acknowledging the limitations of our work and providing guidance for <lb/>future improvement. Firstly, as the first attempt to generate connectomes from dynamic axon <lb/>guidance, the model simplifies the brain as a two-dimensional circle and ignores complex <lb/>brain structures such as sulci, gyri, deep gray matter, and cerebrospinal fluid. While this <lb/>approach contributed to model simplicity and axon visualization, it also introduced limita-<lb/>tions, such as the loss of nodal correspondence between generated and empirical connec-<lb/>tomes. Using a realistic brain mesh/volume to incorporate three-dimensional neuroanatomical <lb/>constraints in axonal outgrowth would not only naturally address these limitations but also <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Network Neuroscience <lb/></note>

        <page>1203 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A generative model of the connectome with dynamic axon growth <lb/>Downloaded from http://direct.mit.edu/netn/article-pdf/8/4/1192/2479295/netn_a_00397.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>entail higher computational demands. Additionally, neurodevelopment is patterned in space <lb/>and time. Neurogenesis and axon growth initially occurs in the neural tube (Kintner, 2002); the <lb/>development of long-range projection and commissural fibers occurs concurrently with the <lb/>morphogenesis of primary foldings; the accelerated growth of short cortico-cortical association <lb/>fibers coincides with the formation of secondary and tertiary foldings (Chavoshnejad et al., <lb/>2021). Future studies could investigate the evolution of connectivity in a spatially embedded <lb/>developing brain. Secondly, we assume that all brain regions have the same distance-<lb/>dependent attractiveness and that all axons are equally sensitive to guidance from brain <lb/>regions. These assumptions are likely breached in the brain given the diversity in regional <lb/>properties (e.g., cortical thickness, curvature of folds, laminar structure, cellular composition, <lb/>and neuronal density), neuron types, and guiding cues (attractive and repulsive, chemical and <lb/>mechanical). For example, we do not consider the impact of axonal repellents in our current <lb/>model. Repellents are critical to the formation of long-range commissural fibers (Dickson, <lb/>2002), and modeling the forces resulting from repellents is an important avenue for future <lb/>investigation. Recent efforts in generating high-resolution brain maps such as molecular and <lb/>cytoarchitectural profiles (Amunts et al., 2013; Arnatkevičiūtė et al., 2019; Hansen et al., 2022; <lb/>Markello et al., 2022) might provide an opportunity to refine the assumptions and improve the <lb/>model&apos;s capacity. Thirdly, while our model generates axon organization that is visually akin to <lb/>axon bundles and white matter fascicles, factors that contribute to axon bundling are not con-<lb/>sidered. Incorporating fasciculation mechanisms such as the contact attraction between axons <lb/>and axon-released guiding cues (Hentschel &amp; van Ooyen, 2000) might help to build a more <lb/>nuanced white matter and connectome organization. In addition, the model implements a <lb/>deterministic axonal guidance rule, and as such, stochasticity, which is also fundamental to <lb/>neural development (Carozza et al., 2023; Hassan &amp; Hiesinger, 2015), was not taken into <lb/>account. Future work could evaluate the robustness of the model with the presence of stochas-<lb/>ticity, such as random noise in guiding cues and axon growth. Axonal branching that results in <lb/>multiple synaptic connections is also ignored in our study. This property allows for one-to-<lb/>many connections, promoting the formation of sophisticated connectome topology, whose <lb/>impact could be evaluated in future work. Finally, our model generates macroscale connec-<lb/>tomes, yet this is achieved by simulating axons that are microscale anatomical concepts. <lb/>Future studies could investigate our model&apos;s application in generating microscale <lb/>connectomes. <lb/>METHODS <lb/>Model Implementation <lb/>An overview of our model is described in the Results section. Here, we provide finer details of <lb/>the model, elaborating on aspects including node heterogeneity, path constraints, axon termi-<lb/>nation, and parameter specifications. <lb/>To parcellate the hypothetical gray matter, N n node centers were evenly positioned along <lb/>the circle perimeter, such that the angular distance between adjacent nodes equals 2π/N n . <lb/>Next, nodal heterogeneity was introduced by randomly perturbing node center coordinates. This <lb/>was accomplished by applying a uniformly distributed angular displacement, ε ~ρ * U(-π/N n , <lb/>π/N n ), to each node center. Specifically, ρ = 1 was used in this study to maximize nodal <lb/>heterogeneity while preserving the sequential arrangement of nodes along the perimeter. <lb/>Axons were simulated based on the distance rule in Equation 1. To encourage axons to <lb/>traverse relatively noncurved trajectories, regularity constraints were applied to each axon <lb/>from the second extending step onward. The regularity constraints stipulate that the angle <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Network Neuroscience <lb/></note>

        <page>1204 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A generative model of the connectome with dynamic axon growth <lb/>Downloaded from http://direct.mit.edu/netn/article-pdf/8/4/1192/2479295/netn_a_00397.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>formed between the direction of two consecutive steps cannot exceed the angle θ. In other <lb/>words, if the angle between two consecutive steps exceeds θ, the second step is adjusted <lb/>such that the angular difference is forced to θ (Supporting Information Figure S2). <lb/>Ideally, axons would terminate on the circle circumference, connecting two points of the <lb/>hypothetical gray matter. However, not all simulated axons can successfully reach the circle <lb/>perimeter. When the value of β was small, a &quot;black hole&quot; region emerged within the circle, as <lb/>shown in Supporting Information Figure S3. Axons entering the &quot;black hole&quot; cannot escape, <lb/>forming a circular trajectory of infinite loops. To address the problem, a parameter S max was <lb/>introduced to stipulate the maximum number of growing steps allowed. Axons failing to reach <lb/>the circle circumference within S max steps were considered unsuccessful and were excluded <lb/>from network construction and analyses. <lb/>Eight parameters were defined in the model. Unless otherwise specified, default values of <lb/>parameters (Table 1) were used. A comprehensive justification for the parameter choice was <lb/>included in the Supporting Information. <lb/>Weight and Degree Measures of Generated Networks <lb/>We investigated the associations between edge weights and distances, and the weight distri-<lb/>butions in generated networks. The edge weights were normalized by the average nodal <lb/>strengths of the two regions they connect and were evaluated using a common logarithm <lb/>scale. <lb/>The weight-distance associations were evaluated by calculating the Pearson&apos;s correlation <lb/>coefficient between edge lengths (i.e., the Euclidean space distance between two nodes <lb/>connected by an edge) and the edge weights. Weight distributions were evaluated against <lb/>fitted lognormal, gamma, normal, exponential, and Weibull distributions using one-sample <lb/>Kolmogorov-Smirnov (KS) test. <lb/>We also analyzed the degree distributions of generated networks. To reduce the bias of the <lb/>finite network size, 1,000 networks, each comprising 300 nodes (N n = 300), were generated <lb/>for each evaluated parameter combination. Next, generated networks were thresholded and <lb/>binarized to a network density of 5% (except β = 0.98, 0.99, and L s = 0.1 that were evaluated <lb/>at a lower density because their generated networks are too sparse. However, these parameters <lb/>do not generate brain-like networks). To assess the scale-free property of degree distributions, <lb/>Table 1. Default values of model parameters <lb/>Parameters <lb/>Meaning explained <lb/>Default values <lb/>R <lb/>Circle radius <lb/>30 <lb/>N n <lb/>Number of nodes <lb/>84 <lb/>ρ <lb/>Controls nodal heterogeneity <lb/>1 <lb/>N a <lb/>Number of axons <lb/>2 × 10 5 <lb/>θ <lb/>Angular constraint <lb/>15°β <lb/>Power-law decay of attractive force <lb/>To be optimized <lb/>L s <lb/>Growth step length <lb/>To be optimized <lb/>S max <lb/>Maximum growing steps <lb/>3R/L s <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Network Neuroscience <lb/></note>

        <page>1205 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A generative model of the connectome with dynamic axon growth <lb/>Downloaded from http://direct.mit.edu/netn/article-pdf/8/4/1192/2479295/netn_a_00397.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>we employed the method developed by Clauset et al. (2009). Considering a network whose <lb/>nodal degrees K adhere to a scale-free distribution for K ≥ K min , its probability density function <lb/>is given by the following: <lb/>P K <lb/>ð Þ ¼ <lb/>K -α <lb/>P ∞ <lb/>i¼0 i þ K min <lb/>ð <lb/>Þ -α <lb/>(2) <lb/>The Clauset method estimated K min by a KS minimization approach and optimized α through a <lb/>maximum likelihood estimation. The goodness-of-fit was assessed with a bootstrap approach, <lb/>and the null hypothesis of the scale-free distribution was rejected if p &lt; 0.1. Applied to a <lb/>network population (in our study, 1,000 networks were generated from the same model <lb/>parameters), scale-free distribution was deemed a plausible hypothesis if more than 50% <lb/>networks showed p ≥ 0.1. Further details of the scale-free test can be found in Broido and <lb/>Clauset (2019). <lb/>Results of weight and degree analyses were visualized for representative parameters (L s = 1, <lb/>β = 0.98, 0.99, 1, 1.01, and 1.02; β = 1, L s = 0.1, 0.5, 1, 2, and 5). These parameters were <lb/>selected to generate diverse network properties while delineating the isolated effects of each <lb/>parameter. Compared with an exhaustive grid search (used in a later section to evaluate global <lb/>topology), this approach enabled us to uncover details (Figures 2 and 3) that were obscured in <lb/>summary metrics (i.e., Pearson r, KS statistics, and p values). <lb/>Null networks generated from a constrained random walk were used to benchmark model <lb/>networks. Specifically, axon growth directions were randomly sampled from U(-θ, θ) rather <lb/>than being calculated from the distance rule in Equation 1. The step length parameter of L s = 1 <lb/>was used. All other parameters remained consistent with the model. <lb/>Global Topology of Generated Networks <lb/>To characterize the global topology of generated networks, model parameters were drawn <lb/>from a grid combination of β and L s (0.99 ≤ β ≤ 1.01, 0.1 ≤ L s ≤ 2.1; 101-by-101 grid). This <lb/>parameter space was determined from preliminary experiments and was found to generate <lb/>networks that replicated connectomic features. To account for the stochastic variability arising <lb/>from node and axon sampling, 50 networks were generated for each parameter combination, <lb/>forming 50 network landscapes. The network topology corresponding to each parameter com-<lb/>bination was described by the average topological metrics over 50 landscapes. <lb/>We considered the weighted CC, characteristic pathlength, SW, and modularity Q of gen-<lb/>erated networks. Because topological measures are fundamentally related to network density <lb/>and connectivity strengths, all generated networks were thresholded and normalized to have <lb/>the same network density (10%) and total connectivity (2e 5 ). Parameters whose generated net-<lb/>works have a density smaller than 10% were ignored. Topological measures were evaluated <lb/>using the Brain Connectivity Toolbox (BCT), benchmarked to weight and degree preserved <lb/>null networks constructed using the null_model_und_sign() function in BCT. <lb/>Empirical Datasets <lb/>This study utilized the HCP Young Adults (1,064 subjects) datasets (Glasser et al., 2013; <lb/>Uğurbil et al., 2013). A comprehensive description of data acquisition and connectome con-<lb/>struction has been detailed elsewhere (Mansour L. et al., 2021). The HCP connectomes were <lb/>mapped to the Desikan-Killiany atlas, comprising 68 cortical and 16 subcortical brain regions. <lb/>Networks were thresholded to a density of 10%. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Network Neuroscience <lb/></note>

        <page>1206 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A generative model of the connectome with dynamic axon growth <lb/>Downloaded from http://direct.mit.edu/netn/article-pdf/8/4/1192/2479295/netn_a_00397.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <body>Optimize Model Parameters Against Connectomes <lb/>We optimized the model parameters for the HCP connectomes. Because topological measures <lb/>are related to network density and connectivity strengths, empirical and model networks were <lb/>thresholded and linearly scaled to the same network density and total connectivity (discussed <lb/>in the Supporting Information). Parameters were fitted to minimize the discrepancies between <lb/>empirical and model networks, measured by the rooted mean squared error (RMSE) in <lb/>weighted CC, CPL, and modularity Q (Equation 3). SW was excluded because it is a combi-<lb/>nation of CC and CPL. <lb/>RMSE ¼ <lb/>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi <lb/>Err CC <lb/>ð Þ 2 þ Err CPL <lb/>ð <lb/>Þ 2 þ Err Q <lb/>ð Þ 2 <lb/>2 <lb/>q <lb/>(3) <lb/>To mitigate the inconsistent scales among topological measures, metrics were normalized by <lb/>the values in degree and strength preserved null networks and standardized using the standard <lb/>deviation in empirical connectomes. <lb/>Parameters were optimized using a Monte Carlo method through an exhaustive grid search <lb/>(see the Global Topology of Generated Networks section). To account for the stochasticity-<lb/>dependent inaccuracy and unreliability, and to improve the computational tractability, we <lb/>employed the fast landscape generation and the multilandscape method (generating 50 land-<lb/>scapes) developed by Liu et al. (2023). For each landscape, the best-fit parameters (with the <lb/>smallest RMSE; values shown in Supporting Information Figure S18) were selected, and the <lb/>average across 50 landscapes was deemed the optimal parameters. <lb/></body>

        <div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>Data were provided by the Human Connectome Project, WU-Minn Consortium (Principal <lb/>Investigators: David Van Essen and Kamil Ugurbil; 1U54MH091657) funded by the 16 NIH <lb/>Institutes and Centers that support the NIH Blueprint for Neuroscience Research and by the <lb/>McDonnell Center for Systems Neuroscience at Washington University. The computation is <lb/>supported by The University of Melbourne&apos;s Research Computing Services and by the <lb/>Petascale Campus Initiative. Y.L. is funded by the Melbourne Research Scholarship. C.S. is <lb/>supported by the Australian Research Council (grant number DP170101815). R.F.B. is sup-<lb/>ported by the National Science Foundation (award ID: 2023985). D.A. is supported by the <lb/>James S. McDonnell Foundation Opportunity Award and the Templeton World Charity <lb/>Foundation, Inc. (funder DOI 501100011730) under the grant TWCF-2022-30510. M.A.D.B. <lb/>was supported by an NHMRC Investigator Grant (1175754). A.Z. is supported by research <lb/>fellowships from the NHMRC (APP1118153). <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">SUPPORTING INFORMATION <lb/>Supporting information for this article is available at https://doi.org/10.1162/netn_a_00397. <lb/></div>

        <div type="contribution">AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS <lb/>Yuanzhe Liu: Conceptualization; Formal analysis; Methodology; Software; Writing -original <lb/>draft; Writing -review &amp; editing. Caio Seguin: Conceptualization; Methodology; Supervision; <lb/>Writing -original draft; Writing -review &amp; editing. Richard F. Betzel: Methodology; Writing -<lb/>original draft; Writing -review &amp; editing. Daniel Han: Formal analysis; Writing -review &amp; <lb/>editing. Danyal Akarca: Methodology; Writing -original draft; Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/>Maria A. Di Biase: Conceptualization; Methodology; Supervision; Writing -original draft; <lb/></div>

        <note place="footnote">Network Neuroscience <lb/></note>

        <page>1207 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A generative model of the connectome with dynamic axon growth <lb/>Downloaded from http://direct.mit.edu/netn/article-pdf/8/4/1192/2479295/netn_a_00397.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <div type="contribution">Writing -review &amp; editing. Andrew Zalesky: Conceptualization; Methodology; Supervision; <lb/>Writing -original draft; Writing -review &amp; editing. <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">FUNDING INFORMATION <lb/>Yuanzhe Liu, Melbourne Research, Award ID: 720358. Caio Seguin, Australian Research <lb/>Council (https://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000923), Award ID: DP170101815. Richard F. <lb/>Betzel, National Science Foundation (https://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000001), Award ID: <lb/>2023985. Danyal Akarca, Templeton World Charity Foundation (https://dx.doi.org/10.13039 <lb/>/501100011730), Award ID: TWCF-2022-30510. Maria A. Di Biase, National Health and <lb/>Medical Research Council (https://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000925), Award ID: <lb/>1175754. Andrew Zalesky, National Health and Medical Research Council (https://dx.doi <lb/>.org/10.13039/501100000925), Award ID: APP1118153. <lb/></div>

        <div type="availability">CODE AND DATA AVAILABILITY <lb/>The data of HCP are publicly available from https://www.humanconnectome.org/. The code <lb/>for the generative model is available from https://github.com/yuanzhel94/connectome_from <lb/>_pathfinding. <lb/></div>

        <listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>Akarca, D., Schiavi, S., Achterberg, J., Genc, S., Jones, D. K., &amp; <lb/>Astle, D. E. (2023). A weighted generative model of the human <lb/>connectome. bioRxiv. https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.06.23.546237 <lb/>Akarca, D., Vértes, P. E., Bullmore, E. T., CALM team, &amp; Astle, D. E. <lb/>(2021). A generative network model of neurodevelopmental <lb/>diversity in structural brain organization. Nature Communica-<lb/>tions, 12(1), 4216. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-021-24430-z, <lb/>PubMed: 34244490 <lb/>Alberts, B. (2017). Molecular biology of the cell. Garland Science. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1201/9781315735368 <lb/>Amunts, K., Lepage, C., Borgeat, L., Mohlberg, H., Dickscheid, T., <lb/>Rousseau, M.-É., … Evans, A. C. (2013). BigBrain: An <lb/>ultrahigh-resolution 3D human brain model. Science, 340(6139), <lb/>1472-1475. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1235381, PubMed: <lb/>23788795 <lb/>Arnatkevičiūtė, A., Fulcher, B. D., &amp; Fornito, A. (2019). A practical <lb/>guide to linking brain-wide gene expression and neuroimaging <lb/>data. NeuroImage, 189, 353-367. https://doi.org/10.1016/j <lb/>.neuroimage.2019.01.011, PubMed: 30648605 <lb/>Bassett, D. S., &amp; Bullmore, E. T. (2017). Small-world brain networks <lb/>revisited. Neuroscientist, 23(5), 499-516. https://doi.org/10.1177 <lb/>/1073858416667720, PubMed: 27655008 <lb/>Betzel, R. F., Avena-Koenigsberger, A., Goñi, J., He, Y., de Reus, <lb/>M. A., Griffa, A., … Sporns, O. (2016). Generative models of <lb/>the human connectome. NeuroImage, 124(Pt A), 1054-1064. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroimage.2015.09.041, PubMed: <lb/>26427642 <lb/>Betzel, R. F., &amp; Bassett, D. S. (2018). Specificity and robustness of <lb/>long-distance connections in weighted, interareal connectomes. <lb/>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 115(21), <lb/>E4880-E4889. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1720186115, <lb/>PubMed: 29739890 <lb/>Beul, S. F., Goulas, A., &amp; Hilgetag, C. C. (2018). Comprehensive <lb/>computational modelling of the development of mammalian cor-<lb/>tical connectivity underlying an architectonic type principle. <lb/>PLoS Computational Biology, 14(11), e1006550. https://doi.org <lb/>/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006550, PubMed: 30475798 <lb/>Broido, A. D., &amp; Clauset, A. (2019). Scale-free networks are rare. <lb/>Nature Communications, 10(1), 1017. https://doi.org/10.1038 <lb/>/s41467-019-08746-5, PubMed: 30833554 <lb/>Brose, K., Bland, K. S., Wang, K. H., Arnott, D., Henzel, W., <lb/>Goodman, C. S., … Kidd, T. (1999). Slit proteins bind Robo recep-<lb/>tors and have an evolutionarily conserved role in repulsive axon <lb/>guidance. Cell, 96(6), 795-806. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0092 <lb/>-8674(00)80590-5, PubMed: 10102268 <lb/>Buzsáki, G., &amp; Mizuseki, K. (2014). The log-dynamic brain: How <lb/>skewed distributions affect network operations. Nature Reviews <lb/>Neuroscience, 15(4), 264-278. https://doi.org/10.1038 <lb/>/nrn3687, PubMed: 24569488 <lb/>Cahalane, D. J., Clancy, B., Kingsbury, M. A., Graf, E., Sporns, O., &amp; <lb/>Finlay, B. L. (2011). Network structure implied by initial axon <lb/>outgrowth in rodent cortex: Empirical measurement and models. <lb/>PLOS ONE, 6(1), e16113. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone <lb/>.0016113, PubMed: 21264302 <lb/>Cajal, R. (1890). A quelle epoque apparissent les expensions des <lb/>cellules nerveuses de la molle epiniere du poulet. Anatomischer <lb/>Anseiger, 5, 609-613. <lb/>Canty, A. J., &amp; Murphy, M. (2008). Molecular mechanisms of axon <lb/>guidance in the developing corticospinal tract. Progress in Neu-<lb/>robiology, 85(2), 214-235. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pneurobio <lb/>.2008.02.001, PubMed: 18378059 <lb/>Carozza, S., Akarca, D., &amp; Astle, D. (2023). The adaptive stochas-<lb/>ticity hypothesis: Modeling equifinality, multifinality, and adapta-<lb/>tion to adversity. Proceedings of the National Academy of <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Network Neuroscience <lb/></note>

        <page>1208 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A generative model of the connectome with dynamic axon growth <lb/>Downloaded from http://direct.mit.edu/netn/article-pdf/8/4/1192/2479295/netn_a_00397.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>Sciences of the United States of America, 120(42), e2307508120. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2307508120, PubMed: 37816058 <lb/>Chavoshnejad, P., Li, X., Zhang, S., Dai, W., Vasung, L., Liu, T., … <lb/>Razavi, M. J. (2021). Role of axonal fibers in the cortical folding <lb/>patterns: A tale of variability and regularity. Brain Multiphysics, 2, <lb/>100029. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.brain.2021.100029 <lb/>Chilton, J. K. (2006). Molecular mechanisms of axon guidance. <lb/>Developmental Biology, 292(1), 13-24. https://doi.org/10.1016 <lb/>/j.ydbio.2005.12.048, PubMed: 16476423 <lb/>Clauset, A., Shalizi, C. R., &amp; Newman, M. E. J. (2009). Power-law <lb/>distributions in empirical data. SIAM Review, 51(4), 661-703. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1137/070710111 <lb/>Deco, G., Perl, Y. S., Vuust, P., Tagliazucchi, E., Kennedy, H., &amp; <lb/>Kringelbach, M. L. (2021). Rare long-range cortical connections <lb/>enhance human information processing. Current Biology, 31(20), <lb/>4436-4448. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2021.07.064, <lb/>PubMed: 34437842 <lb/>Dickson, B. J. (2002). Molecular mechanisms of axon guidance. <lb/>Science, 298(5600), 1959-1964. https://doi.org/10.1126 <lb/>/science.1072165, PubMed: 12471249 <lb/>Eguíluz, V. M., Chialvo, D. R., Cecchi, G. A., Baliki, M., &amp; <lb/>Apkarian, A. V. (2005). Scale-free brain functional networks. <lb/>Physical Review Letters, 94(1), 018102. https://doi.org/10.1103 <lb/>/PhysRevLett.94.018102, PubMed: 15698136 <lb/>Ercsey-Ravasz, M., Markov, N. T., Lamy, C., Van Essen, D. C., <lb/>Knoblauch, K., Toroczkai, Z., &amp; Kennedy, H. (2013). A predictive <lb/>network model of cerebral cortical connectivity based on a <lb/>distance rule. Neuron, 80(1), 184-197. https://doi.org/10.1016/j <lb/>.neuron.2013.07.036, PubMed: 24094111 <lb/>Faskowitz, J., Yan, X., Zuo, X.-N., &amp; Sporns, O. (2018). Weighted <lb/>stochastic block models of the human connectome across the life <lb/>span. Scientific Reports, 8(1), 12997. https://doi.org/10.1038 <lb/>/s41598-018-31202-1, PubMed: 30158553 <lb/>Fornito, A., Zalesky, A., &amp; Breakspear, M. (2015). The connec-<lb/>tomics of brain disorders. Nature Reviews Neuroscience, 16(3), <lb/>159-172. https://doi.org/10.1038/nrn3901, PubMed: 25697159 <lb/>Fornito, A., Zalesky, A., &amp; Bullmore, E. (2016). Fundamentals of <lb/>brain network analysis. Academic Press. https://doi.org/10.1016 <lb/>/C2012-0-06036-X <lb/>Gămănuţ, R., Kennedy, H., Toroczkai, Z., Ercsey-Ravasz, M., Van <lb/>Essen, D. C., Knoblauch, K., &amp; Burkhalter, A. (2018). The mouse <lb/>cortical connectome, characterized by an ultra-dense cortical <lb/>graph, maintains specificity by distinct connectivity profiles. <lb/>Neuron, 97(3), 698-715. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2017 <lb/>.12.037, PubMed: 29420935 <lb/>Gastner, M. T., &amp; Ódor, G. (2016). The topology of large open con-<lb/>nectome networks for the human brain. Scientific Reports, 6(1), <lb/>27249. https://doi.org/10.1038/srep27249, PubMed: 27270602 <lb/>Giacopelli, G., Migliore, M., &amp; Tegolo, D. (2020). Graph-theoretical <lb/>derivation of brain structural connectivity. Applied Mathematics <lb/>and Computation, 377, 125150. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.amc <lb/>.2020.125150 <lb/>Glasser, M. F., Sotiropoulos, S. N., Wilson, J. A., Coalson, T. S., <lb/>Fischl, B., Andersson, J. L., … WU-Minn HCP Consortium. <lb/>(2013). The minimal preprocessing pipelines for the Human <lb/>Connectome Project. NeuroImage, 80, 105-124. https://doi.org <lb/>/10.1016/j.neuroimage.2013.04.127, PubMed: 23668970 <lb/>Hagmann, P. (2005). From diffusion MRI to brain connectomics. EPFL. <lb/>Hansen, J. Y., Shafiei, G., Markello, R. D., Smart, K., Cox, S. M. L., <lb/>Nørgaard, M., … Misic, B. (2022). Mapping neurotransmitter sys-<lb/>tems to the structural and functional organization of the human <lb/>neocortex. Nature Neuroscience, 25(11), 1569-1581. https://doi <lb/>.org/10.1038/s41593-022-01186-3, PubMed: 36303070 <lb/>Hassan, B. A., &amp; Hiesinger, P. R. (2015). Beyond molecular codes: <lb/>Simple rules to wire complex brains. Cell, 163(2), 285-291. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2015.09.031, PubMed: 26451480 <lb/>Henriksen, S., Pang, R., &amp; Wronkiewicz, M. (2016). A simple <lb/>generative model of the mouse mesoscale connectome. elife, <lb/>5, e12366. https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.12366, PubMed: <lb/>26978793 <lb/>Hentschel, H. G., &amp; van Ooyen, A. (1999). Models of axon guid-<lb/>ance and bundling during development. Proceedings of the <lb/>Royal Society of London. Series B: Biological Sciences, <lb/>266(1434), 2231-2238. https://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.1999 <lb/>.0913, PubMed: 10649638 <lb/>Hentschel, H. G. E., &amp; van Ooyen, A. (2000). Dynamic mechanisms <lb/>for bundling and guidance during neural network formation. <lb/>Physica A: Statistical Mechanics and its Applications, 288(1-4), <lb/>369-379. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0378-4371(00)00434-9 <lb/>Horvát, S., Gămănuţ, R., Ercsey-Ravasz, M., Magrou, L., Gămănuţ, <lb/>B., Van Essen, D. C., … Kennedy, H. (2016). Spatial embedding <lb/>and wiring cost constrain the functional layout of the cortical net-<lb/>work of rodents and primates. PLoS Biology, 14(7), e1002512. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.1002512, PubMed: <lb/>27441598 <lb/>Kaiser, M., &amp; Hilgetag, C. C. (2004). Modelling the development of <lb/>cortical systems networks. Neurocomputing, 58, 297-302. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neucom.2004.01.059 <lb/>Kaiser, M., Hilgetag, C. C., &amp; van Ooyen, A. (2009). A simple rule <lb/>for axon outgrowth and synaptic competition generates realistic <lb/>connection lengths and filling fractions. Cerebral Cortex, 19(12), <lb/>3001-3010. https://doi.org/10.1093/cercor/ bhp071, PubMed: <lb/>19435708 <lb/>Katz, M. J. (1985). How straight do axons grow? Journal of Neuro-<lb/>science, 5(3), 589-595. https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.05 <lb/>-03-00589.1985, PubMed: 3973686 <lb/>Katz, M. J., George, E. B., &amp; Gilbert, L. J. (1984). Axonal elongation <lb/>as a stochastic walk. Cell Motility, 4(5), 351-370. https://doi.org <lb/>/10.1002/cm.970040505, PubMed: 6509522 <lb/>Kennedy, T. E., Serafini, T., de la Torre, J. R., &amp; Tessier-Lavigne, M. <lb/>(1994). Netrins are diffusible chemotropic factors for commis-<lb/>sural axons in the embryonic spinal cord. Cell, 78(3), 425-435. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/0092-8674(94)90421-9, PubMed: <lb/>8062385 <lb/>Kerstjens, S., Michel, G., &amp; Douglas, R. J. (2022). Constructive con-<lb/>nectomics: How neuronal axons get from here to there using <lb/>gene-expression maps derived from their family trees. PLoS <lb/>Computational Biology, 18(8), e1010382. https://doi.org/10 <lb/>.1371/journal.pcbi.1010382, PubMed: 36006873 <lb/>Kidd, T., Bland, K. S., &amp; Goodman, C. S. (1999). Slit is the midline <lb/>repellent for the robo receptor in Drosophila. Cell, 96(6), <lb/>785-794. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0092-8674(00)80589-9, <lb/>PubMed: 10102267 <lb/>Kintner, C. (2002). Neurogenesis in embryos and in adult neural stem <lb/>cells. Journal of Neuroscience, 22(3), 639-643. https://doi.org/10 <lb/>.1523/JNEUROSCI.22-03-00639.2002, PubMed: 11826093 <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Network Neuroscience <lb/></note>

        <page>1209 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A generative model of the connectome with dynamic axon growth <lb/>Downloaded from http://direct.mit.edu/netn/article-pdf/8/4/1192/2479295/netn_a_00397.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>Klimm, F., Bassett, D. S., Carlson, J. M., &amp; Mucha, P. J. (2014). <lb/>Resolving structural variability in network models and the brain. <lb/>PLoS Computational Biology, 10(3), e1003491. https://doi.org/10 <lb/>.1371/journal.pcbi.1003491, PubMed: 24675546 <lb/>Liu, Y., Seguin, C., Mansour, S., Oldham, S., Betzel, R., Di Biase, <lb/>M. A., &amp; Zalesky, A. (2023). Parameter estimation for connec-<lb/>tome generative models: Accuracy, reliability, and a fast param-<lb/>eter fitting method. NeuroImage, 270, 119962. https://doi.org/10 <lb/>.1016/j.neuroimage.2023.119962, PubMed: 36822248 <lb/>Mansour L., S., Tian, Y., Yeo, B. T. T., Cropley, V., &amp; Zalesky, A. <lb/>(2021). High-resolution connectomic fingerprints: Mapping neural <lb/>identity and behavior. NeuroImage, 229, 117695. https://doi.org <lb/>/10.1016/j.neuroimage.2020.117695, PubMed: 33422711 <lb/>Markello, R. D., Hansen, J. Y., Liu, Z.-Q., Bazinet, V., Shafiei, G., <lb/>Suárez, L. E., … Misic, B. (2022). Neuromaps: Structural and <lb/>functional interpretation of brain maps. Nature Methods, <lb/>19(11), 1472-1479. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41592-022-01625-w, <lb/>PubMed: 36203018 <lb/>Markov, N. T., Ercsey-Ravasz, M. M., Ribeiro Gomes, A. R., Lamy, <lb/>C., Magrou, L., Vezoli, J., … Kennedy, H. (2014). A weighted and <lb/>directed interareal connectivity matrix for macaque cerebral <lb/>cortex. Cerebral Cortex, 24(1), 17-36. https://doi.org/10.1093 <lb/>/cercor/bhs270, PubMed: 23010748 <lb/>Murray, J. D. (2002). Mathematical biology: I. An introduction. <lb/>Springer. https://doi.org/10.1007/b98868 <lb/>Oh, S. W., Harris, J. A., Ng, L., Winslow, B., Cain, N., Mihalas, S., … <lb/>Zeng, H. (2014). A mesoscale connectome of the mouse brain. <lb/>Nature, 508(7495), 207-214. https://doi.org/10.1038 <lb/>/nature13186, PubMed: 24695228 <lb/>Oldham, S., Fulcher, B. D., Aquino, K., Arnatkevičiūtė, A., Paquola, <lb/>C., Shishegar, R., &amp; Fornito, A. (2022). Modeling spatial, devel-<lb/>opmental, physiological, and topological constraints on human <lb/>brain connectivity. Science Advances, 8(22), eabm6127. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.abm6127, PubMed: 35658036 <lb/>Oliveri, H., &amp; Goriely, A. (2022). Mathematical models of neuronal <lb/>growth. Biomechanics and Modeling in Mechanobiology, 21(1), <lb/>89-118. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10237-021-01539-0, PubMed: <lb/>34994872 <lb/>Pavlovic, D. M., Vértes, P. E., Bullmore, E. T., Schafer, W. R., &amp; <lb/>Nichols, T. E. (2014). Stochastic blockmodeling of the modules <lb/>and core of the Caenorhabditis elegans connectome. PLOS ONE, <lb/>9(7), e97584. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0097584, <lb/>PubMed: 24988196 <lb/>Priebe, C. E., Park, Y., Tang, M., Athreya, A., Lyzinski, V., Vogelstein, <lb/>J. T., … Cardona, A. (2017). Semiparametric spectral modeling of <lb/>the Drosophila connectome. arXiv. https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv <lb/>.1705.03297 <lb/>Roberts, J. A., Perry, A., Lord, A. R., Roberts, G., Mitchell, P. B., <lb/>Smith, R. E., … Breakspear, M. (2016). The contribution of geometry <lb/>to the human connectome. NeuroImage, 124, 379-393. https://doi <lb/>.org/10.1016/j.neuroimage.2015.09.009, PubMed: 26364864 <lb/>Rubinov, M., Ypma, R. J. F., Watson, C., &amp; Bullmore, E. T. (2015). <lb/>Wiring cost and topological participation of the mouse brain <lb/>connectome. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, <lb/>112(32), 10032-10037. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1420315112, <lb/>PubMed: 26216962 <lb/>Scannell, J. W., Blakemore, C., &amp; Young, M. P. (1995). Analysis of <lb/>connectivity in the cat cerebral cortex. Journal of Neuroscience, <lb/>15(2), 1463-1483. https://doi.org/10.1523/ JNEUROSCI.15-02 <lb/>-01463.1995, PubMed: 7869111 <lb/>Serafini, T., Kennedy, T. E., Gaiko, M. J., Mirzayan, C., Jessell, T. M., <lb/>&amp; Tessier-Lavigne, M. (1994). The netrins define a family of <lb/>axon outgrowth-promoting proteins homologous to C. elegans <lb/>UNC-6. Cell, 78(3), 409-424. https://doi.org/10.1016/0092 <lb/>-8674(94)90420-0, PubMed: 8062384 <lb/>Simpson, S. L., Hayasaka, S., &amp; Laurienti, P. J. (2011). Exponential <lb/>random graph modeling for complex brain networks. PLOS ONE, <lb/>6(5), e20039. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0020039, <lb/>PubMed: 21647450 <lb/>Sinke, M. R. T., Dijkhuizen, R. M., Caimo, A., Stam, C. J., &amp; Otte, <lb/>W. M. (2016). Bayesian exponential random graph modeling of <lb/>whole-brain structural networks across lifespan. NeuroImage, <lb/>135, 79-91. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroimage.2016.04.066, <lb/>PubMed: 27132542 <lb/>Siugzdaite, R., Akarca, D., Johnson, A., Carozza, S., Anwyl-Irvine, <lb/>A. L., Uh, S., … Astle, D. E. (2022). Socio-economic disadvantage <lb/>is associated with alterations in brain wiring economy. bioRxiv. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.06.08.495247 <lb/>Song, H. F., Kennedy, H., &amp; Wang, X.-J. (2014). Spatial embedding <lb/>of structural similarity in the cerebral cortex. Proceedings of the <lb/>National Academy of Sciences, 111(46), 16580-16585. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1414153111, PubMed: 25368200 <lb/>Song, S., Sjöström, P. J., Reigl, M., Nelson, S., &amp; Chklovskii, D. B. <lb/>(2005). Highly nonrandom features of synaptic connectivity in <lb/>local cortical circuits. PLoS Biology, 3(3), e68. https://doi.org/10 <lb/>.1371/journal.pbio.0030068, PubMed: 15737062 <lb/>Sperry, R. W. (1963). Chemoaffinity in the orderly growth of nerve <lb/>fiber patterns and connections. Proceedings of the National <lb/>Academy of Sciences, 50(4), 703-710. https://doi.org/10.1073 <lb/>/pnas.50.4.703, PubMed: 14077501 <lb/>Sporns, O., &amp; Betzel, R. F. (2016). Modular brain networks. Annual <lb/>Review of Psychology, 67, 613-640. https://doi.org/10.1146 <lb/>/annurev-psych-122414-033634, PubMed: 26393868 <lb/>Sporns, O., Chialvo, D. R., Kaiser, M., &amp; Hilgetag, C. C. (2004). <lb/>Organization, development and function of complex brain net-<lb/>works. Trends in Cognitive Sciences, 8(9), 418-425. https://doi <lb/>.org/10.1016/j.tics.2004.07.008, PubMed: 15350243 <lb/>Sporns, O., Tononi, G., &amp; Kötter, R. (2005). The human connec-<lb/>tome: A structural description of the human brain. PLoS Compu-<lb/>tational Biology, 1(4), e42. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi <lb/>.0010042, PubMed: 16201007 <lb/>Tournier, J.-D., Calamante, F., King, M. D., Gadian, D. G., &amp; <lb/>Connelly, A. (2002). Limitations and requirements of diffusion <lb/>tensor fiber tracking: An assessment using simulations. Magnetic <lb/>Resonance in Medicine, 47(4), 701-708. https://doi.org/10.1002 <lb/>/mrm.10116, PubMed: 11948731 <lb/>Uğurbil, K., Xu, J., Auerbach, E. J., Moeller, S., Vu, A. T., Duarte-<lb/>Carvajalino, J. M., … WU-Minn HCP Consortium. (2013). Pushing <lb/>spatial and temporal resolution for functional and diffusion MRI in <lb/>the Human Connectome Project. NeuroImage, 80, 80-104. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroimage.2013.05.012, PubMed: 23702417 <lb/>van den Heuvel, M. P., Stam, C. J., Boersma, M., &amp; Pol, H. E. H. <lb/>(2008). Small-world and scale-free organization of voxel-based <lb/>resting-state functional connectivity in the human brain. Neuro-<lb/>Image, 43(3), 528-539. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroimage <lb/>.2008.08.010, PubMed: 18786642 <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Network Neuroscience <lb/></note>

        <page>1210 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A generative model of the connectome with dynamic axon growth <lb/>Downloaded from http://direct.mit.edu/netn/article-pdf/8/4/1192/2479295/netn_a_00397.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>Van Essen, D. C., Smith, S. M., Barch, D. M., Behrens, T. E. J., <lb/>Yacoub, E., Ugurbil, K., &amp; WU-Minn HCP Consortium. (2013). <lb/>The WU-Minn human connectome project: An overview. Neuro-<lb/>Image, 80, 62-79. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroimage.2013.05 <lb/>.041, PubMed: 23684880 <lb/>Vértes, P. E., Alexander-Bloch, A. F., Gogtay, N., Giedd, J. N., <lb/>Rapoport, J. L., &amp; Bullmore, E. T. (2012). Simple models of <lb/>human brain functional networks. Proceedings of the National <lb/>Academy of Sciences, 109(15), 5868-5873. https://doi.org/10 <lb/>.1073/pnas.1111738109, PubMed: 22467830 <lb/>Wadsworth, W. G. (2015). Understanding axon guidance: Attraction, <lb/>repulsion, and statistical physics. Neural Regeneration Research, <lb/>10(2), 176-179. https://doi.org/10.4103/1673-5374.152360, <lb/>PubMed: 25883605 <lb/>Wang, Q., Sporns, O., &amp; Burkhalter, A. (2012). Network analysis of <lb/>corticocortical connections reveals ventral and dorsal processing <lb/>streams in mouse visual cortex. Journal of Neuroscience, 32(13), <lb/>4386-4399. https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.6063-11.2012, <lb/>PubMed: 22457489 <lb/>Zang, Y., Chaudhari, K., &amp; Bashaw, G. J. (2021). New insights into the <lb/>molecular mechanisms of axon guidance receptor regulation and <lb/>signaling. Current Topics in Developmental Biology, 142, 147-196. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/bs.ctdb.2020.11.008, PubMed: 33706917 <lb/>Zhang, X., Braun, U., Harneit, A., Zang, Z., Geiger, L. S., Betzel, <lb/>R. F., … Tost, H. (2021). Generative network models of altered <lb/>structural brain connectivity in schizophrenia. NeuroImage, 225, <lb/>117510. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroimage.2020.117510, <lb/>PubMed: 33160087 <lb/>Zucca, R., Arsiwalla, X. D., Le, H., Rubinov, M., Gurguí, A., &amp; <lb/>Verschure, P. (2019). The degree distribution of human brain <lb/>functional connectivity is generalized Pareto: A multi-scale <lb/>analysis. bioRxiv. https://doi.org/10.1101/840066 <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Network Neuroscience <lb/></note>

        <page>1211 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A generative model of the connectome with dynamic axon growth <lb/>Downloaded from http://direct.mit.edu/netn/article-pdf/8/4/1192/2479295/netn_a_00397.pdf by guest on 10 September 2025 </note>


	</text>

</TEI>