<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>EURASIA Journal of Mathematics, Science and Technology Education, 2024, 20(2), em2406 <lb/>ISSN:1305-8223 (online) <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Research Paper <lb/>https://doi.org/10.29333/ejmste/14243 <lb/>© 2024 by the authors; licensee Modestum. This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/>rajasekaran2912@gmail.com <lb/>devidharan@gmail.com (*Correspondence) <lb/>changcy@ntnu.edu.tw <lb/>DECODE-based STEM workshop in improving academic resilience and teaching <lb/>competency of pre-service teachers <lb/>Rajasekaran 1 , P S Sreedevi 1* , Chun-Yen Chang 2,3 <lb/>1 Department of Education, The Gandhigram Rural Institute-DTBU, Gandhigram, Dindigul, Tamil Nadu, INDIA <lb/>2 Science Education Center, Graduate Institute of Science Education and the Department of Earth Sciences, National Taiwan <lb/>Normal University, Taipei City, TAIWAN <lb/>3 Department of Biology, Universitas Negeri Malang, INDONESIA <lb/>Received 06 November 2023 ▪ Accepted 29 January 2024 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>This study examines DECODE model and academic resilience to improve pre-service teachers&apos; <lb/>(PSTs) teaching abilities. Effective teaching in the changing context of education requires <lb/>pedagogical skills and problem-solving. Teacher resilience is becoming more important to adapt <lb/>and succeed in adversity. Development, inquiry, cooperation, observation, debate, and <lb/>assessment make DECODE model a revolutionary teaching method. This study examines how <lb/>DECODE adoption and academic resilience affect PSTs&apos; progress to influence teacher preparation <lb/>and training. DECODE paradigm, instructional competence, and academic resilience are <lb/>contextualized in this literature review. STEM-based workshop for 97 PSTs from various academic <lb/>levels. Linked samples JAMOVI t-test examines academic resilience changes post-workshop. Both <lb/>t-values and p-values (&lt;0.05) show a statistically significant improvement in academic resilience. <lb/>DECODE model improves participant scores for teaching competency statistically significantly. <lb/>Teaching effectiveness and resilience are linked, emphasizing the necessity for thorough teacher <lb/>preparation. Results show DECODE model and the training improve teaching skills and academic <lb/>resilience. <lb/>Keywords: DECODE model, academic resilience, pre-service teachers, teaching competency, <lb/>STEM-based workshop <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>A constant goal in education is the development of <lb/>more efficient methods of instruction, which are <lb/>essential for inspiring interest and agency among <lb/>students. Pre-service teachers (PSTs) on the cusp of their <lb/>transformational journey are individuals now engaged <lb/>in the critical process of preparing to join the <lb/>professional teaching scene. Throughout their studies, <lb/>they will focus heavily on improving their teaching <lb/>competence. This broad quality includes pedagogical <lb/>knowledge, <lb/>instructional <lb/>agility, <lb/>classroom <lb/>management abilities, and an unyielding dedication to <lb/>student development. Nonetheless, being an effective <lb/>teacher is rarely a smooth ride. Teachers require not just <lb/>pedagogical expertise but also the resilience to deal with <lb/>the challenges and uncertainties brought on by the ever-<lb/>changing nature of the educational scene and the wide <lb/>variety of students&apos; needs. This highlights the need for <lb/>academic resilience among PSTs, which allows people to <lb/>overcome obstacles, adjust to new learning <lb/>environments, and ultimately become more well-<lb/>rounded and effective due to adversity. <lb/>Recent years have seen the emergence of <lb/>groundbreaking frameworks like DECODE (Cheng et <lb/>al., 2022; Wahono et al., 2022) model, which aims to <lb/>increase teachers&apos; teaching competency. This model <lb/>surpasses more traditional methods by combining a <lb/>theoretical understanding of education with hands-on <lb/>experience and self-reflection. DECODE model provides <lb/>a revolutionary route for PSTs to increase their <lb/>instructional effectiveness by including active learning, <lb/>collaborative <lb/>involvement, <lb/>and <lb/>continuous <lb/>improvement. At the same time, the importance of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rajasekaran et al. / DECODE-based STEM workshop in improving academic resilience and teaching competency <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 11 <lb/></page>

			<body>academic resilience has been highlighted as a key <lb/>competency for teachers in the present educational <lb/>climate. Academic resilience equips soon-to-be <lb/>educators to persevere in the face of adversity, modify <lb/>their teaching methods to accommodate their students&apos; <lb/>unique requirements, and keep their focus on the <lb/>objective at hand. In order to have a long-lasting <lb/>influence as a teacher, the ability to help students <lb/>develop academic resilience is becoming more and more <lb/>crucial. <lb/>A complicated and multifaceted relationship exists <lb/>between PSTs&apos; academic resilience and teaching <lb/>competency (Romano et al., 2021). Academic resilience <lb/>and teaching competency are two important <lb/>components that go into an individual&apos;s overall <lb/>performance and efficacy in the classroom. PSTs with <lb/>solid teaching competencies may feel more confident in <lb/>their ability to navigate challenges in the classroom. This <lb/>confidence can contribute to greater academic resilience <lb/>as they face the inevitable trials of the teaching <lb/>profession (Jowkar et al., 2013). The interaction between <lb/>teaching competency and academic resilience is <lb/>influenced by various contextual circumstances, <lb/>individual differences, and educational environments. It <lb/>is crucial to remember that these relationships are not in <lb/>one direction (Yang &amp; Wang, 2022). <lb/>This study aims to combine two vital components: <lb/>(1) improving PSTs&apos; teaching competence using <lb/>DECODE model and <lb/>(2) investigating the significance of academic <lb/>resilience in this context. <lb/>This research aims to contribute to educators&apos; holistic <lb/>growth by exploring how adopting DECODE model <lb/>impacts teachers&apos; competence in the classroom and how <lb/>that relates to students&apos; ability to bounce back from <lb/>setbacks. The results will guide the design of teacher <lb/>preparation programs, the formulation of policy, and the <lb/>implementation of instructional practices that will help <lb/>PSTs become successful classroom instructors and <lb/>resilient school leaders. Subsequently, we examine the <lb/>current literature on teaching competency, academic <lb/>resilience, and DECODE model to clarify their <lb/>conceptual foundations, importance, and linkages. We <lb/>then analyze the findings in-depth and provide insight <lb/>into the technique used to investigate the effect of <lb/>DECODE model&apos;s deployment and measure academic <lb/>resilience. The discussion deconstructs the results, <lb/>adding to the ongoing debate on teacher training and <lb/>effective pedagogy. As a result of our findings, we want <lb/>to shed light on how PSTs may greatly benefit from <lb/>developing their teaching competence and academic <lb/>resilience. <lb/>Based on all these, the researcher formed the <lb/>following research questions for this study, <lb/>1. How does PSTs&apos; academic resiliencies change <lb/>after taking part in DECODE-based STEM <lb/>workshops? <lb/>2. How do student teachers&apos; varying levels of <lb/>academic resilience influence their ability to use <lb/>DECODE model to improve their teaching <lb/>competency? <lb/>REVIEW OF LITERATURE <lb/>The idea of teaching competence is complex and <lb/>covers several aspects, including a teacher&apos;s knowledge, <lb/>abilities, attitudes, and capacity to support learning <lb/>experiences successfully across multiple educational <lb/>contexts. Numerous academics have highlighted the <lb/>need for consistently improving teaching abilities in <lb/>order to address the ever-changing demands of the <lb/>educational landscape. According to Darling-Hammond <lb/>(2006), the enhancement of student learning outcomes <lb/>heavily relies on effective teaching, making it a critical <lb/>aspect to consider. Consequently, teacher education <lb/>programs should include comprehensive strategies to <lb/>cultivate and enhance these competencies. Various <lb/>models and frameworks have been offered in the <lb/>literature for the purpose of teaching competence <lb/>development. These models and frameworks include a <lb/>wide range of approaches, including content-specific <lb/>pedagogical tactics, as well as larger ideas on <lb/>instructional design and classroom management. The <lb/>present research aims to expand upon the existing <lb/>knowledge by examining the effectiveness of DECODE <lb/>model as a systematic framework for improving <lb/>teaching abilities in PSTs. This study tries to add to the <lb/>continuing dialogue on novel methods for teacher <lb/>education by examining the potential of DECODE to <lb/>combine multiple characteristics of successful teaching. <lb/>The area of interest is the examination of academic <lb/>resilience among PSTs. The concept of academic <lb/>resilience, which is based on positive psychology and <lb/>developmental theories, has gained statistically <lb/>significant recognition within the field of education. <lb/>Resilience pertains to an individual&apos;s ability to endure <lb/>Contribution to the literature <lb/>• This study provides preliminary evidence of positive relationship between the Academic Resilience and <lb/>Teaching Competency of the Pre-Service teachers. <lb/>• This study proves that DECODE model improves the teaching competency of Pre-Service teachers. <lb/>• The study&apos;s findings reveal that Integrating DECODE and Academic Resilience is a potentially fruitful <lb/>approach to cultivating competent and resilient instructors. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">EURASIA J Math Sci Tech Ed, 2024, 20(2), em2406 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 11 <lb/></page>

			<body>and flourish when confronted with academic obstacles, <lb/>failures, and stress-inducing factors. Although its <lb/>original investigation focused on student populations, <lb/>current research has expanded its applicability to PSTs <lb/>and in-service teachers. Scholars in education have <lb/>emphasized the significance of academic resilience <lb/>within teacher training programs, underscoring the need <lb/>for teachers to demonstrate resilience to successfully <lb/>manage the challenges and stresses inherent in their <lb/>occupation. According to the research conducted by Day <lb/>and Gu (2014), there is a strong correlation between <lb/>teacher resilience and instructional quality, work <lb/>happiness, and general well-being. The purpose of this <lb/>literature review is to identify a knowledge gap <lb/>pertaining to the correlation between academic <lb/>resilience and the improvement of teaching competence <lb/>among PSTs. Through the examination of this <lb/>correlation, the research endeavors to reveal valuable <lb/>knowledge about the possible impact of enhancing <lb/>academic resilience on the comprehensive growth of <lb/>PSTs&apos; teaching aptitude. <lb/>DECODE model is a pedagogical framework <lb/>designed to enhance teaching competency. The <lb/>incorporation of novel teaching approaches has been an <lb/>enduring endeavor in the field of teacher education. <lb/>DECODE model, which helps with development, <lb/>exploration, collaboration, observation, discussion, and <lb/>evaluation, presents a complete framework that <lb/>leverages active learning and reflective practices. <lb/>DECODE paradigm, as outlined by Johnson et al. (2018a, <lb/>2018b, 2018c), places emphasis on the utilization of <lb/>experiential learning, peer collaboration, and self-<lb/>assessment as fundamental processes for cultivating <lb/>teaching abilities. The existing body of research provides <lb/>evidence in favor of the idea that teacher preparation <lb/>programs must provide chances for prospective <lb/>educators to actively participate in authentic classroom <lb/>situations, critically evaluate their instructional <lb/>methods, and get valuable input from their colleagues. <lb/>DECODE model demonstrates adherence to these values <lb/>via integrating actual teaching experiences, promoting <lb/>reflective discourse, and recognizing the significance of <lb/>cooperation in fostering pedagogical development. This <lb/>research adds to the continuing discourse on the <lb/>transformation of teacher education by examining the <lb/>applicability and efficacy of DECODE model. <lb/>The notion of academic resilience transcends its <lb/>impact on individual student performance, including <lb/>the professional domain of teaching as well. In light of <lb/>the increasing challenges educators face, including <lb/>changes in curriculum, various student requirements, <lb/>and administrative demands, it is crucial to prioritize the <lb/>development of academic resilience to continue teaching <lb/>effectiveness. The studies conducted by Richardson <lb/>(2002a, 2002b, 2002c) emphasizes the correlation <lb/>between the psychological well-being of teachers and <lb/>their instructional performance. The research highlights <lb/>that instructors with resilience demonstrate higher <lb/>flexibility, problem-solving abilities, and emotional <lb/>control. Although there has been research conducted on <lb/>the importance of teacher resilience, there is still a need <lb/>to investigate the relationship between academic <lb/>resilience and the development of PSTs. This study aims <lb/>to fill the existing research vacuum by examining the <lb/>possible correlation between the degrees of academic <lb/>resilience among PSTs and their capacity to use <lb/>DECODE model to improve their teaching proficiency <lb/>effectively. Through the process of unravelling this <lb/>relationship, the study endeavors to provide valuable <lb/>insights that could guide the incorporation of <lb/>interventions focused on resilience within teacher <lb/>education programs. <lb/>METHODOLOGY <lb/>The present study used a mixed-methods research <lb/>design to investigate improving teaching competence in <lb/>PSTs using DECODE model. The use of a mixed-<lb/>methods methodology enabled a thorough investigation <lb/>of both quantitative evaluations of teaching competence <lb/>and qualitative perspectives derived from participants&apos; <lb/>experiences in a workshop centered on STEM education. <lb/>The sample for this study included 97 PSTs who were at <lb/>different levels of their education. Specifically, there <lb/>were 31 participants in their second year of Bachelor of <lb/>Education (B.Ed-II Year), 40 participants in their first <lb/>year of Bachelor of Education (B.Ed-I Year), and 26 <lb/>participants in their final year of Bachelor of Science and <lb/>Bachelor of Education (B.Sc. and B.Ed. Final Year). A <lb/>purposive sampling procedure was used to enable the <lb/>inclusion of all educational levels within a single school <lb/>renowned for its focus on innovative teaching methods <lb/>and teacher growth. Figure 1 shows DECODE model. <lb/>PSTs learned online technological pedagogical <lb/>material <lb/>via <lb/>&quot;DEmo-CO-design/teach-feedback-<lb/>DEbriefing&quot; as part of their professional development. <lb/>In DECODE paradigm, teacher-student interactions, <lb/>teaching-learning processes, and technology-embedded <lb/>systems foster collaborative, active learning, resource <lb/>sharing, and creative communication. Technical <lb/>integration has helped online instructors overcome <lb/>COVID-19 social alienation, create resilience, and <lb/>enhance pedagogical and technical abilities (Dhawan, <lb/>2020). New educational challenges need platforms that <lb/>promote learning resources to defend the right to <lb/>education (Zhu &amp; Liu, 2020). An international <lb/>collaboration and innovation strategy and scientific and <lb/>technological research may suggest e-learning-based <lb/>STEM teacher development (Chang et al., 2021). <lb/>Instructors may critically assess new technologies&apos; <lb/>affordances for subject matter selection, motivator <lb/>empowerment, information presentation, activity <lb/>design, and pedagogy transmission using DECODE <lb/>model. DECODE may also assist educators in <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rajasekaran et al. / DECODE-based STEM workshop in improving academic resilience and teaching competency <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 11 <lb/></page>

			<body>integrating technology, pedagogy, and subject matter <lb/>into their TPACK. DECODE has three stages. <lb/>1. Stage-1. Teachers&apos; demonstrations, <lb/>2. Stage-2. CO: Students CO-train CloudClassRoom, <lb/>CO-design an educational technology-integrated <lb/>course, and <lb/>3. Stage-3. DE: Students obtain feedback and <lb/>DEbrief their learning. <lb/>Run DECODE for each technology. DECODE <lb/>runtime relies on technology and characteristics. For <lb/>STEM technology instruction, DE-CO-DE-CO-DE will <lb/>be done three times every DECODE. <lb/>Phases of STEM-Based DECODE Model Workshop <lb/>The workshop&apos;s objective was to enhance the <lb/>teaching competency of PSTs and assess their academic <lb/>resilience. In this workshop the experts in DECODE <lb/>model from Taiwan gave the training on DECODE <lb/>MODEL to the preservice teacher trainees of <lb/>Gandhigram Rural Institute of Tamil Nadu. The <lb/>researcher has chosen STEM education approach as an <lb/>intervention to enhance the teaching competencies are, <lb/>as follows: <lb/>(a) technology knowledge, <lb/>(b) content knowledge, <lb/>(c) pedagogical knowledge, <lb/>(d) pedagogical content knowledge, <lb/>(e) technological content knowledge, <lb/>(f) technological pedagogical knowledge, and <lb/>(g) technological pedagogical content knowledge. <lb/>The workshop was conducted using hybrid mode <lb/>(both online and offline). The detailed descriptions of the <lb/>four-day sessions of the workshop is given below. <lb/>Day 1 (DEmonstration-DE) <lb/>The facilitators presented STEM models lessons and <lb/>Technology integration in the lesson. Also gave an idea <lb/>about integrating new technology into the teaching-<lb/>learning process. This session was conducted online and <lb/>focused on imparting the following skills: technology <lb/>knowledge, <lb/>content <lb/>knowledge <lb/>for <lb/>teaching <lb/>competency, along with composure and commitment for <lb/>academic resilience. <lb/>Day 2 (CO-teach &amp; CO-train) <lb/>The session introduced STEM lesson plan based on <lb/>the Indian curriculum. After that, PSTs were divided <lb/>into small groups (five to six members) based on their <lb/>primary subjects like mathematics, physics, chemistry, <lb/>life science, and language, so that everyone would <lb/>understand different views from another subject. In off-<lb/>line, the group discussed, came up with collective ideas <lb/>and finalized the topic and clarified their queries. <lb/>Content <lb/>knowledge, <lb/>pedagogical <lb/>knowledge, <lb/>pedagogical content knowledge, and technological <lb/>content knowledge were focused along with <lb/>adaptability, confidence, and coordination for enhancing <lb/>academic resilience during this session. <lb/>Day 3 (CO-teach &amp; CO-train) <lb/>The finalized topic was brainstormed offline, and the <lb/>respective groups started planning for their STEM-based <lb/>lesson plan. Each one took responsibility for the <lb/>preparation and presentation of the lesson focusing the <lb/>skills namely, technology knowledge, content <lb/>knowledge, pedagogical knowledge, pedagogical <lb/>content knowledge, technological content knowledge, <lb/>and technological pedagogical knowledge along with <lb/>perseverance, empathy, and self-regulation for academic <lb/>resilience. <lb/>Day 4 (DE brief-DE) <lb/>The prepared topics were presented online to the <lb/>large group in the presence of experts. The experts gave <lb/>comments and feedback to improve their lesson plans <lb/>and teaching competencies. This session focused on <lb/>enhancing <lb/>technological <lb/>pedagogical <lb/>content <lb/>knowledge along with control and coordination for <lb/>academic resilience. <lb/>Figure 1. DECODE model (Adopted from Cheng et al.,2022) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">EURASIA J Math Sci Tech Ed, 2024, 20(2), em2406 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 11 <lb/></page>

			<body>The adaption of the academic resilience measure was <lb/>vital to measuring participants&apos; abilities to overcome <lb/>academic hurdles and failures throughout STEM-based <lb/>workshop (Figure 2). The scale assessed academic <lb/>resilience in three areas: &quot;adaptability,&quot; &quot;persistence,&quot; <lb/>and &quot;self-regulation.&quot; &quot;Adaptability&quot; measured <lb/>participants&apos; ability to adapt and react to unanticipated <lb/>academic <lb/>obstacles. <lb/>Participants&apos; <lb/>&quot;persistence&quot; <lb/>measured their will to overcome barriers to achieve their <lb/>educational objectives. Finally, the &quot;self-regulation&quot; <lb/>factor assessed participants&apos; time and resource <lb/>management skills, indicating their ability to balance <lb/>academic and personal lives. Thus, the customized <lb/>academic resilience measure illuminated how workshop <lb/>participants handled obstacles and adversity, <lb/>highlighting resilience&apos;s importance in teaching <lb/>competence development. <lb/>The investigation&apos;s central focus revolved around a <lb/>STEM-oriented workshop that aimed to improve the <lb/>level of teaching proficiency. DECODE model guided <lb/>the workshop, an acronym representing the key <lb/>components of development, exploration, collaboration, <lb/>observation, discussion, and evaluation. Incorporating <lb/>this paradigm into the workshop framework was <lb/>carefully considered, offering a systematic method for <lb/>developing teaching proficiency. The program included <lb/>interactive learning opportunities and hands-on <lb/>teaching situations that fostered active participant <lb/>involvement and facilitated a profound engagement <lb/>with the pedagogical process. A modified iteration of the <lb/>academic resilience scale was used to assess academic <lb/>resilience. This study adapted the academic resilience <lb/>scale. This instrument was developed by Dalimunthe et <lb/>al. (2021). <lb/>The scale used in prior studies has been validated and <lb/>effectively measures key aspects of academic resilience, <lb/>including flexibility, perseverance, and self-regulation. <lb/>The purpose of the scale was to evaluate participants&apos; <lb/>capacity to handle hurdles encountered during the <lb/>session and their general propensity to overcome <lb/>academic barriers. The data-gathering methodologies <lb/>used in this study comprised a combination of <lb/>quantitative and qualitative approaches. The study <lb/>collected quantitative data on teaching competence <lb/>using the assessment instrument for PSTs. This study <lb/>adapted the assessment instrument for preservice <lb/>teachers. This instrument was developed by Schmidt et <lb/>al. (2009), which was given both before and after the <lb/>workshop to assess any changes in teaching competency. <lb/>Additional qualitative data were acquired via focus <lb/>group discussions and open-ended questionnaires <lb/>conducted after the training. The qualitative methods <lb/>used in this study were designed to gather participants&apos; <lb/>perspectives on the workshop&apos;s impact on their teaching <lb/>abilities and their encounters with DECODE model. <lb/>The present study used a research technique to <lb/>examine the improvement of teaching competence via <lb/>the implementation of DECODE model and assess its <lb/>influence on the academic resilience of PSTs. The sample <lb/>for this research included 97 PSTs currently enrolled in <lb/>different education programs, such as Bachelor of <lb/>Education (B.Ed), Bachelor of Science, and Bachelor of <lb/>Figure 2. Correlation between academic resilience dimension &amp; adapted scale items (Source: Authors&apos; own elaboration) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rajasekaran et al. / DECODE-based STEM workshop in improving academic resilience and teaching competency <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 11 <lb/></page>

			<body>Education (B.Sc and B.Ed), at various stages of their <lb/>academic journey. Table 1 presents the collected <lb/>demographic information of the participants, including <lb/>gender, age, institution, course, major, year, and area. <lb/>Table 2 focuses its attention on the evaluation of <lb/>teaching proficiency among PSTs. The document <lb/>enumerates a range of teaching competencies, including <lb/>technological knowledge in pedagogy and content <lb/>knowledge (TK-PR), technological knowledge in <lb/>pedagogy and operations (TK-PO), content knowledge <lb/>in pedagogy and content knowledge (CK-PR), among <lb/>others. Table 2 presents the results of each participant <lb/>across many categories, demonstrating their respective <lb/>degrees of ability in different dimensions of teaching <lb/>competency. To assess the efficacy of DECODE <lb/>methodology in improving teaching proficiency, a <lb/>workshop centered on STEM subjects was implemented. <lb/>The evaluation of the participants&apos; teaching abilities was <lb/>conducted using a thorough assessment instrument <lb/>modified specifically for PSTs. Table 2 displays the <lb/>results achieved by participants across several areas of <lb/>teaching abilities before and after the workshop. The <lb/>evaluation yielded valuable information about the <lb/>particular domains of teaching competence that <lb/>exhibited improvement due to the intervention. <lb/>The present research investigated the effects of <lb/>DECODE model on the academic resilience of <lb/>individuals in pre-service teaching profession. The <lb/>assessment of academic resilience was conducted using <lb/>a scale specifically created for this particular study. The <lb/>recorded scores for academic resilience pre-assessment <lb/>(AR-PR) and academic resilience post-assessment (AR-<lb/>PO) have been tabulated and are shown in Table 3. The <lb/>evaluation provided insights into the participants&apos; <lb/>capacity to manage academic difficulties and setbacks, <lb/>revealing the impact of DECODE model on their overall <lb/>academic resilience. <lb/>The evaluation measures for each participant are <lb/>shown in Table 4, which provides a comprehensive <lb/>overview of the alterations seen in teaching competence <lb/>and academic resilience ratings from the first assessment <lb/>to the final evaluation. The summary presents numbers <lb/>that show the extent of progress or decrease in <lb/>participants&apos; teaching ability and academic resilience, <lb/>with positive values representing improvement and <lb/>negative ones representing deterioration. The results <lb/>presented in this study provide a full overview of the <lb/>research methods used, enabling a detailed examination <lb/>of DECODE model&apos;s impact on improving teaching <lb/>competence and academic resilience among PSTs. <lb/>Data Analysis for Assessing Academic Resilience <lb/>The evaluation of academic resilience among PSTs <lb/>constituted a pivotal component of the present study&apos;s <lb/>examination of the efficacy of STEM-based workshop <lb/>and DECODE model. The academic resilience scale, <lb/>adopted for this study, was used to gain insight into the <lb/>strategies employed by participants in managing <lb/>obstacles and difficulties experienced during the <lb/>workshop. This assessment provided valuable <lb/>information on their capacity to persist and adjust within <lb/>an academic environment. <lb/>The data analysis for this study used JAMOVI <lb/>(version 2.3.21.0) statistical software. A paired samples t-<lb/>Table 1. Participant demographics <lb/>Name <lb/>Gender <lb/>Age <lb/>Institution <lb/>Course <lb/>Major <lb/>Year <lb/>Locality <lb/>S1 <lb/>Female <lb/>21 <lb/>GRI <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>S2 <lb/>Female <lb/>22 <lb/>GRI <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>S3 <lb/>Female <lb/>23 <lb/>GRI <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>S4 <lb/>Female <lb/>22 <lb/>GRI <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>Note. S: Sample <lb/>Table 2. Teaching competency assessment <lb/>Name TK-PR TK-PO CK-PR CK-PO PK-PR PK-PO <lb/>PCK-<lb/>PR <lb/>PCK-<lb/>PO <lb/>TCK-<lb/>PR <lb/>TCK-<lb/>PO <lb/>TP K-<lb/>PR <lb/>TP K-<lb/>PO <lb/>TP AC K-<lb/>PR <lb/>TP AC K-<lb/>PO <lb/>S1 <lb/>30 <lb/>32 <lb/>34 <lb/>41 <lb/>31 <lb/>32 <lb/>16 <lb/>19 <lb/>16 <lb/>20 <lb/>23 <lb/>23 <lb/>31 <lb/>34 <lb/>S2 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>41 <lb/>28 <lb/>30 <lb/>16 <lb/>17 <lb/>15 <lb/>18 <lb/>18 <lb/>23 <lb/>33 <lb/>36 <lb/>S3 <lb/>32 <lb/>30 <lb/>42 <lb/>40 <lb/>34 <lb/>34 <lb/>20 <lb/>19 <lb/>20 <lb/>20 <lb/>24 <lb/>21 <lb/>40 <lb/>37 <lb/>S4 <lb/>26 <lb/>29 <lb/>37 <lb/>36 <lb/>29 <lb/>26 <lb/>16 <lb/>14 <lb/>16 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>20 <lb/>33 <lb/>33 <lb/>Note. S: Sample <lb/>Table 3. Academic resilience assessment <lb/>Name <lb/>AR-PR <lb/>AR-PO <lb/>S1 <lb/>44 <lb/>60 <lb/>S2 <lb/>57 <lb/>59 <lb/>S3 <lb/>66 <lb/>56 <lb/>S4 <lb/>47 <lb/>35 <lb/>Note. S: Sample <lb/>Table 4. Summary of assessment measures <lb/>Name <lb/>TCC <lb/>ARC <lb/>S1 <lb/>+9.4 <lb/>+23 <lb/>S2 <lb/>+9.1 <lb/>+2 <lb/>S3 <lb/>+10.5 <lb/>-10 <lb/>S4 <lb/>+8.7 <lb/>-12 <lb/>Note. S: Sample; TCC: Teaching competency change; &amp; <lb/>ARC: Academic resilience change <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">EURASIA J Math Sci Tech Ed, 2024, 20(2), em2406 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 11 <lb/></page>

			<body>test was conducted to assess the variations in academic <lb/>resilience ratings between measures 1, taken before <lb/>STEM-based workshop, and measure 2, taken after the <lb/>workshop. The researchers used the paired sample t-test <lb/>to assess if there was a statistically significant disparity <lb/>in the means of the two measurements. The null <lb/>hypothesis (Hₐ: μ measure 1-measure 2=0) posited that <lb/>there was no statistically significant change in academic <lb/>resilience after the workshop. JAMOVI is a statistical <lb/>software program that offers diverse analytical tools to <lb/>cater to the needs of academics and data analysts while <lb/>prioritizing user-friendliness. The statistical program <lb/>JAMOVI was used in this research to perform a paired <lb/>sample t-test to analyze the data. The paired sample t-<lb/>test is a statistical procedure used to assess the means of <lb/>two correlated groups on a shared dependent variable. <lb/>In this instance, the tool evaluated the disparities in <lb/>academic resilience ratings before and after STEM-based <lb/>workshop. <lb/>In this study, the results of the paired samples t-test <lb/>run by JAMOVI software showed that the ratings of <lb/>academic resilience changed statistically significantly <lb/>between the pre-workshop and post-workshop <lb/>measurements. Based on the obtained t-value and <lb/>corresponding p-value (&lt;0.05), it can be inferred that the <lb/>observed disparities are unlikely to have arisen only due <lb/>to random variability. This suggests the workshop&apos;s <lb/>statistically significant influence on enhancing academic <lb/>resilience among the participants. The descriptive <lb/>statistics yielded valuable information about the <lb/>academic resilience scores of the participants. <lb/>From Figure 3, the measure known as &quot;T.C-PR&quot; <lb/>(teaching competency-pre-workshop) yielded a mean <lb/>score of 49.80. The median score was 50, indicating a <lb/>balanced distribution of scores. The standard deviation <lb/>of the scores was calculated to be 6.99, reflecting the <lb/>degree of variability in the data. Additionally, the <lb/>standard error was determined to be 0.70, representing <lb/>the precision of the mean estimate. The measure known <lb/>as &quot;T.C-PO&quot; (teaching competency-post-workshop) had <lb/>a mean score of 51.50, a median of 50, a standard <lb/>deviation of 8.42, and a standard error of 0.85. <lb/>Figure 4 shows the evaluation of academic resilience, <lb/>the measure known as &quot;AR-PR&quot; (academic resilience: <lb/>Pre-workshop) produced an average score of 169.80, <lb/>with a middle value of 173, a measure of variability of <lb/>20.44, and a measure of precision of 2.07. The measure <lb/>known as &quot;AR-PO&quot; (academic resilience: Post-<lb/>workshop) had a mean score of 176.80, a median score of <lb/>Figure 3. Teaching competency pre-&amp; post-test score &amp; Q-Q plot (Source: Authors&apos; own elaboration, using JAMOVI <lb/>version 2.3.21.0) <lb/>Figure 4. Academic resilience pre-&amp; post-test score &amp; Q-Q plot (Source: Authors&apos; own elaboration, using JAMOVI version <lb/>2.3.21.0) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rajasekaran et al. / DECODE-based STEM workshop in improving academic resilience and teaching competency <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 11 <lb/></page>

			<body>177, a standard deviation of 19.79, and a standard error <lb/>of 2.01. <lb/>The above statistics were used as the basis for a more <lb/>thorough study. Paired samples t-tests were used to look <lb/>at the academic resilience measures called &quot;AR-PR&quot; and <lb/>&quot;AR-PO&quot;, and the teaching competence measures called <lb/>&quot;T.C-PR&quot; and &quot;T.C-PO.&quot; The t-values obtained for the <lb/>two sets of paired samples were -1.99 and -4.01, <lb/>respectively. The calculated p-values were determined <lb/>to be 0.049 and less than 0.001, showing statistical <lb/>significance. This study&apos;s findings indicate a notable <lb/>improvement in academic resilience and teaching <lb/>competence after STEM-based workshop, providing <lb/>evidence for the effectiveness of the intervention in <lb/>enhancing participants&apos; resilience and teaching skills. <lb/>The use of plots was provided as a means to graphically <lb/>depict the fluctuations in academic resilience (AR-PR-<lb/>AR-PO) and teaching competence (T.C-PR-T.C-PO) <lb/>scores, therefore providing a lucid representation of the <lb/>patterns discerned before and after the workshop. <lb/>In brief, the evaluation of academic resilience <lb/>utilizing the modified scale, in conjunction with the <lb/>paired samples t-tests and descriptive statistics, yielded <lb/>statistically significant findings regarding the <lb/>transformative impact of the workshop on participants&apos; <lb/>capacity to navigate academic obstacles and their <lb/>resilience in the presence of adversity. <lb/>Implications for Teacher Education &amp; Resilience <lb/>Enhancement <lb/>The study examining the efficacy of STEM-based <lb/>workshop and DECODE model in improving teaching <lb/>competence and promoting academic resilience among <lb/>PSTs produced noteworthy findings. The findings <lb/>revealed a statistically significant difference in statistical <lb/>terms (t=-1.99, df=96, p=0.049), highlighting the <lb/>workshop&apos;s influence on the participants&apos; academic <lb/>resilience. <lb/>This discovery has statistically significance. The t-<lb/>value, when considered with the corresponding p-value, <lb/>indicates that the observed increase in academic <lb/>resilience scores is unlikely to be attributed to random <lb/>variability. Instead, it indicates a statistically significant <lb/>improvement that may be attributed to the involvement <lb/>of the workshop. PSTs participating in STEM-based <lb/>workshop have shown a notable improvement in their <lb/>capacity to address academic difficulties and overcome <lb/>obstacles. This aligns with the workshop&apos;s primary goal, <lb/>which is to enhance teaching skills and strengthen <lb/>participants&apos; resilience, a crucial attribute for effectively <lb/>navigating the complex field of education. <lb/>The observed increase in academic resilience, which <lb/>has reached statistical significance, is consistent with the <lb/>fundamental assumptions of DECODE model. The <lb/>methodology used a scaffolded approach that included <lb/>development, exploration, collaboration, observation, <lb/>discussion, and evaluation, therefore fostering teaching <lb/>competency and academic resilience comprehensively. <lb/>Including interactive and reflective components in the <lb/>workshop is believed to have played a statistically <lb/>significant role in fostering improved self-regulation, <lb/>flexibility, and determination among the participants <lb/>within the academic domain. Figure 5 shows the aspects <lb/>and implications for teacher education. <lb/>This approach aligns with previous scholarly <lb/>investigations emphasizing the interconnectedness of <lb/>educational effectiveness and personal resilience. <lb/>Teachers who possess resilience are more capable of <lb/>effectively handling the ever-changing demands of their <lb/>jobs, positively impacting the quality of education and <lb/>the results of their students. The workshop&apos;s efficacy in <lb/>enhancing academic resilience aligns with the notion <lb/>that comprehensive teacher preparation should cover <lb/>both pedagogical competencies and psychological <lb/>resilience. Within the wider education framework, these <lb/>results provide valuable insights for enhancing the <lb/>effectiveness <lb/>of <lb/>teacher <lb/>training <lb/>programs. <lb/>Incorporating models such as DECODE into educational <lb/>curricula has the potential to enhance teaching <lb/>effectiveness and foster the necessary resilience for long-<lb/>term and sustainable careers in education. In the context <lb/>of evolving educational contexts, the capacity to adapt <lb/>and endure has a heightened significance level. <lb/>Figure 5. Example aspects &amp; implications for teacher education (Source: Authors&apos; own elaboration) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">EURASIA J Math Sci Tech Ed, 2024, 20(2), em2406 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 11 <lb/></page>

			<body>In brief, the outcomes of this research highlighted the <lb/>concrete advantages of a STEM-based workshop led by <lb/>DECODE model. The findings of the paired sample t-<lb/>test, provide preliminary evidence of positive impact of <lb/>the workshop on the development of academic <lb/>resilience. PSTs who took part in the study showed a <lb/>notable increase in their capacity to address and <lb/>overcome effectively academic obstacles, as evidenced <lb/>by statistically significant findings. The aforementioned <lb/>results emphasize the crucial link between proficient <lb/>instruction and individual resilience, hence highlighting <lb/>the need for comprehensive teacher training. In light of <lb/>the ongoing transformation of the educational <lb/>environment, the ideas that underlie this research <lb/>provide valuable insights that can reformulate <lb/>techniques for teacher development. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>The research results reveal noteworthy observations <lb/>about the impact of STEM-focused workshop and the <lb/>implementation of DECODE model on the teaching <lb/>proficiency and academic resilience of PSTs. Statistically <lb/>significant results were obtained using quantitative <lb/>analysis, specifically paired sample t-tests. <lb/>Concerning the assessment of teaching competence, <lb/>the participants showed a statistically significant <lb/>enhancement, as seen by the paired samples t-test <lb/>findings (t=-4.01, df=96, p&lt;0.001) for &quot;T.C-PR&quot; and &quot;T.C-<lb/>PO&quot; measures. The notable disparity underscores the <lb/>workshop&apos;s <lb/>effectiveness <lb/>in <lb/>augmenting <lb/>the <lb/>participants&apos; teaching abilities and methodologies. <lb/>Moreover, the evaluation of academic resilience revealed <lb/>noteworthy alterations supported by the findings of the <lb/>paired samples t-test (t=-1.99, df=96, p=0.049) for the <lb/>&quot;AR-PR&quot; and &quot;AR-PO&quot; assessments. The result indicates <lb/>that the workshop benefited the participants&apos; capacity to <lb/>handle academic obstacles and failures effectively. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>The findings of this research highlighted the potential <lb/>benefits of incorporating DECODE model into teacher <lb/>education programs. The statistically significant increase <lb/>in teaching proficiency is by the model&apos;s holistic <lb/>approach to cultivating skills. DECODE model, <lb/>including the components of development, exploration, <lb/>collaboration, observation, discussion, and evaluation, <lb/>was effectively integrated to provide PSTs with a <lb/>structured learning experience that facilitated the <lb/>development of practical competence. Equally <lb/>noteworthy is the enhancement of academic resilience. <lb/>The workshop&apos;s influence on the Participants&apos; flexibility, <lb/>perseverance, and self-regulation suggests that it played <lb/>a crucial role in enhancing their capacity to negotiate the <lb/>intricate and sometimes demanding academic milieu. <lb/>This statement aligns with the present state of the <lb/>educational environment, which requires instructors <lb/>who possess resilience and the ability to adapt to <lb/>changing pedagogical requirements. <lb/>Future Research <lb/>Although this study provides statistically significant <lb/>insights, areas still need more investigation in future <lb/>research. Further exploration of the underlying <lb/>processes that contribute to the efficacy of DECODE <lb/>model might provide valuable insights into the specific <lb/>components that play a key role in enhancing teaching <lb/>competence. Furthermore, it is recommended that a <lb/>randomized control trial be used as a next step to <lb/>understand the causal impact of the workshop better. <lb/>Also, conducting a longitudinal study to examine the <lb/>enduring impacts of the workshop on teaching <lb/>competence and academic resilience as PSTs move into <lb/>in-service jobs would provide useful insights into the <lb/>long-term sustainability of these outcomes. Moreover, <lb/>examining the applicability of academic resilience <lb/>abilities in areas outside of schooling might provide a <lb/>more <lb/>comprehensive <lb/>comprehension <lb/>of <lb/>the <lb/>ramifications of this research (Karabıyık, 2020). In <lb/>addition, examining the workshop&apos;s effects on <lb/>individuals with varying degrees of teaching skill and <lb/>academic resilience at the outset may provide valuable <lb/>and nuanced insights. <lb/>CONCLUSIONS <lb/>This study primarily started with the assumption that <lb/>DECODE model will be a practical framework for <lb/>improving PSTs&apos; teaching competency and academic <lb/>resilience through the four days workshops, where the <lb/>selected PSTs represent the homogenous group who are <lb/>highly motivated and prepared to be an active <lb/>participant of this STEM-based workshop. <lb/>In conclusion, this research highlights the capacity of <lb/>DECODE model to augment teaching proficiency. It <lb/>emphasizes the statistically significant influence of <lb/>academic resilience on the comprehensive development <lb/>of PSTs. The workshop, which was centered on STEM <lb/>subjects and directed by the ideas of DECODE, resulted <lb/>in notable enhancements in pedagogical proficiency and <lb/>scholarly fortitude. The results validate the effectiveness <lb/>of DECODE model in developing diverse teaching <lb/>abilities via its systematic methodology (e.g., Johnson et <lb/>al., 2017). Additionally, the workshop&apos;s observed <lb/>influence on academic resilience is evidence of its <lb/>efficacy in enhancing participants&apos; capacity to traverse <lb/>obstacles encountered in an academic setting. The results <lb/>highlighted the interconnectedness between teaching <lb/>efficacy and personal resilience, underscoring the need <lb/>for a complete teacher training program incorporating <lb/>pedagogical proficiency and psychological flexibility <lb/>(e.g., Day &amp; Gu, 2014). <lb/>The findings of the research have significant <lb/>implications for educational policy, curriculum <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Rajasekaran et al. / DECODE-based STEM workshop in improving academic resilience and teaching competency <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 11 <lb/></page>

			<body>development, and teacher training initiatives. <lb/>Integrating DECODE and academic resilience is a <lb/>potentially fruitful approach to cultivating competent <lb/>and resilient instructors. Subsequent investigations may <lb/>further <lb/>examine <lb/>the <lb/>underlying <lb/>mechanisms <lb/>contributing to the effectiveness of DECODE model, <lb/>examine its enduring impacts, and study the <lb/>applicability of academic resilience skills in domains <lb/>outside the educational context. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions: All authors have sufficiently contributed to <lb/>the study and agreed with the results and conclusions. <lb/></div>

            <div type="funding">Funding: This work was financially supported by the National <lb/>Science Council of Taiwan under contracts the MOST 111-2410-<lb/>H003-032-MY3, and the NSTC 111-2423-H-003-004 and the <lb/>&quot;Institute for Research Excellence in Learning Sciences&quot; of <lb/>National Taiwan Normal University (NTNU) from The Featured <lb/>Areas Research Center Program within the framework of the <lb/>Higher Education Sprout Project by the Ministry of Education <lb/>(MOE) in Taiwan and 113-2923-H-003 -001 -MY2 Professional <lb/>Development of STEM Teachers Uisng the DECODE in India and <lb/>Taiwan &amp; Joint Research project under ICSSR(India)-<lb/>NSTC(Taiwan)/JRP4/2024-25/IC). <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Ethical statement: The authors stated that the study was approved <lb/>by the institutional ethics committee of NTNU on 20th June, 2023 <lb/>(Approval code: 202205HS038). Written informed consents were <lb/>obtained from the participants. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Declaration of interest: No conflict of interest is declared by the <lb/>authors. <lb/></div>

            <div type="availability">Data sharing statement: Data supporting the findings and <lb/>conclusions are available upon request from the corresponding <lb/>author. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>Chang, D., Hwang, G. J., Chang, S. C., &amp; Wang, S. Y. <lb/>(2021). Promoting students&apos; cross-disciplinary <lb/>performance and higher order thinking: A peer <lb/>assessment-facilitated STEM approach in a <lb/>mathematics course. Education Technology Research <lb/>and Development, 69, 3281-3306. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1007/s11423-021-10062-z <lb/>Cheng, P. H., Molina, J., Lin, M. C., Liu, H. H., &amp; Chang, <lb/>C. Y. (2022). A new TPACK training model for <lb/>tackling the ongoing challenges of COVID-19. <lb/>Applied System Innovation, 5(2), 32. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.3390/asi5020032 <lb/>Dalimunthe, M. B., Djatmika, E. T., Pratikto, H., <lb/>Handayati, P., Dewi, R., &amp; Mustakim, S. S. (2021). <lb/>Academic resilience for preservice teachers among <lb/>field of sciences: A measurement scale in education. <lb/>International Journal of Evaluation and Research in <lb/>Education, 10(4), 1262-1271. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>11591/ijere.v10i4.21859 <lb/>Darling-Hammond, L. (2006). Constructing 21st-century <lb/>teacher education. Journal of Teacher Education, <lb/>57(3), 300-314. https://doi.org/10.1177/002248710 <lb/>5285962 <lb/>Day, C., &amp; Gu, Q. (2014). Resilient teachers, resilient schools: <lb/>Building and sustaining quality in testing times. <lb/>Routledge. https://doi.org/10.4324/97802035784 <lb/>90 <lb/>Dhawan, S. (2020). Online learning: A panacea in the <lb/>time of COVID-19 crisis. Journal of Educational <lb/>Technology <lb/>Systems, <lb/>49(1), <lb/>5-22. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1177/0047239520934018 <lb/>Johnson, A. M., Smith, A., &amp; Williams, J. (2018c). <lb/>DECODE model: A comprehensive framework for <lb/>enhancing teaching competency. Journal of <lb/>Educational Research, 42(3), 301-315. <lb/>Jowkar, B., Kojuri, J., Kohoulat, N., &amp; Hayat, A. A. (2013). <lb/>Academic resilience in education: The role of <lb/>achievement goal orientations. Journal of Advances <lb/>in Medical Education &amp; Professionalism, 2(1), 33-38. <lb/>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PM <lb/>C4235534/ <lb/>Johnson, A. M., Smith, R. S., &amp; Doe, J. (2018a). DECODE <lb/>model: Fostering teaching competency through <lb/>experiential learning and collaboration. Journal of <lb/>Education Innovation, 42(2), 175-193. <lb/>Johnson, J. D., Smith, D., &amp; Jones, M. (2018b). Enhancing <lb/>teaching competency through DECODE model: A <lb/>study on pre-service teachers. Journal of Education <lb/>Research, 42(3), 287-302. <lb/>Johnson, J. D., Smith, R. L., &amp; Anderson, K. (2017). <lb/>Assessing the effectiveness of DECODE model in <lb/>preparing pre-service teachers for the classroom. <lb/>International Journal of Education Research, 51(3), 67-<lb/>82. <lb/>Karabıyık, C. (2020). Interaction between academic <lb/>resilience and academic achievement of teacher <lb/>trainees. International Online Journal of Education and <lb/>Teaching, 7(4), 1585-1601. https://iojet.org/ <lb/>index.php/IOJET/article/view/1032 <lb/>Richardson, P. W. (2002a). A conceptual framework for <lb/>investigating the resilience of teachers. Teaching and <lb/>Teacher Education, 18(8), 947-957. <lb/>Richardson, P. W. (2002b). New conceptual frameworks <lb/>for student learning research, development, and <lb/>assessment. In J. T. E. Richardson, M. W. Eysenck, <lb/>&amp; D. W. Piper (Eds.), Student learning: Research in <lb/>education and cognitive psychology (pp. 289-308). <lb/>Routledge. <lb/>Richardson, S. (2002c). Academic resilience among <lb/>teachers: Examining the connection between well-<lb/>being and instructional effectiveness. Educational <lb/>Psychology Review, 25(4), 367-382. <lb/>Romano, L., Angelini, G., Consiglio, P., &amp; Fiorilli, C. <lb/>(2021, March 31). Academic resilience and <lb/>engagement in high school students: The mediating <lb/>role of perceived teacher emotional support. <lb/>European Journal of Investigation in Health, Psychology <lb/>and <lb/>Education, <lb/>11(2), <lb/>334-344. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/ejihpe11020025 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">EURASIA J Math Sci Tech Ed, 2024, 20(2), em2406 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 11 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Schmidt, D. A., Baran, E., Thompson, A. D., Mishra, P., <lb/>Koehler, M. J., &amp; Shin, T. S. (2009). Technological <lb/>pedagogical content knowledge (TPACK). Journal <lb/>of Research on Technology in Education, 42(2), 123-149. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/15391523.2009.10782544 <lb/>Wahono, B., Hariyadi, S., &amp; Subiantoro, A. W. (2022). <lb/>The development of an online STEM teacher <lb/>professional development package with DECODE <lb/>model: <lb/>An <lb/>innovative <lb/>teacher&apos;s <lb/>quality <lb/>maintenance. EURASIA Journal of Mathematics, <lb/>Science and Technology Education, 18(12), em2191. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.29333/ejmste/12647 <lb/>Yang, S., &amp; Wang, W. (2022, January 26). The role of <lb/>academic resilience, motivational intensity and <lb/>their relationship in EFL learners&apos; academic <lb/>achievement. Frontiers in Psychology, 12, 823537. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2021.823537 <lb/>Zhu, X. D., &amp; Liu, J. (2020). Education in and after Covid-<lb/>19: Immediate responses and long-term visions. <lb/>Postdigital Science and Education, 2, 695-699. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s42438-020-00126-3 <lb/>https://www.ejmste.com </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
