<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Available online at www.HighTechJournal.org <lb/>HighTech and Innovation <lb/>Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/>489 <lb/>ISSN: 2723-9535 <lb/>Evaluating Household Consumption Patterns: Comparative <lb/>Analysis Using Ordinary Least Squares and Random Forest <lb/>Regression Models <lb/>En Lee 1 , Thian Song Ong 1* , Yvonne Lee 2 <lb/>1 Faculty of Information Science and Technology, Multimedia University, 75450 Melaka, Malaysia. <lb/>2 Faculty of Management, Multimedia University, Persiaran Multimedia, 63100 Cyberjaya, Malaysia. <lb/>Received 24 January 2024; Revised 19 May 2024; Accepted 24 May 2024; Published 01 June 2024 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>This research aims to decompose the contribution of socioeconomic factors towards household consumption expenditure <lb/>using a regression approach, with log per capita expenditure as the dependent variable. Our study stands out as the first to <lb/>utilise SHAP analysis and Machine Learning models to analyse household consumption expenditure. We select both OLS <lb/>(linear) and Random Forest (nonlinear) models to compare how they estimate consumption expenditure differently. Both <lb/>models explain about 85% of the variation in log per capita expenditure. The SHAP analysis reveals the nonlinear <lb/>relationships inside the Random Forest model. Several insightful findings were suggested that can be integrated into current <lb/>policy-making. The results are as follows: (1) Both models agree that income, household size, and educational level are <lb/>major factors in the purchasing power of household heads. (2) The Random Forest model demonstrated a nonlinear <lb/>contribution of age and household size towards log per capita expenditure, contrasting with previous studies that treated <lb/>them as linear. (3) Household heads with a higher income and educational level tend to spend more. (4) Current policy <lb/>should consider focusing on households with larger sizes and lower incomes, who tend to spend more despite earning less, <lb/>primarily by assisting them with non-cash transfers and subsidies. <lb/>Keywords: Household Consumption; Machine Learning; Linear Regression; Random Forest; Shapley Value. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>For many years, poverty, as commonly measured by income, has been at the forefront of social and economic policy <lb/>debates [1, 2]. Absolute poverty describes a situation where households or individuals are unable to meet minimum <lb/>levels of standard of living in terms of income, food, health care, shelter, and other needs [3]. As a nation aspiring to <lb/>achieve high-income status, the Malaysian government has introduced a series of initiatives to overcome the nation&apos;s <lb/>poverty issues, from the New Economic Policy (NEP) in the 1970s to the present Twelfth Malaysia Plan. The earliest <lb/>and most universally recognised method for measuring poverty is Poverty Line Income (PLI) [3]. It is a basic threshold <lb/>to determine whether a household has adequate means for survival. By summing the two PLI indicators, food and non-<lb/>food, households with a total income less than the combined PLI are considered to be in poverty, while households with <lb/>a total income less than the food PLI are known as households in absolute poverty. In 2019, the Malaysian government <lb/>adjusted the PLI threshold to RM2208, compared to only RM980 in 2005. However, although the 2019 PLI methodology <lb/></body>

			<front>* Corresponding author: tsong@mmu.edu.my <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.28991/HIJ-2024-05-02-019 <lb/>â¢ This is an open access article under the CC-BY license (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/>Â© Authors retain all copyrights. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>490 <lb/></page>

			<body>includes a household&apos;s food and non-food consumption in measuring poverty, it is just too narrow to reflect the <lb/>complexity of households living in poverty [4]. A holistic poverty measurement methodology that covers different socio-<lb/>economic indicators must be considered for economic policy planning, such as the multidimensional poverty index <lb/>(MPI), which utilises three dimensions: health, education, and standard of living [5]. Rahman et al. (2021) [6] proposed <lb/>an improved Malaysia MPI framework to enhance the poverty indicator&apos;s predictive powers with indicators for three <lb/>dimensions, namely education, living standards, and employment. The indicators are literacy, education level, sanitation, <lb/>housing, access to television services, and assets owned. <lb/>The current approaches used in Malaysia focus on using household income to define what constitutes a poor <lb/>household in Malaysia. Simply relying on income data is neither sufficient nor accurate, especially with the increase in <lb/>Malaysian household debt levels [7]. Income alone may not be enough to track poor households, especially the urban <lb/>poor. Various factors must be considered in constructing an accurate household poverty classification method. One of <lb/>the limitations of the income-based approach is the varying cost of living across states and regions. Besides that, income <lb/>variations due to age and life stage can have an impact on the accuracy of poverty estimates. For instance, a retired <lb/>couple with little or no income but substantial savings or assets may have a higher standard of living than a younger <lb/>household with more income but less savings or assets. Furthermore, income data may fail to account for differences in <lb/>the cost of living across strata, for example, the rural-urban gap. Recent trends show that consumption or expenditure <lb/>patterns could be a good indicator for measuring poverty. Household consumption expenditure, which includes spending <lb/>on necessities such as food, education, and health, can help infer the level of deprivation based on the type and quantity <lb/>of consumption expenditure. Analysing the proportion of household consumption expenditure on basic needs such as <lb/>food can tell whether the household faced deprivation or otherwise. Bhanoji Rao (1981) [8] mentioned that calculating <lb/>the deprivation point from annual expenditure can measure incidences of deprivation and thus construct the poverty line. <lb/>Besides that, Kumar et al. (2009) [9] investigated the deprivation of food in India by looking at expenditures on cereal <lb/>to understand whether the trend was declining or increasing before and during the India Reform Period to determine <lb/>household poverty status. <lb/>Recently, empirical literature has begun to employ machine learning for analysing the factors that influence <lb/>household income and expenditure [10-13]. Herrera et al. (2023) [10] utilised the traditional linear regression model as <lb/>well as other machine learning regression models such as Elastic Net, XGBoost, and Neural Network to investigate the <lb/>correlation between household socioeconomic and ICT characteristics and household income. It is important to mention <lb/>that although Elastic Net is part of the machine learning field, it is a linear model. The findings indicate a correlation <lb/>between educational attainment and the use of information and communication technologies (ICTs). Higher educational <lb/>levels and an older average age of household members are associated with higher incomes. Among the 4 models, <lb/>XGBoost and the neural network outperforms the rest in terms of accuracy. The authors emphasised the superiority of <lb/>the two nonlinear machine learning models due to their ability to uncover nonlinear relationships between variables, <lb/>which are often masked by the linear-based regression model. This can be verified by the SHAP summary plot inside <lb/>the study, as the XGBoost and Neural Network models treated the education level (the top-ranked variable in all the <lb/>proposed models) as an exponential function, while the linear and Elastic Net models assumed a linear relationship <lb/>between the educational level and income. Overall, this study shows that individuals with higher levels of education tend <lb/>to perform a broader range of complex tasks online and are more likely to gain more income. The finding further <lb/>emphasises the role of education in driving socioeconomic outcomes. <lb/>Hwang et al. (2022) [11] proposed deep learning clustering and logistic regression models to analyse the <lb/>heterogeneity in about 50,000 households in Korea. A clustering model was first constructed to examine the financial <lb/>heterogeneity of households in 8 clusters. The primary factor for a household to fall into wealthy clusters is their assets <lb/>in real estate, followed by loans obtained for real-estate investments. Later, demographical analysis was done by building <lb/>a logistic regression model with household demographic variables (age, educational level, income level, and household <lb/>size). Generally speaking, across the clusters, household heads with a higher age, better education, and higher income <lb/>live in the wealthy clusters, and vice versa. Moreover, the authors also investigated the probability of certain households <lb/>climbing from poor clusters to wealthy clusters from year 2017-2020. Unfortunately, those living in poor clusters are <lb/>more likely to move within the four poor clusters only. <lb/>Chowdhury et al. (2023) [12] investigated the impact of BRAC&apos;s Ultra-Poor Graduation (UPG) model on the <lb/>participant&apos;s wealth and expenditure level using Honest Causal Forest (HCF), one of the recent tree-based machine <lb/>learning algorithms. The UPG model offered participants both consumption expenditure supports or a grant of productive <lb/>assets with technical skills training. Findings show that the UPG programme led to significant gains by participants in <lb/>either wealth accumulation or consumption gain only. The affected households with a higher gain in asset outcome are <lb/>generally older, more dependent on wage income, and had less self-employment income at the baseline, while <lb/>participants experiencing consumption gains that led to increased expenditures are younger and earned higher income <lb/>from self-employment activities. <lb/>Zeng &amp; Chen (2022) [13] studied the urban-rural integration types in China and their changes within a ten-year period <lb/>from 1990 to 2020 using partitioning around medoids (PAM), a clustering-based machine learning model. Clustering <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>491 <lb/></page>

			<body>was first done, and the authors concluded that the rural-urban transition should be represented in 4 clusters (high-level <lb/>urban-rural integration, urban-rural integration in transition, early urban-rural integration in the backward stage, and <lb/>low-level urban-rural integration). Overall, results suggest that urbanisation lifts up economic growth. The most <lb/>important finding can be seen in Cluster 1. It is the highest urbanisation rate cluster, and the income, expenditure, housing <lb/>areas, and educational level gaps are the lowest among all, implying negative relationships (the higher the urbanisation, <lb/>the lower the gaps). <lb/>Although the importance of using consumption expenditure or income data for poverty analysis is recognised <lb/>globally, research focusing on measuring poverty through consumption expenditure, especially in Malaysia, is still <lb/>limited. To the best of the authors knowledge, the recent literature works that discuss household consumption issues with <lb/>a regression approach in Malaysia are as follows: Ang &amp; Cheah (2023), Zin &amp; Nabilah (2015), and Ayyash &amp; Sek (2020) <lb/>[14-16]. Ang &amp; Cheah (2023) [14] discussed the consumption inequality issue among different income groups in terms <lb/>of consumption of pharmaceutical goods only. Although the study highlighted disparities in expenditure in this industry, <lb/>the broader scope of the consequences of household sociodemographic characteristics on other expenditure types <lb/>remains unknown. On the other hand, Zin &amp; Nabilah (2015) [15] conducted linear and quantile regression to identify the <lb/>factors that contribute to household expenditure across urban and rural areas, but only considered three quantiles (three <lb/>expenditure levels). Moreover, the authors only ranked the determinants without showing their coefficients; the degree <lb/>of the determinants&apos; impacts remains unknown. Ayyash &amp; Sek (2020) [16] proposed Fields&apos; regression approach to <lb/>decompose consumption inequality based on household demographical variables. However, the proposed regression <lb/>model assumes linearity, which might not hold for certain important variables such as the age of the household head. <lb/>Given this research constraint, the purpose of this study is to investigate the regression analysis of consumption patterns <lb/>using a machine learning approach. We suggest using Random Forest because of its broad application. Random Forest, <lb/>along with many other Machine Learning models, has the ability to handle data that exhibits nonlinearity. In fact, our <lb/>finding shows that age has a nonlinear relationship with log per capita expenditure, contrasting with that which was <lb/>identified as having a positive linear relationship [15, 16]. Meanwhile, the contribution of household size towards log <lb/>per capita expenditure was also found to be complex, although closely to negatively linear. These nonlinearities are <lb/>discussed in detail in Section 3. One may question the black box nature of the Random Forest model, with concerns <lb/>about the lack of transparency that makes it challenging to &apos;view&apos; the relationship among variables. To address this issue, <lb/>we proposed another interpretability tool called SHapley Additive exPlanations (SHAP), which allows us to better <lb/>understand and explain the complex relationships between variables within the Random Forest model. <lb/>In this work, we mainly compare our result with Ayyash &amp; Sek&apos;s (2020) [16] study. This study can be viewed as an <lb/>extension of Ayyash &amp; Sek&apos;s (2020) [16] study, as both studies use the same data source (Household Expenditure Survey, <lb/>HES), select the same target variable (per capita expenditure), and decompose the degree to which determinants <lb/>contribute to household expenditure, but this study further explores the scope using Machine Learning model. HES is <lb/>an official survey programme launched by the Malaysian Department of Statistics (DOSM) that is conducted twice every <lb/>five years to collect individual information and expenditure patterns via personal interviews. Ayyash &amp; Sek&apos;s (2020) <lb/>[16] study was conducted using the 2014 version of the survey, while this study uses the 2019 version, which updates <lb/>the previous study&apos;s findings in addition to introducing an expanded analytical methodology. <lb/>Therefore, this study would like to investigate and analyse the consumption expenditure pattern in Malaysia, with <lb/>the following objectives: 1) To implement and evaluate the performance of Linear and Random Forest regression models. <lb/>2) To understand the determinants&apos; importance and the relationships that exist between a set of determinants and <lb/>household expenditure. 3) To compare the two models based on their respective findings. <lb/>The main contribution of this study can be summarised as follows: (1) To the best of the authors&apos; knowledge, this is <lb/>the first study to attempt to use Machine Learning model in conjunction with an explainable model to quantify and <lb/>visualise the impact of household demographic factors on household expenditure in Malaysia. (2) Income is the most <lb/>significant determinant in both models. Similar to Ayyash &amp; Sek&apos;s (2020) [16] result, from our proposed Ordinary Least <lb/>Squares (OLS) model, household size and educational level are the next two most influential factors that determine <lb/>household expenditure, followed by ethnicity and regional variables. However, findings from Machine Learning model <lb/>surprisingly indicate that regional variables contribute to household expenditure more than educational level, while the <lb/>importance of household size remains unchanged. (3) Based on the SHAP results, variables such as age and household <lb/>size are found to have nonlinear relationships towards per capita log expenditure, compared to positive linear <lb/>relationships found by Zin and Nabilah (2015) as well as Ayyash &amp; Sek (2020) [15, 16]. This suggests that when <lb/>decomposing household expenditure using regression, one should consider a regression model that can handle the <lb/>variables that appear to be nonlinear in nature. (4) Instead of interpreting the contribution of each determinant alone, <lb/>SHAP allows interpretation in three dimensions, providing a detailed picture of the overall relationship. Moreover, <lb/>conveying the results visually enhances interpretation for broader audiences, such as policymakers. <lb/>The remaining parts are organised as follows: Section 2 introduces the dataset and the methodology used; Section 3 <lb/>discusses the results of the study; and Section 4 summarises the study. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>492 <lb/></page>

			<body>2. Material and Methods <lb/>2.1. Overview <lb/>In general, there are several phases in this work: data preparation, feature engineering, modelling, and the evaluation <lb/>phase. At the end, SHAP analysis will be performed to further explain how the chosen Machine Learning model <lb/>influences its decision to make such predictions. During the data preparation phase, samples from household and member <lb/>records will go through a series of pre-processing steps before being fed into prediction models. In the feature <lb/>engineering phase, per capita income and expenditure are computed and converted into natural logarithm form. Next, <lb/>during the modelling phase, two models will be selected, which are OLS and Random Forest. Later, in the evaluation <lb/>phase, several metrics are chosen to compare and assess their performance. Figure 1 exhibits the flowchart of the <lb/>methodology and outlines the specific processes involved in the process, starting with data collection and concluding <lb/>with model evaluation and SHAP analysis. <lb/>2.2. Datasets <lb/>This study makes use of two dataset records: household and member datasets. Both datasets can work independently <lb/>or be linked with a unique key index column called HID (household ID) present in each dataset. HID serves as a unique <lb/>identifier for every household. The information about the two datasets utilised is explained in the following section. <lb/>a) Household Dataset <lb/>The first dataset is the household dataset, which has a total of 16,354 observations, each of which represents a single <lb/>household. This dataset contains ten columns. The first column, HID, represents the unique household ID that uniquely <lb/>identifies each row. The variables, data type, data format, and description are shown in Table 1. <lb/>Figure 1. Flowchart of the research methodology <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>493 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. Variable in household dataset <lb/>Variable <lb/>Data Type <lb/>Data Format <lb/>Description <lb/>HID <lb/>object <lb/>28 Numerical objects <lb/>Unique Household ID <lb/>Weight <lb/>float <lb/>Numerical <lb/>Statistical adjustments that are made to household survey data <lb/>NO_HH <lb/>int <lb/>1-21 <lb/>Household No <lb/>Saiz_HH <lb/>int <lb/>1-5 <lb/>Total household members <lb/>State <lb/>int <lb/>1-16 <lb/>Each represents a state/territory <lb/>Region <lb/>int <lb/>1-3 <lb/>1= Peninsular Malaysia or <lb/>2= Sabah &amp; Labuan <lb/>3 = Sarawak <lb/>Strata <lb/>int <lb/>1-2 <lb/>1 = Urban <lb/>2 = rural <lb/>Ethnic <lb/>int <lb/>1-4 <lb/>1 = Bumiputera <lb/>2 = Chinese <lb/>3 = Indian <lb/>4 = Others <lb/>Total_Exp_01_12 <lb/>float <lb/>Numerical <lb/>Total Household Expenditure for 12 expense types <lb/>Total_Inc <lb/>float <lb/>Numerical <lb/>Monthly household gross income <lb/>b) Member Dataset <lb/>This dataset contains 214,719 observations, with samples gathered at the individual level. Because each person has <lb/>a household ID, one or more people can originate from the same household. The variable, HID, which is the same as in <lb/>the household dataset, serves as the key column to merge individual-level data with the household-level dataset. Among <lb/>all observations, 64,160 individuals came from 16,354 different households. As a result, using the aggregation method, <lb/>these 64,160 people can be combined into 16,354 households. The remaining 150,559 individuals, who represent 38,147 <lb/>households, have no household-based data. Table 2 lists the dataset&apos;s variables, data type, data format, and description. <lb/>Table 2. Variable in member dataset <lb/>Variable <lb/>Data Type <lb/>Data Format <lb/>Description <lb/>HID <lb/>object <lb/>28 Numerical objects <lb/>Unique Household ID <lb/>NO_AIR <lb/>int <lb/>Numerical <lb/>Household Member No. <lb/>Relationship <lb/>int <lb/>1-12 <lb/>Position of member in household <lb/>Sex <lb/>int <lb/>1-2 <lb/>1 = Male <lb/>2 = Female <lb/>Age <lb/>int <lb/>0-98 <lb/>00 = children &lt; 1 year <lb/>01 = 1 to 97 years <lb/>98 = aged &gt;= 98 years <lb/>Ethnic <lb/>int <lb/>1-4 <lb/>1 = Bumiputera <lb/>2 = Chinese <lb/>3 = Indian <lb/>4 = Others <lb/>Marital_Status <lb/>int <lb/>1-5 <lb/>1 = Never Married <lb/>2 = Married <lb/>3 = Widow/Widower <lb/>4 = Divorced <lb/>5 = Separated <lb/>Highest_Certificate <lb/>float <lb/>1-6 <lb/>1 = No Certificate <lb/>2 = PMR/SRP <lb/>3 = SPM/ SPMV <lb/>4 = STPM <lb/>5 = Diploma / certificate <lb/>6 = Degree/Advance Diploma <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>494 <lb/></page>

			<body>Act_Status <lb/>int <lb/>1-15 <lb/>1 = Employer <lb/>2 = Government employee <lb/>3 = Private employee <lb/>4 = Own account worker <lb/>5 = Unpaid family worker <lb/>6 = Unemployed <lb/>7 =Housewife/looking after home <lb/>8 = Student <lb/>9 = Government pensioner <lb/>10 = Private pensioner <lb/>11 = Elderly <lb/>12 = Persons with Disabilities <lb/>13 = Child not at school <lb/>14 = Infant <lb/>15 = Others <lb/>Income_Recipient <lb/>int <lb/>1-2 <lb/>1 = Yes <lb/>2 = No <lb/>Occupation <lb/>int <lb/>1-3 <lb/>01 = Manager <lb/>02 = Professional <lb/>03 = Technician and associate professionals <lb/>2.3. Data Preparation <lb/>The household and member records are made up of several household and member samples with various attributes <lb/>that define each household&apos;s economic and non-economic condition. First, household and member records are merged <lb/>into a dataset by using the variable HID as the key index. This joined dataset is based on the household dataset, which <lb/>means it returns all household rows from the household table and matching records having the same households&apos; ID <lb/>from the member table. The remaining 38,147 households that have no household information are discarded. The merged <lb/>dataset is a dataset with 64,160 rows and a total of 16,354 households inside. All records from the household dataset are <lb/>retained, and then those records are matched with the same key index HID in the household dataset from the member <lb/>dataset. Finally, only household head rows inside the table are retained, producing a dataset with 16,354 rows. <lb/>2.4. Modelling Phase <lb/>In this phase, two models, OLS and Random Forest, are chosen. Both models can be used to examine the relationship <lb/>between household expenditure and its influencing factors. The Ordinary Least Squares represents a linear approach to <lb/>regression, while the Random Forest offers nonlinear modelling that can capture nonlinear and complex relationships <lb/>between predictors and the dependent variable. The aim of this work is to compare the performance of Random and OLS <lb/>models, focusing on the models&apos; interpretability of the nonlinearity connections and their overall accuracy scores. <lb/>c) Econometric Model <lb/>Model (1) is an application of OLS, which is a common econometric model used in economics. Following is the <lb/>linear model built for this study: <lb/>ğ‘™ğ‘œğ‘”(ğ‘¦ ğ‘– ) = ğ›½ 0 + ğ›½ 1 ğ‘‹ ğ‘–1 + ğ›½ 2 ğ‘‹ ğ‘–2 + â‹¯ + ğ›½ ğ¾ ğ‘‹ ğ‘–ğ¾ +âˆˆ ğ‘– <lb/>(1) <lb/>where ğ‘¦ ğ‘– denotes the dependent variable (per capita expenditure), log(ğ‘¦ ğ‘– ) is the natural logarithm form, ğ‘‹ ğ‘– are <lb/>independent variables, Î² ğ‘– are coefficients, Î² 0 is the intercept and âˆˆ ğ‘– is the error term. <lb/>d) Random Forest Regression <lb/>This is one of the most common supervised Machine Learning algorithms that relies on ensemble learning to perform <lb/>regression tasks. Multiple decision tree models predict the outcomes independently and then average them. For each <lb/>decision tree model in the Random Forest model, subset of sample is selected independently to train it. Generally, <lb/>Random Forest eliminates the overfitting problem due to its averaging properties. Random Forest can rank the feature <lb/>importance by finding out their impurity decrease. The feature with the highest impurity decrease is the most significant <lb/>feature. The equation of mean decreases the impurity measure as follows: <lb/>ğ‘–ğ‘šğ‘(ğ‘‹ ğ‘š ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>ğ‘ ğ‘‡ <lb/>âˆ‘ âˆ‘ <lb/>ğ‘(ğ‘¡)ğ›¥ğ‘–(ğ‘  ğ‘¡ <lb/>ğ‘¡ğœ–ğ‘‡:ğœ(ğ‘  ğ‘¡ )=ğ‘‹ ğ‘š <lb/>ğ‘‡ <lb/>, ğ‘¡) <lb/>(2) <lb/>where ğ‘‹ ğ‘š represents a variable, ğ‘(ğ‘¡) is the proportion of ğ‘ ğ‘‡ /ğ‘ of samples reaching ğ‘¡ and ğœ(ğ‘  ğ‘¡ )is the variable that was <lb/>used when making a split, and ğ‘(ğ‘¡)Î”i(ğ‘  ğ‘¡ , ğ‘¡) is the total weighted impurity decrease for all nodes ğ‘¡when considering the <lb/>ğ‘‹ ğ‘š variable. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>495 <lb/></page>

			<body>2.5. Experiment Setup <lb/>The dataset is initially divided into a training set and a testing set in a 4:1 ratio. This means that 80% of the data is <lb/>used to train the model, with the remaining 20% used to test it. The performance of trained model will be evaluated <lb/>based on the coefficient of determination or more commonly, R-squared (ğ‘… 2 ). It measures the total explainable variance <lb/>of predicted dependent variable from determinants. The formula of ğ‘… 2 is as follows: <lb/>ğ‘… 2 = 1 -<lb/>ğ‘†ğ‘† ğ‘Ÿğ‘’ğ‘  <lb/>ğ‘†ğ‘† ğ‘¡ğ‘œğ‘¡ <lb/>(3) <lb/>where ğ‘†ğ‘† ğ‘Ÿğ‘’ğ‘  is the sum of the residuals squared, while ğ‘†ğ‘† ğ‘¡ğ‘œğ‘¡ is the sum of distance the sample observations are from <lb/>mean squared. <lb/>Besides that, mean squared error (ğ‘€ğ‘†ğ¸) also used to evaluate the model performance. It computes the average <lb/>squared difference between the estimated value, ğ‘¦ Ì‚ and the true value, ğ‘¦. The ğ‘€ğ‘†ğ¸ can have only positive value, the <lb/>closer the value to 0, the better the model performance. The ğ‘€ğ‘†ğ¸ is calculated as follows: <lb/>ğ‘€ğ‘†ğ¸ = <lb/>1 <lb/>ğ‘ <lb/>âˆ‘ (ğ‘¦ ğ‘– -ğ‘¦ Ì‚ğ‘–) 2 <lb/>ğ‘ <lb/>ğ‘–=1 <lb/>(4) <lb/>where ğ‘¦ ğ‘– is true value, and ğ‘¦ Ì‚ğ‘– is the predicted value. <lb/>2.6. K-Means Clustering Approach for Stratification <lb/>The stratification process is done to ensure the training and testing sets have an equivalent proportion of expenditure <lb/>groups. There is no such expenditure group inside the dataset; hence, clustering groups are created before performing <lb/>stratification. K-means clustering is chosen to discover the clusters from these households that best represent the <lb/>distribution. The K-means algorithm is an unsupervised learning method that iteratively assigns each of the observations <lb/>to one of the clusters. The iteration stops when no further changes are found. The goal of K-means is to minimize the <lb/>sum of Sum of Squared Error (ğ‘†ğ‘†ğ¸) between the data points inside the clusters. The formula is shown below: <lb/>ğ‘†ğ‘†ğ¸ = âˆ‘ âˆ‘ <lb/>ğ‘‘ğ‘–ğ‘ ğ‘¡(ğ‘œ, ğ‘ğ‘’ğ‘› ğ‘– ) 2 <lb/>ğ‘œâˆˆğº ğ‘– <lb/>ğ‘˜ <lb/>ğ‘–=1 <lb/>(5) <lb/>where ğ‘˜ denoted the number of clusters, ğ‘œ 1 , â€¦ , ğ‘œ ğ‘› denoted the data, ğº 1 , â€¦ , ğº ğ‘˜ is the list of clusters, ğ‘ğ‘’ğ‘› 1 , â€¦ , ğ‘ğ‘’ğ‘› ğ‘˜ is the <lb/>list of centroids from each cluster. <lb/>If there is no fixed number of ğ‘˜ (cluster), the elbow method can help to determine the ideal ğ‘˜ value. It works by <lb/>looping through different values of ğ‘˜, then compute and plot the average ğ‘†ğ‘†ğ¸ for corresponding ğ‘˜. The best ğ‘˜ value is <lb/>found at the elbow of the plot, and the decreasing effect of averaging ğ‘†ğ‘†ğ¸ afterward is minor. <lb/>Silhouette is another way to find out the optimal ğ‘˜. In this method, silhouette score is computed to measure how <lb/>closer an observation is within-cluster (cohesion) as compared to the neighbour clusters (separation). Silhouette score <lb/>has a range of [-1 to 1], the closer the value to 1, the tightly the observation is to the centroid, 0 means that the observation <lb/>is on a boundary that could be assigned to any two neighbouring clusters. -1 means observation assigned to a wrong <lb/>cluster. Formula below shows the silhouette score, ğ‘  for a single observation, ğ‘–. <lb/>ğ‘ (ğ‘–) = <lb/>ğ‘(ğ‘–)-ğ‘(ğ‘–) <lb/>ğ‘šğ‘ğ‘¥{ğ‘(ğ‘–),ğ‘(ğ‘–)} <lb/>(6) <lb/>where ğ‘(ğ‘–) is the average distance between observation ğ‘– and all the other observations within the same cluster, ğ‘(ğ‘–) is <lb/>the average distance from observation ğ‘– to all the other clusters. The average silhouette score is then taken from all <lb/>observations and repeated for all value of ğ‘˜ to determine which number of ğ‘˜ produce the highest score. <lb/>Though the primary goal of this research is to predict poverty in terms of consumption expenditure, analysing the <lb/>results from k-means clustering will complement our findings by explaining the strength of determinants through a <lb/>supervised regression approach. To achieve this, descriptive statistics are carried out to summarise the data from clusters, <lb/>assess the similarity of the variables within the clusters, and identify any obvious differences between clusters. <lb/>2.7. Shapley and Owen Values <lb/>Shapley value is a game theory introduced by Lloyd Shapley. The idea is to fairly distribute the total gain to players <lb/>of a game from the total contribution by them. In the regression field, ğ‘… 2 measure the overall goodness of fit. However, <lb/>being able to decompose the overall ğ‘… 2 into individual ğ‘… ğ‘– <lb/>2 &apos;s represented by a single determinant is also desirable. To <lb/>achieve this, the Shapley value is needed. It is represented by the partial, ğ‘… ğ‘– <lb/>2 which is contributed by determinant ğ‘¥ ğ‘– , and <lb/>is given by following formula: <lb/>ğ‘… ğ‘– <lb/>2 = âˆ‘ <lb/>ğ‘˜!(ğ‘-1-ğ‘˜)! <lb/>ğ‘! <lb/>ğ‘‡âŠ†{ğ‘¥ 1 ,â€¦,ğ‘¥ ğ‘ }\{ğ‘¥ ğ‘– } <lb/>[ğ‘… 2 (ğ‘‡ âˆª {ğ‘¥ ğ‘– }) -ğ‘… 2 (ğ‘‡)] <lb/>(7) <lb/>where ğ‘‡ is a model trained with ğ‘˜ determinants but without determinant ğ‘¥ ğ‘– . ğ‘‡ âˆª {ğ‘¥ ğ‘– } representing model with all <lb/>determinants (including ğ‘¥ ğ‘– ). ğ‘ represent the number of determinants and ğ‘˜ represent the subset of determinants used. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>496 <lb/></page>

			<body>The Shapley value will be used to assess the determinants&apos; contribution toward household expenditure in term of ğ‘… ğ‘– <lb/>2 . <lb/>Summing up all the Shapley value is equivalent to the total explained variance, ğ‘… 2 . <lb/>The dummy variables will be examined further using the Owen value, which is an extension of the Shapley value. <lb/>The method considers a set of determinants as a coalition structure and calculate the coalitional value of those <lb/>determinants. Its concept is closely aligned with Shapley value. For the linear model&apos;s determinants, Shapley value will <lb/>aid in estimating the partial ğ‘… 2 for the linear model&apos;s determinants and ranking them based on their significant and <lb/>contribution to the model. <lb/>2.8. SHAP <lb/>SHAP is an approach to explain the model&apos;s predictions by interpreting the features&apos; contribution based on Shapley <lb/>value. Lundberg &amp; Lee (2017) [17] published the method, which has helped a lot of researchers discover the black box <lb/>properties behind machine learning models. The benefits of SHAP are its global interpretability over the machine <lb/>learning models through various plot analysis. The global explanation (which refers to several samples) is usually plotted <lb/>with a bee swarm plot, commonly known as a summary plot in SHAP. Every dot inside the summary plot represents a <lb/>Shapley value associated with a feature, and the colour represents the feature value. Besides that, the SHAP summary <lb/>plot will rank the features according to their contribution. The SHAP dependence plot, a scatter plot that shows how <lb/>various features influence the model&apos;s predictions, is another visualisation tool in our study. In this work, we employ <lb/>SHAP to investigate the relationships between determinants and dependent variables, using both the dependence plot <lb/>and summary plot for detailed insights. <lb/>3. Result and Discussion <lb/>3.1. Overview <lb/>In this section, we present our results and analysis from Sections 3.2 to 3.8. Subsequently, in Section 3.9, we discuss <lb/>the findings by comparing between the OLS and Random Forest models used in this study. Additionally, we contrast <lb/>these results with those from other studies. Following this comparison, we discuss the implications of our findings for <lb/>existing literature and policy-making. <lb/>3.2. Pre-Processing for Modelling <lb/>As explained in Section 1, the dependent variable is household expenditure (Total_Exp_01_12) instead of income, <lb/>due to a better reflection of the overall living standard of households. It is worth mentioning here that household <lb/>expenditure is recorded for discretionary items and services, yet it does not encompass any investment allocations. The <lb/>independent variables considered in this study are household size (Saiz_HH), educational level (Highest_Certificate), <lb/>household income (Total_Inc), strata (Strata), ethnicity (Ethnic), region (Region). Total income is the monthly gross <lb/>household income. <lb/>The dummy variables are created for ethnicity to facilitate regression analysis. The educational level is a ranking <lb/>variable, which consists of six categorical values. Household size consists of five categorical values, ranging from 1 to <lb/>5. A household size of 5 also captures households with more than 5 members. Outliers of household expenditure are <lb/>removed by removing the top 5% of the household expenditure distribution. Meanwhile, those households with <lb/>household expenditures greater than their income were discarded. Following these changes, the dataset now contains <lb/>14,525 households, indicating a reduction of 1,829 households from the original dataset. In this study, we focus on per <lb/>capita income, which is sourced from total household income, and expenditure, which is derived from total household <lb/>expenditure. The Oxford Scale (also known as the OECD Equivalence Scale) is used to calculate the average income <lb/>and expenditure for each household member. Instead of simply dividing income and expenditure by household size (the <lb/>divisor), the Oxford Scale adjusts the divisor according to the following rule: <lb/>â€¢ The first adult receives 1 point. <lb/>â€¢ Each subsequent adult is assigned 0.7 points. <lb/>â€¢ 0.5 points are given to each child. <lb/>Using the Oxford Scale as a divisor to divide household income and expenditure, the per capita income and <lb/>expenditure are then calculated. Later, the experiment is continued by taking the natural logarithm form of per capita <lb/>income and expenditure. The use of natural logarithms ensures that the income and expenditure distributions are more <lb/>symmetrical, and it eases the building of regression models. Tables 3 and 4 display all the descriptive statistics for the <lb/>variables used in this study. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>497 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 3. Descriptive statistics <lb/>Variable <lb/>Mean <lb/>Std Dev. <lb/>Total_Exp_01_12 <lb/>3749.03 <lb/>1844.23 <lb/>Per_Capita_Exp <lb/>1498.32 <lb/>860.39 <lb/>Log_Exp <lb/>7.17 <lb/>0.54 <lb/>Total_Inc <lb/>6428.27 <lb/>4083.59 <lb/>Per_Capita_Inc <lb/>2558.87 <lb/>1829.71 <lb/>Log_Inc <lb/>7.64 <lb/>0.63 <lb/>Age <lb/>47.01 <lb/>13.76 <lb/>Saiz_HH <lb/>3.54 <lb/>1.34 <lb/>Highest_Certificate <lb/>3.12 <lb/>1.60 <lb/>Table 4. Descriptive statistics for categorical variable <lb/>Variable <lb/>Number of Observations, N <lb/>Sex <lb/>Male <lb/>Female <lb/>11895 <lb/>2630 <lb/>Strata <lb/>Urban <lb/>Rural <lb/>10872 <lb/>3653 <lb/>Region <lb/>Centre <lb/>East <lb/>North <lb/>South <lb/>East Malaysia <lb/>2222 <lb/>2351 <lb/>3400 <lb/>2197 <lb/>4355 <lb/>Ethnicity <lb/>Bumiputera <lb/>Chinese <lb/>Indian <lb/>Others <lb/>9741 <lb/>3290 <lb/>884 <lb/>610 <lb/>3.3. Cluster Analysis <lb/>This experiment set ğ‘˜=5, meaning that there will be 5 clusters used to perform clustering. The optimal ğ‘˜ is found by <lb/>looking at the elbow, as shown in the scatter plot in Figure 2. <lb/>To strengthen the assumption that ğ‘˜=5 is the best value, silhouette analysis is performed. The experiments are <lb/>repeated 7 times, for ğ‘˜ value in the range of 2 to 8. For each iteration, average silhouette score is computed. The best <lb/>silhouette score obtained is at ğ‘˜=5, where the score is 0.4951. Figure 3 shows the silhouette plot when ğ‘˜=5. It can be <lb/>noticed that from all the clusters, their silhouette scores exceed the average silhouette score (denoted by the vertical <lb/>dotted line). Besides that, all observations in each cluster have no negative value. <lb/>Table 5 presents the clustering results, which highlight socioeconomic factors across clusters. Cluster 3 represents <lb/>the rural cluster because it includes all rural homes, whereas Clusters 1, 2, and 4 represent the urban cluster, with fewer <lb/>than 10% of each cluster comprising rural households. Cluster 5 is a mixed cluster, with the majority (68.85%) hailing <lb/>from cities. Clusters 3 and 5 are more likely to be multidimensionally poor because they have the lowest means for total <lb/>income, total expenditure, per capita income, and per capita expenditure than any of the other clusters. Secondly, these <lb/>two clusters exhibit the highest percentage of household heads without an educational certificate (32.54% from cluster <lb/>3 and 49.67% from cluster 5) and the lowest rates (7.25% from cluster 3 and 5.57% from cluster 5) of household heads <lb/>with Degree/Advance Diploma certificate. It is noticeable that Cluster 3 has the most households with five or more <lb/>members, accounting for 40.74% of all households, while Cluster 5 has 31.8% in this category. Clusters 3 and 5 are <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>498 <lb/></page>

			<body>categorised as two distinct groups according to the k-means approach, although both clusters are multidimensionally <lb/>poor. The difference is that Cluster 3 represents rural poor households, while Cluster 5 represents mostly urban poor <lb/>households. Cluster 5 has closely similar household income and expenditure to Cluster 3, implying that the urban poor <lb/>is a more serious problem as urban households should have higher incomes and spend more to achieve a similar quality <lb/>of life. Thus, they typically lack adequate housing, facilities, and basic services due to the higher prices of these <lb/>necessities in an urban setting. <lb/>Figure 2. The Elbow Method <lb/>Figure 3. The Silhouette Plot <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>499 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 5. K-means clustering result <lb/>Description <lb/>Cluster <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>mean of Total_Inc <lb/>6778.89 <lb/>7396.75 <lb/>4913.98 <lb/>6709.67 <lb/>4742.70 <lb/>median of Total_Inc <lb/>5840.08 <lb/>6408.83 <lb/>3896.58 <lb/>5579.10 <lb/>3683.75 <lb/>mean of Per_Capita_Inc <lb/>2551.42 <lb/>3314.23 <lb/>1862.86 <lb/>2693.04 <lb/>1933.38 <lb/>median of Per_Capita_Inc <lb/>2123.67 <lb/>2769.96 <lb/>1476.63 <lb/>2164.70 <lb/>1583.11 <lb/>mean of Total_Exp_01_12 <lb/>3891.41 <lb/>4371.72 <lb/>2935.15 <lb/>3945.72 <lb/>2726.01 <lb/>median of Total_Exp_01_12 <lb/>3550.02 <lb/>4072.31 <lb/>2605.55 <lb/>3575.53 <lb/>2291.90 <lb/>mean of Per_Capita_Exp <lb/>1467.02 <lb/>1970.59 <lb/>1116.33 <lb/>1576.90 <lb/>1131.86 <lb/>median of Per_Capita_Exp <lb/>1297.22 <lb/>1768.30 <lb/>961.71 <lb/>1360.36 <lb/>930.56 <lb/>mean of Age <lb/>45 <lb/>51 <lb/>49 <lb/>47 <lb/>41 <lb/>median of Age <lb/>43 <lb/>50 <lb/>49 <lb/>46 <lb/>40 <lb/>Highest_Certificate <lb/>No Certificate <lb/>11.26% <lb/>21.34% <lb/>32.54% <lb/>19.80% <lb/>49.67% <lb/>PMR/SRP <lb/>9.44% <lb/>14.26% <lb/>14.29% <lb/>17.53% <lb/>10.82% <lb/>SPM/ SPMV <lb/>45.11% <lb/>37.02% <lb/>35.33% <lb/>37.10% <lb/>25.74% <lb/>STPM <lb/>3.29% <lb/>2.25% <lb/>2.98% <lb/>1.81% <lb/>2.79% <lb/>Diploma / certificate <lb/>16.88% <lb/>11.85% <lb/>7.59% <lb/>12.67% <lb/>5.41% <lb/>Degree/Advance Diploma <lb/>14.02% <lb/>13.28% <lb/>7.27% <lb/>11.09% <lb/>5.57% <lb/>Saiz_HH <lb/>1 <lb/>6.19% <lb/>11.61% <lb/>9.10% <lb/>7.35% <lb/>10.49% <lb/>2 <lb/>14.29% <lb/>26.78% <lb/>16.08% <lb/>19.12% <lb/>20.00% <lb/>3 <lb/>18.87% <lb/>22.71% <lb/>17.49% <lb/>20.59% <lb/>19.18% <lb/>4 <lb/>21.53% <lb/>19.60% <lb/>16.59% <lb/>22.29% <lb/>18.52% <lb/>5 <lb/>39.11% <lb/>19.30% <lb/>40.74% <lb/>30.66% <lb/>31.80% <lb/>Strata <lb/>Rural <lb/>0% <lb/>8.60% <lb/>100% <lb/>6.56% <lb/>31.15% <lb/>Urban <lb/>100% <lb/>91.40% <lb/>0% <lb/>93.44% <lb/>68.85% <lb/>Number of Observations <lb/>6619 <lb/>3290 <lb/>3122 <lb/>884 <lb/>610 <lb/>3.4. OLS Regression Analysis -Econometric Model <lb/>Table 6 presents the regression result using natural logarithm form of per capita expenditure (the dependent variable) <lb/>and per capita income (the determinant/independent variables). The left side of the table shows the determinants, the <lb/>intercept (constant), and the ğ‘… 2 ,while the right side shows the unstandardized coefficients. Asterisks denote the statistical <lb/>significance of variables. The t-test utilises the p-value to test whether an independent variable have a significant <lb/>relationship with the dependent variable. As an example, using a significance level of 0.05, hypothesis testing can be <lb/>carried out to determine whether household size is a significant determinant in explaining log per capita expenditure: <lb/>â€¢ H0: Household size has no effect over log per capita expenditure. <lb/>â€¢ H1: Household size has significant effect over log per capita expenditure. <lb/>Based on the result from Table 6, the p-value of household size (Saiz_HH) is âˆ¼0, which means the null hypothesis <lb/>is rejected. In other words, at the 5 percent significance level, household size has a significant effect on log per capita <lb/>expenditure. Similarly, the hypotheses for all the determinants&apos; relationships to the dependent variable are tested through <lb/>the regression model. It is found that all determinants have a significant relationship with log per capita expenditure at <lb/>the 1% level of significance except the variables Age and Sex (Table 6 presents the regression result after removing <lb/>these two variables). Income, educational level, strata, ethnic groups, and regions are found to have positive relationships <lb/>with the dependent variable. Household size is the only variable found to have a negative impact on the log per capita <lb/>expenditure. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>500 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 6. Regression result for linear regression (log per capita expenditure) <lb/>Variable <lb/>Coefficient <lb/>Log_Inc (Log Per Capita Income) <lb/>0.6614 *** <lb/>Highest_Certificate (Educational level) <lb/>0.0186 *** <lb/>Saiz_HH (Household Size) <lb/>-0.0598 *** <lb/>Strata (rural reference) <lb/>0.0292 *** <lb/>Bumiputera <lb/>0.3786 *** <lb/>Chinese <lb/>0.4766 *** <lb/>Indian <lb/>0.3871 *** <lb/>Others Ethnicities <lb/>0.3085 *** <lb/>Centre Peninsular <lb/>0.3642 *** <lb/>East Peninsular <lb/>0.3267 *** <lb/>Eastern Malaysia <lb/>0.2297 *** <lb/>North Peninsular <lb/>0.2545 *** <lb/>South Peninsular <lb/>0.3757 *** <lb/>Constant <lb/>1.5403 *** <lb/>R-squared, ğ‘… 2 <lb/>0.855 *** <lb/>Notes: *** indicate p-value &lt;0.01, ** indicate p-value &lt;0.05, * indicate p-value &lt;0.1 <lb/>3.5. Shapley Decomposition <lb/>The partial ğ‘… 2 of the significant variables in the model of Table 7 are calculated by computing the Shapley value. <lb/>Here, the Owen value is also the Shapley value or partial ğ‘… 2 . Panel (b) shows the general contribution from each Owen <lb/>group and panel (a) shows the details of each determinant. Looking at panel (b), total income alone contributes 54.39% <lb/>of ğ‘… 2 . Household size is the second highest, with 9.55% of ğ‘… 2 , follow by educational level, with 8.72% of ğ‘… 2 . The rest <lb/>of the determinants have very minimum impact on the prediction. Noted that Shapley values will only find out the <lb/>contribution of determinants, it does not point out the relationships between dependent variable and determinants. <lb/>Table 7. Shapley and Owen Value of Determinants <lb/>Variable <lb/>Owen Group <lb/>Owen values/Partial ğ‘… 2 <lb/>(a) <lb/>Log Inc (Log Per Capita Income) <lb/>B1 <lb/>0.5439 <lb/>Highest Certificate (Educational level) <lb/>B2 <lb/>0.0872 <lb/>Saiz HH (Household Size) <lb/>B3 <lb/>0.0955 <lb/>Strata (rural reference) <lb/>B4 <lb/>0.0229 <lb/>Bumiputera <lb/>B5 <lb/>0.0135 <lb/>Chinese <lb/>B5 <lb/>0.0224 <lb/>Indian <lb/>B5 <lb/>0.0014 <lb/>Other Ethnicities <lb/>B5 <lb/>0.0063 <lb/>Centre Peninsular <lb/>B6 <lb/>0.0214 <lb/>East Peninsular <lb/>B6 <lb/>0.0045 <lb/>Eastern Malaysia <lb/>B6 <lb/>0.0172 <lb/>North Peninsular <lb/>B6 <lb/>0.0035 <lb/>South Peninsular <lb/>B6 <lb/>0.0084 <lb/>(b) <lb/>Log Inc (Log Per Capita Income) <lb/>B1 <lb/>0.5439 <lb/>Highest Certificate (Educational level) <lb/>B2 <lb/>0.0872 <lb/>Saiz HH (Household Size) <lb/>B3 <lb/>0.0955 <lb/>Strata (rural reference) <lb/>B4 <lb/>0.0229 <lb/>Ethnics <lb/>B5 <lb/>0.0436 <lb/>Region <lb/>B6 <lb/>0.0550 <lb/>ğ‘… 2 <lb/>0.848 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>501 <lb/></page>

			<body>3.6. Machine Learning -Random Forest <lb/>Random Forest comes with various hypermeters that can be set before the experiment. A good combination of <lb/>hyperparameters often performs well in predicting. However, it is inefficient to attempt every possible combination <lb/>manually. To deal with it, Random search function (RandomizedSearchCV from the Scikit-Learn API) is used to find <lb/>the best hyperparameters. Inside the function, 5-fold cross-validation is performed too to ensure a less biased model is <lb/>produced at the end. The final hyperparameters used are: <lb/>â€¢ Number of estimators/trees: 750 <lb/>â€¢ Maximum depth=10 <lb/>â€¢ Minimum number of samples in a leaf =4 <lb/>â€¢ Minimum number of samples required to split =20 <lb/>3.7. SHAP Analysis <lb/>Once the model has been trained, the testing set is then used to evaluate the model&apos;s performance and used in SHAP <lb/>analysis to calculate the Shapley value. These SHAP values are used to create plots such as summary plot, dependence <lb/>plot, and force plot. Figure 4 shows the SHAP summary plot. The x-axis typically represents the predictor&apos;s SHAP <lb/>values. The corresponding SHAP values for that specific feature determinant are represented on the y-axis. Note that the <lb/>SHAP value here refers to the dependent variable; they are having the same scale. The importance of feature determinants <lb/>can be seen by looking at the y-axis of the SHAP summary plot. Log per capita income, household size, educational <lb/>level, and age are variables of interest, which are discussed in Section 3.9. <lb/>Figure 4. SHAP Summary Plot for Random Forest <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>502 <lb/></page>

			<body>The direction of the colour shift can be used to determine the relationship. For example, the colour blue on the left <lb/>side of the log per capita income changes to red as it moves to the right, indicating a positive association. A positive <lb/>relationship is found between educational level and log per capita expenditure. This is applicable to log per capita income <lb/>too. Log per capita expenditure has a negative relationship with household size, as the colour changes from red to blue <lb/>from left to right side. No clear relationship exists between log per capita expenditure and age, as denoted by the mixture <lb/>of red and blue colours. <lb/>Figure 5, on the other hand, displays some significant 3-dimensional SHAP dependence plots for a few chosen <lb/>determinants. By examining the trends, this plot can be used to analyse the relationship between determinants, including <lb/>nonlinear relationships. Age, household size, and log per capita expenditure appear to have a nonlinear relationship in <lb/>Figures 5a) and d), while Figures 5b) and c) show linear associations. The interacting or third feature value is often <lb/>represented by colour in SHAP dependency plots. <lb/>Figure 5. SHAP Dependence Plots <lb/>3.8. Models Evaluation <lb/>The ğ‘… 2 and MSE values for two prediction models are presented in Table 8 for OLS (Model 1) and Random Forest <lb/>(Model 2), with the testing set serving as the evaluation. Model 2: Random Forest are found to have the highest ğ‘… 2 and <lb/>lowest MSE scores, slightly better than the OLS model. Both models have very high ğ‘… 2 and MSE scores, which means <lb/>that they explain the variation very well, and do not have an overfitting problem. <lb/>Table 8. Models Evaluation <lb/>Model <lb/>Model 1: OLS <lb/>Model 2: Random Forest <lb/>ğ‘… 2 <lb/>0.847 <lb/>0.848 <lb/>MSE <lb/>0.0454 <lb/>0.0453 <lb/>3.9. Discussion of Findings <lb/>We begin to discuss the variables&apos; importance to the expenditure (Log_Exp) first. Table 9 shows the comparison of <lb/>variables&apos; ranks for OLS and Random Forest regression. Overall, the determinants&apos; top two rankings are similar. Income <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>503 <lb/></page>

			<body>(Log_Inc) and household size (Size_HH) are ranked as the two most powerful predictors for both models. In both models, <lb/>income is ranked as the most important determinant because expenditure is generally correlated with income. Household <lb/>size is ranked second in both models, as we measure household expenditure in per capita form, so an increase in a single <lb/>household unit can significantly reduce per capita expenditure. OLS treats educational level (Highest_Certificate) as 3 rd <lb/>important variable, but it is only the 6 th important variable in Random Forest, which unexpectedly has a lower rank than <lb/>the regional variables but is still an influential factor. To this extent, both models&apos; results are consistent with Ayyash &amp; <lb/>Sek&apos;s (2020) [16] finding, which stated that educational level and household size are the most important contributing <lb/>factors toward household expenditure. Meanwhile, both models also agree that whether the household is a Chinese <lb/>family can greatly determine one&apos;s expenditure power. As implied by the positive relationships in Table 6 (OLS) and <lb/>Figure 5 (Random Forest), Chinese household heads generally have higher expenditures due to their higher income. This <lb/>aligned with the statistics reported by DOSM Malaysia [18]. <lb/>In terms of differences, in the OLS model, the top 6 variables selected are Log_Inc (log per capita income), Saiz_HH <lb/>(Household size), Highest_Certificate (educational level), Strata, Chinese (Ethnics), Centre Peninsular (Region). All <lb/>these variables come from different dimensions, e.g., income is an indicator of household economic status, and Chinese <lb/>is an indicator of ethnicity. Moreover, all determinants except household size have positive relationships with log per <lb/>capita expenditure. On the other hand, the Random Forest model ranks the East Malaysia region as the third most-<lb/>important variable, while the North Peninsular (the Northern Region) is in 5 th place. This may be because most of the <lb/>states in these regions had lower mean monthly household consumption expenditures compared to the other regions, as <lb/>reported in 2019 [18]. Thus, the model ranked them as significant variables in reducing the log per capital expenditure. <lb/>The 6 th variable is Highest_Certificate, which unexpectedly has a lower rank than the regional variable but is still an <lb/>influential factor. From here, we can conclude that the Random Forest model focused more on regional variables. <lb/>Another interesting finding is that the 2 nd , 3 rd , 5 th determinants have negative effects on log per capita expenditure. This <lb/>also suggests that the trained Random Forest model focused more on determinants that have a decreasing effect toward <lb/>the expected log per capita expenditure value, as calculated by the SHAP model. <lb/>Next, we investigate the relationships between age, educational level, income, household size, and expenditure <lb/>(Figure 5). Firstly, OLS found that age is statistically insignificant. Unlike the Random Forest model in Figure 5a, it <lb/>shows that as age increases, the log per capita expenditure also increases. This is only true until age around 40, when, at <lb/>this point, the log per capita expenditure starts to decrease until age around 60. This is believed to be the reason that the <lb/>age determinant did not pass the significant test in the proposed OLS model, as age appeared in an inverted U-shaped <lb/>when considering its influence toward expenditure. Chowdhury et al. (2023) [12] present similar findings too, with <lb/>younger individuals tending to have a higher income and spend more, while older individuals are inclined to accumulate <lb/>their wealth. However, this result contrasts with the previous findings, where expenditure has a purely positive linear <lb/>relationship with age [15, 16]. Our Random Forest suggests this is the complex and nonlinear relationships that are <lb/>unable to be captured by such linear model from the OLS model in this study and other studies [15, 16]. Relating to real-<lb/>life situations, such an upward and downward trend is reasonable too, as young workers tend to be paid a higher salary <lb/>and are more willing to spend more than older workers. Thus, this study suggests that age forms a nonlinear relationship <lb/>with expenditure. As we further explore the Figure 5a), by treating the educational level as interaction feature, from age <lb/>18 to 60, most of the observations here have a higher average educational level as compared to those after age 60 (denoted <lb/>by colour in the Figure 5a. Age 60 is the retirement age in Malaysia, so we could say that observations below age 60 <lb/>mostly work in the formal sector, whereas observations above age 60 may be those self-employed workers in the informal <lb/>sector of the economy who generally have lower education levels, as denoted by the blue colour. <lb/>Secondly, the relationship between expenditure and educational level is depicted by the coefficient (0.0186) in Table <lb/>3 (OLS) and the trend in Figure 5b (Random Forest). It is possible to characterise this positive relationship as nearly <lb/>linear, but not entirely so. Comparing the educational levels of 5 and 6, their implications for expenditure are similar. In <lb/>other words, the spending habits of household heads who possess diplomas, degrees, or advanced diplomas are generally <lb/>comparable. This close linear relationship corresponds to the previously built clustering model (refer to Table 5). Clusters <lb/>1, 2, and 4 exhibit higher average expenditure and educational level, whereas clusters 3 and 5 have lower average <lb/>expenditure and educational level. Furthermore, Ayyash &amp; Sek (2020) [16] also noted that households with better <lb/>education ought to possess greater expenditure power. In Figure 5b, too, with age serving as an interaction feature, most <lb/>of the observations at educational levels 1 and 2 have a higher average age (mostly red). As educational level increases, <lb/>the average age observed is lower (mostly blue). We discussed the reason for this in the previous paragraph. <lb/>Thirdly, regarding how income affects expenditure, both OLS (see Table 6, coefficient of 0.6614) and Random Forest <lb/>(see Figure 5b) models agree that a positive linear relationship best represents the relationship between log per capita <lb/>expenditure and log per capita income. This is not surprising since, theoretically, income and expenditure are highly <lb/>correlated. As observed in Figure 5c, with educational level serving as an interaction feature, these variables are found <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>504 <lb/></page>

			<body>to have perfect positive correlations; the greater any one of their values, the higher the values of the other two variables. <lb/>Some observations that have a higher educational level (purple dots) but low log per capita expenditure and income (as <lb/>shown in Figure 5a) can be explained by individuals who are young workers or are nearing retirement. <lb/>Lastly, investigating the coefficient of household size (-0.0598) in Table 6 and the trend in Figure 5d shows a negative <lb/>relationship. Again, consistent with Ayyash &amp; Sek (2020) [16], the larger the household size, the lower the per capita <lb/>expenditure of the household head. This is not a perfect linear trend. Further analysis by integrating income as an <lb/>interacting variable into household size yields more interesting patterns. If the household size is a single individual <lb/>household, log per capita expenditure increases in tandem with log per capita income. In households with two members, <lb/>there is no clear relationship. When household size is greater than three members, the higher the log per capita income, <lb/>the lower the log per capita expenditure. This is clearly another complex relationship. The possible reason for this <lb/>phenomenon is that these households prefer saving and investing rather than spending on discretionary items. Also, they <lb/>may have financial goals such as saving for retirement, investing in their children&apos;s education, or building a nest egg for <lb/>unexpected expenses required by household members. <lb/>On the other hand, it is crucial to point out that the expenditure pattern of those households with lower income and a <lb/>household size larger than or equal to three members makes them vulnerable to being multidimensionally poor. <lb/>Measuring in the absolute sense, we can take an example to explain this situation by comparing two household heads, A <lb/>(with RM1000 per capita income) and B (with RM1500 per capita income). Household head A normally spends most of <lb/>his/her income (say, RM800), and thus their saving per month (RM200) is far less than household head B, who spends <lb/>part of his/her income (said RM600), and thus their saving per month is RM900. This overspending behaviour may come <lb/>from conspicuous consumption due to low levels of human capital (in our case, educational level) typically found <lb/>amongst those living in poverty [19]. This requires further analysis of the types of goods and services purchased, which <lb/>is not covered in this study. One may wonder the accuracy of the example given because both the per capita income and <lb/>expenditure in Figure 5d are in log form, but the log-based income and expenditure can be easily converted back by <lb/>using the exponential function. Thus, our finding suggests that households that comprise three or more members with <lb/>lower incomes but typically have higher expenditures require attention from policymakers. <lb/>At a glance, this study utilises both linear (OLS) and nonlinear (Random Forest) to demonstrate the relationships <lb/>between socioeconomic factors and household consumption expenditure. Relying on a nonlinear random forest model <lb/>allows the model to process complex relationships that exist in some determinants, achieving a more accurate and <lb/>promising result. Moreover, the SHAP analysis lends a helping hand for us to visualize the trend inside a graph up to 3 <lb/>dimensions, conveying our findings in a simple yet convincing manner to policymakers. To the best of our knowledge, <lb/>this is the first study attempt to use the Machine Learning model followed by a SHAP model in analysing the <lb/>socioeconomic variables that contribute to household consumption expenditure. <lb/>The findings of this study significantly contribute to the understanding of microeconomic dynamics within Malaysia&apos;s <lb/>socio-economic landscape, offering insights into the current policy-making decision. Firstly, the observed positive linear <lb/>relationship between income, expenditure, and educational level emphasises the importance of investing in education to <lb/>boost economic growth and promote individual and household well-being. Secondly, the nonlinear relationship between <lb/>age and expenditure highlights the need for targeted policies to address the spending habits of different age groups, <lb/>particularly those above the age of 40 who may require specific support in managing their finances. Last but most <lb/>importantly, the complex relationship between household size, income, and expenditure required caution and strategic <lb/>policy-making. <lb/>It is essential to assist those households that comprise three or more members with lower incomes but typically have <lb/>higher expenditures, particularly those with children or infants. Possible interventions can be done, including some non-<lb/>cash interventions such as housing subsidies, utility bill assistance, and free health insurance. We strongly suggest the <lb/>continuation of current running policies such as the RM40 Electric Rebate Programme (utility subsidy), mySalam (free <lb/>health insurance), and Back-to-School Aid (cash for children in primary and secondary school), primarily targeting the <lb/>group described above. It is advisable to exercise caution when it comes to maintaining direct cash subsidy programmes <lb/>like i-SINAR and Bantuan Sara Hidup (BSH), given the intricate expenditure patterns observed in the aforementioned <lb/>group. While direct cash transfers can provide immediate financial relief, there is a risk that households may channel <lb/>them for immediate consumption instead of wealth accumulation through long-term saving and investment schemes, as <lb/>Moav &amp; Neeman (2012) [19] have stressed. Ensuring equal access to educational resources to improve human capital is <lb/>one of the approaches to increasing their saving rate. Last but not least, our OLS ranking and clustering results, presented <lb/>in Tables 5 and 9, also suggest the aid should be focused on urban households that exhibit identical characteristic patterns <lb/>to those found in Cluster 3. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>505 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 9. Variables&apos; Ranks for OLS and Random Forest Regressions <lb/>Rank <lb/>OLS <lb/>Random Forest <lb/>1. <lb/>Log_Inc (Log per capita income) <lb/>Log_Inc (Log per capita income) <lb/>2. <lb/>Saiz_HH (Household size) <lb/>Saiz_HH (Household size) <lb/>3. <lb/>Highest_Certificate (educational level) <lb/>Region (East Malaysia) <lb/>4. <lb/>Strata (Urban ref.) <lb/>Chinese (Ethnics) <lb/>5. <lb/>Chinese (Ethnics) <lb/>Region (North) <lb/>6. <lb/>Region (Central Peninsular) <lb/>Highest_Certificate (educational level) <lb/>7. <lb/>Bumiputera (Ethnics) <lb/>Region (South) <lb/>8. <lb/>Region (South Peninsular) <lb/>Age <lb/>9. <lb/>Other (Ethnic) <lb/>Strata (Urban ref.) <lb/>10. <lb/>Region (North Peninsular) <lb/>Bumiputera (Ethnics) <lb/>11. <lb/>Region (East Malaysia) <lb/>Region (Centre) <lb/>Region (East Peninsular) <lb/>Other (Ethnic) <lb/>13. <lb/>Ethnic (Indian) <lb/>Region (East) <lb/>14. <lb/>Sex <lb/>15. <lb/>Ethnic (Indian) <lb/>4. Conclusion <lb/>This research focuses on household expenditure patterns in Malaysia, using 14,525 households from two dataset <lb/>records: households and members. To estimate the relationship between the log of per capita expenditure and its various <lb/>determinants, this study uses both a linear approach (via Ordinary Least Squares, or OLS) and a nonlinear approach (via <lb/>Random Forest). In the socioeconomic field, recent studies have proved the robustness of machine learning in terms of <lb/>its accuracy in predicting and complexity in handling linear and nonlinear data [10-13]. On the other hand, the traditional <lb/>linear econometric model remained a popular choice in most studies due to its simplicity and standard interpretability <lb/>(from coefficients). Considering this situation, we select both OLS and Random Forest models as our solution to examine <lb/>the contribution of socioeconomic factors toward household expenditure by comparing how they treat the relationships <lb/>between these variables. To address the black box problem inside Random Forest, we propose the SHAP model to <lb/>visualise the correlations, providing valuable insights and interesting findings. <lb/>Overall, both models are powerful in predicting the consumption expenditure power of a household head, as they <lb/>explain about 85% proportion of the variance (ğ‘… 2 ) and obtain an MSE score of 0.0045 using both the training and testing <lb/>sets. This also suggests both models generalise well toward unseen household data. Firstly, regarding the determinants&apos; <lb/>importance, both models suggest that income is the most important variable in explaining household expenditure. The <lb/>second one is the household size. The educational level is ranked differently in the two models, with the OLS model <lb/>ranking third and the Random Forest model ranking sixth. Comparing the OLS model from this study and Ayyash &amp; <lb/>Sek&apos;s (2020) [16] study, household size and educational level are two influential factors in explaining per capita <lb/>expenditure. In this study, the OLS model tends to favour a diversity of determinants from different dimensions: income <lb/>(log per capita income), household characteristic (Household Size), educational level (Highest Certificate), geographical <lb/>location (Strata, Region) and ethnicity (Chinese). On the other hand, the Random Forest model ranked regional <lb/>determinants higher in predicting per capita expenditure, which are East Malaysia as well as the North and South <lb/>Peninsular regions. Although both models presented different ranking results, the difference is minor. <lb/>Furthermore, with respect to the relationship estimates gathered from both models, this work highlights that there is <lb/>a positive linear relationship between household head income and educational level and their propensity to spend more, <lb/>exhibiting positive linear relationships. These relationships align with the findings of Ayyash &amp; Sek&apos;s (2020) study [16]. <lb/>However, as shown in Figures 5a and 5d, nonlinear relationships indeed exist. Firstly, the larger the household, the lower <lb/>the household&apos;s per capita expenditure. The contribution of each household size toward per capita expenditure varies <lb/>within a boundary. As soon as we put in the per capita income, the relationship becomes obvious. The most interesting <lb/>finding from Figure 5d is that if a household has three or more members, then the household heads with lower per capita <lb/>incomes will spend more on basic needs and wants than those who have higher per capita incomes. Secondly, the per <lb/>capita expenditure increases initially with the household head&apos;s age and then starts to decline when he/she reaches 40. <lb/>The consumption expenditure subsequently decreases until age 60, which is the retirement age of Malaysia. <lb/>The research findings indicate significant implications for policy-making and interventions aimed at reducing <lb/>disparities in household spending. As presented in Figure 5a, the nonlinear relationship between age and per capita <lb/>expenditure highlights the need for specific targeted policies to address the expenditure patterns of different age groups, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>506 <lb/></page>

            <body>especially for those household heads before and after age 40. Looking at Figure 5d, the current policy should emphasise <lb/>that those households with a size larger than or equal to 3 earn less but spend more. Subsidy assistance such as housing <lb/>subsidies, utility bill assistance, and free health insurance are recommended. Direct cash subsidy programmes running <lb/>right now, such as the Bantuan Sara Hidup (BSH) and i-SINAR, must establish rigorous approval processes to ensure <lb/>the funds are allocated to household heads that are able to maximise their wealth through long-term investments. The <lb/>priority of the assistance programmes should be to benefit urban poor households, followed by rural poor households. <lb/>We contend for policies that seek to increase education levels among household heads and members to achieve higher <lb/>living standards and enhanced well-being for all. In short, strategies that aim to reduce disparity in consumption <lb/>expenditure should consider multiple dimensions of household characteristics. <lb/>This study reveals the possible characteristics of households that are vulnerable to being multidimensionally poor in <lb/>terms of their expenditure pattern, income, age, and household size. However, it also has some limitations. Firstly, this <lb/>study did not further investigate the different expenditure types. Secondly, the log per capita income itself explains more <lb/>than half of the variability of both OLS and Random Forest models, so the influence of the determinants is minimized. <lb/>However, as we focused primarily on decomposing the household consumption and expenditure pattern, including <lb/>income is necessary. Thirdly, a wider variety of machine learning models should be considered to ensure the robustness <lb/>and reliability of the findings. Finally, the findings of the OLS model and the SHAP analysis used to interpret the Random <lb/>Forest model should be viewed as correlational, not as casual inferences. <lb/></body>

            <div type="annex">5. Declarations <lb/></div>

            <div type="contribution">5.1. Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization, T.S.O. and Y.L.; methodology, E.L. and T.S.O.; software, E.L.; validation, T.S.O. and Y.L.; <lb/>formal analysis, E.L. and T.S.O.; investigation, E.L. and T.S.O.; resources, T.S.O. and Y.L.; data curation, E.L. and <lb/>Y.L.; writing-original draft preparation, E.L.; writing-review and editing, T.S.O. and Y.L.; visualization, E.L.; <lb/>supervision, T.S.O. and Y.L.; project administration, T.S.O.; funding acquisition, T.S.O. All authors have read and <lb/>agreed to the published version of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

            <div type="availability">5.2. Data Availability Statement <lb/>The data presented in this study are available in the article. <lb/></div>

            <div type="funding">5.3. Funding <lb/>The work was supported by Telekom Malaysia Research &amp; Development under Grant RDTC/241111 <lb/>(MMUE/240064). <lb/></div>

            <div type="acknowledgement">5.4. Acknowledgements <lb/>The author would like also to thank the Department of Statistics Malaysia (DOSM) for providing the Household <lb/>Expenditure Survey dataset that was essential in conducting this study. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">5.5. Institutional Review Board Statement <lb/>Not applicable. <lb/>5.6. Informed Consent Statement <lb/>Not applicable. <lb/></div>

            <div type="conflict">5.7. Declaration of Competing Interest <lb/>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have <lb/>appeared to influence the work reported in this paper. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>6. References <lb/>[1] Akyelken, N. (2020). Urban conceptions of economic inequalities. Regional Studies, 54(6), 863-872. <lb/>doi:10.1080/00343404.2020.1732902. <lb/>[2] Saari, M. Y., Dietzenbacher, E., &amp; Los, B. (2014). Production interdependencies and poverty reduction across ethnic groups in <lb/>Malaysia. Economic Modelling, 42, 146-158. doi:10.1016/j.econmod.2014.06.008. <lb/>[3] Todaro, M. P., &amp; Smith, S. C. (2020). Economic Development. Pearson Hall, London, United Kingdom. <lb/>[4] Wang, X. (2022). On the Relationship Between Income Poverty and Multidimensional Poverty in China. International Research <lb/>on Poverty Reduction, 85-106. doi:10.1007/978-981-19-1189-7_5. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>507 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[5] UNDP. (2023). Unstacking Global Poverty: Data for high impact action. In Global Multi-dimensional Poverty Index 2023. United <lb/>Nations Development Programme, New York, United States. Available online: https://hdr.undp.org/content/2023-global-<lb/>multidimensional-poverty-index-mpi#/indicies/MPI (accessed on March 2024). <lb/>[6] Abdul Rahman, M., Sani, N. S., Hamdan, R., Ali Othman, Z., &amp; Abu Bakar, A. (2021). A clustering approach to identify <lb/>multidimensional poverty indicators for the bottom 40 percent group. PloS one, 16(8), e0255312. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0255312. <lb/>[7] Rani, M. S. A., Nordin, S. H. B., Chin Ching Lau, Lim, S. heng L., &amp; Siow, Z. S. (2016). Rich Debt, Poor Debt: Assessing <lb/>Household Indebtedness and Debt Repayment Capacity. BNM-BIS Conference on Financial Systems and the Real Economy, 91, <lb/>153-166. <lb/>[8] Bhanoji Rao, V. V. (1981). Measurement of deprivation and poverty based on the proportion spent on food: An exploratory <lb/>exercise. World Development, 9(4), 337-353. doi:10.1016/0305-750X(81)90081-4. <lb/>[9] Kumar, T. K., Mallick, S., &amp; Holla, J. (2009). Estimating consumption deprivation in India using survey data: A state-level rural <lb/>-Urban analysis before and during reform period. Journal of Development Studies, 45(4), 441-470. <lb/>doi:10.1080/00220380802265207. <lb/>[10] Herrera, G. P., Constantino, M., Su, J. J., &amp; Naranpanawa, A. (2023). The use of ICTs and income distribution in Brazil: A <lb/>machine learning explanation using SHAP values. Telecommunications Policy, 47(8), 102598. doi:10.1016/j.telpol.2023.102598. <lb/>[11] Hwang, Y., Lee, Y., &amp; Fabozzi, F. J. (2023). Identifying household finance heterogeneity via deep clustering. Annals of <lb/>Operations Research, 325(2), 1255-1289. doi:10.1007/s10479-022-04900-3. <lb/>[12] Chowdhury, R. A., Ceballos-Sierra, F., &amp; Sulaiman, M. (2023). Grow the pie, or have it? Using machine learning to impact <lb/>heterogeneity <lb/>in <lb/>the <lb/>Ultra-poor <lb/>graduation <lb/>model. <lb/>Journal <lb/>of <lb/>Development <lb/>Effectiveness, <lb/>1-20. <lb/>doi:10.1080/19439342.2023.2276928. <lb/>[13] Zeng, Q., &amp; Chen, X. (2023). Identification of urban-rural integration types in China -an unsupervised machine learning <lb/>approach. China Agricultural Economic Review, 15(2), 400-415. doi:10.1108/CAER-03-2022-0045. <lb/>[14] Ang, W. C., &amp; Cheah, Y. K. (2023). Inequalities in Consumption Expenditure on Pharmaceuticals: Evidence from Malaysia. <lb/>International Journal of Social Determinants of Health and Health Services, 53(4), 528-538. doi:10.1177/27551938231170831. <lb/>[15] Zawiah, W., Zin, W., &amp; Nabilah, S. F. (1998). Malaysian Household Consumption Expenditure: Rural vs Urban. Department of <lb/>Statistics, Malaysia, MyStats 2015 Conference Papers, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia. <lb/>[16] Ayyash, M., &amp; Sek, S. K. (2020). Decomposing inequality in household consumption expenditure in Malaysia. Economies, 8(4), <lb/>83. doi:10.3390/economies8040083. <lb/>[17] Lundberg, S. M., &amp; Lee, S. I. (2017). A unified approach to interpreting model predictions. Advances in Neural Information <lb/>Processing Systems, NIPS 2017, 30. <lb/>[18] DOSM. (2020). Penemuan Utama -The Key Findings. Department of Statistics Malaysia (DOSM), Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia. <lb/>[19] Moav, O., &amp; Neeman, Z. (2012). Saving Rates and Poverty: The Role of Conspicuous Consumption and Human Capital. <lb/>Economic Journal, 122(563), 933-956. doi:10.1111/j.1468-0297.2012.02516.x. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
