<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">Denosumab combined with radiotherapy as an alternative to surgery for advanced metastatic bone lesions and pathologic fractures: a retrospective case study of 38 patients</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Mehdy</forename>
            <surname>Farhang</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Martin</forename>
            <surname>Isaksson</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Johan</forename>
            <surname>Wänman</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Richard</forename>
            <surname>Löfvenberg</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Sead</forename>
            <surname>Crnalic</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-11-04T09:32:05.044125Z">04.11.2025 09:32:05</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.2340$1$1651-226x.2024.40977</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>MJS Publishing, Medical Journals Sweden AB</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.2340/1651-226x.2024.40977</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Mehdy Farhang, Martin Isaksson, Johan Wänman, Richard Löfvenberg, Sead Crnalic. (2024). Denosumab combined with radiotherapy as an alternative to surgery for advanced metastatic bone lesions and pathologic fractures: a retrospective case study of 38 patients. Acta Oncologica, 63(None), 932-938. DOI: 10.2340/1651-226x.2024.40977</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-04T09:32:05.044125Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-11-04T09:32:05.044125Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>ActaDV <lb/>ActaDV <lb/>Advances in dermatology and venereology <lb/>Acta Dermato-Venereologica <lb/>ORIGINAL REPORT <lb/>1/6 <lb/>Published by Medical Journals Sweden, on behalf of the Society for Publication of Acta Dermato-Venereologica. This is an Open Access article distributed <lb/>under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) <lb/>SIGNIFICANCE <lb/>Hidradenitis suppurativa is a chronic inflammatory disease <lb/>of hair follicles, characterized by painful oozing lesions. <lb/>Due to negative stigmatization of the disease, patients with <lb/>hidradenitis suppurativa do not easily seek help from phy-<lb/>sicians. This study examined the prevalence and characte-<lb/>ristics of hidradenitis suppurativa in the Northern Finland <lb/>Birth Cohort 1986 Study (n = 2,775). The study found that <lb/>hidradenitis suppurativa affected 4.0% of the population. <lb/>Only 4 cases of the study population were found to have <lb/>diagnosis of hidradenitis suppurativa, either in hospital or <lb/>in primary healthcare data. Hidradenitis suppurativa was <lb/>associated with severe obesity, female sex, smoking and <lb/>poor overall health status. <lb/>Prevalence and Characteristics of Hidradenitis Suppurativa in the <lb/>Northern Finland Birth Cohort 1986 Study: A Cross-sectional Study <lb/>of 2,775 Subjects <lb/>Suvi-PÄIVIKKI SINIKUMPU 1,2 , Jari JOKELAINEN 3 and Laura HUILAJA 1,2 <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Dermatology, University Hospital of Oulu, 2 Medical Research Center, Research Unit of Clinical Medicine, University of Oulu and <lb/>3 <lb/>Northern Finland Birth Cohorts, Arctic Biobank, Infrastructure for Population Studies, Faculty of Medicine, University of Oulu, Oulu, Finland <lb/>A negative stigmatization related to hidradenitis sup-<lb/>purativa may prevent patients from seeking care. <lb/>Thus, a large proportion of patients with hidradenitis <lb/>suppurativa may be missing from studies based on <lb/>hospital data. The aim of this study was to examine <lb/>the prevalence and characteristics of hidradenitis sup-<lb/>purativa among 2,775 subjects in the Northern Fin-<lb/>land Birth Cohort 1986 Study (NFBC1986), who were <lb/>in their mid-thirties. The prevalence of hidradenitis <lb/>suppurativa was 4.0% (n = 110/2,775), being higher <lb/>in females (4.8%) than in males (2.5%) (p &lt; 0.01). Of <lb/>those defined as having hidradenitis suppurativa in <lb/>this study, only 4 cases (n = 4/110, 3.6%) were found <lb/>to have a hidradenitis suppurativa diagnosis either in <lb/>the hospital (Care Register for Health Care) or in the <lb/>primary healthcare data. In an adjusted model in lo-<lb/>gistic regression analyses, hidradenitis suppurativa <lb/>was significantly associated with obesity (body mass <lb/>index 30-55 kg/m 2 ) (odds ratio 3.81, 95% confidence <lb/>interval 2.80-5.22), female sex (1.99, 1.53-2.61) and <lb/>smoking (1.56, 1.21-2.00). In addition, there was an <lb/>association between hidradenitis suppurativa and self-<lb/>reported poor overall health status. Hidradenitis sup-<lb/>purativa seems to be common at the population level <lb/>and only a minority of these patients seek care for the <lb/>condition. <lb/>Key words: hidradenitis suppurativa; prevalence; characteris-<lb/>tics; risk factors; overall health; general population; cohort <lb/>study. <lb/>Submitted Jun 15, 2023. Accepted after review Nov 17, 2023 <lb/>Published XX. DOI: 10.2340/actadv.v104.14732 <lb/>Acta Derm Venereol 2024; 104: adv14732. <lb/>Corr: Suvi-Päivikki Sinikumpu, Department of Dermatology, Oulu <lb/>University Hospital, P.B. 20, FIN-90029 Oulu, Finland. E-mail: suvi-<lb/>paivikki.sinikumpu@oulu.fi <lb/></front>

        <body>H idradenitis suppurativa (HS) is a chronic, recurrent <lb/>inflammatory disease of hair follicles, characterized <lb/>by painful, subcutaneous lesions, most commonly located <lb/>in the inguinal, axillary and anogenital regions (1). HS <lb/>is one of the most distressing diseases in dermatology, <lb/>with known impact on quality of life (2). The annual <lb/>incidence of HS has not been widely studied, and has <lb/>been reported to be 3.0-6.0/100,000 persons/year in <lb/>Finland and Minnesota, US. (3, 4). Prevalence of HS <lb/>varies between 0.1 and 4% (3, 4). HS affects women more <lb/>frequently than men (female:male ratio 2:1-5:1) and the <lb/>incidence is highest among young women (the highest <lb/>reported prevalence is among those aged 20-39 years) <lb/>(4-6). HS is associated with many comorbidities, such <lb/>as cardiovascular diseases, inflammatory bowel disease, <lb/>and depression (3, 7). <lb/>Although knowledge of HS and its associative comor-<lb/>bidities has increased in recent years there is little epide-<lb/>miological data about the disease. In particular, there is a <lb/>lack of epidemiological studies performed in the general <lb/>population (8). Registry studies have large datasets as <lb/>their strength; however, cases with mild symptoms may <lb/>be missing. In addition, as the symptoms of HS are often <lb/>embarrassing, patients may delay seeking help from a <lb/>physician (9). Thus, the precise prevalence of HS remains <lb/>unknown. The aim of this cross-sectional study was to <lb/>examine the prevalence and characteristics of HS at the <lb/>population level among 2,775 cases belonging to the <lb/>Northern Finland Birth Cohort 1986 Study (NFBC1986) <lb/>in their mid-thirties. <lb/>MATERIALS AND METHODS <lb/>The NFBC1986 Study is a population-based, longitudinal cohort <lb/>study and research programme. Initially, the NFBC1986 included <lb/>all 9,749 (9,432 live born) children in the 2 northernmost provinces <lb/>of Finland whose expected days of birth fell between 1 July 1985, <lb/>and 30 June 1986 (covering 99% of the children in that area) (10). <lb/>The cohort subjects have been evaluated regularly since birth by <lb/>means of health questionnaires and clinical examinations. In 2019 <lb/>to 2020, at the age of 33-35 years, cohort members were invited <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">ActaDV <lb/>ActaDV <lb/>Advances in dermatology and venereology <lb/>Acta Dermato-Venereologica <lb/>S-P. Sinikumpu et al. &quot;Hidradenitis suppurativa in the Northern Finland Birth Cohort 1986 Study&quot; <lb/></note>

        <page>2/6 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Acta Derm Venereol 2024 <lb/></note>

        <body>to participate in a large follow-up study. In connection with that <lb/>study the cohort members answered diverse health questionnaires <lb/>regarding health and health-related factors. <lb/>Assessment of hidradenitis suppurativa <lb/>The presence of HS was based on the questionnaires. The study <lb/>cases were asked: (i) &quot;Have you had an outbreak of boils during <lb/>the last 6 months in the following areas: axilla, groin, genitals, <lb/>under the breast or abdomen, buttock or gluteal cleft?&quot; and (ii) <lb/>&quot;How many boils have you had?&quot;; the number of boils: (a) at <lb/>least 2, (b) 3-5, (c) 6 or more. HS was defined if there was an <lb/>affirmative answer to the first question combined with at least 2 <lb/>boils (Appendix S1). These criteria are modified from validated <lb/>criteria by Vinding et al. (11). <lb/>Assessment of other parameters <lb/>In the questionnaires, the study cases self-reported their weight, <lb/>height, living habits (including smoking status, alcohol use, and <lb/>physical activity) and their opinion about their current health status. <lb/>Body mass index (BMI) was calculated as the ratio of weight to <lb/>height squared (kg/m 2 ). Study participants were classified into 4 <lb/>groups according to BMI and World Health Organization (WHO) <lb/>criteria: underweight &lt; 18.5 kg/m 2 ; normal weight 18.5-25 kg/m 2 ; <lb/>overweight 25-30 kg/m 2 ; and obese 30-55 kg/m 2 . To determine <lb/>the use of alcohol, the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test <lb/>was used (12). Smoking status was classified as (a) no smoking, <lb/>(b) former smokers &gt; 6 months (quit smoking less than 6 months <lb/>ago), (c) former smokers &lt; 6 months (quit smoking more than 6 <lb/>months ago), and (d) current smoking. In addition, the history of <lb/>other diseases (both somatic and psychiatric diseases) was asked <lb/>as follows: &quot;Do you currently have or have you had a below-men-<lb/>tioned doctor-diagnosed disease?&quot; (Appendix S2). By the reported <lb/>frequency of participation in physical and recreational activities <lb/>during leisure time, the study cases were classified into 4 groups: <lb/>Inactive (those who preferred to stay indoors reading or watching <lb/>television and did not like sports much); Lightly active (those who <lb/>exercised at least 4 h per week, e.g. by walking, cycling, fishing); <lb/>Active (those who liked fitness training and had, e.g. running, <lb/>swimming or skiing as a regular sport activity for at least 2 h per <lb/>week); Very active (those who exercised several hours per week by <lb/>running, orienteering or playing ball games. Socioeconomic status <lb/>(SES) was determined by education: ((a) basic education or high <lb/>school, (b) vocational education, (c) lower academic education, <lb/>and (d) upper academic education), and by livelihood status: ((a) <lb/>regular income, (b) social benefits such as unemployment benefit, <lb/>(c) student allowance/sickness benefit, (d) no regular income). <lb/>Finnish Care Register of Health Care (CRHC) <lb/>Patient records (history of HS diagnosed in secondary or public <lb/>primary care) were obtained from the Finnish Institute of Health <lb/>and Welfare&apos;s statutory Care Register of Health Care (CRHC) <lb/>and the AvoHILMO (Care Register for Primary Health Care), <lb/>and diagnosis of HS was searched using the International Clas-<lb/>sification of Diseases (ICD) codes 7058C and L73.2. The CRHC <lb/>contains inpatient data from all state-administered Finnish hos-<lb/>pitals and from the largest private hospitals from 1987 onwards <lb/>and outpatient visits from 1998 onwards. Outpatient visits in <lb/>primary healthcare are included since 2011. Each record contains <lb/>the identification numbers of the patient and hospital, primary and <lb/>subsidiary diagnoses, and duration of hospital stay. <lb/>Statistical analyses <lb/>The characteristics of the study population are presented as pro-<lb/>portions, means and medians. The two-sample t-test and Person&apos;s <lb/>χ 2 test were used to compare the distribution between HS groups. <lb/>A logistic regression analysis was used to examine associations <lb/>between HS and risk factors with crude (OR) and adjusted odds <lb/>ratios (aOR) and 95% confidence intervals (95% CIs). The fol-<lb/>lowing potential confounding factors were adjusted for: sex, <lb/>comorbidities, smoking, and overall health status. An additional <lb/>adjustment was performed for BMI. The inverse probability weigh-<lb/>ting, utilizing propensity score methods were used, to generate <lb/>sampling weights for survey respondents that accurately represent <lb/>the eligible cohort, in multivariate logistics regression. Propensity <lb/>score for participation was conducted using sex and education, <lb/>socioeconomic and employment status as auxiliary variable. These <lb/>methods were used to correct the participation bias, since there <lb/>was over-representation of highly educated women in the cohort <lb/>(personal communication with Nordström et al.). OR was used as <lb/>a relative risk. The data were analysed using R software package <lb/>version 4.1.0 (R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, <lb/>Austria). A p-value &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>In connection with a 33-to 35-year follow-up study, <lb/>health questionnaires were sent to n = 8,896 study ca-<lb/>ses. Of these, n = 2,831 responded to the questionnaires <lb/>(31.8%); 62.9% of respondents were female. There was <lb/>some missing data (n = 56) and, thus, the final study <lb/>population included n = 2,775 cases. <lb/>The prevalence of HS was 4.0% (n = 110/2,775), being <lb/>higher in females (4.8%) than in males (2.5%) (p &lt; 0.01) <lb/>(Table I). The majority of the patients (n = 90/110, <lb/>81.8%) had had 3 or more boils during the previous 6 <lb/>months. Of those defined as having HS in this study, 4 <lb/>cases (n = 4/110, 3.6%) were found to have a diagnosis <lb/>of HS, either in hospital (CRHC) or in primary health-<lb/>care data. <lb/>The most common localization of boils was genitals <lb/>(53.6%), seen more commonly in females (61.2%) than <lb/>males (28.0%) (p &lt; 0.01). In addition to the genital area, <lb/>groins (57.6%) were a typical site of boils in females. <lb/>In males, the buttocks were the most usual site (48.0%) <lb/>of HS, followed by axilla (36.0%) and groins (36.0%). <lb/>There was more smoking (31.8%) and obesity (41.3%) <lb/>among those with HS than among those without (24.3% <lb/>and 16.1%, respectively) (p &lt; 0.001 and p &lt; 0.05, respec-<lb/>tively). Study cases with HS also had more alcohol use <lb/>and less physical activity compared with their controls, <lb/>but the difference was not statistically significant. There <lb/>was no statistical difference in SES between cases and <lb/>controls (Table I). <lb/>The cases with HS reported their overall health to be <lb/>significantly worse than the controls (p &lt; 0.01) and they <lb/>more commonly reported both somatic and psychiatric <lb/>comorbidities than did controls (Table II and Fig. 1). In <lb/>logistic regression analyses (adjusted with comorbidities, <lb/>BMI, sex, current health status (patient&apos;s own opinion) <lb/>and smoking), subjects with obesity (BMI 30 -55 kg/m 2 ) <lb/>had nearly 4-fold risk (OR 3.81, 95% CI 2.80-5.22) of <lb/>having HS compared with controls. Correspondingly, <lb/>female sex (OR 1.99, 95% CI 1.53-2.61) and smoking <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">ActaDV <lb/>ActaDV <lb/>Advances in dermatology and venereology <lb/>Acta Dermato-Venereologica <lb/></note>

        <page>3/6 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">S-P. Sinikumpu et al. &quot;Hidradenitis suppurativa in the Northern Finland Birth Cohort 1986 Study&quot; <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">Acta Derm Venereol 2024 <lb/></note>

        <body>(OR 1.56, 95% CI 1.21-2.00) increased the risk of HS <lb/>nearly 2-fold compared with males and non-smokers. <lb/>There was also a significant association between poor <lb/>overall health status and HS (OR 2.47, 95% CI 1.21-<lb/>2.00) (Table III). <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>This study was conducted to chart the prevalence rate <lb/>of HS in a unique NFBC1986 Study. The prevalence of <lb/>self-reported HS was 4.0%, which is higher than that <lb/>reported in larger studies from the USA (0.1%, n = 48 <lb/>million) (5), France (~1%, n = 6,887) (8) or Denmark <lb/>(1.8%, n = 27,275) (13). However, the prevalence level <lb/>in 2 small Danish studies by Jemec and co-workers cor-<lb/>respond to ours (~4%) (14, 15). The variation in the pre-<lb/>valence between the current study and previous studies is <lb/>probably due to the differences in study methodology and <lb/>study groups. For example, the general US population <lb/>study included only cases who had sought care in health <lb/>systems or had been diagnosed with HS (5). The large <lb/>Danish study, in turn, consisted of blood donors and, thus, <lb/>the study sample is probably not directly comparable <lb/>with the general population (13). There were also some <lb/>heterogeneities in mean age between the studies (8), with <lb/>ours including only adults in their mid-thirties. Since <lb/>HS is reported to affect young adults especially (with <lb/>a female predominance), resembling our study popula-<lb/>tion, the relatively high prevalence in the current study <lb/>is reasonable. Surprisingly, only very few (n = 4/110) of <lb/>the subjects with HS in the current study were found to <lb/>have a healthcare contact regarding HS or diagnosed <lb/>HS, strengthening the hypothesis that stigmatization <lb/>related to HS may prevent patients from seeking care. <lb/>Table I. Basic characteristics of the study population a <lb/>HS (N = 110) <lb/>No HS (N = 2,665) <lb/>Total (N = 2,775) <lb/>p-value b <lb/>Sex, n (%) <lb/>0.002 <lb/>Male <lb/>25 (22.7) <lb/>990 (37.1) <lb/>1,015 (36.6) <lb/>Female <lb/>85 (77.3) <lb/>1,675 (62.9) <lb/>1,760 (63.4) <lb/>How satisfied are you with your current situation in life in general? n (%) <lb/>0.002 <lb/>Very satisfied <lb/>9 (8.3) <lb/>499 (18.9) <lb/>508 (18.4) <lb/>Somewhat satisfied <lb/>63 (57.8) <lb/>1,608 (60.8) <lb/>1,671 (60.7) <lb/>Somewhat dissatisfied <lb/>33 (30.3) <lb/>495 (18.7) <lb/>528 (19.2) <lb/>Very dissatisfied <lb/>4 (3.7) <lb/>41 (1.5) <lb/>45 (1.6) <lb/>Cannot say <lb/>0 (0.0%) <lb/>3 (0.1%) <lb/>3 (0.1) <lb/>BMI, kg/m 2 <lb/>&lt; 0.001 <lb/>Mean (SD) <lb/>29.5 (6.9) <lb/>25.9 (4.8) <lb/>26.1 (5.0) <lb/>Median (Q1, Q3) <lb/>27.9 (24.0, 34.6) <lb/>25.0 (22.8, 28.0) <lb/>25.1 (22.8, 28.2) <lb/>Min-Max <lb/>19.5-59.1 <lb/>14.9-56.8 <lb/>14.9-59.1 <lb/>BMI according to WHO criteria, n (%) <lb/>&lt; 0.001 <lb/>Underweight <lb/>0 (0.0) <lb/>32 (1.2) <lb/>32 (1.2) <lb/>Normal weight <lb/>33 (30.3) <lb/>1,265 (47.8) <lb/>1,298 (47.1) <lb/>Pre-obesity <lb/>31 (28.4) <lb/>924 (34.9) <lb/>955 (34.6) <lb/>Obesity <lb/>45 (41.3) <lb/>427 (16.1) <lb/>472 (17.1) <lb/>Alcohol use according to AUDIT, n (%) <lb/>0.360 <lb/>Low-risk consumption (score 0-7) <lb/>75 (75.0) <lb/>1,787 (78.7) <lb/>1,862 (78.5) <lb/>Hazardous or harmful alcohol consumption (score 8-13) <lb/>18 (18.0) <lb/>391 (17.2) <lb/>409 (17.2) <lb/>Likelihood of alcohol dependence (scores 14-) <lb/>7 (7.0) <lb/>94 (4.1) <lb/>101 (4.3) <lb/>Smoking c , n (%) <lb/>0.006 <lb/>No <lb/>27 (24.5) <lb/>949 (35.8) <lb/>976 (35.3) <lb/>Former smoker &gt; 6kk <lb/>37 (33.6) <lb/>936 (35.3) <lb/>973 (35.2) <lb/>Former smoker &lt; 6kk <lb/>11 (10.0) <lb/>124 (4.7) <lb/>135 (4.9) <lb/>Current smoker <lb/>35 (31.8) <lb/>644 (24.3) <lb/>679 (24.6) <lb/>Livelihood status, n (%) <lb/>0.967 <lb/>Regular income <lb/>85 (77.3) <lb/>2,111 (79.2) <lb/>2,196 (79.1) <lb/>Social benefits <lb/>10 (9.1) <lb/>218 (8.2) <lb/>228 (8.2) <lb/>Study grants/nursing leave benefits <lb/>13 (11.8) <lb/>287 (10.8) <lb/>300 (10.8) <lb/>No regular income <lb/>2 (1.8) <lb/>49 (1.8) <lb/>51 (1.8) <lb/>Education, n (%) <lb/>0.247 <lb/>Basic education or high school <lb/>15 (13.6) <lb/>229 (8.6) <lb/>244 (8.8) <lb/>Vocational education <lb/>34 (30.9) <lb/>800 (30.2) <lb/>834 (30.2) <lb/>Lower academic education <lb/>38 (34.5) <lb/>928 (35.0) <lb/>966 (35.0) <lb/>Upper academic education <lb/>23 (20.9) <lb/>694 (26.2) <lb/>717 (26.0) <lb/>Civilization, n (%) <lb/>0.474 <lb/>Divorced/judicial separation/single <lb/>43 (39.1) <lb/>948 (35.7) <lb/>991 (35.9) <lb/>Relationship <lb/>67 (60.9) <lb/>1,704 (64.3) <lb/>1,771 (64.1) <lb/>Physical activity, n (%) <lb/>0.069 <lb/>Inactive <lb/>32 (29.6) <lb/>551 (20.9) <lb/>583 (21.3) <lb/>Lightly active <lb/>45 (41.7) <lb/>1,039 (39.4) <lb/>1,084 (39.5) <lb/>Active <lb/>29 (26.9) <lb/>958 (36.4) <lb/>987 (36.0) <lb/>Very active <lb/>2 (1.9) <lb/>86 (3.3) <lb/>88 (3.2) <lb/>a <lb/>There may be some missing data while all study cases did not answer to all questions. b Two sample t-test otherwise χ 2 test. c Smoking status: former smokers &gt; 6 <lb/>months (quit smoking less than 6 months ago), former smokers &lt; 6 months (quit smoking more than 6 months ago). <lb/>HS: hidradenitis suppurativa: BMI: body mass index; SD: standard deviation; WHO: World Health Organization; AUDIT: Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">ActaDV <lb/>ActaDV <lb/>Advances in dermatology and venereology <lb/>Acta Dermato-Venereologica <lb/>S-P. Sinikumpu et al. &quot;Hidradenitis suppurativa in the Northern Finland Birth Cohort 1986 Study&quot; <lb/></note>

        <page>4/6 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Acta Derm Venereol 2024 <lb/></note>

        <body>However, since the healthcare data in the current study <lb/>is registry-based, we cannot exclude the possibility of <lb/>misdiagnosed HS (i.e. regular boils/abscesses). <lb/>In this study, there was a female preponderance in HS <lb/>(2-fold risk), corresponding to other studies reporting <lb/>the female-to-male ratio to be as high as 5:1 (6). The <lb/>exact mechanisms behind the sex difference in preva-<lb/>lence of HS is unknown, but sex hormones are thought <lb/>to be involved in the pathophysiology; e.g. pregnancy <lb/>and premenstrual flares are known to exacerbate the <lb/>symptoms of HS, whereas onset of HS is rare after <lb/>menopause (16). <lb/>The association between obesity and HS is well known <lb/>from previous studies and the current study finding <lb/>is consistent with others (4, 13, 17). The mean BMI <lb/>among HS cases in the current study was 29.5 kg/m 2 <lb/>(overweight) and nearly half (41.3%) of the cases were <lb/>obese (females significantly more often than males) (4, <lb/>13, 17). In a Danish study, the mean BMI among sub-<lb/>jects with HS was 27.0 kg/m 2 (13), and in a US study, <lb/>32.6 kg/m 2 (4). Some studies have found over 75% of <lb/>patients with HS to be obese (17). Obesity can activate <lb/>HS in many ways; it contributes to an abnormal hormonal <lb/>metabolic status, causes low-grade inflammation, and, <lb/>via increased skin-to-skin contact, leads to increased <lb/>friction, maceration and occlusion, which may result in <lb/>follicular hyperkeratosis and plugging (17). In addition <lb/>to obesity, smoking is an important environmental risk <lb/>factor of HS (17). In the current study, the subjects with <lb/>HS reported significantly more smoking than controls. <lb/>Like obesity, smoking influences the structure of the skin <lb/>(e.g. stimulates follicular hyperplasia and occlusion, mo-<lb/>difies sweat gland activity) and produces inflammatory <lb/>reactions (17, 18). <lb/>The subjects with HS in this study considered their <lb/>overall health to be worse than the controls. The burden <lb/>of HS is known to be high and parallel to many chronic <lb/>diseases, such as rheumatoid diseases (21). Correspon-<lb/>dingly in the other Finnish study (2) patients with HS <lb/>(n = 92, patients in tertiary care, evaluated by the ge-<lb/>neric 15 D questionnaire) had significantly diminished <lb/>health-related quality of life compared with the general <lb/>population. It is notable that, in that study, the findings <lb/>were independent of HS severity (2). HS may be a very <lb/>embarrassing disease with serious consequences, and <lb/>patients with HS, especially females, consider the burden <lb/>of HS to be very high (22), and have also been reported <lb/>to have an increased risk of suicide regardless of whether <lb/>they have a previous psychiatric diagnosis (23). <lb/>Association of HS with multiple somatic and psychia-<lb/>tric diseases has been shown in several studies (3, 7). In <lb/>line with these, the current study found higher <lb/>prevalences of many diseases in our subjects with <lb/>HS compared with controls. Nevertheless, the as-<lb/>sociation between comorbidities and HS may be <lb/>modified by other factors, such as sex, smoking <lb/>and BMI, as seen in our analyses. In particular, <lb/>BMI was a strong risk factor for HS, which was <lb/>the reason we performed an additional adjustment <lb/>for BMI. However, due to the rather small group <lb/>size, more studies are needed to evaluate specific <lb/>diseases more accurately. <lb/>The major strength of this study is that it is <lb/>based on a large (nearly 3,000 subjects) birth <lb/>cohort population. Studies such as this one offer <lb/>important information about the more realistic <lb/>Table II. Somatic and psychiatric comorbidities between those with <lb/>hidradenitis suppurativa (HS) and controls <lb/>Comorbidities* <lb/>HS (N = 110) <lb/>n (%) <lb/>No HS (N = 2,665) <lb/>n (%) <lb/>p-value <lb/>Cardiovascular diseases <lb/>0.933 <lb/>No <lb/>99 (90.0) <lb/>2,391 (89.8) <lb/>Yes <lb/>11 (10.0) <lb/>273 (10.2) <lb/>Diabetes <lb/>0.008 <lb/>No <lb/>105 (95.5) <lb/>2,627 (98.6) <lb/>Yes <lb/>5 (4.5) <lb/>37 (1.4) <lb/>Thyroid diseases <lb/>0.752 <lb/>No <lb/>104 (94.5) <lb/>2,499 (93.8) <lb/>Yes <lb/>6 (5.5) <lb/>165 (6.2) <lb/>Gastrointestinal diseases <lb/>0.083 <lb/>No <lb/>86 (78.2) <lb/>2,247 (84.3) <lb/>True <lb/>24 (21.8) <lb/>417 (15.7) <lb/>Neurological diseases <lb/>&lt; 0.001 <lb/>No <lb/>68 (61.8) <lb/>2,039 (76.5) <lb/>Yes <lb/>42 (38.2) <lb/>625 (23.5) <lb/>Malignancies <lb/>0.055 <lb/>No <lb/>103 (93.6) <lb/>2,582 (96.9) <lb/>Yes <lb/>7 (6.4) <lb/>82 (3.1) <lb/>Psychiatric diseases <lb/>0.019 <lb/>No <lb/>75 (68.2) <lb/>2,070 (77.7) <lb/>Yes <lb/>35 (31.8) <lb/>594 (22.3) <lb/>Apnoea <lb/>0.027 <lb/>No <lb/>105 (95.5) <lb/>2,619 (98.3) <lb/>Yes <lb/>5 (4.5) <lb/>45 (1.7) <lb/>Asthma <lb/>0.071 <lb/>No <lb/>90 (81.8) <lb/>2,335 (87.7) <lb/>Yes <lb/>20 (18.2) <lb/>329 (12.3) <lb/>Chronic obstructive pulmonary <lb/>disease <lb/>0.463 <lb/>No <lb/>105 (95.5) <lb/>2,577 (96.7) <lb/>Yes <lb/>5 (4.5) <lb/>87 (3.3) <lb/>Musculoskeletal disorders and <lb/>rheumatic diseases <lb/>0.375 <lb/>No <lb/>77 (70.0) <lb/>1,966 (73.8) <lb/>Yes <lb/>33 (30.0) <lb/>698 (26.2) <lb/>*The detailed list of comorbidities is shown in Appendix S1. <lb/>Fig. 1. Prevalence of psychiatric and somatic morbidity in patients with <lb/>hidradenitis suppurativa (HS) and in those without HS. Values in brackets <lb/>are the pure or comorbid prevalence of psychiatric or somatic disorders. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">ActaDV <lb/>ActaDV <lb/>Advances in dermatology and venereology <lb/>Acta Dermato-Venereologica <lb/></note>

        <page>5/6 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">S-P. Sinikumpu et al. &quot;Hidradenitis suppurativa in the Northern Finland Birth Cohort 1986 Study&quot; <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">Acta Derm Venereol 2024 <lb/></note>

        <body>prevalence of HS, since they are not focused on selec-<lb/>ted patient groups: as seen in the current study, only a <lb/>minority of the subjects with HS were found from the <lb/>hospital/primary care register data. The participation <lb/>rate in the study was satisfactory and comparable with <lb/>the participation rates in other cross-sectional European <lb/>health examination surveys (24, 25). In addition, due <lb/>to the study design, we were able to evaluate compre-<lb/>hensively the basic characteristics and comorbidities <lb/>of the patients with HS. As a limitation, even though <lb/>the definition of HS in this study was based on the <lb/>internationally accepted criteria (11), the possibility of <lb/>misdiagnosis remains (due to self-reporting data) (26). <lb/>However, self-reported diagnoses are, in turn, also stated <lb/>to produce the highest estimates of HS prevalence (1). <lb/>Nevertheless, since Koptyev et al. (26) have questioned <lb/>the reliability of self-reporting in HS definition, we deci-<lb/>ded to slightly modify the criteria presented by Vinding <lb/>and co-workers (11). Furthermore, we studied a narrow <lb/>age cohort of Caucasian subjects, which may limit the <lb/>generalization of the current results outside the birth co-<lb/>hort or to other age groups or ethnicities. Finally, not all <lb/>invited cohort members participated in the study (there <lb/>was an over-representation of highly educated women <lb/>(personal communication with Nordström et al.), and, the <lb/>rate of non-response must be regarded as sample bias. <lb/>Furthermore, this may have led to some bias, both in the <lb/>prevalence of HS and in the prevalence of comorbidities <lb/>studied. However, the inverse probability weighting <lb/>methods were used to correct this bias. <lb/>In conclusion, this study demonstrated a high preva-<lb/>lence of HS in this cohort population among subjects in <lb/>their mid-thirties. HS was more common in females than <lb/>in males and was associated with obesity and smoking. <lb/>Subjects with HS were affected with a high burden of <lb/>comorbidities and they considered their own health to be <lb/>poor. Thus, the risk factors of HS in this unselected po-<lb/>pulation seem to correspond to those in hospital register <lb/>studies (7). It is noteworthy that only a few of the current <lb/>study cases were registered in healthcare data because of <lb/>HS, and thus, it is important to remember that HS cases <lb/>are less likely to seek help for their disease. <lb/></body>

        <div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>We thank all cohort members and researchers who participated in <lb/>the 33-to 35-year study. We also wish to acknowledge the work <lb/>of the NFBC project center. <lb/></div>

        <div type="availability">Data referral: http://urn.fi/urn:nbn:fi:att:f5c10eef-3d25-4bd0-<lb/>beb8-f2d59df95b8e <lb/>A data availability statement: NFBC data is available from the <lb/>University of Oulu, Infrastructure for Population Studies. Permis-<lb/>sion to use the data can be applied for research purposes via the <lb/>electronic material request portal. In the use of data, we follow the <lb/>EU general data protection regulation (679/2016) and the Finnish <lb/>Data Protection Act. The use of personal data is based on cohort <lb/>participants&apos; written informed consent at their latest follow-up <lb/>study, which may cause limitations to its use. More information <lb/>is available by contacting the NFBC project center (NFBC project <lb/>center (at)oulu.fi) and visiting the cohort website. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">The ethics committee of the Northern Ostrobothnia Hospital <lb/>District approved the present study ( §108/2017), which was <lb/>performed according to the principles of the 1983 Declaration <lb/>of Helsinki. The subjects took part on a voluntary basis and gave <lb/>their informed consent. The data was handled on a group level <lb/>and was pseudonymized for analyses. <lb/></div>

        <div type="conflict">The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare. <lb/></div>

        <body>Table III. Association between hidradenitis suppurativa and risk factors <lb/>Hidradenitis suppurativa <lb/>Crude odds ratio <lb/>Adjusted model 1 a <lb/>Adjusted model 2 b <lb/>Comorbidities <lb/>Somatic or psychiatric comorbid <lb/>1.30 (0.84, 2.05) <lb/>1.07 (0.80, 1.43) <lb/>1.07 (0.80, 1.43) <lb/>p = 0.252 <lb/>p = 0.65 <lb/>p = 0.67 <lb/>Somatic and psychiatric comorbid <lb/>2.14 (1.24, 3.64) <lb/>1.24 (0.86, 1.79) <lb/>1.12 (0.77, 1.62) <lb/>p = 0.006 <lb/>p = 0.25 <lb/>p = 0.54 <lb/>Sex <lb/>Female <lb/>2.01 (1.30, 3.22) <lb/>1.92 (1.48, 2.50) <lb/>1.99 (1.53, 2.61) <lb/>p = 0.003 <lb/>p = 0.00001 <lb/>p = 0.0001 <lb/>How satisfied are you with your current situation in life in general? <lb/>Satisfied <lb/>2.17 (1.13, 4.71) <lb/>1.99 (1.26, 3.31) <lb/>1.64 (1.03, 2.73) <lb/>p = 0.032 <lb/>p = 0.01 <lb/>p = 0.05 <lb/>Somewhat satisfied <lb/>3.70 (1.83, 8.29) <lb/>3.43 (2.11, 5.84) <lb/>2.12 (1.29, 3.66) <lb/>p = 0.001 <lb/>p = 0.0001 <lb/>p = 0.005 <lb/>Somewhat or very dissatisfied <lb/>5.04 (1.32, 16.17) <lb/>3.76 (1.73, 7.97) <lb/>2.47 (1.12, 5.29) <lb/>p = 0.010 <lb/>p = 0.001 <lb/>p = 0.03 <lb/>Smoking status <lb/>Current smoker or Former smoker &lt; 6 months <lb/>1.74 (1.17, 2.55) <lb/>1.54 (1.20, 1.97) <lb/>1.56 (1.21, 2.00) <lb/>p = 0.006 <lb/>p = 0.001 <lb/>p = 0.001 <lb/>Body mass index c <lb/>25-30 kg/m 2 <lb/>1.32 (0.80, 2.17) <lb/>1.38 (1.00, 1.92) <lb/>p = 0.276 <lb/>p = 0.06 <lb/>30-55 kg/m 2 <lb/>4.14 (2.62, 6.62) <lb/>3.81 (2.80, 5.22) <lb/>p &lt; 0.001 <lb/>p &lt; 0.001 <lb/>Logistic regression analyses: a Adjusted by comorbidities, sex, overall health status, smoking. b An additional adjustment for body mass index. c According to the World <lb/>Health Organization (WHO) classification. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">ActaDV <lb/>ActaDV <lb/>Advances in dermatology and venereology <lb/>Acta Dermato-Venereologica <lb/>S-P. Sinikumpu et al. &quot;Hidradenitis suppurativa in the Northern Finland Birth Cohort 1986 Study&quot; <lb/></note>

        <page>6/6 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Acta Derm Venereol 2024 <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Jemec GBE, Kimball AB. Hidradenitis suppurativa: epide-<lb/>miology and scope of the problem. J Am Acad Dermatol <lb/>2015; 73: 4-7. <lb/>2. Hirvonen MJ, Pasternack R, Lipitsä T, Vihervaara A, Harvima <lb/>R, Ranta M, et al. Patients with hidradenitis suppurativa suf-<lb/>fer from low health-related quality of life as measured by <lb/>the generic 15D instrument. Skin Appendage Disord 2022; <lb/>8: 221-227. <lb/>3. Huilaja L, Tiri H, Jokelainen J, Timonen M, Tasanen K. Pa-<lb/>tients with hidradenitis suppurativa have a high psychiatric <lb/>disease burden: a Finnish Nationwide Registry Study. J Invest <lb/>Dermatol 2018; 138: 46-51. <lb/>4. Vazquez BG, Alikhan A, Weaver AL, Wetter DA, Davis MD. <lb/>Incidence of hidradenitis suppurativa and associated factors: <lb/>a population-based study of Olmsted County, Minnesota. J <lb/>Invest Dermatol 2013; 133: 97-103. <lb/>5. Garg A, Kirby JS, Lavian J, Lin G, Strunk A. Sex-and age-<lb/>adjusted population analysis of prevalence estimates for <lb/>hidradenitis suppurativa in the United States. JAMA Dermatol <lb/>2017; 153: 760-764. <lb/>6. Wiseman MC. Hidradenitis suppurativa: a review. Dermatol <lb/>Ther 2004; 17: 50-54. <lb/>7. Garg A, Malviya N, Strunk A, Wright S, Alavi A, Alhusayen <lb/>R, et al. Comorbidity screening in hidradenitis suppurativa: <lb/>evidence-based recommendations from the US and Canadian <lb/>Hidradenitis Suppurativa Foundations. J Am Acad Dermatol <lb/>2022; 86: 1092-1101. <lb/>8. Revuz JE, Canoui-Poitrine F, Wolkenstein P, Viallette C, Ga-<lb/>bison G, Pouget F, et al. Prevalence and factors associated <lb/>with hidradenitis suppurativa: results from two case-control <lb/>studies. J Am Acad Dermatol 2008; 59: 596-601. <lb/>9. Garg A, Neuren E, Cha D, Kirby JS, Ingram JR, Jemec GBE, <lb/>et al. Evaluating patients&apos; unmet needs in hidradenitis sup-<lb/>purativa: results from the Global Survey Of Impact and <lb/>Healthcare Needs (VOICE) Project. J Am Acad Dermatol <lb/>2020; 82: 366-376. <lb/>10. NFBC 1986 Data Collection. Northern Finland Cohorts. [ac-<lb/>cessed 2022 May 30] Available from: https://www.oulu.fi/ <lb/>en/university/faculties-and-units/faculty-medicine/northern-<lb/>finland-birth-cohorts-and-arctic-biobank/research-program-<lb/>health-and-well-being. <lb/>11. Vinding GR, Miller IM, Zarchi K, Ibler KS, Ellervik C, Jemec <lb/>GBE. The prevalence of inverse recurrent suppuration: a <lb/>population-based study of possible hidradenitis suppurativa. <lb/>Br J Dermatol 2014; 170: 884-889. <lb/>12. Saunders JB, Aasland O, Babor T, de la Fuente J, Grant M. <lb/>Development of the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test <lb/>(AUDIT): WHO Collaborative Project on Early Detection of <lb/>Persons with Harmful Alcohol Consumption -II. Addiction <lb/>(Abingdon, England) 1993; 88: 791-804. <lb/>13. Theut Riis P, Pedersen OB, Sigsgaard V, Erikstrup C, Paarup <lb/>HM, Nielsen KR, et al. Prevalence of patients with self-<lb/>reported hidradenitis suppurativa in a cohort of Danish <lb/>blood donors: a cross-sectional study. Br J Dermatol 2019; <lb/>180: 774-781. <lb/>14. Jemec GB. The symptomatology of hidradenitis suppurativa <lb/>in women. Br J Dermatol 1988; 119: 345-350. <lb/>15. Jemec GB, Heidenheim M, Nielsen NH. The prevalence of <lb/>hidradenitis suppurativa and its potential precursor lesions. <lb/>J Am Acad Dermatol 1996; 35: 191-194. <lb/>16. Riis P, Ring H. Themstrup L, Jemec GB. The role of androgens <lb/>and estrogens in hidradenitis suppurativa -a systematic <lb/>review. Acta Dermatovenereol Croat 2016; 24: 239-249. <lb/>17. Alikhan A, Lynch PJ, Eisen DB. Hidradenitis suppurativa: <lb/>a comprehensive review. J Am Acad Dermatol 2009; 60: <lb/>539-561. <lb/>18. Mokos ZB, Miše J, Balić A, Marinović B. Understanding the <lb/>relationship between smoking and hidradenitis suppurativa. <lb/>Acta Dermatovenerol Croat 2020; 28: 9-13. <lb/>19. Deckers I, Janse I, van der Zee H, Nijsten T, Boer J, Horváth <lb/>B, et al. Hidradenitis suppurativa (HS) is associated with <lb/>low socioeconomic status (SES): a cross-sectional reference <lb/>study. J Am Acad Dermatol 2016; 75: 755-759. <lb/>20. Adler NE, Boyce T, Chesney MA, Cohen S, Folkman S, Kahn <lb/>RL, et al. Socioeconomic status and health: the challenge of <lb/>the gradient. American Psychologist 1994; 49: 15-24. <lb/>21. Kluger N, Ranta M, Serlachius M. The burden of hidrade-<lb/>nitis suppurativa in a cohort of patients in southern Fin-<lb/>land: a pilot study 2017. Skin Appendage Disord 2017; 3: <lb/>20-27. <lb/>22. Samela T, Dattolo A, Cordella G, Antinone V, Mastroeni S, <lb/>Fusari R, et al. Similar levels of disease severity correspond <lb/>to a greater burden of illness in women compared with men <lb/>with hidradenitis suppurativa. Acta Derm Venereol 2023; <lb/>103: adv00856. <lb/>23. Tiri H, Huilaja L, Jokelainen J, Timonen M, Tasanen K. Women <lb/>with hidradenitis suppurativa have an elevated risk of suicide. <lb/>J Invest Dermatol 2018; 138: 2672-2674. <lb/>24. Nordström T, Auvinen J, Ala-Mursula L, Keinänen-Kiuka-<lb/>anniemi S, Veijola J, Järvelin MR et al. Cohort Profile: 46 <lb/>years of follow-up of the Northern Finland Birth Cohort 1966 <lb/>(NFBC1966). Int J Epidemiol 2021; 50: 1-12. <lb/>25. Mindell JS, Giampaoli S, Goesswald A, Kamtsiuris P, Mann <lb/>C, Mannisto S, et al. Sample selection, recruitment and <lb/>participation rates in health examination surveys in Europe -<lb/>experience from seven national surveys. BMC Med Res Met-<lb/>hodol 2015; 15: 74-78. <lb/>26. Koptyev J, Strunk A, Garg A. Low predictive value of ques-<lb/>tionnaire-based diagnosis of hidradenitis suppurativa. Br J <lb/>Dermatol 2022; 187: 1015-1017. </listBibl>


	</text>

</TEI>