<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Improving the Air Quality Monitoring Framework Using Artificial Intelligence for Environmentally Conscious Development</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Danny</forename>
          <surname>Manongga</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Untung</forename>
          <surname>Rahardja</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Irwan</forename>
          <surname>Sembiring</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Qurotul</forename>
          <surname>Aini</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Abdul</forename>
          <surname>Wahab</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-07T08:45:07.696Z">11/7/2025 8:45:07 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Ital Publication</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.28991/hij-2024-05-03-017</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Danny Manongga, Untung Rahardja, Irwan Sembiring, Qurotul Aini, Abdul Wahab. (2024). Improving the Air Quality Monitoring Framework Using Artificial Intelligence for Environmentally Conscious Development. HighTech and Innovation Journal, 5(3), 794-813. DOI: 10.28991/hij-2024-05-03-017</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-07T08:44:04.883843Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-07T08:44:04.883843Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>Available online at www.ijournalse.org <lb/>Emerging Science Journal <lb/>(ISSN: 2610-9182) <lb/>Vol. 8, No. 2, April, 2024 <lb/>Page | 644 <lb/>The Relationship Between Thinking Ability, Emotional <lb/>Intelligence, and Decision-Making <lb/>Thuc Duc Tran 1* , Thong Van Pham 2 <lb/>1 Ho Chi Minh University of Banking, 56 Hoang Dieu 2, Thu Duc, Ho Chi Minh City, 70000, Viet Nam. <lb/>2 Faculty of Basic Sciences, Thu Duc College of Economics and Technology, Viet Nam. <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Despite a significant amount of research on decision-making, academics find it difficult to explain <lb/>the decision-making process. The purpose of this paper is to examine the relationship between <lb/>emotional intelligence, thinking ability, and decision-making, as well as develop measurement <lb/>instruments for thinking ability to better model decision-making. By following a deductive research <lb/>approach associated with positivist philosophy, a cross-sectional study was conducted and surveyed <lb/>547 respondents in South Vietnam via email sent randomly by Google Forms using a convenience <lb/>sampling method. To avoid common method bias, the reliability and validity of all items were <lb/>assessed by Cronbach&apos;s alpha and using the SPSS program. Then, to assess the structural model and <lb/>test hypotheses, partial least squares structural equation modeling was applied using the SmartPLS <lb/>program. The findings not only have proven the significantly positive effects of emotional <lb/>intelligence and thinking ability on decision-making but also highlight the suitability of the <lb/>measurement instruments related to thinking ability in explaining decision-making that no research <lb/>has ever built before. Based on the findings, this research opens up a novel research approach to <lb/>decision-making and provides the foundation for policymakers and managers to improve decision-<lb/>making efficiency and human resource quality. <lb/>Keywords: <lb/>Thinking Ability; <lb/>Emotional Intelligence; <lb/>Decision-Making; <lb/>TED Model. <lb/>Article History: <lb/>Received: <lb/>24 October <lb/>2023 <lb/>Revised: <lb/>19 February 2024 <lb/>Accepted: <lb/>04 March <lb/>2024 <lb/>Published: <lb/>01 April <lb/>2024 <lb/></front>

        <body>1-Introduction <lb/>The fifth industrial revolution, with a focus on humans and robots working together, was the trend that many firms <lb/>needed to consider regarding their company strategy. Nevertheless, humans are still at the center of decision-making, <lb/>requiring effective and high-quality decisions [1]. Recognizing the significance of decision-making, over the last two <lb/>decades, numerous scholars have focused their emphasis on cognitive science, behavioral economics, academic <lb/>marketing, and organizational behavior to clarify the decision-making process. Most previous studies focused on <lb/>emotional and rational aspects to show how emotions or rationality impacted the decision-making process [2-6]. Despite <lb/>this, few studies have examined whether rationality and emotions should be used while making decisions [6]. As a result, <lb/>the first aim of this research is to examine the effects of emotions and rationality on decision-making. <lb/>In terms of the relationship between emotions and decision-making, former researchers indicated that emotional <lb/>intelligence played an important role in shaping decision-making as well as having a strong effect on decision-making <lb/>[2, 5, 7-12]. However, if addressed in specific situations (e.g., within organizations or under time constraints), decisions <lb/>based on emotions continue to have significant limitations [13], since emotions are powerful, ubiquitous, and <lb/>foreseeable, sometimes detrimental, and sometimes helpful decision-making drivers [14]. In line with this, Lerner et al. <lb/>[14] revealed that emotion and decision-making research was still in its initial stages, and the majority of research was <lb/>conducted in laboratory settings. Hence, the second aim of this study is to identify the components of emotions that are <lb/>able to make effective and useful decisions and apply them in operation. <lb/></body>

        <front>* CONTACT: thuctd@hub.edu.vn <lb/>DOI: http://dx.doi.org/10.28991/ESJ-2024-08-02-017 <lb/>© 2024 by the authors. Licensee ESJ, Italy. This is an open access article under the terms and conditions of the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution (CC-BY) license (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/></front>

        <note place="headnote">Emerging Science Journal | Vol. 8, No. 2 <lb/></note>

        <page>Page | 645 <lb/></page>

        <body>In essence, decision-making is an unstable, convoluted process that involves emotional and rational aspects [2, 3, <lb/>13]. Additionally, decision-making based on emotional intelligence is not optimal, and other factors need to be <lb/>considered in the process of understanding the situation, such as cognitive factors [2, 6]. Bruch &amp; Feinberg [2] <lb/>indicated that cognitive factors played a significant role in shaping decision-making; specifically, the final decision <lb/>would be made when going through cognitive processes, which involved consideration of irrelevant or unattainable <lb/>options [15]. In addition, Taleb [16] asserted that traditional intelligence measures (e.g., general intelligence, reasoning <lb/>ability, understanding of alternatives and their implications) commonly failed to predict or assess &quot;Black Swan&quot; <lb/>occurrences, which were unusual and unpredictable but extremely significant. The intellect was frequently limited in <lb/>recognizing and dealing with unusual events [17]. It is challenging to discover a scale that is both practical and highly <lb/>general for evaluating human cognitive aptitude in a certain sector. Therefore, the third aim of this research is to <lb/>develop a new set of scales to assess cognitive competency (thinking ability) in an operational setting and in any <lb/>specific sector to better provide high-quality decisions. <lb/>On the other hand, decision-making is frequently regarded as complicated individual behavior since it is influenced <lb/>by a variety of personal characteristics such as attitudes, beliefs, and behaviors [18]. Similarly, Sahu et al. [3] considered <lb/>that decision-making behavior was a result of factors affecting the intentions after receiving the beliefs and values <lb/>(behavioral beliefs, normative beliefs, control beliefs) through the reasons (reasons for and reasons against) and global <lb/>motives (attitude, subjective norm, perceived behavioral control). In this approach, numerous studies have been <lb/>conducted based on behavioral theories such as field theory (FT), cognitive dissonance theory (CDT), theory of reasoned <lb/>action (TRA), spreading activation theory (SAT), expectancy-value theory (EVT), decisional balance theory (DBT), <lb/>theory of planned behavior (TPB), theory of explanation-based decision-making (TEBDM), technology acceptance <lb/>model (TAM), reason theory (RT), unified theory of acceptance and use of technology (UTAUT), and behavior reason <lb/>theory (BRT) to explain decision-making. Nevertheless, this approach has four fundamental gaps, including context <lb/>(primarily limited to marketing and consumer behavior areas), study design (a lack of causality and common method <lb/>biases), mediation and moderation effects in SEM, and external influences [3]. Besides, most previous studies <lb/>concentrated on factors (subjective norms and perceived behavioral control) impacting attitudes and intentions in the <lb/>decision-making process [19-22]; however, the emotional and rational aspects of attitudes and intentions were not strong <lb/>enough to make the final decision and corresponded to remembering or knowing levels [23, 24]. Based on these <lb/>arguments, the last aim of this research is to build up a research model that combines both emotional and rational factors <lb/>in explaining decision-making and considers the mediating role of rational factors in the relationship between emotions <lb/>and decision-making. <lb/>Based on the research aims and gaps linked to decision-making in this field, the research approach was identified, <lb/>and it will be explained in detail in the section of the literature review to show how this research was more distinctive <lb/>than others. To improve the limitations of previous studies related to emotions and rationality in explaining decision-<lb/>making, the ability model by Salovey &amp; Grewal [25], the theory of emotional intelligence by Goleman [5], and the <lb/>taxonomy of educational objectives by Bloom et al. [26] were applied. By constructing the research model from the <lb/>ability model, the theory of emotional intelligence, and the taxonomy of educational objectives, this research model can <lb/>enhance the process of individual reaction to an emotional situation and then adapt the appropriate behavior to resolve <lb/>this situation. Furthermore, through the mediating role of thinking ability in the relationship between emotions and <lb/>decision-making, the components of emotions will go through a cognitive process to make an effective and quality <lb/>decision. Based on the findings, practical and theoretical implications will be proposed for policymakers and managers <lb/>to improve decision-making efficiency regarding future policies and strategies. <lb/>The remainder of this research is organized into five sections. Section 2 synthesizes the available literature in order <lb/>to adopt the theoretical framework of the research and develop the research hypotheses. Section 3 describes the research <lb/>methodology, including data collection and analytic methodologies. Section 4 will provide the findings, and Section 5 <lb/>will go through them in depth. The last section will discuss the limits and future research. <lb/>2-Literature Review and Hypothesis Development <lb/>2-1-Literature Review <lb/>Decision-making is the process by which a person, group, or organization recognizes a choice or judgment to be <lb/>made, gathers and evaluates information regarding alternatives, and then selects from among the options [27]. According <lb/>to Bruch &amp; Feinberg [2], making decisions requires a significant amount of cognitive work. In other words, the cognitive <lb/>process is the first stage in the decision-making process before assessing the acquired information, and the greatest <lb/>degree of this process is creation. In line with this, according to Sevdalis et al. [11], while empirical research has <lb/>emphasized the importance of emotions in decision-making processes, individual variations in emotion perception and <lb/>experience have been largely disregarded. In other words, when individuals make decisions, they frequently consider <lb/>the emotions that the consequences are likely to elicit [11]. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Emerging Science Journal | Vol. 8, No. 2 <lb/></note>

        <page>Page | 646 <lb/></page>

        <body>To provide a strong explanation for this study approach, the authors carefully evaluated various papers in this area <lb/>and identified four major findings linked to the interaction between cognitive competency, emotions, and decision-<lb/>making: <lb/> Most previous studies indicated a relationship between cognition and decision-making [4, 28, 29]. Although these <lb/>studies demonstrated several aspects of cognitive competence (general intelligence, working memory, etc.) in <lb/>relation to decision-making, they were not able to show how the cognitive process worked when receiving <lb/>information. <lb/> A large number of former scholars have identified the relationship between emotions and decision-making [2, 25, <lb/>30, 31]. As mentioned above, in this approach, the outcomes of a decision may be detrimental or helpful, and they <lb/>are hard to control. As a result, the objective to consider is how to make decisions that are helpful rather than <lb/>harmful under the influence of emotions. <lb/> Numerous studies have demonstrated the relationship between emotions and cognition (e.g., attitude, intention, <lb/>etc.) [19, 20, 22, 32, 33]. These studies emphasized the effect of emotional components (such as emotional states, <lb/>fear, sadness, etc.) on attitudes or intentions. Nevertheless, attitudes or intentions were regarded as a low extent <lb/>of the cognitive process (e.g., remembering or knowing) that could make a decision (applying). In line with this, <lb/>Miles [34] indicated that TPB theory also assumed a behavioral approach in one&apos;s environment that induced <lb/>intentions and behaviors, ignoring individual processes and perceptions such as personality and outcome <lb/>expectations [35]. <lb/> Few studies have recognized the relationship between cognition, emotions, and decision-making [2, 36]. These <lb/>studies highlighted the role of cognitive factors in conjunction with the relationship between emotions and <lb/>decision-making [2]. However, cognition in these studies was limited to recognition (knowing) and recall <lb/>(remembering), as well as being absolutely inadequate for making critical choices (such as choosing a life partner <lb/>or implementing a company strategy) that required humans to analyze and evaluate [2]. <lb/>According to these findings, this study approaches decision-making by examining the relationship between cognitive <lb/>competency (thinking ability), emotions (recognizing emotions, using emotions, understanding emotions, and managing <lb/>emotions), and decision-making. The attributes of cognition here are the results of learning and life experiences <lb/>corresponding to the taxonomy of educational objectives [26]. The emotions here are the four-branch model of emotional <lb/>intelligence of Goleman [5] and Salovey [25]. The unique aspect of this approach is that the components of emotions <lb/>will go through a cognitive process from low to high (remembering to evaluating), and the outcome is an effective <lb/>decision. <lb/>The cognitive domain of the original taxonomy of educational objectives contains six levels structured in a hierarchy: <lb/>knowledge, understanding, application, analysis, synthesis, and evaluation. Then, the revision released in 2001 [37] by <lb/>Lorin Anderson and his associates, A Taxonomy for Learning, Teaching, and Assessing: A Revision of the Taxonomy <lb/>of Educational Objectives, received the most acceptance. As a result, objectives developed using the revised taxonomy <lb/>now explain cognitive processes rather than behavior. The updated Taxonomy of Educational Objectives includes the <lb/>following categories: remembering, understanding, applying, analyzing, evaluating, and creating. <lb/>Regarding the theory of emotional intelligence (EI), Goleman [5] provided five fundamental features or abilities, <lb/>including: knowing one&apos;s emotions; managing emotions; motivating oneself; recognizing emotions in others; and <lb/>handling relationships. Then, Goleman [38] continued to develop a performance-based EQ model to measure employee <lb/>emotional intelligence for identifying possibilities for development by making up five parts of the model, such as self-<lb/>awareness, self-regulation, social awareness, and relationship management. Besides, to evaluate one&apos;s emotion-related <lb/>abilities, Salovey &amp; Grewal [25] provided the four-branch model of emotional intelligence and its usefulness as a guiding <lb/>framework for emotion research. The four-branch model of emotional intelligence by Salovey &amp; Grewal [25] addresses <lb/>the following components: perceiving emotions, using emotions, understanding emotions, and managing emotions. <lb/>Recognizing the significant contributions of the theory of emotional intelligence [5] and ability model [25], this study <lb/>proposes four main components of emotional intelligence that will be examined in relation to thinking ability and <lb/>decision-making, including recognizing emotions (REC), using emotions (USE), understanding emotions (UND), and <lb/>managing emotions (MAN). <lb/>2-2-Hypothesis Development <lb/>Alkhatib [39] defined thinking as the ability to challenge and eventually improve acquired information to a higher <lb/>level of attainment. These processes begin with the stages of learning and retaining fundamental knowledge, which is a <lb/>basic precondition to assisting the human cognitive process in moving to a higher level of applying the information to <lb/>solve issues, matching the taxonomy of educational objectives [26]. This is the basic ability of the mind to receive <lb/>information from its surroundings and produce consciousness, cognition, and problem-solving. People may make their <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Emerging Science Journal | Vol. 8, No. 2 <lb/></note>

        <page>Page | 647 <lb/></page>

        <body>decisions based on the consequences of this cognitive process [11]. People can make decisions based on the outcomes <lb/>of this cognitive process [15, 40, 41]. Therefore, the first hypothesis is proposed: <lb/>H1: Thinking ability has a positive effect on decision-making. <lb/>Recognizing emotion is the capacity of humans to recognize their emotional states in order to aid in the processes of <lb/>analysis, thinking, judgement, and control, with emotions being used to lead to understanding and problem solutions [5, <lb/>42]. According to Mayer &amp; Salovey [42], emotion recognition enables people to recognize and input information from <lb/>their emotional systems, both verbally and nonverbally. These fundamental information-gathering mechanisms are <lb/>required for the later generation of emotional information for problem-solving. Typically, the physiological origins of <lb/>an emotion occur before a person is cognitively aware of the experience itself [5]. Based on the above arguments, the <lb/>proposed hypotheses are as follows: <lb/>H2: Recognizing emotions has a positive effect on decision-making. <lb/>H3: Recognizing emotions has a positive effect on thinking ability. <lb/>According to Yates and Zukowski [43], each individual can select or integrate various signals in a similar <lb/>circumstance. To reach a final choice, each individual must utilize emotions to analyze, interpret signals, and examine <lb/>all sides of the situation [11]. Besides, Schutte et al. [31] indicated that students had the capacity to employ emotions <lb/>intentionally to help the thinking process, considering, judging, and making decisions. Mellers et al. [44] concluded that <lb/>emotions people expected or had experienced as a result of their decisions were major predictors of their current and <lb/>future behavior. On that basis, the following hypotheses are proposed: <lb/>H4: Using emotions has a positive effect on decision-making. <lb/>H5: Using emotions has a positive effect on thinking ability. <lb/>Emotional understanding is defined as the ability to comprehend emotions and interior states, in addition to the <lb/>reasons for and development of emotions, to deduce the operating laws of emotions in oneself and others [31, 42]. <lb/>According to Goleman [5], understanding others&apos; feelings and accepting their perspective, as well as appreciating <lb/>variances in how others feel about things, are all important social skills. Acquiring knowledge to be an effective listener <lb/>and question-asker; distinguishing between what an individual says or does and your own responses and judgments; <lb/>being assertive rather than angry or passive; and learning the arts of cooperation, conflict resolution, and negotiating <lb/>compromise are all priorities [5]. Hence, the following hypotheses are proposed: <lb/>H6: Understanding emotions has a positive effect on decision-making. <lb/>H7: Understanding emotions has a positive effect on thinking ability. <lb/>Emotional management refers to students&apos; capacity to control and self-regulate their emotions in order to encourage <lb/>and assist the attainment of a certain work objective; it also refers to students&apos; ability to control or affect the emotions of <lb/>others [42]. In the study of Salovey &amp; Grewal [25], the capacity to regulate emotions in ourselves and others is referred <lb/>to as emotion management. Lerner and Shonk [45] investigated the impact of residual anger on decision-making and <lb/>discovered that decision-makers who had to be responsible for their judgments were better at regulating the consequences <lb/>of their anger. In other words, being aware of one&apos;s feelings and regulating them in difficult circumstances can allow <lb/>one to make more effective decisions. Thus, the following hypotheses are proposed: <lb/>H8: Managing emotions has a positive effect on decision-making. <lb/>H9: Managing emotions has a positive effect on thinking ability. <lb/>Based on the proposed hypotheses and research approach, the following research conceptual model was proposed: <lb/>Figure 1. Conceptual framework of emotional intelligence, thinking ability and decision-making (TK: Thinking ability; REC: <lb/>Recognizing emotions; USE: Using emotions; UND: Understanding emotions; MAN: Managing emotions; DM: Decision-making) <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Emerging Science Journal | Vol. 8, No. 2 <lb/></note>

        <page>Page | 648 <lb/></page>

        <body>3-Research Methodology <lb/>3-1-Respondents and Procedures <lb/>As the approach of this study was to examine a model constructed from the ability model by Salovey &amp; Grewal [25], <lb/>the theory of emotional intelligence by Goleman [5], and the taxonomy of educational objectives by Bloom et al. [26], <lb/>a deductive approach was deemed most appropriate for method creation [46]. The technique of this study was separated <lb/>into two parts, which incorporate qualitative and quantitative methods. <lb/>Phase 1 consisted of qualitative research to construct the theoretical framework as well as the measuring tools based <lb/>on the literature review. The assessment scales were developed in collaboration with a group of focus specialists (6 <lb/>participants, including 5 doctors and 1 PhD student in this subject). The authors performed a survey with 30 university <lb/>students to test the clarity and understanding of questions after they were translated into Vietnamese by a Bachelor of <lb/>English, then changed based on the input and used structured questionnaires for the main study (Appendix I). <lb/>In Phase 2 (the quantitative research), to prevent common method bias, Cronbach&apos;s alpha and the SPSS programme <lb/>were used to analyse the reliability and validity of all items (presented in part 3-2-Measurement Instruments). The <lb/>collinearity test was then performed, and all VIF values were less than 3.3 [47]. As a result, the common method bias <lb/>was avoided. After checking the common method bias, the assessment of the measurement model will be conducted <lb/>(convergent validity, composite reliability, and discriminant validity) following the conditions of Hair et al. [48] by <lb/>SmartPLS software. The authors next propose using Partial Least Squares Structural Equation Modelling (PLS-SEM) to <lb/>evaluate the structural model and test hypotheses because it pertains to analysing the intricate relationships between the <lb/>numerous indirect and direct consequences [48]. <lb/>Regarding the respondents in the main study, the authors propose that the study focuses on university students due to <lb/>the consistency in some characteristics (such as age, knowledge, skills, life experience, and source of income primarily <lb/>dependent on the family due to only graduating from high school). Furthermore, the respondents were chosen in part <lb/>using the Invitro approach, which allows for the simple elimination of additional bias variables when surveying a large <lb/>number of samples that fit the overall research parameters. A total of 2000 questionnaires were issued at random to <lb/>university students in Ho Chi Minh City through Google Forms, and 620 responses were collected, of which 547 were <lb/>valid and utilized in the study. <lb/>3-2-Measurement Instruments <lb/>The construct measurement scales of this study were developed from the literature. Following the results after testing <lb/>reliability, the scales to measure thinking ability (seven items, α = 0.895) were adapted from the taxonomy of educational <lb/>objectives [26]. The scales to measure recognizing emotions (seven items, α = 0.828), using emotions (six items, α = <lb/>0.835), understanding emotions (six items, α = 0.822), and managing emotions (six items, α = 0.833) were adapted from <lb/>Goleman [5] and Salovey &amp; Grewal [25]. The scales to measure decision-making (seven items, α = 0.838) were adapted <lb/>from Carroll &amp; Johnson [27] and Elwyn &amp; Miron-Shatz [18]. The responses ranged from strongly disagree (1) to strongly <lb/>agree (5) on a five-point Likert scale. A detailed description of the measurement instrument is shown in Appendix I. <lb/>4-Research Results <lb/>4-1-Respondent Profile <lb/>The brief respondent profile for this study is presented in Table 1. Most respondents were female (82.1%) and studied <lb/>for 1 year (58.7%). Regarding the place of birth and university, many students came from Regions 2, 3, and 4 (78.2%), <lb/>and all studied at HUB (Ho Chi Minh University of Banking), accounting for 100%. <lb/>Table 1. Demographic characteristics <lb/>Indicator <lb/>Value <lb/>N/647 Percentage <lb/>Gender <lb/>Female <lb/>449 <lb/>82.1 <lb/>Male <lb/>98 <lb/>17.9 <lb/>Student <lb/>Freshman <lb/>321 <lb/>58.7 <lb/>Sophomore <lb/>112 <lb/>20.5 <lb/>Junior <lb/>76 <lb/>13.9 <lb/>Senior <lb/>36 <lb/>6.6 <lb/>Graduate student <lb/>2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>Place of birth <lb/>Region 1 <lb/>119 <lb/>21.8 <lb/>Region 2 <lb/>260 <lb/>47.5 <lb/>Region 3 <lb/>130 <lb/>23.8 <lb/>Region 4 <lb/>38 <lb/>6.9 <lb/>University <lb/>HUB <lb/>547 <lb/>100 <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Emerging Science Journal | Vol. 8, No. 2 <lb/></note>

        <page>Page | 649 <lb/></page>

        <body>4-2-Assessment of the Measurement Model <lb/>In terms of variable reliability and validity, Cronbach&apos;s Alpha and composite reliability (0.7) standards [49] were <lb/>used. The minimum α and CR values were 0.801 and 0.871, respectively. After evaluating the measurement model, the <lb/>initial scales with 39 items have been eliminated with 10 items (REC1, REC2, REC7, USE1, UND1, MAN4, MAN5, <lb/>DM1, DM3, DM5) due to the outer loading &lt; 0.7. As a result, 29 components were used in the structural model analysis <lb/>(Table 2). <lb/>Table 2. Outer loadings, reliability and convergent validity <lb/>Variables <lb/>Items <lb/>Loading <lb/>α <lb/>CR <lb/>AVE <lb/>Thinking ability <lb/>TK1 <lb/>0.716 <lb/>0.896 0.919 0.619 <lb/>TK2 <lb/>0.749 <lb/>TK3 <lb/>0.832 <lb/>TK4 <lb/>0.839 <lb/>TK5 <lb/>0.824 <lb/>TK6 <lb/>0.718 <lb/>TK7 <lb/>0.823 <lb/>Recognizing emotions <lb/>REC3 <lb/>0.832 <lb/>0.801 0.871 0.628 <lb/>REC4 <lb/>0.817 <lb/>REC5 <lb/>0.788 <lb/>REC6 <lb/>0.730 <lb/>Using emotions <lb/>USE2 <lb/>0.785 <lb/>0.820 0.874 0.581 <lb/>USE3 <lb/>0.765 <lb/>USE4 <lb/>0.762 <lb/>USE5 <lb/>0.768 <lb/>USE6 <lb/>0.733 <lb/>Managing emotions <lb/>MAN1 <lb/>0.812 <lb/>0.839 0.892 0.675 <lb/>MAN2 <lb/>0.840 <lb/>MAN3 <lb/>0.844 <lb/>MAN6 <lb/>0.788 <lb/>Understanding emotions <lb/>UND2 <lb/>0.790 <lb/>0.835 0.884 0.603 <lb/>UND3 <lb/>0.737 <lb/>UND4 <lb/>0.760 <lb/>UND5 <lb/>0.809 <lb/>UND6 <lb/>0.784 <lb/>Decision-making <lb/>DM2 <lb/>0.730 <lb/>0.806 0.873 0.633 <lb/>DN4 <lb/>0.819 <lb/>DM6 <lb/>0.782 <lb/>DM7 <lb/>0.846 <lb/>Related to convergent validity, the threshold of the average variance extracted (0.5) and the minimum outer loadings <lb/>(0.6) were commonly applied [50, 51]. In this study, the factor loadings were higher than 0.7 and the AVE values were <lb/>above 0.5; hence, the convergent validity was assured (Table 2). <lb/>In addition, the Fornell-Larcker criterion and the Heterotrait-Monotrait ratio (HTMT) were used to examine the <lb/>measurement model&apos;s discriminant validity. Garson [52] states that the HTMT number should be less than 1. Therefore, <lb/>this study&apos;s discriminant validity was assured, and all values were less than one (Table 3). <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Emerging Science Journal | Vol. 8, No. 2 <lb/></note>

        <page>Page | 650 <lb/></page>

        <body>Table 3. Heterotrait-monotrait ratio (HTMT) -Matrix <lb/>Items <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>1. DM <lb/>2. MAN 0.794 <lb/>3. REC <lb/>0.653 0.649 <lb/>4. TK <lb/>0.720 0.614 0.715 <lb/>5. UND 0.762 0.766 0.788 0.771 <lb/>6. USE <lb/>0.688 0.692 0.767 0.782 0.824 <lb/>4-3-Assessment of the Structural Model <lb/>Regarding the hypothesis testing and structural directions, the findings are shown in Table 4. Most path coefficients <lb/>are found to have significant levels of 1%, except for the relationships between managing emotions  thinking ability, <lb/>recognizing emotions  decision-making, and using emotions  decision-making. Therefore, all the hypotheses will <lb/>be accepted apart from H2, H4, and H9. Particularly, H1, H3, H5, H6, H7, and H8 were accepted with a significant level <lb/>of 1%. Hence, the positive influences of thinking ability on decision-making (β = 0.263), recognizing emotions on <lb/>thinking ability (β = 0.193), using emotions on thinking ability (β =0.313), understanding emotions on decision-making <lb/>(β = 0.155), understanding emotions on thinking ability (β = 0.289), and managing emotions on decision-making (β = <lb/>0.361) were confirmed. <lb/>Table 4. Hypothesized structural paths <lb/>Hypotheses <lb/>Path relationships <lb/>Estimate <lb/>SD <lb/>T -value P value <lb/>Result <lb/>H1 <lb/>Thinking ability  Decision-making <lb/>0.263 <lb/>0.047 <lb/>5.598* <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Accepted <lb/>H2 <lb/>Recognizing emotions  Decision-making <lb/>0.050 <lb/>0.047 <lb/>1.056 <lb/>0.291 <lb/>Rejected <lb/>H3 <lb/>Recognizing emotions  Thinking ability <lb/>0.193 <lb/>0.043 <lb/>4.447* <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Accepted <lb/>H4 <lb/>Using emotions  Decision-making <lb/>0.044 <lb/>0.052 <lb/>0.852 <lb/>0.394 <lb/>Rejected <lb/>H5 <lb/>Using emotions  Thinking ability <lb/>0.313 <lb/>0.050 <lb/>6.254* <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Accepted <lb/>H6 <lb/>Understanding emotions Decision-making <lb/>0.155 <lb/>0.053 <lb/>2.924 <lb/>0.003 <lb/>Accepted <lb/>H7 <lb/>Understanding emotions Thinking ability <lb/>0.289 <lb/>0.053 <lb/>5.442* <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Accepted <lb/>H8 <lb/>Managing emotions  Decision-making <lb/>0.361 <lb/>0.043 <lb/>8.416* <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Accepted <lb/>H9 <lb/>Managing emotions  Thinking ability <lb/>0.065 <lb/>0.044 <lb/>1.499 <lb/>0.134 <lb/>Rejected <lb/>R 2 <lb/>Decision-making = 0.548, R 2 <lb/>Thinking ability = 0.555 <lb/>Note: SD = standard deviation; *significant at p&lt;0.01; **significant at p&lt;0.05; ns = not significant. <lb/>In terms of the mediating role of thinking ability, the findings indicated that thinking ability mediated the relationship <lb/>between understanding emotions and decision-making; recognizing emotions and decision-making; and using emotions <lb/>and decision-making (see Table 5). Particularly, the p-values of UND -&gt; TK -&gt; DM, REC -&gt; TK -&gt; DM, and USE -&gt; <lb/>TK -&gt;DM were under 1%. The total impacts of understanding emotions on decision-making, recognizing emotions and <lb/>decision-making, and using emotions and decision-making via the mediating role of thinking ability were 0.076, 0.051, <lb/>and 0.082, respectively. Additionally, the mediating effect of thinking ability on managing emotions and decision-<lb/>making was rejected because the p-value was higher than 10% (0.166). <lb/>Table 5. The results of indirect effects <lb/>Relationships <lb/>Estimate <lb/>SD <lb/>T -value P value <lb/>Result <lb/>MAN  TK  DM <lb/>0.017 <lb/>0.012 <lb/>1.386 <lb/>0.166 <lb/>Rejected <lb/>UND  TK  DM <lb/>0.076 <lb/>0.019 <lb/>3.923* <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Accepted <lb/>REC  TK  DM <lb/>0.051 <lb/>0.015 <lb/>3.443* <lb/>0.001 <lb/>Accepted <lb/>USE  TK  DM <lb/>0.082 <lb/>0.019 <lb/>4.273* <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Accepted <lb/>Note: SD = standard deviation; *significant at p&lt;0.01; **significant at p&lt;0.05; ns = not significant. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Emerging Science Journal | Vol. 8, No. 2 <lb/></note>

        <page>Page | 651 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 2. The final path model <lb/>5-Discussion <lb/>As mentioned above, humans are still at the center of decision-making, but a desire for efficient and high-quality <lb/>decisions requires much cognitive effort. The findings of this study demonstrated the importance of explaining the <lb/>relationship between thinking ability, emotional intelligence, and decision-making. In other words, thinking ability is <lb/>what people can learn and gain during the learning and working process, then control emotional stages before making <lb/>effective decisions. This study also offers a holistic research model to explain decision-making under the influence of <lb/>both emotions and cognition (R 2 <lb/>Decision-making = 0.548). This emphasizes the significant roles of both emotional and <lb/>rational aspects when making decisions and is consistent with Simon [53] and Hess and Bacigalupo [6] ideas that emotion <lb/>and rationality are inexorably interconnected and that emotional intelligence may function as the required connection <lb/>between the two. <lb/>In terms of the direct impacts of emotions on decision-making and thinking ability, understanding and managing <lb/>emotions both have greatly positive impacts on decision-making; however, recognizing and using emotions have no <lb/>impacts on decision-making (p &gt; 0.1). Similarly, recognizing, using, and understanding emotions have strongly positive <lb/>effects on thinking ability; in contrast, managing emotions has no effect on thinking ability (p&gt;0.1). Although <lb/>recognizing and using emotions has no impact on decision-making, via thinking ability, recognizing and using emotions <lb/>has positive effects on decision-making. As a result, the mediating role of thinking ability underlines that the research <lb/>approach is entirely feasible and conveys robust justification for the decision-making model, particularly through the <lb/>cognitive process of coming up with effective and helpful decisions (R 2 <lb/>Thinking ability = 0.555). Hence, the findings of this <lb/>study not only extend significant contributions to theoretical material but also offer the foundation for practical <lb/>implications. <lb/>Related to the contributions to theoretical material, this study opens up a novel research approach to decision-making <lb/>theories in which the components of emotions are reaffirmed for their critical roles in decision-making and is consistent <lb/>with the results of previous studies [5, 25, 36]. Besides, the combination of emotions and thinking ability refers to the <lb/>cognitive process before making decisions, in which the components of emotions have gone through a cognitive process <lb/>from low to high (remembering to evaluating). Therefore, the expected outcomes would be easily predicted and brought <lb/>to the benefit. Compared to the previous studies, these results match the conclusions of [2, 4] regarding the recognition <lb/>of the roles of emotions and cognition in shaping decision-making behavior. Nevertheless, Bruch &amp; Feinberg [2] insisted <lb/>that most previous models, for example, were built to capture mundane decisions like grocery shopping, where qualities <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Emerging Science Journal | Vol. 8, No. 2 <lb/></note>

        <page>Page | 652 <lb/></page>

        <body>were known, options were ready, and stakes were modest. Therefore, this study distinguished itself from earlier research <lb/>by demonstrating and developing a cognitive competency scale to maximize the benefits of decision-making based on <lb/>low-level cognitive processes compared to high-level cognitive processes. <lb/>On the other hand, as the initial aim was to develop a scale to assess cognitive competency, the results of this research <lb/>have proven not only the stable operation but also the high meeting levels of requirements of a cognitive measurement <lb/>scale (such as reliability, convergence, and discriminant validity). Additionally, almost all existing behavioral theories <lb/>or models have taken into account both emotional and cognitive aspects involved in the decision-making process; <lb/>however, as mentioned, most cognitive scales in behavioral theories and models only indicate a low cognitive level (e.g., <lb/>remembering, knowing, or applying), such as attitudes, intentions, perceived usefulness, etc. Although the research is <lb/>only at the beginning of building the relationship between emotions, thinking ability, and decision-making through the <lb/>Invitro method, this will be an ideal theoretical model for future research. Moreover, the process of developing and <lb/>perfecting this scale will be continued, with all cognitive attributes being integrated and considered in a specific context <lb/>to evaluate the scale&apos;s stability. <lb/>In addition to the considerable theoretical contributions, the practical contributions have been recognized. In <lb/>conjunction with the significant positive effects of understanding and managing emotions on decision-making, several <lb/>management implications were proposed: <lb/> Develop training plans and intervention measures to help employees understand their own emotions as well as <lb/>manage their own emotions in making decisions. <lb/> Improve knowledge-sharing activities for managing emotions, such as how to deal with depression as well as <lb/>stress at work and in life. <lb/> Build up a friendly working environment and support opportunities for individuals to express their strengths and <lb/>weaknesses to receive sharing from colleagues and the community. <lb/>Regarding the positive impacts of recognizing, using, and understanding emotions on thinking ability as well as <lb/>thinking ability on decision-making, the following practical implications were proposed: <lb/> Target input information to a specific audience (e.g., students, employees, consumers, smokers) in order to <lb/>improve cognitive competency and optimize judgments. <lb/> Pay attention to aspects related to personal self-perception as well as the influence of relationships around the <lb/>subjects to improve their thinking ability in the decision-making process. <lb/> Be flexible in the way of conveying and sharing information related to emotional aspects, as well as always <lb/>considering and evaluating emotional situations that need to be addressed related to relationships between <lb/>individuals and organizations. <lb/>Listen to the individuals frequently and encourage them to reveal periods in which they are unable to manage or <lb/>understand their own emotions, then review and offer appropriate messages to this audience (e.g., victims, smokers, <lb/>etc.). <lb/>6-Conclusion <lb/>Based on the findings, this study has proved the great significance of examining the interaction between emotions, <lb/>rationality, and the decision-making process. The role of cognitive ability (e.g., thinking ability) is extremely critical in <lb/>making a decision. Whether emotional factors may have a direct impact on decision-making or not, when going through <lb/>the thinking process, they all influence decision-making. The research findings also addressed all of the objectives that <lb/>were initially set out. First, the positive effects of emotional and rational aspects on decision-making were confirmed, <lb/>both directly and indirectly. Second, the significant positive effects of understanding and managing emotions on <lb/>decision-making provide evidence for the components of emotions to make effective and useful decisions. Third, this <lb/>study is successful in developing a new set of scales to assess cognitive competency (thinking ability) in an operational <lb/>setting and any specific sector to better provide high-quality decisions. Finally, this study has demonstrated a unique and <lb/>novel research approach through the relationship between emotions, cognition, and decision-making, in which the <lb/>components of emotions undergo a cognitive process from low to high levels. <lb/>On the other hand, this study has faced certain limitations. First, although current research protocols were strictly <lb/>followed, this was a cross-sectional study, so some biases may have occurred. Second, even though the extent of the <lb/>explanation of the model is quite good for an exploratory study, there will be other factors affecting the variables in the <lb/>model that have not yet been identified. This is also an interesting direction for future research. Third, the attributes of <lb/>cognition have not yet been fully exploited in this study, so future research can follow this direction to further perfect <lb/>the cognitive ability scale. Finally, since this research model is still in the early stages of research, using the Invitro <lb/>method related to respondents, future studies can apply this model to specific contexts to consider the stability of the <lb/>model. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Emerging Science Journal | Vol. 8, No. 2 <lb/></note>

        <page>Page | 653 <lb/></page>

        <div type="annex">7-Declarations <lb/></div>

        <div type="contribution">7-1-Author Contributions <lb/>T.D.T. and T.V.P. contributed to the design and implementation of the research, to the analysis of the results and to <lb/>the writing of the manuscript. All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

        <div type="availability">7-2-Data Availability Statement <lb/>The data presented in this study are available on request from the corresponding author. <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">7-3-Funding <lb/>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">7-4-Institutional Review Board Statement <lb/>Not applicable. <lb/>7-5-Informed Consent Statement <lb/>Informed consent was obtained from all subjects involved in the study. <lb/></div>

        <div type="conflict">7-6-Conflicts of Interest <lb/>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interest regarding the publication of this manuscript. In addition, the <lb/>ethical issues, including plagiarism, informed consent, misconduct, data fabrication and/or falsification, double <lb/>publication and/or submission, and redundancies have been completely observed by the authors. <lb/></div>

        <listBibl>8-References <lb/>[1] Noble, S. M., Mende, M., Grewal, D., &amp; Parasuraman, A. (2022). The Fifth Industrial Revolution: How Harmonious Human-<lb/>Machine Collaboration is Triggering a Retail and Service [R]evolution. Journal of Retailing, 98(2), 199-208. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.jretai.2022.04.003. <lb/>[2] Bruch, E., &amp; Feinberg, F. (2017). Decision-making processes in social contexts. Annual Review of Sociology, 43, 207-227. <lb/>doi:10.1146/annurev-soc-060116-053622. <lb/>[3] Sahu, A. K., Padhy, R. K., &amp; Dhir, A. (2020). Envisioning the future of behavioral decision-making: A systematic literature review <lb/>of behavioral reasoning theory. Australasian Marketing Journal, 28(4), 145-159. doi:10.1016/j.ausmj.2020.05.001. <lb/>[4] Skagerlund, K., Forsblad, M., Tinghög, G., &amp; Västfjäll, D. (2022). Decision-making competence and cognitive abilities: Which <lb/>abilities matter? Journal of Behavioral Decision Making, 35(1), 2242. doi:10.1002/bdm.2242. <lb/>[5] Goleman, D. (1995). Emotional Intelligence Bantam Books. Bantam, New York, United States. <lb/>[6] Hess, J. D., &amp; Bacigalupo, A. C. (2011). Enhancing decisions and decision-making processes through the application of emotional <lb/>intelligence skills. Management Decision, 49(5), 710-721. doi:10.1108/00251741111130805. <lb/>[7] Bradberry, T., &amp; Greaves, J. (2003). Emotional Intelligence Quick book. TalentSmart, San Diego, United States. <lb/>[8] Newell, A., &amp; Simon, H. A. (1972). Human problem solving. Prentice-hall, Englewood Cliffs, United States. <lb/>[9] Petrides, K. V., Pita, R., &amp; Kokkinaki, F. (2007). The location of trait emotional intelligence in personality factor space. British <lb/>Journal of Psychology, 98(2), 273-289. doi:10.1348/000712606X120618. <lb/>[10] Salovey, P., &amp; Mayer, J. D. (1990). Emotional Intelligence. Imagination, Cognition and Personality, 9(3), 185-211. <lb/>doi:10.2190/dugg-p24e-52wk-6cdg. <lb/>[11] Sevdalis, N., Petrides, K. V., &amp; Harvey, N. (2007). Trait emotional intelligence and decision-related emotions. Personality and <lb/>Individual Differences, 42(7), 1347-1358. doi:10.1016/j.paid.2006.10.012. <lb/>[12] Slovic, P., Finucane, M. L., Peters, E., &amp; MacGregor, D. G. (2013). Risk as analysis and risk as feelings: Some thoughts about <lb/>affect, reason, risk and rationality. Routledge, London, United Kingdom. <lb/>[13] George, J. M., &amp; Dane, E. (2016). Affect, emotion, and decision making. Organizational Behavior and Human Decision <lb/>Processes, 136, 47-55. doi:10.1016/j.obhdp.2016.06.004. <lb/>[14] Lerner, J. S., Li, Y., Valdesolo, P., &amp; Kassam, K. S. (2015). Emotion and decision making. Annual Review of Psychology, 66, <lb/>799-823. doi:10.1146/annurev-psych-010213-115043. <lb/>[15] Haines, G. H., Howard, J. A., &amp; Sheth, J. N. (1970). The Theory of Buyer Behavior. Journal of the American Statistical <lb/>Association, 65(331), 1406. doi:10.2307/2284311. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="headnote">Emerging Science Journal | Vol. 8, No. 2 <lb/></note>

        <page>Page | 654 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>[16] Taleb, N. N. (2007). The black swan: The impact of the highly improbable. Random House, New York, United States. <lb/>[17] Klaczynski, P. A., Byrnes, J. P., &amp; Jacobs, J. E. (2001). Introduction to the special issue: The development of decision making. <lb/>Journal of Applied Developmental Psychology, 22(3), 225-236. doi:10.1016/S0193-3973(01)00081-8. <lb/>[18] Elwyn, G., &amp; Miron-Shatz, T. (2010). Deliberation before determination: The definition and evaluation of good decision making. <lb/>Health Expectations, 13(2), 139-147. doi:10.1111/j.1369-7625.2009.00572.x. <lb/>[19] Al Amin, M. (2022). The Influence of Psychological, Situational and the Interactive Technological Feedback-Related Variables <lb/>on Customers&apos; Technology Adoption to Use Online Shopping Applications. Journal of Global Marketing, 35(5), 384-407. <lb/>doi:10.1080/08911762.2022.2051157. <lb/>[20] Han, Z. M., Huang, C. Q., Yu, J. H., &amp; Tsai, C. C. (2021). Identifying patterns of epistemic emotions with respect to interactions <lb/>in massive online open courses using deep learning and social network analysis. Computers in Human Behavior, 122, 106843. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.chb.2021.106843. <lb/>[21] Su, Z., Li, Y., Liu, S., Zhao, L., Liu, Z., &amp; Peng, X. (2022). Explore the interrelationship of cognition, emotion and interaction <lb/>when learners engage in online discussion. 2022 International Conference on Intelligent Education and Intelligent Research <lb/>(IEIR), 94-100. doi:10.1109/IEIR56323.2022.10050057. <lb/>[22] Tan, W. K., &amp; Chen, P. Y. (2023). Flash sales: how consumers&apos; emotional responses to negative word-of-mouth affect <lb/>diagnosticity and purchase intentions. Service Business, 17(4), 1001-1024. doi:10.1007/s11628-023-00549-5. <lb/>[23] Atav, G., Chatterjee, S., &amp; Roy, R. (2021). To forgive or retaliate? How regulatory fit affects emotional reactions and repurchase <lb/>decisions following product failures. Journal of Consumer Marketing, 38(4), 397-409. doi:10.1108/JCM-05-2020-3843. <lb/>[24] Tran, T. D. (2023). Gen Z&apos;s Intention to Repurchase Food Online in The Context of a Crisis: A Case Study in Vietnam Under <lb/>COVID-19. In Journal of Distribution Science, 21(12), 23-34. <lb/>[25] Salovey, P., &amp; Grewal, D. (2005). The science of emotional intelligence. Current Directions in Psychological Science, 14(6), <lb/>281-285. doi:10.1111/j.0963-7214.2005.00381.x. <lb/>[26] Bloom, B. S., Engelhart, M. D., Furst, E. J., Hill, W. H., &amp; Krathwohl, D. R. (1956). Handbook I: cognitive domain. Addison-<lb/>Wesley Longman Ltd, Massachusetts, United States. <lb/>[27] Carroll, J. S., &amp; Johnson, E. J. (1990). Decision research: A field guide. Sage Publications, Inc, Washington, United States. <lb/>[28] George, J. M. (2007). 9 Creativity in Organizations. Academy of Management Annals, 1(1), 439-477. doi:10.5465/078559814. <lb/>[29] Gigerenzer, G. (2004). Fast and Frugal Heuristics: The Tools of Bounded Rationality. Blackwell Handbook of Judgment and <lb/>Decision Making, John Wiley &amp; Sons, Hoboken, United States. doi:10.1002/9780470752937.ch4. <lb/>[30] Li, M., Ge, M., Zhao, H., &amp; An, Z. (2022). Modeling and Analysis of Learners&apos; Emotions and Behaviors Based on Online Forum <lb/>Texts. Computational Intelligence and Neuroscience, 2022. doi:10.1155/2022/9696422. <lb/>[31] Schutte, N. S., Malouff, J. M., Hall, L. E., Haggerty, D. J., Cooper, J. T., Golden, C. J., &amp; Dornheim, L. (1998). Development <lb/>and validation of a measure of emotional intelligence. Personality and Individual Differences, 25(2), 167-177. <lb/>doi:10.1016/S0191-8869(98)00001-4. <lb/>[32] Liu, S., Liu, S., Liu, Z., Peng, X., &amp; Yang, Z. (2022). Automated detection of emotional and cognitive engagement in MOOC <lb/>discussions to predict learning achievement. Computers and Education, 181, 104461. doi:10.1016/j.compedu.2022.104461. <lb/>[33] Sakhaei, H., Biloria, N., &amp; Azizmohammad Looha, M. (2022). Spatial stimuli in films: Uncovering the relationship between <lb/>cognitive emotion and perceived environmental quality. Frontiers in Psychology, 13, 940882. doi:10.3389/fpsyg.2022.940882. <lb/>[34] Miles, J. A. (2012). Management and organization theory: A Jossey-Bass reader. Jossey-Bass, Hoboken, United States. <lb/>[35] Bandura, A. (2003). Social cognitive theory for personal and social change by enabling media. Entertainment-education and <lb/>social change, Routledge, Milton Park, United Kingdom. <lb/>[36] Goyal, D., &amp; Sharma, U. (2022). Emotion, Cognition, and COVID-19: A Study Exploring the Association Between Fear of <lb/>COVID-19 Intolerance of Uncertainty and Decision-Making in Indian Adolescents. Journal of Indian Association for Child and <lb/>Adolescent Mental Health, 18(1), 92-99. doi:10.1177/09731342221096479. <lb/>[37] [Mullakhmetov, K. (2016). Control in the system of managerial decisions procedures: A conceptual view. Problems and <lb/>Perspectives in Management, 14(3), 203-215. doi:10.21511/ppm.14(3-1).2016.07. <lb/>[38] Goleman, D. (2001). An EI-based theory of performance. The emotionally intelligent workplace: How to select for, measure, <lb/>and improve emotional intelligence in individuals, groups, and organizations. Jossey-Bass, Hoboken, United States. <lb/>[39] Alkhatib, O. J. (2019). A Framework for Implementing Higher-Order Thinking Skills (Problem-Solving, Critical Thinking, <lb/>Creative Thinking, and Decision-Making) in Engineering &amp; Humanities. 2019 Advances in Science and Engineering <lb/>Technology International Conferences (ASET). doi:10.1109/icaset.2019.8714232. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="headnote">Emerging Science Journal | Vol. 8, No. 2 <lb/></note>

        <page>Page | 655 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>[40] Roberts, J. H., &amp; Lattin, J. M. (1991). Development and Testing of a Model of Consideration Set Composition. Journal of <lb/>Marketing Research, 28(4), 429-440. doi:10.1177/002224379102800405. <lb/>[41] [39]Roberts, J. H., &amp; Lattin, J. M. (1997). Consideration: Review of Research and Prospects for Future Insights. Journal of <lb/>Marketing Research, 34(3), 406-410. doi:10.1177/002224379703400309. <lb/>[42] Salovey, P., &amp; Sluyter, D. (1997). Emotional Development and Emotional Intelligence. Basic Books, New York, United States. <lb/>[43] Yates, J. F., &amp; Zukowski, L. G. (1976). Characterization of ambiguity in decision making. Behavioral Science, 21(1), 19-25. <lb/>doi:10.1002/bs.3830210104. <lb/>[44] Mellers, B., Schwartz, A., &amp; Ritov, I. (1999). Emotion-based choice. Journal of Experimental Psychology: General, 128(3), 332-<lb/>345. doi:10.1037/0096-3445.128.3.332. <lb/>[45] Lerner, J. S., &amp; Shonk, K. (2010). How anger poisons decision making. Harvard Business Review, 88(9), 26. <lb/>[46] Persson, J. (2010). Misconceptions of positivism and five unnecessary science theoretic mistakes they bring in their train. <lb/>International Journal of Nursing Studies, 47(5), 651-661. doi:10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2009.12.009. <lb/>[47] Kock, N., &amp; Lynn, G. S. (2012). Lateral collinearity and misleading results in variance-based SEM: An illustration and <lb/>recommendations. Journal of the Association for Information Systems, 13(7), 546-580. doi:10.17705/1jais.00302. <lb/>[48] Hair, J. F., Hult, G. T. M., Ringle, C. M., Sarstedt, M., Danks, N. P., &amp; Ray, S. (2021). Partial Least Squares Structural Equation <lb/>Modeling (PLS-SEM) Using R. Classroom Companion: Business. Springer International Publishing, New York, United States. <lb/>doi:10.1007/978-3-030-80519-7. <lb/>[49] Hair Jr., J. F., Gabriel, M. L. D. da S., &amp; Patel, V. K. (2014). Covariance-Based Structural Equation Modeling (CB-SEM) with <lb/>AMOS: Guidance on its application as a Marketing Research Tool. Revista Brasileira de Marketing, 13(2), 44-55. <lb/>doi:10.5585/remark.v13i2.2718. (In Portuguese). <lb/>[50] Chin, W. W., Marcelin, B. L., &amp; Newsted, P. R. (2003). A partial least squares latent variable modeling approach for measuring <lb/>interaction effects: Results from a Monte Carlo simulation study and an electronic-mail emotion/adoption study. Information <lb/>Systems Research, 14(2), 189-217. doi:10.1287/isre.14.2.189.16018. <lb/>[51] Hair, J. F., Risher, J. J., Sarstedt, M., &amp; Ringle, C. M. (2019). When to use and how to report the results of PLS-SEM. European <lb/>Business Review, 31(1), 2-24. doi:10.1108/EBR-11-2018-0203. <lb/>[52] Garson, G. D. (2016). Partial Least Squares: Regression and Structural Equation Models. Statistical Associates Publishers, Fargo, <lb/>United States. <lb/>[53] Simon, H. A. (1967). Motivational and Emotional Controls of Cognition. Psychological Review, 74(1), 29-39. <lb/>doi:10.1037/h0024127. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="headnote">Emerging Science Journal | Vol. 8, No. 2 <lb/></note>

        <page>Page | 656 <lb/></page>

        <div type="annex">Appendix I <lb/>Table A-1. A brief report of discussion questions with experts&apos; and students&apos; groups <lb/>Discussion questions with experts <lb/>Experts&apos; answers <lb/>Results <lb/>1. Do the indicators of the Thinking ability scale <lb/>reasonably represent the nature of self-awareness of <lb/>Thinking ability? In your opinion, do you need to add, <lb/>remove, or adjust any indicators? <lb/>Need to adjust: <lb/>TK1: When asked to name the events and phenomena <lb/>that occurred in a story that was just told/heard, I have <lb/>the ability to remember and recount the details I heard. <lb/>TK3: I always have a good mind-set when <lb/>approaching problem solving. <lb/>Add 2 ideas: <lb/>TK1: I always remember well and can restate <lb/>events that have just happened. <lb/>TK3: I always have good logical thinking when <lb/>approaching problem solving <lb/>2. In your opinion, is it reasonable to divide emotional <lb/>intelligence into 4 groups? <lb/>-REC: Recognizing emotions; <lb/>-USE: Using emotions; <lb/>-UND: Understanding emotions; <lb/>-MAN: Managing emotions. <lb/>No idea <lb/>3. Do the indicators of the REC -Recognizing emotions <lb/>scale reasonably represent the nature of self-awareness of <lb/>Recognizing emotions? In your opinion, do any indicators <lb/>need to be added, removed or adjusted? <lb/>Need to adjust: <lb/>REC1: When my feelings towards work change (from <lb/>excitement to boredom or vice versa...), I know clearly <lb/>why my feelings change like that. <lb/>Add 1 idea: <lb/>REC1: When my feelings towards work change <lb/>(from excitement to boredom or vice versa...), I <lb/>clearly understand the reason for the change. <lb/>4. Do the indicators of the USE-Using emotions scale <lb/>reasonably represent the nature of self-awareness of Using <lb/>emotions? In your opinion, do any indicators need to be <lb/>added, removed or adjusted? <lb/>No idea <lb/>5. Do the indicators of the UND-Understanding emotions <lb/>scale reasonably represent the nature of self-awareness of <lb/>Understanding emotions? In your opinion, do any <lb/>indicators need to be added, removed, or adjusted? <lb/>Need to adjust: <lb/>UND6: I often help others feel better when they are in <lb/>a bad mood (sad/lonely...) <lb/>Add 1 idea: <lb/>UND6: I often help others feel more secure <lb/>when they are in a bad mood (sad/lonely...) <lb/>6. I Do the indicators of the MAN-Managing emotions <lb/>scale reasonably represent the nature of self-awareness of <lb/>Managing emotions? In your opinion, do any indicators <lb/>need to be added, removed, or adjusted? <lb/>No idea <lb/>7. In your opinion, do the indicators of the DM-Decision-<lb/>making scale reasonably represent the nature of self-<lb/>awareness of the benefits of Decision-making? In your <lb/>opinion, do you need to add, remove, or adjust any <lb/>indicators? <lb/>Need to adjust: <lb/>DM3: I decided because I got extra training points <lb/>during my participation <lb/>Add 1 idea: <lb/>DM3: I decided to participate because I got <lb/>extra training points <lb/>8. According to you, the proposed research model <lb/>includes: decision-making (a dependent variable); <lb/>thinking ability (a mediating variable); and four <lb/>independent variables: REC: Emotions Recognition; <lb/>USE: Using Emotions; UND: Understanding Emotions; <lb/>MAN: Managing Emotions. Is this model meaningful and <lb/>reasonable? In your opinion, do you need to add, remove, <lb/>or adjust any indicators? <lb/>No idea <lb/>Discussion questions with a group of 30 <lb/>students <lb/>Students&apos; answers <lb/>Results <lb/>1. In your opinion, are there any indicators in this survey <lb/>questionnaire that cause confusion or confusion? If so, <lb/>how should it be adjusted? <lb/>Adjust the statement: <lb/>DM1: I decided because there was an influencer. <lb/>Adjust: <lb/>DM1: I make decisions because of other <lb/>people&apos;s influence <lb/>2. Do you think the survey questions are difficult to read <lb/>and answer? <lb/>No idea <lb/></div>

        <note place="headnote">Emerging Science Journal | Vol. 8, No. 2 <lb/></note>

        <page>Page | 657 <lb/></page>

        <div type="annex">Table A-2. Description of items of the survey <lb/>Theoretical Constructs <lb/>Item Code <lb/>Items/Indicators <lb/>Thinking ability <lb/>TK1 <lb/>I always remember well and can restate events that have just happened. <lb/>TK2 <lb/>I always try to reason and think accurately when solving difficult problems. <lb/>TK3 <lb/>I always have good logical thinking when approaching problem solving. <lb/>TK4 <lb/>I always grasp quickly and clearly understand the context of situations that occur. <lb/>TK5 <lb/>I quickly get prioritized issues that need to be addressed. <lb/>TK6 <lb/>I always try to look at things and phenomena objectively. <lb/>TK7 <lb/>I have the ability to evaluate and choose optimal solutions. <lb/>Recognizing emotions <lb/>REC1 <lb/>When my feelings towards work change (from excitement to boredom or vice versa...), I clearly understand <lb/>the reason for the change. <lb/>REC2 <lb/>I easily recognize my true emotions instantly (happy/ uncomfortable/ stressed...). <lb/>REC3 <lb/>I always recognize the hidden meaning behind other people&apos;s gestures and actions towards me (for example, <lb/>whether they are feeling confident/ disappointed/ indignant/ scared...). <lb/>Just by looking at a person I can know how they are feeling. <lb/>REC5 <lb/>I can tell how people are feeling by listening to their tone. <lb/>REC6 <lb/>I am clearly aware of the messages/implications I am conveying when communicating with others (e.g. I am <lb/>feeling confident/ uncertain/ apprehensive...) <lb/>REC7 <lb/>I always believe that I will do everything well. <lb/>Using emotions <lb/>US1 <lb/>I know when to share my private matters with others. <lb/>US2 <lb/>When I experience a positive emotion (joy/ optimism...), I know how to prolong that mood. <lb/>US3 <lb/>I always look for jobs that bring me joy and excitement. <lb/>US4 <lb/>I always control my emotions in every situation <lb/>US5 <lb/>I motivate/ promote myself by imagining a good outcome to the task I am undertaking. <lb/>US6 <lb/>I am always calm (not panicked) when facing difficulties/challenges. <lb/>Understanding emotions <lb/>UND1 <lb/>I like sharing my feelings with others. <lb/>UND2 <lb/>When you need to express yourself to someone, I always know how to make a good impression on that person. <lb/>UND3 <lb/>I often compliment others when they do something well. <lb/>UND4 <lb/>People often find it easy to confide in me. <lb/>UND5 <lb/>When communicating, I know how to arrange events to make others happy. <lb/>UND6 <lb/>I often help others feel more secure when they are in a bad mood (sad/lonely...). <lb/>Managing emotions <lb/>MAN1 <lb/>Emotions are one of the things that make my life meaningful. <lb/>MAN2 <lb/>When I am in a positive mood, problem solving is easy for me. <lb/>MAN3 <lb/>When I&apos;m in a positive mood (happy/excited...), I can come up with new ideas. <lb/>MAN4 <lb/>When someone tells me about an important event in their life, I almost feel as if I have experienced the <lb/>situation myself. <lb/>MAN5 <lb/>Whenever I face obstacles/difficulties at work, I often remember the times when I faced similar obstacles that <lb/>caused emotions in me and how I overcame them. <lb/>MAN6 <lb/>When my mood changes (from sad to happy...), I find myself more enthusiastic about work. <lb/>Decision-making <lb/>DM1 <lb/>I decided because of the influence of others. <lb/>DM2 <lb/>I decided because I had already planned to participate. <lb/>DM3 <lb/>I decided to participate because I got extra training points. <lb/>DM4 <lb/>I decided because I see the long-term benefits for my future work. <lb/>DM5 <lb/>I am willing to spend time and money to study/ participate in extracurricular classes <lb/>DM6 <lb/>I decided to participate because it helps improve my personal skills <lb/>DM7 <lb/>I decided to participate based on the reputation of the organizer. </div>


	</text>

</TEI>