<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="a">On &lt;i&gt;I&lt;/i&gt; -Statistically Cauchy Sequences &amp;amp; the Class of &lt;i&gt;I&lt;/i&gt; -Statistically Concurrent Sequences</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Debjani</forename>
            <surname>Rakshit</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Prasenjit</forename>
            <surname>Bal</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Shyamal</forename>
            <surname>Debnath</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2025-11-04T10:24:30.529946Z">04.11.2025 10:24:30</date>
          <title>grobid.training.segmentation [default]</title>
          <idno type="fileref">10.2478$1$tmmp-2024-0013</idno>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Walter de Gruyter GmbH</publisher>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
        </availability>
        <date type="publication">2024</date>
        <idno type="DOI">10.2478/tmmp-2024-0013</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Debjani Rakshit, Prasenjit Bal, Shyamal Debnath. (2024). On &lt;i&gt;I&lt;/i&gt; -Statistically Cauchy Sequences &amp;amp; the Class of &lt;i&gt;I&lt;/i&gt; -Statistically Concurrent Sequences. Tatra Mountains Mathematical Publications, 86(1), 111-122. DOI: 10.2478/tmmp-2024-0013</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
          <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
        </application>
        <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-04T10:24:30.529946Z" type="extractor">
          <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
          <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
          <label type="flavor">default</label>
          <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
          <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2025-11-04T10:24:30.529946Z" status="draft">
        <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>Chunyu Huang, Weipeng Liang and Yuying Sun* <lb/>The role of BMI, serum lipid profile molecules and <lb/>their derivative indexes in colorectal polyps <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1515/almed-2023-0170 <lb/>Received December 18, 2023; accepted March 16, 2024; <lb/>published online April 26, 2024 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Objectives: To investigate the role of body mass index <lb/>(BMI), serum lipid profile molecules and their derivative <lb/>indexes in colorectal polyps. <lb/>Methods: A total of 352 individuals who underwent colo-<lb/>noscopy at our center were included in this retrospective <lb/>analysis. Of these, 247 patients without evident abnormal-<lb/>ities (control group), while 105 patients diagnosed with <lb/>colorectal polyps (patient group). Serum lipid profile mol-<lb/>ecules and their derivative indexes were then compared <lb/>between the two groups. <lb/>Results: The patient group exhibited significantly higher <lb/>levels of total cholesterol (TC) and apolipoprotein B (ApoB) <lb/>compared to the control group (p&lt;0.05). In males, the patient <lb/>group displayed elevated levels of ApoB and ApoB/ApoA1 <lb/>ratio compared to the control group (p&lt;0.05). Additionally, <lb/>the triglycerides (TG) and TG/high-density lipoprotein-<lb/>cholesterol (HDL-C) ratios were significantly higher in the <lb/>multiple polyps group than in the single polyp group <lb/>(p&lt;0.05). Furthermore, the HDL-C and HDL-C/ApoA1 ratio <lb/>levels were higher in the adenomatous polyp group when <lb/>compared to the non-adenomatous polyp group (p&lt;0.05). <lb/>Multiple logistic regression analysis indicated that total <lb/>cholesterol (TC), TG, low-density lipoprotein-cholesterol <lb/>(LDL-C), TC/HDL-C ratio, TG/HDL-C ratio and LDL-C/HDL-C <lb/>ratio were risk factors for the occurrence of colorectal <lb/>polyps (p&lt;0.05). ROC curve analyses revealed that TC, ApoB, <lb/>and ApoB/ApoA1 ratio were associated with colorectal <lb/>polyps. No significant difference in BMI between the two <lb/>groups (p&gt;0.05). <lb/>Conclusions: The incidence and progression of colorectal <lb/>polyps are linked to serum lipid molecules and their deriv-<lb/>ative indexes. Dyslipidemia may increase the risk of colo-<lb/>rectal polyps, potentially leading to colorectal cancer (CRC). <lb/>Keywords: body mass index; colorectal polyp; serum lipids <lb/></front>

        <body>Introduction <lb/>Colorectal polyps refer to the growth of excessive hyper-<lb/>plasia of the mucosa in the colon and rectum. Due to the <lb/>increase in colonoscopy screenings and people&apos;s changing <lb/>lifestyle habits, the detection rate of colorectal polyps has <lb/>significantly increased. Colorectal adenoma is considered a <lb/>precancerous lesion since the recognized cancerous pro-<lb/>gression pattern of colorectal cancer is &quot;adenoma-atypical <lb/>hyperplasia-carcinoma&quot; [1, 2]. Studies have shown that early <lb/>removal of colorectal polyps can reduce the mortality rate of <lb/>colorectal cancer [3]. Hence, exploring the risk factors <lb/>associated with colorectal polyps is of great clinical signifi-<lb/>cance in the prevention of colorectal cancer (CRC). However, <lb/>there are controversy on the association between colorectal <lb/>polyps and serum lipid levels. Studies have been shown that <lb/>metabolic syndrome is closely related to the occurrence of <lb/>colorectal polyps, and dyslipidemia has been identified as <lb/>one of the pathogenesis factors of CRC [4-6], but other <lb/>studies showed no relationship between serum lipid and <lb/>colorectal polyps [7, 8]. In this study, we aim to retrospec-<lb/>tively analyze the levels of serum lipid profile molecules and <lb/>their derivative indexes in the patients with colorectal <lb/>polyps and controls, observe the correlation between indi-<lb/>vidual lipid levels and colorectal polyps, to explore the risk <lb/>factors for the development of colorectal polyps and to <lb/>provide a theoretical reference basis for the screening of <lb/>high-risk groups for colorectal polyps. It can also reduce the <lb/>incidence of CRC and improve people&apos;s quality of life. This <lb/>study discovered that serum lipid levels are related to colo-<lb/>rectal polyps. Dyslipidemia, such as higher leves of total <lb/>cholesterol (TC), triglycerides (TG), low-density lipoprotein-<lb/>cholesterol (LDL-C), and apolipoprotein B (ApoB), may <lb/></body>

        <front>*Corresponding author: Prof. Yuying Sun, State Key Laboratory of <lb/>Oncology in South China, Guangdong Provincial Clinical Research Center <lb/>for Cancer, Sun Yat-sen University Cancer Center, Guangzhou, 510060 <lb/>P.R. China; and Cancer Prevention Center, Sun Yat-sen University Cancer <lb/>Center, Guangzhou 510060, P.R. China Phone: 86-20-87343888, <lb/>E-mail: sunyy@sysucc.org.cn. https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5789-256X <lb/>Chunyu Huang, State Key Laboratory of Oncology in South China, <lb/>Guangdong Provincial Clinical Research Center for Cancer, Sun Yat-sen <lb/>University Cancer Center, Guangzhou, P.R. China; and Department of <lb/>Endoscopy, Sun Yat-sen University Cancer Center, Guangzhou, P.R. China <lb/>Weipeng Liang, State Key Laboratory of Oncology in South China, <lb/>Guangdong Provincial Clinical Research Center for Cancer, Sun Yat-sen <lb/>University Cancer Center, Guangzhou, P.R. China; and Cancer Prevention <lb/>Center, Sun Yat-sen University Cancer Center, Guangzhou, P.R. China <lb/>Adv Lab Med 2024; 5(3): 276-282 <lb/>Open Access. © 2024 the author(s), published by De Gruyter. <lb/>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. <lb/></front>

        <body>enhance the likelihood of colorectal polyps formation. This <lb/>study also analyzed the relationship between lipid deriva-<lb/>tive indexes and colorectal polyps, and found that the serum <lb/>lipid derivative indexes, including TC/high-density lipopro-<lb/>tein-cholesterol (HDL-C) ratio, TG/HDL-C ratio, LDL-C/HDL-C <lb/>ratio and ApoB/apolipoprotein A1(ApoA1) ratio were related <lb/>to colorectal polyps. The derivative indexes of serum lipid <lb/>profile components may have changed while they are <lb/>normal. The serum lipid derivative indexes, rather than the <lb/>serum lipid profile molecules, are superior predictors of <lb/>disease state. The results of lipid profile molecules and their <lb/>derivative indexes can be obtained through simple inspec-<lb/>tion methods, which are convenient, fast, easy to repeat, of <lb/>low price, and of great significance to the prevention of CRC. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Patient population <lb/>From January 2019 to December 2020, 435 patients who had a colonos-<lb/>copy at Cancer Prevention Center, Sun Yat-sen University Cancer Center, <lb/>and six blood lipid tests were performed simultaneously. Most of these <lb/>patients voluntarily came to our physical examination centre for a co-<lb/>lonoscopy, and the majority of them did not consider having a disease <lb/>prior to the colonoscopy, only for a regular health physical. However, 83 <lb/>patients were excluded due to colon inflammation or colonic divertic-<lb/>ulum or intestine black disease or lymphatic follicular hyperplasia, or <lb/>submucosal bulge or early colon cancer and so on, resulting in a total of <lb/>352 patients enrolled in the study. Among these 352 patients, 247 were <lb/>confirmed to have no polyps upon colonoscopy and were included in the <lb/>control group. The remaining 105 patients were diagnosed with colo-<lb/>rectal polyps and were assigned to the patient group. Subgroups of the <lb/>patient group were created based on the colonoscopy results of the <lb/>diameter, quantity, location, and tissue type of colorectal polyps. Two <lb/>groups&apos; serum lipid profile molecules and their derivative indices were <lb/>extensively examined. The patient group was further separated into <lb/>different subgroups to examine the blood lipid profile molecules based <lb/>on the varied clinical features of colorectal polyps. All participants <lb/>involved in the study signed an informed consent form. This research <lb/>was approved by the Ethics Committee of the Sun Yat-sen University <lb/>Cancer Center, and followed the guidelines outlined in the Declaration <lb/>of Helsinki. <lb/>Clinical data of the patients were retrospectively analyzed, <lb/>including gender, age, weight, height, colorectal polyps properties (the <lb/>diameter, quantity, location, and tissue type of colorectal polyps), serum <lb/>lipid profile molecules and their derivative indexes. The individual <lb/>serum lipid profile molecules include TG, TC, HDL-C, LDL-C, ApoA1 <lb/>and ApoB, and their derivative indexes including LDL-C/HDL-C ratio, <lb/>TC/HDL-C ratio, TG/HDL-C ratio, HDL-C/ApoA1ratio and ApoB/ApoA1 <lb/>ratio. The diameter, quantity, location, and tissue type of colorectal <lb/>polyps are all characteristics. <lb/>Patients with exclusion criteria listed as follows were excluded: <lb/>(1) a surgery history of colorectal polyps and colorectal cancer; (2) <lb/>other colorectal diseases apart from colorectal polyps, such as colitis, <lb/>inflammatory colorectal disease, colon disease, colon diverticular, and <lb/>colorectal cancer; (3) primary lipid metabolism-related diseases with <lb/>intake of lipid-regulating drugs and other drugs that might affect <lb/>serum lipid profile molecules in the past 3 months; (4) serious cardiac <lb/>and brain diseases, as well as liver and kidney dysfunction. <lb/>Colonoscopy <lb/>Colonoscopy using OLYMPUS CF-H290i electronic colonoscopy was <lb/>performed by experienced endoscopists. All the patient group were <lb/>undergone pathological biopsy, otherwise, their polyp was removed <lb/>and sent for pathological examination. Two senior pathologists read <lb/>the histology sections. <lb/>Patient group was further divided into &lt;1 cm and ≥1 cm according <lb/>to diameter; single and multiple according to number. It is also divided <lb/>by location in the colon, with the left hemicolon consisting of the splenic <lb/>flexure, descending colon, and sigmoid colon, and the right hemicolon <lb/>consisting of the cecum, ascending colon, hepatic flexure, and trans-<lb/>verse colon. According to histopathological types, they were divided into <lb/>adenomatous polyps (tubular adenoma, villous adenoma, tubular-<lb/>villous adenoma and serrated adenoma) and non-adenomatous polyps <lb/>(inflammatory polyps, hyperplastic polyps). <lb/>Serum lipid testing <lb/>Blood samples were collected from all participants after 8-12 h of fast-<lb/>ing, through the cubital vein, with a volume of 3 mL. Once the plasma <lb/>was separated, the levels of TC, TG, HDL-C, LDL-C, ApoA1 and ApoB were <lb/>analyzed using an automatic biochemical analyzer (Cobas 8000 c702, <lb/>Roche Diagnostics GmbH, Mannheim, Germany). The reference ranges <lb/>of serum lipid profile molecules are: TC: 3.1-5.69 mmol/L; TG: <lb/>0.2-1.7 mmol/L; HDL-C: 1.16-1.42 mmol/L; LDL-C:2.2-3.1 mmol/L; ApoA1: <lb/>1.2-1.6 g/L; and ApoB: 0.6-1.0 g/L. According to the results of the serum <lb/>lipid profile molecules, their derivative indexes include LDL-C/HDL-C <lb/>ratio, TC/HDL-C ratio, TG/HDL-C ratio, HDL-C/ApoA1 ratio, and ApoB/ <lb/>ApoA1 ratio were calculated. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>Data analysis was performed using SPSS 25.0 statistical software (SPSS <lb/>Inc. Chicago, IL, USA). Prior to conducting the t-test, a normality study <lb/>was performed to assess the distribution of the data. The enumeration <lb/>data were calculated as mean ± standard deviation (x ± s). The com-<lb/>parison between different groups was analyzed using the independent <lb/>sample t-test, assuming normal distribution of the data. The indepen-<lb/>dent risk factors of colorectal polyps were analyzed by multiple logistic <lb/>regression analysis method and ROC curve analysis. A p-value &lt;0.05 was <lb/>considered statistically significant. <lb/>Results <lb/>Comparative analysis of serum lipid profile <lb/>molecules <lb/>There were no differences in age or gender between the <lb/>control and patient groups. There were 55 males and 50 <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Huang et al.: The role of BMI and serum lipid in colorectal polyps <lb/></note>

        <page>277 <lb/></page>

        <body>females in the patient group, with an average age of <lb/>51.14 ± 9.01. In the control group, there were 111 males and <lb/>136 females, with an average age of 49.74 ± 7.10. The levels <lb/>of TC and ApoB in the patient group were significantly <lb/>higher than those in the control group (p&lt;0.05). The dif-<lb/>ference in serum lipid derivative indexes, the ApoB/ApoA1 <lb/>ratio, between the two groups was statistically significant <lb/>(p=0.002) (Table 1). In the patient group, ApoB (p=0.025) and <lb/>ApoB/ApoA1 ratio (p=0.024) were significantly greater than <lb/>in the control group among males. However, there were no <lb/>significant differences among females (p&gt;0.05) (Table 3). <lb/>There was no association between body mass index (BMI) <lb/>and colorectal polyps (p&gt;0.05) (Table 1). <lb/>The relationship between different clinical <lb/>characteristics of colorectal polyps and <lb/>serum lipid profile molecules <lb/>There were 105 cases in the patient group, including 30 cases <lb/>of ≥45 years old, and 75 cases of &lt;45 years old; 58 cases with <lb/>single polyps, and 47 cases of multiple polyps; 18 cases with <lb/>polyps ≥1 cm, and 87 cases with polyps &lt;1 cm; 48 cases with <lb/>polyps located in the right colon, and 57 located in the left <lb/>colon or rectum; 64 cases with adenomatous polyps, and 41 <lb/>non-adenomatous polyps (Table 2). In the patient group, <lb/>ApoB and ApoB/ApoA1 ratio were significantly greater than <lb/>the control group in males (p&lt;0.05) (Supplementary Table 1), <lb/>while there have no significant difference in females (p&gt;0.05) <lb/>(Supplementary Table 2).The levels of TG, TG/HDL-C ratio in <lb/>the multiple polyps subgroup were significantly higher than <lb/>those in the single polyp subgroup (p&lt;0.05) (Table 3). The <lb/>levels of HDL-C and HDL-C/ApoA1 ratio in the adenomatous <lb/>polyps were higher than those with non-adenomatous <lb/>polyps (p&lt;0.05) (Table 4). While lipid levels in the patient <lb/>group showed no correlation with age, polyp size, and polyp <lb/>location (p&gt;0.05). In general, age, locations and sizes of the <lb/>polyps were not significantly correlated with the occurrence <lb/>of dyslipidemia. <lb/>Analysis of independent risk factors for <lb/>colorectal polyps <lb/>Multiple logistic regression analysis of the serum lipid pro-<lb/>file molecules and their derivative indexes, using the <lb/>occurrence of colorectal polyps as the dependent variable, <lb/>revealed that TC, TG, LDL-C, TC/HDL-C ratio, TG/HDL-C ratio <lb/>and LDL-C/HDL-C ratio were risk factors for the onset of colo-<lb/>rectal polyps (p&lt;0.05) (Table 5). The TC, TG, and ApoB/ApoA1 <lb/>ratios were also linked to colorectal polyps, according to ROC <lb/>curve analyses (Table 6). We conducted ROC curve analysis <lb/>for all variables, including TC, TG, LDL-C, HDL-C, ApoA1, ApoB, <lb/>TC/HDL-C ratio, TG/HDL-C ratio, and ApoB/ApoA1 ratio. Our <lb/>findings revealed that TC, TG, and ApoB/ApoA1 ratio displayed <lb/>comparatively higher levels of sensitivity and specificity in <lb/>these outcomes. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>CRC is one of the most common malignant tumorsglobally, <lb/>with high morbidity and mortality rates [9]. CRC has a low <lb/>detection rate in general population screening, and there is <lb/>no easy and effective method for population census. Fecal <lb/>hemoglobin detection tests, is a common non-invasive <lb/>examination, which are increasingly utilized worldwide in <lb/>colorectal cancer screening programs, were not performed <lb/>in this study due to poor compliance among participants. <lb/>Endostroscopy is the standard for the diagnosis of lesions <lb/>[10], but due to the severe shortage of experienced endo-<lb/>scopists in China, and the fact that endoscopy is an invasive <lb/>and expensive test that is difficult for many asymptomatic <lb/>people to accept, it is difficult to carry out CRC screening <lb/>using endoscopy, and the only potentially effective method is <lb/>to screen the population at high risk of CRC. The aim of the <lb/>present study is to assist in determining the population at <lb/>risk of CRC by identifying high risk factors for colorectal <lb/>polyps, and to act as a guide for CRC screening. Therefore, <lb/>Table : Univariate analysis of patient group and control group. <lb/>Parameters <lb/>Patient <lb/>group <lb/>(n=) <lb/>Control <lb/>group <lb/>(n=) <lb/>T-value p-Value <lb/>Gender (male, %) <lb/> (.) <lb/> (.) <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>Age (x ± s, year) <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>BMI (x ± s, kg/m  ) <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>TC (x ± s, mmol/L) <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. . a <lb/>TG (x ± s, mmol/L) <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>HDL-C (x ± s, mmol/L) <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . -. <lb/>. <lb/>LDL-C (x ± s, mmol/L) <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>ApoAl (x ± s, mmol/L) <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . -. <lb/>. <lb/>Apo-B (x ± s, mmol/L) <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. . a <lb/>TC/HDL-C (x ± s) <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>TG/HDL-C (x ± s) <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>LDL-C/HDL-C (x ± s) <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>HDL-C/ApoAl (x ± s) <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>Apo-B/ApoAl (x ± s) <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. . a <lb/>ApoA, apolipoprotein A; ApoB, apolipoprotein B; BMI, body mass index; <lb/>HDL-C, high-density lipoprotein-cholesterol; LDL-C, low-density lipoprotein-<lb/>cholesterol; TC, total cholesterol; TG, triglycerides. a p&lt;.. <lb/></body>

        <page>278 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Huang et al.: The role of BMI and serum lipid in colorectal polyps <lb/></note>

        <body>studying the risk factors of colorectal polyps is of great sig-<lb/>nificance for the reduction of the incidence of CRC. <lb/>Studies have found that dyslipidemia plays a critical role <lb/>in the occurrence and development of a variety of cancers, <lb/>which might be a potential target for anti-cancer therapy <lb/>[11]. The main characteristics of cancer tissue are that the <lb/>body loses control and endures excessive cell proliferation, <lb/>resulting in the formation of a cancer. Fast cell growth <lb/>demands the addition of more cholesterol because choles-<lb/>terol is the major component of cell membranes [12, 13]. <lb/>Dyslipidemia and colorectal cancer have a strong associa-<lb/>tion. Dyslipidemia was shown to be substantially more <lb/>common in people with CRC. Diabetes, hyperlipidemia, and <lb/>inflammatory bowel illness are all independently related to <lb/>the risk of multiple CRC, according to a large retrospective <lb/>case-control research in China [4]. Due to the popularity of <lb/>endoscopic technology, the detection rate of colorectal <lb/>polyps has increased significantly in recent years. While it <lb/>is reported that colorectal polyps are associated with age, <lb/>Table : Characteristics of the subjects. <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>n (%) <lb/>Patient group <lb/> (.) <lb/>Sex <lb/>Males <lb/> (.) <lb/>Females <lb/> (.) <lb/>Age, years <lb/>≤ <lb/> (.) <lb/>&gt; <lb/> (.) <lb/>BMI <lb/>Normal <lb/> (.) <lb/>Overweight <lb/> (.) <lb/>Obesity <lb/> (.) <lb/>Polyps location <lb/>Left hemicolon/rectum <lb/> (.) <lb/>Right hemicolon <lb/> (.) <lb/>Polyps size, mm <lb/>≥ <lb/> (.) <lb/>&lt; <lb/> (.) <lb/>Polyps pathology <lb/>adenoma <lb/> (.) <lb/>Non-adenoma <lb/> (.) <lb/>Polyps number <lb/>Single <lb/> (.) <lb/>Multiple <lb/> (.) <lb/>Control group <lb/> (.) <lb/>Sex <lb/>Males <lb/> (.) <lb/>Females <lb/> (.) <lb/>Age, years <lb/>≤ <lb/> (.) <lb/>＞ <lb/> (.) <lb/>BMI <lb/>Normal <lb/> (.) <lb/>Overweight <lb/> (.) <lb/>Obesity <lb/> (.) <lb/>Table : Univariate analysis of subgroup according to the number of the <lb/>polyps in patient group. <lb/>Parameters <lb/>Multiple polyps <lb/>group (n=) <lb/>Single polyp <lb/>group (n=) <lb/>T-value p-Value <lb/>TC, mmol/L <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . -. <lb/>. <lb/>TG, mmol/L <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. . a <lb/>HDL-C, mmol/L <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . -. <lb/>. <lb/>LDL-C, mmol/L <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . -. <lb/>. <lb/>ApoA, g/L <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . -. <lb/>. <lb/>ApoB, g/L <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>TC/HDL-C ratio <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>TG/HDL-C ratio <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. . a <lb/>LDL-C/HDL-C <lb/>ratio <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>HDL-C/ApoA <lb/>ratio <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . -. <lb/>. <lb/>ApoB/ApoA <lb/>ratio <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>ApoA, apolipoprotein A; ApoB, apolipoprotein B, HDL-C, high-density <lb/>lipoprotein-cholesterol; LDL-C, low-density lipoprotein-cholesterol; TC, total <lb/>cholesterol; TG, triglycerides. a p&lt;.. <lb/>Table : Univariate analysis of pathological type subgroup within the <lb/>patient group. <lb/>Parameters <lb/>Adenomatous <lb/>polyps (n=) <lb/>Non-adenoma-<lb/>tous polyps <lb/>(n=) <lb/>T-value p-Value <lb/>TC, mmol/L <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . -. <lb/>. <lb/>TG, mmol/L <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . -. <lb/>. <lb/>HDL-C, mmol/L <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>LDL-C, mmol/L <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . -. <lb/>. <lb/>ApoA, g/L <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>ApoB, g/L <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . -. <lb/>. <lb/>TC/HDL-C ratio <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . -. <lb/>. <lb/>TG/HDL-C ratio <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . -. <lb/>. <lb/>LDL-C/HDL-C <lb/>ratio <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . -. <lb/>. <lb/>HDL-C/ApoAl <lb/>ratio <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. . a <lb/>ApoB/ApoAl <lb/>ratio <lb/>. ± . <lb/>. ± . -. <lb/>. <lb/>ApoA, apolipoprotein A; ApoB, apolipoprotein B; HDL-C, high-density <lb/>lipoprotein-cholesterol; LDL-C, low-density lipoprotein-cholesterol; TC, total <lb/>cholesterol; TG, triglycerides. a p&lt;.. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Huang et al.: The role of BMI and serum lipid in colorectal polyps <lb/></note>

        <page>279 <lb/></page>

        <body>gender, smoking, drinking, high-fat diet, obesity, diabetes, <lb/>metabolic syndrome and other factors, the etiology and <lb/>pathogenesis of colorectal polyps are still unclear. Some <lb/>studies suggest that dyslipidemia is also closely related to <lb/>colorectal adenoma [14-21], but there is still controversy. <lb/>Some researchers believe that dyslipidemia has nothing to <lb/>do with colorectal adenoma [7, 8], while others believe it is a <lb/>risk factor for their occurrence and progression. Polyps and <lb/>serum lipids, on the other hand, were the subject of very <lb/>few studies [22-25]. In colorectal polyps, we found that <lb/>significantly higher levels of TC and ApoB than non-polyp <lb/>(Table 1), which demonstrated that dyslipidemia possibility <lb/>associated with colorectal polyp, consistent with the <lb/>previous investigations. <lb/>At present, the correlation of dyslipidemia and colo-<lb/>rectal polyps is not yet clear. Studies have found that TG can <lb/>not only activate insulin-like growth factor-1 and regulate <lb/>the activity of K-ras protein, but also stimulate the abnormal <lb/>proliferation of intestinal epithelial cells and promote the <lb/>transformation of colorectal adenoma into tumor [17]. <lb/>Studies have also suggested that dyslipidemia activates the <lb/>MAPK pathway by increasing the reactive oxygen species <lb/>activity of colon adenoma cells, leading to excessive cell <lb/>proliferation and promoting the development of polyps into <lb/>tumors [26]. High levels of TG can increase pro-inflammatory <lb/>factors while decreasing inflammatory inhibitory cytokines, <lb/>which affects the growth, apoptosis and proliferation of <lb/>tumors and stromal cells, and promotes the carcinogenesis <lb/>of adenomas [27]. Dyslipidemia can also cause oxidative <lb/>stress and work together with inflammation to produce <lb/>carcinogenic effects. Considered as an important pathogenic <lb/>factor of many diseases, oxidative stress will lead to the <lb/>production of more reactive oxygen species, lipid peroxi-<lb/>dation, lipid macromolecules of cell membrane into lipid <lb/>peroxide, causing tissue damage. This demonstrates that <lb/>oxidative stress and lipid peroxidation are linked, and that <lb/>Table : Multiple logistic regression analysis of serum lipid molecules in patient group. <lb/>Parameters <lb/>B <lb/>Standard error <lb/>Wald <lb/>p-Value <lb/>OR <lb/> % CI <lb/>Age (x ± s, year) <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>.-. <lb/>BMI (x ± s, kg/m  ) <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>.-. <lb/>TC, mmol/L <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>&lt;. a <lb/>. <lb/>.-. ×   <lb/>TG, mmol/L <lb/>-. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. a <lb/>. <lb/>.-. <lb/>HDL-C, mmol/L <lb/>-. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>.-. <lb/>LDL-C, mmol/L <lb/>-. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>&lt;. a <lb/>&lt;. <lb/>.-. <lb/>ApoA, g/L <lb/>-. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>.-. ×   <lb/>ApoB, g/L <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>.-. ×   <lb/>TC/HDL-C ratio <lb/>-. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. a <lb/>&lt;. <lb/>.-. <lb/>TG/HDL-C ratio <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. a <lb/>. <lb/>.-. <lb/>LDL-C/HDL-C ratio <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. a <lb/>. <lb/>.-. ×   <lb/>HDL-C/ApoA ratio <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>.-. ×   <lb/>ApoB/ApoA ratio <lb/>-. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>.-. ×   <lb/>ApoA, apolipoprotein A; ApoB, apolipoprotein B; B, regression coefficient; BMI, body mass index; HDL-C, high-density lipoprotein-cholesterol; LDL-C, low-<lb/>density lipoprotein-cholesterol; OR, odds ratio; TC, total cholesterol; TG, triglycerides;  % CI= % confidence interval. a p&lt;.. <lb/>Table : ROC curve analysis results of the diagnostic value of related lipid indexes for colorectal polyps. <lb/>Parameters <lb/>AUC <lb/>SE <lb/>p-Value <lb/> % CI <lb/>Cut-off value <lb/>Sensitivity <lb/>Specificity <lb/>Youden index <lb/>TC <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. a <lb/>.-. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>TG <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>.-. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>HDL-C <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>.-. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>LDL-C <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>.-. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>ApoA <lb/> . <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>.-. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>ApoB <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. a <lb/>.-. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>TC/HDL-C <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>.-. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>TG/HDL-C <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>.-. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>ApoB/ApoA <lb/> . <lb/>. <lb/>. a <lb/>.-. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/>ApoA, apolipoprotein A; ApoB, apolipoprotein B; HDL-C, high-density lipoprotein-cholesterol; LDL-C, low-density lipoprotein-cholesterol; TC, total <lb/>cholesterol; TG, triglycerides;  % CI= % confidence interval. a p&lt;.. <lb/></body>

        <page>280 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Huang et al.: The role of BMI and serum lipid in colorectal polyps <lb/></note>

        <body>the degree of lipid peroxide is connected to serum choles-<lb/>terol and TG [28, 29]. In addition, the increase of serum lipid <lb/>profile molecules can also change the excretion and circu-<lb/>lation of bile acid, lead to the mechanism of bile acid <lb/>absorption or butyric acid inhibition, increase the content of <lb/>secondary bile acid in the intestine, and cause DNA damage, <lb/>cell proliferation and angiogenesis microenvironment, pro-<lb/>motes the occurrence of colorectal polyps [20]. <lb/>Studies have suggested that serum lipid derivative <lb/>indexes are related to the occurrence and development of <lb/>some cancers. Some studies report that the ApoB/ApoA1 ratio <lb/>is associated with the increase of overall cancer incidence in <lb/>males [30]. In this study, they also find results regarding <lb/>ApoB, which is also associated. Furthermore, focusing on <lb/>patients with CRC, they observe a relationship with ApoB, <lb/>not with ApoA1, similar to the findings of this study. The <lb/>ApoB/ApoA1 ratio rose in patients with gastric cancer (GC), <lb/>according to Kimak et al. and Ma et al. [31, 32]. Increased <lb/>preoperative serum LDL-C/HDL-C ratio is an independent <lb/>risk factor for CRC tumor-node-metastasis staging and is <lb/>closely related to CRC prognosis [33]. However, there are <lb/>currently very few studies on the relationship between <lb/>serum lipid derivative indexes and the occurrence and <lb/>development of colorectal polyps. Therefore, we further <lb/>analyzed the relationship between colorectal polyps and <lb/>serum lipids and their derivatives, and this article is to study <lb/>these correlations based on their location, size, number and <lb/>pathological types. The present study found that dyslipide-<lb/>mia, such as TG, TC, LDL-C, ApoB, TC/HDL-C ratio, TG/HDL-C <lb/>ratio, LDL-C/HDL-C ratio, and ApoB/ApoA1ratio, plays an <lb/>important role in the occurrence and development of colo-<lb/>rectal polyps. This finding aligns with studies conducted by <lb/>Isakov et al., demonstrating an association between a high <lb/>TG/HDL ratio and serrated polyps [34]. We further analyzed <lb/>the relationship between colorectal polyps and serum lipids <lb/>derivative indexes in subgroup, and found that the age, <lb/>location, and size of polyps are not significantly correlated <lb/>with dyslipidemia. According to multiple regression anal-<lb/>ysis, TC, TG, LDL-C, and ApoB may increase the incidence of <lb/>colorectal polyps (p&lt;0.05). The TC, ApoB and ApoB/ApoA1 <lb/>ratios were also linked to colorectal polyps, according to ROC <lb/>curve analyses. These results are consistent with the previ-<lb/>ous research [23]. <lb/>We also studied the relationship between lipids and BMI <lb/>in colorectal polyps. Previous studies have tested the lipid <lb/>association with BMI, yielding inconclusive results [34-36]. <lb/>In present study, we found that there is no meaningful <lb/>correlation between BMI and colorectal polyps. <lb/>There were several limitations in our research. This <lb/>study was conducted in a single location, and the sample size <lb/>was relatively small. Because the subjects in this study were <lb/>selected among people who attended to the hospital for <lb/>routine health exams and colonoscopies, there could have <lb/>been a selection bias. Moreover, the current research on the <lb/>related risk factors of colorectal polyps are not yet perfect, <lb/>and it is necessary to expand the sample size to obtain more <lb/>accurate results. Thus, our results are preliminary. <lb/>In summary, this study found that dyslipidemia plays <lb/>an important role in the occurrence and development of <lb/>colorectal polyps, and dyslipidemia is an independent risk <lb/>factor for colorectal polyps. We found that serum lipid <lb/>profile molecules and their derivative indexes could be <lb/>used as predict factors in the process of colorectal polyps. <lb/>People with dyslipidemia need colonoscopy more than the <lb/>general population. <lb/></body>

        <div type="annex">Research ethics: The study was approved by the Ethics <lb/>Committee of the Sun Yat-sen University Cancer Center. <lb/>Informed consent: All of the patients have signed the <lb/>informed consent form. <lb/></div>

        <div type="contribution">Author contributions: The authors have accepted respon-<lb/>sibility for the entire content of this manuscript and approved <lb/>its submission. Chunyu Huang (First Author): Investigation, <lb/>Formal Analysis, Writing-the manuscript, Funding Acquisi-<lb/>tion; Weipeng Liang: Data analysis, Investigation; Yuying Sun <lb/>(Corresponding Author): Conceptualization, Resources, Su-<lb/>pervision, Writing -Review &amp; Editing. <lb/></div>

        <div type="conflict">Competing interests: The authors state no conflict of <lb/>interest. <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">Research funding: This work was supported by the Guang-<lb/>dong Medical Research Foundation [grant number A2021369]. <lb/></div>

        <div type="availability">Data availability: The raw data used to support the findings <lb/>of this study could be obtained by getting in touch the cor-<lb/>responding author. <lb/></div>

        <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Segal E, Prestwood TR, van der Linden WA, Carmi Y, Bhattacharya N, <lb/>Withana N, et al. Detection of intestinal cancer by local, topical <lb/>application of a quenched fluorescence probe for cysteine cathepsins. <lb/>Chem Biol 2015;22:148-58. <lb/>2. Waniczek D, Śnietura M, Młynarczyk-Liszka J, Pigłowski W, Kopeć A, <lb/>Lange D, et al. PTEN expression profiles in colorectal adenocarcinoma <lb/>and its precancerous lesions. Pol J Pathol 2013;64:15-20. <lb/>3. Zauber AG, Winawer SJ, O&apos;Brien MJ, Lansdorp-Vogelaar I, <lb/>van Ballegooijen M, Hankey BF, et al. Colonoscopic polypectomy and <lb/>long-term prevention of colorectal-cancer deaths. New Engl J Med <lb/>2012;366:687-96. <lb/>4. Chen H, Zheng X, Zong X, Li Z, Li N, Hur J, et al. Metabolic syndrome, <lb/>metabolic comorbid conditions and risk of early-onset colorectal <lb/>cancer. Gut 2021;70:1147-54. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="headnote">Huang et al.: The role of BMI and serum lipid in colorectal polyps <lb/></note>

        <page>281 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>5. Rodriguez-Broadbent H, Law PJ, Sud A, Palin K, Tuupanen S, Gylfe A, <lb/>et al. Mendelian randomisation implicates hyperlipidaemia as a risk <lb/>factor for colorectal cancer. Int J Cancer 2017;140:2701-8. <lb/>6. Zhang R, Yin J, Huo C, Li X, Ye J, Zhao W, et al. The relationship between <lb/>colorectal polyps and serum lipid levels: a systematic review and meta-<lb/>analysis. J Clin Gastroenterol 2022;56:654-67. <lb/>7. Chung YW, Han DS, Park YK, Son BK, Paik CH, Lee H, et al. Association of <lb/>obesity, serum glucose and lipids with the risk of advanced colorectal <lb/>adenoma and cancer: a case control study in Korea. Dig Liver Dis 2006; <lb/>38:668-72. <lb/>8. Kono S, Imanishi K, Shinchi K, Yanai F. Serum lipids and left-sided <lb/>adenomas of the large bowel: an extended study of self-defense <lb/>officials in Japan. Cancer Causes Control 1993;4:117-21. <lb/>9. Glynne-Jones R, Wyrwicz L, Tiret E, Brown G, Rödel C, Cervantes A, et al. <lb/>ESMO Guidelines Committee. Rectal cancer: ESMO clinical Practice <lb/>guidelines for diagnosis, treatment and follow-up. Ann Oncol 2017;28: <lb/>iv22-40. <lb/>10. Li L, Ou Y, Yue H, Sun H, Chen P, Liu S, et al. Comparison of the detection <lb/>of colorectal lesions in different endoscopic modalities: a network <lb/>meta-analysis and systematic review. Exp Ther Med 2019;18:154-62. <lb/>11. Pirmoradi L, Seyfizadeh N, Ghavami S, Zeki AA, Shojaei S. Targeting <lb/>cholesterol metabolism in glioblastoma: a new therapeutic approach in <lb/>cancer therapy. J Invest Med 2019;67:715-19. <lb/>12. Che L, Chi W, Qiao Y, Zhang J, Song X, Liu Y, et al. Cholesterol <lb/>biosynthesis supports the growth of hepatocarcinoma lesions depleted <lb/>of fatty acid synthase in mice and humans. Gut 2020;69:177-86. <lb/>13. Xi Y, Yani Z, Jing M, Yinhang W, Xiaohui H, Jing Z, et al. Mechanisms of <lb/>induction of tumors by cholesterol and potential therapeutic prospects. <lb/>Biomed Pharmacother 2021;144:112277. <lb/>14. Passarelli MN, Newcomb PA. Blood lipid concentrations and colorectal <lb/>adenomas: a systematic review and meta-analysis of colonoscopy <lb/>studies in Asia, 2000-2014. Am J Epidemiol 2016;183:691-700. <lb/>15. Kim YJ, Lee KJ, Park SY, Han JH, Kwon KY, Kim JH. Association between <lb/>dyslipidemia and the prevalence of colon polyps based on a health <lb/>evaluation of subjects at a hospital. Korean J Fam Med 2014;35:143-51. <lb/>16. Hwang ST, Cho YK, Park JH, Kim HJ, Park DI, Sohn CI, et al. Relationship <lb/>of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease to colorectal adenomatous polyps. J <lb/>Gastroenterol Hepatol 2010;25:562-7. <lb/>17. Yang MH, Rampal S, Sung J, Choi YH, Son HJ, Lee JH, et al. The <lb/>association of serum lipids with colorectal adenomas. Am J <lb/>Gastroenterol 2013;108:833-41. <lb/>18. Orannapalai N, Attawettayanon W, Kanngern S, Boonpipattanapong T, <lb/>Sangkhathat S. Predicting the occurrence of cancer-associated <lb/>colorectal polyp using a metabolic risk score. Mol Clin Oncol 2014;2: <lb/>124-8. <lb/>19. Yang W, Chang Y, Huang H, Wang Y, Yu X. Association between obesity, <lb/>serum lipids, and colorectal polyps in old Chinese people. Gastroenterol <lb/>Res Pract 2013;931084. https://doi.org/10.1155/2013/931084. <lb/>20. Tian Y, Wang K, Li J, Wang J, Wang Z, Fan Y, et al. The association <lb/>between serum lipids and colorectal neoplasm: a systemic review and <lb/>meta-analysis. Public Health Nutr 2015;18:3350-70. <lb/>21. Chen QF, Zhou XD, Sun YJ, Fang DH, Zhao Q, Huang JH, et al. <lb/>Sex-influenced association of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease with <lb/>colorectal adenomatous and hyperplastic polyps. World J <lb/>Gastroenterol 2017;23:5206-15. <lb/>22. Sun ZJ, Huang YH, Wu JS, Yang YC, Chang YF, Lu FH, et al. The <lb/>association of serum lipids with the histological pattern of <lb/>rectosigmoid adenoma in Taiwanese adults. BMC Gastroenterol 2011; <lb/>11:54. <lb/>23. Liu CS, Hsu HS, Li CI, Jan CI, Li TC, Lin WY, et al. Central obesity and <lb/>atherogenic dyslipidemia in metabolic syndrome are associated with <lb/>increased risk for colorectal adenoma in a Chinese population. BMC <lb/>Gastroenterol 2010;10:51. <lb/>24. Tsilidis KK, Brancati FL, Pollak MN, Rifai N, Clipp SL, Hoffman-Bolton J, <lb/>et al. Metabolic syndrome components and colorectal adenoma in the <lb/>CLUE II cohort. Cancer Causes Control 2010;21:1-10. <lb/>25. Chronis A, Thomopoulos K, Sapountzis A, Triantos C, Kalafateli M, <lb/>Kalofonos C, et al. Adiposity factors are not related to the presence of <lb/>colorectal adenomas. Clin Exp Gastroenterol 2011;4:257-61. <lb/>26. Wang C, Li P, Xuan J, Zhu C, Liu J, Shan L, et al. Cholesterol enhances <lb/>colorectal cancer progression via ROS elevation and MAPK signaling <lb/>pathway activation. Cell Physiol Biochem 2017;42:729-42. <lb/>27. Cowey S, Hardy RW. The metabolic syndrome: a high-risk state for <lb/>cancer? Am J Pathol 2006;169:1505-22. <lb/>28. Ahmad A, Ahsan H. Biomarkers of inflammation and oxidative stress in <lb/>ophthalmic disorders. J Immunoassay Immunochem 2020;41:257-71. <lb/>29. Pérez-Rodríguez L, Romero-Haro AA, Sternalski A, Muriel J, Mougeot F, <lb/>Gil D, et al. Measuring oxidative stress: the confounding effect of lipid <lb/>concentration in measures of lipid peroxidation. Physiol Biochem Zool <lb/>2015;88:345-51. <lb/>30. Borgquist S, Butt T, Almgren P, Shiffman D, Stocks T, Orho-Melander M, <lb/>et al. Apolipoproteins, lipids and risk of cancer. Int J Cancer 2016;138: <lb/>2648-56. <lb/>31. Kimak E, Nurczyk K, Skoczylas T, Duma D, Gieroba R, Solski J. Fibroblast <lb/>growth factor 21, epidermal growth factor receptor, interleukin 6, <lb/>myeloperoxidase, lipid hydroperoxide, apolipoproteins A-1 and B, as <lb/>well as lipid and lipoprotein ratios as diagnostic serum biomarkers for <lb/>gastric cancer. Pol Arch Intern Med 2019;129:559-62. <lb/>32. Ma M, Yuan S, Chen Y, Zhou Z. Preoperative apolipoprotein <lb/>B/apolipoprotein A1 ratio: a novel prognostic factor for gastric cancer. <lb/>Onco Targets Ther 2018;11:2169-76. <lb/>33. Liu YL, Qian HX, Zhou XJ, Zhang B. Serum LDL-C and LDL-C/HDL-C ratio <lb/>are positively correlated to lymph node stages in males with colorectal <lb/>cancer. Hepatogastroenterology 2011;58:383-7. <lb/>34. Isakov NF, Sagi SZ, Webb M, Halpern Z, Shibolet O, Kariv R. Distinct <lb/>metabolic profiles are associated with colorectal adenomas and <lb/>serrated polyps. Obesity 2017;25:72-80. <lb/>35. Fu Z, Shrubsole MJ, Smalley WE, Wu H, Chen Z, Shyr Y, et al. Lifestyle <lb/>factors and their combined impact on the risk of colorectal polyps. Am J <lb/>Epidemiol 2012;176:766-76. <lb/>36. Martinez-Useros J, Garcia-Foncillas J. Obesity and colorectal cancer: <lb/>molecular features of adipose tissue. J Transl Med 2016;14:21. <lb/></listBibl>

        <div type="annex">Supplementary Material: This article contains supplementary material <lb/>(https://doi.org/10.1515/almed-2023-0170). <lb/>Article Note: A translation of this article can be found here: https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1515/almed-2024-0060. <lb/></div>

        <page>282 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Huang et al.: The role of BMI and serum lipid in colorectal polyps </note>


	</text>

</TEI>