<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Assessing Air Quality Using Multivariate Statistical Approaches</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Nguyen Quoc</forename>
          <surname>Pham</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Giao Thanh</forename>
          <surname>Nguyen</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-07T08:33:23.447Z">11/7/2025 8:33:23 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Ital Publication</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.28991/cej-2024-010-02-012</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Nguyen Quoc Pham, Giao Thanh Nguyen. (2024). Assessing Air Quality Using Multivariate Statistical Approaches. Civil Engineering Journal, 10(2), 521-533. DOI: 10.28991/cej-2024-010-02-012</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-07T08:33:02.883588Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-07T08:33:02.883588Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>Available online at www.HighTechJournal.org <lb/>HighTech and Innovation <lb/>Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/>410 <lb/>ISSN: 2723-9535 <lb/>A Consumer Data Privacy Protection Model Based on Non-Parametric <lb/>Statistics for Dynamic Data Publishing in e-Commerce Platforms <lb/>Jiao Jia 1* <lb/>1 Southwest Jiaotong University Hope College, Chengdu, Sichuan, 610400, China. <lb/>Received 07 December 2023; Revised 24 April 2024; Accepted 08 May 2024; Published 01 June 2024 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Objectives: Consumer data privacy on e-commerce platforms is increasingly crucial. This study aims to investigate privacy <lb/>protection mechanisms, particularly focusing on personal and corporate secrets. It seeks to understand individual <lb/>perspectives on privacy and preferences for data disclosure. The primary objective is to explore methods for safeguarding <lb/>personal information while maintaining data integrity. Methods/Analysis: We employ non-parametric statistical techniques <lb/>to analyze consumer behavior and preferences on e-commerce platforms. This involves examining patterns of data <lb/>disclosure and identifying sensitive information shared by users. By studying communication dynamics and recording <lb/>practices, we assess the efficacy of current privacy protection measures. Novelty/Improvement: This study contributes to <lb/>the understanding of consumer privacy protection by emphasizing the importance of non-parametric statistical methods in <lb/>e-commerce research. Our findings underscore the need for enhanced privacy measures. We advocate for further research <lb/>and development of innovative privacy-enhancing technologies to address evolving privacy challenges in online <lb/>commerce. Findings: Our research highlights the significance of personal privacy concerns in e-commerce settings. We <lb/>identify a spectrum of privacy attitudes among users, ranging from strict confidentiality to selective disclosure. <lb/>Furthermore, our analysis reveals potential vulnerabilities in current privacy safeguards, particularly regarding the <lb/>collection and storage of sensitive data on e-commerce platforms. <lb/>Keywords: Non-Parametric Statistics; Dynamic Data; Electronic Commerce; Consumer Privacy. <lb/></front>

        <body>1. Introduction <lb/>Since everyone lives in a digital age and can access data with the help of modern-aided technologies, mobile security <lb/>has never been more important. When taking lessons, students were routed to e-commerce platforms, shoppers were <lb/>able to access e-and mobile commerce, and office workers were able to access online work-from-home modes of internet <lb/>access both during and after the COVID-19 pandemic. A complete strategy for protecting customer privacy in online <lb/>commerce environments is suggested by the customer Data Privacy Protection Model, which is based on non-parametric <lb/>statistics for dynamic data publishing on e-commerce platforms. To address the changing issues of privacy protection, <lb/>this strategy combines dynamic data publishing procedures with sophisticated statistical methodologies [1, 2]. <lb/>The approach permits the investigation of customer behavior and preferences while upholding data confidentiality <lb/>by utilizing non-parametric statistical techniques. The privacy of sensitive data saved on e-commerce platforms is <lb/>protected by the use of encryption methods and secure communication routes. Dynamic data publication techniques are <lb/>included in the concept, which permits information to be securely distributed while maintaining customer <lb/></body>

        <front>* Corresponding author: jiajiao870909@163.com <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.28991/HIJ-2024-05-02-013 <lb/>➢ This is an open access article under the CC-BY license (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/>© Authors retain all copyrights. <lb/></front>

        <note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>411 <lb/></page>

        <body>confidentiality. This approach attempts to provide a strong framework for customer data privacy protection in the <lb/>dynamic and fast-paced world of e-commerce platforms using a combination of encryption, statistical analysis, and <lb/>dynamic data management. <lb/>For dynamic data publishing on e-commerce platforms, the Consumer Data Privacy Protection Model based on non-<lb/>parametric statistics is a state-of-the-art solution meant to tackle the complex issues related to consumer privacy in online <lb/>purchasing environments. Fundamentally, this approach acknowledges how crucial it is to protect personal data while <lb/>maintaining the smooth operation of e-commerce platforms. The concept protects individual privacy while enabling <lb/>sophisticated consumer data analysis through the use of non-parametric statistical methods [3, 4]. <lb/>The study investigated the moral ramifications and potential for data phishing by consumers who used unencrypted <lb/>electronic apps downloaded on cell phones through m-commerce sites. Using a combination of methods, the study <lb/>checks the secure information of M-commerce data, conducts semi-structured discussions with consumers and industry <lb/>experts, and analyzes pertinent literature [5]. The study was based on conventional hidden stochastic modeling. Notably, <lb/>we employed a model-free method that eliminates a specific reaction time distribution shape. This has the significant <lb/>benefit of preventing results that could be untrustworthy when an incorrect reaction time allocation is anticipated [6]. <lb/>The study proposed a dual-channel feature extraction module-based multivariate time-series anomaly detection <lb/>approach. Using the spatial characteristics of a short-time Fourier transformation (STFT) and the graphed attentiveness <lb/>system, respectively, the module targeted the spatial and temporal characteristics of the multivariate information. The <lb/>efficiency of the model in detecting anomalies is therefore enhanced by fusing the two characteristics [7]. The article <lb/>addressed customer privacy security between crypto-currency and adaptable clients, as well as the significance of e-<lb/>commerce online purchasing software&apos;s dependability. Based on that, the article used theoretical inquiry and empirical <lb/>investigation to explore the effects of consumer platform-based shopping portals on credibility as well as the elements <lb/>and mechanisms that govern consumer shopping behavior. It also creates a survey verification table for block-chain <lb/>technology and mobile client privacy safeguarding [8]. The research exposed a variety of factors that contribute to <lb/>security lapses that compromise the integrity of online transactions. The report identified a range of actions that <lb/>organizations could take to combat the growing risk to the security of web-based companies. Users&apos; attention has been <lb/>drawn to discussions about privacy and security issues in the field of information sciences and data privacy [9]. The <lb/>study suggested a threshold secret exchange system with a verified threshold homomorphic encryption approach to <lb/>create a secure and provable statistical analysis strategy for an e-commerce platform. By using a unique distribution <lb/>model to provide secret shares, our method reduced the need for secure channels by approximately 40% when compared <lb/>to a typical criterion privacy sharing scheme [10]. <lb/>The limitations of earlier research are addressed in this study, which focuses on the following areas: consumer <lb/>perceptions and behaviors regarding data privacy in e-commerce; the effectiveness of current security measures in online <lb/>transactions; and the lack of research on workable solutions for improving privacy and security in e-commerce platforms, <lb/>specifically about data phishing and cryptography techniques. <lb/>Contribution <lb/>The paper presents a thorough analysis of privacy protection strategies, focusing on corporate and individual secrets. <lb/>This richness makes it possible to comprehend the several facets of privacy concerns in e-commerce in a nuanced <lb/>manner. The research improves the depth and dependability of the analysis by introducing novel analytical strategies <lb/>that are suited to the complexity of e-commerce privacy data through the use of non-parametric statistical methods. <lb/>It highlights the need for further research and development of novel privacy-enhancing technologies in e-commerce, <lb/>defines a range of user privacy attitudes, highlights flaws in the security measures in place, and promotes tailored privacy <lb/>solutions. The second part of this study provides the method of this research, the third part explores the result analysis, <lb/>and the fourth part discusses the study&apos;s conclusion. <lb/>2. Research Methods <lb/>In methodology, we used the algorithm of correlation factors of non-parametric statistical and multiple correlations <lb/>that described the coefficients of correlation in four steps. Figure 1 shows the process of methodology. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>412 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 1. The process of methodology <lb/>2.1. Correlation Factors of Non-Parametric Statistical Algorithms <lb/>The concept of &quot;correlation&quot; is derived from the investigation of height genes in the human body. Correlation can be <lb/>defined as &quot;when one variable changes, another variable changes&quot; and the statistics that measure correlation is a <lb/>correlation. In these data, the duty is bigger and the correlation degree is higher, but the duty is low and the correlation <lb/>degree is low. In addition, the link is directional, when one variable increases, this change is called direct ratio, reduced <lb/>when the other variables, this change is called negative correlation. <lb/>cov(X, Y) Covariance measures the degree to which two random variables vary together. If the covariance is positive, <lb/>it indicates that as one variable increases, the other tends to increase as well and vice versa. If the covariance is negative, <lb/>it means that as one variable increases, the other tends to decrease. <lb/>Here σ X σ Y denotes the standard deviation that measures the spread or dispersion of a random variable&apos;s values around <lb/>its mean. It provides a measure of how much the values of a random variable deviate from the mean.μX and μY represent <lb/>the means (or expected values) of the random variables X and Y respectively. E (Expectation operator), this operator <lb/>calculates the expected value, which is the mean of a random variable when averaged over all possible outcomes. <lb/>The relationship number is defined as the quotient of the covariance and standard deviation between two variables: <lb/>ρ X,Y = <lb/>cov (X,Y) <lb/>σ X σ Y <lb/>= <lb/>E[(X-μX)(Y-μY)] <lb/>σ X σ Y <lb/>(1) <lb/>This is the population correlation coefficient. By estimating the covariance and standard deviation, between two sets <lb/>of data points 𝑋 and 𝑌, where n is the number of data points, X i and Y i are individual data points from each set and X ⃐ <lb/>and Y ⃐ are the means (or averages) of the respective data sets. r Indicates a perfect positive linear relationship, Pearson <lb/>correlation coefficient can be obtained: <lb/>r = <lb/>∑ <lb/>n <lb/>i=1 (X i -X ⃐ )(Y i -Y ⃐ ) <lb/>√ ∑ <lb/>n <lb/>i=1 (X i -X ⃐ ) <lb/>2 √ ∑ <lb/>n <lb/>i=1 (Y i -Y ⃐ ) <lb/>2 <lb/>(2) <lb/>r = <lb/>1 <lb/>n-1 <lb/>∑ ( <lb/>X i -X ⃐ <lb/>σX <lb/>) ( <lb/>Y i -Y ⃐ <lb/>σY <lb/>) <lb/>n <lb/>i=1 <lb/>(3) <lb/>where the standard score, the sample mean and sample standard deviation of the sample respectively. <lb/>X i -X ⃐ <lb/>σX <lb/>、X ⃐ σXX i <lb/>Since it is similar, μ x = E(X), σ X <lb/>2 = E[(X -E(X) 2 )] = E[X 2 ] -E 2 [X], Y. <lb/>And: <lb/>E[(X -E(X))(Y -E(Y))] = E[XY] -E[X]E[Y] <lb/>(4) <lb/>Therefore, the correlation coefficient can also be expressed as: <lb/>ρ X,Y = <lb/>E(XY)-E(X)E(Y) <lb/>√E(X 2 )-(E(X)) 2 √E(Y 2 )-(E(Y)) 2 <lb/>(5) <lb/>For the sample Pearson correlation coefficient: <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>413 <lb/></page>

        <body>r xy = <lb/>∑ x i y i -nxy ̅̅̅̅̅ <lb/>(n-1)s x s x <lb/>= <lb/>n ∑ x i y i -∑ x i ∑ y i <lb/>√n ∑ x i <lb/>2 -(∑ x i ) 2 √n ∑ y i <lb/>2 -(∑ y i ) 2 <lb/>(6) <lb/>Partial correlation coefficient: It&apos;s a random variable. X, Y, ξ 1 , ξ 2 , … , ξ p p + 2 <lb/>When the partial correlation coefficient refers to the correlation coefficient and after removing the influence of the <lb/>third variable: p = 1ξ 1 X. YXY. <lb/>r XY1 = <lb/>(r XY -r Y1 r X1 ) <lb/>√1-r X1 <lb/>2 √1-r X1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(7) <lb/>This represents Pearson correlation coefficient. X, Y, r X1 , r r 1 XY, Xξ 1 , Yξ 1 . When the type of promotion, the partial <lb/>correlation coefficient is the number of the correlation between and after removing the influence. The formula is as <lb/>follows: <lb/>p = 2ξ 1 , ξ 2 X, YXY <lb/>(8) <lb/>r XY12 = <lb/>(r XY1 -r Y21 r X21 ) <lb/>√1-r X21 <lb/>2 √1-r Y21 <lb/>2 <lb/>(9) <lb/>r XY133 = <lb/>(r XY12 -r Y312r X312 ) <lb/>√1-r X312 <lb/>2 <lb/>√1-r Y312 <lb/>2 <lb/>(10) <lb/>Semi-partial correlation coefficient: <lb/>If only to have an impact, it&apos;s called a semi-partial correlation coefficient. The formula is as follows: ξ 1 x <lb/>r Y(X11) = <lb/>(I XY -r Y1 r X1 ) <lb/>√1-r X1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(11) <lb/>Multiple correlation coefficients: <lb/>Describe the multiple correlation coefficients with the correlation between variables, mainly divided into four steps: <lb/>Initialization: analysts must be in Certificate Authority (CA) identifying the certification bodies. The CA allows the <lb/>analyst to generate public keys and authentication keys at the beginning [11, 12]. <lb/>Data collection and storage: When massive data is generated, the remaining data in each processing process is collected <lb/>by the collection center, distributed randomly through a secure channel and transmitted to multiple data servers for <lb/>storage. <lb/>Cipher text operation process: The user&apos;s data is received by each data server. Implement the confidential data between <lb/>multiple servers and network steps to save the cipher. <lb/>Information retrieval: The information server to confirm the user&apos;s recognition and instructions after receiving message <lb/>parsing instructions will conform to the requirements of the data back to the analytic program. Analysts in their private <lb/>keys are used to encrypt and classify the corresponding analysis conclusions. <lb/>The mode of the database is a database that contains multiple data servers. In this system, all data is true, that is to <lb/>say, all the data that follow the convention and the execution time, will be as far as possible from the execution of this <lb/>agreement for more information. In the process of use, there are more than three data, whereas, in a real environment, <lb/>the number of data servers will be more than three. In this mode, when multiple data servers exist at the same time, all <lb/>the servers in this mode can guarantee their security, so that one of the servers in this mode cannot be attacked. <lb/>This model mainly studies the inside and outside of the two different ways of being offensive and defensive. Here, <lb/>outside of the attack, it was aimed at the pattern of the attacker hoping to obtain the user&apos;s data from the system without <lb/>knowing the private key. Internal damage is, for example, a malicious action by a system participant, such as a server <lb/>or an analyst, or if they want to learn and recover a confidential message from a program. The model includes three <lb/>aspects: between the user and the server, the server, and the analysis of the communication with the server [13, 14]. <lb/>User profiles can be decimal numbers. Under this condition, the data collection center puts the data into an integer <lb/>and the distributed data, data unit, data and other data are transmitted to the corresponding three data servers. The <lb/>collection center is classified into three and its transmission through the security channel respectively to the data server, <lb/>the server for the following operations: S 1 , S 2 , S 3 . <lb/>S 1 -Select a random number, to encrypt, get the cipher-text and storage; r 1 ∈ Z N <lb/> * λC λ = g λ r 1 <lb/>N (modN 2 ) <lb/>S 2 -Select a random number, to encrypt, get the cipher-text and storage; r 2 ∈ Z N <lb/> * μC μ = g μ r 2 <lb/>N (modN 2 ) <lb/>S 3 -Select a random number, to encrypt, get the cipher-text and storage. r 3 ∈ Z N <lb/> * vC v = g v r 3 <lb/>N (modN 2 ) <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>414 <lb/></page>

        <body>Because it has the following properties: <lb/>C λ * C μ * C v = <lb/>= E(λ, pk) E(μ, pk) E(v, pk) <lb/>= (g λ r 1 <lb/>N ) (g μ r 2 <lb/>N ) (g v r 3 <lb/>N ) (modN 2 ) <lb/>= g λ+μ+v (r 1 r 2 r 3 ) N (modN 2 ) <lb/>= E(λ + μ + v, pk) <lb/>= E(η, pk) <lb/>(12) <lb/>So, the encrypted information is stored in three servers, only the cipher-text multiplication and in the case of knowing <lb/>the private key can get complete information. λ、μ、vη. So, the illicit close sex of the user&apos;s data can be guaranteed, <lb/>the premise is the three data servers that do not separate the data together. <lb/>2.2. Based on Nonparametric Statistics Consumer Information of Electric Business Platform Security <lb/>Safety Guarantee 1: Data storage security, information storage security, and cipher key storage security certificate: <lb/>early in the program, through secret channels, open authentication, and encryption. In this article, both methods are <lb/>based on the minimum version of Secure Hash Algorithm (SHA)-3, r=40, and SHA-3 is the minimum, which provides <lb/>efficient security for most programs. In the process of data collection, using SHA-3 produced an arbitrary number. Due <lb/>to the use of a smaller cryptographic system, data confidentiality, authenticity, and integrity can be maintained between <lb/>the receipt center and the data servers. The user and the server communication, according to SHA-3, produces <lb/>information isolation if it is from the outside or if the server was invaded or colluded with other servers. In the absence <lb/>of a key, the user is unable to determine the block, and data segmentation is necessary to avoid an internal attack on the <lb/>data server. So, the data stored on the server is guaranteed. <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>Likely represents the result of a cryptographic operation, perhaps encryption or decryption.φ represents Euler&apos;s <lb/>totient function.∑ i=1 <lb/>n x i y i This indicates a summation operation, where x i and y i are variables that are summed up <lb/>from 𝑖 = 1 𝑡𝑜 𝑛. pk r represents raising a public key 𝑝𝑘 to the power of r. <lb/>g r(sk 1 +sk 2 +sk 3 +sk 4 ) This part appears to involve exponentiation of a base g raised to the power of the sum of multiple <lb/>secret keys sk 1 + sk 2 + sk 3 + sk 4 all raised to the power of r. (modN 2 )This indicates that the entire expression is taken <lb/>modulo N 2 , where 𝑁 is likely a large composite number. <lb/>The password we can obtain is Analysts calculated according to the private key: 𝑠𝐾 denotes the secret key, 𝐴 is likely <lb/>some input value, 𝑎𝑛𝑑 𝐷 is the result of the operation, computed by rising 𝐴 to the power of sk 4 modulo N 2 . <lb/>sk 4 D = A sk 4 (modN 2 ) <lb/>(13) <lb/>So, there are: <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>= <lb/>φ <lb/>∑ i=1 <lb/>n x i y i pk r <lb/>g r(sk 1 +sk 2 +sk 3 +sk 4 ) (modN 2 ) <lb/>= <lb/>φ <lb/>∑ i=1 <lb/>n x,y i g skr <lb/>g r(sk 1 +sk 2 +sk 3 +sk 4 ) (modN 2 ) <lb/>= φ <lb/>∑ i=1 <lb/>n x i y i (modN 2 ) = (1 + N) p∑ i=1 <lb/>n xy i (modN 2 ) = 1 + (p∑ i=1 <lb/>n x i y i )N(modN 2 ) <lb/>We can get, <lb/>T xy = L(C/D(modN 2 ))/p <lb/>= <lb/>1+(p ∑ <lb/>n <lb/>i=1 x i y i )N)-1 <lb/>Np <lb/>= ∑ <lb/>n <lb/>i=1 x i y i <lb/>(14) <lb/>Similarly, through the above analysis, we can also, verify the effectiveness of the method. ∑ i-1 <lb/>n x i a i , ∑ i-1 <lb/>n y i a i So, <lb/>during the period of data storage, three separate integer confidential information is transmitted via a secret channel to <lb/>three data servers and by the nonparametric statistics password of algorithms for data security operation in security <lb/>fields, are stored in the server S values. The value of 𝑆 typically depends on the specific cryptographic protocol that is <lb/>used. If they don&apos;t have to deal with the problem of nonparametric statistics, the encryption program will become very <lb/>safe and an outside attack also cannot access the file, according to the provisions of the agreement, as long as all the <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>415 <lb/></page>

        <body>passwords are multiplied by time and then decrypted, can obtain confidential information. The user data is carried out <lb/>by the user&apos;s public key cryptographic processing, unless the three data servers do not spread its merger, otherwise, the <lb/>user data we preserve the right of privacy, without a user&apos;s private key, is unable to obtain by the information users. <lb/>In the process of user registration, the user and the data server are done on a secret channel access and transmission <lb/>of the private key. Because of three data servers and the user&apos;s computing device has large operation and transmission <lb/>performance, therefore, Advanced Encryption Standard (AES) is a good safe passage. The key can be made by a public <lb/>key encryption system, such as a Diffie-Hellman key exchange or Rivest-Shamir-Adleman algorithm (RSA). Encrypt <lb/>using AES and Digital Signature Standard (DSS) channel, to ensure the user with the confidentiality, authenticity and <lb/>integrity of the data server. <lb/>Safety Guarantee 2: The security of data parsing -even a breach of one or more servers accomplice, also won&apos;t leak <lb/>personal data [15, 16]. <lb/>The experimental results show that all of the data processing is carried out by three sets of data servers for encrypted <lb/>information exchange, realizing the information exchange of three data servers. The user&apos;s data is always carried out by <lb/>the user&apos;s public key password, even if the internal attack on the other two data servers, without the user&apos;s private key, <lb/>is also unable to obtain the user&apos;s information. In addition, the data server can also use a public way, namely the three <lb/>data communication between the server and the three sets of data to the servo communication, namely a password-based <lb/>approach to secondary password exchange, to ensure the correctness of the three-servo end communication and integrity. <lb/>The server is not credible, there is no crack, and even if someone within the attack or used the most important password, <lb/>8 could not parse out all the information. So, this method can guarantee the safety of data. <lb/>Safety Guarantee 3: The security of the data query is that only a legal order can get the result of the operation. <lb/>Proof: At the time of the visit, permissions authorized by the name will be signed by the user&apos;s manual key and then <lb/>used by the server authentication key to ensure the validity of the license and its correctness using the above-mentioned <lb/>safe passage for the analysts and server communication. To ask for information, the resulting statistics are encrypted, as <lb/>shown in Figure 2, and only after the authentication and certification of authorized users can they use this password to <lb/>crack it to prevent malicious invasion from the outside. <lb/>Figure 2. Based on the parameters of the dynamic data system <lb/>Even if people with authority did not receive the news, even with all the strength, the people can get the password <lb/>but can only get a small piece of data. It is impossible to determine what kind of things they are in the absence of clear <lb/>data. However, there is no place where statistical integration can ensure the patient&apos;s information. Even if an authorized <lb/>user sends the password back through a server, he can&apos;t crack it without the cooperation of three servers, so the hacker <lb/>will only collect some data but not disclose the user&apos;s data. <lb/>Ultimately, only the data that can be used can be obtained when the user cannot statistically understand the data of <lb/>the individual user. In this paper, the digital signature criterion is selected to ensure the correctness and integrity of <lb/>communication between users and servers. This method guarantees the security of the data [17]. <lb/>The above explanation satisfies the security requirements for the system: <lb/>Data storage security: This system will use all data transmitted to multiple data servers for storage, and in the <lb/>security operation of encrypted data, it can also ensure its security. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>416 <lb/></page>

        <body>Data parsing security: No matter which server or multiple servers collude; the user&apos;s data will not be disclosed <lb/>during the association calculation. <lb/>Security of data query: only certified analysts can enter the system, and the certified instructions can get the <lb/>numerical value of the calculation, while unauthorized analysts and illegal instructions cannot get the algorithm. Even <lb/>if the server and the analyst collude, the user&apos;s private data will not be disclosed. <lb/>3. Result Analysis <lb/>3.1. Dynamic Data Plays a Certain Role in the Protection of Consumer Information on e-Commerce Platforms <lb/>The primary protocol is a strong answer to the problem of heterogeneous consumer data scattered across various <lb/>platforms. Utilizing non-parametric statistical encryption approaches, the protocol guarantees safe data transfer and <lb/>analysis while maintaining user privacy. Secure communication lines and data server isolation strengthen the system&apos;s <lb/>defenses against both internal and external threats. In Crypto++5.6.0 Benchmarks, takes one microsecond to perform <lb/>a 1,024-bit simulation. He writes programs in Microsoft Visual C++2005SP1 and uses AMD Holon 8354 on Linux. <lb/>According to this conclusion, in a 1024-bit Pallier decryption system, a simulation with the rest of the Chinese theory <lb/>takes a few microseconds. Taking the maximum computationally complex correlation as an example, when three data <lb/>servers are networked by 100 Gb network sites, the computation and establishment time of communication are 1 minute <lb/>and 1 second. The algorithm in this paper is to support parallel computing. If a data server is running 10 computers at <lb/>the same time, the overall running time will be reduced to 16 seconds in the double correlation calculation. <lb/>The complexity of the three algorithms in the scheme is shown in Table 1. <lb/>Table 1. Complexity Analysis <lb/>Method 1 <lb/>Method 2 <lb/>Method 3 <lb/>Meter complexity <lb/>6 nm <lb/>12 nm <lb/>6 nm( m -1) <lb/>Communication complexity <lb/>0 (nm) <lb/>0 (nm) <lb/>0 (nm 2 ) <lb/>In the process of cipher-text calculation, if each consumer has an attribute and three data servers cooperate, algorithm <lb/>1 is used to calculate equal cipher-text values (where is the number of combinations). mC x , C y , C a C n <lb/>1 = mC n <lb/>1 Equal <lb/>ciphertext values are calculated by algorithm 2; C x 2 , C y 2 , C a 2 C n <lb/>1 = m Equal ciphertext values are calculated by algorithm <lb/>3. C xy , C xa , C m C n <lb/>2 = m(m -1)/2. Finally, the statistical value of the correlation coefficient is calculated [18, 19]. <lb/>Therefore, the computational complexity of the algorithm is respectively: algorithm 1 requires sub-modular operation <lb/>in total and the computational complexity is 6 nm6 nm. In algorithm 2, a total of sub-modular operations should be <lb/>performed, and the computational complexity is 12 nm12 nm. Algorithm 3 requires a total of sub-modular operations <lb/>and the computational complexity is 6 nm(m -1)6 nm(m -1). The communication complexity is respectively: in <lb/>algorithm 1, the data server needs to carry out round communication, and the communication complex complexity <lb/>is (3n -1)m0(nm); in algorithm 2, the data server needs to carry out round communication, and the communication <lb/>complexity is O(nm). (6n -1)m; in algorithm 3, the data server needs to carry out roll communication and the <lb/>communication complexity is (6n -1)m(m -1)/20(nm 2 ). Figure 3 and Table 2 show the Execution time for different <lb/>MBs, among the cryptography algorithms AES takes the lowest time to encrypt the data. <lb/>Table 2 shows execution times (in seconds) for the Advanced Encryption Standard (AES), Data Encryption Standard <lb/>(DES), Elliptical Curve-Diffie-Hellman (ECDH), and BF cryptographic algorithms across different file sizes (MBs). As <lb/>file size increases, execution times generally rise. AES tends to perform better than DES, ECDH, and BF across all file <lb/>sizes. <lb/>Table 2. Execution time of cryptographic algorithms <lb/>File Size <lb/>(MBs) <lb/>Execution Time (Sec) <lb/>AES <lb/>DES <lb/>ECDH <lb/>BF <lb/>100 <lb/>15 <lb/>17 <lb/>17 <lb/>18 <lb/>200 <lb/>24 <lb/>26 <lb/>27 <lb/>25 <lb/>400 <lb/>56 <lb/>58 <lb/>59 <lb/>57 <lb/>600 <lb/>81 <lb/>84 <lb/>85 <lb/>84 <lb/>800 <lb/>105 <lb/>117 <lb/>116 <lb/>115 <lb/>1000 <lb/>161 <lb/>170 <lb/>171 <lb/>169 <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>417 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 3. Execution Time of Cryptographic Algorithms <lb/>3.2. Multi-Information Security Operation Protocol Based on Non-Parametric Statistics <lb/>Problem description: Suppose that a consumer buys or browses goods in a single consumer unit and leaves private <lb/>information in the data servers of multiple platforms. Due to the differences in time, place, unit, etc., the information <lb/>left in each data server is different and incomplete, so each server has its own data for the same attribute, the attribute <lb/>value of the consumer to remember, the information is stored in a server, and the need to each server calculation data <lb/>contribute to participate in the multilateral security, each server and analysts can get a full analysis of consumer data but <lb/>can&apos;t get any information of other participants storage, where; nm(s n ); mXix i (i = 1,2, … , n); mx i1 , x i2 , … … x iv <lb/>To solve the above problems, this paper proposes a multi-party secure computing protocol (Protocol 1), in which <lb/>each participant confidentially analyzes its data to obtain complete consumer analysis data, m. For the convenience of <lb/>description, let m = 3. Enter a single attribute of a consumer, where; nX = (x 1 , x 2 , x 3 , … , x n ); x i = x i1 + x i2 + ⋯ + <lb/>x iv i = 1, 2, 3, … , n; m = 3. <lb/>Because of user data and server communications, each part of the user&apos;s data after a secret channel encryption is sent <lb/>to the corresponding data server because each server is completely isolated and cannot understand other server <lb/>information. If a server is not compromised, the system won&apos;t receive all the information if a foreign adversary is present. <lb/>This method can protect the system from internal attacks. Therefore, the data stored on the server is very secure [20, <lb/>21]. <lb/>In this program, the encryption is carried out by a non-parametric statistical encryption algorithm, it is stored in the <lb/>medical application, and the security calculation is performed in the cipher text. If the problem of non-parametric <lb/>statistics is not dealt with, the cryptographic system is protected, and the hacked person cannot access the files, thus <lb/>ensuring the security of the key. <lb/>Aiming at the user data existing in different user units, the non-parametric statistical homomorphic key is used to <lb/>encrypt the user, and the improved non-parametric statistical algorithm is used to establish multiple security measures <lb/>between the user and the data server to ensure the security of the communication between the user and the data server <lb/>and that the data will not be leaked at the same time. In our system, if there is no damage to any data, the safety of the <lb/>user&apos;s personal information can be ensured. In addition, access control procedures ensure that only permissive analysis <lb/>will yield qualified analysis results. On this basis, through the cooperation of three servers, the user&apos;s personal <lb/>information is treated confidentially. Finally, the methods are verified, including reliability analysis and performance <lb/>analysis. This method can resist both external attacks and internal attacks [22]. <lb/>Encryption Time: Encryption time refers to the amount of time it takes for a cryptographic algorithm to transform <lb/>plaintext into cipher-text. This process involves applying a specific encryption algorithm and possibly additional steps <lb/>such as key generation and initialization vector (IV) generation. <lb/>Decryption Time: Decryption time refers to the amount of time it takes for a cryptographic algorithm to transform <lb/>cipher-text back into plaintext. This process involves applying the decryption algorithm and, if applicable, using the <lb/>decryption key. <lb/>For both encryption and decryption, the choice of algorithm can significantly impact the time taken to perform these <lb/>operations. Some algorithms are designed for speed, while others prioritize security. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>418 <lb/></page>

        <body>Hardware acceleration techniques, such as using dedicated cryptographic hardware or instruction set extensions, can <lb/>reduce encryption and decryption times. <lb/>In scenarios where real-time processing is required, minimizing encryption and decryption times is crucial. This <lb/>involves selecting algorithms and key sizes that balance security with performance requirements. <lb/>Table 3. Comparison of Cryptography algorithm&apos;s Encryption and decryption <lb/>Algorithm <lb/>Encryption Time (seconds) <lb/>Decryption Time (seconds) <lb/>AES <lb/>3.5 <lb/>3.5 <lb/>SHA <lb/>7.0 <lb/>-<lb/>RSA <lb/>6.0 <lb/>6.0 <lb/>In summary, AES tends to have the fastest encryption and decryption times among the three algorithms. Table 3 <lb/>provides rough estimates of the encryption and decryption times based on the common performance characteristics of <lb/>these algorithms. AES generally outperforms SHA in terms of speed and security, while RSA is used for key exchange <lb/>rather than direct encryption and decryption. <lb/>For RSA, the encryption and times increase with the size of the data and key size. AES encryption and <lb/>decryption times remain relatively constant regardless of the data size, assuming the same key size and implementation <lb/>efficiency. SHA is a hashing algorithm and does not perform decryption. Therefore, only encryption times are listed for <lb/>SHA. <lb/>4. Conclusion <lb/>With the rapid development of network technology, electronic commerce has transformed traditional trade practices, <lb/>facilitating daily activities while introducing security challenges. To address these concerns, this paper aims to assess <lb/>the correlation degree of data, particularly within the realm of e-commerce. The study utilizes correlation analysis based <lb/>on customer shopping records to analyze the relationships between various indicators of customer data. This approach <lb/>aims to safeguard customer information by identifying patterns, anomalies, and potential security risks. Additionally, <lb/>several secure multilateral computing mechanisms are implemented to prevent network attacks effectively. Access to <lb/>the network is restricted to authorized analysts only, who can perform complex correlation analysis on the data. <lb/>Furthermore, the paper introduces some public key encryption methods, such as nonparametric statistics, to enhance <lb/>security. Basic principles are discussed, laying a theoretical foundation for future algorithm design. In the context of big <lb/>data, the paper constructs a data-based data segment storage and statistical dependency method for passwords. By <lb/>leveraging advanced encryption methods, the paper aims to strengthen the overall security posture of e-commerce <lb/>systems and ensure the privacy of user data. In terms of encryption and decryption performance, AES typically performs <lb/>better than DES and ECDH; the choice of algorithm is based on several variables, such as security needs, compatibility, <lb/>and the particular use case. The AES algorithm is employed to provide authorization and authentication for users. <lb/>Through statistical analysis of data security measures, the protection of users&apos; personal information from leakage is <lb/>ensured. These efforts are aimed at bolstering user privacy and maintaining the confidentiality of sensitive data <lb/>transmitted over e-commerce networks. <lb/></body>

        <div type="annex">5. Declarations <lb/></div>

        <div type="availability">5.1. Data Availability Statement <lb/>The data presented in this study are available on request from the corresponding author. <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">5.2. Funding <lb/>The author received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">5.3. Institutional Review Board Statement <lb/>Not applicable. <lb/>5.4. Informed Consent Statement <lb/>Not applicable. <lb/></div>

        <div type="conflict">5.5. Declaration of Competing Interest <lb/>The author declares that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have <lb/>appeared to influence the work reported in this paper. <lb/></div>

        <note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 2, June, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>419 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>6. References <lb/>[1] Yuniar, A. D. (2024). Thin privacy boundaries: proximity and accessibility of E-commerce privacy policy in young consumers of <lb/>Indonesia. International Journal of Social Economics, 1-11. doi:10.1108/IJSE-11-2022-0740. <lb/>[2] Tao, S., Liu, Y., &amp; Sun, C. (2024). Understanding information sensitivity perceptions and its impact on information privacy <lb/>concerns in e-commerce services: Insights from China. Computers and Security, 138, 103646. doi:10.1016/j.cose.2023.103646. <lb/>[3] Tao, S., Liu, Y., &amp; Sun, (2024). Examining the inconsistent effect of privacy control on privacy concerns in e-commerce <lb/>services: The moderating role of privacy experience and risk propensity. Computers and Security, 140. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.cose.2024.103794. <lb/>[4] Mutambik, I., Lee, J., Almuqrin, A., Zhang, J. Z., &amp; Homadi, A. (2023). The Growth of Social Commerce: How It Is Affected by <lb/>Users&apos; Privacy Concerns. Journal of Theoretical and Applied Electronic Commerce Research, 18(1), 725-743. <lb/>doi:10.3390/jtaer18010037. <lb/>[5] Paulson, G. (2024). Assessing data phishing risks associated with unencrypted apps on smartphones with non-parametric test and <lb/>random forest model: Insights from Kuwait phishing scam calls. Journal of Engineering Research (Kuwait), 1-7. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.jer.2023.09.017. <lb/>[6] Verdier, H., Laurent, F., Cassé, A., Vestergaard, C. L., Specht, C. G., &amp; Masson, J. B. (2023). Simulation-based inference for <lb/>nonparametric statistical comparison of biomolecule dynamics. PLoS Computational Biology, 19(2), 1010088. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1010088. <lb/>[7] Xu, Z., Yang, Y., Gao, X., &amp; Hu, M. (2023). DCFF-MTAD: A Multivariate Time-Series Anomaly Detection Model Based on <lb/>Dual-Channel Feature Fusion. Sensors, 23(8), 3910. doi:10.3390/s23083910. <lb/>[8] Liu, R., &amp; Wang, E. (2023). Blockchain and mobile client privacy protection in e-commerce consumer shopping tendency <lb/>identification application. Soft Computing, 27(9), 6019-6031. doi:10.1007/s00500-023-08099-8. <lb/>[9] Srivastava, S., &amp; Shobhna Jeet, D. R. (2023). E-Commerce and Privacy Issues. Russian Law Journal, XI(5), 2170-2175. <lb/>[10] Shen, H., Wu, G., Xia, Z., Susilo, W., &amp; Zhang, M. (2023). A Privacy-Preserving and Verifiable Statistical Analysis Scheme for <lb/>an E-Commerce Platform. IEEE Transactions on Information Forensics and Security, 18, 2637-2652. <lb/>doi:10.1109/TIFS.2023.3269669. <lb/>[11] Ren, X. Y., Zhang, P., &amp; Zhou, Y. Q. (2019). Distinct model on privacy protection of dynamic data publication. Cluster <lb/>Computing, 22, 15127-15136. doi:10.1007/s10586-018-2506-3. <lb/>[12] Sharma, K. (2010). An Evaluation of Consumer Privacy Protection in E-Commerce Websites: A Comparative Study of Six E-<lb/>Stores: Part II. EDPACS, 42(2), 1-19. doi:10.1080/07366981.2010.526040. <lb/>[13] Bresson, G., &amp; Logossah, K. (2011). Crowding-out effects of cruise tourism on stay-over tourism in the Caribbean: Non-<lb/>parametric panel data evidence. Tourism Economics, 17(1), 127-158. doi:10.5367/te.2011.0028. <lb/>[14] Wu, Y., Wang, W., Toll, M., Alkhoury, W., Sauter, M., &amp; Kolditz, O. (2011). Development of a 3D groundwater model based <lb/>on scarce data: The Wadi Kafrein catchment/Jordan. Environmental Earth Sciences, 64, 771-785. doi:10.1007/s12665-010-0898-<lb/>3. <lb/>[15] Yonghui, Z., Su, L., &amp; Phillips, P. C. (2011). Testing for Common Trends in Semiparametric Panel Data Models with Fixed <lb/>Effects. Cowles Foundation Discussion Paper No. 1832. doi:10.2139/ssrn.1951892. <lb/>[16] Yang, C. (2011). Analysis on protection of e-commerce consumer network privacy. Procedia Engineering, 15, 5519-5524. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.proeng.2011.08.1024. <lb/>[17] Diwandari, S., &amp; Hidayat, A. T. (2021, March). Comparison of classification performance based on dynamic mining of user <lb/>interest navigation pattern in e-commerce websites. In Journal of Physics: Conference Series: IOP Publishing, 1844(1), 012025. <lb/>doi:10.1088/1742-6596/1844/1/012025. <lb/>[18] Wang, X., Dai, H. N., &amp; Zhang, K. (2019). Secure and flexible economic data sharing protocol based on ID-based dynamic <lb/>exclusive broadcast encryption in economic system. Future Generation Computer Systems, 99, 177-185. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.future.2018.11.013. <lb/>[19] Sreedevi, E. P., Kattumannil, S. K., &amp; Dewan, I. (2021). A non-parametric test for independence of time to failure and cause of <lb/>failure for discrete competing risks data. Statistics, 55(5), 1107-1122. doi:10.1080/02331888.2021.1975712. <lb/>[20] Serrano, E., Such, J. M., Botía, J. A., &amp; García-Fornes, A. (2014). Strategies for avoiding preference profiling in agent-based e-<lb/>commerce environments. Applied Intelligence, 40(1), 127-142. doi:10.1007/s10489-013-0448-2. <lb/>[21] Qiuyang, G., Qilian, N., Xiangzhao, M., &amp; Zhijiao, Y. (2019). Dynamic social privacy protection based on graph mode partition <lb/>in complex social network. Personal and Ubiquitous Computing, 23, 511-519. doi:10.1007/s00779-019-01249-6. <lb/>[22] Ding, H., Peng, C., Tian, Y., &amp; Xiang, S. (2019). A risk adaptive access control model based on Markov for big data in the cloud. <lb/>International Journal of High-Performance Computing and Networking, 13(4), 464-475. doi:10.1504/IJHPCN.2019.099269. </listBibl>


	</text>

</TEI>