<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>EURASIA Journal of Mathematics, Science and Technology Education, 2024, 20(6), em2449 <lb/>ISSN:1305-8223 (online) <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Research Paper <lb/>https://doi.org/10.29333/ejmste/14587 <lb/>© 2024 by the authors; licensee Modestum. This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/>tothk0711@gmail.com (*Correspondence) <lb/>marisa.michelini@uniud.it <lb/>philipp.bitzenbauer@fau.de <lb/>From light polarization to quantum physics: Supporting lower secondary school <lb/>students&apos; transition from gestalt to functional thinking <lb/>Kristóf Tóth 1,2* , Marisa Michelini 3 , Philipp Bitzenbauer 4 <lb/>1 Institute of Physics and Astronomy, ELTE Eötvös Loránd University, Budapest, HUNGARY <lb/>2 Czuczor Gergely Benedictine Secondary School, Győr, HUNGARY <lb/>3 Physics Education Research Unit, University of Udine, Udine, ITALY <lb/>4 Department of Physics, Friedrich-Alexander-Universität Erlangen-Nürnberg, Erlangen, GERMANY <lb/>Received 11 February 2024 ▪ Accepted 24 April 2024 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>In this paper, we present a new minimal mathematical conceptual approach to quantum <lb/>mechanics using light polarization for lower secondary school students with the aim of bringing <lb/>students closer to the so-called quantum mechanical way of thinking. We investigated how <lb/>students think about some of the basic concepts and fundamental laws and we found that certain <lb/>concepts are quite well-understandable in younger grades too. We studied the introduction of <lb/>the so-called state circle, which can faithfully represent quantum mechanical formalism without <lb/>involving students in abstract algebraic calculations. We then categorized and analyzed students&apos; <lb/>thoughts on the superposition principle and the lack of trajectory, finding that the concept of <lb/>measurement and the lack of trajectory were problematic. We explored that younger students <lb/>tend to hold gestalt-like mental models of quantum concepts, while at the same time being able <lb/>to use visualizations correctly for reasoning in the quantum realm. Overall, this paper provides <lb/>evidence in favor of introducing basic features of quantum mechanics as early as in lower <lb/>secondary school. <lb/>Keywords: quantum physics, polarization, conceptual approach, photon, mental models <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>The introduction of the basic ideas of quantum <lb/>mechanics (QM) via two-state systems is receiving a lot <lb/>of attention (Faletič et al., 2024; Greinert &amp; Müller, 2023; <lb/>Michelini et al., 2021, 2022a, 2022b; Nobel Prize Outreach <lb/>AB, 2023; Quantum Technology Education Project, 2020; <lb/>Tóth &amp; Tél, 2023). One possible way of doing so is to use <lb/>photon polarization, known as Dirac approach, named <lb/>after Paul Dirac, who first applied light polarization to <lb/>introduce QM (Dirac, 1958). One of the first <lb/>developments of Dirac approach in secondary school <lb/>material was carried out by researchers from Udine <lb/>(Ghirardi et al., 1996; Michelini et al., 2000). They <lb/>introduced the elements of quantum concepts and <lb/>simplified mathematics through easy-to-implement <lb/>student experiments and single photons thought <lb/>experiments (Cobal et al., 2002a, 2002b; Michelini, 2008; <lb/>Michelini &amp; Stefanel, 2006, 2014, 2023). In addition, many <lb/>educational pathways making use of light polarization <lb/>have been developed to introduce university students <lb/>(French &amp; Taylor, 1978; Singh, 2008; Tóth, 2023, 2024) <lb/>and secondary school learners to QM (Migdał et al., 2022; <lb/>Müller &amp; Wiesner, 2002; Schlummer et al., 2022) and to <lb/>quantum computing (Berbhardt, 2019; Bondani et al., <lb/>2022; Migdał et al., 2022; Walsh et al., 2022). <lb/>Since the subject of physics ends at the age of 16 for <lb/>several citizens, QM does not reach the wider society. In <lb/>fact, material for lower grade is not only relevant for its <lb/>cultural value (Stadermann &amp; Goedhart, 2021) and for <lb/>contributing to the statistical thinking that is so often <lb/>lacking. However, to the best of our knowledge, no such <lb/>implementation has been empirically researched yet. In <lb/>this paper we present a new teaching-learning sequence, <lb/>which comprises five lessons (45 minutes each) that <lb/>requires almost no mathematics and focuses on the basic <lb/>concepts for lower secondary school students. The <lb/>presented learning path relies on the previous materials <lb/>of Udine (Cobal et al., 2002a, 2022b; Ghirardi et al., 1996; <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Tóth et al. / From light polarization to quantum physics <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 16 <lb/></page>

			<body>Michelini, 2008; Michelini &amp; Stefanel, 2021, 2023; <lb/>Michelini et al., 2000, 2011). <lb/>As our goal is to present some conceptual <lb/>foundations of QM for its cultural value and to try to <lb/>guide students towards a quantum mechanical way of <lb/>thinking, the mathematical formalism is beyond the <lb/>scope, we focus on the students&apos; initial thinking patterns. <lb/>We investigate students&apos; perceptions of some <lb/>fundamental laws (Krijtenburg-Lewerissa et al., 2018): <lb/>the probability law, the lack of trajectory, quantum <lb/>measurement and the superposition principle. To this <lb/>end, we conducted a field study with n=51 16-year-old <lb/>students at Czuczor Gergely Benedictine Secondary <lb/>School in Győr, Hungary, in the spring of 2023. <lb/>RESEARCH BACKGROUND <lb/>Teaching &amp; Learning Quantum Physics <lb/>Students often interpret quantum phenomena in <lb/>classical terms (Fischler &amp; Lichtfeldt, 1992; Greca &amp; <lb/>Freire, 2003; Johnston et al., 1998; Kalkanis et al., 2003) <lb/>and they tend to use previous classical knowledge in <lb/>quantum situations (Bouchée et al., 2022), for instance <lb/>using a temporal and spatial continuous description of <lb/>quantum phenomena, whereas the quantum formalism <lb/>does not allow for what happens between the <lb/>preparation of state and the measurement: this is the <lb/>classical way of thinking. In addition, researchers from <lb/>Udine have described another reasoning pattern, the <lb/>hidden variable way of thinking. That is, students often <lb/>think that microscopic systems preserve some properties <lb/>of classical macroscopic systems in theory, even if they <lb/>are not knowable/detectable in real experiments, e.g., <lb/>students believe in the temporal and spatial continuous <lb/>description, but they also add that this behavior is not <lb/>accessible due to experimental limitations; and the <lb/>statistical behavior is often due to the uncontrollable <lb/>disturbance caused by the (even ideal) measurement <lb/>itself (Michelini &amp; Stefanel, 2021; Michelini et al., 2011). <lb/>Michelini et al. (2011) proposed that students&apos; arguments <lb/>about the lack of trajectory illustrates their way of <lb/>thinking in QM. <lb/>Developing the quantum mechanical way of thinking is <lb/>difficult in general (Stefani &amp; Tsaparlis, 2009), even for <lb/>younger students, who are more in need of tangible, <lb/>visual models, and representations. However, the <lb/>abstract and unintuitive nature of QM is exacerbated by <lb/>the fact that quantum systems are very difficult to <lb/>visualize and to imagine (Stefani &amp; Tsaparlis, 2009). As <lb/>highlighted in Ubben and Bitzenbauer (2022), the <lb/>quantum models presented are often misunderstood by <lb/>learners, who often believe that the models are an <lb/>upscaled or downscaled exact representations of the real <lb/>phenomena. German researchers identified two <lb/>cognitive dimensions suitable to explain a substantial <lb/>amount of the variance in learners&apos; perceptions of <lb/>quantum concepts. The dimension fidelity of gestalt (FG) <lb/>• describes that the one can understand their way of <lb/>thinking &quot;as exact visual representations of <lb/>phenomena or exact depictions of how things look&quot; <lb/>(Ubben &amp; Bitzenbauer, 2022, p. 1356) and <lb/>• &quot;how much the mental models&apos; gestalt is perceived as <lb/>accurate&quot; (Ubben &amp; Bitzenbauer, 2022, p. 1360). <lb/>For example, gestalt thinking students imagine the <lb/>photons as small balls with certain trajectories. On the <lb/>other hand, the dimension functional fidelity (FF) <lb/>• … describes that the one can understand their <lb/>mental models as &quot;appropriate descriptions of how <lb/>phenomena work&quot; (Ubben &amp; Bitzenbauer, 2022, p. <lb/>1356) and <lb/>• &quot;how much the mental models&apos; underlying abstract <lb/>functionality […] is perceived as accurate&quot; (Ubben &amp; <lb/>Bitzenbauer, 2022, p. 1360). <lb/>It is found that functional and gestalt thinking <lb/>correlate with a high and low conceptual understanding <lb/>of QM, respectively (Ubben &amp; Bitzenbauer, 2023). <lb/>Depending on the manifestation of FG and FF in the <lb/>learners&apos; mental models of the atomic shell, these <lb/>archetypes were designated as non-developed type (low <lb/>FG and low FF), architectural type (high FG and low FF), <lb/>dual type (high FG and high FF) and functional type (low <lb/>FG and high FF). In accordance with Ireson (2000), the <lb/>Udine categories (Michelini &amp; Stefanel, 2021; Michelini <lb/>et al., 2011) can be associated with the German ones. The <lb/>architectural, dual, and functional types correspond to <lb/>classical, hidden variable and quantum mechanical <lb/>thinking, respectively. <lb/>Teaching QM at the secondary school level should <lb/>aim at fostering students&apos; conceptual transition from a <lb/>rather gestalt-oriented to a functional thinking about <lb/>quantum concepts. In the following we therefore <lb/>Contribution to the literature <lb/>• We present a new conceptual approach to QM with minimal mathematics using light polarization for <lb/>lower secondary school students based on previous research from Udine. <lb/>• We provide evidence that it is worth to introduce quantum formalism for some younger students too <lb/>because a portion of them reached the functional thinking; in contrast several students have difficulties to <lb/>understand the lack of trajectory and the concept of quantum measurement. <lb/>• We show that presenting hypotheses related to quantum probabilities and representing states on the state <lb/>circle can enhance younger students&apos; understanding. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">EURASIA J Math Sci Tech Ed, 2024, 20(6), em2449 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 16 <lb/></page>

			<body>overview the students&apos; difficulties in different <lb/>approaches, in particular in Dirac approach. Then we <lb/>focus on Dirac approach considering the gestalt-<lb/>functional transition. <lb/>Introducing Learners to Quantum Physics via Light <lb/>Polarization: A Brief Overview <lb/>Prior research has provided evidence that a <lb/>polarization approach may be conducive to student <lb/>learning about QM. However, learning obstacles <lb/>hindering a transition to a fully functional <lb/>understanding of quantum concepts have been <lb/>documented in prior research. For example, a review <lb/>reported that several university students mistakenly <lb/>think that polarization state could not be described by <lb/>two basic states because polarization can take an infinite <lb/>direction, which requires an infinite basis (Singh &amp; <lb/>Marshman, 2015). There is also a problem in <lb/>distinguishing the abstract Hilbert space from the real <lb/>space (Singh &amp; Marshman, 2015). This is like secondary <lb/>school education, where students often confuse the <lb/>concepts of property (which corresponds to the <lb/>measured values), physical quantities and quantum <lb/>states in Dirac approach (Chiofalo et al., 2022; Michelini &amp; <lb/>Stefanel, 2021; Pospiech et al., 2021). <lb/>Some students often refer to superposition states in a <lb/>mathematical way or as a sum of possible properties or <lb/>often explain the quantum state as a vector (Michelini &amp; <lb/>Stefanel, 2021; Michelini et al., 2022b), which is only a <lb/>mathematical concept showing that students have <lb/>difficulty using conceptual arguments in quantum <lb/>situations. In Michelini et al. (2022b), it is argued that <lb/>students often do not understand physical state and <lb/>measurement even in classical physics, which makes <lb/>them clueless in QM. <lb/>As shown in Passante et al. (2015) and Styer (1996), a <lb/>common misconception is that the reason for the <lb/>probabilistic measurement outcome is the unknown <lb/>state or the mixed state indicating that students do not <lb/>even understand why probability is generally used in <lb/>QM. Several students believed that the effect of the <lb/>measurement can be neglected as in classical physics <lb/>(Montagnani et al., 2023). We note that polarization itself <lb/>is a classical property of light and that this indeed is a <lb/>problem of polarization approach, while students often <lb/>think polarization is a quantum concept itself. <lb/>All approaches to QM agree on the difficulty of <lb/>accepting that quantum objects cannot be described via <lb/>the concept of trajectory. It is widely believed by <lb/>students that quantum objects have well-defined <lb/>position and momentum simultaneously, but this is <lb/>inaccessible because the measurement itself disturbs the <lb/>systems (Montagnani et al., 2023) (hidden variable <lb/>thinking). Previous research in all educational <lb/>approaches has found that students have difficulties in <lb/>accepting the fact that the trajectory of the single <lb/>quantum objects does not exist; and they try to develop <lb/>strategies to preserve the classical concept of particle <lb/>motion (which can be observed in Dirac approach <lb/>(Michelini &amp; Stefanel, 2011) and also in traditional <lb/>approaches (Ambrose et al., 1999; Krijtenburg-Lewerissa <lb/>et al., 2017; Thacker, 2003; Vokos et al., 2002). The above <lb/>problems relate to the most central quantum concepts <lb/>(Fischler &amp; Lichtfeldt, 1992) highlighting the fact that <lb/>conceptualization of QM and comparison with classical <lb/>physics can be a crucial part of secondary school <lb/>education. <lb/>DEVELOPMENT OF A NEW TEACHING-<lb/>LEARNING SEQUENCE ON QUANTUM <lb/>PHYSICS AT LOWER SECONDARY <lb/>SCHOOL LEVEL <lb/>Definition of Key Idea &amp; Goal of Teaching-Learning <lb/>Sequence <lb/>Our aim is to present, through the phenomenon of <lb/>light polarization, a QM learning path that is accessible <lb/>to a wide range of people, with minimal mathematical <lb/>apparatus, and that introduces some of the basic features <lb/>of the subject at a conceptual level, while promoting a <lb/>statistical mindset. The structure of the teaching-<lb/>learning sequence is shown in Table 1. <lb/>Description of Design Process, Time Requirements, &amp; <lb/>Learning Prerequisites <lb/>The teaching-learning sequence is based on the <lb/>following ideas. <lb/>• It is developed according to the model of <lb/>educational reconstruction by Duit et al. (2012). <lb/>• It is embedded in a design-based research process <lb/>of development, evaluation, and refinement <lb/>(Anderson &amp; Shattzcjm 2012), where this paper <lb/>reports on one evaluation cycle withing a larger <lb/>research project (cf. Michelini et al., 2022b). <lb/>• Students had to learn about polarization using <lb/>polarizers and birefringent calcite crystals, <lb/>including the measurement of the Malus law <lb/>before participating in this teaching-learning <lb/>sequence. We highlight that it is not required to <lb/>learn about the wave model of light, since the <lb/>presented <lb/>material <lb/>is <lb/>based <lb/>on <lb/>the <lb/>phenomenological approach to polarization as <lb/>can be seen in (Michelini &amp; Stefanel, 2006, 2014; <lb/>Tóth et al., 2024a). <lb/>• To be appropriate for the use under real school <lb/>conditions, in addition to the phenomenology of <lb/>polarization, only a few lessons are sufficient. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Tóth et al. / From light polarization to quantum physics <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 16 <lb/></page>

			<body>Design Principles of Teaching-Learning Sequence <lb/>Two frames of interpretation: Classical &amp; quantum <lb/>physics <lb/>Although being a fully classical concept, a single <lb/>photon can be assigned polarization states in the <lb/>quantum realm. For example, students may perform <lb/>experiments with high light intensity (Tóth et al., 2024a) <lb/>and then they reinterpret the experiments in terms of <lb/>single photons using a computer simulation Java <lb/>quantum mechanics-JQM (Cobal et al., 2002a, 2022b; <lb/>Tóth et al., 2024b). <lb/>The link between the two interpretive frameworks is <lb/>established by the students accepting the idea that light <lb/>consists of indistinguishable photons and that the <lb/>intensity of monochromatic light is proportional to the <lb/>number of photons, so that the experiments can be <lb/>interpreted in terms of the number of photons. <lb/>Throughout the learning process, we constantly build <lb/>on the possibility that certain incorrect answers given in <lb/>QM are incompatible with classical physics. <lb/>Conceptual framework &amp; reduced mathematics <lb/>The mathematical apparatus is reduced to a <lb/>minimum as has already been proposed in earlier <lb/>research (Hennig et al., 2024). The trigonometric <lb/>functions are left: the students measure the Malus law <lb/>and draw up a table showing the change in intensity for <lb/>angles (in particular 0°, 30°, 45°, 60°, and 90°). This table <lb/>is used as a learning instrument. Only the most basic <lb/>concepts of probability theory are used, such as relative <lb/>frequency, probability, law of large numbers observed in <lb/>simulations, expected value, stochastic deviation; but <lb/>these are all repeated in the quantum context. Statistical <lb/>calculations are fully replaced by JQM simulations, the <lb/>students perform simulations and analyze the stochastic <lb/>result. <lb/>Comparison of classical physics with idealized <lb/>quantum mechanics <lb/>The laws of QM are constantly compared with the <lb/>laws of macroscopic world, which helps to review the <lb/>concepts of classical physics and highlight the <lb/>differences. <lb/>Table 1. Summary of learning path (each lesson is 45 minutes long) <lb/>Lessons Concepts &amp; laws <lb/>Structure of learning path <lb/>Used materials <lb/>Before <lb/>quantum <lb/>studies <lb/>• Light intensity &amp; <lb/>polarization <lb/>• Ideal polarizers <lb/>• Malus law <lb/>(1) Light intensity &amp; polarization of light <lb/>(2) Ideal polarizers &amp; birefringent calcite crystals: Measuring <lb/>Malus law <lb/>Michelini and <lb/>Stefanel (2006, 2014) <lb/>&amp; Tóth et al. (2024a) <lb/>#1 <lb/>• Probability law <lb/>• Relative frequency &amp; <lb/>probability <lb/>• Law of large numbers &amp; <lb/>correspondence principle <lb/>(1) Existence of photons <lb/>(2) Photonic interpretation of Malus law <lb/>(3) Single photon interpretation of Malus &amp; probability laws <lb/>(4) Statistical predictions for many photons: Comparison of <lb/>experimental result with theoretical prediction <lb/>JQM (Cobal et al., <lb/>2002a, 2022b; Tóth <lb/>et al., 2024b) &amp; <lb/>Worksheet #1 (Tóth <lb/>et al., 2024b) <lb/>#2 <lb/>• Mutually exclusive, <lb/>compatible, &amp; incompatible <lb/>properties <lb/>• Uncertainty principle. <lb/>• Superposition principle <lb/>• Quantum measurement <lb/>(1) Polarization property &amp; iconography (*, ◊, &amp; ∆ is horizontal, <lb/>45° &amp; vertical polarization property, respectively) <lb/>(2) Mutually exclusive properties in classical physics &amp; quantum <lb/>mechanics (polarization) <lb/>(3) Compatible &amp; incompatible properties comparing QM with <lb/>macroscopic physics <lb/>(4) Uncertainty principle: Existence of incompatible properties <lb/>(5) Superposition principle: Existence of state in which <lb/>measurement outcome is uncertain <lb/>Worksheet #2 (Tóth <lb/>et al., 2024b) <lb/>#3 <lb/>• Superposition principle <lb/>(1) A comparison of causes of probabilities in everyday life &amp; <lb/>QM <lb/>(2) Comparing effect of measurement in classical &amp; quantum <lb/>physics <lb/>(3) Lack of trajectory <lb/>JQM (Tóth et al., <lb/>2024b) &amp; <lb/>Worksheet #3 (Tóth <lb/>et al., 2024b) <lb/>#4 <lb/>• Probability law <lb/>(1) Two interpretative hypotheses are considered corresponding <lb/>to classical interpretation of probabilities <lb/>(2) Students see that quantum probabilities are due to internal <lb/>nature of microscopic world <lb/>(3) Superposition exists: Physics Nobel Prize 2022 <lb/>Hypotheses (Tóth et <lb/>al., 2024b) <lb/>#5 <lb/>• Quantum states <lb/>• Eigenstates <lb/>• State circle <lb/>• Quantum measurement <lb/>(1) Unit vectors assigned to polarization directions: Quantum <lb/>state &amp; Definition of eigenstates: Permitted states after a <lb/>measurement <lb/>(2) State circle: All states are represented in a circle <lb/>(3) Effect of quantum measurement on state circle <lb/>Worksheet #4 (Tóth <lb/>et al., 2024b) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">EURASIA J Math Sci Tech Ed, 2024, 20(6), em2449 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 16 <lb/></page>

			<body>In the thought experiments, only ideal polarizers and <lb/>calcites are considered: when the loss of light intensity is <lb/>due only to the change in polarization. Therefore, the <lb/>measurement uncertainties caused by the imperfect <lb/>measuring devices are ignored, which helps the <lb/>comparison with classical physics. <lb/>Geometric representation of states <lb/>As described in before, students tend to believe that <lb/>visual models of phenomena are an exact representation <lb/>of the phenomenon (gestalt thinking). Therefore, we try <lb/>to avoid the narrow validity models: States are <lb/>represented in the state circle (Pospiech et al., 2021; Tóth <lb/>&amp; Tél, 2023), where the whole measurement process is <lb/>represented in a physically correct way. The only <lb/>exception is JQM simulations; but students discuss why <lb/>it cannot faithfully represent quantum phenomena. <lb/>Research Questions <lb/>To get an insight into students&apos; thinking about the <lb/>basic concepts, we address our first research question <lb/>(RQ). <lb/>1. RQ1. How students think about the addressed <lb/>concepts (the probability law, lack of trajectory, <lb/>quantum measurement, and superposition state) <lb/>via the presented conceptual approach? <lb/>As we are interested not only in the perceptions of the <lb/>concepts, but also in the thinking style of each student, <lb/>we address our second research question. <lb/>2. RQ2. To what extent does the teaching-learning <lb/>sequence foster the transition towards a <lb/>functional thinking of quantum concepts in <lb/>secondary school students? <lb/>Description of the Teaching-Learning Sequence <lb/>Lesson 1: Probability law <lb/>As Michelini and Stefanel (2021) and Michelini et al. <lb/>(2011, 2022b) propose and based on the design principle <lb/>1, at the beginning, the students are faced with the task <lb/>&quot;If we replace the light source to a single photon source, what <lb/>can the fraction I/I0=N/N0 in the Malus law mean in the case <lb/>of a single photons?&quot; The answer is: it is the probability in <lb/>a sequence of many repeated identical measurements of <lb/>transmission because photons are undividable (the <lb/>probability law). Since photons are indistinguishable, <lb/>measuring many photons together is equivalent to a <lb/>repeated measurement on only a single photon. <lb/>Referring to the design principle 2, the statistical <lb/>analysis is done via JQM: a typical task is when students <lb/>compare the theoretical prediction with the <lb/>experimental result, linking the concept of relative <lb/>frequency with probability, a value fluctuates around the <lb/>relative frequency (design principle 2). Students then <lb/>explore that (design principle 2) for many photons, the <lb/>expected number of transmitted photons approaches the <lb/>mean of the measured number in JQM. Since the Malus <lb/>law gives this expected number, the classical theory of <lb/>light polarization appears in a limit. <lb/>Lesson 2: Uncertainty principle <lb/>We again rely on the proposals of as Michelini and <lb/>Stefanel (2021) and Michelini et al. (2011, 2022b), so we <lb/>start the lesson begins with a thought experiment in <lb/>which a single photon is emitted onto a system of <lb/>polarizers with the same permitted directions. Photons <lb/>will certainly pass through all if they have passed <lb/>through the first one. They have acquired a property, <lb/>called polarization property, which remains the same after <lb/>passing through the others. This property implies that <lb/>photons can certainly pass through a corresponding <lb/>polarizer. Experiments have shown that (design principle <lb/>1) a horizontally polarized light would certainly be <lb/>absorbed by a polarizer with vertical permitted <lb/>direction: horizontally polarized photons do not possess <lb/>the vertical polarization property. The vertical and <lb/>horizontal polarization properties are mutually exclusive <lb/>properties corresponding to mutually exclusive events. <lb/>Measurements always define mutually exclusive <lb/>observable properties; the sum of the probabilities of <lb/>measuring them must be one. <lb/>The students then investigate a thought experiment <lb/>when a single photon with diagonal polarization is <lb/>emitted onto a polarizer with horizontal permitted <lb/>direction. No one can say that a single photon possesses <lb/>vertical/horizontal polarization property, because it is <lb/>impossible to predict the transmission/absorption for a <lb/>single measurement: these observable properties are <lb/>uncertain. The diagonal polarization is incompatible with <lb/>the horizontal/vertical ones. Two properties are <lb/>incompatible if the possession of one makes the <lb/>possession of the other uncertain. This is, where the <lb/>uncertainty principle appears (for deeper explanation, see <lb/>Tóth, 2023, 2024; Tóth &amp; Tél, 2023): incompatible <lb/>properties exist in QM. Two incompatible properties <lb/>cannot certainly be associated with a system <lb/>simultaneously, one of them will always remain <lb/>uncertain; but the uncertain one can also be measured <lb/>with a given probability. If a measurement is <lb/>probabilistic, the photons are initially in a superposition: <lb/>all indistinguishable photons are in the same state (this <lb/>term is used in its ordinary sense) in which the <lb/>measurement outcome is uncertain. Students then make <lb/>comparisons (design principle 3): even ideal <lb/>measurements in QM have effect. <lb/>Lesson 3: Superposition principle <lb/>The lesson begins with a game in which students <lb/>explore the reason for the probabilities behind various <lb/>cases (design principle 3): predicting the suit of the top <lb/>card of a shuffled deck of French cards, whether tossed <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Tóth et al. / From light polarization to quantum physics <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 16 <lb/></page>

			<body>coins will come up heads or tails, or the polarization <lb/>measurement of a single photon. In the previous <lb/>everyday examples, the reason for the probability was <lb/>the unknown properties of the cards and the complexity <lb/>of dropped coins. In contrast in QM, the reason is the <lb/>superposition. Students will also learn that ideal <lb/>quantum measurements can change the polarization of <lb/>photons (superposition collapse) in contrast with <lb/>classical physics. At the end of the lesson, we take the <lb/>idea from Michelini and Stefanel (2021) and Michelini et <lb/>al. (2011, 2022b) articles that if a single photon is emitted <lb/>onto a birefringent calcite crystal, then the spatial <lb/>location of a single photon and its polarization are <lb/>entangled. They explore that a single photon has no certain <lb/>trajectory. Reconsidering the experiment of a single <lb/>photon is emitted onto a polarizer, the photons have also <lb/>no certain trajectory, they are &quot;between&quot; absorption <lb/>(death) and transmission (life) between the polarizer and <lb/>the detector (the analogy of the Schrödinger&apos;s cat). <lb/>Lesson 4: Interpretative hypotheses <lb/>Previously, students considered indistinguishable <lb/>photons, but now, they focus on individual photons <lb/>giving up the indistinguishability, the individual <lb/>photons are endowed with properties; and students are <lb/>introduced to two hypotheses (Michelini &amp; Stefanel, <lb/>2021; Michelini et al., 2011, 2022b) based on our <lb/>macroscopic view: the reason for probabilities will be the <lb/>lack of knowledge. The first is the statistical mixture <lb/>theory, which is analogous to a well-shuffled deck of <lb/>cards (design principle 3). Students apply the shuffled <lb/>deck theory (the top card can be in one of two colors, but <lb/>we have no chance to know what it is) to photons. It is <lb/>assumed that the photons cannot be in a superposition, <lb/>when photons are emitted on a polarizer with horizontal <lb/>permitted direction, they are previously polarized in two <lb/>ways, corresponding to certain transmission and <lb/>absorption (just like the cards are red or black). But we <lb/>do not know the polarization of the individual photons: <lb/>the fate of each photon is determined, but not knowing <lb/>the properties of each photon forces us to use <lb/>probability. Students can disprove this hypothesis by an <lb/>experiment (design principle 1): if there are only two <lb/>polarizations (vertical and horizontal), it would be <lb/>impossible for light with diagonal polarization to pass <lb/>completely through a corresponding ideal polarizer with <lb/>diagonal permitted direction. <lb/>The second hypothesis, called the co-existing properties <lb/>hypothesis, is an upgraded version of the previous one. <lb/>Instead of one, two polarization properties are assigned <lb/>to the individual photons simultaneously: All photons <lb/>possess the property of certain transmission through the <lb/>polarizer with diagonal permitted direction and, in <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">1 In two hypotheses, we have distinguished photons &amp; associated them with properties. These are two examples of so-called <lb/>hidden variable problem. Note that these examples are not suitable to disprove existence of hidden variables. Slightly more <lb/>complicated hidden variable ideas would not be ruled out in such a simple situation. <lb/></note>

			<body>addition, half of the photons possesses the property of <lb/>certain transmission through a polarizer with horizontal <lb/>permitted direction and the other half of them possess <lb/>the property of certain absorption. Thus, a refutation as <lb/>in the previous hypothesis cannot be applied, the <lb/>property gives a result that is consistent with reality. <lb/>Since we do not know which photon has which <lb/>properties, this forces us to use probabilities. The <lb/>hypothesis can nevertheless be disproved. If the <lb/>polarizers with horizontal and diagonal permitted <lb/>directions are placed one after the other, the real <lb/>experiments show that the result varies depending on <lb/>the order of the polarizers, but the hypothesis suggests <lb/>that half of the photons are always expected to pass <lb/>through the system. Students see that probabilities from <lb/>everyday life leads to a contradiction in QM, hence the <lb/>probabilistic behavior and the indistinguishability of <lb/>photons are physical laws 1 . <lb/>Lesson 5: State circle <lb/>In this lesson the state circle (Pospiech et al., 2021; <lb/>Tóth &amp; Tél, 2023) is introduced for representing <lb/>quantum measurement (design principle 4). Like the <lb/>teaching material of Udine (Michelini &amp; Stefanel, 2021; <lb/>Michelini et al., 2011, 2022b) we assign unit vectors to the <lb/>polarization directions of photons, and these represent <lb/>quantum states. The permitted states after a <lb/>measurement are called eigenstates of the measurement. <lb/>We illustrate all states in a state circle, as shown in Table <lb/>2. The red vector is the state u in which a measurement <lb/>is performed, the dashed lines show the permitted states <lb/>after the measurement (H, V). The eigenstates <lb/>correspond to mutually exclusive properties and are <lb/>perpendicular to each other, the eigenstate H is associated <lb/>with certain transmission and the eigenstate V with <lb/>certain absorption. The state u is a superposition state <lb/>because it is not equal to any of the states that can be <lb/>measured. This is the appearance of the superposition <lb/>principle for states. When a measurement is performed, <lb/>this state of a single photon &quot;collapses&quot; into one of the <lb/>eigenstates. <lb/>METHODS <lb/>Study Design &amp; Sample <lb/>This study is an evaluation study with a pre-and <lb/>post-test. The sample comprises n=51 (25 females and 26 <lb/>males) Hungarian secondary school (Czuczor Gergely <lb/>Benedictine Secondary School, Győr, Hungary) students <lb/>(grade 10 with age of 16) who participated in the <lb/>teaching-learning sequence in spring of 2023 during <lb/>their regular physics lessons. Since we examine the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">EURASIA J Math Sci Tech Ed, 2024, 20(6), em2449 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 16 <lb/></page>

			<body>impact of the last two lessons (hypotheses and state <lb/>circle), the students completed the pre-test after lesson 3 <lb/>and the post-test after lesson 5. As they had no previous <lb/>knowledge about QM, they did not write the test before <lb/>the intervention. <lb/>Instrument <lb/>The instrument used in this study comprised a total <lb/>of four tasks that were adopted from Michelini et al. <lb/>(2022). Tasks 1, 2, and 3 are single-choice questions and <lb/>task 4 is an open-ended question. The questionnaire is <lb/>shown in Table 3. <lb/>The answers to each single-choice question contained <lb/>two gestalt thinking answers, one corresponding to a <lb/>classical and one to a hidden variable way of thinking. <lb/>Task 1 is about the probability law in QM. QM way of <lb/>thinking is option &apos;a&apos; indicates that students understand <lb/>that probabilities are unavoidable in QM. Option &apos;b&apos; and <lb/>&apos;c&apos; are related to the classical and the hidden variable <lb/>way of thinking. <lb/>Task 2 is about the effect of quantum measurement. <lb/>Task 3 investigates how students react to the lack of <lb/>trajectory. <lb/>Option &apos;a&apos; and option &apos;b&apos; correspond to the classical <lb/>(photons have well-defined trajectory) and hidden <lb/>Table 2. Pictorial representation of measurement process on state circle (Tóth &amp; Tél, 2023) <lb/>Before measurement <lb/>(prepared state) <lb/>Measurement process <lb/>(superposition collapse) <lb/>After measurement <lb/>(outcome state) <lb/>State (u) of single photons is assigned <lb/>with a red vector. Eigenstates (H &amp; V) <lb/>of measurement are assigned with <lb/>dashed lines. <lb/>Measurement process is indicated as <lb/>a probabilistic change of state into <lb/>one of eigenstates. <lb/>Measurements have changed state of single <lb/>photons into one of eigenstates: H or V. <lb/>Table 3. Questionnaire used in pre-&amp; post-test (QM thinking responses are shown in blue, the gestalt thinking in red, and <lb/>the mixed thinking remained black) <lb/>Task 1. Consider two probabilistic examples! <lb/>(1) There is a 50.0% probability that top card of a shuffled deck of French suit cards is red. Probabilities have to be because of <lb/>lack of knowledge about cards. <lb/>(2) There is a 50.0% probability that a 45° polarized single photon will pass through an ideal polarizer with horizontal permitted <lb/>direction. <lb/>What is reason for using probabilities in (2)? <lb/>(a) In (2), probabilities are used even if we have enough knowledge about photons because uncertainty is an internal nature of <lb/>microworld. <lb/>(b) In (2), probabilities are used because of lack of knowledge about photons. <lb/>(c) In (2), measurement process is unknown, little knowledge about photon-polarizer interaction forces us to use probabilities. <lb/>Task 2. Suppose we have prepared 45° polarized photons. These are emitted onto an ideal polarizer with horizontal permitted <lb/>direction. Suppose that some of these photons have passed through it. What can we say if these transmitted photons encounter <lb/>with a second ideal polarizer with horizontal permitted direction? <lb/>(a) Photons will go through it with certainty. <lb/>(b) Photons have a 50% probability of passing through. <lb/>(c) Photons will be absorbed with certainty. <lb/>20 <lb/>12 <lb/>18 <lb/>1 <lb/>28 <lb/>13 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>NA <lb/>Absolute <lb/>frequency <lb/>Pre-test <lb/>Post-test <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Tóth et al. / From light polarization to quantum physics <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 16 <lb/></page>

			<body>variable way of thinking about motion (photons have <lb/>well-defined trajectory but it is inaccessible), <lb/>respectively. In this task, students were also asked to <lb/>justify their answer because the way of thinking about <lb/>the motion is a good indicator of the students&apos; <lb/>perception. We inductively categorized all justifications <lb/>to get a better insight into the students&apos; ideas. <lb/>Task 4 asks students about superposition principles. <lb/>Students&apos; responses were analyzed, and different <lb/>categories were established. <lb/>Data Analysis <lb/>We answer research question RQ1 by investigating <lb/>the frequency of chosen answer options that are <lb/>indicators for QM thinking apparent among the <lb/>participants. We then examine the students&apos; <lb/>explanations for task 3 (lack of trajectory) and task 4 <lb/>(superposition) and categorize them inductively. <lb/>We tend to answer research question RQ2 by <lb/>categorizing each student&apos;s work into one of the thinking <lb/>types: gestalt, mixed and functional thinking. Mixed <lb/>thinking expresses a well-developed way of thinking <lb/>about quantum phenomena, but also uses elements of <lb/>gestalt thinking in argumentation. We define a student <lb/>as having mixed thinking if: <lb/>• Two single-choice questions correspond to QM <lb/>thinking and the argumentation on trajectory and <lb/>superposition contains only a small gestalt <lb/>element in addition to the functional elements. <lb/>• The trajectory or superposition argument is <lb/>appropriate, but at least two single-choice <lb/>answers do not correspond to QM thinking. <lb/>Table 3 (Continued). Questionnaire used in pre-&amp; post-test (QM thinking responses are shown in blue, the gestalt thinking <lb/>in red, and the mixed thinking remained black) <lb/>Task 3. In classical physics a moving object always has a well-defined path, e.g., a kicked ball follows a parabolic path. What <lb/>can we say about a single photon emitted on a birefringent calcite crystal? Explain your answer! <lb/>(a) As in example of ball, a certain path could also be associated with each individual photon, but in general we do not know <lb/>enough about photons. If we knew enough, we would always know path of them. <lb/>(b) Contrary to example of ball, a certain path can only be theoretically assigned to each individual photons, but it is impossible <lb/>to observe this experimentally, because measuring device disturbs path of photons, so that we get a result different from real <lb/>one. <lb/>(c) In contrast to ball, it is usually impossible to assign a certain path to a single photon, we do not even have theoretical <lb/>possibility of doing so. <lb/>Task 4. In your own words, how would you explain the superposition principle? <lb/>25 <lb/>24 <lb/>2 <lb/>34 <lb/>14 <lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>Absolute <lb/>frequency <lb/>Pre-test Post-test <lb/>12 <lb/>27 <lb/>11 <lb/>1 <lb/>7 <lb/>23 <lb/>20 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>NA <lb/>Absolute <lb/>frequency <lb/>Pre-test Post-test <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">EURASIA J Math Sci Tech Ed, 2024, 20(6), em2449 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 16 <lb/></page>

			<body>If somebody performs worse or better than the mixed <lb/>thinking, we say that the student holds the gestalt or <lb/>functional thinking type. <lb/>FINDINGS <lb/>Findings From Single-Choice Items <lb/>The number of responses to option &apos;c&apos; in task 1 (the <lb/>belief that the probability is used due to the <lb/>measurement process being unknown) is reduced in the <lb/>post-test from 18 to 10, while the number of QM thinking <lb/>responses (probabilities cannot be avoided) is improved <lb/>from 20 to 28. It seems that the studied hypotheses were <lb/>able to decrease the number of responses on option &apos;c&apos;. <lb/>As an effect of lesson 4-lesson 5, there is a strong <lb/>upward trend from 25 to 34 QM thinking answers in task <lb/>2. This shows that students basically remember that <lb/>quantum measurement changes the state of photons, <lb/>and the number of students answering correctly is <lb/>further improved by the introduction of a state circle. <lb/>Task 3 was the most difficult question, in the pre-test <lb/>only 11 and in the post-test 20 students answered <lb/>correctly. There are six students who answered &apos;a&apos; <lb/>(classical motion) in the pre-test and then &apos;b&apos; (hidden <lb/>variable motion) in the post-test, while no students did <lb/>the opposite. Ten students answered &apos;b&apos; and one <lb/>answered &apos;a&apos; in the pre-test and then &apos;c&apos; (quantum <lb/>thinking) in the post-test. We can observe an evolution <lb/>of thinking about trajectory, some students who chose <lb/>the classical way of motion in the pre-test switched to a <lb/>hidden variable way of motion in the post-test and only <lb/>students who chose the hidden variable way of motion <lb/>were able to give QM solution. <lb/>Findings From Open-Ended Questions <lb/>Students&apos; justifications in task 3 (33 responses in total: <lb/>18 students did not give any argument) are summarized <lb/>in Table 4. <lb/>Only four students in the pre-and seven students in <lb/>the post-test argued that single photons do not have a <lb/>certain trajectory. Many students used the concept of <lb/>&apos;measurement&apos; (12 in the pre-and 18 in the post-test) and <lb/>&apos;superposition&apos; (nine and 18, respectively) as an <lb/>argument. A common misconception reported in the <lb/>literature, the &apos;measurement disturbance&apos; (when <lb/>students believe that the effect of the measurement is <lb/>due to the disruptive effect of the non-ideal <lb/>instruments), appeared remarkably few times, only once <lb/>and twice in the pre-and post-test, respectively. <lb/>Table 4. Categories of students&apos; justifications for task 3 (lack of trajectory) (frequency of each category is also shown in <lb/>aggregate &amp; broken down into response options &amp; categories are not mutually exclusive) <lb/>Categories <lb/>Description <lb/>Anchor example <lb/>Total <lb/>Pre Post <lb/>There is no path This category is assigned to an answer, <lb/>which suggests that it is impossible to <lb/>assign a certain path to photons because <lb/>of laws of QM. <lb/>&quot;Because of superposition, even the photon itself does not <lb/>&apos;know&apos; where it is until it is measured, so its path can only be <lb/>determined by probabilities.&quot; <lb/>4 <lb/>7 <lb/>A single photon <lb/>has certain path <lb/>This category is assigned to an answer, <lb/>which suggests that photons have certain <lb/>well-defined trajectories in theory. <lb/>&quot;Photon is in a superposition until it reaches detector, then <lb/>superposition collapses &amp; you find out which orbit photon was <lb/>in.&quot; <lb/>7 <lb/>4 <lb/>Path of a single <lb/>photon is not <lb/>known by us <lb/>This category is assigned to an answer, <lb/>which suggests that we do not know <lb/>trajectories of photons. It is important <lb/>that subject of statement is <lb/>us/experimenter. <lb/>&quot;We cannot predict from a single photon, which path it will <lb/>follow, because we do not know which of possible paths it will <lb/>eventually follow.&quot; <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>Single photons <lb/>have two paths <lb/>simultaneously <lb/>This category is assigned to an answer <lb/>when students claim that photons have <lb/>more trajectories simultaneously. <lb/>&quot;Because of principle of superposition until measurement <lb/>result is known its orbit is uncertain &amp; it is present in both <lb/>orbits at same time. A photon can only be assigned a path after <lb/>measurement result.&quot; <lb/>6 <lb/>1 <lb/>Probabilistic <lb/>description <lb/>This category is assigned to an answer <lb/>when student refers to probabilistic <lb/>description. <lb/>&quot;Photon is in superposition until moment of measurement, so <lb/>there is no fixed position. It is only a probability, where it <lb/>could be &amp; since orbit is a sequence of successive positions, if <lb/>it has no fixed position, it cannot have an orbit.&quot; <lb/>3 <lb/>5 <lb/>Lack of <lb/>knowledge <lb/>This category is assigned to an answer <lb/>when it particularly highlights our lack <lb/>of knowledge as a reason. <lb/>&quot;During measurement, although device indicates that photon <lb/>has arrived, we may get false information because measuring <lb/>device is disturbing photon. When detector signals, <lb/>superposition collapses, &amp; we never know what path it took.&quot; <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>Measurement <lb/>We assign this category to an answer <lb/>when a student involves measurement <lb/>process into argument. <lb/>&quot;We know little about photons, we do not know what <lb/>influences which path they take. Before photon has even passed <lb/>through path into detector, we do not know which path it will <lb/>choose, so from this point of view it can NOT be associated <lb/>with a path. All we know is that, for example, it will certainly <lb/>choose one of two paths, but it may get lost halfway through.&quot; <lb/>12 18 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Tóth et al. / From light polarization to quantum physics <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 16 <lb/></page>

			<body>In the written tests some students wrote a special <lb/>argumentation in task 3 and task 4, an example is: &quot;the <lb/>photon goes into superposition after passing through a <lb/>polarizer&quot; showing that students often believe that <lb/>superposition only occurs when photons have passed <lb/>through a polarizer or calcite. In this type of argument, <lb/>the superposition in the polarization is not considered by <lb/>the students to be a superposition state. Other two <lb/>students wrote that &quot;the measurement has no effect on the <lb/>photon, all we know by measurement is whether the photon <lb/>has passed through&quot;, which indicates that some students <lb/>identify the measurement with the signal of the detector, <lb/>and it is not with the polarizer, which suggests a classical <lb/>way of thinking about the motion. <lb/>For task 4 (explain the superposition principle) we <lb/>received one answer that fits into the previously <lb/>mentioned pattern: <lb/>&quot;Due to the measurements [authors&apos; comment: <lb/>students identified measurements with the effect <lb/>of the polarizer or calcite], the photons go into a <lb/>superposition in which state we cannot say yes or <lb/>no that they possess a property, we can only say <lb/>maybe, e.g., if we turn over a card from a French-<lb/>suited deck of cards, it will be red or black with a <lb/>50-50% probability, but we do not know which <lb/>one will be, but the card &apos;knows about itself&apos;.&quot; <lb/>This student claimed that the photons are not initially <lb/>in a superposition state, but after passing through the <lb/>polarizer/calcite the superposition appears. This means <lb/>that in this students&apos; mind the superposition only exists <lb/>because of the measurement. <lb/>In Table 5 we summarize our categorization of all the <lb/>reasonable answers (27 in the pre-, and 34 in the post-<lb/>test). Almost all students (22 then 19) gave an example, <lb/>where the superposition was in the trajectory/position <lb/>and very few students gave an example, where the <lb/>superposition was in the polarization (one then six). The <lb/>post-test shows an improvement in the category &quot;in <lb/>general a certain property cannot be assigned to a single <lb/>photon&quot; (from 16 to 22 responses) and many students <lb/>used the term &apos;measurement&apos; in their argument (13 then <lb/>19). The &apos;measurement device disturbs the system&apos; <lb/>misconception appeared only once by the same student <lb/>who used this misconception in the argumentation of <lb/>Task 3. It can also be seen that students who used the <lb/>category &quot;the photons can possess more mutually exclusive <lb/>properties simultaneously&quot; often also stated &quot;in general a <lb/>certain property cannot be assigned to a single photon&quot; in <lb/>relation to the superposition of trajectories/positions. <lb/>The supplementary (in particular the state circle) <lb/>Table 4 (Continued). Categories of students&apos; justifications for task 3 (lack of trajectory) (frequency of each category is also <lb/>shown in aggregate &amp; broken down into response options &amp; categories are not mutually exclusive) <lb/>Categories <lb/>Description <lb/>Anchor example <lb/>Total <lb/>Pre Post <lb/>It is impossible <lb/>to observe a <lb/>single photon <lb/>This is a subcategory of previous one <lb/>when students highlights that it is <lb/>impossible to observe path of photons <lb/>even if it exists. <lb/>&quot;In many cases measurements will be different, we will not be <lb/>able to observe exact results.&quot; <lb/>6 <lb/>3 <lb/>Superposition <lb/>When students&apos; argument contains term <lb/>superposition. <lb/>&quot;Photon is in superposition until it reaches detector, at which <lb/>point superposition collapses &amp; we find out which orbit <lb/>photon was in.&quot; <lb/>9 <lb/>18 <lb/>Disturbance <lb/>When students&apos; attribute to a <lb/>disturbance effect to measurement&apos;s <lb/>instruments. <lb/>&quot;Photon is attracted to measuring device, so it is deflected <lb/>from its own orbit, &amp; photons can travel in more than two <lb/>orbits.&quot; <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>Effect of <lb/>measurement <lb/>When students&apos; use effect of quantum <lb/>measurements as an argument. <lb/>&quot;You cannot assign a path to a photon because it is in <lb/>superposition until you measure it. As soon as we measure it, <lb/>it collapses &amp; falls, either through or not.&quot; <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>Table 5. Categories of students&apos; answers for task 4 (superposition) (categories are not mutually exclusive) <lb/>Categories <lb/>Description: Category is used if... <lb/>Anchor example <lb/>Total <lb/>Pre Post <lb/>No answer/not <lb/>understandable <lb/>24 17 <lb/>In general, a certain property <lb/>cannot be assigned to a <lb/>single photon <lb/>students&apos; answers highlight that it is <lb/>impossible to say for sure that a single <lb/>photon possess certain properties. <lb/>&quot;When given quantum is not in path, but a <lb/>probability can be assigned to each path, <lb/>which shows chance that given quantum is <lb/>there.&quot; <lb/>16 22 <lb/>In general, a certain property <lb/>cannot be known by us <lb/>students&apos; answers state that we do not know <lb/>properties of photon. <lb/>&quot;Superposition is state in which photon is <lb/>until moment of measurement. We do not <lb/>know if photon will be transmitted or <lb/>absorbed until we measure it.&quot; <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>Photons can possess more <lb/>mutually exclusive <lb/>properties simultaneously <lb/>students&apos; answers state that photons possess <lb/>all observable properties simultaneously. <lb/>&quot;When photon passes through calcite <lb/>crystal, it is here &amp; there at same time.&quot; <lb/>10 <lb/>9 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">EURASIA J Math Sci Tech Ed, 2024, 20(6), em2449 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 16 <lb/></page>

			<body>material also created a new type of argument, &quot;the <lb/>photons are in between the observable properties&quot;. <lb/>Analysis of Students&apos; Conceptual Development: <lb/>Gestalt-Functional Transitions <lb/>We have categorized each student into one of the <lb/>cognitive mental models. We provide an archetype for <lb/>each mental model. For instance, a student is identified <lb/>as a gestalt thinker because she/he answered &apos;b&apos;, &apos;a&apos; and <lb/>&apos;a&apos; in tasks 1, 2, and 3, respectively. This means that the <lb/>student believed that probability is used due to the lack <lb/>of knowledge about the photons, and we do not know <lb/>their trajectories because of the same external reason. As <lb/>it is written by a student in task 3, &quot;We cannot predict the <lb/>path of a single photon, because we do not know which of the <lb/>possible trajectories it is following&quot;. Or in task 4, &quot;The photon <lb/>is in such a situation that it can continue on any path, we can <lb/>only know its position when it has been found by a detector&quot;. <lb/>As we can see in Table 6, the student argues that each <lb/>photon follows a certain path, but which is unknown to <lb/>us. One of the students is put in the mixed thinking <lb/>mental model because the options &apos;b&apos;, &apos;a&apos;, and &apos;c&apos; were <lb/>answered in tasks 1, 2, and 3, respectively. The student <lb/>made a misconception in task 1, where the lack of <lb/>knowledge (hidden variable way of thinking) about the <lb/>photons was given as the reason for the probabilities. <lb/>However, the argument for the lack of trajectory is quite <lb/>interesting: <lb/>&quot;Because of the superposition principle, until we <lb/>know the measurement result, its path is <lb/>uncertain, and it is present in both trajectories <lb/>simultaneously. A photon can only be assigned a <lb/>path after the measurement result.&quot; <lb/>This student explained the superposition principle as <lb/>&quot;the photons have the property that they can be in a state <lb/>between measurements&quot;. This answer is from the post-test, <lb/>and the state circle appeared as a possible argument for <lb/>superposition: the state of the photon can be between the <lb/>measured states. It seems that this visual representation <lb/>of mathematics is used by some students to explain <lb/>superposition without using linear algebra. <lb/>A typical student with functional understanding <lb/>correctly chose &apos;a&apos;, &apos;a&apos;, and &apos;c&apos; in tasks 1, 2, and 3, <lb/>respectively. In Task 3, the argument is, <lb/>Table 5 (Continued). Categories of students&apos; answers for task 4 (superposition) (categories are not mutually exclusive) <lb/>Categories <lb/>Description: Category is used if... <lb/>Anchor example <lb/>Total <lb/>Pre Post <lb/>Measurement disturbs <lb/>system <lb/>students&apos; answers state that measurement <lb/>uncontrollably disturbs photons as detectors <lb/>are macroscopic. Photons have certain <lb/>properties, but this disturbance makes it <lb/>impossible to observe them. <lb/>&quot;Photon refracted on calcite crystal is <lb/>attracted by measuring device &amp; deviates <lb/>from its path.&quot; <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>Photons are in between <lb/>observable properties <lb/>students&apos; answers describe superposition as a <lb/>mixture of observable properties. <lb/>&quot;Situation is that we do not know anything <lb/>about photon. We have launched xy-<lb/>polarized photon &amp; until our instrument <lb/>signs, our photon floats somewhere between <lb/>life &amp; death.&quot; <lb/>0 <lb/>4 <lb/>Photons live in another <lb/>world <lb/>students&apos; answers state that superposition is <lb/>another world, where photons live before <lb/>measurement. <lb/>&quot;Photon moves to a position that cannot be <lb/>detected experimentally, only at end of <lb/>process, detector reveals its existence.&quot; <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>Position/path <lb/>students use position or path in their <lb/>example to explain superposition. <lb/>22 19 <lb/>Photon-polarizer interaction students use example of photon polarizer <lb/>interaction to explain superposition. <lb/>1 <lb/>6 <lb/>General property <lb/>students do not use certain examples, but <lb/>state generally via arbitrary properties. <lb/>2 <lb/>5 <lb/>State <lb/>students use word &quot;state&quot; or &quot;status&quot; to <lb/>describe superposition. <lb/>3 <lb/>14 <lb/>Measurement changes <lb/>something <lb/>students highlight effect of measurements. <lb/>2 <lb/>5 <lb/>Measurement as an example students include measurement process into <lb/>explanation of superposition. <lb/>13 19 <lb/>Strong highlighting of lack of <lb/>knowledge <lb/>students highlight that superposition <lb/>expresses our lack of knowledge showing a <lb/>hidden variable way of thinking. <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>Probabilities <lb/>students state that probabilities are used <lb/>when photons are in a superposition state. <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>Table 6. Number of students in each mental model after <lb/>pre-&amp; post-test <lb/>Gestalt thinking <lb/>Mixed thinking <lb/>Functional thinking <lb/>Pre-test Post-test Pre-test Post-test Pre-test <lb/>Post-test <lb/>43 <lb/>34 <lb/>0 <lb/>9 <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Tóth et al. / From light polarization to quantum physics <lb/></note>

			<page>12 / 16 <lb/></page>

			<body>&quot;The photon is in superposition up to the moment <lb/>of measurement, so there is no fixed position, only <lb/>a probability of where it might be, and since the <lb/>orbit is a sequence of successive positions, since it <lb/>has no fixed position, it has no path either.&quot; <lb/>The superposition principle in task 4 is explained as <lb/>&quot;Quanta are not at any point in space, but there is <lb/>a probability associated with each path, which is <lb/>the probability of finding the quantum there&quot;. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>The presented teaching-learning sequence seems to <lb/>be appropriate for younger students. To answer RQ1, we <lb/>conclude that students&apos; ideas about the probability law <lb/>(task 1), the measurement effect and a qualitative <lb/>interpretation of the superposition principle (task 4) are <lb/>quite well developed, while we experienced difficulties <lb/>in understanding the lack of trajectory (task 3) and the <lb/>meaning of quantum measurement. The data from task 3 <lb/>shows that students are very attached to the classical <lb/>way of thinking about motion and that a high number of <lb/>students follow the hidden variable pattern of thinking. <lb/>The difficulties related to the lack of a trajectory are not <lb/>surprising, as they have already been pointed out in a <lb/>huge number of articles in older age groups (see research <lb/>background section), which is new, but it is not <lb/>surprising that younger students have similar problems. <lb/>It was interesting to see that some of the students <lb/>switched to the hidden variable way of thinking before <lb/>reaching the quantum mechanical way of thinking. <lb/>Something similar has been seen in Italian results <lb/>(Michelini &amp; Stefanel, 2021; Michelini et al., 2011), but an <lb/>important addition may be that the emergence of a <lb/>hidden variable way of thinking seems to be determined. <lb/>A similar developmental path has been pointed out by <lb/>German researchers in which the so-called &quot;dual type of <lb/>mental model&quot; emerged as a transitional mental model <lb/>(between gestalt and functional) (Ubben &amp; Bitzenbauer, <lb/>2023). A new finding is that several students think that <lb/>photons move like classical particles, and now when the <lb/>photons reach the polarizer, the probability law is <lb/>realized via an instantaneous decision by the photon. <lb/>This belief corresponds to the gestalt mental model <lb/>(Ubben &amp; Bitzenbauer, 2022), the idea is very similar to <lb/>the presentation of visual models like JQM. This way of <lb/>thinking has two very important consequences that we <lb/>explored and, to our best of our knowledge, cannot be <lb/>found in the literature: <lb/>First, some students believe that the measurement <lb/>has no effect. It is because if quantum measurement is <lb/>just a signal from the detector, it has no effect, even <lb/>though we know that the polarization of the photons has <lb/>changed, but this change is due to the polarizer itself, <lb/>which is by some students is not considered as part of <lb/>the measurement. <lb/>Second, some students who identified the <lb/>measurement with the effect of the polarizer believed <lb/>that a measurement creates a superposition. This is <lb/>because, as we observed in task 4, students forget that the <lb/>superposition in polarization is &quot;the&quot; superposition; and <lb/>they only focus on the superposition of trajectories or <lb/>other everyday concepts. This might be because <lb/>polarization is not an everyday concept. <lb/>We also observed (through task 3 and task 4) that a <lb/>common misconception &apos;measurement disturbs the <lb/>system&apos; appeared very few times, showing a <lb/>fundamentally different pattern of thinking from what <lb/>physics education researchers have found in traditional <lb/>approaches in so much research (Ambrose et al., 1999; <lb/>Krijtenburg-Lewerissa et al., 2017; Thacker, 2003; Vokos <lb/>et al., 2002). <lb/>Regarding RQ2, we observe that a substantial <lb/>proportion of students remain in gestalt thinking. For <lb/>example, when students described the motion of <lb/>photons in QM perfectly according to JQM visualization, <lb/>i.e., they identified a narrow model as a faithful <lb/>representation of the real world, although we discussed <lb/>this in the lessons. Obviously, this is due to the lower <lb/>level of abstraction, as the participants were lower <lb/>secondary school students, and we also used a <lb/>conceptual approach that reduced the mathematical <lb/>formalism to a minimum. However, we stress that there <lb/>are some students who have already achieved a <lb/>functional understanding. Furthermore, the last two <lb/>lessons (hypothesis and state circle) helped a certain <lb/>group to switch to mixed thinking. In our opinion, it <lb/>might be fruitful to analyze as to how a transition to a <lb/>reduced mathematical formalism might help these <lb/>learners take the step towards a more functional <lb/>understanding of the respective quantum concepts. <lb/>Regarding RQ3, we found that the last two lessons <lb/>(hypotheses and state circle) had a positive effect on half <lb/>of the students&apos; thinking. In the pre-test, 20 students <lb/>understood that the use of probabilities is an inevitable <lb/>approach, which increased to 28. A positive outcome is <lb/>that a very low proportion of students, 12 in the pre-test, <lb/>used the classical concept of motion as an argument, <lb/>which is greatly reduced to seven in the post-test. The <lb/>hypotheses and the state circle promoted students&apos; <lb/>thinking with limitations because almost half of the <lb/>students stuck to the hidden variable way of thinking <lb/>after the course. We can also see that the state circle helps <lb/>to understand the measurement effect, the amount of <lb/>QM thinking answers grew from 25 to 34 (task 2). The <lb/>state circle represents the state changes in a physically <lb/>correct way, by means of which we can correctly <lb/>represent the superposition and the quantum <lb/>measurement. In addition, much more sophisticated <lb/>categories appeared in task 3 and task 4. <lb/>The application of the presented teaching-learning <lb/>material can be threefold: <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">EURASIA J Math Sci Tech Ed, 2024, 20(6), em2449 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 / 16 <lb/></page>

			<body>(1) For half of the students, it may be sufficient to do <lb/>only the first three lessons. <lb/>(2) Since the last two lessons brought improvement to <lb/>half of the group the entire five-hour course could <lb/>be appropriate for engaged students. <lb/>(3) It may be advisable for the mixed and functional <lb/>thinking students to continue the course with the <lb/>introduction of a simplified quantum formalism <lb/>(Michelini et al., 2002, 2022b; Tóth, 2023, 2024). <lb/>There are limits to research, however. On the one <lb/>hand, the sample size is small, and on the other hand, a <lb/>deeper analysis could have been done with respect to the <lb/>gestalt-functional analysis, as not too many questions <lb/>were addressed to the students. However, we would <lb/>point out that this is a pilot experiment on a well-<lb/>constructed material that has yielded several new results <lb/>and, to our knowledge, the educational potential of QM <lb/>for this age group has not yet been explored. An exciting <lb/>emerging research question is what other learning <lb/>strategies can be used to move more students from <lb/>classical thinking or the gestalt mental model to mixed <lb/>or quantum thinking or the functional mental model. <lb/>CONCLUSIONS <lb/>In this paper we presented a new minimal <lb/>mathematical conceptual approach to QM using light <lb/>polarization for lower secondary school students based <lb/>on previous research from Udine. We found that several <lb/>students can comprehend the probability law, the effect <lb/>of quantum measurement, and the superposition <lb/>principle, while there are difficulties in understanding <lb/>the lack of trajectory and the concept of quantum <lb/>measurement. We inductively categorized students&apos; <lb/>thinking on the lack of trajectory and superposition. We <lb/>explored that younger students tend to use gestalt <lb/>thinking and use the visualization of JQM as an accurate <lb/>representation of the phenomenology. However, there is <lb/>a proportion of students who were able to achieve the <lb/>mixed thinking or functional understanding. <lb/>An important message from our research is that we <lb/>need to pay close attention to what students understand <lb/>by superposition and quantum measurement. Students <lb/>often think in a fundamentally sensible and well-<lb/>constructed way that may not be obvious to the teacher <lb/>at first: for example, students believe that the <lb/>measurement creates a superposition basically due to <lb/>the misconception that superposition in polarization is <lb/>not recognized as a superposition, which should be <lb/>taken with care in a next teaching experience. In <lb/>addition, the effect of the polarizer is often not <lb/>recognized by students because they attribute the <lb/>measurement itself to the detector signal, this another <lb/>point can also be developed. We believe, however, that <lb/>it is possible and even worthwhile to teach QM to <lb/>younger students if we are careful enough to accept that <lb/>certain concepts, such as the fact that quantum objects do <lb/>not obey the temporal and spatial description, will cause <lb/>problems and that many students will remain in a semi-<lb/>classical model. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions: All authors have sufficiently contributed to <lb/>the study and agreed with the results and conclusions. <lb/></div>

            <div type="funding">Funding: This study was supported by KDP-2021 Program of <lb/>Ministry of Innovation &amp; Technology from source of National <lb/>Research Development &amp; Innovation Fund &amp; Research Program <lb/>for Public Education Development of Hungarian Academy of <lb/>Sciences (Project Number: SZKF-7/2022). <lb/></div>

            <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements: The authors would like to thank Tamás Tél <lb/>for several helpful suggestions. The authors would also like to <lb/>thank Péter Nagy for providing a website (Tóth et al., 2024b). <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Ethical statement: The authors stated that ethical review &amp; <lb/>approval were waived for this study because it was in accordance <lb/>with local legislation &amp; institutional requirements. Informed <lb/>consent was obtained from participants, their parents, or legal <lb/>guardians involved in this study. Participating students <lb/>voluntarily applied, by replying to a free call describing activity, <lb/>launched by &quot;Czuczor Gergely Benedictine Secondary School&quot; in <lb/>Győr (Hungary). All participants received a detailed explanation <lb/>of research objectives. Also, researchers obtained informed consent <lb/>from students, thus ensuring their full understanding &amp; voluntary <lb/>adherence to participation in this study. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Declaration of interest: No conflict of interest is declared by the <lb/>authors. <lb/></div>

            <div type="availability">Data sharing statement: Data supporting the findings and <lb/>conclusions are available upon request from the corresponding <lb/>author. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>Ambrose, B. S., Shaffer, P. S., Steinberg, R. N., &amp; <lb/>McDermott, L. C. (1999). An investigation of <lb/>student understanding of single-slit diffraction and <lb/>double-slit interference. American Journal of Physics, <lb/>67(2), 146-155. https://doi.org/10.1119/1.19210 <lb/>Anderson, T., &amp; Shattuck, J. (2012). Design-based <lb/>research: A decade of progress in education <lb/>research? Educational Researcher, 41(1) 16-25. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3102/0013189X11428813 <lb/>Berbhardt, C. (2019). Quantum computing for everyone. <lb/>MIT Press. https://doi.org/10.7551/mitpress/ <lb/>11860.001.0001 <lb/>Bondani, M., Chiofalo, M. L., Ercolessi, E., Macchiavello, <lb/>C., Malgieri, M., Michelini, M., Mishina, O., <lb/>Onorato, P., Pallotta, F., Satanassi, S., Stefanel, A., <lb/>Sutrini, C., Testa, I., &amp; Zuccarini, G. (2022). <lb/>Introducing quantum technologies at secondary <lb/>school level: Challenges and potential impact of an <lb/>online extracurricular course. Physics, 4, 1150-1167. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/physics4040075 <lb/>Bouchée, T., de Putter-Smits, L., Thurlings, M., &amp; Pepin, <lb/>B. (2022). Towards a better understanding of <lb/>conceptual difficulties in introductory quantum <lb/>physics courses. Studies in Science Education, 58(2), <lb/>183-202. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/03057267.2021.1963579 <lb/>Chiofalo, M. L., Foti, C., Michelini, M., Santi, L., &amp; <lb/>Stefanel, A. (2022). Games for teaching/learning <lb/>quantum mechanics: A pilot study with high-<lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Tóth et al. / From light polarization to quantum physics <lb/></note>

			<page>14 / 16 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>school students. Education Sciences, 12(7), 446. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/educsci12070446 <lb/>Cobal, M., Corni, F., Michelini, M., Santi, L., &amp; Stefanel, <lb/>A. (2002a). A resource environment to learn optical <lb/>polarization. In Proceedings of the GIREP <lb/>International Conference Proceedings (pp. 5-9). <lb/>Cobal, M., Michelini, M., &amp; Corni, F. (2002b). Thinking <lb/>on vectors and formal description of the light <lb/>polarization for a new educational approach. In M. <lb/>Michelini, &amp; M. Cobal (Eds.), Developing formal <lb/>thinking in physics (pp. 310-319). Girep. <lb/>Dirac, P. A. M. (1958). The principles of quantum mechanics. <lb/>Clarendon. https://doi.org/10.1063/1.3062610 <lb/>Duit, R., Gropengiesser, H., Kattmann, U., Komorek, M., <lb/>&amp; Parchmann, I. (2012). The model of educational <lb/>reconstruction-A framework for improving <lb/>teaching and learning science. In D. Jorde, &amp; J. <lb/>Dillon (Eds.), Science education research and practice <lb/>in Europe. Sense Publishers. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1007/978-94-6091-900-8_2 <lb/>Faletič, S., Bitzenbauer, P., Bondani, M., Chiofalo, M., <lb/>Goorney, S., Krijtenburg-Lewerissa, K., Mishina, <lb/>O., Muller, R., Pospiech, G., Ercan, I., Malgieri, M., <lb/>Merzel, A., Michelini, M., Onorato, P., Pol, H., <lb/>Santi, L., Seskir, Z. C., Sherson, J., Stadermann, K., <lb/>Stefanel, A., Surer, E., Tóth, K., Malo, J. Y., &amp; <lb/>Zabello, O. (2024). Contributions from pilot projects <lb/>in quantum technology education as support action <lb/>to quantum flagship. arXiv. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>48550/arXiv.2303.07055 <lb/>Fischler, H. R., &amp; Lichtfeldt, M. (1992). Modern physics <lb/>and students&apos; conceptions. International Journal of <lb/>Science Education, 14(2), 181-190. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1080/0950069920140206 <lb/>French, A. P., &amp; Taylor, E. F. (1978). An introduction to <lb/>quantum physics. Norton. <lb/>Ghirardi, G. C., Grassi, R., &amp; Michelini, M. (1996). A <lb/>fundamental concept in quantum theory: The <lb/>superposition principle in thinking physics for teaching. <lb/>Plenum Publishing Corporation. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1007/978-1-4615-1921-8_26 <lb/>Greca, I. M., &amp; Freire, O. (2003). Does an emphasis on the <lb/>concept of quantum states enhance students&apos; <lb/>understanding of quantum mechanics? Science &amp; <lb/>Education, 12(5), 541-557. https://doi.org/10.1023/ <lb/>A:1025385609694 <lb/>Greinert, F., &amp; Müller, R. (2023). Future quantum <lb/>workforce: Competences, requirements, and <lb/>forecasts. Physical Review Physics Education Research, <lb/>19, 010137. https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevPhys <lb/>EducRes.19.010137 <lb/>Hennig, F., Tóth, K., Förster, M., &amp; Bitzenbauer, P. (2024). <lb/>A new teaching-learning sequence to promote <lb/>secondary school students&apos; learning of quantum <lb/>physics using Dirac notation. Physics Education, 59, <lb/>045007. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1088/1361-<lb/>6552/ad353d <lb/>Ireson, G. (2000). The quantum understanding of pre-<lb/>University physics students. Physics Education, 35, <lb/>15-21. https://doi.org/10.1088/0031-9120/35/1/ <lb/>302 <lb/>Johnston, I. D., Crawford, K., &amp; Fletcher, P. R. (1998). <lb/>Student difficulties in learning quantum <lb/>mechanics. International Journal of Science Education, <lb/>20(4), 427-446. https://doi.org/10.1080/095006998 <lb/>0200404 <lb/>Kalkanis, G., Hadzidaki, P., &amp; Stavrou, D. (2003). An <lb/>instructional model for a radical conceptual change <lb/>towards quantum mechanics concepts. Science <lb/>Education, 87(2), 257-280. https://doi.org/10.1002/ <lb/>sce.10033 <lb/>Krijtenburg-Lewerissa, K., Pol, H. J., Brinkman, A., &amp; <lb/>van Joolingen, W. R. (2017). Insights into teaching <lb/>quantum mechanics in secondary and lower <lb/>undergraduate education. Physical Review Physics <lb/>Education Research, 13(1), 010109. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1103/PhysRevPhysEducRes.13.010109 <lb/>Krijtenburg-Lewerissa, K., Pol, H. J., Brinkman, A., &amp; <lb/>van Joolingen, W. R. (2018). Key topics for quantum <lb/>mechanics at secondary schools: A Delphi study <lb/>into expert opinions. International Journal of Science <lb/>Education, 40(3), 349-366. https://doi.org/10.1080/ <lb/>09500693.2018.1550273 <lb/>Michelini, M., Santi, L., &amp; Stefanel, A. (2011). Building <lb/>quantum formalism in upper secondary school <lb/>students. In Proceedings of the International <lb/>Conference GIREP-ICPE-MPTL 2010. <lb/>Michelini, M. (2008). Approaching the theory of <lb/>quantum mechanics: The first steps towards a <lb/>coherent synthesized interpretation with a <lb/>supporting formalism. In Frontiers of physics <lb/>education (pp. 93-101). <lb/>Michelini, M., &amp; Stefanel, A. (2006). Hands-on sensors <lb/>for the exploration of light polarization. In G. <lb/>Planinsic, &amp; A. Mohoric (Eds.), Informal learning and <lb/>public understanding of physics (pp. 202-208). <lb/>Michelini, M., &amp; Stefanel, A. (2014). Proposte didattiche <lb/>sulla polarizzazione ottica. Percorsi e strumenti per <lb/>una didattica laboratoriale [Teaching proposals on <lb/>optical polarization. Paths and tools for laboratory <lb/>teaching]. Pasian di Prato. https://www.fisica. <lb/>uniud.it/URDF/laurea/materiali/pdf/01Propost <lb/>eDidatticheSullaPolarizzazioneOttica.pdf <lb/>Michelini, M., &amp; Stefanel, A. (2021). A path to build basic <lb/>quantum mechanics ideas in the context of light <lb/>polarization and learning outcomes of secondary <lb/>students. Journal of Physics: Conference Series, 1929, <lb/>012052. https://doi.org/10.1088/1742-6596/1929/ <lb/>1/012052 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">EURASIA J Math Sci Tech Ed, 2024, 20(6), em2449 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 / 16 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Michelini, M., &amp; Stefanel, A. (2023). Research studies on <lb/>learning quantum physics. In M. F. Tasar, &amp; P. R. L. <lb/>Heron (Eds.), The international handbook of physics <lb/>education research: Learning physics (pp. 8-34). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1063/9780735425477_008 <lb/>Michelini, M., Faletič, S., &amp; Pospiech, G. (2022a). Work <lb/>group 3 position paper: Teacher education and <lb/>teaching/learning quantum physics. Journal of <lb/>Physics: <lb/>Conference <lb/>Series, <lb/>2297, <lb/>012015. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1088/1742-6596/2297/1/ <lb/>012015 <lb/>Michelini, M., Pospiech, G., Faletič S., &amp; Stefanel, A. <lb/>(2021). GIREP Community on teaching/learning <lb/>quantum physics in secondary school. Journal of <lb/>Physics: <lb/>Conference <lb/>Series, <lb/>1929, <lb/>012044. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1088/1742-6596/1929/1/ <lb/>012044 <lb/>Michelini, M., Ragazzon, R., Santi, L., &amp; Stefanel, A. <lb/>(2000). Proposal for quantum physics in secondary <lb/>school. Physics Education, 35, 406. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1088/0031-9120/35/6/305 <lb/>Michelini, M., Stefanel, A., &amp; Tóth, K. (2022b). <lb/>Implementing Dirac approach to quantum <lb/>mechanics in a Hungarian secondary school. <lb/>Education Sciences, 12(9), 606. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>3390/educsci12090606 <lb/>Migdał, P., Jankiewicz, K., Grabarz, P., Decaroli, C., &amp; <lb/>Cochin, P. (2022). Visualizing quantum mechanics <lb/>in an interactive simulation-Virtual lab by <lb/>quantum flytrap. Optical Engineering, 61(8), 081808. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1117/1.OE.61.8.081808 <lb/>Montagnani, S., Stefanel, A., Chiofalo, M. L., Santi, L., &amp; <lb/>Michelini, M. (2023). An experiential program on <lb/>the foundations of quantum mechanics for final-<lb/>year high-school students. Physics Education, 58(3), <lb/>035003. https://doi.org/10.1088/1361-6552/acb5 <lb/>da <lb/>Müller R., &amp; Wiesner, H. (2002). Teaching quantum <lb/>mechanics on an introductory level. American <lb/>Journal of Physics, 70, 200-209. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1119/1.1435346 <lb/>Nobel Prize Outreach AB. (2023). The Nobel Prize in <lb/>physics 2022. https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/ <lb/>physics/2022/summary/ <lb/>Passante, G., Emigh, P. J., &amp; Shaffer, P. S. (2015). Student <lb/>ability to distinguish between superposition states <lb/>and mixed states in quantum mechanics. Physics <lb/>Education Research, 11(2), 020135. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1103/PhysRevSTPER.11.020135 <lb/>Pospiech, G., Merzel, A., Zuccarini, G., Weissman, E., <lb/>Katz, N., Galili, I., Santi, L., &amp; Michelini, M. (2021). <lb/>The role of mathematics in teaching quantum <lb/>physics at high school. In B. Jarosievitz, &amp; C. <lb/>Sükösd (Eds.), Teaching-learning contemporary <lb/>physics: Challenges in physics education. Springer. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-78720-2_4 <lb/>Quantum Technology Education Project. (2020). <lb/>Quantum technology education project. European <lb/>Union. https://qtedu.eu/ <lb/>Schlummer, P., Abazi, A., Borkamp, R., Lauströer, J., <lb/>Schulz-Schaeffer, R., Schuck, C., Pernice, W., <lb/>Heusler, S., &amp; Laumann, D. (2023). Seeing the <lb/>unseen-Enhancing and evaluating undergraduate <lb/>polarization experiments with interactive mixed-<lb/>reality technology. European Journal of Physics, 44(6), <lb/>065701. https://doi.org/10.1088/1361-6404/acf0a <lb/>7 <lb/>Singh, C. (2008). Interactive learning tutorials on <lb/>quantum mechanics. American Journal of Physics, <lb/>76(4), 400-405. https://doi.org/10.1119/1.2837812 <lb/>Singh, C., &amp; Marshman, E. (2015). Review of student <lb/>difficulties in upper-level quantum mechanics. <lb/>Physics Education Research, 11(2), 020117. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevSTPER.11.02011 <lb/>7 <lb/>Stadermann, K., E., &amp; Goedhart, M. J. (2021). Why and <lb/>how teachers use the nature of science in teaching <lb/>quantum physics: Research on the use of an <lb/>ecological teaching intervention in upper <lb/>secondary schools. Physics Education Research, 17, <lb/>020132. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevPhys <lb/>EducRes.17.020132 <lb/>Stefani, C., &amp; Tsaparlis, G. (2009). Students&apos; levels of <lb/>explanations, models, and misconceptions in basic <lb/>quantum chemistry: A phenomenographic study. <lb/>Journal of Research in Science Teaching, 46(5), 520-536. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/tea.20279 <lb/>Styer, D. F. (1996). Common misconceptions regarding <lb/>quantum mechanics. American Journal of Physics, <lb/>64(1), 31-34. https://doi.org/10.1119/1.18288 <lb/>Thacker, B. A. (2003). A study of the nature of students&apos; <lb/>models of microscopic processes in the context of <lb/>modern physics experiments. American Journal of <lb/>Physics, 71(6), 599-606. https://doi.org/10.1119/1. <lb/>1566431 <lb/>Tóth, K. (2023). Integrating Dirac approach to quantum <lb/>mechanics into physics teacher education. AIP <lb/>Conference <lb/>Proceedings, <lb/>2843, <lb/>050011. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1063/5.0150429 <lb/>Tóth, K. (2024). Dirac&apos;s approach to quantum mechanics <lb/>in physics teacher education: From linear to circular <lb/>polarization. Journal of Physics: Conference Series. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1063/5.0150429 <lb/>Tóth, K., &amp; Tél, T. (2023). Quantum uncertainty: What to <lb/>teach? <lb/>Physics <lb/>Education, <lb/>58, <lb/>025019. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1088/1361-6552/acb036 <lb/>Tóth, K., Michelini, M., &amp; Bitzenbauer, P. (2024a) <lb/>Exploring the effect of a phenomenological <lb/>teaching-learning sequence on lower secondary <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Tóth et al. / From light polarization to quantum physics <lb/></note>

			<page>16 / 16 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>school students&apos; views of light polarization. Physics <lb/>Education, 59, 035009. https://doi.org/10.1088/ <lb/>1361-6552/ad2b9f <lb/>Tóth, K., Michelini, M., &amp; Bitzenbauer, P. (2024b). From <lb/>light polarization to quantum physics: Supporting lower <lb/>secondary school students&apos; transition from gestalt to <lb/>functional thinking. https://fiztan.phd.elte.hu/ <lb/>letolt/gyor-qm/index.html <lb/>Ubben, M., &amp; Bitzenbauer, P. (2022). Two cognitive <lb/>dimensions of students&apos; mental models in science: <lb/>Fidelity of gestalt and functional fidelity. Education <lb/>Sciences, 12, 163. https://doi.org/10.3390/educsci <lb/>12030163 <lb/>Ubben, M., &amp; Bitzenbauer, P. (2023). Exploring the <lb/>relationship <lb/>between <lb/>students&apos; <lb/>conceptual <lb/>understanding and model thinking in quantum <lb/>optics. Frontiers in Quantum Science and Technology, <lb/>12. https://doi.org/10.3389/frqst.2023.1207619 <lb/>Vokos, S., Shaffer, P. S., Ambrose, B. S., &amp; McDermott, L. <lb/>C. (2000). Student understanding of the wave <lb/>nature of matter: Diffraction and interference of <lb/>particles. American Journal of Physics, 68(S1), S42-<lb/>S51. https://doi.org/10.1119/1.19519 <lb/>Walsh, J. A., Fenech, M., Tucker, D. L., Riegle-Crumb, C., <lb/>&amp; Cour, B. R. (2022). Piloting a full-year, optics-<lb/>based high school course on quantum computing. <lb/>Physics Education, 57, 025010. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1088/1361-6552/ac3dc2 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">https://www.ejmste.com </note>


	</text>
</tei>
