<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF RESEARCH IN BUSINESS AND SOCIAL SCIENCE 13(3) (2024) 122-132 <lb/>* Corresponding author. ORCID ID: 0000-0002-1183-0689 <lb/>© 2024 by the authors. Hosting by SSBFNET. Peer review under responsibility of Center for Strategic Studies in Business and Finance. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.20525/ijrbs.v13i3.3263 <lb/>Precursors of customer satisfaction for sustainable high-end footwear <lb/>fashion in omni-channel retailing <lb/>Tatenda T. Chabata (a)* <lb/>(a) Ph.D., Department of Marketing and Retail Management, University of South Africa, Preller Street, Muckleneuk Ridge, Pretoria, South Africa <lb/>A R T I C L E I N F O <lb/>Article history: <lb/>Received 16 February 2024 <lb/>Received in rev. form 22 March 2024 <lb/>Accepted 29 April 2024 <lb/>Keywords: <lb/>Customer satisfaction, sustainable <lb/>fashion, high-end footwear, omni-<lb/>channel retailing <lb/>JEL Classification: <lb/>M19, M30 <lb/>A B S T R A C T <lb/>This study investigates the intricate relationship between omni-channel retailing, high-end sustainable <lb/>footwear, and customer satisfaction within an emerging market context. With a focus on Generation Z <lb/>consumers, the research delves into the correlation between customisation, pricing, customer service, <lb/>personalisation, and supply chain transparency as precursors of customer satisfaction in the high-end <lb/>sustainable footwear fashion sector. The study is grounded in the recognition of the growing <lb/>importance of sustainability in the fashion industry, whereby eco-conscious consumption is on the rise. <lb/>The research addresses the gap in fragmented studies on omni-channel retail strategies in the high-<lb/>end sustainable market. Utilising a positivist quantitative research approach, the researcher employs <lb/>a convenience sampling technique by collecting data from a total sample of 268 Generation Z <lb/>consumers who have purchased high-end sustainable footwear from South African omni-channel <lb/>retailers. A structured online survey questionnaire, featuring five Likert-scale questions is used for <lb/>data collection. The researcher proposes hypotheses that are tested primarily by utilising the latest <lb/>SPSS version. The results of the study demonstrate that customisation, price, customer service, <lb/>personalisation and supply chain transparency all positively influence customer satisfaction with <lb/>regard to high-end sustainable footwear. The significance of the study lies in its potential to contribute <lb/>valuable insights for high-end sustainable footwear omni-channel retailers in an emerging market, <lb/>enabling them to enhance customer satisfaction levels and align with the growing demand for <lb/>environmentally friendly and ethically sourced sustainable fashion. Additionally, the research aims to <lb/>fill existing knowledge gaps in the South African market and contribute to the global discourse on <lb/>sustainable fashion and consumer behaviour. <lb/>© 2024 by the authors. Licensee SSBFNET, Istanbul, Turkey. This article is an open access article <lb/>distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution (CC BY) license <lb/>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>The retailing industry is moving towards omni-channel (OC) retailing, where customers can move seamlessly from one channel to <lb/>another (Melacini et al., 2018). The COVID-19 pandemic accelerated the shift towards omni-channel retail supply chain procedures, <lb/>with large and small retailers investing in multi-channel supply processes (Wajid Ali &amp; Islamia, 2022). Omni-channel retailing has <lb/>become a phenomenon in the retail sector, revolutionising and enabling both retailers and customers to transact across diverse <lb/>platforms. Omni-channel retailing refers to &quot;an approach that involves the use of various digital and physical channels by retailers to <lb/>interact with their customers&quot; (Intel, 2019). It includes social media, mobile applications (apps), e-commerce sites, conventional <lb/>brick-and-mortar retailers, etc (Siregar et al., 2023). <lb/>Omni-channel retailing can also be considered a customer-centric approach that focuses on delivering a unified and consistent brand <lb/>experience across multiple channels. In addition, omni-channel retailing refers to the seamless integration of various shopping <lb/>channels, such as online platforms, mobile apps and physical stores, to provide customers with a unified and enhanced shopping <lb/>experience (Riaz et al., 2021). The definitions of &quot;omni-channel retailing provided in this study highlight the emphasis on the <lb/>integration of channels, consistency, personalisation and a customer-centric approach to deliver a unified shopping experience <lb/></body>

			<front>Research in Business &amp; Social Science <lb/>IJRBS VOL 13 NO 3 (2024) ISSN: 2147-4478 <lb/>Available online at www.ssbfnet.com <lb/>Journal homepage: https://www.ssbfnet.com/ojs/index.php/ijrbs <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">T.T., Chabata, International Journal of Research in Business &amp; Social Science 13(3) (2024), 122-132 <lb/></note>

			123 <lb/>

			<body>(Mulder &amp; Cunningham, 2022). The shopping experience in the fashion industry has been altered by omni-channel shopping <lb/>procedures, which have also influenced consumer behaviour in general. <lb/>Trends show that the fashion industry is investing heavily in digitalisation to meet the needs of a new generation that demands <lb/>mobility and immediacy (Lorenzo-Romero et al., 2020), while catering for customers&apos; channel preferences. On the other hand, the <lb/>notion of sustainability has grown enormously in significance in the modern fashion industry. Customers are looking for products <lb/>that are both eco-friendly and stylish. High-end sustainable footwear has come to represent responsible consumption; it is <lb/>distinguished by its eco-friendly materials, craftsmanship and ethical sourcing (Popa et al., 2019). Therefore, it becomes crucial to <lb/>comprehend the elements and circumstances that influence consumer satisfaction -through their purchase of sustainable high-end <lb/>footwear -to increase sustainable product consumption. <lb/>&quot;Customer satisfaction&quot; is defined as a measure of how happy customers are with a business&apos;s product or service (Franklin, 2023). <lb/>Jegadeeswari et al. (2021) define &quot;customer satisfaction&quot; as the overall positive impression of a supplier, encompassing all customer <lb/>interactions. According to Jocevski et al. (2019), business views and the process of business changes through omni-channel strategies <lb/>remain underinvestigated from a customer satisfaction perspective. Focusing on South Africa specifically, this study investigates the <lb/>complex interaction between omni-channel shopping, high-end sustainable footwear and customer satisfaction (Wedebrand &amp; <lb/>Ödling, 2021) as the main variables of interest. South Africa, which has one of the largest economies on the African continent, has <lb/>experienced an increase in the interest of eco-conscious consumption and a growing understanding of environmental challenges. The <lb/>research gaps identified reveal a dearth of empirical studies that are specific to South Africa and limited research on the impact of <lb/>omni-channel retailing antecedents on customer satisfaction specific to high-end sustainable footwear fashion. <lb/>Jibril et al. (2020) explored the initial adoption of online retail stores in a low internet penetration context, which could be relevant <lb/>to the digital aspect of omni-channel retailing; however, that study was not conducted in the context of high-end sustainable footwear, <lb/>which is a growing sector among South African consumers. Furthermore, Hole et al. (2019) provided a broader perspective on the <lb/>opportunities and challenges of omni-channel retailing but did not focus on the South African context. These studies collectively <lb/>point to the need for more comprehensive research on South African omni-channel retailers, particularly in terms of fashion-related <lb/>consumer behaviour and digital transformation. Therefore, there is a need to better understand the specific challenges and <lb/>opportunities for omni-channel retailers in the South African market. Customer satisfaction dynamics are further complicated by the <lb/>dynamic nature of omni-channel retailing, which requires additional empirical studies to investigate and provides novel insights for <lb/>omni-channel retailers. Businesses need to know the precise omni-channel factors that influence customer satisfaction to optimise <lb/>their operations and satisfy sustainability-conscious customers. This research recognises the importance of customer satisfaction in <lb/>the retail industry through the process of assessing the influence of omni-channel retailing strategies on customer satisfaction. The <lb/>study researcher emphasises the need for retailers to prioritise and understand their customers&apos; preferences, expectations and <lb/>experiences across such a channel. A better understanding of the factors that influence customer satisfaction from an omni-channel <lb/>retailing perspective may ultimately foster customer loyalty and retention. <lb/>The research problem firstly revolves around the limited understanding of omni-channel retailing, then around the antecedents that <lb/>result in customer satisfaction: when purchasing high-end sustainable footwear brands through omni-channel retailers. The problem <lb/>further revolves around the lack of insight into the factors within omni-channel retailing that influence customer satisfaction in <lb/>general. Thus, the key research question that guides this study is as follows: <lb/>What are the omni-channel retailing factors that influence Generation Z customer satisfaction, derived from purchasing high-end <lb/>sustainable footwear fashion? <lb/>The objectives of this study are as follows: i) to investigate the effect of omni-channel customisation on customer satisfaction; ii) to <lb/>ascertain the relationship between omni-channel prices and customer satisfaction with regard to high-end sustainable footwear; and <lb/>iii) to evaluate the contribution of customer service to customer satisfaction. iv) Determine the effect of personalised omnichannel <lb/>sustainable product offerings on customer contentment. v) Assess the relationship between supply chain transparency and customer <lb/>satisfaction. vi) Determine the overall level of consumer satisfaction that is obtained from the purchase of premium sustainable <lb/>footwear through an omni-channel retail setting. <lb/>Literature Review <lb/>Omni-channel retailing is conceptualised as a strategic approach adopted by sustainable high-end footwear retailers to provide a <lb/>seamless and integrated shopping experience across various channels, including physical stores and online platforms (website and <lb/>mobile) for their customers. Whereas people sometimes confuse omni-channel retailing with multichannel retailing, where the latter <lb/>focuses on offering multiple channels independently, in this study the researcher clearly shows that omni-channel retailing <lb/>emphasises the importance of multichannel integration to enhance sustainable high-end footwear customer experience (Hee et al., <lb/>2021). <lb/>Omni-channel selling is especially noteworthy in the realm of high-end sustainable footwear. Customers who are interested in such <lb/>products typically seek out items that strike a harmonious mix between luxury and environmental responsibility (Afonso, 2021). <lb/>Consumers of such products desire a shopping experience that is consistent with their principles, one that skilfully blends the luxury <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">T.T., Chabata, International Journal of Research in Business &amp; Social Science 13(3) (2024), 122-132 <lb/></note>

			<page>124 <lb/></page>

			<body>appeal of fashion with the comforts of environmental sustainability. Within this framework, omni-channel strategies let merchants <lb/>demonstrate their dedication to sustainability while satisfying the needs and wants of customers seeking high-end, environmentally <lb/>friendly products. <lb/>Although the uptake of omni-channel retailing was on the rise because of technological innovation and the demand for convenience <lb/>by consumers, the COVID-19 pandemic increased the significance and adoption of omni-channel retailing. The pandemic gave rise <lb/>to abrupt changes in consumer behaviour, most notably a rapid uptake of digital touchpoints and online buying. Lockdowns and <lb/>health concerns made it difficult for customers to shop in-store, so many resorted to social commerce, mobile app purchases and e-<lb/>commerce (Solem et al., 2023). Consequently, it is now more important than ever to integrate online and offline channels to meet the <lb/>ever-evolving demands of customers&apos; purchasing habits. Because omni-channel retailing provided a link between the physical and <lb/>digital worlds and allowed customers to access luxury sustainable footwear while maintaining social distancing and safety protocols, <lb/>it became a lifeline for both retailers and customers (Nguyen, 2023; Petit Olavarrieta, 2022). <lb/>Omni-channel retailers aim to connect all customer touchpoints by enabling customers to transition seamlessly between channels <lb/>during their shopping journey. This integration requires retailers to align inventory, promotions, pricing and customer information <lb/>across all channels (Locad, 2023). Channel integration enables customers to switch between channels effortlessly, allowing them to <lb/>browse, purchase and interact with the retailer seamlessly (Schmidt, 2022). Moreover, retailers aim to provide consistent brand <lb/>messaging and experiences across channels. This approach is crucial in omni-channel retailing as customers expect a seamless <lb/>transition and access to the same product information, prices and promotions, regardless of the channel that they choose (Lee et al., <lb/>2019). <lb/>Numerous studies have been conducted on omni-channel retailing and customer satisfaction within the larger field of retailing (Wang <lb/>et al., 2022; Sorkun et al., 2020). In another study, Zhang et al. (2018) showed that when a retailer integrates their channels, it can <lb/>lead to increased consumer empowerment, trust and satisfaction. Furthermore, the use of online services in omni-channel retailing <lb/>can enhance customer satisfaction and increase profits, with the optimal strategy depending on the specific scenario and the <lb/>webrooming effect (Ji et al., 2022). Researchers and industry professionals have investigated how integrating several shopping <lb/>channels, such as physical storefronts, online retailers and mobile apps, can improve customers&apos; overall shopping experiences (Sousa <lb/>et al., 2021; Lin &amp; Chen, 2022). Exceptional shopping experience is particularly important for those consumers who are tech-savvy <lb/>and value seamless interactions across channels (Gunawan et al., 2021) <lb/>To achieve a seamless customer experience, customers can begin their shopping journey through one channel and then continue <lb/>through another without disruption or disturbance. A good example could be a customer&apos;s starting by browsing high-end sustainable <lb/>footwear online, then visiting a physical store to try the product on, and then making the final purchase through a mobile app (Locad, <lb/>2023), after which the product is couriered to their doorstep. Therefore, the ability of customers using omni-channel retailing to <lb/>transition between channels effortlessly provides them with convenience, flexibility and a wider choice, which can enrich the <lb/>purchase satisfaction of customers. <lb/>Customer satisfaction is the degree to which a customer&apos;s expectations are fulfilled by a product or service (Hee et al., 2021). It <lb/>consists of the subjective judgement of the customer&apos;s encounter with the business, product or service while considering multiple <lb/>elements like product quality, service interactions, pricing, convenience and post-purchase encounters (Al Mamun &amp; Nawi, 2017; <lb/>Kibebsii et al., 2022). Customer satisfaction signifies the customer&apos;s viewpoint on the value they have received in comparison with <lb/>their initial expectations, and it significantly influences their loyalty, repurchase intentions and likelihood of recommending the brand <lb/>to others. <lb/>Therefore, the link between omni-channel retailing and customer satisfaction is noteworthy as, firstly, omni-channel retailing and <lb/>meeting customer expectations are vital across various aspects. Meeting customers&apos; expectations is not always easy for businesses, <lb/>but ensuring product quality is delivered is ideal for customer satisfaction. Thus, it is important that consumers find products that <lb/>match their needs and desires. Secondly, pricing plays a role in customer satisfaction because customers are becoming increasingly <lb/>price-conscious and expect competitive pricing across all channels. Moreover, customer perception of value is influenced by the <lb/>price they pay and the benefits they receive from the products or services they buy. Retailers who implement fair pricing, discounts, <lb/>promotions, and transparent pricing strategies enhance the perceived value of their offerings, thus contributing to greater customer <lb/>satisfaction (Mulder &amp; Cunningham, 2022). <lb/>In addition, retailers who excel in excellent customer service delivery across all touchpoints can build trust and foster loyalty in their <lb/>customers (Christoforou &amp; Melanthiou, 2019). Supply chain transparency has a significant impact on customer satisfaction in the <lb/>retail industry. Ahmed (2021) found that a strategic supplier partnership, customer relationship, information sharing, information <lb/>quality and postponement practice all positively influence customer satisfaction. Customisation in retail also significantly influences <lb/>customer satisfaction. In a study by Wang et al. (2022), it was established that the trade-off between customer satisfaction and <lb/>enterprise profit in a dynamic customisation model was crucial in co-creating the need for a balance of trade. <lb/>Research has shown the importance of personalisation for customer satisfaction in the retail industry (Sharko &amp; Ivanova, 2022). <lb/>Tyrväinen et al. (2020) found that personalised marketing in e-grocery settings can increase customer trust. The positive effects of <lb/>personalisation on customer experience and loyalty in omni-channel retailing is also regarded as essential. Herbas Torrico and Frank <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">T.T., Chabata, International Journal of Research in Business &amp; Social Science 13(3) (2024), 122-132 <lb/></note>

			<page>125 <lb/></page>

			<body>(2019) added a cultural perspective, showing that consumer desire for personalisation can moderately affect customer satisfaction <lb/>and enhance the importance of perceived usage benefits in product evaluations. The aforementioned studies collectively underscore <lb/>the importance of personalisation in driving customer satisfaction in the retail sector. By focusing on these key areas, omni-channel <lb/>retailers can create a positive and satisfying shopping experience that resonates with their customers and drives business success. <lb/>In the world of fashion, high-end sustainable footwear is a unique symbol of ethical consumption, which seems to be less addressed <lb/>in extant literature. High-end sustainable footwear is distinguished from traditional luxury goods by its unwavering dedication to <lb/>exceptional quality, ethical sourcing, environmentally friendly materials and flawless craftsmanship (Marques, 2018). High-end <lb/>sustainable footwear is the epitome of a tasteful yet sensible fusion of fashion and environmental consciousness. Customer <lb/>satisfaction becomes a very complex and multidimensional aspect in such a setting. It goes beyond the conventional characteristics, <lb/>such as cost and ease of use, that are usually linked with customer satisfaction (Dabija et al., 2019). When purchasing such products, <lb/>consumers expect that their purchases will both express a strong commitment to environmental and ethical ideals and complement <lb/>their unique style. <lb/>Consumers of high-end sustainable footwear prioritise the product&apos;s environmental and ethical features, which are linked with their <lb/>level of satisfaction. This involves incorporating aspects such as ethical labour practices, sustainable material sourcing, fair labour <lb/>treatment and lowering the carbon footprint of the product over its whole existence. These are the essential components that set <lb/>sustainable high-end footwear apart and attract customers (Cagnin &amp; Nicolas, 2022). Consumers of high-end sustainable fashion are <lb/>fulfilled by knowing that their purchase makes a real difference in the fashion industry&apos;s transition to a more ethical and sustainable <lb/>one. Additionally, being delighted with the product&apos;s appearance and functionality (Gazzola et al., 2020) would fulfil customers&apos; <lb/>requirements, while reducing any potential post-purchase dissonance. <lb/>Consequently, the elements affecting customer satisfaction in the context of high-end sustainable footwear are deeply ingrained in <lb/>ethics and sustainability rather than being purely transactional. These goods are appealing not only because they are luxurious but <lb/>also because they are good examples of responsible consumption. Fulfilling the demands of customers of high-end sustainable <lb/>footwear means providing more than simply a fashionable shoe; it is also a means of representing their dedication to a better, more <lb/>conscientious fashion future. High-end sustainable footwear can be better identified by its adherence to sustainability principles. <lb/>Customers are searching for items that can demonstrate their dedication to sustainability in addition to those that simply claim to be <lb/>eco-friendly (Priporas et al., 2017). Consumers of high-end, sustainable footwear are becoming increasingly interested in <lb/>customisation choices (Baier et al., 2020). This interest is driven by a desire for unique, personalised products that align with their <lb/>ethical and sustainable values (Luca &amp; Loghin, 2016). This feature gives customers the ability to influence the style and customisation <lb/>of their shoes. In addition, personalisation not only makes a product more distinctive, but it also shows a brand&apos;s dedication to making <lb/>shoes that suit individual preferences and morals. <lb/>Supply chain transparency is another essential component of consumer happiness that cannot be compromised. Customers are curious <lb/>about the process that goes into making their shoes, from sourcing to production (Cotarelo et al., 2021). They may be guaranteed <lb/>ethical, responsible labour practices and traceable materials with a transparent supply chain. A brand and its customers create a <lb/>trusted relationship when there is a mutually acceptable level of transparency. <lb/>While research on sustainability in luxury goods and fashion has been conducted, relatively little of it focuses on high-end sustainable <lb/>footwear in the context of omni-channel factors influencing customer satisfaction of such niche products. This research deficit is <lb/>especially noticeable in the South African setting, where there is a distinct consumer base with sophisticated and environmentally <lb/>concerned preferences (Purcărea et al., 2022). <lb/>Theoretical and Conceptual Background <lb/>Theoretical and conceptual frameworks are mandatory in research, with the former explaining the nature of being and the latter <lb/>guiding the research process (Wade et al., 2016). The integration of a theoretical framework into a research study is challenging but <lb/>essential, as it informs the problem, purpose and significance of the research (Heale &amp; Noble, 2019). Moreover, theoretical <lb/>frameworks reflect the researcher&apos;s ontological and epistemological perspective and should be integrated into every aspect of the <lb/>research to demonstrate its contribution to knowledge (Heale &amp; Noble, 2019). The theoretical framework that underpins this study <lb/>consists of five omni-channel factors adopted from the omni-channel retailing model, as well as how those factors influence customer <lb/>satisfaction. In this study, they are referred to as the five precursors of customer satisfaction, namely customisation, pricing, customer <lb/>service delivery, personalisation and supply chain transparency. <lb/>The omni-channel retailing model highlights how crucial it is to provide clients with a unified and consistent purchasing experience <lb/>in the context of high-end sustainable footwear. By adopting the omni-channel retailing model, the researcher recognises that buyers <lb/>of luxury sustainable products, such as expensive or premium sustainable shoes, anticipate a shopping experience that goes beyond <lb/>typical brick-and-mortar stores and online retailers (Ye et al., 2018). Consumers want ease of use, adaptability and the ability to <lb/>communicate with brands through a variety of channels, including social media, mobile apps, online shopping and physical stores <lb/>(Quang Hung et al., 2022). <lb/>Consequently, the sustainable fashion theory is important in this study because it provides crucial background information and <lb/>guiding ideas for comprehending the idea of upscale sustainable footwear. This theory goes beyond the simple aesthetics of apparel <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">T.T., Chabata, International Journal of Research in Business &amp; Social Science 13(3) (2024), 122-132 <lb/></note>

			<page>126 <lb/></page>

			<body>and accessories to explore the many facets of sustainability in the fashion industry. It emphasises the importance of ethical sourcing <lb/>and promotes materials that are produced and acquired in a way that respect workers&apos; rights and dignity and lessen social exploitation <lb/>(Hwang et al., 2023). The sustainable fashion theory also promotes the use of environmentally friendly materials, encouraging the <lb/>use of materials and components with low environmental impact during manufacturing and disposal (Bhutto et al., 2023). The theory <lb/>further supports supply chain transparency, advocating for an identifiable and transparent route from the outsourced raw material to <lb/>the finished product and to the purchase and use of the product; as such, it guarantees that ethical standards are maintained throughout <lb/>the value chain. The sustainable fashion theory promotes ethical production methods and encourages fashion labels to cut back on <lb/>pollution, waste and energy use during production (Zaka &amp; Al Juboori, 2023). <lb/>Additionally, the sustainable fashion theory serves as the cornerstone for understanding the qualities that are most significant to <lb/>environmentally concerned buyers of luxury sustainable footwear. These customers are not merely looking for a fashionable item; <lb/>they are also using their purchase to demonstrate their devotion to moral and environmental principles (Sony &amp; Ferguson, 2023). <lb/>Hence, this research focuses on how the factors derived from the theoretical framework influence customer satisfaction in a high-end <lb/>sustainable footwear environment. <lb/>Empirical Review and Hypothesis Development <lb/>Figure 1 illustrates the proposed conceptual model developed for this study. <lb/>Figure 1: Conceptual model explaining customer satisfaction precursors; Source: Authors (2024) <lb/>H1: Omni-channel customisation positively influences customer satisfaction regarding high-end sustainable footwear. <lb/>H2: Omni-channel prices have a significantly positive influence on customer satisfaction regarding high-end sustainable footwear. <lb/>H3: Omni-channel customer service delivery positively influences customer satisfaction regarding high-end sustainable footwear. <lb/>H4: Omni-channel personalisation positively influences customer satisfaction regarding high-end sustainable footwear. <lb/>H5: Supply chain transparency through omni-channel retailing has a significantly positive influence on customer satisfaction <lb/>regarding high-end sustainable footwear. <lb/>The researcher therefore aims to test the proposed hypotheses to address the aforementioned research objectives. <lb/>Research and Methodology <lb/>Data were collected through an online questionnaire in the months of September and October 2023. The questionnaire was provided <lb/>to young Generation Z individuals who had purchased high-end sustainable footwear from an omni-channel retailer. The online <lb/>questionnaire was shared using convenience sampling techniques through social networks (Facebook, Instagram, and X (formerly <lb/>Twitter). Participation was voluntary and anonymous, and participants were informed about the purpose of the study so that the <lb/>researcher could obtain their informed consent. A pre-test of the survey was also performed to assess whether respondents understood <lb/>the questions. The sample collected contained successfully completed responses from 268 participants. The questionnaire comprised <lb/>two main sections: the first section contained questions regarding the socio-demographic characterisation of the participants; the <lb/>second section contained questions pertaining to the variables of interest for the study. The questions were anchored on a 5-point <lb/>scale, where 1 = Strongly Disagree and 5 = Strongly Agree. The data were analysed by using the latest Statistical Package for Social <lb/>Sciences to obtain both descriptive and inferential statistics. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">T.T., Chabata, International Journal of Research in Business &amp; Social Science 13(3) (2024), 122-132 <lb/></note>

			<page>127 <lb/></page>

			<body>Results and findings <lb/>Reliability and validity <lb/>Reliability and validity are crucial aspects of research, ensuring the consistency and accuracy of data collection and analysis (Bashir <lb/>&amp; Marudhar, 2018; Ahmed &amp; Ishtiaq, 2021). Reliability refers to the consistency and stability of results, while validity concerns the <lb/>truthfulness and accuracy of the data (Mohajan, 2017). A Cronbach alpha result/value above 0.70 would be considered acceptable, <lb/>but higher values, such as 0.80 or 0.90, are preferred, especially when dealing with critical assessments (Bhattacherjee, 2011). Table <lb/>1 provides the Cronbach alpha results for the constructs in question. <lb/>Table 1: Cronbach alpha empirical results <lb/>Construct <lb/>α coefficient alpha) <lb/>Customisation <lb/>0.761 <lb/>Price <lb/>0.867 <lb/>Customer service delivery <lb/>0.792 <lb/>Personalisation <lb/>0.890 <lb/>Supply chain transparency <lb/>0.784 <lb/>Customer satisfaction <lb/>0.865 <lb/>Source: Authors (2024) <lb/>All the constructs obtained a Cronbach alpha value above 0.7 and were thus acceptable based on the criteria for reliability tests. <lb/>Generally, a Cronbach alpha above 0.70 is considered acceptable, but it is important to acknowledge that the level of reliability can <lb/>vary depending on the nature of the construct being measured and the specific goals of the research (Ellis, 2012). In this context, the <lb/>reliability coefficient obtained suggests a reasonable and acceptable degree of consistency among the items in question, indicating <lb/>that the scale or instrument used in the procedure has an acceptable level of reliability. <lb/>The socio-demographic results regarding age revealed that most respondents were within the 18-20-year age bracket, thus accounting <lb/>for the Generation Z cohort of respondents. In terms of gender, 64.15% of the respondents were female and only 35.85% were male. <lb/>Based on their academic qualifications, the majority had a bachelor&apos;s degree, accounting for 49.1% of the sample. This was aligned <lb/>with their knowledge of sustainable consumption practices. Most respondents earned below R10 000, accounting for 66% of the <lb/>sample. Table 2 provides the results of the hypotheses. <lb/>Table 2: Empirical results of the tested hypotheses <lb/>Hypothesised <lb/>relationships <lb/>Path coefficients <lb/>P-values <lb/>Significant/Insignificant <lb/>H1 <lb/>0.688 <lb/>0.001 <lb/>Significant and supported <lb/>H2 <lb/>0.908 <lb/>0.001 <lb/>Significant and supported <lb/>H3 <lb/>0.732 <lb/>0.001 <lb/>Significant and supported <lb/>H4 <lb/>0.751 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Significant and supported <lb/>H5 <lb/>0.965 <lb/>0.001 <lb/>Significant and supported <lb/>Source: Authors (2024) <lb/>Table 2 provides a summary confirming the positive significance of all the variables as precursors of customer satisfaction in an <lb/>omni-channel retail environment. The p-value of all the precursors was less than 0.05, signifying that all the hypotheses were <lb/>accepted. Supply chain transparency had a much stronger effect on customer satisfaction in terms of the purchase of high-end <lb/>sustainable footwear, with a beta coefficient of 0.965. This was followed by price, with a beta coefficient of 0.908. Personalisation <lb/>also influences customer satisfaction regarding the purchase of high-end sustainable footwear, with a beta coefficient of 0.751. Both <lb/>customer service delivery and customisation had a positive and significant impact on customer satisfaction, with a beta coefficient <lb/>of 0.732 and 0.688, respectively. <lb/>Findings and Discussions <lb/>Customisation was statistically significant (F (1, 51) = 31.118, p &lt; 0.001), explaining 37.9% of the variance in customer satisfaction <lb/>(R² = 0.379). The unstandardised coefficient for customisation (B = 0.688, p &lt; 0.001) indicates that for each one-unit increase in <lb/>customisation, customer satisfaction is expected to increase by 0.688 units. Greater customisation options contribute positively to <lb/>customer perceptions of product satisfaction. This can also be seen in previous research. Hu et al. (2016) and Hu et al. (2022) both <lb/>highlight the positive impact of customised logistics services on online shoppers&apos; satisfaction and loyalty. The findings in this study <lb/>align with the work of Jain and Sundström (2021), who emphasised the importance of customisation in creating unique and satisfying <lb/>customer experiences. Customisation fosters a sense of personal connection and ownership, contributing to overall satisfaction <lb/>(Scholl-Grissemann, et al., 2020). <lb/>The price variable is highly significant (F (1, 51) = 93.488, p &lt; 0.001), explaining 64.7% of the variance in customer satisfaction (R² <lb/>= 0.647). The unstandardised coefficient for price (B = 0.908, p &lt; 0.001) indicates that for each one-unit increase in prices, customer <lb/>satisfaction is expected to increase by 0.908 units. This finding aligns with economic theories suggesting that consumers often <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">T.T., Chabata, International Journal of Research in Business &amp; Social Science 13(3) (2024), 122-132 <lb/></note>

			<page>128 <lb/></page>

			<body>associate higher prices with enhanced product quality or exclusivity, thus positively affecting satisfaction. Price positively influences <lb/>satisfaction (Ramadhaniati et al., 2020; Indajang et al., 2023) in different settings and contexts. <lb/>The customer service variable is highly significant (F (1, 51) = 74.547, p &lt; 0.001), explaining 59.4% of the variance in customer <lb/>satisfaction (R² = 0.594). The unstandardised coefficient for customer service (B = 0.732, p &lt; 0.001) indicates that for each one-unit <lb/>increase in customer service quality, customer satisfaction is expected to increase by 0.732 units. This aligns with established <lb/>principles in customer relationship management, emphasising the critical role of service delivery in shaping positive customer <lb/>perceptions. Hee et al. (2021) and Merritt and Zhao (2020) also highlight the importance of a seamless and integrated shopping <lb/>experience in increasing customer satisfaction. Superior customer service has consistently been linked to increased satisfaction and <lb/>loyalty (Khan et al., 2022). These findings reinforce the notion that exceptional service is a key driver of overall customer satisfaction <lb/>in the high-end sustainable footwear sector. <lb/>The regression model, featuring the personalisation variable, is statistically significant (F (1, 51) = 38.796, p &lt; 0.000), explaining <lb/>43.2% of the variance in customer satisfaction (R² = 0.432). The unstandardised coefficient for personalisation (B = 0.751, p &lt; 0.000) <lb/>indicates that for each one-unit increase in personalisation, customer satisfaction is expected to increase by 0.751 units. These findings <lb/>align with contemporary marketing principles that highlight the significance of tailored and personalised experiences in shaping <lb/>positive customer perceptions. Therefore, omni-channel retailers in the high-end sustainable footwear industry should prioritise and <lb/>invest in effective omni-channel personalisation strategies to enhance overall customer satisfaction and potentially foster long-term <lb/>customer loyalty. This is supported by previous research, which emphasises the importance of personalisation in enhancing customer <lb/>satisfaction in retail (Baier &amp; Rese, 2020; Tyrväinen et al., 2020). Personalisation tailors services to individual preferences, enhancing <lb/>the overall shopping experience (Tyrväinen et al., 2020). This aligns with the growing trend in retail literature highlighting the role <lb/>of personalisation in influencing and building customer loyalty and satisfaction. Sartortt et al. (2020) focused on the personalisation <lb/>of the consumer experience in fashion e-commerce, particularly using virtual fitting rooms and personalised recommendations for <lb/>shoppers. <lb/>The regression model indicating the supply chain transparency variable is highly significant (F (1, 51) = 119.670, p &lt; 0.001), <lb/>explaining 70.1% of the variance in customer satisfaction (R² = 0.701). The unstandardised coefficient for supply chain transparency <lb/>(B = 0.965, p &lt; 0.001) indicates that for each one-unit increase in supply chain transparency, customer satisfaction is expected to <lb/>increase by 0.965 units. Transparent supply chains enhance consumer trust and satisfaction, reflecting the increasing importance of <lb/>corporate social responsibility in consumer decision-making (Alshurideh et al. 2023). Increasing cross-channel coordination, <lb/>optimising online and offline interfaces and using customer data to provide tailored recommendations are important tactics. <lb/>This study is significant for omni-channel retail stores in South Africa selling sustainable high-end footwear, as well as those <lb/>intending to enter the lucrative fashion market. The study findings shed lighter on the factors influencing customer satisfaction <lb/>regarding sustainable high-end footwear by emerging market Generation Z consumers. The understanding of customer satisfaction <lb/>in the study context will assist businesses to formulate more appropriate strategies targeted at the market to achieve greater loyalty <lb/>and retention of customers. <lb/>Omni-channel retailers in the high-end sustainable footwear industry should consider investing in customisation strategies, <lb/>competitive pricing, customer service delivery, personalisation and robust supply chain transparency to enhance customer satisfaction <lb/>and potentially gain a competitive edge in the market. These are strategic recommendations that are in line with the distinct traits, <lb/>interests, and behaviours of the target market, which consists of Gen Z customers. This entails improving the quality of the products <lb/>offered, significantly improving omni-channel fulfilment procedures and utilising technology to provide a smooth and customised <lb/>purchasing experience. As a result of the findings, businesses in the high-end sustainable footwear sector are urged to apply and <lb/>maximise the proposed omni-channel components from this study carefully to improve consumer satisfaction. <lb/>Omni-channel retailers&apos; plans should include customisation, competitive pricing that matches perceived value, excellent customer <lb/>service, tailored experiences, and open supply chain procedures. It is essential to invest in technology to enable smooth and <lb/>customised interactions across channels. Furthermore, encouraging an ethical and transparent culture in the supply chain not only <lb/>improves customer satisfaction but also reflects the values of socially and environmentally conscious consumers. Businesses may <lb/>improve consumer loyalty, strengthen their position in the market and support the long-term viability of the high-end footwear sector <lb/>by implementing these suggestions. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>Retailers in the South African fashion industry can benefit greatly from the insights provided by this study, especially those that aim <lb/>to improve their sustainability initiatives through omni-channel retailing best practices. The study offers a roadmap for those omni-<lb/>channel retailers to optimise their operations and services by examining the effect of pricing strategies, supply chain transparency, <lb/>personalisation and product customisation on customer satisfaction. This helps their bottom line and harmonises with the increasing <lb/>demand for environmentally ethical retailing. Although the data analysis offers insightful information, it is important to recognise <lb/>some constraints that might affect the applicability and complexity of the conclusions. The study is limited in its applicability to <lb/>diverse consumer categories or businesses because of its reliance on a specific sample within the high-end sustainable footwear <lb/>market. Furthermore, the cross-sectional nature of the data limits our capacity to determine the long-term relationship between the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">T.T., Chabata, International Journal of Research in Business &amp; Social Science 13(3) (2024), 122-132 <lb/></note>

			<page>129 <lb/></page>

			<body>variables in question. Longitudinal research would offer a more thorough understanding of the dynamic correlations between the <lb/>constructs in question. Future research projects could use a longitudinal design to capture the changing dynamics of customer <lb/>satisfaction in response to shifting omni-channel tactics, thereby addressing the constraints, and building on the insights obtained. <lb/>Lastly, there are other variables that were not considered in this study, such as the state of the economy and world events; these might <lb/>have an impact on customer satisfaction and require further investigation. A more thorough perspective would be derived from <lb/>considering how external influences, including cultural changes and technological improvements, affect customer satisfaction. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>The project received an ethics certificate from UNISA&apos;s Department of Marketing and Retail Management ethics committee. Witho ut ethical <lb/>approval, this study would have not been conducted and completed. <lb/>All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions: The whole paper was conceptualized and completed by Dr Tatenda T. Chabata <lb/></div>

            <div type="funding">Funding: This research was funded by the University of South Africa (UNISA) research grant. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Informed Consent Statement: Informed consent was obtained from all subjects involved in the study. <lb/></div>

            <div type="availability">Data Availability Statement: The data presented in this study are available on request from the corresponding author. The data are not publicly <lb/>available due to restrictions. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Conflicts of Interest: The author declares no conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

            <listBibl>References <lb/>Afonso, V. A. M. (2021). Shopper phenomenon: Combinations of channels and touchpoints on the customer journey in Generation <lb/>Z. [Doctoral dissertation, Universidade Do Algarve]. <lb/>Ahmed, A. (2021). The importance of supply chain management practices in increasing customer satisfaction and customer <lb/>retention: Evidence from Saudi Arabia. International Journal of Scientific Research and Management, 9(03), 2136-2151. <lb/>doi.org/https://doi.org/10.18535/ijsrm/v9i03.em04 <lb/>Ahmed, I., and Ishtiaq, S. (2021). Reliability and validity: Importance in medical research. The Journal of the Pakistan Medical <lb/>Association, 71(10). doi.org/https://doi.org/10.47391/JPMA.06-861 <lb/>Al Mamun, A., and Nawi, N. B. C. (2017). Customer satisfaction of online apparel businesses in Malaysia: Point-purchase and <lb/>post-purchase comparison. International Journal of Business Innovation and Research, 12(3), 386. <lb/>doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1504/ijbir.2017.10002772 <lb/>Alshurideh, M., Hamadneh, S., Al Kurdi, B., and Alrawabdeh, W. (2023). Exposing corporate value: Synergizing global <lb/>diversification and operational flexibility in SMEs. International Journal of Business Analytics and Security (IJBAS), 3(2), <lb/>130-142. <lb/>Baier, D., Rausch, T. M., and Wagner, T. F. (2020). The drivers of sustainable apparel and sportswear consumption: A segmented <lb/>Kano perspective. Sustainability, 12(7), 2788. doi.org/https://doi.org/10.3390/su12072788 <lb/>Baier, D., and Rese, A. (2020). How to increase multichannel shopping satisfaction. An adapted Kano-based stage-gate approach to <lb/>select new technologies. Journal of Retailing and Consumer Services, 56, 102172. <lb/>doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jretconser.2020.102172 <lb/>Bashir, J., and Marudhar, M. (2018). Reliability &amp; validity of the research. Scientific Journal of India, 3(1), 66-69. <lb/>Bhattacherjee, A. (2011). Chapter 7: Scale reliability and validity | Research Methods for the Social Sciences. <lb/>https://courses.lumenlearning.com/suny-hccc-research-methods/chapter/chapter-7-scale-reliability-and-<lb/>validity/#:~:text=Validity%20%2C%20often%20called%20construct%20validity [Accessed May 18, 2023]. <lb/>Bhutto, M. Y., Khan, M. A., Sun, C., Hashim, S., and Khan, H. T. (2023). Factors affecting repurchase intention of organic food <lb/>among Generation Z (Evidence from developing economy). Plos One, 18(3), e0281527. <lb/>Cagnin, N., and Nicolas, M. (2022). Generation Z and brand loyalty: The influence of Gen Z specific expectations on attitudinal <lb/>and behavioural loyalty, [Master&apos;s Program in Management, Umea University]. <lb/>Christoforou, T., and Melanthiou, Y. (2019). The practicable aspect of the omni-channel retailing strategy and its impact on <lb/>customer loyalty. Palgrave Studies in Cross-disciplinary Business Research in Association with EuroMed Academy of <lb/>Business, 239-260. doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-17523-8_11 <lb/>Cotarelo, M., Fayos, T., Calderón, H., and Mollá, A. (2021). Omni-channel intensity and shopping value as key drivers of customer <lb/>satisfaction and loyalty. Sustainability, 13(11), 5961. <lb/>Dabija, D. C., Bejan, B. M., and Dinu, V. (2019). How sustainability oriented is Generation Z in retail? A literature <lb/>review. Transformations in Business &amp; Economics, 18(2). <lb/>Ellis, J. L. (2012). A standard for test reliability in group research. Behavior Research Methods, 45(1),16-24. <lb/>doi.org/https://doi.org/10.3758/s13428-012-0223-z <lb/>Franklin, A. (2023). 3 steps to achieving customer satisfaction and loyalty. Zendesk. https://www.zendesk.com/blog/3-steps-<lb/>achieving-customer-satisfaction-loyalty/ <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">T.T., Chabata, International Journal of Research in Business &amp; Social Science 13(3) (2024), 122-132 <lb/></note>

			<page>130 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Gazzola, P., Pavione, E., Pezzetti, R., and Grechi, D. (2020). Trends in the fashion industry. The perception of sustainability and <lb/>circular economy: A gender/generation quantitative approach. Sustainability, 12(7), 2809. <lb/>Gunawan, D., Mursitama, T., Maulana, A., and Hamsal, M. (2021, August 30). Omni-interaction strategy to create holistic <lb/>omnichannel consumer experience. Proceedings of the 2nd International Conference on Industrial and Technology and <lb/>Information Design, ICITID , Yogyakarta, Indonesia. <lb/>Heale, R., and Noble, H. (2019). Integration of a theoretical framework into your research study. Evidence Based Nursing, 22(2), <lb/>36-37. doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1136/ebnurs-2019-103077 <lb/>Hee, S. N. J., Mohd Rizal, A., Khalid, H., Ho, T. C. F., and Sahimi, M. (2021). Increasing customer satisfaction through <lb/>omnichannel retailing. International Journal of Academic Research in Business and Social Sciences, 11(11). <lb/>doi.org/https://doi.org/10.6007/ijarbss/v11-i11/11267 <lb/>Herbas Torrico, B., and Frank, B. (2019). Consumer desire for personalisation of products and services: Cultural antecedents and <lb/>consequences for customer evaluations. Total Quality Management &amp; Business Excellence, 30(3-4), 355-369. <lb/>Hole, Y., Pawar, Ms Snehal, and Khedkar, E. B. (2019). Omni channel retailing: An opportunity and challenges in the Indian <lb/>market. Journal of Physics: Conference Series, 1362:012121. doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1088/1742-6596/1362/1/012121 <lb/>Hu, M., Chaudhry, P. E., and Chaudhry, S. S. (2022). Linking customized logistics service in online retailing with E-satisfaction <lb/>and E-loyalty. International Journal of Engineering Business Management, 14, 18479790221097528. <lb/>Hu, M., Huang, F., Hou, H., Chen, Y., and Bulysheva, L. (2016). Customized logistics service and online shoppers&apos; satisfaction: <lb/>An empirical study. Internet Research, 26(2), 484-497. doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1108/intr-11-2014-0295 <lb/>Hwang, J. S., Kim, E. Y., and Hwang, Y. M. (2023). Empirical study on effects of gratification on continuous usage intention of <lb/>AR avatars in smart mirrors: Focus on Generation Z. International Journal of Human-Computer Interaction, 1-14. <lb/>Indajang, K., Candra, V., Sianipar, M. Y., Sembiring, L. D., and Simatupang, S. (2023). The effect of service quality and price on <lb/>customer satisfaction. Ekonomi, Keuangan, Investasi dan Syariah (EKUITAS), 4(3), 942-950. <lb/>Intel. (2019). What is omnichannel retail? <lb/>https://www.intel.com/content/www/us/en/retail/omnichannel.html#:~:text=Omnichannel%20retail%20is%20a%20strategy <lb/>[Accessed June 20, 2023]. <lb/>Jain, S., and Sundström, M. (2021). Toward a conceptualization of personalized services in apparel e-commerce fulfillment. <lb/>Research Journal of Textile and Apparel (ahead of print). doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1108/rjta-06-2020-0066 <lb/>Jegadeeswari, G., Kumaran, T., Baskaran, S., Lakshmi, D., and Kirubadurai, B. (2021). Performance investigation of cascaded <lb/>multilevel inverter-fed brushless DC motor drive. International Journal of Aquatic Science, 12(3), 484-489. <lb/>Ji, G., Fu, T., Chen, J., and Tan, K. H. (2022). Optimal online service strategy and price decision in omnichannel retail. <lb/>Mathematical Problems in Engineering, 1-35. doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1155/2022/8698309 <lb/>Jibril, A. B., Kwarteng, M. A., Pilik, M., Botha, E., and Osakwe, C. N. (2020). Towards understanding the initial adoption of <lb/>online retail stores in a low internet penetration context: An exploratory work in Ghana. Sustainability, 12(3), 854. <lb/>doi.org/https://doi.org/10.3390/su12030854 <lb/>Jocevski, M., Arvidsson, N., Miragliotta, G., Ghezzi, A., and Mangiaracina, R. (2019). Transitions towards omni-channel retailing <lb/>strategies: A business model perspective. International Journal of Retail &amp; Distribution Management. 47(2), 78-93. <lb/>doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1108/ijrdm-08-2018-0176 <lb/>Khan, F., Mehmood, A., and Talat, A. (2022). The impact of social media marketing, perceived quality and brand awareness on <lb/>consumer&apos;s brand loyalty in Pakistan. Pakistan Journal of Psychological Research, 37(4), 533-550. <lb/>Kibebsii, N. M., Egwu, P. B. J., and Ntangti, D. C. F. (2022). The influence of service and product quality on customer satisfaction: <lb/>A study of UBa-Ventures PLC Bambili, Cameroon. International Journal of Research and Innovation in Social Science, <lb/>06(12), 603-607. doi.org/https://doi.org/10.47772/ijriss.2022.61233 <lb/>Lee, Z. W. Y., Chan, T. K. H., Chong, A.Y.-L., and Thadani, D. R. (2019). Customer engagement through omnichannel retailing: <lb/>The effects of channel integration quality. Industrial Marketing Management. 77, 90-101. <lb/>doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1016/j.indmarman.2018.12.004 <lb/>Lin, P. H., and Chen, W. H. (2022). Factors that influence consumers&apos; sustainable apparel purchase intention: The moderating <lb/>effect of generational cohorts. Sustainability, 14(14), 8950. <lb/>Locad. (2023). The ultimate guide to omnichannel retail: How to revolutionize your retail business with insightful strategies. <lb/>https://golocad.com/blog/omnichannel-retailing/ <lb/>Lorenzo-Romero, C., Andrés-Martínez, M.-E., and Mondéjar-Jiménez, J.-A. (2020). Omnichannel in the fashion industry: A <lb/>qualitative analysis from a supply-side perspective. Heliyon. 6(6), e04198. <lb/>doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2020.e04198 <lb/>Luca, A. and Loghin, M. (2016). Sustainable consumption and ethical behavior of consumers in the footwear industry. <lb/>https://icams.ro/icamsresurse/2016/proceedings/VI_Economics_02.pdf [Accessed August 2, 2023]. <lb/>Marques, S. M. E. (2018). The disruption of retail through Gen Z: An exploratory study on the new customer journey and the <lb/>impact of customer touchpoints on brand loyalty. [Doctoral dissertation, Universidade do Porto, Portugal]. <lb/>Melacini, M., Perotti, S., Rasini, M., and Tappia, E. (2018). E-fulfilment and distribution in omni-channel retailing: A systematic <lb/>literature review. International Journal of Physical Distribution &amp; Logistics Management. 48(4), 391-414. <lb/>doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1108/ijpdlm-02-2017-0101 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">T.T., Chabata, International Journal of Research in Business &amp; Social Science 13(3) (2024), 122-132 <lb/></note>

			<page>131 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Merritt, K., and Zhao, S. (2020). An investigation of what factors determine the way in which customer satisfaction is increased <lb/>through omni-channel marketing in retail. Administrative Sciences, 10(4), 85. <lb/>Mohajan, H. K. (2017). Two criteria for good measurements in research: Validity and reliability. Annals of Spiru Haret University. <lb/>Economic Series. 17(4), 59-82. doi.org/https://doi.org/10.26458/1746 <lb/>Mulder, B. S., and Cunningham, N. (2022). Omni-channel retailing: Low-income consumers&apos; experience. <lb/>https://www.wrseta.org.za/downloads/WRLC%20Gauteng%20RESEARCH%20REPORT%20Omni%20Channel%20Retai <lb/>ling%20(Low%20income%20consumer).pdf [Accessed July 4, 2023] <lb/>Nguyen, H. (2023). Omnichannel marketing strategy for fashion retailers. [Business Management Thesis, Centria University of <lb/>Applied Sciences]. <lb/>Petit Olavarrieta, S. L. (2022). Generation Z&apos;s leadership in retail demand for sustainable products. [Doctoral dissertation, <lb/>Technische Hochschule Ingolstadt]. <lb/>Popa, I. D., Dabija, D. C., and Grant, D. B. (2019). Exploring omnichannel retailing differences and preferences among consumer <lb/>generations. In Applied ethics for entrepreneurial success: Recommendations for the developing world. 2018 Griffiths <lb/>School of Management Annual Conference (GSMAC) on Business, Entrepreneurship and Ethics 9, 129-146. <lb/>Priporas, C.V., Stylos, N., and Fotiadis, A. K. (2017). Generation Z consumers&apos; expectations of interactions in smart retailing: A <lb/>future agenda. Computers in Human Behavior, 77(1), 74-381. doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2017.01.058 <lb/>Purcărea, T., Ioan-Franc, V., Ionescu, Ş. A., Purcărea, I. M., Purcărea, V. L., Purcărea, I., and Orzan, A. O. (2022). Major shifts in <lb/>sustainable consumer behavior in Romania and retailers&apos; priorities in agilely adapting to it. Sustainability, 14(3), 1627. <lb/>Quang Hung, L. E., Thi Thao, T. R. A., Thuy Thanh Tam, V. O., Viet Anh Thu Duong, T. N., Anh Nguyen, N. C. N., Thi Hoai <lb/>Phuong, T. R. A. N., and Thi Minh Nguyen, L. E. (2022). Online shopping decision of Gen Z students in Vietnam. Part <lb/>1_Literature review. Journal of Positive School Psychology, 6(8), 10180-10191. <lb/>Ramadhaniati, S., Susanti, E., Wiwaha, A., and Tyas, I. W. (2020). Effect of service quality and price on customer satisfaction. <lb/>International Journal of Digital Entrepreneurship and Business, 1(1), 1-10. <lb/>Riaz, H., Baig, U., Meidute-Kavaliauskiene, I., and Ahmed, H. (2021). Factors effecting omnichannel customer experience: <lb/>Evidence from fashion retail. Information, 13(1), 12. doi.org/https://doi.org/10.3390/info13010012 <lb/>Sartortt, M., Bernardino, J. and Pedrosa, I., (2020). Customer experience personalization in fashion e-commerce through virtual <lb/>fitting rooms. In 2020 15th Iberian conference on information systems and technologies (CISTI) (pp. 1-7). IEEE. <lb/>Schmidt, K. M. (2022). What is unified commerce? Key advantages &amp; best practices. https://www.stibosystems.com/blog/unified-<lb/>commerce [Accessed December 12, 2023]. <lb/>Scholl-Grissemann, U., Stokburger-Sauer, N. E. and Teichmann, K. (2020). The importance of perceived fairness in product <lb/>customization settings. The Service Industries Journal, September 20,1-20. <lb/>doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1080/02642069.2020.1819252 <lb/>Sharko, E. R., and Ivanova, A. A. (2022). Personalised marketing effect on consumer trust formation on e-grocery Russian market. <lb/>Moscow University Economics Bulletin, (6), 221-250. doi.org/https://doi.org/10.38050/013001052022610 <lb/>Siregar, Y., Kent, A., Peirson-Smith, A., and Guan, C. (2023). Disrupting the fashion retail journey: Social media and GenZ&apos;s <lb/>fashion consumption. International Journal of Retail &amp; Distribution Management, 51(7). <lb/>doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1108/ijrdm-01-2022-0002 <lb/>Solem, B. A. A., Fredriksen, J. I., and Sørebø, Ø. (2023). Dynamic capabilities in the realisation of omnichannel retailing. <lb/>International Journal of Retail &amp; Distribution Management, 51(1), 21-38. <lb/>Sony, A., and Ferguson, D. L. (2023). Delivering value to Generation Z: Uncovering channel, pricing, and advocacy preferences <lb/>within Thailand. Journal of Family Business and Management Studies, 14(1), 75-96. <lb/>Sorkun, M. F., Yumurtacı Hüseyinoğlu, I. Ö., and Börühan, G. (2020). Omni-channel capability and customer satisfaction: <lb/>Mediating roles of flexibility and operational logistics service quality. International Journal of Retail &amp; Distribution <lb/>Management, 48(6), 629-648. doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1108/ijrdm-07-2019-0235 <lb/>Sousa, P. R. de, Barbosa, M. W., Oliveira, L. K. de, Resende, P. T. V de, Rodrigues, R. R., Moura, M. T., and Matoso, D. (2021). <lb/>Challenges, opportunities, and lessons learned: Sustainability in Brazilian omnichannel retail. Sustainability, 13(2), 666. <lb/>doi.org/https://doi.org/10.3390/su13020666 <lb/>Tyrväinen, O., Karjaluoto, H. and Saarijärvi, H. (2020). Personalization and hedonic motivation in creating customer experiences <lb/>and loyalty in omnichannel retail. Journal of Retailing and Consumer Services. 57, 102233. <lb/>doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jretconser.2020.102233 <lb/>Wade, V., Gray, L., and Carati, C. (2016). Theoretical frameworks in telemedicine research. Journal of Telemedicine and Telecare, <lb/>23(1), 181-187. doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1177/1357633x15626650 <lb/>Wajid Ali, S., and Islamia, J. M. (2022). A qualitative study on innovation and dimensional aspects of the omnichannel retail <lb/>business model. International Journal of E-Business Research. 18(2). doi.org/https://doi.org/10.4018/ijebr.294108 <lb/>Wang, K., Li, Y. and Zhou, Y. (2022). Execution of omni-channel retailing based on a practical order fulfillment policy. Journal of <lb/>Theoretical and Applied Electronic Commerce Research, 17(3), 1185-1203. doi.org/https://doi.org/10.3390/jtaer17030060 <lb/>Wang, W., Cao, D., and Ameen, N. (2022). Understanding customer satisfaction of augmented reality in retail: A human value <lb/>orientation and consumption value perspective. Information Technology &amp; People, August 9. <lb/>doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1108/itp-04-2021-0293 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">T.T., Chabata, International Journal of Research in Business &amp; Social Science 13(3) (2024), 122-132 <lb/></note>

			<page>132 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Wedebrand, A., and Ödling, C. (2021). The role of the physical store in an omnichannel strategy: A qualitative study of Generation <lb/>Z in the Swedish fashion industry. [Master&apos;s Thesis in Business Administration, Umea University]. <lb/>Ye, Y., Lau, K. H., and Teo, L. K. Y. (2018). Drivers and barriers of omni-channel retailing in China: A case study of the fashion <lb/>and apparel industry. International Journal of Retail &amp; Distribution Management, 46(7), 657-689. <lb/>Zaka, K., and Al Juboori, M. M. S. (2023). The impact of Generation-Z on international branding strategy: An analysis of startup <lb/>fashion brands: What are the possible challenges and advantages faced by startup fashion brands in adapting to the Gen-Z <lb/>effect in their international branding strategies? [Bachelor Thesis, Linnaeus University]. <lb/>Zhang, M., Ren, C., Wang, G. A., and He, Z. (2018). The impact of channel integration on consumer responses in omni-channel <lb/>retailing: The mediating effect of consumer empowerment. Electronic Commerce Research and Applications, 28, 181-193. <lb/>doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1016/j.elerap.2018.02.002 <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s Note: SSBFNET stays neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations. <lb/></div>

			<front>© 2024 by the authors. Licensee SSBFNET, Istanbul, Turkey. This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and <lb/>conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution (CC BY) license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/>International Journal of Research in Business and Social Science (2147-4478) by SSBFNET is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 <lb/>International License. </front>


	</text>
</tei>
