<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Poli et al. Hepatoma Res 2024;10:15 <lb/>DOI: 10.20517/2394-5079.2023.101 <lb/>Hepatoma Research <lb/>© The Author(s) 2024. Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 <lb/>International License (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, sharing, <lb/>adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, for any purpose, even commercially, as <lb/>long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and <lb/>indicate if changes were made. <lb/>www.oaepublish.com/hr <lb/>Open Access <lb/>Review <lb/>Progression of liver disease and associated risk of <lb/>hepatocellular carcinoma <lb/>Edoardo Poli 1,2 , Eleonora De Martin 1 <lb/>1 AP-HP, Hôpital Paul-Brousse, Centre Hépato-Biliaire, FHU Hepatinov, INSERM Unit 1193, Villejuif 91400, France. <lb/>2 Department of internal Medicine, Division of Gastroenterology and hepatology, Groupe Hospitalier Nord Essonne, Longjumeau <lb/>91160, France. <lb/>Correspondence to: Dr. Edoardo Poli, Department of internal Medicine, Division of Gastroenterology and hepatology, Groupe <lb/>Hospitalier Nord Essonne, 159 Rue du Président François Mitterrand, Longjumeau 91160, France. E-mail: edoardo.poli@aphp.fr <lb/>How to cite this article: Poli E, De Martin E. Progression of liver disease and associated risk of hepatocellular carcinoma. <lb/>Hepatoma Res 2024;10:15. https://dx.doi.org/10.20517/2394-5079.2023.101 <lb/>Received: 30 Aug 2023 First Decision: 30 Oct 2023 Revised: 18 Jan 2024 Accepted: 20 Mar 2024 Published: 28 Mar 2024 <lb/>Academic Editor: Matias A Avila Copy Editor: Yanbing Bai Production Editor: Yanbing Bai <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is the primary liver cancer type, often seen in individuals with chronic liver <lb/>disease. Once the patient progresses to the cirrhotic stage, the annual incidence of HCC is approximately 2%-4%. <lb/>As it exceeds the minimum threshold of 1.0%-1.5% per year, HCC screening every 6 months through abdominal <lb/>ultrasound is indicated in the cirrhotic population. While the incidence of viral hepatitis-associated HCC is <lb/>decreasing, there is a notable rise of HCC associated with metabolic dysfunction-related steatotic liver disease and <lb/>alcohol-related liver disease, particularly in high-income countries. The most effective approach for oncological <lb/>prevention remains addressing the cause of liver disease. The indications for HCC screening in patients without <lb/>cirrhosis depend on the etiology of liver disease and the stage of fibrosis, assessed by liver biopsy or noninvasive <lb/>tests such as FIB-4 or transient elastography. However, clear recommendations for HCC screening in patients <lb/>without cirrhosis and for the different etiologies are currently unavailable. Research efforts should focus on <lb/>identifying markers, or combinations thereof, to provide a more accurate estimate of HCC occurrence. Such <lb/>advancements would enable the effective targeting of populations at the highest risk of HCC and the establishment <lb/>of the correct timing to start the screening. <lb/>Keywords: HCC, chronic liver disease, cirrhosis, HCC screening <lb/></front>

			<page>Page 2 of <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Poli et al. Hepatoma Res 2024;10:15 https://dx.doi.org/10.20517/2394-5079.2023.101 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Liver cancer is the second most prevalent cause of cancer-related deaths globally. According to the latest <lb/>report from the World Health Organization published in 2020, liver cancer accounts for 4.7% of all cancers. <lb/>It is estimated that about 1.3 million people will die from liver cancer by the year 2040 [1] . Hepatocellular <lb/>carcinoma (HCC) is the most common type of hepatic cancer and it represents the first indication for liver <lb/>transplantation in cirrhotic patients [2] . Its incidence is 2 to 3 times higher in men than in women, <lb/>particularly in certain European countries. In addition to the different distribution of modifiable risk factors <lb/>such as alcohol consumption among genders, a range of non-modifiable risk factors for HCC associated <lb/>with individual genetic predispositions and variances between male and female sexes has been <lb/>documented [3] . Hepatocarcinogenesis is a multistep process involving the transformation of hepatocytes, <lb/>which undergo malignant genomic and epigenomic changes. It is characterized by high clinical and <lb/>molecular heterogeneity [4,5] . Although the exact molecular mechanisms triggering the onset and progression <lb/>of HCC are far from being completely elucidated, the number of mutated genes and dysregulated signaling <lb/>pathways associated with HCC are going to be progressively revealed, offering novel prospects for <lb/>treatment [6,7] . Within this context, the fibrogenic process appears not to be the primary trigger; instead, <lb/>chronic non-resolving inflammation seems to play a pivotal role, by chronically producing cytokines such <lb/>as IL-6, growth factors, chemokines, and proangiogenic factors. The onset of this environment favoring <lb/>immune escape has been shown to be critical for the transformation of hepatic progenitor cells into a <lb/>cancerous phenotype, alongside promoting the activation of anti-apoptotic pathway and inhibiting immune <lb/>surveillance [8,9] . <lb/>Once the patient progresses to cirrhosis, the annual incidence of HCC is about 2%-4% [10-13] . Consequently, <lb/>screening is recommended in the cirrhotic population as it is exceeding the minimum threshold of <lb/>1.0%-1.5% per year [14,15] . <lb/>The worldwide disparity in HCC incidence is due to variations in the prevalence of viral hepatitis, which is <lb/>more prevalent in low-income countries, and environmental factors, predominant in high-income <lb/>countries. The underlying etiology of liver disease often represents an independent risk factor for HCC <lb/>occurrence, posing a significant oncologic risk also in the early stages of liver disease [12,13] . Indeed, different <lb/>etiologies of liver disease bring with them a different degree and pattern of chronic inflammation, which <lb/>may or may not increase HCC risk even in pre-cirrhotic stages of compensated advanced chronic liver <lb/>disease. Consequently, identifying the risk of developing HCC for each patient group is crucial for defining <lb/>the appropriate screening and follow-up strategies. <lb/>As reported by the Global Burden of Disease study in 2019, hepatitis B virus (HBV) accounted for 41.0% of <lb/>HCC cases, hepatitis C virus (HCV) for 28.5%, alcohol-related liver disease (ALD) for 18.4%, metabolic <lb/>dysfunction-associated steatotic liver disease (MASLD) for 6.8%, and other etiologies for 5.3% [13] . <lb/>Early diagnosis of HCC poses a significant challenge, and the availability of noninvasive biomarkers is <lb/>crucial. Currently, serum alpha-fetoprotein (AFP) serves as the primary serum biomarker for HCC, yet <lb/>AFP-based diagnostic approaches remain less than satisfactory. While serum AFP alone lacks satisfactory <lb/>sensitivity and specificity to serve as a standalone screening test, its combination with abdominal ultrasound <lb/>significantly enhances sensitivity in detecting early-stage HCC (within the Milan criteria) [16] . Several <lb/>biomarkers have been identified and retrospectively studied as diagnostic tools, but few have undergone <lb/>external validation and biomarkers validated across different populations are yet to be identified and <lb/>included in HCC clinical guidelines [17] . The challenge in finding appropriate biomarkers may also be <lb/>attributed to the different etiologies of underlying cirrhosis. Nonetheless, with proper validation, the shift <lb/></body>

			<page>Page 3 of <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Poli et al. Hepatoma Res 2024;10:15 https://dx.doi.org/10.20517/2394-5079.2023.101 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>from using ultrasound-based methods to a biomarker-based screening approach for HCC appears viable in <lb/>the near future, offering the potential for a substantial decrease in the incidence of HCC among high-risk <lb/>populations [18] . The introduction of biomarker-based screening will facilitate the implementation of <lb/>screening programs in low-income countries, where, at the moment, the majority of HCC cases are <lb/>diagnosed at an advanced stage [12] . <lb/>HCC RISK ACCORDING TO LIVER DISEASE ETIOLOGY <lb/>HCC and HBV +/-HDV infection <lb/>HBV infection remains the main risk factor for HCC worldwide, particularly in Asian countries, where <lb/>more than half of the global HCC population resides [11,13,19] . HBV may increase the risk of HCC by <lb/>5-100 fold [12] . In endemic areas, HBV is etiologically implicated in up to 80% of all HCC cases, while in <lb/>Western countries, it accounts for about 20% of HCC cases [19] . <lb/>Beyond its role in causing cirrhosis, HBV itself plays a critical role in the development of HCC, initiating <lb/>the activation of oncogenic pathways by integrating into host DNA [20-22] . As a matter of fact, chronic HBV <lb/>non-cirrhotic carriers can develop liver cancer and the incidence of HCC in these patients is reported to be <lb/>around 0.2/100 person-years [12,19] . In patients with chronic hepatitis B without cirrhosis, the most significant <lb/>factor associated with HCC occurrence is HBV viral load: patients receiving NUCs with incomplete <lb/>suppression, even with low levels of viremia, showed a higher risk of HCC compared to patients with <lb/>undetectable HBV-DNA [23,24] . When cirrhosis occurs, independently from viral load, the incidence of HCC <lb/>rises to 3.7 per 100 person-years, signifying a 31-fold increased risk of HCC and 44-fold increased <lb/>mortality [11,12] . <lb/>In the context of HBV-HDV co-infection, a significant increase in the global risk of HCC development is <lb/>reported compared to HBV mono-infection. The cumulative incidence of HCC was 2.3%, 5.4%, and 7.5% at <lb/>1, 3, and 5 years, respectively, in non-cirrhotic patients, rising to 5.4%, 15.9%, and 23.1% at 1, 3, and 5 years, <lb/>respectively, in cirrhotic patients [25] . Major risk factors are liver cirrhosis, high HDV-RNA serum level, age &gt; <lb/>50 years, male gender, obesity, and lower platelet count. <lb/>Moreover, a significant six-fold increase in the risk of HCC was observed in patients with triple infection of <lb/>HIV, HBV, and HDV, compared to those with HIV/HBV co-infection [26] . <lb/>Several noninvasive HCC risk scores have been published worldwide in HBV patients with or without <lb/>antiviral treatment [27] . Even with their high negative predictive values for HCC occurrence spanning a <lb/>3-to 10-year period, there is no universally appliable score. <lb/>Paik et al. evaluated the effectiveness of two noninvasive serum biomarkers, the aspartate aminotransferase <lb/>to platelet ratio index (APRI, threshold of 0.5), and the Fibrosis 4 score (FIB-4, threshold of 1.45), in <lb/>stratifying the risk of HCC among chronic HBV-infected patients (both cirrhotic and non-cirrhotic) with <lb/>low-level viremia (HBV DNA &lt; 2,000 IU/mL). The authors showed that in the entire cohort, the 5-year <lb/>cumulative incidence rates of HCC were 13.9%, 1.4%, and 1.2% for those with both high, any high, and both <lb/>low, respectively. Among non-cirrhotic patients (n = 867, P &lt; 0.001), the rates were 11.4%, 1.5%, and 0.4%, <lb/>respectively [28] . Additionally, the PAGE-B and modified-PAGE-B models [29,30] have been validated for <lb/>predicting HCC risk in HBV patients undergoing NUC treatment. <lb/>Thus, in patients with chronic HBV infection, the two main risk factors for HCC occurrence are the stage of <lb/>liver disease and viral load. Besides initiating early HCC screening and antiviral treatment in patients that <lb/></body>

			<page>Page 4 of <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Poli et al. Hepatoma Res 2024;10:15 https://dx.doi.org/10.20517/2394-5079.2023.101 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>are already infected, immunization against HBV should always be checked as it is the best prevention <lb/>strategy. In Taiwan, 30 years after the beginning of universal newborn vaccination, HBV carrier rates have <lb/>dropped from 10%-17% to 0.7%-1.7%, resulting in an 80% reduction in HCC rates [31] . <lb/>HCC and HCV infection <lb/>Historically, the majority of HCC cases in high-income countries were associated with chronic HCV <lb/>infection. However, this trend has recently shown a decline due to the advent of new direct antiviral agents <lb/>(DAA). The risk of HCC occurrence in patients with HCV-related cirrhosis is approximately 2%-6% per <lb/>year, almost 17-fold higher compared to other cirrhotic patients with compensated disease [19] . Typically, <lb/>HCC development occurs after two or more decades of HCV infection, and the increased risk has <lb/>traditionally been limited to patients with cirrhosis. Notably, the incidence of HCC in the USA has tripled <lb/>over the last four decades, likely due to the aging chronic hepatitis C patient pool, alongside a significant <lb/>increase in MASLD, and the implementation of more accurate screening programs using ultrasounds in <lb/>cirrhotic patients [32] . <lb/>In the context of HCV-related cirrhosis, the FIB-4 score has a better prognostic performance for HCC <lb/>occurrence prediction than APRI. Values &gt; 2.18 were able to predict the occurrence of HCC with high <lb/>sensitivity and specificity (92.4% and 87.2%, respectively) [33] . Degasperi et al. described a significantly <lb/>increased 3-year risk of HCC in cirrhotic patients with LSM values &gt; 30 kPa or with FIB-4 &gt; 9 at baseline [34] . <lb/>A multicenter French study developed an HCC score [taking into account age &gt; 50 years, past excessive <lb/>alcohol intake, low platelets count, high gammaGT levels, and absence of sustained virological response <lb/>(SVR)], which can accurately predict the 1-, 3-and 5-year HCC occurrence [35] . The presence of clinically <lb/>significant portal hypertension, defined as the presence of esophageal varices and/or ascites, was also found <lb/>to be an independent predictor of HCC occurrence in several studies involving HCV cirrhotic patients <lb/>treated with DAA [36,37] . <lb/>Therefore, the prevention of liver disease progression seems to be the most important factor affecting HCC <lb/>risk in HCV patients. The early achievement of a SVR in HCV-infected patients has led to a substantial <lb/>decrease in the risk of HCC worldwide, esteemed to be around 50% to 80% [38,39] . However, Eradicating HCV <lb/>reduces, though does not completely eliminate, the risk of HCC in patients with confirmed cirrhosis, <lb/>necessitating lifelong monitoring [40,41] . <lb/>Interestingly, it has been demonstrated that machine learning algorithms can enhance HCC risk prediction <lb/>in HCV patients, and possibly in individuals with other causes of liver disease [42] . <lb/>HCC and MASLD <lb/>The MASLD, now replacing the term non-alcoholic fatty liver disease/steatohepatitis according to the new <lb/>nomenclature, is rapidly emerging as the most common etiology of chronic liver disease worldwide [12,43] and <lb/>is the fastest-rising cause of HCC. As the occurrence of HBV-related HCC is expected to decrease thanks to <lb/>vaccination coverage and viral suppression with antiviral treatments, and HCV-related HCC diminishes <lb/>with the advent of DAA, the absolute prevalence increase in MASLD is becoming even more significant <lb/>when assessed in terms of percentages and is destinated to become the most common etiology of liver <lb/>disease underlying HCC in numerous countries [44] . In Western countries, MASLD-related HCC has <lb/>increased by up to threefold in the last decades [15] . The stage of fibrosis is identified as one of the strongest <lb/>liver-related predictors of overall survival and HCC development in MASLD patients [45] . <lb/></body>

			<page>Page 5 of <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Poli et al. Hepatoma Res 2024;10:15 https://dx.doi.org/10.20517/2394-5079.2023.101 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Nevertheless, around 25% of HCC cases associated with MASLD happen without cirrhosis, showing a 2.61 <lb/>times higher HCC incidence in non-cirrhotic MASLD livers compared to patients with chronic liver <lb/>diseases from different causes [46] . <lb/>According to the latest EASL guidelines, HCC surveillance is recommended in patients with MASLD <lb/>cirrhosis; surveillance is suggested to be considered also in patients with F3 fibrosis (either histologically or <lb/>via elastography) [47] . In cohort studies including MASLD patients without cirrhosis, the incidence of HCC <lb/>ranges from 0.08/1,000 patient-years to a maximum of 0.62/1,000 patient-years, with a recent meta-analysis <lb/>reporting an incidence of HCC in non-cirrhotic livers of 0.3/1,000 patient-years [48] . These rates are <lb/>significantly higher compared to the incidence of HCC in chronic liver diseases from other etiologies in the <lb/>absence of cirrhosis [46,49] . In the context of MASLD-related cirrhosis, the incidence of HCC ranges from 2 to <lb/>26/1,000 person-years, depending on cohort characteristics [48,50,51] . <lb/>Concerning the role of noninvasive tests of fibrosis, Kanwal et al. suggested that a FIB-4 score &gt; 3.25 can <lb/>predict an HCC risk &gt; 1%, thereby recommending HCC surveillance in these patients [50] . <lb/>HCC and alcohol-related liver disease <lb/>The established causal relationship between alcohol intake and HCC occurrence is well-documented [15,52] . A <lb/>recent meta-analysis reported a cumulative risk of HCC at 5 and 10 years in alcohol-related cirrhosis of 3% <lb/>and 9%, respectively [53] . Indeed, in addition to the duration of chronic alcohol consumption, a metanalysis <lb/>estimated a 16% increase in the risk of HCC among those patients consuming 3 or more alcoholic units/day <lb/>and a 22% increased risk among those consuming &gt; 6 units/day [54] , compared to non-drinking patients. <lb/>Moreover, alcohol can act synergistically with other liver disease etiologies, exacerbating the progression of <lb/>liver disease and further elevating the risk for HCC occurrence [55,56] . <lb/>Regarding the role of noninvasive tests, the cumulative incidence rate of HCC at 3 years was 4.1% in <lb/>patients with a modified FIB-4 index &gt; 4 and 0.7% in patients with an index &lt; 4. This suggests the need for <lb/>HCC screening in the former group [57] . In the context of ALD, total abstinence from alcoholic beverages <lb/>stands as the only effective method to reduce HCC-risk occurrence. This recommendation should also be <lb/>extended to patients with other underlying etiologies of liver disease, as in these patients, the role of alcohol <lb/>in promoting liver disease progression and increasing oncologic risk tends to be underestimated. <lb/>HCC and rare liver diseases <lb/>In the context of autoimmune hepatitis (AIH), the occurrence of HCC has historically been considered a <lb/>rare complication [58] . However, a recent retrospective, observational, multicentric study revealed an <lb/>incidence rate of HCC in patients with AIH of 1.44/1,000 patient-years. After cirrhosis develops, the <lb/>cumulative incidence of HCC increases to 2.6%, 4.6%, 5.6%, and 6.6% at 5, 10, 15, and 20 years, <lb/>respectively [59] . Obesity, cirrhosis, and AIH/primary sclerosing cholangitis overlap syndrome were <lb/>independent risk factors for HCC occurrence. These incidences meet the cut-off value of 1.5%, thereby <lb/>recommending HCC screening as recommended and cost-effective. <lb/>Patients with primary biliary cholangitis (PBC) show an incidence of HCC of 2.4%. According to the latest <lb/>Japanese data, HCC incidence is 5.1% in males and 2.0% in females [60] . A recent multicenter international <lb/>study in Europe reported an HCC incidence of 3.4/1,000 patient-years, with a similar increased incidence in <lb/>men [61] . This increased incidence of HCC in males was irrespective of histological stage, emphasizing the <lb/>importance of HCC screening for males with PBC from an early stage of the disease. <lb/></body>

			<page>Page 6 of <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Poli et al. Hepatoma Res 2024;10:15 https://dx.doi.org/10.20517/2394-5079.2023.101 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

            <body>The exact annual incidence of HCC in HFE-related hereditary hemochromatosis remains undefined, but it <lb/>appears to be close to 1.5%. The majority of HCC occurs in cirrhotic livers with iron overload, but the <lb/>occurrence of HCC in non-cirrhotic livers of patients with hemochromatosis has also been described. <lb/>According to the latest EASL recommendations, HCC screening in patients with hemochromatosis should <lb/>be proposed if, at the time of diagnosis, the fibrosis stage is at least F3 and should be continued even if iron <lb/>depletion allows regression of liver fibrosis to a lower stage [62] . <lb/>In Wilson&apos;s disease, the chance of developing primary liver cancer is said to be low. A European study of <lb/>1,186 patients found that only 1.2% had liver cancer, with an incidence rate of 0.28 per 1,000 patient-years. <lb/>Cirrhosis continues to be the main risk factor for liver cancer in these patients [58] . <lb/>Table 1 summarizes the actual indications for 6-month interval ultra-sounds HCC screening according to <lb/>liver disease etiology and stage of liver disease. <lb/>CONCLUSION <lb/>In conclusion, the risk of HCC is primarily determined by the progression of liver disease, which is strongly <lb/>influenced by the underlying etiological factor. A 6-month HCC surveillance by abdominal ultrasound and <lb/>serum AFP is recommended for patients with cirrhosis of any etiology and some selected patients with <lb/>chronic HBV infection. The etiological treatment of liver disease remains the most effective oncological <lb/>prevention. Some etiologies demonstrate significant HCC incidence rates even in the non-cirrhotic <lb/>population; nevertheless, the paucity of data does not allow the formulation of robust guidelines in this <lb/>regard at present. <lb/></body>

            <div type="annex">DECLARATIONS <lb/></div>

            <div type="contribution">Authors&apos; contributions <lb/>Draft manuscript preparation, review of the manuscript, and approval of the final version of the <lb/>manuscript: Poli E <lb/>Review of the manuscript and approval of the final version of the manuscript: De Martin E <lb/></div>

            <div type="availability">Availability of data and materials <lb/>Original data from the literature, elaborated by the authors. <lb/></div>

            <body>Table 1. Actual indications for 6-month interval ultra-sounds HCC screening according to liver disease etiology and stage of liver <lb/>disease <lb/>Liver disease etiology <lb/>Non-cirrhotic patients <lb/>Cirrhotic patients <lb/>HBV <lb/>Any chronic HBV with ≥ 10 PAGE-B score <lb/>Family history of HCC <lb/>Africans, African-Americans, Asian males &gt; 40 yr <lb/>Asian females &gt; 50 yr <lb/>HCV <lb/>Chronic HCV with bridging fibrosis (Metavir F3) <lb/>MASLD <lb/>Suggested to be considered if F3 fibrosis (either histologically or via elastography) <lb/>Suggested to be considered if FIB-4 &gt; 3.25 <lb/>Alcohol <lb/>Not recommended <lb/>PBC <lb/>Suggested to be considered in males (irrespective of histological stage) <lb/>AIH <lb/>Not recommended <lb/>Hemochromatosis <lb/>Suggested to be considered if F3 fibrosis (either histologically or via elastography) <lb/>Wilson disease <lb/>Not recommended <lb/>All, any etiology <lb/></body>

			<page>Page 7 of <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Poli et al. Hepatoma Res 2024;10:15 https://dx.doi.org/10.20517/2394-5079.2023.101 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<div type="funding">Financial support and sponsorship <lb/>None. <lb/></div>

            <div type="conflict">Conflicts of interest <lb/>Both declared that there are no conflicts of interest. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Ethical approval and consent to participate <lb/>Not applicable. <lb/>Consent for publication <lb/>Not applicable. <lb/></div>

			<front>Copyright <lb/>© The Author(s) 2024. <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>Rumgay H, Arnold M, Ferlay J, et al. Global burden of primary liver cancer in 2020 and predictions to 2040. J Hepatol 2022;77:1598-<lb/>606. DOI <lb/>1. <lb/>Overall indications and results for liver transplantation in Europe. Available online: http://www.eltr.org/spip.php?article161. <lb/>2. <lb/>Nevola R, Tortorella G, Rosato V, et al. Gender differences in the pathogenesis and risk factors of hepatocellular carcinoma. Biology <lb/>2023;12:984. DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>3. <lb/>Vij M, Calderaro J. Pathologic and molecular features of hepatocellular carcinoma: an update. World J Hepatol 2021;13:393-410. <lb/>DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>4. <lb/>Zhuravleva E, O&apos;Rourke CJ, Andersen JB. Mutational signatures and processes in hepatobiliary cancers. Nat Rev Gastroenterol <lb/>Hepatol 2022;19:367-82. DOI PubMed <lb/>5. <lb/>Fernández-Barrena MG, Arechederra M, Colyn L, Berasain C, Avila MA. Epigenetics in hepatocellular carcinoma development and <lb/>therapy: The tip of the iceberg. JHEP Rep 2020;2:100167. DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>6. <lb/>Llovet JM, Pinyol R, Kelley RK, et al. Molecular pathogenesis and systemic therapies for hepatocellular carcinoma. Nat Cancer <lb/>2022;3:386-401. DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>7. <lb/>Nenu I, Toadere TM, Topor I, et al. Interleukin-6 in hepatocellular carcinoma: a dualistic point of view. Biomedicines 2023;11:2623. <lb/>DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>8. <lb/>Allaire M, Rudler M, Thabut D. Portal hypertension and hepatocellular carcinoma: Des liaisons dangereuses…. Liver Int <lb/>2021;41:1734-43. DOI PubMed <lb/>9. <lb/>Sung H, Ferlay J, Siegel RL, et al. Global cancer statistics 2020: GLOBOCAN estimates of incidence and mortality worldwide for 36 <lb/>cancers in 185 countries. CA Cancer J Clin 2021;71:209-49. DOI <lb/>10. <lb/>Sagnelli E, Macera M, Russo A, Coppola N, Sagnelli C. Epidemiological and etiological variations in hepatocellular carcinoma. <lb/>Infection 2020;48:7-17. DOI PubMed <lb/>11. <lb/>Devarbhavi H, Asrani SK, Arab JP, Nartey YA, Pose E, Kamath PS. Global burden of liver disease: 2023 update. J Hepatol <lb/>2023;79:516-37. DOI PubMed <lb/>12. <lb/>Liu Y, Zheng J, Hao J, et al. Global burden of primary liver cancer by five etiologies and global prediction by 2035 based on global <lb/>burden of disease study 2019. Cancer Med 2022;11:1310-23. DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>13. <lb/>Parikh ND, Singal AG, Hutton DW, Tapper EB. Cost-effectiveness of hepatocellular carcinoma surveillance: an assessment of benefits <lb/>and harms. Am J Gastroenterol 2020;115:1642-9. DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>14. <lb/>Singal AG, Kanwal F, Llovet JM. Global trends in hepatocellular carcinoma epidemiology: implications for screening, prevention and <lb/>therapy. Nat Rev Clin Oncol 2023;20:864-84. DOI PubMed <lb/>15. <lb/>Tzartzeva K, Obi J, Rich NE, et al. Surveillance imaging and alpha fetoprotein for early detection of hepatocellular carcinoma in <lb/>patients with cirrhosis: a meta-analysis. Gastroenterology 2018;154:1706-1718.e1. DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>16. <lb/>Marques H, Gomes da Silva S, De Martin E, Agopian VG, Martins PN. Emerging biomarkers in HCC patients: current status. Int J <lb/>Surg 2020;82S:70-6. DOI PubMed <lb/>17. <lb/>Parikh ND, Tayob N, Singal AG. Blood-based biomarkers for hepatocellular carcinoma screening: approaching the end of the <lb/>ultrasound era? J Hepatol 2023;78:207-16. DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>18. <lb/>Shen C, Jiang X, Li M, Luo Y. Hepatitis virus and hepatocellular carcinoma: recent advances. Cancers 2023;15:533. DOI PubMed <lb/>PMC <lb/>19. <lb/>Péneau C, Imbeaud S, La Bella T, et al. Hepatitis B virus integrations promote local and distant oncogenic driver alterations in <lb/>hepatocellular carcinoma. Gut 2022;71:616-26. DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>20. <lb/>Dhanasekaran R, Nault JC, Roberts LR, Zucman-Rossi J. Genomic medicine and implications for hepatocellular carcinoma prevention <lb/>21. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>Page 8 of <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Poli et al. Hepatoma Res 2024;10:15 https://dx.doi.org/10.20517/2394-5079.2023.101 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>and therapy. Gastroenterology 2019;156:492-509. DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>Ligat G, Schuster C, Baumert TF. Hepatitis B virus core variants, liver fibrosis, and hepatocellular carcinoma. Hepatology 2019;69:5-<lb/>8. DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>22. <lb/>Battistella S, Lynch EN, Gambato M, et al. Hepatocellular carcinoma risk in patients with HBV-related liver disease receiving antiviral <lb/>therapy. Minerva Gastroenterol 2021;67:38-49. DOI <lb/>23. <lb/>Kim JH, Sinn DH, Kang W, et al. Low-level viremia and the increased risk of hepatocellular carcinoma in patients receiving entecavir <lb/>treatment. Hepatology 2017;66:335-43. DOI PubMed <lb/>24. <lb/>Jang TY, Wei YJ, Liu TW, et al. Role of hepatitis D virus infection in development of hepatocellular carcinoma among chronic <lb/>hepatitis B patients treated with nucleotide/nucleoside analogues. Sci Rep 2021;11:8184. DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>25. <lb/>Kamal H, Fornes R, Simin J, et al. Risk of hepatocellular carcinoma in hepatitis B and D virus co-infected patients: a systematic <lb/>review and meta-analysis of longitudinal studies. J Viral Hepat 2021;28:1431-42. DOI PubMed <lb/>26. <lb/>Hao X, Fan R, Zeng HM, Hou JL. Hepatocellular Carcinoma risk scores from modeling to real clinical practice in areas highly <lb/>endemic for hepatitis B infection. J Clin Transl Hepatol 2023;11:1508-19. DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>27. <lb/>Paik N, Sinn DH, Lee JH, et al. Non-invasive tests for liver disease severity and the hepatocellular carcinoma risk in chronic hepatitis <lb/>B patients with low-level viremia. Liver Int 2018;38:68-75. DOI PubMed <lb/>28. <lb/>Papatheodoridis G, Dalekos G, Sypsa V, et al. PAGE-B predicts the risk of developing hepatocellular carcinoma in Caucasians with <lb/>chronic hepatitis B on 5-year antiviral therapy. J Hepatol 2016;64:800-6. DOI <lb/>29. <lb/>Kim JH, Kim YD, Lee M, et al. Modified PAGE-B score predicts the risk of hepatocellular carcinoma in Asians with chronic hepatitis <lb/>B on antiviral therapy. J Hepatol 2018;69:1066-73. DOI <lb/>30. <lb/>Chang MH, You SL, Chen CJ, et al; Taiwan Hepatoma Study Group. Long-term effects of hepatitis B immunization of infants in <lb/>preventing liver cancer. Gastroenterology 2016;151:472-80.e1. DOI <lb/>31. <lb/>Koshiol J, Argirion I, Liu Z, et al. Immunologic markers and risk of hepatocellular carcinoma in hepatitis B virus-and hepatitis C <lb/>virus-infected individuals. Aliment Pharmacol Ther 2021;54:833-42. DOI PubMed <lb/>32. <lb/>Li X, Xu H, Gao P. Fibrosis index based on 4 factors (FIB-4) predicts liver cirrhosis and hepatocellular carcinoma in chronic hepatitis <lb/>C virus (HCV) patients. Med Sci Monit 2019;25:7243-50. DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>33. <lb/>Degasperi E, D&apos;Ambrosio R, Iavarone M, et al. Factors associated with increased risk of de novo or recurrent hepatocellular carcinoma <lb/>in patients with cirrhosis treated with direct-acting antivirals for HCV infection. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol 2019;17:1183-1191.e7. <lb/>DOI PubMed <lb/>34. <lb/>Ganne-Carrié N, Layese R, Bourcier V, et al; ANRS CO12 CirVir Study Group. Nomogram for individualized prediction of <lb/>hepatocellular carcinoma occurrence in hepatitis C virus cirrhosis (ANRS CO12 CirVir). Hepatology 2016;64:1136-47. DOI PubMed <lb/>35. <lb/>Lleo A, Aglitti A, Aghemo A, et al. Predictors of hepatocellular carcinoma in HCV cirrhotic patients treated with direct acting <lb/>antivirals. Dig Liv Dis 2019;51:310-7. DOI PubMed <lb/>36. <lb/>Sangiovanni A, Alimenti E, Gattai R, et al. Undefined/non-malignant hepatic nodules are associated with early occurrence of HCC in <lb/>DAA-treated patients with HCV-related cirrhosis. J Hepatol 2020;73:593-602. DOI <lb/>37. <lb/>Marrero JA, Kulik LM, Sirlin CB, et al. Diagnosis, staging, and management of hepatocellular carcinoma: 2018 practice guidance by <lb/>the american association for the study of liver diseases. Hepatology 2018;68:723-50. DOI PubMed <lb/>38. <lb/>Kanwal F, Kramer J, Asch SM, Chayanupatkul M, Cao Y, El-Serag HB. Risk of hepatocellular cancer in HCV patients treated with <lb/>direct-acting antiviral agents. Gastroenterology 2017;153:996-1005.e1. DOI PubMed <lb/>39. <lb/>Ioannou GN. HCC surveillance after SVR in patients with F3/F4 fibrosis. J Hepatol 2021;74:458-65. DOI PubMed <lb/>40. <lb/>Beste LA, Green P, Berry K, Belperio P, Ioannou GN. Hepatitis C-related hepatocellular carcinoma incidence in the veterans health <lb/>administration after introduction of direct-acting antivirals. JAMA 2020;324:1003-5. DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>41. <lb/>Audureau E, Carrat F, Layese R, et al; ANRS CO12 CirVir group. Personalized surveillance for hepatocellular carcinoma in cirrhosis -<lb/>using machine learning adapted to HCV status. J Hepatol 2020;73:1434-45. DOI PubMed <lb/>42. <lb/>Younossi Z, Anstee QM, Marietti M, et al. Global burden of NAFLD and NASH: trends, predictions, risk factors and prevention. Nat <lb/>Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol 2018;15:11-20. DOI <lb/>43. <lb/>Estes C, Anstee QM, Arias-Loste MT, et al. Modeling NAFLD disease burden in China, France, Germany, Italy, Japan, Spain, United <lb/>Kingdom, and United States for the period 2016-2030. J Hepatol 2018;69:896-904. DOI PubMed <lb/>44. <lb/>Ekstedt M, Hagström H, Nasr P, et al. Fibrosis stage is the strongest predictor for disease-specific mortality in NAFLD after up to 33 <lb/>years of follow-up. Hepatology 2015;61:1547-54. DOI PubMed <lb/>45. <lb/>Stine JG, Wentworth BJ, Zimmet A, et al. Systematic review with meta-analysis: risk of hepatocellular carcinoma in non-alcoholic <lb/>steatohepatitis without cirrhosis compared to other liver diseases. Aliment Pharmacol Ther 2018;48:696-703. DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>46. <lb/>Association for the Study of the Liver. EASL clinical practice guidelines: management of hepatocellular carcinoma. J Hepatol <lb/>2018;69:182-236. DOI PubMed <lb/>47. <lb/>Orci LA, Sanduzzi-Zamparelli M, Caballol B, et al. Incidence of hepatocellular carcinoma in patients with nonalcoholic fatty liver <lb/>disease: a systematic review, meta-analysis, and meta-regression. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol 2022;20:283-292.e10. DOI <lb/>48. <lb/>Mittal S, El-Serag HB, Sada YH, et al. Hepatocellular carcinoma in the absence of cirrhosis in United States Veterans is associated <lb/>with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol 2016;14:124-31.e1. DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>49. <lb/>Kanwal F, Kramer JR, Mapakshi S, et al. Risk of hepatocellular cancer in patients with non-alcoholic fatty liver disease. <lb/>Gastroenterology 2018;155:1828-1837.e2. DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>50. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>Page 9 of <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Poli et al. Hepatoma Res 2024;10:15 https://dx.doi.org/10.20517/2394-5079.2023.101 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Ioannou GN, Green P, Kerr KF, Berry K. Models estimating risk of hepatocellular carcinoma in patients with alcohol or NAFLD-<lb/>related cirrhosis for risk stratification. J Hepatol 2019;71:523-33. DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>51. <lb/>Morgan TR, Mandayam S, Jamal MM. Alcohol and hepatocellular carcinoma. Gastroenterology 2004;127:S87-96. DOI PubMed <lb/>52. <lb/>Huang DQ, Tan DJH, Ng CH, et al. Hepatocellular carcinoma incidence in alcohol-associated cirrhosis: systematic review and meta-<lb/>analysis. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol 2023;21:1169-77. DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>53. <lb/>Turati F, Galeone C, Rota M, et al. Alcohol and liver cancer: a systematic review and meta-analysis of prospective studies. Ann Oncol <lb/>2014;25:1526-35. DOI <lb/>54. <lb/>Lin CW, Lin CC, Mo LR, et al. Heavy alcohol consumption increases the incidence of hepatocellular carcinoma in hepatitis B virus-<lb/>related cirrhosis. J Hepatol 2013;58:730-5. DOI <lb/>55. <lb/>Innes HA, Hutchinson SJ, Barclay S, et al; Hepatitis C Clinical Database Monitoring Committee. Quantifying the fraction of cirrhosis <lb/>attributable to alcohol among chronic hepatitis C virus patients: implications for treatment cost-effectiveness. Hepatology <lb/>2013;57:451-60. DOI <lb/>56. <lb/>Kim JH, Lee M, Park SW, et al. Validation of modified fibrosis-4 index for predicting hepatocellular carcinoma in patients with <lb/>compensated alcoholic liver cirrhosis. Medicine 2018;97:e13438. DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>57. <lb/>Tansel A, Katz LH, El-Serag HB, et al. Incidence and determinants of hepatocellular carcinoma in autoimmune hepatitis: a systematic <lb/>review and meta-analysis. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol 2017;15:1207-17. DOI PubMed PMC <lb/>58. <lb/>Colapietro F, Maisonneuve P, Lytvyak E, et al; Dutch AIH Study Group; International Autoimmune Hepatitis Group. Incidence and <lb/>predictors of hepatocellular carcinoma in patients with autoimmune hepatitis. J Hepatol 2024;80:53-61. DOI PubMed <lb/>59. <lb/>Harada K, Hirohara J, Ueno Y, et al. Incidence of and risk factors for hepatocellular carcinoma in primary biliary cirrhosis: national <lb/>data from Japan. Hepatology 2013;57:1942-9. DOI <lb/>60. <lb/>Trivedi PJ, Lammers WJ, van Buuren HR, et al; Global PBC Study Group. Stratification of hepatocellular carcinoma risk in primary <lb/>biliary cirrhosis: a multicentre international study. Gut 2016;65:321-9. DOI <lb/>61. <lb/>Association for the Study of the Liver. EASL clinical practice guidelines on haemochromatosis. J Hepatol 2022;77:479-502. DOI <lb/>PubMed <lb/>62. <lb/>Pfeiffenberger J, Mogler C, Gotthardt DN, et al. Hepatobiliary malignancies in Wilson disease. Liver Int 2015;35:1615-22. DOI <lb/>63. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
