<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Available online at www.HighTechJournal.org <lb/>HighTech and Innovation <lb/>Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 1, March, 2024 <lb/>143 <lb/>ISSN: 2723-9535 <lb/>An Effective Model of Viral Marketing for e-Commerce <lb/>Enterprises: An Empirical Study <lb/>Radwan Moh&apos;d Al-Dwairi 1* , Ali Alawneh 2 <lb/>1 Department of Information Technology, Yarmouk University, Irbid, Jordan. <lb/>2 Management Information Systems Department, Faculty of Information Technology, Philadelphia University, Amman 19392, Jordan. <lb/>Received 02 October 2023; Revised 24 February 2024; Accepted 27 February 2024; Published 01 March 2024 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Despite the widespread significance of digital marketing in disseminating information about products and services across <lb/>a vast customer base via diverse networks, a noteworthy proportion of businesses still struggle to comprehend the crucial <lb/>factors underpinning the success of viral campaigns. This study aims not only to bridge this knowledge gap but also to <lb/>introduce an innovative framework that underscores various factors that amplify the potency of social networks and <lb/>emphasizes an often-overlooked element in customer engagement: the psychological state of customers. Empirical <lb/>validation of the framework was conducted using a sample of 135 respondents, which was analyzed using the structured <lb/>equation modeling technique. The study&apos;s findings show that the strength of social connections (strong ties) and the <lb/>psychological disposition of customers significantly shape the generation and viral dissemination of marketing content <lb/>across diverse networks. The importance of this research lies in its potential application by commercial companies for <lb/>conducting promotional and marketing campaigns. By leveraging the proposed model, businesses can effectively promote <lb/>their products and services, thus achieving their strategic objectives and gaining a competitive advantage in an environment <lb/>characterized by intense competition and constant change. <lb/>Keywords: Viral Marketing; Social Networks; Strong Ties; Social Support; Psychological State; Customers&apos; Similarities; Word-of-Mouth. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>In physical marketplaces, businesses use several forms of communication tools to influence consumers&apos; buying <lb/>processes. Traditional marketing tools such as radio, TV, in-store promotion, and print advertising can increase <lb/>awareness of goods; hence, this can help in implementing different types of marketing strategies. During the Internet <lb/>and social media age, e-commerce and social commerce are flourishing, and consequently, the entire buying process for <lb/>customers as well as marketing strategies and techniques have dramatically changed. In addition, the influencers of <lb/>social media start to play a vital role in customers&apos; buying decisions as well as their attitudes towards business brands. <lb/>The Internet is considered the &quot;fifth channel,&quot; following the traditional channels for implementing e-commerce <lb/>practices and marketing tools [1]. However, the usage of the Internet in this domain does not stop the use of traditional <lb/>marketing methods to encourage potential customers to enter the online buying process. In addition, the business market <lb/>changed dramatically in communication strategies for implementing marketing campaigns. Hence, a new theme like <lb/>viral marketing has started to be deployed using word-of-mouth in different types of networks [2]. For example, it is <lb/></body>

			<front>* Corresponding author: r.aldwairi@yu.edu.jo <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.28991/HIJ-2024-05-01-011 <lb/> This is an open access article under the CC-BY license (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/>© Authors retain all copyrights. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 1, March, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>144 <lb/></page>

			<body>easier than ever to communicate a message to many people and share information among them with exponential speed <lb/>[1]. Social media marketing is understood as a group of Internet-based applications that build on the Web, which allow <lb/>the exchange and creation of user-generated content and allow businesses to buy, sell, and reach their customers <lb/>effectively [3]. This can help e-commerce enterprises get useful feedback for improvements in their business models <lb/>and running processes. So that the one-to-one model of interaction or the podcasting model is replaced with a two-way <lb/>communication model. In addition, customers can interact easily with their friends and share, like hash tags, etc., a <lb/>particular message or ad that opens the door for utilizing a new type of marketing, which is called viral marketing. <lb/>Social media is an effective medium suited for viral marketing that is convenient to transmit the marketing message <lb/>to a large group of people. The effect of users on other users is nine times more effective and powerful than advertising <lb/>in a newspaper, magazine, or TV channel [1]. Turban et al. [4] mentioned that the unhappy consumer could share her <lb/>feelings with 10 friends in a traditional environment; however, her behaviour can reach hundreds in the era of social <lb/>networks. In addition, the authors mentioned that a musician initiated a social media firestorm against an airline company <lb/>that refused to pay for damaging his guitar in an airport by producing three YouTube videos that spread virally and <lb/>consequently gained more than ten million views. The difference between viral marketing and other types of marketing <lb/>is that viral marketing has content that provokes people, whereas creative content, due to its authenticity on electronic <lb/>social networks, can reach a large number of audiences by virally spreading from one individual to another on social <lb/>networks [5]. Because of that, successful viral campaigns easily spread in such networks in an inexpensive way, which <lb/>has a wonderful impact on customers purchasing behavior [6]. Consequently, viral marketing is an effective marketing <lb/>technique where electronic communications about a particular brand or service are triggered throughout a wide network <lb/>of buyers [7]. Besides, viral marketing is a marketing mechanism in which it uses the services of social networking <lb/>platforms and other techniques to maximize brand awareness or gain more marketing goals by self-repeating the process <lb/>of viral marketing, like the propagation of viruses among computer systems on a network. To get benefits from utilizing <lb/>viral marketing, three parameters should be considered and checked carefully: the right message (content), the right <lb/>messenger or receiver, and the right environment [5]. The role of the receiver (customer) is very crucial in this domain <lb/>since her negative experience with a particular company or brand formulates a significant risk, which should be avoided <lb/>[8]. Consequently, how to maximize the sales of a business company by using different advertising tools and selecting <lb/>positive users for advertisements is a critical problem and considered a challenge for marketers [9]. <lb/>Within the existing literature, there are multiple studies that delve into user patterns to facilitate the deployment of <lb/>impactful marketing campaigns. However, it is important to highlight that only a limited subset of these studies squarely <lb/>focus on the domain of viral marketing [10]. Moreover, while certain scholars have ventured into empirical research to <lb/>understand the influence of viral marketing on customer attitudes, a mere handful have presented frameworks designed <lb/>to steer marketers toward executing effective campaigns [2], and unfortunately, some of these studies remain scarce [7]. <lb/>What is particularly significant, and often overlooked, is a factor entwined with the distribution of content and marketing <lb/>advertisements across diverse networks: the customer&apos;s psychological state. Consequently, this study strives to do more <lb/>than bridge this gap; it seeks to introduce an innovative framework tailored to the needs of business enterprises. This <lb/>framework has been subjected to empirical testing, accumulating a wealth of information and insights that can inform <lb/>business decision-making and elevate the execution of successful viral marketing campaigns. Additionally, the study <lb/>seeks to answer the following major research question: <lb/>RQ. What are the major factors, which are related to the tools of social media and customers&apos; behaviour, that <lb/>effectively contribute to implementing viral marketing campaigns? <lb/>This article is structured as follows: Section 2 offers an overview of related work and the formulation of hypotheses. <lb/>Section 3 details the research methodology, and Section 4 presents the data analysis and results. The discussion is <lb/>presented in Section 5, while Section 6 encompasses the research conclusions and implications. Following that, Section <lb/>7 presents research declarations, and the article concludes with a references section. <lb/>2. The Related Work and Hypotheses Development <lb/>Viral marketing is a popular and effective strategy for promoting products or services among users to spread a <lb/>message on social networks and create viral content through word-of-mouth. The success of viral marketing campaigns <lb/>depends on a variety of factors. On the other side, social media is a term used for online tools and web sites that offer a <lb/>chance for different types of interactions among individuals through new ideas, feelings, information, opinions, interests, <lb/>etc. [1]. Social media represents a group of Internet-based tools and applications that build what is known as Web 2.0 <lb/>and that allow the creation and exchange of user-generated content [11]. <lb/>Reviewing the literature in this domain revealed that some scholars pointed to the effectiveness of influencers and <lb/>communication and interactivity among individuals to create a type of social support, which in turn affects individual <lb/>attitudes and word-of-mouth towards a product or a service. For example, Hmoud et al. [12] conducted a study to <lb/>examine the role of online social media influencers on customers&apos; intentions to buy a product. Their study revealed that <lb/>trustworthiness, information quality, attractiveness, and expertise had a vital and significant role in customers&apos; <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 1, March, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>145 <lb/></page>

			<body>purchasing processes. Tu et al. [4] studied individuals&apos; opinion formation and information flows in online social <lb/>networks. They present a new model that can quantify users&apos; opinion changes as they are subjected to viral content. <lb/>Their experimental results showed that the effects of marketing campaigns on users are different from polarizing <lb/>contents, where the latter have a stronger effect. Ebrahimi et al. [13] studied how social networking sites affect <lb/>customers&apos; purchase behaviour. The result of their study demonstrated that interactions, word-of-mouth, and trends had <lb/>significantly affected customer purchasing behaviour. <lb/>The concept of viral marketing implies that peer-to-peer (consumer-to-consumer) communications are an effective <lb/>means to transform different types of digital messages using different types of internet-based tools to capture recipients&apos; <lb/>attention, trigger interest, and finally lead to the consumer&apos;s final decision. In this arena, email seems to continue to play <lb/>an informational and powerful role in recipients&apos; behaviour. The spread of spam or unsolicited bulk e-mails, viruses, and <lb/>other types of malicious software has made recipients doubtful and has caused a high level of noise in most unsolicited <lb/>e-mails. Consequently, similarities, strong ties, and social support [14] have a vital role in persuading recipients to accept <lb/>the sent invitation. Zahid et al. [15] found that customers&apos; social support led to more engagement and content sharing. <lb/>Duffett [16] conducted research to examine the effect of interactive social media marketing communications on <lb/>teenagers&apos; cognitive, affective, and behavioural attitude factors. The study assured that social media marketing <lb/>communications had a positive effect on each attitude component among users. In addition, results also showed that <lb/>teenagers who used social media for a long time and updated their profiles continuously displayed the most responses <lb/>to social media marketing communications. The study also considers the impact of several additional factors such as <lb/>usage (access, length of usage, log-on frequency, log-on duration, and profile update incidence) and demographic <lb/>(gender, age, and population group) variables on young consumers&apos; attitudes toward social media marketing <lb/>communications. <lb/>Huynh et al. [6] develop a cognitive-affective-behaviour model of viral marketing to examine the factors that affect <lb/>viral advertising using factors like tie strength, perceptual affinity, and emotions. Their study proves the significant <lb/>effect of the factors used in viral advertising. Interactivity among peers via social networking sites and their ability to <lb/>participate in content generation and transmit their experiences, opinions, and feedback to their peers help in making a <lb/>positive interface and offer a type of social support to their peers [17]. This social environment encourages peers to share <lb/>their shopping familiarities and product information with their friends. Liang &amp; Turban [18] pointed out that if a recipient <lb/>receives a type of support from a peer on a social platform, then the recipient may perform the same action. This will <lb/>boost the role of social support in affecting consumers&apos; intentions to shop online and transmitting viral marketing <lb/>messages among peers in online environments [17]. Furthermore, the study by Tobon &amp; García-Madariaga [19] <lb/>mentioned that individuals are connected in social networks where public leaders recommendations and comments have <lb/>a significant impact on their decision-making behaviours. In addition, Wang &amp; Huang [20] mentioned that digital <lb/>influencers social power can influence individuals content participation and creation. <lb/>Based on this information, we suggest the following hypothesis: <lb/>H1o: Social support and strong ties among customers have not had a significant positive impact on forwarding ads to <lb/>others. <lb/>H1: Social support and strong ties among customers have a significant positive impact on forwarding ads to others. <lb/>Currently, social networks have become an effective marketing tool to create viral marketing. However, the <lb/>accomplishment of marketing campaigns mainly depends on individuals&apos; participation in this process. Therefore, trust, <lb/>desire, and willingness among peers are important factors that play a crucial role in encouraging individuals to participate <lb/>in spreading marketing ads in a network. Trust is a transitive concept. For example, if A trusts B and B trusts C, then A <lb/>trusts C, which assists the concept of trust transitivity [21] and its propagation in social networks [22, 23]. In the literature <lb/>of psychology, people with feelings of preference give a big role to personal values before taking a decision. In contrast, <lb/>people with intuitional preferences may trust others without any previous interaction [19]. Hence, trust and willingness <lb/>are formulating a type of psychological state for the recipient, and they are proposed to have a significant effect on users&apos; <lb/>behaviour. Furthermore, Yadav &amp; Rai [24] pointed out that customer satisfaction resulted in a psychological attribute, <lb/>which entails a type of interpretation of its effect on the customer&apos;s decision process. In addition, it is important to <lb/>understand the psychological mechanisms that affected individuals&apos; behaviour in sharing fake contents about some <lb/>brands using social networks [25]. Additionally, Gvili &amp; Levy [26] showed customer engagement in sharing WOM <lb/>content because of trust. Balamoorthy &amp; Chandra [27] showed that people with high psychological impact have a robust <lb/>incentive to engage in customer engagement to participate in e-WOM statements. <lb/>Based on this information, we suggest the following hypothesis: <lb/>H2o: Customers&apos; positive psychological state has not a significant impact on forwarding marketing ads to others. <lb/>H2: Customers&apos; positive psychological state has a significant impact on forwarding marketing ads to others. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 1, March, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>146 <lb/></page>

			<body>Viral advertising is an individual effort where the ads usually come from a source to a receiver. That means the <lb/>companies do not give any kind of payment for ads Spreading [11]. Viral marketing takes several styles to propagate <lb/>the ads: videos, interactive games, eBooks, some photos and images, text, email messages, and webpages. The main <lb/>goal of marketers is to create exceptional viral marketing programs by sending viral messages to individuals who have <lb/>high social networking skills and who can display, propagate, and advertise the messages to their friends and relatives. <lb/>For this reason, the similarities and benefits between the beers also have a significant effect. For example, the strong <lb/>ties and common attributes between peers also build strong relationships in the network and offer a high level of social <lb/>support. Consequently, if the receiver thinks that there is a good benefit from the received ads, she may pass them on or <lb/>forward them to her friends. This is especially true if the ads have a good attraction, create a strong emotion, drive users&apos; <lb/>attention, or WOW the recipient [6]. <lb/>In social networks, there is a need to identify users&apos; communities based on their social connections and needs. In <lb/>addition, the spread of a new idea can be maximized if there is a possibility to identify a group of peers who share the <lb/>same opinions and are interested in the same topic, taking into consideration social support and strong ties and their <lb/>effects on peers&apos; behaviours and attitudes. Hence, Moscato &amp; Speril [28] conducted a survey that presents an overall <lb/>study of different community detection techniques proposed for social networks, considering the related complex <lb/>features. Based on this information, we suggest the following hypotheses: <lb/>H3o: Customers&apos; similarities have not had a significant positive impact on forwarding ads to others. <lb/>H3: Customers&apos; similarities have a significant positive impact on forwarding ads to others. <lb/>H4o: Customers&apos; benefits have not had a significant positive impact on forwarding ads to others. <lb/>H4: Customers&apos; benefits have a significant positive impact on forwarding ads to others. <lb/>Word-of-mouth and viral marketing are two related concepts that have a significant role in promoting products and <lb/>services for business enterprises. Many scholars in the marketing literature discussed the concept of word-of-mouth and <lb/>showed that it has an important role in generating viral marketing (for example, [1, 2, 5, 7, 13, 29, 30]). Many scholars <lb/>link between the effect of WOM and customers purchase intention [31-35]. Aljarah et al. (2022) [36] distinguished <lb/>between user-generated content and firm-generated content and showed that user engagement by generating online <lb/>content about brands has more effect than firm-generated content. Puriwat &amp; Tripopsakul [2] examined the effect of <lb/>viral marketing strategies on brand recognition and brand preference by suggesting a framework for the effectiveness of <lb/>viral marketing in social media contexts. Their results showed that effective viral marketing points positively to brand <lb/>recognition and preference. Domingos [7] suggested a social network model to design viral marketing plans that <lb/>maximize positive word-of-mouth among customers. His experiments achieved much higher profits than ignoring <lb/>interactions among customers and the equivalent network effects, as a traditional marketing technique does. Petrescu &amp; <lb/>Korgaonkar [29] clarify the concepts of WOM, eWOM, and viral marketing, aiming to reduce the ambiguities between <lb/>those concepts. WoM is more effective than traditional print advertising in affecting consumers&apos; buying processes [37]. <lb/>Alsuwaidan et al. [10] propose a novel spreading framework for viral marketing. Their work ensures optimization in <lb/>terms of cost and time by focusing only on the most energetic users on online social networks. Their framework divided <lb/>the overall community into clusters, each of which had its own interests. In addition, it ensures overlapping between <lb/>clusters when users have more than one interest. <lb/>Figure 1. The research model <lb/>Social support &amp; <lb/>strong ties <lb/>Psychological <lb/>state <lb/>Similarities <lb/>Benefits <lb/>Word-of-Mouth <lb/>Viral Marketing <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Vol. 5, No. 1, March, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>147 <lb/></page>

			<body>Kaplan &amp; Haenlein [38] defined viral marketing as electronic word-of-mouth where a message is spread in an <lb/>exponentially growing way via social media networks and considered three conditions to be fulfilled to attain the set <lb/>goals and objectives. These three conditions are the message, the right person, and the environment. They recommended <lb/>some caution that managers should consider when trying to launch their viral marketing campaigns. Figure 1 shows the <lb/>research framework. <lb/>3. Research Methodology <lb/>To achieve the objectives of the study and to test the proposed model, a questionnaire was prepared based on multiple <lb/>ideas from previous studies in the same field. The questionnaire consists of two main parts. The first part contains <lb/>questions related to the demographic factors of the participants in the study, while the second part contains questions <lb/>based on a Likert scale ranging from 1 being &quot;strongly disagree&quot; to 5 being &quot;strongly agree&quot; related to measuring the <lb/>constructs of the proposed model. <lb/>The questionnaire was prepared in English to be in line with exactly the ideas and terminology used in the field of <lb/>study. The opinion of three lecturers in the Department of Information Technology at Yarmouk University was taken <lb/>regarding the quality of the questions included, clarity, and ability to measure the studied phenomenon. Based on their <lb/>feedback, the required amendments were made to the questionnaire to improve its quality. After that, the questionnaire <lb/>was distributed to three students in the master&apos;s level and eleven students in the bachelor&apos;s stage, where they were <lb/>requested to answer the questionnaire and give their comments and observations about the questions used in the study. <lb/>All comments were considered, and the questionnaire was modified accordingly. After that, the questionnaire was <lb/>translated into Arabic so that it would be appropriate to answer it from different segments of participants who do not <lb/>know the English language well. Finally, the questionnaire was prepared using Microsoft Forms, and its link was <lb/>distributed to social networking sites, forums, and online groups to give different types of respondents a good <lb/>opportunity to answer it. Moreover, participation in this study is voluntary, without any financial incentives. <lb/>Consequently, the sample of the study consists of 135 employees who filled out the questionnaire. Table 1 shows the <lb/>respondents&apos; profiles. <lb/>Table 1. The respondents profile <lb/>Category <lb/>Type <lb/>Frequency <lb/>Percent <lb/>Total (N) <lb/>Gender <lb/>Male <lb/>85 <lb/>63 <lb/>135 <lb/>Female <lb/>50 <lb/>37 <lb/>Age <lb/>From 18-25 <lb/>53 <lb/>39.3 <lb/>From 25-36 <lb/>19 <lb/>14.1 <lb/>From 36-45 <lb/>40 <lb/>29.6 <lb/>&gt;=46 <lb/>23 <lb/>17 <lb/>Educational level <lb/>Bachelor <lb/>66 <lb/>48.9 <lb/>Master <lb/>37 <lb/>27.4 <lb/>PhD <lb/>22 <lb/>16.3 <lb/>Others <lb/>10 <lb/>7.4 <lb/>4. Data Analysis and Research Results <lb/>Data analysis for the collected data was done using IBM SPSS Statistics version 20.0. For the purposes of proceeding <lb/>to analyse the gathered data, it&apos;s required to test the requirements of linear regression, namely linearity, normality, <lb/>multicollinearity, and outliers. <lb/>4.1. Linearity <lb/>Figure 2 illustrates a scatter plot displaying a clear linear pattern, with points evenly and randomly distributed across <lb/>the chart. This observation supports the assumption of linearity being met [39]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 1, March, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>148 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 2. Scatter plot for factors of viral marketing vs. eWOM <lb/>4.2. Normality <lb/>Figure 3 demonstrates that the residual data are well distributed throughout the chart, exhibiting no significant <lb/>skewness. This indicates that the assumption of linearity is satisfied [39]. <lb/>Figure 3. Histogram: Factors of Viral Marketing vs. eWOM <lb/>4.3. Multicollinearity <lb/>In Table 2, the Variance Inflation Factor (VIF) values are observed to be within an acceptable range, all less than or <lb/>equal to 4, indicating the absence of serious multicollinearity [39]. Additionally, the tolerance values for all predictors <lb/>are greater than 0.10, indicating that it is feasible to identify the predictors contributing significantly to predicting the <lb/>dependent variable. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 1, March, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>149 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 2. Collinearity Statistics <lb/>Model <lb/>Unstandardized Coefficients <lb/>Standardized Coefficients <lb/>Collinearity Statistics <lb/>B <lb/>Std. Error <lb/>Beta <lb/>Tolerance <lb/>VIF <lb/>1 <lb/>(Constant) <lb/>-0.472 <lb/>0.435 <lb/>social_support <lb/>0.286 <lb/>0.104 <lb/>0.237 <lb/>0.638 <lb/>1.568 <lb/>psychological_state <lb/>0.436 <lb/>0.145 <lb/>0.329 <lb/>0.394 <lb/>2.540 <lb/>Similarities <lb/>0.078 <lb/>0.141 <lb/>0.052 <lb/>0.523 <lb/>1.913 <lb/>Benefits <lb/>0.163 <lb/>0.104 <lb/>0.132 <lb/>0.669 <lb/>1.494 <lb/>4.4. Outlier Analysis <lb/>In Table 3, the calculated value of Durbin-Watson is 2.150, indicating no violation of the independence assumption <lb/>for the residuals data. The proximity of the Durbin-Watson value to 2 suggests that the regression model adequacy is <lb/>achieved, as there is no evidence of outliers or influential points affecting the regression analysis [39]. <lb/>Table 3. Outlier Statistics <lb/>Model <lb/>R <lb/>R Square <lb/>Adjusted R Square <lb/>Std. Error of the <lb/>Estimate <lb/>Durbin-Watson <lb/>1 <lb/>0.625 a <lb/>0.390 <lb/>0.371 <lb/>0.79690 <lb/>2.150 <lb/>a. Predictors: (Constant), benefits, social_support, similarities, psychological_state <lb/>Dependent Variable: eWOM <lb/>5. Discussion <lb/>Multiple linear regression (MLR) is a statistical approach used to explain the causal relationship between two or more <lb/>independent explanatory variables and a dependent predictor variable [17]. In addition, it is a multivariate statistical <lb/>technique used to examine the relationship between an outcome variable and several predictors. Furthermore, MLR is <lb/>used to predict the relative contribution of social support, psychological state, similarities, and benefits to the outcome <lb/>variable eWOM. Hair et al. [39] state that MLR provides a means of objectively assessing the magnitude and direction <lb/>of each predictor&apos;s relationship to its outcome variable. The forced entry regression method is used, and the &apos;stepwise&apos; <lb/>regression is more appropriate in the exploratory phase of research or for the purposes of predicting the change in <lb/>dependent variable attributed by independents [40]. Therefore, the change in the R 2 and the F statistic is examined in <lb/>each step. <lb/>The unstandardized coefficient B (constant) represents the average value of the dependent variable when all the <lb/>independent variables are set to zero. In this study, as seen in Table 4, when social support, psychological state, <lb/>similarities, and benefits are all equal to zero, the average value of eWOM is -0.472. The unstandardized coefficient B <lb/>(social support) indicates the average change in electronic word-of-mouth (eWOM) associated with a one-unit increase <lb/>in social support while holding the other independent variables constant. Table 4 shows that each additional unit of <lb/>social support is associated with a 0.286 increase in eWOM. The significance level (Sig.) for social support is represented <lb/>by the p-value, which in this case is 0.007. Since this value is lower than the predetermined significance level of 0.05, <lb/>we can conclude that social support has a statistically significant association with eWOM. <lb/>Table 4. Regression coefficients <lb/>Model <lb/>Unstandardized Coefficients <lb/>Standardized Coefficients <lb/>t <lb/>Sig. <lb/>B <lb/>Std. Error <lb/>Beta <lb/>1 <lb/>(Constant) <lb/>-0.472 <lb/>0.435 <lb/>-1.084 <lb/>0.280 <lb/>social_support <lb/>0.286 <lb/>0.104 <lb/>0.237 <lb/>2.759 <lb/>0.007 <lb/>psychological_state <lb/>0.436 <lb/>0.145 <lb/>0.329 <lb/>3.011 <lb/>0.003 <lb/>similarities <lb/>0.078 <lb/>0.141 <lb/>0.052 <lb/>0.552 <lb/>0.582 <lb/>benefits <lb/>0.163 <lb/>0.104 <lb/>0.132 <lb/>1.574 <lb/>0.118 <lb/>Similarly, for psychological state, the calculated t-value is 2.759, and the associated significance level from the test <lb/>is 0.007, which is lower than the chosen significance level of 0.05. Thus, we reject the null hypothesis and accept that <lb/>B1 is significantly different from zero. Consequently, we approve hypothesis H1. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 1, March, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>150 <lb/></page>

			<body>This result highlights the significant role of social support and strong ties among customers (peers) in disseminating <lb/>marketing ads and promotions on social networks. As such, this study shows that customers will share a marketing ad <lb/>if their friends have positive feedback about it. In addition, if customers get encouragement from their peers to share an <lb/>ad, they will positively respond to such a recommendation. This result also recommends that people are the main part <lb/>of social networks and rely heavily on online communications and interactivity to get the required information and <lb/>experiences from their peers to formulate their purchasing decisions and generate positive WOM for others by <lb/>forwarding the marketing ads to their other peers. Hence, through engagement, sharing, and confirmation, customers <lb/>become loyal and brand advocates on social networks. This result is consistent with [15, 23, 40, 41]. Social support <lb/>usually comes in the form of positive comments: WOM from peers in social networks that encourage customers to <lb/>mimic the same decisions of their peers. <lb/>Puriwat &amp; Tripopsakul [2], who mentioned that viral marketing is a type of WOM communication among individuals, <lb/>assist in this result. Hence, WOM marketing is a way of communicating and transferring business promotions and <lb/>messages among customers from person to person. In addition, word-of-mouth marketing covers the efforts of <lb/>businesses to lead customers to create marketing-related content and communicate this information to other consumers <lb/>using new communication channels like smart phones, email, SMS messages, blogs, and business Web sites [1]. Akyol <lb/>[1] pointed out that WOM is four times more effective than personal sales and seven times more effective than <lb/>advertisements. He also presented the new form of WOM, which is done using the Internet as eWOM, and defined it as <lb/>&quot;All kinds of positive and negative feedback or comments that belong to customers referred to a product or a company <lb/>through the Internet. eWOM covers customer comments on Internet mediums like social networking sites. Even though <lb/>each social platform on the Internet has its own common features and capability to distribute information very fast to a <lb/>very wide range of individuals globally. The unstandardized coefficient B (psychological state) indicates the average <lb/>change in electronic word-of-mouth (eWOM) associated with a one-unit increase in psychological state while holding <lb/>the remaining independent variables constant. In this case, each additional unit of psychological state is associated with <lb/>a 0.436 increase in eWOM. The significance level (Sig.) for psychological state represents the p-value, which in this <lb/>instance is 0.003. Since this value is lower than the predetermined significance level of 0.05, we can conclude that <lb/>psychological state has a statistically significant association with eWOM. <lb/>Similarly, for psychological state, the calculated t-value is 3.011, and the associated significance level from the test <lb/>is 0.003, which is lower than the chosen significance level of 0.05. Thus, we reject the null hypothesis and accept that <lb/>B1 is significantly different from zero. Consequently, we approve hypothesis H2. This result assures that individuals are <lb/>living in a new, risky online environment where trust and willingness are playing a vital role in shaping positive customer <lb/>buying decisions as well as positive behaviour about the brand or the given service. Consequently, trust is an important <lb/>component in recommending and sharing marketing content with others. Hence, such factors are important components <lb/>for disseminating positive messages and contents virally on social networks. In addition, customers are able to participate <lb/>in the spreading of the marketing ads when they are happy, excited, or in a good and positive mood. This result is <lb/>consistent with the recommendations of [22, 42]. <lb/>The unstandardized coefficient B (similarities) indicates the average change in electronic word-of-mouth (eWOM) <lb/>associated with a one-unit increase in similarities while holding the remaining independent variables constant. In this <lb/>case, each additional unit of similarity is associated with a 0.078 increase in eWOM. The significance level (Sig.) for <lb/>similarities represents the p-value, which in this instance is 0.582. Since this value is not lower than the predetermined <lb/>significance level of 0.05, we cannot conclude that similarities have a statistically significant association with eWOM. <lb/>Additionally, the calculated t-value for similarities is 0.552, further supporting the lack of significance. Therefore, we <lb/>accept the null hypothesis, indicating that B3 is equal to zero, and as a result, we reject hypothesis H3. Similarly, for <lb/>benefits, the unstandardized coefficient B represents the average change in eWOM associated with a one-unit increase <lb/>in benefits while holding the remaining independent variables constant. In this case, each additional unit of benefits is <lb/>associated with a 0.163 increase in eWOM. The significance level (Sig.) for benefits is 0.118, which is not lower than <lb/>the predetermined significance level of 0.05. Consequently, we cannot conclude that benefits have a statistically <lb/>significant association with eWOM. This result indicates that the null hypothesis is accepted and B4 is equal to zero. <lb/>Therefore, we reject hypothesis H4. These results of this study show that customers&apos; similarities in opinions, genders, <lb/>and perceived benefits are not necessary to participate in sharing marketing ads on social networks. As such, the study <lb/>shows no significant effect on reposting a commercial ad if customers receive such promotions from a friend that has a <lb/>similar interest. <lb/>R squared shows the proportion of the variance in the dependent variable that can be explained by the independent <lb/>variables. Table 5 shows that 39% of the variation in eWOM can be explained by social support, psychological state, <lb/>similarities, and benefits. On the other side, Std. Error of the Estimate represents the average distance that the observed <lb/>values fall from the regression line. In this study, the observed values fall by an average of 0.79690 units from the <lb/>regression line. The coefficient of determination R 2 indicating the percent of how much of the total variance is explained <lb/>by the independent variables, is 39%. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 1, March, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>151 <lb/></page>

			<body>The regression equation based on Unstandardized Coefficients is as follows: <lb/>Estimated eWOM = -0.472+ 0.286 × (social_support) + 0.436 × (psychological_state)+0.078 × (similarities) + 0.163 × (benefits) <lb/>Table 5. Model&apos;s Summary <lb/>Model <lb/>R <lb/>R Square <lb/>Adjusted R Square <lb/>Std. Error of the Estimate <lb/>1 <lb/>0.625 a <lb/>0.390 <lb/>0.371 <lb/>0.79690 <lb/>a. Predictors: (Constant), benefits, social_support, similarities, psychological_state <lb/>Dependent Variable: eWOM <lb/>The F-statistic is calculated as the ratio of the regression mean square (MS) to the residual mean square. This statistic <lb/>serves as a measure of whether the regression model offers a superior fit to the data compared to a model containing no <lb/>independent variables. In essence, it evaluates the overall usefulness of the regression model. When the obtained p-value <lb/>(P) is less than the chosen significance level, there is substantial evidence to conclude that the regression model provides <lb/>a better fit to the data than the model with no predictor variables [39]. This result is favourable because it indicates that <lb/>the predictor variables in the model significantly enhance the model&apos;s fit. Moreover, it is worth noting that if none of the <lb/>predictor variables in the model are statistically significant, the overall F statistic is also not statistically significant. In <lb/>Table 6, the overall F statistic for the regression model is calculated as the ratio of the Mean Square Regression (13.203) <lb/>to the Mean Square Residual (0.635), resulting in a value of 20.791. This indicates that a significant portion of the total <lb/>variance in the data is attributed to the regression equation. The calculated F value of 20.791 represents the variance <lb/>generated by the regression, and this finding is promising as it suggests that the predictor variables in the model indeed <lb/>contribute to improving the model&apos;s fit [39]. It&apos;s important to note that when none of the predictor variables in the model <lb/>are statistically significant, the overall F statistic also becomes statistically insignificant. However, in this case, the <lb/>obtained F value signifies a substantial impact of the predictor variables on the model&apos;s performance, further validating <lb/>the model&apos;s appropriateness. <lb/>Table 6. Variation analysis <lb/>Model <lb/>Sum of Squares <lb/>df <lb/>Mean Square <lb/>F <lb/>Sig. <lb/>1 <lb/>Regression <lb/>52.813 <lb/>4 <lb/>13.203 <lb/>20.791 <lb/>0.000 b <lb/>Residual <lb/>2.556 <lb/>130 <lb/>0.635 <lb/>Total <lb/>135.370 <lb/>134 <lb/>Dependent Variable: eWOM <lb/>b. Predictors: (Constant), benefits, social_support, similarities, psychological_state <lb/>Table 7 presents the Sig values, which represent the p-values associated with the overall F statistic. These values <lb/>determine whether the regression model, as a whole, is statistically significant. In essence, these p-values indicate <lb/>whether the four independent variables in this study have a statistically significant association with the dependent <lb/>variable (eWOM). The study&apos;s results, as shown in Table 6, reveal that the p-value is calculated to be 0.000, indicating <lb/>a statistically significant association between the independent variables (social support, psychological state, similarities, <lb/>and benefits) and eWOM (the dependent variable). However, the analysis in Table 6 also reveals that two variables, <lb/>namely, similarities and benefits, do not act as significant predictors for eWOM. Therefore, these variables are excluded <lb/>from the regression model. Consequently, Table 7 displays the new regression model for this study, reflecting the <lb/>removal of these non-significant predictors. <lb/>Table 7. Modified Regression Coefficient <lb/>Model <lb/>Unstandardized Coefficients <lb/>Standardized Coefficients <lb/>t <lb/>Sig. <lb/>B <lb/>Std. Error <lb/>Beta <lb/>1 <lb/>(Constant) <lb/>-0.110 <lb/>0.368 <lb/>-0.298 <lb/>0.766 <lb/>social_support <lb/>0.308 <lb/>0.104 <lb/>0.254 <lb/>2.970 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>psychological_state <lb/>0.566 <lb/>0.114 <lb/>0.426 <lb/>4.983 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>As a result, the updated coefficient of determination (R2) in Table 8 is recorded as 37.5. Moreover, the analysis in <lb/>Table 9 reaffirms that the two significant predictors, namely, social support and psychological state, significantly <lb/>influence the dependent variable eWOM. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 1, March, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>152 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 8. Modified Model&apos;s summary <lb/>Model <lb/>R <lb/>R Square <lb/>Adjusted R Square <lb/>Std. Error of the Estimate <lb/>1 <lb/>0.613 a <lb/>0.375 <lb/>0.366 <lb/>0.80037 <lb/>a. Predictors: (Constant), psychological_state, social_support <lb/>Dependent Variable: eWOM <lb/>Table 9. Modified variation analysis <lb/>Model <lb/>Sum of Squares <lb/>df <lb/>Mean Square <lb/>F <lb/>Sig. <lb/>1 <lb/>Regression <lb/>50.812 <lb/>2 <lb/>25.406 <lb/>39.661 <lb/>0.000 b <lb/>Residual <lb/>84.557 <lb/>132 <lb/>0.641 <lb/>Total <lb/>135.370 <lb/>134 <lb/>6. Conclusions <lb/>Viral marketing has emerged as one of the most effective techniques for the widespread dissemination of marketing <lb/>ads to a global audience. The rise of e-commerce and social media platforms has provided businesses with abundant <lb/>opportunities to thrive and succeed. Among these opportunities, social platforms stand out as valuable channels that <lb/>enable companies to advertise their products and services at a low cost while reaching millions of individuals worldwide. <lb/>Viral marketing, as an internet-based tool, effectively engages third parties in the advertising process. Every business <lb/>recognizes the significance of marketing, and the primary objective of viral marketing is to expand market reach and <lb/>grow the customer base at the lowest possible cost. This objective can be achieved by generating powerful word-of-<lb/>mouth (WOM) recommendations. The success of viral marketing campaigns hinges on achieving widespread <lb/>dissemination with minimal or no cost to the marketer. Ultimately, the primary goals of viral marketing encompass <lb/>economic objectives such as fostering customer loyalty and advocacy, which are vital for realizing the company&apos;s <lb/>strategic goals. <lb/>This study emphasizes the essential role of tie strength, social support, and customers&apos; positive psychological state as <lb/>critical factors for successful viral marketing campaigns. By comprehending and harnessing these factors, businesses <lb/>can optimize the impact and reach of their viral marketing efforts, ultimately achieving strategic goals and gaining a <lb/>competitive advantage in the marketplace. However, it is important to acknowledge the limitations of this study. Firstly, <lb/>the sample size is relatively small, which may limit the generalizability of the findings. To enhance the robustness of <lb/>future research, larger sample sizes should be considered. Additionally, the proposed model could benefit from the <lb/>inclusion of additional factors that are relevant to this study, leading to a more precise and accurate result. To overcome <lb/>these limitations, future research may be conducted in diverse environments and cultures, allowing for the collection of <lb/>more extensive data records. Expanding the study to encompass more relevant factors could provide new insights and <lb/>yield novel findings. By addressing these shortcomings and conducting further research, we can deepen our <lb/>understanding of viral marketing and its impact on business outcomes. This will enable companies to refine their <lb/>strategies and capitalize on the full potential of viral marketing to achieve their goals. <lb/>6.1. Research Implications <lb/>The significance of this study lies in the proposal of a viral marketing model for business enterprises. The model <lb/>outlines a set of factors that can be utilized to generate positive electronic content about a specific product or service. <lb/>This content can then be disseminated across various networks, groups, and online platforms, effectively reaching a large <lb/>number of users and resulting in what is commonly known as viral marketing. To validate the effectiveness of the <lb/>proposed model, a practical test was conducted involving 135 users from diverse backgrounds, including different <lb/>genders, ages, and academic levels. The study&apos;s findings underscored the importance of strong social connections and <lb/>support among users in generating positive word-of-mouth and facilitating its viral spread to millions of people. In <lb/>addition, the importance of this research lies in its potential application by commercial companies for conducting <lb/>promotional and marketing campaigns. By leveraging the proposed model, businesses can effectively promote their <lb/>products and services, thus achieving their strategic objectives and gaining a competitive advantage in an environment <lb/>characterized by intense competition and constant change. Furthermore, from a theoretical perspective, this study <lb/>contributes new insights and findings to the existing body of knowledge. These findings can serve as a foundation for <lb/>further research and exploration, enabling researchers to build upon them and achieve even greater advancements in this <lb/>field. <lb/></body>

            <div type="annex">7. Declarations <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">7.1. Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization, R.A. and A.A.; methodology, R.A.; software, A.A.; validation, R.A. and A.A.; formal analysis, <lb/>A.A.; investigation, A.A.; resources, R.A.; data curation, R.A.; writing-original draft preparation, R.A.; writing-<lb/>review and editing, A.A.; visualization, A.A.; supervision, R.A.; project administration, R.A. and A.A.; funding <lb/>acquisition, R.A. and A.A. All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 1, March, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>153 <lb/></page>

            <div type="availability">7.2. Data Availability Statement <lb/>The data presented in this study are available in the article. <lb/></div>

            <div type="funding">7.3. Funding <lb/>The authors received financial support for the research and/or publication of this article from the Deanships of <lb/>Scientific Research and Graduate Studies in Yarmouk University and Philadelphia University, Jordan. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">7.4. Institutional Review Board Statement <lb/>Not applicable. <lb/>7.5. Informed Consent Statement <lb/>Not applicable. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">7.6. Declaration of Competing Interest <lb/>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have <lb/>appeared to influence the work reported in this paper. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>8. References <lb/>[1] Akyol, Ş. (2013). Social Media and Marketing: Viral Marketing. Academic Journal of Interdisciplinary Studies, 2(8), 586-590. <lb/>doi:10.5901/ajis.2013.v2n8p586. <lb/>[2] Puriwat, W., &amp; Tripopsakul, S. (2021). The role of viral marketing in social media on brand recognition and preference. Emerging <lb/>Science Journal, 5(6), 855-867. doi:10.28991/esj-2021-01315. <lb/>[3] Al-Dwairi, R. M. D., &amp; Al-Khataybeh, M. (2023). Web 2.0 Tools and Service Quality: The Key to Effective Customer <lb/>Relationships in E-Commerce Environments. 2023 International Conference on Information Technology: Cybersecurity <lb/>Challenges for Sustainable Cities, ICIT 2023 -Proceeding, 827-831. doi:10.1109/ICIT58056.2023.10226159. <lb/>[4] Tu, S., &amp; Neumann, S. (2022). A Viral Marketing-Based Model for Opinion Dynamics in Online Social Networks. WWW 2022 <lb/>-Proceedings of the ACM Web Conference 2022, 1570-1578. doi:10.1145/3485447.3512203. <lb/>[5] Dwivedi, Y. K., Ismagilova, E., Hughes, D. L., Carlson, J., Filieri, R., Jacobson, J., Jain, V., Karjaluoto, H., Kefi, H., Krishen, A. <lb/>S., Kumar, V., Rahman, M. M., Raman, R., Rauschnabel, P. A., Rowley, J., Salo, J., Tran, G. A., &amp; Wang, Y. (2021). Setting the <lb/>future of digital and social media marketing research: Perspectives and research propositions. International Journal of Information <lb/>Management, 59, 102168. doi:10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2020.102168. <lb/>[6] Huynh, K. (2016). Factors Affecting the Success of Viral Marketing an Affective -Cognitive-Behavioral Process. Business and <lb/>Management Research, 5(1), 40-45. doi:10.5430/bmr.v5n1p40. <lb/>[7] Domingos, P. (2005). Mining social networks for viral marketing. IEEE Intelligent Systems, 20(1), 80-82. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.jretconser.2007.02.005. <lb/>[8] Liao, M., Qi, L., &amp; Zhang, J. (2020). The dynamic evolution mechanism of heterogeneous OWOM-an improved viral marketing <lb/>model. Information (Switzerland), 11(3), 140. doi:10.3390/info11030140. <lb/>[9] Shuai, H. H., Shen, C. Y., Hsu, H. C., Yang, D. N., Chou, C. K., Lin, J. H., &amp; Chen, M. S. (2015). Revenue maximization for <lb/>Telecommunications Company with social viral marketing. Proceedings -IEEE International Conference on Big Data, IEEE Big <lb/>Data 2015, 1306-1310. doi:10.1109/BigData.2015.7363886. <lb/>[10] Alsuwaidan, L., Ykhlef, M., &amp; Alnuem, M. A. (2014). A novel spreading framework using incremental clustering for viral <lb/>marketing. In Proceedings of IEEE/ACS International Conference on Computer Systems and Applications, AICCSA, 78-83. <lb/>doi:10.1109/AICCSA.2014.7073182. <lb/>[11] Mora, E., Vila-Lopez, N., &amp; Küster-Boluda, I. (2021). Segmenting the audience of a cause-related marketing viral campaign. <lb/>International Journal of Information Management, 59(1), 102296. doi:10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2020.102296. <lb/>[12] Hmoud, H., Nofal, M., Yaseen, H., Al-Masaeed, S., &amp; Alfawwaz, B. M. (2022). The effects of social media attributes on <lb/>customer purchase intention: The mediation role of brand attitude. International Journal of Data and Network Science, 6(4), <lb/>1543-1556. doi:10.5267/j.ijdns.2022.4.022. <lb/>[13] Ebrahimi, P., Basirat, M., Yousefi, A., Nekmahmud, M., Gholampour, A., &amp; Fekete-farkas, M. (2022). Social Networks <lb/>Marketing and Consumer Purchase Behavior: The Combination of SEM and Unsupervised Machine Learning Approaches. Big <lb/>Data and Cognitive Computing, 6(2), 35. doi:10.3390/bdcc6020035. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 1, March, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>154 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[14] Al-Dwairi, R. (2017). Social commerce adoption among Jordanian youth: Empirical study. International Journal of Business <lb/>Information Systems, 26(3), 277-296. doi:10.1504/IJBIS.2017.10007573. <lb/>[15] Zahid, M. M., Ali, B., Samdani, H., &amp; Kamal, N. (2021). Linking Social Media Engagement with Customer Relationships and <lb/>Brand Loyalty : A Consumer-based Perspective. VFAST Transactions on Education and Social Sciences, 9(3), 90-99. <lb/>[16] Duffett, R. G. (2017). Influence of social media marketing communications on young consumers&apos; attitudes. Young Consumers, <lb/>18(1), 19-39. doi:10.1108/YC-07-2016-00622. <lb/>[17] Alawneh, A. A., Ai-Taani, F., Ai-Azzam, A., &amp; Al-Radaideh, R. (2013). A proposed measurement scale for e-banking services <lb/>quality in Jordan. International Conference on Computer Applications Technology, ICCAT 2013, Sousse, Tunisia. <lb/>doi:10.1109/ICCAT.2013.6521961. <lb/>[18] Liang, T. P., Ho, Y. T., Li, Y. W., &amp; Turban, E. (2011). What drives social commerce: The role of social support and relationship <lb/>quality? International Journal of Electronic Commerce, 16(2), 69-90. doi:10.2753/JEC1086-4415160204. <lb/>[19] Tobon, S., &amp; García-Madariaga, J. (2021). The influence of opinion leaders&apos; eWOM on online consumer decisions: A study on <lb/>social influence. Journal of Theoretical and Applied Electronic Commerce Research, 16(4), 748-767. doi:10.3390/jtaer16040043. <lb/>[20] Wang, P., &amp; Huang, Q. (2023). Digital influencers, social power and consumer engagement in social commerce. Internet <lb/>Research, 33(1), 178-207. doi:10.1108/INTR-08-2020-0467. <lb/>[21] Heilman, R. M., &amp; Kusev, P. (2020). Personal Values Associated with Prosocial Decisions. Behavioral Sciences, 10(4), 77. <lb/>doi:10.3390/bs10040077. <lb/>[22] Nasir, S. U., &amp; Kim, T. H. (2020). Trust Computation in Online Social Networks Using Co-Citation and Transpose Trust <lb/>Propagation. IEEE Access, 8, 41362-41371. doi:10.1109/ACCESS.2020.2975782. <lb/>[23] Al-Dwairi, R. M., &amp; Kamala, M. A. (2009). An integrated trust model for business-to-consumer (B2C) e-commerce: Integrating <lb/>trust with the Technology Acceptance Model. 2009 International Conference on Cyber Worlds, 351-356. doi:10.1109/CW.2009.34. <lb/>[24] Yadav, M. K., &amp; Rai, D. A. K. (2015). Exploring the Relational Impact of Service Quality on Customer Satisfication. Ushus -<lb/>Journal of Business Management, 14(4), 17-31. doi:10.12725/ujbm.33.2. <lb/>[25] Obadă, D. R., &amp; Dabija, D. C. (2022). &quot;In Flow&quot;! Why Do Users Share Fake News about Environmentally Friendly Brands on <lb/>Social Media? International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 19(8), 4861. doi:10.3390/ijerph19084861. <lb/>[26] Gvili, Y., &amp; Levy, S. (2023). I Share, Therefore I Trust: A moderated mediation model of the influence of eWOM engagement <lb/>on social commerce. Journal of Business Research, 166. doi:10.1016/j.jbusres.2023.114131. <lb/>[27] Balamoorthy, S., &amp; Chandra, B. (2023). The influence of intrinsic and extrinsic motivational factors on e-WOM behaviour: The <lb/>role of psychological impact during the time of COVID-19 crisis. Heliyon, 9(2), e13270. doi:10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e13270. <lb/>[28] Moscato, V., &amp; Sperlì, G. (2021). A survey about community detection over On-line Social and Heterogeneous Information <lb/>Networks. Knowledge-Based Systems, 224, 107112. doi:10.1016/j.knosys.2021.107112. <lb/>[29] Petrescu, M., &amp; Korgaonkar, P. (2011). Viral advertising: Definitional review and synthesis. Journal of Internet Commerce, <lb/>10(3), 208-226. doi:10.1080/15332861.2011.596007. <lb/>[30] Hendrayati, H., &amp; Pamungkas, P. (2020). Viral Marketing and E-Word of Mouth Communication in Social Media Marketing. <lb/>3rd Global Conference on Business, Management, and Entrepreneurship, 41-48. doi:10.2991/aebmr.k.200131.010. <lb/>[31] Al Qaimari, R., Al Hassan, M., Al Dmour, H., &amp; Aloqaily, A. (2021). The effect of the electronic word of mouth on purchase <lb/>intention via the brand image as a mediating factor: an empirical study. International Journal of Networking and Virtual <lb/>Organisations, 24(2), 182. doi:10.1504/ijnvo.2021.10037256. <lb/>[32] Alfandi, A. M., &amp; Marco, V. (2021). Electronic Word of Mouth Effects on Middle East Destination Overall Image and <lb/>Behavioral Intention. In New Governance and Management in Touristic Destinations, IGI Global, 134-151. doi:10.4018/978-<lb/>1-6684-3889-3.ch009. <lb/>[33] Khan, S. (2023). Evaluating the Impact of eWOM Adoption on Consumer Purchasing Intentions. International Journal of Social <lb/>Sciences and Entrepreneurship (IJSSE), 3(1), 2790-7724. <lb/>[34] Indrawati, Putri Yones, P. C., &amp; Muthaiyah, S. (2023). eWOM via the TikTok application and its influence on the purchase <lb/>intention of somethinc products. Asia Pacific Management Review, 28(2), 174-184. doi:10.1016/j.apmrv.2022.07.007. <lb/>[35] Mainardes, E. W., Portelada, P. H. M., &amp; Damasceno, F. S. (2023). The Influence on Cosmetics Purchase Intention of Electronic <lb/>Word of Mouth on Instagram. Journal of Promotion Management, 29(7), 961-991. doi:10.1080/10496491.2023.2167897. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 1, March, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>155 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[36] Aljarah, A., Sawaftah, D., Ibrahim, B., &amp; Lahuerta-Otero, E. (2022). The differential impact of user-and firm-generated content <lb/>on online brand advocacy: customer engagement and brand familiarity matter. European Journal of Innovation Management. <lb/>doi:10.1108/EJIM-05-2022-0259. <lb/>[37] Tănase, G. C. (2016). The 6C Model of Social Media and Developing a Viral Marketing Campaign. Romanian Distribution <lb/>Committee Magazine, Romanian Distribution Committee, 7(3), 20-25. <lb/>[38] Kaplan, A. M., &amp; Haenlein, M. (2011). Two hearts in three-quarter time: How to waltz the social media/viral marketing dance. <lb/>Business horizons, 54(3), 253-263. doi:10.1016/j.bushor.2011.01.006. <lb/>[39] Hair, J. F., Anderson, R. E., Tatham, R. L., &amp; Black, W. C. (2006). Multivariate data analysis with readings. Pearson Prentice <lb/>Hall, New York, Untied States. <lb/>[40] Alawneh, A., &amp; Hattab, E. (2010). E-business Value Creation Jordanian Banking Services Industry: An Empirical Analysis of <lb/>Key Factors. International Arab Conference on e-technology. Arab Open University, October 15-10, 2010, Amman-Jordan. <lb/>[41] Al-Dwairi, R., Harb, Y., &amp; Shehabat, I. (2020). The role of social platforms in establishing brand awareness for B2C e-<lb/>commerce: Empirical study. International Journal of Business Information Systems, 33(4), 488-504. <lb/>doi:10.1504/IJBIS.2020.10027510. <lb/>[42] Cai Shi, M., &amp; Lucietto, A. M. (2022). The Preference of the Use of Intuition over Other Methods of Problem Solving by <lb/>Undergraduate Students. The European Educational Researcher, 5(3), 253-275. doi:10.31757/euer.532. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">HighTech and Innovation Journal <lb/>Vol. 5, No. 1, March, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>156 <lb/></page>

			<body>Appendix I: Questionnaire <lb/>Part 1: Demographic data <lb/>Gender <lb/> Male <lb/> Female <lb/>Age <lb/> From 18-22 <lb/> From 23-30 <lb/> From 31-45 <lb/> &gt; 45 <lb/>Online Shopping Experience using social media <lb/>None <lb/> 1-3 years <lb/> above three years <lb/>Educational Level <lb/> Bachelor degree <lb/> Master degree <lb/> PhD <lb/> Others <lb/>Part 2: Using social media to create a new model for viral marketing for e-commerce enterprises <lb/>Please select the appropriate choice of evaluation by ticking the number beside the statement you read. To help, <lb/>numbers mean: <lb/>1= Strongly disagree <lb/>2= Disagree <lb/>3= Neutral <lb/>4= Agree <lb/>5= Strongly agree <lb/>Social support <lb/># <lb/>Statement <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 <lb/>I will share or like an ad if my friends or relatives have a positive feedback about it. <lb/>2 <lb/>I will share or like an ad if my friends encourage me to do so. <lb/>3 <lb/>I think the positive or negative comments from my friend or relatives will affect my decision to like or resend an <lb/>ad in the social platform <lb/>Psychological state <lb/># <lb/>Statement <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 <lb/>I am more likely to share an ad when I am in a positive mood <lb/>2 <lb/>I am more likely to share an ad when I am happy or exited <lb/>3 <lb/>I will not share an ad when I am in a bad psychological state <lb/>Similarities <lb/># <lb/>Statement <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 <lb/>I will share an ad if it comes to me from a group of my favourite friends <lb/>2 <lb/>I will participate in re-sending an ad if it comes to me from a group of my relatives with whom I have a strong tie. <lb/>3 <lb/>I will participate in reposting a commercial ad to my friends if they have similar interests to me <lb/>Benefits <lb/># <lb/>Statement <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 <lb/>I will share or like an ad with my friends who can benefit from it is worthwhile <lb/>2 <lb/>I will forward an advertising e-mail to my friends if I think they will get some incentives from it. <lb/>3 <lb/>I will like an ad if it is useful to my friends <lb/>Word-of-Mouth <lb/># <lb/>Statement <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 <lb/>I will probably forward some of advertising emails to my friends <lb/>2 <lb/>I&apos;m likely to be positive about some ads on social media <lb/>3 <lb/>I will share some ads on social media </body>


	</text>
</tei>
