<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Diagnostic Role of Serum Adenosine Deaminase In Smear-negative Pulmonary Tuberculosis</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Nishat</forename>
          <surname>Ali</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Isha Abdullah</forename>
          <surname>Ali</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Khan Abul Kalam</forename>
          <surname>Azad</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-04T15:31:39.959Z">11/4/2025 3:31:39 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Bangladesh Academy of Sciences</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.3329/bjm.v35i2.70630</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Nishat Ali, Isha Abdullah Ali, Khan Abul Kalam Azad. (2024). Diagnostic Role of Serum Adenosine Deaminase In Smear-negative Pulmonary Tuberculosis. Bangladesh Journal of Medicine, 35(2), 61-69. DOI: 10.3329/bjm.v35i2.70630</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-04T15:31:26.753107Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-04T15:31:26.753107Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>S 53 <lb/>Assessment of knowledge and attitude about bio banking amongst <lb/>the general public and their willingness to donate bio specimens <lb/>from a hospital in India <lb/>Arathi K 1 , Vina Vaswani 2 , Vijaya Hegde 3 , Arvind Karikal 4 . <lb/>ORIGINAL RESEARCH <lb/>1. Reader, Department of Oral and Maxillofacial <lb/>Pathology, A.J. Institute of Dental Sciences. <lb/>2. Director, Centre for Ethics, Professor, Department <lb/>of Forensic Medicine &amp; Toxicology, Yenepoya <lb/>(Deemed to be University) <lb/>3. Professor &amp; Head Department of Public Health <lb/>Dentistry, A.J. Institute of Dental Sciences. <lb/>4. Professor, Department of Oral &amp; Maxillofacial <lb/>Surgery, AB Shetty Memorial institute of Dental <lb/>Sciences NITTE (Deemed to be University). <lb/></front>

        <body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Patients submit blood, tissue, biological <lb/>material to hospitals or institutes during surgical <lb/>procedures or as a part of the diagnostic work <lb/>up. Only a small part of the collected sample is <lb/>usually processed for the diagnostic purpose, <lb/>the remaining portion of such biological <lb/>material can be either disposed or be retained <lb/>for academic or research studies. Commercial <lb/>entities which store such biological materials <lb/>for a fee are known as biobanks. These biobanks <lb/>collect and store different types of biological <lb/>material, ranging from specimens for therapy <lb/>such as biopsies to those left over from surgery 1 . <lb/>All over the world a huge quantity of <lb/>biological material has been retained under <lb/></body>

        <front>Bangladesh Journal of Medical Science Vol. 23 Special Issue 2024 <lb/>Correspondence: <lb/>Arvind Karikal Professor, Department of Oral &amp; <lb/>Maxillofacial Surgery, AB Shetty Memorial institute <lb/>of Dental Sciences NITTE (Deemed to be University). <lb/>Mangalore, India. <lb/>Email: draravindkarikal@nitte.edu.in, <lb/>Orcid ID: 0000-0002-3444-9063 <lb/>Cell Phone: +919008964130 <lb/>This study aims to know the attitude and perceptions of biobanks <lb/>among the general public and their willingness to donate bio <lb/>specimens from a hospital in India. Biobanks collect, store <lb/>bio specimens for diagnosis, treatment and research purpose. <lb/>According to modern bio banking, bio specimens needs to have <lb/>standard operating procedures to do so. The bio specimen should <lb/>be kept confidential and anonymous. Do they have an awareness <lb/>of the role of biobanks? Do they know the concept of consent <lb/>and implications of retaining specimens in biobanks? This paper <lb/>evaluates these areas. A cross sectional study was conducted <lb/>among general public above 18 years of age using convenience <lb/>sampling. The data was obtained through a questionnaire which <lb/>was distributed via online using Google forms and assessed <lb/>the ethical perception of the general public regarding their <lb/>willingness to donate own biological samples for teaching and <lb/>research purposes and their awareness and attitude on biobanks. <lb/>A total of 200 participants were included in the study. 71.4% <lb/>participants did not have any prior knowledge about biobanks. <lb/>59.6% of the participants were willing to donate the biospecimens <lb/>for advancement in medical research, benefit the society and <lb/>future generation. 43.8% of respondents emphasised the main <lb/>discouraging factor in participation in biobank research is that <lb/>they have fear of sample exploitation. 37.9 percent participants <lb/>responded that they would like to specify the scope for use when <lb/>granting permission to use their sample for research. Biobank <lb/>will advance in medical research only when medical institutes <lb/>and government bodies&apos; install privacy, consent laws and initiate <lb/>lot of awareness programmes to improve public perspectives <lb/>and knowledge about biobanking. <lb/>Keywords <lb/>Biobanking, Consent, Biospecimens, Ethics, Perception. <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.3329/bjms.v23i10.71737 <lb/></front>

        <note place="headnote">Bangladesh Journal of Medical Science <lb/>Volume 23 Special Issue 2024 <lb/>©The Ibn Sina Trust <lb/></note>

        <page>S 54 <lb/></page>

        <body>various circumstances, such as in archives, museums, <lb/>archaeological digs, this material mostly was acquired <lb/>under known and unknown circumstances. Such <lb/>anonymised archival material could be used for teaching, <lb/>research, remain in storage or be disposed in a safe <lb/>manner 2 . Biological samples for research purpose have <lb/>a long history being used in healthcare and education <lb/>The twenty first century has brought new challenges, <lb/>with new methods of preservation of biological samples <lb/>and an increase in the number, size, and importance of <lb/>biobanks has drawn attention to the changing nature of <lb/>biomedical research. The relationship of the investigator, <lb/>participant and funding organizations funding biobanks <lb/>have changed 3 . Biobanking for medical research <lb/>depends on the availability of biological material along <lb/>with associated clinical data, genetic information and <lb/>lifestyle information. Thus its success depends heavily <lb/>on trust and good will between the participants the <lb/>researchers and academicians as they not only provide <lb/>the biological material but also personal details about <lb/>their health and living habits 4 . <lb/>Pamela Tozzo et al, in 2017 3 noted a huge increase <lb/>in scientific literature concerning novel applications <lb/>both in public and private research bodies and thus <lb/>emphasized the importance of biobanks. Internationally <lb/>the awareness of biobanks has increased due to the <lb/>growing trend of research towards personalized <lb/>medicine, especially in the field of oncology. Still a <lb/>vast majority of people around the world are new to <lb/>biobanks and are hesitant to be involved in biobanks <lb/>related research as participants or as donors in cohort <lb/>studies 3 . In India public knowledge and awareness is <lb/>still nascent, hence we would like to asses a sample of <lb/>Indian adults on their knowledge, perception towards <lb/>participation in a biobanks and willingness to donate <lb/>their own biological samples for research. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>A cross sectional study was conducted amongst the <lb/>general public. The data was collected using convenience <lb/>sampling. The study protocol obtained clearance from <lb/>the Institutional Ethics Committee. The Questionnaire <lb/>was developed in English, and was pilot tested to <lb/>ensure that the questions and the language that was <lb/>used were clear and comprehensible to the participants. <lb/>The questionnaire was validated by subject experts in <lb/>Bioethics. The questionnaire was modified based on the <lb/>pilot testing and expert feedback. It was then distributed <lb/>online using Google forms. The questionnaire was <lb/>collected from participants an informed consent was <lb/>provided to the participants before the questionnaire. <lb/>No identifying personal information was obtained from <lb/>the participants. <lb/>The questionnaire consisted of three parts <lb/>1. <lb/>Demographic <lb/>and <lb/>socioeconomic <lb/>characteristics <lb/>2. <lb/>Participants&apos; perspectives toward participation <lb/>in biobanks and storage of their samples. <lb/>3. <lb/>Participants perspectives on consent in <lb/>biobanking. <lb/>Inclusion Criteria: <lb/>1. <lb/>Participants above the age group of 18 years <lb/>as they are competent to understand the concept of <lb/>biobanking and give consent independently. <lb/>2. <lb/>Participants who were fluent in English <lb/>language and are digitally literate with access to the <lb/>internet. <lb/>Statistical analysis and methods <lb/>The obtained data was analysed using SPSS version 17, <lb/>descriptive analysis was done. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>350 Google forms were circulated, out of which 203 <lb/>participants responded. The data showed that 43.3 % <lb/>participants were from the age group 18-28 years, 24.1 <lb/>% were between the age group of 29-38 and 32.5% <lb/>were between 38 years and above. The data showed <lb/>that 63.1 % of the participants were females and 36.5% <lb/>were male. Among the total participants, 53.2% of the <lb/>participants were graduates, 38.4 % were postgraduates <lb/>and 8.4% of the participants had completed their Pre-<lb/>university collage. The questionnaire assessed the <lb/>participants&apos; perspectives toward biobanks and storage <lb/>of their samples [Chart 1]. 85.2 % of the participants <lb/>knew that biobank is a bank used for storing biological <lb/>samples and related data. 11.8% of the participants were <lb/>not aware about biobank. 42.4% of the participants <lb/>knew that there are separate biobanks for research <lb/>and legal purposes. Whereas 33% of the participants <lb/>responded that the biobank is only for research and <lb/>23.2% responded that there is only one biobank for <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Bangladesh Journal of Medical Science <lb/>Volume 23 Special Issue 2024 <lb/>©The Ibn Sina Trust <lb/></note>

        <page>S 55 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Available at: http://www.banglajol.info/index.php/BJMS <lb/></note>

        <body>research and legal purposes. 57.1% of the participants <lb/>do not know that there are any biobanks in India, <lb/>whereas 40.9% knew that there are research biobanks in <lb/>India. 47.3 % of the participants agreed that the purpose <lb/>of a biobank is to collect and store biospecimens for <lb/>diagnosis, treatment and research purposes. 37.4 % of <lb/>the participants strongly agreed to it. Whereas 14.3 % <lb/>of them reported that they don&apos;t have any idea about <lb/>biobanking concept. 45.3 % of the participants strongly <lb/>agreed that modern biobanking biospecimens needs to <lb/>have standard operating procedures to collect process, <lb/>store and release biospecimens and 23.2 % of the <lb/>participants had no idea about biobanking protocols. <lb/>Regarding confidentiality and anonymity of data 78.8% <lb/>responded that their data should be kept confidential <lb/>whereas 15.8% were not aware of confidentiality and <lb/>anonymity of personal data. 79.8% of the participants <lb/>did not have any experience in participating in research <lb/>and 17.2% agreed that they did have experience in <lb/>dealing with biobanking. The participants were asked <lb/>if they had prior knowledge about biobanks, 71.4% <lb/>participants did not have any, whereas 24.6% responded <lb/>that they did have prior knowledge about biobanks. <lb/>Perception on biobanking participation and barriers <lb/>The domain focussing on the discouraging factors in <lb/>participating in biobanking, 43.8% of them said that <lb/>they have fear of sample exploitation, 37.9% responded <lb/>that the research procedure was unclear. 24.1% of <lb/>them had fear of negative impact of research on their <lb/>privacy and confidentiality. Whereas 19.7% and 19.2% <lb/>responded that they do not have time to participate in <lb/>research and they do not feel comfortable conducting <lb/>experiments on their biospecimens. 70.4%, Among <lb/>the study participants 59.6% of the participants were <lb/>willing to donate the biospecimens for advancement in <lb/>medical research and to benefit the society and future <lb/>generation. Around 21.7% of the participants responded <lb/>that Biobanks are already established as the core facility <lb/>of biomedical research in developed countries. <lb/>Perspective on consent in biobanking <lb/>The domain focussing on participants&apos; perspectives <lb/>on consent on biobanking, 64.5 % of them strongly <lb/>agreed to sign the consent form, whereas 12.8% of the <lb/>participants had no idea about consent form. <lb/>The participants were asked &quot;in collection of biological <lb/>samples for biobanking, what type of informed consent <lb/>would you be willing to give? 45.8% responded that <lb/>consent must be sought for each new study. 43.3% <lb/>reported that consent must be sought if the new study <lb/>uses their data with their social security number and <lb/>33% responded that consent must be sought if the <lb/>new study contains diverging steps from the original. <lb/>Around 26.65 of the participants responded that they <lb/>would not place any restrictions. It was enough that an <lb/>ethics review board has given permission [Chart 2,3]. <lb/>Perception of participants on the use and re-use of <lb/>biological sample <lb/>The study participants were asked in their opinion, for <lb/>what purposes can old samples be used without having <lb/>to ask the patient&apos;s permission? 48.8% responded that <lb/>could be used for the development of medicines and <lb/>treatments in pharmaceutical and biotech firms. 42.4% <lb/>responded for the original purpose of diagnosis. 40.4% <lb/>for Medical research in public institutions (such as <lb/>universities and public hospitals), 30.5% were for solving <lb/>crimes and 19.2 and 16.3% were for the development of <lb/>medicines and treatments in international firms and for <lb/>determining family relations respectively. The <lb/>study participants were asked for what purposes can <lb/>these research samples be used without having to <lb/>ask patients permission?&quot; 46.8% of the participants <lb/>opted only for the original purpose of diagnosis. <lb/>46.3% for development of medicines and treatments <lb/>in pharmaceutical and biotech firms. 34.5 % and 33% <lb/>were for Medical research in public institutions (such as <lb/>universities and public hospitals) and for solving crimes <lb/>respectively. 20.2% and 14.8% for the development of <lb/>medicines and treatments in international firms and for <lb/>determining family relations respectively [Chart 4]. <lb/>Perception on consent type in biobanking <lb/>Here the participants were asked if they were to give <lb/>sample (biological materials) to a biobank, and what <lb/>type of consent would you be willing to give? 37.9% <lb/>wanted to define the scope of use where as 26.1% <lb/>informed that re-consent should be sought if the <lb/>research setting changes. 18.2 % agreed that they would <lb/>give open consent and 17.7% reported that they would <lb/>not give consent to add their sample to a biobank. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>Research on biological samples is an investigation <lb/>conducted to discover new facts or to get additional <lb/>information about a certain disorder, by collecting and <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Bangladesh Journal of Medical Science <lb/>Volume 23 Special Issue 2024 <lb/>©The Ibn Sina Trust <lb/></note>

        <page>S 56 <lb/></page>

        <body>conducting experiments on biospecimens such as blood, <lb/>urine, hair, nails or body tissue removed after surgery, <lb/>or by collecting information either from health records <lb/>or questionnaires. <lb/>Biobank is an organised repository in which donated <lb/>biospecimens are stored. Biospecimens complied are <lb/>linked to the donor along with identifiable personal <lb/>and health information. These repositories of archived <lb/>material usually support various studies including that <lb/>on genetics. Hence protocols are mandatory for biobanks <lb/>to operate under strict privacy and confidentiality to <lb/>ensure protection of all personal identifying information <lb/>of the donor. This works by encryption of data using <lb/>codes to make it impossible to identify the donor. These <lb/>codes are then kept under supervision and given limited <lb/>access only. Any research team intending to use these <lb/>samples in research will not have the code that links <lb/>samples to identifying personal information 5 . <lb/>Trust is an integral part in successful operation of <lb/>biobanks 6 . This study investigated what a sample <lb/>of the Indian general public knew and thought about <lb/>biobanking, taking an approach to examine the general <lb/>public&apos;s willingness to donate biological samples to a <lb/>biobank for research purposes and the reasons behind <lb/>their answers. confirming a previous report from Porteri <lb/>et al. (2014) in a survey conducted in a smaller, different <lb/>sample population 6 . <lb/>This study found that members of the public are <lb/>concerned about the possibility of residual clinical <lb/>material being used by biobanks without adequate <lb/>knowledge of participation. While this concern is not <lb/>likely to translate directly into participant willingness <lb/>to participate at the time of procurement, the informed <lb/>consent process is very important to participants and <lb/>should be a key consideration when implementing <lb/>either sample collection strategy. Appropriate, easy to <lb/>understand language on procurement strategies should <lb/>be included in biobank consent information, wherever <lb/>it is applicable. <lb/>The discouraging factors in participating in biobanking <lb/>were fear of sample exploitation, research procedure <lb/>being unclear, fear of negative impact of research <lb/>on their privacy and confidentiality, not having time <lb/>to participate in research and not being comfortable <lb/>conducting experiments on their biospecimens. Similar <lb/>apprehensions were assessed in a survey conducted by <lb/>David Wendlerv One-time general consent for research <lb/>on biological samples in 2006 7 . <lb/>Confidentiality was considered important by the <lb/>participants. Recent studies and legal cases indicate that <lb/>the general public do not understand the information <lb/>presented during the informed consent process for <lb/>biospecimen and biobank research 8,9 . The use and <lb/>disclosure of the details of one&apos;s illness and medical <lb/>history, though without the mention of one&apos;s name and <lb/>personal identifiers, were considered acceptable. These <lb/>studies emphasise the importance of appropriately <lb/>informing and obtaining consent from individuals. <lb/>Consent must be sought for each new study, if the new <lb/>study uses their data with their social security number <lb/>and if the new study contains diverging steps from the <lb/>original. The consent form should define the scope for <lb/>use and re-consent should be sought if the research <lb/>setting changes. <lb/>Technological advances, automated sample processor, <lb/>computerisation have initiated revolutionary changes in <lb/>the field of medical research. In addition to all these, <lb/>the International Organisation for Standardization <lb/>has illustrated the requirements for archives stored in <lb/>biobanks (ISO 20387:2018) 10-12 Wherein it stresses <lb/>the concept of biobanks being legal entities driving <lb/>the process of acquisition, processing, storage, testing, <lb/>analysing the biological samples and their related <lb/>information and data 13,14 . Confidentiality and data <lb/>protection, are the two main concerns in biobanking, <lb/>as samples contain extensive genetic information and <lb/>the stored samples have rich value in research. Hence <lb/>there is a need for data protection law. A breach of <lb/>confidentiality is the greatest potential risk to the donors <lb/>and their families, which may result in public disclosure <lb/>of donor&apos;s identities, their genetic and private health <lb/>information. In a study conducted by Oliver et al, 34.6% <lb/>of donors reported that their greatest risk to biobanking <lb/>participation was revealing their identity 15 . The present <lb/>study also emphasised on the elevated privacy concerns <lb/>and confidentiality which affects participation consent. <lb/>The discouraging factors in participating in biobanking <lb/>were fear of sample exploitation (43.8%), research <lb/>procedure being unclear (37.9%), fear of negative <lb/>impact of research on their privacy and confidentiality <lb/>(15.8%). <lb/>Participants in the present study strongly agreed that <lb/>modern biobanking needs to have standard operating <lb/>procedures to collect, process, and store and release <lb/>biospecimens. From the point of view of the public or <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Bangladesh Journal of Medical Science <lb/>Volume 23 Special Issue 2024 <lb/>©The Ibn Sina Trust <lb/></note>

        <page>S 57 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Available at: http://www.banglajol.info/index.php/BJMS <lb/></note>

        <body>prospective participants, there is a clear need for a legal <lb/>and institutional body that can protect their interest. <lb/>Therefore, In the ICMR 2017 guidelines, Biobanks <lb/>should have well-structured standard operating <lb/>procedures for collection, coding, anonymization, <lb/>storage, access and sharing of specimens. Similar <lb/>opinions were voiced by Manjulika Vaz et al 2015, <lb/>where emphasis was placed on the role of the <lb/>Institutional Ethical Committee (IEC). IEC should not <lb/>be restricted only to the concerned Institution, instead it <lb/>should also consider the benefit of the society at large <lb/>and also extend its role and responsibilities towards <lb/>the study participants through regular monitoring and <lb/>frequent interactions 15 . The present study, however, <lb/>considerably expanded our understanding of people&apos;s <lb/>perceptions towards biobanking in India, and thus can <lb/>serve as a basis for more focused enquiry into the area. <lb/>The participants in the current study were from educated <lb/>groups and hence, were possibly more articulate and <lb/>able to voice independent views than the average <lb/>member of the general public. The study stresses on <lb/>the need to initiate public awareness and educational <lb/>programs to encourage participation in research and <lb/>inform participants of their rights and responsibilities. <lb/>CONCLUSION <lb/>The vast majority of the general public invited to take <lb/>part in the survey answered the questionnaire, making <lb/>up a representative sample of the target population. <lb/>Although the questionnaire was administered to a <lb/>particular sample of educated young Indians, which <lb/>cannot represent the Indian population at large, our <lb/>findings suggest a generally positive attitude to the <lb/>idea of donating biological samples to a biobank for <lb/>research purposes, archiving of biological specimens <lb/>from donors for use in research, has become a vital <lb/>resource for healthcare research, medical care, and <lb/>drug discovery. The creation of biobanks depends <lb/>majorly upon people&apos;s willingness to donate their <lb/>samples for research purposes and to agree to sample <lb/>storage. Therefore, knowing public&apos;s attitudes towards <lb/>participation in a biobank and biobank management <lb/>is important and deserves investigation. In India, due <lb/>to low level of literacy, paternalism and therapeutic <lb/>misconception, the idea of consent in Biobanking is mere <lb/>formality, without empowering the concerned patients. <lb/>Hence multi-tiered consent and re-consent becomes <lb/>mandatory. The biobanks also need to be accredited <lb/>and licensed. Further studies are required considering <lb/>various other parameters like socioeconomic status, <lb/>literacy, different cultural and ethnic background as this <lb/>would give us more insight to assess the perception of <lb/>the general public towards biobanking. <lb/></body>

        <div type="annex">Consent for Publication: The author reviewed and <lb/>approved the final version and has agreed to be <lb/>accountable for all aspects of the work, including any <lb/>accuracy or integrity issues. <lb/></div>

        <div type="conflict">Disclosure: The author declares that they do not <lb/>have any financial involvement, association, or entity <lb/>directly or indirectly with the subject matter or materials <lb/>presented in this editorial. This includes honoraria, <lb/>expert testimony, employment, ownership of stocks or <lb/>options, patents, or grants received or pending royalties. <lb/></div>

        <div type="availability">Data Availability: The data is exclusively available <lb/>from the principal author for research purposes only. <lb/></div>

        <div type="contribution">Authorship Contribution: All authors contributed <lb/>significantly to the work, whether in the conception, <lb/>design, utilization, collection, analysis, and interpretation <lb/>of data or all these areas. They also participated in the <lb/>paper&apos;s drafting, revision, or critical review, gave their <lb/>final approval for the version that would be published, <lb/>decided on the journal to which the article would be <lb/>submitted, and made the responsible decision to be held <lb/>accountable for all aspects of the work. <lb/></div>

        <body>Chart 1: <lb/>Chart 2: <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Bangladesh Journal of Medical Science <lb/>Volume 23 Special Issue 2024 <lb/>©The Ibn Sina Trust <lb/></note>

        <page>S 58 <lb/></page>

        <body>Chart 3: <lb/>Chart 4: <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Bangladesh Journal of Medical Science <lb/>Volume 23 Special Issue 2024 <lb/>©The Ibn Sina Trust <lb/></note>

        <page>S 59 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Available at: http://www.banglajol.info/index.php/BJMS <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Carlo Petrini. Ethical and legal considerations regarding the <lb/>ownership and commercial use of human biological materials <lb/>and their derivatives. Journal of Blood Medicine 2012:3 <lb/>2. Jones DG R Gear, K A Galvin J. Stored human tissue: an <lb/>ethical perspective on the fate of anonymous, archival material. <lb/>Journal of Medical Ethics. 2003 Dec 1;29(6):343-7. <lb/>3. Pamela Tozzo, Antonio Fassina and Luciana Caenazzo Tozzi <lb/>et al. Young people&apos;s awareness on biobanking and DNA <lb/>profiling: results of a questionnaire administered to Italian <lb/>University students. Life Sciences, Society and Policy (2017) <lb/>13:9. <lb/>4. Kumar S, Dagli N, Haque M. Human-on-Chip Technology: <lb/>Current State and Future Challenges. Bangladesh J Med Sci. <lb/>2024 Jan;23(1):7-11. <lb/>5. Leena Merdad, Lama Aldakhil, Rawan Gadi, Mourad Assidi, <lb/>Salina Y. Saddick, Adel Abuzenadah, Jim Vaught, Abdelbaset <lb/>Buhmeida and Mohammed H. Al-Qahtani. Assessment of <lb/>knowledge about biobanking among healthcare students and <lb/>their willingness to donate biospecimens. BMC Medical Ethics <lb/>(2017) 18:32. <lb/>6. Hanin Makhlouf, Nasr Alrabadi, Omar F Khabour, Karem <lb/>H Xlzoubi, Wael Al-Delaimy. Population&apos;s perspectives <lb/>toward biobanks in scientific research: a study from Jordan. <lb/>Pharmacogenomics and Personalized Medicine 2019:12 23-32. <lb/>7. Porteri C, Pasqualetti P, Togni E, Parker M. Public&apos;s attitudes <lb/>on participation in a biobank for research: An Italian survey. <lb/>BMC Medical Ethics. 2014;15:81. <lb/>8. David Wendlerv One-time general consent for research on <lb/>biological samples BMJ vol 332 4 March 2006;332:544-7 <lb/>9. Allen J, McNamara B. Reconsidering the value of consent in <lb/>biobank research. Bioethics 2011; 25:155-166. <lb/>10. Riegman PH, Morente MM, Betsou F, De Blasio P, Geary <lb/>P, Marble Arch International Working Group on Biobanking <lb/>for Biomedical Research. Biobanking for better healthcare. <lb/>Molecular oncology. 2008 Oct 1;2(3):213-22. <lb/>11. Sarojini S, Goy A, Pecora A, Suh KS. Proactive biobanking <lb/>to improve research and health care. J Tissue Sci Eng. <lb/>2012;3(02):116. <lb/>12. Hubel A, Spindler R, Skubitz APN. Storage of the human <lb/>biospecimens: selection of the optimal storage temperature, <lb/>Biopresev biobank, 2014;165-175. <lb/>13. Annaratone L, De Palma G, Bonizzi G, Sapino A, Botti G, <lb/>Berrino E, Mannelli C, Arcella P, Di Martino S, Steffan A, <lb/>Daidone MG. Basic principles of biobanking: from biological <lb/>samples to precision medicine for patients. Virchows Archiv. <lb/>2021 Aug; 479:233-46. <lb/>14. Ranju GA, Serice T. Ethical gap to implement utilitarianism <lb/>in healthcare policy: A hidden Pandemic Ethics Crisis. <lb/>Bangladesh J Med Sci. 2021 Sep;20(5):178-82. <lb/>15. De Souza YG, Greenspan JS, Biobanking past present <lb/>and Future: responsibilities and benefits. AIDS 2013 Jan <lb/>1;27(3):303. <lb/>16. Ahmed N, Abbasi MS, Zuberi F, Qamar W, Halim MSB, <lb/>Maqsood A, Alam MK. Artificial Intelligence Techniques: <lb/>Analysis, Application, and Outcome in Dentistry-A Systematic <lb/>Review. Biomed Res Int. 2021 Jun 22;2021:9751564. <lb/>17. Oliver JM, Slashinski MJ, Wang T, Kelly PA, Hilsenbeck SG, <lb/>McGuire AL. Balancing the risks and benefits of genomic data <lb/>sharing: genome research participants&apos; perspectives. Public <lb/>health genomics. 2012 Dec 30;15(2):106-14. <lb/>18. K Khan MB, Khan FA, Vaswani V, Kulkarni U, Mohan PR. The <lb/>awareness and perception about the Ethical concerns related <lb/>to the Biobanks among Medical and Dental practitioners-A <lb/>questionnaire based study. Annals of Applied Bio-Sciences. <lb/>2017 Apr 10;4(2): A99-103. </listBibl>


	</text>

</TEI>