<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Safety and efficacy of acalabrutinib plus bendamustine and rituximab in patients with treatment-naive or relapsed / refractory mantle cell lymphoma: phase Ib trial</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Tycel</forename>
          <surname>Phillips</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Michael</forename>
          <surname>Wang</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Tadeusz</forename>
          <surname>Robak</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>David</forename>
          <surname>Gallinson</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Don</forename>
          <surname>Stevens</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Krish</forename>
          <surname>Patel</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Safaa</forename>
          <surname>Ramadan</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Chuan-Chuan</forename>
          <surname>Wun</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Wojciech</forename>
          <surname>Jurczak</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Stephen D.</forename>
          <surname>Smith</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-04T14:33:14.187Z">11/4/2025 2:33:14 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Ferrata Storti Foundation (Haematologica)</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.3324/haematol.2023.284896</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Tycel Phillips, Michael Wang, Tadeusz Robak, David Gallinson, Don Stevens, Krish Patel, Safaa Ramadan, Chuan-Chuan Wun, Wojciech Jurczak, Stephen D. Smith. (2024). Safety and efficacy of acalabrutinib plus bendamustine and rituximab in patients with treatment-naive or relapsed / refractory mantle cell lymphoma: phase Ib trial. Haematologica, None(None), None. DOI: 10.3324/haematol.2023.284896</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-04T14:32:59.777580Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-04T14:32:59.777580Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>Haematologica | 110 January 2025 <lb/>142 <lb/>-Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma <lb/>ARTICLE <lb/>Atezolizumab combined with immunogenic salvage <lb/>chemoimmunotherapy in patients with transformed <lb/>diffuse large B-cell lymphoma <lb/>Tamer Othman, 1 Paul Frankel, 2 Pamela Allen, 3 Leslie L. Popplewell, 1 Geoffrey Shouse, 1 Tanya <lb/>Siddiqi, 1 Alexey V. Danilov, 1 Nora Ruel, 2 Shari Daniels, 1 Lacolle Peters, 1 Stella Khoo, 1 Steven T. <lb/>Rosen, 1 Elad Sharon, 4 Miguel Villalona-Calero, 5 Christopher Ruel, 2 Joseph Tuscano 6 and Alex <lb/>F. Herrera 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Hematology and Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation, City of Hope National <lb/>Medical Center, Duarte, CA; 2 Department of Computational and Quantitative Medicine, City <lb/>of Hope National Medical Center, Duarte, CA; 3 Winship Cancer Institute at Emory University, <lb/>Decatur, GA; 4 Division of Cancer Treatment and Diagnosis, National Cancer Institute, Cancer <lb/>Therapy Evaluation Program, Bethesda, MD; 5 Department of Medical Oncology &amp; <lb/>Therapeutics Research, City of Hope National Cancer Center, Duarte, CA and 6 Department of <lb/>Internal Medicine, Division of Malignant Hematology, Cellular Therapy and Transplantation, <lb/>University of California Davis School of Medicine, Sacramento, CA, USA <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Patients with relapsed/refractory diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL) transformed from indolent B-cell lymphomas, <lb/>including Richter transformation, have a poor prognosis. PD-1/PD-L1 antibodies produce modest objective and complete <lb/>response rates in B-cell non-Hodgkin lymphoma as monotherapy but may synergize with immunogenic chemotherapies <lb/>such as gemcitabine and oxaliplatin (GemOx). Thus, we evaluated the safety and efficacy of atezolizumab plus rituximab <lb/>and GemOx (R-GemOx+Atezo) in R/R transformed DLBCL, including Richter transformation. We conducted a phase I trial <lb/>including patients with transformed DLBCL after ≥1 prior therapy. Patients received up to four cycles of R-GemOx+Atezo. <lb/>Patients in complete remission could then proceed to R-Atezo maintenance until progression. A safety lead-in with eval-<lb/>uation of dose-limiting toxicity was performed to confirm the recommended phase II dose; subsequently the treatment <lb/>was administered to two expansion cohorts: one with transformed follicular lymphoma (FL) and the other with non-FL <lb/>transformed DLBCL, including Richter transformation. Twenty-seven patients were enrolled. One of the six patients in the <lb/>safety lead-in had a dose-limiting toxicity attributed to atezolizumab, a grade 4 Stevens-Johnson syndrome. The most <lb/>common grade ≥3 events were neutropenia (18.5%), lymphopenia (18.5%), and thrombocytopenia (14.8%). The overall and <lb/>complete response rates were 59% and 33%, respectively. The overall and complete response rates in transformed FL were <lb/>79% and 43%, respectively, and 38% and 23% in transformed non-FL, respectively. The median progression-free survival <lb/>and overall survival of the total population were 4.2 and 7.7 months, respectively. R-GemOx+Atezo was well tolerated and <lb/>demonstrated promising preliminary efficacy in patients with relapsed/refractory transformed DLBCL. <lb/></front>

        <body>Introduction <lb/>Patients with chronic lymphocytic leukemia/small lympho-<lb/>cytic lymphoma and indolent B-cell non-Hodgkin lympho-<lb/>mas, including follicular lymphoma (FL), can experience <lb/>histological transformation to diffuse large B-cell lymphoma <lb/>(DLBCL). Transformed DLBCL can be challenging to man-<lb/>age, especially if patients develop relapsed/refractory (R/R) <lb/>disease. 1,2 Patients with R/R transformed DLBCL have a poor <lb/>prognosis, with an estimated 4-year event free survival and <lb/>overall survival of 27% and 39%, respectively. 3 Standard <lb/>therapy for patients with R/R DLBCL who have primary <lb/>refractory disease or relapse within 12 months after initial <lb/>anthracycline-based chemoimmunotherapy is to proceed <lb/>to chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) T-cell therapy, while for <lb/>those who relapse after more than 12 months the standard <lb/>management is salvage chemoimmunotherapy followed by <lb/>autologous hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT) <lb/>in chemosensitive patients eligible for transplant, or palliative <lb/>therapies in patients who are not candidates for transplan-<lb/>tation. 4-6 Among patients with R/R transformed DLBCL, a <lb/>minority of patients who undergo autologous HSCT or re-<lb/></body>

        <front>Correspondence: A.F. Herrera <lb/>aherrera@coh.org <lb/>Received: <lb/>January 29, 2024. <lb/>Accepted: <lb/>July 10, 2024. <lb/>Early view: <lb/>July 18, 2024. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3324/haematol.2024.285185 <lb/>©2025 Ferrata Storti Foundation <lb/>Published under a CC BY-NC license <lb/></front>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 110 January 2025 <lb/></note>

        <page>143 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -R-GemOx+Atezo in R/R transformed DLBCL <lb/>T. Othman et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>ceive CAR T cells achieve long-term disease-free survival. 3,5-7 <lb/>There were small subsets of patients with transformed FL <lb/>in the pivotal and randomized CAR T-cell studies and there <lb/>is no clear standard treatment for patients with Richter <lb/>transformation (RT). Thus, better therapies for transformed <lb/>DLBCL, including RT, is a clear unmet need. <lb/>Atezolizumab is a monoclonal antibody that binds pro-<lb/>grammed death ligand-1 (PD-L1) to inhibit the interaction <lb/>between the programmed cell death-1 receptor (PD-1) and <lb/>PD-L1. 8 PD-1 or PD-L1 is overexpressed in several types of <lb/>non-Hodgkin lymphoma, including DLBCL 9 , FL, and RT. 10-12 <lb/>Anti-PD-1/PD-L1 monotherapy has demonstrated modest <lb/>overall response rates ranging from 4-18% in FL and DLB-<lb/>CL. 13 Atezolizumab has been safely combined with several <lb/>agents in R/R DLBCL, such as polatuzumab vedotin, taze-<lb/>metostat, and obinutuzumab, but these combinations again <lb/>demonstrated limited overall response rates ranging from <lb/>16-25%. 14-16 Preclinical data suggest synergy between immu-<lb/>nogenic chemotherapy with anti-PD-L1 antibodies, leading <lb/>to eradication of PD-1/PD-L1 blockade-refractory tumor <lb/>cells. 17 One such immunogenic chemotherapy is oxaliplatin, <lb/>which increases T-and dendritic cell infiltration, thereby <lb/>increasing the cytotoxic T-cell:regulatory T-cell ratio and <lb/>enhancing dendritic cell/macrophage function. 17,18 Another <lb/>example is gemcitabine, which depletes myeloid-derived <lb/>suppressor cells, increases tumor cell expression of major <lb/>histocompatibility complex class I, and shifts the polarity <lb/>of tumor-associated macrophages. 19-22 <lb/>The combination of gemcitabine and oxaliplatin (GemOx) is <lb/>a commonly used salvage regimen for DLBCL. Transformed <lb/>DLBCL is an ideal disease in which to evaluate the combina-<lb/>tion of immunogenic chemotherapy and checkpoint inhibitors <lb/>given the genomic complexity of transformed FL. PD-1/PD-L1 <lb/>antibodies exhibit their greatest efficacy in tumors with high <lb/>genomic instability (i.e., high tumor mutational burden and <lb/>microsatellite instability). 23,24 Transformed DLBCL, and in <lb/>particular transformed FL, are more genomically complex <lb/>than the underlying indolent B-cell non-Hodgkin lympho-<lb/>mas, 25,26 and therefore may provide more neo-antigens ripe <lb/>for recognition by T cells stimulated by checkpoint inhibi-<lb/>tors. We hypothesized that combining PD-L1 blockade with <lb/>immunogenic R-GemOx would be safe and could enhance <lb/>the antitumor activity driven by each type of therapy and <lb/>lead to a higher response rate than chemotherapy or im-<lb/>munotherapy alone. We developed a pilot study to combine <lb/>immunogenic chemotherapy, R-GemOx, with atezolizumab <lb/>(R-GemOx+Atezo), to assess the safety and preliminary ac-<lb/>tivity of this combination in patients with R/R transformed <lb/>DLBCL, including RT, and report our findings here. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Study design and participants <lb/>We conducted a multicenter phase I trial through the Na-<lb/>tional Cancer Institute Experimental Therapeutics Clinical <lb/>Trials Network (NCI ETCTN). Participating centers included <lb/>City of Hope, University of California Davis, and Emory Uni-<lb/>versity. All participating sites obtained institutional review <lb/>board approval. The trial was registered at clinicaltrials. <lb/>gov (NCT03321643). Eligible patients were ≥18 years old <lb/>with histologically confirmed transformed DLBCL, including <lb/>histological transformation from any indolent lymphoma, <lb/>such as FL, marginal zone lymphoma, lymphoplasmacytic <lb/>lymphoma or RT of chronic lymphocytic leukemia. Addi-<lb/>tionally, they must have had documented R/R disease after <lb/>at least one prior treatment regimen (which did not have <lb/>to be DLBCL-directed therapy), as defined using the 2014 <lb/>Lugano classification. 27 Other inclusion criteria included an <lb/>Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status <lb/>≤2 and adequate organ function. Exclusion criteria included <lb/>prior receipt of GemOx, anti-PD1/PD-L1 therapy or alloge-<lb/>neic HSCT; prior chemotherapy, radiotherapy or systemic <lb/>immunosuppressive therapy (with the exception of acute, <lb/>low dose, systemic immunosuppressant medications) within <lb/>2 weeks of enrollment; active central nervous system lym-<lb/>phoma; history of autoimmune disease; and pregnancy. A <lb/>full list of eligibility criteria is provided in the Online Sup-<lb/>plementary Appendix. <lb/>The study had a six-patient safety lead-in with a dose-lim-<lb/>iting toxicity (DLT) evaluation. Patients were enrolled in the <lb/>safety lead-in via the traditional 3+3 method to establish <lb/>the recommended phase II dose (RP2D). We included a dose <lb/>de-escalation level in the event that excess toxicity was ob-<lb/>served at the starting dose level. Once the RP2D had been <lb/>established, two separate expansion cohorts were enrolled: <lb/>a cohort of patients with transformed FL and another cohort <lb/>of patients with transformation of other non-FL indolent <lb/>lymphomas or RT. The six patients from the safety lead-in <lb/>portion of the study treated at RP2D were included in the <lb/>expansion cohort accrual. R-GemOx consisted of rituximab <lb/>375 mg/m 2 intravenously (IV), gemcitabine 1000 mg/m 2 IV, <lb/>and oxaliplatin 100 mg/m 2 on day 1 every 2 weeks. Atezoli-<lb/>zumab was given at a fixed dose of 840 mg IV every 2 weeks <lb/>on day 1 starting with cycle 2. Patients could receive up to <lb/>a maximum of four 21-day cycles of R-GemOx. Responding <lb/>patients could then receive maintenance therapy with ritux-<lb/>imab 375 mg/m 2 IV plus a fixed dose of atezolizumab 1,200 <lb/>mg IV (R-Atezo) every 4 weeks until disease progression or <lb/>unacceptable toxicity (Figure 1A). Patients who achieved a <lb/>complete response could transition to maintenance thera-<lb/>py after completing at least two cycles. Patients who were <lb/>transplant candidates were required to complete at least <lb/>the first two cycles of study therapy before proceeding to <lb/>HSCT at the discretion of the treating physician. Positron <lb/>emission tomography/computed tomography (PET/CT) was <lb/>performed at baseline, followed by PET/CT (or CT scans <lb/>once a complete response had been confirmed) after cycles <lb/>2 and 4. For those receiving maintenance, PET/CT or CT <lb/>scans were performed every 12 weeks until 2 years from <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 110 January 2025 <lb/></note>

        <page>144 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -R-GemOx+Atezo in R/R transformed DLBCL <lb/>T. Othman et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>the start of the study, then every 6 months while receiving <lb/>maintenance therapy. <lb/>Study outcomes and statistical analyses <lb/>The primary endpoint was to establish safety and dosing <lb/>of R-GemOx+Atezo by documenting adverse events and <lb/>determining the maximum tolerated dose/RP2D. To be <lb/>evaluable for DLT, a patient must have either experienced <lb/>a DLT during the DLT period (i.e., cycle 2), or received the <lb/>total planned doses of all drugs during the DLT period and <lb/>not experienced a DLT (which included a therapy delay of <lb/>&gt;2 weeks due to a treatment-related toxicity). During the <lb/>safety portion of the study, patients who were not evalu-<lb/>able for DLT were replaced. A list of the full DLT criteria can <lb/>be found in the Online Supplementary Appendix. Toxicity <lb/>monitoring was continued beyond the 28-day DLT period <lb/>because of the immune-related adverse events associat-<lb/>ed with checkpoint inhibitors. Secondary endpoints were <lb/>overall response rate, complete response rate, duration of <lb/>response, progression-free survival, and overall survival. <lb/>Baseline characteristics were summarized using descriptive <lb/>statistics. Responses were determined using the Lugano <lb/>2014 criteria. 27 Duration of response was calculated from <lb/>the time of first documented response to progression or <lb/>death. Progression-free survival was calculated as the <lb/>time from start of treatment to the date of progression or <lb/>death, whichever came first. Overall survival was calculated <lb/>as the time from start of treatment until death. Patients <lb/>who were alive and free of progression were censored at <lb/>the date of last follow-up. Patients who started another <lb/>therapy prior to progression were censored at that time. <lb/>Survival estimates were calculated using the Kaplan-Meier <lb/>method. <lb/>Results <lb/>Participants&apos; characteristics <lb/>Twenty-seven patients were enrolled and received treat-<lb/>ment (Figure 1B). All patients were evaluable for efficacy <lb/>and safety. The patients&apos; baseline characteristics are listed <lb/>in Table 1. The median age was 68 years (range, 44-80), 14 <lb/>patients (52%) had transformed FL, while 13 patients (48%) <lb/>had transformed non-FL (9 chronic lymphocytic leukemia/ <lb/>Figure 1. Clinical trial profile of this sin-<lb/>gle-arm trial of rituximab, gemcitabine, <lb/>oxaliplatin, and atezolizumab. (A) Study <lb/>schema. (B) CONSORT diagram. EOT: end <lb/>of treatment; DLT: dose-limiting toxicity; <lb/>PET/CT: positron emission tomography/ <lb/>computed tomography; PB: peripheral <lb/>blood; BX: biopsy; C8D1: cycle 8, day 1. <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 110 January 2025 <lb/></note>

        <page>145 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -R-GemOx+Atezo in R/R transformed DLBCL <lb/>T. Othman et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>small lymphocytic lymphoma, 3 marginal zone lymphoma, <lb/>1 lymphoplasmacytic lymphoma). The median number of <lb/>prior lines of treatment was 2 (range, 1-7), and two pa-<lb/>tients had received prior CAR T-cell therapy, one patient <lb/>had previously received a CD20-CD3 bispecific antibody <lb/>(mosunetuzumab), and one patient underwent autologous <lb/>HSCT prior to enrollment. <lb/>Safety <lb/>During the safety lead-in, eight patients were enrolled. Two <lb/>patients were replaced because of progressive disease prior <lb/>to completing the DLT evaluation period but were included <lb/>in the response rate calculations. One of six patients eval-<lb/>uable for DLT had a DLT attributed to atezolizumab during <lb/>the safety lead-in, a grade 4 Stevens-Johnson syndrome <lb/>followed by infectious complications, eventually leading <lb/>to asystole and death. The maximum tolerated dose/RP2D <lb/>was dose level 1. The most common adverse events of any <lb/>grade were fatigue (N=15), raised levels of transaminases <lb/>(N=14), thrombocytopenia (N=13), nausea/vomiting (N=12), <lb/>and hypertension (N=10) (Table 2). The most common grade <lb/>≥3 events were neutropenia (N=5, 18.5%), lymphopenia <lb/>(N=5, 18.5%), and thrombocytopenia (N=4, 14.8%) (Table <lb/>2). There was only one grade ≥3 immune-related adverse <lb/>event, which was the grade 4 Stevens-Johnson syndrome <lb/>previously mentioned. There were two treatment-related <lb/>deaths: the patient with Stevens-Johnson syndrome and <lb/>one patient who experienced an infusion reaction that led <lb/>to respiratory failure who simultaneously had progressive <lb/>disease. Eleven patients (40.7%) proceeded to R-Atezo <lb/>maintenance, and the most common grade ≥3 adverse <lb/>events during maintenance were lymphopenia (N=3), hy-<lb/>pertension (N=2), leukopenia (N=2), and thrombocytopenia <lb/>(N=2) (Online Supplementary Table S1). <lb/>Six deaths occurred either during treatment or within 30 <lb/>days of last treatment: disease progression (N=4), disease <lb/>progression with concurrent sepsis during maintenance <lb/>(N=1), and COVID-19 pneumonia (N=1). Other non-lym-<lb/>phoma related deaths include infection after coming off <lb/>treatment for progressive disease (N=2) and respiratory <lb/>failure from pneumonia after autologous HSCT. All patients <lb/>have discontinued or completed protocol therapy. Reasons <lb/>for discontinuing treatment included lack of objective re-<lb/>sponse or progression of lymphoma (N=12), switching to an <lb/>alternative therapy (N=7) (5 patients underwent autologous <lb/>HSCT, 2 patients received CAR T cells), non-fatal adverse <lb/>events (N=4), and death on study (N=3). <lb/>Efficacy <lb/>The overall and complete response rates in all patients <lb/>were 59% (N=16) and 33% (N=9), respectively. Seven pa-<lb/>tients (26%) had a partial response, one patient (4%) had <lb/>stable disease, nine patients (33%) had progressive disease, <lb/>and one patient (4%) was not assessed for a response. A <lb/>waterfall plot demonstrating the maximum change in tu-<lb/>mor size from baseline of all patients is shown in Online <lb/>Supplementary Figure S2. The median duration of response <lb/>in all responders was 4.0 months (Figure 2A), whereas <lb/>that in patients achieving a complete response or a par-<lb/>tial response was 42.6 versus 3.0 months, respectively <lb/>(Figure 2B). Of the nine patients who achieved a complete <lb/>response, five (55.6%) in complete remission proceeded to <lb/>autologous HSCT, one (11.1%) proceeded to maintenance, <lb/>two discontinued treatment due to toxicity (peripheral <lb/>neuropathy and an inflammatory reaction), and one died of <lb/>a myocardial infarction, which was unrelated to treatment, <lb/>after 42 months of maintenance therapy. The duration of <lb/>therapy for each patient is summarized in Figure 2C. We <lb/>note that durable remissions were observed irrespective <lb/>of response to last therapy prior to enrollment and time <lb/>elapsed from last line of treatment to enrollment. Table 3 <lb/>lists the response to R-GemOx+Atezo for each individual <lb/>patient based on prior lines of therapy. We did not discern <lb/>any clear correlation between prior receipt of and response <lb/>to an anthracycline-containing regimen, response to CAR T <lb/>cells, and time from last line of treatment to enrollment. <lb/>Among the 14 patients with FL, the overall and complete <lb/>Table 1. Baseline characteristics of the patients. <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>All patients <lb/>N=27 <lb/>Age in years, median (range) <lb/>68 (44-80) <lb/>Male, N (%) <lb/>16 (59) <lb/>Race/Ethnicity, N (%) <lb/>Asian <lb/>Black <lb/>Non-Hispanic White <lb/>Hispanic or Latino <lb/>Pacific Islander <lb/>2 (7) <lb/>1 (4) <lb/>18 (67) <lb/>5 (19) <lb/>1 (4) <lb/>Subgroup, N (%) <lb/>Transformed follicular lymphoma <lb/>Other transformed indolent lymphoma <lb/>14 (52) <lb/>13 (48) <lb/>Performance status, N (%) <lb/>ECOG 0-1 <lb/>ECOG 2 <lb/>26 (96) <lb/>1 (4) <lb/>Extra-nodal involvement, N (%) <lb/>10 (37) <lb/>MYC rearranged, N (%) <lb/>4 (15) <lb/>Double/triple-hit, N (%) <lb/>Unknown <lb/>7 (25.9) <lb/>1 (4) <lb/>Prior lines of therapy, median (range) <lb/>2 (1-7) <lb/>Refractory to last line of therapy, N (%) <lb/>8 (30) <lb/>Underlying Indolent lymphoma, N (%) <lb/>Follicular lymphoma <lb/>CLL/SLL <lb/>Marginal zone lymphoma <lb/>Lymphoplasmacytic lymphoma <lb/>14 (52) <lb/>9 (33) <lb/>3 (11) <lb/>1 (4) <lb/>ECOG: Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group; CLL: chronic lym-<lb/>phocytic leukemia; SLL: small lymphocytic lymphoma. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 110 January 2025 <lb/></note>

        <page>146 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -R-GemOx+Atezo in R/R transformed DLBCL <lb/>T. Othman et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>response rates were 79% and 43%, respectively. In non-FL <lb/>transformed lymphomas, the overall and complete re-<lb/>sponse rates were 38% and 23%, respectively. There were <lb/>three patients with transformed marginal zone lymphoma, <lb/>of whom two achieved a complete response, while one pa-<lb/>tient achieved a partial response. There were nine patients <lb/>with RT; the overall and complete response rates were <lb/>22% and 11%, respectively. The median progression-free <lb/>survival and overall survival of the total population were <lb/>3.7 and 7.7 months, respectively (Figure 3A). The median <lb/>progression-free survival in patients with transformed FL <lb/>or non-FL were 3.7 and 3.1 months, respectively (P=0.4) <lb/>(Figure 3B), and the median overall survival for the two <lb/>groups were 22.5 and 7.3 months, respectively (P=0.4) <lb/>(Figure 3C). Notably, one patient who received both an <lb/>autologous HSCT and CAR T cells prior to enrollment <lb/>had a partial response to R-GemOx+Atezo, while another <lb/>patient who had been treated with mosunetuzumab and <lb/>CAR T cells had progressive disease during treatment <lb/>with R-GemOx+Atezo. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>R-GemOx+Atezo was tolerable and effective in R/R trans-<lb/>formed DLBCL. The starting dose was the RP2D, and most <lb/>Table 2. Adverse events. <lb/>Adverse events related to treatment <lb/>with at least two grade ≥ 2 events, N (%) <lb/>Transformed follicular lymphoma <lb/>Other transformed lymphomas <lb/>Grade 1-2 <lb/>Grade 3-4 <lb/>Grade 5 <lb/>Grade 1-2 <lb/>Grade 3-4 <lb/>Grade 5 <lb/>Cardiac arrest <lb/>-<lb/>1 (7) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1 (8) <lb/>White blood cell count decreased <lb/>-<lb/>3 (21) <lb/>-<lb/>2 (15) <lb/>1 (8) <lb/>-<lb/>Lymphocyte count decreased <lb/>-<lb/>4 (29) <lb/>-<lb/>2 (15) <lb/>1 (8) <lb/>-<lb/>Neutrophil count decreased <lb/>1 (7) <lb/>3 (21) <lb/>-<lb/>2 (15) <lb/>2 (15) <lb/>-<lb/>Fever <lb/>3 (21) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>3 (31) <lb/>1 (8) <lb/>-<lb/>Dyspnea <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1 (8) <lb/>1 (8) <lb/>-<lb/>Acute kidney injury <lb/>-<lb/>1 (7) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1 (8) <lb/>-<lb/>Atrial fibrillation <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1 (8) <lb/>-<lb/>Hyperkalemia <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1 (8) <lb/>-<lb/>Hypernatremia <lb/>1 (7) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1 (8) <lb/>-<lb/>Respiratory failure <lb/>-<lb/>1 (7) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1 (8) <lb/>-<lb/>Platelet count decreased <lb/>3 (21) <lb/>3 (21) <lb/>-<lb/>6 (46) <lb/>1 (8) <lb/>-<lb/>Maculo-papular rash <lb/>2 (14) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1 (8) <lb/>-<lb/>Aspergillosis <lb/>-<lb/>1 (7) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Multi-organ failure <lb/>-<lb/>1 (7) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Sepsis <lb/>-<lb/>1 (7) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Stevens-Johnson syndrome <lb/>-<lb/>1 (7) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Hypertension <lb/>6 (43) <lb/>2 (14) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>2 (15) <lb/>-<lb/>Infusion related reaction <lb/>2 (14) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1 (8) <lb/>1 (8) <lb/>-<lb/>Increased alanine transaminase <lb/>6 (43) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>7 (54) <lb/>1 (8) <lb/>-<lb/>Dizziness <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1 (8) <lb/>-<lb/>Febrile neutropenia <lb/>-<lb/>1 (7) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1 (8) <lb/>-<lb/>Anemia <lb/>3 (21) <lb/>1 (7) <lb/>-<lb/>3 (31) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Hypokalemia <lb/>2 (14) <lb/>1 (7) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Hypocalcemia <lb/>1 (7) <lb/>1 (7) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Nausea/vomiting <lb/>5 (36) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>7 (54) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Fatigue <lb/>7 (50) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>8 (62) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Peripheral sensory neuropathy <lb/>2 (14) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>3 (31) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 110 January 2025 <lb/></note>

        <page>147 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -R-GemOx+Atezo in R/R transformed DLBCL <lb/>T. Othman et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>toxicities were manageable. With the caveat of the small <lb/>sample size, response rates were numerically higher in <lb/>the FL cohort than in the non-FL cohort, although pro-<lb/>gression-free survival and overall survival were similar in <lb/>the two groups. Durable responses were observed and <lb/>appeared to be longer for those who achieved a complete <lb/>response than in those who had a partial response. Nota-<lb/>bly, over a quarter of patients enrolled were successfully <lb/>transitioned to autologous HSCT or CAR T-cell therapy. <lb/>However, there was a rare but fatal complication with this <lb/>regimen, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, which is known to <lb/>occur with PD-1/PD-L1 blockade. 28 Although uncommon, <lb/>severe immune toxicities are an important limitation of <lb/>using regimens that incorporate PD-1 blockade into ther-<lb/>apy for DLBCL. <lb/>Although R-GemOx previously demonstrated overall and <lb/>complete response rates of 61% and 44%, respectively, in <lb/>DLBCL, 29 the patient population in that study is not directly <lb/>comparable to ours: in the previous study the cohort pre-<lb/>dominately consisted of de novo DLBCL patients receiving <lb/>second-line therapy, and none had RT. Moreover, the man-<lb/>agement of R/R DLBCL has evolved significantly since the <lb/>original R-GemOx studies were conducted. Our trial was <lb/>carried out more recently, with some patients having re-<lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>Continued on following page. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 110 January 2025 <lb/></note>

        <page>148 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -R-GemOx+Atezo in R/R transformed DLBCL <lb/>T. Othman et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>ceived prior, novel therapies. Recently, the phase III NIVEAU <lb/>study showed no benefit in progression-free survival from <lb/>the addition of nivolumab to R-GemOx in R/R DLBCL, and <lb/>a median progression-free survival similar to that in our <lb/>study. 30 However, these patients were not restricted to <lb/>transformed DLBCL and patients enrolled in the NIVEAU <lb/>study had received only one prior line of therapy, which <lb/>limits direct comparisons with our study. Regardless, the <lb/>short progression-free survival we observed suggests that <lb/>our regimen serves best as a bridge to more definitive ther-<lb/>apy, such as autologous HSCT or CAR T cells. In contrast <lb/>to the efficacy of R-GemOx-Atezo that we observed in R/R <lb/>transformed FL, the treatment was not very effective in RT. <lb/>This finding parallels the results seen in KEYNOTE-170, 31 <lb/>in which the response rate to pembrolizumab in R/R RT <lb/>with DLBCL histology was only 6%, but differs from those <lb/>of prior studies conducted by Ding et al. and Jain et al., <lb/>which utilized pembrolizumab and nivolumab, leading to <lb/>response rates of 44% and 42%, respectively. 32,33 The striking <lb/>difference in efficacy between these two studies and ours <lb/>may be related to the use of a BTK inhibitor. The two prior <lb/>studies included patients with recent or concurrent BTK <lb/>inhibition, which may have immunomodulatory effects that <lb/>possibly enhance the efficacy of PD-1/PD-L1 blockade. 34,35 A <lb/>third study of venetoclax, obinutuzumab, and atezolizum-<lb/>ab demonstrated overall and complete response rates of <lb/>100% and 71%, respectively, in six patients. 36 <lb/>The responses we observed may have been due to chemo-<lb/>therapy sensitizing lymphoma cells to PD-1/PD-L1 block-<lb/>ade, possibly due to the immunogenic effects of certain <lb/>chemotherapeutic agents. This apparent chemosensitiza-<lb/>tion by PD-1 blockade has been observed in non-Hodgkin <lb/>lymphoma, with several studies demonstrating improved <lb/>response rates to chemotherapy in previously chemorefrac-<lb/>tory patients after PD1 blockade was given. 37 Our study, as <lb/>well as those conducted in RT by others, support the idea <lb/>that PD1 combined with chemotherapy may be effective in <lb/>non-Hodgkin lymphoma, but the types of chemotherapy or <lb/>other concurrent/subsequent therapies may be important, <lb/>as well as the immunogenicity of that particular agent. <lb/>We note several important limitations to our study, such <lb/>as the small sample size and lack of a comparator arm to <lb/>determine whether the addition of atezolizumab affects <lb/>the response rate to the immunogenic chemotherapy. At <lb/>the time this study was conceived, there was a signifi-<lb/>cant dearth of trials studying transformed indolent lym-<lb/>Figure 2. Duration of response in patients treated with rituximab, gemcitabine, oxaliplatin, and atezolizumab. (A) Duration of <lb/>response in all treated patients. (B) Duration of response in patients achieving complete or partial response. (C) Swimmer plot <lb/>of patients enrolled. 95% CI: 95% confidence interval; NR: not reached; CR: complete response; PR: partial response; SD: stable <lb/>disease; PD: progressive disease; NA: not available; Tx: treatment; R-Atezo: rituximab and atezolizumab. <lb/>C <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 110 January 2025 <lb/></note>

        <page>149 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -R-GemOx+Atezo in R/R transformed DLBCL <lb/>T. Othman et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>Table 3. Responses to the rituximab, gemcitabine, oxaliplatin and atezolizumab treatment regimen based on prior lines of therapy. <lb/>Patient <lb/>ID <lb/>N of prior <lb/>lines <lb/>N of prior <lb/>lines for <lb/>transformed <lb/>lymphoma <lb/>Prior <lb/>anthracycline <lb/>Response to <lb/>R-CHOP or <lb/>DA-EPOCH-R <lb/>Last line of <lb/>therapy <lb/>Response to <lb/>last line of <lb/>therapy <lb/>Last line treating <lb/>indolent or <lb/>transformed <lb/>lymphoma <lb/>Response to <lb/>CAR T cells <lb/>Time from last <lb/>line of therapy <lb/>to enrollment <lb/>Response to <lb/>R-GemOx+ <lb/>Atezo <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>Yes <lb/>CR <lb/>Bendamustine/ <lb/>Obinutuzumab <lb/>PR <lb/>Indolent <lb/>N/A <lb/>7.1 months <lb/>PR <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Yes <lb/>PD <lb/>DA-EPOCH-R <lb/>PD <lb/>Transformed <lb/>N/A <lb/>27 days <lb/>CR <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Yes <lb/>CR <lb/>R-CHOP <lb/>CR <lb/>Transformed <lb/>N/A <lb/>15.7 years <lb/>CR <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/>No <lb/>N/A <lb/>Venetoclax/ <lb/>obinutuzumab <lb/>CR <lb/>Indolent <lb/>N/A <lb/>6.4 months <lb/>PD <lb/>5 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>No <lb/>N/A <lb/>Ibrutinib <lb/>CR <lb/>Indolent <lb/>N/A <lb/>19 days <lb/>PD <lb/>6 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Yes <lb/>SD <lb/>R-CHOP <lb/>CR <lb/>Transformed <lb/>N/A <lb/>25 days <lb/>PD <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>1 <lb/>Yes <lb/>PD <lb/>DA-EPOCH-R <lb/>PD <lb/>Transformed <lb/>N/A <lb/>1.3 months <lb/>PD <lb/>8 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>Yes <lb/>CR <lb/>Axicabtagene <lb/>ciloleucel <lb/>CR <lb/>Transformed <lb/>CR <lb/>1.1 years <lb/>PR <lb/>9 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>No <lb/>N/A <lb/>Venetoclax <lb/>PD <lb/>Indolent <lb/>N/A <lb/>1.1 months <lb/>N/A <lb/>10 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>No <lb/>N/A <lb/>Bendamustine/ <lb/>rituximab <lb/>CR <lb/>Indolent <lb/>N/A <lb/>4.3 years <lb/>SD <lb/>11 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>Yes <lb/>PR <lb/>Bendamustine/ <lb/>rituximab <lb/>SD <lb/>Indolent <lb/>N/A <lb/>23 days <lb/>CR <lb/>12 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>Yes <lb/>PR <lb/>R-CHOP <lb/>PR <lb/>Transformed <lb/>N/A <lb/>2.5 months <lb/>PD <lb/>13 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Yes <lb/>PR <lb/>R-CHOP <lb/>PR <lb/>Transformed <lb/>N/A <lb/>1.5 months <lb/>PR <lb/>14 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Yes <lb/>PR <lb/>R-CHOP <lb/>PR <lb/>Transformed <lb/>N/A <lb/>9.1 months <lb/>CR <lb/>15 <lb/>7 <lb/>4 <lb/>Yes <lb/>PD <lb/>Clinical Trial <lb/>PD <lb/>Transformed <lb/>CR <lb/>23 days <lb/>PD <lb/>16 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Yes <lb/>CR <lb/>R-CHOP <lb/>CR <lb/>Transformed <lb/>N/A <lb/>1.7 years <lb/>CR <lb/>17 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Yes <lb/>CR <lb/>DA-EPOCH-R <lb/>CR <lb/>Transformed <lb/>N/A <lb/>2.3 years <lb/>CR <lb/>18 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>Yes <lb/>CR <lb/>Bendamustine/ <lb/>Obinutuzumab <lb/>CR <lb/>Indolent <lb/>N/A <lb/>1.9 years <lb/>PD <lb/>19 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>Yes <lb/>SD <lb/>ICE <lb/>PD <lb/>Transformed <lb/>N/A <lb/>1.5 months <lb/>PD <lb/>20 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>Yes <lb/>PR <lb/>DA-EPOCH-R <lb/>PR <lb/>Transformed <lb/>N/A <lb/>5.4 months <lb/>PR <lb/>21 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Yes <lb/>PD <lb/>R-CHOP <lb/>PD <lb/>Transformed <lb/>N/A <lb/>1.7 months <lb/>PD <lb/>22 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Yes <lb/>CR <lb/>R-CHOP <lb/>CR <lb/>Transformed <lb/>N/A <lb/>1.2 years <lb/>CR <lb/>23 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Yes <lb/>PR <lb/>DA-EPOCH-R <lb/>PR <lb/>Transformed <lb/>N/A <lb/>5.8 months <lb/>PR <lb/>24 <lb/>4 <lb/>1 <lb/>Yes <lb/>CR <lb/>Bendamustine/ <lb/>rituximab <lb/>SD <lb/>Indolent <lb/>N/A <lb/>3.8 years <lb/>PR <lb/>25 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>Yes <lb/>CR <lb/>R-CHOP <lb/>CR <lb/>Transformed <lb/>N/A <lb/>1.2 years <lb/>CR <lb/>26 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Yes <lb/>CR <lb/>R-CHOP <lb/>CR <lb/>Transformed <lb/>N/A <lb/>1.8 years <lb/>PR <lb/>27 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Yes <lb/>CR <lb/>R-CHOP <lb/>CR <lb/>Transformed <lb/>N/A <lb/>6.4 years <lb/>CR <lb/>ID. Identity; R-CHOP: rituximab, cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, vincristine, and prednisone; DA-EPOCH-R: dose-adjusted etoposide, prednisone, vincristine, cyclophosphamide, <lb/>doxorubicin, and rituximab; CAR: chimeric antigen receptor; R-GemOx+Atezo: rituximab, gemcitabine, oxaliplatin, and atezolizumab; CR: complete response; PR: partial response; <lb/>N/A: not applicable; PD: progressive disease; SD: stable disease; ICE: ifosfamide, carboplatin, and etoposide. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 110 January 2025 <lb/></note>

        <page>150 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -R-GemOx+Atezo in R/R transformed DLBCL <lb/>T. Othman et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 3. Survival outcomes in patients <lb/>treated with rituximab, gemcitabine, ox-<lb/>aliplatin, and atezolizumab. (A) Progres-<lb/>sion-free and overall survival for all treat-<lb/>ed patients. (B) Progression-free survival <lb/>for patients with follicular lymphoma or <lb/>non-follicular lymphoma. (C) Overall sur-<lb/>vival for patients with follicular lymphoma <lb/>or non-follicular lymphoma. 95% CI: 95% <lb/>confidence interval; NR: not reached. <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 110 January 2025 <lb/></note>

        <page>151 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -R-GemOx+Atezo in R/R transformed DLBCL <lb/>T. Othman et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>phomas. Over the past few years, however, the Food and <lb/>Drug Administration has approved newer agents such as <lb/>CAR T-cell therapy and bispecific antibodies, which have <lb/>all shown promising efficacy in transformed indolent lym-<lb/>phomas. 6,38-40 Since the study was conducted primarily in <lb/>the era before these therapies were available, our study <lb/>cohort included a small number of patients receiving CAR <lb/>T cells and bispecific antibodies. Moreover, we note that <lb/>four patients did not receive an anthracycline-contain-<lb/>ing therapy for transformed DLBCL prior to enrollment, a <lb/>standard-of-care treatment for this disease. The reasons <lb/>for the treating investigators&apos; choice to forego a standard <lb/>anthracycline-containing therapy for DLBCL were not col-<lb/>lected during the trial. <lb/>With further validation, the R-GemOx-Atezo regimen could <lb/>be considered as an option for patients who relapse after <lb/>CAR T-cell and bispecific antibody therapy. There may be <lb/>appeal from using a PD-1/PD-L1 blocking antibody after <lb/>these immunotherapies as there may be augmentation <lb/>or re-sensitization of the prior immunotherapy. Moreover, <lb/>this regimen has potential use as a bridging regimen for <lb/>those intended to receive CAR T cells, for patients with <lb/>late relapses after initial chemoimmunotherapy with an <lb/>indication for autologous HSCT, or for allogeneic HSCT. The <lb/>immunogenic and/or chemosensitizing effects of R-GemOx <lb/>and PD-1/PD-L1 blockade may possibly impact the efficacy <lb/>of subsequent immunotherapies, such as CAR T cells or <lb/>bispecific antibodies, as has previously been observed with <lb/>PD-1/PD-L1 blockade. 37 <lb/>In conclusion, R-GemOx+Atezo was tolerable and effec-<lb/>tive in transformed DLBCL. The highest response rate to <lb/>R-GemOx+Atezo was in patients with transformed FL. The <lb/>response rate in patients with RT was lower than what has <lb/>been described in some prior studies employing check-<lb/>point inhibitors. Our results support future evaluation of <lb/>immunogenic chemotherapy combined with checkpoint <lb/>inhibitors to improve outcomes in R/R transformed DLBCL. <lb/></body>

        <div type="conflict">Disclosures <lb/>AFH has received research funding from and provided con-<lb/>sultancy for ADC Therapeutics, AstraZeneca, Bristol Myers <lb/>Squibb, Genentech, Merck, and Seattle Genetics; has received <lb/>research funding from Gilead Sciences and KiTE Pharma; and <lb/>has acted as a consultant for AbbVie, Adicet Bio, Allogene <lb/>Therapeutics, Caribou Biosciences, Genmab, Karyopharm, <lb/>Pfizer, Regeneron, Takeda, and Tubulis. The other authors <lb/>have no conflicts of interest to disclose. <lb/></div>

        <div type="contribution">Contributions <lb/>TO and MV interpreted the analyses and wrote the manu-<lb/>script. PF, NR, and CR conducted the statistical analyses. PA, <lb/>LLP, GS, TS, AVD, and STR enrolled patients and edited the <lb/>manuscript. SD, LP, and SK collected data and edited the <lb/>manuscript. ES designed the study and edited the manu-<lb/>script. JT designed the study, enrolled patients, and edited <lb/>the manuscript. AFH designed the study, enrolled patients, <lb/>interpreted the analyses, and wrote the manuscript. <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">Funding <lb/>AFH was supported by the Emmet and Toni Stephenson <lb/>Leukemia and Lymphoma Society Scholar Award, and the <lb/>Lymphoma Research Foundation Larry and Denise Mason <lb/>Clinical Investigator Career Development Award. The research <lb/>reported was supported by the National Cancer Institute <lb/>of the National Institutes of Health under Award Number <lb/>UM1CA186717. <lb/></div>

        <div type="availability">Data-sharing statement <lb/>Original data and the protocol are available upon request. <lb/>Please contact the corresponding author. <lb/></div>

        <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Smith S. Transformed lymphoma: what should I do now? <lb/>Hematology Am Soc Hematol Educ Program. <lb/>2020;2020(1):306-311. <lb/>2. Ding W. Richter transformation in the era of novel agents. <lb/>Hematology Am Soc Hematol Educ Program. <lb/>2018;2018(1):256-263. <lb/>3. Kuruvilla J, MacDonald DA, Kouroukis CT, et al. Salvage <lb/>chemotherapy and autologous stem cell transplantation for <lb/>transformed indolent lymphoma: a subset analysis of NCIC CTG <lb/>LY12. Blood. 2015;126(6):733-738. <lb/>4. Zelenetz AD, Gordon LI, Chang JE, et al. NCCN Guidelines® <lb/>insights: B-cell lymphomas, version 5.2021. J Natl Compr Canc <lb/>Netw. 2021;19(11):1218-1230. <lb/>5. Locke FL, Miklos DB, Jacobson CA, et al. Axicabtagene <lb/>ciloleucel as second-line therapy for large B-cell lymphoma. N <lb/>Engl J Med. 2022;386(7):640-654. <lb/>6. Kamdar M, Solomon SR, Arnason J, et al. Lisocabtagene <lb/>maraleucel versus standard of care with salvage chemotherapy <lb/>followed by autologous stem cell transplantation as second-<lb/>line treatment in patients with relapsed or refractory large <lb/>B-cell lymphoma (TRANSFORM): results from an interim <lb/>analysis of an open-label, randomised, phase 3 trial. Lancet. <lb/>2022;399(10343):2294-2308. <lb/>7. Herrera AF, Ahn KW, Litovich C, et al. Autologous and allogeneic <lb/>hematopoietic cell transplantation for diffuse large B-cell <lb/>lymphoma-type Richter syndrome. Blood Adv. <lb/>2021;5(18):3528-3539. <lb/>8. Horn L, Mansfield AS, Szczęsna A, et al. First-line atezolizumab <lb/>plus chemotherapy in extensive-stage small-cell lung cancer. N <lb/>Engl J Med. 2018;379(23):2220-2229. <lb/>9. Chen BJ, Chapuy B, Ouyang J, et al. PD-L1 expression is <lb/>characteristic of a subset of aggressive B-cell lymphomas and <lb/>virus-associated malignancies. Clin Cancer Res. <lb/>2013;19(13):3462-3473. <lb/>10. Carreras J, Lopez-Guillermo A, Roncador G, et al. High numbers <lb/>of tumor-infiltrating programmed cell death 1-positive <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 110 January 2025 <lb/></note>

        <page>152 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -R-GemOx+Atezo in R/R transformed DLBCL <lb/>T. Othman et al. <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>regulatory lymphocytes are associated with improved overall <lb/>survival in follicular lymphoma. J Clin Oncol. <lb/>2009;27(9):1470-1476. <lb/>11. Xerri L, Chetaille B, Serriari N, et al. Programmed death 1 is a <lb/>marker of angioimmunoblastic T-cell lymphoma and B-cell <lb/>small lymphocytic lymphoma/chronic lymphocytic leukemia. <lb/>Hum Pathol. 2008;39(7):1050-1058. <lb/>12. Behdad A, Griffin B, Chen Y-H, et al. PD-1 is highly expressed by <lb/>neoplastic B-cells in Richter transformation. Br J Haematol. <lb/>2019;185(2):370-373. <lb/>13. Armengol M, Santos JC, Fernández-Serrano M, Profitós-Pelejà <lb/>N, Ribeiro ML, Roué G. Immune-checkpoint inhibitors in B-cell <lb/>lymphoma. Cancers (Basel). 2021;13(2):214. <lb/>14. Topp MS, Eradat H, Florschütz A, et al. Anti-CD20-<lb/>atezolizumab-polatuzumab vedotin in relapsed/refractory <lb/>follicular and diffuse large B-cell lymphoma. J Cancer Res Clin <lb/>Oncol. 2023;149(2):811-817. <lb/>15. Palomba ML, Cartron G, Popplewell L, et al. Combination of <lb/>atezolizumab and tazemetostat in patients with relapsed/ <lb/>refractory diffuse large B-cell lymphoma: results from a phase <lb/>Ib study. Clin Lymphoma Myeloma Leuk. 2022;22(7):504-512. <lb/>16. Palomba ML, Till BG, Park SI, et al. Combination of <lb/>atezolizumab and obinutuzumab in patients with relapsed/ <lb/>refractory follicular lymphoma and diffuse large B-cell <lb/>lymphoma: results from a phase 1b study. Clin Lymphoma <lb/>Myeloma Leuk. 2022;22(7):e443-e451. <lb/>17. Pfirschke C, Engblom C, Rickelt S, et al. Immunogenic <lb/>chemotherapy sensitizes tumors to checkpoint blockade <lb/>therapy. Immunity. 2016;44(2):343-354. <lb/>18. Wang W, Wu L, Zhang J, Wu H, Han E, Guo Q. <lb/>Chemoimmunotherapy by combining oxaliplatin with immune <lb/>checkpoint blockades reduced tumor burden in colorectal <lb/>cancer animal model. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. <lb/>2017;487(1):1-7. <lb/>19. Noguchi T, Ward JP, Gubin MM, et al. Temporally distinct PD-L1 <lb/>expression by tumor and host cells contributes to immune <lb/>escape. Cancer Immunol Res. 2017;5(2):106-117. <lb/>20. Parra ER, Behrens C, Rodriguez-Canales J, et al. Image analysis-<lb/>based assessment of PD-L1 and tumor-associated immune <lb/>cells density supports distinct intratumoral microenvironment <lb/>groups in non-small cell lung carcinoma patients. Clin Cancer <lb/>Res. 2016;22(24):6278-6289. <lb/>21. Pham CD, Flores C, Yang C, et al. Differential immune <lb/>microenvironments and response to immune checkpoint <lb/>blockade among molecular subtypes of murine <lb/>medulloblastoma. Clin Cancer Res. 2016;22(3):582-595. <lb/>22. Galluzzi L, Buque A, Kepp O, Zitvogel L, Kroemer G. <lb/>Immunological effects of conventional chemotherapy and <lb/>targeted anticancer agents. Cancer Cell. 2015;28(6):690-714. <lb/>23. Rizvi NA, Hellmann MD, Snyder A, et al. Cancer immunology. <lb/>Mutational landscape determines sensitivity to PD-1 blockade <lb/>in non-small cell lung cancer. Science. 2015;348(6230):124-128. <lb/>24. Snyder A, Makarov V, Merghoub T, et al. Genetic basis for <lb/>clinical response to CTLA-4 blockade in melanoma. N Engl J <lb/>Med. 2014;371(23):2189-2199. <lb/>25. Casulo C, Burack WR, Friedberg JW. Transformed follicular <lb/>non-Hodgkin lymphoma. Blood. 2015;125(1):40-47. <lb/>26. Scherer F, Kurtz DM, Newman AM, et al. Distinct biological <lb/>subtypes and patterns of genome evolution in lymphoma <lb/>revealed by circulating tumor DNA. Sci Transl Med. <lb/>2016;8(364):364ra155. <lb/>27. Cheson BD, Fisher RI, Barrington SF, et al. Recommendations <lb/>for initial evaluation, staging, and response assessment of <lb/>Hodgkin and non-Hodgkin lymphoma: the Lugano classification. <lb/>J Clin Oncol. 2014;32(27):3059-3068. <lb/>28. Zhu J, Chen G, He Z, et al. Stevens-Johnson syndrome/toxic <lb/>epidermal necrolysis in patients treated with immune <lb/>checkpoint inhibitors: a safety analysis of clinical trials and FDA <lb/>pharmacovigilance database. EClinicalMedicine. 2021;37:100951. <lb/>29. Mounier N, El Gnaoui T, Tilly H, et al. Rituximab plus <lb/>gemcitabine and oxaliplatin in patients with refractory/relapsed <lb/>diffuse large B-cell lymphoma who are not candidates for <lb/>high-dose therapy. A phase II Lymphoma Study Association <lb/>trial. Haematologica. 2013;98(11):1726-1731. <lb/>30. Held G, Altmann B, Kerkhoff A, et al. R-GemOx plus nivolumab <lb/>vs R-GemOx as second-line therapy for large B-cell lymphoma <lb/>in transplant-ineligible patients: interim analysis of the Niveau <lb/>trial, an international, randomized phase 3 study of the AGMT, <lb/>GLA, HOVON, Lysa and PLRG. Blood. <lb/>2023;142(Supplement 1):435. <lb/>31. Armand P, Murawski N, Molin D, et al. Pembrolizumab in <lb/>relapsed or refractory Richter syndrome. Br J Haematol. <lb/>2020;190(2):e117-e120. <lb/>32. Ding W, LaPlant BR, Call TG, et al. Pembrolizumab in patients <lb/>with CLL and Richter transformation or with relapsed CLL. <lb/>Blood. 2017;129(26):3419-3427. <lb/>33. Jain N, Senapati J, Thakral B, et al. A phase 2 study of <lb/>nivolumab combined with ibrutinib in patients with diffuse <lb/>large B-cell Richter transformation of CLL. Blood Adv. <lb/>2023;7(10):1958-1966. <lb/>34. Dubovsky JA, Beckwith KA, Natarajan G, et al. Ibrutinib is an <lb/>irreversible molecular inhibitor of ITK driving a Th1-selective <lb/>pressure in T lymphocytes. Blood. 2013;122(15):2539-2549. <lb/>35. Sagiv-Barfi I, Kohrt HE, Czerwinski DK, Ng PP, Chang BY, Levy R. <lb/>Therapeutic antitumor immunity by checkpoint blockade is <lb/>enhanced by ibrutinib, an inhibitor of both BTK and ITK. Proc <lb/>Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2015;112(9):E966-E972. <lb/>36. Jain N, Ferrajoli A, Thompson PA, et al. Venetoclax, <lb/>obinutuzumab and atezolizumab (PD-L1 checkpoint inhibitor) <lb/>for treatment for patients with Richter transformation. Blood. <lb/>2021;138 (Supplement 1):1550. <lb/>37. Carreau NA, Armand P, Merryman RW, et al. Checkpoint <lb/>blockade treatment sensitises relapsed/refractory non-Hodgkin <lb/>lymphoma to subsequent therapy. Br J Haematol. <lb/>2020;191(1):44-51. <lb/>38. Hutchings M, Mous R, Clausen MR, et al. Dose escalation of <lb/>subcutaneous epcoritamab in patients with relapsed or <lb/>refractory B-cell non-Hodgkin lymphoma: an open-label, phase <lb/>1/2 study. Lancet. 2021;398(10306):1157-1169. <lb/>39. Dickinson MJ, Carlo-Stella C, Morschhauser F, et al. Glofitamab <lb/>for relapsed or refractory diffuse large B-cell lymphoma. N Engl <lb/>J Med. 2022;387(24):2220-2231. <lb/>40. Neelapu SS, Dickinson M, Munoz J, et al. Axicabtagene <lb/>ciloleucel as first-line therapy in high-risk large B-cell <lb/>lymphoma: the phase 2 ZUMA-12 trial. Nat Med. <lb/>2022;28(4):735-742. </listBibl>


	</text>

</TEI>