<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>http://wydawnictwa.pzh.gov.pl/roczniki_pzh/ <lb/>This article is available in Open Access model and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial 3.0.Poland License <lb/>(CC BY-NC) (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/pl/deed.en) <lb/>Publisher: National Institute of Public Health NIH -National Research Institute <lb/>Corresponding author: Elżbieta Szczepańska, Department of Human Nutrition, Department of Dietetics, Faculty of Public Health in <lb/>Bytom, Medical University of Silesia in Katowice, Jordana 19, 41-808 Zabrze, Poland, e-mail: eszczepanska@sum.edu.pl <lb/>https://doi.org/10.32394/rpzh.2024.0290 <lb/>Rocz Panstw Zakl Hig 2024;75(1):35-44 <lb/>ORIGINAL ARTICLE <lb/>KNOWLEDGE AND EATING HABITS REGARDING FUNCTIONAL FOOD <lb/>AMONG ADULTS <lb/>Elżbieta Szczepańska 1, , Aleksandra Liedtka 1 , Elżbieta Czech 2, <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Human Nutrition, Department of Dietetics, Faculty of Public Health in Bytom, Medical <lb/>University of Silesia in Katowice, Zabrze, Poland <lb/>2 Department of Biostatistics, Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, Faculty of Public Health in <lb/>Bytom, Medical University of Silesia in Katowice, Bytom, Poland <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Background. Functional food is a key element in the prevention and treatment of many diseases. The ingredients it <lb/>contains, such as phytosterols that lower cholesterol, also have a preventive effect on type 2 diabetes, atherosclerosis and <lb/>heart attack. Phenolic compounds have antioxidant, anti-inflammatory and antiviral properties. Xylo-oligosaccharides <lb/>control insulin levels, and fibre lowers blood pressure, potentially reducing insulin resistance. These beneficial properties <lb/>mean that there is an increasing interest in this kind of food. <lb/>Objective. The aim of the study was to assess the state of knowledge and behaviour regarding functional food among <lb/>adults and to answer the question whether there are differences between the state of knowledge and behaviour of women <lb/>and men. <lb/>Material and methods. The survey was conducted among 301 people, including 181 women and 120 men. The research <lb/>tool was an original survey questionnaire. <lb/>Results. The definition of functional food is known to 42.5% of people (47.5% of women and 35% of men), while the <lb/>definition of prebiotic is known to 41.9% of people (43.1% of women and 40.0% of men). For 56.2% of respondents, <lb/>the factor encouraging the consumption of functional food was a healthy lifestyle, and for 54.7% of them, the product <lb/>composition was the main purchase criterion. Among functional products, cereals or muesli were most often consumed <lb/>for breakfast by 35% of men and 55.8% of women, 42.5% of men and 33.7% of women were eaten oils for lunch. For <lb/>dinner they most often consumed fruit teas, herbal teas, herbal mixtures, this answer was given by 25.8% of men and <lb/>29.8% of women. <lb/>Conclusions. Knowledge of functional foods is unsatisfactory, and no differences in the knowledge of women and men <lb/>have been observed. Consumption of functional food is generally low, and no differences in consumption have been <lb/>observed between women and men. <lb/>Key words: functional food, eating habits, nutritional knowledge, adults <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Functional food is this kind of food that has <lb/>a proved beneficial effect on functioning of the body <lb/>by reducing the risk of certain diseases, improving <lb/>well-being and, consequently, increasing the quality <lb/>of life of people who consume it [24]. These foods may <lb/>have a beneficial effect on both one and several body <lb/>functions. In addition to the ingredients normally <lb/>included in its composition, it also contains additional <lb/>substances or an increased concentration of one of the <lb/>ingredients originally included in its composition [24]. <lb/>Nowadays, there is an increasing interest in <lb/>maintaining a good quality of life, and one of the <lb/>methods is taking care of health. This has led to an <lb/>increase in consumer interest in functional foods. <lb/>Its attractiveness arises from the possibility of <lb/>application by various consumer groups, such as <lb/>pregnant women, infants, children, school youth, <lb/>elderly individuals, and athletes. Additionally, its <lb/>preventive and therapeutic properties in the context <lb/>of many diseases are appealing. [11]. The presence <lb/>of phytosterols in its composition lowers cholesterol <lb/>levels, preventing atherosclerosis and type 2 diabetes. <lb/>[17,19]. The phenolic compounds contained in it have <lb/>antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, antibacterial, antiviral <lb/>and antithrombotic properties [14]. Functional food <lb/>plays a crucial role in the prevention of cardiovascular <lb/>diseases, protection of the central and peripheral <lb/>nervous systems, increase in the number of T <lb/></body>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">No 1 <lb/></note>

			<body>lymphocytes, and improvement of immune function. <lb/>[16, 26, 27]. <lb/>Additionally, it exhibits anticancer properties [9]. <lb/>Polyphenols in food lower blood pressure, improve <lb/>endothelial function, normalize lipid profile, and <lb/>minimize the risk of cardiovascular diseases [22]. <lb/>They improve the condition of blood vessels and <lb/>the circulatory system by factors vasoprotective [1]. <lb/>They also protect the heart during chemotherapy [6]. <lb/>Resveratrol and hydroxytyrosol inhibit platelet <lb/>aggregation and reduce venous inflammation [22]. <lb/>Xylooligosaccharides, as components of functional <lb/>food, regulate insulin secretion without increasing <lb/>the glucose level in the blood, thus preventing the <lb/>occurrence of insulin resistance and diabetes [20]. <lb/>They exhibit prebiotic properties, supporting <lb/>immunity [20]. Dietary fiber present in functional <lb/>products lowers blood pressure and may contribute to <lb/>reducing insulin resistance, which is a cause of arterial <lb/>hypertension [12, 18]. Continuous technological <lb/>progress and a regularly increasing assortment on the <lb/>food market encourage consumers to increase their <lb/>knowledge in this area. Thanks to this, more and more <lb/>people are aware of the health benefits of choosing <lb/>functional products. Due to their versatile applications <lb/>and increasing interest in them, an assessment of <lb/>knowledge and behaviors related to their consumption <lb/>has been undertaken. The study was conducted among <lb/>employees in the food industry, considering the fact <lb/>that they are responsible for its production. Their <lb/>awareness and behaviors in this regard are therefore <lb/>significant. <lb/>The aim of the study was to assess the state of <lb/>knowledge and eating habits related to functional <lb/>food among adults and to answer the question whether <lb/>there are differences between the state of knowledge <lb/>and habits among women and men. <lb/>MATERIAL AND METHODS <lb/>301 people took part in the study, including 181 <lb/>women and 120 men, average age -39.9 years. The <lb/>survey was conducted at the turn of July and August <lb/>2021 among employees of food industry plants in <lb/>Katowice. The inclusion criterion was employment in <lb/>departments directly involved in food production and <lb/>conscious consent to participate in the study, while the <lb/>exclusion criteria were employment in administrative <lb/>departments and lack of consent to participate in the <lb/>study. All study participants expressed their consent <lb/>to the use of its results. <lb/>The research tool was an original anonymous <lb/>survey questionnaire consisting of 25 questions, <lb/>including both single and multiple-choice questions. <lb/>The first part, referred to as the specification, included <lb/>questions about gender, year of birth, education, place <lb/>of residence, number of people in the household, type <lb/>of occupation and department of employment, as well <lb/>as the weight and height of the respondents. <lb/>The questions included in the pivotal part covered <lb/>knowledge about functional food and its consumption, <lb/>knowledge of understanding of definition of <lb/>functional food, recognizing correct statements about <lb/>it, sources of information on functional products, and <lb/>understanding the definition of prebiotics and their <lb/>role. Participants were also asked to self-assess their <lb/>knowledge of functional food. Consumption-related <lb/>questions verified information such as consumption <lb/>frequency, factors influencing its consumption, <lb/>place of purchase, and types of functional products <lb/>consumed. <lb/>Body weight and height were used to assess <lb/>participants&apos; BMI, following WHO criteria: <lb/>underweight &lt;18.5, normal weight -18.5-24.99, <lb/>overweight 25-29.99 and obesity ≥30 [23]. <lb/>Statistical analysis was performed based on <lb/>procedures available in the Statistica v. 13.3 program <lb/>(StatSoft Inc., Tulsa, OK, USA). The statistical <lb/>significance of differences between the frequencies of <lb/>qualitative variables was assessed based on the results <lb/>of the Pearson Chi-square test, the Yates correction <lb/>test and the Fisher exact test. The correlation analysis <lb/>was performed based on the Φ-Yule and V-Cramer <lb/>contingency coefficient. The interpretation of the <lb/>results was based on the criterion of statistical <lb/>significance p&lt;0.05. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>301 people took part in the study, including 60.1% <lb/>(N=181) women and 39.9% (N=120) men. The largest <lb/>group were people aged 41-50, 32.6% (N=98), with <lb/>secondary education, 37.9% (N=114), living in the city, <lb/>88.0% (N=265), living in multi-person households and <lb/>having normal body weight, 47.2% (N=142). <lb/>Knowledge of functional food <lb/>The answers to the question about the functional <lb/>food definition, statements about it, and sources where <lb/>to look for information on its daily consumption in the <lb/>study group in general and taking account of gender <lb/>are presented in Figures 1, 2 and 3. <lb/>When asked about the definition of functional <lb/>food, respondents most often indicated the correct <lb/>answer and noted that it is food that has a documented <lb/>beneficial impact on health, much bigger than that <lb/>resulting from the presence of nutrients considered <lb/>essential. This answer was given by 42.5% of people, <lb/>including more women (47.5%) than men (35.0%) <lb/>(Figure 1). When asked which statement related to <lb/>functional food, the respondents indicated that it <lb/>is food used in the daily diet that has an additional <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Knowledge and eating habits regarding functional food among adults <lb/></note>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">No 1 <lb/></note>

            <body>Figure 1. Knowledge of the definition of functional food, in total and by gender (N=301) <lb/>Figure 2. Responses to the question which statement pertains to functional food, total and by gender (N=301) <lb/>Figure 3. Responses to the question where to look for recommendations for daily consumption of functional food, total <lb/>and be gender (N=301) <lb/>positive effect on the human body, moreover, it <lb/>reduces the risk of disease development. This answer <lb/>was given by 37.2% of people, including more women <lb/>(42.5%) than men (29.2%) (Figure 2). When asked <lb/>where to look first for recommendations on the daily <lb/>consumption of functional food, the respondents <lb/>most often indicated that this information should be <lb/>included in a functional food label; this answer was <lb/>given by 58.8% of people, including more women <lb/>(61.3%) than men (55.0%) (Figure 3). <lb/>Answers to questions about the definition of <lb/>prebiotics and their functions in functional foods in <lb/>the studied group in general and taking account of <lb/>gender are presented in Figures 4 and 5. <lb/>In the question about the definition of a prebiotic, <lb/>respondents most often indicated that they are <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">E. Szczepańska, A. Liedtka, E. Czech <lb/></note>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">No 1 <lb/></note>

            <body>ingredients that stimulate the action of health-<lb/>promoting bacteria; this answer was given by 41.9% <lb/>of people, including slightly more women (43.1%) <lb/>than men (40.0%) (Figure 4). The surveyed people <lb/>most often pointed out that the role of probiotics is to <lb/>support the human immune system; this answer was <lb/>given by 66.1% of the respondents, including more <lb/>women (68.5%) than men (62.5%) (Figure 5). <lb/>When asked how the surveyed people assessed <lb/>their knowledge of functional food, 44,5% marked <lb/>a unsatisfactory level, more men (50.8%) than women <lb/>(40.3%) indicated such a response. An analysis of <lb/>gender differences in the level of knowledge regarding <lb/>functional foods showed a higher level of knowledge <lb/>among women compared to men, but these differences <lb/>are not statistically significant (p=0.14). <lb/>Habits related to functional food <lb/>The answers to the question about the frequency of <lb/>consumption of functional food and the health factors <lb/>encouraging its consumption in the study group in <lb/>general and by gender are presented in Table 2. The <lb/>respondents most often indicated that they did not <lb/>consume functional food (33.2%), this answer was <lb/>given by more men (40.0%) than women (28.7%). The <lb/>analysis mostly did not reveal statistically significant <lb/>gender differences in the frequency of consumption of <lb/>functional products; only the frequency of functional <lb/>product consumption (daily or several times a week) <lb/>was slightly (p=0.07) higher among women (Table 2). <lb/>To the question about factors encouraging food <lb/>consumption, 203 individuals responded, and among <lb/>the factors, the most frequently indicated was leading <lb/>a healthy lifestyle (56.2%). This response was more <lb/>commonly chosen by men (59.7%) than women <lb/>(54.2%). No significant differences were observed in <lb/>the frequency of indicating individual health factors <lb/>that encourage the consumption of functional products <lb/>(Table 2). <lb/>The answers to the question about features, apart <lb/>from a price, taken into account when choosing <lb/>functional food and about a place of purchase of <lb/>functional food, in the surveyed group in total and <lb/>taking into account gender, are presented in Table 3. <lb/>The surveyed people indicated that the ingredients <lb/>of the product is a feature they take into account when <lb/>choosing the food; this answer was given by 54.7% of <lb/>people, more women (59.5%) than men (45.8%). <lb/>Figure 4. Knowledge of the definition of prebiotics, total and by gender (N=301) <lb/>Figure 5. Knowledge of the role of probiotics in functional food, total and by gender (N=301) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Knowledge and eating habits regarding functional food among adults <lb/></note>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">No 1 <lb/></note>

            <body>Table 1. Gender-based differences in functional food knowledge (N=301) <lb/>Total <lb/>Women <lb/>Men <lb/>Test; p <lb/>Correlation <lb/>coefficients <lb/>N(%) <lb/>N(%) <lb/>N(%) <lb/>Level of knowledge of functional food <lb/>Unsatisfactory <lb/>134 (44.5) <lb/>73 (40.3) <lb/>61 (50.8) <lb/>Fi=5.46 <lb/>p= 0.14 <lb/>V c = 0.13 <lb/>Satisfactory <lb/>89 (29.6) <lb/>53 (29.3) <lb/>36 (30.0) <lb/>Good <lb/>72 (23.9) <lb/>51 (28.2) <lb/>21 (17.5) <lb/>Very good <lb/>6 (2.0) <lb/>4 (2.2) <lb/>2 (1.7) <lb/>N -number of observations; Fi -Fisher&apos;s exact test; p -level of statistical significance; Vc -V Cramer&apos;s contingency <lb/>coefficient <lb/>Table 2. Functional food consumption frequency (N=301) Health factors encouraging functional food consumption <lb/>(N=203) <lb/>Total <lb/>Woman <lb/>Men <lb/>Test; p <lb/>Correlation <lb/>coefficient <lb/>N (%) <lb/>N (%) <lb/>N (%) <lb/>Frequency of consumption of functional products <lb/>Daily <lb/>14 (4.7%) <lb/>9 (5.0%) <lb/>5 (4.2%) <lb/>χ y ² = 10.07 <lb/>p=0.07 <lb/>V c = 0.18 <lb/>Several times a week <lb/>57 (18.9%) <lb/>40 (22.1%) <lb/>17 (14.2%) <lb/>Several times a month <lb/>60 (19.9%) <lb/>39 (21.5%) <lb/>21 (17.5%) <lb/>Once a month <lb/>22 (7.3%) <lb/>9 (5.0%) <lb/>13 (10.8%) <lb/>Less than once a month <lb/>48 (16.0%) <lb/>32 (17.7%) <lb/>16 (13.3%) <lb/>Not at all <lb/>100 (33.2%) <lb/>52 (28.7%) <lb/>48 (40.0%) <lb/>Health factors encouraging the consumption of functional food (max 3 answers) <lb/>Possible answers <lb/>Total (N=203) <lb/>Woman (n=131) <lb/>Men (n=72) <lb/>The presence of own or family members&apos; chronic <lb/>diseases <lb/>41 (20.2%) <lb/>26 (19.9%) <lb/>15 (20.8%) <lb/>Food allergies or intolerances to certain food <lb/>ingredients in oneself or family members <lb/>49 (24.1%) <lb/>31 (23.7%) <lb/>18 (25.0%) <lb/>Preventive action against chronic diseases <lb/>84 (41.4) <lb/>57 (43.5%) <lb/>27 (37.5%) <lb/>Weight loss <lb/>81 (39.9%) <lb/>46 (35.1%) <lb/>35 (48.6%) <lb/>Leading a healthy lifestyle without any specific <lb/>reasons. <lb/>114 (56.2%) <lb/>71 (54.2%) <lb/>43 (59.7%) <lb/>Other, e.g. the desire to improve physical performance <lb/>3 (1.5%) <lb/>2 (1.5%) <lb/>1 (1.4%) <lb/>Most frequently indicated health factors <lb/>Prevention against <lb/>chronic diseases <lb/>No <lb/>119 (58.6%) <lb/>74 (56.5%) <lb/>45 (62.5%) <lb/>χ²=0.69 <lb/>p= 0.41 <lb/>Φ =0.06 <lb/>Yes <lb/>84 (41.4%) <lb/>57 (43.5%) <lb/>27 (37.5%) <lb/>Weight loss <lb/>No <lb/>122 (60.1%) <lb/>85 (64.9%) <lb/>37 (51.4%) <lb/>χ²=3.53 <lb/>p=0.06 <lb/>Φ = 0.13 <lb/>Yes <lb/>81 (39.9%) <lb/>46 (35.1%) <lb/>35 (48.6%) <lb/>Healthy lifestyle <lb/>No <lb/>89 (43.8%) <lb/>60 (45.8%) <lb/>29 (40.3%) <lb/>χ²= 0.58 <lb/>p= 0.45 <lb/>Φ =0.05 <lb/>Yes <lb/>114 (56.2%) <lb/>71 (54.2%) <lb/>43 (59.7%) <lb/>N -number of observations; χ y ² -Chi square test with Yates correction; χ² -Chi square test result; p -level of statistical <lb/>significance; Vc -V Cramer&apos;s contingency coefficient; Φ-Yule&apos;a -Mean Square Contingency Coefficient <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">E. Szczepańska, A. Liedtka, E. Czech <lb/></note>

			<page>40 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">No 1 <lb/></note>

            <body>The analysis did not reveal statistically significant <lb/>differences between genders in terms of the frequency <lb/>of indicating individual features of functional <lb/>products taken into account when purchasing <lb/>them. When purchasing functional food, a similar <lb/>percentage of women and men took into account <lb/>a product content, information about health benefits <lb/>and a recommendation from friends. <lb/>To the question of where they purchase functional <lb/>food, respondents most frequently indicated <lb/>supermarkets or shopping centers (54.0%), with more <lb/>men (59.1%) than women (51.2%) providing such <lb/>responses (Table 3). <lb/>The surveyed people indicated that they most often <lb/>eat cereals or muesli for breakfast (47.5%), this answer <lb/>was given by more women (55.8%) than men (35.0%) <lb/>and vegetable oils for dinner (37.2%), this answer was <lb/>given by more men (42.5%) than women (33.7%). The <lb/>respondents most often consume fruit, herbal teas <lb/>and herbal mixtures for dinner (28.2%), a comparable <lb/>percentage of women (29.8%) and men (25.8%), and <lb/>chocolate between main meals (31 %), this answer was <lb/>given by more women (31.5%) than men (30.3%). <lb/>Statistically significant differences were observed <lb/>in the frequency of consumption for breakfast cereals <lb/>and muesli (p&lt;0.001) as well as yogurts (p=0.01). <lb/>A similar, significant relationship was noted for the <lb/>frequency of yogurt consumption (p=0.03) and fruit, <lb/>herbal, and herbal blend teas (p=0.03) as snacks <lb/>between meals. For each of the mentioned products, <lb/>the frequency of consumption was higher in the female <lb/>group (Table 4). <lb/>Table 3. Gender-based analysis of determinants and purchase locations (N=203) <lb/>Criteria apart from price that guide you when choosing functional food (max 3 answers) <lb/>-<lb/>Total (N=203) <lb/>N (%) <lb/>Woman (N=131) <lb/>N (%) <lb/>Men (N=72) <lb/>N (%) <lb/>Product composition <lb/>111 (54.7) <lb/>78 (59.5) <lb/>33 (45.8) <lb/>Taste and smell <lb/>78 (38.4) <lb/>45 (34.4) <lb/>33 (45.8) <lb/>Info on the health benefits of product <lb/>88 (43.6) <lb/>60 (45.8) <lb/>28 (39.4) <lb/>Content of additional nutrients <lb/>57 (28.1) <lb/>37 (28.2) <lb/>20 (27.8) <lb/>Recommendations of friends <lb/>81 (40.1) <lb/>49 (37.7) <lb/>32 (44.4) <lb/>Product brand <lb/>15 (7.4) <lb/>7 (5.3) <lb/>8 (11.1) <lb/>Nice packaging <lb/>14 (7.0) <lb/>7 (5.4) <lb/>7 (9.9) <lb/>Advertising and marketing <lb/>8 (3.9) <lb/>7 (5.3) <lb/>1 (1.4) <lb/>Other e.g. fashion <lb/>3 (1.5) <lb/>2 (1.5) <lb/>1 (1.4) <lb/>Total <lb/>Woman <lb/>Men <lb/>Test; p <lb/>Correlation <lb/>coefficient <lb/>N (%) <lb/>N (%) <lb/>N (%) <lb/>Most frequently indicated characteristics of products <lb/>Product composition <lb/>No <lb/>92 (45.3) <lb/>53 (40.5) <lb/>39 (54.2) <lb/>χ²=3.52 <lb/>p=0.06 <lb/>Φ = 0.13 <lb/>Yes <lb/>111 (54.7) <lb/>78 (59.5) <lb/>33 (45.8) <lb/>Information about the health benefits of <lb/>specific products <lb/>No <lb/>114 (56.4) <lb/>71 (54.2) <lb/>43 (60.6) <lb/>χ²=0.76 <lb/>p= 0.38 <lb/>Φ =0.06 <lb/>Yes <lb/>88 (43.6) <lb/>60 (45.8) <lb/>28 (39.4) <lb/>Recommendations of friends <lb/>No <lb/>121 (59.9) <lb/>81 (62.3) <lb/>40 (55.6) <lb/>χ²=0.88 <lb/>p= 0.35 <lb/>Φ =0.07 <lb/>Yes <lb/>81 (40.1) <lb/>49 (37.7) <lb/>32 (44.4) <lb/>Place where you most often buy functional food <lb/>Small shops near the place of residence <lb/>56 (27.7) <lb/>43 (32.8) <lb/>13 (18.3) <lb/>χ y ² =5.59 <lb/>p= 0.13 <lb/>V c = 0.16 <lb/>Supermarkets or shopping centers <lb/>109 (54.0) <lb/>67 (51.2) <lb/>42 (59.1) <lb/>Stores specializing in functional food <lb/>18 (8.9) <lb/>11 (8.4) <lb/>7 (9.9) <lb/>Online stores specializing in functional food <lb/>19 (9.4) <lb/>10 (7.6) <lb/>9 (12.7) <lb/>N -number of observations; χ² -Chi square test result; χ y ² -Chi square test with Yates correction; p -level of statistical <lb/>significance; Vc -V Cramer&apos;s contingency coefficient; Φ-Yule&apos;a -Mean Square Contingency Coefficient <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Knowledge and eating habits regarding functional food among adults <lb/></note>

			<page>41 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">No 1 <lb/></note>

            <body>DISCUSSION <lb/>Nowadays, there is an increase in consumer&apos;s <lb/>awareness of health issues. The consequence of which <lb/>is an increased interest in functional food, which <lb/>helps to meet this task, both in terms of improving <lb/>health as well as improving the quality and length of <lb/>life. The analysis of my own research results showed <lb/>that 42.5% of the respondents pointed to the correct <lb/>answer defining functional food as food having <lb/>a documented beneficial effect on health beyond that <lb/>resulting from the presence of nutrients considered <lb/>essential. In turn, in a study conducted by Demir Hüly <lb/>among students of nutrition and dietetics, 46.3% of <lb/>Table 4. Common functional product consumption across meals (N=203) <lb/>Total <lb/>Woman <lb/>Men <lb/>Test; p <lb/>Correlation <lb/>coefficient <lb/>N (%) <lb/>N (%) <lb/>N (%) <lb/>Most commonly consumed functional products for breakfast <lb/>Cereals and muesli <lb/>No <lb/>158 (52.5) <lb/>80 (44.2) <lb/>78 (65.0) <lb/>χ²=12.52 <lb/>p&lt;0.001 <lb/>Φ =0.20 <lb/>Yes <lb/>143 (47.5) <lb/>101 (55.8) <lb/>42 (35.0) <lb/>Yogurts <lb/>No <lb/>167 (55.5) <lb/>90 (49.7) <lb/>77 (64.2) <lb/>χ²=6.09 <lb/>p=0.01 <lb/>Φ = 0.14 <lb/>Yes <lb/>134 (44.5) <lb/>91 (50.3) <lb/>43 (35.8) <lb/>Crispbread and waffles <lb/>No <lb/>216 (71.8) <lb/>133 (73.5) <lb/>83 (69.2) <lb/>χ²=0.66 <lb/>p= 0.42 <lb/>Φ =0.05 <lb/>Yes <lb/>85 (28.2) <lb/>48 (26.5) <lb/>37 (30.8) <lb/>Most commonly consumed functional products for lunch <lb/>Low-fat enriched cheeses, curds and kefir <lb/>No <lb/>273 (90.7) <lb/>166 (91.7) <lb/>107 (89.2) <lb/>χ²=0.55 <lb/>p=0.46 <lb/>Φ =0.04 <lb/>Yes <lb/>28 (9.3) <lb/>15 (8.3) <lb/>13 (10.8) <lb/>Juices, nectars,and multivitamin fruit <lb/>drinks <lb/>No <lb/>249 (82.7) <lb/>148 (81.8) <lb/>101 (84.2) <lb/>χ²=0.29 <lb/>p= 0.59 <lb/>Φ =0.03 <lb/>Yes <lb/>52 (17.3) <lb/>33 (18.2) <lb/>19 (15.8) <lb/>Vegetable oils <lb/>No <lb/>189 (62.8) <lb/>120 (66.3) <lb/>69 (57.5) <lb/>χ²=2.39 <lb/>p= 0.12 <lb/>Φ =0.09 <lb/>Yes <lb/>112 (37.2) <lb/>61 (33.7) <lb/>51 (42.5) <lb/>Most commonly consumed functional products for dinner <lb/>Crispbread and waffles <lb/>No <lb/>230 (76.4) <lb/>141 (77.9) <lb/>89 (74.2) <lb/>χ²=0.56 <lb/>p=0.46 <lb/>Φ =0.04 <lb/>Yes <lb/>71 (23.6) <lb/>40 (22.1) <lb/>31 (25.8) <lb/>Fruit teas, herbal teas, herb blends <lb/>No <lb/>216 (71.8) <lb/>127 (70.2) <lb/>89 (74.2) <lb/>χ²=0.57 <lb/>p= 0.45 <lb/>Φ =0.04 <lb/>Yes <lb/>85 (28.2) <lb/>54 (29.8) <lb/>31 (25.8) <lb/>Low-fat enriched cheeses. curds, and <lb/>kefir <lb/>No <lb/>244 (81.1) <lb/>142 (78.5) <lb/>102 (85.0) <lb/>χ²=2.01 <lb/>p= 0.16 <lb/>Φ =0.08 <lb/>Yes <lb/>57 (18.9) <lb/>39 (21.5) <lb/>18 (15.0) <lb/>Most commonly consumed functional products between main meals <lb/>Yogurts <lb/>No <lb/>228 (75.7) <lb/>129 (71.3) <lb/>99 (82.5) <lb/>χ²=4.95 <lb/>p=0.03 <lb/>Φ = 0.13 <lb/>Yes <lb/>73 (24.3) <lb/>52 (28.7) <lb/>21 (17.5) <lb/>Fruit teas, herbal teas, herb blends <lb/>No <lb/>218 (72.4) <lb/>123 (68.0) <lb/>95 (79.2) <lb/>χ²=4.54 <lb/>p=0.03 <lb/>Φ = 0.12 <lb/>Yes <lb/>83 (27.6) <lb/>58 (32.0) <lb/>25 (20.8) <lb/>Chocolate <lb/>No <lb/>207 (69.0) <lb/>124 (68.5) <lb/>83 (69.7) <lb/>χ²=0.05 <lb/>p=0.82 <lb/>Φ =0.01 <lb/>Yes <lb/>93 (31.0) <lb/>57 (31.5) <lb/>36 (30.3) <lb/>N -number of observations; χ² -Chi square test result; p -level of statistical significance; Φ-Yule&apos;a -Mean Square <lb/>Contingency Coefficient <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">E. Szczepańska, A. Liedtka, E. Czech <lb/></note>

			<page>42 <lb/></page>

            <note place="headnote">No 1 <lb/></note>

			<body>fourth-year students associate functional food with <lb/>functional products and 43.9% with food products that <lb/>have a beneficial effect on the body. However, in the <lb/>first-year group, 25.6% associate it with food products <lb/>that have a beneficial effect on the body, 23.0% with <lb/>functional products, and 41% did not answer this <lb/>question [10]. Meanwhile, in the study by Balogh et al. <lb/>[5] conducted among 168 consumers, 91.7% of them <lb/>indicated the correct definition of functional food as <lb/>one that has detectable positive effects on one or more <lb/>important body functions. However, in the first-year <lb/>group, 25.6% associate it with food products that have <lb/>a beneficial effect on the body, 23.0% with functional <lb/>products, and 41% did not answer this question [10]. <lb/>Meanwhile, in a study by Balogh et al. conducted <lb/>among 168 consumers, 91.7% of them indicated the <lb/>correct definition of functional food as one that has <lb/>detectable positive effects on one or more important <lb/>body functions [5]. <lb/>The results of our own research showed that 37.2% <lb/>of people indicated that functional food is one that, <lb/>when used in the daily diet, has an additional positive <lb/>effect on the human body, including reducing the <lb/>risk of disease development. This is consistent with <lb/>the results of the research by the Interactive Market <lb/>Research Institute, conducted among 1,000 people <lb/>over 15 years of age, where a similar answer was given <lb/>by 50% of respondents, characterizing functional food <lb/>as used in a daily diet and having an additional positive <lb/>effect on the human body, including reducing the risk <lb/>of developing a disease. [21]. Author&apos;s research shows <lb/>that the largest percentage of respondents (43.2%) <lb/>rate their knowledge of functional food as sufficient. <lb/>In turn, the results of the study by Zabrocki and <lb/>Suszek show that 50.7% of the people participating in <lb/>the study describe their level of knowledge as rather <lb/>small and fragmentary [28]. As the results of our <lb/>own research show, 41.9% respondents most often <lb/>indicated the correct definition of a prebiotic. Students <lb/>of the Medical University of Wrocław demonstrated <lb/>greater knowledge in this area, with 85% correctly <lb/>defining prebiotics [13] Also in the study by Turgul <lb/>Ersak et al. conducted among obstetricians, 61.8% <lb/>of them working for less than 12 years and 60% of <lb/>them working for 12 years or more were able to define <lb/>prebiotics correctly as compounds that stimulate the <lb/>growth and activity of beneficial microorganisms <lb/>[25]. In our own study, 66.1% of respondents declared <lb/>that the main function of probiotics is to support the <lb/>human immune system. As a comparison, in the study <lb/>by Jamy-Kmiecik et al., 52.4% of people gave correct <lb/>answers, stating that probiotics have an immunological <lb/>and digestive protective function [13]. However, in the <lb/>study by Babin et al. conducted among students and <lb/>lecturers of Sechenov University in Moscow, it was <lb/>shown that the surveyed people knew that probiotics <lb/>have a beneficial effect on digestion (98% of lecturers <lb/>and 95% of students), were aware of the role of <lb/>probiotics in the functioning of the immune system <lb/>( 93% of lecturers and 85% of students), in the fight <lb/>against obesity (72% of lecturers and 66% of students) <lb/>and in the prevention of respiratory (76% of lecturers <lb/>and 56% of students) and urinary tract infections (65% <lb/>of lecturers and 63% of students). However, they are <lb/>less likely to associate the impact of probiotics on <lb/>heart health (52% of lecturers and 56% of students) [4]. <lb/>According to the study by Betz et al. conducted among <lb/>patients from hospitals in Chicago, 60% of those who <lb/>knew the correct definition of probiotics believed that <lb/>they had a beneficial effect on heart [7]. <lb/>The author&apos;s study shows that most people do <lb/>not consume functional food. However, taking into <lb/>account the fact that only 42.5% of respondents are <lb/>able to indicate the correct definition of functional <lb/>food, its consumption at least several times a month <lb/>by 43.5% of all the respondents can be considered <lb/>sufficient. This result contradicts the findings of <lb/>a study conducted by Akhter and Dil Bahadur, where <lb/>37% of the participants indicated that they consume <lb/>functional food daily <lb/>According to the author&apos;s research, the factor <lb/>encouraging people to consume functional foods is the <lb/>desire to lead a healthy lifestyle (56.2% of responses) <lb/>and to take preventive measures against chronic <lb/>diseases (41.4% of responses). In turn, in the study <lb/>by Krupa and Dec, the most frequently mentioned <lb/>factors were health care, affordable price and taste; <lb/>such answers were given by 51% and 39% of people, <lb/>respectively [15]. Altun et al. conducted a study on <lb/>a group of 550 dietitians who graduated from the <lb/>Faculty of Nutrition and Dietetics of universities in <lb/>Turkey. As the authors showed, during the COVID-19 <lb/>pandemic, 38.5% of them consumed functional food <lb/>to maintain intestinal health, 36.8% wanted to lead <lb/>a healthy lifestyle and 34.9% to protect themselves <lb/>against COVID-19 [3]. <lb/>Our own research indicates that, when choosing <lb/>functional products, the composition of the product is <lb/>of the utmost importance, in addition to price -this <lb/>answer was given by 54.7% of respondents. Similar <lb/>results were obtained in research by the Market <lb/>Research Institute, where the same answer was given <lb/>by 49% of respondents [21]. According to our own <lb/>research, the majority of individuals obtain information <lb/>about functional food from labels on the packaging of <lb/>such food (58.8%). Quantitative research by Krupa <lb/>and Dec conducted among customers of grocery <lb/>stores also shows that the most frequently indicated <lb/>source of information about the biological value of <lb/>these products are the labels on the packaging [15]. As <lb/>our own research shows, 54.0% of individuals most <lb/>commonly purchase functional food in supermarkets <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Knowledge and eating habits regarding functional food among adults <lb/></note>

			<page>43 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">No 1 <lb/></note>

<body>or shopping centers. However, in a study by Deborah et <lb/>al. conducted among a group of 427 Italian consumers, <lb/>as many as 90% indicated supermarkets as the place of <lb/>purchase for this type of food [8]. <lb/>Our own research, similar to a study conducted by <lb/>the Interactive Market Research Institute, indicates <lb/>variations in the consumption of functional products <lb/>depending on the type of meal. Both studies show that <lb/>the most frequently consumed products for breakfast <lb/>are cereals or muesli. For lunch, people most often <lb/>choose vegetable oils, juices, nectars and multivitamin <lb/>drinks. However, for dinner, crispbread and wafers are <lb/>preferred, and between main meals, chocolate, juices, <lb/>nectars, multivitamin drinks, and yogurts are reached <lb/>for [21]. In contrast, in the study by Krupa and Dec, <lb/>fruit and vegetable preparations, probiotic yoghurts, <lb/>cereals and bakery products were indicated as the most <lb/>commonly consumed products. However, in this study <lb/>the consumption of these products was not divided in <lb/>relation to meals [15]. <lb/>CONCLUSIONS <lb/>Knowledge of functional foods is unsatisfactory, <lb/>and no differences in the knowledge of women and <lb/>men have been observed. <lb/>The consumption of functional food is generally <lb/>low, and no differences in its consumption have been <lb/>observed between women and men. <lb/>It seems important to continue spreading nutritional <lb/>education regarding the role of functional food in both <lb/>prevention and treatment of many diseases. <lb/></body>

            <div type="conflict">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors declare no conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

            <listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Adriouch S., Lampuré A., Nechba Baudry J., Assmann <lb/>K., Kesse-Guyot E., Hercberg S., Scalbert A., Touvier <lb/>M., Fezeu K.L.: Prospective Association between <lb/>Total and Specific Dietary Polyphenol Intakes and <lb/>Cardiovascular Disease Risk in the Nutrinet-Santé <lb/>French Cohort. Nutrients 2018;10(11):1-15 doi:10.3390/ <lb/>nu10111587. <lb/>2. Akhter A., Dil Bahadur R.: Healthy Foods as Proxy <lb/>for Functional Foods: Consumers&apos; Awareness, <lb/>Perception, and Demand for Natural Functional <lb/>Foods in Pakistan. Int. J. Food Sci. 2019;2019:1-12 <lb/>doi:10.1155/2019/6390650. <lb/>3. Altun H.K., Ermumcu M.S.K., Kurklu N.S.: Evaluation <lb/>of dietary supplement, functional food and herbal <lb/>medicine use by dietitians during the COVID-19 <lb/>pandemic. Public Health Nutr 2020;24(5):861-869 <lb/>doi:10.1017/S1368980020005297. <lb/>4. Babina K., Salikhova D., Polyakova M., Zaytsev <lb/>A., Egiazaryan A., Novozhilova N.: Knowledge and <lb/>Attitude towards Probiotics among Dental Students <lb/>and Teachers: A Cross-Sectional Survey. Dent. J <lb/>2023;11(5):1-13 doi:10.3390/dj11050119. <lb/>5. Balogh T., Kőszegi I., Hoyk E.: Knowledge of functional <lb/>foods by consumers. Gradus 2020;7(2):155-160 doi: <lb/>10.47833/2020.2.AGR.030. <lb/>6. Barylski M., Filipiak K.J., Okopień B., Szymański F.M., <lb/>Wożakowska-Kapłon B., Mamcarz A.: Stanowisko <lb/>grupy ekspertów wsparte przez Sekcję Farmakoterapii <lb/>Sercowo-Naczyniowej <lb/>Polskiego <lb/>Towarzystwa <lb/>Kardiologicznego dotyczące miejsca standaryzowanej <lb/>kompozycji polifenoli z bergamoty w terapii <lb/>dyslipidemii oraz jej innego potencjalnego zastosowania <lb/>w praktyce klinicznej [Expert group consensus <lb/>endorsed by the Polish Cardiac Society Working Group <lb/>on Cardiovascular Pharmacotherapy on the place of <lb/>a standardized bergamot polyphenolic fraction in the <lb/>treatment of dyslipidaemia and its other potential use in <lb/>clinical practice]. Folia Cardiol. 2018;13(3):222-235 doi: <lb/>10.5603/FC.2018.0039 (in Polish). <lb/>7. Betz M., Uzueta A., Rasmussen H., Gregoire M., <lb/>Vanderwall C., Witowich G.: Knowledge, use and <lb/>perceptions of probiotics and prebiotics in hospitalised <lb/>patients. Nutr Diet 2015;72:261-266 doi: 10.1111/1747-<lb/>0080.12177. <lb/>8. Bentivoglio D., Rotordam M., Giacomo S., Chiaraluce <lb/>G., Finco A.: Understanding consumption choices of <lb/>innovative products: an outlook on the Italian functional <lb/>food market. AIMS Agric. Food 2021;6(3):818-837 doi: <lb/>10.3934/agrfood.2021050. <lb/>9. Cornwall S, Cull G, Joske D, Ghassemifar R.: Green tea <lb/>polyphenol &quot;epigallocatechin-3-gallate&quot;, differentially <lb/>induces apoptosis in CLL B-and T-Cells but not in <lb/>healthy B-and T-Cells in a dose dependant manner. Leuk <lb/>Res 2016;51:56-61 doi: 10.1016/j.leukres.2016.10.011. <lb/>10. Demir H.: Üniversite Öğrencilerinin Fonksiyonel <lb/>Gıdalar Konusundaki Farkındalıklarının Araştırılması <lb/>[Research of Awareness of University Students on <lb/>Functional Foods]. HSP 2018;5(2):154-160 doi: 10.17681/ <lb/>hsp.396902 (in Turkish). <lb/>11. Grochowicz J., Fabisiak A.: Żywność funkcjonalna -<lb/>aspekty prawne i znaczenie wybranych składników <lb/>bioaktywnych[Functional Food -Legal Aspects <lb/>and Significance of Selected Bioactive Ingredients]. <lb/>Zeszyty Naukowe Uczelni Vistula 2018;60(3):143-153 <lb/>(in Polish). <lb/>12. Houston M.: Nutrition and nutraceutical supplements for <lb/>the treatment of hypertension: part II. J Clin Hypertens <lb/>2013;15(11):845-851 doi: 10.1111/jch.12212. <lb/>13. Jama-Kmiecik A. Gil K., Frej-Mądrzak M., Sarowska J., <lb/>Choroszczy-Król I.: Znajomość roli pro-i prebiotyków <lb/>w profilaktyce zdrowia i leczeniu chorób w świetle <lb/>badan [Knowledge of the role of pro and prebiotics <lb/>in health prevention and treatment of diseases in the <lb/>light of research]. Prawnicza I Ekonomiczna Biblioteka <lb/>Cyfrowa. 2020; doi: 10.34616/23.20.115. <lb/>14. Joseph S.V, Edirisinghe I, Burton-Freeman B.M.: Fruit <lb/>Polyphenols: A Review of Anti-inflammatory Effects <lb/>in Humans. Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr 2016;56(3):419-444 <lb/>doi: 10.1080/10408398.2013.767221. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">E. Szczepańska, A. Liedtka, E. Czech <lb/></note>

			<page>44 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>No 1 <lb/>15. Krupa J., Dec B.: Preferencje konsumenckie na rynku <lb/>żywności wzbogaconej i ekologicznej w aspekcie <lb/>zdrowego stylu życia [Consumer Preferences in the <lb/>Enriched and Organic Food Market in the Context of <lb/>a Healthy Lifestyle]. In: Krupa J., Dec B. eds. Kreowanie <lb/>przedsiębiorczości w turystyce na terenach wiejskich <lb/>oraz ochrona środowiska i dziedzictwa kulturowego <lb/>[Creating enterepreneurship in tourism in rural areas <lb/>and protection of the environment and cultural heritage]. <lb/>Dynów, Wyd. Związek Gmin Turystycznych Pogórza <lb/>Dynowskiego, 2015. <lb/>16. Mangels D.R., Mohler E.R.: Catechins as potential <lb/>mediators of cardiovascular health. Arterioscler <lb/>Thromb Vasc Biol 2017;37(5):757-776 doi: 10.1161/ <lb/>ATVBAHA.117.309048. <lb/>17. Naruse R, Hori K, Terasawa T, Hara K., Suetsugu <lb/>M., Takebayashi K., Morita K., Aso Y., Inukai T.: <lb/>Alterations of plant sterols, lathosterol, oxidative <lb/>stress and inflammatory markers after the combination <lb/>therapy of ezetimibe and statin drugs in type 2 diabetic <lb/>patients. Obes Res Clin Pract 2015;9(1):67-74 doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.orcp.2014.02.001 <lb/>18. Pal S, Radavelli-Bagatini S.: Effects of psyllium <lb/>on metabolic syndrome risk factors. Obes <lb/>Rev <lb/>2012;13(11):1034-1047 <lb/>doi: 10.1111/j.1467-<lb/>789X.2012.01020.x. <lb/>19. Ras R. T., van der Schouw Y. T., Trautwein E. A., <lb/>Sioen I., Dalmeijer G. W., Zock P. L., Beulens J. W. J.: <lb/>Intake of phytosterols from natural sources and risk <lb/>of cardiovascular disease in the European Prospective <lb/>Investigation into Cancer and Nutrition-the Netherlands <lb/>(EPIC-NL) population. Eur J Prev Cardiol 2015; <lb/>22(8):1067-1075 doi: 10.1177/2047487314554864. <lb/>20. Samanta A. K, Jayapal N., Jayaram C., Roy S.: <lb/>Xylooligosaccharides as prebiotics from agricultural <lb/>by-products: production and applications. Bioact. <lb/>Carbohydr. Diet. Fibre 2015;5(1):62-71 doi: 10.1016/j. <lb/>bcdf.2014.12.003. <lb/>21. Siewierska M. Interaktywny Instytut Badań <lb/>Rynkowych. Żywność funkcjonalna 2012 -czyli co ma <lb/>Polak na talerzu? Żywność funkcjonalna 2012 Raport. <lb/>Warszawa. <lb/>22. Szczepańska E., Białek-Dratwa A., Janota B., Kowalski <lb/>O.: Dietary Therapy in Prevention of Cardiovascular <lb/>Disease (CVD)-Tradition or Modernity? A Review of <lb/>the Latest Approaches to Nutrition in CVD. Nutrients <lb/>2022;14(13):1-15 doi: 10.3390/nu14132649. <lb/>23. Tarnowski W., Jaworski P.: Operacje bariatryczne <lb/>w praktyce [Bariatric operations in clinical practice]. <lb/>Gastroenterol. Klin 2018;10(3) 93-101 doi: 10.5603/ <lb/>gek.60328 (in Polish). <lb/>24. Trziszka T, Rozanski H.: Żywność funkcjonalna <lb/>i nutraceutyki w profilaktyce chorób cywilizacyjnych <lb/>[Functional foods and nutraceuticals in prevention of <lb/>civilization diseases]. HERBALISM. 2015;1(1):9-19 <lb/>doi: 10.12775/HERB.2015.001. <lb/>25. Tugrul Ersak D., Kara O., Tanacan A., Ersak B., <lb/>Menekse Beser D., Sahin D.: A New Awareness: <lb/>Probiotic, Prebiotic and Microbiota Knowledge and <lb/>Attitude of Obstetricians. Obstet Gynaecol Reprod Med <lb/>2023;29(2):107-113 doi: 10.21613/GORM.2022.1395. <lb/>26. Xiao L., Liu L., Guo X., Zhang S., Wang J., Zhou F., Liu <lb/>L., Tang Y., Yao P.: Quercetin attenuates high fat diet-<lb/>induced atherosclerosis in apolipoprotein E knockout <lb/>mice: A critical role of NADPH oxidase. Food Chem <lb/>Toxicol 2017;105:22-33 doi: 10.1016/j.fct.2017.03.048 <lb/>27. Xicota L., Rodriguez-Morato J., Dierssen M., de la <lb/>Torre R.: Potential role of (Epigallocatechin-3-Gallate <lb/>(EGCG) in the secondary prevention of Alzheimer <lb/>disease. Curr Drug Targets 2017;18(2), 174-195 doi: 10.2 <lb/>174/1389450116666150825113655. <lb/>28. Zabrocki R., Suszek A.: Postawy i zachowania <lb/>konsumentów w wieku 60+ wobec żywności <lb/>funkcjonalnej [Attitudes and Behaviors of Consumers <lb/>aged 60+ towards Functional Food]. Marketing <lb/>i Zarządzanie 2018;3(53):219-232 doi: 10.18276/ <lb/>miz.2018.53-19 <lb/></listBibl>

			<front>Received: 06.11.2023 <lb/>Revised: 25.01.2024 <lb/>Accepted: 29.01.2024 <lb/>Knowledge and eating habits regarding functional food among adults <lb/>This article is available in Open Access model and licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial 3.0.Poland License (CC-BY-NC) <lb/>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/pl/deed.en) </front>


	</text>
</tei>
