<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention, Vol 25 971 <lb/>DOI:10.31557/APJCP.2024.25.3.971 <lb/>Diagnostic Value of the Neutrophil-to-Lymphocyte Ratio in Predicting Ovarian Cancer <lb/>Asian Pac J Cancer Prev, 25 (3), 971-976 <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Ovarian cancer (EOC) ranks as the seventh most <lb/>prevalent cancer globally and is the deadliest among <lb/>gynecological malignancies [1]. Most patients are <lb/>diagnosed with advanced-stage disease, which is <lb/>associated with significant morbidity and mortality <lb/>[2]. EOC is a silent malignancy, and survival rates <lb/>strongly depend on early detection. The discovery of <lb/>reliable EOC biomarkers plays a crucial role in disease <lb/>management and greatly impacts patient prognosis [3]. <lb/>Population-based screening has been ineffective, but <lb/>new approaches for early detection and prevention are <lb/>currently being developed [4]. Following its discovery <lb/></body>

			<front>Abstract <lb/>Purpose: This research aims to establish a neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio (NLR) threshold and evaluate its <lb/>diagnostic accuracy compared to pathological criteria for diagnosing Epithelial Ovarian Cancer (EOC). Methods: We <lb/>conducted a cross-sectional study at Imam Hossein Hospital involving 204 women aged 18 and older with confirmed <lb/>ovarian mass based on pathology. We recorded clinical, pathological, and preoperative blood count data, including <lb/>neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio (NLR). Patients were categorized into malignant and benign ovarian mass groups based <lb/>on postoperative pathology. The power of NLR to diagnosis of EOC was evaluated using ROC curve. Results: At total, <lb/>204 patients (Benign 75.5% vs. Malignant 24.5%) were included in the analysis with mean age of 54.26 ±12.04 yrs in <lb/>malignant and 46.31±13.21 in benign. In all cases, the proportion of patients with the following tumor markers HE4 <lb/>(&gt;140 Pm), CA 125 (&gt; 35U/Ml) and CEA (&gt;5 ng/Ml) were 52.45%, 41.67% and 3.43%, respectively, and proportion <lb/>of abnormal tumor markers was statistically higher in malignant group compared to benign mass (p &lt;0.05). Odds of <lb/>having higher NLR levels in the malignancy group was higher than benign group (e.g., OR of 4.45 for NLR in quartile 4 <lb/>vs. quartile 1). According to model selection criteria, the full model with including NLR level and age, BMI and tumor <lb/>markers has best performance for diagnosis of malignancy (AUC =0.87). Conclusion: High NLR in combination with <lb/>tumor markers including CA125, HE4 and CEA were associated with malignancy in patients with ovarian mass. More <lb/>attention and further examinations should be devoted for patients with ovarian mass having high NLR and abnormal <lb/>tumor markers levels to detect the probable malignancy as soon as possible. <lb/>Keywords: Neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio-epithelial ovarian cancer-tumor marker <lb/>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Evaluation of the Cutoff Point and Diagnostic Value of the <lb/>Neutrophil-to-Lymphocyte Ratio in Predicting Ovarian Cancer <lb/>Compared to Pathological Findings <lb/></front>

			<body>about 40 years ago, carbohydrate antigen 125 (CA125) <lb/>has been widely used but remains the most concerning <lb/>biomarker in EOC screening. However, there is still <lb/>controversy regarding its role in clinical practice. CA125 <lb/>is not sufficiently reliable for diagnosing early-stage <lb/>EOC. On the other hand, CA125 has been a valuable <lb/>marker for assessing treatment efficacy and prognosis. <lb/>We still have limited knowledge about its biological <lb/>role, and multiple studies have shown its involvement in <lb/>EOC development and progression [5]. While CA125 is <lb/>a classical EOC biomarker, current research aims to find <lb/>alternative biomarkers using proteomic or metabolomic <lb/>approaches, utilizing non-invasive or minimally invasive <lb/>sources such as urine, serum, plasma, tissue, ascites, or <lb/></body>

			<front>Editorial Process: Submission:10/24/2023 Acceptance:02/29/2024 <lb/>1 <lb/>Preventative Gynecology Research Center, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran. 2 Department of <lb/>Paramedicine, Amol School of Paramedical sciences, Mazandaran University of Medical Sciences, Sari, Iran. 3 Department of <lb/>Obstetrics and Gynecology, Preventative Gynecology Research Center, Imam Hossein Hospital, Shahid Beheshti University of <lb/>Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran. 4 Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Imam Hossein Hospital, Shahid Beheshti University <lb/>of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran. *For Correspondence: amiri.f.986@gmail.com <lb/>Maryam Sadat Hosseini 1 , Fatemeh Amiri 1 *, Maysam Rezapour 2 , Tahereh Ashraf <lb/>Ganjoei 3 , Farah Farzaneh 1 , Maliheh Arab 1 , Maryam Talayeh 4 , Rezvaneh Beheshti <lb/>Rooy 1 , Fatemeh Hadi 1 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Maryam Sadat Hosseini et al <lb/>Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention, Vol 25 <lb/></note>

			<page>972 <lb/></page>

			<body>exosomes. Metabolism and metabolites play key roles <lb/>in cancer biology, and their significance in the discovery <lb/>of biomarkers cannot be overlooked [3]. Inflammatory <lb/>markers, such as the neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio <lb/>(NLR), have been studied in various cancers prior to <lb/>surgery [6]. NLR is a useful factor in evaluating immune <lb/>status [7], and is linked to epithelial ovarian cancers <lb/>(EOCs), making it a useful tool for predicting post-<lb/>treatment follow-up. Elevated NLR levels are correlated <lb/>with an unfavorable prognosis. The results of conducted <lb/>studies have shown that NLR may be a good marker for <lb/>use in EOC screening [6]. <lb/>Hence, it is crucial to find a solution to avoid false-<lb/>negative outcomes resulting from low CA125 levels, <lb/>specifically in the detection of EOC during regular <lb/>physical examinations. Building upon the information <lb/>mentioned above, this research project seeks to establish <lb/>a threshold value for the neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio, <lb/>in comparison to pathological criteria, for diagnosing <lb/>EOC in patients with suspected EOC. Subsequently, the <lb/>study aims to assess the sensitivity, specificity, positive <lb/>predictive value, and negative predictive value of the <lb/>determined threshold in relation to the pathological criteria <lb/>for diagnosing EOC. <lb/>Materials and Methods <lb/>This cross-sectional study was conducted in 2022 at <lb/>Imam Hossein Hospital and included 204 women aged <lb/>18 and above who were diagnosed with ovarian mass <lb/>confirmed by pathology. The inclusion criteria consisted <lb/>of women 18 years and older with an ovarian mass who <lb/>required surgery and had malignant or benign disease <lb/>confirmed by pathology. The exclusion criteria were <lb/>concurrent infectious diseases, autoimmune diseases, <lb/>current or history of extra-ovarian malignancy, systemic <lb/>hematological disorders and thrombosis as criteria for <lb/>withdrawal from the study. <lb/>After obtaining the ethical code from Shahid Beheshti <lb/>University of Medical Sciences, and receiving approval <lb/>for the study protocol, informed consent was obtained <lb/>from the patients. At the time of initial diagnosis, clinical <lb/>and pathological information of the patients was recorded. <lb/>After surgery, the pathology diagnosis determined <lb/>the benign or malignant nature of their ovarian mass. <lb/>Additionally, preoperative blood count values, including <lb/>absolute neutrophil count, absolute lymphocyte count and <lb/>NLR (neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio), were recorded <lb/>and calculated for the purpose of this study. NLR was <lb/>calculated by dividing the absolute neutrophil count by <lb/>the absolute lymphocyte count. The study variables were <lb/>determined based on the patients&apos; clinical records, which <lb/>included age, gravidity, BMI, menstruation, involvement <lb/>of the right or left ovary, family history of cancer, diabetes, <lb/>hypertension, and hypothyroidism morbidity. In addition, <lb/>laboratory tests were conducted to measure complete <lb/>blood cell count (platelet, neutrophil, and lymphocyte <lb/>counts), as well as Ca_125, CEA, and HE4 tumor markers. <lb/>These variables were considered important for the analysis <lb/>and evaluation of the study. <lb/>Based on the postoperative pathological results <lb/>reviewed by a trained pathologist, enrolled patients were <lb/>divided into two groups, including 50 malignant and 154 <lb/>benign ovaraion cancer. <lb/>Continuous variable data were reported as means ± <lb/>standard deviation, while categorical variable data were <lb/>presented as frequencies and percentage. For comparisons <lb/>between two groups of benign and malignant masses, <lb/>Student&apos;s t-test was employed. The chi-square test was <lb/>used to compare rates or frequencies. The association <lb/>between NLR and postoperative pathological diagnosis <lb/>were assessed using univariate and multivariable logistic <lb/>regression model. The power of NLR to diagnosis of <lb/>EOC was evaluated using ROC curve, sensitivity and <lb/>specificity. Data were analysed using Stata-17 software. <lb/>The significant level was considered less than 0.05. <lb/>Results <lb/>At total, 204 patients were included in the analysis <lb/>with mean (SD) age of 48.25 (13.35) years. Malignant <lb/>and benign tumors composed 50 (24.51%) and 154 <lb/>(75.49%) of the patients, respectively. High-grade serous <lb/>carcinoma (70%), mucinous ovarian cancer (14%) and <lb/>endometrioid carcinomas (12%) were most common <lb/>subtypes of EOC, while serous cystadenoma (35.1%), <lb/>mucinous cystadenomas (20.8%) and mature cystic <lb/>teratoma (18.2%) were most common bengin ovarian <lb/>masses, respectively (Figure 1). <lb/>Patient characteristics according to the type of tumor <lb/>as well as resulting odds ratio (95% confidence interval) <lb/>are presented in Table 1. Compared to benign mass group, <lb/>patients with ovaian malignancy were significantly older, <lb/>with lower BMI, reduced Hb level, increased platelets <lb/>level and higher proportion of both ovaries&apos; involvement <lb/>(p-value&lt;0.05). The proportion of patients with HE4 <lb/>(&gt;140 Pm), CA 125 (&gt; 35U/Ml) and CEA (&gt;5 ng/Ml) were <lb/>52.45%, 41.67% and 3.43%, respectively and proportion <lb/>of abnormal tumor markers was statistically higher in <lb/>malignant group compared to benign tumor (p&lt;0.05). <lb/>Odds of having higher NLR levels in the malignancy <lb/>group was higher than benign group (e.g., OR of 4.45 for <lb/>NLR in quartile 4 vs. quartile 1). <lb/>The multivariable analysis for the association between <lb/>NLR level and ovarian malignancy are shown in Table 2, <lb/>in which we showed ORs (95% CI) for the quartile 2, 3 <lb/>and 4 vs. quartile 1 after adjusting for age, BMI and tumor <lb/>markers. The predictive performance of the developed <lb/>models is shown in Figure 2. In all developed models <lb/>higher NLR levels (quartile 4) was identified as significant <lb/>predictor of malignancy, however, in the model 2, NLR <lb/>exhibited no significant association with malignancy after <lb/>adjusting CA125. Odds of malignancy in patients with <lb/>NLR of 3.87 to 55.41 compred to those with NLR of 0.14 <lb/>to 1.60 were 7.08, 4.14 and 4.32 after adjusting age and <lb/>BMI, HE4 and CEA, respectively. The corsponding OR <lb/>(95% CI) for NLR quartile 4 vs quartile 1 in the model 5 <lb/>(full model) was 3.66 (95% CI: 1.00, 13.49). According <lb/>to model selection criteria, the full model with including <lb/>NLR level and age, BMI and cancer tumor markers has <lb/>best performance for diagnosis of tumor malignancy <lb/>(AIC=166.46, BIC=196.33, AUC =0.87) (Table 2 and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention, Vol 25 </note>

            <page>973 <lb/></page>

			<body>DOI:10.31557/APJCP.2024.25.3.971 <lb/>Diagnostic Value of the Neutrophil-to-Lymphocyte Ratio in Predicting Ovarian Cancer <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>Malignant <lb/>(N=50) <lb/>Benign <lb/>(N=154) <lb/>OR (95% CI) <lb/>p-value <lb/>Age (yrs) <lb/>54.26 (12.04) <lb/>46.31 (13.21) <lb/>1.05 (1.02, 1.07) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>Gravidity <lb/>0 <lb/>10 (20.00) <lb/>33 (21.43) <lb/>Reference <lb/>1 <lb/>3 (6.00) <lb/>14 (9.09) <lb/>0.71 (0.17, 2.96) <lb/>0.63 <lb/>2 <lb/>8 (16.00) <lb/>37 (24.03) <lb/>0.71 (0.25, 2.02) <lb/>0.52 <lb/>3 <lb/>13 (26.00) <lb/>29 (18.83) <lb/>1.47 (0.56, 3.87) <lb/>0.42 <lb/>&gt;3 <lb/>16 (32.00) <lb/>41 (26.62) <lb/>1.29 (0.51, 3.21) <lb/>0.59 <lb/>BMI (kg/m 2 ) <lb/>25.19 (3.70) <lb/>27.84 (4.28) <lb/>0.84 (0.76, 0.92) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>Menstruation <lb/>Regular periods <lb/>8 (16.00) <lb/>50 (32.47) <lb/>Reference <lb/>Irregular periods <lb/>11 (22.00) <lb/>45 (29.22) <lb/>1.50 (0.56, 3.97) <lb/>0.41 <lb/>Hysterectomy <lb/>0 <lb/>12 (7.79) <lb/>0.23 (0.01, 4.40) <lb/>0.33 <lb/>Menopause <lb/>31 (62.00) <lb/>47 (30.52) <lb/>3.94 (1.67, 9.26) <lb/>0.002 <lb/>Rh blood group <lb/>Positive <lb/>43 (87.76) <lb/>139 (90.26) <lb/>Reference <lb/>Negative <lb/>6 (12.24) <lb/>15 (9.74) <lb/>1.29 (0.47, 3.53) <lb/>0.62 <lb/>Diabetes <lb/>No <lb/>43 (86.00) <lb/>135 (87.66) <lb/>Reference <lb/>Yes <lb/>7 (14.00) <lb/>19 (12.34) <lb/>1.15 (0.45, 2.93) <lb/>0.76 <lb/>Hypertension <lb/>No <lb/>35 (70.00) <lb/>119 (77.27) <lb/>Reference <lb/>Yes <lb/>15 (30.00) <lb/>35 (22.73) <lb/>1.45 (0.71, 2.97) <lb/>0.3 <lb/>Hypothyroidism <lb/>No <lb/>46 (92.00) <lb/>137 (88.96) <lb/>Reference <lb/>Yes <lb/>4 (8.00) <lb/>17 (11.04) <lb/>0.70 (0.22, 2.19) <lb/>0.54 <lb/>Family history <lb/>No <lb/>38 (76.00) <lb/>134 (87.01) <lb/>Reference <lb/>Yes <lb/>12 (24.00) <lb/>20 (12.99) <lb/>2.11 (0.95, 4.71) <lb/>0.07 <lb/>Tumor size <lb/>87.12 (6.55) <lb/>80.18 (4.07) <lb/>1.002 (0.99, 1.008) <lb/>0.39 <lb/>Ovarian involvement, <lb/>Left <lb/>12 (24.00) <lb/>83 (53.90) <lb/>Reference <lb/>Right <lb/>21 (42.00) <lb/>58 (37.66) <lb/>2.50 (1.14, 5.48) <lb/>0.02 <lb/>Both <lb/>17 (34.00) <lb/>13 (8.44) <lb/>9.04 (3.52, 23.20) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>HE4 <lb/>&lt;140 <lb/>16 (32.00) <lb/>81 (52.60) <lb/>&gt;140 <lb/>34 (68.00) <lb/>73 (47.70) <lb/>2.36 (1.20, 4.62) <lb/>0.01 <lb/>CA125 <lb/>&lt;35 <lb/>13 (26.00) <lb/>106 (68.83) <lb/>&gt;35 <lb/>37 (74.00) <lb/>48 (31.17) <lb/>6.28 (3.06, 12.88) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>CEA <lb/>&lt;5 <lb/>44 (88.00) <lb/>153 (99.35) <lb/>&gt;5 <lb/>6 (12.00) <lb/>1 (0.65) <lb/>20.86 (2.44, 177.93) <lb/>&lt;0.005 <lb/>NLR <lb/>Q1 (0.14-1.60) <lb/>6 (12.00) <lb/>45 (29.22) <lb/>Reference <lb/>Q2 (1.61-2.10) <lb/>13 (26.00) <lb/>38 (24.68) <lb/>2.56 (0.89, 7.40) <lb/>0.08 <lb/>Q3 (2.17-3.75) <lb/>12 (24.00) <lb/>39 (25.32) <lb/>2.30 (0.79, 6.72) <lb/>0.12 <lb/>Q4 (3.87-55.41) <lb/>19 (38.00) <lb/>32 (20.78) <lb/>4.45 (1.59, 12.39) <lb/>0.004 <lb/>Table 1. Patient Characteristics According the Type of Tumor as Well as Resulting Odds Ratio (95% Confidence <lb/>Interval) <lb/>Presented data in the cells are mean (standard deviation) for age and BMI, otherwise are number (%) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Maryam Sadat Hosseini et al <lb/>Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention, Vol 25 <lb/></note>

			<page>974 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 1. The Distribution of most Common Type of Ovarian Cancer <lb/>NLR <lb/>Median NLR <lb/>Model 1 <lb/>Model 2 <lb/>Model 3 <lb/>Model 4 <lb/>Model 5 <lb/>Q1 (0.14-1.60) <lb/>1.35 <lb/>Reference <lb/>Reference <lb/>Reference <lb/>Reference <lb/>Reference <lb/>Q2 (1.61-2.10) <lb/>1.87 <lb/>3.19 (0.99, 10.28) <lb/>2.32 (0.76, 7.12) <lb/>2.79 (0.95, 8.20) <lb/>2.35 (0.77, 7.11) <lb/>2.85 (0.75, 10.81) <lb/>Q3 (2.17-3.75) <lb/>2.73 <lb/>2.49 (0.77, 8.02) <lb/>1.52 (0.49, 4.74) <lb/>2.35 (0.79, 6.93) <lb/>2.59 (0.86, 7.79) <lb/>1.75 (0.46, 6.58) <lb/>Q4 (3.87-55.41) <lb/>7.05 <lb/>7.08 (2.22, 22.61) <lb/>2.62 (0.88, 7.82) 4.14 (1.47, 11.67) 4.32 (1.49, 12.52) <lb/>3.66 (1.00, 13.49) <lb/>AIC, BIC <lb/>191.72, 211.63 <lb/>204.50, 221.10 <lb/>222.26, 238.85 <lb/>216.68, 233.27 <lb/>166.46, 196.33 <lb/>Table 2. The Effect of NLR as Categorical Variable on Ovarian Malignant Tumor in Combination with General <lb/>Characteristics and Tumor Markers <lb/>Model 1, age and BMI adjusted; Model 2, CA125 adjusted; Model 3, HE4 adjusted; Model 4, CEA adjusted; Model 5, Full model <lb/>Optimal cut point <lb/>Model <lb/>OR (95% CI) <lb/>NLR <lb/>Tumor marker AUC <lb/>Maximum youden index Sensitivity Specificity <lb/>NLR <lb/>1.04 (1.00, 1.09) <lb/>2.61 <lb/>-<lb/>0.62 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.63 <lb/>NLR+CA125 <lb/>1.03 (0.98, 1.08) <lb/>13.82 <lb/>149.65 <lb/>0.82 <lb/>0.53 <lb/>0.56 <lb/>0.97 <lb/>NLR+HE4 <lb/>1.04 (1.00, 1.09) <lb/>4.92 <lb/>146.85 <lb/>0.71 <lb/>0.33 <lb/>0.46 <lb/>0.87 <lb/>NLR+CEA <lb/>1.04 (1.00, 1.09) <lb/>4.53 <lb/>2.56 <lb/>0.56 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.38 <lb/>0.82 <lb/>Tble 3. The Effect of NLR as Continuous Variable on Ovarian Malignant Tumor in Combination with Tumor Markers <lb/>Figure 2). <lb/>The effect of NLR as continuous variable on ovarian <lb/>malignant tumor in combination with tumor markers is <lb/>shown in the Table 3. In the naïve model, one-unit increase <lb/>in NLR is associated with odds of ovarian malignant <lb/>tumor by 4%, however, the diagnositic criteria is lower <lb/>than acceptable cutoff of 0.70. The highest diagnostic <lb/>performance is expected to be yielded from NLR <lb/>with cutpoint 13.82 and CA125 with cutpoint 149.65 <lb/>(AUC=0.82 and maximum youden index=0.53). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>This study provides evidence about the prognostic <lb/>value of NLR alone and in combination with patient <lb/>characteristics (e.g., age and BMI) and tumor markers <lb/>(CA125, HE4 and CEA) for malignancy among patients <lb/>with ovarian mass. We found that high level of NLR in <lb/>combination with age, BMI and tumor markers can reach <lb/>to high accuracy 87% to discriminate malignancy from <lb/>bengin tumor among patient with ovarian mass. <lb/>The effect of NLR on prognosis of EOC has been well <lb/>documented in the literature. Higher level of NLR might <lb/>be a surrogate of poor lymphocyte-mediated immune <lb/>response against tumors and also association between <lb/>neutrophils and transforming growth factor β (TGF-β) and <lb/>then it is expected that this phenomenon contribute with <lb/>significant impact on tumor cell proliferation and poor <lb/>prognosis [8]. One other study has showed that the role <lb/>of NLR on the prognosis in EOC is function of T cells <lb/>and B cells counts [9]. Low T and B cells and elevated <lb/>NLR are related with lower response to treatment and poor <lb/>prognosis in EOC [9]. <lb/>The predictive value of systemic inflammatory <lb/>markers such as NLR in prognosis of EOC [10] and <lb/>combination tumor markers (e.g., CA125, CA199 and <lb/>CEA) have been previously suggested [11], however, <lb/>the independent effect of NLR alone and in combination <lb/>with tumor markers still require further studies. It has <lb/>been noted that tumor markers stimulate inflammatory <lb/>markers immunosuppressive in EOC [12]. Also, it argued <lb/>that tumor marker (e.g., CA125) and NLR is linked by <lb/>thrombocytes and an immunosuppressive cytokine-profile <lb/>and then constellation of these factors can infelence the <lb/>survaival rate of EOC patients [13]. We did not found <lb/>significant association between NLR and EOC and this <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention, Vol 25</note>

            <page>975 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">DOI:10.31557/APJCP.2024.25.3.971 <lb/>Diagnostic Value of the Neutrophil-to-Lymphocyte Ratio in Predicting Ovarian Cancer <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 2. Area under the Curve (AUC) for Evaluating Power of NLR to Diagnosis Ovarian Cancer Maligna <lb/>results was inconsistent with study by Li et al. that showed <lb/>patients with low CA125 level, elevated NLR is related <lb/>with the risk of EOC [14]. <lb/>Consistent with our findings, Cho et al. examined the <lb/>diagnostic utility of NLR in cases of epithelial ovarian <lb/>cancer and discovered that the preoperative NLR in EOC <lb/>patients was markedly elevated when compared to that <lb/>of patients with benign ovarian tumors [15]. Moreover, <lb/>Yildirim et al. in their study found that NLR alone has <lb/>not enough power for differentiation between benign and <lb/>malignant ovarian masses in the preoperative period, <lb/>which was in line with our findings [16]. Considering <lb/>these findings, NLR appears to be a promising indicator for <lb/>EOC. Moreover, since NLR results can be easily obtained, <lb/>makes it a cost-effective choice that aligns well with the <lb/>requirements of routine screening markers for regular <lb/>physical examinations. <lb/>Several limitations should be considered when <lb/>interpreting the results; some part of prognostic value of <lb/>NLR may be due to inflammatory factors (e.g., Monocyte-<lb/>to-Lymphocyte Ratio, lymphocyte-to-monocyte ratio, <lb/>IL-6, IL-8, IL-10), however, data on these factors was <lb/>not available to include in the analysis. The interaction <lb/>between the NLR and tumor mrkers may varies depending <lb/>on the type of treatment (e.g., chemotherapy) and this <lb/>important issue should be considered in the mind. Limited <lb/>sample size and lack of survival data precludes us to <lb/>evaluate the associations with higher statistical power. <lb/>In conclusion, while NLR by itself may lack <lb/>significant predictive power, the precence of high NLR in <lb/>combination with tumor markers including CA125, HE4 <lb/>and CEA was associated with malignancy in patients with <lb/>ovarian mass. These findings suggest that NLR, along with <lb/>these factors, could serve as a valuable tool in clinical <lb/>practice for better risk assessment and decision-making <lb/>in the management of EOC patients. More pay attention <lb/>and further examinations should be performed for EOC <lb/>patients with elevated NLR and abnormal tumor markers <lb/>level for detecting malignancy in EOC patients as early <lb/>as possible. <lb/></body>

            <div type="annex">Author Contribution Statement <lb/>MSH and FA conceived and designed the study. MSH, <lb/>TA, FF, MA, MT, RA and FA performed data collection <lb/>and analysis. MR contributed to interpretation of the <lb/>results. FA drafted the initial manuscript. All authors <lb/>critically reviewed and approved the final version of the <lb/>manuscript <lb/></div>

            <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>Deputy of Research and Technology of Shahid <lb/>Beheshti University of Medical Sciences approved our <lb/>study and financially supported the study. We would like <lb/>gratefully acknowledge the medical staff of the Imam <lb/>Hussain Hospitol. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding statement <lb/>Deputy of Research and Technology of Shahid <lb/>Beheshti University of Medical Sciences approved our <lb/>study and financially supported the study. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Ethics <lb/>The ethics committee of Shahid Beheshti University <lb/>of Medical Sciences approved the study (IR.SBMU. <lb/>RETECH.REC.1402.134) <lb/></div>

            <div type="availability">Availability of data <lb/>The datasets generated and analyzed during the current <lb/>study are available from the corresponding author upon <lb/>reasonable request. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Maryam Sadat Hosseini et al <lb/>Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention, Vol 25 <lb/></note>

			<page>976 <lb/></page>

            <!-- Wrong order -->
			<listBibl>al. Pre-treatment neutrophil to lymphocyte ratio is elevated <lb/>in epithelial ovarian cancer and predicts survival after <lb/>treatment. Cancer Immunol Immunother. 2009;58:15-23. <lb/>16. Yildirim M, Cendek BD, Avsar AF. Differentiation between <lb/>benign and malignant ovarian masses in the preoperative <lb/>period using neutrophil-to-lymphocyte and platelet-to-<lb/>lymphocyte ratios. Mol Clin Oncol. 2015;3(2):317-21. <lb/></listBibl>

            <div type="annex">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors claimed no conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

            <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Zhang Y, Luo G, Li M, Guo P, Xiao Y, Ji H, et al. Global <lb/>patterns and trends in ovarian cancer incidence: Age, period <lb/>and birth cohort analysis. BMC cancer. 2019;19(1):1-14. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12885-019-6139-6 <lb/>2. Nash Z, Menon U. Ovarian cancer screening: Current <lb/>status and future directions. Best Pract Res Clin Obstet <lb/>Gynaecol. 2020;65:32-45. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>bpobgyn.2020.02.010 <lb/>3. Bonifácio VDB. Ovarian cancer biomarkers: Moving forward <lb/>in early detection. Adv Exp Med Biol. 2020;1219:355-63. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-34025-4_18. <lb/>4. Nebgen DR, Lu KH, Bast RC, Jr. Novel approaches to ovarian <lb/>cancer screening. Curr Oncol Rep. 2019;21(8):75. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1007/s11912-019-0816-0. <lb/>5. Zhang M, Cheng S, Jin Y, Zhao Y, Wang Y. Roles of ca125 <lb/>in diagnosis, prediction, and oncogenesis of ovarian cancer. <lb/>Biochim Biophys Acta Rev Cancer. 2021;1875(2):188503. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbcan.2021.188503. <lb/>6. Zhang H, Huo Q, Huang L, Cheng Y, Liu Y, Bao H. Neutrophil-<lb/>to-lymphocyte ratio in ovarian cancer patients with low <lb/>ca125 concentration. Biomed Res Int. 2019;2019:8107906 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1155/2019/8107906. <lb/>7. Farzaneh F, Faghih N, Hosseini MS, Arab M, Ashrafganjoei <lb/>T, Bahman A. Evaluation of neutrophil-lymphocyte ratio <lb/>as a prognostic factor in cervical intraepithelial neoplasia <lb/>recurrence. Asian Pac J Cancer Prev. 2019;20(8):2365-72. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.31557/apjcp.2019.20.8.2365. <lb/>8. Templeton AJ, McNamara MG, Šeruga B, Vera-Badillo FE, <lb/>Aneja P, Ocaña A, et al. Prognostic role of neutrophil-to-<lb/>lymphocyte ratio in solid tumors: A systematic review and <lb/>meta-analysis. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2014;106(6):dju124. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/jnci/dju124. <lb/>9. Henriksen JR, Nederby L, Donskov F, Waldstrøm M, Adimi P, <lb/>Jakobsen A, et al. Prognostic significance of baseline t cells, <lb/>b cells and neutrophil-lymphocyte ratio (nlr) in recurrent <lb/>ovarian cancer treated with chemotherapy. J Ovarian Res. <lb/>2020;13(1):59. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13048-020-00661-<lb/>4. <lb/>10. Zhu Y, Zhou S, Liu Y, Zhai L, Sun X. Prognostic value <lb/>of systemic inflammatory markers in ovarian cancer: A <lb/>prisma-compliant meta-analysis and systematic review. <lb/>BMC Cancer. 2018;18(1):443. https://doi.org/10.1186/ <lb/>s12885-018-4318-5. <lb/>11. Guo J, Yu J, Song X, Mi H. Serum ca125, ca199 and cea <lb/>combined detection for epithelial ovarian cancer diagnosis: <lb/>A meta-analysis. Open Medicine (Wars). 2017;12:131-7. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1515/med-2017-0020. <lb/>12. Wu Y, Liu Q, Xie Y, Zhu J, Zhang S, Ge Y, et al. <lb/>Muc16 stimulates neutrophils to an inflammatory and <lb/>immunosuppressive phenotype in ovarian cancer. J Ovarian <lb/>Res. 2023;16(1):181. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13048-023-<lb/>01207-0. <lb/>13. Baert T, Van Camp J, Vanbrabant L, Busschaert P, Laenen <lb/>A, Han S, et al. Influence of ca125, platelet count and <lb/>neutrophil to lymphocyte ratio on the immune system of <lb/>ovarian cancer patients. Gynecol Oncol. 2018;150(1):31-7. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ygyno.2018.05.004. <lb/>14. Li L, Tian J, Zhang L, Liu L, Sheng C, Huang Y, et al. <lb/>Utility of preoperative inflammatory markers to distinguish <lb/>epithelial ovarian cancer from benign ovarian masses. J <lb/>Cancer. 2021;12(9):2687. <lb/>15. Cho H, Hur HW, Kim SW, Kim SH, Kim JH, Kim YT, et <lb/></listBibl>

            <front>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-<lb/>Non  Commercial 4.0 International License. </front>


	</text>
</tei>
