<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">BCAT1 is a NOTCH1 target and sustains the oncogenic function of NOTCH1</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Valeria</forename>
          <surname>Tosello</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Ludovica</forename>
          <surname>Di Martino</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Adonia E.</forename>
          <surname>Papathanassiu</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Silvia Dalla</forename>
          <surname>Santa</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Marco</forename>
          <surname>Pizzi</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Lara</forename>
          <surname>Mussolin</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Jingjing</forename>
          <surname>Liu</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Pieter</forename>
          <surname>Van Vlierberghe</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Erich</forename>
          <surname>Piovan</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-04T14:51:46.445Z">11/4/2025 2:51:46 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Ferrata Storti Foundation (Haematologica)</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.3324/haematol.2024.285552</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Valeria Tosello, Ludovica Di Martino, Adonia E. Papathanassiu, Silvia Dalla Santa, Marco Pizzi, Lara Mussolin, Jingjing Liu, Pieter Van Vlierberghe, Erich Piovan. (2024). BCAT1 is a NOTCH1 target and sustains the oncogenic function of NOTCH1. Haematologica, None(None), None. DOI: 10.3324/haematol.2024.285552</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-04T14:51:33.787841Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-04T14:51:33.787841Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>Haematologica | 109 September 2024 <lb/>2908 <lb/>-Myeloproliferative Disorders <lb/>ARTICLE <lb/>A predictive classifier of poor prognosis in transplanted <lb/>patients with juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia: a study <lb/>on behalf of the Société Francophone de Greffe de Moelle <lb/>et de Thérapie Cellulaire <lb/>Déborah Meyran, 1,2,3 Chloé Arfeuille, 4,5 Sylvie Chevret, 6 Quentin Neven, 1 Aurélie Caye-Eude, 4 Elodie <lb/>Lainey, 5,7 Arnaud Petit, 8 Fanny Rialland, 9 Gérard Michel, 10 Dominique Plantaz, 11 Charlotte Jubert, 12 <lb/>Alexandre Theron, 13,14 Virginie Gandemer, 15 Marie Ouachée-Chardin, 16 Catherine Paillard, 17 Bénédicte <lb/>Bruno, 18 Nimrod Buchbinder, 19 Cécile Pochon, 20 Charlotte Calvo, 1 Mony Fahd, 1 André Baruchel, 1,21 <lb/>Hélène Cavé, 4,5 Jean-Hugues Dalle 1,21 and Marion Strullu 1,5 <lb/>1 <lb/>Service d&apos;Hémato-Immunologie Pédiatrique, Hôpital Robert Debré, GHU AP-HP Nord-Université <lb/>Paris Cité, Paris, France; 2 Children&apos;s Cancer Centre, Royal Children&apos;s Hospital, Parkville, Victoria, <lb/>Australia; 3 Sir Peter MacCallum Department of Oncology, University of Melbourne, Melbourne, <lb/>Australia; 4 Service de Génétique Moléculaire, Hôpital Robert Debré, GHU AP-HP Nord-Université <lb/>Paris Cité, Paris, France; 5 INSERM UMR_S1131, Institut Universitaire d&apos;Hématologie, Université Paris <lb/>Cité, Paris-Cité, Paris, France; 6 Service de Biostatistique et Information Médicale, Hôpital Saint <lb/>Louis, GHU AP-HP Nord-Université Paris Cité, Paris, France; 7 Service d&apos;Hématologie Biologique, <lb/>Hôpital Robert Debré, GHU AP-HP Nord-Université Paris Cité, Paris, France; 8 Service d&apos;Hémato-<lb/>Immunologie Pédiatrique, Hôpital Armand Trousseau, Université Paris Sorbonne, Paris, France; <lb/>9 <lb/>Service d&apos;Onco-Hématologie Pédiatrique, CHU de Nantes, Nantes, France; 10 Service d&apos;Hématologie <lb/>Pédiatrique, Assistance Publique des Hôpitaux de Marseille AP-HM, Marseille, France; 11 Service <lb/>d&apos;Onco-Hématologie Pédiatrique, CHU de Grenoble, Grenoble, France; 12 CHU Bordeaux, Service <lb/>d&apos;Hématologie Oncologie Pédiatrique, F-33000 Bordeaux, France; 13 Department of Pediatric <lb/>Oncology and Hematology, CHU CHU Montpellier, Montpellier, France; 14 IRMB, University of <lb/>Montpellier, INSERM, Montpellier, France; 15 Service d&apos;Onco-Hématologie Pédiatrique, CHU de <lb/>Rennes, Rennes, France; 16 Service d&apos;Onco-Hématologie Pédiatrique, IHOPE, Lyon, France; 17 Service <lb/>de Pédiatrie, Hôpital de Hautepierre, Strasbourg, France; 18 Service de Pédiatrie, Hôpital de Jeanne <lb/>de Flandre, Lille, France; 19 Service d&apos;Onco-Hématologie Pédiatrique, CHU de Rouen, Rouen, France; <lb/>20 <lb/>Service d&apos;Onco-Hématologie Pédiatrique, Hôpital d&apos;Enfants de Brabois, Vandoeuvre lès Nancy, <lb/>France and 21 Unité Inserm U976, Université Paris Cité, Paris-Cité, Paris, France <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia (JMML) is an aggressive pediatric myeloproliferative neoplasm requiring hematopoietic <lb/>stem cell transplantation (HSCT) in most cases. We retrospectively analyzed 119 JMML patients who underwent first alloge-<lb/>neic HSCT between 2002 and 2021. The majority (97%) carried a RAS-pathway mutation, and 62% exhibited karyotypic alter-<lb/>ations or additional mutations in SETBP1, ASXL1, JAK3 and/or the RAS pathway. Relapse was the primary cause of death, with <lb/>a 5-year cumulative incidence of 24.6% (95% CI: 17.1-32.9). Toxic deaths occurred in 12 patients, resulting in treatment-related <lb/>mortality (TRM) of 9.0% (95% CI: 4.6-15.3). The 5-year overall (OS) and event-free survival were 73.6% (95% CI: 65.7-82.4) and <lb/>66.4% (95% CI: 58.2-75.8), respectively. Four independent adverse prognostic factors for OS were identified: age at diagnosis <lb/>&gt;2 years, time from diagnosis to HSCT ≥6 months, monocyte count at diagnosis &gt;7.2x10 9 /L, and the presence of additional <lb/>genetic alterations. Based on these factors, we proposed a predictive classifier. Patients with 3 or more predictors (21% of the <lb/>cohort) had a 5-year OS of 34.2%, whereas those with none (7%) had a 5-year OS of 100%. Our study demonstrates improved <lb/>transplant outcomes compared to prior published data, which can be attributed to the synergistic impacts of a low TRM and <lb/>a reduced, yet still substantial, relapse incidence. By integrating genetic information with clinical and hematologic features, <lb/>we have devised a predictive classifier. This classifier effectively identifies a subgroup of patients who are at a heightened risk <lb/>of unfavorable post-transplant outcomes who would benefit from novel therapeutic agents and post-transplant strategies. <lb/>Correspondence: M. Strullu <lb/>marion.strullu@aphp.fr <lb/>Received: <lb/>August 17, 2023. <lb/>Accepted: <lb/>February 13, 2024. <lb/>Early view: <lb/>February 22, 2024. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3324/haematol.2023.284103 <lb/>©2024 Ferrata Storti Foundation <lb/>Published under a CC BY-NC license <lb/>Haematologica | 109 September 2024 <lb/>2909 <lb/>ARTICLE -HSCT in JMML <lb/>D. Meyran et al. <lb/></front>

        <body>Introduction <lb/>Juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia (JMML) is an aggressive <lb/>hematologic malignancy of early childhood. It results from <lb/>the hyperactivation of the RAS signal transduction pathway <lb/>mainly caused by mutations of PTPN11, KRAS, NRAS, RRAS, <lb/>RRAS2, CBL, SH2B3 and NF1. 1-3 Except for a small subset of <lb/>patients who exhibit spontaneous remissions, the disease <lb/>usually progresses and leads to death within months of <lb/>diagnosis. Unlike acute leukemia, intensive chemotherapy <lb/>is insufficient to eradicate the disease and hematopoi-<lb/>etic stem cell transplantation (HSCT) is the only curative <lb/>treatment for most patients. 4,5 However, the rarity of the <lb/>disease has resulted in only a few large cohorts of HSCT <lb/>being reported over the last 20 years. 6-10 These studies <lb/>showed that JMML is associated with a poor outcome, with <lb/>a 5-year overall survival (OS) ranging from 52% to 72% due <lb/>to high-risk post-transplant relapse combined with high <lb/>treatment-related mortality (TRM). Predictive variables of <lb/>poor outcome identified across these trials encompass <lb/>age at diagnosis and at transplant, abnormal karyotype <lb/>and HLA disparities. Previously published studies including <lb/>non-transplanted patients also identified other predictive <lb/>factors of death and relapse, such as low platelet count <lb/>and high fetal hemoglobin level (HbF). 11,12 Since then, prog-<lb/>ress has been made in deciphering the genomic landscape <lb/>of JMML, contributing to a deeper understanding of the <lb/>marked heterogeneity that characterizes this disease. 13,14 <lb/>Indeed, certain initiating mutations, such as NF1 or PTPN11, <lb/>have been shown to correlate with disease aggressive-<lb/>ness. Furthermore, the occurrence of additional genetic <lb/>mutations, including double RAS mutations, ASXL1, SETBP1 <lb/>or JAK3, while uncommon in JMML, further worsens the <lb/>overall prognosis of patients. 13-16 <lb/>However, it is worth noting that most previously published <lb/>studies on HSCT in JMML have provided either incomplete or <lb/>no genetic information. Consequently, the recent molecular <lb/>insights associated with aggressive disease have not been <lb/>challenged within a cohort of transplanted JMML patients. <lb/>In this study, we report the outcome of 119 children with <lb/>JMML who underwent HSCT over the past 20 years and <lb/>were genetically characterized. We evaluated the impact <lb/>of previously described parameters, as well as the role of <lb/>the initiating RAS mutation and additional ASXL1, SETBP1 <lb/>and JAK3 mutations on prognosis. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Patients and data collection <lb/>This study investigated 119 consecutive children diagnosed <lb/>with JMML who received a first allogeneic HSCT between <lb/>June 2002 and August 2021 in France (Table 1). All patients <lb/>met the World Health Organization (WHO) consensus crite-<lb/>ria for JMML. 2 Patients&apos; data were collected retrospectively <lb/>using the PROMISE database of the European Bone Marrow <lb/>Transplant group (EBMT) through the Société Francophone <lb/>de Greffe de Moelle et de Thérapie Cellulaire (SFGM-TC). <lb/>JMML patient samples, bone marrow (BM) and/or peripheral <lb/>blood (PB), were collected on EDTA at diagnosis. Genomic <lb/>DNA was extracted from mononucleated cells. Mutational <lb/>screening using bi-directional Sanger and/or next generation <lb/>sequencing (NGS) of exons and their flanking intron-exon <lb/>boundaries was performed on genomic DNA as part of the <lb/>classic diagnostic workup for JMML, and included NRAS, <lb/>KRAS, PTPN11, CBL, NF1, SH2B3, RRAS, RRAS2, ASXL1, SETBP1 <lb/>and JAK3, as previously described. 13,17 Written informed con-<lb/>sent for the study was provided by the patients or their <lb/>guardians in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki <lb/>(IRB: 00006477). <lb/>Definitions and endpoints <lb/>Elevated HbF levels at the time of JMML diagnosis were <lb/>defined as follows: ≥10% for children aged ≥6 to &lt;12 months, <lb/>and ≥1% for children aged ≥12 months. HbF levels were con-<lb/>sidered not interpretable for children under six months old. <lb/>Relapse was defined as the recurrence of JMML, clinically <lb/>and morphologically on PB and/or BM analysis, after HSCT. <lb/>HLA matching and engraftment definitions are provided <lb/>in the Online Supplementary Methods. Acute and chronic <lb/>graft-versus-host disease (GvHD) were diagnosed and graded <lb/>by each transplantation center according to conventional <lb/>criteria. 18,19 Treatment of GvHD was based on the protocols <lb/>used in each center. <lb/>Treatment-related mortality was defined as any death oc-<lb/>curring from any cause but disease relapse. One patient <lb/>died of Pneumocystis jirovecii lung infection after JMML re-<lb/>lapse while waiting for a second transplant. We considered <lb/>the death of this patient as related to the HSCT. Event-<lb/>free survival (EFS) was defined as a composite outcome, <lb/>including relapse and death, whichever occurred first. In <lb/>exploratory analyses, we also considered secondary allograft <lb/>and secondary malignancy as additional events defining a <lb/>&apos;stringent EFS&apos;. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>Time-to-event outcomes were measured from the date of <lb/>transplant to the date of event or date of last follow-up, <lb/>with a cut-off date of December 30, 2021. TRM and relapse <lb/>were considered as mutually competing risk events, while <lb/>death was considered a competing risk for engraftment <lb/>and GvHD. Engraftment and acute GvHD were arbitrarily <lb/>censored at 100 days. <lb/>The OS and EFS were estimated using Kaplan-Meier es-<lb/>timator. For competing risk analyses of TRM, relapse and <lb/>GvHD, cumulative incidence functions were estimated. 20 <lb/>Factors associated with outcomes were analyzed using <lb/>the Fine and Gray model for GvHD, proportional hazards <lb/>models for the cause-specific hazard for relapse and TRM, <lb/>and Cox proportional hazards models for EFS and OS. 21,22 <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 109 September 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2910 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -HSCT in JMML <lb/>D. Meyran et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>The proportional hazards assumption was checked by <lb/>examination of Schoenfeld residuals and Grambsch and <lb/>Therneau lack-of-fit test. 23 <lb/>All tests were two-sided. P≤0.05 was considered statisti-<lb/>cally significant. The analyses were performed using the R <lb/>statistical software version 4.1.1. <lb/>Results <lb/>Patients&apos; characteristics at juvenile myelomonocytic <lb/>leukemia diagnosis and pre-transplant treatment <lb/>Table 1 provides a summary of patients&apos; characteristics <lb/>(N=119). At diagnosis, 64 patients (54%) were &lt;2 years of <lb/>age. JMML occurred in the setting of a germline predispos-<lb/>ing condition in 16 patients (14%): type 1 neurofibromatosis <lb/>(N=8), Casitas B-lineage lymphoma (CBL) syndrome (N=7), <lb/>and SH2B3 germline biallelic mutation (N=1). A RAS-path-<lb/>way mutation was observed in 115 out of 118 patients (97%). <lb/>The most commonly mutated gene was PTPN11, observed <lb/>in 40% of patients, followed by KRAS (22%), NRAS (19%), <lb/>NF1 (7%), CBL (6%), and other less frequent mutations (3%; <lb/>including RRAS, RRAS2 and SH2B3). <lb/>The time from diagnosis to HSCT varied among patients, <lb/>ranging from 1.8 to 44.3 months, but remained consistent <lb/>throughout the study period and across the genetic sub-<lb/>Table 1. Patients&apos; characteristics at diagnosis. <lb/>N of patients assessed <lb/>Value <lb/>M/F ratio <lb/>Female, N (%) <lb/>Male, N (%) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>2.2 <lb/>37 (31.1) <lb/>82 (68.9) <lb/>Median age at diagnosis in years (IQR) <lb/>119 <lb/>1.6 (0.7-3.2) <lb/>Hepatomegaly, N (%) <lb/>117 <lb/>89 (76.1) <lb/>Splenomegaly, N (%) <lb/>117 <lb/>109 (93.2) <lb/>PB cell count x10 9 /L, median (IQR) <lb/>White blood cells <lb/>Platelets <lb/>Platelets &lt;33x10 9 /L, N (%) <lb/>Monocytes <lb/>Hemoglobin, g/dL <lb/>Presence of myeloid precursors, N (%) <lb/>Presence of blast cells, N (%) <lb/>-<lb/>118 <lb/>116 <lb/>116 <lb/>119 <lb/>117 <lb/>116 <lb/>115 <lb/>-<lb/>25.5 (16.4-46.8) <lb/>59 (33-110) <lb/>30 (25.9) <lb/>5.1 (2.7-7.2) <lb/>8.9 (8-10.3) <lb/>106 (91.4) <lb/>80 (69.6) <lb/>BM blast percentage, median (range) <lb/>118 <lb/>4 (0-37) <lb/>Elevated HbF,* N (%) <lb/>88 <lb/>73 (82.9) <lb/>Karyotypic alterations, N (%) <lb/>Del7/7q <lb/>Other aneuploidies <lb/>Normal <lb/>113 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>45 (39.8) <lb/>26 (23.0) <lb/>19 (16.8) <lb/>68 (60.2) <lb/>RAS-pathway mutations, N (%) <lb/>PTPN11 <lb/>KRAS <lb/>NRAS <lb/>CBL <lb/>NF1 <lb/>Other $ <lb/>No mutation <lb/>118 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>47 (39.8) <lb/>26 (22.0) <lb/>23 (19.5) <lb/>7 (5.9) <lb/>8 (6.8) <lb/>4 (3.4) <lb/>3 (2.5) <lb/>Additional mutations, N (%) <lb/>JAK3 <lb/>SETBP1 <lb/>ASXL1 <lb/>Double RAS pathway mutation <lb/>114 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>39 (34.2) <lb/>10 (8.8) <lb/>9 (7.9) <lb/>11 (9.6) <lb/>25 (21.9) <lb/>Additional alterations,** N (%) <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>111 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>42 (37.8) <lb/>69 (62.2) <lb/>20 (18.0) <lb/>AML: acute myeloid leukemia; BM: bone marrow; F: female; HbF: fetal hemoglobin; IQR: interquartile range; M: male; N: number; <lb/>PB: peripheral blood. *For patients aged ≥6 months. **0, 1 or 2 alterations among the following genes: ASXL1, JAK3, SETBP1, or <lb/>double RAS mutation or karyotype anomaly. $ Other mutations include RRAS, RRAS2 and SH2B3. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 109 September 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2911 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -HSCT in JMML <lb/>D. Meyran et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>groups (Table 2, Online Supplementary Figure S1). Prior to <lb/>conditioning regimen and transplant, patients received <lb/>either no treatment (N=13, 11%), low-dose chemothera-<lb/>py (N=77, 65%; including 6-mercaptopurine, azacytidine <lb/>[N=8] and low-dose cytarabine), or acute myeloid leuke-<lb/>mia-type (AML-type) chemotherapy (N=28, 23.7%) at the <lb/>physician&apos;s discretion (Table 2). The pre-HSCT strategies <lb/>were uniformly distributed among the NF1, PTPN11, KRAS, <lb/>and NRAS groups, while CBL patients exclusively received <lb/>low-intensity treatment and those without mutation, only <lb/>intensive chemotherapy (Online Supplementary Figure S1). <lb/>Transplant, engraftment and graft-versus-host disease <lb/>occurrence <lb/>Transplant characteristics are described in Table 2. All <lb/>patients underwent myeloablative conditioning regimens, <lb/>with the majority receiving busulfan / fludarabine / mel-<lb/>phalan (Bu/Flu/Mel, N=46) or busulfan / cyclophosphamide <lb/>/ melphalan (Bu/Cy/Mel, N=41) (Table 2, Online Supplemen-<lb/>tary Table S1). The Bu/Cy/Mel and Bu/Flu/Mel conditioning <lb/>regimens were administered at the median year of 2007 <lb/>(range, 2002-2019) and 2016 (range, 2010-2021), respectively. <lb/>GvHD prophylaxis according to donor type is provided in <lb/>Table 2. Pre-transplant treatment and transplant characteristics. <lb/>N of patients assessed <lb/>Value <lb/>Pre-HSCT treatment, N (%) <lb/>Low-dose chemotherapy <lb/>AML-like chemotherapy <lb/>No chemotherapy <lb/>118 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>(65.3) <lb/>(23.7) <lb/>(11.0) <lb/>Splenectomy, N (%) <lb/>119 <lb/>(4.2) <lb/>Median age at HSCT in years (IQR) <lb/>119 <lb/>2.5 (1.5-3.9) <lb/>Median interval from diagnosis to HSCT in months (IQR) <lb/>-<lb/>5.8 (4.2-8.6) <lb/>Donor, N (%) <lb/>Matched sibling <lb/>Haploidentical <lb/>Matched unrelated <lb/>Mismatched unrelated <lb/>119 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>(20.2) <lb/>(3.4) <lb/>(38.7) <lb/>(37.8) <lb/>Source of cells, N (%) <lb/>Cord blood <lb/>Bone marrow <lb/>Peripheral blood <lb/>119 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>(32.7) <lb/>(58.8) <lb/>10 (8.4) <lb/>Donor/recipient gender, N (%) <lb/>Female/Female <lb/>Female/Male <lb/>Male/Female <lb/>Male/Male <lb/>114 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>(13.2) <lb/>(19.3) <lb/>(24.6) <lb/>(43.0) <lb/>Donor/recipient CMV status, N (%) <lb/>Negative/Negative <lb/>Negative/Positive <lb/>Positive/Negative <lb/>Positive/Positive <lb/>115 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>(49.6) <lb/>(16.5) <lb/>(16.5) <lb/>(17.4) <lb/>Conditioning, N (%) <lb/>Bu/Cy/Mel <lb/>Bu/Flu/Mel <lb/>Other <lb/>119 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>(34.4) <lb/>(38.7) <lb/>(26.9) <lb/>Total body irradiation, N (%) <lb/>-<lb/>(2.5) <lb/>Anti-thymoglobulin, N (%) <lb/>-<lb/>(47.9) <lb/>GvHD prophylaxis <lb/>CsA + MTX <lb/>CsA <lb/>CsA + corticosteroids <lb/>CsA + MMF <lb/>CsA + other combinations <lb/>117 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>(35.0) <lb/>(28.2) <lb/>(23.1) <lb/>10 (8.5) <lb/>(5.1) <lb/>AML: acute myeloid leukemia; Bu/Cy/Mel: busulfan / cyclophosphamide / melphalan; Bu/Flu/Mel: busulfan / fludarabine / mel-<lb/>phalan; CMV: cytomegalovirus; CsA: cyclosporin A; GvHD: graft-versus-host disease; HSCT: hematopoietic stem cell transplanta-<lb/>tion; IQR: interquartile range; MMF: mycophenolate mofetil; MTX: methotrexate; N: number. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 109 September 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2912 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -HSCT in JMML <lb/>D. Meyran et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>Online Supplementary Table S2. <lb/>Of the 116 patients assessable for engraftment, 100 showed <lb/>sustained engraftment (Figure 1). The median time to neu-<lb/>trophil recovery was 23 days (range, 12-56), and the median <lb/>time to a self-sustained platelet count higher than 50x10 9 /L <lb/>was 43 days (range, 14-160). Sixteen patients experienced <lb/>either primary (N=9) or secondary (N=7) graft failure after a <lb/>median time of four months (range, 2-10). Complete loss of <lb/>chimerism was concomitant with relapse in 4/16 patients <lb/>(1 patient with primary and 3 patients with secondary graft <lb/>failure) (Online Supplementary Figure S2). Patients who <lb/>encountered graft failure exhibited a higher prevalence of <lb/>CBL mutations, HLA disparities, cord blood source, and <lb/>alternative conditioning regimens (other than Bu/Cy/Mel <lb/>or Bu/Flu/Mel) compared to the rest of the cohort (Online <lb/>Supplementary Table S3). <lb/>Acute GvHD grade 2-4 was observed in 63 patients (100-<lb/>day cumulative incidence 53.8%, 95% CI: 44.4-62.3) and <lb/>acute GvHD grade 3-4 in 38 patients (100-day cumulative <lb/>incidence 31.9%, 95% CI: 23.7-40.4) (Online Supplementary <lb/>Figure S3). Univariate analyses identified cytomegalovirus <lb/>(CMV) status (donor positive / recipient negative) and the <lb/>absence of elevated HbF as risk factors for developing <lb/>grade 2-4 acute GvHD, and the NRAS mutation as a risk <lb/>factor for grade 3-4 acute GvHD (Online Supplementary <lb/>Table S4). Chronic GvHD was observed in 42 patients (with <lb/>a 36-month cumulative incidence of 36.0%, 95% CI: 27.2-<lb/>44.9) (Online Supplementary Figure S3). Twenty-four had <lb/>extensive disease and 17 had limited disease (unknown <lb/>for 1). Only the presence of a mismatched relative HLA <lb/>status of the donor was significantly associated with the <lb/>onset of chronic GvHD while having NF1, KRAS, and no/ <lb/>other mutation appeared to be protective factors (Online <lb/>Supplementary Table S4). The occurrence of acute GvHD <lb/>grade 3-4 did not significantly impact the 5-year EFS, which <lb/>was 69.0% (95% CI: 56.8-84.0) with acute GvHD, compared <lb/>to 65.4% without (95% CI: 54.5-78.6) (P=0.72). In contrast, <lb/>the occurrence of chronic GvHD led to a reduction in the <lb/>incidence of relapse or death, although not statistically <lb/>significant, with a 5-year EFS of 78.8% (95% CI: 64.7-96.1) <lb/>with chronic GvHD versus 68.3% without (95% CI: 59.5-78.4) <lb/>(P=0.09) (Online Supplementary Figure S3). <lb/>Patient outcome <lb/>The median follow-up after transplant was 59.5 months <lb/>(IQR: 21.7-118.6). The 5-year OS was 73.6% (95% CI: 65.7-<lb/>82.4), and the 10-year OS 72.2% (95% CI: 64.1-81.4) (Figure 2). <lb/>Twenty-eight patients relapsed after a median time of 4.6 <lb/>Figure 1. Flow chart of the transplanted juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia cohort. CR: complete remission; DOD: dead of disease; <lb/>HSCT: hematopoietic stem cell transplant; JMML: juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia; N: number; TRM: treatment-related mortality. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 109 September 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2913 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -HSCT in JMML <lb/>D. Meyran et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>months (range: 0.5-43.6) from HSCT, resulting in a 5-year <lb/>cumulative incidence of relapse (CIR) of 24.6% (95% CI: 17.1-<lb/>32.8). Twelve of them (43%) received a second allogeneic <lb/>transplant, including 6 with the same donor. Six patients <lb/>remained disease-free over a prolonged post-transplant <lb/>follow up (median 7 years, range 5-17) while 6 patients <lb/>relapsed once again (Figure 1). Five died of disease; none <lb/>from TRM. Time to relapse, time to second transplant, type <lb/>of donor and conditioning regimen did not differ between <lb/>the 2 groups. Of note, 4/6 who did not relapse developed <lb/>grade 2-4 acute GvHD while it occurred in 1/6 patients in the <lb/>relapse group. Among the 16 patients who relapsed but did <lb/>not receive a 2 nd transplant, 3 are still alive at three, eight <lb/>and nine years after HSCT. Patient #192, carrying a PTPN11 <lb/>mutation, received 7 cycles of azacitidine. Patient #44, <lb/>without any identified mutation, received weekly etoposide <lb/>injections for three months, followed by rapamycine until <lb/>the 6 th -month post HSCT. Finally, patient #55, with a CBL <lb/>mutation, achieved CR within a few months of a course of <lb/>6-mercaptopurine. <lb/>Twelve patients died from transplant toxicity with a median <lb/>time of 2.9 months (range, 23 days-67.2 months) result-<lb/>ing in an estimated TRM of 9.0% (95% CI: 4.6-15.3). Toxic <lb/>causes of deaths included severe GvHD + associated with <lb/>disseminated viral or bacterial infections (N=5), infections <lb/>(N=4), acute hepatitis of unknown origin (N=1), sinusoidal <lb/>obstruction syndrome (SOS) (N=1), and thrombotic micro-<lb/>angiopathy (N=1). SOS was observed in 32 patients (26.9%). <lb/>Of the 16 patients who did not engraft, 9 underwent a second <lb/>transplant within a year, in the absence of relapse (N=5) or <lb/>after JMML relapse (N=4) (Figure 1, Online Supplementary <lb/>Figure S2). Among the 7 patients who did not receive a <lb/>subsequent transplant, 3 died of disease recurrence. The <lb/>remaining 4 patients, comprising one CBL patient and 3 <lb/>KRAS patients, maintained sustained JMML remission with <lb/>autologous reconstitution. None had undergone splenec-<lb/>tomy before HSCT. The KRAS patients have been followed <lb/>up for five, eight, and ten years. <lb/>Two patients developed secondary malignancies. One pa-<lb/>tient with a KRAS mutation, who experienced graft failure, <lb/>developed T-cell precursor acute lymphoblastic leukemia <lb/>(ALL) seven years post HSCT while still in autologous re-<lb/>mission. Remarkably, the same KRAS p.Gly13Cys mutation <lb/>detected in the patient&apos;s JMML cells was also identified in <lb/>the acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) blast cells. Another <lb/>patient, who carried a PTPN11 mutation, developed AML <lb/>with minimal differentiation four years after transplant. <lb/>The PTPN11 p.Ala72Val mutation initially detected in JMML <lb/>was also found in the AML blasts. <lb/>Overall, 39 patients experienced an event, resulting in a <lb/>5-year EFS at 66.4% (95% CI: 58.2-75.8), and a 10-year EFS <lb/>at 65.0% (95% CI: 56.5-74.7) (Figure 2). Also considering <lb/>second transplants for graft failure without relapse and <lb/>secondary malignancies as events, the 5-year &apos;stringent <lb/>EFS&apos; was estimated at 63.6% (95% CI: 55.3-73.3) (Online <lb/>Supplementary Figure S4). <lb/>Prognostic factors for overall survival, event-free <lb/>survival, relapse and treatment-related mortality <lb/>Table 3 presents the univariate analysis of the patients&apos; <lb/>characteristics that influence the outcomes. Age at diagnosis <lb/>or age at transplant &gt;2 years, as well as a monocyte count <lb/>at diagnosis &gt;3 rd quartile (&gt;7.2x10 9 /L), were associated with <lb/>a lower rate of OS, EFS, and &apos;stringent EFS&apos; (Table 3, Figure <lb/>3, Online Supplementary Table S5). The negative effect of <lb/>monocyte count on survival was linked to a higher incidence <lb/>of relapse (Figure 3). Monocytes &gt;7.2x10 9 /L were associated <lb/>with higher white blood cell, neutrophil, and lymphocyte <lb/>counts, as well as a higher BM blast percentage but were <lb/>not correlated with platelet count, HbF levels, cytogenetic <lb/>features, or molecular features (Online Supplementary Table <lb/>S6). Although patients with NF1 mutations tended to show <lb/>worse outcomes, no significant association was found be-<lb/>tween RAS initiating variants and OS, EFS, or cumulative <lb/>incidence of relapse (CIR) (Figure 3). Considered individually, <lb/>abnormal karyotype, pathogenic variants of SETBP1, ASXL1, <lb/>JAK3 or additional RAS mutation had no impact on outcome. <lb/>However, when analyzed collectively, the presence of any <lb/>Figure 2. Estimated outcomes of the 119 transplanted patients. Overall survival (OS) (A) and event-free survival (EFS) (B) were <lb/>analyzed using Kaplan-Meier methodology. Cumulative incidence function for relapse and treatment-related mortality (TRM) (C). <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 109 September 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2914 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -HSCT in JMML <lb/>D. Meyran et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>Table 3. Univariable predictive analyses of the outcomes based on Cox models. <lb/>Outcomes <lb/>N of patients <lb/>OS % <lb/>EFS % <lb/>Relapse % <lb/>TRM % <lb/>60-month OS <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>60-month EFS <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>60-month <lb/>cumulative <lb/>incidence <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>60-month <lb/>cumulative <lb/>incidence <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>Overall <lb/>119 <lb/>73.6 (65.7-82.4) <lb/>66.4 (58.2-75.8) <lb/>24.6 (17.1-32.8) <lb/>9.0 (4.6-15.3) <lb/>N of events <lb/>-<lb/>30 deaths <lb/>39 events <lb/>28 relapses <lb/>11 toxic deaths <lb/>Age at diagnosis &gt; 2 yr <lb/>55 <lb/>3.08 (1.41-6.74) + <lb/>2.34 (1.22-4.51) + <lb/>1.99 (0.93-4.24) <lb/>3.68 (0.97-13.9) <lb/>Platelets &lt;33x10 9 /L <lb/>28 <lb/>0.88 (0.36-2.18) <lb/>1.01 (0.48-2.15) <lb/>0.93 (0.38-2.33) <lb/>1.21 (0.32-4.58) <lb/>Monocytes &gt; Q3 (7.2 x10 9 /L) <lb/>30 <lb/>2.21 (1.06-4.60) + <lb/>2.38 (1.24-4.54) + <lb/>2.90 (1.37-6.14) + <lb/>1.36 (0.36-5.15) <lb/>Elevated HbF* <lb/>73/88 <lb/>0.84 (0.35-1.97) <lb/>1.30 (0.63-2.70) <lb/>0.76 (0.32-1.80) <lb/>1.23 (0.27-5.70) <lb/>Abnormal karyotype <lb/>45 <lb/>1.77 (0.84-3.75) <lb/>1.45 (0.76-2.77) <lb/>1.82 (0.84-3.96) <lb/>1.67 (0.51-5.47) <lb/>RAS-pathway mutations <lb/>PTPN11 <lb/>CBL <lb/>KRAS <lb/>NF1 <lb/>NRAS <lb/>No/other <lb/>46 <lb/>7 <lb/>26 <lb/>8 <lb/>23 <lb/>9 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>NA <lb/>0.35 (0.10-1.21) <lb/>2.79 (0.99-7.88) <lb/>1.38 (0.57-3.33) <lb/>0.35 (0.05-2.69) <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.38 (0.05-2.85) <lb/>0.44 (0.16-1.20) <lb/>1.98 (0.73-5.38) <lb/>1.00 (0.43-2.32) <lb/>0.92 (0.27-3.13) <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.43 (0.04-4.13) <lb/>0.29 (0.06-1.44) <lb/>2.10 (0.50-8.83) <lb/>0.70 (0.17-2.91) <lb/>0.71 (0.20-2.56) <lb/>1.00 <lb/>NA <lb/>0.50 (0.10-2.49) <lb/>NA <lb/>1.05 (0.26-4.18) <lb/>NA <lb/>Additional mutations <lb/>JAK3 <lb/>SETBP1 <lb/>ASXL1 <lb/>Double RAS pathway mutation <lb/>10 <lb/>9 <lb/>11 <lb/>25 <lb/>1.55 (0.54-4.47) <lb/>2.58 (0.98-6.77) <lb/>1.65 (0.57-4.74) <lb/>0.96 (0.39-2.36) <lb/>2.00 (0.84-4.81) <lb/>2.38 (0.99-5.70) <lb/>1.09 (0.39-3.08) <lb/>0.94 (0.43-2.06) <lb/>0.69 (0.26-1.87) <lb/>0.74 (0.22-2.53) <lb/>0.70 (0.20-2.43) <lb/>0.86 (0.29-2.53) <lb/>1.20 (0.15-9.41) <lb/>4.68 (1.24-17.69) + <lb/>0.96 (0.12-7.50) <lb/>2.10 (0.62-7.19) <lb/>Additional alteration** <lb/>≥1 Alteration <lb/>≥2 Alterations <lb/>67 <lb/>20 <lb/>2.55 (1.04-6.27) + <lb/>1.51 (0.64-3.53) <lb/>2.10 (0.99-4.44) <lb/>1.68 (0.82-3.47) <lb/>0.82 (0.35-1.95) <lb/>0.45 (0.18-1.12) <lb/>NA <lb/>1.94 (0.51-7.36) <lb/>Pre-HSCT treatment <lb/>Low-dose chemotherapy <lb/>No chemotherapy <lb/>AML-type chemotherapy <lb/>77 <lb/>13 <lb/>28 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.50 (0.12-2.12) <lb/>0.69 (0.28-1.71) <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.30 (0.07-1.25) <lb/>0.88 (0.45-1.75) <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.28 (0.04-2.12) <lb/>1.41 (0.63-3.13) <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.67 (0.08-5.35) <lb/>0.70 (0.15-3.32) <lb/>Pre-HSCT BM ≥ 5% <lb/>42 <lb/>1.05 (0.50-2.22) <lb/>0.84 (0.45-1.55) <lb/>0.98 (0.45-2.11) <lb/>1.04 (0.31-3.56) <lb/>Time to HSCT ≥ 6 mth <lb/>52 <lb/>2.65 (1.26-5.58) + <lb/>1.46 (0.82-2.61) <lb/>1.52 (0.72-3.18) <lb/>3.78 (1.00-14.2) + <lb/>Donor <lb/>Genoidentical sibling <lb/>Matched unrelated <lb/>Mismatched relative <lb/>Mismatch unrelated <lb/>24 <lb/>46 <lb/>4 <lb/>45 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.54 (0.22-1.33) <lb/>NA <lb/>0.62 (0.26-1.49) <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.60 (0.27-1.32) <lb/>0.50 (0.06-3.89) <lb/>1.00 (0.48-2.09) <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.41 (0.17-1.02) <lb/>0.55 (0.07-4.26) <lb/>0.43 (0.17-1.10) <lb/>1.00 <lb/>1.33 (0.14-12.9) <lb/>NA <lb/>3.43 (0.42-28.0) <lb/>HLA disparities &gt;2 <lb/>40 <lb/>0.77 (0.35-1.68) <lb/>1.11 (0.61-2.03) <lb/>0.64 (0.27-1.50) <lb/>3.09 (0.90-10.6) <lb/>Stem cells <lb/>Bone marrow <lb/>Cord blood <lb/>Peripheral blood <lb/>70 <lb/>39 <lb/>10 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.81 (0.37-1.80) <lb/>0.72 (0.17-3.10) <lb/>1.00 <lb/>1.07 (0.58-1.97) <lb/>0.48 (0.11-2.01) <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.54 (0.22-1.35) <lb/>0.70 (0.16-3.01) <lb/>1.00 <lb/>2.87 (0.84-9.83) <lb/>NA <lb/>Conditioning <lb/>Bu/Cy/Mel <lb/>Bu/Flu/Mel <lb/>Other <lb/>41 <lb/>46 <lb/>32 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>1.35 (0.58-3.13) <lb/>1.20 (0.47-3.05) <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.87 (0.42-1.83) <lb/>2.04 (1.03-4.05) + <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.34 (0.11-1.04) <lb/>1.77 (0.79-3.95) <lb/>1.00 <lb/>4.26 (0.90-20.29) <lb/>0.84 (0.08-9.26) <lb/>NA refers to the models that do not converge due to too low a number of events in one stratum. + Significant results. *For patients ≥6 months. <lb/>**At least 1 or 2 alterations among the following genes: ASXL1, JAK3, SETBP1, or double RAS mutation or karyotype anomaly. AML: acute my-<lb/>eloid leukemia; BM: bone marrow; Bu/Cy/Mel: busulfan / cyclophosphamide / melphalan; Bu/Flu/Mel: busulfan / fludarabine / melphalan; CB: <lb/>cord blood; EFS: event-free survival; HbF: fetal hemoglobin; HSCT: hematopoietic stem cell transplantation; mth: months; N: number; OS: <lb/>overall survival; PB: peripheral blood; TRM: treatment-related mortality; yr: years. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 109 September 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2915 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -HSCT in JMML <lb/>D. Meyran et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>of them had a negative impact on OS (Table 3). Conditioning <lb/>regimens other than Bu/Cy/Mel or Bu/Flu/Mel were associ-<lb/>ated with lower EFS. Finally, time to HSCT &gt;6 months had a <lb/>negative impact on OS related to a higher TRM. <lb/>The multivariable model confirmed the prognostic impact <lb/>of monocyte count on OS, EFS and relapse. Age at diagnosis <lb/>remained significant for OS and EFS. Additionally, time to <lb/>HSCT and any additional alteration were found significant <lb/>for OS (Table 4). <lb/>Finally, we derived a prognostic classifier based on the 4 pre-<lb/>dictors of death in the multivariate analysis (age at diagnosis, <lb/>time to transplant, monocyte count and any additional alter-<lb/>ation). This classifier defined prognostic groups of patients <lb/>with 5-year OS ranging from 34.2% for patients with at least <lb/>3 predictors (N=23, 20.7%) to 100% for patients with none of <lb/>the four predictors (N=8, 7%) (Figure 4). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>We present here a comprehensive analysis of the outcome <lb/>of a large cohort of transplanted JMML patients. All patients <lb/>met the JMML diagnostic criteria, recently revised in the <lb/>WHO classification, including genetic characterization, which <lb/>enables us to formally establish the JMML diagnosis. 24,25 <lb/>With a 5-year EFS of 66% and OS of 74%, our results <lb/>compare favorably with previous published studies 5,7-10,26-30 <lb/>(Online Supplementary Table S7). The improvement in OS <lb/>among JMML patients over time has been remarkable, <lb/>with survival rates increasing from 31% in the 1990s to <lb/>72% in the most recent reports. 31 While the results have <lb/>plateaued in recent years, it is important to consider that <lb/>the composition of the transplanted cohorts has changed <lb/>over time, gradually leading to the exclusion of patients <lb/>with the most favorable prognosis. Indeed, it has been <lb/>demonstrated that patients with CBL mutations experience <lb/>a naturally favorable evolution and may no longer require <lb/>HSCT, unless they demonstrate an aggressive clinical course <lb/>or a high mutational burden. 32 Additionally, a smaller sub-<lb/>set of NRAS patients with non-high-risk features can also <lb/>avoid HSCT. Despite encompassing a time span of over 20 <lb/>years, the incidence of CBL mutations in our transplanted <lb/>Figure 3. Effect of monocyte count and ini-<lb/>tiating RAS-mutation on outcomes. Effect <lb/>of monocyte count: (A) overall survival (OS) <lb/>and (B) cumulative incidence function of <lb/>relapse. Effect of initiating RAS-mutation: <lb/>(C) OS and (D) event-free survival (EFS). OS <lb/>and EFS were analyzed using Kaplan-Meier <lb/>methodology. HSCT: hematopoietic stem cell <lb/>transplant. <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>B <lb/>D <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 109 September 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2916 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -HSCT in JMML <lb/>D. Meyran et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>series (6%) is lower than the typical expectation for JMML <lb/>at diagnosis. This difference probably reflects the imple-<lb/>mentation of the &apos;watch-and-wait&apos; recommendations for <lb/>these patients. As the proportion of transplanted patients <lb/>with more severe conditions increased over time, it is rea-<lb/>sonable to infer that the observed improvement in OS and <lb/>EFS in our study are significant. <lb/>In our cohort, the survival improvement can be attributed <lb/>to a reduction in TRM, coupled with a decrease in relapse <lb/>incidence, which nevertheless still accounts for approx-<lb/>imately one-quarter of patient deaths and remains the <lb/>leading cause of mortality. Indeed, the relapse incidence <lb/>in our cohort was estimated at 25%, which is lower com-<lb/>pared to most reported series where it often surpassed <lb/>30% (Online Supplementary Table S7). Previous studies have <lb/>demonstrated the critical role of both acute and chronic <lb/>GvHD in preventing disease recurrence. 8,9,28,33 Consistent <lb/>with these findings, we noted a significant association <lb/>between chronic GvHD and improved CIR, which can be <lb/>attributed to the potent graft-versus-leukemia (GvL) effect. <lb/>The high incidence of GvHD in our cohort may be related <lb/>to the frequent utilization of unrelated donors and could <lb/>also reflect physicians&apos; endeavors to enhance alloreactivity <lb/>in patients known to be sensitive to GvL through the ac-<lb/>celerated tapering of immunosuppressors, although these <lb/>data were not captured. The impact of GvHD on disease <lb/>control following a 2 nd transplant is suggested in our co-<lb/>hort. However, its translation into OS could be hindered by <lb/>the TRM associated with extensive GvHD, as reported in <lb/>a recent series. 34 The TRM in our cohort was evaluated at <lb/>9%, which is below the levels observed in earlier studies, <lb/>where reported TRM exceeded 10% (Online Supplementary <lb/>Table S7). This improvement may be attributed to the overall <lb/>advancement in supportive care in transplantation over <lb/>time, the limited use of total body irradiation in our cohort <lb/>and the low frequency of HLA mismatched donors. Our <lb/>analysis identified that an extended duration between di-<lb/>agnosis and transplant has a negative impact on TRM and <lb/>OS. This variable encompasses several parameters that <lb/>could contribute to an increased TRM, including iterative <lb/>transfusions, compromised nutritional status, and infec-<lb/>tions. The specific factors influencing the decision of the <lb/>transplant date have not been identified within our cohort. <lb/>These factors could encompass organizational constraints, <lb/>including graft availability, or disease-related considerations, <lb/>such as the aggressive nature of JMML requiring multiple <lb/>courses of chemotherapy. However, within our patient <lb/>series, the median time from diagnosis to HSCT remained <lb/>consistent, both for patients requiring AML-type chemo-<lb/>therapy and those who had no or low-dose chemotherapy. <lb/>This finding suggests that transplantation was sometimes <lb/>planned with a considerable long delay, even for patients <lb/>with non-aggressive diseases. Given the impact of this delay <lb/>on TRM, our results suggest the prompt scheduling of the <lb/>transplant once the diagnosis of JMML is confirmed. The <lb/>association between SETBP1 and TRM is more difficult to <lb/>understand and may be biased by the limited size of this <lb/>group. The Japanese group adopted the Bu/Flu/Mel reg-<lb/>imen in JMML with promising results, aiming to mitigate <lb/>the toxicity associated with the triple alkylation of the Bu/ <lb/>Cy/Mel regimen. 10,35 Although there is no evidence favoring <lb/>one of these two conditioning regimens over the other <lb/>in the literature, it is crucial to recognize the pivotal role <lb/>of their intensity. Notably, in the only randomized study <lb/>focusing on JMML conditioning, attempts to reduce the <lb/>regimen&apos;s intensity were unsuccessful, as Bu/Flu resulted <lb/>in a significantly higher relapse rate when compared to <lb/>Bu/Cy/Mel. 28 In our study, both Bu/Flu/Mel and Bu/Cy/Mel <lb/>conditionings led to similar EFS and OS, while other types <lb/>of conditioning impaired EFS. <lb/>Five patients with autologous reconstitution survived. In <lb/>CBL patients, as in NRAS patients, this outcome is expected <lb/>Table 4. Multivariate analyses for overall survival, event-free <lb/>survival and relapse. <lb/>Outcome/model <lb/>HR (95% CI) <lb/>P <lb/>Overall survival <lb/>Age &gt;2 years at diagnosis <lb/>Time to HSCT ≥ 6 months <lb/>Monocytes &gt;7.2 x10 9 /L <lb/>&gt;1 additional alteration <lb/>3.14 (1.31-7.51) <lb/>6.48 (2.84-14.76) <lb/>3.59 (1.65-7.84) <lb/>2.88 (1.05-7.86) <lb/>0.010 <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>0.001 <lb/>0.039 <lb/>Event-free survival <lb/>Age &gt;2 years at diagnosis <lb/>Monocytes &gt;7.2 x10 9 /L <lb/>2.61 (1.35-5.05) <lb/>2.70 (1.40-5.18) <lb/>0.0044 <lb/>0.0029 <lb/>Relapse <lb/>Monocytes &gt;7.2 x10 9 /L <lb/>4.07 (1.82-9.09) <lb/>0.00061 <lb/>HR: Hazard Ratio; HSCT: hematopoietic stem cell transplantation. <lb/>Figure 4. Prognostic classifier for overall survival. This classi-<lb/>fier defined 4 prognostic groups of patients according to the 4 <lb/>predictor factors from the multivariate analysis. OS: overall <lb/>survival; HSCT: hematopoietic stem cell transplant. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 109 September 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2917 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -HSCT in JMML <lb/>D. Meyran et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>as many of them show a spontaneously favorable evolu-<lb/>tion without HSCT. On the contrary, patients with KRAS <lb/>mutations typically have an aggressive disease course and <lb/>require HSCT to be cured. Nevertheless, case reports have <lb/>described prolonged remissions in some KRAS patients <lb/>treated with azacitidine or without any treatment at all. 36-38 <lb/>It has also been reported that patients with Ras-associ-<lb/>ated autoimmune leukoproliferative disorder (RALD), car-<lb/>rying the same somatic KRAS mutations as in JMML, can <lb/>present an indolent condition difficult to distinguish from <lb/>JMML. 39 In our cohort, the 3 KRAS patients who survived <lb/>with autologous reconstitution had no clinical autoimmune <lb/>manifestations or immunophenotypic abnormalities. While <lb/>the conditioning regimen and the transient presence of <lb/>allogeneic stem cells could have contributed to disease <lb/>control, our findings are consistent with observations in <lb/>RALD and indolent KRAS JMML cases, suggesting that <lb/>KRAS-mutated patients might encompass a spectrum of <lb/>conditions ranging from mild to highly aggressive diseases. <lb/>Exploring this matter further remains essential to refine <lb/>treatment strategies and accurately differentiate patients <lb/>who truly require transplantation from those who could <lb/>potentially avoid it. 40 <lb/>Age at diagnosis over one, two or four years and time be-<lb/>tween diagnosis and HSCT over six months, which have <lb/>been consistently described by independent study groups to <lb/>influence the outcome of transplanted JMML patients, were <lb/>also identified in our cohort to alter survival in multivariate <lb/>analysis (Online Supplementary Table S7). Conversely, other <lb/>classical prognostic factors such as platelet counts &lt;33x10 9 /L, <lb/>elevated HbF for age, elevated BM blast percentage and <lb/>abnormal karyotype were not found to influence outcome. <lb/>Some of these prognostic markers have been demonstrat-<lb/>ed to be closely related to the genetic background of the <lb/>disease, PTPN11 or NF1-JMML tending to harbor significantly <lb/>lower platelet count, higher HbF or more frequent karyotypic <lb/>alteration than CBL or NRAS-JMML. 41 As previously discussed, <lb/>when considering the comparability of studies conducted <lb/>over time, the prognostic impact of some markers may have <lb/>been lost in this selected aggressive group of JMML patients. <lb/>Additionally, it is plausible that the relatively limited num-<lb/>ber of patients included in our study may have resulted in <lb/>insufficient statistical power to detect their influence on <lb/>survival. The role of pre-transplant chemotherapy in sur-<lb/>vival for patients with JMML remains controversial. In line <lb/>with previous studies, we did not find any difference in EFS, <lb/>or relapse incidence based on the chemotherapy regimen <lb/>received before transplant. 6,8 This finding reaffirms that pa-<lb/>tients with a clinical condition compatible with low-intensity <lb/>treatment do not require intensive chemotherapy. Due to the <lb/>infrequent use of azacitidine in our cohort, we were unable <lb/>to compare the outcomes of this subgroup with those of <lb/>patients who received 6-mercaptopurine. <lb/>Among our 8 patients who received azacitidine, 3 relapsed <lb/>after transplant and 4 died consequently to relapse or TRM <lb/>(N=1). The European Working Group (EWOG) recently pub-<lb/>lished the prospective AZA-JMML-001 trial, investigating the <lb/>impact of pre-transplant azacitidine in 18 patients. After 3 <lb/>cycles, 61% of patients showed a partial response, and 14 <lb/>achieved complete remission (CR) after HSCT during a 2-year <lb/>follow-up. 42 The recent wider use of azacitidine will allow <lb/>us to determine on a larger scale whether this approach in-<lb/>deed yields a positive impact on post-transplant outcomes. <lb/>In JMML, secondary genetic alterations including karyotype <lb/>anomalies and additional mutations of the RAS pathway <lb/>or SETBP1, ASXL1 and JAK3 have been demonstrated to be <lb/>associated with an unfavorable prognosis. This has been <lb/>highlighted by studies conducted by our group and others in <lb/>unbiased cohorts of JMML patients, including transplanted <lb/>and non-transplanted ones. 13,14 In this study, we confirm the <lb/>relevance of these secondary alterations in a selected pop-<lb/>ulation of transplanted patients and found that the number <lb/>of genetic alterations, rather than the type of the alteration, <lb/>was the main determinant factor for OS. However, secondary <lb/>alterations did not impact the incidence of relapse. Unlike <lb/>secondary alterations, the initiating RAS-pathway alterations <lb/>were not associated with the outcome in our study, possibly <lb/>due to insufficient statistical power. Indeed, CBL patients <lb/>exhibited an excellent prognosis while NF1 patients had the <lb/>worst survival rates due to a high incidence of relapse, in <lb/>line with results from previous studies. 13,14 In recent years, <lb/>DNA methylation profiling has emerged as a novel prognostic <lb/>marker in JMML, as demonstrated in 3 distinct patient co-<lb/>horts. 41,43,44 This methylation profile has shown associations <lb/>with disease biology and clinical outcomes. Methylation has <lb/>not been investigated in the current cohort, but it would be <lb/>intriguing to explore its relevance as a prognostic marker <lb/>in a cohort of transplanted JMML patients, predominantly <lb/>comprising patients with high-risk features. <lb/>In addition, our study shows that monocyte count &gt;7.2x10 9 /L <lb/>was an independent factor of adverse outcomes and relapse. <lb/>To our knowledge, this is the first time that monocyte count <lb/>has been identified as a prognostic factor for JMML, although <lb/>this variable has not often been evaluated in past series. <lb/>Monocytosis in PB is the hallmark of JMML and is a mandatory <lb/>criterion to ascertain the diagnosis. Elevated monocyte count <lb/>has been linked to disease aggressiveness and worse survival <lb/>in adult myelodysplastic syndromes, myeloproliferative neo-<lb/>plasms, and chronic myelomonocytic leukemia (CMML). 45-48 <lb/>In CMML, the closest adult counterpart of JMML, different <lb/>subsets of monocytes, as well as their levels, may play a role in <lb/>the outcome of patients, with a specific inflammatory fraction <lb/>being associated with a poor prognosis. 49-51 The distribution of <lb/>the different monocyte fractions in JMML has not yet been <lb/>thoroughly explored, and, therefore, we could not correlate <lb/>our findings with a comprehensive immunophenotypic and <lb/>functional analysis. It would be valuable to investigate this in <lb/>the future to determine if the adverse outcomes are linked <lb/>to a specific subset. <lb/>Overall, this study underscores promising survival outcome <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 109 September 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2918 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -HSCT in JMML <lb/>D. Meyran et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>for transplanted JMML patients that can primarily be at-<lb/>tributed to the remarkably low TRM. However, it is import-<lb/>ant to note the persistent high relapse rate, which reflects <lb/>the limited availability of novel and effective anti-tumoral <lb/>agents. We confirmed, on a genetically tested cohort, the <lb/>significant impact of additional alterations on prognosis <lb/>and found that elevated monocyte count is independently <lb/>correlated with poor outcome. The prognostic classifier <lb/>we developed identifies transplanted patients who are <lb/>most susceptible to relapse and who could benefit from <lb/>post-transplant interventions. This personalized approach <lb/>holds promise for improving the outcomes and long-term <lb/>survival of high-risk JMML patients after transplantation. <lb/></body>

        <div type="conflict">Disclosures <lb/>No conflicts of interest to disclose. <lb/></div>

        <div type="contribution">Contributions <lb/>DM collected data and wrote the manuscript. CA and ACE <lb/>performed genetic analyses and produced data. SC pro-<lb/>duced statistical analysis. EL reviewed cytological data. <lb/>QN collected and reviewed clinical data. AP, FR, GM, DP, <lb/>CJ, AT, VG, MOC, CP, BB, NB, CP, CC, MF and AB provided <lb/>clinical assessments. HC supervised genomic analyses, <lb/>co-ordinated the project, and wrote the manuscript. JHD <lb/>co-ordinated the project and wrote the manuscript. MS <lb/>designed and co-ordinated the project, supervised data <lb/>collection, and wrote the manuscript. All authors reviewed <lb/>the manuscript. <lb/></div>

        <div type="availability">Data-sharing statement <lb/>The data that support the findings of this study are available <lb/>on request from the corresponding author. <lb/></div>

        <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Arfeuille C, Vial Y, Cadenet M, et al. Germline bi-allelic SH2B3/ <lb/>LNK alteration predisposes to a neonatal juvenile <lb/>myelomonocytic leukemia-like disorder. Haematologica. 2023 <lb/>Nov 16. doi: 10.3324/haematol.2023.283917. [Epub ahead of print]. <lb/>2. Khoury JD, Solary E, Abla O, et al. The 5th edition of the World <lb/>Health Organization Classification of Haematolymphoid <lb/>Tumours: Myeloid and Histiocytic/Dendritic Neoplasms. <lb/>Leukemia. 2022;36(7):1703-1719. <lb/>3. Niemeyer CM, Flotho C. Juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia: <lb/>who&apos;s the driver at the wheel? Blood. 2019;133(10):1060-1070. <lb/>4. Loh ML. Recent advances in the pathogenesis and treatment of <lb/>juvenile myelomonocytic leukaemia. Br J Haematol. <lb/>2011;152(6):677-687. <lb/>5. De Vos N, Hofmans M, Lammens T, De Wilde B, Van Roy N, De <lb/>Moerloose B. Targeted therapy in juvenile myelomonocytic <lb/>leukemia: where are we now? Pediatr Blood Cancer. <lb/>2022;69(11):e29930. <lb/>6. Locatelli F, Nöllke P, Zecca M, et al. Hematopoietic stem cell <lb/>transplantation (HSCT) in children with juvenile <lb/>myelomonocytic leukemia (JMML): results of the EWOG-MDS/ <lb/>EBMT trial. Blood. 2005;105(1):410-419. <lb/>7. Locatelli F, Crotta A, Ruggeri A, et al. Analysis of risk factors <lb/>influencing outcomes after cord blood transplantation in <lb/>children with juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia: a EUROCORD, <lb/>EBMT, EWOG-MDS, CIBMTR study. Blood. 2013;122(12):2135-2141. <lb/>8. Yoshida N, Sakaguchi H, Yabe M, et al. Clinical outcomes after <lb/>allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation in children <lb/>with juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia: a report from the <lb/>Japan Society for Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation. Biol <lb/>Blood Marrow Transplant. 2020;26(5):902-910. <lb/>9. Yi ES, Kim SK, Ju HY, et al. Allogeneic hematopoietic cell <lb/>transplantation in patients with juvenile myelomonocytic <lb/>leukemia in Korea: a report of the Korean Pediatric Hematology-<lb/>Oncology Group. Bone Marrow Transplant. 2023;58(1):20-29. <lb/>10. Yabe M, Ohtsuka Y, Watanabe K, et al. Transplantation for <lb/>juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia: a retrospective study of 30 <lb/>children treated with a regimen of busulfan, fludarabine, and <lb/>melphalan. Int J Hematol. 2015;101(2):184-190. <lb/>11. Niemeyer CM, Arico M, Basso G, et al. Chronic myelomonocytic <lb/>leukemia in childhood: a retrospective analysis of 110 cases. <lb/>European Working Group on Myelodysplastic Syndromes in <lb/>Childhood (EWOG-MDS). Blood. 1997;89(10):3534-3543. <lb/>12. Hasle H, Baumann I, Bergsträsser E, et al. The International <lb/>Prognostic Scoring System (IPSS) for childhood myelodysplastic <lb/>syndrome (MDS) and juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia (JMML). <lb/>Leukemia. 2004;18(12):2008-2014. <lb/>13. Caye A, Strullu M, Guidez F, et al. Juvenile myelomonocytic <lb/>leukemia displays mutations in components of the RAS pathway <lb/>and the PRC2 network. Nat Genet. 2015;47(11):1334-1340. <lb/>14. Stieglitz E, Taylor-Weiner AN, Chang TY, et al. The genomic <lb/>landscape of juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. Nat Genet. <lb/>2015;47(11):1326-1333. <lb/>15. Sakaguchi H, Okuno Y, Muramatsu H, et al. Exome sequencing <lb/>identifies secondary mutations of SETBP1 and JAK3 in juvenile <lb/>myelomonocytic leukemia. Nat Genet. 2013;45(8):937-941. <lb/>16. Sugimoto Y, Muramatsu H, Makishima H, et al. Spectrum of <lb/>molecular defects in juvenile myelomonocytic leukaemia <lb/>includes ASXL1 mutations. Br J Haematol. 2010;150(1):83-87. <lb/>17. Pérez B, Kosmider O, Cassinat B, et al. Genetic typing of CBL, <lb/>ASXL1, RUNX1, TET2 and JAK2 in juvenile myelomonocytic <lb/>leukaemia reveals a genetic profile distinct from chronic <lb/>myelomonocytic leukaemia. Br J Haematol. 2010;151(5):460-468. <lb/>18. Przepiorka D, Weisdorf D, Martin P, et al. 1994 Consensus <lb/>Conference on Acute GVHD Grading. Bone Marrow Transplant. <lb/>1995;15(6):825-828. <lb/>19. Jagasia MH, Greinix HT, Arora M, et al. National Institutes of <lb/>Health Consensus Development Project on Criteria for Clinical <lb/>Trials in Chronic Graft-versus-Host Disease: I. The 2014 <lb/>Diagnosis and Staging Working Group report. Biol Blood Marrow <lb/>Transplant. 2015;21(3):389-401. <lb/>20. Prentice RL. The statistical analysis of failure time data. 2nd ed. <lb/>Hoboken, NJ: J. Wiley; 2010. <lb/>21. Prentice RL, Kalbfleisch JD, Peterson AV, Flournoy N, Farewell <lb/>VT, Breslow NE. The analysis of failure times in the presence of <lb/>competing risks. Biometrics. 1978;34(4):541-554. <lb/>22. White IR, Royston P. Imputing missing covariate values for the <lb/>Cox model. Stat Med. 2009;28(15):1982-1998. <lb/>23. Grambsch PM, Therneau TM. Proportional hazards tests and <lb/>diagnostics based on weighted residuals. Biometrika. <lb/>1994;81(3):515-526. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 109 September 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2919 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -HSCT in JMML <lb/>D. Meyran et al. <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>24. Niemeyer CM. JMML genomics and decisions. Hematology Am <lb/>Soc Hematol Educ Program. 2018;2018(1):307-312. <lb/>25. Yoshimi A, Kamachi Y, Imai K, et al. Wiskott-Aldrich syndrome <lb/>presenting with a clinical picture mimicking juvenile <lb/>myelomonocytic leukaemia. Pediatr Blood Cancer. <lb/>2013;60(5):836-841. <lb/>26. Manabe A, Okamura J, Yumura-Yagi K, et al. Allogeneic <lb/>hematopoietic stem cell transplantation for 27 children with <lb/>juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia diagnosed based on the <lb/>criteria of the International JMML Working Group. Leukemia. <lb/>2002;16(4):645-649. <lb/>27. Stieglitz E, Ward AF, Gerbing RB, et al. Phase II/III trial of a <lb/>pre-transplant farnesyl transferase inhibitor in juvenile <lb/>myelomonocytic leukemia: a report from the Children&apos;s <lb/>Oncology Group. Pediatr Blood Cancer. 2015;62(4):629-636. <lb/>28. Dvorak CC, Satwani P, Stieglitz E, et al. Disease burden and <lb/>conditioning regimens in ASCT1221, a randomized phase II trial <lb/>in children with juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia: a Children&apos;s <lb/>Oncology Group study. Pediatr Blood Cancer. 2018;65(7):e27034. <lb/>29. Lin Y-C, Luo C-J, Miao Y, et al. Human leukocyte antigen <lb/>disparities reduce relapse after hematopoietic stem cell <lb/>transplantation in children with juvenile myelomonocytic <lb/>leukemia: a single-center retrospective study from China. <lb/>Pediatr Transplant. 2021;25(2):e13825. <lb/>30. Smith FO, King R, Nelson G, et al. Unrelated donor bone marrow <lb/>transplantation for children with juvenile myelomonocytic <lb/>leukaemia. Br J Haematol. 2002;116(3):716-724. <lb/>31. Locatelli F, Niemeyer C, Angelucci E, et al. Allogeneic bone <lb/>marrow transplantation for chronic myelomonocytic leukemia <lb/>in childhood: a report from the European Working Group on <lb/>Myelodysplastic Syndrome in Childhood. J Clin Oncol. <lb/>1997;15(2):566-573. <lb/>32. Niemeyer CM, Kang MW, Shin DH, et al. Germline CBL mutations <lb/>cause developmental abnormalities and predispose to juvenile <lb/>myelomonocytic leukemia. Nat Genet. 2010;42(9):794-800. <lb/>33. Hecht A, Meyer J, Chehab FF, et al. Molecular assessment of <lb/>pretransplant chemotherapy in the treatment of juvenile <lb/>myelomonocytic leukemia. Pediatr Blood Cancer. <lb/>2019;66(11):e27948. <lb/>34. Vinci L, Flotho C, Noellke P, et al. Second allogeneic stem cell <lb/>transplantation can rescue a significant proportion of patients <lb/>with JMML relapsing after first allograft. Bone Marrow <lb/>Transplant. 2023;58(5):607-609. <lb/>35. Yabe M, Sako M, Yabe H, et al. A conditioning regimen of <lb/>busulfan, fludarabine, and melphalan for allogeneic stem cell <lb/>transplantation in children with juvenile myelomonocytic <lb/>leukemia. Pediatr Transplant. 2008;12(8):862-867. <lb/>36. Hashmi SK, Punia JN, Marcogliese AN, et al. Sustained <lb/>remission with azacitidine monotherapy and an aberrant <lb/>precursor B-lymphoblast population in juvenile myelomonocytic <lb/>leukemia. Pediatr Blood Cancer. 2019;66(10):e27905. <lb/>37. Furlan I, Batz C, Flotho C, et al. Intriguing response to <lb/>azacitidine in a patient with juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia <lb/>and monosomy 7. Blood. 2009;113(12):2867-2868. <lb/>38. Matsuda K, Shimada A, Yoshida N, et al. Spontaneous <lb/>improvement of hematologic abnormalities in patients having <lb/>juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia with specific RAS mutations. <lb/>Blood. 2007;109(12):5477-5480. <lb/>39. Calvo KR, Price S, Braylan RC, et al. JMML and RALD (Ras-<lb/>associated autoimmune leukoproliferative disorder): common <lb/>genetic etiology yet clinically distinct entities. Blood. <lb/>2015;125(18):2753-2758. <lb/>40. Mayerhofer C, Niemeyer CM, Flotho C. Current treatment of <lb/>juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. J Clin Med. 2021;10(14):3084. <lb/>41. Murakami N, Okuno Y, Yoshida K, et al. Integrated molecular <lb/>profiling of juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia. Blood. <lb/>2018;131(14):1576-1586. <lb/>42. Niemeyer CM, Flotho C, Lipka DB, et al. Response to upfront <lb/>azacitidine in juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia in the AZA-<lb/>JMML-001 trial. Blood Adv. 2021;5(14):2901-2908. <lb/>43. Stieglitz E, Mazor T, Olshen AB, et al. Genome-wide DNA <lb/>methylation is predictive of outcome in juvenile <lb/>myelomonocytic leukemia. Nat Commun. 2017;8(1):2127. <lb/>44. Lipka DB, Witte T, Toth R, et al. RAS-pathway mutation patterns <lb/>define epigenetic subclasses in juvenile myelomonocytic <lb/>leukemia. Nat Commun. 2017;8(1):2126. <lb/>45. Tefferi A, Shah S, Mudireddy M, et al. Monocytosis is a powerful <lb/>and independent predictor of inferior survival in primary <lb/>myelofibrosis. Br J Haematol. 2018;183(5):835-838. <lb/>46. Patnaik MM, Tefferi A. Chronic myelomonocytic leukemia: 2022 <lb/>update on diagnosis, risk stratification, and management. Am J <lb/>Hematol. 2022;97(3):352-372. <lb/>47. Patnaik MM, Padron E, LaBorde RR, et al. Mayo prognostic <lb/>model for WHO-defined chronic myelomonocytic leukemia: <lb/>ASXL1 and spliceosome component mutations and outcomes. <lb/>Leukemia. 2013;27(7):1504-1510. <lb/>48. Barraco D, Cerquozzi S, Gangat N, et al. Monocytosis in <lb/>polycythemia vera: clinical and molecular correlates. Am J <lb/>Hematol. 2017;92(7):640-645. <lb/>49. Jestin M, Tarfi S, Duchmann M, et al. Prognostic value of <lb/>monocyte subset distribution in chronic myelomonocytic <lb/>leukemia: results of a multicenter study. Leukemia. <lb/>2021;35(3):893-896. <lb/>50. Selimoglu-Buet D, Wagner-Ballon O, Saada V, et al. <lb/>Characteristic repartition of monocyte subsets as a diagnostic <lb/>signature of chronic myelomonocytic leukemia. Blood. <lb/>2015;125(23):3618-3626. <lb/>51. Selimoglu-Buet D, Rivière J, Ghamlouch H, et al. A miR-150/ <lb/>TET3 pathway regulates the generation of mouse and human <lb/>non-classical monocyte subset. Nat Commun. 2018;9(1):5455. </listBibl>


	</text>

</TEI>