<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Rethinking Public Transit Networks Using Climate Change Mitigation and Social Justice Lenses: Great Victoria Area Case Study</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Mohaddese</forename>
          <surname>Ghadiri</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Robert</forename>
          <surname>Newell</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-04T15:46:08.456Z">11/4/2025 3:46:08 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>MDPI AG</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.3390/su16062414</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Mohaddese Ghadiri, Robert Newell. (2024). Rethinking Public Transit Networks Using Climate Change Mitigation and Social Justice Lenses: Great Victoria Area Case Study. Sustainability, 16(6), 2414. DOI: 10.3390/su16062414</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-04T15:45:53.931240Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-04T15:45:53.931240Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>Chaos-Assisted Dynamical Tunneling in Flat Band Superwires <lb/>Anton M. Graf, 1, 2, 3 Ke Lin, 2, 4 MyeongSeo Kim, 2, 5 Joonas Keski-Rahkonen, 2, 3 Alvar Daza, 3, 6 and E.J. Heller 2, 3 <lb/>1 Harvard John A. Paulson School of Engineering and Applied Sciences, <lb/>Harvard University, Cambridge, MA 02138, USA <lb/>2 Department of Physics, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA 02138, USA <lb/>3 Department of Chemistry and Chemical Biology, <lb/>Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts 02138, USA <lb/>4 Zhiyuan College, Shanghai Jiao Tong University, Shanghai, Shanghai 200240, China <lb/>5 Harvard College, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA 02138, USA <lb/>6 Nonlinear Dynamics, Chaos and Complex Systems Group, Departamento de Física, <lb/>Universidad Rey Juan Carlos,Tulipán s/n, 28933 Móstoles, Madrid <lb/>(Dated: May 1, 2024) <lb/>Recent theoretical investigations have revealed unconventional transport mechanisms within high <lb/>Brilliouin zones of two-dimensional superlattices. Electrons can navigate along channels we call su-<lb/>perwires, gently guided without brute force confinement. Such dynamical confinement is caused by <lb/>weak superlattice deflections, markedly different from the static or energetic confinement observed <lb/>in traditional wave guides or one-dimensional electron wires. The quantum properties of super-<lb/>wires give rise to elastic dynamical tunneling, linking disjoint regions of the corresponding classical <lb/>phase space, and enabling the emergence of several parallel channels. This paper provides the un-<lb/>derlying theory and mechanisms that facilitate dynamical tunneling assisted by chaos in periodic <lb/>lattices. Moreover, we show that the mechanism of dynamical tunneling can be effectively concep-<lb/>tualized through the lens of a paraxial approximation. Our results further reveal that superwires <lb/>predominantly exist within flat bands, emerging from eigenstates that represent linear combinations <lb/>of conventional degenerate Bloch states. Finally, we quantify tunneling rates across various lattice <lb/>configurations, and demonstrate the tunneling can be suppressed in a controlled fashion, illustrating <lb/>potential implications in future nanodevices. <lb/></front>

        <body>I. INTRODUCTION <lb/>Two-dimensional (2D) materials and electronic systems <lb/>have become a focal point in solid-state physics research, <lb/>offering numerous potential applications in the realm of <lb/>electronics. [1] Motivated by the discovery of twisted <lb/>bilayer graphene and advancements in artificial super-<lb/>lattices (see, e.g. Refs. [2-6]), various versions of soft <lb/>Lorentz gases, i.e. arrays of fixed scatterers, have been <lb/>explored, including trigonometric functions [7], Lennard-<lb/>Jones potentials [8], and hard-wall disks with reduced <lb/>potentials [9]. In fact, a recent study has unveiled a <lb/>complex interaction between trapped and ballistic peri-<lb/>odic orbits, leading to both normal and anomalous diffu-<lb/>sion in a soft Lorentz gas model that replaces the disks <lb/>with Fermi-type potential profile [10]. Moreover, recent <lb/>work by some of the present authors revealed branched <lb/>flow [11] in a soft Lorentz gas, thus not restricted to dis-<lb/>ordered media wherein a travelling quantum wave scat-<lb/>tered by random smooth obstacles generates a tree-like <lb/>&quot;branched flow&quot; pattern [12]. <lb/>In addition to the branched flow, indefinitely stable <lb/>branches were also seen to form in the channels of a <lb/>periodic lattice of smooth bumps or dips [12]. Within <lb/>these stable branches, propagating waves are dynami-<lb/>cally confined to quasi one-dimensional channels called <lb/>superwires. In contrast to conventional wires relying on <lb/>deep potential barriers, the traveling waves in these su-<lb/>perwires have enough energy to surmount the channel <lb/>potential and thus would not be restricted into the chan-<lb/>nel. The formation of the superwires is governed by the <lb/>underlying dynamics of the system, a mechanism of con-<lb/>finement that diverges fundamentally from the likes of <lb/>Luttinger liquids or from states induced by static disor-<lb/>der, such as those seen in Anderson localization. This <lb/>introduces a distinctive framework, marking a clear de-<lb/>parture from traditional paradigms of wave confinement. <lb/>In this work we show that for identical parallel wires <lb/>tunneling between them inevitably occurs, and flux <lb/>slowly flows to neighboring channels. The slow tunneling <lb/>rate gives rise to nearly flat bands in the direction per-<lb/>pendicular to the wire propagation. Since the classical <lb/>motion is stable flow down the channel, with no insur-<lb/>mountable potential barrier, and chaos lurks in parts of <lb/>phase space, we will attribute this leakage to side chan-<lb/>nels as &quot;chaos-assisted dynamical tunneling&quot; [13-15]. In <lb/>this work, we explore the mechanisms behind dynami-<lb/>cal tunneling in superwires and quantify tunneling rates <lb/>across different lattice configurations. We can under-<lb/>stand much of the physics through a simple model based <lb/>on the paraxial approximation. We can selectively sup-<lb/>press or enhance tunneling between channels in a con-<lb/>trolled manner, offering a pathway to leverage super-<lb/>wires in advanced nanodevices of the future, as in next-<lb/>generation high-precision measurement and sensing in-<lb/>struments. <lb/>We begin in Section II with examples of superwire flow <lb/>over many lattice cells. Subsection II A discusses pa-<lb/>rameters necessary for highly stable superwires. Subsec-<lb/>tion II B describes the flat bands associated with super-<lb/>wires, and discusses the construction of superwire states <lb/></body>

        <front>arXiv:2404.19074v1 [cond-mat.mes-hall] 29 Apr 2024 <lb/></front>

        <page>2 <lb/></page>

        <body>using degenerate Bloch waves. Subsection II C shows <lb/>the generation of superwire eigenstates through quantum <lb/>wavepacket dynamics simulations. Subsection II D aims <lb/>to simplify the concept of dynamical tunneling, present-<lb/>ing it through the lens of a paraxial approximation to <lb/>make the quantum mechanical principles more accessi-<lb/>ble. Section III focuses on comparing the quantum and <lb/>classical aspects of superwires. Here we justify the dy-<lb/>namical nature of tunneling, using classical simulations <lb/>and Poincaré surfaces of section (PSS) as evidence. In <lb/>Section IV, we investigate how slight alterations in the <lb/>geometry of superlattice features can influence dynami-<lb/>cal tunneling. Our analysis, which quantifies tunneling <lb/>rates in different lattice channels, reveals that even minor <lb/>changes can significantly suppress dynamical tunneling. <lb/>Section V concludes the paper by summarizing our key <lb/>results and proposing directions for future investigation. <lb/>II. QUANTUM SUPERWIRES, DYNAMICAL <lb/>TUNNELING, AND FLAT BANDS <lb/>In a nutshell, superwires give rise to electron trans-<lb/>port in solids confined to narrow channels, almost one-<lb/>dimensional paths. This behavior emerges a conse-<lb/>quence of quasi-periodic deflections from the static, non-<lb/>integrable superlattice structure accommodating mul-<lb/>tiple electron wavelengths between its features, corre-<lb/>sponding to higher Brillouin zones. The energy of the <lb/>electron wave significantly exceeds the peak and trough <lb/>values of the superlattice potential, enabling them to <lb/>surmount potential barriers while still being confined to <lb/>channels. Either the Moiré patterns of twisted atomic <lb/>layers or direct fabrication can achieve this regime. As <lb/>discussed above, we probe the dynamics of superwires <lb/>within a two-dimensional soft Lorentz gas, which were re-<lb/>cently reported in Ref. [12]. More specifically, we aim to <lb/>understand the quantum nature of superwires within su-<lb/>perlattices and investigate the fundamental mechanisms <lb/>behind their robust dynamical properties, particularly in <lb/>relation to chaos-assisted dynamical tunneling. Figure 1 <lb/>collects our main results: A superwire eigenstate illus-<lb/>trating the dynamics of an electronic wavepacket propa-<lb/>gating along a single channel but eventually leaking into <lb/>adjacent channels, a feature which can be understood in <lb/>terms of a simple paraxial approximation. The remain-<lb/>der of the paper explores and analyzes these results. <lb/>A. Setup of superwire systems <lb/>It was previously demonstrated that superwires appear <lb/>across a diverse range of superlattice geometries, with <lb/>numerical evidence for both square and trigonal lattices <lb/>formed by concave (dips) or convex (bumps) potential <lb/>features [12]. In the same spirit, we study a simple ex-<lb/>ample model, characterized by smooth potential bumps <lb/>at equidistant lattice points in a square lattice, with five <lb/>to six electron wavelengths per unit cell. The potential is <lb/>specified by Fermi-type functions centered at each lattice <lb/>point [10, 12]. <lb/>More specifically, we consider the following Hamilto-<lb/>nian H(r, k) <lb/>H(r, k) = <lb/>h2 |k| 2 <lb/>2m <lb/>+ <lb/>ri∈S <lb/>V 0 <lb/>1 + exp[(|r -r i | -r 0 )/α] <lb/>, (1) <lb/>which yields a mixed system containing features of both <lb/>non-integrable (chaotic) and integrable (regular) dynam-<lb/>ics in classical and quantum considerations. In the <lb/>Hamiltonian, r and k are the location and momentum <lb/>of an electron with mass m, respectively. The potential <lb/>is composed of individual bumps located at a (finite) set <lb/>of lattice points r i that are characterized by their am-<lb/>plitude V 0 and (effective) radius r 0 . The smoothness of <lb/>the Fermi-potential bumps is controlled by α. We want <lb/>to emphasize that this potential model potentials is feasi-<lb/>ble for artificial superlattice experiments [2-6]). Without <lb/>losing generality, we set the distance between bums to be <lb/>0.4 nm, and α to be 0.2 nm, with a lattice spacing of <lb/>ca 6.67 nm. Remarkably, the potential features do not <lb/>need to be strong for superwires to form. The height of <lb/>the potential is scaled to approximately 0.45 eV at the <lb/>top and 0 eV at the bottom. The resulting superlattice <lb/>structure is illustrated in Figure 2. <lb/>B. Band structure <lb/>Analyzing the band structure of the system offers ad-<lb/>ditional insights with experimental significance for the <lb/>study of quantum transport superlattices. High index <lb/>bands, are crucial for comprehending superwire physics. <lb/>We focus on the superlattice potential, rather than the <lb/>atomic lattice, simplifying the investigation of the band <lb/>structure in high Brillouin zones of a 2D square lattice. <lb/>The procedure is explained in V. <lb/>Figure 3A presents the projected band structure, <lb/>B(k x , k y , E), of the 10 th band, which is identified as one <lb/>of the bands exhibiting superwire states within the su-<lb/>perlattices discussed in this study. <lb/>One of the bands we have found has a geometry close <lb/>to a four-sided pyramid with a peak at the center. There <lb/>is a gap between the peak of the pyramid and the band <lb/>above. The contour map in panel B reveals the existence <lb/>of flat bands along the sides of the pyramidal structure. <lb/>The flat bands shown are uniform along one momentum <lb/>component; at the corners they turn between flat in k x <lb/>to flat in k y . Flat bands are of considerable interest in <lb/>the study of engineered superlattice structures [16-21] <lb/>and superconductivity [22-25]. Flat bands play an im-<lb/>portant role in twisted bilayer graphene superconductiv-<lb/>ity [26-30], and their presence is vital for the dynamics <lb/>of superwires. Energy eigenstates can be described by <lb/>Bloch waves which have a given pseudomomentum and <lb/>energy. Our superwire eigenstates, shown in Figure 1A <lb/></body>

        <page>3 <lb/></page>

        <body>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>0 . 3 <lb/>-0 . 3 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 . 2 <lb/>0 . 4 <lb/>0 . 6 <lb/>x <lb/>y <lb/>0 <lb/>0 . 4 <lb/>0 . 8 <lb/>-0 . 4 <lb/>-0 . 8 <lb/>4 0 n m <lb/>2 0 n m <lb/>+ 3 . 3 + 1 0 . 0 + 1 6 . 7 <lb/>-1 6 . 7 <lb/>0 <lb/>-1 0 . 0 -3 . 3 <lb/>+ 3 . 3 + 1 0 . 0 + 1 6 . 7 <lb/>-1 6 . 7 <lb/>0 <lb/>-1 0 . 0 -3 . 3 <lb/>+ 3 . 3 + 1 0 . 0 + 1 6 . 7 <lb/>-1 6 . 7 <lb/>0 <lb/>-1 0 . 0 -3 . 3 <lb/>( n m) <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>4 0 n m <lb/>2 0 f s <lb/>0 <lb/>0 . 2 <lb/>0 . 4 <lb/>0 . 6 <lb/>t <lb/>y <lb/>( i ) <lb/>( i i i ) <lb/>( i i ) <lb/>( i i ) <lb/>( i ) <lb/>( i i i ) <lb/>FIG. 1. Chaos-assisted dynamical Tunneling in superwires. A) The probability density P (x, y) of a superwire eigenstate <lb/>extracted from quantum dynamics simulation. B) Real part of the wavefunction ℜ(ψ(y, t)) magnified in the regions (i), (ii), <lb/>and (iii) indicated by grey boxes. C) Cross-section ℜ(ψ(x, y)) (red dotted line) and |ψ(x, y)| (black line) at x = 90.8 nm, <lb/>x = 295.7 nm, and x = 598.5 nm (indicated by grey lines for (i), (ii), and (iii) in panels B). The oscillator eigenstates at the <lb/>bottom schematically explain the contributions of the ground state (GS) in blue and first excited state components (1ES) in red <lb/>in each channel. Large oscillator symbols indicate major contribution, small symbols a minor, and missing symbols negligible <lb/>contribution to the wavefunction. D) P (x, y) of a superwire in time extracted from a quasi one-dimensional model via paraxial <lb/>approximation. <lb/>for example, are analogous to a focused laser beam in <lb/>free space: The focused laser beam has a single frequency <lb/>(fixed energy), but many plane waves of different wave <lb/>vector (different momentum) are required to make it fo-<lb/>cus. Here we have similarly sacrificed pseudomomentum <lb/>yet have maintained fixed energy. The beams are made <lb/>of linear combination of Bloch waves with momentum <lb/>along a flat band contour, as highlighted by the red line. <lb/>Using the method of generating functions, as detailed in <lb/>Ref. [31], we determine the overlaps between the super-<lb/>wire state and all states along the contour marked in red. <lb/>The probability distribution P (x, y) of the eigenstate is <lb/>seen in panel C, producing a superwire eigenstate. <lb/></body>

        <page>4 <lb/></page>

        <body>r ₒ = 0 . 6 7 n m <lb/>6 . 6 7 n m <lb/>x ( n m) <lb/>V ( e V ) <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>α = 0 . 0 3 <lb/>α = 0 . 0 5 <lb/>α = 0 . 1 0 <lb/>( e V ) <lb/>0 . 4 <lb/>0 . 3 <lb/>0 . 2 <lb/>0 . 1 <lb/>FIG. 2. Superlattice structure. The potential is depicted <lb/>through grayscale dots generated by Fermi functions. The <lb/>inset presents a cross-sectional view through the center of <lb/>the bump, highlighting the smoothness and relative height <lb/>of the bumps for three different α values. The pink dashed <lb/>line represents the (effective) radius, and the dark green line <lb/>denotes the lattice constant chosen for the simulations. <lb/>C. Wavepacket Dynamics and Eigenstates <lb/>Our investigation of dynamical tunneling starts with <lb/>a squeezed Gaussian that is a common tool in multiple <lb/>fields, such as quantum optics [32, 33] and quantum scar-<lb/>ring [31, 34, 35], launched along the superwire with high <lb/>fidelity. The initial wavepacket is elongated along the <lb/>center channel in x, and chosen to have a large overlap <lb/>with superwire eigenstates: <lb/>ψ(0) = exp -<lb/>(x -x 0 ) cos(θ) -(y -y 0 ) sin(θ) <lb/>√ σ x <lb/>2 <lb/>-<lb/>(x -x 0 ) sin(θ) + (y -y 0 ) cos(θ) <lb/>√ σ y <lb/>2 <lb/>+ i(k x x + k y y) . <lb/>(2) <lb/>In order to study the tunneling into neighboring chan-<lb/>nels, we isolate the initial flow into one channel with high <lb/>fidelity &gt; 99% explained in Section II C. Therefore, we <lb/>choose standard deviations of σ x = 10 nm and σ y = 2 nm <lb/>in the x-and y-directions, respectively, and the momen-<lb/>tum k x ≫ k y . As a consequence, the wavepacket pre-<lb/>dominantly moves in the +x-direction. The local elec-<lb/>tron wavelength, λ e = 1.31 nm, corresponds to roughly <lb/>5λ e per unit cell along the propagation direction. Fur-<lb/>thermore, we initialized the wavepacket with momentum <lb/>directed towards the right, targeting the center chan-<lb/>nel. We employ the third-order split-operator method <lb/>V to propagate the wavepacket according to the time-<lb/>dependent Schrödinger equation <lb/>Ĥψ(x, y, t) = ih <lb/>∂ <lb/>∂, t <lb/>ψ(x, y, t) <lb/>(3) <lb/>where the Hamiltonian is given by equation 1. Through-<lb/>out the simulation, we find that the probability density <lb/>propagates from left to right, while remaining almost ex-<lb/>clusively confined to the central channel. As the wave-<lb/>function evolves, it reaches the rightmost boundary of <lb/>the position grid, spanning several unit cells of the super-<lb/>lattice potential. To enable the computation of a large <lb/>grid where tunneling can be studied we used a matrix <lb/>extension technique, with further details provided in V. <lb/>In supplement to analysis of the wavepacket evolution, <lb/>we construct an eigenstate of the Hamiltionian from the <lb/>given wavepacket as <lb/>|ψ n (x, y)⟩ ≈ lim <lb/>T →∞ <lb/>1 <lb/>2T <lb/>T <lb/>-T <lb/>exp(-E n t)|ψ(x, y, t)⟩ dt, (4) <lb/>which gives the wanted eigenstate after an convenient <lb/>renormalization to the simulation box size. The studied <lb/>energy E n of the eigenstate is selected as the highest <lb/>weight in the power spectrum <lb/>S(E) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πh <lb/>T <lb/>-T <lb/>e iEt/h ⟨ψ(0)|ψ(t)⟩ dt , <lb/>(5) <lb/>which is the Fourier transform of the autocorrelation <lb/>function c(t) = ⟨ψ(0)|ψ(t)⟩. Figure 1 illustrates the su-<lb/>perwire confinement and tunneling mechanism via a con-<lb/>structed eigenstates at an energy of 0.9 eV, double the <lb/>maximum of V 0 whose corresponding probability distri-<lb/>bution P (x, y) is shown in Figure 1A. The probability <lb/>density peaks in the central channel near the left launch <lb/>point. As the wavepacket propagates to the right, it ex-<lb/>pands into adjacent channels through dynamical tunnel-<lb/>ing. Subsequently, a significant portion of density P (x, y) <lb/>tunnels into neighboring channels after a critical time <lb/>threshold, defying classical phase space boundaries set <lb/>by the stability islands. This behavior, elucidated in Sec-<lb/>tion III and numerically validated in Figure 5, results in <lb/>probability growth in adjacent channels at the expense <lb/>of the middle channel. In Figure 1B, the real part of the <lb/>wavefunction ℜ(ψ), is visualized with red representing <lb/>positive amplitude and blue indicating negative ampli-<lb/>tude against a grayscale background delineating lattice <lb/>potential bumps in white and uniform potential in black. <lb/>Additionally, Figure 1 C presents a cross-sectional view <lb/>of the real part ℜ(ψ), in red and its magnitude in black <lb/>across the y-direction, averaged over the examined sec-<lb/>tion, with grey dashed lines demarcating lattice points to <lb/>facilitate channel separation. <lb/>D. Understanding Tunneling through the Lens of a <lb/>Paraxial Approximation <lb/>The paraxial approximation significantly simplifies the <lb/>analysis of superwire dynamics, particularly in under-<lb/>standing the mechanism of dynamical tunneling. By ap-<lb/>plying this approximation under the condition k x ≫ k y , <lb/></body>

        <page>5 <lb/></page>

        <body>0 . 5 4 <lb/>0 . 6 7 <lb/>0 . 8 0 e V <lb/>k x <lb/>k y <lb/>x 1 0 9 <lb/>-1 . 0 <lb/>0 . 5 <lb/>0 . 6 <lb/>0 . 7 <lb/>0 . 8 <lb/>0 . 9 <lb/>-1 . 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 . 0 <lb/>1 . 0 <lb/>A <lb/>k x <lb/>0 <lb/>1 . 5 <lb/>-1 . 5 <lb/>k y <lb/>-1 . 5 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 . 5 <lb/>x 1 0 9 <lb/>x 1 0 9 <lb/>0 . 6 <lb/>0 . 7 <lb/>0 . 8 e V <lb/>B <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>-2 <lb/>-2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>x <lb/>y <lb/>x 1 0 -9 <lb/>x 1 0 -9 <lb/>x 1 0 -4 <lb/>1 . 6 <lb/>1 . 2 <lb/>0 . 8 <lb/>C <lb/>FIG. 3. The band structure B(kx, ky, E) of the 10 th band where superwire states are found. The band shows features of a <lb/>four-sided pyramid with flat bands along the side. B) Contour map of the 10 th band B(kx, ky, E) emphasizing the flat bands. <lb/>The red line indicates the flat band with degenerate Bloch states that are used to generate the eigenstate shown on the right. <lb/>C) Probability density of Superwire eigenstate that has maximal overlap with the degenerate Bloch states on the red flat band <lb/>contour. <lb/>and acknowledging the superwire states&apos; x-direction <lb/>propagation, we focus on the y-component of the wave-<lb/>function. We substitute the x-direction (distance of the <lb/>superwire) with a temporal dimension x -→ t. We <lb/>then solve the time-dependent Schrödinger equation for a <lb/>quasi-one-dimensional system for a potential that varies <lb/>periodically in time. The motion in the x-direction, or <lb/>equivalently, the group velocity, is represented by the rate <lb/>of change of the potential in time, allowing us to fine-tune <lb/>the simulation to match the physical scenario closely. <lb/>In this system, the paraxial motion through the propa-<lb/>gating channel periodically alters the transverse potential <lb/>harmonic force constant, in the manner of a parametri-<lb/>cally driven oscillator. Thus the Mathieu equation and <lb/>its attendant stability approximately applies[12]. The ac-<lb/>tual phase space diagram for the chosen energy resembles <lb/>that of a kicked rotor. In (figure 5), we see the stable is-<lb/>land, but at other energies the kicking frequency changes <lb/>and can become resonant with the transverse mode fre-<lb/>quency, destabilizing the motion down the channel. <lb/>The results in Figure 1D demonstrates that the super-<lb/>wire dynamics, including the tunneling seen in panel A, <lb/>are successfully (and nearly indistinguishably) captured <lb/>within the paraxial approximation. This justifies the use <lb/>of a quasi-one dimensional interpretation when we discuss <lb/>tunneling in the two-dimensional potential of Figure 1A <lb/>as follows: <lb/>In Figure 1B(i), ℜ(ψ) displays the consequence of the <lb/>wavepacket being launched slightly off-center in the chan-<lb/>nel. This offset creates a combination of the ground and <lb/>first excited transverse modes, causing a gentle oscilla-<lb/>tion between the upper and lower bumps as it travels <lb/>down the channel. <lb/>In this non-integrable superlattice potential, the pseu-<lb/>domomentum components k x and k y can exchange en-<lb/>ergy in principle, leading to the electron scattering more <lb/>widely into the 2D lattice. Such high angle scattering is <lb/>nonetheless absent here: the stable dynamics maintains <lb/>superwire flow over long distances without significant dis-<lb/>persion, apart from a dynamical tunneling populating <lb/>the adjacent channels as shown in 1B(ii) and (iii). Fig-<lb/>ure 4 provides a close up of a wave in the middle channel <lb/>tunneling into adjacent channels. The tunneled compo-<lb/>FIG. 4. Zoomed-in view depicting quantum dynamics fea-<lb/>turing dynamical tunneling. The image illustrates the inter-<lb/>face between the primary superwire channel and its adjacent <lb/>channels. Transparent features, depicted in grayscale, repre-<lb/>sent the superlattice bumps. Notably, the wave propagates <lb/>without decay across the top of these bumps, indicating the <lb/>are classically surmountable. Examination of the real part <lb/>of ψ reveals an approximate phase shift of π/2 between each <lb/>channel. <lb/>nents continue to propagate in the original direction and <lb/>the confinement within the next channel is maintained. <lb/>Remarkably, the oscillatory rocking motion within the <lb/>first adjacent channels is more pronounced, occurring <lb/>synchronously on both sides. We do not observe back <lb/>scattering but we see a phase shift of approximately π/2 <lb/>between ℜ(ψ) in the center channel and those in adja-<lb/>cent channels. Figure 4 illustrates that the wave also <lb/>over rides the potential bumps. The potential barriers <lb/>are comparable in size to λ e . The relatively low po-<lb/></body>

        <page>6 <lb/></page>

        <body>tential strength, substantially reduces the probability of <lb/>notable diffracting phenomena. <lb/>Applying the insight from the paraxial approximation <lb/>in Figure 1C(i) helps to understand the underlying tun-<lb/>neling mechanism. The y-component of the superwire <lb/>eigenstate inside a channel is closely resembling the 1D <lb/>eigenstates of a single harmonic quantum well. The real <lb/>part of the wave function, ℜ(ψ(y, t)), demonstrates that <lb/>the center channel is made of linear combinations of <lb/>ground state-like (abbreviated GS; Gaussian without a <lb/>node) and first excited state-like (abbreviated 1ES; Gaus-<lb/>sian with one node) components. The composition of <lb/>the states in each &quot;well&quot; is schematically depicted at the <lb/>bottom of the figure: Large oscillator symbols indicate <lb/>major contribution, small symbols a minor, and missing <lb/>symbols negligible contribution to the wavefunction. <lb/>In panel C(i) the absolute value reflects this as a <lb/>slightly deformed Gaussian. The tunneled components in <lb/>the adjacent channels are still relatively small but close <lb/>inspection shows that they carry a node in the middle. <lb/>Our interpretation is that the adjacent channels at this <lb/>distance contain a quantum state that is still a mix of GS <lb/>and 1ES -but the fraction of the component resembling <lb/>1ES is already larger here. Hence ℜ(ψ) and the absolute <lb/>value show a node. This is expected because, despite <lb/>the different mechanisms between barrier and dynami-<lb/>cal tunneling, modes with higher energy typically tunnel <lb/>faster. This behaviour will become more pronounced in <lb/>the following zoomed in sections C(ii) and C(iii) and sup-<lb/>ports the claim that dynamical tunneling in superwires <lb/>could be used to separate the different transverse energy <lb/>components of the channel eigenstates. <lb/>There are several indications in Figure 1 of more facile <lb/>tunneling of the first excited transverse mode of the cen-<lb/>tral channel: damping of the central channel oscillations <lb/>with progress to the right, and a higher population of <lb/>1ES over GS in the side channels compared to the par-<lb/>ent channel as further shown in the later sections of the <lb/>superwire. <lb/>III. INSIGHTS FROM CLASSICAL <lb/>SUPERWIRES <lb/>Tunneling is a quantum mechanical phenomenon that <lb/>allows particles to transition between states or regions <lb/>that are not directly connected or accessible according to <lb/>classical mechanics but they do not have to involve a po-<lb/>tential barrier, as is the case here. Dynamical tunneling <lb/>occurs between classically disjoint regions in phase space. <lb/>We will also see that here the classically distinct regions <lb/>are separated by a chaotic sea, so the tunneling falls into <lb/>another class: the chaos-assisted tunneling of Tomsovic <lb/>and Ullmo[15]. Classical particles are initialized with de-<lb/>fined velocity v (corresponding to the expectation value <lb/>in Section II) and positioned at the bottom of the center <lb/>channel. By adjusting their initial angles, we explore a <lb/>range of trajectories shown in Figure 3A. Utilizing a Ver-<lb/>let integration scheme, we calculate the particle motion <lb/>over time, enabling us to map their trajectories and ana-<lb/>lyze the associated phase space. To simplify the analysis <lb/>of the four-dimensional phase space, we employ Poincaré <lb/>surfaces of section (PSS), focusing on slices along the v y <lb/>and y dimensions, as depicted in Figure 3B. The position <lb/>of each particle, recorded at intervals equal to integer <lb/>multiples of the lattice constant from the starting point, <lb/>is projected onto this PSS, facilitating a comprehensive <lb/>phase space examination projected on the unit cell of the <lb/>square lattice. <lb/>Figure 3 demonstrates clearly that most trajectories in <lb/>this parameter regime (pink, blue, red, green, yellow, or-<lb/>ange and red) form stable wires inside the center channel, <lb/>maintaining their confinement over extended distances. <lb/>This stability is primarily due to what is termed the <lb/>&quot;rocking-chair&quot; motion: trajectories oscillate in a man-<lb/>ner that is slightly off-resonance with the lattice&apos;s pe-<lb/>riodic potential, preventing escape. This off-resonant <lb/>oscillation underpinning the dynamical self-confinement <lb/>of these superwire trajectories, is corroborated by the <lb/>emergence of stable (so-called) calm islands in the PSS <lb/>shown in Figure 3B, where quasi-periodic elliptical or-<lb/>bits manifest. According to predictions by the Kol-<lb/>mogorov-Arnold-Moser (KAM) theorem, quasi-periodic <lb/>motions persists within these elliptically bounded islands. <lb/>Each colored elliptical region matches the trajectory <lb/>color in the panel to the left. Remarkably, despite inter-<lb/>action with a non-integrable potential, these trajectories <lb/>exhibit almost periodic motion in the PSS. In contrast, <lb/>classical particles wandering through a periodic lattice <lb/>but not confined by channels, typically are chaotic, and <lb/>have been shown to exhibits features, such as branched <lb/>flow [11] and Lévy flights [10]. <lb/>The light blue trajectories correspond to the same ini-<lb/>tial conditions but launched in the neighboring channel. <lb/>Upon examining the light blue orbits in the PSS, it is ev-<lb/>ident they occupy separate elliptical orbits, completely <lb/>disjoint in phase space. This observation implies that, <lb/>from a classical perspective, a superwire trajectory re-<lb/>mains dynamically confined, preventing it from migrating <lb/>into adjacent channels whereas quantum mechanically we <lb/>find probability density to tunnel across the disjoint re-<lb/>gions in phase space indicated by the formation of the <lb/>parallel wires in neighboring channels. <lb/>The trajectories shown in light blue originate from <lb/>identical initial conditions but are initiated in neighbor-<lb/>ing channels. When analyzing these light blue paths on <lb/>the PSS, it&apos;s clear they follow distinct elliptical orbits <lb/>that do not overlap in phase space. This separation sug-<lb/>gests that, according to classical mechanics, a trajectory <lb/>within a superwire is dynamically confined, which in-<lb/>hibits its movement into adjacent channels. In contrast, <lb/>the quantum mechanical simulations show that proba-<lb/>bility density tunnels through these disjoint regions in <lb/>phase space, as demonstrated by the presence of parallel <lb/>superwires in neighboring channels. <lb/>We also plot (purple) unstable classical trajectories <lb/></body>

        <page>7 <lb/></page>

        <body>v <lb/>y (m/s) <lb/>5e5 <lb/>-5e5 <lb/>-6.7 <lb/>6.7 <lb/>y (nm) <lb/>FIG. 5. Classical dynamics of superwires in periodic lattices. A) Trajectories of classical particles in coordinate space of x and <lb/>y. All particles were launched with fixed initial momentum and varying launch angle. Light blue trajectories are translated <lb/>by a lattice constant to form stable superwire in adjacent horizontal channels. Purple trajectories are not stable inside the <lb/>horizontal superwire. B) Poincaré surface of section (PSS) for a unit cell with colors corresponding to the trajectories on <lb/>the left. Stable superwires are indicated by quasi-periodic orbits. The light blue disjoint orbits correspond to disconnected <lb/>superwires in neighboring channels. Purple dots form the chaotic sea. <lb/>that do not remain confined within the horizontal super-<lb/>wire. Figure 3A demonstrates that trajectories tending <lb/>towards instability are typically associated with larger <lb/>launch angles. Some of these trajectories find channels <lb/>at different angles, occasionally forming less populated <lb/>wires. A few paths initially follow the horizontal chan-<lb/>nel but fail to meet the established criteria for stability, <lb/>diverging at greater distances. In this regime, certain <lb/>particles are deflected, leading to early signs of branched <lb/>flow. Crucially, these diverging trajectories cross the po-<lb/>tential peaks, showing that they are not restricted by any <lb/>potential energy confinement. These unstable trajecto-<lb/>ries contribute to the scattered data points in the PSS, <lb/>together creating the &quot;chaotic sea&quot;-a region in phase <lb/>space where dynamics become chaotic. The stable quasi-<lb/>periodic orbits within and adjacent to the central chan-<lb/>nel are distinctly separated by the chaotic sea. There-<lb/>fore, particle dynamics within the periodic lattice pre-<lb/>cludes transitioning between superwire channels without <lb/>encountering this chaotic region. Thus, the shift from <lb/>one superwire to another is classically forbidden, indi-<lb/>cating that observed transitions in quantum superwires <lb/>are indeed the result of dynamical tunneling and more <lb/>specifically chaos-assisted tunneling. <lb/>IV. CONTROLLING DYNAMICAL <lb/>TUNNELING IN ENGINEERED SUPERLATTICE <lb/>STRUCTURES <lb/>Although superwire stability is generally resilient to <lb/>minor parameter changes, the tunneling rate into ad-<lb/>jacent channels is highly sensitive to these variations. <lb/>Given the vast array of possible lattice configurations, a <lb/>comprehensive study of each is impractical. Nonetheless, <lb/>we demonstrate that the tunneling rate can be effectively <lb/>controlled through minor modifications in the superlat-<lb/>tice fabrication process. <lb/>The tunneling is influenced by the parameter α in the <lb/>Fermi function of the superlattice, which affects both the <lb/>sharpness of convex features on lattice sites and their <lb/>maximum height. Figure 2 provides a detailed view of the <lb/>superlattice, displaying bump heights in grayscale. The <lb/>inset details the variation in bump height with distance <lb/>from lattice points for three distinct α values. <lb/>We conducted wavepacket dynamics simulations con-<lb/>sistent with those described in Section II. Figure 6 dis-<lb/>plays snapshots of ℜ(ψ) at a specific timestep for three <lb/>superlattice configurations in the left column: panel A(i) <lb/>for α = 0.03, panel B(i) for α = 0.0, and panel C(i) for <lb/>α = 0.10. The snapshots reveal that smoother potential <lb/>features, despite a slight reduction in potential height, <lb/>result in better confinement of ℜ(ψ). The images also <lb/>support that most of ℜ(ψ) are contained within 4/5 of <lb/>the simulation box and the matrix extension technique <lb/></body>

        <page>8 <lb/></page>

        <body>can be applied. The probability distribution, P (x, y), <lb/>of the eigenfunctions for the entire run is presented in <lb/>the middle column of Figure 6 and directly corresponds <lb/>to the ℜ(ψ) images on their left. With increasing α, <lb/>P (x, y) demonstrates improved confinement over longer <lb/>distances with smoother potential features. For sharp <lb/>potential features, α = 0.03 in panel A(ii), P (x, y) gets <lb/>rapidly distributed over adjacent channels, with a no-<lb/>table reduction in intensity within the central channel, <lb/>indicating a high tunneling rate. Again we can recognize <lb/>that at the end of the simulation the GS and 1ES com-<lb/>ponents (indicated by nodes or rocking motion in 2D) of <lb/>the eigenstate get filtered successively with tunneling into <lb/>each parallel channel. At the end of the simulation the <lb/>outermost channel always contains the highest 1ES com-<lb/>ponent. For α = 0.05, panel B(ii), the majority of P (x, y) <lb/>is confined within the center and first adjacent channels <lb/>on either side. With α = 0.10, panel C(ii), the distribu-<lb/>tion primarily stays within the center channels and small <lb/>contributions in the first adjacent channels, demonstrat-<lb/>ing the effect of α on confinement over experimentally <lb/>relevant distances. <lb/>To quantify the tunneling rates in more detail, we <lb/>present the distribution of probability density, P (x, y), <lb/>across different channels: the center (P 0 , black line), the <lb/>first adjacent (P 1 , red line), and the second adjacent (P 2 , <lb/>blue line) in the right column of Figure 6. For a mini-<lb/>mal α value of 0.03, depicted in panel A(iii), P 0 starts at <lb/>value one, indicating complete initial confinement within <lb/>the center channel. The probability P 0 exhibits a nearly <lb/>linear decline. Concurrently, P 1 and P 2 increase linearly, <lb/>albeit at a reduced rate, with P 2 lagging slightly until suf-<lb/>ficient probability density has transitioned into the first <lb/>adjacent channels. Remarkably, by the conclusion of the <lb/>simulation over a span of 700 nm, P 0 and P 1 converge to-<lb/>wards comparable values, i.e. the combined probability <lb/>in the first two adjacent channels is comparable to that <lb/>of the center channel. In this regime, the tunneling pro-<lb/>cess can be viewed as interaction of an infinite sequence <lb/>of potential wells. Over time, P (x, y) disperses uniformly <lb/>across all channels, akin to behavior in an open system, <lb/>leading P 0 to approach zero, followed by a similar deple-<lb/>tion in the first and second adjacent channels. We call <lb/>this regime &quot;tunneling escape&quot;. <lb/>The slight increase in α to 0.05 impacts the tunnel-<lb/>ing dynamics quantitatively as demonstrated in Figure <lb/>6B. The probability P 0 still decreases linearly, albeit at <lb/>a reduced rate, while P 1 exhibits a further delayed lin-<lb/>ear increase, and P 2 stays near zero, displaying minimal <lb/>fluctuation throughout the simulation. <lb/>For the highest α value of 0.10, Figure6C shows the <lb/>tunneling dynamics change qualitatively. Initially, P 0 de-<lb/>creases linearly but reaches a temporary plateau, coincid-<lb/>ing with the peak and subsequent oscillation of P 1 . The <lb/>probability P 2 remains minimal throughout the simula-<lb/>tion but mimics P 1 &apos;s oscillations with a phase difference. <lb/>This behavior suggests a distinct tunneling regime closer <lb/>to a three-well problem, characterized by suppressed tun-<lb/>neling rates. Such suppression allows for bidirectional <lb/>tunneling, contributing to the observed oscillations in <lb/>tunneling rates. We anticipate that, over extended peri-<lb/>ods, the superwire would still undergo tunneling escape, <lb/>but at significantly prolonged timescales, thereby delay-<lb/>ing thermalization. The tunneling rate from the center <lb/>channel was notably lowest for an α value of 0.10, de-<lb/>spite a marginal decrease in potential maximum relative <lb/>to other α values. This α-dependent behavior under-<lb/>scores that confinement is primarily due to quasi-periodic <lb/>scattering/deflections of the wavefunction across the po-<lb/>tential landscape. Thus, the tunneling mechanism relies <lb/>not solely on barrier height but is significantly affected <lb/>by the potential&apos;s smooth contours. Furthermore, tun-<lb/>neling can be nearly eliminated by disrupting the over-<lb/>lap between neighboring states, for instance, by creat-<lb/>ing channels with varying bottom heights or employing <lb/>nonuniform bump heights in fabrication. These strate-<lb/>gies highlight the potential for precise control over dy-<lb/>namical tunneling through tailored potential landscapes. <lb/>We want to point out that the level of (classical) chaos <lb/>does not change monotonically when the smoothness <lb/>of the bumps varies from the fully chaotic case of the <lb/>paradigmatic Lorentz gas composed of hard-wall disk to <lb/>regular dynamics of the high-softness limit resembling an <lb/>integrable cosine potential. Instead, there is a rich struc-<lb/>ture of normal and anomalous diffusion depending on the <lb/>smoothness (and separation) of the bumps, as reported <lb/>in Ref. [10] for a similar soft Lorentz gas. An interest-<lb/>ing avenue of future research is to investigate how this <lb/>diversity in classical dynamics affects chaos-assisted dy-<lb/>namical tunneling between channels, alongside with the <lb/>more general studies on the robustness of superwires, e.g., <lb/>against various defects and impurities within the lattice. <lb/>V. CONCLUSION AND FUTURE DIRECTIONS <lb/>The conduction problem in superlattices thrusts us <lb/>into the unfamiliar territory of high Brillioun zones and <lb/>robust efficacy of semiclassical correspondence, since elec-<lb/>tron wavelengths can become short compared to smooth <lb/>features of the potential. Here we have used the classical <lb/>motion to define the existence of tunneling between chan-<lb/>nels that are otherwise stable quantum mechanically. <lb/>This is the first study of dynamical tunneling in flat-<lb/>band superwires. Our model system has revealed that <lb/>even when superlattice features are relatively weak com-<lb/>pared to the kinetic energy of the electron, the dynamical <lb/>confinement within superwires remains robust. This may <lb/>make it relatively easier to fabricate superwires <lb/>Flat bands and channeling superwires go hand in hand. <lb/>The channel eigenstates are linear combinations of con-<lb/>ventional degenerate Bloch states. This realization opens <lb/>up new avenues for leveraging superwires in advanced <lb/>nanodevices, promising novel approaches to electron con-<lb/>finement and transport. <lb/>Through the use of both quantum mechanical and clas-<lb/></body>

        <page>9 <lb/></page>

        <body>-0 . 0 0 3 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 . 0 0 3 0 <lb/>0 . 2 <lb/>0 . 4 <lb/>0 . 6 <lb/>4 0 n m <lb/>4 0 n m <lb/>( i ) <lb/>( i ) <lb/>( i ) <lb/>( i i ) <lb/>( i i ) <lb/>( i i ) <lb/>( i i i ) <lb/>( i i i ) <lb/>( i i i ) <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>FIG. 6. Study of tunneling rates with varying lattice features. A), B), and C) show the results for the different α values at <lb/>0.03, 0.05 and 0.10, respectively. For each case panels (i) corresponds to real part of the wavefunction ψ(x, y, t) at t = 0.66 ps. <lb/>Panels (ii) correspond to the probability densities P (x, t) of the eigenstates in each scenario. Panels (iii) show the probability <lb/>densities in the center channel (P0, black line), the first adjacent channels combined (P1, red line) and the second adjacent <lb/>channels combined (P2, blue line) for all αs used here. Note that the wave oscillations in the channel diminish from left to <lb/>right. as the first transverse excited state preferentially escapes the center channel, leaving it a higher percentage of ground <lb/>state amplitude heading from left to right. In panel A(ii) especially, it can be seen that channels furthest from the initially <lb/>populated center channel become increasingly purely the first excited transverse mode. <lb/>sical methods, we have shown that dynamical tunneling is <lb/>distinct from traditional barrier tunneling, offering a nu-<lb/>anced understanding of superwire stability and the con-<lb/>ditions necessary for their formation and stability. Be-<lb/>cause of the chaotic zones intervening between channels, <lb/>tunneling between them should be further understood as <lb/>chaos-assisted[15]. <lb/>By use of a paraxial approximation we have been <lb/>able to understand dynamical tunneling as a quasi-one-<lb/>dimensional process in a time-dependent potential. This <lb/>model allows us to approximate the superwires by ground <lb/>and first excited states in series of periodically driven har-<lb/>monic quantum wells. <lb/>Analyzing the effects of superlattice parameter varia-<lb/>tions, particularly the α parameter, on electron tunneling <lb/>and confinement, we found pathways for potential con-<lb/>trol schemes of electron transport in nanoscale devices. <lb/>For example, we showed how the channel tunneling rate <lb/>depends on the transverse mode of the channel, thus fil-<lb/>tering energy across multiple parallel channels. This may <lb/>have implications as a mechanism for energy component <lb/>filtration and quantum state purification. <lb/>The findings suggest exciting prospects for the design <lb/>and fabrication of quantum devices, where electron can <lb/>be guided in quasi one-dimensional channels under con-<lb/>sideration of varying superlattice parameters. Current <lb/>investigations are focused on understanding how multi-<lb/>ple electrons interact both within individual channels and <lb/>across neighboring ones, and on the question of limited <lb/>pathways for electron-vibration interactions in the chan-<lb/>nels. The inherent decrease of phonon-electron interac-<lb/>tions within these quasi-one-dimensional wires could be <lb/></body>

        <page>10 <lb/></page>

        <body>an important step to realize near zero-resistivity trans-<lb/>port of electrons in superlattices <lb/>Exploring the stability of superwires in real-world ma-<lb/>terials presents a fascinating challenge, especially when <lb/>considering small lattice displacements or within dynam-<lb/>ically disordered potential landscapes, for a classical per-<lb/>spective on this issue, see Ref. [36]. Our formalism ac-<lb/>commodates various approaches to explore both frozen <lb/>and dynamical deformation potentials in crystal lattices <lb/>described Ref. [37, 38]. <lb/>We hope that future research will explore experimental <lb/>validation (e.g. through STM studies of twisted multi-<lb/>layered materials) to further harness superwires and their <lb/>inherent tunneling for device applications. It is impor-<lb/>tant to note that the principles of superwires and dynam-<lb/>ical tunneling extend to photons and quantum-optical <lb/>systems, suggesting potential experimental investigations <lb/>in optical setups, including photorefractive crystals and <lb/>various photonic structures. <lb/>The ability to manipulate tunneling dynamics through <lb/>tailored potential landscapes offers a pathway to nearly <lb/>eliminate tunneling, presenting strategies for enhanced <lb/>electron localization and stability. On the other hand, <lb/>controlled tunneling can be used to couple initially iso-<lb/>lated quantum channels. <lb/></body>

        <div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>We want to thank everyone who provided feedback and <lb/>support through constructive discussions. Specifically we <lb/>want to thank Alhun Aydin, Esa Räsänen, Ragnar Fleis-<lb/>chmann, Lev Kaplan, Jairo Velasco, Norman Yao, Arthur <lb/>Jaffe, Roy Garcia and Kaifeng Bu for valuable comments. <lb/>A. M. G. wants to thank the Harvard Quantum Initiative <lb/>for financial support. M.K. thanks the Harvard College <lb/>Research Program for financial support. J.K.-R. thanks <lb/>the Emil Aaltonen Foundation, Vaisala Foundation, and <lb/>the Oskar Huttunen Foundation for financial support. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">APPENDIX <lb/>Appendix A: Calculation of band structure <lb/>Tight-binding models typically assume electrons are lo-<lb/>calized at atomic sites with a finite probability of hopping <lb/>to adjacent sites. However, this framework proves inad-<lb/>equate for electrons in superlattices, where their pres-<lb/>ence extends between potential peaks. Consequently, we <lb/>adopt a continuous model approach to accurately capture <lb/>the electronic band structure in superlattices, grounded <lb/>in the time-independent Schrödinger equation <lb/>-<lb/>h2 <lb/>2m <lb/>∇ 2 + V (⃗ r) ϕ(⃗ r) = Eϕ(⃗ r. <lb/>(6) <lb/>According to the Bloch theorem, we have ϕ(⃗ r) = <lb/>e i ⃗ k•⃗ r u k (⃗ r), satisfying the following equation. <lb/>-<lb/>h2 <lb/>2m <lb/>∇ 2 + V (⃗ r) e i ⃗ k•⃗ r u k (⃗ r) = E( ⃗ k)e i ⃗ k•⃗ r u k (⃗ r). <lb/>(7) <lb/>In order to reduce our calculation, we only focus on the <lb/>periodic potential in a unit cell. By multiplying e -i ⃗ k•⃗ r <lb/>on both sides, the equation reduces to <lb/>e -i ⃗ k•⃗ r -<lb/>h2 <lb/>2m <lb/>∇ 2 + V (⃗ r) e i ⃗ k•⃗ r u k (⃗ r) <lb/>= e -i ⃗ k•⃗ r E( ⃗ k)e i ⃗ k•⃗ r u k (⃗ r). <lb/>(8) <lb/>Since e -i ⃗ k•⃗ r and e i ⃗ k•⃗ r cancel each other on the right hand <lb/>side, we obtain the following equation, <lb/>H k u k (⃗ r) = <lb/>h2 <lb/>2m <lb/>(-i∇ + ⃗ k) 2 + V (⃗ r) u k (⃗ r) = Eu k (⃗ r) <lb/>(9) <lb/>where E( ⃗ k) is the eigenvalue and u k (⃗ r) is the Bloch state. <lb/>For a two-dimensional superlattice, we get <lb/>H k = <lb/>h2 <lb/>2m <lb/>(-i∇ + ⃗ k) 2 + V (⃗ r) <lb/>= <lb/>h2 <lb/>2m <lb/>-<lb/>d 2 <lb/>dx 2 -<lb/>d 2 <lb/>dy 2 -ik x <lb/>d <lb/>dx <lb/>-ik y <lb/>d <lb/>dy <lb/>+ k 2 + V (x) . <lb/>(10) <lb/>Given the exact form of potential in a unit cell, di-<lb/>agonalization process of Hamiltonian can be executed by <lb/>constructing the numerical form of the ∇ operator. Thus, <lb/>we can get the full 2D electronic band structure. <lb/>Appendix B: Wavepacket dynamics with matrix <lb/>extension <lb/>We are employing the well-known split-operator <lb/>method (with Strang splitting) to propagate the wave-<lb/>function in time with the kinetic energy operator T and <lb/>the potential energy operator V . Each iteration is using <lb/>the following steps: <lb/>1. Apply the potential term in real space for one half-<lb/>time step: <lb/>ψ(x, t + ∆t/2) = e -iV (x)∆t/2 ψ(x, t) <lb/>(11) <lb/>2. Fourier transform to momentum space: <lb/></div>

        <page>11 <lb/></page>

        <div type="annex">ψ(k, t + ∆t/2) = F{ψ(x, t + ∆t/2)} <lb/>(12) <lb/>3. Apply the kinetic term in momentum space: <lb/>ψ(k, t + ∆t) = e -iT (k)∆t ψ(k, t + ∆t/2), <lb/>(13) <lb/>where T (k) = <lb/>h2 k 2 <lb/>2m is the kinetic energy operator in <lb/>momentum space, with k being the wavevector, h the re-<lb/>duced Planck&apos;s constant, and m the mass of the particle. <lb/>4. Inverse Fourier transform to return to real space: <lb/>ψ(x, t + ∆t) = F -1 { ψ(k, t + ∆t)} <lb/>(14) <lb/>5. Apply the potential term again in real space for <lb/>another half-time step: <lb/>ψ(x, t + ∆t) = e -iV (x)∆t/2 ψ(x, t + ∆t) <lb/>(15) <lb/>Together, the full step from t to t + ∆t can be written as: <lb/>ψ(x, t + ∆t) = e -iV (x)∆t/2 F -1 {e -iT (k)∆t <lb/>× F {e -iV (x)∆t/2 ψ(x, t)}} <lb/>(16) <lb/>With this algorithm applied to superwires the wave-<lb/>function predominantly propagates confined within a <lb/>channel in +x direction (almost no backscattering). This <lb/>special case of a quasi 1D localization allows to follow <lb/>the wavefunction over multiple simulation boxes without <lb/>changing the size of the grid at any given time step. In-<lb/>stead we move the frame as follows: <lb/>When some small probability, defined by an adjustable <lb/>threshold value, is found in the right-most column of the <lb/>position grid, we shift our frame to the right, following <lb/>the main part of the wavefunction. This is specifically <lb/>achieved by leveraging the potential&apos;s symmetry, wherein <lb/>we augment the simulation grid by appending a poten-<lb/>tial matrix one-fifth (equivalent to three unit cells) the <lb/>width of the position grid. This extension provides ad-<lb/>ditional space, allowing the wavefunction to continue its <lb/>propagation towards the right. To preserve the original <lb/>grid dimensions, we remove the initial one-fifth of the <lb/>simulation box, a section that, upon careful examina-<lb/>tion, contains less than 1% of the probability density. In <lb/>our simulations, we ensure that forward scattering pre-<lb/>dominates, preventing the wavepacket from backscatter-<lb/>ing and self-interference. As a result, the eigenstates are <lb/>extractable from the wavepacket after a single traverse <lb/>through the simulation box. Subsequent to each matrix <lb/>extension step, the ensuing segment of the eigenstate is <lb/>spatially appended to the preceding frame, resulting in a <lb/>composite eigenstate seamlessly spanning the entire dis-<lb/>tance it has traversed. It is important to note that the <lb/>matrix extension technique can potentially lead to am-<lb/>plitude truncation if the wavepacket extends excessively <lb/>into the matrix section slated for removal during the ex-<lb/>tension process. To mitigate this, we calibrated the sim-<lb/>ulation parameters to ensure that, within the simulation <lb/>duration, over 99% of the wavepacket&apos;s probability den-<lb/>sity remains outside the excised region. The eliminated <lb/>components are primarily minor amplitude constituents <lb/>that propagate slower or are directionally shed from the <lb/>initial trajectory at launch, which may be regarded as <lb/>initial impurities within simulation. Minimal leakage to-<lb/>wards the top and bottom of the frame is effectively mit-<lb/>igated by implementing a smooth absorption boundary. <lb/></div>

        <listBibl>[1] S. Zeng, Z. Tang, C. Liu, and P. Zhou, Electronics based <lb/>on two-dimensional materials: Status and outlook, Nano <lb/>Research 14, 1752 (2021). <lb/>[2] C.-C. Lu, Y.-C. Lin, Z. Liu, C.-H. Yeh, K. Suenaga, <lb/>and P.-W. Chiu, Twisting bilayer graphene superlattices, <lb/>ACS nano 7, 2587 (2013). <lb/>[3] E. Y. Andrei and A. H. MacDonald, Graphene bilayers <lb/>with a twist, Nature materials 19, 1265 (2020). <lb/>[4] E. Räsänen, C. A. Rozzi, S. Pittalis, and G. Vi-<lb/>gnale, Electron-electron interactions in artificial <lb/>graphene, Physical Review Letters 108, 10.1103/phys-<lb/>revlett.108.246803 (2012). <lb/>[5] S. Paavilainen, M. Ropo, J. Nieminen, J. Akola, and <lb/>E. Räsänen, Coexisting honeycomb and kagome char-<lb/>acteristics in the electronic band structure of molecular <lb/>graphene, Nano Letters 16, 3519-3523 (2016). <lb/>[6] M. Polini, F. Guinea, M. Lewenstein, H. C. Manoha-<lb/>ran, and V. Pellegrini, Artificial honeycomb lattices for <lb/>electrons, atoms and photons, Nature Nanotechnology 8, <lb/>625-633 (2013). <lb/>[7] T. Geisel, J. Wagenhuber, P. Niebauer, and G. Obermair, <lb/>Chaotic dynamics of ballistic electrons in lateral super-<lb/>lattices and magnetic fields, Phys. Rev. Lett. 64, 1581 <lb/>(1990). <lb/>[8] C. G. Joslin and P. A. Egelstaff, Computer simulation of <lb/>some dynamical properties of the lorentz gas, Journal of <lb/>Statistical Physics 56, 127 (1989). <lb/>[9] P. Baldwin, Soft billiard systems, Physica D: Nonlinear <lb/>Phenomena 29, 321 (1988). <lb/>[10] H. Lorentz, The motion of electrons in metallic bodies i, <lb/>in KNAW, proceedings, Vol. 7 (1905) pp. 438-453. <lb/>[11] E. J. Heller, R. Fleischmann, and T. Kramer, Branched <lb/>flow, Physics Today 74, 44 (2021). <lb/>[12] A. Daza, E. J. Heller, A. M. Graf, and E. Räsänen, <lb/>Propagation of waves in high brillouin zones: Chaotic <lb/>branched flow and stable superwires, Proceedings of the <lb/>National Academy of Sciences 118, e2110285118 (2021), <lb/>https://www.pnas.org/doi/pdf/10.1073/pnas.2110285118. <lb/>[13] M. J. Davis and E. J. Heller, Quantum dynamical tun-<lb/>neling in bound states, The Journal of Chemical Physics <lb/>75, 246 (1981). <lb/>[14] Keshavamurthy, Srihari, and Peter Schlagheck, Dynami-<lb/></listBibl>

        <page>12 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>cal Tunneling: Theory and Experiment (Taylor &amp; Fran-<lb/>cis, 2011). <lb/>[15] S. Tomsovic and D. Ullmo, Chaos-assisted tunneling, <lb/>Phys. Rev. E 50, 145 (1994). <lb/>[16] H. Li, S. Li, M. H. Naik, J. Xie, X. Li, J. Wang, E. Re-<lb/>gan, D. Wang, W. Zhao, S. Zhao, et al., Imaging moiré <lb/>flat bands in three-dimensional reconstructed wse2/ws2 <lb/>superlattices, Nature materials 20, 945 (2021). <lb/>[17] D. Leykam, A. Andreanov, and S. Flach, Artificial flat <lb/>band systems: from lattice models to experiments, Ad-<lb/>vances in Physics: X 3, 1473052 (2018). <lb/>[18] Q. Tian, S. Izadi Vishkayi, M. Bagheri Tagani, L. Zhang, <lb/>Y. Tian, L.-J. Yin, L. Zhang, and Z. Qin, Two-<lb/>dimensional artificial ge superlattice confining in elec-<lb/>tronic kagome lattice potential valleys, Nano Letters 23, <lb/>9851 (2023). <lb/>[19] H. Tamura, K. Shiraishi, T. Kimura, and H. Takayanagi, <lb/>Flat-band ferromagnetism in quantum dot superlattices, <lb/>Physical Review B 65, 085324 (2002). <lb/>[20] J. Mao, S. P. Milovanovic, M. Andelkovic, X. Lai, Y. Cao, <lb/>K. Watanabe, T. Taniguchi, L. Covaci, F. M. Peeters, <lb/>A. K. Geim, Y. Jiang, and E. Y. Andrei, Evidence of flat <lb/>bands and correlated states in buckled graphene super-<lb/>lattices, Nature 584, 215 (2020). <lb/>[21] E. Andrade, P. A. Pantaleón, F. Guinea, and G. G. Nau-<lb/>mis, Flat bands and electronic localization in twisted bi-<lb/>layer graphene nanoribbons, Phys. Rev. B 108, 235418 <lb/>(2023). <lb/>[22] T. Li, J. Ingham, and H. D. Scammell, Artificial <lb/>graphene: Unconventional superconductivity in a honey-<lb/>comb superlattice, Physical Review Research 2, 043155 <lb/>(2020). <lb/>[23] M. Thumin and G. Bouzerar, Flat-band superconductiv-<lb/>ity in a system with a tunable quantum metric: The stub <lb/>lattice, Phys. Rev. B 107, 214508 (2023). <lb/>[24] H. Tian, X. Gao, Y. Zhang, S. Che, T. Xu, P. Che-<lb/>ung, K. Watanabe, T. Taniguchi, M. Randeria, F. Zhang, <lb/>et al., Evidence for dirac flat band superconductivity en-<lb/>abled by quantum geometry, Nature 614, 440 (2023). <lb/>[25] L. Balents, C. R. Dean, D. K. Efetov, and A. F. Young, <lb/>Superconductivity and strong correlations in moiré flat <lb/>bands, Nature Physics 16, 725 (2020). <lb/>[26] S. Lisi, X. Lu, T. Benschop, T. A. de Jong, P. Stepanov, <lb/>J. R. Duran, F. Margot, I. Cucchi, E. Cappelli, <lb/>A. Hunter, et al., Observation of flat bands in twisted <lb/>bilayer graphene, Nature Physics 17, 189 (2021). <lb/>[27] M. Yankowitz, S. Chen, H. Polshyn, Y. Zhang, K. Watan-<lb/>abe, T. Taniguchi, D. Graf, A. F. Young, and C. R. Dean, <lb/>Tuning superconductivity in twisted bilayer graphene, <lb/>Science 363, 1059 (2019). <lb/>[28] D. Marchenko, D. Evtushinsky, E. Golias, A. Varykhalov, <lb/>T. Seyller, and O. Rader, Extremely flat band in bilayer <lb/>graphene, Science advances 4, eaau0059 (2018). <lb/>[29] M. Oh, K. P. Nuckolls, D. Wong, R. L. Lee, X. Liu, <lb/>K. Watanabe, T. Taniguchi, and A. Yazdani, Evidence <lb/>for unconventional superconductivity in twisted bilayer <lb/>graphene, Nature 600, 240 (2021). <lb/>[30] N. R. Chebrolu, B. L. Chittari, and J. Jung, Flat bands <lb/>in twisted double bilayer graphene, Physical Review B <lb/>99, 235417 (2019). <lb/>[31] E. J. Heller, The semiclassical way to dynamics and spec-<lb/>troscopy (Princeton University Press, 2018). <lb/>[32] M. Scully and M. Zubairy, Quantum Optics (Cambridge <lb/>University Press, 1997). <lb/>[33] D. Walls and G. Milburn, Quantum Optics (Springer <lb/>Berlin Heidelberg, 2007). <lb/>[34] J. Keski-Rahkonen, P. J. J. Luukko, L. Kaplan, E. J. <lb/>Heller, and E. Räsänen, Controllable quantum scars in <lb/>semiconductor quantum dots, Phys. Rev. B 96, 094204 <lb/>(2017). <lb/>[35] J. Keski-Rahkonen, A. Ruhanen, E. J. Heller, and <lb/>E. Räsänen, Quantum lissajous scars, Phys. Rev. Lett. <lb/>123, 214101 (2019). <lb/>[36] J. P. Bernick and P. R. Baldwin, Loss of channeling in a <lb/>disordered lattice of focusing scatterers, Physics Letters <lb/>A 197, 305 (1995). <lb/>[37] A. Aydin, J. Keski-Rahkonen, and E. J. Heller, Quan-<lb/>tum acoustics spawns planckian resistivity, Quantum <lb/>acoustics spawns Planckian resistivity, arXiv preprint <lb/>arXiv:2303.06077 (Submitted) (2023). <lb/>[38] J. Keski-Rahkonen, X.-Y. Ouyang, S. Yuan, A. Graf, <lb/>A. Aydin, and E. Heller, Quantum-acoustical drude <lb/>peak shift, Quantum-Acoustical Drude Peak Shift, arXiv <lb/>preprint arXiv:2310.19143 (Submitted) (2023). </listBibl>


	</text>

</TEI>