<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Checkpoint inhibition enhances cell contacts between CD4&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;+&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt; T cells and Hodgkin-Reed-Sternberg cells of classic Hodgkin lymphoma</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Kübra</forename>
          <surname>Yadigaroglu</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Sonja</forename>
          <surname>Scharf</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Steffen</forename>
          <surname>Gretser</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Hendrik</forename>
          <surname>Schäfer</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Aresu Sadeghi Shoreh</forename>
          <surname>Deli</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Andreas G.</forename>
          <surname>Loth</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Hasmik</forename>
          <surname>Yegoryan</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Roland</forename>
          <surname>Schmitz</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Emmanuel</forename>
          <surname>Donnadieu</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Martin-Leo</forename>
          <surname>Hansmann</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Sylvia</forename>
          <surname>Hartmann</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-04T14:21:49.488Z">11/4/2025 2:21:49 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Ferrata Storti Foundation (Haematologica)</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.3324/haematol.2023.284512</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Kübra Yadigaroglu, Sonja Scharf, Steffen Gretser, Hendrik Schäfer, Aresu Sadeghi Shoreh Deli, Andreas G. Loth, Hasmik Yegoryan, Roland Schmitz, Emmanuel Donnadieu, Martin-Leo Hansmann, Sylvia Hartmann. (2024). Checkpoint inhibition enhances cell contacts between CD4&amp;lt;sup&amp;gt;+&amp;lt;/sup&amp;gt; T cells and Hodgkin-Reed-Sternberg cells of classic Hodgkin lymphoma. Haematologica, 109(10), 3295-3304. DOI: 10.3324/haematol.2023.284512</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-04T14:19:33.944819Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-04T14:19:33.944819Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>Haematologica | 109 July 2024 <lb/>2122 <lb/>-Acute Myeloid Leukemia <lb/>ARTICLE <lb/>Matched unrelated donor transplantation versus <lb/>haploidentical transplantation with post-transplant <lb/>cyclophosphamide in children with acute myeloid <lb/>leukemia: a PDWP-EBMT study <lb/>Annalisa Ruggeri, 1* Nicole Santoro, 2* Jacques-Emmanuel Galimard, 3 Krzysztof Kalwak, 4 Mattia <lb/>Algeri, 5,6 Ludmila Zubarovskaya, 7 Krzysztof Czyzewski, 8 Elena Skorobogatova, 9 Petr Sedlacek, 10 <lb/>Caroline Besley, 11 Adriana Balduzzi, 12,13 Yves Bertrand, 14 Julia Peristeri, 15 Franca Fagioli, 16 Mariane <lb/>Ifversen, 17 Jolanta Gozdzik, 18 Christina Peters, 19 Birgitta Versluijs, 20 Alessandra Biffi, 21 Arcangelo <lb/>Prete, 22 Maura Faraci, 23 Ibrahim Ghemlas, 24 Ivana Bodova, 25 Olga Aleinikova, 26 Arnaud Dalissier, 27 <lb/>Vanderson Rocha 28 and Selim Corbacioglu 29 <lb/>1 <lb/>IRCCS San Raffaele Scientific Institute, Milano, Italy; 2 Hematology Unit, Department of <lb/>Oncology and Hematology, Santo Spirito Hospital, Pescara, Italy; 3 EBMT Statistical Unit, Paris, <lb/>France; 4 Department of Pediatric Hematology, Oncology and Bone Marrow Transplantation, <lb/>Wroclaw Medical University, Wroclaw, Poland; 5 Department of Pediatric Hematology Oncology, <lb/>IRCCS Bambino Gesu Children&apos; s Hospital, Rome, Italy; 6 Department of Health Sciences, Magna <lb/>Graecia University, Catanzaro, Italy; 7 RM Gorbacheva Research Institute, Pavlov University, St. <lb/>Petersburg, Russia; 8 Department of Pediatric Hematology and Oncology, Collegium Medicum, <lb/>Nicolaus Copernicus University Torun, Bydgoszcz, Poland; 9 The Russian Children&apos; s Research <lb/>Hospital, Department of Bone Marrow Transplantation, Moscow, Russia; 10 University Hospital <lb/>Motol, Department of Pediatric Hematology and Oncology, Prague, Czech Republic; 11 Bristol <lb/>Royal Hospital for Children, Department of Pediatric Oncology/BMT, Bristol, UK; <lb/>12 <lb/>Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation Unit, Fondazione IRCCS San Gerardo dei Tintori, <lb/>Monza, Italy; 13 Department of Medicine and Surgery, Milano-Bicocca University, Monza, Italy; <lb/>14 <lb/>Institut d`Hematologie et d`Oncologie Pediatrique, Lyon, France; 15 St Sophia Children&apos;s <lb/>Hospital Oncology Center, Athens, Greece; 16 Onco-Ematologia Pediatrica Centro Trapianti <lb/>Cellule Staminali, Torino, Italy; 17 Copenhagen University Hospital, Rigshospitalet, Department <lb/>of Children and Adolescents Medicine, Copenhagen, Denmark; 18 Department of Clinical <lb/>Immunology and Transplantation, Jagiellonian University Medical College, Children&apos;s Hospital, <lb/>Krakow, Poland; 19 St. Anna Children&apos;s Hospital, Department of Pediatrics, Medical University of <lb/>Vienna, Vienna, Austria; 20 Princess Maxima Center, Utrecht, the Netherlands; 21 Clinica di <lb/>Oncoematologia Pediatrica, Dipartimento di Pediatria, Padova, Italy; 22 IRCCS-Azienda <lb/>Ospedaliero Universitaria, Bologna, Italy; 23 HSCT Unit, Department Hemato-Oncology, IRCSS <lb/>Istituto G. Gaslini, Genova, Italy; 24 Pediatric Hematology/Oncology, King Faisal Specialist <lb/>Hospital and Research Center, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia; 25 Pediatric University Teaching Hospital <lb/>BMT Unit, II Children`s Clinic Bratislava, Slovakia; 26 Belorussian Center for Pediatric Oncology <lb/>and Hematology, Minsk, Russia; 27 EBMT Paris Study Unit, Paris, France; 28 BMT Unit, Sao Paolo <lb/>University, Sao Paolo, Brasil and 29 University of Regensburg, Regensburg, Germany <lb/>*AR and NS contributed equally as first authors. <lb/>Abstract <lb/>In children with acute myeloid leukemia (AML) who lack a human leukocyte antigen (HLA) identical sibling, the donor can <lb/>be replaced with an HLA-matched unrelated donor (MUD) or a haploidentical donor (haplo). We compared outcomes of <lb/>patients &lt;18 years with AML in first and second complete remission (CR1 &amp; CR2) undergoing a hematopoietic stem cell <lb/>transplantation (HCT) either with a MUD with anti-thymocyte globulin (ATG) (N=420) or a haplo HCT with post-transplant <lb/>cyclophosphamide (PT-CY) (N=96) after a myeloablative conditioning regimen (MAC) between 2011 and 2021, reported to the <lb/>Correspondence: A. Ruggeri <lb/>ruggeri.annalisa@hsr.it <lb/>Received: <lb/>October 26, 2023. <lb/>Accepted: <lb/>December 28, 2023. <lb/>Early view: <lb/>January 4, 2024. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3324/haematol.2023.284445 <lb/>©2024 Ferrata Storti Foundation <lb/>Published under a CC BY-NC license <lb/>Haematologica | 109 July 2024 <lb/>2123 <lb/>ARTICLE -MUD versus haplo PT-CY stem cell transplantation in children with AML <lb/>A. Ruggeri et al. <lb/></front>

        <body>Introduction <lb/>Childhood acute myeloid leukemia (AML) is a rare and <lb/>heterogeneous disease, with an incidence of seven cases <lb/>per million children younger than 15 years. 1 Improvements <lb/>in genomic characterization, disease response monitoring, 2 <lb/>as well as the introduction of new drugs 3 and advances in <lb/>allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplantation (HCT) tech-<lb/>niques 4 have resulted in improved outcomes with survival <lb/>rates reaching 70% in high-income countries. First line <lb/>treatment approaches for pediatric AML include four or <lb/>five cycles of myelosuppressive chemotherapy followed by <lb/>HCT for high-risk patients, 5 while HCT is offered in second <lb/>clinical remission for other cases. 5,6 <lb/>In recent years, the development of HCT from alternative <lb/>donors, preferably from matched unrelated donors (MUD), <lb/>has provided the means to offer HCT, when no human <lb/>leukocyte antigen (HLA)-matched family donor is available. <lb/>However, in up to 40% of patients a MUD cannot be iden-<lb/>tified in international donor registries. 7 Recently, HCT from <lb/>relatives sharing only one HLA-haplotype with the recipient <lb/>(haplo-HCT) has emerged as a suitable alternative, with <lb/>the great advantage that haplo-donors may be available for <lb/>almost all patients, in due time, with a flexible schedule <lb/>and additional cellular therapies being readily available. <lb/>In haplo-HCT, different techniques to overcome the HLA <lb/>barrier 8-12 have been developed for improving immune re-<lb/>constitution and graft-versus-leukemia with no excess of <lb/>graft-versus-host disease (GVHD). In the last years, the use <lb/>of T-cell replete haplo-HCT with post-transplant cyclophos-<lb/>phamide (PT-CY), 8 has rapidly increased across the world, <lb/>showing identical clinical outcomes to matched donors <lb/>(MD) in several retrospective studies in adults. 8 <lb/>Many studies demonstrated that PT-CY given after graft <lb/>infusion can eliminate alloreactive T cells while preserving <lb/>hematopoietic cells as well as memory and regulatory T <lb/>cells. 13,14 In pediatric patients affected by acute leukemia, <lb/>promising clinical results have been reported, 13,15-19 but spe-<lb/>cific data on AML are lacking. <lb/>Here, we compared the results of a haplo-HCT with PT-<lb/>CY to a MUD HCT using anti-thymocyte globulin (ATG) for <lb/>the treatment of children affected by AML reported to the <lb/>European Society for Blood and Marrow Transplantation <lb/>(EBMT) registry. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Study design and definitions <lb/>This multicenter retrospective study was conducted on <lb/>behalf of the Pediatric Diseases Working Party (PDWP) of <lb/>EBMT after approval by the institutional review board of <lb/>the PDWP. Data were collected according to EBMT rules. <lb/>Patients or legal guardians provided written informed con-<lb/>sent for data collection and analysis in accordance with the <lb/>Declaration of Helsinki. Included were pediatric patients <lb/>(age &lt;18 years) diagnosed with AML, transplanted in first <lb/>or second complete remission from 2011 to 2021, who un-<lb/>derwent a first allo-HCT using either a 10/10 MUD with ATG <lb/>or a haploidentical family donor (≥2 recipient-donor HLA <lb/>mismatch number) in a haplo-HCT with PT-CY. Transplants <lb/>were performed in 117 EBMT centers. All patients received <lb/>a myeloablative conditioning (MAC) regimen, and the graft <lb/>source was bone marrow (BM) or peripheral blood, accord-<lb/>ing to the transplant center policy. In patients receiving ex <lb/>vivo T-cell depletion, alemtuzumab or a combination of <lb/>ATG and PT-CY was excluded. <lb/>Outcomes <lb/>The primary objective was to compare the leukemia-free <lb/>survival (LFS) of AML patients receiving either a haplo-PT-<lb/>CY or a MUD-ATG HCT. The secondary objectives were the <lb/>comparison of overall survival (OS), non-relapse mortali-<lb/>ty (NRM), relapse incidence (RI), incidence of both acute <lb/>GVHD (aGVHD) and chronic GVHD (cGVHD), GVHD-free/ <lb/>relapse-free survival (GRFS) in both groups. LFS was de-<lb/>fined as time from HCT to first event of relapse or death. <lb/>OS was defined as the time from HCT to death from any <lb/>cause. RI was defined as the time from HCT to the first <lb/>event of leukemia recurrence. Non-relapse mortality (NRM) <lb/>was defined as death without evidence of relapse. RI and <lb/>NRM were mutually competing events. GRFS was defined <lb/>as the time from HCT to the first event among grade 3-4 <lb/>aGVHD, extensive cGVHD, relapse, and death. 20 Grade 2-4 <lb/></body>

        <front>European Society for Blood and Marrow Transplantation. A matched pair analysis was performed to adjust for differences <lb/>among groups. The final analysis was performed on 253 MUD and 95 haplo-HCT. In the matched cohort, median age at HCT <lb/>was 11.2 and 10 years and median year of HCT was 2017 and 2018, in MUD and haplo-HCT recipients, respectively. The risk <lb/>of grade III-IV acute graft-versus-host disease (aGVHD) was significantly higher in the haplo group (hazard ratio [HR]=2.33, <lb/>95% confidence interval [CI]: 1.18-4.58; P=0.01). No significant differences were found in 2 years overall survival (OS; 78.4% <lb/>vs. 71.5%; HR=1.39, 95% CI: 0.84-2.31; P=0.19), leukemia-free survival (LFS; 72.7% vs. 69.5%; HR=1.22, 95% CI: 0.76-1.95; P=0.41), <lb/>CI of relapse (RI; 19.3% vs. 19.5%; HR=1.14, 95% CI: 0.62-2.08; P=0.68) non-relapse-mortality (NRM; 8% vs. 11%; HR=1.39, 95% <lb/>CI: 0.66-2.93; P=0.39) and graft-versus-host free relapse-free survival (GRFS; 60.7% vs. 54.5%, HR=1.38, 95% CI: 0.95-2.02; <lb/>P=0.09) after MUD and haplo-HCT respectively. Our study suggests that haplo-HCT with PT-CY is a suitable option to trans-<lb/>plant children with AML lacking a matched related donor. <lb/></front>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 109 July 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2124 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -MUD versus haplo PT-CY stem cell transplantation in children with AML <lb/>A. Ruggeri et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>aGVHD and cGVHD were assigned and graded using stan-<lb/>dard criteria. 21, 22 Competing events of aGVHD and cGVHD <lb/>were relapse and death. Cytogenetics abnormalities were <lb/>classified according to the genetically defined prognostic <lb/>stratification of the 2017 European Leukemia Net cytogenetic <lb/>classification system. 1 Neutrophil recovery was defined as <lb/>the time from HCT to the first of 3 consecutive days with <lb/>neutrophil counts above 0.5x10 9 /L; platelet recovery was <lb/>defined as independence from platelet transfusion for at <lb/>least 7 days with a platelet count of more than &gt;20×10 9 /L. <lb/>Death and consecutive HCT were competing events. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>The overall population included 420 MUD and 96 haplo PT-<lb/>CY. A matched pair analysis was performed to reduce or <lb/>eliminate confounding factors: the matching included exact <lb/>match on disease status, cell source and age group at HCT, <lb/>and nearest match on year of HCT, age at diagnosis, female <lb/>donor to male recipient, Lansky score and cytomegalovirus <lb/>match. A maximum of three MUD matched patients was <lb/>allowed for one haplo PT-CY. There were three controls for <lb/>73, two for 12 and one for ten haplo PT-CY. For one haplo <lb/>PT-CY it was impossible to find a control. Finally, a match <lb/>could be identified for 253 MUD and 95 haplo PT-CY. <lb/>Median values with respective interquartile ranges (IQR), <lb/>were used to express quantitative variables while frequen-<lb/>cies and percentages were used for categorical variables. <lb/>On the unmatched population, differences between MUD <lb/>and haplo PT-CY on quantitative and qualitative variables <lb/>have been tested using χ 2 and Wilcoxon tests respectively. <lb/>LFS, OS and GRFS were estimated using the Kaplan-Meier <lb/>estimator. All outcomes with competing events were esti-<lb/>mated using the cumulative incidence function. Median fol-<lb/>low-up was estimated using the reverse of the Kaplan-Meier <lb/>method. All outcomes were censored at last follow-up or <lb/>at 2 years due to a different follow-up between the groups. <lb/>Differences in outcomes were tested using a Cox model <lb/>including a cluster term for each pair. Results are expressed <lb/>as hazard ratio (HR). Outcomes and HR are presented with <lb/>their 95% confidence interval (CI). All tests are two-sided <lb/>with an error rate fixed at 5%. Analyses were done using R <lb/>statistical software version 4.0.2 (http://www.R-project.org), <lb/>and matching was performed using the MatchIt package. <lb/>Results <lb/>Patients and transplant characteristics <lb/>Patient and transplant characteristics are summarized in <lb/>Table 1. Overall, 96 and 420 patients receiving a haplo PT-<lb/>CY or MUD HCT, respectively, fulfilled the inclusion criteria. <lb/>Median age at transplant was 9.8 (IQR, 3.0-15.2) years for <lb/>haplo PT-CY and 7.7 (IQR, 2.8-13.6) years for MUD (P=0.03). <lb/>Patients in the haplo group were transplanted more recently <lb/>(median 2018 for haplo vs. 2016 for MUD, P&lt;0.01). In both <lb/>groups the majority of patients were in CR1 at transplant <lb/>(72.9% haplo vs. 70.5% MUD; P=0.63). <lb/>Cytogenetic risk at diagnosis was not significantly different <lb/>in the two groups (good: 21.3% vs. 13.6%, intermediate: 48% <lb/>vs. 44.3%, poor: 30.7% vs. 42.1% in haplo PT-CY and MUD <lb/>respectively). <lb/>Donors were older in the haplo PT-CY than in the MUD <lb/>cohort: 35.7 years (IQR, 29.9-42.7) versus 27.7 years (IQR, <lb/>23.3-34.2; P&lt;0.01). BM was the most frequently used stem <lb/>cell source in both groups (65.6% for haplo vs. 63.6% for <lb/>MUD; P=0.71). <lb/>Conditioning regimen was MAC, mainly based on busulfan <lb/>(Bu), with Bu/fludarabine (66.7%) based in the haplo PT-CY <lb/>and Bu/CY (28.8%) or Bu/CY/melphalan (38.3%) being the <lb/>most common in MUD. <lb/>Post-HCT immunosuppression consisted mainly of cyc-<lb/>losporine (CSA) plus mycophenolate mofetil (MMF) in the <lb/>haplo PT-CY (52.1%) and CSA plus methotrexate (MTX) in <lb/>the MUD cohort (68.6%). <lb/>The baseline characteristics of the matched cohort are <lb/>described in Table 2. <lb/>Engraftment, acute and chronic graft-versus-host <lb/>disease <lb/>The CI of day 60 neutrophils and day 180 platelet recovery <lb/>for haplo PT-CY was 90.4% (95% CI: 82-95) and 92.2% (95% <lb/>CI: 82.6-96.6) while for MUD it was 97.1% (95% CI: 93.9-98.6) <lb/>and 93.8% (95% CI: 89.1-96.4) respectively. <lb/>The 100 day grade 2-4 aGVHD was 36.7% (95% CI: 26.8-46.6) <lb/>for haplo PT-CY and 28.7% (95% CI: 23.2-34.4) for MUD and <lb/>CI of grade 3-4 aGvHD was 14.4% (95% CI: 8.1-22.5) versus <lb/>6.4% (95% CI: 3.8-9.9), respectively. <lb/>2-year CI of cGVHD was 22.4% (95% CI: 13.4-32.8) and 18.5% <lb/>(95% CI: 13.5-24.1) for haplo PT-CY and MUD respectively; <lb/>2-year CI of extensive cGVHD was 6.6% (95% CI: 2.4-13.8) <lb/>and 8.6% (95% CI: 5.3-13) for haplo PT-CY and MUD (Table 3). <lb/>According to donor type, there were no statistically signifi-<lb/>cant differences between groups on the incidence of grade <lb/>2-4 aGVHD (HR=1.26, 95% CI: 0.84-1.89; P=0.27), cGVHD <lb/>(HR=1.81, 95% CI: 0.75-4.37; P=0.19) and extensive cGVHD <lb/>(HR=1.01, 95% CI: 0.25-4.03; P=0.99). The risk of grade 3-4 <lb/>aGvHD was significantly higher in haplo PT-CY (HR=2.33, <lb/>95% CI: 1.18-4.58; P=0.03) (Table 4). <lb/>Main outcomes <lb/>Results of the punctual estimation of outcomes after <lb/>matched-pair analysis are summarized in Table 3. <lb/>The 2-year CI of RI was 19.5% (95% 11.4-29.2) for haplo PT-<lb/>CY versus 19.3% (95% CI: 14.4-29.4) for MUD. The 2-year <lb/>NRM was 11% (95% CI: 5.2-19.1) versus 8% (95% CI: 5-11.9) <lb/>after haplo PT-CY and MUD respectively. <lb/>The 2-year OS was 71.5% (95% CI: 59.1-80.7) and 78.4% (95% <lb/>CI: 72.2-83.4), the 2-year LFS was 69.5% (95% CI: 57.7-78.6) <lb/>and 72.7% (95% CI: 66.3-78.1) and the 2-year GRFS was <lb/>54.5% (95% CI: 42.5-65) and 60.7% (95% CI: 53.8-66.9) for <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 109 July 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2125 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -MUD versus haplo PT-CY stem cell transplantation in children with AML <lb/>A. Ruggeri et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>Variables <lb/>Modalities <lb/>N=516 <lb/>N (%) <lb/>MUD N=420 <lb/>N (%) <lb/>Haplo PT-CY N=96 <lb/>N (%) <lb/>P <lb/>Age in years at HCT <lb/>median (IQR) <lb/>8.5 (2.8-13.7) <lb/>7.7 (2.8-13.6) <lb/>9.8 (3-15.2) <lb/>0.03 <lb/>Age in years at HCT <lb/>0-7 <lb/>231 (44.8) <lb/>200 (47.6) <lb/>31 (32.3) <lb/>Not done <lb/>7-12 <lb/>107 (20.7) <lb/>82 (19.5) <lb/>25 (26) <lb/>-<lb/>12-18 <lb/>178 (34.5) <lb/>138 (32.9) <lb/>40 (41.7) <lb/>-<lb/>Disease status at HCT <lb/>CR1 <lb/>366 (70.9) <lb/>296 (70.5) <lb/>70 (72.9) <lb/>0.63 <lb/>CR2 <lb/>150 (29.1) <lb/>124 (29.5) <lb/>26 (27.1) <lb/>-<lb/>Molecular remission <lb/>No <lb/>49 (15.6) <lb/>41 (15.9) <lb/>8 (14) <lb/>0.73 <lb/>Yes <lb/>266 (84.4) <lb/>217 (84.1) <lb/>49 (86) <lb/>-<lb/>Missing <lb/>201 <lb/>162 <lb/>39 <lb/>-<lb/>Year of HCT <lb/>Median (IQR) <lb/>2017 (2014-2019) <lb/>2016 (2014-2018) <lb/>2018 (2017-2020) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>Range <lb/>2011-2021 <lb/>2011-2021 <lb/>2011-2021 <lb/>-<lb/>Relation to donor <lb/>Parent <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>70 (83.3) <lb/>Not done <lb/>Sibling <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>14 (16.7) <lb/>-<lb/>Missing <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>12 <lb/>-<lb/>Donor age in years <lb/>Median (IQR) <lb/>29.1 (23.8-36.3) <lb/>27.7 (23.3-34.2) <lb/>35.7 (29.5-42.7) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>Missing <lb/>104 <lb/>91 <lb/>13 <lb/>-<lb/>Cell source <lb/>BM <lb/>330 (64) <lb/>267 (63.6) <lb/>63 (65.6) <lb/>0.71 <lb/>PB <lb/>186 (36) <lb/>153 (36.4) <lb/>33 (34.4) <lb/>-<lb/>Patient sex <lb/>Female <lb/>242 (46.9) <lb/>197 (46.9) <lb/>45 (46.9) <lb/>0.99 <lb/>Male <lb/>274 (53.1) <lb/>223 (53.1) <lb/>51 (53.1) <lb/>-<lb/>Female donor to male <lb/>recipient <lb/>No <lb/>434 (84.1) <lb/>365 (86.9) <lb/>69 (71.9) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>Yes <lb/>82 (15.9) <lb/>55 (13.1) <lb/>27 (28.1) <lb/>-<lb/>Lansky or KPS <lb/>&lt;90 <lb/>119 (23.1) <lb/>104 (24.8) <lb/>15 (15.6) <lb/>0.06 <lb/>≥90 <lb/>397 (76.9) <lb/>316 (75.2) <lb/>81 (84.4) <lb/>-<lb/>CMV-IgG match <lb/>(donor-recipient) <lb/>Neg to Neg <lb/>120 (23.3) <lb/>112 (26.7) <lb/>8 (8.3) <lb/>&lt; 0.001 <lb/>Neg to Pos <lb/>130 (25.2) <lb/>123 (29.3) <lb/>7 (7.3) <lb/>-<lb/>Pos to Neg <lb/>60 (11.6) <lb/>50 (11.9) <lb/>10 (10.4) <lb/>-<lb/>Pos to Pos <lb/>206 (39.9) <lb/>135 (32.1) <lb/>71 (74) <lb/>-<lb/>Cytogenetic risk <lb/>Good <lb/>66 (14.9) <lb/>50 (13.6) <lb/>16 (21.3) <lb/>0.09 <lb/>Intermediate <lb/>199 (44.9) <lb/>163 (44.3) <lb/>36 (48) <lb/>-<lb/>Poor <lb/>178 (40.2) <lb/>155 (42.1) <lb/>23 (30.7) <lb/>-<lb/>Missing <lb/>73 <lb/>52 <lb/>21 <lb/>-<lb/>GVHD prophylaxis <lb/>CSA+MTX based <lb/>289 (56) <lb/>288 (68.6) <lb/>1 (1) <lb/>Not done <lb/>CSA based <lb/>71 (13.8) <lb/>66 (15.7) <lb/>5 (5.2) <lb/>-<lb/>CSA+MMF based <lb/>67 (13) <lb/>17 (4) <lb/>50 (52.1) <lb/>-<lb/>CSA+MMF+MTX based <lb/>12 (2.3) <lb/>9 (2.1) <lb/>3 (3.1) <lb/>-<lb/>Other <lb/>77 (14.9) <lb/>40 (9.5) <lb/>37 (38.5) <lb/>-<lb/>Conditioning regimen <lb/>BuCyMel based <lb/>162 (31.4) <lb/>161 (38.3) <lb/>1 (1) <lb/>Not done <lb/>BuCy based <lb/>131 (25.4) <lb/>121 (28.8) <lb/>10 (10.4) <lb/>-<lb/>BuFlu based <lb/>123 (23.8) <lb/>59 (14) <lb/>64 (66.7) <lb/>-<lb/>Treo based <lb/>88 (17.1) <lb/>70 (16.7) <lb/>18 (18.8) <lb/>-<lb/>Other combinations <lb/>12 (2.3) <lb/>9 (2.1) <lb/>3 (3.1) <lb/>-<lb/>MUD: matched unrelated donors; haplo: haploidentical; PT-CY: post-transplant cyclophosphamide, HCT: hematopoietic stem cell transplan-<lb/>tation; IQR: interquartile range; CR: complete remission; BM: bone marrow; PB: peripheral blood; KPS: Karnofsky Performance status, CMV: <lb/>cytomegalovirus; GVHD: graft-versus-host disease; CSA: cyclosporin; MTX: methotrexate, MMF: mycophenolate mofetile; Bu: busulfan, Flu: <lb/>fludarabine; Cy: cyclophosphamide; Mel: melphalan; Treo: treosulfan; Pos: positive; Neg: negative. <lb/>Table 1. Patients and transplant characteristics. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 109 July 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2126 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -MUD versus haplo PT-CY stem cell transplantation in children with AML <lb/>A. Ruggeri et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>Table 2. Patients and transplant characteristics in the matched pair cohort. <lb/>Variables <lb/>Modalities <lb/>MUD N=253 <lb/>N (%) <lb/>Haplo PT-CY N=95 <lb/>N (%) <lb/>Age in years at HCT <lb/>Median (IQR) <lb/>11.2 (4.9-14.6) <lb/>10 <lb/>Age in years at HCT <lb/>0-7 <lb/>87 (34.4) <lb/>31 (32.6) <lb/>7-12 <lb/>51 (20.2) <lb/>24 (25.3) <lb/>12-18 <lb/>115 (45.5) <lb/>40 (42.1) <lb/>Disease status at HCT <lb/>CR1 <lb/>178 (70.4) <lb/>69 (72.6) <lb/>CR2 <lb/>75 (29.6) <lb/>26 (27.4) <lb/>Molecular remission <lb/>No <lb/>26 (16) <lb/>7 (12.5) <lb/>Yes <lb/>136 (84) <lb/>49 (87.5) <lb/>Missing <lb/>91 <lb/>39 <lb/>Year of HCT <lb/>Median (IQR) <lb/>2017 (2014-2019) <lb/>2018 (2017-2020) <lb/>Relation to donor <lb/>Parent <lb/>-<lb/>69 (83.1) <lb/>Sibling <lb/>-<lb/>14 (16.9) <lb/>Missing <lb/>-<lb/>12 <lb/>Donor age in years <lb/>Median (IQR) <lb/>27 (23.2-34.2) <lb/>35.7 (29.5-42.89 <lb/>Range <lb/>18.4-57.4 <lb/>4.4-54.3 <lb/>Missing <lb/>48 <lb/>13 <lb/>Source of cells <lb/>BM <lb/>163 (64.4) <lb/>62 (65.3) <lb/>PB <lb/>90 (35.6) <lb/>33 (34.7) <lb/>Patient sex <lb/>Female <lb/>123 (48.6) <lb/>44 (46.3) <lb/>Male <lb/>130 (51.4) <lb/>51 (53.7) <lb/>Female donor to male recipient <lb/>No <lb/>217 (85.8) <lb/>68 (71.6) <lb/>Yes <lb/>36 (14.2) <lb/>27 (28.4) <lb/>Lansky or KPS <lb/>&lt;90 <lb/>62 (24.5) <lb/>15 (15.8) <lb/>≥90 <lb/>191 (75.5) <lb/>80 (84.2) <lb/>CMV IgG match donor-recipient <lb/>Neg to Neg <lb/>50 (19.8) <lb/>7 (7.4) <lb/>Neg to Pos <lb/>64 (25.3) <lb/>7 (7.4) <lb/>Pos to Neg <lb/>35 (13.8) <lb/>10 (10.5) <lb/>Pos to Pos <lb/>104 (41.1) <lb/>71 (74.7) <lb/>Cytogenetic risk <lb/>Good <lb/>30 (13.7) <lb/>15 (20.3) <lb/>Intermediate <lb/>123 (56.2) <lb/>36 (48.6) <lb/>Poor <lb/>66 (30.1) <lb/>23 (31.1) <lb/>Missing <lb/>34 <lb/>21 <lb/>GVHD prophylaxis <lb/>CSA+MTX based <lb/>169 (66.8) <lb/>1 (1.1) <lb/>CSA based <lb/>46 (18.2) <lb/>5 (5.3) <lb/>CSA+MMF based <lb/>11 (4.3) <lb/>49 (51.6) <lb/>CSA+MMF+MTX based <lb/>3 (1.2) <lb/>3 (3.2) <lb/>Other <lb/>24 (9.5) <lb/>37 (38.9) <lb/>Conditionning regimen <lb/>BuCyMel based <lb/>89 (35.2) <lb/>1 (1.1) <lb/>BuCy based <lb/>71 (28.1) <lb/>10 (10.5) <lb/>BuFlu based <lb/>36 (14.2) <lb/>63 (66.3) <lb/>Treo based <lb/>51 (20.2) <lb/>18 (18.9) <lb/>Other combinations <lb/>6 (2.4) <lb/>3 (3.2) <lb/>MUD: matched unrelated donors; haplo: haploidentical; PT-CY: post-transplant cyclophosphamide, HCT: hematopoietic stem cell transplan-<lb/>tation; IQR: interquartile range; CR: complete remission; BM: bone marrow; PB: peripheral blood; KPS: Karnofsky Performance status, CMV: <lb/>cytomegalovirus; CSA: cyclosporin; MTX: methotrexate, MMF: mycophenolate mofetile; Bu: busulfan; Flu: fludarabine; Cy: cyclophosphamide; <lb/>Mel: melphalan; Treo: treosulfan; Pos: positive; Neg: negative. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 109 July 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2127 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -MUD versus haplo PT-CY stem cell transplantation in children with AML <lb/>A. Ruggeri et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>haplo PT-CY and MUD respectively (Figure 1). <lb/>The most common causes of death were disease recur-<lb/>rence (61.9% in the haplo and 59.6% in the MUD group, <lb/>respectively), infections (28.6% vs. 19.1%), and GVHD (9.5% <lb/>vs. 8.5%). <lb/>There were no statistically significant differences between <lb/>groups on RI (HR=1.14, 95% CI: 0.62-2.08; P=0.68), NRM <lb/>(HR=1.39, 95% CI: 0.66-2.93; P=0.39), OS (HR=1.39, 95% CI: <lb/>0.84-2.31; P=0.19), LFS (HR= 1.22, 95% CI=0.76-1.95; P=0.41) <lb/>and GRFS (HR=1.38, 95% CI: 0.95-2.02; P=0.09) (Table 4). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Allogeneic HCT from MUD remains the standard of care in <lb/>patients who lack a MSD, especially for pediatric patients <lb/>in which transplant-related toxicities and late effects are <lb/>particularly relevant with regard to a long life expectan-<lb/>cy. 23-28 The recent emergence of HLA haplo-HCT extended <lb/>the availability of donors to most pediatric patients with-<lb/>out a MD. 29 Significant improvements of supportive care <lb/>and the technical development of highly effective T-cell <lb/>depleted and T-cell replete HLA-haploidentical platforms, <lb/>have resulted in improved outcomes and reduced trans-<lb/>plant-related mortality for patients undergoing haplo-HCT, 30 <lb/>independently of the haplo platform used. 31,36,37 <lb/>T-cell-depleted haploidentical platforms have been suc-<lb/>cessfully used despite high costs for graft processing and <lb/>specialized expertise. 11,32,33 Of particular interest, Locatelli et <lb/>al. 10 reported the outcome of a cohort of 80 children with <lb/>acute leukemia transplanted from a haplo donor after αb <lb/>T-cell and CD19 + B-cell depletion. All children received a <lb/>myeloablative conditioning and ATG for GVHD prophylaxis <lb/>and graft rejection; no post-transplant GVHD prophylaxis <lb/>was given. The 5-year OS was 72% and LFS 71% with no <lb/>differences in AML and ALL. TRM was 5% and RI was 24%. <lb/>No patients developed grade 2-4 aGVHD with visceral in-<lb/>volvement, grade 3-4 aGVHD or Bertaina et al. 12 <lb/>compared the outcomes of 98 children treated with αb T-cell <lb/>depletion compared with 127 MUD and 118 mismatched UD <lb/>(MMUD). Five-year LFS was not significantly different in the <lb/>three groups (67%, 55%, and 62%, respectively), while a <lb/>lower incidence of aGVHD was reported in patients treated <lb/>with T-cell depleted haplo-HCT, compared with MUD and <lb/>MMUD (2-4 aGVHD was 35% vs. 44% vs. 16%, respectively). <lb/>On the other hand, T-cell-replete haplo-HCT approaches <lb/>are mainly based on PT-CY, pioneered by the John Hopkins <lb/>Table 3. Survival outcomes after matched-pair analysis. <lb/>Outcomes <lb/>N=348 <lb/>MUD <lb/>N=253 <lb/>Haplo <lb/>N=95 <lb/>Estimation, % (95% CI) <lb/>Estimation, % (95% CI) <lb/>Estimation, % (95% CI) <lb/>OS 2-year <lb/>76.6 (71.2-81.2) <lb/>78.4 (72.2-83.4) <lb/>71.5 (59.1-80.7) <lb/>LFS 2-year <lb/>71.8 (66.3-76.6) <lb/>72.7 (66.3-78.1) <lb/>69.5 (57.7-78.6) <lb/>RI 2-year <lb/>19.4 (15.1-24.2) <lb/>19.3 (14.4-24.9) <lb/>19.5 (11.4-29.2) <lb/>NRM 2-year <lb/>8.8 (6-12.2) <lb/>8 (5-11.9) <lb/>11 (5.2-19.1) <lb/>aGVHD 2-4 100 days <lb/>30.8 (26-35.7) <lb/>28.7 (23.2-34.4) <lb/>36.7 (26.8-46.6) <lb/>aGVHD 3-4 100 days <lb/>8.5 (5.8-11.8) <lb/>6.4 (3.8-9.9) <lb/>14.4 (8.1-22.5) <lb/>cGVHD 2-year <lb/>19.5 (15-24.4) <lb/>18.5 (13.5-24.1) <lb/>22.4 (13.4-32.8) <lb/>cGVHD Ext 2-year <lb/>8.2 (5.3-11.8) <lb/>8.6 (5.3-13) <lb/>6.6 (2.4-13.8) <lb/>GRFS 2-year <lb/>59 (53-64.4) <lb/>60.7 (53.8-66.9) <lb/>54.5 (42.5-65) <lb/>Neutrophil engraftment 60 days <lb/>95.3 (92.3-97.1) <lb/>97.1 (93.9-98.6) <lb/>90.4 (82-95) <lb/>Platelet engraftment 180 days <lb/>93.3 (89.5-95.8) <lb/>93.8 (89.1-96.4) <lb/>92.2 (82.6-96.6) <lb/>MUD: matched unrelated donors; haplo: haploidentical; CI: confidence interval; OS: overall survival; LFS: leukemia-free survival; RI: relapse <lb/>incidence; NRM: non-relapse mortality; a: acute, c: chronic; GVHD: graft-versus-host disease; ext: extensive; GRFS: graft-versus-host free, <lb/>relapse-free survival. <lb/>Table 4. Impact of donor type for outcomes censored at 2 years <lb/>in the matched cohort. <lb/>Outcome <lb/>HR (95% CI) <lb/>P <lb/>OS <lb/>1.39 (0.84-2.31) <lb/>0.19 <lb/>LFS <lb/>1.22 (0.76-1.95) <lb/>0.41 <lb/>RI <lb/>1.14 (0.62-2.08) <lb/>0.68 <lb/>NRM <lb/>1.39 (0.66-2.93) <lb/>0.39 <lb/>aGVHD 2-4 <lb/>1.26 (0.84-1.89) <lb/>0.27 <lb/>aGVHD 3-4 <lb/>2.33 (1.18-4.58) <lb/>0.01 <lb/>cGVHD <lb/>1.81 (0.75-4.37) <lb/>0.19 <lb/>Ext cGVHD <lb/>1.01 (0.25-4.03) <lb/>0.99 <lb/>GRFS <lb/>1.38 (0.95-2.02) <lb/>0.09 <lb/>HR: hazard ratio; CI: confidence interval; OS: overall survival; LFS: <lb/>leukemia-free survival; RI: relapse incidence; NRM: non-relapse mor-<lb/>tality; a: acute, c: chronic; GVHD: graft-versus-host disease; ext: ex-<lb/>tensive; GRFS: graft-versus-host free, relapse-free survival. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 109 July 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2128 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -MUD versus haplo PT-CY stem cell transplantation in children with AML <lb/>A. Ruggeri et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>group in the adult setting. 8,34 This platform is now the most <lb/>widely adopted strategy because it is cost-effective and <lb/>easily replicated. In recent years, emerging evidence also <lb/>supports the use of this platform in the pediatric popula-<lb/>tion with hematological malignancies. 19,35 <lb/>Saglio et al. 15 retrospectively compared the outcome of 23 <lb/>pediatric patients undergoing haplo-HCT with PT-CY for <lb/>acute leukemia with patients undergoing HCT from MUD <lb/>(N=41) and HLA-mismatched unrelated donor (MMUD) (N=26) <lb/>from a single institution. Five-year OS, NRM and RI were <lb/>not different for the three groups, confirming that haplo <lb/>PT-CY is a suitable clinical option for pediatric patients. <lb/>More recently, Srinivasan et al. 16 compared outcomes of <lb/>haplo-HCT PT-CY with peripheral blood (N=26) to matched <lb/>sibling donor (MSD) (N=31) and MUD HCT (N=47), both with <lb/>BM as stem cell source. Results showed that haplo-HCT <lb/>PT-CY with peripheral blood had comparable outcomes to <lb/>BM MSD and MUD HCT. Hong et al. 17 compared the outcomes <lb/>of children and adolescents with high-risk acute leuke-<lb/>mia who underwent haplo-HCT PT-CY (N=35) or MUD HCT <lb/>(N=45) after a busulfan-based myeloablative conditioning. <lb/>No differences were observed in the main outcomes. In a <lb/>subgroup analysis of patients with AML (haplo, N=16; MUD, <lb/>N=16), the 3-year GRFS, LFS, and OS rates in haplo-HCT <lb/>and MUD groups were 80.8% versus 61.9%, 87.1% versus <lb/>73.9%, and 93.8% versus 85.6%, respectively. <lb/>Here, we report the largest series of children with AML <lb/>treated with haplo PT-CY reported to the EBMT registry. Our <lb/>results are in line with the previous single center reports <lb/>and confirmed the overall feasibility of the PT-CY approach <lb/>Figure 1. Two-years survival outcomes after matched unrelated donor and haploidential hematopoietic cell transplantation after <lb/>matched pair analysis. Two-year leukemia-free survival (LFS), overall survival (OS), relapse incidence (RI) and non-relapse mortal-<lb/>ity (NRM) after matched unrelated donor (MUD) and haploidential hematopoietic cell transplantation in children with acute myleoid <lb/>leukemia after matched pair analysis. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 109 July 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2129 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -MUD versus haplo PT-CY stem cell transplantation in children with AML <lb/>A. Ruggeri et al. <lb/></note>

        <body>in pediatric AML. Importantly, in our cohort haplo HCT was <lb/>associated with higher incidence of grade 3-4 aGVHD and <lb/>this could be related to the graft source itself, namely the <lb/>content of CD3 + cells in the poeripheral blood stem cells <lb/>as well to the differences in the overall GVHD prophylax-<lb/>is in the two group. Importantly MUD recipients received <lb/>ATG which is a key factor associated with reduced risk of <lb/>GVHD. Whenever the combination of ATG and PTCY could <lb/>be considered in the pediatric setting deserves further <lb/>investigation. Overall, no differences in pivotal outcome <lb/>parameters were found between haplo PT-CY and MUD. The <lb/>results were consistent across the different disease sta-<lb/>tus when we checked for interaction between the disease <lb/>status and the donor type. We are aware of the limitations <lb/>of this study, namely the retrospective nature, the short <lb/>follow-up, due to the recent use of PT-CY in this setting and <lb/>the limited data on infection and immune reconstitution <lb/>due to the registry based analysis. However, we believe <lb/>that our results are important and highlight the feasibility <lb/>of this approach also in children. How the PTCY approach <lb/>could be adopted also in the unrelated donor setting in the <lb/>pediatric HCT deserves further investigation. <lb/>Eligibility criteria for HCT for each cooperative group are be-<lb/>yond the purpose of this multinational retrospective study. <lb/>Nevertheless, eligibility for haplo-HCT may be either the <lb/>same as for MUD or more restricted to higher risk patients <lb/>only. Therefore, in case any unknown prognostic feature <lb/>could not be adjusted within the matched pair analysis, <lb/>the worst risk distribution would affect the outcome of the <lb/>haplo PT-CY more than the MUD cohort. In the pair match <lb/>analysis, the year of transplant was not considered as ex-<lb/>act matching but using a propensity score. This resulted <lb/>in a median year of transplant of 2017 and 2018 for MUD <lb/>and haplo respectively. Consequently, the median follow-up <lb/>was different in the two groups. In order to solve this issue <lb/>and make the groups more comparable, we censored the <lb/>outcomes at 2 years preventing us to provide results at a <lb/>longer period to avoid imbalance between the groups. <lb/>Such a haplo platform may enlarge access to HCT to virtually <lb/>all eligible pediatric patients with AML. Furthermore, the <lb/>prompt availability and the flexibility of a family member <lb/>may be crucial in the challenging HCT scheduling of rapidly <lb/>evolving pediatric malignancies, such as high-risk AML. Albeit <lb/>MUD HCT remains the standard of care, our study confirmed <lb/>in a large international analysis the comparable results of <lb/>haplo-HCT with PT-CY and MD HCT, so that pediatric patients <lb/>with AML who either lack a MD or cannot afford a MUD HCT, <lb/>can be safely transplanted without delay. <lb/></body>

        <div type="conflict">Disclosures <lb/>No conflicts of interest to disclose. <lb/></div>

        <div type="contribution">Contributions <lb/>AR and SC designed the study. NS and AR wrote the man-<lb/>uscript. JEG performed the statistical analysis. KK, MA, LZ, <lb/>KC, ES, PS, CB, AB, YB, JP, FG, MI, JG, CP, BV, AB, AP, MF, IG, <lb/>IB, OA, AD, and VR provided cases for the study. All authors <lb/>edited and approved the manuscript. <lb/></div>

        <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We thank the clinical staff and investigators of the EBMT <lb/>centers involved in this research and especially thank the <lb/>patients who participated in the study. <lb/></div>

        <div type="availability">Data-sharing statement <lb/>Data cannot be shared unless a specific request is sent to <lb/>the EBMT. <lb/></div>

        <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Döhner H, Estey E, Grimwade D, et al. Diagnosis and <lb/>management of AML in adults: 2017 ELN recommendations <lb/>from an international expert panel. Blood. 2017;129(4):424-447. <lb/>2. Segerink WH, de Haas V, Kaspers GJL. Measurable residual <lb/>disease in pediatric acute myeloid leukemia: a systematic <lb/>review. Expert Rev Anticancer Ther. 2021;21(4):451-459. <lb/>3. Egan G, Chopra Y, Mourad S, Chiang KY, Hitzler J. Treatment of <lb/>acute myeloid leukemia in children: a practical perspective. <lb/>Pediatr Blood Cancer. 2021;68(7):e28979. <lb/>4. Reinhardt D, Antoniou E, Waack K. Pediatric acute myeloid <lb/>leukemia -past, present, and future. J Clin Med. 2022;1(3):504. <lb/>5. Rubnitz JE, Kaspers GJL. How I treat pediatric acute myeloid <lb/>leukemia. Blood.2021;138(12):1009-1018. <lb/>6. Horan JT, Alonzo TA, Lyman GH, et al. Impact of disease risk on <lb/>efficacy of matched related bone marrow transplantation for <lb/>pediatric acute myeloid leukemia: the Children&apos;s Oncology <lb/>Group. J Clin Oncol. 2008;26(35):5797-5801. <lb/>7. Gragert L, Eapen M, Williams E, et al. HLA match likelihoods for <lb/>hematopoietic stem-cell grafts in the U.S. Registry. N Engl J <lb/>Med. 2014;371(4):339-348. <lb/>8. Luznik L, O&apos;Donnell PV, Symons HJ, et al. HLA-haploidentical <lb/>bone marrow transplantation for hematologic malignancies <lb/>using nonmyeloablative conditioning and high-iose, <lb/>posttransplantation cyclophosphamide. Biol Blood Marrow <lb/>Transplant. 2008;14(6):641-650. <lb/>9. Di Bartolomeo P, Santarone S, De Angelis G, et al. <lb/>Haploidentical, unmanipulated, G-CSF-primed bone marrow <lb/>transplantation for patients with high-risk hematologic <lb/>malignancies. Blood. 2013;121(5):849-857. <lb/>10. Locatelli F, Merli P, Pagliara D, et al. Outcome of children with <lb/>acute leukemia given HLA-haploidentical HSCT after ab T-cell <lb/>and B-cell depletion. Blood. 2017;130(5):677-685. <lb/>11. Massei MS, Capolsini I, Perruccio K, et al. HLA-haploidentical <lb/>transplantation with regulatory and conventional T-cells <lb/>adoptive immunotherapy in pediatric patients with high-risk <lb/>acute leukemia. Transplant Cell Ther. 2021;58(5):526-533. <lb/>12. Bertaina A, Zecca M, Buldini B, et al. Unrelated donor vs HLA-<lb/>haploidentical a/b T-cell-and B-cell-depleted HSCT in children <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Haematologica | 109 July 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2130 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">ARTICLE -MUD versus haplo PT-CY stem cell transplantation in children with AML <lb/>A. Ruggeri et al. <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>with acute leukemia. Blood. 2018;132(24):2594-2607. <lb/>13. Symons HJ, Zahurak M, Cao Y, et al. Myeloablative <lb/>haploidentical BMT with posttransplant cyclophosphamide for <lb/>hematologic malignancies in children and adults. Blood Adv. <lb/>2020;4(16):3913-3925. <lb/>14. Bolaños-Meade J, Hamadani M, Wu J, et al. Post-<lb/>transplantation cyclophosphamide-based graft-versus-host <lb/>disease prophylaxis. N Engl J Med. 2023;388(25):2338-2348. <lb/>15. Saglio F, Berger M, Spadea M, et al. Haploidentical HSCT with <lb/>post transplantation cyclophosphamide versus unrelated donor <lb/>HSCT in pediatric patients affected by acute leukemia. Bone <lb/>Marrow Transplant. 2021;56(3):586-595. <lb/>16. Srinivasan A, Raffa E, Wall DA, et al. Outcome of haploidentical <lb/>peripheral blood allografts using post-transplantation <lb/>cyclophosphamide compared to matched sibling and unrelated <lb/>donor bone marrow allografts in pediatric patients with <lb/>hematologic malignancies: a single-center analysis. Transplant <lb/>Cell Ther. 2022;28(3):158.e1-158.e9. <lb/>17. Hong KT, Park HJ, Kim BK, An HY, Choi JY, Kang HJ. Post-<lb/>transplantation cyclophosphamide-based haploidentical versus <lb/>matched unrelated donor peripheral blood hematopoietic stem <lb/>cell transplantation using myeloablative targeted busulfan-<lb/>based conditioning for pediatric acute leukemia. Transplant Cell <lb/>Ther. 2022;28(4):195.e1-195.e7. <lb/>18. Berger M, Lanino E, Cesaro S, et al. Feasibility and outcome of <lb/>haploidentical hematopoietic stem cell transplantation with <lb/>post-transplant high-dose cyclophosphamide for children and <lb/>adolescents with hematologic malignancies: an AIEOP-GITMO <lb/>retrospective multicenter study. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant. <lb/>2016;22(5):902-909. <lb/>19. Ruggeri A, Galimard JE, Paina O, et al. Outcomes of <lb/>unmanipulated haploidentical transplantation using post-<lb/>transplant cyclophosphamide (PT-Cy) in pediatric patients with <lb/>acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Transplant Cell Ther. <lb/>2021;27(5):424.e1-424.e9. <lb/>20. Ruggeri A, Labopin M, Ciceri F, Mohty M, Nagler A. Definition of <lb/>GvHD-free, relapse-free survival for registry-based studies: an <lb/>ALWP-EBMT analysis on patients with AML in remission. Bone <lb/>Marrow Transplant. 2016;51(4):610-611. <lb/>21. Martino R, Romero P, Subirá M, et al. Comparison of the classic <lb/>Glucksberg criteria and the IBMTR Severity Index for grading <lb/>acute graft-versus-host disease following HLA-identical sibling <lb/>stem cell transplantation. Bone Marrow Transplant. <lb/>1999;24(3):283-287. <lb/>22. Jagasia MH, Greinix HT, Arora M, et al. National Institutes of <lb/>Health consensus development project on criteria for clinical <lb/>trials in chronic graft-versus-host disease: I. The 2014 Diagnosis <lb/>and Staging Working Group Report. Biol Blood Marrow <lb/>Transplant. 2015;21(3):389-401. <lb/>23. Willemze AJ, Geskus RB, Noordijk EM, Kal HB, Egeler RM, <lb/>Vossen JM. HLA-identical haematopoietic stem cell <lb/>transplantation for acute leukaemia in children: less relapse <lb/>with higher biologically effective dose of TBI. Bone Marrow <lb/>Transplant. 2007;40(4):319-327. <lb/>24. Peters C, Matthes-Martin S, Poetschger U, et al. Stem-cell <lb/>transplantation in children with acute lymphoblastic leukemia: <lb/>a prospective international multicenter trial comparing sibling <lb/>donors with matched unrelated donors-The ALL-SCT-BFM-2003 <lb/>trial. J Clin Oncol. 2015;33(11):1265-1274. <lb/>25. Saarinen-Pihkala UM, Gustafsson G, Ringdén O, et al. No <lb/>disadvantage in outcome of using matched unrelated donors as <lb/>compared with matched sibling donors for bone marrow <lb/>transplantation in children with acute lymphoblastic leukemia <lb/>in second remission. J Clin Oncol. 2001;19(14):3406-3414. <lb/>26. Gu Z, Wang L, Yuan L, et al. Similar outcomes after <lb/>haploidentical transplantation with post-transplant <lb/>cyclophosphamide versus HLA-matched transplantation: a <lb/>meta-analysis of case-control studies. Oncotarget. <lb/>2017;29;8(38):63574-63586. <lb/>27. Shaw PJ, Kan F, Ahn KW, et al. Outcomes of pediatric bone <lb/>marrow transplantation for leukemia and myelodysplasia using <lb/>matched sibling, mismatched related, or matched unrelated <lb/>donors. Blood. 2010;116(20):4360-4367. <lb/>28. Leung W, Campana D, Yang J, et al. High success rate of <lb/>hematopoietic cell transplantation regardless of donor source in <lb/>children with very high-risk leukemia. Blood. 2011;118(2):223-230. <lb/>29. Passweg JR, Baldomero H, Chabannon C, et al. Hematopoietic <lb/>cell transplantation and cellular therapy survey of the EBMT: <lb/>monitoring of activities and trends over 30 years. Bone Marrow <lb/>Transplant. 2021;56(7):1651-1664. <lb/>30. Shah RM. Contemporary haploidentical stem cell transplant <lb/>strategies in children with hematological malignancies. Bone <lb/>Marrow Transplant. 2021;56(7):1518-1534. <lb/>31. Algeri M, Merli P, Locatelli F, Pagliara D. The role of allogeneic <lb/>hematopoietic stem cell transplantation in pediatric leukemia. <lb/>J Clin Med. 2021;10(17):3790. <lb/>32. Bertaina A, Merli P, Rutella S, et al. HLA-haploidentical stem cell <lb/>transplantation after removal of αb+ T and B cells in children <lb/>with nonmalignant disorders. Blood. 2014;124(5):822-826. <lb/>33. Merli P, Algeri M, Li Pira G, et al. Alpha/beta T-cell and B-cell <lb/>depletion HLA-haploidentical hematopoietic stem cell <lb/>transplantation is an effective treatment for children/young <lb/>adults with acute leukemia. Blood. 2018;132(Suppl 1):2169. <lb/>34. Bashey A, Zhang MJ, McCurdy SR, et al. Mobilized peripheral <lb/>blood stem cells versus unstimulated bone marrow as a graft <lb/>source for T-cell-replete haploidentical donor transplantation <lb/>using post-transplant cyclophosphamide. J Clin Oncol. <lb/>2017;35(26):3002-3009. <lb/>35. Jaiswal SR, Chakrabarti A, Chatterjee S, et al. Haploidentical <lb/>peripheral blood stem cell transplantation with post-<lb/>transplantation cyclophosphamide in children with advanced <lb/>acute leukemia with fludarabine-, busulfan-, and melphalan-<lb/>based conditioning. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant. <lb/>2016;22(3):499-504. <lb/>36. Pérez-Martínez A, Ferreras C, Pascual A, et al. Haploidentical <lb/>transplantation in high-risk pediatric leukemia: a retrospective <lb/>comparative analysis on behalf of the Spanish working Group <lb/>for bone marrow transplantation in children (GETMON) and the <lb/>Spanish Grupo for Hematopoietic Transplantation (GETH). Am J <lb/>Hematol. 2020;95(1):28-37. <lb/>37. Shelikhova L, Ilushina M, Shekhovtsova Z, et al. αb T cell-<lb/>depleted haploidentical hematopoietic stem cell <lb/>transplantation without antithymocyte globulin in children with <lb/>chemorefractory acute myelogenous leukemia. Biol. Blood <lb/>Marrow Transplant. 2019;25(5):e179-e182. </listBibl>


	</text>

</TEI>