<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Impact of Asian aerosols on the summer monsoon strongly modulated by regional precipitation biases</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Zhen</forename>
          <surname>Liu</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Massimo A.</forename>
          <surname>Bollasina</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Laura J.</forename>
          <surname>Wilcox</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-05T14:27:11.744Z">11/5/2025 2:27:11 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Copernicus GmbH</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.5194/acp-24-7227-2024</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Zhen Liu, Massimo A. Bollasina, Laura J. Wilcox. (2024). Impact of Asian aerosols on the summer monsoon strongly modulated by regional precipitation biases. Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics, 24(12), 7227-7252. DOI: 10.5194/acp-24-7227-2024</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-05T14:26:56.674769Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-05T14:26:56.674769Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2605-2624, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2605-2024 <lb/>© Author(s) 2024. This work is distributed under <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License. <lb/>The ABoVE L-band and P-band airborne synthetic <lb/>aperture radar surveys <lb/>Charles E. Miller 1 , Peter C. Griffith 2 , Elizabeth Hoy 3 , Naiara S. Pinto 1 , Yunling Lou 1 , Scott Hensley 1 , <lb/>Bruce D. Chapman 1 , Jennifer Baltzer 4 , Kazem Bakian-Dogaheh 5 , W. Robert Bolton 6,20 , <lb/>Laura Bourgeau-Chavez 7 , Richard H. Chen 1 , Byung-Hun Choe 8 , Leah K. Clayton 9 , <lb/>Thomas A. Douglas 10 , Nancy French 7 , Jean E. Holloway 11 , Gang Hong 8 , Lingcao Huang 12 , <lb/>Go Iwahana 6 , Liza Jenkins 7 , John S. Kimball 13 , Tatiana Loboda 14 , Michelle Mack 15 , Philip Marsh 16 , <lb/>Roger J. Michaelides 17 , Mahta Moghaddam 5 , Andrew Parsekian 18 , Kevin Schaefer 12 , <lb/>Paul R. Siqueira 19 , Debjani Singh 20 , Alireza Tabatabaeenejad 5 , Merritt Turetsky 21 , Ridha Touzi 8 , <lb/>Elizabeth Wig 22 , Cathy J. Wilson 23 , Paul Wilson 8 , Stan D. Wullschleger 20 , Yonghong Yi 1,24 , <lb/>Howard A. Zebker 22 , Yu Zhang 8 , Yuhuan Zhao 5 , and Scott J. Goetz 25 <lb/>1 Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, CA 91109, USA <lb/>2 NASA Goddard Space Flight Center/SSAI, Greenbelt, MD, USA <lb/>3 NASA Goddard Space Flight Center/GST, Inc., Greenbelt, MD, USA <lb/>4 Department of Biology, Wilfrid Laurier University, Waterloo, Ontario, Canada <lb/>5 Department of Electrical Engineering, University of Southern California, Los Angeles, CA, USA <lb/>6 International Arctic Research Center, University of Alaska Fairbanks, Fairbanks, AK 99775-7340, USA <lb/>7 Michigan Tech Research Institute, Michigan Technological University, Ann Arbor, MI 48105, USA <lb/>8 Canada Centre for Remote Sensing, Ottawa, Ontario K1A 0E4, Canada <lb/>9 Department of Earth &amp; Planetary Sciences, Yale University, New Haven, CT, USA <lb/>10 U.S. Army Cold Regions Research and Engineering Laboratory, Fort Wainwright, AK 99709, USA <lb/>11 Department of Geography, University of Ottawa, Ottawa, Ontario K1N 6N5, Canada <lb/>12 National Snow and Ice Data Center (NSIDC), University of Colorado Boulder, Boulder, <lb/>CO 80309-0449, USA <lb/>13 NTSG, WA Franke College of Forestry &amp; Conservation, The University of Montana, <lb/>Missoula, MT, USA <lb/>14 Department of Geographical Sciences, University of Maryland, College Park, MD 20742, USA <lb/>15 Center for Ecosystem Science and Society and Department of Biological Sciences, Northern Arizona <lb/>University, Flagstaff, AZ 86011, USA <lb/>16 Department of Geography and Cold Regions Research Centre, Wilfrid Laurier University, <lb/>Waterloo, Ontario, Canada <lb/>17 Department of Geophysics, Colorado School of Mines, Golden, CO, USA <lb/>18 Department of Geology &amp; Geophysics, University of Wyoming, 1000 E University Ave., Laramie, WY, USA <lb/>19 Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, University of Massachusetts, <lb/>Amherst, MA 01003-9284, USA <lb/>20 Biological and Environmental Systems Science Directorate, Oak Ridge National Laboratory, <lb/>Oak Ridge, TN, USA <lb/>21 Ecology and Evolutionary Biology Department, University of Colorado Boulder, Boulder, CO, USA <lb/>22 Department of Geophysics, Stanford University, Stanford, CA, USA <lb/>23 Earth and Environmental Sciences Division, Los Alamos National Laboratory, Los Alamos, <lb/>NM, USA <lb/>24 Joint Institute for Regional Earth System Science &amp; Engineering, The University of California, <lb/>Los Angeles, CA 90095-7228, USA <lb/>Published by Copernicus Publications. <lb/>2606 <lb/>C. E. Miller et al.: The ABoVE L-band and P-band airborne SAR surveys <lb/>25 School of Informatics, Computing, and Cyber Systems, Northern Arizona University, <lb/>Flagstaff, AZ 86011, USA <lb/>Correspondence: Charles E. Miller (charles.e.miller@jpl.nasa.gov) <lb/>Received: 19 May 2021 -Discussion started: 15 September 2023 <lb/>Revised: 23 January 2024 -Accepted: 27 January 2024 -Published: 4 June 2024 <lb/>Abstract. Permafrost-affected ecosystems of the Arctic-boreal zone in northwestern North America are un-<lb/>dergoing profound transformation due to rapid climate change. NASA&apos;s Arctic Boreal Vulnerability Experi-<lb/>ment (ABoVE) is investigating characteristics that make these ecosystems vulnerable or resilient to this change. <lb/>ABoVE employs airborne synthetic aperture radar (SAR) as a powerful tool to characterize tundra, taiga, peat-<lb/>lands, and fens. Here, we present an annotated guide to the L-band and P-band airborne SAR data acquired during <lb/>the 2017, 2018, 2019, and 2022 ABoVE airborne campaigns. We summarize the ∼ 80 SAR flight lines and how <lb/>they fit into the ABoVE experimental design (Miller et al., 2023; https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/2150). <lb/>The Supplement provides hyperlinks to extensive maps, tables, and every flight plan as well as individual flight <lb/>lines. We illustrate the interdisciplinary nature of airborne SAR data with examples of preliminary results from <lb/>ABoVE studies including boreal forest canopy structure from TomoSAR data over Delta Junction, AK, and <lb/>the Boreal Ecosystem Research and Monitoring Sites (BERMS) area in northern Saskatchewan and active layer <lb/>thickness and soil moisture data product validation. This paper is presented as a guide to enable interested readers <lb/>to fully explore the ABoVE L-and P-band airborne SAR data (https://uavsar.jpl.nasa.gov/cgi-bin/data.pl). <lb/>Copyright statement. © California Institute of Technology. Gov-<lb/>ernment funding acknowledged. <lb/></front>

        <body>1 Introduction <lb/>The Arctic region contains a remarkable diversity of cold-<lb/>adapted biota, habitats, and permafrost-affected ecosystems <lb/>(McGuire et al., 2009; Vincent et al., 2011). As with other <lb/>components of the Arctic system, Arctic ecosystems are <lb/>strongly interdependent, and the rapid degradation of the <lb/>Arctic cryosphere is altering their physical, biogeochemi-<lb/>cal, and biological linkages in ways that may be irreversible <lb/>(Vincent et al., 2011; Hinzman et al., 2013). Understand-<lb/>ing characteristics that make Arctic ecosystems vulnerable <lb/>or resilient to this change is the overarching objective of <lb/>NASA&apos;s Arctic Boreal Vulnerability Experiment (ABoVE; <lb/>https://above.nasa.gov/, last access: 19 April 2024). Miller <lb/>et al. (2019) describe how airborne campaigns fit into the <lb/>broader ABoVE research strategy and how the foundational <lb/>synthetic aperture radar (SAR) measurements formed the <lb/>framework around which all other airborne data acquisitions <lb/>were planned. <lb/>ABoVE SAR flight lines (Fig. 1) were planned to lever-<lb/>age legacy L-and P-band SAR transects acquired during <lb/>the pre-ABoVE period; remotely sensed permafrost active <lb/>layer thickness time series derived from satellite interfero-<lb/>metric SAR observations (ReSALT) (Schaefer et al., 2015); <lb/>SAR data from PALSAR, PALSAR-2, RadarSat, RadarSat-<lb/>2, and Sentinel-1; historic or planned airborne lidar acquisi-<lb/>tions; and data from existing field sites (Hoy et al., 2018). <lb/>Legacy airborne SAR flight lines include the L-band grid ac-<lb/>quired over the Boreal Ecosystem Research and Monitoring <lb/>Sites (BERMS) area near Prince Albert, SK, during SMAP <lb/>CanEx 2010 (Magagi et al., 2013); the P-band lines over <lb/>the BERMS area acquired from 2012-2015 during the Air-<lb/>borne Microwave Observatory of Subcanopy and Subsurface <lb/>(AirMOSS) Earth Ventures Suborbital (EV-S1) investigation <lb/>(Allen et al., 2010; Moghaddam et al., 2016); and a collec-<lb/>tion of 10 L-and P-band flight lines acquired over the Se-<lb/>ward Peninsula, northwestern Interior, and North Slope of <lb/>Alaska during 2014 and 2015 (Chen et al., 2019a, b). The <lb/>BERMS area observations, in particular, link ABoVE to the <lb/>Boreal Ecosystem-Atmosphere Study (BOREAS) studies of <lb/>the 1990s (Sellers et al., 1995, 1997). <lb/>Hoy et al. (2018) compiled information on more than 6700 <lb/>field sites and previous remote sensing data sets to help <lb/>plan the SAR flight lines and the ABoVE airborne cam-<lb/>paigns (Miller et al., 2019). This compilation is intended to <lb/>help investigators understand flight line choices and iden-<lb/>tify ground locations used to anchor individual flight lines. <lb/>SAR data users may also search for the underlying data <lb/>available within each flight line. Key anchor points for the <lb/>SAR flight lines include active layer thickness measure-<lb/>ments from the Circumpolar Active Layer Monitoring net-<lb/>work (CALM); permafrost temperatures and annual thaw <lb/>depths from the Global Terrestrial Network for Permafrost <lb/>(GTN-P) database; soil moisture and permafrost state data <lb/>from the Department of Energy&apos;s Next Generation Ecologi-<lb/>cal Experiment-Arctic (NGEE-Arctic) field sites on the Se-<lb/>ward Peninsula and near Utqiaġvik (formerly Barrow) (AK); <lb/>extensive in situ terrestrial and aquatic ecosystem data as <lb/>well as airborne lidar and spectral imagery from NSF&apos;s Na-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2605-2624, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2605-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">C. E. Miller et al.: The ABoVE L-band and P-band airborne SAR surveys <lb/></note>

        <page>2607 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 1. Flight lines for the L-band and P-band PolInSAR measurements capture critical bioclimatic, permafrost, and geographic gradients <lb/>as well as key field sites and long-term measurement records across the 4 × 10 6 km 2 ABoVE domain. The flight lines are collected into 10 <lb/>composites which roughly correspond to the Alaskan (A1-A4) and Canadian (C1-C6) regions sampled on individual flight days. © Google <lb/>Maps. <lb/>tional Ecological Observatory Network (NEON) D18 tundra <lb/>field sites near Utqiaġvik (Barrow) (AK) and Toolik Lake <lb/>(AK) and from the D19 taiga field sites near Caribou/Poker <lb/>Creek (AK), Delta Junction (AK), and Healy (AK); detailed <lb/>ecological and physical climate time series from NSF&apos;s Long <lb/>Term Ecological Research (LTER) Arctic (Toolik Lake) and <lb/>Boreal Forest (Bonanza Creek) sites; long-term boreal forest <lb/>inventory data from the Canadian Forestry Service&apos;s (CFS) <lb/>Climate Impacts on Productivity and Health of Aspen (CI-<lb/>PHA) and High Elevation and Latitude Climate Change Im-<lb/>pacts and Adaptation (HELCIA) plots; and long-term per-<lb/>mafrost, hydrology, and ecology time series records from <lb/>the Canadian Changing Cold Regions Network (CCRN) sites <lb/>at Trail Valley Creek, NWT, Havikpak Creek, NWT, Scotty <lb/>Creek, NWT, Baker Creek, NWT, Wolf Creek Research <lb/>Basin, YT, and the BERMS site at White Gull Creek, SK. <lb/>Airborne SAR data enable numerous ecosystem and <lb/>ecosystem change research investigations (NRC, 2014). <lb/>ABoVE researchers are using the airborne L-and P-band <lb/>data to quantify permafrost active layer thickness and soil <lb/>moisture content (Bakian-Dogaheh et al., 2020a, b); com-<lb/>plement AirSWOT Ka-band acquisitions to determine wa-<lb/>ter surface elevations (WSEs) in Arctic lakes, wetlands, and <lb/>rivers (Pitcher et al., 2019a, b); investigate boreal forest and <lb/>tundra fire scars, especially in conjunction with fire dis-<lb/>turbance plots (Tank et al., 2018; Walker et al., 2018a, b, <lb/>2019a, b; French et al., 2020a, b; Holloway et al., 2020; Lo-<lb/>boda et al., 2022); map tree density and distribution across <lb/>the Tundra-Taiga ecotone; provide control point data for the <lb/>ArcticDEM (Porter et al., 2018; Meddens et al., 2018); in-<lb/>vestigate lidar-radar fusion remote sensing for boreal forest <lb/>characterization as a precursor to NISAR/IceSAT-2 inves-<lb/>tigations (Silva et al., 2021); quantify expansion and sedi-<lb/>ment mass flow from massive retrogressive thaw slumps -<lb/>so-called megaslumps -on the Peel Plateau along the Demp-<lb/>ster Hwy west of Fort McPherson, NT (Kokelj et al., 2013, <lb/>2015); classify Arctic wetlands and habitats (French, 2020); <lb/>and support algorithm development for NISAR (L-band) and <lb/>BIOMASS (P-band) estimates of boreal forest structure and <lb/>aboveground biomass (Quegan et al., 2019; Saatchi et al., <lb/>2019). Goetz et al. (2022) summarize how the ABoVE air-<lb/>borne SAR data are helping advance Arctic-boreal under-<lb/>standing and the remaining knowledge gaps still to be ad-<lb/>dressed. <lb/>This paper presents an annotated guide to enable inter-<lb/>ested readers to fully explore the ABoVE L-and P-band <lb/>SAR data acquired during the 2017, 2018, 2019, and 2022 <lb/>ABoVE airborne campaigns. Section 2 provides details on <lb/>the L-and P-band SAR instruments and the flight line cat-<lb/>alog. Section 3 summarizes the daily sorties from each air-<lb/>borne campaign. Section 4 briefly describes the tomographic <lb/>SAR (TomoSAR) experiments flown over Delta Junction, <lb/>AK, and the BERMS site near Prince Albert, SK. Section 5 <lb/>describes some of the ABoVE SAR data products and their <lb/>validation. Section 6 highlights the synergies between the L-<lb/>and P-band airborne SAR data and other airborne sensors. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2605-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2605-2624, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2608 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">C. E. Miller et al.: The ABoVE L-band and P-band airborne SAR surveys <lb/></note>

        <body>Section 7 summarizes access to the data products. Section 8 <lb/>discusses potential future acquisitions and outlooks for ex-<lb/>ploiting these data. Additionally, we include supplementary <lb/>information which describes the ∼ 80 ABoVE SAR flight <lb/>lines and how each line fits into the ABoVE experimental <lb/>design. The Supplement also provides extensive maps and <lb/>tables for every flight plan and individual flight lines as well <lb/>as a list of the acronyms and abbreviations and hyperlinked <lb/>versions of the tables for direct access to flight lines and flight <lb/>plans. <lb/>2 The L-band and P-band airborne SAR instruments <lb/>and data acquisition <lb/>Both the L-and P-band airborne SARs are sensitive to geo-<lb/>metrical and material properties of vegetation, soil surface, <lb/>and subsurface profiles (Saatchi and Moghaddam, 2000; <lb/>Tabatabaeenejad et al., 2011, 2015). The joint use of the <lb/>L-and P-band gives enhanced sensitivity to near-surface <lb/>(&lt; 5 cm, L-band) and root zone (10-40 cm, P-band) por-<lb/>tions of the subsurface profile compared to the use of ei-<lb/>ther wavelength alone (Du et al., 2015). Airborne acqui-<lb/>sitions with both SARs provide 6-10 m spatial resolution, <lb/>∼ 15 km swaths, and transect lengths of 100-200 km, mak-<lb/>ing them ideal for surveying aboveground biomass and veg-<lb/>etation canopy structure (Hensley et al., 2014, 2016) as well <lb/>as the tundra-taiga ecotone (Montesano et al., 2016). Special <lb/>TomoSAR data were acquired over the well-characterized <lb/>BERMS site in northern Saskatchewan and the NEON site <lb/>in Delta Junction, AK, to quantify the performance of both <lb/>SARs in reproducing the structure and biomass of boreal <lb/>forests. <lb/>2.1 The L-band SAR instrument <lb/>NASA&apos;s airborne L-band SAR (initially named the Unin-<lb/>habited Aerial Vehicle Synthetic Aperture Radar (UAVSAR) <lb/>system) is a compact pod-mounted polarimetric instrument <lb/>for interferometric repeat-track observations that was devel-<lb/>oped at the NASA Jet Propulsion Laboratory (JPL) and Dry-<lb/>den Flight Research Center (DFRC) in Edwards, CA. It op-<lb/>erates at a center frequency of 1.2575 GHz (wavelength = <lb/>23.8 cm) with 80 MHz bandwidth. It is deployed on a Gulf-<lb/>stream III aircraft and images the Earth surface from a nom-<lb/>inal 12.5 km altitude. The image data are collected off-nadir <lb/>in a ∼ 22 km wide swath with incidence angles ranging from <lb/>∼ 22-67°. The instrument spatial resolution is 0.8 m (along <lb/>flight-line) by 1.7 m (slant range, along line-of-sight (LOS) <lb/>from the antenna to the ground). Topographic information <lb/>is derived from phase measurements that, in turn, are ob-<lb/>tained from two or more passes over a given target region. <lb/>Its 1.26 GHz frequency results in radar images that are well-<lb/>correlated from pass to pass. Polarization agility facilitates <lb/>terrain and land-use classification. <lb/>All L-band SAR data are publicly available at https: <lb/>//uavsar.jpl.nasa.gov/ (last access: 19 April 2024) as in-<lb/>dividual interferometric SAR (InSAR) products or as a <lb/>single-look-complex (SLC) stack product of coregistered im-<lb/>ages for individual flight lines. Products are also available <lb/>from the UAVSAR data portal at the Alaska SAR Facil-<lb/>ity Distributed Active Archive Center (https://asf.alaska.edu/ <lb/>data-sets/sar-data-sets/uavsar/, last access: 19 April 2024). <lb/>The L-band SAR provides key pre-launch algorithm devel-<lb/>opment and validation data sets (Saatchi et al., 2019) for the <lb/>NASA-ISRO SAR (NISAR) mission (Rosen et al., 2017). <lb/>2.2 The P-band SAR instrument <lb/>The P-band SAR was developed circa 2012 for the Earth <lb/>Ventures Suborbital (EV-S1) Airborne Microwave Obser-<lb/>vatory of Subcanopy and Subsurface (AirMOSS) investi-<lb/>gation (Allen et al., 2010; Moghaddam et al., 2016). The <lb/>radar is based on JPL&apos;s L-band UAVSAR system. The P-<lb/>band SAR inherits UAVSAR&apos;s existing L-band radio fre-<lb/>quency and digital electronics subsystems. New up and down <lb/>converters convert the L-band signals to UHF frequencies <lb/>(280-440 MHz). The passive antenna is based on the legacy <lb/>GeoSAR design (Chapin et al., 2012). <lb/>The P-band SAR was flown more than 1200 h from 2012 <lb/>to 2015, covering regions of 2500 km 2 spread over nine ma-<lb/>jor biomes in North America during the AirMOSS EV-S1 <lb/>investigation (Tabatabaeenejad et al., 2020). Legacy acquisi-<lb/>tions in Alaska (Chen, 2019a, b) and over the BERMS site <lb/>in northern Saskatchewan (Chapin et al., 2012, 2018) pro-<lb/>vide an opportunity for extended time series analysis. All <lb/>P-band SAR data are publicly available at https://uavsar.jpl. <lb/>nasa.gov/ (last access: 19 April 2024). Additionally, ABoVE <lb/>P-band SAR data will provide valuable insights into the char-<lb/>acterization of boreal forest and tundra ecosystems by the <lb/>upcoming BIOMASS mission (Le Toan et al., 2011; Quegan <lb/>et al., 2019). <lb/>2.3 The Platform Precision Autopilot (PPA) system <lb/>To support centimeter-precision interferometric land surface <lb/>characterization, repeat pass measurements acquired by the <lb/>SARs need to be taken from flight paths that are nearly iden-<lb/>tical. Both the L-and P-band SARs utilize real-time GPS <lb/>that interfaces with the platform flight management system <lb/>(FMS) to confine the repeat flight path to within a 10 m tube <lb/>over a 200 km course in conditions of calm to light turbu-<lb/>lence. The FMS is also referred to as the Platform Precision <lb/>Autopilot (PPA). Additionally, the radar vector from the air-<lb/>craft to the ground target area must be similar from pass to <lb/>pass. This is accomplished with an actively scanned antenna <lb/>designed to support electronic steering of the antenna beam <lb/>with a minimum of 1°increments over a range not to exceed <lb/>±15°in the flight direction. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2605-2624, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2605-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">C. E. Miller et al.: The ABoVE L-band and P-band airborne SAR surveys <lb/></note>

        <page>2609 <lb/></page>

        <body>ABoVE SAR measurements were typically acquired with <lb/>platform root mean square deviations less than ±3 m. Any <lb/>platform deviations larger than ±10 m from the programmed <lb/>flight path resulted in the acquisition being terminated and <lb/>a real-time decision made to reacquire the line from the be-<lb/>ginning or to continue with the flight plan and proceed to <lb/>the next line. This decision balanced the science priority of <lb/>the flight line, fuel consumption and remaining endurance, <lb/>the number of flight lines yet to be acquired in the day&apos;s <lb/>flight plan, distance from our base of operations, and whether <lb/>there would be future opportunities to collect a given line by <lb/>adding it to an upcoming flight plan. The flight team was <lb/>extremely efficient in executing these decisions, resulting in <lb/>95 % flight line acquisition success across the 2017-2022 pe-<lb/>riod. <lb/>2.4 Airborne SAR flight line and flight plan designations <lb/>The JPL SAR team devised a convenient and powerful way <lb/>to identify airborne SAR data acquisitions for the Facility <lb/>and PI instruments under their charge. Each L-band or P-<lb/>band SAR flight line receives a unique five-digit identifier <lb/>consisting of the three-digit GPS compass heading followed <lb/>by a two-digit index. A six-character text string is also as-<lb/>sociated with each line for ease of identification. The text <lb/>string precedes the numerical ID and usually provides abbre-<lb/>viated geographic or infrastructure information that charac-<lb/>terizes the line. For example, L-band flight line Teller_04901 <lb/>identifies the flight line on the Seward Peninsula that over-<lb/>flies the NGEE-Arctic Teller watershed. The flight line iden-<lb/>tifier is a constant and, once assigned, is used whenever a <lb/>line is reflown. In some cases, there are overlapping or nearly <lb/>identical flight lines which differ slightly in their ID number. <lb/>L-band and P-band flight lines use the same flight line identi-<lb/>fication system, allowing rapid identification of overlapping <lb/>L-and P-band data acquisitions. <lb/>Flight plans are assembled from the composite flight lines <lb/>for a given sortie. Each flight plan also receives a unique <lb/>five-digit identifier based on the year flown (digits 1 and 2) <lb/>and the flight number for that year (digits 3-5). For exam-<lb/>ple, L-band flight plan 17093 was flown in 2017 and was the <lb/>93rd sortie flown that year. Note that there may be more than <lb/>one sortie flown on a given day, in which case each would <lb/>have a unique flight plan identifier even though they were <lb/>flown on the same calendar day and may include some or all <lb/>of the same flight lines. <lb/>In the Supplement we provide hyperlinks to the JPL <lb/>UAVSAR data portal (https://uavsar.jpl.nasa.gov/cgi-bin/ <lb/>data.pl, last access: 19 April 2024). This provides links to <lb/>the individual flight line data, maps, and related flight plans <lb/>that acquired data over one or more of the individual flight <lb/>lines. We hope this enables interested readers to explore the <lb/>ABoVE L-and P-band SAR data more fully. These data <lb/>and all other airborne data from the ABoVE campaigns may <lb/>be explored on NASA&apos;s EarthData ABoVE portal (https: <lb/>//search.earthdata.nasa.gov/portal/above/search, last access: <lb/>19 April 2024). Ground sites used to design the orientation <lb/>and locations of the flight lines are archived at the ORNL <lb/>DAAC (Hoy et al., 2018). <lb/>3 The ABoVE airborne SAR campaigns <lb/>The L-band (Fig. 2) and P-band (Fig. 3) SARs were con-<lb/>sidered foundational measurements in the ABoVE airborne <lb/>campaign strategy (Miller et al., 2019). The ∼ 80 flight lines <lb/>described in the Supplement formed the framework for the <lb/>remainder of the airborne remote sensing acquisitions. The <lb/>ABoVE SAR strategy was to execute same day acquisitions <lb/>of both L-and P-band flight lines (Fig. 1) for a given sortie <lb/>during 2017 to optimize dual-frequency retrievals; however, <lb/>technical issues forced us to fly the instruments sequentially. <lb/>The baseline L-band campaigns were flown in June (DOY <lb/>164-173) and September (DOY 251-263) 2017 to character-<lb/>ize the land surface during periods of minimum and maxi-<lb/>mum active layer thickness, respectively. Subsequent L-band <lb/>campaigns in 2018 (DOY 231-241), 2019 (DOY 247-260) <lb/>and 2022 (DOY 226-237) provide a time series synched to <lb/>maximum annual active layer thickness. P-band campaigns <lb/>were conducted in May-June (DOY 142-157) and August <lb/>(DOY 219-227) of 2017. There was a 2 d P-band mini-<lb/>campaign in October 2017 to extend the legacy time series <lb/>of early-cold-season acquisitions over the Seward Peninsula, <lb/>NW Alaska, and North Slope Alaska (DOY 280-283). <lb/>3.1 Alaskan flight lines <lb/>The Alaskan SAR flight lines are broken into four main re-<lb/>gional collections: (A1) North Slope Alaska, (A2) Seward <lb/>Peninsula and Northwest Alaska, (A3) eastern Interior, and <lb/>(A4) Southwest Alaska and the Yukon-Kuskokwim Delta <lb/>(Fig. 1). Individual flight lines were planned based on long-<lb/>term ground monitoring sites (Hoy et al., 2018), existing or <lb/>planned field research, recent disturbances, important geo-<lb/>graphic or ecological gradients, complementary remote sens-<lb/>ing data, and consultation with indigenous peoples and gov-<lb/>ernments (Miller et al., 2019). Legacy L-and P-band flight <lb/>lines from the AirMOSS EV-S1 investigation (Allen et al., <lb/>2010; Moghaddam et al., 2016) in the Seward Peninsula, NW <lb/>Alaska, and the North Slope were adapted for ABoVE use. <lb/>Acquisition of P-band flight lines in the central Interior was <lb/>not possible due to a military radar keep-out zone centered <lb/>near Clear, AK. The keep-out zone is shown in all P-band <lb/>flight plan maps (Ex. Fig. 4). <lb/>3.2 Canadian flight lines <lb/>The Canadian SAR flight lines are broken into six regional <lb/>collections: (C1) Lower Mackenzie Valley and Northern <lb/>Yukon Territory, (C2) Southern Yukon Territory, (C3) Up-<lb/>per Mackenzie Valley, (C4) Great Slave Lake Region, <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2605-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2605-2624, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2610 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">C. E. Miller et al.: The ABoVE L-band and P-band airborne SAR surveys <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 2. Sahtu students Mandy Bayha (front left) and Joanne Speakman (front center) pose with their mentor Cindy Gilday (front right) and <lb/>NASA flight crew in Yellowknife, NT, after completing a L-band SAR survey flight around the Great Slave Lake Region on 22 August 2018 <lb/>(flight plan 18048). This experience gave these Northerners a new appreciation for how NASA was helping understand, preserve, and protect <lb/>their lands. Photo credit: Stephen M. Fochuk, Government of Northwest Territories. <lb/>Figure 3. The P-band SAR team with the NASA JSC G-III (N992NA) on the tarmac in Fairbanks, AK, on 18 August 2017 after completing <lb/>a survey of the Upper Mackenzie Valley (flight plan 17083). Photo credit: Mahta Moghaddam. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2605-2624, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2605-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">C. E. Miller et al.: The ABoVE L-band and P-band airborne SAR surveys <lb/></note>

        <page>2611 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 4. The military radar at Clear, AK, creates a large P-band <lb/>operations keep-out zone in the central Interior (red areas). The <lb/>aircraft symbol marks our Fairbanks International Airport (PAFA) <lb/>base of operations. Data acquisitions (blue bars) are from flight plan <lb/>17054. © Google Maps. <lb/>(C5) Transboundary Watershed, and (C6) Southern Boreal <lb/>Forest/BERMS. Individual lines were planned based on <lb/>long-term ground monitoring sites (Hoy et al., 2018), exist-<lb/>ing or planned field research, recent disturbances, important <lb/>geographic or ecological gradients, complementary remote <lb/>sensing data, and consultation with local inhabitants and gov-<lb/>ernments (Miller et al., 2019). Legacy L-and P-band flight <lb/>lines in the BERMS area from the CANEX 2010 campaign <lb/>(Magagi et al., 2013) and the AirMOSS EV-S1 investigation <lb/>(Chapin et al., 2012, 2018) provide the potential to establish <lb/>longer time series. <lb/>Flight planning for the Canadian transects benefited <lb/>tremendously from consultations with our Canadian col-<lb/>leagues and interested parties in Yellowknife, NT, and White-<lb/>horse, YT, in 2015 and 2016. Extensive discussions with <lb/>the Government of the Northwest Territories (GNWT); the <lb/>Government of the Yukon Territory; First Nations represen-<lb/>tatives; and scientists from Polar Knowledge Canada (PO-<lb/>LAR), the NWT Center for Geomatics, and the Canadian <lb/>Forestry Service (CFS) Northern Forestry Centre (NoFC) <lb/>were critical to designing a strategy that captured many of <lb/>their observing priorities. Subsequent discussions in Yel-<lb/>lowknife during 2017 and 2018 enabled us to disseminate <lb/>preliminary results and coordinate the flights with same-day <lb/>field data acquisitions. <lb/>4 TomoSAR measurements of boreal forest <lb/>structure <lb/>SAR tomographic methods have proven extremely adept at <lb/>measuring vegetation vertical structure at a variety of wave-<lb/>lengths including L-and P-bands. The three-dimensional <lb/>vegetation structure and its changes resulting from either nat-<lb/>ural or anthropogenic causes are key ecosystem monitoring <lb/>parameters. ABoVE collected tomographic L-and P-band <lb/>SAR data over the boreal forest near Delta Junction, AK, <lb/>in September of 2017. UAVSAR (L-band) and the German <lb/>Space Agency&apos;s F-SAR (L-and S-bands) acquired coordi-<lb/>nated tomographic SAR data at the BERMS site near Saska-<lb/>toon, SK, in August 2018. Ground truth data sets and li-<lb/>dar data from the NASA Land, Vegetation, and Ice Sensor <lb/>(LVIS) system were also acquired at BERMS in 2017 (Blair <lb/>and Hofton, 2018a, b). We compared L-and P-band tomog-<lb/>raphy at Delta Junction and L-band and S-band tomography <lb/>from the two systems, to each other, and to the lidar data sets <lb/>at BERMS. Here we provide a preliminary analysis of the <lb/>data acquired at BERMS. <lb/>BERMS is a southern boreal forest site with gentle <lb/>topography dominated by jack pine and aspen stands. <lb/>There is active logging in the area, and the site contains <lb/>clear-cut areas and new growth stands in various matu-<lb/>rity states. The tomography data acquisition at BERMS <lb/>was planned jointly in cooperation with the German Space <lb/>Agency (DLR), who flew the F-SAR radar and acquired <lb/>data at the L-band and S-band. The UAVSAR and F-<lb/>SAR flight lines were designed to overlap each other and <lb/>LVIS data acquired at the site in 2017. LVIS reacquired <lb/>BERMS area data again in 2019 with the LVIS-F and <lb/>LVIS-C instruments (https://lvis.gsfc.nasa.gov/Data/Maps/ <lb/>ABoVE2019Map.html, last access: 19 April 2024). Figure 5 <lb/>(left) shows swaths for the UAVSAR and F-SAR radars along <lb/>with the LVIS data. UAVSAR acquired L-band tomogra-<lb/>phy data on a racetrack pattern to get multiple incidence <lb/>angle data for most points in the swath. Because UAVSAR <lb/>and F-SAR fly at 12 500 and 4200 m a.g.l., respectively, it <lb/>is not possible to acquire data with the same incidence an-<lb/>gles across the swath. Thus, we configured the flight lines to <lb/>overlap so that the 40°incidence angle points would coin-<lb/>cide. Figure 5 (right) shows photos collected at 4 of our 17 <lb/>ground truth sites during the TomoSAR acquisitions. <lb/>LVIS full-waveform lidar provides surface elevations and <lb/>tree height estimates as well as lidar echo strength through-<lb/>out the canopy and thereby information on the canopy in-<lb/>ternal structure. From LVIS waveforms, many products are <lb/>possible, including surface elevation, tree height, moments <lb/>of the returned waveform distribution, and cumulative per-<lb/>centile elevations. We compared these waveforms to radar <lb/>tomographic profiles for the different radar wavelengths. <lb/>BERMS field measurements consist of soil moisture mea-<lb/>surements at the 17 sites using the average of 15 measure-<lb/>ments distributed over 60 m × 60 m plots on the day of the <lb/>UAVSAR radar observations. At BERMS the soil was very <lb/>dry, roughly 10 % volumetric soil moisture or less, during <lb/>the radar observations. During the summer of 2020, measure-<lb/>ments of diameter at breast height (DBH), used to estimate <lb/>biomass, for a subset of our selected sites were planned but <lb/>postponed due to COVID-19. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2605-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2605-2624, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2612 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">C. E. Miller et al.: The ABoVE L-band and P-band airborne SAR surveys <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 5. Left: experimental design for the BERMS area TomoSAR flights in August 2018. The large white and yellow boxes show the <lb/>∼ 18 km wide UAVSAR L-band swaths. The offset is due to the off-nadir viewing angle of the L-band SAR -it is pointed to the south when <lb/>flying the 270°swath and pointed north when flying the 90°swath. The small white box near the center of the image marks the ∼ 3 km wide <lb/>F-SAR swath. LVIS lidar data are the ∼ 1.5 km wide colored swaths across the image; the color scaling reflects the canopy height. Right: <lb/>photos from 4 of the 17 plots used for in situ ground truth measurement at BERMS. Vegetation at BERMS was mostly jack pine and aspen, <lb/>with many areas having dense understory vegetation. Most areas have substantial detritus and ground litter left over from previous logging <lb/>operations. © Google Earth. <lb/>Figure 6 compares UAVSAR L-band tomography with F-<lb/>SAR L-band and S-band tomography and LVIS lidar data <lb/>along a transect shown as a yellow line on the right in the fig-<lb/>ure. Tree height along the transect varied from 10-20 m. The <lb/>middle of Fig. 2 is the UAVSAR L-band transect. The top of <lb/>the figure shows the LVIS RH25 m, RH50, RH75, and RH95 <lb/>profiles overlaid on the UAVSAR tomogram, and below are <lb/>the radar and lidar vertical profiles. On the left of Fig. 2 are <lb/>the F-SAR L-band and S-band tomographic profiles along <lb/>with the LVIS RH100 data. The L-band radar profiles exhibit <lb/>power concentrated at the base of the canopy, whereas the <lb/>LVIS lidar data show more return from the middle portion <lb/>of the canopy. The S-band obtains greater returns in the up-<lb/>per canopy compared to the L-band and shows more uniform <lb/>scattering within the canopy. <lb/>5 ABoVE SAR data products <lb/>Here we highlight some data sets enabling or derived from <lb/>the ABoVE L-and P-band airborne SAR acquisitions. <lb/>They represent the current state of the art for the study <lb/>of permafrost-affected ecosystems using SAR. The ABoVE <lb/>science team continues to develop additional products, and <lb/>the insights from these studies will be published separately. <lb/>Links to the repositories for each of these data sets are pro-<lb/>vided below. <lb/>5.1 Active layer thickness (ALT) <lb/>The Permafrost Dynamics Observatory (PDO) data product <lb/>estimates seasonal subsidence, active layer thickness (ALT), <lb/>soil volumetric water content (VWC), and uncertainties at <lb/>30 m resolution for 66 flight lines across Alaska and North-<lb/>west Canada (Michaelides et al., 2021; Chen et al., 2021, <lb/>2023). The PDO retrieval uses L-band synthetic aperture <lb/>radar (SAR) data acquired by the Uninhabited Aerial Vehi-<lb/>cle Synthetic Aperture Radar (UAVSAR) instrument and P-<lb/>band data acquired by the Airborne Microwave Observatory <lb/>of Subcanopy and Subsurface (AirMOSS) instrument. The <lb/>PDO results for each flight line appear in separate NetCDF <lb/>files. Each line has a spatial resolution of 30 m on the ABoVE <lb/>common grid, with a width of 22 km based on the swath <lb/>width of the AirMOSS instrument. The flight lines as a <lb/>whole cover many ecosystem types and provide north-south <lb/>and east-west gradients in ALT and soil moisture across <lb/>the ABoVE domain (https://daac.ornl.gov/cgi-bin/dsviewer. <lb/>pl?ds_id=1796, last access: 19 April 2024). <lb/>Table 1 defines all variables in PDO data files. The first <lb/>eight variables represent the four primary outputs of the PDO <lb/>algorithm and associated uncertainties. Subsidence and ALT <lb/>represent one-time measurements for the 2017 thaw season <lb/>(Schaefer et al., 2021a, b). VWC, defined as the ratio of water <lb/>volume to total soil volume, represents soil moisture at max-<lb/>imum thaw for 2017. We assume a vertical profile of VWC <lb/>and estimate surface saturation fraction (Sw0) and water ta-<lb/>ble depth (wtd), the parameters that define the exact shape of <lb/>the assumed profile. The product includes a Python script that <lb/>will create a map of VWC averaged over any user specified <lb/>depth range. We included maps of VWC averaged over depth <lb/>ranges of handheld soil moisture probes commonly used in <lb/>ABoVE fieldwork. <lb/>5.2 Alaska active layer and soil moisture properties from <lb/>airborne P-band SAR <lb/>Chen et al. (2019a) synthesized the P-band polarimetric <lb/>synthetic aperture radar (PolSAR) data collected in Au-<lb/>gust and October of 2014 and 2015 during the AirMOSS <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2605-2624, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2605-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">C. E. Miller et al.: The ABoVE L-band and P-band airborne SAR surveys <lb/></note>

        <page>2613 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 6. On the left, the location of the transect is shown as a yellow line overlaid on UAVSAR imagery in grayscale and LVIS RH95 <lb/>data in color where UAVSAR L-band, DLR F-SAR L and S-band and LVIS lidar profiles are compared. The center figure shows UAVSAR <lb/>L-band tomographic profiles along the transect along with the corresponding LVIS lidar profiles. On the right are the corresponding F-SAR <lb/>L and S-band tomographic profiles. The L-band radar profiles exhibit power concentrated at the base of the canopy, whereas the LVIS lidar <lb/>data show more return from the middle portion of the canopy. The S-band obtains greater returns in the upper canopy compared to the L-band <lb/>and shows more uniform scattering within the canopy. <lb/>Table 1. Variables in the Permafrost Dynamics Observatory (PDO) data files. <lb/>Variable <lb/>Full name <lb/>Units <lb/>Description <lb/>alt <lb/>Active layer thickness <lb/>m <lb/>Maximum thaw depth at the end of summer <lb/>sub <lb/>Subsidence <lb/>m <lb/>Surface subsidence from start of thaw after snowmelt to maximum thaw <lb/>depth in August or September <lb/>Sw0 <lb/>Surface Saturation Fraction <lb/>m 3 m -3 The ratio of water volume to pore space volume at the surface or 0 m <lb/>depth <lb/>wtd <lb/>Water table depth <lb/>m <lb/>The depth from the surface to the level where the soil is 100 % saturated <lb/>alt_unc <lb/>Uncertainty ALT <lb/>m <lb/>Uncertainty of estimated ALT <lb/>sub_unc <lb/>Uncertainty subsidence <lb/>m <lb/>Uncertainty of estimated seasonal subsidence <lb/>Sw0_unc <lb/>Uncertainty surface saturation <lb/>fraction <lb/>m 3 m -3 Uncertainty of estimated surface water saturation fraction <lb/>wtd_unc <lb/>Uncertainty water table depth <lb/>m <lb/>Uncertainty of estimated water table depth <lb/>mv_6cm <lb/>VWC from 0 to 6 cm <lb/>m 3 m -3 The ratio of water volume to soil volume averaged over 0 to 6 cm depths <lb/>mv_12cm VWC from 0 to 12 cm <lb/>m 3 m -3 The ratio of water volume to soil volume averaged over 0 to 12 cm <lb/>depths <lb/>mv_20cm VWC from 0 to 20 cm <lb/>m 3 m -3 The ratio of water volume to soil volume averaged over 0 to 20 cm <lb/>depths <lb/>mv_alt <lb/>VWC from 0 to ALT <lb/>m 3 m -3 The ratio of water volume to soil volume averaged over the entire active <lb/>layer, from zero to ALT <lb/>EV-S1 investigation with the ABoVE P-band measure-<lb/>ments collected in August and October of 2017 to es-<lb/>timate soil geophysical properties over 12 study sites in <lb/>northern Alaska (see Fig. S2 in the Supplement). Soil <lb/>properties reported include the ALT, soil dielectric con-<lb/>stant, soil moisture profile, surface roughness, and their <lb/>respective uncertainty estimates at 30 m spatial resolu-<lb/>tion (https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1657, Chen et al., <lb/>2019b; https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1676, Schae-<lb/>fer et al., 2019; https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1903 <lb/>Schaefer et al., 2021a; https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/ <lb/>1796 Schaefer et al., 2021b). <lb/>Most of the study sites are located within the continuous <lb/>permafrost zone and where the aboveground vegetation con-<lb/>sisting mainly of dwarf shrub and tussock, sedge, or moss <lb/>tundra has a minimal impact on P-band radar backscatter. <lb/>These data were used as inputs to the L-band ReSALT data <lb/>set described in Sect. 5.1. <lb/>5.3 In situ soil moisture and thaw depth measurements <lb/>In situ measurements of soil moisture, thaw depth, and other <lb/>quantities are essential to calibrate and validate ABoVE SAR <lb/>retrievals. The ABoVE team established a set of standardized <lb/>measurement protocols for field plots to ensure uniform data <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2605-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2605-2624, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2614 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">C. E. Miller et al.: The ABoVE L-band and P-band airborne SAR surveys <lb/></note>

        <body>products and quality in measurements collected by different <lb/>groups across the ABoVE domain and across multiple years. <lb/>Numerous teams collected in situ data during the initial 2017 <lb/>airborne campaign, with more targeted field acquisitions con-<lb/>ducted in 2018 and 2019 (Bourgeau-Chavez et al., 2019a, b; <lb/>Bakian-Dogaheh et al., 2020; Clayton et al., 2021; Loboda <lb/>et al., 2021). <lb/>Bourgeau-Chavez et al. (2019a, b) collected soil moisture <lb/>at 6, 12, 20, and 50 cm depths; ALT; soil profiles; and bio-<lb/>physical measurements of aboveground canopy and ground <lb/>layers in the Great Slave Lake Region (C4). These data <lb/>provide vegetation community characteristics and biophys-<lb/>ical data collected in 2018 from areas that were burned by <lb/>wildfire in 2014 and 2015 and from nine unburned vali-<lb/>dation sites. Vegetation data include vegetation inventories, <lb/>ground cover, regrowth, tree diameter and height, and woody <lb/>seedling/sprouting data at burned sites and similar vegetation <lb/>community characterization at unburned validation sites. Ad-<lb/>ditional measurements included soil moisture, collected for <lb/>validation of the UAVSAR airborne collection, and depth to <lb/>frozen ground at the nine unburned sites. This 2018 fieldwork <lb/>completes 4 years of field sampling at the wildfire areas. <lb/>The measurements by Bakian-Dogaheh et al. (2020a, b) <lb/>included soil dielectric properties, temperature, and mois-<lb/>ture profiles; active layer thickness (ALT); and measure-<lb/>ments of soil organic matter, bulk density, porosity, tex-<lb/>ture, and coarse root biomass from the surface to permafrost <lb/>table in soil pits at selected sites along the Dalton High-<lb/>way in Northern Alaska (A1). Their investigation sites in-<lb/>cluded Franklin Bluffs, Sagwon, Happy Valley, Ice Cut, <lb/>and Imnavait Creek. Measurements collected at Franklin <lb/>Bluffs were concurrent with an August 2018 ABoVE L-band <lb/>flight (https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1759, Bakian-<lb/>Dogaheh, 2020a). <lb/>Loboda et al. (2022) collected field measurements from <lb/>unburned sites and single and repeated burns in the Noatak <lb/>River valley and the Seward Peninsula regions of the <lb/>Alaska tundra in July-August in the years 2016-2018. The <lb/>data include ocular assessment of vegetation cover, soil <lb/>moisture at 6 and 12 cm, soil temperature at 10 cm, or-<lb/>ganic soil thickness, thaw depth, and weather measurements <lb/>(https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1919, Loboda et al., <lb/>2022). <lb/>The strong partnership between the ABoVE and NGEE-<lb/>Arctic projects also resulted in coordinated same-day ac-<lb/>quisition of airborne L-and P-band SAR data with in <lb/>situ soil moisture and thaw depth measurements over the <lb/>NGEE-Arctic study site at Barrow (Utqiaġvik), AK, and <lb/>the Seward Peninsula watersheds near Teller, AK; Coun-<lb/>cil, AK; and Kougarok, AK (Wilson et al., 2018, 2021, <lb/>2022; Dann et al., 2022; Lathrop et al., 2022). These <lb/>data provide critical calibration for the ABoVE SAR re-<lb/>trievals under continuous (Utqiaġvik) and discontinuous <lb/>(Seward Peninsula) permafrost conditions. Version 2 (V2) <lb/>of the in situ soil moisture and thaw depth measure-<lb/>ments covering years 2017-2019 was released in November <lb/>2020 (https://doi.org/10.5440/1423892, Wilson et al., 2018, <lb/>Ver. 2, https://www.osti.gov/biblio/1423892, Wilson et al., <lb/>2021; https://doi.org/10.5440/1856042, Wilson et al., 2022; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5440/1854940, Lathrop et al., 2022.). <lb/>6 Synergy with other airborne sensors <lb/>Miller et al. (2019) described the overall ABoVE airborne <lb/>campaign design strategy and anticipated airborne sensor <lb/>synergies. Here, we highlight three SARs -AirSWOT <lb/>(NASA), F-SAR (DLR), and LS-ASAR (ISRO) -and two <lb/>lidars -LVIS (NASA) and G-LiHT (NASA) -whose acqui-<lb/>sitions in the ABoVE domain were specifically designed to <lb/>complement and leverage the ABoVE L-and/or P-band SAR <lb/>acquisitions. Many other airborne sensor synergies are being <lb/>exploited by the ABoVE science team and are reported sep-<lb/>arately. <lb/>6.1 AirSWOT <lb/>NASA&apos;s AirSWOT airborne instrument suite has been de-<lb/>veloped to support the Surface Water and Ocean Topogra-<lb/>phy (SWOT) mission. The heart of AirSWOT is the Ka-band <lb/>SWOT Phenomenology Airborne Radar (KaSPAR). KaS-<lb/>PAR collects two swaths of across-track interferometry data: <lb/>one swath from nadir to 1 km and a second swath that ex-<lb/>tends from 1 to 5 km off-nadir. AirSWOT flight lines for <lb/>ABoVE were designed to center the AirSWOT swath on the <lb/>center of the P-band swath for maximum overlap. KaSPAR <lb/>is complemented by a high-resolution color-infrared (CIR) <lb/>digital camera system (Kyzivat et al., 2019, 2020) and a Pre-<lb/>cision Inertial Measurement Unit (IMU) for accurate attitude <lb/>and positioning information. In 2015 AirSWOT made pre-<lb/>ABoVE deployments to the Tanana River valley (Altenau <lb/>et al., 2017) and the Yukon Flats (Pitcher et al., 2019a, b) <lb/>in Region A3. <lb/>In 2017, AirSWOT deployed to acquire early-season <lb/>(May-June) and late-season (August) WSEs across the <lb/>ABoVE domain. Figure 7 shows the concentration of Air-<lb/>SWOT lines in wetlands complexes in the boreal forest, <lb/>across the Canadian Shield, along the Mackenzie River val-<lb/>ley, and into the Arctic tundra. All of these regions contain <lb/>overlapping L-and P-band acquisitions. Of special interest <lb/>are the lines in the Peace-Athabasca Delta (36000: PADelE <lb/>and 18035: PADelW) and the Yukon Flats (21508: YFlatW, <lb/>21609: YflatE, and 04707: FtYuko) and Trail Valley Creek, <lb/>NT (01703: TukHwy), where extensive on-water measure-<lb/>ments were made (Pitcher et al., 2020). Future joint analyses <lb/>of the Ka-and L-band data will highlight the advances possi-<lb/>ble in pan-Arctic hydrology from the upcoming NISAR and <lb/>SWOT missions. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2605-2624, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2605-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">C. E. Miller et al.: The ABoVE L-band and P-band airborne SAR surveys <lb/></note>

        <page>2615 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 7. AirSWOT flight lines acquired during the 2017 ABoVE airborne campaign sampled wetlands ranging from the Arctic Ocean coast <lb/>to the southern boreal forest. AirSWOT&apos;s Ka-band acquisitions were designed to overlap with the L-and P-band SAR near-field acquisitions <lb/>(See Fig. 1). © Google Earth. <lb/>6.2 F-SAR <lb/>The German Space Agency (DLR) developed the F-SAR in-<lb/>strument as an advanced airborne SAR test bed for technol-<lb/>ogy and remote sensing applications (Reigber et al., 2013). <lb/>F-SAR operates fully polarimetrically at X-, C-, S-, L-, and <lb/>P-bands and features single-pass polarimetric interferomet-<lb/>ric SAR (PolInSAR) capabilities in X-and S-bands (Reigber <lb/>et al., 2013). The radar covers an off-nadir angle range of 25 <lb/>to 60°and provides sub-meter-scale spatial resolution from <lb/>flight altitudes up to 6000 m a.g.l. <lb/>During August 2018 and April 2019, F-SAR was deployed <lb/>to northern Canada as part of DLR&apos;s permafrost airborne <lb/>SAR experiment (PermASAR). It was configured in X-, C-<lb/>, S-, and L-band mode and flew on board a Dornier DO <lb/>228-212 research aircraft. Measurements were acquired from <lb/>∼ 4500 m a.g.l. Coordinated TomoSAR transects were flown <lb/>over the BERMS site in the southern boreal forest on 18 Au-<lb/>gust (UAVSAR) and 23 August (F-SAR). Preliminary results <lb/>(Hensley et al., 2020) are summarized in Sect. 4. F-SAR also <lb/>acquired data over the Scotty Creek watershed, flux towers, <lb/>and areas of interest (AOI; Fig. 8); the Smith Creek flux <lb/>tower (Wrigley, NT); Baker Lake; Havipak Creek; Trail Val-<lb/>ley Creek; and Herschel Island, providing extensive opportu-<lb/>nities to cross-compare F-SAR and the ABoVE SAR acqui-<lb/>sitions. <lb/>6.3 LS-ASAR (ISRO) <lb/>The Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO) and NASA <lb/>are jointly developing the NASA-ISRO Synthetic Aperture <lb/>Radar (NISAR), which will map Earth&apos;s surface in L-band <lb/>and S-band every 12 d (Rosen et al., 2017). As a precursor <lb/>to the NISAR mission, ISRO has developed a L-and S-band <lb/>airborne SAR (LS-ASAR) to prepare the community to max-<lb/>imize the scientific and societal benefits of NISAR data (Ra-<lb/>manujam et al., 2016; Ramanujam and Mehra, 2019; Mehra <lb/>and Ramanujam, 2019). LS-ASAR operates in dual-, quad-, <lb/>and hybrid-polarization modes in both L-and S-bands. It <lb/>covers incidence angles from 24-77°, with swaths ranging <lb/>from 5.5 to 15 km. <lb/>In December 2019 LS-ASAR flew a series of Arctic sea <lb/>ice sorties from Fairbanks, AK. During this deployment, LS-<lb/>ASAR also acquired data over a number of the ABoVE <lb/>flight lines in Regions A1 (North Slope) and A3 (eastern <lb/>Interior) as well as over a number of glacier sites in the <lb/>Alaska Range. The acquisitions may be accessed via the <lb/>NASA and ISRO ASAR campaign page (https://uavsar.jpl. <lb/>nasa.gov/cgi-bin/deployment.pl?id=L20191101, last access: <lb/>19 April 2024) and are summarized in Fig. 9. These data <lb/>provide snow-on coverage that was a known deficiency of <lb/>previous ABoVE airborne campaigns. Additionally, the LS-<lb/>ASAR data extend coverage of these regions to S-band. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2605-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2605-2624, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2616 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">C. E. Miller et al.: The ABoVE L-band and P-band airborne SAR surveys <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 8. Overlap of the F-SAR acquisition at Scotty Creek, NT (yellow box), and the ABoVE L-band SAR line 16713 (red box and <lb/>polarized SAR false color). The ABoVE line also captures Scotty Creek AOI 2-6 (see Region C3 details, Sect. 5.3). The SAR data will <lb/>complement and benefit from the extensive ground-based data acquired in this area (Quinton et al., 2019). © Google Earth. <lb/>6.4 LVIS <lb/>The Land, Vegetation, and Ice Sensor (LVIS) is an airborne, <lb/>full-waveform scanning laser altimeter which produces to-<lb/>pographic maps with decimeter accuracy as well as veg-<lb/>etation vertical height and structure measurements (Blair <lb/>et al., 1999; Blair and Hofton, 1999). Flight lines for LVIS <lb/>(∼ 1.4 km swath) were slaved to the centerline of the P-<lb/>band swath during ABoVE, except where deviations were <lb/>required to capture critical ground sites. LVIS-C (classic con-<lb/>figuration) was deployed in 2017 aboard a B-200 aircraft and <lb/>achieved limited coverage (Fig. 10, left panel). During 2019, <lb/>the new LVIS Facility instrument (LVIS-F) and LVIS-C were <lb/>deployed on the NASA Gulfstream V and achieved coverage <lb/>of all legacy SAR lines (Fig. 10, right panel). <lb/>LVIS&apos; unique capability for measuring the sub-meter to-<lb/>pography beneath boreal forest canopies complemented the <lb/>TomoSAR acquisitions over Delta Junction, AK and the <lb/>BERMS site in northern Saskatchewan (Hensley et al., 2020; <lb/>Sect. 4). LVIS altimetry will also prove valuable in analy-<lb/>ses of such variables as permafrost degradation, active layer <lb/>thickness, and water surface elevation; however, LVIS&apos; sig-<lb/>nificantly narrower swath limits the spatial extent over which <lb/>these analyses may be performed. <lb/>In June-July 2017, NASA&apos;s LVIS Classic was deployed to <lb/>sites in northern Canada and Alaska as part of the ABoVE <lb/>2017 airborne campaign. During the 4-week deployment of <lb/>LVIS-F, a total of 15 flights were flown over diverse science <lb/>targets based out of multiple airports in Canada and Alaska. <lb/>Data are available in both Level 1B and Level 2 formats <lb/>(Table 2). The Level 1b data files contain the geolocated <lb/>laser waveform data for each laser footprint. The Level 2 <lb/>data files contain canopy top and ground elevations and <lb/>relative heights derived from the Level 1b data. ABoVE <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2605-2624, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2605-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">C. E. Miller et al.: The ABoVE L-band and P-band airborne SAR surveys <lb/></note>

        <page>2617 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 9. L-and S-band SAR lines acquired over Alaska during the December 2019 ASAR campaign. ASAR flight lines on the North Slope, <lb/>in the Yukon Flats, and in the western Interior exactly overlap ABoVE flight lines. These early-winter acquisitions provide a preliminary <lb/>look at cold-season SAR data that will be explored in greater detail in the planned ABoVE-SnowEx campaign. © Google Earth. <lb/>LVIS L1B Geolocated Return Energy Waveforms, Version 1 <lb/>(Blair and Hofton, 2018a) and L2 Geolocated Surface <lb/>Elevation Product, Version 1 (Blair and Hofton, 2018b), <lb/>may be obtained from the National Snow and Ice Data <lb/>Center via https://doi.org/10.5067/UMRAWS57QAFU <lb/>(Blair <lb/>and <lb/>Hofton <lb/>2018a) <lb/>and <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5067/IA5WAX7K3YGY <lb/>(Blair <lb/>and <lb/>Hofton, 2018b), respectively. <lb/>In July-August 2019, the NASA LVIS Facility and LVIS <lb/>Classic were deployed to sites in northern Canada and Alaska <lb/>as part of NASA&apos;s ABoVE 2019 airborne campaign. The in-<lb/>creased range and endurance of the Gulfstream V platform <lb/>Table 2. 2017 LVIS data products. <lb/>LVIS data products <lb/>Format <lb/>Flight trajectories <lb/>KMZ <lb/>Camera trajectories <lb/>KMZ <lb/>LVIS L1A camera imagery <lb/>JPG* <lb/>LVIS L1B geolocated waveforms <lb/>HDF, LDS 2.0.2 <lb/>LVIS L2 elevation and height products ASCII TXT, LDS 2.0.2a <lb/>enabled extensive sampling, including all L-band SAR lines, <lb/>multiple IceSAT-2 underflights, and numerous ABoVE field <lb/>sites. The available data products are given in Table 3. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2605-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2605-2624, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2618 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">C. E. Miller et al.: The ABoVE L-band and P-band airborne SAR surveys <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 10. Flight lines for the LVIS 2017 flights (left) and 2019 flights (right) were designed to overlap with the near-field portions of the <lb/>L-band and P-band SAR swaths to maximize opportunities for synergistic science. Aircraft and weather limited coverage during the 2017 <lb/>campaign, but complete coverage of the SAR flight lines, was achieved in 2019. These data will enable studies of SAR-lidar fusion over the <lb/>Arctic-boreal regions as a precursor to NISAR/IceSat-2 studies. © National Geographic Society. <lb/>Table 3. 2019 LVIS data products. <lb/>LVIS data products <lb/>Format <lb/>Flight trajectories <lb/>KMZ <lb/>Coverage maps <lb/>KMZ <lb/>LVIS classic L1B geolocated waveforms <lb/>HDF, LDS 2.0.3 <lb/>LVIS classic L2 elevation and height products ASCII TXT, LDS 2.0.3 <lb/>LVIS facility L1B geolocated waveforms <lb/>HDF, LDS 2.0.3 <lb/>LVIS facility L2 elevation and height products ASCII TXT, LDS 2.0.3 <lb/>6.5 G-LiHT <lb/>Zhao et al. (2022) used ABoVE airborne L-and P-band SAR <lb/>to map boreal forest species and canopy height in the Tanana <lb/>Valley State Forest (TVSF) near Delta Junction, AK. They <lb/>employed machine learning (random forests) to train sep-<lb/>arate regression models for canopy height mapping and a <lb/>classification model for forest species mapping. Data derived <lb/>from NASA&apos;s Goddard lidar, Hyperspectral, and Thermal <lb/>Imager (G-LiHT) system (Cook et al., 2013) were treated <lb/>as ground truth for the canopy height model (CHM). Forest <lb/>species prediction were referenced against (TVSF) timber in-<lb/>ventory and Forest Inventory and Analysis (FIA) data. The <lb/>experimental results show the proposed method yields a root <lb/>mean square error of 1.90 m for forest height estimation and <lb/>overall accuracy of 79.5 % for forest species classification. A <lb/>significant finding was that PolSAR decomposition parame-<lb/>ters, such as volume scattering and entropy, strongly influ-<lb/>enced the canopy height estimates. Interestingly, topography <lb/>played a crucial role in the species classification. <lb/>7 Data availability <lb/>Links to the ABoVE L-and P-band SAR products, support-<lb/>ing data, derived products, and ancillary measurements are <lb/>provided in the Supplement. Formal citations to all DOIs are <lb/>provided in the References. The L-and P-band SAR data <lb/>may be found at the JPL UAVSAR data portal, https://uavsar. <lb/>jpl.nasa.gov/cgi-bin/data.pl (last access: 19 April 2024). L-<lb/>band data may also be accessed via the UAVSAR portal at the <lb/>Alaska SAR Facility (ASF) DAAC (https://asf.alaska.edu/ <lb/>data-sets/sar-data-sets/uavsar/, last access: 19 April 2024), <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2605-2624, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2605-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">C. E. Miller et al.: The ABoVE L-band and P-band airborne SAR surveys <lb/></note>

        <page>2619 <lb/></page>

        <body>while AirMOSS P-band data may be accessed via the ORNL <lb/>DAAC, https://daac.ornl.gov/get_data/#projects (last access: <lb/>19 April 2024), select &quot;AirMOSS&quot;. <lb/>Miller et al. (2023; https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/ <lb/>2150) provide a detailed description of all 80 SAR flight <lb/>lines and how each fits into the ABoVE experimental design. <lb/>Extensive maps, tables, and hyperlinks give direct access to <lb/>every flight plan as well as individual flight lines. It is a guide <lb/>to enable interested readers to fully explore the ABoVE <lb/>L-and P-band SAR data. Key supporting data sets include <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1676 (Schaefer et al., <lb/>2021b), https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1657 (Chen et <lb/>al., 2019b), https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1759 <lb/>(Bakian-Dogaheh <lb/>et <lb/>al., <lb/>2020a), <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5440/1423892 (Wilson et al., 2018), <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5440/1854940 (Lathrop et al., 2022), <lb/>and https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1582 (Hoy et al., <lb/>2018). <lb/>8 Summary <lb/>The ABoVE project conducted airborne L-band PolInSAR <lb/>surveys in 2017, 2018, 2019 and 2022 across Alaska and <lb/>northwestern Canada. These were complemented by a P-<lb/>band PolInSAR survey in 2017 along the same transects. <lb/>This time series provides a powerful data set with which <lb/>to evaluate the state of permafrost, active layer thickness, <lb/>soil moisture, boreal forest structure, aboveground biomass, <lb/>and water surface elevation. Additional studies leverage <lb/>the PolInSAR data to address fire disturbance and recov-<lb/>ery, thermokarst feature development, and retrogressive per-<lb/>mafrost thaw megaslumps. Many of these analyses are in <lb/>progress and will be published separately. <lb/>Miller et al. (2023) provide extensive, fully hyperlinked <lb/>notes on the airborne SAR data. Researchers may discover <lb/>these data via daily sorties and/or individual flight lines. Al-<lb/>ternatively, they may be explored via the interactive map <lb/>at the JPL UAVSAR data portal (https://uavsar.jpl.nasa.gov/ <lb/>cgi-bin/data.pl, last access: 19 April 2024), which provides <lb/>links to the individual flight line data, maps, and related <lb/>flight plans that acquired data over one or more of the in-<lb/>dividual flight lines. We have also identified the ground-<lb/>based anchor points for each flight line to facilitate compar-<lb/>isons with those data. Calibration and validation data sets as <lb/>well as many derived products produced by the ABoVE Sci-<lb/>ence Team may be found at the Arctic Boreal Vulnerabil-<lb/>ity Experiment (ABoVE) landing page at the ORNL DAAC <lb/>(https://daac.ornl.gov/cgi-bin/dataset_lister.pl?p=34, last ac-<lb/>cess: 19 April 2024). <lb/>The example studies (Sects. 4 and 5) and multi-instrument <lb/>synergies (Sect. 6) described here are only a small portion <lb/>of the studies currently being undertaken by the ABoVE Sci-<lb/>ence Team and the SAR Working Group. We anticipate many <lb/>new and innovative uses of the L-band and P-band SAR data <lb/>as the ABoVE team expands its range of synthesis activities <lb/>in Phase 3. <lb/>The ABoVE L-band SAR flights planned for 2020 and <lb/>2021 were postponed due to the global COVID-19 pandemic <lb/>and safety considerations; however, flights were resumed in <lb/>2022, and we anticipate at least one more thaw season cam-<lb/>paign in 2024. Finally, we note that the data and analyses <lb/>discussed here set the stage for the upcoming NISAR mis-<lb/>sion (expected launch in 2024). NISAR will deliver global <lb/>L-and S-band imagery with a 12 d revisit. Its emphasis on <lb/>snow-and ice-covered surfaces has obvious applications in <lb/>the ABoVE domain, and its global coverage will allow re-<lb/>searchers to test the methods developed for the ABoVE do-<lb/>main across the pan-Arctic. Beyond NISAR, NASA is study-<lb/>ing architectures for the Surface Deformation and Change <lb/>(SDC) Earth System Observatory Mission and ESA are de-<lb/>veloping the Rose-L Copernicus expansion mission. SDC <lb/>and Rose-L are also envisioned as L-band sensors. NISAR, <lb/>SDC, and Rose-L will all benefit from the ABoVE SAR stud-<lb/>ies, algorithmic advances, and lessons learned. <lb/></body>

        <div type="annex">Supplement. The Supplement contains detailed descriptions of <lb/>all L-band flight lines, as well as tables with hyperlinks to <lb/>all L-band lines and sorties. Additionally, the Supplement in-<lb/>cludes tables and links to the P-band flight lines acquired dur-<lb/>ing the ABoVE campaigns and to all Legacy L-band and P-band <lb/>flight lines. The SI is identical to the file Summary ABoVE L-<lb/>&amp; P-Band SAR Surveys -hyperlinked.pdf that may be found <lb/>in the /data folder of the uncompressed data download from <lb/>Miller et al. (2023; https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/2150). <lb/>The supplement related to this article is available online <lb/>at: https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2605-2024-supplement. <lb/></div>

        <div type="contribution">Author contributions. SJG, CEM, PCG, and the ABoVE Sci-<lb/>ence Definition Team developed the preliminary ABoVE Imple-<lb/>mentation Plan; this was updated by SJG, CEM, PCG, and the <lb/>ABoVE Science Team. CEM, PCG, and EH developed the initial <lb/>flight lines based on the ABoVE Implementation Plan and consul-<lb/>tations with the ABoVE Science Team and partners. NSP trans-<lb/>lated the notional flight lines into the UAVSAR planning system. <lb/>NSP, YL, MaM, PCG, ELH, and CEM served as scientist on board <lb/>during the data acquisition flights. YL, SH, BC, NP and the JPL <lb/>Suborbital Radar Science and Engineering Team (334F) processed <lb/>the L-and P-band SAR data. CW, KS, MT, JB, LBC, RHC, MiM, <lb/>SW, MaM, RJM, TL, LJ, PS, AT, and RD collected calibration-<lb/>validation (cal/val) field data. CW and SW coordinated ground cal/-<lb/>val data acquisitions at the NGEE-Arctic sites. SH, PS, and NSP <lb/>performed the TomoSAR analyses, and SH contributed the text and <lb/>images for Sect. 6. KS, MaM, and the ABoVE SAR Working Group <lb/>calibrated the L-band SAR data. MaM, AT, and RHC processed the <lb/>P-band data. NSP and YL coordinated the LS-ASAR flights and the <lb/>joint BERMS area TomoSAR flights with F-SAR. DS coordinated <lb/>all data product submissions to the ORNL DAAC. CEM wrote the <lb/>initial manuscript, and all co-authors contributed to the final ver-<lb/>sion. <lb/></div>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2605-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2605-2624, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2620 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">C. E. Miller et al.: The ABoVE L-band and P-band airborne SAR surveys <lb/></note>

        <div type="conflict">Competing interests. The contact author has declared that none <lb/>of the authors has any competing interests. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Disclaimer. Publisher&apos;s note: Copernicus Publications remains <lb/>neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims made in the text, pub-<lb/>lished maps, institutional affiliations, or any other geographical rep-<lb/>resentation in this paper. While Copernicus Publications makes ev-<lb/>ery effort to include appropriate place names, the final responsibility <lb/>lies with the authors. <lb/></div>

        <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements. The L-and P-band SAR data acquisitions <lb/>would not have been possible without the indefatigable support of <lb/>our NASA pilots and flight crews. We thank John McGrath and the <lb/>NASA AFRC C-20 (N30502) team as well as Derek Rutovic and <lb/>the NASA JSC G-III (N995NA) team. We also thank the instru-<lb/>ment scientists, operators, and data processing team from the JPL <lb/>Suborbital Radar Science and Engineering Team (334F), who were <lb/>essential to the successful execution of these experiments and rapid <lb/>processing of the resulting data products. The fieldwork support-<lb/>ing the SAR campaigns was made possible by the excellent support <lb/>from Dan Hodkinson, Sarah Sackett, and the ABoVE Logistics Of-<lb/>fice. Finally, we thank the data curation team at the Oak Ridge Dis-<lb/>tributed Active Archive Center for their support and expert advice. <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">Financial support. This work was supported by the NASA Ter-<lb/>restrial Ecology Program&apos;s Arctic Boreal Vulnerability Experiment <lb/>(ABoVE). Jennifer Baltzer was supported by GNWT CIMP 170 <lb/>and the Canada Research Chairs program. Laura Bourgeau-Chavez <lb/>was supported by NASA ABoVE (grant nos. NNX15AT83A <lb/>and 80NSSC19M0107). Thomas A. Douglas was supported by <lb/>the Strategic Environmental Research and Development Program <lb/>(project RC18-1170) and the Environmental Security Technology <lb/>Demonstration Program (project RC22-7408). Nancy French was <lb/>supported under grant no. 80NSSC19M0108 from the NASA Ter-<lb/>restrial Ecology Program ABoVE project. Scott J. Goetz received <lb/>support from NASA (grant no. 80NSSC22K1247). John S. Kim-<lb/>ball was supported under the NASA Terrestrial Ecology program <lb/>(grant no. 80NSSC22K1238). This work was performed in part at <lb/>the University of Southern California under grants from the Na-<lb/>tional Aeronautics and Space Administration, Science Mission Di-<lb/>rectorate, Arctic Boreal Vulnerability Experiment program. Kevin <lb/>Schaefer and Leah K. Clayton were supported by NASA (grant <lb/>nos. NNX17AC59A and NNX16AH36A) and award 1562619 from <lb/>the National Science Foundation. A portion of this work was per-<lb/>formed at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory, California Institute of <lb/>Technology, under contract with National Aeronautics and Space <lb/>Administration (grant no. 80NM0018D0004). Government funding <lb/>was received. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Review statement. This paper was edited by Kirsten Elger and <lb/>reviewed by two anonymous referees. <lb/></div>

        <listBibl>References <lb/>Allen, B. D., Braun, S. A., Crawford, J. H., Jensen, E. J., Miller, <lb/>C. E., Moghaddam, M., and Maring, H.: Proposed investiga-<lb/>tions from NASA&apos;s Earth Venture-1 (EV-1) airborne science se-<lb/>lections, in: 2010 IEEE International Geoscience and Remote <lb/>Sensing Symposium, Honolulu, HI, USA, 2010, 2575-2578, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1109/IGARSS.2010.5651920, 2010. <lb/>Altenau, E. H., Pavelsky, T. M., Moller, D., Lion, C., Pitcher, L. H., <lb/>Allen, G. H., Bates, P. D., Calmant, S., Durand, M., and Smith, <lb/>L. C.: AirSWOT measurements of river water surface elevation <lb/>and slope: Tanana River, AK, Geophys. Res. Lett., 44, 181-189, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/2016GL071577, 2017. <lb/>Bakian-Dogaheh, K., Chen, R. H., Moghaddam, M., Yi, Y., <lb/>and Tabatabaeenejad, A.: ABoVE: Active Layer Soil <lb/>Characterization of Permafrost Sites, Northern Alaska, <lb/>2018, ORNL DAAC, Oak Ridge, Tennessee, USA, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1759, 2020a. <lb/>Bakian-Dogaheh, K., Chen, R. H., Moghaddam, M., and <lb/>Tabatabaeenejad, A.: Electromagnetic scattering behavior of a <lb/>new organic soil dielectric model for long-wavelength radar re-<lb/>trieval of permafrost active layer soil properties, 2020 IEEE In-<lb/>ternational Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium, Virtual <lb/>Symposium, 26 September-2 October 2020b. <lb/>Blair, J. B. and Hofton, M. A.: Modeling laser altimeter re-<lb/>turn waveforms over complex vegetation using high-reso-<lb/>lution elevation data, Geophy. Res. Lett., 26, 2509-2512, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/1999GL010484, 1999. <lb/>Blair, J. B. and Hofton, M.: ABoVE LVIS L1B Ge-<lb/>olocated Return Energy Waveforms, Version 1,NASA <lb/>National Snow and Ice Data Center Distributed Ac-<lb/>tive Archive Center, Boulder, Colorado USA [data set], <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5067/UMRAWS57QAFU, 2018a. <lb/>Blair, J. B. and Hofton, M.: ABoVE LVIS L2 Geolocated <lb/>Surface Elevation Product, Version 1, National Snow and <lb/>Ice Data Center (NSIDC), the LVIS DAAC [data set], <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5067/IA5WAX7K3YGY, 2018b. <lb/>Blair, J. B., Rabine, D. L., and Hofton, M. A.: The Laser Vegetation <lb/>Imaging Sensor: a medium-altitude, digitisation-only, airborne <lb/>laser altimeter for mapping vegetation and topography, ISPRS <lb/>J. Photogramm., 54, 115-122, https://doi.org/10.1016/S0924-<lb/>2716(99)00002-7, 1999. <lb/>Bourgeau-Chavez, L. L., Battaglia, M., Kane, E. S., Cohen, L. <lb/>M., and Tanzer, D.: ABoVE: Post-Fire and Unburned Vegetation <lb/>Community and Field Data, NWT, Canada, 2018, ORNL DAAC, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1703, 2019a. <lb/>Bourgeau-Chavez, L. L., Graham, J. A., Grelick, S. E., <lb/>French, N. H. F., Battaglia, M., Hansen, D., and Tanzer, <lb/>D.: ABoVE: Ecosystem Map, Great Slave Lake Area, <lb/>Northwest Territories, Canada, 1997-2011, ORNL DAAC, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1695, 2019b. <lb/>Chapin, E., Chau, A., Chen, J., Heavey, B., Hensley, S., Lou, Y., <lb/>Machuzak, R., and Moghaddam, M.: AirMOSS: An Airborne P-<lb/>band SAR to measure root-zone soil moisture, in: 2012 IEEE <lb/>Radar Conference, Atlanta, GA, USA, 7-11 May 2012, 0693-<lb/>0698, https://doi.org/10.1109/RADAR.2012.6212227, 2012. <lb/>Chapin, E., Flores, S., Harcke, L., Hawkins, B. P., Hensley, S., <lb/>Michel, T. R., Muellerschoen, R. J., Shimada, J. G., Tung, W. W., <lb/>and Veeramachaneni, C.: AirMOSS: L1 S-0 Polarimetric Data <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2605-2624, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2605-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">C. E. Miller et al.: The ABoVE L-band and P-band airborne SAR surveys <lb/></note>

        <page>2621 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>from AirMOSS P-band SAR, BERMS, Canada, 2012-2015, <lb/>ORNL DAAC, https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1406, <lb/>2018. <lb/>Chen, R. H., Bakian-Dogaheh, K., Tabatabaeenejad, A., and <lb/>Moghaddam, M.: Modeling and Retrieving Soil Moisture <lb/>and Organic Matter Profiles in the Active Layer of Per-<lb/>mafrost Soils From P-Band Radar Observations, IGARSS <lb/>2019 -2019 IEEE International Geoscience and Remote <lb/>Sensing Symposium, Yokohama, Japan, 2019, 10095-10098, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1109/IGARSS.2019.8899802, 2019a. <lb/>Chen, R. H., Tabatabaeenejad, A., and Moghaddam, M.: <lb/>ABoVE: Active Layer and Soil Moisture Properties from Air-<lb/>MOSS P-band SAR in Alaska, ORNL DAAC [data set], <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1657, 2019b. <lb/>Chen, R. H., Michaelides, R. J., Zhao, Y., Huang, L., Wig, E., Sulli-<lb/>van, T. D., Parsekian, A. D., Zebker, H. A., Moghaddam, M., and <lb/>Schaefer, K. M.: Permafrost Dynamics Observatory: Retrieval <lb/>of Active Layer Thickness and Soil Moisture from Airborne <lb/>Insar and Polsar Data, in: 2021 IEEE International Geoscience <lb/>and Remote Sensing Symposium IGARSS, Brussels, Belgium, <lb/>2021, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1109/IGARSS47720.2021.9554288, <lb/>1444-1447, 2021. <lb/>Chen, R. H., Michaelides, R. J., Zhao, Y., Huang, L., Wig, E., <lb/>Sullivan, T. D., Parsekian, A. D., Zebker, H. A., Moghad-<lb/>dam, M., and Schaefer, K. M.: Permafrost Dynamics Obser-<lb/>vatory (PDO): 2. Joint Retrieval of Permafrost Active Layer <lb/>Thickness and Soil Moisture From L-Band InSAR and P-<lb/>Band PolSAR, Earth and Space Science, 10, e2022EA002453, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2022EA002453, 2023. <lb/>Clayton, L. K., Schaefer, K., Battaglia, M. J., Bourgeau-Chavez, <lb/>L., Chen, J., Chen, R. H., Chen, A., Bakian-Dogaheh, K., Gre-<lb/>lik, S., Jafarov, E., and Liu, L.: Active layer thickness as a <lb/>function of soil water content, Environ. Res. Lett., 16, 055028, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/abfa4c, 2021. <lb/>Cook, B. D., Corp, L. W., Nelson, R. F., Middleton, E. M., Mor-<lb/>ton, D. C., McCorkel, J. T., Masek, J. G., Ranson, K. J., Ly, V., <lb/>and Montesano, P. M.: NASA Goddard&apos;s Lidar, Hyperspectral <lb/>and Thermal (G-LiHT) airborne imager, Remote Sens.-Basel, 5, <lb/>4045-4066, https://doi.org/10.3390/rs5084045, 2013. <lb/>Dann, J., Bennett, K. E., Bolton, W. R., and Wilson, C. <lb/>J.: Factors Controlling a Synthetic Aperture Radar (SAR) <lb/>Derived Root-Zone Soil Moisture Product over The Se-<lb/>ward Peninsula of Alaska, Remote Sens.-Basel, 14, 4927, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/rs14194927, 2022. <lb/>Du, J., Kimball, J. S., and Moghaddam, M.: Theoretical Modeling <lb/>and Analysis of L-and P-band Radar Backscatter Sensitivity to <lb/>Soil Active Layer Dielectric Variations, Remote Sens.-Basel, 7, <lb/>9450-9472, https://doi.org/10.3390/rs70709450, 2015. <lb/>French, N. H. F., Graham, J. A., Bourgeau-Chavez, L. L., and <lb/>Whitman, E.: ABoVE: Burn Severity of Soil Organic Mat-<lb/>ter, Northwest Territories, Canada, 2014-2015, ORNL DAAC, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1694, 2020. <lb/>Goetz, S. J., Miller, C. E., Griffith, P. C., Chatterjee, A., Boel-<lb/>man, N., Bourgeau-Chavez, L., Butman, D., Epstein, H., Fisher, <lb/>J., French, N., Hoy, E., Kimball, J. S., Larson, E., Loboda, T., <lb/>Mack, M., Moghaddam, M., Montesano, P., Prugh, L., Rawlins, <lb/>M., Rocha, A. V., Rogers, B. M., and Schaefer, K.: An overview <lb/>of NASA&apos;s Arctic Boreal Vulnerability Experiment (ABoVE): <lb/>An integrated research campaign to assess ecosystem vulnera-<lb/>bility and its implications within the Arctic and boreal domain, <lb/>Environmental Research Letters (ABoVE Special Collection), <lb/>Manuscript ERL-112259, in review, 2022. <lb/>Hensley, S., Oveisgharan, S., Saatchi, S., Simard, M., Ahmed, R., <lb/>and Haddad, Z.: An error model for biomass estimates derived <lb/>from polarimetric radar backscatter, IEEE T. Geosci. Remote, 52, <lb/>4065-4082, 2014. <lb/>Hensley, S., Lou, Y., Michel, T., Muellerschoen, R., Hawkins, <lb/>B., Lavalle, M., Pinto, N., Reigber, A., and Pardini, M.: <lb/>UAVSAR PolInSAR and tomographic experiments in Germany, <lb/>in: 2016 IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing <lb/>Symposium (IGARSS), Beijing, China, July 2016, 7517-7520, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1109/IGARSS.2016.7730960, 2016. <lb/>Hensley, S., Chapman, B., Lavalle, M., Hawkins, B., Riel, B., <lb/>Michel, T., Muellerschoen, R., Lou, Y., and Simard, M.: <lb/>UAVSAR L-Band and P-Band Tomographic Experiments in <lb/>Boreal Forests, IGARSS 2018 -2018 IEEE International Geo-<lb/>science and Remote Sensing Symposium, Valencia, Spain, 2018, <lb/>8679-8682, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1109/IGARSS.2018.8518784, <lb/>2018. <lb/>Hensley, S., Ahmed, R., Chapman, B., Hawkins, B., Lavalle, <lb/>M., Pinto, N., Pardini, M., Papathanassiou, K., Siqueria, <lb/>P., and Treuhaft, R.: Boreal Forest Radar Tomography at <lb/>P, L and S-Bands at Berms and Delta Junction, IGARSS <lb/>2020 -2020 IEEE International Geoscience and Remote <lb/>Sensing Symposium, Waikoloa, HI, USA, 2020, 96-99, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1109/IGARSS39084.2020.9323337, 2020. <lb/>Hinzman, L. D., Deal, C. J., McGuire, A. D., Mernild, S. H., <lb/>Polyakov, I. V., and Walsh, J. E.: Trajectory of the Arc-<lb/>tic as an integrated system, Ecol. Appl., 23, 1837-1868, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1890/11-1498.1, 2013. <lb/>Holloway, J. E., Lewkowicz, A. G., Douglas, T. A., Li, X., <lb/>Turetsky, M. R., Baltzer, J. L., and Jin, H.: Impact of <lb/>wildfire on permafrost landscapes: A review of recent ad-<lb/>vances and future prospects, Permafrost Periglac., 31, 371-382, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/ppp.2048, 2020. <lb/>Hoy, E. E., Griffith, P., Miller, C. E., and ABoVE Science <lb/>Team: ABoVE: Directory of Field Sites Associated with <lb/>2017 ABoVE Airborne Campaign, ORNL DAAC [data set], <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1582, 2018. <lb/>Kokelj, S. V., Lacelle, D., Lantz, T. C., Tunnicliffe, J., Malone, L., <lb/>Clark, I. D., and Chin, K. S.: Thawing of massive ground ice in <lb/>mega slumps drives increases in stream sediment and solute flux <lb/>across a range of watershed scales, J. Geophys. Res.-Earth, 118, <lb/>681-692, https://doi.org/10.1002/jgrf.20063, 2013. <lb/>Kokelj, S. V., Tunnicliffe, J., Lacelle, D., Lantz, T. C., Chin, K. <lb/>S., and Fraser, R.: Increased precipitation drives mega slump <lb/>development and destabilization of ice-rich permafrost ter-<lb/>rain, northwestern Canada, Glob. Planet. Change, 129, 56-68, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gloplacha.2015.02.008, 2015. <lb/>Kyzivat, E. D., Smith, L. C., Pitcher, L. H., Fayne, J. V., Coo-<lb/>ley, S. W., Cooper, M. G., Topp, S. N., Langhorst, T., Har-<lb/>lan, M. E., Horvat, C., Gleason, C. J., and Pavelsky, T. M.: A <lb/>High-Resolution Airborne Color-Infrared Camera Water Mask <lb/>for the NASA ABoVE Campaign, Remote Sens.-Basel, 11, 2163, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/rs11182163, 2019. <lb/>Kyzivat, E. D., Smith, L. C., Pitcher, L. H., Fayne, J. V., Cooley, S. <lb/>W., Cooper, M. G., Topp, S., Langhorst, T., Harlan, M. E., Glea-<lb/>son, C. J., and Pavelsky, T. M.: ABoVE: AirSWOT Water Masks <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2605-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2605-2624, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2622 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">C. E. Miller et al.: The ABoVE L-band and P-band airborne SAR surveys <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>from Color-Infrared Imagery over Alaska and Canada, 2017, <lb/>ORNL DAAC, https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1707, <lb/>2020. <lb/>Lantz, T. C. and Turner, K. W.: Changes in lake area <lb/>in response to thermokarst processes and climate in Old <lb/>Crow Flats, Yukon, J. Geophys. Res.-Biogeo., 120, 513-524, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/2014JG002744, 2015. <lb/>Lathrop, E., Nutt, M., Wilson, C., Bolton, R., Perkins, G., and Har-<lb/>ris, R.: Soil moisture, physical and chemical properties coin-<lb/>cident with airborne SAR data collections for 2017 and 2019, <lb/>Seward Peninsula, Alaska, Next Generation Ecosystem Experi-<lb/>ments Arctic Data Collection, Oak Ridge National Laboratory, <lb/>U.S. Department of Energy, Oak Ridge, Tennessee, USA [data <lb/>set], https://doi.org/10.5440/1854940, 2022. <lb/>Le Toan, T., Quegan, S., Davidson, M. W. J., Balzter, H., Pail-<lb/>lou, P., Papathanassiou, K., Plummer, S., Rocca, F., Saatchi, <lb/>S., Shugart, H., and Ulander, L.: The BIOMASS mission: <lb/>Mapping global forest biomass to better understand the ter-<lb/>restrial carbon cycle, Remote Sens. Environ., 115, 2850-2860, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rse.2011.03.020, 2011. <lb/>Loboda, T. V., Jenkins, L. K., Chen, D., He, J., and Baer, A.: Burned <lb/>and Unburned Field Site Data, Noatak, Seward, and North Slope, <lb/>AK, 2016-2018, ORNL DAAC, Oak Ridge, Tennessee, USA, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1919, 2022. <lb/>Magagi, R., Berg, A. A., Goita, K., Belair, S., Jackson, T. J., Toth, <lb/>B., Walker, A., McNairn, H., O&apos;Neill, P. E., Moghaddam, M., <lb/>Gherboudj, I., Colliander, A., Cosh, M. H., Burgin, M., Fisher, <lb/>J. B., Kim, S.-B., Mladenova, I., Djamai, N., Rousseau, L.-P. <lb/>B., Belanger, J., Shang, J., and Merzouki, A.: Canadian Ex-<lb/>periment for Soil Moisture in 2010 (CanEx-SM10): Overview <lb/>and Preliminary Results, IEEE T. Geosci. Remote, 51, 347-363, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1109/TGRS.2012.2198920, 2013. <lb/>McGuire, A. D., Anderson, L. G., Christensen, T. R., Dallimore, <lb/>S., Guo, L., Hayes, D. J., Heimann, M., Lorenson, T. D., Mac-<lb/>donald, R. W., and Roulet, N.: Sensitivity of the carbon cycle <lb/>in the Arctic to climate change, Ecol. Monogr., 79, 523-555, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1890/08-2025.1, 2009. <lb/>Meddens, A. J. H., Vierling, L. A., Eitel, J. U. H., Jennewein, J. <lb/>S., White, J. C., and Wulder, M. A.: Developing 5 m resolu-<lb/>tion canopy height and digital terrain models from WorldView <lb/>and ArcticDEM data, Remote Sens. Environ., 218, 174-188, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rse.2018.09.010, 2018. <lb/>Mehra, R. and Ramanujam, V. M.: L S Band Airborne SAR Data <lb/>Products Calibration, in: 2019 URSI Asia-Pacific Radio Science <lb/>Conference (AP-RASC), New Delhi, India, 9-15 March 2019, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.23919/URSIAP-RASC.2019.8738681, 2019. <lb/>Meyer, G., Humphreys, E. R., Melton, J. R., Cannon, A. J., and <lb/>Lafleur, P. M.: Simulating shrubs and their energy and carbon <lb/>dioxide fluxes in Canada&apos;s Low Arctic with the Canadian Land <lb/>Surface Scheme Including Biogeochemical Cycles (CLASSIC), <lb/>Biogeosciences, 18, 3263-3283, https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-18-<lb/>3263-2021, 2021. <lb/>Michaelides, R. J., Chen, R. H., Zhao, Y., Schaefer, K., <lb/>Parsekian, A. D., Sullivan, T., Moghaddam, M., Zebker, H. <lb/>A., Liu, L., Xu, X., and Chen, J.: Permafrost Dynamics <lb/>Observatory -part I: Postprocessing and calibration meth-<lb/>ods of UAVSAR L-band InSAR data for seasonal sub-<lb/>sidence estimation, Earth Space Sci., 8, e2020EA001630, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2020EA001630, 2021. <lb/>Miller, C. E., Griffith, P. C., Goetz, S. J., Hoy, E. E., Pinto, N., <lb/>McCubbin, I. B., Thorpe, A. K., Hofton, M., Hodkinson, D., <lb/>Hansen, C., Woods, J., Larson, E., Kasischke, E. S., and Mar-<lb/>golis, H. A.: An overview of ABoVE airborne campaign data <lb/>acquisitions and science opportunities, Environ. Res. Lett., 14, <lb/>080201, https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/ab0d44, 2019. <lb/>Miller, C. E., Griffith, P., Hoy, E. E., Pinto, N., Lou, Y., Hensley, <lb/>S., Chapman, B., Baltzer, J. L., Bakian-Dogaheh, K., Bolton, W. <lb/>R., Bourgeau-Chavez, L. L., Chen, R. H., Choe, B.-H., Clay-<lb/>ton, L. K., Douglas, T. A., French, N. H. F., Holloway, J. E., <lb/>Hong, G., Huang, L., Iwahana, G., Jenkins, L. K., Kimball, <lb/>J. S., Loboda, T. V., Mack, M. C., Marsh, P., Michaelides, R. <lb/>J., Moghaddam, M., Parsekian, A. D., Schaefer, K., Siqueira, <lb/>P., Singh, D., Tabatabaeenejad, A., Turetsky, M. R., Touzi, R., <lb/>Wig, E., Wilson, P., Wilson, C. J., Wullschleger, S. D., Yi, Y., <lb/>Zebker, H. A., Zhang, Y., Zhao, Y., and Goetz, S. J.: Sum-<lb/>mary of the ABoVE L-band and P-band Airborne SAR Sur-<lb/>veys, ORNL DAAC, Oak Ridge, Tennessee, USA [data set], <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/2150, 2023. <lb/>Moghaddam, M., Tabatabaeenejad, A., Chen, R. H., Saatchi, <lb/>S. S., Jaruwatanadilok, S., Burgin, M., Duan, X., and <lb/>Truong-Loi, M. L.: AirMOSS: L2/3 Volumetric Soil Mois-<lb/>ture Profiles Derived From Radar, 2012-2015, ORNL DAAC, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1418, 2016. <lb/>Montesano, P. M., Sun, G., Dubayah, R. O., and Ranson, <lb/>K. J.: Spaceborne potential for examining taiga-tundra eco-<lb/>tone form and vulnerability, Biogeosciences, 13, 3847-3861, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-13-3847-2016, 2016. <lb/>National Research Council (NRC): Opportunities to Use Remote <lb/>Sensing in Understanding Permafrost and Related Ecological <lb/>Characteristics: Report of a Workshop, The National Academies <lb/>Press, Washington, DC, https://doi.org/10.17226/18711, 2014. <lb/>Pitcher, L. H., Pavelsky, T. M., Smith, L. C., Moller, D. K., Alte-<lb/>nau, E. H., Allen, G. H., Lion, C., Butman, D., Cooley, S. W., <lb/>Fayne, J. V., and Bertram, M.: AirSWOT InSAR Mapping of <lb/>Surface Water Elevations and Hydraulic Gradients Across the <lb/>Yukon Flats Basin, Alaska, Water Resour. Res., 55, 937-953, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2018WR023274, 2019a. <lb/>Pitcher, L. H., Smith, L. C., Pavelsky, T. M., Fayne, J. <lb/>V., Cooley, S. W., Altenau, E. H., Moller, D. K., and <lb/>Arvesen, J.: ABoVE: AirSWOT Radar, Orthomosaic, and Wa-<lb/>ter Masks, Yukon Flats Basin, Alaska, 2015, ORNL DAAC, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1655, 2019b. <lb/>Pitcher, L. H., Smith, L. C., Cooley, S. W., Zaino, A., Carlson, R., <lb/>Pettit, J., Gleason, C. J., Minear, J. T., Fayne, J. V., Willis, M. <lb/>J., Hansen, J. S., Easterday, K. J., Harlan, M. E., Langhorst, T., <lb/>Topp, S. N., Dolan, W., Kyzivat, E. D., Pietroniro, A., Marsh, P., <lb/>Yang, D., Carter, T., Onclin, C., Hosseini, N., Wilcox, E., Mor-<lb/>eira, D., Berge-Nguyen, M., Cretaux, J.-F., and Pavelsky, T. M.: <lb/>Advancing Field-Based GNSS Surveying for Validation of Re-<lb/>motely Sensed Water Surface Elevation Products, Front. Earth <lb/>Sci., 8, 278, https://doi.org/10.3389/feart.2020.00278, 2020. <lb/>Porter, C., Morin, P., Howat, I., Noh, M.-J., Bates, B., Peterman, <lb/>K., Keesey, S., Schlenk, M., Gardiner, J., Tomko, K., Willis, M., <lb/>Kelleher, C., Cloutier, M., Husby, E., Foga, S., Nakamura, H., <lb/>Platson, M., Wethington, M., Williamson, C., Bauer, G., Enos, <lb/>J., Arnold, G., Kramer, W., Becker, P., Doshi, A., D&apos;Souza, <lb/>C., Cummens, P., Laurier, F., and Bojesen, M.: ArcticDEM, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.7910/DVN/OHHUKH, 2018. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2605-2624, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2605-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">C. E. Miller et al.: The ABoVE L-band and P-band airborne SAR surveys <lb/></note>

        <page>2623 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>Quegan, S., Le Toan, T., Chave, J., Dall, J., Exbrayat, J.-F., <lb/>Minh, D. H. T., Lomas, M., D&apos;Alessandro, M. M., Pail-<lb/>lou, P., Papathanassiou, K., Rocca, F., Saatchi, S., Scipal, <lb/>K., Shugart, H., Smallman, T. L., Soja, M. J., Tebaldini, S., <lb/>Ulander, L., Villard, L., and Williams, M.: The European <lb/>Space Agency BIOMASS mission: Measuring forest above-<lb/>ground biomass from space, Remote Sens. Environ., 227, 44-60, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rse.2019.03.032, 2019. <lb/>Quinton, W., Berg, A., Braverman, M., Carpino, O., Chasmer, L., <lb/>Connon, R., Craig, J., Devoie, É., Hayashi, M., Haynes, K., Ole-<lb/>feldt, D., Pietroniro, A., Rezanezhad, F., Schincariol, R., and <lb/>Sonnentag, O.: A synthesis of three decades of hydrological <lb/>research at Scotty Creek, NWT, Canada, Hydrol. Earth Syst. <lb/>Sci., 23, 2015-2039, https://doi.org/10.5194/hess-23-2015-2019, <lb/>2019. <lb/>Ramanujam, V. M. and Mehra, R.: L&amp;S Band SAR Data <lb/>Processing and Products, in: 2019 URSI Asia-Pacific Ra-<lb/>dio Science Conference (AP-RASC), New Delhi, India, 2019, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.23919/URSIAP-RASC.2019.8738235, 2019. <lb/>Ramanujam, V. M., Suneela, T. J. V. D., and Bhan, R.: <lb/>ISRO&apos;s dual frequency airborne SAR pre-cursor to NISAR, <lb/>in: Earth Observing Missions and Sensors: Develop-<lb/>ment, Implementation, and Characterization IV, 98810A, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1117/12.2228086, 2016. <lb/>Reigber, A., Papathanassiou, K., Jger, M., and Scheiber, R.: First re-<lb/>sults of multispectral polarimetry and single-pass PolInSAR with <lb/>the F-SAR airborne SAR instrument, in: 2013 IEEE International <lb/>Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium-IGARSS, IEEE, <lb/>2305-2308, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1109/IGARSS.2013.6723279, <lb/>2013. <lb/>Rosen, P. A., Kim, Y., Kumar, R., Misra, T., Bhan, R., and <lb/>Sagi, V. R.: Global persistent SAR sampling with the NASA-<lb/>ISRO SAR (NISAR) mission, in; 2017 IEEE Radar Con-<lb/>ference (RadarConf), Seattle, WA, USA, 2017, 0410-0414, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1109/RADAR.2017.7944237, 2017. <lb/>Saatchi, S., Xu, L., Yang, Y., and Yu, Y.: Evaluation of <lb/>NISAR Biomass Algorithm in Temperate and Boreal Forests, <lb/>IGARSS 2019-2019 IEEE International Geoscience and Re-<lb/>mote Sensing Symposium, Yokohama, Japan, 2019, 7363-7366, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1109/IGARSS.2019.8898657, 2019. <lb/>Saatchi, S. S. and Moghaddam, M.: Estimation of crown and <lb/>stem water content and biomass of boreal forest using polari-<lb/>metric SAR imagery, IEEE T. Geosci. Remote, 38, 697-709, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1109/36.841999, 2000. <lb/>Schaefer, K., Liu, L., Parsekian, A., Jafarov, E., Chen, A., Zhang, <lb/>T., Gusmeroli, A., Panda, S., Zebker, H. A., and Schaefer, T.: <lb/>Remotely sensed active layer thickness (ReSALT) at Barrow, <lb/>Alaska using interferometric synthetic aperture radar, Remote <lb/>sensing, 7, 3735-3759, https://doi.org/10.3390/rs70403735, <lb/>2015. <lb/>Schaefer, K., Michaelides, R. J., Chen, R. H., Sullivan, T. D., <lb/>Parsekian, A. D., Bakian-Dogaheh, K., Tabatabaeenejad, A., <lb/>Moghaddam, M., Chen, J., Chen, A. C., Liu, L., and Zebker, <lb/>H. A.: ABoVE: Active Layer Thickness Derived from Airborne <lb/>L-and P-band SAR, Alaska, 2017, ORNL DAAC [data set], <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1676, 2019. <lb/>Schaefer, K., Clayton, L. K., Battaglia, M. J., Bourgeau-Chavez, <lb/>L. L., Chen, R. H., Chen, A. C., Chen, J., Bakian-Dogaheh, <lb/>K., Douglas, T. A., Grelick, S. E., Iwahana, G., Jafarov, E., <lb/>Liu, L., Ludwig, S., Michaelides, R. J., Moghaddam, M., Na-<lb/>tali, S., Panda, S. K., Parsekian, A. D., Rocha, A. V., Schae-<lb/>fer, S. R., Sullivan, T. D., Tabatabaeenejad, A., Wang, K., Wil-<lb/>son, C. J., Zebker, H. A., Zhang, T., and Zhao, Y.: ABoVE: <lb/>Soil Moisture and Active Layer Thickness in Alaska and NWT, <lb/>Canada, 2008-2020, ORNL DAAC, Oak Ridge, Tennessee, <lb/>USA, https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1903, 2021a. <lb/>Schaefer, K., Michaelides, R. J., Chen, R. H., Sullivan, <lb/>T. D., Parsekian, A. D., Zhao, Y., Bakian-Dogaheh, K., <lb/>Tabatabaeenejad, A., Moghaddam, M., Chen, J., Chen, A. <lb/>C., Liu, L., and Zebker, H. A.: ABoVE: Active Layer <lb/>Thickness Derived from Airborne L-and P-band SAR, <lb/>Alaska, 2017, ORNL DAAC, Oak Ridge, Tennessee, USA, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1796, 2021b. <lb/>Sellers, P., Hall, F., Margolis, H., Kelly, B., Baldocchi, D., den <lb/>Hartog, G., Cihlar, J., Ryan, M. G., Goodison, B., Crill, <lb/>P., Ranson, K. J., Lettenmaier, D., and Wickland, D. E.: <lb/>The Boreal Ecosystem-Atmosphere Study (BOREAS): An <lb/>Overview and Early Results from the 1994 Field Year, B. Am. <lb/>Meteorol. Soc., 76, 1549-1577, https://doi.org/10.1175/1520-<lb/>0477(1995)076&lt;1549:TBESAO&gt;2.0.CO;2, 1995. <lb/>Sellers, P. J., Hall, F. G., Kelly, R. D., Black, A., Baldoc-<lb/>chi, D., Berry, J., Ryan, M., Ranson, K. J., Crill, P. M., <lb/>Lettenmaier, D. P., Margolis, H., Cihlar, J., Newcomer, J., <lb/>Fitzjarrald, D., Jarvis, P. G., Gower, S. T., Halliwell, D., <lb/>Williams, D., Goodison, B., Wickland, D. E., and Guertin, F. E.: <lb/>BOREAS in 1997: Experiment overview, scientific results, and <lb/>future directions, J. Geophys. Res.-Atmos., 102, 28731-28769, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/97JD03300, 1997. <lb/>Silva, C. A., Duncanson, L., Hancock, S., Neuenschwander, A., <lb/>Thomas, N., Hofton, M., Fatoyinbo, L., Simard, M., Marshak, <lb/>C. Z., Armston, J., Lutchke, S., and Dubayah, R.: Fusing sim-<lb/>ulated GEDI, ICESat-2 and NISAR data for regional above-<lb/>ground biomass mapping, Remote Sens. Environ., 253, 112234, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rse.2020.112234, 2021. <lb/>Tabatabaeenejad, A., Burgin, M., and Moghaddam, M.: Potential <lb/>of L-band radar for retrieval of canopy and subcanopy parame-<lb/>ters of boreal forests, IEEE T. Geosci. Remote, 50, 2150-2160, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1109/TGRS.2011.2173349, 2011. <lb/>Tabatabaeenejad, A., Burgin, M., Duan, X., and Moghad-<lb/>dam, M.: P-Band Radar Retrieval of Subsurface Soil Mois-<lb/>ture Profile as a Second-Order Polynomial: First Air-<lb/>MOSS Results, IEEE T. Geosci. Remote, 53, 645-658, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1109/TGRS.2014.2326839, 2015. <lb/>Tabatabaeenejad, A., Chen, R. H., Burgin, M. S., Duan, X., Cuenca, <lb/>R. H., Cosh, M. H., Scott, R. L., and Moghaddam, M.: As-<lb/>sessment and Validation of AirMOSS P-Band Root-Zone Soil <lb/>Moisture Products, IEEE T. Geosci. Remote, 58, 6181-6196, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1109/TGRS.2020.2974976, 2020. <lb/>Tank, S. E., Olefeldt, D., Quinton, W. L., Spence, C., Dion, N., Ack-<lb/>ley, C., Burd, K., Hutchins, R., and Mengistu, S.: Fire in the Arc-<lb/>tic: The effect of wildfire across diverse aquatic ecosystems of <lb/>the Northwest Territories, Polar Knowledge: Aqhaliat, 1, 31-38, <lb/>2018. <lb/>Vincent, W. F., Callaghan, T. V., Dahl-Jensen, D., Jo-<lb/>hansson, M., Kovacs, K. M., Michel, C., Prowse, T., <lb/>Reist, J. D., and Sharp, M.: Ecological Implications of <lb/>Changes in the Arctic Cryosphere, AMBIO, 40, 87-99, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s13280-011-0218-5, 2011. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2605-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2605-2624, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2624 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">C. E. Miller et al.: The ABoVE L-band and P-band airborne SAR surveys <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>Walker, X. J., Rogers, B. M., Baltzer, J. L., Cumming, S. G., Day, <lb/>N. J., Goetz, S. J., Johnstone, J. F., Schuur, E. A. G., Turet-<lb/>sky, M. R., and Mack, M. C.: Cross-scale controls on carbon <lb/>emissions from boreal forest megafires, Glob. Change Biol., 24, <lb/>4251-4265, https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.14287, 2018a. <lb/>Walker, X. J., Rogers, B. M., Baltzer, J. L., Cummings, S. R., <lb/>Day, N. J., Goetz, S. J., Johnstone, J. F., Turetsky, M. R., and <lb/>Mack, M. C.: ABoVE: Wildfire Carbon Emissions and Burned <lb/>Plot Characteristics, NWT, CA, 2014-2016, ORNL DAAC, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1561, 2018b. <lb/>Walker, X. J., Baltzer, J. L., Cumming, S. G., Day, N. J., Ebert, C., <lb/>Goetz, S., Johnstone, J. F., Potter, S., Rogers, B. M., Schuur, E. <lb/>A. G., Turetsky, M. R., and Mack, M. C.: Increasing wildfires <lb/>threaten historic carbon sink of boreal forest soils, Nature, 572, <lb/>520-523, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-019-1474-y, 2019a. <lb/>Walker, X. J., Baltzer, J. L., Laurier, W., Cumming, S. G., <lb/>Day, N. J., Goetz, S. J., Johnstone, J. F., Potter, S., Rogers, <lb/>B. M., Schuur, E. A. G., Turetsky, M. R., and Mack, <lb/>M. C.: ABoVE: Characterization of Carbon Dynamics in <lb/>Burned Forest Plots, NWT, Canada, 2014, ORNL DAAC, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3334/ORNLDAAC/1664, 2019b. <lb/>Wilson, C., Dann, J., Bolton, R., Charsley-Groffman, L., Ja-<lb/>farov, E., Musa, D., and Wullschleger, S.: In Situ Soil Mois-<lb/>ture and Thaw Depth Measurements Coincident with Air-<lb/>borne SAR Data Collections, Barrow and Seward Peninsulas, <lb/>Alaska, 2017, Next Generation Ecosystem Experiments Arc-<lb/>tic Data Collection, Oak Ridge National Laboratory, U.S. De-<lb/>partment of Energy, Oak Ridge, Tennessee, USA [data set], <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5440/1423892, 2018. <lb/>Wilson, C., Dann, J., Bolton, R., Charsley-Groffman, L., Jafarov, E., <lb/>Musa, D., and Wullschleger, S.: In Situ Soil Moisture and Thaw <lb/>Depth Measurements Coincident with Airborne SAR Data Col-<lb/>lections, Barrow and Seward Peninsulas, Alaska, 2017, United <lb/>States, Version 2, U.S. Department of Energy, Oak Ridge, <lb/>Tennessee, USA [data set], https://www.osti.gov/biblio/1423892 <lb/>(last access: 19 April 2024), 2021. <lb/>Wilson, C., Lathrop, E., Bolton, R., Jin, X., Nutt, M., and Dann, <lb/>J.: In Situ Soil Moisture and Thaw Depth Measurements Co-<lb/>incident with Airborne SAR Data Collections, Seward Penin-<lb/>sula, Alaska, 2019, Next Generation Ecosystem Experiments <lb/>Arctic Data Collection, Oak Ridge National Laboratory, U.S. <lb/>Department of Energy, Oak Ridge, Tennessee, USA [data set], <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5440/1856042, 2022. <lb/>Zhao, Y., Chen, R. H., Bakina-Dogaheh, K., Whitcomb, J., <lb/>Yi, Y., Kimball, J. S., and Moghaddam, M.: Mapping Bo-<lb/>real Forest Species and Canopy Height using Airborne <lb/>SAR and Lidar Data in Interior Alaska, IGARSS 2022-<lb/>2022 IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing <lb/>Symposium, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, 2022, 4955-4958, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1109/IGARSS46834.2022.9883311, 2022. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2605-2624, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2605-2024 </note>


	</text>

</TEI>