<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Evaluation of conical 9 well dish on bovine oocyte maturation and
                    subsequent embryonic development</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Byung Hyun</forename>
          <surname>Ju</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>You Jin</forename>
          <surname>Kim</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Youn Bae</forename>
          <surname>Park</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Byeong Ho</forename>
          <surname>Kim</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Min Kyu</forename>
          <surname>Kim</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-05T14:03:00.775Z">11/5/2025 2:03:00 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Korean Society of Animal Science and Technology</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.5187/jast.2024.e68</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Byung Hyun Ju, You Jin Kim, Youn Bae Park, Byeong Ho Kim, Min Kyu Kim. (2024). Evaluation of conical 9 well dish on bovine oocyte maturation and
                    subsequent embryonic development. Journal of Animal Science and Technology, 66(5), 936-948. DOI: 10.5187/jast.2024.e68</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-05T14:02:32.386415Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-05T14:02:32.386415Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>1 <lb/>JAST (Journal of Animal Science and Technology) TITLE PAGE <lb/>Upload this completed form to website with submission <lb/>ARTICLE INFORMATION <lb/>Fill in information in each box below <lb/>Article Type <lb/>Research Article <lb/>Article Title (within 20 words without abbreviations) Applicability of non-invasive, digital palpation device to detection of <lb/>woody breast conditions in chicken breast muscle <lb/>Running Title (within 10 words) <lb/>Applicability of palpation device to detection of woody breast <lb/>conditions <lb/>Author <lb/>Sang-Hyon OH [first_author] 1, Euyeon Noh2, Byungrok Min2 <lb/>Affiliation <lb/>1 Division of Animal Science, Gyeongsang National University, Jinju <lb/>52725, Korea, Republic of <lb/>2 Department of Agriculture, Food, and Resource Sciences, <lb/>University of Maryland Eastern Shore, Princess Ann 21853, United <lb/>States <lb/>ORCID (for more information, please visit <lb/>https://orcid.org) <lb/>Sang-Hyon OH (https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9696-9638) <lb/>Euyeon Noh (https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000) <lb/>Byungrok Min (https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4108-6579) <lb/>Competing interests <lb/>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported. <lb/>Funding sources <lb/>State funding sources (grants, funding sources, <lb/>equipment, and supplies). Include name and number of <lb/>grant if available. <lb/>This work was supported by the research grant of the Gyeongsang <lb/>National University in 2023. <lb/>Acknowledgements <lb/>Availability of data and material <lb/>Authors&apos; contributions <lb/>Please specify the authors&apos; role using this form. <lb/>Conceptualization: OH SH, Min B <lb/>Data curation: OH SH, Noh E, Min B <lb/>Formal analysis: OH SH, Noh E, Min B <lb/>Methodology: OH SH, Noh E, Min B <lb/>Software: OH SH, Noh E <lb/>Validation: OH SH, Noh E, Min B <lb/>Investigation: OH SH, Noh E, Min B <lb/>Writing -original draft: OH SH <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: OH SH, Noh E, Min B <lb/>Ethics approval and consent to participate <lb/>This article does not require IRB/IACUC approval because there are <lb/>no human and animal participants. <lb/>CORRESPONDING AUTHOR CONTACT INFORMATION <lb/>For the corresponding author <lb/>(responsible for correspondence, <lb/>proofreading, and reprints) <lb/>Fill in information in each box below <lb/>First name, middle initial, last name <lb/>Sang-Hyon OH <lb/>Email address -this is where your proofs will be sent <lb/>shoh@gnu.ac.kr <lb/>Secondary Email address <lb/>Address <lb/>Cell phone number <lb/>+82-10-3402-5663 <lb/>Office phone number <lb/>Fax number <lb/>A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/></front>

        <page>2 <lb/></page>

        <front>Applicability of non-invasive, digital palpation device to detection of woody breast <lb/>conditions in chicken breast muscle <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Woody Breast (WB) is one of muscle myopathy found in chicken breast, characterized with <lb/>enlarged size and extremely stiff texture. The WB condition is one of the most prevalent quality <lb/>issues in the modern poultry industry. WB has been shown to be heritable, but no effective <lb/>detection method of WB severity in live birds exists for the selection purpose. The objective <lb/>of this study was to determine potential of a non-invasive, portable digital palpation device as <lb/>WB detection method that can be used for the selection to estimate the heritability of WB. The <lb/>physical and functional properties of WB was also investigated in comparison with normal <lb/>breast (NB). Two hundred ten breast muscles were obtained from a local processing plant one <lb/>day after harvest and sorted based on WB scoring (1 for NB and 2 and 3 for WB). The samples <lb/>were subjected to physical and physicochemical analyses, determining biomechanical <lb/>properties (muscle tone, stiffness, elasticity, relaxation, and creep), pH, color, cooking yield, <lb/>and texture (firmness and compression energy were used for raw meat and shear force and <lb/>energy for cooked meat). The least squares means of the following variables were significantly <lb/>different between WB and NB (p&lt;0.01): stiffness (603.4 vs 565.8; N/m), and elasticity (1.40 <lb/>vs 1.55). However, relaxation and creep were not significantly different (p&gt;0.05). These results <lb/>collectively showed that biomechanical properties of WB differ from NB. The degree of <lb/>muscle stiffness in WB can be considered as a trait to be selected. The WB score showed strong <lb/>negative correlations with cooking yield (-0.77) and cooked L*(-0.74), which means that as the <lb/>breast becomes harder, the cooking yield decreases, and the color becomes darker after cooking. <lb/>The WB score showed high correlations with physical and functional characteristics and <lb/>exhibited strong correlations with the biomechanical properties measured by the device. <lb/></front>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <page>3 <lb/></page>

        <front>Therefore, the results indicated that the digital palpation device has potential to detect the WB <lb/>severity (degree of stiffness) of breast muscle. <lb/>Keywords: woody breast, Myoton, characteristics, broiler, breast meat <lb/></front>

        <body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Poultry producers&apos; main goal is to raise chickens as fast and large as possible. This quest <lb/>for growth efficiency is thought to have caused many muscle abnormalities, and a woody breast <lb/>(WB) is one of them that is a significant concern for numerous producers and consumers in <lb/>countries throughout the world, yet no practical solution has been proposed [1,2]. <lb/>&quot;Woody Breast&quot; is the broiler breast muscle abnormality featured with enlarged size and <lb/>extremely stiff textural properties often accompanies by hemorrhages on the surface, causing <lb/>quality issues of broiler breast meat [2]. The WB condition is one of the most prevalent issues <lb/>in the modern poultry industry. The frequency of the defect in Europe is over 30% and some <lb/>have argued that similar levels may exist in the US, depending on the weight of the bird at <lb/>harvest [3,4]. Given that chicken with WB is of poor economic value and are discriminated by <lb/>the consumers, producers face significant economic hardship under the current production <lb/>paradigm as the producers can find out occurrences of WB only after harvest [5-9]. <lb/>One of the problems in identifying a solution is that the occurrence and severity of WB can <lb/>be identified only after harvest. More specifically, WB is subjectively evaluated and separated <lb/>by meat processors using visual cues and manual palpation after harvest [10]. Because more <lb/>and more wholesale and retail vendors discriminate against WB chicken, WB is becoming a <lb/>huge economic liability for the poultry industry [6,9]. As a result, defining and selecting against <lb/>this quality defect is absolutely necessary for the future health of the poultry industry, <lb/>specifically chicken (broiler) production. <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <page>4 <lb/></page>

        <body>Despite its largely unknown etiology, genetics, especially higher growth rate and breast <lb/>muscle yield, are believed to be closely associated with the incidence and severity of WB [1,11-<lb/>13]. Studies have indicated that WB shows moderate heritability (h 2 = 0.1 -0.49) [14,15]. <lb/>Therefore, if WB is heritable and measurable before harvest, it means that it can be controlled <lb/>by genes to certain extent and therefore can be reduced by animal breeding -selection and <lb/>mating. Genetic selection is a method to estimate the genetic (breeding) values of individual <lb/>animals with pedigree information and environmental factors. Breeding value is the value of <lb/>an individual as a (genetic) parent in a breeding program for a specific trait [16]. Bailey et al. <lb/>[17] showed that the incidence of WB was reduced by 18.4% after 2 years of the genetic <lb/>selection process. <lb/>Based on the previous studies, we hypothesized in this study that WB is heritable and <lb/>therefore it can be selected for, based on the severity of WB at certain point of growth of live <lb/>birds. In order to successfully carry out the effective selection, we need to know the degrees to <lb/>which the severity of WB could be adequately measured in live birds and quantified as a <lb/>phenotype. Then the phenotype can be subjected to a selection study in the area of animal <lb/>breeding using genetic (pedigree) information and quantitative (statistical) genetics. <lb/>However, the major obstacle against animal breeding research for the solutions of WB is an <lb/>absence in an effective, reliable detection system of WB in the breast tissues of live birds along <lb/>with an accurate, quick method to evaluate the severity of WB, which would be considered as <lb/>the level of hardness. There have been advancements in this area. Tijare et al. [18] described <lb/>the WB scoring method with regard to level of hardness and location (cranial vs. entire fillet) <lb/>and Mudalal et al. [19] used texture analysis measuring the force required to compress fillets <lb/>to determine the WB severity of chicken breasts. While those evaluations methods for textural <lb/>characterization of WB after harvest are useful for separating WB from normal breast, they <lb/>cannot be used for the detection of WB and its severity in affected muscle tissue of live birds <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <page>5 <lb/></page>

        <body>for animal breeding. <lb/>Myotonometry is a non-invasive technique that can measure biomechanical characteristics <lb/>of muscle tone including stiffness by applying mechanical force perpendicularly to the muscle <lb/>tissues [20]. Validity, reliability, and convenience of hand-held myotonometer measuring <lb/>muscle stiffness in vivo have been demonstrated by previous clinical studies [20-22]. This <lb/>demonstrates that the portable myotonometer can be used to measure WB in live birds. The <lb/>objective of this study was to determine the applicability of myotonometer, a non-invasive, <lb/>hand-held, digital palpation device, to the quantification of the severity of WB as a trait that <lb/>can be used for the selection study to estimate the heritability of WB. This study also <lb/>determines the physical and functional characteristics of WB in comparison with normal breast <lb/>(NB). <lb/>MATERIALS AND METHODS <lb/>Sample preparation <lb/>Two hundred ten chicken breast fillets (Pectoralis major) with woody and normal conditions <lb/>(35 WB and 35 NB per replication, 3 replications) were obtained from a local processing plant <lb/>one day after slaughtering. The breast fillets were sorted into woody and normal conditions at <lb/>the processing plant based on the plant processing procedure. Up on receipt, the severity of <lb/>woody breast conditions of the samples was evaluated based on the WB scoring system <lb/>described by Tijare et al. [18] with some modifications: 1 -normal (flexible throughout), 2 -<lb/>moderate (rigid mainly in the cranial region but flexible in the caudal region), and 3 -severe <lb/>(extremely rigid throughout the breast meat). They were divided into 2 groups based on the <lb/>WB scoring: NB -1 and WB -2 and 3. Subsequently, the fillets were prepared for the <lb/>evaluation of physical, physicochemical, and functional properties, including pH, color, water <lb/>holding capacity, cooking yield, and textural properties. All the assays were completed within <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <page>6 <lb/></page>

        <body>2 days after the receipt. <lb/>Biomechanical properties of raw breast muscle <lb/>Biomechanical properties of the samples were determined using a myotonometer, non-invasive, <lb/>portable digital palpation device (MyotonPRO, Myoton, Tallinn, Estonia). The probe of the <lb/>device was placed perpendicular to the cranial portion of the breast muscle and then the <lb/>mechanical impulse was briefly applied to the muscle at a force of 0.60 N for 15 ms [23]. The <lb/>resulting oscillation curve of the muscle were recorded and used to calculate 5 biomechanical <lb/>properties of muscle, including muscle tone, stiffness, elasticity, relaxation, and creep. Those <lb/>properties were defined as follows: 1) muscle tone, intrinsic tension in the relaxed muscle <lb/>measured as oscillation frequency (Hz), 2) stiffness, the resistance of muscle to deformation <lb/>force measured as dynamic stiffness (N/m), 3) elasticity, the ability to recover its initial shape <lb/>after removal of an external force of deformation measured as logarithmic decrement, 4) <lb/>relaxation, the time for muscle to recover its shape from deformation after the removal of an <lb/>external force measured as mechanical stress relaxation time (ms, MSRT), and 5) creep, the <lb/>gradual elongation of a tissue over time when placed under a constant tensile stress measured <lb/>as ratio of deformation and relaxation time (RDRT) [20,24,25]. <lb/>pH and color <lb/>The pH of each breast fillet was measured using a portable pH meter (HI98163, Hanna <lb/>Instrument, Smithfield, RI) equipped with an insertion pH electrode (FC2323). The electrode <lb/>tip was inserted into the fillet approximately 1 cm below the surface and the reading was <lb/>recorded after stabilized. Color on the skin-side surface of the fillet was determined using a <lb/>colorimeter (CR-400, Konica Minolta Sensing America, Ramsey, NJ, USA) with 8 mm <lb/>aperture, illuminant D65, and 2° standard observer. The color values taken from 3 random <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <page>7 <lb/></page>

        <body>locations in the cranial region of each fillet were averaged and reported. The color of the cooked <lb/>breast fillet was also determined. <lb/>Water holding capacity <lb/>The water holding capacity (WHC) of the raw fillet sample was determined using a <lb/>centrifugation method [26]. A cell strainer containing a thin slice of breast fillet (approximately <lb/>1 g and 1-2 mm in thickness) was placed onto a tube and centrifuged at 400 × g for 1 hr at 4 °C <lb/>to remove free and loosely bound water from the meat. WHC (%) was calculated as the ratio <lb/>of the weight of water removed to the initial weight of the slice and represented the amount of <lb/>removable water (water loss) in 100 g of meat. <lb/>Cooking yield <lb/>A portion of breast fillet including the cranial region (approximately 200 g) was vacuum-<lb/>packaged and cooked in a boiling water bath until the internal temperature reached 73.9 °C. <lb/>After excessive moisture and fat on the surface, the cooked sample was stored at 4 °C in a <lb/>refrigerator overnight prior to weighing. Cooking yield (%) was calculated as a ratio of the <lb/>weight of the sample after and before cooking and expressed as a percentage. Subsequently, <lb/>the cooked meat was used to determine the shear force and energy. <lb/>Firmness of raw breast fillet <lb/>The firmness and compression energy of the raw breast fillet sample were determined in the <lb/>cranial region using a Texture analyzer (model TA-XT2i, Texture Technologies, Hamilton, <lb/>MA) equipped with a 50-kg loading cell and a cylinder probe (TA-10ss, 12.5 mm in diameter) <lb/>attached to a converter (TA-71). The cranial region of the samples was compressed 10 mm in <lb/>depth by the probe at the crosshead speed of 10 mm/sec. Peak force (N) and area under the <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <page>8 <lb/></page>

        <body>time-force curve (N*sec) were reported as firmness and compression energy. <lb/>Shear force of cooked breast meat <lb/>Shear force and energy of the cooked breast meat were determined using the Meullenet-Owens <lb/>Razor Shear (MORS) method [27], using a Texture analyzer equipped with a 5-kg loading cell <lb/>and MORS blade (TA-46, 9 mm (blade) x 38 mm). The cooked breast meat was penetrated by <lb/>the MORS blade perpendicular to the fiber direction. The penetration depth and crosshead <lb/>speed were 20 mm and 10 mm/sec, respectively. The peak force (N) and area under the time-<lb/>force curve (N*mm) were calculated and reported as the shear force and energy, respectively. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Table 1 shows the significance of factors included in the statistical model. The effects of test <lb/>and breast type were significant in almost all dependent variables except for water loss, b* and <lb/>frequency. The interaction effect was generally not significant, but it was significant in some <lb/>cases and was not excluded from the statistical model. <lb/>Least square means of physical and physicochemical characteristics are shown in Table 2. <lb/>The least squares means of the following variables were significantly different between WB <lb/>and NB (p&lt;0.01): DS (603.4 vs 565.8; N/m), and elasticity (1.40 vs 1.55). However, MSRT <lb/>and RDRT were not significantly different (p&gt;0.05). These results collectively show that the <lb/>non-invasive measurements of WB differ from NB. The degree of muscle hardness in WB can <lb/>be considered as a trait to be selected, and utilized for the genetic/genomic selection program <lb/>collecting the measurements before harvest. <lb/>Pearson correlations are shown among parameters studied in Table 3. The WB score showed <lb/>strong negative correlations with cooking yield (-0.77) and cooked L*(-0.74), which means <lb/>that as the breast becomes harder, the cooking yield decreases, and the color becomes darker <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <page>9 <lb/></page>

        <body>after cooking. The WB score showed high correlations with physicochemical characteristics <lb/>and also exhibited strong correlations with the values measured by the device used in this study. <lb/>Therefore, it was possible to measure the hardness of breast meat using the device and also <lb/>observe the presence of variability. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>There are large amounts of research going on in the industry to try and improve meat quality <lb/>without decreasing the performance of the bird or negatively impacting the poultry industry <lb/>and human health [6]. To date, the biological mechanism responsible for WB remains unknown <lb/>[28]. About 90 studies were found in PubMed regarding WB, of which 34% were done on how <lb/>it affected the different qualities of the meat; 23% on how the feeding regimen/diet affected <lb/>the incidence or severity of the meat; 15.5% on how different genetic lines affected the <lb/>incidence of the condition and which genes were expressed due to the condition; about 18% on <lb/>the histology and morphology of the affected meat; 5.5% on the pathology; 2% on the incidence <lb/>of the condition is affected by the age of the bird; and just 1% on how the time of hatch and <lb/>incubation temperature can affect the morphology score [29]. <lb/>Although WB poses trouble for poultry industries across the globe, there still hasn&apos;t been a <lb/>practical solution or set of policies that are proposed or in use today because of limited research <lb/>and information on it [30]. Woody breast is a phenomenon that affects the physical composition <lb/>of broiler raw breast fillets. It has been reported that WB leads to multiple histological lesions <lb/>such as myodegeneration and necrosis and regenerative changes [31,32]. <lb/>Over the last 10 years, continuous selection for broilers resulted in about a 5% increase in <lb/>breast meat yield [32]. This selection effort to increase bird size has led to a higher risk of <lb/>disease incidences, economic loss, and welfare concerns, as well as a negative influence on <lb/>meat quality traits [33,34]. Increased growth rate and continuous selection saw various <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <page>10 <lb/></page>

        <body>muscular defects [35,36] and increased muscle damage in chickens [37]. Furthermore, heavy <lb/>broilers under intensive selection also had higher rates of myodegeneration and diminished <lb/>thermoregulatory capacity, altered cation regulation in muscle cells and more resulting in <lb/>various meat quality defects [32,38]. Why increased growth rates in modern broilers causes <lb/>such myopathies is not known, but some researchers reported that heavier birds have higher <lb/>incidence of severe WB [1,11-13]. Another consequence the WB phenomenon brings about is <lb/>severe economic loss. As breast meat is a widely sought out source of lean meat across the <lb/>nation, changes in the composition and anatomy of the breast translates to degradation of meat <lb/>quality, texture, nutrition and taste, a devastating blow to the domestic poultry industry [9]. <lb/>There have been some reports regarding hereditary muscular dystrophy in domestic fowl <lb/>[39], in which affected birds exhibit a broad shallow body and short thick limb bones [40]. <lb/>Histopathological studies saw wide variations in fiber size, fast deposition, degeneration of the <lb/>muscle fibers and more [41,42]. On top of changes in appearance, tenderness and fat content <lb/>were also influenced [43,44]. Hereditary muscular dystrophy shares histological lesions with <lb/>WB. Hete and Shung [45] observed that the tissue of WB chicken was stiff and had a rubbery <lb/>texture compared to their control lines with flaccid muscles. There have also been approaches <lb/>to studying gene expressions of WB meat. <lb/>Velleman [46] studied gene expressions of WB affected meat and reported that different <lb/>broiler lines in the study possessed different cellular mechanisms. Lack of these nutrients could <lb/>damage cells and retard integral cellular reactions and processes, raising the influence and <lb/>occurrence of harmful pathological conditions. Moreover, increased selection process and <lb/>higher breast yield could be the source behind the various myopathies, according to Petracci et <lb/>al. [32]. This statement was highlighted in Bailey et al. [14] when they observed two different <lb/>lines of broiler chicken and the chicken with higher breast yield showed a greater incidence in <lb/>myopathies than the chicken with lower breast yield. <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <page>11 <lb/></page>

        <body>Challenge regarding WB research is an absence of an effective standardized scoring scale <lb/>since recording and judging WB relies on a subjective scoring system. When scoring, having <lb/>multiple people as opposed to one person reaching a consensus on the severity of WS and WB <lb/>may be more effective until scorers are familiar with the existing or upcoming scoring systems. <lb/>Fast methods to evaluate hardness would also be helpful. There have been some advancements <lb/>in this area, where Tijare et al. [18] described scoring methods with regard to level of hardness <lb/>and location (cranial vs. entire fillet) and Mudalal et al. [19] used texture analysis to determine <lb/>the force required to compress fillets, thus determining the severity of the physical state of <lb/>chicken breasts with WB. <lb/>CONCLUSION <lb/>In this study, WB was found to be measurable with a device and it has a variation, which <lb/>means that chickens would be selected based on the severity of WB. We knew that the severity <lb/>in the symptom of WB (meat) could be scored (quantified) as a phenotype. The next stage of <lb/>the study will score the parameters of breast muscle during the growth of broilers (live birds) <lb/>to assess the exact time or time interval of when WB can be detected and indexed to pinpoint <lb/>the onset of WB in growing broilers. Each individual can be scored based on its severity, and <lb/>the scores will be used to select the chickens to be mated. In sum, a selection study will be <lb/>possible with this proposed study to establish a genetic line to minimize the severity of WB <lb/>while maximizing the growth rate and all other economically important traits using genetic <lb/>(pedigree) information and quantitative genetics (statistical animal breeding) [47]. <lb/></body>

        <div type="acknowledgment">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>This work was supported by the research grant of the Gyeongsang National University in <lb/>2023. <lb/></div>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <page>12 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Kuttappan VA, Brewer VB, Waldroup PW, Owens CM. Influence of growth rate on the <lb/>occurrence of WS in broiler breast fillets. Poult Sci. 2012a;91:2677-85. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3382/ps.2012-02259 <lb/>2. Sihvo HK, Immonen K, Puolanne E. Myodegeneration with fibrosis and regeneration in <lb/>the pectoralis major muscle of broilers. Vet Pathol. 2014;51:619-23. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1177/0300985813497488 <lb/>3. Kuttappan VA, Hargis BM, Owens CM. White striping and woody breast myopathies in <lb/>the modern poultry industry: a review. Poult Sci. 2016;95:2724-33. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3382/ps/pew216 <lb/>4. Radaelli G, Piccirillo A, Birolo M, Bertotto D, Gratta F, Ballarin C, et al. Effect of age on <lb/>the occurrence of muscle fiber degeneration associated with myopathies in broiler <lb/>chickens <lb/>submitted <lb/>to <lb/>feed <lb/>restriction. <lb/>Poult <lb/>Sci. <lb/>2017;96:309-19. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3382/ps/pew270 <lb/>5. Abasht B, Mutryn MF, Michalek RD, Lee WR. Oxidative stress and metabolic <lb/>perturbations in wooden breast disorder in chickens. PLoS One. 2016;11(4):e0153750. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0153750 <lb/>6. Babak MP. Morphological and molecular characterization of wooden breast myopathy in <lb/>commercial broiler chickens. [Ph.D. dissertation]. Newark, DE: University of Delaware; <lb/>2019. <lb/>7. Bunge J. Fast-Growth Chickens Produce New Industry Woe: &apos;Spaghetti Meat&apos; [Internet]. <lb/>Wall Street Journal. 2019. [cited 2023 Jan 14]. https://www.wsj.com/articles/fast-growth-<lb/>chickens-produce-new-industry-woe-spaghetti-meat-11552226401 <lb/>8. Gee K. Bigger Chickens Bring a Tough New Problem: &apos;Woody Breast&apos; [Internet]. Wall <lb/>Street Journal. 2016. [cited 2023 Jan 14]. https://www.wsj.com/articles/bigger-chickens-<lb/>bring-a-tough-new-problem-woody-breast-1459207291 <lb/>9. Soglia F, Mudalal S, Babini E, Di Nunzio M, Mazzoni M, Sirri F, et al. Histology, <lb/>composition, and quality traits of chicken Pectoralis major muscle affected by wooden <lb/>breast abnormality. Poult Sci. 2016;95:651-9. https://doi.org/10.3382/ps/pev353 <lb/>10. Lorenzi M, Mudalal S, Cavani C, Petracci M. Incidence of white striping under <lb/>commercial conditions in medium and heavy broiler chickens in Italy. J Appl Poult Res. <lb/>2014;23:754-8. https://doi.org/10.3382/japr.2014-00968 <lb/></listBibl>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <page>13 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>11. Velleman SG, Clark DL. Histopathologic and myogenic gene expression changes <lb/>associated with wooden breast in broiler breast muscles. Avian Dis. 2015;59:410-8. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1637/11097-042015-Reg.1 <lb/>12. Russo E, Drigo M, Longoni C, Pezzotti R, Fasoli P, Recordati C. Evaluation of white <lb/>striping prevalence and predisposing factors in broilers at slaughter. Poult Sci. <lb/>2015;94:1843-8. https://doi.org/10.3382/ps/pev172 <lb/>13. Trocino A, Piccirillo A, Birolo M, Radaelli G, Bertotto D, Filiou E, et al. Effect of <lb/>genotype, gender and feed restriction on growth, meat quality and the occurrence of white <lb/>striping and wooden breast in broiler chickens. Poult Sci. 2015;94:2996-3004. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3382/ps/pev296 <lb/>14. Bailey RA, Watson KA, Bilgili SF, Avendano S. The genetic basis of pectoralis major <lb/>myopathies in modern broiler chicken lines. Poult Sci. 2015;94:2870-9. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3382/ps/pev304 <lb/>15. Lake JA, Dekkers JCM, Abasht B. Genetic basis and identification of candidate genes for <lb/>wooden breast and white striping in commercial broiler chickens. Sci Rep. 2021;11:6785. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fs41598-021-86176-4 <lb/>16. Weigel KA, VanRaden PM, Norman HD, Grosu H. A 100-Year Review: Methods and <lb/>impact of genetic selection in dairy cattle -From daughter-dam comparisons to deep <lb/>learning <lb/>algorithms. <lb/>J <lb/>Dairy <lb/>Sci. <lb/>2017;100(12):10234-50. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3168/jds.2017-12954 <lb/>17. Bailey RA, Souza E, Avendano S. Characterising the influence of genetics on breast <lb/>muscle <lb/>myopathies <lb/>in <lb/>broiler <lb/>chickens. Front <lb/>Physiol. 2020;11:1-12. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3389/fphys.2020.01041 <lb/>18. Tijare VV, Yang FL, Kuttappan VA, Alvarado CZ, Coon CN, Owens CM. Meat quality <lb/>of broiler breast fillets with white striping and woody breast muscle myophthies. Poult <lb/>Sci. 2016;95:2167-73. https://doi.org/10.3382/ps/pew129 <lb/>19. Mudalal S, Lorenzi M, Soglia F, Cavani C, Petracci M. Implications of white striping and <lb/>wooden breast abnormalities on quality traits of raw and marinated chicken meat. Animal. <lb/>2015;9:728-34. https://doi.org/10.1017/S175173111400295X <lb/>20. Davidson MJ, Bryant AL, Bower WF, Frawley HC. Myotonometry reliably measures <lb/>muscle stiffness in the thenar and perineal muscles. Physiother Can. 2017;69(2):104-12. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3138/ptc.2015-85 <lb/></listBibl>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <page>14 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>21. Garcia-Bernal MI, AM Herdia-Rizo, P Gonzalez-Garcia, MD Cortes-Vega, MJ Casuso-<lb/>Holgado. Validity and reliability of myotonometry for assessing muscle viscoelastic <lb/>properties in patients with stroke: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Sci Rep. <lb/>2021;11(1):1-12. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-021-84656-1 <lb/>22. McGowen JM, Hoppes CW, Forsse JS, Albin SR, Abt J, Koppenhaver SL. Myotonometry <lb/>is capable of reliably obtaining trunk and thigh muscle stiffness measures in military <lb/>cadets <lb/>during <lb/>standing <lb/>and <lb/>squatting <lb/>postures. <lb/>Mil <lb/>Med. <lb/>2023. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/milmed/usad179 <lb/>23. Myoton AS. MyotonPro digital palpation device user manual. Tallinn, Estonia. 2023. <lb/>24. Schneider S, Peipsi A, Stokes M, Knicker A, Abeln V. Feasibility of monitoring muscle <lb/>health in microgravity environments using Myoton technology. Med Biol Eng Comput. <lb/>2015;53:57-66. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11517-014-1211-5 <lb/>25. Dellalana LE, Chen F, Vain A, Gandelman JS, Põldemaa M, Chen H, et al. <lb/>Reproducibility of the durometer and myoton devices for skin stiffness measurement in <lb/>healthy subjects. Skin Res Technol. 2019;25(3):289-93. https://doi.org/10.1111/srt.12646 <lb/>26. Bouton PE, Harris PV, Shorthose WR. The effects of ultimate pH on ovine muscle: <lb/>Mechanical properties. J Food Sci. 1972;37(3):356-60. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-<lb/>2621.1972.tb02636.x <lb/>27. Cavitt LC, Youm GW, Meullenet JF, Owens CM, Xiong R. Prediction of poultry meat <lb/>tenderness using razor blade shear, Allo-Kramer shear, and sarcomere length. J Food Sci. <lb/>2004;69:11-5. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2621.2004.tb17879.x <lb/>28. Abasht B. Metabolic risk factors of wooden breast disease in commercial broiler chickens. <lb/>Plant and Animal Genome XXVII Conference (January 12-16, 2019). 2019. <lb/>29. Oh SH, Oh M, Brown D. Systematic review of the different causes and effects of the <lb/>wooden breast condition in poultry production. 2020 International Poultry Scientific <lb/>Forum, p66. <lb/>30. Kuttappan VA, Lee YS, Erf GF, Meullenet JFC, McKee SR, Owens CM. Consumer <lb/>acceptance of visual appearance of broiler breast meat with varying degrees of WS. Poult <lb/>Sci. 2012b;91:1240-7. https://doi.org/10.3382/ps.2011-01947 <lb/>31. Kuttappan VA, Shivaprasad HL, Shaw DP, Valentine BA, Hargis BM, Clark FD, et al. <lb/>Pathological changes associated with WS in broiler breast muscles. Poult Sci. <lb/>2013;92:331-8. https://doi.org/10.3382/ps.2012-02646 <lb/></listBibl>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <page>15 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>32. Petracci M, Mudalal S, Soglia F, Cavani C. Meat quality in fast-growing broiler chickens. <lb/>Worlds Poult Sci J. 2015;71:363-74. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0043933915000367 <lb/>33. Anthony NB. A review of genetic practices in poultry: Efforts to improve meat quality. J <lb/>Muscle Foods. 1998;9:25-33. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1745-4573.1998.tb00641.x <lb/>34. Julian RJ. Production and growth related disorders and other metabolic diseases of <lb/>poultry-A review. Vet J. 2005;169:350-69. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tvjl.2004.04.015 <lb/>35. Hoving-Bolink AH, Kranen RW, Klont RE, Gerritsen CLM, de Greef KH. Fibre area and <lb/>capillary supply in broiler breast muscle in relation to productivity and ascites. Meat Sci. <lb/>2000;56:397-402. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0309-1740(00)00071-1 <lb/>36. Macrae VE, Mahon M, Gilpin S, Sandercock DA, Mitchell MA. Skeletal muscle fibre <lb/>growth and growth associated myopathy in the domestic chicken (Gallus domesticus). Br <lb/>Poult Sci. 2006;47:264-72. https://doi.org/10.1080/00071660600753615 <lb/>37. Velleman SG, Nestor KE. Effect of selection for growth rate on myosin heavy chain <lb/>temporal and spatial localization during turkey breast muscle development. Poult Sci. <lb/>2003;82:1373-7. https://doi.org/10.1093/ps/82.9.1373 <lb/>38. Mazzoni M, Petracci M, Meluzzi A, Cavani C, Clavenzani P, Sirri F. Relationship <lb/>between pectoralis major muscle histology and quality traits of chicken meat. Poult Sci. <lb/>2015;94:123-30. https://doi.org/10.3382/ps/peu043 <lb/>39. Julian L, Asmundson V. Muscular dystrophy of the chicken. Muscular Dystrophy in Man <lb/>and Animals. 1963;458-98. <lb/>40. Wilson BW, Randall WR, Patterson GT, Entrikin RK. Major physiologic and <lb/>histochemical characteristics of inherited dystrophy of the chicken. Ann N Y Acad Sci. <lb/>1979;317:224-46. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1749-6632.1979.tb56531.x <lb/>41. Jordan JP, Kratzer FH, Johnson AM, Freeman RL. Fat deposition in musculature of the <lb/>genetically <lb/>dystrophic <lb/>chicken. <lb/>Exp <lb/>Biol <lb/>Med. <lb/>1959;101:449-51. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3181/00379727-101-24975 <lb/>42. McMurtry SL, Julian LM, Asmundson VS. Hereditary muscular dystrophy of the chicken. <lb/>Quantitative histopathological findings of the Pectoralis at 6 weeks of age. Arch Pathol. <lb/>1972;94:217-224. <lb/>43. Scholtyssek S, Bele LM, Sayre RN, Klose AA, Peterson DW. Tenderness of dystrophic <lb/></listBibl>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <page>16 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>chicken meat. Poult Sci. 1967;46:1050-3. <lb/>44. Hete B, Shung KK. Using RF ultrasound to monitor the progression of muscular <lb/>dystrophy through passive stretching. Ultrasonics Symposium, Proceedings. Institute of <lb/>Electrical and Electronics Engineers. 1991;2:1123-6. <lb/>45. Peterson DW, Lilyblade AL. Relative differences in tenderness of breast muscle in normal <lb/>and two dystrophic mutant strains of chickens. J Food Sci. 1969;34:142-5. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2621.1969.tb00905.x <lb/>46. Velleman SG. Relationship of skeletal muscle development and growth to breast muscle <lb/>myopathies: A review. Avian Dis. 2015;59:525-31. https://doi.org/10.1637/11223-<lb/>063015-Review.1 <lb/>47. Cho E, Kim M, Kim JH, Roh HJ, Kim SC, Jin DH, et al. Application of genomic big data <lb/>to analyze the genetic diversity and population structure of Korean domestic chickens. J <lb/>Anim Sci Technol. 2023;65(5):912-21. https://doi.org/10.5187/jast.2023.e8 <lb/></listBibl>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <page>17 <lb/></page>

        <body>Table 1. Significance of factors included in the statistical model. <lb/>394 <lb/>Test <lb/>Breast Type <lb/>Interaction <lb/>pH <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>NS <lb/>Cooking Yield <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>Water Loss <lb/>NS <lb/>** <lb/>NS <lb/>Raw L * <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>NS <lb/>Raw a * <lb/>NS <lb/>** <lb/>NS <lb/>Raw b * <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>Cooked L <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>Cooked a <lb/>* <lb/>** <lb/>NS <lb/>Cooked b <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>NS <lb/>Firmness <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>Work Penetration <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>Shear Force <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>Shear Energy <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>Muscle tone <lb/>** <lb/>NS <lb/>NS <lb/>Stiffness <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>NS <lb/>Elasticity <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>NS <lb/>Relaxation <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>NS <lb/>Creep <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>NS <lb/>** p &lt; 0.01; * p &lt; 0.05; NS: Not Significant <lb/>395 <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <page>18 <lb/></page>

        <body>Table 2. Least square means of physical, physicochemical, and functional characteristics. <lb/>Test 1 <lb/>Test 2 <lb/>Test 3 <lb/>Normal <lb/>Wooden <lb/>Normal <lb/>Wooden <lb/>Normal <lb/>Wooden <lb/>pH <lb/>6.00±0.02 a (30) <lb/>6.12±0.01 b (33) <lb/>5.79±0.01 a (35) <lb/>5.96±0.01 b (34) <lb/>5.76±0.01 a (33) <lb/>5.92±0.01 b (31) <lb/>Cooking Yield (%) <lb/>73.5±0.46 a (31) <lb/>60.2±0.43 b (35) <lb/>72.3±0.45 a (33) <lb/>66.7±0.44 b (34) <lb/>69.9±0.44 a (34) <lb/>59.5±0.43 b (35) <lb/>Water Loss (%) <lb/>9.22±0.46 a (35) <lb/>11.8±0.46 b (35) <lb/>9.95±0.46 a (35) <lb/>11.7±0.48 b (32) <lb/>9.57±0.46 a (35) <lb/>11.9±0.47 b (33) <lb/>Raw L * <lb/>63.3±0.38 a (35) <lb/>66.2±0.38 b (34) <lb/>61.9±0.38 a (35) <lb/>65.9±0.38 b (34) <lb/>61.4±0.39 a (33) <lb/>64.6±0.38 b (35) <lb/>Raw a * <lb/>0.73±0.14 a (34) <lb/>1.56±0.14 b (33) <lb/>0.89±0.14 a (34) <lb/>1.35±0.13 b (35) <lb/>0.55±0.14 a (31) <lb/>1.67±0.13 b (35) <lb/>Raw b * <lb/>6.96±0.32 a (35) <lb/>9.74±0.33 b (33) <lb/>8.90±0.32 a (35) <lb/>9.65±0.36 a (27) <lb/>9.05±0.33 a (33) <lb/>10.4±0.32 b (34) <lb/>Cooked L * <lb/>83.1±0.34 a (33) <lb/>76.4±0.34 b (34) <lb/>83.1±0.34 a (33) <lb/>78.4±0.33 b (35) <lb/>82.7±0.34 a (33) <lb/>75.5±0.34 b (34) <lb/>Cooked a * <lb/>0.75±0.09 a (30) <lb/>1.98±0.09 b (33) <lb/>0.71±0.09 a (34) <lb/>1.93±0.09 b (34) <lb/>1.09±0.09 a (35) <lb/>1.97±0.09 b (34) <lb/>Cooked b * <lb/>14.9±0.18 a (31) <lb/>15.8±0.19 b (30) <lb/>15.5±0.18 a (33) <lb/>16.2±0.18 b (33) <lb/>15.6±0.17 a (35) <lb/>16.0±0.18 a (32) <lb/>Firmness (N) <lb/>14.9±1.27 a (35) <lb/>33.6±1.29 b (34) <lb/>14.3±1.27 a (35) <lb/>37.5±1.27 b (35) <lb/>14.7±1.27 a (35) <lb/>46.2±1.27 b (35) <lb/>Work Penetration (N*sec) <lb/>47.0±3.58 a (34) <lb/>103±3.69 b (32) <lb/>46.5±3.69 a (32) <lb/>118±3.69 b (32) <lb/>50.0±3.53 a (35) <lb/>151±3.53 b (35) <lb/>Shear Force (N) <lb/>10.9±0.39 a (29) <lb/>12.6±0.37 b (33) <lb/>10.8±0.37 a (33) <lb/>12.3±0.36 b (35) <lb/>10.8±0.37 a (33) <lb/>15.8±0.37 b (33) <lb/>Shear Energy (N*mm) <lb/>15.1±0.56 a (31) <lb/>18.7±0.53 b (34) <lb/>14.5±0.53 a (35) <lb/>17.1±0.53 b (35) <lb/>14.3±0.57 a (30) <lb/>23.8±0.54 b (33) <lb/>Muscle tone (Hz) <lb/>25.1±0.21 a (33) <lb/>24.9±0.22 a (31) <lb/>26.1±0.21 a (34) <lb/>25.5±0.21 a (34) <lb/>25.8±0.21 a (34) <lb/>26.0±0.22 a (30) <lb/>Stiffness (N/m) <lb/>508±7.03 a (33) <lb/>575±6.92 b (34) <lb/>546±6.92 a (34) <lb/>602±6.92 b (34) <lb/>546±6.83 a (35) <lb/>612±6.92 b (34) <lb/>Elasticity <lb/>1.66±0.02 a (35) <lb/>1.45±0.02 b (31) <lb/>1.56±0.02 a (31) <lb/>1.32±0.02 b (35) <lb/>1.52±0.02 a (34) <lb/>1.33±0.02 b (34) <lb/>Relaxation (ms) <lb/>9.87±0.12 a (32) <lb/>9.13±0.11 b (34) <lb/>9.12±0.11 a (34) <lb/>8.65±0.11 b (33) <lb/>9.26±0.11 a (35) <lb/>8.50±0.12 b (32) <lb/>Creep <lb/>0.64±0.01 a (33) <lb/>0.60±0.01 b (34) <lb/>0.59±0.01 a (34) <lb/>0.58±0.01 a (35) <lb/>0.60±0.01 a (35) <lb/>0.57±0.01 b (31) <lb/>* Subscripts represent the comparative results of the breast condition within each test. Different letters indicate significant differences <lb/>(p&lt;0.05). <lb/>** The numbers in parentheses represent the sample size. <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <page>19 <lb/></page>

        <body>Table 3. Pearson correlations among parameters studied. <lb/>401 <lb/>(2) <lb/>(3) <lb/>(4) <lb/>(5) <lb/>(6) <lb/>(7) <lb/>(8) <lb/>(9) <lb/>(10) <lb/>(11) <lb/>(12) <lb/>(13) <lb/>(14) <lb/>(15) <lb/>(16) <lb/>(17) <lb/>(18) (19) 1 <lb/>(1) WB Score <lb/>0.48 <lb/>-0.77 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>0.52 <lb/>0.39 <lb/>0.36 <lb/>-0.74 <lb/>0.68 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>0.77 <lb/>0.77 <lb/>0.51 <lb/>0.59 <lb/>-0.07 * 0.56 <lb/>-0.61 -0.38 <lb/>-0.30 <lb/>(2) pH <lb/>-0.44 <lb/>0.08 * <lb/>0.48 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>-0.06 * -0.48 <lb/>0.38 <lb/>0.07 * <lb/>0.37 <lb/>0.34 <lb/>0.17 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>-0.29 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>-0.15 0.00 * <lb/>0.05 * <lb/>(3) Cooking Yield <lb/>-0.34 -0.45 <lb/>-0.45 <lb/>-0.40 <lb/>0.87 <lb/>-0.70 -0.24 <lb/>-0.78 <lb/>-0.76 -0.60 <lb/>-0.69 0.02 * <lb/>-0.56 <lb/>0.58 <lb/>0.40 <lb/>0.34 <lb/>(4) Water Loss <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.17 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>-0.33 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>0.10 * <lb/>0.32 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>0.08 * <lb/>0.14 -0.13 * <lb/>0.16 <lb/>-0.33 -0.09 * -0.09 * <lb/>(5) Raw L * <lb/>0.08 * <lb/>0.40 <lb/>-0.43 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>0.42 <lb/>0.44 <lb/>0.10 * <lb/>0.14 <lb/>-0.39 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>-0.41 0.04 * <lb/>0.09 * <lb/>(6) Raw a * <lb/>0.20 <lb/>-0.59 <lb/>0.53 <lb/>-0.04 * 0.41 <lb/>0.39 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>0.41 <lb/>0.05 * <lb/>0.28 <lb/>-0.25 -0.23 <lb/>-0.22 <lb/>(7) Raw b * <lb/>-0.38 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.47 <lb/>0.33 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.17 -0.12 * <lb/>0.26 <lb/>-0.42 -0.15 -0.10 * <lb/>(8) Cooked L * <lb/>-0.81 -0.37 <lb/>-0.76 <lb/>-0.75 -0.60 <lb/>-0.68 -0.02 * -0.59 <lb/>0.56 <lb/>0.42 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>(9) Cooked a * <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.67 <lb/>0.63 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.54 <lb/>0.02 * <lb/>0.53 <lb/>-0.50 -0.37 <lb/>-0.31 <lb/>(10) Cooked b * <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>0.08 * <lb/>0.10 * -0.00 * <lb/>0.25 <lb/>-0.27 -0.15 -0.12 * <lb/>(11) Firmness <lb/>0.99 <lb/>0.61 <lb/>0.67 <lb/>0.11 * <lb/>0.66 <lb/>-0.67 -0.51 <lb/>-0.45 <lb/>(12) Work Penetration <lb/>0.59 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>0.10 * <lb/>0.67 <lb/>-0.70 -0.51 <lb/>-0.44 <lb/>(13) Shear Force <lb/>0.96 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>0.49 <lb/>-0.30 -0.40 <lb/>-0.36 <lb/>(14) Shear Energy <lb/>0.24 <lb/>0.52 <lb/>-0.32 -0.44 <lb/>-0.39 <lb/>(15) Muscle tone <lb/>0.65 <lb/>-0.12 * -0.79 <lb/>-0.81 <lb/>(16) Stiffness <lb/>-0.69 -0.97 <lb/>-0.95 <lb/>(17) Elasticity <lb/>0.56 <lb/>0.52 <lb/>(18) Relaxation <lb/>0.99 <lb/>1 (19) Creep <lb/>402 <lb/>* The correlation coefficients are not significantly different from zero (p &gt; 0.05). <lb/>403 <lb/>WB: Woody Breast <lb/>404 <lb/>405 <lb/>406 <lb/>407 <lb/>408 <lb/>409 <lb/>410 <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D


	</text>

</TEI>