<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Empirical: Single or Multiple Studies <lb/>Exploring Public Support for Farmed Animal Welfare <lb/>Policy and Advocacy Across 23 Countries <lb/>Christopher Bryant 1 , Christopher J. Hopwood 2 , João Graça 3,4 , <lb/>Adam T. Nissen 5 , Courtney Dillard 6 , Andie Thompkins 6 <lb/>[1] Department of Psychology, University of Bath, Bath, United Kingdom. [2] Department of Psychology, University of <lb/>Zurich, Zürich, Switzerland. [3] University of Groningen, Groningen, the Netherlands. [4] Instituto de Ciências Sociais, <lb/>Universidade de Lisboa, Lisbon, Portugal. [5] Department of Psychology, University of California, Davis, CA, USA. <lb/>[6] Mercy For Animals, Los Angeles, CA, USA. <lb/>Psychology of Human-Animal Intergroup Relations, 2024, Vol. 3, Article e10337, https://doi.org/10.5964/phair.10337 <lb/>Received: 2022-09-23 • Accepted: 2023-08-17 • Published (VoR): 2024-03-19 <lb/>Handling Editor: Catherine Amiot, Université du Québec à Montréal, Quebec, Canada <lb/>Corresponding Author: Christopher Bryant, 10 West, Department of Psychology, University of Bath, Claverton <lb/>Down, Bath, BA2 7AY, United Kingdom. E-mail: C.J.Bryant@bath.ac.uk <lb/>Supplementary Materials: Code, Data, Materials, Preregistration [see Index of <lb/>Supplementary Materials] <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Farmed animal policy and advocacy efforts both attempt to generate and depend upon public <lb/>support. However, relatively little is known about the factors that predict support for animal <lb/>protection legislation and advocacy across the globe. We analyse data from a large international <lb/>survey (23 countries, n = 20,966) alongside other data sources on animal advocacy to investigate <lb/>knowledge of factory farming, the connection between attitudes towards animals and the strength <lb/>of animal protection legislation, attitudes towards animals based on their food status in different <lb/>countries, and the connection between personal support for policy, animal advocacy, civic activism, <lb/>and animal advocacy organisations. We found that higher support for animal welfare is associated <lb/>with stronger farm animal protection legislation across countries and that concerns about specific <lb/>animals can vary depending on cultural and religious factors. Contrary to study hypotheses, we did <lb/>not find greater support for advocacy in countries with more advocacy organisations, suggesting <lb/>important opportunities to pursue advocacy in relatively neglected regions. Results are interpreted <lb/>in terms of how farmed animal advocates can take advantage of and potentially generate support <lb/>for animal welfare throughout the world. <lb/>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons <lb/>Attribution 4.0 International License, CC BY 4.0, which permits unrestricted use, <lb/>distribution, and reproduction, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/>Keywords <lb/>attitudes, cross-country comparisons, animal welfare, legislation, policy, farmed animals <lb/></front>

			<body>Intensive animal agriculture is linked to a range of environmental and public health <lb/>issues, including climate change, deforestation, antibiotic resistance, and pandemic po <lb/>tential, as well as significant cruelty to animals (Amiot &amp; Bastian, 2015; Anomaly, 2015; <lb/>Godfray et al., 2018). Animal advocacy organizations are committed to increasing aware <lb/>ness of these issues to increase support for animal welfare. Because cultures vary in <lb/>patterns of animal agriculture, the importance they attribute to animal welfare in general <lb/>(Cembalo et al., 2016), and which animals tend to be the focus of these welfare concerns <lb/>(e.g., Li et al., 2017), the most effective approaches to animal advocacy depends in part on <lb/>contextual factors involving culture, norms, geography, and economics. <lb/>Varying attitudes and practices with regard to animal consumption across countries <lb/>or cultures are likely related to varying levels of knowledge, concern, and support for <lb/>animal welfare among citizens. This variation may in turn be related to institutional <lb/>and legislative protection of animals. The general goal of this study is to examine how <lb/>countries differ in their attitudes about farmed animal welfare, and what implications <lb/>such differences may have for broader social policy and advocacy. We tested several <lb/>possible connections between culture-based attitudes and support for farmed animal <lb/>welfare. <lb/>First, if we assume that social policies tend to both shape and reflect the public&apos;s <lb/>values (Oreg &amp; Katz-Gerro, 2006), then public support for farmed/aquatic animal welfare <lb/>should be higher in countries with more progressive government policies on farmed <lb/>animal welfare (World Animal Protection, 2020). This finding would establish a basic <lb/>premise in animal advocacy regarding the connection between public attitudes and <lb/>institutional policies. <lb/>Second, we expect that the public&apos;s attitudes towards certain animal species will vary <lb/>depending on their food status within that country. Previous research has shown that <lb/>people show less concern towards animals that are categorised as food compared to ani <lb/>mals categorised as non-food (Krings et al., 2021). However, animal consumption practi <lb/>ces vary across cultures: for example, whereas goat meat is commonly consumed across <lb/>Asia and South America, it is rarer in North America and northern Europe (Mandolesi <lb/>et al., 2020). Pig meat, while common across Europe and America, is less common in <lb/>some Asian countries, particularly those in which Islam is a dominant religion (Ritchie <lb/>&amp; Roser, 2017). Likewise, cow meat is less common in India because many Indians are <lb/>Hindu, and cows are considered sacred and thus not eaten in Hinduism (Sarkar &amp; Sarkar, <lb/>2016). Therefore, there is considerable cultural variation in the animals regarded as food. <lb/>Given that eating animals is associated with higher cognitive dissonance (Loughnan et <lb/>al., 2010), people in countries where an animal is not categorised as food may tend <lb/>to show greater feeling of connection to that particular animal. At the same time, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">International Animal Welfare Support <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>Psychology of Human-Animal Intergroup Relations <lb/>2024, Vol. 3, Article e10337 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5964/phair.10337 <lb/></front>

			<body>culture-based reasons for avoiding eating certain animals may also be important. For <lb/>example, cow meat is generally shunned in Hinduism, which regards cows as sacred. In <lb/>contrast, pig meat is forbidden in Islam because it is regarded as impure. While both <lb/>religions restrict the consumption of certain animals, the underlying basis for doing <lb/>so is very different, and thus it is possible that their adherents regard those animals <lb/>very differently. Specifically, Hindus would be expected to show an increased feeling of <lb/>personal connection to cows whereas Muslims would tend to show a decreased feeling of <lb/>personal connection to pigs. Understanding how cultural and religious values are linked <lb/>with attitudes about specific animals could help advocates tailor their efforts to certain <lb/>species in certain regions where advocacy efforts may be most effective. <lb/>Third, we expect that consumers generally underestimate the extent of factory <lb/>farming, given that this information is typically not made readily available, and that <lb/>consumers are generally motivated to minimize the harm they view themselves as tak <lb/>ing part in (Bastian &amp; Loughnan, 2017). For example, the Sentience Institute reported <lb/>that the majority of Americans believe most farmed animals are treated well before <lb/>slaughter (Reese-Anthis, 2017). Similarly, research suggests that rates of farmed animals <lb/>living on large factory farms may be underestimated throughout the world (Anthis &amp; <lb/>Reese-Anthis, 2019). Greater knowledge of the rates and practices of large factory farms <lb/>could be important for redressing these perceptions and potentially encouraging support <lb/>for animal welfare (Sparkman et al., 2022). It is thus important to know whether and in <lb/>which countries consumers underestimate these rates and practices. <lb/>Fourth, we might expect higher levels of animal advocacy in more activist countries <lb/>with more support for animal welfare. If we assume that animal advocacy organizations <lb/>increase awareness of animal issues, and are dependent on the financial support of the <lb/>public, we would expect greater support for animal welfare in countries with more such <lb/>organisations. Likewise, it is likely that people are more willing to engage in activism on <lb/>behalf of animals in countries where there is a high level of overall civic engagement. <lb/>It is established that people with higher solidarity with animals at an individual level <lb/>are more likely to intend to help animals, even where this means withdrawing human <lb/>privileges (Amiot et al., 2020). However, it is less clear how such individual differences <lb/>measures relate to commitment toward animals across different countries. We expected <lb/>that support for, and personal commitment to, animal advocacy would be positively <lb/>correlated with civic engagement in general and with the number of animal advocacy <lb/>organizations observed within a country in particular. <lb/>Although many of these expectations are consistent with previous research on indi <lb/>vidual differences in attitudes towards animals (Amiot et al., 2020, Heise &amp; Theuvsen, <lb/>2017), relatively little research has been done in large international studies to examine <lb/>how culture and region shape attitudes about animal welfare (Randler et al., 2021). More <lb/>over, attitudes about animal welfare may change quickly (Dhont et al., 2019; Grassian, <lb/>2020), and both researchers and animal welfare advocates benefit from regular updates <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bryant, Hopwood, Graça et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<front>Psychology of Human-Animal Intergroup Relations <lb/>2024, Vol. 3, Article e10337 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5964/phair.10337 <lb/></front>

			<body>about patterns during particular windows in time. By collecting relatively large and dem <lb/>ographically diverse countries from four continents, this study can provide a relatively <lb/>comprehensive and current snapshot of cross-cultural trends in the factors that shape <lb/>support for animal welfare. This study sought to test the following specific hypotheses: <lb/>• H1a: People will have higher support for farmed animal welfare in countries with <lb/>stronger animal welfare legislation (according to the Animal Protection Index; World <lb/>Animal Protection, 2020). <lb/>• H1b: People will have higher support for aquatic animal welfare in countries with <lb/>stronger animal welfare legislation (according to the Animal Protection Index; World <lb/>Animal Protection, 2020). <lb/>• H2a: The feeling of personal connection to goats will be significantly higher in non-<lb/>goat-eating countries (Brazil, Canada, Chile, Colombia, Germany, Indonesia, Korea, <lb/>Malaysia, Mexico, Poland, Russia, Singapore, Spain, Thailand, USA) compared to goat-<lb/>eating countries (Argentina, China, India, Mexico, Singapore, Russia, Spain, France, <lb/>Netherlands, UK). <lb/>• H2b: The feelings of personal connection to pigs will be significantly higher in non-<lb/>pig-eating countries (India, Singapore) compared to pig-eating countries (Canada, <lb/>France, Germany, Netherlands, UK, USA, Argentina, Brazil, Chile, China, Colombia, <lb/>Italy, Indonesia, Japan, Korea, Malaysia, Mexico, Poland, Russia, Spain, Thailand). <lb/>• H2c: The feelings of personal connection to cows will be significantly higher in a non-<lb/>cow-eating country (India) compared to cow-eating countries (Canada, France, <lb/>Germany, Netherlands, UK, USA, Argentina, Brazil, Chile, China, Colombia, Indonesia, <lb/>Italy, Japan, Korea, Malaysia, Mexico, Poland, Russia, Singapore, Spain, Thailand). <lb/>• H2d: The feelings of personal connection to pigs will be significantly lower among <lb/>Muslims compared to non-Muslims in countries with high Muslim populations <lb/>(Indonesia, Malaysia). <lb/>• H2e: The feelings of personal connection to cows will be significantly higher among <lb/>Hindus compared to non-Hindus in a country with a high Hindu population (India). <lb/>• H3: People&apos;s knowledge of farm conditions will tend to represent an underestimate <lb/>of factory farming within their own country, such that the majority (more than half) of <lb/>survey estimate percentages are lower than the actual percentages for the given <lb/>country (as estimated by Sentience Institute; Anthis &amp; Reese-Anthis, 2019). <lb/>• H4a: There will be higher support for animal advocacy in countries with more <lb/>animal advocacy organizations per capita (according to the World Animal Net <lb/>Directory; World Animal Net, 2017). <lb/>• H4b: There will be higher personal commitment to animal advocacy in countries <lb/>with higher levels of civic activism (according to the Civic Activism Index; <lb/>International Institute of Social Studies, 2020). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">International Animal Welfare Support <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<front>Psychology of Human-Animal Intergroup Relations <lb/>2024, Vol. 3, Article e10337 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5964/phair.10337 <lb/></front>

			<body>Method <lb/>To investigate these hypotheses, we used data from the animal rights organization Mercy <lb/>For Animals&apos; 2021 Multinational Survey which examined individuals in 23 countries <lb/>around the world. The Codebook describing the overall study and its measures can be <lb/>found at Hopwood et al. (2023). <lb/>Participants <lb/>Participants from 23 countries (Table 1) were recruited using a stratified sampling ap <lb/>proach created by the survey platform Cint, such that participants from each country <lb/>were representative of the nation in terms of gender, age groups, and other indicators <lb/>per the standard Cint algorithm. Participants gave their consent to take part in the study <lb/>using a checkbox in the online survey, and were paid according to the Cint incentive <lb/>scheme as described at https://www.cint.com/esomar28. Recruitment was set to 1000 <lb/>participants per country. Once this quota was met, the study team went through the <lb/>responses to remove any incomplete responses as mentioned above. Once incomplete <lb/>responses were counted, the survey was reopened to reach 1000 responses per country. <lb/>This was done two times during the data collection period. One final assessment was <lb/>done at the end of the study to remove any incomplete surveys that may have been <lb/>missed as the study team felt they would not be able to get any more complete responses. <lb/>Only complete responses were recorded and compensated. Participants who did not <lb/>complete 100% of the survey, failed an attention check item (i.e., not selecting the option <lb/>&apos;apple&apos; after being instructed to do so), or provided nonsense responses to two open-text <lb/>questions (e.g., single word responses, reusing the same response, blank responses) <lb/>were considered incomplete and removed. This led to an initial overall sample size of <lb/>28,229 participants to account for incomplete surveys. Using our data quality checking <lb/>procedures mentioned above resulted in a usable sample of 20,966 participants from the <lb/>larger project. For the purpose of this study, we additionally removed participants who <lb/>identified as non-binary or another gender outside male or female as sample sizes were <lb/>low (Total n = 164). The final sample size of this study was 20,802 participants. The <lb/>country samples for this study ranged from 553-987. We only used these participants <lb/>for our analyses. Table 1 includes the demographic breakdown for each country and the <lb/>overall final sample. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bryant, Hopwood, Graça et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Psychology of Human-Animal Intergroup Relations <lb/>2024, Vol. 3, Article e10337 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5964/phair.10337 <lb/></note>

			<body>Materials <lb/>This paper focuses on participants&apos; knowledge and support for farmed animal welfare. <lb/>The specific question wording and answer options are shown in Table 2, as are data from <lb/>several external sources. <lb/>Table 1 <lb/>Country-Level Demographics <lb/>Country <lb/>N <lb/>Mean age (SD) <lb/>% Female <lb/>Mean years of education (SD) <lb/>Argentina <lb/>924 <lb/>41.60 (14.61) <lb/>50.00 <lb/>13.76 (5.78) <lb/>Brazil <lb/>983 <lb/>39.36 (13.55) <lb/>50.86 <lb/>14.19 (5.85) <lb/>Canada <lb/>867 <lb/>45.92 (16.28) <lb/>52.94 <lb/>12.59 (5.46) <lb/>Chile <lb/>932 <lb/>41.50 (14.80) <lb/>50.75 <lb/>11.83 (5.96) <lb/>China <lb/>884 <lb/>39.13 (12.40) <lb/>50.57 <lb/>15.35 (3.19) <lb/>Colombia <lb/>975 <lb/>36.64 (11.78) <lb/>52.21 <lb/>13.41 (5.11) <lb/>France <lb/>909 <lb/>47.48 (15.07) <lb/>53.03 <lb/>11.64 (6.29) <lb/>Germany <lb/>968 <lb/>47.44 (15.21) <lb/>52.38 <lb/>11.73 (2.49) <lb/>India <lb/>894 <lb/>36.53 (12.95) <lb/>44.18 <lb/>15.55 (6.00) <lb/>Indonesia <lb/>987 <lb/>36.68 (12.28) <lb/>49.04 <lb/>13.78 (4.33) <lb/>Italy <lb/>947 <lb/>47.21 (14.64) <lb/>51.00 <lb/>14.27 (4.77) <lb/>Japan <lb/>553 <lb/>51.14 (15.84) <lb/>50.45 <lb/>14.33 (2.99) <lb/>Korea <lb/>917 <lb/>41.79 (13.96) <lb/>49.95 <lb/>15.38 (9.92) <lb/>Malaysia <lb/>932 <lb/>38.49 (13.22) <lb/>48.28 <lb/>13.87 (5.73) <lb/>Mexico <lb/>973 <lb/>38.31 (13.48) <lb/>51.39 <lb/>15.13 (5.06) <lb/>Netherlands <lb/>903 <lb/>47.80 (16.10) <lb/>52.05 <lb/>9.55 (5.85) <lb/>Poland <lb/>962 <lb/>43.99 (15.04) <lb/>52.29 <lb/>15.17 (4.25) <lb/>Russia <lb/>959 <lb/>40.43 (13.39) <lb/>53.49 <lb/>11.03 (4.82) <lb/>Singapore <lb/>730 <lb/>42.34 (13.87) <lb/>53.15 <lb/>15.08 (4.08) <lb/>Spain <lb/>971 <lb/>44.84 (14.46) <lb/>49.12 <lb/>14.22 (6.08) <lb/>Thailand <lb/>942 <lb/>40.07 (14.67) <lb/>51.06 <lb/>16.43 (8.66) <lb/>United Kingdom <lb/>828 <lb/>46.95 (15.95) <lb/>49.15 <lb/>13.85 (4.57) <lb/>United States <lb/>862 <lb/>46.37 (16.69) <lb/>51.39 <lb/>13.01 (4.59) <lb/>Overall <lb/>20,802 <lb/>42.48 (14.92) <lb/>50.81 <lb/>13.68 (5.81) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">International Animal Welfare Support <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Psychology of Human-Animal Intergroup Relations <lb/>2024, Vol. 3, Article e10337 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5964/phair.10337 <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 2 <lb/>Survey and External Measures <lb/>Hypothesis <lb/>Measure <lb/>Items/Description <lb/>Scale <lb/>Alpha <lb/>Survey measures <lb/>H1a <lb/>Support for farmed animal welfare <lb/>(mean of 4 items). Adapted from <lb/>Vanhonacker et al. (2008). <lb/>1. <lb/>Corporations should commit to treating farm <lb/>animals well. <lb/>2. <lb/>My government should pass laws to ensure that <lb/>farm animals are treated well. <lb/>3. <lb/>My government should pass laws to ensure that <lb/>farm animals&apos; needs are met. <lb/>4. <lb/>Corporations should commit to ensuring that <lb/>farm animals&apos; needs are met. <lb/>Strongly disagree (1) -<lb/>Strongly agree (7) <lb/>.93 <lb/>H1b <lb/>Support for aquatic animal welfare <lb/>(mean of 4 items). Adapted from <lb/>Vanhonacker et al. (2008). <lb/>1. <lb/>Corporations should commit to treating farmed <lb/>aquatic animals well. <lb/>2. <lb/>My government should pass laws to ensure that <lb/>farmed aquatic animals are treated well. <lb/>3. <lb/>My government should pass laws to ensure that <lb/>farmed aquatic animals&apos; needs are met. <lb/>4. <lb/>Corporations should commit to ensuring that <lb/>farmed aquatic animals&apos; needs are met. <lb/>Strongly disagree (1) -<lb/>Strongly agree (7) <lb/>.94 <lb/>H2a, H2b, H2c, <lb/>H2d, H2e <lb/>Feeling of personal connection to <lb/>animals (individual scores for 6 animals). <lb/>Which statement best describes how you feel about <lb/>farm animals? <lb/>1. Cows <lb/>1. Pigs <lb/>1. Goats <lb/>1. Chickens <lb/>1. Fish <lb/>1. Other farmed aquatic animals <lb/>No personal connection at <lb/>all (1) -Strong personal <lb/>connection (7) <lb/>-<lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Bryant, Hopwood, Graça et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Psychology of Human-Animal Intergroup Relations <lb/>2024, Vol. 3, Article e10337 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5964/phair.10337 <lb/></note>

			<body>Hypothesis <lb/>Measure <lb/>Items/Description <lb/>Scale <lb/>Alpha <lb/>H3 <lb/>Survey estimate of factory farming <lb/>(percentage). <lb/>1. <lb/>In industrialized farms, a large number of animals <lb/>are kept indoors in conditions intended to <lb/>maximize production at a minimal cost. What <lb/>percentage of farm animals do you think are <lb/>raised in large industrialized farms in your <lb/>country? <lb/>0%, 10%, 20%, … 100% <lb/>-<lb/>H4a <lb/>Support for animal advocacy (single <lb/>item). <lb/>1. <lb/>If you learned that an organization working to <lb/>protect farm animals and encouraging people to <lb/>eat food from plant sources started in your <lb/>country, how favorable would you be towards <lb/>their work? <lb/>Very unfavorable (1) -Very <lb/>favorable (7) <lb/>-<lb/>H4b <lb/>Personal commitment to animal <lb/>advocacy (mean of 6 items). <lb/>How likely are you to engage in each of the following <lb/>forms of animal advocacy? <lb/>1. <lb/>Volunteer. <lb/>2. <lb/>Donate money. <lb/>3. <lb/>Like or follow on social media. <lb/>4. <lb/>Share content with friends via social media. <lb/>5. <lb/>Sign a petition urging a corporation or the <lb/>government to better care for farm animals. <lb/>6. <lb/>Participate in a peaceful protest to <lb/>encourage better care for farm animals. <lb/>Very unlikely (1) -Very <lb/>likely (7) <lb/>.93 <lb/>Control variables included in analyses <lb/>All <lb/>Age <lb/>In what year were you born? (converted to years) <lb/>18 -110 <lb/>-<lb/>All <lb/>Gender <lb/>What is your gender? <lb/>Male (0), Female (1) <lb/>-<lb/>All <lb/>Education <lb/>How many years of education have you completed? <lb/>0 -50 <lb/>-<lb/>External measures included from other sources <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">International Animal Welfare Support <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Psychology of Human-Animal Intergroup Relations <lb/>2024, Vol. 3, Article e10337 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5964/phair.10337 <lb/></note>

			<body>Hypothesis <lb/>Measure <lb/>Items/Description <lb/>Scale <lb/>Alpha <lb/>H1a, H1b <lb/>Strength of farmed animal welfare <lb/>legislation (World Animal Protection, <lb/>2020). <lb/>A &apos;grade&apos; given by World Animal Protection based on <lb/>an assessment of existing animal protection legislation <lb/>in 50 countries. <lb/>Specifically, Indicator 3 relates to laws <lb/>applying to animals used in farming. <lb/>A grade (1) -G grade (7) <lb/>-<lb/>H2a, H2b, H2c <lb/>Animal-eating or non-eating countries <lb/>(Ritchie &amp; Roser, 2017). <lb/>A country is determined as &apos;non-eating&apos; if their annual <lb/>per capita consumption of the animal is less than 1kg <lb/>or less than 1% of all meat consumed according to Our <lb/>World in Data. <lb/>Eating (1), Non-eating (0) <lb/>-<lb/>H3 <lb/>Actual estimates of caged hens (Anthis &amp; <lb/>Reese-Anthis, 2019). <lb/>Estimates by Sentience Institute of the proportion of <lb/>egg-laying hens living in cages in 35 countries. While <lb/>this is an imperfect representation of all farmed <lb/>animals, poultry make up the vast majority of farmed <lb/>land animals, so it is likely a reasonable proxy. <lb/>0% -100% <lb/>-<lb/>H4a <lb/>Animal organizations per capita (World <lb/>Animal Net, 2017). <lb/>The number of animal protection organizations <lb/>counted in the World Animal Net directory, divided by <lb/>the population of each country. <lb/>0 -1 <lb/>-<lb/>H4b <lb/>Civic Activism Index (International <lb/>Institute of Social Studies, 2020). <lb/>A measure of engagement with matters of societal <lb/>concern compiled by the International Institute of <lb/>Social Studies, including engaging with news media, <lb/>participating in petitions or boycotts, and attending <lb/>protests and demonstrations. <lb/>0 -1 <lb/>-<lb/>All <lb/>Gross Domestic Product per Capita <lb/>(World Bank Group, 2021). <lb/>The wealth of a nation as measured by the economic <lb/>output of the nation <lb/>USD$ <lb/>-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bryant, Hopwood, Graça et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Psychology of Human-Animal Intergroup Relations <lb/>2024, Vol. 3, Article e10337 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5964/phair.10337 <lb/></note>

			<body>Analysis <lb/>We preregistered our hypotheses (see Hopwood et al., 2022). Data were cleaned and <lb/>analysed in R (R Core Team, 2021). We primarily used multilevel models to test study <lb/>hypotheses as participants were nested within countries (note that this deviation from <lb/>our preregistration followed reviewer suggestions). For comparisons that included two <lb/>countries or fewer (i.e., H2d and H2e), we used multiple regression models. We ran <lb/>multilevel models with random intercepts using the nlme package (Pinheiro et al., 2022) <lb/>and multiple regression models using the stats package (Revelle, 2022). We fit secondary <lb/>models that included control variables including age, gender, education, and Gross Do <lb/>mestic Product (GDP) per capita for each country for all hypotheses. We country-centred <lb/>age and education variables for each individual participant to the mean value of the <lb/>participant&apos;s country. Countries for which data were unavailable on relevant external <lb/>variables were not included in analyses. <lb/>To test H1a and H1b, we examined the relationship between the strength of exist <lb/>ing farmed animal welfare laws and reported support for both farmed and aquatic <lb/>animal welfare, respectively. We used the Animal Protection Index (API; World Animal <lb/>Protection, 2020) as a measure of animal welfare laws. The API rates countries from A <lb/>(best) to G (worst). <lb/>To test hypotheses H2a-H2c, we examined whether there were significant differences <lb/>in the feelings of personal connection to goats, pigs, and cows in countries that do or do <lb/>not tend to eat those animals, respectively (note that, in line with reviewer suggestions, <lb/>this differs from our pre-registration where the variable is labelled &apos;concern for [animal] <lb/>welfare&apos;). Countries were coded as either eating (1) or non-eating (0) for the specific <lb/>animals of interest. To test hypotheses H2d and H2e, we examined whether certain <lb/>religious groups differed in their feelings of personal connection to pigs and cows using <lb/>multiple regressions. For H2d, we expected that Muslims would report lower feelings <lb/>of personal connection to pigs than non-Muslims in high-population Muslim countries <lb/>(Indonesia and Malaysia). For H2e, we expected Hindus to report greater feelings of per <lb/>sonal connection to cows than non-Hindus in a high-population Hindu country (India). <lb/>To test H3, we compared participants&apos; estimates of the proportion of animals that <lb/>are factory farmed in each country to the estimates of actual levels of factory farming <lb/>from the Sentience Institute. To test H4a and H4b, we examined the relationship between <lb/>support for animal advocacy organisations and the number of animal advocacy organi <lb/>sations per capita (H4a), and the relationship between personal commitment to animal <lb/>advocacy and the Civic Activism Index (H4b). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">International Animal Welfare Support <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Psychology of Human-Animal Intergroup Relations <lb/>2024, Vol. 3, Article e10337 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5964/phair.10337 <lb/></note>

			<body>Results <lb/>Script, data, and full results for multilevel and regression models are provided at <lb/>Hopwood et al. (2023). Table S1 in Bryant et al. (2024) provides the results from models <lb/>with just the predictors of interest while Table S2 provides the results from models with <lb/>covariates. <lb/>Support for Animal Welfare and Strength of Legislation <lb/>Our first analyses determined the degree to which the strength of animal welfare legis <lb/>lation (as determined by the API) was associated with support for farmed (H1a) and <lb/>aquatic (H1b) animal welfare across countries. We found that countries with weaker <lb/>animal welfare legislation scored lower in support of farmed animal welfare, β = -.14, <lb/>95% CI [-.24, -.04], even when controlling for covariates, β = -.19, 95% CI [-.29, -.08]. For <lb/>aquatic animal welfare, while countries with worse animal welfare legislation also scored <lb/>lower on support for their welfare, the results were not significant, β = -.11, 95% CI [-.22, <lb/>.004]. However, this effect became significant when adjusting for covariates, β = -.15, 95% <lb/>CI [-.27, -.04]. We interpreted this as mixed support for our hypothesis about aquatic <lb/>animal welfare. <lb/>Feelings of Personal Connection to Animals Based on Animal <lb/>Consumption Norms <lb/>The next set of analyses focused on how feelings of personal connection to animals <lb/>are related to cultural and religious practices across and within countries. We expected <lb/>that individuals in countries that eat more goat would express lower feelings of person <lb/>al connection to goats compared to those in non-goat-eating countries (H2a). Results <lb/>indicated that goat-eating and non-goat-eating countries did not differ in their feelings <lb/>of personal connection to goats, β = .18, 95% CI [-.31, .67], even when controlling for <lb/>covariates, β = .20, 95% CI [-.29, .68]. We expected that individuals in pig-eating countries <lb/>would report lower feelings of personal connection to pigs than those in non-pig-eating <lb/>countries (H2b). Similar to H2a, we found that pig-eating and non-pig-eating countries <lb/>did not differ in their feelings of personal connection to pigs, β = .25, 95% CI [-.74, <lb/>1.24], even when controlling for covariates, β = .23, 95% CI [-.79, 1.25]. We expected <lb/>that individuals in a non-cow-eating country (i.e., India) would have higher feelings <lb/>of personal connection to cows than those in cow-eating countries (H2c). In line with <lb/>our hypothesis, countries that eat cows reported less feelings of personal connection to <lb/>cows than a country that do not eat cows, β = -1.57, 95% CI [-2.67, -.47], even when <lb/>controlling for covariates, β = -1.36, 95% CI [-2.45, -.26]. In this case, India was the only <lb/>non-cow-eating country. <lb/>We next examined whether different religious groups differed in their feelings of <lb/>personal connection to animals. We expected that Muslims would show less feelings of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bryant, Hopwood, Graça et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Psychology of Human-Animal Intergroup Relations <lb/>2024, Vol. 3, Article e10337 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5964/phair.10337 <lb/></note>

			<body>personal connection to pigs than non-Muslims in the Muslim-populous countries Malay <lb/>sia and Indonesia (H2d). Supporting our hypothesis, we found that Muslims showed less <lb/>feelings of personal connection to pigs than non-Muslims in both the regression models <lb/>without, β = -1.78, 95% CI [-1.93, -1.63], and with covariates, β = -1.85, 95% CI [-2.01, <lb/>-1.68]. Conversely, we expected that Hindus would show greater feelings of personal <lb/>connection to cows than non-Hindus in India (a Hindu-populous country; H2e). Results <lb/>indicated that Hindus reported greater feelings of personal connection to cows than <lb/>non-Hindus, β = .58, 95% CI [.27, .88], even when controlling for covariates, β = .54, 95% <lb/>CI [.23, .84]. <lb/>Factory Farming Perceptions and Reality <lb/>We next tested the degree to which people in various countries over-or underestimated <lb/>the percent of factory farms in their country (H3). We expected for people to generally <lb/>underestimate the percent of factory farms in their countries. Average estimates of <lb/>factory farming ranged from 50-70% across all of the 21 countries for which both figures <lb/>were available. In 86% of these countries, people tended to underestimate the rate of <lb/>factory farming. The exceptions-the UK, the Netherlands, and Germany-had relatively <lb/>low rates of factory farming (50% or less, in contrast to 75% or higher for other countries <lb/>in the survey). However, in the overall sample we found no significant differences in <lb/>estimation, in both the simple model, β = .04, 95% CI [-.05, .12], and the model adjusting <lb/>for covariates, β = .03, 95% CI [-.07, .14]. We interpret this as mixed support, given that <lb/>most countries do indeed underestimate the rate of factory farming, even though this <lb/>effect was not significant in the model, primarily due to comparably low rates of actual <lb/>factory farming in three countries. <lb/>Support for Animal Advocacy <lb/>Our final analyses focused on the hypothesis that countries with more animal advocacy <lb/>organisations per capita would show greater support for animal advocacy organizations <lb/>(H4a). However, we found the effect of the number of animal organizations per capita <lb/>was unrelated to animal advocacy organization support, β = -.14, 95% CI [-.39, .12], even <lb/>when controlling for covariates, β = .16, 95% CI [-.17, .49]. We additionally expected <lb/>that countries with greater civic engagement (as measured through the Civic Activism <lb/>Index [CAI]; International Institute of Social Studies, 2020) would display a greater <lb/>commitment to animal advocacy. We grand mean centered the CAI for this model. We <lb/>found no significant results for both the simple model, β = -7.62, 95% CI [-34.19, 18.96], <lb/>and the model with covariates, β = 7.60, 95% CI [-6.79, 21.98]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">International Animal Welfare Support <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Psychology of Human-Animal Intergroup Relations <lb/>2024, Vol. 3, Article e10337 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5964/phair.10337 <lb/></note>

			<body>Discussion <lb/>This study aimed to explore the country-level links between (a) public support for <lb/>farmed animal welfare and advocacy and (b) the robustness of animal welfare laws, the <lb/>food status of different animals, the prevalence of factory farming, and the level of civic <lb/>activism and of animal advocacy. As shown in the table, four out of 10 of our hypotheses <lb/>were supported by the analyses, four were not, and there was mixed support for two <lb/>(Table 3). <lb/>Table 3 <lb/>Hypotheses and Results <lb/>Hypothesis <lb/>Result <lb/>1a. People will have higher support for farmed animal welfare in countries with <lb/>stronger animal welfare legislation <lb/>Supported <lb/>1b. People will have higher support for aquatic animal welfare in countries with <lb/>stronger animal welfare legislation <lb/>Mixed Support <lb/>2a. The feelings of personal connection to goats will be significantly higher in <lb/>non-goat-eating countries compared to goat-eating countries <lb/>Not supported <lb/>2b. The feelings of personal connection to pigs will be significantly higher in non-<lb/>pig-eating countries compared to pig-eating countries <lb/>Not supported <lb/>2c. The feelings of personal connection to cows will be significantly higher in a <lb/>non-cow-eating country compared to cow-eating countries <lb/>Supported <lb/>2d. The feelings of personal connection to pigs will be significantly lower among <lb/>Muslims compared to non-Muslims in countries with high Muslim populations <lb/>Supported <lb/>2e. The feelings of personal connection to cows will be significantly higher among <lb/>Hindus compared to non-Hindus in India <lb/>Supported <lb/>3. People&apos;s knowledge of farm conditions will tend to represent an underestimate <lb/>of factory farming within their own country, such that the majority (more than <lb/>half) of survey estimate percentages are lower than the actual percentages for the <lb/>given country <lb/>Mixed Support <lb/>4a. There will be higher support for animal advocacy in countries with more <lb/>animal advocacy organizations per capita <lb/>Not supported <lb/>4b. There will be higher personal commitment to animal advocacy in countries <lb/>with higher levels of civic activism <lb/>Not supported <lb/>First, we observed significantly more robust farmed animal welfare laws in countries <lb/>with higher support for farmed and aquatic animal welfare. This may imply that public <lb/>opinions on animal welfare tend to translate into regulation of animal agriculture, that <lb/>stronger animal welfare laws influence public attitudes, or both. The cross-sectional <lb/>design utilized in this study cannot parse these possibilities. However, the link between <lb/>animal welfare laws and countries&apos; public support for animal welfare is important for <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bryant, Hopwood, Graça et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Psychology of Human-Animal Intergroup Relations <lb/>2024, Vol. 3, Article e10337 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5964/phair.10337 <lb/></note>

			<body>advocacy organizations, who must decide whether to dedicate limited resources to influ <lb/>encing governmental policies or individual attitudes. Institutional advocacy is generally <lb/>considered more effective than individual advocacy, since it impacts a far greater number <lb/>of animals (Broad, 2018). However, if public support leads to policy, it would suggest <lb/>that advocacy for animals is likely to be more successful in countries where the public <lb/>considers this a priority and lends support to the importance of individual advocacy <lb/>to enable institutional change. Future research should focus both on determining the <lb/>directionality of this effect, and more specifically on the efficacy and cost-effectiveness of <lb/>animal advocacy focused on individual or public support as opposed to (or together with) <lb/>institutional or legal policy. <lb/>Second, we observed mixed results with respect to personal connection to specific <lb/>animals in countries where those animals are/not generally consumed. While we did <lb/>observe significantly higher connection to cows in a non-cow-eating country (i.e., India) <lb/>compared to cow-eating countries, we observed no significant difference in connection <lb/>to pigs in non-pig-eating countries compared to pig-eating countries. The disparity <lb/>between the findings on cows and pigs may be attributable to the differing religious <lb/>reasons for avoiding consumption of these animals. As hypothesized, we observed signif <lb/>icantly higher personal connection to cows among Hindus compared to non-Hindus in <lb/>India, and we observed significantly lower personal connection to pigs among Muslims <lb/>compared to non-Muslims in countries with large Muslim populations. While cows <lb/>are regarded as holy in Hinduism, pigs are regarded as impure in Islam. Hence, while <lb/>both religions avoid consumption of specific animals, different reasons underlie these <lb/>avoidances, and this may explain the differing country-wise results on consideration of <lb/>these animals. <lb/>We also observed no significant difference in personal connection to goats in goat-<lb/>eating compared to non-goat-eating countries. Previous studies have observed that peo <lb/>ple tend to attribute higher moral status to non-food animals compared to food animals <lb/>(Krings et al., 2021), but that was not reflected here on a country-level basis. One <lb/>possible interpretation is that for meat products that are embedded in a given culture, <lb/>familiarity with the product renders meat-animal reminders and associations morally less <lb/>problematic (Benningstad &amp; Kunst, 2020; Possidónio et al., 2022). It may be the case that <lb/>a higher proportion of people from goat-eating countries live rurally in close proximity <lb/>to livestock compared to people from non-goat-eating countries. In other words, a feeling <lb/>of personal connection to goats may develop as a result of spending time with goats, but <lb/>this went hand-in-hand with having goats as livestock, and therefore eating them. In this <lb/>instance, a feeling of personal connection to an animal appears not necessarily to imply a <lb/>belief that the animal ought not be eaten. <lb/>Third, we observed that the majority of countries for which data was available (18 <lb/>out of 21) underestimate the proportion of animals on factory farms. Residents in all <lb/>countries estimated that 50-70% of animals in their country are factory farmed, while <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">International Animal Welfare Support <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Psychology of Human-Animal Intergroup Relations <lb/>2024, Vol. 3, Article e10337 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5964/phair.10337 <lb/></note>

			<body>Sentience Institute&apos;s figures typically put the number of caged egg-laying hens at over <lb/>80%. It is worth noting that, although chickens make up a disproportionate number of <lb/>farmed land animals, estimates of the percentage of caged egg-laying hens is a rather <lb/>imperfect proxy for the extent of factory farming overall. Interestingly, there was not <lb/>much variance in the survey estimates of factory farming, but some countries (the <lb/>Netherlands, the UK, and Germany) had substantially lower rates of factory farming <lb/>than others on this measure, and these are the countries which represented significant <lb/>overestimates, while all of the other countries represented significant underestimates. <lb/>Notably, these are among the most progressive countries with respect to animal rights; as <lb/>well as scoring high on animal welfare law robustness, they are also the biggest markets <lb/>for plant-based meat substitutes in Europe (Bechtold &amp; Will, 2021). <lb/>Fourth, we found no relationship between the support for animal advocacy and the <lb/>number of animal advocacy organisations per capita, nor between the level of personal <lb/>commitment to animal advocacy and the Civic Activism Index. The former finding <lb/>suggests that there are some countries-those with relatively high support for animal <lb/>advocacy but relatively few animal advocacy organisations-where there is potential for <lb/>more animal advocacy organisations. This includes China, India, Brazil, and Indonesia. <lb/>These are all countries where there are relatively few animal advocacy organisations <lb/>despite a relatively high level of claimed support. Advocates in these countries may <lb/>be able to draw additional resources from a supportive public. The latter finding may <lb/>be attributable to the relatively niche status of animal welfare as a political concern; <lb/>therefore, while people in different countries may be more or less likely to engage in <lb/>civic activism in general, this tendency may not translate to animal activism depending <lb/>on the level of concern for animals per se. <lb/>This study was limited in several ways. First, the survey data included is the result <lb/>of self-reported questionnaires administered online, which are subject to data quality <lb/>concerns including demand effects as well as cultural interpretation of questions. While <lb/>such concerns can never be entirely mitigated for online surveys, steps were taken to <lb/>safeguard data quality including attention check questions and removing low-quality <lb/>responses. Second, some of the analyses included herein may be limited in their scope <lb/>-for instance, it is possible that the Civic Activism Index would be correlated with <lb/>personal willingness to take part in animal advocacy if support for animal welfare was <lb/>also considered, or that support for animal advocacy organisations would be correlated <lb/>with the number of animal advocacy organisations per capita if GDP per capita were <lb/>also considered. In general, our use of brief measures that had largely not been validated <lb/>in previous work and the lack of detail with which some of important issues could be <lb/>measured (e.g., variation in treatment or prevalence of agriculture pertinent to different <lb/>species) limited the generalizability and nuance provided by this study. <lb/>Future research could explore these more complex relationships between survey <lb/>data and other animal welfare-related data sources and could additionally explore other <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bryant, Hopwood, Graça et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Psychology of Human-Animal Intergroup Relations <lb/>2024, Vol. 3, Article e10337 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5964/phair.10337 <lb/></note>

			<body>variables in the dataset. The survey data and external data associated with this project <lb/>are all Open Access, and they can be a valuable source of information for policymakers, <lb/>researchers, advocates, and public and private organisations. Future research could also <lb/>consider different ways of affecting the measures in this survey-for example, the opti <lb/>mal way to increase support for animal welfare may be different in different countries, <lb/>which again has implications for policy and advocacy. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>In conclusion, concern for animal welfare varies around the world, and it is important to <lb/>understand this variation and its implication for policy and advocacy. Higher support for <lb/>animal welfare tends to be linked with stronger animal welfare legislation. Cultural and <lb/>religious factors also impact how people tend to think about animal welfare for certain <lb/>species. People in most countries tend to underestimate the extent of factory farming, <lb/>suggesting that education about factory farming may be a promising area of focus for <lb/>policy and advocacy. Finally, there was no correlation between stated support for animal <lb/>organisations and the number of animal advocacy organisations per capita, nor between <lb/>personal commitment to animal advocacy and the level of civic activism more broadly. <lb/>Regions of the world with relatively high support but relatively few animal advocacy <lb/>organizations may have high potential to benefit from advocacy work. <lb/></body>

			<div type="funding">Funding: This study was not associated with any particular funding or grant. Collection of the survey data was <lb/>funded by Mercy For Animals. <lb/>Acknowledgments: The authors have no additional (i.e., non-financial) support to report. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Competing Interests: Christopher Bryant is the owner and Director of Bryant Research Ltd, a research company <lb/>that uses social science to help alternative protein companies and animal protection non-profits advance the protein <lb/>transition. Christopher J. Hopwood is Editor-in-Chief of the journal but played no editorial role in this particular <lb/>article nor intervened in any form in the peer review process. João Graça is an Associate Editor of the journal but <lb/>played no editorial role in this particular article nor intervened in any form in the peer review process. Adam T. <lb/>Nissen declares no conflicts of interest. Courtney Dillard is employed by Mercy For Animals, a non-profit <lb/>organization which works to reduce global animal suffering. Andie Thompkins is employed by Mercy For Animals, a <lb/>non-profit organization which works to reduce global animal suffering. <lb/></div>

            <div type="availability">Data Availability: Data is freely available, see Hopwood et al. (2023) <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Supplementary Materials <lb/>The supplementary materials provided are the preregistration of hypothesis in Hopwood et al. <lb/>(2022), the OSF project page containing codebook, script, data, and full results in Hopwood et al. <lb/>(2023), and additional analyses and tables in Bryant et al. (2024). <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">International Animal Welfare Support <lb/></note>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Psychology of Human-Animal Intergroup Relations <lb/>2024, Vol. 3, Article e10337 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5964/phair.10337 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Amiot, C. E., &amp; Bastian, B. (2015). Toward a psychology of human-animal relations. Psychological <lb/>Bulletin, 141(1), 6-47. https://doi.org/10.1037/a0038147 <lb/>Amiot, C. E., Sukhanova, K., &amp; Bastian, B. (2020). Social identification with animals: Unpacking our <lb/>psychological connection with other animals. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, <lb/>118(5), 991-1017. https://doi.org/10.1037/pspi0000199 <lb/>Anomaly, J. (2015). What&apos;s wrong with factory farming? Public Health Ethics, 8(3), 246-254. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/phe/phu001 <lb/>Anthis, K., &amp; Reese-Anthis, J. (2019, February 21). Global farmed &amp; factory farmed animals <lb/>estimates. Sentience Institute. <lb/>https://www.sentienceinstitute.org/global-animal-farming-estimates <lb/>Bastian, B., &amp; Loughnan, S. (2017). Resolving the meat-paradox: A motivational account of morally <lb/>troublesome behavior and its maintenance. Personality and Social Psychology Review, 21(3), 278-<lb/>299. https://doi.org/10.1177/1088868316647562 <lb/>Bechtold, K.-B., &amp; Will, D. (2021). Plant-based foods in Europe: How big is the market? Smart Protein <lb/>Project. <lb/>https://smartproteinproject.eu/wp-content/uploads/Smart-Protein-Plant-based-Food-Sector-<lb/>Report_-Webinar-slides.pdf <lb/>Benningstad, N. C., &amp; Kunst, J. R. (2020). Dissociating meat from its animal origins: A systematic <lb/>literature review. Appetite, 147, Article 104554. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.appet.2019.104554 <lb/>Broad, G. M. (2018). Effective animal advocacy: Effective altruism, the social economy, and the <lb/>animal protection movement. Agriculture and Human Values, 35(4), 777-789. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10460-018-9873-5 <lb/>Bryant, C., Hopwood, C. J., Graça, J., Nissen, A. T., Dillard, C., &amp; Thompkins, A. (2024). <lb/>Supplementary materials to &quot;Exploring public support for farmed animal welfare policy and <lb/>advocacy across 23 countries&quot; [Additional analyses, tables]. PsychOpen GOLD. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.23668/psycharchives.14134 <lb/>Cembalo, L., Caracciolo, F., Lombardi, A., Del Giudice, T., Grunert, K. G., &amp; Cicia, G. (2016). <lb/>Determinants of individual attitudes toward animal welfare-friendly food products. Journal of <lb/>Agricultural &amp; Environmental Ethics, 29(2), 237-254. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10806-015-9598-z <lb/>Dhont, K., Hodson, G., Loughnan, S., &amp; Amiot, C. E. (2019). Rethinking human-animal relations: <lb/>The critical role of social psychology. Group Processes &amp; Intergroup Relations, 22(6), 769-784. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1177/1368430219864455 <lb/>Godfray, H. C. J., Aveyard, P., Garnett, T., Hall, J. W., Key, T. J., Lorimer, J., Pierrehumbert, R. T., <lb/>Scarborough, P., Springmann, M., &amp; Jebb, S. A. (2018). Meat consumption, health, and the <lb/>environment. Science, 361(6399), Article eaam5324. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aam5324 <lb/>Grassian, D. T. (2020). The dietary behaviors of participants in UK-based meat reduction and vegan <lb/>campaigns-A longitudinal, mixed-methods study. Appetite, 154, Article 104788. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.appet.2020.104788 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Bryant, Hopwood, Graça et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Psychology of Human-Animal Intergroup Relations <lb/>2024, Vol. 3, Article e10337 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5964/phair.10337 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Heise, H., &amp; Theuvsen, L. (2017). What do consumers think about farm animal welfare in modern <lb/>agriculture? Attitudes and shopping behaviour. International Food and Agribusiness <lb/>Management Review, 20(3), 379-399. https://doi.org/10.22434/IFAMR2016.0115 <lb/>Hopwood, C., Olaru, G., Dillard, C., Graça, J., Romero Waldhorn, D., Sanchez-Suarez, W., Nissen, A. <lb/>T., Thompkins, A., &amp; Bryant, C. (2022). MFA Advocacy Support Preregistration [Preregistration <lb/>of hypothesis]. OSF. https://doi.org/10.17605/OSF.IO/XEJGU <lb/>Hopwood, C., Olaru, G., Dillard, C., Graça, J., Romero Waldhorn, D., Sanchez-Suarez, W., Nissen, A. <lb/>T., Thompkins, A., &amp; Bryant, C. (2023). International Attitudes about Farmed Animals [OSF <lb/>project page containing codebook, script, data, and full results]. OSF. https://osf.io/tx3u9 <lb/>International Institute of Social Studies. (2020). Civic Activism. <lb/>https://isd.iss.nl/home/civic-activism/ <lb/>Krings, V. C., Dhont, K., &amp; Salmen, A. (2021). The moral divide between high-and low-status <lb/>animals: The role of human supremacy beliefs. Anthrozoos, 34(6), 787-802. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/08927936.2021.1926712 <lb/>Li, P. J., Sun, J., &amp; Yu, D. (2017). Dog &quot;meat&quot; consumption in China: A survey of the controversial <lb/>eating habit in two cities. Society &amp; Animals, 25(6), 513-532. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1163/15685306-12341471 <lb/>Loughnan, S., Haslam, N., &amp; Bastian, B. (2010). The role of meat consumption in the denial of moral <lb/>status and mind to meat animals. Appetite, 55(1), 156-159. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.appet.2010.05.043 <lb/>Mandolesi, S., Naspetti, S., Arsenos, G., Caramelle-Holtz, E., Latvala, T., Martin-Collado, D., Orsini, <lb/>S., Ozturk, E., &amp; Zanoli, R. (2020). Motivations and barriers for sheep and goat meat <lb/>consumption in Europe: A means-end chain study. Animals, 10(6), Article 1105. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/ani10061105 <lb/>Oreg, S., &amp; Katz-Gerro, T. (2006). Predicting pro environmental behavior cross-nationally: Values, <lb/>the theory of planned behavior, and value-belief-norm theory. Environment and Behavior, 38(4), <lb/>462-483. https://doi.org/10.1177/0013916505286012 <lb/>Pinheiro, J., Bates, D., DebRoy, S., Sarkar, D., Heisterkamp, S., Van Willigen, B., &amp; Ranke, J. (2022). <lb/>Package &quot;nlme&quot; (3.1-161) [Computer software]. CRAN R Project. <lb/>https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/nlme/nlme.pdf <lb/>Possidónio, C., Piazza, J., Graça, J., &amp; Prada, M. (2022). An appetite for meat? Disentangling the <lb/>influence of animal resemblance and familiarity. Appetite, 170, Article 105875. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.appet.2021.105875 <lb/>R Core Team. (2021). R: A language and environment for statistical computing (4.1.0) [Computer <lb/>software]. R Foundation for Statistical Computing. https://www.R-project.org/ <lb/>Randler, C., Adan, A., Antofie, M. M., Arrona-Palacios, A., Candido, M., Boeve-de Pauw, J., <lb/>Chandrakar, P., Demirhan, E., Detsis, V., Di Milia, L., Fančovičová, J., Gericke, N., Haldar, P., <lb/>Heidari, Z., Jankowski, K. S., Lehto, J. E., Lundell-Creagh, R., Medina-Jerez, W., Meule, <lb/>A., . . .Vollmer, C. (2021). Animal welfare attitudes: Effects of gender and diet in university <lb/>samples from 22 Countries. Animals, 11(7), Article 1893. https://doi.org/10.3390/ani11071893 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">International Animal Welfare Support <lb/></note>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Psychology of Human-Animal Intergroup Relations <lb/>2024, Vol. 3, Article e10337 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5964/phair.10337 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Reese-Anthis, J. (2017, November 20). Animals, Food, and Technology (AFT) Survey 2017. Sentience <lb/>Institute. https://www.sentienceinstitute.org/animal-farming-attitudes-survey-2017 <lb/>Revelle, W. (2022) psych: Procedures for Personality and Psychological Research (2.2.9) [Computer <lb/>software]. CRAN R Project. https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=psych <lb/>Ritchie, H., &amp; Roser, M. (2017). Meat and dairy production. Our World in Data. <lb/>https://ourworldindata.org/meat-production <lb/>Sarkar, R., &amp; Sarkar, A. (2016). Sacred slaughter: An analysis of historical, communal, and <lb/>constitutional aspects of beef bans in India. Politics. Religion &amp; Ideology, 17(4), 329-351. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/21567689.2016.1259108 <lb/>Sparkman, G., Geiger, N., &amp; Weber, E. U. (2022). Americans experience a false social reality by <lb/>underestimating popular climate policy support by nearly half. Nature Communications, 13(1), <lb/>Article 4779. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-022-32412-y <lb/>Vanhonacker, F., Verbeke, W., Van Poucke, E., &amp; Tuyttens, F. A. (2008). Do citizens and farmers <lb/>interpret the concept of farm animal welfare differently? Livestock Science, 116(1-3), 126-136. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.livsci.2007.09.017 <lb/>World Animal Net. (2017). World Animal Net Directory. <lb/>https://worldanimal.net/directory/search-wan-directory <lb/>World Bank Group. (2021). GDP per capita. World Bank. <lb/>https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/NY.GDP.PCAP.CD <lb/>World Animal Protection. (2020). Animal Protection Index. World Animal Protection. <lb/>https://api.worldanimalprotection.org/ <lb/>Psychology of Human-Animal <lb/>Intergroup Relations (PHAIR) is an <lb/>official journal of the PHAIR <lb/>Society. <lb/>PsychOpen GOLD is a publishing <lb/>service by Leibniz Institute for <lb/>Psychology (ZPID), Germany. <lb/>Bryant, Hopwood, Graça et al. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Psychology of Human-Animal Intergroup Relations <lb/>2024, Vol. 3, Article e10337 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5964/phair.10337 </note>


	</text>
</tei>
