<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Biomass-burning sources control ambient particulate matter, but traffic and industrial sources control volatile organic compound (VOC) emissions and secondary-pollutant formation during extreme pollution events in Delhi</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Arpit</forename>
          <surname>Awasthi</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Baerbel</forename>
          <surname>Sinha</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Haseeb</forename>
          <surname>Hakkim</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Sachin</forename>
          <surname>Mishra</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Varkrishna</forename>
          <surname>Mummidivarapu</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Gurmanjot</forename>
          <surname>Singh</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Sachin D.</forename>
          <surname>Ghude</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Vijay Kumar</forename>
          <surname>Soni</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Narendra</forename>
          <surname>Nigam</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Vinayak</forename>
          <surname>Sinha</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Madhavan N.</forename>
          <surname>Rajeevan</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-05T14:40:20.961Z">11/5/2025 2:40:20 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Copernicus GmbH</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.5194/acp-24-10279-2024</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Arpit Awasthi, Baerbel Sinha, Haseeb Hakkim, Sachin Mishra, Varkrishna Mummidivarapu, Gurmanjot Singh, Sachin D. Ghude, Vijay Kumar Soni, Narendra Nigam, Vinayak Sinha, Madhavan N. Rajeevan. (2024). Biomass-burning sources control ambient particulate matter, but traffic and industrial sources control volatile organic compound (VOC) emissions and secondary-pollutant formation during extreme pollution events in Delhi. Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics, 24(18), 10279-10304. DOI: 10.5194/acp-24-10279-2024</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-05T14:40:10.287899Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-05T14:40:10.287899Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>Biogeosciences, 21, 2937-2954, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-2937-2024 <lb/>© Author(s) 2024. This work is distributed under <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License. <lb/>Research article <lb/>Spatial patterns of organic matter content in the surface soil of the <lb/>salt marshes of the Venice Lagoon (Italy) <lb/>Alice Puppin 1,2 , Davide Tognin 3 , Massimiliano Ghinassi 2 , Erica Franceschinis 4 , Nicola Realdon 4 , Marco Marani 3 , and <lb/>Andrea D&apos;Alpaos 2 <lb/>1 Department of Land, Environment, Agriculture And Forestry, University of Padua, Padua, 35131, Italy <lb/>2 Department of Geosciences, University of Padua, Padua, 35131, Italy <lb/>3 Department of Civil, Environmental and Architectural Engineering, University of Padua, Padua, 35131, Italy <lb/>4 Department of Pharmaceutical and Pharmacological Sciences, University of Padua, Padua, 35131, Italy <lb/>Correspondence: Alice Puppin (alice.puppin@unipd.it) <lb/>Received: 1 December 2023 -Discussion started: 18 December 2023 <lb/>Revised: 22 March 2024 -Accepted: 27 April 2024 -Published: 18 June 2024 <lb/>Abstract. Salt marshes are crucial eco-geomorphic features <lb/>of tidal environments as they provide important ecological <lb/>functions and deliver a wide range of ecosystem services. Be-<lb/>ing controlled by the interplay between hydrodynamics, geo-<lb/>morphology, and vegetation, the contribution of both organic <lb/>matter (OM) and inorganic sediments drives salt marsh verti-<lb/>cal accretion. This allows marshes to keep pace with relative <lb/>sea level rise and likewise capture and store carbon, making <lb/>them valuable allies in climate mitigation strategies. Thus, <lb/>soil organic matter (SOM), i.e. the organic component of the <lb/>soil, plays a key role within salt marsh environments, directly <lb/>contributing to soil formation and supporting carbon storage. <lb/>This study aims at inspecting spatial patterns of OM in sur-<lb/>face salt marsh soils (top 20 cm), providing further insights <lb/>into the physical and biological factors driving OM dynam-<lb/>ics that affect salt marsh survival and carbon sink potential. <lb/>Our results reveal two scales of variations in SOM content <lb/>in marsh environments. At the marsh scale, OM variability <lb/>is influenced by the interplay between surface elevation and <lb/>changes in sediment supply linked with the distance from <lb/>the marsh edge. At the system scale, OM content distribution <lb/>is dominated by the gradient generated by marine and flu-<lb/>vial influence. The observed variations in SOM are explained <lb/>by the combination of inorganic and organic input, preser-<lb/>vation conditions, and sediment grain size. Our results high-<lb/>light the importance of marshes as carbon sink environments, <lb/>further emphasising that environmental conditions within a <lb/>tidal system may generate strongly variable and site-specific <lb/>carbon accumulation patterns, enhancing blue carbon assess-<lb/>ment complexity. <lb/></front>

        <body>1 Introduction <lb/>Salt marshes may be defined as halophytic grasslands or <lb/>dwarf brushwoods encroaching sediment platforms border-<lb/>ing saline tidal water bodies (Beeftink, 1977; Silvestri and <lb/>Marani, 2004). Salt marshes lie at the upper margin of the <lb/>intertidal environment, and they are regularly flooded by <lb/>the tides and occasionally by storm surges (Allen, 2000; <lb/>Friedrichs and Perry, 2001; D&apos;Alpaos and D&apos;Alpaos, 2021; <lb/>D&apos;Alpaos et al., 2007; D&apos;Alpaos, 2011). They occur world-<lb/>wide, particularly in middle and high latitudes on low-energy <lb/>coasts, from microtidal to macrotidal regimes (Allen and <lb/>Pye, 1992). Coastal wetlands, situated at the interface be-<lb/>tween terrestrial and marine ecosystems, often lie in some of <lb/>the world&apos;s most densely populated areas and deliver a wide <lb/>range of ecosystem services that contribute to human well-<lb/>being, as they are simultaneously some of the most economi-<lb/>cally relevant and vulnerable ecosystems on Earth (D&apos;Alpaos <lb/>and D&apos;Alpaos, 2021; Costanza et al., 1997; de Groot et al., <lb/>2012). Salt marshes provide a critical habitat for numerous <lb/>species, protect coastal areas by buffering floods and wave <lb/>action, improve water quality, support commercial fisheries, <lb/>provide recreational opportunities, and contribute to climate <lb/>regulation by acting as carbon (C) sinks (e.g. Barbier et al., <lb/>2011; Boesch and Turner, 1984; Costanza et al., 1997; Lefeu-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Published by Copernicus Publications on behalf of the European Geosciences Union. <lb/></note>

        <page>2938 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A. Puppin et al.: Spatial patterns of organic matter content in the surface soil of the salt marshes <lb/></note>

        <body>vre et al., 2003; Temmerman et al., 2013; Fairchild et al., <lb/>2021; Möller et al., 2014). <lb/>However, salt marsh ecosystems are exceptionally vulner-<lb/>able to the effects of climate changes and increasing human <lb/>pressure such as accelerating relative sea level rise, declin-<lb/>ing sediment supply, and coastal land reclamation (D&apos;Alpaos <lb/>et al., 2011; Gedan et al., 2009; Kirwan et al., 2010; Marani <lb/>et al., 2007; Morris et al., 2002; Mudd et al., 2004; Mudd, <lb/>2011; Temmerman et al., 2005; Silvestri et al., 2018; Breda <lb/>et al., 2022), having lost between 25 % and 50 % of their <lb/>global historical coverage (Mcowen et al., 2017). <lb/>Salt marshes are intrinsically dynamic environments, and <lb/>their evolution importantly depends on complex feedbacks <lb/>between physical and biological components. The inter-<lb/>play between hydrodynamics, geomorphology, and vegeta-<lb/>tion controls marsh vertical accretion, which has allowed <lb/>marshes to keep pace with relative sea level rise over thou-<lb/>sands of years (D&apos;Alpaos et al., 2007; Marani et al., 2007; <lb/>Fagherazzi et al., 2012; Mudd et al., 2009, 2004; Allen, 2000; <lb/>Brückner et al., 2019). Vertical accretion in tidal marshes is <lb/>driven by the contribution of both organic matter (OM) and <lb/>inorganic sediments (Mudd et al., 2009; Fagherazzi et al., <lb/>2012; Nyman et al., 2006; Neubauer, 2008). Tides, wind <lb/>waves, and storms are the main mechanisms for sediment <lb/>transport, deposition, or mobilisation on the marsh platform, <lb/>shaping marsh morphology, which in turn influences wa-<lb/>ter depth and flow velocity. Halophytic plants, spatially or-<lb/>ganised in characteristic patches related to soil elevation <lb/>and hydroperiod (Bertness and Ellison, 1987; Pennings and <lb/>Callaway, 1992; Silvestri et al., 2005; Silvestri and Marani, <lb/>2004), contribute considerably to marsh accretion, influenc-<lb/>ing the water flow, enhancing sediment settling, damping <lb/>sediment resuspension, and producing biomass, which re-<lb/>sults in OM accumulation (D&apos;Alpaos et al., 2007; Marani <lb/>et al., 2006; Mudd et al., 2009). In some cases, OM contribu-<lb/>tion to marsh surface vertical accretion can be much greater <lb/>than that of sediment deposition (Ewers Lewis et al., 2020; <lb/>Morris et al., 2016; Allen et al., 2021). The organic material <lb/>that helps to build marsh elevation is likely a combination of <lb/>in situ production of belowground root tissue inserted into <lb/>the sediments (Craft et al., 1993; Day et al., 1999) and au-<lb/>tochthonous or allochthonous organic materials that are de-<lb/>posited over the surface (Nyman et al., 2006; Mudd et al., <lb/>2009; Ewers Lewis et al., 2019; Mueller et al., 2019). Sur-<lb/>face litter produced during the annual cycles of plant growth <lb/>and decay settles on the ground and is trapped within the <lb/>inorganic sediments deposited. A variable proportion of the <lb/>salt marsh soil organic matter (SOM) (Drexler et al., 2020; <lb/>Middelburg et al., 1997; Mueller et al., 2019) has an al-<lb/>lochthonous source, deriving from suspended particulate or-<lb/>ganic matter, and is often adsorbed on mineral matter and <lb/>on estuarine and marine phytoplankton, microphytobenthos, <lb/>and non-local macrophyte litter carried to the marsh surface <lb/>by waves and tides. Furthermore, tidal flooding inhibits mi-<lb/>crobial aerobic activity and slows down decomposition, fos-<lb/>tering C accumulation in marsh soils (Keuskamp et al., 2013; <lb/>Mueller et al., 2018; Kirwan et al., 2014; Morris et al., 2016). <lb/>As a result of these dynamics, the C captured through plant <lb/>photosynthesis is buried and preserved as soil organic car-<lb/>bon (SOC) and may be locked away from the atmosphere <lb/>over centennial to millennial timescales (Perillo et al., 2009; <lb/>Duarte et al., 2005). This process allows salt marsh environ-<lb/>ments to act as carbon sinks, serving as natural or artificial <lb/>reservoirs that accumulate and store carbon-containing com-<lb/>pounds, thereby helping to offset the effects of greenhouse <lb/>gas emissions on the Earth&apos;s climate (Watson et al., 2000). <lb/>The C sink function of vegetated coastal ecosystems, includ-<lb/>ing salt marshes, mangrove forests, and seagrass meadows, <lb/>has been increasingly recognised in recent years, and the <lb/>term &quot;blue carbon&quot; was coined to indicate the C sequestered <lb/>in these ecosystems, with a potential role in climate change <lb/>mitigation (Chmura et al., 2003; Duarte et al., 2005; McLeod <lb/>et al., 2011; Macreadie et al., 2019; Nellemann et al., 2009). <lb/>Recent models of intertidal system dynamics predict <lb/>marsh evolution incorporating both physical and ecological <lb/>processes (e.g. D&apos;Alpaos et al., 2007; Kirwan and Murray, <lb/>2007; Marani et al., 2007, 2013; Morris et al., 2002; Mudd <lb/>et al., 2004, 2009). However, to refine current representa-<lb/>tions of OM accumulation, a deeper understanding is needed <lb/>of crucial biogeomorphological factors driving OM dynam-<lb/>ics in tidal environments. Drivers of SOM variability in salt <lb/>marshes are innately difficult to identify, as SOM content is <lb/>the result of many complex processes acting simultaneously. <lb/>The study of the interplay between these processes is compli-<lb/>cated by the fact that they occur over a wide range of spatial <lb/>scales (Marani et al., 2006; Ewers Lewis et al., 2020). <lb/>While, at the global scale, climatic parameters appear to <lb/>be important drivers for C sequestration and storage (Chmura <lb/>et al., 2003), at the system scale, the position within the gra-<lb/>dient generated by marine and fluvial influence was observed <lb/>to be a key predictor of organic content, with the environ-<lb/>mental conditions resulting from the interplay between phys-<lb/>ical and biological factors (Kelleway et al., 2016; Van de <lb/>Broek et al., 2016). Geomorphological factors and vegeta-<lb/>tion characteristics appear to be important drivers of soil or-<lb/>ganic content variability when considering finer spatial scales <lb/>(e.g. Chen et al., 2016; Leonard et al., 2002; Roner et al., <lb/>2016). For instance, elevation and hydroperiod importantly <lb/>affect vegetation characteristics, organic matter supply, and <lb/>sediment deposition (Chmura et al., 2003) other than micro-<lb/>bial community and organic matter preservation conditions <lb/>(Kirwan et al., 2013; Marani et al., 2006; Mudd et al., 2009; <lb/>Yousefi Lalimi et al., 2018). The latter are also influenced <lb/>by sediment type and grain size, which are additionally as-<lb/>sociated with different concentrations of suspended partic-<lb/>ulate organic matter (Kelleway et al., 2016; Van de Broek <lb/>et al., 2016; Saintilan et al., 2013). Therefore, sediment grain <lb/>size was pointed out as a key predictor of organic content by <lb/>Ford et al. (2019) and Kelleway et al. (2016), whereas Van de <lb/>Broek et al. (2016) reported variations in suspended sediment <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Biogeosciences, 21, 2937-2954, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-2937-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">A. Puppin et al.: Spatial patterns of organic matter content in the surface soil of the salt marshes <lb/></note>

        <page>2939 <lb/></page>

        <body>concentration and stable particulate OC as the main drivers <lb/>of observed differences in organic storage. The vegetation <lb/>type was also observed to significantly affect soil organic <lb/>content at different scales (Ewers Lewis et al., 2020; Sainti-<lb/>lan et al., 2013). Above-and belowground production greatly <lb/>varies across and within plant species, both in terms of quan-<lb/>tity and quality, the latter determining different degrees of <lb/>decay resistance (Scarton et al., 2002; Stagg et al., 2018). In <lb/>addition, Van de Broek et al. (2018) show that SOC from <lb/>allochthonous sources (e.g. particulate organic matter, phy-<lb/>toplankton, microphytobenthos, and non-local macrophyte <lb/>litter) may be a main component of SOC stock preserved <lb/>in marsh sediments, and this finding could significantly im-<lb/>pact organic carbon sequestration assessments (Van de Broek <lb/>et al., 2018). <lb/>Here we aim to investigate spatial patterns of OM in salt <lb/>marsh soils, providing further insights into the physical and <lb/>biological factors driving OM dynamics, which affect salt <lb/>marsh survival and C sink potential. Toward these goals, we <lb/>analysed soil organic content and SOC stock for the surface <lb/>soil layer (0-20 cm) in 10 salt marshes of the Venice Lagoon <lb/>from 60 sediment cores together with different variables in-<lb/>cluding soil and morphological and vegetation characteris-<lb/>tics. The choice to analyse surface marsh soil for assessing <lb/>spatial patterns of soil organic content is driven by the need to <lb/>capture the layer most directly influenced by current environ-<lb/>mental variables. By contributing to a better understanding of <lb/>OM distribution and its controls in tidal marshes, our study <lb/>has the potential to improve spatially explicit biomorpholog-<lb/>ical models of salt marsh evolution, allowing the evaluation <lb/>of marsh resilience and associated C storage as an ecosys-<lb/>tem service. Improved representation of SOM dynamics in <lb/>biomorphodynamic models will provide critical information <lb/>for management and conservation strategies, favouring the <lb/>identification of optimal locations and actions to direct pro-<lb/>tection and restoration efforts. <lb/>2 Material and methods <lb/>2.1 Study site <lb/>The Venice Lagoon, situated in the northwestern Adriatic <lb/>Sea (Italy), is the largest brackish tidal waterbody within the <lb/>Mediterranean Sea. It is a shallow, microtidal, back-barrier <lb/>system, characterised by a semidiurnal tidal regime with an <lb/>average range of 1.0 m and a mean water depth over tidal flats <lb/>of about 1.5 m, and is connected to the Adriatic through three <lb/>inlets known as Lido, Malamocco, and Chioggia (Fig. 1). <lb/>The Venice Lagoon is also highly influenced by meteo-<lb/>rological forcings, with the southeasterly Sirocco wind re-<lb/>sponsible for severe storm surges flooding the city of Venice, <lb/>northeasterly Bora wind responsible for large wind waves <lb/>(Tommasini et al., 2019). The present-day morphology of <lb/>the Venice Lagoon is strongly affected by the intense hu-<lb/>man pressure occurring over the last centuries, going from <lb/>the diversion of the main rivers, which are now debouching <lb/>out of the lagoon, to the more recent construction of jetties <lb/>at the inlets and the excavation of large navigable channels, <lb/>to the rash groundwater exploitation in the 20th century. The <lb/>above interventions have seriously modified sediment supply <lb/>and dynamics, local hydrodynamics and morphology, and <lb/>rates of relative sea level rise, favouring sediment starva-<lb/>tion and the deepening of the lagoon (Zecchin et al., 2009; <lb/>Brambati et al., 2003). The recent activation of storm surge <lb/>barriers, designed to prevent flooding of the city of Venice, <lb/>was proved to further alter the lagoon hydrodynamics (Mel <lb/>et al., 2021) contributing to the deepening of the tidal flats <lb/>and reducing salt marsh sedimentation (Tognin et al., 2021, <lb/>2022). Salt marsh areas of the Venice Lagoon have dramat-<lb/>ically shrunk in the last centuries, with a decrease in exten-<lb/>sion from about 180 km 2 in 1811 to about 43 km 2 in 2002 <lb/>(Carniello et al., 2009; D&apos;Alpaos, 2010; Tommasini et al., <lb/>2019; Finotello et al., 2023). In addition, historical river di-<lb/>versions have significantly reduced freshwater inputs into the <lb/>lagoon, thereby impacting water salinity and vegetation char-<lb/>acteristics. Freshwater inputs currently flow into the lagoon <lb/>through 12 main tributaries distributed along the landward <lb/>boundary of the lagoon, with a mean annual contribution <lb/>of about 35 m 3 s -1 and a peak discharge of 344 m 3 s -1 (Zu-<lb/>liani et al., 2005). Spatial and temporal variability in salinity <lb/>in the Venice Lagoon is additionally influenced by ground-<lb/>water inputs (Gieskes et al., 2013). Estimates of the vol-<lb/>ume of underground freshwaters entering the lagoon floor <lb/>vary widely, from 15 % of total freshwater flow to more than <lb/>100 % (Zirino et al., 2014). Salinity levels in the Venice La-<lb/>goon today vary from approximately 20 PSU at the north-<lb/>eastern mainland edge to about 34-35 PSU at the three inlets <lb/>(Zirino et al., 2014). <lb/>The study sites are located in 10 salt marshes of the Venice <lb/>Lagoon, at variable distances from the inlets (Fig. 1). In <lb/>the northern lagoon, the Sant&apos;Erasmo (SE), San Felice (SF), <lb/>and Saline (SA) salt marshes border large tidal channels <lb/>departing from the Lido inlet. These marshes host exclu-<lb/>sively halophytic vegetation, mainly constituted by Salicor-<lb/>nia veneta, Limonium narbonense, and Sarcocornia fruti-<lb/>cosa, associated with Spartina maritima, Juncus maritimus, <lb/>Puccinellia palustris, Inula crithmoides, Suaeda maritima, <lb/>and Arthrocnemum macrostachyum (Silvestri, 2000; Silvestri <lb/>et al., 2005; Yang et al., 2020). In contrast, the Pagliaga (PA) <lb/>and Campalto (CA) sites are located at the lagoon-mainland <lb/>boundary in the northern lagoon, with PA being close to the <lb/>estuary of the spring water Dese River which debouches into <lb/>the lagoon, carrying an average 65 m 3 s -1 of freshwater dis-<lb/>charge and negligible sediment supply. Freshwater inputs at <lb/>the PA site maintain a near-freshwater plant community dom-<lb/>inated by Phragmites australis, together with the halophytic <lb/>species Juncus maritimus, Salicornia veneta, and Halimione <lb/>portulacoides (Silvestri, 2000). The CA marsh, whose main <lb/>edge faces a shallow tidal flat exposed to Sirocco wind, hosts <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-2937-2024 <lb/>Biogeosciences, 21, 2937-2954, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2940 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A. Puppin et al.: Spatial patterns of organic matter content in the surface soil of the salt marshes <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 1. Location of the study areas within the Venice Lagoon (Italy). Insets show the position of the 30 m long transects (orange lines) <lb/>within each study area located perpendicularly to the main marsh edge: MI, CA, PA, SA, SF, SE, VB, CO, FO, and CV (Map data: © 2022 <lb/>Google-Landsat/Copernicus, Maxar Technologies). <lb/>halophytic species dominated by Limonium narbonense, as-<lb/>sociated with Sarcocornia fruticosa, Spartina maritima, Sal-<lb/>icornia veneta, and the scarce Suaeda maritima, Triglochin <lb/>maritima, and Juncus gerardii. In the southern part of the <lb/>Venice Lagoon, the Mira (MI) marsh is close to the land-<lb/>ward boundary, and it is characterised by the presence of <lb/>Phragmites australis on the marsh edge, together with the <lb/>halophytic species Juncus maritimus, Puccinellia palustris, <lb/>Limonium narbonense, and Sarcocornia fruticosa. Canale <lb/>Virgilio (CV) and Fossei (FO) are located within the marsh <lb/>belt in front of the Malamocco and Chioggia inlets and host <lb/>halophytic vegetation consisting mainly of Limonium narbo-<lb/>nense, Sarcocornia fruticosa, and Puccinellia palustris, to-<lb/>gether with Juncus maritimus, Spartina maritima, Salicornia <lb/>veneta, and Suaeda maritima. The Conche (CO) salt marsh <lb/>fringes the mainland and faces the wide subtidal flat that oc-<lb/>cupies the central southern Venice Lagoon, being exposed <lb/>to Bora wind. CO hosts halophytic species dominated by <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Biogeosciences, 21, 2937-2954, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-2937-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">A. Puppin et al.: Spatial patterns of organic matter content in the surface soil of the salt marshes <lb/></note>

        <page>2941 <lb/></page>

        <body>Sarcocornia fruticosa, Suaeda maritima, Inula crithmoides, <lb/>and Halimione portulacoides. Finally, the Valle di Brenta <lb/>(VB) salt marsh, at the southern end of the lagoon, is sep-<lb/>arated from the mainland by a channel and is characterised <lb/>by the dominance of Juncus maritimus, Sarcocornia fruti-<lb/>cosa, Limonium narbonense, and Puccinellia palustris, with <lb/>the presence of Triglochin maritima. The marsh areas un-<lb/>der study were already mapped by Sebastiano Alberti in <lb/>1611, and, considering an overall accretion rate of about 2.0-<lb/>3.0 mm yr -1 , the study deposits were probably accumulated <lb/>over the past century (Tommasini et al., 2019). <lb/>2.2 Experimental design and sample analysis <lb/>Six sediment cores were collected along transects from the <lb/>marsh edge to the inner part of each of the 10 salt marshes for <lb/>a total of 60 cores. The selected sites are distributed across <lb/>the Venice Lagoon in order to represent the different envi-<lb/>ronmental conditions typical of the system (Fig. 1). Tran-<lb/>sects typically start on the marsh edge facing a channel and <lb/>therefore show a tide-dominated sedimentation. In contrast, <lb/>the CA and CO transects face tidal flats and are exposed to <lb/>energetic wind waves. At each site, cores were collected at <lb/>an increasing distance from the marsh edge (0, 2.5, 5, 10, <lb/>20, and 30 m) so as to represent morphological and vegeta-<lb/>tion zonation. The position of each core was surveyed us-<lb/>ing a GPS (Leica GS16) in RTK mode, and vegetation char-<lb/>acteristics were recorded within a 1 m × 1 m quadrat by the <lb/>Braun-Blanquet method (Braun-Blanquet, 1964) and regis-<lb/>tering species cover percentages (Table S3 in the Supple-<lb/>ment). The Shannon diversity index was used to measure the <lb/>diversity of species in each 1 m × 1 m quadrat. <lb/>Soil samples were taken every 5 cm up to the depth of <lb/>20 cm (0, 5, 10, 15, and 20 cm) from each core, collected <lb/>through a Eijkelkamp auger, 3 cm diameter corer (Howard <lb/>et al., 2014), and subsamples were oven-dried at 60 °C for <lb/>48 h or to constant weight and prepared for different anal-<lb/>yses, including OM and C content, soil density, and grain <lb/>size distribution. The percent of OM of each sample was <lb/>determined through a loss-on-ignition (LOI) procedure by <lb/>combusting ∼ 2 g of ground sediment in a muffle furnace at <lb/>375 °C for 16 h of ground samples (Ball, 1964; Frangipane <lb/>et al., 2009; Roner et al., 2016). The difference in weight be-<lb/>tween pre-and post-treatment provided the OM content as a <lb/>weight percentage. The percent of organic C was calculated <lb/>from LOI using the following local conversion equation built <lb/>on a subsample analysed with an elemental analyser (Puppin, <lb/>2023; Puppin et al., 2023b): <lb/>OC = (0.37 ± 0.01)LOI + (0.0024 ± 0.0004)LOI 2 . <lb/>(1) <lb/>Sediment dry bulk density (DBD) was calculated from <lb/>the water content as the difference in weight between wet <lb/>and dry samples and between organic and inorganic frac-<lb/>tions, according to Kolker et al. (2009), by assuming a water <lb/>density of 1.02 and a mineral and organic sediment density <lb/>of ρ i = 2.6 g m -3 and ρ o = 1.2 g m -3 , respectively, knowing <lb/>the inorganic sediment and OM percentage from LOI anal-<lb/>ysis (Kolker et al., 2009). The product of the percent of OC <lb/>and DBD determined soil carbon density (SCD). Soil carbon <lb/>stocks in the top 20 cm of the soil were calculated based on <lb/>Howard et al. (2014), summing the C content in each soil <lb/>interval along the core in order to better represent OM con-<lb/>tent variability within the depth interval. Inorganic particle <lb/>size distribution analyses were performed, after the removal <lb/>of the OM through a treatment with 35 % hydrogen peroxide <lb/>(H 2 O 2 ) for 36 h, using laser granulometry (Mastersizer 2000 <lb/>version 5.40, Malvern Instruments). <lb/>As to the analysis of OM content, we considered sediments <lb/>up to the depth of 20 cm because we wanted to investigate the <lb/>soil layer directly impacted by current vegetation. Indeed, ac-<lb/>cording to Trumbore (2009), in most vegetated ecosystems <lb/>the majority of underground plant biomass and microbial ac-<lb/>tivity exist within the top 20 cm of soils. Conversely, in order <lb/>to analyse sediment characteristics with reference to current <lb/>hydrodynamics and morphological dynamics, we limited the <lb/>reference depth for grain size analysis to 5 cm, considering <lb/>the accreting behaviour of salt marshes. <lb/>Values of water salinity for each study area were calcu-<lb/>lated as the mean of the last 5 years of quarterly measure-<lb/>ments from the CTD multiparameter probes of the Veneto <lb/>Region Environmental Protection Agency (ARPAV, 2024) <lb/>(Table S5). <lb/>2.3 Statistical analysis <lb/>Statistical analyses were performed using MATLAB <lb/>R2021a. Analyses included the use of the Kendall test, the <lb/>Kruskal-Wallis H test, and post hoc median comparisons. <lb/>The Kendall test is a non-parametric, rank-based method, <lb/>aimed to determine whether there exists a monotonic rela-<lb/>tionship between two variables of interest. The value of the <lb/>τ coefficient ranges from 1 to -1, indicating a positive or a <lb/>negative association, respectively. The Kruskal-Wallis test is <lb/>a non-parametric version of the classical one-way ANOVA <lb/>using ranks of data to compute the chi-square statistic and <lb/>compare the medians of the groups of data to determine if the <lb/>samples come from the same population. When the Kruskal-<lb/>Wallis test showed a significant difference between groups, a <lb/>multiple comparison test was used to determine which pairs <lb/>of means were significantly different. For the statistical tests, <lb/>we included all available data in the analysis without attempt-<lb/>ing to identify and eliminate possible outliers. <lb/>3 Results <lb/>3.1 Distribution of surface sediment variables along <lb/>the transects <lb/>We examined the distribution of the surface sediment OM <lb/>content, DBD, grain size distribution, and the vegetation <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-2937-2024 <lb/>Biogeosciences, 21, 2937-2954, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2942 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A. Puppin et al.: Spatial patterns of organic matter content in the surface soil of the salt marshes <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 2. Distribution of surface sediment variables analysed and the surface elevation profile along the transects in the northern lagoon: <lb/>organic matter content (LOI %; mean value and standard deviation in top 20 cm), dry bulk density (g cm -3 ; mean value and standard deviation <lb/>in top 20 cm), vegetation cover (%), grain size distribution (D 50 µm and sand-silt-clay percentage; mean value and standard deviation in top <lb/>5 cm), and surface elevation (m a.m.s.l.). The dashed line represents the linear regression between the percent of organic matter values. <lb/>cover along the surface elevation profile of study transects <lb/>in the northern (Fig. 2) and southern (Fig. 3) lagoon. <lb/>The topographic GPS field surveys (Figs. 2 and 3d, g, j, <lb/>m, and p) show that marsh surface elevations along the tran-<lb/>sects range between about 0.20 and 0.60 m a.m.s.l. CO is the <lb/>highest site, with an average elevation along the transect of <lb/>0.55 m a.m.s.l., while FO is the lowest site, with an average <lb/>elevation of 0.24 m a.m.s.l. Surface elevations are generally <lb/>higher near the marsh edge and adjacent to the channel lev-<lb/>ees, and they decrease toward the inner marsh. Some sites <lb/>show a pronounced levee morphology (i.e. SF, SA, and FO), <lb/>while at other sites the latter is less distinct due to irregular <lb/>profiles (i.e. MI, CV, and VB) or flattened profiles (i.e. PA <lb/>and SE). The CA and CO transects, which face a tidal flat and <lb/>are exposed to wave energy, are characterised by higher sur-<lb/>face elevations toward the inner marsh, with a convex shape <lb/>profile (Tognin, 2022). <lb/>The vegetation cover is generally high (never below 50 %), <lb/>with no detectable trends along the transects. <lb/>OM content in surface soils (mean value in top 20 cm) <lb/>ranges between 4 % and 30 % (green lines in Figs. 2 and 3b, <lb/>e, h, k, and n) and shows important differences both within <lb/>and among study areas. CA, FO, PA, VB, CV, and MI show <lb/>generally higher organic content, with average OM content <lb/>values along the transects ranging between 15 % and 21 %, <lb/>than CO, SF, SE, and SA, with average OM content values <lb/>along the transects ranging between 5 % and 7 %. Trends in <lb/>OM content along the transects suggest an increase toward <lb/>the inner marsh in most of the study sites (e.g. CA, PA, SF, <lb/>SE, CV, CO, and VB). The DBD in surface soil (grey lines in <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Biogeosciences, 21, 2937-2954, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-2937-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">A. Puppin et al.: Spatial patterns of organic matter content in the surface soil of the salt marshes <lb/></note>

        <page>2943 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 3. Distribution of surface sediment variables analysed and the surface elevation profile along the transects in the southern lagoon: <lb/>organic matter content (LOI %; mean value and standard deviation in top 20 cm), dry bulk density (g cm -3 ; mean value and standard deviation <lb/>in top 20 cm), vegetation cover (%), grain size distribution (D 50 µm and sand-silt-clay percentage; mean value and standard deviation in top <lb/>5 cm), and surface elevation (m a.m.s.l.). The dashed line represents the linear regression between the percent of organic matter values. <lb/>Figs. 2 and. 3b, e, h, k, and n) shows a distribution mirrored <lb/>to that of OM content, with values ranging between 0.28 and <lb/>1.15 g cm -3 , displaying a more or less marked decrease to-<lb/>ward the inner marsh in most of the study sites. The highest <lb/>values of DBD are found at the CO, SE, SF, and SA sites, <lb/>with average values of 1.02, 0.81, 0.94, and 0.80 g cm -3 , re-<lb/>spectively. <lb/>The grain size of the surface inorganic sediment fraction <lb/>(Figs. 2 and 3c, f, i, l, and o) ranges from clay to very fine <lb/>sand, with a D 50 (mean value in top 5 cm) ranging between 7 <lb/>and 28 µm, with a mean value of 14 µm. Finer median grain <lb/>size values are found at the PA site (average D 50 value of <lb/>5 µm), which is characterised by higher percentages of clay, <lb/>whereas coarser median grain size values are found at the <lb/>SF and CO sites (average D 50 value of 19 and 20 µm, re-<lb/>spectively), with the latter being characterised by some shell <lb/>layers on the marsh surface. As to the distribution of the me-<lb/>dian grain size, D 50 , along the transects, we observe coarser <lb/>grains along the marsh edges (i.e. along the tidal channel lev-<lb/>ees) at SF, SA, and VB. CA and CO median grain sizes show <lb/>a smooth trend with coarser particles in the central part of <lb/>the transects. The SE transect shows slightly coarsening sed-<lb/>iments toward the inner marsh, bordered by a tidal flat. <lb/>3.2 Dependence of sediment variables on the distance <lb/>from the marsh edge <lb/>Considering the data from all our study areas, OM content in <lb/>surface soils was significantly positively correlated with the <lb/>distance from the marsh edge (Kendall&apos;s tau test; τ = 0.1551, <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-2937-2024 <lb/>Biogeosciences, 21, 2937-2954, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2944 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A. Puppin et al.: Spatial patterns of organic matter content in the surface soil of the salt marshes <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 4. Effects of the distance from the marsh edge on OM, <lb/>DBD, and grain size: organic matter content (LOI %; mean value <lb/>in top 20 cm) (a), dry bulk density (g cm -3 ; mean value in the top <lb/>20 cm) (b), and sediment median grain size distribution (D 50 µm; <lb/>mean value in the top 5 cm) (c). In the box plots the central mark in-<lb/>dicates the median, and the bottom and top edges of the box indicate <lb/>the 25th and 75th percentiles, respectively. The whiskers extending <lb/>to the most extreme data points are not regarded as outliers. Swarm <lb/>plots show single values (circles). <lb/>p value = 0.0002) (Fig. 4a), whereas the DBD was signifi-<lb/>cantly negatively correlated with the distance from the marsh <lb/>edge (Kendall&apos;s tau test; τ = -0.2302, p value &lt; 0.0001) <lb/>(Fig. 4b). A significant negative correlation was also found <lb/>between the median sediment grain size (D 50 ) on the marsh <lb/>surface and the distance from the marsh edge (Kendall&apos;s tau <lb/>test; τ = -0.0924, p value = 0.0269) (Fig. 4c). The distance <lb/>from the marsh edge was negatively correlated to surface el-<lb/>evation in our study case (Kendall&apos;s tau test; τ = -0.1204, p <lb/>value = 0.0040); thus, as expected, DBD and D 50 were posi-<lb/>tively correlated to marsh surface elevations (τ = 0.1387 and <lb/>0.1503, p value = 0.0003 and 0.0001, respectively). Never-<lb/>theless, no significant relationship was found between the <lb/>OM content and surface elevation. <lb/>3.3 Vegetation distribution and influence on SOM <lb/>The vegetation surveys revealed that Sarcocornia fruticosa, <lb/>Limonium narbonense, Puccinellia palustris, and Juncus <lb/>maritimus are among the most abundant species in terms of <lb/>percent cover along the analysed transects (Fig. 5a). Sarco-<lb/>cornia fruticosa exhibits an increasing trend in cover with <lb/>distance from the marsh edge, peaking at approximately 5 m <lb/>from the edge before declining. Conversely, the cover of <lb/>Limonium narbonense and Puccinellia palustris increases <lb/>towards the inner marsh. The cover of Juncus maritimus <lb/>varies along the transect. At the lagoon scale, Phragmites <lb/>australis, typically found in brackish water environments, <lb/>was observed only at two sites, PA and MI (Fig. S1 in the <lb/>Supplement). Additionally, Puccinellia palustris was more <lb/>abundant at sites located in the southern part of the la-<lb/>goon (Fig. S1). We found no relationship between OM con-<lb/>tent and vegetation cover. When considering the dominant <lb/>species, OM content of marsh surface soil displayed a wide <lb/>variability (Fig. 5c). Higher mean organic content was ob-<lb/>served in the presence of Limonium narbonense (Fig. 5b) and <lb/>Phragmites australis (Fig. 5f) as dominant species. Although <lb/>highly variable, organic content showed a significant posi-<lb/>tive correlation with vegetation species diversity (Kendall&apos;s <lb/>tau test for Shannon diversity index H and OC stock in <lb/>top 20 cm: τ = 0.1931, p value = 0.0300. Mean SCD in top <lb/>20 cm: τ = 0.1818, p value = 0.0412) (Fig. 5d and e). <lb/>3.4 Variability in sediment characteristics among study <lb/>sites <lb/>As to the variability in marsh soil characteristics in differ-<lb/>ent areas, the Kruskal-Wallis analysis indicated that there <lb/>was a significant difference between OM content at the 10 <lb/>sites (p value = &lt; 0.0001), and the post hoc test confirmed <lb/>that CO, SA, SE, and SF have significantly lower mean OM <lb/>content in surface soil (Fig. 6a). Study sites were charac-<lb/>terised by different mean water salinity ranging between 24.3 <lb/>and 32.4 PSU, which revealed a significant negative relation-<lb/>ship with OM content (Kendall&apos;s tau test; τ = -0.3524, p <lb/>value = 0.0002). CO, SA, SE, and SF also show significantly <lb/>higher values of DBD (Kruskal-Wallis; p value = &lt; 0.0001) <lb/>(Fig. 6b). <lb/>Mean SOC density in the top 20 cm (product of the percent <lb/>of OC, which is function of the OM and DBD determined) <lb/>ranged between 0.014 and 0.026 g cm -3 with lower values <lb/>at SA, SF, and SE (Fig. 6b). Carbon stock in the top 20 cm <lb/>ranged between 0.21 and 0.66 g cm -2 , with lower values at <lb/>SA, SF, and SE (Fig. 6c). CO, which showed a mean organic <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Biogeosciences, 21, 2937-2954, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-2937-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">A. Puppin et al.: Spatial patterns of organic matter content in the surface soil of the salt marshes <lb/></note>

        <page>2945 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 5. Vegetation distribution and influence on SOM. Species cumulative percent cover at each station along the transect (a). Organic <lb/>matter content in marsh surface soils (LOI %; mean value in top 20 cm) as a function of dominant species (c). Organic matter content in <lb/>marsh surface soils (LOI %; mean value in top 20 cm) (d) and OC stock in the top 20 cm (e) as a function of the Shannon diversity index H in <lb/>the 1 m × 1 m plot around core sites. Limonium narbonense roots exposed by marsh edge erosion at the SE site (b) and Phragmites australis <lb/>roots and stems within PA site soil (f). Panel (c) includes mean values (horizontal-line markers) and standard deviations. Swarm plots show <lb/>single values (closed grey circles). Panels (d) and (e) include the median and standard deviation of binned values. Open circles represent <lb/>single values, and bold lines represent their linear regressions (OM = 9.91 +H 4.43, R 2 <lb/>= 0.0679, p value = 0.0444; C stock (20 cm) = 0.39 <lb/>+H 0.08, R 2 <lb/>= 0.0982, p value = 0.0147). INU: Inula crithmoides. AST: Aster tripolium. LIM: Limonium narbonense. SAL: Salicornia <lb/>veneta. SAR: Sarcocornia fruticosa. SPA: Spartina spp. HAL: Halimione portulacoides. SUA: Suaeda maritima. PUC: Puccinellia palustris. <lb/>JUN: Juncus maritimus. PHR: Phragmites australis. TRI: Triglochin maritima. <lb/>matter percentage similar to SA, SF, and SE, displays, in con-<lb/>trast, higher values of SCD and C stock compared to SA, SF, <lb/>and SE, due to particularly high DBD values at this site. <lb/>Median sediment grain size (D 50 ) on the marsh surface <lb/>was not equal at different study sites (Kruskal-Wallis; p <lb/>value = &lt; 0.0001), although it did not show clear distribu-<lb/>tion patterns (Fig. 6d). <lb/>4 Discussion <lb/>The sources of OM content in salt marsh soils are influenced <lb/>both by local and non-local processes. Firstly, OM is the <lb/>result of in situ production of belowground (root, rhizome, <lb/>and tuber tissue) (Craft et al., 1993; Rybczyk and Cahoon, <lb/>2002) and aboveground biomass, thus directly depending on <lb/>the local primary production. OM content is also affected <lb/>by the accumulation of organic material produced at other <lb/>sites (Nyman et al., 2006; Mudd et al., 2009; Ewer Lewis, <lb/>2019; Mueller et al., 2019), which is transported eventually <lb/>deposited on the marsh surface by hydrodynamic processes <lb/>(i.e. tides and waves) acting at larger spatial scales . Both au-<lb/>tochthonous and allochthonous organic materials, once part <lb/>of marsh soil, are also affected by decomposition resulting <lb/>from local topographic, sedimentological, and environmen-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-2937-2024 <lb/>Biogeosciences, 21, 2937-2954, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2946 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A. Puppin et al.: Spatial patterns of organic matter content in the surface soil of the salt marshes <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 6. Surface sediment variables at different study sites: organic content (LOI %; mean value in top 20 cm) and water salinity at each <lb/>study area (a), dry bulk density (g cm -3 ; mean value in top 20 cm) (b), OC stock in the top 20 cm (g cm -2 ) and SOC density (g cm -3 ; mean <lb/>value in top 20 cm) (c), grain size distribution (D 50 µm; mean value in top 5 cm) (d). In the box plots the central mark indicates the median, <lb/>and the bottom and top edges of the box indicate the 25th and 75th percentiles, respectively. The whiskers extending to the most extreme <lb/>data points are not regarded as outliers. Swarm plots show single values (circles). Different letters above the box plots indicate significant <lb/>differences on the basis of the Kruskal-Wallis test and post hoc multiple comparison test (when two groups do not show a significant <lb/>difference, they have at least one letter in common). <lb/>tal conditions (Chen et al., 2016). Due to the intricate in-<lb/>teraction of these local and non-local dynamics, two main <lb/>spatial scales in OM variations can be identified: the marsh <lb/>scale (metres to tens of metres) and the system scale (ranging <lb/>from kilometres, encompassing the entire lagoon or estuary). <lb/>In the following discussion, we will first examine evidence <lb/>of OM variations in our results at the marsh scale by consid-<lb/>ering trends along the transects. Subsequently, we will shift <lb/>our focus to the system scale by comparing results among <lb/>study sites. <lb/>At the marsh scale, our results show that OM content in <lb/>surface soils displays a significant trend with the distance <lb/>from the marsh edge, with OM content generally increasing <lb/>towards the inner marsh (Fig. 4a), consistently with previ-<lb/>ous findings (e.g. Chen et al., 2016; Leonard et al., 2002; <lb/>Roner et al., 2016). This overall trend in OM with distance <lb/>from the edge is influenced by various processes acting at the <lb/>marsh scale, among which the interaction between sediment <lb/>delivery and local topography plays a pre-eminent role. Sus-<lb/>pended material is primarily delivered onto the marsh plat-<lb/>form through inundation by overbank flow along tidal chan-<lb/>nels (Bayliss-Smith et al., 1979) and by apical flow at creek <lb/>heads (Torres and Styles, 2007). As soon as the flow reaches <lb/>the vegetated marsh platform, current velocities and turbu-<lb/>lent energy rapidly decrease (D&apos;Alpaos et al., 2007; Mudd <lb/>et al., 2010), thus promoting the deposition of more abundant <lb/>sediments during the flooding initial phase in close proxim-<lb/>ity of the marsh edge (Christiansen et al., 2000; Roner et al., <lb/>2016). As a result of the larger deposition close to the edge, <lb/>inner marshes generally present slightly lower elevation than <lb/>that of the marsh margin (Figs. 2 and 3). Lower elevations <lb/>promote the persistence of an anaerobic environment, which <lb/>slows down OM decomposition by reducing microbial respi-<lb/>ration (Halupa and Howes, 1995; Kirwan et al., 2013; Puppin <lb/>et al., 2023a; Roner et al., 2016). <lb/>Progressive energy dissipation over the vegetated marsh <lb/>platform also promotes selective material settling. Coarser, <lb/>denser inorganic sediment is mainly deposited near the marsh <lb/>edge, while the inner marsh receives a higher proportion of <lb/>finer sediments, as supported by the observed grain size dis-<lb/>tribution along the transect (Fig. 4c), and less dense organic <lb/>material (Leonard et al., 2002; Miller et al., 2022). In addi-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Biogeosciences, 21, 2937-2954, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-2937-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">A. Puppin et al.: Spatial patterns of organic matter content in the surface soil of the salt marshes <lb/></note>

        <page>2947 <lb/></page>

        <body>tion to the already larger proportion of organic material set-<lb/>tling in the inner marsh, the supply of finer inorganic sedi-<lb/>ment (Fig. 4c) may also promote conditions favourable for <lb/>OM preservation. This can occur due to the reduced oxygen <lb/>exchange resulting from the lower porosity and drainage ca-<lb/>pacity of finer sediments, as well as their greater potential for <lb/>protecting C from decay through organic mineral interactions <lb/>and the formation of micro-or macro-aggregates (Kelleway <lb/>et al., 2016). <lb/>Considering all available data along transects allows us to <lb/>capture global trends and average out variabilities related to <lb/>local conditions. However, analysing site-specific trends can <lb/>offer an interesting perspective on drivers locally affecting <lb/>OM dynamics. Overall, 7 out of 10 analysed transects show <lb/>an increasing trend in OM with the distance from the marsh <lb/>edge (CA, PA, SF, SE, CV, CO, and VB). At the SA, MI, and <lb/>FO study sites the trend in OM content deviates from the av-<lb/>erage behaviour, and this can be attributed to the effects of <lb/>local variability. At the SA site, observed OM content is very <lb/>low (Fig. 3n), and its distribution pattern may be masked by <lb/>the intrinsic variability in the measurements. At the MI site, <lb/>Phragmites australis grows on the marsh edge, providing a <lb/>contribution of OM that outcompetes that provided by the <lb/>halophytic vegetation of the inner marsh (Fig. S1). At the <lb/>FO site, we observed abundant beach-cast seagrass wracks <lb/>on the marsh edge, which are likely transported from the ex-<lb/>tensive seagrass meadows located on the tidal flats adjacent <lb/>to the FO area (Fig. 1f). These wracks may serve as an addi-<lb/>tional source of OM, locally influencing the OM trend with <lb/>the distance from the marsh margin. <lb/>Conversely, in some transects where the organic matter <lb/>trend aligns with the average increasing trend with distance <lb/>from the marsh margin, we observe particular cases in the <lb/>behaviour of grain size and topographic variables, which oc-<lb/>casionally deviate from the average trend. For example, at <lb/>the inner end of the SE transect, we can observe an unex-<lb/>pected slight increase both in sediment grain size (Fig. 2l) <lb/>and in topographic elevation (Fig. 2m). This may be related <lb/>to the presence of a tidal flat at the inner border of the SE <lb/>marsh (Fig. 1j), which can represent an additional source of <lb/>sediment supply. Two notable exceptions in terms of marsh <lb/>topography are also represented by the CA and CO marshes, <lb/>which face a tidal flat (Fig. 1b and h) and are exposed to ener-<lb/>getic wind waves. As a consequence of the influence of wind <lb/>waves, the elevation profiles exhibit a subtly convex shape, <lb/>with the disappearance of the raised margin and a slight in-<lb/>ward shift (i.e. between 5 and 10 m from the edge) of the <lb/>maximum elevation along with the locations of higher me-<lb/>dian grain size values. However, these variations do not ap-<lb/>pear to affect the overall increasing trend of OM content to-<lb/>wards the inner marsh at the SE, CA, and CO sites. <lb/>We also observe variations and patterns of OM at the sys-<lb/>tem scale. The position within the gradient generated by ma-<lb/>rine and fluvial influence was previously observed to be a key <lb/>predictor of OM content (e.g. Van de Broek et al., 2016; Ew-<lb/>ers Lewis et al., 2020; Kelleway et al., 2016; Macreadie et al., <lb/>2017). At the lagoon scale, our results show lower mean OM <lb/>content in surface soil in areas which are directly affected by <lb/>marine influence, being closer to the inlets or along the main <lb/>channels branching from them (CO, SE, SF, and SA) (Figs. 1 <lb/>and 6a). Conversely, higher OM contents are observed at <lb/>sites closer to the mainland, e.g. CA, MI, and PA. In agree-<lb/>ment with this result, a significant negative relationship is ob-<lb/>served between OM content and water salinity. However, it <lb/>is unlikely that salinity as such directly controls soil organic <lb/>content, as previous observations suggest an inverse relation-<lb/>ship between soil salinity and decomposition (Hemminga <lb/>et al., 1991; Wang et al., 2019). The effect of salinity on de-<lb/>composition may be overcome by the co-occurring effects <lb/>of other factors acting at different positions within the la-<lb/>goon, such as vegetation characteristics, hydrodynamic con-<lb/>ditions, sediment supply, and freshwater inputs. OM increase <lb/>at less-saline sites is likely minimally related to the supply <lb/>of already-stabilised organic suspended particles from terres-<lb/>trial sources as suggested for other study areas (e.g. Van de <lb/>Broek et al., 2016, 2018; Gorham et al., 2021; Omengo et al., <lb/>2016) because, in the Venice Lagoon, after historical river di-<lb/>versions, the fluvial supply of organic and inorganic material <lb/>dramatically decreased. However, residual freshwater inputs, <lb/>especially in terms of groundwater, can still locally reduce <lb/>salinity levels and consequently affect vegetation character-<lb/>istics, with usually increasing macrophyte biomass at lower <lb/>salinity values (Hansen et al., 2017; Van de Broek et al., <lb/>2016). <lb/>A relationship between OM and grain size can also be ob-<lb/>served at the lagoon scale. Higher values of median grain <lb/>size are observed at sites closer to the inlet (i.e. SF and SE) <lb/>or adjacent to first-order channels connected to them (SA) <lb/>(Fig. 6d), whereas higher fractions of fine sediments are ob-<lb/>served at the lagoon-mainland boundary near the Dese River <lb/>mouth (PA) (Fig. 2). This pattern is consistent with the gen-<lb/>eral grain size gradient observed in the Venice Lagoon, re-<lb/>flecting the typical pattern of decreasing hydrodynamic en-<lb/>ergy conditions from the inlets to the landward shore (Zonta <lb/>et al., 2018). Considering the landward decreasing grain size <lb/>gradient observed within the lagoon, enhanced C preserva-<lb/>tion capacity of fine sediments (Kelleway et al., 2016) may <lb/>have a role in the observed organic content pattern. Fur-<lb/>thermore, we may hypothesise that at sites where inorganic <lb/>sediment inputs are greater, where hydrodynamic energy is <lb/>higher, the soil organic fraction is proportionally lower. <lb/>Another potentially important factor controlling OM con-<lb/>tent is vegetation type, as different species exhibit varying <lb/>biomass production and decomposition resistance (e.g. Van <lb/>de Broek et al., 2016; Ewers Lewis et al., 2020; Ford et al., <lb/>2019; Saintilan et al., 2013; Yuan et al., 2020). <lb/>While our data do not allow for a full statistical analysis <lb/>of the relationship between OM content and vegetation type, <lb/>we can derive some interesting qualitative observations. We <lb/>find no discernible trend in vegetation cover along the tran-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-2937-2024 <lb/>Biogeosciences, 21, 2937-2954, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2948 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A. Puppin et al.: Spatial patterns of organic matter content in the surface soil of the salt marshes <lb/></note>

        <body>sects nor a significant relationship between OM content and <lb/>vegetation cover. <lb/>Considering the relationship between SOM and dominant <lb/>species, we observe that higher OM percentages in surface <lb/>soil are not necessarily associated with dominant species <lb/>having greater aboveground biomass (as reported in the lit-<lb/>erature; see Table S4). We speculate that the lack of a rela-<lb/>tionship between aboveground biomass and OM may be due <lb/>to the continuous transport and mixing of locally produced <lb/>litter by marsh flooding, weakening the effect of local above-<lb/>ground biomass production. Moreover, previous studies in-<lb/>dicate a major impact from belowground biomass, which, <lb/>inserted into the sediments, directly contributes to OM con-<lb/>tent (Craft et al., 1993; Rybczyk and Cahoon, 2002). The <lb/>highest mean organic contents are observed in the presence <lb/>of Limonium narbonense and Phragmites australis as dom-<lb/>inant species (Fig. 5c). Phragmites australis, characterised <lb/>by high aboveground biomass and even higher belowground <lb/>biomass, forms a dense and deep network of leathery stems, <lb/>roots, and rhizomes (Fig. 5f) (Moore et al., 2012; Scar-<lb/>ton et al., 2002). Limonium narbonense, despite low above-<lb/>ground biomass (Table S4), produces massive woody roots <lb/>(Fig. 5b) (Brooks et al., 2021). The belowground biomass <lb/>of these plants may importantly contribute to SOM content <lb/>quantitatively and qualitatively, as belowground litter decom-<lb/>position was observed to decline with increasing lignin con-<lb/>tent (Stagg et al., 2018; Puppin et al., 2023a). Interestingly, <lb/>these species are more abundant in locations associated with <lb/>higher values of SOM, such as the inner marsh for Limo-<lb/>nium narbonense and brackish areas for Phragmites australis <lb/>(Figs. 5a and S1). However, it was not feasible to directly <lb/>measure or estimate the relationship between aboveground <lb/>and belowground biomass and their effect on SOM content <lb/>in this study. <lb/>In addition, soil organic content shows a significant pos-<lb/>itive correlation with vegetation species diversity (Fig. 5d <lb/>and e) in agreement with Ford et al. (2019). Ford et al. (2016) <lb/>found that plant species richness was one of the most im-<lb/>portant explanatory variables of root biomass, and Xu et al. <lb/>(2020) suggested that species richness may increase biomass <lb/>productivity due to multiple mechanisms including competi-<lb/>tion reduction, niche complementarity, selection effects, and <lb/>biotic and abiotic facilitation. <lb/>Overall, the interplay of these dynamics at both marsh and <lb/>system scales also impacts sediment bulk density. We ob-<lb/>serve higher soil densities along marsh edges and at sites <lb/>such as CO, SE, SF, and SA, where organic content is gen-<lb/>erally lower and coarser sediments predominate (Figs. 4b <lb/>and 6b). This observation aligns with previous research in-<lb/>dicating that soil density is influenced by both organic mat-<lb/>ter content and grain size. Indeed, several studies have re-<lb/>ported a significant and negative correlation between SOM <lb/>and bulk density (e.g. Holmquist et al., 2018; Morris et al., <lb/>2016), while sand content has been shown to correlate posi-<lb/>tively with soil bulk density (Tanveera et al., 2016). <lb/>As a consequence of the variability in soil organic con-<lb/>tent and density both at the marsh and at the system scale, <lb/>SOC density and C stock show significant variations across <lb/>and within different salt marshes, enhancing the complex-<lb/>ity of blue C assessment. Based on our estimates of mean <lb/>SOC density in the top 20 cm, and considering an expected <lb/>accretion rate of about 0.3 cm yr -1 for salt marshes in equi-<lb/>librium with relative sea level rise (RSLR) (Day et al., <lb/>1998), the average C accumulation rate for the salt marshes <lb/>in the Venice Lagoon is estimated to be approximately <lb/>equal to 69 g C m -2 yr -1 . Our results are consistent with the <lb/>mean C accumulation rate in the Australian tidal marshes <lb/>of 54.52 g C m -2 yr -1 calculated by Macreadie et al. (2017) <lb/>from 323 soil cores to the depth of 30 cm all around Australia <lb/>and using a mean accretion rate of 0.21 cm yr -1 . However, <lb/>we observed that, under the same accretion rate, estimated <lb/>SOC from our study may result in C accumulation rates vary-<lb/>ing up to 50 % from one place to another because of the <lb/>two-scale variability highlighted by our measurements. This <lb/>underscores the need for careful consideration of local vari-<lb/>ability when assessing blue carbon sequestration and storage <lb/>potential in wetland environments. <lb/>5 Conclusions <lb/>Overall, our data reveal two scales of variations in sedimen-<lb/>tary OM content in salt marsh soils. One occurs at the marsh <lb/>scale and is influenced by the interplay between surface el-<lb/>evation and sediment supply dynamics along the distance <lb/>from the marsh edge. The other occurs at the system scale, <lb/>dominated by the gradient generated by marine and fluvial <lb/>influence. <lb/>The observations on morphological, sedimentological, and <lb/>vegetational features emphasise the dynamic feedbacks be-<lb/>tween hydrological dynamics, sediment supply, surface ele-<lb/>vation, and vegetation characteristics and allowed us to relate <lb/>them to SOM spatial patterns. <lb/>Our results show that OM content generally follows an <lb/>inverse relationship with the distance from the marsh edge <lb/>and, broadly, is greatest in salt marshes subjected to freshwa-<lb/>ter inputs and characterised by the presence of fine-grained <lb/>sediments. Although the interplay between physical and bio-<lb/>logical factors makes it difficult to unravel the direct cause-<lb/>effect relationship, variations in allochthonous inputs, sedi-<lb/>ment grain size, and/or preservation condition may explain <lb/>the observed variation in SOM. Our data on local vegeta-<lb/>tion do not allow us to detect plant community characteris-<lb/>tics controlling overall variations in SOM. Hence, we high-<lb/>light the need for further analyses of quantitative and qualita-<lb/>tive characteristics of different tidal marsh vegetation types. <lb/>However, species diversity was observed to be an important <lb/>factor influencing SOM content. <lb/>Our data on the spatial distribution of SOM provide addi-<lb/>tional insights on organic matter dynamics in salt marshes <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Biogeosciences, 21, 2937-2954, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-2937-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">A. Puppin et al.: Spatial patterns of organic matter content in the surface soil of the salt marshes <lb/></note>

        <page>2949 <lb/></page>

        <body>and inform model representations of SOM accumulation, <lb/>with the possibility to help improve the ability for biogeo-<lb/>morphological models to describe marsh response to the <lb/>effects of climate change and anthropogenic perturbation. <lb/>Moreover, our analyses emphasise the potential complica-<lb/>tions introduced by local variability in assessing the blue <lb/>carbon sequestration and storage potential in wetland envi-<lb/>ronments. This underscores the importance of carefully con-<lb/>sidering both the local variability and the factors influencing <lb/>it. Finally, our findings may inform conservation strategies <lb/>and restoration interventions, providing information on con-<lb/>ditions promoting OM storage and preservation, such as the <lb/>maintenance or recovery of freshwater inputs, the supply of <lb/>finer sediments, and the enhancement of vegetation diversity. <lb/></body>

        <div type="availability">Data availability. The <lb/>datasets <lb/>needed <lb/>to <lb/>evalu-<lb/>ate the conclusions in the paper are available at <lb/>https://doi.org/10.25430/researchdata.cab.unipd.it.00001240 <lb/>(Puppin et al., 2024). Salinity data for the Venice Lagoon are <lb/>also freely available at https://www.arpa.veneto.it/dati-ambientali/ <lb/>open-data/file-e-allegati/soaml/laguna-di-venezia/dati-sonda <lb/>(ARPAV, 2024). <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Supplement. The supplement related to this article is available on-<lb/>line at: https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-2937-2024-supplement. <lb/></div>

        <div type="contribution">Author contributions. AP, DT, AD, and MM designed the study. <lb/>AP, DT, AD, and MM developed the methodology. AP and DT col-<lb/>lected the data and performed laboratory analyses. EF and NR pro-<lb/>vided the instrumentation and tools for grain size analysis. AP and <lb/>DT were responsible for data analysis and interpretation with the <lb/>supervision of AD, MM, and MG. All the authors discussed the <lb/>data and agreed on their interpretation. AP wrote the original draft. <lb/>DT, AD, MG, and MM provided comments and suggestions to im-<lb/>prove the original draft. All the co-authors contributed to the final <lb/>polishing of the article. <lb/></div>

        <div type="conflict">Competing interests. The contact author has declared that none of <lb/>the authors has any competing interests. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Disclaimer. Publisher&apos;s note: Copernicus Publications remains <lb/>neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims made in the text, pub-<lb/>lished maps, institutional affiliations, or any other geographical rep-<lb/>resentation in this paper. While Copernicus Publications makes ev-<lb/>ery effort to include appropriate place names, the final responsibility <lb/>lies with the authors. <lb/></div>

        <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements. The authors thank the colleagues and technical <lb/>staff of the Department of Biology, the Department of Pharmaceu-<lb/>tical and Pharmacological Sciences, and the Department of Geo-<lb/>sciences, University of Padua, for fieldwork and laboratory analysis <lb/>support. <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">Financial support. This scientific activity was performed in the re-<lb/>search programme Venezia2021, coordinated by CORILA, with the <lb/>contribution of the Provveditorato for the Public Works of Veneto, <lb/>Trentino Alto Adige, and Friuli Venezia Giulia, Research Line 3.2 <lb/>(PI A.D.). The University of Padua SID2021 project, &quot;Unraveling <lb/>Carbon Sequestration Potential by Salt-Marsh Ecosystems&quot;, is also <lb/>acknowledged (PI A.D.). This study was carried out within the RE-<lb/>TURN Extended Partnership and received funding from the Euro-<lb/>pean Union NextGenerationEU (National Recovery and Resilience <lb/>Plan -NRRP, Mission 4, Component 2, Investment 1.3 -D.D. 1243 <lb/>2/8/2022, PE0000005). This study was carried out within the PRIN <lb/>2022 project &quot;Eco-geomorphic CArbon Pumping from rivers To <lb/>blUe caRbon Ecosystems&quot; (e-CAPTURE). <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Review statement. This paper was edited by Steven Bouillon and <lb/>reviewed by two anonymous referees. <lb/></div>

        <listBibl>References <lb/>Allen, J. R., Cornwell, J. C., and Baldwin, A. H.: Contributions of <lb/>organic and mineral matter to vertical accretion in tidal wetlands <lb/>across a chesapeake bay subestuary, J. Mar. Sci. Eng., 9, 751, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/jmse9070751, 2021. <lb/>Allen, J. R. L.: Morphodynamics of Holocene salt marshes: <lb/>A review sketch from the Atlantic and Southern North <lb/>sea coasts of Europe, Quaternary Sci. Rev., 19, 1255-1331, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/S0277-3791(00)00157-8, 2000. <lb/>Allen, J. R. L. and Pye, K. (Eds.): Saltmarshes, Morphodynamics, <lb/>Conservation and Engineering Significance, Cambridge Univer-<lb/>sity Press, Cambridge, 184 pp., 1992. <lb/>Ball, D. F.: Loss-on-ignition as an estimate of organic matter and <lb/>organic carbon in non-calcareous soils, J. Soil Sci., 15, 84-92, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2389.1964.tb00247.x, 1964. <lb/>Barbier, E. B., Hacker, S. D., Kennedy, C., Koch, E. W., <lb/>Stier, A. C., and Silliman, B. R.: The value of estuarine <lb/>and coastal ecosystem services, Ecol. Monogr., 81, 169-193, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1890/10-1510.1, 2011. <lb/>Bayliss-Smith, T. P., Healey, R., Lailey, R., Spencer, T., and Stod-<lb/>dart, D. R.: Tidal flows in salt marsh creeks, Estuar. Coast. Mar. <lb/>Sci., 9, 235-255, https://doi.org/10.1016/0302-3524(79)90038-<lb/>0, 1979. <lb/>Beeftink, W. G.: The coastal salt marshes of western and north-<lb/>ern Europe: an ecological and phytosociological approach, in: <lb/>Ecosystems of the World 1: wet coastal ecosystems, edited by: <lb/>Chapman, V. J., Elsevier, Amsterdam, ISBN-10 0444415602, <lb/>ISBN-13 978-0444415608, 1977. <lb/>Bertness, M. D. and Ellison, A. M.: Determinants of Pattern in a <lb/>New England Salt Marsh Plant Community, Ecol. Monogr., 57, <lb/>129-147, https://doi.org/10.2307/1942621, 1987. <lb/>Boesch, D. F. and Turner, R. E.: Dependence of Fishery Species on <lb/>Salt Marshes: The Role of Food and Refuge, Estuaries, 7, 460-<lb/>468, https://doi.org/10.2307/1351627, 1984. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-2937-2024 <lb/>Biogeosciences, 21, 2937-2954, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2950 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A. Puppin et al.: Spatial patterns of organic matter content in the surface soil of the salt marshes <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>Brambati, A., Carbognin, L., Quaia, T., Teatini, P., and <lb/>Tosi, L.: The Lagoon of Venice: Geological setting, <lb/>evolution and land subsidence, Episodes, 26, 264-265, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.18814/epiiugs/2003/v26i3/020, 2003. <lb/>Braun-Blanquet, J.: Pflanzensoziologie. Grundzüge der <lb/>Vegetationskunde, 3rd edn., Springer Vienna, Wien, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-7091-8110-2, 866 pp., 1964. <lb/>Breda, A., Saco, P. M., Rodríguez, J. F., Sandi, S. G., and Ric-<lb/>cardi, G.: Assessing the effects of sediment and tidal level vari-<lb/>ability on coastal wetland evolution, J. Hydrol., 613, 128387, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhydrol.2022.128387, 2022. <lb/>Brooks, H., Möller, I., Carr, S., Chirol, C., Christie, E., <lb/>Evans, B., Spencer, K. L., Spencer, T., and Royse, K.: Re-<lb/>sistance of salt marsh substrates to near-instantaneous hy-<lb/>drodynamic forcing, Earth Surf. Proc. Land., 46, 67-88, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/esp.4912, 2021. <lb/>Brückner, M. Z. M., Schwarz, C., van Dijk, W. M., van Oorschot, <lb/>M., Douma, H., and Kleinhans, M. G.: Salt Marsh Establishment <lb/>and Eco-Engineering Effects in Dynamic Estuaries Determined <lb/>by Species Growth and Mortality, J. Geophys. Res.-Earth, 124, <lb/>2962-2986, https://doi.org/10.1029/2019JF005092, 2019. <lb/>Carniello, L., Defina, A., and D&apos;Alpaos, L.: Morphological evo-<lb/>lution of the Venice lagoon: Evidence from the past and <lb/>trend for the future, J. Geophys. Res.-Earth, 114, F04002, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2008JF001157, 2009. <lb/>Chen, S., Torres, R., and Goñi, M. A.: The Role of Salt Marsh Struc-<lb/>ture in the Distribution of Surface Sedimentary Organic Mat-<lb/>ter, Estuar. Coast., 39, 108-122, https://doi.org/10.1007/s12237-<lb/>015-9957-z, 2016. <lb/>Chmura, G. L., Anisfeld, S. C., Cahoon, D. R. D. R., and <lb/>Lynch, J. C. J. C.: Global carbon sequestration in tidal, <lb/>saline wetland soils, Global Biogeochem. Cy., 17, 22-1, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2002GB001917, 2003. <lb/>Christiansen, T., Wiberg, P. L., and Milligan, T. G.: Flow and Sed-<lb/>iment Transport on a Tidal Salt Marsh Surface, Estuar. Coast. <lb/>Shelf S., 50, 315-331, https://doi.org/10.1006/ECSS.2000.0548, <lb/>2000. <lb/>Costanza, R., D&apos;Arge, R., De Groot, R., Farber, S., Grasso, M., Han-<lb/>non, B., Limburg, K., Naeem, S., O&apos;Neill, R. V. V, Paruelo, J., <lb/>Raskin, R. G., Sutton, P., and Van Den Belt, M.: The value of <lb/>the world&apos;s ecosystem services and natural capital, Nature, 387, <lb/>253-260, https://doi.org/10.1038/387253a0, 1997. <lb/>Craft, C. B., Seneca, E. D., and Broome, S. W.: Vertical <lb/>Accretion in Microtidal Regularly and Irregularly Flooded <lb/>Estuarine Marshes, Estuar. Coast. Shelf S., 37, 371-386, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1006/ecss.1993.1062, 1993. <lb/>D&apos;Alpaos, A.: The mutual influence of biotic and abiotic <lb/>components on the long-term ecomorphodynamic evolution <lb/>of salt-marsh ecosystems, Geomorphology, 126, 269-278, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/J.GEOMORPH.2010.04.027, 2011. <lb/>D&apos;Alpaos, A., Lanzoni, S., Marani, M., and Rinaldo, A.: Land-<lb/>scape evolution in tidal embayments: Modeling the interplay of <lb/>erosion, sedimentation, and vegetation dynamics, J. Geophys. <lb/>Res.-Earth, 112, F01008, https://doi.org/10.1029/2006JF000537, <lb/>2007. <lb/>D&apos;Alpaos, A., Mudd, S. M., and Carniello, L.: Dynamic response of <lb/>marshes to perturbations in suspended sediment concentrations <lb/>and rates of relative sea level rise, J. Geophys. Res.-Earth, 116, <lb/>F04020, https://doi.org/10.1029/2011JF002093, 2011. <lb/>D&apos;Alpaos, C. and D&apos;Alpaos, A.: The valuation of ecosystem ser-<lb/>vices in the venice lagoon: A multicriteria approach, Sustainabil-<lb/>ity, 13, 9485, https://doi.org/10.3390/su13179485, 2021. <lb/>D&apos;Alpaos, L.: Fatti e misfatti di idraulica lagunare. La laguna di <lb/>Venezia dalla diversione dei fiumi alle nuove opere delle boc-<lb/>che di porto, edited by: Istituto Veneto di Scienze Lettere e Arti, <lb/>329 pp., ISSN 1122-3642, ISBN 978-88-95996-21-9, 2010. <lb/>Day, J. W., Rismondo, A., Scarton, F., Are, D., and Cecconi, G.: <lb/>Relative sea level rise and Venice lagoon wetlands, J. Coast. Con-<lb/>serv., 4, 27-34, https://doi.org/10.1007/BF02806486, 1998. <lb/>Day, J. W., Rybczyk, J., Scarton, F., Rismondo, A., Are, D., <lb/>and Cecconi, G.: Soil accretionary dynamics, sea-level rise <lb/>and the survival of wetlands in Venice Lagoon: A field and <lb/>modelling approach, Estuar. Coast. Shelf S., 49, 607-628, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1006/ecss.1999.0522, 1999. <lb/>de Groot, R., Brander, L., van der Ploeg, S., Costanza, R., <lb/>Bernard, F., Braat, L., Christie, M., Crossman, N., Gher-<lb/>mandi, A., Hein, L., Hussain, S., Kumar, P., McVittie, A., <lb/>Portela, R., Rodriguez, L. C., ten Brink, P., and van Beuk-<lb/>ering, P.: Global estimates of the value of ecosystems and <lb/>their services in monetary units, Ecosyst. Serv., 1, 50-61, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/J.ECOSER.2012.07.005, 2012. <lb/>Drexler, J. Z., Davis, M. J., Woo, I., and De La Cruz, S.: <lb/>Carbon Sources in the Sediments of a Restoring vs. Histor-<lb/>ically Unaltered Salt Marsh, Estuar. Coast., 43, 1345-1360, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s12237-020-00748-7, 2020. <lb/>Duarte, C. M., Middelburg, J. J., and Caraco, N.: Major role of ma-<lb/>rine vegetation on the oceanic carbon cycle, Biogeosciences, 2, <lb/>1-8, https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-2-1-2005, 2005. <lb/>Ewers Lewis, C. J., Baldock, J. A., Hawke, B., Gadd, P. <lb/>S., Zawadzki, A., Heijnis, H., Jacobsen, G. E., Rogers, K., <lb/>and Macreadie, P. I.: Impacts of land reclamation on tidal <lb/>marsh &apos;blue carbon&apos; stocks, Sci. Total Environ., 672, 427-437, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.03.345, 2019. <lb/>Ewers Lewis, C. J., Young, M. A., Ierodiaconou, D., Baldock, J. <lb/>A., Hawke, B., Sanderman, J., Carnell, P. E., and Macreadie, P. <lb/>I.: Drivers and modelling of blue carbon stock variability in sedi-<lb/>ments of southeastern Australia, Biogeosciences, 17, 2041-2059, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-17-2041-2020, 2020. <lb/>Fagherazzi, S., Kirwan, M. L., Mudd, S. M., Guntenspergen, G. R. <lb/>G. R., Temmerman, S., D&apos;Alpaos, A., Van De Koppel, J., Ry-<lb/>bczyk, J. M. J. M., Reyes, E., Craft, C., Craft, C., and Clough, <lb/>J.: Numerical models of salt marsh evolution: Ecological, ge-<lb/>omorphic, and climatic factors, Rev. Geophys., 50, RG1002, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2011RG000359, 2012. <lb/>Fairchild, T. P., Bennett, W. G., Smith, G., Day, B., Skov, M. <lb/>W., Möller, I., Beaumont, N., Karunarathna, H., and Grif-<lb/>fin, J. N.: Coastal wetlands mitigate storm flooding and as-<lb/>sociated costs in estuaries, Environ. Res. Lett., 16, 74034, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/ac0c45, 2021. <lb/>Finotello, A., Tognin, D., Carniello, L., Ghinassi, M., Bertuzzo, <lb/>E., and D&apos;Alpaos, A.: Hydrodynamic Feedbacks of Salt-<lb/>Marsh Loss in the Shallow Microtidal Back-Barrier Lagoon <lb/>of Venice (Italy), Water Resour. Res., 59, e2022WR032881, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2022WR032881, 2023. <lb/>Ford, H., Garbutt, A., Ladd, C., Malarkey, J., and Skov, M. <lb/>W.: Soil stabilization linked to plant diversity and environ-<lb/>mental context in coastal wetlands, J. Veg. Sci., 27, 259-268, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/jvs.12367, 2016. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Biogeosciences, 21, 2937-2954, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-2937-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">A. Puppin et al.: Spatial patterns of organic matter content in the surface soil of the salt marshes <lb/></note>

        <page>2951 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>Ford, H., Garbutt, A., Duggan-Edwards, M., Pagès, J. F., Har-<lb/>vey, R., Ladd, C., and Skov, M. W.: Large-scale predictions <lb/>of salt-marsh carbon stock based on simple observations of <lb/>plant community and soil type, Biogeosciences, 16, 425-436, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-16-425-2019, 2019. <lb/>Frangipane, G., Pistolato, M., Molinaroli, E., Guerzoni, S., <lb/>and Tagliapietra, D.: Comparison of loss on ignition and <lb/>thermal analysis stepwise methods for determination of <lb/>sedimentary organic matter, Aquat. Conserv., 19, 24-33, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/aqc.970, 2009. <lb/>Friedrichs, C. T. and Perry, J. E.: Tidal Salt Marsh Morphodynam-<lb/>ics: A Synthesis, J. Coastal Res., 27, 7-37, 2001. <lb/>Gedan, K. B., Silliman, B. R., and Bertness, M. D.: <lb/>Centuries of Human-Driven Change in Salt Marsh <lb/>Ecosystems, Annu. Rev. Mar. Sci., 1, 117-141, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.marine.010908.163930, 2009. <lb/>Gieskes, J. M., Elwany, H., Rasmussen, L., Han, S., Rath-<lb/>burn, A., and Deheyn, D. D.: Salinity variations in the <lb/>Venice Lagoon, Italy: Results from the SIOSED Project, <lb/>May 2005-February 2007, Mar. Chem., 154, 77-86, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/J.MARCHEM.2013.05.011, 2013. <lb/>Gorham, C., Lavery, P., Kelleway, J. J., Salinas, C., and Serrano, <lb/>O.: Soil Carbon Stocks Vary Across Geomorphic Settings in <lb/>Australian Temperate Tidal Marsh Ecosystems, Ecosystems, 24, <lb/>319-334, https://doi.org/10.1007/S10021-020-00520-9, 2021. <lb/>Halupa, P. J. and Howes, B. L.: Effects of tidally medi-<lb/>ated litter moisture content on decomposition of Spartina <lb/>alterniflora and S. patens, Mar. Biol., 123, 379-391, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00353629, 1995. <lb/>Hansen, K., Butzeck, C., Eschenbach, A., Gröngröft, A., Jensen, K., <lb/>and Pfeiffer, E.-M.: Factors influencing the organic carbon pools <lb/>in tidal marsh soils of the Elbe estuary (Germany), J. Soils Sed-<lb/>iments, 17, 47-60, https://doi.org/10.1007/s11368-016-1500-8, <lb/>2017. <lb/>Hemminga, M. A., De Leeuw, J., De Munck, W., and Kout-<lb/>staal, B. P.: Decomposition in estuarine salt marshes: the ef-<lb/>fect of soil salinity and soil water content, Vegetatio, 94, 25-33, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00044913, 1991. <lb/>Holmquist, J. R., Windham-Myers, L., Bliss, N., Crooks, S., Mor-<lb/>ris, J. T., Megonigal, J. P., Troxler, T., Weller, D., Callaway, <lb/>J., Drexler, J., Ferner, M. C., Gonneea, M. E., Kroeger, K. D., <lb/>Schile-Beers, L., Woo, I., Buffington, K., Breithaupt, J., Boyd, B. <lb/>M., Brown, L. N., Dix, N., Hice, L., Horton, B. P., Macdonald, <lb/>G. M., Moyer, R. P., Reay, W., Shaw, T., Smith, E., Smoak, J. M., <lb/>Sommerfield, C., Thorne, K., Velinsky, D., Watson, E., Grimes, <lb/>K. W., and Woodrey, M.: Accuracy and precision of tidal wet-<lb/>land soil carbon mapping in the conterminous United States, Sci. <lb/>Rep.-UK, 8, 9478, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-26948-7, <lb/>2018. <lb/>Howard, J., Hoyt, S., Isensee, K., Telszewski, M., and Pidgeon, <lb/>E.: Coastal blue carbon: methods for assessing carbon stocks <lb/>and emissions factors in mangroves, tidal salt marshes, and sea-<lb/>grasses, edited by: Howard, J., Hoyt, S., Isensee, K., Telszewski, <lb/>M., and Pidgeon, E., Conservation International, Intergovern-<lb/>mental Oceanographic Commission of UNESCO, International <lb/>Union for Conservation of Nature, Arlington, Virginia, USA, <lb/>2014. <lb/>Kelleway, J. J., Saintilan, N., Macreadie, P. I., and Ralph, P. <lb/>J.: Sedimentary Factors are Key Predictors of Carbon Stor-<lb/>age in SE Australian Saltmarshes, Ecosystems, 19, 865-880, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10021-016-9972-3, 2016. <lb/>Keuskamp, J. A., Dingemans, B. J. J., Lehtinen, T., Sarneel, J. M., <lb/>and Hefting, M. M.: Tea Bag Index: A novel approach to collect <lb/>uniform decomposition data across ecosystems, Methods Ecol. <lb/>Evol., 4, 1070-1075, https://doi.org/10.1111/2041-210X.12097, <lb/>2013. <lb/>Kirwan, M. L. and Murray, A. B.: A coupled geomorphic and eco-<lb/>logical model of tidal marsh evolution, P. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, <lb/>104, 6118-6122, https://doi.org/10.1073/PNAS.0700958104, <lb/>2007. <lb/>Kirwan, M. L., Guntenspergen, G. R., D&apos;Alpaos, A., Morris, J. T., <lb/>Mudd, S. M., and Temmerman, S.: Limits on the adaptability <lb/>of coastal marshes to rising sea level, Geophys. Res. Lett., 37, <lb/>L23401, https://doi.org/10.1029/2010GL045489, 2010. <lb/>Kirwan, M. L., Langley, J. A., Guntenspergen, G. R., and Megoni-<lb/>gal, J. P.: The impact of sea-level rise on organic matter decay <lb/>rates in Chesapeake Bay brackish tidal marshes, Biogeosciences, <lb/>10, 1869-1876, https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-10-1869-2013, 2013. <lb/>Kirwan, M. L., Guntenspergen, G. R., and Langley, J. A.: Tem-<lb/>perature sensitivity of organic-matter decay in tidal marshes, <lb/>Biogeosciences, 11, 4801-4808, https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-11-<lb/>4801-2014, 2014. <lb/>Kolker, A. S., Goodbred, S. L., Hameed, S., and Cochran, <lb/>J. K.: High-resolution records of the response of coastal <lb/>wetland systems to long-term and short-term sea-<lb/>level variability, Estuar. Coast. Shelf S., 84, 493-508, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecss.2009.06.030, 2009. <lb/>Lefeuvre, J.-C., Laffaille, P., Feunteun, E., Bouchard, V., and <lb/>Radureau, A.: Biodiversity in salt marshes: from patrimo-<lb/>nial value to ecosystem functioning. The case study of <lb/>the Mont-Saint-Michel bay, C. R. Biol., 326, 125-131, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/S1631-0691(03)00049-0, 2003. <lb/>Leonard, L. A., Wren, P. A., and Beavers, R. L.: Flow dy-<lb/>namics and sedimentation in Spartina alterniflora and <lb/>Phragmites australis marshes of the Chesapeake Bay, <lb/>Wetlands, <lb/>22, <lb/>415-424, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1672/0277-<lb/>5212(2002)022[0415:FDASIS]2.0.CO;2, 2002. <lb/>Macreadie, P. I., Ollivier, Q. R., Kelleway, J. J., Serrano, O., <lb/>Carnell, P. E., Ewers Lewis, C. J., Atwood, T. B., Sander-<lb/>man, J., Baldock, J., Connolly, R. M., Duarte, C. M., Lav-<lb/>ery, P. S., Steven, A., and Lovelock, C. E.: Carbon seques-<lb/>tration by Australian tidal marshes, Sci. Rep.-UK, 7, 44071, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/srep44071, 2017. <lb/>Macreadie, P. I., Anton, A., Raven, J. A., Beaumont, N., Connolly, <lb/>R. M., Friess, D. A., Kelleway, J. J., Kennedy, H., Kuwae, T., <lb/>Lavery, P. S., Lovelock, C. E., Smale, D. A., Apostolaki, E. T., <lb/>Atwood, T. B., Baldock, J., Bianchi, T. S., Chmura, G. L., Eyre, <lb/>B. D., Fourqurean, J. W., Hall-Spencer, J. M., Huxham, M., Hen-<lb/>driks, I. E., Krause-Jensen, D., Laffoley, D., Luisetti, T., Marbà, <lb/>N., Masque, P., McGlathery, K. J., Megonigal, J. P., Murdi-<lb/>yarso, D., Russell, B. D., Santos, R., Serrano, O., Silliman, B. R., <lb/>Watanabe, K., and Duarte, C. M.: The future of Blue Carbon sci-<lb/>ence, Nat. Commun., 10, 1-13, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-<lb/>019-11693-w, 2019. <lb/>Marani, M., Belluco, E., Ferrari, S., Silvestri, S., D&apos;Alpaos, <lb/>A., Lanzoni, S., Feola, A., and Rinaldo, A.: Analy-<lb/>sis, synthesis and modelling of high-resolution obser-<lb/>vations of salt-marsh eco-geomorphological patterns in <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-2937-2024 <lb/>Biogeosciences, 21, 2937-2954, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2952 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A. Puppin et al.: Spatial patterns of organic matter content in the surface soil of the salt marshes <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>the Venice lagoon, Estuar. Coast. Shelf S., 69, 414-426, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecss.2006.05.021, 2006. <lb/>Marani, M., D&apos;Alpaos, A., Lanzoni, S., Carniello, L., and Rinaldo, <lb/>A.: Biologically-controlled multiple equilibria of tidal landforms <lb/>and the fate of the Venice lagoon, Geophys. Res. Lett., 34, <lb/>L11402, https://doi.org/10.1029/2007GL030178, 2007. <lb/>Marani, M., Da Lio, C., and D&apos;Alpaos, A.: Vegetation en-<lb/>gineers marsh morphology through multiple competing sta-<lb/>ble states, P. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 110, 3259-3263, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1218327110, 2013. <lb/>McLeod, E., Chmura, G. L., Bouillon, S., Salm, R., Björk, M., <lb/>Duarte, C. M., Lovelock, C. E., Schlesinger, W. H., and Sil-<lb/>liman, B. R.: A blueprint for blue carbon: Toward an im-<lb/>proved understanding of the role of vegetated coastal habi-<lb/>tats in sequestering CO 2 , Front. Ecol. Environ., 9, 552-560, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1890/110004, 2011. <lb/>Mcowen, C. J., Weatherdon, L. V, Van Bochove, J.-W., Sulli-<lb/>van, E., Blyth, S., Zockler, C., Stanwell-Smith, D., Kingston, <lb/>N., Martin, C. S., Spalding, M., Fletcher, S., Van Bochove, <lb/>J.-W., Sullivan, E., Blyth, S., Zockler, C., Stanwell-Smith, D., <lb/>Kingston, N., Martin, C. S., Spalding, M., Fletcher, S., Bochove, <lb/>J.-W., Sullivan, E., Blyth, S., Zockler, C., Stanwell-Smith, D., <lb/>Kingston, N., Martin, C. S., Spalding, M., and Fletcher, S.: <lb/>A global map of saltmarshes, Biodivers. Data J., 5, e11764, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3897/BDJ.5.e11764, 2017. <lb/>Mel, R. A., Viero, D. P., Carniello, L., Defina, A., and D&apos;Alpaos, <lb/>L.: The first operations of Mo.S. E. system to prevent <lb/>the flooding of Venice: Insights on the hydrodynamics of <lb/>a regulated lagoon, Estuar. Coast. Shelf S., 261, 107547, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecss.2021.107547, 2021. <lb/>Middelburg, J. J., Nieuwenhuize, J., Lubberts, R. K., and <lb/>Van De Plassche, O.: Organic carbon isotope systematics <lb/>of coastal marshes, Estuar. Coast. Shelf S., 45, 681-687, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1006/ecss.1997.0247, 1997. <lb/>Miller, C. B., Rodriguez, A. B., Bost, M. C., Mckee, B. A., and Mc-<lb/>tigue, N. D.: Carbon accumulation rates are highest at young and <lb/>expanding salt marsh edges, Commun. Earth Environ., 3, 173, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-022-00501-x, 2022. <lb/>Möller, I., Kudella, M., Rupprecht, F., Spencer, T., Paul, M., <lb/>Van Wesenbeeck, B. K., Wolters, G., Jensen, K., Bouma, <lb/>T. J., Miranda-Lange, M., Miranda-Lange, M., and Schim-<lb/>mels, S.: Wave attenuation over coastal salt marshes un-<lb/>der storm surge conditions, Nat. Geosci., 7, 727-731, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/NGEO2251, 2014. <lb/>Moore, G. E., Burdick, D. M., Peter, C. R., and Keirstead, <lb/>D. R.: Belowground Biomass of Phragmites australis <lb/>in Coastal Marshes, Northeast. Nat., 19, 611-626, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1656/045.019.0406, 2012. <lb/>Morris, J. T., Sundareshwar, P. V., Nietch, C. T., Kjerfve, B., <lb/>and Cahoon, D. R.: Responses of coastal wetlands to rising <lb/>sea level, Ecology, 83, 2869-2877, https://doi.org/10.1890/0012-<lb/>9658(2002)083[2869:ROCWTR]2.0.CO;2, 2002. <lb/>Morris, J. T., Barber, D. C., Callaway, J. C., Chambers, R., Ha-<lb/>gen, S. C., Hopkinson, C. S., Johnson, B. J., Megonigal, P., <lb/>Neubauer, S. C., Troxler, T., and Wigand, C.: Contributions of <lb/>organic and inorganic matter to sediment volume and accre-<lb/>tion in tidal wetlands at steady state, Earths Future, 4, 110-121, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/2015EF000334, 2016. <lb/>Mueller, P., Ladiges, N., Jack, A., Schmiedl, G., Kutzbach, <lb/>L., Jensen, K., and Nolte, S.: Assessing the long-term <lb/>carbon-sequestration potential of the semi-natural salt <lb/>marshes in the European Wadden Sea, Ecosphere, 10, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/ecs2.2556, 2019. <lb/>Mudd, S. M.: The life and death of salt marshes in response to an-<lb/>thropogenic disturbance of sediment supply, Geology, 39, 511-<lb/>512, https://doi.org/10.1130/focus052011.1, 2011. <lb/>Mudd, S. M., Fagherazzi, S., Morris, J. T., and Furbish, D. J.: Flow, <lb/>Sedimentation, and Biomass Production on a Vegetated Salt <lb/>Marsh in South Carolina: Toward a Predictive Model of Marsh <lb/>Morphologic and Ecologic Evolution, in: The Ecogeomorphol-<lb/>ogy of Tidal Marshes -Volume 59, edited by: Fagherazzi, S., <lb/>Marani, M., and Blum, L. K., American Geophysical Union <lb/>(AGU), 165-188, https://doi.org/10.1029/CE059p0165, 2004. <lb/>Mudd, S. M., Howell, S. M., and Morris, J. T.: Impact of dy-<lb/>namic feedbacks between sedimentation, sea-level rise, and <lb/>biomass production on near-surface marsh stratigraphy and <lb/>carbon accumulation, Estuar. Coast. Shelf S., 82, 377-389, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecss.2009.01.028, 2009. <lb/>Mudd, S. M., D&apos;Alpaos, A., and Morris, J. T.: How does vege-<lb/>tation affect sedimentation on tidal marshes? Investigating par-<lb/>ticle capture and hydrodynamic controls on biologically me-<lb/>diated sedimentation, J. Geophys. Res.-Earth, 115, F03029, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2009JF001566, 2010. <lb/>Mueller, P., Schile-Beers, L. M., Mozdzer, T. J., Chmura, G. L., <lb/>Dinter, T., Kuzyakov, Y., de Groot, A. V., Esselink, P., Smit, <lb/>C., D&apos;Alpaos, A., Ibáñez, C., Lazarus, M., Neumeier, U., John-<lb/>son, B. J., Baldwin, A. H., Yarwood, S. A., Montemayor, D. <lb/>I., Yang, Z., Wu, J., Jensen, K., and Nolte, S.: Global-change <lb/>effects on early-stage decomposition processes in tidal wet-<lb/>lands -implications from a global survey using standardized lit-<lb/>ter, Biogeosciences, 15, 3189-3202, https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-<lb/>15-3189-2018, 2018. <lb/>Mueller, P., Ladiges, N., Jack, A., Schmiedl, G., Kutzbach, <lb/>L., Jensen, K., and Nolte, S.: Assessing the long-term <lb/>carbon-sequestration potential of the semi-natural salt marshes <lb/>in the European Wadden Sea, Ecosphere, 10, e02556, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/ecs2.2556, 2019. <lb/>Nellemann, C., Corcoran, E., Duarte, C. M., Valdes, L., DeYoung, <lb/>C., Fonseca, L., and Grimsditch, G.: Blue carbon: A Rapid Re-<lb/>sponse Assessment, edited by: Nellemann, C., Corcoran, E., <lb/>Duarte, C. M., Valdés, L., De Young, C., Fonseca, L., and Grims-<lb/>ditch, G., UN Environment, GRID-Arendal, ISBN 978-82-7701-<lb/>060-1, 2009. <lb/>Neubauer, S. C.: Contributions of mineral and organic components <lb/>to tidal freshwater marsh accretion, Estuar. Coast. Shelf S., 78, <lb/>78-88, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecss.2007.11.011, 2008. <lb/>Nyman, J. A., Walters, R. J., Delaune, R. D., and <lb/>Patrick, W. H.: Marsh vertical accretion via vege-<lb/>tative growth, Estuar. Coast. Shelf S., 69, 370-380, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecss.2006.05.041, 2006. <lb/>Omengo, F. O., Geeraert, N., Bouillon, S., and Govers, <lb/>G.: Deposition and fate of organic carbon in flood-<lb/>plains along a tropical semiarid lowland river (Tana <lb/>River, Kenya), J. Geophys. Res.-Biogeo., 121, 1131-1143, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/2015JG003288, 2016. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Biogeosciences, 21, 2937-2954, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-2937-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">A. Puppin et al.: Spatial patterns of organic matter content in the surface soil of the salt marshes <lb/></note>

        <page>2953 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>Pennings, S. C. and Callaway, R. M.: Salt Marsh Plant Zonation: <lb/>The Relative Importance of Competition and Physical Factors, <lb/>Ecology, 73, 681-690, https://doi.org/10.2307/1940774, 1992. <lb/>Perillo, G. M. E., Wolanski, E., Cahoon, D. R., and Hopkinson, <lb/>C. S.: Coastal wetlands: an integrated ecosystem approach, II, <lb/>edited by: Perillo, G. M. E., Wolanski E., Cahoon, D. R., and <lb/>Hopkinson, C. S., Elsevier, ISBN 978-0-444-63893-9, 2009. <lb/>Puppin, A.: Soil organic matter and carbon dynamics in Venice <lb/>Lagoon salt marshes under natural and anthropogenic forc-<lb/>ing, University of Padova, https://doi.org/https://hdl.handle.net/ <lb/>11577/3472562 (last access: 10 June 2024), 2023. <lb/>Puppin, A., Roner, M., Finotello, A., Ghinassi, M., Tommasini, L., <lb/>Marani, M., and D&apos;Alpaos, A.: Analysis of Organic Matter De-<lb/>composition in the Salt Marshes of the Venice Lagoon (Italy) <lb/>Using Standard Litter Bags, J. Geophys. Res.-Biogeo., 128, <lb/>e2022JG007289, https://doi.org/10.1029/2022JG007289, 2023a. <lb/>Puppin, A., Tognin, D., Paccagnella, M., Zancato, M., Ghinassi, <lb/>M., D&apos;Alpaos, C., Marani, M., and D&apos;Alpaos, A.: Blue Car-<lb/>bon assessment in the salt marshes of the Venice Lagoon: di-<lb/>mensions, variability and influence of storm-surge regulation, <lb/>Res. Sq. [preprint], https://doi.org/10.21203/rs.3.rs-3639902/v1, <lb/>2023b. <lb/>Puppin, A., Tognin, D., and D&apos;Alpaos, A.: Spatial patterns of Or-<lb/>ganic Matter content in the surface soil of the salt marshes <lb/>of the Venice Lagoon (Italy), Research Data Unipd [data <lb/>set], https://doi.org/10.25430/RESEARCHDATA.CAB.UNIPD. <lb/>IT.00001240, 2024. <lb/>Roner, M., D&apos;Alpaos, A., Ghinassi, M., Marani, M., Sil-<lb/>vestri, S., Franceschinis, E., and Realdon, N.: Spatial <lb/>variation of salt-marsh organic and inorganic deposition <lb/>and organic carbon accumulation: Inferences from the <lb/>Venice lagoon, Italy, Adv. Water Resour., 93, 276-287, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.advwatres.2015.11.011, 2016. <lb/>Rybczyk, J. M. and Cahoon, D. R.: Estimating the potential for sub-<lb/>mergence for two wetlands in the Mississippi River delta, Estu-<lb/>aries, 25, 985-998, https://doi.org/10.1007/BF02691346, 2002. <lb/>Saintilan, N., Rogers, K., Mazumder, D., and Woodroffe, <lb/>C.: Allochthonous and autochthonous contributions to car-<lb/>bon accumulation and carbon store in southeastern Aus-<lb/>tralian coastal wetlands, Estuar. Coast. Shelf S., 128, 84-92, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecss.2013.05.010, 2013. <lb/>Scarton, F., Day, J. W., and Rismondo, A.: Primary production and <lb/>decomposition of Sarcocornia fruticosa (L.) scott and Phrag-<lb/>mites australis Trin. Ex Steudel in the Po Delta, Italy, Estuaries, <lb/>25, 325-336, https://doi.org/10.1007/BF02695977, 2002. <lb/>Silvestri, S.: La vegetazione alofila quale indicatore morfologico <lb/>negli ambienti a marea, University of Padova, 2000. <lb/>Silvestri, S. and Marani, M.: Salt-Marsh Vegetation and Morphol-<lb/>ogy: Basic Physiology, Modelling and Remote Sensing Obser-<lb/>vations, Ecogeomorphology Tidal Marshes, Coast. Estuar. Stud, <lb/>59, 5-25, https://doi.org/10.1029/ce059p0005, 2004. <lb/>Silvestri, S., Defina, A., and Marani, M.: Tidal regime, salinity and <lb/>salt marsh plant zonation, Estuar. Coast. Shelf S., 62, 119-130, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecss.2004.08.010, 2005. <lb/>Silvestri, S., D&apos;Alpaos, A., Nordio, G., and Carniello, L.: An-<lb/>thropogenic Modifications Can Significantly Influence the Lo-<lb/>cal Mean Sea Level and Affect the Survival of Salt Marshes in <lb/>Shallow Tidal Systems, J. Geophys. Res.-Earth, 123, 996-1012, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2017JF004503, 2018. <lb/>Stagg, C. L., Baustian, M. M., Perry, C. L., Carruthers, T. J. <lb/>B., and Hall, C. T.: Direct and indirect controls on organic <lb/>matter decomposition in four coastal wetland communities <lb/>along a landscape salinity gradient, J. Ecol., 106, 655-670, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2745.12901, 2018. <lb/>Tanveera, A., Kanth, T. A., Tali, P. A., and Naikoo, M.: Relation of <lb/>soil bulk density with texture, total organic matter content and <lb/>porosity in the soils of Kandi Area of Kashmir valley, India, Int. <lb/>J. Earth Sci., 4, 1-6, 2016. <lb/>Temmerman, S., Bouma, T. J., Govers, G., Wang, Z. B., De Vries, <lb/>M. B., and Herman, P. M. J.: Impact of vegetation on flow <lb/>routing and sedimentation patterns: Three-dimensional model-<lb/>ing for a tidal marsh, J. Geophys. Res.-Earth, 110, F04019, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2005JF000301, 2005. <lb/>Temmerman, S., Meire, P., Bouma, T. J., Herman, P. M. J., <lb/>Ysebaert, T., and De Vriend, H. J.: Ecosystem-based coastal <lb/>defence in the face of global change, Nature, 504, 79-83, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/nature12859, 2013. <lb/>Tognin, D.: Natural and anthropogenic drivers of erosional and <lb/>depositional dynamics in shallow tidal systems, University <lb/>of Padova, https://doi.org/https://hdl.handle.net/11577/3446285 <lb/>(last access: 10 June 2024), 2022. <lb/>Tognin, D., D&apos;Alpaos, A., Marani, M., and Carniello, L.: <lb/>Marsh resilience to sea-level rise reduced by storm-surge <lb/>barriers in the Venice Lagoon, Nat. Geosci., 14, 906-911, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-021-00853-7, 2021. <lb/>Tognin, D., Finotello, A., D&apos;Alpaos, A., Viero, D. P., Pivato, M., <lb/>Mel, R. A., Defina, A., Bertuzzo, E., Marani, M., and Carniello, <lb/>L.: Loss of geomorphic diversity in shallow tidal embayments <lb/>promoted by storm-surge barriers, Sci. Adv., 8, eabm8446, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.abm8446, 2022. <lb/>Tommasini, L., Carniello, L., Ghinassi, M., Roner, M., and <lb/>D&apos;Alpaos, A.: Changes in the wind-wave field and related salt-<lb/>marsh lateral erosion: inferences from the evolution of the Venice <lb/>Lagoon in the last four centuries, Earth Surf. Proc. Land., 44, <lb/>1633-1646, https://doi.org/10.1002/esp.4599, 2019. <lb/>Torres, R. and Styles, R.: Effects of topographic structure on <lb/>salt marsh currents, J. Geophys. Res.-Earth, 112, F02023, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2006JF000508, 2007. <lb/>Trumbore, S.: Radiocarbon and Soil Carbon Dy-<lb/>namics, Annu. Rev. Earth Pl. Sci., 37, 47-66, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.earth.36.031207.124300, 2009. <lb/>Van de Broek, M., Temmerman, S., Merckx, R., and Govers, G.: <lb/>Controls on soil organic carbon stocks in tidal marshes along <lb/>an estuarine salinity gradient, Biogeosciences, 13, 6611-6624, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-13-6611-2016, 2016. <lb/>Van de Broek, M., Vandendriessche, C., Poppelmonde, D., Merckx, <lb/>R., Temmerman, S., and Govers, G.: Long-term organic carbon <lb/>sequestration in tidal marsh sediments is dominated by old-aged <lb/>allochthonous inputs in a macrotidal estuary, Glob. Change Biol., <lb/>24, 2498-2512, https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.14089, 2018. <lb/>Veneto Region Environmental Protection Agency (ARPAV): <lb/>Laguna di Venezia -dati sonda, https://www.arpa. <lb/>veneto.it/dati-ambientali/open-data/file-e-allegati/soaml/ <lb/>laguna-di-venezia/dati-sonda (last access: 10 June 2024), 2024. <lb/>Wang, F., Kroeger, K. D., Gonneea, M. E., Pohlman, J. <lb/>W., and Tang, J.: Water salinity and inundation con-<lb/>trol soil carbon decomposition during salt marsh restora-<lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-2937-2024 <lb/>Biogeosciences, 21, 2937-2954, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2954 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">A. Puppin et al.: Spatial patterns of organic matter content in the surface soil of the salt marshes <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>tion: An incubation experiment, Ecol. Evol., 9, 1911-1921, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/ece3.4884, 2019. <lb/>Watson, R., Noble, I., Bolin, B., Ravindranath, N., Verardo, D., and <lb/>Dokken, D.: Land Use, Land-Use Change, and Forestry, Inter-<lb/>governmental Panel on Climate Change Special Report, ISBN-<lb/>10 0521800838, ISBN-13 978-0521800839, 2000. <lb/>Xu, S., Eisenhauer, N., Ferlian, O., Zhang, J., Zhou, G., Lu, X., <lb/>Liu, C., and Zhang, D.: Evidence synthesis Species richness pro-<lb/>motes ecosystem carbon storage: evidence from biodiversity-<lb/>ecosystem functioning experiments, P. R. Soc. B, 287, 1-14, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2020.2063, 2020. <lb/>Yang, Z., D&apos;Alpaos, A., Marani, M., and Silvestri, S.: Assessing <lb/>the fractional abundance of highly mixed salt-marsh vegetation <lb/>using random forest soft classification, Remote Sens.-Basel, 12, <lb/>1-25, https://doi.org/10.3390/rs12193224, 2020. <lb/>Yousefi Lalimi, F., Silvestri, S., D&apos;Alpaos, A., Roner, <lb/>M., and Marani, M.: The Spatial Variability of Or-<lb/>ganic Matter and Decomposition Processes at the Marsh <lb/>Scale, J. Geophys. Res.-Biogeo., 123, 3713-3727, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2017JG004211, 2018. <lb/>Yuan, Y., Li, X., Jiang, J., Xue, L., and Craft, C. B.: Distribution of <lb/>organic carbon storage in different salt-marsh plant communities: <lb/>A case study at the Yangtze Estuary, Estuar. Coast. Shelf S., 243, <lb/>106900, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecss.2020.106900, 2020. <lb/>Zecchin, M., Brancolini, G., Tosi, L., Rizzetto, F., Caffau, <lb/>M., and Baradello, L.: Anatomy of the Holocene succes-<lb/>sion of the southern Venice lagoon revealed by very high-<lb/>resolution seismic data, Cont. Shelf Res., 29, 1343-1359, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/J.CSR.2009.03.006, 2009. <lb/>Zirino, A., Elwany, H., Neira, C., Maicu, F., Mendoza, G., <lb/>and Levin, L. A.: Salinity and its variability in the Lagoon <lb/>of Venice, 2000-2009, Adv. Oceanogr. Limnol., 5, 41-59, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/19475721.2014.900113, 2014. <lb/>Zonta, R., Botter, M., Cassin, D., Bellucci, L. G., Pini, R., and <lb/>Dominik, J.: Sediment texture and metal contamination in the <lb/>Venice Lagoon (Italy): A snapshot before the installation of <lb/>the MOSE system, Estuar. Coast. Shelf S., 205, 131-151, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecss.2018.03.007, 2018. <lb/>Zuliani, A., Zaggia, L., Collavini, F., and Zonta, R.: <lb/>Freshwater discharge from the drainage basin to the <lb/>Venice Lagoon (Italy), Environ. Int., 31, 929-938, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/J.ENVINT.2005.05.004, 2005. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Biogeosciences, 21, 2937-2954, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-21-2937-2024 </note>


	</text>

</TEI>