<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Anesth Pain Med. 2024 February; 14(1):e142051. <lb/>Published online 2024 January 20. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5812/aapm-142051. <lb/>Research Article <lb/>Efficacy Comparison Between Interscalene Block with and Without <lb/>Superficial Cervical Plexus Block for Anesthesia in Clavicle Surgery <lb/>Faramarz Mosaffa 1 , Mahshid Ghasemi 1 , Afsaneh Habibi 1 , Reza Minaei 2 , Narges Bazgir 3 , <lb/>Elham Memary 1 and Alireza Shakeri 1, * <lb/>1 Anesthesiology Research Center, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran <lb/>2 Akhtar Orthopedic Research Center, Shahid Beheshti Medical University, Tehran, Iran <lb/>3 Hearing Disorders Research Center, Loghman Hakim Hospital, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran <lb/>* Corresponding author: Anesthesiology Research Center, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran. Email: dr.alirezashakeri@gmail.com <lb/>Received 2023 October 14; Revised 2023 December 27; Accepted 2023 December 29. <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Background: Clavicle fractures account for over one-third of shoulder injuries and up to 3.3% of all fractures in adults. While the <lb/>majority of these fractures can be managed non-surgically, there are instances where surgical intervention is performed. Regional <lb/>anesthesia (RA) can be a preferred alternative to general anesthesia (GA) to avoid complications and high costs in this surgery. <lb/>Moreover, the identification of the most optimal approach for RA remains challenging. <lb/>Objectives: This study aimed to compare the efficacy of interscalene block (ISB) with and without superficial cervical plexus block <lb/>(SCPB) as an anesthetic technique for clavicular fracture operation. <lb/>Methods: This double-blinded, non-inferiority clinical trial was conducted on 120 patients randomly divided into 2 groups: One <lb/>receiving ISB and the other receiving ISB with SCPB. The primary outcome was defined as the conversion to GA. Various factors <lb/>were recorded, including surgery duration, nerve block initiation, analgesics required in the postanesthesia care unit (PACU), and <lb/>sedation during surgery. Pain was evaluated using the Visual Analog Scale (VAS) in PACU. SPSS version 26 was used for statistical <lb/>analysis, performing descriptive analysis, Student&apos;s t-tests, and Mann-Whitney U tests to compare non-parametric variables between <lb/>the 2 groups. Statistically significant results had a P value of less than 0.05. <lb/>Results: A total of 120 patients were randomly divided into 2 equal groups, each consisting of 50 males and 10 females. The mean age <lb/>of intervention and case groups were 37.23 ± 13.30 and 38.43 ± 11.95 years, respectively. After performing statistical tests (Student&apos;s <lb/>t-test and Mann-Whitney U test), there was no significant difference in the initiation time of nerve block, surgery initiation time, <lb/>surgery duration, the amount of required sedation, VAS scores, and meperidine consumption (P &gt; 0.05). None of the patients in <lb/>both groups required conversion to GA. <lb/>Conclusions: The primary goal was achieved in all included cases, and no patients required conversion to GA. The efficacy of ISB is <lb/>the same whether or not it is combined with a SCPB. Interscalene block is an alternative RA approach for clavicle fractures. Thus, ISB <lb/>alone is as efficient as when used in combination with SCPB. <lb/>Keywords: Clavicle Surgery, Interscalene Block, Superficial Cervical Plexus Block <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Background <lb/>Clavicle fractures make up 44% of all shoulder girdle <lb/>fractures and 2.6% -3.3% of all orthopedic fractures (1, <lb/>2). Clavicle fractures usually occur after blunt traumas. <lb/>The majority of clavicle fractures are successfully managed <lb/>conservatively (3). The surgical indication for a clavicle <lb/>fracture is more than 2 cm displacement (4-6). In <lb/>shortening more than the mentioned amount, open <lb/>reduction and internal fixation (ORIF) are used (4, 7, 8). <lb/>Due to the complex innervation of the clavicle by <lb/>subscapular, supraclavicular, and subclavian nerves <lb/>(Figure 1), ORIF is commonly performed under general <lb/>anesthesia (GA) (8). <lb/>The complex innervation of the clavicle and <lb/>interpersonal differences between patients in clavicular <lb/>innervation are the major concerns for regional anesthesia <lb/>(RA) (8). <lb/>Although GA provides complete immobility, increased <lb/>airway adverse events, elevated risk of hemodynamic <lb/>stresses, nausea, and vomiting are among its side effects <lb/>(9, 10). On the other hand, RA can prevent unwanted <lb/></body>

			<front>Copyright © 2024, Mosaffa et al. This open-access article is available under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 (CC BY 4.0) International License <lb/>(https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which allows for unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided that the original work is <lb/>properly cited. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Mosaffa F et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 1. The innervation of the clavicle <lb/>side effects of GA and provide better analgesia and faster <lb/>recovery and movement for the patient (9). The lower cost <lb/>of RA is also one of its other benefits (11, 12). <lb/>Understanding the innervation of the clavicle is crucial <lb/>for designing effective RA techniques. The supraclavicular <lb/>nerve provides sensory innervation to the clavicular skin, <lb/>while the clavicle itself is innervated by several nerves <lb/>(Figure 1). The ventral and cephalic parts are supplied <lb/>by supraclavicular nerves. The innervations of the caudal <lb/>and dorsal parts of the clavicle are provided by both <lb/>the subclavian and lateral pectoral nerves. The sensory <lb/>innervations of the clavicle medial and lateral parts are <lb/>provided by spinal accessory and subscapular and axillary <lb/>nerves, respectively (8, 13, 14). <lb/>Many studies have suggested interventional strategies <lb/>of RA for clavicular fractures, including superficial <lb/>cervical plexus block (SCPB), interscalene block (ISB), and <lb/>combined superficial cervical-deep cervical plexus (8). <lb/>Regarding the neuroanatomy and clinical experiences, <lb/>the combined interscalene-cervical block in clavicular <lb/>fracture surgeries provides sufficient analgesia. Thus, <lb/>regarding clavicle innervation, we hypothesized that ISB <lb/>may be as efficient as the combination of ISB and SCPB. <lb/>2. Objectives <lb/>This study aimed to compare the efficacy of ISB with <lb/>and without SCPB as an anesthesiologic technique for <lb/>clavicular fracture operation. <lb/>3. Methods <lb/>A randomized, double-blinded, non-inferiority clinical <lb/>trial was conducted in Akhtar Hospital from March to <lb/>June 2023. Patients with clavicle fractures aged 18 to 60, <lb/>weighing less than 80 kg and consenting to participate <lb/>in the study were included. Included patients must <lb/>have had normal neuromotor and sensory function. <lb/>Patients treated with narcotics or had a history of alcohol, <lb/>narcotics, or any addictive drug abuse were excluded. <lb/>Other exclusion criteria included any contraindication of <lb/>nerve blocks like local infections, coagulopathy, and any <lb/>allergy to local anesthetics. <lb/>Furthermore, patients with mental disorders, <lb/>restrictive pulmonary disease, pregnancy, bradycardia <lb/>(heart rate less than 50), and those who consumed beta <lb/>blockers were all excluded. A complete history was <lb/>obtained from each case. All the included individuals <lb/>underwent a thorough neurological examination. <lb/>The Ethics Committee of Shahid Beheshti University <lb/>of Medical Sciences approved this survey (code: <lb/>IR.SBMU.MSP.REC.1401.526, <lb/>date <lb/>of <lb/>registration: <lb/>25/01/2023; the Iranian Registry of Clinical Trials. code: <lb/>IRCT20230204057318N1). The study protocol followed the <lb/>Declaration of Helsinki. All the included patients were <lb/>informed about the purpose of the study, and written <lb/>consent was obtained. <lb/>G power software was used to determine the sample <lb/>size. Based on Ryan et al.&apos;s study (15), by considering the <lb/>effect size = 0.54, α = 0.05, and β (Power) = 0.90, 120 <lb/>patients for the sample size were chosen for the sample <lb/>size. Afterward, patients were randomly divided into 2 <lb/>groups. To ensure fairness, we used computer-generated <lb/>software to create equal groups through a randomized <lb/>method. An assistant who was not associated with this <lb/>study was responsible for generating and managing a <lb/>random sequence. The randomization code was placed <lb/>in a sealed opaque envelope by the assistant. A total of <lb/>120 cards were selected, with 60 cards in each group. The <lb/>cards were placed in sealed opaque envelopes and shuffled. <lb/>Patients selected envelopes without knowledge of the <lb/>contents. Only those responsible for the randomization <lb/>process knew which cards were in each envelope, while <lb/>other members of the research team were kept unaware. <lb/>After enrolling a patient in the study, an anesthesiologist <lb/>opened the sealed envelope and proceeded with the <lb/>allocated procedure. To prevent accidental revelation <lb/>of allocation to the participants, the block needle is <lb/>introduced through the same area for both interventions. <lb/>Additionally, the ultrasound monitor was not within the <lb/>participant&apos;s line of sight. After the procedures, the <lb/>researcher who assessed the outcome was unaware of the <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Anesth Pain Med. 2024; 14(1):e142051. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Mosaffa F et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>randomization. In case of serious adverse events that <lb/>could potentially harm the participants, the patients were <lb/>immediately removed from the trial. The blinding was also <lb/>removed, and the events were reported. Additionally, the <lb/>data analyst was also kept unaware of the randomization <lb/>process. <lb/>In the block room, all patients underwent standard <lb/>monitoring (pulse oximetry, noninvasive blood pressure, <lb/>and electrocardiogram). In the first group, after placing <lb/>patients in a supine position with a 30°head-up and <lb/>dis-infecting the neck with povidone-iodine, ISB was <lb/>performed by a single anesthesiologist who is an expert in <lb/>RA (Figure 2). <lb/>Initially, the brachial plexus was identified between the <lb/>anterior and middle scalene muscles. Then, via ultrasound <lb/>visualization, a needle was inserted from lateral to medial <lb/>into the interscalene grove between the nerve roots. <lb/>Consequently, 20 mL of 1.5% lidocaine (Caspin Company), <lb/>1 mL of 8.4% bicarbonate (Caspin Company), 1: 200 000 <lb/>epinephrine (Daroupakhsh Company), and 4 mL of 0.5% <lb/>bupivacaine (AstraZeneca Company) were used. <lb/>In addition to the mentioned ISB method, SCPB was <lb/>performed. The high-frequency linear ultrasound probe <lb/>was slid to the lateral side of the neck at the midpoint <lb/>of the sternocleidomastoid (SCM) muscle, corresponding <lb/>to the C6 transverse apophysis and its anterior tubercle <lb/>at the level of the cricoid cartilage. After identifying <lb/>the muscle, the probe was moved backward until the <lb/>posterior edge of the muscle was found. The interscalene <lb/>groove between the anterior and middle scalene muscles <lb/>was then identified. Next, SCP was located just above <lb/>the prevertebral fascia that covers the interscalene groove <lb/>enclosed within the interstitial space, separating the <lb/>cervical fascia and the posterior sheath of SCM. A block <lb/>needle was then introduced from lateral to medial using <lb/>the posterior-in-plane technique till its tip was placed near <lb/>the SCP above the prevertebral fascia. After careful negative <lb/>aspiration to exclude intravascular placement, 10 mL of <lb/>1.5% lidocaine (Caspin Company), 1 mL of 8.4% bicarbonate <lb/>(Caspin Company), 1: 200 000 epinephrine (Daroupakhsh <lb/>Company), and 4 mL of 0.5% bupivacaine (AstraZeneca <lb/>Company) were deposited (Figure 3). <lb/>In both groups, nerve blocks were performed by a <lb/>single anesthesiologist who is an expert in RA under <lb/>an ultrasonographic guide (S-Nerve ultrasound Sonosite <lb/>machine) with a linear transducer with 6 -15 MHz <lb/>frequency using the in-plane method with a block needle <lb/>(B. Braun needle, 22Ga, 80 mm, Stimuplex Ultra 360). <lb/>All common challenges of nerve blocks, such as <lb/>nerve injury, vascular injury, local anesthesia toxicity, <lb/>and the absence of neurological lesions and neurological <lb/>evaluation after nerve blocks, were considered for safety <lb/>considerations. <lb/>Loss of shoulder abduction was used to identify motor <lb/>blockade, while the pinprick test and palpitation were <lb/>used to determine sensory blockade at the operation site. <lb/>Also, the arm mobilized passively to assess further pain. <lb/>A block was deemed successful if all the examinations, <lb/>as mentioned earlier, were present. If uncontrolled pain <lb/>occurred after starting surgery that required conversion to <lb/>GA, the block was considered incompetence. <lb/>In the case of patient anxiety, 2 mg of midazolam was <lb/>administered, and if a patient complained of pain, 50 µg <lb/>of fentanyl was administered intravenously. If adverse <lb/>reactions, like bradypnea (respiratory rate less than 8), <lb/>apnea of more than 15 s, and oxygen saturation of less than <lb/>94%, were observed, the process was held, and patients&apos; <lb/>respiration was aided. At the end of the operation, patients <lb/>were transferred to the postanesthesia care unit (PACU). <lb/>Our primary goal was to compare the need for <lb/>inducing GA for the operation between intervention and <lb/>control groups. The secondary outcomes included the <lb/>requirement for sedation during surgery, comparing <lb/>postoperative Visual Analog Scale (VAS) scores, and the <lb/>amount of narcotics used in the PACU between the 2 <lb/>groups. <lb/>Demographic data, the duration of surgery, the <lb/>beginning of the nerve block, the surgery initiation time, <lb/>the amount of required sedation during surgery, and the <lb/>amount of required analgesics in the PACU (meperidine) <lb/>were all thoroughly recorded. The meperidine was <lb/>used in fixed doses of 20 mg, repeated every 5 min to <lb/>achieve adequate response. We also evaluated the pain <lb/>experienced by patients after the VAS operation in the <lb/>PACU. All included individuals were followed up until <lb/>their discharge from the PACU. <lb/>The group-matching method was used to omit the <lb/>confounders. Selection, performance, and detection <lb/>biases were all omitted by randomization and blinding, <lb/>respectively. <lb/>We reported all the significant and <lb/>insignificant findings of the study. The results were <lb/>reported completely and clearly. Initially, 7 patients did <lb/>not consent to receive RA, but no patient was lost during <lb/>follow-up. To minimize the random error, the sample size <lb/>was carefully determined prior to the study. <lb/>To remove the biases from the randomization <lb/>process, the allocation was random, and the allocation <lb/>sequences were concealed. Patients were unaware of the <lb/>allocation. The main researchers and the expert regional <lb/>anesthesiologist were the only people who were aware <lb/>of randomization. The data of all included cases were <lb/>available, and we had no missing data. Furthermore, the <lb/>method of measurement was the same in both groups, <lb/>and the outcome assessor was not aware of allocation. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Anesth Pain Med. 2024; 14(1):e142051. <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Mosaffa F et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 2. Sonography of the brachial plexus, middle scalene muscle, and anterior scalene muscle. The b and a are before and after the injection, respectively (Abbreviations: <lb/>MSM, middle scalene muscle; ASM, anterior scalene muscle). <lb/>Figure 3. The sternocleidomastoid, internal jugular vein, carotid artery, transverse process, and needle. The A and B are before and after the injection, respectively <lb/>(Abbreviations: SCM, sternocleidomastoid; IJV, internal jugular vein; CA, carotid artery; TP, transverse process; N, needle). <lb/>Afterward, data were completely gathered, and all of them <lb/>were transferred to a blinded data analyst. <lb/>The statistical analysis was conducted using SPSS <lb/>version 26. Descriptive analysis and Students&apos; t-tests were <lb/>performed. The Mann-Whitney U test was conducted to <lb/>compare non-parametric variables between the 2 groups. <lb/>P values less than 0.05 were considered statistically <lb/>significant. <lb/>4. Results <lb/>We conducted a double-blinded clinical trial in Akhtar <lb/>Hospital. Initially, 136 patients were assessed for eligibility. <lb/>Seven patients did not consent to enroll in the study. A <lb/>hundred and twenty-nine patients with clavicle fractures <lb/>were included in this survey (64 patients in the ISB + <lb/>SCPB group and 65 in the ISB group). Nine patients were <lb/>excluded due to an unsuccessful shoulder motor block. <lb/>Thus, 120 patients remained (60 in each group). Further, <lb/>during the survey, no individual was excluded. Thus, all <lb/>primary and secondary outcomes were evaluated for 60 <lb/>participants in each group. <lb/>Each group comprised 10 females (16.75%) and 50 males <lb/>(83.3%). The mean age of intervention and case groups <lb/>were 37.23 ± 13.30 and 38.43 ± 11.95 years, respectively. After <lb/>conducting the Students&apos; t-test, there was no significant <lb/>difference in mean ages between the 2 groups (P = 0.604). <lb/>No case in either group required conversion to GA. The <lb/>mean and SD of surgery duration, nerve block initiation <lb/>time, and surgery initiation time are listed in Table 1. <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Anesth Pain Med. 2024; 14(1):e142051. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Mosaffa F et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 1. Means, SDs, and the Resulting P Values from Student&apos;s t-Test a <lb/>Variables <lb/>Combined <lb/>Interscalene and <lb/>Cervical Plexus <lb/>Block Group (n = <lb/>60) <lb/>Interscalene <lb/>Group (n = 60) <lb/>P-Value <lb/>Duration of <lb/>surgery (min) <lb/>66.57 ± 7.37 <lb/>65.87 ± 6.29 <lb/>0.557 <lb/>Nerve block <lb/>initiation (min) <lb/>10.63 ± 1.96 <lb/>11.15 ± 2.07 <lb/>0.276 <lb/>Surgery <lb/>initiation time <lb/>(min) <lb/>22.33 ± 2.81 <lb/>22.02 ± 2.81 <lb/>0.474 <lb/>a Values are presented as mean ± SD. <lb/>A Student&apos;s t-test was conducted to compare these <lb/>variables. As shown in Table 1, the nerve block initiation <lb/>was slightly lower in patients who received ISB and SCPB <lb/>(10.63 ± 1.96 vs 11.15 ± 2.07 min). However, this difference <lb/>was not statistically significant. Besides, no significant <lb/>differences were observed between the 2 groups in surgery <lb/>duration, the time of nerve block initiation, and surgery <lb/>initiation time (P &gt; 0.05). The means and SDs of these <lb/>variables and resultant P values are demonstrated in Table <lb/>1. <lb/>As demonstrated in Table 2, there was no significant <lb/>difference between sedation requirements and the <lb/>amount of meperidine consumption in PACU between the <lb/>2 groups. <lb/>Table 2. Sedation Needs and Analgesic in the Postanesthesia Care Unit and the <lb/>Resulting P-Values from the Mann-Whitney U Test a <lb/>Variables <lb/>Combined <lb/>Interscalene <lb/>with Cervical <lb/>Plexus Block <lb/>Group (n = 60) <lb/>Interscalene <lb/>Group (n = 60) <lb/>P-Value <lb/>Fentanyl 50 mcg <lb/>5 (8.3) <lb/>6 (10.0) <lb/>0.752 <lb/>Midazolam 2 mg <lb/>11 (18.3) <lb/>10 (16.7) <lb/>0.810 <lb/>Analgesic in <lb/>PACU <lb/>4 (6.7) <lb/>4 (6.7) <lb/>&gt; 0.999 <lb/>Meperidine 20 <lb/>mg <lb/>4 (6.7) <lb/>4 (6.7) <lb/>&gt; 0.999 <lb/>Abbreviation: PACU, postanesthesia care unit. <lb/>a Values are presented as No. (%). <lb/>Furthermore, the VAS means of ISB and ISB + SCPB were <lb/>11.43 ± 4.25 and 10.6 ± 4.28, respectively. After analyzing the <lb/>VAS means with the Mann-Whitney U test, it was revealed <lb/>that there was no significant difference between the 2 <lb/>groups (P = 0.338). Figure 4 shows the mean of VAS in the 2 <lb/>groups. <lb/>5. Discussion <lb/>This article aimed to compare the efficacy of ISB with <lb/>and without SCPB as an alternative RA approach for clavicle <lb/>fractures. As demonstrated, there was no significant <lb/>difference between the 2 groups in surgery duration, onset <lb/>of nerve block, onset of surgery, VAS scores, amount of <lb/>required sedation, and meperidine consumption in the <lb/>PACU. No complications were recorded in the 2 groups. No <lb/>case required conversion to GA and all the operations were <lb/>performed successfully. <lb/>Several previous studies have proved that RA and <lb/>GA had the same efficacy. In addition, Ryan et al. <lb/>retrospectively reviewed 110 clavicle fractures and <lb/>demonstrated that the average operation time of patients <lb/>who underwent RA was 30 minutes shorter than patients <lb/>with GA. Since the estimated cost of surgery in their center <lb/>was $60/min, RA decreased the time of operation and the <lb/>costs significantly (15). <lb/>A study compared 2 groups of patients with clavicle <lb/>fractures. One group received GA, while the other received <lb/>a combination of nerve blocks. The second group required <lb/>less opioid medication and had a shorter stay in the PACU <lb/>(16). Similarly, patients with clavicle fractures who received <lb/>RA had less pain and consumed fewer opioids than those <lb/>who received GA. Cervical and interscalene brachial plexus <lb/>blocks resulted in minimal pain and opioid use (17). <lb/>Consequently, RA approaches were as efficient as GA. <lb/>Also, RA methods have fewer side effects and a lower need <lb/>for sedation postoperatively. <lb/>Fugelli et al. evaluated 10 patients with midshaft <lb/>clavicle fractures who received ISB + SCPB. They showed <lb/>that all patients successfully underwent clavicle surgery <lb/>with no need for GA conversion. They observed no adverse <lb/>events in their cases. Accordingly, our cases had no side <lb/>effects, and none of our cases required conversion to GA <lb/>(18). <lb/>A clinical trial compared ultrasound-guided ISB with <lb/>SCPB and ISB with intermediate cervical plexus block <lb/>(ICPB) for clavicle surgery in 50 patients divided into 2 <lb/>groups. Group 1 had higher nerve block success with ISB <lb/>and ICPB, while group 2 experienced delayed onset and <lb/>shorter nerve block duration; ISB with ICPB was a better <lb/>anesthetic approach for clavicle surgery (13). The sensory <lb/>block initiation in this study for patients who received ISB <lb/>and SCPB was 4.3 ± 0.5 min, which was clearly less than <lb/>the nerve block initiation in our survey (10.63 ± 1.96 min). <lb/>The difference is that Arjun et al. evaluated the sensory <lb/>block while we measured the motor nerve block initiation. <lb/>Furthermore, the type and amount of analgesics used in <lb/>our survey differed from those in Arjun et al. (13). <lb/>A randomized clinical trial was conducted by Gupta <lb/></body>

            <note place="footnote">Anesth Pain Med. 2024; 14(1):e142051. <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Mosaffa F et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>15.00 <lb/>10.00 <lb/>5.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>ISB + SCPB <lb/>ISB + SCPB <lb/>Group <lb/>Mean VAS in recovery <lb/>Figure 4. The bar chart of the Visual Analog Scale in the 2 groups. The interscalene block (ISB) + superficial cervical plexus block (SCPB) group received combined interscalene <lb/>with CPB. The ISB group received ISB (Abbreviations: VAS, Visual Analog Scale; ISB, interscalene block; SCPB, superficial cervical plexus block). <lb/>et al. with 60 patients divided into 2 groups. One <lb/>group received cervical plexus blockage and ISB, while <lb/>the other only received ISB. A nerve locator was used to <lb/>perform the nerve block. The latter group required extra <lb/>RA for over a quarter of patients, and about 10% needed <lb/>conversion to GA (14). In contrast, none of our cases needed <lb/>more local anesthesia or conversion to GA. Although the <lb/>supraclavicular nerve was not directly anesthetized, all <lb/>individuals in our study reached sufficient anesthesia for <lb/>clavicle surgery. This difference may be due to diffusion <lb/>of the higher volume of local anesthetic we used, thus <lb/>affecting the supraclavicular nerve, making ISB sufficient. <lb/>Our study had a larger sample size, leading to more precise <lb/>results, making our study superior to Gupta et al. Besides, <lb/>we also used sonography instead of a nerve locator for <lb/>nerve block (14). <lb/>Abdelghany et al. included 70 patients with clavicle <lb/>fractures who were candidates for internal fixation. These <lb/>patients were equally divided into 2 groups. One receiving <lb/>SCPB and the other ISB + SCPB. It was revealed that the <lb/>incidence of phrenic nerve palsy was less in the group that <lb/>received SCPB. As a result, they concluded that SCPB is as <lb/>efficient as ISB and SCPB and it has fewer complications <lb/>(19). Likewise, the fentanyl consumption between the <lb/>2 groups in Abdelghany et al.&apos;s study was the same. <lb/>Compared to this study, the duration of surgery in ours <lb/>was shorter. However, the VAS score in the current study <lb/>was much higher. The reason for the higher VAS score is <lb/>that the VAS was measured immediately in the PACU, while <lb/>in Abdelghany et al.&apos;s study, the VAS was measured after 2 <lb/>h. Furthermore, the type of the anesthetic and the dosage <lb/>varied between the 2 studies (19). <lb/>New methods have been developed to provide more <lb/>targeted pain relief. A clinical trial conducted by Han <lb/>et al. looked into the effectiveness of 2 different nerve <lb/>block methods on 91 patients with medial shaft and medial <lb/>clavicle fractures. The participants were divided into 2 <lb/>groups: one group received C3, C4, and C5 nerve blocks <lb/>using 5 mL of 0.5% ropivacaine; in contrast, the other <lb/>group received ISB combined with ICPB using 20 mL of <lb/>0.5% ropivacaine under ultrasound guidance. The study <lb/>found that C3, C4, and C5 nerve blocks were more effective <lb/>than ISB combined with ICPB. Patients who underwent <lb/>C3, C4, and C5 nerve blocks experienced a quicker onset <lb/>of sensory block, and the duration of the sensory block <lb/>was longer than in the other group. Many patients in the <lb/>C3, C4, and C5 groups also had successful nerve blocks. <lb/>However, the 2 groups had no difference in the Numeric <lb/>Rating Scale (NRS). Therefore, C3, C4, and C5 nerve blocks <lb/>are a suitable RA method for middle clavicle fractures (20). <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Anesth Pain Med. 2024; 14(1):e142051. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Mosaffa F et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>Consequently, this study shows that RA approaches, which <lb/>are more selective and less extensive, are as efficient as the <lb/>conventional methods. <lb/>In a case series with 20 patients with clavicle fractures, <lb/>the C5 root and supraclavicular nerve block were used. <lb/>However, 4 patients experienced inadequate anesthesia, <lb/>3 needed further sedations, and 1 had to undergo GA. <lb/>This could be attributed to the complex nerve supply <lb/>of the clavicle. To prevent such occurrences, exploring <lb/>alternative methods that require reduced anesthesia <lb/>and offer superior outcomes compared to GA would <lb/>be advantageous (21). Less extensive RA approaches are <lb/>preferable due to fewer complications and lower costs. <lb/>However, proper nerve paralysis is necessary to avoid <lb/>conversion to GA and resulting complications. <lb/>5.1. Limitations <lb/>This study has several limitations. First, we did not <lb/>consider the classifications of clavicle fractures. Second, <lb/>due to the high incidence of clavicle fracture in the <lb/>younger population, most included patients were young <lb/>with good medical status. The analgesic effects were <lb/>evaluated until the discharge from the PACU. A longer <lb/>follow-up duration for recording analgesic effects and side <lb/>effects is required. A larger multi-centric clinical trial with <lb/>a longer follow-up duration should be performed to obtain <lb/>results that are more precise. <lb/>5.2. Conclusions <lb/>No significant differences were found in surgery <lb/>duration, nerve block initiation time, surgery initiation <lb/>time, sedation requirements, or meperidine consumption <lb/>in the PACU between the 2 groups. The VAS means of the <lb/>ISB and ISB + SCPB groups were not significantly different <lb/>between the 2 groups. The rate of the conversion to GA <lb/>did not differ between the 2 groups. As a result, it was <lb/>found that ISB was as efficient as SCPB in combination <lb/>with clavicle fracture surgery. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We wish to thank those who contributed to <lb/>this study. <lb/>Parts of the figure were drawn by <lb/>using pictures from Servier Medical Art. <lb/>Servier <lb/>Medical Art by Servier is licensed under a Creative <lb/>Commons <lb/>Attribution <lb/>3.0 <lb/>Unported <lb/>License <lb/>(https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/). <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Footnotes <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Authors&apos; Contribution: AS and FM: Conceptualization <lb/>of the study. RM and AH: Acquisition of data. MG and EM: <lb/>analysis and interpretation of data and statistical analysis. <lb/>NB: Drafting of the manuscript. AS and FM: Revision of the <lb/>critical intellectual concept and approval of the version to <lb/>be submitted. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Clinical <lb/>Trial <lb/>Registration <lb/>Code: <lb/>IRCT20230204057318N1. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Conflict of Interests: There are no conflicts of interest <lb/>relevant to this work. <lb/></div>

            <div type="availability">Data Availability: All analyzed data during this study are <lb/>included in this article. Further inquiries can be directed <lb/>to the corresponding author. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Ethical Approval: This study was ethically approved <lb/>by the Ethics Committee of Shahid Beheshti University of <lb/>Medical Sciences (code: IR.SBMU.MSP.REC.1401.526). <lb/></div>

            <div type="funding">Funding/Support: No fund was received for this survey. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Informed Consent: <lb/>Written informed consent was <lb/>obtained from all participants. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Postacchini F, Gumina S, De Santis P, Albo F. Epidemiology <lb/>of clavicle fractures. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2002;11(5):452-6. <lb/>[PubMed ID: 12378163]. https://doi.org/10.1067/mse.2002.126613. <lb/>2. Court-Brown CM, Caesar B. Epidemiology of adult fractures: A <lb/>review. Injury. 2006;37(8):691-7. [PubMed ID: 16814787]. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.injury.2006.04.130. <lb/>3. Amer KM, Congiusta DV, Suri P, Choudhry A, Otero K, Adams M. <lb/>Clavicle fractures: Associated trauma and morbidity. J Clin Orthop <lb/>Trauma. 2021;13:53-6. [PubMed ID: 33717875]. [PubMed Central ID: <lb/>PMC7919969]. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcot.2020.08.020. <lb/>4. Althausen PL, Shannon S, Lu M, O&apos;Mara TJ, Bray TJ. Clinical and <lb/>financial comparison of operative and nonoperative treatment of <lb/>displaced clavicle fractures. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2013;22(5):608-11. <lb/>[PubMed ID: 22960145]. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jse.2012.06.006. <lb/>5. Khan LA, Bradnock TJ, Scott C, Robinson CM. Fractures of the clavicle. <lb/>J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2009;91(2):447-60. [PubMed ID: 19181992]. https: <lb/>//doi.org/10.2106/JBJS.H.00034. <lb/>6. Preston CF, Egol KA. Midshaft clavicle fractures in adults. Bulletin of the <lb/>NYU Hospital for Joint Diseases. 2009;67(1). <lb/>7. Canadian Orthopaedic Trauma S. Nonoperative treatment <lb/>compared with plate fixation of displaced midshaft clavicular <lb/>fractures. A multicenter, randomized clinical trial. J Bone <lb/>Joint Surg Am. 2007;89(1):1-10. [PubMed ID: 17200303]. https: <lb/>//doi.org/10.2106/JBJS.F.00020. <lb/>8. Tran DQ, Tiyaprasertkul W, Gonzalez AP. Analgesia for clavicular <lb/>fracture and surgery: A call for evidence. Reg Anesth Pain Med. <lb/>2013;38(6):539-43. [PubMed ID: 24121609]. https://doi.org/10.1097/AAP. <lb/>0000000000000012. <lb/>9. Hadzic A, Arliss J, Kerimoglu B, Karaca PE, Yufa M, Claudio <lb/>RE, et al. A comparison of infraclavicular nerve block versus <lb/>general anesthesia for hand and wrist day-case surgeries. <lb/>Anesthesiology. 2004;101(1):127-32. [PubMed ID: 15220781]. https: <lb/>//doi.org/10.1097/00000542-200407000-00020. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Anesth Pain Med. 2024; 14(1):e142051. <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Mosaffa F et al. <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>10. Movasseghi G, Hassani V, Mohaghegh MR, Safaeian R, Safari S, Zamani <lb/>MM, et al. Comparison between spinal and general anesthesia in <lb/>percutaneous nephrolithotomy. Anesth Pain Med. 2014;4(1). e13871. <lb/>[PubMed ID: 24660147]. [PubMed Central ID: PMC3961021]. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.5812/aapm.13871. <lb/>11. Chakladar A, White SM. Cost estimates of spinal versus general <lb/>anaesthesia for fractured neck of femur surgery. Anaesthesia. <lb/>2010;65(8):810-4. [PubMed ID: 20528835]. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-<lb/>2044.2010.06382.x. <lb/>12. Ponde V, Borse D, More J, Mange T. Is dedicating an ultrasound <lb/>machine to regional anesthesia an economically viable <lb/>option? <lb/>J Anaesthesiol Clin Pharmacol. 2016;32(4):519-22. <lb/>[PubMed ID: 28096587]. [PubMed Central ID: PMC5187621]. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.4103/0970-9185.194767. <lb/>13. Arjun BK, Vinod CN, Puneeth J, Narendrababu MC. Ultrasound-guided <lb/>interscalene block combined with intermediate or superficial <lb/>cervical plexus block for clavicle surgery: A randomised double blind <lb/>study. Eur J Anaesthesiol. 2020;37(11):979-83. [PubMed ID: 32833851]. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1097/EJA.0000000000001300. <lb/>14. Gupta N, Gupta V, Kumar G, Gupta V, Gupta DK. Comparative <lb/>evaluation of efficacy of interscalene block vs. Interscalene block and <lb/>superficial cervical plexus block for fixation of clavicular fractures. <lb/>Inter J Contemporary Med Res [IJCMR]. 2019;6(3). https://doi.org/10. <lb/>21276/ijcmr.2019.6.3.22. <lb/>15. Ryan DJ, Iofin N, Furgiuele D, Johnson J, Egol K. Regional anesthesia <lb/>for clavicle fracture surgery is safe and effective. J Shoulder Elbow <lb/>Surg. 2021;30(7):e356-60. [PubMed ID: 33197587]. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.jse.2020.10.009. <lb/>16. Banerjee S, Acharya R, Sriramka B. Ultrasound-guided inter-scalene <lb/>brachial plexus block with superficial cervical plexus block <lb/>compared with general anesthesia in patients undergoing <lb/>clavicular surgery: A comparative analysis. Anesth Essays Res. <lb/>2019;13(1):149-54. [PubMed ID: 31031496]. [PubMed Central ID: <lb/>PMC6444954]. https://doi.org/10.4103/aer.AER 185 18. <lb/>17. Lee CCM, Lua CB, Peng K, Beh ZY, Fathil SM, Hou JD, et al. Regional <lb/>anesthetic and analgesic techniques for clavicle fractures and clavicle <lb/>surgeries: Part 2-A retrospective study. Healthcare (Basel). 2022;10(10). <lb/>[PubMed ID: 36292434]. [PubMed Central ID: PMC9602537]. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.3390/healthcare10101987. <lb/>18. Fugelli CG, Westlye ET, Hege Ersdal MD, Kristian Strand MD, Conrad <lb/>Bjørshol MD. Combined interscalene brachial plexus and superficial <lb/>cervical plexus nerve block for midshaft clavicle surgery: A case series. <lb/>AANA journal. 2019;87(5):374-8. <lb/>19. Abdelghany MS, Ahmed SA, Afandy ME. Superficial cervical plexus <lb/>block alone or combined with interscalene brachial plexus block in <lb/>surgery for clavicle fractures: A randomized clinical trial. Minerva <lb/>Anestesiol. 2021;87(5):523-32. [PubMed ID: 33591139]. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>23736/S0375-9393.21.14865-5. <lb/>20. Han J, Xu Y, Shan Y, Xie Y, Wang A, Gu C. Could C3, 4, and 5 nerve root <lb/>block be a better alternative to interscalene block plus intermediate <lb/>cervical plexus block for patients undergoing surgery for midshaft <lb/>and medial clavicle fractures? A randomized controlled trial. <lb/>Clin Orthop Relat Res. 2023;481(4):798-807. [PubMed ID: 36730478]. <lb/>[PubMed Central ID: PMC10013610]. https://doi.org/10.1097/CORR. <lb/>0000000000002479. <lb/>21. Diwan S, Nair A, Sermeus LA, Patil AA, Attarde DS. Low-Volume <lb/>local anesthetics for C5 and supraclavicular nerve blocks for mid <lb/>and lateral clavicle surgery: A case series. A A Pract. 2020;14(12). <lb/>e01322. <lb/>[PubMed ID: 33094947]. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1213/XAA. <lb/>0000000000001322. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Anesth Pain Med. 2024; 14(1):e142051. </note>


	</text>
</tei>
