<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Complete genome sequence of potential probiotic Ligilactobacillus ruminis CACC881 isolated from swine</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Soyeon</forename>
          <surname>Park</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Mi Ae</forename>
          <surname>Park</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Hyun-Jun</forename>
          <surname>Jang</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Dae-Hyuk</forename>
          <surname>Kim</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Yangseon</forename>
          <surname>Kim</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-05T13:48:35.712Z">11/5/2025 1:48:35 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Korean Society of Animal Science and Technology</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.5187/jast.2024.e50</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Soyeon Park, Mi Ae Park, Hyun-Jun Jang, Dae-Hyuk Kim, Yangseon Kim. (2024). Complete genome sequence of potential probiotic Ligilactobacillus ruminis CACC881 isolated from swine. Journal of Animal Science and Technology, None(None), None. DOI: 10.5187/jast.2024.e50</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-05T13:48:26.075698Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-05T13:48:26.075698Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>JAST (Journal of Animal Science and Technology) TITLE PAGE <lb/>Upload this completed form to website with submission <lb/>ARTICLE INFORMATION <lb/>Fill in information in each box below <lb/>Article Type <lb/>Research article <lb/>Article Title (within 20 words without <lb/>abbreviations) <lb/>Dietary coated copper and zinc improve growth performance by modulating immune <lb/>responses and fecal microbiota of weaned pigs <lb/>Running Title (within 10 words) <lb/>Effects of dietary coated copper and zinc in weaned pigs <lb/>Author <lb/>Jinuk Nam1#, Hyunjin Kyoung1#, Yonghee Kim# Jinho Cho2#, Jinmu Ahn1, Kimoon <lb/>Kim1, Ikcheol Shin1, Sheena Kim 3, Jin Tae Kim 4, Sung Woo Jung 5, Hyeun Bum <lb/>Kim 3*, and Minho Song 1* <lb/>Affiliation <lb/>1 Division of Animal and Dairy Science, Chungnam National University, Daejeon <lb/>34134, Korea <lb/>2 Department of Animal Science, Chungbuk National University, Cheongju 28644, <lb/>Korea <lb/>3 Department of Animal Resources Science, Dankook University, Cheonan 31116, <lb/>Korea <lb/>4 AGRANCO Corp., Florida 33134, United States of America <lb/>5 ACC Inc., Seongnam 13647, Republic of Korea <lb/>ORCID (for more information, please <lb/>visit https://orcid.org) <lb/>Jinuk Nam (https://orcid.org/0009-0003-8696-5697) <lb/>Hyunjin Kyoung (https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5742-5374) <lb/>Yonghee Kim (https://orcid.org/0009-0009-8334-3706) <lb/>Jinho Cho (https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7151-0778) <lb/>Jinmu Ahn (https://orcid.org/0009-0005-1490-2974) <lb/>Kimoon Kim (https://orcid.org/0009-0008-2988-5179) <lb/>Ikcheol Shin (https://orcid.org/0009-0003-0072-5626) <lb/>Sheena Kim (https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5410-1347) <lb/>Jin Tae Kim (https://orcid.org/0009-0007-4964-2994) <lb/>Sung Woo Jung (https://orcid.org/0009-0007-5587-8864) <lb/>Hyeun Bum Kim (https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1366-6090) <lb/>Minho Song (https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4515-5212) <lb/>Competing interests <lb/>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported. <lb/>Funding sources <lb/>State funding sources (grants, funding <lb/>sources, equipment, and supplies). <lb/>Include name and number of grant if <lb/>available. <lb/>This work was carried out with the support of &quot;Cooperative Research Program for <lb/>Agriculture Science and Technology Development (RS-2023-00230754), Rural <lb/>Development Administration, Republic of Korea. <lb/>Acknowledgements <lb/>Not applicable. <lb/>Availability of data and material <lb/>Upon reasonable request, the datasets of this study can be available from the <lb/>corresponding author. <lb/>Authors&apos; contributions <lb/>Please specify the authors&apos; role using <lb/>this form. <lb/>Conceptualization: Nam J, Kyoung H, Kim Y, Cho J, Kim HB, Song M <lb/>Data curation: Nam J, Kyoung H, Kim Y, Cho J, Kim HB, Song M <lb/>Formal analysis: Nam J, Ahn J, Kim K, Shin I, Kim S, Kim JT, Jung SW <lb/>Methodology: Nam J, Kyoung H, Kim Y, Cho J <lb/>Software: Nam J, Kyoun H, Kim Y, Cho J <lb/>Validation: Kyoung H, Kim Y, Cho J, Kim HB, Song M <lb/>Investigation: Nam J, Kyoung H, Kim Y, Cho J <lb/>Writing -original draft: Nam J, Kyoung H, Kim Y, Cho J <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Nam J, Kyoung H, Cho J, Kim Y, Ahn J, Kim K, Shin I, <lb/>Kim S, Kim JT, Jung SW, Kim HB, Song M <lb/>Ethics approval and consent to <lb/>participate <lb/>The experimental protocol for this study was reviewed and approved by the <lb/>Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Chungnam National University, <lb/>Daejeon, Republic of Korea. (approval# 202103A-CNU-080) <lb/>A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>CORRESPONDING AUTHOR CONTACT INFORMATION <lb/>For the corresponding author (responsible for <lb/>correspondence, proofreading, and reprints) <lb/>Fill in information in each box below <lb/>First name, middle initial, last name <lb/>Hyeun Bum Kim <lb/>Minho Song <lb/>Email address -this is where your proofs will be sent <lb/>hbkim@dankook.ac.kr <lb/>mhsong@cnu.ac.kr <lb/>Secondary Email address <lb/>Address <lb/>Department of Animal Resources Science, Dankook University, <lb/>Cheonan 31116, Korea. <lb/>Division of Animal and Dairy Science, Chungnam National <lb/>University, Daejeon 34134, Korea. <lb/>Cell phone number <lb/>Office phone number <lb/>+82-41-550-3653 <lb/>+82-42-821-5776 <lb/>Fax number <lb/>A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>Abstract (up to 350 words) <lb/>In the swine industry, supplementation with high levels of zinc oxide and copper sulfate in the weaner diet could <lb/>be excreted through feces without being normally absorbed in the intestine, resulting in environmental pollution. <lb/>Therefore, the various methods have been proposed to address this issue. The objective of this study was to <lb/>investigate effects of a low dietary dose of coated copper sulfate (CuSO 4 ) and zinc oxide (ZnO) on growth <lb/>performance, frequency of diarrhea, nutrient digestibility, and immune responses of weaned pigs. The four dietary <lb/>treatments were (1) a basal weaner diet based on corn and soybean meal (CON), (2) CON supplemented with <lb/>2,500 ppm standard ZnO (T1), (3) CON supplemented with 100 mg/kg dietary coated CuSO 4 and 100 mg/kg <lb/>dietary coated ZnO (T2), and (4) CON supplemented with 200 mg/kg dietary coated CuSO 4 and 200 mg/kg dietary <lb/>coated ZnO (T3). Dietary T2 and T3 increased (p &lt; 0.05) the average daily gain for the first two weeks and the <lb/>overall experimental period compared to that with CON. In addition, the groups supplemented with Cu and Zn <lb/>tended to have a decreased (p &lt; 0.10) frequency of diarrhea. Pigs fed dietary T2 and/or T3 had lower (p &lt; 0.10) <lb/>number of white blood cells on day 7 and hematocrit on day 14 compared to those fed CON. However, no <lb/>difference was observed in the number of red blood cells among the dietary treatments. Regarding immune <lb/>responses, dietary T2 decreased (p &lt; 0.10) serum tumor necrosis factor-α on day 7 and increased (p &lt; 0.10) <lb/>immunoglobulin G on day 14 compared with CON. Moreover, pigs fed dietary T2 tended to have increased <lb/>Limosilacatobacilus (p &lt; 0.10). Dietary T3 had higher (p &lt; 0.05) relative abundance of the genus Agathobacter <lb/>compared to those fed CON and dietary T1 and decreased (p &lt; 0.05) genus Terrisporobacter compared to those <lb/>fed dietary T1. These results suggested the supplementation of dietary coated ZnO and CuSO 4 enhanced growth <lb/>performance and modulated immune responses associated with changes in the fecal microbiota composition. <lb/>Keywords: Copper; Growth performance; Immune response; Microbiota; Weaned pig; Zinc <lb/>A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/></front>

        <body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Post-weaning diarrhea (PWD) is a potentially fatal disease in swine production worldwide, causing <lb/>dehydration, growth delay, and death in severe cases causes of negative impacts on the industry [1]. During the <lb/>post-weaning period, various stress factors, including dietary, environmental, social, and physiological stressors, <lb/>affect weaning pigs. These factors reduce feed intake and growth, thus resulting in intestinal dysfunction, and an <lb/>increased susceptibility to inflammation [2,3]. Furthermore, permeability increases as the intestinal barrier is <lb/>disrupted, leading to PWD due to infections by intestinal pathogens such as Escherichia coli (E. coli) [4]. To solve <lb/>these issues, in-feed antibiotics have been widely utilized in the livestock industry for growth promotion and <lb/>disease treatment including PWD. However, the incidence of antimicrobial resistance and residual issues remain <lb/>concerning for animal and public health due to the overuse of in-feed antibiotics[5]. Therefore, various nutritive <lb/>alternatives such as probiotics, enzymes, minerals, and others, have been utilized to enhance animal health and <lb/>performance [6]. <lb/>It is known that copper (Cu) and zinc (Zn) are vital trace elements that act as components of metabolic <lb/>enzymes and perform biological functions [7]. Both support immunity, reproduction, and growth of animals [8,9]. <lb/>The most commercial forms in the swine industry are zinc oxide (ZnO) and copper sulfate (CuSO4) because of <lb/>their relatively low cost compared with other forms [10,11]. These act as alternatives to in-feed antibiotics for <lb/>promoting growth and have antimicrobial effects such as reducing diarrhea incidence in weaned pigs at <lb/>concentration levels exceeding normal nutritional requirements according to the National Research Council [11]. <lb/>Specifically, pharmacological levels (2,000 to 4,000 mg/kg) of ZnO have been commonly supplemented in <lb/>weanling diets to promote growth performance and reduce diarrhea frequency by enhancing morphological <lb/>structure and maintaining gut integrity [12,13] . In addition, previous studies reported that a dose of 150 to 250 <lb/>mg/kg supplementation of CuSO 4 stimulates growth rate, and feed intake, and sustains fecal consistency via <lb/>modulating gut microbiota homeostasis in the intestine [14,15]. <lb/>However, supplementation of high doses of CuSO 4 (200 to 250 mg/kg) and ZnO (2,000 to 4,000 mg/kg) <lb/>in the nursery diet can be excreted through manure without being normally absorbed into the intestine, resulting <lb/>in environmental pollution [16-18]. Based on these issues, the European Union has legislated new maximum <lb/>levels to limit Zn and Cu supplementation to 150 mg/kg up to 4 weeks after weaning [19,20]. Thus, new forms of <lb/>Cu and Zn at lower doses have been proposed to reduce excretions and improve growth performance during the <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <body>weaning phase. Lipid-coated and concentrated forms of ZnO and CuSO 4 , protect against the formation of insoluble <lb/>complexes with other minerals and dissociation in the stomach. They are dissociated by pancreatic lipase, and <lb/>efficiently absorbed in the small intestine of monogastric animals [21-23]. A previous in vitro study presented the <lb/>dissociation percentage of coated and uncoated ZnO in the stomach. The results showed that the percentages were <lb/>25.03% for coated and 85.26% in uncoated ZnO [24]. Consequently, this reduced the quantity released into the <lb/>soil through the manure. Therefore, the objective of this study was to evaluate the effects of low doses of lipid-<lb/>coated CuSO 4 and ZnO on the growth performance, diarrhea, nutrient digestibility, immune responses, and fecal <lb/>microbiota of weaned pigs. <lb/>MATERIALS AND METHODS <lb/>All the experimental protocol for this study was reviewed and approved by the Institutional Animal Care <lb/>and Use Committee of Chungnam National University, Daejeon, Republic of Korea. (approval# 202103A-CNU-<lb/>080) <lb/>Source of tested products <lb/>The lipid-coated ZnO and CuSO 4 practiced in this study were provided by a commercial company (ACC <lb/>Inc., Seongnam, Republic of Korea). These products are concentrated forms of Zn and Cu from zinc oxide (ZnO) <lb/>and copper sulfate pentahydrate (CuSO 4 •5H2O) which are microencapsulated in a lipid matrix by fatty acids and <lb/>hydrogenated palm oil according to the manufacturer&apos;s information. <lb/>Experimental design, animals, and diets <lb/>A total of 96 weaned piglets [(Landrace × Yorkshire) × Duroc; 7.29 ± 0.69 kg of average initial body <lb/>weight (BW)] were assigned to four dietary treatments (4 pigs/pen; 6 replicates/treatment) in a randomized <lb/>complete block design (block = initial BW). The dietary treatments were (1) basal weaner diet based on corn-<lb/>soybean meal (CON), (2) CON supplemented with 2,500 ppm standard ZnO (T1), (3) CON supplemented with <lb/>100 mg/kg dietary coated CuSO 4 and 100 mg/kg dietary coated ZnO (T2), and (4) CON supplemented with 200 <lb/>mg/kg dietary coated CuSO 4 and 200 mg/kg dietary coated ZnO (T3). The basal diet was mixed to meet or exceed <lb/>the nutritional requirements of the National Research Council (NRC, 2012) for weaned pigs. The study was <lb/>conducted for 6 weeks, and the pigs were allowed ad libitum access to feeders and water and were housed in the <lb/>same-sized pen (2 m × 2 m) throughout the experimental period. <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <body>Data and sample collection <lb/>In each pen, pigs&apos; BW and remaining feed were weighed on days 1, 14, and 42 to figure out the average <lb/>daily gain (ADG), average daily feed intake (ADFI), and gain to feed ratio (G:F). The fecal score of the pigs was <lb/>visually monitored in each pen by two independent observers during the first 2 weeks. The score ranged from 1 <lb/>to 5 (1 = hard and dry feces, 2 = soft feces, 3 = moist feces, 4 = mild diarrhea, and 5 = mild and severe diarrhea) <lb/>and were calculated by counting the number of pen days with a diarrhea score of 4 or higher as a percentage. <lb/>Blood samples were collected from the jugular vein of one randomly selected pig per pen using 10 mL tubes with <lb/>or without ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA) on days 1, 7, and 14. Blood samples from tubes without EDTA <lb/>were left to clot at room temperature for 2 hours and then centrifuged for 15 min at 3,000 × g at 4 ℃ to obtain <lb/>serum. These samples were stored at -80℃ for immune response analysis. In the final week of the experiment, <lb/>0.2 % chromic oxide (Cr2O3) was fed to all pigs as an indigestible marker. Fecal samples were collected from a <lb/>randomly one selected pig per pen using rectal palpation for three days after the adaption period and stored at <lb/>-20°C to measure nutrient digestibility [25,26]. Fecal samples were obtained from three randomly chosen pigs in <lb/>each dietary treatment on the last day of the experiment and stored at -80°C until metagenomic and fecal microbial <lb/>analysis <lb/>Nutrient digestibility analysis <lb/>Diets and fecal samples were dried using a forced-air drying oven at 65°C for 72 h and then ground <lb/>through a grinder (80350, Hamilton Beach Inc, Virginia, USA) for apparent total tract digestibility (ATTD) <lb/>analysis. All ground samples were examined for dry matter (DM), crude protein (CP) by Kjeldahl method, and <lb/>energy using a bomb calorimeter (Parr 1281 Bomb Calorimeter, Parr Instrument, Moline, IL, USA) following the <lb/>procedures of the Association of Official Analytical Chemists [27]. The concentration of chromium in the samples <lb/>was determined using an absorption spectrophotometer (Hitachi Z-5000 Absorption Spectrophotometer, Hitachi <lb/>High-Technologies Co., Tokyo, Japan). The ATTD of the DM, CP, and energy for each dietary treatment were <lb/>calculated according to the previous study [28]. <lb/>Blood samples analysis <lb/>Whole blood samples were collected in EDTA tubes using an automated hematology analyzer (scil Vet <lb/>abc hematology analyzer; scil animal care company, F-67120 Altorf, France) [29] . The measurements included <lb/>the numbers of white blood cell (WBC), red blood cell (RBC), and hematocrit (HCT). The serum samples were <lb/>applied to determine immune responses including tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α) and cortisol using porcine <lb/>enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay kits (ELISA) kits (R&amp;D Systems Inc., Minneapolis, MN, USA). <lb/>Additionally, levels of serum immunoglobulin A (IgA), serum immunoglobulin G (IgG), and serum <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <body>immunoglobulin M (IgM) were determined using ELSA kits (Bethyl Laboratories, Inc., Waltham, MA, USA). All <lb/>assays were performed according to the manufacturer&apos;s instructions. <lb/>Fecal microbiota analysis <lb/>DNA was extracted from fecal samples (200 mg of feces per sample) using the QIAamp Fast DNA Stool <lb/>Mini Kit (QIAGEN, Hilden, Germany) based on the manufacturer&apos;s protocol. The concentration of DNA was <lb/>measured using the Colibri Microvolume Spectrometer (Titertek Berthold, Pforzheim, Germany), and the samples <lb/>with OD260/280 ratios between 1.80 and 2.15 were used to additional analysis [30]. The V5 to V6 regions of the <lb/>16S rRNA genes were amplified using sets of polymerase chain reaction (PCR) primers consisted of 799F-mod6 and <lb/>114R [31]. After PCR amplification, the products were refined using a Wizard® SV Gel and PCR Clean Up System <lb/>purification kit (Promega, Madison, United States). The sequencing of purified 16S rRNA gene was performed <lb/>using the Illumina MiSeq platform at BRD Inc (Dongtan, Republic of Korea) following the manufacturer&apos;s <lb/>protocols. Quality control of all raw sequence data was checked utilizing FastQC [32], and then the 16S rRNA <lb/>gene sequences were analyzed using the Deblur algorithm, which is executed in both QIIME2 software and the <lb/>Microbiome Helper pipeline [33]. After applying the algorithm, sequences were grouped into operational <lb/>taxonomic units (OTUs), determined at a similarity cutoff of 97% [34]. Alpha diversity indices such as the <lb/>observed OTUs, Shannon, Simpson, and Chao1 were measured to compare the diversity of microbial communities <lb/>within each dietary treatment. In addition, principal coordinated analysis (PCoA) based on unweighted and <lb/>weighted UniFrac distances was used to visualize differences in microbial communities among the dietary <lb/>treatments. Taxonomic composition of the dietary treatments was expressed as a percentage at the phylum and <lb/>genus levels based on their relative abundance. <lb/>Statistical analyses <lb/>Data were subjected to the GLM procedure of SAS (SAS Inst., Cary, NC, USA) using a randomized <lb/>complete block design (block = initial BW). The experimental unit was the pen. The statistical models for growth <lb/>performance, nutrient digestibility, blood profiles, and immune responses of weaned pigs included the effects of <lb/>dietary treatment as the main effect and initial BW as a covariate. The frequency of diarrhea was analyzed using <lb/>the Chi-square test. The MicrobiomeAnalyst webtool (https://www.microbiomeanalyst.ca/) was used to analyze <lb/>alpha and beta diversity. STAMP software v. 2.1.3 [35] was used for taxonomic classification using a two-sided <lb/>Welch&apos;s t-test. Alpha diversity indices were measured using ANOVA and beta diversity based on unweighted and <lb/>weighted UniFrac distances was estimated using ANOSIM to determine the differences in microbial diversity <lb/>among the dietary treatments. Statistical difference and tendency for dietary treatment effects were set at p &lt; 0.05 <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <body>and 0.05 ≤ p &lt; 0.10, respectively. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Growth performance, frequency of diarrhea, and nutrient digestibility <lb/>Pigs fed dietary T2 and T3 had higher (p &lt; 0.05) ADG and G:F on day 1 to 14 than those fed CON (Table <lb/>2). Additionally, the groups supplemented with Cu and Zn tended to have a lower (p &lt; 0.10) frequency of diarrhea <lb/>than those fed CON. However, no differences were found in overall average ADFI for the first 14 days after <lb/>weaning among the dietary treatments. In addition, dietary T2 and T3 increased (p &lt; 0.05) ADG over the entire <lb/>experimental period compared with the CON. As shown in Table 3, no differences were found ATTD of DM, CP <lb/>and energy among dietary treatments. <lb/>Blood profiles and immune responses <lb/>Pigs fed dietary T2 tended to have lower (p &lt; 0.10) number of WBC on day 7 and HCT on day 14 than <lb/>those fed CON (Table 4). However, there was no difference in RBC among dietary treatments. Regarding immune <lb/>responses (Table 4), dietary T1 tended to have a lower (p &lt; 0.10) concentration of serum cortisol on day 7 and a <lb/>higher (p &lt; 0.10) serum immunoglobulin M (IgM) than CON. In addition, dietary T2 tended to have decreased (p <lb/>&lt; 0.10) serum concentrations of TNF-α on day 7 and increased (p &lt; 0.10) serum IgG on day 14 compared with <lb/>CON. However, no differences were found in serum IgA levels among the dietary treatments. <lb/>Fecal microbiota <lb/>The microbial alpha diversity indices are shown in Fig. 1. Dietary T1 tended to have lower (p &lt; 0.10) <lb/>Chao1, Simpson, and Shannon indices than CON and T3. The beta diversity of the fecal microbiota determined <lb/>using PCoA plots is presented in Fig. 2. PCoA plots based on the unweighted UniFrac distance, confirmed that <lb/>T1 had distinct clustering from other groups, but overlapped clustering with CON, T2, and T3 (R = 0.463, p &lt; <lb/>0.05). However, there was some distinct separation of fecal microbial communities based on the weighted UniFrac <lb/>distance among the dietary treatments (R = 0.201, p &lt; 0.10). The relative abundances of the fecal microbes at the <lb/>phylum and genus level among the dietary treatments are shown in Figures 3 and 4, respectively. At the phylum <lb/>level (Fig. 3), Firmicutes were the most predominant bacteria in all dietary treatments (CON, 83.82%; T1, 82.98%; <lb/>T2, 91.44%; T3, 80.19%), followed by Bacteroidetes in CON (5.83%) and T1 (14.67%), and Actinobacteria and <lb/>Proteobacteria in T2 (2.9%) and T3 (7.16%). At the genus level (Fig. 4), dietary T2 tended to increase (p &lt; 0.10) <lb/>relative abundance of Limosilactobacilus (24.77%) compared to those fed dietary T1 (0.33%). In addition, pigs <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <body>fed dietary T3 had higher (p &lt; 0.05) relative abundance of Agathobacter (3.39%) than those fed CON (1.26%) <lb/>and dietary T1 (0.04%). Additionally, dietary T3 had a lower relative abundance of Terrisporobacter (1.74%) <lb/>compared to those fed dietary T1 (12.77%). <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>Minerals are inorganic elements that improve growth and reproduction in pigs [11]. In the livestock <lb/>industry, micro minerals such as Cu and Zn, typically in the form of CuSO 4 and ZnO are widely supplemented <lb/>into the diet in amounts that exceed the nutritional requirements of weanling pigs [24-26]. However, when <lb/>these compounds reach the stomach of piglets, large amounts of ZnO and CuSO 4 are dissociated into Zn and <lb/>Cu ions, respectively, and great quantities are lost in the digestive tract. Because only a small amount of these <lb/>complexes can reach the intestinal tract, high doses are required. However, the inclusion level in feed must be <lb/>lowered owing to global regulations on environmental pollution through excretion and/or malabsorption by <lb/>overnutrition. Therefore, modified forms such as organic, nanoparticles and lipid-coated forms have been <lb/>researched and utilized into swine feed [27-30]. Results from this study demonstrated that the dietary T2 and <lb/>T3 groups enhanced the ADG and G:F for the first two weeks and the overall period compared with that of the <lb/>CON group, which is consistent with previous studies where supplementation in coated or nano-sized forms <lb/>[31-33]. An improvement in growth performance was observed with the supplementation of a lower dosage of <lb/>dietary-coated CuSO 4 and ZnO in the present study due to the relatively high bioavailability and absorption of <lb/>Cu and Zn in the small intestine compared with standard forms of CuSO 4 and ZnO. In general, no additive <lb/>effects were observed when excess Zn was added to Cu [39]. Specifically, metallothionein in the intestinal <lb/>mucosa is induced by high concentrations of Zn, resulting in Cu binding, and causing Cu deficiency by <lb/>disturbing its absorption [40,41]. Therefore, the results suggested that balanced doses of coated CuSO 4 and <lb/>ZnO were better absorbed and enhanced growth rate compare with CON as same as supplementation of <lb/>pharmacological levels of ZnO. <lb/>In this study, supplementation with dietary coated CuSO 4 and ZnO tended to have decreased the <lb/>frequency of diarrhea. In addition, HCT in the blood profiles, which increases with dehydration and is used as <lb/>an indicator of increases in diarrhea [42], did not differ among the dietary treatments in the first week after <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <body>weaning. However, supplementation with low dose of dietary coated microminerals tended to decrease HCT <lb/>on day 14, and we demonstrated that this supplementation positively affected the fecal score. Furthermore, no <lb/>differences in the ATTD of DM, CP, and energy among the dietary treatments. However, several previous <lb/>studies have reported that ZnO and CuSO 4 supplementation in the form of lipid-coated or nano-type positively <lb/>affected nutrient and energy digestibility, which were attributed to digestive enzymes and morphological <lb/>changes in the small intestine [43-45]. Therefore, additional research on digestive enzyme activity and nutrient <lb/>digestibility should be conducted because they may differ depending on the processing type, method, or <lb/>concentrations of the microminerals. <lb/>As intestinal permeability increases due to weaning stress, potentially pathogenic bacteria can penetrate <lb/>and cause not only intestinal inflammation but also systemic inflammatory responses [42]. Changes in the WBC <lb/>count, indicative of systemic inflammation, are associated with alterations in the levels of cytokines involved <lb/>in maintaining immunity and homeostasis [46,47]. Serum TNF-α is one of the pro-inflammatory cytokines, <lb/>used as a potential indicator of inflammatory reactions and damaging the mucosal barrier system [48]. Changes <lb/>in these parameters regulate the systemic immune responses against infections or diseases caused by weaning <lb/>stress. Previous studies reported that supplementation of CuSO 4 and ZnO reduced and downregulated the <lb/>concentrations and mRNA levels of inflammatory cytokines including TNF-α in the intestinal mucosa of <lb/>weaned pigs [24,37]. The current study further demonstrated that dietary coated CuSO 4 and ZnO alleviated <lb/>systemic immune responses caused by weaning stress through the reduction of WBC and serum TNF-α levels. <lb/>Serum IgA, IgM, and IgG levels, which are the major components of humoral immunity, are reduced by <lb/>weaning stress and immature immunity of piglets [49]. In this study, dietary coated CuSO 4 and ZnO improved <lb/>serum IgG levels of weaned pigs, consistent with the results of previous studies [17,50]. IgG is a type of <lb/>antibody that leads to control the infection via binding many pathogens such as bacteria and viruses by immune <lb/>cells such as macrophages. Furthermore, it has been reported that free Cu and Zn ions possess antimicrobial <lb/>properties against E.coli in the small intestine [51]. Although the specific mechanisms of microminerals <lb/>activities are not entirely elucidated yet, it is widely accepted that these metallic ions degrade bacterial cell <lb/>membranes by disrupting the integrity of bacterial cell membranes, inducing cell death. In addition, ions <lb/>increase the release of reactive oxygen species within microorganisms, leading to pathogen destruction [52]. <lb/>Collectively, dietary supplementation with coated Cu and Zn modulates immune responses by preventing the <lb/>breakdown of the intestinal barrier and overproduction of pro-inflammatory cytokines. <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <body>Many studies have reported that dietary supplementation of pharmacological concentration of Cu and Zn <lb/>improves intestinal microorganisms by increasing the number of beneficial bacteria and reducing pathogenic <lb/>microbial composition [53,54]. The diversity and composition of the intestinal microbiota in pigs are <lb/>considerably affected by health condition and the digestion of nutrients compositions through physiological <lb/>functions [55]. In our study, the Shannon index tended to increase with coated CuSO 4 and ZnO compared to <lb/>that with the standard dosage of ZnO, indicating greater diversity in the fecal microbiota of piglets. Shen et al. <lb/>[24] showed that a pharmacological dosage of ZnO reduced the richness of microbial populations in the <lb/>jejunum and feces of weaning pigs, which was consistent with the results of our study. In general, diversity is <lb/>often associated with the presence of beneficial bacteria that can counteract pathogens [56]. However, the <lb/>relative abundance of bacteria among dietary treatments was compared through taxonomic classification for a <lb/>more precise interpretation. At the phylum level, the Firmicutes and Bacteroidetes accounted for approximately <lb/>90% of all treatments in the fecal microbiomes of weaned pigs. Among the dietary treatments, dietary T2 had <lb/>the highest proportion of Firmicutes. Since Lactobacillus and Clostridium were dominant genera within <lb/>Firmicutes, we determined that the overall portion of Lactobacillus (22.4%), Limosilactobacilus (24.78%), and <lb/>Clostridium sensu stricto (10.23%) in the T2 was higher than in the other treatments. At the genus level, the <lb/>present study showed that pigs fed dietary T2 had a higher relative abundance of genus Limosilactobacilus <lb/>compared with T1. Limosilactobacilus is a genus of lactic acid bacteria that recently split from Lactobacillus <lb/>and includes the species Limosilactobacilus reuteri, which is a microorganism with properties that promotes <lb/>intestinal health and is widely used as a probiotic strain [54,57]. Furthermore, the relative abundance of fecal <lb/>microbiota increased Agathobacter and decreased Terrisporobacter in dietary T3 compared with that in CON <lb/>and dietary T1. Agathobacter is a beneficial bacterium that contributes to short-chain fatty acid production, <lb/>particularly butyrate, and is positively correlated with overall gut health in humans through metabolic <lb/>interactions of the gut microbiota [58]. Furthermore, Terrisporobacter shows a positive correlation with <lb/>increased serum markers such as endotoxin and TNF-α, which promote oxidative stress, inflammation, and <lb/>malnutrition of gut microbiota in weaned pigs [59,60]. Therefore, the higher relative abundance of <lb/>Limosilactobacilus and Agathobacter may have contributed to the suppression of Terrisporobacter and <lb/>stabilization of the intestinal environment, thereby enhancing the growth performance of pigs fed dietary coated <lb/>CuSO 4 and ZnO than those fed CON and standard ZnO diets. <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <body>CONCLUSION <lb/>Our study demonstrated that dietary coated CuSO 4 and ZnO supplementation in a nursery diet had <lb/>beneficial effects on growth performance and modulation of immune response and gut microbiota in weaned pigs. <lb/>These results indicate that improvement in growth performance and immune response may be associated with <lb/>changes in the fecal microbiota composition compared with CON group. In conclusion, dietary coated CuSO 4 and <lb/>ZnO have positive effects in weaned pigs and represent potential alternatives to high levels of ZnO diets. <lb/></body>

        <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>This work was carried out with the support of &quot;Cooperative Research Program for Agriculture Science <lb/>and Technology Development (RS-2023-00230754), Rural Development Administration, Republic of Korea, and <lb/>ACC Inc., Seongnam, Republic of Korea. <lb/></div>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Rhouma M, Fairbrother JM, Beaudry F, Letellier A. Post weaning diarrhea in pigs: Risk factors and non-<lb/>colistin-based control strategies. Acta Vet Scand. BioMed Central Ltd.; 2017 <lb/>2. Lallès JP, Boudry G, Favier C, Le Floc&apos;h N, Luron I, Montagne L, et al. Gut function and dysfunction in <lb/>young pigs: Physiology. Animal Res. 2004;53:301-16 <lb/>3. Campbell JM, Crenshaw JD, Polo J. The biological stress of early weaned piglets. J Anim Sci Biotechnol. <lb/>2013;4:19 <lb/>4. Moeser AJ, Klok C Vander, Ryan KA, Wooten JG, Little D, Cook VL, et al. Stress signaling pathways <lb/>activated by weaning mediate intestinal dysfunction in the pig. Am J Physiol Gastrointest liver Physiol. <lb/>2007;292(1):G173-181 <lb/>5. Girard M, Bee G. Invited review: Tannins as a potential alternative to antibiotics to prevent coliform diarrhea <lb/>in weaned pigs. Anim. Cambridge University Press; 2020;14;95-107 <lb/>6. Stein HH, Kil DY. Reduced use of antibiotic growth promoters in diets fed to weanling pigs: Dietary tools, <lb/>part 2. Anim Biotechnol. 2006;17:217-31 <lb/>7. Yazdankhah S, Rudi K, Bernhoft A. Zinc and copper in animal feed -development of resistance and co-<lb/>resistance to antimicrobial agents in bacteria of animal origin. Microb Ecol Health Dis. 2014. doi: <lb/>10.3402/mehd.v25.25862 <lb/>8. Hedemann MS, Jensen BB, Poulsen HD. Influence of dietary zinc and copper on digestive enzyme activity <lb/>and intestinal morphology in weaned pigs. J Anim Sci. 2006;84:3310-20 <lb/>9. Bonetti A, Tugnoli B, Piva A, Grilli E. Towards zero zinc oxide: Feeding strategies to manage post-weaning <lb/>diarrhea in piglets. Animals. MDPI AG; 2021;11:1-24 <lb/>10. Wen Y, Li R, Piao X, Lin G, He P. Different copper sources and levels affect growth performance, copper <lb/>content, carcass characteristics, intestinal microorganism and metabolism of finishing pigs. Anim Nutr. <lb/>2022;8:321-30 <lb/>11. Liu Y, Espinosa CD, Abelilla JJ, Casas GA, Lagos LV, Lee SA, et al. Non-antibiotic feed additives in diets <lb/>for pigs: A review. Anim Nutr. 2018;4(2):113-25 <lb/>12. Hu C, Song J, Li Y, Luan Z, Zhu K. Diosmectite-zinc oxide composite improves intestinal barrier function, <lb/>modulates expression of pro-inflammatory cytokines and tight junction protein in early weaned pigs. British <lb/>Journal of Nutrition. 2013;110:681-8 <lb/>13. Zhu C, Lv H, Chen Z, Wang L, Wu X, Chen Z, et al. Dietary Zinc Oxide Modulates Antioxidant Capacity, <lb/>Small Intestine Development, and Jejunal Gene Expression in Weaned Piglets. Biol Trace Elem Res. <lb/></listBibl>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <listBibl>2017;175:331-8 <lb/>14. Bikker P, Jongbloed AW, Van Baal J. Dose-dependent effects of copper supplementation of nursery diets on <lb/>growth performance and fecal consistency in weaned pigs. J Anim Sci. 2016;94:181-6. <lb/>15. Cromwell GL, Stahly TS, Monegue HJ. Effects of source and level of copper on performance and liver <lb/>copper stores in weanling pigs. J Anim Sci. 1989;67:2996-3002 <lb/>16. Zhao J, Allee G, Gerlemann G, Ma L, Gracia MI, Parker D, et al. Effects of a chelated copper as growth <lb/>promoter on performance and carcass traits in pigs. Asian-Australas J Anim Sci. 2014;27:965-73 <lb/>17. Sun YB, Xia T, Wu H, Zhang WJ, Zhu YH, Xue JX, et al. Effects of nano zinc oxide as an alternative to <lb/>pharmacological dose of zinc oxide on growth performance, diarrhea, immune responses, and intestinal <lb/>microflora profile in weaned piglets. Anim Feed Sci Technol. 2019;258:114312 <lb/>18. Lei XJ, Liu ZZ, Park JH, Kim IH. Novel zinc sources as antimicrobial growth promoters for monogastric <lb/>animals: a review. J Anim Sci Technol. 2022;64:187 <lb/>19. Blavi L, Villagómez-Estrada S, Solà-Oriol D, Pérez JF. Exploring zinc deficiency using serum Zn levels: <lb/>consequences and potential solutions in suckling pigs. J Anim Sci. 2024;102 <lb/>20. Revision of the currently authorised maximum copper content in complete feed. EFSA Journal. 2016;14 <lb/>21. Jang I, Kwon C, Ha D, Jung D, Kang S, Park M, et al. Effects of a lipid-encapsulated zinc oxide supplement <lb/>on growth performance and intestinal morphology and digestive enzyme activities in weanling pigs. J Anim <lb/>Sci Technol. 2014;56:29 <lb/>22. Wilk M, Pecka-Kiełb E, Pastuszak J, Asghar MU, Mól L. Effects of Copper Sulfate and Encapsulated Copper <lb/>Addition on In Vitro Rumen Fermentation and Methane Production. Agriculture (Switzerland). 2022;12:1943 <lb/>23. Liu Y, Ma YL, Zhao JM, Vazquez-Añón M, Stein HH. Digestibility and retention of zinc, copper, manganese, <lb/>iron, calcium, and phosphorus in pigs fed diets containing inorganic or organic minerals 1. J Anim Sci. <lb/>2014;92:3407-15 <lb/>24. Shen J, Chen Y, Wang Z, Zhou A, He M, Mao L, et al. Coated zinc oxide improves intestinal immunity <lb/>function and regulates microbiota composition in weaned piglets. British Journal of Nutrition. <lb/>2014;111:2123-34 <lb/>25. Song M, Kim B, Cho JH, Kyoung H, Park S, Cho JY, et al. Effects of dietary protease supplementation on <lb/>growth rate, nutrient digestibility, and intestinal morphology of weaned pigs. J Anim Sci Technol. <lb/>2022;64:462-70 <lb/>26. Park S, Choe J, Cho JH, Jang KB, Kyoung H, Park KI, et al. Determination of optimal energy system and <lb/>level for growing pigs. J Anim Sci Technol. 2024;66:514-22 <lb/></listBibl>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <listBibl>27. AOAC.2010. Official Methods of Analysis of AOAC International 962.09 2-4 <lb/>28. Stein HH, Sève B, Fuller MF, Moughan PJ, De Lange CFM. Invited review: Amino acid bioavailability and <lb/>digestibility in pig feed ingredients: Terminology and application. J Anim Sci. 2007;85(1):172-80 <lb/>29. Nam J, Kyoung H, Kim JN, Cho JH, Kim Y, Ahn J, et al. Effects of dietary aluminosilicate on growth <lb/>performance,frequency of diarrhea, and blood profiles of weaned pigs. J Anim Sci Technol. <lb/>2024;jast.2024.e21 <lb/>30. Keum GB, Kim ES, Cho J, Song M, Oh KK, Cho JH, et al. Analysis of antibiotic resistance genes in pig <lb/>feces during the weaning transition using whole metagenome shotgun sequencing. J Anim Sci Technol. <lb/>2023;65:175-82 <lb/>31. Lee JH, Kim S, Kim ES, Keum GB, Doo H, Kwak J, et al. Comparative analysis of the pig gut microbiome <lb/>associated with the pig growth performance. J Anim Sci Technol. 2023;65:856-64 <lb/>32. Kim H, Cho JH, Cho JH, Song M, Shin H, Kim S, et al. Complete genome sequence of Escherichia coli <lb/>K_EC180, a bacterium producing Shiga-like toxin isolated from swine feces. J Anim Sci Technol. <lb/>2021;63:461-4 <lb/>33. Kim S, Kwak J, Song M, Cho J, Kim ES, Keum GB, et al. Effects of Lacticaseibacillus casei (Lactobacillus <lb/>casei) and Saccharomyces cerevisiae mixture on growth performance, hematological parameters, <lb/>immunological responses, and intestinal microbiome in weaned pigs. Front Vet Sci. 2023;10:1140718 <lb/>34. Li W, Fu L, Niu B, Wu S, Wooley J. Ultrafast clustering algorithms for metagenomic sequence analysis. Brief <lb/>Bioinform. 2012;13:656-68 <lb/>35. Parks DH, Tyson GW, Hugenholtz P, Beiko RG. STAMP: Statistical analysis of taxonomic and functional <lb/>profiles. Bioinformatics. 2014;30:3123-4 <lb/>36. Schell TC, Kornegay ET. Zinc Concentration in Tissues and Performance of Weanling Pigs Fed <lb/>Pharmacological Levels of Zinc from ZnO, Zn-Methionine, Zn-Lysine, or ZnSO4. J Anim Sci. <lb/>1996;74:1584-93 <lb/>37. Shelton NW, Tokach MD, Nelssen JL, Goodband RD, Dritz SS, Derouchey JM, et al. Effects of copper <lb/>sulfate, tri-basic copper chloride, and zinc oxide on weanling pig performance. J Anim Sci. 2011;89:2440-<lb/>51 <lb/>38. Oh HJ, Kim MH, Lee JH, Kim YJ, An JW, Chang SY, et al. Effects of different inorganic: organic zinc ratios <lb/>or combination of low crude protein diet and mixed feed additive in weaned piglet diets. J Anim Sci Technol. <lb/>2022;64:23-37 <lb/>39. Esparza Gonzalez BP, Fong RN, Gibson CJ, Fuentealba IC, George Cherian AM. Zinc Supplementation <lb/>Decreases Hepatic Copper Accumulation in LEC Rat A Model of Wilson&apos;s Disease. Biol Trace Elem Res. <lb/>2005;105:117-134 <lb/></listBibl>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <listBibl>40. Cousins RJ. Absorption, Transport, and Hepatic Metabolism of Copper and Zinc: Special Reference to <lb/>Metallothionein and Ceruloplasmin. Physiol Rev. 1985;65:238-309 <lb/>41. Jeng SS, Chen YH. Association of Zinc with Anemia. Nutrients. 2022;14:4918 <lb/>42. Moeser AJ, Pohl CS, Rajput M. Weaning stress and gastrointestinal barrier development: Implications for <lb/>lifelong gut health in pigs. Anim Nutr. 2017;3(4):313-21 <lb/>43. Oh HJ, Park YJ, Cho JH, Song MH, Gu BH, Yun W, et al. Changes in diarrhea score, nutrient digestibility, <lb/>zinc utilization, intestinal immune profiles, and fecal microbiome in weaned piglets by different forms of <lb/>zinc. Animals. 2021;11:1356 <lb/>44. Lei XJ, Kim IH. Low dose of coated zinc oxide is as effective as pharmacological zinc oxide in promoting <lb/>growth performance, reducing fecal scores, and improving nutrient digestibility and intestinal morphology <lb/>in weaned pigs. Anim Feed Sci Technol. 2018;245:117-25 <lb/>45. Kim M, Hosseindoust A, Choi Y, Lee J, Kim K, Kim T, et al. Effects of Hot-Melt Extruded Nano-Copper as <lb/>an Alternative for the Pharmacological Dose of Copper Sulfate in Weanling Pigs. 2021;199:2925-35 <lb/>46. Han Y, Zhan T, Tang C, Zhao Q, Dansou DM, Yu Y, et al. Effect of replacing in-feed antibiotic growth <lb/>promoters with a combination of egg immunoglobulins and phytomolecules on the performance, serum <lb/>immunity, and intestinal health of weaned pigs challenged with escherichia coli k88. Animals. 2021;11:1292 <lb/>47. Liu Y, Song M, Che TM, Almeida JAS, Lee JJ, Bravo D, et al. Dietary plant extracts alleviate diarrhea and <lb/>alter immune responses of weaned pigs experimentally infected with a pathogenic. J Anim Sci. <lb/>2013;91:5294-306 <lb/>48. Zhang L, Xu YQ, Liu HY, Lai T, Ma JL, Wang JF, et al. Evaluation of Lactobacillus rhamnosus GG using an <lb/>Escherichia coli K88 model of piglet diarrhoea: Effects on diarrhoea incidence, faecal microflora and <lb/>immune responses. Vet Microbiol. 2010;141:142-8 <lb/>49. Klobasa F, Butler JE, Werhahn E, Habe F. Maternal-neonatal immunoregulation in swine. II. Influence of <lb/>multiparity on de novo immunoglobulin synthesis by piglets. Vet Immunol Immunopathol. 1986;11:149-59 <lb/>50. Gonzales-Eguia A, Fu CM, Lu FY, Lien TF. Effects of nanocopper on copper availability and nutrients <lb/>digestibility, growth performance and serum traits of piglets. Livest Sci. 2009;126:122-9 <lb/>51. Raja FNS, Worthington T, Martin RA. The antimicrobial efficacy of copper, cobalt, zinc and silver <lb/>nanoparticles: alone and in combination. Biomedical Materials (Bristol). 2023;18:0405003 <lb/>52. Duarte ME, Garavito-Duarte Y, Kim SW. Impacts of F18+ Escherichia coli on Intestinal Health of Nursery <lb/>Pigs and Dietary Interventions. Animals. 2023;13:2791 <lb/>53. Zheng J, Wittouck S, Salvetti E, Franz CMAP, Harris HMB, Mattarelli P, et al. A taxonomic note on the <lb/>genus Lactobacillus: Description of 23 novel genera, emended description of the genus Lactobacillus <lb/></listBibl>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <listBibl>beijerinck 1901, and union of Lactobacillaceae and Leuconostocaceae. Int J Syst Evol Microbiol. <lb/>2020;70:2782-858 <lb/>54. Abuqwider J, Altamimi M, Mauriello G. Limosilactobacillus reuteri in Health and Disease. Microorganisms. <lb/>2022;10:522 <lb/>55. Rist VTS, Weiss E, Eklund M, Mosenthin R. Impact of dietary protein on microbiota composition and activity <lb/>in the gastrointestinal tract of piglets in relation to gut health: A review. Animal. 2013;7:1067-78 <lb/>56. Schokker D, Kar SK, Willems E, Bossers A, Dekker RA, Jansman AJM. Dietary supplementation of zinc <lb/>oxide modulates intestinal functionality during the post-weaning period in clinically healthy piglets. J Anim <lb/>Sci Biotechnol. 2023;14 <lb/>57. Duar RM, Frese SA, Lin XB, Fernando SC, Burkey TE, Tasseva G, et al. Experimental evaluation of host <lb/>adaptation of Lactobacillus reuteri to different vertebrate species. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2017;83 <lb/>58. Granado-Serrano AB, Martín-Garí M, Sánchez V, Riart Solans M, Berdún R, Ludwig IA, et al. Faecal <lb/>bacterial and short-chain fatty acids signature in hypercholesterolemia. Sci Rep. 2019;9:1772 <lb/>59. Cai C, Zhang Z, Morales M, Wang Y, Khafipour E, Friel J. Feeding practice influences gut microbiome <lb/>composition in very low birth weight preterm infants and the association with oxidative stress: A prospective <lb/>cohort study. Free Radic Biol Med. 2019;142:146-54 <lb/>60. Liu B, Zhu X, Cui Y, Wang W, Liu H, Li Z, et al. Consumption of Dietary Fiber from Different Sources <lb/>during Pregnancy Alters Sow Gut Microbiota and Improves Performance and Reduces Inflammation in Sows <lb/>and Piglets. Msystems. 2021;6:10-1128 <lb/></listBibl>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <body>Table 1. Composition of basal diet for weaned pigs (as-fed basis) <lb/>Item <lb/>Basal diet <lb/>Ingredient, % <lb/>Corn <lb/>49.86 <lb/>Soybean meal, 44% <lb/>25.00 <lb/>Whey powder <lb/>12.50 <lb/>Soy protein concentrate <lb/>6.25 <lb/>Soybean oil <lb/>3.00 <lb/>Limestone <lb/>1.14 <lb/>Monocalcium phosphate <lb/>1.05 <lb/>Vitamin premix 1) <lb/>0.20 <lb/>Mineral premix 2) <lb/>0.20 <lb/>L-Lysine•HCl <lb/>0.45 <lb/>DL-Methionine <lb/>0.16 <lb/>L-Threonine <lb/>0.13 <lb/>L-Valine <lb/>0.06 <lb/>Total <lb/>100.00 <lb/>Calculated energy and nutrient <lb/>Metabolizable energy, kcal/kg <lb/>3,465 <lb/>Crude protein, % <lb/>21.26 <lb/>Calcium, % <lb/>0.81 <lb/>Phosphorous, % <lb/>0.65 <lb/>Lysine, % <lb/>1.53 <lb/>Methionine, % <lb/>0.47 <lb/>Threonine, % <lb/>0.95 <lb/>Tryptophan, % <lb/>0.25 <lb/>1) Vitamin premix provided the following quantities of vitamin per kilogram of complete diet: vitamin A, 12,000 <lb/>IU; vitamin D 3 , 2,500 IU; vitamin E, 30 IU; vitamin K 3 , 3 mg; D-pantothenic acid, 15 mg; nicotinic acid, 40 mg; <lb/>choline, 400 mg; and vitamin B 12 , 12 μg. <lb/>2) Mineral premix provided the following quantities of mineral per kilogram of complete diet: Fe, 90 mg from <lb/>iron sulfate; Cu, 8.8 mg from copper sulfate; Zn, 100 mg from zinc oxide; Mn, 54 mg from manganese oxide; I, <lb/>0.35 mg from potassium iodide; Se, 0.30 mg from sodium selenite. <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <body>Table 2. Effects of dietary coated CuSO 4 and ZnO on growth performance of weaned pigs 1) <lb/>Item 2) <lb/>CON <lb/>T1 <lb/>T2 <lb/>T3 <lb/>SEM <lb/>p-value <lb/>Day 1 to 14 <lb/>Initial BW, kg <lb/>7.30 <lb/>7.31 <lb/>7.29 <lb/>7.27 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>1.000 <lb/>Final BW, kg <lb/>10.73 <lb/>11.27 <lb/>11.75 <lb/>11.87 <lb/>0.44 <lb/>0.503 <lb/>ADG, g/d <lb/>245 a <lb/>283 ab <lb/>319 b <lb/>328 b <lb/>20.72 <lb/>0.040 <lb/>ADFI, g/d <lb/>437 <lb/>429 <lb/>415 <lb/>429 <lb/>26.52 <lb/>0.994 <lb/>G:F, g/g <lb/>0.561 a <lb/>0.659 ab <lb/>0.768 b <lb/>0.766 b <lb/>0.042 <lb/>0.021 <lb/>Day 15 to 42 <lb/>Initial BW, kg <lb/>10.73 <lb/>11.27 <lb/>11.75 <lb/>11.87 <lb/>0.44 <lb/>0.503 <lb/>Final BW, kg <lb/>21.49 a <lb/>22.23 ab <lb/>22.85 b <lb/>22.98 b <lb/>0.31 <lb/>0.030 <lb/>ADG, g/d <lb/>384 <lb/>391 <lb/>396 <lb/>397 <lb/>13.02 <lb/>0.925 <lb/>ADFI, g/d <lb/>956 <lb/>951 <lb/>963 <lb/>965 <lb/>29.55 <lb/>0.999 <lb/>G:F, g/g <lb/>0.402 <lb/>0.412 <lb/>0.412 <lb/>0.411 <lb/>0.020 <lb/>0.993 <lb/>Day 1 to 42 <lb/>Initial BW, kg <lb/>7.30 <lb/>7.31 <lb/>7.29 <lb/>7.27 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>1.000 <lb/>Final BW, kg <lb/>21.49 a <lb/>22.23 ab <lb/>22.85 b <lb/>22.98 b <lb/>0.31 <lb/>0.030 <lb/>ADG, g/d <lb/>338 a <lb/>355 ab <lb/>371 b <lb/>374 b <lb/>7.28 <lb/>0.020 <lb/>ADFI, g/d <lb/>783 <lb/>777 <lb/>780 <lb/>786 <lb/>24.78 <lb/>0.999 <lb/>G:F, g/g <lb/>0.431 <lb/>0.457 <lb/>0.475 <lb/>0.476 <lb/>0.016 <lb/>0.419 <lb/>Frequency of diarrhea 3 , % <lb/>13.87 <lb/>9.28 <lb/>10.14 <lb/>9.92 <lb/>0.051 <lb/>1) Each value is the mean of 6 replicates (4 pigs/pen). <lb/>2) CON = basal weaner diet based on corn and soybean meal, T1 = CON + 2,500 ppm standard ZnO, T2 = CON <lb/>+ 100 mg/kg dietary coated CuSO 4 and 100 mg/kg dietary coated ZnO, T3 = CON + 200 mg/kg dietary coated <lb/>CuSO 4 and 200 mg/kg dietary coated ZnO, BW = body weight, ADG = average daily gain, ADFI = average daily <lb/>feed intake, G:F = gain to feed ratio. <lb/>3) Frequency of diarrhea for the first 2 weeks after weaning (%) = (number of diarrhea score of 4 or higher / number <lb/>of pen days) × 100. Data was analyzed using the Chi-square test. <lb/>a,b <lb/>Means in the same row with different superscripts are different (p &lt; 0.05) <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <body>Table 3. Effects of dietary coated CuSO 4 and ZnO on apparent total tract digestibility of weaned pigs 1) <lb/>Item 2) <lb/>CON <lb/>T1 <lb/>T2 <lb/>T3 <lb/>SEM <lb/>p-value <lb/>DM, % <lb/>70.68 <lb/>75.27 <lb/>80.17 <lb/>81.15 <lb/>5.67 <lb/>0.324 <lb/>Energy, % <lb/>75.34 <lb/>77.83 <lb/>79.74 <lb/>84.33 <lb/>5.21 <lb/>0.414 <lb/>CP, % <lb/>69.84 <lb/>73.33 <lb/>76.40 <lb/>82.59 <lb/>6.48 <lb/>0.542 <lb/>1) Each value is the mean of 6 replicates (1 pig/pen). <lb/>2) CON = basal weaner diet based on corn and soybean meal, T1 = CON + 2,500 ppm standard ZnO, T2 = CON <lb/>+ 100 mg/kg dietary coated CuSO 4 and 100 mg/kg dietary coated ZnO, T3 = CON + 200 mg/kg dietary coated <lb/>CuSO 4 and 200 mg/kg dietary coated ZnO, DM= dry matter, CP= crude protein. <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <body>Table 4. Effects of dietary coated CuSO 4 and ZnO on blood profiles and immune responses of weaned pigs 1) <lb/>Item 2) <lb/>CON <lb/>T1 <lb/>T2 <lb/>T3 <lb/>SEM <lb/>p-value <lb/>WBC, ×10 3 /µL <lb/>Day 1 <lb/>13.88 <lb/>13.56 <lb/>12.18 <lb/>14.88 <lb/>2.48 <lb/>0.474 <lb/>Day 7 <lb/>23.08 <lb/>19.76 <lb/>18.70 <lb/>20.42 <lb/>1.31 <lb/>0.074 <lb/>Day 14 <lb/>24.70 <lb/>23.32 <lb/>19.20 <lb/>19.14 <lb/>2.53 <lb/>0.459 <lb/>RBC, ×10 6 /µL <lb/>Day 1 <lb/>4.70 <lb/>4.94 <lb/>4.54 <lb/>4.65 <lb/>0.18 <lb/>0.355 <lb/>Day 7 <lb/>6.00 <lb/>6.33 <lb/>6.19 <lb/>6.10 <lb/>0.41 <lb/>0.984 <lb/>Day 14 <lb/>6.45 <lb/>6.50 <lb/>6.70 <lb/>6.74 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>0.325 <lb/>HCT, % <lb/>Day 1 <lb/>25.08 <lb/>26.02 <lb/>25.02 <lb/>24.92 <lb/>0.87 <lb/>0.885 <lb/>Day 7 <lb/>30.66 <lb/>29.74 <lb/>29.66 <lb/>29.54 <lb/>2.05 <lb/>0.985 <lb/>Day 14 <lb/>35.56 <lb/>30.30 <lb/>29.26 <lb/>29.56 <lb/>1.85 <lb/>0.084 <lb/>TNF-α, pg/mL <lb/>Day 1 <lb/>141.21 <lb/>131.53 <lb/>125.35 <lb/>121.35 <lb/>30.25 <lb/>0.506 <lb/>Day 7 <lb/>108.81 <lb/>78.57 <lb/>77.79 <lb/>78.97 <lb/>10.08 <lb/>0.095 <lb/>Day 14 <lb/>104.99 <lb/>84.44 <lb/>77.27 <lb/>81.43 <lb/>38.91 <lb/>0.550 <lb/>Cortisol, ng/mL <lb/>Day 1 <lb/>115.05 <lb/>118.74 <lb/>107.32 <lb/>105.83 <lb/>18.64 <lb/>0.691 <lb/>Day 7 <lb/>122.98 <lb/>81.18 <lb/>83.77 <lb/>90.17 <lb/>13.84 <lb/>0.063 <lb/>Day 14 <lb/>105.50 <lb/>98.64 <lb/>92.11 <lb/>94.88 <lb/>17.39 <lb/>0.330 <lb/>IgG, mg/mL <lb/>Day 1 <lb/>5.37 <lb/>4.86 <lb/>4.91 <lb/>5.24 <lb/>0.71 <lb/>0.721 <lb/>Day 7 <lb/>3.72 <lb/>3.84 <lb/>3.77 <lb/>3.94 <lb/>1.01 <lb/>0.650 <lb/>Day 14 <lb/>3.86 <lb/>4.55 <lb/>4.79 <lb/>4.75 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>0.076 <lb/>IgM, mg/mL <lb/>Day 1 <lb/>1.36 <lb/>1.57 <lb/>1.15 <lb/>1.43 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.413 <lb/>Day 7 <lb/>1.35 <lb/>1.37 <lb/>1.44 <lb/>1.56 <lb/>0.17 <lb/>0.361 <lb/>Day 14 <lb/>1.23 <lb/>1.62 <lb/>1.60 <lb/>1.51 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>0.067 <lb/>IgA, mg/mL <lb/>Day 1 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>0.36 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.385 <lb/>Day 7 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>0.857 <lb/>Day 14 <lb/>0.40 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>0.46 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>0.354 <lb/>1) Each value is the mean of 6 replicates (1 pig/pen). <lb/>2) CON = basal weaner diet based on corn and soybean meal, T1 = CON + 2,500 ppm standard ZnO, T2 = CON <lb/>+ 100 mg/kg dietary coated CuSO 4 and 100 mg/kg dietary coated ZnO, T3 = CON + 200 mg/kg dietary coated <lb/>CuSO 4 and 200 mg/kg dietary coated ZnO, WBC = white blood cell, RBC = red blood cell, HCT = hematocrit, <lb/>TNF-α = tumor necrosis factor-alpha, IgG = immunoglobulin G, IgM = immunoglobulin M, IgA = <lb/>immunoglobulin A. <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <body>Fig. 1. Effects of dietary coated CuSO4 and ZnO on alpha diversity of fecal microbiota of <lb/>weaned pigs (n = 3). Alpha diversity indices were (a) observed OTUs, (b) Chao1, (c) Shannon, <lb/>and (d) Simpson. Statistical difference was performed using the analysis of ANOVA. CON = <lb/>basal weaner diet based on corn and soybean meal, T1 = CON + 2,500 ppm standard ZnO, T2 <lb/>= CON + 100 mg/kg dietary coated CuSO4 and 100 mg/kg dietary coated ZnO, T3 = CON + <lb/>200 mg/kg dietary coated CuSO4 and 200 mg/kg dietary coated ZnO. <lb/>A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>Fig. 2. Effects of dietary coated CuSO4 and ZnO on beta diversity of fecal microbiota of <lb/>weaned pigs (n = 3). Principal coordinated analysis based on (a) unweighted and (b) weighted <lb/>Unifrac distances. The ANOSIM test was used for statistically significant distances. T1 = CON <lb/>+ 2,500 ppm standard ZnO, T2 = CON + 100 mg/kg dietary coated CuSO4 and 100 mg/kg <lb/>dietary coated ZnO, T3 = CON + 200 mg/kg dietary coated CuSO4 and 200 mg/kg dietary <lb/>coated ZnO. <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <body>Fig. 3. Effects of dietary coated CuSO4 and ZnO on relative taxonomic abundance at the <lb/>phylum level of fecal microbiota of weaned pigs (n = 3). CON = basal weaner diet based on <lb/>corn and soybean meal, T1 = CON + 2,500 ppm standard ZnO, T2 = CON + 100 mg/kg dietary <lb/>coated CuSO4 and 100 mg/kg dietary coated ZnO, T3 = CON + 200 mg/kg dietary coated <lb/>CuSO4 and 200 mg/kg dietary coated ZnO. <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>CON <lb/>T1 <lb/>T2 <lb/>T3 <lb/>Relative abundance, % <lb/>Unclassified <lb/>Others <lb/>Proteobacteria <lb/>Actinobacteria <lb/>Bacteriodetes <lb/>Firmicutes <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <body>(a) <lb/>484 <lb/>485 <lb/>(b) <lb/>486 <lb/>CON <lb/>T1 <lb/>T2 <lb/>T3 <lb/>Relative abundance, % <lb/>Others <lb/>Mediterraneibacter <lb/>Agathobacter <lb/>Chlamydia <lb/>Roseburia <lb/>Blautia <lb/>Terrisporobacter <lb/>Eubacterium <lb/>Treponema <lb/>Prevotella <lb/>Collinsella <lb/>Clostridiumsensustricto <lb/>Limosilactobacillus <lb/>Dysosmobacter <lb/>Lactobacillus <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <page>487 <lb/></page>

        <page>488 <lb/></page>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D <lb/>

        <body>Fig. 4. Effects of dietary coated CuSO4 and ZnO on relative taxonomic abundance at the genus <lb/>level (a) and relative abundances of Agathobacter, Terrisporobacter, and Limosilactobacilus <lb/>(b) of fecal microbiota of weaned pigs (n = 3). CON = basal weaner diet based on corn and <lb/>soybean meal, T1 = CON + 2,500 ppm standard ZnO, T2 = CON + 100 mg/kg dietary coated <lb/>CuSO4 and 100 mg/kg dietary coated ZnO, T3 = CON + 200 mg/kg dietary coated CuSO4 and <lb/>200 mg/kg of dietary coated ZnO. <lb/></body>

        A C <lb/>C <lb/>E P T E D


	</text>

</TEI>