<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Tropospheric links to uncertainty in stratospheric subseasonal  predictions</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Rachel W.-Y.</forename>
          <surname>Wu</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Gabriel</forename>
          <surname>Chiodo</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Inna</forename>
          <surname>Polichtchouk</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Daniela I. V.</forename>
          <surname>Domeisen</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-05T14:56:29.643Z">11/5/2025 2:56:29 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Copernicus GmbH</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.5194/acp-24-12259-2024</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Rachel W.-Y. Wu, Gabriel Chiodo, Inna Polichtchouk, Daniela I. V. Domeisen. (2024). Tropospheric links to uncertainty in stratospheric subseasonal  predictions. Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics, 24(21), 12259-12275. DOI: 10.5194/acp-24-12259-2024</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-05T14:56:17.346227Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-05T14:56:17.346227Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2465-2481, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2465-2024 <lb/>© Author(s) 2024. This work is distributed under <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License. <lb/>National forest carbon harvesting and allocation dataset <lb/>for the period 2003 to 2018 <lb/>Daju Wang 1 , Peiyang Ren 1 , Xiaosheng Xia 1 , Lei Fan 2 , Zhangcai Qin 1 , Xiuzhi Chen 1 , and <lb/>Wenping Yuan 3 <lb/>1 School of Atmospheric Sciences, Guangdong Province Data Center of Terrestrial and Marine Ecosystems <lb/>Carbon Cycle, Sun Yat-sen University, Zhuhai, Guangdong 510245, China <lb/>2 Chongqing Jinfo Mountain Karst Ecosystem National Observation and Research Station, <lb/>School of Geographical Sciences, Southwest University, Chongqing 400715, China <lb/>3 Institute of Carbon Neutrality, Sino-French Institute for Earth System Science, College of Urban and <lb/>Environmental Sciences, Peking University, Beijing 100091, China <lb/>Correspondence: Wenping Yuan (yuanwp3@mail.sysu.edu.cn) <lb/>Received: 31 July 2023 -Discussion started: 24 August 2023 <lb/>Revised: 5 April 2024 -Accepted: 9 April 2024 -Published: 24 May 2024 <lb/>Abstract. Forest harvesting is one of the anthropogenic activities that most significantly affect the carbon bud-<lb/>get of forests. However, the absence of explicit spatial information on harvested carbon poses a huge challenge <lb/>in assessing forest-harvesting impacts, as well as the forest carbon budget. This study utilized provincial-level <lb/>statistical data on wood harvest, the tree cover loss (TCL) dataset, and a satellite-based vegetation index to <lb/>develop a Long-term harvEst and Allocation of Forest Biomass (LEAF) dataset. The aim was to provide the <lb/>spatial location of forest harvesting with a spatial resolution of 30 m and to quantify the post-harvest car-<lb/>bon dynamics. The validations against the surveyed forest harvesting in 133 cities and counties indicated a <lb/>good performance of the LEAF dataset in capturing the spatial variation of harvested carbon, with a coeffi-<lb/>cient of determination (R 2 ) of 0.83 between the identified and surveyed harvested carbon. The linear regression <lb/>slope was up to 0.99. Averaged from 2003 to 2018, forest harvesting removed 68.3 ± 9.3 Mt C yr -1 , of which <lb/>more than 80 % was from selective logging. Of the harvested carbon, 19.6 ± 4.0 %, 2.1 ± 1.1 %, 35.5 ± 12.6 % <lb/>6.2 ± 0.3 %, 17.5 ± 0.9 %, and 19.1 ± 9.8 % entered the fuelwood, paper and paperboard, wood-based panels, <lb/>solid wooden furniture, structural constructions, and residue pools, respectively. Direct combustion of fuelwood <lb/>was the primary source of carbon emissions after wood harvest. However, carbon can be stored in wood prod-<lb/>ucts for a long time, and by 2100, almost 40 % of the carbon harvested during the study period will still be <lb/>retained. This dataset is expected to provide a foundation and reference for estimating the forestry and na-<lb/>tional carbon budgets. The 30 m × 30 m harvested-carbon dataset from forests in China can be downloaded at <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.23641164.v2 (Wang et al., 2023). <lb/></front>

        <body>1 Introduction <lb/>As a critical terrestrial ecosystem type, forests play a pivotal <lb/>role in regulating the global carbon cycle (Dixon et al., 1994). <lb/>Over the period 2001 to 2019, global forests sequestrated <lb/>2.07 Gt C yr -1 from the atmosphere (Harris et al., 2021), <lb/>contributing more than 70 % of the global terrestrial carbon <lb/>sinks (Friedlingstein et al., 2022). Forests also provide nu-<lb/>merous important ecosystem services to society (Costanza et <lb/>al., 1997), which may substantially impact the forests car-<lb/>bon sink (Lal et al., 2013). One of the most important ser-<lb/>vices is the provision of wood products (Deal and White, <lb/>2012), which results in the transference of carbon from for-<lb/>est ecosystems into the social system. The carbon harvested <lb/>from forests is typically transferred into the pools of har-<lb/>vested wood products (HWPs) (the full names and abbrevi-<lb/>ations of terminologies are listed in Table S1 in the Supple-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Published by Copernicus Publications. <lb/></note>

        <page>2466 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">D. Wang et al.: National forest carbon harvesting and allocation dataset <lb/></note>

        <body>ment) through the usage of wood for constructions, furniture, <lb/>and fine papers, among others. These products are eventually <lb/>decomposed and emitted into the atmosphere with different <lb/>turnover times (IPCC, 2014, 2019a). For example, when har-<lb/>vested wood is used to make paper, the carbon within the pa-<lb/>per decomposes and returns to the atmosphere within several <lb/>years (Brunet-Navarro et al., 2017). On the contrary, the har-<lb/>vested carbon entering the wood used for constructions has a <lb/>slow turnover rate and can be stored for many years (Brunet-<lb/>Navarro et al., 2017). Previous studies have highlighted the <lb/>large uncertainties in estimating carbon emissions of wood <lb/>post-harvest due to a lack of information about the proportion <lb/>of wood entering various wood pools (Skog et al., 2004). <lb/>In China, forests are playing an increasingly important <lb/>role in terrestrial carbon sinks benefiting from long-term af-<lb/>forestation projects (Liu et al., 2014). A recent study based <lb/>on satellite data revealed that China is one of the few coun-<lb/>tries that has experienced persistent greening over the past <lb/>decades (Chen et al., 2019; Yuan et al., 2019). Unlike India, <lb/>where croplands dominate greening, nearly half of China&apos;s <lb/>greening comes from forests (Chen et al., 2019). However, <lb/>despite these positive trends, China ranks as the second-<lb/>largest timber consumer and the largest wood importer glob-<lb/>ally (Research and Market, 2019). In 2017, the consumption <lb/>of wood in China reached 1.925 × 10 8 m 3 , with 43.6 % of <lb/>that consumption being supplied by domestic harvests (Re-<lb/>search and Market, 2019). A previous study has highlighted <lb/>that harvesting is the primary cause of forest disturbance in <lb/>China, accounting for 85 % of the average annual forest loss <lb/>(Curtis et al., 2018). However, the impacts of forest harvest-<lb/>ing on the terrestrial carbon cycle have not been estimated yet <lb/>due to a lack of available data on harvested carbon. Accurate <lb/>forest-harvesting data are crucial for measuring the national <lb/>carbon sink-source balance, an important component of na-<lb/>tional carbon budget analysis related to forest resources and <lb/>wood utilization (Winjum, et al., 1998). <lb/>Although some efforts have been made, there are still large <lb/>uncertainties in estimating harvested carbon in forest ecosys-<lb/>tems (Hurtt et al., 2011, 2020). For example, the Land-Use <lb/>Harmonization 2 (LUH2) dataset provides annual harvested <lb/>biomass carbon data from primary and secondary forests <lb/>(Hurtt et al., 2011, 2020). However, the spatial resolution <lb/>of the LUH2 dataset (0.25°× 0.25°) is too coarse to analyze <lb/>the dynamics of forest ecosystems at the regional or local <lb/>scales, and its performance in assessing carbon harvest has <lb/>not been examined in China. In addition, to our knowledge, <lb/>no studies have been conducted to quantify the proportion <lb/>of harvested wood or carbon entering various wood pools, <lb/>which is crucial for estimating carbon emissions returning to <lb/>the atmosphere (Skog et al., 2004; Johnston and Radeloff, <lb/>2019). Over the past decades, constructions, paper-making, <lb/>and furniture manufacturing have shown substantial changes <lb/>in China (Zhang et al., 2019; FAO, 2020), largely influenc-<lb/>ing the proportion of harvested carbon among various wood <lb/>pools and the magnitude of emissions. <lb/>In this study, we developed the Long-term harvEst and Al-<lb/>location of Forest Biomass (LEAF) dataset to provide (1) the <lb/>spatial location of harvested carbon with a high resolution of <lb/>30 m, (2) the proportion of harvested carbon allocated into <lb/>various wood pools, and (3) the lagged carbon emissions <lb/>of harvested carbon from the aforementioned wood pools. <lb/>The tree cover loss (TCL) dataset developed by Hansen et <lb/>al. (2013) and the interannual variation of a satellite-based <lb/>vegetation index were used to determine the location of har-<lb/>vested carbon, and the provincial statistical biomass stor-<lb/>age provided by the China Forestry and Grassland Statis-<lb/>tical Yearbook was used to quantify the magnitude of har-<lb/>vested carbon. Post-harvest carbon dynamics were estimated <lb/>based on a first-order decay (FOD) function according to the <lb/>post-harvest wood use provided by the statistical data (IPCC, <lb/>2014, 2019a). <lb/>2 Methods and materials <lb/>This study aimed to generate the LEAF dataset, which is a <lb/>component of the Terrestrial Ecosystem Disturbance (TED) <lb/>dataset, referred to as TED-LEAF. The LEAF dataset in-<lb/>cludes the location and magnitude of forest harvesting and <lb/>the estimates of post-harvest carbon dynamics. The iden-<lb/>tification of forest harvesting was based on the detection <lb/>of changes in multi-temporal vegetation indices. Combined <lb/>with statistical harvest data, the forest harvesting and other <lb/>disturbances causing such changes could be separated. Uti-<lb/>lizing the classification of HWPs provided by statistical data, <lb/>we estimated the delayed carbon emissions up to 2100 from <lb/>HWPs based on IPCC methodologies with China-specific ac-<lb/>tivity data. <lb/>2.1 Method of calculating harvested carbon <lb/>We aimed to identify two types of forest harvesting: clear-<lb/>cutting and selective logging (Fig. 1). In this study, clear-<lb/>cutting is the harvesting of an entire stand at once on a scale <lb/>of 30 m × 30 m, while selective logging is the harvesting of <lb/>a portion of the stand within that area that is suitable and <lb/>should be harvested. <lb/>For clear-cutting, the location was determined using the <lb/>TCL dataset produced by Hansen et al. (2013). The TCL <lb/>dataset indicates stand replacement disturbance or the com-<lb/>plete removal of tree cover canopy at a scale of 30 m × 30 m. <lb/>It has been widely used to identify deforestation globally <lb/>or in multiple regions (Hansen et al., 2013; Curtis et al., <lb/>2018). To calculate the harvested carbon from clear-cutting, <lb/>it was necessary to determine the aboveground biomass car-<lb/>bon (AGB, t C) storage for each pixel. Only the ninth Na-<lb/>tional Forest Inventory (NFI) provided both provincial forest <lb/>AGB density (CD, t C ha -1 ) and forest area (S, ha). Then, we <lb/>calculated pixel-level (30 m × 30 m) AGB storage for 2014 to <lb/>2018 as follows: <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2465-2481, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2465-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">D. Wang et al.: National forest carbon harvesting and allocation dataset <lb/></note>

        <page>2467 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 1. Flowchart for mapping forest carbon harvesting. <lb/>AGB j = CD × S × <lb/>NDVI j <lb/>SNDVI <lb/>, <lb/>(1) <lb/>where AGB j indicates the AGB of the j th forest pixel in <lb/>a given province and year, NDVI j denotes the normalized <lb/>difference vegetation index (NDVI) of the j th forest pixel <lb/>in that province for that year, and SNDVI is the sum of the <lb/>NDVI of all forest pixels in that province for that year. Ac-<lb/>cording to the province-level biomass storage (V , m 3 ) pro-<lb/>vided by the sixth to eighth NFIs covering 1998 to 2013 <lb/>at 5-year intervals, this study used the following method to <lb/>calculate pixel-level (30 m × 30 m) AGB storage for 2003 to <lb/>2013: <lb/>AGB j = V × <lb/>NDVI j <lb/>SNDVI <lb/>× Coef, <lb/>(2) <lb/>where Coef (t C m -3 ) is the coefficient that converts biomass <lb/>storage (V ) to biomass carbon (AGB). Combining the <lb/>provincial forest biomass storage (V 9 , m 3 ) from the ninth <lb/>NFI, we calculated the provincial Coef (Table S2) as follows: <lb/>Coef = <lb/>CD × S <lb/>V 9 <lb/>. <lb/>(3) <lb/>Then, the harvested carbon was calculated for all pixels cor-<lb/>responding to clear-cutting derived from the TCL dataset. <lb/>The total harvested carbon from clear-cutting (HC C , t C) in <lb/>a given province can be calculated by aggregating all pixels <lb/>occurring tree cover loss. <lb/>For selective logging, we developed a satellite-based <lb/>method to identify the location and magnitude of selec-<lb/>tive logging. The method was based on the principle of <lb/>multitemporal satellite-based vegetation index analysis and <lb/>detected the changes of NDVI between 2 adjacent years. <lb/>This approach relied on two fundamental assumptions. First, <lb/>we assumed that NDVI values decreased as a result of se-<lb/>lective logging. Therefore, we calculated the NDVI dif-<lb/>ference (NDVI diff ) between the current year (NDVI t ) and <lb/>the subsequent year (NDVI t+1 ) for all pixels (Eq. 4) and <lb/>determined the possible logging locations with decreased <lb/>NDVI diff , where NDVI diff &lt; 0 indicated potential selective <lb/>logging. <lb/>NDVI diff = NDVI t+1 -NDVI t <lb/>(4) <lb/>Second, we assumed that the reductions in NDVI values <lb/>resulting from selective logging would be more significant <lb/>compared to the decreases caused by other factors such as <lb/>droughts, heatwaves, ice storms, and insect outbreaks (Yuan <lb/>et al., 2014); note that we did not consider fires due to their <lb/>low frequency in China (Curtis et al., 2018). Changes in veg-<lb/>etation coverage caused by logging activities were expected <lb/>to have a drastic and rapid impact on ecosystems compared <lb/>to other environmental changes and disturbances. Therefore, <lb/>the decreased magnitude of NDVI values due to selective <lb/>logging was assumed to be the largest. Based on this assump-<lb/>tion, we can identify selective-logging areas by focusing on <lb/>pixels exhibiting larger NDVI diff . For a specific province, all <lb/>pixels with negative NDVI diff values were sorted by ascend-<lb/>ing order in NDVI diff . The pixels at the front of the sorted list <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2465-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2465-2481, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2468 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">D. Wang et al.: National forest carbon harvesting and allocation dataset <lb/></note>

        <body>had more negative NDVI diff values and a larger likelihood <lb/>of being logging locations. Thereby, a threshold of NDVI diff <lb/>(NDVI Th ) was needed to distinguish selective logging from <lb/>other disturbed pixels. Selective logging was considered to <lb/>have occurred only when NDVI diff &lt; NDVI Th . Then, the har-<lb/>vested carbon (HC S , tC) was calculated in all pixels corre-<lb/>sponding to selective logging according to Eq. (5): <lb/>HC S j = <lb/>NDVI diff j <lb/>NDVI j <lb/>× AGB j . <lb/>(5) <lb/>Therefore, the province-level statistical harvested carbon <lb/>(SHC) was used to determine the NDVI Th of each province, <lb/>which made the sum of HC C and HC S equal to SHC. The-<lb/>oretically, the determined NDVI Th should be less than 0. <lb/>However, in several provinces, when NDVI Th was set to 0, <lb/>the sum of HC C and HC S (identified harvested carbon) was <lb/>still lower than SHC (e.g., Anhui), implying that the identi-<lb/>fied harvested carbon was underestimated. Then we assigned <lb/>the unidentified harvested carbon (SHC-HC C -HC S ) to pix-<lb/>els where selective logging occurred: <lb/>HC S1 j = (SHC -HC C -HC S ) × <lb/>NDVI diff j <lb/>SNDVI diff <lb/>, <lb/>(6) <lb/>where HC S1 j is the harvested carbon added by the j th pixel <lb/>where selective logging occurred, NDVI diff j indicates the <lb/>NDVI diff of the j th pixel, and SNDVI diff is the sum of the <lb/>NDVI diff of all pixels where selective logging occurred in <lb/>that province. This approach increased the harvested carbon <lb/>for all pixels where selective logging occurred; thus, we also <lb/>examined whether the harvested carbon exceeded their AGB <lb/>at the pixel scale. If so, we counted these pixels as clear-<lb/>cutting. To assess the accuracy and validity of the dataset, <lb/>we additionally quantified the proportion of pixels with har-<lb/>vested carbon exceeding their AGB compared to the total <lb/>number of harvested pixels at the province level. <lb/>In addition, this study assumed that forest harvesting did <lb/>not occur in the national nature reserves and high-altitude <lb/>regions because of high transport costs and harvesting ex-<lb/>penses. For the Tibetan Plateau and Yunnan Province, we as-<lb/>sumed no harvesting at elevations higher than 2500 m. In the <lb/>other provinces, harvesting was assumed to be absent at el-<lb/>evations higher than 1500 m, in accordance with Nabuurs et <lb/>al. (2019). <lb/>2.2 Annual carbon changes from in-use and end-use <lb/>HWPs <lb/>The harvested wood was allocated into six wood pools <lb/>(Fig. 2): (1) fuelwood pool, which is the sum of commer-<lb/>cial fuelwood and non-commercial fuelwood (i.e., farmers&apos; <lb/>fuelwood), where the wood is burned as fuel, resulting in im-<lb/>mediate carbon emissions through combustion; (2) paper and <lb/>paperboard pool, including household paper, printing paper, <lb/>packaging paper, etc.; (3) wood-based panel pool, including <lb/>plywood, fiberboard, particle board, and other wood-based <lb/>panels made from roundwood, wood residues (such as bark, <lb/>branches, sawdust), or small stems bonded with adhesives <lb/>-these are commonly used as decorative panels for various <lb/>applications like wall cladding and ceiling finishes; (4) solid <lb/>wooden furniture pool, referring to solid wooden household <lb/>items such as tables, chairs, wooden beds, etc.; (5) struc-<lb/>tural constructions pool, referring to the structural compo-<lb/>nents used to support buildings, such as beams, columns, <lb/>and trusses; and (6) residue pool, including leaves, killed un-<lb/>derstory vegetation, and unutilized wood residues, which are <lb/>typically left on the logging site or are treated as fuel (Lippke <lb/>et al., 2011; Stockmann et al., 2012) and which were assumed <lb/>to be fuel in this study. The wood pools of (2), (3), (4), and <lb/>(5) belong to the HWP pool, where the carbon will remain <lb/>stored until the products are retired from use or reach the <lb/>end of their service life (Table S3) and are consequently dis-<lb/>carded. Subsequently, these discarded products are then sent <lb/>directly to landfills, where they decompose (Stockmann et <lb/>al., 2012; IPCC, 2019a). <lb/>In this study, the volume (m 3 ) of fuelwood, pulpwood <lb/>(wood for paper and paperboard), and wood-based panels <lb/>and the sum volume (m 3 ) of wood for solid wooden fur-<lb/>niture and structural constructions can be obtained directly <lb/>from the China Forestry Statistical Yearbook. The structural <lb/>constructions and solid wooden furniture pools were allo-<lb/>cated as the percentages of 74.6 ± 6.2 % and 25.4 ± 6.2 % of <lb/>their sum, respectively, according to the China Timber and <lb/>Wood Products Distribution Industry Yearbook. The wood <lb/>in pools (1) to (5) was converted into carbon, with a conver-<lb/>sion factor of 0.229 for fuelwood and roundwood and 0.269 <lb/>for wood-based panels. Then, the carbon entering the residue <lb/>pool (Residue C ) can be calculated by subtracting the carbon <lb/>in pools (1) to (5) from the total harvested carbon (SHC in <lb/>Eq. (21) of Sect. 2.3.2), as in Eq. (7): <lb/>Residue C = SHC -W output + F log <lb/>× 0.229 -wood_based panels × 0.269, <lb/>(7) <lb/>where SHC (Eq. (21) is the total harvested carbon for a given <lb/>province, W output represents the volume of commercial wood <lb/>output, and F log represents the volume of non-commercial <lb/>wood. Unlike commercial wood, the actual logging volume <lb/>of non-commercial wood can be used effectively by farmers <lb/>(Sect. 2.3.2). The sum of W output and F log is the total vol-<lb/>ume of pools (1) to (4), and, here, wood-based panels do not <lb/>include plywood (Fig. 2). <lb/>2.2.1 Annual carbon changes in in-use HWPs <lb/>Carbon stocks and decays from in-use HWPs were calcu-<lb/>lated using the methodologies for estimating carbon removal <lb/>from HWPs described in the 2006 IPCC Guidelines for Na-<lb/>tional Greenhouse Gas Inventories (IPCC, 2006a) and the <lb/>2013 Revised Supplementary Methods and Good Practice <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2465-2481, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2465-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">D. Wang et al.: National forest carbon harvesting and allocation dataset <lb/></note>

        <page>2469 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 2. The allocation of post-harvest wood to the six wood pools. The green boxes indicate the variables that are available from the China <lb/>Forestry and Grassland Statistics Yearbook. R is wood output rate of commercial wood, and Coef (t C m -3 ) is the coefficient that converts <lb/>harvested wood (m 3 ) to harvested carbon (t C) (i.e., biomass carbon of trunks, branches, leaves, and understory vegetation). <lb/>Guidance Arising from the Kyoto Protocol (IPCC, 2014). <lb/>&quot;Decay&quot; in this paper refers to the discarding of HWPs from <lb/>end uses (sent to landfills) and not biological decay. More-<lb/>over, here, we focused on the carbon fate of wood harvested <lb/>in China; the imports and exports were not considered. The <lb/>FOD method (Pingoud and Wagner, 2006) was used to esti-<lb/>mate the carbon change in the HWPs pool as follows: <lb/>C (i + 1) = e -k <lb/>× C (i) + <lb/>1 -e -k <lb/>k <lb/>× Inflow(i), <lb/>(8) <lb/>C (i) = C (i + 1) -C(i), <lb/>(9) <lb/>where i denotes the year, C(i) is the carbon stock in the HWP <lb/>pool at the beginning of year i, and k (k = ln(2)/HL) is the <lb/>decay constant (yr -1 ). HL is the number of years it takes to <lb/>lose half of the existing material in the pool, which is a func-<lb/>tion of the country-specific service life of particular HWPs <lb/>(HL = service life × ln(2)) (IPCC, 2019b); k values for pa-<lb/>per and paperboard, wood-based panels, solid wooden furni-<lb/>ture, and structural constructions were calculated to be 0.333, <lb/>0.125, 0.067, and 0.025, respectively. Inflow(i) is the inflow <lb/>to the HWP pool during year i, and C(i) represents the car-<lb/>bon stock change of the HWP pool during year i. Next, the <lb/>amount of discarded organic carbon (DOC) deposited in the <lb/>landfills as the HWPs go out of use in year i was calculated <lb/>using Eq. (10): <lb/>DOC i = Inflow(i) -C i . <lb/>(10) <lb/>2.2.2 Annual carbon changes in landfills <lb/>The DOC deposited in landfills was divided into three parts: <lb/>(1) DOC for aerobic decomposition (DOC ar ), producing CO 2 <lb/>until all available oxygen has been used up; (2) DOC for <lb/>anaerobic decomposition (DOC an ), producing both CH 4 and <lb/>CO 2 ; (3) DOC that will not be decomposed but stored long-<lb/>term in the landfill (DOC ls ). <lb/>The DOC ar was calculated as follows: <lb/>DOC ar i = DOC i × f ar , <lb/>(11) <lb/>where f ar denotes the proportion of DOC undergoing aerobic <lb/>decomposition. Based on the landfill situation in China, the <lb/>f ar was assumed to be 0.28 ± 0.15 (Table S4). The DOC ar i <lb/>undergoes aerobic decomposition and is released as CO 2 in <lb/>year i: <lb/>CO 2 ar i = DOC ar i × <lb/>44 <lb/>12 <lb/>. <lb/>(12) <lb/>The DOC an is calculated with Eq. (13) as follows: <lb/>DOC an i = DOC i × (1 -f ar ) × DOC f , <lb/>(13) <lb/>where DOC f indicates the fraction of DOC that can be de-<lb/>composed under anaerobic conditions (Table S5). The an-<lb/>nual carbon change in DOC an in the landfill was calculated <lb/>according to the FOD method (Pingoud and Wagner, 2006): <lb/>DOC an a i = DOC an i + DOC an a i-1 × e -k , <lb/>(14) <lb/>DOC an decomp i = DOC an a i-1 × (1 -e -k ), <lb/>(15) <lb/>where DOC an a i represents the DOC an accumulated in the <lb/>landfill at the end of year i, and DOC an decomp i denotes <lb/>DOC an decomposed in the landfill in year i. The anaerobic <lb/>decomposition generally occurs in the following year of de-<lb/>position. Furthermore, k is the decay constant (yr -1 ), esti-<lb/>mated based on the environmental conditions of landfill in <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2465-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2465-2481, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2470 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">D. Wang et al.: National forest carbon harvesting and allocation dataset <lb/></note>

        <body>China (Table S5). Then, the potentials to generate CH 4 and <lb/>CO 2 from the anaerobic decomposition of DOC an were cal-<lb/>culated as follows: <lb/>CH 4 i = DOC an decomp i × F × <lb/>16 <lb/>12 <lb/>× (1 -R T ) <lb/>× (1 -OX T ), <lb/>(16) <lb/>CO 2 an i = DOC an decomp i × (1 -F ) × <lb/>44 <lb/>12 <lb/>, <lb/>(17) <lb/>where CH 4 i and CO 2 an i are CH 4 and CO 2 produced by <lb/>anaerobic decomposition in landfills in year i. F denotes the <lb/>volume fraction of CH 4 in the generated landfill gas, with a <lb/>value of 0.5 ± 0.1 (Cai et al., 2018). R T and OX T are the re-<lb/>covery rate and oxidation rate of CH 4 in China (Table S4). <lb/>The total CO 2 decomposed from DOC in year i was the sum <lb/>of CO 2 ar i and CO 2 an i . The CH 4 emissions were transformed <lb/>to CO 2 equivalents (CO 2 e) to harmonize calculations of the <lb/>overall global warming potential (IPCC, 2023). <lb/>The DOC ls can be calculated as follows: <lb/>DOC ls i = DOC i -DOC ar i -DOC an i . <lb/>(18) <lb/>Then, the carbon stock in the landfill at the end of year i was <lb/>calculated as follows: <lb/>DOC s i = <lb/>i <lb/>0 DOC ls i + DOC an a i . <lb/>(19) <lb/>2.3 Datasets <lb/>2.3.1 National Forest Inventories <lb/>The NFIs provided nine periods of provincial biomass stor-<lb/>age for 1973-1976, 1977-1981, 1984-1988, 1989-1993, <lb/>1994-1998, 1999-2003, 2004-2008, 2009-2013, and 2014-<lb/>2018 (National Forestry and Grassland Administration, <lb/>2019). We used the biomass storage data during the sixth-<lb/>ninth NFIs to generate the distribution of AGB for 2003-<lb/>2018. <lb/>2.3.2 Statistical forest-harvesting data <lb/>The annual provincial wood output (m 3 ), extracted from <lb/>the China Forestry and Grassland Statistical Yearbook, was <lb/>categorized into two main types: commercial and non-<lb/>commercial wood. Commercial wood includes fuelwood and <lb/>roundwood, and roundwood was further divided into pulp-<lb/>wood, wood for plywood, and other roundwood (roundwood <lb/>for direct use, internally processed roundwood, etc.). Non-<lb/>commercial wood included farmers&apos; fuelwood (i.e., the vol-<lb/>ume of wood logged by farmers for burning) and farmers&apos; <lb/>self-use wood (i.e., the volume of wood logged by farm-<lb/>ers for their personal consumption). Non-commercial wood <lb/>refers to the actual logged volume, which can be totally used <lb/>by farmers. Commercial wood refers to the wood output vol-<lb/>ume of peeled wood that meets the national wood standards <lb/>and not the actual logging volume. After wood logging, pre-<lb/>liminary processing (such as peeling, sawing, etc.) is carried <lb/>out, and some unusable or poor-quality wood is eliminated. <lb/>Therefore, the commercial wood output is generally less than <lb/>the actual logged wood (National Forestry Administration, <lb/>2000). Based on the provincial wood output rate (R, i.e., the <lb/>ratio of commercial wood output to wood logged) provided <lb/>by China&apos;s timber production plan from the National Bureau <lb/>of Statistics (Table S2), we calculated the actual annual wood <lb/>logged for each province as follows: <lb/>W log = <lb/>W output <lb/>R <lb/>, <lb/>(20) <lb/>where W log is the actual annual wood logged for producing <lb/>commercial wood, and W output is the volume of commercial <lb/>wood output. Then, the total harvested carbon (i.e., the SHC <lb/>in Sect. 2.1) for a given province was calculated as follows: <lb/>SHC = W log + F log × Coef, <lb/>(21) <lb/>where F log is the volume of non-commercial wood, and Coef <lb/>(t C m -3 ) is the coefficient that converts harvested wood (m 3 ) <lb/>to harvested carbon (t C) (i.e., biomass carbon of trunks, <lb/>branches, leaves, and understory vegetation) (Table S2). <lb/>2.3.3 Surveyed forest-harvesting data <lb/>The surveyed forest-harvesting data, i.e., the harvested vol-<lb/>ume at the city and county level, were retrieved from the <lb/>official website of each provincial Forestry Bureau. To en-<lb/>sure the effective implementation of the forest-harvesting <lb/>quota system, the provincial Forestry Bureau randomly se-<lb/>lects several cities and/or counties, conducting comprehen-<lb/>sive field inspections of the annual forest harvesting. The <lb/>actual annual harvest volume of a specific city or county is <lb/>determined through comprehensive cross-validation of mul-<lb/>tiple methods, including declaration and approval record re-<lb/>viewing, on-site measurements, remote sensing monitoring, <lb/>etc. These techniques are employed to ensure the accuracy <lb/>and reliability of the obtained harvest data. There were 133 <lb/>records nationwide, available from 2006 to 2018, concen-<lb/>trated in the provinces of Guizhou, Yunnan, Zhejiang, and <lb/>Sichuan (Fig. S1 in the Supplement). <lb/>2.3.4 Forest cover map <lb/>The Chinese Forest Cover Dataset, reconstructed by fusing <lb/>the NFIs and 20 land use and land cover datasets, was used <lb/>as the forest cover base map. This forest cover accurately <lb/>depicts the historical changes in China&apos;s forest cover in the <lb/>period of 1980-2015, with overall accuracy from 76.9 % to <lb/>99.4 % (Xia et al., 2023). <lb/>2.3.5 Satellite-based vegetation index <lb/>The NDVI dataset from 2000 to 2020 calculated by Dong <lb/>et al. (2021) was applied to allocate AGB and identify se-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2465-2481, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2465-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">D. Wang et al.: National forest carbon harvesting and allocation dataset <lb/></note>

        <page>2471 <lb/></page>

        <body>lective logging. This NDVI dataset was calculated using all <lb/>Landsat 5,7, and 8 remote sensing data for the whole year; <lb/>the NDVI maxima in each image year were obtained by data <lb/>pre-processing and data smoothing (Dong et al., 2021). <lb/>2.3.6 Mask data <lb/>This study used the elevation and national nature reserves <lb/>to exclude the regions where harvesting rarely occurs. The <lb/>elevation dataset was obtained from the Resource and Envi-<lb/>ronment Science and Data Center of the Chinese Academy of <lb/>Sciences (https://www.resdc.cn/, last access: 1 August 2022), <lb/>and the distribution of national nature reserves was provided <lb/>by the National Earth System Science Data Center of the <lb/>National Science and Technology Infrastructure of China <lb/>(http://www.geodata.cn, last access: 1 August 2022). <lb/>2.4 Accuracy assessment <lb/>The surveyed forest-harvesting data at the city and county <lb/>level were employed to validate the accuracy of the LEAF <lb/>dataset by conducting a comparison with the estimated har-<lb/>vested carbon. The relationships between the estimated har-<lb/>vested carbon and the corresponding surveyed harvested car-<lb/>bon were assessed by linear regression. Following this, the <lb/>coefficient of determination (R 2 ) and the slope of linear re-<lb/>gression can be calculated, and the closer these two values <lb/>are to 1, the better the estimates are. <lb/>3 Results <lb/>3.1 Accuracy evaluation of the LEAF dataset <lb/>Accuracy evaluation of the LEAF dataset generated from this <lb/>study showed good performance in indicating spatial varia-<lb/>tions of harvested carbon in China. This study used province-<lb/>level statistical harvested carbon to determine the threshold <lb/>for identifying selective logging and used city-and county-<lb/>level surveyed harvested carbon ranging from 2006 to 2018 <lb/>to examine the performance. The estimated harvested car-<lb/>bon showed high consistency with surveyed harvested car-<lb/>bon, with R 2 of 0.83 and a linear regression slope of 0.99 <lb/>(Fig. 3). <lb/>The validation also showed the performance of the LEAF <lb/>dataset across various provinces and periods. The dataset <lb/>exhibited excellent skill in simulating the spatial variation <lb/>of harvested carbon across all surveyed provinces, with R 2 <lb/>between estimates and surveyed data ranging from 0.24 to <lb/>0.96 (Fig. S2). Zhejiang performed the best (Fig. S2e), while <lb/>Sichuan&apos;s performance was relatively low, with R 2 less than <lb/>0.5 (Fig. S2c). The LEAF dataset also effectively reproduced <lb/>the spatial variations of harvested carbon across different pe-<lb/>riods, with R 2 values ranging from 0.31 to 0.99 (Fig. S3). <lb/>The estimates for 2013 and 2017 demonstrated superior per-<lb/>formance, with both linear regression slopes approximating <lb/>Figure 3. Comparison of estimated and surveyed harvested carbon <lb/>from the official website of each provincial forestry bureau at the <lb/>city and county levels across all investigated provinces. The solid <lb/>line indicates the regression line, and the dashed red line indicates <lb/>the 1 : 1 line. <lb/>1 (Fig. S3c and g). However, except for 2016, estimates from <lb/>other periods displayed varying degrees of underestimation <lb/>or overestimation (Fig. S3). <lb/>3.2 Spatial and temporal patterns of harvested carbon <lb/>in China <lb/>There was large heterogeneity in harvested carbon over the <lb/>regional scale. Harvesting mainly occurred in eastern and <lb/>southern China and rarely occurred in northwestern China <lb/>(Fig. 4a and b). Guangxi Province recorded the highest har-<lb/>vested carbon, constituting approximately 30 % of China&apos;s <lb/>annual total harvested carbon. This volume is 2.5 times larger <lb/>than that of Fujian, the province with the second highest <lb/>harvested carbon (Fig. 4c). In terms of harvesting methods, <lb/>over 80 % of the nationwide clear-cutting-harvested carbon <lb/>originated from Guangxi, Guangdong, Fujian, Yunnan, and <lb/>Jiangxi (Fig. 4c). Forest harvesting in Jiangxi, Guangdong, <lb/>Yunnan, and Hainan was dominated by clear-cutting; in these <lb/>provinces, harvested carbon from clear-cutting comprised <lb/>more than 50 % of the total harvested carbon (Figs. 4c, 5a). <lb/>For other provinces, selective logging was the main method <lb/>of forest harvesting (Fig. 5b). <lb/>China experienced an overall upward trend in for-<lb/>est carbon harvesting, with average harvesting of <lb/>68.3 ± 9.3 Mt C yr -1 from 2003 to 2018 (Fig. 6). The <lb/>most substantial growth in harvested carbon was observed <lb/>from 2003 to 2008, increasing approximately 1.6 times from <lb/>49.8 Mt C yr -1 in 2003 to 79.5 Mt C yr -1 in 2008 (Fig. 6). <lb/>Among all surveyed years, the harvested carbon peaked in <lb/>2008, primarily driven by an uptick in fuelwood harvest <lb/>(Fig. 7). In subsequent years, the harvested carbon generally <lb/>plateaued, with minor fluctuations. Selective logging was <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2465-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2465-2481, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2472 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">D. Wang et al.: National forest carbon harvesting and allocation dataset <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 4. Map of forest harvested carbon for China in 2016 at (a) 30 m and (b) 0.1°resolution and the zoomed-in view of the example areas <lb/>of (a) (a1, a2, and a3); the map at 0.1°was derived from a 30 m data upscaling, and (c) shows the harvested carbon from clear-cutting and <lb/>selective logging by province in 2016. <lb/>the main method of forest harvesting (Fig. 6). Averaged <lb/>from 2003 to 2018, there was 55.6 ± 7.2 Mt C yr -1 from <lb/>selective logging, accounting for around 82 % of the total <lb/>harvested carbon (Fig. 6). Nevertheless, the proportion of <lb/>harvested carbon from clear-cutting was overall on the rise, <lb/>reaching its peak in 2012 when it constituted 30 % of the <lb/>total harvested carbon for that year (Fig. 6). <lb/>3.3 Allocation of harvested carbon into the various <lb/>wood pools <lb/>This study also provides the allocation of harvested carbon <lb/>into the various wood pools with different lifetimes, includ-<lb/>ing the fuelwood pool, the paper and paperboard pool, the <lb/>wood-based panel pool, the solid wooden furniture pool, the <lb/>structural constructions pool, and the residue pool (Sect. 2.2). <lb/>Averaged from 2003 to 2018, over the entirety of China, har-<lb/>vested carbon was allocated into six pools with 19.6 ± 4.0 %, <lb/>2.1 ± 1.1 %, 35.5 ± 12.6 %, 6.2 ± 0.3 %, 17.5 ± 0.9 %, and <lb/>19.1 ± 9.8 %, respectively (Fig. 7). Wood for HWPs mainly <lb/>came from southern China, with Guangxi contributing more <lb/>than 20 % of the national wood for HWPs annually, followed <lb/>by Fujian (7.5 %). Meanwhile, Guangxi also contributed up <lb/>to 45.5 % of the wood used for paper production (Fig. 8). <lb/>Over 50 % of the wood in Fujian was used for fuelwood, <lb/>contributing nearly 30 % of the national fuelwood. Similarly <lb/>to Fujian, more than 50 % of the wood in Yunnan was used <lb/>for fuelwood, making Yunnan the second-largest province in <lb/>terms of wood supply for fuelwood (Fig. 8). From 2003 to <lb/>2018, wood harvesting increased, while wood for fuel de-<lb/>creased, with its share decreasing from 29 % to 13 %. More <lb/>wood was used for HWP production. The wood residues de-<lb/>creased from 2003 to 2018 (Fig. 7). <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2465-2481, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2465-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">D. Wang et al.: National forest carbon harvesting and allocation dataset <lb/></note>

        <page>2473 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 5. Map of forest harvested carbon from (a) clear-cutting and (b) selective logging for China in 2016 at 0.1°resolution. <lb/>Figure 6. Long-term changes in harvested carbon in China between <lb/>2003 and 2018 from statistical, LUH2, FAO, and LEAF datasets. <lb/>We further quantified the delayed emissions of harvested <lb/>carbon in various pools. Combustion of fuelwood resulted <lb/>in major carbon emissions, and wood-based panels con-<lb/>tributed a major share of the carbon stock (Fig. 9). Fuel-<lb/>wood was typically burned for a short period of time (1 year), <lb/>resulting in average emissions of 48.1 ± 7.4 Mt CO 2 e yr -1 <lb/>from 2003 to 2018 (Fig. 9c). Additionally, discarded HWPs <lb/>that enter landfills undergo gradual decomposition, releas-<lb/>ing an average of 3.1 ± 3.0, 14.4 ± 12.2, 2.5 ± 1.8, and <lb/>6.5 ± 3.3 Mt CO 2 e yr -1 for paper and paperboard, wood-<lb/>based panels, solid wooden furniture, and structural con-<lb/>structions, respectively, from 2003 to 2100 (Fig. 9d). The <lb/>total carbon stock sustained an upward trend, peaking at <lb/>2126.9 ± 244.9 Mt CO 2 e in 2018 (Fig. 9a, b). As products <lb/>were discarded and/or retired, the carbon stock in currently <lb/>used products persistently declines without ongoing wood in-<lb/>puts (Fig. 9a). Furthermore, most of the waste products that <lb/>enter landfills do not decompose and become a permanent <lb/>carbon sink (Fig. 9b). About 39.2 % ± 10.0 % of carbon har-<lb/>Figure 7. Long-term changes in different pools of harvested carbon <lb/>from 2003 to 2018 in China. <lb/>vested during 2003-2018 will still be stored in the HWPs by <lb/>2100 (Fig. 9b). <lb/>4 Discussion <lb/>4.1 Implications for simulating the carbon sink in China <lb/>Forest harvesting is one of the most important human activi-<lb/>ties determining the terrestrial ecosystem carbon budget (Liu <lb/>et al., 2011; Pan et al., 2011). Forest harvesting largely de-<lb/>creases the leaf area index, increases litter biomass, and al-<lb/>ters stand temperature and moisture, strongly impacting the <lb/>structure and function of ecosystems (Nepstad et al., 1999; <lb/>Liu et al., 2011; Jian et al., 2022). Harvesting causes damage <lb/>to the forest canopy and soils, leading to temporary increases <lb/>in litter carbon stock. It ultimately results in a net loss of <lb/>soil carbon due to the damages inflicted on the forest canopy <lb/>and soil. Following a disturbance, soil carbon loss can exceed <lb/>carbon gain in aboveground biomass (Kowalski et al., 2004). <lb/>Pennock and van Kessel (1997) found that soil carbon de-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2465-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2465-2481, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2474 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">D. Wang et al.: National forest carbon harvesting and allocation dataset <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 8. Pools of provincial harvested carbon averaged from 2003 to 2018. <lb/>creased by 5 to 20 t C ha -1 over a 20-year period following <lb/>clear-cutting, a significant loss compared to the carbon ac-<lb/>cumulated in a maturing forest&apos;s biomass (Pennock and Van <lb/>Kessel, 1997). <lb/>Forest harvesting is a type of human activity that cannot <lb/>be simulated by ecosystem modeling. Therefore, the devel-<lb/>opment of regional and global datasets is necessary for quan-<lb/>tifying the impacts of forest harvesting. The LUH2 dataset is <lb/>an important source of data for indicating global forest har-<lb/>vesting and has been widely used to simulate the impacts <lb/>of forest harvesting on the terrestrial carbon sink (Harper <lb/>et al., 2018; Hurtt et al., 2020; Friedlingstein et al., 2022). <lb/>However, our results showed that the LUH2 dataset under-<lb/>estimated harvested carbon by about 38.5 % on average for <lb/>China compared with the statistical data (Fig. 5, Fig. S4). The <lb/>LUH2 dataset used national wood volume harvest data from <lb/>the Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO, 2020). Across <lb/>all of China, the harvested carbon data from FAO were ap-<lb/>proximately 40 % higher compared to the statistical data av-<lb/>eraged from 2003 to 2018, caused by the different statistical <lb/>methodologies and data sources used in FAO and China&apos;s sta-<lb/>tistical data. Nevertheless, in LUH2, the wood from agricul-<lb/>tural expansion was subtracted, and the remaining national <lb/>wood was then explicitly harvested (Hurtt et al., 2020). How-<lb/>ever, according to LUH2, the cropland area has increased by <lb/>4.1×10 7 ha since 1980 in China, which significantly deviates <lb/>from the actual situation (i.e., decreased by 1.4 × 10 7 ha) (Yu <lb/>et al., 2022). Therefore, LUH2 has overestimated wood har-<lb/>vests due to agricultural expansion, leading to the underes-<lb/>timation of wood from forest harvesting. Furthermore, after <lb/>2000, the spatial pattern of forest harvesting was constrained <lb/>using the Landsat forest loss data (i.e., TCL) (Hansen et al., <lb/>2013) by verifying whether the annualized gridded forest loss <lb/>derived from the Landsat data matched the forest-harvesting <lb/>information in the LUH2 dataset. However, the TCL dataset <lb/>only indicates clear-cutting and does not include selective <lb/>logging. Our result showed that there was a large proportion <lb/>of selective logging (Fig. 6), indicating that the LUH2 dataset <lb/>largely underestimates the harvest area. <lb/>This study not only represents the temporal and spatial <lb/>patterns of harvested carbon but also provides the alloca-<lb/>tion of harvested carbon among the pools. Unlike harvested <lb/>crop carbon, which will emit into the atmosphere at a faster <lb/>rate, harvested forest carbon is stored in various HWP pools <lb/>and emits back into the atmosphere with different lifetimes <lb/>(Skog, 2008; IPCC, 2019a). As an extension of forest re-<lb/>sources, the carbon dynamics of HWPs in use and after use <lb/>have multiple impacts on national greenhouse gas (GHG) in-<lb/>ventories (Johnston and Radeloff, 2019). Clarifying the pro-<lb/>portion of post-harvest carbon allocated to different pools is <lb/>the key to accurately assessing carbon dynamics. In addition, <lb/>previous studies focused more on the carbon stored in HWPs <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2465-2481, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2465-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">D. Wang et al.: National forest carbon harvesting and allocation dataset <lb/></note>

        <page>2475 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 9. The post-harvest carbon dynamics: (a) the accumulated carbon stock of in-use HWPs; (b) the accumulated carbon stock in landfills; <lb/>(c) annual carbon emissions of fuelwood and residues -since the burning of residues is not a definite fact, we represented it using dashed <lb/>lines; and (d) annual carbon emissions in landfills. The dashed black line indicates the year of 2018, when there is no new wood inflow in <lb/>the HWPs, the other dashed lines in (b) and (d) indicate the year when the corresponding products were all discarded, and the solid purple <lb/>line indicates the year when the first construction wood reached its service life. Since paper and paperboard, wood-based panels, and solid <lb/>wooden furniture have a service life of less than 16 years, carbon stock of emissions has no sharp changes before and after the year that the <lb/>service life was reached. The shaded area represents the variation range. <lb/>(Stockmann et al., 2012; Matsumoto et al., 2022; Wei et al., <lb/>2023). However, the assessment of the global potential of <lb/>HWPs as a carbon sink is subject to the balance between car-<lb/>bon inflows and outflows (Johnston and Radeloff, 2019). In <lb/>particular, waste products emit non-CO 2 GHGs such as CH 4 , <lb/>contributing to climate change (Cai et al., 2018). Moreover, <lb/>the carbon emissions from harvested wood exhibit delayed <lb/>and long-term effects. Tracking the long-term dynamics of <lb/>carbon and assessing the future climate mitigation potential <lb/>can provide a better foundation for GHG management in the <lb/>forestry sector. <lb/>4.2 Spatiotemporal changes in harvested carbon and <lb/>allocation in China <lb/>The spatial heterogeneity of forest harvesting is influenced <lb/>by the distribution of forest resources in China (Fig. 4). In-<lb/>tensive harvesting in southern China (e.g., Guangxi and Fu-<lb/>jian) indicates a demand for specific tree species, such as Eu-<lb/>calyptus and Cunninghamia lanceolata (Yu et al., 2020). As <lb/>the total harvesting increased, both clear-cutting and selec-<lb/>tive logging exhibited a general upward trend (Fig. 6), mir-<lb/>roring the dynamic equilibrium in the allocation of harvest-<lb/>ing methods across China&apos;s forests. The rate of increase in <lb/>clear-cutting significantly outpaced that of selective logging <lb/>(Fig. 6). A growing demand for wood is driving an upward <lb/>trend in large-scale forest harvesting. Nevertheless, selective <lb/>logging has remained the principal method of forest harvest-<lb/>ing in China. For the entirety of China, the number of pix-<lb/>els in which selective logging occurred is about 50 times the <lb/>number of pixels in which clear-cutting occurred (Fig. S5), <lb/>and the mean harvested biomass in a pixel from selective <lb/>logging is 8 % of that from clear-cutting (Figs. S5, 6). The <lb/>occurrence of such a small percentage of biomass removal <lb/>at the pixel level suggests the ability of the LEAF dataset <lb/>to capture minor disturbances. Moreover, selective logging <lb/>is a widely employed silvicultural practice that plays a cen-<lb/>tral role in forest management worldwide (Liu et al., 2011). <lb/>In the United States, the area covered by selective logging is <lb/>approximately 61 % of that occupied by clear-cutting (Masek <lb/>et al., 2011). In Brazil, selective logging doubles the previ-<lb/>ous estimates of the total forest degraded by human activi-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2465-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2465-2481, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2476 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">D. Wang et al.: National forest carbon harvesting and allocation dataset <lb/></note>

        <body>ties (Asner et al., 2005). Selective logging is a more diffuse <lb/>disturbance than forest clearance (Fisher et al., 2014) and is <lb/>mostly invisible to satellites (Asner et al., 2005; Matricardi <lb/>et al., 2010; Hethcoat et al., 2019). Despite many efforts to <lb/>address the challenge of estimating selective logging using <lb/>satellite data through image classification, it is still difficult <lb/>to monitor low-intensity selective logging due to the coarse <lb/>resolution of satellite imagery (Asner et al., 2005; Matricardi <lb/>et al., 2010; Hethcoat et al., 2019). Objective spatially ex-<lb/>plicit reporting on selective logging is the basis for model-<lb/>based assessment of the impact of forest harvesting on the <lb/>carbon budget. <lb/>Forest harvesting in China continued to increase during the <lb/>study period. However, the wood for fuel declined by nearly <lb/>23 %; in particular, the harvesting for burning by farmers, <lb/>contributing an average of nearly 70 % of burned timber an-<lb/>nually, decreased by nearly 35 % (Fig. S6). This rapid decline <lb/>in rural areas indicates that China is successful in the rural <lb/>energy transition, benefiting the mitigation of air pollution <lb/>and climate change (Chen et al., 2016; Tao et al., 2018). Pro-<lb/>duction of wood and paper products in China was on the rise <lb/>(Fig. 7), constituting a carbon pool that delays carbon release <lb/>(Fig. 9). HWPs in use rarely emit carbon if there is no de-<lb/>cay or combustion (e.g., building fire), being a stable carbon <lb/>sink during their lifespan, especially wood used for construc-<lb/>tions (Profft et al., 2009; Churkina et al., 2020). Although <lb/>the CO 2 emitted in landfills is considered to be carbon neu-<lb/>tral (Van Ewijk et al., 2020), CH 4 emissions from landfills <lb/>are detrimental to climate due to their higher global warm-<lb/>ing potential (IPCC, 2023). Promoting an increase in carbon <lb/>storage and a reduction in carbon emissions can be achieved <lb/>by extending the lifespan and improving the recycling rate <lb/>of HWPs (Brunet-Navarro et al., 2017). However, this ap-<lb/>proach may not be as effective for paper products as they of-<lb/>ten have low or even negative recycling benefits (Van Ewijk <lb/>et al., 2020). Therefore, recommendations in the wood sector <lb/>prioritize allocating harvested wood to long-lasting products <lb/>(Fortin et al., 2012; Smyth et al., 2014) and products with <lb/>high recycling rates (Brunet-Navarro et al., 2016; Werner et <lb/>al., 2010). Improving the efficiency of wood harvesting and <lb/>processing processes, as well as enhancing forest ecological <lb/>management, is also necessary for the reduction of carbon <lb/>emissions. <lb/>4.3 Uncertainties of the LEAF dataset <lb/>Although the LEAF dataset demonstrated a good perfor-<lb/>mance in capturing the spatial variability of harvested car-<lb/>bon in China, several potential uncertainties exist. First, cur-<lb/>rently, the use of forest wood was majorly extracted from the <lb/>aboveground components. Typically, roots of logged trees <lb/>will be disposed of in several ways, including decay stimula-<lb/>tion, sprout regeneration, combustion, and the production of <lb/>small boards (Li et al., 2012). There is no detailed informa-<lb/>tion regarding roots due to large differences over the regions <lb/>and species. Therefore, this study did not include the root <lb/>biomass in the entire estimate, which may result in underes-<lb/>timation of HWPs and their subsequent emissions. <lb/>Second, the harvested carbon was found to be underesti-<lb/>mated in several provinces over several years. Among the <lb/>estimates covering a span of 16 years across 31 provinces, <lb/>approximately 28 % of them were underestimated, with the <lb/>highest frequency of underestimation occurring in south-<lb/>ern provinces (Fig. 10a). Compared to statistical values, <lb/>the harvested carbon was underestimated by an average of <lb/>0.4 %-60.4 % from 2003 to 2018 across these investigated <lb/>provinces (Fig. 10b). Anhui Province had the highest de-<lb/>gree of underestimation, with underestimation occurring in <lb/>all years (Fig. 10). To avoid this underestimation, we as-<lb/>signed the unidentified harvested carbon to the pixels where <lb/>selective logging occurred, increasing the harvested carbon <lb/>of these pixels (Sect. 2.1, Eq. 6) and resulting in an estima-<lb/>tion of more harvested carbon than the actual AGB at several <lb/>pixels. We examined the number of pixels where the har-<lb/>vested carbon exceeded its AGB at the province level. The <lb/>results showed that the number of pixels where harvested <lb/>carbon exceeded its AGB was less than 2 % of the number <lb/>of pixels where harvesting occurred for each province annu-<lb/>ally (Fig. S7). <lb/>The underestimation of harvested carbon is closely related <lb/>to the accuracy of identifying both selective logging and <lb/>clear-cutting. (1) Wood output rate (R) is a key parameter <lb/>for calculating the total wood harvest at the provincial level. <lb/>Its value varies depending on factors such as tree species, <lb/>wood quality, and processing methods (Jiang et al., 2022). <lb/>Even within the same province, R can vary significantly. <lb/>However, due to the lack of R data at the sub-provincial <lb/>level, this study utilized the provincial R values for 2009 ob-<lb/>tained from the official website of the National Bureau of <lb/>Statistics (Table S2). Using provincial-level R for a single <lb/>year overlooked the intra-provincial and inter-annual vari-<lb/>ations in R, potentially leading to bias in estimating the <lb/>total wood harvest. (2) AGB is another important poten-<lb/>tial cause. After forest harvesting, tree regeneration would <lb/>form new biomass. This study used the National Forest In-<lb/>ventory datasets to estimate AGB, conducted at 5-year in-<lb/>tervals. Within this 5-year period, the forest inventory can-<lb/>not include the increased biomass due to tree regeneration, <lb/>which will lead to an underestimation of AGB. (3) The con-<lb/>version of biomass storage to AGB (Coef) exhibited signif-<lb/>icant variations among provinces, possibly due to different <lb/>dominant vegetation types and growing stock levels across <lb/>provinces. The default biomass conversion and expansion <lb/>factors (BCEFs, equivalent to Coef in this study) provided <lb/>by the IPCC also confirmed the significant differences in <lb/>Coef across vegetation types and growing stock levels (IPCC, <lb/>2006b). However, compared to the IPCC&apos;s coarse regional <lb/>classification, the provincial-level Coef we utilized in this <lb/>study is more detailed. (4) The quality of selective logging <lb/>identification largely depends on the quality and performance <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2465-2481, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2465-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">D. Wang et al.: National forest carbon harvesting and allocation dataset <lb/></note>

        <page>2477 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 10. (a) Annual NDVI diff thresholds (NDVI Th ) for each province. An NDVI Th of 0 indicates that the province&apos;s harvested carbon <lb/>was underestimated that year, and a blank NDVI Th denotes that there was no harvesting in that province that year according to the statistics. <lb/>(b) Average percentage of underestimated harvested carbon in the provinces where underestimation occurred from 2003 to 2018. <lb/>of NDVI. The accuracy is largely impacted by low data qual-<lb/>ity in cloudy and rainy southern areas. In addition, NDVI is <lb/>sensitive to green vegetation cover but not dense vegetation <lb/>(Huete et al., 2002) and begins to saturate over dense veg-<lb/>etation with AGB values higher than 25 t C ha -1 (Chang et <lb/>al., 2023), contributing to the underestimation of AGB. Over-<lb/>looking the continued growth after harvesting within a pixel <lb/>and the regional-scale climate impacts led to an underestima-<lb/>tion of NDVI diff . Consequently, the harvested carbon may be <lb/>underestimated at regional scales, particularly in provinces <lb/>with substantial forest coverage (e.g., Guangxi). (5) The es-<lb/>timation of clear-cutting was primarily limited by the perfor-<lb/>mance of the TCL dataset generated by Hansen et al. (2013). <lb/>In subtropical and temperate regions, the producer&apos;s accuracy <lb/>and user&apos;s accuracy of TCL are both approximately 80 %, <lb/>indicating that the dataset can identify tree cover loss with <lb/>relatively high accuracy. However, there is still a 20 % level <lb/>of uncertainty (Hansen et al., 2013), and further efforts are <lb/>needed to improve the identification of clear-cutting. <lb/>Third, we compared our estimates of carbon stocks of <lb/>HWPs with previous studies. Zhang et al. (2019) estimated <lb/>the carbon stock of HWPs to be 1.7 Gt CO 2 e for the period of <lb/>2003-2016, which is 1.3 times higher than our estimates for <lb/>the same period (Fig. 8b). Zhang et al. (2019) used statistical <lb/>data of HWPs provided by FAO, which show a significant <lb/>disparity compared to China&apos;s official figures (Fig. 6). Zhang <lb/>et al. (2018) estimated carbon stocks of HWPs from 1950 <lb/>to 2015 using China&apos;s official data, but these also included <lb/>the imported HWPs. As China&apos;s wood imports are consider-<lb/>able, the estimates of Zhang et al. (2018) for 2003-2015 are <lb/>nearly 1.8 times our estimates. This study aims to quantity <lb/>the contribution of harvested wood to national CO 2 emis-<lb/>sion in China; therefore, we excluded the imported wood ac-<lb/>cording to the IPCC standard. Moreover, these previous esti-<lb/>mates depended on default factors recommend by the IPCC <lb/>inventory method to calculate CO 2 emissions and stocks in <lb/>HWPs, and these showed large differences with specific fac-<lb/>tors in China used by this study. In addition, this study also <lb/>provides estimates of stocks and CO 2 emission dynamics, <lb/>which is quite important for understanding their long-term <lb/>contributions. Nevertheless, information on the end products <lb/>of harvested wood (i.e., bathroom tissue, tableware, types of <lb/>furniture, columns) is unavailable (Profft et al., 2009), lead-<lb/>ing to rough estimates of wood destination and product ser-<lb/>vice life. In this study, all residual wood was assumed to be <lb/>burned as fuelwood, which would induce an overestimation <lb/>of carbon emissions. Meanwhile, this study ignored recy-<lb/>cled wood products, which may extend the carbon storage in <lb/>products (Brunet-Navarro et al., 2017), causing an underes-<lb/>timation of carbon stock in products in use. More efforts are <lb/>needed to track the production and end use of the harvested <lb/>wood as they play a key role in the estimation of the effects <lb/>on national GHG inventories (White et al., 2005; Johnston <lb/>and Radeloff, 2019). <lb/>5 Data availability <lb/>The 30 m × 30 m Long-term harvEst and Allocation <lb/>of Forest Biomass (LEAF) dataset is available at <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.23641164.v2 <lb/>(Wang <lb/>et al., 2023). <lb/>The file format of the product is GeoTIFF, with the spatial <lb/>reference of WGS84 (EPSG:4326). Each GeoTIFF file rep-<lb/>resents annual harvested forest carbon (unit: g C m -2 yr -1 ), <lb/>and the absolute harvested carbon per pixel is obtained by <lb/>multiplying by the corresponding pixel area. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2465-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2465-2481, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2478 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">D. Wang et al.: National forest carbon harvesting and allocation dataset <lb/></note>

        <body>6 Conclusions <lb/>This study produced the LEAF dataset, which provides spa-<lb/>tial information on forest harvesting at a resolution of 30 m. <lb/>The validation results demonstrated the accuracy and relia-<lb/>bility of the LEAF dataset in capturing the spatial variations <lb/>of harvested carbon. From 2003 to 2018, harvested carbon <lb/>showed an increasing trend. Additionally, our dataset showed <lb/>that selective logging resulted in more than 80 % of the total <lb/>harvested carbon. The carbon taken away from forest har-<lb/>vesting was allocated to six wood pools, with the direct com-<lb/>bustion of fuelwood as the primary source of carbon emis-<lb/>sions after harvesting. However, it is important to highlight <lb/>that the carbon stored in wooden products has the potential <lb/>for long-term retention. In summary, the development of the <lb/>LEAF dataset enhances our understanding of the spatial pat-<lb/>terns of forest harvesting and post-harvest carbon dynamics <lb/>in China. The LEAF dataset generated by this study is an im-<lb/>portant data source for estimating the carbon budget of forest <lb/>ecosystems in China, which can also provide essential in-<lb/>sights for sustainable forest management and climate change <lb/>mitigation efforts. <lb/></body>

        <div type="annex">Supplement. The supplement related to this article is available <lb/>online at: https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2465-2024-supplement. <lb/></div>

        <div type="contribution">Author contributions. WY and DW designed the research, per-<lb/>formed the analysis, and wrote the paper; PR and XX performed <lb/>the analysis; LF, ZQ, and XC edited and revised the paper. <lb/></div>

        <div type="conflict">Competing interests. The contact author has declared that none <lb/>of the authors has any competing interests. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Disclaimer. Publisher&apos;s note: Copernicus Publications remains <lb/>neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims made in the text, pub-<lb/>lished maps, institutional affiliations, or any other geographical rep-<lb/>resentation in this paper. While Copernicus Publications makes ev-<lb/>ery effort to include appropriate place names, the final responsibility <lb/>lies with the authors. Regarding the maps used in this paper, please <lb/>note that Figs. 4, 5 and 8 contain disputed territories. <lb/></div>

        <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements. We acknowledge the data on the distribu-<lb/>tion of national nature reserve support from the National Earth Sys-<lb/>tem Data Center, National Science and Technology Infrastructure <lb/>of China (http://www.geodata.cn, last access: 1 August 2022). <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">Financial support. This research was supported by the key <lb/>project of the National Natural Science Foundation of China (grant <lb/>no. 42141020). <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Review statement. This paper was edited by Zhen Yu and re-<lb/>viewed by three anonymous referees. <lb/></div>

        <listBibl>References <lb/>Asner, G. P., Knapp, D. E., Broadbent, E. N., Oliveira, <lb/>P. J. C., Keller, M., and Silva, J. N.: Selective log-<lb/>ging in the Brazilian Amazon, Science, 310, 480-482, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1118051, 2005. <lb/>Brunet-Navarro, P., Jochheim, H., and Muys, B.: Modelling <lb/>carbon stocks and fluxes in the wood product sector: a <lb/>comparative review, Glob. Change Biol., 22, 2555-2569, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.13235, 2016. <lb/>Brunet-Navarro, P., Jochheim, H., and Muys, B.: The effect of in-<lb/>creasing lifespan and recycling rate on carbon storage in wood <lb/>products from theoretical model to application for the European <lb/>wood sector, Mitig. Adapt. Strateg. Glob. Change, 22, 1193-<lb/>1205, https://doi.org/10.1007/s11027-016-9722-z, 2017. <lb/>Cai, B., Lou, Z., Wang, J., Geng, Y., Sarkis, J., Liu, J., and <lb/>Gao, Q.: CH 4 mitigation potentials from China landfills and <lb/>related environmental co-benefits, Sci. Adv., 4, eaar8400, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aar8400, 2018. <lb/>Chang, Z., Fan, L., Wigneron, J.-P., Wang, Y.-P., Ciais, P., Chave, <lb/>J., Fensholt, R., Chen, J. M., Yuan, W., Ju, W., Li, X., Jiang, <lb/>F., Wu, M., Chen, X., Qin, Y., Frappart, F., Li, X., Wang, M., <lb/>Liu, X., Tang, X., Hobeichi, S., Yu, M., Ma, M., Wen, J., Xiao, <lb/>Q., Shi, W., Liu, D., and Yan, J.: Estimating aboveground car-<lb/>bon dynamic of China using optical and microwave remote <lb/>sensing datasets from 2013 to 2019, J. Remote Sens., 3, 0005, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.34133/remotesensing.0005, 2023. <lb/>Chen, C., Park, T., Wang, X., Piao, S., Xu, B., Chaturvedi, R. K., <lb/>Fuchs, R., Brovkin, V., Ciais, P., Fensholt, R., Tømmervik, H., <lb/>Bala, G., Zhu, Z., Nemani, R. R., and Myneni, R. B.: China and <lb/>India lead in greening of the world through land-use manage-<lb/>ment, Nat. Sustain., 2, 122-129, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41893-<lb/>019-0220-7, 2019. <lb/>Chen, Y., Shen, H., Zhong, Q., Chen, H., Huang, T., Liu, J., Cheng, <lb/>H., Zeng, E. Y., Smith, K. R., and Tao, S.: Transition of house-<lb/>hold cookfuels in China from 2010 to 2012, Appl. Energ., 184, <lb/>800-809, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apenergy.2016.07.136, 2016. <lb/>Churkina, G., Organschi, A., Reyer, C. P. O., Ruff, A., Vinke, K., <lb/>Liu, Z., Reck, B. K., Graedel, T. E., and Schellnhuber, H. J.: <lb/>Buildings as a global carbon sink, Nat. Sustain., 3, 269-276, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41893-019-0462-4, 2020. <lb/>Costanza, R., d&apos;Arge, R., de Groot, R., Farberl, S., Grasso, M., <lb/>Hannon, B., Limburg, K., Naeem, S., O&apos;Neil, R. V., Paruelo, J., <lb/>Raskin, R. G., Suttonl, P., and van den Belt, M.: The value of the <lb/>world&apos;s ecosystem services and natural capital, Nature, 387, 253-<lb/>260, https://doi.org/10.1016/S0921-8009(98)00020-2, 1997. <lb/>Curtis, P. G., Slay, C. M., Harris, N. L., Tyukavina, A., and Hansen, <lb/>M. C.: Classifying drivers of global forest loss, Science, 361, <lb/>1108-1111, https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aau3445, 2018. <lb/>Deal, R. L. and White, R.: Integrating forest products with ecosys-<lb/>tem services: A global perspective, For. Policy Econ., 17, 1-2, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.forpol.2012.02.014, 2012. <lb/>Dixon, R. K., Solomon, A. M., Brown, S., Houghton, R. <lb/>A., Trexier, M. C., and Wisniewski, J.: Carbon pools and <lb/>flux of global forest ecosystems, Science, 263, 185-190, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1126/science.263.5144.185, 1994. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2465-2481, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2465-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">D. Wang et al.: National forest carbon harvesting and allocation dataset <lb/></note>

        <page>2479 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>Dong, J., Zhou, Y., and You, N.: A 30 m annual maximum <lb/>NDVI dataset for China from 2000 to 2020 [DB/OL], <lb/>National Ecosystem Science Data Center [data set], <lb/>https://doi.org/10.12199/nesdc.ecodb.rs.2021.012, 2021. <lb/>FAO: Forestry data, FAOSTAT Database, Food and Agriculture Or-<lb/>ganization of the United Nations, Rome, Italy, https://www.fao. <lb/>org/faostat/en/#data/FO (last access: 25 June 2023), 2020. <lb/>Fisher, B., Edwards, D. P., and Wilcove, D. S.: Logging and con-<lb/>servation: Economic impacts of the stocking rates and prices <lb/>of commercial timber species, For. Policy Econ., 38, 65-71, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.forpol.2013.05.006, 2014. <lb/>Fortin, M., Ningre, F., Robert, N., and Mothe, F.: Quantifying <lb/>the impact of forest management on the carbon balance of <lb/>the forest-wood product chain: A case study applied to even-<lb/>aged oak stands in France, Forest Ecol. Manag., 279, 176-188, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foreco.2012.05.031, 2012. <lb/>Friedlingstein, P., O&apos;Sullivan, M., Jones, M. W., Andrew, R. M., <lb/>Gregor, L., Hauck, J., Le Quéré, C., Luijkx, I. T., Olsen, A., Pe-<lb/>ters, G. P., Peters, W., Pongratz, J., Schwingshackl, C., Sitch, S., <lb/>Canadell, J. G., Ciais, P., Jackson, R. B., Alin, S. R., Alkama, R., <lb/>Arneth, A., Arora, V. K., Bates, N. R., Becker, M., Bellouin, N., <lb/>Bittig, H. C., Bopp, L., Chevallier, F., Chini, L. P., Cronin, M., <lb/>Evans, W., Falk, S., Feely, R. A., Gasser, T., Gehlen, M., Gkritza-<lb/>lis, T., Gloege, L., Grassi, G., Gruber, N., Gürses, Ö., Harris, I., <lb/>Hefner, M., Houghton, R. A., Hurtt, G. C., Iida, Y., Ilyina, T., <lb/>Jain, A. K., Jersild, A., Kadono, K., Kato, E., Kennedy, D., Klein <lb/>Goldewijk, K., Knauer, J., Korsbakken, J. I., Landschützer, P., <lb/>Lefèvre, N., Lindsay, K., Liu, J., Liu, Z., Marland, G., Mayot, <lb/>N., McGrath, M. J., Metzl, N., Monacci, N. M., Munro, D. R., <lb/>Nakaoka, S.-I., Niwa, Y., O&apos;Brien, K., Ono, T., Palmer, P. I., Pan, <lb/>N., Pierrot, D., Pocock, K., Poulter, B., Resplandy, L., Robert-<lb/>son, E., Rödenbeck, C., Rodriguez, C., Rosan, T. M., Schwinger, <lb/>J., Séférian, R., Shutler, J. D., Skjelvan, I., Steinhoff, T., Sun, Q., <lb/>Sutton, A. J., Sweeney, C., Takao, S., Tanhua, T., Tans, P. P., Tian, <lb/>X., Tian, H., Tilbrook, B., Tsujino, H., Tubiello, F., van der Werf, <lb/>G. R., Walker, A. P., Wanninkhof, R., Whitehead, C., Willstrand <lb/>Wranne, A., Wright, R., Yuan, W., Yue, C., Yue, X., Zaehle, S., <lb/>Zeng, J., and Zheng, B.: Global Carbon Budget 2022, Earth Syst. <lb/>Sci. Data, 14, 4811-4900, https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-14-4811-<lb/>2022, 2022. <lb/>Hansen, M. C., Potapov, P. V., Moore, R., Hancher, M., Turubanova, <lb/>S. A., Tyukavina, A., Thau, D., Stehman, S. V., Goetz, S. J., <lb/>Loveland, T. R., Kommareddy, A., Egorov, A., Chini, L., Jus-<lb/>tice, C. O., and Townshend, J. R. G.: High-resolution global <lb/>maps of 21st-century forest cover change, Science, 342, 850-<lb/>853, https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1244693, 2013. <lb/>Harper, A. B., Powell, T., Cox, P. M., House, J., Huntingford, C., <lb/>Lenton, T. M., Sitch, S., Burke, E., Chadburn, S. E., Collins, W. <lb/>J., Comyn-Platt, E., Daioglou, V., Doelman, J. C., Hayman, G., <lb/>Robertson, E., Van Vuuren, D., Wiltshire, A., Webber, C. P., Bas-<lb/>tos, A., Boysen, L., Ciais, P., Devaraju, N., Jain, A. K., Krause, <lb/>A., Poulter, B., and Shu, S.: Land-use emissions play a criti-<lb/>cal role in landbased mitigation for Paris climate targets, Nat. <lb/>Commun., 9, 2938, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-018-05340-<lb/>z, 2018. <lb/>Harris, N. L., Gibbs, D. A., Baccini, A., Birdsey, R. A., De Bruin, S., <lb/>Farina, M., Fatoyinbo, L., Hansen, M. C., Herold, M., Houghton, <lb/>R. A., Potapov, P. V., Suarez, D. R., Roman-Cuesta, R. M., <lb/>Saatchi, S. S., Slay, C. M., Turubanova, S. A., and Tyukavina, <lb/>A.: Global maps of twenty-first century forest carbon fluxes, Nat. <lb/>Clim. Change, 11, 234-240, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41558-<lb/>020-00976-6, 2021. <lb/>Hethcoat, M. G., Edwards, D. P., Carreiras, J. M. B., Bryant, R. <lb/>G., França, F. M., and Quegan, S.: A machine learning approach <lb/>to map tropical selective logging, Remote Sens. Environ., 221, <lb/>569-582, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rse.2018.11.044, 2019. <lb/>Huete, A., Didan, K., Miura, T., Rodriguez, E. P., Gao, X., and Fer-<lb/>reira, L. G.: Overview of the radiometric and biophysical perfor-<lb/>mance of the MODIS vegetation indices, Remote Sens. Environ., <lb/>83, 195-213, https://doi.org/10.1016/S0034-4257(02)00096-2, <lb/>2002. <lb/>Hurtt, G. C., Chini, L. P., Frolking, S., Betts, R. A., Feddema, J., Fis-<lb/>cher, G., Fisk, J. P., Hibbard, K., Houghton, R. A., Janetos, A., <lb/>Jones, C. D., Kindermann, G., Kinoshita, T., Klein Goldewijk, <lb/>K., Riahi, K., Shevliakova, E., Smith, S., Stehfest, E., Thomson, <lb/>A., Thornton, P., Van Vuuren, D. P., and Wang, Y. P.: Harmo-<lb/>nization of land-use scenarios for the period 1500-2100: 600 <lb/>years of global gridded annual land-use transitions, wood har-<lb/>vest, and resulting secondary lands, Climatic Change, 109, 117-<lb/>161, https://doi.org/10.1007/s10584-011-0153-2, 2011. <lb/>Hurtt, G. C., Chini, L., Sahajpal, R., Frolking, S., Bodirsky, <lb/>B. L., Calvin, K., Doelman, J. C., Fisk, J., Fujimori, S., <lb/>Klein Goldewijk, K., Hasegawa, T., Havlik, P., Heinimann, <lb/>A., Humpenöder, F., Jungclaus, J., Kaplan, J. O., Kennedy, J., <lb/>Krisztin, T., Lawrence, D., Lawrence, P., Ma, L., Mertz, O., Pon-<lb/>gratz, J., Popp, A., Poulter, B., Riahi, K., Shevliakova, E., Ste-<lb/>hfest, E., Thornton, P., Tubiello, F. N., van Vuuren, D. P., and <lb/>Zhang, X.: Harmonization of global land use change and man-<lb/>agement for the period 850-2100 (LUH2) for CMIP6, Geosci. <lb/>Model Dev., 13, 5425-5464, https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-13-<lb/>5425-2020, 2020. <lb/>IPCC: 2006 IPCC Guidelines for National Greenhouse Gas Invento-<lb/>ries, Volume 4: Agriculture, Forestry and Other Land Use, Chap. <lb/>12: Harvested Wood Products, https://www.ipcc-nggip.iges.or. <lb/>jp/support/Primer_2006GLs.pdf (last access: 25 June 2023), <lb/>2006a. <lb/>IPCC: 2006 IPCC Guidelines for National Greenhouse Gas Invento-<lb/>ries, Volume 4: Agriculture, Forestry and Other Land Use, Chap. <lb/>4: Forest Land, https://www.ipcc-nggip.iges.or.jp/public/2006gl/ <lb/>pdf/4_Volume4/V4_04_Ch4_Forest_Land.pdf (last access: 27 <lb/>December 2023), 2006b. <lb/>IPCC: 2013 revised supplementary methods and good prac-<lb/>tice guidance arising from the Kyoto Protocol, Intergov-<lb/>ernmental Panel on Climate Change, Geneva, Switzer-<lb/>land, <lb/>https://www.ipcc-nggip.iges.or.jp/public/kpsg/pdf/KP_ <lb/>Supplement_Entire_Report.pdf (last access: 24 June 2023), <lb/>2014. <lb/>IPCC: Refinement to the 2006 IPCC Guidelines for National <lb/>Greenhouse Gas Inventories. Volume 5: Waste, Chap. 3: <lb/>Solid Waste Disposal, https://www.ipcc-nggip.iges.or.jp/public/ <lb/>2019rf/pdf/5_Volume5/19R_V5_3_Ch03_SWDS.pdf (last ac-<lb/>cess: 25 June 2023), 2019a. <lb/>IPCC: Refinement to the 2006 IPCC Guidelines for National <lb/>Greenhouse Gas Inventories. Volume 4: Agriculture, Forestry <lb/>and Other Land Use, Chap. 12: Harvested Wood Prod-<lb/>ucts, <lb/>https://www.ipcc-nggip.iges.or.jp/public/2019rf/pdf/4_ <lb/>Volume4/19R_V4_Ch12_HarvestedWoodProducts.pdf <lb/>(last <lb/>access: 27 December 2023), 2019b. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2465-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2465-2481, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2480 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">D. Wang et al.: National forest carbon harvesting and allocation dataset <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>IPCC: Climate Change 2021 -The Physical Science Ba-<lb/>sis: Working Group I Contribution to the Sixth Assess-<lb/>ment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Cli-<lb/>mate Change, 1st Edn., Cambridge University Press, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017/9781009157896, 2023. <lb/>Jian, X., Zhang, X., Liu, Y., Liu, X., Chen, K., Wang, L., Li, J., <lb/>Zhao, Y., Luo, J., Zhugu, R., and Ma, J.: The response of radiative <lb/>forcing to high spatiotemporally resolved land-use change and <lb/>transition from 1982 to 2010 in China, Geophys. Res. Lett., 49, <lb/>e2022GL099003, https://doi.org/10.1029/2022GL099003, 2022. <lb/>Jiang, X., Li, K., and Jiang, B.: Analysis on influencing factors of <lb/>wood products blank outturn rate, Sci. Technol. Eng., 22, 10930-<lb/>10938, 2022. <lb/>Johnston, C. M. T. and Radeloff, V. C.: Global miti-<lb/>gation potential of carbon stored in harvested wood <lb/>products, P. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 116, 14526-14531, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1904231116, 2019. <lb/>Kowalski, A. S., Loustau, D., Berbigier, P., Manca, G., Tedeschi, V., <lb/>Borghetti, M., Valentini, R., Kolari, P., Berninger, F., Rannik, Ü., <lb/>Hari, P., Rayment, M., Mencuccini, M., Moncrieff, J., and Grace, <lb/>J.: Paired comparisons of carbon exchange between undis-<lb/>turbed and regenerating stands in four managed forests in Eu-<lb/>rope: Carbon exchange in mature and regenerating forest, Glob. <lb/>Change Biol., 10, 1707-1723, https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-<lb/>2486.2004.00846.x, 2004. <lb/>Lal, R., Lorenz, K., Hüttl, R. F., Schneider, B. U., and Von <lb/>Braun, J. (Eds.): Ecosystem services and the global car-<lb/>bon cycle, in: Ecosystem services and carbon sequestration <lb/>in the biosphere, Springer Netherlands, Dordrecht, 151-181, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-94-007-6455-2, 2013. <lb/>Li, F., He, B., and Yang, Z.: Progress of research on tree felling <lb/>root treatment and application technology, Pract. For. Technol., <lb/>8, 9-11, https://doi.org/10.13456/j.cnki.lykt.2012.08.017, 2012. <lb/>Lippke, B., Oneil, E., Harrison, R., Skog, K., Gustavsson, L., and <lb/>Sathre, R.: Life cycle impacts of forest management and wood <lb/>utilization on carbon mitigation: knowns and unknowns, Carbon <lb/>Manag., 2, 303-333, https://doi.org/10.4155/cmt.11.24, 2011. <lb/>Liu, D., Chen, Y., Cai, W., Dong, W., Xiao, J., Chen, J., Zhang, H., <lb/>Xia, J., and Yuan, W.: The contribution of China&apos;s Grain to Green <lb/>Program to carbon sequestration, Landsc. Ecol., 29, 1675-1688, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10980-014-0081-4, 2014. <lb/>Liu, S., Bond-Lamberty, B., Hicke, J. A., Vargas, R., Zhao, <lb/>S., Chen, J., Edburg, S. L., Hu, Y., Liu, J., McGuire, A. <lb/>D., Xiao, J., Keane, R., Yuan, W., Tang, J., Luo, Y., Pot-<lb/>ter, C., and Oeding, J.: Simulating the impacts of distur-<lb/>bances on forest carbon cycling in North America: Processes, <lb/>data, models, and challenges, J. Geophys. Res., 116, G00K08, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2010JG001585, 2011. <lb/>Masek, J. G., Cohen, W. B., Leckie, D., Wulder, M. A., Vargas, R., <lb/>De Jong, B., Healey, S., Law, B., Birdsey, R., Houghton, R. A., <lb/>Mildrexler, D., Goward, S., and Smith, W. B.: Recent rates of for-<lb/>est harvest and conversion in North America, J. Geophys. Res., <lb/>116, G00K03, https://doi.org/10.1029/2010JG001471, 2011. <lb/>Matricardi, E. A. T., Skole, D. L., Pedlowski, M. A., Cho-<lb/>mentowski, W., and Fernandes, L. C.: Assessment of trop-<lb/>ical forest degradation by selective logging and fire using <lb/>Landsat imagery, Remote Sens. Environ., 114, 1117-1129, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rse.2010.01.001, 2010. <lb/>Matsumoto, R., Kayo, C., Kita, S., Nakamura, K., Lauk, C., <lb/>and Funada, R.: Estimation of carbon stocks in wood prod-<lb/>ucts for private building companies, Sci. Rep., 12, 18112, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-23112-0, 2022. <lb/>Nabuurs, G.-J., Verweij, P., Van Eupen, M., Pérez-Soba, M., Pülzl, <lb/>H., and Hendriks, K.: Next-generation information to support a <lb/>sustainable course for European forests, Nat. Sustain., 2, 815-<lb/>818, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41893-019-0374-3, 2019. <lb/>National Forestry Administration: The definition of China <lb/>forestry statistic indicators, China Forestry Press, Beijing, 117-<lb/>137, https://www.stats.gov.cn/zt_18555/ztsj/hjtjzl/2013/202303/ <lb/>t20230302_1920915.html (last access: 12 January 2024), 2000. <lb/>National Forestry and Grassland Administration: China Forest Re-<lb/>sources Report in 2014-2018, China Forestry Publishing, ISBN <lb/>978-7-5038-9982-9, 2019. <lb/>Nepstad, D. C., Nobre, C., Lima, E., Lefebvre, P., Schlesinger, P., <lb/>Potter, C., Mendoza, E., Cochrane, M., and Brooks, V.: Large-<lb/>scale impoverishment of Amazonian forests by logging and fire, <lb/>398, 505-508, https://doi.org/10.1038/19066, 1999. <lb/>Pan, Y., Birdsey, R. A., Fang, J., Houghton, R., Kauppi, P. E., Kurz, <lb/>W. A., Phillips, O. L., Shvidenko, A., Lewis, S. L., Canadell, <lb/>J. G., Ciais, P., Jackson, R. B., Pacala, S. W., McGuire, A. D., <lb/>Piao, S., Rautiainen, A., Sitch, S., and Hayes, D.: A large and <lb/>persistent carbon sink in the world&apos;s forests, Science, 333, 988-<lb/>993, https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1201609, 2011. <lb/>Pennock, D. J. and Van Kessel, C.: Clear-cut forest har-<lb/>vest impacts on soil quality indicators in the mixedwood <lb/>forest of Saskatchewan, Canada, Geoderma, 75, 13-32, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/S0016-7061(96)00075-4, 1997. <lb/>Pingoud, K. and Wagner, F.: Methane emissions from landfills and <lb/>carbon dynamics of harvested wood products: The First-Order <lb/>Decay revisited, Mitig. Adapt. Strateg. Glob. Change, 11, 961-<lb/>978, https://doi.org/10.1007/s11027-006-9029-6, 2006. <lb/>Profft, I., Mund, M., Weber, G.-E., Weller, E., and Schulze, E.-D.: <lb/>Forest management and carbon sequestration in wood products, <lb/>Eur. J. For. Res., 128, 399-413, https://doi.org/10.1007/s10342-<lb/>009-0283-5, 2009. <lb/>Research and Market: Research report on timber import in <lb/>China, 2019-2023, China Research &amp; Intelligence, https://www. <lb/>researchandmarkets.com/reports/4744796 (last access: 27 July <lb/>2023), 2019. <lb/>Skog, K. E.: Sequestration of carbon in harvested wood products <lb/>for the United States, For. Prod. J., 58, 56-72, 2008. <lb/>Skog, K. E., Pingoud, K., and Smith, J. E.: A method countries can <lb/>use to estimate changes in carbon stored in harvested wood prod-<lb/>ucts and the uncertainty of such estimates, Environ. Manage., 33, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00267-003-9118-1, 2004. <lb/>Smyth, C. E., Stinson, G., Neilson, E., Lemprière, T. C., Hafer, M., <lb/>Rampley, G. J., and Kurz, W. A.: Quantifying the biophysical <lb/>climate change mitigation potential of Canada&apos;s forest sector, <lb/>Biogeosciences, 11, 3515-3529, https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-11-<lb/>3515-2014, 2014. <lb/>Stockmann, K. D., Anderson, N. M., Skog, K. E., Healey, S. P., Lo-<lb/>effler, D. R., Jones, G., and Morrison, J. F.: Estimates of carbon <lb/>stored in harvested wood products from the United States forest <lb/>service northern region, 1906-2010, Carbon Balance Manag., 7, <lb/>1, https://doi.org/10.1186/1750-0680-7-1, 2012. <lb/>Tao, S., Ru, M. Y., Du, W., Zhu, X., Zhong, Q. R., Li, B. G., Shen, <lb/>G. F., Pan, X. L., Meng, W. J., Chen, Y. L., Shen, H. Z., Lin, N., <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2465-2481, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2465-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">D. Wang et al.: National forest carbon harvesting and allocation dataset <lb/></note>

        <page>2481 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>Su, S., Zhuo, S. J., Huang, T. B., Xu, Y., Yun, X., Liu, J. F., Wang, <lb/>X. L., Liu, W. X., Cheng, H. F., and Zhu, D. Q.: Quantifying the <lb/>rural residential energy transition in China from 1992 to 2012 <lb/>through a representative national survey, Nat. Energy, 3, 567-<lb/>573, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41560-018-0158-4, 2018. <lb/>Van Ewijk, S., Stegemann, J. A., and Ekins, P.: Limited climate ben-<lb/>efits of global recycling of pulp and paper, Nat. Sustain., 4, 180-<lb/>187, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41893-020-00624-z, 2020. <lb/>Wang, D., Ren, P., Xia, X., Fan, L., Qin, Z., Chen, X., and <lb/>Yuan, W.: National forest carbon harvesting and allocation <lb/>dataset for the period 2003 to 2018. figshare [data set], <lb/>https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.23641164.v2, 2023. <lb/>Wei, X., Zhao, J., Hayes, D. J., Daigneault, A., and Zhu, H.: A <lb/>life cycle and product type based estimator for quantifying the <lb/>carbon stored in wood products, Carbon Balance Manag., 18, 1, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1186/s13021-022-00220-y, 2023. <lb/>Werner, F., Taverna, R., Hofer, P., Thürig, E., and Kauf-<lb/>mann, E.: National and global greenhouse gas dynamics <lb/>of different forest management and wood use scenarios: a <lb/>model-based assessment, Environ. Sci. Policy, 13, 72-85, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envsci.2009.10.004, 2010. <lb/>White, M. K., Gower, S. T., and Ahl, D. E.: Life cycle inventories <lb/>of roundwood production in northern Wisconsin: Inputs into an <lb/>industrial forest carbon budget, Forest Ecol. Manag., 219, 13-28, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foreco.2005.08.039, 2005. <lb/>Winjum, J. K., Brown, S., and Schlamadinger, B.: For-<lb/>est harvests and wood products: Sources and sinks of <lb/>atmospheric carbon dioxide, For. Sci., 44, 272-284, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1093/forestscience/44.2.272, 1998. <lb/>Xia, X., Xia, J., Chen, X., Fan, L., Liu, S., Qin, Y., Qin, Z., Xiao, <lb/>X., Xu, W., Yue, C., Yue, X., and Yuan, W.: Reconstructing long-<lb/>term forest cover in China by fusing national forest inventory and <lb/>20 land use and land cover data sets, J. Geophys. Res.-Biogeo., <lb/>128, e2022JG007101, https://doi.org/10.1029/2022JG007101, <lb/>2023. <lb/>Yu, Z., Zhao, H., Liu, S., Zhou, G., Fang, J., Yu, G., Tang, <lb/>X., Wang, W., Yan, J., Wang, G., Ma, K., Li, S., Du, <lb/>S., Han, S., Ma, Y., Zhang, D., Liu, J., Liu, S., Chu, <lb/>G., Zhang, Q., and Li, Y.: Mapping forest type and age <lb/>in China&apos;s plantations, Sci. Total Environ., 744, 140790, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.140790, 2020. <lb/>Yu, Z., Ciais, P., Piao, S., Houghton, R. A., Lu, C., Tian, H., Agath-<lb/>okleous, E., Kattel, G. R., Sitch, S., Goll, D., Yue, X., Walker, <lb/>A., Friedlingstein, P., Jain, A. K., Liu, S., and Zhou, G.: Forest <lb/>expansion dominates China&apos;s land carbon sink since 1980, Nat. <lb/>Commun., 13, 5374, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-022-32961-<lb/>2, 2022. <lb/>Yuan, W., Li, X., Liang, S., Cui, X., Dong, W., Liu, S., <lb/>Xia, J., Chen, Y., Liu, D., and Zhu, W.: Characterization <lb/>of locations and extents of afforestation from the Grain for <lb/>Green Project in China, Remote Sens. Lett., 5, 221-229, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/2150704X.2014.894655, 2014. <lb/>Yuan, W., Zheng, Y., Piao, S., Ciais, P., Lombardozzi, D., Wang, <lb/>Y., Ryu, Y., Chen, G., Dong, W., Hu, Z., Jain, A. K., Jiang, <lb/>C., Kato, E., Li, S., Lienert, S., Liu, S., Nabel, J. E. M. S., <lb/>Qin, Z., Quine, T., Sitch, S., Smith, W. K., Wang, F., Wu, C., <lb/>Xiao, Z., and Yang, S.: Increased atmospheric vapor pressure <lb/>deficit reduces global vegetation growth, Sci. Adv., 5, eaax1396, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aax1396, 2019. <lb/>Zhang, L., Sun, Y., Song, T., and Xu, J.: Harvested wood products <lb/>as a carbon sink in China, 1900-2016, Int. J. Environ. Res. Pub. <lb/>He., 16, 445, https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph16030445, 2019. <lb/>Zhang, X., Yang, H., and Chen, J.: Life-cycle car-<lb/>bon budget of China&apos;s harvested wood products <lb/>in 1900-2015, For. Policy Econ., 92, 181-192, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.forpol.2018.05.005, 2018. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2465-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2465-2481, 2024 </note>


	</text>

</TEI>