<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Short-term variation in pH in seawaters around coastal areas of Japan: characteristics and forcings</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Tsuneo</forename>
          <surname>Ono</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Daisuke</forename>
          <surname>Muraoka</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Masahiro</forename>
          <surname>Hayashi</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Makiko</forename>
          <surname>Yorifuji</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Akihiro</forename>
          <surname>Dazai</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Shigeyuki</forename>
          <surname>Omoto</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Takehiro</forename>
          <surname>Tanaka</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Tomohiro</forename>
          <surname>Okamura</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Goh</forename>
          <surname>Onitsuka</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Kenji</forename>
          <surname>Sudo</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Masahiko</forename>
          <surname>Fujii</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Ryuji</forename>
          <surname>Hamanoue</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Masahide</forename>
          <surname>Wakita</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-05T15:11:15.322Z">11/5/2025 3:11:15 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Copernicus GmbH</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.5194/bg-21-177-2024</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Tsuneo Ono, Daisuke Muraoka, Masahiro Hayashi, Makiko Yorifuji, Akihiro Dazai, Shigeyuki Omoto, Takehiro Tanaka, Tomohiro Okamura, Goh Onitsuka, Kenji Sudo, Masahiko Fujii, Ryuji Hamanoue, Masahide Wakita. (2024). Short-term variation in pH in seawaters around coastal areas of Japan: characteristics and forcings. Biogeosciences, 21(1), 177-199. DOI: 10.5194/bg-21-177-2024</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-05T15:10:15.170502Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-05T15:10:15.170502Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/>© Author(s) 2024. This work is distributed under <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License. <lb/>IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 : a daily 0.25°resolution dataset of <lb/>in situ-produced biogenic methanesulfonic acid and <lb/>sulfate over the North Atlantic during 1998-2022 based <lb/>on machine learning <lb/>Karam Mansour 1,2 , Stefano Decesari 1 , Darius Ceburnis 3 , Jurgita Ovadnevaite 3 , Lynn M. Russell 4 , <lb/>Marco Paglione 1 , Laurent Poulain 5 , Shan Huang 5,a , Colin O&apos;Dowd 3 , and Matteo Rinaldi 1 <lb/>1 Institute of Atmospheric Sciences and Climate, Italian National Research Council (CNR-ISAC), <lb/>Bologna, Italy <lb/>2 Oceanography Department, Faculty of Science, Alexandria University, Alexandria, Egypt <lb/>3 School of Natural Sciences, Ryan Institute Centre for Climate and Air Pollution Studies, <lb/>University of Galway, Galway, Ireland <lb/>4 Scripps Institution of Oceanography, University of California, San Diego, La Jolla, CA, USA <lb/>5 Atmospheric Chemistry Department (ACD), Leibniz Institute for Tropospheric Research (TROPOS), <lb/>Leipzig, Germany <lb/>a now at: Institute for Environmental and Climate Research (ECI), Jinan University, Guangzhou, China <lb/>Correspondence: Karam Mansour (k.mansour@isac.cnr.it) and Matteo Rinaldi (m.rinaldi@isac.cnr.it) <lb/>Received: 1 September 2023 -Discussion started: 6 December 2023 <lb/>Revised: 18 April 2024 -Accepted: 23 April 2024 -Published: 12 June 2024 <lb/>Abstract. Accurate long-term marine-derived biogenic sulfur aerosol concentrations at high spatial and tem-<lb/>poral resolutions are critical for a wide range of studies, including climatology, trend analysis, and model eval-<lb/>uation; this information is also imperative for the accurate investigation of the contribution of marine-derived <lb/>biogenic sulfur aerosol concentrations to the aerosol burden, for the elucidation of their radiative impacts, and <lb/>to provide boundary conditions for regional models. By applying machine learning algorithms, we constructed <lb/>the first publicly available daily gridded dataset of in situ-produced biogenic methanesulfonic acid (MSA) and <lb/>non-sea-salt sulfate (nss-SO = <lb/>4 ) concentrations covering the North Atlantic. The dataset is of high spatial resolu-<lb/>tion (0.25°× 0.25°) and spans 25 years (1998-2022), far exceeding what observations alone could achieve both <lb/>spatially and temporally. The machine learning models were generated by combining in situ observations of sul-<lb/>fur aerosol data from Mace Head Atmospheric Research Station, located on the west coast of Ireland, and from <lb/>the North Atlantic Aerosols and Marine Ecosystems Study (NAAMES) cruises in the northwestern Atlantic with <lb/>the constructed sea-to-air dimethylsulfide flux (F DMS ) and ECMWF ERA5 reanalysis datasets. To determine <lb/>the optimal method for regression, we employed five machine learning model types: support vector machines, <lb/>decision tree, regression ensemble, Gaussian process regression, and artificial neural networks. A comparison <lb/>of the mean absolute error (MAE), root-mean-square error (RMSE), and coefficient of determination (R 2 ) re-<lb/>vealed that Gaussian process regression (GPR) was the most effective algorithm, outperforming the other models <lb/>with respect to simulating the biogenic MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 concentrations. For predicting daily MSA (nss-SO = <lb/>4 ), <lb/>GPR displayed the highest R 2 value of 0.86 (0.72) and the lowest MAE of 0.014 (0.10) µg m -3 . GPR partial <lb/>dependence analysis suggests that the relationships between predictors and MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 concentrations <lb/>are complex rather than linear. Using the GPR algorithm, we produced a high-resolution daily dataset of in situ-<lb/>produced biogenic MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 sea-level concentrations over the North Atlantic, which we named &quot;In-situ <lb/>Produced Biogenic Methanesulfonic Acid and Sulfate over the North Atlantic&quot; (IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 ). The obtained <lb/>IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 data allowed us to analyze the spatiotemporal patterns of MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 as well as the ratio <lb/>Published by Copernicus Publications. <lb/>2718 <lb/>K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/>between them (MSA : nss-SO = <lb/>4 ). A comparison with the existing Copernicus Atmosphere Monitoring Service <lb/>ECMWF Atmospheric Composition Reanalysis 4 (CAMS-EAC4) reanalysis suggested that our high-resolution <lb/>dataset reproduces the spatial and temporal patterns of the biogenic sulfur aerosol concentration with high accu-<lb/>racy and has high consistency with independent measurements in the Atlantic Ocean. IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 is publicly <lb/>available at https://doi.org/10.17632/j8bzd5dvpx.1 (Mansour et al., 2023b). <lb/></front>

        <body>1 Introduction <lb/>Marine-derived biogenic sulfur aerosol particles exert an im-<lb/>portant influence on the radiative properties of the atmo-<lb/>sphere, both directly by scattering solar radiation and indi-<lb/>rectly by modifying cloud properties (Langmann et al., 2008; <lb/>Charlson et al., 1987). Dimethylsulfide (DMS), a volatile or-<lb/>ganic compound produced by marine microbes, is the main <lb/>precursor of biogenic sulfur-containing aerosols in the ma-<lb/>rine boundary layer (MBL). After being ventilated into the <lb/>atmosphere, DMS is oxidized to form two of the major sec-<lb/>ondary marine aerosol species: methanesulfonic acid (MSA) <lb/>and non-sea-salt sulfate (nss-SO = <lb/>4 ). Sulfur emitted by ma-<lb/>rine organisms constitutes 20 % (Fiddes et al., 2018) to 40 % <lb/>(Simo, 2001) of the total sulfur burden of the atmosphere. <lb/>An understanding of the role of MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 concen-<lb/>trations in Earth&apos;s climate is elusive (Mansour et al., 2020a; <lb/>Hodshire et al., 2019). According to the CLAW hypothesis <lb/>(Charlson et al., 1987), a negative climate feedback is ex-<lb/>pected to occur if phytoplankton respond to elevated tem-<lb/>perature or solar radiation levels by increasing their DMS <lb/>production, thereby exerting a cooling effect by increasing <lb/>the planetary albedo. Indeed, some studies have confirmed <lb/>that DMS emissions contribute significantly to stabilizing <lb/>the Earth&apos;s atmosphere (Sanchez et al., 2018; Thomas et al., <lb/>2010; Kim et al., 2018; Mahmood et al., 2019; Mansour et <lb/>al., 2022, 2020b), while a few others have claimed that the bi-<lb/>ological control over cloud condensation nuclei (CCN) goes <lb/>even beyond the climatic feedback role of DMS in the CLAW <lb/>hypothesis (Quinn and Bates, 2011; Woodhouse et al., 2010; <lb/>O&apos;Dowd et al., 2004). As a result, biogenic sulfur aerosols <lb/>play a central role in ocean-atmosphere interactions and re-<lb/>gional climate change, and it is critical to parameterize and <lb/>characterize biogenic MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 across different sea <lb/>areas and identify their sources to constrain the past, current, <lb/>and future climate impacts of both species (Hodshire et al., <lb/>2019; Gondwe et al., 2003). For instance, MSA observations <lb/>from Greenlandic ice cores have been used to study the vari-<lb/>ability in subarctic Atlantic Ocean productivity from decadal <lb/>to centennial timescales (Osman et al., 2019). <lb/>Global aerosol-chemistry-climate general circulation <lb/>models are used widely to assess the radiative forcing of <lb/>DMS-derived aerosols. A negative forcing of between -1.7 <lb/>and -2.3 W m -2 due to the DMS effect is predicted (Fiddes <lb/>et al., 2018; Fung et al., 2022; Thomas et al., 2010; Mahajan <lb/>et al., 2015). This range is comparable to the positive forcing <lb/>impact of anthropogenic CO 2 emissions (1.83 ± 0.2 W m -2 ) <lb/>(Etminan et al., 2016). Large uncertainties in DMS forc-<lb/>ing estimates (up to ±10 W m -2 ) are partly because models <lb/>overlook the high-frequency spatial, temporal, and seasonal <lb/>variability in DMS fluxes (Mansour et al., 2023a; Royer et <lb/>al., 2015; McNabb and Tortell, 2022) as well as consequent <lb/>oxidation products (Riccobono et al., 2014), which are not <lb/>adequately constrained by the available sparse observations <lb/>(Bock et al., 2021). This level of uncertainty underlines the <lb/>need for improved parameterizations of natural sulfur aerosol <lb/>cycling and fluxes at regional scales (Hulswar et al., 2022; <lb/>Galí et al., 2018; Mahajan et al., 2015), which are essential <lb/>to determine their impact on climate. Recently, multilinear <lb/>regression was utilized to simulate monthly MSA over the <lb/>Bohai Sea, Yellow Sea, and East China Sea at a spatial reso-<lb/>lution of 1°× 1°(Zhou et al., 2023), and it was concluded <lb/>that spatial and seasonal patterns of MSA exhibit signifi-<lb/>cant variability, primarily governed by surface phytoplankton <lb/>biomass and the atmospheric boundary layer height. <lb/>Focusing on the North Atlantic (NA), sulfur-containing <lb/>aerosols, MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 , have been measured at Mace <lb/>Head Atmospheric Research Station, a coastal area in the <lb/>eastern NA, to quantify the contribution of phytoplankton <lb/>emissions to aerosol mass concentrations in the MBL (Ri-<lb/>naldi et al., 2010, 2009; O&apos;Dowd et al., 2004), to assess the <lb/>long-term seasonal patterns in the chemical composition of <lb/>submicron aerosol in the different origin of marine air masses <lb/>(Ovadnevaite et al., 2014), and to identify the oceanic re-<lb/>gions acting as the main source of biogenic aerosols (Man-<lb/>sour et al., 2020b). During the North Atlantic Aerosols and <lb/>Marine Ecosystems Study (NAAMES) field campaigns, re-<lb/>search cruises aimed at comprehending the relationships be-<lb/>tween ecosystems, aerosols, and clouds (Behrenfeld et al., <lb/>2019), Saliba et al. (2020) evaluated the origins and contribu-<lb/>tions of submicron organic and sulfate components to CCN <lb/>concentrations in the MBL. They concluded that the DMS-<lb/>derived secondary nss-SO = <lb/>4 enhanced hygroscopicity, parti-<lb/>cle size, and CCN concentrations by 5 %-66 %, especially <lb/>in the spring, highlighting the importance of phytoplankton-<lb/>produced DMS emissions for the CCN budget in the NA <lb/>(Mansour et al., 2022, 2020b; Sanchez et al., 2018). How-<lb/>ever, it is currently challenging to effectively investigate cli-<lb/>matology and long-term trends and climate forcing of bio-<lb/>genic sulfur compounds as well as to validate inherent model <lb/>outputs, as there is a lack of high-temporal-resolution data on <lb/>these compounds. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/></note>

        <page>2719 <lb/></page>

        <body>In this study, we present the first high-resolution, long-<lb/>term daily gridded time series of freshly formed in situ-<lb/>produced biogenic MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 (IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 ) <lb/>concentrations over the NA at a 0.25°× 0.25°spatial reso-<lb/>lution. The data cover 25 years, from 1998 to 2022, with the <lb/>possibility of future year-by-year updates. The dataset is a <lb/>unique and novel product in that it extends the spatial and <lb/>temporal representativeness of atmospheric in situ observa-<lb/>tions of marine aerosol chemical properties over the NA by <lb/>exploiting the potential of machine learning. The dataset rep-<lb/>resents the sea-level concentrations of MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 , in <lb/>each grid point of the domain, resulting from the interplay <lb/>between precursor emissions and local atmospheric condi-<lb/>tions. We created the IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 dataset using in situ <lb/>MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 data measured at the Mace Head (MHD) <lb/>site and during the NAAMES cruises, the gridded dataset <lb/>from the ECMWF ERA5, and reconstructed F DMS (Man-<lb/>sour et al., 2023a) as input data. To achieve this aim, we <lb/>employed the following machine learning (ML) approaches: <lb/>support vector machines (SVMs), decision tree (DT), regres-<lb/>sion ensemble (RE), Gaussian process regression (GPR), and <lb/>artificial neural networks (ANNs). ML has been applied in <lb/>a variety of scientific areas for model approximation, ex-<lb/>periment design, and multivariate regression of oceanic and <lb/>atmospheric complex systems; however, to our knowledge, <lb/>no prior applications to MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 prediction have <lb/>been published. During model training, we evaluated the var-<lb/>ious possible kernel functions and hyperparameters in each <lb/>ML type (details in Table 1), employing the 5-fold cross-<lb/>validation strategy to select the best-performing (optimal) <lb/>function capable of properly predicting MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 . <lb/>A partial dependence analysis is also used to assess the effect <lb/>of different predictors on the modeled MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 . <lb/>Furthermore, we investigate the annual and monthly spatial <lb/>distributions of MSA, nss-SO = <lb/>4 , and the ratio between them <lb/>(MSA : nss-SO = <lb/>4 ) to examine the evolution of MSA and nss-<lb/>SO = <lb/>4 in the different regions of the NA domain from 1998 <lb/>to 2022. The output data (IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 ) from this study <lb/>should be useful for filling the data gap, particularly for the <lb/>NA, and be applicable to a variety of investigations, such as <lb/>climatology, trend analysis, model evaluation, and radiative <lb/>impact assessment, as well as providing boundary conditions <lb/>for regional models. <lb/>2 Study domain and data sources <lb/>2.1 Study area and measurement sites <lb/>The study area extends from 20°to 66°N and from 72°W <lb/>to the prime meridian (Fig. 1), covering the NA. The key <lb/>climate-relevant features in the study domain are the Gulf <lb/>Stream, its northern extension towards Europe known as the <lb/>North Atlantic Current (NAC), and the cyclonic subpolar <lb/>gyre (SPG) (Rhein et al., 2011). The Gulf Stream is a warm <lb/>Atlantic Ocean flow that begins in the Gulf of Mexico and <lb/>moves through the Straits of Florida before continuing up <lb/>the eastern coast of the United States (Buckley and Marshall, <lb/>2016). These warm northward-flowing waters meet the cold <lb/>southward-flowing waters of the Labrador Current and the <lb/>western boundary current of the cyclonic subpolar gyre, ulti-<lb/>mately turning east and heading toward northwestern Europe <lb/>as the NAC. The NAC then splits into multiple branches that <lb/>enter the subpolar gyre, one of which passes via the Iceland <lb/>Basin and the other through the Rockall Trough (Fratantoni, <lb/>2001). The NA SPG extends from 45 to around 65°N and <lb/>comprises the sills between Greenland, Iceland, the Faroe Is-<lb/>lands, and Scotland. Such circulation phenomena are crucial <lb/>for the modulation of the temperate climate of northwest-<lb/>ern Europe (Marzocchi et al., 2015), and the dynamics of <lb/>the SPG determine the rate of deep-and intermediate-water <lb/>formation (sinking dense and cold surface waters through <lb/>air-sea heat exchanges in the wintertime), particularly in the <lb/>Labrador Sea (Katsman et al., 2004). Accordingly, they con-<lb/>tribute to the regional changes in primary production and the <lb/>subsequent biogenic emissions in the study domain. <lb/>The MHD Global Atmosphere Watch (GAW) research sta-<lb/>tion (53.33°N, 09.90°W) is located on Ireland&apos;s west coast <lb/>(Fig. 1), about 80 m from the coastline and 21 m above mean <lb/>sea level. MHD is the only GAW station in the eastern At-<lb/>lantic region; moreover, it is the globally acknowledged clean <lb/>background western European station, providing key base-<lb/>line input for intercomparison with levels elsewhere in Eu-<lb/>rope (Grigas et al., 2017; O&apos;Dowd et al., 2014). <lb/>Four shipboard field campaigns were carried out as part <lb/>of the NAAMES research project (Behrenfeld et al., 2019). <lb/>The tracks of cruises representing marine conditions during <lb/>aerosol sampling (Saliba et al., 2020) are shown in Fig. 1. <lb/>The measurements cover the periods of November 2015, <lb/>May-June 2016, September 2017, and March 2018. Behren-<lb/>feld et al. (2019) provide a thorough explanation of the <lb/>NAAMES project&apos;s goals, objectives, and atmospheric and <lb/>oceanic conditions. <lb/>2.2 Observational data <lb/>Long-term atmospheric concentrations of submicron sulfur <lb/>aerosol species (methanesulfonic acid, MSA, and sulfate, <lb/>SO = <lb/>4 ) from January 2009 to June 2018 measured at MHD <lb/>were used. The measurements were performed using the <lb/>Aerodyne high-resolution time-of-flight aerosol mass spec-<lb/>trometer (HR-ToF-AMS). The HR-ToF-AMS (DeCarlo et <lb/>al., 2006) output has a time resolution of ∼ 5-10 min, and the <lb/>instrument was operated according to the recommendations <lb/>of Jimenez et al. (2003), Allan et al. (2003), and Canagaratna <lb/>et al. (2007). MSA was derived from the concentration of the <lb/>mass fragment CH 3 SO + <lb/>2 (Ovadnevaite et al., 2014). Further <lb/>information on the MSA measurement can be found in Man-<lb/>sour et al. (2020a). The black carbon (BC) concentrations <lb/>were measured in situ at MHD using a multi-angle absorp-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2720 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/></note>

        <body>Table 1. List of machine learning models used in the present study. <lb/>Model type <lb/>Preset <lb/>Hyperparameters <lb/>(if any) <lb/>Support vector <lb/>Linear <lb/>machines <lb/>Quadratic <lb/>Cubic <lb/>Fine Gaussian <lb/>Kernel scale = 0.61 <lb/>Medium Gaussian <lb/>Kernel scale = 2.4 <lb/>Coarse Gaussian <lb/>Kernel scale = 9.8 <lb/>Decision tree <lb/>Fine <lb/>Minimum leaf size = 4 <lb/>Medium <lb/>Minimum leaf size = 12 <lb/>Coarse <lb/>Minimum leaf size = 36 <lb/>Regression ensemble <lb/>Boosted <lb/>Minimum leaf size = 8 <lb/>Number of learners = 30 <lb/>Bagged <lb/>Minimum leaf size = 8 <lb/>Number of learners = 30 <lb/>Gaussian process <lb/>Squared exponential <lb/>regression <lb/>Matern 5/2 <lb/>Exponential <lb/>Rational quadratic <lb/>Artificial neural <lb/>networks <lb/>Narrow <lb/>Number of fully connected layers = 1 <lb/>First layer size = 10 <lb/>Medium <lb/>Number of fully connected layers = 1 <lb/>First layer size = 25 <lb/>Wide <lb/>Number of fully connected layers = 1 <lb/>First layer size = 100 <lb/>Bi-layered <lb/>Number of fully connected layers = 2 <lb/>First layer size = 10 <lb/>2nd layer size = 10 <lb/>Tri-layered <lb/>Number of fully connected layers = 3 <lb/>First layer size = 10 <lb/>Second layer size = 10 <lb/>Third layer size = 10 <lb/>tion photometer (O&apos;Dowd et al., 2014) to identify the anthro-<lb/>pogenically impacted air masses, as detailed in Sect. 3.1.1. <lb/>High-resolution in situ shipborne measurements of non-<lb/>refractory submicron SO = <lb/>4 concentrations were measured ev-<lb/>ery 5 min using HR-ToF-AMS during four open-ocean re-<lb/>search cruises (NAAMES) in the northwestern Atlantic: win-<lb/>ter (November 2015), late spring (May-June 2016), autumn <lb/>(September 2017), and early spring (March 2018) (Saliba <lb/>et al., 2020). We employ this SO = <lb/>4 concentration informa-<lb/>tion (no high-resolution MSA datasets available from the <lb/>NAAMES campaigns) during periods that were largely ma-<lb/>rine aerosol sources, which were defined as periods when <lb/>particle number concentrations were &lt;1500 cm -3 , BC was <lb/>&lt;50 ng m -3 , 2 d back trajectories originated from the North <lb/>Atlantic or tropical Atlantic, and radon concentrations were <lb/>&lt;500 mBq m -3 according to Saliba et al. (2020). The mea-<lb/>sured SO = <lb/>4 from the AMS excludes refractory particles that <lb/>likely contain the majority of sea-salt sulfate; therefore, <lb/>the measured SO = <lb/>4 is approximately equivalent to nss-SO = <lb/>4 <lb/>(Frossard et al., 2014). <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/></note>

        <page>2721 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 1. The study region in the North Atlantic (20-66°N, 72-0°W) with bathymetry presented in meters. The gridded bathymetric dataset <lb/>was extracted from the General Bathymetric Chart of the Oceans (https://www.gebco.net, last access: 25 May 2023) GEBCO_2023 Grid. <lb/>The green pentagram represents the Mace Head measuring station on the west coast of Ireland, the dark-red points are the sampling points <lb/>that represent marine conditions in the NAAMES cruises track, and the violet points represent the ship track during Polarstern campaigns. <lb/>2.3 Air mass back trajectories <lb/>The National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration <lb/>(NOAA) Air Resources Laboratory (ARL) developed the <lb/>Hybrid Single-Particle Lagrangian Integrated Trajectory <lb/>(HYSPLIT4) model (Rolph et al., 2017; Stein et al., 2015), <lb/>which is used to calculate the air mass back trajecto-<lb/>ries (BTs). The archived Global Data Assimilation System <lb/>(GDAS1; 1°× 1°) of the National Centers for Environmental <lb/>Prediction (NCEP) was used as a driver of the trajectory cal-<lb/>culation (ftp://arlftp.arlhq.noaa.gov/pub/archives/gdas1, last <lb/>access: 10 November 2022). We ran the model at the MHD <lb/>sampling station as a fixed source location, whereas the <lb/>NAAMES cruises were run as a moving source location. The <lb/>starting height was set to 100 m above ground level, and the <lb/>backward time was 3 d with an interval of 1 h along each en-<lb/>tire trajectory track. The schematic diagram of BT calcula-<lb/>tion is shown in Fig. S1. The arrival frequency of BTs at <lb/>MHD is 3 h (8 tracks a day), covering the period from 1 Jan-<lb/>uary 2009 to 30 June 2018, whereas the arrival frequency of <lb/>NAAMES is hourly (24 tracks a day), covering the time of <lb/>the four campaigns identified as marine periods (Saliba et al., <lb/>2020). <lb/>2.4 Dimethylsulfide flux data <lb/>Seawater DMS is the primary contributor to biogenic sulfur <lb/>aerosol in the atmosphere. For this reason, we use the sea-<lb/>to-air DMS flux (F DMS ) as a predictor of MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 <lb/>concentrations. Mansour et al. (2023a) used an ML predic-<lb/>tive algorithm based on Gaussian process regression (GPR) <lb/>to simulate the distribution of daily seawater DMS concen-<lb/>trations and related F DMS in the NA areas from 35 to 66°N <lb/>and from 0 to 55°W at a 0.25°× 0.25°spatial resolution. We <lb/>extended the GPR model within the NA to encompass the <lb/>NAAMES measurements, which are essential because they <lb/>cover the westernmost section of the study area. Figure S2 <lb/>displays the main differences between the two domains. Sim-<lb/>ply, the GPR was trained once more, utilizing the same ap-<lb/>proach as that outlined in Mansour et al. (2023a), with a <lb/>higher number of data points, and it yielded an enhanced R 2 <lb/>value up to 0.77 on the independent test dataset. The daily <lb/>sea-to-air F DMS was calculated using the gas transfer veloc-<lb/>ity (Goddijn-Murphy et al., 2012) and the DMS derived from <lb/>GPR predictions. For more details about the data product, we <lb/>refer the reader to Mansour et al. (2023a). <lb/>2.5 Meteorological data <lb/>The ECMWF ERA5 reanalysis data (Hersbach et al., 2020) <lb/>were downloaded to extract the meteorological parameters <lb/>used as predictors of MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 in the ML mod-<lb/>els. ERA5 provides estimates for the hourly state of the at-<lb/>mosphere, worldwide, with a 0.25°× 0.25°spatial resolution <lb/>at the surface and different pressure levels. From the global <lb/>domain, we extracted multiple atmospheric components, in-<lb/>cluding air temperature at 2 m above sea level (AT) and sur-<lb/>face net shortwave radiation flux (SRF), as representative of <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2722 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/></note>

        <body>thermal heating, and the relative humidity (RH), as represen-<lb/>tative of water vapor abundance in the atmosphere. To rep-<lb/>resent the dispersion of aerosol particles in the troposphere <lb/>and wet removal through the below-cloud scavenging pro-<lb/>cess, the boundary layer height (BLH) and the precipitation <lb/>rate (PR) were utilized, respectively. <lb/>3 Methods <lb/>3.1 Data preparation <lb/>In this section, we describe the preparation of predictors and <lb/>responses that were used to train, cross-validate, and generate <lb/>the ML models. <lb/>3.1.1 Air mass selection <lb/>In previous studies (Mansour et al., 2020b; O&apos;Dowd et al., <lb/>2015; Ovadnevaite et al., 2014), the BC concentration has of-<lb/>ten been considered to be a useful tool to select clean marine <lb/>air masses excluding inputs from continental emissions or <lb/>ship trails. In this study, we still relied on BC measurements <lb/>as a precious tool to identify and exclude anthropogenically <lb/>impacted air masses, but we also developed a more complete <lb/>approach aimed at identifying air masses characterized by a <lb/>high degree of contact with the ocean surface. This was nec-<lb/>essary in order to select, from the in situ observations, data <lb/>points representing almost entirely oceanic sources to pro-<lb/>vide the best dataset for training the ML models. <lb/>The retention ratio of the air mass over the ocean (R O ) was <lb/>calculated to determine whether an air mass (identified by BT <lb/>track) arriving at the MHD sampling station or at the ship lo-<lb/>cation, in the case of shipborne measurements, was primarily <lb/>from the NA region or not. We used 3 d BTs arriving 100 m <lb/>above the MHD sampling station and NAAMES tracks. The <lb/>BT tracks at the MHD arrival point were calculated 8 times <lb/>per day, whereas they were calculated 24 times per day at <lb/>NAAMES measuring points, considering only the measure-<lb/>ments classified as marine periods (Saliba et al., 2020). The <lb/>R O was calculated for each track as follows: <lb/>R O = <lb/>N Ocean <lb/>i=1 e <lb/>-t i <lb/>72 <lb/>N Total <lb/>i=1 e <lb/>-t i <lb/>72 <lb/>, <lb/>(1) <lb/>where N Total is the total number of trajectory endpoints, <lb/>which is equal to 73 (arrival point + 72 backward hours); <lb/>N Ocean is the total number of trajectory endpoints passing <lb/>over the ocean; and t i is the backward-tracking time, with the <lb/>unit of hours and spanning values from 0 to 72. Because air <lb/>mass diffusion and particle deposition potentially occur dur-<lb/>ing the air mass transport, a weighting factor e -t i /72 related <lb/>to tracking time has been introduced. The weighting factor <lb/>takes values from 1 (at the arrival point) up to 0.37 (farthest <lb/>point); hence, oceanic areas far from the arrival point, cor-<lb/>responding to longer backward-tracking time, have a weaker <lb/>influence than areas closer to the sampling point. As a re-<lb/>sult, a higher R O value implies that oceanic emissions have <lb/>a greater influence on the air mass and that the source re-<lb/>gion is more likely to be the ocean. Other studies have used <lb/>similar methods to characterize air mass source regions. For <lb/>example, Zhou et al. (2021) studied the contribution of non-<lb/>marine MSA sources in the coastal East China Sea and the <lb/>Gulf of Aqaba by characterizing the land air masses. Rinaldi <lb/>et al. (2021) used a combination of low-traveling air mass <lb/>BTs and satellite ground-type maps to investigate the effect <lb/>of ground conditions (sea ice, snow, seawater, and land) on <lb/>air samples at Ny-Ålesund station in the Arctic Ocean. <lb/>Because oceanic air masses crossing the NA can pass <lb/>above the BLH, its connection to local sea surface pro-<lb/>cesses, such as marine biogenic emission and subsequent at-<lb/>mospheric reactions, may be significantly weaker. To address <lb/>this issue, Eq. (2) was used to calculate the retention ratio of <lb/>an ocean air mass within the marine boundary layer (R B ). <lb/>R B = <lb/>N Below <lb/>i=1 e <lb/>-t i <lb/>72 <lb/>N Ocean <lb/>i=1 e <lb/>-t i <lb/>72 <lb/>, <lb/>(2) <lb/>where N Ocean is the total number of trajectory endpoints lo-<lb/>cated over the ocean (i.e., marine endpoints) and N Below is <lb/>the number of marine endpoints with an altitude below the <lb/>BLH. The higher the R B value, the more airflow over the <lb/>ocean is confined to the MBL. The BLH datasets at each end-<lb/>point were extracted from the hourly ERA5 dataset. <lb/>The total number of BT tracks arriving at MHD during the <lb/>period from January 2009 to June 2018 is 27 744 (3468 d × 8 <lb/>tracks per day). We counted the number of endpoints of all <lb/>BTs in each 1°× 1°grid cell and normalized them to the <lb/>maximum value to find the percentage of endpoints for all <lb/>grid cells (Fig. S3). The larger density of BT endpoints is <lb/>concentrated over the NA oceanic region, indicating that the <lb/>main source regions for air masses transported to MHD sam-<lb/>pling stations are most likely oceanic. At MHD, we inves-<lb/>tigated how MSA (a marine biogenic tracer) responds to <lb/>change in BC (a tracer of anthropogenic input), as seen in <lb/>Fig. S4, by considering hourly data simultaneous to the ar-<lb/>rival time of BTs (i.e., 8 times a day). We found that MSA <lb/>tends to fluctuate minimally when BC is less than 15 ng m -3 <lb/>(slope = 0.05), whereas MSA tends to rise slightly when BC <lb/>exceeds 15 ng m -3 (slope = 0.28). Such cases with hourly <lb/>BC concentrations &lt;15 ng m -3 were classified as represen-<lb/>tative of marine conditions, which are likely not influenced <lb/>by anthropogenic sources. To constrain the impact of marine <lb/>biogenic emissions and meteorological parameters on MSA <lb/>and nss-SO = <lb/>4 , air masses were included in this analysis only <lb/>if they were characterized by R O + R B ≥ 1.75, meaning that <lb/>the air mass had experienced a high degree of contact with <lb/>the ocean surface within the last 3 d (Fig. S4). Indeed, con-<lb/>sidering the above condition, an air mass must have an R O <lb/>equal to at least 0.75 and, in such case, the track must be trav-<lb/>eling below the BLH 100 % of the time. By introducing the <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/></note>

        <page>2723 <lb/></page>

        <body>criterion of R O + R B ≥ 1.75, approximately 72 % of the BT <lb/>tracks were considered. This reflects the significance of the <lb/>MHD research station for studying NA biogenic emissions as <lb/>well as the frequency with which it is impacted by MBL air <lb/>masses (Grigas et al., 2017; O&apos;Dowd et al., 2014). After con-<lb/>sidering the BC threshold (&lt;15 ng m -3 ) and conservatively <lb/>removing all of the observations done when the BC data were <lb/>unavailable (instrument downtime), 9211 (33 % of the total) <lb/>tracks were classified as representative of marine conditions <lb/>(selected marine BTs frequency is presented in Fig. S5). <lb/>Regarding the NAAMES measurements, the total num-<lb/>ber of calculated BT tracks was 832 (Fig. S6) during back-<lb/>ground marine conditions, identified by Saliba et al. (2020). <lb/>In this study, we kept 660 tracks (Fig. S7) of the above <lb/>832 as representative samples of marine conditions during <lb/>NAAMES cruises by limiting the analysis to hourly samples <lb/>with R O + R B ≥ 1.75. <lb/>3.1.2 Predictor extraction along back trajectories <lb/>In order to train the ML models, it was necessary to asso-<lb/>ciate each observed MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 data point with the <lb/>corresponding potential predictors. The potential predictors <lb/>(F DMS , AT, SRF, RH, BLH, and PR) were extracted at each <lb/>endpoint of the BTs associated with each of the selected <lb/>clean marine observational data points (see Sect. 3.1.1), <lb/>inside the oceanic region within 20-66°N and 0-72°W <lb/>(Fig. S1). The extracted predictor values were then averaged <lb/>along each marine BT track, providing the most representa-<lb/>tive picture of the conditions (air mass history) that led to <lb/>the formation of the observed sulfur aerosol concentrations. <lb/>The few endpoints over land or crossing above the BLH were <lb/>eliminated. <lb/>The Pearson correlation coefficients between the poten-<lb/>tial predictors and observational MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 data <lb/>were compared, considering different BT lengths of 1, 2, <lb/>and 3 d, to assess which BT length was more representative <lb/>of the timescale of sulfur aerosol formation processes. As <lb/>seen from Table 2, both MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 correlate better <lb/>with F DMS considering a 3 d BT length. Similarly, the ma-<lb/>jority of the other predictors, except for AT, tended to maxi-<lb/>mize their correlations considering a 2 or 3 d BT length. Ulti-<lb/>mately, for each predictor, we considered the BT length that <lb/>maximized the correlation coefficient for the analyses in the <lb/>present study. <lb/>3.1.3 Responses at measuring sites <lb/>Hourly nss-SO = <lb/>4 at MHD and from the NAAMES campaigns <lb/>as well as MSA at MHD, measured concurrently with the se-<lb/>lected marine BTs (Sect. 3.3.1), were used to build ML mod-<lb/>els. A total of 6162 (6920) data points for MSA (nss-SO = <lb/>4 ) <lb/>were obtained. Furthermore, we also applied a 0.1 and 99.9 <lb/>percentile lower and upper threshold filter to remove the ex-<lb/>tremely low and high values that could bias the ML models&apos; <lb/>training and cross-validation. This helped to identify and re-<lb/>move outliers in each dataset, thereby reducing the number of <lb/>data points to 6150 (6905) for MSA (nss-SO = <lb/>4 ) (∼ 0.2 % of <lb/>data points were rejected). Details of the MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 <lb/>percentile thresholds, along with the number of data before <lb/>and after applying the filters are given in Table 3. The hourly <lb/>data after cleanup are used for training/cross-validation and <lb/>testing of ML models. <lb/>3.2 Machine learning models <lb/>The methodological flowchart of the present study is shown <lb/>in Fig. 2. The core of the framework uses supervised ML re-<lb/>gression techniques to build predictive models for estimat-<lb/>ing the atmospheric concentrations of biogenic MSA and <lb/>nss-SO = <lb/>4 (responses) from independent variables (predic-<lb/>tors). Predictors include the sea-to-air F DMS and meteorolog-<lb/>ical parameters that control the aerosol concentration in the <lb/>MBL. We used multilinear regression to assess the contribu-<lb/>tion of each predictor to MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 variations. Ini-<lb/>tially, we ran the multilinear regression model using the total <lb/>of the following potential six predictors: F DMS , AT, SRF, RH, <lb/>BLH, and PR. Secondly, we applied the multilinear regres-<lb/>sion models by eliminating one predictor each time. Each in-<lb/>dependent variable&apos;s contribution to R 2 is the reduction in to-<lb/>tal R 2 when that variable is eliminated. The results (Table 4) <lb/>showed that the six predictors used can explain up to 74 % <lb/>(53 %) of MSA (nss-SO = <lb/>4 ) variance. Such predictors tend to <lb/>contribute differently to MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 . SRF, F DMS , and <lb/>the BLH are the most effective parameters for MSA (explain-<lb/>ing up to 64 % of the variability), while SRF, AT, and F DMS <lb/>are the most influential with respect to nss-SO = <lb/>4 (explaining <lb/>up to 44 % of the variability). RH has a minor contribution to <lb/>the MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 variance. To know if a predictor con-<lb/>tributes significantly to the explained variance, we performed <lb/>an analysis of variance (ANOVA) on the implemented mul-<lb/>tilinear regression model. The ANOVA revealed that all of <lb/>the tested predictors have statistically significant (p&lt;0.05) <lb/>contributions to MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 . For these reasons, we <lb/>applied the ML models using all six potential predictors. <lb/>The datasets, containing the corresponding predictors <lb/>and each one of the responses (MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 ) sep-<lb/>arately, were split randomly into two subsets, defined as <lb/>the training/cross-validation set and the test/evaluation set, <lb/>for each response. The training/cross-validation sets include <lb/>80 % of the total points (n = 4920 for MSA and n = 5524 for <lb/>nss-SO = <lb/>4 ), while the test/evaluation sets comprise the remain-<lb/>ing 20 % (n = 1230 for MSA and n = 1381 for nss-SO = <lb/>4 ). <lb/>To improve ML algorithms&apos; accuracy and protect against <lb/>overfitting, a k-fold cross-validation strategy with k = 5 was <lb/>used, as this has been shown to provide maximal model <lb/>prediction robustness and minimal bias (Rodriguez et al., <lb/>2010; Fushiki, 2011). The k-fold cross-validation is a pro-<lb/>cedure used to estimate the skill of the model on new data <lb/>and generally results in a less biased estimate of the model <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2724 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/></note>

        <body>Table 2. The Pearson coefficients between possible predictors for the selected marine air masses and the in situ observed MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 <lb/>concentrations. The MSA, nss-SO = <lb/>4 , and F DMS values are used on a log scale. All values are statistically significant at p&lt;0.05, except the <lb/>value indicated by &quot;*&quot;. Bold text denotes the maximum during different days of air mass history. <lb/>Predictors BT length (in days) <lb/>MSA <lb/>nss-SO = <lb/>4 <lb/>MHD <lb/>MHD NAAMES <lb/>F DMS <lb/>0 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.24 0.04 * <lb/>1 <lb/>0.64 <lb/>0.53 0.24 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.66 <lb/>0.54 0.38 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.69 <lb/>0.55 0.47 <lb/>AT <lb/>0 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>0.61 0.17 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.57 <lb/>0.56 0.29 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.53 <lb/>0.53 0.35 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.53 <lb/>0.51 0.37 <lb/>RH <lb/>0 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.15 0.27 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.33 <lb/>0.27 0.22 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.39 <lb/>0.31 0.24 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.44 <lb/>0.33 0.28 <lb/>PR <lb/>0 -0.18 -0.12 -0.09 <lb/>1 -0.27 -0.26 -0.27 <lb/>2 -0.33 -0.31 -0.34 <lb/>3 -0.35 -0.33 -0.32 <lb/>BLH <lb/>0 -0.41 -0.32 -0.32 <lb/>1 -0.53 -0.45 -0.34 <lb/>2 -0.58 -0.49 -0.36 <lb/>3 -0.60 -0.49 -0.35 <lb/>SRF <lb/>0 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>0.23 0.14 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.73 <lb/>0.61 0.53 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.77 <lb/>0.65 0.62 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.78 <lb/>0.67 0.63 <lb/>Table 3. Details of the number of hourly (MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 ) data points corresponding to selected marine BTs. The threshold used for <lb/>filtering outlier values and the number of data points after filtering are given. <lb/>Response No. of hourly <lb/>Lower threshold <lb/>Upper threshold <lb/>No. of data lost <lb/>No. of hourly data <lb/>data points <lb/>according to the 0.1 according to the 99.9 <lb/>due to filtering points after cleanup <lb/>percentile <lb/>percentile <lb/>MSA <lb/>Source: MHD <lb/>0.0001 µg m -3 <lb/>0.45 µg m -3 <lb/>12 <lb/>6150 <lb/>n = 6162 <lb/>nss-SO = <lb/>4 <lb/>Source: MHD <lb/>0.006 µg m -3 <lb/>2.116 µg m -3 <lb/>12 <lb/>6905 <lb/>n = 6260 <lb/>Source: NAAMES 0.007 µg m -3 <lb/>1.107 µg m -3 <lb/>3 <lb/>n = 660 <lb/>skill. The k-fold number refers to how many groups a given <lb/>data sample is to be split into. In this study, where k = 5, <lb/>the training/cross-validation dataset was further randomly di-<lb/>vided into five folds of roughly equal size. For each trial, one <lb/>group is designated as a holdout or validation dataset, while <lb/>the remaining four groups are designated as training data <lb/>(Fig. 2). The model is then fit on the training set (four folds) <lb/>and evaluated on the validation set (last fold), and the av-<lb/>erage evaluation measures (accuracy) on the validation sub-<lb/>sets of the five iterations are reported. To better examine the <lb/>model&apos;s repeatability on a new independent dataset, the gen-<lb/>erated models were evaluated on the test data that were not <lb/>included in the model construction. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/></note>

        <page>2725 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 2. The methodology&apos;s workflow, showing the predictor and response variable data preparation, the overall framework for the genera-<lb/>tion and development of the trained models (including a schematic diagram of 5-fold cross-validation, model export and validation details), <lb/>and post-processing analysis. <lb/>Table 4. Multilinear regression of MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 as a function of predictors. The MSA, nss-SO = <lb/>4 , and F DMS values are used on a log <lb/>scale. Each independent variable&apos;s contribution to R 2 is the decrease in total R 2 when that variable is eliminated. Individual R 2 contributions <lb/>are normalized and added together to equal the overall R 2 . According to the analysis of variance (ANOVA) on the multilinear regression <lb/>models, all predictors have a statistically significant (p&lt;0.05) contribution to the MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 variance. <lb/>Total explained <lb/>Normalized contribution to R 2 (%) <lb/>variance by R 2 <lb/>AT <lb/>RH <lb/>PR BLH <lb/>SRF F DMS <lb/>MSA <lb/>74.36 % <lb/>6.86 0.47 2.82 <lb/>8.66 42.77 <lb/>12.97 <lb/>nss-SO = <lb/>4 <lb/>53.39 % 11.64 0.55 5.07 <lb/>3.63 25.83 <lb/>6.66 <lb/>Five types of ML models were trained/cross-validated and <lb/>evaluated to identify the best-performing model with respect <lb/>to estimating sulfur aerosol concentrations (MSA and nss-<lb/>SO = <lb/>4 ). The ML algorithms are SVM, DT, RE, GPR, and <lb/>ANN. These are the most common types of algorithms; how-<lb/>ever, there are subtypes for which advanced options and op-<lb/>timizations in the model can increase the performance and <lb/>resilience of the algorithms. In general, each supervised ML <lb/>model performs differently and has various strengths and <lb/>shortcomings. Finding the proper ML algorithm is largely <lb/>based on trial and error; even experienced data scientists can-<lb/>not anticipate if an algorithm will work without testing it. <lb/>Thus, understanding the fundamentals of various ML algo-<lb/>rithms and their applicability to diverse applications is criti-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2726 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/></note>

        <body>cal (Sarker et al., 2019). As a result, we initially assessed 20 <lb/>algorithms belonging to the aforementioned five types and <lb/>chose the model with the best performance skill from each <lb/>type (Table 1), as detailed in the following sections. <lb/>3.2.1 Support vector machines (SVMs) <lb/>A SVM is a powerful mathematical model based on the sta-<lb/>tistical learning theory (Vapnik, 2013) that can be used either <lb/>for classification or regression analysis. In recent decades, <lb/>SVMs have demonstrated high prediction accuracy for a <lb/>wide range of regression problems in fields such as oceanog-<lb/>raphy, meteorology, and atmospheric sciences (Lins et al., <lb/>2013; Sachindra et al., 2018; Shabani et al., 2020; Shrestha <lb/>and Shukla, 2015; Fan et al., 2018). The SVM model es-<lb/>timates the regression using a series of kernel functions <lb/>that are capable of implicitly converting the original, lower-<lb/>dimensional input data to a higher-dimensional feature space. <lb/>To achieve the best prediction accuracy for MSA and nss-<lb/>SO = <lb/>4 , we assessed the different SVM kernel functions, such <lb/>as linear, polynomial (quadratic and cubic), and Gaussian <lb/>(Table 1). The Gaussian kernel was adopted by trying var-<lb/>ious kernel scales, setting them to 0.61 (fine), 2.4 (medium), <lb/>and 9.8 (coarse). For more information on SVMs, the reader <lb/>is referred to https://www.mathworks.com/help/stats/fitrsvm. <lb/>html (last access: 10 January 2023). <lb/>3.2.2 Decision tree (DT) <lb/>The DT model is a nonparametric, nonlinear model that gen-<lb/>erates a structure resembling a tree for classification and re-<lb/>gression (Kotsiantis, 2013; Quinlan, 1986). It repeatedly di-<lb/>vides the dataset into smaller subsets based on independent <lb/>features from the input dataset. The split seeks to reduce vari-<lb/>ability within each group while increasing the variance be-<lb/>tween subsets. The final tree is made up of decision and leaf <lb/>nodes. The decision node represents a condition on an at-<lb/>tribute, and its branches indicate the conditions&apos; outcomes. <lb/>For additional information on DT, the reader is directed to <lb/>https://www.mathworks.com/help/stats/fitrtree.html (last ac-<lb/>cess: 10 January 2023). The critical parameter in this tech-<lb/>nique is determining when to terminate the division process. <lb/>In this study, we set up three different minimum leaf sizes <lb/>(minimum samples to split) to control the number of data <lb/>that should be in the sub-branch to continue the splitting pro-<lb/>cess, namely 4 (fine tree), 12 (medium tree), and 36 (coarse <lb/>tree), as seen in Table 1. <lb/>3.2.3 Regression ensemble (RE) <lb/>RE is a technique that employs a collection of DT models <lb/>(referred to as weak learners or base models), each of which <lb/>is produced by applying a learning process to a specific prob-<lb/>lem and then combining them to provide the final prediction <lb/>(Mendes-Moreira et al., 2012). The performance and accu-<lb/>racy of ensembles are determined by the aggregation of weak <lb/>learners (Hengl et al., 2018). The well-known types of ag-<lb/>gregation are the bagging and boosting methods (Breiman, <lb/>2001). In the bagging method (also known as bootstrap ag-<lb/>gregating), the base models are generated using random sub-<lb/>samples drawn from the original dataset with the bootstrap <lb/>sampling method, where some original examples appear sev-<lb/>eral times, whereas others do not appear at all. On the other <lb/>hand, the main idea of the boosting method is that it is possi-<lb/>ble to convert a base model that performs slightly better into <lb/>one that arbitrarily achieves high accuracy. This conversion <lb/>is performed by combining the estimations of several pre-<lb/>dictors. For more information on RE, the reader is referred <lb/>to https://www.mathworks.com/help/stats/fitrensemble.html <lb/>(last access: 10 January 2023). <lb/>3.2.4 Gaussian process regression (GPR) <lb/>GPR is a nonparametric technique for solving nonlinear re-<lb/>gression problems (Williams and Rasmussen, 1996) that is <lb/>based on Bayesian theory and statistical learning theory. The <lb/>accuracy of GPR is dependent on the adopted kernel (co-<lb/>variance) functions (Verrelst et al., 2016). We assessed the <lb/>different base kernel functions, namely exponential, Matern <lb/>5/2, squared exponential, and rational quadratic (Asante-<lb/>Okyere et al., 2018; Mansour et al., 2023a) to determine <lb/>the optimal covariance function that could produce reliable <lb/>predictions of MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 . For more information <lb/>on GPR, the reader is referred to Mansour et al. (2023a) <lb/>and https://www.mathworks.com/help/stats/fitrgp.html (last <lb/>access: 10 January 2023). <lb/>3.2.5 Artificial neural networks (ANNs) <lb/>An ANN is an information processing system that can be <lb/>used to understand the complex nonlinear relationship be-<lb/>tween the response and predictors (Kalogirou, 2001). It con-<lb/>sists of interconnected groups of artificial neurons that work <lb/>in the same way as biological neurons. The ANN structure <lb/>comprises three distinctive groups called input (corresponds <lb/>to the predictors), several hidden layers (fully connected), <lb/>and output (corresponds to the predicted response values). <lb/>The input introduces data to the ANN model, the hidden <lb/>layer processes the data, and the results are produced in the <lb/>output. Further details on ANNs can be found at https://www. <lb/>mathworks.com/help/stats/fitrnet.html (last access: 10 Jan-<lb/>uary 2023). We trained various types of ANNs as single-layer <lb/>(number of fully connected layers = 1), bi-layered (number <lb/>of fully connected layers = 2), and tri-layered (number of <lb/>fully connected layers = 3) neural networks, as detailed in <lb/>Table 1. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/></note>

        <page>2727 <lb/></page>

        <body>3.3 Evaluation measures <lb/>In this study, we use different validation metrics to evalu-<lb/>ate the ML models&apos; performance. Each of the metrics is cal-<lb/>culated using &quot;residuals&quot;. Residuals are the differences be-<lb/>tween the observed data points O i and the predicted values <lb/>P i , where i = 1, 2, . . .n; here, n refers to the number of ob-<lb/>servations. Better models with respect to predicting the re-<lb/>sponse have residuals close to zero. The average magnitude <lb/>of the residuals is called mean absolute error (MAE): <lb/>MAE = <lb/>1 <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>i=1 |O i -P i | . <lb/>(3) <lb/>Regression models tend to use the square of the residuals <lb/>instead of the absolute. The square root of the average of <lb/>the squared residuals is called the root-mean-square error <lb/>(RMSE). A low RMSE denotes confidence that the model <lb/>has relatively few large errors. <lb/>RMSE = <lb/>1 <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>i (P i -O i ) 2 <lb/>(4) <lb/>The metrics listed in Eqs. (3) and (4) can only provide in-<lb/>formation on how a model compares to observations and/or <lb/>other models. Neither can objectively say whether a model <lb/>is a good fit for the data. Comparing a model to a simple <lb/>baseline model is a different approach. This is the motiva-<lb/>tion behind the use of the coefficient of determination (R 2 ) <lb/>metric (Eq. 5). R 2 is the relative difference in the total error <lb/>obtained by fitting a model, resulting in a value of between 0 <lb/>and 1. If a model fits the data well, the model error is small <lb/>and R 2 will be close to 1, and vice versa. <lb/>R 2 <lb/>= 1 -<lb/>n <lb/>i (O i -P i ) 2 <lb/>n <lb/>i (O i -O i ) 2 <lb/>, <lb/>(5) <lb/>where O i is the average of observations. The predicted-<lb/>observed linear slope is the last metric used to evaluate the <lb/>performance of ML models. It determines the rate of change <lb/>in the predicted variable concerning the observed variable <lb/>and should be close to unity for skilled model predictions. <lb/>4 Results and discussion <lb/>4.1 Evaluation of ML model performance <lb/>As a first step, we assessed different possible hyperparam-<lb/>eter optimizations in each of the five types of ML models <lb/>used (SVM, DT, RE, GPR, and ANN) to determine which <lb/>one had the best fit and lower errors for sulfur aerosol (MSA <lb/>and nss-SO = <lb/>4 ) predictability. We chose the best model with <lb/>the lowest errors in each type for further evaluation and anal-<lb/>ysis based on the evaluation measures (RMSE, MAE, and <lb/>R 2 ). The evaluation measures are summarized in Table S1. <lb/>The medium Gaussian SVM, which utilizes a Gaussian ker-<lb/>nel scale equal to the square root of the number of predictors <lb/>(2.4), displayed better performance. The coarse DT, which <lb/>sets the minimum sample size to split equal to 36; the ensem-<lb/>ble bagged trees (EBT) of a bootstrap aggregated ensemble; <lb/>and the GPR, which employs the rational quadratic kernel, <lb/>represent the minimum errors. Finally, a medium ANN of <lb/>layer size 25 with one fully connected layer was selected. <lb/>The five best-performing (optimal) models were exported <lb/>and saved so that they could be used to make new predic-<lb/>tions on a new dataset. <lb/>Figures 3a-e and 4a-e present a detailed comparison be-<lb/>tween observed and predicted MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 , respec-<lb/>tively, for the five optimal ML models developed. When <lb/>compared with the multilinear regression (Table 4), it is clear <lb/>that ML models can generally reconstruct the observations <lb/>with a markedly higher R 2 value, which means that the se-<lb/>lected ML approaches capture much more of the observed <lb/>MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 variability. While the five applied opti-<lb/>mal algorithms have quasi-similar measures, the best model <lb/>for predicting MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 is GPR. For hourly MSA <lb/>(nss-SO = <lb/>4 ), GPR achieves the highest R 2 value of 0.79 (0.64) <lb/>and the lowest RMSE of 0.362 (0.282) for the cross-validated <lb/>data (average measures of each validation fold). When ex-<lb/>tending this to the test data, the R 2 and RMSE reach 0.81 <lb/>(0.67) and 0.347 (0.272), respectively. The EBT comes sec-<lb/>ond in terms of performance with respect to predicting MSA <lb/>(nss-SO = <lb/>4 ) with an R 2 of 0.80 (0.64) for the independent test <lb/>data. The SVM and ANN achieve a reasonable accuracy with <lb/>a respective R 2 value of 0.79 (0.61) and 0.78 (0.60) for MSA <lb/>(nss-SO = <lb/>4 ) based on the test data. Lastly, based on the hourly <lb/>test data, DT shows the lowest, although still respectable, ac-<lb/>curacy with an R 2 of 0.76 for MSA and of 0.57 for nss-SO = <lb/>4 . <lb/>Importantly, the implemented ML models can reconstruct <lb/>MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 daily time series&apos; characteristics with re-<lb/>markable consistency between observed and predicted data, <lb/>except for extremely high and low concentrations. This is <lb/>mostly due to the low probability of such concentrations in <lb/>the observed dataset, which inhibits ML models from re-<lb/>constructing them. The quantitative comprehension of ex-<lb/>ceptional emission extremes is not addressed in this study; <lb/>nonetheless, their occurrence and possible implications de-<lb/>serve to be investigated in future studies. It is worth noting <lb/>that the daily averages of MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 have been cal-<lb/>culated from the validation folds and the test set. The MAE <lb/>of GPR is close to 0.014 (0.100) µg m -3 for MSA (nss-SO = <lb/>4 ). <lb/>The MAE values of EBT, SVM, ANN, and DT are higher <lb/>than those of GPR. According to the R 2 , the ranking order is <lb/>the same as for the MAE, i.e., GPR outperforms EBT, SVM, <lb/>ANN, and DT for both MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 , although the dif-<lb/>ferences in the R 2 values of the five models are small. An <lb/>in-depth look at the MAE and R 2 from MHD and NAAMES <lb/>(Fig. 4, right panels) demonstrates that the ML models per-<lb/>form well with respect to predicting nss-SO = <lb/>4 across different <lb/>datasets. All five models show relatively high R 2 values for <lb/>the NAAMES dataset. EBT, SVM, and ANN have R 2 values <lb/>that are similar (equal to 0.81), whilst GPR has the highest <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2728 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 3. Comparison of predicted and observed MSA on the hourly (left panels) and daily (right panels) scales: (a) GPR, (b) EBT, (c) <lb/>SVM, (d) ANN, and (e) DT. The validation and test data subsets are used to compute the model&apos;s performance. R 2 and RMSE are computed <lb/>in a logarithmic space, whereas MAE is computed on a normal scale. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/></note>

        <page>2729 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 4. Comparison of predicted and observed nss-SO = <lb/>4 on the hourly (left panels) and daily (right panels) scales: (a) GPR, (b) EBT, (c) <lb/>SVM, (d) ANN, and (e) DT. The validation and test data subsets are used to compute the model&apos;s performance. R 2 and RMSE are computed <lb/>in a logarithmic space, whereas MAE is computed on a normal scale. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2730 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/></note>

        <body>R 2 value (reaching 0.87) and DT has the lowest (0.72). In <lb/>essence, the performance metrics indicate that GPR always <lb/>has the highest accuracy and lowest errors, reflecting the ro-<lb/>bustness of GPR. Therefore, GPR was selected as the optimal <lb/>regressor for further analysis in this study. <lb/>Knowing that the GPR model could be biased due to the <lb/>inhomogeneous distribution of in situ observations, we as-<lb/>sessed the applicability of the GPR model in regions poorly <lb/>covered by atmospheric observational data (such as the cen-<lb/>tral part of the domain) by running the model in a worst-<lb/>case scenario deployment. In this exercise, we predicted <lb/>the daily variations in nss-SO = <lb/>4 measurements in the west-<lb/>ernmost portion of the study area by training the model <lb/>using only observations from the eastern part of the do-<lb/>main (i.e., data collected at MHD). In this case, MHD <lb/>data were used for training/cross-validation, while the four <lb/>NAAMES campaigns were employed as independent test <lb/>data. The evaluation on the test data (Fig. S8) revealed that <lb/>GPR can explain 55 % of the daily observed nss-SO = <lb/>4 vari-<lb/>ance (MAE = 0.129 µg m -3 ), even in this worst-case sce-<lb/>nario and on a limited test dataset (n = 57). This more-than-<lb/>acceptable model performance supports the reliability of the <lb/>IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 dataset in the central part of the NA, where <lb/>measurements of MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 are missing. In addition, <lb/>Sect. 4.5 describes the validation of the GPR model with re-<lb/>spect to predicting observed MSA concentrations during the <lb/>Polarstern campaigns, which were not included in either the <lb/>model training/cross-validation or in the model test. <lb/>4.2 Partial dependence analysis <lb/>Most ML models are referred to as &quot;black box&quot; models, as <lb/>the internal computations inside multiple operational layers <lb/>in a model are concealed, and most systems have only ob-<lb/>servable inputs and outputs out of the box. A partial depen-<lb/>dence analysis (Friedman, 2001) is used to assess how pre-<lb/>dictors influence ML model output and shows whether the <lb/>relationship between the response and any of the features <lb/>is linear, monotonic, or more complex. The method entails <lb/>altering one feature and constraining the remaining features <lb/>to unaltered average values to illustrate the marginal effect <lb/>of the changed feature on the expected outcome. The par-<lb/>tial dependence plots of MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 as a function of <lb/>the predictors in the best-performing GPR model are shown <lb/>in Fig. 5; these plots indicate that the interactions between <lb/>predictors and response are generally complex. MSA and <lb/>nss-SO = <lb/>4 levels tend to rise as F DMS levels rise from 3 to <lb/>10 µmol m -2 d -1 . MSA continues to rise with stronger F DMS <lb/>emission rates (&gt;10 µmol m -2 d -1 ); nevertheless, the nss-<lb/>SO = <lb/>4 concentration appears independent of F DMS after this <lb/>threshold. AT exhibits a positive relationship with MSA and <lb/>the nss-SO = <lb/>4 concentration in the range of 5-15 °C and a neg-<lb/>ative relationship above 15 °C. RH, which has the least im-<lb/>pact on MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 (Table 4), has an unclear pattern <lb/>regarding the MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 marginal changes. MSA <lb/>and nss-SO = <lb/>4 present a negative dependence on PR, as rain <lb/>is expected to scavenge aerosol particles; nevertheless, at <lb/>higher PR levels, nss-SO = <lb/>4 concentrations tend to increase. <lb/>This may be partly linked to enhanced cloudiness, associ-<lb/>ated with high PR, where the aqueous-phase formation of <lb/>nss-SO = <lb/>4 in the MBL may be favored (Zhu et al., 2006; von <lb/>Glasow and Crutzen, 2004). This is also in agreement with <lb/>the enhancement of the nss-SO = <lb/>4 concentration at high RH. <lb/>Finally, BLH and SRF are the parameters that show the most <lb/>straightforward influence on the MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 levels, <lb/>with a deep BLH resulting in a dilution of their concentra-<lb/>tions and high SRF leading to high MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 levels, <lb/>as expected for DMS photooxidation products. <lb/>4.3 The IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 dataset <lb/>The GPR model was used to generate the long-term gridded <lb/>fields of high-resolution (0.25°× 0.25°) MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 <lb/>concentrations. At each pixel, daily time series of MSA and <lb/>nss-SO = <lb/>4 have been generated spanning from 1998 to 2022 <lb/>(9131 d). The total number of pixels in the entire NA domain <lb/>is 43 840, for a total of 400 303 040 data points. The daily <lb/>time series of MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 averaged over the entire <lb/>NA domain are presented in Fig. S9. The dataset represents <lb/>the sea-level concentrations of MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 associated <lb/>with in situ production in the MBL derived based on the six <lb/>selected predictors, which, in turn, represent the sea-to-air <lb/>flux of DMS (the precursor) and the meteorological condi-<lb/>tions that can mostly affect, in one direction or another, the <lb/>formation of the two products. For this reason, we consider <lb/>the data to be representative of the concentration of sulfur <lb/>aerosol species resulting, in each pixel, from the local bio-<lb/>genic emissions in combination with local atmospheric con-<lb/>ditions. As such, we called the achieved data product the &quot;In-<lb/>situ Produced Biogenic Methanesulfonic Acid and Sulfate <lb/>over the North Atlantic&quot; (IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 ). It is important to <lb/>note that atmospheric motion is not considered in our prod-<lb/>uct and that the maps resulting from the data represent a static <lb/>picture of potential sea-level concentrations of MSA and nss-<lb/>SO = <lb/>4 (in a certain pixel and at a certain time as a result of only <lb/>the interplay between local DMS emissions, photochemistry, <lb/>and dilution/removal processes) and provide accurate pre-<lb/>dictions of the actual sea-level concentrations of MSA and <lb/>nss-SO = <lb/>4 once averaged over 2-3 d transport tracts. Accord-<lb/>ingly, the IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 data presented hereafter are differ-<lb/>ent from the output of a chemical transport model. Neverthe-<lb/>less, we believe that this unprecedented dataset may be useful <lb/>for many research purposes, for instance, investigating long-<lb/>term trends or addressing the interannual or spatial variability <lb/>in the production of biogenic sulfur aerosol species. Exam-<lb/>ples of the scientific information that can be extracted from <lb/>the data and how the data can be compared to model output <lb/>or in situ observations are provided in the next sections. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/></note>

        <page>2731 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 5. Partial dependence plots of MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 as a function of the predictors revealed by the GPR model. <lb/>4.4 Comparison with CAMS Reanalysis <lb/>To further examine the effectiveness of our GPR model, we <lb/>compared the observed MSA concentrations at MHD with <lb/>the most recently released CAMS-EAC4 (Inness et al., 2019) <lb/>reanalysis datasets. EAC4 (ECMWF Atmospheric Composi-<lb/>tion Reanalysis 4) is the fourth generation of the ECMWF <lb/>global reanalysis dataset of atmospheric composition from <lb/>the Copernicus Atmosphere Monitoring Service (CAMS). <lb/>CAMS-EAC4 is a collection of atmospheric composition <lb/>fields from 2003 to the present, including aerosols and chem-<lb/>ical species -for which MSA data are available. The spa-<lb/>tial resolution of the CAMS datasets is about 0.75°× 0.75°a <lb/>nd the temporal resolution is 3 h. Our datasets have a <lb/>0.25°× 0.25°resolution and start from 1998. To compare the <lb/>two products, we extracted MSA data from CAMS locally, <lb/>at the grid cell in front of the MHD station, corresponding to <lb/>maritime BT timings, and averaged them to a daily resolu-<lb/>tion. Conservatively, the MSA concentration data simulated <lb/>by GPR were taken from the validation and test sets, which <lb/>were not included in the model training. Such MSA concen-<lb/>trations at MHD were projected by incorporating predictors <lb/>along the BTs to account for air motion (see Sect. 3.1.2 for <lb/>details). <lb/>Scatterplots and joint probability histograms of residual <lb/>errors (Fig. 6) were constructed to compare the accuracy <lb/>between GPR, CAMS, and observations (with the latter re-<lb/>ferred to as OBS). From the scatterplots (Fig. 6a, b), it can <lb/>be seen that the GPR-simulated MSA best matches the ob-<lb/>servations, with a 0.84 fitted slope, a 0.93 correlation coeffi-<lb/>cient, and most of the data points within the 95 % confidence <lb/>bounds. The joint probability histograms between observed <lb/>MSA and the residuals, OBS -GPR and OBS -CAMS, are <lb/>used to verify the variance of residual errors around zero. <lb/>The GPR histograms (Fig. 6c, e) show that the residual er-<lb/>rors are mostly centered around zero (dashed black line in <lb/>the right) up to a value of 0.1 µg m -3 , where the majority <lb/>of data points lie, while CAMS points are skewed toward <lb/>negative residuals followed by positive residuals, mainly at <lb/>high MSA values (Fig. 6d, f). Quantitatively, the GPR has a <lb/>relative MAE equal to 4.3 %, in comparison with 6.3 % for <lb/>CAMS. In summary, GPR better captures the low concen-<lb/>trations of MSA, which CAMS tends to overestimate, while <lb/>both CAMS and GPR show limitations with respect to re-<lb/>trieving the extreme points of MSA concentrations. A quanti-<lb/>tative statistical analysis (Fig. 6g) showed that no statistically <lb/>significant (p&lt;0.05) difference exists between the seasonal <lb/>median MSA from OBS and GPR, whereas CAMS presents <lb/>a significant (p&lt;0.05) difference in all seasons except sum-<lb/>mer. Nevertheless, the two datasets (GPR and CAMS) prop-<lb/>erly retrieve the observed MSA seasonal cycle. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2732 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 6. Comparison between observed MSA at the MHD measuring site and both MSA predicted by GPR (a) and MSA extracted <lb/>from CAMS Reanalysis (b). Panels (c) and (d) present joint probability histograms between observed MSA and residual errors (ob-<lb/>served -predicted); the dashed black lines represent the change in MSA residual errors in each bin. MAE is the mean absolute error, <lb/>and the relative MAE has been calculated as the MAE divided by the range of observed MSA. Panels (e) and (f) show frequency distributions <lb/>of the residual errors. Panel (g) contains seasonal box charts from different datasets. Each box chart displays the median (line inside of each <lb/>box), the 1st and 3rd quartiles (bottom and top edges of each box), the minimum and maximum values that are not outliers (whiskers), and <lb/>any outliers (represented by &quot;+&quot; and computed as values that are more than 1.5 of the interquartile range away from the top or bottom of the <lb/>box). Box charts whose notches (the shaded region around each median) do not overlap have different medians at the 95 % confidence level. <lb/>4.5 Comparison with the Polarstern cruise results <lb/>In this section, we present a case study exemplifying how <lb/>the IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 datasets can be used. Because the data <lb/>product represents the concentration of freshly formed sul-<lb/>fur aerosol species and the ML model does not account for <lb/>atmospheric transport, users must interpret the datasets con-<lb/>sidering the air mass history. To better clarify the idea, we <lb/>employed the independent MSA data measured during the <lb/>Polarstern campaigns in the NA (Huang et al., 2017), which <lb/>were not used in the training/validation or testing/evaluation <lb/>of the ML models, and compared them with MSA predicted <lb/>by GPR. In particular, the MSA predicted by GPR was ex-<lb/>tracted along air mass BTs arriving at the hourly sites of <lb/>the ship tracks and then averaged considering a 0 d (no air <lb/>mass history), 1, 2, and 3 d air mass history. The MSA mea-<lb/>surements on Polarstern were performed during four scien-<lb/>tific cruises, including two spring seasons (April-May 2011 <lb/>and April-May 2012) and two autumn seasons (October-<lb/>November 2011 and October-November 2012). The ship <lb/>tracks of the cruises from which the data were taken in the <lb/>present study are shown in Fig. 7. It can be seen that the best <lb/>match between GPR-simulated MSA and observed MSA oc-<lb/>curred when 2 d air masses were considered. At a 2 d air mass <lb/>history, the slope reached 0.78 and the correlation coefficient <lb/>reached 0.81 (Fig. 7a-d). Again, as seen in Fig. 7f, GPR <lb/>MSA is considerably more consistent with observations than <lb/>CAMS, for which a significant difference with observations <lb/>(p&lt;0.05) can be appreciated. <lb/>4.6 Spatial distributions of MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 <lb/>In order to elucidate the geographical distributions of bio-<lb/>genic sulfur aerosol production across the NA domain, the <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/></note>

        <page>2733 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 7. (a) Scatterplots between observed MSA during the Po-<lb/>larstern campaigns (Huang et al., 2017) and predicted MSA by <lb/>GPR, considering (a) 0 d, (b) 1 d, (c) 2 d, and (d) 3 d air mass his-<lb/>tory. Panel (f) contains seasonal box charts from different datasets. <lb/>The features displayed on each box chart are the same as those given <lb/>in Fig. 6. <lb/>IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 datasets for the 25 years (1998-2022) were <lb/>averaged to obtain the climatic annual and monthly distri-<lb/>butions of MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 , as illustrated in Figs. 8 and <lb/>9. Across the NA domain, the annual average of MSA is <lb/>0.016 ± 0.007 µg m -3 , whereas the annual average of nss-<lb/>SO = <lb/>4 is 0.250 ± 0.077 µg m -3 (Table S2). The annual spatial <lb/>distributions of MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 exhibit a latitudinal gra-<lb/>dient over the majority of the NA area that increases from <lb/>north to south, except below approximately 35°N, where it <lb/>increases from west to east. Notwithstanding, the latitudinal <lb/>gradients are much more evident than longitudinal variations. <lb/>For instance, MSA grows at a rate of 0.0016 (R 2 <lb/>= 0.93; <lb/>p&lt;0.05) µg m -3 per degree latitude towards the south and <lb/>0.00036 (R 2 <lb/>= 0.53; p&lt;0.05) µg m -3 per degree longitude <lb/>eastward (it reaches its peak between 20 and 10°W). Fur-<lb/>thermore, for each degree southward, nss-SO = <lb/>4 increases by <lb/>0.0212 (R 2 <lb/>= 0.96; p&lt;0.05) µg m -3 , whereas there are no <lb/>significant changes in nss-SO = <lb/>4 with longitude (R 2 <lb/>= 0.01; <lb/>p&gt;0.05). The highest concentrations of both components <lb/>(&gt;90th percentile) are primarily found in the southeast of <lb/>the domain (in front of the Moroccan coast and the Strait <lb/>of Gibraltar). Minimum annual concentrations (&lt;10th per-<lb/>centile) are found in northern areas of the domain, particu-<lb/>larly in the Labrador Sea and near the shores of Greenland <lb/>and Iceland. <lb/>The annual average MSA-to-nss-SO = <lb/>4 ratio (MSA : <lb/>nss-SO = <lb/>4 ) is 0.053 ± 0.012 (Table S2), with a consis-<lb/>tent latitudinal gradient increasing southward (rate of <lb/>change = 0.0028 (R 2 <lb/>= 0.93; p&lt;0.05) per degree latitude). <lb/>Lower MSA: nss-SO = <lb/>4 values are found in the northwest of <lb/>the domain, while higher values are apparent in front of the <lb/>African coast; the ratio is practically constant across the same <lb/>latitudinal band. It is worth noting that the region with ex-<lb/>tremely high MSA concentrations and high MSA : nss-SO = <lb/>4 <lb/>(above the mean + 3 times the standard deviation) is linked <lb/>to the Canary upwelling system on the northwest African <lb/>coast. The Canary Current system is one of the world&apos;s most <lb/>productive regions of the ocean, known as eastern bound-<lb/>ary upwelling systems (EBUSs) (Chavez and Messié, 2009; <lb/>Carr, 2001). This may indicate a link between EBUSs and the <lb/>potential formation of biogenic aerosol in the atmosphere. <lb/>Previous research has shown how EBUSs changed in re-<lb/>sponse to climate change (Bograd et al., 2023; Sydeman et <lb/>al., 2014; Bonino et al., 2019), including the trend toward <lb/>increased upwelling intensity (Wang et al., 2015; García-<lb/>Reyes et al., 2015); however, little is known about the im-<lb/>pact of EBUSs on marine biogenic emissions and the re-<lb/>sultant aerosol fluxes. Future studies are needed to address <lb/>these issues in order to better understand the role of EBUSs <lb/>in aerosol-climate systems. <lb/>Looking at the monthly climatological maps (Fig. 9), it <lb/>is revealed that MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 display a gradual south-<lb/>ward increase in their concentrations, clearly evident from <lb/>October to March, resulting in a large difference between the <lb/>northern and southern parts of the domain. On the contrary, <lb/>during summer, the concentrations are more homogeneous <lb/>over the domain (see latitudinal patterns in Fig. 9), still with <lb/>a tendency toward higher concentrations over the northeast-<lb/>ern part of the region. The seasonality of MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 <lb/>is evident: the increase in both compounds starts in April, <lb/>peaks in June-July, and is followed by a gradual decrease <lb/>in September (Fig. S9, Table S2). The lowest MSA (nss-<lb/>SO = <lb/>4 ) concentration occurs in December at 0.006 ± 0.005 <lb/>(0.155 ± 0.079) µg m -3 , whereas the highest concentration <lb/>occurs in June at 0.029 ± 0.013 (0.364 ± 0.075) µg m -3 (Ta-<lb/>ble S2), consistent with the fact that winter and summer are <lb/>typically the lowest and highest seasons with respect to bi-<lb/>ological activity, respectively, for the NA (Mansour et al., <lb/>2023a). The coefficient of variation (COV), defined as the <lb/>ratio between the standard deviation and the mean value, <lb/>expressed as a percentage at each grid point, is used to as-<lb/>sess how much MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 vary around their mean <lb/>value in each month; variability increases with a higher COV. <lb/>The maps (Fig. S10) confirm that the variability in sul-<lb/>fur aerosol species depends strongly on the season: MSA <lb/>and nss-SO = <lb/>4 are mostly stable (small variations) during the <lb/>winter, whereas most variations occur between April (late <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2734 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/></note>

      <body>Figure 8. The annual averages of (a) MSA, (b) nss-SO = <lb/>4 , and <lb/>(c) MSA : nss-SO = <lb/>4 spatial distributions based on GPR at a <lb/>0.25°× 0.25°resolution during the 1998-2022 period. The latitudi-<lb/>nal (longitudinal) gradients of each component are displayed in the <lb/>left (bottom) panels, shaded areas represent ± standard deviations, <lb/>and the black crosses evidence the extremely high concentrations <lb/>(more than 3 times the standard deviation plus the annual mean cli-<lb/>matology). <lb/>spring) and June (early summer) and preferentially over the <lb/>eastern part of the NA compared with the western part. <lb/>MSA : nss-SO = <lb/>4 also exhibits a seasonal pattern, with the <lb/>lowest (highest) values observed during the winter (summer), <lb/>as presented in Fig. 9c. July has the highest spatial aver-<lb/>age of the ratio of 0.077 ± 0.022, while the lowest value <lb/>of 0.032 ± 0.012 occurs in December (Table S2). Looking <lb/>at the overall distributions, MSA : nss-SO = <lb/>4 demonstrates <lb/>a general southward increase, with the exception of sum-<lb/>mer months. In summer (mainly July and August), MSA : <lb/>nss-SO = <lb/>4 above 50°N has an opposite trend with respect to <lb/>the ratio below 50°N. In detail, from north to south, we re-<lb/>port a sharp increase in MSA : nss-SO = <lb/>4 , maximized around <lb/>50°N, followed by an abrupt decrease toward the Equator. A <lb/>possible explanation for the decline in MSA : nss-SO = <lb/>4 be-<lb/>low 50°N is that the reduction is related to an increase in <lb/>AT caused by warmer air nearing the Equator, in line with <lb/>observations in the Pacific Ocean (Bates et al., 1992) and <lb/>with the higher ratio observed in colder (marine polar and <lb/>arctic) air masses with respect to warmer (marine tropical) <lb/>air masses at MHD (Ovadnevaite et al., 2014). As a final re-<lb/>mark, we report that the summertime low MSA : nss-SO = <lb/>4 <lb/>below 50°N is linked to a decrease in F DMS in the same <lb/>latitudinal zone (Mansour et al., 2023a). Owing to the low <lb/>DMS emissions, different DMS oxidation patterns may be in <lb/>competition (Barone et al., 1995); as MSA is formed pref-<lb/>erentially through the pathway of OH addition at low tem-<lb/>peratures (Shen et al., 2022), the production of MSA may be <lb/>decreased relative to that of nss-SO = <lb/>4 in the warm southern <lb/>part of the domain, during summer, leading to the observed <lb/>decrease in MSA : nss-SO = <lb/>4 . <lb/></body>

      <div type="availability">5 Data availability <lb/>The dataset includes daily MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 concentra-<lb/>tions at a 0.25°× 0.25°spatial resolution over the North At-<lb/>lantic from January 1998 to December 2022. The data are <lb/>publicly available in NetCDF format as daily files on the <lb/>Mendeley Data online repository at https://doi.org/10.17632/ <lb/>j8bzd5dvpx.1 (Mansour et al., 2023b). <lb/></div>

      <body>6 Conclusions <lb/>Marine aerosol data can be obtained from in situ coastal ob-<lb/>servatories or from shipborne measurements; however, coast <lb/>observations at individual measurement points are limited <lb/>with respect to their spatial representativity, while shipborne <lb/>measurements suffer from limitations in terms of tempo-<lb/>ral coverage. Understanding the dynamics of marine-derived <lb/>biogenic sulfur aerosols and their radiative effects, as well as <lb/>carrying out relevant scientific studies, requires long-term, <lb/>continuous, high-resolution (both spatial and temporal reso-<lb/>lution) datasets. To overcome the limitations of point-based <lb/>measurements, we combined the in situ observations of sul-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/></note>

        <page>2735 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 9. Monthly spatial distributions of (a) MSA, (b) nss-SO = <lb/>4 , and (c) MSA : nss-SO = <lb/>4 based on GPR over 1998-2022 at a 0.25°× 0.25°r <lb/>esolution. Panel (d) shows monthly latitudinal distributions of each component, with the shaded areas representing ± standard deviations. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2736 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/></note>

        <body>fur aerosol data at Mace Head and those from NAAMES <lb/>cruises, as dependent variables, and the sea-to-air DMS flux <lb/>and ECMWF ERA5 reanalysis meteorological datasets, as <lb/>independent variables, to investigate the potential of machine <lb/>learning techniques for the prediction of daily MSA and nss-<lb/>SO = <lb/>4 sea-level concentrations over the North Atlantic. We <lb/>evaluated five machine learning models (i.e., SVM, DT, RE, <lb/>GPR, and ANN), considering various sets of hyperparameter <lb/>optimizations. Our findings demonstrate that the GPR model <lb/>outperforms other approaches with respect to simulating the <lb/>concentrations of biogenic sulfur aerosols, capturing up to <lb/>86 % and 72 % of the observed variance in daily MSA and <lb/>nss-SO = <lb/>4 , respectively. This makes the GPR an effective tool <lb/>for obtaining trustworthy sea-level MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 con-<lb/>centrations over the North Atlantic, which may also result in <lb/>it be successful in other oceanic regions or over the entire <lb/>global ocean. The impact of the six independent predictors <lb/>on the simulated MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 is further evaluated us-<lb/>ing the GPR partial dependence analysis, which reveals that <lb/>the relationships between them are multifaceted rather than <lb/>linear or monotonically varying. <lb/>Using the GPR machine learning method, we constructed <lb/>a novel 0.25°× 0.25°resolution daily gridded dataset of <lb/>in situ-produced biogenic MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 concentrations <lb/>(named IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 ) covering the North Atlantic from <lb/>1998 to 2022. The dataset represents the sea-level concentra-<lb/>tions of MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 associated with in situ production <lb/>in the MBL, i.e., the concentration of sulfur aerosol species <lb/>resulting, in each pixel, from the local biogenic emissions <lb/>in combination with local atmospheric conditions. Other in-<lb/>puts, such as terrestrial emissions or sinking of sulfur species <lb/>produced in the free troposphere are not accounted for in the <lb/>present dataset. <lb/>Comparison of the GPR-derived MSA with existing <lb/>CAMS-EAC4 reanalysis product reveals that our high-<lb/>resolution dataset accurately reproduces the spatial and tem-<lb/>poral patterns of the biogenic sulfur aerosol concentration <lb/>and has high consistency with the independent observations <lb/>of the Polarstern cruises&apos; measurements in the Atlantic. The <lb/>obtained IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 data were used to analyze the spa-<lb/>tiotemporal variations in MSA, nss-SO = <lb/>4 , and the ratio be-<lb/>tween them (MSA : nss-SO = <lb/>4 ). It was found that the monthly <lb/>concentrations of MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 across the NA are char-<lb/>acterized by a significant southward increase in each month, <lb/>with the exception of summertime when MSA and nss-SO = <lb/>4 <lb/>displayed more homogeneous spatial patterns with a ten-<lb/>dency toward higher concentrations over the northeastern <lb/>part of the domain. MSA : nss-SO = <lb/>4 exhibits a seasonal vari-<lb/>ation from winter (low) to summer (high), characterized by <lb/>a sharp decline from the 50°N parallel toward the Equator <lb/>mainly in July-August. In general, the atmospheric concen-<lb/>tration of sulfur aerosol species tends to be more stable in <lb/>winter, whereas wider variations are associated with late-<lb/>spring and early summertime and more with the eastern part <lb/>of the domain than with the western part. <lb/>More in-depth analyses can be conducted based on the pre-<lb/>sented biogenic sulfur aerosol concentration dataset, which <lb/>could help further the understanding of marine-aerosol-<lb/>cloud interactions. For instance, we evidence that the Ca-<lb/>nary eastern upwelling system emerges from the dataset as <lb/>a hot spot of high sea-level MSA concentrations and high <lb/>MSA : nss-SO = <lb/>4 values. Such a finding is worth further in-<lb/>vestigation and may shed light on the role of EBUSs in the <lb/>production of biogenic marine aerosols and on their climate <lb/>relevance. <lb/></body>

        <div type="annex">Supplement. The supplement related to this article is available <lb/>online at: https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024-supplement. <lb/></div>

        <div type="contribution">Author contributions. KM and MR contributed to the conceptu-<lb/>alization and design of the study. KM organized the datasets, con-<lb/>structed the models, analyzed the data, and visualized the results. <lb/>KM wrote the first draft of the manuscript under the supervision <lb/>of MR. KM, MR, SD, DC, JO, LMR, MP, LP, SH, and CO&apos;D con-<lb/>tributed to the investigation of the results, manuscript revision, read-<lb/>ing and editing, and approval of the submitted version. <lb/></div>

        <div type="conflict">Competing interests. The contact author has declared that none <lb/>of the authors has any competing interests. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Disclaimer. Publisher&apos;s note: Copernicus Publications remains <lb/>neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims made in the text, pub-<lb/>lished maps, institutional affiliations, or any other geographical rep-<lb/>resentation in this paper. While Copernicus Publications makes ev-<lb/>ery effort to include appropriate place names, the final responsibility <lb/>lies with the authors. <lb/></div>

        <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements. We gratefully acknowledge the Copernicus <lb/>Climate Change Service (C3S) for provision of ECMWF ERA5 re-<lb/>analysis meteorological data and the NOAA Air Resources Labo-<lb/>ratory (ARL) for provision of the HYSPLIT transport and disper-<lb/>sion model. The University of Galway team acknowledges support <lb/>from the Irish EPA (AC3 and AEROSOURCE, 2016-CCRP-MS-<lb/>31); the Department of Environment, Climate and Communications; <lb/>and MaREI -the SFI Research Centre for Energy, Climate, and Ma-<lb/>rine. <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">Financial support. This research has been supported by the Euro-<lb/>pean Commission&apos;s EU Horizon 2020 Framework program, project <lb/>FORCeS (grant no. 821205). <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Review statement. This paper was edited by François G. Schmitt <lb/>and reviewed by Rui Li and one anonymous referee. <lb/></div>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/></note>

        <page>2737 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>References <lb/>Allan, J. D., Jimenez, J. L., Williams, P. I., Alfarra, M. R., Bower, K. <lb/>N., Jayne, J. T., Coe, H., and Worsnop, D. R.: Quantitative sam-<lb/>pling using an Aerodyne aerosol mass spectrometer -1. Tech-<lb/>niques of data interpretation and error analysis, J. Geophys. Res.-<lb/>Atmos., 108, 4090, https://doi.org/10.1029/2002jd002358, 2003. <lb/>Asante-Okyere, S., Shen, C. B., Ziggah, Y. Y., Rulegeya, M. M., and <lb/>Zhu, X. F.: Investigating the Predictive Performance of Gaussian <lb/>Process Regression in Evaluating Reservoir Porosity and Perme-<lb/>ability, Energies, 11, https://doi.org/10.3390/en11123261, 2018. <lb/>Barone, S. B., Turnipseed, A. A., and Ravishankara, A. R.: Role of <lb/>adducts in the atmospheric oxidation of dimethyl sulfide, Faraday <lb/>Discuss., 100, 39-54, https://doi.org/10.1039/fd9950000039, <lb/>1995. <lb/>Bates, T. S., Calhoun, J. A., and Quinn, P. K.: Varia-<lb/>tions in the Methanesulfonate to Sulfate Molar Ratio in <lb/>Submicrometer Marine Aerosol-Particles over the South-<lb/>Pacific Ocean, J. Geophys. Res.-Atmos., 97, 9859-9865, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/92jd00411, 1992. <lb/>Behrenfeld, M. J., Moore, R. H., Hostetler, C. A., Graff, J., Gaube, <lb/>P., Russell, L. M., Chen, G., Doney, S. C., Giovannoni, S., Liu, <lb/>H. Y., Proctor, C., Bolalios, L. M., Baetge, N., Davie-Martin, <lb/>C., Westberry, T. K., Bates, T. S., Bell, T. G., Bidle, K. D., <lb/>Boss, E. S., Brooks, S. D., Cairns, B., Carlson, C., Halsey, K., <lb/>Harvey, E. L., Hu, C. M., Karp-Boss, L., Kleb, M., Menden-<lb/>Deuer, S., Morison, F., Quinn, P. K., Scarino, A. J., Anderson, <lb/>B., Chowdhary, J., Crosbie, E., Ferrare, R., Haire, J. W., Hu, Y. <lb/>X., Janz, S., Redemann, J., Saltzman, E., Shook, M., Siegel, D. <lb/>A., Wisthaler, A., Martine, M. Y., and Ziemba, L.: The North <lb/>Atlantic Aerosol and Marine Ecosystem Study (NAAMES): Sci-<lb/>ence Motive and Mission Overview, Frontiers in Marine Science, <lb/>6, 122, https://doi.org/10.3389/fmars.2019.00122, 2019. <lb/>Bock, J., Michou, M., Nabat, P., Abe, M., Mulcahy, J. P., <lb/>Olivié, D. J. L., Schwinger, J., Suntharalingam, P., Tjiputra, <lb/>J., van Hulten, M., Watanabe, M., Yool, A., and Séférian, <lb/>R.: Evaluation of ocean dimethylsulfide concentration and <lb/>emission in CMIP6 models, Biogeosciences, 18, 3823-3860, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-18-3823-2021, 2021. <lb/>Bograd, S. J., Jacox, M. G., Hazen, E. L., Lovecchio, E., <lb/>Montes, I., Buil, M. P., Shannon, L. J., Sydeman, W. J., and <lb/>Rykaczewski, R. R.: Climate Change Impacts on Eastern Bound-<lb/>ary Upwelling Systems, Annu. Rev. Mar. Sci., 15, 303-328, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-marine-032122-021945, 2023. <lb/>Bonino, G., Di Lorenzo, E., Masina, S., and Iovino, D.: In-<lb/>terannual to decadal variability within and across the major <lb/>Eastern Boundary Upwelling Systems, Scientific Reports, 9, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-019-56514-8, 2019. <lb/>Breiman, L.: Random forests, Machine Learning, 45, 5-32, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1023/a:1010933404324, 2001. <lb/>Buckley, M. W. and Marshall, J.: Observations, inferences, <lb/>and mechanisms of the Atlantic Meridional Overturn-<lb/>ing Circulation: A review, Rev. Geophys., 54, 5-63, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/2015rg000493, 2016. <lb/>Canagaratna, M. R., Jayne, J. T., Jimenez, J. L., Allan, J. D., <lb/>Alfarra, M. R., Zhang, Q., Onasch, T. B., Drewnick, F., Coe, <lb/>H., Middlebrook, A., Delia, A., Williams, L. R., Trimborn, <lb/>A. M., Northway, M. J., DeCarlo, P. F., Kolb, C. E., Davi-<lb/>dovits, P., and Worsnop, D. R.: Chemical and microphys-<lb/>ical characterization of ambient aerosols with the aerodyne <lb/>aerosol mass spectrometer, Mass Spectrom. Rev., 26, 185-222, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/mas.20115, 2007. <lb/>Carr, M. E.: Estimation of potential productivity in Eastern Bound-<lb/>ary Currents using remote sensing, Deep-Sea Res. Pt. II, 49, 59-<lb/>80, 2001. <lb/>Charlson, R. J., Lovelock, J. E., Andreae, M. O., and <lb/>Warren, S. G.: Oceanic Phytoplankton, Atmospheric Sul-<lb/>fur, Cloud Albedo and Climate, Nature, 326, 655-661, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/326655a0, 1987. <lb/>Chavez, F. P. and Messié, M.: A comparison of Eastern <lb/>Boundary Upwelling Ecosystems, Prog. Oceanogr., 83, 80-96, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pocean.2009.07.032, 2009. <lb/>DeCarlo, P. F., Kimmel, J. R., Trimborn, A., Northway, <lb/>M. J., Jayne, J. T., Aiken, A. C., Gonin, M., Fuhrer, <lb/>K., Horvath, T., Docherty, K. S., Worsnop, D. R., and <lb/>Jimenez, J. L.: Field-deployable, high-resolution, time-of-flight <lb/>aerosol mass spectrometer, Anal. Chem., 78, 8281-8289, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1021/ac061249n, 2006. <lb/>Etminan, M., Myhre, G., Highwood, E. J., and Shine, K. P.: Radia-<lb/>tive forcing of carbon dioxide, methane, and nitrous oxide: A sig-<lb/>nificant revision of the methane radiative forcing, Geophys. Res. <lb/>Lett., 43, 12614-12623, https://doi.org/10.1002/2016gl071930, <lb/>2016. <lb/>Fan, J. L., Yue, W. J., Wu, L. F., Zhang, F. C., Cai, H. J., Wang, <lb/>X. K., Lu, X. H., and Xiang, Y. Z.: Evaluation of SVM, ELM <lb/>and four tree-based ensemble models for predicting daily refer-<lb/>ence evapotranspiration using limited meteorological data in dif-<lb/>ferent climates of China, Agr. Forest Meteorol., 263, 225-241, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agrformet.2018.08.019, 2018. <lb/>Fiddes, S. L., Woodhouse, M. T., Nicholls, Z., Lane, T. P., and <lb/>Schofield, R.: Cloud, precipitation and radiation responses to <lb/>large perturbations in global dimethyl sulfide, Atmos. Chem. <lb/>Phys., 18, 10177-10198, https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-18-10177-<lb/>2018, 2018. <lb/>Fratantoni, D. M.: North Atlantic surface circulation <lb/>during <lb/>the <lb/>1990&apos;s <lb/>observed <lb/>with <lb/>satellite-tracked <lb/>drifters, J. Geophys. Res.-Oceans, 106, 22067-22093, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2000jc000730, 2001. <lb/>Friedman, J. H.: Greedy function approximation: A gra-<lb/>dient boosting machine, Ann. Stat., 29, 1189-1232, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1214/aos/1013203451, 2001. <lb/>Frossard, A. A., Russell, L. M., Massoli, P., Bates, T. S., and Quinn, <lb/>P. K.: Side-by-Side Comparison of Four Techniques Explains the <lb/>Apparent Differences in the Organic Composition of Generated <lb/>and Ambient Marine Aerosol Particles, Aerosol Sci. Tech., 48, <lb/>V-X, https://doi.org/10.1080/02786826.2013.879979, 2014. <lb/>Fung, K. M., Heald, C. L., Kroll, J. H., Wang, S., Jo, D. S., <lb/>Gettelman, A., Lu, Z., Liu, X., Zaveri, R. A., Apel, E. C., <lb/>Blake, D. R., Jimenez, J.-L., Campuzano-Jost, P., Veres, P. R., <lb/>Bates, T. S., Shilling, J. E., and Zawadowicz, M.: Exploring <lb/>dimethyl sulfide (DMS) oxidation and implications for global <lb/>aerosol radiative forcing, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 22, 1549-1573, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-22-1549-2022, 2022. <lb/>Fushiki, T.: Estimation of prediction error by using K-<lb/>fold cross-validation, Stat. Comput., 21, 137-146, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11222-009-9153-8, 2011. <lb/>Galí, M., Levasseur, M., Devred, E., Simó, R., and Babin, M.: Sea-<lb/>surface dimethylsulfide (DMS) concentration from satellite data <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2738 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>at global and regional scales, Biogeosciences, 15, 3497-3519, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-15-3497-2018, 2018. <lb/>García-Reyes, M., Sydeman, W. J., Schoeman, D. S., Rykaczewski, <lb/>R. R., Black, B. A., Smit, A. J., and Bograd, S. J.: Under <lb/>Pressure: Climate Change, Upwelling, and Eastern Boundary <lb/>Upwelling Ecosystems, Frontiers in Marine Science, 2, 109, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3389/fmars.2015.00109, 2015. <lb/>Goddijn-Murphy, L., Woolf, D. K., and Marandino, C.: Space-<lb/>based retrievals of air-sea gas transfer velocities using altimeters: <lb/>Calibration for dimethyl sulfide, J. Geophys. Res.-Oceans, 117, <lb/>C08028, https://doi.org/10.1029/2011jc007535, 2012. <lb/>Gondwe, M., Krol, M., Gieskes, W., Klaassen, W., and de Baar, <lb/>H.: The contribution of ocean-leaving DMS to the global atmo-<lb/>spheric burdens of DMS, MSA, SO 2 , and NSS SO = <lb/>4 , Global Bio-<lb/>geochem. Cy., 17, 1056, https://doi.org/10.1029/2002gb001937, <lb/>2003. <lb/>Grigas, T., Ovadnevaite, J., Ceburnis, D., Moran, E., McGov-<lb/>ern, F. M., Jennings, S. G., and O&apos;Dowd, C.: Sophisti-<lb/>cated Clean Air Strategies Required to Mitigate Against <lb/>Particulate Organic Pollution, Scientific Reports, 7, 44737, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/srep44737, 2017. <lb/>Hengl, T., Nussbaum, M., Wright, M. N., Heuvelink, G. B. M., and <lb/>Graler, B.: Random forest as a generic framework for predic-<lb/>tive modeling of spatial and spatio-temporal variables, PeerJ, 6, <lb/>e5518, https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.5518, 2018. <lb/>Hersbach, H., Bell, B., Berrisford, P., Hirahara, S., Horanyi, A., <lb/>Munoz-Sabater, J., Nicolas, J., Peubey, C., Radu, R., Schepers, <lb/>D., Simmons, A., Soci, C., Abdalla, S., Abellan, X., Balsamo, <lb/>G., Bechtold, P., Biavati, G., Bidlot, J., Bonavita, M., De Chiara, <lb/>G., Dahlgren, P., Dee, D., Diamantakis, M., Dragani, R., Flem-<lb/>ming, J., Forbes, R., Fuentes, M., Geer, A., Haimberger, L., <lb/>Healy, S., Hogan, R. J., Holm, E., Janiskova, M., Keeley, S., <lb/>Laloyaux, P., Lopez, P., Lupu, C., Radnoti, G., de Rosnay, P., <lb/>Rozum, I., Vamborg, F., Villaume, S., and Thepaut, J. N.: The <lb/>ERA5 global reanalysis, Q. J. Roy. Meteor. Soc., 146, 1999-<lb/>2049, https://doi.org/10.1002/qj.3803, 2020. <lb/>Hodshire, A. L., Campuzano-Jost, P., Kodros, J. K., Croft, B., Nault, <lb/>B. A., Schroder, J. C., Jimenez, J. L., and Pierce, J. R.: The <lb/>potential role of methanesulfonic acid (MSA) in aerosol for-<lb/>mation and growth and the associated radiative forcings, At-<lb/>mos. Chem. Phys., 19, 3137-3160, https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-<lb/>19-3137-2019, 2019. <lb/>Huang, S., Poulain, L., van Pinxteren, D., van Pinxteren, M., Wu, Z. <lb/>J., Herrmann, H., and Wiedensohler, A.: Latitudinal and Seasonal <lb/>Distribution of Particulate MSA over the Atlantic using a Vali-<lb/>dated Quantification Method with HR-ToF-AMS, Environ. Sci. <lb/>Technol., 51, 418-426, https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.6b03186, <lb/>2017. <lb/>Hulswar, S., Simó, R., Galí, M., Bell, T. G., Lana, A., Inamdar, <lb/>S., Halloran, P. R., Manville, G., and Mahajan, A. S.: Third <lb/>revision of the global surface seawater dimethyl sulfide cli-<lb/>matology (DMS-Rev3), Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 14, 2963-2987, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-14-2963-2022, 2022. <lb/>Inness, A., Ades, M., Agustí-Panareda, A., Barré, J., Benedic-<lb/>tow, A., Blechschmidt, A.-M., Dominguez, J. J., Engelen, R., <lb/>Eskes, H., Flemming, J., Huijnen, V., Jones, L., Kipling, Z., <lb/>Massart, S., Parrington, M., Peuch, V.-H., Razinger, M., Remy, <lb/>S., Schulz, M., and Suttie, M.: The CAMS reanalysis of at-<lb/>mospheric composition, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 19, 3515-3556, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-19-3515-2019, 2019. <lb/>Jimenez, J. L., Jayne, J. T., Shi, Q., Kolb, C. E., Worsnop, <lb/>D. R., Yourshaw, I., Seinfeld, J. H., Flagan, R. C., Zhang, <lb/>X. F., Smith, K. A., Morris, J. W., and Davidovits, P.: <lb/>Ambient aerosol sampling using the Aerodyne Aerosol <lb/>Mass Spectrometer, J. Geophys. Res.-Atmos., 108, 8425, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2001jd001213, 2003. <lb/>Kalogirou, S. A.: Artificial neural networks in renewable energy <lb/>systems applications: a review, Renew. Sust. Energ. Rev., 5, 373-<lb/>401, https://doi.org/10.1016/s1364-0321(01)00006-5, 2001. <lb/>Katsman, C. A., Spall, M. A., and Pickart, R. S.: Boundary current <lb/>eddies and their role in the restratification of the Labrador Sea, J. <lb/>Phys. Oceanogr., 34, 1967-1983, https://doi.org/10.1175/1520-<lb/>0485(2004)034&lt;1967:bceatr&gt;2.0.co;2, 2004. <lb/>Kim, A. H., Yum, S. S., Lee, H., Chang, D. Y., and Shim, <lb/>S.: Polar Cooling Effect Due to Increase of Phytoplank-<lb/>ton and Dimethyl-Sulfide Emission, Atmosphere, 9, 384 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/atmos9100384, 2018. <lb/>Kotsiantis, S. B.: Decision trees: a recent overview, Artif. Intell. <lb/>Rev., 39, 261-283, https://doi.org/10.1007/s10462-011-9272-4, <lb/>2013. <lb/>Langmann, B., Scannell, C., and O&apos;Dowd, C.: New Direc-<lb/>tions: Organic matter contribution to marine aerosols and <lb/>cloud condensation nuclei, Atmos. Environ., 42, 7821-7822, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.atmosenv.2008.09.002, 2008. <lb/>Lins, I. D., Araujo, M., Moura, M. D., Silva, M. A., and Droguett, E. <lb/>L.: Prediction of sea surface temperature in the tropical Atlantic <lb/>by support vector machines, Comput. Stat. Data An., 61, 187-<lb/>198, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.csda.2012.12.003, 2013. <lb/>Mahajan, A. S., Fadnavis, S., Thomas, M. A., Pozzoli, L., Gupta, S., <lb/>Royer, S. J., Saiz-Lopez, A., and Simo, R.: Quantifying the im-<lb/>pacts of an updated global dimethyl sulfide climatology on cloud <lb/>microphysics and aerosol radiative forcing, J. Geophys. Res.-<lb/>Atmos., 120, 2524-2536, https://doi.org/10.1002/2014jd022687, <lb/>2015. <lb/>Mahmood, R., von Salzen, K., Norman, A.-L., Galí, M., and <lb/>Levasseur, M.: Sensitivity of Arctic sulfate aerosol and <lb/>clouds to changes in future surface seawater dimethylsul-<lb/>fide concentrations, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 19, 6419-6435, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-19-6419-2019, 2019. <lb/>Mansour, K., Decesari, S., Bellacicco, M., Marullo, S., Santoleri, <lb/>R., Bonasoni, P., Facchini, M. C., Ovadnevaite, J., Ceburnis, D., <lb/>O&apos;Dowd, C., and Rinaldi, M.: Particulate methanesulfonic acid <lb/>over the central Mediterranean Sea: Source region identification <lb/>and relationship with phytoplankton activity, Atmos. Res., 237, <lb/>104837, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.atmosres.2019.104837, 2020a. <lb/>Mansour, K., Decesari, S., Facchini, M. C., Belosi, F., Paglione, M., <lb/>Sandrini, S., Bellacicco, M., Marullo, S., Santoleri, R., Ovad-<lb/>nevaite, J., Ceburnis, D., O&apos;Dowd, C., Roberts, G., Sanchez, <lb/>K., and Rinaldi, M.: Linking Marine Biological Activity to <lb/>Aerosol Chemical Composition and Cloud-Relevant Properties <lb/>Over the North Atlantic Ocean, J. Geophys. Res.-Atmos., 125, <lb/>e2019JD032246, https://doi.org/10.1029/2019jd032246, 2020b. <lb/>Mansour, K., Rinaldi, M., Preissler, J., Decesari, S., Ovadnevaite, <lb/>J., Ceburnis, D., Paglione, M., Facchini, M. C., and O&apos;Dowd, C.: <lb/>Phytoplankton Impact on Marine Cloud Microphysical Proper-<lb/>ties Over the Northeast Atlantic Ocean, J. Geophys. Res.-Atmos., <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/></note>

        <page>2739 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>127, e2021JD036355, https://doi.org/10.1029/2021jd036355, <lb/>2022. <lb/>Mansour, K., Decesari, S., Ceburnis, D., Ovadnevaite, J., and Ri-<lb/>naldi, M.: Machine learning for prediction of daily sea surface <lb/>dimethylsulfide concentration and emission flux over the North <lb/>Atlantic Ocean (1998-2021) Sci. Total Environ., 871, 162123, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.162123, 2023a. <lb/>Mansour, K., Decesari, S., Ceburnis, D., Ovadnevaite, J., Rus-<lb/>sell, L., Paglione, M., O&apos;Dowd, C., and Rinaldi, M.: IPB-<lb/>MSA&amp;SO4: In-situ Produced Biogenic Methanesulfonic Acid <lb/>and Sulfate over the North Atlantic (V1), Mendeley Data [data <lb/>set], https://doi.org/10.17632/j8bzd5dvpx.1, 2023b. <lb/>Marzocchi, A., Hirschi, J. J. M., Holliday, N. P., Cunning-<lb/>ham, S. A., Blaker, A. T., and Coward, A. C.: The <lb/>North Atlantic subpolar circulation in an eddy-resolving <lb/>global ocean model, J. Marine Syst., 142, 126-143, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jmarsys.2014.10.007, 2015. <lb/>McNabb, B. J. and Tortell, P. D.: Improved prediction of dimethyl <lb/>sulfide (DMS) distributions in the northeast subarctic Pacific <lb/>using machine-learning algorithms, Biogeosciences, 19, 1705-<lb/>1721, https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-19-1705-2022, 2022. <lb/>Mendes-Moreira, J., Soares, C., Jorge, A. M., and De Sousa, J. F.: <lb/>Ensemble Approaches for Regression: A Survey, ACM Comput. <lb/>Surv., 45, 10, https://doi.org/10.1145/2379776.2379786, 2012. <lb/>O&apos;Dowd, C., Ceburnis, D., Ovadnevaite, J., Vaishya, A., Ri-<lb/>naldi, M., and Facchini, M. C.: Do anthropogenic, continental <lb/>or coastal aerosol sources impact on a marine aerosol signa-<lb/>ture at Mace Head?, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 14, 10687-10704, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-14-10687-2014, 2014. <lb/>O&apos;Dowd, C., Ceburnis, D., Ovadnevaite, J., Bialek, J., Stengel, D. <lb/>B., Zacharias, M., Nitschke, U., Connan, S., Rinaldi, M., Fuzzi, <lb/>S., Decesari, S., Facchini, M. C., Marullo, S., Santoleri, R., <lb/>Dell&apos;Anno, A., Corinaldesi, C., Tangherlini, M., and Danovaro, <lb/>R.: Connecting marine productivity to sea-spray via nanoscale <lb/>biological processes: Phytoplankton Dance or Death Disco?, <lb/>Scientific Reports, 5, 14883, https://doi.org/10.1038/srep14883, <lb/>2015. <lb/>O&apos;Dowd, C. D., Facchini, M. C., Cavalli, F., Ceburnis, D., Mircea, <lb/>M., Decesari, S., Fuzzi, S., Yoon, Y. J., and Putaud, J. P.: Bio-<lb/>genically driven organic contribution to marine aerosol, Nature, <lb/>431, 676-680, https://doi.org/10.1038/nature02959, 2004. <lb/>Osman, M. B., Das, S. B., Trusel, L. D., Evans, M. J., Fischer, <lb/>H., Grieman, M. M., Kipfstuhl, S., McConnell, J. R., and Saltz-<lb/>man, E. S.: Industrial-era decline in subarctic Atlantic productiv-<lb/>ity, Nature, 569, 551-555, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-019-<lb/>1181-8, 2019. <lb/>Ovadnevaite, J., Ceburnis, D., Leinert, S., Dall&apos;Osto, M., Cana-<lb/>garatna, M., O&apos;Doherty, S., Berresheim, H., and O&apos;Dowd, <lb/>C.: Submicron NE Atlantic marine aerosol chemical com-<lb/>position and abundance: Seasonal trends and air mass cat-<lb/>egorization, J. Geophys. Res.-Atmos., 119, 11850-11863, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/2013jd021330, 2014. <lb/>Quinlan, J. R.: Induction of decision trees, Machine Learning, 1, <lb/>81-106, https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00116251, 1986. <lb/>Quinn, P. K. and Bates, T. S.: The case against climate regulation <lb/>via oceanic phytoplankton sulphur emissions, Nature, 480, 51-<lb/>56, https://doi.org/10.1038/nature10580, 2011. <lb/>Rhein, M., Kieke, D., Huttl-Kabus, S., Roessler, A., Mertens, C., <lb/>Meissner, R., Klein, B., Boning, C. W., and Yashayaev, I.: Deep <lb/>water formation, the subpolar gyre, and the meridional overturn-<lb/>ing circulation in the subpolar North Atlantic, Deep-Sea Res. Pt. <lb/>II, 58, 1819-1832, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.dsr2.2010.10.061, <lb/>2011. <lb/>Riccobono, F., Schobesberger, S., Scott, C. E., Dommen, J., Ortega, <lb/>I. K., Rondo, L., Almeida, J., Amorim, A., Bianchi, F., Breiten-<lb/>lechner, M., David, A., Downard, A., Dunne, E. M., Duplissy, <lb/>J., Ehrhart, S., Flagan, R. C., Franchin, A., Hansel, A., Junni-<lb/>nen, H., Kajos, M., Keskinen, H., Kupc, A., Kurten, A., Kvashin, <lb/>A. N., Laaksonen, A., Lehtipalo, K., Makhmutov, V., Mathot, <lb/>S., Nieminen, T., Onnela, A., Petaja, T., Praplan, A. P., Santos, <lb/>F. D., Schallhart, S., Seinfeld, J. H., Sipila, M., Spracklen, D. <lb/>V., Stozhkov, Y., Stratmann, F., Tome, A., Tsagkogeorgas, G., <lb/>Vaattovaara, P., Viisanen, Y., Vrtala, A., Wagner, P. E., Wein-<lb/>gartner, E., Wex, H., Wimmer, D., Carslaw, K. S., Curtius, J., <lb/>Donahue, N. M., Kirkby, J., Kulmala, M., Worsnop, D. R., and <lb/>Baltensperger, U.: Oxidation Products of Biogenic Emissions <lb/>Contribute to Nucleation of Atmospheric Particles, Science, 344, <lb/>717-721, https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1243527, 2014. <lb/>Rinaldi, M., Facchini, M. C., Decesari, S., Carbone, C., Finessi, <lb/>E., Mircea, M., Fuzzi, S., Ceburnis, D., Ehn, M., Kulmala, <lb/>M., de Leeuw, G., and O&apos;Dowd, C. D.: On the representative-<lb/>ness of coastal aerosol studies to open ocean studies: Mace <lb/>Head -a case study, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 9, 9635-9646, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-9-9635-2009, 2009. <lb/>Rinaldi, M., Decesari, S., Finessi, E., Giulianelli, L., Carbone, <lb/>C., Fuzzi, S., O&apos;Dowd, C. D., Ceburnis, D., and Facchini, <lb/>M. C.: Primary and Secondary Organic Marine Aerosol and <lb/>Oceanic Biological Activity: Recent Results and New Per-<lb/>spectives for Future Studies, Adv. Meteorol., 2010, 310682, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1155/2010/310682, 2010. <lb/>Rinaldi, M., Hiranuma, N., Santachiara, G., Mazzola, M., Man-<lb/>sour, K., Paglione, M., Rodriguez, C. A., Traversi, R., Becagli, <lb/>S., Cappelletti, D., and Belosi, F.: Ice-nucleating particle con-<lb/>centration measurements from Ny-Ålesund during the Arctic <lb/>spring-summer in 2018, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 21, 14725-14748, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-21-14725-2021, 2021. <lb/>Rodriguez, J. D., Perez, A., and Lozano, J. A.: Sensi-<lb/>tivity Analysis of k-Fold Cross Validation in Prediction <lb/>Error Estimation, IEEE T. Pattern Anal., 32, 569-575, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1109/tpami.2009.187, 2010. <lb/>Rolph, G., Stein, A., and Stunder, B.: Real-time En-<lb/>vironmental <lb/>Applications <lb/>and <lb/>Display <lb/>sYstem: <lb/>READY, <lb/>Environ. <lb/>Modell. <lb/>Softw., <lb/>95, <lb/>210-228, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envsoft.2017.06.025, 2017. <lb/>Royer, S. J., Mahajan, A. S., Galí, M., Saltzman, E., and Simo, <lb/>R.: Small-scale variability patterns of DMS and phytoplankton <lb/>in surface waters of the tropical and subtropical Atlantic, In-<lb/>dian, and Pacific Oceans, Geophys. Res. Lett., 42, 475-483, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/2014gl062543, 2015. <lb/>Sachindra, D. A., Ahmed, K., Rashid, M. M., Shahid, S., and <lb/>Perera, B. J. C.: Statistical downscaling of precipitation us-<lb/>ing machine learning techniques, Atmos. Res., 212, 240-258, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.atmosres.2018.05.022, 2018. <lb/>Saliba, G., Chen, C. L., Lewis, S., Russell, L. M., Quinn, P. K., <lb/>Bates, T. S., Bell, T. G., Lawler, M. J., Saltzman, E. S., Sanchez, <lb/>K. J., Moore, R., Shook, M., Rivellini, L. H., Lee, A., Baetge, <lb/>N., Carlson, C. A., and Behrenfeld, M. J.: Seasonal Differ-<lb/>ences and Variability of Concentrations, Chemical Composition, <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2740 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">K. Mansour et al.: IPB-MSA&amp;SO 4 <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>and Cloud Condensation Nuclei of Marine Aerosol Over the <lb/>North Atlantic, J. Geophys. Res.-Atmos., 125, e2020JD033145, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2020jd033145, 2020. <lb/>Sanchez, K. J., Chen, C. L., Russell, L. M., Betha, R., Liu, J., <lb/>Price, D. J., Massoli, P., Ziemba, L. D., Crosbie, E. C., Moore, <lb/>R. H., Muller, M., Schiller, S. A., Wisthaler, A., Lee, A. K. <lb/>Y., Quinn, P. K., Bates, T. S., Porter, J., Bell, T. G., Saltz-<lb/>man, E. S., Vaillancourt, R. D., and Behrenfeld, M. J.: Substan-<lb/>tial Seasonal Contribution of Observed Biogenic Sulfate Parti-<lb/>cles to Cloud Condensation Nuclei, Scientific Reports, 8, 3235, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-21590-9, 2018. <lb/>Sarker, I. H., Kayes, A. S. M., and Watters, P.: Effectiveness analysis <lb/>of machine learning classification models for predicting person-<lb/>alized context-aware smartphone usage, Journal of Big Data, 6, <lb/>57, https://doi.org/10.1186/s40537-019-0219-y, 2019. <lb/>Shabani, S., Samadianfard, S., Sattari, M. T., Mosavi, A., <lb/>Shamshirband, S., Kmet, T., and Varkonyi-Koczy, A. R.: <lb/>Modeling Pan Evaporation Using Gaussian Process Regres-<lb/>sion K-Nearest Neighbors Random Forest and Support Vec-<lb/>tor Machines; Comparative Analysis, Atmosphere, 11, 66, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/atmos11010066, 2020. <lb/>Shen, J. L., Scholz, W., He, X. C., Zhou, P. T., Marie, G., Wang, <lb/>M. Y., Marten, R., Surdu, M., Rorup, B., Baalbaki, R., Amorim, <lb/>A., Ataei, F., Bell, D. M., Bertozzi, B., Brasseur, Z., Caudillo, <lb/>L., Chen, D. X., Chu, B. W., Dada, L., Duplissy, J., Finken-<lb/>zeller, H., Granzin, M., Guida, R., Heinritzi, M., Hofbauer, V., <lb/>Iyer, S., Kemppainen, D., Kong, W. M., Krechmer, J. E., Kurten, <lb/>A., Lamkaddam, H., Lee, C. P., Lopez, B., Mahfouz, N. G. A., <lb/>Manninen, H. E., Massabo, D., Mauldin, R. L., Mentler, B., <lb/>Muller, T., Pfeifer, J., Philippov, M., Piedehierro, A. A., Roldin, <lb/>P., Schobesberger, S., Simon, M., Stolzenburg, D., Tham, Y. J., <lb/>Tome, A., Umo, N. S., Wang, D. Y., Wang, Y. H., Weber, S. K., <lb/>Welti, A., de Jonge, R. W., Wu, Y. S., Zauner-Wieczorek, M., <lb/>Zust, F., Baltensperger, U., Curtius, J., Flagan, R. C., Hansel, <lb/>A., Mohler, O., Petaja, T., Volkamer, R., Kulmala, M., Lehti-<lb/>palo, K., Rissanen, M., Kirkby, J., El-Haddad, I., Bianchi, F., Sip-<lb/>ila, M., Donahue, N. M., and Worsnop, D. R.: High Gas-Phase <lb/>Methanesulfonic Acid Production in the OH-Initiated Oxidation <lb/>of Dimethyl Sulfide at Low Temperatures, Environ. Sci. Tech-<lb/>nol., 56, 13931-13944, https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.2c05154, <lb/>2022. <lb/>Shrestha, N. K. and Shukla, S.: Support vector machine based mod-<lb/>eling of evapotranspiration using hydro-climatic variables in a <lb/>sub-tropical environment, Agr. Forest Meteorol., 200, 172-184, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agrformet.2014.09.025, 2015. <lb/>Simo, R.: Production of atmospheric sulfur by oceanic plankton: <lb/>biogeochemical, ecological and evolutionary links, Trends <lb/>Ecol. Evol., 16, 287-294, https://doi.org/10.1016/s0169-<lb/>5347(01)02152-8, 2001. <lb/>Stein, A. F., Draxler, R. R., Rolph, G. D., Stunder, B. J. B., Cohen, <lb/>M. D., and Ngan, F.: NOAA&apos;s Hysplit Atmospheric Transport <lb/>and Dispersion Modeling System, B. Am. Meteorol. Soc., 96, <lb/>2059-2077, https://doi.org/10.1175/bams-d-14-00110.1, 2015. <lb/>Sydeman, W. J., García-Reyes, M., Schoeman, D. S., Rykaczewski, <lb/>R. R., Thompson, S. A., Black, B. A., and Bograd, S. J.: Climate <lb/>change and wind intensification in coastal upwelling ecosystems, <lb/>Science, 345, 77-80, https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1251635, <lb/>2014. <lb/>Thomas, M. A., Suntharalingam, P., Pozzoli, L., Rast, S., Dev-<lb/>asthale, A., Kloster, S., Feichter, J., and Lenton, T. M.: Quan-<lb/>tification of DMS aerosol-cloud-climate interactions using the <lb/>ECHAM5-HAMMOZ model in a current climate scenario, At-<lb/>mos. Chem. Phys., 10, 7425-7438, https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-<lb/>10-7425-2010, 2010. <lb/>Vapnik, V. N.: The Nature of Statistical Learning Theory, 2, <lb/>Springer New York, NY, https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4757-<lb/>3264-1, 2013. <lb/>Verrelst, J., Rivera, J. P., Gitelson, A., Delegido, J., Moreno, <lb/>J., and Camps-Valls, G.: Spectral band selection for <lb/>vegetation properties retrieval using Gaussian pro-<lb/>cesses regression, Int. J. Appl. Earth Obs., 52, 554-567, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jag.2016.07.016, 2016. <lb/>von Glasow, R. and Crutzen, P. J.: Model study of multiphase DMS <lb/>oxidation with a focus on halogens, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 4, 589-<lb/>608, https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-4-589-2004, 2004. <lb/>Wang, D. W., Gouhier, T. C., Menge, B. A., and Gan-<lb/>guly, A. R.: Intensification and spatial homogenization of <lb/>coastal upwelling under climate change, Nature, 518, 390-394, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/nature14235, 2015. <lb/>Williams, C. K. I. and Rasmussen, C. E.: Gaussian pro-<lb/>cesses for regression, Advances in Neural Information <lb/>Processing Systems 8: Proceedings of the 1995 Confer-<lb/>ence, Denver, Colorado, USA, 3-5 December 1996, 8, <lb/>514-520, <lb/>https://papers.nips.cc/paper_files/paper/1995/hash/ <lb/>7cce53cf90577442771720a370c3c723-Abstract.html <lb/>(last <lb/>access: 10 January 2023), 1996. <lb/>Woodhouse, M. T., Carslaw, K. S., Mann, G. W., Vallina, S. <lb/>M., Vogt, M., Halloran, P. R., and Boucher, O.: Low sensi-<lb/>tivity of cloud condensation nuclei to changes in the sea-air <lb/>flux of dimethyl-sulphide, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 10, 7545-7559, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-10-7545-2010, 2010. <lb/>Zhou, S. Q., Chen, Y., Paytan, A., Li, H. W., Wang, F. H., <lb/>Zhu, Y. C., Yang, T. J., Zhang, Y., and Zhang, R. F.: Non-<lb/>Marine Sources Contribute to Aerosol Methanesulfonate Over <lb/>Coastal Seas, J. Geophys. Res.-Atmos., 126, e2021JD034960, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2021jd034960, 2021. <lb/>Zhou, S. Q., Chen, Y., Wang, F. H., Bao, Y., Ding, X. P., <lb/>and Xu, Z. J.: Assessing the Intensity of Marine Biogenic <lb/>Influence on the Lower Atmosphere: An Insight into the <lb/>Distribution of Marine Biogenic Aerosols over the East-<lb/>ern China Seas, Environ. Sci. Technol., 57, 12741-12751 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.3c04382, 2023. <lb/>Zhu, L., Nenes, A., Wine, P. H., and Nicovich, J. M.: <lb/>Effects of aqueous organosulfur chemistry on particulate <lb/>methanesulfonate to non-sea salt sulfate ratios in the ma-<lb/>rine atmosphere, J. Geophys. Res.-Atmos., 111, D05316, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2005jd006326, 2006. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2717-2740, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2717-2024 </note>


	</text>

</TEI>