<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Return to the Ross Ice Shelf Project (RISP), Site J-9 (1977–1979): perspectives of West Antarctic Ice Sheet history from Miocene and Holocene benthic foraminifera</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Serena N.</forename>
          <surname>Dameron</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>R. Mark</forename>
          <surname>Leckie</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>David</forename>
          <surname>Harwood</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Reed</forename>
          <surname>Scherer</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Peter-Noel</forename>
          <surname>Webb</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-06T08:52:08.866Z">11/6/2025 8:52:08 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Copernicus GmbH</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.5194/jm-43-187-2024</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Serena N. Dameron, R. Mark Leckie, David Harwood, Reed Scherer, Peter-Noel Webb. (2024). Return to the Ross Ice Shelf Project (RISP), Site J-9 (1977–1979): perspectives of West Antarctic Ice Sheet history from Miocene and Holocene benthic foraminifera. Journal of Micropalaeontology, 43(1), 187-209. DOI: 10.5194/jm-43-187-2024</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-06T08:51:58.770027Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-06T08:51:58.770027Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>Atmos. Chem. Phys., 24, 4771-4788, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-24-4771-2024 <lb/>© Author(s) 2024. This work is distributed under <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License. <lb/>Research article <lb/>Characterization of refractory aerosol particles collected <lb/>in the tropical upper troposphere-lower stratosphere <lb/>(UTLS) within the Asian tropopause <lb/>aerosol layer (ATAL) <lb/>Martin Ebert 1 , Ralf Weigel 2 , Stephan Weinbruch 1 , Lisa Schneider 1 , Konrad Kandler 1 , <lb/>Stefan Lauterbach 1 , Franziska Köllner 2,4 , Felix Plöger 3 , Gebhard Günther 3 , Bärbel Vogel 3 , and <lb/>Stephan Borrmann 2,4 <lb/>1 Institut für Angewandte Geowissenschaften, Technische Universität Darmstadt, Darmstadt, Germany <lb/>2 Institut für Physik der Atmosphäre, Johannes Gutenberg-Universität, Mainz, Germany <lb/>3 Institut für Energie und Klimaforschung (IEK-7), Forschungszentrum Jülich, Jülich, Germany <lb/>4 Partikelchemie, Max-Planck-Institut für Chemie, Mainz, Germany <lb/>Correspondence: Martin Ebert (mebert@geo.tu-darmstadt.de) <lb/>Received: 2 October 2023 -Discussion started: 11 October 2023 <lb/>Revised: 28 February 2024 -Accepted: 28 February 2024 -Published: 22 April 2024 <lb/>Abstract. Aerosol particles with diameters larger than 40 nm were collected during the flight campaign Stra-<lb/>toClim 2017 within the Asian tropopause aerosol layer (ATAL) of the 2017 monsoon anticyclone above the <lb/>Indian subcontinent. A multi-impactor system was installed on board the aircraft M-55 Geophysica, which was <lb/>operated from Kathmandu, Nepal. The size and chemical composition of more than 5000 refractory particles/in-<lb/>clusions of 17 selected particle samples from seven different flights were analyzed by use of scanning electron <lb/>microscopy (SEM) and transmission electron microscopy (TEM) combined with energy dispersive X-ray (EDX) <lb/>microanalysis. Based on chemical composition and morphology, the refractory particles were assigned to the <lb/>following particle groups: extraterrestrial, silicates, Fe-rich, Al-rich, Hg-rich, other metals, C-rich, soot, Cl-rich, <lb/>and Ca-rich. <lb/>Most abundant particle groups within the refractory particles are silicates and C-rich (non-volatile organics). <lb/>In samples taken above the tropopause, extraterrestrial particles are becoming increasingly important with rising <lb/>altitude. The most frequent particle sources for the small (maximum in size distribution D P-max = 120 nm) refrac-<lb/>tory particles carried into the ATAL are combustion processes at the ground (burning of fossil fuels/biomass burn-<lb/>ing) and the agitation of soil material. The refractory particles in the ATAL represent only a very small fraction <lb/>(&lt; 2 % by number for particles &gt; 40 nm) of the total aerosol particles, which are dominated by species like am-<lb/>monium, sulfate, nitrate, and volatile organics. During one flight, a large number of very small (D P-max = 25 nm) <lb/>cinnabar particles (HgS) were detected, which are supposed to originate from a ground source such as coal com-<lb/>bustion or underground coal fires. <lb/>Published by Copernicus Publications on behalf of the European Geosciences Union. <lb/></front>

        <page>4772 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">M. Ebert et al.: Characterization of refractory aerosol particles <lb/></note>

        <body>1 Introduction <lb/>Each year during the summer monsoon from June to Septem-<lb/>ber, the Asian tropopause aerosol layer (ATAL) develops in-<lb/>side the Asian monsoon anticyclone (AMA) (Vernier et al., <lb/>2018; Zhang et al., 2019). The ATAL forms in the upper-<lb/>troposphere-lower-stratosphere (UTLS) region at altitudes <lb/>of about 14 to 18 km, corresponding to potential tempera-<lb/>ture levels of 360 to 420 K (Hanumanthu et al., 2020). The <lb/>lateral dimensions of the AMA can extend from the eastern <lb/>Mediterranean up to East Asia (Vernier et al., 2011). <lb/>During the summer monsoon, large-scale convection in <lb/>the Himalayan region provides a strong upward transport of <lb/>gases and particles from the ground to the ATAL. Because <lb/>of &quot;eddy shedding&quot; (Dethof et al., 1999; Popovic and Plumb, <lb/>2001; Pan et al., 2016), a smaller fraction of the particles is <lb/>even transported into the lower stratosphere and can be sub-<lb/>ject to long-range transport there (Vogel et al., 2016, 2019; <lb/>Fujiwara et al., 2021). <lb/>Model analysis by Fairlie et al. (2020) showed the dom-<lb/>inance of regional anthropogenic emissions of particle pre-<lb/>cursors like sulfate, nitrate, ammonia, and organic aerosol <lb/>particles from China and the Indian subcontinent in affect-<lb/>ing observed aerosol concentrations in the ATAL. The first <lb/>in situ mass spectrometric analysis of aerosol particles within <lb/>the ATAL (Appel et al., 2022) determined that the particles <lb/>in the ATAL consist mainly of ammonium nitrate and organ-<lb/>ics. It was further found that up to 70 % of these are formed <lb/>from the conversion of inorganic and organic gas-phase pre-<lb/>cursors rather than from a direct uplift of primary particles <lb/>from the boundary layer. Höpfner et al. (2019) gained impor-<lb/>tant insights into the formation of ammonium nitrate from <lb/>agricultural emissions of ammonia uplifted within the Asian <lb/>monsoon in the UTLS region. <lb/>But still, all details of processes involved in nucleation <lb/>of inorganic compounds (including sulfuric acid, ammonium <lb/>salts, and nitric acid) as well as secondary organic aerosol <lb/>(SOA) formation in the AMA are not completely understood. <lb/>It is also not clear whether aerosol particles from the AMA <lb/>(either transported from below or newly formed within the <lb/>AMA) are a relevant source of the stratospheric Junge layer <lb/>(Appel et al., 2022). <lb/>An increased particle concentration has a variety of severe <lb/>atmospheric implications, including the high relevance for <lb/>the climate system. First, aerosol particles within the ATAL <lb/>can directly influence/affect the radiative budget at the top of <lb/>the atmosphere (Vernier et al., 2015). Second, aerosol parti-<lb/>cles inside the AMA are involved in ice-cloud formation be-<lb/>low the tropopause and in the tropical transition layer (Wag-<lb/>ner et al., 2020; Ueyama et al., 2018). They can act as het-<lb/>erogeneous ice nuclei influencing cirrus cloud properties (see <lb/>e.g., Liu et al., 2009; Fadnavis et al., 2013). <lb/>It was shown in modeling studies that some of UTLS parti-<lb/>cles in the AMA should include refractory components (Fad-<lb/>navis et al., 2013; Lau et al., 2018; Ma et al., 2019), even <lb/>though the main components are sulfuric acid/sulfates, ni-<lb/>tric acid/nitrates, water, ammonium, and organic compounds <lb/>(Appel et al., 2022; Höpfner et al., 2019). <lb/>The physicochemical properties of refractory particles <lb/>(concentration, chemical composition, size, mixing state) are <lb/>important for model calculations of all the processes men-<lb/>tioned above. In lower-stratosphere aerosol particle studies <lb/>conducted outside the AMA, most refractory particles are as-<lb/>sumed to originate from meteoric ablation, space debris, or <lb/>rocket exhaust (e.g., Borrmann et al., 2010; Murphy et al., <lb/>2014; Ebert et al., 2016; Schneider et al., 2021). Apart from <lb/>volcanic eruptions and wildfires, the transport of refractory <lb/>particles from the Earth&apos;s surface is considered to be of mi-<lb/>nor importance (Kremser et al., 2016). <lb/>For the ATAL, vertical transport of gases and particles <lb/>from the boundary layer plays a much larger role. Based on <lb/>the investigation of the transport pathways and the dynamics <lb/>in the tropics, several studies conclude that the most impor-<lb/>tant refractory particles in the ATAL are mineral dust, black <lb/>carbon, metal (oxides), and to a smaller extent meteoric ma-<lb/>terial (e.g., Lelieveld et al., 2018; Lau et al., 2018; Ma et <lb/>al., 2019; Bossolasco et al., 2021). A few studies even state <lb/>that the main constituents within the ATAL are mineral dust <lb/>and black carbon aerosol (Bossolasco et al., 2021; Ma et al., <lb/>2019). On the Indian subcontinent, numerous anthropogenic <lb/>sources exist for small refractory particles which have a low <lb/>enough inertia to enable transport to such high altitudes (e.g., <lb/>Lawrence and Lelieveld, 2010). <lb/>Some of the particles originating on the ground will expe-<lb/>rience scavenging and chemical processing during transport <lb/>through convective mixed-phase clouds. Consequently, the <lb/>chemical composition of aerosol particles in the ATAL may <lb/>differ from the ground conditions (Froyd et al., 2009; Jost <lb/>et al., 2017). However, experimental data on physicochem-<lb/>ical properties of refractory particles within the ATAL and <lb/>their sources are sparse (Vernier et al., 2022). This contribu-<lb/>tion aims to improve the experimental data available in order <lb/>to gain a better understanding of particle transport into the <lb/>ATAL. <lb/>Please be aware that different definitions of the term &quot;re-<lb/>fractory&quot; and &quot;non-volatile&quot; are used in the literature. For <lb/>example, during StratoClim 2017, Mahnke et al. (2021) used <lb/>a multi-channel condensation particle counter and an opti-<lb/>cal particle spectrometer (ultra-high-sensitivity aerosol spec-<lb/>trometer, UHSAS-A) for detecting total aerosol densities of <lb/>submicrometer-sized particles in the ATAL. In these mea-<lb/>surements, particles which have passed through a heated tube <lb/>section of about 1 m length at 270 °C within COPAS (the <lb/>COndensation PArticle counting System) are classified as <lb/>non-volatile. <lb/>In this way, in these measurements some of the secondary <lb/>sulfate, nitrate, and organic particles could be classified as <lb/>non-volatile (i.e., thermostable at up to 270 °C). <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Atmos. Chem. Phys., 24, 4771-4788, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-24-4771-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">M. Ebert et al.: Characterization of refractory aerosol particles <lb/></note>

        <page>4773 <lb/></page>

        <body>In this work, the term refractory refers to all particles that <lb/>are stable during electron bombardment under high-vacuum <lb/>conditions in the scanning electron microscope. <lb/>2 Methods <lb/>2.1 Flight campaign StratoClim 2017 <lb/>Within the EU Seventh Framework Programme project Stra-<lb/>toClim (Stratospheric and upper tropospheric processes for <lb/>better climate predictions), a stratospheric aircraft campaign <lb/>(StratoClim 2017) was conducted in July-August 2017 in <lb/>Kathmandu, Nepal. One main goal was the characterization <lb/>of the Asian tropopause aerosol layer (ATAL) within the <lb/>2017 monsoon anticyclone. In total, eight flights were per-<lb/>formed by the Russian high-altitude aircraft M-55 Geophys-<lb/>ica. The aircraft was equipped with a variety of in situ and <lb/>remote sensing equipment for the measurement of particle <lb/>and gas composition. The flights took place every second <lb/>day during the period 27 July-10 August. Sampling details <lb/>can be found in Table 1. <lb/>The flights were conducted from Kathmandu (Nepal) Trib-<lb/>huvan International Airport (TIA) with a total flight time of <lb/>about 31 h. Three flights (nos. 2, 4, 5) took place exclusively <lb/>above Nepal. These flights were carried out along an axis par-<lb/>allel to the Himalaya over almost the entire east-west exten-<lb/>sion of this country. Three further flights (nos. 3, 7, 8) were <lb/>performed over northeastern India. These flight patterns al-<lb/>lowed the study of the horizontal structure of the AMA over <lb/>large parts of its north-south extension, although the flight <lb/>tracks did not reach beyond the anticyclone core (von Hobe <lb/>et al., 2021). For more details, see Khaykin et al. (2022). <lb/>According to Bucci et al. (2020) and Brunamonti et <lb/>al. (2018), the first half of the StratoClim 2017 campaign <lb/>(nos. 1-4) was less affected by regional convective activity <lb/>than the second half (nos. 5-8). The minimum and maxi-<lb/>mum flight height during the particle collection periods of <lb/>the particle samples studied in detail are given in Table 1. <lb/>The absolute potential temperature ( ) throughout sampling <lb/>based on ambient-condition data (air temperature and static <lb/>pressure from aircraft Unit for Connection with the Scientific <lb/>Equipment (UCSE)) during the sampling period is given as <lb/>boxplots in Fig. 1a. In both parts of Fig. 1, the boxes rep-<lb/>resent the lower and upper quartiles. A horizontal black line <lb/>within the box marks the median and a horizontal red line the <lb/>mean. Whiskers below and above the box indicate the 10th <lb/>and 90th percentiles. Crosshair symbols represent the 5th and <lb/>95th percentiles. <lb/>The boxplot illustration in Fig. 1b illustrates the poten-<lb/>tial temperature ( ) difference from the 1 Hz calculated <lb/>level of the cold point tropopause (CPT) during the sam-<lb/>pling period. Positive (negative) <lb/>values indicate a sam-<lb/>pling above (underneath) the CPT. The CPT potential tem-<lb/>perature is extracted from ERA-Interim data (Weigel et al., <lb/>2021a). The potential temperature ( ) was calculated based <lb/>Figure 1. Boxplot of the absolute potential temperature (a) and <lb/>of the potential temperature <lb/>difference to the 1 Hz calculated <lb/>level of the cold point tropopause (CPT) throughout the sampling <lb/>period (b). <lb/>on UCSE data of ambient temperature and pressure as de-<lb/>fined by the World Meteorological Organization (WMO, <lb/>1966). For the vertical temperature and pressure distribu-<lb/>tion during the impactor collection phases in StratoClim <lb/>2017, the WMO-compliant values deviate by no more than <lb/>∼ 1 K from the results according to the refined calculation <lb/>(Baumgartner et al., 2020). <lb/>2.2 Sampling technique <lb/>Particle samples were taken by the inlet line of COPAS (Cur-<lb/>tius et al., 2005; Weigel et al., 2009; Borrmann et al., 2010) <lb/>with a Y-shape manifold. According to Weigel et al. (2009), <lb/>the inlet efficiency is comparable with the inlet system char-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-24-4771-2024 <lb/>Atmos. Chem. Phys., 24, 4771-4788, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>4774 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">M. Ebert et al.: Characterization of refractory aerosol particles <lb/></note>

        <body>Table 1. Parameters for particle samples (coarse: equivalent projected area diameter &gt; 0.4 µm; fine: equivalent projected area diameter <lb/>0.04-0.4 µm). <lb/>Flight Date <lb/>Sample Particle size <lb/>Sampling <lb/>Sampling <lb/>Flight height <lb/>no. <lb/>[mm/dd/yy] no. <lb/>fraction <lb/>start* [UTC] duration [min] <lb/>[km] <lb/>2 <lb/>07/29/17 <lb/>2.1 <lb/>coarse <lb/>03:22 <lb/>13 <lb/>12.5-15.0 <lb/>3 <lb/>07/31/17 <lb/>3.6 <lb/>coarse <lb/>05:09 <lb/>13 <lb/>19.8 <lb/>4 <lb/>08/02/17 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>coarse <lb/>10:15 <lb/>15 <lb/>17.5-18.0 <lb/>5 <lb/>08/04/17 <lb/>5.2 <lb/>coarse <lb/>04:35 <lb/>18 <lb/>16.3-17.0 <lb/>5.2f <lb/>fine <lb/>04:35 <lb/>18 <lb/>16.3-17.0 <lb/>6 <lb/>08/06/17 <lb/>6.5 <lb/>coarse <lb/>10:05 <lb/>15 <lb/>16.2 <lb/>7 <lb/>08/08/17 <lb/>7.1 <lb/>coarse <lb/>04:29 <lb/>17 <lb/>12.6-14.3 <lb/>7.1f <lb/>fine <lb/>04:29 <lb/>17 <lb/>12.6-14.3 <lb/>7.4 <lb/>coarse <lb/>05:29 <lb/>17 <lb/>13.0-18.0 <lb/>7.4f <lb/>fine <lb/>05:29 <lb/>17 <lb/>13.0-18.0 <lb/>8 <lb/>08/10/17 <lb/>8.1 <lb/>coarse <lb/>09:19 <lb/>17 <lb/>12.0-16.0 <lb/>8.1f <lb/>fine <lb/>09:19 <lb/>17 <lb/>12.0-16.0 <lb/>8.2 <lb/>coarse <lb/>09:40 <lb/>17 <lb/>16.0-17.0 <lb/>8.2f <lb/>fine <lb/>09:40 <lb/>17 <lb/>16.0-17.0 <lb/>8.4 <lb/>coarse <lb/>10:20 <lb/>17 <lb/>17.0 <lb/>8.5f <lb/>fine <lb/>10:40 <lb/>17 <lb/>17.0 <lb/>8.6 <lb/>coarse <lb/>11:01 <lb/>17 <lb/>17.1-17.8 <lb/> * Local time is UTC + 5.45. <lb/>acterized by Hermann et al. (2001). For the superisokineti-<lb/>cally operated, predominantly isoaxially aligned aerosol in-<lb/>let, it is determined that the aspiration, transmission, and <lb/>transport of particles with diameters (D p ) of up to 1 µm <lb/>through the aerosol lines to the instruments occur without <lb/>significant losses. For submicron particles, the transmission <lb/>efficiency of the COPAS inlet is ≥ 90 %. The inlet perfor-<lb/>mance rapidly deteriorates for increasing particle diameters <lb/>and is between 30 %-40 % for particles with 4 µm diameters <lb/>and ≤ 5 % for particles larger than 6 µm. Even larger particles <lb/>(D p &gt; 10 µm) are in general unlikely to be aspirated by the <lb/>inlet despite superisokinetic operation. The sample flow is <lb/>branched towards the multi-cascade impaction system Multi-<lb/>MINI (Ebert et al., 2016) after about three-quarters of the en-<lb/>tire aerosol line between the inlet system and the COPAS en-<lb/>try (after 45 cm of a total length of 55 cm, 0.25 in. stainless-<lb/>steel aerosol line with connections of electrically conductive <lb/>tubing). Downstream of this flow splitter, the sample stream <lb/>is passed via an approximately 20 cm long stainless-steel <lb/>tube (0.25 in. diameter) towards the Multi-MINI impactor. <lb/>The exhaust air from the Multi-MINI impactor pump is led <lb/>into the exhaust line shared with the COPAS system and re-<lb/>leased outside the aircraft. <lb/>In the Multi-MINI, 12 dual-stage impactors are integrated <lb/>into a single housing and particle sampling of the single-<lb/>stage impactors is controlled by a set of valves. A 12-fold <lb/>symmetrical manifold directs the aerosol to the separate <lb/>units. <lb/>The orifices of the individual dual-stage impactors are 0.75 <lb/>and 0.25 mm in diameter. Air velocity in the second nozzle <lb/>is at the speed of sound and is thus controlling the impactor <lb/>flow, which was calculated to be around 7.7 cm 3 s -1 . During <lb/>UTLS sampling, temperature in the COPAS system varied <lb/>between 272 and 290 K and pressure between 50 and 67 hPa. <lb/>In these conditions in the UTLS, 50 % efficiency cut-<lb/>offs (calculated according to Raabe et al., 1988) are a <lb/>∼ 400 nm aerodynamic diameter for the first impactor stage <lb/>and ∼ 40 nm for the second. Please note that under UTLS <lb/>conditions the strictness of the impactor size discrimination <lb/>is inferior compared to tropospheric conditions. <lb/>In this study, particle samples of the first impactor stage <lb/>are referred to as the coarse fraction (&gt; 400 nm) and those of <lb/>the second stage as the fine fraction (∼ 40-400 nm). <lb/>A purge flow system is added to the Multi-MINI, which <lb/>floods the tubing and the interior of the manifold prior to <lb/>each sampling with ambient air to avoid any carryover of par-<lb/>ticles from previous measurements. The purge flow extends <lb/>to the front of the first impaction nozzle, so the potential vol-<lb/>ume affected by carryover is minimal. The purge time (7 min) <lb/>was chosen so that the tube and manifold volume could be <lb/>filled at least 10 times with the current aerosol. Such a purge <lb/>flow system has proven to be crucial in UTLS aerosol parti-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Atmos. Chem. Phys., 24, 4771-4788, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-24-4771-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">M. Ebert et al.: Characterization of refractory aerosol particles <lb/></note>

        <page>4775 <lb/></page>

        <body>cle sampling in order to minimize sampling artifacts, above <lb/>all a carryover from the boundary layer (Ebert et al., 2016). <lb/>During StratoClim 2017, the separate impactors were op-<lb/>erated in the UTLS for 13-18 min each (Table 1). This sam-<lb/>pling time was a compromise between receiving a sufficient <lb/>number of refractory particles and simultaneously avoiding <lb/>an overloading of the sampling substrate by the dominating <lb/>semi-volatile sulfate, organic, and/or nitrate particles, which <lb/>would hinder accurate electron microscopic analysis of the <lb/>much smaller number of refractory particles. Furthermore, <lb/>the chosen sampling time allowed us to collect six UTLS par-<lb/>ticle samples during each flight. <lb/>Particles were collected on Ni transmission electron mi-<lb/>croscopy (TEM) grids (S162-N9, Plano GmbH, Wetzlar, <lb/>Germany). A total of 42 dual-stage impactor samples were <lb/>collected during seven mission flights. The individual sample <lb/>labels follow this sequence. For example, sample 8.5 corre-<lb/>sponds to the fifth particle sampling in flight 8. The first flight <lb/>of the campaign (27 July) was exclusively used for testing <lb/>the sampling setup, including blind sampling for detection <lb/>and elimination of possible particulate artifacts. <lb/>The main goal of the present study is the physicochemi-<lb/>cal characterization and source apportionment of refractory <lb/>particles within the ATAL. These non-volatile particles are <lb/>expected to be very small (&lt; 500 nm) and to occur in very <lb/>small numbers. Furthermore, they will often be embedded in <lb/>or agglomerated with the dominating secondary sulfate, ni-<lb/>trate, and/or organic particles. Please note that the analyzed <lb/>refractory inclusions can be much smaller than the lower cut-<lb/>off diameter of the sampling device. <lb/>It should be emphasized here again that the term &quot;refrac-<lb/>tory&quot; is used in the present paper for all particles which <lb/>are stable during electron bombardment under the high-<lb/>vacuum conditions of the electron microscope in contrast to <lb/>the sulfate-, organic-, and nitrate-containing particles, which <lb/>evaporate quickly. <lb/>2.3 Sampling and analysis strategy <lb/>A major challenge of particle sampling in the UTLS region is <lb/>avoiding sampling artifacts which can be caused by abrasion <lb/>within the aircraft sampling line (manifold, inlet, collector) <lb/>or by carryover of particles from the boundary layer. <lb/>As the particle concentrations in the UTLS are very <lb/>low and refractory particles/inclusions represent the small-<lb/>est share, even a small contribution of refractory artifacts will <lb/>severely distort the results. In order to minimize the risk of ar-<lb/>tifacts, impactor sampling has the advantage that all collected <lb/>particles are deposited within a very small area (impaction <lb/>spot) on the sampling substrate. Since TEM substrates are <lb/>almost particle-free before sampling and in impactor collec-<lb/>tion, the impaction spot on the sampling substrate is very <lb/>small ( 1 mm 2 ), the number of artifact particles is negligi-<lb/>ble if the number of collected particles within the impaction <lb/>spot is high, and no artifact particles originate from the sam-<lb/>pling line itself. In several procedural blank tests (e.g., com-<lb/>plete flight 1), no particulate artifacts were detected in sam-<lb/>ples after the rinsing unit was used. <lb/>Nevertheless, for any individual ambient collection there <lb/>is still the risk of artifact introduction into the samples due <lb/>to individual events during installation, in flight, or during <lb/>removal and transport of the particulate samples. <lb/>To minimize the risk of interpreting artifact particles as <lb/>real refractory components, all samples for which errors were <lb/>recorded during the sample change or afterwards during han-<lb/>dling that could have led to possible contamination were <lb/>sorted out (in total five samples). <lb/>Furthermore, samples were excluded when too few par-<lb/>ticles were found on the substrate as in this case it cannot <lb/>be guaranteed that the number of potential refractory artifact <lb/>particles is negligible. Based on this criterion, many of the <lb/>received particle samples from flight nos. 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6 <lb/>had to be excluded. <lb/>Finally, samples which were selected for analysis but with <lb/>fewer than 25 refractory particles found were also excluded <lb/>for final data analysis for statistical reasons. <lb/>In this way, only 17 out of 84 received particle samples <lb/>were investigated in detail. Of these samples, 6 were fine <lb/>stage and 11 coarse stage. In five cases it was possible to <lb/>analyze fine-and coarse-stage pairs of the same sample (nos. <lb/>5.2, 7.1, 7.4, 8.1, and 8.2). <lb/>2.4 Characterization of refractory particles/inclusions by <lb/>electron microscopy <lb/>Individual particle analysis was performed in a FEI Quanta <lb/>200 (Eindhoven, the Netherlands) FEG environmental scan-<lb/>ning electron microscope (ESEM) equipped with an energy-<lb/>dispersive X-ray (EDX) detector (EDAX, Tilburg, the <lb/>Netherlands). As the instrument was operated under high-<lb/>vacuum conditions only, we will refer to the method as scan-<lb/>ning electron microscopy (SEM) throughout the paper. <lb/>A detailed analysis of the dominating sulfates and nitrate <lb/>particles was not intended. Instead, we focus on the detec-<lb/>tion of refractory particles/inclusions. In a first step, many <lb/>refractory particles were detected using backscattered elec-<lb/>tron (BSE) imaging by their higher average atomic number <lb/>(leading to higher brightness) compared to the dominating <lb/>sulfate, nitrate, and organic species. <lb/>This procedure was successful in detecting externally <lb/>mixed high-Z refractory particles, but low-Z refractory par-<lb/>ticles (dominantly carbonaceous particles) and completely <lb/>embedded refractory inclusions stayed undetected. <lb/>For the detection of embedded refractory inclusions, sev-<lb/>eral thousands to tens of thousands volatile particles in each <lb/>sample were evaporated. This could be achieved by focus-<lb/>ing the electron beam on each individual particle for some <lb/>seconds with SEM. In this way, refractory residuals were de-<lb/>tected in 1 %-2 % of the (vaporized) volatile particles. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-24-4771-2024 <lb/>Atmos. Chem. Phys., 24, 4771-4788, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>4776 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">M. Ebert et al.: Characterization of refractory aerosol particles <lb/></note>

        <body>This time-intensive analytical step (vaporization of <lb/>270 000 individual particles) was also necessary to provide a <lb/>statistically significant number of refractory particles for in-<lb/>dividual particle samples. Using this approach, it was possi-<lb/>ble to analyze a significant number of refractory particles/in-<lb/>clusions (28-741 particles per sample, 5033 in total) in 17 <lb/>flight samples (Table 2). <lb/>Additional measurements were performed in a Jeol 2100 <lb/>transmission electron microscope, which was equipped with <lb/>an Oxford INCA EDX system to determine the mineralogical <lb/>phase of nanometer-sized Hg-rich particles. <lb/>3 Results <lb/>Even though refractory particles play an important role in <lb/>many atmospheric processes in the UTLS (see Introduction) <lb/>they only account for a small fraction of the total aerosol <lb/>population in the ATAL. In this SEM-EDX study, heteroge-<lb/>neous inclusions of refractory components were observed in <lb/>around 2 % of the analyzed ATAL particles. <lb/>During StratoClim 2017, simultaneous aerosol mass spec-<lb/>trometric measurements with the ERICA-LAMS (ERC In-<lb/>strument for Chemical composition of Aerosols laser ab-<lb/>lation mass spectrometer) instrument were conducted. The <lb/>ERICA-LAMS can measure refractory and non-refractory <lb/>aerosol components by laser ablation and the ionization tech-<lb/>nique followed by time-of-flight aerosol mass spectrometry. <lb/>The instrument has been described before in detail (Hünig <lb/>et al., 2022; Dragoneas et al., 2022) and is only briefly re-<lb/>viewed here. Particles enter the system through a pressure-<lb/>controlled inlet (Molleker et al., 2020). The following aero-<lb/>dynamic lens focuses particles into a narrow beam. The par-<lb/>ticles are optically detected by scattering light when passing <lb/>through two laser beams. This setup provides the particle&apos;s <lb/>time of flight and its velocity. By using a calibration with <lb/>particles of known size, density, and shape, we can derive the <lb/>aerodynamic diameter. The d 50 cutoff of the ERICA-LAMS <lb/>is thus limited by the optical particle detection efficiency to <lb/>180 nm. The detected and sized particles are ablated and ion-<lb/>ized by a single triggered laser shot (wavelength = 266 nm), <lb/>and the ions are guided into a time-of-flight mass spectrom-<lb/>eter. As a result, the ERICA-LAMS provides bipolar mass <lb/>spectra and size of individual particles. <lb/>In these measurements, it was determined that between <lb/>20 % and 50 % of all measured particles (by number) in-<lb/>clude refractory material, depending on altitude (Appel et <lb/>al., 2022). The values between the two techniques differ, ob-<lb/>viously, for different reasons. The refractory number abun-<lb/>dance of 2 % determined by SEM-EDX measurements refers <lb/>to refractory heterogeneous inclusions within ATAL particles <lb/>only (see Sect. 2.4), while the value of 20 %-50 % derived <lb/>from mass spectrometry (MS) reflects the proportion of par-<lb/>ticles that provides any refractory signal, including dissolved <lb/>refractory elements, which may also play an important role <lb/>(e.g., for extraterrestrial material, see Schneider et al., 2021, <lb/>and discussion in Sect. 4.3). <lb/>Contrary to earlier modeling studies (Fadnavis et al., 2013; <lb/>Lau et al., 2018; Ma et al., 2019; Bossolasco et al., 2021), we <lb/>found that refractory particles (including desert dust) make <lb/>up the minority aerosol components in the ATAL. <lb/>In all samples, the secondary components (sulfate, nitrate, <lb/>and organic aerosol particles) are the dominant particle types. <lb/>These mainly volatile species, however, are not in the scope <lb/>of this work and are not regarded further. Detailed data on the <lb/>concentration and distribution of the volatile main species <lb/>of UTLS particles during StratoClim 2017 can be found in <lb/>Höpfner et al. (2019), Yu et al. (2022), and Appel et al. <lb/>(2022). <lb/>In total, 5033 refractory particles/inclusions were detected <lb/>within the 17 selected UTLS particle samples. Based on <lb/>EDX spectra and morphological criteria, these refractive par-<lb/>ticles/inclusions were classified into 10 particle groups: sili-<lb/>cate, extraterrestrial, Ca-rich, Cl-rich, Fe-rich, Al-rich, other <lb/>metals, soot, C-rich, and Hg-rich. All refractory particles, <lb/>which fit in none of these groups were summarized in an <lb/>eleventh &quot;other&quot; group. The classification criteria, secondary <lb/>electron images, and EDX spectra of all groups are shown <lb/>in Figs. S3 and S4 in the Supplement. Ni and C are often <lb/>present in the EDX particle spectra because of the Ni grid <lb/>sample substrate used. To take this into account, the classifi-<lb/>cation was carried out in two steps. In the first step, all ele-<lb/>ments (except Ni) with Z ≥ 4 are used for the classification <lb/>of carbon-dominated particle groups (soot and C-rich). In the <lb/>second classification step, all elements with Z ≥ 8 are used <lb/>for the classification of all other particles (Fig. S3). <lb/>It must be noted that because of the small size of most de-<lb/>tected refractory particles (D P &lt; 100 nm for 50 % of all de-<lb/>tected refractory particles), only the major elements of such <lb/>small particles can be detected by EDX and minor elements <lb/>are often not clearly distinguishable from the spectrum back-<lb/>ground. <lb/>The absolute number of detected particles for each group <lb/>and flight sample is given in Table 2, and their relative abun-<lb/>dances are in Fig. 2. <lb/>The smoothed relative size distributions of five refractive <lb/>particle groups are plotted in Fig. 3 (all diameters are pro-<lb/>jected area diameters). Because of the limited number of par-<lb/>ticles, this distribution can only be shown for the most abun-<lb/>dant refractory particle groups. <lb/>Approximately 30 % (1499 out of 5033) of refractory par-<lb/>ticles were Hg-rich particles with very small diameters (max-<lb/>imum of size distribution D P-max = 25 nm). These particles <lb/>occur almost exclusively in all samples of flight 8. Based on <lb/>the absolute particle numbers, it is assumed that the Hg-rich <lb/>particles are an additional load. Since relative abundances are <lb/>compositional data (i.e., they have a constant sum), the com-<lb/>parison of samples from different days can be misleading. <lb/>Therefore, the Hg-rich particles were excluded in the further <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Atmos. Chem. Phys., 24, 4771-4788, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-24-4771-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">M. Ebert et al.: Characterization of refractory aerosol particles <lb/></note>

        <page>4777 <lb/></page>

        <body>Table 2. Number of analyzed refractory particles/inclusions after evaporation of the volatile matrix. <lb/>Sample number 2.1 <lb/>3.6 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>5.2 5.2f * 6.5 <lb/>7.1 7.1f * <lb/>7.4 7.4f * <lb/>8.1 8.1f * <lb/>8.2 8.2f * <lb/>8.4 8.5f * <lb/>8.6 Total <lb/>Extraterrestrial <lb/>1 <lb/>16 <lb/>35 <lb/>25 <lb/>10 <lb/>33 <lb/>3 <lb/>19 <lb/>52 <lb/>28 <lb/>11 <lb/>8 <lb/>12 <lb/>15 <lb/>3 <lb/>14 <lb/>296 <lb/>Silicate <lb/>15 <lb/>62 <lb/>71 <lb/>76 <lb/>22 <lb/>29 <lb/>42 <lb/>306 <lb/>87 <lb/>88 <lb/>35 <lb/>241 <lb/>15 <lb/>43 <lb/>54 <lb/>57 1622 <lb/>Ca-rich <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>6 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>18 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>7 <lb/>2 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>7 <lb/>94 <lb/>Cl-rich <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>8 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>2 <lb/>6 <lb/>47 <lb/>Fe-rich <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>9 <lb/>7 <lb/>6 <lb/>10 <lb/>61 <lb/>11 <lb/>14 <lb/>14 <lb/>28 <lb/>35 <lb/>24 <lb/>3 <lb/>16 <lb/>315 <lb/>Al-rich <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>8 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>39 <lb/>Other metals <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>9 <lb/>5 <lb/>3 <lb/>39 <lb/>55 <lb/>12 <lb/>13 <lb/>25 <lb/>41 <lb/>23 <lb/>10 <lb/>6 <lb/>10 <lb/>302 <lb/>Soot <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>13 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>20 <lb/>1 <lb/>18 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>1 <lb/>8 <lb/>23 <lb/>8 <lb/>124 <lb/>C-rich <lb/>5 <lb/>39 <lb/>21 <lb/>26 <lb/>19 <lb/>8 <lb/>4 <lb/>61 <lb/>14 <lb/>24 <lb/>53 <lb/>66 <lb/>12 <lb/>35 <lb/>11 <lb/>85 <lb/>531 <lb/>Hg-rich <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 303 <lb/>26 <lb/>38 <lb/>454 <lb/>288 292 1499 <lb/>Others <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>22 <lb/>32 <lb/>5 <lb/>14 <lb/>11 <lb/>11 <lb/>6 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>5 <lb/>164 <lb/>Total <lb/>28 134 140 156 <lb/>89 <lb/>83 125 <lb/>581 197 <lb/>207 467 <lb/>431 154 <lb/>602 <lb/>395 501 5033 <lb/> * f denotes fine-stage sample 0.04-0.4 µm equivalent projected diameter. <lb/>Figure 2. Relative number abundance of refractory aerosol particles/inclusions within the 17 UTLS flight samples from seven different <lb/>flights during StratoClim 2017 (f denotes fine stage). <lb/>comparisons of the relative particle abundance in this section <lb/>and are discussed separately (Sect. 4.4). <lb/>3.1 Extraterrestrial material <lb/>Mg-rich silicates as well as Mg-and Fe-rich particles were <lb/>classified as extraterrestrial (chondritic composition as pro-<lb/>posed by Rietmeijer, 1998). Following the Rietmeijer clas-<lb/>sification, the extraterrestrial group has an average relative <lb/>abundance of 11 % within the refractory particles (2 %-40 % <lb/>in the individual samples). The average particle diameter <lb/>(D P ) was 290 nm. <lb/>3.2 Silicates <lb/>All particles with Si and O as major elements but without Mg <lb/>were classified as silicates. As minor elements Na, Al, K, Ca, <lb/>and Fe were often found. In total, % of all detected refrac-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-24-4771-2024 <lb/>Atmos. Chem. Phys., 24, 4771-4788, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>4778 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">M. Ebert et al.: Characterization of refractory aerosol particles <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 3. Smoothed relative size distribution of five refractory par-<lb/>ticle/inclusion groups (dN * is the total number of analyzed refrac-<lb/>tory particles/inclusions of a specific group within all 17 analyzed <lb/>samples.). <lb/>tory particles were classified as silicates. They were found in <lb/>all 17 samples with an abundance between 21 % and 58 %, <lb/>which means these particles belong to the most abundant re-<lb/>fractory particle group. D P-max for the silicates was found to <lb/>be 120 nm (D P = 170 nm). <lb/>3.3 Ca-rich <lb/>All particles with Ca and O as major elements were classified <lb/>as Ca-rich. Additionally, carbon was found in most of these <lb/>particles as the main element. <lb/>The abundance of the Ca-rich particle group is mostly low. <lb/>In only 5 of the 17 samples does this group contribute to more <lb/>than 2 % of the detected refractory particles (maximum 7 %). <lb/>D P of the Ca-rich particles is 210 nm. <lb/>3.4 Cl-rich <lb/>Particles with Cl as the main peak were classified as Cl-rich. <lb/>Besides Cl, only carbon and oxygen were detected as the <lb/>main peaks. Single Cl-rich particles were detected in 15 of <lb/>the 17 samples but always with very low abundances (0 %-<lb/>4 %). With 510 nm, these particles have the largest D P of all <lb/>refractory particle groups. <lb/>3.5 Fe-rich <lb/>Particles with Fe and O as the main peak (without detectable <lb/>Mg) were classified as Fe-rich. Most of these particles show <lb/>no other metal peaks; only in single particles were very small <lb/>peaks of Al, Cr, or Mn detected. Fe-rich particles were ob-<lb/>served in all 17 particle samples with an average abundance <lb/>of 9 % (2 %-30 %). D P of Fe-rich particles was 250 nm. <lb/>3.6 Al-rich <lb/>Aluminum-and oxygen-rich particles were classified as Al-<lb/>rich. These particles play only a minor role in the UTLS, <lb/>and only some individual particles were detected (average <lb/>1 %, range 0 %-4 %). D P-max was found at 125 nm (D P = <lb/>250 nm). <lb/>3.7 Other metals <lb/>Besides Al-and Fe-rich particles, about 300 refractory par-<lb/>ticles of different metals (or metal oxides) were detected <lb/>and summarized in the group named &quot;other metals&quot;. Most <lb/>of these particles were Mn-rich (78), Cr-rich (71), Zn-rich <lb/>(63), Sn-rich (26), Pb-rich (20), W-rich (17), or Ti-rich (14). <lb/>Additionally, a few individual particles of Ba, La, Mg, Sb, <lb/>Cu, and Ce were found. D P of this group was 290 nm. <lb/>3.8 C-rich and soot <lb/>All refractory particles, which show only carbon and oxygen <lb/>peaks, were classified as soot or C-rich. Soot can be recog-<lb/>nized in SEM by its typical morphology of agglomerates of <lb/>spherical primary particles. As the lateral resolution of the <lb/>SEM instrument is limited and the characteristic morphology <lb/>described is often no longer observable for very small soot <lb/>particles (D P ≤ 100 nm), this morphological criterion cannot <lb/>be applied for these particles. Thus, the abundance of the soot <lb/>group represents a minimum share and the received average <lb/>diameter of this group (D P = 250 nm) will be too high. Soot <lb/>particles were detected in 13 of the 17 samples. All refrac-<lb/>tory carbon-rich particles which could not clearly be identi-<lb/>fied as soot were categorized as C-rich. C-rich particles (or <lb/>non-volatile organic compounds, NVOCs) were detected in <lb/>all 17 samples with an average abundance of 17 % (3 %-<lb/>41 %). D P of the C-rich group was 180 nm. As the TEM <lb/>mesh is also excited in the case of very small particles, the <lb/>C background in the spectrum is significantly increased in <lb/>many of these spectra, which generally makes the clear iden-<lb/>tification of small carbonaceous (C-rich and soot) particles <lb/>more difficult. Therefore, the proportion of refractory car-<lb/>bonaceous particles shown in this work is only a minimum <lb/>proportion. Other studies have clearly demonstrated the spe-<lb/>cial importance of organic particles in the ATAL (e.g., Appel <lb/>et al., 2022). <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Atmos. Chem. Phys., 24, 4771-4788, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-24-4771-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">M. Ebert et al.: Characterization of refractory aerosol particles <lb/></note>

        <page>4779 <lb/></page>

        <body>4 Discussion <lb/>4.1 Sources of the refractory particles in the AMA <lb/>4.1.1 Extraterrestrial <lb/>For the classification of stratospheric particles, a broader <lb/>classification than was used here is often applied. For ex-<lb/>ample, in the NASA cosmic dust catalogue (Warren et al., <lb/>2011) not only chondritic compositions but also composi-<lb/>tions strongly modified by ablative heating or melting dur-<lb/>ing passage through the atmosphere are classified as &quot;cos-<lb/>mic&quot;. Following the NASA definition (which is not com-<lb/>pletely applicable to this work as it is defined for optical mi-<lb/>croscopic data of large super-µm particles), all particles from <lb/>our extraterrestrial-, silicate-, and Fe-rich groups would be <lb/>classified as cosmic. The NASA definition is appropriate for <lb/>stratospheric particles, collected well above the tropopause <lb/>where little terrestrial admixture is present. For particles col-<lb/>lected below the tropopause and especially inside the ATAL, <lb/>where terrestrial silicate material increasingly enters, an un-<lb/>ambiguous attribution of Mg-, Si-, and/or Fe-containing par-<lb/>ticles to a terrestrial or extraterrestrial source is difficult. <lb/>Thus, the classification of extraterrestrial particles in the up-<lb/>per troposphere used here is associated with a substantial un-<lb/>certainty. <lb/>Furthermore, it has to be considered that after ablation pro-<lb/>cesses, a part of the incoming extraterrestrial material (iron) <lb/>may be &quot;dissolved&quot; in sulfuric acid droplets (discussion in <lb/>Sect. 4.3). If the total extraterrestrial input should be esti-<lb/>mated, both the dissolved fraction and the refractory parti-<lb/>cles/inclusions must be considered. <lb/>4.1.2 Silicates <lb/>The particles of the silicate group (Si-and O-rich and Mg-<lb/>free) show the typical element signatures of terrestrial sili-<lb/>cates with minor elements, for example Na, Al, K, Ca, or Fe. <lb/>Soil, coal burning and modified extraterrestrial material <lb/>are the three most important sources for the silicates. Only <lb/>the smallest soil particles managed transport into the UTLS, <lb/>while the larger ones sedimented prior to this due to their <lb/>inertia. <lb/>4.1.3 Ca-rich <lb/>As most of the Ca-rich particles also contain C and S as major <lb/>elements (sometimes Mg and K as minor elements), they are <lb/>interpreted as calcium carbonates (calcite/dolomite) or cal-<lb/>cium sulfates (gypsum/anhydrite). The main sources of these <lb/>Ca-rich particles are soil and industrial combustion processes <lb/>such as coal and fossil fuel burning. <lb/>4.1.4 Cl-rich <lb/>Particles containing only Cl, C, and O as the main elements <lb/>are interpreted as an organochlorine compound from indus-<lb/>trial or secondary processes. An internal mixture of sea salt <lb/>and organic particles is also conceivable, but it is unlikely, as <lb/>Na and Mg were not detected in any of these particles. <lb/>4.1.5 Fe-rich <lb/>While the highest observed abundance of the Fe-rich group <lb/>for samples from flights 2-7 was 11 % (range 2 %-11 %), <lb/>in samples of flight 8, significantly higher abundances of up <lb/>to 30 % (range 7 %-30 %) were encountered. Since flight 8 <lb/>is characterized by a strong updraft (Sect. 4.3 and 4.4) and <lb/>there is an increased input of terrestrial refractory particles <lb/>in these samples, it is assumed that a large fraction of these <lb/>Fe-rich particles stem from terrestrial sources, most likely <lb/>due to industrial high-temperature processes (e.g., in forges <lb/>or smelters) and burning of fossil fuels. However, the terres-<lb/>trial/extraterrestrial origin of Fe-rich particles in the UTLS <lb/>is a subject of current debate and an extraterrestrial origin <lb/>of single Fe-rich particles cannot be excluded (Ebert et al., <lb/>2016). <lb/>4.1.6 Al-rich <lb/>Al-rich particles are supposed to be mainly aluminum ox-<lb/>ide and originate either from Al-rich minerals or from solid <lb/>rocket fuel exhausts (Mackinnon et al., 1982; Cziczo et al., <lb/>2002). Al-rich particles in the stratosphere and their impact <lb/>on stratospheric ozone have been studied since the early <lb/>1970s (Hoshizaki et al., 1975; Denison et al., 1994; Jackman <lb/>et al., 1998; Danilin et al., 2001). <lb/>Cofer et al. (1991) measured a bimodal size distribution <lb/>of aluminum oxide particles in the Space Shuttle plume <lb/>with peaks at &lt; 0.3 and 2 µm, while in this study no super-<lb/>micrometer-sized Al particles were detected. <lb/>4.1.7 Other metals <lb/>Anthropogenic high-temperature processes and burning of <lb/>fossil fuels are assumed to be the main sources of the di-<lb/>verse metal/metal oxide particles (Mn, Cr, Zn, Sn, Pb, W, Ti) <lb/>detected in this study. <lb/>4.1.8 Soot <lb/>During data analysis, the assumption that the abundance of <lb/>the small refractory particles/inclusions would be the same in <lb/>the coarse and fine stages was disproved for the soot group. <lb/>Soot is observed at higher abundances for the fine-stage par-<lb/>ticles (3 %-22 %) in contrast to the coarse-stage ones (0 %-<lb/>5 %). As soot agglomerates have a very small aerodynamic <lb/>diameter (small D P , low density, and high pore volume) and <lb/>-in contrast to all other refractory particles -they were often <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-24-4771-2024 <lb/>Atmos. Chem. Phys., 24, 4771-4788, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>4780 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">M. Ebert et al.: Characterization of refractory aerosol particles <lb/></note>

        <body>not embedded within larger particles, a much higher abun-<lb/>dance of these particles was found for the fine stage. Fos-<lb/>sil fuel burning, industrial processes, and traffic are the most <lb/>likely terrestrial sources. However, no strong enrichment of <lb/>soot was observed for flights 7 and 8, which were character-<lb/>ized by significant updraft. <lb/>4.1.9 C-rich <lb/>The sources for the small refractory carbon-rich particles <lb/>and NVOCs are nucleation processes. Sources of such nu-<lb/>cleation particles can be either natural or anthropogenic pri-<lb/>mary emissions at the ground (e.g., fossil fuel burning) as <lb/>well as secondary atmospheric processes. During the Strato-<lb/>Clim aircraft campaign in 2017, it was detected that organics <lb/>in general along with ammonium, sulfate, and nitrate are the <lb/>main constituents of the ATAL (Yu et al., 2022). <lb/>4.2 Absolute concentration of refractory particles in the <lb/>AMA <lb/>All abundances of refractory particles discussed so far are <lb/>relative proportions. Direct estimation of absolute concentra-<lb/>tions is associated with large uncertainties. The two main un-<lb/>certainties are the poorly known collection efficiency in the <lb/>airborne particle collection system under extreme and vari-<lb/>able ambient conditions and the inhomogeneous deposition <lb/>of the secondary particles (splattering) on the TEM grids. <lb/>Therefore, the main discussion is focused on the relative pro-<lb/>portions to avoid misinterpretations. <lb/>Nevertheless, an estimation can be made about the quan-<lb/>titative proportion of refractory particles by the known total <lb/>aerosol concentration (Appel et al., 2022; Yu et al., 2022; <lb/>Höpfner et al., 2019) and the determined ratio of the refrac-<lb/>tive particles / volatile particles in this work. During Stra-<lb/>toClim 2017, a total of 5033 refractory particles / residuals <lb/>within 270 000 analyzed volatile sulfate, nitrate, and organic <lb/>particles was found (∼ 1.9 % by number). The total particu-<lb/>late concentration in the ATAL during StratoClim 2017 was <lb/>on the order of 1-2 µg m -3 (Appel et al., 2022; Yu et al., <lb/>2022; Höpfner et al., 2019). Taking into account the small <lb/>size of most refractory particles/inclusions, we estimate that <lb/>the total concentration of refractory particles in the ATAL <lb/>above Nepal during StratoClim 2017 will be &lt; 10 ng m -3 . <lb/>This estimate is based on our definition of refractory parti-<lb/>cles and represents a lower estimate, as we do not capture all <lb/>refractory residues (especially refractory organic particles) in <lb/>the SEM analysis described above. <lb/>4.3 Variability in the relative abundance of refractory <lb/>particles in the AMA <lb/>For the whole StratoClim 2017 campaign, the silicate group <lb/>was the main refractory particle group (41 %), followed by <lb/>carbonaceous particles (17 %) and extraterrestrial particles <lb/>(11 %). Fe-rich particles and those classified as other met-<lb/>als also occur at higher relative abundance (8 % each), while <lb/>only minor portions (1 %-4 % each) were determined of <lb/>the Ca-rich, chloride, Al-rich, and soot groups. All percent-<lb/>ages given above are calculated without Hg particles (see <lb/>Sect. 3.1), which are discussed separately (Sect. 4.4). <lb/>Only a small fraction of refractory particles emitted <lb/>at the ground reach the lower stratosphere, and only a <lb/>small fraction of extraterrestrial particles reach the AMA. <lb/>This can be seen from the average ratio of ground-<lb/>emitted / extraterrestrial refractory particles, which drops <lb/>from 16.6 in all samples collected below the tropopause <lb/>(2743 ground-emitted particles / 165 extraterrestrial parti-<lb/>cles) to 4.2 in all samples collected above the tropopause <lb/>(549 ground-emitted particles / 131 extraterrestrial parti-<lb/>cles). During StratoClim 2017, terrestrial particles dominate <lb/>the composition of refractory particles clearly in the ATAL <lb/>and slightly above the tropopause. <lb/>In our measurements the relative number abundance of <lb/>the extraterrestrial particles decreases from 19.3 % above the <lb/>tropopause to 5.7 % below the tropopause (within the refrac-<lb/>tory particles). In the same campaign, a substantial decrease <lb/>from 13.3 % to 0.3 % was also detected by Schneider et al. <lb/>(2021) by single-particle mass MS with the ERICA instru-<lb/>ment. A variety of stratospheric MS measurements have de-<lb/>tected signatures of elements from meteoric material within a <lb/>significant fraction of the dominant sulfuric acid/sulfate par-<lb/>ticles (Murphy et al., 1998, 2014; Cziczo et al., 2001; Froyd <lb/>et al., 2009; Schütze et al., 2017). <lb/>However, the results of Schneider et al. (2021) and our <lb/>measurements cannot be compared directly due to the differ-<lb/>ent size range analyzed and the different sensitivity of the two <lb/>analytical techniques. Furthermore, the complete extraterres-<lb/>trial material detected by ERICA will not be present in the <lb/>form of heterogeneous refractory particles. Instead, after ab-<lb/>lation, some fraction of the extraterrestrial material may be <lb/>dissolved within sulfuric acid droplets (Kremser et al., 2016). <lb/>For example, Murphy et al. (2014) assumed that Fe, Ni, and <lb/>Mg within UTLS particles are dissolved, while Si and Al <lb/>may be present in the form of refractory solid inclusions. Fe <lb/>and Mg occurring in small amounts within sulfate particles <lb/>collected at 2-8 km height in the vicinity of a tropopause <lb/>fold over the western Pacific in 2013 were also interpreted <lb/>as dissolved components originating from meteoric ablation <lb/>(Adachi et al., 2022). <lb/>The presence of Fe and Mg in dissolved form would ex-<lb/>plain the fact that in our SEM study only a very small number <lb/>of solid Mg-rich Fe particles were found and that the parti-<lb/>cles classified as extraterrestrial mainly consist of Mg-rich <lb/>silicates. Furthermore, this partial dissolution of some mete-<lb/>oric elements will also strongly modify the composition of <lb/>the resulting silicates (in contrast to the composition of orig-<lb/>inal meteoric material). Thus, it is possible that some of the <lb/>particles classified as silicates in this study will have an ex-<lb/>traterrestrial origin. At least in the samples collected above <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Atmos. Chem. Phys., 24, 4771-4788, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-24-4771-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">M. Ebert et al.: Characterization of refractory aerosol particles <lb/></note>

        <page>4781 <lb/></page>

        <body>the tropopause, a relevant part of the silicate particles may be <lb/>residuals of ablation processes, even when it is not possible <lb/>to differentiate them from terrestrial silicates by their main <lb/>elemental composition. <lb/>The relative abundance of all terrestrial refractory parti-<lb/>cle groups shows quite low variability within the 17 different <lb/>flight samples regardless of the specific flight altitude. This is <lb/>remarkable as some samples were collected at the lowermost <lb/>levels of the ATAL (e.g., sample 2.1 in 12.5-15 km), some <lb/>samples well within the ATAL (just below the tropopause), <lb/>and some samples significantly above the tropopause (e.g., <lb/>sample 3.6 in the free stratosphere at 19.8 km). This implies <lb/>that a small fraction of the refractory particles emitted at the <lb/>ground were transported into the lower stratosphere in the <lb/>Asian monsoon region in 2017. This is consistent with re-<lb/>sults of CO 2 measurements during StratoClim, showing that <lb/>during the Asian monsoon spatio-temporal patterns of CO 2 <lb/>on the Indian subcontinent driven by regional flux variations <lb/>rapidly propagate to approximately 13 km with slower ascent <lb/>above. Enhanced CO 2 compared to the stratospheric back-<lb/>ground can be detected at up to 20 km. Mixing with older <lb/>stratospheric air indicated by the decrease in measured N 2 O <lb/>is found above ∼ 17.5 km (400 K potential temperature) (Vo-<lb/>gel et al., 2023a). <lb/>Even when in our measurements no strong correlation be-<lb/>tween the relative abundance of the terrestrial refractory par-<lb/>ticle groups and the flight height was observed, a dependence <lb/>on meteorology of the specific flight day was seen. <lb/>Bucci et al. (2020) showed that there was an enhanced con-<lb/>vective influence in the second part of the StratoClim 2017 <lb/>campaign (flights 5-8). This also becomes visible in the in-<lb/>creasing abundance of specific groups of refractive particles <lb/>for flights 7 and 8. <lb/>For flight 7, the abundance of other metals is enhanced <lb/>(on average from 3.3 % for flights 2-6 to 13.3 %). On this <lb/>day various small metallic/alloy particles (dominantly Cr-, <lb/>Mn-, and Zn-rich) from a specific ground region were trans-<lb/>ported into the ATAL. The ground regions from which the <lb/>strongest input (or updraft) was observed indicate indus-<lb/>trial high-temperature emissions in the Indo-Gangetic Plain-<lb/>northern India as the source for these particles. <lb/>Flight 8 represents a special situation. In these samples the <lb/>relative abundance of the Fe-rich and other metal group is <lb/>increased in comparison to the results from all samples of <lb/>flights 2-6 (Table 2). Additionally, a large share of Hg-rich <lb/>particles were detected in all samples of flight 8. These Hg-<lb/>rich particles were almost absent in all other flight samples. <lb/>All three refractory particle groups are supposed to orig-<lb/>inate from fossil fuel burning or industrial high-temperature <lb/>processes. The specific source (or sources) is (are) located in <lb/>northeastern India or southern China. A detailed discussion <lb/>of sources and pathways of the Hg-rich particles is given in <lb/>the following subsection. <lb/>4.4 Mercury-rich particles <lb/>Besides the refractory particle groups discussed so far, Hg-<lb/>rich particles were detected in all samples of flight 8 (10 Au-<lb/>gust 2017). They were the most abundant particle group in <lb/>flight 8 (1491 particles in total, on average 45 % of all refrac-<lb/>tory particles), while Hg-rich particles were almost absent in <lb/>the 11 samples of flights 2-7 (in total only eight Hg-rich par-<lb/>ticles). <lb/>Mercury is of high interest due to its toxicity and its ability <lb/>to undergo long-range transport in the atmosphere. Natural <lb/>sources include volcanic emissions, geothermal sources, and <lb/>biomass burning. South Asia is known to show enhanced an-<lb/>thropogenic Hg emissions (Kumari et al., 2015) from metal <lb/>refining, incineration of waste, smelters, and manufacturing <lb/>units, as well as coal and oil combustion (Pirrone et al., <lb/>2010). <lb/>All Hg-rich particles during StratoClim 2017 are very <lb/>small with a D P-max of 25 nm (Fig. 3). They agglomerate on <lb/>the surface of larger sulfate, nitrate, and/or organic particles. <lb/>The small size is a clear indicator that these particles are <lb/>formed by nucleation. The most probable terrestrial source <lb/>for this of Hg-particle precursors will be the burning of fossil <lb/>fuels (e.g., coal burning). Almost identical Hg-rich particles <lb/>were found by Weinbruch et al. (2022) in samples directly <lb/>taken at the stacks of diesel-and coal-fired power plants on <lb/>Svalbard. During fossil fuel burning, mercury mainly passes <lb/>into the gas phase as Hg 0 . However, in the original plume <lb/>directly, parts of Hg 0 may adsorb as Hg II components on <lb/>the surface of existing particles. For example, Seigneur et al. <lb/>(1998) show that adsorption of Hg II species such as HgO and <lb/>HgS on the surface of aerosol particles can account for up to <lb/>35 % of total atmospheric mercury emissions. <lb/>In order to identify the specific mineralogical phase of <lb/>these Hg-rich particles, additional measurements were per-<lb/>formed using transmission electron microscopy (TEM). All <lb/>25 particles examined by TEM-EDX (D P = 15-35 nm) have <lb/>an Hg : S atomic ratio of about 1, while no other elements <lb/>(besides carbon and oxygen) were detected. In high resolu-<lb/>tion within the Hg-rich particles (Fig. 4), lattice planes could <lb/>be imaged (Fig. 4 right inset) and diffraction patterns could <lb/>be obtained (Fig. 4 left inset). The indexing confirmed HgS <lb/>(cinnabar) as the phase for all Hg-rich particles studied. Nu-<lb/>cleation of HgS particles can only take place under reducing <lb/>conditions. Such conditions can exist in soils or during fos-<lb/>sil fuel burning at the ground but are unlikely in the UTLS. <lb/>Therefore, we conclude that the small HgS particles were al-<lb/>ready formed at the ground and then entered the UTLS as <lb/>primary particles with an appropriate updraft. Most proba-<lb/>bly, the small HgS particles will agglomerate quite fast on <lb/>the surface of other existing particles (organics, sulfate, ni-<lb/>trates, or soot). This assumption is also supported by the <lb/>fact that cinnabar particles were only found in samples from <lb/>one flight (flight 8). If these particles had been formed in <lb/>a secondary process in the lower stratosphere or near the <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-24-4771-2024 <lb/>Atmos. Chem. Phys., 24, 4771-4788, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>4782 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">M. Ebert et al.: Characterization of refractory aerosol particles <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 4. High-resolution TEM image of a small 20 nm polycrys-<lb/>talline HgS (cinnabar) particle. Inset left: corresponding conver-<lb/>gent beam electron diffraction (CBED) pattern. Inset right: inverse <lb/>fast Fourier transform (IFFT) image from the area indicated by the <lb/>square. <lb/>tropopause, they would instead have been found as a general <lb/>component in all flight samples of StratoClim 2017 collected <lb/>near the tropopause and especially in the samples of flight 3, <lb/>taken in the free stratosphere, which was not the case. <lb/>To identify a possible cinnabar source region at the <lb/>ground, back trajectories were calculated based on the Chem-<lb/>ical Lagrangian Model of the Stratosphere (ClaMS) using <lb/>high-resolution ERA5 reanalysis (for details see Vogel et al., <lb/>2023a, b). The trajectories were calculated starting at the spe-<lb/>cific UTLS particle sampling time and location back to the <lb/>start of the monsoon season (1 June 2017). Endpoints are <lb/>shown for all trajectories that had reached the model bound-<lb/>ary layer by then. Furthermore, in order to identify the po-<lb/>sition of the strongest uplift of air along the back trajecto-<lb/>ries, the mean location of the strongest change in potential <lb/>temperature along the back trajectories (running mean over <lb/>6 h) was calculated. The results for flight sample 8.5 (exem-<lb/>plary for all very similar graphs of the flight-8 samples) are <lb/>shown in Fig. 5 (the results for all other samples are given in <lb/>Fig. S2 in the Supplement). The frequency distribution (fd) of <lb/>air mass origins shows that the possible source regions for an <lb/>entry of terrestrial particles are located in the Indo-Gangetic <lb/>Plain and northeastern Indian subcontinent and in southern <lb/>China. Anthropogenic emissions in the Indo-Gangetic Plain <lb/>are higher compared to other regions in India, caused by the <lb/>dense concentration of industries as well as by the very high <lb/>population density in this area. Air masses transported from <lb/>the Indo-Gangetic Plain (or passing it) take up the anthro-<lb/>pogenic emissions and are mainly uplifted along the south-<lb/>Figure 5. (a) Frequency distribution (fd) of air mass origins at the <lb/>model boundary layer for sample 8.5. Back trajectories were calcu-<lb/>lated using ERA5 reanalysis back to the start time of the monsoon <lb/>season (1 June 2017). Only back trajectories are considered to have <lb/>reached the model boundary layer by then. (b) The frequency dis-<lb/>tribution (fd) of the mean location of the strongest change in po-<lb/>tential temperature along the back trajectories (running mean over <lb/>6 h), indicating the position of the strongest uplift of air along the <lb/>trajectory. <lb/>ern edge of the Himalaya or by strong convection to UTLS <lb/>altitudes. <lb/>These specific source regions as well as meteorological <lb/>conditions for particle transport from the ground to the UTLS <lb/>for this flight are discussed in detail by Bucci et al. (2020), <lb/>who studied the impact of deep convective transport on the <lb/>ATAL during the StratoClim 2017 campaign. They describe <lb/>that the CO values during flight 8 decrease from around <lb/>80 ppm to below 60 ppm (see also Lee et al., 2021), and <lb/>O 3 concentrations increase from around 120 ppbv to around <lb/>150 ppbv. This corresponds to an increasing mixing of strato-<lb/>spheric air and a decrease in the convective influence from <lb/>100 % to around 50 %. For the HgS particles of flight 8, this <lb/>could indicate a stratospheric source. However, Bucci et al. <lb/>(2020) also show in a detailed analysis that flight 8 captured <lb/>some very intense overshoots and convective outflows from <lb/>exceptionally fast (less than an hour) and localized plumes. <lb/>These events are only visible as sharp peaks in the CO con-<lb/>centrations and happened on such a small temporal and spa-<lb/>tial scale that they will not be visible in, for example, most <lb/>satellite data (with coarser resolution). These outflows may <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Atmos. Chem. Phys., 24, 4771-4788, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-24-4771-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">M. Ebert et al.: Characterization of refractory aerosol particles <lb/></note>

        <page>4783 <lb/></page>

        <body>be responsible for the fast convective transport of HgS parti-<lb/>cles from ground sources during flight 8. <lb/>India and China are among the largest emitters of atmo-<lb/>spheric mercury in the world (Jetashree et al., 2022; Wu et <lb/>al., 2006). For example, the Indian Jharia region, which is <lb/>located directly within the identified source region, with the <lb/>Jharia coal fields (23.75°N, 86.42°E), produces most of In-<lb/>dia&apos;s coal. Jharia coal mines are India&apos;s most important store-<lb/>house of prime coke coal and consist of 23 large underground <lb/>and nine large open-cast mines. Furthermore, there have been <lb/>persistent smoldering coal field fires in this region for more <lb/>than a century. The Hg concentration of the coal is higher <lb/>than the world average, and the coal field fires are known to <lb/>be a source of Hg pollution in the mining area (Raj et al., <lb/>2017). <lb/>According to Nádudvari et al. (2022), HgS particles are <lb/>found above underground coal deposit fires and thermally af-<lb/>fected waste dumps from hard coal mining due to the reduc-<lb/>ing environment in the bituminous surface layer. Therefore, <lb/>one likely possibility is that the detected cinnabar particles <lb/>in flight 8 originate from underground coal fires in north-<lb/>ern India or southern China and/or from industrial coal burn-<lb/>ing. Cinnabar may have formed either under or at the ground <lb/>under reducing conditions and have been instantly adsorbed <lb/>on the surface of other aerosol particles transported into the <lb/>UTLS by a strong updraft, maybe during the intense over-<lb/>shoot events observed during flight 8. <lb/>If there were a case of strong convective input of coal <lb/>combustion (at or under the ground) during flight 8, an in-<lb/>creased level of soot, CO, and other Hg particles such as <lb/>HgCl 2 (Srivastava et al., 2006; Peng et al., 2021) would also <lb/>be expected, which is not the case. While the observations <lb/>of Bucci et al. (2020) can explain the CO values, the non-<lb/>discovery of other Hg species and the lack of clearly in-<lb/>creased soot abundance contradict a ground source being the <lb/>source of the determined HgS particles. <lb/>In all the previous literature, a stratospheric origin of par-<lb/>ticulate Hg II components in the UTLS was inferred. Mur-<lb/>phy et al. (1998) discussed Hg-rich particles from UTLS <lb/>and stratospheric aircraft experiments. Hg was detected in <lb/>a large number of MS particle spectra during one flight leg <lb/>near the tropopause south of Houston to 10°N. In contrast, <lb/>no mercury was found during flights in a remote continen-<lb/>tal surface site (Idaho Hill, Colorado) and a remote marine <lb/>surface site (Kennaook / Cape Grim, Tasmania). During dif-<lb/>ferent aircraft campaigns in the tropics and middle latitudes, <lb/>Murphy et al. (2006) detected Hg-containing particles close <lb/>to the tropopause, while no Hg-containing particles were <lb/>detected below 5 km height. They concluded that particu-<lb/>late Hg II most likely originates from oxidization of gaseous <lb/>Hg 0 in the lower stratosphere and not from a primary ter-<lb/>restrial Hg-particle source. This conclusion is also supported <lb/>by Lyman and Jaffe (2012). During aircraft measurements at <lb/>6-7 km altitude, Hg II was positively correlated with strato-<lb/>spheric tracers (ozone and potential vorticity), indicating that <lb/>Hg II increased with increasing stratospheric influence. <lb/>The Hg chemistry in the atmosphere is quite complex and <lb/>the subject of current scientific research. Excellent overviews <lb/>of possible mercury oxidation pathways in the atmosphere <lb/>are, for example, Schroeder and Munthe (1998), Holmes et <lb/>al. (2010), Shah et al. (2016), Obrist et al. (2018), and Ly-<lb/>man et al. (2020). They summarize the possible role of OH, <lb/>O 3 , bromine, photochemistry, and aqueous-phase reduction. <lb/>Gratz et al. (2015) reported results from the 2013 Nitrogen, <lb/>Oxidants, Mercury and Aerosol Distributions, Sources and <lb/>Sinks campaign, which supported the role of bromine as the <lb/>dominant oxidant of mercury in the upper troposphere and <lb/>the importance of subtropical anticyclones for the formation <lb/>of Hg II . <lb/>This is worth highlighting because during the StratoClim <lb/>flight campaign in 2017, Adcock et al. (2021) detected en-<lb/>hanced bromine values in the UTLS. <lb/>Up to now it has been concluded that the source of Hg II <lb/>particles in the UTLS must be completely attributed to strato-<lb/>spheric oxidation of gaseous Hg 0 . The observation of HgS <lb/>particles in the UTLS during flight 8 shows the possibil-<lb/>ity that quick convective outflows of very fast and localized <lb/>plumes could cause direct transport of HgS particles in the <lb/>UTLS region. <lb/>This transport from the ground could also be responsible <lb/>for the Hg particles described in Murphy et al. (2006) for a <lb/>lower-stratospheric sample. Even though no mineralogical-<lb/>phase information is given by Murphy et al. (2006), their <lb/>observed Hg-rich particles seem to be identical to the HgS <lb/>(cinnabar) particles observed by us. The size (10-20 nm in <lb/>diameter), mixing state (attached to sulfate particles), Hg : S <lb/>ratio, and beam sensitivity in STEM (scanning transmission <lb/>electron microscope; volatilization under STEM conditions <lb/>in a few seconds) were identical to those of our cinnabar par-<lb/>ticles found during StratoClim. Thus, the presence of HgS <lb/>particles in the UTLS seems not to be limited to the specific <lb/>conditions within the ATAL during the 2017 monsoon anti-<lb/>cyclone. <lb/>5 Conclusion <lb/>It was shown that within the 2017 monsoon anticyclone there <lb/>is a predominantly terrestrial input of refractory particles into <lb/>the ATAL. <lb/>In contrast to prior modeling studies, we found that re-<lb/>fractory particles (including desert dust) play only a minor <lb/>role in the total composition of aerosol particles within the <lb/>ATAL. In SEM measurements, about 2 % by number of the <lb/>typical ATAL particles (main components: ammonium, sul-<lb/>fate, nitrate, and organics) show visible inclusions/agglomer-<lb/>ates of refractory particles. The main components within the <lb/>refractory particles were silicates and NVOCs. In addition, <lb/>Fe-rich particles, other metal-rich particles (Mn, Cr, Zn), and <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-24-4771-2024 <lb/>Atmos. Chem. Phys., 24, 4771-4788, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>4784 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">M. Ebert et al.: Characterization of refractory aerosol particles <lb/></note>

        <body>extraterrestrial particles were found, as well as some small <lb/>quantities of soot and Ca-, Cl-, and Al-rich particles. <lb/>In general, most refractory particles found are very small. <lb/>The maximum of the dN/d log D P distribution is ∼ 125 nm. <lb/>This also means that, besides some very small terrestrial soil <lb/>particles, nucleation processes are the predominant source. <lb/>For most refractory particles these are mainly anthropogenic <lb/>combustion processes (coal burning, biomass burning, indus-<lb/>trial processes). For the NVOCs secondary atmospheric pro-<lb/>cesses are additionally important. <lb/>The variability in the relative number abundance of indi-<lb/>vidual ground-emitted refractory particle groups was quite <lb/>low during StratoClim 2017 for most sampling days and at <lb/>different flight altitudes between ∼ 12-19 km. This suggests <lb/>that there was generally a roughly uniform background com-<lb/>position for the terrestrial refractory particles in the ATAL <lb/>and also just beyond the tropopause (lower stratosphere). Ex-<lb/>traterrestrial refractory particles play a larger role above the <lb/>tropopause; within the ATAL their relative abundance is low. <lb/>During flights 7 and 8, additional refractory particles were <lb/>detected. These particles originated from an additional input <lb/>from special anthropogenic ground sources and were rapidly <lb/>transported into the UTLS under enhanced convective influ-<lb/>ence. The ground regions from which the strongest input (or <lb/>updraft) was observed indicate industrial emissions in the <lb/>Indo-Gangetic Plain for flight 7, which additionally intro-<lb/>duced various metals and metal oxides into the ATAL here. <lb/>The exact source of the Hg-rich particles found in flight <lb/>8 remains unclear. As previously described in the literature, <lb/>they could have originated in the lower stratosphere. How-<lb/>ever, the TEM characterization of cinnabar (HgS) suggests a <lb/>ground source such as coal combustion or underground coal <lb/>fires. <lb/></body>

        <div type="availability">Data availability. The complete SEM original data set is avail-<lb/>able for the community and can be accessed by request to Mar-<lb/>tin Ebert (mebert@geo.tu-darmstadt.de) of the Technical University <lb/>of Darmstadt. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Supplement. The supplement related to this article is available <lb/>online at: https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-24-4771-2024-supplement. <lb/></div>

        <div type="contribution">Author contributions. RW: potential temperature, CPT data <lb/>analysis and classification of particle origin, data discussion and <lb/>interpretation; SW: manuscript data interpretation and discussion; <lb/>LS: SEM data evaluation, interpretation and discussion; KK: data <lb/>evaluation and classification, interpretation and discussion; SL: <lb/>TEM measurements, TEM data interpretation and discussion; FK: <lb/>classification, comparison, and interpretation of refractory (SEM <lb/>and MS) particle data; FP: field experiment data, data discussion <lb/>and interpretation (meteorology, ATAL, UTLS); GG: field experi-<lb/>ment data, data discussion and interpretation (meteorology, ATAL, <lb/>UTLS); BV: back-trajectory analysis, air mass origin discussion; <lb/>SB: manuscript data interpretation and discussion. <lb/></div>

        <div type="conflict">Competing interests. The contact author has declared that none <lb/>of the authors has any competing interests. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Disclaimer. Publisher&apos;s note: Copernicus Publications remains <lb/>neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims made in the text, pub-<lb/>lished maps, institutional affiliations, or any other geographical rep-<lb/>resentation in this paper. While Copernicus Publications makes ev-<lb/>ery effort to include appropriate place names, the final responsibility <lb/>lies with the authors. <lb/></div>

        <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements. This work was supported by TPChange <lb/>(The Tropopause Region in a Changing Atmosphere), DFG <lb/>TRR 301, project ID 428312742. The Nepal aircraft campaign was <lb/>conducted within the project StratoClim sponsored by the Euro-<lb/>pean Union Seventh Framework Programme (FP7/2007-2013, grant <lb/>no. 603557). The StratoClim project was also financially supported <lb/>by the German &quot;Bundesministerium für Bildung und Forschung&quot; <lb/>(BMBF) under the joint ROMIC project SPITFIRE (grant no. <lb/>01LG1205A) as well as by the European Union Seventh Framework <lb/>Programme (FP7/2007-2013, ERC grant no. 321040-Excatro). The <lb/>presented work includes contributions of the NSFC-DFG 2020 <lb/>project ATAL-track (BO 1829/12-1 and VO 1276/6-1). The authors <lb/>thank the M-55 Geophysica team and the MDB (Myasishchev De-<lb/>sign Bureau, Moscow, Russia) for planning and carrying out the <lb/>flights. <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">Financial support. This research has been supported by the <lb/>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (grant nos. DFG TRR 301, <lb/>project ID 428312742, BO 1829/12-1, and VO 1276/6-1); the Sev-<lb/>enth Framework Programme, FP7 Coordination of Research Activ-<lb/>ities (grant nos. 603557 and 321040); and the Bundesministerium <lb/>für Bildung und Forschung (grant no. 01LG1205A). <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Review statement. This paper was edited by Alexander Laskin <lb/>and reviewed by two anonymous referees. <lb/></div>

        <listBibl>References <lb/>Adachi, K., Oshima, N., Takegawa, N., Moteki, N., and Koike, M.: <lb/>Meteoric materials within sulfate aerosol particles in the tropo-<lb/>sphere are detected with transmission electron microscopy, Com-<lb/>mun. Earth Environ., 3, 1-9, 2022. <lb/>Adcock, K. E., Fraser, P. J., Hall, B. D., Langenfelds, R. L., Lee, <lb/>G., Montzka, S. A., Oram, D. E., Röckmann, T., Stroh, F., <lb/>Sturges, W. T., Vogel, B., and Laube, J. C.: Aircraft-Based Ob-<lb/>servations of Ozone-Depleting Substances in the Upper Tro-<lb/>posphere and Lower Stratosphere in and Above the Asian <lb/>Summer Monsoon, J. Geophys. Res., 126, e2020JD033137, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2020JD033137, 2021. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Atmos. Chem. Phys., 24, 4771-4788, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-24-4771-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">M. Ebert et al.: Characterization of refractory aerosol particles <lb/></note>

        <page>4785 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>Appel, O., Köllner, F., Dragoneas, A., Hünig, A., Molleker, S., <lb/>Schlager, H., Mahnke, C., Weigel, R., Port, M., Schulz, C., <lb/>Drewnick, F., Vogel, B., Stroh, F., and Borrmann, S.: Chemi-<lb/>cal analysis of the Asian tropopause aerosol layer (ATAL) with <lb/>emphasis on secondary aerosol particles using aircraft-based in <lb/>situ aerosol mass spectrometry, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 22, 13607-<lb/>13630, https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-22-13607-2022, 2022. <lb/>Baumgartner, M., Weigel, R., Harvey, A. H., Plöger, F., Achatz, U., <lb/>and Spichtinger, P.: Reappraising the appropriate calculation of a <lb/>common meteorological quantity: potential temperature, Atmos. <lb/>Chem. Phys., 20, 15585-15616, https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-20-<lb/>15585-2020, 2020. <lb/>Borrmann, S., Kunkel, D., Weigel, R., Minikin, A., Deshler, T., Wil-<lb/>son, J. C., Curtius, J., Volk, C. M., Homan, C. D., Ulanovsky, <lb/>A., Ravegnani, F., Viciani, S., Shur, G. N., Belyaev, G. V., <lb/>Law, K. S., and Cairo, F.: Aerosols in the tropical and sub-<lb/>tropical UT/LS: in-situ measurements of submicron particle <lb/>abundance and volatility, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 10, 5573-5592, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-10-5573-2010, 2010. <lb/>Bossolasco, A., Jegou, F., Sellitto, P., Berthet, G., Kloss, C., <lb/>and Legras, B.: Global modeling studies of composition and <lb/>decadal trends of the Asian Tropopause Aerosol Layer, At-<lb/>mos. Chem. Phys., 21, 2745-2764, https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-<lb/>21-2745-2021, 2021. <lb/>Brunamonti, S., Jorge, T., Oelsner, P., Hanumanthu, S., Singh, <lb/>B. B., Kumar, K. R., Sonbawne, S., Meier, S., Singh, D., <lb/>Wienhold, F. G., Luo, B. P., Boettcher, M., Poltera, Y., Jauhi-<lb/>ainen, H., Kayastha, R., Karmacharya, J., Dirksen, R., Naja, M., <lb/>Rex, M., Fadnavis, S., and Peter, T.: Balloon-borne measure-<lb/>ments of temperature, water vapor, ozone and aerosol backscat-<lb/>ter on the southern slopes of the Himalayas during Stra-<lb/>toClim 2016-2017, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 18, 15937-15957, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-18-15937-2018, 2018. <lb/>Bucci, S., Legras, B., Sellitto, P., D&apos;Amato, F., Viciani, S., Montori, <lb/>A., Chiarugi, A., Ravegnani, F., Ulanovsky, A., Cairo, F., and <lb/>Stroh, F.: Deep-convective influence on the upper troposphere-<lb/>lower stratosphere composition in the Asian monsoon anticy-<lb/>clone region: 2017 StratoClim campaign results, Atmos. Chem. <lb/>Phys., 20, 12193-12210, https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-20-12193-<lb/>2020, 2020. <lb/>Cofer III, W. R., Purgold, G. C., Winstead, E. L., and Edahl, R. A.: <lb/>Space Shuttle Exhausted Aluminum Oxide: A measured parti-<lb/>cle size distribution, J. Geophys. Res.-Atmos., 96, 17371-17376, <lb/>1991. <lb/>Curtius, J., Weigel, R., Vössing, H.-J., Wernli, H., Werner, A., <lb/>Volk, C.-M., Konopka, P., Krebsbach, M., Schiller, C., Roiger, <lb/>A., Schlager, H., Dreiling, V., and Borrmann, S.: Observa-<lb/>tions of meteoric material and implications for aerosol nucle-<lb/>ation in the winter Arctic lower stratosphere derived from in <lb/>situ particle measurements, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 5, 3053-3069, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-5-3053-2005, 2005. <lb/>Cziczo, D. J., Thomson, D. S., and Murphy, D. M.: Ab-<lb/>lation, flux, and atmospheric implications of meteors in-<lb/>ferred from stratospheric aerosol, Science, 291, 1772-1775, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1057737, 2001. <lb/>Cziczo, D. J., Murphy, D. M., Thomson, D. S., and Ross, M. N.: <lb/>Composition of individual particles in the wakes of an Athena <lb/>II rocket and the space shuttle, Geophys. Res. Lett., 29, 2037, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2002GL015991, 2002. <lb/>Danilin, M. Y., Ko, M. K. W., and Weisenstein, D. K.: Global impli-<lb/>cations of ozone loss in a space shuttle wake, J. Geophys. Res.-<lb/>Atmos., 106, 3591-3601, 2001. <lb/>Denison, M., Lamb, J. J., Bjorndahl, W. D., Wong, E. Y., and <lb/>Lohn, P. D.: Solid rocket exhaust in the stratosphere-Plume diffu-<lb/>sion and chemical reactions, J. Spacecraft Rockets, 31, 435-442, <lb/>1994. <lb/>Dethof, A., O&apos;Neill, A., Slingo, J. M., and Smit, H. G. J.: A mech-<lb/>anism for moistening the lower stratosphere involving the Asian <lb/>summer monsoon, Q. J. Roy. Meteor. Soc., 556, 1079-1106, <lb/>1999. <lb/>Dragoneas, A., Molleker, S., Appel, O., Hünig, A., Böttger, T., <lb/>Hermann, M., Drewnick, F., Schneider, J., Weigel, R., and <lb/>Borrmann, S.: The realization of autonomous, aircraft-based, <lb/>real-time aerosol mass spectrometry in the upper troposphere <lb/>and lower stratosphere, Atmos. Meas. Tech., 15, 5719-5742, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-15-5719-2022, 2022. <lb/>Ebert, M., Weigel, R., Kandler, K., Günther, G., Molleker, <lb/>S., Grooß, J.-U., Vogel, B., Weinbruch, S., and Borrmann, <lb/>S.: Chemical analysis of refractory stratospheric aerosol par-<lb/>ticles collected within the arctic vortex and inside polar <lb/>stratospheric clouds, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 16, 8405-8421, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-16-8405-2016, 2016. <lb/>Fadnavis, S., Semeniuk, K., Pozzoli, L., Schultz, M. G., Ghude, <lb/>S. D., Das, S., and Kakatkar, R.: Transport of aerosols into the <lb/>UTLS and their impact on the Asian monsoon region as seen in <lb/>a global model simulation, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 13, 8771-8786, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-13-8771-2013, 2013. <lb/>Fairlie, T. D., Liu, H., Vernier, J.-P., Campuzano-Jost, P., Jimenez, <lb/>J. L., Jo, D. S., Zhang, B., Natarajan, M., Avery, M. A., and <lb/>Huey, G.: Estimates of Regional Source Contributions to the <lb/>Asian Tropopause Aerosol Layer Using a Chemical Trans-<lb/>port Model, J. Geophys. Res.-Atmos., 125, e2019JD031506, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2019JD031506, 2020. <lb/>Froyd, K. D., Murphy, D. M., Sanford, T. J., Thomson, D. S., Wil-<lb/>son, J. C., Pfister, L., and Lait, L.: Aerosol composition of the <lb/>tropical upper troposphere, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 9, 4363-4385, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-9-4363-2009, 2009. <lb/>Fujiwara, M., Sakai, T., Nagai, T., Shiraishi, K., Inai, Y., Khaykin, <lb/>S., Xi, H., Shibata, T., Shiotani, M., and Pan, L. L.: Lower-<lb/>stratospheric aerosol measurements in eastward-shedding vor-<lb/>tices over Japan from the Asian summer monsoon anticyclone <lb/>during the summer of 2018, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 21, 3073-<lb/>3090, https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-21-3073-2021, 2021. <lb/>Gratz, L. E., Ambrose, J. L., Jaffe, D. A., Shah, V., Jaeglé, L., Stutz, <lb/>J., Festa, J., Spolaor, M., Tsai, C., Selin, N. E., Song, S., Zhou, <lb/>X., Weinheimer, A. J., Knapp, D. J., Montzke, D. D., Flocke, F. <lb/>M., Campos, T. L., Apel, E., Hornbrook, R., Blake, N. J., Hall, <lb/>S., Tyndall, G. S., Reeves, M., Stechman, D., and Stell, M.: Oxi-<lb/>dation of mercury by bromine in the subtropical Pacific free tro-<lb/>posphere, Geophys. Res. Lett., 42, 10494-10502, 2015. <lb/>Hanumanthu, S., Vogel, B., Müller, R., Brunamonti, S., Fadnavis, <lb/>S., Li, D., Ölsner, P., Naja, M., Singh, B. B., Kumar, K. R., <lb/>Sonbawne, S., Jauhiainen, H., Vömel, H., Luo, B., Jorge, T., <lb/>Wienhold, F. G., Dirkson, R., and Peter, T.: Strong day-to-<lb/>day variability of the Asian Tropopause Aerosol Layer (ATAL) <lb/>in August 2016 at the Himalayan foothills, Atmos. Chem. <lb/>Phys., 20, 14273-14302, https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-20-14273-<lb/>2020, 2020. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-24-4771-2024 <lb/>Atmos. Chem. Phys., 24, 4771-4788, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>4786 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">M. Ebert et al.: Characterization of refractory aerosol particles <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>Hermann, M., Stratmann, F., Wilck, M., and Wiedensohler, A.: <lb/>Sampling Characteristics of an Aircraft-Borne Aerosol Inlet Sys-<lb/>tem, J. Atmos. Ocean. Tech., 18, 7-19, 2001. <lb/>Holmes, C. D., Jacob, D. J., Corbitt, E. S., Mao, J., Yang, X., <lb/>Talbot, R., and Slemr, F.: Global atmospheric model for mer-<lb/>cury including oxidation by bromine atoms, Atmos. Chem. <lb/>Phys., 10, 12037-12057, https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-10-12037-<lb/>2010, 2010. <lb/>Höpfner, M., Ungermann, J., Borrmann, S., Wagner, R. Spang, R., <lb/>Riese, M., Stiller, G., Appel, O., Bat enburg, A.M., Bucci, S., <lb/>Cairo, F., Dragoneas, A., Friedl Vallon, F., Hünig, A., Johansson, <lb/>S., Kras auskas, L., Legras, B., Leisner, T., Mahnke, C., Möhler, <lb/>O., Molleker, S., Müller, R., Ne u bert, T., Orphal, J., Preusse, P., <lb/>Rex, M., Saathoff, H., Stroh, F., Weigel, R., and Wohltmann, I. I.: <lb/>Ammonium nitrate particles formed in upper troposphere from g <lb/>round ammonia sources during Asian monsoons, Nat. Geosci., <lb/>12, 608-612, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-019-0385-8, 2019. <lb/>Hoshizaki, H., Anderson, L. B., Conti, R. J., Farlow, N., Meyer, J. <lb/>W., Overcamp, T., Redler, K. O., and Watson, V.: Aircraft wake <lb/>microscale phenomena, CIAP Monograph, 3, 60-73, 1975. <lb/>Hünig, A., Appel, O., Dragoneas, A., Molleker, S., Clemen, H.-<lb/>C., Helleis, F., Klimach, T., Köllner, F., Böttger, T., Drewnick, <lb/>F., Schneider, J., and Borrmann, S.: Design, characterization, <lb/>and first field deployment of a novel aircraft-based aerosol <lb/>mass spectrometer combining the laser ablation and flash va-<lb/>porization techniques, Atmos. Meas. Tech., 15, 2889-2921, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-15-2889-2022, 2022. <lb/>Jackman, C. H., Considine, D. B., and Fleming, E. L.: A global <lb/>modeling study of solid rocket aluminum oxide emission effects <lb/>on stratospheric ozone, Geophys. Res. Lett., 25, 907-910, 1998. <lb/>Jetashree, Q. Z., Zhou, H., Li, Y., Liu, Y., Li, J., and Liang, S.: <lb/>Role of Trade in India&apos;s Rising Atmospheric Mercury Emissions, <lb/>Environ. Sci. Technol., 56, 790-803, 2021. <lb/>Jost, A., Szakáll, M., Diehl, K., Mitra, S. K., and Borrmann, S.: <lb/>Chemistry of riming: the retention of organic and inorganic at-<lb/>mospheric trace constituents, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 17, 9717-<lb/>9732, https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-17-9717-2017, 2017. <lb/>Khaykin, S. M., Moyer, E., Krämer, M., Clouser, B., Bucci, <lb/>S., Legras, B., Lykov, A., Afchine, A., Cairo, F., Formanyuk, <lb/>I., Mitev, V., Matthey, R., Rolf, C., Singer, C. E., Spel-<lb/>ten, N., Volkov, V., Yushkov, V., and Stroh, F.: Persistence <lb/>of moist plumes from overshooting convection in the Asian <lb/>monsoon anticyclone, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 22, 3169-3189, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-22-3169-2022, 2022. <lb/>Kremser, S., Thomason, L. W., von Hobe, M., Hermann, M., Desh-<lb/>ler, T., Timmreck, C., Toohey, M., Stenke, A., Schwarz, J. P., <lb/>Weigel, R., Fueglistaler, S., Prata, F. J., Vernier, J.-P., Schlager, <lb/>H., Barnes, J. E., Antu na-Marrero, J.-C., Fairlie, D., Palm, M., <lb/>Mahieu, E., Notholt, J., Rex, M., Bingen, C., Vanhellemont, F., <lb/>Bourassa, A., Plane, J. M. C., Klocke, D., Carn, S. A., Clarisse, <lb/>L., Trickl, T., Neely, R., James, A. D., Rieger, L., Wilson, J. <lb/>C., and Meland, B.: Stratospheric aerosol -Observations, pro-<lb/>cesses, and impact on climate, Rev. Geophys., 54, 278-335, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/2015rg000511, 2016. <lb/>Kumari, A., Kumar, B., Manzoor, S., and Kulshrestha, <lb/>U.: Status of Atmospheric Mercury Research in South <lb/>Asia: A Review, Aerosol Air Qual. Res., 15, 1092-1109, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.4209/aaqr.2014.05.0098, 2015. <lb/>Lau, W. K. M., Yuan, C., and Li, Z.: Origin, Maintenance and <lb/>Variability of the Asian Tropopause Aerosol Layer (ATAL): <lb/>The Roles of Monsoon Dynamics, Sci. Rep.-UK, 8, 3960, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-22267-z, 2018. <lb/>Lawrence, M. G. and Lelieveld, J.: Atmospheric pollutant outflow <lb/>from southern Asia: a review, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 10, 11017-<lb/>11096, https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-10-11017-2010, 2010. <lb/>Lee, K.-O., Barret, B., Flochmoën, E. L., Tulet, P., Bucci, S., <lb/>von Hobe, M., Kloss, C., Legras, B., Leriche, M., Sauvage, B., <lb/>Ravegnani, F., and Ulanovsky, A.: Convective uplift of pollution <lb/>from the Sichuan Basin into the Asian monsoon anticyclone dur-<lb/>ing the StratoClim aircraft campaign, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 21, <lb/>3255-3274, https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-21-3255-2021, 2021. <lb/>Lelieveld, J., Bourtsoukidis, E., Brühl, C., Fischer, H., Fuchs, H., <lb/>Harder, H., Hofzumahaus, A., Holland, F., Marno, D., Neumaier, <lb/>M., Pozzer, A., Schlager, H., Williams, J., Zahn, A., and Ziereis, <lb/>H.: The South Asian monsoon -pollution pump and purifier, <lb/>Science, 361, 270-273, https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aar2501, <lb/>2018. <lb/>Liu, X., Penner, J. E., and Wang, M.: Influence of anthro-<lb/>pogenic sulfate and black carbon on upper tropospheric <lb/>clouds in the NCAR CAM3 model coupled to the IM-<lb/>PACT global aerosol model, J. Geophys. Res., 114, D03204, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2008JD010492, 2009. <lb/>Lyman, S. N. and Jaffe, D. A.: Formation and fate of oxidized <lb/>mercury in the upper troposphere and lower stratosphere, Nat. <lb/>Geosci., 5, 114-117, 2012. <lb/>Lyman, S. N., Cheng, I., Gratz, L. E., Weiss-Penzias, <lb/>P., and Zhang, L.: An updated review of atmo-<lb/>spheric mercury, Sci. Total Environ., 707, 135575, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.135575, 2020. <lb/>Ma, J., Brühl, C., He, Q., Steil, B., Karydis, V. A., Klingmüller, <lb/>K., Tost, H., Chen, B., Jin, Y., Liu, N., Xu, X., Yan, P., Zhou, <lb/>X., Abdelrahman, K., Pozzer, A., and Lelieveld, J.: Modeling <lb/>the aerosol chemical composition of the tropopause over the Ti-<lb/>betan Plateau during the Asian summer monsoon, Atmos. Chem. <lb/>Phys., 19, 11587-11612, https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-19-11587-<lb/>2019, 2019. <lb/>Mackinnon, I. D. R., Mckay, D. S., Nace, G., and Isaacs, A. M.: <lb/>Classification of the Johnson Space Center Stratospheric Dust <lb/>Collection, J. Geophys. Res., 87, A413-A421, 1982. <lb/>Mahnke, C., Weigel, R., Cairo, F., Vernier, J.-P., Afchine, A., <lb/>Krämer, M., Mitev, V., Matthey, R., Viciani, S., D&apos;Amato, <lb/>F., Ploeger, F., Deshler, T., and Borrmann, S.: The Asian <lb/>tropopause aerosol layer within the 2017 monsoon anticy-<lb/>clone: microphysical properties derived from aircraft-borne in <lb/>situ measurements, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 21, 15259-15282, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-21-15259-2021, 2021. <lb/>Molleker, S., Helleis, F., Klimach, T., Appel, O., Clemen, H.-<lb/>C., Dragoneas, A., Gurk, C., Hünig, A., Köllner, F., Rubach, <lb/>F., Schulz, C., Schneider, J., and Borrmann, S.: Application <lb/>of an O-ring pinch device as a constant-pressure inlet (CPI) <lb/>for airborne sampling, Atmos. Meas. Tech., 13, 3651-3660, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-13-3651-2020, 2020. <lb/>Murphy, D. M., Thomson, D. S., and Mahoney, M. J.: In situ mea-<lb/>surements of organics, meteoritic material, mercury, and other <lb/>elements in aerosols at 5 to 19 kilometers, Science, 282, 1664-<lb/>1669, 1998. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Atmos. Chem. Phys., 24, 4771-4788, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-24-4771-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">M. Ebert et al.: Characterization of refractory aerosol particles <lb/></note>

        <page>4787 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>Murphy, D. M., Hudson, P. K., Thomson, D. S., Sheridan, P. J., <lb/>and Wilson, J. C.: Observations of mercury-containing aerosols, <lb/>Environ. Sci. Technol., 40, 3163-3167, 2006. <lb/>Murphy, D. M., Froyd, K. D., Schwarz, J. P., and Wilson, J. <lb/>C.: Observations of the chemical composition of stratospheric <lb/>aerosol particles, Q. J. Roy. Meteor. Soc., 140, 1269-1278, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/qj.2213, 2014. <lb/>Nádudvari, Á., Cabała, J., Marynowski, L., Jabłońska, M., Dz-<lb/>iurowicz, M., Malczewski, D., Kozielska, B., Siupka, P., <lb/>Piotrowska-Seget, Z., Simoneit, B. R. T., and Szczyrba, <lb/>M.: High concentrations of HgS, MeHg and toxic gas <lb/>emissions in thermally affected waste dumps from hard <lb/>coal mining in Poland, J. Hazard. Mater., 431, 128542, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhazmat.2022.128542, 2022. <lb/>Obrist, D., Kirk, J. L., Zhang, L., Sunderland, E. M., Jiskra, M., <lb/>and Selin, N. E.: A review of global environmental mercury pro-<lb/>cesses in response to human and natural perturbations: Changes <lb/>of emissions, climate, and land use, Ambio, 47, 116-140, 2018. <lb/>Pan, L. L., Honomichl, S. B., Kinnison, D. E., Abalos, <lb/>M., Randel, W. J., Bergman, J. W., and Bian, J.: Trans-<lb/>port of chemical tracers from the boundary layer to strato-<lb/>sphere associated with the dynamics of the Asian sum-<lb/>mer monsoon, J. Geophys. Res.-Atmos., 121, 14159-14174, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/2016jd025616, 2016. <lb/>Peng, Y., Shi, N., Wang, J., Wang, T., and Pan, W. P.: Mercury spe-<lb/>ciation and size-specific distribution in filterable and condens-<lb/>able particulate matter from coal combustion, Sci. Total Environ., <lb/>787, 147597, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.147597, <lb/>2021. <lb/>Pirrone, N., Cinnirella, S., Feng, X., Finkelman, R. B., Friedli, <lb/>H. R., Leaner, J., Mason, R., Mukherjee, A. B., Stracher, G. <lb/>B., Streets, D. G., and Telmer, K.: Global mercury emissions <lb/>to the atmosphere from anthropogenic and natural sources, At-<lb/>mos. Chem. Phys., 10, 5951-5964, https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-<lb/>10-5951-2010, 2010. <lb/>Popovic, J. M. and Plumb, R. A.: Eddy Shedding from the upper-<lb/>tropospheric Asian monsoon anticyclone, J. Atmos. Sci., 58, 93-<lb/>104, 2001. <lb/>Raabe, O. G., Braaten, D. A., Axelbaum, R. L., Teague, S. V., <lb/>and Cahill, T. A.: Calibration studies of the DRUM impactor, <lb/>J. Aerosol Sci., 19, 183-195, 1988. <lb/>Raj, D., Chowdhury, A., and Maiti, S. K.: Ecological risk assess-<lb/>ment of mercury and other heavy metals in soils of coal mining <lb/>area: A case study from the eastern part of a Jharia coal field, <lb/>India, Hum. Ecol. Risk Assess., 23, 767-787, 2017. <lb/>Rietmeijer, F. J. M.: Chap. 2 -Interplanetary dust particles in Re-<lb/>views in Mineralogy, vol. 36, in: Planetary Materials, The Min-<lb/>eralogical Society of America, Washington DC, USA, ISBN 0-<lb/>939950-46-4, 1998. <lb/>Schneider, J., Weigel, R., Klimach, T., Dragoneas, A., Appel, O., <lb/>Hünig, A., Molleker, S., Köllner, F., Clemen, H.-C., Eppers, O., <lb/>Hoppe, P., Hoor, P., Mahnke, C., Krämer, M., Rolf, C., Grooß, <lb/>J.-U., Zahn, A., Obersteiner, F., Ravegnani, F., Ulanovsky, A., <lb/>Schlager, H., Scheibe, M., Diskin, G. S., DiGangi, J. P., Nowak, <lb/>J. B., Zöger, M., and Borrmann, S.: Aircraft-based observa-<lb/>tion of meteoric material in lower-stratospheric aerosol parti-<lb/>cles between 15 and 68°N, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 21, 989-1013, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-21-989-2021, 2021. <lb/>Schroeder, W. H. and Munthe, J.: Atmospheric mercury -an <lb/>overview, Atmos. Environ., 32, 809-822, 1998. <lb/>Schütze, K., Wilson, J. C., Weinbruch, S., Benker, N., Ebert, M., <lb/>Günther, G., Weigel, R., and Borrmann, S.: Sub-micrometer re-<lb/>fractory carbonaceous particles in the polar stratosphere, Atmos. <lb/>Chem. Phys., 17, 12475-12493, https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-17-<lb/>12475-2017, 2017. <lb/>Seigneur, C., Abeck, H., Chia, G., Reinhard, M., Bloom, N. S., <lb/>Prestbo, E., and Saxena, P.: Mercury adsorption to elemental car-<lb/>bon (soot) particles and atmospheric particulate matter, Atmos. <lb/>Environ., 32, 2649-2657, 1998. <lb/>Shah, V., Jaeglé, L., Gratz, L. E., Ambrose, J. L., Jaffe, D. A., <lb/>Selin, N. E., Song, S., Campos, T. L., Flocke, F. M., Reeves, M., <lb/>Stechman, D., Stell, M., Festa, J., Stutz, J., Weinheimer, A. J., <lb/>Knapp, D. J., Montzka, D. D., Tyndall, G. S., Apel, E. C., Horn-<lb/>brook, R. S., Hills, A. J., Riemer, D. D., Blake, N. J., Cantrell, <lb/>C. A., and Mauldin III, R. L.: Origin of oxidized mercury in <lb/>the summertime free troposphere over the southeastern US, At-<lb/>mos. Chem. Phys., 16, 1511-1530, https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-<lb/>16-1511-2016, 2016. <lb/>Srivastava, R. K., Hutson, N., Martin, B., Princiotta, F., and Staudt, <lb/>J.: Control of mercury emissions from coal-fired electric utility <lb/>boilers, Environ. Sci. Technol., 40, 1385-1393, 2006. <lb/>Ueyama, R., Jensen, E. J., and Pfister, L.: Convective Influence on <lb/>the Humidity and Clouds in the Tropical Tropopause Layer Dur-<lb/>ing Boreal Summer, J. Geophys. Res.-Atmos., 123, 7576-7593, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2018JD028674, 2018. <lb/>Vernier, J.-P., Thomason, L. W., and Kar, J.: CALIPSO detection <lb/>of an Asian tropopause aerosol layer, Geophys. Res. Lett., 38, <lb/>L07804, https://doi.org/10.1029/2010GL046614, 2011. <lb/>Vernier, J. P., Fairlie, T. D., Natarajan, M., Wienhold, F. G., <lb/>Bian, J., Martinsson, B. G., Crumeyrolle, S., Thomason, L. <lb/>W., and Bedka, K. M.: Increase in upper tropospheric and <lb/>lower stratospheric aerosol levels and its potential connection <lb/>with Asian pollution, J. Geophys. Res.-Atmos., 120, 1608-1619, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/2014JD022372, 2015. <lb/>Vernier, J.-P., Fairlie, T. D., Deshler, T., Ratnam, M. V., Gadhavi, <lb/>H., Kumar, B. S., Natarajan, M., Pandit, A. K., Raj, S. T. A., Ku-<lb/>mar, A. H., Jayaraman, A., Singh, A. K., Rastogi, N., Sinha, P. <lb/>R., Kumar, S., Tiwari, S., Wegner, T., Baker, N., Vignelles, D., <lb/>Stenchikov, G., Shevchenko, I., Smith, J., Bedka, K., Kesarkar, <lb/>A., Singh, V., Bhate, J., Ravikiran, V., Rao, M. D., Ravindrababu, <lb/>S., Patel, A., Vernier, H., Wienhold, F. G., Liu, H., Knepp, T. <lb/>N., Thomason, L., Crawford, J., Ziemba, L., Moore, J., Crumey-<lb/>rolle, S., Williamson, M., Berthet, Jégou, F., and Renard, J.-<lb/>B.: BATAL: The Balloon Measurement Campaigns of the Asian <lb/>Tropopause Aerosol Layer, B. Am. Meteorol. Soc., 99, 955-973, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1175/BAMS-D-17-0014.1, 2018. <lb/>Vernier, H., Rastogi, N., Liu, H., Pandit, A. K., Bedka, K., Patel, A., <lb/>Ratnam, M. V., Kumar, B. S., Zhang, B., Gadhavi, H., Wienhold, <lb/>F., Berthet, G., and Vernier, J.-P.: Exploring the inorganic com-<lb/>position of the Asian Tropopause Aerosol Layer using medium-<lb/>duration balloon flights, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 22, 12675-12694, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-22-12675-2022, 2022. <lb/>Vogel, B., Günther, G., Müller, R., Grooß, J.-U., Afchine, A., <lb/>Bozem, H., Hoor, P., Krämer, M., Müller, S., Riese, M., Rolf, C., <lb/>Spelten, N., Stiller, G. P., Ungermann, J., and Zahn, A.: Long-<lb/>range transport pathways of tropospheric source gases originat-<lb/>ing in Asia into the northern lower stratosphere during the Asian <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-24-4771-2024 <lb/>Atmos. Chem. Phys., 24, 4771-4788, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>4788 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">M. Ebert et al.: Characterization of refractory aerosol particles <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>monsoon season 2012, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 16, 15301-15325, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-16-15301-2016, 2016. <lb/>Vogel, B., Müller, R., Günther, G., Spang, R., Hanumanthu, S., Li, <lb/>D., Riese, M., and Stiller, G. P.: Lagrangian simulations of the <lb/>transport of young air masses to the top of the Asian monsoon <lb/>anticyclone and into the tropical pipe, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 19, <lb/>6007-6034, https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-19-6007-2019, 2019. <lb/>Vogel, B., Volk, C. M., Wintel, J., Lauther, V., Müller, R., Patra, <lb/>P. K., Riese, M., Terao, Y., and Stroh, F.: Reconstructing high-<lb/>resolution in-situ vertical carbon dioxide profiles in the sparsely <lb/>monitored Asian monsoon region, Commun. Earth Environ., 4, <lb/>72, https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-023-00725-5, 2023a. <lb/>Vogel, B., Volk, M., Wintel, J., Lauther, V., Clemens, J., Grooß, <lb/>J.-U., Günther, G., Hoffmann, L., Laube, J. C., Müller, R., <lb/>Ploeger, F., and Stroh, F.: Evaluation of vertical transport <lb/>in the Asian monsoon 2017 from CO 2 reconstruction in <lb/>the ERA5 and ERA-Interim reanalysis, EGUsphere [preprint], <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/egusphere-2023-1026, 2023b. <lb/>von Hobe, M., Ploeger, F., Konopka, P., Kloss, C., Ulanowski, A., <lb/>Yushkov, V., Ravegnani, F., Volk, C. M., Pan, L. L., Honomichl, <lb/>S. B., Tilmes, S., Kinnison, D. E., Garcia, R. R., and Wright, J. <lb/>S.: Upward transport into and within the Asian monsoon anti-<lb/>cyclone as inferred from StratoClim trace gas observations, At-<lb/>mos. Chem. Phys., 21, 1267-1285, https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-<lb/>21-1267-2021, 2021. <lb/>Wagner, R., Bertozzi, B., Höpfner, M., Höhler, K., Möhler, <lb/>O., Saathoff, H., and Leisner, T.: Solid Ammonium Ni-<lb/>trate Aerosols as Efficient Ice Nucleating Particles at Cirrus <lb/>Temperatures, J. Geophys. Res.-Atmos., 125, e2019JD032248, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2019JD032248, 2020. <lb/>Warren, J. L., Achilles, C. N., Todd, N. S., Bastien, R. K., and <lb/>Zolensky, M. E.: Cosmic Dust Catalog Volume 18 Particles from <lb/>Collectors L2071, L2076, L2079, L2083, and W7068, NASA <lb/>Johnson Space Center, Houston, TX 77058, 2011. <lb/>Weigel, R., Hermann, M., Curtius, J., Voigt, C., Walter, S., Böttger, <lb/>T., Lepukhov, B., Belyaev, G., and Borrmann, S.: Experimental <lb/>characterization of the COndensation PArticle counting System <lb/>for high altitude aircraft-borne application, Atmos. Meas. Tech., <lb/>2, 243-258, https://doi.org/10.5194/amt-2-243-2009, 2009. <lb/>Weigel, R., Mahnke, C., Baumgartner, M., Dragoneas, A., Vo-<lb/>gel, B., Ploeger, F., Viciani, S., D&apos;Amato, F., Bucci, S., Legras, <lb/>B., Luo, B., and Borrmann, S.: In situ observation of new <lb/>particle formation (NPF) in the tropical tropopause layer of <lb/>the 2017 Asian monsoon anticyclone -Part 1: Summary of <lb/>StratoClim results, Atmos. Chem. Phys., 21, 11689-11722, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-21-11689-2021, 2021a. <lb/>Weinbruch, S., Zou, L., Ebert, M., Benker, N., Drotikova, <lb/>T., and Kallenborn, R.: Emission of nanoparticles from <lb/>coal and diesel fired power plants on Svalbard: An elec-<lb/>tron microscopy study, Atmos. Environ., 282, 119138, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.atmosenv.2022.119138, 2022. <lb/>WMO: International Meteorological Tables, WMO-No. 188.TP97, <lb/>edited by: Letestu, S., Secretariat of the World Meteorological <lb/>Organization, Geneva, Switzerland, WMO No. 188.TP97, 1966. <lb/>Wu, Y., Wang, S., Streets, D. G., Hao, J., Chan, M., and Jiang, J.: <lb/>Trends in Anthropogenic Mercury Emissions in China from 1995 <lb/>to 2003, Environ. Sci. Technol., 40, 5312-5318, 2006. <lb/>Yu, P., Lian, S., Zhu, Y, Toon, O. B., Höpfner, M., and Borrmann, <lb/>S.: Abundant Nitrate and Nitric Acid Aerosol in the Upper <lb/>Troposphere and Lower Stratosphere, Geophys. Res. Lett., 49, <lb/>e2022GL100258, https://doi.org/10.1029/2022GL100258, 2022. <lb/>Zhang, J., Wu, X., Liu, S., Bai, Z., Xia, X., Chen, B., Zong, <lb/>X., and Bian, J.: In situ measurements and backward-trajectory <lb/>analysis of high-concentration, fine-mode aerosols in the UTLS <lb/>over the Tibetan Plateau, Environ. Res. Lett., 14, 124068, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/ab5a9f, 2019. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Atmos. Chem. Phys., 24, 4771-4788, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-24-4771-2024 </note>


	</text>

</TEI>