<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Generation of global 1 km all-weather instantaneous and daily mean land surface temperatures from MODIS data</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Bing</forename>
          <surname>Li</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Shunlin</forename>
          <surname>Liang</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Han</forename>
          <surname>Ma</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Guanpeng</forename>
          <surname>Dong</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Xiaobang</forename>
          <surname>Liu</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Tao</forename>
          <surname>He</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Yufang</forename>
          <surname>Zhang</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-05T15:38:56.335Z">11/5/2025 3:38:56 PM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Copernicus GmbH</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.5194/essd-16-3795-2024</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Bing Li, Shunlin Liang, Han Ma, Guanpeng Dong, Xiaobang Liu, Tao He, Yufang Zhang. (2024). Generation of global 1 km all-weather instantaneous and daily mean land surface temperatures from MODIS data. Earth System Science Data, 16(8), 3795-3819. DOI: 10.5194/essd-16-3795-2024</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-05T15:38:22.793841Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-05T15:38:22.793841Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2033-2045, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2033-2024 <lb/>© Author(s) 2024. This work is distributed under <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License. <lb/>The first hillslope thermokarst inventory for the <lb/>permafrost region of the Qilian Mountains <lb/>Xiaoqing Peng 1,3 , Guangshang Yang 1 , Oliver W. Frauenfeld 2 , Xuanjia Li 1 , Weiwei Tian 1 , <lb/>Guanqun Chen 1 , Yuan Huang 1 , Gang Wei 1 , Jing Luo 4 , Cuicui Mu 1,3 , and Fujun Niu 4 <lb/>1 Key Laboratory of Western China&apos;s Environmental Systems (Ministry of Education), College of Earth and <lb/>Environmental Sciences, Lanzhou University, Lanzhou 730000, China <lb/>2 Department of Geography, Texas A&amp;M University, College Station, TX 77843-3147, USA <lb/>3 Observation and Research Station on Eco-Environment of Frozen Ground in the Qilian Mountains, <lb/>Lanzhou University, Lanzhou 730000, China <lb/>4 State Key Laboratory of Frozen Soil Engineering, Northwest Institute of Eco-Environment and Resources, <lb/>Chinese Academy of Sciences, Lanzhou 730000, China <lb/>Correspondence: Guangshang Yang (220220948511@lzu.edu.cn) <lb/>Received: 20 October 2023 -Discussion started: 20 November 2023 <lb/>Revised: 5 March 2024 -Accepted: 17 March 2024 -Published: 29 April 2024 <lb/>Abstract. Climate warming and anthropogenic disturbances result in permafrost degradation in cold regions, <lb/>including in the Qilian Mountains. These changes lead to extensive hillslope thermokarst (HT) formation, such as <lb/>retrogressive thaw slumps, active-layer detachment slides, and thermal erosion gullies. These in turn cause, e.g., <lb/>degradation of local vegetation, economic losses, infrastructure damages, and threats to human safety. However, <lb/>despite its importance, there is currently no thermokarst inventory for the Qilian Mountains. Through manual <lb/>visual interpretation and field validation, we therefore produce the first quantification of HT features. We count a <lb/>total of 1064 HT features, with 67 % located in the upper reaches of the Heihe River basin, which encompasses <lb/>∼ 13 % of the Qilian Mountains region. We further identified that 187 HT features (18 %) existed before 2010, <lb/>while the remaining 874 (82 %) were initiated in the recent period. More specifically, 392 sites (37 %) were <lb/>initiated during 2010-2015 and 482 (45 %) after 2015. Thermokarst terrain is observed primarily in areas with <lb/>shallow active-layer depths (average thickness 2.98 m) on northern shaded slopes of 3-25°, with low solar radi-<lb/>ation and moderate elevations ranging from 3200 to 4000 m. This first inventory of HT features is an important <lb/>and missing piece in documenting changes on the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau, and this new dataset also provides <lb/>an important basis for further studies, such as automated extraction of HT features, susceptibility analysis of HT, <lb/>and estimation of losses caused by HT. The datasets are available from the National Tibetan Plateau/Third Pole <lb/>Environment Data Center and can be downloaded from https://doi.org/10.11888/Cryos.tpdc.300805 (Peng and <lb/>Yang, 2023). <lb/></front>

        <body>1 Introduction <lb/>The Qilian Mountains are located in the northeastern part of <lb/>the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau, at the confluence of three ma-<lb/>jor geographical regions, i.e., the eastern monsoon zone, the <lb/>northwestern arid zone, and the alpine zone of the Qinghai-<lb/>Tibetan Plateau. The Qilian Mountains play an important role <lb/>in maintaining the ecological balance of the Tibetan Plateau, <lb/>stopping the southward progression of deserts, and maintain-<lb/>ing the stability of the oases in the Hexi Corridor. Due to its <lb/>unique geographical and environmental characteristics, per-<lb/>mafrost is widespread and underlies about 50 % of the area <lb/>(Ran et al., 2021). Permafrost has an important role in stor-<lb/>ing frozen water, thereby contributing to water conservation <lb/>(Wang et al., 2022). These roles can aid in inland river runoff <lb/>recharge, which is crucial to regional ecology, production, <lb/></body>

        <front>Published by Copernicus Publications. <lb/></front>

        <page>2034 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">X. Peng et al.: Hillslope thermokarst in the Qilian Mountains <lb/></note>

        <body>and life. Due to climate warming and human activities, sig-<lb/>nificant permafrost degradation results in the frequent occur-<lb/>rence of thermokarst, representing a serious threat to ecolog-<lb/>ical security and adversely impacting the environment and <lb/>human beings (Li et al., 2022a). <lb/>Despite the importance of thermokarst processes and their <lb/>potential geohazards, the distribution of thermokarst land-<lb/>scapes is currently mostly undocumented. The available dis-<lb/>tribution of thermokarst in the Northern Hemisphere, includ-<lb/>ing retrogressive thaw slumps (RTSs), thermokarst lakes, <lb/>and other terrain features, represents mainly probabilistic <lb/>estimates (Olefeldt et al., 2016; Yin et al., 2021; Huang <lb/>et al., 2023; Yang et al., 2023). Muster et al. (2017) de-<lb/>termined the distribution of circumpolar Arctic permafrost <lb/>lakes and ponds from 2002 to 2013 at a resolution of 5 m <lb/>using optical remote sensing, satellite (Geo-Eye, QuickBird, <lb/>WorldView-1 and WorldView-2, KOMPSAT-2), and radar <lb/>imagery (TerraSAR-X), but temporal inconsistencies make <lb/>comparisons in time and space difficult. At the regional scale, <lb/>the techniques and spatial resolution of remote sensing im-<lb/>agery currently used in different study areas are inconsis-<lb/>tent, e.g., estimating the distribution and development of <lb/>RTSs on Banks Island, Canada, based on the interpretation <lb/>of a Google Earth Engine Timelapse dataset (Lewkowicz and <lb/>Way, 2019). Satellite imagery at 30 m resolution from Land-<lb/>sat has been used to analyze RTSs and thermokarst lakes in <lb/>the region of Alaska within the circumpolar Arctic, eastern <lb/>Canada, and Siberia (Nitze et al., 2018). Nicu et al. (2023) <lb/>employed orthorectified imagery with a resolution of 5 m to <lb/>visually interpret and identify cryospheric hazards (such as <lb/>thaw slumps and thermo-erosion gullies) in Nordenskiöld <lb/>Land, covering an approximate area of 4000 km 2 in the <lb/>Svalbard Archipelago. The permafrost zone of the Qinghai-<lb/>Tibetan Plateau (QTP) has been a site of thermokarst geo-<lb/>morphology research in recent years. For example, combin-<lb/>ing field surveys and SPOT-5 satellite data for August 2010, <lb/>a total of 2163 thermokarst lakes and ponds were recorded <lb/>within 10 km on either side of the Chumar River to the <lb/>Fenghuo Mountains of the Qinghai-Tibet Railway, with a <lb/>total surface area of 1.09 × 10 7 m 2 and ranging in size from <lb/>100 m 2 to 4.49 × 10 5 m 2 (Luo et al., 2015; Niu et al., 2014). <lb/>In the Beiluhe region of the central QTP, the number of RTSs <lb/>increased from 124 to 438 between 2008 and 2017, with an <lb/>approximately 9-fold increase in area (Huang et al., 2020; <lb/>Luo et al., 2019). The latest results show that the number of <lb/>RTSs on the QTP is 2669, but for the Qilian Mountains in <lb/>the northeastern part of the region, only 6 (Luo et al., 2022) <lb/>or as many as 15 are documented (Mu et al., 2020). A lack <lb/>of a thermokarst inventory in this region is therefore evident, <lb/>representing a crucial gap in the RTS inventory on the QTP. <lb/>There is a frequent occurrence of hillslope thermokarst <lb/>hazards due to permafrost degradation, with significant eco-<lb/>logical impacts on the Qilian Mountains. The ecological en-<lb/>vironment of the permafrost areas has a significant impact, <lb/>and there is a direct correlation between human activities <lb/>and major permafrost engineering problems, including un-<lb/>even subsidence of infrastructure, slumps, and cracks. Mean-<lb/>while, there is little to no information regarding hillslope <lb/>thermokarst (HT) features such as RTSs, active-layer de-<lb/>tachment slides, and thermal erosion gullies (Gooseff et al., <lb/>2009) in the Qilian Mountains. HT refers to a specific type <lb/>of thermokarst formation that occurs in permafrost regions. <lb/>While this is similar to regular thermokarst, what distin-<lb/>guishes hillslope thermokarst is its occurrence on sloped <lb/>terrain or hillsides, where permafrost thaw leads to slope <lb/>instability. This can result in various landforms like ret-<lb/>rogressive thaw slumps, thermal erosion gullies, or active-<lb/>layer detachments, affecting the stability and shape of hill-<lb/>slopes in permafrost regions. These features can significantly <lb/>impact the landscape and have implications for infrastruc-<lb/>ture, ecosystems, and land use in areas affected by hillslope <lb/>thermokarst processes (Kokelj and Jorgenson, 2013; Olefeldt <lb/>et al., 2016; Gooseff et al., 2009). Thus, the urgent need to <lb/>survey and quantify these undocumented HT features in the <lb/>Qilian Mountains motivates and represents the goal of this <lb/>study. <lb/>2 Study area <lb/>The Qilian Mountains are located at the northern edge of <lb/>the QTP, with an average elevation of 3855 m. The region <lb/>is underlain by permafrost and seasonally frozen ground <lb/>(36-40°N, 94-104°E; Fig. 1a), with a permafrost area of <lb/>94 235 km 2 that accounts for 49 % of the study domain. Char-<lb/>acterized by both an alpine mountain climate and a temper-<lb/>ate continental monsoon climate, the mean annual air tem-<lb/>perature is 0.30 °C (Jin et al., 2022) with high precipitation <lb/>variability and higher amounts in the southeast during the <lb/>thawing season of June to September (Chen et al., 2013; Li <lb/>et al., 2022b). Due to human activities, climate change, and <lb/>earthquakes, permafrost instability in the Qilian Mountains <lb/>has gradually increased, resulting in HT formation includ-<lb/>ing RTSs, active-layer detachment slides, and thermal ero-<lb/>sion gullies, which pose a direct threat to the local economy, <lb/>ecology, and safety. <lb/>3 Data sources <lb/>We collected and collated validated satellite imagery avail-<lb/>able starting in 1999 for temporal detection of the onset of <lb/>the HT formation. These data include uncrewed aerial vehi-<lb/>cle imagery (e.g., Fig. 1b-h) and 30 m resolution digital ele-<lb/>vation model data from the Shuttle Radar Topography Mis-<lb/>sion (Farr et al., 2007). A combination of Omap and Google <lb/>Earth software was used to detect the location of HT occur-<lb/>rence, and Wayback Imagery provided by ESRI was used to <lb/>access high-resolution (&lt; 1 m) satellite imagery and Jilin-1 <lb/>satellite imagery (0.75 m) provided free of charge by China <lb/>Commercial Satellite Corporation to aid in the identification <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2033-2045, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2033-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">X. Peng et al.: Hillslope thermokarst in the Qilian Mountains <lb/></note>

        <page>2035 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 1. The location of the study area and (a) its HT distribution (Qilian Mountains permafrost extent data are from TPDC, 2020) and <lb/>(b-h) HT features obtained from different watersheds during our field surveys with the exception of (e) a Google Earth image. As this site is <lb/>too difficult to access, the positions corresponding to panels (b)-(h) have been labeled in panel (a). <lb/>Table 1. List of the data used for manual interpretation and mapping of HT features. <lb/>Software platform <lb/>Time span <lb/>Resolution Data sources <lb/>Google Earth Pro <lb/>1999-2022 <lb/>0.6-15 m <lb/>Quickbird, IKONOS <lb/>Omap <lb/>Since 2021 <lb/>&lt; 1 m <lb/>GF-2 <lb/>ESRI World Imagery Since 2014 <lb/>&lt; 1 m <lb/>WorldView-3, WorldView-4, etc. <lb/>Jilin-1 website <lb/>2022 <lb/>0.75 m <lb/>Jilin-1 <lb/>UAV images <lb/>Feb, Apr, May 2023 ∼ 15 cm <lb/>Field surveys <lb/>(Table 1). In addition, we used digital elevation model data <lb/>to calculate variables such as the slope and topographic posi-<lb/>tion index (TPI) of the HT. The TPI is calculated as follows <lb/>(Liang, 2023): <lb/>TPI = log 10 <lb/>E <lb/>Mean E <lb/>+ 1 × <lb/>S <lb/>Mean S <lb/>+ 1 , <lb/>(1) <lb/>where E is the elevation (m), S is the slope (°), and Mean <lb/>indicates that the mean value for the entire Qilian Mountains <lb/>region is used. <lb/>To further analyze the distribution of HT and the anal-<lb/>ogous environmental variables, we obtained seismic data <lb/>from the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS, 2024) describing <lb/>earthquakes, including their timing, epicenter location, and <lb/>magnitude. Categorizing vegetation types into deciduous-<lb/>coniferous forests (DCF), undergrowth (U ), alpine scrub <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2033-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2033-2045, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2036 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">X. Peng et al.: Hillslope thermokarst in the Qilian Mountains <lb/></note>

        <body>meadow (ASM), alpine meadow (AM), alpine grassland <lb/>(AG), alpine vegetation (AV), and non-vegetated area (NA) <lb/>was based on data from the Resource and Environment Sci-<lb/>ence and Data Center (RESDC, 2001). To assess the rela-<lb/>tionship of air temperature and precipitation with HT, we <lb/>downloaded monthly mean air temperature and precipitation <lb/>at 2 m a.g.l. from the fifth generation of the European Centre <lb/>for Medium-Range Weather Forecasts (ECMWF) reanalysis <lb/>(ERA5; Muñoz Sabater, 2019). <lb/>4 Methods <lb/>4.1 Manual mapping <lb/>We first quantified and mapped HT via remote sensing ob-<lb/>servations. Most occurrences of HT in the permafrost re-<lb/>gion of the Qilian Mountains since 2000 were compiled <lb/>by visual interpretation in Google Earth Pro and Omap. <lb/>They were also aided by high-resolution (&lt; 1 m) observa-<lb/>tions from ESRI Wayback Imagery, which archives all pub-<lb/>lished versions of world imagery (Table 1). We used a fish-<lb/>net with a mesh size of 1 × 1 km to segment the latest satel-<lb/>lite imagery for the entire Qilian Mountains area to quan-<lb/>tify HT mesh by mesh. RTSs are often horseshoe-shaped, <lb/>tongue-shaped, elongated, branched, and circle-chair-shaped <lb/>(Lantuit and Pollard, 2008; Yin et al., 2021) and character-<lb/>ized by a steep backwall, low-angle bottom, and tongue of <lb/>displaced saturated soil (Lantz and Kokelj, 2008; Nicu et al., <lb/>2021). These features are tonally and morphologically differ-<lb/>ent from their surroundings in color satellite images during <lb/>the thawing season. RTSs also produce folded textures due to <lb/>soil accumulation, which appear as laterally folded stripes on <lb/>imagery. Active-layer detachment slides are a common shal-<lb/>low landslide in permafrost areas. Their morphological char-<lb/>acteristics vary based on vegetation cover, slope, and per-<lb/>mafrost conditions, but common features include highly dis-<lb/>turbed slopes, lateral shear zones, and fracture zones formed <lb/>after the sliding of the active layer (Lewkowicz, 2007). We <lb/>detected and sketched these features based on morphologi-<lb/>cal, tonal, textural, shading, and other characteristics on re-<lb/>mote sensing images and then digitized their morphological <lb/>features into polygonal data. Although the accuracy of this <lb/>type of visual interpretation is relatively high, some HT fea-<lb/>tures can be missed via this manual interpretation. To reduce <lb/>such errors, satellite images of a similar period from differ-<lb/>ent sources were evaluated four times using the same meth-<lb/>ods to ensure accurate results. The date of the satellite image <lb/>when perturbations caused by HT can be first observed was <lb/>defined as the initiation year of a particular HT feature. De-<lb/>pending on the initiation year, HT is categorized as occurring <lb/>before 2010, during 2010-2015, or after 2015. To observe <lb/>the temporal evolution of HT features, we used the initia-<lb/>tion year and retraced historical images covering the Qilian <lb/>Mountains, a process that also helped us distinguish between <lb/>HT features and one-time transient landslides. <lb/>4.2 Field verification <lb/>Similar HT can have different morphological characteristics <lb/>due to different triggers. It is thus difficult to identify the type <lb/>of HT simply through imagery. In addition, after an initial <lb/>trigger and HT formation, thermokarst can evolve into differ-<lb/>ent types. For example, active-layer detachment slides may <lb/>transition into RTSs due to the exposure of subsurface ice at <lb/>the trailing edge and water erosion due to thawing, which can <lb/>cause the RTS to further progress into mudflows. Therefore, <lb/>with visual interpretation based on imagery only providing <lb/>individual snapshots, it is essential to also conduct field sur-<lb/>veys as a validation exercise. We conducted a total of three <lb/>field surveys in the winter of 2022 and the spring and sum-<lb/>mer of 2023. Field work covered the Shiyanghe basin, Heihe <lb/>basin, Datonghe basin, Qinghai Lake basin, and Shulehe <lb/>basin. Due to the harsh climatic conditions and accessibil-<lb/>ity issues in the Qilian Mountains, uncrewed aerial vehicles <lb/>were used to survey and verify hard-to-reach areas. <lb/>4.3 Morphological and spatial statistical analysis <lb/>A landscape shape index (LSI) can be quantified to character-<lb/>ize shape complexity by calculating the degree of deviation <lb/>of a given patch from a circle or square of the same area. To <lb/>quantify the shape characteristics of HT features, two LSIs <lb/>are calculated as follows: <lb/>LSI square = <lb/>0.25P <lb/>√ <lb/>A <lb/>, <lb/>(2) <lb/>LSI round = <lb/>P <lb/>2 <lb/>√ <lb/>π A <lb/>, <lb/>(3) <lb/>where P is the perimeter (m) and A is the area (m 2 ). The <lb/>closer the values of LSI square or LSI round are to 1, the squarer <lb/>or rounder, respectively, the shape of the HT feature is. <lb/>To further investigate the spatial distribution of HT, we <lb/>computed a global Moran index, z score, and p value to de-<lb/>termine whether there is autocorrelation in the spatial distri-<lb/>bution of HT, where p values of z scores are used to mea-<lb/>sure statistical significance. When the p value &lt; 0.01 and <lb/>the z score &gt; 2.58, there is a 99 % probability that HTs will <lb/>be clustered within the study area. The smaller the p value <lb/>and the larger the z score, the greater the probability that <lb/>such spatial patterns will be clustered. Moran&apos;s index ranges <lb/>from -1 to 1, with negative values corresponding to negative <lb/>correlations and positive values to positive correlations, and <lb/>0 denotes that the spatial objects in the study area are inde-<lb/>pendent of each other. Additionally, the closer the index is <lb/>to 1, the more clustered the HT features are, and the closer <lb/>the index is to -1, the more dispersed the HT features are. <lb/>To delineate the regions that may have spatial autocorrelation <lb/>(Bivand and Wong, 2018), we further process local autocor-<lb/>relation on this basis. The local autocorrelation regions are <lb/>divided into four types based on the local Moran index: high-<lb/>high (HH) clustering, high-low (HL) clustering, low-high <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2033-2045, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2033-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">X. Peng et al.: Hillslope thermokarst in the Qilian Mountains <lb/></note>

        <page>2037 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 2. Frequency distribution of HT on the Qilian Mountains. The concentration of HT features is shown per 100 km 2 grid cell. <lb/>(LH) clustering, and low-low (LL) clustering. HH signifies a <lb/>region with both a higher amount of HT and a higher number <lb/>of neighboring regions also with a higher amount of HT, HL <lb/>indicates a region with a higher amount of HT surrounded <lb/>by neighboring regions with a lower amount of HT, LH indi-<lb/>cates a region with a lower number of HT neighboring areas <lb/>with a higher amount of HT, and LL represents a region with <lb/>both a lower amount of HT and neighboring regions with a <lb/>lower amount of HT. Although the methods described above <lb/>can identify global and local spatial autocorrelations, respec-<lb/>tively, they are unable to identify clusters of concentrated HT <lb/>features. We therefore also apply hotspot analysis, which is <lb/>another effective way of exploring the characteristics of lo-<lb/>cal spatial distributions. All the above techniques are based <lb/>on spatial statistical analysis functions in ArcGIS. <lb/>To explore the effects of climate on HT, we obtained the <lb/>monthly mean air temperature and precipitation at 2 m a.g.l. <lb/>from ERA5 over the period 2000-2020 and calculated their <lb/>annual spatial means and standard deviations (Fig. 6). <lb/>5 Results <lb/>Our inventory of HT includes the Heihe basin, Shulehe basin, <lb/>Datonghe basin, Shiyanghe basin, Qinghai Lake basin, and <lb/>Tsaidam basin within the Qilian Mountains, with a total of <lb/>1064 HT features. In any 100 km 2 grid cell, the maximum <lb/>density of HT is 63 (Fig. 2). This density is lower than the <lb/>68 per 25 km 2 in the central Tibetan Plateau reported by Luo <lb/>et al. (2022) and the 88 per 25 km 2 on Banks Island, Canada, <lb/>from Lewkowicz and Way (2019); 67 % of these HT features <lb/>were identified in the Heihe River basin, followed by the Da-<lb/>tonghe River basin, accounting for 19 %. The HT distribution <lb/>in these river basins is irregular, corroborated by a positive <lb/>statistically significant Moran index value of 0.3, a p value <lb/>of 0.00001, and a z score of 32.5. Of all the HT features, <lb/>the largest area is 58 ha and the smallest area is 0.01 ha, with <lb/>most being smaller than 10 ha. The average area is 1.75 ha, <lb/>with a total area of 1708 ha. <lb/>The spatial distribution of RTSs on the QTP is strongly <lb/>controlled by terrain factors such as the elevation, slope, TPI, <lb/>and aspect (Luo et al., 2022). The statistical results indi-<lb/>cate that HT is observed at elevations ranging from 2835 <lb/>to 4550 m. However, 90 % of HTs are more likely to occur <lb/>at elevations ranging from 3200 to 4000 m in the middle-<lb/>or high-elevation areas of the Qilian Mountains. HT tends <lb/>to occur on north-facing slopes (Fig. 3b and d), with slopes <lb/>ranging from 3 to 25°(Fig. 3c). In addition, the TPI shows <lb/>that ∼ 85 % of the HTs occur mainly between 0.5 and 0.8 <lb/>(Fig. 3a), suggesting that they commonly occur in locations <lb/>that are lower than their surroundings. Both LSI indices sug-<lb/>gest that 75 % of the HTs have values close to 1.0 (Fig. 3e), <lb/>indicating that most HTs are simple in shape and compact in <lb/>morphology (Niu et al., 2016). Alpine meadow areas contain <lb/>∼ 53 % of HTs, followed by alpine scrub meadows, which <lb/>contain 13 % (Fig. 3f). <lb/>The initiation years of HT features are variable across <lb/>the study area: 187 HT features (18 %) were identified be-<lb/>fore 2010 and the remaining 82 % in the last 10 years; 392 <lb/>sites (37 %) were initiated in 2010-2015 and 482 (45 %) af-<lb/>ter 2015. Much of the newly initiated HT occurred in the <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2033-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2033-2045, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2038 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">X. Peng et al.: Hillslope thermokarst in the Qilian Mountains <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 3. The number of HT terrain features (y axes) of HT as categorized by the (a) topographic position index (TPI), (b) elevation, <lb/>(c) slope, (d) aspect, (e) landscape shape index (LSI), and (f) vegetation type, including deciduous-coniferous forests (DCF), undergrowth <lb/>(U ), alpine scrub meadow (ASM), alpine meadow (AM), alpine grassland (AG), alpine vegetation (AV), and non-vegetated area (NA). The <lb/>blue vertical lines at the bottom of panels (a-c) represent the number of HT features in each x-axis bin. <lb/>Heihe basin and the middle and upper reaches of the Da-<lb/>tonghe basin (Fig. 4), which is also a HT hotspot region. <lb/>The recent increase in HT can be attributed to the anomalous <lb/>weather conditions in the corresponding years. The associ-<lb/>ation between newly observed HT and meteorological data <lb/>indicates a sudden HT increase in years with unusually high <lb/>temperatures during the thawing season (Fig. 6). <lb/>6 Discussion <lb/>6.1 Drivers of HT in the Qilian Mountains <lb/>6.1.1 Permafrost conditions <lb/>Formation of HT is facilitated by thick subsurface ice <lb/>and various internal and external environmental conditions <lb/>(Stephani et al., 2023). Permafrost stability in ∼ 80 % of the <lb/>permafrost area of the Qilian Mountains is predominantly <lb/>transitional, and higher permafrost temperatures (Ran et al., <lb/>2021) will exacerbate the climate sensitivity of this area <lb/>(Lewkowicz and Way, 2019; Patton et al., 2021), leading to <lb/>melting of the subsurface ice and an increase in active-layer <lb/>thickness, thus decreasing the stability of the slope (Behnia <lb/>and Blais-Stevens, 2018). This is also supported by our find-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2033-2045, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2033-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">X. Peng et al.: Hillslope thermokarst in the Qilian Mountains <lb/></note>

        <page>2039 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 4. The timing of HT initiation within 100 km 2 grid cells. <lb/>ing that ∼ 90 % of HT occurs in the transition zone between <lb/>permafrost and seasonally frozen soil where the mean annual <lb/>ground temperature is greater than -1 °C. <lb/>6.1.2 Environmental factors <lb/>Topographic conditions facilitate the formation of subsurface <lb/>ice and the continuous development of HT. At elevations be-<lb/>low 5100 m on the QTP, aspect dominates the distribution <lb/>of permafrost. More permafrost underlies regions of shaded, <lb/>north-facing slopes than sunny, south-facing slopes (Ran <lb/>et al., 2021). Indeed, we find that ∼ 95 % of Qilian Moun-<lb/>tains HT is found on north-facing slopes, where it also en-<lb/>hances vegetation growth and soil moisture storage (Jin et al., <lb/>2009). Lower solar radiation, higher permafrost ice content, <lb/>and shallow active-layer thickness (Lacelle et al., 2015; Ward <lb/>Jones et al., 2019) also enable HT formation (Luo et al., <lb/>2022; Niu et al., 2016; Xia et al., 2022). We find that more <lb/>than half of the HT occurs in alpine meadows, which requires <lb/>more water content than alpine steppes (Yin et al., 2017) and <lb/>consequently also results in more ground ice development <lb/>under this vegetation type. We determined that ∼ 90 % of <lb/>HT in the Qilian Mountains occurs on 3 to 25°slopes. Low <lb/>and gentle slopes are favorable for groundwater pooling (Luo <lb/>et al., 2022), whereas slopes greater than 16°are relatively <lb/>steep and therefore not conducive to groundwater enrichment <lb/>for ice formation, but such slopes also provide dynamic con-<lb/>ditions for active-layer detachments and collapsing ground <lb/>(Wang, 1990). We also observe more HT initiation at loca-<lb/>tions that are lower compared to their surroundings, as such <lb/>depressions favor the accumulation of snow and rainwater <lb/>(Stieglitz et al., 2003) and prevent heat loss from the soil. <lb/>This encourages melting of subsurface ice (Zhang, 2005) at <lb/>the base of the active layer and, after an unstable layer is <lb/>formed between the permafrost and the active layer, the over-<lb/>lying soil can slide along the slope (Patton et al., 2021). <lb/>The Qilian Mountains were and are still formed by the on-<lb/>going collision of the Indian Ocean Plate and the Eurasian <lb/>Plate, resulting in the Qilian Mountains-Hexi Corridor ac-<lb/>tive fault system (Xiong et al., 2017) that has seen nearly <lb/>400 earthquakes of magnitude 2 or greater over the past <lb/>2 decades. In particular, the high seismic activity of the <lb/>Heihe, Shiyanghe, and Datonghe basins (Fig. 7a) represents <lb/>a potential threat to the safety and integrity of current and <lb/>future infrastructure in the region. During our field investiga-<lb/>tions we found a nearly 3 km long and 2 m deep slope frac-<lb/>ture caused by a 6.9 magnitude earthquake in 2022, resulting <lb/>in a massive exposure of subsurface ice and the collapse of <lb/>the Lanzhou-Xinjiang high-speed rail tunnel (Fig. 7b and c). <lb/>The occurrence of an earthquake can result in an instanta-<lb/>neous increase in porewater pressure and sliding forces that <lb/>reduce slope stability and potentially lead to a massive ex-<lb/>posure of subsurface ice (Niu et al., 2016; Xia et al., 2022), <lb/>sediment liquefaction (Dadfar et al., 2017), and permafrost <lb/>warming due to the seismic vibrations. These vibrations lead <lb/>to cracking and deformation of the ice layers within the per-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2033-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2033-2045, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2040 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">X. Peng et al.: Hillslope thermokarst in the Qilian Mountains <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 5. (a) Spatial autocorrelation indicating high-high (HH), high-low (HL), and low-high (LH) clustering, together with (b) hotspot <lb/>analysis where the different colors represent the confidence levels. <lb/>mafrost, releasing moisture and heat and consequently re-<lb/>sulting in a temperature rise of the permafrost. Additionally, <lb/>earthquakes can induce the flow of porewater within the per-<lb/>mafrost, further influencing its temperature (Che et al., 2014) <lb/>and creating the ideal setting for active-layer detachment <lb/>slides. The clustering of earthquake activity in the lower-left <lb/>corner of Fig. 7a is not associated with HT features, because <lb/>there is no permafrost in this region. <lb/>6.1.3 Climate factors <lb/>Extreme summer temperatures and precipitation have been <lb/>identified as triggers for the initiation of RTSs in many Arc-<lb/>tic permafrost zones (Balser et al., 2014; Kokelj et al., 2015; <lb/>Lewkowicz and Way, 2019; Segal et al., 2016). Given our <lb/>finding that 82 % of HT was initiated in approximately the <lb/>last decade (Fig. 4), mostly during 2010-2015 and after <lb/>2015, we used ERA5 to determine the temperature and pre-<lb/>cipitation characteristics for the Qilian Mountains over the <lb/>last 20 years (Li et al., 2022b) (Fig. 6, square symbols). The <lb/>mean thawing season air temperatures in 2010 and 2016 were <lb/>higher than in other years (Fig. 6a, red square symbols). A <lb/>warming thaw season could lead to thaw consolidation at the <lb/>base of the active layer or to higher porewater pressure in <lb/>the transient thaw layer, reducing the effective shear strength <lb/>and causing slope failure (Lewkowicz and Way, 2019). The <lb/>anomalous air temperatures during the thawing season could <lb/>accelerate permafrost thaw and expose ice-rich permafrost, <lb/>thus leading to new HT (Fig. 6a, dark brown and dark red <lb/>bars, respectively). Rainfall infiltration may transfer heat to <lb/>the top layer of the permafrost and induce melting of ground <lb/>ice in ice-rich transient layers, which would increase the <lb/>porewater pressure at the active layer-permafrost interface <lb/>and thereby trigger formation of HT (Luo et al., 2022). How-<lb/>ever, precipitation variability during the thawing season does <lb/>not match HT formation (Fig. 6b). Despite high precipitation <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2033-2045, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2033-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">X. Peng et al.: Hillslope thermokarst in the Qilian Mountains <lb/></note>

        <page>2041 <lb/></page>

      <body>Figure 6. The relationship between HT numbers (variable-width <lb/>bars, with the darker colors representing years with extreme weather <lb/>events) and (a) temperature and (b) precipitation in the thawing <lb/>season from 2000 to 2020 (square symbols, with the red squares <lb/>and the blue squares representing the extreme weather events). The <lb/>solid horizontal line represents the mean air temperature and pre-<lb/>cipitation, respectively, and the dashed lines represent ± 1 standard <lb/>deviation. <lb/>in both 2007 and 2018 (Fig. 6b, blue squares), no initiation <lb/>of HT was found to subsequently coincide with these peaks <lb/>(blue squares), and precipitation also does not explain the <lb/>significant initiation of HTs between 2010 and 2015 or after <lb/>2015 (Fig. 6b, yellow and red bars, respectively). The same <lb/>conclusion also applies to the other three subregions -Hoh <lb/>Xil, Maqu County, and Honglianghe -and it could be specu-<lb/>lated that the nature of the soils on the QTP may instead play <lb/>a role (Luo et al., 2022). <lb/>6.1.4 Human activities <lb/>Extensive and increasing human activities have been shown <lb/>to significantly accelerate permafrost degradation (Cheng <lb/>and Jin, 2013; IPCC, 2019). The total population of the <lb/>Qilian Mountains is about 60 000, and there are approxi-<lb/>mately 1000 metal, energy, and other types of mineral de-<lb/>posits (NMPD, 2021) and ∼ 8000 km of railroads and high-<lb/>ways. The core of this human activity is concentrated on the <lb/>eastern side of the Qilian Mountains, which generally co-<lb/>incides with the spatial distribution of the HT hotspots we <lb/>documented. This qualitatively suggests a role of human ac-<lb/>tivities in HT from, e.g., engineering disturbances or vegeta-<lb/>tion degradation due to overgrazing (Sharkhuu et al., 2007). <lb/>Establishing the impact of human activities on HT quanti-<lb/>tatively is still a difficult challenge, but our identification of <lb/>the location and timing of HT formation is a first, important <lb/>step for further future studies, and especially for the socioe-<lb/>conomic development in the region. <lb/></body>

      <div type="availability">7 Data availability <lb/>DEM data can be accessed through NASA (https:// <lb/>www.earthdata.nasa.gov/sensors/srtm, Farr et al., 2007). <lb/>Landsat5-8 data are available from the USGS (https://www. <lb/>usgs.gov/, last access: 29 April 2024; Gorelick et al., 2017) <lb/>and Sentinel-2 from the ESA (https://www.esa.int/, last ac-<lb/>cess: 29 April 2024; Gorelick et al., 2017) and can be down-<lb/>loaded through Google Earth Engine. ESRI World Imagery <lb/>can be accessed through ESRI Wayback Imagery at https: <lb/>//livingatlas.arcgis.com/wayback (Esri Inc., 2023). Some <lb/>GF-2 imagery is also available online through the Omap <lb/>software (https://www.ovital.com/283-2/, GF-2, 2020), and <lb/>high-resolution 3D satellite imagery of the Qilian Moun-<lb/>tains region can be viewed in Google Earth software. High-<lb/>resolution satellite images captured by the Jilin-1 satellite <lb/>in China can be viewed by accessing https://www.jl1mall. <lb/>com/rskit/viewMapSource (Jilin-1 satellite Inc., 2022). The <lb/>HT inventory for the Qilian Mountains can be freely down-<lb/>loaded from the National Tibetan Plateau/Third Pole En-<lb/>vironment Data Center (https://doi.org/10.11888/Cryos.tpdc. <lb/>300805, Peng and Yang, 2023). <lb/></div>

      <body>8 Conclusion <lb/>This study used visual interpretation and field investigations <lb/>with repeated verification to investigate HT in the permafrost <lb/>zone of the Qilian Mountains. We successfully produced the <lb/>first HT inventory for this area, identifying a total of 1064 <lb/>HT features. The area of these features ranged from 0.01 to <lb/>58 ha, with an average of 1.75 ha. Thermokarst is primarily <lb/>concentrated at the junction between the upstream portion <lb/>of the Heihe basin and the middle and upstream portions of <lb/>the Datonghe basin. Within a 10 × 10 km area, thermokarst <lb/>has a maximum density of 63 features, affecting an area <lb/>of ∼ 20 km 2 . HT in the Qilian Mountains is more likely to <lb/>occur on north-facing shaded slopes at elevations between <lb/>3200 and 4000 m, on slopes of 3-25°, with 0.5 &lt; TPI &lt; 0.8, <lb/>and in alpine meadow vegetation. Based on long-term satel-<lb/>lite imagery, 874 new HT features were initiated after 2010, <lb/>accounting for 82 % of all HT features. Of these, 392 and <lb/>482 were initiated during the periods of 2010-2015 and af-<lb/>ter 2015, respectively. Recent higher air temperatures during <lb/>the thawing season are likely important reasons for the in-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2033-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2033-2045, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2042 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">X. Peng et al.: Hillslope thermokarst in the Qilian Mountains <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 7. Qilian Mountains showing (a) the location of HT locations and earthquakes with magnitude &gt; 2 in the last 20 years, (b) slope <lb/>fractures caused by earthquakes, and (c) exposed subsurface ice. <lb/>tensification of HT formation in the Qilian Mountains, while <lb/>precipitation does not seem to play a role. This first HT in-<lb/>ventory for the Qilian Mountains will be fundamental for <lb/>quantitative assessments that explore the exact causes and <lb/>underlying thermokarst processes, providing observational <lb/>data support for automated extraction of HT features and ulti-<lb/>mately enhancing the identification and prediction of regions <lb/>prone to thermokarst processes in the future. Furthermore, <lb/>it will facilitate the evaluation of local risk levels, potential <lb/>economic losses, population casualties, and other impacts, <lb/>thereby furnishing governmental decision-makers and rele-<lb/>vant stakeholders with essential reference materials for miti-<lb/>gating potential risks. <lb/></body>

        <div type="contribution">Author contributions. XP and GY designed the research and ob-<lb/>tained funding. GY analyzed the data and prepared the data files. <lb/>GY, WT, XL, and XP conducted the field work. GY, XP, OWF, JL, <lb/>CM, and FN wrote the paper with input from the co-authors and <lb/>coordinated the analysis and contributions from all the co-authors. <lb/>XP and GY contributed to the work equally and should be regarded <lb/>as co-first authors. <lb/></div>

        <div type="conflict">Competing interests. The contact author has declared that none <lb/>of the authors has any competing interests. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Disclaimer. Publisher&apos;s note: Copernicus Publications remains <lb/>neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims made in the text, pub-<lb/>lished maps, institutional affiliations, or any other geographical rep-<lb/>resentation in this paper. While Copernicus Publications makes ev-<lb/>ery effort to include appropriate place names, the final responsibility <lb/>lies with the authors. <lb/></div>

        <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements. We sincerely appreciate the valuable feed-<lb/>back and constructive suggestions provided by the two anonymous <lb/>reviewers and Haijun Qiu on this manuscript. Their insightful com-<lb/>ments have significantly enhanced the quality and clarity of our <lb/>work. We also extend our heartfelt gratitude to the editors for their <lb/>dedication and meticulous attention throughout the review and pub-<lb/></div>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2033-2045, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2033-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">X. Peng et al.: Hillslope thermokarst in the Qilian Mountains <lb/></note>

        <page>2043 <lb/></page>

        <div type="acknowledgement">lication process. Furthermore, we express our gratitude to the data <lb/>providers mentioned in the manuscript for their selfless sharing of <lb/>datasets. Their spirit of open collaboration and their willingness to <lb/>share data have been crucial to the completion of this research. <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">Financial support. This research has been supported by the Sec-<lb/>ond Tibetan Plateau Scientific Expedition and Research Program <lb/>(STEP) (grant no. 2019QZKK0905), the National Natural Science <lb/>Foundation of China (grant nos. 42161160328 and 42171120), and <lb/>the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities (grant <lb/>no. lzujbky2023-01). <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Review statement. This paper was edited by Hao Shi and re-<lb/>viewed by Haijun Qiu and two anonymous referees. <lb/></div>

        <listBibl>References <lb/>Balser, A. W., Jones, J. B., and Gens, R.: Timing of retro-<lb/>gressive thaw slump initiation in the Noatak Basin, north-<lb/>west Alaska, USA, J. Geophys. Res.-Earth, 119, 1106-1120, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/2013JF002889, 2014. <lb/>Behnia, P. and Blais-Stevens, A.: Landslide susceptibility modelling <lb/>using the quantitative random forest method along the north-<lb/>ern portion of the Yukon Alaska Highway Corridor, Canada, <lb/>Nat. Hazards, 90, 1407-1426, https://doi.org/10.1007/s11069-<lb/>017-3104-z, 2018. <lb/>Bivand, R. S. and Wong, D. W. S.: Comparing implementations of <lb/>global and local indicators of spatial association, TEST, 27, 716-<lb/>748, https://doi.org/10.1007/s11749-018-0599-x, 2018. <lb/>Che, A., Wu, Z., and Wang, P.: Stability of pile founda-<lb/>tions base on warming effects on the permafrost un-<lb/>der earthquake motions, Soils Found., 54, 639-647, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sandf.2014.06.006, 2014. <lb/>Chen, H., Zhu, Q., Peng, C., Wu, N., Wang, Y., Fang, X., Gao, <lb/>Y., Zhu, D., Yang, G., Tian, J., Kang, X., Piao, S., Ouyang, <lb/>H., Xiang, W., Luo, Z., Jiang, H., Song, X., Zhang, Y., Yu, G., <lb/>Zhao, X., Gong, P., Yao, T., and Wu, J.: The impacts of climate <lb/>change and human activities on biogeochemical cycles on the <lb/>Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau, Glob. Change Biol., 19, 2940-2955, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.12277, 2013. <lb/>Cheng, G. and Jin, H.: Permafrost and groundwater on the Qinghai-<lb/>Tibet Plateau and in northeast China, Hydrogeol. J., 21, 5-23, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10040-012-0927-2, 2013. <lb/>Dadfar, B., El Naggar, M. H., and Nastev, M.: Quantifying expo-<lb/>sure of linear infrastructures to earthquake-triggered transverse <lb/>landslides in permafrost thawing slopes, Can. Geotech. J., 54, <lb/>1002-1012, https://doi.org/10.1139/cgj-2017-0076, 2017. <lb/>Esri Inc.: Wayback imagery, Esri Inc. [data set], https://livingatlas. <lb/>arcgis.com/wayback/ (last access: 25 April 2024), 2023. <lb/>Farr, T. G., Rosen, P. A., Caro, E., Crippen, R., Duren, R., <lb/>Hensley, S., Kobrick, M., Paller, M., Rodriguez, E., Roth, <lb/>L., Seal, D., Shaffer, S., Shimada, J., Umland, J., Werner, <lb/>M., Oskin, M., Burbank, D., and Alsdorf, D.: The Shuttle <lb/>Radar Topography Mission, Rev. Geophys., 45, 2005RG000183, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2005RG000183, 2007 (data available <lb/>at: https://www.earthdata.nasa.gov/sensors/srtm, last access: <lb/>29 April 2024). <lb/>GF-2: Gaofen-2 imagery, Omap Inc. [data set], https://www.ovital. <lb/>com/283-2/ (last access: 25 April 2024), 2020. <lb/>Gooseff, M. N., Balser, A., Bowden, W. B., and Jones, J. B.: Effects <lb/>of Hillslope Thermokarst in Northern Alaska, Eos T. Am. Geo-<lb/>phys. Un., 90, 29-30, https://doi.org/10.1029/2009EO040001, <lb/>2009. <lb/>Gorelick, N., Hancher, M., Dixon, M., Ilyushchenko, S., Thau, D., <lb/>and Moore, R.: Google Earth Engine: Planetary-scale geospa-<lb/>tial analysis for everyone, Remote Sens. Environ., 202, 18-27, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rse.2017.06.031, 2017. <lb/>Huang, L., Luo, J., Lin, Z., Niu, F., and Liu, L.: Using deep learn-<lb/>ing to map retrogressive thaw slumps in the Beiluhe region (Ti-<lb/>betan Plateau) from CubeSat images, Remote Sens. Environ., <lb/>237, 111534, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.rse.2019.111534, 2020. <lb/>Huang, L., Willis, M. J., Li, G., Lantz, T. C., Schaefer, K., Wig, E., <lb/>Cao, G., and Tiampo, K. F.: Identifying active retrogressive thaw <lb/>slumps from ArcticDEM, ISPRS J. Photogramm., 205, 301-316, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.isprsjprs.2023.10.008, 2023. <lb/>Jilin-1 satellite Inc.: Jilin-1 satellite imagery, Jilin-1 satellite Inc. <lb/>[data set], https://www.jl1mall.com/rskit/viewMapSource (last <lb/>access: 25 April 2024), 2022. <lb/>Jin, H., Li, X., Frauenfeld, O. W., Zhao, Y., Chen, C., Du, R., <lb/>Du, J., and Peng, X.: Comparisons of statistical downscaling <lb/>methods for air temperature over the Qilian Mountains, Theor. <lb/>Appl. Climatol., 149, 893-896, https://doi.org/10.1007/s00704-<lb/>022-04081-w, 2022. <lb/>Jin, X., Wan, L., Zhang, Y.-K., Hu, G., Schaepman, M. E., <lb/>Clevers, J. G. P. W., and Su, Z. B.: Quantification of spa-<lb/>tial distribution of vegetation in the Qilian Mountain area <lb/>with MODIS NDVI, Int. J. Remote Sens., 30, 5751-5766, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/01431160902736635, 2009. <lb/>Kokelj, S. V. and Jorgenson, M. T.: Advances in Thermokarst <lb/>Research: Recent Advances in Research Investigating <lb/>Thermokarst Processes, Permafrost Periglac., 24, 108-119, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/ppp.1779, 2013. <lb/>Kokelj, S. V., Tunnicliffe, J., Lacelle, D., Lantz, T. C., Chin, K. <lb/>S., and Fraser, R.: Increased precipitation drives mega slump <lb/>development and destabilization of ice-rich permafrost ter-<lb/>rain, northwestern Canada, Global Planet. Change, 129, 56-68, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gloplacha.2015.02.008, 2015. <lb/>Lacelle, D., Brooker, A., Fraser, R. H., and Kokelj, S. V.: Distribu-<lb/>tion and growth of thaw slumps in the Richardson Mountains-<lb/>Peel Plateau region, northwestern Canada, Geomorphology, 235, <lb/>40-51, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.geomorph.2015.01.024, 2015. <lb/>Lantuit, H. and Pollard, W. H.: Fifty years of coastal erosion and <lb/>retrogressive thaw slump activity on Herschel Island, southern <lb/>Beaufort Sea, Yukon Territory, Canada, Geomorphology, 95, 84-<lb/>102, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.geomorph.2006.07.040, 2008. <lb/>Lantz, T. C. and Kokelj, S. V.: Increasing rates of retro-<lb/>gressive thaw slump activity in the Mackenzie Delta re-<lb/>gion, N. W. T., Canada, Geophys. Res. Lett., 35, L06502, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2007GL032433, 2008. <lb/>Lewkowicz, A. G.: Dynamics of active-layer detachment failures, <lb/>Fosheim Peninsula, Ellesmere Island, Nunavut, Canada, Per-<lb/>mafrost Periglac., 18, 89-103, https://doi.org/10.1002/ppp.578, <lb/>2007. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2033-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2033-2045, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>2044 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">X. Peng et al.: Hillslope thermokarst in the Qilian Mountains <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>Lewkowicz, A. G. and Way, R. G.: Extremes of sum-<lb/>mer climate trigger thousands of thermokarst landslides <lb/>in a High Arctic environment, Nat. Commun., 10, 1329, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-019-09314-7, 2019. <lb/>Li, Y., Qin, X., Liu, Y., Jin, Z., Liu, J., Wang, L., and Chen, <lb/>J.: Evaluation of Long-Term and High-Resolution Gridded <lb/>Precipitation and Temperature Products in the Qilian Moun-<lb/>tains, Qinghai-Tibet Plateau, Front. Environ. Sci., 10, 906821, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3389/fenvs.2022.906821, 2022. <lb/>Liang, L., Sun, Y., Guan, Q., Pan, N., Du, Q., Mi, J., and Shan, Y.: <lb/>Projection of landscape ecological risk and exploration of terrain <lb/>effects in the Qilian Mountains, China, Land Degrad. Dev., 34, <lb/>4575-4593, https://doi.org/10.1002/ldr.4794, 2023. <lb/>Luo, J., Niu, F., Lin, Z., Liu, M., and Yin, G.: Thermokarst <lb/>lake changes between 1969 and 2010 in the Beilu River <lb/>Basin, Qinghai-Tibet Plateau, China, Sci. Bull., 60, 556-564, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11434-015-0730-2, 2015. <lb/>Luo, J., Niu, F., Lin, Z., Liu, M., and Yin, G.: Recent acceleration <lb/>of thaw slumping in permafrost terrain of Qinghai-Tibet Plateau: <lb/>An example from the Beiluhe Region, Geomorphology, 341, 79-<lb/>85, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.geomorph.2019.05.020, 2019. <lb/>Luo, J., Niu, F., Lin, Z., Liu, M., Yin, G., and Gao, Z.: Inven-<lb/>tory and Frequency of Retrogressive Thaw Slumps in Permafrost <lb/>Region of the Qinghai-Tibet Plateau, Geophys. Res. Lett., 49, <lb/>e2022GL099829, https://doi.org/10.1029/2022GL099829, 2022. <lb/>Mu, C., Shang, J., Zhang, T., Fan, C., Wang, S., Peng, X., <lb/>Zhong, W., Zhang, F., Mu, M., and Jia, L.: Acceleration of <lb/>thaw slump during 1997-2017 in the Qilian Mountains of the <lb/>northern Qinghai-Tibetan plateau, Landslides, 17, 1051-1062, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10346-020-01344-3, 2020. <lb/>Muñoz Sabater, J.: ERA5-Land monthly averaged data from 1950 to <lb/>present Copernicus Climate Change Service (C3S) Climate Data <lb/>Store (CDS) [data set], https://doi.org/10.24381/cds.68d2bb30, <lb/>2019. <lb/>Muster, S., Roth, K., Langer, M., Lange, S., Cresto Aleina, F., <lb/>Bartsch, A., Morgenstern, A., Grosse, G., Jones, B., Sannel, A. <lb/>B. K., Sjöberg, Y., Günther, F., Andresen, C., Veremeeva, A., <lb/>Lindgren, P. R., Bouchard, F., Lara, M. J., Fortier, D., Charbon-<lb/>neau, S., Virtanen, T. A., Hugelius, G., Palmtag, J., Siewert, M. <lb/>B., Riley, W. J., Koven, C. D., and Boike, J.: PeRL: a circum-<lb/>Arctic Permafrost Region Pond and Lake database, Earth Syst. <lb/>Sci. Data, 9, 317-348, https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-9-317-2017, <lb/>2017. <lb/>National Mineral Properties Database (NMPD): National Mineral <lb/>Properties Database 2021 Edition [data set], http://data.ngac. <lb/>org.cn/mineralresource/index.html (last access: 25 April 2024), <lb/>2021. <lb/>Nicu, I. C., Lombardo, L., and Rubensdotter, L.: Preliminary <lb/>assessment of thaw slump hazard to Arctic cultural heritage <lb/>in Nordenskiöld Land, Svalbard, Landslides, 18, 2935-2947, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10346-021-01684-8, 2021. <lb/>Nicu, I. C., Elia, L., Rubensdotter, L., Tanyaş, H., and Lom-<lb/>bardo, L.: Multi-hazard susceptibility mapping of cryospheric <lb/>hazards in a high-Arctic environment: Svalbard Archipelago, <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 15, 447-464, https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-<lb/>15-447-2023, 2023. <lb/>Nitze, I., Grosse, G., Jones, B. M., Romanovsky, V. E., and Boike, <lb/>J.: Remote sensing quantifies widespread abundance of per-<lb/>mafrost region disturbances across the Arctic and Subarctic, Nat. <lb/>Commun., 9, 5423, https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-018-07663-<lb/>3, 2018. <lb/>Niu, F., Luo, J., Lin, Z., Liu, M., and Yin, G.: Morphological <lb/>Characteristics of Thermokarst Lakes along the Qinghai-Tibet <lb/>Engineering Corridor, Arct. Antarct. Alp. Res., 46, 963-974, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1657/1938-4246-46.4.963, 2014. <lb/>Niu, F., Luo, J., Lin, Z., Fang, J., and Liu, M.: Thaw-induced <lb/>slope failures and stability analyses in permafrost regions <lb/>of the Qinghai-Tibet Plateau, China, Landslides, 13, 55-65, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10346-014-0545-2, 2016. <lb/>Olefeldt, D., Goswami, S., Grosse, G., Hayes, D., Hugelius, G., <lb/>Kuhry, P., McGuire, A. D., Romanovsky, V. E., Sannel, A. B. K., <lb/>Schuur, E. A. G., and Turetsky, M. R.: Circumpolar distribution <lb/>and carbon storage of thermokarst landscapes, Nat. Commun., 7, <lb/>13043, https://doi.org/10.1038/ncomms13043, 2016. <lb/>Patton, A. I., Rathburn, S. L., Capps, D. M., McGrath, D., <lb/>and Brown, R. A.: Ongoing Landslide Deformation in Thaw-<lb/>ing Permafrost, Geophys. Res. Lett., 48, e2021GL092959, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2021GL092959, 2021. <lb/>Peng, X. and Yang, G.: The hillslope thermokarst inventory for <lb/>the permafrost region of the Qilian Mountains (2000-2020), <lb/>National Tibetan Plateau/Third Pole Environment Data Center <lb/>[data set], https://doi.org/10.11888/Cryos.tpdc.300805 (last ac-<lb/>cess: 25 April 2024), 2023. <lb/>Ran, Y., Li, X., Cheng, G., Nan, Z., Che, J., Sheng, Y., Wu, Q., Jin, <lb/>H., Luo, D., Tang, Z., and Wu, X.: Mapping the permafrost stabil-<lb/>ity on the Tibetan Plateau for 2005-2015, Sci. China Earth Sci., <lb/>64, 62-79, https://doi.org/10.1007/s11430-020-9685-3, 2021. <lb/>Resource and Environment Science Data Center (RESDC): <lb/>Spatial distribution data of vegetation types in China, <lb/>RESDC, https://www.resdc.cn/data.aspx?DATAID=122 (last ac-<lb/>cess: 25 April 2024), 2001. <lb/>Segal, R. A., Lantz, T. C., and Kokelj, S. V.: Accelera-<lb/>tion of thaw slump activity in glaciated landscapes of the <lb/>Western Canadian Arctic, Environ. Res. Lett., 11, 034025, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/11/3/034025, 2016. <lb/>Sharkhuu, A., Sharkhuu, N., Etzelmüller, B., Heggem, E. S. <lb/>F., Nelson, F. E., Shiklomanov, N. I., Goulden, C. E., and <lb/>Brown, J.: Permafrost monitoring in the Hovsgol moun-<lb/>tain region, Mongolia, J. Geophys. Res., 112, F02S06, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2006JF000543, 2007. <lb/>Stephani, E., Darrow, M. M., Kanevskiy, M., Wuttig, F., Daa-<lb/>nen, R. P., Schwarber, J. A., Doré, G., Shur, Y., Jorgen-<lb/>son, M. T., Croft, P., and Drage, J. S.: Hillslope erosional <lb/>features and permafrost dynamics along infrastructure in the <lb/>Arctic Foothills, Alaska, Permafrost Periglac., 34, 208-228, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/ppp.2188, 2023. <lb/>Stieglitz, M., Déry, S. J., Romanovsky, V. E., and Os-<lb/>terkamp, T. E.: The role of snow cover in the warm-<lb/>ing of arctic permafrost, Geophys. Res. Lett., 30, 1721, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2003GL017337, 2003. <lb/>The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC): The <lb/>Ocean and Cryosphere in a Changing Climate, https://www.ipcc. <lb/>ch/srocc/ (last access: 25 April 2024), 2019. <lb/>Third Pole Environment Data Center (TPDC): Map of per-<lb/>mafrost distribution in the Qilian Mountains, National Ti-<lb/>betan Plateau/Third Pole Environment Data Center [data set], <lb/>https://doi.org/10.11888/Geocry.tpdc.270456, 2020. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2033-2045, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2033-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">X. Peng et al.: Hillslope thermokarst in the Qilian Mountains <lb/></note>

        <page>2045 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>United States Geological Survey (USGS): Earthquake hazards pro-<lb/>gram, USGS, https://earthquake.usgs.gov/earthquakes/search/, <lb/>last access: 25 April 2024. <lb/>Wang, R., Peng, Q., Zhang, W., Zhao, W., Liu, C., and Zhou, <lb/>L.: Ecohydrological Service Characteristics of Qilian Mountain <lb/>Ecosystem in the Next 30 Years Based on Scenario Simulation, <lb/>Sustainability, 14, 1819, https://doi.org/10.3390/su14031819, <lb/>2022. <lb/>Wang, S.: Thaw Slumping in Fenghuo Mountain Area Along <lb/>Qinghai-Xizang Highway, Journal of Glaciology and <lb/>Geocryology, 12, 63-70, https://doi.org/10.7522/j.issn.1000-<lb/>0240.1990.0007, 1990. <lb/>Ward Jones, M. K., Pollard, W. H., and Jones, B. M.: Rapid <lb/>initialization of retrogressive thaw slumps in the Canadian <lb/>high Arctic and their response to climate and terrain factors, <lb/>Environ. Res. Lett., 14, 055006, https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-<lb/>9326/ab12fd, 2019. <lb/>Xia, Z., Huang, L., Fan, C., Jia, S., Lin, Z., Liu, L., Luo, J., Niu, <lb/>F., and Zhang, T.: Retrogressive thaw slumps along the Qinghai-<lb/>Tibet Engineering Corridor: a comprehensive inventory and their <lb/>distribution characteristics, Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 14, 3875-3887, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-14-3875-2022, 2022. <lb/>Xiong, J., Li, Y., Zhong, Y., Lu, H., Lei, J., Xin, W., Wang, L., <lb/>Hu, and Zhang, P.: Latest Pleistocene to Holocene Thrust-<lb/>ing Recorded by a Flight of Strath Terraces in the Eastern Qil-<lb/>ian Shan, NE Tibetan Plateau, TECTONICS, 36, 2973-2986, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/2017TC004648, 2017. <lb/>Yang, D., Qiu, H., Ye, B., Liu, Y., Zhang, J., and Zhu, Y.: <lb/>Distribution and Recurrence of Warming-Induced Ret-<lb/>rogressive Thaw Slumps on the Central Qinghai-Tibet <lb/>Plateau, J. Geophys. Res.-Earth, 128, e2022JF007047, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2022JF007047, 2023. <lb/>Yin, G., Niu, F., Lin, Z., Luo, J., and Liu, M.: Effects of local factors <lb/>and climate on permafrost conditions and distribution in Beiluhe <lb/>basin, Qinghai-Tibet Plateau, China, Sci. Total Environ., 581-<lb/>582, 472-485, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2016.12.155, <lb/>2017. <lb/>Yin, G., Luo, J., Niu, F., Lin, Z., and Liu, M.: Machine learning-<lb/>based thermokarst landslide susceptibility modeling across the <lb/>permafrost region on the Qinghai-Tibet Plateau, Landslides, 18, <lb/>2639-2649, https://doi.org/10.1007/s10346-021-01669-7, 2021. <lb/>Zhang, T.: Influence of the seasonal snow cover on the ground <lb/>thermal regime: An overview, Rev. Geophys., 43, RG4002, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2004RG000157, 2005. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-16-2033-2024 <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci. Data, 16, 2033-2045, 2024 </note>


	</text>

</TEI>