<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Estimating velocity distribution and flood discharge  at river bridges using entropy theory – insights  from computational fluid dynamics flow fields</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Farhad</forename>
          <surname>Bahmanpouri</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Tommaso</forename>
          <surname>Lazzarin</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Silvia</forename>
          <surname>Barbetta</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Tommaso</forename>
          <surname>Moramarco</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Daniele P.</forename>
          <surname>Viero</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-06T08:29:28.320Z">11/6/2025 8:29:28 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Copernicus GmbH</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.5194/hess-28-3717-2024</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Farhad Bahmanpouri, Tommaso Lazzarin, Silvia Barbetta, Tommaso Moramarco, Daniele P. Viero. (2024). Estimating velocity distribution and flood discharge  at river bridges using entropy theory – insights  from computational fluid dynamics flow fields. Hydrology and Earth System Sciences, 28(16), 3717-3737. DOI: 10.5194/hess-28-3717-2024</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-06T08:28:46.335196Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-06T08:28:46.335196Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/>© Author(s) 2024. This work is distributed under <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License. <lb/>Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/>using potential vorticity <lb/>Yonatan Givon 1 , Or Hess 1 , Emmanouil Flaounas 2 , Jennifer Louise Catto 3 , Michael Sprenger 4 , and <lb/>Shira Raveh-Rubin 1 <lb/>1 Department of Earth and Planetary Sciences, Weizmann Institute of Science, Rehovot, Israel <lb/>2 Institute of Oceanography, Hellenic Centre for Marine Research, Athens, Greece <lb/>3 Department of Mathematics and Statistics, University of Exeter, Exeter, UK <lb/>4 Institute for Atmospheric and Climate Science, ETH Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland <lb/>Correspondence: Yonatan Givon (yonatan.givon@weizmann.ac.il) <lb/>Received: 8 June 2023 -Discussion started: 19 June 2023 <lb/>Revised: 31 October 2023 -Accepted: 5 December 2023 -Published: 2 February 2024 <lb/>Abstract. Mediterranean cyclones (MCs) govern extreme <lb/>weather events across the Euro-African Basin, affecting the <lb/>lives of hundreds of millions. Despite many studies ad-<lb/>dressing MCs in the last few decades, their correct simu-<lb/>lation and prediction remain a significant challenge to the <lb/>present day, which may be attributed to the large variabil-<lb/>ity among MCs. Past classifications of MCs are primarily <lb/>based on geographical and/or seasonal separations; however, <lb/>here we focus on cyclone genesis and deepening mecha-<lb/>nisms. A variety of processes combine to govern MC gene-<lb/>sis and evolution, including adiabatic and diabatic processes, <lb/>topographic influences, land-sea contrasts, and local tem-<lb/>perature anomalies. As each process bears a distinct signa-<lb/>ture on the potential vorticity (PV) field, a PV approach is <lb/>used to distinguish among different &quot;types&quot; of MCs. Here, a <lb/>combined cyclone-tracking algorithm is used to detect 3190 <lb/>Mediterranean cyclone tracks in ECMWF ERA5 from 1979-<lb/>2020. Cyclone-centered, upper-level isentropic PV structures <lb/>in the peak time of each cyclone track are classified us-<lb/>ing a self-organizing map (SOM). The SOM analysis re-<lb/>veals nine classes of Mediterranean cyclones, with distinct <lb/>Rossby-wave-breaking patterns, discernible in correspond-<lb/>ing PV structures. Although classified by upper-level PV <lb/>structures, each class shows different contributions of lower-<lb/>tropospheric PV and flow structures down to the surface. <lb/>Unique cyclone life cycle characteristics, associated hazards <lb/>(precipitation, winds, and temperature anomalies), and long-<lb/>term trends, as well as synoptic, thermal, dynamical, sea-<lb/>sonal, and geographical features of each cyclone class, in-<lb/>dicate dominant processes in their evolution. Among others, <lb/>the classification reveals the importance of topographically <lb/>induced Rossby wave breaking to the generation of the most <lb/>extreme Mediterranean cyclones. These results enhance our <lb/>understanding of MC predictability by linking the large-scale <lb/>Rossby wave formations and life cycles to coherent classes <lb/>of under-predicted cyclone aspects. <lb/></front>

        <body>1 Introduction <lb/>The Mediterranean has long been described as a global cy-<lb/>clogenesis hotspot and one of the most sensitive regions in <lb/>terms of global warming (Giorgi and Lionello, 2008; Tuel <lb/>and Eltahir, 2020). This relationship appears intertwined <lb/>since Mediterranean cyclones (MCs) form the bulk of ex-<lb/>treme weather events across the region, which are a manifes-<lb/>tation of the warming climate (Zittis et al., 2022; Hochman <lb/>et al., 2022a). MCs are the primary source of extreme precip-<lb/>itation, winds, temperatures, and dust events. As such, MCs <lb/>pose significant threats to society and challenges to weather <lb/>and climate predictions (Flaounas et al., 2022). The impact <lb/>of under-predicted MCs on the heavily populated Mediter-<lb/>ranean coast, and further inland, is tremendous. Flood and <lb/>wind damage may result in the loss of homes and even <lb/>lives, while better weather predictions may allow for better <lb/>warnings and preparations to reduce costs significantly. On <lb/>climate scales, low confidence in the response of MCs to <lb/>a changing climate may lead to an underestimation of the <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Published by Copernicus Publications on behalf of the European Geosciences Union. <lb/></note>

        <page>134 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <body>severity of the impact of global warming on the Mediter-<lb/>ranean and to inadequate infrastructure planning. The recent <lb/>increase in extreme weather events in the Mediterranean, <lb/>such as droughts, windstorms, and hot spells, is linked to <lb/>changes in MCs&apos; behavior (Lionello et al., 2008; Dubrovský <lb/>et al., 2014; Trigo et al., 2000). MCs are expected to decrease <lb/>in frequency across the northern Mediterranean, along with <lb/>an expected poleward shift of the Atlantic storm track, but <lb/>their intensity may increase in some cases as the Mediter-<lb/>ranean becomes warmer and tropical-like cyclones emerge <lb/>(Gaertner et al., 2007; Cavicchia et al., 2014a, b). To improve <lb/>the understanding of present and future extreme weather <lb/>events in the Mediterranean, it is crucial to better under-<lb/>stand their mediators -MCs. Changes in MCs&apos; intensity, fre-<lb/>quency, duration, propagation, or extent all have implications <lb/>for future climate response (Nissen et al., 2014; Reale et al., <lb/>2022). <lb/>Mediterranean cyclogenesis has been attributed to down-<lb/>stream development, as Atlantic cyclones contribute to the <lb/>amplification of ridges over the eastern Atlantic, which <lb/>in turn induces troughs over Europe and cyclogenesis in <lb/>the Mediterranean. Indeed, Atlantic cyclones were detected <lb/>as precursors of intense MCs (Raveh-Rubin and Flaounas, <lb/>2017). In this context, MCs have often been referred to as <lb/>daughter cyclones (Romem et al., 2007; Ziv et al., 2015). <lb/>Mediterranean daughter cyclones can appear in various re-<lb/>gions relative to their parent cyclone, commonly along the <lb/>parental frontal system but also in the warm sector, or can be <lb/>linked to a separate synoptic system (Saaroni et al., 2017). <lb/>Nevertheless, MCs differ strongly by season, location, dura-<lb/>tion, extent, and impact. <lb/>One feature known to modify Mediterranean cyclogenesis <lb/>is topography. Climatological studies of MCs (Alpert et al., <lb/>1990; Campins et al., 2011; Lionello et al., 2006) reveal the <lb/>uneven distribution of MCs across the basin, with primary <lb/>cyclogenesis hotspots strongly linked to topography. For this <lb/>reason, most classifications of MCs focus on geographical <lb/>and seasonal features (Campins et al., 2000; Maheras et al., <lb/>2001; Trigo et al., 2002; Alpert et al., 2004; Hofstätter et al., <lb/>2016; Lionello et al., 2016; Flaounas et al., 2022), coining the <lb/>Genoa cyclones, north African (&quot;Sharav&quot;) lows, and Cyprus <lb/>lows as the dominant modes of MCs. Genoa cyclones form <lb/>in the lee of the Alps and dominate throughout the winter <lb/>season. These lee cyclones tend to travel east towards the <lb/>Balkans, Greece, or Turkey. The Sharav lows are known to <lb/>appear mostly during summer and spring and tend to initiate <lb/>in the lee of the Atlas Mountains (Trigo et al., 1999). Cyprus <lb/>lows also frequently occur in the winter and autumn seasons, <lb/>providing the majority of precipitation events in the Middle <lb/>East (Saaroni et al., 2010). Other recognized climatological <lb/>hotspots of cyclogenesis include the Adriatic, Aegean, and <lb/>Black seas, as well as the Iberian Peninsula. However, even <lb/>for a given region of cyclogenesis, large case-to-case vari-<lb/>ability emerges due to the wide variety of processes affecting <lb/>MCs (Trigo et al., 2002). With baroclinic instability driving <lb/>cyclogenesis, the Norwegian model (Henry, 1922) and the re-<lb/>fined Shapiro-Keyser model (Shapiro and Keyser, 1990) of-<lb/>ten describe the life cycle of extratropical cyclones over the <lb/>open oceans conceptually. Observed discrepancies with the-<lb/>ory have given rise to various approaches to extratropical cy-<lb/>clone classification, as reviewed by Catto (2016). However, <lb/>these classifications are less relevant for the Mediterranean <lb/>region, where additional mechanisms strongly modulate cy-<lb/>clogenesis and MC evolution. <lb/>The driving mechanisms of Alpine cyclogenesis were re-<lb/>cently reviewed by Buzzi et al. (2020). The impact of topog-<lb/>raphy is considered to be the most crucial in the first stage <lb/>(stage A) of lee cyclogenesis when the surface cold front is <lb/>physically blocked by topography. The rapid deepening dur-<lb/>ing stage A is attributed to geostrophic adjustment processes <lb/>necessary to balance the lag of the cold front impinging on <lb/>the Alps. This phase lasts until sufficient cold-air mass pen-<lb/>etrates the Mediterranean for the surface cold pool of the <lb/>Rossby wave to propagate across the barrier. Stage B is then <lb/>characterized by the development of a frontal structure fur-<lb/>ther away from the mountain and a continuous, yet slower, <lb/>deepening of the cyclone by the release of potential baro-<lb/>clinic instability from the synoptic-scale reservoir (Mattocks <lb/>and Bleck, 1986). As illustrated in Givon et al. (2021), the <lb/>transition between stages A and B is often manifested in up-<lb/>per levels as filaments of potential vorticity (PV) streamers <lb/>and cutoffs attributed to cyclonic and anticyclonic Rossby <lb/>wave breaking (hereafter CWB and AWB; Thorncroft et al., <lb/>1993). Tsidulko and Alpert (2001) showed that stage A is <lb/>dominated by the cyclogenetic contribution of the synergy <lb/>between adiabatic PV advection and topography, while stage <lb/>B is purely dominated by PV advection. This constructive <lb/>interaction between PV advection and topography acts to en-<lb/>hance the vertical motions and deepen the surface cyclone. <lb/>Thermal lows demonstrate another mechanism for cyclo-<lb/>genesis, mostly attributed to regional surface temperature <lb/>anomalies leading to local instability and convection (Rácz <lb/>and Smith, 1999; Johnson, 2003). In the Mediterranean <lb/>Basin, these may be further separated into continental heat <lb/>lows, mostly found along northern Africa as Sharav lows, <lb/>and heat lows scattered across the Mediterranean. The first is <lb/>dry and usually does not precipitate and is hence shallower <lb/>and shorter-lived (Ammar et al., 2014). The latter can be sus-<lb/>tained by a wind-induced surface heat exchange mechanism <lb/>(WISHE) and grows as a &quot;diabatic Rossby wave&quot;, which <lb/>owes its deepening to evaporation-precipitation feedback, <lb/>leading to the release of latent heat by condensation (Lin, <lb/>1982; Boettcher and Wernli, 2011, 2013). Kouroutzoglou et <lb/>al. (2018) showed the importance of WISHE for the gen-<lb/>eration of explosive cyclones (Kouroutzoglou et al., 2011), <lb/>another often-used sub-class of MCs. Recently, a growing <lb/>scientific interest has been noted in the appearance of &quot;med-<lb/>icanes&quot;: tropical-like MCs that wreak havoc across Europe <lb/>(Cavicchia et al., 2014a, b; Flaounas et al., 2022). While a <lb/>conclusive definition of medicanes is still pending, it is de-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <page>135 <lb/></page>

        <body>scribed as a warm-core, axisymmetric MC with low verti-<lb/>cal shear of horizontal wind speed. Medicanes are charac-<lb/>terized by intense deepening, precipitation, and wind speeds. <lb/>Numerical simulations of two medicane cases (Miglietta and <lb/>Rotunno, 2019) suggest that WISHE may function as an im-<lb/>portant driving mechanism, though this relationship may be <lb/>case dependent. <lb/>While the most common MC classification relies on <lb/>geographical-seasonal features, no current classification of <lb/>MCs is based on their dominating driving mechanisms <lb/>(Flaounas et al., 2022). Campins et al. (2000) performed an <lb/>objective analysis of sea-level pressure (SLP) patterns using <lb/>a cyclone-centered approach; however, the analysis was lim-<lb/>ited to western MCs, and the results mostly converge back to <lb/>geographical features. Flaounas et al. (2021) analyzed MCs <lb/>from a PV perspective and showed the alternating dominance <lb/>of adiabatic and diabatic processes. Flocas (2000) performed <lb/>a PV analysis of MCs and asserted the dominance of upper-<lb/>level PV, as opposed to low-or mid-level PV, in the evolution <lb/>of MCs. Portmann (2020) showed, using forecast ensembles, <lb/>how cyclone prediction is closely related to the prediction of <lb/>the non-linear upper-tropospheric PV cutoff. The high sen-<lb/>sitivity of Rossby wave evolution to simulated topography <lb/>makes MCs challenging to predict or numerically reproduce <lb/>(Smith, 1984; Mattocks and Bleck, 1986; Tafferner, 1990; <lb/>Tsidulko and Alpert, 2001; Buzzi et al., 2020). The deepen-<lb/>ing rate and motion of the cyclone are major sources of fore-<lb/>cast busts, and a better understanding of the PV-topography <lb/>relationship is called for (Rodwell, 2013; Buzzi et al., 2020; <lb/>Portmann et al., 2021). <lb/>Upper-level PV anomalies are a crucial condition for <lb/>Mediterranean cyclogenesis and play a major role in MC <lb/>evolution. Furthermore, as an adiabatically conserved quan-<lb/>tity, upper-level PV distributions provide a dynamic diagnos-<lb/>tic of the atmosphere, indicative of different dynamical and <lb/>thermodynamical processes (Hoskins et al., 2015). As such, <lb/>it is natural to think of upper-level PV in terms of a dynami-<lb/>cal classification framework. <lb/>Each cyclone-deepening mechanism is expected to show a <lb/>unique signature in the PV field, paving the way for a system-<lb/>atic, dynamics-based classification of MCs from a PV per-<lb/>spective. More specifically, we aim to address the following <lb/>question(s): <lb/>1. Are there coherent recurring classes of MCs, from a <lb/>cyclone-centered, upper-level PV perspective? <lb/>2. Are the different MC classes indicative of domi-<lb/>nant deepening mechanisms, involving coherent lower-<lb/>tropospheric PV signatures and/or near-surface anoma-<lb/>lies? <lb/>3. How do the classes differ in terms of the variability of <lb/>their life cycles and associated hazards? <lb/>To address the above, we analyze 3190 MC tracks using <lb/>ECMWF ERA5 from 1979 to 2020. Upper-level PV near the <lb/>cyclone is used to classify MCs. We then explore the geo-<lb/>graphical, seasonal, thermal, and dynamic features of each <lb/>class to conclude the dominant process driving the cyclones. <lb/>This article is structured as follows: the data and meth-<lb/>ods are outlined in Sect. 2, with a brief review of the cy-<lb/>clone dataset, clustering approach, and cyclone diagnostics. <lb/>Results are discussed in Sect. 3, including the total mean pat-<lb/>terns of MCs (Sect. 3.1) followed by the classification results <lb/>(PV patterns, Sect. 3.2), cyclone-track features (Sect. 3.3), <lb/>surface impact (Sect. 3.4), and cluster trends and predictabil-<lb/>ity (Sect. 3.5). An overview of the results is presented in <lb/>Sect. 4, followed by concluding remarks in Sect. 5. More <lb/>details on the SOM analysis, cyclone dynamic features (PV <lb/>streamers, cutoffs, fronts, and warm conveyor belts), 3D PV <lb/>analysis, and medicane distributions are included in Ap-<lb/>pendix A-D. <lb/>2 Data and methods <lb/>To explore the large-scale PV patterns associated with the <lb/>evolution of the different MC types, a self-organizing map <lb/>(SOM) analysis is applied to an MC track dataset, classify-<lb/>ing upper-level PV structures at the peak time of each cy-<lb/>clone track. Various features are then explored between the <lb/>different classes to highlight dominant processes. <lb/>2.1 Combined cyclone-tracking algorithm <lb/>In this study, we use composite Mediterranean cyclone tracks <lb/>from the 1979-2020 period, produced from hourly atmo-<lb/>spheric fields of ERA5 reanalysis (Hersbach et al., 2020). <lb/>Composite tracks have been produced using a novel approach <lb/>(Flaounas et al., 2023) that combines the ensemble of outputs <lb/>from 10 different cyclone-tracking methods to retain only the <lb/>tracks that concentrate higher agreement among the methods <lb/>and discard the rest. Composite tracks enable larger confi-<lb/>dence levels in the detected cyclones and more distinct dy-<lb/>namical life stages (from genesis to decay) compared to sin-<lb/>gle methods which may present different biases. In this study, <lb/>we choose composite tracks of confidence level 5, denoting <lb/>the agreement of at least five cyclone detection methods upon <lb/>the presence of a cyclone for at least one time step in its life-<lb/>time. At this confidence level, the seasonal cycle attains a <lb/>distinct cycle with a minimum in summer and a maximum <lb/>in spring, compared to confidence levels of four or less, sug-<lb/>gesting the removal of shallow heat lows that are of lesser in-<lb/>terest from a dynamic perspective (Scherrmann et al., 2023). <lb/>The cyclone&apos;s center position and sea-level pressure (SLP) <lb/>minimum are tracked throughout its lifetime. Only cyclones <lb/>that enter the Mediterranean (i.e., any part of their track is <lb/>present east of 5 • W) are accounted for, resulting in 3190 cy-<lb/>clones. The peak time of the cyclone is defined based on the <lb/>minimum SLP, while cyclogenesis (lysis) is defined as the <lb/>first (last) time step in each cyclone track. For ∼ 2% of the <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/>Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>136 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <body>cyclones, the minimum SLP of the track is located west of <lb/>5 • W. To avoid classifying cyclones away from the Mediter-<lb/>ranean Basin, we iteratively seek a new minimum starting <lb/>at the following time step until a minimum is found east of <lb/>5 • W. However, a few (∼ 0.1 %) cyclones display anomalous <lb/>westbound trajectories, originating east of 5 • W and peaking <lb/>over the Atlantic/western Africa. In these cases, the mini-<lb/>mum SLP point is considered to be the last point in the track <lb/>that lies east of 5 W. Consistently, all other atmospheric data <lb/>are based on ERA5, interpolated to 0.5 • horizontal resolution <lb/>and 3-hourly time steps. <lb/>2.2 Self-organizing map (SOM) classification <lb/>The cyclone tracks are classified at the time of their peak <lb/>intensity (minimum SLP), according to the regional upper-<lb/>tropospheric isentropic PV. For each track, the cyclone po-<lb/>sition is taken at the peak time, and PV on isentropic layers <lb/>320-340 K (vertically averaged with 5 K intervals) is con-<lb/>sidered in a cyclone-centered domain of 20 • east and west, <lb/>20 • south, and 40 • north of the cyclone center. Note that <lb/>the domain is extended poleward to account for the main <lb/>PV reservoir. This isentropic layer was chosen so that it in-<lb/>tersects the dynamical tropopause across all seasons. The <lb/>3190 cyclone-centered PV fields are then classified using a <lb/>self-organizing map (SOM) algorithm. The choice to clas-<lb/>sify PV values rather than PV anomalies was made to re-<lb/>tain the seasonal separation between the clusters, as well as <lb/>to obtain the actual flow structure as it is better illustrated <lb/>directly by PV. The use of SOM classifications is becom-<lb/>ing popular in the meteorological field (Liu and Weisberg, <lb/>2011; Skific and Francis, 2012; Berkovic et al., 2021). The <lb/>SOM algorithm relies on a neural network that minimizes <lb/>Euclidean distances within each cluster, while maximizing <lb/>the dissimilarity between the clusters, enabling the depic-<lb/>tion of distinct patterns. The SOM algorithm maps the vari-<lb/>ance within the dataset onto an array of composite maps, <lb/>each corresponding to a reoccurring phase of the parame-<lb/>ter under consideration. Similar clusters are placed closer <lb/>together on the resulting map, while substantially different <lb/>clusters are placed further from their neighbors. The SOM <lb/>is a powerful climatological tool that neatly separates the <lb/>continuum of various states occurring in the system. Here <lb/>we use a single-layer SOM algorithm, provided by Math-<lb/>Works (https://www.mathworks.com/help/deeplearning/gs/ <lb/>cluster-data-with-a-self-organizingmap.html, last access: 1 <lb/>February 2023). The SOM errors, defined as mean squared <lb/>errors within each cluster and averaged over the entire net-<lb/>work, suggest nine as the optimal choice for the number of <lb/>clusters, in a 3-by-3 hexagonal configuration (Fig. A1 in Ap-<lb/>pendix A). Adding further clusters reduced the SOM error at <lb/>an ever-decreasing rate. This setup results in roughly 300 cy-<lb/>clones per cluster. More details regarding the SOM analysis <lb/>are presented in Appendix A. <lb/>2.3 Cyclone-track features <lb/>Cyclone features are extracted from the cyclone tracks and <lb/>compared across the different clusters. These features in-<lb/>clude seasonal and geographical cyclone occurrence distri-<lb/>butions, the cyclone propagation velocity, and the cyclone <lb/>deepening rate. The cyclone propagation velocity is evalu-<lb/>ated following the track of the cyclone center and averaged <lb/>along the whole track, defined as <lb/>u cyclone = <lb/>2π r <lb/>360 • cos (ϕ) <lb/>dλ cyclone <lb/>dt <lb/>, <lb/>v cyclone = <lb/>2π r <lb/>360 • <lb/>dϕ cyclone <lb/>dt <lb/>, <lb/>(1) <lb/>where r is Earth&apos;s radius and λ cyclone , ϕ cyclone the longitude <lb/>and latitude of the cyclone center at every time step. The cy-<lb/>clone maximum deepening rate is quantified with Bergeron <lb/>units (Tsukijihara et al., 2019; Sanders and Gyakum, 1980), <lb/>given at time t as <lb/>Bergeron t = <lb/>sin (60) <lb/>sin (φ t ) <lb/>(SLP t-12 h -SLP t+12 h ) <lb/>24 h <lb/>, <lb/>(2) <lb/>where φ t is the latitude of the cyclone center at time t. Thus, <lb/>a 24 h window centered around time t is shifted along each <lb/>cyclone track, and the maximum Bergeron number captured <lb/>for each cyclone track is considered. Values greater than 1 <lb/>Bergeron imply an explosive cyclone, while negative values <lb/>imply the minimum depth is reached in less than 12 h. <lb/>2.4 Surface impact <lb/>The surface impact of each cluster is evaluated based on <lb/>deviations from the total cyclone-centered composite av-<lb/>erage of large-scale and convective precipitation rates and <lb/>10 m winds, as well as the deviations of 2 m tempera-<lb/>ture and upper-level PV from the local monthly climatol-<lb/>ogy (i.e., grid-point based and not cyclone-relative). Grid-<lb/>ded Student&apos;s t test is conducted on a 99 % confidence level <lb/>(α = 0.01), tightened by multiple-testing correction criteria <lb/>(Wilks, 2016). As suggested by Wilks (2016), false positives <lb/>may arise from multiple grid-point statistical testing and can <lb/>be reduced by imposing an appropriate threshold on the indi-<lb/>vidual p values, which changes by the number of grid points <lb/>included in the analysis. Specifically, the threshold is set to <lb/>α walker = 1 -(1 -α) 1/N , <lb/>(3) <lb/>where α = 0.01 is the desired confidence level (correspond-<lb/>ing to 99 % significance), and N = 9801 is the number of <lb/>grid points included in the test. The gridded signal is deemed <lb/>significant only if its p value is below α walker (after Walker, <lb/>1914). <lb/>Precipitation rates are evaluated based on 1-hourly accu-<lb/>mulated precipitation until the date under evaluation (ERA5). <lb/>Both large-scale precipitation and convective precipitation <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <page>137 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 1. Geographical climatological density of all 3190 cyclones at the time of cyclogenesis (blue shading), peak intensity (red shading), <lb/>and cyclolysis (yellow shading) for 1979-2020. Each cyclone location is gridded with an impact radius of 100 km. The color scale is <lb/>logarithmic; i.e., dark patches stand for 10-fold the density of the lighter patches, and the values are the normalized frequencies (percentage <lb/>of all cyclones in 100 km cells). The underlying map is provided by MathWorks (https://www.mathworks.com/help/map/ref/geoshow.html, <lb/>last access: 10 December 2023). <lb/>are provided by the ERA5 reanalysis product, using output <lb/>from parametrization schemes (Hersbach et al., 2020). While <lb/>these results are parametrized and are expected to show sen-<lb/>sitivity to model resolution (especially convective precipita-<lb/>tion), it does allow for the drawing of conclusions regarding <lb/>the sign and relative response of precipitation under the dif-<lb/>ferent PV classes. <lb/>2.5 Dynamical features <lb/>To better understand the patterns obtained by the composite <lb/>means, we consider additional dynamical features that are <lb/>objectively identified individually for each cyclone. <lb/>2.5.1 PV streamers and cutoffs <lb/>The identifications of PV streamers and cutoffs follow the <lb/>methodology of Sprenger et al. (2017), which was initially <lb/>developed and applied for ERA-15 and ERA-Interim (see <lb/>Wernli and Sprenger, 2007) and then adapted to ERA5. Es-<lb/>sentially, PV is interpolated onto a stack of isentropic lev-<lb/>els (320-340 K, in steps of 5 K). On each of these isentropic <lb/>PV maps, the largest connected region with PV &gt; 2 PVU is <lb/>taken as the stratospheric high-PV reservoir, and PV cutoffs <lb/>are identified as connected regions outside the stratosphere <lb/>with PV &gt; 2 PVU, i.e., as regions that are surrounded by tro-<lb/>pospheric PV air (PV &lt; 2 PVU). The ERA5 grid points on <lb/>the isentropic levels inside such a PV cutoff feature are la-<lb/>beled as 1 and grid points outside as 0. PV streamers are also <lb/>identified on single isentropic levels. To this aim, on each <lb/>isentropic level, the 2 PVU contour delimiting the strato-<lb/>spheric PV reservoir is extracted, and then PV streamers are <lb/>identified based on this contour as narrow, elongated distur-<lb/>bances. More specifically, for each point along the contour, it <lb/>is checked whether a corresponding further point along the <lb/>contour exists such that (i) the great-circle (baseline) dis-<lb/>tance between these two anchor points is less than 2000 km <lb/>and (ii) the along-contour distance between the two points <lb/>exceeds the baseline distance by at least a factor of 2. A <lb/>more detailed description of the algorithm, including some <lb/>examples, can be found in the Supplement of Sprenger et <lb/>al. (2017). <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/>Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>138 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 2. Composite mean of (a) upper-level (320-340 K averaged) PV (PVU, shading) and SLP (unlabeled contours, at 2 hPa intervals, <lb/>dashed for values above 1015 hPa), (b) 2 m temperature anomaly from the monthly local climatology (K), (c) 10 m wind speed (m s -1 ), (d) to-<lb/>tal (mm h -1 , shading) and convective (0.2 mm h -1 , black contour) precipitation rates, (e) annual MC occurrences with a 5-year smoothing <lb/>(thick line) and linear best fit to the data, and (f) the mean velocity of the cyclone center (m s -1 ). Note the smaller domain in (d). These <lb/>climatological patterns are used as a reference to establish the statistical significance of the cluster composites and evaluate the variance <lb/>within the cyclone population. <lb/>2.5.2 Warm conveyor belts (WCBs) <lb/>WCBs are identified according to the methodology intro-<lb/>duced by Madonna et al. (2014) and applied to 1-hourly <lb/>ERA5 data. Forward trajectories are started globally on an <lb/>equidistant (80 km) grid at 14 equally spaced layers between <lb/>1050 and 790 hPa. The 48 h trajectories must fulfill two crite-<lb/>ria to be classified as WCB trajectories: (i) they must ascend <lb/>by at least 600 hPa within a 48 h time window, and (ii) the <lb/>ascent must occur in the vicinity of an (extratropical) cy-<lb/>clone. A detailed description of the algorithm and some re-<lb/>finements compared to Madonna et al. (2014) are presented <lb/>in Heitmann et al. (2023). The regions where the WCB tra-<lb/>jectories ascend, defined as the vertical range 800-400 hPa, <lb/>are labeled as 1 to obtain an Eulerian WCB weather feature. <lb/>2.5.3 Fronts <lb/>Fronts have been identified using a thermal front parameter <lb/>method, based on Hewson (1998), and are detailed in San-<lb/>som and Catto (2022). This method applies to the smooth <lb/>ERA5 fields of 850 hPa wet-bulb potential temperature (θ w ); <lb/>then potential fronts are identified where the contours of <lb/>∇ 2 <lb/>|∇θ w | = 0 (see Fig. 3 in Hewson, 1998). A mask is ap-<lb/>plied to keep only the contours that meet some threshold <lb/>of ∇ |∇θ w | • ∇θ w <lb/>∇|θ w | , known as the thermal front parameter, <lb/>and where the gradient of θ w in the adjacent baroclinic <lb/>zone meets another threshold. Fronts are designated as cold, <lb/>warm, or quasi-stationary depending on the frontal speed, <lb/>and the linear contour features are placed on the ERA5 reso-<lb/>lution. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <page>139 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 3. Cyclone-centered cluster composites of upper-level (320-340 K averaged) PV (PVU, shading) and SLP (black contours at 2 hPa <lb/>intervals, dashed above 1015 hPa). Stippling indicates a 99 % significance level of the PV field concerning the total cyclone average (Fig. 2a). <lb/>The mean frequency of each cluster out of all cyclones considered is given in the title. <lb/>3 Results <lb/>3.1 Mean cyclone climatology <lb/>We first examine the whole cyclone dataset, depicting the <lb/>mean climatological patterns that will then be decomposed <lb/>into the clusters in Sect. 3.2. Figure 1 depicts the density of <lb/>all Mediterranean cyclones at three stages of their evolution: <lb/>cyclogenesis, peak intensity, and lysis. Cyclogenesis regions <lb/>are closely linked to topography, while cyclones tend to peak <lb/>over open waters and decay along the eastern coasts and over <lb/>land (Alpert et al., 1990; Trigo et al., 1999; Campins et al., <lb/>2011). <lb/>From a cyclone-centered perspective, Fig. 2 shows a com-<lb/>posite mean of atmospheric fields around all the analyzed <lb/>MCs, as well as the number of MCs per year and their aver-<lb/>age propagation velocity. The upper-tropospheric isentropic <lb/>PV confirms the typical synoptic setting of MCs in the form <lb/>of a westward-tilted upper-level trough compared to the cy-<lb/>clone center. The warm and cold sectors are evident from the <lb/>2 m temperature anomaly field. The asymmetric wind struc-<lb/>ture is portrayed by the 10 m wind speed composite, exhibit-<lb/>ing a maximum to the south of the cyclone center, as well <lb/>as another maximum further in the northwestern corner, sug-<lb/>gesting the imprint of potential parent Atlantic cyclones in <lb/>some of the cases (Fig. 2c). The composite precipitation dis-<lb/>plays maxima just to the north of the cyclone&apos;s center. An-<lb/>nual cyclone occurrences (Fig. 2e) show a weakly increas-<lb/>ing trend, though only statistically significant if evaluated for <lb/>the smoothed time series. On average, MCs propagate to-<lb/>wards the east with a weak poleward component (Fig. 2f), <lb/>at a 3.5 m s -1 mean speed. These results agree with multiple <lb/>past climatological studies addressing MCs (Flaounas et al., <lb/>2015; Raveh-Rubin and Wernli, 2015; Flaounas et al., 2021), <lb/>emphasizing the robustness of the cyclone detection method. <lb/>3.2 SOM classification <lb/>The SOM analysis produced nine remarkably distinct clus-<lb/>ters, shown in Fig. 3 with the composite mean PV and SLP <lb/>for each. The wide variety of PV formations driving MCs <lb/>spans from cluster 1 having the strongest PV signal to cluster <lb/>6 showing the cyclone center furthest from the stratospheric <lb/>PV reservoir. Various stages of Rossby wave evolution are <lb/>captured, including cyclonically breaking PV streamers (8), <lb/>anticyclonically (5) breaking PV streamers, and the combi-<lb/>nation of both (2), as well as cutoffs (3, 9), heat lows (6), and <lb/>daughter cyclones forming adjacently to synoptic cyclones <lb/>(7). The frequencies of objectively defined PV streamers and <lb/>cutoffs are composited in Fig. C1, confirming their high rel-<lb/>evance also when not directly evident from the composite <lb/>mean PV. For example, streamers and cutoffs are both most <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/>Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>140 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 4. Zonal vertical cross-section composites through the center of the cyclones by cluster. PV is shaded (PVU) with 0.7 PVU and <lb/>denoted with black contours. Note the different color scale compared to Fig. 3. <lb/>frequent for cyclones in clusters 6 and 9, evidently under <lb/>ridge conditions with a streamer and/or a cutoff closer to the <lb/>cyclone center. The relevance of PV streamers is confirmed <lb/>by their high occurrence under clusters 5 and 8 (both 94 %), <lb/>which also possess a streamer-like composite mean pattern. <lb/>By construction, the similarity among individual members is <lb/>larger within clusters than across clusters. Indeed, the cluster <lb/>means are very distinct from one another, with their position <lb/>in the SOM indicating a higher similarity with neighboring <lb/>clusters compared to distant ones (considering their hexag-<lb/>onal organization, Fig. A1). While clusters 4 and 5 are still <lb/>very different from one another, the differentiation between <lb/>clusters 1 and 4 is subtle but meaningful nonetheless (Figs. 3, <lb/>C3). The separation of clusters 1 and 4 indicates a different <lb/>orientation of the dynamical tropopause, hinting towards a <lb/>different stage of lee cyclogenesis. This point is discussed <lb/>further along with the cyclone features. Together, the SOM <lb/>successfully forms a catalog of distinct PV formations driv-<lb/>ing MCs. <lb/>Addressing the variance in SLP, some cyclones have a <lb/>smaller impact radius (clusters 5, 6, 8, 9) as expected from <lb/>their shortwave PV disturbance, while cyclones in clusters <lb/>1, 2, and 4 where a longwave perturbation is portrayed have <lb/>much greater extents. A surface anticyclone is seen under low <lb/>PV values (clusters 2, 3, 5, 6, and 8) in different orientations <lb/>relative to the MC. <lb/>The classification is based on upper-level PV to distinguish <lb/>between the adiabatic, large-scale drivers of cyclone gene-<lb/>sis and deepening. The diabatic contribution is often per-<lb/>ceived as an independent contributor to cyclone deepening <lb/>and can be diagnosed by a positive PV anomaly in the mid-<lb/>troposphere. Figure 4 shows the composite vertical cross-<lb/>section of PV in each cluster in the zonal direction, show-<lb/>ing not only that upper-tropospheric PV varies across clus-<lb/>ters but also that significant differences in the PV distribu-<lb/>tion down to the surface are also clear. Here, the low-/mid-<lb/>tropospheric PV is generally higher in clusters with more <lb/>pronounced upper-level PV anomalies, suggesting a relation-<lb/>ship between the two PV maxima. Thus, the classification by <lb/>upper-level PV also sheds light on non-conserved PV in the <lb/>low-and mid-troposphere, as some clusters (1, 2, 4, 8) show <lb/>a low-level PV signal, while others do not (3, 5, 6, 7, 9). In-<lb/>terestingly, clusters 3 and 7 show large PV values near the <lb/>surface but none in the mid-troposphere. This feature may be <lb/>the result of boundary-layer instability or friction over land <lb/>and/or high orography (Adamson et al., 2006); however, the <lb/>sources of these PV signals need to be further investigated. <lb/>A detailed 3D PV analysis is presented in Figs. B1 and B2. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <page>141 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 5. Horizontal composites of upper-level PV anomalies (0.5 PVU intervals, black contours, dashed for negative) and 10 m wind speed <lb/>anomalies (shading) with respect to the local monthly climatology. Overlaid is the corresponding composite of the 30 m s -1 isotach on the <lb/>300 hPa geopotential surface (cyan contour, roughly denoting the subpolar and subtropical jets). Stippling denotes regions where the PV <lb/>anomaly is statistically significant in the 99 % confidence level compared to the total average. <lb/>Figure 6. Monthly distribution of the cyclones in each cluster. The <lb/>month of each cyclone peak is given on the x axis, and the corre-<lb/>sponding relative frequency is given in shading. The probabilities <lb/>are normalized relative to the cluster size; i.e., each row sums up <lb/>to 1. <lb/>The anomalies of the composite PV patterns and 10 m <lb/>winds are now examined together with 300 hPa wind speed <lb/>(Fig. 5). The large magnitude of PV anomalies in clusters <lb/>8 and 2 (&gt; 2.5 PVU) may be attributed to initially anticy-<lb/>clonically breaking PV streamers, later forming cyclonically <lb/>curving tips. This formation is accompanied by a double-jet <lb/>structure on the 300 hPa level, prominently for cluster 2. This <lb/>setup allows the PV streamer to penetrate the furthest equa-<lb/>torward while sustaining large amplitudes above the cyclone, <lb/>generating the largest upper-level PV anomalies that in turn <lb/>induce the strongest low-level PV anomalies (Figs. 4 and B2) <lb/>and surface circulation (Figs. 5 and 12). Also noteworthy are <lb/>the negative PV anomalies indicative of AWB in clusters 5 <lb/>and 2 and for CWB in cluster 8. Clusters 3 and 9 show pos-<lb/>itive PV anomalies above the cyclone center with negative <lb/>anomalies to the north, indicative of cutoff and/or streamer <lb/>formations under ridge environments. More details on the PV <lb/>streamers and cutoffs and their variance across the clusters <lb/>are included in Appendix C (Fig. C1). <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/>Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>142 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <body>3.3 Cyclone characteristics <lb/>The seasonal distribution of cyclones varies sharply by clus-<lb/>ter (Fig. 6). Clusters 1, 2, and 4 prominently dominate <lb/>throughout the winter months, while clusters 6 and 9 mostly <lb/>occur in summer. The other clusters occur mostly in the tran-<lb/>sition seasons, some more in spring (3, 7), others peaking <lb/>in autumn (8), and cluster 5 appears rather equally during <lb/>both. Note that despite their high frequency, only three win-<lb/>ter clusters are obtained, compared to four clusters for the <lb/>transition seasons. This is due to the larger variety of PV fea-<lb/>tures in spring and autumn compared to winter when broad <lb/>troughs dominate the region. Of course, the seasonal sepa-<lb/>ration among clusters is a result of the choice of the clas-<lb/>sifying parameter, the absolute values of PV, which varies <lb/>by season due to the choice of the isentropic layer, and the <lb/>equatorward migration and strengthening of the jet in winter. <lb/>Alternatively, classifying by PV anomalies would cancel out <lb/>some of these differences (not shown). We choose to employ <lb/>the full PV values and through this also distinguish among <lb/>the seasons more clearly. <lb/>Examining the geographic distributions by cluster (Fig. 7) <lb/>reveals highly localized clusters (1, 3, 5, 6, 8) alongside <lb/>broadly distributed ones (2, 4, 7, 9). Cluster 6 cyclones reside <lb/>almost exclusively on the African continent, supporting their <lb/>identification as African heat lows (or Sharav lows), while <lb/>cluster 1 appears to mainly correspond to Genoa cyclones. <lb/>Clusters 2 and 4 also originate in the lee of the Alps; how-<lb/>ever, their peak locations vary greatly, favoring open mar-<lb/>itime environments. Clusters 3, 7, and 5 share strong sig-<lb/>nals near the Atlas Mountains, though the latter occasionally <lb/>forms in the Black Sea. Regarding the separation between <lb/>clusters 1 and 4, the results suggest that cluster 4 cyclones <lb/>tend to peak further away from topography (as in stage B <lb/>cyclogenesis) compared to cluster 1 (stage A cyclogenesis). <lb/>This interpretation is further examined by their frontal struc-<lb/>ture in Sect. 3.4. While these geographical-seasonal relation-<lb/>ships are well known for MCs (Flaounas et al., 2022), we also <lb/>detect cyclones appearing in less common locations and sea-<lb/>sons, hinting that from an upper-level perspective, dynami-<lb/>cally similar cyclones may appear in substantially different <lb/>spatiotemporal settings. For example, the rare occurrence of <lb/>a cluster 6 cyclone centered above Italy was co-located with <lb/>an extreme heat wave that struck Poland and the Balkans in <lb/>August 2015, leading to the warmest summer recorded in the <lb/>region since the 1980s (Krzyżewska et al., 2018). Likewise, <lb/>an unusual occurrence of a cluster 2 cyclone near Cyprus <lb/>resulted in the 2013 Storm Alexa, causing record-breaking <lb/>snowfall across the Middle East (Sawalha, 2014; Hochman <lb/>et al., 2022b). Thus, the value of the present analysis lies in <lb/>the fact that it is geographically unbound and focused purely <lb/>on PV dynamics. <lb/>An important aspect of MCs, and particularly challeng-<lb/>ing to predict, is the tendency of a given cyclone to deepen <lb/>rapidly and become explosive, i.e., cross the threshold of 1 <lb/>Bergeron at any point in its lifetime. The distribution of the <lb/>cyclone maximum 24 h deepening rate by cluster is shown <lb/>in Fig. 8. Clusters 1, 2, and 4 are the most explosive, with <lb/>a fraction of cluster 5 and cluster 8 cyclones also exhibiting <lb/>explosive systems under Rossby-wave-breaking scenarios. In <lb/>contrast, clusters 6, 3, and 9 tend to deepen more slowly, <lb/>primarily attributed to the dry environment where these cy-<lb/>clones develop, devoid of humidity fluxes to sustain signifi-<lb/>cant precipitation and latent heat release. Negative Bergeron <lb/>values indicate tracks that peaked at stages earlier than 12 h <lb/>following cyclogenesis and are most prominent in cluster 1, <lb/>again suggesting the rapid and early geostrophic adjustment <lb/>stage A as the cluster&apos;s dominant deepening mechanism. This <lb/>may also be an artifact of Atlantic cyclones entering the do-<lb/>main while becoming shallower, although only a few such <lb/>tracks were detected. Cluster 4 also shows a significant num-<lb/>ber of negative values, in agreement with the notion that most <lb/>stage B cyclones initiate with a stage A deepening phase yet <lb/>manage to propagate far enough from the topography and <lb/>deepen further by releasing baroclinic instability. Thus, while <lb/>the minimum SLP of cluster 4 cyclones appears to corre-<lb/>spond to stage B, the maximum deepening rate, as expected <lb/>from theory, often occurs during their stage A phase. The <lb/>same holds for cluster 2 cyclones, to a lesser extent. <lb/>Throughout their lifetime, the cyclones generally propa-<lb/>gate to the east with an average speed of 3.5 m s -1 (Fig. 2f). <lb/>Figure 9 shows the cluster mean anomalies in the cyclone <lb/>propagation velocity relative to the total average and the <lb/>radial distribution of the members composing these means <lb/>(Fig. 9b). When broken down into clusters, coherent posi-<lb/>tive and negative anomalies of the order of 1-2 m s -1 are <lb/>evident. These anomalies are relatively consistent through-<lb/>out each track and among each cluster, as seen by the ra-<lb/>dial histograms. Some clusters (1, 3, 4, 7) propagate eastward <lb/>faster than average, while others (2, 5, 6, 8, 9) appear more <lb/>static. Stationary cyclones pose a significant threat to extreme <lb/>weather occurrences by influencing local regions for longer <lb/>periods. This aspect is discussed further when examining sur-<lb/>face impacts in Sect. 3.4. <lb/>3.4 Surface impact <lb/>The emerging differences among clusters in terms of their <lb/>PV distributions, as well as their variability in terms of spa-<lb/>tiotemporal occurrence and cyclone characteristics, indicate <lb/>that different clusters are linked to different kinds of sur-<lb/>face impacts. Here we examine composites of meteorological <lb/>hazards (2 m temperature, 10 m winds, and precipitation) by <lb/>cluster to examine the range of possible surface impacts and <lb/>their mean cyclone-relative distribution and area of impact <lb/>for the timing of peak cyclone intensity. Indeed, the cluster <lb/>composites of 2 m temperature anomalies depicted in Fig. 10 <lb/>are strikingly different. Cold cyclones (clusters 1 and 2) show <lb/>negative anomalies across the domain, while the opposite <lb/>is true for northern African heat lows (cluster 6). Extended <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <page>143 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 7. As in Fig. 1 but for each of the clusters, with frequency normalized separately for each cluster. The underlying map is provided by <lb/>MathWorks (https://www.mathworks.com/help/map/ref/geoshow.html, last access: 10 December 2023). <lb/>warm anomalies also govern the summer cutoff low (cluster <lb/>9). Dominant warm surface anomalies prevail in clusters 3, <lb/>5, and 7, providing the cyclonic (positive) surface PV in all <lb/>these clusters (compare Figs. 4 and 9). Cluster 4, as opposed <lb/>to cluster 1, shows the development of a warm sector along-<lb/>side the cold one, again emphasizing the thematic separa-<lb/>tion between stages A and B of lee cyclogenesis. The daugh-<lb/>ter cyclones attributed to cluster 7 appear to form along the <lb/>frontal system of the parent cyclone, evidently preferentially <lb/>in the warm sector. Given the large variation from the av-<lb/>eraged MCs presented in Fig. 2, classification by upper-level <lb/>PV also enables a distinction among meaningful surface tem-<lb/>perature distributions, with clusters 3, 4, 5, 7, and 8 showing <lb/>a frontal structure with both warm and cold anomalies; clus-<lb/>ters 1 and 2 having a pronounced cold sector; and clusters 6 <lb/>and 9 marked by a warm anomaly throughout, without an evi-<lb/>dent frontal structure. The frequency of warm and cold fronts <lb/>detected around the cyclone is derived using composites of <lb/>the identified front objects (Fig. C4). Consistently, fronts are <lb/>more likely to be identified in clusters 1, 2, and 4 than in <lb/>clusters 6 and 9, and their spatial alignment varies strongly. <lb/>Precipitation variability is a key feature when classifying <lb/>MCs, and in Fig. 11 the precipitation by cluster is illus-<lb/>trated in terms of convective and large-scale contributions. <lb/>Generally, winter cyclones (e.g., clusters 1, 2, and 4) pre-<lb/>cipitate the most, primarily due to large-scale uplifting. The <lb/>autumn cluster 8 also exhibits comparable precipitation av-<lb/>erages, although with a relatively smaller large-scale contri-<lb/>bution. Summer clusters 6 and 9 are drier, especially African <lb/>heat lows. The former, cluster 6, has rain rates smaller than <lb/>0.2 mm h -1 (on average), and in 92 % of the cases it has no <lb/>significant precipitation at all (below 0.1 mm h -1 at a range <lb/>of ±5 • from the center). Cluster 6 is, however, closely re-<lb/>lated to significant convective precipitation anomalies further <lb/>to the south, attributed to the African monsoon (not shown). <lb/>Precipitation from cluster 2 and cluster 8 cyclones may be <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/>Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>144 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 8. Boxplots and distribution plots of the maximum 24 h deepening rate (Bergeron, 1 denotes the minimum threshold for an explosive <lb/>cyclone). Encircled dots denote the median values, while the box covers the ±25th percentiles. Whiskers denote 97.5th percentiles and define <lb/>the limit for the outliers, denoted by small dots. <lb/>Figure 9. Distributions of cyclone propagation anomalies averaged throughout the cyclone track by cluster. (a) The polar vectors indicate <lb/>the cluster mean deviation from the total average shown in Fig. 2f (colored vectors). The azimuth and radial labels show the angle (0 • marks <lb/>eastward propagation) and magnitude (m s -1 ) of the anomalies. Note that clusters 2 and 8 share a similar vector space, making cluster 2&apos;s <lb/>vector hardly visible. (b) The polar density plot illustrates the anomaly distributions of the angle composing each colored vector to the left. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <page>145 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 10. Composites of 2 m temperature anomaly from the local monthly climatology (K, shading) by cluster. Stippling denotes the 99 % <lb/>confidence level compared to the averaged field shown in Fig. 2b. Cold and warm front occurrence frequencies in the ±5 • box around the <lb/>cyclone are given in the title. Reference composite SLP contours are shown as in Fig. 3. <lb/>particularly impactful, as these cyclones tend to be more <lb/>static (compared to the other clusters; see Fig. 9). <lb/>The changes in convective precipitation mostly comple-<lb/>ment those driven by the large-scale dynamics, except for <lb/>clusters 1 and 8. In cluster 1, a competing effect is evident, as <lb/>convective precipitation decreases to the north of the cyclone <lb/>where the large-scale contribution increases compared to the <lb/>overall cyclone&apos;s mean. This may be due to the downward <lb/>movement into the lower levels found on the leeside of the <lb/>mountains influencing cluster 1 cyclones (i.e., the Alps, pri-<lb/>marily). This downward motion is expected to increase sta-<lb/>bility and hence reduce convective precipitation. However, <lb/>the large-scale contribution dominates and leads to overall <lb/>increased precipitation, likely by WCBs (Fig. C2). In cluster <lb/>8 the opposing competitive effect is evident. Increased con-<lb/>vection overlaps with a large-scale decrease in precipitation. <lb/>This feature might also be linked to the topography, which <lb/>enables the southward extension of the PV streamer, gener-<lb/>ating convection near the tip. The decrease in the large-scale <lb/>precipitation corresponds to the anticyclonic wave-breaking <lb/>fraction of the streamer, while the cyclonic tip triggers con-<lb/>vection on lower levels. Overall, cluster 8 shows the strongest <lb/>precipitation rates of all non-winter modes, again highlight-<lb/>ing a unique autumn contribution to precipitation and sug-<lb/>gesting the importance of the double wave-breaking pattern <lb/>(anticyclonic followed by cyclonic wave breaking) to the in-<lb/>tensity of MCs (see Fig. B1). <lb/>The presence of warm conveyor belts and their spatial ori-<lb/>entation are highly influential with respect to precipitation <lb/>patterns. WCB mask composites for the mid-troposphere <lb/>are presented in Fig. C2, with large variations between the <lb/>clusters. Interestingly, while WCBs indeed dominate clusters <lb/>with clear wet deviations (both large-scale and convective), <lb/>such as clusters 1 and 4 (but somewhat less in cluster 2), <lb/>WCBs also dominate clusters 3 and 7 while their precipi-<lb/>tation amounts are low, represented by negative deviations. <lb/>The latter is likely due to the large fraction of cluster 3 and <lb/>cluster 7 cyclones over land in northwestern Africa, where <lb/>moisture sources for precipitation are limited. In these cases, <lb/>dust is likely transported along dry WCBs (Fluck and Raveh-<lb/>Rubin, 2023; Rousseau-Rizzi et al., 2023). Notably, a clus-<lb/>ter 7 cyclone peaking on 15 April 2005 traveled from north-<lb/>ern Africa towards Greece, generating an extreme dust storm <lb/>(Kaskaoutis et al., 2008). <lb/>The response of the 10 m wind speed is presented in <lb/>Fig. 12. While summer clusters (6, 9) show significantly <lb/>weaker winds revolving the cyclone compared to winter cy-<lb/>clones (1, 2, 4), the response of the other clusters is mostly <lb/>statistically insignificant. Interestingly, AWB and CWB cy-<lb/>clones (cluster 2) demonstrate the most intense cyclonic mo-<lb/>tion at the surface, despite being shallower than the lee cy-<lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/>Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>146 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 11. Precipitation deviation with respect to the cyclone mean in Fig. 2d, shown separately for the large-scale (mm h -1 , shading) <lb/>and convective (±0.05 mm h -1 , cyan and yellow contours for positive and negative) precipitation deviations. The black contours show the <lb/>absolute, cluster-averaged daily precipitation rate (sum of large-scale and convective precipitation, 0.2 and 0.5 mm h -1 ), while rain rates <lb/>exceeding 1 mm h -1 are shown in magenta. Stippling denotes regions where the large-scale response is statistically significant in the 90 % <lb/>confidence level compared to the total mean, and yellow dots denote the corresponding significance level for the convective response. Note <lb/>that the domain size is smaller than the other composites. In parentheses is the cluster frequency of cyclones with a total precipitation rate <lb/>greater than 0.1 mm h -1 anywhere within ±5 • (i.e., the 10 • <lb/>× 10 • box around the cyclone). <lb/>clones 1 and 4. This apparent contradiction is resolved by <lb/>linking the enhanced upper-level PV anomaly in cluster 2 to <lb/>surface winds, as further discussed in Appendix B, highlight-<lb/>ing the importance of the topographically induced Rossby <lb/>wave breaking (RWB). The PV streamer acquires an anticy-<lb/>clonic curvature over the wind side of the Alps and cyclonic <lb/>curving/wrapping on the leeside, which extends far to lower <lb/>levels and intersects with low-level PV to form a PV tower. <lb/>3.5 Trends and predictability <lb/>To explore the potential of the PV cluster framework to im-<lb/>prove the understanding of MC predictability, we examine <lb/>the cluster composites of PV at cyclogenesis, namely the ini-<lb/>tiation time (and location) of the same tracks that build up the <lb/>cluster. Noting that it takes ∼ 40 h on average from cycloge-<lb/>nesis to reach the cyclone minimum SLP (not shown), the <lb/>cluster composites at time 0 resemble the peak time compos-<lb/>ites (compare Fig. 13 to Fig. 3). Thus, each track can be read-<lb/>ily assigned to its cluster already at the cyclogenesis stage, <lb/>suggesting high predictability of the cluster type due to the <lb/>little change in the PV signature between these time steps. <lb/>Considering the fundamental differences among cyclone <lb/>classes, it is useful to evaluate observed long-term trends <lb/>in their frequency of occurrence. Despite large year-to-year <lb/>variability, using a 5-year moving mean, significant trends <lb/>emerge for some clusters. Generally, when considering all <lb/>cyclones together, a weak increasing trend emerges with one <lb/>to two more cyclones per decade (Fig. 2e). The decompo-<lb/>sition into clusters, however, reveals some competing trends <lb/>that make up this weak signal (Fig. 14). A significant de-<lb/>crease in the occurrence of winter clusters 1 and 4 is evident. <lb/>At the same time, there is an increase in the occurrence fre-<lb/>quencies of summer clusters 6 and 9 and transition-season <lb/>clusters 3 and 5, though the latter two only show significance <lb/>when computed for the moving mean. These trends agree <lb/>with the expected poleward shift of the storm track (Caian <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <page>147 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 12. Composites of the deviation of 10 m wind speeds with respect to the total cyclone average. Reference composite PV contours <lb/>are shown as in Fig. 3 (black contours). Stippling denotes regions where the wind speed response is statistically significant in the 99 % <lb/>confidence level compared to the total cyclone mean. <lb/>et al., 2021), reducing the impact of Atlantic cyclones on the <lb/>northern Mediterranean winter and expanding tropical influ-<lb/>ences poleward in summer (Cook and Vizy, 2019; Tuel and <lb/>Eltahir, 2020). These changes have led to the recent decrease <lb/>in precipitation and increasing heat waves, reported through-<lb/>out western Europe and the Middle East (Lionello et al., <lb/>2014). The significance of these trends in reanalysis serves <lb/>as motivation to investigate future projections of the clus-<lb/>ter&apos;s frequency by decomposing Mediterranean cyclones into <lb/>their different types, which likely have opposing trends. Fur-<lb/>thermore, a significant increase is noted in anomalous occur-<lb/>rences of cluster 6 cyclones (not shown) in spring over Eu-<lb/>rope, indicating a mechanism of European drying that poses <lb/>concerning prospects to regional climate. <lb/>4 Summary and discussion <lb/>The climatological SOM classification of MCs by their <lb/>upper-level PV distributions resulted in nine fundamentally <lb/>different MC types. Despite classifying a 2D map at the peak <lb/>time of each cyclone track, each cluster displays significant <lb/>variability across the 3D space and throughout the cyclone&apos;s <lb/>lifetime. Considered as a whole, distinct surface impacts and <lb/>cluster features highlight the dominant process driving MCs <lb/>in each cluster: from daughter and topographically induced <lb/>cyclones to heat (thermal) and cutoff lows. A separation be-<lb/>tween stages A and B of lee cyclogenesis (Buzzi and Tibaldi, <lb/>1978; McGinley, 1982) is reflected in this analysis, and AWB <lb/>and CWB (corresponding to life cycles 1 and 2, respectively; <lb/>Thorncroft et al., 1993) are captured as well. While some <lb/>clusters are highly influenced by topography, the cyclone-<lb/>centered perspective enables us to tell apart differently driven <lb/>MCs even when sharing similar regional and seasonal ampli-<lb/>tudes and vice versa, i.e., to relate dynamically similar cy-<lb/>clones occurring in different regions or seasons. For example, <lb/>a Cyprus low may appear in similar seasons as cluster 2 or 4, <lb/>with substantially different weather implications, while sim-<lb/>ilar cyclones in those clusters frequently occur in other re-<lb/>gions but Cyprus. Table 1 qualitatively summarizes the main <lb/>MC-driving mechanism by cluster, based on the collective <lb/>information of its geographic, seasonal, thermal, and dynam-<lb/>ical features as discussed throughout this work. <lb/>The SOM illustrates the spectrum of MC variability on <lb/>a scale ranging from midlatitude winter cyclones (clusters <lb/>1 and 4) to subtropical summer heat lows (clusters 6 and <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/>Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>148 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 13. As Fig. 3 but at the cyclogenesis stage. <lb/>9), highlighting the different Rossby wave life cycles in be-<lb/>tween. Cluster 5 indicates the dominance of AWB, while <lb/>cluster 8 shows a modified pattern of CWB. A cutoff low <lb/>dominates cluster 3, while cluster 7 appears to correspond to <lb/>daughter lows forming along the frontal system of a synoptic-<lb/>scale cyclone (possibly a Mediterranean cyclone of cluster <lb/>1 or 4, or an Atlantic cyclone). Cluster 2 includes some of <lb/>the most intense MCs and yields the largest PV anomalies <lb/>despite being dominated by AWB, usually associated with <lb/>the cyclone decaying phase. This highlights the coupling be-<lb/>tween upper-and lower-PV anomalies that may be an arti-<lb/>fact of PV interaction with orography. Indeed, for a cyclone <lb/>initiated in the Gulf of Genoa (as clusters 2 and 8 often <lb/>are), AWB is expected on the windward side of the Alps, <lb/>while cyclonic shear is forced on the leeside, joined by the <lb/>mistral further south, possibly leading to a secondary CWB <lb/>event. Such an event is presented in Givon et al. (2021), in <lb/>which the PV streamer rotates anticyclonically on the wind-<lb/>ward side of the Alps and flows over the Rhone Valley. It <lb/>then curves cyclonically and breaks on the leeside, form-<lb/>ing a spiral that converges toward the surface cyclone, and <lb/>eventually forms a cutoff low (see Appendix B). The process <lb/>is accompanied by rapid deepening of the surface cyclone <lb/>that peaks during the CWB stage. Similar formations with <lb/>different magnitudes/wavelengths appear to form clusters 8 <lb/>and 2, the most intense clusters in their respective seasons. <lb/>This double wave-breaking pattern is further discussed in the <lb/>Appendix. Compared to cyclone-centered classifications per-<lb/>formed in other regions on the globe (e.g., Catto, 2018), MCs <lb/>appear smaller, with larger influences of heat lows and AWB. <lb/>However, since this is the first attempt to classify cyclones <lb/>by their upper-level PV structures, it is still unknown how <lb/>the PV patterns are expected to vary in different geographic <lb/>regions. Overall, the dynamic classification represents sub-<lb/>stantially different MCs that vary in their driving mechanism, <lb/>with significant implications for weather and climate fore-<lb/>casting. <lb/>5 Concluding remarks <lb/>Mediterranean cyclones are a major cause of severe weather, <lb/>affecting the lives of millions throughout Europe, northern <lb/>Africa, and the Middle East. Current understanding of MC <lb/>predictability is lacking, with an emphasis on predicting the <lb/>cyclone location, deepening rate, and distribution and in-<lb/>tensity of its meteorological impact (precipitation, tempera-<lb/>ture, surface winds). Using a SOM approach, upper-level PV <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <page>149 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 14. Inter-annual cyclone frequency by cluster (thin line) and 5-year moving mean (thick line). The long-term trend statistical signifi-<lb/>cance is evaluated with the Mann-Kendall (MK) test for the smoothed data on a 90 % confidence level. The MK results (binary, 1 indicates <lb/>a significant trend) are given in the title. The dashed line shows the linear best fit. <lb/>serves to classify cyclones and systematically evaluate the <lb/>large-scale patterns driving different cyclone types, with dis-<lb/>tinct seasonal and geographical distributions, a characteristic <lb/>cyclone life cycle, dynamic and thermodynamic responses, <lb/>and associated hazards. Specifically, differences in the ex-<lb/>plosiveness and propagation of each cluster are evident, and <lb/>a dynamic relation between upper-level PV anomalies and <lb/>low-to mid-tropospheric PV anomalies is suggested. <lb/>A caveat of this approach is the indirect link to the con-<lb/>tribution of orography to cyclone development. For exam-<lb/>ple, clusters 2 and 8 are influenced by orography. In what <lb/>may be a unique PV structure for the Mediterranean Basin, <lb/>these cyclones appear to portray an anticyclonically breaking <lb/>PV streamer that curves and breaks cyclonically near its tip <lb/>(Fig. B1 in Appendix B). It is shown that such PV streamers <lb/>penetrate lower latitudes, creating the largest PV anomalies <lb/>in both upper and lower levels, resulting in the most vigorous <lb/>cyclones with the strongest surface winds and precipitation <lb/>rates for their respective season. Furthermore, due to their <lb/>interaction with orography, these cyclones propagate slower <lb/>than average, making their surface impact even more destruc-<lb/>tive. <lb/>We trace each cyclone track back to initiation time to show <lb/>that the PV clusters may already be identified at cycloge-<lb/>nesis. This may allow forecasters to identify the cyclone <lb/>type only by its cyclone-relative PV distribution, with pro-<lb/>found implications for the cyclone&apos;s expected intensity, ther-<lb/>mal structure, precipitation rate, propagation velocity, etc., <lb/>as shown here throughout. These insights may be useful for <lb/>constraining the large ensemble spread that often arises in <lb/>MC forecasts (Binder et al., 2021; Portmann et al., 2020). <lb/>We conclude with long-term trends suggesting a future in-<lb/>crease in summer heat lows and a corresponding decrease <lb/>in cold cyclones near the Gulf of Genoa. While the latter <lb/>has been shown in past studies, in both historical analysis <lb/>and future projections (Trigo et al., 2000; Zappa et al., 2015; <lb/>Reale et al., 2022), increasing trends of Mediterranean ther-<lb/>mal lows were only reported by future projections (Lionello <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/>Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>150 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <body>Table 1. <lb/>Summary of the main cyclone cluster characteristics. Precipitation is summarized as the mean absolute pattern as well as large-scale (LS) and convective (C) anomaly <lb/>signs. <lb/>Cluster <lb/>(1) Stage A lee low (2) AWB + <lb/>CWB low (3) Longwave cutoff low (4) Stage B lee low (5) AWB low <lb/>(6) Heat low (Sharav) (7) Daughter low (8) CWB low <lb/>(9) Shortwave cutoff low <lb/>Season <lb/>winter <lb/>winter <lb/>spring <lb/>winter <lb/>spring/autumn <lb/>summer <lb/>spring <lb/>autumn <lb/>summer <lb/>Genesis <lb/>Alps <lb/>Alps <lb/>Atlas <lb/>Alps <lb/>Atlas <lb/>Atlas <lb/>diverse <lb/>Alps <lb/>diverse <lb/>Peak <lb/>Ligurian Sea <lb/>diverse <lb/>Atlas <lb/>diverse <lb/>Atlas <lb/>Sahara <lb/>diverse <lb/>Ligurian sea <lb/>diverse <lb/>Cold sector <lb/>extreme <lb/>extreme <lb/>weak <lb/>strong <lb/>mild <lb/>faint <lb/>weak <lb/>mild <lb/>faint <lb/>Warm sector faint <lb/>Weak <lb/>strong <lb/>mild <lb/>strong <lb/>extreme <lb/>extreme <lb/>mild <lb/>strong <lb/>Precipitation heavy, LS+ C-<lb/>heavy, LS+ C+ <lb/>mild, LS-C-<lb/>heavy, LS+ C+ <lb/>mild, LS-C-weak, LS-C-<lb/>mild, LS-C-<lb/>heavy, LS-C+ mild, LS-C-<lb/>Mobility <lb/>fast <lb/>slow <lb/>fast <lb/>fast <lb/>average <lb/>slow <lb/>fast <lb/>slow <lb/>slow <lb/>Trend <lb/>decrease <lb/>none <lb/>increase <lb/>decrease <lb/>increase <lb/>increase <lb/>none <lb/>none <lb/>increase <lb/>and Giorgi, 2007) and were not detected in historical data un-<lb/>til now. The distinct and at times opposing trends of differ-<lb/>ent MC types have important implications for understanding <lb/>and mitigating the future impacts of MCs across the Mediter-<lb/>ranean region and far into Europe, northern Africa, and the <lb/>Middle East. We emphasize the importance of considering <lb/>the cyclone class when associating current and future impacts <lb/>with MCs, extending to aspects not considered here, such as <lb/>hail, dust transport, fires, or compound hazards (Rousseau-<lb/>Rizzi et al., 2023). <lb/>The upper-level PV classification yielded a thematic sep-<lb/>aration between different cyclone-driving mechanisms, un-<lb/>bound by geographical considerations. This method tran-<lb/>scends the common geographical-seasonal classifications of <lb/>MCs, enabling the identification of highly similar events oc-<lb/>curring in different seasons and/or geographical regions. We <lb/>hope this perspective can be used to enhance the understand-<lb/>ing of MCs&apos; predictability on both weather and climate scales <lb/>and serve as an insightful approach to classifying extratropi-<lb/>cal cyclones at large. <lb/></body>

        <div type="annex">Appendix A: SOM analysis <lb/>The SOM is composed of a hexagonal grid topology, with <lb/>an initial coverage period of 400 steps (∼ 12 % of all cy-<lb/>clones, in this case). The initial neighborhood size is set to <lb/>2, and the SOM analysis includes 800 iterations. The PV in-<lb/>put is rescaled by its total average and standard deviation to <lb/>range between 0-1 (as in Givon et al., 2021), which helps <lb/>reduce SOM errors, defined as the total mean squared error <lb/>(MSE) between the cluster&apos;s members and composites, av-<lb/>eraged across all clusters. SOM shows weak sensitivity to <lb/>these initial parameters within a reasonable range of values <lb/>(not shown). The number of clusters (N = 9) is selected us-<lb/>ing the elbow method (Liu and Deng, 2020), as the number <lb/>beyond which a sharp decrease in the SOM learning rate (i.e., <lb/>SOM error reduction per added cluster) is evident. <lb/></div>

        <note place="footnote">Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <page>151 <lb/></page>

        <div type="annex">Figure A1. Self-organizing map configuration with neighbor sim-<lb/>ilarity, illustrating the differences between neighboring clusters. <lb/>Cluster numbers are noted in the purple nodes; note their different <lb/>order compared to other figures in the paper. <lb/>Appendix B: The 3D PV structure <lb/>We explore the 3D structure of the upper and lower isobaric <lb/>PV. This structure of the PV sheds light on the tropopause <lb/>height and the low-level PV signature, highlighting the exis-<lb/>tence of PV towers, known to occur during the mature phase <lb/>of the most intense cyclones (Rossa et al., 2000; Čampa <lb/>and Wernli, 2012). A PV tower is characterized by values <lb/>greater than 0.5 PVU throughout the atmospheric column, <lb/>representing a column vortex extending from the surface to <lb/>the tropopause. Here, a simplified 3D PV structure is shown <lb/>by the lowermost pressure level of the 2 PVU surface for <lb/>upper-level PV and the uppermost level of the 0.5 PVU sur-<lb/>face for low-level PV (Figs. B1 and B2). Specifically, the PV <lb/>field was scanned for values greater than 0.5 PVU across the <lb/>800 hPa level, as below the 800 hPa level the pressure sur-<lb/>faces may intersect the mountains, leading to unrealistically <lb/>large PV anomalies. The minimum pressure where the PV <lb/>drops below 0.5 PVU is defined as the upper boundary of the <lb/>low-level PV surface for a given cyclone. This method suc-<lb/>cessfully filters out topographic influences and emphasizes <lb/>the PV signature of the surface cyclone. <lb/>One surprising fact arising from the present study is that <lb/>the stormiest MCs are attributed to AWB cluster 2, despite <lb/>AWB being expected to lead to a rapid decay of the cyclone. <lb/>Moreover, surface cyclones attributed to this cluster are not <lb/>the deepest in terms of SLP (not shown). Instead, the sur-<lb/>face cyclones seem contracted, resulting in sharper SLP gra-<lb/>dients. The results suggest that the cyclones deepen due to <lb/>the AWB streamers&apos; southward extension and the cyclonic <lb/>curvature at their tip, just above the surface cyclone. This <lb/>setup induces extreme PV anomalies across the tropospheric <lb/>column and leads to the formation of prominent tropospheric <lb/>PV towers. Note that the PV towers are obscured by the aver-<lb/>aging and thus do not cross the tropopause. Nevertheless, the <lb/>tallest low-level PV features are evidence of a larger like-<lb/>lihood of the presence of PV towers that enter the strato-<lb/>sphere. As shown in Fig. B1, cluster 2 (and 8, to a lesser <lb/>extent) extends farthest from the main PV reservoir (low-<lb/>ered tropopause along the northern part of the domain) and <lb/>breaks cyclonically on lower levels. The response in mid-<lb/>level is shown in Fig. B2, in the form of the tallest low-level <lb/>PV tower coupled to the lowermost dip of the tropopause <lb/>(and vice versa, e.g., clusters 6 and 9). This explains both the <lb/>precipitation and surface wind maxima of clusters 2 and 8, <lb/>compared to the other clusters in the corresponding seasons. <lb/></div>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/>Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>152 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <div type="annex">Figure B1. Cluster composite of the lower boundary of the 2 PVU surfaces, at classification time (minimum SLP) in pressure coordinates <lb/>(hPa), as viewed from the east-northeast. <lb/>Figure B2. As in B1, showing the y-z plane across the cyclone center, coupled to the upper boundary of the 0.5 PVU surface, illustrating the <lb/>presence of PV towers. <lb/></div>

        <note place="footnote">Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <page>153 <lb/></page>

        <div type="annex">Appendix C: PV streamers and cutoffs, WCB, and <lb/>fronts <lb/>The presence of PV streamers varies strongly between clus-<lb/>ters (Fig. C1), with the peak frequencies of both PV stream-<lb/>ers and cutoffs lying mostly along the equatorward border of <lb/>the trough. For some clusters, the average PV feature itself <lb/>is detected as a PV streamer (clusters 2, 5, and 8), and for <lb/>others (clusters 3, 4, 6, and 7), the streamers are smoothed <lb/>in the PV composite, an indication of their smaller-scale and <lb/>large spatial variability. Though possibly on lower isentropic <lb/>levels, PV cutoffs often overlap with the streamers and are <lb/>significantly less frequent for winter clusters. The exception <lb/>is cluster 7 (daughter cyclones) where the cutoff is distinctly <lb/>separated from the streamer. This suggests that daughter cy-<lb/>clones form at the tip of a PV streamer emanating from the <lb/>synoptic system, possibly forming a cutoff as they approach <lb/>their maximum intensity (i.e., classification time). PV cut-<lb/>offs are most dominant in clusters 6 and 9, and again while <lb/>the cutoff is evident in the PV composite for cluster 9, it is <lb/>not evident for cluster 6. This suggests weaker and/or more <lb/>scattered PV cutoffs (but most frequent) in cluster 6. <lb/>Mid-tropospheric WCB reveals the uneven contribution <lb/>of diabatic effects between the different cyclone clusters <lb/>(Fig. C2). While a WCB is reported across 90 % of most clus-<lb/>ters, cluster 6 is distinguished with a mere 50 % frequency, <lb/>as expected from the dry environment where it is found. The <lb/>frequency of WCB peaks in cluster 4, possibly due to the <lb/>advection of moist air as the lee cyclone propagates over <lb/>the Mediterranean, transitioning from stage A (cluster 1) to <lb/>stage B (cluster 4). This conclusion is supported by a tongue <lb/>of warm equivalent potential temperatures on the 850 hPa <lb/>surface noted for cluster 4 but much weaker for cluster 1 <lb/>(Fig. C3). <lb/>Cluster composites of equivalent potential temperatures <lb/>(θ e , Fig. C3) cover a wide range of temperatures. Besides the <lb/>different extremes (clusters 1 and 6), the patterns vary from <lb/>meridional gradients (clusters 3, 5, and 8) to partly zonal ones <lb/>(clusters 2 and 4), to near-homogeneous conditions (clus-<lb/>ters 1, 6, and 9). Clusters 2, 4, and 8 display occluding air <lb/>as a warm tongue curving into the cyclone center from the <lb/>south. The large difference between clusters 1 and 4, given <lb/>their similar geography and surface temperature anomalies, <lb/>appears to indicate the dominant role of moisture in type B <lb/>cyclones compared to type A. <lb/>Meteorological fronts are an objectively challenging fea-<lb/>ture to handle with means of composites, as they are identi-<lb/>fied as long, thin objects at varying locations relative to the <lb/>cyclone. Nevertheless, front mask composites (Fig. C4) show <lb/>warm and cold fronts emanating east and west of the center, <lb/>respectively, for at least 50 % of the cyclones. A trailing cold <lb/>front is evident for clusters 2, 4, and 8. The warm fronts are <lb/>relatively spatially consistent throughout the clusters, though <lb/>the averaged frequencies differ from 36 % for warm fronts in <lb/>cluster 6 to 81 % for cluster 1. <lb/></div>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/>Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>154 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <div type="annex">Figure C1. Composites of PV streamer frequency (%, shading) and 10 % contour for PV cutoff frequency (cyan), integrated over the 320-<lb/>340 K isentropes, in 5 K intervals. A streamer/cutoff mask is applied to grid points where a streamer/cutoff is identified on at least one <lb/>isentropic level. Cluster frequencies of PV streamers and cutoffs are noted in the title, where the streamer frequency accounts for any signal <lb/>within the domain, and cutoff frequency accounts for cyclones that report a cutoff present in at least five grid points. Black contours show <lb/>cluster PV composites (as in Fig. 3, 0.5 PV intervals), with dashed contours for values below 3 PVU. Note the smaller domain compared to <lb/>Fig. 3. <lb/>Figure C2. As Fig. C1 but with shading for the mid-troposphere (800-400 hPa) warm conveyor belt (WCB) mask frequency. The cluster <lb/>mean frequency where a WCB is detected somewhere in the domain is reported in the panel titles. <lb/></div>

        <note place="footnote">Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <page>155 <lb/></page>

        <div type="annex">Figure C3. As in C1 but with shading of 850 hPa θ e (K). <lb/>Figure C4. Composite cluster frequencies of cold fronts (shading) and warm fronts (contours). The cluster mean frequencies of a nonzero <lb/>front signal are reported in the panel titles (left: cold, right: warm), corresponding to the fraction of cyclones showing a front present <lb/>somewhere in a 10 • box around the cyclone. <lb/></div>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/>Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>156 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <div type="annex">Appendix D: Distribution of medicanes between clusters <lb/>On the continuum between tropical and extratropical cy-<lb/>clones, medicanes are a specific set of tropical-like cyclones <lb/>forming in the Mediterranean (extratropical environment). <lb/>This elusive class of MCs was first noted in the 1980s (see <lb/>Table 1). However, until now the features that render an MC a <lb/>medicane were mostly subjective, relying on cloud structure <lb/>observations and the presence of a warm core. To date, an <lb/>objective, consistent definition of medicane is still pending. <lb/>Attempting to put medicanes into the context of the PV-<lb/>based classification here, we examine a list of 12 agreed <lb/>medicanes from the literature (Table D1). The table consists <lb/>of all medicanes for which a warm core has been confirmed <lb/>(Marcelo Miglietta, personal communication, 2023; see Ac-<lb/>knowledgements section). While too few cases are consid-<lb/>ered to make conclusive statements, it appears that most win-<lb/>ter medicanes are captured as a stage B lee cyclone (cluster 4) <lb/>and AWB and CWB cyclones (cluster 2, 25 % of the medi-<lb/>canes). Autumn cases are mostly captured as shortwave cut-<lb/>off lows (cluster 9) that form another 25 % of the medicanes. <lb/>Recalling that the first (cluster 4) is in line with the charac-<lb/>terization of cluster 4 cyclones as &quot;free-traveling waves&quot; as <lb/>opposed to the stationary cluster 1, these medicanes are more <lb/>likely to attain their warm core initially through warm seclu-<lb/>sion (see Fig. C3). The latter (cluster 9), given the extended <lb/>warm anomalies, possibly induces intense ocean evaporation <lb/>and diabatic heat release to grow as medicanes. Indeed, both <lb/>mechanisms are considered to be among the drivers of dif-<lb/>ferent medicanes. As for cluster 2 medicanes, these include <lb/>the category B case shown in Miglietta and Rotunno (2019), <lb/>where the medicane maintains its connection with the main <lb/>PV reservoir. However, since the MC clusters are defined <lb/>based on the minimum SLP time of the cyclone, and tropical <lb/>characteristics may develop in different life stages of the cy-<lb/>clone, the association of PV clusters with medicanes cannot, <lb/>by construction, explain the full life cycle development of the <lb/>medicanes. Moreover, the spatial scale in which medicanes <lb/>are usually diagnosed is much smaller than the large-scale <lb/>structures examined here. Thus, medicanes do not form un-<lb/>der a single large-scale PV scenario, and a systematic inves-<lb/>tigation of the PV distribution of medicanes is still an open <lb/>issue. <lb/>Table D1. <lb/>Date (yyyy-mm-dd), cluster number, name, and references of 12 confirmed medicane cases. <lb/>Dates <lb/>Cluster Name <lb/>Area <lb/>References <lb/>1982-01-24-28 <lb/>2 Leucosia <lb/>S Med <lb/>Ernst and Matson (1983), Pytharoulis et al. (2000), Reed et al. (2001) <lb/>1983-09-10-27-02 <lb/>9 Callisto <lb/>W Med <lb/>Pytharoulis et al. (2000) <lb/>1995-01-14-18 <lb/>2 Celeno <lb/>E Med <lb/>Cavicchia and von Storch (2012), Pytharoulis et al. (1999), Pytharoulis et al. (2000) <lb/>1996-10-06-11 <lb/>5 Cornelia <lb/>C Med <lb/>Cavicchia and von Storch (2012), Pytharoulis et al. (2000), Miglietta and Rotunno (2019) <lb/>2005-12-13-16 <lb/>2 Zeo <lb/>E Med <lb/>Fita et al. (2007), Luque et al. (2007), Miglietta et al. (2013), Fita and Flaounas (2018), <lb/>Dafis et al. (2000), Miglietta and Rotunno (2019), Miglietta et al. (2021) <lb/>2006-09-25-26 <lb/>9 Maria/Querida <lb/>C Med <lb/>Moscatello et al. (2008), Davolio et al. (2009), Miglietta et al. (2011), Chaboureau et al. (2012), <lb/>Miglietta et al. (2013, 2015), Dafis et al. (2020) <lb/>2011-11-04-09 <lb/>4 Rolf <lb/>W Med <lb/>Miglietta et al. (2013), Dafis et al. (2018, 2020) <lb/>2014-01-19-22 <lb/>4 Ilona <lb/>W Med <lb/>Cioni et al. (2016), Dafis et al. (2020) <lb/>2014-11-07-09 <lb/>5 Qendresa <lb/>S Med <lb/>Homar et al. (2003), Carrió et al. (2017), Cioni et al. (2018), Pytharoulis (2018), <lb/>Mylonas et al. (2019), Noyelle et al. (2019), Bouin and Lebeaupin Brossier (2020), Dafis et al. (2020) <lb/>2017-11-16-19 <lb/>4 Numa <lb/>Ionian Sea Marra et al. (2019), Dafis et al. (2020) <lb/>2018-09-27-30 <lb/>9 Zorbas <lb/>Ionian Sea Dafis et al. (2020), Kouroutzoglou et al. (2021) <lb/>2020-09-15-18 <lb/>6 Udine-Cassilda-Ianos S Med <lb/>Lagouvardos et al. (2022), Prat et al. (2021), D&apos;Adderio et al. (2022), Zimbo et al. (2022) <lb/></div>

        <note place="footnote">Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <page>157 <lb/></page>

        <div type="annex">Code availability. The code for the SOM classification algo-<lb/>rithm is openly available at https://www.mathworks.com/help/ <lb/>deeplearning/gs/cluster-data-with-a-self-organizingmap.html (last <lb/>access: 29 January 2024). <lb/></div>

        <div type="availability">Data availability. The composite cyclone tracks with the resulting <lb/>cluster attribution are available in the supplementary assets of this <lb/>paper. The track labels correspond to the composite cyclone track <lb/>dataset at confidence level 5, made available as a Supplement by <lb/>Flaounas et al. (2023) (&quot;TRACKS_CL5.dat&quot;). <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Video supplement. To <lb/>illustrate <lb/>the <lb/>combined <lb/>Rossby <lb/>lifecycle (AWB + CWB) highlighted by cluster 2, we <lb/>show the upper-level PV and SLP distributions during <lb/>the evolution of the storm &quot;Vaia/Adrian&quot; on a 6 h basis <lb/>(https://www.dropbox.com/scl/fi/6s5uw97089a83r6nnp2zi/Vaia_ <lb/>Storm.mp4?rlkey=tzshhuyutd0vgdz151ntza53d&amp;dl=0, <lb/>Givon, <lb/>2023). <lb/></div>

        <div type="contribution">Author contributions. YG and SRR conceptualized the research. <lb/>YG conducted the research, performed the analysis, and wrote the <lb/>underlying codes and the manuscript. EF provided the composite <lb/>cyclone track data, JLC provided dynamic fronts data, and MS pro-<lb/>vided PV streamers, cut-offs, and WCB data. OH assisted in the de-<lb/>velopment of the cyclone centered SOM application and performed <lb/>sensitivity analysis. All coauthors took part in reviewing and editing <lb/>the final draft. <lb/></div>

        <div type="conflict">Competing interests. At least one of the (co-)authors is a member <lb/>of the editorial board of Weather and Climate Dynamics. The peer-<lb/>review process was guided by an independent editor, and the authors <lb/>also have no other competing interests to declare. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Disclaimer. Publisher&apos;s note: Copernicus Publications remains <lb/>neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims made in the text, pub-<lb/>lished maps, institutional affiliations, or any other geographical rep-<lb/>resentation in this paper. While Copernicus Publications makes ev-<lb/>ery effort to include appropriate place names, the final responsibility <lb/>lies with the authors. <lb/></div>

        <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements. This article is based on work from the COST <lb/>Action CA19109 titled European network for Mediterranean cy-<lb/>clones in weather and climate (Hatzaki et al. 2023), supported <lb/>by the European Cooperation in Science and Technology (COST; <lb/>https://www.cost.eu, last access: 21 January 2024). We are grate-<lb/>ful to the COST Action initiative for the definition of a medicane, <lb/>led by Marcello Miglietta, for the insightful discussions, and for <lb/>providing the list of medicanes. We further acknowledge Giulia <lb/>Panegrossi, Valentina Di Francesca, and Leo Pio D&apos;Adderio for <lb/>generously associating the medicanes with the clusters. Finally, we <lb/>thank all COST Action members for insightful discussions and two <lb/>anonymous reviewers for their helpful suggestions. <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">Financial support. This research was partially supported by the de <lb/>Botton Center for Marine Science, the Israeli Council for Higher <lb/>Education (CHE) via the Weizmann Data Science Research Cen-<lb/>ter, and the Weizmann Institute Sustainability and Energy Research <lb/>Initiative (SAERI). <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Review statement. This paper was edited by Michael Riemer and <lb/>reviewed by two anonymous referees. <lb/></div>

        <listBibl>References <lb/>Adamson, D. S., Belcher, S. E., Hoskins, B. J., and Plant, R. <lb/>S.: Boundary-layer friction in midlatitude cyclones, Q. J. Roy. <lb/>Meteor. Soc., 132, 101-124, https://doi.org/10.1256/qj.04.145, <lb/>2006. <lb/>Alpert, P., Neeman, B. U., and Shay-El, Y.: Climatological analysis <lb/>of Mediterranean cyclones using ECMWF data, Tellus A, 42, 65-<lb/>77, https://doi.org/10.3402/tellusa.v42i1.11860, 1990. <lb/>Alpert, P., Osetinsky, I., Ziv, B., and Shafir, H.: A new seasons def-<lb/>inition based on classified daily synoptic systems: an example <lb/>for the eastern Mediterranean, Int. J. Climatol., 24, 1013-1021, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/joc.1037, 2004. <lb/>Ammar, K., El-Metwally, M., Almazroui, M., and Abdel Wahab, <lb/>M. M.: A climatological analysis of Saharan cyclones, Clim. Dy-<lb/>nam., 43, 483-501, https://rdcu.be/dbI7T, 2014. <lb/>Berkovic, S., Mendelsohn, O. Y., Ilotoviz, E., and Raveh-<lb/>Rubin, S.: Self-organizing map classification of the bound-<lb/>ary layer profile: a refinement of Eastern Mediterranean <lb/>winter synoptic regimes, Int. J. Climatol., 41, 3317-3338, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/joc.7021, 2021. <lb/>Binder, H., Rivière, G., Arbogast, P., Maynard, K., Bosser, P., Joly, <lb/>B., and Labadie, C.: Dynamics of forecast-error growth along <lb/>cut-off Sanchez and its consequence for the prediction of a high-<lb/>impact weather event over southern France, Q. J. Roy. Meteor. <lb/>Soc., 147, 3263-3285, https://doi.org/10.1002/qj.4127, 2021. <lb/>Boettcher, M. and Wernli, H.: Life cycle study of a diabatic Rossby <lb/>wave as a precursor to rapid cyclogenesis in the North Atlantic <lb/>-Dynamics and forecast performance, Mon. Weather Rev., 139, <lb/>1861-1878, https://doi.org/10.1175/2011MWR3504.1, 2011. <lb/>Boettcher, M. and Wernli, H.: A 10-yr climatology of di-<lb/>abatic Rossby waves in the Northern Hemisphere, Mon. <lb/>Weather Rev., 141, 1139-1154, https://doi.org/10.1175/MWR-<lb/>D-12-00012.1, 2013. <lb/>Bouin, M.-N. and Lebeaupin Brossier, C.: Impact of a medicane on <lb/>the oceanic surface layer from a coupled, kilometre-scale sim-<lb/>ulation, Ocean Sci., 16, 1125-1142, https://doi.org/10.5194/os-<lb/>16-1125-2020, 2020. <lb/>Buzzi, A. and Tibaldi, S.: Cyclogenesis in the lee of the <lb/>Alps: A case study, Q. J. Roy. Meteor. Soc., 104, 271-287, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/qj.49710444004, 1978. <lb/>Buzzi, A., Davolio, S., and Fantini, M.: Cyclogenesis in the lee of <lb/>the Alps: a review of theories, B. Atmos. Sci. Technol, 1, 433-<lb/>457, https://doi.org/10.1007/s42865-020-00021-6, 2020. <lb/>Caian, M., Georgescu, F., Pietrisi, M., and Catrina, O.: Recent <lb/>changes in storm track over the Southeast Europe: a mecha-<lb/>nism for changes in extreme cyclone variability, Atmosphere, 12, <lb/>1362, https://doi.org/10.3390/atmos12101362, 2021. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/>Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>158 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>Carrió, D. S., Homar, V., Jansa, A., Romero, R., and Picornell, M. <lb/>A.: Tropicalization process of the 7 November 2014 Mediter-<lb/>ranean cyclone: numerical sensitivity study, Atmos. Res., 197, <lb/>300-312, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.atmosres.2017.07.018, 2017. <lb/>Cavicchia, L. and von Storch, H.: The simulation of medicanes <lb/>in a high-resolution regional climate model, Clim. Dynam., 39, <lb/>2273-2290, https://doi.org/10.1007/s00382-011-1220-0, 2012. <lb/>Čampa, J. and Wernli, H.: A PV perspective on the vertical struc-<lb/>ture of mature midlatitude cyclones in the Northern Hemisphere, <lb/>J. Atmos. Sci., 69, 725-740, https://doi.org/10.1175/JAS-D-11-<lb/>050.1, 2012. <lb/>Campins, J., Genovés, A., Jansa, A., Guijarro, J. A., and Ramis, <lb/>C.: A catalogue and a classification of surface cyclones for <lb/>the western Mediterranean, Int. J. Climatol., 20, 969-984, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/1097-0088(200007)20:9&lt;969::AID-<lb/>JOC519&gt;3.0.CO;2-4, 2000. <lb/>Campins, J., Genovés, A., Picornell, M. A., and Jansà, A.: Clima-<lb/>tology of Mediterranean cyclones using the ERA-40 dataset, Int. <lb/>J. Climatol., 31, 1596-1614, https://doi.org/10.1002/joc.2183, <lb/>2011. <lb/>Catto, J. L.: Extratropical cyclone classification and its <lb/>use in climate studies, Rev. Geophys., 54, 486-520, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/2016RG000519, 2016. <lb/>Catto, J. L.: A New Method to Objectively Classify Extra-<lb/>tropical Cyclones for Climate Studies: Testing in the <lb/>Southwest Pacific Region, J. Climate, 31, 4683-4704, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1175/JCLI-D-17-0746.1, 2018. <lb/>Cavicchia, L., von Storch, H., and Gualdi, S.: Mediterranean <lb/>tropical-like cyclones in present and future climate, J. <lb/>Climate, 27, 7493-7501, https://doi.org/10.1175/JCLI-D-14-<lb/>00339.1, 2014a. <lb/>Cavicchia, L., von Storch, H., and Gualdi, S.: A long-term <lb/>climatology of medicanes, Clim. Dynam., 43, 1183-1195, <lb/>https://rdcu.be/dbIRr, 2014b. <lb/>Chaboureau, J. P., Pantillon, F., Lambert, D., Richard, E., <lb/>and Claud, C.: Tropical transition of a Mediterranean storm <lb/>by jet crossing, Q. J. Roy. Meteor. Soc., 138, 596-611, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/qj.960, 2012. <lb/>Cioni, G., Malguzzi, P., and Buzzi, A.: Thermal structure <lb/>and dynamical precursor of a Mediterranean tropical-<lb/>like cyclone, Q. J. Roy. Meteor. Soc., 142, 1757-1766, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/qj.2773, 2016. <lb/>Cioni, G., Cerrai, D., and Klocke, D.: Investigating the predictabil-<lb/>ity of a Mediterranean tropical-like cyclone using a storm-<lb/>resolving model, Q. J. Roy. Meteor. Soc., 144, 1598-1610, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/qj.3322, 2018. <lb/>Comellas Prat, A., Federico, S., Torcasio, R. C., D&apos;Adderio, L. <lb/>P., Dietrich, S., and Panegrossi, G.: Evaluation of the sensitiv-<lb/>ity of medicane ianos to model microphysics and initial con-<lb/>ditions using satellite measurements, Remote Sens., 13, 4984, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/rs13244984, 2021. <lb/>Cook, K. H. and Vizy, E. K.: Contemporary climate change of the <lb/>African monsoon systems, Current Climate Change Reports, 5, <lb/>145-159, https://rdcu.be/dbJxy (last access: 21 January 2024), <lb/>2019. <lb/>D&apos;Adderio, L. P., Casella, D., Dietrich, S., Sanò, P., and <lb/>Panegrossi, G.: GPM-CO observations of Medicane Ianos: <lb/>Comparative analysis of precipitation structure between de-<lb/>velopment and mature phase, Atmos. Res., 273, 106174, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.atmosres.2022.106174, 2022. <lb/>Dafis, S., Rysman, J. F., Claud, C., and Flaounas, E.: Re-<lb/>mote sensing of deep convection within a tropical-like cy-<lb/>clone over the Mediterranean Sea, Atmos. Sci. Lett., 19, e823, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/asl.823, 2018. <lb/>Dafis, S., Claud, C., Kotroni, V., Lagouvardos, K., and Rysman, <lb/>J. F.: Insights into the convective evolution of Mediterranean <lb/>tropical-like cyclones, Q. J. Roy. Meteor. Soc., 146, 4147-4169, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/qj.3896, 2020. <lb/>Davolio, S., Miglietta, M. M., Moscatello, A., Pacifico, F., <lb/>Buzzi, A., and Rotunno, R.: Numerical forecast and analy-<lb/>sis of a tropical-like cyclone in the Ionian Sea, Nat. Hazards <lb/>Earth Syst. Sci., 9, 551-562, https://doi.org/10.5194/nhess-9-<lb/>551-2009, 2009. <lb/>Dubrovský, M., Hayes, M., Duce, P., Trnka, M., Svoboda, M., and <lb/>Zara, P.: Multi-GCM projections of future drought and climate <lb/>variability indicators for the Mediterranean region, Reg. Environ. <lb/>Change, 14, 1907-1919, https://rdcu.be/dbIPJ, 2014. <lb/>Ernst, <lb/>J. <lb/>A. <lb/>and <lb/>Matson, <lb/>M.: <lb/>A <lb/>Mediter-<lb/>ranean <lb/>tropical <lb/>storm?, <lb/>Weather, <lb/>38, <lb/>332-337, <lb/>https://doi-org.ezproxy.weizmann.ac.il/10.1002/j.1477-<lb/>8696.1983.tb04818.x, 1983. <lb/>Fita, L. and Flaounas, E.: Medicanes as subtropical cyclones: the <lb/>December 2005 case from the perspective of surface pressure <lb/>tendency diagnostics and atmospheric water budget, Q. J. Roy. <lb/>Meteor. Soc., 144, 1028-1044, https://doi.org/10.1002/qj.3273, <lb/>2018. <lb/>Fita, L., Romero, R., Luque, A., Emanuel, K., and Ramis, C.: <lb/>Analysis of the environments of seven Mediterranean tropical-<lb/>like storms using an axisymmetric, nonhydrostatic, cloud re-<lb/>solving model, Nat. Hazards Earth Syst. Sci., 7, 41-56, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/nhess-7-41-2007, 2007. <lb/>Flaounas, E., Raveh-Rubin, S., Wernli, H., Drobinski, P., and <lb/>Bastin, S.: The dynamical structure of intense Mediterranean <lb/>cyclones, Clim. Dynam., 44, 2411-2427, https://rdcu.be/dbJsY, <lb/>2015. <lb/>Flaounas, E., Gray, S. L., and Teubler, F.: A process-based <lb/>anatomy of Mediterranean cyclones: from baroclinic lows to <lb/>tropical-like systems, Weather Clim. Dynam., 2, 255-279, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-2-255-2021, 2021. <lb/>Flaounas, E., Davolio, S., Raveh-Rubin, S., Pantillon, F., Migli-<lb/>etta, M. M., Gaertner, M. A., Hatzaki, M., Homar, V., Khodayar, <lb/>S., Korres, G., Kotroni, V., Kushta, J., Reale, M., and Ricard, <lb/>D.: Mediterranean cyclones: current knowledge and open ques-<lb/>tions on dynamics, prediction, climatology and impacts, Weather <lb/>Clim. Dynam., 3, 173-208, https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-3-173-<lb/>2022, 2022. <lb/>Flaounas, E., Aragão, L., Bernini, L., Dafis, S., Doiteau, B., <lb/>Flocas, H., Gray, S. L., Karwat, A., Kouroutzoglou, J., Li-<lb/>onello, P., Miglietta, M. M., Pantillon, F., Pasquero, C., Pat-<lb/>lakas, P., Picornell, M. Á., Porcù, F., Priestley, M. D. K., Reale, <lb/>M., Roberts, M. J., Saaroni, H., Sandler, D., Scoccimarro, E., <lb/>Sprenger, M., and Ziv, B.: A composite approach to produce <lb/>reference datasets for extratropical cyclone tracks: application <lb/>to Mediterranean cyclones, Weather Clim. Dynam., 4, 639-661, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-4-639-2023, 2023. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <page>159 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>Flocas, H. A.: Diagnostics of cyclogenesis over the Aegean Sea us-<lb/>ing potential vorticity inversion, Meteorol. Atmos. Phys., 73, 25-<lb/>33, https://rdcu.be/dbIS5 (last access: 21 January 2024), 2000. <lb/>Fluck, E. and Raveh-Rubin, S.: Dry air intrusions link Rossby <lb/>wave breaking to large-scale dust storms in Northwest <lb/>Africa: Four extreme cases, Atmos. Res., 286, 106663, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.atmosres.2023.106663, 2023. <lb/>Gaertner, M. A., Jacob, D., Gil, V., Domínguez, M., Padorno, <lb/>E., Sánchez, E., and Castro, M.: Tropical cyclones over the <lb/>Mediterranean Sea in climate change simulations, Geophys. Res. <lb/>Lett., 34, L14711, https://doi.org/10.1029/2007GL029977, 2007. <lb/>Giorgi, F. and Lionello, P.: Climate change projections for the <lb/>Mediterranean region, Global Planet. Change, 63, 90-104, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gloplacha.2007.09.005, 2008. <lb/>Givon, Y., Keller Jr., D., Silverman, V., Pennel, R., Drobinski, P., <lb/>and Raveh-Rubin, S.: Large-scale drivers of the mistral wind: <lb/>link to Rossby wave life cycles and seasonal variability, Weather <lb/>Clim. Dynam., 2, 609-630, https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-2-609-<lb/>2021, 2021. <lb/>Givon, Y.: The Vaia storm from a PV perspective, Dropbox [video], <lb/>https://www.dropbox.com/scl/fi/6s5uw97089a83r6nnp2zi/Vaia_ <lb/>Storm.mp4?rlkey=tzshhuyutd0vgdz151ntza53d&amp;dl=0, 2023. <lb/>Hatzaki, M., Flaounas, E., Davolio, S., Pantillon, F., Patlakas, P., <lb/>Raveh-Rubin, S., Hochman, A., Kushta, J., Khodayar, S., Dafis, <lb/>S., and Liberato, M. L.: MedCyclones: Working Together to-<lb/>ward Understanding Mediterranean Cyclones, B. Am. Mete-<lb/>orol. Soc., 104, E480-E487, https://doi.org/10.1175/BAMS-D-<lb/>22-0280.1, 2023. <lb/>Heitmann, K., Sprenger, M., Binder, H., Wernli, H., and Joos, <lb/>H.: Warm conveyor belt characteristics and impacts along <lb/>the life cycle of extratropical cyclones: Case studies and cli-<lb/>matological analysis based on ERA5, EGUsphere [preprint], <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/egusphere-2023-1092, 2023. <lb/>Henry, A. J., Bjerknes, J., and Solberg, H.: on the life cycle of <lb/>cyclones and the polar front theory of atmospheric circulation, <lb/>Mon. Weather Rev., 50, 468-473, https://doi.org/10.1175/1520-<lb/>0493(1922)50&lt;468:JBAHSO&gt;2.0.CO;2, 1922. <lb/>Hersbach, H., Bell, B., Berrisford, P., Hirahara, S., Horányi, A., <lb/>Muñoz-Sabater, J., Nicolas, J., Peubey, C., Radu, R., Schep-<lb/>ers, D., Simmons, A., Soci, C., Abdallah, S., Abellan, X., Bal-<lb/>samo, G., Bechtold, P., Biavati, G., Bidlot, J., Bonavita, M., <lb/>De Chiara, G., Dahlgren, P., Dee, D., Diamantakis, M., Dra-<lb/>gani, R., Flemming, J., Forbes, R., Fuentes, M., Geer, A., Haim-<lb/>berger, L., Healy, S., Hogan, R., Hólm, E., Janisková, M., Kee-<lb/>ley, S., Laloyaux, P., Lopez, P., Lupu, C., Radnoti, G., de Ros-<lb/>nay, P., Rozum, I., Vamborg, F., Villaume, S., and Thépaut, J. <lb/>N.: The ERA5 global reanalysis, Q. J. Roy. Meteor. Soc., 146, <lb/>1999-2049, https://doi.org/10.1002/qj.3803, 2020. <lb/>Hewson, T. D.: Objective fronts, Meteorol. Appl., 5, 37-65, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1017/S1350482798000553 1998. <lb/>Hochman, A., Marra, F., Messori, G., Pinto, J. G., Raveh-Rubin, S., <lb/>Yosef, Y., and Zittis, G.: Extreme weather and societal impacts <lb/>in the eastern Mediterranean, Earth Syst. Dynam., 13, 749-777, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/esd-13-749-2022, 2022a. <lb/>Hochman, A., Scher, S., Quinting, J., Pinto, J. G., and Mes-<lb/>sori, G.: Dynamics and predictability of cold spells over <lb/>the Eastern Mediterranean, Clim. Dynam., 58, 2047-2064, <lb/>https://rdcu.be/dbINB, 2022b. <lb/>Hofstätter, M., Chimani, B., Lexer, A., and Blöschl, G.: A new <lb/>classification scheme of European cyclone tracks with rele-<lb/>vance to precipitation, Water Resour. Res., 52, 7086-7104, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/2016WR019146, 2016. <lb/>Homar, V., Romero, R., Stensrud, D. J., Ramis, C., and <lb/>Alonso, S.: Numerical diagnosis of a small, quasi-tropi-<lb/>cal cyclone over the western Mediterranean: Dynamical vs. <lb/>boundary factors, Q. J. Roy. Meteor. Soc., 129, 1469-1490, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1256/qj.01.91, 2003. <lb/>Hoskins, B.: Potential vorticity and the PV perspective, Adv. At-<lb/>mos. Sci., 32, 2-9, https://doi.org/10.1007/s00376-014-0007-8, <lb/>2015. <lb/>Johnson, R. H.: Thermal low, Encyclopedia of Atmospheric <lb/>Science, <lb/>2269-2273, <lb/>https://johnson.atmos.colostate.edu/ <lb/>publications/books/Thermal_Low-Johnson.pdf (last access: 21 <lb/>January 2024), 2003. <lb/>Kaskaoutis, D. G., Kambezidis, H. D., Nastos, P. T., <lb/>and Kosmopoulos, P. G.: Study on an intense dust <lb/>storm over Greece, Atmos. Environ., 42, 6884-6896, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.atmosenv.2008.05.017, 2008. <lb/>Kouroutzoglou, J., Flocas, H. A., Keay, K., Simmonds, I., <lb/>and Hatzaki, M.: Climatological aspects of explosive cy-<lb/>clones in the Mediterranean, Int. J. Climatol., 31, 1785-1802, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/joc.2203, 2011. <lb/>Kouroutzoglou, J., Avgoustoglou, E. N., Flocas, H. A., Hatzaki, M., <lb/>Skrimizeas, P., and Keay, K.: Assessment of the role of sea sur-<lb/>face fluxes on eastern Mediterranean explosive cyclogenesis with <lb/>the aid of the limited-area model COSMO GR, Atmos. Res., 208, <lb/>132-147, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.atmosres.2017.10.005, 2018. <lb/>Kouroutzoglou, J., Samos, I., Flocas, H. A., Hatzaki, M., <lb/>Lamaris, C., Mamara, A., and Emmannouil, A.: Anal-<lb/>ysis of the Transition of an Explosive Cyclone to a <lb/>Mediterranean Tropical-like Cyclone, Atmosphere, 12, 1438, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/atmos12111438, 2021. <lb/>Krzyżewska, A. and Dyer, J.: The August 2015 mega-heatwave <lb/>in Poland in the context of past events, Weather, 73, 207-214, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/wea.3244, 2018. <lb/>Lagouvardos, K., Karagiannidis, A., Dafis, S., Kalimeris, A., <lb/>and Kotroni, V.: Ianos -A hurricane in the Mediter-<lb/>ranean, B. Am. Meteorol. Soc., 103, E1621-E1636, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1175/BAMS-D-20-0274.1, 2022. <lb/>Lin, B. D.: The behavior of winter stationary planetary <lb/>waves forced by topography and diabatic heating, J. At-<lb/>mos. Sci., 39, 1206-1226, https://doi.org/10.1175/1520-<lb/>0469(1982)039%3C1206:TBOWSP%3E2.0.CO;2, 1982. <lb/>Lionello, P. and Giorgi, F.: Winter precipitation and cy-<lb/>clones in the Mediterranean region: future climate scenar-<lb/>ios in a regional simulation, Adv. Geosci., 12, 153-158, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/adgeo-12-153-2007, 2007. <lb/>Lionello, P., Bhend, J., Buzzi, A., Della-Marta, P. M., Krichak, <lb/>S. O., Jansa, A., Maheras, P., Sanna, A., Trigo, I. F., and <lb/>Trigo, R.: Cyclones in the Mediterranean region: climatol-<lb/>ogy and effects on the environment, in: Developments in <lb/>Earth and Environmental Sciences, Vol. 4, Elsevier, 325-372, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/S1571-9197(06)80009-1, 2006. <lb/>Lionello, P., Boldrin, U., and Giorgi, F.: Future changes in cyclone <lb/>climatology over Europe as inferred from a regional climate sim-<lb/>ulation, Clim. Dynam., 30, 657-671, https://rdcu.be/dbIO6 (last <lb/>access: 21 January 2024), 2008. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/>Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>160 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>Lionello, P., Abrantes, F., Gacic, M., Planton, S., Trigo, R., and <lb/>Ulbrich, U.: The climate of the Mediterranean region: research <lb/>progress and climate change impacts, Reg. Environ. Change, 14, <lb/>1679-1684, https://rdcu.be/dbIPs (last access: 21 January 2024), <lb/>2014. <lb/>Lionello, P., Trigo, I. F., Gil, V., Liberato, M. L., Nissen, K. M., <lb/>Pinto, J. G., and Ulbrich, U.: Objective climatology of cyclones <lb/>in the Mediterranean region: a consensus view among methods <lb/>with different system identification and tracking criteria, Tellus <lb/>A, 68, 29391, https://doi.org/10.3402/tellusa.v68.29391, 2016. <lb/>Liu, F. and Deng, Y.: Determine the number of unknown targets in <lb/>open world based on elbow method, IEEE T. Fuzzy Syst., 29, <lb/>986-995, https://doi.org/10.1109/TFUZZ.2020.2966182, 2020. <lb/>Liu, Y. and Weisberg, R. H.: A Review of Self-Organizing Map Ap-<lb/>plications in Meteorology and Oceanography&quot; Self Organizing <lb/>Maps -Applications and Novel Algorithm Design, InTech, 253-<lb/>272, https://doi.org/10.5772/13146, 2011. <lb/>Luque, A., Fita, L., Romero, R., and Alonso, S.: Tropical-like <lb/>Mediterranean storms: an analysis from satellite, Proceeding <lb/>2007 Joint EUMETSAT/AMS Conference, Amsterdam, (Països <lb/>Baixos), https://www-cdn.eumetsat.int/files/2020-04/pdf_conf_ <lb/>p50_s8_05_luque_v.pdf (last access: 21 January 2024), 2007. <lb/>Madonna, E., Wernli, H., Joos, H., and Martius, O.: Warm Con-<lb/>veyor Belts in the ERA-Interim Dataset (1979-2010). Part I: Cli-<lb/>matology and Potential Vorticity Evolution, J. Climate, 27, 3-26, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1175/JCLI-D-12-00720.1, 2014. <lb/>Maheras, P., Flocas, H. A., Patrikas, I., and Anagnostopoulou, C.: A <lb/>40 year objective climatology of surface cyclones in the Mediter-<lb/>ranean region. spatial and temporal distribution, Int. J. Clima-<lb/>tol., 21, 109-130, https://doi.org/10.1002/joc.599, 2001. <lb/>Marra, A. C., Federico, S., Montopoli, M., Avolio, E., Baldini, <lb/>L., Casella, D., D&apos;Adderio, L. P., Dietrich, S., Sanò, P., Torca-<lb/>sio, R. C., and Panegrossi, G.: The precipitation structure of the <lb/>Mediterranean tropical-like cyclone Numa: analysis of GPM ob-<lb/>servations and numerical weather prediction model simulations, <lb/>Remote Sens., 11, 1690, https://doi.org/10.3390/rs11141690, <lb/>2019. <lb/>Mattocks, C. and Bleck, R.: Jet streak dynamics and <lb/>geostrophic <lb/>adjustment <lb/>processes <lb/>during <lb/>the <lb/>ini-<lb/>tial <lb/>stages <lb/>of <lb/>lee <lb/>cyclogenesis, <lb/>Mon. <lb/>Weather <lb/>Rev., <lb/>114, <lb/>2033-2056, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1175/1520-<lb/>0493(1986)114%3C2033:JSDAGA%3E2.0.CO;2, 1986. <lb/>McGinley, J.: A diagnosis of Alpine lee cyclogenesis, Mon. <lb/>Weather Rev., 110, 1271-1287, https://doi.org/10.1175/1520-<lb/>0493(1982)110&lt;1271:ADOALC&gt;2.0.CO;2, 1982. <lb/>McTaggart-Cowan, R., Galarneau Jr., T. J., Bosart, L. F., and <lb/>Milbrandt, J. A.: Development and tropical transition of an <lb/>Alpine lee cyclone. Part I: Case analysis and evaluation of <lb/>numerical guidance, Mon. Weather Rev., 138, 2281-2307, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1175/2009MWR3147.1, 2010. <lb/>Miglietta, M. M. and Rotunno, R.: Development mechanisms for <lb/>Mediterranean tropical-like cyclones (medicanes), Q. J. Roy. <lb/>Meteor. Soc., 145, 1444-1460, https://doi.org/10.1002/qj.3503, <lb/>2019. <lb/>Miglietta, M. M., Moscatello, A., Conte, D., Mannarini, G., La-<lb/>corata, G., and Rotunno, R.: Numerical analysis of a Mediter-<lb/>ranean &quot;hurricane&quot; over south-eastern Italy: sensitivity experi-<lb/>ments to sea surface temperature, Atmos. Res., 101, 412-426, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.atmosres.2011.04.006, 2011. <lb/>Miglietta, M. M., Laviola, S., Malvaldi, A., Conte, D., Lev-<lb/>izzani, V., and Price, C.: Analysis of tropical-like cyclones <lb/>over the Mediterranean Sea through a combined modeling <lb/>and satellite approach, Geophys. Res. Lett., 40, 2400-2405, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/grl.50432, 2013. <lb/>Miglietta, M. M., Mastrangelo, D., and Conte, D.: Influence of <lb/>physics parameterization schemes on the simulation of a tropical-<lb/>like cyclone in the Mediterranean Sea, Atmos. Res., 153, 360-<lb/>375, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.atmosres.2014.09.008, 2015. <lb/>Miglietta, M. M., Carnevale, D., Levizzani, V., and Rotunno, R.: <lb/>Role of moist and dry air advection in the development of <lb/>Mediterranean Tropical-Like Cyclones (Medicanes), Q. J. Roy. <lb/>Meteor. Soc., 147, 876-899, https://doi.org/10.1002/qj.3951, <lb/>2021. <lb/>Moscatello, A., Miglietta, M. M., and Rotunno, R.: Nu-<lb/>merical analysis of a Mediterranean &quot;hurricane&quot; over <lb/>south-eastern Italy, Mon. Weather Rev., 136, 4373-4397, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1175/2008MWR2512.1, 2008. <lb/>Mylonas, M., Douvis, K. C., Polychroni, I. D., Politi, N. <lb/>and Nastos ,P.: Analysis of a Mediterranean Tropical-<lb/>Like <lb/>Cyclone.Sensitivity <lb/>to <lb/>WRF Parameterizations <lb/>and Horizontal Resolution, Atmosphere, 10, 425, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/atmos10080425, 2019. <lb/>Nissen, K. M., Leckebusch, G. C., Pinto, J. G., and Ulbrich, U.: <lb/>Mediterranean cyclones and windstorms in a changing climate, <lb/>Reg. Environ. Change, 14, 1873-1890, https://rdcu.be/dbIVh <lb/>(last access: 21 January 2024), 2014. <lb/>Noyelle, R., Ulbrich, U., Becker, N., and Meredith, E. P.: Assessing <lb/>the impact of sea surface temperatures on a simulated medicane <lb/>using ensemble simulations, Nat. Hazards Earth Syst. Sci., 19, <lb/>941-955, https://doi.org/10.5194/nhess-19-941-2019, 2019. <lb/>Portmann, R.: The life cycles of potential vorticity cut-offs, Clima-<lb/>tology, predictability and high impact weather, Doctoral disser-<lb/>tation, ETH Zurich, https://doi.org/10.3929/ethz-b-000466735, <lb/>2020. <lb/>Portmann, R., Sprenger, M., and Wernli, H.: The three-dimensional <lb/>life cycles of potential vorticity cutoffs: a global and selected <lb/>regional climatologies in ERA-Interim (1979-2018), Weather <lb/>Clim. Dynam., 2, 507-534, https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-2-507-<lb/>2021, 2021. <lb/>Prat, A. C., Federico, S., Torcasio, R. C., D&apos;Adderio, L. .P, Di-<lb/>etrich, S., and Panegrossi, G.: Evaluation of the Sensitivity <lb/>of Medicane Ianos to Model Microphysics and Initial Condi-<lb/>tions Using Satellite Measurements, Remote Sens., 13, 4984, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/rs13244984, 2021. <lb/>Pytharoulis, I.: Analysis of a Mediterranean tropical-like cyclone <lb/>and its sensitivity to the sea surface temperatures, Atmos. Res., <lb/>208, 167-179, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.atmosres.2017.08.009, <lb/>2018. <lb/>Pytharoulis, I., Craig, G. C., and Ballard, S. P.: Study of the <lb/>Hurricane-like Mediterranean cyclone of January 1995, Phys. <lb/>Chem. Earth Pt. B, 24, 627-632, https://doi.org/10.1016/S1464-<lb/>1909(99)00056-8 1999. <lb/>Pytharoulis, I., Craig, G. C., and Ballard, S. P.: The hurricane-<lb/>like Mediterranean cyclone of January 1995, Meteorol. Appl., <lb/>7, 261-279, https://doi.org/10.1017/S1350482700001511, 2000. <lb/>Rácz, Z. and Smith, R. K.: The dynamics of heat <lb/>lows, Q. J. Roy. Meteor. Soc., 125, 225-252, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/qj.49712555313, 1999. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <page>161 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>Raveh-Rubin, S. and Flaounas, E.: A dynamical link be-<lb/>tween deep Atlantic extratropical cyclones and intense <lb/>Mediterranean cyclones, Atmos. Sci. Lett., 18, 215-221, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/asl.745, 2017. <lb/>Raveh-Rubin, S. and Wernli, H.: Large-scale wind and precipi-<lb/>tation extremes in the Mediterranean: a climatological analy-<lb/>sis for 1979-2012, Q. J. Roy. Meteor. Soc., 141, 2404-2417, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/qj.2531, 2015. <lb/>Reale, M., Cabos Narvaez, W. D., Cavicchia, L., Conte, D., Cop-<lb/>pola, E., Flaounas, E., Giorgi F., Gualdi S., Hochman S., Li <lb/>L., Lionello P., Podrascanin Z., Salon S., Sacnchez-Gomez E., <lb/>Scoccimarro E., Sein D., and Somot, S.: Future projections of <lb/>Mediterranean cyclone characteristics using the Med-CORDEX <lb/>ensemble of coupled regional climate system models, Clim. <lb/>Dynam., 58, 1-24, https://doi.org/10.1007/s00382-021-06018-x, <lb/>2022. <lb/>Reed, R. J., Kuo, Y. H., Albright, M. D., Gao, K., Guo, Y. R., and <lb/>Huang, W.: Analysis and modelling of a tropical-like cyclone in <lb/>the Mediterranean Sea, Meteorol. Atmos. Phys., 76, 183-202, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s007030170029, 2001. <lb/>Rodwell, M. J., Magnusson, L., Bauer, P., Bechtold, P., Bonavita, <lb/>M., Cardinali, C., Diamantakis, M., Earnshaw, P., Garcia-<lb/>Mendez, A., Isaksen, L., Källén, E., Klocke, D., Lopez, P., <lb/>McNally, T., Persson, A., Prates, F., and Wedi, N.: Char-<lb/>acteristics of occasional poor medium-range weather fore-<lb/>casts for Europe, B. Am. Meteorol. Soc., 94, 1393-1405, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1175/BAMS-D-12-00099.1, 2013. <lb/>Romem, M., Ziv, B., and Saaroni, H.: Scenarios in the devel-<lb/>opment of Mediterranean cyclones, Adv. Geosci., 12, 59-65, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/adgeo-12-59-2007, 2007. <lb/>Rossa, A. M., Wernli, H., and Davies, H. C.: Growth and decay of an <lb/>extra-tropical cyclone&apos;s PV-tower, Meteorol. Atmos. Phys., 73, <lb/>139-156, https://doi.org/10.1007/s007030050070, 2000. <lb/>Rousseau-Rizzi, R., Raveh-Rubin, S., Catto, J., Portal, A., Givon, <lb/>Y., and Martius, O.: A storm-relative climatology of compound <lb/>hazards in Mediterranean cyclones, EGUsphere [preprint], <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/egusphere-2023-2322, 2023. <lb/>Saaroni, H., Halfon, N., Ziv, B., Alpert, P., and Kutiel, H.: <lb/>Links between the rainfall regime in Israel and location and <lb/>intensity of Cyprus lows, Int. J. Climatol., 30, 1014-1025, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/joc.1912, 2010. <lb/>Saaroni, H., Harpaz, T., and Ziv, B.: A new classification algo-<lb/>rithm for daughter cyclone formation with respect to the par-<lb/>ent&apos;s frontal system-application for the Mediterranean Basin, Int. <lb/>J. Climatol., 37, 1050-1065, https://doi.org/10.1002/joc.4759, <lb/>2017. <lb/>Sanders, F. and Gyakum, J. R.: Synoptic-dynamic <lb/>climatology <lb/>of <lb/>the <lb/>&quot;bomb&quot;, <lb/>Mon. <lb/>Weather <lb/>Rev., <lb/>108, <lb/>1589-1606, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1175/1520-<lb/>0493(1980)108%3C1589:SDCOT%3E2.0.CO;2, 1980. <lb/>Sansom, P. G. and Catto, J. L.: Improved objective identification of <lb/>meteorological fronts: a case study with ERA-Interim, Geosci. <lb/>Model Dev. Discuss. [preprint], https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-<lb/>2022-255, in review, 2022. <lb/>Sawalha, I. H. S.: Collaboration in crisis and emergency manage-<lb/>ment: Identifying the gaps in the case of storm &quot;Alexa&quot;, J. Buss. <lb/>Cont. Emergy Plann., 7, 312-323, https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-<lb/>2458-6-285, 2014. <lb/>Shapiro, M. A. and Keyser, D.: Fronts, jet streams <lb/>and the tropopause, Am. Meteorol. Soc., 167-1991, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-944970-33-8_10, 1990. <lb/>Scherrmann, A., Wernli, H., and Flaounas, E.: Origin <lb/>of low-tropospheric potential vorticity in Mediter-<lb/>ranean cyclones, Weather Clim. Dynam., 4, 157-173, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-4-157-2023, 2023. <lb/>Skific, N. and Francis, J.: Self-organizing maps: a powerful tool for <lb/>the atmospheric sciences, Applications of self-organizing maps, <lb/>251-268, https://doi.org/10.5772/54299, 2012. <lb/>Smith, R. B.: A theory of lee cyclogenesis, J. Atmos. <lb/>Sci., <lb/>41, <lb/>1159-1168, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1175/1520-<lb/>0469(1984)041&lt;1159:ATOLC&gt;2.0.CO;2, 1984. <lb/>Sprenger, M., Fragkoulidis, G., Binder, H., Croci-Maspoli, M., <lb/>Graf, P., Grams, C. M., Knippertz, P., Madonna, E., Schemm, <lb/>S., Škerlak, B., and, Wernli, H.: Global climatologies of Eule-<lb/>rian and Lagrangian flow features based on ERA-Interim, B. Am. <lb/>Meteorol. Soc., 98, 1739-1748, https://doi.org/10.1175/BAMS-<lb/>D-15-00299.1, 2017. <lb/>Tafferner, A.: Lee cyclogenesis resulting from the com-<lb/>bined outbreak of cold air and potential vorticity <lb/>against the Alps, Meteorol. Atmos. Phys., 43, 31-47, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/BF01028107, 1990. <lb/>Thorncroft, C. D., Hoskins, B. J., and McIntyre, M. <lb/>E.: <lb/>Two <lb/>paradigms <lb/>of <lb/>baroclinic-wave <lb/>life-cycle <lb/>behaviour, Q. J. Roy. Meteor. Soc., 119, 17-55, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/qj.49711950903, 1993. <lb/>Trigo, I. F., Davies, T. D., and Bigg, G. R.: Objective cli-<lb/>matology of cyclones in the Mediterranean region, J. <lb/>Climate, <lb/>12, <lb/>1685-1696, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1175/1520-<lb/>0442(1999)012&lt;1685:OCOCIT&gt;2.0.CO;2, 1999. <lb/>Trigo, I. F., Davies, T. D., and Bigg, G. R.: Decline in <lb/>Mediterranean rainfall caused by weakening of Mediter-<lb/>ranean cyclones, Geophys. Res. Lett., 27, 2913-2916, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2000GL011526, 2000. <lb/>Trigo, I. F., Bigg, G. R., and Davies, T. D: Climatology <lb/>of cyclogenesis mechanisms in the Mediterranean, Mon. <lb/>Weather Rev., 130, 549-569, https://doi.org/10.1175/1520-<lb/>0493(2002)130%3C0549:COCMIT%3E2.0.CO;2, 2002. <lb/>Tsidulko, M. and Alpert, P.: Synergism of upper-level poten-<lb/>tial vorticity and mountains in Genoa lee cyclogenesis -<lb/>A numerical study, Meteorol. Atmos. Phys., 78, 261-285, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s703-001-8178-8, 2001. <lb/>Tsukijihara, T., Kawamura, R., and Kawano, T: Influential role <lb/>of inter-decadal explosive cyclone activity on the increased <lb/>frequency of winter storm events in Hokkaido, the north-<lb/>ernmost island of Japan, Int. J. Climatol., 39, 1700-1715, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/joc.5910, 2019. <lb/>Tuel, A. and Eltahir, E. A.: Why is the Mediterranean <lb/>a climate change hot spot?, J. Climate, 33, 5829-5843, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1175/JCLI-D-19-0910.1, 2020. <lb/>Walker, S. G. T.: Correlation in seasonal variations of weather, iii: <lb/>On the criterion for the reality of relationships or periodicities, <lb/>Meteorological Office, https://www.rmets.org/sites/default/files/ <lb/>papers/classicindia1.pdf (last access: 27 January 2024), 1914. <lb/>Wernli, H. and M. Sprenger: Identification and ERA-15 Cli-<lb/>matology of Potential Vorticity Streamers and Cutoffs near <lb/>the Extratropical Tropopause, J. Atmos. Sci., 64, 1569-1586, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1175/JAS3912.1, 2007. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 <lb/>Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/></note>

        <page>162 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">Y. Givon et al.: Process-based classification of Mediterranean cyclones <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>Wilks, D.: &quot;The stippling shows statistically significant grid points&quot;: <lb/>How research results are routinely overstated and overinter-<lb/>preted, and what to do about it, B. Am. Meteorol. Soc., 97, 2263-<lb/>2273, https://doi.org/10.1175/BAMS-D-15-00267.1, 2016. <lb/>Zappa, G., Hawcroft, M. K., Shaffrey, L., Black, E., and Brayshaw, <lb/>D. J.: Extratropical cyclones and the projected decline of win-<lb/>ter Mediterranean precipitation in the CMIP5 models, Clim. Dy-<lb/>nam., 45, 1727-1738, https://doi.org/10.1007/s00382-014-2426-<lb/>8, 2015. <lb/>Zimbo, F., Ingemi, D., and Guidi, G.: The Tropical-like Cy-<lb/>clone &quot;Ianos&quot; in September 2020, Meteorology, 1, 29-44, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/meteorology1010004, 2022. <lb/>Zittis, G., Almazroui, M., Alpert, P., Ciais, P., Cramer, <lb/>W., Dahdal, Y., Fnais, M., Francis, D., Hadjinicolaou, P., <lb/>Howari, F., Jrrar, A., Kaskaoutis, D. G., Kulmala, M., La-<lb/>zoglou, G., Mihalopoulos, N., Lin, X., Rudich, Y., Sciare, <lb/>J., Stenchikov, G., Xoplaki, E., and Lelieveld, J.: Cli-<lb/>mate change and weather extremes in the Eastern Mediter-<lb/>ranean and Middle East, Rev. Geophys., 60, e2021RG000762, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1029/2021RG000762, 2022. <lb/>Ziv, B., Harpaz, T., Saaroni, H., and Blender, R.: A new method-<lb/>ology for identifying daughter cyclogenesis: application for <lb/>the Mediterranean Basin, Int. J. Climatol., 35, 3847-3861, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/joc.4250, 2015. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Weather Clim. Dynam., 5, 133-162, 2024 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5194/wcd-5-133-2024 </note>


	</text>

</TEI>