<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Research data in paleobotany: petrographic thin sections fossil wood dataset</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Alexandre Ribas</forename>
          <surname>Semeler</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Margot</forename>
          <surname>Guerra-Sommer</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-05T11:12:59.739Z">11/5/2025 11:12:59 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina (UFSC)</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.5007/1518-2924.2024.e95688</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Alexandre Ribas Semeler, Margot Guerra-Sommer. (2024). Research data in paleobotany: petrographic thin sections fossil wood dataset. Encontros Bibli: revista eletrônica de biblioteconomia e ciência da informação, 29(None), 01-12. DOI: 10.5007/1518-2924.2024.e95688</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-05T11:12:48.470105Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-05T11:12:48.470105Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>Encontros Bibli, Florianópolis, v. 29, 2024: e95688 <lb/>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina. ISSN 1518-2924. <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.5007/1518-2924.2024.e95688/EN <lb/>Data <lb/>Paper <lb/>RESEARCH DATA IN PALEOBOTANY: PETROGRAPHIC <lb/>THIN SECTIONS FOSSIL WOOD DATASET <lb/>Dados de pesquisa em paleobotânica: conjunto de dados petrográficos de lâminas delgadas de <lb/>lenhos fósseis <lb/>Alexandre Ribas Semeler <lb/>Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, Instituto de Geociências <lb/>Porto Alegre, RS, Brazil <lb/>alexandre.semeler@ufrgs.br <lb/>https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9517-4593 <lb/>Margot Guerra Sommer <lb/>Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, <lb/>Porto Alegre, RS, Brazil <lb/>margot.sommer@ufrgs.br <lb/>https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8036-4271 <lb/>A lista completa com informações dos autores está no final do artigo <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Objective: This study was aimed at analyzing and disseminating the fossil wood collection data stored in the thin sections <lb/>of the paleobotany collection of the Department of Paleontology and Stratigraphy of the Institute of Geosciences at the <lb/>Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul. Thin sections of petrified wood are described. Research data used in geosciences <lb/>specifically seek to develop a model for the use of this type of sheet in paleobotany, enabling visualization of its <lb/>representativeness in studies published over 40 years to obtain the anatomical characteristics of fossil woods and define <lb/>their systematic affinities as a specific typology of research data in geosciences. <lb/>Methods: The methodology involved interviewing a paleobotanical specialist and using different techniques applied in <lb/>metric studies to map scientific production in petrified wood. Thus, a dataset of (20) thin slide sections of petrified fossil <lb/>wood used in &quot;Stressing environmental conditions in the &apos;petrified forest&apos; from the Mata Sequence in the Triassic context <lb/>of the Paraná Basin,&quot; a paper published by the Journal of South American Earth Sciences <lb/>(DOI:10.1016/j.jsames.2023.104415), was used. Depending on the methodology, these thin sections petrified wood can <lb/>reveal systematic paleoclimatic signatures based on the anatomical characteristics of the fossil wood. In addition to this <lb/>case study, which represents a collection of more than (2.000) thousand blades of fossil wood and approximately 40 years <lb/>of research, the paleobotanical collection of the department is reused in methodology classes. The collection comprises a <lb/>database created by research physicists that provides information on anatomical features, systematic affinities, <lb/>paleoclimatic conditions, and paleoenvironmental insights. <lb/>Potential for reuse: The reuse, registration, storage, identification, and preservation of thin sections as a type of research <lb/>data used in paleobotany aims to improve the methodology associated with the organization of the physical database of <lb/>the institution. The research data and blades of fossil wood are being digitized. They will soon be available under CC BY <lb/>4.0, according to the sample described in this data paper (DOI Mendeley: 10.17632/b8phfcsync.3). Furthermore, the data <lb/>can be reused in optical and electronic scanning microscopy software. <lb/>KEYWORDS: Petrographic thin sections. Fossil woods. Palaeoxylology. Research data in geosciences. Physical <lb/>database. <lb/>RESUMO <lb/>Objetivo: O estudo visa divulgar e analisar a coleção de lenhos fósseis armazenadas no acervo de lâminas delgadas da <lb/>coleção de paleobotânica do Departamento de Paleontologia e Estratigrafia do Instituto de Geociências da Universidade <lb/>Federal do Rio Grande do Sul. Descrevem-se lâminas delgadas de madeira petrificada, enquanto dados de pesquisa <lb/>utilizados para investigação em Geociências, em específico, busca-se compor um modelo para utilização deste tipo de <lb/>lâmina na paleobotânica o que permite visualizar sua representatividade em estudos publicados durante 40 anos. Assim, <lb/>obter-se-á as características anatômicas de laminas de lenhos fósseis com vistas a definir suas afinidades sistemáticas <lb/>como uma tipologia específica de dados de pesquisa em Geociências. <lb/>Métodos: A metodologia envolve entrevista com um especialista em paleobotânica e a utilização de diferentes técnicas <lb/>aplicadas em estudos métricos para mapear a sua produção científica em lenhos fósseis. Nesse sentido, como exemplo <lb/>Encontros Bibli, Florianópolis, v. 29, 2024: e95688 <lb/>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina. ISSN 1518-2924. <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.5007/1518-2924.2024.e95688/EN <lb/>2 de 12 <lb/>descrevem-se um conjunto de dados de (20) lâminas delgadas de lenhos fósseis petrificados utilizados no paper Stressing <lb/>environmental conditions in the &quot;petrified forest&quot; from the Mata Sequence in the Triassic context of the Paraná Basin <lb/>publicados pelo periódico Journal of South American Earth Sciences, conforme DOI: 10.1016/j.jsames.2023.104415. A <lb/>metodologia de utilização dessas lâminas no paper permite a identificação de assinaturas paleoclimáticas, com base em <lb/>características anatômicas de lenhos fósseis. Além desse estudo de caso, esse data paper serve para representar uma <lb/>coleção de mais de (2.000) mil lâminas de lenhos fósseis, cerca de 40 anos de pesquisa em paleobotânica que é <lb/>reutilizada em aulas de metodologia e compõem uma base de dados de pesquisa que fornece informações sobre <lb/>características anatômicas, afinidades sistemáticas, condições paleoclimáticas e percepções paleoambientais. <lb/>Potencial de reutilização: A reutilização desse conjunto de dados permite o registro, o armazenamento, a identificação <lb/>e a preservação de lâminas delgadas de lenhos fósseis enquanto um tipo de dado de pesquisa em Geociências, também <lb/>objetiva aprimorar a organização de um banco de dados. Esses dados da pesquisa estão sendo digitalizados e em breve <lb/>todos estarão disponíveis sob a licença CC BY 4.0, conforme a amostra descrita nesse data paper. (Mendeley DOI: <lb/>10.17632/b8phfcsync.3) os quais poderão ser reutilizados por softwares de microscopia óptica e de varredura eletrônica. <lb/>PALAVRAS-CHAVE: Lâminas petrográficas. Lenhos fosseis. Paleoxilologia. Dados de pesquisa em geociências. Base <lb/>de dados física. <lb/></front>

        <body>1 PRESENTATION <lb/>Thin sections of petrified wood, which are an object of investigation in geosciences, <lb/>specifically in paleobotany and palaeoxylology, contain the anatomical characteristics of <lb/>fossil wood used for defining systematic affinities (Santos et al. (2022); Santos et al. (2021); <lb/>Pires and Guerra Sommer (2004)), in addition to paleoclimatic and paleoenvironmental <lb/>insights (Santos et al., (2023); Guerra Sommer et al., (2021); Santos et al. (2020); Pires and <lb/>Guerra Sommer, (2011); Pires et al., (2011)). This paper presents twenty (20) thin sections <lb/>of petrified wood discussed by Santos et al. (2023). <lb/>According to Santos et al. (2023), these datasets indicated sedimentary deposits of <lb/>petrified wood that correspond to architectural elements exclusively related to the filling <lb/>processes of river channels. <lb/>Thin sections have been the most crucial physical database for the analysis of the <lb/>anatomical features of petrified woods at different geological intervals, in distinct Brazilian <lb/>sedimentary basins used, used since 1972 by researchers in the field of paleobotany from <lb/>the Department of Paleontology and Stratigraphy at the Federal University of Rio Grande <lb/>do Sul, when the paleobotany section was created at the Institute of Geosciences at the <lb/>Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul. The thin sections are housed within the <lb/>Department&apos;s General Collection to make these physical databases easily accessible. This <lb/>collection represents a database of thin sections used to prepare theses and scientific <lb/>papers on petrified wood from different geological intervals of the Phanerozoic era, which <lb/>have been studied by Guerra Sommer for over 40 years. <lb/>The main aim of the present study was to highlight the collection of thin sections of <lb/>petrified wood as physical research data related to the field of geosciences available in the <lb/>repository of the Institute of Geosciences in the Department of Paleontology and <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Encontros Bibli, Florianópolis, v. 29, 2024: e95688 <lb/>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina. ISSN 1518-2924. <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.5007/1518-2924.2024.e95688/EN <lb/></note>

        <page>3 de 12 <lb/></page>

        <body>Stratigraphy at the Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul, as presented in Santos et al. <lb/>(2023). <lb/>Fossil woods can be used in research with stratigraphic significance as paleoclimatic <lb/>indicators by analyzing wood growth rings, among other types of studies in <lb/>paleobotany (SANTOS, et al., 2023) (SANTOS, et al., 2022) (GUERRA-SOMMER, et al., <lb/>2021) (SANTOS, et al., 2021) (SANTOS, et al., 2020) (DEGANI-SCHMIDT, et al., 2015.) <lb/>(PIRES, et al., 2014) (GUERRA-SOMMER, et al., 2014) (PIRES ; GUERRA-SOMMER, <lb/>2014) (MEDEIROS, ; GUERRA-SOMMER, 2014) (PIRES, et al., 2011) (ARAÚJO, et al., <lb/>2011) (PIRES; GUERRA-SOMMER, 2011) (PIRES, et al., 2001) (BARDOLA, et al., 2009) <lb/>(GUERRA-SOMMER, et <lb/>al., 2007) (ALVES; GUERRA-SOMMER, 2005) (PIRES; <lb/>GUERRA-SOMMER ; SCHERER, 2005) (PIRES; GUERRA-SOMMER, 2004) (GUERRA-<lb/>SOMMER.; SCHERER, 2000) (ALVES; GUERRA-SOMMER, 2000) (GUERRA-SOMMER, <lb/>1976) (GUERRA-SOMMER, 1975) (GUERRA-SOMMER, 1974) (GUERRA-SOMMER, <lb/>1972). <lb/>Therefore, it is important to emphasize that the focus of this study is not on the analysis <lb/>of potential anatomical details preserved by the thin sections of petrified wood, but rather on <lb/>their representativeness as data from paleobotanical research that generate results related <lb/>to taxonomic, paleoclimatic, and paleoenvironmental inferences. <lb/>The additional potential of this dataset is the registration of thin sections with the same <lb/>acronym as the macroscopic-type specimens housed in the paleobotanical collection of the <lb/>Department of Paleontology and Stratigraphy for easy access. Thin sections are stored in <lb/>specific cabinets, mostly in wooden and metal trays (Figure 1). <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Encontros Bibli, Florianópolis, v. 29, 2024: e95688 <lb/>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina. ISSN 1518-2924. <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.5007/1518-2924.2024.e95688/EN <lb/></note>

        <page>4 de 12 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figures 1: Physical database: storage of thin sections in cabinets and thin sections <lb/>stored in metal trays. <lb/>Source: Prepared by the authors (2023). <lb/>The current study was aimed at analyzing and describing twenty (20) thin sections of <lb/>petrified wood registered in the Laboratory of Paleobotany at the Federal University of Rio <lb/>Grande do Sul as a type of research data in paleobotany and palaeoxylology in geosciences, <lb/>involving research conducted since 1972 (when the paleobotany section was established in <lb/>the Department of Paleontology and Stratigraphy at the Federal University of Rio Grande <lb/>do Sul). <lb/>It is imperative that paleobotanists and geoscientists share and learn about the <lb/>registered thin sections of petrified wood to collaborate on reusing these research data. <lb/>Finally, the information in petrified wood is a heterogeneous dataset that makes it possible <lb/>to access and preserve a wide range of research data types. In this context, the research <lb/>will answer different questions to improve the model related to this physical database, such <lb/>as, what are the correct procedures for registering petrified wood thin sections in <lb/>paleobotanical collections? What is the best methodology to house the collection of thin <lb/>sections in the laboratory repository of the Department of Paleontology and Stratigraphy at <lb/>the university? Are there any more suitable identification methods for housing thin sections <lb/>of petrified wood that would enhance consultation efficiency? What is the best method for <lb/>preserving thin sections against degradation processes resulting from suboptimal <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Encontros Bibli, Florianópolis, v. 29, 2024: e95688 <lb/>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina. ISSN 1518-2924. <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.5007/1518-2924.2024.e95688/EN <lb/></note>

        <page>5 de 12 <lb/></page>

        <body>conditions? These questions, in addition to other questions that may arise during data <lb/>interpretation, will be considered in this study. These issues demonstrate the complexity <lb/>involved in obtaining biological data from petrified materials. Identifying these data enabled <lb/>us to characterize the descriptive model that underlies all anatomical research on petrified <lb/>wood. <lb/>2 <lb/>METHODOLOGICAL INSTRUMENTS <lb/>The thin sections represent the physical data of petrified wood. They were prepared <lb/>according to the standard technique for obtaining thin sections, as described in the literature. <lb/>However, distinctively from the grounding of 5my used for petrographic rock slides, the <lb/>average slide thickness for wood analyses is 40 µm. <lb/>The research method was based on an open interview with a paleobotanist, head <lb/>professor, professor emeritus, and the leader of a research group registered in the <lb/>CNPQ/Brazil Directory (ORCID:0000-0002-9517-4593), with more than 40 years of <lb/>experience in the field of palaeobotany and extensive experience in the application of <lb/>different methodologies in fossil wood analysis. <lb/>The spectrum of information provided by this type of biological data has expanded <lb/>over 40 years of paleobotanical analysis on thin sections of petrified wood. In addition to <lb/>systematic results, the following information has been obtained from the surface <lb/>metallization of thin sections with gold or carbon by scanning electron microscopy (SEM) <lb/>(Santos et al., 2023): (i) details of wood attack by microorganisms, (ii) details of the <lb/>fossilization process, and (iii) identification of remnants of organic products produced by the <lb/>plant in response to biological attack. <lb/>For labeling, the following data are recorded on each thin sections: (i) PB (indicates <lb/>Paleobotany Collection), (ii) an acronym that is the same as the macroscopic specimen <lb/>housed in the paleobotanical collection of the Department of Paleontology and Stratigraphy, <lb/>followed by; (iii) a dot and a numeral that indicates the ordering of the thin sections in the <lb/>sequence of slides from the specimen; (iv) the type of section that the thin sections <lb/>represents, mentioned in parentheses: transverse (t), radial (r), or tangential [e.g., PB <lb/>5569.3(t) ]. <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Encontros Bibli, Florianópolis, v. 29, 2024: e95688 <lb/>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina. ISSN 1518-2924. <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.5007/1518-2924.2024.e95688/EN <lb/></note>

        <page>6 de 12 <lb/></page>

        <body>Figure 2: Example of thin sections of fossil Agathoxylon type of wood (Figure 1a). Thin <lb/>sections latewood in each ring with mainly one, rarely two rows, of tracheids (Figure 1b). <lb/>Source: (Santos et al, 2023). <lb/>The thin sections were registered in the Mendeley Data Repository, where the <lb/>following information was detailed: acronym, systematic affinities, procedure, geological <lb/>age, author, stratigraphic unit, date of registration, anatomical section, and observation. The <lb/>methodological procedures for collecting and analyzing data from the slides analyzed in this <lb/>study require a minimum understanding of geosciences and paleobotany. The collected <lb/>data, photographs, and digitized thin sections were published following the Research Data <lb/>Management Plan (PGD) and are available under the CC BY 4.0 license from (DOI: <lb/>10.17632/b8phfcsync.3). <lb/>Figure 1a <lb/>Figure 1b <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Encontros Bibli, Florianópolis, v. 29, 2024: e95688 <lb/>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina. ISSN 1518-2924. <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.5007/1518-2924.2024.e95688/EN <lb/></note>

        <page>7 de 12 <lb/></page>

        <body>1 SPECIFICATION TABLE <lb/>Table 1: Data Specification Table <lb/>Area of knowledge <lb/>B. Earth Science <lb/>Specific subject area <lb/>Paleobotany <lb/>Language <lb/>English <lb/>Data type <lb/>Physical data of petrified wood, Laboratory notes, Thin <lb/>sections <lb/>Data acquisition method Thin sections represent the set of physical data of <lb/>petrified wood. They are prepared according to the <lb/>standard technique for obtaining thin sections of rocks, <lb/>following the usual techniques described in the <lb/>literature. <lb/>Data state <lb/>Primary <lb/>Parameters <lb/>for <lb/>data <lb/>collection <lb/>Thin sections were prepared and recorded as follows: <lb/>1) precise laboratory preparation techniques were <lb/>developed to obtain segments of wood corresponding <lb/>to the transverse, radial, and tangential planes, <lb/>following the standard principles for conventional rock <lb/>sectioning procedures (cutting, sanding, and washing), <lb/>aiming at the anatomical characterization of the wood <lb/>in distinct sections; 2) elaboration of thin sections in <lb/>transverse (t) radial (r) and tangential ( tg) planes, <lb/>following the principles of the standard technique for <lb/>elaboration of petrographic slides, but with an average <lb/>thickness of 40 µm.3) metallization of the slides with <lb/>gold in case of SEM observation; 4) Photomicrographic <lb/>documentation of the thin sections produced in <lb/>different planes: transverse (t) radial (r) and tangential <lb/>( tg). <lb/>Data source location <lb/>Department of Paleontology and Stratigraphy at <lb/>Federal University of Rio Grande do Su, Porto Alegre, <lb/>Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil. <lb/>Data accessibility <lb/>Repository name: Mendeley <lb/>Data identification number: <lb/>DOI: 10.17632/b8phfcsync.3 <lb/>Source: Prepared by the authors (2023). <lb/></body>

        <note place="footnote">Encontros Bibli, Florianópolis, v. 29, 2024: e95688 <lb/>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina. ISSN 1518-2924. <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.5007/1518-2924.2024.e95688/EN <lb/></note>

        <page>8 de 12 <lb/></page>

        <body>2 <lb/>DATASET DESCRIPTION <lb/>The dataset contains (1) one metal tray (Figure 3) in the root directory with (20) thin <lb/>sections of petrified wood digitized in Joint Photographic Experts Group image format (. <lb/>JPG). The thin sections of petrified wood were published by Santos et al. (2023) with the <lb/>authors of the data and technical descriptions for the analysis. The root folder contains the <lb/>images and the file (metal_trays.pdf) table in PDF with explanations of the use of thin <lb/>sections on paper. <lb/>Figure 3: Example of slides of fossil wood in metal trays <lb/>Source: (Santos et al, 2023) <lb/>The thin sections petrified wood slides is a database that digitizes the (20) thin <lb/>sections and collection of thin sections in the repository of the Laboratory of Paleobotanical <lb/>Collections of the Department of Paleontology and Stratigraphy at Federal University of Rio <lb/>Grande do Sul. Physical data, code nº, designation, background, age, formation, author, <lb/>date, section, notes, and images are available in the physical database. The datasets <lb/>produced in this study are available from Mendeley Data, DOI: 10.17632/b8phfcsync.3. <lb/>Finally, <lb/>the <lb/>dataset, <lb/>which <lb/>can <lb/>be <lb/>can <lb/>be <lb/>downloaded <lb/>from <lb/>(DOI:10.17632/b8phfcsync.3), can be reused for studies in palaeobotanical fields, such as <lb/>paleozoic flora of South America, paleophytogeography, phytostratigraphy, <lb/>paleophytoecology, plant taphonomy introduction, and methodologies. <lb/></body>

        <listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Encontros Bibli, Florianópolis, v. 29, 2024: e95688 <lb/>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina. ISSN 1518-2924. <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.5007/1518-2924.2024.e95688/EN <lb/></note>

        <page>9 de 12 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>SANTOS, Â. C. S.; GUERRA-SOMMER, M.; BARBOZA, E. G.; DEGANI-SCHMIDT, I.; <lb/>SIEGLOCH, A. M.; VIEIRA, C. E. L.; VIEIRA, D. T.; BARDOLA, T. P.; SCHULTZ, C. L.. <lb/>Stressing environmental conditions in the petrified forest from the mata sequence in the <lb/>Triassic context of the Paraná Basin. Journal Of South American Earth Sciences, 128, p. <lb/>104415, 2023. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jsames.2023.104415.Disponível em: <lb/>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0895981123002262. Acesso em: 24 <lb/>Jan. 2024. <lb/>SANTOS, Â. C. S.; GUERRA-SOMMER, M.; DEGANI-SCHMIDT, I.; SIEGLOCH, A. M.; <lb/>MENDONÇA, J.; MENDONÇA FILHO, J.; CARVALHO, I. Record of Brachyoxylon <lb/>patagium, a Cheirolepidiaceae wood preserved by gelification in the Aptian Maceió <lb/>Formation, Sergipe-Alagoas Basin, NE Brazil. Journal of South American Earth Sciences <lb/>118, p. 103950, 2022. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jsames.2022.103950. Disponível em: <lb/>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0895981122002395?via%3Dihub. <lb/>Acesso em: 24 Jan. 2024. <lb/>GUERRA-SOMMER, M.; SIEGLOCH, ANELISE MARTA; DEGANI-SCHMIDT, I.; <lb/>SANTOS, SANTOS, Â. C. S; CARVALHO, I.; ANDRADE, J. A.; FREITAS, F. I. Climate <lb/>change during the deposition of the Aptian Santana Formation (Araripe Basin, Brazil): <lb/>Preliminary data based on wood signatures. Journal Of South American Earth Sciences <lb/>111, p. 103462, 2021. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jsames.2021.103462. Disponível em: <lb/>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0895981121003096. Acesso em: 24 <lb/>Jan. 2024. <lb/>SANTOS, Â. C. S; SIEGLOCH, A. M.; GUERRA-SOMMER, M.; DEGANI-SCHMIDT, I.; <lb/>CARVALHO, I. Agathoxylon santanensis sp. nov. from the Aptian Crato fossil Lagerstätte, <lb/>Santana Formation, Araripe Basin, Brazil. Journal Of South American Earth Sciences, <lb/>112, 103633, 2021. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jsames.2021.103633. Disponível em: <lb/>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0895981121004788. Acesso em: 24 <lb/>Jan. 2024. <lb/>SANTOS, Â. C. S.; SIEGLOCH, Â. C.; GUERRA-SOMMER, M.; DEGANI-SCHMIDT, I.; <lb/>SIEGLOCH, A. M.; DE SOUZA, I.; MENDONÇA FILHO, J.G.; OLIVEIRA, J. Fungus-plant <lb/>interactions in Aptian Tropical Equatorial Hot arid belt: White rot in araucarian wood from <lb/>Crato fossil Lagerstätte (Araripe Basin, Brazil). Cretaceous Research, 114, p. 104525, <lb/>2020. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cretres.2020.104525. Disponível em: <lb/>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0195667120302111. Acesso em: 24 <lb/>Jan. 2024. <lb/>DEGANI-SCHMIDT, I.; GUERRA-SOMMER, M; MENDONÇA, J. G.; JASPER, <lb/>A.; CAZZULO-KLEPZIG, M.; IANNUZZI, R. Charcoalified logs are evidence of <lb/>hyperautochthonous/autochthonous wildfire events in a peat-forming environment from the <lb/>Permian in the southern Paraná Basin (Brazil). International Journal of Coal Geology, 146, <lb/>p. 55-67, 2015.DOI: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.coal.2015.05.002. Disponível em: <lb/>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S016651621500110X. Acesso em: 24 <lb/>Jan. 2024. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Encontros Bibli, Florianópolis, v. 29, 2024: e95688 <lb/>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina. ISSN 1518-2924. <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.5007/1518-2924.2024.e95688/EN <lb/></note>

        <page>10 de 12 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>PIRES, E. F. ; GUERRA-SOMMER, M. The Paleoclimatic Record Provided by <lb/>Dendrological Analyses in Early Cretaceous Coniferous Woods from a Paleoerg (Paraná <lb/>Basin, Brazil). In: CARVALHO, I; GARCIA, M. J; LANA, C.; STROHSCHOEN, O. (Org.). <lb/>Paleontologia: Cenários de vida -Paleoclimas. 1 ed. Rio Janeiro: Interciência, 5, p. 77-86, <lb/>2014. <lb/>GUERRA-SOMMER, MARGOT; DEGANI-SCHMIDT, I.; MUSSA, D.; KAVALI, P. S.; <lb/>SHIVANNA, M. Stratigraphic significance of the Solenoid Complex in the Permian of <lb/>Gondwana. Geologia USP. Série Científica, 14, p. 139-148, 2014. DOI: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5327/Z1519-874X201400020008.Disponível em: <lb/>https://www.revistas.usp.br/guspsc/article/view/85371. Acesso em: 24 Jan. 2024. <lb/>PIRES, E. F.; GUERRA-SOMMER, M. Paleoclimatic Inferences From Missão Velha <lb/>Formation (Tithonian/Berriasian, Araripe Basin Brazil) Based On Fossil Wood Analyses. <lb/>In: CARVALHO, I; GARCIA, M. J; LANA, C.; STROHSCHOEN, O. (Org.). Paleontologia: <lb/>Cenários de vida -Paleoclimas. 1 ed. Rio Janeiro: Interciência, 5, p. 77-86, 2014. <lb/>MEDEIROS, M. A.; GUERRA-SOMMER, M. Fósseis como indicadores paleoclimáticos <lb/>para o Eocenomaniano da Bacia de São Luíz-Grajaú. In: CARVALHO, I; GARCIA, M. J; <lb/>LANA, C.; STROHSCHOEN, O. (Org.). Paleontologia: Cenários de vida -Paleoclimas. 1 <lb/>ed. Rio Janeiro: Interciência, 5, p. 77-86, 2014. <lb/>PIRES, E. F.; GUERRA-SOMMER, M.; BARDOLA, T. P.; VEECK, G. P. Padrões de <lb/>crescimento em lenhos gimnospérmicos como indicadores paleoclimáticos na Floresta <lb/>Petrificada do Tocantins Setentrional (Permiano), Bacia do Parnaíba, Tocantins, Brasil. In: <lb/>MORAES, F. (Org.). Contribuições à Geografia Física do Estado do Tocantins. 1 ed. <lb/>Goiânia: Kelps, p. 111-132, 2011. <lb/>ARAÚJO, K. C. O.; GUERRA-SOMMER, M.; MEDEIROS, M. A. A.; GIRNOS, E. <lb/>C.; DEGANI-SCHMIDT, I. Lenhos de coníferas do Mesocretáceo do norte do Maranhão, <lb/>Brasil. Revista Brasileira de Paleontologia, 14, p. 29-38, 2011. Disponível em: <lb/>https://www.sbpbrasil.org/revista/edicoes/14_1/Artigo%203%20-<lb/>%20(COLORIDO)%20Araujo%20et%20al.pdf. Acesso em: 24 Jan. 2024. <lb/>PIRES, E. F.; GUERRA-SOMMER, M. Growth ring analysis of fossil coniferous woods <lb/>from the Early Cretaceous of the Araripe Basin (Brazil). Anais da Academia Brasileira de <lb/>Ciências (Impresso), version 83, p. 409-423, 2011. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1590/S0001-<lb/>37652011005000005. Disponível em: <lb/>https://www.scielo.br/j/aabc/a/WHwhxJHSVzKcvmy359cRwpb/?lang=en. Acesso em: 24 <lb/>Jan. 2024. <lb/>PIRES, E. F.; GUERRA-SOMMER, M.; SCHERER, C. M. S.; SANTOS, A. R.; CARDOSO, <lb/>E. Early Cretaceous coniferous wood assemblage from a paleoclimate (Botucatu et al., <lb/>Brazil): Dendrological parameters and their relationship to paleoclimatic data. Journal Of <lb/>South American Earth Sciences 32, p. 96-109, 2001. DOI: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jsames.2011.04.001. Disponível em: <lb/>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S089598111100054X. Acesso em: 24 <lb/>Jan. 2024. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Encontros Bibli, Florianópolis, v. 29, 2024: e95688 <lb/>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina. ISSN 1518-2924. <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.5007/1518-2924.2024.e95688/EN <lb/></note>

        <page>11 de 12 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>BARDOLA, T. P.; DEGANI-SCHMIDT, I.; GUERRA-SOMMER, M.; SCHULTZ, C. L. <lb/>Lenhos de Ginkgophyta em florestas petrificadas no Triássico Superior sul-rio-grandense, <lb/>Brasil. Revista Brasileira de Paleontologia, 12, p. 139-148, 2009. Disponível em: <lb/>https://www.sbpbrasil.org/revista/edicoes/12_2/Artigo%204%20-<lb/>%20Bardola%20et%20al.pdf. Acesso em: 24 Jan. 2024. <lb/>GUERRA-SOMMER, M.; PIRES, E. F.; ALVES, L. S. R. CAZZULO-KLEPZIG, M. Análises <lb/>Dendroclimatologicas No Gonduana Sul Brasileiro. In: IANNUZZI, R.; FRANTZ, J. C. <lb/>(Org.). 50 Anos de Geologia. Instituto de Geociências. Contribuições. 1 ed.Porto Alegre: <lb/>Editora Comunicação e Identidade, 1, p. 249-263, 2007. <lb/>ALVES, L. S. R.; GUERRA-SOMMER, M. Growth rings in fossil woods and paleoclimates <lb/>in applied stratigraphy. In: KOUTSOUKOS, E. (Org.). Applied Stratigraphy. 1st ed. New <lb/>York: Springer, 23, p. 181-193, 2005. <lb/>PIRES, E. F.; GUERRA-SOMMER, M.; SCHERER, C. Late Triassic climate in the <lb/>southernmost Paraná Basin (Brazil): evidence from dendrochronological data. Journal Of <lb/>South American Earth Sciences, Columbia -South Carolina, 18 (2), p. 213-221, 2005. <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jsames.2004.10.004. Disponível em: <lb/>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0895981104001361. Acesso em: 24 <lb/>Jan. 2024. <lb/>PIRES, E. F.; GUERRA-SOMMER, M. Sommerxylon spirals from the Upper Triassic in the <lb/>southernmost Paraná Basin (Brazil): a new taxon with taxacean affinity. Anais da <lb/>Academia Brasileira de Ciências, Rio de Janeiro, 76(03), p. 595-609, 2004. <lb/>ALVES, L. S. R.; GUERRA-SOMMER, M. Inferências Tafonômicas para um fragmento de <lb/>lenho da Formação Irati, Permiano superior, da bacia do Paraná, RS, Brasil. Revista <lb/>Universidade Guarulhos, São Paulo, 1(5), p. 49-53, 2000. <lb/>GUERRA-SOMMER, M.; SCHERER, C. Middle-Late Triassic Petrified Forests from mata <lb/>sandstone at Rio Grande do Sul State, BR: a preliminary geological, taphonomic and <lb/>biostratigraphic setting. Revista Universidade Guarulhos, Guarulhos, 5, p. 117-120, 2000. <lb/>GUERRA-SOMMER, M. Vertebraria (Royle) Schopf (1965). Un Genre Présent Dans La <lb/>Formation Irati du Rio Grande do Sul (Brésil). In: 101 Congrés National Des Societés <lb/>Savantes, 1976, Lille. Actes du 101 Congrès national des societés savantes, 1976. p. 51-<lb/>68, 1976. <lb/>GUERRA-SOMMER, M. Presença do Gênero Polysolenoxylon Formação Irati, do Rio <lb/>Grande do Sul, Brasil. In: I Congresso Argentino de Paleontologia y Bioestratigrafia, 1975, <lb/>Tucumán. ACTAS I congresso Argentino de Paleontologia y Bioestratigrafia, 1. p. 371-400, <lb/>1975. <lb/>GUERRA-SOMMER, M. Uma Nova Madeira Petrificada na Formação Irati do Rio Grande <lb/>do Sul. Ameghiniana, Argentina, XIII, (3-4), p. 254-267, 1974. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="footnote">Encontros Bibli, Florianópolis, v. 29, 2024: e95688 <lb/>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina. ISSN 1518-2924. <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.5007/1518-2924.2024.e95688/EN <lb/></note>

        <page>12 de 12 <lb/></page>

        <listBibl>GUERRA-SOMMER, M. Damudoxylon (Maheshwari), 1972, Un Gênero Ocorrente no <lb/>Gondwana do Brasil. Pesquisas em Geociências, 7, p. 131-144, 1972. DOI: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.22456/1807-9806.21824.Disponível em: <lb/>https://seer.ufrgs.br/PesquisasemGeociencias/article/view/21824. Acesso em: 24 Jan. <lb/>2024. <lb/></listBibl>

        <div type="annex">NOTAS <lb/></div>

        <div type="contribution">CONTRIBUIÇÃO DE AUTORIA <lb/>Concepção e elaboração do manuscrito: Guerra-somer, M; Semeler, A. R., <lb/>Coleta de dados: Guerra-somer, M; Semeler, A. R., <lb/>Análise de dados: Guerra-somer, M; Semeler, A. R., <lb/>Discussão dos resultados: Guerra-somer, M; Semeler, A. <lb/>Revisão e aprovação: Guerra-somer, M; Semeler, A. R., <lb/>Caso necessário veja outros papéis em: https://credit.niso.org <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">CONJUNTO DE DADOS DE PESQUISA <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">FINANCIAMENTO <lb/>Não se aplica. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">CONSENTIMENTO DE USO DE IMAGEM <lb/>Não se aplica. <lb/>APROVAÇÃO DE COMITÊ DE ÉTICA EM PESQUISA <lb/>Não se aplica. <lb/></div>

        <div type="conflict">CONFLITO DE INTERESSES <lb/>Informar conflitos de interesse: financeiros, pessoais, entre possíveis revisores e editores, e/ou possíveis vieses temáticos. <lb/>Se <lb/>não <lb/>houver, <lb/>mencionar: <lb/>Não <lb/>se <lb/>aplica. <lb/>Para <lb/>mais <lb/>informações: <lb/>https://www.abecbrasil.org.br/arquivos/whitepaper_CSE.pdf <lb/></div>

        <front>LICENÇA DE USO -uso exclusivo da revista <lb/>Os autores cedem à Encontros Bibli os direitos exclusivos de primeira publicação, com o trabalho simultaneamente <lb/>licenciado sob a Licença Creative Commons Attribution (CC BY) 4.0 International. Estra licença permite que terceiros <lb/>remixem, adaptem e criem a partir do trabalho publicado, atribuindo o devido crédito de autoria e publicação inicial neste <lb/>periódico. Os autores têm autorização para assumir contratos adicionais separadamente, para distribuição não exclusiva <lb/>da versão do trabalho publicada neste periódico (ex.: publicar em repositório institucional, em site pessoal, publicar uma <lb/>tradução, ou como capítulo de livro), com reconhecimento de autoria e publicação inicial neste periódico. <lb/>PUBLISHER <lb/>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina. Programa de Pós-graduação em Ciência da Informação. Publicação no Portal <lb/>de Periódicos UFSC. As ideias expressadas neste artigo são de responsabilidade de seus autores, não representando, <lb/>necessariamente, a opinião dos editores ou da universidade. <lb/>EDITORES <lb/>Edgar Bisset Alvarez, Ana Clara Cândido, Patrícia Neubert, Genilson Geraldo, Jônatas Edison da Silva, <lb/>Mayara Madeira Trevisol. <lb/>HISTÓRICO <lb/>Recebido em: 09-09-2023 -Aprovado em: 29-01-2024 -Publicado em: 23-02-2024 </front>


	</text>

</TEI>