<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Severe Corrosive Injury Secondary to Chlorine Bleach Ingestion: A Case Report</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Yonghoon</forename>
          <surname>Choi</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-06T11:18:04.529Z">11/6/2025 11:18:04 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>Korean College of Helicobacter and Upper Gastrointestinal Research</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.7704/kjhugr.2024.0055</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Yonghoon Choi. (2024). Severe Corrosive Injury Secondary to Chlorine Bleach Ingestion: A Case Report. The Korean Journal of Helicobacter and Upper Gastrointestinal Research, 24(4), 365-369. DOI: 10.7704/kjhugr.2024.0055</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-06T11:17:53.733606Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-06T11:17:53.733606Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>86 Copyright © 2024 Korean College of Helicobacter and Upper Gastrointestinal Research <lb/></front>

        <body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Gastric adenocarcinoma with enteroblastic differentiation <lb/>(GAED), also known as clear cell gastric carcinoma, is rare, and <lb/>its clinicopathological characteristics are not well known. 1,2 To <lb/>summarize the results of the studies so far, GAED is known to <lb/>be associated with the production of alpha-fetoprotein (AFP) <lb/>in the blood and tissue; 3 however, not all GAEDs are positive <lb/>for AFP and connected to sal-like protein 4 (SALL4) and glypi-<lb/>can 3, the fetal gastrointestinal markers. 3 Clinically, it exhib-<lb/>its aggressive characteristics compared to conventional gastric <lb/>adenocarcinoma (CGA), which has a higher risk of lymphatic <lb/>invasion 4 and liver metastasis. 5 Herein, we reported a case of <lb/>GAED with rapid recurrence and progression after radical <lb/>resection. <lb/>CASE REPORT <lb/>A 55-year-old male patient with a history of cerebral infarc-<lb/>tion (13 years prior to the diagnosis of gastric cancer [GC]), hy-<lb/>pertension, and dyslipidemia was referred from a local clinic <lb/>because of a suspected malignant lesion detected on screen-<lb/></body>

        <front>CASE REPORT <lb/>KJHUGR <lb/>pISSN 1738-3331 / eISSN 2671-826X https://doi.org/10.7704/kjhugr.2024.0007 Korean J Helicobacter Up Gastrointest Res 2024;24(1):86-90 <lb/>https://www.helicojournal.org <lb/>Received January 17, 2024 <lb/>Revised <lb/>February 9, 2024 <lb/>Accepted February 10, 2024 <lb/>Corresponding author <lb/>Yonghoon Choi, MD <lb/>Department of Internal Medicine, <lb/>Seoul National University <lb/>Bundang Hospital, <lb/>82 Gumi-ro 173beon-gil, Bundang-gu, <lb/>Seongnam 13620, Korea <lb/>E-mail: 89796@snubh.org <lb/>Availability of Data and Material <lb/>The datasets generated or analyzed <lb/>during the study are available from the <lb/>corresponding author upon reasonable <lb/>request. <lb/>Conflicts of Interest <lb/>Yonghoon Choi, a contributing editor of <lb/>the Korean Journal of Helicobacter and <lb/>Upper Gastrointestinal Research, was not <lb/>involved in the editorial evaluation or <lb/>decision to publish this article. <lb/>Funding Statement <lb/>None <lb/>Acknowledgements <lb/>None <lb/>This is an Open Access article distributed <lb/>under the terms of the Creative Commons <lb/>Attribution Non-Commercial License <lb/>(https://creativecommons.org/licenses/ <lb/>by-nc/4.0) which permits unrestricted <lb/>non-commercial use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the <lb/>original work is properly cited. <lb/>Gastric Cancer Showing Rapid Recurrence <lb/>and Progression: A Case of Gastric <lb/>Adenocarcinoma With Enteroblastic <lb/>Differentiation <lb/>Yonghoon Choi <lb/>Department of Internal Medicine, Seoul National University Bundang Hospital, Seongnam, Korea <lb/>Gastric adenocarcinoma with enteroblastic differentiation (GAED) is rare and its clinicopatho-<lb/>logical characteristics are not well documented. However, reports indicate that it exhibits more <lb/>aggressive characteristics, including lymph node metastasis or liver metastasis, than a conven-<lb/>tional gastric adenocarcinoma. Herein, we report a case of GAED with rapid recurrence and <lb/>disease progression. A 55-year-old male, diagnosed with gastric cancer (GC), demonstrated <lb/>initial endoscopic findings suggestive of advanced GC. He underwent curative resection since <lb/>there was no evidence of lymph node or distant metastases. The disease was reported as an <lb/>early GC that was confined to the submucosal layer, without evidence of lymph node metasta-<lb/>sis in the final pathological results. However, six months after surgery, multiple hepatic metasta-<lb/>ses were found during abdominal computed tomography; the pathological results were consis-<lb/>tent with metastasis from the GC. Immunohistochemistry of the primary carcinoma pathological <lb/>specimens showed positive results for alpha-fetoprotein and sal-like protein 4, suggesting en-<lb/>teroblastic differentiation, which is thought to be associated with rapid recurrence and disease <lb/>progression. <lb/>Keywords Gastric cancer; Enteroblastic differentiation; Alpha-fetoprotein; Prognosis. <lb/></front>

        <note place="headnote">A Case of Gastric Adenocarcinoma With Enteroblastic Differentiation <lb/>Yonghoon Choi <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.7704/kjhugr.2024.0007 </note>

        <page>87 <lb/></page>

        <body>ing upper endoscopy. Endoscopically, a mass lesion approxi-<lb/>mately 5 cm in size with central ulceration and thickening of <lb/>the surrounding mucosal folds was observed on the anterior <lb/>wall of the midbody, which was grossly consistent with Bor-<lb/>rmann type III advanced gastric cancer (AGC) (Fig. 1). Ab-<lb/>dominal computed tomography (CT) showed thickening of <lb/>the stomach wall without enlarged lymph nodes or distant <lb/>metastasis (Fig. 2); therefore, the patient was clinically diag-<lb/>nosed with resectable AGC (cT2-3, N0, M0). Other preopera-<lb/>tive evaluations, including laboratory tests, were within nor-<lb/>mal ranges. <lb/>Surgical treatment was decided based on the above findings, <lb/>and laparoscopy-assisted total gastrectomy with Roux-en-Y <lb/>reconstruction was performed one month after the diagnosis. <lb/>The operation and postoperative recovery processes were as <lb/>usual, and the patient was discharged one week after surgery. <lb/>The pathology report revealed moderately differentiated gas-<lb/>tric adenocarcinoma that was 7.6×5.4×1.5 cm in size, which <lb/>corresponded to the intestinal type in the Lauren classifica-<lb/>tion. The final staging was early gastric cancer (EGC) (pT1b, <lb/>N0, stage IA according to the American Joint Committee on <lb/>Cancer 8th Edition 6 ) since the tumor invaded the submucosa <lb/>and corresponded to T1b (depth from the mucularis mucosa <lb/>2000 μm), and there were no lymph node metastasis (Fig. 3). <lb/>The follow-up was performed without further treatment. <lb/>During follow-up, multiple hepatic metastases were observed <lb/>on abdominal CT performed six months after surgery (Fig. 4A <lb/>and B). Positron tomography (PET) (Fig. 4C and D) scan and <lb/>percutaneous biopsy for metastatic lesions of the liver were <lb/>performed for the possibility of metastasis from other organs. <lb/>Histological finding was consistent with hepatic metastasis, <lb/>not originated from the liver (Fig. 5A), and PET scan was neg-<lb/>ative for other suspected primary lesions. A thorough and de-<lb/>tailed pathologic review of the initial surgical specimen found <lb/>Fig. 1. Initial esophagogastroduodenoscopy. The lesion, a mass approximately 5 cm in size, with central ulceration and thickening of the sur-<lb/>rounding mucosal folds on the anterior wall of the midbody. <lb/>Fig. 2. Initial abdomen-pelvis CT. Wall-thickening lesions of T2 or T3 were observed on CT scan (red circles), and no lymph node metastasis <lb/>or distant metastasis was found. CT, computed tomography. <lb/></body>

        <page>88</page>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.7704/kjhugr.2024.0007 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">KJHUGR <lb/></note>

        <body>a small portion of high-grade changes in the nucleus with a <lb/>clear cytoplasm suggesting enteroblastic differentiation simi-<lb/>lar to histologic finding of liver metastasis, which was not found <lb/>in the initial representative section of the lesion (Fig. 5B). Ad-<lb/>ditionally, immunohistochemistry performed on pathological <lb/>specimens of the primary carcinoma showed positive results <lb/>for SALL4 and AFP, suggesting GAED (Fig. 5C and D). The <lb/>staining for glypican 3 was negative (Fig. 5E). <lb/>The patient died of disease progression during palliative che-<lb/>motherapy approximately 14 months after diagnosis with re-<lb/>currence of GAED and hepatic metastases. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>Histologically, GAED, hepatoid adenocarcinoma (HAC), <lb/>and papillary adenocarcinoma are representative histologic <lb/>subtypes of gastric adenocarcinoma with clear cells. 7 Among <lb/>them, GAED and HAC shows variable expression of oncofe-<lb/>Fig. 3. Initial histologic findings. A: Cross section of the surgical specimen. B: Tumor infiltration to the submucosal layer was confirmed (H&amp;E, <lb/>×10). C: Tubulopapillary growth pattern was mainly observed, and the tumor was initially diagnosed as tubuloadenocarcinoma with moderate <lb/>differentiation (H&amp;E, ×200). H&amp;E, hematoxylin and eosin. <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>Fig. 4. Abdomen-pelvis CT and PET-CT at the 6th month of follow-up. Multiple hepatic metastases (red arrows) were found on CT scan (A and B) <lb/>and PET-CT scan six months after surgery (C and D). CT, computed tomography; PET, positron-emission tomography. <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">A Case of Gastric Adenocarcinoma With Enteroblastic Differentiation <lb/>Yonghoon Choi <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.7704/kjhugr.2024.0007 </note>

        <page>89 <lb/></page>

        <body>tal proteins, while papillary adenocarcinoma is characterized <lb/>and easily recognized by well-formed papillae. 7 According to <lb/>a Japanese study, GAED is less frequent than CGA, account-<lb/>ing for approximately 2.2% of all GCs, 1 and there are few large-<lb/>scale studies on GAED; therefore, its clinicopathological char-<lb/>acteristics are not well understood. 2 In GAED has <lb/>a primitive intestine-like structure, histologically composed of <lb/>cuboidal or columnar cells with a transparent cytoplasm. 8,9 <lb/>GAED is also known to be associated with the production of <lb/>AFP in the blood and tumor tissues and is associated with SALL4 <lb/>and glypican 3, which are fetal gastrointestinal markers. Mu-<lb/>rakami et al. 3 have summarized GAED as an &quot;adenocarcino-<lb/>ma composed of cells resembling the fetal gastrointestinal epi-<lb/>thelium, with a pale cytoplasm, with immunopositivity for AFP, <lb/>glypican 3, or SALL4.&quot; However, not all GAEDs are positive <lb/>for AFP, since there are reports of AFP-negative GAEDs. 2,10 <lb/>Whether GAED develops from CGA or occurs sporadically <lb/>has not been clearly established. 11 Recent studies have shown <lb/>that SALL4 staining can diagnose GAED more sensitively than <lb/>AFP; 12 the positive rate of AFP was 45% (13/29), whereas that <lb/>of SALL4 was 72% (20/29) in a recent Japanese study compar-<lb/>ing the two fetal gastrointestinal markers. 3 In addition, glypi-<lb/>can 3 expression has been reported as a useful marker for the <lb/>diagnosis of GAED. 3 <lb/>Clinically, GAED is associated with rapid progression and <lb/>poor prognosis, 5,13 particularly with common lymphovascular <lb/>invasion. Previous studies in Japan reported that 40% of early <lb/>lesions and 84% of advanced lesions were accompanied by <lb/>lymphatic invasion. 4 Hepatic metastasis is also known to be <lb/>common in GAED as compared to CGA; there are reports of <lb/>more than 30% of GAEDs that are accompanied by hepatic me-<lb/>tastasis at diagnosis. 3,5 There are few studies on the prognosis of <lb/>GAED in Korea; however, a study in 2019 reported that GAED <lb/>showed a better prognosis than previously known, whereas <lb/>HAC showed higher hepatic metastasis and recurrence rates. 7 <lb/>They also reported that HAC showed characteristics distinct <lb/>from GAED, including aggressive features and diffuse and <lb/>strong expression of all oncofetal proteins. 7 These findings sug-<lb/>gested the need for further large-scale studies on the clinical <lb/>features and prognosis of GAED in Korea. <lb/>There are case reports of GAEDs treated with endoscopic <lb/>submucosal dissection (ESD) in Japan. 14,15 In these cases, there <lb/>Fig. 5. Histologic findings at the 6th month of follow-up. Percutaneous biopsy specimen of hepatic lesions. A: Biopsy specimen of the hepatic <lb/>lesions showed adenocarcinoma, compatible for metastasis from the stomach (H&amp;E, ×100). B: Some portions of the surgical specimen <lb/>showed focal high grade changes in the nucleus with a clear cytoplasm (red circle), which suggested enteroblastic differentiation (H&amp;E, ×100). <lb/>The surgical specimen showed focal AFP (C) and SALL4 (D) expression, while the stain for glypican 3 (E) was negative (Immunohistochemis-<lb/>try, ×100). H&amp;E, hematoxylin and eosin; AFP, alpha-fetoprotein; SALL4, sal-like protein 4. <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/></body>

        <page>90</page>

        <note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.7704/kjhugr.2024.0007 <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">KJHUGR <lb/></note>

        <body>was no specific feature in distinguishing GAED from CGA on <lb/>endoscopy, narrow-band imaging, and endoscopic ultrasound, <lb/>and no reported long-term follow-up results for more than a <lb/>year. Therefore, special care should be taken when selecting <lb/>ESD for the treatment of GAED, considering that previous <lb/>studies have reported a high possibility of lymphovascular in-<lb/>vasion or that this case observed rapid recurrence with exten-<lb/>sive hepatic metastasis after radical resection. In addition, close <lb/>follow-up for recurrence and metastasis is required if GAED <lb/>is to be diagnosed after ESD. <lb/>This study had some limitations. First, serum AFP was not <lb/>tested because AFP is not routinely tested in GC, and AFP-<lb/>producing GC was not suspected at the time of initial diagno-<lb/>sis. Not all GAEDs produce AFP; however, in this case, addi-<lb/>tional staining for AFP in the pathological specimen of the <lb/>primary carcinoma was positive. Therefore, it is thought that <lb/>the possibility of GAED could have been predicted earlier if <lb/>serum AFP had been tested at the time of the initial diagno-<lb/>sis of GC. In addition, only a part of the tumor tissue was pos-<lb/>itive for AFP and SALL4 staining, which was presumed to be <lb/>due to technical problems, such as tissue fixation. <lb/>In conclusion, GAED has a high possibility of lymphovas-<lb/>cular invasion and hepatic metastasis, showing rapid progres-<lb/>sion and poor prognosis; therefore, we reported a case in which <lb/>care should be taken in the treatment and follow-up of GAED. <lb/></body>

        <front>ORCID iD <lb/>Yonghoon Choi <lb/>https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1331-969X <lb/></front>

        <div type="annex">Ethics Statement <lb/>This study was reviewed and approved by the Institutional Review Board <lb/>(IRB) of The Seoul National University Bundang Hospital (B-2402-880-<lb/>701). Informed consent was waived by the IRB. <lb/></div>

        <listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Yao T, Akazawa Y, Murakami T, Saito T. [HAC (hepatoidadenocar-<lb/>cinoma) and ACED (adenocarcinoma with enteroblastic differentia-<lb/>tion)]. Stomach Intest (Tokyo) 2018;53:746-751. Japanese <lb/>2. Govender D, Ramdial PK, Clarke B, Chetty R. Clear cell (glycogen-<lb/>rich) gastric adenocarcinoma. Ann Diagn Pathol 2004;8:69-73. <lb/>3. Murakami T, Yao T, Mitomi H, et al. Clinicopathologic and immu-<lb/>nohistochemical characteristics of gastric adenocarcinoma with en-<lb/>teroblastic differentiation: a study of 29 cases. Gastric Cancer 2016; <lb/>19:498-507. <lb/>4. Ushiku T, Shinozaki A, Shibahara J, et al. SALL4 represents fetal gut <lb/>differentiation of gastric cancer, and is diagnostically useful in dis-<lb/>tinguishing hepatoid gastric carcinoma from hepatocellular carcino-<lb/>ma. Am J Surg Pathol 2010;34:533-540. <lb/>5. Maehara Y, Emi Y, Baba H, et al. Recurrences and related character-<lb/>istics of gastric cancer. Br J Cancer 1996;74:975-979. <lb/>6. Amin MB, Greene FL, Edge SB, et al. The eighth edition AJCC can-<lb/>cer staging manual: continuing to build a bridge from a population-<lb/>based to a more &quot;personalized&quot; approach to cancer staging. CA Can-<lb/>cer J Clin 2017;67:93-99. <lb/>7. Kwon MJ, Byeon S, Kang SY, Kim KM. Gastric adenocarcinoma with <lb/>enteroblastic differentiation should be differentiated from hepatoid <lb/>adenocarcinoma: a study with emphasis on clear cells and clinico-<lb/>pathologic spectrum. Pathol Res Pract 2019;215:152525. <lb/>8. Kodama T, Kameya T, Hirota T, et al. Production of alpha-fetopro-<lb/>tein, normal serum proteins, and human chorionic gonadotropin in <lb/>stomach cancer: histologic and immunohistochemical analyses of 35 <lb/>cases. Cancer 1981;48:1647-1655. <lb/>9. Kinjo T, Taniguchi H, Kushima R, et al. Histologic and immunohis-<lb/>tochemical analyses of α-fetoprotein--producing cancer of the stom-<lb/>ach. Am J Surg Pathol 2012;36:56-65. <lb/>10. Ghotli ZA, Serra S, Chetty R. Clear cell (glycogen rich) gastric adeno-<lb/>carcinoma: a distinct tubulo-papillary variant with a predilection for <lb/>the cardia/gastro-oesophageal region. Pathology 2007;39:466-469. <lb/>11. Yamada R, Horiguchi SI, Onishi T, Motoi T, Hishima T. Early gastric <lb/>cancer with purely enteroblastic differentiation and no conventional <lb/>adenocarcinoma component. Case Rep Pathol 2018;2018:3620293. <lb/>12. Chang YC, Nagasue N, Kohno H, et al. Clinicopathologic features <lb/>and long-term results of alpha-fetoprotein-producing gastric cancer. <lb/>Am J Gastroenterol 1990;85:1480-1485. <lb/>13. Adachi Y, Tsuchihashi J, Shiraishi N, Yasuda K, Etoh T, Kitano S. <lb/>AFP-producing gastric carcinoma: multivariate analysis of prognos-<lb/>tic factors in 270 patients. Oncology 2003;65:95-101. <lb/>14. Kato T, Hikichi T, Nakamura J, et al. Two cases of gastric adenocarci-<lb/>noma with enteroblastic differentiation resected by endoscopic sub-<lb/>mucosal dissection. Clin J Gastroenterol 2021;14:736-744. <lb/>15. Ikezawa N, Tanaka S, Kaku H, et al. Early gastric cancer involving a <lb/>pure enteroblastic differentiation component that was curatively re-<lb/>sected via endoscopic submucosal dissection. Clin J Gastroenterol <lb/>2020;13:512-516. </listBibl>


	</text>

</TEI>