<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Levels, trends and inequalities in mortality among 5–19-year-olds in Tanzania: Magu Health and Demographic Surveillance Study (1995–2022)</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Sophia</forename>
          <surname>Kagoye</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Eveline T</forename>
          <surname>Konje</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Jim</forename>
          <surname>Todd</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Charles</forename>
          <surname>Mangya</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Mark</forename>
          <surname>Urassa</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Abdoulaye</forename>
          <surname>Maïga</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Milly</forename>
          <surname>Marston</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Ties</forename>
          <surname>Boerma</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-06T10:44:22.741Z">11/6/2025 10:44:22 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      </edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>International Society of Global Health</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.7189/jogh.14.04124</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Sophia Kagoye, Eveline T Konje, Jim Todd, Charles Mangya, Mark Urassa, Abdoulaye Maïga, Milly Marston, Ties Boerma. (2024). Levels, trends and inequalities in mortality among 5–19-year-olds in Tanzania: Magu Health and Demographic Surveillance Study (1995–2022). Journal of Global Health, 14(None), None. DOI: 10.7189/jogh.14.04124</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-06T10:43:57.630798Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-06T10:43:57.630798Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
        <front>PAPERS <lb/>www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04124 <lb/>1 <lb/>2024 • Vol. 14 • 04124 <lb/>Levels, trends and inequalities <lb/>in mortality among 5-19-year-<lb/>olds in Tanzania: Magu Health <lb/>and Demographic Surveillance <lb/>Study (1995-2022) <lb/>Electronic supplementary material: <lb/>The online version of this article contains supplementary material. <lb/>Cite as: Kagoye S, Konje ET, Todd J, Mangya C, Urassa M, Maïga A, Marston M, Boerma T. <lb/>Levels, trends and inequalities in mortality among 5-19-year-olds in Tanzania: Magu Health <lb/>and Demographic Surveillance Study (1995-2022). J Glob Health 2024;14:04124. <lb/>Sophia Kagoye 1,2 , <lb/>Eveline T Konje 2 , <lb/>Jim Todd 3 , <lb/>Charles Mangya 1,2 , <lb/>Mark Urassa 1 , <lb/>Abdoulaye Maïga 4 , <lb/>Milly Marston 3 <lb/>Ties Boerma 5 <lb/>1 <lb/>National Institute for Medical <lb/>Research, Mwanza Research <lb/>Centre, Mwanza, Tanzania <lb/>2 <lb/>Department of Epidemiology and <lb/>Biostatistics, Catholic University <lb/>of Health and Allied Sciences, <lb/>Mwanza Tanzania <lb/>3 <lb/>Department of Population Health, <lb/>London School of Hygiene and <lb/>Tropical Medicine, London, UK <lb/>4 <lb/>Department of International <lb/>Health, Johns Hopkins University <lb/>Bloomberg School of Public <lb/>Health, Baltimore, Maryland, USA <lb/>5 <lb/>Community Health Science, <lb/>University of Manitoba, Winnipeg, <lb/>Manitoba, Canada <lb/>Correspondence to: <lb/>Sophia Kagoye <lb/>National Institute for Medical Research <lb/>-Mwanza Research Centre, Catholic <lb/>University of Health and Allied <lb/>Sciences <lb/>P.O. Box 1462, Isamilo Street, Mwanza <lb/>Tanzania <lb/>sophyadam90@gmail.com <lb/>Background For the past two decades, health priorities in Tanzania have focussed <lb/>on children under-five, leaving behind the older children and adolescents (5-19 <lb/>years). Understanding mortality patterns beyond 5 years is important in bridging <lb/>a healthy gap between childhood to adulthood. We aimed to estimate mortality <lb/>levels, trends, and inequalities among 5-19-year-olds using population data from <lb/>the Magu Health and Demographic Surveillance Site (HDSS) in Tanzania and fur-<lb/>ther compare the population level estimates with global estimates. <lb/>Methods Using data from the Magu HDSS from 1995 to 2022, from Kaplan Meir <lb/>survival probabilities, we computed annual mortality probabilities for ages 5-9, <lb/>10-14 and 15-19 and determined the average annual rate of change in mortality by <lb/>fitting the variance weighted least square regression on annual mortality probabil-<lb/>ities. We compared 5-19 trends with younger children aged 1-4 years. We further <lb/>disaggregated mortality by sex, area of residence and wealth tertiles, and we com-<lb/>puted age-stratified risk ratios with respective 95% confidence intervals (CIs) using <lb/>Cox proportional hazard model to determine inequalities. We further compared <lb/>population-level estimates in all-cause mortality with global estimates from the <lb/>United Nations Inter-agency Group for Child Mortality Estimation and the Glob-<lb/>al Burden of Disease study by computing the relative differences to the estimates. <lb/>Results Mortality declined steadily among the three age groups from 1995 to 2022, <lb/>whereby the average annual rate of decline increased with age (2.2%, 2.7%, and <lb/>2.9% for 5-9-, 10-14-, and 15-19-year-old age groups, respectively). The pace of <lb/>this decline was lower than that of younger children aged 1-4 years (4.8% de-<lb/>cline). We observed significant mortality inequalities with boys, those residing in <lb/>rural areas, and those from poorest wealth tertiles lagging behind. While Magu <lb/>estimates were close to global estimates for the 5-9-year-old age group, we ob-<lb/>served divergent results for adolescents (10-19 years), with Magu estimates lying <lb/>between the global estimates. <lb/>Conclusion The pace of mortality decline was lower for the 5-19-year-old age <lb/>group compared to younger children, with observable inequalities by socio-demo-<lb/>graphic characteristics. Determining the burden of disease across different strata <lb/>is important in the development of evidence-based targeted interventions to ad-<lb/>dress the mortality burden and inequalities in this age group, as it is an important <lb/>transition period to adulthood. <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s) <lb/></front>

        <note place="headnote">Kagoye et al. <lb/>PAPERS <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04124 <lb/></note>

        <page>2 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04124 <lb/></note>

        <body>Children and adolescents under 20 years of age account for 33% of the population globally and 52% of the <lb/>population in sub-Saharan Africa [1], as well as more than 45% of the population in Tanzania [2]. Trends <lb/>in mortality among children under five years are well studied [3-6]; however, the focus on mortality shifts <lb/>to adulthood, ignoring the middle age group beyond five years, which is an important transition stage to <lb/>adulthood [7]. Less is known about mortality among older children and adolescents; yet estimates for 2021 <lb/>suggested that over 1 million deaths occurred at ages 5-19 years globally, including 700 000 in sub-Saha-<lb/>ran Africa [8-10]. Therefore, reliable and timely data on levels, trends, and inequalities in mortality in this <lb/>age group are important for comprehensive planning, programming, and monitoring of health and social <lb/>services [11,12]. <lb/>In the absence of well-functioning civil registration and vital statistics systems [13,14], household surveys <lb/>are the primary source of data on mortality in low-and middle-income countries (LMICs). For Tanzania, <lb/>national household surveys, primarily the Demographic and Health Surveys (DHS), are the main data source <lb/>of global all-cause mortality estimates for the 5-19-year-old age group [10,15]. However, in the absence of <lb/>empirical data, the assumptions behind the global estimates do not reflect the realities at a population lev-<lb/>el. Survey reports generally do not include mortality statistics for older children and adolescents because of <lb/>large uncertainty due to smaller sample sizes. <lb/>In several countries in sub-Saharan Africa (including Tanzania), local populations are followed up using <lb/>standardised procedures as part of prospective health and demographic surveillance systems (HDSSs) to <lb/>collect vital event data on births, deaths and migration [14]. For example, the Magu HDSS is located in a ru-<lb/>ral area in northwestern Tanzania, and its population, socioeconomic, and health indicators are considered <lb/>typical for the country as a whole [16]. As the Magu HDSS has been in operation since 1994, its longitudi-<lb/>nal nature provides an opportunity for studying the long-term trends in mortality for the 5-19-year-old age <lb/>groups during a period characterised by a strong focus on the survival of children under-five years, a major <lb/>human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) epidemic, rapid population growth, and increasing education and <lb/>economic growth [16,17] -factor which are unlikely to be captured in cross-sectional surveys. <lb/>In this study, we estimated long-term trends in all-cause mortality rate among children aged 5-9, 10-14 <lb/>and 15-19 years during 1995-2022, using population data from Magu HDSS, and compared the chang-<lb/>es in trends among older children and adolescents with that among younger children aged 1-4 years. We <lb/>also examined the differences between the HDSS levels and trends and global estimates for Tanzania, and <lb/>assessed inequalities within the Magu HDSS itself by disaggregating the mortality estimates by sex, place <lb/>of residence, and wealth tertiles. <lb/>METHODS <lb/>Study setting <lb/>The Magu HDSS is located in Kisesa ward, Magu district, Mwanza region, Tanzania. Kisesa ward is one of <lb/>the 31 wards of the Magu district, while Magu is one of seven districts of the Mwanza region in northwest-<lb/>ern Tanzania. The Magu HDSS is an open community cohort, which has been in operation in a contiguous <lb/>area of seven villages since 1994 (administratively expanded to nine villages from 2018), located 20 km east <lb/>of the city of Mwanza. Within the area, the villages closest to Mwanza city and that are part of or near the <lb/>trading centre are considered as semi-urban, while all others are considered rural. The semi-urban and rural <lb/>boundaries in Magu HDSS have not changed since 1994 and the distribution of the population in semi-ur-<lb/>ban/rural villages in Magu HDSS is 49% to 51% (Figure 1). <lb/>The population in the Magu HDSS has expanded from 19 347 in 1994 to 54 024 in 2022, with an annu-<lb/>al population growth rate of 3.7% per year from 1994 to 2022. The population is and has remained young <lb/>over time with 46-48% of it being under 15 years of age. The total fertility rate among women 15-49 years <lb/>of age was 4.5 between 2018 and 2021, a decline from 6.3 in 1996. In our prior comparison of a range of <lb/>demographic, socioeconomic, and health indicators, we showed that the Magu HDSS characteristics were <lb/>very similar to Tanzania as a whole [16]. <lb/>Data collection <lb/>The data are collected by a team of nine local field workers who reside in the areas, with full-time supervi-<lb/>sion and regular monitoring visits from the National Institute for Medical Research. Each round of demo-<lb/>graphic surveillance was preceded by a training of field workers. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Mortality among 5-19-year-olds in Tanzania <lb/>PAPERS <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04124 <lb/></note>

        <page>3 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04124 <lb/></note>

        <body>The Magu HDSS monitored birth, death, cause of death, and migration in the general population at inter-<lb/>vals of approximately eight months since its conception in 1994, making a total of 40 HDSS rounds until <lb/>2022. All residents of households within the HDSS area are registered through home visits using a demo-<lb/>graphic household card with their names, age, sex, and relation to the household head. An HDSS number <lb/>is allocated to each listed individual based on administrative subdivisions in the HDSS area, i.e. village, <lb/>sub-village, ten household leaders, household number, and line number of a person in the household card. <lb/>The data collection process was paper-based from 1994 to 2012 (HDSS round 26), after which the update <lb/>of the HDSS data switched to an electronic format by the use of personal digital assistants (PDAs). Informa-<lb/>tion is currently collected using tablets, with data entry and management handled through the Census and <lb/>Survey Processing System (CSPro), version 8 (USA Census Bureau, USA) [18]. Regular data quality tables <lb/>were run to detect any problems in the field work. Data quality issues that emerged during merging with <lb/>previous rounds were addressed through consultation with the field team, after which the full data set was <lb/>finally edited and cleaned for analysis. The process of reconciling data from multiple rounds became more <lb/>efficient from 2012 onward with the introduction of PDAs and (eventually) tablets. Detailed information on <lb/>HDSS data collection methods are given elsewhere [17]. <lb/>Measurements <lb/>To calculate mortality, we created a residency episodes file using data form each round, defining it for each <lb/>period an individual aged 5-19 years spent in the Magu HDSS. We then used this file to calculate the total <lb/>person-years of observation in this analysis. The Magu HDSS defines residency as living for three months <lb/>or more in the study area [17]. All residency episodes started at birth, in migration, or the date first seen <lb/>in Magu HDSS (including at the beginning of the study); they finished at death, outmigration, or the date <lb/>last seen as a lost-to-follow-up or the right censoring date (31 December 2022). A new person (in-migrant) <lb/>was listed as a household member if the household respondent had stayed or was intending to stay in the <lb/>household for at least three months. Those who left a household in the Magu HDSS and were not expected <lb/>to return to that household were considered out-migrants from the household, but maintained their line <lb/>number, allowing returning household members to be relisted according to their original HDSS numbers. <lb/>Dates of in-and out-migration were recorded for older children and adolescents who moved out of house-<lb/>holds and changed residences. <lb/>We measured household wealth tertiles as a proxy indicator using information on the household asset indi-<lb/>cators that include construction materials of the main dwelling; type of toilet facilities; sources of water and <lb/>energy; ownership of modern assets; and livestock (Table S1 in the Online Supplementary Document). <lb/>Our rationale of using household asset indicators as a measure of socioeconomic status over &apos;direct&apos; mea-<lb/>sures such as income, expenditure, and financial assets (e.g. savings and pensions) was their reliability over <lb/>Figure 1. Map of Tanzania with the location of the Magu HDSS showing semi-urban and rural residence boundaries <lb/>and location of health facilities. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Kagoye et al. <lb/>PAPERS <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04124 <lb/></note>

        <page>4 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04124 <lb/></note>

        <body>time and cost-effectiveness, as the information is relatively easy and inexpensive to collect. Additionally, <lb/>household assets provide a better proxy for a household&apos;s long-run wealth compared to information on in-<lb/>come or expenditures; this is due to seasonal variability in earnings, income from potentially multiple and <lb/>diverse informal activities, high rates of self-employment, possible recall bias, and misreporting [19]. Infor-<lb/>mation on household assets was updated three more times from the baseline census as part of demograph-<lb/>ic rounds in 2004/05, 2018 and 2022. We used principal component analysis (PCA) to construct a wealth <lb/>score, which we divided into three equal parts as wealth tertiles [19,20]. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>Using time-to-event analysis with age as a time scale, we obtained the total number of deaths and the total <lb/>person years of observation annually from full periods of observation (January 1995 to December 2022) <lb/>which were grouped into four-year periods. Entry to risk began at birth, in-migration, or study start date. <lb/>Exit from risk was at the earliest of study end date (December 2022), out-migration, or death. If an out-mi-<lb/>gration is followed by an in-migration, the period between the out-and in-migration was excluded from <lb/>the risk period to avoid survivor bias. <lb/>We calculated crude mortality rates (CMR) for years 1995 to 2022 by dividing the total number of deaths <lb/>with total person years of observation at that year, per the following equation: <lb/>CMR j = d j /n j <lb/>Here, n j denotes the total person-years of older children and adolescents aged 5-9, 10-14, and 15-19 years <lb/>at year j = 1995-2022, respectively, while d j denotes the corresponding number of deaths. <lb/>Further, we computed age-specific mortality probabilities or risks and their 95% confidence intervals (CIs) <lb/>from Kaplan-Meier survival probabilities at 5-year age groups, i.e. the probability of a 5-year-old dying be-<lb/>fore reaching the 10th birthday ( 5 q 5 ), the probability of a 10-year-old dying before reaching the 15th birth-<lb/>day ( 5 q 10 ), and a probability of a 15-year-old dying before reaching the 20th birthday ( 5 q 15 ). <lb/>The Magu HDSS present a census, and not a sample. However, we computed 95% CIs for all mortality sta-<lb/>tistics using Poisson regression models and presented these in the Online Supplementary Document to <lb/>give an indication of uncertainty related to the number of observations and assess the differences between <lb/>subgroups. <lb/>To determine the average annual rate of change (AARC) in age-specific mortality probabilities from 1995 to <lb/>2022, we fitted a variance weighted least square regression to annual mortality probabilities. We presented <lb/>the AARC with respective 95% CIs. We also computed the AARC for child mortality trends (1-4 years) to <lb/>compare them with trends among older children and adolescents (5-19 years). We selected the 1-4-year-<lb/>old age group because it appeared that infant mortality (particularly neonatal mortality) was underestimat-<lb/>ed, as has been found in other HDSS assessments [21]. <lb/>We analysed the data in the subgroups of sex, geographical location (semi-urban/rural residence), and house-<lb/>hold wealth tertiles. We used the semi-urban to rural grouping of villages which had shown to be a major <lb/>factor in the HIV epidemic [22]. For socioeconomic status, we were able to link 74.8% of individual obser-<lb/>vations with household wealth data. Based on the asset score, we classified households into wealth tertiles, <lb/>i.e. the poorest, middle, and richest 33%, to obtain adequate numbers of observations in each category. <lb/>We examined sociodemographic inequalities of all-cause mortality risk among older children and adoles-<lb/>cents using an age stratified Cox proportional hazards model, disaggregated by sex, area of residence, and <lb/>wealth tertiles, presenting the measure of effect using hazards ratio with corresponding 95% CIs. Here, a <lb/>P-value of &lt;0.05 denoted statistical significance. <lb/>We compared the population data findings from the Magu HDSS with the global estimates for Tanzania by <lb/>computing relative differences for 4-year averages from 1995 onward for the mortality of 1-4-, 5-9-, 10-14-<lb/>, and 15-19-year-old-age groups. <lb/>The United Nations Interagency Group on Child Mortality estimates (UN IGME) uses nationally represen-<lb/>tative data to estimate child mortality; in countries with no reliable vial registration data specifically, it uses <lb/>household deaths from population census and household surveys (DHS). Mortality rates among children <lb/>aged 1-4 years and older children and younger adolescents (5-14 years) are derived from full birth histories, <lb/>while mortality among older adolescents (15-19 years) are derived from sibling survival histories. Recalcu-<lb/>lation are then done from data inputs and adjustments, after which a statistical model is fit to these data to <lb/>generate a smooth trend curve and further extrapolate the model to a target year [10]. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Mortality among 5-19-year-olds in Tanzania <lb/>PAPERS <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04124 <lb/></note>

        <page>5 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04124 <lb/></note>

        <body>The Global Burden of Disease (GBD) study utilises available data sources from household surveys, popula-<lb/>tion censuses, health and demographic surveillance, and epidemiological studies to estimate under-five and <lb/>adult mortality rates. There are no specific underlying data sources for the estimation of mortality among <lb/>older children and adolescents; mortality estimates for this age group are obtained using model life tables <lb/>with two entry parameters: the under-five mortality rate and adult mortality to obtain age-specific mortal-<lb/>ity probabilities [23]. <lb/>We defined the relative difference as the difference between the population data estimate and each global <lb/>estimate (UN IGME or GBD) divided by the Magu HDSS estimate [24] so as to put the population data es-<lb/>timates in the context of other modelled estimates and to test the external validity of our population data. <lb/>We analysed all data in Stata, version 18.0 (StataCorp LLC, College Station, Texas, USA). <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Mortality levels and trends (1995-2022) <lb/>We observed 635 deaths and 328 078.8 person years among older children and adolescents (5-19 years), <lb/>with 308 deaths and 131 507.5 person years among older children 5-9 years, 148 deaths and 111 432.5 per-<lb/>son years among younger adolescents (10-14 years), and 179 deaths and 85 139.8 person years among older <lb/>adolescents (15-19 years) (Table S2 in the Online Supplementary Document). <lb/>Mortality was the lowest in the 10-14-year-old <lb/>group compared to the 5-9-and 15-19-year-<lb/>olds, although the gap in mortality between <lb/>the three age groups was small during the last <lb/>period. Mortality was 5.8, 5.6, and 6.0 deaths <lb/>per 1000 during the final period (2019-22) <lb/>for older children aged 5-9 years, adolescents <lb/>aged 10-14, and 15-19 years, respectively <lb/>(Figure 2). <lb/>Mortality among children aged 5-9 years ( 5 q 5 ) <lb/>fluctuated over time, with a rapid decline in <lb/>the first decade (from 16.9 to 9.6 deaths per <lb/>1000). However, we then observed a reversal <lb/>in the trend, peaking in the 2011-14 period to <lb/>15.7, followed by a second rapid decline to 5.8 <lb/>deaths per 1000 in the final, 2019-22 period <lb/>(Figure 2). Mortality among adolescents (10-14 and 15-19 years) showed two periods with higher mortal-<lb/>ity in the earlier years, followed by a decline from 2003 in both age groups. However, we observed a period <lb/>with no steady improvement in adolescents&apos; survival from 2011 to 2019-22 among 10-14-year-olds (rang-<lb/>ing between 5.9 to 5.0 deaths per 1000) and from 2007 to 2018 among 15-19-year-olds (ranging between <lb/>10.9 to 9.8 deaths per 1000) (Figure 2). <lb/>There was a strong, sustained mortality decline in all age groups (Figure 2). The annual rate of mortality <lb/>declines since 1995 to 2022 among older children and adolescents increased with age, with older children <lb/>(5-9 years) having the lowest annual rate of decline of 2.0%, followed by younger adolescents (10-14 years) <lb/>with a decline of 2.7% and older adolescents (15-19 years) with the highest rate of decline of 2.9% per year. <lb/>The pace of mortality decline in all three age groups (5-9, 10-14, and 15-19 years) was much lower com-<lb/>pared to the 1-4-year-old age group, where mortality declined at 4.8% per year. (Table S9 in the Online <lb/>Supplementary Document). <lb/>Mortality inequalities <lb/>Mortality declined for both sexes but females had a higher annual rate of decline in mortality compared <lb/>to males among 5-14-year-olds (children aged 5-9 years: 2.6% vs 2.0%, younger adolescents aged 10-14 <lb/>years: 6.4% vs 1.3%). Older adolescents (15-19 years) showed a similar rate of mortality decline among both <lb/>males and females at 2.5% decline every year. This is in contrast to younger children aged 1-4 years, where <lb/>mortality declined faster among males compared to females (5.1% vs 4.3%) (Figure 3, Figure 4, Figure 5; <lb/>Tables S3-5 and S9 in the Online Supplementary Document). <lb/>Figure 2. Mortality per 1000 among older children (5-9 years), younger adoles-<lb/>cents (10-14 years), and older adolescents (15-19 years) in the Magu HDSS by <lb/>4-year time periods (1995-2022). <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Kagoye et al. <lb/>PAPERS <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04124 <lb/></note>

        <page>6 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04124 <lb/></note>

        <body>Mortality risk was higher among males compared to females for 5-9-and 10-14-year-olds. After adjusting <lb/>for other factors, mortality risk ratio was 44% higher and 51% higher among males aged 5-9 years (adjust-<lb/>ed hazard ratio (aHR) = 1.44; 95% CI = 1.13-1.82) and 10-14 years (aHR = 1.51; 95% CI = 1.06-2.14), respec-<lb/>tively, compared to females. There were no significant differences in mortality by sex among older adoles-<lb/>cents aged 15-19 years (Table 1). <lb/>Figure 3. Mortality per 1000 among older children and adolescents aged 5-9, 10-14, and 15-19 years in the Magu HDSS by sex and <lb/>4-year time periods (1995-2022). <lb/>Figure 4. Mortality probabilities per 1000 among older children and adolescents aged 5-9, 10-14, and 15-19 years in the Magu HDSS <lb/>by area of residence and 4-year time periods (1995-2022). <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Mortality among 5-19-year-olds in Tanzania <lb/>PAPERS <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04124 <lb/></note>

        <page>7 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04124 <lb/></note>

        <body>Figure 5. Mortality probabilities per 1000 among older children and adolescents aged 5-9, 10-14, and 15-19 years in the Magu HDSS <lb/>by wealth tertiles and 4-year time periods (1995-2022). <lb/>Table 1. Socio-demographic determinants of all-cause mortality risk among older children and adolescents (5-19 y) (age stratified Cox <lb/>proportional hazard model), 1995-2022 <lb/>5-9 years <lb/>10-14 years <lb/>15-19 years <lb/>Crude HR <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>P-value <lb/>aHR <lb/>(95% CI)* <lb/>P-value Crude HR <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>P-value <lb/>aHR <lb/>(95% CI)* <lb/>P-value Crude HR <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>P-value aHR (95% <lb/>CI)* <lb/>P-value <lb/>Time periods <lb/>1995-98 <lb/>2.92 <lb/>(1.86-4.58) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>2.60 <lb/>(1.59-4.25) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>1.71 <lb/>(0.96-3.03) <lb/>0.067 <lb/>1.27 <lb/>(0.64-2.52) <lb/>0.433 <lb/>2.39 <lb/>(1.35-4.23) <lb/>0.003 <lb/>1.54 <lb/>(0.78-3.04) <lb/>0.207 <lb/>1999-2002 <lb/>2.68 <lb/>(1.71-4.19) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>2.54 <lb/>(1.59-4.04) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>1.80 <lb/>(1.04-3.10) <lb/>0.035 <lb/>1.77 <lb/>(1.00-3.13) <lb/>0.050 <lb/>2.49 <lb/>(1.43-4.35) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>2.36 <lb/>(1.33-4.19) <lb/>0.003 <lb/>2003-06 <lb/>1.64 <lb/>(1.01-2.66) <lb/>0.047 <lb/>1.58 <lb/>(0.97-2.57) <lb/>0.054 <lb/>1.01 <lb/>(0.55-1.87) <lb/>0.967 <lb/>0.97 <lb/>(0.52-1.83) <lb/>0.987 <lb/>2.17 <lb/>(1.25-3.77) <lb/>0.006 <lb/>1.89 <lb/>(1.07-3.34) <lb/>0.026 <lb/>2007-10 <lb/>1.84 <lb/>(1.16-2.92) <lb/>0.010 <lb/>1.74 <lb/>(1.08-2.79) <lb/>0.018 <lb/>1.25 <lb/>(0.72-2.19) <lb/>0.429 <lb/>1.13 <lb/>(0.63-2.04) <lb/>0.635 <lb/>1.75 <lb/>(1.00-3.07) <lb/>0.050 <lb/>1.78 <lb/>(1.01-3.12) <lb/>0.043 <lb/>2011-14 <lb/>2.72 <lb/>(1.79-4.14) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>2.75 <lb/>(1.80-4.19) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>1.03 <lb/>(0.58-1.83) <lb/>0.923 <lb/>1.06 <lb/>(0.59-1.90) <lb/>0.811 <lb/>1.59 <lb/>(0.90-2.80) <lb/>0.109 <lb/>1.57 <lb/>(0.89-2.78) <lb/>0.165 <lb/>2015-18 <lb/>1.96 <lb/>(1.26-3.05) <lb/>0.003 <lb/>1.88 <lb/>(1.20-2.94) <lb/>0.005 <lb/>0.86 <lb/>(0.47-1.55) <lb/>0.606 <lb/>0.89 <lb/>(0.49-1.61) <lb/>0.717 <lb/>1.56 <lb/>(0.89-2.74) <lb/>0.118 <lb/>1.57 <lb/>(0.90-2.75) <lb/>0.113 <lb/>2019-22 <lb/>ref <lb/>ref <lb/>ref <lb/>ref <lb/>ref <lb/>ref <lb/>Sex <lb/>Male <lb/>1.40 <lb/>(1.12-1.76) <lb/>0.003 <lb/>1.44 <lb/>(1.13-1.82) <lb/>0.003 <lb/>1.54 <lb/>(1.11-2.13) <lb/>0.010 <lb/>1.51 <lb/>(1.06-2.14) <lb/>0.021 <lb/>1.09 <lb/>(0.81-1.46) <lb/>0.573 <lb/>1.03 <lb/>(0.75-1.40) <lb/>0.792 <lb/>Female <lb/>ref <lb/>ref <lb/>ref <lb/>ref <lb/>ref <lb/>ref <lb/>Area of residence <lb/>Semi-urban <lb/>ref <lb/>ref <lb/>ref <lb/>ref <lb/>ref <lb/>ref <lb/>Rural <lb/>1.37 <lb/>(1.08-1.73) <lb/>0.009 <lb/>1.09 <lb/>(0.82-1.45) <lb/>0.206 <lb/>2.07 <lb/>(1.44-1.98) <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>1.98 <lb/>(1.27-3.09) <lb/>0.001 <lb/>1.35 <lb/>(0.99-1.83) <lb/>0.052 <lb/>0.97 <lb/>(0.67-1.39) <lb/>0.844 <lb/>Wealth tertiles <lb/>Poor <lb/>1.67 <lb/>(1.23-2.25) <lb/>0.009 <lb/>1.48 <lb/>(1.05-2.10) <lb/>0.020 <lb/>1.72 <lb/>(1.08-2.72) <lb/>0.045 <lb/>1.13 <lb/>(0.67-1.92) <lb/>0.852 <lb/>1.78 <lb/>(1.19-2.67) <lb/>0.004 <lb/>1.74 <lb/>(1.09-2.78) <lb/>0.019 <lb/>Middle <lb/>1.24 <lb/>(0.89-1.72) <lb/>0.143 <lb/>1.15 <lb/>(0.82-1.62) <lb/>0.477 <lb/>1.77 <lb/>(1.07-2.73) <lb/>0.047 <lb/>1.35 <lb/>(0.82-2.23) <lb/>0.646 <lb/>1.56 <lb/>(1.02-2.36) <lb/>0.026 <lb/>1.52 <lb/>(0.98-2.35) <lb/>0.285 <lb/>Rich <lb/>ref <lb/>ref <lb/>ref <lb/>ref <lb/>ref <lb/>ref <lb/>aHR -adjusted hazard ratio, CI -confidence interval, ref -reference <lb/>*Adjusted for time periods-sex-area of residence and household wealth tertiles. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Kagoye et al. <lb/>PAPERS <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04124 <lb/></note>

        <page>8 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04124 <lb/></note>

        <body>Mortality within the HDSS declined quicker in rural than in semi-urban villages for older children (5-9 <lb/>years) and younger adolescents (10-14 years) (rural vs semi-urban children (5-9 years): 1.8% vs 1.2%, ru-<lb/>ral vs semi-urban younger adolescents (10-14 years): 2.8% vs 1.7%). Mortality decline among older adoles-<lb/>cents (15-19 years) was similar in both areas (rural: 3.2%, semi-urban: 3.1%). Among younger children (1-4 <lb/>years), there was a faster mortality decline in semi-urban villages (5.6% per year) compared to rural villages <lb/>(4.1% per year) (Table S9 in the Online Supplementary Document). <lb/>Mortality was higher in the rural than in the semi-urban villages in all three age groups. This remained <lb/>statistically significant for only younger adolescents after adjusting for household wealth and other factors. <lb/>The mortality risk ratio among younger adolescents (10-14 years) residing in rural areas increased by 98% <lb/>compared to their counterparts in urban areas (aHR = 1.98; 95% CI = 1.27-3.09). Although not statistically <lb/>significant, we found lower mortality risk ratio in rural areas compared to their counterparts among older <lb/>adolescents (15-19 years) (aHR = 0.97; 95% CI = 0.67-1.39). <lb/>The mortality risks by household wealth tertiles differed significantly among children aged 5-9 years and <lb/>older adolescents aged 15-19 years (Table 1). The risk was higher among the poorest followed by the middle <lb/>wealth tertiles, as compared to the richest wealth tertile. For 5-9-year-olds, those from poorest and middle <lb/>tertiles had a 48% (aHR = 1.48; 95% CI = 1.05-2.10) and 15% (aHR = 1.15; 95% CI = 0.82-1.62) higher mor-<lb/>tality risk compared to those from the richest wealth tertile, respectively. For adolescents (15-19-year-olds), <lb/>those in the poorest wealth tertile had 74% higher risk of dying (aHR = 1.74; 95% CI = 1.09-2.78), while <lb/>those from the middle tertile had a 52% higher risk of dying compared to those in the richest wealth tertile <lb/>(aHR = 1.52; 95% CI = 0.98-2.35). <lb/>Comparison with global estimates <lb/>The mean absolute difference in four-year mortality risks for the three age groups combined (5-19 years) <lb/>was 2.1 per 1000 between the HDSS and UN estimates, 2.7 per 1000 between the HDSS and the GBD study, <lb/>and 3.4 per 1000 between the two global estimates. <lb/>At 5-9-years, the Magu HDSS mortality risks were comparable to those estimated by the UN IGME, with <lb/>relative differences ranging from 3-20%. For the GBD study, the Magu mortality risks were comparable in <lb/>1995-98, 1999-2002, and 2007-10, with relative differences ranging from 5-10%. We observed differenc-<lb/>es in the 2003-06 period, with lower mortality rates in Magu (33.8% difference with GBD estimates). We <lb/>also found major differences between th eMagu HDSS data and global estimates in the 2011-14 period, with <lb/>higher estimated mortality in the Magu HDSS by 35.8% and 35.2% compared to UNIGME and GBD study <lb/>estimates, respectively (Figure 6 and Table S10 in the Online Supplementary Document). <lb/>The two global estimates for mortality among younger adolescents (10-14 years) diverge widely, with GBD <lb/>study estimates being higher than the UN ones. The Magu HDSS results showed an intermediate pattern, <lb/>closer to the GBD study estimates during the earlier periods (relative differences of 1.9% and 6.5% in 1995-<lb/>98 and 1999-2002 periods) and closer to the UN IGME trend in more recent years (relative difference 21.5% <lb/>in 2015-18 period compared to 44% with the GBD study). <lb/>For the 15-19-year-olds, the HDSS trends were similar to the UN estimates (relative difference ranging <lb/>from 6% to 26.8%), while the GBD study estimates for Tanzania were higher during all periods, with rela-<lb/>tive differences of up to 51.3%. <lb/>We also compared 1-4 mortality estimates from the Magu HDSS with global estimates. Here, the Magu <lb/>HDSS estimates were comparable to the UN IGME ones across the time periods, with relative differences <lb/>ranging from 1.3% to 11%. However, we observed differences in 2007-10 and 2011-14 periods, with rela-<lb/>tive differences of 31.9% and 46.9%, respectively. We otherwise saw major differences with the GBD study <lb/>estimates, with the Magu HDSS estimating lower rates by at least 65.4%. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>The Magu HDSS analyses provide insights into mortality levels, trends, and inequalities among older chil-<lb/>dren and adolescents (aged 5-19 years) during the 1995-2022 period. This study is the first of its kind in <lb/>Tanzania and one of the few long-term assessments at a population level for this age group in sub-Saharan <lb/>Africa [27-31]. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Mortality among 5-19-year-olds in Tanzania <lb/>PAPERS <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04124 <lb/></note>

        <page>9 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04124 <lb/></note>

        <body>Overall, the risk of dying was lowest among younger adolescents 10-14 years and highest among older <lb/>children aged 5-9 years. This is similar to what was observed in other LMICs [29,32] and in contrast to <lb/>high-income countries, where the risk of dying is lowest at ages 5-9 years [32]. The higher mortality bur-<lb/>den at ages 5-9 in our study suggests that there is likely a continuing mortality risk from infectious child-<lb/>hood diseases. According to global estimates, infectious diseases (including malaria, diarrhoeal diseases, <lb/>and HIV/AIDS) account for more than 50% of deaths at ages 5-9 in Tanzania [33]. Further work analysing <lb/>the cause of death patterns in this age group within the HDSS is ongoing. <lb/>We observed a steady decline in mortality over time across the three age groups, although reversals of the <lb/>downward mortality trend occurred in a few four-year periods. Children aged 5-9 years had a slower an-<lb/>nual rate of decline in mortality (2.2%) compared to adolescents (2.7% and 2.9% decline for 10-14-and <lb/>15-19-year-olds, respectively). This is remarkable, given that there has been little specific health programme <lb/>focus on this age group in Tanzania during the last two decades. However, the pace of mortality decline <lb/>in this age group was about half of that among children 1-4 years (4.8% decline per year), similar to what <lb/>was observed in other studies in LMICs [32]. Early childhood mortality (1-4 years) has been a major pro-<lb/>grammatic focus over time, which influenced a major mortality decline in this age group [34,35]. We did <lb/>not find evidence of impact of the HIV epidemic on 5-19 years mortality, which had its greatest impact on <lb/>adult mortality in the population around 2000-03 [18]. A refocus of policies and interventions on the age <lb/>groups beyond five years is necessary to expedite reductions in mortality and improve quality of life in this <lb/>age group, which encompasses a critical transition period to adulthood. <lb/>The Magu HDSS also allowed us to assess the inequalities within a local population in adjacent villages. We <lb/>found large male excess mortality at 5-9 and 10-14 years: 1.44 and 1.51, respectively. Male excess mortality <lb/>was much higher than that estimated by the UN-IGME for Tanzania, where the average male-female ratios <lb/>were 1.04, 1.2, and 1.1 for the 5-9-, 10-14-, and 15-19-year-olds, respectively. This was higher compared <lb/>to what was observed in other studies [36]. Additionally, mortality decline was slower among males com-<lb/>pared to females across all age groups, similar to what has been observed elsewhere [27,36,37]. The poten-<lb/>tial reason for the observed sex differences in mortality is likely the differences in exposure to risk factors <lb/>between males and females, with males being at a higher risk for injuries compared to females, which is one <lb/>of the leading causes of death in this age group [29,31]. Further research on the underlying differences in <lb/>cause-specific mortality by sex could help address sex-specific inequalities in this age group. <lb/>Figure 6. All-cause mortality estimates for 1-4, 5-9-, 10-14-, and 15-19-year-olds comparing global estimates from the UN IGME [25], <lb/>GBD [26], and population data from the Magu HDSS. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Kagoye et al. <lb/>PAPERS <lb/></note>

        <note place="headnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04124 <lb/></note>

        <page>10 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04124 <lb/></note>

        <body>A second inequality concerned the place of residence. Our findings show that older children and younger <lb/>adolescents (5-9 and 10-14 years, respectively) in semi-urban villages experienced much lower mortality <lb/>risk than those in rural households. However, after controlling for wealth, this gap only remained statisti-<lb/>cally significant at the 10-14-year-old age group, where mortality was nearly two times higher among rural <lb/>children within this small area of the HDSS. One possible explanation is the poor access to health services <lb/>among those residing in rural areas, especially due to the distribution of lower-level facilities in the rural <lb/>areas compared to semi-urban area, leading to the observed lagging. <lb/>In terms of wealth, individuals from the poorest wealth tertiles had a 70-80% higher mortality risk than <lb/>those in the richest tertile. Such patterns of inequality have been reported by other studies [29], highlight-<lb/>ing the need to focus health programmes on the poorest populations. Differences in place of residence could <lb/>only explain a small part of these differences in mortality risk between the poorest and richest households. <lb/>Lastly, we compared our results with global estimates for Tanzania. As noted elsewhere, there is evidence <lb/>that the Magu HDSS can be considered representative of the Tanzanian population, given the close cor-<lb/>respondence for a wide range of population, socioeconomic, and health indicators over the past two de-<lb/>cades [16]. Therefore, we expected our mortality estimates to be close to the global estimates for Tanza-<lb/>nia. This was indeed the case for children 5-9 years, where there was little difference with the UN-IGME <lb/>and the GBD study estimates. At ages 10-14 and 15-19 years, however, we observed major differences <lb/>between the two global estimates; in both cases, with the Magu HDSS results falling in between in both <lb/>cases. The discrepancies are likely related to the different empirical data and estimation methods used in <lb/>each global estimate. <lb/>In general, our findings suggest that the global trend estimates of mortality 5-19 years are a useful source <lb/>for Tanzania, though the wide difference between the global sources themselves needs to be addressed. It <lb/>was surprising, however, that the differences between the two global estimates for Tanzania were larger than <lb/>the differences between each global estimate and the results from the Magu HDSS. More and better national <lb/>and subnational data on mortality 5-19 years are needed for tracking mortality in the future. <lb/>One of the limitations of our study is the relatively small number of child and adolescent deaths spread out <lb/>over a long period, resulting in considerable mortality fluctuations. We partially reduced this bias by con-<lb/>sidering four-year periods and CIs, as well as by focussing on long-term trends. As in any death registration <lb/>system, we may have missed deaths in the relevant age groups; however, the Magu HDSS has been charac-<lb/>terised by an intensive and well-established system of follow up [17]. The consistency of the mortality re-<lb/>sults with other sources and over time suggests that omission was not a major issue. Furthermore, while <lb/>migration may affect the denominators, our strict inclusion criteria to compute person years of observation <lb/>have minimised this risk. Finally, our comparison with global estimates can only be tentative, as the Magu <lb/>HDSS is a local study, even though it appears to be quite representative for Tanzania [16]. <lb/>CONCLUSION <lb/>Our study provides evidence on long-term trends and inequalities in child and adolescent mortality based <lb/>on 28 years of demographic surveillance in a rural population in northwest Tanzania. Despite little pro-<lb/>grammatic focus on the older children and adolescent during 1995-2022, mortality risks in the 5-9-, <lb/>10-14-, and 15-19-year-old age groups declined to 5-6 per 1000 population. This decline was, however, <lb/>was at an average annual rate of reduction that was only half of what was observed at ages 1-4 years. Im-<lb/>provements in survival occurred in all subgroups, but boys, children in rural villages, and children in the <lb/>poorest households had considerably higher mortality than girls (5-14 years), children in semi-urban vil-<lb/>lages, and children in in the richest households, respectively. The trend data suggest that a greater focus <lb/>on health and survival of children beyond age five years can accelerate the mortality decline, especially <lb/>when focussed on the more disadvantaged children and adolescents. We also showed empirical data are <lb/>an important input to enhance global estimation of mortality among older children and adolescents. Fur-<lb/>ther investments in measurement and monitoring mortality and other health indicators in this age group <lb/>are critical for successful programs. <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Mortality among 5-19-year-olds in Tanzania <lb/>PAPERS <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04124 <lb/></note>

        <page>11 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04124 <lb/></note>

        <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements: The authors wish to thank the residents of Magu HDSS for their continued participation in the <lb/>surveillance. We would wish also to acknowledge the field workers for their dedication in collecting this data and the <lb/>data management team for supervision of field activities and data management. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Ethics statement: Permission to conduct this study was obtained from the Medical Research Coordinating Committee <lb/>in Tanzania with ethical clearance number NIMR/HQ/R.8c/Vol. I/1496 and from Catholic University of Health of Health <lb/>and Allied Sciences Bugando Research and ethical committee (CREC) with ethical clearance number CREC/580/2022. <lb/>Informed consent was obtained for participants aged 18 and above, while assent was obtained from minors. Unique <lb/>identification numbers were used to identify study participants. Confidentiality was adhered to during data process <lb/>and analysis. <lb/></div>

        <div type="availability">Data availability: Data used for analysis in this study is available upon a formal request to the corresponding author. <lb/></div>

        <div type="funding">Funding: We would like to acknowledge the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation for support to this study through the <lb/>grant to APHRC (Grant number INV-003416 -Countdown to 2030). Also, Fogarty training grant for partial support <lb/>through grant D43 TW011826. Magu Health and Demographic Surveillance System is supported by the Global Affairs <lb/>Canada, as part of the Canadian Collaborative for Global Health and from the Canada Research Chairs program. The <lb/>funding agencies had no role in determining the design and implementation of the study or dissemination of the results. <lb/></div>

        <div type="contribution">Authorship contributions: SK and TB conceptualised the study. JT, MU, MM, AM, and ETK provided inputs on the <lb/>manuscript concept. SK carried out the analysis and drafted the manuscript, MM advised on the analysis, and CM con-<lb/>tributed to data management. TB, JT, MU, AM, MM, and ETK contributed in the interpretation of results. All co-au-<lb/>thors reviewed and approved the final draft. <lb/></div>

        <div type="conflict">Disclosure of interest: The authors completed the ICMJE Disclosure of Interest Form (available upon request from the <lb/>corresponding author) and disclose no relevant interests. <lb/></div>

        <div type="annex">Additional material <lb/>Online supplementary Document <lb/></div>

        <listBibl>1 United Nations. 2024 Revision of World Population Prospects. 2024. Available: https://population.un.org/wpp/. Accessed: <lb/>12 January 2024. <lb/>2 Tanzania National Bureau of Statistics. Census Hub. 2022. Available: https://sensa.nbs.go.tz/. Accessed: 13 January 2024. <lb/>3 Masanja H, de Savigny D, Smithson P, Schellenberg J, John T, Mbuya C, et al. Child survival gains in Tanzania: analy-<lb/>sis of data from demographic and health surveys. Lancet. 2008;371:1276-83. Medline:18406862 doi:10.1016/S0140-<lb/>6736(08)60562-0 <lb/>4 Sathiya Susuman A, Hamisi HF. Under-5 mortality in Tanzania: A demographic scenario. Iran J Public Health. 2012;41:8-<lb/>18. Medline:23641385 <lb/>5 Afnan-Holmes H, Magoma M, John T, Levira F, Msemo G, Armstrong CE, et al. Tanzania&apos;s countdown to 2015: an analysis <lb/>of two decades of progress and gaps for reproductive, maternal, newborn, and child health, to inform priorities for post-<lb/>2015. Lancet Glob Health. 2015;3:e396-409. Medline:26087986 doi:10.1016/S2214-109X(15)00059-5 <lb/>6 Ogbo FA, Ezeh OK, Awosemo AO, Ifegwu IK, Tan L, Jessa E, et al. Determinants of trends in neonatal, post-neonatal, in-<lb/>fant, child and under-five mortalities in Tanzania from 2004 to 2016. BMC Public Health. 2019;19:1243. Medline:31500599 <lb/>doi:10.1186/s12889-019-7547-x <lb/>7 Fadel SA, Amouzou A. Child and adolescent deaths: a call for strengthening mortality surveillance systems. The Lancet <lb/>Global Health. 2022;10:e299-e300. Medline:35180400 doi:10.1016/S2214-109X(22)00009-2 <lb/>8 Masquelier B, Hug L, Sharrow D, You D, Hogan D, Hill K, et al. Global, regional, and national mortality trends in old-<lb/>er children and young adolescents (5-14 years) from 1990 to 2016: an analysis of empirical data. Lancet Glob Health. <lb/>2018;6:e1087-99. Medline:30223984 doi:10.1016/S2214-109X(18)30353-X <lb/>9 Masquelier B, Hug L, Sharrow D, You D, Mathers C, Gerland P, et al. Global, regional, and national mortality trends in youth <lb/>aged 15-24 years between 1990 and 2019: a systematic analysis. Lancet Glob Health. 2021;9:e409-17. Medline:33662320 <lb/>doi:10.1016/S2214-109X(21)00023-1 <lb/>10 United Nations Inter-Agency Group for Child Mortality Estimation. Levels and trends in child mortality, Report 2022. <lb/>New York: United Nations Children&apos;s Fund; 2023. Available: https://data.unicef.org/resources/levels-and-trends-in-child-<lb/>mortality-2024/. Accessed: 15 July 2024. <lb/>11 Tomlinson M, Hunt X, Daelmans B, Rollins N, Ross D, Oberklaid F. Optimising child and adolescent health and develop-<lb/>ment through an integrated ecological life course approach. BMJ. 2021;372:m4784. Medline:33731322 doi:10.1136/bmj. <lb/>m4784 <lb/>12 Lehtimaki S, Schwalbe N, Sollis L. Adolescent Health: The Missing Population in Universal Health Coverage. New York, <lb/>Geneva: United Nations Children&apos;s Fund, World Health Organization; 2022. Available: https://pmnch.who.int/resources/ <lb/>publications/m/item/adolescent-health-the-missing-population-in-universal-health-coverage. Accessed: 15 July 2024. <lb/>13 World Health Organization. WHO Civil Registration and Vital Statistics Strategic Implementation Plan 2021-2025. Gene-<lb/>va: World Health Organization; 2021. Available: https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/342847/97892400224 <lb/>92-eng.pdf?sequence=1%0Ahttps://getinthepicture.org/sites/default/files/resources/WHO CRVS strategic implementation <lb/>plan.pdf. Accessed: 15 July 2024. <lb/>REFERENCES <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="headnote">Kagoye et al. <lb/>PAPERS <lb/></note>

        <note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04124 <lb/></note>

        <page>12 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04124 <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>14 Ye Y, Wamukoya M, Ezeh A, Emina JBO, Sankoh O. Health and demographic surveillance systems: A step towards full <lb/>civil registration and vital statistics system in sub-Sahara Africa? BMC Public Health. 2012;12:741. Medline:22950896 <lb/>doi:10.1186/1471-2458-12-741 <lb/>15 GBD 2019 Diseases and Injuries Collaborators. Global burden of 369 diseases and injuries in 204 countries and territo-<lb/>ries, 1990-2019: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2019. Lancet. 2020;396:1204-22. Med-<lb/>line:33069326 doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30925-9 <lb/>16 Urassa M, Milly M, Charles M, Jacqueline M, Elsabe D, Kinung&apos;hi S, et al. Cohort Profile Update: Magu Health and De-<lb/>mographic Surveillance System, Tanzania. Int J Epidemiol. 2024;53:dyae058. Medline:38676640 doi:10.1093/ije/dyae058 <lb/>17 Kishamawe C, Isingo R, Mtenga B, Zaba B, Todd J, Clark B, et al. Health &amp; Demographic Surveillance System Profile: The <lb/>Magu Health and Demographic Surveillance System (Magu HDSS). Int J Epidemiol. 2015;44:1851-61. Medline:26403815 <lb/>doi:10.1093/ije/dyv188 <lb/>18 U.S. Census Bureau. Census and survey processing system. 2022. Available: https://www.census.gov/data/software/cspro. <lb/>html. Accessed: 15 July 2024. <lb/>19 Kabudula CW, Houle B, Collinson MA, Kahn K, Tollman S, Clark S. Assessing Changes in Household Socioeconom-<lb/>ic Status in Rural South Africa, 2001-2013: A Distributional Analysis Using Household Asset Indicators. Soc Indic Res. <lb/>2017;133:1047-73. Medline:28931968 doi:10.1007/s11205-016-1397-z <lb/>20 Vyas S, Kumaranayake L. Constructing socio-economic status indices: How to use principal components analysis. Health <lb/>Policy Plan. 2006;21:459-68. Medline:17030551 doi:10.1093/heapol/czl029 <lb/>21 Verhulst A, Prieto JR, Alam N, Eilerts-Spinelli H, Erchick DJ, Gerland P, et al. Divergent age patterns of under-5 mortali-<lb/>ty in south Asia and sub-Saharan Africa: a modelling study. Lancet Glob Health. 2022;10:e1566-74. Medline:36088913 <lb/>doi:10.1016/S2214-109X(22)00337-0 <lb/>22 Boerma JT, Urassa M, Senkoro K, Klokke A, Ng&apos;weshemi JZL. Spread of HIV infection in a rural area of Tanzania. AIDS. <lb/>1999;13:1233-40. Medline:10416528 doi:10.1097/00002030-199907090-00013 <lb/>23 GBD 2019 Demographics Collaborators. Global age-sex-specific fertility, mortality, healthy life expectancy (HALE), and <lb/>population estimates in 204 countries and territories, 1950-2019: a comprehensive demographic analysis for the Glob-<lb/>al Burden of Disease Study 2019. Lancet. 2020;396:1160-203. Medline:33069325 doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30977-6 <lb/>24 Liu L, Black RE, Cousens S, Mathers C, Lawn JE, Hogan DR. Causes of child death: Comparison of MCEE and GBD 2013 <lb/>estimates. Lancet. 2015;385:2461-2. Medline:26122064 doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(15)61132-1 <lb/>25 United Nations Inter-Agency Group for Child Mortality Estimation. Under-five mortality rate -Total. 2024. Available: <lb/>https://childmortality.org/all-cause-mortality/data. Accessed: 22 July 2024. <lb/>26 Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation. GBD Results -Causes of death or injury. 2024. Available: https://vizhub.health-<lb/>data.org/gbd-results/. Accessed: 22 July 2024. <lb/>27 Phillips-Howard PA, Odhiambo FO, Hamel M, Adazu K, Ackers M, van Eijk AM, et al. Mortality Trends from 2003 to 2009 <lb/>among Adolescents and Young Adults in Rural Western Kenya Using a Health and Demographic Surveillance System. PLoS <lb/>One. 2012;7:1-13. Medline:23144796 doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0047017 <lb/>28 Osano BO, Were F, Mathews S. Mortality among 5-17-year-old children in Kenya. Pan Afr Med J. 2017;27:121. Med-<lb/>line:28819541 doi:10.11604/pamj.2017.27.121.10727 <lb/>29 Ratovoson R, Masquelier B, Andriatahina T, Mangahasimbola R, Andrianirina Z, Pison G, et al. Inequalities in cause-spe-<lb/>cific mortality in children and adolescents in the Moramanga health survey, Madagascar. Int J Public Health. 2020;65:781-<lb/>90. Medline:32566965 doi:10.1007/s00038-020-01409-z <lb/>30 Kananura RM, Leone T, Nareeba T, Kajungu D, Waiswa P, Gjonca A. Under 10 mortality patterns, risk factors, and mech-<lb/>anisms in low resource settings of Eastern Uganda: An analysis of event history demographic and verbal social autopsy <lb/>data. PLoS One. 2020;15:e0234573. Medline:32525931 doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0234573 <lb/>31 Dedefo M, Zelalem D, Eskinder B, Assefa N, Ashenafi W, Baraki N, et al. Causes of death among children aged 5 to 14 <lb/>years old from 2008 to 2013 in Kersa Health and Demographic Surveillance System (Kersa HDSS), Ethiopia. PLoS One. <lb/>2016;11:e0151929. Medline:27304832 doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0151929 <lb/>32 Hill K, Zimmerman L, Jamison DT. Mortality at Ages 5 to 19: Levels and Trends, 1990-2010. In: Bundy DAP, Nd Silva, <lb/>Horton S, editors. Child Adolescent Health and Development. Washington D.C., USA: The International Bank for Recon-<lb/>struction and Development; 2017. p. 25-6. <lb/>33 World Health Organization. Global health estimates: Leading causes of death. 2022. Available: https://www.who.int/data/ <lb/>gho/data/themes/mortality-and-global-health-estimates/ghe-leading-causes-of-death. Accessed: 15 July 2024. <lb/>34 Ministry of Health. Community development, gender, elderly and children. National Plan for Reproductive, Maternal, <lb/>Newborn, Child and Adolescent Health &amp; Nutrition-One Plan III. Tanzania: Ministry of health, community develop-<lb/>ment, gender, elderly and children; 2021. Available: https://www.globalfinancingfacility.org/sites/default/files/Tanzania-<lb/>One-Plan-III.pdf. Accessed: 15 July 2024. <lb/>35 Ministry of Health. community development, gender, elderly and children. Tanzania Health Sector Strategic Plan V 2021-<lb/>2026. Tanzania: Ministry of health, community development, gender, elderly and children; 2021. Available: https://mitu.or.tz/ <lb/>wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Tanzania-Health-Sector-Strategic-Plan-V-17-06-2021-Final-signed.pdf. Accessed: 15 July 2024. <lb/>36 Chao F, Masquelier B, You D, Hug L, Liu Y, Sharrow D, et al. Sex differences in mortality among children, adolescents, and <lb/>young people aged 0-24 years: a systematic assessment of national, regional, and global trends from 1990 to 2021. Lancet <lb/>Glob Health. 2023;11:e1519-30. Medline:37734797 doi:10.1016/S2214-109X(23)00376-5 <lb/>37 Zhu J, Li Y, Zhang C, He J, Niu L. Trends in mortality and causes of death among Chinese adolescents aged 10-19 years <lb/>from 1990 to 2019. Front Public Health. 2023;11:1075858. Medline:36825144 doi:10.3389/fpubh.2023.1075858 <lb/>REFERENCES </listBibl>


	</text>

</TEI>