<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Review began 01/10/2024 <lb/>Review ended 01/18/2024 <lb/>Published 01/23/2024 <lb/>© Copyright 2024 <lb/>Keche et al. This is an open access article <lb/>distributed under the terms of the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., <lb/>which permits unrestricted use, distribution, <lb/>and reproduction in any medium, provided <lb/>the original author and source are credited. <lb/>Analysis of Drugs Prescribed to Elderly Patients <lb/>in a Tertiary Health Care Center in Raipur, <lb/>Central India: An Observational Study <lb/>Yogendra Keche , Nitin R. Gaikwad , Preetam N. Wasnik , Keshao Nagpure , Md Sabah Siddiqui , <lb/>Apoorva Joshi , Suryaprakash Dhaneria , Gevesh Dewangan , Jhasaketan Meher , Pranita Das <lb/>1. Pharmacology, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Raipur, Raipur, IND 2. General Medicine, All India Institute of <lb/>Medical Sciences, Raipur, Raipur, IND 3. General Medicine, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Nagpur, Nagpur, <lb/>IND 4. Pharmacology and Therapeutics, Ruxmaniben Deepchand Gardi Medical College, Ujjain, IND <lb/>Corresponding author: Yogendra Keche, drynkeche@aiimsraipur.edu.in <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Background <lb/>Most elderly patients suffer from multiple diseases and are on multiple drugs for treatment. Polypharmacy <lb/>in the elderly, physiological changes with old age, changes in the pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamic <lb/>effects of many drugs, and newer drug prescription trends for diseases like diabetes and cardiovascular <lb/>disease make drug prescribing in the elderly more difficult. There are many chances of drug-drug <lb/>interactions with easily available over-the-counter (OTC) medications. To prevent the irrational use of drugs <lb/>in the elderly, there is a need for prescription analysis studies. Prescription analysis studies will help in <lb/>finding errors in prescriptions and also change trends in the use of medication among the elderly. <lb/>Methodology <lb/>This cross-sectional observation study was conducted on 234 elderly patients to investigate medicine use <lb/>patterns among the geriatric patients attending the Medicine Outpatient Department in a tertiary care <lb/>teaching hospital. Drug data were collected from the study participants after obtaining written informed <lb/>consent and analysed, including demographic details, personal history, disease history, and details of the <lb/>drug, including the generic name of the drug, dose and duration of therapy, and prescription pattern. The <lb/>proportions of drugs prescribed for different diseases were analysed. Also, the drugs were analysed as per <lb/>their pharmacological profiles. <lb/>Results and interpretation <lb/>A total of 1298 drug prescriptions were analysed in this study. Of the total participants, 60.26% were male, <lb/>35% were unemployed, 53% were retired, and 27% were taking OTC herbal medications. Most of the patients <lb/>included in this study were suffering from diabetes, hypertension, and other comorbidities. Telmisartan and <lb/>telmisartan in combination with other drugs were the most commonly encountered prescription drugs, i.e., <lb/>24% among the cardiovascular drugs. Aspirin and statins alone or in combination were the most commonly <lb/>encountered prescriptions, i.e., 27.88% of the drugs used for prophylaxis of cardiovascular diseases. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>This study showed a prescription pattern for the elderly and highlighted precautions to be taken with some <lb/>of the prescribed drugs. As polypharmacy is observed with elderly prescriptions, possible drug interactions <lb/>must be taken into account. Regular prescription analysis of drugs prescribed to the elderly will help in the <lb/>appropriate and rational use of drugs. <lb/>Categories: Geriatrics, Internal Medicine, Therapeutics <lb/>Keywords: therapeutics of elderly, chronic disease prescription analysis, drugs and elderly, prescription analysis, <lb/>geriatrics <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>India&apos;s elderly population is growing fast; as of now, 10.1% of the country&apos;s population is over 60 years of <lb/>age. This percentage is expected to increase to 11.4% by 2026. The population aged 60 and over is expected <lb/>to rise from 101.5 million in 2011 to 227.4 million in 2036 as a result of an increased lifespan [1]. Across all <lb/>age groups, the prescription of medications is a crucial component of health care. Because of age-related <lb/>physiological changes, altered pharmacokinetics, and altered pharmacodynamic effects of many drugs, <lb/>prescribing for the elderly is always difficult. Furthermore, as older patients are excluded from clinical trials, <lb/>information regarding the efficacy and safety of numerous medications frequently remains limited [2-4]. <lb/>Numerous illnesses like diabetes mellitus, hypertension, Alzheimer&apos;s disease, Parkinson&apos;s disease, vascular <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/></body>

			<front>Open Access Original <lb/>Article <lb/>DOI: 10.7759/cureus.52770 <lb/>How to cite this article <lb/>Keche Y, Gaikwad N R, Wasnik P N, et al. (January 23, 2024) Analysis of Drugs Prescribed to Elderly Patients in a Tertiary Health Care Center in <lb/>Raipur, Central India: An Observational Study. Cureus 16(1): e52770. DOI 10.7759/cureus.52770 <lb/></front>

			<body>dementia, stroke, visual impairment, cataracts and macular degeneration, dietary issues, and diminished <lb/>financial resources result in decreased dosage compliance among the elderly [5]. There is a decline in renal <lb/>function with ageing. The biomarkers of renal function are altered by malnutrition, a low-protein diet, and <lb/>diminished muscle mass in elderly people. Therefore, normal-appearing urea and creatinine levels <lb/>underestimate the severity of renal disease in the elderly [6-8]. Important alterations connected with the <lb/>ageing process include, for example, forgetting to take one&apos;s medication due to cognitive and memory <lb/>decline associated with a vascular or other disease. Due to lost income and higher costs, sickness causes <lb/>economic strain. Until proven otherwise, all symptoms in an older patient are presumed to be adverse <lb/>medication reactions. The elderly have a high potential for both beneficial and adverse drug effects [5]. <lb/>Polypharmacy in the elderly leads to various adverse drug interactions, which necessitate the modification <lb/>of drug therapy in them to avoid adverse drug interactions [9]. <lb/>Correct use of medication is necessary to maximize therapeutic benefits while improving patients&apos; quality of <lb/>life. Drug prescriptions that are given haphazardly can lead to dangerous and ineffective treatment, <lb/>medication non-adherence, greater rates of mortality and morbidity, disease progression, and higher <lb/>expenditures on healthcare. Identifying the form, extent, and intensity of irrational drug use is a critical first <lb/>step toward improvement in the rational use of medicines or limiting irrational medicine use [10,11]. <lb/>According to a study conducted in Indonesia by Puspitasari et al., the most often prescribed antimicrobials in <lb/>primary care settings were amoxicillin, chloramphenicol, ciprofloxacin, clindamycin, and oxytetracycline, <lb/>while the most commonly prescribed other drugs were paracetamol, chlorpheniramine maleate, amlodipine, <lb/>vitamin B complex, and glyceryl guaiacolat [12]. Abdulah et al. also noted similar results in another study <lb/>conducted in Indonesia [13]. This study was carried out to gain more insight into the prescription pattern of <lb/>drugs used for the elderly at a tertiary care teaching hospital in India. <lb/>Materials And Methods <lb/>This was a cross-sectional observation study for prescription analysis of drugs prescribed to elderly patients <lb/>for chronic diseases. Patients aged above 65 years of age who attended the Medicine Outpatient Department <lb/>(OPD) of All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Raipur, India, and who were on two or more drugs for <lb/>chronic diseases were included in this study. Severely ill patients were excluded from this study. The study <lb/>was approved by the Institute Ethics Committee, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Raipur, India <lb/>(approval number: 780/IEC-AIIMSRPR/2019, dated September 23, 2019). The study is registered with the <lb/>Clinical Trial Registry of India (CTRI/2020/01/022852) [14]. <lb/>Data collection <lb/>The data for this study were collected from 234 elderly patients. The drug data used in this analysis was <lb/>already collected under the previously published study by the authors [15], which was unused earlier. Drug <lb/>data were collected from the study participants after obtaining written informed consent from each <lb/>participant. Collected data included demographic details, dietary history, personal history, history of <lb/>constipation, peptic ulcer disease, and details of the drug, including the generic name of the drug, dose and <lb/>duration of therapy, and prescription pattern. The number of drugs prescribed in every prescription was <lb/>taken into account to calculate the incidence of polypharmacy. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>An analysis of prescribed drug data and other factors in 234 elderly patients was carried out. Data were <lb/>expressed as numbers, proportions, or the mean and standard deviation as applicable. Descriptive statistics <lb/>were applied for analysis. All data was analyzed by use of Microsoft Excel (Microsoft Corporation, Redmond, <lb/>Washington, United States). <lb/>Results <lb/>The data of 234 elderly patients was analysed in this cross-sectional observational study, which included <lb/>1298 prescriptions. The average number of drugs prescribed per prescription was 5.92 ± 2.31 as a single drug <lb/>and 2.15 ± 1.41 as fixed-dose combinations. <lb/>The mean age of the elderly patients in this study was 68.70 ± 5.76, and male patients were more (n=141, <lb/>60.26%). Forty patients (17.09%) were illiterate, 82 (35.04%) patients were unemployed, and 124 (53%) were <lb/>retired from their jobs. A total of 171 (73%) elderly patients had an income of less than Rs. 5,000 per month. <lb/>In the study population, 18 (7.96%) were alcoholics and 56 (23.93%) were smokers. A total of 81 (35%) had a <lb/>history of constipation, 25 (11%) had a history of peptic ulcer disease, and 62 (27%) were taking over-the-<lb/>counter (OTC) herbal medications (Table 1). <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">2024 Keche et al. Cureus 16(1): e52770. DOI 10.7759/cureus.52770 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 of 11 <lb/></page>

			<body>Demographic parameter <lb/>Value <lb/>Age (years), mean ± SD <lb/>68.70 ± 5.76 <lb/>Sex, n (%) <lb/>Male <lb/>141 (60.26) <lb/>Female <lb/>93 (39.74) <lb/>Education status, n (%) <lb/>Illiterate <lb/>40 (17.09) <lb/>Primary School <lb/>55 (23.50) <lb/>Secondary School <lb/>70 (29.91) <lb/>Graduate <lb/>49 (20.94) <lb/>Postgraduate <lb/>20 (8.54) <lb/>Occupation status, n (%) <lb/>Unemployed <lb/>82 (35.04) <lb/>Govt service <lb/>2 (0.85) <lb/>Private sector <lb/>20 (8.54) <lb/>Retired <lb/>124 (52.99) <lb/>Any other <lb/>6 (2.56) <lb/>Monthly income (INR), n (%) <lb/>Less than 4999 per month <lb/>171 (73.08) <lb/>5000-9999 <lb/>8 (3.42) <lb/>10000-49999 <lb/>47 (20.09) <lb/>50000-100000 <lb/>4 (1.71) <lb/>&gt;100000 -04 <lb/>4 (1.71) <lb/>History of diet, n (%) <lb/>Mixed diet <lb/>95 (40.60) <lb/>Vegetarian diet <lb/>139 (59.40) <lb/>Adequate protein in diet <lb/>204 (87.18) <lb/>Personal History, n (%) <lb/>Alcohol <lb/>18 (7.69) <lb/>Smoking <lb/>56 (23.93) <lb/>History of constipation <lb/>81 (34.62) <lb/>History of acute peptic disease <lb/>25 (10.68) <lb/>Taking herbal OTC medications <lb/>62 (26.50) <lb/>TABLE 1: Demographic data of study participants (N=234) <lb/>OTC: over the counter; INR: Indian Rupee <lb/>Data given as frequency (percentage) unless otherwise marked. <lb/>Of the elderly in this study, 21 were suffering from diabetes mellitus (DM) (8.97%), 64 had DM with <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">2024 Keche et al. Cureus 16(1): e52770. DOI 10.7759/cureus.52770 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 of 11 <lb/></page>

			<body>hypertension (27.35%), and 59 had DM with other comorbidities (25.21%). Thirty-one (13.25%) had only <lb/>hypertension and 42 (17.95%) had hypertension with comorbidities (Table 2). <lb/>S.No. Diagnoses <lb/>Frequency <lb/>(Percentage) <lb/>Diabetes mellitus <lb/>21 (8.97) <lb/>1 <lb/>Diabetes with hypertension <lb/>64 (27.35) <lb/>2 <lb/>Diabetes mellitus with hypertension and other co-morbidities like osteoarthritis, chronic kidney disease, benign hypertrophy of <lb/>prostate, coronary artery disease, myocardial infarction, hypothyroidism, diabetic kidney disease, total knee replacement, <lb/>rheumatoid arthritis, Parkinson&apos;s disease, asthma, intervertebral prolapse of disk, cerebrovascular accident, systemic lupus <lb/>erythematous, psychosis with dementia, retinopathy, Nephropathy, heart failure, fatty liver, chronic obstructive pulmonary <lb/>disease, cholelithiasis <lb/>59 (25.21) <lb/>3 <lb/>Hypertension <lb/>31(13.25) <lb/>4 <lb/>Hypertension with other co-morbidities like Parkinson&apos;s disease, hypothyroidism, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, <lb/>herpetic neuralgia ,osteoarthritis, coronary artery disease, left ventricular hypertrophy, migraine, aortic regurgitation, asthma, <lb/>hemiparesis, acute coronary syndrome, piles, benign hypertrophy of prostate, vertigo, peptic ulcer, cerebrovascular accident, <lb/>seizure, dyslipidemia, depression, cholestasis, myocardial infarction, polyarthritis, stroke, myasthenia gravis, rheumatoid <lb/>arthritis, generalized pruritis <lb/>42 (17.95) <lb/>5 <lb/>Bronchial asthma <lb/>(0.85) <lb/>6 <lb/>Sepsis, chronic kidney disease, acute kidney injury, severe anemia <lb/>(0.42) <lb/>7 <lb/>Old cerebrovascular accident with hemiparesis and seizure <lb/>(0.85) <lb/>8 <lb/>Rheumatoid arthritis with interstitial lung disease, chronic pain, cervical spondylosis, intervertebral prolapse of disk <lb/>(1.71) <lb/>9 <lb/>Post-menopausal syndrome <lb/>(0.42) <lb/>10 <lb/>Hepatitis C virus infection, chronic liver disease with portal hypertension, ascites <lb/>(0.42) <lb/>11 <lb/>Chorea <lb/>(0.42) <lb/>12 <lb/>Coronary artery disease, Parkinson <lb/>(0.42) <lb/>13 <lb/>Chronic liver disease with portal hypertension, subclinical hypothyroidism <lb/>(0.42) <lb/>14 <lb/>Vertigo <lb/>(0.42) <lb/>15 <lb/>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease with tuberculosis <lb/>(0.42) <lb/>16 <lb/>Post coronary artery bypass graft <lb/>(0.42) <lb/>TABLE 2: Diagnoses of study participants (N=234) <lb/>Telmisartan (n=58, 9.40%) and telmisartan combined with other drugs (n=82, 13.29%) were the most <lb/>commonly prescribed drugs for cardiovascular disease. Other drugs predominantly prescribed were beta-<lb/>blockers (n=42, 6.81%), calcium channel blockers (n=78, 12.64%), diuretics (n=31, 5.02%), and angiotensin-<lb/>converting enzyme inhibitors (ACEIs) (n=14, 2.27%). Aspirin and statins alone or in combination (n=172, <lb/>27.88%) were most commonly prescribed for the prophylaxis of cardiovascular diseases (Table 3). <lb/>S.No. Name of the drugs <lb/>Frequency (percentage) <lb/>Drugs for cardiovascular and renal diseases (N=617) <lb/>1. <lb/>Telmisartan <lb/>58 (9.40) <lb/>2. <lb/>Telmisartan and amlodipine or cinlidipine or metoprolol or nebivolol or chlorthalidone or hydrochlorothiazide <lb/>79 (12.80) <lb/>3. <lb/>Telmisartan and amlodipine and hydrochlorthiazide <lb/>2 (0.32) <lb/>4. <lb/>Telmisartan and cilnidipine and chlorothalidone <lb/>1 (0.16) <lb/>5. <lb/>Labetolol or bisprolol or carvedilol or nebivolol <lb/>13 (2.11) <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">2024 Keche et al. Cureus 16(1): e52770. DOI 10.7759/cureus.52770 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 of 11 <lb/></page>

			<body>6. <lb/>Metoprolol <lb/>(4.70) <lb/>7. <lb/>Ramipril <lb/>(2.11) <lb/>8. <lb/>Ramipril and hydrochlorothiazide or Cilnidipine and metoprolol <lb/>(0.32) <lb/>9. <lb/>Cilnidipine <lb/>(3.57) <lb/>10. <lb/>Aspirin <lb/>(2.59) <lb/>11. <lb/>Aspirin and atorvastatin or rosuvastatin <lb/>(9.24) <lb/>12. <lb/>Aspirin and clopidogrel <lb/>(0.32) <lb/>13. <lb/>Aspirin and rosuvastatin and clopidogrel <lb/>(0.32) <lb/>14. <lb/>Aspirin and atorvastatin and clopidogrel <lb/>(0.65) <lb/>15. <lb/>Dabigatran <lb/>(0.16) <lb/>16. <lb/>Atorvastatin <lb/>(12.89) <lb/>17. <lb/>Rosuvastatin <lb/>(1.94) <lb/>18. <lb/>Erythropoietin <lb/>(0.32) <lb/>19. <lb/>K bind sachet <lb/>(0.32) <lb/>20. <lb/>Spironolactone and torasemide or furosemide <lb/>(1.45) <lb/>21. <lb/>Nitroglycerine or Isosorbide mononitrate or Isosorbide dinitrate <lb/>(1.30) <lb/>22. <lb/>Furosemide or torasemide or chlorthalidone <lb/>(3.56) <lb/>23. <lb/>Nicorandil <lb/>(1.78) <lb/>24. <lb/>Amlodipine or Nifedipine <lb/>(8.10) <lb/>25. <lb/>Amlodipine and atenolol or hydrochlorothiazide <lb/>(0.97) <lb/>26. <lb/>Ranolazine <lb/>(0.49) <lb/>Drugs for Diabetes (N=262) <lb/>27. <lb/>Insulin <lb/>(9.16) <lb/>28. <lb/>Metformin <lb/>(18.70) <lb/>29. <lb/>Glimepiride <lb/>(11.07) <lb/>30. <lb/>Glimepiride and metformin <lb/>(20.23) <lb/>31. <lb/>Metformin and voglibose or sitagliptin or teneligliptin or vildagliptin or gliclazide <lb/>(10.31) <lb/>32. <lb/>Metformin and glimepiride and pioglitazone <lb/>(1.91) <lb/>33. <lb/>Metformin and glimepiride and voglibose <lb/>(1.53) <lb/>34. <lb/>Teneligliptin <lb/>(10.69) <lb/>35. <lb/>Linagliptin or vildagliptin <lb/>(1.15) <lb/>36. <lb/>Empagliflozin or repaglinide <lb/>(0.76) <lb/>37. <lb/>Gliclazide <lb/>(0.76) <lb/>38. <lb/>Acarbose or voglibose <lb/>(11.83) <lb/>39. <lb/>Pioglitazone <lb/>(1.91) <lb/>TABLE 3: Drug prescribing pattern for cardiovascular diseases, renal diseases, and diabetes <lb/>Metformin (n=49, 18.70%) and glimepiride (n=29, 11.07%) were commonly used drugs for diabetes, either <lb/>alone or in combination (n=89, 33.97). Teneligliptin (n=28, 10.69%) and alpha-glucosidase inhibitors like <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">2024 Keche et al. Cureus 16(1): e52770. DOI 10.7759/cureus.52770 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 of 11 <lb/></page>

            <body>acarbose and voglibose (n=31, 11.83%) were also commonly used for the treatment of diabetes in the elderly <lb/>(Table 3). <lb/>Clonazepam (n=14, 16.47%) was the most commonly prescribed drug for CNS diseases. Gabapentin and <lb/>pregabalin alone or in combinations (n=28, 32.94%) were used for the treatment of neuropathies (Table 4). <lb/>S.No. <lb/>Name of the drugs <lb/>Frequency (percentage) <lb/>Sedatives, hypnotics, psychopharmacological agents (N=85) <lb/>1. <lb/>Alprazolam or lorazepam <lb/>2 (2.35) <lb/>2. <lb/>Clonazepam <lb/>14 (16.47) <lb/>3. <lb/>Zolpidem <lb/>2 (2.35) <lb/>4. <lb/>Carbamazepine or oxcarbazepine <lb/>3 (3.53) <lb/>5. <lb/>Topiramate <lb/>1 (1.18) <lb/>6. <lb/>Valproate <lb/>1 (1.18) <lb/>7. <lb/>Gabapentin and nortriptyline <lb/>9 (10.59) <lb/>8. <lb/>Pregabalin <lb/>2 (2.35) <lb/>9. <lb/>Pregabalin and methylcobalamin <lb/>15 (17.65) <lb/>10. <lb/>Pregabalin and nortriptyline <lb/>2 (2.35) <lb/>11. <lb/>Donepazil and memantine <lb/>1 (1.18) <lb/>12. <lb/>Donepezil <lb/>3 (3.53) <lb/>13. <lb/>Levodopa and carbidopa <lb/>8 (9.41) <lb/>14. <lb/>Olanzapine or quetiapine <lb/>3 (3.53) <lb/>15. <lb/>Levosulpiride <lb/>1 (1.18) <lb/>16. <lb/>Amitriptyline <lb/>5 (5.88) <lb/>17. <lb/>Escitalopram or levetiracetam or sertraline <lb/>6 (7.06) <lb/>18. <lb/>Escitalopram and clonazepam <lb/>1 (1.18) <lb/>19. <lb/>Fluoxetine or paroxetine <lb/>2 (2.35) <lb/>20. <lb/>Taurine and acetylcysteine <lb/>1 (1.18) <lb/>21. <lb/>Tetrabenazine <lb/>1 (1.18) <lb/>22. <lb/>Trihexyphenidyl <lb/>1 (1.18) <lb/>23. <lb/>Pyridostigmine <lb/>1 (1.18) <lb/>Analgesics and anti-inflammatory drugs (N=45) <lb/>24. <lb/>Aceclofenac and paracetamol <lb/>2 (4.44) <lb/>25. <lb/>Chlorzoxazone and ibuprofen and paracetamol <lb/>1 (2.22) <lb/>26. <lb/>Trypsin and chymotrypsin <lb/>1 (2.22) <lb/>27. <lb/>Etoricoxib <lb/>1 (2.22) <lb/>28. <lb/>Ibuprofen and paracetamol <lb/>1 (2.22) <lb/>29. <lb/>Indomethacin <lb/>3 (6.67) <lb/>30. <lb/>Mefenamic acid and dicyclomine <lb/>1 (2.22) <lb/>31. <lb/>Tramadol <lb/>6 (13.33) <lb/>32. <lb/>Tramadol and paracetamol <lb/>1 (2.22) <lb/></body>

            <note place="footnote">2024 Keche et al. Cureus 16(1): e52770. DOI 10.7759/cureus.52770 <lb/></note>

            <page>6 of 11 <lb/></page>

            <body>33. <lb/>Paracetamol <lb/>28 (62.22) <lb/>Antihistaminics and autocoids (N=8) <lb/>33. <lb/>Cetirizine <lb/>2 (25) <lb/>34. <lb/>Cyproheptadine <lb/>2 (25) <lb/>35. <lb/>Betahistine hydrochloride <lb/>1 (12.50) <lb/>36. <lb/>Propranolol and flunarizine <lb/>1 (12.50) <lb/>37. <lb/>Cinnarizine or cinnarizine and dimenhydrinate <lb/>2 (25) <lb/>Corticosteroids (N=3) <lb/>38. <lb/>Decadurabolin <lb/>1 (33.33) <lb/>39. <lb/>Prednisolone <lb/>2 (66.67) <lb/>TABLE 4: Drug prescribing pattern for central nervous system diseases, inflammation, and <lb/>autocoids <lb/>Pantoprazole alone or in combination with domperidone (n=82, 64.57%) was most commonly prescribed for <lb/>acid-peptic disease. Thyroxin (n=26, 100%) was most commonly prescribed for hypothyroidism, and vitamin <lb/>preparations (n=118, 62.43%) were also most commonly prescribed to elderly patients (Table 5). <lb/>S.No. <lb/>Name of the drugs <lb/>Frequency (percentage) <lb/>Gastro-intestinal disorders (N=127) <lb/>1. <lb/>Pantoprazole <lb/>42 (33.07) <lb/>2. <lb/>Pantoprazole and domperidone <lb/>38 (29.92) <lb/>3. <lb/>Pantoprazole and levosulpiride or Esomeprazole and domperidone <lb/>2 (1.57) <lb/>4. <lb/>Omeprazole <lb/>8 (6.30) <lb/>5. <lb/>Omeprazole and tinidazole and amoxicillin <lb/>1 (0.79) <lb/>6. <lb/>Ranitidine <lb/>2 (1.57) <lb/>7. <lb/>Antacid syrups <lb/>4 (3.15) <lb/>8. <lb/>Isabghol husk or bisacodyl <lb/>3 (2.36) <lb/>9. <lb/>Milk of magnesia and liquid paraffin syrup <lb/>12 (9.45) <lb/>10. <lb/>Lactulose syrup <lb/>11 (8.66) <lb/>11. <lb/>Ondansetron <lb/>3 (2.36) <lb/>12. <lb/>Ursodeoxycholic acid <lb/>1 (0.79) <lb/>Endocrine diseases (N=26) <lb/>13. <lb/>Thyroxin <lb/>26 (100) <lb/>Arthritis (N=15) <lb/>14. <lb/>Hydroxychloroquine <lb/>9 (60) <lb/>15. <lb/>Ibandronic acid <lb/>2 (13.33) <lb/>16. <lb/>Methotrexate <lb/>4 (16.67) <lb/>Respiratory diseases (N=11) <lb/>17. <lb/>Omalizumab <lb/>1 (9.09) <lb/>18. <lb/>Doxofylline <lb/>4 (36.36) <lb/></body>

            <note place="footnote">2024 Keche et al. Cureus 16(1): e52770. DOI 10.7759/cureus.52770 <lb/></note>

            <page>7 of 11 <lb/></page>

            <body>19. <lb/>Etophylline and theophylline <lb/>1 (9.09) <lb/>20. <lb/>Montelukast <lb/>2 (18.18) <lb/>21. <lb/>Montelukast and levocetirizine <lb/>3 (27.27) <lb/>Hypertrophy of prostate (N=22) <lb/>22. <lb/>Dutasteride <lb/>1 (4.55) <lb/>23. <lb/>Tamsulosin <lb/>7 (31.81) <lb/>24. <lb/>Tamsulosin and dutasteride <lb/>8 (36.36) <lb/>25. <lb/>Silodosin <lb/>1 (4.55) <lb/>26. <lb/>Solifenacin <lb/>5 (22.73) <lb/>Miscellaneous drugs (N=189) <lb/>27. <lb/>Disodium hydrogen citrate syrup <lb/>3 (1.59) <lb/>28. <lb/>Cough syrup <lb/>3 (1.59) <lb/>29. <lb/>Glycerol syrup <lb/>1 (0.53) <lb/>30. <lb/>Sulfasalazine <lb/>6 (3.17) <lb/>31. <lb/>Febuxostat <lb/>3 (1.59) <lb/>32. <lb/>Flavoxate hydrochloride <lb/>1 (0.53) <lb/>33. <lb/>Iron and folic acid <lb/>7 (3.70) <lb/>34. <lb/>Herbal drugs <lb/>2 (1.06) <lb/>35. <lb/>Topical formulations <lb/>38 (20.11) <lb/>36. <lb/>Vitamins <lb/>118 (62.42) <lb/>37. <lb/>Antimicrobials <lb/>7 (3.70) <lb/>TABLE 5: Drug prescribing pattern for other drugs/disorders <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In this cross-sectional observational study, the average number of drugs prescribed per prescription was 5.92 <lb/>± 2.31 for single drugs and 2.15 ± 1.41 for fixed-dose combinations. The mean age of the elderly patients in <lb/>this study was 68.70 ± 5.76, and 141 (60.26%) patients were male. In a study carried out at Pudducherry, <lb/>India, the average number of drugs prescribed per prescription was 9.4 ± 0.31, which was higher than our <lb/>study [16], but in two other studies, the average number of drugs per prescription was comparable with our <lb/>study [17,18]. The male preponderance that was seen in our study was similar to other studies [16-18]. The <lb/>average number of drugs per prescription is an important index of the scope for review and intervention in <lb/>prescribing practices. <lb/>In the current study, around 82 (35%) patients were unemployed, 124 (53%) were retired, and 171 (73%) had <lb/>an income of less than Rs. 5,000 per month. The majority of patients in a study by Lourdu et al. were found <lb/>to be retired from their jobs, making them dependent on their families for financial support [16]. <lb/>A total of 81 (35%) of the elderly had a history of constipation in the present study. The history of <lb/>constipation is important, as the majority of patients in this study were suffering from hypertension or other <lb/>cardiovascular diseases. Calcium channel blockers (CCBs) like amlodipine and nifedipine are routinely <lb/>prescribed to these patients, and it was observed in a study conducted by Saha et al. that there is an <lb/>increased risk of developing constipation with the use of these drugs [19]. Hence, precautions need to be <lb/>taken while prescribing CCBs to the elderly, especially those who have a history of constipation. Twenty-five <lb/>(11%) had a history of peptic ulcer disease in the current study, but the prescription encounters were more <lb/>for pantoprazole alone or in combination. As per STOPP (Screening Tool of Older Persons&apos; <lb/>Prescriptions)/START (Screening Tool to Alert to Right Treatment) criteria, if proton pump inhibitors (PPI) <lb/>are prescribed for uncomplicated peptic ulcer disease at full therapeutic dosage for more than eight weeks, <lb/>there is usually a need for dose reduction, earlier discontinuation, or H2 antagonist maintenance therapy <lb/>[20]. PPI is to be prescribed carefully if therapy goes beyond eight weeks. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">2024 Keche et al. Cureus 16(1): e52770. DOI 10.7759/cureus.52770 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 of 11 <lb/></page>

			<body>About one-fourth of elderly patients in the current study were taking OTC herbal medications. Scherf-<lb/>Clavel, in a review of OTC medications, identified the groups that were frequently involved in drug-drug <lb/>interactions (DDIs) as NSAIDs, food supplements, antacids, PPIs, H2 antihistamines, laxatives, antidiarrheal <lb/>drugs, and herbal drugs [21]. To avoid adverse drug interactions and appropriate prescriptions of drugs in <lb/>elderly patients, STOPP/START criteria and Beers criteria can be used [15]. <lb/>In the current study, the elderly were suffering from diabetes mellitus, hypertension, and other <lb/>comorbidities. There are regional differences in the prevalence of diseases among the elderly. For example, <lb/>in Jammu and Kashmir, there is a higher prevalence of cardiovascular, respiratory, endocrine, and <lb/>gastrointestinal diseases [16]. In contrast, a study conducted in south India found that respiratory conditions <lb/>like bronchial asthma, chronic bronchitis, and COPD were more common, and drugs used for the treatment <lb/>of these diseases were more commonly prescribed [17]. In a study in Karnataka, the commonly involved <lb/>target organ system that necessitated the need for admission was the respiratory system followed by <lb/>neurological and cardiovascular systems [18]. <lb/>Telmisartan by itself or in combination with other drugs, beta-blockers, calcium channel blockers, diuretics, <lb/>and ACE inhibitors were more commonly prescribed for the treatment and prophylaxis of cardiovascular <lb/>diseases in our study. Aspirin and statins alone or in combinations were most commonly prescribed for <lb/>prophylaxis of cardiovascular diseases. Metformin, glimepiride alone or in combinations, teneligliptin, and <lb/>alpha-glucosidase inhibitors like acarbose and voglibose were also commonly used for the treatment of <lb/>diabetes in the current study. Pantoprazole alone or in combination with domperidone for acid peptic <lb/>disease and thyroxin for hypothyroidism and vitamin preparations were also most commonly prescribed to <lb/>the elderly patients in the current study. Prescription patterns are different in studies carried out in different <lb/>parts of India. Drugs that were prescribed to the elderly in other studies included Deriphyllin most <lb/>commonly, paracetamol, ranitidine, amlodipine, vitamin B12, furosemide, metformin, dexamethasone, <lb/>doxycycline, ceftriaxone, alprazolam, salbutamol, ferrous sulphate, mannitol, and spironolactone [16,18]. <lb/>Benzodiazepines like clonazepam were more commonly prescribed to the elderly than z-hypnotics in the <lb/>current study. In a study carried out in Taiwan that analysed the data on the 10-year use of z hypnotics, it <lb/>was found that there was an increase in the use of z hypnotics in Taiwan [22]. Age has been identified in <lb/>multiple studies as a major risk factor for falls and fractures in the elderly population, particularly those <lb/>associated with z-hypnotics [23,24]. There is insufficient evidence about the safety and efficiency of z-<lb/>hypnotics in the elderly population. Exposure to zolpidem has been linked to an elevated risk of fracture in <lb/>the senior population, with individuals aged over 85 years having the highest risk. <lb/>Additionally, benzodiazepines increase the risk of drug misuse, dependency, tolerance, falls, and fractures <lb/>[25,26]. To avoid adverse events related to hypnotics, appropriate use of these drugs needs to be carried out. <lb/>Gabapentin and pregabalin alone or in combination were used for the treatment of neuropathies in the <lb/>current study. <lb/>Drug utilization and prescription analysis studies are helpful in finding the prescription pattern and <lb/>appropriate and rational use of drugs in the elderly. Apart from drug utilization studies and drug <lb/>appropriateness studies, there is a need for studies on the quality of life of elderly patients, which is affected <lb/>greatly due to various factors like comorbidities, mental status, and physical activity [27]. <lb/>Strengths and limitations <lb/>This study provides insight into the current trends of drug prescription among the elderly in the Indian <lb/>population for chronic diseases. Limitations include the fact that this is a single-centre study, and the <lb/>findings of this study cannot be generalised to other parts of the country. As this study involves only the <lb/>analysis of drugs prescribed to the elderly in terms of names of the drugs prescribed, proportions of drugs, <lb/>and diagnoses of the disease, the inappropriateness of the prescription cannot be commented on. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>Polypharmacy was observed in this study and shows that there is a need for watchfulness for DDIs. As <lb/>cardiovascular diseases and diabetes, with or without comorbidities, were more commonly observed, drugs <lb/>used for treatment and prophylaxis of these ailments were seen to be commonly prescribed in this study. As <lb/>benzodiazepines are prescribed to elderly people, care for falls and fractures needs to be taken, and <lb/>instructions must be given to the patient to avoid falls. PPIs should not be prescribed rampantly to the <lb/>elderly, and similarly, vitamin preparations should be prescribed judiciously. Regular prescription analysis <lb/>of drugs prescribed to the elderly will help in the appropriate and rational use of drugs and will also help <lb/>observe changes in prescription trends in the elderly. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Additional Information <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>All authors have reviewed the final version to be published and agreed to be accountable for all aspects of the <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">2024 Keche et al. Cureus 16(1): e52770. DOI 10.7759/cureus.52770 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 of 11 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">work. <lb/>Concept and design: Yogendra Keche, Nitin R. Gaikwad, Suryaprakash Dhaneria <lb/>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data: Yogendra Keche, Nitin R. Gaikwad, Preetam N. Wasnik, <lb/>Keshao Nagpure, Md Sabah Siddiqui, Apoorva Joshi, Gevesh Dewangan, Jhasaketan Meher, Pranita Das <lb/>Drafting of the manuscript: Yogendra Keche, Apoorva Joshi, Suryaprakash Dhaneria, Pranita Das <lb/>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content: Yogendra Keche, Nitin R. <lb/>Gaikwad, Preetam N. Wasnik, Keshao Nagpure, Md Sabah Siddiqui, Gevesh Dewangan, Jhasaketan Meher <lb/>Supervision: Yogendra Keche, Suryaprakash Dhaneria <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Disclosures <lb/>Human subjects: Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Institute Ethics <lb/>Committee, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, Raipur, India issued approval 780/IEC-AIIMSRPR/2019, <lb/>dated September 23, 2019. Animal subjects: All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve <lb/>animal subjects or tissue. Conflicts of interest: In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all <lb/>authors declare the following: Payment/services info: All authors have declared that no financial support <lb/>was received from any organization for the submitted work. Financial relationships: All authors have <lb/>declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any <lb/>organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work. Other relationships: All authors have <lb/>declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the <lb/>submitted work. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We are highly grateful to all the faculty members and senior residents for helping in the recruitment of <lb/>patients for this study. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Population Statistics. Misnistry fo Statistics and Programme Implementation, New Delhi, India; 2022. <lb/>https://www.mospi.gov.in/sites/default/files/publication_reports/women-men22/PopulationStatistics22.pdf. <lb/>2. Gallagher P, Barry P, O&apos;Mahony D: Inappropriate prescribing in the elderly . J Clin Pharm Ther. 2007, 32:113-<lb/>21. 10.1111/j.1365-2710.2007.00793.x <lb/>3. Bugeja G, Kumar A, Banerjee AK: Exclusion of elderly people from clinical research: a descriptive study of <lb/>published reports. BMJ. 1997, 315:1059. 10.1136/bmj.315.7115.1059 <lb/>4. Weng MC, Tsai CF, Sheu KL, et al.: The impact of number of drugs prescribed on the risk of potentially <lb/>inappropriate medication among outpatient older adults with chronic diseases. QJM. 2013, 106:1009-15. <lb/>10.1093/qjmed/hct141 <lb/>5. Katzung BG: Special aspects of geriatric pharmacology . Basic &amp; Clinical Pharmacology. Katzung BG, <lb/>Vanderah TW (ed): McGraw-Hill Companies, Inc., New York, NY; 2018. 1058-67. <lb/>6. MacLennan WJ, Martin P, Mason BJ: Protein intake and serum albumin levels in the elderly . Gerontology. <lb/>1977, 23:360-7. 10.1159/000212209 <lb/>7. Greenblatt DJ, Sellers EM, Koch-Weser J: Importance of protein binding for the interpretation of serum or <lb/>plasma drug concentrations. J Clin Pharmacol. 1982, 22:259-63. 10.1002/j.1552-4604.1982.tb02671.x <lb/>8. Corti MC, Guralnik JM, Salive ME, Sorkin JD: Serum albumin level and physical disability as predictors of <lb/>mortality in older persons. JAMA. 1994, 272:1036-42. <lb/>9. Keche Y, Gaikwad N, Dhaneria S, Joshi A: Evaluation of the prescribed drugs to elderly in a tertiary <lb/>healthcare center for possible drug interactions with investigational drugs for COVID-19 treatment. J Res <lb/>Pharm Pract. 2020, 9:212-7. <lb/>10. Barkus A, Lisauskienė I: Inappropriate habits of antibiotic use among medical specialists and students in <lb/>Vilnius. Acta Med Litu. 2016, 23:135-41. 10.6001/actamedica.v23i2.3330 <lb/>11. Sköldunger A, Fastbom J, Wimo A, Fratiglioni L, Johnell K: Impact of inappropriate drug use on <lb/>hospitalizations, mortality, and costs in older persons and persons with dementia: findings from the SNAC <lb/>study. Drugs Aging. 2015, 32:671-8. 10.1007/s40266-015-0287-4 <lb/>12. Puspitasari IM, Rano K AH: Sinuraya evaluation of medication use patterns among geriatric patients using <lb/>World Health Organization prescribing indicators. PCPR. 2019, 4:51-5. <lb/>13. Abdulah R, Insani WN, Putri NE, Purba HP, Destiani DP, Barliana MI: Pattern of medication use in geriatric <lb/>patients at primary health care facilities in Karawang, Indonesia. Drug Healthc Patient Saf. 2019, 11:1-5. <lb/>10.2147/DHPS.S187829 <lb/>14. Usefulness of STOPP/START Criteria and Beers Criteria for Prescribing in Geriatric Patients in a Tertiary <lb/>Heath Care Center, Raipur, Central India. (2021). Accessed: January 6, 2024: <lb/>https://www.ctri.nic.in/Clinicaltrials/showallp.php? <lb/>mid1=39486&amp;EncHid=&amp;userName=STOPP/START%20Criteria. <lb/>15. Keche YN, Gaikwad NR, Wasnik PN, Siddiqui S, Nagpure K, Dhaneria S: Usefulness of STOPP/START criteria <lb/>and Beers criteria for prescribing in geriatric patients in a tertiary health care center, Raipur, Central India. J <lb/>Family Med Prim Care. 2022, 11:7064-71. 10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_733_22 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">2024 Keche et al. Cureus 16(1): e52770. DOI 10.7759/cureus.52770 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 of 11 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>16. Lourdu JA, Venkata NK, Udhayalakshmi TJ, Sawadkar MS: Drug utilization patterns of geriatric patients <lb/>admitted in the medicine department of a tertiary care hospital. Int J Pharm Life Sci. 2013, 4:3087-92. <lb/>17. Kumar R., Bhat NK, Kumar D, Gupta S: Drug prescribing pattern in elderly patients admitted in medicine <lb/>department of a tertiary care teaching hospital in North India-a prescription evaluation study. JK Science. <lb/>2017, 19:233-7. <lb/>18. Jyothsna CS, Nagarajaiah BH, Shiva Kumar KM: Drug utilization pattern in geriatric inpatients of medicine <lb/>wards at a government tertiary care hospital. Natl J Physiol Pharm Pharmacol. 2019, 9:320-7. <lb/>19. Saha L, Shekhar Gautam C: The effect of amlodipine alone and in combination with atenolol on bowel habit <lb/>in patients with hypertension: an observation. ISRN Gastroenterol. 2011, 2011:757141. <lb/>10.5402/2011/757141 <lb/>20. O&apos;Mahony D, Cherubini A, Guiteras AR, et al.: STOPP/START criteria for potentially inappropriate <lb/>prescribing in older people: version 3. Eur Geriatr Med. 2023, 14:625-32. 10.1007/s41999-023-00777-y <lb/>21. Scherf-Clavel O: Drug-drug interactions with over-the-counter medicines: mind the unprescribed . Ther <lb/>Drug Monit. 2022, 44:253-74. 10.1097/FTD.0000000000000924 <lb/>22. Fei-Yuan Hsiao, Pei-Hua Hsieh, Churn-Shiouh Gau: Ten-year trend in prescriptions of z-hypnotics among <lb/>the elderly: a nationwide, cross-sectional study in Taiwan. J Clin Gerontol Geriatr. 2013, 4:37-41. <lb/>10.1016/j.jcgg.2012.12.001 <lb/>23. Kang DY, Park S, Rhee CW, Kim YJ, Choi NK, Lee J, Park BJ: Zolpidem use and risk of fracture in elderly <lb/>insomnia patients. J Prev Med Public Health. 2012, 45:219-26. 10.3961/jpmph.2012.45.4.219 <lb/>24. Frost M, Abrahamsen B, Masud T, Brixen K: Risk factors for fracture in elderly men: a population-based <lb/>prospective study. Osteoporos Int. 2012, 23:521-31. 10.1007/s00198-011-1575-4 <lb/>25. Hausken AM, Furu K, Skurtveit S, Engeland A, Bramness JG: Starting insomnia treatment: the use of <lb/>benzodiazepines versus z-hypnotics. A prescription database study of predictors. Eur J Clin Pharmacol. <lb/>2009, 65:295-301. 10.1007/s00228-008-0565-8 <lb/>26. Paterniti S, Dufouil C, Alpérovitch A: Long-term benzodiazepine use and cognitive decline in the elderly: <lb/>the epidemiology of vascular aging study. J Clin Psychopharmacol. 2002, 22:285-93. 10.1097/00004714-<lb/>200206000-00009 <lb/>27. Keche Y, Wasnik P, Nagpure K, Gaikwad N, Dhaneria S, Siddiqui S, Joshi A: Health-related quality of life <lb/>(HRQoL) in elderly patients attending at tertiary health care centre in central India during 1st wave of <lb/>COVID-19 pandemic: a prospective observational study. OBM Geriatrics. 2022, 6:10. <lb/>10.21926/obm.geriatr.2204216 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">2024 Keche et al. Cureus 16(1): e52770. DOI 10.7759/cureus.52770 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 of 11 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
