<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title level="a">Unveiling the strong positive relationship: Maternal characteristics and neonatal outcomes in the Better Outcomes in Labour Difficulty (BOLD) study – a secondary analysis validating neonatal near miss classification</title>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Vicky</forename>
          <surname>Nogueira-Pileggi</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Olufemi T</forename>
          <surname>Oladapo</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>João Paulo</forename>
          <surname>Souza</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Hayala Cristina</forename>
          <surname>Cavenague de Souza</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Cynthia</forename>
          <surname>Pileggi-Castro</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Lawal O</forename>
          <surname>Oyeneyin</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Livia</forename>
          <surname>Oliveira-Ciabati</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>Francisco</forename>
          <surname>Barbosa</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <author>
        <persName>
          <forename>José Simon</forename>
          <surname>Camelo</surname>
        </persName>
      </author>
      <respStmt>
        <persName xml:id="kazuyo">Kazuyo</persName>
        <resp>Annotator</resp>
      </respStmt>
    </titleStmt>
    <editionStmt>
      <edition>
        <date when="2025-11-06T10:17:43.828Z">11/6/2025 10:17:43 AM</date>
        <title>corrections</title>
      <idno type="fileref">10.7189$1$jogh.14.04024</idno></edition>
    </editionStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <publisher>International Society of Global Health</publisher>
      <availability>
        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
      </availability>
      <date type="publication">2024</date>
      <idno type="DOI">10.7189/jogh.14.04024</idno>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <bibl>Vicky Nogueira-Pileggi, Olufemi T Oladapo, João Paulo Souza, Hayala Cristina Cavenague de Souza, Cynthia Pileggi-Castro, Lawal O Oyeneyin, Livia Oliveira-Ciabati, Francisco Barbosa, José Simon Camelo. (2024). Unveiling the strong positive relationship: Maternal characteristics and neonatal outcomes in the Better Outcomes in Labour Difficulty (BOLD) study – a secondary analysis validating neonatal near miss classification. Journal of Global Health, 14(None), None. DOI: 10.7189/jogh.14.04024</bibl>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <appInfo>
      <application version="1.0" ident="pdf-tei-editor" type="editor">
        <ref target="https://github.com/mpilhlt/pdf-tei-editor"/>
      </application>
      <application version="0.8.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-06T10:16:55.867166Z" type="extractor">
        <desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
        <label type="revision">eb7768b</label>
        <label type="flavor">default</label>
        <label type="variant-id">grobid.training.segmentation</label>
        <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
      </application>
    </appInfo>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change when="2025-11-06T10:16:55.867166Z" status="draft">
      <desc>Generated with createTraining API</desc>
    </change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
  <text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <front>PAPERS <lb/>www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04012 <lb/>1 <lb/>2024 • Vol. 14 • 04012 <lb/>The congenital birth defects burden in children <lb/>younger than 14 years of age, 1990 -2019: An <lb/>age-period-cohort analysis of the global burden <lb/>of disease study <lb/>Electronic supplementary material: <lb/>The online version of this article contains supplementary material. <lb/>Cite as: Li X, Hou M, Kong X, Lv J, Yang C, Li D, Zhang R. The congenital birth defects <lb/>burden in children younger than 14 years of age, 1990 -2019: An age-period-cohort analysis <lb/>of the global burden of disease study. J Glob Health 2024;14:04012. <lb/>Xin-yu Li 1 *, Meng-jie Hou 1 *, <lb/>Xiang-meng Kong 2 *, Jia-jie Lv 3 , <lb/>Cheng-hao Yang 4 , Da-tao Li 1 , <lb/>Ru-hong Zhang 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Plastic and Reconstruc-<lb/>tive Surgery, Shanghai Ninth People&apos;s <lb/>Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University <lb/>School of Medicine, Shanghai, China <lb/>2 Department of Cardiology, Shanghai <lb/>Ninth People&apos;s Hospital, Shanghai Jiao <lb/>Tong University School of Medicine, <lb/>Shanghai, China <lb/>3 <lb/>Department of Vascular surgery, Shang-<lb/>hai Ninth People&apos;s Hospital, Shanghai <lb/>Jiao Tong University School of Medi-<lb/>cine, Shanghai, China <lb/>4 <lb/>Department of Vascular surgery, Putuo <lb/>People&apos;s Hospital, School of Medicine, <lb/>Tongji University, Shanghai, China <lb/>*Joint first authorship. <lb/>Correspondence to: <lb/>Da-tao Li, PhD <lb/>Department of Plastic and Reconstructive <lb/>Surgery, Shanghai Ninth People&apos;s Hospital, <lb/>Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of <lb/>Medicine <lb/>Shanghai <lb/>China <lb/>lidt112045@sh9hospital.org.cn <lb/>Ru-hong Zhang, PhD <lb/>Department of Plastic and Reconstructive <lb/>Surgery, Shanghai Ninth People&apos;s Hospital, <lb/>Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of <lb/>Medicine <lb/>Shanghai <lb/>China <lb/>zhangruhong@163.com <lb/>Background This study aims to delineate the burden of congenital birth defects <lb/>(CBDs) in children under 14 years of age from 1990 to 2019, using an age-pe-<lb/>riod-cohort framework to analyse data from the Global Burden of Disease Study <lb/>(GBD). <lb/>Methods Data on prevalence cases, age-standardised prevalence rates (ASPRs), <lb/>death cases, and age-standardised death rates (ASDRs) of congenital birth de-<lb/>fects (CBDs) from 1990 to 2019 were obtained from GBD 2019. Using this data <lb/>set, we conducted an age-period-cohort (APC) analysis to examine patterns and <lb/>trends in mortality, prevalence, and disability-adjusted life years (DALYs) asso-<lb/>ciated with CBDs, while exploring correlations with age, time periods, and gen-<lb/>erational birth cohorts. Furthermore, to quantify the temporal trends, we cal-<lb/>culated the estimated annual percentage changes (EAPCs) for these parameters. <lb/>Results The global prevalence of CBDs decreased from 1404.22 to 1301.66 per <lb/>100 000 with an EAPC of -0.18% from 1990 to 2019. CBD mortality decreased <lb/>by 42.52% between 1990 and 2019, with the global age-standardised death rate <lb/>declining from 49.72 to 25.58 per 100 000. The age-standardised DALY rate de-<lb/>creased from 4529.16 to 2393.61 per 100 000. Prevalence declined most notably <lb/>among older children. The risk of CBDs reached its lowest during adolescence <lb/>(10-14 years) across all regions. The most recent period (2015-2019) showed <lb/>a reduced risk of prevalence compared to 2000-2004. Earlier birth cohorts dis-<lb/>played declining tendencies followed by slight increases in risk. <lb/>Conclusions This study demonstrates encouraging global reductions in the bur-<lb/>den of CBDs among children over the past three decades. Prevalence, mortality, <lb/>and DALYs attributable to CBDs have exhibited downward trajectories, although <lb/>regional disparities remain. APC analysis provides valuable insights to inform <lb/>prevention and management strategies for pediatric CBDs. <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s) <lb/></front>

    <body>Congenital birth defects (CBDs) encompass a diverse range of structural, func-<lb/>tional, and metabolic malformations present at birth, with significant implica-<lb/>tions for global child health [1]. CBDs are a leading cause of neonatal mortality <lb/>and contribute to long-term disability, with varying degrees of severity affecting <lb/>individual quality of life, family dynamics, and health care systems [2]. The etio-<lb/>logical landscape of CBDs is multifaceted, including genetic, environmental, and <lb/>maternal health factors, which can influence the occurrence and severity of these <lb/>conditions [3]. Worldwide, it is estimated that CBDs affect approximately six per-<lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Li et al. <lb/>PAPERS <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04012 <lb/></note>

    <page>2 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04012 <lb/></note>

    <body>cent of infants, leading to the demise of 240 000 newborns within the first 28 days of life and causing the <lb/>death of an additional 170 000 children between the ages of one and 59 months annually [3]. In the year <lb/>2019, these defects emerged as the fourth leading cause of mortality among children under the age of five, <lb/>comprising close to 10% of all fatalities in this age group [4]. However, comprehensive epidemiological pro-<lb/>filing of congenital birth defects, especially regarding disease burden metrics like prevalence, mortality and <lb/>disability-adjusted life years, remains lacking. Quantifying and analysing recent global and regional trends <lb/>is critical for informing resource allocation and tailored prevention strategies to address this substantial yet <lb/>under-examined child health challenge. <lb/>To bridge the existing gap in our understanding, the Global Burden of Disease (GBD) study -launched by <lb/>the World Health Organization and the World Bank -provides an extensive epidemiological analysis detail-<lb/>ing the mortality and morbidity attributable to major diseases, injuries, and their potential risk factors [5,6]. <lb/>By harnessing the most recent GBD 2019 data set along with the age-period-cohort (APC) model, we eluci-<lb/>date the longitudinal trends in the burden of CBDs among children under 14 years of age spanning the last <lb/>three decades. The insights gleaned from these trends will deepen our understanding of the factors contrib-<lb/>uting to the burden of CBDs in this young demographic. Furthermore, this knowledge will underpin the <lb/>theoretical basis for tailoring and enhancing personalised intervention strategies which can be adapted for <lb/>national health care systems and individual patient needs. <lb/>METHODS <lb/>Data source and definitions <lb/>This was a cross-sectional study that used data from the GBD 2019 in 204 countries and territories. Children <lb/>who were aged 0 to 14 years were included in the analysis. Our study utilises data from the 2019 iteration of <lb/>the GBD 2019, adhering closely to its established methodological framework and analytical strategies. The <lb/>GBD 2019 study amassed epidemiological data across a consortium of 204 nations and territories, evaluat-<lb/>ing the prevalence of 369 diseases and injuries alongside 87 risk determinants. The intricate methodologies <lb/>that form the foundation of the GBD 2019 have been extensively delineated in preceding scholarly works <lb/>[7,8]. The GBD collaborative applies a methodical approach, harnessing comprehensive data sets spanning <lb/>various age cohorts, temporal spans, geographic locales, and multifarious health-related factors. These data <lb/>sets are meticulously analysed using harmonised analytical tools within a Bayesian inferential framework. <lb/>Such a stratagem affords the advantage of leveraging extant data sets to surmount the barriers posed by <lb/>the paucity of complete health care information access within the populace. Consequently, this facilitates <lb/>a more informed quantification of the global disease burden, ensuring that estimations are inclusive of all <lb/>constituent countries and territories [9-11]. <lb/>The cataloging system of the GBD delineates a meticulous and non-overlapping compendium of health con-<lb/>ditions, systematically classified into four echelons of hierarchy [12]. Within this classification, birth defects <lb/>are enumerated under the primary rubric of non-communicable diseases at level 1, with a further specifi-<lb/>cation under other non-communicable conditions at level 2. The subgroup identified as Congenital Birth <lb/>Defects (B12.1) incorporates eleven conditions at level 4. <lb/>In adherence to ethical frameworks, the study was executed in concordance with the principles established <lb/>by the Declaration of Helsinki. Utilising de-identified aggregated data sets obviated the need for individual <lb/>informed consent, a stipulation that was reviewed and sanctioned by the Institutional Review Board of the <lb/>University of Washington, which approved the waiver of consent for this research (https://www.healthdata. <lb/>org/Data-tools-practices/data-practices/ihme-free-charge-non-commercial-user-agreement). <lb/>The objective of this investigation was to scrutinise the trends in prevalence, disability-adjusted life years <lb/>(DALYs), and mortality across three decades, from 1990 to 2019. This analysis employed a suite of met-<lb/>rics, comprising the absolute number of deaths, incidence of prevalence, age-standardised prevalence rates, <lb/>age-standardised mortality rates, and estimated annual percentage changes (EAPCs). These measures were <lb/>directly procured from the GBD 2019. The 95% uncertainty intervals (UIs) were delineated by the 2.5th <lb/>and 97.5th percentiles, representing the 25th and 975th values, respectively, from the ordered set of 1000 <lb/>estimates. These intervals were computed in accordance with the algorithmic methodology employed by <lb/>the GBD study. <lb/>To ensure consistency, the study population was divided into six age groups: 0-6 days, 7-27 days, 28-364 <lb/>days,1-4 years,5-9 years and 10-14 years. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">The congenital birth defects in children <lb/>PAPERS <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04012 <lb/></note>

    <page>3 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04012 <lb/></note>

    <body>State-level data <lb/>Moreover, the analysis integrated the Socio-demographic index (SDI) for each nation and region under study. <lb/>The SDI is a synthetic metric that aggregates three core dimensions: per capita income, average educational <lb/>attainment, and fertility rates among females younger than 25 years [13]. The SDI is quantified on a con-<lb/>tinuum from 0 to 1, where ascending values correlate with augmented socioeconomic status. Consequent <lb/>to the computation of these values, we stratified all nations and regions into quintiles predicated on their <lb/>SDI metrics for the year 2019, thereby facilitating a comparison across a spectrum of socio-demographic <lb/>echelons, from high to low. <lb/>Analysis of overall temporal trends in CBDs disorders in children <lb/>Between 1990 and 2019, we analysed the temporal trends in the prevalence of CBDs by employing raw counts <lb/>and ASR. To ascertain the age-specific prevalence rates (ASPR) of CBDs in pediatric cohorts, we utilised <lb/>direct age standardisation, operating under the premise that the rates conform to a weighted summation of <lb/>independent Poisson random variables, as detailed in our referenced methodologies [14,15]. Moreover, we <lb/>conducted an examination of the proportional distribution of CBDs prevalence in children, dividing the <lb/>subjects into three distinct age groups: under five years, five-nine years, and 10-14 years. This categorisa-<lb/>tion facilitated an illustration of the temporal changes in the age-specific prevalence of CBDs. <lb/>Age-Period-Cohort analysis of CBDs disorders in children <lb/>In this study, we utilised the Age-Period-Cohort (APC) model framework, an advanced statistical tool her-<lb/>alded for its applications beyond traditional analysis in health and social sciences [16]. This model was <lb/>employed to dissect the temporal dynamics of prevalence with a particular focus on age, period, and birth <lb/>cohort [16,17]. The APC model has been extensively applied in epidemiological investigations of non-com-<lb/>municable diseases, including congenital heart disease, as evidenced by prior research [17,18]. Despite its <lb/>utility, the model is not without its challenges; a notable issue is the &apos;identification problem&apos; which arises <lb/>due to the exact collinearity among the three variables, as age is the difference between period and birth <lb/>cohort, rendering the independent effects of each variable statistically indistinguishable [16]. To address <lb/>this conundrum, our approach involved generating estimable parameters and functions of the APC model <lb/>without resorting to the imposition of arbitrary constraints [18,19]. The intricate methodological nuances <lb/>of the APC model and its implementation have been expansively explicated in the existing literature [20]. <lb/>In our study, we harnessed population and disease burden data for CBDs to feed the APC model. To main-<lb/>tain methodological rigor, the APC model necessitates that the intervals for age be congruent with those of <lb/>the period; thus, we used 5-year age groups aligned with 5-year calendar periods for consistency. Given <lb/>that the childhood age span was delineated as 0-14 years, we segmented this into three age groups: &lt;5 <lb/>years, five-nine years, and 10-14 years, for subsequent analysis. The temporal scope of the study, span-<lb/>ning from 1990 to 2019, was accordingly divided into six quinquennial periods: 1990-1994, 1995-1999, <lb/>2000-2004, 2005-2009, 2010-2014, and 2015-2019. To complement this, we delineated 12 partially <lb/>overlapping decennial birth cohorts: 1940-1949, 1945-1954, 1950-1959, 1955-1964, 1960-1969, 1965-<lb/>1974, 1970-1979, 1975-1984, 1980-1989, 1985-1994, 1990-1999, and 1995-2004. This stratification <lb/>allowed for a detailed examination of the influences exerted by age, period, and cohort on the trends in <lb/>congenital birth defects. <lb/>The APC model offers a nuanced approach to analysing disease prevalence, providing estimates on both <lb/>the overarching temporal trend and age-specific trends within the prevalence data. The general tempo-<lb/>ral trend, or the net drift, is quantified as the annual percentage change of prevalence, encapsulating the <lb/>aggregated effects attributable to calendar time and consecutive birth cohorts. Conversely, the age-specific <lb/>temporal trend, referred to as the local drift, reflects the annual percentage change within each age group. <lb/>A seemingly minor drift value, expressed as a percentage change per year, can translate to a significant <lb/>alteration in the modeled prevalence rate over a three-decade span. To test the statistical significance of <lb/>these trends, a Wald χ 2 test was employed. Within the confines of the APC model, age effects are mani-<lb/>fested through the modeled longitudinal age-specific rates across various birth cohorts, which are subse-<lb/>quently adjusted for deviations arising from different periods. Conversely, the period and cohort effects <lb/>are elucidated as relative risks of prevalence, calculated as the ratio of age-specific rates for each period <lb/>or cohort against a designated reference. The selection of this reference period or cohort is arbitrary and <lb/>does not influence the interpretability of the results. To forecast the disease burden from 1990 to 2045, we <lb/>employed a log-linear age-period-cohort model. This approach limits linear trend projection and controls <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Li et al. <lb/>PAPERS <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04012 <lb/></note>

    <page>4 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04012 <lb/></note>

    <body>exponential growth, making it appropriate for adapting to current trends. The model was executed in R, <lb/>utilising the NORDPRED package [21]. <lb/>The entirety of the analyses, as well as the visual representations of the data, were conducted using R soft-<lb/>ware, version 4.2.1. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Prevalence <lb/>The global prevalence of CBDs was estimated at 255 090.41 cases (95% UI = 224 268.68-289 785.27) in 2019 <lb/>(Table 1, Figure 1). The global ASPR of CBDs has declined from 1404.22 per 100 000 population to 1301.66 <lb/>per 100 000 population in three decades, with an EAPC of -0.18 (95% confidence interval (CI) = -0.22 <lb/>to -0.14, Table 1). Globally, the incidence of CBDs is higher in males than in females, with the ratio <lb/>between males and females reaching its maximum at ages 10-14 (Figure S1 in the Online Supplementary <lb/>Document). ASPR decreased in all SDI regions, with the lowest (1200.14 per 100 000) in the low-middle <lb/>SDI region and the highest in the low SDI region (1457.05 per 100 000) (Table 1, Figure 1). Across the five <lb/>SDI&apos;s, the incidence was higher in men than women in most age groups (except for low SDI, Figure S1 in the <lb/>Online Supplementary Document). Among the 21 regions, high-income Asia Pacific (1847.11 per 100 000) <lb/>and Oceania (1655.95 per 100 000) had significantly higher ASPR than the others (Table 1, Figure 2). <lb/>Mortality <lb/>In 2019, the number of deaths attributed to CBDs reached 5013.33 (95% UI = 3986.27-6491.41), marking <lb/>a 42.52% decrease from the 1990 count of 8721.54 (95% UI = 5904.33-12 972.58) as shown in Table S1 in <lb/>the Online Supplementary Document. The ASDR of the five SDI regions decreased with time. The ASDR <lb/>of the High SDI was the lowest (8.33 per 100 000), while the ASDR of the low SDI was the highest (42.93 <lb/>per 100 000) (Table S1 in the Online Supplementary Document). In the five SDI, the ratio of male to <lb/>female ASDR showed a decreasing trend with the increase of age (Figure S2 in the Online Supplementary <lb/>Document). In 30 years, the 2019 ASDR in 21 regions was lower than the 1990 ASDR. Western sub-Saha-<lb/>ran Africa had the highest ASRD in 2019 (51.93 per 100 000) (Figure S3A in the Online Supplementary <lb/>Document). <lb/>DALYs <lb/>In 2019, the number of DALYs attributed to CBDs reached 469 083.64 (95% UI = 379 015.44-601 305.28) as <lb/>shown in Table S2 in the Online Supplementary Document. This was accompanied by an EAPC of -1.93 <lb/>(95% CI = -2.02 to -1.84) as reflected in Table S2 in the Online Supplementary Document. Notably, the <lb/>male-female DALY ratio declined with age, suggesting that CBDs impose a higher burden on female chil-<lb/>dren older than one year (Figure S4 in the Online Supplementary Document). The age-standardised DALY <lb/>rate of the five SDI regions decreased with time. The EAPC of High-Middle SDI was the largest (-3.13; 95% <lb/>CI = -3.21 to -3.05), the age-standardised DALY rate of High SDI was the lowest, and the age-standardised <lb/>DALY rate of Low SDI was the highest (Figure 1, Figure S3B and Table S2 in the Online Supplementary <lb/>Document). <lb/>Temporal trends in CBDs burden in children across age groups <lb/>We quantified the annual changes in the prevalence of CBD disorders across various age cohorts. Utilising <lb/>the APC model, we elucidated the local drifts in prevalence (Figure 3, panel A and Table S3 in the Online <lb/>Supplementary Document). Our analysis reveals a discernible decrease in the prevalence of CBD disorders <lb/>among children, particularly evident when comparing the five-nine-year age group with the 10-14-year <lb/>cohort. This declining trend becomes more pronounced as children age, especially from the five-nine to the <lb/>10-14-year groups. Notably, the smallest decrease was observed in the 10-14-year cohort. We observed that <lb/>most SDI regions show a downward trend. In female children with High SDI, aged 0-14 years, the trend <lb/>of local drift is manifested first by rising and then falling (all values are less than 0) (Figure 3, panel A). <lb/>Temporal changes in the age distribution of CBD disorders prevalence in children were illustrated in Figure <lb/>3, panel B. We found that globally and in all five SDI regions, the proportion of CBD disorders prevalence <lb/>in children aged 0-4 years remained dominant over the 30-year period. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">The congenital birth defects in children <lb/>PAPERS <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04012 <lb/></note>

    <page>5 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04012 <lb/></note>

    <body>Table 1. Prevalence of congenital birth defects between 1990 and 2019 in 0 to 14 y at the global and regional level <lb/>1990 <lb/>2019 <lb/>EAPC (95% CI) <lb/>No (95% UI) <lb/>ASR <lb/>No (95% UI) <lb/>ASR <lb/>Overall <lb/>246 295.52 (215 257.15-282 139.56) <lb/>1404.22 (1227.26-1608.58) <lb/>255 090.41 (224 268.68-289 785.27) <lb/>1301.66 (1144.38-1478.7) <lb/>-0.18 (-0.22 to -0.14) <lb/>Female <lb/>116 426.82 (102 278.76-132 691.7) <lb/>1364.47 (1198.66-1555.08) <lb/>121 995.89 (107 441.14-138 327.91) <lb/>1286.81 (1133.28-1459.08) <lb/>-0.12 (-0.17 to -0.07) <lb/>Male <lb/>129 868.70 (112 902.2-149 408.13) <lb/>1441.88 (1253.51-1658.82) <lb/>133 094.52 (117 065.29-151 384.06) <lb/>1315.58 (1157.14-1496.36) <lb/>-0.24 (-0.27 to -0.2) <lb/>High SDI <lb/>23 598.47 (20 907.72-26 718.56) <lb/>1366.63 (1210.81-1547.32) <lb/>20 717.66 (18 448.72-23 202.99) <lb/>1268.98 (1130.01-1421.21) <lb/>-0.32 (-0.39 to -0.24) <lb/>High-middle SDI <lb/>41 352.26 (36 390.61-46 954.16) <lb/>1362.33 (1198.87-1546.88) <lb/>31 380.59 (27 879.64-35 310.89) <lb/>1279.70 (1136.93-1439.98) <lb/>-0.02 (-0.12 to 0.09) <lb/>Middle SDI <lb/>80 640.62 (70 190.49-92 906.97) <lb/>1387.11 (1207.36-1598.11) <lb/>71 089.02 (62 567.84-81021.79) <lb/>1284.12 (1130.2-1463.55) <lb/>-0.15 (-0.23 to -0.07) <lb/>Low-middle SDI <lb/>61 388.39 (53 342.16-71 162.9) <lb/>1353.96 (1176.5-1569.55) <lb/>62 833.18 (55 461.06-71 796.33) <lb/>1200.14 (1059.33-1371.34) <lb/>-0.37 (-0.4 to -0.34) <lb/>Low SDI <lb/>39 183.06 (33 538.19-45 708.12) <lb/>1619.03 (1385.78-1888.64) <lb/>68 900.39 (59 388.84-79 827.77) <lb/>1457.05 (1255.91-1688.13) <lb/>-0.37 (-0.39 to -0.34) <lb/>Andean Latin America <lb/>1375.27 (1178.54-1626.17) <lb/>914.14 (783.37-1080.91) <lb/>1652.37 (1418.71-1937.1) <lb/>913.37 (784.21-1070.76) <lb/>-0.03 (-0.09 to 0.04) <lb/>Australasia <lb/>518.89 (450.71-595.54) <lb/>1131.21 (982.57-1298.31) <lb/>627.93 (549-723.47) <lb/>1145.13 (1001.19-1319.35) <lb/>0.05 (-0.02 to 0.12) <lb/>Caribbean <lb/>1214.59 (1035.89-1416.42) <lb/>1064.17 (907.6-1241) <lb/>1385.54 (1185.72-1612.59) <lb/>1185.88 (1014.85-1380.21) <lb/>0.38 (0.33 to 0.44) <lb/>Central Asia <lb/>3293.93 (2834.29-3795.68) <lb/>1319.90 (1135.72-1520.95) <lb/>3505.68 (3017.38-4067.93) <lb/>1303.24 (1121.71-1512.25) <lb/>0.25 (0.06 to 0.45) <lb/>Central Europe <lb/>3742.15 (3276.39-4260.23) <lb/>1292.78 (1131.87-1471.76) <lb/>2033.21 (1778.09-2303.94) <lb/>1152.84 (1008.19-1306.35) <lb/>-0.1 (-0.25 to 0.06) <lb/>Central Latin America <lb/>10 179.31 (8562.43-12147.42) <lb/>1588.10 (1335.85-1895.15) <lb/>9871.14 (8306.57-11 677.13) <lb/>1509.62 (1270.35-1785.81) <lb/>-0.32 (-0.42 to -0.21) <lb/>Central sub-Saharan Africa <lb/>4239.41 (3614.24-4974.14) <lb/>1641.08 (1399.08-1925.5) <lb/>8161.73 (6956.77-9538.35) <lb/>1430.61 (1219.4-1671.91) <lb/>-0.34 (-0.43 to -0.26) <lb/>East Asia <lb/>47 420.51 (40 813.07-55 108.77) <lb/>1415.79 (1218.52-1645.34) <lb/>32 750.09 (28 834.78-37 126.12) <lb/>1407.36 (1239.11-1595.41) <lb/>0.12 (-0.05 to 0.29) <lb/>Eastern Europe <lb/>7632.25 (6641.12-8699.31) <lb/>1483.44 (1290.8-1690.83) <lb/>4915.13 (4301.94-5591.65) <lb/>1326.29 (1160.83-1508.84) <lb/>0.23 (0.01 to 0.46) <lb/>Eastern sub-Saharan Africa <lb/>15 332.36 (12 813.92-18 152.02) <lb/>1696.67 (1417.98-2008.69) <lb/>25 030.54 (21 222.51-29 403.21) <lb/>1417.92 (1202.2-1665.62) <lb/>-0.63 (-0.66 to -0.6) <lb/>High-income Asia Pacific <lb/>6676.81 (5692.95-7898.27) <lb/>1894.53 (1615.36-2241.12) <lb/>4311.61 (3677.38-5053.04) <lb/>1847.11 (1575.41-2164.75) <lb/>-0.09 (-0.14 to -0.04) <lb/>High-income North America <lb/>7157.58 (6334.08-8033.46) <lb/>1165.52 (1031.41-1308.12) <lb/>7182.60 (6380.11-8017.12) <lb/>1083.83 (962.73-1209.75) <lb/>-0.48 (-0.61 to -0.35) <lb/>North Africa and Middle East <lb/>23 685.56 (20 507.39-27 680.94) <lb/>1648.01 (1426.88-1926) <lb/>26 944.25 (23 456.2-31 224.38) <lb/>1532.29 (1333.93-1775.7) <lb/>-0.20 (-0.25 to -0.15) <lb/>Oceania <lb/>405.79 (339.93-479.84) <lb/>1544.29 (1293.67-1826.1) <lb/>799.82 (674.88-946.93) <lb/>1655.95 (1397.28-1960.53) <lb/>0.34 (0.29 to 0.39) <lb/>South Asia <lb/>51 812.50 (45 212.35-59 928.65) <lb/>1180.29 (1029.94-1365.18) <lb/>52 418.90 (46 487.97-59 637.18) <lb/>1014.38 (899.6-1154.06) <lb/>-0.45 (-0.5 to -0.39) <lb/>Southeast Asia <lb/>25 701.31 (21 543.05-30 690.54) <lb/>1492.27 (1250.83-1781.95) <lb/>22 338 (19 144.49-26 231.22) <lb/>1323.55 (1134.33-1554.23) <lb/>-0.30 (-0.34 to -0.26) <lb/>Southern Latin America <lb/>2178.11 (1873.07-2548.59) <lb/>1458.89 (1254.58-1707.04) <lb/>2274.25 (1961.96-2652.26) <lb/>1525.72 (1316.22-1779.32) <lb/>0.35 (0.28 to 0.42) <lb/>Southern sub-Saharan Africa <lb/>2834.65 (2320.04-3455.57) <lb/>1391.22 (1138.66-1695.96) <lb/>2995.89 (2515.18-3630.09) <lb/>1268.68 (1065.11-1537.24) <lb/>0.15 (-0.01 to 0.31) <lb/>Tropical Latin America <lb/>5947.90 (5122.72-6917.85) <lb/>1102.59 (949.63-1282.4) <lb/>5031.89 (4355.96-5851.68) <lb/>1012.19 (876.23-1177.1) <lb/>-0.36 (-0.46 to -0.27) <lb/>Western Europe <lb/>9268.05 (8260.87-10 410.91) <lb/>1304.41 (1162.66-1465.26) <lb/>8633.03 (7720.24-9665.19) <lb/>1254.41 (1121.77-1404.38) <lb/>-0.15 (-0.21 to -0.08) <lb/>Western sub-Saharan Africa <lb/>15 678.59 (13 207.6-18 673.26) <lb/>1785.37 (1503.99-2126.38) <lb/>32 226.84 (27 350.04-38 203.79) <lb/>1624.90 (1379.01-1926.27) <lb/>-0.34 (-0.4 to -0.28) <lb/>ASR -age-standardised rate, CI -confidence interval, EAPC -estimated annual percentage change, SDI -sociodemographic index, UI -uncertainty interval <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Li et al. <lb/>PAPERS <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04012 <lb/></note>

    <page>6 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04012 <lb/></note>

    <body>Figure 1. Trends in congenital birth defects prevalence, deaths and disability-adjusted life-years from 1990 to 2019. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">The congenital birth defects in children <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PAPERS <lb/>www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04012 <lb/></note>

    <page>7 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04012 <lb/></note>

    <body>Age, period and birth cohort effects on CBDs disorders prevalence in children <lb/>The age, period, and birth cohort effects derived from the APC model are illustrated in Figure 4, Figure 5, <lb/>and Figure 6, and detailed in the online Tables S4-6 in the Online Supplementary Document. A consis-<lb/>tent pattern emerged in the age effects across regions stratified by SDI, indicating that the nadir of risk was <lb/>observed during the adolescent phase, specifically at ages 10-14 years, with a subsequent decrease in risk <lb/>as age advanced. The high-middle SDI region, middle SDI region, and low-middle SDI generally had lower <lb/>period risks over the study period. When assessing the period effects, individuals in the 2015-2019 period <lb/>exhibited a decrease in risk compared to those in the baseline period of 2000-2004; this decrease ranged <lb/>from a relative risk of 0.98 (95% CI = 0.97-0.99) in regions with high SDI, to 0.93 (95% CI = 0.92-0.94) in <lb/>both high-middle and middle SDI regions. <lb/>Analysis of birth cohort effects revealed a global pattern characterised by an initial decline followed by an <lb/>increased risk of disorder prevalence in successive birth cohorts. This trend was largely mirrored across most <lb/>regions classified by SDI, with high SDI regions exhibiting particularly reduced risks in prevalence among <lb/>successive birth cohorts. When comparing individuals born in the 1995-2004 reference cohort to those <lb/>born in the 2010-2019 cohort, the relative cohort risk increased slightly, ranging from 1.02 (95% CI = 1.01-<lb/>1.03) in the high-middle SDI region to 1.01 (95% CI = 1.00-1.02) in the middle SDI region <lb/>Future burden of CBDs <lb/>Figure S5 in the Online Supplementary Document displays the forecasted trends in DALYs for global and <lb/>five SDI categories related to CBD. The projection indicates a global decline in DALYs for children under 14 <lb/>years affected by CBD. This downward trend is mirrored in countries categorised as high-middle, low-mid-<lb/>dle, and middle SDI. In contrast, countries with a low SDI demonstrate a consistent upward trend in DALYs <lb/>associated with CBD. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>CBDs represent the predominant etiology of neonatal mortality, with an estimated 10-20% of such fatali-<lb/>ties being attributable to these anomalies [22,23]. Accurate and comprehensive monitoring of the burden or <lb/>Figure 2. The global disease burden of congenital birth defects prevalence for both sexes in 204 countries and territories. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Li et al. <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PAPERS <lb/>2024 • Vol. 14 • 04012 <lb/></note>

    <page>8 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04012 <lb/></note>

    <body>Figure 3. Local drift and age distribution of prevalence from 1990 to 2019 for congenital birth defects disorders across SDI <lb/>quintiles. Panel A. Local drift of prevalence from 1990 to 2019 for congenital birth defects disorders for 3 age groups. The <lb/>dots and shaded areas denote the local drift (i.e. annual percentage change of age-specific prevalence, % per year) and their <lb/>corresponding 95% confidence intervals. Panel B. Temporal changes in age distribution of congenital birth defects disor-<lb/>ders prevalence from 1990 to 2019. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">The congenital birth defects in children <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PAPERS <lb/>www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04012 <lb/></note>

    <page>9 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04012 <lb/></note>

    <body>Figure 4. Age effects are illustrated by the fitted longitudinal age-specific rates for a given number of birth cohorts adjusted for period devi-<lb/>ations. The dots and shaded areas denote the prevalence rates or rate ratios and their corresponding 95% confidence intervals. <lb/>Figure 5. Period effects are illustrated by the period relative risk of prevalence (prevalence rate ratio) and calculated as the ratio of age-spe-<lb/>cific rates from 1990-1994 period to 2015-2019 period, with the reference period set at 2000-2004. The dots and shaded areas denote <lb/>the prevalence rates or rate ratios and their corresponding 95% confidence intervals. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Li et al. <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PAPERS <lb/>2024 • Vol. 14 • 04012 <lb/></note>

    <page>10 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04012 <lb/></note>

    <body>incidence of CBDs is an essential part of achieving the Millennium Goal of reducing infant mortality and the <lb/>2030 Sustainable Development Goals [24]. To our knowledge, this is the first use of APC models to analyse <lb/>time trends in CBD on a global scale, allowing comparisons between different regions. <lb/>Globally, our results demonstrate an overall decline in the ASPR of CBDs, from 1404.22 to 1301.66 per <lb/>100 000 population between 1990 and 2019. This downward trajectory was mirrored across all SDI regions, <lb/>albeit with variances in the magnitude of the decrement. However, notable disparities remain, as under-<lb/>scored by the substantially higher ASPR observed in 2019 among the low SDI region (1457.05 per 100 000) <lb/>compared to high SDI areas (1268.98 per 100 000). Closing this gap by enhancing health care provisions <lb/>and resources for underprivileged populations must constitute a pivotal public health priority. The observed <lb/>disparities likely stem from a range of inequalities spanning from preconception to postnatal care. Factors <lb/>contributing to these disparities include limited access to prenatal screening and diagnostic services, varia-<lb/>tions in the quality of antenatal care, differing sociocultural perceptions of disability, a lack of safe delivery <lb/>facilities, and inadequate rehabilitative services in less advantaged areas [17,25]. The disparities in global <lb/>health care are exacerbated by unequal access to ultrasound technology, variability in perinatal diagnostics, <lb/>and diverse approaches to pregnancy and postnatal care [26]. Recognising these discrepancies across differ-<lb/>ent regions and populations is vital for understanding and addressing global health disparities. Of course, <lb/>due to the inherent limitations of the study&apos;s observational design, caution is required in establishing cau-<lb/>sality, and the results may not be universally applicable due to differences in data reliability and availability <lb/>across regions. Severe birth anomalies are often identified with reliability, yet milder conditions frequently <lb/>remain undiagnosed and untreated, especially in disadvantaged areas. To tackle these multifaceted issues, <lb/>an integrated approach encompassing health care provision, community mobilisation, and policy innovation <lb/>is essential. Key interventions should focus on ensuring equitable access to comprehensive preconception <lb/>counselling, effective antenatal screening, safe childbirth practices, quality rehabilitative services, and robust <lb/>social support networks [27]. A deep understanding of the specific barriers and enablers unique to each <lb/>community is critical for devising and implementing context-sensitive strategies. Collaborative, action-ori-<lb/>ented research, coupled with strong global partnerships, is imperative to catalyse meaningful progress in <lb/>mitigating these health disparities [26]. <lb/>Figure 6. Birth cohort effects are illustrated by the cohort relative risk of prevalence (prevalence rate ratio) and calculated as the ratio of <lb/>age-specific rates from 1975-1984 cohort to 2010-2019 cohort, with the reference cohort set at 1985-1994. The dots and shaded areas <lb/>denote the prevalence rates or rate ratios and their corresponding 95% confidence intervals. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">The congenital birth defects in children <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PAPERS <lb/>www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04012 <lb/></note>

    <page>11 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04012 <lb/></note>

    <body>Beyond prevalence, our analysis demonstrates an encouraging 42.52% reduction in CBD-related mortal-<lb/>ity between 1990 and 2019, with the global ASDR decreasing from 49.72 to 25.58 per 100 000 over this <lb/>period. This trend of ameliorating ASDRs was reflected across all SDI regions classified by socioeconomic <lb/>development. The disease burden imposed by CBDs, as quantified through DALYs, demonstrated conso-<lb/>nant trends. Plausible drivers include medical advancements enabling improved survival for children born <lb/>with congenital disorders, coupled with greater accessibility to these interventions over time [28]. However, <lb/>notable disparities remain, as underscored by the substantially higher ASDR observed in 2019 among the <lb/>low SDI region (42.93 per 100 000) compared to high SDI areas (8.33 per 100 000). Closing this gap by <lb/>enhancing health care provisions and resources for underprivileged populations must constitute a pivotal <lb/>public health priority [17]. <lb/>APC model analysis allowed granular insights into the temporal dynamics shaping CBD burden across strat-<lb/>ified age groups. Local drift values, reflecting the annual percent change in age-specific prevalence, pointed <lb/>to a progressive decline in the prevalence of CBDs with ascending age. This reduction was most pronounced <lb/>when comparing the 10-14-year age bracket against the preceding five-nine-year category. The mitigation of <lb/>prevalence among older children may be indicative of reduced survival over time. Segmenting the pediatric <lb/>population by age revealed that the proportion of CBD cases within the 0-4 year demographic remained <lb/>consistently dominant over the decades, underpinning the necessity of interventions targeting this critical <lb/>developmental window. <lb/>The independent effects of age, period, and cohort on CBD prevalence could be extracted through the APC <lb/>framework. A coherent age effect was discernible, with the nadir of risk manifesting during adolescence <lb/>between 10-14 years. This pattern held true universally across all SDI regions, resonating with the age-spe-<lb/>cific prevalence trends observed. Regarding period effects, the most recent time interval from 2015-2019 <lb/>showed a modest but significant reduction in prevalence risk relative to the 2000-2004 reference period. <lb/>This aligns with the overall declining trend in CBD rates over time. Finally, analysis of birth cohort influences <lb/>indicated that earlier cohorts exhibited a declining tendency, followed by a slight reversal with increased risk <lb/>among more recent generations. This parabolic pattern was observed to varying degrees across SDI regions. <lb/>The low magnitude of risk ratios underscores the complex interplay of demographic and generational fac-<lb/>tors impacting secular shifts in the prevalence of CBDs. <lb/>The study has several limitations. Our analysis primarily relies on the GBD study framework, which com-<lb/>piles secondary data sources rather than original, primary data sets. This approach is particularly relevant <lb/>in many countries in the Global South, including several African nations affected by conflict and social <lb/>unrest, where data often depend on unvalidated estimations. These regions face numerous challenges, such <lb/>as limited resources, quality of the diagnostics, expertise gaps, and inadequate infrastructure, which are <lb/>essential for comprehensive epidemiological surveillance of CBDs. Such factors can introduce biases and <lb/>potential inaccuracies into our findings. Additionally, GBD database does not provide data categorised by <lb/>disease severity. This limitation restricts our ability to conduct an analysis comparing disease rates of sim-<lb/>ilar severity across various countries. Furthermore, the observational design of our study inherently limits <lb/>the ability to establish causative relationships between observed trends in prevalence, mortality, and disease <lb/>burden, and their underlying determinants. <lb/>CONCLUSIONS <lb/>Our analysis of the extensive GBD 2019 data set reveals encouraging downward trajectories in CBD prev-<lb/>alence, mortality, and DALYs over the past three decades. Nevertheless, notable disparities persist across <lb/>geographic regions and socioeconomic strata. The prevalence of CBDs progressively declines with age, likely <lb/>reflecting reduced survival among affected children over time. Our findings can inform resource allocation, <lb/>public health planning, and targeted interventions to advance the prevention and management of CBDs <lb/>globally. <lb/></body>

    <note place="headnote">Li et al. <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">PAPERS <lb/>2024 • Vol. 14 • 04012 <lb/></note>

    <page>12 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04012 <lb/></note>

    <div type="availability">Data availability: GBD study 2019 data resources were available online from the Global Health Data Exchange (GHDx) <lb/>query tool (http://ghdx.healthdata.org/gbd-results-tool). <lb/></div>

    <div type="funding">Funding: This work was supported by grants from the China Postdoctoral Science Foundation (NO. 2023M732292) <lb/>and the National Natural Science Foundation of China (grant no. 81974291) and Shanghai Clinical Research Center of <lb/>Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery supported by Science and Technology Commision of Shanghai Municipality (Grant <lb/>No. 22MC1940300). <lb/></div>

    <div type="contribution">Authorship contributions: All authors made substantial contributions to conception and design, acquisition of data, <lb/>or analysis and interpretation of data; took part in drafting the article or revising it critically for important intellectual <lb/>content; agreed to submit to the current journal; gave final approval of the version to be published; and agree to be <lb/>accountable for all aspects of the work. <lb/></div>

    <div type="conflict">Disclosure of interest: The authors completed the ICMJE Disclosure of Interest Form (available upon request from the <lb/>corresponding author) and disclose no relevant interests <lb/></div>

    <div type="annex">Additional material <lb/>Online Supplementary Document <lb/></div>

    <listBibl>1 Nelson KB, Bingham P, Edwards EM, Horbar JD, Kenny MJ, Inder T, et al. Antecedents of neonatal encephalopathy in <lb/>the Vermont Oxford Network Encephalopathy Registry. Pediatrics. 2012;130:878-86. Medline:23071210 doi:10.1542/ <lb/>peds.2012-0714 <lb/>2 Lynn MK, Aquino MSR, Self SCW, Kanyangarara M, Campbell BA, Nolan MS. TORCH Congenital Syndrome Infections <lb/>in Central America&apos;s Northern Triangle. Microorganisms. 2023;11:257. Medline:36838223 doi:10.3390/microorgan-<lb/>isms11020257 <lb/>3 Kang L, Cao G, Jing W, Liu J, Liu M. Global, regional, and national incidence and mortality of congenital birth defects from <lb/>1990 to 2019. Eur J Pediatr. 2023;182:1781-92. Medline:36781460 doi:10.1007/s00431-023-04865-w <lb/>4 GBD 2019 Under-5 Mortality Collaborators. Global, regional, and national progress towards Sustainable Development Goal <lb/>3.2 for neonatal and child health: all-cause and cause-specific mortality findings from the Global Burden of Disease Study <lb/>2019. Lancet. 2021;398:870-905. Medline:34416195 doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(21)01207-1 <lb/>5 GBD 2015 DALYs and HALE Collaborators. Global, regional, and national disability-adjusted life-years (DALYs) for 315 dis-<lb/>eases and injuries and healthy life expectancy (HALE), 1990-2015: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease <lb/>Study 2015. Lancet. 2016;388:1603-58. Medline:27733283 doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(16)31460-X <lb/>6 Cieza A, Causey K, Kamenov K, Hanson SW, Chatterji S, Vos T. Global estimates of the need for rehabilitation based <lb/>on the Global Burden of Disease study 2019: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2019. Lancet. <lb/>2021;396:2006-17. Medline:33275908 doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(20)32340-0 <lb/>7 Safiri S, Carson-Chahhoud K, Noori M, Nejadghaderi SA, Sullman MJM, Ahmadian Heris J, et al. Burden of chronic <lb/>obstructive pulmonary disease and its attributable risk factors in 204 countries and territories, 1990-2019: results from <lb/>the Global Burden of Disease Study 2019. BMJ. 2022;378:e069679. Medline:35896191 doi:10.1136/bmj-2021-069679 <lb/>8 GBD 2019 Hearing Loss Collaborators. Hearing loss prevalence and years lived with disability, 1990-2019: findings from the <lb/>Global Burden of Disease Study 2019. Lancet. 2021;397:996-1009. Medline:33714390 doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(21)00516-X <lb/>9 GBD 2019 Demographics Collaborators. Global age-sex-specific fertility, mortality, healthy life expectancy (HALE), and <lb/>population estimates in 204 countries and territories, 1950-2019: a comprehensive demographic analysis for the Global <lb/>Burden of Disease Study 2019. Lancet. 2020;396:1160-203. Medline:33069325 doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30977-6 <lb/>10 GBD 2019 Child and Adolescent Communicable Disease Collaborators. The unfinished agenda of communicable diseases <lb/>among children and adolescents before the COVID-19 pandemic, 1990-2019: a systematic analysis of the Global Burden <lb/>of Disease Study 2019. Lancet. 2023;402:313-35. Medline:37393924 doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(23)00860-7 <lb/>11 GBD 2021 Diabetes Collaborators. Global, regional, and national burden of diabetes from 1990 to 2021, with projec-<lb/>tions of prevalence to 2050: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2021. Lancet. 2023;402:203-34. <lb/>Medline:37356446 doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(23)01301-6 <lb/>12 Cieza A, Causey K, Kamenov K, Hanson SW, Chatterji S, Vos T. Global estimates of the need for rehabilitation based <lb/>on the Global Burden of Disease study 2019: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2019. Lancet. <lb/>2021;396:2006-17. Medline:33275908 doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(20)32340-0 <lb/>13 Mboi N, Murty Surbakti I, Trihandini I, Elyazar I, Houston Smith K, Bahjuri Ali P, et al. On the road to universal health <lb/>care in Indonesia, 1990-2016: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2016. Lancet. 2018;392:581-91. <lb/>Medline:29961639 doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(18)30595-6 <lb/>14 Fay MP, Feuer EJ. Confidence intervals for directly standardized rates: a method based on the gamma distribution. Stat <lb/>Med. 1997;16:791-801. Medline:9131766 doi:10.1002/(SICI)1097-0258(19970415)16:7&lt;791::AID-SIM500&gt;3.0.CO;2-# <lb/>15 Butler WJ, Kalasinski LA. Statistical analysis of epidemiologic data of pregnancy outcomes. Environ Health Perspect. <lb/>1989;79:223-7. Medline:2707203 doi:10.1289/ehp.8979223 <lb/>16 Bell A. Age period cohort analysis: a review of what we should and shouldn&apos;t do. Ann Hum Biol. 2020;47:208-17. <lb/>Medline:32429768 doi:10.1080/03014460.2019.1707872 <lb/></listBibl>

    <note place="headnote">REFERENCES <lb/>The congenital birth defects in children <lb/>PAPERS <lb/></note>

    <note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04012 <lb/></note>

    <page>13 <lb/></page>

    <note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04012 <lb/></note>

    <listBibl>17 GBD 2017 Congenital Heart Disease Collaborators. Global, regional, and national burden of congenital heart disease, 1990-<lb/>2017: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2017. Lancet Child Adolesc Health. 2020;4:185-200. <lb/>Medline:31978374 doi:10.1016/S2352-4642(19)30402-X <lb/>18 Su Z, Zou Z, Hay SI, Liu Y, Li S, Chen H, et al. Global, regional, and national time trends in mortality for congenital <lb/>heart disease, 1990-2019: An age-period-cohort analysis for the Global Burden of Disease 2019 study. EClinicalMedicine. <lb/>2022;43:101249. Medline:35059612 doi:10.1016/j.eclinm.2021.101249 <lb/>19 Rosenberg PS, Anderson WF. Age-period-cohort models in cancer surveillance research: ready for prime time? Cancer <lb/>Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev. 2011;20:1263-8. Medline:21610223 doi:10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-11-0421 <lb/>20 Rosenberg PS, Check DP, Anderson WF. A web tool for age-period-cohort analysis of cancer incidence and mortality rates. <lb/>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev. 2014;23:2296-302. Medline:25146089 doi:10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-14-0300 <lb/>21 Li XY, Yang C, Lv J, Liu H, Zhang L, Yin M, et al. Global, regional, and national epidemiology of migraine and tension-type <lb/>headache in youths and young adults aged 15-39 years from 1990 to 2019: findings from the global burden of disease study <lb/>2019. J Headache Pain. 2023;24:126. Medline:37718436 doi:10.1186/s10194-023-01659-1 <lb/>22 Boyle B, Addor M, Arriola L, Barisic I, Bianchi F, Csáky-Szunyogh M, et al. Estimating Global Burden of Disease due to <lb/>congenital anomaly: an analysis of European data. Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed. 2018;103:F22-8. Medline:28667189 <lb/>doi:10.1136/archdischild-2016-311845 <lb/>23 Heisey AS, Bell EM, Herdt-Losavio ML, Druschel C. Surveillance of congenital malformations in infants conceived through <lb/>assisted reproductive technology or other fertility treatments. Birth Defects Res A Clin Mol Teratol. 2015;103:119-26. <lb/>Medline:25684703 doi:10.1002/bdra.23355 <lb/>24 Perin J, Mulick A, Yeung D, Villavicencio F, Lopez G, Strong KL, et al. Global, regional, and national causes of under-5 <lb/>mortality in 2000-19: an updated systematic analysis with implications for the Sustainable Development Goals. Lancet <lb/>Child Adolesc Health. 2022;6:106-15. Medline:34800370 doi:10.1016/S2352-4642(21)00311-4 <lb/>25 Scior K, Addai-Davis J, Kenyon M, Sheridan JC. Stigma, public awareness about intellectual disability and attitudes to <lb/>inclusion among different ethnic groups. Journal of intellectual disability research. J Intellect Disabil Res. 2013;57:1014-<lb/>26. Medline:22845699 doi:10.1111/j.1365-2788.2012.01597.x <lb/>26 Murray CJL. The Global Burden of Disease Study at 30 years. Nat Med. 2022;28:2019-26. Medline:36216939 doi:10.1038/ <lb/>s41591-022-01990-1 <lb/>27 GBD 2019 Diseases and Injuries Collaborators. Global burden of 369 diseases and injuries in 204 countries and ter-<lb/>ritories, 1990-2019: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2019. Lancet. 2020;396:1204-22. <lb/>Medline:33069326 doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30925-9 <lb/>28 Liu L, Oza S, Hogan D, Chu Y, Perin J, Zhu J, et al. Global, regional, and national causes of under-5 mortality in 2000-<lb/>15: an updated systematic analysis with implications for the Sustainable Development Goals. Lancet. 2016;388:3027-35. <lb/>Medline:27839855 doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(16)31593-8 <lb/>REFERENCES </listBibl>

	</text>


  </TEI>