<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>PAPERS <lb/>www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04225 <lb/>1 <lb/>2024 • Vol. 14 • 04225 <lb/>Trends of drug shortages in China <lb/>from 2018 to 2020: A retrospective <lb/>observational study <lb/>Electronic supplementary material: <lb/>The online version of this article contains supplementary material. <lb/>Cite as: Huang T, Bai L, Li H, Li H, Wang Z, Shi L, Guan X. Trends of drug shortages in <lb/>China from 2018 to 2020: A retrospective observational study. J Glob Health 2024;14:04225. <lb/>Tao Huang 1 , <lb/>Lin Bai 1 , <lb/>Huangqianyu Li 2 , <lb/>Hao Li 1 , <lb/>Zhiyuan Wang 1 , <lb/>Luwen Shi 1,2 , <lb/>Xiaodong Guan 1,2 <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Pharmacy <lb/>Administration and Clinical <lb/>Pharmacy, School of Pharmaceutical <lb/>Sciences, Peking University, Beijing, <lb/>China <lb/>2 <lb/>International Research Center for <lb/>Medicinal Administration, Peking <lb/>University, Beijing, China <lb/>Correspondence to: <lb/>Xiaodong Guan <lb/>Peking University Health Science Center <lb/>Xueyuan Road No.38, Haidian District, <lb/>Beijing <lb/>China <lb/>guanxiaodong@pku.edu.cn <lb/>Background Drug shortage is a significant global public health challenge, threat-<lb/>ening both drug safety and patient health. While several studies concerning this <lb/>issue have been conducted in the USA and in European countries, research in <lb/>China remains limited. In this study, we aimed to analyse the characteristics <lb/>and trends of drug shortage in China. <lb/>Methods We obtained monthly data reporting drug shortages from January <lb/>2018 to December 2020 from 1124 medical institutions in 258 prefecture-level <lb/>cities. We described the characteristics of drugs reported to be in shortage and <lb/>calculated the occurrence, geographical coverage, and duration of drug short-<lb/>ages. We conducted the modified Mann-Kendall test to analyse trends in drug <lb/>shortages at the city level over time. <lb/>Results We identified 2368 drugs from 121 814 shortage records. During the <lb/>study period, the mean monthly occurrence of shortages for each drug was 1.2 <lb/>(standard deviation (SD) = 2.5), affecting on average 2.8 (SD = 4.0) cities, with <lb/>a mean duration of 3.6 (SD = 5.7) months. Around half of the shortages influ-<lb/>enced only one city (n = 19 215, 51.6%) and lasted only one month (n = 19 024, <lb/>55.8%). The occurrence (z-statistic (Z) = -3.83; P &lt; 0.001), geographical coverage <lb/>(Z = -2.02; P = 0.043), and duration (Z = -3.10; P = 0.002) of shortages showed <lb/>decreasing trends over time. However, there was no significant change in the <lb/>occurrence (Z = 0.90; P = 0.367), geographical coverage (Z = 1.70; P = 0.090), or <lb/>duration (Z = -1.64; P = 0.102) of emergency medication shortages during the <lb/>study period. <lb/>Conclusions Decreasing trends were observed for the occurrence, geographical <lb/>coverage, and duration of drug shortages in China; most were observed only in <lb/>limited geographical areas and lasted short periods. More efforts are needed to <lb/>alleviate the shortage of emergency and antineoplastic medicines. <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s) <lb/></front>

			<body>Drug shortages are a major public health threat worldwide [1-3], frequently leading <lb/>to suboptimal treatment, increased medical costs, and increased risks of death for <lb/>patients, particularly in developing countries with limited medical sources [4-7]. <lb/>It was estimated that 38% of medical errors and an additional USD 359 million per <lb/>year were directly related to drug shortages [8]. Despite measures to alleviate this <lb/>issue [9], such as the 2012 Food and Drug Administration Safety and Innovation Act <lb/>in the USA [10], shortages remained and even increased, especially for injections, <lb/>gastroenterology medicines, and emergency medicines [11-14]. The most recent <lb/>studies in European countries and the USA showed that over 95% of pharmacists <lb/>have witnessed or are witnessing drug shortages [12,15]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Huang et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PAPERS <lb/>2024 • Vol. 14 • 04225 <lb/></note>

            <page>2 <lb/></page>

            <note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04225 <lb/></note>

			<body>China, one of the largest and most populous developing countries, also suffers drug shortages, such as those <lb/>of cytarabine and trastuzumab in 2018 [16-18]. In contrast to the USA and other developed countries, where <lb/>numerous studies have investigated the full scope and changing trends of drug shortages [11-15,19], limited <lb/>evidence is available for China [2]. Moreover, drug shortages in developing countries can have more serious <lb/>clinical implications compared to developed countries, due to a lack of approved alternative treatments and <lb/>limited capacity to predict and detect drug shortages [20]. For this reason, like many developed countries, <lb/>China established a national drug shortage reporting system and a strategic national stockpile programme, <lb/>as well as released a national catalogue of critical drugs on shortage [2,21-24]. Estimating the magnitude <lb/>and identifying the changing trends of drug shortages in China may reveal the effectiveness of these policy <lb/>tools, providing references for the design of relevant policies in developing countries. <lb/>In this study, we retrospectively described the characteristics of and trends in reported drug shortages in <lb/>China using national records from 1124 hospitals in 256 prefecture-level cities between 2018 and 2020. <lb/>METHODS <lb/>Data source <lb/>The China Medical Economic Information (CMEI) database of the Chinese Pharmaceutical Association has <lb/>been collecting monthly data on drug shortages from hospitals across the country. In this context, a shortage <lb/>is defined as a drug either being out of stock or not being supplied on time at the reporting hospital during <lb/>the month. A total of 1124 hospitals that consecutively reported drugs in shortage every month between <lb/>2018 and 2020 were sampled. These hospitals covered 258 cities across 31 provinces in China, including <lb/>four municipalities (Beijing, Tianjin, Shanghai and Chongqing) and 254 prefecture-level cities (spanning <lb/>76.3% of the total 333 prefecture-level cities in China) [25]. The CMEI was responsible for checking the <lb/>completeness of the reported data monthly. <lb/>Data collection and processing <lb/>We obtained monthly drug shortage data between 2018 and 2020 from the CMEI database. This information <lb/>included the hospital name, city name, and shortage month, as well as information on the drug reporting <lb/>shortage, including the generic name of the drug, dosage form, and route of administration. Dosage forms <lb/>were grouped into aerosol, capsule, drop, emulsion, gel, granule, liquid, ointment, patch, pill, powder, solu-<lb/>tion, suppository, suspension, syrup, tablet, tincture, and miscellaneous forms. Routes of administration <lb/>were categorised as buccal, cutaneous, haemodialysis, inhalation, nasal, ophthalmic, oral, optic, parenteral, <lb/>rectal, sublingual, and vaginal. We identified therapeutic areas of each drug according to the World Health <lb/>Organization Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical Classification [26] and classified whether the drug was des-<lb/>ignated as an emergency medicine based on the list published by the Chinese Medical Association and the <lb/>Chinese Medical Doctor Association [27]. <lb/>We considered products with the same generic name, dosage form, and route of administration as the same <lb/>drug. We then aggregated hospital-reported shortage data to create city-level summaries based on the loca-<lb/>tion of the hospitals for further analysis. If a hospital reported a drug shortage, that drug was considered to be <lb/>in shortage for the entire city during the report month (Figure S1 in the Online Supplementary Document). <lb/>Outcome measures <lb/>Three outcomes were calculated using the city-level data to capture the landscape of drug shortages in Chi-<lb/>na (Figure S1 in the Online Supplementary Document). First, we calculated the occurrence of reported <lb/>shortages of drugs by calculating the number of times that they were reported to be in shortage by cities <lb/>during the month. Second, we assessed the geographical coverage of the shortage of every drug each month <lb/>by calculating the number of cities reporting that the drug was in shortage during the month. Third, we as-<lb/>sessed the duration of each drug shortage in each city by counting the number of consecutive months when <lb/>the drug was reported to be in shortage in that specific city. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>We used descriptive analyses to describe the characteristics of drugs that experienced shortages during the <lb/>study period, presenting continuous variables as means (x ˉ) and standard deviations (SDs) and categorical <lb/>variables as numbers and proportions. Outcomes, including the overall and monthly occurrences, average <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Trends of drug shortages in China <lb/>PAPERS <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04225 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04225 <lb/></note>

			<body>geographical coverages, and average durations of drug shortages, were calculated for all drugs. We conducted <lb/>the modified Mann-Kendall test to analyse the changing trend in the monthly occurrence, average geograph-<lb/>ical coverage, and average duration of drug shortages during the study period [28]. To avoid bias stemming <lb/>from the possibility that shortages starting earlier would expect longer duration, we performed trend tests <lb/>for the duration of shortages after excluding data from the first and last six months (almost one SD of av-<lb/>erage shortage duration) of the study period. Subgroup analyses were conducted based on the dosage form <lb/>of the drug, route of administration, therapeutic area, and whether it was included on the emergency list. <lb/>We performed all analyses in Microsoft Excel 2019 (Redmond, Washington, USA) and R, version 4.3.1 (R <lb/>Core Team, Vienna, Austria). A two-sided P &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Characteristics of drugs in <lb/>shortage <lb/>Overall, 121 814 drug shortage records and <lb/>2368 drugs reporting shortages were iden-<lb/>tified in 258 cities between 2018 and 2020 <lb/>(Table 1). Among all drug shortage re-<lb/>cords, the most frequently observed dosage <lb/>forms were solutions (n = 42 203, 34.6%), <lb/>tablets (n = 42 150, 27.7%), and powders <lb/>(n = 22 689, 18.6%). The most frequent-<lb/>ly observed routes of administration were <lb/>parenteral (n = 59 004, 48.4%) and oral <lb/>(n = 49 539, 40.7%). Among all therapeutic <lb/>areas, drugs for antineoplastic and immuno-<lb/>modulating agents (n = 14 587, 12.0%) and <lb/>anti-infectives for systemic use (n = 12 160, <lb/>10.0%) contributed to a little over a fifth <lb/>of all shortage records. Emergency medi-<lb/>cine drugs comprised 11.1% (n = 13 564) of <lb/>all drug shortage records. Drugs that were <lb/>most frequently reported to be in shortage <lb/>were methotrexate, allopurinol, ketamine, <lb/>cytarabine, nitroglycerin, vincristine, atro-<lb/>pine, vitamin K1, and posterior pituitary <lb/>and pyridostigmine bromide (Table S1 in <lb/>the Online Supplementary Document). <lb/>Notably, seven out of these ten drugs were <lb/>administered via parenteral injections. <lb/>Monthly number of reported drug shortages <lb/>The monthly occurrence of all drug shortages in the 258 cities showed a decreasing trend of 20.6%, from <lb/>2655 times in January 2018 to 2109 times in December 2020 (z-statistic (Z) = -3.83; P &lt; 0.001) (Figure 1, <lb/>panel A; Table S2 in the Online Supplementary Document). Decreasing trends in the monthly numbers <lb/>of reported shortages were also observed in the subgroup analyses of the five most commonly reported <lb/>dosage forms, routes of administration, and therapeutic areas, except for drugs that are in the powder form <lb/>(Z = 0.81; P = 0.416), administered via cutaneous (Z = -1.48; P = 0.139) and vaginal routes (Z = -1.54; P = 0.123), <lb/>and for the therapeutic areas of the cardiovascular system (Z = -0.74; P = 0.485) and antineoplastic and im-<lb/>munomodulating agents (Z = -0.13; P = 0.900). We further observed a non-significant increasing trend for <lb/>the monthly number of shortages of emergency medicine (Z = 0.90, P = 0.367). <lb/>Geographical coverage of reported shortages <lb/>Each month, the drug shortages affected between 1 and 67 cities across 258 cities in China, with a mean <lb/>of 2.8 (SD = 4.0) cities experiencing shortages. Among all drug shortages, around half (n = 19 215, 51.6%) of <lb/>Table 1. Characteristics of reported shortages and included drugs <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>Reported shortage <lb/>(n = 121 814), n (%) <lb/>Drug <lb/>(n = 2368), n (%) <lb/>Dosage form <lb/>Solutions <lb/>42 203 (34.6) <lb/>655 (27.7) <lb/>Tablets <lb/>42 150 (34.6) <lb/>702 (29.6) <lb/>Powders <lb/>22 689 (18.6) <lb/>391 (16.5) <lb/>Capsules <lb/>5858 (4.8) <lb/>272 (11.5) <lb/>Ointments <lb/>2312 (1.9) <lb/>51 (2.3) <lb/>Others* <lb/>6602 (5.4) <lb/>297 (12.5) <lb/>Route of administration <lb/>Parenteral <lb/>59 004 (48.4) <lb/>829 (35.0) <lb/>Oral <lb/>49 539 (40.7) <lb/>1142 (48.2) <lb/>Cutaneous <lb/>4525 (3.7) <lb/>175 (7.4) <lb/>Ophthalmic <lb/>4019 (3.3) <lb/>101 (4.3) <lb/>Vaginal <lb/>1607 (1.3) <lb/>45 (1.9) <lb/>Others † <lb/>3120 (2.6) <lb/>76 (3.2) <lb/>Therapeutic area <lb/>Alimentary tract and metabolism <lb/>16 904 (13.9) <lb/>397 (16.8) <lb/>Nervous system <lb/>16 502 (13.5) <lb/>289 (12.2) <lb/>Cardiovascular system <lb/>15 633 (12.8) <lb/>235 (9.9) <lb/>Antineoplastic and immunomodulating agents <lb/>14 587 (12.0) <lb/>209 (8.8) <lb/>Anti-infectives for systemic use <lb/>12 160 (10.0) <lb/>284 (12.0) <lb/>Others ‡ <lb/>46 028 (37.8) <lb/>954 (40.3) <lb/>Emergency medicine <lb/>13 564 (11.1) <lb/>83 (3.5) <lb/>*Aerosol, drop, emulsion, gel, granule, liquid, patch, pill, suppository, suspension, syrup, <lb/>tincture, and miscellaneous forms. <lb/> †Buccal, haemodialysis, inhalation, nasal, optic, rectal, and sublingual. <lb/> ‡Antiparasitic products, insecticides and repellents, blood and blood-forming organs, der-<lb/>matological, genitourinary system and sex hormones, musculoskeletal system, respiratory <lb/>system, sensory organs, systemic hormonal preparations (excluding sex hormones and in-<lb/>sulins), and others. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Huang et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PAPERS <lb/>2024 • Vol. 14 • 04225 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04225 <lb/></note>
			<body>shortages influenced only one city, while 10.4% (n = 3857) of shortages covered more than five cities (Fig-<lb/>ure 2, panel A). <lb/>The overall average shortage coverage in the 258 cities showed a downward trend from 2018 to 2020 <lb/>(Z = -2.02; P = 0.043) (Figure 2, panel B; Table S2 in the Online Supplementary Document). Similar decreas-<lb/>ing trends were observed in the subgroup analyses of the five most commonly reported dosage forms, routes <lb/>of administration, and therapeutic areas during the study period, except for drugs that were in the powder <lb/>forms (Z = 1.30; P = 0.192), administered via parenteral (Z = -1.16; P = 0.622) and vaginal routes (Z = -0.01; <lb/>P = 0.995), and for the therapeutic areas of the cardiovascular system (Z = -0.74; P = 0.485) and antineoplas-<lb/>tic and immunomodulating agents (Z = -0.13; P = 0.900) (Figure 3; Table S2 in the Online Supplementary <lb/>Document). A statistically insignificant increase in the coverage of shortages of emergency medicine was <lb/>observed (Z = 1.70; P = 0.090) (Figure 3, panel A). <lb/>Duration of reported shortages <lb/>Overall, the duration of drug shortages in the 258 cities was between 1 and 36 months, with a mean of 3.6 <lb/>months (SD = 5.7). Among drug shortages, around half had a duration of one month (n = 19 024, 55.8%), <lb/>while 13.1% (n = 4449) lasted more than six months (Figure 2, panel C). <lb/>Overall, the average drug shortage duration in the 258 cities showed a downward trend, with a decrease <lb/>of 11.5% from 2.9 months in July 2018 to 2.6 months in June 2020 (Z = -3.10; P = 0.002) (Figure 2, pan-<lb/>el D; Table S2 in the Online Supplementary Document). Decreasing trends in the durations of report-<lb/>ed shortages were also observed in the subgroup analyses, except for drugs that were in the forms of <lb/>solutions (Z = -1.46; P = 0.143) and capsules (Z = -1.36; P = 0.172), administered via the cutaneous route <lb/>(Z = -1.61, P = 0.107), and for the therapeutic areas of alimentary tract and metabolism (Z = -1.46; P = 0.143) <lb/>and anti-infectives (Z = -0.51, P = 0.613) (Figure 4; Table S2 in the Online Supplementary Document). <lb/>There was no significant decrease in the shortage duration of emergency medicine (Z = -1.64, P = 0.102) <lb/>(Figure 4, panel A). <lb/>Figure 1. Trends in the monthly number of reported shortages for all drugs and different subgroups between 2018 and 2020: Panel A. <lb/>Emergency medicines and non-emergency medicines. Panel B. Dosage forms. Panel C. Route of administrations. Panel D. Therapeu-<lb/>tic areas. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Trends of drug shortages in China <lb/>PAPERS <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04225 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04225 <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 2. Distribution of and trends in geographical coverage and duration of reported shortages from 2018 to 2020: Panel A. Number <lb/>of reported shortages for different levels of geographical coverage. Panel B. Monthly trends in the average geographical coverage of re-<lb/>ported shortages. Panel C. Number of reported shortages for different durations. Panel D. Monthly trends in the average duration of <lb/>reported shortages. To avoid possible bias stemming from the possibility that shortages starting earlier would expect longer duration, <lb/>trend tests for the duration of shortages were performed after excluding data from the first and last six months (almost one standard <lb/>deviation of average shortage duration) of the study period. <lb/>Figure 3. Monthly trends in the geographical coverage of reported shortages for different subgroups from 2018 to 2020: Panel A. Emer-<lb/>gency medicines and non-emergency medicines. Panel B. Dosage forms. Panel C. Route of administrations. Panel D. Therapeutic ar-<lb/>eas. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Huang et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PAPERS <lb/>2024 • Vol. 14 • 04225 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04225 <lb/></note>
			<body>DISCUSSION <lb/>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study to evaluate drug shortages across China using a nation-<lb/>ally representative data of records reporting drug shortages. Our findings showed that the overall occur-<lb/>rence, geographical coverage, and duration of drug shortages showed decreasing trends between 2018 and <lb/>2020. After aggregating hospital-level into city-level data, the influence of over half of the drug shortages <lb/>did not extend to more than one city or one month. However, drug shortages for emergency drugs did not <lb/>show significant alleviation in either occurrence or coverage over time. <lb/>The overall geographical coverage of drug shortages in China was limited, and the average duration of 3.6 <lb/>months was significantly shorter than that of six to nine months that have been reported by studies in the <lb/>USA and Belgium [29-32]. This discrepancy may be attributed to the different causes of drug shortages in <lb/>China, the USA, and European countries. For example, over 70% of drug shortages in the USA and Europe <lb/>were caused by problems with drug manufacturing and lack of raw materials [33-38], while most drug <lb/>shortages in China were caused by problems with drug tendering and pricing [35]. The limited geograph-<lb/>ical coverage of drug shortages in this study also indicated that temporary disruptions in the tendering, <lb/>procurement, or distribution contributed to most drug shortages in China, as disruptions in pharmaceuti-<lb/>cal manufacturing usually resulted in national drug shortages, such as the national shortage of cytarabine <lb/>and trastuzumab in 2018 [16-18]. Therefore, improving clarity and transparency of information about drug <lb/>pricing, tendering, and inventory to better distribute drugs can help hospitals and cities recover from drug <lb/>shortages in China [39,40]. <lb/>Our results further highlight that drug shortages in China were alleviated despite disruptions rising from <lb/>the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic, as shown by significant downward trends in the over-<lb/>all occurrence, geographical reach, and duration of drug shortages. This contradicts results from the USA <lb/>and European countries, such as France and Italy [12,41,42]. According to the 2022 Food and Drug Admin-<lb/>istration Drug Shortage Report, the number of ongoing drug shortages nearly doubled from 2017 to 2020 <lb/>[12]. A study based on the French national drug shortage reporting system also showed a 4-fold increase <lb/>in drug shortages during the study period [41]. The difference in changing trends can be explained by the <lb/>Figure 4. Monthly trends in the duration of reported shortages for different subgroups from 2018 to 2020: Panel A. Emergency medi-<lb/>cines and non-emergency medicines. Panel B. Dosage forms. Panel C. Route of administrations. Panel D. Therapeutic areas. To avoid <lb/>possible bias stemming from the possibility that shortages starting earlier would expect longer duration, trend tests for the duration of <lb/>shortages were performed after excluding data from the first and last six months (almost one standard deviation of average shortage <lb/>duration) of the study period. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Trends of drug shortages in China <lb/>PAPERS <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04225 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04225 <lb/></note>

			<body>different reasons behind the drug shortages. Drug shortages in developed countries are mostly caused by a <lb/>lack of raw materials and issues concerned with the quality of drug manufacturing, like the 2019 cefazolin <lb/>shortage in Japan and the 2023 cisplatin shortage in the USA [43,44]. In contrast, drug shortages in China <lb/>are usually caused by problems with drug tendering and pricing, and serval policy tools have proven effec-<lb/>tive in addressing these problems. To ensure a stable supply of drugs with small market demand and low <lb/>prices, such as methimazole and digoxin, the Chinese government has been establishing designated fac-<lb/>tories to produce these drugs through bidding since 2012, which proved to increase drug availability [45]. <lb/>Provinces also have their stockpile plans for drugs susceptible to shortages, including emergency medicines <lb/>and drugs with small market demand, to further mitigate the effects of these shortages [9,46]. Additionally, <lb/>the national drug shortage monitoring system and collaborative initiatives involving multiple stakeholders <lb/>(including provincial regulators, drug distributors, and manufacturers) contributed to the earlier detection <lb/>of and response to drug shortages, especially shortages that were derived from disruptions in the process <lb/>of tendering, procurement, and distribution of drugs [46]. However, efforts are still needed to improve the <lb/>transparency of designating drug factories and stockpile plans and to align these decisions with evidence <lb/>in China. A previous study also showed complaints that collaborative efforts were time-consuming and of-<lb/>ten delayed response to short shortages, aside from a low sensitivity of detection of these shortages in the <lb/>first place [47]. Therefore, systematic evaluations of the effectiveness of these policies and evidence-based <lb/>efforts are urgently needed. <lb/>It is worth noting that the monthly occurrence and coverage of shortages of emergency medicine were not <lb/>alleviated during the study period; instead, they showed upward trends, similar to findings observed in the <lb/>USA [11,30]. Additionally, the geographical coverage of shortages of emergency medicines was wider than <lb/>that of other drugs. Possible reasons may be that emergency medicines are generally lower priced and lack <lb/>alternatives [48]. The unpredictable clinical demand for emergency medicines may worsen their shortage <lb/>and make them harder to prevent and prepare for. Additionally, during the COVID-19 pandemic, the clini-<lb/>cal demand for essential life-saving drugs (e.g. norepinephrine) increased while the manufacturing of these <lb/>medicines was shut down due to quarantine measures, resulting in a serious imbalance between supply and <lb/>demand [49]. Alongside current policies and interventions, actions like appropriate ration plans shall be tak-<lb/>en to manage the emergency medicine shortage and to prepare for possible future shortage incidences [50]. <lb/>We also discovered that nearly 10% of shortages influenced more than five cities and over 6% of shortages <lb/>lasted for over a year. Qualitative research suggested that manufacturing problems and single-source provid-<lb/>ers are contributors to drug shortages with wider or more long-lasting influence [35,51], such as the short-<lb/>age of methotrexate in 2019 that was derived from the discontinuation of one manufacturer. Our findings <lb/>also suggested that the geographical coverage of shortages of drugs administered parenterally contributed <lb/>the most to lasting shortages, consistent with results from other countries [19,52]. Seven out of ten drugs <lb/>most frequently reported as being in shortage were administered via parenteral injections. Parenteral drugs <lb/>are more difficult to produce and transport than other drugs and thus are more susceptible to disruptions <lb/>in manufacturing and delivery [53]. Consistent with previous studies in the USA and Europe [41,52], an-<lb/>ti-infective, cardiovascular, and antineoplastic drugs contributed significantly to the occurrence of drug <lb/>shortages. The shortages of drugs like benzylpenicillin and vincristine are likely caused by a lack of market <lb/>incentives and low profitability [54,55]. With increasing occurrence and geographical coverage of shortages <lb/>of these drugs, they became a greater threat to public health [56,57]. Future research should seek to design <lb/>targeted measures to reduce the risks these shortages pose to patient health. <lb/>Strengths and limitations <lb/>The strength of our study is that, to our knowledge, it is the first estimate the nationwide magnitude and <lb/>changing trends of drug shortages in China using data reporting drug shortages across the country. Previ-<lb/>ous studies were mostly conducted based on data from a single hospital or province obtained through ques-<lb/>tionnaires [35,48,58-60], making it hard to generalise the results to the entire country. <lb/>This study also has several limitations. First, caution should be taken while extrapolating our results to hos-<lb/>pitals not included in our sample. Nevertheless, the sampled hospitals were from nearly 80% of all prefec-<lb/>ture-level cities in China, spanning cities with different levels of economic development and health care re-<lb/>sources, and thus our data set was nationally representative and provided the most comprehensive pool of <lb/>drug shortage data during the study period. Second, the uncertainty of study results may arise from varying <lb/>criteria for delayed supply. Sampled hospitals had differing definitions for timely drug restocking, preventing <lb/>more accurate estimations of drug shortages in China. Still, the CMEI database is the largest in China, re-<lb/>porting drug shortages and providing the most detailed information. We also aggregated the data at the city <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Huang et al. <lb/>PAPERS <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04225 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04225 <lb/></note>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements: We are grateful to CMEI for providing the drug shortage data and related information. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Ethics statement: The study was considered not human subjects research by the Peking University Health Science Re-<lb/>view Board. Patients or the public were not involved in the design, conduct, reporting, or dissemination plans of our <lb/>research. <lb/></div>

            <div type="availability">Data availability: Due to legislative restrictions, person-level data from this study cannot be shared, However, aggre-<lb/>gated data are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request, following approval from the relevant <lb/>data custodians. <lb/></div>

            <div type="funding">Funding: There was no funding for this study. <lb/></div>

            <div type="contribution">Authorship contributions: GXD and SLW conceptualised and designed the study. HT, LH, WZY and BL screened <lb/>data and completed analyses. HT, BL, and GXD contributed to interpreting the results. HT, BL, GXD, and SLW helped <lb/>in drafting this work. BL, LHQY, and GXD provided input into the analyses, and critically reviewed and modified the <lb/>manuscript drafts. GXD supervised the study project. <lb/></div>

            <div type="conflict">Disclosure of interest: The authors completed the ICMJE Disclosure of Interest Form (available upon request from the <lb/>corresponding author) and disclose no relevant interests. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Additional material <lb/>Online Supplementary Document <lb/></div>

            <listBibl>1 Fox ER, Sweet BV, Jensen V. Drug shortages: a complex health care crisis. Mayo Clin Proc. 2014;89:361-73. Med-<lb/>line:24582195 doi:10.1016/j.mayocp.2013.11.014 <lb/>2 Acosta A, Vanegas EP, Rovira J, Godman B, Bochenek T. Medicine Shortages: Gaps Between Countries and Global Perspec-<lb/>tives. Front Pharmacol. 2019;10:763. Medline:31379565 doi:10.3389/fphar.2019.00763 <lb/>3 Biedermann F. Seeking solutions to global drugs shortages. Lancet. 2023;401:720-1. Medline:36871561 doi:10.1016/ <lb/>S0140-6736(23)00437-3 <lb/>4 Butterfield L, Cash J, Pham K. Drug shortages and implications for pediatric patients. J Pediatr Pharmacol Ther. 2015;20:149-<lb/>52. Medline:25964733 doi:10.5863/1551-6776-20.2.149 <lb/>5 Bible JR, Evans DC, Payne B, Mostafavifar L. Impact of drug shortages on patients receiving parenteral nutrition after lap-<lb/>arotomy. JPEN J Parenter Enteral Nutr. 2014;38:65S-71S. Medline:25239113 doi:10.1177/0148607114550317 <lb/>6 Hayes MS, Ward MA, Slabaugh SL, Xu Y. Lessons from the leucovorin shortages between 2009 and 2012 in a Medicare <lb/>advantage population: where do we go from here? Am Health Drug Benefits. 2014;7:264-70. Medline:25237422 <lb/>7 Hughes KM, Goswami ES, Morris JL. Impact of a Drug Shortage on Medication Errors and Clinical Outcomes in the Pedi-<lb/>atric Intensive Care Unit. J Pediatr Pharmacol Ther. 2015;20:453-61. Medline:26766934 doi:10.5863/1551-6776-20.6.453 <lb/>8 Vizient. Drug shortages and labor costs: measuring the hidden costs of drug shortages on U.S. hospitals. 2019. Available: <lb/>https://wieck-vizient-production.s3.us-west-1.amazonaws.com/page-Brum/attachment/c9dba646f40b9b5def8032480e-<lb/>a51e1e85194129. Accessed: 23 February 2024. <lb/>9 Vogler S, Fischer S. How to address medicines shortages: Findings from a cross-sectional study of 24 countries. Health <lb/>Policy. 2020;124:1287-96. Medline:33032846 doi:10.1016/j.healthpol.2020.09.001 <lb/>10 Food and Drug Administration. Food and Drug Administration Safety and Innovation Act (FDASIA). 2018. Available: <lb/>https://www.fda.gov/regulatory-information/selected-amendments-fdc-act/food-and-drug-administration-safety-and-in-<lb/>novation-act-fdasia. Accessed: 23 February 2024. <lb/>REFERENCES <lb/></listBibl>

            <body>level to further mitigate the effect of the varying criteria and enhance the robustness of our results. Third, <lb/>our study design was not powered to draw causal effects between concerned policy tools and the number <lb/>of drug shortages in China. Further studies using rigorous study designs, such as difference-in-difference or <lb/>interrupted time-series analysis, are needed to evaluate the effect of these tools in different settings. Lastly, <lb/>we lacked data on the characteristics of manufacturing, prices, and distribution of drug products. Future <lb/>work needs to incorporate these factors to analyse the causes of drug shortages, especially for emergency <lb/>and antineoplastic medicines. <lb/>CONCLUSIONS <lb/>We found decreasing trends in the occurrence, geographical coverage, and duration of drug shortages be-<lb/>tween 2018 and 2020 in China. Most drug shortages observed covered limited geographical areas and last-<lb/>ed short periods. However, for emergency medicines with no therapeutic alternative available, continued <lb/>efforts and interventions by the industry and the government are needed, such as mandating the reporting <lb/>of production discontinuation and strategic stockpiling. Further studies should focus on understanding the <lb/>root causes and estimating the social and patient losses due to drug shortages. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Trends of drug shortages in China <lb/></note>

            <note place="footnote">PAPERS <lb/>www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04225 <lb/></note>

            <page>9 <lb/></page>

            <note place="footnote">2024 • Vol. 14 • 04225 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>11 Chen SI, Fox ER, Hall MK, Ross JS, Bucholz EM, Krumholz HM, et al. Despite Federal Legislation, Shortages Of Drugs <lb/>Used In Acute Care Settings Remain Persistent And Prolonged. Health Aff (Millwood). 2016;35:798-804. Accessed Feb-<lb/>ruary 23, 2024. Medline:27140985 doi:10.1377/hlthaff.2015.1157 <lb/>12 Food and Drug Administration. Tenth Annual Report on Drug Shortages for Calendar Year 2022. Silver Spring, Mary-<lb/>land, USA: Food and Drug Administration; 2022. Available: https://www.fda.gov/media/169302/download. Accessed: 23 <lb/>February 2024. <lb/>13 Patel J, Fox ER, Zocchi M, Lee ZE, Mazer-Amirshahi M. Trends in United States drug shortages for medications used in <lb/>gastroenterology (2001-2014). J Med Access. 2017;1:e58-64. <lb/>14 Mazer-Amirshahi M, Fox ER, Zocchi MS, Pines JM, van den Anker JN. Longitudinal trends in U.S. shortages of sterile solu-<lb/>tions, 2001-17. Am J Health Syst Pharm. 2018;75:1903-8. Medline:30463866 doi:10.2146/ajhp180203 <lb/>15 European Association of Hospital Pharmacists. EAHP 2023 Shortage Survey Report. Brussels, Belgium: European Asso-<lb/>ciation of Hospital Pharmacists; 2023. Available: https://www.acadpharm.org/dos_public/SHORTAGES_SURVEY_RE-<lb/>PORT_FINAL.PDF. Accessed: 23 February 2024. <lb/>16 National Health Commission. [Notice on ensuring the supply of cytarabine injection]. 2019. Available: http://yp.ynyyzb. <lb/>com.cn/detail.html?infoId=10915&amp;CatalogId=3. Accessed: 23 February 2024. Chinese. <lb/>17 Network of Liaoning Province. [Notice on ensuring the supply of cytarabine injection of Liaoning Province: Medi-<lb/>cine and Medical Consumables Centralized Procurement 2019]. Available: https://ypzb2015.lnypcg.com.cn/Upload-<lb/>File/20190121_92951_6119.pdf. Accessed: 23 February 2024. Chinese. <lb/>18 Beijing Youth Daily. Breast cancer &apos;life-saving drug&apos; Herceptin is out of stock. 2018. Available: https://www.thepaper.cn/ <lb/>newsDetail_forward_2163884. Accessed: 23 February 2024. <lb/>19 Food and Drug Administration. Drug Shortages CY 2022: U.S. Food and Drug Administration. Silver Spring, Maryland, <lb/>USA: Food and Drug Administration; 2023. Available: https://www.fda.gov/media/169302/download. Accessed: 23 Feb-<lb/>ruary 2024. <lb/>20 Shukar S, Zahoor F, Hayat K, Saeed A, Gillani AH, Omer S, et al. Drug Shortage: Causes, Impact, and Mitigation Strate-<lb/>gies. Front Pharmacol. 2021;12:693426. Medline:34305603 doi:10.3389/fphar.2021.693426 <lb/>21 Shi Y, Yang P, Li X, Lv J, Yin T, Gong Z, et al. Combating drug shortages in China: surveillance warning and practice stan-<lb/>dardization. Int J Clin Pharm. 2020;42:309-14. Medline:32048122 doi:10.1007/s11096-020-00987-5 <lb/>22 National Health Commission. [Notice on issuing the National List of drugs on shortage National Health Commission]. <lb/>2020. Available: http://www.nhc.gov.cn/yaozs/s7653/202012/f30aad8ec4ba48a9afa2e559f4d20e7c.shtml. Accessed: 23 <lb/>February 2024. Chinese. <lb/>23 European Medicines Agency. First version of the Union list of critical medicines agreed to help avoid potential shortages <lb/>in the EU. 2023. Available: https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/news/first-version-union-list-critical-medicines-agreed-help-<lb/>avoid-potential-shortages-eu. Accessed: 23 February 2024. <lb/>24 Health Affairs. Strategic Reserve Stockpiling: A Proposal To Prevent Critical Drug Shortages 2012. Available: https://www. <lb/>healthaffairs.org/content/forefront/strategic-reserve-stockpiling-proposal-prevent-critical-drug-shortages. Accessed: 23 <lb/>February 2024. <lb/>25 Ministry of Civil Affairs of the People&apos;s Republic of China. [Statistical table of administrative divisions of the People&apos;s Re-<lb/>public of China]. 2020. Available: http://xzqh.mca.gov.cn/statistics/2020.html. Accessed: 23 February 2024. Chinese. <lb/>26 Norwegian Institute of Public Health. ATC/DDD Index 2024. 2024. Available: https://www.whocc.no/atc_ddd_index/. Ac-<lb/>cessed: 14 January 2024. <lb/>27 National Health Commission. [Notice on the publication of selection principles and drug list (chemicals and biological <lb/>products) for women and pediatric medicine and emergency medicine]. 2015. Available: http://www.nhc.gov.cn/yaozs/ <lb/>s7652/201509/105a04136fad412e9f57fa8034126bd9.shtml. Accessed: 23 February 2024. Chinese. <lb/>28 Yue S, Wang C. The Mann-Kendall Test Modified by Effective Sample Size to Detect Trend in Serially Correlated Hydro-<lb/>logical Series. Water Resources Management. 2004;18:201-18. doi:10.1023/B:WARM.0000043140.61082.60 <lb/>29 Quadri F, Mazer-Amirshahi M, Fox ER, Hawley KL, Pines JM, Zocchi MS, et al. Antibacterial drug shortages from 2001 <lb/>to 2013: implications for clinical practice. Clin Infect Dis. 2015;60:1737-42. Medline:25908680 doi:10.1093/cid/civ201 <lb/>30 Hawley KL, Mazer-Amirshahi M, Zocchi MS, Fox ER, Pines JM. Longitudinal Trends in U.S. Drug Shortages for Medications <lb/>Used in Emergency Departments (2001-2014). Acad Emerg Med. 2016;23:63-9. Medline:26715487 doi:10.1111/acem.12838 <lb/>31 Bauters T, Claus BOM, Norga K, Huys I, Simoens S, Laureys G. Chemotherapy drug shortages in paediatric on-<lb/>cology: A 14-year single-centre experience in Belgium. J Oncol Pharm Pract. 2016;22:766-70. Medline:26447099 <lb/>doi:10.1177/1078155215610915 <lb/>32 Patel JM, Fox ER, Zocchi M, Lee ZE, Mazer-Amirshahi M. Trends in United States drug shortages for medications used in <lb/>gastroenterology. Med Access Point Care. 2017;1:e58-64. doi:10.5301/maapoc.0000012 <lb/>33 Kweder SL, Dill S. Drug shortages: the cycle of quantity and quality. Clin Pharmacol Ther. 2013;93:245-51. Med-<lb/>line:23340474 doi:10.1038/clpt.2012.235 <lb/>34 European Commission. Future-proofing pharmaceutical legislation -Study on medicine shortages -Final report (revised). <lb/>Brussels, Belgium: Publications Office of the European Union; 2021. Available: https://data.europa.eu/doi/10.2875/211485. <lb/>Accessed: 23 February 2024. <lb/>35 Yang C, Wu L, Cai W, Zhu W, Shen Q, Li Z, et al. Current situation, determinants, and solutions to drug shortages in Shaanxi <lb/>Province, China: a qualitative study. PLoS One. 2016;11:e0165183. Medline:27780218 doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0165183 <lb/>36 Dill S, Ahn J. Drug shortages in developed countries-reasons, therapeutic consequences, and handling. Eur J Clin Phar-<lb/>macol. 2014;70:1405-12. Medline:25228250 doi:10.1007/s00228-014-1747-1 <lb/>REFERENCES <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Huang et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PAPERS <lb/>2024 • Vol. 14 • 04225 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">www.jogh.org • doi: 10.7189/jogh.14.04225 <lb/></note>
			<listBibl>37 Health Canada. Drug shortages in Canada: Fiscal year 2022 to 2023 in review. 2023. Available: https://www.canada.ca/ <lb/>en/health-canada/services/drugs-health-products/drug-products/drug-shortages/2022-2023-review.html. Accessed: 23 <lb/>February 2024. <lb/>38 Izutsu KI, Ando D, Morita T, Abe Y, Yoshida H. Generic Drug Shortage in Japan: GMP Noncompliance and Associated <lb/>Quality Issues. J Pharm Sci. 2023;112:1763-71. Medline:36965844 doi:10.1016/j.xphs.2023.03.006 <lb/>39 Lee J, Lee HS, Shin H, Krishnan V. Alleviating drug shortages: The role of mandated reporting induced operational trans-<lb/>parency. Manage Sci. 2021;67:2326-39. doi:10.1287/mnsc.2020.3857 <lb/>40 Lücker F, Seifert RW. Building up resilience in a pharmaceutical supply chain through inventory, dual sourcing and agil-<lb/>ity capacity. Omega. 2017;73:114-24. doi:10.1016/j.omega.2017.01.001 <lb/>41 Benhabib A, Ioughlissen S, Ratignier-Carbonneil C, Maison P. The French reporting system for drug shortages: descrip-<lb/>tion and trends from 2012 to 2018: an observational retrospective study. BMJ Open. 2020;10:e034033. Medline:32139487 <lb/>doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2019-034033 <lb/>42 Zovi A, Inserra C, Piacenza M, Stefania V. Drug shortages and drug unavailability: Analysis from an Italian hospital. Eu-<lb/>ropean Journal of Hospital Pharmacy. 2020;27:A19. <lb/>43 Yang YT, Socal M, Bennett CL. Addressing the Drug-Shortage Crisis in Oncology. JAMA Oncol. 2024;10:155-6. Med-<lb/>line:38175651 doi:10.1001/jamaoncol.2023.5722 <lb/>44 Nagano H, Shin J-h, Kunisawa S, Fushimi K, Nagao M, Imanaka Y. Impact of the cefazolin shortage on the selection and <lb/>cost of parenteral antibiotics during the supply disruption period in Japan: A controlled interrupted time series analysis. <lb/>J Infect Public Health. 2023;16:467-73. Medline:36738690 doi:10.1016/j.jiph.2023.01.021 <lb/>45 National Medical Products Administration. [Notice on the pilot project for settling production bases of essential drug with <lb/>small market demand]. 2012. Available: https://www.nmpa.gov.cn/xxgk/fgwj/gzwj/gzwjyp/20121107120001888.html. <lb/>Accessed: 23 February 2024. Chinese. <lb/>46 National Health and Medicine Administration. [Implementation opinions on reforming and improving the sup-<lb/>ply mechanism of drugs on shortage]. 2017. Available: https://www.gov.cn/xinwen/2017-06/29/content_5206573. <lb/>htm#:~:text=%E4%B8%BA%E8%B4%AF%E5%BD%BB%E8%90%BD%E5%AE%9E%E5%85%A8%E5%9B%B-<lb/>D%E5%8D%AB,%E5%87%BA%E4%BB%A5%E4%B8%8B%E5%AE%9E%E6%96%BD%E6%84%8F%E8%A7-<lb/>%81%E3%80%82. Accessed: 23 February 2024. Chinese. <lb/>47 General Office of the State Council. [Opinions on further improving the work of ensuring supply and stabilizing prices of <lb/>drugs on shortage]. 2019. Available: https://www.gov.cn/zhengce/content/2019-10/11/content_5438499.htm. Accessed: <lb/>23 February 2024. Chinese. <lb/>48 Yang C, Cai W, Li Z, Page AT, Fang Y. The current status and effects of emergency drug shortages in China: Perceptions of <lb/>emergency department physicians. PLoS One. 2018;13:e0205238. Medline:30300412 doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0205238 <lb/>49 Sen-Crowe B, McKenney M, Elkbuli A. Medication shortages during the COVID-19 pandemic: Saving more than COVID <lb/>lives. Am J Emerg Med. 2021;45:557-9. Medline:32763102 doi:10.1016/j.ajem.2020.07.044 <lb/>50 Verma AA, Pai M, Saha S, Bean S, Fralick M, Gibson JL, et al. Managing drug shortages during a pandemic: tocilizumab <lb/>and COVID-19. CMAJ. 2021;193:E771-6. Medline:33952621 doi:10.1503/cmaj.210531 <lb/>51 The Economist Intelligence Unit. Addressing medicine shortages in Europe taking a concerted approach to drive action on <lb/>economic, manufacturing and regulatory factors. London, England: Economist Intelligence Unit; 2017. Available: http:// <lb/>graphics.eiu.com/upload/topic-pages/medicine-shortages/Addressing-medicine-shortages-in-Europe-EIU.pdf. Accessed: <lb/>23 February 2024. <lb/>52 Miljković N, Batista A, Polidori P, Kohl S, Horák P. Results of EAHP&apos;s 2019 Medicines Shortages Survey. European Journal <lb/>of Hospital Pharmacy. 2020;27:202-8. Medline:32471816 doi:10.1136/ejhpharm-2020-002341 <lb/>53 Francas D, Mohr S, Hoberg K. On the drivers of drug shortages: empirical evidence from Germany. Int J Oper Prod Man-<lb/>age. 2023;43:1520-38. doi:10.1108/IJOPM-09-2022-0581 <lb/>54 Nurse-Findlay S, Taylor MM, Savage M, Mello MB, Saliyou S, Lavayen M, et al. Shortages of benzathine penicillin for pre-<lb/>vention of mother-to-child transmission of syphilis: An evaluation from multi-country surveys and stakeholder interviews. <lb/>PLoS Med. 2017;14:e1002473. Medline:29281619 doi:10.1371/journal.pmed.1002473 <lb/>55 Fox ER, Unguru Y. Oncology drug shortages in the USA -business as usual. Nat Rev Clin Oncol. 2020;17:128-9. Med-<lb/>line:31831853 doi:10.1038/s41571-019-0318-x <lb/>56 Gourd E. Cancer care critically affected by USA drug shortages. Lancet Oncol. 2023;24:727. Medline:37331355 doi:10.1016/ <lb/>S1470-2045(23)00289-9 <lb/>57 Shafiq N, Pandey AK, Malhotra S, Holmes A, Mendelson M, Malpani R, et al. Shortage of essential antimicrobials: A major <lb/>challenge to global health security. BMJ Glob Health. 2021;6:e006961. Medline:34728479 doi:10.1136/bmjgh-2021-006961 <lb/>58 LI Y, WU Z, HU X. Analysis of drug use in pediatric patients from 78 sample hospitals in 7 regions of China from 2013 to <lb/>2014. China Pharmacy. 2016;12:4058-61. <lb/>59 Hu A, Li Y, Ma A, Fu Y, Sheng Y, Zhao M. Investigation and Analysis of the Reasons for Drug Shortage from 26 Medical <lb/>Institutions in China. China Pharmacy. 2017;12:3754-3678. <lb/>60 Ji X, Wang Q, Xu J, Ding L, Zeng Y, Li M. Investigation and Suggestion on the Situation of Pediatric Drug Shortage in <lb/>Third-level Hospitals from Ji-angsu Province. China Pharmacy. 2017;12:4617-20. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">REFERENCES </note>


	</text>
</tei>
