<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Discrete Choices under Social Influence: <lb/>Generic Properties <lb/>Mirta B. Gordon (1), Jean-Pierre Nadal (2,3), <lb/>Denis Phan (4,5), Viktoriya Semeshenko (1) <lb/>(1) Laboratoire Techniques de l&apos;Ingénierie Médicale et de la Complexité <lb/>(TIMC-IMAG, UMR 5525 CNRS-UJF), Université Joseph Fourier, Grenoble <lb/>(2) Centre d&apos;Analyse et Mathématique Sociales (CAMS, UMR 8557 CNRS-EHESS), <lb/>Ecole des Hautes Etudes en Sciences Sociales, Paris <lb/>(3) Laboratoire de Physique Statistique (LPS, UMR 8550 CNRS-ENS-Paris 6-Paris 7), <lb/>Ecole Normale Supérieure, Paris <lb/>(4) Centre de Recherche en Economie et Management <lb/>(CREM, UMR 6211 CNRS-Université de Caen-Université de Rennes 1), Université de Rennes 1 <lb/>(5) Groupe d&apos;Etude des Méthodes de l&apos;Analyse Sociologique <lb/>(GEMAS, UMR 8598 CNRS-Université Paris Sorbonne -Paris IV), Paris <lb/>March 7, 2007 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>We consider a model of socially interacting individuals that make a binary choice in a <lb/>context of positive additive endogenous externalities. It encompasses as particular cases <lb/>several models from the sociology and economics literature. We extend previous results <lb/>to the case of a general distribution of idiosyncratic preferences, called here Idiosyncratic <lb/>Willingnesses to Pay (IWP). <lb/>Positive additive externalities yield a family of inverse demand curves that include the <lb/>classical downward sloping ones but also new ones with non constant convexity. When j, <lb/>the ratio of the social influence strength to the standard deviation of the IWP distribution, <lb/>is small enough, the inverse demand is a classical monotonic (decreasing) function of the <lb/>adoption rate. Even if the IWP distribution is mono-modal, there is a critical value of j <lb/>above which the inverse demand is non monotonic, decreasing for small and high adoption <lb/>rates, but increasing within some intermediate range. Depending on the price there are <lb/>thus either one or two equilibria. <lb/>Beyond this first result, we exhibit the generic properties of the boundaries limiting <lb/>the regions where the system presents different types of equilibria (unique or multiple). <lb/>These properties are shown to depend only on qualitative features of the IWP distribution: <lb/>modality (number of maxima), smoothness and type of support (compact or infinite). The <lb/>main results are summarized as phase diagrams in the space of the model parameters, on <lb/>which the regions of multiple equilibria are precisely delimited. <lb/>1 <lb/>halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></front>

			<body>Contents <lb/>1 Introduction <lb/>1.1 Modeling social influences with heterogeneous agents . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3 <lb/>1.2 More on related models . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 5 <lb/>1.3 Main specific results . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 6 <lb/>1.4 Organization of the paper . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7 <lb/>2 Model of discrete choices with heterogeneous agents and positive externali-<lb/>ties <lb/>2.1 Agents model . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 8 <lb/>2.2 Aggregate behavior: normalized equations . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 10 <lb/>2.3 Hints from two extreme cases . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>2.4 The idiosyncratic willingness-to-pay distribution . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 11 <lb/>3 Aggregate choices and coordination dilemma <lb/>13 <lb/>3.1 The direct and inverse demand functions . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>3.2 Demand phase diagram . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>3.2.1 The demand multiple-solution region . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>3.2.2 Generic properties . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>3.2.3 The phase diagram . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>3.2.4 Vicinity of the bifurcation point . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>3.2.5 Pareto optimality and coordination . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>3.3 Summary of the generic customers&apos; model . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/> 4 Conclusion and perspectives <lb/>22 <lb/>A Appendix: Demand for other distributions <lb/>30 <lb/>A.1 Pdfs with compact support . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>A.2 Pdfs with fat tails . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>A.3 Aggregate demand for multimodal pdfs . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>A.3.1 Smooth pdfs: generic properties . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>A.3.2 A degenerate case: 2 Dirac . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<body>1 Introduction <lb/>1.1 Modeling social influences with heterogeneous agents <lb/>There are many circumstances in social and economic contexts where, faced with different <lb/>alternatives, the best choice for an individual depends on the choices of other individuals in the <lb/>population. The decision of leaving a neighborhood [78], to attend a seminar [78] or a crowded <lb/>bar [2, 3], to participate to collective actions such as strikes and riots [46], are particular <lb/>examples taken from social sciences. It has been suggested that social interactions may explain <lb/>the school dropout [24], the persistence in the educational level within some neighborhoods [30] <lb/>and the related consequences in the stratification of investment in human capital and economic <lb/>segregation [11], the large dispersion in urban crime through cities with similar characteristics <lb/>[42], the emergence of social norms [71], the labor market behavior and related unemployment <lb/>patterns [88, 86], the housing demand [96], the existence of poverty traps [34], the smoking <lb/>behavior [56, 55, 83], etc. <lb/>Similarly, there is a growing economic literature that recognizes the influence on consumers <lb/>of the social world they live in. In market situations like the subscription to a telephone <lb/>network [5, 75, 90, 25] or the choice of a computer operating system [52], the willingness to <lb/>pay generally depends not only on the individual preferences but also on the choice made by <lb/>others [81, 76]. If the externality is positive the utility of the most popular choice increases even <lb/>for individuals who otherwise would never make this choice. In other words, the conformity <lb/>effect may dominate the heterogeneity of preferences, as pointed out by Bernheim [12]. General <lb/>aspects of these issues have been discussed in the literature [10, 60]. Particular insightful papers <lb/>are Becker&apos;s note [9] about restaurants pricing, and the qualitative analysis by Granoveter and <lb/>Soong [47] of the consequences of interpersonal influences (&quot;bandwagon effects&quot;[57, 76]) on the <lb/>consumers demand and on the supply prices. <lb/>In the present paper we consider the general properties of a model of socially interacting <lb/>heterogeneous individuals that make a binary choice in a context of positive endogenous ex-<lb/>ternalities. The model encompasses, as particular cases, most of the above mentioned models <lb/>presented in the sociology and economics literature. In a forthcoming paper [44] we explore the <lb/>consequences of the externalities on the economy, taking as an example the simplest market, <lb/>i.e. that of a monopolist pricing a single good. <lb/>In social sciences, the question of discrete (typically binary) choices with heterogeneous <lb/>agents and positive externalities has been first addressed in the 70&apos;s by Schelling [77, 78], who <lb/>borrowed from Physics the concept of critical mass: in a repeated-decisions setting, depending <lb/>on whether this critical mass is or not reached, the system may end up at very different equi-<lb/>libria. Granovetter further develops Schelling&apos;s model, applying it to particular problems such <lb/>as joining or not a riot [46], voting, etc [47]. The same topic is reconsidered within a statis-<lb/>tical physics point of view in the early 80&apos;s by Galam et al [39]. The notion of critical mass <lb/>is then related to the Physics concept of phase transition at a critical point, in the neighbor-<lb/>hood of which the system may be extremely susceptible: by tipping effects, small microscopic <lb/>changes can lead to drastic changes at the macroscopic level. Similar tools have been applied <lb/>in 1980 by Kindermann and Snell [53] to the study of social networks. These authors intro-<lb/>duced into the sociology and economics literature the equivalence between statistical physics <lb/>approaches -that use the Boltzmann-Gibbs distribution-and Markov Random Fields. An-<lb/>other physically-inspired approach for modeling social phenomena such as opinion diffusion <lb/>has been developed by Weidlich and Haag [93, 92] in 1983, through a master equation and <lb/>the Fokker-Planck approximation. Later, these physically inspired models of opinion contagion <lb/>have been exploited in economics by Orléan [69, 70] for the analysis of mimetic behaviors in <lb/>the context of financial markets. There is now a large and growing literature on opinion and <lb/>innovation diffusion (see e.g. [89, 49, 26, 91, 84]) closely related to the general discrete choice <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<body>model considered in this paper. Since the beginning of the 90&apos;s the general framework of social <lb/>interactions in non-market contexts is reconsidered in a Beckerian way [8, 10], in particular by <lb/>Glaeser et al [41, 42, 40]. <lb/>The first application of statistical mechanics approaches in economics may be traced back <lb/>to the pioneering work of Fölmer [36]. Introducing an economic interpretation of the Ising <lb/>model of ferromagnetism at finite temperature, he shows that strong externalities may hinder <lb/>the stabilization of an economy. These models introduce Markov random fields (equivalently <lb/>Boltzmann-Gibbs distributions) to model uncertainty in the decision making process, allowing <lb/>for the definition of a general equilibrium concept. According to Fölmer, Hildebrand&apos;s [48] justi-<lb/>fication of the representative agent approach breaks down when agents&apos; decisions are correlated <lb/>due to their social interactions (for a discussion, see also [54]). <lb/>A renewal of interest for models of binary decisions with externalities arose in economics <lb/>in the 90&apos;s. On one side, Durlauf and collaborators [27, 28, 29, 30] and Kirman and Weis-<lb/>buch [94] among others, consider agents that choose an action according to a Boltzmann-Gibbs <lb/>distribution, that is a logistic choice function, reflecting some random aspects in the agent&apos;s <lb/>utility. In this context Brock [19] and Blume [13, 14] explicit the links between Game Theory <lb/>and Statistical Mechanics, while Kirman and coworkers [67] show that the logistic choice func-<lb/>tion may be seen as resulting from an exploration-exploitation compromise. These and other <lb/>recent papers [4, 31, 32, 20, 21, 40, 95, 35, 45, 65, 16] analyze with statistical physics tools the <lb/>consequences of positive social (market and non-market) interactions in the aggregate behavior <lb/>of large populations (for a short introduction to statistical physics approaches see [43] and for <lb/>their application to economics see [72]; see also [7] for a survey). Most of the above mentioned <lb/>authors restrict the analysis of the model to the case where all the individuals have the same <lb/>idiosyncratic preference. Heterogeneity in the population is introduced through the probabilis-<lb/>tic decision-making process (random utility model [58, 59]), like in Fölmer&apos;s work [36]. Then, <lb/>the actual equilibrium reached by the system depends on the fixed points of the decision dy-<lb/>namics, generally a myopic best reply. An interesting characteristic of these models is that they <lb/>present multiple equilibria for some range of the parameters. Becker [9] pointed out important <lb/>consequences of these multiple equilibria, induced by externalities, on the economy: he suggests <lb/>that they could be the reason of seemingly suboptimal pricing in situations of persistent excess <lb/>demand. <lb/>In this paper we consider intrinsically heterogeneous agents with fixed utilities, like in Mc-<lb/>Fadden&apos;s approach to Quantal Choice models [62, 63]. Each individual has an Idiosyncratic <lb/>Willingness to Pay (IWP) that remains fixed on time. We mainly (but not exclusively) decline <lb/>the model within a market context, in which the binary choice corresponds to buying or not a <lb/>given good at a posted price. This general setting allows us to generalize Becker&apos;s qualitative <lb/>analysis [9] of the optimal pricing problem. Putting the price to zero allows us to recover the <lb/>social sciences models. We assume that these IWP are random variables that are distributed <lb/>among the population according to a given probability density function (pdf). <lb/>We determine the possible equilibria of the system without assuming any precise decision-<lb/>making dynamics. We show that the model&apos;s properties depend on the strength of the ex-<lb/>ternality and on qualitative properties of the IWP pdf, like its modality class (the number <lb/>of maxima), its smoothness properties and the kind of support. We display the main results <lb/>on a plane whose axes are the parameters of the model, namely, the average IWP and the <lb/>strength of the social component, both measured in units of the standard deviation of the IWP <lb/>distribution. Particular cases of our model have been published elsewhere [66, 45]. This paper <lb/>extends those result to the case of a general IWP distribution. The particularly important case <lb/>of a uni-modal pdf (with a single maximum) is thoroughly studied, but we also discuss the <lb/>consequences of multi-modality. Our results are summarized on phase diagrams, that is, we <lb/>plot in the parameters space the boundaries of the regions where different types of solutions <lb/>exist. <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<body>Before entering into the details of our approach (section 2) we discuss the analogies and <lb/>differences between our model and other models of social interactions (section 1.2) and we <lb/>summarize our main results (section 1.3). <lb/>1.2 More on related models <lb/>In this section we briefly discuss the relationship between the model to be considered here <lb/>and other models studied in the literature. Let us first consider models of discrete choices <lb/>in the absence of externalities. According to the typology proposed by Anderson et al. [1], <lb/>within the general framework of Random Utility Models (RUM)[58, 59] with additive stochastic <lb/>utilities, there are two distinct approaches to individual choices: a &quot;psychological&quot; one and an <lb/>&quot;economic&quot; one. In the psychological perspective (Thurstone [87], Luce [58]) the randomness is a <lb/>time-dependent i.i.d. random variable: the random components of the idiosyncratic preferences <lb/>are assumed to be independently drawn afresh by each individual from a given pdf, each time <lb/>the choice has to be made. They are interpreted as individual temporary changes, or mistakes <lb/>in the estimated utilities. In the simplest case -actually, the only one treated in the social <lb/>and economic literature-the agents IWPs have identical deterministic parts and only differ <lb/>by this random time-varying term which is systematically assumed to be drawn from a logistic <lb/>pdf. In practice many approaches like in [20] consider the choice rule as deriving from a random <lb/>utility model [58]. As shown by McFadden [62], in this context the logistic form is obtained if <lb/>the random terms in the underlying Thurstone&apos;s discriminant process are i.i.d. Weibull random <lb/>variables, i.e. have a double exponential (extreme value, type I) distribution (see also [1]). <lb/>In the presence of strategic complementarities ([22, 23]), the resulting model is well known <lb/>in statistical physics: it corresponds to the standard Ising model, i.e. with ferromagnetic in-<lb/>teractions and annealed disorder, that is, at finite temperature T . The latter is the inverse of <lb/>the standard logistic parameter β ≡ 1/T and is thus proportional to the standard deviation of <lb/>the IWP distribution. The ferromagnetic interaction constant J corresponds to the strength <lb/>of the social externality. Introduced by Fölmer [36] in the economics context, this standard <lb/>Ising model has recently been reconsidered in the social and economic literature mainly by <lb/>Durlauf and coworkers [31, 32, 20, 21] and by Kirman and Weisbuch [94, 67]. The correspond-<lb/>ing equilibria are reminiscent of the Quantal Response Equilibria [64] used in the context of <lb/>experimental economics and behavioral game theory. These are equilibria &quot;on the average&quot;, <lb/>in the statistical sense (as in Physics): they do not correspond to the strict maximization of <lb/>the utilities (that are random variables) but to that of their estimated or expected values. In <lb/>the generally considered infinite population limit (where the variance of the expected values <lb/>vanishes) the expected utilities are systematically smaller that the maximal ones. <lb/>The standard Ising model is quite well understood [85]. Ising himself [51] gave an analytic <lb/>description of its properties in the simplest case of a linear chain where each agent interacts only <lb/>with his right and left nearest neighbors. There is also an analytical description of the stationary <lb/>states of the model, due to Onsager [68], in the case where the agents are situated on the vertices <lb/>of a 2-dimensional square lattice, each having four neighbors. However, no analytic results exist <lb/>for arbitrary neighborhoods except for the specific case of a global neighborhood, known as the <lb/>mean field approximation in Physics. Accordingly, considering global neighborhoods, Brock and <lb/>Durlauf [20] analyze the properties of the expected demand in the case of rational expectations <lb/>under the assumption of a logistic distribution of such expectations (assuming thus double <lb/>exponential random utilities). They find, in agreement with standard results in statistical <lb/>mechanics [85], that there exist either one, two or three solutions for the demand function, <lb/>depending on the relative magnitudes of the idiosyncratic uniform social term, the variance of <lb/>the stochastic term and the strength of the social effects. <lb/>In the following we adopt instead McFadden&apos;s [62] economic approach (see also [59, 1]): <lb/>we assume that each agent has a willingness to pay invariable in time, that is different from <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<body>one agent to the other. In statistical physics this heterogeneity is called quenched disorder. <lb/>The particular model we study is analogous to the ferromagnetic Random Field Ising Model <lb/>(RFIM) at zero temperature (corresponding to the fact that the agents make deterministic <lb/>choices). Thus, our modeling approach assumes the so called &quot;risky&quot; situation: an external <lb/>observer (e.g. a seller) does not have access to the individual preferences, but may know their <lb/>probability distribution. According to McFadden, &quot;Thurstone&apos;s construction is appealing to an <lb/>economist because the assumption that a single subject will draw independent utility functions <lb/>in repeated choice settings and then proceed to maximize them is formally equivalent to a model <lb/>in which the experimenter draws individuals randomly from a population with differing, but <lb/>fixed, utility functions, and offers each a single choice; the latter model is consistent with the <lb/>classical postulates of economic rationality&quot; ([63], p 365). However, in the presence of social <lb/>interactions this statement is in general incorrect. In a repeated choice setting, individual <lb/>utilities evolve in time according to the others&apos; decisions. In fact, the equilibria of systems <lb/>reached through a dynamics that corresponds to an iterated game where agents make myopic <lb/>choices at each time-step is one of the main concerns of statistical physics. It is known that <lb/>the equilibria of systems with annealed or quenched disorder are of very different nature. The <lb/>time average on a single agent and the population average at a given time do not necessarily <lb/>coincide. <lb/>In contrast to the standard Ising model at finite temperature (annealed disorder), the prop-<lb/>erties of the RFIM with externalities, both at zero and at finite temperatures, are far from being <lb/>fully understood. The properties of quenched disordered systems have been and are still the <lb/>subject of numerous studies. Since the first studies of the RFIM, which date back to Aharony <lb/>and Galam [38, 37], a number of important results have been published in the physics literature <lb/>on this model (see e. g. [80]). Several variants of the RFIM have already been used in the <lb/>context of socio-economic modeling, both by physicists and economists [39, 70, 18, 95]. <lb/>The quenched-utilities model (RFIM at zero temperature) and the annealed-disorder model <lb/>(standard mean field Ising model at finite temperature) have the same aggregate behavior <lb/>(i.e. demand function for the market case) and equilibria under the following conditions -but <lb/>essentially only under such conditions: <lb/>1. the choice function with annealed utilities is identical to the cumulative distribution of <lb/>the quenched IWPs; <lb/>2. in the annealed case, equilibrium is reached through repeated best reply choices, where <lb/>the expected demand is myopically estimated; <lb/>3. the population size is infinite, guaranteeing that the variance of the demand vanishes in <lb/>both models. <lb/>However, the economic interpretation of these equilibria are very different: in the case of <lb/>quenched utilities these are standard Nash equilibria, while in the case of annealed utilities <lb/>these are similar (although not identical) to Quantal Response equilibria. <lb/>1.3 Main specific results <lb/>In the present paper we determine the equilibrium properties in the case of a global neighborhood <lb/>with time invariant (quenched) random utilities, in the limit of an infinite number of agents. <lb/>Since our paper focuses on equilibrium (static) properties, the social influence depends on the <lb/>actual choices of the neighbors, in contrast with [20], where the social influence in the surplus <lb/>function depends on the agent&apos;s expected demand. <lb/>Previous studies using annealed or quenched utilities consider specific probability distribu-<lb/>tions, mostly a logistic or a Gaussian [87]. Some papers have determined conditions on the <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<body>choice function for having multi-equilibria [67, 40]. From the Physics literature we expect that <lb/>specific properties near a critical point (a bifurcation point, see Section 3.2.1 below) are inde-<lb/>pendent of the details of the model: this is used in [80] for describing the hysteresis effects in <lb/>a family of (physical) systems at such a critical point, and exploited in [65] for the analysis of <lb/>empirical socio-economic data in cases where the actual pdfs are not known. However, the full <lb/>description of the phase diagram for an arbitrary pdf has not been done yet. Here we present <lb/>this detailed analysis for a typical probability distribution of the IWP. We show how uniqueness <lb/>or multiplicity of equilibria, related to convexity properties of the inverse demand functions, <lb/>result from modality and smoothness of the pdf, as well as from the strength of the externality. <lb/>We show that for small enough strengths of the social influence (the case of moderate social <lb/>influence in [40]), the demand has a classical shape, that is, with a continuous decreasing <lb/>adoption rate for increasing prices. However, if the ratio between the social influence strength <lb/>and the standard deviation of the IWP distribution exceeds a critical value, the inverse demand <lb/>function exhibits a non-classical, non-monotonic, behavior. As a result, depending on the price, <lb/>there are either one or two stable equilibria for the demand: the positive (additive) externalities <lb/>in a market context may give raise to a family of non-monotonic demand curves generalizing <lb/>thus the classical ones. <lb/>Beyond this first main result, we exhibit the generic properties of the boundaries limiting <lb/>the regions where the system presents different types of equilibria (unique or multiple). We <lb/>call these properties generic since we show that they depend only on qualitative features of <lb/>the IWP distribution: modality (number of maxima), smoothness (continuity and derivability <lb/>properties) and type of support (compact or infinite). The main results are summarized as <lb/>phase diagrams in the space of the relevant parameters of the model, namely (i) the social <lb/>influence strength and (ii) the difference between the population average of the IWP and the <lb/>posted price, both parameters conveniently normalized by the standard deviation of the IWP <lb/>distribution (which measures the importance of the heterogeneity). <lb/>1.4 Organization of the paper <lb/>The paper is organized as follows. In Section 2 we present the model: we first (section 2.1) <lb/>specify the agents (customers) model, then in 2.2 we introduce a normalized form of the basic <lb/>equations which is convenient for analyzing the demand, and in 2.3 we show on two simple <lb/>extreme cases what to expect from these equations. In 2.4 we detail the families of probability <lb/>distributions of the IWP covered by this paper. <lb/>In Section 3 we analyze the aggregate demand (its collective behavior) for a generic smooth <lb/>pdf. In 3.1 we introduce and study the direct and inverse demand functions; the demand <lb/>phase diagram is derived in Section 3.2: in 3.2.1 we obtain the domain of multiple solutions <lb/>which allows to plot the phase diagram (section 3.2.3). We analyze in details the vicinity of <lb/>the bifurcation point (section 3.2.4) and the question of Pareto optimality (section 3.2.5). A <lb/>summary of the demand properties is given in 3.3. <lb/>We leave to the Appendix A the analysis of other kinds of pdfs, where we study the demand <lb/>phase diagrams of IWP distributions with compact support (section A.1) and with fat tails <lb/>(section A.2). The demand phase diagram for a pdf with an arbitrary number of maxima is <lb/>studied in A.3 -in details for a smooth multimodal pdf in Section A.3.1, and on a simple <lb/>example of singular bimodal distribution in section A.3.2-. <lb/>Finally we summarize the main results and give several perspectives for further research in <lb/>Section 4. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<body>2 Model of discrete choices with heterogeneous agents <lb/>and positive externalities <lb/>2.1 Agents model <lb/>We consider a population of N agents (i = 1, 2, . . . , N ). Each individual i has to make a binary <lb/>choice. Depending on the context, this binary decision may represent the fact of buying or <lb/>not a good, adopting or not a given standard, adopting or not some social behavior such as <lb/>joining a riot [46], or a journal club [77], [78], etc. Formally each agent i must choose a strategy <lb/>ω i in the strategic set Ω = {0, 1} (ω i = 1 denotes to buy/adopt/join, ω i = 0 otherwise) 1 . <lb/>Hereafter, without loss of generality, we will refer to the simplest market situation where the <lb/>agents are customers who must choose whether to buy or not a single good at a price P . Our <lb/>main concern is with the agents&apos; behaviors, and P is considered as an exogenous parameter <lb/>-e.g. it is posted by a monopolist selling the good-. Non-market models like those recently <lb/>considered by, i.e., Glaeser et al. [40] are obtained by setting P = 0 or by considering P as an <lb/>exogenous social cost, common to all the agents. We are interested in the collective outcome of <lb/>the agents decisions. In a following paper [44] focusing on the market context we will analyze <lb/>the consequences of the customers collective behavior on a monopolist&apos;s program for fixing the <lb/>optimal price. <lb/>The population is heterogeneous. Each individual i has an idiosyncratic preference or will-<lb/>ingness to pay/adopt (hereafter IWP) H i , meaning that in the absence of social influences, an <lb/>agent i adopts the state ω i = 1 if H i is larger than the price P . Following Mc-Fadden [62] and <lb/>Manski [59], we work within the framework of Random Utility Models (RUM): we assume that <lb/>the H i are time independent random variables independently and identically distributed (i.i.d.) <lb/>in the population. Denoting by H the mean and by σ the variance of the IWP distribution, <lb/>hereafter we assume that the random variable (H i − H)/σ is distributed according to: <lb/>P(x &lt; <lb/>H i − H <lb/>σ <lb/>&lt; x + dx) = f (x)dx, <lb/>(1) <lb/>so that f is a pdf with zero mean and unitary variance. In the RUM view point, the agents <lb/>have utilities H 0 <lb/>i and H 1 <lb/>i for not adopting and adopting respectively, with H 0 and H 1 the <lb/>corresponding population averages. For k = 0, 1, one writes H k <lb/>i = H k + k <lb/>i , where k <lb/>i are <lb/>independent random variables with zero mean and standard deviation σ k , with not necessarily <lb/>identical pdfs for k = 0 and k = 1. Then in our model we have H i = H 1 <lb/>i − H 0 <lb/>i , H = H 1 − H 0 <lb/>and f is the pdf of the normalized difference x i = ( 1 <lb/>i − 0 <lb/>i )/σ, with σ 2 = (σ 0 ) 2 + (σ 1 ) 2 because <lb/>of the additivity of the variances of independent variables. As particular examples, if k <lb/>i are <lb/>Gaussian variables, then x i is also Gaussian; if k <lb/>i are uniformly distributed on, say the intervals <lb/>[−a k , a k ], then x i has a trapezoidal pdf, which becomes a triangular distribution if e.g. a 0 = 0 <lb/>(no uncertainty in the utility of not adopting). In the following we do not assume any specific <lb/>form of the pdf of x. In Section 2.4 below, we present in details the class of pdfs considered in <lb/>this paper. <lb/>If all the individuals had the same IWP, the outcome in absence of social interactions would <lb/>be very simple: either the price is below this common value, and everybody buys, or it is above it <lb/>and nobody buys. All the individuals would behave in the same way, obtaining the same payoffs, <lb/>and in the market aggregate analysis, they may be replaced by a fictitious representative agent <lb/>[54]. In the case of a heterogeneous population considered here, only the agents with H i ≥ P <lb/>would buy at price P , but getting different payoffs. <lb/>The situation is more complex when the decision of each agent depends also on the decisions <lb/>of others ([59] and references therein). We assume that each agent is the more willing to pay <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">1 Some authors use the notation s i = 1 and s i = −1; both encodings are equivalent: it suffices to replace <lb/>ω i = (s i + 1)/2 in our model and identify the coefficients of corresponding expressions. <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<body>the larger the number of buyers in the population. We consider a linear separable surplus, that <lb/>is if agent i buys at the posted price P , his surplus is <lb/>S i = H i + Jη − P, <lb/>(2) <lb/>where η is the fraction of buyers in the population. Taking into account the definition of ω i : <lb/>η ≡ <lb/>1 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>i=1 <lb/>ω i . <lb/>(3) <lb/>We assume also that the externality Jη corresponds to strategic complementarities, i.e. that <lb/>the strength of the social influence is positive: J &gt; 0 2 . <lb/>The actual surplus of agent i is: <lb/>W i = S i ω i . <lb/>(4) <lb/>In order to maximize his surplus, agent i should buy/adopt (ω i = 1) if S i &gt; 0, but not (ω i = 0) <lb/>when S i &lt; 0. Since the IWP are i.i.d., when N is very large (more precisely, in the limit <lb/>N → ∞), by the law of large numbers, the fraction of buyers (3) -which is the average of ω i -<lb/>converges to the expected value of ω i over the IWP distribution. Thus, η is given by the fixed <lb/>point equation: <lb/>η = P(H i − P + Jη &gt; 0). <lb/>(5) <lb/>The marginal customer m, indifferent between adopting or not, is defined by the condition of <lb/>zero surplus, S m = 0: <lb/>H m − P + Jη = 0 <lb/>(6) <lb/>so that (5) may be written as <lb/>η = P(H i &gt; H m ). <lb/>(7) <lb/>For what follows it is more useful to write (5) as <lb/>η = P(H i − H &gt; −S) <lb/>(8) <lb/>where <lb/>S = S(J, H, P ; η) ≡ H − P + Jη <lb/>(9) <lb/>is the population average of the (ex ante) surplus S i . It depends on the parameters J and H, <lb/>which are properties of the customers population, and P , the exogenous price. <lb/>Notation. Generally, upon manipulating functions, we put in parenthesis the parameters <lb/>in front, separated with a semicolon (;) from what we consider the variable. Our notation <lb/>S(J, H, P ; η) in (9) indicates that J, H and P are considered as parameters, whereas η is the <lb/>variable. Sometimes, when the context is clear, we drop down the parameters and keep only <lb/>the variable, writing thus S(η). Whenever we consider functions of two variables, they are <lb/>separated by a simple colon, like in equations (37) and (38), and in Appendix A.3. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">2 More generally, the social term may be proportional to the fraction of buyers in an individual-depending <lb/>subset of the population, called &quot;neighbors&quot; of agent i. In this paper, we consider a global neighborhood, where <lb/>every agent has social connections with every other agent, mainly because this case can be studied analytically. <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<body>2.2 Aggregate behavior: normalized equations <lb/>Clearly, the fraction of buyers η depends on the strength of the social influence J, the price <lb/>P and the average willingness to pay in the population H, and on the distribution of the <lb/>deviation of the IWP H i from its population average H. The agents choices depend only on <lb/>the surplus sign, and they are invariant under changes of the surplus scale. Since the surplus is <lb/>linear, we can formally multiply every term of the surplus by a same strictly positive number <lb/>without changing the agents&apos; choices. An adequate scale is given by the typical scale of the <lb/>IWP distribution: it is convenient to measure each quantity (J, H, P ) in units of the width σ of <lb/>the IWP pdf. Hence instead of four parameters, we are left with three independent parameters. <lb/>Hereafter we will thus work with the following normalized variables <lb/>j ≡ <lb/>J <lb/>σ <lb/>, h ≡ <lb/>H <lb/>σ <lb/>, p ≡ <lb/>P <lb/>σ <lb/>(10) <lb/>In addition, as it is obvious from equations (8) and (9), η depends on the price P and the <lb/>average willingness to pay H only through their difference H − P . We introduce the normalized <lb/>difference: <lb/>δ ≡ <lb/>H − P <lb/>σ <lb/>= h − p, <lb/>(11) <lb/>which is the average ex-ante surplus in the absence of externality. For short hereafter we call δ <lb/>the bare surplus. In non-market models (p = 0) it is the average willingness to adopt. <lb/>Remark. In (almost) all the following we will work with the above reduced variables (10), <lb/>(11), referring to them as the (normalized) strength of social influence, average willingness to <lb/>pay, price, and bare surplus. However one should keep in mind, especially when interpreting the <lb/>results, that they represent the ratios of the non normalized parameters to the width of the IWP <lb/>distribution. Clearly other normalizations are possible. An alternative of particular interest is <lb/>the normalization obtained by measuring every quantity in units of the social strength J: the <lb/>relevant parameters are theñ <lb/>σ ≡ <lb/>σ <lb/>J <lb/>,h ≡ <lb/>H <lb/>J <lb/>,p ≡ <lb/>P <lb/>J <lb/>,δ ≡ <lb/>H − P <lb/>J <lb/>=h −p <lb/>(12) <lb/>(equivalently one can do as if J = 1). Note that this choice of normalization is no more than an <lb/>equivalent representation of the parameters space; indeed one hasσ = 1/j,h = h/j,p = p/j. <lb/>It is also interesting to analyze the results in term of the set of parameters (12), which allow to <lb/>stress the model properties as a function of the degree of heterogeneity (relative to the strength <lb/>of the social influence) -a homogeneous population corresponding to the limiting caseσ = 0, <lb/>a highly heterogeneous one to a largeσ-. <lb/>With the normalized variables (10), (11), equation (8) becomes <lb/>η = <lb/>∞ <lb/>−s <lb/>f (x)dx = 1 − F (−s), <lb/>(13) <lb/>where F is the cumulative probability distribution and s = S/σ, with S defined by (9), depends <lb/>on h and p through the bare surplus δ, that is <lb/>s = s(j, δ; η) ≡ δ + jη. <lb/>(14) <lb/>If the pdf has infinite support, <lb/>F (−s) ≡ P(x ≤ −s) = <lb/>−s <lb/>−∞ <lb/>f (x)dx. <lb/>(15) <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<body>In the case of a compact support [x m , x M ], one can write: <lb/>η = 1 − F (−s) = <lb/>max{xM ,−s} <lb/>max{xm,−s} <lb/>f (x)dx. <lb/>(16) <lb/>Obviously, when −s &lt; x m , we have η = 1, and when −s &gt; x M we have η = 0. <lb/>2.3 Hints from two extreme cases <lb/>In the absence of social influence the problem is simple because after introduction of j = 0 <lb/>in (14) we obtain s = δ which does not depend on η. Then, due to the monotonicity of <lb/>cumulative distributions, the fraction of buyers (13) is a monotonically increasing function of δ <lb/>(equivalently, at fixed h, a decreasing function of the price p): <lb/>η = 1 − F (−δ). <lb/>(17) <lb/>Another extreme case is that of a homogeneous population: H i = H for every i -a sit-<lb/>uation obtained in the singular limitσ = 1/j → 0 (the IWP distribution becoming a Dirac <lb/>distribution)-. In that case every agent is faced to exactly the same decision problem, so that <lb/>at equilibrium either η = 0 or η = 1. For each agent the surplus in case of adoption would be <lb/>H − P if no other agent adopt (η = 0), whereas if η = 1 the surplus is H − P + J. In fact, η = 0 <lb/>is a solution for H &lt; P , while η = 1 is a solution for H &gt; P − J. Hence there is a domain, <lb/>P − J &lt; H &lt; P , where the two solutions coexist. The whole population behaves as a single <lb/>agent who either does not adopt, η = 0, or adopts, η = 1, with a different surplus depending on <lb/>whether he is &quot;in&quot; or &quot;out of&quot; the market: this is analogous to the problem of multi-equilibria <lb/>with hysteresis in trade analyzed by Baldwin and Krugman [6], except that here the problem <lb/>arises only at the collective level. <lb/>We have thus on one side, for J = 0 and σ finite, a unique well behaved equilibrium, and for <lb/>J &gt; 0 but σ = 0 a situation of multiequilibria. The question addressed in the following aims <lb/>at understanding what happens &quot;in between&quot;. We will show that when the social interaction <lb/>strength is large enough compared to the heterogeneity width, the demand faces a complex <lb/>problem. More precisely, there is a critical value j B of j = J/σ. Below it, the fraction of buyers <lb/>(equation (13)) follows monotonically the price variations. Beyond j B , equation (13) presents <lb/>multiple solutions. Among them, the (possibly multiple) Nash equilibria are those solutions <lb/>that have an economic meaning, i.e. for which the demand decreases when prices increase. <lb/>The Section 3 of the paper is devoted to a detailed study of the nature of the solutions <lb/>of equations (13) and (14) with j ≥ 0 for distributions satisfying very general smoothness <lb/>hypotheses, detailed in the next section. <lb/>2.4 The idiosyncratic willingness-to-pay distribution <lb/>Since we are interested in the generic properties of the model, we explicit the general charac-<lb/>teristics of the idiosyncratic willingness-to-pay (IWP) distributions covered by our analysis. <lb/>Since a pdf must be integrable, f (x) (equation (1) ) must vanish in the limits x → ±∞. <lb/>For sufficiently regular pdfs, this can happen in two different ways: either the pdf decreases <lb/>continuously to 0 as x → ±∞, or it is strictly zero outside some compact support [x m , x M ]. <lb/>Most of the analysis in this paper is restricted to the class of pdfs obeying to the following <lb/>hypotheses: <lb/>H1. Modality: f is unimodal, that is it has a unique maximum <lb/>f B ≡ sup <lb/>x <lb/>f (x). <lb/>(18) <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<body>H2. Smoothness: f is non zero, continuous, and at least piecewise twice continuously differ-<lb/>entiable inside its support, ]x m , x M [ , where x m and x M may be finite or equal to ±∞. <lb/>In the latter case f is stricly monotonically decreasing towards zero as x → ±∞. <lb/>H3. Boundedness: the maximum of f , f B (that may be reached at x m or x M if these numbers <lb/>are finite), is finite: <lb/>f B &lt; ∞ <lb/>(19) <lb/>Within the class of pdfs satisfying H1, H2 and H3, we will consider more specifically the <lb/>important following prototypical cases: <lb/>1. Unbounded supports: The support of the distribution is the real axis; the pdf is continuous <lb/>and twice continuously derivable on ] − ∞, ∞[, with a unique maximum. A typical ex-<lb/>ample, relevant to economics (see e.g. [1]), is given by the logistic distribution, although <lb/>more generally we do not assume that the pdf is symmetric. We make the following <lb/>supplementary hypothesis, that amount to impose that the pdf decreases fast enough for <lb/>x → ±∞: <lb/>H4. Mean value: the pdf has a finite mean value. Then, the smoothness condition H2 <lb/>imposes that f decreases when x → ±∞ faster than |x| −1 . <lb/>H5. Variance: the pdf has a finite variance. Then, the smoothness condition H2 imposes <lb/>that f decreases when x → ±∞ faster than |x| −2 . <lb/>2. Compact supports: the support of the distribution is some interval [x m , x M ], with x m and <lb/>x M finite; the pdf is continuous on [x m , x M ] and continuously derivable on ]x m , x M [, with <lb/>a unique maximum on [x m , x M ]. Note that, since f has zero mean, x m &lt; 0 &lt; x M . <lb/>Hypothesis H2 and H3 exclude cases where the pdf is not a function but a distribution -<lb/>containing, e.g., a Dirac delta -. Clearly, if the pdf&apos;s support is the real line, ] − ∞, +∞[, <lb/>the boundedness hypothesis H3 is a consequence of the smoothness hypothesis H2. In the <lb/>case of compact supports, H3 excludes pdfs diverging at a boundary of the support. Although <lb/>hypothesis H3 is actually true under H2 if f is continuous on the closed interval [x m , x M ], we <lb/>explicit it because some of our results are valid under H3 even for pdfs less regular than those <lb/>satisfying H2. <lb/>Although hypothesis H5 is not necessary for the study of the aggregate demand, it corre-<lb/>sponds to a wide family of realistic distributions for which one can conveniently use the standard <lb/>deviation as the unit for measuring the relevant parameters (i.e., using normalization (10)). <lb/>Generic results for unbounded support pdfs satisfying H1 to H5 are presented in the main <lb/>body of the paper. They extend previous results obtained for a logistic distribution [66]. The <lb/>analysis of other types of pdfs is left to Appendix A: <lb/>-In Appendix A.1 we present general results for bounded support pdfs. The case of a <lb/>uniform distribution on a finite interval [x m , x M ], which corresponds to an interesting <lb/>degenerate case (f is maximal at every point within the interval), has been presented <lb/>elsewhere [45]. The particular case of general a triangular pdf is explicitly worked out for <lb/>illustration. <lb/>-In Appendix A.2 we extend the analysis to fat-tail distributions, which correspond to <lb/>an important limiting case of pdfs with infinite variance (for such distributions, the nor-<lb/>malization constant σ in (1) and in equations (10) and (11) is no longer the standard <lb/>deviation, but an arbitrary positive constant setting the units of H, J, P and C). <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<body>-Finally, in Appendix A.3 we extend the discussion to the case of multimodal pdfs (distri-<lb/>butions with an arbitrary number of maxima): we derive the demand phase diagram for <lb/>a generic smooth multimodal pdf and we discuss the case of a singular pdf using as an <lb/>illustrative example a pdf with two Dirac peaks. <lb/>3 Aggregate choices and coordination dilemma <lb/>In this section we discuss the demand function, that is the relationship between price p and <lb/>fraction of buyers (or adopters, in non market contexts) η, expressed by equation (13). As <lb/>we have already seen, this means studying the relationship between η and the bare surplus <lb/>δ = h − p, and how it depends on the externality parameter j. We show that, for a large range <lb/>of values of the parameters j and δ, the demand presents two equilibria which can be qualified <lb/>as Nash equilibria from a game-theoretic point of view. This result is valid for any pdf satisfying <lb/>the general hypothesis described in the preceding section. <lb/>3.1 The direct and inverse demand functions <lb/>The expected demand η d at a given value of δ is obtained as the implicit solution of (13) and <lb/>(14). As we will see, the application η → 1 − F (−s(η)) may be a multiply valued function <lb/>of η; it is thus preferable to express δ, or p = h − δ, as a function of η, and determine the <lb/>inverse demand function p d (η), that is, the price at which exactly N η units of the good would <lb/>be bought 3 . <lb/>Under the hypothesis H2 the cumulative distribution F is a continuous and strictly mono-<lb/>tonic function on ]x m , x M [ and has a unique inflexion point. Hence it is invertible. Denoting Γ <lb/>the inverse of 1 − F (−s), we have the following equivalence: <lb/>η = 1 − F (−s) ⇐⇒ s = Γ(η), <lb/>(20) <lb/>with s defined by (14). For unbounded supports, Γ(η) increases monotonically from −∞ to +∞ <lb/>when η goes from 0 to 1 (see figure 1 for an example, and Appendix A for other cases). In the <lb/>case of a compact support [x m , x M ], Γ(η) takes the finite values, Γ(0) = −x M , and Γ(1) = −x m <lb/>for η respectively 0 and 1. Note that neither we assume f to be symmetric nor to have its <lb/>maximum at x = 0. <lb/>Replacing s in the r.h.s. of (20) by its expression (14) yields <lb/>δ = D(j; η), <lb/>(21) <lb/>with <lb/>D(j; η) ≡ Γ(η) − jη. <lb/>(22) <lb/>Interestingly, D(j; η) depends on the parameter j but not on h. Actually, in Section 3.2 and in <lb/>Appendix A.3, we will have to consider D(j; η) as a function of the two variables, j and η. In <lb/>the present subsection however, we consider D(j; η) as a function of the single variable η, with <lb/>j as a (fixed) parameter -hence according to our convention on notations introduced in Section <lb/>2.1, we keep in mind the dependency of D on j by writing D(j; η), and derivatives of D(j; η) <lb/>with respect to η are denoted D (j; η). <lb/>Plots of D(j; η) against η for different values of j are presented on figure 2 for the logistic <lb/>distribution. Solutions to (21) correspond to the intersections of these functions with horizontal <lb/>lines at y = δ. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">3 In non market models, where generally p = 0, results in this section give the aggregate choice N η d (j, h) as <lb/>a function of j and h. This is the relationship between the fraction of adopters, the average willingness to adopt <lb/>of the population and the strength of the social interactions. <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<body>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>-5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>Γ(η) <lb/>Γ&apos;(η) <lb/>Γ&apos;&apos;(η) <lb/>η <lb/>Figure 1: Γ(η) and derivatives as a function of η for the logistic pdf of unitary variance. Remark: <lb/>all these functions diverge at η = 0 and at η = 1. <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>(η B ,δ B ) <lb/>(η U ,δ U ) <lb/>η <lb/>j=1 <lb/>j=j B <lb/>j=5 <lb/>D(η) <lb/>(η L ,δ L ) <lb/>Figure 2: D(j; η) as a function of η in the case of a logistic distribution of the IWP, for three <lb/>values of j: j = 1 &lt; j B , j = j B = 2.20532 and j = 5 &gt; j B . <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<body>The stable equilibrium values of the demand satisfy <lb/>D (j; η) ≥ 0. <lb/>(23) <lb/>Thus, the intersections of y = δ with D when D &lt; 0 correspond to unstable equilibria and will <lb/>be ignored, as explained below. <lb/>Given an externality parameter j and a given value of δ, the solution η = η d (j; δ) of equation <lb/>(21) satisfying (23) gives the expected demand N η d (j; δ) at a price p = h − δ. <lb/>From the definition of δ and (22), the inverse demand function is thus <lb/>p d (η) = h − D(j; η). <lb/>(24) <lb/>This function depends on both parameters h and j, and when necessary we will write p d (η) = <lb/>p d (h, j; η). <lb/>As we will see, the demand η d (j; δ) can be a multivalued function of δ for some range of <lb/>parameters. On the contrary, since the function Γ(η) is a uniquely defined function of η, so is <lb/>D(j; η). This is the reason why, instead of considering (13), we prefer to obtain the properties <lb/>of the demand η d (j; δ) from the analysis of equations (21) and (22). <lb/>Under assumption H2, Γ(η) is at least piecewise three times continuously derivable on ]0, 1[; <lb/>its derivative Γ is continuous and strictly positive. In particular, at any point η in ]0, 1[, we <lb/>have: <lb/>D (j; η) = Γ (η) − j. <lb/>(25) <lb/>In the case of a compact support, the above equation also holds for the right and left derivatives <lb/>at, respectively, η = 0 and η = 1. <lb/>In terms of the pdf f , <lb/>Γ (η) = <lb/>1 <lb/>f (−s) <lb/>, with s = Γ(η). <lb/>(26) <lb/>Under H1, Γ has a unique absolute minimum (qualitatively there is a unique point where the <lb/>curvature of Γ changes from convex to concave; if Γ is smooth, it has a unique inflexion point). <lb/>Thus <lb/>min <lb/>η <lb/>Γ (η) = <lb/>1 <lb/>f B <lb/>&gt; 0. <lb/>(27) <lb/>This minimum is reached at some value η = η B : <lb/>η B ≡ arg min <lb/>η <lb/>Γ (η). <lb/>(28) <lb/>If f is smooth enough at its maximum, then Γ (η B ) = 0: η B is the inflexion point of Γ. For <lb/>symmetric pdfs, η B = 1/2, but we do not restrict to this case. <lb/>As a consequence of the properties of Γ(η), we see from equation (25) that D (j; η) is strictly <lb/>positive for j &lt; j B , with <lb/>j B ≡ Γ (η B ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>f B <lb/>. <lb/>(29) <lb/>The value j B separates two regions where the model presents qualitatively different behav-<lb/>iors. When j &lt; j B , the function D(j; η) is strictly increasing from −∞ to +∞ as η goes from <lb/>0 to 1. As a result it is invertible: for any δ in ] − ∞, +∞[, equation (21) has a unique solution <lb/>η d (δ). <lb/>If j &gt; j B , there is a range of values of δ for which (21) has several solutions. <lb/>The existence of multiple solutions in the demand is thus a generic property of discrete choice <lb/>models with heterogeneous agents and social interactions (externalities). This is true whatever <lb/>the number of maxima of f , as shown in Section A.3 of Appendix A. Actually, the domain <lb/>where there is a unique solution, that is 0 ≤ j ≤ j B = 1/f B , is very narrow if f B is large: a <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<body>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>-8 <lb/>-6 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>δ B <lb/>δ U δ L <lb/>η L <lb/>η B <lb/>η U <lb/>δ <lb/>η <lb/>d <lb/>(j;δ) <lb/>j=1 <lb/>j=j B <lb/>j=5 <lb/>multiple <lb/>equilibria <lb/>Figure 3: Demand η d (j; δ) as function of δ ≡ h − p in the case of a logistic distribution of the <lb/>IWP, for three values of j: j = 1 &lt; j B , j = j B = 2.20532 and j = 5 &gt; j B . Notice that the <lb/>origin of the horizontal axis (δ = 0) corresponds to h = p. Remark that prices increase from <lb/>right to left. Unstable solutions: the negative slope curve joining (δ L (j), η L (j)) to (δ U (j), η U (j)) <lb/>for j = 5 is not shown. <lb/>leptokurtic distribution will have in general a narrower domain of unicity of the demand than <lb/>a platykurtic distribution of same variance. <lb/>In our case of unimodal pdfs, equation (21) may have three solutions for j &gt; j B (see <lb/>figure 2). The intermediate solution, laying on a branch with D (j; η) &lt; 0 -where η increases <lb/>as δ = h − p decreases-is sometimes called a critical mass point in the literature [77]: it <lb/>corresponds to a demand that would increase for increasing prices. Hence, in a tatonnement <lb/>dynamics, this corresponds to an unstable solution separating the basins of attraction of the <lb/>two stable equilibria. The marginal case, j = j B , is a bifurcation point (hence the subscript B) <lb/>where multiple solutions to (21) appear on increasing j. The stable equilibria of the demand <lb/>that satisfy (23) are represented against δ on figure 3. <lb/>3.2 Demand phase diagram <lb/>3.2.1 The demand multiple-solution region <lb/>Let us consider more in details the behavior of the application δ → η d (δ) in the case of a <lb/>smooth unimodal pdf on ] − ∞, +∞[. Considerations specific to compact support pdfs are left <lb/>to Section A.1 of Appendix A. <lb/>The functions Γ(η) corresponding to pdfs satisfying H1 to H5 are at least three times con-<lb/>tinuously derivable on ]0, 1[, and diverge towards −∞ and +∞ as η goes to 0 and 1 respectively. <lb/>We have already seen that for j &lt; j B there is a unique solution, and η d goes from 0 to 1 as <lb/>δ = h − p goes smoothly from −∞ to +∞. <lb/>For j &gt; j B , (21) has 3 solutions whenever δ U &lt; δ &lt; δ L (see figure 2), where δ L and δ U are <lb/>the values of δ that satisfy the equality (marginal stability condition) in equation (23). That <lb/>is, the boundaries of the region with multiple solutions are the values for which D(j; η) has a <lb/>horizontal slope (see figure 2): <lb/>D (j; η) = 0 <lb/>(30) <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<body>which is equivalent to <lb/>dp d (η) <lb/>dη <lb/>= 0. <lb/>(31) <lb/>Considering the definition (22) of D, this means that on these boundaries D(j, η(j)), as a <lb/>function of j, is the Legendre transform of Γ(η). Under our hypothesis H1, Γ has a unique <lb/>minimum, and necessarily tends towards +∞ as η goes to either 0 or 1; Γ is strictly convex on <lb/>]η B , 1[, and strictly concave on ]0, η B [, hence the Legendre transform is well defined and unique <lb/>on each one of these intervals: equation (30) for j &gt; j B has indeed two solutions η L (j) and <lb/>η U (j), given by <lb/>j = Γ (η Λ ), Λ = U, L. <lb/>(32) <lb/>with <lb/>η L (j) &lt; η B &lt; η U (j). <lb/>(33) <lb/>From the knowledge of η U (j) and η L (j), using (21) one gets the marginal stability curves <lb/>δ U (j) and δ L (j), that is, the extreme values of δ bounding the region where multiple solutions <lb/>exist: <lb/>δ Λ (j) = D(j; η Λ (j)) = Γ(η Λ (j)) − jη Λ (j), Λ = U, L. <lb/>(34) <lb/>As already stated, for δ U (j) &lt; δ &lt; δ L (j), equation (21) has three solutions. The curve <lb/>η d (j; δ) has two stable branches (see figure 3): an upper one η d <lb/>U (j; δ) with η d <lb/>U (j; δ) &gt; η U (j) &gt; η B , <lb/>and a lower one η d <lb/>L (j; δ) with η d <lb/>L (j; δ) &lt; η L (j) &lt; η B ; they are joined by a branch of unstable <lb/>solutions -the above mentioned set of unstable equilibria (see figure 3)-. The upper branch <lb/>exists for δ ≥ δ U (j), the lower one for δ ≤ δ L (j). At the end points dη d <lb/>dδ | L,U = ∞. In other <lb/>words, solutions with large fractions of buyers, i.e. high-η solutions, only exist for δ ≥ δ U (j) <lb/>whereas low-η solutions exist only if δ ≤ δ L (j). Since δ U (j) ≤ δ L (j), the system has multiple <lb/>solutions for the demand η d whenever δ U (j) ≤ δ ≤ δ L (j). <lb/>For j = j B , these marginal stability curves merge at a single (degenerate) point δ L (j B ) = <lb/>δ U (j B ) = δ B with <lb/>δ B ≡ −Γ (η B ) η B + Γ(η B ) <lb/>(35) <lb/>This defines the bifurcation point B in the (j, δ) plane, <lb/>B ≡ {j B , δ B }. <lb/>(36) <lb/>One should note that η U,L (j) and δ U,L (j), which depend on j (and on the function Γ(.)), are <lb/>independent of h and p. <lb/>3.2.2 Generic properties <lb/>In fact, the preceding analysis can be made more general because the main results may be <lb/>obtained only based on the continuity and the convexity properties of Γ, without assuming any <lb/>smoothness properties of the derivatives of f . Let us consider this alternative. <lb/>First, whatever the smoothness properties of f , the demand η d must be a decreasing function <lb/>of the price: the economically acceptable values of the equilibrium demand, η d ∈ [0, 1], have <lb/>to increase when δ increases (p decreases). Thus, among the solutions of (21), the equilibria <lb/>lie on the branches where D (defined by equation (22)), is an increasing function of η (for <lb/>differentiable pdfs, this condition is given by equation (23) ). <lb/>Next, let us analyze D(j; η) as a function of η (see figure 2). By continuity of the function <lb/>Γ(η), D(j; η) is a continuous function of η ∈ [0, 1]. As η → 0, D → −∞, and as η → 1, <lb/>D → +∞. Since Γ is concave on ]0, η B ], on increasing η from 0 within [0, η B ], D(j, η) has <lb/>a maximum, δ L (j), on this interval. δ L (j) is by definition the Legendre transform of Γ(η) <lb/>restricted to ]0, η B ]. For η ≥ η B , Γ is convex, and thus D(j, η) has a minimum δ U (j) on [η B , 1], <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<body>0 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-2 <lb/>0 <lb/>δ U (j) <lb/>δ L (j) <lb/>δ=h-p <lb/>j <lb/>B <lb/>δ B <lb/>j B <lb/>Figure 4: Demand phase diagram on the plane (j = J/σ, δ = (H − P )/σ), for a smooth <lb/>IWP distribution (here the logistic). In the shaded region the demand presents multiple Nash <lb/>equilibria. Outside this region, the demand is a single valued function of j and δ. <lb/>which is the Legendre transform of Γ(η) restricted to [η B , 1[. Beyond this minimum, D(j; η) <lb/>increases with η. <lb/>Now, for j &lt; j B , the maximum on [0, η B ] and the minimum on [η B , 1] of D(j; η) are both <lb/>reached at η B , hence D(j; η) increases monotonically as a function of η ∈ [0, 1]. Therefore, <lb/>the solutions η d to equation (21) are unique monotonically increasing functions of δ for each j. <lb/>As a result, the inverse demand (24) is a uniquely defined continuously decreasing function of <lb/>η ∈ [0, 1]. <lb/>For j &gt; j B , the maximum δ L (j) is reached at η = η L (j) ∈]0, η B [. Beyond this maximum, <lb/>D(j; η) decreases as η increases. The minimum δ U (j) is reached at η = η U (j) ∈]η B , 1[: there <lb/>is an intermediate interval ]η L (j), η U (j)[ containing η B where D(j; η) decreases with η, from <lb/>δ L to δ U . No value of η within this interval can be a stable economic equilibrium. Hence, <lb/>for δ ranging between these extrema of D(j; η) the demand η d (j; δ) as a function of δ has two <lb/>branches, a lower one for δ ≤ δ L , with η d <lb/>L (j; δ) ≤ η L (j) &lt; η B and and an upper one for δ ≥ δ U , <lb/>with η d <lb/>U (j; δ) ≥ η U (j) &gt; η B . <lb/>In the case of a continuously differentiable function, the preceding results are recovered, <lb/>since the Legendre transforms -the above mentioned minimum and maximum of D(j; η) for <lb/>j &gt; j B -are reached at the values of η solutions of (30). All this discussion based on convexity <lb/>arguments can be extended to multimodal pdfs, that is to cases where the distributions of the <lb/>IWPs have more than one maximum. This is done in Appendix A.3. <lb/>3.2.3 The phase diagram <lb/>The results of the preceding section may be summarized on a customers phase diagram in the <lb/>plane (j, δ), where we represent the boundary of the multiple solutions region, as in figure <lb/>4. These boundaries are the functions δ Λ (j), (Λ = L, U ) defined by equations (34), which <lb/>are the two branches of the Legendre transform of Γ(η), one for η &lt; η B and the other for <lb/>η &gt; η B . Note that in term of prices, the extreme values δ L (j) and δ U (j) correspond to prices <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<body>0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>−1 <lb/>−0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>B <lb/>σ / J <lb/>(H−P) / J <lb/>Figure 5: Demand phase diagram in the plane (σ = σ/J,δ = (H − P )/J), for a smooth IWP <lb/>distribution (here the logistic). Inside the dashed region the demand presents multiple Nash <lb/>equilibria. Outside this region, the demand is a single valued function ofσ andδ. <lb/>p L (j, h) &lt; p U (j, h) given by <lb/>p Λ (j, h) = h − δ Λ (j), Λ = U, L. <lb/>(37) <lb/>By construction of the Legendre transforms, the branch δ = δ U (j) is concave, and the branch <lb/>δ = δ L (j) is convex. In addition, under the smoothness hypothesis, along each branch of the <lb/>multiple solutions region in the phase diagram: <lb/>dδ Λ (j) <lb/>dj <lb/>= <lb/>dD(j, η Λ (j)) <lb/>dj <lb/>= −η Λ (j), ; Λ ∈ {L, U }. <lb/>(38) <lb/>This property may be easily checked by deriving (34) with respect to j and making use of <lb/>(32). This means that the tangents to the boundaries have a slope given by the value of η <lb/>that is marginally stable on the corresponding boundary (i.e. by the η value of the solution <lb/>which appears/disappears as one crosses the boundary). Consequently, in the phase diagram, <lb/>the width along the δ-axis of the multiple solutions region increases with j as a result of the <lb/>convexity properties of the functions δ Λ (j), (Λ = L, U ). This may also be seen from (33), since <lb/>the slope of the L boundary (the one corresponding to η L ) is larger than that of the U boundary <lb/>(defined through η U ). At the bifurcation point B, these two boundaries merge, and, according <lb/>to (38), have a common slope −η B . <lb/>Referring back to figure 2, upon increasing δ from −∞, we have the following picture: if <lb/>j &lt; j B , the fraction η increases smoothly from 0 and reaches its upper value 1 for δ → ∞. <lb/>That is, to each value of the bare surplus δ, -or each value of the average willingness to adopt, <lb/>in non-market situations-corresponds a unique fraction of buyers/adopters. In the phase <lb/>diagram, figure 4, these solutions lie on the white region. On the other hand, if j &gt; j B , when δ <lb/>reaches the value δ U (j), a second, high-η solution appears besides the low-η one. These solutions <lb/>co-exist for δ U (j) ≤ δ ≤ δ L (j). The low-η solution disappears when δ increases beyond δ L (j), <lb/>leaving only the high-η solution. The parameter values for which there are multiple equilibria <lb/>is the grey region of the phase diagram, figure 4. Notice that in this region, there exists a third <lb/>solution that we neglected because it corresponds to the unstable situation where the demand <lb/>would increase with the price (or decrease with the bare surplus). <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<body>As mentioned in Section 2.2, it is also useful to consider the same results in terms of the <lb/>parametersσ = σ/J andδ = (H − P )/J (see (12). The phase diagram in the plane (σ,δ) <lb/>is shown on figure 5. For large heterogeneity (σ/J larger thanσ B ≡ 1/j B ), there is a single <lb/>smooth solution. For weak enough heterogeneity (σ B &lt; 1/j B ), there is a domain with multiple <lb/>solutions. In the limitσ → 0, one recovers the simple results for a homogeneous population, as <lb/>briefly discussed Section 2.3. <lb/>3.2.4 Vicinity of the bifurcation point <lb/>The vicinity of the bifurcation point B in the phase diagram is of particular interest. Under the <lb/>smoothness assumption H2, we can study analytically its properties. Let us consider j = j B + <lb/>with 0 &lt; &lt;&lt; 1. Expanding (32) about j B , remembering that Γ (η B ) = 0, one gets, to the <lb/>lowest order in , the singular behavior <lb/>η d <lb/>L,U = η B ± <lb/>2 <lb/>Γ (η B ) <lb/>1/2 , <lb/>(39a) <lb/>δ L,U (j) = Γ(η B ) − η B j B − η B ∓ <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>Γ (η B ) <lb/>3/2 . <lb/>(39b) <lb/>The above singular behaviors are typical examples of scaling properties which are universal: <lb/>the same scaling is obtained for any smooth distribution. From studies in statistical physics one <lb/>expects the exponents (e.g., here, 1/2 for the behavior of η) to depend mainly on the structure of <lb/>the network of interactions: the exponents would be different at the analogous critical point for <lb/>the model with agents situated on the vertices of a d-dimensional square lattice and interacting <lb/>only with their nearest neighbors. Typically the exponents depend on d up to some critical <lb/>dimension d c , above which they become identical to the &quot;mean-field&quot; exponents, which are <lb/>those obtained here with the global neighborhood. For the present model, other universal <lb/>scaling properties have been obtained, in relation with the hysteresis effects [80], and these <lb/>have been used in order to analyze empirical socio-economics data [65]. In a related work (with <lb/>a generalization of the model to more than two choices), Borghesi and Bouchaud [16] analyze <lb/>empirical data for which the social strength can be estimated, and is found to be close to the <lb/>critical value (the analogous of j B ). <lb/>In [44], where we consider the supply side, it will be seen that the bifurcation point B = <lb/>{j B , δ B } in the (j, δ) plane gives a singular point {j B , h B ≡ δ B } in the (j, h) plane which plays <lb/>an important role in the phase diagram associated to the optimal strategy for the monopolist. <lb/>3.2.5 Pareto optimality and coordination <lb/>Each one of the equilibria η d (j; δ) discussed in the preceding section is a Nash equilibrium for <lb/>the customers, at a posted price p. In this section we show that, whenever multiple solutions <lb/>exist, that is for j &gt; j B , the solution with the largest η is Pareto optimal. This is the solution <lb/>η d (j; δ) that satisfies η d (j; δ) ≥ η U (j). <lb/>Let us recall that if a customer i decides to buy, it is because his (normalized) surplus <lb/>s i = δ + jη + x i , <lb/>(40) <lb/>is positive. When s i &lt; 0 he doesn&apos;t buy and his surplus vanishes. Thus, his actual surplus is <lb/>w i = s i ω i (see Section 2). <lb/>Consider now the two equilibria η d (j; δ) in the region δ U (j) &lt; δ &lt; δ L (j) (see the curve <lb/>D(j; η) for j = 5 on figure 2). Let&apos;s denote by η d <lb/>L (j; δ) the low-η equilibrium (η d <lb/>L (j; δ) ≤ η L (j)), <lb/>and by η d <lb/>U (j; δ) the high-η equilibrium (η U (j) ≤ η d <lb/>U (j; δ)). In either equilibrium, the agents who <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<body>0 <lb/>0.25 0.5 0.75 <lb/>1 <lb/>Η <lb/>0 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>5 <lb/>7.5 <lb/>10 <lb/>j <lb/>2.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>5 <lb/>7.5 <lb/>p h <lb/>0 <lb/>0.25 0.5 0.75 <lb/>1 <lb/>Η <lb/>Figure 6: Inverse demand p − h (= −δ) as a function of η for different externality strength <lb/>values j, illustrated on the case of a logistic IWP distribution. <lb/>buy are those with x i &gt; −δ − jη d (j; δ). Since η d <lb/>L (j; δ) &lt; η d <lb/>U (j; δ), agents with x i &lt; −δ − jη d <lb/>U (j) <lb/>are not buyers in any of the equilibria whereas agents with x i &gt; −δ − jη d <lb/>L (j) are buyers in <lb/>both equilibria. Those with −δ − jη d <lb/>U (j) &lt; x i &lt; −δ − jη d <lb/>L (j) are buyers only in the high-<lb/>η equilibrium, and their utility is thus larger (strictly positive instead of zero) in that case. <lb/>Moreover, even those agents that would buy in both cases have a larger surplus if the realized <lb/>equilibrium is the high-η one. Hence, in the high-η equilibrium all these agents have a larger <lb/>surplus than in the low-η one. This situation with two possible Nash equilibria, where the <lb/>strictly dominant one may be risk dominated, is reminiscent of coordination problems in game <lb/>theory. For a detailed analysis of this analogy see Phan and Semeshenko [74]. The present <lb/>analysis shows that coordination problems may arise in systems with heterogeneous agents <lb/>whenever the externalities are strong enough. <lb/>Whether a Nash equilibrium -and which one in the case of multiple equilibria-is actually <lb/>realized depends on the rationality of the agents and the information they have access to. <lb/>In the context of bounded rationality and of repeated choices, a natural hypothesis is that <lb/>agents estimate what will be the fraction of adopters, and may base their estimate on previous <lb/>observations. In this paper we will not discuss these issues, that we are currently analyzing. <lb/>Some partial results (dynamics with myopic agents and with various reinforcement learning <lb/>paradigms) are discussed elsewhere [45, 79]. <lb/>3.3 Summary of the generic customers&apos; model <lb/>To summarize this section, if the social influence is small enough to satisfy the condition j &lt; j B , <lb/>at each value of the bare surplus δ = h − p, which measures the gap between the population <lb/>average willingness to pay and the price, there is a unique solution η d (j; δ) to equation (21). <lb/>This demand is a monotonic increasing function of δ. However, if the social influence is large <lb/>enough (j &gt; j B ), there is a range of values δ U (j) ≤ δ ≤ δ L (j) for which two different (stable) <lb/>solutions exist, a high demand one (η d (j; δ) ≥ η U (j) &gt; η B ) and a low demand one (η d (j; δ) ≤ <lb/>η L (j) &lt; η B ). In this region, the customers are faced with a coordination problem. If δ is <lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<body>modified dynamically within this range, the demand may jump abruptly between these two <lb/>solutions, a situation analogous to so called first order phase transitions in physics. Outside <lb/>the range [δ U (j), δ L (j)], there is a single solution, like in the small j case. <lb/>We showed that the threshold j B , which corresponds to the onset of a bifurcation in the <lb/>customers phase diagram, is determined by the maximum f B of the IWP pdf: j B = 1/f B . <lb/>Although most of the analysis has been done for smooth pdfs, we have shown that the generic <lb/>behavior stems only from convexity properties of the function Γ(η), that is from the fact that <lb/>the pdf f (x) is strictly increasing for x &lt; x B and strictly decreasing for x &gt; x B , where x B is <lb/>the mode of f . <lb/>Some specific properties which arise for distributions with compact support are discussed in <lb/>appendix A.1, and the case of distributions with infinite variance is studied in appendix A.2. <lb/>In appendix A.3 we extend the results of this section to multimodal distributions. <lb/>In market contexts (and in particular for the market analysis of [44]), it is useful to consider <lb/>the inverse demand p d instead of δ, as in standard approaches. In figure 6 we plot the values <lb/>of δ = p − h as a function of the demand η and the strength j of the social externality for the <lb/>case of a logistic distribution. <lb/>4 Conclusion and perspectives <lb/>The model of collective behavior considered in this paper, under the general hypothesis detailed <lb/>in Section 2, may be declined in both non-economic and economic contexts. In the first case, <lb/>one is interested in the fraction of adopters, which corresponds to studying the demand function <lb/>for an exogenous price in the second case. <lb/>Like in many other models in the recent literature, we consider optimizing agents making <lb/>binary choices, with willingnesses to adopt that depend additively on an idiosyncratic part <lb/>(IWP) and on the choices of other agents. The population is intrinsically heterogeneous: the <lb/>IWPs are drawn from some distribution of mean H and variance σ 2 . In contrast with other <lb/>most studied models, here the idiosyncratic willingness-to-adopt heterogeneity is frozen: it <lb/>does not result from (time varying) random shocks. In other words, each agent&apos;s choice is <lb/>deterministic with a well known (to him) IWP, and we concentrate on the aggregate behaviors. <lb/>We analyze the equilibrium properties (Nash equilibria) characterized by the emergence of a <lb/>collective behavior resulting from the combined effect of externalities and heterogeneity. <lb/>Our results, for global uniform interactions -a global social influence of uniform strength-<lb/>in the limit of an infinite population -through the application of the central limit theorem-<lb/>are summarized on phase diagrams. The axes of a phase diagram are the relevant model <lb/>parameters. In the case of the demand, the parameters are: δ, the bare surplus (that is, in <lb/>the economic context, the gap between the average IWP and the posted price), and j, the <lb/>social influence strength, both parameters being measured in units of the standard deviation <lb/>σ of the idiosyncratic term distribution (see 2.2). In this space of parameters, one draws <lb/>the boundaries between regions (&quot;phases&quot;) of qualitatively different collective behaviors. The <lb/>boundaries, where &quot;phase transitions&quot; occur, are lines of non-analyticity (e.g. the demand is <lb/>discontinuous on the boundary). In our problem, the main feature characterizing a given region <lb/>is the number of equilibria in this region. <lb/>From a constructivist point of view, our model encompasses the classical downward sloping <lb/>demand curve as a particular case. Indeed, one of the main results for the demand is that, for <lb/>very general IWP distributions, there is a region in the phase diagram with multiple equilibria. <lb/>More precisely, if the IWP distribution is mono-modal, there are two Nash equilibria for any j <lb/>larger than a distribution-dependent value j B . For smaller values of j, the (Marshallian) demand <lb/>curves are, ceteris paribus, downward sloping (i.e. monotonically decreasing with increasing <lb/>prices). For large externality strengths (j &gt; j B ), when the population average willingness to <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<body>pay is small enough, the demand becomes not-monotonic (as in Becker&apos;s example [9]). This is <lb/>a very general property of the model with additive externalities, and does not depend on the <lb/>particular statistical distribution of the idiosyncratic preferences. We also discuss (although <lb/>more briefly) the results for multimodal distributions -for which there exist several regions <lb/>with multiple equilibria, with possibly more than two equlibria for some of them-, and present <lb/>detailed analysis of many illustrative examples. <lb/>An important contribution of this paper is to exhibit the detailed properties of the bound-<lb/>aries of the regions (in the parameters space) where multiple solutions exist. These properties <lb/>are generic, in that they depend only on qualitative features of the IWP distribution. <lb/>Future work may extend the results presented in this paper in several directions. First, the <lb/>individual preferences may include a stochastic (noise) term like in [36, 33, 94, 19, 13, 14, 67, 4], <lb/>on top of the idiosyncratic one. Second, the present paper concentrates on the equilibrium <lb/>properties -that may be considered as the &quot;static&quot; analysis of long term equilibria in the <lb/>Marshallian tradition. Further studies should focus on the process that makes the system <lb/>reach one or the other of the possible equilibria. A first study, implying revision of beliefs <lb/>in an repeated choice setting, has already been published [79]: in the region with multiple <lb/>equilibria, interesting complex dynamics occur with a large family of different equilibria being <lb/>reached, depending on the particular learning rule used by the agents. Third, literature on <lb/>marketing and studies of social psychology shows that choices very often depend on imitation <lb/>effects or social influence. For example, the existence of externalities in the Communication <lb/>and Information Technologies (CIT) sector is well established, and may result in a multiplicity <lb/>of equilibria [76]. This may arise in other sectors also. Yet, empirical and econometric studies <lb/>allowing identification of the corresponding preferences distributions and the strength of the <lb/>social influence are lacking [15]. Fourth, the influence of social networks topologies deserves <lb/>further attention. Ioannides [50] reported results for the &quot;Thurnstone model, i.e. homogeneous <lb/>IWP and stochastic (logistic) choices, mainly for tree-like and one-dimensional networks with <lb/>nearest-neighbor interactions. It would be interesting to explore how the phase diagrams for <lb/>the model considered here -heterogeneous IWPs and deterministic choices-are affected by <lb/>short range interactions. Analytical and simulation studies on the RFIM [80, 73] show that <lb/>the heterogeneity introduces hysteretic effects in the dynamics, with interesting path-dependant <lb/>properties (return-point memory effect [80]). A statistical method to calculate the return points <lb/>exactly, starting from an arbitrary initial state, has been recently proposed [82] for the simple <lb/>case of a one dimensional periodic network with nearest-neighbor interactions (called cyclic <lb/>topology in [50]). The impact of such properties on both individual and collective economic <lb/>behavior remains to be investigated. <lb/>In a companion paper [44], we will discuss within the market context the profit optimization <lb/>by a monopolist fixing the price. Other extensions of the results of this second part involve the <lb/>study of how, with repeated choices, the long term equilibria depend on the entangled dynamics <lb/>where customers and monopolist learn from each other. Finally, at least two directions are <lb/>worth to be explored: the case of an oligopolistic competition and the consequences of Coase <lb/>conjecture in the case of choices with externalities involving a durable good -an issue already <lb/>addressed in the literature [61], but not yet in the regime where multiple equilibria exist. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>This work is part of the project &quot;ELICCIR&quot; supported by the joint program &quot;Complex Systems <lb/>in Human and Social Sciences&quot; of the French Ministry of Research and of the CNRS. M.B. G., <lb/>J.-P. N. and D. P. are CNRS members. This work has been partly done while M.B. G. and V. <lb/>S. were with the laboratory LEIBNIZ, CNRS-IMAG, Grenoble. <lb/></div>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] S. P. Anderson, A. de Palma, and J.-F. Thisse. Discrete Choice Theory of Product Differ-<lb/>entiation. MIT Press, Cambridge MA, (1992). <lb/>[2] W. B. Arthur. El farol. Amer. Econ. Review, 84:406-, (1994). <lb/>[3] W. B. Arthur. Complexity and the economy. Science, 284:107-109, (1999). <lb/>[4] W.B. Arthur, S.N. Durlauf, and D.A. Lane Eds. The Economy as an Evolving Complex <lb/>System II. Santa Fe Institute Studies in the Sciences of Complexity, Volume XXVII, <lb/>Addison-Wesley Pub.Co., Reading Ma., (1997). <lb/>[5] R. Artle and C. Averous. The telephone system as a public good: Static and dynamic <lb/>aspects. The Bell Journal of Economics and Management Science, 4 (1):89-100, (1973). <lb/>[6] R. Baldwin and P. Krugman. Persistent trade effects of large exchange rate shocks. Quar-<lb/>terly Journal of Economics, 419:635-654, (1989). <lb/>[7] P. Ball. The physical modelling of human social systems. Complexus, 1:190-206, (2003). <lb/>[8] G. S. Becker. A theory of social interactions. The Journal of Political Economy, 82 <lb/>(6):1063-1093, (1974). <lb/>[9] G. S. Becker. A note on restaurant pricing and other examples of social influences on price. <lb/>The Journal of Political Economy, 99:1109-1116, (1991). <lb/>[10] G. S. Becker and K.M Murphy. Social Economics. Market Behavior in a Social Environ-<lb/>ment. Cambrige Ma. The Belknap Press &amp; Harvard University Press, (2000). <lb/>[11] R. Benabou. Equity and efficiency in human capital investment: The local connection. <lb/>Review of Economic Studies, 63:237-264, (1996). <lb/>[12] B.D. Bernheim. A theory of conformity. Journal of Political Economy, 102:841-77, (1994). <lb/>[13] L. E. Blume. The statistical mechanics of strategic interaction. Games and Economic <lb/>Behavior, 5:387-424, (1993). <lb/>[14] L. E. Blume. The statistical mechanics of best-response strategy revisions. Games and <lb/>Economic Behavior, 11:111-145, (1995). <lb/>[15] L. E. Blume and S. N. Durlauf. Identifying social interactions: a review. Working paper, <lb/>(2005). <lb/>[16] C. Borghesi and J.-P. Bouchaud. Of songs and men: a model for multiple choice with <lb/>herding. Working paper http://fr.arxiv.org/abs/physics/0606224, 2006. <lb/>[17] J.-P. Bouchaud and M. Potters. Theory of Financial Risk and Derivative Pricing. Cam-<lb/>bridge University Press, 2nd Edition, 2003. <lb/>[18] J-Ph. Bouchaud. Power-laws in economics and finance: some ideas from physics. Quanti-<lb/>tative finance, 1:105, (2000). <lb/>[19] W. A. Brock. Pathways to randomness in the economy: Emergent non-linerarity and chaos <lb/>in economic and finance. Estudios Economicos, 8:1:3-55, (1993). <lb/>[20] W. A. Brock and S. N. Durlauf. Discrete choice with social interactions. Review of Eco-<lb/>nomic Studies, 68:235-260, (2001). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[21] W. A. Brock and S. N. Durlauf. Interactions-based models. In Heckman J. and Leamer <lb/>E., editors, Handbook of Economics, volume 5, Amsterdam, (2001). North-Holland. <lb/>[22] J. I. Bulow, J. D. Geanalopolos, and P. D. Klemperer. Multimarket oligopoly: strategic <lb/>substitutes and complements. Journal of Political Economy, 93/3:488-511, (1985). <lb/>[23] R. W. Cooper. Coordination Games, Complementarities and Macroeconomics. Cambridge <lb/>University Press, (1999). <lb/>[24] J. Crane. The epidemic theory of ghettos and neighborhood effects of dropping out and <lb/>teenage childbearing. American Journal of Sociology, 96:1226-1259, (1991). <lb/>[25] N. Curien and M. Gensollen. Les théories de la demande de raccordement téléphonique. <lb/>Revue Economique, 2 mars:203-255, 1987. <lb/>[26] G. Deffuant, D. Neau, F. Amblard, and G. Weisbuch. Mixing beliefs among interacting <lb/>agents. Advances in Complex Systems, 3:87-98, (2001). <lb/>[27] S. N. Durlauf. Multiple equilibria and persistence in aggregate fluctuations. American <lb/>Economic Review, 81:70-74, (1993). <lb/>[28] S. N. Durlauf. Nonergodic economic growth. Review of Economic Studies, 60:203:349-366, <lb/>(1993). <lb/>[29] S. N. Durlauf. Path dependance in aggegate output. Industrial and Corporate Change, <lb/>1:149-172, (1994). <lb/>[30] S. N. Durlauf. A theory of persistent income inequality. Journal of Economic Growth, <lb/>1:349-366, (1996). <lb/>[31] S. N. Durlauf. Statistical mechanics approaches to socioeconomic behavior. In B. Arthur, <lb/>S. N. Durlauf, and D. Lane, editors, The Economy as an Evolving Complex System II. <lb/>Santa Fe Institute Studies in the Sciences of Complexity, Volume XVII, Addison-Wesley <lb/>Pub. Co, (1997). <lb/>[32] S. N. Durlauf. How can statistical mechanics contribute to social science? Proceedings of <lb/>the National Academy of Sciences, 96:10582-10584, (1999). <lb/>[33] S. N. Durlauf. A framework for the study of individual behaviour and social interactions. <lb/>Working paper, , (2001). <lb/>[34] S. N. Durlauf. Groups, social influences, and inequality: A membership theory perspec-<lb/>tive on poverty traps. In S. Bowles, S. N. Durlauf, and K. Hoff, editors, Poverty Traps. <lb/>Princeton: Princeton University Press, (2006). <lb/>[35] G. Ehrhardt, M. Marsili, and F. Vega-Redondo. Emergence and resilience of so-<lb/>cial networks: a general theoretical framework. <lb/>Working paper, ArXiv e-prints, <lb/>http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0504124, (2005). <lb/>[36] H. Föllmer. Random economies with many interacting agents. Journal of Mathematical <lb/>Economics, 1:1:51-62, (1974). <lb/>[37] S. Galam. A new multicritical point in anisotropic magnets. III. Ferromagnets in both a <lb/>random and a uniform longitudinal field. Journal of Physics C, 15:529-545, (1982). <lb/>[38] S. Galam and A. Aharony. New multicritical points in anisotropic magnets, i. ferromagnets <lb/>in a random longitudinal field. Journal of Physics C, 13:1065-1081, (1980). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[39] S. Galam, Y. Gefen, and Y. Shapir. Sociophysics: A mean behavior model for the process <lb/>of strike. Mathematical Journal of Sociology, 9:1-13, (1982). <lb/>[40] E. Glaeser and J. A. Scheinkman. Non-market interactions. In M. Dewatripont, L.P. <lb/>Hansen, and S. Turnovsky, editors, Advances in Economics and Econometrics: Theory <lb/>and Applications, Eight World Congress. Cambridge University Press, (2002). <lb/>[41] E. L. Glaeser, H. D. Kallai, J. A. Scheinkman, and A. Shleifer. Growth in cities. Journal <lb/>of Political Economy, 100:6:1126-1152, (1992). <lb/>[42] E. L. Glaeser, B. Sacerdote, and J. A. Scheinkman. Crime and social interactions. Quarterly <lb/>Journal of Economics, CXI:507-548, (1996). <lb/>[43] M. B. Gordon. An introduction to statistical mechanics. In Bourgine P. and Nadal J-P., <lb/>editors, Cognitive Economics, pages 131-155. Springer, (2004). <lb/>[44] M. B. Gordon, J.-P. Nadal, D. Phan, and V. Semeshenko. The perplex monopolist: Optimal <lb/>pricing with customers under social influence. In preparation, (2007). <lb/>[45] M. B. Gordon, J.-P. Nadal, D. Phan, and J. Vannimeuns. Seller&apos;s dilemma due to social <lb/>interactions between customers. Physica A, 356, Issues 2-4:628-640, (2005). <lb/>[46] M. Granovetter. Threshold models of collective behavior. American Journal of Sociology, <lb/>83(6):1360-1380, (1978). <lb/>[47] M. Granovetter and R. Soong. Threshold models of interpersonal effects in consumer <lb/>demand. Journal of Economic Behavior &amp; Organization, 7 (1):83-99, (1986). <lb/>[48] W. Hildebrand. On the &quot;laws of demand&quot;. Econometrica, 51:997-1019, (1983). <lb/>[49] J. Holyst, K. Kacperski, and F. Schweitzer. Social impact models of opinion dynamics. In <lb/>D. Stauffer, editor, Annual Reviews of Computational Physics IX, pages 253-273. World <lb/>Scientific, Singapore, (2001). <lb/>[50] Y.M. Ioannides. Topologies of social interactions. Economic Theory, 28:559-584, (2006). <lb/>[51] Ernst Ising. Beitrag zur Theorie des Ferromagnetismus. Dissertation, (1924). <lb/>[52] M. L. Katz and C. Shapiro. Systems competition and network effects. The Journal of <lb/>Economic Perspectives, 8(2):93-115, (1994). <lb/>[53] R. Kindermann and J. L. Snell. Random Markov Fields and their Applications. American <lb/>Mathematical Society, Providence, Rhode Island, (1980). <lb/>[54] A. P. Kirman. Whom or what does the representative individual represent? Journal of <lb/>Economic Perspective, 6(2):117-136, (1992). <lb/>[55] B. Krauth. Simulation-based estimation of peer effects. Journal of Econometrics, forth-<lb/>coming, (2006). <lb/>[56] B. Krauth. Social interactions in small groups. Canadian Journal of Economics, 39 (2) <lb/>May:414-433, (2006). <lb/>[57] H. Leibenstein. Bandwagon, snob, and veblen effects in the theory of consumers&apos; demand. <lb/>Quarterly Journal of Economics, 64:2:183-207, (1950). <lb/>[58] R. D. Luce. Individual Choice Behavior. Wiley, New-York, (1959). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[59] C.F. Manski. The structure of random utility models. Theory and Decision, 8:229-254, <lb/>(1977). <lb/>[60] C.F. Manski. Economic analysis of social interactions. Journal of Economic Perspectives, <lb/>14 (3) Summer:115-136, (2000). <lb/>[61] R. Manson. Network externalities and the coase conjecture. European Economic Review, <lb/>44(10):1981-1992, (2000). <lb/>[62] D.L. McFadden. Conditional logit analysis of qualitative choice analysis. In Zarembka, <lb/>editor, Frontiers of Econometrics, pages 105-142. New York: Academic Press, (1974). <lb/>[63] D.L. McFadden. Quantal choice analysis: A survey. Annals of Economic and Social <lb/>Measurement, 5 No. 4:363-390, (1976). <lb/>[64] R. D. McKelvey and T. R. Palfrey. Quantal response equilibria for normal games. Games <lb/>and Economic Behavior, 10:6-38, (1995). <lb/>[65] Q. Michard and J.-P. Bouchaud. Theory of collective opinion shifts: from smooth trends <lb/>to abrupt swings. The European Physical Journal B -Condensed Matter and Complex <lb/>Systems, 47:151-159, (2005). <lb/>[66] J.-P. Nadal, D. Phan, M. B. Gordon, and J. Vannimenus. Multiple equilibria in a monopoly <lb/>market with heterogeneous agents and externalities. Quantitative Finance, 5(6):557-568, <lb/>(2006). Presented at the 8th Annual Workshop on Economics with Heterogeneous Inter-<lb/>acting Agents (WEHIA 2003). <lb/>[67] J.-P. Nadal, G. Weisbuch, O. Chenevez, and A. Kirman. A formal approach to market <lb/>organisation: Choice functions, mean field approximation and maximum entropy principle. <lb/>In J. Lesourne and A. Orléan, editors, Advances in Self-Organization and Evolutionary <lb/>Economics, pages 149-159. Economica, London, (1998). <lb/>[68] L. Onsager. Crystal statistics, I. A two-dimensional model with an order disorder transition. <lb/>Physical Review, 65:117-149, (1944). <lb/>[69] A. Orléan. Le rôle des influences interpersonnelles dans la détermination des cours bour-<lb/>siers. Revue Economique, vol. 41, n.5:839-868, (1990). <lb/>[70] A. Orléan. Bayesian interactions and collective dynamics of opinion: Herd behaviour and <lb/>mimetic contagion. Journal of Economic Behavior and Organization, 28:257-274, (1995). <lb/>[71] E. Ostrom. Collective action and the behaviour of social norms. Journal of Economic <lb/>Perspectives, 14:137-158, (2000). <lb/>[72] D. Phan, M. B. Gordon, and J.-P. Nadal. Social interactions in economic theory: an insight <lb/>from statistical mechanics. In Bourgine P. and Nadal J-P., editors, Cognitive Economics. <lb/>Springer, (2004). <lb/>[73] D. Phan, S. Pajot, and J-P. Nadal. The monopolist&apos;s market with discrete choices and <lb/>network externality revisited: Small-worlds, phase transition and avalanches in an ace <lb/>framework. In Ninth annual meeting of the Society of Computational Economics, Univer-<lb/>sity of Washington, Seattle, USA, July 11-13, 2003, (2003). <lb/>[74] D. Phan and V. Semeshenko. Equilibria in models of binary choice with heterogeneous <lb/>agents and social influence. submitted to European Journal of Economic and Social Sys-<lb/>tems, , (2007). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[75] J. Rohlfs. Theory of interdependent demand for a communications service. Bell Journal <lb/>of Economics and Management Science, Vol. 5, No. 1, Spring:16-37, (1974). <lb/>[76] J. Rohlfs. Bandwagon effects in High-Technology Industries. Cambridge, Ma., MIT Press, <lb/>(2001). <lb/>[77] T. S. Schelling. Hockey helmets, concealed weapons, and daylight saving: A study of binary <lb/>choices with externalities. The Journal of Conflict Resolution, t. XVII, N. 3, (1973). <lb/>[78] T. S. Schelling. Micromotives and Macrobehavior. W.W. Norton and Co, N.LY., (1978). <lb/>[79] V. Semeshenko, M. B. Gordon, J.-P. Nadal, and D. Phan. Choice under social influence: <lb/>effects of learning behaviors on the collective dynamics. In Topol R. and Walliser B., <lb/>editors, Contributions to economic analysis. Cognitive Economics. New Trends, pages 177-<lb/>203. Elsevier, (2007). <lb/>[80] J. P. Sethna, K. Dahmen, S. Kartha, J. A. Krumhansl, B.W. Roberts, and J. D. Shore. <lb/>Hysteresis and hierarchies: Dynamics of disorder-driven first-order phase transformations. <lb/>Physical Review Letters, 70:3347-3350, (1993). <lb/>[81] C. Shapiro and H. Varian. Information Rules: A Strategic Guide to the Network Economy. <lb/>Harvard Business School Press, (1999). <lb/>[82] P. Shukla. Exact solution of return hysteresis loops in a one-dimensional random-field ising <lb/>model at zero temperature. Phys. Rev. E, 62 (4) October:4725-4729, (2000). <lb/>[83] A.R. Soetevent and P. Kooreman. A discrete choice model with social interactions; with an <lb/>application to high school teen behavior. Journal of Applied Econometrics, forthcoming, <lb/>(2006). <lb/>[84] S. Solomon, G. Weisbuch, L. de Arcangelis, N. Jan, and D. Stauffer. Social percolation <lb/>models. Physica A, 277:239-247, (2000). <lb/>[85] H.E. Stanley. Introduction to phase transitions and critical phenomena. Oxford University <lb/>Press, (1971). <lb/>[86] G. Topa T. Conley. Socio-economic distance and spatial patterns in unemployment. Journal <lb/>of Applied Econometrics, 17 (4):303-327, (2002). <lb/>[87] L. L. Thurstone. Psychological analysis. American Journal of Psychology, 38:368-398, <lb/>(1927). <lb/>[88] G. Topa. Social interactions, local spillovers and unemployment. Review of Economic <lb/>Studies, 68 (2):261-295, (2001). <lb/>[89] T. W. Valente. Network Models of the Diffusion of Innovations. Hampton Press, Cresskill, <lb/>NJ, (1995). <lb/>[90] B. Von Rabenau and K. Stahl. Dynamic aspects of public goods: a further analysis of the <lb/>telephone system. Bell Journal of Economics and Management Science, Vol. 5, n2:651-669, <lb/>1974. <lb/>[91] D. J. Watts. A simple model of global cascades on random networks. PNAS, Vol. 99 no. <lb/>9:5766-5771, (2002). <lb/>[92] W. Weidlich. Sociodynamics: A Systematic Approach to Mathematical Modelling in the <lb/>Social Sciences. Harwood Academic Publishers, (2000). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[93] W. Weidlich and G. Haag. Concepts and models of a quantitative sociology. Berlin, Hei-<lb/>delberg/New York, Springer-Verlag, (1983). <lb/>[94] G. Weisbuch, A. Kirman, and D. Herreiner. Market organisation and trading relationships. <lb/>Working paper 1996, published in: The Economic Journal, Volume 110 Issue 463:411-462, <lb/>(2000). <lb/>[95] G. Weisbuch and D. Stauffer. Adjustment and social choice. Physica A, 323:651-662, <lb/>(2003). <lb/>[96] J. Zabel Y.M. Ioannides. Neighborhood effects and housing demand. Journal of Applied <lb/>Econometrics, 18:563-584, (2003). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<body>Γ <lb/>Γ <lb/>η <lb/>Γ η <lb/>Γ η <lb/>η <lb/>Γ η <lb/>η <lb/>η <lb/>δ <lb/>δ <lb/>δ <lb/>δ <lb/>δ <lb/>η <lb/>η <lb/>η <lb/>δ <lb/>Figure 7: Triangular pdf of unitary variance and a maximum at x B = −1. Left: Γ(η) and its <lb/>first derivative. Right: D(j; η) for different values of j. The values of η L , δ L , η U and δ U are <lb/>represented for the particular value j = 5. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">A Appendix: Demand for other distributions <lb/>In this Appendix we extend our analysis to more general distributions. <lb/>We first (A.1) explicit the particularities introduced on the above generic results when the <lb/>pdf has a bounded support. In Section A.2 we relax hypothesis H5, and consider pdfs with <lb/>unbounded support called fat tail distributions in the literature. Finally, we extend our results <lb/>to multimodal distributions in Section A.3. <lb/>A.1 Pdfs with compact support <lb/>We consider here pdfs f (x) with compact supports: x ∈ [x m , x M ] presenting a unique maxi-<lb/>mum (which may be located at one boundary). Clearly, such pdfs have finite variances. The <lb/>discussion follows the same lines as that of the generic smooth distributions, except that in <lb/>addition one has to pay attention to the values of Γ and its derivatives at the boundaries η = 0, <lb/>η = 1. A simple uniform distribution, analyzed in [45], is a particular case where the maximum <lb/>of the pdf is degenerate. <lb/>In this section, derivatives like Γ (1) or Γ (0), stand for the left and the right derivative of <lb/>Γ at η = 1 and η = 0, respectively. Due to the fact that the pdf strictly vanishes beyond its <lb/>support, if the price is very high with respect to h (small δ) there may be no buyers at all, <lb/>and η = 0. On the contrary, if the price is very low (large δ) the market may or not saturate, <lb/>i.e. η = 1, depending on the behaviour of the pdf in the vicinity of x m . We represent the <lb/>lines delimiting the regions where these solutions exist on the phase diagram. It should be <lb/>stressed that these lines only indicate saturation and non-existence of a market. Their nature <lb/>is different from that of the boundaries δ L and δ U . In the following we consider a triangular <lb/>distribution with a maximum f B at x B to illustrate our general results. The figures in this <lb/>section correspond to x B = −1, i.e. a case where the maximum lies inside the support. The <lb/>case x B = x m has been considered in the study of the learning dynamics [79]. <lb/>In the case of compact supports [x m , x M ], Γ(η) increases from Γ(0) = −x M &lt; 0, to Γ(1) = <lb/>−x m &gt; 0. Like in the generic case of unbounded supports, Γ reaches a minimum at η B , and <lb/>there is a critical value j B = 1/f B beyond which multiple solutions appear. Notice that if <lb/>the maximum of the pdf lies at x m or at x M , η B lies at one of the boundaries of the [0, 1] <lb/>interval. As already shown in Section 3.1, if the pdf is symmetric -as is the case for the <lb/></div>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">uniform distribution-, η B = 1/2. <lb/>In our example of a triangular pdf with maximum at x B we have: <lb/>f (x) = <lb/>2(x−xm) <lb/>(xM −xm)(xB −xm) <lb/>if x m ≤ x ≤ x B , <lb/>2(xM −x) <lb/>(xM −xm)(xM −xB ) <lb/>if x B ≤ x ≤ x M , <lb/>(A-1) <lb/>with f (x) = 0 outside the support. At its maximum, f B = 2/(x M − x m ). The constraint of <lb/>zero mean and unit variance imposes a relationship between the support boundaries and the <lb/>value of x B : x m = (−x B − 3(8 − x 2 <lb/>B ))/2, x M = (−x B + 3(8 − x 2 <lb/>B ))/2. <lb/>If x B = x M the distribution increases monotonically from 0 at x m , reaching its maximum <lb/>at x M , and is defined only by the first equation in (A-1). Conversely, if x B = x m then f (x) <lb/>decreases inside its support, and is defined by the second equation in (A-1). In both cases, f (x) <lb/>presents a discontinuity at one boundary of its support. <lb/>The function Γ and its first derivative for the triangular distribution are respectively <lb/>Γ(η) = <lb/>−x M + (x M − x m )(x M − x B )η <lb/>if 0 ≤ η ≤ η B <lb/>−x m − (x M − x m )(x B − x m )(1 − η) if η B ≤ η ≤ 1 <lb/>(A-2) <lb/>and <lb/>Γ (η) = <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>√ <lb/>(xM −xm)(xM −xB ) <lb/>2 <lb/>√ <lb/>η <lb/>if 0 ≤ η ≤ η B <lb/>√ <lb/>(xM −xm)(xB−xm) <lb/>2 <lb/>√ <lb/>(1−η) <lb/>if η B ≤ η ≤ 1 <lb/>(A-3) <lb/>where η B = (x M − x B )/(x M − x m ) is the inflexion point of Γ. They are represented on figure 7 <lb/>(left) for the particular value x B = −1. Notice that Γ (η) is discontinuous at η B , because the <lb/>maximum of f (x) is a cusp. <lb/>The corresponding inverse demand function D(j; η) (equation (22 ) ) is represented on figure <lb/>7 (right). Due to the finite range of the compact support, there are two new particular values <lb/>of δ: δ 0 ≡ D(j; 0) = Γ(0) = −x M , independent of j, and δ 1 (j) ≡ D(j; 1) = Γ(1) − j = −x m − j: <lb/>for δ &lt; δ 0 , η = 0 (no-market) is a solution, while for δ &gt; δ 1 (j) there is a solution η = 1 (market <lb/>saturation). These extreme values of η may be reached upon finite values of δ (i.e. finite prices <lb/>and finite average IWP) only in the case of compact supports. <lb/>For j &lt; j B , D(j; η) is strictly increasing and invertible on ]0, 1[: for any δ in ]−x M , −x m −j[, <lb/>equation (21) has a unique solution η d (δ) = {0, 1}. One can easily check that j &lt; j B implies <lb/>j ≤ x M − x m , so that −x M &lt; −x m − j and consequently D(j; 0) &lt; D(j; 1). In the particular <lb/>case where f is the uniform distribution, one has precisely j B = x M − x m . For the triangular <lb/>pdf (A-1), (29) gives j B = (x M − x m )/2, the support&apos;s half-width. Thus, for δ 0 &lt; δ &lt; δ 1 (j) the <lb/>fraction of buyers/adopters is a monotonic increasing function of δ. For δ &lt; δ 0 , η = 0, and for <lb/>δ &gt; δ 1 (j) the market saturates (η = 1). <lb/>For j &gt; j B there are two stable solutions whenever δ U (j) ≤ δ ≤ δ L (j). Due to the existence <lb/>of the extreme solutions η = 0 and η = 1, the analysis is more cumbersome than for infinite <lb/>supports. If the maximum of the pdf lies inside the support, the solutions η L (j) and η U (j) <lb/>of equation (30) lie in ]0, 1[ and δ U (j) and δ L (j) both satisfy D = 0. On increasing δ from <lb/>−∞, there is no demand until δ = min{δ 0 , δ U (j)}. If δ 0 &lt; δ U (j), when δ increases beyond δ 0 <lb/>the demand becomes finite and remains unique provided that δ 0 &lt; δ &lt; δ U (j). For δ &gt; δ U (j) <lb/>we enter the region of multiple solutions. On the other hand, if δ 0 &gt; δ U (j), the system steps <lb/>directly from the no-demand solution into a region where a finite demand equilibrium with <lb/>η &gt; η B coexists with the no-demand one. Notice that the high-η solution may correspond <lb/>to either a fraction of buyers strictly smaller than 1 (if δ L (j) &lt; δ 1 (j)) or to saturation (if <lb/>δ L (j) &gt; δ 1 (j)). In the case of the triangular distribution it is straightforward to check that the <lb/>multiple solutions region sets in at j B = (x M − x m )/2, δ B = x B /2. <lb/></div>

			<page>31 <lb/>halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">δ <lb/>δ <lb/>η <lb/>η <lb/>δ <lb/>η <lb/>δ <lb/>δ <lb/>δ <lb/>Figure 8: Triangular pdf of unitary variance and a maximum at x B = −1: customers phase <lb/>diagram. <lb/>If the pdf has its maximum at one of the boundaries of its support, either η U or η L coincide <lb/>with η B . More precisely, if x B = x m then η U = η B = 1, if x B = x M , η L = η B = 0. <lb/>Summarizing, the customers phase diagram for pdfs with compact supports have two sup-<lb/>plementary lines with respect to that with unbounded supports. They indicate the boundary of <lb/>the viability region (no market exists below this line) and the saturation boundary (above which <lb/>all the customers are buyers). Figure 8 presents the customers&apos; phase diagram for our example <lb/>corresponding to the triangular pdf of unitary variance (A-1), with a maximum at x B = −1. <lb/>A.2 Pdfs with fat tails <lb/>Fat-tail distributions are characterized by the fact that the pdf f has a slow decrease at large <lb/>values of x, so that the variance is infinite -or even the mean is infinite. Equivalently this <lb/>occurs if Γ(η) diverges &apos;too fast&apos; to −∞ when η → 0. In the case of the logistic, Γ ∼ log η; for <lb/>the Gaussian, Γ ∼ − <lb/>√ <lb/>−2 log η; for a power law, Γ ∼ − 1 <lb/>η b . This suggest to consider the general <lb/>following smooth behavior: <lb/>as η → 0: Γ(η) ∼ −K(− log η) a 1 <lb/>η b , <lb/>(A-4) <lb/>with the constant K &gt; 0, a ≥ 0 and b ≥ 0 (ab = 0). The fat-tail case corresponds then to a = 0 <lb/>and b ≥ 1 in the above equation (A-4). <lb/>A particular example of a fat tail distribution is a pdf with a power law decrease, which for <lb/>large x behaves like: <lb/>f (x) ∼ x −(1+µ) <lb/>(A-5) <lb/>with µ ≥ 0. Then, for small η, Γ ∼ − 1 <lb/>η b with b = 1/µ, so that b ≥ 1 means µ ≤ 1. For µ &lt; 1, <lb/>not only the variance but also the mean value of the random variable x is infinite. <lb/>For fat-tails distributions one has to look at finite size effects: it is no more possible to <lb/>take directly the large N limit and make use of the central limit theorem: quantities like <lb/>(1/N ) i G(x i ) for any function G will be dominated by rare events, that is by the largest <lb/></div>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>-40 <lb/>-20 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>η <lb/>Γ <lb/>Γ&apos; <lb/>Γ&apos;&apos; <lb/>Figure 9: Γ function and derivatives corresponding to the function (A-6). <lb/>values encountered in the population of (large but finite) size N . There is, however, no difficulty <lb/>in doing this analysis: the results are obtained by doing as if the pdf had a finite support, the <lb/>upper bound x M being given as an increasing function of N (for an introduction to statistics <lb/>with fat tails, see e.g. [17]). <lb/>Since we considered compact supports in the preceding section, we concentrate here on the <lb/>marginal case µ = b = 1, which can be analyzed as a limiting case of distributions with infinite <lb/>support. <lb/>For µ = 1, f (x) does not have a finite variance. Then, the value of σ that defines the <lb/>normalized variables (10) may be any (finite) measure of the width of the distribution, as for <lb/>example, the value of x at which f (x) is equal to half its maximum. Let us discuss this marginal <lb/>case on a simple example (see figure 9): <lb/>Γ ≡ − <lb/>1 <lb/>η <lb/>+ <lb/>1 <lb/>1 − η <lb/>, <lb/>(A-6) <lb/>corresponding to the cumulative function: <lb/>F (z) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>− <lb/>1 <lb/>z <lb/>+ sgn(z) <lb/>1 <lb/>z 2 + <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>. <lb/>(A-7) <lb/>The corresponding pdf is, <lb/>f (x) = <lb/>1 <lb/>x 2 [1 − <lb/>2 <lb/>√ <lb/>4 + x 2 <lb/>], <lb/>(A-8) <lb/>as represented on figure 10. Since this is a symmetric distribution, η B = 1/2, and one finds <lb/>(see equations (28), (29) and (35) ) that the point B in the customers phase diagram is j B = <lb/>Γ (η B ) = 8, δ B = −4. Notice that, like for any monomodal distribution (satisfying thus <lb/>hypothesis H1), Γ(η) is convex for η &gt; η B and concave for η &lt; η B , with as before η B being the <lb/>inflexion point. The supply function has thus the generic behavior described in Section 3 even <lb/>for fat-tail distributions. <lb/></div>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">-20 <lb/>-10 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.14 f(x) <lb/>x <lb/>Figure 10: Pdf corresponding to equation (A-8). <lb/>A.3 Aggregate demand for multimodal pdfs <lb/>A.3.1 Smooth pdfs: generic properties <lb/>In this section we consider the behavior of the application δ → η d (δ) in the case of a smooth <lb/>multimodal pdf with support on ] − ∞, +∞[. The discussion Section 3.2, based on convexity <lb/>arguments, can be extended to describe the phase diagram for the aggregate demand in the <lb/>multimodal case. <lb/>The minimal hypotheses we consider are the following. <lb/>• HA0. The pdf f (x) is continuous with a finite number K ≥ 2 of x-values, −∞ &lt; x K <lb/>B &lt; <lb/>x K−1 <lb/>B <lb/>&lt; ... &lt; x 1 <lb/>B &lt; ∞, for which f has a (possibly local) bounded maximum, <lb/>f (x k <lb/>B ) &lt; ∞ k = 1, ..., K. <lb/>(A-9) <lb/>For simplicity we assume also that the pdf is not constant on any interval of finite length. <lb/>Actually, the discussion can be easily extended to less regular pdfs (in particular piecewise <lb/>continuous pdfs), and pdfs constant on some intervals, but to keep the discussion shorter <lb/>will leave that to the interested reader (in the case of a monomodal pdf, see the discussion <lb/>on compact supports, and for the bimodal case see also below, Section A.3.2, the singular <lb/>case of a distribution composed of two Diracs). <lb/>• HA1. When considering smoother functions, we will assume f to be twice continuously <lb/>differentiable, so that in particular it has a zero derivative at every maximum and every <lb/>minimum. <lb/>Let us denote by x k <lb/>C the location of the minimum between x k+1 <lb/>B <lb/>and x k <lb/>B . We assume f &gt; 0 <lb/>everywhere on its support except possibly at some minima, and f (x) goes to zero as x → ±∞. <lb/>By convention we set x 0 <lb/>C = +∞ and x K <lb/>C = −∞ (and we may write f (x 0 <lb/>C ) = f (x K <lb/>C ) = 0). <lb/>In the monomodal case, we have seen that the critical value of j for the appearance of several <lb/>solutions is j B = 1/f (x B ). Here we will see that the relevant critical values are <lb/>j k <lb/>B ≡ <lb/>1 <lb/>f (x k <lb/>B ) <lb/>k = 1, ..., K <lb/>(A-10) <lb/></div>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">and also <lb/>j k <lb/>C ≡ <lb/>1 <lb/>f (x k <lb/>C ) <lb/>k = 1, ..., K − 1 <lb/>(A-11) <lb/>(and it will be convenient to define as well j 0 <lb/>C = j K <lb/>C = ∞). <lb/>Consider now the inverse demand at a given value of j. The ensemble of equilibria δ d (η) for <lb/>η ∈ [0, 1] is the subset of the ensemble of solutions of (21) for which δ increases (p decreases) <lb/>as η increases. As for the monomodal case we study the function of η defined by (21) for <lb/>any given j, δ(η) = D(j; η). By continuity of the function Γ, δ(η) is a continuous function of <lb/>η ∈ [0, 1]. As η → 0, δ → −∞, and as η → 1, δ → +∞. Increasing η from 0, δ(η) increases. <lb/>Similarly, decreasing η from η = 1, δ(η) decreases. Since f (x) is continuous, Γ(η) is continuously <lb/>differentiable, with Γ (η) ≡ dΓ(η)/dη = 1/f (x) at x = −Γ(η). Hence Γ (η) has (local) minima <lb/>at values of η given by <lb/>Γ (η k <lb/>B ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>f (x k <lb/>B ) <lb/>k = 1, ..., K <lb/>(A-12) <lb/>and (local) maxima at values of η given by <lb/>Γ (η k <lb/>C ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>f (x k <lb/>C ) <lb/>k = 1, ..., K − 1 <lb/>(A-13) <lb/>For a smooth enough pdf, the η k <lb/>B and η k <lb/>C s are inflexion points for Γ. Note that for any k = <lb/>1, ..., K, η k−1 <lb/>C <lb/>&lt; η k <lb/>B &lt; η k <lb/>C . <lb/>The most important remark is that Γ(η) is strictly concave on every interval ]η k−1 <lb/>C , η k <lb/>B [, k = <lb/>1, ..., K, and strictly convex on every interval ]η k <lb/>B , η k <lb/>C [, k = 1, ..., K. Then as η varies on <lb/>[η k−1 <lb/>C , η k <lb/>B ], the function D(j, η) = Γ(η) − jη has, at some value η k <lb/>L (j), a maximum δ k <lb/>L (j) which <lb/>is by definition the Legendre transform of Γ(η) restricted to [η k−1 <lb/>C , η k <lb/>B ]. Similarly, on [η k <lb/>B , η k <lb/>C ], <lb/>D(j, η) has, at some value η k <lb/>U (j), a minimum δ k <lb/>U (j), the Legendre transform of Γ(η) restricted <lb/>to [η k <lb/>B , η k <lb/>C ]. <lb/>Depending on the value of j compared to the values j k <lb/>B , j k <lb/>C , these min and max may be <lb/>reached either at a boundary of an interval, or in the interior. More precisely: <lb/>j &lt; j k <lb/>B , η k <lb/>L = η k <lb/>U = η k <lb/>B <lb/>(A-14) <lb/>j k <lb/>B &lt; j &lt; j k <lb/>C , η k <lb/>B &lt; η k <lb/>U &lt; η k <lb/>C <lb/>(A-15) <lb/>j k <lb/>B &lt; j &lt; j k−1 <lb/>C , η k−1 <lb/>C <lb/>&lt; η k <lb/>L &lt; η k <lb/>B <lb/>(A-16) <lb/>j k <lb/>C &lt; j, η k+1 <lb/>L <lb/>= η k <lb/>U = η k <lb/>C <lb/>(A-17) <lb/>(and η k <lb/>U increases from η k <lb/>B to η k <lb/>C as j increases from j k <lb/>B to j k <lb/>C , whereas η k <lb/>L decreases from η k <lb/>B <lb/>to η k−1 <lb/>C <lb/>as j increases from j k <lb/>B to j k−1 <lb/>C ). In the case of a continuously differentiable pdf, every <lb/>Legendre transform η k <lb/>Λ (j), Λ = L, U satisfies the marginal stability equation, <lb/>∂D(j, η) <lb/>∂η <lb/>| η=η k <lb/>Λ (j) = 0. <lb/>(A-18) <lb/>One should note that η k <lb/>U,L and δ k <lb/>U,L depend on j (and on the function Γ(.)), but not on h or p. <lb/>Now for j &lt; j B ≡ min k j k <lb/>B , every min and max are reached at the corresponding value η k <lb/>B : <lb/>this means that there is no intermediate regime with a decreasing behavior of δ(η) as η increases, <lb/>hence δ d (η) = D(j, η), uniquely defined, is a continuously increasing function of η ∈ [0, 1]. For <lb/>j &gt; j B , there is at least one k where the maximum δ k <lb/>L (j) is reached for η = η k <lb/>L (j) &lt; η k <lb/>B , and <lb/>the minimum δ k <lb/>U (j) is reached for η = η k <lb/>U (j) &gt; η k <lb/>B , so that there is at least one finite interval of <lb/>η on which the function D(j, η) decreases with η, and thus does not correspond to an economic <lb/>equilibrium. Hence the demand η d (δ) has at least two branches. <lb/></div>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">−2 <lb/>−1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>x <lb/>f(x) <lb/>B 1 <lb/>C 1 <lb/>B 2 <lb/>Figure 11: An example of bimodal pdf. <lb/>In the plane (j, δ), the boundaries of the multiple solutions regions are thus given by the <lb/>fonctions δ k <lb/>Λ (j) = D(j, η k <lb/>Λ (j)), Λ = L, U , which are the graphs of all the branches of the <lb/>Legendre transform of Γ. By construction of the Legendre transform, every branch δ = δ k <lb/>U (j) <lb/>is a concave curve, and every branch δ = δ k <lb/>L (j) is a convex curve, and, under the smoothness <lb/>hypothesis HA1, along each branch Λ = L, U , <lb/>dδ k <lb/>Λ (j) <lb/>dj <lb/>= <lb/>dD(j, η k <lb/>Λ (j)) <lb/>dj <lb/>= −η k <lb/>Λ (j). <lb/>(A-19) <lb/>Recall that η k <lb/>Λ is the value of η for the solution which is marginally stable on this boundary. <lb/>These boundaries can be easily drawn for any distribution making use of a parameterization <lb/>by s (or equivalently x ≡ −s): from the basic equations η = 1−F (−s) where F is the cumulative <lb/>of the pdf f , s = Γ(η), and Γ (η) = 1/f (−s); with the marginal stability condition (A-18) <lb/>which gives j = Γ (η), the locus of marginal stability is then given in the plane (j, δ) by the <lb/>parameterized curve <lb/>for x ∈ support(f ), <lb/>j = 1/f (x) <lb/>(A-20) <lb/>δ = −x − <lb/>1 − F (x) <lb/>f (x) <lb/>(A-21) <lb/>This is this representation that we have used to draw the phase diagram, figure 12, for the <lb/>particular example of the bimodal distribution shown on figure 11. <lb/>The domain of multiple solutions can then be described as follows. The phase diagram is a <lb/>kind of superposition of diagrams associated to mono-modal phase diagrams, every maximum <lb/></div>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>−12 <lb/>−10 <lb/>−8 <lb/>−6 <lb/>−4 <lb/>−2 <lb/>0 <lb/>δ L <lb/>1 <lb/>δ U <lb/>2 <lb/>δ <lb/>δ U <lb/>1 <lb/>δ L <lb/>2 <lb/>j <lb/>B 2 <lb/>B <lb/>1 <lb/>C <lb/>1 <lb/>Figure 12: Phase diagram (aggregate demand) for the case of the smooth bimodal pdf shown on <lb/>figure 11. <lb/></div>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">0 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>1/j <lb/>x <lb/>f(x) <lb/>Figure 13: Examples of multimodal pdfs. At a given value of j = J/σ, the qualitative properties <lb/>are obtained by looking at the intersection of the horizontal line y = 1/j with the graph of the <lb/>pdf, y = f (x): for the particular value of j corresponding to the horizontal line on this figure, <lb/>the two pdfs lead to the same qualitative properties of the Demand. <lb/>(every &apos;bump&apos; in the pdf) k being responsible of the appearance of a domain of multistability: <lb/>when j becomes larger than j k <lb/>B , a continuous solution split into two solutions, with a lower <lb/>solution η d (j, δ) ≤ η k <lb/>L (j) &lt; η k <lb/>B and δ ≤ δ k <lb/>L , and an upper one with η d (j, δ) ≥ η k <lb/>U (j) &gt; η k <lb/>B and <lb/>δ ≥ δ k <lb/>U (see figure 12). When j becomes larger than j k <lb/>C , this bump is no more &apos;seen&apos;. Since <lb/>a minimum of the pdf, if not at a boundary, is in between two maxima, such an intermediate <lb/>solution may exist either because of one bump or the other -or both. <lb/>The branch δ = δ k <lb/>U (j) has thus as left end point, B k ≡ (j k <lb/>B , δ k <lb/>B = D(j k <lb/>B , η k <lb/>B )), and as right <lb/>endpoint (if j k <lb/>C is finite), C k ≡ (j k <lb/>C , δ k <lb/>C = D(j k <lb/>C , η k <lb/>C )). B k is the merging point of δ k <lb/>U and δ k <lb/>L , <lb/>and C k the merging point of δ k <lb/>U and δ k+1 <lb/>L . Since δ k <lb/>L and δ k+1 <lb/>L <lb/>must be both above δ k <lb/>U , these <lb/>two branches must intersect one another for some value of j = j k <lb/>BC between j k <lb/>B and j k <lb/>C : there <lb/>is thus coexistence of three solutions in the triangular-like domain bounded below by δ k <lb/>U (or <lb/>max(δ k <lb/>U , δ k+1 <lb/>U ) if B k is below the branch δ k+1 <lb/>U ), and above by δ k <lb/>L for j ≤ j k <lb/>BC , and by δ k+1 <lb/>L <lb/>for <lb/>j ≥ j k <lb/>BC . <lb/>In the smooth case (HA1), at every bifurcation point B k , resp. C k where two boundaries <lb/>merge, according to A-19 there is a common slope −η k <lb/>B , resp. −η k <lb/>C . <lb/>One may say that the pdf is probed at different scales for different values of j. Consider <lb/>the graph y = f (x). Every maximum below the line y = 1/j is not seen (it does not change <lb/>the structure of the solution), whereas a set of maxima higher than 1/j, but joined by minima <lb/>where f is still higher than 1/j, is seen as a single global bump. This gives in particular that for <lb/>j &gt; j B , the number of solutions is equal to one plus the number of times the line y = 1/j cut <lb/>the graph y = f (x) at points where f is increasing. Note that this does not give the number of <lb/>solutions for a given value of δ. On figure 13, two pdfs are shown; the intersection of the graph <lb/></div>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>-6 <lb/>-5 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-3 <lb/>-2 <lb/>-1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>η=1/2 <lb/>η=0 <lb/>h-p <lb/>j <lb/>η=1 <lb/>Figure 14: Phase diagram (aggregate demand) for the case of a bimodal pdf composed of two <lb/>Dirac peaks. <lb/>y = f (x) with the line y = 1/j gives the structure of the demand at this particular value of j <lb/>(in the case illustrated on the figure, the demand has 3 solutions for the two pdfs). <lb/>A.3.2 A degenerate case: 2 Dirac <lb/>Let us consider the particular case of an IWP distribution given by two Delta pics: x i = ±x 0 <lb/>with equal probability (x 0 = 1/ <lb/>√ <lb/>2 since the variance of f is normalized to 1). For j = 0, one <lb/>has clearly η = 0, 1/2 or 1 depending on δ &lt; −x 0 , −x 0 &lt; δ &lt; +x 0 or δ &gt; x 0 . For j &gt; 0, <lb/>obviously η can still take only these three values. One gets easily the domain of existence and <lb/>stability of these solutions, η = 0, 1/2, 1, by direct inspection of the equation (13). The resulting <lb/>phase diagram is shown on figure 14. <lb/>This phase diagram for a singular distribution can also be understood by comparison with <lb/>the predicted phase diagram for a continuous distribution. In the present case, the two maxima <lb/>have equal height, +∞, which gives j 1 <lb/>B = j 2 <lb/>B = 0, in agreement with the fact that boundary <lb/>lines meet at j = 0. The minimum between the two maxima is at f = 0, hence j C = ∞: the <lb/>domain of stability of the intermediate solution η = 1/2 extends to infinity, as it is the case <lb/>whenever a minimum is at f (x 1 <lb/>C ) = 0. The marginal stability lines are straight lines -hence, <lb/>marginally concave and convex curves -, with slopes 0, 1/2 and 1 corresponding to the values of <lb/>the solution marginally stable on the boundary, in agreement with (A-19). Since here there is <lb/>no continuity in the demand at the singular points B 1 = (0, −1), B 2 = (0, 1), two branches do <lb/>not merge with a common slope: besides the fact that the demand can take only three values, <lb/>this is the only place where the non smoothness of the pdf gives a feature of the phase diagram <lb/>qualitatively different from what is obtained for a smooth pdf. <lb/></div>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">halshs-00135405, version 1 -7 Mar 2007 </note>


	</text>
</tei>
