<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Numerical simulations of oscillating soliton stars: Excited states in spherical symmetry and <lb/>ground state evolutions in 3D <lb/>Jayashree Balakrishna, 1 Ruxandra Bondarescu, 2 Gregory Daues, 3 and Mihai Bondarescu 4,5 <lb/>1 Harris-Stowe State University, St. Louis, Missouri, USA <lb/>2 Cornell University, Ithaca, New York, USA <lb/>3 <lb/>National Center for Supercomputing Applications, Urbana, Illinois, USA <lb/>4 Max Planck Institut für Gravitationsphysik, Albert Einstein Institut, Golm, Germany <lb/>5 <lb/>California Institute of Technology, California, USA <lb/>(Received 17 October 2007; published 16 January 2008) <lb/>Excited state soliton stars are studied numerically for the first time. The stability of spherically <lb/>symmetric S-branch excited state oscillatons under radial perturbations is investigated using a 1D <lb/>code. We find that these stars are inherently unstable either migrating to the ground state or collapsing <lb/>to black holes. Higher excited state configurations are observed to cascade through intermediate excited <lb/>states during their migration to the ground state. This is similar to excited state boson stars [J. Balakrishna, <lb/>E. Seidel, and W.-M. Suen, Phys. Rev. D 58, 104004 (1998).]. Ground state oscillatons are then studied in <lb/>full 3D numerical relativity. Finding the appropriate gauge condition for the dynamic oscillatons is much <lb/>more challenging than in the case of boson stars. Different slicing conditions are explored, and a <lb/>customized gauge condition that approximates polar slicing in spherical symmetry is implemented. <lb/>Comparisons with 1D results and convergence tests are performed. The behavior of these stars under small <lb/>axisymmetric perturbations is studied and gravitational waveforms are extracted. We find that the <lb/>gravitational waves damp out on a short time scale, enabling us to obtain the complete waveform. This <lb/>work is a starting point for the evolution of real scalar field systems with arbitrary symmetries. <lb/>DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.77.024028 <lb/>PACS numbers: 04.25.Dÿ, 04.30.Db, 95.35.+d <lb/></front>

			<body>I. INTRODUCTION <lb/>Real scalar fields play an important role in many models <lb/>in particle physics and cosmology. The axion is described <lb/>by a real field as is the inflaton. Scalar particles are im-<lb/>portant dark matter candidates. Models of real scalar field <lb/>dark matter have given good fits for the velocity profile of <lb/>spiral galaxies [1]. Recently there has been widely publi-<lb/>cized observational evidence by NASA for the existence of <lb/>dark matter with both the Hubble telescope [2] and the <lb/>Chandra X-ray observatory [3]. These particles could come <lb/>together through some kind of Jeans instability mechanism <lb/>to form gravitationally bounded objects such as oscillating <lb/>soliton stars (also called oscillatons) [4]. <lb/>Soliton stars possess a spectrum of states: ground state <lb/>and excited states. The ground state scalar field has no <lb/>nodes, a first excited state has one node and so on. The <lb/>stability of spherically symmetric ground state oscillatons <lb/>has been studied numerically [5,6]. In this paper we extend <lb/>this study to the case of excited states. Studying the stabil-<lb/>ity of excited states is important because they may be <lb/>intermediate states during the formation of these stars. <lb/>In this work we also begin an exploratory investigation <lb/>of ground state soliton stars in three-dimensional numeri-<lb/>cal relativity with the goal of performing stable evolutions <lb/>and extracting gravitational waveforms. Numerical relativ-<lb/>ity has made major progress in the past few years. It is now <lb/>possible to evolve binary black hole inspirals stably for <lb/>many orbits [7,8]. Gravitational waveforms from black <lb/>hole simulations have been extracted and match accurately <lb/>against post-Newtonian estimates [9]. Gravitational wave <lb/>detectors have reached their design sensitivity and wave-<lb/>form templates are required to analyze data produced by <lb/>the science runs [10,11]. Generating numerical waveforms <lb/>from other compact objects predicted by general relativity <lb/>such as soliton stars (comprised from real scalar fields) and <lb/>boson stars (made up from complex scalar fields) is a <lb/>timely and necessary effort. Gravitational waveforms <lb/>from two colliding boson stars [12 -14] as well as from <lb/>single distorted boson stars [15] have been extracted. To <lb/>our knowledge this is the first soliton star study in 3D <lb/>numerical relativity. <lb/>Numerous authors have studied soliton stars numerically <lb/>in spherical symmetry [5,6,16,17]. Mathematically, oscil-<lb/>lating soliton stars are nonsingular solutions to the <lb/>Einstein-Klein-Gordon (EKG) equations represented by a <lb/>massive real scalar field for which both the metric and the <lb/>scalar field are periodic in time [5]. The absence of static <lb/>equilibrium configurations contrasts oscillatons with the <lb/>case of boson stars, which are complex scalar field solu-<lb/>tions to the EKG equations that have equilibrium configu-<lb/>rations characterized by static metric components (the <lb/>scalar field has an r; t re i!t time dependence <lb/>but the metric and energy itself are time independent), <lb/>and makes their evolution more challenging numerically. <lb/>Similar to boson stars and neutron stars, the mass profile of <lb/>ground state soliton stars has a stable (S-branch) and an <lb/>unstable branch (U-branch) [5,6]. The mass profile has a <lb/>maximum at M c ground st: 0:607M 2 <lb/>Pl =m corresponding to a <lb/>central density 1 0 0:48 [6] (here m is the mass of the <lb/>scalar field.) The configurations to the left (lower central <lb/></body>

			<front>PHYSICAL REVIEW D 77, 024028 (2008) <lb/>1550-7998= 2008=77(2)=024028(12) <lb/>024028-1 <lb/>© 2008 The American Physical Society <lb/></front>

			<body>density) of this critical mass are stable, while those to the <lb/>right (greater central density) are unstable. <lb/>In this paper we study the stability of excited state <lb/>oscillatons under radial perturbations and find that all <lb/>excited configurations are inherently unstable. They either <lb/>migrate to the ground state or collapse to black holes. We <lb/>present simulations for both scenarios for configurations in <lb/>the first excited state. We find the mass profile of first <lb/>excited state configurations as a function of central density <lb/>1 0 (see Fig. 1.) It has a maximum at a similar critical <lb/>density as for ground state stars, but in this case it corre-<lb/>sponds to a higher critical mass of M c 1st excited st: <lb/>1:33M 2 <lb/>Pl =m. We evolve S-branch one-node stars when no <lb/>explicit perturbation is applied other than that induced by <lb/>the numerical grid (we covered the 95% mass radius of the <lb/>star with the same number of grid points 187 to make <lb/>meaningful comparisons) and find that stars that are unable <lb/>to migrate to the ground state collapse to black holes. The <lb/>migration can occur only if the star can lose enough mass <lb/>through scalar radiation to become an S-branch ground <lb/>state configuration with M &lt; M c ground st: 0:607M 2 <lb/>Pl =m. <lb/>A first excited state star of mass M &lt; 0:84M 2 <lb/>Pl =m succeeds <lb/>in losing its excess mass and migrates to the ground state. <lb/>We study the relative times of collapse to black holes of <lb/>different configurations for S-branch stars with mass M &gt; <lb/>0:84M 2 <lb/>Pl =m. The collapse times that we tabulate are ap-<lb/>proximate because polar slicing does not penetrate black <lb/>hole horizons. We find that this time decreases as the <lb/>central density increases. We also present a simulation of <lb/>the migration of a one-node star to the ground state and find <lb/>the ground state configuration that it migrated to. We then <lb/>simulate the migration of a 5-node configuration to the <lb/>ground state. During the migration process the star cas-<lb/>cades through a superposition of lower excited state con-<lb/>figurations. We are able to determine an approximate 4-<lb/>node intermediate state and then follow the evolution until <lb/>the star settles into a ground state configuration. The <lb/>simulations are performed using the polar slicing condition <lb/>K <lb/>K <lb/>0, which is a natural choice for spherically <lb/>symmetric spacetimes [18]. <lb/>In the second part of the paper we focus on 3D simula-<lb/>tions of ground state soliton stars. We use the Cactus <lb/>Computational Toolkit [19] with the scalar field evolution <lb/>of Guzman [20] and the BSSN implementation [21,22] of <lb/>the Einstein equations. Soliton stars retain some of the <lb/>properties of boson star systems that made them a good <lb/>test bed for numerical relativity in that the space-time is <lb/>singularity free and the star has a smooth outer boundary. <lb/>However, the evolutions are challenging because the sys-<lb/>tem is highly dynamic, i.e., the metric functions, extrinsic <lb/>curvature components, and gauge functions are always <lb/>rapidly oscillating in time. In particular, finding an appro-<lb/>priate slicing condition and implementing it accurately to <lb/>obtain stable evolutions is a challenge for such dynamic <lb/>spacetimes. We introduce a customized slicing condition <lb/>based on the features of an eigenstate of a stable branch <lb/>oscillaton in spherical symmetry and we refer to it as <lb/>truncated Fourier slicing. Instead of enforcing that K be <lb/>zero as in the case of dynamic boson star evolutions [15], <lb/>for this system we drive K to the time dependent K j max t, <lb/>which is the trace of extrinsic curvature appropriate for a <lb/>spherically symmetric oscillaton eigenstate expanded to <lb/>finite order in a Fourier series. While this condition is <lb/>based on an eigenstate, we find that it is effective in <lb/>simulations with small nonspherical perturbations applied <lb/>to the star. With this choice of gauge we are able to <lb/>reproduce results from 1D codes within the 3D context, <lb/>and we are able to perform stable simulations of sufficient <lb/>duration to extract gravitational waveforms. <lb/>We then study soliton stars under small nonradial per-<lb/>turbations and the emitted gravitational waves. We use two <lb/>types of perturbations. The first type was previously ap-<lb/>plied to boson stars by Guzman [20]. It consists of an <lb/>imposed asymmetry in the grid resolution x y Þ <lb/>z, while choosing the number of points n x n y Þ n z <lb/>such that the distance from the origin to the boundary of the <lb/>grid is kept the same. In this case the resolution itself is the <lb/>perturbation. Consequently, the amplitude of the &apos; 2, <lb/>m 0 Zerilli waveform [23] is expected to be zero in the <lb/>limit of infinite resolution and is observed numerically to <lb/>converge away with resolution at approximately second <lb/>order. We next study an oscillaton under a perturbation <lb/>proportional to the &apos; 2, m 0 spherical harmonic that <lb/>perturbs the metric of the eigenstate nonradially. This <lb/>perturbation is more physical as it could mimic a distur-<lb/>bance in the gravitational field of the star due to the <lb/>presence of another object. The Zerilli and Newman-<lb/>Penrose 4 [24] gravitational waveforms are extracted <lb/>FIG. 1. The mass is shown as a function of central density for <lb/>stars in their first excited state. The mass increases monotoni-<lb/>cally until it reaches a critical point at 1c 0:45, and M c <lb/>1:33M 2 <lb/>Pl =m after which it starts decreasing. This point marks the <lb/>end of the S-branch, and the beginning of the U-branch. These <lb/>stars are more massive than ground state stars. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">BALAKRISHNA, BONDARESCU, DAUES, AND BONDARESCU <lb/>PHYSICAL REVIEW D 77, 024028 (2008) <lb/></note>

			<page>024028-2 <lb/></page>

			<body>and compared at different detectors. The waveforms damp <lb/>out on a short time scale. This is consistent with the <lb/>expectation that, similar to boson stars, soliton stars have <lb/>only strongly damped modes because the scalar field ex-<lb/>tends to infinity and this allows energy to be radiated away <lb/>rapidly [25-27]. We also calculate the energy radiated in <lb/>gravitational waves from the Zerilli function. By the end of <lb/>our simulations the energy as a function of time is seen to <lb/>flatten out, suggesting that the full gravitational waveform <lb/>has been extracted. <lb/>In Sec. II A we describe the equations for spherically <lb/>symmetric oscillatons. The eigenvalue problem and bound-<lb/>ary conditions are then discussed in Sec. II B. In Sec. II C <lb/>our results for the excited state evolutions are presented. <lb/>Sec. III A discusses the evolution equations for the 3D <lb/>code. The gauge conditions are presented next in <lb/>Sec. III B with convergence tests and comparison to 1D <lb/>results. Sec. III C details the application of small nonradial <lb/>perturbations to ground state soliton stars and discusses the <lb/>extracted gravitational waveforms for different perturba-<lb/>tions. The results are summarized in the conclusion. <lb/>II. SPHERICALLY SYMMETRIC <lb/>CONFIGURATIONS <lb/>A. Mathematical background <lb/>The action describing a self-gravitating real scalar field <lb/>in a curved spacetime is given by <lb/>I <lb/>Z <lb/>d 4 x <lb/>ÿg <lb/>p <lb/>1 <lb/>16G <lb/>R ÿ <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>g @ @ V <lb/>; <lb/>(1) <lb/>where R is the Ricci scalar, g is the metric of the space-<lb/>time, g is the determinant of the metric, is the scalar <lb/>field, V its potential of self-interaction, and units with @ <lb/>c 1 have been used. Greek indices take values between 0 <lb/>and 3 and the Einstein summation convention is used. The <lb/>variation of this action with respect to the scalar field leads <lb/>to the Klein-Gordon equation, which can be written as <lb/>; <lb/>; ÿ <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>dV <lb/>d <lb/>0: <lb/>(2) <lb/>When the variation of Eq. (1) is made with respect to the <lb/>metric g , the Einstein&apos;s equations G 8GT arise, <lb/>and the resulting stress-energy tensor reads <lb/>T @ @ ÿ 1 <lb/>2 g ; ; V: <lb/>(3) <lb/>In the present manuscript we focus on the free-field case, <lb/>for which the potential is V m 2 2 , where m is <lb/>interpreted as the mass of the field. <lb/>The spherically symmetric line element is <lb/>ds 2 ÿN 2 dt 2 g 2 dr 2 r 2 d 2 sin 2 d 2 ; (4) <lb/>where Nr; t is the lapse function and g 2 r; t is the radial <lb/>metric function. We use a polar slicing condition and this <lb/>ensures that the line element retains the above form <lb/>throughout the evolution [5,6]. We follow Refs. [6,17] <lb/>and write the coupled Einstein-Klein-Gordon equations as <lb/>A 0 4GrAC _ <lb/>2 02 Am 2 2 <lb/>A <lb/>r <lb/>1 ÿ A; (5) <lb/>C 0 <lb/>2C <lb/>r <lb/>1 A4Gr 2 2 ÿ 1; <lb/>(6) <lb/>C <lb/>ÿ <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>_ <lb/>C _ <lb/>00 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>r <lb/>ÿ <lb/>C 0 <lb/>2C <lb/>ÿ Am 2 ; <lb/>(7) <lb/>_ <lb/>A 8GrA _ <lb/>0 ; <lb/>(8) <lb/>where Ar; t g 2 , Cr; t gr; t=Nt; r 2 and r; t <lb/>is the real scalar field. These equations have no equilibrium <lb/>solutions with static metric components [5]. The simplest <lb/>solutions are periodic expansions of the form <lb/>t; r <lb/>X <lb/>j max <lb/>j1 <lb/>2jÿ1 cos2j ÿ 1!t; <lb/>(9) <lb/>At; r <lb/>X <lb/>j max <lb/>j0 <lb/>A 2j r cos2j!t; <lb/>(10) <lb/>Ct; r <lb/>X <lb/>j max <lb/>j0 <lb/>C 2j r cos2j!t; <lb/>(11) <lb/>where ! is the fundamental frequency and j max represents <lb/>the value of j at which the series is truncated for numerical <lb/>computations. The actual solution is an infinite Fourier <lb/>expansion of the above form that is convergent [5,6]. <lb/>For numerical convenience in the code we use dimen-<lb/>sionless variables <lb/>! <lb/>8G <lb/>p <lb/>; <lb/>r! r=m; <lb/>C ! Cm 2 =! 2 ; <lb/>t! !t: <lb/>(12) <lb/>B. Boundary conditions and eigenvalue problem <lb/>The system is asymptotically flat: Ar 1; t 1 and <lb/>r 1; t 0. Thus the coefficients A 0 1 1, <lb/>A j 1 0 for j Þ 0, j 1 0 for all j, and C j 1 <lb/>0 for j Þ 0. The series is truncated at j max 2 and the <lb/>coefficients of sinjt and cosjt are matched in Eqs. (5)-<lb/>(7). Equation (8) is used as an algebraic relation to deter-<lb/>mine A 0 only. The system of equations is solved as an <lb/>eigenvalue problem for C j after specifying the central field <lb/>1 0. The lapse at the boundary gives the value of !. See <lb/>Ref. [17] for further details. One sets t 0 in Eq. (8) to <lb/>determine the initial metric components g rr t 0 <lb/>A 0 A 2 A 4 , <lb/>g tt t 0 ÿA 0 A 2 A 4 =C 0 <lb/>C 2 C 4 . <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">NUMERICAL SIMULATIONS OF OSCILLATING SOLITON . . . <lb/>PHYSICAL REVIEW D 77, 024028 (2008) <lb/></note>

			<page>024028-3 <lb/></page>

			<body>The configurations we consider are excited states. The <lb/>fields 2jÿ1 with j 1; 2; . . . have nodes. The first excited <lb/>state field configurations have 1 node, the second have 2 <lb/>and so on. <lb/>After determining the initial configuration, the evolution <lb/>of the system is studied using the 1D boson star evolution <lb/>code of Refs. [18,28] with the field and its derivative <lb/>having one component (real field) instead of two (complex <lb/>field). The mass of the star is determined by the value of <lb/>g rr At; r at the edge of the grid <lb/>M lim <lb/>r!1 <lb/>r <lb/>2 <lb/>1 ÿ <lb/>1 <lb/>At; r <lb/>M 2 <lb/>Pl <lb/>m <lb/>: <lb/>(13) <lb/>C. Stability of excited states <lb/>The mass profile of ground state soliton stars have been <lb/>described in Refs. [6,17]. In Fig. 1 we show the mass of <lb/>first excited state oscillatons as a function of 1 0. These <lb/>stars have two branches similar to the ground state con-<lb/>figurations with the mass increasing to a maximum mass of <lb/>M c 1:3M 2 <lb/>Pl =m. This is higher than the maximum mass of <lb/>a ground state star. In general, excited configurations of a <lb/>given central field density 1 0 are larger and more <lb/>massive than ground state configurations with the same <lb/>central density. The branch to the left of the maximum is <lb/>traditionally called the S-branch and the branch to the right <lb/>is called the U-branch. <lb/>In the case of ground state stars the S-branch is found to <lb/>be stable to radial perturbations [6]. Stability here means <lb/>that stars on this branch move to new lower mass configu-<lb/>rations on the same branch under small perturbations. <lb/>U-branch stars are inherently unstable to small perturba-<lb/>tions and collapse to black holes. Under large perturbations <lb/>that reduce their mass sufficiently they can migrate to the <lb/>S-branch [6]. <lb/>In this work we study the stability of excited state <lb/>S-branch oscillaton stars. In Fig. 2 the evolution of the <lb/>radial metric g rr of an S-branch first excited state star is <lb/>shown. The central density of this configuration is 1 0 <lb/>0:2828 and no explicit perturbation has been applied. The <lb/>numerical grid (r 0:1) is the only source of perturba-<lb/>tion. As can be seen from the sharp rise in the radial metric <lb/>[Fig. 2(a)] and collapse of the lapse [Fig. 2(b)] the star is <lb/>going to form a black hole. The polar slicing condition <lb/>causes the lapse to collapse and the radial metric to rise <lb/>sharply when an apparent horizon is approached [18]. <lb/>Clearly, the star is unstable although this configuration <lb/>lies on the S-branch. <lb/>We next study the time of collapse of one node S-branch <lb/>oscillaton configurations to black holes as a function of <lb/>central density. Excited states are inherently unstable and <lb/>the discretization error due to the numerical grid is suffi-<lb/>cient to make them collapse to black holes or migrate to the <lb/>ground state. To compare the effects of radial perturbations <lb/>on stars with different central densities, we use the discre-<lb/>tization of the grid as a perturbation with the stars covered <lb/>by the same numbers of grid points. The stars need to be <lb/>resolved differently because of their different central den-<lb/>sities. In the following simulations the 95% mass radius <lb/>R 95 was considered to be the radius of the star. <lb/>The first configuration considered is close to the critical <lb/>mass and has 1 0 0:41 and a radius of R 95 14:9=m. <lb/>This was covered by 187 grid points with a resolution <lb/>r 0:08. The second configuration has 1 0 <lb/>0:2828 star with R 95 18:7=m and was covered by the <lb/>same number of grid points with r 0:1. This star <lb/>collapsed in a longer time. We took the time of collapse <lb/>(polar slicing does not allow us to find the actual time of <lb/>formation of a black hole horizon [18]) to be the beginning <lb/>of the sharp rise in the metric. Coordinate grid stretching <lb/>[29] (due to the differential rates that test particles on <lb/>geodesic curves fall into the black hole) causes the metric <lb/>function g rr to rise and form a sharp peak. The formation of <lb/>the peak signals the approach of horizon formation on a <lb/>short time scale. <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>r <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>Lapse <lb/>t = 0 <lb/>t = 305.58 <lb/>t = 450.86 <lb/>t = 460.87 <lb/>t = 465.88 <lb/>t = 475.90 <lb/>6 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>8 <lb/>1 0 <lb/>1 2 <lb/>1 4 <lb/>r <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>g <lb/>rr <lb/>t=0 <lb/>t=305.58 <lb/>t=450.86 <lb/>t=460.87 <lb/>t=465.88 <lb/>t = 475.90 <lb/>FIG. 2. (a) The lapse and (b) the radial metric are shown at <lb/>different times as a star with a central density of 1 0 0:2828 <lb/>collapses to a black hole. The polar slicing condition causes the <lb/>lapse to collapse and the metric to rise sharply as an apparent <lb/>horizon is approached. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">BALAKRISHNA, BONDARESCU, DAUES, AND BONDARESCU <lb/>PHYSICAL REVIEW D 77, 024028 (2008) <lb/></note>

			<page>024028-4 <lb/></page>

			<body>In Table I we show the time of collapse to a black hole <lb/>for different S-branch configurations. The table shows the <lb/>central field density, mass, and radius of each configura-<lb/>tion. The time of collapse to a black hole increases as the <lb/>central density decreases until a central density of about <lb/>1 0 0:075. For central densities of 0.075 and lower the <lb/>stars did not collapse but migrated to configurations in the <lb/>ground state. Although a first excited state star of central <lb/>density 1 0:075 is more massive than any ground state <lb/>star (maximum mass of ground state configurations is <lb/>about 0:61M 2 <lb/>Pl =m) it lost the excess mass through scalar <lb/>radiation and settled in the ground state. Excited state <lb/>S-branch stars are clearly inherently unstable and either <lb/>collapse to black holes or migrate to the ground state. <lb/>In Fig. 3 and 4 we show a first excited state star with <lb/>1 0 0:041 of mass 0:655M 2 <lb/>Pl =m migrating to the <lb/>ground state. No explicit perturbation was applied. In <lb/>Fig. 3(a) the initial (one node) and final (no nodes) field <lb/>configurations are displayed. In Fig. 3(b) the initial and <lb/>final radial metric g rr are shown. The initial radial metric <lb/>has two maxima, which is characteristic of a first excited <lb/>state configuration. The final radial metric (t <lb/>218 998=m) has one maximum indicating the star has <lb/>gone to the ground state. The final configuration shown <lb/>corresponds to a time which is an integral multiple of . <lb/>This is to ensure that we get the same phase as the t 0 <lb/>configuration to facilitate comparison. In Fig. 3(c) the <lb/>radial metric of the star at the end of the run is plotted <lb/>together with the radial metric of a ground state star of <lb/>central density 1 0 0:11. The final radial metric of the <lb/>migrating star is very close, to this ground state configu-<lb/>ration. For comparison the mass of the star at the end of the <lb/>run was about M 0:44M 2 <lb/>Pl =m as compared to a mass of <lb/>M 0:43M 2 <lb/>Pl =m for a 1 0 0:11 star. The migrating <lb/>star is settling to a configuration close to the 1 0 0:11 <lb/>ground state star. <lb/>The mass loss is calculated using Eq. (13) for the above <lb/>configuration and is plotted as a function of time in <lb/>Fig. 4(a). The star loses more than 30% of its mass through <lb/>0 <lb/>1 0 <lb/>2 0 <lb/>3 0 <lb/>4 0 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>r <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>Φ <lb/>t = 0 <lb/>t = 688, 002.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 0 <lb/>4 0 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>140 <lb/>r <lb/>1 <lb/>1.01 <lb/>1.02 <lb/>1.03 <lb/>1.04 <lb/>1.05 <lb/>1.06 <lb/>1.07 <lb/>g <lb/>rr <lb/>t=0 <lb/>t=688, 002.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 15 20 25 30 35 40 45 50 55 60 <lb/>r <lb/>1 <lb/>1.01 <lb/>1.02 <lb/>1.03 <lb/>1.04 <lb/>1.05 <lb/>1.06 <lb/>1.07 <lb/>g <lb/>rr <lb/>Excited State: t = 688, 002.5 <lb/>Ground State with φ 1 (0) = 0.11: t=0 <lb/>FIG. 3. In (a) the scalar field and (b) metric component g rr <lb/>are plotted against radius at t 0 and t 690 000=m. The <lb/>initial g rr has two maxima (first excited state star; 1 0 <lb/>0:041 and R 95 51:35=m). By t 690 000=m the star has <lb/>migrated to a denser ground state configuration of R 95 16=m <lb/>with lower mass. (c) The final metric g rr is compared to that of a <lb/>ground state t 0, 1 0 0:11 star. Although the ground state <lb/>g rr in slightly lower because the star has not fully settled, the <lb/>overall agreement is very good. <lb/>TABLE I. Physical characteristics of S-branch soliton stars in <lb/>the first excited state are listed together with the collapse time to <lb/>black holes. Each star is covered by the same number of grid <lb/>points ( 187) to facilitate the comparison. The radius of the <lb/>star is taken to be the radius within which 95% of the mass of the <lb/>star is contained. Configurations with a mass below 0:84M 2 <lb/>Pl =m <lb/>lose enough mass through scalar radiation to migrate to the <lb/>ground state. <lb/>S-branch Soliton Stars collapse times <lb/>1 0 <lb/>M(M 2 <lb/>Pl =m) <lb/>R 95 1=m <lb/>collapse time <lb/>0.41 <lb/>1.32 <lb/>14.9 <lb/>250 <lb/>0.2828 <lb/>1.26 <lb/>18.7 <lb/>445 <lb/>0.1414 <lb/>1.07 <lb/>27.0 <lb/>1280 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.92 <lb/>33.7 <lb/>2250 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.84 <lb/>38.0 <lb/>4160 <lb/>0.075 <lb/>0.82 <lb/>39.5 <lb/>goes to gr. state <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">NUMERICAL SIMULATIONS OF OSCILLATING SOLITON . . . <lb/>PHYSICAL REVIEW D 77, 024028 (2008) <lb/></note>

			<page>024028-5 <lb/></page>

			<body>scalar radiation. The amount of mass loss decreases in time <lb/>as the star settles to its final ground state configuration. In <lb/>Fig. 4(b) the maximum of the metric function g rr of a <lb/>perturbed excited state star is plotted against time. As the <lb/>star settles into its new ground state configuration, it oscil-<lb/>lates at two different frequencies. One is approximately the <lb/>fundamental unperturbed oscillation of period =! <lb/>(t code ). The second has much higher period that <lb/>changes as the star goes through different intermediate <lb/>configurations and eventually settles into the quasinormal <lb/>mode of the ground state configuration [6]. <lb/>We next simulate the migration of an oscillaton in the <lb/>5th excited state to the ground state. The initial configura-<lb/>tion is that of a five-node excited state S-branch star of <lb/>central density 1 0 0:006 and mass M <lb/>0:792M 2 <lb/>Pl =m. As usual, no explicit has been applied per-<lb/>turbation other than that due to the discretization of the <lb/>numerical grid (resolution r 0:1). In Fig. 5(a) we show <lb/>the radial metric g rr of the star at t 0, and t <lb/>172 000=m. The initial configuration (t 0) has six max-<lb/>ima in the radial metric. By the end of the simulation the <lb/>radial metric has just one maximum indicating the star has <lb/>gone to the ground state (the mass at this stage is M <lb/>0:463M 2 <lb/>Pl =m.) During the evolution the star appears to pass <lb/>through an intermediate four-node state. This can be seen <lb/>in Fig. 5(b). In the figure = cos2t ( is the density of the <lb/>star and the division by cos2t is in order to facilitate <lb/>comparison as it helps avoid phase differences) is plotted at <lb/>0 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/>1000 <lb/>r <lb/>1 <lb/>1.005 <lb/>1.01 <lb/>1.015 <lb/>1.02 <lb/>1.025 <lb/>g <lb/>rr <lb/>t=0 <lb/>t = 171915.46 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>700 <lb/>r <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>ρ [x 10 <lb/>6 <lb/>M <lb/>Pl <lb/>2 <lb/>m <lb/>2 <lb/>] <lb/>t=0, φ 1 (0) = 0.006, 5-node star <lb/>t = 102,002.88, intermediate state <lb/>t = 0, φ 1 (0) = 0.007, 4-node star <lb/>FIG. 5. (a) The radial metric g rr of a migrating five-node <lb/>soliton star configuration ( 1 0 0:006; M 0:79M 2 <lb/>Pl =m) is <lb/>displayed as a function of radius on two time slices. The t 0 <lb/>radial metric has 6 maxima, which is characteristic to 5th excited <lb/>state configurations. By t 172 000=m the star has migrated to <lb/>the ground state. Although, the migration process is not yet <lb/>complete by this stage, the star has lost 29% of its mass through <lb/>scalar radiation and the radial metric has only one maximum. <lb/>(b) The central density of the same star is shown at t 0 and in a <lb/>intermediate state at t 102 000=m. In this intermediate state <lb/>the star has four nodes (central density has five maxima). We plot <lb/>the density of a four-node star with 1 0 0:007 for compari-<lb/>son. <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>t [ x 10 <lb/>5 <lb/>] <lb/>0.45 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>Mass [M <lb/>Pl <lb/>2 <lb/>/m] <lb/>0.5 0.6 <lb/>t [x 10 <lb/>5 <lb/>] <lb/>0 <lb/>0.1 0.2 <lb/>0.3 0.4 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 0.9 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.02 <lb/>1.03 <lb/>1.04 <lb/>1.05 <lb/>1.06 <lb/>1.07 <lb/>1.08 <lb/>1.09 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>Peak of g <lb/>rr <lb/>FIG. 4. (a) The mass of the same 1 0 0:041 star is shown <lb/>as the star migrates to the ground state. The mass flattens out as <lb/>the star is settling towards a final ground state configuration. The <lb/>oscillations in the metric also settle down to an approximately <lb/>constant oscillation. The mass of the star at the end of the run is <lb/>M 0:44M 2 <lb/>Pl =m, and is within 2% of the ground state configu-<lb/>ration ( 1 0 0:11 and M 0:43M 2 <lb/>Pl =m) that the star is <lb/>estimated to migrate to. (b) The maximum of g rr is shown as <lb/>a function of time. The star loses more than 30% of its mass <lb/>during the migration. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">BALAKRISHNA, BONDARESCU, DAUES, AND BONDARESCU <lb/>PHYSICAL REVIEW D 77, 024028 (2008) <lb/></note>

			<page>024028-6 <lb/></page>

			<body>t 0 and t 102 000=m against the t 0 density of a <lb/>four-node 1 0 0:007 star. The evolving star initially <lb/>had a density with six maxima characteristic of a five-<lb/>node star. By time t 102; 000=m it has lost one of these <lb/>maxima and appears to be in an intermediate four-node <lb/>state. We have plotted the density of a four-node 1 0 <lb/>0:007 star to compare the positions of the peaks and profile <lb/>of . The positions of the peaks are close to each other <lb/>(especially the first three) but the sizes of the peaks are not. <lb/>The star probably cascades through superpositions of lower <lb/>excited configurations due to the inherent nonlinearity of <lb/>the system. <lb/>III. NUMERICAL SIMULATIONS OF GROUND <lb/>STATE SOLITON STARS IN 3D <lb/>A. 3D Evolution equations <lb/>In order to find solutions to the Einstein-Klein-Gordon <lb/>system of equations we use the 3 1 decomposition of <lb/>Einstein&apos;s equations, for which the line element can be <lb/>written as <lb/>ds 2 ÿ 2 dt 2 ab dx a a dtdx b b dt; (14) <lb/>where ab is the three-dimensional metric; from now on <lb/>latin indices label the three spatial coordinates. The func-<lb/>tions and a in Eq. (14) are freely specifiable gauge <lb/>parameters, known as the lapse function and the shift <lb/>vector, respectively, and is the determinant of the 3-<lb/>metric. Throughout the rest of the paper the standard <lb/>general relativity notation is used. The Greek indices run <lb/>from 0 to 3 and the Latin indices run from 1 to 3. In this <lb/>section we use geometric units with G c 1. <lb/>The Klein-Gordon equation can be written as a first-<lb/>order evolution system by defining two new variables in <lb/>terms of combinations of their derivatives: <lb/>p = <lb/>@ t ÿ c @ c and a @ a . With this notation the <lb/>evolution equations become<lb/>@ t <lb/>1=2 a <lb/>a ; <lb/>@ t a @ a<lb/>1=2 b <lb/>b <lb/>; <lb/>@ t @ a <lb/>p <lb/>a ÿ <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>p @V <lb/>@ <lb/>: <lb/>(15)<lb/>On the other hand, the geometry of the spacetime is <lb/>evolved using the BSSN formulation of the 3 1 decom-<lb/>position. According to this formulation, the variables to be <lb/>evolved are <lb/>ln=12, ab e ÿ4 ab , K ab K ab , <lb/>A ab e ÿ4 K ab ÿ ab K=3 <lb/>and <lb/>the <lb/>contracted <lb/>Christoffel symbolsÿ a bc ÿ a <lb/>bc , instead of the usual <lb/>ADM variables ab and K ab . The evolution equations for <lb/>these new variables are described in Refs. [21,22]: <lb/>@ t ÿ 1 <lb/>6 K; <lb/>(16)<lb/>@ tab ÿ2Ã ab ; <lb/>(17)<lb/>@ t K ÿ ab D a D b Ã abÃ <lb/>ab 1 <lb/>3 K 2 1 <lb/>2 ÿT t <lb/>t T; <lb/>(18)<lb/>@ tÃab e ÿ4 ÿD a D b R ab ÿ T ab TF<lb/>KÃ ab ÿ 2Ã acÃ <lb/>c <lb/>b ; <lb/>(19) <lb/>@ <lb/>@tÿ <lb/>a ÿ2Ã ab ;b 2 <lb/>ÿ<lb/>a <lb/>bcÃ <lb/>cb ÿ <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>ab K ;b <lb/>ÿ ab T bt 6Ã ab ;b <lb/>ÿ <lb/>@ <lb/>@x b <lb/>cab <lb/>;c ÿ 2 cb a <lb/>;c <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>ab c <lb/>;c <lb/>; (20) <lb/>where D a is the covariant derivative in the spatial hyper-<lb/>surface, T is the trace of the stress-energy tensor (3) and the <lb/>label TF indicates the trace-free part of the quantity in <lb/>brackets. The coupling between the evolution of the BSSN <lb/>variables and the variables describing the evolution of the <lb/>scalar field is first order. That is, Eqs. (15) are solved using <lb/>the method of lines with a modified version of the second <lb/>order iterative Crank-Nicholson (ICN) integrator (see <lb/>Ref. [30]). After a full time step the stress-energy tensor <lb/>in Eq. (3) is calculated and used to solve the BSSN evolu-<lb/>tion equations with an independent evolution loop based on <lb/>the standard second order ICN [31]. <lb/>In order to set up the correct scaled quantities to be <lb/>evolved we use dimensionless variables. For an equilib-<lb/>rium configuration the real scalar field can be expanded in <lb/>a Fourier series of the form r; t <lb/>P j max <lb/>j1 2jÿ1 r <lb/>cos2j ÿ 1!t, where the total central density is 0 <lb/>P j max <lb/>j1 2jÿ1 0. This implies that the stress-energy compo-<lb/>nents given in Eq. (3) also have a periodic time depen-<lb/>dence. The characteristic frequency ! together with the <lb/>mass of the boson m provide the natural dimensionless <lb/>units, <lb/>r code mr=M 2 <lb/>Pl ; <lb/>t code !t; <lb/>code <lb/>4 <lb/>p <lb/>M Pl <lb/>; <lb/>code <lb/>m <lb/>M 2 <lb/>Pl ! <lb/>; <lb/>(21) <lb/>which are the ones used within the present analysis. For <lb/>further code details refer to Ref. [20]. <lb/>B. Slicing condition and convergence tests <lb/>In this section we introduce the slicing condition used <lb/>for our 3D simulations. We base it on the observed dynam-<lb/>ics of the trace of the extrinsic curvature tensor K for <lb/>oscillaton eigenstates, and find that the slicing is accurate <lb/>for evolving spherically symmetric oscillatons with small <lb/>nonradial perturbations. For soliton star eigenstates Kt <lb/>0 K rr t 0 0. However, as time evolves the metric <lb/>function g rr changes with time and consequently K oscil-<lb/>lates periodically, given by <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">NUMERICAL SIMULATIONS OF OSCILLATING SOLITON . . . <lb/>PHYSICAL REVIEW D 77, 024028 (2008) <lb/></note>

			<page>024028-7 <lb/></page>

			<body>K <lb/>ij _ <lb/>ij <lb/>ÿ2 <lb/>rr _ <lb/>rr <lb/>ÿ2 <lb/>X 1 <lb/>j1 <lb/>K 2j sin2jt: <lb/>(22) <lb/>We denote K expanded to order j max as <lb/>K j max <lb/>X <lb/>j max <lb/>j1 <lb/>K 2j sin2jt: <lb/>(23) <lb/>In the case of spherical symmetry with the gauge condition <lb/>provided by polar slicing one can determine K 2j by using <lb/>the Fourier expansion of rr and <lb/>A=C <lb/>p <lb/>from <lb/>Eqs. (10) and (11) in the expression for K [Eq. (22)]. <lb/>One can match the coefficients of sin2jt for each j and <lb/>obtain K 2j in terms of a combination of A 2j and C 2j . The <lb/>first two coefficients K 2 and K 4 are approximately given by <lb/>K 2 A 2 <lb/>C 0 <lb/>A 3 <lb/>0 <lb/>1=2 <lb/>; <lb/>(24) <lb/>K 4 <lb/>A 2 C 2 <lb/>4C 1=2 <lb/>0 A 3=2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2A 4 C 1=2 <lb/>0 <lb/>A 3=2 <lb/>0 <lb/>ÿ <lb/>3A 2 <lb/>2 C 1=2 <lb/>0 <lb/>4A 5=2 <lb/>0 <lb/>: <lb/>(25) <lb/>For 3D simulations we propose to enforce that K take the <lb/>value K j max of Eq. (23), and do so in stable manner. <lb/>Various authors [32] have noted that one can enforce <lb/>maximal slicing _ <lb/>K 0 K in a stable manner by solving <lb/>@K <lb/>@t <lb/>ÿcK; <lb/>(26) <lb/>where c is a positive constant. Analogously, we drive K to <lb/>the expanded K j max for an eigenstate using <lb/>@ <lb/>@t <lb/>K ÿ K j max ÿcK ÿ K j max : <lb/>(27) <lb/>Using the identity <lb/>r 2 ÿ K ab K ab ÿ 4S ÿ <lb/>@K <lb/>@t <lb/>; <lb/>(28) <lb/>where is the energy density and S is the trace of the <lb/>spatial stress tensor, we rewrite Eq. (27) as an elliptic <lb/>equation to solve for the lapse <lb/>r 2 ÿ K ab K ab ÿ 4S <lb/>ÿ <lb/>@K j max <lb/>@t <lb/>cK ÿ K j max : <lb/>(29) <lb/>We refer to the slicing obtained from this gauge condition <lb/>[Eqs. (27) and (29)] as truncated Fourier slicing. <lb/>For the 3D simulations described in this section and the <lb/>subsequent section, we use a ground state oscillating soli-<lb/>ton star with <lb/>1 0 0:20; <lb/>! 0:91 <lb/>m <lb/>M 2 <lb/>Pl <lb/>; <lb/>M 0:57 <lb/>M 2 <lb/>Pl <lb/>m <lb/>; <lb/>R 95 8:8 <lb/>M 2 <lb/>Pl <lb/>m <lb/>; <lb/>(30) <lb/>and we label this as the model S 1 oscillaton for future <lb/>reference. For initial data within the 3D simulations we <lb/>take high resolution 1D spherical data for this model and <lb/>interpolate it onto the 3D Cartesian grid using bspline <lb/>interpolation. All our 3D simulations are performed in <lb/>octant symmetry. <lb/>Figure 6 shows K as a function of r on different time <lb/>slices for a model S 1 soliton star simulated on a 192 3 three-<lb/>dimensional grid with a resolution of x y z <lb/>0:15. This is compared with the 1D result for a r 0:01 <lb/>resolution. The spherically symmetric 1D evolution of K <lb/>for a soliton star eigenstate is a periodic oscillation be-<lb/>tween an upper bounding profile at approximately t =4 <lb/>and a lower bounding profile at t 3=4. The oscillations <lb/>of K are observed to match the expected time dependence <lb/>of Eq. (23) and the agreement between the 1D and 3D <lb/>results is good, indicating the truncated Fourier slicing <lb/>condition is enforced accurately. <lb/>In order to demonstrate the advantages of applying this <lb/>gauge condition, we simulate the same model S 1 star on a <lb/>96 3 grid with x y z 0:30 with truncated <lb/>Fourier slicing and two widely used slicing conditions: <lb/>maximal slicing (K 0) and 1 log slicing (@ t <lb/>ÿ2K). Figure 7 compares the L2-norm of the <lb/>Hamiltonian constraint for these three simulations. It can <lb/>be seen that the Hamiltonian for the truncated Fourier <lb/>slicing is by far the lowest (smaller by approximately a <lb/>factor of 2 than 1 log and maximal slicing) and behaves <lb/>is a stable manner. These three test runs are carried out to a <lb/>time of 4; for longer simulations that study perturbed <lb/>soliton stars we find that the use of the truncated Fourier <lb/>slicing condition is necessary to control the coordinate <lb/>drifting of metric functions to an acceptable tolerance <lb/>and to perform the gravitational wave extraction <lb/>accurately. <lb/>6 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>8 <lb/>1 0 <lb/>1 2 <lb/>1 4 <lb/>r <lb/>-8 <lb/>-6 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>K [x 10 <lb/>-3 <lb/>] <lb/>1D data, ∆r = 0.01 <lb/>t = 3π/4 <lb/>t = 7π/8 <lb/>t = 5π/8 <lb/>t = 3π/8 <lb/>t = π/8 <lb/>t = π/4 <lb/> FIG. 6. The extrinsic curvature K is shown for a model S 1 star <lb/>on different time slices as a function of r. The solid lines <lb/>represent the results obtained from a 1D spherically symmetric <lb/>simulation, while the symbols (filled and empty circles, squares, <lb/>and triangles) are 3D data on the same time slices from a model <lb/>S 1 star simulation on a 192 3 grid with x y z 0:15 <lb/>resolution. Good agreement is observed. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">BALAKRISHNA, BONDARESCU, DAUES, AND BONDARESCU <lb/>PHYSICAL REVIEW D 77, 024028 (2008) <lb/></note>

			<page>024028-8 <lb/></page>

			<body>A further test of the accuracy of the evolution code using <lb/>the truncated Fourier slicing condition is the convergence <lb/>test shown in Fig. 8. Figure 8(a) displays the first oscilla-<lb/>tion of the maximum of the density of the model S 1 star <lb/>converging to the 1D result as the 3D resolution is im-<lb/>proved. We take three different resolutions: 48 3 grid with <lb/>x y z 0:60 resolution, 96 3 grid with x <lb/>y z 0:30 and 192 3 grid with x y z <lb/>0:15 resolution. These are compared to a high resolution <lb/>spherically symmetric simulation (r 0:01) with the 1D <lb/>code. Figure 8(b) shows the convergence of the <lb/>Hamiltonian constraint, which is observed to be approxi-<lb/>mately second order. <lb/>C. Nonradial perturbations of soliton stars and <lb/>waveform extraction <lb/>The focus of this section is the study of small non-<lb/>spherical perturbations applied to spherically symmetric <lb/>soliton stars and the extraction of gravitational waveforms <lb/>for such systems. We first perturb the star by imposing an <lb/>asymmetry in the grid resolution. We simulate the model <lb/>S 1 star using a different resolution in the z-direction than in <lb/>the x and y directions, while keeping the distance from the <lb/>origin to the boundary on each axis the same. Figure 9 <lb/>shows the Zerilli waveform extracted at r 43M 2 <lb/>Pl =m for <lb/>three different resolutions labeled as (1) high resolution for <lb/>x y 0:196, z 0:201 with n x n y 244, <lb/>n z 238, (2) medium resolution for x y 0:294, <lb/>z 0:3015 with n x n y 164, n z 160, and (3) low <lb/>resolution for x y 0:392, z 0:402 with n x <lb/>n y 122, n z 119. The waveforms are observed to have <lb/>the same frequency but different amplitudes. For this series <lb/>of simulations the uneven resolution is itself the perturba-<lb/>tion, and thus the waveform should converge away as the <lb/>resolution is improved. We observe the appropriate second <lb/>t <lb/>2.1 <lb/>2.2 <lb/>2.3 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>2.7 <lb/>ρ <lb/>max [x 10 <lb/>2 <lb/>] <lb/>48 <lb/>3 , ∆x = 0.60 <lb/>96 <lb/>3 , ∆x = 0.30 <lb/>192 <lb/>3 , ∆x = 0.15 <lb/>1D code, ∆r = 0.01 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>t <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>||H|| <lb/>2 [x 10 <lb/>-4 <lb/>] <lb/>48 <lb/>3 , ∆x = 0.60 <lb/>96 <lb/>3 , ∆x = 0.30 <lb/>192 <lb/>3 , ∆x = 0.15 <lb/>FIG. 8. (a) The maximum density of the model S 1 soliton <lb/>star is shown converging to the spherically symmetric 1D result. <lb/>(b) The L2-norm of the Hamiltonian constraint is displayed for <lb/>the three different resolutions. The code is observed to exhibit <lb/>roughly second order convergence. <lb/>35 <lb/>40 <lb/>45 <lb/>50 <lb/>t <lb/>-2.5 <lb/>-2 <lb/>-1.5 <lb/>-1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>L=2, m=0 Zerilli Function [x 10 <lb/>-3 <lb/>] <lb/>Low Resolution <lb/>Medium Resolution <lb/>High Resolution <lb/>FIG. 9. The &apos; 2, m 0 Zerilli function extracted at r 43 <lb/>is shown for a perturbed model S 1 soliton star at different <lb/>resolutions labeled as: High for x y 0:196, z <lb/>0:201 with n x n y 244, n z 238, Medium for x y <lb/>0:294, z 0:3015 with n x n y 164, n z 160, and low <lb/>resolution for x y 0:392, z 0:402 with n x n y <lb/>122, n z 119. The perturbation in this case is the asymmetric <lb/>resolution itself and amplitude of the waveform is seen to <lb/>converge away. The convergence rate is roughly second order. <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>t <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>||H|| <lb/>2 [x 10 <lb/>-4 <lb/>] <lb/>1+log Slicing <lb/>Maximal Slicing <lb/>Truncated Fourier Slicing <lb/>FIG. 7. The L2-norm of the Hamiltonian is displayed as a <lb/>function of time for three slicing conditions: (1) 1 log slicing, <lb/>(2) maximal slicing, and (3) truncated Fourier slicing. The latter <lb/>is clearly smaller and leads to more stable simulations. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">NUMERICAL SIMULATIONS OF OSCILLATING SOLITON . . . <lb/>PHYSICAL REVIEW D 77, 024028 (2008) <lb/></note>

			<page>024028-9 <lb/></page>

			<body>order converge rate, with a factor of 4 difference between <lb/>the waveform amplitudes of the high resolution and the low <lb/>resolution case. Each of the simulations is performed using <lb/>the truncated Fourier slicing condition and is run up to a <lb/>time t 60. <lb/>We next study an oscillating soliton star with a pertur-<lb/>bation applied to the radial metric component g rr of the <lb/>form <lb/>g rr r; ; 20 fr=RY 20 ; g rr r <lb/>(31) <lb/>where 20 is a constant much less than unity and the <lb/>function fr=R r=R p 2 expÿcr 2 . The constants c <lb/>and R p are chosen to localize the perturbation on the star <lb/>and also not perturb the metric functions at the origin. This <lb/>perturbation does not significantly alter the mass of the <lb/>star. We expect that physical perturbations of soliton stars <lb/>can be easily described as linear combinations of spherical <lb/>harmonics. This type of perturbation in the metric may <lb/>mimic the effect that gravitation of another star has on the <lb/>oscillaton. In the current study we simply apply the per-<lb/>turbation of Eq. (31) without resolving the initial data <lb/>problem. This procedure causes the constraints to no lon-<lb/>ger be obeyed and hence makes the perturbation nonphys-<lb/>ical. A more complete treatment that incorporates an initial <lb/>value problem solver that couples a scalar field and metric <lb/>perturbation is the subject of future work. <lb/>We study the effects of a perturbation with 20 10 ÿ4 , <lb/>c 1=16 and R p 5 on a model S 1 soliton star. In <lb/>Fig. 10(a) the &apos; 2, m 0 Zerilli functions extracted at <lb/>a detector radius of r 45M 2 <lb/>Pl =m are shown for three <lb/>different resolutions. The waveforms oscillate through a <lb/>couple of nodes and then damp to zero on a fairly short <lb/>time scale. This is similar to the case of boson stars [15,25] <lb/>and consistent with the expectation that a star with a scalar <lb/>field extending to infinity would have only rapidly damped <lb/>modes [25,26]. The energy emitted in gravitational waves <lb/>[see Fig. 10(b)] is calculated and found to flatten out at <lb/>about 5 10 ÿ5 M 2 <lb/>Pl =m. This suggests that the whole gravi-<lb/>tational waveform has been extracted. <lb/>We now investigate gravitational waveforms using the <lb/>Newman-Penrose scalar 4 for the simulation described <lb/>above. Figure 11 shows r 4 at three different detectors. <lb/>The waveforms are time shifted by the distance in flat <lb/>space between each detector and the last detector to facili-<lb/>tate comparison. The frequencies and amplitudes of the <lb/>waveforms at the three detectors are in good agreement. <lb/>This is consistent with the expected behavior of 4 / 1=r <lb/>in the far wave zone [24]. High frequency oscillations <lb/>appear at late times. They are likely an artifact of the <lb/>numerical discretization. The frequency and amplitude of <lb/>these oscillations are resolution dependent (see inset); <lb/>these data show the amplitude to converge away to second <lb/>order. A more advanced technique such as adaptive mesh <lb/>refinement that provides higher resolution would enable us <lb/>to extend the convergence test to finer grid resolutions. <lb/>35 <lb/>40 <lb/>45 <lb/>50 <lb/>t <lb/>-10 <lb/>-5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>L=2, m=0 Zerilli Function [x 10 <lb/>-4 <lb/>] <lb/>Low Resolution <lb/>Medium Resolution <lb/>High Resolution <lb/>No Perturbation <lb/>40 <lb/>45 <lb/>50 <lb/>t <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>Zerilli Energy [x 10 <lb/>-5 <lb/>] <lb/>FIG. 10. (a) The &apos; 2, m 0 Zerilli function extracted at <lb/>r 45 is shown for a model S 1 soliton star under a Y 20 <lb/>perturbation at three different resolutions: High for x y <lb/>z 0:196 with n x n y n z 244, Medium for x <lb/>y z 0:294 with n x n y n z 164, and low resolu-<lb/>tion for x y z 0:392 with n x n y n z 122. <lb/>The waveforms have roughly the same frequency and amplitude. <lb/>(b) The Zerilli energy is displayed and is observed to flatted out <lb/>on the same time scale as the gravitational wave signal. <lb/>FIG. 11. The Newman-Penrose scalar 4 multiplied by the <lb/>radius at the detector is shown at three different detectors. The <lb/>signals have been time shifted by the distance in flat space <lb/>between detectors to match the last detector. The agreement in <lb/>both frequency and amplitude is good. The inset shows that the <lb/>high frequency oscillations are noise and converge away with <lb/>resolution. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">BALAKRISHNA, BONDARESCU, DAUES, AND BONDARESCU <lb/>PHYSICAL REVIEW D 77, 024028 (2008) <lb/></note>

			<page>024028-10 <lb/></page>

			<body>Within all our 3D simulations we use the L2-norm of the <lb/>Hamiltonian constant as a measure of the error. This is <lb/>typically of the order of a few 10 ÿ5 and below 1 10 ÿ4 <lb/>for all the simulations in this section. <lb/>IV. CONCLUSIONS <lb/>For the first time excited state soliton stars have been <lb/>studied. Excited state configurations have field configura-<lb/>tions characterized by nodes. For a given central field <lb/>density 1 0, these stars are typically larger (greater <lb/>radius) and more massive than corresponding ground state <lb/>stars. We find that their mass profile is similar to that of <lb/>ground state configurations; they have two branches sepa-<lb/>rated at the maximum mass. The branch to the left of this <lb/>maximum is traditionally called the S-branch because <lb/>ground state configurations on this branch are stable to <lb/>radial perturbations in the sense that they migrate to new <lb/>configurations on the same branch. In spite of this similar-<lb/>ity in the mass profile, we find that all excited state con-<lb/>figurations are inherently unstable. Unlike ground state <lb/>configurations, excite state stars on the S-branch do not <lb/>migrate to new configurations on the excited state S-branch <lb/>when perturbed. They can either migrate to the ground <lb/>state if they lose enough mass through scalar radiation or <lb/>collapse to black holes. <lb/>Higher excited state configurations migrate to the <lb/>ground state sometimes cascading through intermediate <lb/>excited states. We show one such migration for a five-<lb/>node excited state star and find the four-node intermediate <lb/>state that it is nearest to during the migration process. <lb/>Studying the stability of excited states is very important <lb/>because they may be intermediate states during the for-<lb/>mation process of soliton stars. <lb/>Also, for the first time, the numerical evolution of <lb/>ground state oscillaton stars is conducted on a full 3D <lb/>grid, allowing the study of nonradial perturbations with <lb/>gravitation waveform extraction. These simulations are <lb/>challenging because soliton stars are very dynamic, with <lb/>no equilibrium configurations having static metric compo-<lb/>nents. In this paper we compare slicing conditions previ-<lb/>ously used for 3D boson star simulations with a new slicing <lb/>condition specifically designed for soliton stars. We find <lb/>that the latter is more accurate and more stable. We see the <lb/>energy density in 3D converging with resolution to that in <lb/>1D for the spherically symmetric case and the highest <lb/>resolution 3D simulation matching the 1D result very <lb/>accurately. <lb/>In 3D we explore two types of nonradial axisymmetric <lb/>perturbations. First, the spherically symmetric 1D eigen-<lb/>state data is interpolated on the 3D grid with an imposed <lb/>asymmetry in the grid resolution x y Þ z. No ex-<lb/>plicit perturbation is applied. This has the advantage that <lb/>the initial data automatically satisfies the Einstein-Klein-<lb/>Gordon equations. However, this perturbation is not easy to <lb/>interpret physically. We successfully extract the Zerilli <lb/>gravitational waveforms for a series of simulations at <lb/>different resolutions and observe the amplitude of the <lb/>signal due to this resolution-based perturbation to converge <lb/>away with improved resolution. The convergence rate is <lb/>approximately second order as expected. A second pertur-<lb/>bation is applied explicitly to the metric function g rr and is <lb/>proportional to the Y 20 spherical harmonic. Both the &apos; 2, <lb/>m 0 Zerilli function and the Newman-Penrose scalar 4 <lb/>are extracted. This perturbation more closely represents a <lb/>physical disturbance of the star and leads to a finite signal <lb/>that does not converge away as in the previous case. The <lb/>waveforms damp rapidly and thus the complete gravita-<lb/>tional waveform could be extracted on a relatively short <lb/>time scale. This is consistent with expectations from per-<lb/>turbation theory for stars that have a scalar field extending <lb/>to infinity such as soliton stars and boson stars [25]. We <lb/>also measure the energy radiated in gravitational waves as <lb/>a function of time and find that it flattens as the signal <lb/>damps out. <lb/>This is an exploratory investigation that is meant as a <lb/>starting point for future work. Possible improvements in-<lb/>clude using an adaptive mesh refinement technique for <lb/>better resolution and finding a more general gauge condi-<lb/>tion that would be applicable to strongly perturbed soliton <lb/>stars. These would enable the study of more advanced <lb/>scenarios involving real fields such as soliton star <lb/>collisions. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>We make extensive use of the Cactus Computational <lb/>Toolkit, and its infrastructure for solving Einstein&apos;s equa-<lb/>tions. The simulations have been performed on the NCSA <lb/>Tungsten cluster under computer allocation TG-<lb/>MCA02N014. We use the bspline package from the GNU <lb/>software library [33] for interpolation of initial data and the <lb/>PETSc solver [34] for solving elliptic equations. We espe-<lb/>cially want to thank Francisco S. Guzman for advice and <lb/>encouragement at the beginning of the project, without <lb/>which this paper would not have been completed. We <lb/>would also like to acknowledge Francisco for developing <lb/>the 3D evolution routine for the scalar field. We thank Peter <lb/>Diener for useful discussions and Ed Seidel and Wai-Mo <lb/>Suen for allowing us to use their 1D scalar field evolution <lb/>code. We are very grateful to Doina Costescu and Cornel <lb/>Costescu for hospitality, support, and discussions during <lb/>R. B.&apos;s stays in Champaign-Urbana. We have received <lb/>partial funding from NSF grants PHY-0652952 and AST-<lb/>0606710, and the Sofja Kovalevskaja Program from the <lb/>Alexander Von Humboldt Foundation. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">NUMERICAL SIMULATIONS OF OSCILLATING SOLITON . . . <lb/>PHYSICAL REVIEW D 77, 024028 (2008) <lb/></note>

			<page>024028-11 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[1] F. Siddhartha Guzman et al., Classical Quantum Gravity <lb/>17, L9 (2000). <lb/>[2] M.-J. Jee, et al., Astrophys. J. 661, 728 (2007). <lb/>[3] D. Clowe, et al., Astrophys. J. 648, L109 (2006). <lb/>[4] E. Seidel and W.-M. Suen, Phys. Rev. Lett. 72, 2516 <lb/>(1994). <lb/>[5] E. Seidel and W.-M. Suen, Phys. Rev. Lett. 66, 1659 <lb/>(1991). <lb/>[6] M. Alcubierre et al., Classical Quantum Gravity 20, 2883 <lb/>(2003). <lb/>[7] M. Campanelli et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 96, 111101 (2006); <lb/>P. Diener et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 96, 121101 (2006); D. <lb/>Pollney et al., Phys. Rev. D 76, 124002 (2007). <lb/>[8] M. A. Scheel et al., Phys. Rev. D 74, 104006 (2006); M. <lb/>Boyle et al., Phys. Rev. D 75, 024006 (2007). <lb/>[9] J. G. Baker et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 99, 181101 (2007); M. <lb/>Boyle et al., Phys. Rev. D 76, 124038 (2007). <lb/>[10] (LIGO scientific collaboration) http://www.ligo.org/. <lb/>[11] The Laser Interferometer Gravitational Wave Observatory <lb/>in the US: http://www.ligo.caltech.edu. <lb/>[12] J. Balakrishna, Ph.D. thesis, Washington University, St. <lb/>Louis, 1999. <lb/>[13] C. Palenzuela et al., Phys. Rev. D 75, 064005 (2007). <lb/>[14] C. Palenzuela et al., arXiv:0706.2435. <lb/>[15] J. Balakrishna, R. Bondarescu, G. Daues, F. S. Guzman, <lb/>and E. Seidel, Classical Quantum Gravity 23, 2631 (2006). <lb/>[16] L. A. Urena-Lopez, Classical Quantum Gravity 19, 2617 <lb/>(2002). <lb/>[17] L. A. Urena-Lopez, T. Matos, and R. Becerril, Classical <lb/>Quantum Gravity 19, 6259 (2002). <lb/>[18] E. Seidel and W.-M. Suen, Phys. Rev. D 42, 384 (1990). <lb/>[19] http://www.cactuscode.org. <lb/>[20] F. S. Guzman, Phys. Rev. D 70, 044033 (2004). <lb/>[21] M. Alcubierre, B. Breugmann, T. Dramlitsch, J. A. Font, P. <lb/>Papadopoulos, E. Seidel, N. Stergioulas, and R. Takahashi, <lb/>Phys. Rev. D 62, 124011 (2000). <lb/>[22] T. W. Baumgarte and S. L. Shapiro, Phys. Rev. D 59, <lb/>024007 (1998); M. Shibata and T. Nakamura, Phys. Rev. <lb/>D 52, 5428 (1995). <lb/>[23] F. J. Zerilli, Phys. Rev. D 2, 2141 (1970); V. Moncrief, <lb/>Ann. Phys. (N.Y.) 88, 323 (1974). <lb/>[24] E. T. Newman and R. Penrose, J. Math. Phys. (N.Y.) 3, 566 <lb/>(1962); R. Penrose, Phys. Rev. Lett. 10, 66 (1963). <lb/>[25] S. Yoshida, Y. Eriguchi, and T. Futamase, Phys. Rev. D 50, <lb/>6235 (1994). <lb/>[26] Similar to the case of boson stars and neutron stars, one <lb/>can construct a toy model for oscillatons in which the star <lb/>and the spacetime are each represented by a semi-infinite <lb/>string fastened at one end. The two strings are connected <lb/>via a massless spring. Since the strings extend to infinity <lb/>the system has no means to store energy and allows only <lb/>strongly damped modes. See Ref. [25] for details on the <lb/>boson star model and Ref. [27] for the description of the <lb/>neutron star case. <lb/>[27] K. D. Kokkotas and B. F. Schutz, Gen. Relativ. Gravit. 18, <lb/>913 (1986). <lb/>[28] J. Balakrishna, E. Seidel, and W.-M. Suen, Phys. Rev. D <lb/>58, 104004 (1998). <lb/>[29] L. Smarr, Ann. N.Y. Acad. Sci. 302, 569 (1977); P. <lb/>Anninos, G. Daues, J. Masso, E. Seidel, and W.-M. <lb/>Suen, Phys. Rev. D 51, 5562 (1995); P. Anninos, K. <lb/>Camarda, J. Masso, E. Seidel, W.-M. Suen, and J. Town, <lb/>Phys. Rev. D 52, 2059 (1995). <lb/>[30] M. Alcubierre, F. S. Guzmán, T. Matos, D. Núñez, L. A. <lb/>Ureña-López, and P. Wiederhold, Classical Quantum <lb/>Gravity 19, 5017 (2002). <lb/>[31] S. Teukolsky, Phys. Rev. D 61, 087501 (2000). <lb/>[32] J. Balakrishna, G. Daues, E. Seidel, W.-M. Suen, M. <lb/>Tobias, and E. Wang, Classical Quantum Gravity 13, <lb/>L135 (1996). <lb/>[33] GNU Scientific Library: http://www.gnu.org/software/gsl/. <lb/>[34] Portable, Extensible Toolkit for Scientific Computation: <lb/>http://www-unix.mcs.anl.gov/petsc/petsc-as/. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">BALAKRISHNA, BONDARESCU, DAUES, AND BONDARESCU <lb/>PHYSICAL REVIEW D 77, 024028 (2008) <lb/></note>

			<page>024028-12 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
