<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>7 th Congress of Baltic Librarians DIVERSITY IN UNITY: BALTIC LIBRARIES IN THE EUROPEAN UNION <lb/>________________________________________________________________________________________________ <lb/>Jurgita Rudžionienė <lb/>Lecturer, Institute of Library and Information Science, <lb/>Faculty of Communication, Vilnius University (Lithuania) <lb/>Ramunė Petuchovaitė <lb/>Lecturer, Institute of Library and Information Science, <lb/>Faculty of Communication, Vilnius University (Lithuania) <lb/>PROFILES OF CONTINUING EDUCATION FOR LIBRARY AND <lb/>INFORMATION SCIENCE SPECIALISTS IN LITHUANIA <lb/>Прoблeмы нeпpepывнoгo библиoтeчнoгo oбучeния и oбpaзoвaния всё чaщe <lb/>нaхoдит мeстo тaк и в лoкaльнoм, тaк и в интepнaциoнaльнoм кoнтeкcтe. B <lb/>мнoгиx cтpaнax и peгиoнax имeeтся нaкoплeнный oпpeдeлeнный oпыт в этoй <lb/>cфepe. Цeль дoклaдa -идeнтификaция и aнaлиз глaвныx пpoфилeй нeпpepывнoгo <lb/>библиoтeчнoгo <lb/>oбучeния нa ocнoвe дeятeльнocти Tpeйнинг Цeнтpa для <lb/>библиoтeчныx paбoтникoв, ocнoвaннoм Инcтитутoм Oткpытoгo Oбщecтвa в <lb/>Будaпeштe (ИOO), нa Фaкультeтe Koммуникaции Bильнюccкoгo унивepcитeтa <lb/>(Литвa). <lb/>The aim of the paper is to identify several profiles of continuing education for LIS <lb/>specialists. It contains different aspects of the matter with the emphasized attention on <lb/>training content and management issues. <lb/></front>

			<body>Prerequisites for CPE and local context <lb/>The widest spectrum of factors has shaped the background for Continuing <lb/>Professional Education (CPE) for library and information workers at Training Centre for <lb/>LIS specialists of Vilnius University Faculty of Communication. It covers forms and <lb/>methods, occurrences and phenomena. The following items took their place in Lithuania: <lb/>1. New requirements raised for libraries, new services, new resources, new <lb/>funding models. <lb/>2. Impact of Open Society Institution (OSI) and OSF-Lithuania Library <lb/>programs 1993-2002: library as community centre. <lb/>3. Library automation. <lb/>4. Public internet access points (PIAPs): Ministry of Culture, Business alliance <lb/>Window to the future, Ministry of Internal Affairs (with Phare support). <lb/>5. EU Structural funds: employability, social inclusion, new (ICT) skills. <lb/>6. Result: huge demand for CPE for LIS specialists as agents of change <lb/>(Glosiene, Petuchovaite, 2003). <lb/></body>

			<page>182 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">7 th Congress of Baltic Librarians DIVERSITY IN UNITY: BALTIC LIBRARIES IN THE EUROPEAN UNION <lb/></note>

			________________________________________________________________________________________________ <lb/>

			<body>Who we are: institutional background. Since 1991 education is provided by the <lb/>newly established Faculty of Communication (FC). The creation of the FC should be <lb/>regarded as a determined effort to start the education of a new generation of <lb/>communication and information professionals. The international dimension of this <lb/>professional area has been especially successfully revealed. Since its foundation, the FC <lb/>has aimed not only at meeting the needs of the emerging information society, but also at <lb/>influencing its development, concentrating on the role of knowledge, on the optimal ways <lb/>of the organization of information, and on designing possible future models of virtual <lb/>organizations. <lb/>Vilnius University (founded at 1547) Faculty of Communication is the leading <lb/>institution of higher education for the widest scope of communication and information <lb/>specialists in Lithuania. Education was provided since 1949. In 1949-1999, almost 4 <lb/>thousands qualified librarians graduated Vilnius University. The mission of the FC is to <lb/>educate professionals who are able to organize and manage information and knowledge <lb/>in the institutions of culture, research, business and/or government, to present the <lb/>information to society, to formulate and implement the policy of information; to conduct <lb/>research in various spheres and aspects of communication and information science. The <lb/>FC strives to carry on as nationally and internationally recognized institution of higher <lb/>education. It cooperates with more than 30 academic partners in Europe and United <lb/>States of America. It is a member of IFLA, ICA, EUCLID, NORDIS-NET, FID, <lb/>European Journalism Training Association, Baltic Association for Media Research, <lb/>INFOBALT Association. <lb/>Fifty years of continuous work in the field of LIS at Vilnius University, recent <lb/>attempts to modernize teaching, learning and research with regard to the highest <lb/>international standards, to integrate the best achievement of the foreign countries create <lb/>new approaches and strategies of education of the professionals for libraries which are <lb/>important tools of democratization and creation of open civic society. <lb/>Professional development: the international dimension <lb/>One can observe continuing process of seeking optimal ways of implementing <lb/>CPE for LIS specialists worldwide. From the 1 st conference of IFLA Continuing <lb/>Professional Education Round Table (CPERT) in 1985, it provided a forum for educators <lb/>and trainers who have an interest in the management and provision of continuing <lb/>professional development activities for librarians and other information professionals. <lb/>Since August 2002 CPERT was reorganized into Continuing Professional Development <lb/>and Workplace Learning Section. In its strategic plan for years 2004-2005 the mission <lb/>and goals find their place. <lb/>The 5 th World Conference on Continuing Professional Education for the Library <lb/>and Information Science Professions, held in August 2002, represented the final activity <lb/>of CPERT as an IFLA Round Table. Transformation the Round Table to the IFLA <lb/>Section for Continuing Professional Development and Workplace Learning was aimed to <lb/>lead to greater visibility within IFLA to issues associated with continuing professional <lb/>development. The forum gave the possibility for the broad theoretical discussions, reports <lb/></body>

			<page>183 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">7 th Congress of Baltic Librarians DIVERSITY IN UNITY: BALTIC LIBRARIES IN THE EUROPEAN UNION <lb/></note>

			________________________________________________________________________________________________ <lb/>

			<body>of research studies, descriptions of &apos;good practice&apos;, case studies, analyses of problems, <lb/>project reports and evaluations, and a state-of-the-art reviews (Clyde, 2003). <lb/>From the OSI Information Program (previous OSI NLP -Network Library <lb/>Program) viewpoint, professional development encompasses knowledge or skills needed <lb/>by those employed in the field of library and information science in order to develop their <lb/>abilities within the discipline (Robinson, 2000) at postgraduate level, many of <lb/>contemporary concepts were not addressed to undergraduate level education which is <lb/>undertook by workers some years ago -it does not aim to cover issues which are included <lb/>in most undergraduate courses. In this case professional education has the right place. <lb/>OSI (Open Society Institute, Information Program) Training Center <lb/>Initiative <lb/>The Training Center Initiative (OSI Information program), established in 1999 <lb/>has the aim was to promote modern, service-oriented libraries throughout Central and <lb/>East Europe and post soviet area, via strategic approach to professional development of <lb/>library and information staff. It aimed to achieve this stimulating continuing education <lb/>activities both on national level (19 Centers have received direct OSI funding, <lb/>methodological development) and on international level, covering the region including <lb/>Central and East Europe states (Hungary, Czech Republic, Slovenia, Lithuania) and post <lb/>soviet area (Ukraine, Moldova, Georgia, Kazachstan, Kirgyzstan) and Mongolia. Each of <lb/>these countries host a single center. An individual center may comprise several <lb/>cooperating organizations or institutions. The Training Center initiative was conceived to <lb/>create a network of independent centers for CPE of LIS professionals in countries <lb/>throughout the regions. Funding was planned for one or two years, after which centers <lb/>were expected to continue on a self-financing basis (Training Centers Network, 2002). <lb/>Training Center (TC) for LIS Specialists at Vilnius University <lb/>Extension training organizational model was chosen and carried out at Vilnius <lb/>University Faculty of Communication (VU FC): VU TC for LIS Specialists is a coalition <lb/>of the main players in the field concerning the content. It integrates the resources, <lb/>competencies and strengths of the partners. Institutionally TC is an unit of Vilnius <lb/>University Faculty of Communication -satellite of Library and Information Science <lb/>Institute. Main sources of funding are project funds and fees of course participants. Main <lb/>funds came from international projects: <lb/>• Open Society Institute-Budapest (OSI) support, 1999-2002, <lb/>• EC Leonardo da Vinci DELCIS project 2000-2002, <lb/>• EC Phare 2001 project Bibliotemlink, 2003-2004. <lb/>In the landscape of CPE for LIS specialists in Lithuania actually appear some <lb/>more self-dependent players: Lithuanian Cultural Administrators Training Center <lb/>(LCATC) -it covers employees from cultural institutions: museums, cultural centers <lb/></body>

			<page>184 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">7 th Congress of Baltic Librarians DIVERSITY IN UNITY: BALTIC LIBRARIES IN THE EUROPEAN UNION <lb/></note>

			________________________________________________________________________________________________ <lb/>

			<body>mostly, and public libraries; National M. Mazvydas Library of Lithuania (NLL) training <lb/>activities are addressed to public librarians too, and Pedagogical Professional Training <lb/>Center (it offers CPE only for school librarians). All of them are state financing, and this <lb/>is significant difference from VU TC. It is not made an attempt to discuss their input in <lb/>CPE in Lithuania in this paper (e.g. LCATC and NLL). <lb/>The objective of the TC for LIS Specialists at Vilnius University is to organize <lb/>continuing professional training in the field and to serve the training needs of the library <lb/>and information specialists of all types. It is aimed to achieve improvement the <lb/>institutional and continuing professional education of librarians, and bring them closer to <lb/>users through a networked cooperation. <lb/>The main players and partners during the period of 1999-2004 are: National M. <lb/>Mazvydas Library of Lithuania, Klaipeda University Library, Vilnius County A. <lb/>Mickevicius Public Library, Vilnius Central Public Library, Lithuanian Librarian&apos;s <lb/>Association, Lithuanian Cultural Administrators Training Center, SME Baltic Computer <lb/>Academy (MicroLink Netcoms). <lb/>Experiencing shift from training the individual to meeting organizational <lb/>objectives TC is expected to serve customers well. Scheme and model of Lithuanian <lb/>perception and case of CPE of library and information workers at the TC is analyzed <lb/>from the approach of several profiles: content profile (curriculum development and <lb/>training strategies and methods), organizational/managerial profile, marketing and <lb/>promotion. <lb/>Content profile <lb/>1. Curriculum development. TC training curriculum tends to maximum flexibility <lb/>according to: <lb/>• requirements for information society, <lb/>• needs of LIS specialists. <lb/>This was reached by offering 3 training curricula during 4 years. Each curriculum <lb/>insize/volume is 400-484 hours. The training at TC is implemented in modular way. Each <lb/>of these curriculum was offered twice per year. The core elements of the training <lb/>curricula should be in constant correlation with the main elements of the market and <lb/>should response current and future needs of specialists. Core elements of the perfect <lb/>curriculum, according to L. Robinson, should be: <lb/>1. The information environment and information policy. <lb/>2. Information generation, communication and use. <lb/>3. Assessing information needs and designing responsive services. <lb/>4. The information transfer process. <lb/>5. Organization and retrieval of information. <lb/>6. Research, analysis and interpretation of information. <lb/></body>

			<page>185 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">7 th Congress of Baltic Librarians DIVERSITY IN UNITY: BALTIC LIBRARIES IN THE EUROPEAN UNION <lb/></note>

			________________________________________________________________________________________________ <lb/>

			<body>7. Applications of information and communication technologies to <lb/>library and information products and services. <lb/>8. Information resource management and knowledge management. <lb/>9. Management of information agencies. <lb/>10. Quantitative and qualitative evaluation of outcomes of information <lb/>and library use (Robinson, 2000). <lb/>Most of these elements are adapted and elaborated in each of 9 class-training <lb/>modules and 3 distance-training courses, which cover basic computer skills, internet <lb/>based information services, Web page design, computer competencies (ECDL), <lb/>integrated library systems, library in information society, library and information center <lb/>management, bibliographic control, legislation and regulations for library services, <lb/>managing change in libraries, digital library community services, EU library and <lb/>information policy, psychology of communication and management etc. The length of <lb/>each module is 24-40 hours. The key principle of the training module is constant <lb/>migration of training curriculum content and forms (Glosiene, Petuchovaite, 2003). <lb/>2. Training strategies and methods. Typically, when conducting educational <lb/>programs, instructors often identify a set of program learning expectations, as well as a <lb/>set of active-like and passive-like teaching techniques, such as case studies, individual <lb/>research projects, group projects, classroom discussions, lectures by instructor, guest <lb/>speakers, videos shown in class, classroom presentations by students, computerized <lb/>learning assignments, which they believe best help accomplish the learning expectations. <lb/>(Rodrigues, 2004). <lb/>Organizational/managerial profile <lb/>It is extremely complicated profile, required ability to balance and well planned <lb/>schedule of various activities of training. Its successful implementation assures equal and <lb/>effective flow of all planned and necessary activities both financial and technical. 10 core <lb/>elements can be identified in the process of implementation of CPE activities via TC as <lb/>umbrella organization, covering several partner institutions and other bodies necessary <lb/>involved for the implementation of CPE content. Those institutions or bodies are internal <lb/>and external. Day-to-day mutual contacts are maintained between TC and each of 10 core <lb/>elements, and impact in play-back direction is constantly made to the TC activity result <lb/>from each of these core elements (see figure 1). Those elements could be considered as <lb/>different levels too. Actually the communication between TC, as one side, and other <lb/>segments, as another side, is going on at least at two levels/ways parallelly: <lb/>• vertical level (according to waterfall model), <lb/>• horizontal level (each element individually with CPE, and vice versa). <lb/></body>

			<page>186 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">7 th Congress of Baltic Librarians DIVERSITY IN UNITY: BALTIC LIBRARIES IN THE EUROPEAN UNION <lb/></note>

			________________________________________________________________________________________________ <lb/>

			<body>Figure 1. Core elements / levels of CPE content realization <lb/>CPE for LIS Specialists <lb/>at Faculty of Communication, <lb/>Vilnius University <lb/>International <lb/>dimension / Inter-state cooperation <lb/>Local dimension / State CPE strategy <lb/>Financial <lb/>organizations/bodies/sources/funds <lb/>TC partner institutions <lb/>(libraries, universities, SME) <lb/>Marketing and promotion institutions <lb/>Trainees <lb/>TC pedagogical personal / lecturers (local, from <lb/>other partner institutions, external experts, guest <lb/>speakers) <lb/>CPE administration <lb/>(TC coordinator, vicecoordinator, finance <lb/>specialist, computer specialists) <lb/>Faculty administration <lb/>University administration <lb/>(rector&apos;s office, finance/accounting <lb/>department) <lb/>Marketing and promotion profile <lb/>After the process of undergoing of marketing mix 7 P of CPE at TC : prelude, <lb/>product, publics, price, place, promotion, postlude, main elements of SWOT analysis <lb/>could be identified. Main strengths of CPE for LIS specialists at TC are infrastructure, <lb/>professional cooperation both local, national and international, corps of qualified <lb/>lecturers, flexible and actual curriculum, need for training, ability for TC management. <lb/>Threats: lack of state support, lack of understanding at national level, low salaries. <lb/>Main lessons and results: quantitative versus qualitative? <lb/>Quantitative results of the 4 years activity of TC are: <lb/>1. Almost 25 percent of all Lithuanian librarians received training at TC (1.664 <lb/>participants). <lb/></body>

			<page>187 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">7 th Congress of Baltic Librarians DIVERSITY IN UNITY: BALTIC LIBRARIES IN THE EUROPEAN UNION <lb/></note>

			________________________________________________________________________________________________ <lb/>

			<body>2. Training courses duration -171 weeks (3,5 years non-stop during 4 years <lb/>period). <lb/>3. More than 10 TC lecturers were involved into OSI Network Teaching <lb/>Program -they conducted training courses in Kirgyzstan, Kazachstan, <lb/>Moldova, Georgia, Azerbaijan, Mongolia during years 2002-2003. <lb/>It is obviously, that amount and quality and up-to-date training is an important <lb/>precursor for organizations -libraries, archives, museums who wish to improve their <lb/>productivity and to survive in the competitive climate by offering high quality services. <lb/>Discussed model is the flexible establishment of lifelong learning idea. It is universal, as <lb/>the main principles and rules of CPE are elaborated. It has all necessary prerequisites for <lb/>implementation of the idea of lifelong learning. The most serious lack and obstacle -lack <lb/>of CPE policy at Vilnius University still as well as adequate Lithuanian state policy in the <lb/>field. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Clyde L. A. Continuing Professional Education for the Information Society. In: IFLA Journal, vol. 29, <lb/>No1, 2003. P. 18-23. <lb/>2. Continuing Professional Development and Workplace Learning Section [interactive]. International <lb/>Federation of Library Associations and Institutions, March 15, 2004. [žiūrėta 2004 m. kovo 21 d.]. <lb/>http://www.ifla.org/VII/s43/annual/sp43-04.htm <lb/>3. Evans S., Gonzalez J. et all. Whose capital is it? Trends in human capital. In: Ivey Business Journal, <lb/>January-February, 2000. P. 30-37. <lb/>4. Glosiene A., Petuchovaite R. CPE for the information competent society. The future of LIS education <lb/>and professional development: OSI-Budapest Information Program Meeting, November 12-16, 2003, <lb/>London City University (UK). <lb/>5. Gorman G. A. Social exclusion -do collections matter? In: Library collection development and <lb/>management. January, 2004. [interactive]. http://masetto.emeraldinsight.com <lb/>6. Lawson K. Savery, J., Luks A.. Does training influence outcomes of organizations? Some Australian <lb/>evidence. In: Journal of Management Development, vol. 23, No. 2, 2004, p. 119-123. <lb/>7. Layzell W. P. (Ed.) Continuing Professional Education for the Information Society: The Fifth World <lb/>Conference on Continuing Professional Education for the Library and Information Profession. <lb/>München: K G Saur, 2002. 316 p. <lb/>8. Open Society Institute Information Program: Content, tools and networks for open society. Strategy <lb/>2001-2002. Budapest, March 2001.23 p. <lb/>9. Robinson L. NLP Training Centre Initiative: Curriculum for Professional Development: 1st draft for <lb/>discussion. NLP Training Centre Initiative, Budapest, 2000. 11 p. <lb/>9a. Robinson L. OSI Information Program, Training Centers Initiative: Report. June <lb/>Meeting, July 13-14 , 2002, National Szechenyj Library, Budapest (Hungary). 9 p. <lb/>10. Rodrigues Carl A. The importance level of ten teaching/learning techniques as rated by university <lb/>business students and instructors. In: Journal of Management Development, vol. 23, No. 2, 2004, p. <lb/>169-182. <lb/>11. Skills for knowledge management: building a knowledge economy: A report by TFPL Ltd.London, <lb/>1999. 120 p. <lb/>12. Training Centers Network for continuing professional development of library and information <lb/>workers [interactive]. Open Society Institute-Budapest (OSI), 2002. http://www.tcnlis.org <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>188 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
