<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Short Communications <lb/>DOI: 10.1002/zaac.200700528 <lb/>Crystal Structure and Disorder Phenomena of the Adduct of Neutral C 60 and <lb/>the Ionic Gold Complex (Ptol 3 ) 2 AuNO 3 <lb/>Martin Schulz-Dobrick and Martin Jansen* <lb/>Stuttgart, Max Planck Institute for Solid State Research, Germany <lb/>Received November 26th, 2007. <lb/>Abstract. The adduct C 60 • (Ptol 3 ) 2 AuNO 3 has been crystallized <lb/>from toluene solutions of C 60 and (Ptol 3 ) 2 AuNO 3 as violet, trigonal <lb/>plate-shaped crystals. The compound was studied by single-crystal <lb/>x-ray diffraction (P31c, a ϭ 1278.17(3), c ϭ 2282.92(6) pm). The <lb/>gold complex is dissociated into [(Ptol 3 ) 2 Au] ϩ cations, which <lb/>encapsulate the neutral C 60 molecules, and nitrate anions. The in-<lb/>termolecular interactions between the fullerene molecules and the <lb/></front>

			<body>Since the discovery of fullerenes [1] and their interesting electronic <lb/>and magnetic properties [2, 3], there has also been a considerable <lb/>interest in their supramolecular chemistry. Due to their electron <lb/>accepting properties, fullerenes interact and form co-crystals with <lb/>electron donor molecules that can adapt to the spherical shape of <lb/>the fullerenes. Examples include porphyrins, calixarenes and <lb/>molecules with aromatic donors [4Ϫ8]. The crystal chemistry of <lb/>C 60 and its co-crystals has been recently reviewed [9, 10]. <lb/> The adaption to the spherical shape of the C 60 molecules may be <lb/>either realized by molecules with concave surfaces or the organiz-<lb/>ation of small donors into networks of concave shape. Depending <lb/>on the flexibility of the molecules or the networks, respectively, a <lb/>structure with optimal donor-acceptor interaction is possible. For <lb/>example phenol as a co-crystallizing agent is able to form highly <lb/>flexible supramolecular arrangements, which can encapsulate <lb/>fullerene molecules to form well-ordered compounds [11, 12]. In <lb/>this work, the synthesis and crystal structure of the adduct of neu-<lb/>tral C 60 with an ionic compound, the gold complex (Ptol 3 ) 2 AuNO 3 <lb/>(tol: tolyl, -C 6 H 4 CH 3 ), is described and analyzed with respect to <lb/>the encapsulation and ordering of the fullerene molecules. <lb/>Results and Discussion <lb/>C 60 • (Ptol 3 ) 2 AuNO 3 precipitates from a solution of C 60 and <lb/>(Ptol 3 ) 2 AuNO 3 in toluene as violet, trigonal plate-shaped crystals. <lb/>The compound, once formed, is insoluble in toluene, which <lb/>accounts for a relatively high stability of the adduct. Growing <lb/>C 60 • (Ptol 3 ) 2 AuNO 3 from a rather diluted solution leads to larger <lb/>* Prof. Dr. Dr. h.c. M. Jansen <lb/>Max-Planck-Institut für Festkörperforschung <lb/>Heisenbergstraße 1 <lb/>D-70569 Stuttgart <lb/>Tel.: 0711/689-1500 <lb/>Fax: 0711/689-1502 <lb/>e-mail: M.Jansen@fkf.mpg.de <lb/></body>

			<front>Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem. 2008, 634, 817Ϫ819 <lb/> © 2008 WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/> 817 <lb/> gold complex cations and the resulting disorder is investigated. The <lb/>crystal structure of C 60 • (Ptol 3 ) 2 AuNO 3 is providing an instructive <lb/>example, demonstrating that symmetry-matching is not always <lb/>sufficient for avoiding disorder. <lb/>Keywords: Fullerenes; Gold; Co-crystals; Solid-state structures; <lb/>Supramolecular chemistry; Crystal engineering <lb/></front>

			<body>and less intergrown crystals. The crystal structure was determined <lb/>by single crystal x-ray diffraction. <lb/>C 60 • (Ptol 3 ) 2 AuNO 3 crystallizes with trigonal symmetry and two <lb/>formula units in the unit cell. The gold complex is dissociated into <lb/>the linear [(Ptol 3 ) 2 Au] ϩ cation and the nitrate anion. In the crystal <lb/>structure, the cations are forming strands along [001] with the <lb/>supramolecular motif of sixfold phenyl embraces [13], i.e. six <lb/>C-H/π interactions between the tolyl-rings (see figure 1b). These <lb/>strands are in a hexagonal arrangement, as depicted in figure 1c. <lb/>In every hexagonal layer of the [(Ptol 3 ) 2 Au] ϩ cations, there are two <lb/>different kinds of voids. The small voids are occupied by the nitrate <lb/>ions and the large voids are occupied by the fullerene molecules. <lb/>In consecutive layers, the position of the small and large voids in-<lb/>terchange, as the [(Ptol 3 ) 2 Au] ϩ cations in are rotated by 60°. The <lb/>nitrate anions are disordered over several orientations, which could <lb/>not be resolved unambiguously. <lb/>The center of the C 60 molecule resides on the special position (2c, <lb/>2/3, 1/3, 3/4) with site symmetry 3.2. The molecule was found to <lb/>be disordered over two orientations, which are related by the crys-<lb/>tallographic twofold axes (figure 1a). All split positions could be <lb/>refined individually. It is interesting to ask why the C 60 molecule is <lb/>disordered, because the site symmetry of the void (3.2), which is <lb/>formed by the [(Ptol 3 ) 2 Au] ϩ cations, is a subgroup of the icosahed-<lb/>ral symmetry of C 60 . Thus, the C 60 molecule could in principle <lb/>be ordered in the crystal structure, but this unique orientation is <lb/>obviously not energetically favored. In order to further investigate <lb/>this phenomenon, an ordered model was constructed by rotating <lb/>the C 60 molecule until the crystallographic and the molecular two-<lb/>fold axes match and then the interaction with the surrounding tolyl <lb/>rings in the disordered and ordered model was examined. In the <lb/>resulting orientation, each fullerene is interacting with six tolyl <lb/>rings via π-π interactions and six additional tolyl rings via C-H/π <lb/>interactions. All of the six respective interactions are crystallo-<lb/>graphically equivalent, c.f. figure 2. In the disordered model, as <lb/>found experimentally, the hydrogen atom involved in the C-H/π <lb/>interaction points towards the center a hexagon and the border of <lb/>hexagon, respectively. In other words, every C 60 molecule is coordi-<lb/>nated by three hydrogen atoms pointing towards the center and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">M. Schulz-Dobrick, M. Jansen <lb/></note>

			<body>three hydrogen atoms pointing towards the border of a hexagon. <lb/>In the constructed, ordered model all hydrogen atoms are pointing <lb/>towards a 5:6 ring junction. The C-H/π interaction with the hexa-<lb/>gons is more favorable than with the pentagons, as the electron <lb/>density in the pentagons is lower [14]. Therefore, the overall C-H/ <lb/>π interactions seem to be more efficient with the C 60 molecule in <lb/>the position of the disordered model compared to the ordered one. <lb/>The same conclusions can be drawn by looking at the π-π interac-<lb/>tions (figure 2c and d). According to the Hunter-Sanders rules [15], <lb/>the most favorable interaction should be between the π-electrons <lb/>of the tolyl-rings and the electron-poor 5:6 bonds of C 60 . In the <lb/>hypothetical ordered model, the tolyl-rings cover two 5:6 bonds <lb/>and two 6:6 bonds. In the disordered model, half of the tolyl-rings <lb/>cover two 5:6 bonds and two 6:6 bonds as well. The other half <lb/>covers four 5:6 bonds, so that this orientation of the C 60 molecule <lb/>should be slightly favored. <lb/>Figure 1 a) The two orientations of C 60 are depicted in green and <lb/>red. The view is along [1Ϫ10], which is parallel to the crystallo-<lb/>graphic twofold axis that is marked by the blue circle and relates <lb/>the two orientations. b) Visualization of the strands along [001] of <lb/>the [(Ptol 3 ) 2 Au] ϩ cations. c) Projection of the crystal structure <lb/>along [001]. Purple: P, blue: N, red: O. <lb/>By the inspection of both, the C-H/π and the π-π interactions, it is <lb/>plausible that the orientation of the C 60 molecule of the disordered <lb/>model is preferred over the orientation in the ordered model. The <lb/>occurrence of the disorder is inevitable as there are two crystallo-<lb/>graphically equivalent orientations. The crystal structure of <lb/>C 60 • (Ptol 3 ) 2 AuNO 3 is an instructive example, demonstrating that <lb/>symmetry-matching is not always sufficient for avoiding disorder. <lb/>Figure 3 shows a comparison between the experimental and calcu-<lb/>lated powder x-ray diffractograms of C 60 • (Ptol 3 ) 2 AuNO 3 , which <lb/>approves the structural model and the purity of the synthesized <lb/>bulk sample. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">www.zaac.wiley-vch.de <lb/> © 2008 WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem. 2008, 817Ϫ819 <lb/></note>

			<page>818 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 2 Visualization of the C-H/π contacts (a and b) and π-π <lb/>contacts (c and d) between the phenyl ligands and the fullerene <lb/>molecules of the disordered (a and c) and the hypothetical, ordered <lb/>model (b and d). The dark blue ball represent the hydrogen atom <lb/>of the C-H/π contact. All projections are parallel to the shortest <lb/>distances between the fullerenes and the hydrogen atom or the π-<lb/>system, respectively. <lb/>Figure 3 Comparison of the experimental and calculated x-ray <lb/>diffractograms. The experimental room temperature cell parame-<lb/>ters were used in the calculated pattern. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>The fullerene adduct C 60 • (Ptol 3 ) 2 AuNO 3 has been synthesized as <lb/>a single phase. In the crystal structure, the C 60 molecule is dis-<lb/>ordered over two orientations, although the symmetry of C 60 and <lb/>its specific crystal environment would allow for adopting a unique <lb/>orientation. The reason for the disorder was found in the coordi-<lb/>nation to the surrounding tolyl-rings and the enhanced C-H/π and <lb/>π-π interactions present in the disordered model. <lb/> The Adduct of Neutral C 60 and the Ionic Gold Complex (Ptol 3 ) 2 AuNO 3 <lb/> Table 1 Data collection and structure determination parameters <lb/>for C 60 • (Ptol 3 ) 2 AuNO 3 . <lb/>Crystal data <lb/>formula <lb/>AuP 2 C 102 H 42 NO 3 <lb/>formula weight / g • mol Ϫ1 <lb/>1584.90 <lb/>crystal size / mm <lb/>0.3 x 0.1 x 0.05 <lb/>crystal system <lb/>trigonal <lb/>space group, Z <lb/>P31c, 2 <lb/>lattice constants a / Å <lb/>12.5467(18) <lb/>c / Å <lb/>22.929(5) <lb/>unit cell volume V /Å 3 <lb/>3126.0(9) <lb/>calc. density d / g•cm Ϫ3 <lb/>1.684 <lb/>absorption coeff μ / mm Ϫ1 <lb/>2.472 <lb/>Data collection <lb/>diffractometer <lb/>AXS Bruker, Smart APEX <lb/>radiation <lb/>MoKα, (0.7103 Å ) <lb/>scan mode <lb/>ω-scan <lb/>temperature / K <lb/>100 <lb/>range /°1.78 Յ θ Յ 35.18 <lb/>measured reflections <lb/>48286 <lb/>unique reflections <lb/>4488 <lb/>absorption correction <lb/>empirical (SADABS) <lb/>Structure solution and refinement <lb/>structure solution <lb/>Patterson, Shelx-97 <lb/>refinement <lb/>refinement details given in <lb/>Experimental Part <lb/>number of parameters <lb/>230 <lb/>R1 (all), R1 (Fo&gt;4σ(Fo)) <lb/>0.0440, 0.0338 <lb/>wR2 (all) <lb/>0.0908 <lb/>GooF <lb/>1.116 <lb/>Experimental Part <lb/>C 60 (0.011 mmol), Ptol 3 AuNO 3 (0.016 mmol) and Ptol 3 <lb/>(0.018 mmol) were dissolved in toluene (50 ml). The solvent was <lb/>evaporated slowly over the period of one week. During this time, <lb/>violet, plate-shaped crystals had formed. The supernatant solution <lb/>was removed and the crystals were washed with acetone. Single <lb/>crystals were mounted on glass capillaries for single crystal x-ray <lb/>measurements at 100 K. A powder x-ray measurement was per-<lb/>formed on a Stoe PSD diffractometer using Cu-Kα-radiation. <lb/>Room temperature unit cell parameters were determined by the Le <lb/>Bail-method: a ϭ 12.7817(3) Å , c ϭ 22.8292(6) Å , R p ϭ 0.044. The <lb/>IR spectrum (KBr pellet) can be attributed to the constituting spec-<lb/>ies. C 60 : 1428w, 1182w, 579w, 527m, NO 3 <lb/>Ϫ : 1333s, (Ptol 3 ) 2 Au ϩ : <lb/>1549m, 1496m, 1444w, 1397w, 1384w, 1308m, 1262w, 1190w, 1102s, <lb/>1017w, 848w, 813s, 731w, 707w, 649m, 615m, 508s (in cm Ϫ1 ). <lb/>The crystal structure was solved by the Patterson method and sub-<lb/>sequent difference fourier maps and refined on F 2 (Shelxtl). The <lb/>fullerene molecules are disordered over two orientations. All split-<lb/>positions have been refined individually without restraints. All <lb/>non-hydrogen atoms were refined with anisotropic displacement <lb/>parameters. Hydrogen positions were calculated using the HFIX <lb/>command. The oxygen atoms of the nitrate ion were found to be <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem. 2008, 817Ϫ819 <lb/>© 2008 WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>www.zaac.wiley-vch.de <lb/></note>

			<page>819 <lb/></page>

			<body>disordered over 5 different positions (2 crystallographic sites) and <lb/>refined with isotropic parameters. Table 1 contains further details <lb/>of the refinement. <lb/>CCDC 668341 contains the supplementary crystallographic data <lb/>for this paper. These data can be obtained free of charge from The <lb/>Cambridge Crystallographic Data Centre via www.ccdc.cam.ac.uk/ <lb/>data request/cif. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgement. The authors would like to thank Alexandra <lb/>Müller for preparative assistance, Dr. Jürgen Nuss for single-crystal <lb/>measurements and the Fonds der Chemischen Industrie for a <lb/>scholarship. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>[1] H. W. Kroto, J. R. Heath, S. C. Obrien, R. F. Curl, R. E. <lb/>Smalley, Nature 1985, 318, 162Ϫ163. <lb/>[2] A. F. Hebard, M. J. Rosseinsky, R. C. Haddon, D. W. Murphy, <lb/>S. H. Glarum, T. T. M. Palstra, A. P. Ramirez, A. R. Kortan, <lb/>Nature 1991, 350, 600Ϫ601. <lb/>[3] P. W. Stephens, D. Cox, J. W. Lauher, L. Mihaly, J. B. Wiley, <lb/>P. M. Allemand, A. Hirsch, K. Holczer, Q. Li, J. D. Thomp-<lb/>son, F. Wudl, Nature 1992, 355, 331Ϫ332. <lb/>[4] D. V. Konarev, I. S. Neretin, Y. L. Slovokhotov, E. I. Yud-<lb/>anova, N. V. Drichko, Y. M. Shul&apos;ga, B. P. Tarasov, L. L. Gum-<lb/>anov, A. S. Batsanov, J. A. K. Howard, R. N. Lyubovskaya, <lb/>Chem. Eur. J. 2001, 7, 2605Ϫ2616. <lb/>[5] M. M. Olmstead, D. A. Costa, K. Maitra, B. C. Noll, S. L. <lb/>Philipps, P. M. Van Calcar, A. L. Balch, J. Am. Chem. Soc. <lb/>1999, 121, 7090Ϫ7097. <lb/>[6] J. L. Atwood, L. J. Barbour, M. W. Heaven, C. L. Raston, <lb/>Angew. Chem. 2003, 115, 3376Ϫ3379, Angew. Chem., Int. Ed. <lb/>2003, 42, 3254Ϫ3257. <lb/>[7] A. L. Litvinov, D. V. Konarev, A. Y. Kovalevsky, I. S. Neretin, <lb/>Y. L. Slovokhotov, P. Coppens, R. N. Lyubovskaya, Crys-<lb/>tengcomm 2002, 618Ϫ622. <lb/>[8] G. Waidmann, M. Jansen, Z. Naturforsch. 1998, 53b, <lb/>161Ϫ164. <lb/>[9] M. Makha, A. Purich, C. L. Raston, A. N. Sobolev, Eur. J. <lb/>Inorg. Chem. 2006, 507Ϫ517. <lb/>[10] I. S. Neretin, Y. L. Slovokhotov, Russ. Chem. Rev. 2004, 73, <lb/>455Ϫ468. <lb/>[11] M. Schulz-Dobrick, M. Panthöfer, M. Jansen, Eur. J. Inorg. <lb/>Chem. 2005, 4064Ϫ4069. <lb/>[12] M. Schulz-Dobrick, M. Panthöfer, M. Jansen, Crystengcomm <lb/>2006, 8, 163Ϫ166. <lb/>[13] I. Dance, M. Scudder, J. Chem. Soc., Dalton Trans. 2000, 10, <lb/>1579Ϫ1585. <lb/>[14] H. Suezawa, T. Yoshida, S. Ishihara, Y. Umezawa, M. Nishio, <lb/>Crystengcomm 2003, 5, 514Ϫ518. <lb/>[15] C. A. Hunter, J. K. M. Sanders, J. Am. Chem. Soc. 1990, <lb/>112, 5525Ϫ5534. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
