<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>DOI: 10.1002/zaac.200700527 <lb/>Synthesis and Structure of the Novel Pentaselenidohexaarsenate(I,II) Cluster <lb/>Anion [As 6 Se 5 ] 2؊ <lb/>Anna Kromm and William S. Sheldrick* <lb/>Bochum, Lehrstuhl für Analytische Chemie der Ruhr-Universität Bochum <lb/>Received November 26 th , 2007. <lb/>Abstract. Methanolothermal reaction of [MnCl 3 (9-ane-N 3 )] with <lb/>As 2 Se 3 at 150°C in the presence of Cs 2 CO 3 affords violet-coloured <lb/>[Mn(9-ane-N 3 ) 2 ]As 6 Se 5 (1). Its novel tricyclic selenidoarsenate(I,II) <lb/>anion [As 6 Se 5 ] 2Ϫ contains two five-membered [As 3 As(Se)Se] rings <lb/>that are symmetry-related by a crystallographic C 2 axis passing <lb/>through the common As I -As I bond between their respective first <lb/></front>

			<body>A variety of discrete multinuclear chalcogenidoarsenate and -anti-<lb/>monate anions containing trivalent arsenic or antimony atoms have <lb/>been isolated from solvothermal solutions in the presence of large <lb/>counter cations [1Ϫ3]. For instance, corner-sharing condensation <lb/>of pyramidal [AE 3 ] 3Ϫ anions (A ϭ As, Sb; E ϭ S, Se) can lead to <lb/>the formation of cyclic chalcogenidometalate(III) anions <lb/>[{AE 2 } n ] nϪ , for which examples are known with n ϭ 2 (A ϭ As, <lb/>E ϭ S [4]; A ϭ Sb, E ϭ S [5], Se [4]), n ϭ 3 (A ϭ As, E ϭ S [6, <lb/>7], Se [8, 9]; A ϭ Sb, E ϭ S [10]) and n ϭ 4 (A ϭ As, E ϭ Se [11]; <lb/>A ϭ Sb, E ϭ S [12]). Corner-sharing has also been reported for <lb/>dinuclear anions (A ϭ As, Sb; E ϭ S, Se) of the type [A 2 E 5 ] 4Ϫ in <lb/>complexes [M(en) 3 ] 2 A 2 E 5 (M ϭ Mn, Fe, Ni [13Ϫ17]; en ϭ ethylene-<lb/>diamine) and for the linear tetranuclear [Sb 4 Se 9 ] 6Ϫ anion in <lb/>Cs 6 Sb 4 Se 9 • 0.5H 2 O [18]. <lb/>Cluster anions containing both A-E-A linkages and direct A-A <lb/>bonds have been characterized for species containing 4, 7 and <lb/>10Ϫ12 arsenic atoms, and 4 and 6 antimony atoms. The ubiquitous <lb/>bicyclic [A 4 E 6 ] 2Ϫ anions (A ϭ As, Sb; E ϭ S, Se) [3, 19Ϫ21] can <lb/>be regarded as being derived from a realgar-like A 4 E 4 structure by <lb/>addition of chalcogenide anions at two opposite A atoms in the <lb/>A 4 E 4 basket and concomitant cleavage of their transannular A-A <lb/>bond. In the related [Sb 6 S 6 ] 2Ϫ anion of (PPh 4 ) 2 Sb 6 S 6 [21], the re-<lb/>maining transannular bond of the bicyclic [Sb 4 S 6 ] 2Ϫ anion is re-<lb/>placed by an Sb 4 rectangle. Cyclic [As 4 Te 6 ] 4Ϫ anions containing a <lb/>six-membered (As 2 Te) 2 ring are present in [Ba(en) 4 ] 2 As 4 Te 6 [22] and <lb/>[enH 2 ]As 4 Te 6 • 2en [23] and cage-like chalcogenidoarsenate anions <lb/>of nuclearity n ϭ 7 and 10 have been characterised in respectively <lb/>(PPh 4 )As 7 Se 4 [24] and the compounds [K(2.2.2-crypt)] 2 As 10 S 3 [3] <lb/>(2.2.2-crypt ϭ 4,7,13,16,21,24-hexaoxa-1,10-diazabicyclo[8.8.8]-<lb/>hexacosane) and (PPh 4 ) 2 As 10 E 3 (E ϭ Se [25], Te [26]). The struc-<lb/></body>

			<front>* Prof. Dr. W. S. Sheldrick <lb/>Lehrstuhl für Analytische Chemie <lb/>Ruhr-Universität Bochum <lb/>D-44780 Bochum <lb/>Tel.: ϩ49-234-3224192 <lb/>Fax: ϩ49-2343214420 <lb/>E-mail: william.sheldrick@rub.de <lb/> 820 <lb/> © 2008 WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem. 2008, 634, 820Ϫ822 <lb/> two ring members. The adjacent As I atoms in the individual rings <lb/>are bridged by the Se atom of the third [As 4 Se] ring. <lb/>Keywords: Selenidoarsenate; Manganese; Cluster anion; Solvother-<lb/>mal synthesis; Crystal structure <lb/></front>

			<body>Fig. 1 The molecular structure of the [As 6 Se 5 ] 2Ϫ anion of 1 <lb/>showing the atom numbering scheme [symmetry code A: 3/2 Ϫx, <lb/>Ϫy, z]. <lb/>Selected bond lengths/Å and angles/°: As1-Se1 2.308(3), As1-Se2 2.449(3), <lb/>As1-As2 2.417(3), As2-Se3 2.374(3), As2-As3a 2.430(3), As3-Se2 2.381(3), <lb/>As3-As3a 2.450(4); Se1-As1-As2 92.28(11), Se1-As1-Se2 104.88(10), <lb/>As2-As1-Se2 99.67(10), Se3-As2-As1 101.67(10), Se3-As2-As3a 103.34(11), <lb/>As1-As2 As3a 96.57(9), Se2-As3-As2a 100.05(10), Se2-As3-As3a 97.52(12), <lb/>As2a-As3-As3a 98.88(8), As3-Se2-As1 109.44(10), As2a-Se3-As2 107.45(14) <lb/>tures of the latter [As 10 E 3 ] 3Ϫ anions are based on that of the tris-<lb/>homocubane-like [As 11 ] 3Ϫ anion [27], as is that of [As 11 Te] 3Ϫ in <lb/>[K(2.2.2-crypt)] 3 As 11 Te • en [28]. A nuclearity n ϭ 12 has been re-<lb/>ported for [As 12 Se 4 ] 4Ϫ in [Co(NH 3 ) 6 ] 2 As 12 Se • 12NH 3 [29]. Pyrami-<lb/>dal [AE 3 ] 3Ϫ anions can also link through E-E bonds as observed <lb/>in cyclic [A 2 E 6 ] 2Ϫ anions (A ϭ As, E ϭ Se [29]; A ϭ Sb, E ϭ Se <lb/>[30]) and chainlike 1 <lb/>ϱ [AsSe 3 <lb/>Ϫ ] polymers [31]. <lb/>We now report the synthesis and structure of [Mn(9-ane-N 3 ) 2 ] <lb/>As 6 Se 5 (1) (9-ane-N 3 ϭ 1,4,7-triazacyclononane), whose novel <lb/>pentaselenidohexaarsenate(I,II) cluster anion is depicted in Figure <lb/>1. Violet crystals of 1 were prepared by methanolothermal reaction <lb/>of [MnCl 3 (9-ane-N 3 )] with As 2 Se 3 in an equimolar ratio at a tem-<lb/>perature of 150°C in the presence of Cs 2 CO 3 as a mineralizer. It <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Novel Pentaselenidohexaarsenate(I,II) Cluster Anion [As 6 Se 5 ] 2Ϫ <lb/></note>

			<body>is interesting to note that the analogous solvothermal reaction of <lb/>[MnCl 3 (9-ane-N 3 )] with elemental As and Se in H 2 O/CH 3 OH (1/1) <lb/>at a 1:1:2 molar ratio leads to formation of [Mn(9-ane-N 3 ) 2 ]As 2 Se 6 <lb/>in 70 % yield [32]. The tricyclic [As 6 Se 5 ] 2Ϫ anion exhibits crystallo-<lb/>graphic C 2 symmetry with the twofold axis passing through Se3 <lb/>and the centre of the As3-As3a bond. It contains three five-<lb/>membered As 4 Se rings and can be regarded as being related to <lb/>the bicyclic [As 4 Se 6 ] 2Ϫ anion of [K(2.2.2-crypt)] 2 As 4 Se 6 [3] and <lb/>(PPh 4 ) 2 As 4 Se 6 [33] with As2 and As2a replacing Se atoms and <lb/>being linked by an additional atom Se3. The terminal As1-Se1 <lb/>distance is much shorter [2.308(3) Å ] than those observed for the <lb/>endocyclic As-Se bonds [2.374(3)Ϫ2.449(3) Å ] and As-As distances <lb/>within the As 6 chain lie in the range 2.417(3)Ϫ2.450(4) Å . <lb/>On ignoring longer As-Se interactions greater than 2.63 Å , the <lb/>structure of the [As 7 Se 4 ] Ϫ anion in (PPh 4 )As 7 Se 4 [24] can also be <lb/>related to the realgar-like atom arrangement in As 4 Se 4 , in this case <lb/>by replacing both Se atoms of one of the As 3 Se 2 rings by As atoms <lb/>and then bridging these by an As(Se)Se unit. As both [K(2.2.2-<lb/>crypt)] 2 As 4 Se 6 and (PPh 4 )As 7 Se 4 were, indeed, prepared from <lb/>As 4 Se 4 under reducing conditions (K/NH 3 and K/en), such a struc-<lb/>tural relationship is to be expected. It is more surprising for the <lb/>[As 6 Se 5 ] 2Ϫ anions of [Mn(9-ane-N 3 ) 2 ]As 6 Se 5 as no reducing agent <lb/>was present for the methanolothermal reaction. However, it should <lb/>be noted that disproportionation reactions are rather typical for <lb/>reactions carried out on As/Se systems in superheated methanol <lb/>[34]. For instance hydrothermally synthesized CsAsSe 3 • 0.5H 2 O <lb/>[31] disproportionates to the polymeric selenidoarsenate(II,III) <lb/>Cs 2 As 4 Se 6 , the cyclic selenidoarsenate(III) Cs 4 As 4 Se 8 [11], and the <lb/>selenidoarsenates(V) Cs 2 [As(CH 3 )Se 3 ] • 2H 2 O and Cs[As(CH 3 ) 2 Se 2 ] <lb/>[35] in methanol at 190°C [36]. The 1 <lb/>ϱ [As 4 Se 6 <lb/>2Ϫ ] chains of <lb/>Cs 2 As 4 Se 6 can be regarded as being constructed from discrete bi-<lb/>cyclic [As 4 Se 6 ] 2Ϫ anions by cleavage of an endocyclic As-Se bond <lb/>and concomitant formation of new As-Se bonds to adjacent units <lb/>in the resulting 1D polyanion [36]. We did not study the compo-<lb/>sition of the mother liquor for the reaction of[MnCl 3 (9-ane-N 3 )] <lb/>with As 2 Se 3 but assume that it will once again contain As V anions <lb/>such as those of [As(CH 3 )Se 3 ] 2Ϫ and [As(CH 3 ) 2 Se 2 ] Ϫ obtained by <lb/>the disproportionation of CsAsSe 3 • 0.5H 2 O in superheated meth-<lb/>anol. <lb/>Experimental Section <lb/>The starting compound [MnCl 3 (9-ane-N 3 )] was prepared in accord-<lb/>ance with the literature procedure [37]. <lb/>[Mn(9-ane-N 3 ) 2 ]As 6 Se 5 (1) <lb/>150.6 mg of [MnCl 3 (9-ane-N 3 )] (0.52 mmol) was tempered in a <lb/>sealed glass tube at 150°C for 25 h in 1 ml methanol together with <lb/>201.1 mg As 2 Se 3 (0.52 mmol) and 165.3 mg Cs 2 CO 3 (0.51 mmol). <lb/>Slow cooling to 20°C at 1°C/h afforded violet crystals of <lb/>[Mn(9-ane-N 3 ) 2 ]As 6 Se 5 (1) in 15 % yield (45.2 mg). EDX measure-<lb/>ments on a LEO 1530 Gemini were in accordance with the expected <lb/>1:6:5 ratio for Mn:As:Se. <lb/>X-ray structural analyses <lb/>(1), Siemens P4 diffractometer, 294(2) K, orthorhombic Pnna, a ϭ <lb/>12.729(6), b ϭ 18.845(5), c ϭ 11.798(3) Å , V ϭ 2830.1(17) Å 3 , Z ϭ <lb/>4, M ϭ 1157.7, D c ϭ 2.717 Mg • m Ϫ3 , μ ϭ 13.87 mm Ϫ1 , F(000) ϭ <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem. 2008, 820Ϫ822 <lb/>© 2008 WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/></note>www.zaac.wiley-vch.de <lb/>

			<page>821 <lb/></page>

			<body>2148. Intensity data were collected with ω-scans in the range 2.04 <lb/>Յ θ Յ 25.0°for a crystal of dimensions 0.45 x 0.17 x 0.16 mm <lb/>using MoKα radiation (λ ϭ 0.71073 Å ) and corrected for absorp-<lb/>tion with γ scan data. The structure was solved by direct methods <lb/>and refined against F o <lb/>2 with SHELX-97 [38] to R 1 ϭ 0.074 <lb/>[I &gt; 2σ(I)], wR 2 ϭ 0.184 (all data) for 2463 independent reflections <lb/>[39]. All non-hydrogen atoms were refined anisotropically. H atoms <lb/>were constrained to idealized positions and refined using a riding <lb/>model, with d(N-H) ϭ 0.91 and d(C-H) ϭ 0.97 Å , and with U iso <lb/>(H) ϭ 1.2 U eq (N) or 1.2 U eq (C). The highest peak of residual elec-<lb/>tron density (1.06 e • Å Ϫ3 ) is located 1.08 Å from Se1 and the deep-<lb/>est hole (Ϫ0.90 e • Å Ϫ3 ) 0.70 Å from Se3. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>[1] W. S. Sheldrick, J. Chem. Soc., Dalton Trans. 2000, 3041. <lb/>[2] W. S. Sheldrick, H.-J. Häusler, Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem. 1988, <lb/>557, 98Ϫ104. <lb/>[3] W. S. Sheldrick, H.-J. Häusler, Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem. 1988, <lb/>561, 149Ϫ156. <lb/>[4] D. M. Smith, C.-W. Park, J. A. Ibers, Inorg. Chem. 1996, 35, <lb/>6682. <lb/>[5] M. Schur, A. Gruhl, C. Näther, I. Jess, W. Bensch, Z. Natur-<lb/>forsch. 1999, 54b, 1524. <lb/>[6] W. S. Sheldrick, J. Kaub, Z. Naturforsch. 1985, 40b, 19. <lb/>[7] M.-L. Fu, G.-C. Guo, L.-Z. Cai, Inorg. Chem. Commun. 2005, <lb/>44, 184. <lb/>[8] W. S. Sheldrick, J. Kaub, Z. Naturforsch. 1985, 40b, 1020. <lb/>[9] M.-L. Fu, G.-C. Guo, X. Liu, B. Liu, L.-Z. Cai, J.-S. Huang, <lb/>Inorg. Chem. Commun. 2005, 8, 18. <lb/>[10] R. Kiebach, F. Studt, C. Näther, W. Bensch, Eur. J. Inorg. <lb/>Chem. 2004, 2553. <lb/>[11] T. van Almsick, W. S. Sheldrick, Acta Crystallogr. 2006, E62, <lb/>i41. <lb/>[12] L. Engelke, W. Bensch, Acta Crystallogr. 2003, E59, m378. <lb/>[13] D.-X. Jia, Q.-X. Zhao, J. Dai, Y. Zhang, Q.-Y. Zhu, Z. Anorg. <lb/>Allg. Chem. 2006, 632, 349. <lb/>[14] D.-X. Jia, Q.-X. Zhao, L.-F. Song, Y. Zhang, J. Dai, Chinese <lb/>J. Struct. Chem. 2006, 25, 110. <lb/>[15] D.-X. Jia, Y. Zhang, J. Dai, Q.-Y. Zhu, X.-M. Gu, J. Solid <lb/>State Chem. 2004, 177, 2477. <lb/>[16] C. Näther, F. Wendland, W. Bensch, Acta Crystallogr. 2003, <lb/>E59, m119. <lb/>[17] Z. Chen, R.-J. Wang, X.-Y. Huang, J. Li, Acta Crystallogr. <lb/>2000, E56, 1100. <lb/>[18] T. van Almsick, W. S. Sheldrick, Acta Crystallogr. 2005, E61, <lb/>i240. <lb/>[19] E. J. Porter, G. M. Sheldrick, J. Chem. Soc. A 1971, 3130. <lb/>[20] T. M. Martin, G. L. Schimek, W. T. Pennington, J. W. Kolis, <lb/>J. Chem. Soc., Dalton Trans. 1995, 501. <lb/>[21] T. M. Martin, G. L. Schimek, D. A. Misna, J. W. Kolis, Phos-<lb/>phorus, Sulfur, Silicon, Relat. Elem. 1994, 93, 93. <lb/>[22] B. Eisenmann, R. Zagler, Z. Naturforsch. 1987, 42b, 1079. <lb/>[23] C. J. Warren, R. C. Haushalter, A. B. Bocarsly, Chem. Mater. <lb/>1994, 6, 780. <lb/>[24] V. Angilelia, H. Mercier, C. Belin, Chem. Commun. 1989, 1654. <lb/>[25] C. Belin, V. Angilelia, H. Mercier, Acta Crystallogr. 1991, <lb/>C47, 61. <lb/>[26] R. S. Haushalter, Chem. Commun. 1987, 196. <lb/>[27] C. H. E. Belin, J. Am. Chem. Soc. 1980, 102, 6036 <lb/>[28] C. Belin, H. Mercier, Chem. Commun. 1987, 190. <lb/>[29] C. H. E. Belin, M. M. Charbonnel, Inorg. Chem. 1982, 21, <lb/>2504. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">A. Kromm, W. S. Sheldrick <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[30] D. M. Smith, C.-W. Park, J. A. Ibers, Inorg. Chem. 1997, 36, <lb/>3798. <lb/>[31] W. S. Sheldrick, J. Kaub, Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem. 1986, 535, 179. <lb/>[32] A. Kromm, W. S. Sheldrick, Acta Crystallogr. 2007, E63, <lb/>m581. <lb/>[33] M. A. Ansari, J. A. Ibers, S. C. O&apos;Neal, W. T. Pennington, J. <lb/>W. Kolis, Polyhedron 1992, 11, 1877. <lb/>[34] W. S. Sheldrick, M. Wachhold, Angew. Chem. 1997, 109, 214; <lb/>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. Engl. 1997, 36, 206. <lb/>[35] T. van Almsick, W. S. Sheldrick, Acta Crystallogr. 2005, E61, <lb/>m2661. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">www.zaac.wiley-vch.de <lb/>© 2008 WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem. 2008, 820Ϫ822 <lb/></note>

			<page>822 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[36] T. van Almsick, W. S. Sheldrick, Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem. 2006, <lb/>632, 1409. <lb/>[37] K. Wieghardt, U. Bossek,B. Naber, J. Weiss, J. Bonvoisin, M. <lb/>Carbella, S. E. Vitols, J. J. Girerd, J. Am. Chem. Soc. 1988, <lb/>110, 7398. <lb/>[38] G. M. Sheldrick, SHELX-97, Program for Crystal Structure <lb/>solution and Refinement, Göttingen, 1997. <lb/>[39] Crystallographic data for 1 have been deposited at the Cam-<lb/>bridge Crystallographic Data Centre, 12 Union Road, <lb/>Cambridge CB2 1EZ, UK (fax: int.code ϩ44(0)1223/336-033, <lb/>e-mail: deposit@chemcrys.cam.ac.uk) under CCDC 668446. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
