<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<front>Using an integrated approach to assess the sediment quality of an Mediterranean <lb/>lagoon, the Bizerte lagoon (Tunisia) <lb/>Badreddine Barhoumi 1,2,* , Anis Elbarhoumi II 3 , Christelle Clérandeau Sr. 2 , Abdulla M. <lb/>Al-Rawabdeh 4 , Atef Atyaoui 3,5 , Soufiane de Touil 1 , Mohamed Ridha Driss 1 , Jérôme <lb/>Cachot 2 <lb/>1 Laboratory of Heteroatom Organic Chemistry, Department of Chemistry, Faculty of Sciences <lb/>of Bizerte, University of Carthage, Four Fountains Road, 7021 Jarzouna, Tunisia Tel.: +216 <lb/>22 199 496 * e-mail: barhoumibadredine@yahoo.fr <lb/>2 University of Bordeaux, UMR CNRS EPOC 5805, 10 N Two Pier Avenue, 33405 Talence <lb/>Cedex, France <lb/>3 Department of Earth Sciences, Faculty of Sciences of Bizerte, University of Carthage, Four <lb/>Fountains Road, 7021 Jarzouna, Tunisia <lb/>4 Department of Geomatics Engineering, University of Calgary, Twelve North Street, Calgary, <lb/>Canada <lb/>5 Delhi University, Nine Horses Street, New Delhi, India <lb/>6 URL: http://www.natureview.com <lb/>Abstract: <lb/>The present study investigates the quality of surface sediments from the Bizerte lagoon (North Tunisia) using an <lb/>integrated approach including chemical contaminant analysis, bioassays and sediment quality guidelines (SQGs). <lb/>Sediment samples were collected at 9 sites and analyzed for eight heavy metals (Hg, Cd, Cr, Cu, Pb, Zn, Ni, Fe <lb/>and Mn). PAHs, PCBs, OCPs were measured previously in the same sediment samples. Our results indicated <lb/>that the highest concentrations of metals were found near urban areas due to the municipial and industrial <lb/>wastewater discharges. Sediment pollution assessment was carried out using geoaccumulation index (Igeo) and <lb/>enrichment factor (EF), which indicate a widespread pollution by Cd, Pb, Ni and Zn in the studied sediments. <lb/>For bioassays, aqueous and organic extracts were used to assess toxicity and genotoxicity in sediments by using <lb/>Microtox ® and SOS Chromotest, respectively. Toxicity levels were compared to metallic and organic pollutants <lb/>contents. Our results highlight differences in the pattern of responses between the different assays and show no <lb/>correlation with all the studied contaminants, emphasizing the influence of other contaminants not analyzed in <lb/>the present study. Based on SQGs, the results of toxicity assessment indicated that adverse effects caused by Ni <lb/>and Zn would be expected frequently. Nickel was found to have the highest predicted acute toxicity, followed by <lb/>Zn, Pb, Cd, Cu and Cr. There was no significant relationship between sediment toxicity calculated from heavy <lb/>metal concentrations (SQG approach) and those measured with bioassays. These findings support the use of <lb/>integrated approachs for evaluating the environmental risks of sediments. <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>Keywords: marine lagoon, surface sediments, metals, organic pollutants, toxicity assays <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Bizerte lagoon (northern coast of Tunisia) represents an ecosystem whose biological balance has been modified <lb/>in relation to the anthropogenic development and big industries settlement (about 100 industries). The steel <lb/>complex -El Fouledh‖, the petroleum refinery and the cement factory are the main industries settled in the <lb/>vicinity of the lagoon. Marine sediments can be suitable indicators for monitoring of past and present <lb/>contamination in aquatic environments (Balls et al. 1997; Atgın et al. 2000). They have been found polluted with <lb/>various kinds of hazardous and toxic substances (Fukue et al. 1999; Zabetoglou et al. 2002), including heavy <lb/>metal which accumulate in sediments. Metals can be discharged in the aquatique environment via several <lb/>pathways, including disposal of liquid effluents, terrestrial runoff, and leachates, shipping, as well as <lb/>atmospheric deposition (Lamotte et al. 1996; Karageorgis et al. 2002; Mucha et al. 2003). Heavy metal pollution <lb/>has become an important issue worldwide due to their high toxicity, abundance and persistence in ecosystems <lb/>(Cooke et al. 1990; Lim et al. 2008; Weng et al. 2008; Varol 2011). Heavy metal residues in contaminated <lb/>habitats may accumulate in microorganisms, aquatic flora and fauna, which, in turn, may enter into the human <lb/>food chain and result in health problems (Cook et al. 1990; Deniseger et al. 1990). The bioavailability of these <lb/>contaminants and consequently their toxicity may be strongly influenced by factors such as reduction/oxidation <lb/>state, sediment grain size, salinity, pH, and organic matter content, that can change daily due to the natural <lb/>dynamics of coastal area (Buccolieri et al. 2006; Choueri et al. 2009). Such accumulation is enhanced in <lb/>enclosed and semi-enclosed areas where exchange of water with the open sea is limited (Okay et al. 1996; <lb/>Karageorgis et al. 2002). <lb/>In response to concerns about chemical pollution and environmental degradation, legislation world-wide has <lb/>been implemented to protect and restore ecological quality in estuarine, coastal and marine systems; for instance <lb/>the Water Framework Directive (WFD, 2000/60/EC) and the Marine Strategic Framework Directive (MSFD, <lb/>2008/56/EC) in Europe. At present, assessment and monitoring of sediment quality in Tunisia, particularly in the <lb/>Bizerte lagoon, is predominantly reliant on chemical analyses (Ben Garali et al. 2013; Barhoumi et al. 2014a, b). <lb/>Measurement of contaminant concentrations alone is often insufficient to derive accurate conclusions on the <lb/>potential toxicity of contaminated environmental samples, as it is virtually impossible to identify and quantify all <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>potential toxicants. In addition, the magnitude of contamination does not necessarily reflect a similar level of <lb/>ecotoxicological effects, as chemical analysis cannot directly assess the combined effects (antagonistic or <lb/>synergistic) and the bioavailability of toxicants to organisms. Thereby, numerous indices (e.g., enrichment factor <lb/>(EF), contamination factor (CF), geoaccumulation index (Igeo), toxicity indices and ecological risk indices) have <lb/>been developed and utilised worldwide to assess extent and hazard of anthropogenic contamination by heavy <lb/>metals (Caeiro et al. 2005; Sekabira et al. 2010). Empirical sediment quality guidelines (SQGs), such as the <lb/>threshold/probable effect level (TEL/PEL) and the effect range low/median (ERL/ERM), are also commonly <lb/>used worldwide as informal benchmarks to aid in the interpretation of sediment chemistry data. These SQGs <lb/>evaluate the degree to which the sediment-associated chemical status might adversely affect aquatic organisms <lb/>and are designed to assist the interpretation of sediment quality (Wenning and Ingersoll 2002). However, their <lb/>assessment is based on the bulk (total) concentration of contaminants in sediments, which does not necessarily <lb/>reflect the bioavailable fraction of contaminants. Furthermore, bioavailability for a same contaminant changes <lb/>according to site conditions and benthic populations (Batley et al. 2005; Burton 2013; Campana et al. 2013). In <lb/>order to provide information on the ecological impact of sediment contamination on aquatic biota, sediment <lb/>toxicity bioassays were recommended (Long and Chapman 1985). Bioassays based on the inhibition of <lb/>bioluminescence of the marine bacterium Vibrio fischeri have gained popularity in sediment toxicity testing <lb/>using variable sediment fractions: aqueous elutriates, organic extracts, pore water or bulk sediment suspensions <lb/>(Ankley et al. 1991; Heida and Van der Oost 1996; Svenson et al. 1996; Salizzato et al. 1998). Also, SOS <lb/>Chromotest with the Escherichia coli PQ37 strain was widely used to test genotoxicity of sediments (Cachot et <lb/>al. 2006; Parrella et al. 2013). Two bioassays were carried out in this study: the Microtox ® was applied to <lb/>measure acute toxicity of sediment organic extracts and aqueous elutriates. The SOS-Chromotest (Quillardet et <lb/>al. 1982) was applied for measuring the genotoxic potency of sediment organic extracts. The use of elutriates <lb/>(aqueous extracts) can provides information on the potential toxic effects of leached contaminants released from <lb/>dredged material (Cheung et al. 1997; Wong et al. 1999), but are unlikely to provide information on the possible <lb/>effects of contaminants retained on the solid phase and deposited on the seabed. Organic solvent extraction <lb/>allows extraction of most organic pollutants adsorbed onto particulate matter. A major drawback of assaying <lb/>sediment toxicity is that the toxicity of the extracts may not be the result of anthropogenic contamination alone. <lb/>Common macrocompounds (e.g. ammonia and sulphur) derived from the natural decomposition of organic <lb/>matter can accumulate in sediments and cause toxic effects once they are made bioavailable through the <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>extraction process (Gagné et al. 1999). After consideration of each test phase, it appears clearly that testing many <lb/>exposure routes is necessary for a more comprehensive assessment of sediment toxicity. <lb/>To our knowledge, there are no studies assessing anthropogenic influences on sediment chemical <lb/>composition using such indices in Bizerte lagoon. Also, the assessment and monitoring of sediment quality in the <lb/>Bizerte lagoon, is predominantly reliant on chemical analyses, and up to date there are no data available <lb/>combining chemical analyses and toxicological assays. Taking that into account, the objectives of this study <lb/>were (i) to determine concentrations and spatial distributions of heavy metals in surface sediments of the Bizerte <lb/>lagoon; (ii) to explore the degree of heavy metal contamination in the lagoon using contamination indices; (iii) to <lb/>evaluate the toxicity and genotoxicity of sediments using two bioassays, Microtox ® and SOS-Chromotest, <lb/>respectively; (iv) to assess environmental risks of these metals in the studied area using sediment quality <lb/>guidelines (SQGs), and (v) to assess correlation analysis among heavy metals, and between heavy metals, <lb/>physico-chemical variables and biological endpoints. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Study area <lb/>The Bizerte lagoon is a large Mediterranean brackish water area of 128 km 2 located in the North part of Tunisia <lb/>(latitude, 37°80′-37°14′ N; longitude, 9°46′-9°56′ E). It is the second largest lagoon in Tunisia with a mean <lb/>depth of 7 m and constitutes one of the first local lentic ecosystems for fisheries and mussel production. This <lb/>lagoon is linked to the Mediterranean Sea via a 7 km long canal and to the Ichkeul Lake by the Tinja River. The <lb/>main tributaries of this lagoon are the rivers Tinja, Mrezig, Garek, Ben Hassine, and Gueniche (Fig. 1). The <lb/>lagoon is subjected to the influence of several physical factors that strongly fluctuate during the year. The most <lb/>frequent and strongest winds are north-westerly, with a frequency of 200 days.year −1 and an average speed of <lb/>6−8 m.s −1 (Ouakad 2007). In the shallowest areas of the lagoon, the highest magnitude wind-mixing events can <lb/>thus supply enough energy to resuspend the superficial layer of the sediment. In winter, winds induce a vertical <lb/>mixture of the water column. At the same time rains are strong, and the freshwater flow coming from the Ichkeul <lb/>Lake is important. On the other hand, in summer, inputs of seawater into the lagoon are important and the water <lb/>column warming can induce its stratification (Sakka Hlaili et al. 2003). The Bizerte lagoon is subjected to <lb/>urbanization, industry, agriculture and aquaculture, as well as treated and untreated municipal sewages (Louati et <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>al. 2013). The human population around the lagoon is estimated at 163,000 inhabitants (2004 census) of which <lb/>approximately % are concentrated in the city of Bizerte. The other main important towns bordering the <lb/>lagoon are Menzel Bourguiba (which has a naval port and a metal factory), Menzel Abderrahman, and Menzel <lb/>Jemil. Some other industries including an iron and steel plant, a cement factory, a refinery, and boatyards, <lb/>textiles, plastics, and tire production factories are established nearby (Essid and Aissa 2002). The majority of <lb/>these surrounding towns and industries discharge their waste into the lagoon. The exchange of water between the <lb/>Mediterranean and the lake determines the salinity of the lagoon, which varies between 32.5 and 38.5‰. The <lb/>water temperature at the sub-surface range between 10 °C during winter (wet season) and 29 °C in summer time <lb/>(dry season). <lb/>Sediments sampling <lb/>Surface sediment samples (0-10 cm) were collected in March 2011 from nine stations in triplicate (nearly 500 g <lb/>for each), using a stainless steel grab. Details of the sampling sites are shown in Fig. 1 and Table 1. Sites were <lb/>selected to be representative of the different anthropic pressures present in the study area, e.g. cement works, <lb/>metallurgical industry, boatyard, tyre production factories and agriculture. After collection, samples were <lb/>wrapped in aluminium foil and cool transported to the laboratory where they were immediately stored in a <lb/>freezer at -20 °C. All sediment samples were freeze-dried, then sieved using a 2-mm mesh to eliminate debris, <lb/>homogenized and stored at 4 °C prior to being characterized with bioassays and chemical analysis. <lb/>Physico-chemical characterisation of sediments <lb/>All sampling sediments were subjected to physical and chemical analyses in order to determine their natural <lb/>characteristics (Table 1). The following physico-chemical water properties were determined in situ at all nine <lb/>stations using a WTW-197i multimeter: temperature, salinity and pH (pH H2O ). The pH of the sampled sediments <lb/>(pH sed ) was measured by shaking an aliquot of sediment in distilled water (10 g of dry sediment in 25 ml of <lb/>water) for 10 min. The suspension was left to stand for 10 min. The pH of the supernatant was measured with an <lb/>electronic pH meter (CONSORT P902, SCIENTIFIC Instruments, Belgium). The percentage of the finer grain <lb/>size fraction (&lt;63 μm) was determined gravimetrically after wet sieving (Savinov et al. 2000). Total organic <lb/>carbon (TOC) content was determined by combustion in an LECO CS 125 analyzer (Etcheber et al. 2007). Dried <lb/>and homogenized sediment samples were acidified in crucibles with 2 N HCl to destroy carbonates, then dried at <lb/>

			60 °C to remove inorganic carbon and most of the remaining acid residues and water. Analyses were performed <lb/>by direct combustion in an induction furnace, and the CO 2 formed was determined quantitatively by infrared <lb/>absorption. TOC content is expressed as a percentage of dry weight (dw) sediment. Sulfur (S) was measured in <lb/>sediment samples using an HORIBA model EMIA-220V C/S analyzer with a resistance furnace and a infrared <lb/>detector. About 0.2 g of sample, mixed with 1 g of granular tin, was combusted in the analyzer to produce SO at <lb/>1350 °C. For the organic pollutant analysis (PAHs, PCBs, OCPs), sediments were freeze-dried, homogenised <lb/>and extracted with an Accelerated Solvent Extraction system (ASE) using dichloromethane (DCM). Details of <lb/>the protocols for the extraction, cleanup and analysis of POPs are described in Barhoumi et al. (2014a, b). <lb/>Potentially hazardous trace metallic elements (Hg, Cd, Cr, Cu, Pb, Zn, and Ni) and major elements (Fe and <lb/>Mn) contents in the sediment were determined after digestion of the samples with aqua regia according to FAO <lb/>(1975). Samples (0.5 g dw) were digested with a mixture of HCl (37 %) and HNO 3 (69 %) in a ratio of 3:1 (v/v) <lb/>at 120 °C under reflux conditions. The obtained suspension was then filtered through a membrane of 0.45 μm <lb/>pore-diameter, diluted to 50 mL with ultra -pure water, and analysed using a Jobin-Yvon Ultima-C inductively <lb/>coupled plasma-atomic emission spectrometer (ICP-AES). The reagent blanks were monitored throughout the <lb/>analysis and were used to accredit the analytical results. Standard reference material IAEA-SL-1 (Lake <lb/>sediment) was analysed at the same time to ensure quality control and accuracy of the analysis. The <lb/>concentrations measured for the reference sediment were in agreement with the certified values (accuracy &lt;10 <lb/>%). <lb/>Sample preparation <lb/>Elutriate <lb/>The protocol applied for sediment elutriate preparation (water-extractable phase) was a derivation of <lb/>Environment Canada (1992): 30 mL 2% NaCl solution was added to 6 g dw sediment. The sediment-water <lb/>suspension was agitated vigorously on a magnetic stirrer for 15 min and centrifuged at 300 g for 10 min at 15 °C. <lb/>The supernatant was collected as elutriate and pH was measured following filtration through a 0.45 µm filter. <lb/>The elutriate was stored at 4 °C in the dark prior to toxicity testing (Microtox ® Acute Toxicity 100% Test), <lb/>which was conducted within 24 h of preparation. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Organic extract <lb/>For the preparation of organic extracts, g freeze-dried sediment from each of the nine sampling stations was <lb/>separately extracted with dichloromethane (Fluka, Buchs, Switzerland) using an ASE 200 accelerated solvent <lb/>extractor (Dionex, France). The parameters used during the extraction procedure were as follows: temperature <lb/>(100 °C), static time (8 min), pressure (100 bars), heating time (5 min), flush volume (60%), and purge time (60 <lb/>s). The volume of the resulting Dichloromethane-dissolved extract was reduced by using a RapidVap evaporator <lb/>(Labconco, Kansas City, MO, USA). Extracts were concentrated to dryness with N 2 and resuspended in 200 µL <lb/>of dimethyl sulphoxide (DMSO, Sigma). A blank of extraction was prepared by the same procedure but without <lb/>sediment. <lb/>Bioassays and exposure conditions <lb/>Microtox ® <lb/>Two Microtox ® protocols were applied for sediment acute toxicity testing; the 100% Test on sediment aqueous <lb/>extract (Elutriate), and the Basic Test on sediment organic extracts. <lb/>Microtox ® is a commercial toxicity bioassay based on the reduction in bioluminescence of the marine <lb/>bacterium Vibrio fischeri following exposure to toxicants. Both the Microtox 100% Test and the Microtox Basic <lb/>Test were used following the standard procedures (AZUR Environmental 1998; ISO 1999). These toxicity tests <lb/>were conducted with a Model 500 analyzer (Kontron Instruments, Montigny le Bretonneux) and lyophilized <lb/>bacteria cultures (Acute Reagent, Modern Water, Guildford, UK). A basic test was conducted with the reference <lb/>standard potassium dichromate (200 mg L -1 K 2 Cr 2 O 7 ) for each fresh vial of bacteria to ensure validity of the test <lb/>method. The Microtox ® data acquisition software was used to calculate the EC50 (%) value, the effective <lb/>concentration of sample (expressed as mg of dw sediment) causing a 50% decrease in the light output. <lb/>The 100% Microtox Test was performed on four serial 1:2 dilutions of each elutriate starting with undiluted <lb/>elutriate (100% elutriate). Each assay was then inoculated with 10 μl of freshly resuspended freeze-dried bacteria <lb/>in 2% NaCl. Each assay was run in duplicate. Bioluminescence was measured after 5, 15 and 30 min of exposure <lb/>and compared with blank (NaCl 2%), and corrected for spontaneous decline in photoactivity. <lb/>The Microtox ® Basic Test was performed on four serial 1:2 dilutions of sediment organic extracts starting <lb/>with 10 µL/mL of organic extract (1%). Each assay was then inoculated with 10 μl of freshly resuspended <lb/>freeze-dried bacteria in 2% NaCl. After 5, 15 and 30 min incubation, the bioluminescence was measured, <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>compared with a blank, and corrected for spontaneous decline in photoactivity. One control solvent (1% v/v <lb/>DMSO) and one saline blank were run with each serie of samples. All samples were tested in duplicate. <lb/>Sediment samples were ranked using the following scale: samples having an inhibition percentage at 30 min <lb/>less than or equal to 20% were considered no toxic and an inhibition percentage between 20-40%, 40-80%, and <lb/>&gt;80% were considered slightly, moderately and highly toxic, respectively. <lb/>SOS-Chromotest <lb/>For detection of direct and indirect acting genotoxicant in sediments the SOS-Chromotest (Quillardet and <lb/>Hofnung 1985) was performed using Escherichia coli PQ37 strain with and without addition of an S9 <lb/>microsomal fraction obtained from the livers of Sprague-Dawley rats treated with β-naphthoflavone <lb/>andphenobarbital (Xenotech). In each series of tests, a solvent control (0.1% v/v DMSO), a blank of extraction <lb/>and a B[a]P positive control (0.5 µg mL −1 ) were analysed. Responses were expressed as mean induction factor <lb/>(three replicates) for 25 mg equivalent dry weight sediment per assay. Samples with significant SOS induction <lb/>factor compare to control solvent were considered as genotoxic when values exceeded 2, moderately genotoxic <lb/>when values were in the range 1.5-2.0, slightly genotoxic when it was comprised between 1.0 and 1.5, and not <lb/>genotoxic when values were less than or equal to 1.0 (Mersch-Sundermann et al. 1992). <lb/>Assessment of sediment contamination <lb/>In the interpretation of geochemical data, choice of background values plays an important role (Memet 2011). <lb/>The best alternative is to compare concentrations between contaminated and mineralogically and texturally <lb/>comparable, uncontaminated sediments (Rubio et al. 2000). Since there were no data on background <lb/>concentrations for the investigated Bizerte sediments of close areas, the average crust values obtained by Martin <lb/>and Whitfield (1983) were used as reference baseline for the elements. In this study, two indices were used to <lb/>assess the degree of heavy metal contamination in sediments of the Bizerte lagoon. <lb/>Geoaccumulation index (Igeo) <lb/>The geoaccumulation index (Igeo) introduced by Muller (1981) may contribute to the estimation of the degree of <lb/>the sediment contamination. It is defined by the following equation: <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>  <lb/>  <lb/>2n <lb/>n <lb/>L o g C <lb/>Ig e o = <lb/>1 .5 B <lb/>Where C n is the concentration of a selected metal n examined in sediment samples and B n is the background <lb/>concentration value (average crust) of the same metal. Factor 1.5 is the background matrix correction factor due <lb/>to lithospheric effects. <lb/>Enrichment factor (EF) <lb/>Enrichment factor (EF) has been widely reported as an important tool to differentiate between anthropogenic and <lb/>natural metal sources in the sediment (Nolting et al. 1999; Selvaraj et al. 2004; Naji and Ismail 2011). Aluminum <lb/>(Al) and iron (Fe) are two main elements used as normalizers for EF computation. Al concentration was not <lb/>analyzed in the studied sediments. Therefore, Fe was used to calculate metal enrichment factor. This element is <lb/>widely used as a crustal reference (Feng et al. 1998; Schiff and Weisberg 1999; Mucha et al. 2003). <lb/>According to Ergin et al. (1991), The EF is computed using the relationship below: <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>M e ta l / F e S a m p le <lb/>E F = <lb/>M e ta l / F e a v e ra g e c ru s t <lb/>As suggested by Wang et al. (2008) 0.5≤EF≤1.5, indicates metal input from natural weathering process, and <lb/>EF&gt;1.5, indicates metal input from anthropogenic sources or a greater percentage from non-natural weathering <lb/>process. However, the degree of enrichment was interpreted as proposed by Birch (2003). EF&lt;1 indicates no <lb/>enrichment, 1&lt;EF&lt;3 indicates minor enrichment, 3≤EF≤5 indicates moderate enrichment, 5≤EF≤10 indicates <lb/>moderate to severe enrichment, 10≤EF≤25 indicates severe enrichment, 25≤ EF≤50 indicates very severe <lb/>enrichment, and EF&gt;50 suggests extremely severe enrichment. <lb/>Sediment quality guidelines <lb/>Sediment quality assessment guidelines (SQGs) are very useful to evaluate sediment contamination by <lb/>comparing sediment contaminant concentration with the corresponding quality guideline (MacDonald et al. <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>2000). These guidelines evaluate the degree to which the sediment-associated chemicals might adversely affect <lb/>aquatic organisms and are designed to assist in the interpretation of sediment quality. <lb/>Two sets of SQGs developed for freshwater ecosystems (MacDonald et al. 2000) were applied in this study <lb/>to evaluate the ecological risks caused by heavy metals in sediments: the effect range low (ERL)/effect range <lb/>median (ERM) and the threshold effect level (TEL)/probable effect level (PEL) values (Zheng et al. 2008). ERL <lb/>and TEL (low range values) are concentrations below which adverse effects are not expected to occur. In <lb/>contrast, the ERM and PEL are concentrations above which adverse effects are expected to occur more often <lb/>than not. Furthermore, toxic units (TUs) were used to normalize the toxicity of the various metals to allow <lb/>comparison of their relative effects, defined as the ratio of the determined content of each metal to the PEL <lb/>value. The ΣTU were used to estimate the potential acute toxicity of metals mixture in sediment samples <lb/>(Pedersen et al. 1998). <lb/>Data analysis <lb/>The results of chemical (metals) and bioassay (SOS-Chromotest) were reported as mean ± S.D. All statistical <lb/>analyses were performed using STATISTICA 7.1 from StatSoft (Maison Alfort, France). Data was initially <lb/>checked for normality (Shapiro-Wilk&apos;s test, 1% risk) and homogeneity of variances (Levene test, 5% risk). Then, <lb/>an ANOVA, followed by the post-hoc Tukey test was performed to determine differences between treatments. If <lb/>data transformation was not sufficient to perform parametric analysis, non-parametric Kruskall-Wallis ANOVA <lb/>and Bonferroni-Dunn&apos;s test were used (p&lt;0.05). The existence and strength of relationships between parameters <lb/>(metals, PAHs, PCBs, OCPs, pH, fine particle (&lt;63 µm), TOC, Sulfur, Microtox ® , SOS-Chromotest) were <lb/>determined by parametric Pearson&apos;s bivariate correlation analysis. The spatial distributions of each heavy metal, <lb/>indices and sediment toxicity were mapped with ARC-GIS desktop software. <lb/>Results and discussion <lb/>General characteristic of sediments <lb/>The results of the physicochemical characterisation of each sediment are presented in Table 1. Temperature and <lb/>salinity varied little between sites ranging from 13.3-15.4 °C and 34.6-35.5 psu, respectively. The pH is an <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>important indicator of environmental quality and pollution degree in a water system (Singh et al. 2005). In <lb/>leaching process of contaminated sediment the pH depends on the buffering capacity of the sediment. When pH <lb/>reaches a certain value, metals will start being released from sediments (Chen and Lin 2001). High pH values <lb/>generally decrease the solubility of heavy metals in water, while low pH values can actually weaken the strength <lb/>of metal association and impede the retention of metals by sediments (Avila-Pérez et al. 1999; Guven and Akinci <lb/>2013). In this study the sediments displayed an alkaline pH between 7.2 and 8.2 and, in this range, there was no <lb/>release of metals except for Mn, as reported by Chen and Lin (2001). The lowest pH (7.2) was determined in the <lb/>sediment taken immediately downstream of the Mrezig and Haima Rivers (S1, S2), and the highest value (8.2) <lb/>was measured in sediments collected in the center of the lagoon (S6, S7). <lb/>As it is well known, metals are not permanently bound to sediments, but can be remobilized by chemical and <lb/>biological agents both in the sediments and in the water column above (Stone and Droppo 1994; Filgueiras et al. <lb/>2004). For these reasons, measurements of pH in the water column above the sediments were made. pH of water <lb/>varied between 6.8 and 7.9 but was not significantly different from pH of sediment (Table 1). The small <lb/>difference between the pH of water and sediments can be explained by different factors, such as CO 2 leakage, <lb/>tidal flooding, bacterial activity, oxydo-redox equilibrium, sediment composition, etc. (Reddy and DeLaune <lb/>2008; Basallote et al. 2012). Since the Bizerte lagoon is rich in organic matter (Ouakad 2000; Ben Garali et al. <lb/>2013), the low pH values in the water column might be due to the decomposition of organic matter leading to the <lb/>release of various organic acids (Bowen 1979). Also, the CO 2 leakage scenario from high anthropogenic <lb/>activities (urbanization, industry, municipal sewages, agriculture and aquaculture...) around the lagoon may be <lb/>another reason of the slight acidification of the water column. The high pH of sediments is probably related to <lb/>microbial activity and more particularly to sulfate-reducing bacteriae which are present in sediments of the study <lb/>area (Ben Said et al. 2010). The Bizerte lagoon represents a fragile environment due to its enclosed nature and <lb/>the long residence time of pollutants (Harzallah 2003). In addition to these conditions, the high content of <lb/>organic matter in this lagoon can lead to oxygen depletion in sediments. Once anoxic conditions are established, <lb/>anaerobic bacterial strains reduce sulfate in sulfides. The massive production of sulfides increases the pH of <lb/>sediments (Heitmann and Blodau 2006). Increase in the pH of sediments due to sulfate reduction has been <lb/>widely documented in various natural sediments (Abd-el-Malek and Rizk 1963; Mills and Herlihy, 1985; <lb/>Kharaka et al. 1994; Michael et al. 2015). <lb/>Sediment grain size and water depth varied within the lagoon. As shows in Table 1, a high percentage of sand <lb/>was found at stations S1 and S4 located at the edges of the lagoon, which has shallow water (2.5 and 3 m, <lb/>

			respectively). The waves and currents at these sites are highly active and can disturb the fine particles deposition. <lb/>However, silt and clay are dominant in other stations, where the water depth is high and the wave slightly lower, <lb/>which favors the precipitation of fine particles. The abundance of fine particles was assumed to come from <lb/>anthropogenic inputs associated with the erosion of surrounding agricultural areas. This result was consistent <lb/>with the findings of Mouldi et al. (2008) and Boufahja (2010) who showed that the surface sediments of the <lb/>Bizerte lagoon are mostly composed of silt and clay fractions. <lb/>Total organic carbon (TOC) content ranges from 0.7 to 2.2%. The highest value was observed at station S2 <lb/>and was probably related to the high occurrence of urban and industrial wastewater discharges, which are rich in <lb/>organic matter. Sulfur (S) was homogeneously distributed in the lagoon (0.3 to 0.8%), except for stations S2, S4 <lb/>and S5, where higher contents were found (2.3, 1.1 and 3.1%, respectively). <lb/>Heavy metals in sediments of the Bizerte lagoon <lb/>Table 2 summarizes the major and the trace elements&apos; concentrations in the sediments from the nine locations of <lb/>the Bizerte lagoon. Spatial distribution map of each element is shown in Fig. 2. The heavy metal concentrations <lb/>in surface sediments (expressed in mg kg -1 sediment dw) from the studied area varied from 0.3 to 1.1 for Cd, 7.2 <lb/>to 30.8 for Cr, 4.0 to 45.2 for Cu, 71.1 to 239.6 for Mn, 62.8 to 177.5 for Pb, 73.8 to 240.7 for Ni, 318.6 to <lb/>1825.5 for Zn and 4209.4 to 17215.5 for Fe. At all sampling stations, concentrations of Hg were below detection <lb/>limits. The distribution of these heavy metals showed large spatial variations among the stations as a result of <lb/>variability in the extent of source input of trace metals. This heterogeneous profile had already been reported in <lb/>the Bizerte lagoon sediments by other authors (Srarfi 2007; Ben Garali et al. 2010; Ben-Khedher et al. 2013). <lb/>The average concentrations of heavy metals mentioned above are in the following order (mg kg -1 ): Hg (&lt; LD) &lt; <lb/>Cd (1 ± 0.2) &lt; Cr (22 ± 7.8) &lt; Cu (23 ± 14.4) &lt; Pb (118 ± 53.5) &lt; Ni (143 ± 54.5) &lt; Mn (176 ± 61.6) &lt; Zn (834 <lb/>± 462.0) &lt; Fe (13428 ± 4732.1). The results were only partly in agreement compatible with previous studies <lb/>(Boufahja et al. 2007; Ben Khedher et al. 2013) conducted in the Bizerte lagoon. Boufahja et al. (2007) found <lb/>that Fe was the most abundant in the sediment, followed by Mn and Zn, and the least was Cu, while Cd, Cr and <lb/>Hg were not analyzed. Ben Khedher et al. (2013) reported that the accumulation order of heavy metals in the <lb/>sediment samples was Fe &gt; Zn &gt; Mn &gt; Pb &gt; Cr &gt; Cu &gt; Ni &gt; Cd. <lb/>Spatial analysis showed that the site with the highest amount of heavy metals (Σmetals) was S6, followed by <lb/>S3 (Table 2). The sediments of both stations were mainly composed of fine particles (90.2 and 89.5%, <lb/>respectively), which may enhance the adsorption process and then sediment accumulation of trace elements due <lb/>

			to the high specific surface of fine particles (Oliveira et al. 2011). According to this observation, sediment at S1, <lb/>with a lower TOC content, and mainly composed of coarse material, contained lower amounts of heavy metals. <lb/>This feature can be explained by its lower adsorption capacity. Low heavy metals content at S1 may be also <lb/>explained by strong hydrodynamism at this station located at the exchange point between the lagoon of Bizerte <lb/>and the Mediterranean Sea. The hydrodynamic conditions are important factors that affect the physical properties <lb/>of sediments; furthermore, they affect the concentration and spatial distribution of heavy metals (Peng et al. <lb/>2004). In this study, total metal concentrations followed the order of station S6 &gt; S3 &gt; S7 &gt; S9 &gt; S8 &gt; S5 &gt; S2 &gt; <lb/>S4 &gt; S1. <lb/>Along with particle size distribution and hydrodynamics, the proximity of contaminant sources plays an <lb/>important role in the distribution of the heavy metal concentrations in the Bizerte lagoon surface sediments. <lb/>Thereby, stations S6 and S3 located near the city of Menzel Bourguiba and Menzel Jemil showed an overall high <lb/>metal concentrations which could be due to the influence of active anthropogenic activities in the adjacent areas <lb/>including a number of sewerage systems and a metallurgic industry discharging domestic and industrial effluents <lb/>in to the lagoon. Altogether, industries and urban sources generate a daily average flow of wastewater of about <lb/>31,600 and 20,000 m 3 /day in the Bizerte Lagoon, respectively (MAERH 2003). Yoshida et al. (2002) measured <lb/>concentrations of heavy metal in bottom sediments of the Bizerte lagoon. They found high concentration in sites <lb/>situated nearby the landfill of Menzel Bourguiba (station S6). Our results confirm the relatively high metal <lb/>contamination of the Menzel Bourguiba&apos;s station found by Yoshida et al. (2002). <lb/>The highest concentrations were found for Fe, Zn, Mn, Ni and Pb. The elements Pb and Zn were generally <lb/>regarded as the identified elements of traffic pollution (Paterson et al. 1999; Dai 2001). The commercial ships <lb/>and small boats (for fishing) which use diesel as fuel are among the main vehicles in the Bizerte lagoon for <lb/>heavy metals. Therefore, traffic transportation might be a potential source of heavy metals in the study area. In <lb/>addition, antifouling paints used in boat maintenance in the south-western sector (SOCOMENA, society) of the <lb/>lagoon could be another source of Cu and Zn in surface sediments. Turner (2010) has demonstrated that <lb/>antifouling paint can be a source of Cu, Cd, Pb and Zn increase in sediments and emphasizes that release of <lb/>those metals is generated during boat maintenance and cleaning. Mn and Fe are considered particle size proxies <lb/>because they are conservative elements and a major constituent of clay minerals (Rubio et al. 2000; Aloupi and <lb/>Angelidis 2001; Burton et al. 2005). In addition, their gradients in the lagoon can be related to continental inputs <lb/>of matter from urban drainages. Nickel is very widespread at stations (S4, S6 and S8) situated close to the <lb/>industrial zones of Menzel Bourguiba and Menzel Jemil. Contamination of the Bizerte lagoon by Ni was also <lb/>

			observed in a precedent research study and was attributed to the closeness of the industrial zone (Yoshida et al. <lb/>2002; Ben Garali et al. 2010). <lb/>According to the study of industrial pollution control carried out in 1998, the amount of heavy metals <lb/>produced by the industrial sector in the Bizerte region is estimated at 141 tons / year (MAERH 2003). The main <lb/>pollution sources of heavy metals are: the steel complex -El Fouledh‖ and the society of maintenance and <lb/>construction of ships (SOCOMENA) at the city of Menzel Bourguiba; the factories of bolts (MATUBO) and <lb/>manufacturing of Spinning, Weaving and Crafts (MAFILTA) at the city of Menzel Jemil and the cement factory <lb/>at the Bizerte city. <lb/>The comparison of our results with those of the 1988-2010 campaigns (Kamens et al. 1989; Boufahja et al. <lb/>2007; El Ati Hellal et al. 2011; Ben Khedher et al. 2013) reveals an overall significant increase of Cd, Cu, Pb, Zn <lb/>and Ni concentrations in the sediments of the Bizerte lagoon (Table 3). During the 22 years time span, the <lb/>average concentrations of Cd and Cu were increased two-fold, while for Pb, Zn and Ni they were increased <lb/>three-fold, four-fold and twelve-fold, respectively. In contrast, the concentrations of Cr, Mn and Fe did not show <lb/>remarkable long-term changes. Our results indicate that the heavy metals content in the sediments of the Bizerte <lb/>lagoon is strongly affected in recent years by Cd, Cu, Pb, Zn and Ni emissions, outcome of the increasing <lb/>development of various industrial, agricultural and urban activities located around the lagoon. To gain a <lb/>comprehensive understanding of the degree of contamination of the Bizerte lagoon, a comparison of the heavy <lb/>metal concentrations with the average crust values and other regions was performed (Table 3). In surface <lb/>sediments from the Bizerte lagoon, the mean total contents of Cd, Pb, Ni and Zn were clearly higher with respect <lb/>to the average crust values. Compared to the data published for other regions, the metal contamination data for <lb/>the Bizerte lagoon indicated that the sediment was not as severely contaminated with Cd, Cr, Cu, Mn, Pb, Ni, <lb/>Hg, Zn, and Fe. The metal contamination in the sediment of the Bizerte lagoon was less severe than that of the <lb/>Pearl Sfax-Kerkennah plateau (Tunisia), Odiel-Tintod Estuary (Spain), Cishan River (China), and Golden Horn <lb/>Estuary (Turkey); however, it was worse than the contamination of the Daya Bay (China), Southern California <lb/>coastal shelf (USA) and Campeche shelf (Mexico). All of these regions have high population densities and <lb/>intense economic activity, and they received effluents from many of the industrial areas, sewage from a number <lb/>of major cities and agricultural runoff. Therefore, heavy metal pollution, which is introduced through rivers, <lb/>runoff, and land-based point sources, is very common in estuarine, lagoons and coastal regions (Christophoridis <lb/>et al. 2009; Qiao et al. 2013). <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>Indices of sediment contamination <lb/>The results of computed geoaccumulation index (Igeo) values are regrouped in Table and their spatial <lb/>distributions in sediments are presented in Fig. 3. This index consists of seven classes in relation to pollution <lb/>extent. According to Igeo values, sediments of Bizerte lagoon can be considered as unpolluted to moderately <lb/>polluted with Cd and Ni, unpolluted to strongly polluted with Zn and moderately to strongly polluted with Pb. <lb/>However, Cr, Cu, Mn and Fe, characterized by negative Igeo values, indicating absence of pollution by these <lb/>elements. <lb/>Contamination and possible anthropogenic impacts on the surface sediment in Bizerte lagoon was also <lb/>assessed using enrichment factor (EF). The mean EFs were calculated with respect to average crust (Martin and <lb/>Whitfield 1983) and are shown in Table 5. Their distribution patterns are illustrated in Fig. 4. The mean EF <lb/>values for all metals studied except Cr and Mn were &gt;1.5, suggesting anthropogenic discharges of metal in the <lb/>lagoon. The highest EF values were found at station S4. The EF values for Zn and Pb in the sediments of this <lb/>station were 72.0 and 66.1, respectively, indicating -extremely severe enrichment‖. The EF values for Ni and Cd <lb/>were between 10 and 25, indicating -severe enrichment‖. The EF value for Cu at station S4 was 5.9, indicating <lb/>-moderate to severe enrichment‖. However, no enrichment (EF&lt;1) was found for Cr and Mn whatever the <lb/>considered station. Zn had the highest EF value among the eight metals studied, followed by Pb. Lead at all <lb/>stations except S4 and S9 had the highest EF values among the eight metals studied. The EF values for other <lb/>studied metals indicated -minor to very severe enrichment‖ of sediments. Stations were ranked according to their <lb/>total EF values according to the following order: S4 &gt; S1 &gt; S8 &gt; S7 &gt; S2 &gt; S9 &gt; S5 &gt; S6 &gt; S3. <lb/>Considering the mean Igeo and EF values of heavy metals, it can be deduce that the Bizerte lagoon surface <lb/>sediments are highly polluted with Cd, Pb, Ni and Zn and therefore require urgent action from appropriate <lb/>quarters. According to these two contamination indices, station S4 appears as the most contaminated by trace <lb/>elements. This result is not surprising, since this station is located near the Menzel Jemil city with high <lb/>anthropogenic activities. <lb/>Sediment toxicity <lb/>We applied the Microtox ® Basic Test to evaluate the toxicity of sediment organic extracts from the nine <lb/>sampling stations studied. This bioassay was carried in order to provide information about the nonpolar <lb/>compounds, which are poorly available for pelagic organisms but can still exert adverse effects on benthic <lb/>dwelling organisms. In the concentration range tested (from 25 to 25x10 -5 g dw equivalent sediment), all <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>sediment organic extracts were very toxic to V. fischeri strain and caused 100% inhibition of bioluminescence <lb/>(data not shown). This toxicity can be related to presence of various organic pollutants in sediment of the Bizerte <lb/>lagoon in particular, PAHs, PCBs, organochlorinated pesticides (Barhoumi et al. 2014a, b). Using the Microtox ® <lb/>Basic Test, Salizzato et al. (1998) showed high toxicity for PAHs and PCBs to V. fischeri. <lb/>The Microtox 100% test was also used to evaluate the toxicity of sediment aqueous extracts (Elutriate). The <lb/>results expressed as milligrams dw of sediment are presented in Table 6 and the spatial distribution of acute <lb/>toxicity is depicted in Fig. 5a. At all stations, the EC50 (%) value was higher than 200 mg equivalent dry <lb/>sediment per mL -1 . The most toxic sediment aqueous extract was collected from stations S1, S4 and S9, with an <lb/>inhibition percentage between 20 and 40 % for 30 min exposure. The other samples are considered as no toxic <lb/>(inhibition below 20% for 30 min exposure). In contrast to S1, S4, S5, S7 and S9 extracts which showed an <lb/>increase in toxicity with increase exposure time, the S2, S3, S6 and S8 elutriates did not show time-dependent <lb/>increase/decrease in toxicity. Based on these results, the toxicity gradient decreases in the following order: <lb/>S1=S4=S9 &gt; S3=S7 &gt; S2=S5=S6=S8. Generally speaking, the elutriates prepared from sediments from the nine <lb/>sampled stations of the Bizerte lagoon exhibited a slight toxicity in the Microtox ® 100 % test. Data from <lb/>chemical analysis showed no significant correlation between metals content of sediment and acute toxicity of <lb/>elutriates. This poor correlation could be explained by the low metal bioavailability in aqueous extracts due to <lb/>the presence of a high content of organic matter in the Bizerte lagoon (Ouakad 2000; Ben Garali et al. 2013). <lb/>Campbell et al. (1988) showed that the presence of organic matter increases the retention of metals by the <lb/>formation of stable complexes between metal-clay-organic matter or metal-organic matter-clay. Also, high <lb/>content of organic matter may increase the Acid-volatile sulfides (AVS), which is an important carrier phase for <lb/>metals (Di Toro et al. 1990; Zheng and Xu 2003). Indeed, several studies have demonstrated an inverse <lb/>relationship between acute sediment toxicity and AVS in marine sediments (Di Toro et al. 1990; Ankley et al. <lb/>1991). When the levels of AVS increase, the binding of metals with sulfides increase, consequently, the <lb/>bioavailability of metals decreases. Concentrations of AVS within sediments depend on several factors including <lb/>organic matter supply, pH, temperature, particle size, sulfate reduction levels, and sediment redox conditions <lb/>(Gambrell 1994; Oehm et al. 1997; Liu et al. 2010). <lb/>In the same manner as metals content, acute toxicity of elutriates was not correlated to organic contaminants <lb/>accumulated in sediments. Toxicity of sediments may have resulted from additional components and <lb/>contaminants not analysed in the present study and the possible occurrence of synergistic or antagonistic <lb/>interactions between constituents present in sediment. For instance, organotins were not analysed in the present <lb/>

			study but have been detected at high concentrations (200 µg kg -1 ) in sediments from the Bizerte lagoon <lb/>(Mzoughi et al. 2005). Stasinakis et al. (2001) noted an inhibition of respiration rate of activated sludge <lb/>heterotrophic micro-organisms with increasing exposure time to tributyltin, dibutyltin and triphenyltin. The <lb/>hypothesis of the intervention of other none analysed toxicants was confirmed by the sediment of station S1 <lb/>which induced a high toxic effect to V. fischeri, despite having lower major and trace elements&apos; concentrations. <lb/>While it was not possible to correlate the observed toxic effects with any of the measured contaminants, it is <lb/>notable that station S4 which exhibits slight elutriate toxicity was consistently ranked the most polluted with all <lb/>contamination indices. <lb/>Elutriate testing was useful in exposing bacteria to water-soluble substances, which provided a realistic <lb/>estimation of pollutant bioavailability (Harkey et al. 1994). Unfortunately, the main limitations of this kind of <lb/>assay are the poor extraction efficiency of nonpolar compounds such as PCBs and polyaromatic hydrocarbons <lb/>and the toxicity measurement of only extractible and hydrosoluble compounds (Harkey et al. 1994). <lb/>Generally speaking, it seems clear that testing sediment toxicity using organic extracts with Microtox ® <lb/>bioassay could provide a better estimation of global toxicity than using elutriates. Similar results were observed <lb/>by Grant and Briggs (2002). <lb/>Genotoxicity <lb/>Genotoxicity of sediment organic extracts were analysed by the SOS Chromotest with and without S9 metabolic <lb/>activation system for detection of indirect and direct acting genotoxicants, respectively. Fig. 5b shows the spatial <lb/>distribution of the genotoxic potential of surface sediments of the Bizerte lagoon. In the absence of the S9 <lb/>microsomal fraction, the sediment extracts from station S1, S3 and S6 show significant differences compared to <lb/>station S7 (p&lt;0.01). In the presence of the S9 microsomal fraction, the sediment extracts from station S1 and S7 <lb/>show significant differences compared to stations S2, S4, S5, S6 and S8 (p&lt;0.01). Also, S3 was significantly <lb/>different from S4 and S8 (p&lt;0.01). According to Mersch-Sundermann et al. (1992), sediment extracts from S1, <lb/>S3 and S7 were moderately genotoxic (1.5&lt;IF&lt;2), and from slightly to no genotoxic from S2, S4, S5, S6, S8 and <lb/>S9 (with S9 microsomal fraction). In addition, sediments from station S1, S3 and S7 contained only pro-<lb/>genotoxic organic compounds since no genotoxic response was obtained without addition of an S9 microsomal <lb/>fraction. Bacterial assays have been widely used to assess the genotoxicity of suspended or bottom sediments <lb/>(reviewed in Chen and White 2004). The SOS responses obtained for the Bizerte lagoon with S9, ranged from <lb/>0.79 to 1.95 IF per gram of dw sediment. Those values were of the same order of magnitude, albeit slightly <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>lower, than those reported for sediments of the Seine estuary (Cachot et al. 2006). However, they are much lower <lb/>than found by Parrella et al. (2013) in the porewaters of two river basins in southern Italy. Previously reported <lb/>data (Dutka et al. 1996; Cachot et al. 2006) on the river sediments showed that PAHs and other POPs such as <lb/>PCBs and OCPs are pro-genotoxicants. In this study, sediments of stations S7 and S3 presented low content of <lb/>these compounds. So, the observed genotoxicity after the addition the S9 microsomal fraction may have resulted <lb/>from additional components and contaminants not analysed in the present study. Data from chemical analysis <lb/>showed also no significant correlation between any of the contaminants analyzed and genotoxicity of sediment <lb/>extracts. <lb/>Toxicity assessment of heavy metals in sediments based on the <lb/>SQGs <lb/>Several sediment quality guidelines (SQGs; including sediment quality criteria, sediment quality objectives, and <lb/>sediment quality standards) have been developed to assess the ecotoxicological hazard of trace elements in <lb/>sediments (MacDonald et al. 2000), such as effect range low (ERL) and effect range median (ERM), threshold <lb/>effect level (TEL) and probable effect level (PEL) values (Table 2). Three ranges in chemical concentrations <lb/>were defined, where adverse effects are observed rarely (&lt;ERL or &lt;TEL), occasionally (ERL-ERM or TEL-<lb/>PEL) and frequently (&gt;ERM or &gt;PEL). Sediment quality was predicted according to sediment quality guideline <lb/>levels for studied metals (Fig. 6). At almost all stations, the concentrations of Ni and Zn exceeded the PEL and <lb/>ERM values, indicating possible adverse effects of these metals. Although concentrations of Cd and Cr were <lb/>below the TEL and ERL values, Cd concentrations at 90% sites being between the TEL and PEL might cause <lb/>adverse effects occasionally. For other metals, 30% of sites were greater than PEL for Pb and 30% of sites were <lb/>being between the TEL and PEL for Cu, which also indicated a potential harm for benthic organisms. <lb/>Fig. 7 shows the mean toxic unit values (TU) and the sum of toxic units (ΣTU) of six heavy metals in <lb/>sediments from the Bizerte lagoon. The average toxic unit values of Cd, Cr, Cu, Pb, Ni and Zn in the studied <lb/>sediments were 0.21, 0.13, 0.21, 1.03, 3.34 and 3.08, respectively. The average ΣTU of these heavy metals was <lb/>always above 4 indicating moderate toxicity to sediment-dwelling fauna whatever the considered sediment <lb/>(Pedersen et al. 1998). Ni and Zn had higher contribution to ΣTU values, indicating that the sediment toxicity <lb/>was mainly ascribed to Zn and Ni. Copper contributed the least to ΣTU. The highest ΣTU value (14.9) was <lb/>observed at station S4 near the Menzel Jemil city, whereas the lowest ΣTU value (5.3) appeared at the exchange <lb/>point S1. <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>Pearson&apos;s correlation analysis <lb/>Correlation coefficients for phyciso-chemical and toxicological parameters are presented in. From this table, the <lb/>heavy metals Ni, Zn and Pb are positively correlated among themselves. Also Fe was highly correlated with Cr <lb/>and Mn. Contents of Cd and Cu were not correlated with none of the studied metals. According to Suresh et al. <lb/>(2011b), if the correlation coefficient between the metals is higher, metals have common sources, mutual <lb/>dependence and identical behavior during their transport. The absence of correlation among the other metals <lb/>suggests that the contents of these metals are not controlled by a single factor. However it is controlled by a <lb/>combination of geochemical support phases and their mixed associations. In the present study, Ni, Zn and Pb, on <lb/>one hand, and Fe, Cr and Mn on other hand, have common source whereas others have not. <lb/>The importance of physical and chemical properties of sediments, including the particle size distribution and <lb/>organic carbon in total sorption capacity for heavy metals and toxic potential of sediments, have been <lb/>documented in previous studies (Baptista Neto et al. 2000; Lin et al. 2002; Huang and Lin 2003). In some field <lb/>studies, strong correlations have been found between heavy metals and TOC content (Zabetoglou et al. 2002; <lb/>Neto et al. 2006), but there are also several field studies including this one in which the relationship between <lb/>concentrations of heavy metal and TOC is not so strong. The absence of correlation is sometimes considered as <lb/>an indicator of anthropogenic pollution; it has been documented that results from sites with high concentrations <lb/>of contaminants can distort and mask the correlation relationship with TOC (Evans et al. 1989). In contrast to <lb/>TOC, the mud (silt and clay) content of the studied sediments showed a significant positive correlation with Cd, <lb/>Cr, Mn, Fe and Σmetals, suggesting that the highest metal concentrations are associated with the fine-grained <lb/>sediments of the study area, as these components are more readily adsorbed on clay minerals. <lb/>The strong correlation (r&gt;0.90, p&lt;0.001) between Ni, Zn and Pb contents with the sum of toxic units (ΣTU), <lb/>indicated a high contribution of these three metals to ΣTU, as shown above. <lb/>Based on the results obtained in the present study, it can be concluded that deriving the potential toxicity of <lb/>sediments from the comparison of single contaminants with SQGs is a simplistic approach, as it does not take <lb/>into account the interaction between contaminants (e.g. antagonism, synergism and additive effects) and the <lb/>bioavailability of these contaminants, which can be the main causes of the potential toxicity (Chapman and <lb/>Mann 1999; Burton 2002; Choueri et al. 2009). This could explain the poor correlation (p&gt;0.05) observed in this <lb/>study between potential toxicity, based on comparison with SQG values, and global toxicity, based on the results <lb/>of bioassays. These findings highlight that SQGs can be used as a first line of evidence (e.g. Burton 2002; <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>Hübner et al. 2009) but that they should not be used alone for regulatory purposes (e.g. DelValls et al. 2004), as <lb/>decisions made based only on the results of the SQGs approach provides uncompleted conclusions. <lb/>The results from this study show clearly that it is important to carry out both chemical and ecotoxicological <lb/>analyses (SQGs and bioassays) to be able to correctly evaluate the potential toxicity and ecological risk of <lb/>sediments. Suter et al. (2000) and Fairbrother (2003) recommended that, within the ecological risk assessment <lb/>framework, multiple lines of evidence be evaluated to more fully characterize environmental risk of chemicals. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>The study provides a baseline for the quality assessment of surface sediments from the Bizerte lagoon (North <lb/>Tunisia) using an integrated approach. The highest concentrations of heavy metals were found near urban areas <lb/>with high anthropogenic activities. Total heavy metal concentrations in the sediment samples followed the order: <lb/>Fe &gt; Zn &gt; Mn &gt; Ni &gt; Pb &gt; Cu &gt; Cr &gt; Cd &gt; Hg. Enrichment factor (EF) and geo-accumulation index (Igeo) were <lb/>successfully applied for the assessment of heavy metals pollution in sediments of the Bizerte lagoon. These <lb/>indices indicate a widespread pollution by Cd, Pb, Ni and Zn in the Bizerte lagoon sediments and show that these <lb/>heavy metals originate from anthropogenic sources -mainly urban runoffs and industrial effluent discharges. <lb/>Comparison of data from this study and previous works suggest there is a progressive increase in metal <lb/>contamination in surface sediment over the past 20 years. <lb/>Toxicity assessment of heavy metals in sediments based on the SQGs suggests that toxicity affected by Ni <lb/>and Zn would be expected frequently. The TUs showed a decrease in an order Ni &gt; Zn &gt; Pb &gt; Cd=Cu &gt; Cr. In <lb/>contrast, the Microtox ® assay showed that sediment aqueous extracts were not or weakly toxic suggesting a low <lb/>mobility of contaminants in sediments. This result highlights the absolute necessity of a combine chemical and <lb/>toxicological approach for a reliable environmental risk assessment of sediments samples. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>The authors are grateful to the Tunisian Ministry of Higher Education and Scientific Research for the PhD. grant <lb/>of B. Barhoumi. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Compliance with Ethical Standards <lb/>This study was funded by the Tunisian Ministry of Higher Education and Scientific Research (MHESR) <lb/>(http://www.mesrst.tn). The authors are responsible for writing of the article and report no conflicts of financial, <lb/>consulting and personal interests. This article does not contain any studies with human participants or animals <lb/>performed by any of the authors. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Abd-el-Malek Y, Rizk SG (1963) Bacterial sulphate reduction and the development of alkalinity. II. Laboratory <lb/>Experiments with Soils. J Appl Bacteriol 26:14-19 <lb/>Aloupi M, Angelidis MO (2001) Geochemistry of natural and anthropogenic metals in the coastal sediments of <lb/>the island of Lesvos, Aegean Sea. Environ Pollut 113:211-219 <lb/>Ankley GT, Dierkes JR, Jensen DA, Peterson GS (1991) Piperonyl butoxide as a tool in aquatic toxicological <lb/>research with organophosphate insecticides. Ecotox Environ Saf 21:266-274 <lb/>Ankley GT, Schubauer-Berigan MK, Dierkes JR (1991) Predicting the toxicity of bulk sediments to aquatic <lb/>organisms with aqueous test fractions: Pore water vs. elutriate. Environ Toxicol Chem 10:1359-1365 <lb/>Atgın RS, El-Agha O, Zararsız A, Kocatas A, Parlak H, Tuncel G (2000) Investigation of the sediment pollution <lb/>in Izmir Bay: trace elements. Spectrochim Acta Part B 55:1151-1164 <lb/>Avila-Pérez P, Balcázar M, Zarazúa-Ortega G, Barceló-Quintal I, Dıaz-Delgado C (1999) Heavy metal <lb/>concentrations in water and bottom sediments of a Mexican reservoir. Sci Total Environ 234:185-196 <lb/>AZUR Environmental (1998) Microtox basic solid-phase test (Basic SPT). Carlsbad, CA, USA <lb/>Balls PW, Hull S, Miller BS, Pirie JM, Proctor W (1997) Trace metal in Scottish Estuarine and coastal <lb/>sediments. Mar Pollut Bull 34:42-50 <lb/>Baptista Neto JA, Smith BJ, Mcalliste JJ (2000) Heavy metal concentrations in surface sediments in a nearshore <lb/>environment, Jurujuba Sound, SE Brazil. Environ Pollut 109:1-9 <lb/>Barhoumi B, LeMenach K, Dévier MH, Ameur WB, Etcheber H, Budzinski H, Cachot J, Driss MR (2014b) <lb/>Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) in surface sediments from the Bizerte lagoon, Tunisia: levels, <lb/>sources and toxicological significance. Environ Monit Assess 186:2653-2669 <lb/>Barhoumi B, LeMenach K, Dévier MH, El megdiche Y, Hammami B, Ameur WB, Hassine, SB, Cachot J, <lb/>Budzinski H, Driss MR (2014a) Distribution and ecological risk of polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs) and <lb/>organochlorine pesticides (OCPs) in surface sediments from the Bizerte lagoon, Tunisia. Environ Sci <lb/>Pollut Res 21:6290-6302 <lb/>

			Basallote MD, Rodriguez-Romero A, Blasco J, Del Valls A, Riba I (2012) Lethal effects on different marine <lb/>organisms, associated with sediment-seawater acidification deriving from CO leakage. Environ Sci <lb/>Pollut Res 19:2550-2560 <lb/>Batley GE, Stahl RG, Babut MP, Bott TL, Clark JR, Field LJ, Ho KT, Mount DR, Swartz RC, Tessier A (2005) <lb/>Scientific underpinnings of sediment quality guidelines. In: Wenning RJ, Batley GE, Ingersoll CG, Moore <lb/>DW (eds) Use of Sediment Quality Guidelines and Related Tools for the Assessment of Contaminated <lb/>Sediments. SETAC Press, Pensacola, FL, pp 39-120 <lb/>Ben Amor R (2007) Géochimie des eaux et des se´diments du littoral (Ghannouche -Gabès) Impact des rejets de <lb/>phosphogypse, Thèse de doctorat en géologie, Faculté des Sciences de Tunis, p 189 <lb/>Ben Garali A, Ouakad M, Gueddari M (2010) Contamination of superficial sediments by heavy metals and iron <lb/>in the Bizerte lagoon, northern Tunisia. Arab J Geosci 3:295-306 <lb/>Ben Garali A, Ouakad M, Gueddari M (2013) Episodic Sedimentation of Heavy Metals and Iron in Bizerte <lb/>Lagoon, Northern Tunisia. Int J Geosci 4:24-35 <lb/>Ben-Khedher S, Jebali J, Kamel N, Banni M, Rameh M, Jrad A (2013) Hamadi Boussetta. Biochemical effects <lb/>in crabs (Carcinus maenas) and contamination levels in the Bizerta Lagoon: an integrated approach in <lb/>biomonitoring of marine complex pollution. Environ Sci Pollut Res 20:2616-2631 <lb/>Ben Said O, Goñi-Urriza M, El Bour M, Aissa P, Duran R (2010) Bacterial Community Structure of Sediments <lb/>of the Bizerte Lagoon (Tunisia), a Southern Mediterranean Coastal Anthropized Lagoon. Microb Ecol <lb/>59:445-456 <lb/>Birch G (2003) Ascheme for assessing human impacts on coastal aquatic environments using sediments. In <lb/>Woodcoffe CD, Furness RA (eds) Coastal GIS, Wollongong University Papers in Center for Marinetime <lb/>Pollicy, <lb/>14, <lb/>Austrailia. <lb/>Retrieved <lb/>from <lb/>http://www.ozestuaries.org/indicators/DEF_sedement_scheme.html <lb/>Boufahja F (2010) Approches communautaires et populationnelles de biosurveillance du milieu marin chez les <lb/>nématodes libres (lagune et baie de Bizerte, Tunisie). Thèse de Doctorat, Université du 7 Novembre à <lb/>Carthage, Tunisie <lb/>Boufahja F, Beyrem H, Essid N, Amorri J, Mahmoudi E, Aïssa P (2007) Morphometry, energetics and diversity <lb/>of free-living nematodes from coasts of Bizerte lagoon (Tunisia): an ecological meaning. Cah Biol Mar <lb/>48:121-137 <lb/>Bowen HTM (1979) Environmental Chemistry of the Elements. Academic Press, London <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Buccolieri A, Buccolieri G, Cardellicchio N, Dell&apos;Atti A, Di Leo A, Maci A (2006) Heavy metals in marine <lb/>sediments of Taranto Gulf (Ionian Sea, Southern Italy). Mar Chem 99:227-235 <lb/>Burton ED, Phillips IR, Hawker DW (2005) Trace metal distribution and enrichment in benthic, estuarine <lb/>sediments: Southport Broadwater, Australia. Environ Geochem Hlth 27:369-383 <lb/>Burton Jr., GA (2002) Sediment quality criteria in use around the World. Limnology 3:65-75 <lb/>Burton Jr., GA (2013) Assessing sediment toxicity: past, present, and future. Environ Toxicol Chem 32:1438-<lb/>1440 <lb/>Cachot J, Geffard O, Augagneur S, Lacroix S, Le Menach K, Peluhet L, Couteau J, Denier X, Devier MH, <lb/>Pottier D, Budzinski H (2006) Evidence of genotoxicity related to high PAH content of sediments in the <lb/>upper part of the Seine estuary (Normandy, France). Aquat Toxicol 79:257-267 <lb/>Caeiro S, Costa MH, Ramos TB, Fernandes F, Silveira N, Coimbra A, Medeiros G, Painho M (2005) Assessing <lb/>heavy metal contamination in Sado estuary sediment: an index analysis approach. Ecol Indic 5:151-169 <lb/>Campbell PGC, Lewis AG, Chapman PM, Crowder AA, Fletcher WK, Imber B, Luoma SN, Stokes PM, <lb/>Winfrey M (1988) Biological Available Metals in Sediments NRCC No 27694, Ottawa <lb/>Campana O, Blasco J, Simpson SL (2013) Demonstrating the appropriateness of developing sediment quality <lb/>guidelines based on sediment geochemical properties. Environ Sci Technol 47:7483-7489 <lb/>Chapman PM, Mann GS (1999) Sediment quality values (SQVs) and ecological risk assessment (ERA). Mar <lb/>Pollut Bull 38:339-344 <lb/>Chen G, White PA (2004) The mutagenic hazards of aquatic sediments: a review. Mutat Res 567:151-225 <lb/>Chen SY, Lin JG (2001) Bioleaching of heavy metals from sediment: significance of pH. Chemosphere <lb/>44:1093-1102 <lb/>Cheung YH, Neller A, Chu KH, Tam NFY, Wong CK, Wong YS, Wong MH (1997) Assessment of sediment <lb/>toxicity using different trophic organisms. Arch Environ Toxicol Chem 32:260-267 <lb/>Choueri RB, Cesar A, Abessa DM, Torres RJ, Morais RD, Riba I, Pereira CDS, Nascimento MRL, Mozeto AA, <lb/>DelValls TA (2009) Development of site-specific sediment quality guidelines for North and South <lb/>Atlantic littoral zones: comparison against national and international sediment quality benchmarks. J <lb/>Hazard Mater 170:320-331 <lb/>Christophoridis C, Dedepsidis D, Fytianos K (2009) Occurrence and distribution of selected heavy metals in the <lb/>surface sediments of Thermaikos Gulf, N. Greece. Assessment using pollution indicators. J Hazard Mater <lb/>168:1082-1091 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Cook, JA, Andrew SM, Johnson MS (1990) Lead, zinc, cadmium and fluoride in small mammals from <lb/>contaminated grass-land established on fluorspar tailings. Water Air Soil Poll 51:43-54 <lb/>Dai S (2001) Environmental chemistry. Beijing: Beijing, Higher Education Press (In Chinese) <lb/>DelValls TA, Andres A, Belzunce MJ, Buceta JL, Casado-Martínez MC, Castro R, Riba I, Viguri JR, Blasco J <lb/>(2004) Chemical and ecotoxicological guidelines used for managing disposal of dredged material. Trend <lb/>Anal Chem 23:819-828 <lb/>Deniseger J, Erickson J, Austin A, Roch M, Clark MJR (1990) The effects of decreasing heavy metal <lb/>concentrations on the biota of Buttle Lake. Water Res 24:403-416 <lb/>Di Toro DM, Mahony JD, Hansen DJ, Scott KJ, Hicks MB, Mayr SM, Redmond MS (1990). Toxicity of <lb/>cadmium in sediments: the role of acid volatile sulfide. Environ Toxicol Chem 9:1487-1502 <lb/>Dutka BJ, Mclnnis R, Jurkovic A, Liu D (1996) Water and Sediment Ecotoxicity Studies in Temuco and Rapel <lb/>River Basin, Chile. Environ Toxicol Water Qual 11:237-247 <lb/>El Ati Hellal M, Hellal F, El Khemissi Z, Jebali R, Dachraoui M (2011) Trace Metals in Algae and Sediments <lb/>from the North-Eastern Tunisian Lagoons. Bull Environ Contam Toxicol 86:194-198 <lb/>Environnement Canada (1992) Méthode d&apos;essai biologique: essai de toxicité sur la bactérie luminescente <lb/>Photobacterium phosphoreum, SPE 1/RM/24, no. cat. En49-24/1-24F, ISBN 0-662-98128-6 <lb/>Ergin M, Ediger V, Bodur MN, Okyar M (1990) A review of modern sedimentation in the Golden Horn estuary <lb/>(Sea ofMarmara), Turkey. Bollettino Dı Oceanologıa Teorica Ed Applicata, III (2), 135-151 <lb/>Ergin M, Saydam C, Basturk O, Erdem E, Yoruk R (1991) Heavy metal concentrations in surface sediments <lb/>from the two coastal inlets (Golden Horn Estuary and Izmit Bay) of the northeastern sea of Marmara. <lb/>Chem Geol 91:269-285 <lb/>Essid N, Aissa P (2002) Etude quantitative des nématodes libres des secteurs Nord et Est de la lagune de Bizerte <lb/>(Tunisie). Bulletin de l&apos;Institut National des Sciences et Technologies de la Mer de Salammbô, Tunisia, <lb/>29:53-63 <lb/>Etcheber H, Taillez A, Abril G, Garnier J, Servais P, Moatar F, Commarieu MV (2007) Particulate organic <lb/>carbon in the estuarine turbidity maxima of the Gironde, Loire and Seine estuaries: origin and lability. <lb/>Hydrobiologia 588:245-259 <lb/>Evans HE, Evans RD, Lingard SM (1989) Factors affecting the variation in the average molecular-weight of <lb/>dissolved organic-carbon in freshwaters. Sci Total Environ 81/82:297-306 <lb/>Fairbrother A (2003) Lines of evidence in wildlife risk assessments. Hum Ecol Risk Assess 9:1475-1491 <lb/>

			FAO (1975) Manual of methods of analysis for heavy metals in aquatic environment reseach, PartI : method for <lb/>detection, measurement and monitoring of water pollution. FAO Fisheries Technical Paper N 137, United <lb/>Nation <lb/>Feng H, Cochran JK, Lwiza H, Brownawell B, Hirschberg DJ (1998) Distribution of heavy metal and PCB <lb/>contaminants in the sediments of an urban estuary: the Hudson River. Mar Environ Res 45:69-88 <lb/>Filgueiras AV, Lavilla I, Bendicho C (2004) Evaluation of distribution, mobility and binding behaviour of heavy <lb/>metals in surficial sediments of Louro River (Galicia, Spain) using chemometric analysis: a case study. <lb/>Sci Total Environ 330:115-129 <lb/>Fukue M, Nakamura T, Kato Y, Yamasaki S (1999) Degree of pollution for marine sediments. Eng Geol <lb/>53:131-137 <lb/>Gagné F, Pardos M, Blaise C, Turcotte P, Quémerais B, Fouquet A (1999) Toxicity evaluation of organic <lb/>sediment extracts resolved by size exclusion chromatography using rainbow trout hepatocytes. <lb/>Chemosphere 39:1545-1570 <lb/>Gambrell RP (1994) Trace and toxic metals in Wetland e a review. J Environ Qual 23:883-891 <lb/>Gao XL, Chen CTA, Wang G, Xue QZ, Tang C, Chen SY (2010) Environmental status of Daya Bay surface <lb/>sediments inferred from a sequential extraction technique. Estuar Coast Shelf S 86:369-378 <lb/>Ghannem N, Azri C, Sarbeji MM, Yaich C (2010) Spatial Distribution of Heavy Metals in the Coastal Zone of <lb/>‗‗Sfax-Kerkennah&apos;&apos; Plateau, Tunisia. Environ Prog Sustain Energy 30:221-233 <lb/>Ghannem N, Gargouri D, Sarbeji MM, Yaich C, Azri C (2014) Metal contamination of surface sediments of the <lb/>Sfax-Chebba coastal line, Tunisia. Environ Earth Sci 72:3419-3427 <lb/>Grant A, Briggs AD (2002) Toxicity of sediments from around a North Sea oil platform: are metals or <lb/>hydrocarbons responsible for ecological impacts? Mar Environ Res 53:95-116 <lb/>Guven DE, Akinci G (2013) Effect of sediment size on bioleaching of heavy metals from contaminated <lb/>sediments of Izmir Inner Bay. J Environ Sci 25:1784-1794 <lb/>Harkey GA, Landrum PF, Klaine SJ (1994) Comparison of whole-sediment, elutriate and pore-water exposures <lb/>for use in assessing sediment-associated organic contaminants in bioassays. Environ Toxicol Chem <lb/>13:1315-1329 <lb/>Harzallah A (2003) Transport de polluants dans la lagune de Bizerte simulé par un modèle de circulation de <lb/>l&apos;eau. Bull &apos;Inst Natl Sci Technol Mer Salambôo 30:121-133 <lb/>Heida H, Van der Oost R (1996) Sediment pore water toxicity testing. Water Sci Technol 34:109-116 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Heitmann T, Blodau C (2006) Oxidation and incorporation of hydrogen sulfide by dissolved organic matter. <lb/>Chem Geol 235:12-20 <lb/>Huang K, Lin S (2003) Consequences and implication of heavy metal spatial variations in sediments of Keelung <lb/>River drainage basin, Taiwan. Chemosphere 53:1113-1121 <lb/>Hübner R, Astin KB, Herbert RJH (2009) Comparison of sediment quality guidelines (SQG) for the assessment <lb/>of metal contamination in marine and estuarine environments. J Environ Monitor 11:713-722 <lb/>ISO (1999) Determination of the inhibitory effect of water samples on the light emission of Vibrio fischerie <lb/>(luminescent bacteria test). Part 3: method using freeze dried bacteria. European Standard ISO 11348-<lb/>3:1998. Bruxelles: European Committee for Standardization <lb/>Kamens J, Pilkey O, Whaling P, Harbridge W, Chaouch A (1989) Etude sédimentologique des lacs de Bizerte et <lb/>de Tunis. Notes du Service Géologique. Office National des Mines, number 57, Tunis, Tunisie <lb/>Karageorgis AP, Sioulas AI, Anagnostou CL (2002) Use of surface sediments in Pagassitikos Gulf, Greece, to <lb/>detect anthropogenic influence. Geo-Mar Lett 21:200-211 <lb/>Kharaka YK, Robinson SW, Law LM, Carothers WW (1994) Hydrogeochemistry of Big Soda Lake, Nevada: an <lb/>alkaline meromictic desert lake. Geochim Cosmochim Acta 48:823-835 <lb/>Lim HS, Lee JS, Chon HT, Sager M (2008) Heavy metal contamination and health risk assessment in the <lb/>vicinity of the abandoned Songcheon Au-Ag mine in Korea. J Geochem Explor 96:223-230 <lb/>Lin S, Hsieh IJ, Huang KM, Wamg CH (2002) Influence of the Yangtze River and grain size on the spatial <lb/>variations of heavy metals and organic carbon in the East China Sea continental shelf sediments. Chem <lb/>Geol 182:377-394 <lb/>Liu JC, Yan CL, Spencer KL, Zhang RF, Lu HL (2010) The distribution of acid-volatile sulfide and <lb/>simultaneously extracted metals in sediments from a mangrove forest and adjacent mudflat in Zhangjiang <lb/>Estuary, China. Mar Pollu Bull 60:1209-1216 <lb/>Long ER, Chapman PM (1985) A sediment quality triad: measures of sediment contamination, toxicity and <lb/>infaunal community composition in Puget Sound. Mar Pollu Bull 16:405-415 <lb/>Louati H, Said OB, Got P, Soltani A, Mahmoudi E, Cravo-Laureau C, Duran R, Aissa P, Pringault O (2013) <lb/>Microbial community responses to bioremediation treatments for the mitigation of low-dose anthracene in <lb/>marine coastal sediments of Bizerte lagoon (Tunisia). Environ Sci Pollut Res 20:300-310 <lb/>MacDonald DD, Ingersoll CG, Berger TA (2000) Development and evaluation of consensus-based sediment <lb/>quality guidelines for freshwater ecosystems. Arch Environ Con Tox 39:20-31 <lb/>

			Macı as-Zamora JV, Villaescusa-Celaya JA, Muñoz-Barbosa A, Gold-Bouchot G (1999) Trace metals in <lb/>sediment cores from the Campeche shelf, Gulf of Mexico. Environ Pollut 104:69-77 <lb/>MAERH (2003) Etude sur la dépollution industrielle dans le bassin versant du lac de Bizerte. Rapport, Ministère <lb/>de l&apos;Agriculture, de l&apos;Environnement et des Ressources Hydrauliques, Tunis, p 182 <lb/>Martin JM, Whitfield M (1983) The significance of the river input of chemical elements to the ocean. In: Wong <lb/>CS, Boyle E, Brul KW, Burton JD, Goldberg ED (eds) Trace metals in sea water, New York, Plenum <lb/>Press, pp 265-296 <lb/>Memet V (2011) Assessment of heavy metal contamination in sediments of the Tigris River (Turkey) using <lb/>pollution indices and multivariate statistical techniques. J Hazard Mater 195:355-364 <lb/>Mersch-Sundermann V, Mochayedi S, Kevekordes S (1992) Genotoxicity of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons <lb/>in Escherichia coli PQ37. Mutat Res 278:1-9 <lb/>Michael PS, Fitzpatrick R, Reid R (2015) The role of organic matter in ameliorating acid sulfate soils with <lb/>sulfuric horizons. Geoderma 255-256:42-49 <lb/>Mills AL, Herlihy AT (1985) Microbial ecology and acidic pollution of impoundments. In: Gunnison D (ed) <lb/>Microbial Processes in Reservoirs. Dr. W. Junk Publishers, Dordrecht, pp 169-189 <lb/>Mouldi B, Bejaoui B, Atoui A (2008) Etude de l&apos;hydrodynamique sédimentaire de la lagune de Bizerte. Bulletin <lb/>de l&apos;Institut National des Sciences et Technologies de la Mer de Salammbô, Tunisia 35:149-160 <lb/>Mucha AP, Vasconcelos MTSD, Bordalo AA (2003) Macro benthic community in the Douro Estuary: relations <lb/>with trace metals and natural sediment characteristics. Environ Pollut 121:169-180 <lb/>Muller G (1981) Die Schwermetallbelastung der sedimente des Neckars und seiner Nebenflusse: eine <lb/>Bestandsaufnahme. ChemZtg 105:157-164 <lb/>Mzoughi N, Lespes G, Bravo M, Dachraoui M, Potin-Gautier M (2005) Organotin speciation in Bizerte lagoon <lb/>(Tunisia). Sci Total Environ 349:211-222 <lb/>Naji A, Ismail A (2011) Assessment of metals contamination in Klang River surface sediments by using <lb/>different indexes. Environ Asia 4:30-38 <lb/>Neto JAB, Gingele FX, Leipe T, Brehme I (2006) Spatial distribution of heavy metals in surficial sediments <lb/>from Guanabara Bay: Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. Environ Geol 49:1051-1063 <lb/>Nolting R, Ramkema A, Everaats J (1999) The geochemistry of Cu, Cd, Zn, Ni and Pb in sediment cores from <lb/>the continental slope of the Banc d&apos;Arguin (Mauritania). Cont Shelf Res 19:665-691 <lb/>

			Oehm NJ, Luben TJ, Ostrofsky MJ (1997) Spatial distribution of acid-volatile sulfur in the sediments of <lb/>Canadohta Lake, PA. Hydrobiology 345:79-85 <lb/>Okay OS, Legovic T, Tufekçi V, Egesel L, Morkoç E (1996) Environmental impact of land-based pollutants on <lb/>Izmit Bay (Turkey): short-term algal bioassays and simulation of toxicity distribution in the marine <lb/>environment. Arch Environ Contam Toxicol 31:459-465 <lb/>Oliveira A, Palma C, Valença M (2011) Heavy metal distribution in surface sediments from the continental shelf <lb/>adjacent to Nazare´ canyon. Deep-Sea Res Pt II 58:2420-2432 <lb/>Ouakad M (2000) Caractères sédimentologiques et géochimiques des dépôts superficiels de la lagune de Bizerte <lb/>(Tunisie septentrionale), pp 187-194 <lb/>Ouakad M (2007) Genèse et évolution des milieux laguno-lacustres du Nord-Est de la Tunisie (Garaet el Ichkeul, <lb/>Lagunes de Bizerte et Ghar el Mehl), Thèse d&apos;état en Sciences Géologiques, Faculté des Sciences de <lb/>Tunis, p 461 <lb/>Parrella A, Lavorgna M, Criscuolo E, Isidori M (2013) Mutagenicity, Genotoxicity, and Estrogenic Activity of <lb/>River Porewaters. Arch Environ Contam Toxicol 65:407-420 <lb/>Paterson E, Sanka M, Clark L (1999) Urban soil as pollutant sinks-a case study from Aberdeen, Scotland. Appl <lb/>Geochem 11:129-131 <lb/>Pedersen F, Bjørnestad E, Andersen HV, Kjølholt J, Poll C (1998) Characterization of sediments from <lb/>Copenhagen Harbour by use of biotests. Water Sci Technol 37:233-240 <lb/>Peng XT, Zhou FY, Ye Y, Chen GQ (2004) Characteristics of sediment grain size and their implications for <lb/>bottom hydrodynamic environment in the Pearl River Estuary. Acta Sedimentol Sin 22:487-493 <lb/>Qiao YM, Pan H, Yang Y, Gu JG, Zhao JG (2013) Distribution and accumulation of heavy metals in surface <lb/>sediments from a subtropical bay affected by the Special Economic Zone, China. Water Sci Technol <lb/>67:2009-2016 <lb/>Quillardet P, Hofnung M (1985) The SOS Chromotest, a colorimetric bacterial assay for genotoxins: procedures. <lb/>Mutat Res 147:65-78 <lb/>Quillardet P, Huisman O, D&apos;Ari R, Hofnung M (1982) SOS Chromotest, adirect assay of induction of an SOS <lb/>function in Escherichia coli K-12 to measure genotoxicity. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 79:5971-5975 <lb/>Reddy KR, DeLaune RD (2008) Biogeochemistry of Wetlands: Science and Applications. CRC Press, Boca <lb/>Raton, p 744 <lb/>

			Lamotte M, Donard OF, Sierra EJ, Robert M (1996) Metal contamination in surface sediments of mangroves, <lb/>lagoons and Southern Bay in Florianopolis Island. Environ Technol 17:1035-1046 <lb/>Rubio B, Nombela MA, Vilas F (2000) Geochemistry of major and trace elements in sediments of the Ria de <lb/>Vigo (NW Spain): an assessment of metal pollution. Mar Pollut Bull 40:968-980 <lb/>Ruiz F (2001) Trace metals in estuarine sediments from the southwestern Spanish coast. Mar Pollut Bull 42:481-<lb/>489 <lb/>Sakka Hlaili A, Chikhaoui MA, El Grami B, Hadj Mabrouk H (2003) Variation hivernoestivale de la <lb/>communauté phytoplanctonique de la lagune de Bizerte en milieux naturel et fertilisé en nutriments. <lb/>Revue de la Faculté des Sciences de Bizerte, Tunisia, 2:37-49 <lb/>Salizzato M, Pavoni B, Volpi-Ghirardini A, Ghetti PF (1998) Sediment toxicity measured using Vibrio fischeri <lb/>as related to the concentrations of organic (PCBs, PAHs) and inorganic (metals, sulphur) pollutants. <lb/>Chemosphere 36:2949-2968 <lb/>Savinov VM, Savinova TN, Carroll J, Mathisov GG, Dahle S, Naes K (2000) Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons <lb/>(PAHs) in sediments of the White Sea, Russia. Mar Pollut Bull 40:807-818 <lb/>Schiff KC, Weisberg SB (1999) Iron as a reference element for determining trace metal enrichment in Southern <lb/>California coast shelf sediments. Mar Environ Res 48:161-176 <lb/>Sekabira K, OryemOriga H, Basamba T, Mutumba G, Kakudidi E (2010) Assessment of heavy metal pollution <lb/>in the urban stream sediments and its tributaries. Int J Environ Sci Technol 7:435-446 <lb/>Selvaraj K, Rammohan V, Szefer P (2004) Evaluation of metal contamination in coastal sediments of the Bay of <lb/>Bengal, India: geochemical and statistical approaches. Mar Pollut Bull 49:174-185 <lb/>Singh KP, Mohan D, Singh VK, Malik A (2005) Studies on distribution and fractionation of heavy metals in <lb/>Gomti River sediments-a tributary of the Ganges, India. J Hydrol 312:14-27 <lb/>Srarfi F (2007) Etude géochimique et état de pollution de la lagune de Bizerte. Thèse de doctorat, Univ. Tunis el <lb/>Manar, Tunis, Tunisie, p 122 <lb/>Stasinakis AS, Thomaidis NS, Lekkas TD (2001) Toxicity of organotin compounds to activated sludge. <lb/>Ecotoxicol Environ Saf 49:275-280 <lb/>Stone M, Droppo IG (1994) Chemical characteristics and implications for contaminant transport in fluvial <lb/>systems. Part II. Hydrol Process 8:113-124 <lb/>

			Suresh G, Ramasamy V, Meenakshisundaram V, Venkatachalapathy R, Ponnusamy V (2011b) Influence of <lb/>mineralogical and heavy metal composition on natural radionuclide contents in the river sediments. Appl <lb/>Radiat Isot 69:1466-1474 <lb/>Suter GW, Efroymson RA, Sample BE, Jones DS (2000) Ecological Risk Assessment for Contaminated Sites. <lb/>Lewis Pub., Boca Raton, FL <lb/>Svenson A, Edsholt E, Ricking M, Remberger M, Rottorp J (1996) Sediment contaminants and Microtox toxicity <lb/>tested in a direct contact exposure test. Environ Toxic Water 11:293-300 <lb/>Turner A (2010) Marine pollution from antifouling paint particles. Mar Pollut Bull 60:159-171 <lb/>Varol M (2011) Assessment of heavy metal contamination in sediments of the Tigris River (Turkey) using <lb/>pollution indices and multivariate statistical techniques. J Hazard Mater 195:355-364 <lb/>Wang W, Qin Y, Song D, Wang K (2008) Column leaching of coal and its combustion residues, Shizuishan, <lb/>China. Int J Coal Geol 75:81-87 <lb/>Weng HX, Zhu YM, Qin YC, Chen JY, Chen XH (2008) Accumulation discrepancy of heavy metal and organic <lb/>pollutants in three near-shore depositional environments, southeastern China. J Asian Earth Sci 31:522-<lb/>532 <lb/>Wenning RJ, Ingersoll CG (eds) (2002) Executive Summary of the SETAC Pellston Workshop on Use of <lb/>Sediment Quality Guidelines and Related Tools for the Assessment of Contaminated Sediments. Society <lb/>of Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry (SETAC), Pensacola, FL, USA <lb/>Wong CKC, Cheung RYH, Wong MH (1999) Toxicological assessment of coastal sediments in Hong Kong <lb/>using a flagellate, Dunaliella tertiolecta. Environ Pollut 105:175-183 <lb/>Yoshida M, Hamdi H, Abdul Nasser I, Jedidi N (2002) Contamination of potentially toxic elements (PTEs) in <lb/>Bizerte lagoon bottom sediments, surface sediment and sediment repository RPPSEPMCL Initial Report, <lb/>pp 13-48 <lb/>Zabetoglou K, Voutsa D, Samara C (2002) Toxicity and heavy metal contamination of surficial sediments from <lb/>the Bay of Thessaloniki (Northwestern Aegean Sea) Greece. Chemosphere 49:17-26 <lb/>Zheng L, Xu XQ (2003) On the vertical distribution and influencing factors of acid-volatile sulfide in the <lb/>sediments of Donghu Lake (Wuhan). J Lake Sci 15:245-251 <lb/>Zheng N, Wang QC, Liang ZZ, Zheng DM (2008) Characterization of heavy metal concentrations in the <lb/>sediments of three freshwater rivers in Huludao City, Northeast China. Environ Pollut 154:135-142 <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Figure captions <lb/>Figure Map of the studied area with location of sampling stations <lb/>Figure 2 Spatial distributions of heavy metal concentrations in surface sediments of the Bizerte lagoon <lb/>Figure 3 Spatial distributions of Igeo values for surface sediments of the Bizerte lagoon <lb/>Figure 4 Spatial distributions of EF values for surface sediments of the Bizerte lagoon <lb/>Figure 5 Spatial distribution of acute toxicity (a) and genotoxicity (b) of surface sediments of the Bizerte lagoon. <lb/>Genotoxicity was measured using the SOS chromotest following bioactivation of pro-genotoxicants with S9 <lb/>fraction <lb/>Figure 6 Prediction of the quality of sediments from the Bizerte lagoon according to sediment quality guideline <lb/>levels for studied metals (MacDonald et al. 2000) <lb/>Figure 7 Toxic unit (TU) of each metal and sum of toxic units (∑TU) of six heavy metals for each sampled <lb/>sediment from the Bizerte lagoon. The solid line (∑TU = 4) represents the threshold above which the toxic <lb/>degree of heavy metals is considered moderate to serious <lb/>Table Captions <lb/>Table 1 Sampling site location and physicochemical characteristics of the studied sediments from the <lb/>Bizerte lagoon. The pH of the water column above the sediments (pH H2O ) was, also, reported <lb/>on <lb/>Depth (m) <lb/>Temperature (°C) Salinity (psu) pH sed <lb/>pH H2O <lb/>TOC (%) <lb/>%&lt;63 <lb/>e <lb/>Longitude <lb/>.905&apos; N <lb/>9°49.491&apos; E <lb/>2.5 <lb/>13.6 <lb/>35.2 <lb/>7.2 <lb/>6.8 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>11. <lb/>.945&apos; N <lb/>9°48.310&apos; E <lb/>4.2 <lb/>14.2 <lb/>34.6 <lb/>7.2 <lb/>6.8 <lb/>2.2 <lb/>57. <lb/>.920&apos; N <lb/>9°50.460&apos; E <lb/>12.1 <lb/>13.5 <lb/>35.1 <lb/>7.8 <lb/>7.4 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>89. <lb/>.998&apos; N <lb/>9°55.602&apos; E <lb/>3.0 <lb/>13.5 <lb/>35.5 <lb/>7.8 <lb/>7.4 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>32. <lb/>.214&apos; N <lb/>9°48.170&apos; E <lb/>4.8 <lb/>15.4 <lb/>35.2 <lb/>8.1 <lb/>7.6 <lb/>1.3 <lb/>65. <lb/>.024&apos; N <lb/>9°50.533&apos; E <lb/>10.3 <lb/>13.5 <lb/>35.3 <lb/>8.2 <lb/>7.9 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>90. <lb/>.957&apos; N <lb/>9°51.355&apos; E <lb/>9.9 <lb/>13.3 <lb/>35.2 <lb/>8.2 <lb/>7.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>87. <lb/>.011&apos; N <lb/>9°54.763&apos; E <lb/>6.9 <lb/>14.0 <lb/>35.5 <lb/>8.1 <lb/>7.9 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>89. <lb/> 910 <lb/> Table 2 Results of chemical analysis for metals (mg kg <lb/>-1 dw, mean value ± standard deviation, n = 3) <lb/>and organic compounds (ng g <lb/>-1 dw) of the fine (&lt;2 mm) sediment fraction for the nine sampling <lb/>912 <lb/>stations in the Bizerte lagoon <lb/>&lt; LD: below the detection limit <lb/>914 <lb/>Stations with different letters are significantly different (p&lt;0.001) <lb/>915 <lb/>a ERL= effect range-low; b ERM = effect range-median; c TEL = threshold effect level; d PEL = <lb/>916 <lb/>probable effect level <lb/>917 <lb/>e Values taken from Barhoumi et al. (2014b) <lb/>918 <lb/>f,g Values taken from Barhoumi et al. (2014a) <lb/>919 <lb/>e <lb/>∑ = naphthalene, acenaphthene, fluorene, phenanthrene, anthracene, fluoranthene, pyrene, <lb/>920 <lb/>benzo[a]anthracene, chrysene, benzo[b]fluoranthene, benzo[k]fluoranthene, benzo[a]pyrene, <lb/>921 <lb/>dibenzo[a,h]anthracene and benzo[g,h,i]perylene <lb/>922 <lb/>f <lb/>∑ =Congeners 28+31, 52, 44, 101, 149, 118, 153, 138, 180, 194, 209 <lb/>923 <lb/>g ∑ = p,p&apos;-DDT, p,p&apos;-DDE, p,p&apos;-DDD <lb/>924 <lb/>925 <lb/>Table 3 Geoaccumulation index, Muller&apos;s classification and ranges of heavy metals in surface <lb/>926 <lb/>sediments of the Bizerte lagoon <lb/>927 <lb/>.282&apos; N <lb/>9°52.641&apos; E <lb/>7.6 <lb/>14.1 <lb/>35.0 <lb/>7.5 <lb/>7.1 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>85. <lb/>S2 <lb/>S3 <lb/>S4 <lb/>S5 <lb/>S6 <lb/>S7 <lb/>S8 <lb/>S9 <lb/>ERL <lb/> a <lb/>E <lb/>0.7±0.0 c <lb/>0.9±0.2 bce <lb/>1.0±0.0 be <lb/>0.8±0.1 bc <lb/>1.0±0.0 be <lb/>0.9±0.0 be <lb/>1.1±0.1 de <lb/>1.1±0.0 de <lb/>1.20 <lb/>21.8±0.4 c <lb/>30.5±2.3 d <lb/>12.9±0.3 b <lb/>20.3±1.0 c <lb/>30.8±0.8 d <lb/>27.6±0.3 e <lb/>20.3±0.2 c <lb/>22.9±0.1 cf <lb/>81.00 <lb/>23.8±1.6 c <lb/>11.4±0.5 d <lb/>37.6±0.7 ab <lb/>36.0±0.2 b <lb/>45.2±0.8 a <lb/>6.5±0.3 d <lb/>20.7±0.4 c <lb/>4.0±0.1 d <lb/>34.00 <lb/>168.0±0.0 a <lb/>263.4±10.6 c <lb/>105.2±2.8 d <lb/>150.6±1.1 e <lb/>239.6±7.7 f <lb/>213.7±1.5 g 170.5±2.2 a <lb/>197.4±1.5 h <lb/>95.7±5.1 de <lb/>106.2±1.4 df <lb/>211.2±1.1 b <lb/>85.1±1.2 e <lb/>90.0±3.1 de <lb/>121.5±6.8 f <lb/>177.5±9.8 c <lb/>89.2±6.7 e <lb/>46.70 <lb/>b <lb/> 92.8±1.3 c <lb/>73.8±2.1 d <lb/>240.7±0.7 e <lb/>101.5±1.0 f <lb/>167.7±3.6 a <lb/>161.7±0.3 a 199.2±1.5 g <lb/>110.9±1.3 h <lb/>20.90 <lb/>&lt; LD <lb/>&lt; LD <lb/>&lt; LD <lb/>&lt; LD <lb/>&lt; LD <lb/>&lt; LD <lb/>&lt; LD <lb/>&lt; LD <lb/>0.15 <lb/>b 630.0±24.6ac 741.0±10.1ce 1825.5±98.1d 455.5±134.7ab <lb/>605.9±18.4ac 864.2±60.0e 1291.0±32.3f 774.0±49.4ce 150.00 <lb/>12844.6± <lb/>176.4 b <lb/>17215.5± <lb/>171.8 ef <lb/>7168.2±66.1 c 14122.5± <lb/>472.6d <lb/>18019.3± <lb/>169.8 e <lb/>16598.5± <lb/>973.5 ef <lb/>14507.9± <lb/>391.7 d <lb/>16168.0± <lb/>204.3 f <lb/>13877.4± <lb/>146.6 d <lb/>18442.7± <lb/>228.3 eg <lb/>9602.2± <lb/>162.5 b <lb/>14972.3 ± <lb/>523.5 cd <lb/>19199.5± <lb/>182.5 g <lb/>17994.5± <lb/>1039.3 eg <lb/>16388.1± <lb/>355.4 cf <lb/>17367.5± <lb/>259.9 ef <lb/>69.7 <lb/>76.7 <lb/>73.3 <lb/>102.8 <lb/>57.5 <lb/>49.2 <lb/>34.9 <lb/>70.8 <lb/>5.2 <lb/>4.7 <lb/>2.3 <lb/>2.1 <lb/>2.9 <lb/>2.2 <lb/>4.2 <lb/>5.3 <lb/> 10.6 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>uller 1981) <lb/>This study <lb/>Class <lb/>Quality of sediment <lb/>Heavy metal <lb/>I geo range <lb/>Quality of sediment <lb/>0 <lb/>Unpolluted <lb/>Cd <lb/>0.0 to 1.9 <lb/>From unpolluted to mode <lb/>1 <lb/>From unpolluted to moderately polluted <lb/>Cr <lb/>-3.9 to -1.8 <lb/>Unpolluted <lb/>2 <lb/>Moderately polluted <lb/>Cu <lb/>-3.6 to -0.4 <lb/>Unpolluted <lb/>From moderately to strongly polluted <lb/>Mn <lb/>-3.9 to -2.0 <lb/>Unpolluted <lb/>Strongly polluted <lb/>Pb <lb/>1.8 to 3.1 <lb/>From moderately to stro <lb/></body>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body>928 <lb/>Table Metal enrichment factors (EFs) for sediments of all studied sites in the Bizerte lagoon <lb/>Sites <lb/>Metal EFs <lb/>Cd <lb/>Cr <lb/>Cu <lb/>Mn <lb/>Pb <lb/>Ni <lb/>Zn <lb/>Fe <lb/>S1 <lb/>12.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>6.0 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>33.5 <lb/>23.5 <lb/>21.4 <lb/>1 <lb/>S2 <lb/>9.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>2.1 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>16.7 <lb/>5.2 <lb/>13.9 <lb/>1 <lb/>S3 <lb/>9.4 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>13.8 <lb/>3.1 <lb/>12.2 <lb/>1 <lb/>S4 <lb/>25.0 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>5.9 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>66.1 <lb/>24.1 <lb/>72.0 <lb/>1 <lb/>S5 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>2.9 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>13.5 <lb/>5.2 <lb/>9.1 <lb/>1 <lb/>S6 <lb/>10.0 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>2.8 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>11.2 <lb/>6.7 <lb/>9.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>S7 <lb/>9.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>16.4 <lb/>7.0 <lb/>14.7 <lb/>1 <lb/>S8 <lb/>13.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>27.5 <lb/>9.9 <lb/>25.2 <lb/>1 <lb/>S9 <lb/>12.2 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>12.4 <lb/>4.9 <lb/>13.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>Mean <lb/>12.5 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>23.5 <lb/>9.9 <lb/>21.3 <lb/>1 <lb/>Min <lb/>1.2 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>11.2 <lb/>3.1 <lb/>9.1 <lb/>Max <lb/>13.6 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>66.1 <lb/>24.1 <lb/>72.0 <lb/>1 <lb/>930 <lb/>Table 5 Toxicity (mg mL <lb/>-1 <lb/>) of elutriates of sediments collected from nine stations of the Bizerte lagoon <lb/>931 <lb/>and measured with the Microtox <lb/>® assay <lb/>932 <lb/>Station <lb/>Exposure time <lb/>(min) <lb/>Percentage of inhibition (%) <lb/>a <lb/>EC 50 (mg mL <lb/>-1 <lb/>) <lb/>S1 <lb/>8.7 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>10.1 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>22.3 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>S2 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>5.1 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>S3 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>18.1 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>S4 <lb/>8.2 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>10.1 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>24.1 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>S5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>4.8 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>9.2 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>S6 <lb/>2.8 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>6.7 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>S7 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>6.8 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>18.4 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>S8 <lb/>3.9 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>2.3 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>9.1 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>5 <lb/>From strongly to extremely polluted <lb/>Ni <lb/>0.0 to 1.7 <lb/>From unpolluted to mode <lb/>6 <lb/>Extremely polluted <lb/>Zn <lb/>0.7 to 3.3 <lb/>From unpolluted to strong <lb/>Fe <lb/>-3.7 to -1.6 <lb/>Unpolluted <lb/></body>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<body>S9 <lb/>3.9 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>12.5 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>29.4 <lb/>&gt;200 <lb/>a <lb/>At the highest tested concentration of mg equivalent dry sediment per mL <lb/>-1 <lb/>Table 6 Pearson correlation coefficients between chemical, physico-chemical variables and <lb/>biological endpoints for sediments of the Bizerte lagoon <lb/>Cd <lb/>Cr <lb/>Cu <lb/>Mn <lb/>Pb <lb/>Ni <lb/>Zn <lb/>Fe <lb/>Microtox <lb/>® <lb/>SOS Chr <lb/>(+ S <lb/>1 <lb/>0.561 <lb/>1 <lb/>-0.063 <lb/>-0.177 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.563 <lb/>-0.276 <lb/>-0.276 <lb/>0.547 <lb/>-0.144 <lb/>0.145 <lb/>-0.144 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.314 <lb/>-0.330 <lb/>0.379 <lb/>-0.361 <lb/>0.777* <lb/>1 <lb/>0.588 <lb/>-0.144 <lb/>0.097 <lb/>-0.132 <lb/>0.979*** <lb/>0.766* <lb/>1 <lb/>0.652 <lb/>0.958*** <lb/>-0.273 0.940*** <lb/>-0.143 <lb/>-0.330 <lb/>-0.147 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.727* <lb/>0.952*** <lb/>-0.222 <lb/>0.798** <lb/>-0.030 <lb/>-0.239 <lb/>-0.032 <lb/>0.993*** <lb/>-0.301 <lb/>-0.0 <lb/>-0.863** <lb/>-0.660 <lb/>0.118 <lb/>-0.628 <lb/>-0.533 <lb/>-0.292 <lb/>-0.520 <lb/>-0.698* <lb/>0.286 <lb/>0.3 <lb/></body>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body>Numbers in bold indicate significant correlations. Asterisks indicate the signification of the correlations: <lb/> 937 <lb/> *p&lt;0.05; **p&lt;0.01; ***p&lt;0.001 <lb/> 938 <lb/>939 <lb/> 0.389 <lb/>0.401 <lb/>-0.459 <lb/>0.479 <lb/>-0.043 <lb/>-0.444 <lb/>0.012 <lb/>0.454 <lb/>-0.053 <lb/>-0.2 <lb/>-0.064 <lb/>0.169 <lb/>-0.126 <lb/>0.148 <lb/>-0.163 <lb/>-0.464 <lb/>-0.154 <lb/>0.142 <lb/>-0.486 <lb/>-0.2 <lb/>0.601 <lb/>0.531 <lb/>0.234 <lb/>0.464 <lb/>0.340 <lb/>0.366 <lb/>0.263 <lb/>0.060 <lb/>-0.292 <lb/>-0.1 <lb/>0.637 <lb/>0.662 <lb/>0.227 <lb/>0.469 <lb/>0.394 <lb/>0.435 <lb/>0.311 <lb/>0.565 <lb/>-0.325 <lb/>-0.1 <lb/>0.738* <lb/>0.904*** <lb/>-0.299 0.905*** <lb/>0.010 <lb/>-0.194 <lb/>-0.005 <lb/>0.973*** <lb/>-0.272 <lb/>-0.0 <lb/>0.135 <lb/>0.160 <lb/>0.150 <lb/>0.109 <lb/>0.081 <lb/>-0.215 <lb/>0.205 <lb/>0.095 <lb/>-0.439 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>-0.298 <lb/>-0.180 <lb/>0.357 <lb/>-0.276 <lb/>-0.197 <lb/>-0.406 <lb/>-0.251 <lb/>-0.151 <lb/>-0.408 <lb/>-0.3 <lb/>0.012 <lb/>-0.335 <lb/>-0.494 <lb/>-0.228 <lb/>0.095 <lb/>0.117 <lb/>0.239 <lb/>-0.322 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>omotest (+ S9) <lb/>-0.480 <lb/>0.062 <lb/>-0.599 <lb/>0.119 <lb/>-0.404 <lb/>-0.312 <lb/>-0.413 <lb/>-0.035 <lb/>0.349 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.525 <lb/>-0.207 <lb/>0.255 <lb/>-0.218 <lb/>0.960*** <lb/>0.909*** 0.962*** <lb/>-0.209 <lb/>0.156 <lb/>-0.4 </body>


	</text>
</tei>
