<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Computer Methods and Programs in Biomedicine (2005) 77, 129-139 <lb/>Robust tests for the multivariate Behrens-Fisher <lb/>problem <lb/>Lisa M. Lix a, * , H.J. Keselman b , Aynslie M. Hinds a <lb/>a Department of Community Health Sciences, Faculty of Medicine, University of Manitoba, 408-727 <lb/>McDermot Avenue, Winnipeg, Man., Canada R3E 3P5 <lb/>b Department of Psychology, University of Manitoba, Winnipeg, Man., Canada R3T 2N2 <lb/>Received 2 December 2003 ; received in revised form 9 July 2004; accepted 9 September 2004 <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>Multivariate; <lb/>Mean equality; <lb/>Two-group design; <lb/>Robust estimation; <lb/>Covariance <lb/>heterogeneity <lb/>Summary Hotelling&apos;s T 2 procedure is used to test the equality of means in two-<lb/>group multivariate designs when covariances are homogeneous. A number of alter-<lb/>natives to T 2 , which are robust to covariance heterogeneity, have been proposed in <lb/>the literature. However, all are sensitive to departures from multivariate normal-<lb/>ity. We demonstrate how to obtain multivariate tests that are robust to covariance <lb/>heterogeneity and non-normality with estimators of location and scale based on <lb/>trimming and Winsorizing. The performance of six alternatives to T 2 was examined <lb/>via Monte Carlo methods when characteristics of the research design, degree of co-<lb/>variance heterogeneity, and degree of non-normality were manipulated. We have <lb/>recently developed a program written in the SAS/IML language that can be used to <lb/>implement these robust multivariate tests. Recommendations are provided on the <lb/>specific data-analytic conditions under which these tests should be adopted. <lb/>© 2004 Elsevier Ireland Ltd. All rights reserved. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>Medical researchers are frequently interested in <lb/>testing hypotheses about the efficacy of treatments <lb/>for two independent groups of subjects. Treatment <lb/>effectiveness is often assessed using multiple out-<lb/>come variables [1-3], such as physiological re-<lb/>sponses and subjective assessments of quality of <lb/>life [4]. <lb/></body>

			<front>* Corresponding author. Tel.: +1 204 9757799; <lb/>fax: +1 204 7893910. <lb/>E-mail address: lisa lix@cpe.umanitoba.ca (L.M. Lix). <lb/></front>

			<body>Student&apos;s t-statistic is the conventional approach <lb/>for testing the equality of population means for <lb/>two independent groups on a single outcome vari-<lb/>able when population variances are equal and the <lb/>data are normally distributed. It is well known that <lb/>Student&apos;s t is sensitive to departures from the as-<lb/>sumption of variance homogeneity and that Welch&apos;s <lb/>statistic [5] should be favored when variances are <lb/>unequal. However, because Welch&apos;s statistic is sen-<lb/>sitive to departures from a normal distribution, <lb/>Reed [6] considered a modification when normality <lb/>can not be assumed. A robust test can be obtained <lb/>by trimming/Winsorizing the most extreme obser-<lb/>vations from the tails of a distribution, a solution <lb/>0169-2607/$ -see front matter © 2004 Elsevier Ireland Ltd. All rights reserved. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.cmpb.2004.09.002 <lb/></body>

			<page>130 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">L.M. Lix et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>recommended by Yuen and Dixon [7] and Yuen [8], <lb/>prior to computing Welch&apos;s statistic. <lb/>The multivariate extension of Student&apos;s t-<lb/>procedure, Hotelling&apos;s T 2 [9], tests the equality of <lb/>means on multiple outcome variables. The T 2 test <lb/>rests on the assumptions of equality of the group <lb/>covariances and a joint normal distribution for the <lb/>outcomes. T 2 is biased when covariances are het-<lb/>erogeneous [10-12], particularly when the design is <lb/>unbalanced, that is, when group sizes are unequal. <lb/>A number of alternatives, which are robust (i.e., <lb/>insensitive) to covariance heterogeneity, have been <lb/>proposed in the literature [13-19]. Like T 2 , all of <lb/>these procedures rely on the assumption of multi-<lb/>variate normality. <lb/>When the data are obtained from non-normal <lb/>distributions, multivariate procedures for testing <lb/>mean equality will produce biased results, partic-<lb/>ularly when the design is unbalanced [10,20-23]. <lb/>Wilcox [23] demonstrated that a two-group multi-<lb/>variate procedure, which is robust to the effects of <lb/>both covariance heterogeneity and non-normality <lb/>may be obtained by substituting robust estimators <lb/>for the usual (i.e., least-squares) means and covari-<lb/>ances in procedures, which are robust to covariance <lb/>heterogeneity. More specifically, Wilcox derived ro-<lb/>bust analogues of the Johansen [24] and Kim [16] <lb/>procedures by replacing least-squares estimators <lb/>with estimators based on trimming/Winsorization. <lb/>He observed that both of these robust procedures <lb/>controlled the rate of Type I errors to the nominal <lb/>level of significance, α, when covariances were het-<lb/>erogeneous and the data were non-normal. More-<lb/>over, these procedures were more powerful than <lb/>those based on least-squares estimators when the <lb/>data were obtained from skewed or heavy-tailed <lb/>distributions. <lb/>Fouladi and Yockey [25] examined six alterna-<lb/>tives to Hotelling&apos;s T 2 [9] under conditions of co-<lb/>variance heterogeneity, including James&apos; first and <lb/>second-order [14], Johansen [24], Kim [16], Nel and <lb/>van der Merwe [17], and Yao [19] procedures. None <lb/>of the procedures demonstrated superior perfor-<lb/>mance across all data-analytic conditions; each was <lb/>influenced by such factors as total sample size, the <lb/>ratio of the group sizes, the correlation between <lb/>outcome variables, and the ratio of the group sizes <lb/>to the number of outcome variables. While Fouladi <lb/>and Yockey [25] observed that the presence of non-<lb/>normal data did not have an adverse effect on the <lb/>Type I error control of the alternate procedures, <lb/>they considered only very modest departures from <lb/>normality. Previous research has demonstrated the <lb/>sensitivity of multivariate procedures to departures <lb/>from normality, particularly when the distributions <lb/>are skewed [26]. <lb/>This paper extends previous research by Reed <lb/>[6] on robust tests for two-group univariate de-<lb/>signs to the multivariate context. The Type I error <lb/>performance of several alternatives to Hotelling&apos;s <lb/>T 2 [9] test under departures from the assumptions <lb/>of covariance homogeneity and multivariate nor-<lb/>mality are compared. The investigated procedures <lb/>include those considered by Fouladi and Yockey <lb/>[25] in addition to a multivariate extension of <lb/>the Brown-Forsythe [27] procedure [28,29]. These <lb/>tests are investigated when least-squares estima-<lb/>tors are employed and when least-squares esti-<lb/>mators are replaced with robust estimators based <lb/>on trimming/Winsorization. A computer program to <lb/>implement these robust strategies is described and <lb/>a numeric example is presented. <lb/>2. Methods with least-squares <lb/>estimators <lb/>Let Y ij = [Y ij1 ••• Y ijp ] represent the vector of p out-<lb/>come measurements for the ith subject in the jth <lb/>group (i = 1, . . ., n j ; j = 1, 2; N = n j ). It is assumed <lb/>that Y ij follows a multivariate normal distribution <lb/>with mean j and variance-covariance matrix j <lb/>(i.e., Y ij ∼ N[ j , j ]). The vector j = [µ j1 , µ j2 , . . ., <lb/>µ jp ] is estimated byȲ j = [Ȳ j1Ȳj2 • • •Ȳ jp ] and j is <lb/>estimated by S j. The null hypothesis is: <lb/>H 0 : 1 = 2 . <lb/>(1) <lb/>The Brown-Forsythe (BF; [27]) procedure is <lb/>based on the test statistic, <lb/>T BF = (Ȳ 1 −Ȳ 2 ) <lb/>T [w • <lb/>1 S 1 + w • <lb/>2 S 2 ] −1 (Ȳ 1 −Ȳ 2 ), <lb/>(2) <lb/>where w • <lb/>j = 1 − w j and w j = n j /N. This T-statistic <lb/>can be expressed as an F-statistic, <lb/>F BF = <lb/>ν BF2 <lb/>pf B2 <lb/>T BF , <lb/>(3) <lb/>where ν BF2 = f B2 − p + 1 and <lb/>f B2 = <lb/>tr(G 1 ) 2 + tr 2 (G 1 ) <lb/>1 <lb/>n 1 − 1 <lb/>tr(w • <lb/>1 S 1 ) 2 + tr 2 (w • <lb/>1 S 1 ) <lb/>+ <lb/>1 <lb/>n 2 − 1 <lb/>tr(w • <lb/>2 S 2 ) 2 + tr 2 (w • <lb/>2 S 2 ) <lb/>. <lb/>(4) <lb/>In Eq. (4), tr denotes the trace of a matrix and <lb/>G 1 = w • <lb/>1 S 1 + w • <lb/>2 S 2 . The original df formulation pro-<lb/>vided by Brown and Forsythe results in a test pro-<lb/>cedure that is not asymptotically correct. The df <lb/>calculations suggested by Mehrotra [30] (see also <lb/>[29]) is recommended instead. Accordingly, the test <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Robust tests for the multivariate Behrens-Fisher problem <lb/></note>

			<page>131 <lb/></page>

			<body>statistic F BF is compared to a critical value from the <lb/>F-distribution, F[1 − ␣, v BF1 , v BF2 ], where <lb/>ν BF1 = <lb/>tr(G 1 ) 2 + tr 2 (G 1 ) <lb/>tr(G 2 ) 2 + tr 2 (G 2 ) + tr w • <lb/>1 S 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>+tr w • <lb/>2 S 2 <lb/>2 + tr 2 w • <lb/>1 S 1 <lb/>+tr 2 w • <lb/>2 S 2 <lb/>, <lb/>(5) <lb/>and G 2 = w 1 S 1 + w 2 S 2 . <lb/>The James second-order (J2; [14]) and Johansen <lb/>(J; [24]) procedures are obtained from the test <lb/>statistic, <lb/>T 2 = (Ȳ 1 −Ȳ 2 ) <lb/>T S 1 <lb/>n 1 <lb/>+ <lb/>S 2 <lb/>n 2 <lb/>−1 <lb/>(Ȳ 1 −Ȳ 2 ). <lb/>(6) <lb/>For the J2 procedure, T 2 is referred to a <lb/>critical value from the χ 2 distribution, χ 2 <lb/>p (1 − ␣, <lb/>A + χ 2 <lb/>p B) + q, where χ 2 <lb/>p is the (1 − ␣) percentile point <lb/>of the 2 distribution with p df, <lb/>A = 1 + <lb/>1 <lb/>2p <lb/>1 <lb/>n 1 − 1 <lb/>tr(A −1 A 1 ) <lb/>2 + <lb/>1 <lb/>n 2 − 1 <lb/>tr(A −1 A 2 ) <lb/>2 , <lb/>(7) <lb/>where A j = S j /n j , A = A 1 + A 2 and <lb/>B = <lb/>1 <lb/>p(p + 2) <lb/>1 <lb/>n 1 − 1 <lb/>tr(A −1 A 1 A −1 A 1 ) <lb/>+ <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>tr(A −1 A 1 ) <lb/>2 + <lb/>1 <lb/>n 2 − 1 <lb/>tr(A −1 A 2 A −1 A 2 ) <lb/>+ <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>tr(A −1 A 2 ) <lb/>2 <lb/>. <lb/>(8) <lb/>The constant, q is based on a lengthy formula which <lb/>has not been reproduced here; it can be found in <lb/>Eqs. (6) and (7) of James [14]. <lb/>For the J procedure, let F J = T 2 /c 2 where <lb/>c 2 = p + 2C − 6C/(p + 1) and <lb/>C = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>j=1 <lb/>1 <lb/>n j − 1 <lb/>tr(A −1 A j ) <lb/>2 + tr 2 (A −1 A j ). <lb/>(9) <lb/>The test statistic F J is compared to the critical <lb/>value F[1 − ␣, p, v J ], where v J = p(p + 2)/3C. <lb/>The Kim (K; [16]) procedure is based on the test <lb/>statistic, <lb/>F K = <lb/>v K (Ȳ 1 −Ȳ 2 ) <lb/>T V −1 (Ȳ 1 −Ȳ 2 ) <lb/>c 1 mf 1 <lb/>, <lb/>(10) <lb/>where V=A 1 +r 2 A 2 + 2rA <lb/>1/2 <lb/>2 (A <lb/>−1/2 <lb/>2 <lb/>A 1 A <lb/>−1/2 <lb/>2 <lb/>) <lb/>1/2 <lb/>A <lb/>−1/2 <lb/>2 <lb/>, <lb/>c 1 = <lb/>p <lb/>l=1 <lb/>h 2 <lb/>l <lb/>p <lb/>l=1 <lb/>h l <lb/>, <lb/>(11) <lb/>m = <lb/>p <lb/>l=1 <lb/>h l <lb/>2 <lb/>p <lb/>l=1 <lb/>h 2 <lb/>l <lb/>, <lb/>(12) <lb/>h l = (d l + 1)/(d <lb/>1/2 <lb/>l <lb/>+ r) <lb/>2 <lb/>, where d l is the lth eigen-<lb/>value of A 1 A −1 <lb/>2 , r = |A 1 A −1 <lb/>2 | 1/(2p) , and |•| is the de-<lb/>terminant of a matrix. The test statistic F K is com-<lb/>pared to the critical value F[1 − ␣, m, v K ], where <lb/>v K = f 1 − p + 1, <lb/>f 1 = <lb/>2 <lb/>j=1 <lb/>1 <lb/>n j − 1 <lb/>T 2 <lb/>b j <lb/>2 <lb/>, <lb/>(13) <lb/>and b j = (Ȳ 1 −Ȳ 2 ) <lb/>T V −1 A j V −1 (Ȳ 1 −Ȳ 2 ). <lb/>The procedure due to Nel and van der Merwe (NV; <lb/>[17]) is also obtained from the test statistic of Eq. <lb/>(6). Let <lb/>F NV = <lb/>v N T 2 <lb/>pf N2 <lb/>, <lb/>(14) <lb/>where v N = f N2 − p + 1 and <lb/>f N2 = (trA 2 + tr 2 A) <lb/>2 <lb/>j=1 <lb/>1 <lb/>n j − 1 <lb/>(trA 2 <lb/>j + tr 2 A j ). (15) <lb/>The F NV statistic is compared to the critical value <lb/>F[1 − ␣, p, ν N ]. <lb/>Finally, for the Yao (Y; [19]) procedure, the <lb/>statistic, <lb/>F Y = <lb/>ν K T 2 <lb/>pf 1 <lb/>, <lb/>(16) <lb/>is evaluated using the critical value F[1 − ␣, p, v K ]. <lb/>3. Methods with robust estimators <lb/>To illustrate the computation of the trimmed mean, <lb/>let Y (1)j ≤ Y (2)j ≤ ••• ≤ Y (n j )j , represent the ordered <lb/>observations for the jth group on a single out-<lb/>come variable. Then, let g j = [γn j ], where γ rep-<lb/>resents the proportion of observations that are to <lb/>be trimmed in each tail of the distribution and [x] is <lb/></body>

			<page>132 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">L.M. Lix et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>the greatest integer ≤x. The sample trimmed mean <lb/>is: <lb/>Y t = <lb/>1 <lb/>h j <lb/>n j −g j <lb/>i=g+1 <lb/>Y (i)j , <lb/>(17) <lb/>where h j = n j − 2g j . Both fixed and adaptive trim-<lb/>ming rules have been proposed in the literature. <lb/>With the former, a fixed proportion of the obser-<lb/>vations is trimmed from each tail of the distri-<lb/>bution; between 10% and 20% trimming is recom-<lb/>mended [31]. With an adaptive trimming approach, <lb/>the amount of trimming in each tail is determined <lb/>based on summary descriptive measures of distri-<lb/>bution shape. A fixed 20% trimming approach was <lb/>adopted in the present study, consistent with the <lb/>work of Wilcox [23]. <lb/>The Winsorized variance is the theoretically cor-<lb/>rect measure of scale that corresponds to the <lb/>trimmed mean [8]. To obtain the Winsorized vari-<lb/>ance, first compute the sample Winsorized mean, <lb/>Y wj = <lb/>1 <lb/>n j <lb/>n j <lb/>i=1 <lb/>Z ij . <lb/>(18) <lb/>where <lb/>Z ij = <lb/> <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/>Y (g j +1)j if Y ij ≤ Y (g j +1)j <lb/>Y ij <lb/>if Y (g j +1)j &lt; Y ij &lt; Y (n j −g j )j <lb/>Y (n j −g j )j if Y ij ≥ Y (n j −g j )j <lb/>. <lb/>The Winsorized variance is <lb/>s 2 <lb/>wj = <lb/>n j <lb/>i=1 <lb/>(Z ij −Ȳ wj ) <lb/>2 <lb/>(n j − 1) <lb/>, <lb/>(19) <lb/>and the standard error of the trimmed mean is (n j − <lb/>1)s 2 <lb/>wj /[h j (h j − 1)]. <lb/>For multivariate data, the Winsorized covariance <lb/>for outcome variables l and l (l, l = 1, . . ., p) is <lb/>s wjll = <lb/>n j <lb/>i=1 <lb/>(Z ijl −Ȳ wjl )(Z ijl −Ȳ wjll ) <lb/>(n j − 1) <lb/>, <lb/>(20) <lb/>and the estimate of error covariance is (n j − <lb/>1)s w jll /[h j (h j − 1)]. <lb/>A test which is robust to the biasing effects <lb/>of both multivariate non-normality and covariance <lb/>heterogeneity can be obtained by using one of the <lb/>BF, J2, J, K, NV, or Y test statistics, and substitut-<lb/>ing trimmed means and the Winsorized covariance <lb/>matrix for the least-squares mean and covariance <lb/>matrix [23]. For example, with robust estimators, <lb/>the T 2 statistic of Eq. (6) becomes <lb/>T t2 = (Ȳ t1 −Ȳ t2 ) <lb/>T (n 1 − 1)S w1 <lb/>h 1 (h 1 − 1) <lb/>+ <lb/>(n 2 − 1)S w2 <lb/>h 2 (h 2 − 1) <lb/>−1 <lb/>×(Ȳ t1 −Ȳ t2 ), <lb/>(21) <lb/>whereȲ tj and S wj are the trimmed mean vector and <lb/>Winsorized covariance matrix for the jth group, re-<lb/>spectively. Note that trimming is conducted inde-<lb/>pendently for each dimension of the data [26]. <lb/>4. Simulation methods <lb/>A Monte Carlo study was used to evaluate the Type <lb/>I error performance of Hotelling&apos;s T 2 [9] and the six <lb/>alternatives for the two-group multivariate prob-<lb/>lem. Eight factors were manipulated in the study. <lb/>These were: (a) number of outcome variables, (b) <lb/>degree of correlation between outcome variables, <lb/>(c) total sample size, (d) degree of group size bal-<lb/>ance/imbalance, (e) equality/inequality of group <lb/>covariance matrices, (f) degree of inequality of <lb/>group covariance matrices, (g) nature of the pair-<lb/>ing of group sizes and group covariance matrices, <lb/>and (h) population distribution. The choice of fac-<lb/>tor levels was based on previous research. <lb/>The value of p, the number of outcome vari-<lb/>ables, was set at two, four, and eight. The degree <lb/>of correlation among the outcome variables, was <lb/>set at ρ = 0.1, 0.5, and 0.8. Without loss of general-<lb/>ity, the correlation was introduced for the second-<lb/>group only, while the intercorrelation among the <lb/>outcome variables for the first group was set at <lb/>ρ = 0 [25]. <lb/>Small, moderate, and large total sample size <lb/>conditions were examined for each value of p such <lb/>that the total number of observations ranged from <lb/>18 to 192. For p = 2, the ratio of N/p was set at 9, <lb/>18, and 24, while for p = 4 and 8 this ratio was set <lb/>at 9, 12, and 24. Both balanced and unbalanced de-<lb/>signs were considered in the study. When the design <lb/>was unbalanced, the group size conditions were se-<lb/>lected to represent a range of values for the ratio of <lb/>the smallest group size to p (i.e., n min /p) and the <lb/>corresponding coefficient of variation of the group <lb/>sizes, n j , where <lb/>n j = <lb/>J <lb/>j=1 <lb/>(n j −n) <lb/>2 /J <lb/>n <lb/>, <lb/>(22) <lb/>andn = n j /J. Table 1 presents the values of both <lb/>the ratio and the coefficient for each combination <lb/>of p and N. The ratio n min /p ranged in value from <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Robust tests for the multivariate Behrens-Fisher problem <lb/></note>

			<page>133 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1 Group sizes for unbalanced designs <lb/>p a <lb/>N <lb/>Group sizes <lb/>n min/p <lb/>n j <lb/>2 <lb/>18 <lb/>6, 12 <lb/>3.00 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>36 <lb/>6, 30 <lb/>3.00 <lb/>2.83 <lb/>12, 24 <lb/>6.00 <lb/>1.41 <lb/>48 <lb/>6, 42 <lb/>3.00 <lb/>3.67 <lb/>12, 36 <lb/>6.00 <lb/>2.45 <lb/>18, 30 <lb/>9.00 <lb/>1.22 <lb/>4 <lb/>36 <lb/>12, 24 <lb/>3.00 <lb/>1.41 <lb/>48 <lb/>12, 36 <lb/>3.00 <lb/>2.45 <lb/>18, 30 <lb/>4.50 <lb/>1.22 <lb/>96 <lb/>12, 84 <lb/>3.00 <lb/>5.20 <lb/>18, 78 <lb/>4.50 <lb/>4.33 <lb/>24, 72 <lb/>6.00 <lb/>3.46 <lb/>8 <lb/>72 <lb/>24, 48 <lb/>3.00 <lb/>2.00 <lb/>96 <lb/>18, 78 <lb/>2.25 <lb/>4.33 <lb/>24, 72 <lb/>3.00 <lb/>3.46 <lb/>192 <lb/>24, 168 <lb/>3.00 <lb/>7.35 <lb/>36, 156 <lb/>4.50 <lb/>6.12 <lb/>48, 144 <lb/>6.00 <lb/>4.90 <lb/>60, 132 <lb/>7.50 <lb/>3.67 <lb/>a p is the number of dependent variables, N the total sam-<lb/>ple size, n min /p the ratio of the smallest group size to p, and <lb/>n j is the coefficient of variation of the group sizes. <lb/>2.25 to 7.5, while n j ranged in value from 1 to <lb/>7.35. <lb/>The procedures were investigated when the <lb/>group covariance matrices were equal and unequal. <lb/>In the latter case, both moderate and large de-<lb/>grees of covariance inequality were examined. In <lb/>the moderate inequality case, the matrices were in <lb/>the ratio of 1:5. In the large covariance inequality <lb/>case, the matrices were in a ratio of 1:9. <lb/>Both positive and negative pairings of group sizes <lb/>and covariance matrices were investigated. A pos-<lb/>itive pairing refers to the case in which the largest <lb/>n j is associated with the covariance matrix contain-<lb/>ing the largest element values; a negative pairing <lb/>refers to the case in which the largest n j is associ-<lb/>ated with the covariance matrix with the smallest <lb/>element values. <lb/>Type I error rates were obtained when the data <lb/>were both multivariate normal and non-normal in <lb/>form. For the former, pseudorandom observation <lb/>vectors Y ij from a multivariate normal distribution <lb/>with mean vector ␤ j and covariance matrix j were <lb/>obtained using the SAS generator RANNOR [32]. To <lb/>obtain each Y ij , a row vector of p deviates in which <lb/>each element has a standard normal distribution <lb/>(i.e., Z ij ), was transformed to a vector of multi-<lb/>variate observations via a triangular (Cholesky) de-<lb/>composition <lb/>Y ij = ␤ j + LZ T <lb/>ij , <lb/>(23) <lb/>where L is a upper triangular matrix of dimension p <lb/>satisfying the equality L T L = j . Three non-normal <lb/>distributions were investigated: heavy-tailed, mod-<lb/>erately skewed, and highly skewed. The heavy-<lb/>tailed distribution had skewness (γ 1 ) and kurto-<lb/>sis (γ 2 ) values equivalent to those of a double-<lb/>exponential distribution (i.e., γ 1 = 0; γ 2 = 3). The <lb/>moderately skewed distribution had the same skew-<lb/>ness and kurtosis values as an exponential distribu-<lb/>tion (i.e., γ 1 = 2; γ 2 = 6). The highly skewed distribu-<lb/>tion had γ 1 = 6.18 and γ 2 = 110.93, which are equiv-<lb/>alent to the shape parameters of a lognormal distri-<lb/>bution. The non-normal data were generated by the <lb/>method developed by Fleishman [33] and extended <lb/>to the multivariate situation by Vale and Maurelli <lb/>[34]. <lb/>The simulation program was written in the <lb/>SAS/Interactive Matrix Language (IML) pro-<lb/>gramming language [35]. For each of the <lb/>3 × 3 × 3 × 4 = 108 combinations of p, ρ, N, and <lb/>population distribution, we examined both equal <lb/>and unequal covariance matrices for balanced and <lb/>unbalanced designs. Five thousand replications <lb/>of each condition were performed using a 0.05 <lb/>significance level. For each replication, the seven <lb/>statistics were computed using least-squares and <lb/>robust estimators. <lb/>Descriptive analyses of empirical Type I error <lb/>rates and of the percentage of bias in the error <lb/>rates, B = 100(α − α)/α, were conducted. Inferen-<lb/>tial analyses involved a between-subjects factorial <lb/>analysis of variance (ANOVA), to assess the signif-<lb/>icance of each of the simulation variables in ex-<lb/>plaining variation in empirical error rates. Sepa-<lb/>rate ANOVA models were defined for balanced and <lb/>unbalanced designs. For the former, a base model <lb/>was defined that included main effect predictors <lb/>only: number of outcome variables (VAR), corre-<lb/>lation between outcome variables (CORR), total <lb/>sample size (NTOT), covariance structure (homo-<lb/>geneous, heterogeneous: COV), and population dis-<lb/>tribution (POPTYPE). For the latter, two different <lb/>base models, each containing only main effect pre-<lb/>dictors, were defined. The first base model con-<lb/>tained VAR, CORR, NTOT, POPTYPE, as well as the <lb/>pairing of group sizes and covariance matrices (pos-<lb/>itive, negative: PAIR), and the degree of covari-<lb/>ance inequality (RATIO). The second included all of <lb/>these predictors except NTOT, which was replaced <lb/>by n j , the coefficient of variation of group size <lb/>inequality (CV). Not all values of CV were repre-<lb/></body>

			<page>134 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">L.M. Lix et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>sented at each value of N, therefore it was impos-<lb/>sible to include both variables in the base model. <lb/>Full models, which were included main effect pre-<lb/>dictors as well as selected two-way interactions, <lb/>were also specified for both balanced and unbal-<lb/>anced designs; these are described in more detail <lb/>in Section 5. <lb/>An empirical criterion of robustness defined by <lb/>Bradley [36] was also used to assess performance of <lb/>the test procedures. According to Bradley&apos;s liberal <lb/>criterion, a procedure is robust if its empirical error <lb/>rate falls within the interval from 0.025 to 0.075 <lb/>for α = 0.05. A procedure was considered liberal if <lb/>its empirical Type I error rate was greater than the <lb/>upper bound of this criterion, while a procedure <lb/>was considered conservative if its error rate was <lb/>below the lower bound of this criterion. <lb/>5. Results <lb/>5.1. ANOVA results for balanced designs <lb/>Table 2 contains the ANOVA results for balanced and <lb/>unbalanced designs for least-squares and trimmed <lb/>estimators. The results are presented for the base <lb/>model, as well as for a full model, which includes <lb/>selected two-way interactions designed to investi-<lb/>gate the effect of non-normality. <lb/>For balanced designs, the proportion of varia-<lb/>tion (R 2 ) explained by the set of main effect pre-<lb/>dictors in the base model for the procedures based <lb/>on least-squares estimators ranged from 0.40 for BF <lb/>to 0.81 for J. The predictors were statistically sig-<lb/>nificant in all of the models, with the exception of <lb/>CORR, which was only significant in the model for <lb/>the J procedure, NTOT, which was not significant <lb/>in the models for the H, BF, N, and Y procedures, <lb/>and VAR, which was not significant in the model for <lb/>the BF procedure. The proportion of variation ex-<lb/>plained by the base model predictors was higher <lb/>for robust estimators than for least-squares estima-<lb/>tors for all test procedures. The explained variation <lb/>ranged from 0.56 for the NV test to 0.96 for J. For <lb/>robust estimators, all of the predictors in the base <lb/>model were significant with the exception of CORR, <lb/>which was a non-significant predictor for the H and <lb/>J2 procedures. <lb/>The full model contained main effect predic-<lb/>tors as well as the two-way interactions of POP-<lb/>TYPE × NTOT and POPTYPE × COV. As Table 2 re-<lb/>veals, the proportion of explained variation in-<lb/>creased substantially for all least-squares proce-<lb/>dures, and was largely due to the POPTYPE × COV <lb/>interaction, which was significant in all mod-<lb/>Table 2 Factorial analysis of variance results for least-squares and robust estimators <lb/>Test statistic a <lb/>Base model b R 2 <lb/>Full model R 2 <lb/>R 2c <lb/>Least-squares <lb/>Robust <lb/>Least squares <lb/>Robust <lb/>Least squares <lb/>Robust <lb/>Balanced designs <lb/>H <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.64 <lb/>0.79 <lb/>0.72 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>BF <lb/>0.40 <lb/>0.63 <lb/>0.81 <lb/>0.76 <lb/>0.41 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>J2 <lb/>0.54 <lb/>0.70 <lb/>0.83 <lb/>0.83 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>J <lb/>0.81 <lb/>0.96 <lb/>0.93 <lb/>0.97 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>K <lb/>0.45 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>0.81 <lb/>0.76 <lb/>0.36 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>NV <lb/>0.51 <lb/>0.56 <lb/>0.83 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>0.19 <lb/>Y <lb/>0.52 <lb/>0.59 <lb/>0.82 <lb/>0.77 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>0.18 <lb/>Unbalanced designs <lb/>H <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.76 <lb/>0.76 <lb/>0.77 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>BF <lb/>0.46 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.78 <lb/>0.66 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>J2 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.87 <lb/>0.71 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>J <lb/>0.45 <lb/>0.60 <lb/>0.53 <lb/>0.61 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>K <lb/>0.42 <lb/>0.52 <lb/>0.76 <lb/>0.62 <lb/>0.34 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>NV <lb/>0.61 <lb/>0.60 <lb/>0.84 <lb/>0.72 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>Y <lb/>0.59 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.84 <lb/>0.67 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>a H: Hotelling&apos;s (1931) T 2 ; BF: Brown-Forsythe (1974); J2: James&apos; second-order (1954); J: Johansen (1980); K: Kim (1992); NV: <lb/>Nel and van der Merwe (1986); Y: Yao (1965). <lb/>b For balanced designs, base model is TYPE1 = VAR + CORR + NTOT + COV + POPTYPE; full model is TYPE1 = VAR + CORR + <lb/>NTOT + COV + POPTYPE + POPTYPE × NTOT + POPTYPE × COV; for unbalanced designs, base model is TYPE1 = VAR + CORR + <lb/>CV + PAIR + RATIO + POPTYPE; full model is TYPE1 = VAR + CORR + CV + PAIR + RATIO + POPTYPE + POPTYPE × CV + POPTYPE × PAIR. <lb/>c <lb/>R 2 = R 2 (full model) − R 2 (base model). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Robust tests for the multivariate Behrens-Fisher problem <lb/></note>

			<page>135 <lb/></page>

			<body>els. The proportion of variation explained by the <lb/>model increased by 0.11-0.36 due to this vari-<lb/>able alone when least-squares estimators were <lb/>adopted. For test procedures based on robust <lb/>estimators, the increase in explained variation <lb/>due to POPTYPE × NTOT and POPTYPE × COV was <lb/>much smaller than for least-squares estimators, <lb/>and ranged from 0.01 to 0.19. Consequently, <lb/>the model accounted for slightly less varia-<lb/>tion in the data when robust estimators were <lb/>adopted than when least-squares estimators were <lb/>adopted. <lb/>Descriptive analyses revealed that when the de-<lb/>sign was balanced and covariances were equal, <lb/>the mean percentages of Type I errors were con-<lb/>tained within the bounds of Bradley&apos;s [36] lib-<lb/>eral criterion for the entire set of test proce-<lb/>dures when least-squares estimators were adopted, <lb/>even when the data were non-normal. When <lb/>covariances were heterogeneous, this was not <lb/>the case. For both the moderately skewed and <lb/>highly skewed distributions, mean error rates fre-<lb/>quently exceeded the upper bound of Bradley&apos;s <lb/>criterion when least-squares estimators were <lb/>adopted but not when trimmed estimators were <lb/>adopted. <lb/>5.2. ANOVA results for unbalanced designs <lb/>For unbalanced designs, the two base models, <lb/>which contained the CV and NTOT predictors, re-<lb/>spectively, explained a similar proportion of the <lb/>variation in the data for all but the J procedure, <lb/>for which CV was a better predictor of Type I error <lb/>rates than NTOT. Hence, we selected the former <lb/>base model for our model comparisons. The pro-<lb/>portion of variation explained by the predictors in <lb/>the base model ranged from 0.42 for K to 0.75 for <lb/>H for least-squares estimators (Table 2). For the H <lb/>procedure, all predictors were significant with the <lb/>exception of CORR and POPTYPE. For the J2, J, NV, <lb/>and Y procedures, CORR was a non-significant pre-<lb/>dictor. CV was a non-significant predictor for the BF, <lb/>J2, and K procedures. RATIO was not significant for <lb/>the Y procedure, and VAR was not significant for the <lb/>BF procedure. <lb/>When trimmed estimators were adopted, the <lb/>proportion of variation explained by predictors in <lb/>the base model ranged from 0.52 for the K proce-<lb/>dure to 0.76 for the H procedure. CORR was a non-<lb/>significant predictor for the J2 and J procedures, <lb/>while RATIO was non-significant for the Y proce-<lb/>dure. VAR was non-significant only for the H pro-<lb/>cedure, as was POPTYPE. The PAIR variable was not <lb/>significant for the J2 procedure. <lb/>For the full model, which included main ef-<lb/>fect predictors and both POPTYPE × CV and POP-<lb/>TYPE × PAIR, the proportion of explained variation <lb/>increased between 0.01 and 0.34 for least-squares <lb/>estimators and between 0.01 and 0.16 for trimmed <lb/>estimators. The interaction terms were significant <lb/>in all of the full models for least-squares estima-<lb/>tors, with the exception of the model for the H <lb/>procedure, where neither were significant. In the <lb/>full models for procedures based on trimmed esti-<lb/>mators, POPTYPE × CV was not significant for the <lb/>H and Y procedures, while POPTYPE × PAIR was not <lb/>significant for the H procedure. <lb/>Descriptive analyses (Table 3) revealed that for <lb/>least-squares estimators, Type I error rates were <lb/>substantially different for positive and negative <lb/>pairings of group sizes and covariance matrices <lb/>when the data were obtained from multivariate <lb/>normal and non-normal distributions. This variation <lb/>was less obvious when trimmed estimators were <lb/>adopted. Table 3 contains the mean percentages <lb/>of Type I error for all of the investigated proce-<lb/>dures for positive and negative pairings of group <lb/>sizes and covariance matrices. For positive pairings, <lb/>mean error rates were contained within the bounds <lb/>of Bradley&apos;s [36] liberal criterion for both least-<lb/>squares and trimmed estimators for all but the H <lb/>and J procedures. Error rates for the former were <lb/>conservative, while those for the latter were lib-<lb/>eral; the degree of liberalness was greater for non-<lb/>normal distributions when least-squares estimators <lb/>were adopted than when robust estimators were <lb/>adopted. In particular, the J procedure with least-<lb/>squares estimators tended to be quite liberal when <lb/>the ratio of n min /p was 3 or less and/or when n j <lb/>was large. For example, the mean Type I error rate <lb/>for n min /p = 4.5 when n j = 1.22 was 6.35 for nor-<lb/>mally distributed data when least-squares estima-<lb/>tors were adopted and was 5.88 when robust esti-<lb/>mators were adopted. However, when n min /p = 4.5 <lb/>when n j = 6.12, the mean error rates were 9.74 <lb/>and 6.44 for least-squares and trimmed estimators, <lb/>respectively. <lb/>For negative pairings, liberal values were ob-<lb/>served for the H procedure across all of the inves-<lb/>tigated population distributions. For the remaining <lb/>six procedures, liberal results were obtained for the <lb/>moderately and highly skewed distributions when <lb/>least-squares estimators were adopted for all but <lb/>the K procedure in the latter distribution. When <lb/>trimmed estimators were adopted, the NV and Y <lb/>procedures produced liberal values for both the <lb/>moderately and highly skewed distributions, while <lb/>the BF procedure was conservative for the normal <lb/>distribution, and the K procedure was conservative <lb/>for the heavy-tailed distribution. <lb/></body>

			<page>136 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">L.M. Lix et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 3 Mean empirical percentages of Type I error for unbalanced designs <lb/>Population distribution <lb/>Test <lb/>Positive pairing a <lb/>Negative pairing <lb/>Least-squares <lb/>Robust <lb/>Least-squares <lb/>Robust <lb/>Normal <lb/>H <lb/>1.00 b <lb/>0.91 <lb/>32.40 <lb/>32.03 <lb/>BF <lb/>5.45 <lb/>4.49 <lb/>4.10 <lb/>2.42 <lb/>J2 <lb/>4.69 <lb/>3.84 <lb/>4.02 <lb/>3.08 <lb/>J <lb/>8.87 <lb/>8.47 <lb/>6.22 <lb/>4.50 <lb/>K <lb/>5 .09 <lb/>4.43 <lb/>3.26 <lb/>2.94 <lb/>NV <lb/>5.17 <lb/>4.47 <lb/>6.22 <lb/>5.91 <lb/>Y <lb/>5 .31 <lb/>4.55 <lb/>6.25 <lb/>5.83 <lb/>Heavy-tailed <lb/>H <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.94 <lb/>31.49 <lb/>31.56 <lb/>BF <lb/>4.97 <lb/>4.14 <lb/>3.48 <lb/>1.98 <lb/>J2 <lb/>4.27 <lb/>3.47 <lb/>3.50 <lb/>2.58 <lb/>J <lb/>9.20 <lb/>7.92 <lb/>5.59 <lb/>3.86 <lb/>K <lb/>4 .66 <lb/>4.08 <lb/>2.75 <lb/>2.42 <lb/>NV <lb/>4.73 <lb/>4.11 <lb/>5.57 <lb/>5.19 <lb/>Y <lb/>4 .88 <lb/>4.23 <lb/>5.65 <lb/>5.20 <lb/>Moderately skewed <lb/>H <lb/>2.23 <lb/>1.59 <lb/>34.93 <lb/>30.70 <lb/>BF <lb/>5.76 <lb/>4.11 <lb/>11.24 <lb/>3.99 <lb/>J2 <lb/>5.04 <lb/>3.50 <lb/>11.97 <lb/>5.30 <lb/>J <lb/>10.77 <lb/>8.42 <lb/>15.22 <lb/>6.82 <lb/>K <lb/>5 .33 <lb/>4.04 <lb/>8.82 <lb/>4.87 <lb/>NV <lb/>5.57 <lb/>4.15 <lb/>15.20 <lb/>8.56 <lb/>Y <lb/>5 .69 <lb/>4.19 <lb/>15.93 <lb/>9.06 <lb/>Highly skewed <lb/>H <lb/>2.06 <lb/>0.92 <lb/>31.44 <lb/>33.95 <lb/>BF <lb/>4.76 <lb/>4.87 <lb/>7.85 <lb/>4.14 <lb/>J2 <lb/>4.69 <lb/>4.56 <lb/>8.31 <lb/>4.90 <lb/>J <lb/>14.21 <lb/>9.76 <lb/>10.32 <lb/>6.45 <lb/>K <lb/>4 .14 <lb/>5.07 <lb/>6.19 <lb/>4.66 <lb/>NV <lb/>5.07 <lb/>4.98 <lb/>10.98 <lb/>8.07 <lb/>Y <lb/>5 .16 <lb/>5.06 <lb/>11.35 <lb/>7.99 <lb/>See Table 2 notes. <lb/>a Positive pairing: positive pairing of group sizes and covariance matrices; negative pairing: negative pairing of group sizes and <lb/>covariance matrices. <lb/>b Bold values are outside the range 2.50-7.50. <lb/>5.3. Percentages of bias <lb/>We investigated the percentages of bias for each <lb/>of the alternatives to Hotelling&apos;s T 2 [9] procedure <lb/>when covariances were heterogeneous and the de-<lb/>sign was either balanced or unbalanced (Table 4). <lb/>When the design was balanced, procedures based <lb/>on least-squares estimators were only slightly bi-<lb/>ased (15.47-28.44%) in either a positive or nega-<lb/>tive direction when the data were obtained from <lb/>a normal distribution. The degree of variation in <lb/>bias increased only slightly when the data were ob-<lb/>tained from a heavy-tailed distribution (−23.18% to <lb/>20.26%); the greatest degree of positive bias was for <lb/>the J procedure and the greatest degree of negative <lb/>bias was for the K procedure. For the moderately <lb/>skewed distribution, the procedures based on least-<lb/>squares estimators exhibited positive bias ranging <lb/>from 30.86% (K) to 98.44% (J). When the data were <lb/>highly skewed the percent of positive bias ranged <lb/>from 5.90% (K) to 70.90% (J). When the design was <lb/>balanced and trimmed estimators were adopted, <lb/>the bias tended to be slightly negative for the <lb/>normal distribution (−30.07% to 17.24%) and the <lb/>heavy-tailed distribution (−36.09% to 6.11%). For <lb/>both of the skewed distributions, the procedures <lb/>based on trimmed estimators exhibited a smaller <lb/>degree of positive bias than when least-squares es-<lb/>timators were adopted. In fact, the BF, J2, and K <lb/>exhibited a slight negative bias. <lb/>When group sizes and covariance matrices were <lb/>positively paired, the procedures based on least-<lb/>squares estimators were only slightly biased regard-<lb/>less of the shape of the population distribution. <lb/>The exception was for the J procedure, which was <lb/>always highly positively biased. For trimmed esti-<lb/>mators, the procedures almost always exhibited a <lb/>small degree of negative bias, with the exception <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Robust tests for the multivariate Behrens-Fisher problem <lb/></note>

			<page>137 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 4 Mean percentages of bias for balanced and unbalanced designs <lb/>Population distribution <lb/>Test <lb/>Balanced; unequal <lb/>covariances <lb/>Positive pairing <lb/>Negative pairing <lb/>Least-squares <lb/>Robust <lb/>Least-squares <lb/>Robust <lb/>Least-squares <lb/>Robust <lb/>Normal <lb/>BF <lb/>−11.73 <lb/>−29.42 <lb/>8.93 <lb/>−10.10 <lb/>−17.99 <lb/>−51.62 <lb/>J2 <lb/>−5.05 <lb/>−20.24 <lb/>−6.29 <lb/>−23.19 <lb/>−19.61 <lb/>−38.48 <lb/>J <lb/>2 8 .44 <lb/>17.24 <lb/>77.38 <lb/>69.34 <lb/>24.40 <lb/>−9.91 <lb/>K <lb/>−15.47 <lb/>−30.07 <lb/>1.79 <lb/>−11.47 <lb/>−34.80 <lb/>−41.29 <lb/>NV <lb/>1.95 <lb/>−7.64 <lb/>3.49 <lb/>−10.57 <lb/>24.50 <lb/>18.18 <lb/>Y <lb/>2 .61 <lb/>−9.39 <lb/>6.30 <lb/>−9.07 <lb/>25.04 <lb/>16.67 <lb/>Heavy-tailed <lb/>BF <lb/>−19.16 <lb/>−35.72 <lb/>−0.62 <lb/>−17.11 <lb/>−30.42 <lb/>−60.47 <lb/>J2 <lb/>−12.55 <lb/>−28.24 <lb/>−14.61 <lb/>−30.63 <lb/>−30.08 <lb/>−48.40 <lb/>J <lb/>2 0 .26 <lb/>6.11 <lb/>83.93 <lb/>58.49 <lb/>11.90 <lb/>−22.76 <lb/>K <lb/>−23.18 <lb/>−36.09 <lb/>−6.88 <lb/>−18.45 <lb/>−44.96 <lb/>−51.64 <lb/>NV <lb/>−6.22 <lb/>−16.03 <lb/>−5.40 <lb/>−17.74 <lb/>11.39 <lb/>3.82 <lb/>Y <lb/>−5.41 <lb/>−17.92 <lb/>−2.40 <lb/>−15.42 <lb/>12.95 <lb/>3.92 <lb/>Moderately skewed <lb/>BF <lb/>58.44 <lb/>−13.73 <lb/>15.26 <lb/>−17.72 <lb/>124.75 <lb/>−20.20 <lb/>J2 <lb/>67.93 <lb/>−4.74 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>−29.98 <lb/>139.47 <lb/>6.05 <lb/>J <lb/>9 8 .44 <lb/>28.16 <lb/>115.43 <lb/>68.32 <lb/>204.47 <lb/>36.40 <lb/>K <lb/>3 0 .86 <lb/>−19.68 <lb/>6.57 <lb/>−19.26 <lb/>76.43 <lb/>−2.58 <lb/>NV <lb/>77.25 <lb/>8.71 <lb/>11.39 <lb/>−17.00 <lb/>203.95 <lb/>71.17 <lb/>Y <lb/>8 1 .27 <lb/>8.98 <lb/>13.79 <lb/>−16.26 <lb/>218.58 <lb/>81.20 <lb/>Highly skewed <lb/>BF <lb/>39.60 <lb/>−10.61 <lb/>−4.82 <lb/>−2.60 <lb/>56.91 <lb/>−17.11 <lb/>J2 <lb/>46.95 <lb/>−3.44 <lb/>−6.11 <lb/>−8.71 <lb/>66.16 <lb/>−2.00 <lb/>J <lb/>7 0 .90 <lb/>31.73 <lb/>184.22 <lb/>95.19 <lb/>106.38 <lb/>28.93 <lb/>K <lb/>5 .90 <lb/>−16.67 <lb/>−17.19 <lb/>1.35 <lb/>23.87 <lb/>−6.80 <lb/>NV <lb/>55.99 <lb/>9.45 <lb/>1.46 <lb/>−0.47 <lb/>119.64 <lb/>61.48 <lb/>Y <lb/>5 9 .04 <lb/>9.05 <lb/>3.26 <lb/>1.18 <lb/>126.99 <lb/>59.80 <lb/>See the notes from Table 2. <lb/>of the J procedure, which was positively biased. As <lb/>well, the K and Y procedures exhibited a very small <lb/>degree of positive bias when the distribution was <lb/>highly skewed. <lb/>When group sizes and covariance matrices were <lb/>negatively paired, the magnitude of the bias varied <lb/>with the shape of the population distribution. When <lb/>the data were obtained from a heavy-tailed distri-<lb/>bution, the BF, J2, and K procedures with least-<lb/>squares estimators exhibited a small degree of neg-<lb/>ative bias. They became slightly more negatively <lb/>biased when robust estimators were adopted. The <lb/>J, NV, and Y procedures with least-squares estima-<lb/>tors exhibited a small degree of positive bias when <lb/>the distribution was heavy-tailed; when trimmed <lb/>estimators were adopted, the procedures became <lb/>less positively biased. When the data were obtained <lb/>from both moderately and highly skewed distribu-<lb/>tions, the procedures based on least squares esti-<lb/>mators were positively biased, with the Y, NV, and <lb/>J procedures exhibiting the greatest degree of bias <lb/>(106.38-218.58%). Adoption of robust estimators <lb/>decreased the degree of bias substantially. In fact, <lb/>some of the procedures (i.e., BF) exhibited a small <lb/>degree of negative bias, particularly when the data <lb/>were obtained from the highly skewed distribution. <lb/>6. Conclusions <lb/>Hotelling&apos;s T 2 [9] is sensitive to departures from co-<lb/>variance heterogeneity and multivariate normality <lb/>for two-group designs. A number of alternatives to <lb/>T 2 have been proposed in the literature. When the <lb/>data are normally distributed and least-squares es-<lb/>timators are adopted, no one procedure is supe-<lb/>rior across all data-analytic situations. When the <lb/>data are non-normal and least-squares estimators <lb/>are adopted, error rates can deviate substantially <lb/>from α, particularly when the distribution is skewed <lb/>and the group with the smallest sample size exhibits <lb/>the largest degree of covariance heterogeneity. <lb/>Procedures that are insensitive to departures <lb/>from covariance heterogeneity and non-normality <lb/>can be obtained when trimmed estimators are sub-<lb/>stituted for least-squares estimators in procedures <lb/>that are robust to covariance heterogeneity. Again, <lb/></body>

			<page>138 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">L.M. Lix et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 5 Test results for the example data set from Selvin [38] <lb/>Least-squares <lb/>Robust <lb/>Test <lb/>F/T statistic <lb/>df <lb/>p-value or <lb/>critical value <lb/>F/T statistic <lb/>df <lb/>p-value or <lb/>critical value <lb/>BF <lb/>7.0 <lb/>(0.7, 30.8) <lb/>0.0213 <lb/>4.2 <lb/>(0.69, 18.2) <lb/>0.0668 <lb/>J2 a <lb/>18.2 <lb/>(6.0) <lb/>16.25 <lb/>12.6 <lb/>(6.0) <lb/>19.44 <lb/>J <lb/>2 .8 <lb/>(6.0, 36.7) <lb/>0.0249 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>(6.0, 23.2) <lb/>0.1352 <lb/>K <lb/>2 .8 <lb/>(5.8, 78.4) <lb/>0.0169 <lb/>1.7 <lb/>(5.8, 47.1) <lb/>0.1365 <lb/>NV <lb/>2.6 <lb/>(6.0, 30.8) <lb/>0.0367 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>(6.0, 18.2) <lb/>0.1903 <lb/>Y <lb/>2 .9 <lb/>(6.0, 78.4) <lb/>0.0146 <lb/>1.9 <lb/>(6.0, 47.1) <lb/>0.1002 <lb/>a For James&apos; second-order procedure, we provide a T-statistic, which is compared to a critical value from a χ 2 distribution <lb/>with six degrees of freedom. For the remaining procedures, we provide an F-statistic. <lb/>no single procedure will perform well in all data-<lb/>analytic situations. As the results demonstrate, the <lb/>Brown and Forsythe [27], James second-order [14], <lb/>and Kim [16] procedures are frequently conserva-<lb/>tive. The Johansen procedure [24] is sensitive to <lb/>the relationship between group sizes and the di-<lb/>mensionality of the data, and will produce liberal <lb/>values when the ratio of the smallest group size to <lb/>the number of outcome variables is small, or when <lb/>the degree of group size imbalance is large. The <lb/>Nel and van der Merwe [17]and Yao [19] procedures <lb/>were more liberal than other procedures when the <lb/>group with the smallest sample size exhibited the <lb/>largest degree of covariance heterogeneity. <lb/>Based on these findings, we recommend that re-<lb/>searchers adopt procedures based on trimmed esti-<lb/>mators if the assumption of multivariate normality <lb/>is untenable. If the degree of group size imbalance <lb/>is large, and the ratio of the smallest group size <lb/>to the number of outcome variables is small, the <lb/>Johansen procedure[24] should be avoided. If the <lb/>degree of covariance heterogeneity is large, then <lb/>Kim&apos;s procedure [16] should be considered, since <lb/>it was the only procedure in unbalanced designs, <lb/>which was insensitive to the degree of covariance <lb/>heterogeneity in the data. Overall, the Kim and <lb/>James second-order procedures based on robust es-<lb/>timators were less sensitive to the factors examined <lb/>in this study than the other four alternative proce-<lb/>dures. <lb/>7. Software and numeric example <lb/>We recently developed a computer program writ-<lb/>ten in version 8 of SAS&apos; Interactive Matrix Language <lb/>that can be used to implement these robust al-<lb/>ternatives with trimmed estimators [37]. This pro-<lb/>gram, along with instructions on its use, is avail-<lb/>able for downloading from the first author&apos;s web-<lb/>site, http://home.cc.umanitoba.ca/∼lixlm. This <lb/>program requires that the data matrix of multi-<lb/>variate observations, group sizes, and proportion <lb/>of trimming be specified. For the current example, <lb/>we examined the procedures using 20% symmetric <lb/>trimming because this amount of trimming has been <lb/>often recommended in the literature. However, the <lb/>program user may select any amount of symmet-<lb/>ric trimming desired. The program will output sum-<lb/>mary descriptive information, including the multi-<lb/>variate group means and covariance matrices. The <lb/>test statistics, degrees of freedom, and p-values or <lb/>critical values for each of the procedures, as de-<lb/>fined in Sections 2 and 3, are produced. <lb/>We demonstrate the application of the program <lb/>using a data set obtained from Selvin [38] on ma-<lb/>ternal weights for 70 primiparous and 23 multi-<lb/>parous women (p. 223). Six measures of prepreg-<lb/>nancy, pregnancy, and postpartum weights, gains, <lb/>and losses were analyzed by Selvin using Hotelling&apos;s <lb/>T 2 [9]. We applied the robust alternatives to these <lb/>data. To illustrate the effect that extreme observa-<lb/>tions can have on the statistical tests when least-<lb/>squares estimators are adopted, we manipulated <lb/>the data so that a constant was added to the first <lb/>six observations for the last dependent variable for <lb/>the primiparous women. This modified data set is <lb/>available from the authors on request. <lb/>The results generated by the SAS/IML program <lb/>are presented in Table 5. Note that with least-<lb/>squares estimators all procedures result in rejec-<lb/>tion of the null hypothesis of equality of multivari-<lb/>ate means for the two groups of women, while with <lb/>trimmed estimators the null hypothesis is retained. <lb/>In this example, all of the tests based on robust es-<lb/>timators lead to the same decision regarding the <lb/>null hypothesis. However, as the simulation results <lb/>reported in this paper indicate, this will not neces-<lb/>sarily be the case for all data sets. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Robust tests for the multivariate Behrens-Fisher problem <lb/></note>

			<page>139 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] L.A. Cupples, T. Heeren, A. Schatzkin, T. Colton, Multiple <lb/>testing of hypotheses&apos; in comparing two groups, Ann. Int. <lb/>Med. 100 (1984) 122-129. <lb/>[2] K.J. Friston, K.M. Stephan, J.D. Healther, C.D. Frith, <lb/>A.A. Ioannides, L.C. Lui, M.D. Rugg, J. Vieth, H. Keber, <lb/>K. Hunter, R.S.J. Frackowiak, A multivariate analysis of <lb/>evoked responses in EEG and MEG data, NeuroImage 3 <lb/>(1996) 167-174. <lb/>[3] P.C. O&apos;Brien, Procedures for comparing samples with mul-<lb/>tiple endpoints, Biometrics 40 (1984) 1079-1087. <lb/>[4] C.R. Touw, L.H.-V. Joijen, P. Verboom, C. Paul, F.F.H. Rut-<lb/>ten, A.Y. Finlay, Quality of life and clinical outcome in pso-<lb/>riasis patients using intermittent cyclosporin, Br. J. Derm. <lb/>144 (2001) 967-972. <lb/>[5] B.L. Welch, The significance of the difference between <lb/>two means when the population variances are unequal, <lb/>Biometrika 29 (1937) 350-362. <lb/>[6] J.F. Reed III, Solutions to the Behrens-Fisher problem, <lb/>Comp. Meth. Prog. Biomed. 70 (2003) 259-263. <lb/>[7] K.K. Yuen, W.J. Dixon, The approximate behavior and per-<lb/>formance of the two sample trimmed t, Biometrika 60 <lb/>(1973) 369-374. <lb/>[8] K.K. Yuen, The two sample trimmed t for unequal popula-<lb/>tion variances, Biometrika 61 (1974) 165-170. <lb/>[9] H. Hotelling, The generalization of Student&apos;s ratio, Ann. <lb/>Math. Stat. 2 (1931) 360-378. <lb/>[10] J. Algina, T.C. Oshima, K.L. Tang, Robustness of Yao&apos;s, <lb/>James&apos;, and Johansen&apos;s tests under variance-covariance <lb/>heteroscedasticity and nonnormality, J. Educ. Stat. 16 <lb/>(1991) 125-139. <lb/>[11] N. de la Rey, D.G. Nel, A comparison of the significance <lb/>levels and power functions of several solutions to the mul-<lb/>tivariate Behrens-Fisher problem, S. Afr. Stat. J. 27 (1993) <lb/>129-148. <lb/>[12] B.S. Everitt, A Monte Carlo investigation of the robustness <lb/>of Hotelling&apos;s one-and two-sample T 2 tests, J. Am. Stat. <lb/>Assoc. 74 (1979) 48-50. <lb/>[13] B.M. Bennett, Note on a solution to the generalized <lb/>Behrens-Fisher problem, Ann. Inst. Stat. Math. 2 (1951) <lb/>87-90. <lb/>[14] G.S. James, Tests of linear hypotheses in univariate and <lb/>multivariate analysis when the ratios of the population vari-<lb/>ances are unknown, Biometrika 41 (1954) 19-43. <lb/>[15] J. Hwang, H. Jorn, J. Kim, On the performance of bivariate <lb/>robust location estimators under contamination, Comput. <lb/>Stat. Data Anal. 44 (2004) 587-601. <lb/>[16] S.-J. Kim, A practical solution to the multivariate <lb/>Behrens-Fisher problem, Biometrika 79 (1992) 171-176. <lb/>[17] D.G. Nel, C.A. van der Merwe, A solution to the multivariate <lb/>Behrens-Fisher problem, Commun. Stat. Theory Meth. 15 <lb/>(1986) 3719-3735. <lb/>[18] M.L. Tiku, N. Balakrishnan, Robust Hotelling-type T 2 statis-<lb/>tics based on the modified maximum likelihood esti-<lb/>mators, Commun. Stat. Theory Meth. 17 (1988) 1789-<lb/>1810. <lb/>[19] Y. Yao, An approximate degrees of freedom solution to the <lb/>multivariate Behrens-Fisher problem, Biometrika 52 (1965) <lb/>139-147. <lb/>[20] P.K. Ito, Robustness of ANOVA and MANOVA test procedures, <lb/>in: P.R. Krishnaiah (Ed.), Handbook of Statistics: Analysis <lb/>of Variance, vol. 1, North-Holland, Amsterdam, New York, <lb/>1980, pp. 199-236. <lb/>[21] K.V. Mardia, The effect on nonnormality on some multi-<lb/>variate tests and robustness to nonnormality in the linear <lb/>model, Biometrika 58 (1971) 105-121. <lb/>[22] C.L. Olson, Comparative robustness of six tests in multi-<lb/>variate analysis of variance, J. Am. Stat. Assoc. 69 (1974) <lb/>894-908. <lb/>[23] R.R. Wilcox, Simulation results on solutions to the multi-<lb/>variate Behrens-Fisher problem via trimmed means, Statis-<lb/>tician (1995) 213-225. <lb/>[24] S. Johansen, The Welch-James approximation to the dis-<lb/>tribution of the residual sum of squares in a weighted linear <lb/>regression, Biometrika 67 (1980) 85-92. <lb/>[25] R.T. Fouladi, R.D. Yockey, Type I error control of two-group <lb/>multivariate tests on means under conditions of heteroge-<lb/>neous correlation structure and varied multivariate distri-<lb/>butions, Commun. Stat Simula. 31 (2002) 375-400. <lb/>[26] D.K. Srivastava, G.S. Mudholkar, Trimmed T 2 : a robust ana-<lb/>log of Hotelling&apos;s T 2 , J. Stat. Plan. Inference 97 (2001) <lb/>343-358. <lb/>[27] M.B. Brown, A.B. Forsythe, The small sample behavior of <lb/>some statistics which test the equality of several means, <lb/>Technometrics 16 (1974) 385-389. <lb/>[28] L.M. Lix, J. Algina, H.J. Keselman, Analyzing multivariate <lb/>repeated measures designs: a comparison of two approxi-<lb/>mate degrees of freedom procedures, Multivariate Behav. <lb/>Res. 27 (2004) 45-69. <lb/>[29] G. Vallejo, A. Fidalgo, P. Fernández, Effects of covariance <lb/>heterogeneity on three procedures for analyzing multivari-<lb/>ate repeated measures designs, Multivariate Behav. Res. 36 <lb/>(2001) 1-27. <lb/>[30] D.V. Mehrotra, Improving the Brown-Forsythe solution to <lb/>the generalized Behrens-Fisher problem, Commun. Stat. <lb/>Simula. 26 (1997) 1139-1145. <lb/>[31] R.R. Wilcox, ANOVA: a paradigm for low power and mis-<lb/>leading measures of effect size? Rev. Educ. Res. 65 (1995) <lb/>51-77. <lb/>[32] SAS Institute, SAS/STAT user&apos;s guide, Version 8. <lb/>[33] A.I. Fleishman, A method for simulating non-normal distri-<lb/>butions, Psychometrika 43 (1978) 521-532. <lb/>[34] C.D. Vale, V.A. Maurelli, Simulating multivariate nonnormal <lb/>distributions, Psychometrika 48 (1983) 465-471. <lb/>[35] SAS Institute, SAS/IML user&apos;s guide, Version 8, SAS Institute, <lb/>Inc., Cary, NC, 1999. <lb/>[36] J.V. Bradley, Robustness? Br. J. Math. Stat. Psychol. 31 <lb/>(1978) 144-152. <lb/>[37] L.M. Lix, H.J. Keselman, Multivariate tests of means in inde-<lb/>pendent groups designs: effects of covariance heterogene-<lb/>ity and non-normality, Eval. Health Prof., in press. <lb/>[38] S. Selvin, Multivariate comparisons of two groups, in: Epi-<lb/>demiological Analysis: A Case-Oriented Approach, Oxford <lb/>University Press, New York, 2001 (Chapter 14). </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
