<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<front>Nonlocal impact ionization and avalanche multiplication <lb/>G J Rees and J P R David <lb/>Department of Electronic and Electrical Engineering <lb/>Sheffield University <lb/>Sheffield S1 3JD <lb/>In memory of Peter Robson, who inspired and <lb/>encouraged scientists and engineers, young and old <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Impact ionization and avalanche multiplication are conventionally described in terms <lb/>of ionization coefficients which depend only upon the local electric field. Such a <lb/>description takes no account of the effect of ionization dead space, within which the <lb/>population distribution, and hence the ionization coefficient of carriers injected cool <lb/>approach equilibrium with the high electric field, inhibiting ionization and reducing <lb/>multiplication. This effect, which increases in importance as device dimensions are <lb/>reduced, clearly benefits such high field devices as transistors by suppressing <lb/>parasitic avalanche multiplication. It also improves the performance of avalanche <lb/>photodiodes (APDs) by reducing the spatial randomness of impact ionization, so that <lb/>the resulting excess multiplication noise is also reduced. It reduces temperature <lb/>sensitivity and may also further enhance APD speed. This article reviews these <lb/>effects and some theoretical models used to describe them. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>At the highest electric fields all semiconductors break down 1 . Free carriers may be <lb/>generated by tunnelling across the spatially tilted band gap, by optical excitation or by <lb/>thermal emission from deep traps. They accelerate in the field to such high energies <lb/>that, in falling back towards the band edge, they can release enough energy and <lb/>crystal momentum to generate a further electron-hole pair in the process of impact <lb/>ionization. Driven in opposite directions by the electric field these extra electrons and <lb/>holes may give rise to a chain of ionization events, leading to charge multiplication. <lb/>If the multiplication region is long enough and the field is high enough then the <lb/>Confidential: not for distribution. Submitted to IOP Publishing for peer review 19 April 2010 <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>multiplication can grow without limit and an avalanche of current is generated which <lb/>increases indefinitely until other effects supervene * . <lb/>Avalanche multiplication is parasitic in a variety of transistors, compromising their <lb/>performance. More usefully it is exploited in Zener Diodes, used widely in electronic <lb/>circuits to regulate voltage. It also provides the internal gain in an APD. These <lb/>devices were originally operated in analogue mode, below breakdown, where the <lb/>multiplication is kept finite and amplifies the photocurrent arising from weak optical <lb/>signals. APDs are now also increasingly operated in Geiger mode, above breakdown, <lb/>where the multiplication is high enough to permit detection of individual photons. <lb/>The avalanche is then quenched, either by the drop in diode voltage provided by a <lb/>series load resistor, or using more sophisticated circuitry. <lb/>The local ionization coefficients, α for electrons and β for holes, conventionally used <lb/>to describe avalanche multiplication, represent a carrier&apos;s mean rate of ionization per <lb/>unit distance and are also equal to the inverse of the mean distance a carrier travels <lb/>before ionizing. They increase rapidly with electric field, since only at high fields can <lb/>carriers acquire enough energy to impact ionize and conserve both energy and crystal <lb/>momentum in the process. <lb/>The term &apos;local&apos; here means that the ionization coefficients depend only on the local <lb/>electric field. This is never strictly true. Carriers injected &apos;cold&apos; (at thermal energies, <lb/>close to the band edge) must travel some distance down the field before their <lb/>distribution in energy heats and their ionization coefficient reaches equilibrium with <lb/>the field. Within this &apos;dead space&apos; ionization is suppressed. <lb/>Early Si APDs were designed for operation with GaAs emitters, at a wavelength of <lb/>around 800nm, for which the absorption length in Si is around 10µm. Their <lb/>multiplication region widths, w were also made not much smaller, easily <lb/>accomplished by the technology at that time. Consequently an applied bias of around <lb/>100V was required to reduce the ionisation path lengths to comparable dimensions <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">* In narrow gap materials breakdown may be dominated by interband tunnelling. <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>and achieve a multiplication of &lt;M&gt;~100. The dead space, of order a few tenths of a <lb/>micron, could then be ignored and the local approximation was good. <lb/>InP based APDs are now used extensively to detect the longer wavelengths preferred <lb/>for low loss in optical fibre communications systems. InP allows epitaxial growth of <lb/>a variety of lattice matched, or controllably strained III-V alloys, including InGaAsP <lb/>and InAlAs, and in the resulting heterostructure devices the multiplication and optical <lb/>absorption regions can be grown from separate materials. Optical absorption in these <lb/>materials is stronger because of their direct band gaps, so that shorter absorption <lb/>regions can be employed. Moreover, the separate multiplication region can be made <lb/>thin to increase device speed using modern growth techniques. <lb/>While the convenient local assumption is often made in the analysis and design of InP <lb/>based APDs it is not always justified because the ionization dead space can constitute <lb/>a significant fraction of the multiplication region. More recently, other materials <lb/>systems have been proposed for use in APDs under conditions where the local <lb/>approximation breaks down, including SiC devices used for visible blind UV <lb/>detection 2 , Si/SiGe strained layer multiple heterostructures 3 and impact ionization <lb/>engineered structures 4 , designed to exploit the benefits which we shall see nonlocal <lb/>impact ionization confers. Moreover, the submicron high field regions of modern <lb/>transistors are all too short for the parasitic avalanche process to be treated locally. <lb/>In this paper we review understanding of impact ionization and multiplication when <lb/>the local assumption is not justified, contrasting and assessing the predictions of the <lb/>local and nonlocal models. While we shall focus mostly on the consequences for <lb/>APDs we shall try to emphasise the underlying physics so that our comments may <lb/>have more general application. <lb/>Avalanche multiplication <lb/>The terminology and analysis of multiplication in the local model follows the physics <lb/>of the gas discharge process 5 and is described widely in the literature 6,7 . We consider <lb/>a multiplication region subject to a high electric field, such as the i-region of an <lb/>idealised, reverse biased pin diode, which extends from x = 0 to x = w and in which <lb/>electrons drift in the positive x-direction. The p + -type cap sits on top at x = 0 and the <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>n + -type substrate extends beyond x = w. A primary carrier pair injected at x will, on <lb/>average enjoy a multiplication &lt;M(x)&gt;, meaning that an average number &lt;M(x)&gt; of <lb/>carrier pairs (including the original pair) will be collected at the terminals. This <lb/>quantity <lb/>obeys <lb/>the <lb/>integral <lb/>equation 8 <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>+ <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>+ <lb/>&gt;= <lb/>&lt; <lb/>w <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>) <lb/> &apos; <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>M <lb/>) <lb/>&apos; <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>&apos; <lb/>dx <lb/>) <lb/>&apos; <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>M <lb/>) <lb/>&apos; <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>&apos; <lb/>dx <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>M <lb/>α <lb/>β <lb/>0 <lb/> 1 <lb/>. This equation states <lb/>merely that the mean multiplication associated with carrier pair injection at x results <lb/>from multiplication chains generated in the interval (0,x) from ionization by the <lb/>primary hole, contributing the second term on the right hand side (RHS), from chains <lb/>generated in the interval (x,w) from ionization by the primary electron, contributing <lb/>the third term, and from the primary pair, contributing unity. <lb/>Such recurrence relationships, in which the unknown quantity on the left appears <lb/>again under an integral on the right, turn up repeatedly in the theory of avalanche <lb/>multiplication, a process which is self regenerating. Differentiating this integral <lb/>equation with respect to x yields a differential equation for &lt;M(x)&gt; which may be <lb/>solved, using the boundary relations provided by the integral equation at x = 0 and x = <lb/>w, to yield 8 <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>&gt;= <lb/>&lt; <lb/>w <lb/>&apos; <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>) <lb/>&apos; <lb/>&apos; <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>&apos; <lb/>&apos; <lb/>dx <lb/>exp <lb/>) <lb/>&apos; <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>&apos; <lb/>dx <lb/>) <lb/>&apos; <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>&apos; <lb/>dx <lb/>exp <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>M <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>γ <lb/>α <lb/>γ <lb/>, <lb/>(1) <lb/>where <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>β <lb/>α <lb/>γ <lb/>− <lb/>≡ <lb/>. <lb/>In this treatment any position dependence of the ionization coefficients, α(x) and β(x) <lb/>in eqn. (1) arises because of that of the electric field, which α and β are assumed to <lb/>track faithfully, and not from nonlocal effects. When the field, and hence α and β, are <lb/>independent of position then eqn. (1) simplifies to <lb/>β <lb/>γ <lb/>α <lb/>γ <lb/>γ <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>&gt;= <lb/>&lt; <lb/>) <lb/>w <lb/>exp( <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>exp( <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>M <lb/>. <lb/>(2) <lb/>In particular, when carriers are injected at x = 0 the holes are immediately collected in <lb/>the p + -region and only the electrons go on to ionize, giving a (mean) multiplication <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>β <lb/>α <lb/>β <lb/>α <lb/>β <lb/>α <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>&gt;= <lb/>≡&lt; <lb/>} <lb/>w <lb/>) <lb/>exp{( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>M <lb/>M e <lb/>0 <lb/>(3a) <lb/>for pure electron injection. Similarly, for pure hole injection at x = w <lb/>} <lb/>w <lb/>) <lb/>exp{( <lb/>) <lb/>w <lb/>( <lb/>M <lb/>M h <lb/>β <lb/>α <lb/>β <lb/>α <lb/>β <lb/>α <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>&gt;= <lb/>≡&lt; <lb/>. <lb/>(3b) <lb/>Avalanche breakdown, corresponding to a divergence in multiplication, occurs when <lb/>the denominators of the right hand sides of these equations approach zero in the <lb/>increasing electric field, because of the positive feedback provided by successive <lb/>impact ionization by daughter electrons and holes. <lb/>Eqns. (3) may be solved for α and β to find <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/> h <lb/>e <lb/>h <lb/>e <lb/>e <lb/>M <lb/>M <lb/>ln <lb/>M <lb/>M <lb/>M <lb/>w <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>α <lb/>(4a) <lb/>and <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/>e <lb/>h <lb/>e <lb/>h <lb/>h <lb/>M <lb/>M <lb/>ln <lb/>M <lb/>M <lb/>M <lb/>w <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>β <lb/>, <lb/>(4b) <lb/>from which we can deduce the field dependence of ionization coefficients from <lb/>measurements of multiplication made under conditions of pure electron and pure hole <lb/>injection. From measurements on a range of devices with different multiplication <lb/>region widths we can extend the field range investigated, since narrower devices will <lb/>need larger ionization coefficients, and so higher fields, to maintain multiplication. <lb/>Figure (1) shows α deduced in this way from measurements 9 of M e and M h on <lb/>Al 0.6 Ga 0.4 As p-i-n diodes (note the logarithmic scale for α and the inverse scale for the <lb/>field). <lb/>Evidently the ionization coefficient increases strongly with electric field and the <lb/>values of α deduced from measurements on devices of different multiplication region <lb/>width all converge to an envelope at high fields. However, at the low end of the field <lb/>range for each device width the ionization coefficient droops below the envelope and <lb/>this low field droop sets in at fields which increase as the devices narrow. This effect <lb/>is well known to be a consequence of ionization dead space. The energy distribution <lb/>of charge carriers approaches an equilibrium in a uniform electric field and so the <lb/>ionization coefficient rises to a stable, &apos;enabled&apos; 10 value. However, this approach to <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>equilibrium spreads over longer distances as the field is reduced. Within this region <lb/>the ionisation coefficient falls below its equilibrium value and the multiplication is <lb/>correspondingly reduced. <lb/>Conversely, calculating multiplication from the &apos;bulk&apos; value of the ionization <lb/>coefficients, corresponding to the envelope in figure (1), gives an overestimate when <lb/>the avalanche region is small enough that dead space effects are significant. This is <lb/>because the local model assumes that ionization can occur in the forbidden dead space <lb/>and so predicts a larger value than measured. This is most apparent at low bias in the <lb/>thinnest devices, where the effect of dead space is to increase the voltage for the onset <lb/>of multiplication over that predicted by the local model. <lb/>At high fields a lower limit on this dead space, d can be estimated very crudely as the <lb/>distance travelled ballistically by a carrier before acquiring from the electric field, F, <lb/>the threshold energy, E T for ionization, determined by considerations of conservation <lb/>of energy and crystal momentum in the impact ionization process 11 . Hence <lb/>d = E T /(eF). <lb/>(5) <lb/>In fact carrier energy losses to phonon generation will generally increase this value <lb/>and, though much less likely, net energy gain by phonon absorption will reduce it, so <lb/>that the dead space is &apos;soft&apos;. <lb/>When the field is increased to the extent that the dead space becomes an appreciable <lb/>fraction of the inverse of the enabled ionisation coefficient then, since ionization is <lb/>prohibited in this dead space region, the measured multiplication is reduced by this <lb/>effect and the value deduced for the ionization coefficient drops below the envelope. <lb/>The envelope can thus be interpreted as the ionization coefficient corresponding to a <lb/>distribution of carriers in equilibrium with the electric field. <lb/>This dead space effect is seen in all semiconductor systems investigated to date, <lb/>including SiC 2 , AlGaAs 9 , GaInP 12 , InAlAs 13 , InP 14 and Si 15 . To account for this effect <lb/>in any theoretical model of multiplication we must go beyond our local description, in <lb/>which the ionization coefficient tracks the local field faithfully. We must also <lb/>acknowledge the region in which the ionization coefficient approaches equilibrium. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Thus, even in a uniform field an electron&apos;s ionization coefficient, α(x) will depend on <lb/>the distance, x travelled down the field since it was injected. Alternatively, we can <lb/>describe ionization in terms of a probability distribution function (pdf), <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>h e <lb/>, <lb/>defined so that <lb/>dx <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>h e <lb/>represents the probability that an electron, injected cool at x <lb/>= 0, will ionize for the first time in the small interval <lb/>) <lb/>, <lb/>( <lb/>dx <lb/>x <lb/>x + <lb/>. The &apos;first time&apos; <lb/>restriction is there because a carrier loses energy on ionising and we need to know <lb/>when this last happened since it must then traverse a further dead space before <lb/>ionising again. History matters in nonlocal impact ionisation. <lb/>We can expect α(x) and <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>h e <lb/>to have the following properties. Both will start at <lb/>zero and rise significantly above this only after the dead space, d, since cold carriers <lb/>cannot ionize. Beyond this region α(x) will approach a constant, &apos;enabled&apos; value, α*, <lb/>corresponding to an electron distribution in equilibrium with the field, while <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>h e <lb/>will peak near x = d and at large distances must decay, roughly as <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>* <lb/>exp( <lb/>α <lb/>− <lb/>, <lb/>because the decay rate of carriers available for &apos;first time&apos; ionisation is proportional to <lb/>their remaining number. <lb/>In fact α(x) and <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>h e <lb/>are related, since the fraction of carriers surviving ionization a <lb/>distance x down field from injection is given both by <lb/>− <lb/>x <lb/>) <lb/>&apos; <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>&apos; <lb/>dx <lb/>exp <lb/>0 <lb/>α <lb/>and by <lb/>− <lb/>x <lb/>e <lb/>) <lb/>&apos; <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>h <lb/>&apos; <lb/>dx <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>. Equating these expressions and differentiating we find that <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/>x <lb/>e <lb/>) <lb/>&apos; <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>&apos; <lb/>dx <lb/>exp <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>h <lb/>0 <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/>. <lb/>(6) <lb/>A little reflection shows that α(x) here must equal the ionisation rate per unit distance <lb/>of electrons which have escaped ionisation out to a distance x; electrons which have <lb/>ionised within this interval have an unknown history. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Relation (6) can be used to deduce a form for <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>h e <lb/>corresponding to some proposed <lb/>physical model for α(x). For example, if we suppose that α(x) = 0 within some dead <lb/>space, 0 &lt; x &lt; d, jumping to a constant value α(x) = α* for <lb/>x <lb/>d ≤ then it follows that <lb/>0 <lb/>= <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>h e <lb/>for <lb/>d <lb/>x &lt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>0 <lb/>, <lb/>)} <lb/>d <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>* <lb/>exp{ <lb/>* <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>h e <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/>for <lb/>x <lb/>d ≤ . <lb/>(7) <lb/>Despite its extreme simplicity this &apos;displaced exponential&apos; model 16 for the ionization <lb/>path length pdf has become a favourite for interpreting nonlocal ionization <lb/>phenomena. <lb/>Several authors have addressed the problem of modelling avalanche multiplication <lb/>including the effects of nonlocal ionization. Okuto and Crowell 16 were among the <lb/>first but Hayat et al. 17 offered perhaps the most transparent exposition, summarised <lb/>here. <lb/>When a carrier precipitates an ionization event both the newly generated carriers and <lb/>the primary carrier cool in the process and all three must travel their respective dead <lb/>spaces before ionizing again. Because of this the arguments leading to eqn. (1) cannot <lb/>easily be adapted. Instead, we imagine a primary electron/hole pair injected cold at x <lb/>and consider the quantity <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>Z <lb/>, equal to the total number of electrons and holes <lb/>generated at the series of successive impact ionisation events in a single trial resulting <lb/>from (and including) the primary electron. We also consider a similar quantity, <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>Y <lb/>resulting from and including the primary hole. Clearly if we add <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>Z <lb/>and <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>Y <lb/>we <lb/>get twice the total number of resulting electrons hole pairs, so that <lb/>( <lb/>) 2 <lb/>/ <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>Y <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>Z <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>M <lb/>+ <lb/>= <lb/>. <lb/>(8) <lb/>In any one trial <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>Z <lb/>will exceed unity only if the injected electron first ionizes <lb/>downstream, at ζ, say, where <lb/>w <lb/>x <lb/>&lt; <lb/>&lt; ζ <lb/>. This process produces two cold electrons <lb/>and a cold hole at ζ, each of which go on to generate Z 1 (ζ), Z 2 (ζ), and Y(ζ) carriers, <lb/>respectively. Thus we can write <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>; <lb/>( <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>ζ <lb/>ζ <lb/>ζ <lb/>ζ <lb/>Y <lb/>Z <lb/>Z <lb/>x <lb/>Z <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>= <lb/>, <lb/>(9) <lb/>where the LHS represents the quantity <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>Z <lb/>, conditional on the injected electron <lb/>ionising at ζ,, and the suffixes on the <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>Z ζ on the RHS refer to each cold electron. <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Z, Y, and so M will vary from trial to trial and thus are stochastic quantities so that <lb/>only their distributions and means are significant. In fact the primary electron may <lb/>ionize for the first time anywhere in <lb/>w <lb/>x <lb/>&lt; <lb/>&lt; ζ <lb/>, or may even avoid ionising <lb/>altogether, so that in evaluating the mean value <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>Z <lb/>, averaged over many trials, <lb/>we must allow for this. We find <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>+ <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>− <lb/>+ <lb/>− <lb/>&gt;= <lb/>&lt; <lb/>− <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>2 <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>&apos; <lb/>( <lb/>&apos; <lb/>1 <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>0 <lb/>ζ <lb/>ζ <lb/>ζ <lb/>ζ <lb/>Y <lb/>Z <lb/>x <lb/>h <lb/>d <lb/>x <lb/>h <lb/>dx <lb/>x <lb/>Z <lb/>w <lb/>x <lb/>e <lb/>x <lb/>w <lb/>e <lb/>. (10a) <lb/>The second integral on the RHS allows for the primary electron to ionize anywhere in <lb/>w <lb/>x <lb/>&lt; <lb/>&lt; ζ <lb/>, with ionization path length pdf <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>h e <lb/>and the factor of 2 and the loss of <lb/>the subscripts from eqn. (9) arise because the stochastic variables <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>Z ζ <lb/>1 <lb/>and <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>Z ζ <lb/>2 <lb/>have identical distributions. The first integral represents the probability that the <lb/>primary electron will ionize before it escapes the multiplication region, so that <lb/>subtracting it from unity represents the converse probability, providing the <lb/>contribution in the event that the primary electron escapes ionization. <lb/>Similar arguments concerning the fortunes of the primary hole lead to the equation <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>+ <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>− <lb/>+ <lb/>− <lb/>&gt;= <lb/>&lt; <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>Z <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>Y <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>h <lb/>d <lb/>) <lb/>&apos; <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>h <lb/>&apos; <lb/>dx <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>Y <lb/>x <lb/>h <lb/>x <lb/>h <lb/>ζ <lb/>ζ <lb/>ζ <lb/>ξ <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>, <lb/>(10b) <lb/>where <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>h h <lb/>is the ionization path length pdf for holes. Given forms for <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>h e <lb/>and <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>h h <lb/>we can solve eqns. (10) using standard numerical techniques, e.g. by iteration <lb/>or by discretising the integrals and solving the resulting matrix equations, to find the <lb/>mean value of multiplication from eqn. (8), <lb/>( <lb/>) 2 <lb/>/ <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>Y <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>Z <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>M <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>+ <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>&gt;= <lb/>&lt; <lb/>. <lb/>(11) <lb/>If we use ionization path length pdfs, <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>exp( <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>h e <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/>and <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>exp( <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>h h <lb/>β <lb/>β <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/>corresponding to uniform, local ionization coefficients (eqn. (7) with d = 0) then it is <lb/>straightforward to show that eqns. (10) and (11) lead to (3). <lb/>While Hayat and Saleh 17 and many other authors use the displaced exponential <lb/>approximation, eqn. (7) for the <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>h h <lb/>, <lb/>e <lb/>, the nonlocal analysis described above is by <lb/>no means restricted to this approximation. More realistic Monte Carlo calculations 18 <lb/>of ionization path length pdfs for GaAs (fig. 2) show the general features captured in <lb/>eqn. (7). However, the dead space is strictly a &apos;sick&apos; space, in which the ionization <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>path length pdf rises more gradually to a softened peak, eventually followed by <lb/>exponential decay. The softening of the peak is associated with the effects of phonon <lb/>scattering, discussed earlier, and also with the finite rate of ionisation above threshold. <lb/>The exponential decay, following from the equilibrium achieved by the carrier gas at <lb/>long distances, is evident. The irregularity in the curves is a consequence of Monte <lb/>Carlo noise, resulting from limitations on computer power, and is the major drawback <lb/>of this technique. <lb/>Avalanche noise <lb/>The primary photocurrent in an APD is generated by photons which arrive and are <lb/>absorbed at a Poisson distributed rate, and is carried by electrons and holes with <lb/>discrete charges, e <lb/>m . The resulting fluctuations about the mean current, I have a <lb/>mean power per unit bandwidth of <lb/>eI <lb/>P N 2 <lb/>= <lb/>corresponding to shot noise 19 . Since <lb/>this is the spectrum of the squared current fluctuations, avalanche multiplication by a <lb/>fixed gain, <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; M would increase this value to <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; M <lb/>eI <lb/>. <lb/>This result is simplistic for two reasons. The &apos;white&apos; noise argument is strictly valid <lb/>only when the current pulses have indefinitely small width. In fact carriers crossing a <lb/>depletion region generate rectangular current pulses 20 , of width equal to their transit <lb/>time, w/v, for a carrier speed v. Consequently the noise is &apos;pink&apos;, with an upper <lb/>frequency limit of order w/v~100Ghz for a 1µm wide depletion region. <lb/>Unfortunately this high frequency noise suppression does not lead to quieter <lb/>photodiodes since this transit time effect also makes this an upper bandwidth limit on <lb/>the gain. <lb/>More importantly, the multiplication is not fixed but may take a wide spread of <lb/>different values for each trial, with a probability distribution not even peaked at the <lb/>mean value 18 , as shown graphically in fig. 3. Now in a typical photomultiplication <lb/>measurement 21 a stream of carriers is injected optically with a CW laser beam, <lb/>chopped at low frequency to help distinguish photocurrent signal from dark, <lb/>tunnelling current (fig. 4). The photocurrent resulting from each photogenerated <lb/>carrier is amplified by a stochastic multiplication, M. Because of the enormous <lb/>number of carriers injected in each pulse the variance on the mean gain from pulse to <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>pulse is negligibly small, so that the photocurrent in each pulse is effectively <lb/>multiplied by the mean multiplication, <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; M . <lb/>However, in calculating the noise we must average over different trials after squaring <lb/>the noise current fluctuation amplified by the fluctuating gain, M, introducing a factor <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; 2 <lb/>M <lb/>. The noise power per unit bandwidth in an APD thus becomes <lb/>F <lb/>M <lb/>eI <lb/>P N <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>= <lb/>, where <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>&gt; <lb/>=&lt; <lb/>M <lb/>/ <lb/>M <lb/>F <lb/>(12) <lb/>is the excess avalanche noise enhancement factor 6,7 . <lb/>Noise can also be measured using phase sensitive detection 21 to eliminate dark current <lb/>contributions (fig. 4). Chopped light is detected in the APD test structure and the <lb/>resulting signal is band pass filtered. This eliminates the DC mean multiplied <lb/>photocurrent and 1/f noise and also makes the frequency range accessible to the <lb/>following square law power meter before detection at the chopping frequency. By <lb/>comparing the noise power measured at a known value of mean multiplication and <lb/>current with that measured on a Si photodiode operated at unit gain, in which <lb/>unmultiplied shot noise dominates, the effective bandwidth of the system can be <lb/>factored out to extract the excess avalanche noise factor. <lb/>McIntyre 8 was the first to calculate this factor, F, within the local approximation, <lb/>whose limitations he was at pains to point out. Using a technique similar to that <lb/>which led to eqn. (1) and ascribing full shot noise to the current generated by each <lb/>ionization event he showed that, for pure electron injection, the noise enhancement <lb/>factor is given by <lb/>) <lb/>k <lb/>)( <lb/>M <lb/>/ <lb/>( <lb/>M <lb/>k <lb/>F <lb/>e <lb/>e <lb/>e <lb/>− <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>− <lb/>+ <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>= <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(13a) <lb/>and for pure hole injection <lb/>) <lb/>k <lb/>/ <lb/>)( <lb/>M <lb/>/ <lb/>( <lb/>k <lb/>/ <lb/>M <lb/>F <lb/>h <lb/>h <lb/>h <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>− <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>− <lb/>+ <lb/>&gt; <lb/>=&lt; <lb/>, <lb/>(13b) <lb/>where <lb/>α <lb/>β / <lb/>k = <lb/>. Two features are particularly worth noting in these expressions. <lb/>Firstly, for a given value of multiplication the excess avalanche noise can be reduced <lb/>by choosing a material with a small ratio of secondary to primary carrier ionization <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>coefficients. This principle has guided the design of low noise APDs for around 40 <lb/>years. However, its naive acceptance and cavalier application outside the restricted <lb/>domain clearly identified by McIntyre may have impeded the development of high <lb/>performance APDs, for reasons which will become clear. <lb/>At low electric fields electrons and holes can have widely differing ionization <lb/>coefficients in the same material, because of the differing details of the band structure <lb/>and of phonon scattering processes which dominate their low field transport. <lb/>However, as the field increases so the increasing ionization coefficients approach one <lb/>another, for the following reason. At the highest fields carriers have little time to <lb/>scatter off phonons before acquiring their ionization threshold energies and reach <lb/>threshold in little more than the ballistic dead space given by eqn. (5), ionising shortly <lb/>afterwards. In this limit the ionization coefficients are given approximately by the <lb/>inverse of these distances for electrons and holes. Since ionization threshold energies <lb/>for electrons and holes normally lie between one and two times the band gap 11 , and so <lb/>are rarely too different, neither are the ionization coefficients at these high fields. <lb/>It follows that a value of k much less than unity, required for low excess noise <lb/>following pure electron injection, or much greater than unity, required if pure hole <lb/>injection is adopted, cannot be achieved at high fields. But at low fields ionization is <lb/>drastically reduced and respectable values of multiplication can be achieved only in <lb/>wide devices, where the multiplication has enough space to grow. Unfortunately, <lb/>long multiplication regions increase the time taken for the avalanche process to build <lb/>up and decay because of the long carrier transit times. Moreover, impact ionization is <lb/>more sensitive to temperature at low fields, since carriers scatter many times before <lb/>ionising, losing or gaining the energy of an optical phonon at a rate which depends on <lb/>temperature via the phonon population. Furthermore, a long multiplication region <lb/>needs an inconveniently large external bias to maintain electric field. <lb/>These evident conflicts between the requirements for low noise, predicted on the local <lb/>model 8 , and other desirable performance characteristics can only have helped relegate <lb/>the APD to second class status in comparison with, say pin-FET modules, where the <lb/>functions of detection and pre-amplification are distributed between the two <lb/>components and the design conflicts described above do not arise. <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Returning to eqns. (13), their second notable feature is that the excess avalanche noise <lb/>is predicted to depend only on the multiplication and ionization coefficient ratio, and <lb/>not on multiplication region width. While this prediction may apply to wide <lb/>multiplication regions fig. 5 shows that it fails when these regions approach the <lb/>submicron scale 22 . In fact at a fixed value of mean multiplication, the excess noise <lb/>factor in GaAs pin diodes falls significantly as the device width is reduced and the <lb/>electric field is increased to maintain multiplication 23 . The faint lines in fig. 5 are <lb/>drawn by plotting the results of eqns. (13) against those of (3) and so constitute the <lb/>predictions of the local model. While this noise reduction effect might have been <lb/>expected for pure hole injection, since in GaAs α/β decreases towards unity with <lb/>increasing field, the corresponding avalanche noise for pure electron injection should <lb/>then increase, by the same token. The observed reduction for both hole and electron <lb/>injection was therefore quite unforseen. <lb/>The reason for this behaviour, which is contrary to the predictions of eqn. (13), is as <lb/>follows 22,23,24 . In wide multiplication regions, operating at low fields, the ionization <lb/>coefficients are &apos;exponentially&apos; small (the linear decrease of <lb/>) <lb/>ln(α with inverse field <lb/>in fig. 1 illustrates this loose terminology), so that the mean electron and hole <lb/>ionization path lengths, equal to 1/α and 1/β, are large. As the multiplication region is <lb/>narrowed then, in order to maintain multiplication, the field must increase to maintain <lb/>αw and βw, the probabilities of ionising at least once in the multiplication region. In <lb/>this process the dead spaces d e and d h also decrease, roughly according to eqn. (5), but <lb/>they do so algebraically and much more slowly than the exponential decrease of 1/α <lb/>and 1/β. As a consequence ionization becomes increasingly confined to a small <lb/>region centred on a distance roughly an ionization dead space downstream from <lb/>carrier injection. This localisation with increasing field is evident in the simulations <lb/>of fig. 2. But the noise factor is a measure of the randomness in multiplication, which <lb/>in turn is caused by the spatial randomness in the ionization process. By localising <lb/>ionization events and making the multiplication process more deterministic we reduce <lb/>this randomness and hence reduce the avalanche noise. <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>The fall in excess avalanche noise as the multiplication region shrinks has now been <lb/>observed in a wide range of materials, including GaAs 25 , AlGaAs 26,27,28 , InGaP 29 , <lb/>InP 30 , InAlAs 30,31 and Si 32 . Fig. (6) shows measurements of excess avalanche noise in <lb/>Si pin diodes resulting from both pure electron injection and also from &apos;mixed&apos; <lb/>injection. In the latter case some light is absorbed within the multiplication region <lb/>itself, so that both electrons and holes go on to multiply, although in this case the <lb/>holes initiate most of the multiplication. The noise is evidently lower for pure <lb/>electron injection, because at low fields α &gt; β in Si, and for the mixed (impure hole) <lb/>injection the noise falls as the multiplication region narrows. However, in the case of <lb/>pure electron injection the noise is largely independent of multiplication region width. <lb/>This results from competition between the increasing importance of dead space, as the <lb/>multiplication width falls, and the increase in β/α as the electric field is increased to <lb/>maintain multiplication in the thinner multiplication regions. <lb/>The advantages of reduced noise combined with increased speed and lower operating <lb/>voltage resulting from narrow multiplication regions are now clear for modern III-V <lb/>APDs. Indeed, it would seem that pragmatic reductions were made in the sizes of III-<lb/>V devices by commercial manufacturers (as evidenced by the reduced breakdown <lb/>voltages on their published data sheets) even before it became publicly apparent why <lb/>shrinking the multiplication region would not necessarily increase noise. <lb/>The problem of how to calculate noise enhancement factor when ionization is <lb/>nonlocal was addressed by Van Vliet et al. 33 . However Hayat and Saleh again give <lb/>the clearest exposition 17 , an extension of their technique for calculating the mean <lb/>multiplication. By squaring the quantities <lb/>) <lb/>, <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>Z ζ (eqn. (9)) and the similarly <lb/>defined quantity for hole injection, <lb/>) <lb/>, <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>Y ζ they were able to construct integral <lb/>equations for <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>Z 2 <lb/>and <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>Y 2 <lb/>, from whose solutions the excess noise <lb/>factor <lb/>( <lb/>) 2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>+ <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&gt;&lt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>+ <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>+ <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>= <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>≡ <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>Y <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>Z <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>Y <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>Z <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>Y <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>Z <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>M <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>M <lb/>) <lb/>x <lb/>( <lb/>F <lb/>(14) <lb/>can be deduced. Application of this nonlocal model for noise in Si accounts well (fig. <lb/>(6)) for the combined effects of increasingly important dead space and converging α/β <lb/>ratio in the increasing electric field. <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>Unfortunately, a high field can lead to a high tunnelling current, which also gets <lb/>multiplied and increases parasitic noise, unless we work with wide band gap <lb/>materials. To this end multiplication and noise were studied 34,35 in a range of Al x Ga 1-<lb/>x As alloys, conveniently close to lattice match with GaAs. As well as the expected <lb/>reduction in noise with reducing multiplication region width an interesting sharp <lb/>increase in the α/β ratio just below x = 80% corresponding to an abrupt fall in β <lb/>becomes apparent in this material. We may speculate that this is perhaps associated <lb/>with the closure of an impact ionization channel as the band structure changes and a <lb/>threshold disappears 11 . Fig. 7 shows the very low noise 36 achievable in this material <lb/>as the multiplication length is reduced. These findings are supported by the work 27 of <lb/>Zheng et al., who have also observed low noise at an Al concentration of 90%. The <lb/>combination of wide band gap to suppress tunnelling, close match to a GaAs <lb/>substrate, large α/β ratio and further noise reduction from the effects of dead space <lb/>makes this a particularly interesting material for APDs. Thus, if ever lattice matched <lb/>dilute nitride GaInAs(N) can be demonstrated to absorb at telecommunications <lb/>wavelengths the GaAs based GaInAs(N)/Al 0.8 Ga 0.2 As APD could become an <lb/>attractive proposition. Alternatively, GaInAs quantum dots might also provide the <lb/>absorption medium, given sufficient optical absorption, perhaps with the help of an <lb/>optical cavity. <lb/>The effects of noise reduction associated with dead space are also seen in the even <lb/>wider band gap material 4H SiC 37,38 , raising the possibility of low noise, visible blind, <lb/>UV APDs. Fig. 8a shows the noise measured on 4H SiC pin APDs resulting from <lb/>230nm optical excitation. This provides electron injection contaminated with some <lb/>mixed injection in the high field region, resulting from incomplete optical absorption <lb/>in the p-type cap. Fig. 8b shows the results of 365nm excitation, providing slightly <lb/>impure hole injection. Reducing the multiplication width from 0.285µm to 0.105µm <lb/>improves the &quot;effective McIntyre ratio&quot;, (β/α) eff (equal to the ratio β/α of the curve <lb/>deduced from eqns (3) and (13) which best fits the measurement) for avalanche noise <lb/>following electron injection from k = 2.7 to 0.8. By contrast, the effective ratio, <lb/>(α/β) eff for hole injection remains approximately unchanged at around k = 0.1. The <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>fact that the products, (β/α) eff ×(α/β) eff , are considerably less than unity for both device <lb/>lengths is evidence that dead space effects are significantly reducing noise. <lb/>Perhaps the most spectacularly nonlocal ionization behaviour was seen 39,40 in <lb/>Hg 0.7 Cd 0.3 Te (CMT). In this material, with a direct band gap at Γ of E g = 0.29eV, the <lb/>heavy hole/conduction band effective mass ratio is around 30. Because of their high <lb/>mass, heavy holes are available close to the top of the band with momentum large <lb/>enough to participate in impact ionisation of electrons with kinetic energy little more <lb/>than the band gap. Consequently the ionization threshold energy for electrons lies at <lb/>0.29eV above the conduction band minimum, well below the L-minimum, which <lb/>lies some 1.2eV higher. Moreover, electrons can accelerate rapidly to threshold, <lb/>while the high rate of hole scattering, resulting from the high density of final <lb/>scattering states in the heavy hole band and degenerate light hole band, suppresses <lb/>hole heating and ionization. Furthermore, not only is the β/α ratio extremely small as <lb/>a consequence, but the momentum randomising process of inter-subband scattering is <lb/>absent for electrons at energies below ionization threshold and their scattering is then <lb/>largely due to the, predominantly forward directed, polar optical phonon scattering <lb/>within the -valley. <lb/>As a result, electrons accelerate quasi-ballistically to ionization threshold each time <lb/>they traverse a ballistic dead space and their numbers double at each of these highly <lb/>deterministic ionization events, much in the manner of electrons in a photomultiplier <lb/>tube. Consequently the mean multiplication increases almost exponentially with <lb/>applied bias and the excess noise factor stays close to unity for gain values of up to <lb/>&lt;M&gt;~1000. The near unity noise figure is very impressive and is strong evidence of <lb/>nonlocal behaviour, since the local model predicts a lower limit (eqn. (15)) of F = 2. <lb/>It seems likely that the feedback process due to hole ionization is sufficiently inhibited <lb/>that the exponential increase of gain with bias is maintained up to these high values of <lb/>multiplication and that true breakdown (resulting from the divergence discussed <lb/>earlier which requires feedback from hole ionisation) is indeed suppressed, at least up <lb/>to these values of field. <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>Similar behaviour is predicted 41 in InSb, and for the same reasons. A narrow band <lb/>gap leads to a large heavy hole/electron mass ratio, together with an increased <lb/>separation between the conduction band edge and the next highest minimum. These <lb/>conditions are also met in InAs, where electron initiated avalanche gain greatly <lb/>exceeds that initiated by holes 42 , suggesting that <lb/>β <lb/>α &gt;&gt; , and the excess noise <lb/>factor 43 for electron initiated multiplication remains below 2, providing the strongest <lb/>evidence for multiplication dominated by dead space. <lb/>The effects of nonlocal ionization on multiplication and noise are observed widely, <lb/>there seems to be little doubt that they are real and can be exploited. Further, <lb/>unforseen benefits for APDs from nonlocal ionization will be discussed in later <lb/>sections. <lb/>Simulation techniques <lb/>The ionization path length pdfs h e (x) and h h (x), often summarised in the displaced <lb/>exponential model of eqn. (7) by a dead space and an enabled ionisation coefficient, <lb/>occupy the key positions in nonlocal models of multiplication taken by the ionization <lb/>coefficients in the local picture. In this section we examine how their structure may <lb/>be determined and understood and how they may be used. We also review some <lb/>alternative techniques for modelling the avalanche multiplication process. <lb/>In real APDs, and even in experimental test structures, electric fields are often <lb/>nonuniform, perhaps because of the diffusion of dopant or carriers from the p + and n + <lb/>caps or because of residual doping in the depleted multiplication region. McIntyre 10 <lb/>proposed a way of extending the displaced exponential model for ionization path <lb/>length pdfs restricted to uniform, 1-D electric fields to account for such 1-D <lb/>nonuniformities. He also showed how to generalise the work of Hayat 17,44,45 et al. to <lb/>calculate multiplication and noise in such one dimensionally nonuniform structures. <lb/>At the other extreme the Monte Carlo technique 46 provides an essentially exact <lb/>solution of the Boltzmann transport equation for semiclassical charge carriers. It <lb/>follows the trajectories of individual particles as they move around in real-and <lb/>momentum-space under the influence of the driving electric fields and accounts for <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>the random influence of scattering with the help of a random number generator. This <lb/>enormously powerful technique is limited only by the capacity of the computer used <lb/>to perform the simulation. At its best, using a band structure calculated with an <lb/>empirical pseudopotential adjusted to fit measurement, a full range of phonon <lb/>scattering processes, first principles calculations of impact ionization rates, etc., it <lb/>represents the gold standard for modelling (at least when scattering processes can be <lb/>described by Fermi&apos;s golden rule and other quantum phenomena are unimportant). It <lb/>is then the numerical equivalent of an experiment and its results can be almost as <lb/>difficult to interpret. It includes automatically the physics behind nonlocal impact <lb/>ionization, it was used to generate the pdfs shown in fig. 2 and can be used to simulate <lb/>the complete avalanche process, including its evolution in time and allowing for the <lb/>awkward 2-D or 3-D structures used in real devices. If required it can be linked to a <lb/>thermal transport simulator to account for effects of heating on carrier transport via <lb/>increased phonon generation and can include the effects of avalanche carrier space <lb/>charge on the electric field profile. However, it can also soak up as much computing <lb/>power as is available and its use can require considerable, dedicated expertise. <lb/>Techniques less sophisticated and demanding are therefore also welcome, provided <lb/>their simplicity does not &apos;throw out the baby with the bath water&apos;. <lb/>Ridley&apos;s &apos;Lucky Drift&apos; model 47,48,49 was remarkably successful in predicting the <lb/>material and field dependences of local ionization coefficients, given its extreme <lb/>simplicity. Ridley 47 observed that, while phonon scattering is the common source of <lb/>both momentum and energy relaxation in ensembles of charge carriers, an artificial <lb/>separation of these two relaxation processes was convenient. In his picture carriers <lb/>acquire energy by &apos;drifting&apos; down the field, a process determined by momentum <lb/>relaxation, while their energy loss to phonons is described by less frequent, random <lb/>&apos;supercollisions&apos; in which carriers lose all of their energy and are condemned to begin <lb/>their journey to ionization threshold all over again. <lb/>The success of this strategy in modelling local ionisation coefficients did not extend to <lb/>the nonlocal regime 50 . Fig. 9 shows calculations 51 of h(x) using the principles of <lb/>Lucky Drift for a simple model material, with a parabolic band, a hard ionization <lb/>threshold and only optical phonon scattering, which also randomises momentum. The <lb/>model gives rise to pathological behaviour in h(x), with a δ-function at the dead space, <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>followed by a plateau and more, though less obvious, unphysical behaviour further <lb/>downstream. While the simple assumptions of Lucky Drift describe well the mean <lb/>value of the ionization path length and its inverse, the ionization coefficient, they <lb/>appear to be far too simplistic to describe the details of its pdf. <lb/>What is wrong here is the assumption that a carrier loses all of its energy in one <lb/>catastrophic scattering event, rather than distributing it to the phonon gas one quantum <lb/>of phonon energy, ω <lb/>h , at a time, and even gaining this energy on occasion. The <lb/>Fokker-Planck technique 52 provides a method for calculating h(x) which retains this <lb/>important physics, while discarding much of the unnecessary complexity. This <lb/>technique is based on two assumptions, namely that momentum relaxation due to <lb/>phonon scattering is so fast that the carriers&apos; phase space distribution function can be <lb/>considered to depend only upon energy, rather than momentum, and that the energy <lb/>gained or lost on phonon scattering is small on the scale of things. The former <lb/>assumption is not too bad, especially at the high fields encountered in impact <lb/>ionization. In this case energetic carriers have a wide choice of scattering destinations <lb/>among the (sub-) bands in most group III-V and IV semiconductors and the forward <lb/>momentum directionality of polar optical phonon scattering is lost (although this <lb/>assumption breaks down when polar optical phonon scattering dominates within the <lb/>Γ-minimum, such as in CMT, InSb and InAs). The latter assumption is quite good <lb/>because invariably <lb/>T <lb/>E <lb/>&lt;&lt; <lb/>ω <lb/>h <lb/>. <lb/>The Fokker-Planck equation can be derived 53 from the Boltzmann transport equation <lb/>by expanding the distribution function in momentum as far as the first two Legendre <lb/>polynomials. The second is then eliminated by replacing the square of the momentum <lb/>by its mean, in order to truncate the series, and the phonon energy is treated as an <lb/>infinitesimal, with suitably adjusted scattering rates. Because the carrier transport in <lb/>position-and energy-space is (quasi-) continuous a diffusion-drift type of differential <lb/>equation in both position and energy results, which can be solved by standard <lb/>numerical techniques. Fig 9 also shows a Fokker-Planck calculation of h(x) using the <lb/>same parameters as used for the Lucky Drift calculation. The Fokker-Planck <lb/>technique would seem to have potential for direct evaluation of the avalanche process <lb/>in realistic APD structures, in which the radial, as well as the longitudinal motion of <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>carriers and dependence of electric field is important. The results are far more <lb/>realistic than those of Lucky Drift and are very close to those of our equivalent <lb/>&apos;simple&apos; Monte Carlo 54 calculation. <lb/>This latter is a Monte Carlo technique stripped down to its bare essentials; single <lb/>parabolic band (regardless of the complexity of the band structure at high energies), <lb/>scattering by dispersion free, momentum randomising optical phonons, with <lb/>ionization threshold energy, softness of threshold, carrier mass and electron-phonon <lb/>coupling constant chosen to fit experiment. However, the method does include the <lb/>acquisition of energy and momentum from the electric field, punctuated and <lb/>moderated by random phonon scattering which introduces momentum relaxation, <lb/>quantised energy gain and loss and hence the diffusion process, in a realistic way <lb/>which eludes analytical treatment. Despite its extreme simplicity and flagrant <lb/>distortion of the known facts about semiconductor band structures this simple <lb/>technique has proved remarkably powerful as a tool for interpreting and <lb/>understanding measurements on both multiplication and noise in the nonlocal regime <lb/>and also, as we shall see later, on device speed. <lb/>An even simpler numerical technique is the &apos;Random Path Length&apos; (RPL) method 55 , a <lb/>kind of poor man&apos;s Monte Carlo model. It takes the pdfs of ionization path length as <lb/>its starting point, maybe using displaced exponentials or perhaps something a little <lb/>more fancy, generated by a more sophisticated Monte Carlo calculation, and uses a <lb/>random number generator to construct a sequence of ionization events to simulate a <lb/>multiplication &apos;trial&apos;. By combining the results of many such trials one can calculate <lb/>suitable running averages to study a variety of statistics. As the number of trials <lb/>increases this method gives identical results to the integral equation methods 10,17 , <lb/>devised for calculating multiplication and noise, since it makes the same assumptions. <lb/>However, it has the added advantages of conceptual simplicity and the capacity to <lb/>evaluate a variety of other statistics as running averages in the same numerical <lb/>experiment. Because of its modest demands we have found this technique extremely <lb/>useful and flexible for interpreting measurements and understanding avalanche <lb/>multiplication in the nonlocal regime. <lb/>Speed <lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>RC time constants and parasitic effects apart, the intrinsic speed of an APD is limited <lb/>by the time taken by the avalanche current to build up and decay, controlled by the <lb/>time for ionising carriers and their offspring to travel back and forth across the <lb/>multiplication region before finally exiting. We can therefore expect the avalanche <lb/>response time to increase with multiplication region width and with the mean value of <lb/>multiplication and to vary inversely with the carrier speeds. <lb/>However, if <lb/>multiplication results only from ionization by carriers of the type which are injected as <lb/>primaries, then these carriers will traverse the multiplication region as a group within <lb/>one transit time. The avalanche will then be over by the time it takes any carriers of <lb/>the opposite type, generated by impact ionization, to make the return journey. We can <lb/>therefore also expect APD speed to depend sensitively on k. These trends were <lb/>confirmed in the calculations of Emmons 56 and of Kuvås and Lee 57 . Both of these <lb/>early treatments assumed uniform electric fields, local ionization and constant drift <lb/>velocities for the charge carriers, ignoring the effects of diffusion. <lb/>Hayat 58,59 et al. adapted their integral equation technique 17 to predict the current <lb/>impulse response of an APD, the mean value of evolving avalanche current, and also <lb/>of its second moment, following primary carrier injection, taking account of the <lb/>effects of dead space. They did this by calculating the time dependence of the <lb/>concentration of carriers in the high field region, assuming that these carriers travel <lb/>with constant velocities, and they used the simple displaced exponential model of eqn. <lb/>(7) to describe their ionization path length pdfs. They concluded that the effect of <lb/>dead space is to slow down the avalanche process. Dead space denies carriers access <lb/>to some of the high field region for the purposes of impact ionization. To maintain <lb/>the same degree of multiplication carriers must travel beyond the dead space to ionize, <lb/>postponing ionization and prolonging the avalanche. <lb/>Ng 60 et al. studied the mechanisms responsible for this reduction of APD speed from <lb/>the effects of dead space using the RPL technique. Again assuming constant carrier <lb/>velocities they concluded that the avalanche response time is determined by <lb/>competition between two processes. The narrowing of the ionization path length pdf <lb/>and the associated increased determinism in the multiplication process actually <lb/>narrows the multiplication distribution, exemplified in fig. 3, by reducing the <lb/>probability of generating higher values of multiplication. This both reduces noise and <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>also speeds up the avalanche process, on average, since the shorter multiplication <lb/>chains take correspondingly shorter to complete. However, the postponement of <lb/>individual ionization events noted by Hayat et al. 17 has the result that any given value <lb/>of multiplication M, which may be produced in a variety of ways by successive <lb/>ionization of either electrons or holes, or their combination, must rely more on <lb/>processes in which electrons and holes travel sequentially back and forth across the <lb/>device, delaying the exit of the final carrier in the chain. It turns out that this latter <lb/>effect wins and dead space effects are predicted to slow down the avalanche process, <lb/>at least according to the assumptions of this model. <lb/>So far we have discussed models which have assumed, quite reasonably, that, at the <lb/>high electric fields needed for avalanche multiplication, carriers travel always at their <lb/>saturated drift velocities and that the effects of carrier diffusion can be ignored. <lb/>However, Monte Carlo simulations of the spatial and temporal statistics of the <lb/>ionization process by Plimmer 61 et al. suggest that this may not be such a good <lb/>approximation. Not only does diffusion appear to be significant but those carriers <lb/>which ionize at short distances down the field, rather than further downstream, appear <lb/>to arrive at these &apos;spatially early&apos; ionization events with unusually high average <lb/>velocities. <lb/>Plimmer 61 et al. used a moderately sophisticated model for the band structure in their <lb/>Monte Carlo simulation, involving three analytically described conduction subbands, <lb/>at Γ, X and L. Hence, it is tempting to ascribe this velocity enhancement to the <lb/>conventional velocity overshoot mechanism which leads to intervalley transfer and <lb/>Gunn oscillation. However, the effect is also seen in the simple Monte Carlo model 54 , <lb/>which uses only a single parabolic conduction band valley and has no intervalley <lb/>transfer, so this cannot provide the explanation. Moreover, it is also predicted by the <lb/>Fokker-Planck technique 53 , in which momentum scattering is supposed fast enough <lb/>that the carrier distribution in the bands depends only on energy. This would <lb/>therefore also appear to rule out ballistic transport as a general explanation, although <lb/>this process is likely to operate at the earliest times during a carrier&apos;s trajectory. The <lb/>effect is also predicted by the most sophisticated Monte Carlo simulation available to <lb/>us 62 , and we believe that it is real. <lb/></body>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 10 shows the effect most clearly in terms of the quantity h(x,t), the pdf of <lb/>ionization events in both space and time, calculated 53 using the Fokker-Planck <lb/>technique for a model semiconductor. This h(x,t) represents the probability, per unit <lb/>time and per unit distance, that a carrier, injected cold at position x = 0 at time t = 0, <lb/>will ionize for the first time at (x, t). The structure shows a ridge in the x-t plane <lb/>whose amplitude decays roughly exponentially with increasing x and t and which also <lb/>decays away rapidly on either side of the ridge. The line of this ridge intersects the <lb/>position axis at a distance which represents the dead space and the decay on either <lb/>side of the ridge corresponds to carrier diffusion. However, perhaps the most <lb/>interesting aspect is the fact that the &apos;dead time&apos; to ionization is negligibly small on <lb/>this diagram. This suggests that carriers arrive at the dead space extremely fast and <lb/>then travel downstream to their ionization events at a constant velocity, given by the <lb/>gradient of the ridge projected onto the x-t plane. Fig. 11 shows a contour plot of the <lb/>same quantity, calculated 63 using the Simple Monte Carlo technique and showing <lb/>similar behaviour. <lb/>If this effect, of velocity enhancement to early ionization, is real then its consequences <lb/>on APD speed are quite promising. By modelling the distribution of exit times of the <lb/>last avalanching carrier from a multiplication region 64,65 , also known as the &apos;avalanche <lb/>duration&apos;, and also by modelling the mean current impulse response 66 Hambleton et <lb/>al. have shown that the effect is to speed up the avalanche process significantly in <lb/>short devices. Monte Carlo simulations suggest that this speed enhancement more <lb/>than compensates for the reduction in APD speed due to the effects of dead space <lb/>alone 54,55 . <lb/>The integral equation technique has been extended 63 to calculate the current impulse <lb/>response, and also its standard deviation, using arbitrary two dimensional pdfs, h(x,t) <lb/>such as illustrated in figs. 10 and 11. Results, shown in fig. 12 confirm that diffusion, <lb/>though apparent in h(x,t), has little effect on the mean current impulse response, since <lb/>the values of diffusion coefficient needed to make an appreciable difference are <lb/>unrealistically large. The results also support the improvements in APD speed <lb/>predicted by Monte Carlo 54,61,62,63,65,66 <lb/>. <lb/></body>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Hayat and Dong 67 derived an integral equation approach to calculate avalanche <lb/>duration, which they termed the &apos;random response time&apos;, also studied numerically by <lb/>Hambleton 64,65 et al. This avalanche duration is a particularly interesting statistic in <lb/>digital optical fibre communications since we are there concerned with how <lb/>photocurrent pulses spread and merge. Avalanche duration is a stochastic variable <lb/>and Hayat and Dong showed how to calculate its pdf for use in estimating its mean <lb/>value and the mean of its inverse, related to the APD bandwidth. Their technique was <lb/>restricted to constant carrier velocities and, although it allowed for an arbitrary <lb/>ionization path length pdf, these authors used the technique only to assess the pdf of <lb/>avalanche duration for the case of local ionization. This approach was subsequently <lb/>generalized by Sun 68 et al. to evaluate the joint pdf of the avalanche duration and the <lb/>avalanche multiplication, allowing determination of the statistical correlation between <lb/>these two quantities. <lb/>A further generalisation 69 of the technique to handle arbitrary two dimensional pdfs, <lb/>h(x,t) shows that the resulting pdfs of avalanche duration are also relatively insensitive <lb/>to the effects of diffusion, as seen in calculations on current impulse response 63 . The <lb/>technique also shows the same speed improvement in the avalanche duration, <lb/>resulting from enhanced speed to early ionisation, as in other statistics and using other <lb/>methods. <lb/>This enhancement in the speed of a carrier to early ionization, although predicted by a <lb/>number of different techniques, eluded physical explanation for some time. Its origin <lb/>now seems obvious with hindsight. Carriers which ionize early in their trajectories <lb/>have had a privileged history; they must have scattered infrequently on their journey <lb/>downstream to ionization. Since the rates of phonon absorption and emission are <lb/>proportional to n and n + 1, where <lb/>1 <lb/>1 − <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/>) <lb/>) <lb/>kT <lb/>/ <lb/>(exp( <lb/>n <lb/>ω <lb/>h <lb/>(15) <lb/>is the phonon occupation number, the carrier loses an energy, on average, of <lb/>) <lb/>n <lb/>/( <lb/>1 <lb/>2 + <lb/>ω <lb/>h <lb/>each time it scatters off a phonon. If we suppose that l <lb/>N represents the <lb/>average number of scattering events by phonons encountered by carriers which go on <lb/>to ionize a distance l down stream from their injection point, then, assuming for <lb/></body>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>simplicity that carriers ionize immediately on reaching threshold, simple energy <lb/>balance arguments show that <lb/>) <lb/>n <lb/>/( <lb/>N <lb/>eFl <lb/>E <lb/>l <lb/>T <lb/>1 <lb/>2 + <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/>ω <lb/>h <lb/>, so that <lb/>) <lb/>d <lb/>l <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>n <lb/>( <lb/>eF <lb/>N l <lb/>− <lb/>+ <lb/>= <lb/>ω <lb/>h <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>. <lb/>(16) <lb/>Thus, carriers whose ionization path length, l is only slightly larger than the ballistic <lb/>dead space, d, given by eqn. (7), will, on average, have scattered very infrequently <lb/>since they were injected. This infrequent scattering is reflected in increased drift <lb/>velocity prior to ionising of this privileged class of carriers, leading to the effects <lb/>observed in our Monte Carlo &apos;experiments&apos;. We should point out that while we have <lb/>seen these enhanced velocities in all of our simulations, they have not yet been <lb/>observed unequivocally in real experiments. <lb/>The dynamics of the growth and decay of populations of carriers born of earlier <lb/>generations have analogies in those of living populations and it is not surprising that <lb/>some of the consequences are similar. By examining the behaviour of the integral <lb/>equations describing the evolution of carrier populations in a uniform multiplication <lb/>region, Hayat and Saleh 17 showed that, below breakdown, both the mean value of the <lb/>avalanche current and its mean square deviation from this mean current decay <lb/>asymptotically as <lb/>) <lb/>t <lb/>exp( <lb/>γ <lb/>− , so that the standard deviation in current decays as <lb/>) <lb/>/ <lb/>t <lb/>exp( <lb/>2 <lb/>γ <lb/>− <lb/>. Here the Malthusian parameter 70 , γ depends only on the ionization <lb/>path length pdfs in position and on the multiplication region width, and not on the <lb/>initial conditions. <lb/>Indeed, we observe this exponential decay of current at long times in our numerical <lb/>(Monte Carlo and RPL) simulations. Groves et al. 71 showed analytically that this <lb/>effect is rather more general, occurring in any 1-D nonuniform field profile and for <lb/>general models of ionization event pdfs. In particular the velocity enhancement effect <lb/>speeds up the process when dead space represents a significant fraction of the <lb/>avalanche width. These authors showed that this Malthusian decay also dominates the <lb/>long term behaviour of the avalanche duration, explaining our observation of this in <lb/>our numerical simulations of this process 69 . <lb/></body>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Temperature stability <lb/>III-V semiconductor band gaps shrink with temperature. For example, the GaAs band <lb/>gap falls by around 5% on warming from liquid He to ambient. Ionization threshold <lb/>energies are likely to change in a similar manner, since they are determined by <lb/>considerations of conservation of energy and crystal momentum within the band <lb/>structure framework 11 . While a reduction in ionisation threshold energy would serve <lb/>to increase the ionisation coefficient, the accompanying changes in band structure <lb/>slope and curvature will also help determine the shift in ionisation threshold energy 11 <lb/>and the net trend is not clear. <lb/>Electron-phonon scattering thermalises and cools the populations of carriers heated in <lb/>strong electric fields. The rates of optical phonon absorption and emission by charge <lb/>carriers are given respectively by nC and <lb/>C <lb/>n ) <lb/>1 <lb/>( + <lb/>, where the factor C depends on <lb/>the band structure and the electron phonon coupling strength and n is the optical <lb/>phonon occupation number, given by eqn. (15). But phonons become more populous <lb/>with temperature. In GaAs, where the optical phonon energy is around 30meV, n <lb/>increases from effectively zero at liquid He to n~0.43 at ambient temperature, so that <lb/>the emission rate increases by 43% over this range and the absorption rate also <lb/>increases, from effectively zero at liquid He to 30% of the emission rate at room <lb/>temperature. Because of this increase in scattering rates with temperature the <lb/>associated cooling of carriers in high electric fields grows stronger as the lattice is <lb/>heated. So, counter intuitively, heating the lattice cools the charge carriers in a high <lb/>field, because at high fields the charge carriers are much hotter than the lattice, whose <lb/>heating serves to enhance its interaction with the carriers. The net effect is to inhibit <lb/>the transport of carriers to ionisation threshold and reduce ionisation coefficients. <lb/>Indeed, Ma et al. 72 observe the saturation expected in the ionization coefficients at low <lb/>temperatures as the optical phonon occupation number approaches zero. <lb/>At large values the mean multiplication is particularly sensitive to the ionization <lb/>coefficients. For example, when α = β in the local model it is given by <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>&gt;= <lb/>&lt; <lb/>) <lb/>w <lb/>( <lb/>M <lb/>α <lb/>, so that <lb/>w <lb/>M <lb/>d <lb/>M <lb/>d <lb/>2 <lb/>&gt; <lb/>=&lt; <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>α <lb/>and the logarithmic temperature <lb/>sensitivity is given by <lb/>dT <lb/>d <lb/>w <lb/>M <lb/>dT <lb/>M <lb/>d <lb/>M <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>&gt; <lb/>=&lt; <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>&gt; <lb/>&lt; <lb/>. At appreciable values of <lb/></body>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>multiplication, when w <lb/>α is close to unity, the temperature sensitivity of the mean <lb/>multiplication is thus proportional to that of the ionization coefficient, but magnified <lb/>by the mean gain. <lb/>Measurements on the Al 0.6 Ga 0.4 As material system show that the temperature <lb/>sensitivity is much reduced for devices with short multiplication regions 73 . Fig. 13 <lb/>shows measurements 74 of mean multiplication, plotted on a log scale to expand the <lb/>range, against bias, for a range of temperatures and of device lengths. The shorter <lb/>devices show considerably reduced variation of multiplication with temperature. We <lb/>believe this results from that fact that as the device length is reduced the ionization <lb/>path lengths must also be reduced (by increasing the field) to maintain the same <lb/>degree of mean multiplication. The reduced temperature dependence follows simply <lb/>because carriers then have a shorter distance in which to scatter off phonons before <lb/>ionising. Similar effects are seen in short GaAs structures 75 and also in Si 76 , though <lb/>the effect of temperature is weaker in this material, possibly 77 because of its softer <lb/>ionisation threshold. <lb/>Above breakdown <lb/>When an APD is biased above breakdown at least one of the many electron-hole pairs <lb/>injected in an optical pulse may give rise to a chain of multiplication events which, in <lb/>principle could go on indefinitely. Such &apos;infinite&apos; chains dominate the mean <lb/>multiplication in any large ensemble of trials and, in the absence of other limiting <lb/>factors, the mean multiplication is then predicted to diverge (as in eqns. (3)). The <lb/>resulting current then continues to increase until other effects intervene to quench the <lb/>flow. However, this does not mean that all trials performed under conditions &apos;above <lb/>breakdown&apos; will lead to a divergent multiplication; many such multiplication chains <lb/>will eventually fizzle out, giving a finite value of multiplication for that trial. The <lb/>breakdown probability, P b for a single trial then becomes the interesting quantity <lb/>above breakdown in an APD. <lb/>The photocurrent generated by a single photogenerated electron-hole pair amounts <lb/>to 20 <lb/>w <lb/>qv /~10 -8 A and lasts for only <lb/>v <lb/>w /~10 -11 s in a w = 1µm wide multiplication <lb/>region. If the photocurrent is to be detected by conventional electronic circuitry then <lb/></body>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>the primary electron-hole pair must go on to enjoy a multiplication of a few orders of <lb/>magnitude, corresponding to a virtually endless multiplication chain. The breakdown <lb/>probability therefore effectively determines the probability of detecting a single <lb/>absorbed photon in an APD operated in Geiger mode, above breakdown. Such Single <lb/>Photon Avalanche Diodes (SPADs) have application in quantum key distribution in <lb/>secure systems, since observation by an eavesdropper of the quantum state of the <lb/>photon can affect this state in a way detectable by the legitimate observer. These <lb/>devices also have a number of other uses; for example in precision range finding, <lb/>satellite laser ranging, deep space laser communication, time resolved photon <lb/>counting spectroscopy and quantum cryptography. <lb/>Breakdown at low electric fields is an advantage in SPADs, since high electric fields <lb/>can strip charge carriers from deep traps, perhaps captured there from a previous <lb/>avalanche. Such carriers may then go on to initiate another avalanche, which, if <lb/>detected, would constitute a &apos;dark count&apos;, registered erroneously as a detected photon. <lb/>However, SPADs with reduced multiplication region widths will require increased <lb/>electric fields to maintain breakdown. Moreover, since ionisation is denied in the <lb/>dead space, avalanche breakdown will be postponed, requiring a further increase in <lb/>electric field. Thus, while short SPADs have obvious speed advantages, because of <lb/>their reduced transit time, the associated enhancement in dead space effects is not of <lb/>obvious advantage to SPAD operation. <lb/>Once breakdown is reached the next important consideration is the rate at which P b <lb/>increases with field; a rapid increase is an advantage if dark counts are to be avoided. <lb/>In the local model breakdown probability was studied by Oldham 78 and McIntyre 79 . <lb/>They showed that P b is zero precisely at breakdown and as the ionization coefficients <lb/>increase with the field above breakdown so the breakdown probability increases first <lb/>linearly with ionisation coefficients and then approaches unity asymptotically. Thus, <lb/>in most trials at fields high above breakdown threshold the current increases until <lb/>limited by external factors. The initial, linear rate of increase was predicted to be <lb/>faster for a larger ratio of primary to secondary ionization coefficient and these local <lb/>predictions were supported by measurements on Si 78 . <lb/></body>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body>McIntyre later extended his local theory 79 to include nonlocal behaviour 10 . Using this <lb/>nonlocal technique Wang et al. 80 predicted that in SPADs with avalanche regions <lb/>composed of GaAs, InAlAs or InP the breakdown probability increases more slowly <lb/>just above breakdown threshold in narrower avalanche regions. These authors <lb/>ascribed this result to the effects of dead space. However, in a more detailed study Ng <lb/>et al. 81 showed that allowing for dead space actually increases this initial linear rate of <lb/>growth of P b , but that this effect competes with that of the convergence of the <lb/>ionization coefficients at high fields. This convergence tends to reduce the rate of <lb/>growth of P b in a SPAD designed so that the primary ionisation coefficient is larger 78 , <lb/>and this effect wins the competition in the specific cases studied by Wang et al. 80 . <lb/>Also of interest is the rate at which the avalanche current increases with time when the <lb/>current in a particular trial happens to grow very large. The sooner the event can be <lb/>detected and registered as a &apos;count&apos; the sooner the system can be reset to detect the <lb/>next incoming photon and the greater is the system band width. To register as a count <lb/>the current must exceed an arbitrary, predetermined threshold, say 1mA <lb/>(corresponding to a gain of M~10 5 ). This threshold is also sometimes confusingly <lb/>referred to as the &apos;breakdown threshold&apos;. In order to avoid confusion with the <lb/>&apos;breakdown threshold&apos; associated with the divergence of eqns. (3) we shall instead <lb/>refer to this as the &apos;decision threshold&apos;. <lb/>Of course, the avalanche current above breakdown is also a stochastic variable and is <lb/>just as susceptible to random fluctuations as it is below. However, in this case we are <lb/>not interested in fluctuations in the measured multiplication (whose mean value <lb/>diverges) but rather in fluctuations in the evolving current. From the time evolution <lb/>of the mean of the stochastic current and of its standard deviation we can evaluate <lb/>both the mean time to decision threshold, which limits the communications bit rate, <lb/>and the standard deviation in this time, also known as the &apos;jitter&apos;. This latter becomes <lb/>the more important criterion when communications bandwidth is less important than <lb/>precision in mean time to decision threshold, such as in laser range finding or in time <lb/>resolved single photon spectroscopy. These considerations are discussed in the <lb/>following. <lb/></body>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<body>Numerical simulations 82 using the RPL technique show that both the mean time to <lb/>decision threshold and the timing jitter decrease with increasing breakdown <lb/>probability as the bias is increased above breakdown. They also decrease with <lb/>decreasing avalanche region width and increasing importance of ionization dead <lb/>space. Saleh et al. 17,83 and Groves et al. 71 showed that Malthusian behaviour also <lb/>develops above breakdown. Indeed, after an initial, brief transient the mean <lb/>avalanche current grows exponentially in time by several orders of magnitude before <lb/>decision threshold is reached. This Malthusian behaviour thus dominates current <lb/>evolution above breakdown. Groves et al. 71 further showed that above breakdown, <lb/>where the Malthusian parameter, is negative, the standard deviation in current grows <lb/>exponentially at the same rate, <lb/>) <lb/>exp( <lb/>t <lb/>γ <lb/>− as the mean avalanche current. This stands <lb/>in curious contrast with the behaviour below breakdown 17 , where is positive, since <lb/>there it decays exponentially at one half of the rate, <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>/ <lb/>exp( <lb/>t <lb/>γ <lb/>− <lb/>of the mean <lb/>current. It follows that in this model the jitter becomes independent of time 71 in this <lb/>Malthusian regime and this result is confirmed by numerical simulations. <lb/>All of these arguments assume very simple models for the devices which are hardly <lb/>justified in practice. Thus, while Groves et al. 71 allow the electric field to vary in <lb/>position in 1-D to deduce Malthusian behaviour above threshold, the field is assumed <lb/>independent of time. Other models 10,17,78,79,80,81,82,83 assume the field is uniform <lb/>everywhere within the multiplication region and at all times. In practice APDs and <lb/>SPADs possess, at best, approximate radial symmetry, so that reliable, detailed <lb/>modelling of real devices requires a Monte-Carlo or Fokker-Planck simulator in 2-D. <lb/>More importantly, in a SPAD the exponentially growing current and associated space <lb/>charge distort the electric field profile, which then changes in time as well, in turn <lb/>affecting the evolution of the avalanche. Using detailed numerical studies Spinelli <lb/>and Lacaita 84 argue that the lateral spread of avalanche charge triggered at a single <lb/>point and the resulting spread in times to reach the lateral boundary of the SPAD <lb/>dominates the jitter. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>The study of impact ionization and avalanche multiplication has been dominated since <lb/>the 1960s by the assumptions of the local model, namely that charge carriers can be <lb/></body>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body>assumed to achieve equilibrium instantaneously with the local electric field in their <lb/>ability to impact ionise, at least compared with other length and time scales in an <lb/>experiment, and that they travel always at some saturated drift velocity. The ability of <lb/>a group of charge carriers to initiate impact ionization is then determined by this local <lb/>field and not by their spatial or temporal history. This simplifying assumption has <lb/>informed the interpretation of measurements on avalanche multiplication and noise <lb/>and the design of APDs for use both below breakdown as noisy, linear amplifiers and <lb/>above breakdown as single photon detectors. While this local assumption may have <lb/>been adequate in early Si APDs and SPADs, whose length scale appears to be <lb/>determined by the small optical absorption coefficient in the indirect band gap, it is <lb/>not justified in devices comprised of direct gap semiconductors, which can be made <lb/>much smaller. <lb/>Fortunately, while nonlocal multiplication is more difficult to model, it does bring <lb/>advantages, of reductions in noise, temperature dependence and operating voltage, <lb/>and of increased speed, so that thin avalanche regions can bring positive benefits, <lb/>contrary to the predictions of the local model. The interpretation of measurements <lb/>and the modelling of stochastic processes in this regime have provided stimulating <lb/>problems with fruitful solutions. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>The authors wish to acknowledge EPSRC, EU, DERA Malvern, Agilent, Marconi-<lb/>Bookham and DTC for financial support. They also wish to thank the research <lb/>fellows and students whose hard work and insights have helped us to arrive at our <lb/>present understanding of these processes and to acknowledge gratefully the <lb/>specialised help of Richard Tozer and of Peter Robson, who originally invited us <lb/>down this path and to whose memory this article is dedicated. Chris Groves and <lb/>Majeed Hayat are thanked for critical readings of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 1: α measured in Al 0.6 Ga 0.4 As pin diodes, with w = 0.027µm (∇), 0.0466µm <lb/>(∆), 0.089µm ( ), 0.512µm ( ) and 0.8µm ( ) vs inverse electric field. The full line <lb/>(-) denotes the envelope. SA Plimmer is thanked for the measurements shown in this <lb/>figure. <lb/>Inverse electric field (cm/V) <lb/>0e+0 <lb/>1e-6 <lb/>2e-6 <lb/>3e-6 <lb/>4e-6 <lb/>5e-6 <lb/>Ionisation coefficients (/cm) <lb/>1e+1 <lb/>1e+2 <lb/>1e+3 <lb/>1e+4 <lb/>1e+5 <lb/>1e+6 <lb/></body>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 2: Ionization path length pdfs for electrons (dotted) and holes (full) in GaAs <lb/>calculated using Monte Carlo. DS Ong is thanked for the calculations shown in this <lb/>figure <lb/>Ionisationpathlength, l(µm) <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>Ionisation path length PDF (µm -1 <lb/>) <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>E=600kV/cm <lb/>&lt;l e &gt;=0.1309µm <lb/>&lt;l h &gt;=0.1657µm <lb/>E=900kV/cm <lb/>&lt;l e &gt;=0.0695µm <lb/>&lt;l h &gt;=0.0793µm <lb/></body>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 3: Probability distribution of multiplication P(M) calculated 18 using Monte <lb/>Carlo for a w = 0.5µm GaAs pin diode, &lt;M&gt;~5. <lb/>M <lb/>0 <lb/>10 20 30 40 50 60 70 <lb/>P(M) <lb/>10 -4 <lb/>10 -3 <lb/>10 -2 <lb/>10 -1 <lb/>10 0 <lb/></body>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 4: Circuit for measuring avalanche gain and noise using phase sensitive <lb/>detection 21 . <lb/></body>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 5: Excess avalanche noise 22 vs mean multiplication in GaAs pin and nip diodes <lb/>for values of w ranging from 1.13µm to 0.049µm (pins) and 0.36µm to 0.05µm (nips). <lb/>Full lines are from eqns. (13) with k increasing from 0 to 1 in steps of 0.1 <lb/>M e <lb/>2 <lb/>3 4 5 6 789 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>Excess Noise, F <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3.5 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>3.0 <lb/>4.0 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>M h <lb/>2 <lb/>3 4 5 6 789 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>Excess Noise, F <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3.5 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>3.0 <lb/>4.0 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>GaAs p-i-ns <lb/>GaAs n-i-ps <lb/>decreasing w <lb/>decreasing w <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/></body>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 6: Excess noise 32 F vs. mean multiplication, &lt;M&gt; for pure electron (open) and <lb/>mixed injection (closed symbols) measured in Si pin diodes, with w = 0.10µm( , ), <lb/>0.15µm( , ) and 0.29µm(∆,σ). Thin dashed lines are calculated from the local <lb/>model, while the solid lines (mixed) and thick dashed lines (pure electron injection) <lb/>are calculated from the nonlocal model. <lb/>multiplication factor, M <lb/>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 <lb/>excess noise factor, F <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>k=0.7 <lb/>k=0.5 <lb/>k=0.4 <lb/>k=0.2 <lb/>k=0 <lb/></body>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 7: Excess noise vs mean multiplication measured 36 in Al 0.8 Ga 0.2 As pin diodes <lb/>for pure electron injection as w is decreased from 1.024µm (rectangles) to 0.02µm <lb/>(hexagons). <lb/>Multiplication factor, M <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>Excess noise factor, F <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/>16 <lb/>1 <lb/>k = 2 <lb/>k = 1 <lb/>k = 0 <lb/></body>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 8: Excess noise characteristics of 4H-SiC pin APDs with a) w = 0.105µm and <lb/>b) w = 0.285µm measured using 365nm (circles) and 230nm (squares) light. Dashed <lb/>lines are McIntyre&apos;s local predictions. B.K. Ng is thanked for these measurements. <lb/></body>

			<page>40 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 9: Ionization path length pdfs calculated 51 from Monte Carlo, Lucky Drift and <lb/>Fokker-Planck at a field of 500kV/cm. <lb/>Ionization path length, x (µm) <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>PDF (µm -1 <lb/>) <lb/>0 <lb/>4 <lb/>8 <lb/>12 <lb/>16 <lb/>Fokker-Planck <lb/>Monte-Carlo <lb/>Lucky Drift <lb/>Field (kV/cm) <lb/>250 <lb/>500 <lb/>750 <lb/>Ionization Coefficient (µm -1 <lb/>) <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>Monte-Carlo <lb/>Fokker Planck <lb/>Lucky Drift <lb/>Dirac Delta <lb/></body>

			<page>41 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 10: Ionization event pdf, h(x,t) calculated 53 by Fokker-Planck at 500kV/cm. <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>hx <lb/>t <lb/>P o s i t i o n ( <lb/>µ m ) <lb/>T im e ( p s ) <lb/></body>

			<page>42 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 11: Contour plot of ionization event pdf in space and time, h(ζ,τ), <lb/>generated 61 by a Simple Monte Carlo model for GaAs at an electric field of 496kV/cm. <lb/>0.0 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>3.0 <lb/>4.0 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0 (µm.ps) -1 <lb/>5 (µm.ps) -1 <lb/>10 (µm.ps) -1 <lb/>15 (µm.ps) -1 <lb/>20 (µm.ps) -1 <lb/>τ (ps) <lb/>ζ (µm) <lb/></body>

			<page>43 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 12: Scaled mean current impulse response, calculated 63 for diffusion <lb/>coefficients of D = 0.1cm 2 s -1 (solid line), 0.2cm 2 s -1 (dashed line), 1.0cm 2 s -1 (dash-dot-<lb/>dot-dashed line) and 2.0cm 2 s -1 (dotted line) for (a) w = 1.0µm (E = 307kV/cm) and <lb/>(b) w = 0.2µm (E = 496kV/cm). Also shown are results calculated assuming a <lb/>constant carrier speed. <lb/>w = 1.0µm <lb/>tv/w <lb/>0.0 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>3.0 <lb/>4.0 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>i(t)w/v (nA.ns) <lb/>0.1 <lb/>1 <lb/>tv/w <lb/>0.0 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>3.0 <lb/>4.0 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>i(t)w/v (nA.ns) <lb/>0.1 <lb/>1 <lb/>increasing D <lb/>w = 0.2µm <lb/>increasing D <lb/>(b) <lb/>(a) <lb/>constant speed <lb/>model <lb/>constant speed <lb/>model <lb/></body>

			<page>44 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 13: Temperature dependence of multiplication 74 in Al 0.6 Ga 0.4 As in the range <lb/>13K to 450K for (a) w = 0.046µm and 0.089µm devices and (b) a w = 0.85µm device. <lb/>Voltage(V) <lb/>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 <lb/>M <lb/>e -1 <lb/>10 -3 <lb/>10 -2 <lb/>10 -1 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>10 1 <lb/>0.089µm <lb/>0.046µm <lb/>Increasing <lb/>Temperature <lb/>(a) <lb/>Voltage(V) <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>35 <lb/>40 <lb/>45 <lb/>50 <lb/>M <lb/>e -1 <lb/>10 -3 <lb/>10 -2 <lb/>10 -1 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>10 1 <lb/>0.85µm <lb/>Increasing <lb/>Temperature <lb/>(b) <lb/></body>

			<page>45 <lb/></page>

			. <lb/>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1 C. Zener, &apos;A theory of electrical breakdown of solid dielectrics&apos;, Proc. Roy. Soc. <lb/>145A, 523 -9, (1934) <lb/>2 B. K. Ng, F. Yan, J. P. R. David, R. C. Tozer, G. J. Rees, C. Qin and J. H. Zhao, <lb/>&apos;Multiplication and excess noise characteristics of thin 4H-SiC UV avalanche <lb/>photodiodes&apos;, IEEE Photonics Technol. Lett., 14, 1342 -4 (2002) <lb/>3 D.C. Herbert, C. J. Williams and M. Jaros, &apos;Impact ionization and noise in SiGe <lb/>multiquantum well structures&apos;, Electron. Letts., 32, 1616 -8 (1996) <lb/>4 P. Yuan, S. Wang, X. Sun, X.G. Zheng, A.L. Holmes and J.C. Campbell, <lb/>&apos;Avalanche photodiodes with an impact ionisation engineered multiplication region&apos;, <lb/>IEEE Photonics Tech. Letts., 12, 1370 -2 (2000) <lb/>5 J.S. Townsend, &apos;The genesis of ions by the motion of positive ions in a gas and a <lb/>theory of the sparking potential&apos;. Phil. Mag. 6, ser. VI, 598 -618 (1903) <lb/>6 G.E. Stillman and C. M. Wolfe, &apos;Avalanche photodiodes&apos;, Semiconductors and <lb/>Semimetals (Eds. R. K. Willardson and A. C. Beer, New York Academic Press), 12, <lb/>291 -392 (1977) <lb/>7 F. Capasso, &apos;Physics of Avalanche Photodiodes&apos;, Semiconductors and Semimetals <lb/>(Eds. R. K. Willardson and A. C. Beer, New York Academic Press), 22, 2 -172 <lb/>(1985) <lb/>8 R.J. McIntyre, &apos;Multiplication noise in uniform avalanche diodes&apos;, IEEE Trans. <lb/>Electron Devices, 13, 164 -8 (1966) <lb/>9 S.A. Plimmer, J.P.R. David, G.J. Rees and P.N. Robson, &apos;Ionisation coefficients in <lb/>Al x Ga 1-x As (x = 0 -0.6)&apos;, Semicond. Sci. Technol., 15 692 -9 (2000) <lb/>10 R. J. McIntyre, &apos;A new look at impact ionization -part 1: a theory of gain, noise, <lb/>breakdown probability and frequency response&apos;, IEEE Trans. Electron Devices, 46, <lb/>1623 -31 (1999) <lb/>11 C.L. Anderson and C.R. Crowell, &apos;Threshold energies for electron-hole pair <lb/>production by impact ionization in semiconductors&apos;, Phys. Rev. B5 2267-72, (1972) <lb/>12 R. Ghin, J.P.R. David, S.A. Plimmer, M. Hopkinson, G.J. Rees, D.C. Herbert and <lb/>D.R Wight, &apos;Avalanche multiplication and breakdown in Ga 0.52 In 0.48 P diodes&apos;, IEEE <lb/>Trans. Electron. Dev., 45, 2096 -101 (1998) <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>46 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>13 Y.L. Goh, D.J. Massey, A.R. J. Marshall, J.S. Ng, C.H. Tan, W.K. Ng, G.J. Rees, <lb/>M. Hopkinson, J.P.R. David and S.K. Jones, &apos;Avalanche multiplication in InAlAs&apos; <lb/>IEEE Trans. Electron. Dev., 54, 11 -16 (2007) <lb/>14 L.J.J. Tan, J.S. Ng, C.H. Tan, M. Hopkinson and J.P.R. David, &apos;Effect of dead <lb/>space on low field avalanche multiplication in InP&apos;, IEEE Trans. Electron. Dev., 54, <lb/>2051 -4 (2007) <lb/>15 D.J. Massey, J.P.R. David, C.H. Tan, B.K. Ng, G.J Rees, D.J. Robbins and D.C. <lb/>Herbert, &apos;Impact ionisation in submicron Si devices&apos;, J. Appl. Phys., 95, 5931 -3 <lb/>(2004) <lb/>16 Y. Okuto and C.R. Crowell, &apos;Ionisation coefficients in semiconductors: a <lb/>nonlocalised property&apos; Phys. Rev. B 10, 4284 -96 (1974) <lb/>17 M.M. Hayat, B.E.A. Saleh and M.C. Teich, &apos;Effect of dead space on gain and noise <lb/>of double carrier multiplication avalanche photodiodes&apos;, IEEE Trans. Electron. Dev., <lb/>39, 546 -52 (1992) <lb/>18 D.S. Ong, K.F. Li, G.J. Rees, G.M. Dunn, J.P.R. David and P.N. Robson, &apos;A Monte <lb/>Carlo investigation of multiplication noise in thin p + in + GaAs avalanche photodiodes&apos; <lb/>IEEE Trans. Electron. Dev. 45, 1804 -10 (1998) <lb/>19 e.g. A. Van der Ziel, &apos;Solid State Physical Electronics&apos; Prentice Hall (1965) <lb/>20 S.Ramo, &apos;Currents induced by electron motion&apos;, Proceedings of the I.R.E, 584-585, <lb/>September (1939) <lb/>21 K.S. Lau, C.H. Tan, B.K. Ng, K.F. Li, R.C. Tozer, J.P.R. David and G.J. Rees, <lb/>&apos;Excess noise measurement in avalanche photodiodes using a transimpedance <lb/>amplifier front end&apos;, Meas. Sci. Technol. 17, 1941 -6 (2006) <lb/>22 K.F. Li, D.S. Ong, J.P.R. David, G.J. Rees, R.C. Tozer, P.N. Robson and R. <lb/>Grey,&apos;Avalanche multiplication noise characteristics in thin GaAs p + in + diodes&apos;, IEEE <lb/>Trans. Electron Dev., 45, 2102 -7 (1998) <lb/>23 C. Hu, K.A. Anselm, B.G. Streetman and J.C. Campbell, &apos;Noise characteristics of <lb/>thin multiplication region GaAs avalanche photodiodes&apos;, &apos;Appl. Phys. Letts.&apos;, 69, <lb/>3734 -6, (1996) <lb/>24 D.C. Herbert, &apos;Avalanche noise in submicron pin diodes&apos;, Electron. Letts., 33, 1257 <lb/>-8 (1997) <lb/>25 K.F. Li, D.S. Ong, J.P.R.David, R.C. Tozer, G.J. Rees, P.N. Robson and R. Grey, <lb/>&apos;Low excess noise characteristics in thin avalanche region GaAs diodes&apos; Electron. <lb/>Letts. 34, 125 -6 (1998) <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>47 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>26 K.F. Li, D.S. Ong, J.P.R. David, R.C. Tozer, G.J. Rees, P.N. Robson and R. Grey, <lb/>&apos;Low noise GaAs and Al 0.3 Ga 0.7 As avalanche photodetectors&apos; IEEE Proc. <lb/>Optoelectron. 146, 21 -4 (1999) <lb/>27 X.G. Zheng, X. Sun, S. Wang, P. Yuan, G.S. Kinsey, A.L. Holmes, B.G. Streetman <lb/>and J.C. Campbell, &apos;Multiplication noise of Al x Ga 1-x As avalanche photodiodes with <lb/>high Al concentration and thin multiplication region&apos;, Appl. Phys. Letts. 78, 3833 -5 <lb/>(2001) <lb/>28 C.H. Tan, J.P.R. David, S.A. Plimmer, G.J. Rees, R.C. Tozer and R. Grey, &apos;Low <lb/>multiplication noise thin Al 0.6 Ga 0.4 As avalanche photodiodes&apos;, IEEE Trans Electron <lb/>Dev. 48, 1310 -7 (2001) <lb/>29 C.H. Tan, R. Ghin, J.P.R. David, G.J. Rees and M. Hopkinson, &apos;The effect of dead <lb/>space on gain and excess noise in In 0.48 Ga 0.52 P p + in + diodes&apos;, Semicond. Sci. Technol. <lb/>18, 803 -6 (2003) <lb/>30 P. Yuan, C.C. Hansing, K. Anselm, C.V. Lennox, H. Nie, A.L. Holmes, B.G. <lb/>Sreetman and J.C. Campbell, &apos;Impact ionisation characteristics of III-V <lb/>semiconductors for a wide range of multiplication thicknesses&apos;, IEEE JQE, 36, 198 -<lb/>204 (2000) <lb/>31 Y.L. Goh, A.R.J. Marshall, D.J. Massey, J.S. Ng, C.H. Tan, M. Hopkinson, J.P.R. <lb/>David, S,K, Jones, C.C. Button and S.M. Pinches, &apos;Excess avalanche noise in <lb/>In 0.52 Al 0.48 As&apos;, IEEE JQE 43, 503 -7 (2007) <lb/>32 C.H. Tan, J.C. Clark, J.P.R. David, G.J. Rees, S.A. Plimmer, R.C. Tozer, D.C. <lb/>Herbert, D.J. Robbins, W.Y. Leong and J. Newey, &apos;Avalanche noise measurement in <lb/>thin Si p + in + diodes&apos; Appl. Phys Letts., 76, 3926 -8 (2000) <lb/>33 K.M. Van Vliet, A. Friedmann and L.M. Rucker, &apos;Theory of carrier multiplication <lb/>and noise in avalanche devices part II: two carrier processes <lb/>34 B.K. Ng, J.P.R. David, S.A. Plimmer, M. Hopkinson, R.C. Tozer and G.J. Rees, <lb/>&apos;Impact ionisation coefficients of Al 0.8 Ga 0.3 As&apos; Appl. Phys. Lett., 77, 4374 -6 (2000) <lb/>35 B.K. Ng, J.P.R. David, G.J. Rees, R.C. Tozer, M. Hopkinson and R.J. Airey, <lb/>&apos;Avalanche multiplication and breakdown in Al x Ga 1 -x As (x &lt; 0.9)&apos;, IEEE Trans. <lb/>Electron Dev. 49, 2349 -51 (2002) <lb/>36 B. K. Ng, J. P. R. David, R. C. Tozer, M. Hopkinson, G. Hill and G. J. Rees, <lb/>&apos;Excess noise characteristics of Al 0.8 Ga 0.2 As avalanche photodiodes&apos; IEEE Photonics <lb/>Tech. Letts., 14, 522 -4 (2002) <lb/>37 B. K. Ng, F. Yan, J. P. R. David, R. C. Tozer, G. J. Rees, C. Qin and J. H. Zhao, <lb/>&apos;Multiplication and excess noise characteristics of thin 4H-SiC UV avalanche <lb/>photodiodes&apos;, IEEE Photonics Technol. Lett., 14, 1342 -4 (2002) <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>48 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>38 B. K. Ng, J. P. R. David, R. C. Tozer, G. J. Rees, F. Yan, J. H. Zhao, and M. <lb/>Weiner, &apos;Nonlocal effects in thin 4H-SiC UV avalanche photodiodes&apos; IEEE Trans. <lb/>Electron Dev. 50, 1724 -32 (2003) <lb/>39 F. Ma, X. Li, J.C. Campbell, J.D. Beck, C.-F. Wan and M.A. Kinch, &apos;Monte Carlo <lb/>simulations of Hg 0.7 Cd 0.3 Te avalanche photodiodes and resonance phenomena in the <lb/>multiplication noise&apos; Appl. Phys. Lett., 83 785 -7 (2003) <lb/>40 M.A. Kinch, J.D. Beck, C.-F. Wan, F. Ma and J.C. Campbell, &apos;HgCdTe electron <lb/>avalanche photodiodes&apos; J. Electron. Mats., 33, 630 -9 (2004) <lb/>41 D.C. Herbert, P.A. Childs, R.A. Abram, G.C. Crow and M. Walmsley, &apos;Self-<lb/>consistent 2-D Monte Carlo simulations of InSb APD&apos;, IEEE Trans Electron. Dev., <lb/>52, 2175 -81 (2005) <lb/>42 A.R.J. Marshall, C.H. Tan, M.J. Steer and J.P.R. David, &apos;Electron dominated <lb/>impact ionisation and avalanche gain characteristics in InAs photodiodes&apos;, Appl. Phys. <lb/>Lett., 93, 111107-9 (2008) <lb/>43 A.R.J. Marshall, C.H. Tan, M.J. Steer and J.P.R. David, &apos;Extremely low excess <lb/>noise in InAs electron avalanche photodiodes&apos; IEEE Photonics Tech. Letts., 21, 866 -<lb/>8 (2009) <lb/>44 M.M. Hayat, W.L. Sargeant and B.A. Saleh, &apos;Effect of dead space on gain and <lb/>noise in Si and GaAs avalanche photodiodes&apos;, IEEE J. Quantum Electron., 28, 1360 -<lb/>5 (1992) <lb/>45 M.M. Hayat, O.-H. Kwon, S. Wang, J.C. Campbell, B.E.A. Saleh and M.C. Teich, <lb/>&apos;Boundary effects on multiplication noise in thin heterostructure avalanche <lb/>photodiodes: theory and experiment&apos; IEEE Trans. Electron Dev., 49, 2114 -23 (2002) <lb/>46 C. Jacoboni and M. Reggiani, &apos;The Monte Carlo method for the solution of charge <lb/>transport in semiconductors with applications to covalent materials&apos;, Rev. Mod. Phys. <lb/>55, 645 -705 (1983) <lb/>47 B.K. Ridley, &apos;The lucky-drift mechanism of impact ionization&apos;, J. Phys. C, 16, 3373 <lb/>-88 (1983) <lb/>48 M.G. Burt, &apos;An alternative expression for the impact ionization coefficient in a <lb/>semiconductor derived using the lucky drift theory&apos;, J. Phys. C., 18, L477 -81 <lb/>(1985) <lb/>49 S. McKenzie and M.G. Burt, &apos;A test of the lucky drift theory of the impact <lb/>ionization coefficient using Monte Carlo simulation&apos;, J. Phys. C., 18, 1959 -73 <lb/>(1986) <lb/>50 B. Jacob, S. A. Plimmer, P. N. Robson and G. J. Rees, &apos;Lucky drift model for non-<lb/>local impact ionization&apos;, IEE Proc. Optoelectron., 148, 81 -3 (2001) <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>49 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>51 B. Jacob, P. N. Robson, J. P. R. David and G. J. Rees, &apos;Fokker-Planck model for <lb/>nonlocal impact ionization in semiconductors&apos;, J. Appl. Phys., 90, 1314 -7 (2001) <lb/>52 E. Bringuier, &apos;Augmented Fokker-Planck equation for electron transport in arbitrary <lb/>fields&apos;, J. Appl. Phys., 86, 6847 -51 (1999) <lb/>53 B. Jacob, P. N. Robson, J. P. R. David and G. J. Rees, &apos;Fokker-Planck approach to <lb/>impact ionization distributions in space and time&apos;, J. Appl. Phys., 91, 5438 -41 <lb/>(2002) <lb/>54 S.A.Plimmer, J.P.R.David, D.S.Ong and K.F.Li, &apos;A simple model for avalanche <lb/>multiplication including deadspace effects&apos;, IEEE Trans. Electron Dev., 46, 769 -75 <lb/>(1999) <lb/>55 D.S. Ong, K.F. Li, G.J. Rees, J.P.R. David and P.N. Robson, &apos;A simple model to <lb/>determine multiplication and noise in avalanche photodiodes&apos;, J. Appl. Phys., 83, <lb/>3426 -8 (1998) <lb/>56 R. B. Emmons, &apos;Avalanche photodiode frequency response&apos;, J. Appl. Phys., 38, <lb/>3705 -14 (1967) <lb/>57 R. Kuvås and C. A. Lee, &apos;Quasistatic approximation for semiconductor avalanches&apos;, <lb/>J. Appl. Phys., 41, 1743 -55 (1970) <lb/>58 B. E. A. Saleh, M. M. Hayat and M. C. Teich, &apos;Effect of dead space on the excess <lb/>noise factor and time response of avalanche photodiodes&apos;, IEEE Trans. Electron Dev., <lb/>37, 1976 -84 (1990) <lb/>59 M.M. Hayat and B.E.A. Saleh, &apos;Statistical properties of the impulse response <lb/>function of double carrier multiplication avalanche photodiodes including the effect of <lb/>dead space&apos;, J. Lightwave Technol., 10, 1415 -25 (1992) <lb/>60 J. S. Ng, C. H. Tan, B. K. Ng, P. J. Hambleton, J. P. R. David, G. J. Rees, A. H. <lb/>You and D. S. Ong, &apos;Effect of dead space on avalanche speed&apos;, IEEE Trans. Electron <lb/>Dev., 49, 544 -9 (2002) <lb/>61 S. A. Plimmer, J. P. R. David, B. Jacob and G. J. Rees, &apos;Impact ionization <lb/>probabilities as functions of two-dimensional space and time&apos;, J. Appl. Phys., 89, <lb/>2742 -51 (2001) <lb/>62 D. S. Ong, G. J. Rees and J. P. R. David, &apos;Avalanche speed in thin avalanche <lb/>photodiodes&apos;, J. Appl. Phys., 93, 4232-4239 (2003) <lb/>63 C.H. Tan, P.J. Hambleton, J.P.R. David, R.C. Tozer, and G.J. Rees, &apos;Calculation of <lb/>APD impulse response using a space-and time-dependent ionization probability <lb/>distribution function&apos; IEEE J. Lightwave Technol., 21, 155 -9 (2003) <lb/>64 P. J. Hambleton, S. A. Plimmer and G. J. Rees, &apos;Limitations of the saturated drift <lb/>velocity approximation for time domain modelling&apos;, Semicond. Sci. Technol., 17, 124 <lb/>-8 (2002) <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>50 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>65 P.J. Hambleton, S.A. Plimmer, J.P.R. David and G.J. Rees, &apos;Time response <lb/>modelling in submicron avalanche photodiodes&apos; &apos;IEE Proc. Optoelectron.&apos;, 150, 167-<lb/>70 (2003) <lb/>66 P.J. Hambleton, S.A. Plimmer, J.P.R. David, G.J. Rees and G.M. Dunn, &apos;Simulated <lb/>current response in avalanche photodiodes&apos; J. Appl Phys., 91, 2107 -111 (2002) <lb/>67 M. M. Hayat and G. Dong, &apos;A new approach for computing the bandwidth statistics <lb/>of avalanche photodiodes&apos;, IEEE Trans. Electron Dev., 47, 1273 -9 (2000) <lb/>68 P. Sun, M.M. Hayat, B.E.A. Saleh and M.C. Teich, &apos;Statistical correlation of gain <lb/>and buildup time in APDs and its effects on receiver performance&apos;, J. Lightwave <lb/>Technol., 24, 755 -68 (2006) <lb/>69 J. S. Ng, C. H. Tan, J. P. R. David and G. J. Rees, &apos;A general method for estimating <lb/>the duration of avalanche multiplication&apos;, Semicon. Sci. and Technol., 17, 1067 -71 <lb/>(2002) <lb/>70 K.B. Athreya and P. Ney., &apos;Branching processes&apos; Berlin-Germany: Springer-Verlag <lb/>(1972) <lb/>71 C. Groves, C.H. Tan, J.P.R. David, G.J. Rees and M.M. Hayat, &apos;Exponential time <lb/>response in analogue and Geiger mode avalanche photodiodes&apos;, IEEE Trans. <lb/>Electron. Dev., 52, 1527 -34 (2005) <lb/>72 F. Ma, G. Karve, X. Zheng, X. Sun, A. L. Holmes and J. C. Campbell, &apos;Low <lb/>temperature breakdown properties of Al x Ga 1-x As avalanche photodiodes&apos;, Appl. Phys. <lb/>Lett., 81, 1908 -10 (2002) <lb/>73 C.N. Harrison, J. P. R. David, M. Hopkinson and G. J. Rees, &apos;Temperature <lb/>dependence of avalanche multiplication in submicron Al 0.6 Ga 0.4 As diodes&apos; J. Appl. <lb/>Phys, 92, 7684 -6 (2002) <lb/>74 C.N. Harrison, J.P.R. David, C. Groves, M. Hopkinson and G.J. Rees, <lb/>&apos;Effect of temperature on the avalanche properties of sub-micron devices&apos; <lb/>Inst. Phys. Conf. Ser., 174, section 4, 263 -6 (2003) <lb/>75 C. Groves, R. Ghin, J.P.R. David and G.J. Rees, &apos;Temperature Dependence of <lb/>Impact Ionization in GaAs&apos;, IEEE Trans. Electron. Dev., 50, 2027 -31 (2003) <lb/>76 D.J. Massey, J.P.R. David and G.J. Rees, &apos;Temperature dependence of impact <lb/>ionisation in submicron silicon devices&apos;, IEEE Trans. Electron Dev., 53, 2328 -34 <lb/>(2006) <lb/> 77 C. Groves, J.P.R. David and G.J. Rees, &apos;The effect of ionisation threshold softness <lb/>on the temperature dependence of the impact ionisation coefficient&apos;, Semicond Sci. <lb/>and Technol., 18, 689 -92 (2003) <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>51 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>78 W.G. Oldham, R.R. Samuelson, and P. Antognetti, &apos;Triggering phenomena in <lb/>avalanche photodiodes&apos;, IEEE Trans. Electron. Dev., 19, 1056 -60 (1972) <lb/>79 R.J. McIntyre, &apos;On the avalanche initiation probability of avalanche diodes above <lb/>the breakdown voltage&apos;, IEEE Trans. Electron. Dev., 20, 637 -41 (1973) <lb/>80 S. Wang, F. Ma, X. Li, G. Karve, X. Zheng and J.C. Campbell &apos;Analysis of <lb/>breakdown probabilities in avalanche photodiodes using history-dependent analytical <lb/>model&apos; Appl. Phys. Lett., 82 1971 -3 (2003) <lb/>81 J. S. Ng, C. H. Tan, G. J. Rees and J. P. R. David, &apos;Effects of dead space on <lb/>breakdown probability in Geiger mode avalanche photodiode&apos;, J. Modern Optics, 54, <lb/>353 -360 (2007) <lb/>82 C.H.Tan, J.S.Ng, G.J.Rees and J.P.R.David, &apos;Statistics of avalanche current build <lb/>up time in single photon avalanche diodes&apos; IEEE J. Selected topics in quantum <lb/>electronics 13, 906 -910 (2007) <lb/>83 M.A. Saleh, M.M. Hayat, O.-H. Kwon, A.L. Holmes, J.C. Campbell, B.E. A. Saleh <lb/>and M.C. Teich, &apos;Breakdown voltage in thin III-V avalanche photodiodes&apos;, Appl. <lb/>Phys. Letts., 79, 4037 -9 (2001) <lb/>84 A Spinelli and A.L. Lacaita, &apos;Physics and numerical simulation of single photon <lb/>avalanche photodiodes&apos;, IEEE Trans. Electron Dev., 44, 1931 -43 (1997) </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
