<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Optically stimulated phosphorescence in quartz over the <lb/>millisecond to second time scale: insights into the role of <lb/>shallow traps in delaying luminescent recombination <lb/>C. Ankjaergaard * , M. Jain <lb/>Radiation Research Division, Risø National Laboratory for Sustainable Energy, <lb/>Technical University of Denmark, DK-4000 Roskilde, Denmark. <lb/>*Corresponding author; email: christina.ankjaergaard@gmail.com; Telephone: +45 <lb/>4677 4920 <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Time-resolved OSL curves from quartz are usually measured over a few hundred µs <lb/>because this time range best illustrates the main component in quartz which lies in the <lb/>range of 30-45 µs. In this study we present the decay form of quartz time-resolved <lb/>optically stimulated luminescence (TR-OSL) and optically stimulated <lb/>phosphorescence (OSP) covering over 8 orders of magnitude from 50 ns to~8 s. A <lb/>detailed characterisation of the previously unstudied slowly decaying signals (ms-s <lb/>time scales) is undertaken to understand the origin of these components and the role <lb/>of re-trapping following optical stimulation. We present preheat and stimulation <lb/>temperature dependence for both the TR-OSL and OSP curves in these time ranges <lb/>and use the latter data to determine the E and s values for the participating shallow <lb/>traps. We observe an abnormal decay behaviour seen as a sudden increase in the <lb/>decay rate (a &apos;kink&apos;) conspicuous at about 2 -3 s in the OSP curves measured at 75 <lb/>and 100°C. We satisfactorily reproduce this behaviour with a numerically solved <lb/>kinetic model consisting of 4 energy levels. The physical interpretation of the kinetic <lb/>rate equations is discussed in terms a three trap -one centre model or a one trap -two <lb/>centres model involving localised charge transfer. <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>Confidential: not for distribution. Submitted to IOP Publishing for peer review 28 April 2010 <lb/>Quartz, Optically Stimulated Luminescence (OSL), Time-Resolved OSL (TR-OSL), <lb/>Optically Stimulated Phosphorescence (OSP), Delayed OSL (DOSL), Photo-<lb/>Transferred Thermoluminescence (PTTL), 110 o C TL trap, kinetic model <lb/></front>

			<body>1. INTRODUCTION <lb/>Natural quartz is widely used in luminescence based retrospective dosimetry (Bøtter-<lb/>Jensen et al., 2003a). The luminescence from previously beta or gamma irradiated <lb/>quartz can be obtained by thermal, or by continuous or pulsed optical stimulation. In <lb/>pulsed optical stimulation mode the luminescence measured during and between the <lb/>pulses is known as Time-Resolved OSL (TR-OSL) and can be used to understand the <lb/>various recombination routes in a crystal. TR-OSL of quartz has been studied for <lb/>almost a decade (Bailiff, 2000; Chithambo and Galloway, 2000; Chithambo et al., <lb/>2007; Pagonis et al., 2009, and references in these papers). <lb/>The main processes that govern the time scales involved in optically stimulated <lb/>luminescence generation are generally exponential in nature. The most important of <lb/>these processes are: (a) detrapping: eviction of a trapped electron by stimulation to the <lb/>conduction band, (b) transition from the conduction band to the luminescence centre, <lb/>and (c) the relaxation from the excited state to the ground state of the luminescence <lb/>centre. <lb/>The rates of each of these processes are in turn determined by the lifetimes of the <lb/>electrons in transition from one energy level to the other. During optical detrapping <lb/>the mean life of a trapped electron is determined by the photoionisation cross-section <lb/>of the trap. In pulsed stimulation where the luminescence signal is analysed after the <lb/>pulse, i.e. in the off-time, process (a) can be eliminated and moreover it can be <lb/>assumed that there is negligible change in the concentration of recombination centres <lb/>as the energy delivered to the sample during a pulse is rather small. Thus, the relevant <lb/>parameter related to process (b) is the mean life of the electrons in the conduction <lb/>band. This lifetime would normally determine the lifetime of the luminescence decay. <lb/>However, in cases, where, depending on the nature of the centre, the recombination <lb/>leads to an excited state there is another delay in the luminescence production; a <lb/>photon is only released after relaxation from the excited to the ground state of the <lb/>centre, process (c). The excited state lifetime is a characteristic of the recombination <lb/>centre and is determined by the excited state to ground state transition, e.g., whether it <lb/>is forbidden (resulting in a long lifetime) or allowed (resulting in a short lifetime). <lb/>Thus, in pulsed OSL measurements the decay form of luminescence measured in the <lb/>off-time will be a combined effect of two exponential functions, namely (b) and (c) <lb/>(we note that we do not discuss localised transitions or tunnelling effects here). The <lb/>timescales involved can be from ns to up to several tens of ms. However, on longer <lb/>timescales, re-trapping and thermal emptying of the shallow traps can become <lb/>important and give rise to long lived phosphorescence. <lb/>Examination of the luminescence decay after a pulse of stimulation light helps to <lb/>understand the relative role of the above processes in luminescence generation. <lb/>Different terminologies have been used to name such a signal, e.g. Time-Resolved <lb/>OSL (TR-OSL), Delayed OSL (DOSL) or optically stimulated phosphorescence (see <lb/>Bøtter-Jensen et al. 2003a, p59-60). One could argue that the term TR-OSL is <lb/>generally used when a train of pulses is used as an alternative to CW-OSL, whereas <lb/>the terms DOSL or optically stimulated phosphorescence (OSP) or afterglow refer to <lb/>measurements in which a single or a few short stimulations (ms to s) are followed by <lb/>extended examination of the subsequent luminescence signal over ms to s time scales, <lb/>such that the afterglow is resolvable by the human eye. <lb/>Quartz TR-OSL measured between the stimulation pulses (after preheating to 260 o C <lb/>for 10 s and stimulating at 125 o C) shows a monotonic decay and consists of a <lb/>dominant exponential transient having a lifetime between 30 and 45 µs and two <lb/>relatively minor transients having relatively shorter and longer lifetimes (Chithambo <lb/>et al., 2007; Ankjaergaard et al., 2010). These lifetimes most likely reflect the <lb/>relaxation of the excited state following electron hole-recombination (Chithambo, <lb/>2007; Pagonis et al., 2010). Almost all published TR-OSL off-time decay curves from <lb/>quartz have been measured over a few hundred microseconds (Chithambo et al., 2008 <lb/>and references therein; Ankjaergaard et al., 2010). However, on longer time scales it is <lb/>likely that the effect of re-trapping will also be apparent. For example, Markey et al. <lb/>(1995) using Al 2 O 3 :C, demonstrated that the main lifetime of~35 ms corresponds to <lb/>the decay of the excited F-centre in Al 2 O 3 :C, but that the much slower decay of~545 <lb/>ms (measured at 25 o C) is due to phosphorescence from transfer of charge from deep <lb/>traps to shallow traps. As these shallow traps are thermally unstable at room <lb/>temperature, they start to leak charge into the conduction band from where it <lb/>recombines and emits light (DOSL -Bøtter-Jensen et al., 2003a). <lb/>Only few measurements have been done to study the TR-OSL decay from quartz on <lb/>the ms to s timescales. Pagonis et al. (2009) show an example from high purity <lb/>synthetic quartz obtained for an off-time of 1 ms. The authors identify a slow <lb/>component within this sample with a lifetime of 14 ± 8 ms and surmise that it could <lb/>be caused by re-trapping in a shallow trap. This effect has previously been used by <lb/>Jaek et al., (1999) to investigate deep traps in quartz, although here it was called <lb/>Optically Stimulated Afterglow (OSA). <lb/>In this study we first establish the decay form of optically stimulated phosphorescence <lb/>in irradiated quartz using different techniques to cover time scales over &gt;8 orders of <lb/>magnitude (50 ns to~8 s). We then make a detailed characterisation of the hitherto <lb/>unstudied slowly decaying signals (ms-s time scales) to understand the origin of these <lb/>components and the role of re-trapping following the optical stimulation. <lb/>We use the terminology time-resolved OSL (TR-OSL) while referring to the ns -µs <lb/>time scales and optically stimulated phosphorescence (OSP) while referring to the ms <lb/>-s time scales. <lb/>2. EXPERIMENTAL DETAILS <lb/>Sample measurements were carried out on two different Risø readers to cover three <lb/>different time scales. Optical stimulation carried out using blue light and detection <lb/>was through a 7.5 mm thick Hoya U340 filter used for detection. The measurement <lb/>details are described below. <lb/>Nanoseconds -microseconds: A Risø TL/OSL-20 reader was used with an <lb/>integrated pulsing option to control the blue LED array, delivering 80 mW.cm -2 CW <lb/>stimulation at the sample position. Furthermore a Photon Timer was attached, based <lb/>on an ORTEC 9353 100 ps Time Digitizer board with a detection resolution (bin-<lb/>width) of 100 ps to record the TR-OSL (Lapp et al., 2009). We define the duration of <lb/>each stimulation LED pulse as the on-time, and the duration of the pause before the <lb/>next stimulation pulse as the off-time (see also Lapp et al., 2009). Measurements on <lb/>this timescale were undertaken using an on-time of 50 µs and an off-time of 500 µs <lb/>producing~40,000 stimulation pulses during 22 s of pulsed stimulation with an <lb/>energy of 3.6 µJ.cm -2 per pulse. <lb/>Microseconds -milliseconds: The same Risø TL/OSL-20 reader as above was used <lb/>but with an on-time of 1 ms and an off-time of 5 ms. The ORTEC board has a pulse <lb/>period (on-time + off-time) limitation of 6 ms, which currently cannot be exceeded. <lb/>Approximately 9,000 pulses with an energy of 72 µJ.cm -2 per pulse were delivered <lb/>during 54 s of pulsed stimulation in this time range. <lb/>Milliseconds -seconds: A standard Risø TL/OSL-15 reader with CW stimulation <lb/>system performed by a LED array delivering~40 mW.cm -2 CW stimulation at the <lb/>sample position (Bøtter-Jensen et al., 2003b) was used to produce a single light pulse <lb/>of 0.2 s duration with an average energy of 6.7 mJ.cm -2 . The phosphorescence was <lb/>detected during the following 7.8 s. <lb/>The on-and off-times mentioned above were adhered to unless otherwise specified in <lb/>the text. <lb/>The work reported here has been undertaken using 90-125 µm sedimentary quartz <lb/>grains (lab code: WIDG8). The quartz grains were extracted from the sample by <lb/>sieving, heavy liquid separation and HF treatment as described in Wintle and Murray <lb/>(1997) and the absence of significant feldspar contamination was confirmed by tests <lb/>using IR stimulation. All aliquots used consisted of grains mounted in steel cups using <lb/>silicon oil. <lb/>3. EXTENDED DECAY FORM OF OPTICALLY STIMULATED <lb/>PHOSPHORESCENCE FROM QUARTZ <lb/>Time-resolved OSL off-time curves from quartz are usually measured over a few <lb/>hundred µs because this time range best illustrates the main component in quartz <lb/>which has a lifetime in the range of 30-45 µs. In Fig. 1(a), this is illustrated by the <lb/>black curve, which has been measured at 125 o C after a 25 Gy dose and a preheat to <lb/>
            260 o C for 10 s. The same curve is shown in Fig. 1(b) on a semi-log scale, where this <lb/> main component can be seen as the linear part of the curve up to~150 µs, after which <lb/>a much slower decaying component starts to dominate. <lb/>To observe in detail the slowly decaying part of the decay, the measurement was <lb/>repeated on the millisecond timescale, which is shown as the red curve in Fig. 1(a) <lb/>and reproduced in Fig. 1(c) on a semi-log scale; the initial fast drop corresponds to the <lb/>main component from Fig. 1(b) marked by #1, followed by the same slowly decaying <lb/>component from 1(b) marked by #2, but now it is clear that the decay continues <lb/>beyond several ms, as the counts have still not reached the background level of~4 cts. <lb/>per channel (6.6 µs). <lb/>To make further extended measurements of the slowly decaying component, a <lb/>measurement was carried out in the standard Risø reader with the CW-OSL <lb/>attachment using a single pulse of blue stimulation. The measurement and preheat <lb/>temperatures were the same as above. These data are shown as the last (blue) curve in <lb/>Fig. 1(a) and on a semi-log scale in Fig. 1(d). The initial fast drop is termed as <lb/>component #3, and continues up to about 2 seconds, after which it is hidden under a <lb/>new component marked as # 4 which continues beyond 7 s. The dark counts in this <lb/>curve will occur at~0.2 cts. per channel (0.002 s) <lb/>We note that the components 1, 2, 3 and 4 mentioned above are defined entirely based <lb/>on visual inspection. Due to lack of data collected from 6 ms up to~60 ms, we cannot <lb/>know whether component 2 and 3 are the same or not. The mosaic of these curves in <lb/>Fig. 1(a) illustrates that the TR-OSL or OSP covers &gt;8 orders of magnitude (50 ns tõ <lb/>8 s). The lower limit of this observation is set by the incapability of our set up to <lb/>achieve pulsing with a diode fall time faster than~20 ns. The upper limit is set by the <lb/>instrument&apos;s sensitivity; we are already quite close to the dark counts of the system by <lb/>about 8 s of OSP measurement. <lb/>In the following sections we make a detailed characterisation of these components <lb/>with a special focus on 2, 3, and 4. <lb/>4. THE MICROSECOND -MILLISECOND (ms) TIME RANGE <lb/>This section investigates the shape of the curve in Fig. 1(c) as a function of preheat <lb/>and stimulation temperature. Fig. 2 shows the normalized time-resolved OSL off-time <lb/>curves measured at 125 o C from a single aliquot of quartz using preheat temperatures <lb/>in the range 200-300 o C. It is observed that the preheat temperature does not affect the <lb/>shape of the curve. The amplitude of the initial component 1 (filled circles) and the <lb/>slower component 2 (estimated from the intensity at 1 ms, open circles) are shown in <lb/>the figure inset as a function of preheat temperature. There is no major change in the <lb/>relative importance of the two components with preheat temperature. <lb/>The normalized blue light stimulated time-resolved OSL from a single aliquot of <lb/>quartz (WIDG8) measured for stimulation temperatures in the range 50-225 o C are <lb/>shown in Figure 3(a). Only the off-time decay is shown. As the stimulation <lb/>temperature is increased, the area under component 2 shows an increase relative to <lb/>that under component 1. For the curves with stimulation temperatures below 125 o C, <lb/>the initial decay has a very similar behaviour (see inset to Fig. 3(a) on log-log plot) <lb/>and the relative ratios between the two components are very similar. For the curves <lb/>with stimulation temperatures above 125 o C, the initial decay becomes faster with <lb/>increasing temperature, and the slower decay becomes relatively more dominant. <lb/>We tried to describe these data mathematically by a multi-exponential fit. However, <lb/>the curves were not successfully described by either two or three or more transients, <lb/>possibly because of very large difference in decay constants (microsecond and <lb/>millisecond) causing an abrupt change in the decay curves (Fig. 3a). Therefore in <lb/>order to study the main characteristics of the curve, we used the very initial part of the <lb/>curve to characterise component 1. Fig. 3(b) shows the lifetime and amplitude for this <lb/>component. For characterisation of component 2 we discarded the initial 400 µs of <lb/>data in the off-time (to remove nearly all influence of the initial fast decay) and <lb/>thereafter removed the contribution from the underlying slower components <lb/>(component 3 and 4, see Fig. 1) by subtraction of an average over the last 50 points. <lb/>The remaining data were satisfactorily approximated with a single exponential decay. <lb/>The lifetime and amplitude of this component as a function of temperature is shown in <lb/>Fig. 3(c). <lb/>Component 1, the dominant component at the microseconds (and also the <lb/>milliseconds) time scales in quartz (Ankjaergaard et al., 2010), shows a decrease in <lb/>both the amplitude and lifetime as a function of temperature (Fig. 3b). The decrease in <lb/>amplitude and lifetime with stimulation temperature can be ascribed to thermal <lb/>quenching (Fig. 3(b), triangles) which arises because of an alternative non-radiative <lb/>recombination and has been studied in quartz by Bailiff (2000), Chithambo and <lb/>Galloway (2001), and Chithambo (2002). <lb/>In (Pagonis et al., 2010), thermal quenching was measured and modelled for the same <lb/>quartz sample as used here (WIDG8). A decrease in lifetime of~45 µs to~10 µs <lb/>observed here (Fig. 3b) for the temperature range 50 o C to 200 o C is consistent with the <lb/>thermal quenching energy of 0.64 eV (See Pagonis et al. 2010 for the details). <lb/>Component 2 shows a relatively smaller decrease in intensity than component 1 with <lb/>an increase in the stimulation temperature; the smaller decrease in the amplitude <lb/>compared to that of component 1 causes the observed changes in the relative <lb/>contributions from the two components in Fig. 3(a). However, unlike component 1, <lb/>the lifetime does not decrease concomitantly with the amplitude. In fact the lifetimes <lb/>show only a slight change for the different stimulation temperatures up to 200°C; <lb/>there is an overall 38% increase in lifetime with temperature up to 200 o C, with a <lb/>
            single reproducible dip at 100 o C, followed by a sharp drop of about 50% between <lb/>200 o C and 225 o C. Thus the lifetime of component 2 does not show an undisputed <lb/>constancy, or a systematic decrease expected from faster emptying of shallow traps or <lb/>greater thermal quenching at a centre such as observed for component 1. One possible <lb/>explanation could be that the so called component 2 in fact has different origins at <lb/>different temperatures and therefore, it is not valid to intercompare the lifetimes; the <lb/>apparent similarity in the lifetimes is then a mere coincidence. We later describe such <lb/>an apparent behaviour in a component in the time range described in Section 5. On the <lb/>other hand if one ignores the drop at 100°C, one could possibly assume a near <lb/>constancy of the lifetimes between 50 to 200°C as a gross simplification. We discuss <lb/>this again in the later sections. <lb/>5. THE MILLISECOND -SECOND TIME RANGE <lb/>Because of the ORTEC board pulse period limitation of 6 ms, the components in this <lb/>range were investigated using a conventional reader by giving a single stimulation <lb/>pulse of 0.2 s and measuring the following phosphorescence decay for 7.8 s. <lb/>5.1 Preheat and Stimulation temperature dependence <lb/>To investigate the off-time signal behaviour as a function of preheat, a series of <lb/>curves were measured at 125 o C using an aliquot of quartz following a single <lb/>stimulation pulse, these are shown in Fig. 4, all normalized to the initial point in the <lb/>off-time. All curves behave identically with a fast drop in the initial 0.01 s (see also <lb/>inset on log-log scale), a slower decay up to about 1 s where the slowest decay starts <lb/>to dominate and continues beyond 7 s. Based both on this and the µs to ms data <lb/>presented in the previous section, we conclude that the preheat temperature range <lb/>(200 to 300°C) does not affect the relative contributions of the different components. <lb/>Fig. 5(a) shows the stimulation temperature dependent decay of the same aliquot of <lb/>quartz used in Fig. 4. The aliquot was heated to 260 o C for 10 s prior to blue light <lb/>stimulation at temperatures in the range 50 -200 o C. The curves show very different <lb/>decay rates during the initial 3 s (see a magnification of this time range in Fig. 5(b)). <lb/>However, in the data following the 3 s (Fig. 5(a)) the decay shapes are very similar for <lb/>all the temperatures, with an exception of the 100 o C curve (green triangles) and to <lb/>some extent the 75 o C curve (red squares) where a clear &apos;kink&apos; is observed at~3 s. <lb/>A clearer picture can be obtained by separating the different components. Because of <lb/>the &apos;kink&apos; in two of the curves (75 and 100 o C), we could not apply a simple multi-<lb/>exponential model to the entire curve. Therefore, to simplify the analysis we fitted <lb/>only the data in the first 3 s assuming first order kinetics (see Fig. 5b). The data were <lb/>successfully fitted with a sum of three exponentials. To determine the effect of <lb/>temperature, an Arrhenius plot is used, which is shown in Fig. 6(a). The three <lb/>different components from each curve are indicated by different symbols (Fast -<lb/>circles, medium -triangles, slow -squares). If one looks at the behaviour of these <lb/>different components, it is apparent that the lifetime of the slow and medium <lb/>component do not vary much with temperature, whereas the lifetime of the fastest <lb/>component rises gradually with temperature up to 150°C (~28 eV -1 ), and then <lb/>decreases rapidly between 150 -200°C (28 -24 eV -1 ). The behaviour of these <lb/>components is in fact very similar to that observed for component 2 on the ms time <lb/>scales (see previous section, Fig. 3(c)) in that it does not show any obvious <lb/>temperature dependence. <lb/>We now explore the possibility that the fast component (and similarly the medium <lb/>component and slow component) actually has different origins in these different <lb/>curves. If one looks closely at Fig. 5(b), i.e. the data in the first three seconds of the <lb/>curves in Fig. 5(a), then it is apparent that a slower component increases relatively in <lb/>magnitude compared to a faster decaying component from about 50 to 100 o C, and the <lb/>fast component is eliminated above 100 o C. From 100 o C to 175°C one also observes a <lb/>systematic change in the decay rate of the dominant component with stimulation, <lb/>which hints to a possible participation of a shallow trap(s). A common dominant <lb/>component of these different curves was picked by visual inspection. This is shown <lb/>by arrows and lettering from a-f for the different curves in Fig. 5(b). It is clear that <lb/>this component shows an increase in the decay rate with temperature; however, note <lb/>that in some curves this is a slow component while in the others it is a fast component. <lb/>The Arrhenius plot helps to test whether the change in the decay rate complies with <lb/>that expected from thermodynamic considerations. Most of the data for this <lb/>component does in fact fall on a straight line (red line in Fig. 6(a)) τ = E/kT -ln(s), <lb/>where τ [s] is the lifetime, E [eV] is the thermal activation energy of the trap giving <lb/>rise to this component, and s [s -1 ] is the frequency factor. This gives E = 0.91 eV and s <lb/>= 1.7⋅10 12 s -1 . Very similar values of E = 0.89 eV and s = 3.8⋅10 11 s -1 were found by <lb/>Spooner and Questiaux (2000) for the so called 110 o C TL peak in the UV emission by <lb/>varying the heating rate in a series of TL measurements. The E and s values found <lb/>from our data predict a TL peak at 93°C for a heating rate of 2°Cs -1 (confirmed later <lb/>by experimental measurements). <lb/>
            Thus, identification of this main component helps to put the other two components <lb/>derived from multi-exponential fitting into perspective. Examination of Fig. 5(b) <lb/>again for temperatures below 100°C now shows that the component derived from the <lb/>110 o C peak (marked with arrows) increases relative to the faster components and <lb/>almost completely replaces these between 100 o C and 125 o C. Thus, these faster <lb/>components are completely eliminated at higher temperatures, since the data <lb/>resolution is not high enough to sample them. Similarly, as the component from the <lb/>110 o C peak forms the new fast component, there is appearance of new slower <lb/>components in the system. Thus, we conclude that the apparent constancy of the fast <lb/>and medium components is misleading since the slower components change into <lb/>faster ones, the faster ones disappear (or are unresolvable at our data collection rate), <lb/>and the new slower components appear at higher and higher temperatures within our <lb/>data range. It is therefore misleading to intercompare the decay rates for a single <lb/>component as the decay rates should in fact be compared across components to obtain <lb/>a meaningful result. <lb/>To confirm the role of the 110 o C peak in OSP, a TL experiment was carried out to <lb/>examine possible charge recuperation during short blue light stimulations; this is <lb/>called phototransferred TL (PTTL). A previously sensitised aliquot was dosed, heated <lb/>to 300 o C for 60 s and then stimulated with a short pulse of blue light. Fig. 7 shows the <lb/>series of &apos;difference&apos; TL curves (subtraction of TL before illumination from that after <lb/>illumination) measured up to 300 o C following these short blue light stimulations of <lb/>durations between 0.1 s and 3.2 s. The~325°C TL peak shows an increasing <lb/>depletion because of bleaching by blue light; this is observed as negative counts in the <lb/>figure. All positive counts are PTTL due to photo transfer. A dominant peak is <lb/>observed at 97 o C followed by relatively smaller peaks in the region between 125 o C <lb/>and 225 o C. Increasing the stimulation pulse length causes an increase of charge <lb/>transfer into the peak centred at 97 o C, which is in reasonable agreement with our <lb/>predicted TL peak at 93 o C from the E and s values found from Fig. 6(a). The charge <lb/>builds up steadily, but for pulse durations longer than 1.6 s, the light stimulation starts <lb/>to deplete the charge transferred into this trap. Based on these data we conclude that <lb/>our multi-exponential analysis as well our approach of comparing decay constants <lb/>across the fast, medium, and slow components gives physically meaningful results. <lb/>With this success we then attempted a similar E-s analysis for the components <lb/>decaying faster than that from the 110°C peak for the stimulation temperatures <lb/>between 50 and100 o C. These are indicated with the blue, green, and grey dashed lines <lb/>in Fig. 6(a). These yield values of E = 0.74 eV and s = 1.5⋅10 12 s -1 (blue line), E = <lb/>0.86 eV and s = 2.9⋅10 13 s -1 (green line), and E = 0.56 eV and s = 3.6⋅10 9 s -1 (grey <lb/>line), which correspond to TL peaks at 87 o C, 63 o C, and 165 o C respectively. In the <lb/>literature, only values for the 160 o C peak are published with E = 1.09 eV and s = <lb/>2.1⋅10 12 s -1 measured in the UV (Spooner and Questiaux, 2000) We recognise that our <lb/>E and s values for this peak are much too small compared to their published value, <lb/>and moreover the s value is smaller than the generally accepted values in the range <lb/>10 12 -10 14 s -1 . Nonetheless, our PTTL results in Fig. 7 show the existence of the 160 o C <lb/>TL peak, consistent with our E-s analysis. <lb/>The slower components (slower than that for the~110°C peak) on the other hand do <lb/>not seem to be amenable to this simple E-s analysis (See the data enclosed in the <lb/>ellipse in Fig. 6(a)). Fitting of these data gave absurd values of E and s. Also a closer <lb/>inspection of Fig. 5(b) suggests that at the higher temperatures the curve shape <lb/>encompassing the medium and slowly decaying parts does not change significantly. <lb/>We, therefore, infer that at about 150 o C there appears a new component in our data <lb/>that decays slower than the component induced from the 110°C peak, and that this <lb/>new component does not show a significant change in the decay rate with stimulation <lb/>temperature. <lb/>The latter part of the off-time decays from 3 to 7 s in Fig. 5(a) shows a similar decay <lb/>rate for the different temperatures, except the curve measured at 100°C. A summary <lb/>of the lifetimes are given in Fig. 6(b). The overall similarity in the decay rate for the <lb/>different temperatures might suggest that this signal has a similar origin or is quite <lb/>simply a continuation of the medium and slow components above (data shown in the <lb/>ellipse, Fig. 6a). <lb/>The presence of the &apos;kink&apos; at around 3 s (Fig. 5a) in the 100 and 75°C data is <lb/>surprising. To our knowledge such a feature has not been reported before and suggests <lb/>a rather different mechanism of luminescence generation, one that could possibly <lb/>involve competition in the refuge (trap receiving charge from optical transfer) traps. <lb/>This is examined in detail in the next sections. <lb/>5.2 &apos;Kink&apos; position for different stimulation pulse durations <lb/>To investigate whether the kink position is related to the amount of charge de-trapped <lb/>from the OSL trap, measurements were carried out for different on-times at 100°C <lb/>stimulation temperature after irradiation (25 Gy) and preheat (260 o C for 10 s). Fig. 8 <lb/>shows five curves with stimulation pulse durations (on-times) between 0.1 s to 1.6 s, <lb/>and it is observed that the &apos;kink&apos; occurs sooner for the longer on-times. A summary of <lb/>the &apos;kink&apos; position is shown in the inset to the figure ranging from approximately 4 s <lb/>for an on-time of 0.1 s to 1 s for an on-time of 1.6 s. We propose below a simple <lb/>numerical model containing four energy levels to explain the possible origin of the <lb/>kink structure in the OSP curve. <lb/>5.3 A three-trap one centre phosphorescence model <lb/>
            Fig. 9(a) shows a band model containing three traps T 1 , T 2 , T 3 and a luminescence <lb/>centre, L. The features of these traps are described below: <lb/>T 3 : An electron trap with negligible retrapping. Thus, the charge population decays <lb/>exponentially at the ambient temperature. Non-retrapping is only an approximation to <lb/>simplify the model and it is not critical to the model results. Majority of the charge <lb/>released from T 3 undergoes recombination at centre L, and a minor amount is trapped <lb/>at T 2 . <lb/>T 2 : This is a deeper electron trap (smaller decay constant at the ambient temperature <lb/>than T 3 ). It can either lose charge to the conduction band (and thereby cause electron-<lb/>hole recombination at the centre L), or it can lose charge by localised transition to the <lb/>trap T 1 . The majority of the charge lost by T 2 is taken by T 1 ; this feature is the most <lb/>critical aspect of the model which helps reproduce the observed kink in the data. For <lb/>simplicity, since only a small fraction of the charge is released to the conduction band, <lb/>we assume that it all undergoes recombination at the centre L and none of it is <lb/>retrapped. <lb/>T 1 : This is the third trap in the system which receives the majority of charge released <lb/>from T 2 by localised transition. The charge released from T 1 either undergoes a <lb/>luminescent recombination with holes at L, or is re-trapped at T 2 through the <lb/>conduction band. Again it is not critical to the model whether T 1 receives any <lb/>electrons directly from the conduction band, not as far as it is only a minor amount <lb/>compared to the charge received from T 2 ; for convenience we have avoided this step. <lb/>The decay of electrons from these traps occurs due to the ambient temperature. The <lb/>decay constants (λ) are assumed to have the following relationship: λ 3 &gt; λ 2 &gt; λ 1 , <lb/>corresponding to T 3 , T 2 and T 1 respectively. At the end of the light stimulation these <lb/>traps will have a certain initial concentration because of re-trapping from the <lb/>conduction band, or as in the case of T 1 charge re-trapping from T 2 . Because of <lb/>charge decay from T 2 with λ 2 &gt; λ 1 , charge will initially build up at T 1 prior to <lb/>recombining at L. The rate equations describing this model for the off-time are given <lb/>as: <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>λ <lb/>n <lb/>dt <lb/>dn <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/>Equation 1 <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>f <lb/>n <lb/>dt <lb/>dn <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/>Equation 2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>n <lb/>f <lb/>n <lb/>dt <lb/>dn <lb/>+ <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/>Equation 3 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>) <lb/>1 <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>)( <lb/>1 <lb/>( <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>n <lb/>f <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>f <lb/>I <lb/>− <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>− <lb/>∝ <lb/>Equation 4 <lb/>Here I is the observed luminescence intensity at time t, f 3 denotes the fraction of <lb/>charge from T 3 or T 1 re-trapped at T 2 , and f 2 the fraction of charge from T 2 trapped at <lb/>T 1 . Fig. 10 shows the phosphorescence contribution from T 3, T 2, and in T 1 together <lb/>with the total phosphorescence when solving the above rate-equations with the <lb/>parameters: n 10 = 50 cm -3 , λ 1 = 0.04 s -1 , n 20 = 300 cm -3 , λ 2 = 0.09 s -1 , n 30 = 25 cm -3 , λ 3 <lb/>= 0.3 s -1 , and f 3 = 0.1, and f 2 = 0.92. The luminescence arising from the T 3 and T 2 traps <lb/>(blue curve and green curve, respectively) shows an exponential decay with time, <lb/>whereas that from the T 1 trap initially builds up to a maximum before it decays (see <lb/>semi-log scale in Fig. 10(b)). The total emitted luminescence from L (black curve) <lb/>being the sum of the light from T 3 , T 2 , and T 1 therefore decrease initially, but as the <lb/>light originating from T 1 starts to dominate over the light originating from T 3 and T 2 , <lb/>the total luminescence curve flattens out to a near constant level before the decay rate <lb/>is increased again in accordance with the depletion of T 1 . This simulated behaviour <lb/>with three traps appears very similar to the kink observed in the 100 o C measurement <lb/>in Fig. 5(a); it was furthermore observed in Fig. 5(a) that the kink disappears as the <lb/>temperature is increased. From Fig. 5(b) and 6(a) we know that the lifetime of the <lb/>110 o C TL trap decreases significantly (thereby an increase in the decay constant) for <lb/>temperatures above 100 o C. An increase in stimulation temperature would thus <lb/>correspond to an increase in the decay constants λ i in this model depending on the <lb/>exact E and s values for each level. For certain combinations of these values such that <lb/>the increase in λ 1 is greater than the increase in λ 2 or λ 3 , it is possible to remove the <lb/>kink and instead have an apparent monotonic decay in the simulation results. <lb/>In Fig. 8 the kink was observed to shift position as a function of the stimulation pulse <lb/>duration. This can be achieved in the model by changing the initial concentration of <lb/>T 1 (n 10 ) at the end of the stimulation pulse. An increase in this initial concentration, as <lb/>would be expected with an increase in the length of the stimulation pulse duration, <lb/>causes the kink to move towards shorter times in the off-time. This behaviour is <lb/>consistent with the data presented in Fig.8. <lb/>A simpler two trap model was also investigated using only T 2 and T 1 with λ 2 &gt; λ 1 It is <lb/>assumed that decay from both T 2 and T 1 produces light, and that a fraction of the <lb/>charge from T 2 is transferred into T 1 . Similar to the model above, the two traps are <lb/>filled during the light stimulation to have an initial charge concentration at the end of <lb/>the stimulation of n 20 &gt; n 10 after which they both start to decay. If f describes the <lb/>fraction of charge transferred to T 1 , then the rate equations describing this situation <lb/>are given as: <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>λ <lb/>n <lb/>dt <lb/>dn − <lb/>= <lb/>Equation 5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>λ <lb/>λ n <lb/>fn <lb/>dt <lb/>dn <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/>Equation 6 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>) <lb/>1 <lb/>( <lb/>λ <lb/>λ n <lb/>n <lb/>f <lb/>I <lb/>+ <lb/>− <lb/>∝ <lb/>Equation 7 <lb/>Using the same values for n 10 , λ 1 , n 20 , and λ 2 as above, the series of curves in Fig. 11 <lb/>shows the total phosphorescence emitted at L for different fractions, f between 0.1 and <lb/>1. The inset shows the behaviour of T 1 , T 2 and L for f = 0.3, which is the green curve <lb/>in the main figure. It is seen from these curves, that it is not possible to produce a kink <lb/>with this simpler model; it is crucial that there are three distinct traps and that there is <lb/>a step of almost complete charge transfer from one to the other. <lb/>5.4 An alternative one-trap, two-centre phosphorescence model <lb/>The mathematical equations above (Eqn. 1-4) can equally be interpreted in terms of <lb/>two different energy levels existing in a single centre. Here we propose an alternative <lb/>interpretation of these equations. The model consists of a single trap, T 3 with lifetime <lb/>λ 3 , and two luminescence centres L a and L b , where L a has two excited states, L a1 and <lb/>L a2 , (Fig. 9(b)). It is assumed that the relaxation from L a2 to L a1 , byλ a2 is non-<lb/>radiative, but that the relaxation of L a1 to L a (the ground state) by λ a1 is radiative. <lb/>During a short light stimulation, charge is transferred to T 3 and L a2. In the off-time, a <lb/>
            fraction of the charge from T 3 recombines at L b and the remaining recombines at the <lb/>excited state L a2 . The equations describing this model are identical to Equations (1-4), <lb/>with the slight modification that the charge loss from the L a1 state is entirely to the <lb/>ground state (unlike in the electron trap model where there is partial loss from level T 1 <lb/>to level T 2 as well), i.e. the value of f 2 =1, the equations thus become: <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>λ <lb/>n <lb/>dt <lb/>dn <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/>Equation 8 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>n <lb/>f <lb/>n <lb/>dt <lb/>dn <lb/>a <lb/>a <lb/>a <lb/>+ <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/>Equation 9 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>a <lb/>a <lb/>a <lb/>a <lb/>a <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>dt <lb/>dn <lb/>λ <lb/>λ + <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/>Equation 10 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>) <lb/>1 <lb/>( <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>n <lb/>f <lb/>n <lb/>I <lb/>a <lb/>a <lb/>− <lb/>+ <lb/>∝ <lb/>Equation 11 <lb/>The results of these are almost identical to those in Fig. 10 because the retrapping <lb/>terms in the trap model were very small (results not shown here). Again the key <lb/>feature of this model is a non-luminescence relaxation from the level L a2 to L a1 , which <lb/>produces the desired result. <lb/>The main difference between the two models is therefore not in the modelling results, <lb/>but rather that they offer different advantages in the explanation of the data in Fig. <lb/>5(a) and Fig. 8. By choosing the one trap -two centres model, it is relatively easier to <lb/>explain the temperature independence of the latter part (after 3 s) of the curves in Fig. <lb/>5(a), and perhaps also the component 2 in Fig. 3(c), as the relaxation from L a1 will <lb/>dominate the curve after the kink, and this process can be temperature independent in <lb/>the absence of thermal quenching. It would however require that the relaxation is <lb/>strongly forbidden to cause delay on the seconds time scale; this needs to be <lb/>investigated. The trap T 3 could be similar to the 110 o C TL trap, which dominates the <lb/>early part of the phosphorescence curves, and this process is highly temperature <lb/>dependent. In this model the commonly observed 40 µs component would be derived <lb/>from the centre L b . <lb/>6. PHOSPHORESCENCE CONTRIBUTION IN THE CW SIGNAL <lb/>It is obvious that phosphorescence is negligible compared to the fast OSL component <lb/>in quartz measured at 125 o C. To evaluate how large the contribution of the <lb/>phosphorescence decay is in a standard CW measurement of the slow component in <lb/>quartz, a series of measurements were carried out where the phosphorescence was <lb/>detected for 10 s following blue CW stimulations at 125 o C for durations of 10 s to 70 <lb/>s. From Fig. 7 it was evident that light stimulation caused photo-transfer of charge <lb/>into the 110 o C TL trap, but that for longer stimulations &gt; 1.6 s, the light started to <lb/>erode the photo-transferred charge instead. To see if this is also true for very long <lb/>stimulations, or if the phosphorescence signal builds up during long stimulations, the <lb/>amount of phosphorescence during the 10 s off-time was summed and is presented in <lb/>Fig. 12, where it has been normalized to the initial 10 s stimulation point. From this <lb/>curve it is clear that the phosphorescence does not increase with increased stimulation <lb/>time, initially there is a faster drop in signal, but at about 40 s, the amount of <lb/>phosphorescence emitted reaches a near constant level independent of the stimulation <lb/>time. The dashed line indicates the level of &apos;dark counts&apos; in the PMT accumulated <lb/>during 10 s after light stimulation (also normalized to the initial value as the other <lb/>points) to show that the phosphorescence level is well above the dark count level. <lb/>These data suggest that a fraction of the slow OSL component observed even at <lb/>125°C temperature may derive from decay of the refuge traps that initially store <lb/>charge during OSL. In order to determine the % of the phosphorescence contained in <lb/>the slow OSL signal, we calculated the ratio between the end point of the OSL signal <lb/>and the first point in the phosphorescence signal (assuming that these points represent <lb/>the equilibrium states at any time). This ratio is plotted for different stimulation times <lb/>in the inset to Fig. 12. The fluctuations in the data reflect the low light levels. We <lb/>note from these data that there may be a contribution from OSP of about 5 % in the <lb/>slow OSL signal. <lb/>7. DISCUSSION <lb/>We find that the shape of the TR-OSL or OSP curves is almost independent of the <lb/>preheat temperature in the range of 200 to 300°C at all time scales investigated here. <lb/>This suggests that the refuge traps and centres participating in these processes must be <lb/>the same irrespective of the preheat temperature. Moreover, the refuge traps must be <lb/>emptied to the same relative levels for different preheats. <lb/>From our stimulation temperature data, a strong temperature dependence is seen in the <lb/>initial 3 s of the phosphorescence curves in Fig. 5(b). An E-s analysis of this changing <lb/>component using an Arrhenius plot finds the trap depth E = 0.91 eV to be consistent <lb/>with that found for the 110 o C TL trap of E = 0.89 eV by Spooner and Questiaux <lb/>(2000), and using our E and s values, a TL peak is predicted at 93 o C for a heating rate <lb/>of 2°Cs -1 . This is further confirmed by TL measurements showing a PTTL peak at <lb/>97 o C. The phosphorescence we observe during the initial 3 s of the curves is, <lb/>therefore, dominated by charge recycled through the 110 o C TL trap. This conclusion <lb/>is consistent with the previous studies on PTTL in quartz (see Wintle and Murray <lb/>1997 and references therein). Wintle and Murray (1997) also show for their quartz <lb/>(WIDG8) the photo-transferred TL (PTTL) at room temperature illumination. In the <lb/>absence of saturation effects, the ratio of 110 o C PTTL to OSL is between 4 and 5% <lb/>(Wintle and Murray, 1997). <lb/>In addition to the OSP component derived from the 110°C peak, we also find that <lb/>there are some components both at the millisecond and second time scales that do not <lb/>show an obvious dependence of their decay rates on the stimulation temperature. One <lb/>possible reason for this could simply be, that we have not recorded data for <lb/>sufficiently long time (e.g. in the milliseconds time scale) to track the movement of <lb/>the different components. Another possible explanation could be the lack of a good <lb/>mathematical model to extract individual components from the data; it is likely, as <lb/>shown in the numerical modelling results, that the data do not follow a multiple-<lb/>exponential form of the type used here for fitting. Thus, the apparent non-dependence <lb/>on temperature could possibly be an artifact of our assumption that the OSP consists <lb/>of linear superimposition of first-order processes. However, we note that the decay of <lb/>the 110 o C peak is conspicuous and has been picked up accurately by the fitting <lb/>analysis (as confirmed by E and s values from Spooner and Questiaux, 2000). <lb/>Similarly, the occurrence of a 160°C TL peak from the fitting analysis is supported by <lb/>the PTTL data. We, therefore, consider that our analysis of the first 3 seconds of the <lb/>data may be relatively error free, especially for the low temperature data (&lt;125°C, Fig. <lb/>6(a)); the more problematic region may be the medium and slow components <lb/>observed above 125°C (and the OSP data &gt;3 s) as these could fall in the region where <lb/>a peak build-up is predicted from the kinetic model (discussed below). <lb/>Two simple kinetic models are proposed to explain an abnormal change in the decay <lb/>rate (the &apos;kink&apos;) in the OSP signals for the 75°and 100°C stimulation temperatures <lb/>(Figs. 5a and 8). The first model consists of three traps and a luminescence centre, <lb/>while the second model consists of a single trap and two luminescence centres. The <lb/>common trap T 3 in both these models could be similar to the 110 o C TL trap. Both <lb/>models share the same equations (with minor modifications) and can, therefore, both <lb/>predict the behaviour observed in Fig. 5(a). The key feature of both the models that <lb/>produces the desired effect is a large non-luminescent transfer and subsequent build-<lb/>up from one energy level to the other. The resultant luminescence has a peak shape, <lb/>and this produces a flattening followed by a steep decay in the luminescence curve. <lb/>An interesting prediction of our alternative model (one trap -two recombination <lb/>centres) is that there could be OSP components which do not show a change in the <lb/>decay rate with the stimulation temperature, thus strengthening the possibility that the <lb/>effect discussed in the previous paragraph concerning data in Figs. 3 and 5 may be <lb/>real and not just an artifact of the measurement or analysis. However, this implies a <lb/>relaxation time in the centre on the seconds time scale, which may or may not be <lb/>realistic. The model results are encouraging, but they need to be investigated in <lb/>greater detail to understand different OSP results from quartz. <lb/>Finally, we note that a similar kink was also observed in the IR stimulated <lb/>phosphorescence signals from orthoclase feldspar (Ankjaergaard and Jain, 2010). <lb/>There and in the following paper (Jain and Ankjaergaard, 2010) it is shown that the <lb/>slowly decaying signals (both on the ms and s time scales) arise from the slow <lb/>emptying of the band tails. As in the case of quartz, these signals show a change in the <lb/>amplitude but a weak dependence of lifetime on stimulation temperature. Although <lb/>band tails have not been explicitly reported in quartz, it is possible that natural quartz <lb/>contains band tails because of deformational strain in the source rocks. These effects <lb/>are well known in common quartz bearing rocks, e.g. quartzite and granite. If band <lb/>tail states are indeed present in our quartz, they could potentially give an alternative <lb/>explanation to the kink structure and temperature independence of the decay rates on <lb/>the ms and s (&gt;3 s) time scales in quartz OSP. <lb/>8. SUMMARY AND CONCLUSIONS <lb/>1. The decay form of Time-Resolved OSL (TR-OSL) and Optically Stimulated <lb/>Phosphorescence (OSP) in quartz has been observed to cover time scales of <lb/>over 8 decades from 50 ns to~8 s. <lb/>2. The decay form of TR-OSL and OSP curves are independent of preheat <lb/>temperature, for all the examined time scales, in the range 200-300 o C <lb/>suggesting that the same centres and refuge traps are used for all these <lb/>conditions. <lb/>3. Together the TR-OSL and OSP curves have been shown to contain at least <lb/>four major components (1-4) by visual inspection. Component 1 has an <lb/>average lifetime of~40 µs at room temperature; it shows strong temperature <lb/>dependent decrease as expected from an excited state lifetime of a centre <lb/>affected by thermal quenching. Component 2 has an average lifetime of~1 ms <lb/>and shows no real systematic behaviour with temperature in our data range. <lb/>Component 3 is strongly stimulation temperature dependent and has been <lb/>identified mainly to originate from the 110 o C TL trap, and partly from some <lb/>other TL peaks determined to lie at 87 o C, 63 o C, and 165 o C. Component 4 with <lb/>an average lifetime of~5 s show an apparent overall temperature <lb/>independence (with the exception at 100 o C). <lb/>4. An abnormal decay behaviour (a &apos;kink&apos;) is observed conspicuously in the OSP <lb/>data at 75°C and 100°C. A simple kinetic model consisting of four energy <lb/>levels is proposed to explain the kink observed in the OSP data at around 3 s. <lb/>This model can successfully reproduce the kink, and can be physically <lb/>interpreted in terms of a 3 traps and 1 luminescence centre model, or <lb/>alternatively, a 1 trap and 2 luminescence centres model with one of the <lb/>centres having two excited states. The key feature of these models that <lb/>produce the kink effect is a large localised, non-luminescent transfer and <lb/>subsequent build-up from one energy level to the other. Although the results <lb/>are encouraging, there needs to be further theoretical investigations into <lb/>charge transfer and re-trapping to fully understand the optically stimulated <lb/>phosphorescence results from quartz. One potential explanation for the <lb/>temperature dependence of lifetimes (components 2 and 4) as well as the kink <lb/>structure could be the possible presence of band tail states in natural <lb/>(deformed) quartz. <lb/>5. The 110°C TL peak plays a significant role even for optical stimulation at <lb/>125°C, although, the lifetime is rather small (0.2 s). It is determined that the <lb/>OSP contribution to the OSL signal in the 10 s-70 s measurement region (for <lb/>blue light stimulation at~40 mW.cm -2 ) is &lt; 5%. Although, this is unimportant <lb/>for dosimetry, it could perhaps have a slight affect on the analysis of slow <lb/>components in the slow OSL signals for derivation of physical parameters. A <lb/>cleaner signal would be obtained by stimulations above 150°C, although at the <lb/>cost of reduced sensitivity because of thermal quenching. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>We thank the two anonymous referees for at thorough review of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

            <listBibl>9. REFERENCES <lb/>Ankjaergaard, C., Jain, M., 2010. Optically stimulated phosphorescence in orthoclase <lb/>feldspar over the millisecond to second time scales. Submitted to Journal of <lb/>Luminescence. <lb/>
			Ankjaergaard C, Jain M, Thomsen K J, Murray A S, 2010 Optimising the separation <lb/>of quartz and feldspar optically stimulated luminescence using pulsed excitation <lb/>Radiation Measurements. In print. DOI: 10.1016/j.radmeas.2010.03.004. <lb/>Bailiff I K 2000 Characteristics of time-resolved luminescence in quartz Radiation <lb/>Measurements 32 401-405 <lb/>Bøtter-Jensen L, McKeever S W S, Wintle A G 2003a Optically Stimulated <lb/>Luminescence Dosimetry (Amsterdam: Elsevier) ISBN: 0-444-50684-5 <lb/>Bøtter-Jensen L, Andersen C E, Duller G A T, Murray A S 2003b Developments in <lb/>radiation, stimulation and observation facilities in luminescence measurements <lb/>Radiation Measurements 37 535-541 <lb/>Chithambo M L 2002 Time-resolved luminescence from annealed quartz Radiation <lb/>Protection Dosimetry 100 273-276 <lb/>Chithambo M L, Galloway R B 2000 A pulsed light-emitting-diode system for <lb/>stimulation of luminescence Meas. Sci. Technol. 11 418-424 <lb/>Chithambo M L, Galloway R B 2001 On the slow component of luminescence <lb/>stimulated from quartz by pulse blue light emitting diodes Nuclear Instruments and <lb/>Methods B 183 358-368 <lb/>Chithambo M L 2007 The analysis of time-resolved optically stimulated <lb/>luminescence: II. Computer simulations and experimental results Journal of Physics <lb/>D: Applied Physics 40 1880-1889 <lb/>Chithambo M L, Preusser F, Ramseyer K, Ogundare F O 2007 Time-resolved <lb/>luminescence of low sensitivity quartz from crystalline rocks Radiation <lb/>Measurements 42 205-212 <lb/>Chithambo M L, Ogundare F O, Feathers J, Hong D G 2008 On the dose-dependence <lb/>of luminescence lifetimes in natural quartz. Radiation Effects and Defects in Solids <lb/>163 945-953 <lb/>Jaek I, Hütt G, Streltsov A 1999 Study of deep traps in alkali feldspar and quartz by <lb/>the optically stimulated afterglow Radiation Protection Dosimetry 84 467-470 <lb/>Jain M, Ankjaergaard C 2010 Towards finding a non-fading signal in feldspar: insight <lb/>into charge transport and tunnelling from time-resolved optically stimulated <lb/>luminescence Radiation Measurements submitted <lb/>Lapp T, Jain M, Ankjaergaard C., Pirzel L 2009 Development of pulsed stimulation <lb/>and photon timer attachments to the Risø TL/OSL reader Radiation Measurements 44 <lb/>571-575 <lb/>Markey B G, Colyott L E, McKeever S W S 1995 Time-resolved optically stimulated <lb/>luminescence from α-Al 2 O 3 :C Radiation Measurements 24 457-463 <lb/>Pagonis V, Mian S M, Chithambo M L, Christensen E, Barnold C 2009 Experimental <lb/>and modelling study of pulsed optically stimulated luminescence in quartz, marble <lb/>and beta irradiated salt J. Phys. D: Appl. Phys 42 1-12 <lb/>
            Pagonis V, Ankjaergaard C, Murray A S, Jain M, Chen R, Lawless J, Greilich S 2010 <lb/>Modelling the thermal quenching mechanism in quartz based on time-resolved <lb/>optically stimulated luminescence Journal of Luminescence 130 902-909 <lb/>Spooner N A, Questiaux D G 2000 Kinetics of red, blue and UV thermoluminescence <lb/>and optically-stimulated luminescence from quartz Radiation Measurements 32 659-<lb/>666 <lb/>Wintle A G, Murray A S, 1997 The relationship between quartz thermoluminescence, <lb/>photo-transferred thermoluminescence, and optically stimulated luminescence <lb/>Radiation Measurements 27 611-624 <lb/></listBibl>

            <body>10. FIGURE CAPTIONS <lb/>Figure 1 <lb/>Time-resolved OSL off-time and optically stimulated phosphorescence curves from a <lb/>single aliquot of quartz (WIDG8) measured on different timescales covering over <lb/>eight decades. (a) The first (black) curve is measured using an on-time of 50 µs, an <lb/>off-time of 500 µs (~40,000 pulses) and has a resolution of 50 ns. The second (red) <lb/>curve is measured using an on-time of 1 ms, an off-time of 5 ms (9,000 pulses) and <lb/>has a resolution of 6.6 µs. The third (blue) curve is measured using an on-time of 0.2 s, <lb/>an off-time of 7.8 s (a single pulse) and has a resolution of 0.002 s. In all three <lb/>measurements the aliquot was dosed with 25 Gy followed by a preheat to 260 o C for <lb/>10 s and blue light stimulation at 125 o C. The curves have been normalized to the <lb/>initial intensity, and the red curve has been reduced by a factor 0.9 and the blue curve <lb/>by a factor of 0.02 for ease of illustration. Note that the scale is double-log. The <lb/>curves in (b), (c), and (d) are the semi-log plots of the individual curves from (a).The <lb/>numbers on the curves 1-4 represent the four major components in the signal which <lb/>has been identified by visual inspection. <lb/>Figure 2 <lb/>Time-resolved blue light stimulated OSL off-time curves from a single aliquot of <lb/>quartz (WIDG8) for different preheats in the range: 200 o C-300 o C in steps of 20 o C. <lb/>The aliquot was dosed with 25 Gy, preheated for 10 s and stimulated at 125 o C using <lb/>an on-time of 1 ms and an off-time of 5 ms. The curves have been normalized to the <lb/>first point in the off-time. Inset: The off-time decay counts integrated for the periods <lb/>0.0-6.6 µs (filled circles) and 1005.0-1011.6 µs (open circles) and plotted as a <lb/>function of preheat temperature. For comparison, the two data sets are normalised to <lb/>their value for the preheat of 200°C. <lb/>Figure 3 <lb/>(a) Time-resolved blue light stimulated OSL off-time curves from a single aliquot of <lb/>quartz (WIDG8) measured at the temperatures: 50 o C-225 o C. The aliquot was dosed <lb/>with 25 Gy and heated to 260 o C for 10 s prior to each measurement using an on-time <lb/>of 1 ms and an off-time of 5 ms. The curves have been normalized to the first point in <lb/>the off-time. Inset: The same curves shown on a log-log scale. (b) Intensity (triangles) <lb/>and lifetime (circles) of the component shown as #1 in Fig. 1(a) plotted as a function <lb/>of stimulation temperature. The intensity is calculated from integrating counts in the <lb/>initial 0.0-6.6 µs of the off-time curve after a background subtraction (the average <lb/>counts per channel derived from data between 5900 and 5990 µs). (c) Intensity <lb/>(circles) and lifetime (triangles) of the component shown as #2 in Fig. 1(a) plotted as <lb/>a function of the stimulation temperature. The lifetime in ms was determined from <lb/>single exponential fitting of the curves after subtraction of an average over the last 50 <lb/>points and removing the initial 400 µs of the off-time. The intensity was calculated at <lb/>400 µs into the off-time. Note that the open symbols denote recycling point <lb/>measurements and that the errors on the lifetimes in (b) and (c) are not visible as they <lb/>are smaller than the size of the symbols. <lb/>Figure 4 <lb/>Blue light stimulated OSL off-time curves from a single aliquot of quartz (WIDG8) <lb/>measured using preheats in the range: 200-300 o C in steps of 20 o C. The aliquot was <lb/>dosed with 25 Gy and preheated for 10 s prior to each measurement and stimulated at <lb/>125 o C using a pulse length of 0.2 s and detecting for 7.8 s following the stimulation <lb/>pulse. The curves have been normalized to the first point in the off-time. The inset <lb/>shows the curves on a log-log scale. <lb/>Figure 5 <lb/>(a) Blue light stimulated OSL off-time curves from a single aliquot of quartz <lb/>(WIDG8) measured in the temperature range: 50-200 o C. The aliquot was dosed with <lb/>25 Gy and heated to 260 o C for 10 s prior to each measurement using a stimulation <lb/>pulse length of 0.2 and detecting for 7.8 s following the stimulation pulse. The curves <lb/>have been normalized to the first point in the off-time. (b) The initial 3 s of the curves <lb/>from (a) labelled with letters from a -f to indicate the behaviour of the OSP from the <lb/>110°C TL peak (see text for details). <lb/>Figure 6 <lb/>(a) Summary of lifetimes (found from fitting the initial 3 s of the curves in Fig. 5 with <lb/>a sum of three exponentials) on an Arrhenius plot. The natural logarithm of the <lb/>lifetimes for fast (circle) medium (triangle) and slow (square) components derived <lb/>from fitting are plotted against the inverse of stimulation temperature (times <lb/>Boltzmann&apos;s constant). (b) Summary of lifetimes found from fitting the remaining <lb/>part of the off-time decays in Fig. 5 after subtraction of a constant term. The curves <lb/>could be adequately fitted with a single decaying exponential. Note that the errors on <lb/>the lifetimes in both (a) and (b) are not visible as they are smaller than the size of the <lb/>symbols. <lb/>Figure 7 <lb/>TL curves showing the effect of photo-transfer in quartz (WIDG8) due to short blue <lb/>light stimulations of different length. An aliquot of quartz was dosed with 25 Gy, <lb/>heated to 300 o C for 10 s, blue light stimulated at 20 o C, and then a TL curve to 300 o C <lb/>was measured using a heating rate of 2 o Cs -1 . The same cycle was repeated with 0 s of <lb/>light stimulation before the TL measurement. The curves shown in the figure have all <lb/>been obtained by subtraction of TL before illumination from that after illumination. <lb/>Repeat measurements showed less than 2% variability. <lb/>Figure 8 <lb/>Off-time curve decay rate change (&apos;kink&apos;) as a function of stimulation pulse duration. <lb/>An aliquot of quartz (WIDG8) was dosed with 25 Gy, preheated to 260 o C for 10 s and <lb/>stimulated at 100 o C with a single on-pulse of varying length between 0.1 s and 1.6 s. <lb/>The curves have been normalized to the initial off-time point. Inset: Position of the <lb/>&apos;kink&apos; in the off-time curve as a function of stimulation pulse duration. <lb/>Figure 9 <lb/>Band diagrams showing (a) A three trap (T 1 , T 2 , and T 3 ) -one recombination centre <lb/>(L) model. The traps T 1 , T 2 , and T 3 have initial concentrations and decay constants n 1 , <lb/>λ 1 , n 2 , λ 2 , and n 3 , λ 3 respectively, and f represents the fraction of charge transfer from <lb/>one energy level to the other (b) A one trap (T 3 ) -two recombination centres (L a and <lb/>L b ) model. L a has two excited states, L a2 and L a1 . The same subscript notation is used <lb/>as in (a) for concentrations and decay constants for the trap and the excited states. <lb/>Figure 10 <lb/>(a) Curves showing the loss from T 3 , T 2 , and T 1 together with the phosphorescence <lb/>emitted at L when solving the rate-equations (1)-(4) using the parameters: n 10 = 50 <lb/>cm -3 , λ 1 = 0.04 s -1 , n 20 = 300 cm -3 , λ 2 = 0.09 s -1 , n 30 = 25 cm -3 , λ 3 = 0.3 s -1 , and f 3 = 0.1, <lb/>and f 2 = 0.92. (b) The same curves from (a) shown on a semi-log scale. <lb/>Figure 11 <lb/>Curves showing the phosphorescence emitted at L when running the rate-equations <lb/>(5)-(7) using the parameters: n 10 = 50 cm -3 , λ 1 = 0.04 s -1 , n 20 = 300 cm -3 , λ 2 = 0.09 s -<lb/>1 for different values of f between 0.1 and 1. The loss from T 2 and T 1 together with the <lb/>light emitted from L for f = 0.3 are shown inset to illustrate the dependence between <lb/>the three. <lb/>Figure 12 <lb/>Normalized cumulative phosphorescence (integrated over 10 s) following different <lb/>lengths of CW stimulations in the range of 10 s to 70 s. The sample was dosed with <lb/>25 Gy, preheated to 260 o C for 10 s and stimulated at 125 o C. The dashed line indicates <lb/>the dark count level also integrated over 10 s. Inset: The percentage ratio between the <lb/>end point of the OSL curve and the first point in the phosphorescence signal given for <lb/>different CW stimulation times. <lb/>Figure 1 (Figure1.eps) <lb/>(b) <lb/>Ti m e,µs <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>C ount ,(50 ns) <lb/>-1 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>10 1 <lb/>10 2 <lb/>10 3 <lb/>10 4 <lb/>(c) <lb/>Ti m e,m s <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>C ount ,(6. 6 µs) <lb/>-1 <lb/>10 2 <lb/>10 3 <lb/>10 4 <lb/>10 5 <lb/>(d) <lb/>Ti m e,s <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>C ount ,(0. 002 s) <lb/>-1 <lb/>10 -1 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>10 1 <lb/>10 2 <lb/>10 3 <lb/>10 4 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>(a) <lb/>Ti m e,s <lb/>10 -8 10 -7 10 -6 10 -5 10 -4 10 -3 10 -2 10 -1 10 0 10 1 <lb/>N orm al i zed count <lb/>10 -6 <lb/>10 -5 <lb/>10 -4 <lb/>10 -3 <lb/>10 -2 <lb/>10 -1 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>Figure 2 (Figure2.eps) <lb/>Preheat <lb/>t em perat ure: <lb/>Ti m e,m s <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>N orm al i zed count <lb/>10 -2 <lb/>10 -1 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>300 o C <lb/>280 <lb/>o <lb/>C <lb/>260 <lb/>o <lb/>C <lb/>240 o C <lb/>220 o C <lb/>200 o C <lb/>Preheatt em perat ure, o C <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>300 <lb/>N orm al i zed count <lb/>0. 00 <lb/>0. 25 <lb/>0. 50 <lb/>0. 75 <lb/>1. 00 <lb/>1. 25 <lb/>Figure 3 (Figure3.eps) <lb/>St i m ul at i on <lb/>t em perat ure: <lb/>Ti m e,m s <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>N orm al i zed count <lb/>0. 01 <lb/>0. 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>50 <lb/>o <lb/>C <lb/>75 o C <lb/>100 o C <lb/>125 <lb/>o <lb/>C <lb/>150 <lb/>o <lb/>C <lb/>175 <lb/>o <lb/>C <lb/>200 <lb/>o <lb/>C <lb/>225 <lb/>o <lb/>C <lb/>(a) <lb/>Ti m e,m s <lb/>10 -2 <lb/>10 -1 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>N orm al i zed count <lb/>10 -2 <lb/>10 -1 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>(b)C om ponent1 <lb/>Li f et i m e,µs <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>I ni t i alct s. ,(6. 6 µs) <lb/>-1 <lb/>0 <lb/>5x10 4 <lb/>10 5 <lb/>1x <lb/>(c)C om ponent2 <lb/>St i m ul at i on t em perat ure, <lb/>o <lb/>C <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>0 <lb/>300 <lb/>600 <lb/>900 <lb/>Li f et i m e,m s <lb/>0. 0 <lb/>0. 5 <lb/>1. 0 <lb/>1. 5 <lb/>Figure 4 (Figure4.eps) <lb/>Preheatt em perat ures: <lb/>Ti m e,s <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>N orm al i zed count <lb/>10 -3 <lb/>10 -2 <lb/>10 -1 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>200 <lb/>o <lb/>C <lb/>220 <lb/>o <lb/>C <lb/>240 o C <lb/>260 <lb/>o <lb/>C <lb/>280 <lb/>o <lb/>C <lb/>300 o C <lb/>Ti m e,s <lb/>10 -3 10 -2 10 -1 10 0 <lb/>N orm al i zed count <lb/>10 -3 <lb/>10 -2 <lb/>10 -1 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>Figure 5 (Figure5.eps) <lb/>Ti m e,s <lb/>0. 0 <lb/>0. 5 <lb/>1. 0 <lb/>1. 5 <lb/>2. 0 <lb/>2. 5 <lb/>3. 0 <lb/>N orm al i zed count <lb/>10 -3 <lb/>10 -2 <lb/>10 -1 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>50 o C <lb/>75 o C <lb/>100 o C <lb/>125 o C <lb/>150 o C <lb/>175 o C <lb/>200 o C <lb/>St i m ul at i on t em perat ures: <lb/>Ti m e,s <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>N orm al i zed count <lb/>10 -3 <lb/>10 -2 <lb/>10 -1 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>f <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>Figure 6 (Figure6.eps) <lb/>(kT) -1 ,eV -1 <lb/>24 26 28 30 32 34 36 38 <lb/>l n( ) <lb/>-6 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>(b) <lb/>St i m ul at i on t em perat ure, <lb/>o <lb/>C <lb/>50 <lb/>75 <lb/>100 125 150 175 <lb/>Li f et i m e,s <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>(a) <lb/>Figure 7 (Figure7.eps) <lb/>Pri orTL bl ue l i ght <lb/>st i m ul at i on durat i on: <lb/>Tem perat ure, o C <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 150 200 250 300 <lb/>C ount s,(1. 2 s) <lb/>-1 <lb/>-10000 <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>0. 1 s <lb/>0. 2 s <lb/>0. 4 s <lb/>0. 8 s <lb/>1. 6 s <lb/>2. 8 s <lb/>3. 2 s <lb/>Figure 8 (Figure8.eps) <lb/>O n-t i m e,s: <lb/>Ti m e,s <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>N orm al i zed count <lb/>10 -2 <lb/>10 -1 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>1. 6 s <lb/>0. 8 s <lb/>0. 4 s <lb/>0. 2 s <lb/>0. 1 s <lb/>O n-t i m e l engt h,s <lb/>0. 0 0. 5 1. 0 1. 5 <lb/>&apos; Ki nk&apos;posi t i on,s <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>Figure 9 (Figure9.eps) <lb/>C O N D U C TI O N BAN D <lb/>VALEN C E BAN D <lb/>h <lb/>L <lb/>T 2 <lb/>Energy <lb/>E c <lb/>E v <lb/>T 1 <lb/>T 3 <lb/>T 3 <lb/>L a1 <lb/>L a2 <lb/>h <lb/>L a <lb/>L b <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>h <lb/>C O N D U C TI O N BAN D <lb/>VALEN C E BAN D <lb/>f 3 <lb/>f 2 <lb/>Figure 10 (Figure10.eps) <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>Si m ul at ed <lb/>phosphorescence,(a. u. ) <lb/>0, 0 <lb/>0, 2 <lb/>0, 4 <lb/>0, 6 <lb/>0, 8 <lb/>1, 0 <lb/>1, 2 <lb/>T 3 l oss t o L <lb/>T 2 l oss t o L <lb/>T 1 l oss t o L <lb/>Tot alem i t t ed f rom L <lb/>Ti m e,(a. u. ) <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>Si m ul at ed <lb/>phosphorescence,(a. u. ) <lb/>10 -2 <lb/>10 -1 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>T 3 l oss t o L <lb/>T 2 l oss t o L <lb/>T 1 l oss t o L <lb/>Tot alem i t t ed f rom L <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>Figure 11 (Figure11.eps) <lb/>Ti m e,(a. u. ) <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>Si m ul at ed <lb/>phosphorescence,(a. u. ) <lb/>0, 0 <lb/>0, 5 <lb/>1, 0 <lb/>1, 5 <lb/>2, 0 <lb/>2, 5 <lb/>3, 0 <lb/>3, 5 <lb/>f= 0. 1 <lb/>f= 0. 2 <lb/>f= 0. 3 <lb/>f= 0. 5 <lb/>f= 0. 7 <lb/>f= 0. 9 <lb/>f= 1. 0 <lb/>Forf= 0. 3 <lb/>Ti m e,s <lb/>0 <lb/>20 40 60 80 <lb/>0, 0 <lb/>0, 2 <lb/>0, 4 <lb/>0, 6 <lb/>0, 8 <lb/>1, 0 <lb/>T 1 <lb/>T 2 <lb/>L <lb/>Figure 12 (Figure12.eps) <lb/>C W st i m ul at i on t i m e,s <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>N orm al i zed phosphorescence <lb/>0, 0 <lb/>0, 2 <lb/>0, 4 <lb/>0, 6 <lb/>0, 8 <lb/>1, 0 <lb/>1, 2 <lb/>C W st i m ul at i on t i m e,s <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>Percent age,% <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 </body>

	</text>
</tei>
