<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>DOI: 10.1002/zaac.200700517 <lb/>Synthesis and Crystal Structure of (CH 3 NH 3 ) 2 [Cu(NO 3 ) 4 ]: a Rare Example of <lb/>a Tetranitratocuprate(II) with a Light Cation of the Type M 2 [Cu(NO 3 ) 4 ] <lb/>Georg Steinhauser a,b, *, Konstantin Karaghiosoff b , and Thomas M. Klapötke b, * <lb/>a Vienna/Austria, Vienna University of Technology, Atominstitut der Österreichischen Universitäten <lb/>b Munich/Germany, Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry, Ludwig-Maximilian University <lb/>Received November 14 th , 2007. <lb/>Abstract. The reaction of methylammonium nitrate and copper(II) <lb/>nitrate pentahemihydrate in concentrated nitric acid yields the <lb/>novel bis(monomethylammonium) tetranitratocuprate(II). By <lb/>evaporation of the nitric acid at elevated temperatures single crys-<lb/>tals suitable for crystal structure analysis by X-ray diffraction were <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Water-free nitratocuprates(II) are a class of oxygen-rich <lb/>compounds with potential applicability as pyrotechnic <lb/>oxidizers [1, 2]. For monovalent cations, the cation:copper <lb/>ratio can generally be 1:1 (compounds of the type <lb/>M[Cu(NO 3 ) 3 ], type 1), 2:1 (M 2 [Cu(NO 3 ) 4 ], type 2), 3:1 <lb/>(M 3 [Cu(NO 3 ] 4 (NO 3 ), type 3) or 4:1 (M 4 [Cu(NO 3 ] 4 (NO 3 ) 2 , <lb/>type 4). The few structurally characterized examples of <lb/>nitratocuprates(II) include the following compounds; type <lb/>1: M ϭ NO ϩ [3, 4]; type 2: M ϭ Na ϩ , Ag ϩ [4], Cs ϩ [5], <lb/>Ph 4 As ϩ [6, 7] and several complexes with cations containing <lb/>large organic ligands [8Ϫ11]; type 3: M ϭ NH 4 <lb/>ϩ , K ϩ , Rb ϩ <lb/>[5]; type 4: M ϭ benzylammonium [12]. <lb/>From the above list, it is obvious that most light cations <lb/>(atomic weight &lt; approx. 100) generally prefer a co-crystal-<lb/>lization of their nitrate and the nitratocuprate(II) anion <lb/>(types 3 and 4). The only exception so far are the corre-<lb/>sponding sodium (type 2) and nitrosylium compounds (type <lb/>1). In this contribution, we present the synthesis and crystal <lb/>structure of the novel bis(methylammonium) tetranitrato-<lb/>cuprate(II), (CH 3 NH 3 ) 2 [Cu(NO 3 ) 4 ] (1). Methylammonium <lb/>is the second lightest cation (M ϭ 32.08), which forms a <lb/>type 2 nitratocuprate salt, characterized by single crystal X-<lb/>ray diffraction. <lb/></body>

			<front>* Prof. Dr. Thomas M. Klapötke <lb/>Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry <lb/>Ludwig-Maximilian University Munich <lb/>Butenandtstr. 5Ϫ13 (D) <lb/>D-81377 Munich, Germany <lb/>E-mail: tmk@cup.uni-muenchen.de <lb/>* Dr. Georg Steinhauser <lb/>Vienna University of Technology <lb/>Atominstitut der Österreichischen Universitäten <lb/>Stadionallee 2 <lb/>A-1020 Vienna, Austria <lb/>E-mail: georg.steinhauser@ati.ac.at <lb/>892 <lb/>© 2008 WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem. 2008, 634, 892Ϫ894 <lb/>obtained. The crystal structure shows a clear Jahn-Teller distortion <lb/>in the octahedral nitratocuprate anion. <lb/>Keywords: Coordination chemistry; Cuprates; Jahn-Teller distor-<lb/>tion; Nitratocuprates(II); Crystal structures <lb/></front>

			<body>Results and Discussion <lb/>The crystal structure of 1 is shown in Figure 1. The Cu II <lb/>ion is coordinated by four nitrate ions. Two of them (N1) <lb/>act as anisobidentate ligands [8, 13]. In this case, the <lb/>Fig. 1 Molecular structure of 1 in the crystal. Only selected hydro-<lb/>gen atoms are labeled for clarity. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Synthesis and Crystal Structure of (CH 3 NH 3 ) 2 [Cu(NO 3 ) 4 ] <lb/></note>

			<body>Cu1ϪO3 bond (2.527(1) Å ) is significantly longer than <lb/>Cu1ϪO1 (1.967(1) Å ), which is due to Jan-Teller distortion. <lb/>The bond length of the monodentate nitrate ligand <lb/>(Cu1ϪO4) is similar (1.958(1) Å ) to the that of Cu1ϪO1. <lb/>Thus the equatorial (almost) square plane is formed by each <lb/>two of O1 and O4 atoms, whereas the elongated axial posi-<lb/>tions of the octahedron are occupied by the two O3 atoms. <lb/>The distorted octahedral coordination environment is simi-<lb/>lar to that of NO[Cu(NO 3 ) 3 ] [4]. In 1, one can differentiate <lb/>three different categories of CuϪO distances; four short <lb/>CuϪO bonds (Cu1ϪO1 and Cu1ϪO4) forming the square <lb/>plane, two elongated axial CuϪO bonds (Cu1ϪO3) and <lb/>two much longer Cu1ϪO5 distances (2.908(1) Å ). In nitra-<lb/>tocuprates(II) described as square planar complexes (e.g. [8, <lb/>12]), only two different categories of CuϪO distances are <lb/>found. In the crystal structure of 1, hydrogen bonds are <lb/>present and allow the assignment of the ammonium and <lb/>the methyl group of the cation (see Table 2). The anions are <lb/>bridged via these hydrogen bonds, which is probably the <lb/>reason for the stability of this unusual type 2-tetranitrato-<lb/>cuprate(II) with a light cation. <lb/>Table 1 Selected bond lengths /Å and angles /°of 1 <lb/>Cu1ϪO1 <lb/>1.967(1) <lb/>N1ϪO2 <lb/>1.221(2) <lb/>Cu1ϪO3 <lb/>2.527(1) <lb/>N1ϪO3 <lb/>1.245(2) <lb/>Cu1ϪO4 <lb/>1.958(1) <lb/>N2ϪO4 <lb/>1.296(1) <lb/>C1ϪN3 <lb/>1.468(2) <lb/>N2ϪO5 <lb/>1.224(2) <lb/>N1ϪO1 <lb/>1.293(2) <lb/>N2ϪO6 <lb/>1.239(2) <lb/>N1ϪO1ϪCu1 <lb/>106.23(8) <lb/>N1ϪO3ϪCu1 <lb/>81.12(8) <lb/>N2ϪO4ϪCu1 <lb/>117.74(8) <lb/>O3ϪCu1ϪO4 <lb/>92.73(4) <lb/>O4ϪCu1ϪO1 <lb/>90.88(4) <lb/>O1ϪCu1ϪO3 <lb/>124.15(4) <lb/>Table 2 Hydrogen bonding in 1 <lb/>DϪH•••A <lb/>D ϪH /Å <lb/>H•••A /Å <lb/>D•••A /Å <lb/>DϪH•••A /°N <lb/>3ϪH1•••O6 i <lb/>0.82(3) <lb/>2.26(3) <lb/>3.037(2) <lb/>158.(2) <lb/>N3ϪH1•••O4 i <lb/>0.82(3) <lb/>2.48(3) <lb/>2.983(2) <lb/>121.(2) <lb/>N3ϪH2•••O3 ii <lb/>0.87(2) <lb/>2.05(2) <lb/>2.914(2) <lb/>175.(2) <lb/>N3ϪH3•••O6 iii <lb/>0.76(2) <lb/>2.19(2) <lb/>2.948(2) <lb/>171.(2) <lb/>Symmetry codes: (i) 1Ϫx, 0.5ϩy, 1.5Ϫz; (ii) x, 1.5Ϫy, 0.5ϩz; (iii) 1Ϫx, 1Ϫy, <lb/>2Ϫz <lb/>The packing of 1 along [010] is shown in Figure 2. It can <lb/>be described as a packing of superposed tetranitratocuprate <lb/>anions intercalated with staggered layers of methyl-<lb/>ammonium cations. <lb/>Compound 1 is the first alkylammonium nitrato-<lb/>cuprate(II), which has been structurally characterized. The <lb/>synthesis of several other alkylammonium nitrates has also <lb/>been tried in this study, e.g. that of the NMe 2 H 2 <lb/>ϩ , <lb/>NMe 3 H ϩ , NMe 4 <lb/>ϩ , NEt 4 <lb/>ϩ , N(nPr) 4 <lb/>ϩ and N(nBu) 4 <lb/>ϩ salts. <lb/>However, in no other case, single crystals of the correspond-<lb/>ing nitratocuprate could be obtained. In several cases, the <lb/>reactions produced dark blue or dark green ionic liquids. <lb/>In some cases, the hot reaction mixture reacted violently <lb/>forming a brown solid and NO x gas. This was probably due <lb/>to the formation of alkyl nitrate esters which exothermally <lb/>decomposed. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem. 2008, 892Ϫ894 <lb/>© 2008 WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>www.zaac.wiley-vch.de <lb/></note>

			<page>893 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 2 View of the unit cell of 1 along [010]. Only selected atoms <lb/>are labeled for clarity. <lb/>Table 3 Crystal structure and refinement data of 1 <lb/>empirical formula <lb/>C 2 H 12 N 6 O 12 Cu <lb/>formula weight /g mol Ϫ1 <lb/>375.72 <lb/>temperature /K <lb/>200 <lb/>crystal size /mm <lb/>0.35 ϫ 0.25 ϫ 0.1 <lb/>crystal system <lb/>monoclinic <lb/>space group <lb/>P2 1 /c <lb/>a /Å <lb/>8.4533(2) <lb/>b /Å <lb/>8.6922(2) <lb/>c /Å <lb/>9.3943(2) <lb/>β /°104.82(0) <lb/>V /Å 3 <lb/>667.3(4) <lb/>Z <lb/>2 <lb/>ρ calc /g cm Ϫ3 <lb/>1.8698 <lb/>μ /mm Ϫ1 <lb/>1.714 <lb/>F(000) <lb/>382 <lb/>θ range /°3.73Ϫ32.25 <lb/>index ranges <lb/>Ϫ12 Յ h Յ 12 <lb/>Ϫ12 Յ k Յ 12 <lb/>Ϫ14 Յ l Յ 13 <lb/>reflections collected <lb/>19343 <lb/>reflections unique <lb/>2276 (R int ϭ 0.036) <lb/>R1 (2σ) <lb/>0.024 <lb/>R1 (all data) <lb/>0.041 <lb/>wR2 (2σ) <lb/>0.060 <lb/>wR2 (all data) <lb/>0.067 <lb/>data/restraints/parameters <lb/>2276/0/122 <lb/>GOOF on F 2 <lb/>1.013 <lb/>Δρ max /e Å Ϫ3 <lb/>0.36 <lb/>Δρ min /e Å Ϫ3 <lb/>Ϫ0.32 <lb/>Experimental Section <lb/>Synthesis <lb/>A solution of 3.46 g (52 mmol) CH 3 NH 3 • HCl in concentrated ni-<lb/>tric acid (3ϫ5 mL, 65 % HNO 3 ) was evaporated (not to complete <lb/>dryness) three times on an oil bath (110°C) to remove any chloride. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">G. Steinhauser, K. Karaghiosoff, T. M. Klapötke <lb/></note>

			<body>To the residual solution, 4 g of Cu(NO 3 ) 2 • 2.5 H 2 O (17 mmol) were <lb/>added. A few drops of nitric acid were added in order to dissolve <lb/>the copper nitrate completely. During slow evaporation at 110°C, <lb/>greenish-blue single crystals of 1 formed in the solution. They were <lb/>removed from the liquid and used for X-ray diffraction. Attention <lb/>has to be paid to the highly hygroscopic character of 1 in air after <lb/>removal from the nitric acid. The crystals rapidly hydrolyse and <lb/>melt in the crystal water. <lb/>IR (Diamond-ATR, cm Ϫ1 ): 3539 (s), 3319 (vs), 3238 (sh), 2468 (w), <lb/>2344 (w), 2088 (vw), 1763 (w), 1732 (vw), 1609 (m), 1511 (sh), 1414 <lb/>(vs), 1277 (vs), 1044 (m), 1017 (s), 939 (w), 874 (w), 800 (m), 759 <lb/>(m), 715 (vw), 664 (m), 517 (m); Raman (25°C, cm Ϫ1 ): 2987 (23), <lb/>2329 (5), 1597 (23), 1526 (28), 1319 (21), 1047 (100), 986 (14), 765 <lb/>(23), 714 (19), 462 (5), 294 (37). <lb/>X-Ray Crystallography <lb/>Data collection was performed with an Oxford Xcalibur dif-<lb/>fractometer equipped with a CCD area detector, using Mo-K α <lb/>radiation (wavelength λ ϭ 0.71073 Å ). The structure was solved <lb/>using direct methods (SHELXS [14]) and refined by full-matrix le-<lb/>ast squares on F 2 . (SHELXL [14]). All non-hydrogen atoms were <lb/>refined anisotropically. The ORTEP plots of the figures show ther-<lb/>mal ellipsoids at the 50 % probability level. Crystallographic data <lb/>for the structure of 1 have been deposited with the the Cambridge <lb/>Crystallographic Data Centre under the depository number <lb/>666736. Copies of the data can be obtained free of charge on <lb/>application to The Director, CCDC, 12 Union Road, Cam-<lb/>bridge, CB2 1EZ, UK (Fax: int. code ϩ (1223)336-033; email <lb/>for inquiry: fileserv@ccdc.cam.ac.uk; e-mail for deposition: <lb/>deposit@ccdc.cam.ac.uk). <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements. Financial support of this work by the Ludwig-<lb/>Maximilian University of Munich (LMU), the Fonds der Chem-<lb/>ischen Industrie (FCI), the European Research Office (ERO) of <lb/>the U.S. Army Research Laboratory (ARL) under contract nos. <lb/>www.zaac.wiley-vch.de <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">© 2008 WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem. 2008, 892Ϫ894 <lb/></note>

			<div type="acknowledgement">894 <lb/>N 62558-05-C-0027, W 911NF-07-1-0569 &amp; 9939-AN-01 and the <lb/>Bundeswehr Research Institute for Materials, Explosives, Fuels and <lb/>Lubricants (WIWEB) under contract nos. E/E210/4D004/X5143 &amp; <lb/>E/E210/7D002/4F088 is gratefully acknowledged. We thank <lb/>Dr. habil. Margaret-Jane Crawford for interesting discussions on <lb/>this topic. Georg Steinhauser thanks the Austrian Science Fund <lb/>(FWF) for financial support (Erwin Schrödinger Auslands-<lb/>stipendium, project no. J2645-N17). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] SNPE Materiaux Energetiques S.A., Fr. (C. Pradere, E. S. <lb/>Sabo, B. Chaudret, G. Jacob) FR 2891822 (April 13, 2007). <lb/>[2] G. Steinhauser, T. M. Klapötke, in preparation. <lb/>[3] L. J. Blackwell, T. J. King, A. Morris, J. Chem. Soc., Chem. <lb/>Commun. 1973, 17, 644. <lb/>[4] K. O. Znamenkov, I. V. Morozov, S. I. Troyanov, Zh. Neorg. <lb/>Khim. 2004, 49, 213. <lb/>[5] I. V. Morozov, A. A. Fedorova, S. I. Troyanov, Z. Anorg. Allg. <lb/>Chem. 1998, 624, 1543. <lb/>[6] J. Drummond, J. S. Wood, J. Chem. Soc. A. 1970, 226. <lb/>[7] T. J. King, A. Morris, Inorg. Nucl. Chem. Lett. 1974, 10, <lb/>237. <lb/>[8] C. Kimblin, V. J. Murphy, T. Hascall, B. M. Bridgewater, J. B. <lb/>Bonanno, G. Parkin, Inorg. Chem. 2000, 39, 967. <lb/>[9] V. I. Sokol, M. A. Ryabov, N. Yu. Merkur&apos;eva, V. S. Sergienko, <lb/>V. V. Davydov, Yu. V. Shklyaev, Zh. Neorg. Khim. 2000, 45, <lb/>1985. <lb/>[10] C.-Y. Su, S. Liao, M. Wanner, J. Fiedler, C. Zhang, B.-S. Kang, <lb/>W. Kaim, J. Chem. Soc., Dalton Trans. 2003, 189. <lb/>[11] J. Martínez, R. Bastida, A. Macías, L. Valencia, M. Vicente, <lb/>Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem. 2005, 631, 2046. <lb/>[12] M. Rademeyer, Acta Crystallogr. 2006, E62, m269. <lb/>[13] G. J. Kleywegt, W. G. R. Wiesmeijer, G. J. Van Driel, W. L. <lb/>Driessen, J. Reedijk, J. H. Noordik, J. Chem. Soc., Dalton <lb/>Trans. 1985, 2177. <lb/>[14] G. M. Sheldrick, Universität Göttingen, Germany, 1997. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
