<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>DOI: 10.1002/zaac.200700461 <lb/>Direct Syntheses of Bis(tetraphenylphosphonium) and <lb/>Bis(ethyltriphenylphosphonium) Hexabromo-diselenates(II), [PPh 4 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] and <lb/>[PEtPh 3 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ]. The Crystal Structure of [PEtPh 3 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] <lb/>Vitalijus Janickis* ,a , Max Herberhold b and Wolfgang Milius b <lb/>a Kaunas/Lithuania , Faculty of Chemical Technology, Kaunas University of Technology <lb/>b Bayreuth/Germany, Laboratory of Inorganic Chemistry, University of Bayreuth <lb/>Received September 21 st , 2007; accepted December 4 th , 2007. <lb/>Abstract. Brown crystals of [PPh 4 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] (1) and <lb/>[PEtPh 3 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] (2) were obtained when selenium and bromine <lb/>reacted in acetonitrile solution in the presence of tetraphenylphos-<lb/>phonium bromide and ethyltriphenylphosphonium bromide, <lb/>respectively. The crystal structure of 2 has been determined by X-<lb/>ray methods and refined to R ϭ 0.0420 for 4161 reflections. The <lb/>crystals are monoclinic, space group P2 1 /n with Z ϭ 2 and a ϭ <lb/>13.055(3) Å , b ϭ 12.628(3) Å , c ϭ 13.530(3) Å , β ϭ 92.40(3)°( <lb/>293(2) K). In the solid state structure of 2 the dinuclear hexa-<lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>The binary compound of selenium(II) with bromine, SeBr 2 , <lb/>has not been isolated but gives a series of anionic complexes <lb/>with bromide ions. The known modifications of such com-<lb/>plexes are the nearly square-planar mononuclear [SeBr 4 ] 2Ϫ <lb/>ion [1, 2], the dinuclear [Se 2 Br 6 ] 2Ϫ ion formed by two edge-<lb/>sharing distorted SeBr 4 squares [1, 3], the trinuclear <lb/>[Se 3 Br 8 ] 2Ϫ ion consisting of three edge-sharing square-<lb/>planar SeBr 4 units [4], the tetranuclear ion [Se 4 Br 14 ] 2Ϫ <lb/>which is built of two parallel planar Se 2 Br 6 units connected <lb/>via two linear Br-bridges [4, 5], and the pentanuclear ion <lb/>[Se 5 Br 12 ] 2Ϫ , consisting of a central square-planar SeBr 4 unit <lb/>with two trans-edges being shared with additional pairs of <lb/>square-planar SeBr 4 units [4]. <lb/>The dinuclear hexabromo-diselenate(II) anion was iso-<lb/>lated for first time as thetetraphenylphosphonium salt, <lb/>[PPh 4 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ], from the reaction of selenium tetrabromide, <lb/>SeBr 4 (which is in equilibrium with SeBr 2 , Se 2 Br 2 and Br 2 <lb/>in solution), and tetraphenylphosphonium bromide, <lb/>[PPh 4 ]Br, [1]. The following sequence of reactions was pro-<lb/>posed for the formation of hexabromo-diselenate ions <lb/>SeBr 4 o SeBr 2 ϩ Br 2 , <lb/>2SeBr 2 ϩ 2Br 2 ϩ 4[PPh 4 ]Br o [PPh 4 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] ϩ 2[PPh 4 ]Br 3 . <lb/></body>

			<front>* Prof. Dr. Vitalijus Janickis <lb/>Faculty of Chemical Technology <lb/>Kaunas University of Technology <lb/>Radvilenų str. 19, LT-50254 Kaunas, Lithuania <lb/>FAX: ϩ370 37 300152. PHONE: ϩ370 37 451464. <lb/>E-Mail: vitalijus.janickis@ktu.lt <lb/>Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem. 2008, 634, 901Ϫ904 <lb/>© 2008 WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>901 <lb/>bromo-diselenate(II) anion is centrosymmetric and consists of two <lb/>distorted almost square-planar SeBr 4 units sharing a common edge <lb/>through two bridging Br atoms. The terminal Se II ϪBr bond dis-<lb/>tances are found to be 2.419(1) and 2.445(1) Å , the bridging <lb/>μBrϪSe II bond distances 2.901(1) and 2.802(1) Å . <lb/>Keywords: Selenium; Hexabromodiselenate(II); Crystal structure; <lb/>Tetraphenylphosphonium and Ethyltriphenylphosphonium ions <lb/></front>

			<body>Selenium reacts with bromine (1:1) in acetonitrile <lb/>solution: <lb/>2Se ϩ Br 2 o Se 2 Br 2 . <lb/>However when the Se/Br 2 ratio is 2.0, the formation of <lb/>Se 2 Br 2 is not quantitative [6, 7], since both Se 2 Br 2 and Br 2 <lb/>participate in the disproportionation equilibria [6Ϫ8]: <lb/>2SeBr 2 o Se 2 Br 2 ϩ Br 2 <lb/>and <lb/>3SeBr 2 o Se 2 Br 2 ϩ SeBr 4 . <lb/>Therefore, the selenium bromides SeBr 4 [8], Se 3 Br 2 and <lb/>Se 4 Br 2 , may be present in minor amounts in the reaction <lb/>mixture as well [6]. <lb/>It had been shown earlier [2, 3, 6, 9, 13Ϫ11] that the <lb/>formation of species which will crystallize from the solution <lb/>when selenium reacts with bromine in the presence of bro-<lb/>mide ions, depends on equilibrium concentrations and solu-<lb/>bilities, respectively, and Ϫ especially Ϫ on the nature of <lb/>the cation, the bromide of which was used for the synthesis. <lb/>For example, the reaction of selenium with bromine <lb/>in the presence of phenyltrimethylammonium bromide, <lb/>[NMe 3 Ph]Br, was adapted [6] to the stoichiometry <lb/>5Se ϩ 4Br 2 ϩ 2Br Ϫ Ǟ [SeBr 6 (Se 2 Br 2 ) 2 ] 2Ϫ <lb/>and the first mixed-valence bromoselenate(IV/I), i.e. phenyl-<lb/>trimethylammonium hexabromoselenate(IV)-bis{dibromo-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">V. Janickis, M. Herberhold, W. Milius <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 1 Crystal data, measurement conditions and results of <lb/>structure solution and refinement for [PEtPh 3 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] (2) <lb/>Formula <lb/>C 40 H 40 P 2 Br 6 Se 2 <lb/>Formula /(weight/gmol Ϫ1 ) <lb/>1220.04 <lb/>Crystal system <lb/>monoclinic <lb/>Space group <lb/>P2 1 /n <lb/>Cell dimensions a/Å <lb/>13.055(3) <lb/>b/Å <lb/>12.628(3) <lb/>c/Å <lb/>13.530(3) <lb/>β/°92.40(3) <lb/>Cell volume/Å 3 <lb/>2228.7(8) <lb/>Formula units/unit cell (Z) <lb/>2 <lb/>Calculated density ρ calc /gcm Ϫ3 <lb/>1.818 <lb/>Absorption coefficient μ/mm Ϫ1 <lb/>7.136 <lb/>Absorption correction <lb/>Empirical (γ-scan) <lb/>Transmission (max., min.) <lb/>0.2957, 0.3097 <lb/>Diffractometer <lb/>STOE IPDS I <lb/>(graphite monochromator) <lb/>Scan type <lb/>Omega <lb/>F(000) <lb/>1176 <lb/>Crystal size <lb/>0.25 x 0.20 x 0.15 mm 3 <lb/>Radiation <lb/>Mo-KͰ (λ ϭ 0.71073) <lb/>Temperature/K <lb/>293(2) <lb/>θ range/°2.12 Յ θ Յ 26.01 <lb/>hkl range <lb/>Ϫ16 Յ h Յ 16 <lb/>Ϫ14 Յ k Յ 14 <lb/>Ϫ16 Յ l Յ 16 <lb/>No. of measured reflections <lb/>16896 <lb/>No. of unique reflections <lb/>4161 <lb/>No. of observed (I &gt; 2σ(I)) reflections <lb/>2221 <lb/>Refinement method <lb/>Full-matrix least-squares on F 2 <lb/>Data /restraints / parameters <lb/>4161 /0/ 226 <lb/>Goodness-of-fit on F 2 <lb/>0.859 <lb/>Final R indices [I&gt;2sigma(I)] <lb/>R 1 ϭ 0.0420, wR 2 ϭ 0.0916 <lb/>R indices (all data) <lb/>R 1 ϭ 0.0908, wR 2 ϭ 0.1066 <lb/>Factors of weighting scheme a, b <lb/>0.0542, 0.00 <lb/>Residual electron density (max., min.) /eÅ Ϫ3 0.695, Ϫ0.676 <lb/>diselenate(I)} [6], in which selenium is present in different <lb/>oxidation states, was isolated. If the same stoichiometry <lb/>for the interaction of selenium with bromine was used <lb/>but phenyltrimethylammonium bromide, [NMe 3 Ph]Br, <lb/>was replaced by tetraethylammonium bromide, [NEt 4 ]Br, <lb/>the first mixed-valence bromoselenate(II,I) containing <lb/>selenium in the oxidation states ϩ2 and ϩ1, <lb/>i.e. bis(tetraethylammonium) octabromo-triselenate(II)-<lb/>{dibromodiselenate(I)}, [NEt 4 ] 2 [Se 3 Br 8 (Se 2 Br 2 )], was ob-<lb/>tained in high yield [10]. <lb/>In continuation of our earlier studies in the area of <lb/>halogenochalcogenates [2, 3, 6, 9Ϫ15], we have investigated <lb/>the reactions between elemental selenium and bromine in <lb/>acetonitrile solution in the presence of tetraphenylphos-<lb/>phonium bromide, [PPh 4 ]Br, and ethyltriphenylphos-<lb/>phonium bromide, [PEtPh 3 ]Br. We now report the new <lb/>direct synthesis of hexabromo-diselenate(II) compounds Ϫ <lb/>bis(tetraphenylphosphonium) and bis(ethyltriphenylphos-<lb/>phonium) hexabromo-diselenate(II), [PEtPh 3 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] and <lb/>[PPh 4 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ], respectively. We also report the crystal <lb/>structure of a new salt of the dinuclear bromoselenate(II) <lb/>anion, [PEtPh 3 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ]. <lb/>Results and Discussion <lb/>As pointed out above, the reaction of selenium with bro-<lb/>mine in acetonitrile solution includes a number of equilibria <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">www.zaac.wiley-vch.de <lb/>© 2008 WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem. 2008, 901Ϫ904 <lb/></note>

			<page>902 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 2 Bond lengths/Å and bond angles/°of the anion in 2 (with <lb/>standard deviations) <lb/>SeϪBr1 <lb/>2.4186(11) <lb/>SeϪBr1••• • • Br2 a <lb/>162.27(4) <lb/>SeϪBr2 <lb/>2.4450(11) <lb/>SeϪBr2••• • • Br1 b <lb/>168.37(3) <lb/>SeϪBr3 <lb/>2.8019(10) <lb/>Br1ϪSeϪBr2 <lb/>94.72(4) <lb/>SeϪBr3a <lb/>2.9014(11) <lb/>Br1ϪSeϪBr3 <lb/>90.51(4) <lb/>Br1••• • • Br2 a <lb/>3.6062(12) <lb/>Br1ϪSeϪBr3a <lb/>175.12(4) <lb/>Br2••• • • Br1 b <lb/>3.6062(12) <lb/>Br2ϪSeϪBr3 <lb/>174.45(4) <lb/>Br2ϪSeϪBr3a <lb/>87.43(4) <lb/>Br3ϪSeϪBr3a <lb/>87.22(3) <lb/>SeϪBr3ϪSea <lb/>92.78(3) <lb/>a Symmetry transformation: Ϫxϩ1/2,yϪ1/2,Ϫzϩ1/2; b Symmetry transfor-<lb/>mation: Ϫxϩ1/2,yϩ1/2,Ϫzϩ1/2 <lb/>in which various selenium bromide species are involved, and <lb/>the nature of the cation the bromide of which is introduced <lb/>into the interacting Se/Br 2 system may have a significant <lb/>influence upon the composition of the bromochalcogenate <lb/>salt which crystallizes from the solution. <lb/>In an extensive experimental study the direct syntheses <lb/>of an earlier known bis(tetraphenylphosphonium) hexa-<lb/>bromo-diselenate(II), [PPh 4 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] (1) and of a new <lb/>bis(ethyltriphenylphosphonium) hexabromo-diselenate(II), <lb/>[PEtPh 4 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] (2), have been optimised. Under defined <lb/>experimental conditions the reactions between elemental <lb/>selenium and bromine, in the presence of the above Ϫ men-<lb/>tioned bromides (and excess of selenium), follow the equa-<lb/>tions <lb/>2Se ϩ 2Br 2 ϩ 2[PPh 4 ]Br Ǟ [PPh 4 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] (1) <lb/>2Se ϩ 2Br 2 ϩ 2[PEtPh 3 ]Br Ǟ [PEtPh 3 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] (2) <lb/>The tetraphenylphosphonium salt, [PPh 4 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] (1), <lb/>was isolated in about 90 % yield and ethyltriphenylphos-<lb/>phonium salt, [PEtPh 3 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] (2), Ϫ in about 85 % yield. <lb/>The compound 2 has been characterized by single-crystal <lb/>X-ray structure analysis. The crystal data, measurement <lb/>conditions, and results of the structure solution and refine-<lb/>ment are summarized in Table 1. The bond lengths and <lb/>angles of the anion in 2 are listed in Table 2. <lb/>The molecular structure of 2 is shown in Figure 1 and <lb/>the net-like association of the anions in the crystals of 2 Ϫ <lb/>formed by interionic Br•••Br contacts Ϫ in Figure 2. <lb/>The [Se 2 Br 6 ] 2Ϫ anion of 2 is centrosymmetric and con-<lb/>sists of two almost planar distorted SeBr 4 units sharing a <lb/>common edge through two bridging Br atoms, Br(3) and <lb/>Br(3A). The deviations of atoms from the least-squares <lb/>[SeBr 4 ] plane defined by Se, Br1, Br2, Br3, Br3a are in the <lb/>range of 0.0173(4)Ϫ0.0547(5) Å ). The atoms of the <lb/>[Se 2 Br 6 ] 2Ϫ anion are nearly in plane too: the deviations of <lb/>atoms from the least squares plane defined by Br1, Br2, Se, <lb/>Br3, Br3a, Sea, Br1a, Br2a are between 0.0065(3) and <lb/>0.0596(5) Å . <lb/>The [Se 2 Br 6 ] 2Ϫ anion of 2 may be compared with the <lb/>same centrosymmetric anion in [PPh 4 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] and asym-<lb/>metric anion of [NMe 3 Ph] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] [1, 3]. In the centrosym-<lb/>metric anion of 2 the asymmetry in the bonding system is <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Direct Syntheses of [PPh 4 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] and [PEtPh 3 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 1 Molecular structure of [PEtPh 3 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] (2). (The hydro-<lb/>gen atoms of the ethyl and phenyl groups are omitted for the sake <lb/>of clarity.) <lb/>more reduced, the two terminal bonds differing by 0.026 Å <lb/>and the two bridging bonds by 0.099 Å . The reason for this <lb/>asxmmetry,which occursin several dihalogeno-bridged chal-<lb/>cogen(II) and chalcogen(IV) compounds [1, 7, 16], is not <lb/>clear. In the case of [PPh 4 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] (1) where the asymmetr <lb/>is relatively large, it was pointed out, that it may be initiated <lb/>by interionic halogen-halogen contacts. But in 2, with even <lb/>smaller asymmetry than in [NMe 3 Ph] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ], all terminal <lb/>Br atoms (Br1 and Br2) have short interionic contacts, <lb/>3.606 Å . In the centrosymmetric anion of [PPh 4 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] <lb/>(1) the bondsof the four-membered ring are alternatively <lb/>long and short; the same is observed in the centrosymmetric <lb/>anion of 2, whereas in the asymmetric anion of <lb/>[NMe 3 Ph] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] the longest bond is situated opposite to <lb/>the shortest one. <lb/>The selenium atoms of the [Se 2 Br 6 ] 2Ϫ anion of 2 are act-<lb/>ing as central atoms in the asymmetric, nearly linear sys-<lb/>tems Br1ϪSeϪBr3a and Br2ϪSeϪBr3. The angles at the <lb/>selenium atom are 175.12(4) and 174.45(4)°, respectively. <lb/>The Br terminal ϪSe II ϪBr terminal bond angle (94.72(4)°) is <lb/>larger than 90°, presumably due to an intramolecular <lb/>ligandϪligand interaction between the terminal Br atoms. <lb/>The bonds in the nearly linear Br t ϪSeϪμBr systems are <lb/>of the three-centre, four-electron (3cϪ4e) type with only <lb/>one occupied bonding orbital. All SeϪμBr bridging bonds <lb/>are considerably longer than the terminal SeϪBr bonds. <lb/>The average value of the total lengths of the linear <lb/>BrϪSeϪBr system in the [Se 2 Br 6 ] 2Ϫ ion of 2 is 5.2835 Å <lb/>which is close to the corresponding values in the [Se 2 Br 6 ] 2Ϫ <lb/>ion of [PPh 4 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] (1), 5.241 Å [1], and of <lb/>[NMe 3 Ph] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ], 5.270 Å [3]. <lb/>In the directions of the SeϪBr1, SeϪBr2, SeaϪBr1a, <lb/>Se1aϪBr2a bonds of adjacent [Se 2 Br 6 ] 2Ϫ anions, the Br1 <lb/>atoms have weak bonds to Br2 atoms and vice versa. These <lb/>intermolecular Br1•••Br2 distances are 3.6062(12) Å . As a <lb/>result, the net-like association of the anions in the crystals <lb/>of 2 is formed (Fig. 2). <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem. 2008, 901Ϫ904 <lb/>© 2008 WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>www.zaac.wiley-vch.de <lb/></note>

			<page>903 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 2 The net-like association of the planar [Se 2 Br 6 ] 2Ϫ anions <lb/>in the crystals of 2, formed by interionic Br••••••Br contacts <lb/>The dimensions of the ethyltriphenylphosphonium <lb/>ion in 2 are within the expected ranges: PϪC ϭ <lb/>1.786(6)Ϫ1.807(6) Å , <lb/>CϪC <lb/>ϭ <lb/>1.36(1)Ϫ1.53(1) Å , <lb/>CϪPϪC <lb/>ϭ <lb/>106.2(3)Ϫ111.8(3)°, <lb/>PϪCϪC <lb/>ϭ <lb/>110.7(5)Ϫ123.1(5)°and CϪCϪC ϭ 118.8(6)Ϫ121.7(7)°; <lb/>they do not deviate from the usual values. <lb/>Experimental Section <lb/>Direct synthesis of [PPh 4 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] (1) <lb/>A suspension of 3.0 mmol (0.237 g) selenium (Aldrich) (an excess <lb/>of selenium Ϫ 3 mmol instead of 2 mmol) was used to prevent the <lb/>formation of Se IV containing particles) and 2.0 mmol (0.839 g) of <lb/>tetraphenylphosphonium bromide in 5 ml of acetonitrile was <lb/>treated with 2.0 mmol (0.32 g) of bromine. The mixture was stirred <lb/>and heated at 80°C for 30 min. Then 7 ml of acetonitrile were ad-<lb/>ded to the mixture, and the temperature was raised to 75°C. A <lb/>clear, dark brown solution was obtained, although small amounts <lb/>of selenium did not react. The reaction mixture was left for about <lb/>4 h at room temperature, and 1.09 g brown crystals of <lb/>[PPh 4 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] (1) were isolated. The filtrate was stored in a re-<lb/>frigerator (ϩ2°C) for 12 h, and 0.11 g more of the pure compound <lb/>1 were isolated. The total yield was 1.20 g (ϳ 90 %) as calculated <lb/>according to the amounts of the reagents used. Selenium was deter-<lb/>mined by treating a solution of the sample in acetonitrile with an <lb/>aqueous sulfite solution, adding bromide and oxidizing with bro-<lb/>mine. Excess of bromine was removed, and the amount of selenium <lb/>was determined iodometrically. Found: Se 12.47 %. Calculated for <lb/>[PPh 4 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] (1): Se 12.00 %. Determination of the unit cell di-<lb/>mensions confirmed that the crystals synthesized are of the com-<lb/>pound 1, earlier obtained by a different reaction [1]. <lb/>The compound 1 forms dark brown, prism-like crystals which in <lb/>the presence of water gradually liberate red amorphous selenium. <lb/>Synthesis of [PEtPh 3 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] (2) <lb/>A suspension of 3.0 mmol (0.237 g) selenium (Aldrich) and <lb/>2.0 mmol (0.743 g) of ethyltriphenylphosphonium bromide in 5 ml <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">V. Janickis, M. Herberhold, W. Milius <lb/></note>

			<body>of acetonitrile was treated with 2.0 mmol (0.32 g) of bromine. The <lb/>mixture was stirred and heated at 78°C for 30 min. Then 15 ml of <lb/>acetonitrile were added to the mixture, and it was stirred and <lb/>heated at 78°C for 30 min more. A clear, dark brown solution was <lb/>obtained, although small amounts of selenium did not react. The <lb/>reaction mixture was left for about 4 h at room temperature, and <lb/>1.05 g brown crystals of [PEtPh 3 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] (2) were isolated. The <lb/>yield was ϳ 85 %, as calculated according to the amounts of the <lb/>reagents used. Found: Se 13.47 %. Calculated for [PEtPh 3 ] 2 [Se 2 Br 6 ] <lb/>(2): Se 12.94 %. <lb/>The compound 2 forms dark brown, short prism-like crystals which <lb/>in the presence of water gradually liberate red amorphous selenium. <lb/>IR spectra (100Ϫ600 cm Ϫ1 ) were recorded on a spectrophotometer <lb/>Rekin-Elmer GX system FT-IR by averaging 64 scans with <lb/>0.3 cm Ϫ1 resolution at room temperature. The bands in the IR spec-<lb/>tra of hexabromo-diselenate(II) anion of compound 2 were found <lb/>at 246, 200, 148, 134, and 114 cm Ϫ1 . according to the literature data <lb/>[1, 17], the band at 114 cm Ϫ1 can be assigned to the asymmetric <lb/>deformation BrϪSeϪBr vibrations, δ as (BrϪSeϪBr), the bands at <lb/>134 and 148 cm Ϫ1 Ϫ to the symmetric deformation BrϪSeϪBr <lb/>vibrations, δ s (BrϪSeϪBr), and at 246 cm Ϫ1 Ϫ to the asymmetric <lb/>valence SeϪBr vibrations, ν as (SeϪBr). <lb/>X-ray structure analysis <lb/>The determination of the unit cell dimensions and the data collec-<lb/>tion were carried out on a STOE IPDS I diffractometer (graphite <lb/>monochromator). The structure was solved by direct methods and <lb/>refined by SHELXTL [18Ϫ20]. Atomic scattering factors were <lb/>taken from Tables 4.2.6.8 and 6.1.1.4 in ref. [21]. The crystal data <lb/>and the conditions for data collection and refinement are summar-<lb/>ised in Table 1. All non-hydrogen atoms were refined aniso-<lb/>tropically. The hydrogen atoms were placed geometrically and re-<lb/>fined using a riding model with isotropic thermal parameters equal <lb/>to 1.2 or 1.3 U(eq) for the phenyl and ethyl carbon atoms, respec-<lb/>tively, to which they are attached. <lb/>Complete lists of the final atomic coordinates, equivalent isotropic <lb/>displacement parameters, bond lengths and angles, anisotropic <lb/>temperature factors, structure factors, hydrogen coordinates and <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">www.zaac.wiley-vch.de <lb/>© 2008 WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem. 2008, 901Ϫ904 <lb/></note>

			<page>904 <lb/></page>

			<body>least-squares planes have been deposited with the Cambridge Crys-<lb/>tallographic Data Centre under No CCDC-. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] B. Krebs, A. Schäffer, S. Pohl, Z. Naturforsch. Teil B 1984, <lb/>39, 1633. <lb/>[2] S. Hauge, V. Janickis, K. Marøy, Acta Chem. Scand. 1998, <lb/>52, 441. <lb/>[3] S. Hauge, V. Janickis, K. Marøy, Acta Chem. Scand. 1998, <lb/>52, 435. <lb/>[4] B. Krebs, F.-P. Ahlers, E. Lührs, Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem. 1991, <lb/>597, 115. <lb/>[5] S. Hauge, K. Marøy, T. Ødegard, Acta Chem. Scand. Ser. A <lb/>1988, 42, 51. <lb/>[6] S. Hauge, V. Janickis, K. Marøy, Acta Chem Scand. 1998, 52, <lb/>1104. <lb/>[7] B. Krebs, F.-P. Ahlers, Adv. Inorg. Chem. 1990, 35, 235. <lb/>[8] A. Maaninen, T. Chivers, M. Parvez, J. Pietikäinen, R. Lait-<lb/>inen, Inorg. Chem. 1999, 38, 4093. <lb/>[9] V. Janickis, K. W. Törnroos, M. Herberhold, J. Songstad, W. <lb/>Milius, Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem. 2002, 628, 1967. <lb/>[10] V. Janickis, W. Milius, K. W. Törnroos, Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem. <lb/>2005, 631, 882. <lb/>[11] V. Janickis, Chemistry (Vilnius, Lithuania) 2007, 18, 28. <lb/>[12] S. Hauge, V. Janickis, K. Marøy, Acta Chem. Scand. 1999, <lb/>53, 992. <lb/>[13] V. Janickis, J. Songstad, K. W. Törnroos, Chemistry (Vilnius, <lb/>Lithuania) 2001, 12, 93. <lb/>[14] V. Janickis, M. Herberhold, W. Milius, Z. Anorg. Allg. Chem. <lb/>2003, 629, 29. <lb/>[15] V. Janickis, M. Herberhold, M. Necas, W. Milius, Z. Anorg. <lb/>Allg. Chem. 2003, 629, 641. <lb/>[16] S. Hauge, K. Marøy, Acta Chem. Scand. 1996, 50, 1095. <lb/>[17] K. J. Wynne, J. Golen, Inorg. Chem 1974, 13, 185. <lb/>[18] G. M. Sheldrick, SHELXS97. Program for Solution of Crystal <lb/>Structures. University of Göttingen, Germany, 1997. <lb/>[19] G. M. Sheldrick, SHELXL. Program for the Refinement of <lb/>Crystal Structures. University of Göttingen, Germany, 1997. <lb/>[20] G. M. Sheldrick, SHELXTL. V. 5.1. Program Package for the <lb/>Solution and Refinement of Crystal Structures, Göttingen, Ger-<lb/>many. <lb/>[21] International Tables for Crystallography, Vol. C. Kluwer Aca-<lb/>demic Press, Dordrecht 1992. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
