<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Reasons Why Patients Remain Uninsured after Massachusetts&apos; <lb/>Health Care Reform: A Survey of Patients at a Safety-Net Hospital <lb/>Rachel Nardin, MD <lb/>1,3 <lb/>, Assaad Sayah, MD <lb/>2,3 <lb/>, Hermione Lokko, BSc <lb/>3 <lb/>, <lb/>Steffie Woolhandler, MD, MPH <lb/>4 <lb/>, and Danny McCormick, MD, MPH <lb/>1,3 <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Medicine, Cambridge Health Alliance, Cambridge, MA, USA; <lb/>2 Department of Emergency Medicine, Cambridge <lb/>Health Alliance, Cambridge, MA, USA; <lb/>3 Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA; <lb/>4 City University of New York School of Public <lb/>Health, New York, NY, USA. <lb/> BACKGROUND: Following the 2006 Massachusetts <lb/>health care reform, an estimated 316,492 residents <lb/>remain uninsured. However, there have been no published <lb/>studies that examine why Massachusetts residents remain <lb/>uninsured four years into health reform. <lb/>OBJECTIVE: To describe the characteristics of uninsured <lb/>patients seeking acute medical care in Massachusetts after <lb/>implementation of health care reform and reasons for <lb/>lacking insurance. <lb/>DESIGN AND PARTICIPANTS: We performed an <lb/>in-person survey of a convenience sample of patients <lb/>visiting the emergency department of the state&apos;s second <lb/>largest safety net hospital between July 25, 2009 and <lb/>March 20, 2010. We interviewed 431 patients age 18–64, <lb/>189 of whom were uninsured. <lb/>MAIN MEASURES: Demographic and clinical character-<lb/>istics, employment and insurance history, reasons for <lb/>lacking insurance and views of the state&apos;s new &quot; individual <lb/>mandate &quot; . <lb/>KEY RESULTS: The uninsured were largely employed <lb/>(65.9%), but only a quarter (25.1%) of the employed <lb/>uninsured had access to employer-sponsored insurance. <lb/>The majority qualified for subsidized insurance (85.7% <lb/>earned ≤300% of the federal poverty level), yet many <lb/>reported being unable to find affordable insurance <lb/>(32.7%). Over a third (35.2%) were uninsured because <lb/>they had lost insurance due predominantly to job loss or <lb/>policy cancellation. For nearly half of the uninsured <lb/>(48.6%), the individual mandate had motivated them to <lb/>try to find insurance, but they were unable to find <lb/>insurance they could afford. <lb/>CONCLUSIONS: After full implementation of the Massa-<lb/>chusetts health reform, those remaining without insur-<lb/>ance are largely the working poor who do not have access <lb/>to, or cannot afford, either employer sponsored insurance <lb/>or state subsidized insurance. <lb/> KEY WORDS: uninsured; health reform; health policy; safety-net <lb/>institutions; health insurance. <lb/>J Gen Intern Med 27(2):250–6 <lb/>DOI: 10.1007/s11606-011-1868-5 <lb/>© Society of General Internal Medicine 2011 <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>In 2006 Massachusetts enacted a multifaceted health care <lb/>reform law with the explicit goals of reducing the number of <lb/>Massachusetts residents without health insurance, improving <lb/>healthcare affordability, decreasing racial and ethnic disparities, <lb/>and reducing the state&apos;s reliance on safety-net hospitals. <lb/>1,2 <lb/>The Massachusetts plan became the model for the 2010 <lb/>national reform law, the Patient Protection and Affordable <lb/>Care Act (ACA). <lb/>Since enactment of the Massachusetts reform, there have <lb/>been a number of estimates of the effect of the law, which was <lb/>fully implemented by 2008, on the uninsurance rate in <lb/>Massachusetts. The state most often reports data from the <lb/>Massachusetts Division of Health Care Finance and Policy&apos;s <lb/>Health Insurance Survey (HIS) suggesting that the percent-<lb/>age of uninsured non-elderly adults was 3.7% in 2008 and <lb/>3.5% in 2009. <lb/>3 However, a significant amount of data <lb/>suggests that the rate of uninsurance for non-elderly adults <lb/>is higher. The statewide Massachusetts Health Reform Sur-<lb/>vey found uninsurance rates of 4.0% in 2008 and 4.8% in <lb/>2009. <lb/>4 The Massachusetts Department of Revenue (DOR) <lb/>reported that 5% of income tax filers were uninsured for the <lb/>2008 tax year. <lb/>5 The Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance <lb/>System and the U.S. Census Bureau found uninsurance <lb/>rates for non-elderly adults of 5.0% and 7.3% respectively in <lb/>2008 and 6.2% in 2009. <lb/>6–9 Based on current population <lb/>estimates from the Census Bureau, and the uninsurance rate <lb/>estimate from the only peer-reviewed publication on this <lb/>topic, approximately 316,492 non-elderly adults remain <lb/>uninsured after full implementation of the reform. <lb/> 4,10 <lb/></body>

			<front>Received April 7, 2011 <lb/>Revised July 24, 2011 <lb/>Accepted August 25, 2011 <lb/>Published online September 16, 2011 <lb/></front>

			<page>250 <lb/></page>

			<body>Previous studies have assessed the demographics of <lb/>uninsured residents, suggesting that the uninsured in <lb/>Massachusetts post-reform are more likely to be young, <lb/>male, single, minority and either non-citizens or non-<lb/>English speaking. <lb/>4,11,12 However, there have been no <lb/>published studies that examine why Massachusetts resi-<lb/>dents remain uninsured four years into health reform, and <lb/>particularly why the most policy-relevant group of unin-<lb/>sured, i.e. those requiring medical treatment, remain <lb/>uncovered. Such data could improve understanding of <lb/>how patients can still &quot; fall through the cracks &quot; and could <lb/>bolster future efforts to further expand coverage in Massa-<lb/>chusetts and nationally. We surveyed patients treated in <lb/>the emergency department (ED) of a large safety-net <lb/>hospital to understand the characteristics of the uninsured <lb/>and determine their self-reported reasons for remaining <lb/>uninsured post-reform. <lb/>COVERAGE UNDER THE MASSACHUSETTS REFORM <lb/>The Massachusetts reform law aimed to achieve near <lb/>universal coverage through several mechanisms. It increased <lb/>coverage for the poor by expanding Medicaid and also by <lb/>subsidizing private insurance for Massachusetts residents <lb/>with incomes ≤300% of the federal poverty level (FPL), but <lb/>excluded workers who turn down employer sponsored <lb/>insurance (ESI), undocumented immigrants and legal immi-<lb/>grants who have been in the U.S. for less than 5 years. It <lb/>did this by creating Commonwealth Care, a group of publicly <lb/>subsidized, private insurance plans for residents with low <lb/>income who are not eligible for Medicaid. Residents with <lb/>incomes below 150% FPL are eligible for fully subsidized <lb/>insurance that requires no premium payments, whereas <lb/>residents with incomes between 150% and 300% of FPL <lb/>pay a sliding scale premium. The 2006 law created a new <lb/>state agency, which runs an insurance exchange called the <lb/>Connector, which brokers subsidized insurance, as well as <lb/>non-subsidized private plans, to individuals with incomes <lb/>&gt;300% FPL and to small businesses. The Connector is also <lb/>tasked with ensuring that the plans offered through the <lb/>exchange are affordable and provide adequate coverage of <lb/>medical services. <lb/>The reform law also requires employers with more than 10 <lb/>employees to offer ESI and make a &quot; fair and reasonable &quot; <lb/>contribution to the premiums or pay a $295 fine per year per <lb/>employee. The law defines a &quot; fair and reasonable &quot; contribution <lb/>as having at least 25% of full-time employees enrolled in an <lb/>employer-sponsored plan and covering at least 33% of the <lb/>premium cost of the individual health insurance plan offered. <lb/>Lastly, the law mandates that all state residents carry <lb/>health insurance or pay a substantial financial penalty <lb/>enforced through the tax code. <lb/>Before passage of the reform law, many low-income unin-<lb/>sured patients received free or nearly free care at designated <lb/>safety-net hospitals and community health centers; the state-<lb/>administered uncompensated care pool reimbursed providers <lb/>for this care. After passage of the reform law, a limited version <lb/>of this program called the health safety net (HSN) continues to <lb/>reimburse providers for the costs of medical care for some of <lb/>the low-income individuals who remain uninsured. According <lb/>to the state, HSN is not health insurance and does not meet <lb/>the individual mandate requirement. <lb/>13 <lb/>METHODS <lb/>Study Design and Setting <lb/>We performed an in-person survey of a convenience sample of <lb/>uninsured patients visiting the ED of the state&apos;s second largest <lb/>safety net hospital, located in Cambridge, Massachusetts. The <lb/>ED receives approximately 33,000 visits annually. Trained <lb/>research assistants conducted the study during daytime shifts <lb/>(usually between 9 am and 5 pm), between July 25, 2009 and <lb/>March 20, 2010. The Cambridge Health Alliance Institutional <lb/>Review Board approved the study protocol. <lb/>The survey included patients who were uninsured; for <lb/>comparison, we also included patients with one of several <lb/>categories of insurance. The two categories of uninsured <lb/>patients surveyed were those who were eligible to have their <lb/>care reimbursed though the state&apos;s Health Safety-Net (HSN) <lb/>fund (income &lt;400% FPL and ineligible for Commonwealth <lb/>Care or Medicaid) and those who were entirely self-pay. The <lb/>insured patients had one of three types of coverage: private <lb/>(commercial) insurance and the two types of insurance made <lb/>available to low-income residents under Massachusetts health <lb/>reform, Medicaid and Commonwealth Care. Insurance status <lb/>was determined by patient report and verified by electronic <lb/>querying of a continuously updated on-line insurance status <lb/>database maintained by a consortium of all Massachusetts <lb/>health insurers, including public payers. <lb/>14 This database <lb/>allows real-time determination of insurance status, which is <lb/>likely to be highly accurate since this information is provided <lb/>by the insurers themselves. When patients&apos; report of insurance <lb/>status differed from that listed in the electronic database, we <lb/>used the database results in determining insurance status. <lb/>Subjects <lb/>We included all patients aged 18–64 years, the age range <lb/>directly affected by the Massachusetts health reform law. We <lb/>excluded subjects who had altered mental status or inability to <lb/>speak according to the assessment of the treating physician. <lb/>We also excluded patients with the highest severity of illness at <lb/>presentation, defined as those with an Emergency Severity <lb/>Index Score of 1. This is a widely used and validated ED triage <lb/>algorithm that stratifies patients into five groups from 1 (most <lb/>urgent) to 5 (least urgent) at the time of initial emergency <lb/>department triage. <lb/>15 We also excluded patients whose primary <lb/>language was other than one of the four languages in which <lb/>the survey was conducted (English, Spanish, Portuguese or <lb/>Haitian Creole). <lb/>Study Recruitment and Survey Procedure <lb/>Research assistants stationed in the ED reviewed the demo-<lb/>graphic and insurance information of all patients presenting <lb/></body>

			<page>251 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Nardin et al.: Reasons for Remaining Uninsured in MA <lb/>JGIM <lb/></note>

			<body>for care during a shift. For patients meeting study entry <lb/>criteria, the research assistant approached the patient to <lb/>invite participation, obtain informed consent and verbally <lb/>administer the survey. For patients whose primary language <lb/>was Spanish, Portuguese or Haitian Creole, an interpreter was <lb/>used for study consent and survey administration. <lb/>Survey Development <lb/>We developed a survey instrument to obtain data on patient <lb/>age, race/ethnicity, income, primary language spoken at <lb/>home, country of origin, employment status, education level, <lb/>self-rated health, number of chronic medical conditions and <lb/>the emergency severity index. We also asked about health <lb/>insurance history, reasons for lacking insurance and the <lb/>effects of the individual mandate. Trained medical interpreters <lb/>translated the survey instrument into Spanish, Portuguese <lb/>and Haitian Creole. We did not ask patients about their legal <lb/>immigration status, to address the human subjects concern <lb/>that such questions might frighten sick patients or discourage <lb/>them from seeking emergency care in the future. We field-tested <lb/>the survey instrument and study recruitment procedures <lb/>on 30 ED patients and made iterative refinements to the <lb/>66-item survey. <lb/>Statistical Analysis <lb/>We used Chi square tests for comparisons between groups; a <lb/>p-value of ≤0.05 was considered to be statistically significant. <lb/>Because we found few demographic differences between the <lb/>uninsured in our sample who were self-pay and who had HSN, <lb/>most analyses are presented for the group of uninsured as a <lb/>whole. All analyses were performed using SAS software version <lb/>9.2 (SAS Institute, Cary, North Carolina). <lb/> RESULTS <lb/>We interviewed 431 out of 549 patients invited to participate in <lb/>the study (response rate 78.4%). There were no statistically <lb/>significant differences between study subjects and those <lb/>declining to participate with regard to age or Emergency <lb/>Severity Index. 189 uninsured patients participated in the <lb/>study, 84 of whom were self-pay and 105 of whom had HSN. <lb/>Table 1 shows the characteristics of the study population. Most <lb/>uninsured patients (91.0%) had low incomes, earning ≤300% of <lb/>the FPL. The uninsured study population was racially and <lb/>ethnically diverse (26.8% white, 22.0% black/non-Hispanic and <lb/>43.5% Hispanic), but nearly three quarters (74.1%) preferred to <lb/>conduct the survey in English. About one quarter (26.1%) reported <lb/>their health as fair or poor and over a third (35%) reported having <lb/>at least one chronic medical condition. Nearly 40% of the <lb/>uninsured sample had at least some college education. There were <lb/>no differences between HSN and self-pay uninsured patients <lb/>except that HSN patients were more likely to be Hispanic (56.7% <lb/>vs. 28.2%) and foreign-born (73.5% vs. 41.8%), and self-pay <lb/>patients were more likely to be white (35.9% vs. 18.9%) and <lb/>English speaking (90.5% vs. 61.0%). The demographics of the <lb/>uninsured population were similar to those of patients with <lb/>Commonwealth Care or Medicaid, although the uninsured were <lb/>more likely to be foreign born. This was in contrast to the privately <lb/>insured, who were more likely to be white, high income, English-<lb/>speaking, employed and have higher self-rated health status and <lb/>educational attainment. <lb/>Nearly two thirds (65.9%) of uninsured patients were currently <lb/>employed with the majority of these (67.0%) employed for longer <lb/>than one year (Table 2). Of those who were employed, about half <lb/>(48.2%) worked part-time and only 24.1% were self-employed. <lb/>Half (51.6%) of those working for an employer worked for one <lb/>with more than 10 employees, the firm size above which the <lb/>Massachusetts reform law mandates that employers offer health <lb/>insurance or pay a fine. Approximately half (51.1%) of those <lb/>working for an employer reported that they had not been offered <lb/>employer-sponsored insurance. Patients who worked at firms with <lb/>10 or fewer employees were much less likely to have been offered <lb/>ESI (20.0% vs. 77.8% for employees of larger firms, p=0.0005), as <lb/>were patients who worked at a job for less than one year (39.0% vs. <lb/>63.6% for longer term employees, p=0.0079). The uninsured were <lb/>as likely to be employed (65.9%) as those with private insurance <lb/>(72.3%) or Commonwealth Care (66.1%), and much more likely to <lb/>be employed than those with Medicaid (27.3%). The uninsured <lb/>were less likely than the privately insured, but just as likely as <lb/>those with Commonwealth Care or Medicaid, to work for an <lb/>employer who offered ESI. <lb/>Figure 1 shows the relationship between employment status, <lb/>income level and access to ESI for our uninsured sample. <lb/>One-third (34.1%) of the sample was unemployed and thus <lb/>did not have access to ESI; 86.4% of these had incomes <lb/>≤300% of the FPL, a level that would qualify eligible <lb/>residents for subsidized insurance. Another 15% of the <lb/>sample was self employed and thus lacked access to ESI; <lb/>90% of these had incomes ≤300% of the FPL. An additional <lb/>24% worked for an employer that did not offer insurance <lb/>and 93% of these had incomes ≤300% of the FPL. Lastly, 25% of <lb/>the sample worked for an employer that offered insurance. Nearly <lb/>three-quarters of these patients earned ≤300% of the FPL; these <lb/>individuals would qualify for state-subsidized insurance only if <lb/>their employer&apos;s plan did not cover at least 20% of the annual <lb/>family premium or 33% of the annual individual premium. <lb/>Nearly a quarter of the uninsured (23.7%) had never had <lb/>insurance and an additional 57.2% had been uninsured for at <lb/>least a year. Compared with patients who were uninsured for <lb/>less than a year, long-term (≥ 1 year) uninsured patients were <lb/>more likely to be non-white and non-English speaking, but were <lb/>similar in age and health status, and were just as likely to be <lb/>employed. <lb/>Examining patients&apos; self-reported reasons for remaining <lb/>uninsured, we found that a third (32.7%) reported being <lb/>uninsured because they could not find affordable insurance. <lb/>Another third (35.2%) reported having lost their insurance. Of <lb/>these, nearly half had lost insurance due to job loss (46.3%), but <lb/>an additional third had had their insurance cancelled without <lb/>notice or because of lapsed paperwork (33.3%). Additional <lb/>reasons for loss of insurance included loss of spouse&apos;s insurance <lb/>(7.4%), transition between jobs (5.6%), aging out of parents&apos; <lb/>insurance (5.6%) and need to cancel insurance due to cost <lb/>(1.9%). Additional reasons why patients remained uninsured <lb/>included their belief that they did not require insurance because <lb/>of HSN coverage (12.4%), their fear of giving personal informa-<lb/>tion (8.0%), the fact that they were denied insurance for which <lb/></body>

			<page>252 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Nardin et al.: Reasons for Remaining Uninsured in MA <lb/> JGIM <lb/></note>

			<body>they had applied (6.2%) and their belief that they did not need <lb/>insurance (5.6%). <lb/>Lastly, we examined the effect of the individual mandate on <lb/>the uninsured in Massachusetts (Table 3). Over two-thirds of <lb/>the uninsured (65.7%) were aware of the legal requirement <lb/>that they carry health insurance; this was similar to patients <lb/>with Medicaid (75.9%), but significantly lower than those with <lb/>Commonwealth Care (90.5%) or private insurance (90.5%). <lb/>For nearly half of the uninsured (48.6%), the mandate had <lb/>motivated them to try to find insurance, but they had been <lb/>unable to find insurance they could afford (88.4% of these <lb/>paid no tax penalty). For an additional 38.5%, the mandate <lb/>had had no effect on their decision to carry health insurance. <lb/>Nearly half of uninsured patients (47.8%) believed the health <lb/>care reform law had been bad for Massachusetts&apos; residents; <lb/>this was significantly higher than for patients with any type <lb/>of insurance. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>This survey of uninsured patients seen in a major safety net <lb/>hospital ED describes some reasons why residents remain <lb/>uninsured in Massachusetts four years after passage of health <lb/>reform. Lack of health insurance was rarely voluntary. Despite a <lb/>third of patients reporting at least one chronic medical condition, <lb/>80.9% had been uninsured for more than a year. The uninsured <lb/>were mostly working poor, but only 25% had access to ESI. The <lb/>vast majority of patients reported being uninsured because of a <lb/>loss of insurance (predominantly from job loss or policy cancel-<lb/>lation) or because insurance was unaffordable. Only 5.6% of our <lb/>sample said they were uninsured because they didn&apos;t think they <lb/>needed insurance, suggesting few &quot; free riders. &quot; <lb/>We found that half of the uninsured worked for employers <lb/>other than themselves, but only half of these worked for an <lb/>employer who offered insurance. Of the uninsured that worked <lb/>Table 1. Demographic and Health Characteristics of Study Patients <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>Insurance Status <lb/>Uninsured <lb/>Insured <lb/>p-value <lb/>(n=189) <lb/>% <lb/>Commonwealth Care <lb/>(n=66) <lb/>% <lb/>Medicaid <lb/>(n=91) <lb/>% <lb/>Private <lb/>(n=86) <lb/>% <lb/>Age (years) <lb/>0.25 <lb/>18–30 <lb/>42.9 <lb/>29.5 <lb/>38.6 <lb/>41.0 <lb/>31–50 <lb/>43.5 <lb/>45.9 <lb/>37.5 <lb/>41.0 <lb/>51–64 <lb/>13.6 <lb/>24.6 <lb/>23.9 <lb/>18.1 <lb/>Race/Ethnicity <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>White/Non-Hispanic <lb/>26.8 <lb/>49.2 <lb/>38.4 <lb/>61.3 <lb/>Black/Non-Hispanic <lb/>22.0 <lb/>18.0 <lb/>33.7 <lb/>13.8 <lb/>Hispanic <lb/>43.5 <lb/>26.2 <lb/>17.4 <lb/>12.5 <lb/>Other <lb/>7.7 <lb/>6.6 <lb/>10.5 <lb/>12.5 <lb/>Income (as % FPL) <lb/>* <lb/>0–150% <lb/>68.2 <lb/>60.6 <lb/>76.1 <lb/>23.0 <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>151–300% <lb/>22.8 <lb/>22.7 <lb/>16.3 <lb/>13.8 <lb/>&gt;300% <lb/>9.0 <lb/>16.7 <lb/>7.6 <lb/>63.2 <lb/>Country of Origin <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>US Born <lb/>40.7 <lb/>74.5 <lb/>84.0 <lb/>81.9 <lb/>Foreign Born <lb/>59.3 <lb/>25.5 <lb/>16.0 <lb/>18.1 <lb/>Language <lb/>English <lb/>74.1 <lb/>92.4 <lb/>96.7 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>Portuguese <lb/>19.6 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>Spanish <lb/>4.2 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>Haitian-Creole <lb/>2.1 <lb/>4.6 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>Education Level <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>&lt;High School <lb/>16.5 <lb/>11.3 <lb/>24.1 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>High School <lb/>43.8 <lb/>33.9 <lb/>28.7 <lb/>18.1 <lb/>Some College or Graduate School <lb/>39.8 <lb/>54.8 <lb/>47.1 <lb/>79.5 <lb/>Self-rated Health <lb/>&lt;0.005 <lb/>Excellent/Very Good <lb/>39.1 <lb/>36.9 <lb/>33.7 <lb/>61.2 <lb/>Good <lb/>34.8 <lb/>33.9 <lb/>32.6 <lb/>24.7 <lb/>Fair or Poor <lb/>26.1 <lb/>29.2 <lb/>33.7 <lb/>14.1 <lb/>Self-reported Chronic Medical Conditions <lb/> † <lb/>None <lb/>65.1 <lb/>65.6 <lb/>56.0 <lb/>62.4 <lb/>0.49 <lb/>One or more <lb/>35.0 <lb/>34.4 <lb/>44.0 <lb/>37.7 <lb/>Emergency Severity Index <lb/> ‡ <lb/>0.14 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>7.7 <lb/>6.1 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>4.8 <lb/>3 <lb/>34.8 <lb/>53.0 <lb/>46.7 <lb/>47.6 <lb/>4 <lb/>43.7 <lb/>31.8 <lb/>38.0 <lb/>36.9 <lb/>5 <lb/>13.8 <lb/>9.1 <lb/>14.1 <lb/>10.7 <lb/>* FPL=Federal Poverty Level <lb/> † Includes the following conditions: heart disease, cancer, arthritis, hypertension, diabetes, asthma and obesity <lb/> ‡ The Emergency Severity Index is a validated measure of severity of illness at the time of presentation to an emergency department and is used to stratify <lb/>patients into 5 groups (Level 1=most severe; Level 5=least severe) for triage priority <lb/></body>

			<page>253 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Nardin et al.: Reasons for Remaining Uninsured in MA <lb/> JGIM <lb/></note>

			<body>for an employer, half worked for a small firm (≤ 10 employees), <lb/>exempt from the requirement to offer insurance. These findings <lb/>imply that the exemption for small firms may be making ESI <lb/>unavailable to those least able to find alternative sources of <lb/>coverage. In addition, the current penalty for larger firms not <lb/>offering ESI—$295 per full time employee—may be too low to <lb/>encourage employer participation and thus ESI availability. <lb/>The finding that some of the working uninsured had access to <lb/>ESI but declined it suggests that for many, the available ESI is <lb/>out of reach financially. This is not surprising, since the state <lb/>requires that an employer cover only 20% of an annual family <lb/>premium or 33% of an annual individual premium. Recent data <lb/>suggest that annual increases in medical insurance costs are <lb/>being increasingly shifted from employers to their employees <lb/>with ESI. <lb/>16 This could lead to even lower uptake rates for ESI in <lb/>the future. <lb/>Irrespective of employment status, more than 85% of this <lb/>uninsured sample had incomes that were low enough that they <lb/>should have qualified for state subsidized insurance (either <lb/>Medicaid or Commonwealth Care). Why, then, were these <lb/>patients uninsured? Nearly a third of our cohort (29.9%) <lb/>reported being uninsured because they could not afford insur-<lb/>ance, suggesting that for some working poor, even heavily <lb/>subsidized insurance premiums may be unaffordable. Although <lb/>the Connector is charged with ensuring that adequate and <lb/>affordable insurance options are available, the rising cost of <lb/>healthcare has made this difficult. Nearly three-quarters of HSN <lb/>patients were foreign-born, suggesting that a high proportion of <lb/>these patients may be ineligible for state subsidized insurance <lb/>on the basis of their legal immigration status. <lb/>Surprisingly, over a third of the sample reported &quot; loss of <lb/>insurance &quot; as the reason for being uninsured at the time of the <lb/>Table 2. Employment Status and Characteristics of Study Patients <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>Insurance Status <lb/>Uninsured <lb/>Insured <lb/>% <lb/>Commonwealth Care <lb/>% <lb/>Medicaid <lb/>% <lb/>Private <lb/>% <lb/>p value <lb/>Employment Status (n) <lb/>(179) <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>Employed <lb/>65.9 <lb/>66.1 <lb/>27.3 <lb/>72.3 <lb/>Unemployed <lb/>34.1 <lb/>33.9 <lb/>72.7 <lb/>27.7 <lb/>Among Employed (n) <lb/>(118) <lb/>(41) <lb/>(24) <lb/>(60) <lb/>Number of Jobs <lb/>0.14 <lb/>1 <lb/>88.0 <lb/>87.8 <lb/>95.8 <lb/>78.3 <lb/>2 or more <lb/>12.0 <lb/>12.2 <lb/>4.2 <lb/>21.7 <lb/>Duration of current employment <lb/>0.30 <lb/>1 year or less <lb/>33.0 <lb/>27.5 <lb/>37.5 <lb/>19.0 <lb/>2–5 years <lb/>45.0 <lb/>42.5 <lb/>45.8 <lb/>44.8 <lb/>More than 5 years <lb/>22.0 <lb/>30.0 <lb/>16.7 <lb/>36.2 <lb/>Hours per week worked <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>&lt;40 <lb/>48.2 <lb/>52.9 <lb/>78.3 <lb/>13.3 <lb/>40 <lb/>27.7 <lb/>20.6 <lb/>17.4 <lb/>40.0 <lb/>&gt;40 <lb/>24.1 <lb/>26.5 <lb/>4.4 <lb/>46.7 <lb/>Type of Employment <lb/>0.02 <lb/>Self-Employed <lb/>24.1 <lb/>20.5 <lb/>20.8 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>Employed by someone else <lb/>75.9 <lb/>79.5 <lb/>79.2 <lb/>95.0 <lb/>Size of Employer <lb/>0.0002 <lb/>≤10 employees <lb/>48.4 <lb/>47.8 <lb/>27.3 <lb/>9.3 <lb/>&gt;10 employees <lb/>51.6 <lb/>52.2 <lb/>72.7 <lb/>90.7 <lb/>Employer Offers Insurance <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>Yes <lb/>51.1 <lb/>58.6 <lb/>62.5 <lb/>93.0 <lb/>No <lb/>48.9 <lb/>41.4 <lb/>37.5 <lb/>7.0 <lb/>189 Uninsured <lb/>Patients <lb/>118 (65.9%) <lb/>Employed <lb/>85.3% ≤300% FPL <lb/>61 (34.1%) <lb/>Unemployed <lb/>86.4% ≤ 300% FPL <lb/>10 (5.3%) Missing data on <lb/>employment status <lb/>88 (49.2%) <lb/>Work for employer <lb/>83.6% ≤300% FPL <lb/>28 (15.6%) <lb/>Self-employed <lb/>90.0% ≤300% FPL <lb/>45 (25.1%) <lb/>Employer offers insurance <lb/>73.1% ≤300% FPL <lb/>43 (24%) <lb/>Employer does not offer <lb/>insurance <lb/>93.1 % ≤300% FPL <lb/>Figure 1. Employment status, access to employer sponsored <lb/>insurance and income (percent ≤300% of the federal poverty level <lb/>[FPL]) of study patients. The percent ≤300% of FPL is given only for <lb/>those patients providing income information. <lb/></body>

			<page>254 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Nardin et al.: Reasons for Remaining Uninsured in MA <lb/>JGIM <lb/></note>

			<body>survey. For subsidized insurance plans, yearly re-enrollment is <lb/>required to maintain coverage and the state mails re-enrollment <lb/>forms to enrollees yearly. However, if completed forms are not <lb/>received by the state within 10 days, the policy is terminated. <lb/>For low-income residents, who often experience substantial <lb/>housing instability in the expensive Boston area, these stringent <lb/>re-enrollment policies could contribute to unnecessary loss of <lb/>insurance for eligible residents. In addition, even a small <lb/>increase in income may disqualify residents for income-based <lb/>subsidized insurance. <lb/>It is also possible that patients who may have been eligible for <lb/>subsidized insurance by income criteria may have been ineligible <lb/>due to immigration status requirements. A limitation of our study <lb/>is that we did not ask about citizenship or legal status directly <lb/>(due to concerns about human subject protections) and thus <lb/>cannot determine which respondents were uninsured because of <lb/>ineligibility on the basis of legal status. While we found that <lb/>59.3% of the total uninsured patients in our sample were born <lb/>outside the United States, three-quarters of our sample answered <lb/>the survey in English, suggesting that this is not predominantly a <lb/>population of recent immigrants. <lb/>We found significant demographic differences between the <lb/>uninsured and the privately insured patients in our sample; <lb/>namely, the uninsured were more likely to be non-white, low <lb/>income, non-English speaking and have lower educational <lb/>attainment. However, with the exception of more foreign-born <lb/>patients among the uninsured, our uninsured patients resem-<lb/>bled those insured by Medicaid and Commonwealth Care, the <lb/>major forms of insurance gained under the reform. This <lb/>suggests that at least in part, the reform failed to fully reach <lb/>the demographic groups it targeted and emphasizes the fragility <lb/>of a system requiring voluntary uptake, periodic renewal, <lb/>dependence on employment and cost-sharing. <lb/>Two-thirds of uninsured patients in our sample (65.7%) <lb/>were aware of the reform law&apos;s individual mandate. Half of <lb/>our sample (48.6%) had responded to the mandate by <lb/>trying to get insurance, but were unable to find insurance <lb/>they could afford. This may explain why only 31.5% of our <lb/>uninsured sample thought the reform had been good for <lb/>Massachusetts, compared to the support of 67% reported <lb/>for unselected nonelderly adults surveyed state-wide, which <lb/>is more similar to the support for the reform we found <lb/>among our privately insured patients (53.6%). <lb/>4 <lb/>The major limitation of our study is that the sample is <lb/>drawn from a single safety-net ED. The uninsured are more <lb/>likely to seek care in safety-net institutions, so this strategy <lb/>allowed us to locate the uninsured efficiently, to obtain a high <lb/>response rate, and to focus our investigation on persons <lb/>actually requiring medical care. Moreover, our methods <lb/>allowed us access to members of marginalized groups such <lb/>as the homeless, the marginally housed, undocumented <lb/>immigrants and linguistic minorities – groups that may be <lb/>both unable to obtain health coverage and difficult to sample <lb/>in phone, mail, and even neighborhood-based surveys. <lb/>Comparison to neighborhood-based American Community <lb/>Survey data on the uninsured in Massachusetts suggests <lb/>that our ED-based sample may over-represent non-white and <lb/>very poor (&lt;150% FPL) individuals, but in terms of age, <lb/>education level and employment status, does not differ <lb/>significantly from the state&apos;s uninsured. <lb/>17 <lb/>Another limitation of our study is that it was conducted at <lb/>a single point in time. This limits our ability to understand <lb/>the temporal changes in factors contributing to uninsurance, <lb/>something that is also important when setting policy <lb/>designed to promote continuous coverage. <lb/>Our findings suggest that several modifications of health <lb/>care reform in Massachusetts could further expand insur-<lb/>ance coverage. Employer sponsored coverage could be ex-<lb/>panded by increasing incentives for more employers to offer <lb/>insurance to employees and by increasing the proportion of <lb/>premiums employers pay for employees, which would in-<lb/>crease the proportion of low-income employees who could <lb/>afford their employer-sponsored insurance. Our study sug-<lb/>gests that the state could reexamine the affordability guide-<lb/>lines for state subsidized insurance; reducing premium cost <lb/>sharing for low-income residents would likely increase the <lb/>proportion of eligible residents actually able to afford subsi-<lb/>dized insurance. Reducing the stringency of the enrollment <lb/>process could also increase the chances that low-income <lb/>residents will obtain—and retain—insurance. Our study <lb/>illustrates some of the ways in which a piecemeal insurance <lb/>coverage system leads to persistent uninsurance. An alter-<lb/>Table 3. Awareness and Effects of Massachusetts&apos; &quot; Individual Mandate &quot; Among Study Patients <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>Insurance Status <lb/>Uninsured <lb/>Insured <lb/>p value <lb/>Common-wealth Care <lb/>Medicaid <lb/>Private <lb/>Aware of the &quot; individual mandate &quot; (n) <lb/>(175) <lb/>(63) <lb/>(87) <lb/>(84) <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>Yes <lb/>65.7 <lb/>90.5 <lb/>75.9 <lb/>90.5 <lb/>No <lb/>34.3 <lb/>9.5 <lb/>24.1 <lb/>9.5 <lb/>Effect of &quot; individual mandate &quot; on respondent&apos;s coverage (n) <lb/>(109) <lb/>(55) <lb/>(65) <lb/>(76) <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/> &quot; Made me get coverage &quot; <lb/>9.2 <lb/>34.6 <lb/>15.4 <lb/>11.8 <lb/> &quot; Made me try to get coverage but there wasn&apos;t any coverage <lb/>I could afford &quot; <lb/>48.6 <lb/>5.5 <lb/>6.2 <lb/>2.6 <lb/> &quot; It did not influence my decision about getting coverage &quot; <lb/>38.5 <lb/>52.7 <lb/>78.5 <lb/>85.5 <lb/>Other <lb/>3.7 <lb/>7.3 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>Effect of Massachusetts health care reform law on Massachusetts <lb/>Residents (n) <lb/>(92) <lb/>(50) <lb/>(58) <lb/>(69) <lb/>0.02 <lb/>Good <lb/>31.5 <lb/>48.0 <lb/>43.1 <lb/>53.6 <lb/>Bad <lb/>47.8 <lb/>30.0 <lb/>25.9 <lb/>26.1 <lb/>Neither good nor bad <lb/>20.7 <lb/>22.0 <lb/>31.0 <lb/>20.3 <lb/></body>

			<page>255 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Nardin et al.: Reasons for Remaining Uninsured in MA <lb/>JGIM <lb/></note>

			<body>native for Massachusetts would be to adopt a more compre-<lb/>hensive reform guaranteeing coverage to all residents without <lb/>eligibility restrictions. <lb/>Although many thought the Massachusetts health reform <lb/>would eliminate or substantially reduce the need for a safety <lb/>net by providing universal insurance that could be used with <lb/>any provider, our study shows that under the current reform, <lb/>patients continue to fall through the cracks of the insurance <lb/>system. Until the barriers to universal coverage that we <lb/>identify here are addressed, safety-net hospitals will remain <lb/>necessary in Massachusetts to provide care for those left <lb/>uninsured who can be turned away from non-safety-net <lb/>institutions. Safety-net institutions will continue to be an <lb/>important source of care for undocumented immigrants who <lb/>are explicitly left out of health care reform. <lb/>Whether such modifications are financially or politically <lb/>feasible in the current political and fiscal climate is debat-<lb/>able. However, because the uninsured experience both worse <lb/>health outcomes across a broad range of medical conditions <lb/>as well as higher mortality, <lb/>18,19 preventing residents from <lb/>falling through the cracks of the reformed health coverage <lb/>system should be a high priority. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments: No funding was received for this study. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Conflict of Interest: None disclosed. <lb/></div>

			<front>Corresponding Author: Rachel Nardin, MD; Department of <lb/>Medicine, Cambridge Health Alliance, 1493 Cambridge St; Macht <lb/>420, Cambridge, MA 02139, USA (e-mail: rnardin@challiance.org). <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Chapter 58: An Act Providing Access to Affordable, Quality, Accountable <lb/>Health Care. Available at: http://www.mass.gov/legis/laws/seslaw06/ <lb/>sl060058.htm. Accessed August 24, 2011. <lb/>2. Holahan J, Blumberg L. Massachusetts health care reform: a look at the <lb/>issues. Health Aff. 2006;25:w432–43. <lb/>3. Long S, Lokendra P, Stockley K. Health insurance coverage in <lb/>Massachusetts: Results from the 2008 and 2009 Massachusetts <lb/>Health Insurance Surveys. Massachusetts Department of Health <lb/>Care Financing and Policy; October, 2009. Available at: http:// <lb/>www.mass.gov/?pageID=eohhs2terminal&amp;L=4&amp;L0=Home&amp;L1= <lb/>Researcher&amp;L2=Insurance±(including±MassHealth)&amp;L3=Health± <lb/>Insurance±Surveys&amp;sid=Eeohhs2&amp;b=terminalcontent&amp;f=dhcfp_ <lb/>researcher_resident_survey&amp;csid=Eeohhs2. Accessed August 24, 2011. <lb/>4. Long S, Stockley K. Sustaining health reform in a recession: an update <lb/>on Massachusetts as of Fall 2009. Health Aff. 2010;29:1234–41. <lb/>5. Data on the Individual Mandate. Massachusetts Health Connector and <lb/>Department of Revenue. Available at: http://www.mass.gov/Ador/docs/ <lb/>dor/News/PressReleases/2010/2008_final_report.pdf. Accessed August <lb/>24, 2011. <lb/>6. Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System. National Center for Chronic <lb/>Disease Prevention and Health Promotion; 2009. Available at: http://pps. <lb/>nccd.cdc.gov/brfss/display.asp?cat=HC&amp;yr=2009&amp;qkey=880&amp;state=MA. <lb/>Accessed August 24, 2011. <lb/>7. Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System. National Center for Chronic <lb/>Disease Prevention and Health Promotion; 2010. Available at: http://apps. <lb/>nccd.cdc.gov/BRFSS/display.asp?cat=HC&amp;yr=2010&amp;qkey=880&amp;state= <lb/>MA. Accessed August 24, 2011. <lb/>8. Current Population Survey, 2009. Table HI06. Health Insurance Coverage <lb/>Status by State for All People: 2008. U.S. Census Bureau. Available at: <lb/>http://www.census.gov/hhes/www/cpstables/032009/health/h05_000. <lb/>htm. Accessed August 24, 2011. <lb/>9. Current Population Survey, 2010. Table HI06. Health Insurance Coverage <lb/>Status by State for All People: 2009. U.S. Census Bureau. Available at: <lb/>http://www.census.gov/hhes/www/cpstables/032010/health/h05_000. <lb/>htm. Accessed August 24, 2011. <lb/>10. Massachusetts QuickFacts from the US Census Bureau. U.S. Census <lb/>Bureau; 2009. Available at: http://quickfacts.census.gov/qfd/states/ <lb/>25000.html. Accessed August 24, 2011. <lb/>11. Long S, Phadera L, Lynch V. Massachusetts Health Reform in 2008: <lb/>Who are the remaining uninsured adults? Robert Wood Johnson <lb/>Foundation; August 2010. Available at: http://www.rwjf.org/files/ <lb/>research/67248.MassReform2008UninsuredBrief.pdf. Accessed August <lb/>24, 2011. <lb/>12. Long S, Stockley K. An Update on Insurance Coverage and Support for <lb/>Reform as of Fall 2008. Urban Institute; September 2009. Available at: <lb/>http://www.urban.org/uploadedpdf/411958_mass_health_reform.pdf. <lb/>Accessed August 24, 2011. <lb/>13. Health safety net provider FAQ: Frequently asked questions about <lb/>Health Safety Net (HSN) regulations, eligibility and billing. Common-<lb/>wealth of Massachusetts, Executive Office of Health and Human <lb/>Services, Division of Health Care Finance and Policy; January 5, 2009. <lb/>Available at: http://www.mass.gov/Eeohhs2/docs/dhcfp/p/hsn/provi-<lb/>der_faq_hsn.pdf. Accessed August 24, 2011. <lb/>14. New England Healthcare Exchange Network. Available at: http://www. <lb/>nehen.net/. Accessed August 24, 2011. <lb/>15. Gilboy N, Tanabe P, Travers D, Rosenau A, Eitel D. Emergency severity <lb/>index, Version 4: Implementation Handbook. Rockville, MD: Agency for <lb/>Healthcare Research and Quality; May 2005. AHRQ Publication No. 05-<lb/>0046-2. Available at: http://www.ahrq.gov/research/esi/. Accessed <lb/>August 24, 2011. <lb/>16. Analysis in brief: employers and Massachusetts health reform. Depart-<lb/>ment of Health Care Finance and Policy; 2009. Available at: http://www. <lb/>mass.gov/Eeohhs2/docs/dhcfp/r/pubs/10/mes_aib_2009.pdf. <lb/>Accessed August 24, 2011. <lb/>17. S2702. Selected Characteristics of the Uninsured in the United States: <lb/>Massachusetts. US Census Bureau; 2009. Available at: http://factfinder. <lb/>census.gov/servlet/STTable?_bm=y&amp;-state=st&amp;-context=st&amp;-qr_ <lb/>name=ACS_2009_1YR_G00_S2702&amp;-ds_name=ACS_2009_1YR_G00_ <lb/>&amp;-tree_id=309&amp;-_caller=geoselect&amp;-geo_id=04000US25&amp;-format=&amp;-_ <lb/>lang=en. Accessed August 24, 2011. <lb/>18. Care Without Coverage, Too Little, Too Late. Washington, DC: Institute of <lb/>Medicine; 2002|. <lb/>19. Wilper A, Woolhandler S, Lasser K, McCormick D, Bor D, Himmelstein <lb/>D. Health insurance and mortality in US adults. Am J Public Health. <lb/>2009;99:2289–95. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>256 <lb/></page>

			<titlePage>Nardin et al.: Reasons for Remaining Uninsured in MA <lb/>JGIM </titlePage>


	</text>
</tei>
