<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Simulating beach and dune evolution at <lb/>decadal to centennial scale under rising sea <lb/>levels <lb/>Caroline Hallin ID *, Magnus Larson, Hans Hanson <lb/>Department of Water Resources Engineering, Lund University, Lund, Sweden <lb/>* caroline.hallin@tvrl.lth.se <lb/>Abstract <lb/>A numerical model for simulating beach-dune evolution at decadal to centennial time scales <lb/>is developed. The work builds on an existing semi-empirical cross-shore model, the CS-<lb/>model, to which the effect of sea level rise is added and the routines for aeolian transport and <lb/>morphological dune evolution are improved. The model development is based on established <lb/>conceptual models from the literature, which are translated into mathematical formulations <lb/>and solved numerically. The capability of the proposed model is demonstrated through a <lb/>case study at A ¨ngelholm Beach, Sweden. The model is calibrated and validated against a <lb/>seven-year long data set on morphological evolution and sediment grain-size samples. <lb/>Beach and dune evolution is then simulated from 2018 to 2100 for a range of sea level rise <lb/>scenarios. The model results are promising, and suggest that the model has potential to be <lb/>used for long-term assessment of climate change impact on beaches and dunes. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Coastal dunes play an important role to protect against flooding and beach erosion, while pro-<lb/>viding nature and recreation values [1,2]. Therefore, both natural and artificial dunes are <lb/>becoming increasingly popular flood protection methods in many coastal areas [3,4]. Mean-<lb/>while, rising sea levels increase the probability of flooding as well as the pressure on beaches <lb/>and dunes [5,6]. The capability to predict future beach and dune evolution is thus of major <lb/>importance for flood risk assessment and design of coastal protection. Several models have <lb/>been developed to separately estimate dune erosion during storms [7-9], dune build-up due to <lb/>aeolian transport [10-12], and long-term coastline evolution [13]. However, models for the <lb/>evolution of the beach and dune system at decadal time scales, which are of particular interest <lb/>in coastal management [14], require a coupling between constructive and destructive near-<lb/>shore, beach, and dune processes [15]. In recent years, there has been advances in the coupling <lb/>of cross-shore and longshore transport processes at decadal time scales, e.g., the CoSMoS--<lb/>COAST model [16] and the LX-model [17]; but, these models do not include dune processes. <lb/>To improve the understanding of how processes in the land-sea interface control the foredune <lb/>evolution, Cohn et al [18] combined three process-based models-X-BEACH [8], CDM [19], <lb/></body>

			<front>PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/>1 / 30 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Hallin C, Larson M, Hanson H (2019) <lb/>Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to <lb/>centennial scale under rising sea levels. PLoS ONE <lb/>14(4): e0215651. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0215651 <lb/>Editor: João Miguel Dias, Universidade de Aveiro, <lb/>PORTUGAL <lb/>Received: October 10, 2018 <lb/>Accepted: April 7, 2019 <lb/>Published: April 19, 2019 <lb/>Copyright: © 2019 Hallin et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: The wind and water <lb/>level data is open access provided by the Swedish <lb/>Meteorological and Hydrological Institute, SMHI, <lb/>through www.smhi.se. The grain size data is <lb/>available through an FTP server with address www. <lb/>tvrl.se/caf/ftp/Sieved_grain_size_samples.xlsx. <lb/>Model code, input and results files will not be <lb/>provided open access but can be made available <lb/>upon request. Contact Caroline Hallin at Lund <lb/>University, Sweden, at caroline.hallin@tvrl.lth.se. <lb/>Topographic and bathymetric data cannot be <lb/>shared publicly because it has not been collected <lb/>by the authors and is not open access. The <lb/></front>

			<body>and Aeolis [20]-in the model framework Windsurf. Windsurf successfully simulated dune <lb/>evolution in one cross-shore transect during one year, however, longer time and spatial scales <lb/>require reduced complexity approaches. In this study, a model is developed that simulates sed-<lb/>iment transport and morphological evolution of the beach and dune on time scales of decades <lb/>to centuries. The aim is to create a robust, computationally efficient model that couples near-<lb/>shore, beach, and dune processes. <lb/>Simulations of long-term beach and dune evolution require integration of sediment trans-<lb/>port processes acting in both the cross-shore and longshore direction on multiple time scales <lb/>[14,21]. This work builds on the CS-model [15], a semi-empirical beach profile evolution <lb/>model that simulates sediment transport due to dune erosion and dune overwash caused by <lb/>wave action, dune build-up from aeolian transport, and beach-bar material exchange. Long-<lb/>shore sediment transport gradients are accounted for as constant sources or sinks, and nour-<lb/>ishment episodes can be added to the beach or dune [22]. Previously, sea level rise (SLR) has <lb/>not been included in the CS-model and the dune build-up from wind-blown sand did not take <lb/>into account sediment availability, which is an important factor for long-term dune evolution <lb/>[23,24]. In this study, the CS-model is developed through introducing SLR and mathematical <lb/>methods to compute aeolian transport and the associated dune growth. <lb/>The included transport processes are active over a range of spatial and temporal scales (Fig <lb/>1). Sediment transport and morphological evolution are simulated in cross-shore transects, <lb/>which may be aggregated to represent coastal evolution at spatial scales of kilometres. Model <lb/>input is SLR, wind, deep water waves, and simultaneous still water levels (SWL). From a <lb/>coastal management perspective model output of interest is e.g. long-term shoreline change, <lb/>the shoreline variation envelope, and dune height and dune volume in relation to storm ero-<lb/>sion rates [25]. The model is computationally efficient due to reduced complexity transport <lb/>equations and a simplified representation of the coastal morphology, which makes it suitable <lb/>for probabilistic approaches. <lb/>The main objective of this study is to develop a simple, robust, and computationally effi-<lb/>cient model for evolution of the beach-dune system under rising sea levels at decadal to cen-<lb/>tennial time scales. Established conceptual morphological models are translated into <lb/>mathematical formulations to extend the CS-model [15] to include the dynamic and intercon-<lb/>nected effects of SLR and aeolian transport. <lb/>The paper starts by presenting the theoretical background for the proposed model develop-<lb/>ment, followed by a model description. The proposed model is then applied to simulate the <lb/>long-term beach and dune evolution at A ¨ngelholm Beach, Sweden. First, the model is cali-<lb/>brated and validated against a seven-year data set and thereafter, the evolution from 2018-<lb/>2100 is simulated considering a range of SLR scenarios. The paper ends with a discussion on <lb/>model performance and suggestions for further development. Notations used throughout the <lb/>paper are summarized in a list of symbols at the end. <lb/>Theoretical background <lb/>Aeolian sediment transport <lb/>The mechanics of sediment transport by wind and the associated morphological evolution of <lb/>coastal dune systems have been studied extensively [26,27], which has provided physical <lb/>insights to aeolian transport processes. Still, existing models do not manage to accurately pre-<lb/>dict transport rates at time scales relevant for coastal management [23,25,28]. Sediment trans-<lb/>port formulas only accounting for wind speed and grain size [26,29-33] are commonly <lb/>overestimating transport rates when compared to field data from beach environments [23,34]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<front>topographic data are available from A ¨ngelholm <lb/>municipality. Requests to access the data should <lb/>be sent to info@engelholm.se. The bathymetric <lb/>data is owned by the Swedish Geological Survey <lb/>(SGU) and can only be accessed by researchers <lb/>who meet the criteria for access to this confidential <lb/>data. For more information on how to access the <lb/>bathymetric data, contact kundservice@sgu.se. <lb/>Since the authors are not in possession of the <lb/>topographic and bathymetric data, we cannot <lb/>guarantee that the organizations who own this data <lb/>will make it available to other researchers. <lb/>However, the observed volumetric changes that are <lb/>presented in the manuscript are sufficient for <lb/>calibration and validation of the model. <lb/>Funding: The authors received no specific funding <lb/>for this work. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

			<body>When modelling yearly to decadal sediment transport rates, limits to transport are of inter-<lb/>est, rather than time-varying forcing conditions [23]. Such limiting factors are sediment avail-<lb/>ability [24], beach width and fetch length [35], beach slope [34], surface moisture [35], snow <lb/>and ice cover [36], vegetation, and crust development on the beach surface [20]. <lb/>Dune build-up by wind requires sediment with a grain size fine enough to be mobilised by <lb/>the wind, and coarse enough to be deposited in the foredune, where the wind shear stress <lb/>Fig 1. Conceptual model of decadal to centennial scale beach and dune evolution. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651.g001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>decreases due to the effect of vegetation and topography [35]. Grain sizes in aeolian deposits <lb/>typically range between 0.15-0.30 mm [37], and are often smaller than those found on the <lb/>beach [38]. Eroding beaches tend to be drained of fine sediment and accreting beaches to be <lb/>supplied with fine sediment due to the selection of grain size in transport processes, where <lb/>smaller grains are more likely to be picked up [39]. In this way, the aeolian sediment transport <lb/>depends on the longshore and cross-shore transport processes, which control the supply of <lb/>sediment of appropriate grain size. <lb/>Dune morphology <lb/>Transport rates alone cannot be used to predict the morphological evolution of foredunes. It is <lb/>also important where the aeolian sediment is deposited; on the crest, the seaward or landward <lb/>slopes. The beach sediment budget, which could be positive, negative, or stable, affects both <lb/>the rate of transport and the morphological evolution [24,25]. According to Psuty&apos;s conceptual <lb/>model [24], dunes at an accreting beach will grow rapidly and create a prograding dune ridge <lb/>topography, where a new foredune is formed in front of the existing ones, creating low dunes <lb/>with mild slopes [40,41]. The dunes will be low because there is not enough time for them to <lb/>grow in height before a new foredune is built in front of them [42]. At a stable beach, the dune <lb/>stays in place and grows higher due to scarping and recovery. Eroding beaches may develop in <lb/>two different ways; if they are slightly eroding, the dune will maintain or even increase its vol-<lb/>ume, grow higher, and be displaced inland through scarping in combination with aeolian <lb/>transport and/or overwash. If the beach is eroding rapidly and overwash processes are domi-<lb/>nant, the dune will be flattened and move landward. <lb/>The explanatory mechanisms behind these different morphological behaviours are sedi-<lb/>ment supply and the influence of vegetation. If vegetation is present at the dune foot, sediment <lb/>is trapped in an embryonal foredune and without vegetation sediment is deposited near the <lb/>foot of the foredune, forming a dune ramp (Fig 2), which facilitates the passage of wind-blown <lb/>sand over the dune crest [43,44]. <lb/>The interaction between dune ramps and morphological evolution was studied at Skallin-<lb/>gen spit in Denmark, which is a retreating coastal feature, subject to overwash and landward <lb/>foredune migration [44]. Christiansen and Davidson-Arnott [44] found that aeolian transport <lb/>over the dune crest increased rapidly as the vertical distance from the top of the ramp to the <lb/>Fig 2. Vegetated embryonal foredune (left) at an accreting beach, and non-vegetated dune ramp (right) at a stable beach in A ¨ngelholm, Sweden. The sites are later <lb/>referred to as profile C and B, respectively. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651.g002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>crest became equal to or less than 1 m, and that the wind during wet conditions eroded the <lb/>ramp to approximately this height. <lb/>The dune ramp concept was further developed in a study at Greenwich Dunes on Prince <lb/>Edward Island in Canada [36]. In 2002-2009 measurements were performed at two stretches of a <lb/>beach with different littoral sediment budgets; one negative and one positive or neutral, although <lb/>both showing a long-term transgressive trend. After scarping, if no ramp was present, very little <lb/>sediment reached the dune crest or landward slope. When a dune ramp was present, accumula-<lb/>tion was observed at the upper seaward slope, crest and landward slope. The beach with a tempo-<lb/>rarily positive sediment transport had vegetated embryonal dunes present for 2-3 years and <lb/>through that time most sediments were deposited at the seaward side of the dune. When the <lb/>embryonal dune was damaged and a vegetated ramp had not yet been formed, the observed <lb/>transport to the crest and landward side of the dune was significant. These studies support that <lb/>the sediment budget affects the morphological evolution, since embryonal foredunes are more <lb/>likely to occur on accreting beaches whereas dune ramps form on eroding or stable beaches. <lb/>For long-term modelling of foredune evolution, dune height is essential as it affects flood <lb/>safety. The conceptual models of Psuty [24] and Sherman and Bauer [25] suggest that dune <lb/>height is depending on the sediment budget. The ratio between height/width of coastal fore-<lb/>dunes are typically about 0.11 [12], but the maximum height varies between different environ-<lb/>ments. Dura ´n and Moore [19] proposed a linear relationship between foredune height and <lb/>wave height, assuming that the dune height was depending on wave impact. Hesp [27] found a <lb/>strong relationship between increasing foredune height and increasing dissipativeness but <lb/>concluded that the trend might also be explained by higher exposure to storm winds at dissipa-<lb/>tive beaches. In summary, the dune height is site-specific and depends on the sediment budget, <lb/>wind and wave climate, and sediment and vegetation characteristics. <lb/>The Bruun rule <lb/>The Bruun rule provides a simple method to estimate the shoreline retreat, R Bruun , under a <lb/>slowly rising sea level [45], <lb/>R Bruun ¼ S SLR <lb/>B Bruun <lb/>h <lb/>ð1Þ <lb/>where S SLR is the sea level rise, B Bruun and h the width and the height of the active profile, <lb/>respectively. The width B Bruun represents the distance from the shoreline to the depth closure, <lb/>and h is the sum of the depth of closure and the beach berm height. <lb/>The Bruun rule is based on the assumption that SLR creates accommodation space for sedi-<lb/>ment within the subaqueous part of the active profile. The Bruun Rule only considers cross-<lb/>shore transport, assuming that the profile consists entirely of sand, that there is a full spectrum <lb/>of waves, wind and water levels to force the profile to its new equilibrium, and that the SLR is <lb/>slow. All sediment transport is in the seaward direction to the subaqueous part of the profile. <lb/>However, infilling sediment can come from various sources, not only the beach. The sediment <lb/>may also originate from a negative longshore sediment transport gradient, artificial nourish-<lb/>ments, or from offshore supplies outside the depth of closure, also known as the Dean equilib-<lb/>rium concept [46-48]. <lb/>The original version of the Bruun rule does not consider any vertical adjustment of the sub-<lb/>aerial part of the profile to SLR. If the mean sea level rises, also the beach berm height and <lb/>dune foot are expected to adjust to the new sea level [49]. For this purpose, extended versions <lb/>of the Bruun Rule that accounts for landward transport due to aeolian processes and overwash <lb/>of the beach berm and dune have been proposed [49-51]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>It should be noted that the Bruun rule is a much discussed method that has been subject to <lb/>numerous critical evaluations [52]. The first main argument against the Bruun rule concerns <lb/>its two-dimensionality and the assumption that other transport processes such as gradients in <lb/>longshore transport and overwash are excluded. In the CS-model, however, the Bruun rule <lb/>will only be applied to compute the transport directly related to SLR. Other relevant transport <lb/>processes are dealt with in separate transport equations, and the morphological evolution of <lb/>the beach and dune is a result of all of these types of transports. <lb/>The second common critique against the Bruun rule is the validity of the concepts of equi-<lb/>librium profiles and depth of closure. In a recent extensive laboratory study [53], both the orig-<lb/>inal Bruun rule [45] and a modified version including landward transport [49] showed good <lb/>agreement with observations and confirmed the underlying assumption of a profile adjust-<lb/>ment to SLR. <lb/>Last, the Bruun rule has also been criticized for ignoring import of sediment from deeper <lb/>water outside depth of closure [47]. However, these processes are more common at geological <lb/>time scales than at engineering time scales. If known to be present they could be added as a <lb/>sediment source in the model. <lb/>Model for long-term foredune and beach evolution <lb/>The CS-model simulates sediment transport and the associated morphological evolution based <lb/>on a set of transport and continuity equations [15]. In this paper, the profile schematization is <lb/>developed and routines are added for aeolian transport, morphological dune evolution, and <lb/>the effect of SLR. For more detailed description of the other model components we refer to <lb/>Larson et al [15]. <lb/>Profile schematization <lb/>The beach profile is schematized through distances, slopes, characteristic heights, and volumes <lb/>(Fig 3), which are updated every time step. Length coordinates, relative to a reference point <lb/>Fig 3. Definition of heights, length coordinates, volumes and transports (red arrows). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651.g003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>behind the dune, are defined for landward and seaward dune foot, y L and y S , and dune crest, <lb/>y&apos; L and y&apos; S , and the intersection with mean sea level, y G . Landward and seaward dune slopes, <lb/>tan β L and tan β S , are assumed to be constant and a maximum foreshore slope, tan β F,max , is <lb/>defined. If tan β F,max is exceeded, β F &gt;β F,max , the entire beach is considered a swash zone. <lb/>Under this condition, sediment that would have been eroded from the beach is instead eroded <lb/>from the dune. <lb/>Depth of closure, D C , and dune foot height, D F , are constants referenced to the mean sea <lb/>level (MSL). The dune height, S, is a variable, specified relative to D F . A maximum value of S, <lb/>S max , is limiting dune height growth if the sediment budget is positive, whereas for negative <lb/>and stable budgets S has no restrictions [12]. S max can be approximated as a representative <lb/>height of prograding dune ridges, present in or near the study area. <lb/>Volumes and transport rates are given per meter of beach width. The specified volumes are <lb/>dune volume, V dune , where the dune ramp volume, V ramp , is an integral part, total beach vol-<lb/>ume, V beach , where the berm volume, V berm , is an integral part, and bar volume, V bar (Fig 3). <lb/>The bar volume represents nearshore subaqueous deposits involved in material exchange with <lb/>the beach and may consist of none, one, or multiple bars. The rest of the subaqueous part of <lb/>the profile, from MSL to D C , is assumed to be in equilibrium [54]. <lb/>The beach volume V beach is defined as the volume of sediment from a reference point <lb/>behind the dune to the intersection with mean sea level, y G , which is vertically limited by the <lb/>depth of closure, D C , and the dune foot height, D F . The sub-volume V berm is used to calculate <lb/>beach width; the quantity y G -y S is defined as a function of V berm based on site specific data. <lb/>Thus, the shape of the beach is not specified; it is only described by its width and volume, indi-<lb/>cated with a dashed line in Fig 3. <lb/>The purpose of the ramp volume V ramp is to determine how the sediment distribution over <lb/>the dune occurs. If the dune is eroded, V ramp is eroded first and if the ramp disappears <lb/>completely, the main part of the dune (behind the seaward dune crest, y&apos; S ) will start to erode. <lb/>The changes in profile schematization compared to previous versions of the CS-model <lb/>require adjustment of the frictional losses over the beach. The runup height significant for <lb/>dune impact, R, is defined as R ¼ 0:158 <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi <lb/>H rms L 0 <lb/>p <lb/>, where H rms and L 0 are deep water root-<lb/>mean-square wave height and mean wavelength, respectively [55]. R is corrected for friction <lb/>over the beach according to [56], <lb/>R 0 ¼ RexpðÀ 2c f xÞ þ ðD F À SWLÞð1 À expðÀ 2c f xÞÞ <lb/>ð2Þ <lb/>where R&apos; is the adjusted runup height, c f is an empirical friction coefficient, and x is the hori-<lb/>zontal travel distance of the wave front. If SWL+ R&apos; &gt; D F dune erosion will occur. Since the <lb/>beach in the CS-model has no shape, the travel distance cannot be exactly known. Instead the <lb/>travel distance x is expressed as a function of the volume V berm , <lb/>x ¼ <lb/>2V berm <lb/>D F <lb/>1 À <lb/>SWL <lb/>D F <lb/>� <lb/>� <lb/>ð3Þ <lb/>Aeolian sediment transport <lb/>The proposed aeolian sediment transport scheme is based on the assumption that, on a decadal <lb/>time scale, the most important limiting factor for aeolian sediment transport is the supply of <lb/>material of appropriate grain size. Sediment available for aeolian transport is assumed to be <lb/>present as a location-specific fraction of the transported sediment volumes longshore and <lb/>cross-shore. Availability is computed through a balance including sediment transport and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>nourishments, to and from V beach . The volume of sediment available for aeolian transport, V W , <lb/>in time step i is calculated as, <lb/>V W;i ¼ V W;iÀ 1 þ ðq S;iÀ 1 À q W;iÀ 1 À A q ðq SLR;iÀ 1 À q LS;iÀ 1 ÞÞDt þ A b V nour;iÀ 1 <lb/>V W � 0 <lb/>ð4Þ <lb/>where q S is the transport rate of eroded sediment from the dune to the beach, q W is the aeolian <lb/>transport rate from the beach to the dune, q SLR is the transport rate of sediment to compensate <lb/>for SLR, &apos;Bruun Rule&apos; transport, q LS is the transport rate due to gradients in longshore trans-<lb/>port, Δt is length of time step, and V nour volume of beach nourishments. The coefficients A q <lb/>and A b describe the fractions of the transport rate and nourished volume, respectively, that are <lb/>within the proper range of grain size and available for aeolian transport. <lb/>If V W,i &gt; 0, aeolian transport will take place during time step t = i. If V W,i � 0, the aeolian <lb/>transport will be turned off and V w,i is set to zero. The initial available volume, V w,0 , depends <lb/>on conditions prior to the simulation period, e.g. nourishments and large dune erosion events. <lb/>The potential aeolian sediment transport rate, m WE , in kg/s/m, can be estimated by [31], <lb/>m WE ¼ K W <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffiffi <lb/>D 50 <lb/>D ref <lb/>50 <lb/>s <lb/>r a <lb/>u 2 <lb/>� <lb/>g <lb/>ðu � À u �c Þ <lb/>ð5Þ <lb/>where D 50 is the median grain size, D 50 <lb/>ref is the median reference grain size of 0.25 mm, ρ a the <lb/>density of air, g the acceleration due to gravity, u� the shear velocity at the bed, u� c the critical <lb/>shear velocity at the bed, and K w an empirical coefficient. If u� &lt; u� c , then m WE = 0. <lb/>The shear velocity, u�, can be calculated using the law of the wall, <lb/>u z <lb/>u � <lb/>¼ <lb/>1 <lb/>k <lb/>ln <lb/>z <lb/>z 0 <lb/>� � <lb/>ð6Þ <lb/>where u z is the wind velocity at z meter above ground, z 0 is the aerodynamic roughness height, <lb/>and κ is von Karman&apos;s constant (� 0.41). For wind conditions below the critical shear velocity <lb/>for initiation of transport, u�&lt;u� c , the roughness height, z 0 , can be parameterized as z 0 = <lb/>0.081log 10 (d/0.18), where d is the grain size in mm [33]. The critical shear velocity can be esti-<lb/>mated through [26], <lb/>u �c ¼ A W <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi <lb/>ðr s À r a Þ <lb/>r a <lb/>gD 50 <lb/>s <lb/>ð7Þ <lb/>where ρ s is the density of sand (typically 2650 kg/m 3 ) and A W is a coefficient of about 0.1. <lb/>To determine the shear velocity during transport, two wind measurements at different <lb/>heights or one wind measurement and an estimate of the roughness height affected by trans-<lb/>port are required. For long-term simulations, wind data is typically not available from the <lb/>beach of interest but from a wind gauge that is not influenced by the sand transport. Consider-<lb/>ing the spatial and temporal resolution of available wind data, the relationship between u z and <lb/>u� can be approximated as linear [57] so that m WE /u z <lb/>2 <lb/>(u z -u z,c ) [58]. The critical velocity for <lb/>transport at z m height, u z,c can be computed through combining Eqs 6 and 7. Eq 5 can then <lb/>be rewritten as, <lb/>m WE ¼ C W <lb/>ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffi ffiffi <lb/>D 50 <lb/>D ref <lb/>50 <lb/>s <lb/>r a <lb/>u 2 <lb/>z <lb/>g <lb/>ðu z À u z;c Þ <lb/>ð8Þ <lb/>where C W is an empirical coefficient. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>The mass flux m WE is converted to a volumetric equilibrium transport rate (q WE ) of sand to <lb/>the dunes by, <lb/>q WE ¼ <lb/>m WE <lb/>r s ð1 À PÞ <lb/>ð9Þ <lb/>where P is the porosity (typically 40%). <lb/>To reach the transport rates described by the equilibrium equations, a critical fetch length is <lb/>required [35,59]. The fetch length, F, depends on the wind angle towards shore normal, θ, and <lb/>the dry beach width, B dry . For 0˚� θ � 80˚, <lb/>F ¼ <lb/>B dry <lb/>cosðyÞ <lb/>ð10Þ <lb/>The beach is assumed to be dry landward of the runup limit. A runup length coordinate, y R , <lb/>is defined as, <lb/>y R ¼ y S þ 1 À <lb/>R þ SWL <lb/>D F <lb/>� <lb/>� <lb/>ðy G À y S Þ <lb/>ð11Þ <lb/>The dry beach width, B dry , is then calculated as the horizontal distance from the runup limit <lb/>to the seaward dune foot B dry = y R -y S . If y R � y S , the whole beach is assumed to be wet and <lb/>there will be no aeolian transport. <lb/>A simplified equation for the potential transport rate, corrected for fetch-limited condi-<lb/>tions, q WF , was developed by Larson et al [15] based on the work by Sauermann et al [60], <lb/>q WF ¼ q WE ð1 À expðÀ d FÞÞ <lb/>ð12Þ <lb/>where δ is an empirical coefficient in the order of 0.1-0.2 m -1 . <lb/>Oblique wind angles have longer fetches and may therefore generate higher aeolian trans-<lb/>port rates. This effect is counteracted by the cosine effect, implying that only the onshore com-<lb/>ponent, q W , adds to the dune volume, <lb/>q W ¼ q WF cosðy Þ <lb/>ð13Þ <lb/>Aeolian transport due to offshore directed wind is neglected. <lb/>When neglecting the impact of grain size, the effect of slope correction on transport rates <lb/>has been found to be small at beaches with slopes below 15˚[34]. Here, grain size is accounted <lb/>for in Eqs 5 and 6 and since most beach slopes are milder than 15˚[61], the effect of beach <lb/>slope is assumed to be negligible. <lb/>Morphological dune evolution <lb/>Dunes evolve differently depending on where the aeolian transported sediment is deposited, in <lb/>front of the dune, on the seaward slope, on the crest, or on the landward slope. Here we intro-<lb/>duce a sediment deposition scheme based on Psuty&apos;s sediment budget formulation [24] and <lb/>the dune ramp concept [36,44]. <lb/>The sediment budget is calculated as the change of volume in the beach-dune system (ΔV T ) <lb/>over a relevant time scale (T bud ) and can either be negative (ΔV T &lt; 0), stable (ΔV T � 0), or pos-<lb/>itive (ΔV T &gt; 0), <lb/>DV T ¼ <lb/>1 <lb/>n <lb/>X t¼i <lb/>t¼iÀ n <lb/>ðÀ q SLR;t þ q LS;t ÞDt þ V nour;t <lb/>À <lb/>� <lb/>ð14Þ <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>where n = T bud /Δt. Here all nourishments are considered in V nour , also dune nourishments. <lb/>The time scale, T bud , is in the order of years and should be long enough to represent long-term <lb/>trends and not seasonal variations. The proposed distribution scheme generates different dune <lb/>evolution depending on the sediment budget (Fig 4). <lb/>In the case of a positive sediment budget, ΔV T &gt; 0, the ramp is filled until the ramp height <lb/>is equal to the dune height, S. After the ramp has filled up, if S &lt; S max , for a trapezoidal shape, <lb/>the sediment will be deposited on the crest, and for a triangular shape, the dune grows while <lb/>maintaining a constant dune crest length coordinate, y&apos; L = y&apos; S = constant, until S max is reached. <lb/>If S � S max , all sediment is deposited on the seaward side of the dune and the dune grows sea-<lb/>ward maintaining a trapezoidal shape. <lb/>For a stable sediment budget, ΔV T � 0, the ramp is filled until the ramp height is equal to <lb/>the dune height, S. Thereafter, in the case of a trapezoidal dune shape, a fraction of the sedi-<lb/>ment, A s , is deposited on the crest and the fraction 1-A s is deposited on the seaward side of the <lb/>dune. If the dune has a triangular shape, the dune grows in height while maintaining a con-<lb/>stant dune crest length coordinate, y&apos; L = y&apos; S = constant. <lb/>When the sediment budget is negative, ΔV T &lt; 0, the ramp is filled until a critical ramp <lb/>height is reached. Thereafter, in the case of a trapezoidal dune shape, a fraction of the sedi-<lb/>ment, A e , is deposited on the crest and the fraction 1-A e is deposited on the landward side <lb/>of the dune. If the dune has a triangular shape, y&apos; L = y&apos; S , the dune grows on its landward <lb/>side. <lb/>The critical ramp height is here defined as 1 m below the crest level [44]. If the model is <lb/>applied in an area where local observations suggest otherwise, a site-specific value of the criti-<lb/>cal ramp height should be adopted. If there are no observations of sediment distribution across <lb/>the dune, the distribution coefficients, A s and A e , can be set to 0.5 based on the observations by <lb/>Ollerhead et al [36]. <lb/>Fig 4. Sediment distribution scheme on a dune due to wind-blown sand. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651.g004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>Impact of sea level rise <lb/>The Bruun Rule is used to calculate the required sediment transport from the beach volume, <lb/>V beach , to the active part of the profile to compensate for SLR. In agreement with previous <lb/>Bruun rule extensions [49-51], also landward transport is accounted for to compensate for an <lb/>elevation adjustment of the dry beach (Fig 5). Analogous to the original Bruun Rule concept, <lb/>the dry beach is assumed to be subject to hydrodynamic forcing capable of adjusting it to a <lb/>slowly rising sea level. The explanatory mechanism is that the beach is built by waves; with a <lb/>higher MSL the waves will build a higher beach. Therefore, the width of the active profile, B, is <lb/>here extended to encompass the horizontal distance from the seaward dune foot, y S , to the <lb/>depth of closure, D C . <lb/>The dune foot height is kept constant relative to MSL. Thus, the dune foot is moving up <lb/>with the same rate as SLR. Since the dune crest elevation is not changing, the lowest part of the <lb/>dune is per definition converted from dune volume, V dune , to beach volume, V beach . Also the <lb/>depth of closure, D C , is constant, so that the lower vertical limit of the beach volume is moving <lb/>up with the same rate as SLR. <lb/>V beach is eroding to supply the active profile with sediment equivalent to the demand from <lb/>the increased accommodation space due to SLR. The difference between the old and new <lb/>V beach is denoted V SLR . Thus, the volume V SLR eroded from the beach is derived from the <lb/>Bruun Rule with the new definition of the active profile width, B, <lb/>V SLR ¼ R Bruun ðD F þ D C Þ ¼ S SLR B <lb/>ð15Þ <lb/>The sediment transport required to maintain the equilibrium profile, q SLR , is taken as the <lb/>time derivative of V SLR , <lb/>q SLR ¼ <lb/>dV SLR <lb/>dt <lb/>¼ <lb/>dS SLR <lb/>dt <lb/>B <lb/>ð16Þ <lb/>Consequently, there are two direct effects of SLR in the CS-model: first, adjustment of the <lb/>equilibrium profile to the new sea level by an offshore &apos;Bruun rule&apos; transport, q SLR , from the <lb/>Fig 5. Impact of sea level rise on beach volume and dune height. The beach and dune volumes are for simplicity of <lb/>the visualisation schematized as rectangular shapes. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651.g005 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>beach volume V beach ; and second, decrease of dune volume, V dune , and height, S, due to an <lb/>upward shift of the reference SWL (Fig 5). The aeolian transport and morphological dune evolu-<lb/>tion scheme are indirectly impacted through q SLR (Eqs 4 and 14). Furthermore, the &apos;Bruun rule&apos; <lb/>transport is a sink for the beach volume, which will affect wave energy dissipation over the beach <lb/>(Eqs 2 and 3). This leads to an increase in the probability of dune erosion and overwash trans-<lb/>port, which are processes already included in the CS-model [15]. In this way, the dune may <lb/>translate landwards and the new scheme for morphological dune evolution allows the dunes to <lb/>adjust in height to the new sea level by keeping S max constant relative the dune foot elevation. <lb/>Case study A ¨ngelholm Beach, Sweden <lb/>To demonstrate the capability of the proposed model to simulate long-term beach and dune evo-<lb/>lution, it was applied to a seven-year data set from A ¨ngelholm Beach in south Sweden (Fig 6). <lb/>Forcing <lb/>Wind data at 10 m height was collected from stations 1, 3, 6, and 7 (Fig 6), operated by the <lb/>Swedish Meteorological and Hydrological Institute (SMHI). Predominant wind direction is <lb/>west to southwest and the shore normal is oriented 310˚N (Fig 7). <lb/>Deep-water wave conditions at the mouth of Ska ¨lderviken Bay were hindcasted from the <lb/>wind data using a modified SMB-method [22,62] (Fig 8). The largest computed significant <lb/>wave height and peak period is 5.3 m and 9.3 s, respectively, which occurred on 06/12/2013. <lb/>Water level data was collected from SMHI station 5 (Fig 6). The water levels were corrected <lb/>for local wind setup, following the method described by Palalane et al [22]. The current decade <lb/>has seen several extreme events compared to the period 1990-2010 (Fig 9). The highest <lb/>observed water level, adjusted for wind setup, was 185 cm above MSL on 27/11/2011. There is <lb/>no significant astronomical tide. <lb/>Morphology <lb/>Beach morphology varies alongshore, with higher dunes and a narrower beach in the north, <lb/>and lower dunes and a wider beach in the south. The observed long-term coastline evolution is <lb/>erosion in the north and accretion in the south (Fig 6). Profiles A, B, and C have been selected <lb/>Fig 6. Maps over the study area and measurement stations. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651.g006 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>to represent stretches of the beach with different long-term evolution (Fig 10). Analysis of <lb/>aerial photos since the 1940&apos;s suggests that the vegetation line has been retreating about 0.3 m/ <lb/>year in profile A, stable in profile B, and accreting about 0.3 m/year in profile C [22]. <lb/>Topographic observations are available from 2010-2017. In Table 1, the dune volume <lb/>changes over time are presented together with the data source. <lb/>Storms causing dune erosion occurred in November 2011, December 2013, January 2015, <lb/>December 2015, and December 2016, of which the storms in 2011 and 2013 were the most <lb/>severe. <lb/>Since 2010, the dune volume has decreased in all three profiles, including the long-term sta-<lb/>ble and accreting profiles, B and C. This is mainly due to the storm erosion in December 2013 <lb/>from which the dunes have not recovered. In profile A, the observed accretion in November <lb/>2014 and September 2015 is due to dune nourishments when sediment was scraped from just <lb/>seaward of the water line and deposited in the dune front. These operations were carried out <lb/>in April 2012, April 2014, and March 2015 to replace the sediment lost from the dunes during <lb/>storms. <lb/>In a bathymetric survey from October 2012 (provided by the Swedish Geological Survey) <lb/>no bars are observed in the subaqueous part of the studied profiles. However, from aerial <lb/>Fig 7. Wind rose compiled with data from 1976-2017. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651.g007 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>photos, parallel bars can be detected south of profile C. Along the entire beach temporary cres-<lb/>centic subaqueous deposit are visible within 70 m from the shoreline. These features indicate <lb/>that there is a cross-shore exchange of sediment stored in nearshore deposits, although, no <lb/>fully developed bars are observed within the measured profiles. <lb/>Sediments <lb/>Sediment samples have been collected at four occasions during 2015 and 2016 to determine <lb/>D 50 across the beach and dune (Fig 11). <lb/>The median grain size at sample points 1-5 on the foreshore and berm is in general decreas-<lb/>ing from profile A to profile C, indicating a longshore sorting. As the sediment is fairly well <lb/>graded, the grain size found in the dune, about 0.2-0.3 mm, is assumed to be representative <lb/>for dune building sediments. The samples from the dune in profile A with lower D 50 are mixed <lb/>with silty material from the artificial fill, and is therefore not considered representative for aeo-<lb/>lian transported sediment. <lb/>In profile C, dune-building sediment was available at all sampling occasions, except for the <lb/>first in October 2015 when it was finer, with D 50 below 0.2 mm. In Profile A, sediment of <lb/>appropriate grain size was only available on the last sampling occasion in October 2016. Profile <lb/>Fig 8. Hindcasted significant wave height at the mouth of Ska ¨lderviken Bay during 1976-2017. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651.g008 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig 9. Yearly maximum SWL in 1976-2016 based on measurements from Viken (dashed grey line) and the yearly maximum corrected for local wind <lb/>setup in Ska ¨lderviken Bay (solid black line). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651.g009 <lb/>Fig 10. Profiles from DEM dated 12/04/2010, dashed lines display model schematization of the dune. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651.g010 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>B had only complete samples from three of the occasions and then showed availability in some <lb/>of the sampling points along the profile, but not all. <lb/>Table 1. Dune volume changes between consecutive measurements. A summation of the changes since the first topographic observation in 2010 is given within <lb/>brackets. <lb/>Volumetric change since previous survey in m 3 /m (accumulated change since <lb/>2010) <lb/>Survey date <lb/>Profile A <lb/>Profile B <lb/>Profile C <lb/>Data source <lb/>12/04/2010 <lb/>initial profile <lb/>initial profile <lb/>initial profile <lb/>DEM LiDAR (resolution 1×1 m) <lb/>30/11/2012 <lb/>-2 (-2) <lb/>-1 (-1) <lb/>1 (1) <lb/>DEM LiDAR (resolution 1×1 m) <lb/>26/11/2014 <lb/>13 (11) <lb/>-10 (-11) <lb/>-10 (-9) <lb/>DEM Photogrammetry (resolution 1×1 m) <lb/>21/01/2015 <lb/>-28 (-17) <lb/>-1 (-12) <lb/>-2 (-11) <lb/>DEM Photogrammetry (resolution 1×1 m) <lb/>30/09/2015 <lb/>13 (-4) <lb/>0 (-12) <lb/>2 (-9) <lb/>Profile RTK-GPS <lb/>15/12/2015 <lb/>-14 (-18) <lb/>-2 (-14) <lb/>-2 (-11) <lb/>DEM Photogrammetry (resolution 1×1 m) <lb/>22/04/2016 <lb/>3 (-15) <lb/>-1 (-15) <lb/>0 (-11) <lb/>Profile RTK-GPS <lb/>27/10/2016 <lb/>0 (-15) <lb/>0 (-15) <lb/>0 (-11) <lb/>Profile RTK-GPS <lb/>05/01/2017(A,C) <lb/>17/01/2017(B) <lb/>-10 (-25) <lb/>1 (-14) <lb/>-1 (-12) <lb/>Profile RTK-GPS <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651.t001 <lb/>Fig 11. Median grain size D 50 for sediment samples in Profile A, B, and C sampled from the shoreline (1) to the dune <lb/>crest (7). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651.g011 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>Model setup <lb/>The initial profile was schematized so that the total sand volume in the subaerial part of the <lb/>profile was represented (Fig 10). Profile C, which consists of three dune rows, was schematized <lb/>into one dune, while preserving dune volume and seaward dune crest position. This procedure <lb/>is necessary as the CS-model can only simulate one row of dunes. The seaward dune slope <lb/>angle, β S , was set equal to the angle of repose of sand (approximately 30-34 ˚), whereas the <lb/>landward dune slope angle, β L , and maximum foreshore slope angle, β F,max , was obtained from <lb/>the topographic observations. <lb/>The relationship between the beach width, y G -y S , and the beach volume, V berm , is deter-<lb/>mined from the topographic observations covering the profile from the dune foot (y S ) to the <lb/>intersection with MSL (y G ) (Fig 12). A linear function was least-square fitted to the data yield-<lb/>ing y G -y S = 1.2V berm -4.3, with a coefficient of determination, R 2 , of 0.76. <lb/>The D 50 used to calculate the fall velocity in the beach-bar exchange formulas [15] and <lb/>employed in the aeolian transport equations was set to 0.2 mm for all three profiles. The dune <lb/>foot height, D F , was estimated to 2 m for all profiles, based on an average of the topographic <lb/>observations. <lb/>The depth of closure, D C , was calculated to be 5.7 m according to Hallermeier [63] and the <lb/>width of the subaqueous part of the active profile was estimated to be 800 m (B = 800+y G -y S ). <lb/>The average sea temperature is assumed to be about 10˚C [64]. <lb/>The gradients in the longshore sediment transport rate was estimated to be 4.1 m 3 /m/year <lb/>in profile A, 0 m 3 /m/year in profile B, and -3.0 m 3 /m/year in profile C, based on the vegetation <lb/>line analysis [22]; thus, q LS equals -4.1, 0, and 3 m 3 /m/year for profile A, B, and C respectively. <lb/>The simulation time step was set to one hour. <lb/>Calibration and validation <lb/>The model was calibrated for the period 12/04/2010-21/04/2016 and then validated for the <lb/>period 22/04/2016-17/01/2017. Literature values were used for all empirical coefficients [22] <lb/>except for C S and C W , which are the most important calibration parameters for the dune <lb/>evolution. <lb/>Dune erosion was calibrated by adjusting the impact coefficient, C S , to fit the observed <lb/>dune erosion. C S describes the resistance of the dunes to wave erosion; the eroded volume <lb/>from the dune during wave attack is proportional to C S [15]. For profiles B and C, which <lb/>Fig 12. Observed relation between beach volume (V berm ) and beach width (y G -y S ). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651.g012 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>involve dunes built up by aeolian transport with similar vegetation, C S was calibrated to a com-<lb/>mon value of 7.5�10 -5 . In profile A, the dune had initially aeolian transported sand, but was <lb/>after April 2012 partly nourished with a silty material. The impact coefficient, C S , was here cali-<lb/>brated to a larger value of 5�10 -4 , meaning that the dune is less resistant to erosion. <lb/>The empirical coefficient in the aeolian transport equation (Eq 7) C W was calibrated to <lb/>1.0�10 -5 , a common value for all profiles. Initial available sediment volume for aeolian trans-<lb/>port, V w , was set to 0 m 3 /m in the calibration phase. <lb/>For this study, there was no information on the morphological evolution of the subaqueous <lb/>part of the profile. The initial bar volume, which represents subaqueous deposits interacting <lb/>with the beach deposits, was set to 20 m 3 /m for profile A, 70 m 3 /m for profile B, and 50 m 3 /m <lb/>for profile C, to reproduce the evolution of the beach volume. For the validation, the bar vol-<lb/>ume at the end of the calibration period was used as the initial value. <lb/>During the calibration period minor dune erosion events occur almost yearly and there are <lb/>two major storm events with significant dune erosion in November 2011 and December 2013 <lb/>(Fig 13). The sudden increases in dune volume in profile A are due to the dune nourishment <lb/>episodes. In agreement with field observations, the aeolian transported volumes throughout <lb/>the simulation period are small compared to the eroded volumes during these storm events. <lb/>The dunes have not fully recovered at the end of the calibration period. <lb/>The validation period contains one storm event in December 2016, with a clear signal of <lb/>erosion in profile A and C (Fig 14). In profile B no erosion is observed, which is probably due <lb/>to an error in the measured topographic data. <lb/>Fig 13. Dune and beach volume evolution for calibration period. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651.g013 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>18 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>The performance of the calibration and validation is satisfactory. For the calibration period, <lb/>the coefficient of determination, R 2 , equals 0.73 for the dune volume evolution and 0.63 for the <lb/>berm volume evolution. For the validation period, R 2 equals 0.69 for the dune evolution, but <lb/>for the berm evolution, R 2 equals 0 because of few observations with only small volume <lb/>changes. The model sensitivity to the calibrated parameters was investigated by comparing a <lb/>modified model to the calibrated model. (Table 2). The mean absolute deviation of dune and <lb/>berm volume was calculated for a simulation period encompassing both the calibration and <lb/>validation period. The sensitivity analysis showed that the model was most sensitive to changes <lb/>Fig 14. Dune and beach volume evolution for validation period. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651.g014 <lb/>Table 2. Result from sensitivity analysis of calibrated parameters. <lb/>Parameter <lb/>Modification <lb/>Mean absolute deviation from calibrated <lb/>model (m 3 /m) <lb/>V dune <lb/>V berm <lb/>Initial V W <lb/>+10 m 3 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>Initial bar volume, V bar,1 <lb/>+25% <lb/>0.37 <lb/>1.24 <lb/>-25% <lb/>0.39 <lb/>1.22 <lb/>C W <lb/>+25% <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.17 <lb/>-25% <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.19 <lb/>C S <lb/>+25% <lb/>4.58 <lb/>1.59 <lb/>-25% <lb/>4.28 <lb/>1.66 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651.t002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>19 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>in the duneha erosion impact coefficient, C S . Changes to the other parameters had only a <lb/>minor impact on the dune and berm volume evolution. <lb/>However, there are uncertainties associated both with the topographic observations and the <lb/>forcing. The beach profiles are derived from DEMs with resolution 1×1 m based on both <lb/>LiDAR data and photogrammetry, and topographic surveys with GPS are carried out by both <lb/>the local municipality and by researchers within this study. Therefore, it is uncertain whether <lb/>some of the minor observed topographic developments are due to actual morphologic changes <lb/>or artefacts related to different data acquisition methods. The eroded volumes under storms <lb/>are on some occasions overestimated, and on other occasions underestimated. This can partly <lb/>be due to both uncertainties in the topographic data and in the forcing. <lb/>In the dune erosion equation, the water level and wave properties both have large impact <lb/>on the eroded volume. The lack of in situ water level gauge data introduces uncertainty when <lb/>the water levels within the bay are corrected for the local wind setup. It is also possible that <lb/>local variation in the wave climate occurs within the study area, which is not considered here; <lb/>this could partly explain the large variation in the value of the impact coefficient, C S , between <lb/>profile A and profiles B-C. Other possible explanations can be the mix of sediment in the dune <lb/>in profile A, where the main part of the dune consists of sand with D 50 around 0.2-0.3 mm <lb/>and the front part consists of finer, silty material from the dune nourishment; and further, that <lb/>vegetation is less abundant in profile A compared to B and C. The dune erosion formula used <lb/>in the CS-model [55] was developed for sandy dunes with D 50 ranging from 0.15 to 0.5 mm, <lb/>and its validity outside this range of grain sizes is uncertain. Future coastal management <lb/>approaches in the area are unknown; possibly the sediment characteristics in the dune may <lb/>change. In the long-term simulations from 2018-2100, dune evolution in profile A is simulated <lb/>with both the high and low calibrated value of C S . <lb/>The simulated yearly average aeolian transport amounts to 0.3 m 3 /m/year in profile A, 0.5 <lb/>m 3 /m/year in profile B and 0.6 m 3 /m/year in profile C (Fig 15), which is significantly lower <lb/>than in previous CS-model applications where a constant rate of about 10-11 m 3 /m/year was <lb/>applied in all three profiles [22]. The new results are more realistic when compared to the <lb/>observed long-term evolution. In the accreting profile C, the vegetation line has advanced 0.3 <lb/>m/year since the 1940s [22], which is approximately equal to an accumulation of 0.6 m 3 /year <lb/>considering the average dune height of 2 m. <lb/>The simulation results, with the highest aeolian transport in profile C and lower transport <lb/>in profile A, are in line with the topographic observations. The simulated differences in the <lb/>Fig 15. Available sediment for aeolian transport (V W ) and accumulated aeolian transport (q W ) during the calibration and validation <lb/>periods. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651.g015 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>20 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>average annual transport rates are due to variations in sediment supply between the different <lb/>profiles as well as the variation in beach width. The four sets of sediment samples taken from <lb/>October 2015 to October 2016 display variations both in space and time (Fig 11), where profile <lb/>C has the most available sediment, profile B less, and profile A only intermittent availability <lb/>during the period 2010-2016. This pattern is reflected in the simulated available sediment (Fig <lb/>15). However, the simulation results show that there should be sediment available for aeolian <lb/>transport within all three profiles during the actual sampling period, which was not supported <lb/>by the sediment grain size data. An explanation for this could be that the material eroded from <lb/>the dune in profile A before the sampling period was finer than the appropriate grain size for <lb/>dune build up, due to the silty nourishment, and thus should not have been accounted for in <lb/>the available sediment volume, V W . <lb/>Long-term simulation with sea level rise <lb/>Long-term beach and dune evolution from 2018-2100 was simulated with a range of SLR sce-<lb/>narios from IPCC [65]. The simulations were run with 10 sets of 83 years of input data, <lb/>obtained by randomly shuffling years (July-June) from 01/07/1976-30/06/2016 with simulta-<lb/>neous values of wind, waves, and water levels relative to MSL. The three different scenarios of <lb/>SLR until 2100 were defined as mean low 0.44 m, mean high 0.74 m, and likely upper range <lb/>high 0.98 m, relative to the average MSL during the years 1986-2005. The first scenario corre-<lb/>sponds to the RCP 2.6 scenario and the latter two to the RCP 8.5 scenario in the fifth assess-<lb/>ment report by IPCC [65]. The SLR rate was derived from fitting quadratic polynomials to the <lb/>data provided by IPCC (Table AII.7.7 in [66]). A post glacial uplift of 1.3 mm/year [67] was <lb/>subtracted from the computed SLR rates and the scenarios were compared to a baseline sce-<lb/>nario with no relative SLR, i.e. where SLR compensates exactly the post-glacial uplift. <lb/>The regional climate change prognosis does not predict any changes to the wind climate <lb/>[67]; therefore no changes in wind speed or direction were considered in this study. The same <lb/>holds for the wave climate, which is dominated by regionally wind-generated waves. <lb/>Profile A was simulated with two different values on the impact coefficient, C S ; the calibrated <lb/>value of 5�10 -4 , which is assumed to partly depend on the dune nourishments during the cali-<lb/>bration period, and the lower value of 7.5�10 -5 , which was estimated for profiles B and C. <lb/>In all profiles, dune volumes decrease for all three scenarios, including profile C despite <lb/>input of sediment due to a negative gradient in longshore transport (Fig 16). In Profile A, the <lb/>dune erodes away completely before year 2100, both with the large and small dune erosion <lb/>coefficient, C S . In the simulations with large C S , dune erosion is more important than the effect <lb/>of SLR, also without SLR the dune is eroded away quickly. Taking into account all SLR scenar-<lb/>ios, the dunes are eroded away completely within the period 2050-2075 with the lower C S coef-<lb/>ficient, compared to 2027-2037 with the higher C S coefficient. This evolution is explained by <lb/>the long-term trend of beach erosion and the severe storms in the last decade that are present <lb/>in the data set. <lb/>For profile B, the dune only disappears completely in the upper high SLR scenario, but the <lb/>volume is markedly diminished also in the other two scenarios. In Profile C, the effect of SLR <lb/>is compensated by the negative gradient in the longshore transport, which is added as a con-<lb/>stant transport rate to the beach volume. Still, the long-term simulation without SLR does not <lb/>show a net dune growth, which could be expected on an accreting beach. This can be explained <lb/>by the severe storm events in 2011 and 2013 that are present in the data set. <lb/>The long-term observation of dune evolution based on aerial photos from the 1940s con-<lb/>tains a period during 1960s and 1970s that was unusually calm with respect to storminess [68]. <lb/>If the wind climate from 1976-2016 is representative for future conditions, model results <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>21 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>indicate that the aeolian transport capacity will not be sufficient to repair storm erosion. In <lb/>profiles B and C, the available sediment for aeolian transport accumulates faster than the aeo-<lb/>lian transport rate, the gradient in longshore transport cause the beach volume to increase and <lb/>the shoreline to extend seawards (Fig 17). The wider beach increases frictional losses, so that <lb/>dune erosion decreases which explains the trend change in dune volume evolution in profile C <lb/>for the low and baseline scenarios (Fig 16). The dune erosion and recovery during the simula-<lb/>tion period are subtracted from, or added to, the foredune. In reality, new foredune ridges <lb/>could form during periods of recovery, however, this is not possible with the present simplified <lb/>dune schematization of the CS-model. <lb/>The dunes are also losing sediment due to the change of reference dune foot elevation when <lb/>the sea level is rising, causing the dune crest height to decrease (Fig 17). In profile B the hori-<lb/>zontal dune crest erodes away completely and the dune attains a triangular shape, so that the <lb/>dune crest is further lowered due to storm erosion. None of the simulations of profile B and C <lb/>results in landward dune translation. In profile B, with no gradient in the longshore transport, <lb/>SLR changes the sediment budget from stable to eroding for all scenarios. Profile C is still <lb/>accreting in the low scenario but changes into a negative sediment budget in the mean high <lb/>and upper high scenarios. In the scenarios with negative sediment budget, the aeolian trans-<lb/>port capacity is too low to restore the dune ramp, which is supposed to produce landward <lb/>translation between consecutive erosion events. <lb/>Fig 16. Simulated dune volume evolution. Solid lines represent mean value, and the dashed lines represent min and max values from the <lb/>10 simulations for each scenario. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651.g016 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>22 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>Discussion and concluding remarks <lb/>In this study, the CS-model was expanded to simulate beach and dune evolution at decadal to <lb/>centennial time scales under SLR. Model development was based on morphological concepts <lb/>from the literature, which were translated into mathematical formulations that were numeri-<lb/>cally solved. The proposed model was applied to a data set from A ¨ngelholm Beach, Sweden. <lb/>First, the model was calibrated and validated for a seven-year period, and then the beach and <lb/>dune evolution was simulated from 2018-2100 for a range of SLR scenarios. <lb/>Topography and grain size data suggests that the morphological evolution at A ¨ngelholm <lb/>Beach conform to the concepts that were introduced in the CS-model. The different profile <lb/>characteristics fit the conceptual sediment budget model by Psuty [24] where the eroding and <lb/>stable dunes in profiles A and B are the highest and the accumulating profile C displays a <lb/>lower, prograding dune-ridge topography. The differences in distribution of D 50 over the pro-<lb/>files are in line with the hypothesis that available sediment is a controlling factor for aeolian <lb/>transport and that preconditions for aeolian transport are variable both in space and time. <lb/>However, although there was sediment available, the aeolian transport that was observed in <lb/>the stable and accreting profiles B and C were not of sufficient rates to repair the storm erosion <lb/>during the study period. <lb/>Overall, the results of the calibration and validation against field data were satisfactory and <lb/>the long-term predictions of beach and dune evolution under different SLR scenarios showed <lb/>reasonable results. The CS-model illustrated the relative importance of longshore transport <lb/>gradients, storm erosion, aeolian transport, and SLR for the profile evolution. The simulations <lb/>demonstrated the importance of extreme storm events for decadal-scale dune evolution, and <lb/>confirmed the need of integration of physical processes acting on multiple time scales [21]. <lb/>At A ¨ngelholm Beach the aeolian transport capacity, rather than sediment availability, lim-<lb/>ited the dune growth in the long-term simulations. In the case with a positive sediment budget <lb/>(the low SLR scenario in profile C), the available sediment was accumulating faster than the <lb/>aeolian transport capacity, so that the shoreline extended seawards, widening the beach. For <lb/>the profiles with negative sediment budget, the dune ramp did not become fully developed <lb/>until the sediment available for aeolian transport had eroded away, suggesting that aeolian <lb/>transport capacity in relation to dune erosion rates is too low to result in landward dune <lb/>migration. The model assumes that the dune ramp is built entirely by wind-blown sand. Field <lb/>studies suggest that the main part of the ramp is built from wind-blown sand [36], however, in <lb/>Fig 17. Simulated beach-dune evolution for profile B and C. The &apos;+&apos; indicates intersection with MSL. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651.g017 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>23 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>future studies it would be worthwhile exploring if an avalanche mechanism should be included <lb/>in the model to facilitate the development of dune ramps. <lb/>Precipitation is not included in the model, but may be an important limiting factor [35]. At <lb/>beaches with seasonal ice and snow cover the effect on aeolian transport may be significant, <lb/>especially if transport is inhibited during periods with strong winds [36]. In areas with signifi-<lb/>cant impact of rain, snow, and ice, the model could be improved through modifying sediment <lb/>availability during wet or frozen conditions to restrict aeolian transport. Blowouts may also be <lb/>an important factor for landward foredune migration [40] but are difficult to include in a 1-D <lb/>model. <lb/>The CS-model assumes an equilibrium profile and therefore the Bruun rule fits well with <lb/>the model concept. Introducing a more realistic profile representation to the CS-model would <lb/>introduce a higher degree of model complexity, which is not desired. It is however important <lb/>to keep the limitations of the equilibrium concept in mind when applying the CS-model and <lb/>the Bruun rule. Furthermore, the depth of closure is time scale dependent. Over longer peri-<lb/>ods, the probability of storm events mobilizing sediment at deeper water increases [69]. There-<lb/>fore, the depth of closure adopted in the CS-model should be chosen with consideration to the <lb/>length of the simulation period. <lb/>In conclusion, the modified CS-model, including SLR related processes and a more <lb/>advanced transport and dune evolution scheme, provides fast and robust simulations with rea-<lb/>sonable results. The simplified model approach enables robust, long-term simulations and <lb/>makes the model suitable for probabilistic simulations. The results presented in this study are <lb/>promising, but more studies with longer-term data sets are required to validate the proposed <lb/>numerical formulations more thoroughly. <lb/>List of symbols <lb/>A b Coefficient describing fraction of nourishments available for aeolian transport [-] <lb/>A e Coefficient describing fraction of sediment deposited on dune crest in a negative sediment <lb/>budget [-] <lb/>A q Coefficient describing fraction of longshore and &apos;Bruun Rule&apos; transport available for aeolian <lb/>transport [-] <lb/>A s Coefficient describing fraction of sediment deposited on dune crest in a stable sediment <lb/>budget [-] <lb/>A W Coefficient in critical shear velocity equation [-] <lb/>B Width of active profile [m] <lb/>B Bruun Width of active profile in the original Bruun rule [m] <lb/>B dry Dry beach width [m] <lb/>c f Empirical friction coefficient for wave runup [-] <lb/>C S Dune erosion impact coefficient [-] <lb/>C W Empirical coefficient in aeolian equilibrium transport formula [-] <lb/>d Grain size [mm] <lb/>D 50 Median grain size [m] <lb/>D 50 <lb/>ref Median reference grain size [m] <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>24 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>D C Depth of closure [m] <lb/>D F Dune foot height [m] <lb/>F Fetch (aeolian transport) [m] <lb/>g Standard acceleration due to gravity [m/s 2 ] <lb/>h Height of active profile [m] <lb/>H m0 Energy based significant wave height [m] <lb/>H rms Deep water root-mean-square wave height [m] <lb/>i Index, time step [-] <lb/>K W Empirical coefficient in aeolian equilibrium transport formula [-] <lb/>L 0 Mean deep water wave length [m] <lb/>MSL Mean sea level [m] <lb/>m WE Potential aeolian transport rate [kg/s/m] <lb/>n Number of timesteps [-] <lb/>P Porosity [-] <lb/>q D Transport rate of eroded sediment from the dune [m 3 /s/m] <lb/>q L Transport rate of eroded sediment from the dune front to the landward side of the dune <lb/>[m 3 /s/m] <lb/>q LS Transport rate due to gradients in longshore transport [m 3 /s/m] <lb/>q S Transport rate of eroded sediment from the dune to the beach [m 3 /s/m] <lb/>q SLR Transport rate of sediment to compensate for sea level rise, &apos;Bruun Rule&apos; transport [m 3 /s/ <lb/>m] <lb/>q W Onshore component of aeolian transport [m 3 /s/m] <lb/>q WE Volumetric aeolian transport rate [m 3 /s/m] <lb/>q WF Potential aeolian transport rate corrected for fetch length [m 3 /s/m] <lb/>R Runup [m] <lb/>R&apos; Runup corrected for friction over beach [m] <lb/>R 2 Coefficient of determination [-] <lb/>R Bruun Shoreline retreat due to sea level rise [m] <lb/>S Dune height [m] <lb/>S max Maximum dune height limiting vertical dune growth for positive sediment budget [m] <lb/>S new Dune height after SLR [m] <lb/>S old Dune height before SLR [m] <lb/>S SLR Height of sea level rise [m] <lb/>SLR Sea level rise [-] <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>25 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>SWL Still water level [m] <lb/>t Time step [-] <lb/>T bud Significant time scale for sediment budget [s] <lb/>u � Shear velocity [m/s] <lb/>u � <lb/>c Critical shear velocity [m/s] <lb/>u z Wind speed at z m elevation [m/s] <lb/>u z,c Critical wind speed at z m elevation [m/s] <lb/>V bar Volume of subaqueous deposits [m 3 /m] <lb/>V berm Volume of beach above mean sea level, between shoreline and dune foot [m 3 /m] <lb/>V beach Total beach volume [m 3 /m] <lb/>V beach, new Total beach volume after SLR [m 3 /m] <lb/>V beach, old Total beach volume before SLR [m 3 /m] <lb/>V dune Dune volume [m 3 /m] <lb/>V nour Nourishment volume [m 3 /m] <lb/>V ramp Dune ramp volume [m 3 /m] <lb/>V SLR Eroded volume from Vbeach, due to SLR [m 3 /m] <lb/>V w Volume of sediment available for aeolian transport [m 3 /m] <lb/>x Horizontal travel distance of wave front [m] <lb/>y&apos; L Landward dune crest length coordinate [m] <lb/>y&apos; S Seaward dune crest length coordinate [m] <lb/>y G Shoreline length coordinate [m] <lb/>y L Landward dune foot length coordinate [m] <lb/>y R Runup limit length coordinate [m] <lb/>y S Seaward dune foot length coordinate [m] <lb/>z Wind gauge elevation [m] <lb/>z 0 Roughness height [m] <lb/>β F Average beach slope angle [˚] <lb/>β F,max Maximum foreshore slope angle [˚] <lb/>β L Landward dune slope angle [˚] <lb/>β S Seaward dune slope angle [˚] <lb/>δ Empirical coefficient to account for fetch effect [m -1 ] <lb/>Δt Length of time step [s] <lb/>ΔV T Change of volume in beach-dune system to determine sediment budget [m 3 /m] <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>26 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>κ von Karman&apos;s constant [-] <lb/>Θ Wind angle against shore normal [˚] <lb/>ρ a Air density [kg/m 3 ] <lb/>ρ s Sand density [kg/m 3 ] <lb/></body>

			<div type="contribution">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Caroline Hallin. <lb/>Data curation: Caroline Hallin. <lb/>Formal analysis: Caroline Hallin. <lb/>Investigation: Caroline Hallin. <lb/>Methodology: Caroline Hallin. <lb/>Supervision: Magnus Larson, Hans Hanson. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Caroline Hallin. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Magnus Larson, Hans Hanson. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Louisse CJ, Van Der Meulen F. Future coastal defence in the Netherlands: strategies for protection and <lb/>sustainable development. J Coast Res. 1991; 7: 1027-1041. <lb/>2. Doody P, Ferreira M, Lombardo S, Lucius I, Misdorp R, Niesing H, et al. Living with Coastal Erosion in <lb/>Europe: Sediment and Space for Sustainability: Results from the EUROSION Study. [Internet]. Euro-<lb/>pean Commission, Luxembourg. 2004. Available: http://repository.tudelft.nl/view/hydro/ <lb/>uuid:483327a3-dcf7-4bd0-a986-21d9c8ec274e/VN-readcube.com <lb/>3. Hanson H, Brampton A, Capobianco M, Dette HH, Hamm L, Laustrup C, et al. Beach nourishment proj-<lb/>ects, practices, and objectives-A European overview. Coast Eng. 2002; 47: 81-111. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/S0378-3839(02)00122-9 <lb/>4. Borsje BW, van Wesenbeeck BK, Dekker F, Paalvast P, Bouma TJ, van Katwijk MM, et al. How ecologi-<lb/>cal engineering can serve in coastal protection. Ecol Eng. Elsevier B.V.; 2011; 37: 113-122. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.ecoleng.2010.11.027 <lb/>5. Leatherman SP, Zhang K, Douglas BC. Sea level rise shown to drive coastal erosion. EOS Trans Am <lb/>Geophys Union. 2000; 81: 55-57. <lb/>6. Wong PP, Losada IJ, Gattuso JP, Hinkel J, Khattabi A, McInnes KL, et al. Coastal systems and low-<lb/>lying areas. Climate Change 2014 Impacts, Adaptation and Vulnerability: Part A: Global and Sectoral <lb/>Aspects. 2015. https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9781107415379.010 <lb/>7. Larson M, Kraus NC. SBEACH: Numerical model for simulating storm-induced beach change, report 1: <lb/>empirical foundation and model development. Tech Rep CERC-89-9 US Army Eng Waterw Exp Station <lb/>Coast Eng Res Center, Vicksburg, MS. 1989; <lb/>8. Roelvink D, Reniers A, van Dongeren A, van Thiel de Vries J, McCall R, Lescinski J. Modelling storm <lb/>impacts on beaches, dunes and barrier islands. Coast Eng. Elsevier B.V.; 2009; 56: 1133-1152. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.coastaleng.2009.08.006 <lb/>9. Vellinga P. Beach and dune erosion during storm surges. Doctoral Thesis, Delft University of Technol-<lb/>ogy, Delft, The Netherlands Publication 372, Delft Hydraulics. 1986. https://doi.org/10.1016/0378-3839 <lb/>(82)90007-2 <lb/>10. Luna MCM de M, Parteli EJR, Dura ´n O, Herrmann HJ. Model for the genesis of coastal dune fields with <lb/>vegetation. Geomorphology. Elsevier B.V.; 2011; 129: 215-224. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.geomorph. <lb/>2011.01.024 <lb/>11. van Boxel JH, Arens SM, van Dijk PM. Aeolian processes across transverse dunes. I: Modelling the air <lb/>flow. Earth Surf Process Landforms. 1999; 24: 255-270. https://doi.org/10.1002/(SICI)1096-9837 <lb/>(199903)24:3&lt;255::AID-ESP962&gt;3.0.CO;2-3 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>27 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>12. van Dijk PM, Arens SM, van Boxel JH. Aeolian processes across transverse dunes. II: Modelling the <lb/>sediment transport and profile development. Earth Surf Process Landforms. 1999; 24: 319-333. <lb/>13. Hanson H, Kraus NC. GENESIS: Generalized model for simulating shoreline change. 1989. <lb/>14. Stive MJF, Aarninkhof SGJ, Hamm L, Hanson H, Larson M, Wijnberg KM, et al. Variability of shore and <lb/>shoreline evolution. Coast Eng. 2002; 47: 211-235. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0378-3839(02)00126-6 <lb/>15. Larson M, Palalane J, Fredriksson C, Hanson H. Simulating cross-shore material exchange at decadal <lb/>scale. Theory and model component validation. Coast Eng. Elsevier B.V.; 2016; 116: 57-66. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.coastaleng.2016.05.009 <lb/>16. Vitousek S, Barnard PL, Limber P, Erikson L, Cole B. A model integrating longshore and cross-shore <lb/>processes for predicting long-term shoreline response to climate change. J Geophys Res Earth Surf. <lb/>2017; 122: 782-806. https://doi.org/10.1002/2016JF004065 <lb/>17. Robinet A, Idier D, Castelle B, Marieu V. A reduced-complexity shoreline change model combining long-<lb/>shore and cross-shore processes: the LX-Shore model. Environ Model Softw. Elsevier; 2018; 109: 1-<lb/>16. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envsoft.2018.08.010 <lb/>18. Cohn N, Hoonhout BM, Goldstein EB, Vries S De. Exploring Marine and Aeolian Controls on Coastal <lb/>Foredune Growth Using a Coupled Numerical Model. J Mar Sci Eng. 2019; 7: 1-25. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>3390/jmse7010013 <lb/>19. Dura ´n O, Moore LJ. Vegetation controls on the maximum size of coastal dunes. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S <lb/>A. 2013; 110: 17217-22. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1307580110 PMID: 24101481 <lb/>20. Hoonhout BM, de Vries S. A Process-based Model for Aeolian Sediment Transport and Spatiotemporal <lb/>Varying Sediment Availability. J Geophys Res. 2016; https://doi.org/10.1002/2015JF003692 <lb/>21. French J, Payo A, Murray B, Orford J, Eliot M, Cowell P. Appropriate complexity for the prediction of <lb/>coastal and estuarine geomorphic behaviour at decadal to centennial scales. Geomorphology. 2016; <lb/>256: 3-16. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.geomorph.2015.10.005 <lb/>22. Palalane J, Fredriksson C, Marinho B, Larson M, Hanson H, Coelho C. Simulating cross-shore material <lb/>exchange at decadal scale. Model application. Coast Eng. Elsevier B.V.; 2016; 116: 26-41. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.coastaleng.2016.05.009 <lb/>23. de Vries S, Southgate HN, Kanning W, Ranasinghe R. Dune behavior and aeolian transport on decadal <lb/>timescales. Coast Eng. Elsevier B.V.; 2012; 67: 41-53. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.coastaleng.2012.04. <lb/>002 <lb/>24. Psuty NP. Sediment budget and dune / beach interaction. J Coast Res. 1988; 3: 1-4. <lb/>25. Sherman DJ, Bauer O. Dynamics of beach-dune systems. Prog Phys Geogr. 1993; 17: 413-447. <lb/>26. Bagnold RA. The transport of sand by wind. Geogr J. 1937; 89: 409-438. <lb/>27. Hesp P. Surfzone, beach and foredune interactions on the Australian southest coast. J Coast Res. <lb/>1988; 3: 15-25. <lb/>28. Barchyn TE, Martin R, Kok J, Hugenholtz CH. Fundamental mismatches between measurements and <lb/>models in aeolian sediment transport prediction: The role of small-scale variability. Aeolian Res. Else-<lb/>vier B.V.; 2014; 15: 245-251. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aeolia.2014.07.002 <lb/>29. Hsu S-A. Wind stress criteria in eolian sand transport. J Geophys Res. 1971; 76: 8684-8686. <lb/>30. Kawamura R. Study on Sand Movement by Wind. Reports Phys Sci Res Inst Tokyo Univ. 1951; 5(3-4): <lb/>95-112. <lb/>31. Lettau K, Lettau H. Experimental and micrometeorological field studies of dune migration. In: Lettau H, <lb/>Lettau K, editors. Exploring the World&apos;s Driest Climate. University of Wisconsin-Madison; 1978. <lb/>32. Owen P. Saltation of uniform grains in air. J Fluid Mech. 1964; 20: 225-242. <lb/>33. Zingg A. Wind tunnel studies of the movement of sedimentary material. Proc 5th Hydraul Conf Bull. <lb/>1953; 34: 111-135. <lb/>34. Sherman DJ, Jackson DWT, Namikas SL, Wang J. Wind-blown sand on beaches: an evaluation of <lb/>models. Geomorphology. 1998; 22: 113-133. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0169-555X(97)00062-7 <lb/>35. Bauer BO, Davidson-Arnott RGD, Hesp P, Namikas SL, Ollerhead J, Walker IJ. Aeolian sediment trans-<lb/>port on a beach: Surface moisture, wind fetch, and mean transport. Geomorphology. Elsevier B.V.; <lb/>2009; 105: 106-116. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.geomorph.2008.02.016 <lb/>36. Ollerhead J, Davidson-Arnott R, Walker IJ, Mathew S. Annual to decadal morphodynamics of the fore-<lb/>dune system at Greenwich Dunes, Prince Edward Island, Canada. Earth Surf Process Landforms. <lb/>2013; 38: 284-298. https://doi.org/10.1002/esp.3327 <lb/>37. Bagnold RA. The physics of blown sand and desert dunes. London: Meuthen; 1941. <lb/>38. Narra P, Coelho C, Fonseca J. Sediment grain size variation along a cross-shore profile-representative <lb/>d50. J Coast Conserv. 2015; 19: 307-320. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11852-015-0392-x <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>28 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>39. McLaren P, Bowles D. The effects of sediment transport on grain-size distributions. J Sediment Petrol. <lb/>1985; 55: 457-470. https://doi.org/10.1306/212F86FC-2B24-11D7-8648000102C1865D <lb/>40. Hesp P. Foredunes and blowouts: initiation, geomorphology and dynamics. Geomorphology. 2002; 48: <lb/>245-268. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0169-555X(02)00184-8 <lb/>41. Moore LJ, Dura ´n Vinent O, Ruggiero P. Vegetation control allows autocyclic formation of multiple dunes <lb/>on prograding coasts. Geology. 2016; 44: 559-562. https://doi.org/10.1130/G37778.1 <lb/>42. Davidson-Arnott R, Hesp P, Ollerhead J, Walker I, Bauer B, Delgado-Fernandez I, et al. Sediment Bud-<lb/>get Controls on Foredune Height: Comparing Simulation Model Results with Field Data. Earth Surf Pro-<lb/>cess Landforms. 2018; https://doi.org/10.1002/esp.4354 <lb/>43. Kuriyama Y, Mochizuki N, Nakashima T. Influence of vegetation on aeolian sand transport rate from a <lb/>backshore to a foredune at Hasaki, Japan. Sedimentology. 2005; 52: 1123-1132. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1111/j.1365-3091.2005.00734.x <lb/>44. Christiansen MB, Davidson-Arnott R. Rates of Landward Sand Transport over the Foredune at Skallin-<lb/>gen, Denmark and the Role of Dune Ramps. Geogr Tidsskr J Geogr. 2004; 104: 31-43. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1080/00167223.2004.10649502 <lb/>45. Bruun P. Sea level rise as a cause of shore erosion. J Waterw Harb Div. 1962;ASCE 88: 117-130. <lb/>46. Dean RG. Additional sediment input to the nearshore region. Shore and Beach. 1987; 76-81. <lb/>47. Dean RG, Houston JR. Determining shoreline response to sea level rise. Coast Eng. Elsevier B.V.; <lb/>2016; 114: 1-8. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.coastaleng.2016.03.009 <lb/>48. Houston JR. Shoreline Response to Sea-Level Rise on the Southwest Coast of Florida. J Coast Res. <lb/>2015; 314: 777-789. https://doi.org/10.2112/JCOASTRES-D-14-00161.1 <lb/>49. Rosati JD, Dean RG, Walton TL. The modified Bruun Rule extended for landward transport. Mar Geol. <lb/>2013; 340: 71-81. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.margeo.2013.04.018 <lb/>50. Wolinsky MA, Brad Murray A. A unifying framework for shoreline migration: 2. Application to wave-dom-<lb/>inated coasts. J Geophys Res Earth Surf. 2009; 114: 1-13. https://doi.org/10.1029/2007JF000856 <lb/>51. Davidson-Arnott RGD. Conceptual Model of the Effects of Sea Level Rise on Sandy Coasts. J Coast <lb/>Res. 2005; 216: 1166-1172. https://doi.org/10.2112/03-0051.1 <lb/>52. Cooper JAG, Pilkey OH. Sea-level rise and shoreline retreat: Time to abandon the Bruun Rule. Glob <lb/>Planet Change. 2004; 43: 157-171. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gloplacha.2004.07.001 <lb/>53. Atkinson AL, Baldock TE, Birrien F, Callaghan DP, Nielsen P, Beuzen T, et al. Laboratory investigation <lb/>of the Bruun Rule and beach response to sea level rise. Coast Eng. Elsevier Ltd; 2018; 136: 183-202. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.coastaleng.2018.03.003 <lb/>54. Dean RG. Equilibrium beach profiles: U.S. Atlantic and Gulf coasts. Dep Civ Eng Ocean Eng Rep No <lb/>12, Univ Delaware, Newark, Delaware. 1977; <lb/>55. Larson M, Erikson L, Hanson H. An analytical model to predict dune erosion due to wave impact. Coast <lb/>Eng. 2004; 51: 675-696. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.coastaleng.2004.07.003 <lb/>56. Hanson H, Larson M, Kraus NC. Calculation of beach change under interacting cross-shore and long-<lb/>shore processes. Coast Eng. Elsevier B.V.; 2010; 57: 610-619. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.coastaleng. <lb/>2010.02.002 <lb/>57. Belly P-Y. Sand movement by wind; Technical Memorandum No. 1, US. Army Corps of Engineers. <lb/>1964. <lb/>58. Fryberger SG, Dean G. Dune Forms and Wind Regimes. In: McKee ED, editor. A Study of Global Sand <lb/>Seas. Reston, VA, USA: U.S. Geological Survey; 1979. pp. 137-169. <lb/>59. Davidson-Arnott RGD, Law MN. Seasonal patterns and controls on sediment supply to coastal fore-<lb/>dunes, Long Point, Lake Erie. Coastal Dunes: Form and Process. 1990. pp. 177-200. <lb/>60. Sauermann G, Kroy K, Herrmann HJ. Continuum saltation model for sand dunes. Phys Rev E Stat Non-<lb/>lin Soft Matter Phys. 2001; 64: 031305. https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevE.64.031305 PMID: 11580330 <lb/>61. Bascom WN. The relationship between sand size and beach-face slope. Trans Am Geophys Union. <lb/>1951; 32: 866-874. <lb/>62. USACE (US Army Corps of Engineers). Shore Protection Manual (SPM). Washington: U.S. Govern-<lb/>ment Printing Office; 1984. <lb/>63. Hallermeier RJ. A profile zonation for seasonal sand beaches from wave climate. Coast Eng. 1981; 4: <lb/>253-277. https://doi.org/10.1016/0378-3839(80)90022-8 <lb/>64. MacKenzie BR, Schiedek D. Long-term sea surface temperature baselines-time series, spatial covaria-<lb/>tion and implications for biological processes. J Mar Syst. 2007; 68: 405-420. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>jmarsys.2007.01.003 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>29 / 30 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>65. Church JA, Clark PU, Cazenave A, Gregory JM, Jevrejeva S, Levermann A, et al. Sea level change. <lb/>Clim Chang 2013 Phys Sci Basis Contrib Work Gr I to Fifth Assess Rep Intergov Panel Clim Chang. <lb/>2013; 1137-1216. https://doi.org/10.1017/CB09781107415315.026 <lb/>66. Prather M, Flato G, Friedlingstein P, Jones C, Lamarque J-F, Liao H, et al. IPCC, 2013: Annex II: Cli-<lb/>mate System Scenario Tables. Clim Chang 2013 Phys Sci Basis Contrib Work Gr I to Fifth Assess Rep <lb/>Intergov Panel Clim Chang. 2013; <lb/>67. Persson G, Sjo ¨kvist E, Åstro ¨m S, Eklund D, Andre ´asson J, Johnell A, et al. Rapport Nr 2011-52 Klima-<lb/>tanalys fo ¨r Skåne la ¨n [in Swedish]. 2012. <lb/>68. BACC II Author Team. Second assessment of climate change for the Baltic Sea Basin. 2015. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-16006-1 <lb/>69. Nicholls RJ, Birkemeier WA, hong Lee G. Evaluation of depth of closure using data from Duck, NC, <lb/>USA. Mar Geol. 1998; 148: 179-201. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0025-3227(98)00011-5 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Simulating beach and dune evolution at decadal to centennial scale under rising sea levels <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0215651 April 19, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>30 / 30 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
