<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>W/Z properties (except mass) form ATLAS and CMS <lb/>J. Santaolalla (on behalf of CMS and ATLAS collaborations) <lb/>Centro de Investigaciones Energéticas MedioAmbientales y Tecnológicas, Avda. Complutense, 22 -28040 Madrid <lb/>Abstract. The results on W and Z boson properties by both ATLAS and CMS (except mass) are presented in <lb/>this document. The inclusive W and Z boson cross section production, the W charge asymmetry, the differential <lb/>production as a function of the boson rapidity and transverse momentum, the W polarization and the sinus of <lb/>the weak angle are shown in this document. The studies included are based on LHC collisions at <lb/>√ <lb/>s = 7 TeV, <lb/>recorded during 2010 and 2011. <lb/></front>

			<body>1 Introduction <lb/>The measurement of electroweak boson properties in CMS [1] <lb/>and ATLAS [2] is of capital importance, especially in the <lb/>first years of operation of the LHC. These measurements <lb/>are useful to test the Standard Model (SM) at a new en-<lb/>ergy scale, to improve our knowledge on the proton com-<lb/>position. They are also sensitive to new physics. They are <lb/>important background for many searches. As standard can-<lb/>dles, they are useful to calibrate our detectors. Addition-<lb/>ally, electroweak bosons are copiously produced in the col-<lb/>lisions, being one of the most common processes, and their <lb/>signal is considerably clean in the leptonic channels (espe-<lb/>cially in the Z boson case). <lb/>All the studies presented here share similar criteria for <lb/>W and Z selection and reconstruction. Z bosons decay into <lb/>two electrons or two muons approximately 10% of the time. <lb/>These events are characterized by two high p T , isolated <lb/>electrons or muons. The strategy in both experiments to se-<lb/>lect Z boson events is based on these characteristics, look-<lb/>ing for energetic leptons (muons or electrons) not recon-<lb/>structed within a jet. Quality criteria applied on the lep-<lb/>tons are necessary to avoid bad reconstructions, bad p T <lb/>measurements and to remove punch-through, cosmic rays <lb/>and decays in flight. The invariant mass distribution for Z <lb/>bosons decaying into two electrons after selection is shown <lb/>in Fig. 1, in the ATLAS case. The distributions in the muon <lb/>channel and in the CMS case are similar. W bosons de-<lb/>cay into one electron (muon) plus an electronic neutrino <lb/>(muonic neutrino) approx. 10% of the times per channel. <lb/>In both cases we consider in the final state the existence of <lb/>an energetic lepton (muon or electron) plus an imbalance <lb/>of energy in the transverse plane (missing transverse en-<lb/>ergy, MET). The reconstruction of such a missing energy <lb/>points generally to the existence of an undetected neutrino. <lb/>The W boson signal is not as clean as the Z boson one <lb/>due to the presence of the neutrino. Extra requirements <lb/>are applied to remove backgrounds: quality criteria and <lb/>electron p T (muon p T ) requirements (similar to the Z bo-<lb/>son ones), Drell-Yan veto (removing events with two en-<lb/>ergetic leptons, to avoid Z bosons to be reconstructed as <lb/>W bosons). In order to get a cleaner sample of W bosons, <lb/>several studies require the transverse mass of the system <lb/>[GeV] <lb/>ee <lb/>m <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>100 <lb/>110 <lb/>Events / 1 GeV <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1200 <lb/>1400 <lb/>= 7 TeV) <lb/>s <lb/>Data 2010 ( <lb/>ee <lb/>→ <lb/>Z <lb/>QCD <lb/>ATLAS <lb/>-1 <lb/>L dt = 36 pb <lb/>∫ <lb/>ee <lb/>→ <lb/>Central Z <lb/>Fig. 1. Z boson invariant mass distribution in the electron channel <lb/>(ATLAS). <lb/>lepton-neutrino, defined as: <lb/>M T = 2p T (µ)MET(1 − cos(∆φ µMET )) <lb/>(1) <lb/>to be higher than a certain value, generally 40-50 GeV (this <lb/>latter requirement removes almost completely the multijet <lb/>background, dominant background in the low M T region). <lb/>In this equation, p T (µ) is the muon transverse momentum, <lb/>MET the missing transverse energy and ∆φ µMET the angle <lb/>between the muon and the MET. <lb/>2 Inclusive electroweak boson production <lb/>The electroweak boson production is studied in both CMS <lb/>and ATLAS in the three leptonic channels. The W and Z <lb/>boson inclusive cross section production through their de-<lb/>cay into electrons are muons is the first electroweak mea-<lb/>surement published by both experiments ( [3], [4]). It is <lb/>measured by counting the number of events reconstructed <lb/>as W or Z bosons for a certain luminosity and correcting <lb/>for lepton reconstruction and identification efficiencies and <lb/>detector acceptance. In the W boson case, the selection <lb/>is optimized to get a reasonably clean sample consisting <lb/>of more than 80% of signal in the Jacobian peak region. <lb/></body>

			<front>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 2.0, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, <lb/>and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/>EPJ Web of Conferences <lb/>DOI: 10.1051/ <lb/>C Owned by the authors, published by EDP Sciences, 2012 <lb/>, <lb/>epjconf 20122 <lb/>/ <lb/>28 0 <lb/>(2012) <lb/>80 <lb/>6007 <lb/>6007 <lb/>Article available at http://www.epj-conferences.org or http://dx.doi.org/10.1051/epjconf/20122806007 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">EPJ Web of Conferences <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 2. Ratio of results of CMS with respect to the theoretical pre-<lb/>diction. All the results are in agreement with the SM prediction <lb/>(CMS). <lb/>The analysis slightly differs in CMS and ATLAS in this <lb/>measurement. ATLAS performs a more restrictive selec-<lb/>tion (removing events with low M T or low MET). In CMS <lb/>a fit to the MET variable is used to extract the signal nor-<lb/>malization. The Z boson case is easier since it is almost <lb/>background free (less than 1%). The results published are <lb/>presented in the form of total and fiducial cross sections <lb/>and ratios of cross sections. This latter measurement is a <lb/>more stringent test of the SM since many systematic uncer-<lb/>tainties are removed or reduced when computing the ratios <lb/>(e.g. the dominant luminosity uncertainty). The total sys-<lb/>tematic uncertainty (excluded luminosity) is of the order of <lb/>2% for both experiments. All the results are in agreement <lb/>with the SM prediction. A summary of results published <lb/>by CMS is shown in Fig. 2. <lb/>W and Z bosons are also studied in the tau decay mode. <lb/>The W boson production cross section when decaying into <lb/>τ and a ν τ neutrino is measured by the ATLAS collabo-<lb/>ration [5] (CMS [6] also published preliminary results). <lb/>The properties of the tau jet (when the tau decays hadroni-<lb/>cally) are exploited to reconstruct these events. They select <lb/>events with low multiplicity, high collimated jets or with <lb/>non-zero flight distance using a boosted decision tree that <lb/>includes all these properties. A clear W to tau signal is ob-<lb/>served (more than 80% signal). The main difficulty in this <lb/>analysis is the electroweak background (W boson decays <lb/>into electrons and muons and Z boson leptonic decays) that <lb/>amounts to some 13% and has a similar shape in the trans-<lb/>verse mass as the signal (see Fig. 3). The cross section is <lb/>measured with an approx. 23% systematic uncertainty and <lb/>is compatible with the SM prediction. The Z boson sig-<lb/>nature in the tau channel is cleaner. It is studied in both <lb/>CMS [8] and ATLAS [7] in four final states: τ µ τ µ , τ µ τ e , <lb/>τ µ τ had , τ e τ had . The electroweak background is partially re-<lb/>moved by inverting the M T and MET requirements. The <lb/>τ l τ had channel is the one with the biggest branching ratio, <lb/>but we have to cope with important backgrounds, mainly <lb/>QCD multijet events. The τ e τ µ is the cleanest since no <lb/>electroweak process can produce both leptons in the same <lb/>event apart from the rare diboson processes. The τ µ τ µ is <lb/>highly affected by the Z → µµ process. A boosted deci-<lb/>sion tree in 5 kinematic variables sensitive to the kinemat-<lb/>ical differences of muons from both processes is used by <lb/>ATLAS. CMS uses a likelihood in 4 variables to separate <lb/>signal and electroweak background. A competitive result <lb/>is obtained after combining the results coming from the 4 <lb/>final states (see Fig. 4). The total cross section is measured <lb/>[GeV] <lb/>T <lb/>m <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 120 140 <lb/>Number of events / 5 GeV <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 120 140 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 120 140 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 120 140 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 120 140 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 120 140 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 120 140 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 120 140 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 ATLAS <lb/>-1 <lb/>L dt = 34 pb <lb/>∫ <lb/>= 7 TeV) <lb/>s <lb/>Data 2010 ( <lb/>τ <lb/>ν <lb/>h <lb/>τ <lb/>→ <lb/>W <lb/>EW background <lb/>QCD background (C) <lb/>Fig. 3. M T distribution for the decay of the W boson into τ and <lb/>neutrino for data (dots), signal (blue), electroweak background <lb/>(green) and QCD background (white) (ATLAS). <lb/>&lt;116 GeV) [nb] <lb/>inv <lb/>ll, 66&lt;m <lb/>→ <lb/>(Z <lb/>σ <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>-1 <lb/>36pb <lb/>combined <lb/>τ <lb/>τ <lb/>→ <lb/>Z <lb/>-1 <lb/>0.3pb <lb/>µ <lb/>µ <lb/>ee/ <lb/>→ <lb/>Z <lb/>h <lb/>τ <lb/>µ <lb/>τ <lb/>h <lb/>τ <lb/>e <lb/>τ <lb/>µ <lb/>τ <lb/>e <lb/>τ <lb/>µ <lb/>τ <lb/>µ <lb/>τ <lb/>Stat <lb/>Stat <lb/>⊕ <lb/>Syst <lb/>Lumi <lb/>⊕ <lb/>Stat <lb/>⊕ <lb/>Syst <lb/>Theory (NNLO) <lb/>Stat <lb/>Stat <lb/>⊕ <lb/>Syst <lb/>Lumi <lb/>⊕ <lb/>Stat <lb/>⊕ <lb/>Syst <lb/>Theory (NNLO) <lb/>ATLAS <lb/>&lt;116 GeV) [nb] <lb/>inv <lb/>ll, 66&lt;m <lb/>→ <lb/>(Z <lb/>σ <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>-1 <lb/>36pb <lb/>combined <lb/>τ <lb/>τ <lb/>→ <lb/>Z <lb/>-1 <lb/>0.3pb <lb/>µ <lb/>µ <lb/>ee/ <lb/>→ <lb/>Z <lb/>h <lb/>τ <lb/>µ <lb/>τ <lb/>h <lb/>τ <lb/>e <lb/>τ <lb/>µ <lb/>τ <lb/>e <lb/>τ <lb/>µ <lb/>τ <lb/>µ <lb/>τ <lb/>Fig. 4. Z boson cross section production studied in the τ channel <lb/>in the four final states: τ µ τ µ , τ µ τ e , τ µ τ had , τ e τ had and compared <lb/>with the theoretical prediction (Gray band) and the cross section <lb/>given in other leptonic decays (ATLAS). <lb/>with approx. 10% uncertainty by both experiments with a <lb/>central value compatible with the SM prediction. <lb/>2.1 Differential distributions <lb/>The differential distributions as a function of boson rapid-<lb/>ity and momentum give valuable information, especially <lb/>on the proton composition (PDFs). The Z boson produc-<lb/>tion is studied in bins of the boson rapidity. The proce-<lb/>dure for the cross section measurement is similar to that <lb/>of the total inclusive production. Results for both muons <lb/>and electrons, and the combination of them are presented <lb/>by both collaborations. In CMS [9] and ATLAS [4] they <lb/>exploit the use of the forward calorimeters to reconstruct <lb/>electrons at high rapidities. In this region the resolution is <lb/>worse but provides information for the PDFs in a new (Q 2 -<lb/>x) region. The results are compatible with the expectations <lb/>given by the reference MC in CMS and ATLAS. System-<lb/>atic uncertainties range from 3% in the central region to <lb/>7% in the forward. Fig. 5 shows the differential rapidity <lb/>distribution for Z bosons in CMS. <lb/>The Z and W boson production is also studied as a <lb/>function of the boson p T in both experiments. Of special <lb/>interest are the low p T and high p T regions of the spec-<lb/>trum. Low p T region uncertainties are dominated by non-<lb/>perturbative QCD and the MC tuning. For the Z boson, in <lb/>CMS [9] the official tune (PYTHIA [15] Z2) gives the best <lb/>agreement data-MC. In ATLAS [11] RESBOS [17] is in <lb/>optimal agreement (see Fig. 6). General disagreement is <lb/>observed in the high p T region in both experiments with <lb/></body>

			<page>06007-p.2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">HCP 2011 <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 5. The normalized differential cross section for Z bosons as <lb/>a function of the absolute value of rapidity, combining the muon <lb/>and electron channels. The error bars correspond to the experi-<lb/>mental statistical and systematic uncertainties. <lb/>[GeV] <lb/>Z <lb/>T <lb/>p <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>[1/GeV] <lb/>Z <lb/>T <lb/>/dp <lb/>fid <lb/>σ <lb/>d <lb/>fid <lb/>σ <lb/>1/ <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>ATLAS <lb/>-1 <lb/>L dt = 35-40 pb <lb/>∫ <lb/>µ <lb/>µ <lb/>Combined ee+ <lb/>Data 2010 <lb/>RESBOS <lb/>PYTHIA <lb/>| &lt; 2.4 <lb/>l <lb/>η <lb/>| <lb/>&gt; 20 GeV <lb/>l <lb/>T <lb/>p <lb/>&lt; 116 GeV <lb/>ll <lb/>66 GeV &lt; m <lb/>Fig. 6. The combined normalized differential cross section as a <lb/>function of p T (Z) for the range p T (Z)&lt;30 GeV compared to the <lb/>predictions of RESBOS and PYTHIA. The error bars shown in-<lb/>clude statistical and systematic uncertainties (ATLAS). <lb/>the theoretical predictions at NNLO. RESBOS in ATLAS <lb/>and POWHEG [16]+PYTHIA Z2 in CMS also show dis-<lb/>crepancies in the high p T region as can be seen in Fig. 7. <lb/>Something similar happens for the W boson [12], where a <lb/>general disagreement in the high p T region (more than 100 <lb/>GeV) is observed in ATLAS. MCatNLO [18] and POWHEG+ <lb/>PYTHIA give a prediction that differs by more than 20% in <lb/>the high p T region with respect to data (giving the best pre-<lb/>diction in the low domain). Despite the general disagree-<lb/>ment shown in these studies, a similar trend is observed <lb/>in the Z and W boson spectrum (see Fig. 8), supporting <lb/>the universality of strong interactions effects in W and Z <lb/>production. A better understanding of the p T spectrum is <lb/>needed, for example, to achieve the precision required in <lb/>future W mass measurements. <lb/>W + and W − are not symmetrically produced in LHC <lb/>collisions. At <lb/>√ <lb/>s = 7 TeV the expected ratio of W + over <lb/>W − is roughly 1.4 and varies with the rapidity of the bo-<lb/>son. The accessible variable in LHC experiments to test <lb/>this asymmetry is the lepton charge asymmetry defined as: <lb/>A(η) = <lb/>dσ/dη(W + → l + ν) − dσ/dη(W − → l − ν) <lb/>dσ/dη(W + → l + ν) + dσ/dη(W − → l − ν) <lb/>(2) <lb/>[GeV] <lb/>Z <lb/>T <lb/>p <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>2 <lb/>10 <lb/>Data (Prediction) / RESBOS <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>µ <lb/>µ <lb/>Combined ee+ <lb/>Data 2010 <lb/>RESBOS <lb/>) <lb/>s <lb/>α <lb/>FEWZ O( <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>s <lb/>α <lb/>FEWZ O( <lb/>| &lt; 2.4 <lb/>l <lb/>η <lb/>| <lb/>&gt; 20 GeV <lb/>l <lb/>T <lb/>p <lb/>&lt; 116 GeV <lb/>ll <lb/>66 GeV &lt; m <lb/>ATLAS <lb/>-1 <lb/>L dt = 35-40 pb <lb/>∫ <lb/>Fig. 7. Ratios of the combined data and the FEWZ predictions <lb/>at NLO and NNLO over the RESBOS prediction for the normal-<lb/>ized differential cross section as a function of p T (Z). The FEWZ <lb/>predictions are shown with combined scale, α s , and PDF uncer-<lb/>tainties. The data points are shown with combined statistical and <lb/>systematic uncertainty (ATLAS). <lb/>[GeV] <lb/>V <lb/>T <lb/>p <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>300 <lb/>Data / RESBOS <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.3 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>-1 <lb/>Ldt = 30-40 pb <lb/>∫ <lb/>= 7 TeV <lb/>s <lb/>Data 2010, <lb/>ATLAS <lb/>ν <lb/>l <lb/>→ <lb/>W <lb/>ll <lb/>→ <lb/>Z <lb/>Fig. 8. Ratio of the combined electron and muon data to the RES-<lb/>BOS prediction, overlaid with the analogous ratio for the Z trans-<lb/>verse momentum distribution measured by ATLAS. <lb/>CMS and ATLAS published results for this charge asym-<lb/>metry with 36 pb −1 in the electron and muon channels, <lb/>(CMS also published results with 234 pb −1 in the muon <lb/>one). They are compared in both experiments with differ-<lb/>ent PDF sets. The best agreement in CMS [10] and AT-<lb/>LAS [4] is for the CT10 PDF set. CMS and ATLAS results <lb/>are also combined with LHCb results, giving information <lb/>on a wide pseudorapidity range (|η| ≤ 4), see Fig. 9. <lb/>2.2 Other properties <lb/>W polarization. W bosons at LHC are left polarized at <lb/>high p T (≈ 75%). This is a consequence of the left-handed <lb/>nature of the electroweak interactions and the prevalence <lb/>of valence quarks in protons. The lepton projection defined <lb/>as: <lb/>L p = <lb/>p T (l) • p T (W) <lb/>|p T (W)| 2 <lb/>(3) <lb/>is a variable strongly correlated with the W polarization <lb/>(the correlation increasing with the boson p T ). The first ob-<lb/>servation of the W polarization at the LHC was performed <lb/></body>

			<page>06007-p.3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">EPJ Web of Conferences <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 9. W charge asymmetry as a function of the muon pseudora-<lb/>pidity with data from ATLAS, CMS and LHCb, compared with <lb/>the MC prediction. <lb/>Fig. 10. Lepton polarization projection variable for the longitu-<lb/>dinal, left and right polarization of the W in the muon channel <lb/>(CMS). <lb/>by CMS [13].To better observe the polarization, only high <lb/>p T W bosons are analyzed (larger than 50 GeV). A fit to <lb/>the lepton projection variable is performed which is sensi-<lb/>tive to the three components (left, right and longitudinal) <lb/>for electrons and muons, see Fig. 10. A left polarization is <lb/>observed in this study (≈ 20%), reduced with respect to the <lb/>theoretical one due to kinematic effects and other subpro-<lb/>cesses <lb/>Electroweak mixing angle. This study performed by the <lb/>CMS collaboration [14] uses 1.1 fb −1 of data. In this study, <lb/>all the electroweak parameters are fixed to their SM val-<lb/>ues but the effective value of the sin θ W (sin θ e f f ) which is <lb/>left free to vary. A multivariate analysis of the three most <lb/>sensitive variables to this parameter (boson rapidity, invari-<lb/>ant mass and Collins-Soper angle) is used to extract it. The <lb/>result: <lb/>sin θ e f f = 0.2287 ± 0.002 (stat.) ± 0.0025 (sys.) (4) <lb/>is in agreement with the SM prediction. <lb/>3 Conclusions <lb/>In this document, the results on W and Z boson properties <lb/>by both ATLAS and CMS using data from proton-proton <lb/>collisions at <lb/>√ <lb/>s = 7 TeV are presented. In general, they <lb/>show a good agreement with the Standard Model predic-<lb/>tions. A few observed deviations, particulary in the study <lb/>of the transverse momenta of W and Z bosons, require <lb/>more dedicated studies. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. The ATLAS experiment at the CERN Large <lb/>Hadron Collider, The ATLAS Collaboration, <lb/>JINST3(2008)S08003. <lb/>2. The CMS experiment at the CERN LHC, The CMS <lb/>Collaboration, JINST3(2008)S08004. <lb/> 3. Measurement of the inclusive W and Z production cross <lb/>sections in pp collisions at <lb/>√ <lb/>s = 7 TeV with the CMS ex-<lb/>periment, The CMS Collaboration, JHEP10(2011)132. <lb/>4. Measurement of the inclusive W+-and Z/gamma cross <lb/>sections in the electron and muon decay channels in pp <lb/>collisions at <lb/>√ <lb/>s = 7 TeV with the ATLAS detector, The <lb/>ATLAS Collaboration, arXiv:1109.5141 [hep-ex] <lb/>5. Measurement of the W → τν cross section in pp colli-<lb/>sions at <lb/>√ <lb/>s = 7 TeV with the ATLAS experiment, The <lb/>ATLAS Collaboration, Phys. Let. B706(2012)276-294. <lb/>6. Measurement of the weak-mixing angle in the Drell-<lb/>Yan process in proton-proton collisions at the LHC, The <lb/>CMS Collaboration, Phys. Rev. D84(2011)112002. <lb/>7. Measurement of the Z → ττ cross section with the <lb/>ATLAS detector, The ATLAS Collaboration, Phys. Rev. <lb/>D84(2011)112006. <lb/>8. Measurement of the inclusive Z cross section via decays <lb/>to tau pairs in pp collisions at <lb/>√ <lb/>s = 7 TeV, The CMS <lb/>Collaboration, JHEP08(2011)117. <lb/>9. Measurement of the Rapidity and Transverse Momen-<lb/>tum Distributions of Z Bosons in pp Collisions at <lb/>√ <lb/>s = 7 <lb/>TeV, The CMS Collaboration, arXiv:1110.4973v1 [hep-<lb/>ex] <lb/>10. Measurement of the lepton charge asymmetry in inclu-<lb/>sive W production in pp collisions at <lb/>√ <lb/>s = 7 TeV, The <lb/>CMS Collaboration, JHEP04(2011)050. <lb/>11. Measurement of the transverse momentum distribu-<lb/>tion of Z/γ* bosons in proton-proton collisions at <lb/>√ <lb/>s = <lb/>7 TeV with the ATLAS detector, The ATLAS Collabora-<lb/>tion, Phys. Let. B705(2011)415-434. <lb/>12. Measurement of the transverse momentum distribu-<lb/>tion of W bosons in pp collisions at <lb/>√ <lb/>s = 7 TeV <lb/>with the ATLAS detector, The ATLAS Collaboration, <lb/>arXiv1108.6308v2 [hep-ex] <lb/>13. Measurement of the Polarization of W Bosons <lb/>with Large Transverse Momenta in W+jets Events <lb/>at the LHC, The CMS Collaboration, Phys. Rev. <lb/>Lett.107(2011)021802. <lb/>14. Measurement of the weak mixing angle with the Drell-<lb/>Yan process in proton-proton collisions at the LHC, The <lb/>CMS Collaboration, Phys. Rev. D84(2011)112002 <lb/>15. PYTHIA 6.2: Physics and manual, T. Sjostrand et al., <lb/>arXiv:hep-ph/0108264 <lb/>16. A new method for combining NLO QCD with shower <lb/>Monte Carlo algorithms, P. Nason, JHEP11(2004)040. <lb/>17. Soft gluon effects on lepton pairs at hadron colliders, <lb/>C. Balazs, C.P. Yuan, Phys. Rev. D56(1997)5558. <lb/>18. Matching NLO QCD computations and parton <lb/>shower simulations, S. Frixione, B. R. Webber, <lb/>JHEP06(2002)029. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>06007-p.4</page>

	</text>
</tei>
