<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage>This is the accepted manuscript made available via CHORUS. The article has been <lb/>published as: <lb/>Studies of the decays D^{0}→K_{S}^{0}K^{-}π^{+} <lb/>and D^{0}→K_{S}^{0}K^{+}π^{-} <lb/>J. Insler et al. (CLEO Collaboration) <lb/>Phys. Rev. D 85, 092016 -Published 29 May 2012 <lb/>DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.85.092016 <lb/></titlePage>

			<front>DQ11056 <lb/> R E V <lb/>I E W <lb/>C O <lb/>P Y <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>T <lb/>F O <lb/>R <lb/>D <lb/>I S T R I B U <lb/>T I O <lb/>N <lb/>Studies of the decays D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K − π + and D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K + π − <lb/> J. Insler, 1 H. Muramatsu, 1 C. S. Park, 1 L. J. Pearson, 1 E. H. Thorndike, 1 S. Ricciardi, 2 C. Thomas, 2, 3 M. Artuso, 4 <lb/>S. Blusk, 4 R. Mountain, 4 T. Skwarnicki, 4 S. Stone, 4 J. C. Wang, 4 L. M. Zhang, 4 G. Bonvicini, 5 D. Cinabro, 5 <lb/>M. J. Smith, 5 P. Zhou, 5 T. Gershon, 6 P. Naik, 7 J. Rademacker, 7 K. W. Edwards, 8 K. Randrianarivony, 8 <lb/>R. A. Briere, 9 H. Vogel, 9 P. U. E. Onyisi, 10 J. L. Rosner, 10 J. P. Alexander, 11 D. G. Cassel, 11 S. Das, 11 <lb/>R. Ehrlich, 11 L. Gibbons, 11 S. W. Gray, 11 D. L. Hartill, 11 D. L. Kreinick, 11 V. E. Kuznetsov, 11 J. R. Patterson, 11 <lb/>D. Peterson, 11 D. Riley, 11 A. Ryd, 11 A. J. Sadoff, 11 X. Shi, 11 W. M. Sun, 11 J. Yelton, 12 P. Rubin, 13 N. Lowrey, 14 <lb/>S. Mehrabyan, 14 M. Selen, 14 J. Wiss, 14 J. Libby, 15 M. Kornicer, 16 R. E. Mitchell, 16 D. Besson, 17 T. K. Pedlar, 18 <lb/>D. Cronin-Hennessy, 19 J. Hietala, 19 S. Dobbs, 20 Z. Metreveli, 20 K. K. Seth, 20 A. Tomaradze, 20 T. Xiao, 20 <lb/>D. Johnson, 3 S. Malde, 3 L. Martin, 3 A. Powell, 3 G. Wilkinson, 3 D. M. Asner, 21 G. Tatishvili, 21 J. Y. Ge, 22 <lb/>D. H. Miller, 22 I. P. J. Shipsey, 22 B. Xin, 22 G. S. Adams, 23 J. Napolitano, 23 and K. M. Ecklund 24 <lb/>(CLEO Collaboration) <lb/>1 University of Rochester, Rochester, New York 14627, USA <lb/>2 STFC Rutherford Appleton Laboratory, Chilton, <lb/>Didcot, Oxfordshire, OX11 0QX, United Kingdom <lb/>3 University of Oxford, Oxford OX1 3RH, United Kingdom <lb/>4 Syracuse University, Syracuse, New York 13244, USA <lb/>5 Wayne State University, Detroit, Michigan 48202, USA <lb/>6 University of Warwick, Coventry CV4 7AL, United Kingdom <lb/>7 University of Bristol, Bristol BS8 1TL, United Kingdom <lb/>8 Carleton University, Ottawa, Ontario, Canada K1S 5B6 <lb/>9 Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania 15213, USA <lb/>10 University of Chicago, Chicago, Illinois 60637, USA <lb/>11 Cornell University, Ithaca, New York 14853, USA <lb/>12 University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida 32611, USA <lb/>13 George Mason University, Fairfax, Virginia 22030, USA <lb/>14 University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign, Illinois 61801, USA <lb/>15 Indian Institute of Technology Madras, Chennai, Tamil Nadu 600036, India <lb/>16 Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana 47405, USA <lb/>17 University of Kansas, Lawrence, Kansas 66045, USA <lb/>18 Luther College, Decorah, Iowa 52101, USA <lb/>19 University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, Minnesota 55455, USA <lb/>20 Northwestern University, Evanston, Illinois 60208, USA <lb/>21 Pacific Northwest National Laboratory, Richland, WA 99352 <lb/>22 Purdue University, West Lafayette, Indiana 47907, USA <lb/>23 Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Troy, New York 12180, USA <lb/>24 Rice University, Houston, Texas 77005, USA <lb/> The first measurements of the coherence factor R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ and the average strong-phase difference <lb/>δ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>in D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K ∓ π ± decays are reported. These parameters can be used to improve the <lb/>determination of the unitary triangle angle γ in B − → DK − decays, where D is either a D 0 or a <lb/>D 0 meson decaying to the same final state, and also in studies of charm mixing. The measurements <lb/>of the coherence factor and strong-phase difference are made using quantum-correlated, fully-<lb/>reconstructed D 0 D 0 pairs produced in e + e − collisions at the ψ(3770) resonance. The measured <lb/>values are R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ = 0.73 ± 0.08 and δ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>= (8.3 ± 15.2) • for an unrestricted kinematic region <lb/>and RK * K = 1.00 ± 0.16 and δ K * K <lb/>D <lb/>= (26.5 ± 15.8) • for a region where the combined K 0 <lb/>S π ± <lb/>invariant mass is within 100 MeV/c 2 of the K * (892) ± mass. These results indicate a significant <lb/>level of coherence in the decay. In addition, isobar models are presented for the two decays, which <lb/>show the dominance of the K * (892) ± resonance. The branching ratio B(D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K + π − )/B(D 0 → <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K − π + ) is determined to be 0.592 ± 0.044 (stat.) ± 0.018 (syst.), which is more precise than <lb/>previous measurements. <lb/>PACS numbers: 13.25.Ft,12.15.Hh,14.40.Lb,11.80.Et <lb/></front>

			<body>I. INTRODUCTION <lb/>Decays of the D 0 meson to the K 0 <lb/>S K ∓ π ± final state <lb/>occur via a singly-Cabibbo-suppressed (SCS) transition. <lb/>There are two possible decays, D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K − π + and <lb/>D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K + π − (charge conjugation is implied through-<lb/>out the paper unless otherwise specified), where the first <lb/>is decay is favored with respect to the second. These twin <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>decays are of interest for a variety of reasons. Firstly <lb/>when produced through a B − → DK − decay, where D <lb/>is either a D 0 or D 0 , they can be exploited to measure <lb/>the Cabibbo-Kobayashi-Maskawa (CKM) phase γ [1]. <lb/>Secondly a time-dependent study can be used to deter-<lb/>mine charm mixing parameters and probe for charm CP <lb/>violation [2]. Finally, examination of the resonant sub-<lb/>structure of the decays allows for tests of SU(3) flavor <lb/>symmetry in charm meson decays [3]. <lb/>This paper describes several measurements performed <lb/>with data collected by the CLEO experiment that are <lb/>valuable for each of these purposes. These are a first de-<lb/>termination of the coherence factor and average strong-<lb/>phase difference for the two decays, a determination of <lb/>the relative branching ratio of the decays that is more <lb/>precise than previous measurements [4], and the presen-<lb/>tation of isobar models to describe each decay. The co-<lb/>herence factor R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ and the average strong-phase dif-<lb/>ference δ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>[5] for D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K ∓ π ± are measured us-<lb/>ing quantum-correlated, fully-reconstructed D 0 D 0 pairs <lb/>produced in e + e − collisions at the ψ(3770) resonance. <lb/>Knowledge of these parameters improves the sensitivity <lb/>of measurements of the unitary triangle angle γ using B − <lb/>meson decays to DK − where the D decays to K 0 <lb/>S K − π + <lb/>or K 0 <lb/>S K + π − . To probe for the effects of physics beyond <lb/>the standard model, it will be necessary to over-constrain <lb/>the CKM quark-mixing matrix. An accurate measure-<lb/>ment of γ in B → DK decays is of particular impor-<lb/>tance as the extracted phase is robust against new physics <lb/>contributions, thus providing a standard model reference <lb/>against which other measurements can be compared. The <lb/>sensitivity to γ comes from the interference of b → u and <lb/>b → c quark transitions. The weak phase between these <lb/>two transitions is −γ. The amplitudes are related by <lb/>A(B − → D0 K − )/A(B − → D 0 K − ) = r B e i(δ b −γ) , where <lb/>r B has a value around 0.1 and is the absolute ampli-<lb/>tude ratio, and δ B is the strong-phase difference. Sen-<lb/>sitivity to γ is obtained by comparing the four separate <lb/>decay rates involving B − and B + , and the two possi-<lb/>ble D final states. This method is directly analogous <lb/>to the ADS method [6], originally proposed to exploit <lb/>Cabibbo-favored (CF) and doubly-Cabibbo-suppressed <lb/>(DCS) decays such as Kπ, Kπππ, and Kππ 0 , rather <lb/>than the SCS modes under consideration here. In the <lb/>case of decays to multi-body flavor specific final states <lb/>it is necessary to take into account that the amplitude <lb/>ratio of D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K − π + and D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K + π − and the <lb/>strong-phase difference will vary over phase space. Rate <lb/>equations for different final states are given by [5] <lb/>Γ(B ∓ → D(K 0 <lb/>S K ∓ π ± )K ∓ ) ∝ 1 + (r B r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>) 2 + 2r B r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ cos(δ B − δ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>∓ γ), <lb/>(1) <lb/>Γ(B ∓ → D(K 0 <lb/>S K ± π ∓ )K ∓ ) ∝ (r B ) 2 + (r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>) 2 + 2r B r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ cos(δ B + δ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>∓ γ), <lb/>(2) <lb/>where R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ , δ K 0 <lb/>S Kπ , and r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>are defined as: <lb/>R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ e <lb/>−iδ K 0 <lb/>S <lb/>Kπ = <lb/>A K 0 <lb/>S K − π + (m 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K , m 2 <lb/>Kπ )A K 0 <lb/>S K + π − (m 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K , m 2 <lb/>Kπ )dm 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K dm 2 <lb/>Kπ <lb/>A K 0 <lb/>S K − π + A K 0 <lb/>S K + π − <lb/>, <lb/>(3) <lb/>and r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>= <lb/>A K 0 <lb/>S K + π − <lb/>A K 0 <lb/>S K − π + <lb/>. <lb/>(4) <lb/>Here, A K 0 <lb/>S K ∓ π ± (m 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K , m 2 <lb/>Kπ ) is the amplitude for D 0 → <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K ∓ π ± at a point in multi-body phase space de-<lb/>scribed by the square of the invariant mass of the <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K and Kπ pairs, (m 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K , m 2 <lb/>Kπ ) respectively, and <lb/>A 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K ∓ π ± = |A K 0 <lb/>S K ∓ π ± (m 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K , m 2 <lb/>Kπ )| 2 dm 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K dm 2 <lb/>Kπ . <lb/>Analogous equations can be written for the decays D 0 → <lb/>K − π + π − π + and D 0 → K − π + π 0 and the coherence fac-<lb/>tors and average strong-phase differences for these final <lb/>states have already been measured [7]. One difference be-<lb/>tween the K ∓ π ± , K ∓ π ± π + π − and K ∓ π ± π 0 modes and <lb/>the K 0 <lb/>S K ∓ π ± mode is that the value r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>is approx-<lb/>imately ten times larger than the corresponding param-<lb/>eters for the other decays. The larger value for r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>occurs because both final states occur via SCS transi-<lb/>tions, while in the case of the K ∓ π ± , K ∓ π ± π + π − and <lb/>K ∓ π ± π 0 decay modes one transition is CF and the other <lb/>DCS. The larger value of r D means that the per-event <lb/>sensitivity to γ from the D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K − π + decays [Eq. (1)] <lb/>is increased in comparison to D 0 → K − π + decays, while <lb/>the per-event sensitivity to γ from the D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K + π − <lb/>decays [Eq. (2)] is reduced in comparison to D 0 → K + π − <lb/>decays. The overall sensitivity to γ remains significant <lb/>if the coherence is large. Therefore knowledge of the co-<lb/>herence factor in D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K ∓ π ± decays is valuable, <lb/>as it enables these channels to be added to the set of <lb/>modes with which γ can be measured using B − → DK − <lb/>decays. The coherence factor and average strong-phase <lb/>difference are also valuable for time-dependent charm-<lb/>mixing measurements as described in [2]. <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>In a region around a resonance that is prominent in <lb/>both decays, the coherence is expected to be close to one. <lb/>A measurement in a bin of the Dalitz plot around such a <lb/>resonance is therefore also useful as the higher coherence <lb/>improves the per-event sensitivity in measurements to <lb/>determine γ. In the case of D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K ∓ π ± decays <lb/>a prominent intermediate resonance is the K * (892) ± . <lb/>Therefore, in this paper the measurement of the coher-<lb/>ence factor and the average strong-phase difference is <lb/>performed for both an unrestricted kinematic region and <lb/>also for events where the K 0 <lb/>S π ± invariant mass is within <lb/>100 MeV/c 2 of the nominal K * (892) ± mass [4]. The <lb/>value of 100 MeV/c 2 corresponds approximately to twice <lb/>the natural width of the K * (892) ± meson. <lb/>In addition to the measurement of the coherence factor <lb/>and average strong-phase difference, two further stud-<lb/>ies are also presented. First, there is the determination <lb/>of the isobar models for the two decays. These can be <lb/>used to test the predictions of SU(3)-flavor symmetry <lb/>in charm meson decays, in particular the relative am-<lb/>plitudes and phases of the modes D 0 → K * 0 K 0 and <lb/>D 0 → K * 0 K 0 [3]. The isobar models are used to estimate <lb/>systematic uncertainties for the other measurements pre-<lb/>sented here and will also be of use as an input to sim-<lb/>ulation when performing future measurements that ex-<lb/>ploit D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K ∓ π ± decays. Secondly, the ratio of the <lb/>branching fractions for the suppressed with respect to the <lb/>favored decay, B K 0 <lb/>S Kπ = B(D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K + π − )/B(D 0 → <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K − π + ), is measured. The current world average is <lb/>0.79 ± 0.19 [4], and a more accurate determination is <lb/>possible using CLEO data. This is valuable as a better <lb/>measurement of B K 0 <lb/>S Kπ allows for a corresponding im-<lb/>provement in the knowledge of r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>, which is an im-<lb/>portant input to the coherence factor analysis, and also <lb/>to measurements of γ and studies of charm mixing. The <lb/>isobar model studies are based on data collected both <lb/>at <lb/>√ <lb/>s = 3770 MeV and from charm mesons produced <lb/>in the continuum at higher energies; the branching ratio <lb/>measurement exploits only the latter sample. <lb/>This paper is organized as follows. Section II gives <lb/>an overview of the detector configurations used and the <lb/>data samples that are used for all the studies presented in <lb/>this paper. Section III describes the isobar models and <lb/>Sec. IV details the measurement of the ratio of branching <lb/>fractions. Section V describes the measurement of the <lb/>coherence factor and the strong-phase difference; and in <lb/>addition the sensitivity to γ using these results is dis-<lb/>cussed. A summary is given in Sec. VI. <lb/>II. DATA SAMPLES <lb/>Two different data samples collected by the CLEO III <lb/>and CLEO-c detectors are used for the studies in this <lb/>paper. A total of 15.3 fb −1 of data was collected by the <lb/>CLEO III detector. For these data the Cornell electron <lb/>storage ring (CESR) accelerator operated at a range of <lb/>energies from <lb/>√ <lb/>s = 7.0 GeV to <lb/>√ <lb/>s = 11.2 GeV. For the <lb/>data collected by the CLEO-c detector analyzed in this <lb/>paper, the CESR energy was <lb/>√ <lb/>s = 3770 MeV and an <lb/>integrated luminosity of 0.818 fb −1 of data was accumu-<lb/>lated. The CLEO III/CLEO-c detector was a solenoidal <lb/>detector which included a gaseous tracking system for <lb/>the measurement of charged particle momenta and ion-<lb/>ization energy loss, a ring-imaging Cherenkov (RICH) <lb/>detector to aid in particle identification, and a CsI crys-<lb/>tal calorimeter to measure the energy of electromagnetic <lb/>showers. The tracking system was particularly important <lb/>in defining the candidate signal sample for the measure-<lb/>ments in this paper. The CLEO III tracking system [8] <lb/>consisted of a silicon strip vertex detector and a large <lb/>drift chamber. The silicon was replaced by a six-layer <lb/>wire vertex detector in the CLEO-c configuration [9]. <lb/>The trackers achieved charged particle momentum reso-<lb/>lution of 0.35% (0.6%) at 1 GeV/c in the 1.5 T (1.0 T) <lb/>axial magnetic field used in CLEO III (CLEO-c) detec-<lb/>tor, respectively. The detectors are described in detail <lb/>elsewhere [10]. <lb/>The intermediate resonances contributing to the D 0 → <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K − π + and D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K + π − decays are not identical, <lb/>so in constructing isobar models it is necessary to know <lb/>the flavor of the decaying D 0 . The isobar models are de-<lb/>termined from flavor-tagged data from the CLEO III and <lb/>CLEO-c detectors. The data collected by CLEO III are <lb/>flavor-tagged using the decay D * + → D 0 π + , in which <lb/>the flavor of the decaying neutral D meson is inferred <lb/>from the charge of the pion. In the case of the data <lb/>collected by the CLEO-c detector the interaction of in-<lb/>terest is e + e − → ψ(3770) → D 0 D0 where one D me-<lb/>son, the signal side, decays to K 0 <lb/>S K ∓ π ± and the other, <lb/>the tag side, decays to either K ∓ π ± , K ∓ π ± π + π − , or <lb/>K ∓ π ± π 0 . Reconstruction of both D mesons is referred <lb/>to as a double tag. The flavor of the signal side D meson <lb/>is inferred from the charge of the kaon on the tag side, <lb/>taking advantage of the fact that the CF transition, for <lb/>example D 0 → K − π + , is dominant. Corrections to this <lb/>assumption from DCS decays are considered in the as-<lb/>signment of systematic uncertainties. The measurement <lb/>of B K 0 <lb/>S Kπ is performed using only the flavor-tagged data <lb/>from CLEO III. <lb/>The coherence factor measurement uses data only from <lb/>CLEO-c. To maximize the sensitivity to the coherence <lb/>factor a range of double tags are used. These include <lb/>the flavor tags used for the isobar model and also dou-<lb/>ble tags where the tag side D meson decays to a CP <lb/>eigenstate or K 0 <lb/>S,L π + π − , which are states of mixed CP . <lb/>Table I lists all the reconstructed double tags used for <lb/>the coherence factor measurement. The neutral mesons <lb/>in the final states are reconstructed via the following de-<lb/>cays: π 0 → γγ, K 0 <lb/>S → π + π − , ω → π + π − π 0 , η → γγ, <lb/>η → π + π − π 0 , and η ′ → η(γγ)π + π − . The K 0 <lb/>L meson is <lb/>not reconstructed directly. Its presence is inferred via a <lb/>missing-mass technique as described in Sec. II B. The <lb/>rest of this section describes the selection requirements <lb/>placed on all the different data types used to perform the <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>measurements presented in this paper. <lb/>TABLE I. A list of the CLEO-c double tags that are selected, <lb/>split by the category of the tag side D meson. All the listed <lb/>double tags are used in the coherence factor measurement, <lb/>but only the flavor double tags are used in the isobar model <lb/>analysis. <lb/>Tag group Tag side decays <lb/>Flavor <lb/>K ± π ∓ , K ± π ∓ π 0 , K ± π ∓ π + π − <lb/>CP even <lb/>K + K − , π + π − , K 0 <lb/>L π 0 , K 0 <lb/>L η, <lb/>K 0 <lb/>L ω, K 0 <lb/>L η ′ , K 0 <lb/>S π 0 π 0 <lb/>CP odd <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S π 0 , K 0 <lb/>S η, K 0 <lb/>S ω, K 0 <lb/>S η ′ , K 0 <lb/>L π 0 π 0 <lb/>Mixed CP K 0 <lb/>S π + π − , K 0 <lb/>L π + π − <lb/>A. Data from CLEO III <lb/>For the flavor-tagged D * data from CLEO III, various <lb/>requirements are made on properties of charged tracks, <lb/>composite particles and mass or vertex fits in order to <lb/>achieve samples of D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K ± π ∓ with high purity. <lb/>The kaon and pion from the D meson and the tagging <lb/>pion from the D * are required to pass close to the in-<lb/>teraction point: within 5 cm along the beam axis, and 5 <lb/>mm perpendicular to it. The cosine of the angle between <lb/>the track and the beam pipe is required to lie between <lb/>−0.9 and 0.9, to ensure that the track lies within the <lb/>detector acceptance. The momentum of the slow pion <lb/>track is required to be between 0.15 and 0.50 GeV/c. All <lb/>other tracks have a minimum momentum requirement <lb/>of 0.2 GeV/c and a maximum momentum of 5.0 GeV/c. <lb/>Charged pions are used to reconstruct the K 0 <lb/>S candidates <lb/>and the flight significance of the K 0 <lb/>S candidate is required <lb/>to be greater than 8, where the flight significance is given <lb/>by the measured flight distance divided by the measured <lb/>flight distance uncertainty. Kaons and pions are distin-<lb/>guished by using information from the RICH detector if <lb/>the momentum of the kaon track is above 500 MeV/c, <lb/>otherwise ionization energy loss from the drift chamber <lb/>is used. Kaon and pion candidates are combined with a <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S candidate to form a D 0 candidate. The slow pion <lb/>candidate is combined with the D 0 candidate to form a <lb/>D * candidate. In order to suppress combinatoric back-<lb/>grounds and backgrounds from B meson decays, the mo-<lb/>mentum of the D * is required to be greater than half <lb/>its maximum possible value (for a given beam energy). <lb/>Loose selection requirements are placed on the D 0 and <lb/>D * fitted vertex χ 2 to remove combinatoric candidates. <lb/>Signal candidates are chosen using the reconstructed <lb/>D 0 meson mass m D 0 and ∆m D = m D * − m D 0 , where <lb/>m D * is the reconstructed D * meson mass. The sig-<lb/>nal region encloses a region 15 MeV/c 2 either side of <lb/>the nominal D 0 meson mass, and 1 MeV/c 2 either side <lb/>of the nominal mass difference, where the nominal D 0 <lb/>and D * masses are taken from [4]. These ranges are <lb/>picked as they correspond approximately to a three stan-<lb/>dard deviation window in either the D 0 mass or ∆m D <lb/>projection, where the width of the signal is determined <lb/>by a fit to each distribution. In each case, when the <lb/>fit is performed on one variable the signal box cut has <lb/>been applied to the other variable. The signal m D 0 <lb/>distribution is described by a bifurcated Gaussian and <lb/>the background is described as a first-order polynomial. <lb/>In ∆m D the signal is also described by a bifurcated <lb/>Gaussian. The background shape is parametrized by <lb/>(∆m D /a) 2 [1−e −(∆mD−d)/c +b(∆m D /d−1)] where a, b, c, <lb/>and d are parameters determined by the fit. A correction <lb/>is required for D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K − π + decays as Monte Carlo <lb/>simulation studies indicate the presence of a peaking <lb/>background. This background is the D 0 → K − π + π + π − <lb/>decay misidentified as K 0 <lb/>S K − π + and contributes approx-<lb/>imately 2% to the peak. Monte Carlo simulation studies <lb/>indicate no other significant peaking backgrounds for ei-<lb/>ther decay. The signal yields from the fits are corrected <lb/>to remove the D 0 → K − π + π + π − contribution. The pu-<lb/>rities of the samples in the signal region are evaluated by <lb/>averaging the purity determined from the fits in both dis-<lb/>tributions, which are consistent with each other. The pu-<lb/>rity of the D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K − π + sample is (92.4 ± 0.5)% with <lb/>a signal yield of 640 ± 27 in the signal region after back-<lb/>ground subtraction. The purity of the D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K + π − <lb/>sample is (90.0 ± 0.7)% with a signal yield of 406 ± 24 in <lb/>the signal region. The given uncertainties on the purities <lb/>and signal yields are statistical only. Figure 1 shows the <lb/>D 0 mass distribution and fit projections for favored and <lb/>supressed decays after the signal window in ∆m D has <lb/>been applied. The signal yield determination is also per-<lb/>formed in the restricted kinematic region where the signal <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S and π ± have an invariant mass within 100 MeV/c 2 <lb/>of the nominal K * (892) ± resonance. In this restricted <lb/>region the signal yield is 445 ± 22 for D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K − π + <lb/>events and 166 ± 14 for D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K + π − events, and the <lb/>purities are (93.8 ± 0.9)% and (90.9 ± 1.2)% respectively. <lb/>B. Data from CLEO-c <lb/>A variety of double tags, as listed in Table I, are re-<lb/>constructed in the CLEO-c data. The standard CLEO-c <lb/>selection criteria for π + , π 0 and K + mesons are adopted <lb/>and are described in [11]. In addition to these criteria, <lb/>the K 0 <lb/>S vertex is required to be separated from the in-<lb/>teraction point by at least two standard deviations and <lb/>candidate K 0 <lb/>S → π + π − decays are required to have a <lb/>mass within 7.5 MeV/c 2 of the nominal mass. This cri-<lb/>terion is reduced to within 5.0 MeV/c 2 of the nominal <lb/>mass when the K 0 <lb/>S forms part of the K 0 <lb/>S K ∓ π ± signal <lb/>tag. This tighter cut is to reduce background from the <lb/>D 0 → K − π + π + π − decay faking the D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K − π + <lb/>signal. The η → γγ candidates are reconstructed in a <lb/>similar fashion to π 0 candidates with the requirement <lb/>that the invariant mass is within 42 MeV/c 2 of the nom-<lb/>inal mass; the same requirement is applied to η → πππ 0 <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>FIG. 1. The reconstructed mass distributions (points) of (a) D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K − π + and (b) D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K + π − in CLEO III data. The <lb/>signal window selection in ∆mD has been applied. The total fit projection (dark line) and background (light line) component <lb/>are also shown. The signal window in the reconstructed mass variable is indicated by the vertical lines. <lb/>candidates. Candidates for ω → πππ 0 decays are re-<lb/>quired to be within 20 MeV/c 2 of the nominal ω mass. <lb/>The η ′ → ηππ candidates are required to have an invari-<lb/>ant mass in the range 950 to 964 MeV/c 2 . All nominal <lb/>masses are taken from [4]. <lb/>For final states that do not contain a K 0 <lb/>L , two kine-<lb/>matic variables are considered: the beam-constrained <lb/>candidate mass m bc = s/(4c 4 ) − p 2 <lb/>D /c 2 , where p D is <lb/>the D candidate momentum, and ∆E = E D − <lb/>√ <lb/>s/2, <lb/>where E D is the sum of the energies of the daughters that <lb/>comprise the D meson candidate. Decays with correctly <lb/>identified signal and tag decays peak at the nominal D 0 <lb/>mass in m bc and zero in ∆E. Mode-dependent require-<lb/>ments are placed on the signal and tag candidates such <lb/>that ∆E is less than three standard deviations from zero. <lb/>The double-tag yield is determined by counting events in <lb/>signal and sideband regions of the [m bc (D sig ), m bc (D tag )] <lb/>plane. Figure 2 shows all the fully-reconstructed double <lb/>tags on the [m bc (D sig ), m bc (D tag )] plane with the signal <lb/>region marked S, and the sidebands illustrated. The rect-<lb/>angular sidebands are populated by decays where only <lb/>one of the D mesons has been correctly identified. The <lb/>triangular sidebands are sparsely populated by combi-<lb/>natoric background as neither D meson candidate has a <lb/>mass consistent with a D meson. The remaining narrow <lb/>diagonal sideband is populated with two types of events. <lb/>One of these is continuum background where the orig-<lb/>inal interaction was e + e − → q q, where q =u, d, or s. <lb/>The other type of background present in this sideband is <lb/>where tracks have been assigned to the wrong D meson. <lb/>Also shown in Fig. 2 are the projections of the signal D <lb/>meson mass in different tag groups. <lb/>The different sidebands contain contributions from dis-<lb/>tinct types of combinatorial background. The yields <lb/>in these sidebands are scaled and subtracted from the <lb/>yield in the signal region. There are some backgrounds <lb/>that peak in the signal region and hence cannot be <lb/>determined from the sidebands. These peaking back-<lb/>ground contributions are estimated from Monte Carlo <lb/>samples. EVTGEN [12] is used to generate the de-<lb/>cays and GEANT [13] is used to simulate the CLEO-c <lb/>detector response. A generic sample of Monte-Carlo-<lb/>simulated data of ψ(3770) → DD decays, with a size <lb/>corresponding to an integrated luminosity twenty times <lb/>that of data is used. The subsequent decay of the D 0 <lb/>or D + meson is to all known decay channels. A further <lb/>sample of simulated continuum data of e + e − → qq where <lb/>q is either the u, d, or s quark, with a size corresponding <lb/>to an integrated luminosity five times that of the data is <lb/>also analyzed. All signal events, determined from truth <lb/>information, are removed, and all background events that <lb/>pass the selection criteria for any double tag are used to <lb/>determine the peaking background for that double tag. <lb/>The background contribution from the continuum is de-<lb/>termined to be small in comparison to that from generic <lb/>DD decays. The samples are combined by scaling the <lb/>small continuum contribution to the integrated luminos-<lb/>ity size of the generic sample. The statistical uncertainty <lb/>due to the Monte Carlo background yields is very small <lb/>in comparison to the uncertainty on the data yields. The <lb/>uncertainty on the scale factor used to determine the <lb/>peaking background yields from Monte Carlo simulation <lb/>is 10%. This is determined by comparing all the double <lb/>tag sideband yields in data to those in Monte Carlo to <lb/>account for differences between Monte Carlo simulation <lb/>and data. <lb/>The largest peaking background to D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K − π + <lb/>decays that remains after selection is from D 0 → <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>FIG. 2. CLEO-c data distribution of fully-reconstructed double tags on the [m bc (Dsig), m bc (Dtag)] plane (a) where the signal <lb/>region is labeled S and the other indicated boxes are the sideband regions. The projections of the m bc (Dsig) are shown separately <lb/>for candidates that are tagged by (b) CP eigenstates, (c) the flavor states, and (d) K 0 <lb/>S π + π − . <lb/>K − π + π − π + decays where a π + π − pair forms a K 0 <lb/>S can-<lb/>didate. The background-subtracted signal region yields <lb/>and purities from flavor tags are given in Table II where <lb/>the errors include the statistical uncertainties from the <lb/>signal, sideband and Monte Carlo yields. Yields of other <lb/>fully-reconstructed CP double tags and the K 0 <lb/>S ππ tag <lb/>are given in Table III. For the K 0 <lb/>S π + π − tag, the yields <lb/>are required separately for 16 specific regions on the <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S π + π − Dalitz plot. These regions are the equal phase-<lb/>difference ∆δ D bins reported in [14], which are defined <lb/>using the isobar model reported in [15]. Signal yields in <lb/>these bins are determined and range between 0.7 ± 1.0 <lb/>and 7.8± 2.8. These uncertainties include the statisti-<lb/>cal uncertainties on the signal region yield and the sub-<lb/>tracted background. <lb/>For final states that include a K 0 <lb/>L meson, the missing <lb/>mass squared recoiling against the fully-reconstructed D <lb/>candidates and the particles from the other D decay con-<lb/>taining the K 0 <lb/>L meson is computed. Events consistent <lb/>with the mass of the K 0 <lb/>L meson squared are selected. <lb/>TABLE II. Background-subtracted yields and purities of <lb/>D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K ∓ π ± for each of the flavor tags in the CLEO-<lb/>c data. The uncertainties include the statistical uncertainties <lb/>of the yields in the signal region, sideband regions and Monte <lb/>Carlo yields that determine the peaking backgrounds. <lb/>Tag <lb/>D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K − π + <lb/>D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K + π − <lb/>Yield <lb/>Purity % <lb/>Yield <lb/>Purity% <lb/>Kπ <lb/>122.0±11.5 93.2±0.5 80.6±9.0 99.5±0.1 <lb/>Kπππ 161.8±13.4 89.8±0.5 101.5±10.2 97.6±0.3 <lb/>Kππ 0 221.4±15.6 91.0±0.4 120.8±11.1 97.4±0.2 <lb/>This technique was introduced in [16]. Further selec-<lb/>tion requirements are as those listed in [14]. The com-<lb/>binatoric background yield in the signal region is esti-<lb/>mated from the population in the lower (L) and upper <lb/>(H) missing mass squared sidebands. Information from <lb/>the generic simulation is used to determine the relative <lb/>composition of the sidebands and the signal region to es-<lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE III. Background-subtracted yields for fully-reconstructed CP tags and K 0 <lb/>S ππ tag over all Dalitz plot bins. The <lb/>uncertainties include the statistical uncertainties of the yields in the signal region, sideband regions and Monte Carlo yields <lb/>that determine the peaking backgrounds. <lb/>KK <lb/>ππ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S π 0 π 0 K 0 <lb/>S π 0 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S ω K 0 <lb/>S η(γγ) K 0 <lb/>S η(πππ 0 ) K 0 <lb/>S η ′ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S ππ <lb/>Yield 1.7±2.5 3.2±3.1 10.6±3.5 22.8±4.9 12.3±3.8 6.9±2.6 <lb/>0.4±1.0 0.8±1.0 60.7±8.1 <lb/>timate better the combinatorial background. There are <lb/>also peaking backgrounds that only appear in the sig-<lb/>nal region of the missing mass squared distribution. The <lb/>largest contribution of peaking background arises from <lb/>D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S X decays, where the K 0 <lb/>S is not reconstructed <lb/>and the decay is mistaken for D 0 → K 0 <lb/>L X. As an ex-<lb/>ample, Fig. 3 shows the missing mass squared spectrum <lb/>for the K 0 <lb/>L π + π − tag in data and the background Monte <lb/>Carlo distribution scaled to the integrated luminosity of <lb/>the data. In the signal region the peaking contribution <lb/>of the K 0 <lb/>S π + π − decays can be seen in the background <lb/>Monte Carlo. The lower and upper sidebands are chosen <lb/>to avoid any peaking structures that do not contribute to <lb/>the background under the peak such as the contribution <lb/>of D 0 → K − π + π 0 that is observed to the left of the lower <lb/>mass sideband in Fig. 3. <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>Events / 0.02 GeV 2 <lb/>/c 4 <lb/>m 2 <lb/>miss (GeV 2 /c 4 ) <lb/>FIG. 3. The distribution for the missing mass squared for the <lb/>K 0 <lb/>L π + π − tagged candidates. The points show the data and <lb/>the solid line is the Monte Carlo background prediction, scaled <lb/>to the data luminosity. The region between the two straight <lb/>solid lines is the signal region, marked S, and the regions <lb/>between the two dotted lines are the sidebands, marked L <lb/>and H, used to determine the combinatorial background. <lb/>The background-subtracted signal yields of the CP <lb/>tags with a K 0 <lb/>L meson in the tag side and the K 0 <lb/>L ππ tag <lb/>are given in Table IV. For the K 0 <lb/>L ππ tag, the candidate <lb/>events are separated into regions on the Dalitz plot and <lb/>the background-subtracted yields in each region range <lb/>from 0.8 ± 1.4 to 24.8 ± 5.7. The purity of K 0 <lb/>L π 0 tagged <lb/>candidates is 67%. Given the very low yield for the can-<lb/>didates tagged by K 0 <lb/>L η(γγ) and the lower branching frac-<lb/>tion and reconstruction efficiency for the K 0 <lb/>L η(π + π − π 0 ) <lb/>tag, the K 0 <lb/>L η(π + π − π 0 ) tag is not worth pursuing. Al-<lb/>though several of the yields are close to zero the corre-<lb/>sponding tag categories are retained in the analysis as <lb/>the sensitivity to the coherence factor comes from the <lb/>combination of many tags. The selection is repeated for <lb/>all tags where the invariant mass of the K 0 <lb/>S and π from <lb/>the signal decay is required to lie within 100 MeV/c 2 of <lb/>the K * (892) ± nominal mass. The yields in this restricted <lb/>region typically lie between 40% and 80% of the reported <lb/>unrestricted yields, depending on tag type. The selected <lb/>samples in the restricted region have similar purities to <lb/>those in the unrestricted region. The efficiency-corrected <lb/>yields of these samples are given in Sec. V D. <lb/>III. ISOBAR MODELS <lb/>The intermediate resonance structure in the decays <lb/>D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K − π + and D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K + π − can be visualized <lb/>through the distribution of the data over the Dalitz plot. <lb/>The Dalitz-plot distributions for each flavor-tagged data <lb/>set are shown in Fig. 4 where all three flavor tags used <lb/>in CLEO-c are plotted together. The horizontal band in <lb/>each plot is a clear indication of the presence of an in-<lb/>termediate K * (892) ± resonance. The remainder of this <lb/>section describes the construction of isobar models for <lb/>the favored and suppressed modes that parametrize the <lb/>relative amplitudes and phases of all intermediate reso-<lb/>nances that contribute to the decay. <lb/>A. Signal model for the amplitude fit <lb/>The signal isobar model considers the decay D 0 → <lb/>CR, R → AB, where A, B, C are pseudoscalar final <lb/>state particles, and R is an intermediate resonance with <lb/>spin 0, 1, or 2. The corresponding four-momenta are p D <lb/>for the initial D, p R for the resonance, and p A , p B , p C for <lb/>the final state particles. For the invariant mass of the res-<lb/>onance (which, due to its width, will vary event by event), <lb/>the symbol m AB is used, with m 2 <lb/>AB = p 2 <lb/>R = (p A + p B ) 2 . <lb/>For the &quot;nominal&quot; mass of the resonance the symbol m R <lb/>is used. The matrix element for a D 0 → CR, R → AB <lb/>decay chain is of the general form for resonance R i <lb/>M i = F D <lb/>Ω J <lb/>m 2 <lb/>R − m 2 <lb/>AB − im R Γ AB <lb/>F R , <lb/>(5) <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE IV. Background-subtracted signal yields for the CP tags with a K 0 <lb/>L and the K 0 <lb/>L ππ tag over all Dalitz plot bins. The <lb/>uncertainties include the statistical uncertainties of the signal region and subtracted background estimates. <lb/>K 0 <lb/>L π 0 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>L ω K 0 <lb/>L η(γγ) K 0 <lb/>L η ′ K 0 <lb/>L π 0 π 0 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>L ππ <lb/>Yield 22.0±5.8 2.9±2.7 −0.1±1.8 0.3±1.0 2.8±2.0 150.9±14.2 <lb/>FIG. 4. Dalitz plot distributions for (a)[(c)] D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K − π + and (b)[(d)] D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K + π − for flavor-tagged CLEO III [CLEO-c] <lb/>data. <lb/>where F D and F R are orbital angular momentum barrier <lb/>penetration factors, 1/(m 2 <lb/>R −m 2 <lb/>AB −im R Γ AB ) is the line-<lb/>shape of the resonance (in this example Breit-Wigner; <lb/>other choices are possible), and Ω J is the spin factor for <lb/>a resonance of spin J. The running width, Γ AB is given <lb/>by <lb/>Γ AB = Γ r <lb/>p AB <lb/>p r <lb/>2J+1 <lb/>m R <lb/>m AB <lb/>F 2 <lb/>R , <lb/>(6) <lb/>where Γ r is the natural width, p AB is the momentum <lb/>of one of the daughters in the AB rest frame, and p r is <lb/>the momentum of one of the daughters in the resonance <lb/>rest frame. The spin factors are calculated as described <lb/>in [17], and are <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Ω 0 = 1, <lb/>(7) <lb/>Ω 1 = (p µ <lb/>D + p µ <lb/>C )T µα (p α <lb/>B − p α <lb/>A )/(GeV) 2 , <lb/>(8) <lb/>Ω 2 = (p µ <lb/>D + p µ <lb/>C )(p ν <lb/>D + p ν <lb/>C )T µναβ (p α <lb/>B − p α <lb/>A )(p β <lb/>B − p β <lb/>A )/(GeV) 4 , <lb/>(9) <lb/>TABLE V. Particle ordering in spin 1 resonances. <lb/>Decay <lb/>A B C <lb/>D 0 → K * 0 K 0 <lb/>S , K * 0 → K − π + K − π + K 0 <lb/>S <lb/>D 0 → K * + K − , K * + → K 0 <lb/>S π + K 0 <lb/>S π + K − <lb/>D 0 → ρ − π + , ρ − → K − K 0 <lb/>S <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K − π + <lb/>TABLE VI. The Blatt-Weisskopf penetration factors for the <lb/>mesons of different spin. The momentum of either daugh-<lb/>ter in the meson rest frame, pr and the momentum of either <lb/>daughter in the candidate rest frame pAB, differ due to the <lb/>use of the mass of the meson or the invariant mass from the <lb/>two-daughter combination. <lb/>Spin <lb/>FR <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1+R 2 p 2 <lb/>r <lb/>1+R 2 p 2 <lb/>AB <lb/>2 <lb/>9+3R 2 p 2 <lb/>r +R 4 p 4 <lb/>r <lb/>9+3R 2 p 2 <lb/>AB +R 4 p 4 <lb/>AB <lb/>where T µα ≡ −g µα + p µ p α /m 2 <lb/>R , and T µναβ = <lb/>(1/2) (T µα T νβ + T µβ T να ) − (1/3)T µν T αβ . The sign of the <lb/>spin-1 factor depends on the ordering of the resonance&apos;s <lb/>decay products. The ordering choice for the different <lb/>spin factors is given in Table V. Care is taken to en-<lb/>sure that CP -conjugate amplitudes such as D → K * K 0 <lb/>S <lb/>and D → K * K 0 <lb/>S are assigned the same spin factor (with <lb/>the same sign). The Blatt-Weisskopf penetration fac-<lb/>tors, F R and F D are described in [18] and are listed in <lb/>Table VI. They rely on one free parameter R, the me-<lb/>son radius and on the momentum of the decay particles <lb/>in the rest frame of the parent. For consistency with <lb/>other experiments [19] R is fixed to be 5 (GeV/c) −1 , and <lb/>1.5 (GeV/c) −1 for the D 0 meson and intermediate reso-<lb/>nances, respectively. <lb/>The signal model is made from a sum of intermediate <lb/>resonances so that the total matrix element is given by <lb/>M tot = <lb/>j <lb/>a j e iφj M j , <lb/>(10) <lb/>where M j is as defined in Eq. (5), and a j and φ j are <lb/>the relative amplitudes and phases between different res-<lb/>onances. There are a number of intermediate resonances <lb/>which could contribute to the decays D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K − π + and <lb/>D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K + π − . The presence of the K * (892) ± reso-<lb/>nance is clearly visible in the Dalitz plot distributions <lb/>for both the favored and suppressed decays. For this <lb/>resonance a j is set to one and φ j to zero, as all other <lb/>amplitudes and phases can be measured relative to this <lb/>component. The Breit-Wigner lineshape is used for this <lb/>resonance. The presence of the K * <lb/>0 (1430) ± is also re-<lb/>quired. It is described with the LASS lineshape [20] with <lb/>the modifications described in [15]. This parametriza-<lb/>tion is used as it includes an S-wave contribution and <lb/>can account for the broad shape of any non-resonant <lb/>component. The finite sample size limits the number of <lb/>contributions that can be fitted to the data, without a <lb/>large number of components having fit fractions consis-<lb/>tent with zero, where the fit fraction F i for resonance i <lb/>is defined as <lb/>F i = <lb/>dm 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K dm 2 <lb/>Kπ |M i (m 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K , m 2 <lb/>Kπ )| 2 <lb/>dm 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K dm 2 <lb/>Kπ | <lb/>n <lb/>k=1 M k (m 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K , m 2 <lb/>Kπ )| 2 . (11) <lb/>The number of intermediate resonances fit to the favored <lb/>decay channel is six as this usually produces a fit where <lb/>no more than two resonances have fit fractions consistent <lb/>with zero. The number of intermediate resonances fit to <lb/>the suppressed decay channel is five, due to the lower sig-<lb/>nal yield of this decay. Hence in addition to the K * (892) ± <lb/>and K * <lb/>0 (1430) ± a further four (three) resonances are <lb/>chosen to make the favored (suppressed) model. These <lb/>resonances are taken from all known possibilities that <lb/>decay into either K 0 <lb/>S π, K ± π ∓ , or K 0 <lb/>S K ± . These are <lb/>the a 0 (980, 1450) + , a 2 (1320) + , K * (892, 1410, 1680) 0/± , <lb/>K * <lb/>0 (1430) 0/± , K * <lb/>2 (1430) 0/± , and ρ(1450, 1700) + , where <lb/>for each resonance the mass and width are taken from <lb/>the PDG [4]. The Breit-Wigner lineshape is used for all <lb/>these resonances except for the K * <lb/>0 (1430) ± which uses <lb/>the lineshape in [15], and a 0 (980) where the Flatté [21] <lb/>lineshape is used. <lb/>B. Detector efficiency and background modeling <lb/>The detector efficiency, which varies over the Dalitz <lb/>plot, and the distributions of the background events need <lb/>to be taken into account when fitting the data to ex-<lb/>tract the amplitudes and phases of each intermediate <lb/>resonance. The models for the detector efficiency are <lb/>determined from Monte Carlo simulation. The efficiency <lb/>shapes for CLEO III and CLEO-c data differ due to the <lb/>different D 0 momentum distributions and detector con-<lb/>figurations. The simulated events are generated non-<lb/>resonantly and hence are distributed evenly over the <lb/>Dalitz plot. The shape of the relative efficiency is largely <lb/>flat although a reduction in efficiency is seen in regions <lb/>where one of the particles has low momentum. The sim-<lb/>ulation samples for CLEO-c are large. The probability <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>density function (PDF) can be integrated using the sim-<lb/>ulated events, and as they are distributed according to <lb/>the efficiency shape there is no need to parametrize the <lb/>CLEO-c efficiency. The Monte Carlo statistics available <lb/>for CLEO III are not as large and in this case the effi-<lb/>ciency shape is parametrized by a second-order polyno-<lb/>mial in (m 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K , m 2 <lb/>Kπ ). <lb/>The flavor-tagged data samples have a purity of 90% <lb/>or greater as described in Sec. II A and Sec. II B. For <lb/>CLEO III data the background shape is determined from <lb/>three sidebands in data. Two of the sidebands require <lb/>∆m D to be less than 1 MeV/c 2 from its nominal value <lb/>and either 1.7 &lt; m D 0 &lt; 1.8 GeV/c 2 or 1.9 &lt; m D 0 &lt; 1.93 <lb/>GeV/c 2 . The second sideband has a more restricted <lb/>mass range in order to avoid contamination from D 0 → <lb/>π + π − π + π − events that peak at higher reconstructed D 0 <lb/>mass. The third sideband requires m D 0 to be within 15 <lb/>MeV/c 2 of its nominal value and 0.148 &lt; ∆m D &lt; 0.155 <lb/>GeV/c 2 . The candidate events from all three sidebands <lb/>are combined as there are insufficient data for separate <lb/>fits. The parametrization of sideband data over the <lb/>Dalitz plot is determined empirically. It is modeled as <lb/>a sum of four incoherent pseudo-resonances where the <lb/>masses, widths and spins of the pseudo-resonances are <lb/>adjusted until a good fit is achieved. Maximum likelihood <lb/>fits are performed on background samples to determine <lb/>the background shapes. The free parameters in these fits <lb/>are the relative contributions of the pseudo-resonances. <lb/>The background shapes are determined separately for the <lb/>favored and suppressed decays as there are different con-<lb/>tributions from misreconstructed D meson decays. For <lb/>CLEO-c data the background shape is determined from <lb/>the combined Monte Carlo samples described in Sec. II B <lb/>in the same way as the CLEO III samples. The data side-<lb/>bands are not used due to insufficient yields to describe <lb/>the shape on the Dalitz plot. <lb/>C. Dalitz plot probability density function <lb/>The data are fit using a similar method to previous <lb/>CLEO analyses [17]. In order to describe the event den-<lb/>sity distribution on the Dalitz plot a probability density <lb/>function is used. For the isobar model fit the PDF is <lb/>given by <lb/>P j (m 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K , m 2 <lb/>Kπ ) = <lb/>f sig,j |M(m 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K , m 2 <lb/>Kπ )| 2 ε j (m 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K , m 2 <lb/>Kπ )+ <lb/>(1 − f sig,j )B j (m 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K , m 2 <lb/>Kπ ), <lb/>(12) <lb/>where ε(m 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K , m 2 <lb/>Kπ ) and B(m 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K , m 2 <lb/>Kπ ) represent the <lb/>functions that describe the efficiency and background <lb/>shapes, respectively, across the Dalitz plot, f sig is the sig-<lb/>nal fraction and j denotes either the CLEO III or CLEO-<lb/>c data. The matrix element M is defined in Sec. III A. <lb/>The PDF components ε, |M | 2 , and B are all normalized <lb/>individually over the Dalitz plot, which leads to P being <lb/>normalized to unity as well. In the maximum likelihood <lb/>fit to determine the isobar model the only free parame-<lb/>ters are the real and imaginary part of each contributing <lb/>intermediate resonance except the K * (892) <lb/>± where the <lb/>amplitude and phase are fixed to one and zero, respec-<lb/>tively. The background shapes and CLEO III efficiency <lb/>shapes are fixed from fits to the individual relevant sam-<lb/>ples described in Sec. III B, and the CLEO-c efficiency is <lb/>taken from the large Monte Carlo sample as described in <lb/>Sec. III B. The total likelihood to determine the isobar <lb/>model is given by <lb/>L = <lb/>j=CLEO-c, <lb/>CLEO III <lb/>i <lb/>f sig,j |M(m 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K,i , m 2 <lb/>Kπ,i )| 2 ε j (m 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K,i , m 2 <lb/>Kπ,i ) + (1 − f sig,j )B j (m 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K,i , m 2 <lb/>Kπ,i ) , <lb/>(13) <lb/>where i labels each event, in data sample j. <lb/>Using the efficiency and background model PDFs, the <lb/>likelihood given in Eq. (13) is constructed where the <lb/>matrix element contains a combination of resonances. <lb/>All possible isobar models, constructed from the full set <lb/>of considered resonances, that have the allowed total <lb/>number of components, and include the K * (892) ± and <lb/>K * <lb/>0 (1430) ± contributions, are tested when fitting to the <lb/>data. <lb/>The contributions of the resonances in the K ± π ∓ chan-<lb/>nel are expected to be suppressed in comparison to reso-<lb/>nances in the K 0 <lb/>S π or K 0 <lb/>S K channel as this process pro-<lb/>ceeds by a suppressed W boson exchange. Hence models <lb/>where there are large contributions in the K ∓ π ± channel <lb/>are considered unphysical and are discarded. Also dis-<lb/>carded are models where the total fit fraction is greater <lb/>than 150% as these fits usually contain contributions that <lb/>are highly correlated with each other and contribute very <lb/>little independently to the fit. <lb/>To estimate the quality of the fit a binned χ 2 quantity <lb/>is computed. The Dalitz plot is split into square bins of <lb/>size 0.18 GeV 2 /c 4 vs. 0.18 GeV 2 /c 4 . There are a total of <lb/>67 bins which contain at least part of the allowed phase <lb/>space. Bins that contain less than 10 events are merged <lb/>with the neighboring bins until the content is greater <lb/>than 10. The χ 2 is defined as (N obs −N exp ) 2 /N exp , where <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>N obs and N exp are the number of observed and expected <lb/>events, respectively. For a given fit, the χ 2 per degree <lb/>of freedom (dof) is evaluated, and used to discriminate <lb/>between different fit models. <lb/>Models that contain the K * (892) 0 resonance are inter-<lb/>esting as they can be used to test SU(3)-flavor symmetry <lb/>predictions [3]. As the best-fit models in both the favored <lb/>and suppressed case do not contain this contribution, an <lb/>additional model is constructed for each decay with this <lb/>resonance required to be present. The models with the <lb/>K * (892) 0 resonance are labeled as model 1 and the best-<lb/>fit models are labeled as model 2. Table VII summarizes <lb/>the resonance contribution, the χ 2 /dof, and the figures <lb/>and tables that display the results for each model. <lb/>D. Systematic uncertainties <lb/>The systematic uncertainties for the measured ampli-<lb/>tudes and phases are determined by performing fits with <lb/>the same resonances as the chosen models in an alter-<lb/>nate manner. The shift between the alternate and de-<lb/>fault fit result is taken to be the systematic uncertainty <lb/>on that parameter. The relative sizes of the systematic <lb/>uncertainties are discussed in relation to the statistical <lb/>uncertainty on the fitted amplitudes and phases and the <lb/>fit fraction. <lb/>The leading systematic uncertainty arises from the <lb/>choice of values for the meson radii in the Blatt-Weiskopff <lb/>penetration factors. In the alternate fit these are changed <lb/>to 1.5 (GeV/c) −1 and 0.5 (GeV/c) −1 for the D 0 meson <lb/>and intermediate resonances, respectively. It is observed <lb/>that the changes in some of the fitted parameters in the <lb/>favored models are up to three times the size of the statis-<lb/>tical uncertainty, whereas in the suppressed models the <lb/>changes are of the same order as the statistical uncer-<lb/>tainty. This is understood as the favored models have a <lb/>larger contribution from resonances where the pole mass <lb/>lies outside the phase space. The change in the value of <lb/>the penetration factor increases with increasing distance <lb/>from the pole mass, and hence this effect is a larger source <lb/>of systematic uncertainty for the favored model. <lb/>The other leading systematic uncertainty is attributed <lb/>to uncertainties in the measured masses and widths of the <lb/>resonances, and the parameters of the K * <lb/>0 (1430) ± line-<lb/>shape. The masses and widths of the resonances, and the <lb/>parameters of the K * <lb/>0 (1430) ± lineshape are varied, each <lb/>in turn by one standard deviation from their measured <lb/>values. The shifts on the fitted amplitudes and phases <lb/>are added in quadrature for each alteration. Overall the <lb/>total systematic uncertainty arising from these changes <lb/>is of order half the statistical uncertainty. <lb/>The PDF used to arrive at the default models neglects <lb/>the DCS amplitude that is present in the flavor tag de-<lb/>cays. Although the DCS rate is much smaller than the <lb/>CF rate, the interference between the two amplitudes is <lb/>a significant effect in the quantum-correlated CLEO-c <lb/>data. To determine the size of this effect the data are fit <lb/>with a modified PDF for the CLEO-c data. In the case <lb/>of the favored data, the alternate PDF uses a total am-<lb/>plitude given by A tot = A fav + 0.05 × 0.7 × A sup e iδ . The <lb/>parameters of the suppressed model are fixed to their de-<lb/>fault values, while the parameters of the favored model <lb/>are free. The factor 0.05 arises from the approximate <lb/>ratio of DCS to CF amplitudes in neutral D meson de-<lb/>cays to Kπ. There is, however, dilution as the Kπππ <lb/>and Kππ 0 tags are not fully coherent. The factor of <lb/>0.7 accounts for the weighted average of the fully coher-<lb/>ent Kπ decay and the coherence factors for the other <lb/>two tags measured in [7]. Additionally there is an un-<lb/>known absolute phase δ between the favored and sup-<lb/>pressed amplitude models. To account for this, the fit <lb/>is repeated assuming a phase difference of zero, π/2, <lb/>π, and 3π/2. The largest shifts in the fitted param-<lb/>eters are observed for a phase difference of zero and <lb/>these are taken to be the systematic uncertainty. In <lb/>general the systematic uncertainty due to this effect is <lb/>about 25% of the statistical error. In the CLEO III <lb/>data there is no quantum-correlation, however mistags <lb/>occur when a track of the wrong charge is misidenti-<lb/>fied as the pion from the D * . The mistag rate is de-<lb/>termined by measuring the relative rate of, for exam-<lb/>ple, D 0 → K + π − π + π− and D 0 − &gt; K − π + π − π + candi-<lb/>dates associated with a D * + → D 0 π + decay chain, and <lb/>attributing to mistags the excess of doubly-Cabibbo-<lb/>suppressed candidates that is observed above expecta-<lb/>tion. The mistag rate is found to be around 0.6%. The <lb/>systematic uncertainty due to this is determined to be <lb/>negligible in comparison to other possible sources of bias. <lb/>The systematic uncertainty due to the background <lb/>fraction is evaluated by modifying the assigned value <lb/>of the purity in the fit PDF by the uncertainty on <lb/>its measured value. In addition, alternate background <lb/>models are determined using a fit to the background <lb/>samples with fewer pseudo-resonances. The alternate <lb/>parametrizations are used in the fit to signal data, and <lb/>the observed shifts are used as the systematic uncer-<lb/>tainty. The uncertainty on the efficiency shape over the <lb/>Dalitz plot is assessed using alternate parametrizations <lb/>for the efficiency shape. In the case of CLEO III a third-<lb/>order polynomial is used instead of the default second-<lb/>order polynomial. In the case of CLEO-c the efficiency <lb/>is parametrized by a fourth-order polynomial instead of <lb/>using the Monte-Carlo-simulated sample directly. The <lb/>uncertainties on efficiency, purity, and background shapes <lb/>each contribute an uncertainty of approximately 10% of <lb/>the statistical uncertainty. The default fit does not take <lb/>into account the detector resolution on the Dalitz plot, <lb/>and hence all data points are slightly shifted from their <lb/>true positions. To account for the resulting uncertainty, <lb/>the K 0 <lb/>S , K, and π momenta are smeared in data, accord-<lb/>ing to parameters determined from Monte Carlo simu-<lb/>lation, and the fit is performed on the smeared sample. <lb/>This systematic uncertainty is negligible in comparison to <lb/>other contributions. The validity of the fitter is assessed <lb/>via fits to many samples of simulated data generated from <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE VII. A summary of the resonance contributions and χ 2 /dof for each model. The figures showing the projection and <lb/>the table listing the fit information are also given. <lb/>Model <lb/>Resonance <lb/>χ 2 /dof Projection Results <lb/>Favored 1 <lb/>K * (892) + , K * (892) 0 , K * <lb/>0 (1430) + , K * (1410) 0 , K * (1680) + , a0(1450) − 42.2/26 Fig. 5 <lb/>Table X <lb/>Favored 2 <lb/>K * (892) + , ρ(1700) − , K * <lb/>0 (1430) + , K * (1410) 0 , K * (1680) + , a0(1450) − 37.3/26 Fig. 6 <lb/>Table XI <lb/>Suppressed 1 K * (892) − , K * (892) 0 , K * <lb/>0 (1430) − , a0(1450) + , ρ(1700) + <lb/>50.9/30 Fig. 7 <lb/>Table XII <lb/>Suppressed 2 K * (892) − , K * <lb/>2 (1430) 0 , K * <lb/>0 (1430) − , a0(1450) + , ρ(1700) + <lb/>46.5/30 Fig. 8 <lb/>Table XIII <lb/>the PDFs. A small uncertainty of order 10% of the statis-<lb/>tical uncertainty is assigned due to small residual biases <lb/>between the generated and fitted parameters. <lb/>A summary of the systematic uncertainties for each <lb/>effect as a fraction of the statistical uncertainty on the <lb/>amplitudes, phases, and fit fractions for models 1 are <lb/>given in Table VIII and IX. The relative sizes of the <lb/>systematic uncertainties are similar for models 2. <lb/>E. Results of the amplitude studies <lb/>The results of the fit are listed in Tables X-XIII. <lb/>These tables show the amplitude, phase and fit fraction <lb/>for each contributing resonance, and the statistical and <lb/>systematic uncertainty for each of these parameters. The <lb/>fit projections for all these models are given in Figs. 5-8. <lb/>The fit projections show good agreement with the data. <lb/>The difference in fit projections between model 1 and and <lb/>model 2 in either of the decay modes is very small. The <lb/>K * (892) ± component, clearly visible in the data, is seen <lb/>to contribute significantly to all four models. This large, <lb/>common resonant structure gives the expectation of sig-<lb/>nificant coherence between the two decay modes, particu-<lb/>larly in the region of the K * (892) ± resonance. The data <lb/>for the suppressed decay show a broad extended shape <lb/>either side of the K * (892) ± resonance in the m 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S π pro-<lb/>jection which is not present in the favored decay. This <lb/>difference is apparent in the models as the favored models <lb/>have a very small contribution from the K * (1430) 0 res-<lb/>onance which is described by a broad S-wave lineshape, <lb/>while in the suppressed models this is a significant con-<lb/>tribution to the overall model. In the favored models the <lb/>fit fraction of the K * (1410) 0 resonance is large, which <lb/>is unexpected as the K ∓ π ± channel proceeds by a sup-<lb/>pressed W boson exchange. However the large fit fraction <lb/>can be understood by considering the destructive inter-<lb/>ference between K * (1410) 0 and K * (1680) ± which is also <lb/>significant. This interference between two resonances can <lb/>be quantified by calculating the interference fit fraction <lb/>between any two resonances (j, l), and is given by <lb/>I j,l = <lb/>Re dm 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K dm 2 <lb/>Kπ a j e iφj M j a * <lb/>l e −iφ l M l <lb/>dm 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K dm 2 <lb/>Kπ | <lb/>n <lb/>k=1 M k (m 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K , m 2 <lb/>Kπ )| 2 . (14) <lb/>For these two resonances the interference fit fraction is <lb/>−21% (−27%) for model 1 (2). The full tables of inter-<lb/>ference fit fractions are provided in Appendix A. There is <lb/>similarity between models 1 and 2 for each decay mode, <lb/>as the contribution of the K * (892) 0 is small. From SU(3) <lb/>flavor symmetry predictions [3], the expected ratio of am-<lb/>plitudes between D 0 → K * 0 K 0 and D 0 → K * + K − is <lb/>0.138±0.033. Using favored model 1 we observe a ratio <lb/>of 0.2 ± 0.1. Although this is consistent with the predic-<lb/>tion, it should be noted that the fit fraction of K * (892) 0 <lb/>is small and consistent with zero at the one standard de-<lb/>viation level. An isobar model determined with a larger <lb/>sample than analyzed here will be required to test the <lb/>prediction with more meaningful precision. <lb/>IV. MEASUREMENT OF THE RATIO OF <lb/>BRANCHING FRACTIONS OF SUPPRESSED <lb/>AND FAVORED DECAYS <lb/>The measurement to determine the ratio of branching <lb/>fractions uses only CLEO III data to avoid the complica-<lb/>tions of accounting for the quantum correlations present <lb/>in the CLEO-c data. The ratio B K 0 <lb/>S Kπ is given by <lb/>B K 0 <lb/>S Kπ = <lb/>N (D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K + π − ) <lb/>N (D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K − π + ) <lb/>× <lb/>ǫ D 0 →K 0 <lb/>S K − π + <lb/>ǫ D 0 →K 0 <lb/>S K + π − <lb/>, (15) <lb/>where N is the number of signal events for each decay, <lb/>and ǫ is the efficiency. <lb/>The ratio of the efficiencies is not exactly unity as the <lb/>distributions of the events over the Dalitz plot are dif-<lb/>ferent in the favored and suppressed decays and the effi-<lb/>ciency over the Dalitz plot is not uniform. The ratio of <lb/>the efficiencies is found by taking the ratio of the inte-<lb/>gral over all of phase space for the default isobar models <lb/>multiplied by the efficiency model, for the favored and <lb/>suppressed decay. The efficiency ratio is determined to <lb/>be 0.940 using favored model 1 and suppressed model <lb/>1. The uncertainty is assessed by altering the detector <lb/>efficiency parametrization and using various alternative <lb/>models arising from the fitting procedure that give a rea-<lb/>sonable fit to data and leads to an uncertainty of ±0.029 <lb/>on the correction factor. Using the tagged CLEO III <lb/>yields and the necessary corrections, B K 0 <lb/>S Kπ is measured <lb/>to be 0.592 ± 0.044 ± 0.018, where the first uncertainty is <lb/>statistical and the second systematic due to uncertainties <lb/>in the correction factors. This measurement is consistent, <lb/>and more precise than 0.79 ± 0.19, the average of previ-<lb/>ous measurements [4]. The measurement for B K 0 <lb/>S Kπ is <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE VIII. Systematic uncertainties on Fi, |ai|, and φi in units of statistical standard deviations (σ) for the decay D 0 → <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K − π + . The different contributions are: (I) Blatt-Weisskopf penetration factors; (II) mass and width of resonances; (III) <lb/>quantum correlations; (IV) CLEO III mistag; (V) background models; (VI) sample purities; (VII) acceptance; (VIII) resolution; <lb/>(IX) fitter bias. <lb/>Source (σ) <lb/>Total (σ) <lb/>I <lb/>II III IV V VI VII VIII IX <lb/>K * (892) + K − Fi 0.36 0.33 0.13 0.08 0.08 0.15 0.16 0.05 0.18 <lb/>0.59 <lb/>K * (892) 0 K 0 <lb/>S |ai| 0.19 0.24 0.06 0.09 0.12 0.16 0.14 0.06 0.06 <lb/>0.42 <lb/>K * (892) 0 K 0 <lb/>S φi <lb/>0.87 0.28 0.11 0.02 0.10 0.08 0.11 0.07 0.05 <lb/>0.94 <lb/>K * (892) 0 K 0 <lb/>S Fi <lb/>0.21 0.21 0.05 0.10 0.13 0.19 0.16 0.05 0.21 <lb/>0.47 <lb/>K * (1410) 0 K 0 <lb/>S |ai| 4.35 0.85 0.23 0.04 0.09 0.07 0.09 0.01 0.12 <lb/>4.44 <lb/>K * (1410) 0 K 0 <lb/>S φi 1.13 0.39 0.05 0.07 0.17 0.13 0.12 0.01 0.13 <lb/>1.23 <lb/>K * (1410) 0 K 0 <lb/>S Fi 0.96 0.35 0.32 0.04 0.07 0.07 0.06 0.02 0.05 <lb/>1.08 <lb/>K * (1680) + K − |ai| 1.53 0.41 0.07 0.08 0.10 0.15 0.14 0.03 0.21 <lb/>1.62 <lb/>K * (1680) + K − φi 1.15 0.41 0.03 0.09 0.11 0.17 0.16 0.02 0.26 <lb/>1.28 <lb/>K * (1680) + K − Fi 1.20 0.32 0.17 0.00 0.03 0.02 0.12 0.02 0.09 <lb/>1.26 <lb/>K * <lb/>0 (1430) + K − |ai| 1.44 0.32 0.20 0.08 0.14 0.15 0.21 0.02 0.39 <lb/>1.57 <lb/>K * <lb/>0 (1430) + K − φi 0.49 0.19 0.08 0.02 0.08 0.04 0.13 0.00 0.05 <lb/>0.56 <lb/>K * <lb/>0 (1430) + K − Fi 1.51 0.35 0.15 0.07 0.12 0.13 0.18 0.03 0.16 <lb/>1.59 <lb/>a0(1450) − π + |ai| 0.41 0.35 0.20 0.04 0.08 0.08 0.15 0.02 0.08 <lb/>0.61 <lb/>a0(1450) − π + φi <lb/>0.42 0.44 0.18 0.03 0.04 0.06 0.08 0.04 0.06 <lb/>0.64 <lb/>a0(1450) − π + Fi <lb/>0.54 0.24 0.29 0.02 0.10 0.04 0.22 0.01 0.73 <lb/>1.01 <lb/>TABLE IX. Systematic uncertainties on Fi, |ai|, and φi in units of statistical standard deviations (σ) for the decay D 0 → <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K + π − . The different contributions are: (I) Blatt-Weisskopf penetration factors; (II) mass and width of resonances; (III) <lb/>quantum correlations; (IV) CLEO III mistag; (V) background models; (VI) sample purities; (VII) acceptance; (VIII) resolution; <lb/>(IX) fitter bias. <lb/>Source (σ) <lb/>Total (σ) <lb/>I <lb/>II III IV V VI VII VIII IX <lb/>K * (892) − K + Fi 0.23 0.21 0.20 0.05 0.03 0.04 0.11 0.00 0.02 <lb/>0.39 <lb/>K * (892) 0 K 0 <lb/>S |ai| 0.13 0.37 0.04 0.03 0.03 0.02 0.05 0.00 0.08 <lb/>0.41 <lb/>K * (892) 0 K 0 <lb/>S φi <lb/>0.20 0.24 0.03 0.01 0.04 0.02 0.12 0.00 0.04 <lb/>0.34 <lb/>K * (892) 0 K 0 <lb/>S Fi <lb/>0.10 0.23 0.01 0.02 0.02 0.04 0.07 0.01 0.07 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>K * <lb/>0 (1430) − K + |ai| 0.33 0.33 0.10 0.03 0.02 0.03 0.08 0.00 0.19 <lb/>0.52 <lb/>K * <lb/>0 (1430) − K + φi 0.23 0.43 0.07 0.02 0.01 0.02 0.03 0.00 0.13 <lb/>0.51 <lb/>K * <lb/>0 (1430) − K + Fi 0.31 0.37 0.09 0.03 0.02 0.01 0.08 0.00 0.15 <lb/>0.52 <lb/>a0(1450) + π − |ai| 0.58 0.56 0.08 0.02 0.01 0.02 0.04 0.01 0.06 <lb/>0.81 <lb/>a0(1450) + π − φi <lb/>0.46 0.58 0.06 0.01 0.02 0.01 0.04 0.00 0.04 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>a0(1450) + π − Fi <lb/>0.43 0.24 0.03 0.00 0.01 0.01 0.03 0.01 0.17 <lb/>0.52 <lb/>ρ(1700) + π − |ai| <lb/>1.25 1.22 0.05 0.00 0.02 0.01 0.07 0.01 0.09 <lb/>1.75 <lb/>ρ(1700) + π − φi <lb/>0.36 0.71 0.09 0.00 0.01 0.01 0.06 0.00 0.02 <lb/>0.80 <lb/>ρ(1700) + π − Fi <lb/>1.01 0.68 0.01 0.01 0.01 0.01 0.09 0.01 0.02 <lb/>1.22 <lb/>TABLE X. The results of the Dalitz plot fit for the decay D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K − π + . This is the best model including the neutral <lb/>K * (892) 0 resonance, favored model 1. The amplitudes, phases, and fit fractions are given. The first uncertainty is statistical, <lb/>and the second systematic. <lb/>Component <lb/>Amplitude <lb/>Phase ( • ) <lb/>Fraction (%) <lb/>D 0 → K * (892) + K − <lb/>1.0 (fixed) <lb/>0.0 (fixed) <lb/>67.6±6.4±3.8 <lb/>D 0 → K * (892) 0 K 0 <lb/>S <lb/>0.2±0.1±0.0 <lb/>96.1±13.2±12.4 1.8±1.7±0.8 <lb/>D 0 → K * (1410) 0 K 0 <lb/>S <lb/>8.4±0.7±3.0 −16.7± 7.5 ± 9.2 23.2±3.9±4.2 <lb/>D 0 → K * (1680) + K − 15.3±2.3±3.8 148.3±11.1±14.2 22.7±4.4±5.6 <lb/>D 0 → K * <lb/>0 (1430) + K − 1.3±0.3±0.5 −101.0±22.0±12.3 2.5±1.2±2.0 <lb/>D 0 → a0(1450) − π + <lb/>0.4±0.2±0.1 −26.8±42.3±27.2 1.0±0.9±0.9 <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>FIG. 5. Fit projections for the D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K − π + decay mode using favored model 1, the best model containing the K * (892) 0 <lb/>resonance. The data are shown as points and the total fit projection is overlaid with the solid line. The projection with the <lb/>dotted line is the contribution of background. Plots (a)-(c)((d)-(f)) show the CLEO III (CLEO-c) data for the three pairs of <lb/>invariant mass distributions. <lb/>TABLE XI. The results of the Dalitz plot fit for the decay D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K − π + . This is the model with the lowest χ 2 per degree <lb/>of freedom, favored model 2. The amplitudes, phases, and fit fractions are given. The first uncertainty is statistical, and the <lb/>second systematic. <lb/>Component <lb/>Amplitude <lb/>Phase ( • ) <lb/>Fraction (%) <lb/>D 0 → K * (892) + K − <lb/>1.0 (fixed) <lb/>0.0 (fixed) <lb/>62.2±4.8± 3.9 <lb/>D 0 → K * (1410) 0 K 0 <lb/>S 10.3±1.0±2.7 −18.5± 5.6 ± 7.0 32.0±6.0±19.6 <lb/>D 0 → K * (1680) + K − 17.1±2.3±2.4 151.6± 8.3 ± 7.3 26.1±6.0±24.0 <lb/>D 0 → ρ(1700) − π + <lb/>5.5±1.8±1.5 <lb/>23.5±12.5±21.5 4.4±3.0± 3.7 <lb/>D 0 → K * <lb/>0 (1430) + K − 1.5±0.3±0.7 −101.5±18.9± 8.7 3.1±1.2± 3.1 <lb/>D 0 → a0(1450) − π + <lb/>0.7±0.2±0.2 -31.7±23.3±16.1 2.3±1.2± 1.5 <lb/>TABLE XII. The results of the Dalitz plot fit for the decay D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K + π − . This is the best model including the neutral <lb/>K * (892) 0 resonance, suppressed model 1. The amplitudes, phases, and fit fractions are given. The first uncertainty is statistical, <lb/>and the second systematic. <lb/>Component <lb/>Amplitude <lb/>Phase ( • ) <lb/>Fraction (%) <lb/>D 0 → K * (892) − K + <lb/>1.0 (fixed) <lb/>0.0 (fixed) <lb/>20.4±2.1±0.8 <lb/>D 0 → K * (892) 0 K 0 <lb/>S <lb/>0.4±0.1±0.0 109.9±10.8±3.7 3.9±1.5±0.4 <lb/>D 0 → K * <lb/>0 (1430) − K + 6.2±0.9±0.5 −114.4± 9.8 ±5.0 18.4±2.8±1.5 <lb/>D 0 → a0(1450) + π − <lb/>3.1±0.5±0.4 −54.0± 8.6 ±6.4 15.8±4.1±2.1 <lb/>D 0 → ρ(1700) + π − <lb/>11.4±2.2±3.9 <lb/>90.3± 9.6 ±7.7 6.2±2.1±2.5 <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>FIG. 6. Fit projections for the D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K − π + decay mode using favored model 2, the best model. The data are shown as <lb/>points and the total fit projection is overlaid with the solid line. The projection with the dotted line is the contribution of <lb/>background. Plots (a)-(c)((d)-(f)) show the CLEO III (CLEO-c) data for the three pairs of invariant mass distributions. <lb/>TABLE XIII. The results of the Dalitz plot fit for the decay D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K + π − . This is the model with the lowest χ 2 per degree <lb/>of freedom, suppressed model 2. The amplitudes, phases, and fit fractions are given. The first uncertainty is statistical, and <lb/>the second systematic. <lb/>Component <lb/>Amplitude <lb/>Phase ( • ) <lb/>Fraction (%) <lb/>D 0 → K * (892) − K + <lb/>1.0 (fixed) <lb/>0.0 (fixed) <lb/>21.1±2.2±3.3 <lb/>D 0 → K * <lb/>0 (1430) − K + 8.0±0.9±0.7 −71.8±13.4± 9.3 31.5±6.2±8.0 <lb/>D 0 → ρ(1700) + π − <lb/>12.7±2.2±5.4 103.7±16.1±11.2 8.0±2.2±3.8 <lb/>D 0 → a0(1450) + π − <lb/>1.8±0.4±0.3 −30.1±14.7±10.9 5.8±2.3±1.6 <lb/>D 0 → K * <lb/>2 (1430) 0 K 0 <lb/>S <lb/>4.7±1.5±2.0 −104.1±14.9± 7.5 4.3±2.8±3.4 <lb/>also required in the restricted kinematic region of 100 <lb/>MeV/c 2 around the K * (892) ± resonance for the coher-<lb/>ence factor measurement and is here determined to be <lb/>B K * K = 0.356 ± 0.034 ± 0.007. <lb/>V. COHERENCE FACTOR AND AVERAGE <lb/>STRONG-PHASE DIFFERENCE <lb/>MEASUREMENT <lb/>A. Quantum-Correlated D Decays <lb/>The coherence factor R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ and the average strong-<lb/>phase difference δ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>can be determined using double-<lb/>tagged D 0 D0 pairs from the ψ(3770) resonance produced <lb/>in e + e − collisions at <lb/>√ <lb/>s = 3770 MeV. The two mesons <lb/>are produced in a C-odd eigenstate and therefore the de-<lb/>cays of the two D mesons are quantum-correlated. There <lb/>are three categories of double tags used. The first of these <lb/>are the flavor tags, where the samples of double tags are <lb/>split into two classes: those where the tag kaon and the <lb/>kaon from the signal side have the same sign of charge <lb/>(SS) and those where the two kaons have opposite sign <lb/>of charge (OS). The second category of double tags are <lb/>those where the tag D meson decays to a CP eigenstate, <lb/>which can either be even or odd. The final category of <lb/>double tags used are those where the tag D meson de-<lb/>cays to K 0 <lb/>S,L π + π − . Each category of double tags has a <lb/>different sensitivity to R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ and δ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>. <lb/>The rate for the two neutral D mesons produced <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>FIG. 7. Fit projections for the D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K + π − decay mode using suppressed model 1, the best model containing the K * (892) 0 <lb/>resonance. The data are shown as points and the total fit projection is overlaid with the solid line. The projection with the <lb/>dotted line is the contribution of background. Plots (a)-(c)((d)-(f)) show the CLEO III (CLEO-c) data for the three pairs of <lb/>invariant mass distributions. <lb/>from ψ(3770) where one decays to the K 0 <lb/>S K ∓ π ± fi-<lb/>nal state and the other decays to any final state G, <lb/>Γ(K 0 <lb/>S K ∓ π ± |G), is given by [5] <lb/>Γ(K 0 <lb/>S K ∓ π ± |G) = Γ 0 <lb/>|A K 0 <lb/>S Kπ (m 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K , m 2 <lb/>Kπ )A G (z) − A K 0 <lb/>S Kπ (m 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K , m 2 <lb/>Kπ )A G (z)| 2 dm 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S K dm 2 <lb/>Kπ dz <lb/>= Γ 0 [A 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ A 2 <lb/>G + A 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ A 2 <lb/>G − 2R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ R G A K 0 <lb/>S Kπ A K 0 <lb/>S Kπ A G A G cos(δ G <lb/>D − δ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>)], <lb/>(16) <lb/>where z describes the multi-body phase space for final <lb/>state G, R G and δ G are the coherence factor and average <lb/>strong-phase difference for the final state G as defined <lb/>in an analogous way to that given in Eq. (3), and Γ 0 <lb/>is the normalization factor. Specifying that the tag D <lb/>meson decays to either a flavor tag or a CP tag, Eq. (16) <lb/>simplifies to the following relations: <lb/>Γ(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|CP ± ) = Γ 0 A 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ A 2 <lb/>CP [1 + (r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>) 2 − 2λ ± r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ cos δ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>], <lb/>(17) <lb/>Γ(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|F SS ) = Γ 0 A 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ A 2 <lb/>F [(r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>) 2 + (r F <lb/>D ) 2 − 2r F <lb/>D r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ R F cos(δ F <lb/>D − δ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>)], <lb/>(18) <lb/>Γ(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|F OS ) = Γ 0 A 2 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ A 2 <lb/>F [1 + (r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>r F <lb/>D ) 2 − 2r F <lb/>D r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ R F cos(δ F <lb/>D − δ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>)], <lb/>(19) <lb/>where F , the flavor tag is either K ∓ π ± , K ∓ π ± π + π − , or <lb/>K ∓ π ± π 0 , the superscript SS or OS denotes the charge <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>FIG. 8. Fit projections for the D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K + π − decay mode using suppressed model 2, the best model. The top plots show the <lb/>projection of the fit on the CLEO III data while the lower plots show the projection onto CLEO-c data. The data are shown <lb/>as points and the total fit projection is overlaid with the solid line. The projection with the dotted line is the contribution of <lb/>background. Plots (a)-(c)((d)-(f)) show the CLEO III (CLEO-c) data for the three pairs of invariant mass distributions. <lb/>relation between the signal and tag kaon, and CP denotes <lb/>a CP eigenstate with eigenvalue λ ± = ±1. The quantity <lb/>r F <lb/>D is analogous to Eq. (4) using the DCS and CF am-<lb/>plitudes for the given flavor tag. These rate expressions <lb/>ignore CP violation in D decays, which is well moti-<lb/>vated theoretically and experimentally known to be very <lb/>small [22, 23]. These rate equations allow for the number <lb/>of expected events in a given data sample to be calculated <lb/>for each category of double tag. The left hand side can <lb/>be replaced with the efficiency-corrected background-<lb/>subtracted signal double-tag yield, S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|G), where <lb/>S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|G) = N (K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|G)/ε(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|G), <lb/>(20) <lb/>where N (K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|G) is the background-subtracted yield <lb/>of double tags where one D meson decays to K 0 <lb/>S Kπ and <lb/>the other to final state G, and ε(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|G) is the effi-<lb/>ciency to select that particular double tag. Ratios of the <lb/>rate equations are taken to remove the dependence on <lb/>the normalization factor and A K 0 <lb/>S Kπ . This leads to the <lb/>useful observables ν F and κ ± defined as <lb/>ν F ≡ <lb/>S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|F SS ) <lb/>S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|F OS ) <lb/>= <lb/>(r F <lb/>D ) 2 + (r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>) 2 − 2r F <lb/>D r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>R F [p cos(δ F ) + q sin(δ F )] <lb/>1 + (r F <lb/>D ) 2 (r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>) 2 − 2r F <lb/>D r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>R F [p cos(δ F ) + q sin(δ F )] <lb/>, <lb/>(21) <lb/>κ ± ≡ <lb/>S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|CP ± )B(D → Kπ) <lb/>S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|Kπ SS )B(D → CP ) <lb/>= <lb/>1 + (r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>) 2 − 2λ ± r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>p <lb/>(1 − λ ± y)(r Kπ <lb/>D ) 2 + (r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>) 2 − 2r Kπ <lb/>D r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>[p cos(δ Kπ ) + q sin(δ Kπ )] <lb/>, <lb/>(22) <lb/>where <lb/>p ≡ R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ cos δ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>, <lb/>(23) <lb/>q ≡ R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ sin δ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>, <lb/>(24) <lb/>and y is the charm mixing parameter given by y = (Γ 2 − <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>Γ 1 )/2Γ where Γ 2 and Γ 1 , are the lifetimes of the two D <lb/>meson mass eigenstates and Γ is the mean of Γ 2 and Γ 1 . <lb/>The branching fractions are included using the following <lb/>relations: B(D 0 → CP ± ) = A 2 <lb/>CP (1 ∓ y) and B(D 0 → <lb/>K − π + ) = A 2 <lb/>K − π + . In the case of the κ observable the <lb/>yields and branching fractions are combined so that the <lb/>true value of the κ + (κ − ) observable is the same for all <lb/>CP even (odd) tags. <lb/>The other tag group which also provides sensitivity <lb/>to R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ and δ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>is K 0 <lb/>S,L π + π − . The Dalitz plot <lb/>of K 0 <lb/>S,L π + π − can be described by two coordinates m 2 <lb/>+ <lb/>and m 2 <lb/>− , where m + (m − ) is the invariant mass of the <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S,L π + (K 0 <lb/>S,L π − ) pair. The Dalitz plot can be divided <lb/>into bins where the i th bin has m 2 <lb/>+ &gt; m 2 <lb/>− , and the <lb/>symmetric bin in the region where m 2 <lb/>+ &lt; m 2 <lb/>− is la-<lb/>beled the −i th bin. For each point the phase difference, <lb/>∆δ D , is defined as ∆δ D ≡ δ D (m 2 <lb/>+ , m 2 <lb/>− ) − δ D (m 2 <lb/>− , m 2 <lb/>+ ), <lb/>where δ D (m 2 <lb/>+ , m 2 <lb/>− ) is the phase of the D 0 decay at that <lb/>point. In each bin the amplitude-weighted averages of <lb/>cos(∆(δ D )) and sin(∆(δ D )) over each Dalitz plot bin, de-<lb/>noted c i and s i respectively can be determined. These c i <lb/>and s i measurements have been performed [14], together <lb/>with the equivalent parameters for K 0 <lb/>L π + π − decays, c ′ <lb/>i <lb/>and s ′ <lb/>i . In addition the flavor tag yields in each bin, L i <lb/>and L −i (L ′ <lb/>i and L ′ <lb/>−i ) for K 0 <lb/>S π + π − (K 0 <lb/>L π + π − ) have also <lb/>been determined. The binning choice used in the current <lb/>analysis is that of the equal regions in ∆(δ D ) as defined <lb/>in [14]. <lb/>In quantum-correlated decays of D mesons at <lb/>√ s = <lb/>3770 MeV, the yield of the double tag where the tag D <lb/>meson decays to K S,L π + π − in the i th bin is given by <lb/>S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|K 0 <lb/>S π + π − ) i = H S (L i + (r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>) 2 L −i − 2r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>(L i L −i )[c i p + s i q]), <lb/>(25) <lb/>S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|K 0 <lb/>L π + π − ) i = H L (L ′ <lb/>i + (r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>) 2 L ′ <lb/>−i + 2r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>(L ′ <lb/>i L ′ <lb/>−i )[c ′ <lb/>i p + s ′ <lb/>i q]), <lb/>(26) <lb/>where H S and H L are normalization factors, and S is <lb/>the efficiency-corrected signal yield in the i th bin of the <lb/>Dalitz plot. The inclusion of the K 0 <lb/>S,L ππ tags is necessary <lb/>in the measurement as the flavor and CP tags on their <lb/>own provide limited sensitivity to q. <lb/>B. Measurement of observables <lb/>The background-subtracted signal yields of each dou-<lb/>ble tag are given in Sec. II B. To determine the <lb/>efficiency-corrected yields it is necessary to know the <lb/>efficiency for each double tag. The double-tag recon-<lb/>struction efficiencies are determined from separate sim-<lb/>ulated signal samples for each final state. The resonant <lb/>decay structure is not simulated for any of the D 0 me-<lb/>son decays because no significant differences are observed <lb/>between the overall efficiency determined with flat sim-<lb/>ulation and the resonant decay simulation. In each fi-<lb/>nal state 20,000 events are generated, except for the <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S,L π + π − tags where 200,000 events are generated so <lb/>that the statistical uncertainty on the determined ef-<lb/>ficiency remains small in each bin of the Dalitz plot. <lb/>The determined efficiencies are corrected for known small <lb/>differences between data and simulation due to π 0 re-<lb/>construction and particle identification efficiencies. The <lb/>double tag reconstruction efficiencies range from 20% for <lb/>π + π − to 2% for the K 0 <lb/>S η ′ tag. The variation in efficiency <lb/>from bin to bin in either K 0 <lb/>S π + π − or K 0 <lb/>L π + π − tags is less <lb/>than 2%. The effect of the resonant structure on the de-<lb/>termined efficiency is taken into account as a systematic <lb/>uncertainty. <lb/>As the resonant decays of either D meson are not sim-<lb/>ulated the measured efficiencies for the SS flavor tags <lb/>and OS flavor double tags are identical. The system-<lb/>atic uncertainty arising from any difference that does ex-<lb/>ist is considered separately. Hence the ν values defined <lb/>in Eq. (21) are simply the ratios of the background-<lb/>subtracted signal yields given in Table II and are 0.66 ± <lb/>0.10, 0.63 ± 0.08, and 0.54 ± 0.06 for ν Kπ , ν Kπππ , and <lb/>ν Kππ 0 , respectively. The values of the S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|CP ) and <lb/>S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|Kπ SS ) yields are listed in Tables XIV and XV, <lb/>respectively. The values of the S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|K 0 ππ) yields <lb/>are listed in Tables XVI and XVII. <lb/>To determine κ for each CP tag the branching frac-<lb/>tions are taken from [4]. All subsidiary branching frac-<lb/>tions such as K 0 <lb/>S → π + π − are included in the calcula-<lb/>tion. The uncertainties on the κ value include a statisti-<lb/>cal component from the double-tag yield, and systematic <lb/>uncertainties arising from the uncertainties in the differ-<lb/>ence between Monte Carlo and data, the scale factors <lb/>used to determine background yields, the uncertainties <lb/>of branching fractions used, and the yield of the Kπ SS <lb/>double tag. A number of these uncertainties are corre-<lb/>lated among some or all of the observables. <lb/>The systematic uncertainties due to branch-<lb/>ing fractions, the background scale factors, and <lb/>N (K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|Kπ SS ) are determined by shifting the de-<lb/>fault value of the branching fraction, scale factor or <lb/>N (K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|Kπ SS ) by one standard deviation and taking <lb/>the shift on the observable as the systematic uncertainty. <lb/>There are systematic uncertainties due to uncorrected <lb/>differences between simulation and data tracking and <lb/>reconstruction efficiencies. <lb/>Relative uncertainties of <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE XIV. Efficiency-corrected yields for double tags with no K 0 <lb/>L in final state. The uncertainties take into account the <lb/>statistical uncertainties on the uncorrected yields only. <lb/>Tag <lb/>KK <lb/>ππ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S π 0 π 0 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S π 0 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S ω <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S η(γγ) K 0 <lb/>S η(πππ 0 ) <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S η ′ <lb/>Kπ SS <lb/>S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|G) 10.7±16.0 16.1±15.1 274.5±89.8 305.0±65.7 293.7±89.9 93.8±36.1 7.5±18.6 52.1±62.6 989.5±110.5 <lb/>TABLE XV. Efficiency-corrected signal yields for the CP tags with a K 0 <lb/>L . The uncertainties take into account the statistical <lb/>uncertainties on the uncorrected yields only. <lb/>Tag <lb/>K 0 <lb/>L π 0 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>L ω <lb/>K 0 <lb/>L η <lb/>K 0 <lb/>L η ′ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>L π 0 π 0 <lb/>S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|G) 171.6±45.0 58.0±53.0 −1.0±13.1 9.1±34.0 363.2±262.3 <lb/>2% for each tag containing a π 0 , 0.6% per kaon track, <lb/>0.3% per charged pion track, and 0.8% for each CP tag <lb/>containing a K 0 <lb/>S are applied, determined from studies <lb/>of simulated and real data. The shift in κ due to the <lb/>altered efficiencies is taken as the systematic uncertainty. <lb/>The systematic effect due to non-uniform efficiency over <lb/>the Dalitz plot is treated separately and discussed in <lb/>Sec. V C. <lb/>To combine the systematic uncertainties an error ma-<lb/>trix is constructed where the diagonal elements are sep-<lb/>arate uncertainties combined in quadrature, and the off-<lb/>diagonal elements are the sum of all σ j σ k where the ef-<lb/>fect of the uncertainty is correlated between observables <lb/>j and k. The systematic uncertainties on the κ observ-<lb/>ables are given in Tables XVIII and XX, and the cen-<lb/>tral values, statistical, and total systematic uncertainties <lb/>summarized in Tables XIX and XXI. The systematic <lb/>uncertainties are smaller than the statistical uncertain-<lb/>ties. The leading systematic uncertainties arise due to <lb/>uncertainties on the branching ratios and the estimated <lb/>background yields. The average values for κ + and κ − , <lb/>taking into account systematic uncertainties and corre-<lb/>lations, are 0.56 ± 0.22 and 2.64 ± 0.67, respectively. <lb/>These averages are determined by minimizing the χ 2 be-<lb/>tween the measured and average κ values. The χ 2 /dof is <lb/>12.0/11 which indicates a good overall compatibility of <lb/>the individual measurements. The significant difference <lb/>between κ + and κ − values indicates the presence of quan-<lb/>tum correlations and a non-zero value for the quantity <lb/>p. In comparison with the incoherent expectation there <lb/>is an excess of CP -odd tags and a reduction in the yield <lb/>of CP -even tags, and hence even the low yields of the <lb/>CP -even tags carry significant information. The error <lb/>matrix for the κ observables is given in Appendix B. <lb/>The systematic uncertainty on the ν observables is <lb/>very small as there are no contributions from efficiencies <lb/>or branching fractions. The only systematic uncertainty <lb/>considered is that on background yields which partly can-<lb/>cels in the ratio. In the case of the K 0 <lb/>S,L π + π − tags the ob-<lb/>servable is simply the efficiency-corrected background-<lb/>subtracted yield. The background yield uncertainty is <lb/>calculated in the same way as for the CP tags and the <lb/>correlations between the uncertainties for the K 0 π + π − <lb/>tags and the CP tags are determined, and included in <lb/>the error matrix. Global changes to the efficiencies, those <lb/>which are the same for all bins, are not relevant as any <lb/>effect on the efficiency-corrected yield will simply be ab-<lb/>sorbed into the normalization factors in the fit. The <lb/>yields are determined per bin in the Dalitz plot, which <lb/>gives rise to the possibility that detector resolution will <lb/>lead to bin migration. This is not considered here as bin <lb/>migration effects are already taken into account in the <lb/>uncertainties on the measured values of c i and s i . <lb/>C. Combination and further systematic <lb/>uncertainties <lb/>To determine the coherence factor and average strong-<lb/>phase difference the information on the observables is <lb/>combined in a χ 2 fit to determine the best-fit values for <lb/>p and q. To take into account all the uncertainties and <lb/>their correlations the χ 2 is given by <lb/>χ 2 = ∆ρE −1 ∆ρ T , <lb/>(27) <lb/>where ∆ρ is a vector of differences between the expected <lb/>and observed values of the observables and E is the er-<lb/>ror matrix derived from the total uncertainties and their <lb/>correlations. The expected values are computed using <lb/>either Eq. (21), Eq. (22), Eq. (25), or Eq. (26) as <lb/>appropriate for a given value of p and q. To calculate <lb/>the expected values a number of external inputs are re-<lb/>quired. These external inputs are free parameters in the <lb/>fit but are Gaussian-constrained to their measured val-<lb/>ues, which takes into account any systematic uncertain-<lb/>ties arising from the measured central values of the exter-<lb/>nal inputs. Correlations between the uncertainties of the <lb/>external parameters are taken into account where known. <lb/>The values of δ Kπ , r Kπ <lb/>D , x, and y and their uncertainties <lb/>and correlations are taken from [24]. The information <lb/>on c <lb/>( ′ ) <lb/>i , s <lb/>( ′ ) <lb/>i <lb/>is from [14], and the coherence information <lb/>on other final states from [7]. The value of r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>used <lb/>is determined using the measured value of B K 0 <lb/>S Kπ and <lb/>the following relation between B K 0 <lb/>S Kπ and the D mixing <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE XVI. Efficiency-corrected signal yields in the K 0 <lb/>S π + π − bins. The uncertainties take into account the statistical <lb/>uncertainties on the uncorrected yields only. <lb/>Bini <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|K 0 <lb/>S π + π − )i 55.9±26.0 17.3±15.0 18.0±14.4 30.8±18.1 70.8±28.9 8.8±10.0 20.1±16.8 37.2±20.2 <lb/>Bini <lb/>−1 <lb/>−2 <lb/>−3 <lb/>−4 <lb/>−5 <lb/>−6 <lb/>−7 <lb/>−8 <lb/>S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|K 0 <lb/>S π + π − )i 42.0±24.1 40.5±22.2 53.6±24.9 35.3±19.4 81.4±29.6 43.2±21.9 5.3±11.1 76.9±29.6 <lb/>TABLE XVII. Efficiency-corrected signal yields in the K 0 <lb/>L π + π − bins. The uncertainties take into account the statistical <lb/>uncertainties on the uncorrected yields only. <lb/>Bini <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|K 0 <lb/>L π + π − )i 123.6±28.4 28.7±14.5 28.5±13.8 4.0±6.8 20.7±13.2 18.2±12.2 107.0±25.2 106.5±25.5 <lb/>Bini <lb/>−1 <lb/>−2 <lb/>−3 <lb/>−4 <lb/>−5 <lb/>−6 <lb/>−7 <lb/>−8 <lb/>S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|K 0 <lb/>L π + π − )i 128.5±29.4 48.5±17.5 20.1±11.5 9.5±9.2 14.3±12.3 21.3±13.0 53.5±18.7 58.0±19.1 <lb/>TABLE XVIII. The systematic uncertainties on the κ + values. <lb/>KK ππ K 0 <lb/>L π 0 K 0 <lb/>L ω K 0 <lb/>L η K 0 <lb/>L η ′ K 0 <lb/>S π 0 π 0 <lb/>CP tag branching fraction <lb/>0.004 0.017 0.095 0.077 0.005 0.060 0.553 <lb/>D 0 → Kπ branching fraction <lb/>0.003 0.012 0.019 0.007 0.001 0.006 0.042 <lb/>Background scaling ratio <lb/>0.057 0.196 0.062 0.028 0.128 0.090 0.015 <lb/>Kπ tag yield <lb/>0.028 0.114 0.183 0.064 0.006 0.058 0.408 <lb/>CP tag tracking and reconstruction 0.002 0.004 0.029 0.010 0.000 0.002 0.070 <lb/>Kπ tracking and reconstruction <lb/>0.001 0.006 0.010 0.003 0.000 0.003 0.022 <lb/>Total syst. <lb/>0.064 0.228 0.218 0.105 0.129 0.122 0.693 <lb/>TABLE XIX. The central values κ + and the statistical and systematic uncertainties. <lb/>KK ππ K 0 <lb/>L π 0 K 0 <lb/>L ω K 0 <lb/>L η K 0 <lb/>L η ′ K 0 <lb/>S π 0 π 0 <lb/>Central κ value <lb/>0.219 0.909 1.456 0.512 −0.049 0.459 3.247 <lb/>Statistical uncertainty <lb/>0.328 0.855 0.382 0.467 0.665 1.702 1.063 <lb/>Total systematic uncertainty 0.064 0.228 0.218 0.105 0.129 0.122 0.693 <lb/>Total stat. + syst. <lb/>0.334 0.885 0.440 0.479 0.677 1.706 1.269 <lb/>TABLE XX. The systematic uncertainties on the κ − values. <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S π 0 K 0 <lb/>S ω K 0 <lb/>S η(γγ) K 0 <lb/>S η(πππ 0 ) K 0 <lb/>S η ′ K 0 <lb/>L π 0 π 0 <lb/>Tag branching fraction <lb/>0.145 0.571 0.773 <lb/>0.117 <lb/>0.498 0.499 <lb/>D 0 → Kπ branching fraction <lb/>0.040 0.049 0.089 <lb/>0.013 <lb/>0.049 0.038 <lb/>Background scaling ratio <lb/>0.004 0.015 0.010 <lb/>0.030 <lb/>0.008 0.075 <lb/>Kπ tag yield <lb/>0.390 0.476 0.873 <lb/>0.131 <lb/>0.483 0.368 <lb/>CP tag tracking and reconstruction 0.067 0.083 0.063 <lb/>0.023 <lb/>0.038 0.057 <lb/>Kπ tracking and reconstruction <lb/>0.021 0.025 0.047 <lb/>0.007 <lb/>0.026 0.020 <lb/>Total syst. <lb/>0.424 0.750 1.172 <lb/>0.180 <lb/>0.697 0.628 <lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE XXI. The central values κ − and the statistical and systematic uncertainties. <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S π 0 K 0 <lb/>S ω K 0 <lb/>S η(γγ) K 0 <lb/>S η(πππ 0 ) K 0 <lb/>S η ′ K 0 <lb/>L π 0 π 0 <lb/>Central κ value <lb/>3.102 3.791 6.949 <lb/>1.043 <lb/>3.841 2.928 <lb/>Statistical uncertainty <lb/>0.669 1.160 2.676 <lb/>2.595 <lb/>4.614 2.114 <lb/>Total systematic uncertainty 0.424 0.750 1.172 <lb/>0.180 <lb/>0.697 0.628 <lb/>Total stat. + syst. <lb/>0.792 1.382 2.921 <lb/>2.602 <lb/>4.667 2.205 <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>parameters [2]: <lb/>B K 0 <lb/>S Kπ = <lb/>(r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>) 2 + (yp − xq)r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>1 + (yp − xq)r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>, <lb/>(28) <lb/>where the quadratic and higher order terms in y and x <lb/>are negligible. <lb/>The χ 2 is minimized to determine the best-fit values <lb/>of p and q. The normalization factors H S and H L of <lb/>Eqs. (25) and (26) are also free parameters in the fit. The <lb/>best-fit values are p = 0.719 ± 0.077 and q = 0.105 ± <lb/>0.194. The χ 2 /dof of the fit is 53.8/41. The performance <lb/>of the fit is tested using simple simulation. The simple <lb/>simulation generates observable values based on input <lb/>values of R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ and δ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>, where the observable value <lb/>for each tag is smeared by the experimentally observed <lb/>uncertainties. The studies using the simple simulation <lb/>confirm that the use of tag yields that are consistent with <lb/>zero do not cause bias and that tags with low yields do <lb/>add sensitivity to the overall measurement. <lb/>The efficiencies are determined from Monte Carlo <lb/>where the decay products are generated uniformly over <lb/>phase space. However the efficiency is not uniform over <lb/>the Dalitz plot, and furthermore as the distribution of <lb/>events over the Dalitz plot is different depending on the <lb/>tag due to quantum correlations a further systematic un-<lb/>certainty must be considered. This uncertainty is deter-<lb/>mined by using the isobar models described in Sec. III. <lb/>The shifts in the values of p and q are computed using <lb/>Eq. (3) and inserting either a flat efficiency or the CLEO-<lb/>c efficiency model for a variety of isobar models including <lb/>the reported ones. The largest shifts observed between <lb/>the flat and CLEO-c efficiency model are 0.016 for p and <lb/>0.002 for q which are small in comparison to the mea-<lb/>sured uncertainty. Hence these shifts are assigned as the <lb/>systematic uncertainty from non-uniform efficiency. <lb/>As p is positive and R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ is defined to be between <lb/>zero and one, the solution for δ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>lies in the range <lb/>from −90 • to 90 • . This leads to R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ = 0.73 ± 0.08 <lb/>and δ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>= (8.3±15.2) • . Figure 9 shows regions of <lb/>(R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ , δ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>) parameter space from the fit consis-<lb/>tent with one, two, and three standard deviations from <lb/>the best-fit point. The likelihood is computed as L = <lb/>e −(χ 2 −χ 2 <lb/>min )/2 at a point in parameter space; the fit is re-<lb/>peated at each point with the values of p and q fixed. The <lb/>isobar models also give predictions of the coherence fac-<lb/>tor via Eq. (3). The isobar models predict a coherence <lb/>factor of 0.72 (0.79) when the central values of favored <lb/>and suppressed models 1 (2) are used. The predictions <lb/>are consistent with the measured value. <lb/>D. Coherence factor in a restricted region <lb/>Around dominant resonances occurring in both Dalitz <lb/>plots, the coherence factor is expected to be close to one, <lb/>FIG. 9. The best-fit point for R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ and δ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>measured <lb/>over the whole Dalitz plot, and the regions enclosing 1, 2, and <lb/>3 standard deviations from that point. <lb/>as this situation approximates the two-body decay which <lb/>is fully coherent. Higher coherence in principle provides <lb/>increased sensitivity to γ. Therefore the analysis is re-<lb/>peated using only the data where the invariant mass <lb/>of the K 0 <lb/>S π combination lies within 100 MeV/c 2 of the <lb/>K * (892) ± mass. The analysis could, in principle, also <lb/>be performed in the region outside this invariant mass <lb/>window; however the data are insufficient for this com-<lb/>plementary study. The efficiencies for each double tag <lb/>are recalculated for the restricted region. The efficiency-<lb/>corrected yields for the CP tags and Kπ SS tag in this <lb/>restricted region are given in Tables XXII and XXIII. <lb/>The efficiency-corrected yields for K 0 <lb/>S,L π + π − tags are <lb/>given in Table XXIV and Table XXV. The expected <lb/>yield of the K 0 <lb/>L η ′ tag is very small and is not used. The <lb/>error matrix relating the uncertainties for the κ observ-<lb/>ables is given in Appendix B. In the restricted region, <lb/>the values of the ν variables are 0.40±0.08, 0.35±0.06 <lb/>and 0.35±0.05 for ν Kπ , ν Kπππ , and ν Kππ 0 , respectively. <lb/>The value of B K * K that is used in the analysis is the <lb/>one calculated for the restricted region in Sec. IV. In <lb/>the restricted kinematic region case, a further system-<lb/>atic uncertainty arises due to detector resolution as the <lb/>candidate events may migrate across the defined bound-<lb/>ary in the Dalitz plot. To account for this migration <lb/>simulated signal data samples are generated using the <lb/>resonant models determined in the amplitude analysis. <lb/>For the CP tags and the K 0 <lb/>S,L π + π − tags the quantum <lb/>correlation between the tag and signal side is emulated. <lb/>Candidate events can migrate into the restricted region, <lb/>or they can migrate out. There is no systematic uncer-<lb/></body>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE XXII. Efficiency-corrected yields in the restricted region for double tags with no K 0 <lb/>L in final state. <lb/>Tag <lb/>KK <lb/>ππ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S π 0 π 0 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S π 0 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S ω <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S η(γγ) K 0 <lb/>S η(πππ 0 ) <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S η ′ <lb/>Kπ SS <lb/>S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|G) 6.0±14.2 2.0±11.1 43.7±37.8 233.1±57.9 199.9±68.7 47.8±28.2 10.1±18.1 83.0±87.5 288.9±48.7 <lb/>TABLE XXIII. Efficiency-corrected signal yields in the re-<lb/>stricted region for the CP tags with a K 0 <lb/>L . <lb/>Tag <lb/>K 0 <lb/>L π 0 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>L ω <lb/>K 0 <lb/>L η <lb/>K 0 <lb/>L π 0 π 0 <lb/>S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|G) 116.2±37.1 25.9±38.9 −4.7±8.5 186.4±194.0 <lb/>tainty if the migration in both directions is equal, but <lb/>the presence of the resonance means that a larger frac-<lb/>tion of events will migrate out of the restricted region <lb/>than migrate in. The net migration factor is determined <lb/>from the simulated data. It is different for different types <lb/>of tags due to the quantum correlations which alter the <lb/>distribution of the K 0 <lb/>S Kπ decay on the Dalitz plot. The <lb/>net migration factor is treated in the same way as a sys-<lb/>tematic uncertainty on the efficiency in the analysis. The <lb/>net migration factor, that is the net loss of events inside <lb/>the region, varies between tag categories and is of order <lb/>1% of the yield within the region. <lb/>Tables XXVI-XXIX give the results for the observable <lb/>κ and its uncertainties for the K * (892) ± bin. The average <lb/>values are κ + = 0.44 ± 0.30 and κ − = 3.18 ± 1.08 with a <lb/>χ 2 /dof of 6.5/10. The uncertainties due to non-uniform <lb/>efficiency are 0.002 and 0.001 for p and q, respectively. <lb/>They are reduced in comparison to the full Dalitz plot <lb/>measurement as the efficiency is more uniform over the <lb/>restricted region. <lb/>The fitted values of p and q are p = 0.893 ± 0.089 and <lb/>q = 0.446 ± 0.304, with χ 2 /dof given by 48.7/40. This <lb/>leads to a measurement of R K * K = 1.00±0.16 and δ K * K <lb/>D <lb/>= <lb/>(26.5 ± 15.8) • . The regions consistent with one, two, <lb/>and three standard deviations from the best-fit point are <lb/>shown in Fig. 10. The coherence in the region of the <lb/>K * (892) ± is larger than the coherence over the full Dalitz <lb/>plot and is consistent with one. The prediction from <lb/>the isobar models for the restricted region is 0.93 (0.94) <lb/>when favored and suppressed models 1 (2) are used. The <lb/>predictions are consistent with the measured value. <lb/>E. Impact on γ measurements <lb/>It is instructive to estimate the impact of the knowl-<lb/>edge of the coherence factor and average strong-phase <lb/>difference on a measurement of γ performed at LHCb or <lb/>a future high luminosity e + e − experiment. Simple sim-<lb/>ulated data are generated assuming 15000 B − → DK − <lb/>events with D decaying to K 0 <lb/>S K ± π ∓ , and γ = 70 • , δ B = <lb/>130 • and r B = 0.1, and r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>and R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ and δ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>as measured here for the full Dalitz plot. The chosen val-<lb/>FIG. 10. The best-fit point for RK * K and δ K * K <lb/>D <lb/>which are <lb/>measured over the restricted region, and the regions enclosing <lb/>1, 2, and 3 standard deviations from that point. <lb/>ues for γ, δ B , and r B are consistent with current knowl-<lb/>edge [4]. The data samples are fit with only the parame-<lb/>ter γ free. The width of the best-fit γ distribution is 10 • . <lb/>The restricted region will have approximately 60% of the <lb/>statistics of the full Dalitz plot. A similar study in the <lb/>restricted region assuming 9000 events and the values of <lb/>r K * K <lb/>D <lb/>and R K * K and δ K * K <lb/>D <lb/>as measured in the restricted <lb/>region has a best-fit γ distribution of 5 • . The better <lb/>sensitivity, despite the smaller sample, is due to a com-<lb/>bination of increased coherence, a lower value of r K * K <lb/>D <lb/>in comparison to r <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>, and a different value of the av-<lb/>erage strong-phase difference. The uncertainties on the <lb/>coherence factor and average strong-phase difference are <lb/>incorporated by making them free parameters in the fit <lb/>and applying Gaussian constraints based on their mea-<lb/>sured uncertainties. In this case the width of the best-fit <lb/>γ distribution increases to 14 • and 7 • for the full Dalitz <lb/>plot and restricted regions, respectively. The uncertain-<lb/>ties R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ , δ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>, R K * K , and δ K * K <lb/>D <lb/>are dominated by <lb/>the statistical uncertainties and hence the precision of <lb/>any measurement of γ could be increased with a more <lb/>accurate measurement of the coherence factors and aver-<lb/>age strong-phase differences. The inclusion of this decay <lb/>channel in a global fit to γ with other channels will im-<lb/></body>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE XXIV. Efficiency-corrected signal yields in the restricted region in the K 0 <lb/>S π + π − bins. <lb/>Bin <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|K 0 <lb/>S π + π − )i 40.3±36.8 48.3±35.8 19.5±23.6 49.3±35.8 128.2±60.4 25.1±27.5 54.6±44.3 18.8±23.8 <lb/>Bin <lb/>−1 <lb/>−2 <lb/>−3 <lb/>−4 <lb/>−5 <lb/>−6 <lb/>−7 <lb/>−8 <lb/>S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|K 0 <lb/>S π + π − )i 65.7±43.7 45.3±38.4 59.0±40.0 23.2±25.4 108.6±50.3 54.8±39.8 16.3±21.8 115.7±59.2 <lb/>TABLE XXV. Efficiency-corrected signal yields in the restricted region in the K 0 <lb/>L π + π − bins. <lb/>Bin <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|K 0 <lb/>L π + π − )i 201.0±54.9 23.3±22.2 60.7±29.2 −9.4±14.0 25.6±21.3 −1.2±13.0 156.2±45.8 176.2±48.5 <lb/>Bin <lb/>−1 <lb/>−2 <lb/>−3 <lb/>−4 <lb/>−5 <lb/>−6 <lb/>−7 <lb/>−8 <lb/>S(K 0 <lb/>S Kπ|K 0 <lb/>L π + π − )i 242.5±59.6 79.2±33.0 26.5±19.4 2.4±12.6 29.0±22.5 12.9±19.8 86.4±34.7 65.2±29.6 <lb/>TABLE XXVI. Systematic uncertainties on the κ + values determined in the restricted region. <lb/>KK π + π − K 0 <lb/>L π 0 K 0 <lb/>L ω K 0 <lb/>L η K 0 <lb/>S π 0 π 0 <lb/>Tag branching fraction <lb/>0.004 0.004 0.109 0.058 0.045 0.149 <lb/>D 0 → Kπ branching fraction <lb/>0.003 0.002 0.021 0.005 0.005 0.011 <lb/>Background scaling ratio <lb/>0.091 0.230 0.062 0.032 0.126 0.017 <lb/>Kπ tag yield <lb/>0.042 0.039 0.338 0.078 0.082 0.177 <lb/>CP tag tracking and reconstruction 0.002 0.001 0.033 0.008 0.000 0.019 <lb/>Kπ tracking and reconstruction <lb/>0.001 0.001 0.011 0.003 0.003 0.006 <lb/>Bin migration <lb/>0.000 0.000 0.003 0.001 0.001 0.001 <lb/>Total syst. <lb/>0.100 0.233 0.363 0.103 0.157 0.233 <lb/>TABLE XXVII. The central values of κ + determined in the restricted region and the statistical and systematic uncertainties. <lb/>KK π + π − K 0 <lb/>L π 0 K 0 <lb/>L ω K 0 <lb/>L η K 0 <lb/>S π 0 π 0 <lb/>Central κ value <lb/>0.205 0.192 1.665 0.386 −0.402 0.873 <lb/>Statistical uncertainty 0.491 1.059 0.532 0.579 0.730 <lb/>0.755 <lb/>Total syst. <lb/>0.100 0.233 0.363 0.103 0.157 <lb/>0.233 <lb/>Total stat. + syst. <lb/>0.501 1.085 0.644 0.588 0.746 <lb/>0.790 <lb/>TABLE XXVIII. Systematic uncertainties on the κ − values determined in the restricted region. <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S π 0 K 0 <lb/>S ω K 0 <lb/>S η(γγ) K 0 <lb/>S η(πππ 0 ) K 0 <lb/>S η ′ K 0 <lb/>L π 0 π 0 <lb/>Tag branching fraction <lb/>0.188 0.656 0.665 <lb/>0.266 <lb/>1.339 0.432 <lb/>D 0 → Kπ branching fraction <lb/>0.051 0.056 0.077 <lb/>0.031 <lb/>0.133 0.033 <lb/>Background scaling ratio <lb/>0.004 0.008 0.016 <lb/>0.045 <lb/>0.000 0.054 <lb/>Kπ tag yield <lb/>0.812 0.884 1.212 <lb/>0.483 <lb/>2.094 0.515 <lb/>CP tag tracking and reconstruction 0.086 0.095 0.054 <lb/>0.052 <lb/>0.102 0.050 <lb/>Kπ tag tracking and reconstruction 0.027 0.029 0.040 <lb/>0.016 <lb/>0.069 0.017 <lb/>Bin migration <lb/>0.006 0.005 0.007 <lb/>0.003 <lb/>0.011 0.003 <lb/>Total syst. <lb/>0.840 1.107 1.386 <lb/>0.557 <lb/>2.493 0.677 <lb/></body>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE XXIX. The central values of κ − determined in the restricted region and the statistical and systematic uncertainties. <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S π 0 K 0 <lb/>S ω K 0 <lb/>S η(γγ) K 0 <lb/>S η(πππ 0 ) K 0 <lb/>S η ′ K 0 <lb/>L π 0 π 0 <lb/>Central κ value <lb/>4.003 4.357 5.975 <lb/>2.382 <lb/>10.324 2.537 <lb/>Statistical uncertainty 0.994 1.498 3.523 <lb/>4.269 <lb/>10.881 2.640 <lb/>Total syst. <lb/>0.840 1.107 1.386 <lb/>0.557 <lb/>2.493 0.677 <lb/>Total stat. + syst. <lb/>1.301 1.862 3.786 <lb/>4.305 <lb/>11.163 2.726 <lb/></body>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>prove the overall sensitivity to this parameter. <lb/>VI. SUMMARY <lb/>Isobar models for the decays D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K − π + and <lb/>D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K + π − have been presented. They are dom-<lb/>inated by the K * (892) ± resonance in the case of the <lb/>favored decay and by the same resonance and a broad <lb/>S-wave component in the suppressed decay. The ratio of <lb/>the branching fractions has been measured, and is more <lb/>precise that the previous average [4]. The coherence fac-<lb/>tor and average strong-phase difference for D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>have been measured in two regions. The first covers all <lb/>final state kinematics, and the second covers a restricted <lb/>region around the K * (892) ± resonance. The coherence <lb/>is high, which makes the D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S Kπ channel inter-<lb/>esting for future determinations of the CKM phase γ. <lb/>The measured values of B K 0 <lb/>S Kπ , R K 0 <lb/>S Kπ , and δ <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S Kπ <lb/>D <lb/>are <lb/>also all useful inputs for charm mixing measurements as <lb/>described in [2]. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>We gratefully acknowledge the effort of the CESR staff <lb/>in providing us with excellent luminosity and running <lb/>conditions. This work was supported by the National <lb/>Science Foundation, the U.S. Department of Energy, the <lb/>Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of <lb/>Canada, and the U.K. Science and Technology Facilities <lb/>Council. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Appendix A: The interference fit fractions <lb/>This appendix gives the full interference fit fractions <lb/>as defined in Eq. (14) between each resonance for each <lb/>model in Tables XXX-XXXIII. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Appendix B: The covariance matrices <lb/>Tables XXXIV and XXXV give the the covariance <lb/>matrices for the uncertainties between the κ measure-<lb/>ments from the different tags. Entries below the diagonal <lb/>are not shown. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>[1] N. Cabibbo, Phys. Rev. Lett. 10, 531 (1963); M. <lb/>Kobayashi and T. Maskawa, Prog. Theor. Phys. 49, 652, <lb/>(1973). <lb/>[2] S. Malde and G. Wilkinson, Phys. Lett. B 701, 353 <lb/>(2011). <lb/>[3] B. Bhattacharya and J. Rosner, arXiv:1104.4962. <lb/>[4] K. Nakamura et al., (Particle Data Group) J. Phys. G <lb/>37, 075021 (2010). <lb/>[5] D. Atwood and A. Soni, Phys. Rev. D 68, 033003 (2003). <lb/>[6] D. Atwood, I. Dunietz, and A. Soni, Phys. Rev. Lett. 78, <lb/>3257 (1997); D. Atwood, I. Dunietz, and A. Soni, Phys. <lb/>Rev. D 63, 036005 (2001). <lb/>[7] N. Lowrey et al. (CLEO Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D <lb/>80, 031105R (2009). <lb/>[8] D. Peterson et al. (CLEO Collaboration), Nucl. Instrum. <lb/>Methods A 478, 142 (2002). <lb/>[9] R.A. Briere et al. (CLEO-c/CESR-c Taskforces and <lb/>CLEO Collaboration) Cornell LEPP preprint CLNS <lb/>01/1742 (2001) (unpublished). <lb/>[10] Y. Kubota et al. (CLEO Collaboration), Nucl. Instrum. <lb/>Methods A 320, 66 (1992); M. Artuso et al. (CLEO Col-<lb/>laboration), Nucl. Instrum. Methods A 502, 91 (2003). <lb/>[11] S. Dobbs et al. (CLEO Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D 76, <lb/>112001 (2007). <lb/>[12] D. Lange et al., Nucl. Instrum. Methods A 462, 152 <lb/>(2001). <lb/>[13] R. Brun et al., GEANT 3.21, CERN Program Library <lb/>Long Writeup W5013 (unpublished). <lb/>[14] J. Libby et al. (CLEO Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D 82, <lb/>112006 (2010). <lb/>[15] B. Aubert et al. (Babar Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D <lb/>78, 034023 (2008). <lb/>[16] Q. He et al. (CLEO Collaboration), Phys. Rev. Lett. 100, <lb/>091801 (2008). <lb/>[17] S. Kopp et al. (CLEO Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D 63, <lb/>092001 (2001). <lb/>[18] J.M. Blatt and V.F. Weisskopf, Theoretical Nuclear <lb/>Physics (John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, 1974). <lb/>[19] P. Frabetti et al. (E687 Collaboration), Phys. Lett. B <lb/>331, 217 (1994). <lb/>[20] D. Aston et al. (LASS Collaboration), Nucl. Phys. B296, <lb/>493 (1988). <lb/>[21] S.M. Flatte, Phys. Lett. B 63, 224 (1976). <lb/>[22] R. Aaij et al. (LHCb Collaboration), Phys. Rev. Lett. <lb/>108, 111602 (2012); T. Altonen et al. (CDF Collabora-<lb/>tion) Phys. Rev. D 85, 012009 (2012). <lb/>[23] For a review, see M. Artuso, B. Meadows, and A.A. <lb/>Petrov, Annu. Rev. Nucl. Part. Sci. 58, 249 (2008). <lb/>[24] D. Asner et al. (HFAG), arXiv:1010.1589. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE XXX. The interference fit fractions between every pair of resonances in favored model 1. The fractions are provided <lb/>as a percent. <lb/>K * (892) 0 <lb/>K * (1410) 0 <lb/>K * (1680) − <lb/>K * <lb/>0 (1430) − <lb/>a0(1450) + <lb/>K * (892) − −0.23±0.65±0.57 −12.29±1.23±3.42 13.62±3.32±2.17 3.38±0.88±0.63 2.56±2.09±1.71 <lb/>K * (892) 0 <lb/>−2.81±1.55±0.79 0.23±0.27±0.75 <lb/>0.57±0.30±0.24 0.26±0.30±0.12 <lb/>K * (1410) 0 <lb/>−21.18±2.73±8.66 1.15±0.61±1.39 0.78±3.19±1.99 <lb/>K * (1680) − <lb/>−6.70±1.79±2.68 0.55±4.08±2.00 <lb/>K * <lb/>0 (1430) − <lb/>1.37±1.17±0.75 <lb/>TABLE XXXI. The interference fit fractions between every pair of resonances in favored model 2. The fractions are provided <lb/>as a percent. <lb/>K * (1410) 0 <lb/>K * (1680) − <lb/>ρ(1700) + <lb/>K * <lb/>0 (1430) − <lb/>a0(1450) + <lb/>K * (892) − −14.04±1.42±2.02 13.05±2.61±4.02 <lb/>3.60±1.52±3.36 3.58±0.70±0.92 4.03±1.60±1.52 <lb/>K * (1410) 0 <lb/>−27.47±5.29±28.07 −7.33±3.45±8.73 1.55±0.74±2.30 1.82±3.41±1.72 <lb/>K * (1680) − <lb/>−4.33±2.76±7.87 −8.06±1.93±7.16 −0.30±4.16±1.98 <lb/>ρ(1700) + <lb/>1.24±0.55±1.57 0.02±0.01±0.01 <lb/>K * <lb/>0 (1430) − <lb/>2.49±1.34±0.86 <lb/>TABLE XXXII. The interference fit fractions between every pair of resonances in suppressed model 1. The fractions are <lb/>provided as a percent. <lb/>K * (892) 0 <lb/>K * <lb/>0 (1430) − <lb/>a0(1450) + <lb/>ρ(1700) + <lb/>K * (892) − −0.74±0.46±0.10 4.91±0.57±0.53 7.01±0.88±0.87 5.74±0.91±1.16 <lb/>K * (892) 0 <lb/>1.34±0.54±0.33 −0.50±0.58±0.40 0.72±0.47±0.29 <lb/>K * <lb/>0 (1430) − <lb/>17.39±1.52±1.69 −0.49±0.75±0.41 <lb/>a0(1450) + <lb/>−0.01±0.01±0.01 <lb/>TABLE XXXIII. The interference fit fractions between every pair of resonances in suppressed model 2. The fractions are <lb/>provided as a percent. <lb/>K * <lb/>0 (1430) − <lb/>ρ(1700) + <lb/>a0(1450) + <lb/>K * <lb/>2 (1430) 0 <lb/>K * (892) − 5.70±0.55±0.31 6.41±0.89±1.41 3.62±0.95±0.64 1.75±0.81±3.32 <lb/>K * <lb/>0 (1430) − <lb/>2.07±0.85±0.80 15.25±2.21±0.91 −5.79±5.60±9.15 <lb/>ρ(1700) + <lb/>0.00±0.01±0.01 4.00±1.23±1.71 <lb/>a0(1450) + <lb/>−3.71±1.64±2.26 <lb/></body>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE XXXIV. The covariance matrix for the κ observables determined using data from the full Dalitz plot. <lb/>κ KK κ ππ κ K L π 0 κ K L ω κ K L η(γγ) κ K L η ′ κ K S π 0 π 0 κ K S π 0 κ K S ω κ K S η(γγ) κ K S η(πππ 0 ) κ K S η ′ κ K L π 0 π 0 <lb/>κ KK <lb/>0.11 0.01 0.01 0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.01 0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>κ ππ <lb/>0.78 0.03 0.01 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.05 0.06 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>κ K L π 0 <lb/>0.19 0.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.07 0.09 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>κ K L ω <lb/>0.23 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.03 0.08 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>κ K L η(γγ) <lb/>0.46 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.00 0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>κ K L η ′ <lb/>2.91 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.02 0.03 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>κ K S π 0 π 0 <lb/>1.61 <lb/>0.16 0.20 <lb/>0.36 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>0.43 <lb/>κ K S π 0 <lb/>0.63 0.19 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.19 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>κ K S ω <lb/>1.91 <lb/>0.42 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>0.18 <lb/>κ K S η(γγ) <lb/>8.53 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>0.43 <lb/>0.33 <lb/>κ K S η(πππ 0 ) <lb/>6.77 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>κ K S η ′ <lb/>21.78 <lb/>0.18 <lb/>κ K L π 0 π 0 <lb/>4.86 <lb/></body>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE XXXV. The covariance matrix for the κ observables determined using data from the restricted region. <lb/>κ KK κ ππ κ K L π 0 κ K L ω κ K L η(γγ) κ K S π 0 π 0 κ K S π 0 κ K S ω κ K S η(γγ) κ K S η(πππ 0 ) κ K S η ′ κ K L π 0 π 0 <lb/>κ KK <lb/>0.25 0.02 0.02 0.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.03 0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>κ ππ <lb/>1.18 0.03 0.01 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.03 0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>κ K L π 0 <lb/>0.41 0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.28 0.30 <lb/>0.41 <lb/>0.17 <lb/>0.71 <lb/>0.18 <lb/>κ K L ω <lb/>0.35 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.06 0.11 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>κ K L η(γγ) <lb/>0.56 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.07 0.07 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.17 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>κ K S π 0 π 0 <lb/>0.62 <lb/>0.14 0.16 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>0.37 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>κ K S π 0 <lb/>1.69 0.72 <lb/>0.99 <lb/>0.39 <lb/>1.71 <lb/>0.42 <lb/>κ K S ω <lb/>3.47 <lb/>1.08 <lb/>0.43 <lb/>1.86 <lb/>0.46 <lb/>κ K S η(γγ) <lb/>14.33 <lb/>0.77 <lb/>2.55 <lb/>0.63 <lb/>κ K S η(πππ 0 ) <lb/>18.53 <lb/>1.02 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>κ K S η ′ <lb/>124.62 1.08 <lb/>κ K L π 0 π 0 <lb/>7.43 </body>


	</text>
</tei>
