<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>J. Cell Commun. Signal. (2011) 5:253–254 <lb/>DOI 10.1007/s12079-011-0155-x <lb/>EDITORIAL <lb/>ICCNS-sponsored meetings <lb/>Bernard Perbal <lb/>Published online: 30 November 2011 <lb/># The International CCN Society 2011 <lb/></front>

			<body>Dear Members of the ICCNS, <lb/>Dear Colleague, <lb/>At the dawn of the 12th birthday of the ICCNS, it is a great <lb/>pleasure to write this end-of -the-year Editorial and share <lb/>with you an overview of our progress. <lb/>This year has been the time for great changes and <lb/>improvements. <lb/>Among these and for the first time since it was created, the <lb/>ICCNS has officially sponsored a scientific meeting (http:// <lb/>www.ccnsociety.com/targets_2011/index.html) which was <lb/>outside of the regular biannual International workshops on <lb/>the CCN family of genes. <lb/>Thanks to Andrew Leask and other co-organizers who <lb/>helped him, the Vancouver meeting was a success and <lb/>opened the road for new ones. <lb/>As I had previously suggested at the 6th CCN workshop <lb/>in Ireland the idea is to broaden the activity of our society <lb/>and make our family of proteins known by scientists work-<lb/>ing in fields that overlap ours. <lb/>Actually, this was and remains one of the very original <lb/>objectives of the ICCNS. <lb/>The ICCNS is ready to sponsor and provide help for orga-<lb/>nizing meetings dealing with all aspects related to signaling and <lb/>cellular communication in normal and pathological conditions. <lb/>Those who wish to organize such ICCNS-sponsored <lb/>meetings should proceed as follows: <lb/>the President elect (presently Professor Masaharu <lb/>Takigawa). <lb/>2) provide in the application a rough estimate of the <lb/>meeting cost and a rough number of expected attendees. <lb/>3) the application should also provide details as to the type <lb/>and amount of local or external funding that is <lb/>expected. <lb/>1) submit a short written proposal and send it directly to <lb/>the ICCNS bureau (ccnsociety@yahoo.com) who will <lb/>centralize, file and forward the various applications to <lb/>The President Elect will consult members of the Scien-<lb/>tific Board and scientists outside of the CCN Society, in <lb/>order to evaluate the feasibility and potential interest of the <lb/>proposed meeting. <lb/>Once the President elect has selected the meeting pro-<lb/>posals, a decision will be made with the Executive Board of <lb/>the ICCNS. <lb/>Please do not hesitate to send us your suggestions <lb/>In any case, these interim meetings are not meant to <lb/>replace or substitute the regular biannual Workshops on <lb/>the family of CCN Genes, that remain the major activity <lb/>sponsored by ICCNS and organized by ICCNS members. <lb/>The next workshop will be held October 21-24th 2012 in <lb/>Sydney and might possibly be followed by a come back to <lb/>Saint-Malo in 2014! <lb/>Discussions regarding these events have already been <lb/>initiated and should be confirmed shortly. <lb/>Another major achievement was reached with our society <lb/>journal JCCS. <lb/>Thanks to Andrew Leask and all the authors who have <lb/>shown strong support to the journal, citations of JCCS <lb/>manuscripts increase at a fast pace and we should be soon <lb/>in a position to apply for an Impact factor at ISI. <lb/>Right now, our unofficial IF is between 2 and 3. <lb/>A series of special issues featuring topics of interest <lb/>should help us in reinforcing our position in the competitive <lb/>field of publication. <lb/></body>

			<front>B. Perbal (*) <lb/>President of the ICCNS, <lb/>Paris, France <lb/>e-mail: bperbal@gmail.com <lb/></front>

			<body>As previously stated on several occasions, active ICCNS <lb/>membership is important and we need you to help us in <lb/>maintaining the high quality of science that we sponsor and <lb/>publish. <lb/>Attracting more members and consolidating our strength <lb/>will depend upon your help. <lb/>The ICCNS is yours and we count on you. <lb/>Let me take this occasion to wish you all the best for the end <lb/>of 2011 and hope that we can all meet in Sydney next year. <lb/>Professor Bernard PERBAL <lb/>Executive President of the ICCNS <lb/></body>

			<page>254 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">B. Perbal </note>


	</text>
</tei>
