<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Marušić et al. BMC Medicine 2014, 12:197 <lb/>http://www.biomedcentral.com/1741-7015/12/197 <lb/> C O R R E S P O N D E N C E <lb/>Open Access <lb/>Five-step authorship framework to improve <lb/>transparency in disclosing contributors to <lb/>industry-sponsored clinical trial publications <lb/>Ana Marušić <lb/>1* <lb/>, Darko Hren <lb/>2 <lb/>, Bernadette Mansi <lb/>3,4 , Neil Lineberry <lb/>4,5 <lb/>, Ananya Bhattacharya <lb/>4,6 , Maureen Garrity <lb/>4,7 , <lb/>Juli Clark <lb/>4,8 <lb/>, Thomas Gesell <lb/>4,9 , Susan Glasser <lb/>4,10 , John Gonzalez <lb/>4,11 , Carolyn Hustad <lb/>4,12 , Mary-Margaret Lannon <lb/>4,13 , <lb/>LaVerne A Mooney <lb/>4,14 and Teresa Peña <lb/>4,15 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Authorship guidelines have established criteria to guide author selection based on significance of contribution and helped <lb/>to define associated responsibilities and accountabilities for the published findings. However, low awareness, variable <lb/>interpretation, and inconsistent application of these guidelines can lead to confusion and a lack of transparency when <lb/>recognizing those who merit authorship. This article describes a research project led by the Medical Publishing Insights and <lb/>Practices (MPIP) Initiative to identify current challenges when determining authorship for industry-sponsored clinical trials <lb/>and develop an improved approach to facilitate decision-making when recognizing authors from related publications. A <lb/>total of 498 clinical investigators, journal editors, publication professionals and medical writers were surveyed to understand <lb/>better how they would adjudicate challenging, real-world authorship case scenarios, determine the perceived frequency of <lb/>each scenario and rate their confidence in the responses provided. Multiple rounds of discussions about these results with <lb/>journal editors, clinical investigators and industry representatives led to the development of key recommendations intended <lb/>to enhance transparency when determining authorship. These included forming a representative group to establish <lb/>authorship criteria early in a trial, having all trial contributors agree to these criteria and documenting trial contributions to <lb/>objectively determine who warrants an invitation to participate in the manuscript development process. The resulting <lb/>Five-step Authorship Framework is designed to create a more standardized approach when determining authorship for <lb/>clinical trial publications. Overall, these recommendations aim to facilitate more transparent authorship decisions and help <lb/>readers better assess the credibility of results and perspectives of the authors for medical research more broadly. <lb/>Please see related article: http://www.biomedcentral.com/1741-7015/12/214. <lb/>Keywords: Authorship, Transparency, Clinical trial, MPIP Initiative, Journal editors, Medical writers, Clinical investigators, <lb/>Publication professionals <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>The designation of authorship is essential for published re-<lb/>search to be represented by those who provide significant <lb/>intellectual contribution to its development and execution. <lb/>More recently, authorship selection has evolved to confer <lb/>not only the credit for the research but also accountability <lb/>and responsibility for accuracy and integrity of the <lb/>work. Yet, making this determination can be especially <lb/>challenging due to the ambiguous nature of available <lb/>authorship guidelines and the increasing complexity of <lb/>clinical trial research [1]. The most common and fre-<lb/>quently referenced authorship guidelines in biomedicine <lb/>are issued by the International Committee of Medical <lb/>Journal Editors (ICMJE). The goal of the ICMJE criteria <lb/>is to enhance transparency in authorship disclosure and <lb/>ultimately to build trust and credibility with the medical <lb/>literature readership [2,3]. Another authorship model, <lb/>referred to as contributorship, lists each person&apos;s contribu-<lb/>tions to the research and manuscript, even for those who <lb/>are not authors. One or more of these contributors will <lb/>fulfill the role as guarantors of the paper [4]. Despite im-<lb/>plementation of these and other approaches by journals <lb/></body>

			<front>* Correspondence: ana.marusic@mefst.hr <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Research in Biomedicine and Health, University of Split <lb/>School of Medicine, Šoltanska 2, 21000 Split, Croatia <lb/>Full list of author information is available at the end of the article <lb/>© 2014 Marusic et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain <lb/>Dedication waiver (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this article, <lb/>unless otherwise stated. <lb/></front>

			<body>and trial sponsors, concerns over clarity in disclosure of <lb/>authorship contributions persist, which ultimately can <lb/>erode credibility in clinical trial research and related publi-<lb/>cations [5-10]. These authorship issues often arise in situa-<lb/>tions where established definitions and guidelines are <lb/>ambiguous, resulting in variations in interpretation and <lb/>application that can contribute to a lack of transparency <lb/>[11]. While ICMJE authorship guidance is intentionally <lb/>broad to accommodate the diversity of scientific research, <lb/>a more structured authorship framework is needed to im-<lb/>prove consistency and clarity in authorship decision-<lb/>making for clinical trials given the complexity in design <lb/>and ongoing evolution [12,13]. <lb/>Improving disclosure of authorship contributions and <lb/>writing assistance was identified as one of ten recommen-<lb/>dations to close the credibility gap in reporting industry-<lb/>sponsored research by the Medical Publishing Insights <lb/>and Practices (MPIP) Initiative [14], a collaboration among <lb/>pharmaceutical companies with representation from the <lb/>International Society for Medical Publication Professionals <lb/>(ISMPP) aimed at elevating trust, transparency and in-<lb/>tegrity in publishing industry-sponsored studies [15]. <lb/>This article describes a research collaboration between <lb/>the MPIP Initiative and academic researchers to iden-<lb/>tify and address challenging authorship case scenarios for <lb/>industry-sponsored clinical trials. Discussions about these <lb/>results with journal editors, clinical investigators, aca-<lb/>demic collaborators and industry representatives allowed <lb/>the MPIP Initiative to develop a Five-Step Authorship <lb/>Framework that facilitates a more prospective, transparent <lb/>and consistent process when determining authorship for <lb/>industry-sponsored publications. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Creation of authorship scenarios <lb/>In early 2012, members of the MPIP Initiative&apos;s Steering <lb/>Committee collaborated with multiple respondent groups <lb/>involved in publication of industry-sponsored clinical trials <lb/>to identify authorship challenges arising from current <lb/>guidelines. Following in-depth discussions with seven pub-<lb/>lication professionals (individuals employed or contracted <lb/>by industry to organize and disseminate scientific and clin-<lb/>ical data through peer reviewed publications), three jour-<lb/>nal editors and three clinical investigators, the MPIP <lb/>Initiative Steering Committee and its academic collabora-<lb/>tors converted these challenging situations into authorship <lb/>case scenarios for further testing. An additional flow dia-<lb/>gram provides a detailed overview of the authorship re-<lb/>search project [see Additional file 1]. <lb/>Survey development, validation, and analysis <lb/>An online survey utilizing these authorship case scenarios <lb/>was created to collect qualitative data regarding the ration-<lb/>ale for adjudication of authorship decisions in individual <lb/>cases (that is, granting of authorship, acknowledgement, <lb/>no recognition, other). The survey also asked for confi-<lb/>dence level in authorship decisions and perceived fre-<lb/>quency of the situation described in the case. Respondents <lb/>were asked to answer based on their professional expe-<lb/>rience, as cases did not mention any specific guidelines. At <lb/>the end of the survey, respondents were also asked about <lb/>their awareness of and reliance on specific authorship <lb/>guidelines, as well as the time point during the clinical <lb/>trial when they would agree on authorship criteria. The <lb/>full survey [see Additional file 2] was piloted for content <lb/>and clarity among a convenience sample of five pro-<lb/>fessionals with experience in publishing or editing clinical <lb/>trials results. The final survey was created after revising <lb/>the original version based on comments generated during <lb/>pilot testing. <lb/>The survey was sent via an email link (to avoid duplicate <lb/>answers) to four respondent groups involved in the publi-<lb/>cation of clinical trial results: clinical investigators involved <lb/>in industry-sponsored clinical trials (as of September <lb/>2012), editors of general or specialty journals who publish <lb/>results from industry-sponsored clinical trials (contacted <lb/>directly by the MPIP Initiative, collaborating publishers, or <lb/>collaborating editors), publication professionals (as defined <lb/>above) and medical writers employed or contracted by <lb/>trial sponsors who collaborate with authors in drafting, re-<lb/>vising and editing medical information for peer-reviewed <lb/>journals and congresses. The last two groups were con-<lb/>tacted through ISMPP, the American Medical Writers <lb/>Association (AMWA), the European Medical Writers <lb/>Association (EMWA) and the MPIP Initiative Steering <lb/>Committee. Cases were presented randomly to minimize <lb/>respondent fatigue. From a total of 498 responses, a sam-<lb/>ple of at least 96 participants per group enabled estimates <lb/>with a 10% margin of error for the largest respondent <lb/>group surveyed (clinical investigators). The online survey <lb/>remained open until all groups surpassed this sample size <lb/>by at least 10%. <lb/>Adjudications of cases, confidence in answers, and <lb/>authorship practices of respondents were summarized <lb/>as frequencies. The answers measuring respondents&apos; <lb/>confidence and perceived frequency of scenarios were <lb/>captured on 6 point scales and categorized into three <lb/>groups: high confidence/frequency (score 1–2), moder-<lb/>ate confidence/frequency (score 3–4) and low confi-<lb/>dence/frequency (score 5–6). Open-ended explanations <lb/>for adjudications were analyzed as qualitative data. An-<lb/>swers were summarized and analyzed using a general <lb/>inductive approach [16]. Participants&apos; answers related <lb/>to each case were analyzed and then common themes <lb/>were identified through initial coding [17]. Overlapping <lb/>themes were then grouped and the final set of themes <lb/>developed. Data were coded and analyzed using NVivo <lb/>10 (QSR International Pty Ltd., Warrington, UK). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Marušić et al. BMC Medicine 2014, 12:197 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 2 of 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1741-7015/12/197 <lb/></note>

			<body>Consultations with stakeholders <lb/>Quantitative survey results were discussed at two separate <lb/>MPIP-hosted roundtable meetings: 10 U.S.-based editors <lb/>and 15 MPIP members (New York, USA, December <lb/>2012), and five European-based editors, one journal repre-<lb/>sentative, and seven MPIP members (Alderley Park, UK, <lb/>April 2013). During these roundtables, a facilitator pre-<lb/>sented quantitative results from the survey-based study. <lb/>Through an iterative process of discussion and consensus <lb/>building, key themes were identified. Findings were further <lb/>refined through analysis of qualitative survey answers and <lb/>in-depth discussions with six clinical investigators who <lb/>participated in the online survey and gave permission for <lb/>follow-up conversations. <lb/>Results <lb/>Survey respondents <lb/>Survey respondents (n = 498) included representation from <lb/>all four target respondent groups: 145 clinical investigators <lb/>(29% of respondents), 108 journal editors (22%), 132 publi-<lb/>cation professionals (26%) and 113 medical writers (23%) <lb/>(Table 1). The survey reached an international audience, <lb/>from North America (44%) and Europe (39%) to Asia <lb/>(13%). A majority of respondents had &gt;5 years of industry-<lb/>sponsored clinical trial experience (82%) and clinical inves-<lb/>tigators surveyed had published ≥3 papers from that <lb/>research (63%). Given the various methods used to contact <lb/>potential respondents and collect survey data, it was not <lb/>possible to calculate a response rate or determine any dif-<lb/>ferences between respondents and those who did not take <lb/>the survey. <lb/>Authorship guidelines <lb/>Following completion of the case scenario section, respon-<lb/>dents were asked about their familiarity and reliance on <lb/>guidelines applicable to industry-sponsored clinical trial <lb/>manuscripts. Respondents were most familiar with ICMJE <lb/>authorship guidelines (49% to 97%), followed by the Good <lb/>Publication Practice (GPP2) guidelines [18] (35% to 87%) <lb/>(Figure 1). Clinical investigators were significantly less fa-<lb/>miliar with these two guidelines (49% and 41%, respect-<lb/>ively) and more often than other groups reported they <lb/>were not aware of any guidelines (28%). Publication pro-<lb/>fessionals had the highest awareness of ICMJE (97%) and <lb/>GPP2 (87%) guidelines, mirroring results from previous <lb/>surveys of this professional group [19]. When asked about <lb/>reliance on other authorship guidelines in addition to spe-<lb/>cific journal guidelines, all respondents selected ICMJE as <lb/>their top choice, although this was less the case among <lb/>clinical investigators (28%) than other respondent groups <lb/>(51% to 70%). Clinical investigators reported using no <lb/>guidelines (25%) more frequently than other groups (2% <lb/>to 10%) when deciding questions of authorship. <lb/>Authorship case scenario responses <lb/>Full descriptions of the seven hypothetical authorship <lb/>case scenarios for industry-sponsored studies and an-<lb/>swers by respondent group are presented in Figure 2 <lb/>and Additional file 3: Table S1. We describe in more de-<lb/>tail the cases with greater disagreement among respond-<lb/>ent groups and relevance for industry-sponsored clinical <lb/>trials. <lb/>Case 1 tests whether patient recruitment and trial site <lb/>management were perceived to be significant enough <lb/>contributions to merit an authorship invitation. Most of <lb/>the respondents (49% to 68%) agreed that these contri-<lb/>butions warranted an invitation to authorship. The ra-<lb/>tionale for this decision is illustrated by the response <lb/>from a clinical investigator: &apos;Recruiting patients is one of <lb/>the most important tasks in a clinical trial, and the qual-<lb/>ity of the study depends on compliance with the inclu-<lb/>sion and exclusion criteria. Therefore, this is probably <lb/>one of the most important persons for the study, and <lb/>should therefore take responsibility/be acknowledged as <lb/>an author.&apos; This case was estimated by respondents to <lb/>occur most frequently, and &gt;73% of respondents in each <lb/>group were confident in their answer. ICMJE criteria for <lb/>authorship available at the time of the survey [20] were <lb/>unclear as to whether patient recruitment was consid-<lb/>ered to be a substantial contribution as part of data <lb/>acquisition. <lb/>Table 1 Survey respondent demographics <lb/>Characteristic <lb/>Frequency <lb/>Percent <lb/>Respondent group: <lb/>Clinical investigator <lb/>145 <lb/>29.1 <lb/>Journal editor <lb/>108 <lb/>21.7 <lb/>Publication professional <lb/>132 <lb/>26.5 <lb/>Medical writer <lb/>113 <lb/>22.7 <lb/>Total <lb/>498 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Years associated with industry-sponsored clinical trial: <lb/>3 to 5 years <lb/>89 <lb/>17.9 <lb/>6 to 10 years <lb/>116 <lb/>23.3 <lb/>11 to 20 years <lb/>176 <lb/>35.3 <lb/>20+ years <lb/>117 <lb/>23.5 <lb/>Total <lb/>498 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>Number of industry-sponsored clinical trial publications as an <lb/>author in the past 10 years <lb/>a <lb/>0 to 2 papers <lb/>54 <lb/>37.2 <lb/>3 to 5 papers <lb/>38 <lb/>26.2 <lb/>6 to 10 papers <lb/>21 <lb/>14.5 <lb/>11 to 20 papers <lb/>17 <lb/>11.7 <lb/>20+ papers <lb/>15 <lb/>10.4 <lb/>Total <lb/>145 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>a <lb/>Note: Clinical investigators only. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Marušić et al. BMC Medicine 2014, 12:197 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 3 of 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1741-7015/12/197 <lb/></note>

			<body>Case 2 explores the two issues: 1) whether a statistician <lb/>who is believed to have made a substantial contribution <lb/>but did not contribute to trial design or drafting of the <lb/>manuscript merits an invitation to authorship; and 2) <lb/>whether timing of authorship criteria fulfillment impacts <lb/>the decision. More publication professionals supported <lb/>consideration for authorship (72%) compared to clinical <lb/>investigators (54%). Qualitative responses highlighted a <lb/>lack of consensus between respondent groups. One editor <lb/>commented that &apos; Authorship on a manuscript needed to <lb/>be decided before the writing of a first draft&apos; , in contrast to <lb/>a clinical investigator who wrote &apos; Authorship should reflect <lb/>a significant contribution to the substance of the study -it <lb/>was an error not to include this person from the start.&apos; <lb/>While respondents had generally high confidence in their <lb/>answers (&gt;72% for all groups), they reported moderate fre-<lb/>quency for this case. ICMJE criteria in place at the time of <lb/>the survey [20] provided guidance on authorship criteria <lb/>but did not address the issue of timing for the fulfillment <lb/>of the criteria. <lb/>Case 3 asks if a contribution from a medical writer <lb/>could qualify the person as an author. In this case, a <lb/>medical writer is hired to help draft the manuscript from <lb/>a trial report and supports authors in manuscript devel-<lb/>opment under the guidance of the authors to final ac-<lb/>ceptance. Nearly one quarter of journal editors (23%) <lb/>and clinical investigators (25%) supported authorship in <lb/>this case. Respondents were aware this choice was not <lb/>concordant with guidelines, exemplified by a clinical in-<lb/>vestigator: &apos;I believe medical writers should be listed as <lb/>authors in those instances where they have contributed <lb/>from the first draft through to submission. (I recognize <lb/>that this would require revision of ICMJE guidelines).&apos; <lb/>This case was estimated by respondents to be the second <lb/>most frequent, and &gt;76% of respondents in each group <lb/>were confident in their answer. ICMJE guidelines at the <lb/>Figure 1 Respondents&apos; familiarity (A) with and reliance (B) on authorship guidelines. More than one guideline could be chosen for <lb/>familiarity. CSE, Council of Science Editors; EMWA, European Medical Writers Association; GPP2, Good publication practice for communicating <lb/>company sponsored medical research; ICMJE, International Committee of Medical Journal Editors; ISMPP, International Society of Medical <lb/>Publication Professionals. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Marušić et al. BMC Medicine 2014, 12:197 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 4 of 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1741-7015/12/197 <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 2 Case scenario adjudication responses by respondent group. Abbreviations: CI, Clinical investigator; JE, Journal editor; MW, Medical writer; <lb/>PP, Publication professional. Confidence in adjudication and perceived frequency of scenarios were captured on 6 point scales and categorized into <lb/>three categories: high confidence/frequency (score 1-2), moderate confidence/frequency (score 3-4) and low confidence/frequency (score 5-6). &quot;Don&apos;t <lb/>know&quot; responses (&lt;10% for any group) are not included. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Marušić et al. BMC Medicine 2014, 12:197 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 5 of 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1741-7015/12/197 <lb/></note>

			<body>time of survey [20] stated that writing assistance, tech-<lb/>nical editing, language editing, and proofreading did not <lb/>qualify as a substantial contribution. <lb/>Finally, Case 7 tests whether providing those who make <lb/>a significant contribution the opportunity to serve as an <lb/>author takes precedence over protection of proprietary in-<lb/>formation. In this scenario, respondents were asked if a <lb/>clinician who leaves a trial sponsor company for a com-<lb/>petitor after making a substantial contribution but prior to <lb/>drafting the manuscript should be invited to contribute as <lb/>an author. A majority of clinical investigators (61%) and <lb/>journal editors (55%) were in favor of inviting the clinician <lb/>to serve as an author versus publication professionals <lb/>(26%) and medical writers (36%). As with other cases, re-<lb/>spondents were more often concerned about what was fair <lb/>and not what was prescribed, as noted by a publication <lb/>professional: &apos;Honestly speaking, I think the clinician <lb/>should be recognized as an author, but he does not meet <lb/>authorship criteria.&apos; More than 72% of respondents in each <lb/>group were confident in their answer. This case was esti-<lb/>mated to occur relatively infrequently. <lb/>When considering answers from the cases as a whole, <lb/>three overarching insights emerged. First, responses per-<lb/>taining to granting authorship, acknowledgement, no rec-<lb/>ognition or other, varied not only across but within the <lb/>four respondent groups for each case. This variability sug-<lb/>gests limited agreement within peer groups as to how to <lb/>determine authorship on challenging cases, as well as dif-<lb/>ferences in opinion between the respondent groups. Sec-<lb/>ond, a majority of respondents in all groups were confident <lb/>in their answers regardless of the case subject, answer <lb/>choice or perceived frequency. Finally, analysis of 2,841 out <lb/>of 3,486 possible open-ended answers (81% response rate) <lb/>highlighted key justifications underlying authorship deci-<lb/>sions in the survey (Table 2). These themes included the <lb/>importance or significance of the contribution for each sce-<lb/>nario, alignment or misalignment with formal authorship <lb/>guideline criteria, importance of transparency and/or re-<lb/>sponsibility and need for prior agreement on authorship <lb/>criteria [see Additional file 4 for example answers]. The <lb/>group of respondents who would grant authorship in case <lb/>scenarios more often used the &apos;importance of contribu-<lb/>tions&apos; in explaining their adjudication (57%) versus <lb/>those who would grant acknowledgment or not offer <lb/>authorship. The latter respondents most often cited <lb/>the following rationales: &apos;importance of contribution&apos; <lb/>(30%), application of &apos;formal criteria&apos; (38%) and &apos;trans-<lb/>parency/responsibility&apos; (26%). <lb/>As clinical investigators with two or fewer published <lb/>articles from clinical trials constitute approximately a <lb/>third of the respondent population (Table 1), we com-<lb/>pared case adjudications from this group with that from <lb/>other respondents. This sensitivity analysis revealed a <lb/>difference only for Case 1, where relatively inexperienced <lb/>clinical investigators would be less likely to invite a clin-<lb/>ical investigator who enrolled the most patients to help <lb/>draft/revise the manuscript. There were no differences <lb/>in confidence or perceived frequency of the case scenar-<lb/>ios, suggesting that publication experience had minimal <lb/>influence on the answers provided. <lb/>Consultations with editors <lb/>The quantitative survey results from the case scenarios <lb/>were shared with fifteen U.S. and five European-based <lb/>journal editors and one journal representative across two <lb/>separate discussion-based roundtables to gain further in-<lb/>sights and begin developing recommendations. Feedback <lb/>highlighted the following areas to help improve author-<lb/>ship disclosure: <lb/>Authorship criteria should be determined as early as <lb/>possible in the course of a clinical trial; <lb/>Authorship criteria can vary between clinical trials, <lb/>assuming current guidelines are followed; <lb/>Authorship criteria should be agreed to by all trial <lb/>contributors via authorship agreements; <lb/>Trial contributions should be documented and <lb/>summarized prior to publication; and, <lb/>The entire author list should agree to any <lb/>authorship changes during the publication process. <lb/>Quantitative survey results and these preliminary themes <lb/>were subsequently discussed with six clinical investigators <lb/>from our survey sample via in-depth teleconference inter-<lb/>views to help further refine initial recommendations. <lb/>Five-step authorship framework <lb/>Using input from quantitative survey results, analysis <lb/>of qualitative open-ended answers, and discussions <lb/>with journal editors, clinical investigators and industry <lb/>representatives, key themes were identified that led to <lb/>the development of the following &apos;Five-Step Authorship <lb/>Framework to Improve Transparency in Disclosing Con-<lb/>tributors to Industry-sponsored Clinical Trial Publications <lb/>(Table 3). <lb/>Table 2 Themes used in adjudication answers when <lb/>invitation for authorship was chosen versus all other <lb/>answers <lb/>Number of references coded within <lb/>the theme (% of all coded references <lb/>within the adjudication choice/choices) <lb/>Theme <lb/>Grant authorship Acknowledgement/ <lb/>No authorship/Other <lb/>Importance of contribution 608 (57%) <lb/>381 (30%) <lb/>Formal criteria <lb/>277 (26%) <lb/>478 (38%) <lb/>Transparency/Responsibility 149 (14%) <lb/>319 (26%) <lb/>Agreement in advance <lb/>30 (3%) <lb/>69 (6%) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Marušić et al. BMC Medicine 2014, 12:197 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 6 of 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1741-7015/12/197 <lb/></note>

			<body>Step 1 – Establish an authorship working group early in the <lb/>trial <lb/>This working group should include core trial contributors <lb/>with broad representation from multiple disciplines, in-<lb/>cluding the trial Steering Committee, clinical investigators <lb/>with relevant expertise, study co-sponsors and external <lb/>experts. Where possible, these working group members <lb/>should remain unchanged throughout the study to help <lb/>ensure continuity. Members of the working group need <lb/>not be authors nor should they be guaranteed authorship <lb/>without meeting authorship criteria for the trial. <lb/>Step 2 – Determine substantial contribution criteria <lb/>The primary task for the authorship working group is to <lb/>determine prospectively which contributions will qualify <lb/>as &apos;substantial&apos; in the context of trial activities. These cri-<lb/>teria should align with external guidelines (for example, <lb/>ICMJE, GPP2 and journals being considered for submis-<lb/>sion) and policies of the sponsor, and they should be fi-<lb/>nalized prior to first patient enrollment. Standardized <lb/>language for those criteria should be included in written <lb/>publication agreements and agreed to by all trial contrib-<lb/>utors, including those in the authorship working group. <lb/>When determining these authorship criteria, trial activ-<lb/>ities meriting an invitation for authorship should be eva-<lb/>luated by their ability to impact broader trial outcomes <lb/>compared to those serving a more narrow function. It is <lb/>important to note that definitions for substantial contribu-<lb/>tions can differ between trials, provided external guidelines <lb/>such as ICMJE are followed, since trial activities vary greatly <lb/>across therapeutic areas, stages of development, sponsors <lb/>and other dimensions. When considering large, multi-<lb/>national trials, it is especially important to clearly determine <lb/>substantial contribution criteria as early as possible in the <lb/>trial, given the large number of contributors involved. <lb/>Step 3 – Document trial contributions <lb/>In addition to setting the criteria for substantial contri-<lb/>bution, the authorship working group should create <lb/>a process for tracking and documenting all relevant <lb/>trial contributions that meet the pre-defined criteria as <lb/>substantial. This process should be made transparent in <lb/>the written publication agreement, and trial contributors <lb/>should be notified of the requirement to provide this in-<lb/>formation as part of ongoing trial responsibilities. To <lb/>avoid creating new tasks and expense, tracking should <lb/>be included among normal trial activities where possible. <lb/>Step 4 – Determine those making a substantial contribution <lb/>Once trial activities for a given manuscript are completed, <lb/>the authorship working group should reconvene to apply <lb/>the criteria to the documented contributions. All trial con-<lb/>tributors, regardless of function, responsibility or relation-<lb/>ship to trial sponsor(s), meeting the authorship criteria for <lb/>substantial contribution determined in Step 2 should then <lb/>be invited to draft/revise the manuscript. However, an in-<lb/>vitation for authorship may be declined by a contributor. <lb/>As part of our discussions with journal editors and clinical <lb/>investigators, it was noted that while up-front participa-<lb/>tion is preferred, later contributions sometimes rise to the <lb/>level of a substantial contribution. The authorship working <lb/>group should have the responsibility to determine which <lb/>potential authors made a substantial contribution based <lb/>on the contribution data and adjudicate disagreements <lb/>that arise from its decisions. Contributions which do not <lb/>meet the standard for &apos;substantial&apos; should be agreed to by <lb/>all authors and noted in the acknowledgements. <lb/>Step 5 – Ensure authors meet remaining authorship criteria <lb/>Those who accept an invitation to draft/revise the <lb/>manuscript will serve as the initial author list. The final <lb/>responsibility of the authorship working group is to en-<lb/>sure timely dissemination of findings that are consistent <lb/>with the pre-specified aims of the clinical trial. Those in <lb/>the author list should agree on their role prior to drafting <lb/>the manuscript and all contributions should be fully docu-<lb/>mented. It is important that members of the author list <lb/>fulfill the remaining authorship criteria beyond substantial <lb/>contribution outlined in the written publication agree-<lb/>ment. Changes to the author list can occur, either adding <lb/>those who make a later substantial contribution or remov-<lb/>ing those who do not fulfill all authorship requirements. <lb/>Table 3 Five-Step Authorship Framework to Improve Transparency in Disclosing Contributors to Industry-sponsored <lb/>Clinical Trial Publications <lb/>Step Tasks <lb/>1 <lb/>Establish an authorship working group of core trial contributors as close as possible to trial commencement but prior to enrollment of first <lb/>patient. For smaller trials where an authorship working group is not feasible, this committee may be a sub-committee of a larger Trial Steering <lb/>Committee where one exists. <lb/>2 <lb/>Determine, in the context of the ICMJE authorship criteria and the specific trial, which authorship contributions will qualify as &apos;substantial&apos; and <lb/>include these details in written publication agreements for all trial contributors. <lb/>3 <lb/>Implement a process to track and document in a concise format progress toward substantial contributions based on agreed-upon <lb/>qualifications. <lb/>4 <lb/>Assess documented trial contributions for the specific study and invite those making a &apos;substantial contribution&apos; to participate as author(s). <lb/>5 <lb/>Ensure invited authors meet remaining ICMJE authorship criteria during content development and publication submission. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Marušić et al. BMC Medicine 2014, 12:197 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 7 of 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1741-7015/12/197 <lb/></note>

			<body>However, to maintain transparency, all authorship changes <lb/>and the accompanying rationale should be documented <lb/>and agreed to by the entire author list. At submission, the <lb/>authors should consider providing a summary of the au-<lb/>thor list and their specific contributions to indicate how <lb/>authorship was determined. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Given the growing demand for increased transparency in <lb/>publications for clinical trials [21-24], the MPIP Initiative <lb/>sought to identify authorship ambiguities encountered in <lb/>industry-sponsored trials not well addressed by current <lb/>guidelines and to develop an approach by which author-<lb/>ship decisions can be more clearly and easily determined. <lb/>Investigation of the rationale used by the respondent <lb/>groups in adjudicating challenging case scenarios identi-<lb/>fied a number of key gaps between authorship guidelines <lb/>and how these scenarios are addressed. Most important <lb/>among these, survey results highlighted the variability in <lb/>responses both across and within peer groups despite <lb/>some groups having high familiarity with and reliance on <lb/>current authorship guidelines. Some cases also tested a <lb/>number of areas where authorship criteria do not explicitly <lb/>provide guidance, such as whether patient recruitment is <lb/>considered a substantial contribution or the impact of tim-<lb/>ing on authorship criteria fulfillment [20], which further <lb/>contributed to response variability. These findings suggest <lb/>the lack of clear authorship guidance on some scenarios <lb/>frequently encountered in real life, and indicate that re-<lb/>spondents acting on judgment contrary to guidance can <lb/>contribute to lack of transparency. Second, despite this het-<lb/>erogeneity, respondents were uniformly confident in their <lb/>own rationale for these authorship decisions. Since the sur-<lb/>vey did not specify or refer to any guidelines during the <lb/>case scenario section, respondents likely believed their ex-<lb/>perience and judgment are a correct approach to resolving <lb/>these scenarios. Finally, clinical investigators, who make up <lb/>a significant percentage of authors on manuscripts from <lb/>clinical trials, appear to be concerned with the importance <lb/>or significance of the contribution rather than following ex-<lb/>ternal guidelines to determine authorship. This perspective <lb/>is exemplified by clinical investigators ranking lowest among <lb/>the groups surveyed for awareness of authorship criteria. <lb/>Through discussions with journal editors, clinical in-<lb/>vestigators and industry representatives on the gaps in <lb/>authorship decision-making that emerged from the survey, <lb/>we identified key themes for improvement. These themes <lb/>included defining the criteria for substantial contributions <lb/>early in the trial, ensuring all trial contributors agree to <lb/>these criteria and documenting contributions to ensure <lb/>these criteria are met. Expanding on these key insights, <lb/>the Five-step Authorship Framework was developed to <lb/>provide a clear and flexible process to facilitate more <lb/>transparent and consistent authorship decision-making. <lb/>The success of the Five-Step Authorship Framework re-<lb/>lies significantly on convening a working group early in <lb/>the trial process to discuss which trial activities should be <lb/>considered a substantial contribution in the context of <lb/>current authorship guidelines. Given the wide diversity of <lb/>trials undertaken and likely future changes in authorship <lb/>guidelines, defining a comprehensive set of potential activ-<lb/>ities that meet the definition of &apos;substantial&apos; for authorship <lb/>is neither practical nor durable. Instead, utilizing the ex-<lb/>perience and judgment of a diverse group of core trial <lb/>contributors in an open discussion format provides a <lb/>transparent process for determining fair and comprehen-<lb/>sive authorship criteria for a given trial. In addition, these <lb/>authorship criteria should align with external guidelines, <lb/>such as ICMJE and GPP2, to avoid potential bias in <lb/>selection of criteria that exclude legitimate authorship. <lb/>Documenting these definitions in authorship agreements <lb/>ensures that all trial contributors are informed in advance <lb/>and provides a basis for conflict resolution should a <lb/>dispute arise. The flexibility of this framework permits <lb/>authorship criteria specific to each trial, as some trial <lb/>groups may define significant patient recruitment to be a <lb/>substantial contribution while others may not (see Case <lb/>1). This adaptable format will help facilitate the continued <lb/>movement away from patient recruitment as sole criteria <lb/>for substantial contribution and place greater emphasis on <lb/>intellectual contributions, thus better aligning with the <lb/>evolving concept of authorship. <lb/>The authorship working group should also be respon-<lb/>sible for determining who has fulfilled the criteria of <lb/>substantial contribution to help draft the manuscript, <lb/>ensuring the results are consistent with the aims of <lb/>the trial. The initial author list should be determined <lb/>through matching the documented contributions of po-<lb/>tential pre-specified authors to the authorship criteria. <lb/>In this way, the authorship working group would have a <lb/>data-driven approach to determine which potential au-<lb/>thors fulfill criteria 1 of the ICMJE authorship recommen-<lb/>dations (see Cases 3, 5 to 7). In addition, the pre-specified <lb/>author criteria provide an objective basis for evaluating <lb/>whether to add or remove an author as contributions come <lb/>to light during manuscript development (see Cases 2 and <lb/>4). Given the importance of its responsibilities, the author-<lb/>ship working group should be a stand-alone group and not <lb/>subsumed into the trial Steering Committee. As outlined, <lb/>the authorship working group will not require substantial <lb/>additional burden and, hence, convening such a group <lb/>should be feasible. <lb/>Our survey results identified divergent opinions both <lb/>within and across respondent groups for how to adjudi-<lb/>cate the cases, with varying awareness and reliance <lb/>on authorship guidelines. Previous research has shown <lb/>that authorship issues can be seen as either matters of <lb/>defined rules or obligation [25]. Decisions about issues <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Marušić et al. BMC Medicine 2014, 12:197 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 8 of 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1741-7015/12/197 <lb/></note>

			<body>using defined rules may differ by time or place, whereas <lb/>for obligation, higher order rules define the right and <lb/>wrong courses for action, and decisions are not contin-<lb/>gent on specific social rules [26]. Our research confirms <lb/>that authorship decisions bring forth issues both based <lb/>on rules (&apos;formal criteria&apos;) and obligation (&apos;importance of <lb/>contributions&apos;), and participants try to compromise be-<lb/>tween these perspectives. Our finding that trial publication <lb/>experience has little influence on the scenario adjudication <lb/>suggests these opinions are not generated by clinical trial <lb/>experience but are rather a characteristic inherent to the <lb/>professionals taking part in clinical trials. Therefore, form-<lb/>ing a diverse group early in the trial can facilitate this <lb/>process by bringing together those who are more aware of <lb/>guidelines and setting mutually agreed upon authorship <lb/>criteria from both domains through broad discussion. <lb/>These findings also independently align with the recent <lb/>change in ICMJE authorship requirements, which added <lb/>accountability for all aspects of work described in the <lb/>manuscript as the fourth criterion [2]. <lb/>Our study has limitations related to its methodological <lb/>approach, which was focused on collecting qualitative input <lb/>from professional groups involved in industry-sponsored <lb/>clinical trial publications rather than quantitative data, <lb/>which can be difficult to collect via online surveys [27,28]. <lb/>The survey contained the possibility for self-selection bias, <lb/>with respondents potentially having a special interest in <lb/>authorship and, therefore, not being representative. How-<lb/>ever, the survey was not meant to collect representative <lb/>input across all relevant characteristics from the four re-<lb/>spondent groups but to learn about possible approaches to <lb/>solving real-life authorship challenges in clinical research to <lb/>inform potential solutions to these problems. In addition, <lb/>the Five-step Authorship Framework will not resolve all <lb/>authorship questions, especially as clinical trials continue to <lb/>evolve in complexity. We see the Framework as a living <lb/>guideline that will change together with clinical research. <lb/>The companies included in this publication will support <lb/>implementation of this tool in their clinical trials to sup-<lb/>plement best practice and would encourage other industry <lb/>members to do so as well to ensure this framework is <lb/>broadly embedded for maximum impact. Given the con-<lb/>tribution from other stakeholders, such as journal editors, <lb/>the authors will be reaching out to them and other organi-<lb/>zations to ask for their help to foster awareness and up-<lb/>take for the Five-step Framework. <lb/> Conclusions <lb/>This research outlines an approach for manuscripts from <lb/>industry-sponsored clinical trials that emphasizes early de-<lb/>termination of substantial contribution by a diverse group of <lb/>core participants, clear communication of authorship cri-<lb/>teria to all participants and documentation of contributions <lb/>that leads to less opaque authorship decisions. This Five-<lb/>Step Authorship Framework has the potential to facilitate <lb/>decision-making with improved transparency and <lb/>consistency when recognizing authors for all clinical trial <lb/>publications, not just those from industry-sponsored efforts. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Additional files <lb/>Additional file 1: Figure S1. Time line for the MPIP Authorship <lb/>Research project with inclusion of principal steps in step-wise fashion. <lb/>Additional file 2: Survey S1. Full online authorship survey. <lb/>Additional file 3: Table S1. Case scenarios used in the survey. <lb/>Additional file 4: Table S2. Representative examples of qualitative <lb/>responses by respondent group and case categorized by different themes. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Abbreviations <lb/>CI: clinical investigator; CSE: Council of Science Editors; EMWA: European <lb/>Medical Writers Association; GPP2: Good publication practice for <lb/>communicating company sponsored medical research; ICMJE: International <lb/>Committee of Medical Journal Editors; ISMPP: International Society of Medical <lb/>Publication Professionals; JE: journal editor; MPIP Initiative: Medical Publishing <lb/>Insights and Practices Initiative; MW: medical writer; PP: publication professional. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests <lb/>TG is employed by Envision Pharma Group and served on the MPIP Initiative <lb/>Steering Committee as a representative of the International Society for <lb/>Medical Publication Professionals (ISMPP), neither of which provides funding <lb/>support to the MPIP Initiative. BM, AB, MG, JC, SG, JG, CH, MML, LM, and TP <lb/>are employees of companies sponsoring the MPIP Initiative, as shown by <lb/>their individual affiliations. NL is employed by Navigant Consulting, a strategy <lb/>consulting firm that advises life science and healthcare companies. The <lb/>remaining authors declare that they have no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Authors&apos; contributions <lb/>The project was conceived by the MPIP Steering Committee and designed <lb/>and executed by all the authors; NL was responsible for data collection while <lb/>AM and DH performed all data analysis. All the authors were involved in <lb/>discussions of the data and formulation of the authorship framework. AM, <lb/>DH, BM, NL, AB, and MG wrote the first draft of the manuscript, which was <lb/>critically reviewed, revised, and approved for submission by all the authors. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>The cases presented in this paper were based in part on the presentation <lb/> &quot; Overcoming Ethical &amp; Compliance Concerns Surrounding Publication &amp; <lb/>Authorship &quot; by Chipperfield, L., Clegg, A., Gillon, J. et al. Elizabeth Wager at <lb/>Sideview along with Kraig Schulz and Timothy Lee, both formerly of Leerink <lb/>Swann Consulting, provided assistance in study design and survey <lb/>development. The MPIP Initiative obtained a list of worldwide clinical <lb/>investigators currently taking part in industry–sponsored clinical trials from <lb/>the Adis Clinical Trials Insight database via Bryce McMurray, Dave Dustin and <lb/>Adrian Beasley at Springer Healthcare. The following publishers assisted in <lb/>disseminating the survey to editors: BioMedCentral, BMJ, Dovepress, Elsevier, <lb/>Informa, Nature, SAGE, Springer, Wiley-Blackwell and Wolters Kluwer. The <lb/>following organizations assisted in disseminating the survey to publication <lb/>professionals and medical writers: AMWA, EMWA and ISMPP. Interim findings <lb/>from the survey were discussed with 15 editors and one representative from <lb/>medical journals at two independent roundtables organized by the MPIP <lb/>Initiative on 3 December 2012 in New York City, USA and 9 April 2013 in <lb/>Alderley Park, UK. Participants and their affiliations at the time of the two <lb/>Roundtables were as follows: Sabina Alam, PhD (editor in chief, BMC <lb/>Medicine), Patricia Baskin, MS (executive editor, Neurology), Wendy Battisti, <lb/>PhD (director, scientific and medical publications, Janssen Research &amp; <lb/>Development, LLC), Ananya Bhattacharya, PhD (director, publication policy <lb/>and education, Bristol-Myers Squibb), Matthew Cahill (associate vice <lb/>president, global scientific and medical publications, Merck &amp; Co), Edward <lb/>Campion, MD (senior deputy editor and online editor, New England Journal <lb/>of Medicine), Juli Clark, PharmD (director, global medical writing, Amgen), <lb/>Thomas Clemens, PhD (editor in chief, Journal of Bone and Mineral Research), <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Marušić et al. BMC Medicine 2014, 12:197 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 9 of 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1741-7015/12/197 <lb/></note>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Finbarr Cotter, MD/PhD (editor in chief, British Journal of Hematology), <lb/>Cynthia Dunbar, MD (editor in chief, Blood), Robert Enck (editor in chief, <lb/>American Journal of Hospice and Palliative Medicine), Lorna Fay (senior <lb/>director, publications management, Pfizer), Phil Fontanarosa (executive editor, <lb/>Journal of the American Medical Association), Maureen Garrity (director, <lb/>publication, Astellas), Thomas Gesell, PharmD (Envision Pharma, on behalf of <lb/>ISMPP), John Gonzalez, PhD (publications director, AstraZeneca), Samantha <lb/>Gothelf, PharmD (executive director, global medical publications, Bristol-<lb/>Myers Squibb), Thomas Grant, PhD (director – publications, AstraZeneca), <lb/>Trish Groves, MBBS MRCPsych (deputy editor, BMJ and editor in chief, BMJ <lb/>Open), Daniel Haller, MD (editor in chief, Gastrointestinal Cancer Research), <lb/>Charlotte Haug, MD/PhD/MSc (editor in chief, Norwegian Medical Journal), <lb/>Carolyn Hustad, PhD (executive director, global scientific and medical <lb/>publications, Merck&amp; Co), Richard Irwin, MD (editor in chief, CHEST), Christine <lb/>Laine, MD, MPH, FACP (editor in chief, Annals of Internal Medicine), <lb/>Mary-Margaret Lannon (senior director, global publications, Takeda), Timothy <lb/>Lee (analyst, Leerink Swann Consulting), Neil Lineberry, PhD (director, Leerink <lb/>Swann Consulting – now with Navigant Consulting), Delong Liu, MD (editor <lb/>in chief, Journal of Hematology and Oncology), Bernadette Mansi (head, <lb/>publications and disclosure practices, GlaxoSmithKline), Ana Marušić, MD/PhD <lb/>(University of Split), LaVerne Mooney, DrPH (director, publications management, <lb/>Pfizer), Teresa Peña (global director, publications, AstraZeneca), Elin Reeves, MSc <lb/>(head of publications, European Respiratory Journal), Kraig Schulz (managing <lb/>director, Leerink Swann Consulting), Stuart Spencer, PhD (executive editor, <lb/>The Lancet), and Ryan Stover (analyst, Leerink Swann Consulting). Quantitative <lb/>survey results and a preliminary Five-Step Authorship Framework were <lb/>discussed with six clinical researchers who took part in the survey and provided <lb/>permission for follow-up: Michael Brown, MBBS, FRACP, FRCPA (Royal Adelaide <lb/>Hospital, Australia), Glen Elliott, MD, PhD (Children&apos;s Health Council, USA), <lb/>Howard Katzenstein, MD (Monroe Carrell Jr. Children&apos;s Hospital at Vanderbilt <lb/>University, USA), Ludo Vanopdenbosch, MD (private practice, Belgium), <lb/>Wolfgang Vanscheidt, MD (private practice, Germany), and Jonathan Wadsley, <lb/>MB, BChir, MA, MRCP, FRCR (University of Sheffield, UK). <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Funding <lb/>AM and DH were supported by a grant from the MPIP Initiative. NL is an <lb/>external consultant employed by Navigant Consulting and was paid by the <lb/>MPIP Initiative for his work. <lb/></div>

			<front>Author details <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Research in Biomedicine and Health, University of Split <lb/>School of Medicine, Šoltanska 2, 21000 Split, Croatia. <lb/>2 <lb/>University of Split <lb/>School of Humanities and Social Sciences, Split, Croatia. <lb/>3 GlaxoSmithKline, <lb/>King of Prussia, PA, USA. <lb/>4 Member of MPIP Initiative Steering Committee, <lb/>Boston, MA, USA. <lb/>5 <lb/>Navigant Consulting, Boston, MA, USA. <lb/>6 <lb/>Bristol-Myers <lb/>Squibb, Princeton, NJ, USA. <lb/>7 <lb/>Astellas, Northbrook, IL, USA. <lb/>8 <lb/>Amgen, Thousand <lb/>Oaks, CA, USA. <lb/>9 <lb/>On behalf of the International Society for Medical Publication <lb/>Professionals, Briarcliff Manor, NY, USA. <lb/>10 <lb/>Janssen Research &amp;Development, <lb/>LLC, Raritan, NJ, USA. <lb/>11 <lb/>AstraZeneca, Alderley Park, UK. <lb/>12 <lb/>Merck &amp; Co, Inc, <lb/>Whitehouse Station, NJ, USA. <lb/>13 <lb/>Takeda, Deerfield, IL, USA. <lb/>14 <lb/>Pfizer, New York, <lb/>NY, USA. <lb/>15 <lb/>AstraZeneca, Wilmington, DE, USA. <lb/>Received: 16 July 2014 Accepted: 1 October 2014 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Kesselheim AS, Robertson CT, Myers JA, Rose SL, Gillet V, Ross KM, Glynn RJ, <lb/>Joffe S, Avorn J: A randomized study of how physicians interpret research <lb/>funding disclosures. N Engl J Med 2012, 367:1119–1127. <lb/>2. Recommendations for the conduct, reporting, editing, and publication <lb/>of scholarly work in medical journals. Updated 2013. [http://www.icmje. <lb/>org/recommendations/archives/2013_aug_urm.pdf] <lb/>3. Wager E: Do medical journals provide clear and consistent guidelines on <lb/>authorship? MedGenMed 2007, 9:16. <lb/>4. Flanagin A, Carey LA, Fontanarosa PB, Phillips SG, Pace BP, Lundberg <lb/>GD, Rennie D: Prevalence of articles with honorary authors and <lb/>ghost authors in peer-reviewed medical journals. JAMA 1998, <lb/>280:222–224. <lb/>5. Rennie D, Yank V, Emanuel L: When authorship fails. A proposal to make <lb/>contributors accountable. JAMA 1997, 278:579–585. <lb/>6. Laine C, Mulrow CD: Exorcising ghosts and unwelcome guests. Ann Intern <lb/>Med 2005, 143:611–612. <lb/>7. Gøtzsche PC, Hrobjartsson A, Johansen HK, Haahr MT, Altman DG, Chan AW: <lb/>Ghost authorship in industry-initiated randomised trials. PLoS Med 2007, <lb/>4:e19. <lb/>8. Wislar JS, Flanagin A, Fontanarosa PB, Deangelis CD: Honorary and ghost <lb/>authorship in high impact biomedical journals: a cross sectional survey. <lb/>BMJ 2011, 343:d6128. <lb/>9. Barbour V: How ghost-writing threatens the credibility of medical <lb/>knowledge and medical journals. Hematologica 2010, 95:1–2. <lb/>10. Matheson A: How industry uses the ICMJE guidelines to manipulate <lb/>authorship—and how they should be revised. PLoS Med 2011, 8:e1001072. <lb/>11. Marusic A, Bosnjak L, Jeroncic A: A systematic review of research on the <lb/>meaning, ethics and practices of authorship across scholarly disciplines. <lb/>PLoS One 2011, 6:e23477. <lb/>12. Getz K, Wenger J, Campo R, Seguine E, Kaitin K: Assessing the impact of <lb/>protocol design change on clinical trial performance. Am J Ther 2008, <lb/>15:450–457. <lb/>13. Getz K, Campo R: Drug development study designs have reached the <lb/>danger zone. Expert Rev Clin Pharmacol 2013, 6:589–591. <lb/>14. Mansi BA, Clark J, David FS, Gesell TM, Glasser S, Gonzalez J, Haller DG, <lb/>Laine C, Miller CL, Mooney LA, Zecevic M: Ten recommendations for <lb/>closing the credibility gap in reporting industry-sponsored clinical <lb/>research: a joint journal and pharmaceutical industry perspective. Mayo <lb/>Clin Proc 2012, 87:424–429. <lb/>15. Clark J, Gonzalez J, Mansi B, Miller C, Mooney LA, Mosdell K, Richards D, <lb/>Schreiweis M, Weigel A, Wager E: Enhancing transparency and efficiency in <lb/>reporting industry-sponsored clinical research: report from the Medical <lb/>Publishing Insights and Practices Initiative. Int J Clin Pract 2010, 64:1028–1033. <lb/>16. Thomas DR: A general inductive approach for analyzing qualitative <lb/>evaluation data. Am J Eval 2006, 27:237–246. <lb/>17. Saldaña J: The Coding Manual for Qualitative Researchers. Los Angeles: Sage; 2009. <lb/>18. Graf C, Battisti WP, Bridges D, Bruce-Winkler V, Conaty JM, Ellison JM, <lb/>Field EA, Gurr JA, Marx ME, Patel M, Sanes-Miller C, Yarker YE, International <lb/>Society for Medical Publication Professionals: Good publication practice for <lb/>communicating company sponsored medical research: the GPP2 <lb/>guidelines. BMJ 2009, 339:b4330. <lb/>19. Wager E, Woolley K, Adshead V, Cairns A, Fullam J, Gonzalez J, Grant T, <lb/>Tortell S: Awareness and enforcement of guidelines for publishing <lb/>industry-sponsored medical research among publication professionals: <lb/>the Global Publication Survey. BMJ Open 2014, 4:e004780. <lb/>20. Uniform requirements for manuscripts submitted to biomedical journals: <lb/>writing and editing for biomedical publication. Updated 2008 <lb/>[http://www.icmje.org/recommendations/archives/2008_urm.pdf] <lb/>21. Jones CW, Handler L, Crowell KE, Keil LG, Weaver MA, Platts-Mills TF: <lb/>Non-publication of large randomized clinical trials: cross sectional <lb/>analysis. BMJ 2013, 347:f6104. <lb/>22. Kmietoxicz Z: Transparency campaigners welcome new rules for clinical <lb/>trials in Europe. BMJ 2014, 348:g2579. <lb/>23. All Trials [http://www.alltrials.net/] <lb/>24. Chan AW, Tetzlaff J, Altman D, Laupacis A, Gøtzsche P, Krleža-Jerić K, <lb/>Hróbjartsson A, Mann H, Dickersin K, Berlin JA, Doré CJ, Parulekar WR, <lb/>Summerskill WS, Groves T, Schulz KF, Sox HC, Rockhold FW, Rennie D, <lb/>Moher D: SPIRIT 2013 statement: defining standard protocol items for <lb/>clinical trials. Ann Intern Med 2013, 158:200–207. <lb/>25. Hren D, Sambunjak D, Marusic M, Marusic A: Medical students&apos; decisions <lb/>about authorship in disputable situations: intervention study. Sci Eng <lb/>Ethics 2013, 19:641–651. <lb/>26. Turiel E: The Development of Social Knowledge: Morality and Convention. New <lb/>York: Cambridge University Press; 1983. <lb/>27. Braithwaite D, Emery J, de Lusignan S, Sutton S: Using the Internet to <lb/>conduct surveys of health professionals: a valid alternative? Fam Pract <lb/>2003, 20:545–551. <lb/>28. Gobo G: Re-Conceptualizing Generalization: old Issues in a New Frame. <lb/>In The SAGE Handbook of Social Research Methods. Edited by Brannen J. <lb/>London: Sage; 2008:193–213. <lb/>doi:10.1186/s12916-014-0197-z <lb/>Cite this article as: Marušić et al.: Five-step authorship framework to <lb/>improve transparency in disclosing contributors to industry-sponsored <lb/>clinical trial publications. BMC Medicine 2014 12:197. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Marušić et al. BMC Medicine 2014, 12:197 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 10 of 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1741-7015/12/197 </note>


	</text>
</tei>
