<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> R E S E A R C H <lb/>Open Access <lb/> Mechanisms downstream of reverse <lb/>transcription reduce serum levels of HBV <lb/>DNA but not of HBsAg in chronic hepatitis <lb/>B virus infection <lb/> Simon B. Larsson * , Sebastian Malmström, Charles Hannoun, Gunnar Norkrans and Magnus Lindh <lb/> Abstract <lb/> Background: Hepatitis B virus (HBV) DNA in serum of chronically infected patients declines by 3–4 log 10 units at <lb/>loss of HBe antigen (HBeAg) from serum. The mechanisms behind this decline, and the much smaller decline of <lb/>surface antigen (HBsAg) levels, are still not well known. The aim of this study was to get a better understanding of <lb/>this process by analysing both serum and intrahepatic markers of HBV replication. <lb/> Methods: Levels of HBV DNA and HBsAg in serum, and covalently closed circular DNA (cccDNA), pregenomic RNA <lb/>(pgRNA) and S-RNA and total intrahepatic HBV DNA (ihDNA) in liver biopsies from 84 chronically infected patients <lb/>(16 positive and 68 negative for HBeAg) were analysed. <lb/> Results: Lower HBV DNA levels within HBeAg-positive stage reflected lower levels of cccDNA and pgRNA with <lb/>strong correlation. In HBeAg-negative patients, ihDNA levels were greater and HBV DNA levels in serum lower than <lb/>expected from pgRNA levels. A lower HBV DNA/HBsAg ratio corresponded with lower pgRNA/cccDNA (p &lt; 0.01) <lb/>and higher S-RNA/cccDNA (p &lt; 0.0001) ratios, suggesting that in HBeAg-negative patients transcription of pgRNA, <lb/>but not of S-RNA, becomes suppressed. <lb/> Conclusions: The marked reduction of HBV DNA in serum after loss of HBeAg appears to be due to combined <lb/>reduction of cccDNA, pgRNA and yet unidentified mechanisms downstream of reverse transcription. Such mechanisms <lb/>include faster clearance of circulating virus or blocked secretion of virions, the latter supported by the observed relative <lb/>increase of ihDNA in HBeAg-negative patients. The smaller reduction of S-RNA than of pgRNA partly explains why <lb/>HBsAg remain high in the HBeAg-negative stage, supporting the possibility of HBsAg synthesis from integrated <lb/>HBV DNA. <lb/> Keywords: HBV DNA, HBsAg, cccDNA, Replication, pgRNA <lb/></front>

			<body> Background <lb/> Despite the availability of an effective vaccine, chronic <lb/>hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection remains an important <lb/>cause of liver cirrhosis and hepatocellular carcinoma, in <lb/>particular in East Asia and Sub-Saharan Africa [1]. In <lb/>clinical diagnostics, HBV DNA levels in serum are the <lb/>most important marker for the assessment of prognosis <lb/>and treatment outcome during chronic HBV infection. <lb/>In early stage of chronic infection HBV DNA usually <lb/>persists at high levels, above 7–8 log 10 IU/mL, for many <lb/>years, often decades. Later in life the HBV DNA levels <lb/>decline when the immune response evolves to more effi-<lb/>ciently suppress viral replication. The greatest reduction <lb/>of HBV DNA is observed at loss of hepatitis B e antigen <lb/>(HBeAg) from the blood, a critical step that typically <lb/>represents a transition from high to low replicative stage, <lb/>usually also conferring clinical improvement [2]. Mecha-<lb/>nisms that explain this pronounced reduction of viremia <lb/>are not fully clarified. Part of the reduction of HBV <lb/></body>

			<front> * Correspondence: simon.b.larsson@gu.se <lb/>Department of Infectious Diseases, Institute of Biomedicine, Sahlgrenska <lb/>Academy, University of Gothenburg, Gothenburg, Sweden <lb/> © 2015 Larsson et al. Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 <lb/>International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to <lb/>the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver <lb/>(http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated. <lb/> Larsson et al. Virology Journal (2015) 12:213 <lb/> DOI 10.1186/s12985-015-0447-5 <lb/></front>

			<body> DNA in serum is a result of reduced intrahepatic levels <lb/>of covalently closed circular DNA (cccDNA), and of <lb/>the pregenomic RNA (pgRNA), a transcript from cccDNA <lb/>that is reverse transcribed to minus strand HBV DNA <lb/>during formation of new viral particles [3]. The cccDNA <lb/>minichromosome is also template for transcripts that are <lb/>translated into hepatitis B surface antigens (HBsAg) em-<lb/>bedded in the envelope of both virions and so-called sub-<lb/>viral particles (SVP), of which the latter are produced in <lb/>great excess [4]. <lb/>In diagnostics, detection of HBsAg has been used as <lb/>the basic test for identification of HBV infection for de-<lb/>cades. Recently, quantification of HBsAg has come into <lb/>focus as a complement to HBV DNA levels for monitor-<lb/>ing both the natural course of infection and the response <lb/>to treatment [5]. Levels of HBsAg, which mainly repre-<lb/>sent the levels of SVP [4], are more stable over time than <lb/>HBV DNA, with a much smaller decline during the <lb/>course of infection. This difference is in particular strik-<lb/>ing during loss of HBeAg when HBV DNA declines by <lb/>3–4 log 10 or even more, whereas the HBsAg levels often <lb/>are reduced by only 1 log 10 [6–8]. As a consequence, the <lb/>ratio between these two serum markers (HBV DNA/ <lb/>HBsAg) decreases when HBV DNA reaches very low or <lb/>even undetectable levels while HBsAg remains at signifi-<lb/>cant levels [9]. Previous studies indeed indicate that re-<lb/>duced transcription of pgRNA from cccDNA may <lb/>contribute to the decline in HBV DNA [10]. It is how-<lb/>ever not well known to what extent such effects are spe-<lb/>cific for pgRNA, i.e. are not also reducing S-RNA. In the <lb/>present study we explored the relations between HBV <lb/>markers in serum and liver biopsies from both HBeAg-<lb/>positive and HBeAg-negative patients, searching for ex-<lb/>planations to the strong reduction of HBV DNA in <lb/>serum and the shift in HBV DNA/HBsAg ratio that <lb/>occur in parallel with loss of HBeAg. The contribution <lb/>of different steps of replication to the reduced serum <lb/>levels of HBV DNA and HBsAg is discussed. <lb/> Results <lb/> Patient characteristics <lb/> A summary of patient characteristics is found in Table 1. <lb/>HBeAg-negative patients had significantly lower levels of <lb/>viral markers than HBeAg-positive patients except for a <lb/>higher ratio of S-RNA to cccDNA. <lb/> Reduction of viral replication prior to loss of HBeAg <lb/> In order to study this, the levels of HBV markers within <lb/>HBeAg-positive patients, and correlations between them, <lb/>were analysed. As shown in Fig. 1a, the levels of <lb/>cccDNA spanned over more than 2 log 10 units within <lb/>this group. Levels of pgRNA correlated well with <lb/>cccDNA (R 2 = 0.88), with a regression line slope of 1.33, <lb/>indicating that a 2 log 10 decline of cccDNA <lb/>corresponded to a 2.7 log 10 decline of pgRNA. The cor-<lb/>relations in Fig. 1b (ihDNA and pgRNA) and C (serum <lb/>HBV DNA and ihDNA) were also strong among <lb/>HBeAg-positive patients, with R 2 = 0.88 and R 2 = 0.77. <lb/>The slopes were however different, indicating that <lb/>ihDNA declines less than pgRNA (k = 0.56), whereas <lb/>HBV DNA in serum declines more than ihDNA (k = <lb/>1.96). As a result, the correlation between pgRNA and <lb/>HBV DNA in serum had k = 1.04 (R 2 = 0.62), indicating <lb/>that until loss of HBeAg, reduction of HBV DNA in <lb/>serum is achieved mainly by mechanisms that lead to re-<lb/>duced pgRNA levels (Fig. 1d). <lb/> Viral markers after loss of HBeAg <lb/> To some extent this can be studied by analysing correlations <lb/>between viral markers within HBeAg-negative patients. <lb/>Figure 2a shows that the correlation between cccDNA <lb/>and pgRNA was poorer (R 2 = 0.36) than in HBeAg-<lb/>positive stage, indicating that the regulation of pgRNA <lb/>levels becomes more variable after loss of HBeAg. By <lb/>contrast, the correlation between pgRNA and ihDNA <lb/>(Fig. 2b) remained strong and with a similar slope in <lb/>HBeAg-negative (R 2 = 0.72, k = 0.50) as in HBeAg-positive <lb/>patients, suggesting that the rate of reverse transcription <lb/>is unaltered after loss of HBeAg. The correlation between <lb/>ihDNA and serum HBV DNA was on the other hand re-<lb/>markably different in HBeAg-negative patients (Fig. 2c) <lb/>with low R 2 (0.14). In particular, the levels of HBV DNA <lb/>in serum were much lower in a large proportion of pa-<lb/>tients than one would expect from the pgRNA and <lb/>ihDNA level (if the correlations had been the same as <lb/>in HBeAg-positive stage), suggesting that viremia is <lb/> Table 1 Summary of patient characteristics and virological <lb/>findings <lb/> HBeAg+ <lb/> n = 16 <lb/>HBeAg– <lb/> n = 68 <lb/> P value <lb/>Age, years, median, (range) 27 (16–60) <lb/>34 (18–59) <lb/>0.02 <lb/>Gender (M/F) <lb/>11/5 <lb/>40/28 <lb/>0.57 <lb/>Genotype (A/B/C/D) <lb/>3/4/2/7 <lb/>15/7/3/43 <lb/> – <lb/> Serum HBV DNA a <lb/> 8.30 ± 0.38 <lb/>4.30 ± 0.14 <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>Serum HBsAg b <lb/> 4.40 ± 0.18 <lb/>3.41 ± 0.11 <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>HBV DNA/HBsAg <lb/>3.90 ± 0.29 <lb/>0.89 ± 0.14 <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>ALT/ULN, median, (range) <lb/>1.37 (0.68–8.6) 0.72 (0.24–12.38) &lt;0.001 <lb/>cccDNA c <lb/> −0.70 ± 0.20 <lb/> −2.67 ± 0.10 <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>S RNA c /cccDNA c <lb/> 1.65 ± 0.20 <lb/>2.73 ± 0.11 <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/>pgRNA c /cccDNA c <lb/> 2.04 ± 0.12 <lb/>1.50 ± 0.11 <lb/>&lt;0.01 <lb/>pgRNA c /S RNA c <lb/> 0.39 ± 0.23 <lb/> −1.22 ± 0.07 <lb/>&lt;0.0001 <lb/> Virological values as mean ± SEM. P values by Mann-Whitney U test for age <lb/>and ALT, t test for virological parameters and Fisher&apos;s exact test for gender <lb/> a <lb/> log 10 cp/mL <lb/> b <lb/> log 10 IU/mL <lb/> c <lb/> log 10 copies/cEq (cell equivalent), ALT/Upper Limit of Normal <lb/></body>

			<front> Larsson et al. Virology Journal (2015) 12:213 <lb/></front>

			<page> Page 2 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<body> supressed by mechanisms acting after reverse tran-<lb/>scription or after secretion into the blood. <lb/>Comparisons of viral markers at group level (HBeAg-<lb/>positive vs. negative) revealed differences due to combined <lb/>effects before and after loss of HBeAg, and are shown by <lb/>box plots in Fig. 3a. Thus, the mean (median) cccDNA <lb/>levels were 1.97 (2.27) log 10 lower, pgRNA levels 2.52 <lb/>(2.98) log 10 lower, and serum HBV DNA levels 4.00 (4.50) <lb/>log 10 lower in HBeAg-negative as compared with HBeAg-<lb/>positive patients. These differences influence the ratios <lb/> Fig. 1 Correlations between intrahepatic HBV DNA (ihDNA) cccDNA, pregenomic RNA (pgRNA) and serum HBV DNA within HBeAg-positive patients. <lb/>pgRNA vs. cccDNA (a), ihDNA vs. pgRNA (b), HBV DNA vs. ihDNA (c), and HBV DNA vs. pgRNA (d). All values are log 10 copies/cell equivalent (cEq) if not <lb/>stated otherwise <lb/> Fig. 2 Correlations between intrahepatic HBV DNA (ihDNA), cccDNA, pregenomic RNA (pgRNA) and serum HBV DNA within HBeAg-negative patients. <lb/>pgRNA vs. cccDNA (a), ihDNA vs pgRNA (b), and HBV DNA vs. ihDNA (c). All values are log 10 copies/cell equivalent (cEq) if not stated otherwise <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Larsson et al. Virology Journal (2015) 12:213 <lb/></note>

			<page> Page 3 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<body> between these parameters as shown in Fig. 3b. Thus, <lb/>the HBV DNA/pgRNA and HBV DNA/ihDNA ratios <lb/>were much lower, whereas the HBsAg/S-RNA ratio was <lb/>the same, in HBeAg-negative as compared with HBeAg-<lb/>positive patients. <lb/> Difference in reduction of viral and subviral particles <lb/> This was studied by comparing HBV DNA and HBsAg <lb/>levels in serum (i.e. the ratio between them), and by <lb/>comparing the corresponding transcripts (pgRNA and <lb/>S-RNA). As shown in Fig. 3a, the levels of HBsAg and <lb/> Fig. 3 Box plots of serum and intrahepatic levels of hepatitis B virus markers in HBeAg-positive and HBeAg-negative patients (a) and their ratios <lb/>(b and c). Each box shows median and 25 th and 75 th percentile, the bars 10 th and 90 th percentile, and open circles results outside the latter range. <lb/>cEq, cell equivalent <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Larsson et al. Virology Journal (2015) 12:213 <lb/></note>

			<page> Page 4 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<body> S-RNA were only moderately lower in HBeAg-negative <lb/>patients (mean 1.0, median 0.87 log 10 for HBsAg; mean <lb/>1.24, median 1.72 log 10 for S-RNA). The diverging de-<lb/>gree of reduction of viral and subviral particles is fur-<lb/>ther illustrated by Fig. 3c, which shows how ratios <lb/>between levels of viral and subviral markers change after <lb/>loss of HBeAg. Thus, there was a marked reduction of <lb/>the HBV DNA/HBsAg ratio, and this was to some ex-<lb/>tent observed also for the corresponding transcripts, <lb/>pgRNA/S-RNA. However, whereas the ratio pgRNA/ <lb/>cccDNA was lower after loss of HBeAg, the ratio S-<lb/>RNA/cccDNA was instead increased. Thus, the pgRNA/ <lb/>cccDNA ratio was significantly lower than S-RNA/cccDNA <lb/>in HBeAg-negative patients (P &lt; 0.0001), but similar in <lb/>HBeAg-positive patients. <lb/> Discussion <lb/> This study of intrahepatic HBV RNA and HBV DNA <lb/>and their correlation with each other and with levels <lb/>of HBV DNA and HBsAg in serum may help to <lb/>understand how HBV replication is suppressed during <lb/>the course of infection and how low serum levels of <lb/>HBV DNA and HBsAg are achieved. Part of our re-<lb/>sults agree well with published studies [11–13], but <lb/>the observations of an increased S-RNA/pgRNA ratio <lb/>after loss of HBeAg, and of the much greater decline <lb/>of serum HBV DNA than of intrahepatic HBV DNA <lb/>have to our knowledge not been described before. <lb/>Within HBeAg-positive patients, lower serum levels of <lb/>HBV DNA essentially reflected lower levels of the <lb/>cccDNA template in combination with reduced amounts <lb/>of pgRNA per cccDNA. Our results, with a 2 log 10 lower <lb/>cccDNA level in HBeAg-negative patients are identical <lb/>with the observations by Werle-Lapostelle et al. [11], <lb/>whereas other studies have reported smaller reduction <lb/>(≈1 log 10 ) after loss of HBeAg [12, 13]. The reduced <lb/>levels of cccDNA after loss of HBeAg is probably mainly <lb/>a result of eradication of infected hepatocytes by cyto-<lb/>toxic T cells [14] in combination with lower cccDNA <lb/>content in each infected cell. <lb/>Concern has been raised regarding the specificity of <lb/>cccDNA PCR assay, i.e. whether this assay amplifies only <lb/>cccDNA. When this method was introduced by Köck <lb/>and Schlicht they showed that the degree of cross-<lb/>reactivity, i.e. amplification by cccDNA primers of other <lb/>forms of HBV DNA, was low, corresponding to a 3 log 10 <lb/> lower sensitivity [15]. We found the same degree of <lb/>cross-reactivity when we repeated their experiments <lb/>using real-time PCR (results not shown). When analys-<lb/>ing liver biopsies, we found that cccDNA levels were on <lb/>average 1.90 log 10 lower than ihDNA, and not 3 log 10 <lb/> lower as one would expect if the cccDNA findings were <lb/>due to cross-reactivity. This indicates that a low <lb/>specificity of the assay should have limited impact on <lb/>our cccDNA results. <lb/>In addition to lower cccDNA levels, we found in HBeAg-<lb/>negative patients a lower pgRNA/cccDNA ratio. This <lb/>mechanism of reduced virus production has been pro-<lb/>posed by others, and might be mediated by different <lb/>mechanisms such as accelerated intracellular clearance <lb/>of pgRNA-containing capsids induced by IFN-alfa/-beta <lb/>[16], or by IFN-alfa mediated suppression of HBV repli-<lb/>cation by epigenetic control of cccDNA function and <lb/>transcription [17]. Among our patients, the reduction <lb/>of the pgRNA/cccDNA ratio was quite moderate (0.57 <lb/>log 10 ), whereas Volz et al. and Laras et al. found larger <lb/>reductions (0.88 and 1.46 log 10 ) [12, 13]. <lb/>Within HBeAg-positive stage, pgRNA and serum HBV <lb/>DNA correlated strongly with a slope of ≈ 1, meaning <lb/>that 1 log 10 decline of pgRNA results in 1 log 10 decline <lb/>of HBV DNA in serum. In HBeAg-negative patients, <lb/>the relations between cccDNA, replicative intermediates <lb/>(pgRNA and ihDNA) and levels of HBV DNA in serum <lb/>were more complex. <lb/>Firstly, levels of pgRNA showed poorer correlation with <lb/>cccDNA, suggesting that suppression acting on this step <lb/>varies considerably between patients. <lb/>Secondly, in patients with lower cccDNA there were <lb/>relatively higher levels of ihDNA, as indicated by both <lb/>the slope of the ihDNA/pgRNA regression line and the <lb/>higher ihDNA/pgRNA ratio in HBeAg-negative patients. <lb/>The explanation to this relative increase of ihDNA among <lb/>HBeAg-negative patients is uncertain. It might be due to <lb/>production of non-productive replicative intermediates, or <lb/>retention of viral particles that are not secreted into the <lb/>blood. The latter possibility would agree with a study de-<lb/>scribing that viral particles can be blocked by anti-HBs <lb/>antibodies internalized in liver cells [18]. Another study <lb/>did however not report differences in virion release be-<lb/>tween HBeAg-positive and negative patients [19], and our <lb/>finding and possible explanations need to be further ex-<lb/>plored. One also has to consider the possibility that inte-<lb/>grated HBV DNA contributes to ihDNA, because such <lb/>integrations would be detected by our real-time PCR as-<lb/>says (if they include the target region). In early stage their <lb/>contribution would probably be minimal, but when the <lb/>production of relaxed circular DNA in virions declines in <lb/>HBeAg-negative patients the amount of integrated HBV <lb/>DNA might be high enough to influence the measured <lb/>ihDNA level. <lb/>Thirdly, in several HBeAg-negative patients the HBV <lb/>DNA level in serum was reduced much more than what <lb/>would be expected by the reduction of ihDNA, suggesting <lb/>that factors acting downstream of reverse transcription <lb/>may have great impact on HBV DNA in serum. Such fac-<lb/>tors might, as mentioned above, be reduced release of vi-<lb/>rions from infected cells, or shorter half-life of viral <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Larsson et al. Virology Journal (2015) 12:213 <lb/></note>

			<page> Page 5 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<body> particles in serum. The possibility that enhanced clearance <lb/>of free virions from the blood contributes to the pro-<lb/>nounced reduction of HBV DNA levels in serum after loss <lb/>of HBeAg has not been much studied or discussed. Math-<lb/>ematical calculations based on HBV kinetics under anti-<lb/>viral therapy [20] suggested that the half-life of free <lb/>virions is ~25 h in HBeAg-positive and ~13 h in <lb/>HBeAg-negative patients [21]. Another study reported <lb/>similar half-lives in HBeAg-positive patients (17 h), but <lb/>extremely short half-life in HBeAg-negative patients <lb/>(0.6 s) [19], data that subsequently were questioned [22]. <lb/>Despite the discrepancies it seems likely that stronger im-<lb/>munologic responses may lead to faster clearance of vi-<lb/>rions, but how much this influences serum levels of HBV <lb/>DNA remains to be elucidated. <lb/>Whereas HBV DNA levels were more than 4.0 log 10 <lb/> lower in HBeAg-negative patients, levels of HBsAg were <lb/>on average only 1.1 log 10 lower. Accordingly, the HBV <lb/>DNA/HBsAg ratio was 3.3 log 10 lower in HBeAg-negative <lb/>patients, as observed also in previous studies [13, 23, 24]. <lb/>To some extent this was explained by a reduced ratio (by <lb/>2.0 log 10 ) between the corresponding transcripts (pgRNA/ <lb/>S-RNA) in HBeAg-negative patients. This reduction of <lb/>pgRNA/S-RNA is greater than the 1.2 log 10 difference re-<lb/>ported by Volz et al. [13], and was explained by both re-<lb/>duced pgRNA/cccDNA (as mentioned above) and an <lb/>increased S-RNA/cccDNA ratio by 1.0 log 10 . This finding <lb/>suggests that the smaller reduction of HBsAg after loss of <lb/>HBeAg than expected from the cccDNA decline might <lb/>be due to an enhanced transcription of S-RNA from <lb/>cccDNA, or possibly transcription of S-RNA from inte-<lb/>grated sequences of HBV DNA that contain the complete <lb/>S region, including the promoter. Such transcription oc-<lb/>curs in the Alexander hepatoma cell line [25], but whether <lb/>this type of integrations occur during natural infection re-<lb/>mains to be demonstrated. <lb/>The ratio between HBsAg/S-RNA was unchanged <lb/>after loss of HBeAg, indicating that post-transcriptional <lb/>processing of S-RNA and turnover of subviral particles <lb/>remain unchanged after loss of HBeAg. <lb/> Conclusions <lb/> Figure 4 summarises the main findings in this study, <lb/>pointing out three novel observations for HBeAg-negative <lb/>patients: <lb/> i. A much lower HBV DNA/ihDNA ratio shows that <lb/>mechanisms downstream of reverse transcription or <lb/>downstream of secretion of virions strongly <lb/>influence HBV DNA levels in serum. <lb/>ii. An unchanged HBsAg/S-RNA ratio suggests that <lb/>secretion and degradation of SVP do not change <lb/>after loss of HBeAg. <lb/>iii. An increased S-RNA/cccDNA ratio suggests that <lb/>S-RNA and HBsAg might be produced from integrated <lb/>S genes. <lb/> Methods <lb/> Patients <lb/> From a cross-sectional study of 160 patients with chronic <lb/>HBV infection focusing on histology and HBV DNA levels <lb/>[26] a total of 84 patients were included in this study, 16 <lb/>positive and 68 negative for HBeAg. The present study is <lb/>an extension of a previous study by our group [3]. From <lb/>these patients liver biopsies were available for analysis <lb/>by molecular techniques. None of the patients were co-<lb/>infected with hepatitis C or D viruses, or HIV. The pa-<lb/>tients represented different genotypes and phases of HBV <lb/> Fig. 4 Flowchart showing differences in intrahepatic and serum viral load between HBeAg-positive and HBeAg-negative patients. Δe indicates <lb/>mean difference between levels in HBeAg-positive and HBeAg-negative patients. Three novel findings are pointed out: (i) a greater reduction of <lb/>HBV DNA in serum as compared with in the liver; (ii) an unchanged HBsAg/S RNA ratio; (iii) an increased S-RNA/cccDNA ratio, in HBeAg-negative <lb/>as compared with HBeAg-positive patients <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Larsson et al. Virology Journal (2015) 12:213 <lb/></note>

			<page> Page 6 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<body> infection. Serum samples that were used for quantification <lb/>of HBV DNA and HBsAg were taken at the time of <lb/>biopsy. All patients gave informed consent and The <lb/>Regional Ethical Review Board in Gothenburg approved <lb/>the study. <lb/> Laboratory assessments <lb/> Serum HBV DNA was analysed by Cobas Amplicor HBV <lb/>Monitor (Roche Diagnostic Systems, Branchburg, NJ) and <lb/>HBsAg in serum was quantified using the Architect assay <lb/>(Abbott, Abbott Park, IL). <lb/>Portions (approximately 5 mg) of liver biopsies were <lb/>investigated. The liver biopsies were stored in –70 °C <lb/>until analysed. After homogenization of the liver tissue <lb/>in a MagNA Lyser instrument (Roche Diagnostics), ex-<lb/>traction of nucleic acids was performed in the MagNA <lb/>Pure (Roche) robot according to the manufacturer&apos;s <lb/>protocol, using the DNA II Tissue kit. <lb/>Real-time PCR was performed using primers specific <lb/>for cccDNA as previously described [3]. These primers <lb/>amplify a segment spanning the gaps in the plus and <lb/>minus strands of the relaxed circular form of the genome <lb/>that is present in viral particles. Levels of cccDNA were <lb/>normalised to the concentration of human betaglobin <lb/>DNA. Total intrahepatic HBV DNA was analysed by the <lb/>same primers as for pgRNA but without the reverse tran-<lb/>scription step. Part of the extracted NAs was treated with <lb/>DNase (Ambion Inc.), and S-RNA and pgRNA transcripts <lb/>were quantified by real-time PCR after a reverse transcrip-<lb/>tion step (details of the primers are shown in Table 2). <lb/>Due to the overlap of S and pgRNA transcripts, the S <lb/>primers and probe also detects pgRNA. Normalization of <lb/>RNA levels was made using 18S RNA as reference. <lb/> Statistical analysis <lb/> Differences in levels of HBV RNA or DNA between <lb/>groups were analysed by unpaired t-test. Correlations <lb/>were made by linear regression and Pearson&apos;s correlation <lb/>analysis. P values below 0.05 were considered significant. <lb/>The Statview software (SAS Institute) was used for stat-<lb/>istical analyses. <lb/></body> 

			<div type="annex"> Abbreviations <lb/> cccDNA: covalently closed circular DNA; HBeAg: hepatitis B e antigen; <lb/>HBsAg: hepatitis B surface antigen; HBV: hepatitis B virus; ihDNA: intrahepatic <lb/>DNA; pgRNA: pregenomic RNA. <lb/></div> 

			<div type="annex"> Competing interests <lb/> None of the authors of the above manuscript has declared any competing <lb/>interests within the last three years. <lb/></div> 

			<div type="annex"> Authors&apos; contributions <lb/> SBL carried out the molecular analyses of liver biopsies, performed the <lb/>statistical analysis and drafted the manuscript. SM carried out the molecular <lb/>analyses of liver biopsies and helped to draft the manuscript. CH participated <lb/>in the development of molecular assays. GN participated in the design of the <lb/>study and acquisition of liver biopsies. ML conceived of the study, participated <lb/>in its design and coordination and in the acquisition of liver biopsies, and <lb/>helped to draft the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final <lb/>manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgements <lb/>Declaration of funding interests <lb/> This work was supported by grants from ALF-LUA (grant ALFGBG-146611) <lb/>and the Swedish Research Council (grant B0060901). <lb/></div> 

			<front>Received: 30 October 2015 Accepted: 3 December 2015 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. Trepo C, Chan HLY, Lok A. Hepatitis B virus infection. Lancet. 2014;384:2053–63. <lb/>2. Maruyama T, Kuwata S, Koike K, Iino S, Yasuda K, Yotsuyanagi H, et al. <lb/>Precore wild-type DNA and immune complexes persist in chronic hepatitis B <lb/>after seroconversion: no association between genome conversion and <lb/>seroconversion. Hepatology. 1998;27:245–53. <lb/>3. Malmström S, Larsson SB, Hannoun C, Lindh M. Hepatitis B viral DNA decline at <lb/>loss of HBeAg is mainly explained by reduced cccDNA load – down-regulated <lb/>transcription of PgRNA has limited impact. PLoS ONE. 2012;7:e36349. <lb/>4. Désiré N, Ngo Y, Franetich J-F, Dembele L, Mazier D, Vaillant J-C, et al. Definition <lb/>of an HBsAg to DNA international unit conversion factor by enrichment of <lb/>circulating hepatitis B virus forms. J Viral Hepat. 2015;22:718–26. <lb/>5. Martinot-Peignoux M, Lapalus M, Asselah T, Marcellin P. HBsAg quantification: <lb/>useful for monitoring natural history and treatment outcome. Liver Int. <lb/>2013;34:97–107. <lb/>6. Chan HL-Y, Wong VW-S, Wong GL-H, Tse C-H, Chan H-Y, Sung JJ-Y. A <lb/>longitudinal study on the natural history of serum hepatitis B surface <lb/>antigen changes in chronic hepatitis B. Hepatology. 2010;52:1232–41. <lb/>7. Nguyen T, Thompson AJV, Bowden S, Croagh C, Bell S, Desmond PV, et al. <lb/>Hepatitis B surface antigen levels during the natural history of chronic <lb/>hepatitis B: a perspective on Asia. J Hepatol. 2010;52:508–13. <lb/>8. Jaroszewicz J, Calle Serrano B, Wursthorn K, Deterding K, Schlue J, Raupach R, <lb/>et al. Hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) levels in the natural history of <lb/>hepatitis B virus (HBV)-infection: a European perspective. J Hepatol. <lb/>2010;52:514–22. <lb/>9. Larsson SB, Eilard A, Malmström S, Hannoun C, Dhillon AP, Norkrans G, et al. <lb/>HBsAg quantification for identification of liver disease in chronic hepatitis B <lb/>virus carriers. Liver Int. 2014;34:e238–45. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body> Table 2 Oligonucleotide sequences of primers and probes <lb/> Target Oligo <lb/>Sequence a <lb/> Nucleotide <lb/>position b <lb/> S-RNA Forward <lb/>primer <lb/>TCCTCCAAYTTGTCCTGGTYATC <lb/>350–372 <lb/>Reverse <lb/>primer <lb/>AGATGAGGCATAGCAGCAGGAT <lb/>432–410 <lb/>Probe <lb/>(AS) <lb/>ATGATAAAACGCCGCAGACACATCCARC 400–373 <lb/>pgRNA Forward <lb/>primer <lb/>GGTCCCCTAGAAGAAGAACTCCCT <lb/>2367–2390 <lb/>Reverse <lb/>primer <lb/>CATTGAGATTCCCGAGATTGAGAT <lb/>2454–2431 <lb/>Probe <lb/>TCTCAATCGCCGCGTCGCAGA <lb/>2408–2428 <lb/>cccDNA Forward <lb/>primer <lb/>CCGTGTGCACTTCGCTTCA <lb/>1575–1593 <lb/>Reverse <lb/>primer <lb/>GCACAGCTTGGAGGCTTGA <lb/>1882–1864 <lb/>Probe <lb/>CATGGAGACCACCGTGAACGCCC <lb/>1607–1629 <lb/> a <lb/> Y, T or C; R, A or G; AS, antisense <lb/> b <lb/> Position in genotype A genome <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Larsson et al. Virology Journal (2015) 12:213 <lb/></note>

			<page> Page 7 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> 10. Pollicino T, Belloni L, Raffa G, Pediconi N, Squadrito G, Raimondo G, et al. <lb/>Hepatitis B virus replication is regulated by the acetylation status of <lb/>hepatitis B virus cccDNA-bound H3 and H4 histones. Gastroenterology. <lb/>2006;130:823–37. <lb/>11. Werle Lapostolle B, Bowden S, Locarnini S, Wursthorn K, Petersen J, Lau G, <lb/>et al. Persistence of cccDNA during the natural history of chronic hepatitis B <lb/>and decline during adefovir dipivoxil therapy1 ☆. Gastroenterology. <lb/>2004;126:1750–8. <lb/>12. Laras A, Koskinas J, Dimou E, Kostamena A, Hadziyannis SJ. Intrahepatic <lb/>levels and replicative activity of covalently closed circular hepatitis B virus <lb/>DNA in chronically infected patients. Hepatology. 2006;44:694–702. <lb/>13. Volz T, Lutgehetmann M, Wachtler P, Jacob A, Quaas A, Murray JM, et al. <lb/>Impaired intrahepatic hepatitis B virus productivity contributes to low viremia <lb/>in most HBeAg-negative patients. Gastroenterology. 2007;133:843–52. <lb/>14. Thimme R, Wieland S, Steiger C, Ghrayeb J, Reimann KA, Purcell RH, et al. <lb/>CD8(+) T cells mediate viral clearance and disease pathogenesis during <lb/>acute hepatitis B virus infection. J Virol. 2003;77:68–76. <lb/>15. Köck J, Schlicht HJ. Analysis of the earliest steps of hepadnavirus replication: <lb/>genome repair after infectious entry into hepatocytes does not depend on <lb/>viral polymerase activity. J Virol. 1993;67:4867–74. <lb/>16. Wieland SF, Guidotti LG, Chisari FV. Intrahepatic induction of alpha/beta <lb/>interferon eliminates viral RNA-containing capsids in hepatitis B virus <lb/>transgenic mice. J Virol. 2000;74:4165–73. <lb/>17. Belloni L, Allweiss L, Guerrieri F, Pediconi N, Volz T, Pollicino T, et al. IFN-α <lb/>inhibits HBV transcription and replication in cell culture and in humanized <lb/>mice by targeting the epigenetic regulation of the nuclear cccDNA <lb/>minichromosome. J Clin Invest. 2012;122:529–37. <lb/>18. Neumann AU, Phillips S, Levine I, Ijaz S, Dahari H, Eren R, et al. Novel <lb/>mechanism of antibodies to hepatitis B virus in blocking viral particle <lb/>release from cells. Hepatology. 2010;52:875–85. <lb/>19. Dandri M, Murray JM, Lutgehetmann M, Volz T, Lohse AW, Petersen J. Virion <lb/>half-life in chronic hepatitis B infection is strongly correlated with levels of <lb/>viremia. Hepatology. 2008;48:1079–86. <lb/>20. Dahari H, Shudo E, Ribeiro RM, Perelson AS. Modeling complex decay profiles <lb/>of hepatitis B virus during antiviral therapy. Hepatology. 2009;49:32–8. <lb/>21. Ribeiro RM, Germanidis G, Powers KA, Pellegrin B, Nikolaidis P, Perelson AS, <lb/>et al. Hepatitis B virus kinetics under antiviral therapy sheds light on differences <lb/>in hepatitis B e antigen positive and negative infections. J Infect Dis. <lb/>2010;202:1309–18. <lb/>22. Dahari H, Cotler SJ, Layden TJ, Perelson AS. Hepatitis B virus clearance rate <lb/>estimates. Hepatology. 2009;49:1779–80. author reply 1780–1. <lb/>23. Jang JW, Yoo SH, Kwon JH, You CR, Lee S, Lee JH, et al. Serum hepatitis B <lb/>surface antigen levels in the natural history of chronic hepatitis B infection. <lb/>Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2011;34:1337–46. <lb/>24. Tuaillon E, Mondain A-M, Nagot N, Ottomani L, Kania D, Nogue E, et al. <lb/>Comparison of serum HBsAg quantitation by four immunoassays, and <lb/>relationships of HBsAg level with HBV replication and HBV genotypes. PLoS <lb/>ONE. 2012;7:e32143. <lb/>25. MacNab GM, Alexander JJ, Lecatsas G, Bey EM, Urbanowicz JM. Hepatitis B <lb/>surface antigen produced by a human hepatoma cell line. Br J Cancer. <lb/>1976;34:509–15. <lb/>26. Lindh M, Horal P, Dhillon AP, Norkrans G. Hepatitis B virus DNA levels, precore <lb/>mutations, genotypes and histological activity in chronic hepatitis B. J Viral <lb/>Hepat. 2000;7:258–67. <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex"> • We accept pre-submission inquiries <lb/> • Our selector tool helps you to find the most relevant journal <lb/> • We provide round the clock customer support <lb/> • Convenient online submission <lb/> • Thorough peer review <lb/> • Inclusion in PubMed and all major indexing services <lb/> • Maximum visibility for your research <lb/>Submit your manuscript at <lb/>www.biomedcentral.com/submit <lb/> Submit your next manuscript to BioMed Central <lb/>and we will help you at every step: <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote"> Larsson et al. Virology Journal (2015) 12:213 <lb/></note>

			<page> Page 8 of 8 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
