<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_130606_Jouhet_et_al"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<page> 1 <lb/></page>

			<front> Glycerolipid transfer for the building of membranes in plant cells <lb/> Juliette JOUHET (1), Eric MARECHAL, and Maryse A. BLOCK <lb/> Laboratoire de Physiologie Cellulaire Végétale, UMR 5168 (CNRS/CEA/Université Joseph <lb/>Fourier/INRA), DRDC/PCV, CEA-Grenoble, 17 rue des Martyrs, F-38054, Grenoble-cedex 9, <lb/>France. <lb/> Corresponding author: Maryse A. Block <lb/>Tel: 33 (0) 438 78 49 85 FAX: 33 (0) 438 78 50 91 E-mail: maryse.blockatcea.fr <lb/>(1) Present address: Department of Plant Sciences, University of Cambridge, Downing Street, <lb/>Cambridge CB2 3EA, UK <lb/> Running title: Lipid transfer in plant cell <lb/> Keywords: lipid transfer, membrane, plant cell, vesicle, membrane contact, glycerolipid <lb/> Type of article: Review <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>Abbreviations: <lb/> CoA : Coenzyme A <lb/> DAG : Diacylglycerol <lb/> DGD : DGDG synthase <lb/> DGDG : Digalactosyldiacylglycerol <lb/> DPG : Diphosphatidylglycerol <lb/> ER : Endoplasmic reticulum <lb/> MGD : MGDG synthase <lb/> MGDG : Monogalactosyldiacylglycerol <lb/> LTP : Lipid transfer protein <lb/> LysoPC : Lysophosphatidylcholine <lb/> PA : Phosphatidate <lb/> PAP : Phosphatidate phosphatase <lb/> PC : Phosphatidylcholine <lb/> PE : Phosphatidylethanolamine <lb/> PG : Phosphatidylglycerol <lb/> PI : Phosphatidylinositol <lb/> PI-TP: Phosphatidylinositol transfer protein <lb/> PS : Phosphatidylserine <lb/> SQD : SQDG synthase <lb/> SQDG : Sulfoquinovosyldiacylglycerol <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<front> Abstract <lb/> Membranes of plant organelles have specific glycerolipid compositions. Selective distribution <lb/>of lipids at the levels of subcellular organelles, membrane leaflets and membrane domains <lb/>reflects a complex and finely tuned lipid homeostasis. Glycerolipid neosynthesis occurs <lb/>mainly in plastid envelope and endoplasmic reticulum membranes. Since most lipids are not <lb/>only present in the membranes where they are synthesised, one cannot explain membrane <lb/>specific lipid distribution by metabolic processes confined in each membrane compartment. In <lb/>this review, we present our current understanding of glycerolipid trafficking in plant cells. We <lb/>examine the potential mechanisms involved in lipid transport inside bilayers and from one <lb/>membrane to another. We survey lipid transfers going through vesicular membrane flow and <lb/>those dependent on lipid transfer proteins at membrane contact sites. By introducing recently <lb/>described membrane lipid reorganisation during phosphate deprivation and recent <lb/>developments issued from mutant analyses, we detail the specific lipid transfers towards or <lb/>outwards the chloroplast envelope. <lb/> </front>
			
			<toc>Contents <lb/> 
			
			1. Introduction ............................................................................................................................ 5 <lb/>2. Membrane glycerolipid diffusion........................................................................................... 6 <lb/>3. Flip-flop movements .............................................................................................................. 7 <lb/>3.1. Energy-independent flippases ......................................................................................... 8 <lb/>3.2. Energy-dependent translocases ...................................................................................... 9 <lb/>4. Vesicular lipid transfer ......................................................................................................... 13 <lb/>4.1. Secretory pathway ........................................................................................................ 13 <lb/>4.1.1. Reticulum and Golgi exchanges............................................................................. 14 <lb/>4.1.2. Transfer to the vacuoles ......................................................................................... 14 <lb/>4.1.3. Transfer to the plasma membrane .......................................................................... 16 <lb/>4.1.4. Endocytosis and exocytosis.................................................................................... 17 <lb/></toc>

			<page>4 <lb/></page> 
			
			<toc>4.2. Transfer from the plastid envelope to the thylakoids.................................................... 19 <lb/>5. Transfer by membrane contact ............................................................................................. 20 <lb/>5.1. Membrane contact sites................................................................................................ 20 <lb/>5.2. Lipid transfer protein or LTP ....................................................................................... 22 <lb/>6. Conclusion............................................................................................................................ 24 <lb/>Acknowledgements: ................................................................................................................. 26 <lb/>References ................................................................................................................................ 26 <lb/></toc>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/> Plant cell membranes contain a wide range of glycerolipids which are not randomly allocated. <lb/>A selective distribution at the levels of subcellular organelles, membrane leaflets and <lb/>membrane domains indicates a complex and finely tuned lipid homeostasis. Additionally, the <lb/>distribution remains relatively well conserved among tissues and plants species (Table 1). In <lb/>standard plant culture conditions, on one hand, glycolipids, i.e. sulfolipid and galactolipids, <lb/>are restricted to plastid membranes and, on the other hand, phospholipids are the main <lb/>components of extraplastidic membranes. PE is excluded from plastidic membranes, PC is <lb/>absent from the inner membranes of chloroplasts and DPG is restricted to mitochondria inner <lb/>membrane. Sterols and glycosphingolipids are present in plant membranes although in much <lb/>lower amounts than glycerolipids [for reviews see 1, 2]. Like in mammalian cells, sterols and <lb/>glycosphingolipids are not homogenously distributed among membranes and are notably <lb/>present in the plasma membrane where they are likely involved in membrane domain <lb/>organisation. <lb/>In plants, phosphate deprivation has been reported to decrease the phospholipid content, <lb/>consistent with a mobilization of the phosphate reserve, and conversely to increase non-<lb/>phosphorous membrane lipids such as DGDG and SQDG [3, 4]. Moreover a form of DGDG <lb/>with specific fatty acids: 16:0 at glycerol sn1 position and 18:2 at sn2 position is especially <lb/>enhanced [5, 6]. Correlated to the lipid composition changes there is also a strong <lb/>modification of the lipid distribution between membranes. Upon phosphate deprivation, <lb/>DGDG, a specific plastid lipid in standard conditions, was found in the plasma membrane [7, <lb/>8], a membranous compartment disconnected from plastid membranes, but dynamically <lb/>connected to the overall endomembrane system. Moreover, several lines of evidence have <lb/>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			shown that large amounts of DGDG are also present in mitochondria upon phosphate <lb/>deprivation [9]. <lb/>One cannot explain the membrane specific lipid distribution only by metabolic processes <lb/>confined in each membrane compartment simply because most lipids are not just present in <lb/>membranes where they were synthesised. The lipid distribution is usually stable despite the <lb/>extensive membrane trafficking that occurs between organelles. The maintained specific lipid <lb/>distribution relies therefore on molecular mechanisms of lipid transport. These mechanisms <lb/>have been studied mostly in yeast and in mammalian cells [for a review 10] and very few data <lb/>have been collected in plant models. Besides information from genetics and proteomics <lb/>analyses, we believe that disturbance of lipid distribution during phosphate deprivation <lb/>represents a promising tool to unravel these molecular mechanisms in plants. In this review, <lb/>we discuss recent data describing the potential mechanisms involved in glycerolipid <lb/>trafficking in plant cells, including recently described membrane lipid reorganization during <lb/>phosphate deprivation. <lb/> 2. Membrane glycerolipid diffusion <lb/> Membrane lipids are subjected to three kinds of dispersive forces: lateral diffusion, diffusion <lb/>across membranes (flip-flop) and movement outside the source membrane, possibly reaching <lb/>other membranes through aqueous phase. Based on the very rapid spontaneous lateral <lb/>diffusion of lipids within membrane lateral surfaces (0.1 to 1 µm 2 .s -1 ; [11]), the lipid <lb/>distribution in vesicular connected organelles should be homogenous. The fact that this is <lb/>clearly not the case indicates that very dynamic homeostatic mechanisms are involved to <lb/>maintain the lipid composition of each organelle. <lb/>In comparison with lateral diffusion, lipid diffusion between the two leaflets of a membrane <lb/>bilayer or from one membrane to another is very slow (Figure 1). The spontaneous flip-flop <lb/>
			
			<page>7 <lb/></page>
			
			movement through a lipid bilayer takes less than one second for DAG but it takes hours for <lb/>lipids with larger polar heads [12]. <lb/>Lipid diffusion between different membranes is fast for single fatty acid chain lipids that <lb/>easily partition into the aqueous phase, like lysoPC, or lipids containing two short fatty acid <lb/>chain (4 to 6 carbons) [12, 13]. By contrast, there is almost no spontaneous transfer of regular <lb/>diacyl lipids although this trafficking is essential for organelle functioning and cell survival. <lb/>Vesicular and non-vesicular transport systems have been reported in plants as in other <lb/>eukaryotic cells. The vesicular pathway supports a complex membrane flow which couples <lb/>lipid and protein movements while non-vesicular pathways require monomeric exchange of <lb/>single lipid molecules. Unlike the vesicular pathway, non-vesicular pathways do not involve <lb/>membrane fusions but rather tight contacts between membranes. A number of enzymes are <lb/>required to ensure and regulate lipid movements and it is likely that enzymes are also <lb/>necessary to control lateral and transbilayer movements both at membrane fusion points in <lb/>vesicular processes and at contact sites in non-vesicular processes. <lb/> 3. Flip-flop movements <lb/> Several types of flip-flop movement exist [for review, see 14]. The spontaneous movement <lb/>across the bilayer is dependent only on the physical and chemical properties of lipids and <lb/>membranes. In vivo, DAG movement seems mostly driven by diffusive forces whereas <lb/>proteins are required for significant rates of phospholipid and glycolipid transbilayer <lb/>movements. Energy-independent flippases catalyse an ATP-independent movement, in which <lb/>lipids probably move along the polar surface created by these proteins [15]. These flippases <lb/>can be specific for some lipid classes but they cannot assist the movement of lipids against a <lb/>physicochemical gradient. They maintain bilayer symmetry by contrast with ATP-dependent <lb/>
			
			<page>8 <lb/></page>
			
			translocases that can accumulate specific lipid classes against equilibrated gradients. ATP-<lb/>dependent translocases are involved in the preservation of membrane asymmetry [16]. <lb/> 3.1. Energy-independent flippases <lb/> To our knowledge, no flippase has been characterized in plant cells although some gene <lb/>sequences exhibit homologies with flippases from other organisms. The biosynthesis of ER <lb/>phospholipids is supposed to be localised in the cytosolic leaflet like in other eukaryotic cells <lb/>[17], therefore half of the newly synthesised lipids has to be transferred to the other leaflet. In <lb/>yeast and mammalian cells, the ATP-independent flip-flop movement in the ER membrane is <lb/>ten times faster than in membranes that do not contain proteins. This movement is sensitive to <lb/>proteases [14] but it is unclear whether it involves a dedicated type of enzymes or the mere <lb/>presence of proteins. Interestingly, peptides that mimic the 񮽙-helices of transmembrane <lb/>proteins can stimulate phospholipid flip-flop in liposomes [18]. Enhanced flippase-type <lb/>transfers are also necessary at membrane contact sites where lipids should be transferred from <lb/>the cytosolic leaflet of the donor membrane to the cytosolic leaflet of the acceptor membrane <lb/>[19]. It is possible that such flippases are involved in the transfer of DGDG from chloroplasts <lb/>to mitochondria during phosphate deprivation since this transfer seems related to membrane <lb/>contact [9 and see below]. <lb/>The first flippases that have been characterized in eukaryotic cells are the RFT1 protein, a <lb/>yeast reticulum pyrophosphoryloligosaccharide-dolichol flippase [20], and the scramblase, a <lb/>red blood cell plasma membrane calcium-dependent flippase [21]. RFT1 transfers dolichol <lb/>from the reticulum cytosolic leaflet, where it is synthesised, to the lumenal leaflet where it is <lb/>eventually located [20]. In Arabidopsis, one RFT1 homologue can be retrieved (At5g07630), <lb/>but is still functionally uncharacterized. In red blood cell membranes, sphingomyelin and <lb/>most of the PC are located in the plasma membrane outer leaflet whereas PS and a part of the <lb/>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			PE are in the cytosolic leaflet. An increase of calcium influx activates the scramblase, which <lb/>equilibrates the phospholipid composition between the two plasma membrane leaflets, by <lb/>catalysing bidirectional transfer of each lipid species. Movement of PS to the outer leaflet can <lb/>subsequently induce blood coagulation [21]. In Arabidopsis, a scramblase-related gene has a <lb/>weak but significant similarity (At2g04940) and should be examined in the context of lipid <lb/>transfers. <lb/> 3.2. Energy-dependent translocases <lb/> In plants, many reports highlight asymmetric distributions of lipids in several membranes. <lb/>The plant plasma membrane is asymmetric, like in red blood cells, and PS externalisation can <lb/>induce cell death processes [22]. The above-mentioned scramblase-like plant protein may <lb/>play a role in affecting the plasma membrane asymmetry. The thylakoids show a marked <lb/>asymmetry in the transversal distribution of the lipids with an enrichment of the outer leaflet <lb/>in MGDG and PG while DGDG and SQDG are essentially confined to the inner leaflet [23]. <lb/>Since these lipids are linked to specific structures of the photosystems, the lipid asymmetry of <lb/>the thylakoids is likely to reflect the organisation of the photosynthetic machinery [24]. It has <lb/>also been proposed that the asymmetry is preestablished in the inner envelope membrane due <lb/>to the topography of lipid synthesising proteins and is transferred to thylakoids by membrane <lb/>fusion [25]. In the plastid two-membrane envelope, PC is present only in the cytosolic leaflet <lb/>of the outer membrane [26]. The tonoplast membrane exhibits a slight asymmetry due to a <lb/>higher amount of PE in the cytosolic leaflet [27]. The biological significance of the <lb/>asymmetry of plastid envelope and tonoplast membranes is still unknown but is possibly <lb/>related to signalling or membrane identification mechanism. <lb/>Two translocase families are well documented. The first family includes aminophospholipid <lb/>translocases that belongs to the P-type ATPase superfamily. The first identified enzyme of <lb/>
			
			<page>10 <lb/></page>
			
			this family was DRS2, a yeast translocase [28]. The drs2 mutant is cold-sensitive and has no <lb/>asymmetrical accumulation of PS in the inner leaflet of the plasma membrane. Although the <lb/>initial study was controversial, new data supports the proposal that DRS2 plays a role in the <lb/>translocation of lipids in the trans-Golgi and endosomal compartments during budding of <lb/>membrane vesicles [for review, see 14]. In Arabidopsis, eleven genes belong to this family <lb/>(ALA1 to ALA11) (Table 2). ALA1 exhibits the strongest homology to DRS2 and its <lb/>expression in drs2 yeast mutant restores cold resistance and internalisation of the plasma <lb/>membrane PS [29]. However, ALA1 localization and function in planta are not characterized. <lb/>Furthermore, the roles of the other ALA proteins remain speculative. <lb/>The second family belongs to the ABC (ATP-binding cassette) protein superfamily that <lb/>comprises transporters for a whole variety of organic and inorganic compounds. Typically, <lb/>ABC proteins possess two nucleotide-binding domains and two transmembrane domains. <lb/>Multi-drug resistance studies in cancerous cells and in yeast first suggested that some ABC <lb/>transporters participated in the externalisation of plasma membrane lipids and there are now <lb/>many indications for lipid transport mediated by ABC proteins in cellular membranes [for <lb/>reviews, see 30, 31]. Arabidopsis contains 129 genes belonging to this family [32]. Data on <lb/>plant ABC transporters indicate that they play a key role in numerous processes necessary for <lb/>plant development: chlorophyll biosynthesis, iron-sulphur cluster formation, stomata <lb/>movement and possibly ionic fluxes [for review, see 33]. Recent reports have pointed out <lb/>their role in plant lipid transport (Table 2). A potential transporter of plastid fatty acids, <lb/>identified in the Arabidopsis genome (At1g54350), belongs to this family [34]. The major site <lb/>of de novo synthesis of fatty acids in plant cells is the plastid stroma. Fatty acids are produced <lb/>predominantly as C18:1-ACP and C16:0-ACP and are metabolic substrates for numerous <lb/>pathways such as membrane glycerolipid biosyntheses in the plastid envelope as well as in the <lb/>
			
			<page>11 <lb/></page>
			
			ER [for a review see 2]. An acyl-ACP thioesterase, localized in the inner envelope membrane, <lb/>can hydrolyze acyl-ACP and release free fatty acids. Free fatty acids released from the inner <lb/>envelope are channelled to the outer envelope, possibly via the At1g54350 ABC transporter <lb/>and reactivated to acyl-CoA in the outer envelope [35]. <lb/>Xu et al. identified another chloroplastic ABC type protein (TGD1) (At1g19800) that is likely <lb/>dedicated to the import of phosphatidate from the ER to the chloroplast for the synthesis of <lb/>eukaryotic galactoglycerolipids [36, 37]. The so-called prokaryotic and eukaryotic types of <lb/>galactoglycerolipid structures exist in plants [for a review see 2]. Both types are generated in <lb/>the chloroplast envelope by galactosylation of DAG molecular species of distinct origins. <lb/>Whereas prokaryotic DAG is fully synthesized in plastids, eukaryotic DAG originates from <lb/>PC formed in the ER. Studies with labelled lipid precursors indicated that PC provides its <lb/>eukaryotic DAG backbone to plastid glycerolipids [38, 39]. This transfer requires desaturated <lb/>PC since the fad2 Arabidopsis mutant, deficient in the desaturation of C18:1 localised in ER, <lb/>contains a smaller eukaryotic/prokaryotic monogalactosyldiacylglycerol (MGDG) ratio than <lb/>wild type plants [40]. Although PC is present in the outer membrane of the plastid envelope, <lb/>the only known site of PC de novo biosynthesis is localised in the ER. A direct import of PC <lb/>from ER, or an import of intermediates derived from endoplasmic reticulum PC, possibly <lb/>DAG or phosphatidate, is therefore required for the synthesis of eukaryotic galactolipids <lb/>(Figure 2). It is still unclear which lipid is transported. Some clues have been deduced from <lb/>the in-depth examination of lipids of plant cell suspensions after transferring the cells into a <lb/>phosphate-deprived medium [6]. Since phosphate starvation induced a high increase in the <lb/>synthesis of eukaryotic DGDG (notably the above-mentioned 16:0-18:2 molecular species), <lb/>the exposure to phosphate starvation conditions was therefore a way to analyze the passage of <lb/>the DAG-backbone from the ER PC to the plastid galactolipids. Phosphate starvation induced <lb/>
			
			<page>12 <lb/></page>
			
			an increase of DAG with an identical fatty acid composition as PC. Since DAG was not <lb/>detected in plastid membranes and a phosphatidate pool was not detected in the cells, Jouhet <lb/> et al. proposed that DAG is the molecule transported from ER to chloroplast. Several <lb/>phospholipases C specifically activated during Pi deprivation are probably involved in the <lb/>formation of this DAG pool [41, 42]. The transferred DAG is presumably galactosylated into <lb/>MGDG and DGDG through the actions of the enzymes MGD2 (or MGD3) and DGD1 (or <lb/>DGD2) induced by phosphate deprivation and present in the outer envelope membrane. <lb/>However, the existence of a phospholipase D (PLD񮽙2) activated by phosphate deprivation <lb/>[42, 43], the accumulation of phosphatidate in the tgd1 mutant and the localization of TGD1 <lb/>in the chloroplast inner envelope membrane [37] suggest that the transported molecule could <lb/>be phosphatidate. To understand this latter scheme, the precise localization of the <lb/>phosphatidic acid phosphatase (PAP) involved in the transformation of eukaryotic <lb/>phosphatidate into DAG is crucial since part of the eukaryotic DAG is galactosylated by <lb/>MGD1, the constitutive MGDG synthase that is present in the inner envelope membrane. In <lb/>some plants such as spinach, PAP has been detected in the inner envelope membrane and this <lb/>was considered to be dedicated to the formation of prokaryotic DAG [for a review see 2]. <lb/>Therefore, either this PAP is also involved in the formation of eukaryotic DAG or a <lb/>complementary transport of eukaryotic DAG is necessary. Moreover, in some other plants <lb/>such as pea, even though MGDG synthase is present in the inner envelope membrane, PAP <lb/>activity has never been detected in the envelope, possibly related to the fact that no <lb/>prokaryotic DAG is formed in these plants. Therefore, at least in plants such as pea, transport <lb/>of eukaryotic DAG up to the inner envelope membrane is necessary to ensure MGDG <lb/>synthesis and thylakoid development. Altogether, it is likely that in all plants eukaryotic DAG <lb/>is transported from the ER to the inner envelope membrane. Recent findings from the tgd1 <lb/>
			
			<page>13 <lb/></page>
			
			mutant analysis indicate that eukaryotic phosphatidate is also transported to the inner <lb/>envelope membrane where it plays a role in enhancing of MGDG synthesis (Figure 2). <lb/> 4. Vesicular lipid transfer <lb/> 4.1. Secretory pathway <lb/> Since most phospholipids, sterol, sphingolipid and many proteins are synthesized in the ER, <lb/>this compartment can be considered as a cell central metabolic organelle in relation with other <lb/>compartments. During interphase, the ER is in direct connection with the nucleus. On electron <lb/>micrographs, the ER and nucleus membranes appear as connected, although a lumen <lb/>constriction is observed at the junction area [44]. With or without Golgi participation, the ER <lb/>is involved in protein and lipid supply for the vacuolar and plasma membranes by vesicles <lb/>moving along actin filaments [45]. <lb/>The general mechanism of vesicular transfer is carried out in several steps [for reviews see, <lb/>46, 47]. Briefly, small type Ras GTPases, coupled to GTP exchange factors, support the <lb/>recruiting of protein complexes and their anchoring to the donor membrane. Coat proteins, <lb/>like adaptatin or clathrin, can participate with these complexes. Then, vesicles extrude from <lb/>the donor membrane (following mechanisms that remain to be fully characterized), and move <lb/>away using the actin cytoskeleton and myosin. Dynamin, a large GTPase is involved in the <lb/>scission of nascent vesicles from the parent membrane. Anchoring and fusion to the target <lb/>membrane are mediated by SNARE (Soluble N-ethylmaleimide-sensitive factor Attachment <lb/>protein REceptors) proteins, located both on the vesicles (v-SNARE) and on the target <lb/>membrane (t-SNARE), and small GTPases. <lb/>This process has been intensively studied at the level of protein trafficking and, although <lb/>vesicles obviously transfer lipid material, very little data on lipids exist. In the following <lb/>paragraphs, we present current information on the molecular machineries involved in <lb/>
			
			<page>14 <lb/></page>
			
			vesicular trafficking in plants, specifically in endomembranes (Figure 3) and from chloroplast <lb/>envelope to thylakoids. This is then developed in relation to specific lipid transfers. <lb/> 4.1.1. Reticulum and Golgi exchanges <lb/> These exchanges are mediated by transport vesicles that bud from the donor membrane due to <lb/>the assembly of a cytosolic coat protein known as coatomer protein I or II. Vesicles <lb/>containing these proteins are called respectively COPI and COPII. The ER to Golgi pathway <lb/>transfers phospholipids, sterols, sphingolipids and proteins. In mammalian and yeast, this <lb/>transfer is mediated by COPII-type coated vesicles. In plants, the Golgi apparatus is close to <lb/>the ER but, although proteins exhibiting substantial homology with partners of the COPII <lb/>complex are known, it was never possible to visualize any COPII-type vesicles. The ER to <lb/>Golgi transfer does not seem to imply a vesicular stage [48]. It probably works with the <lb/>COPII machinery but a COPII independent pathway is also possible [49]. Surprisingly, the <lb/>transfer from ER to Golgi is independent of actin or microtubules [50]. The long-standing <lb/>contact between the reticulum and the Golgi is apparently sufficient to support the transfer. <lb/>Several studies have shown the existence of a Golgi to ER pathway in plants presumably <lb/>working through COPI vesicles [48]. There is no doubt that the COPI machinery exists in <lb/>plants and it is likely that COPI and COPII pathways are interdependent due to the necessity <lb/>for recycling the regulatory machinery of the secretory pathway. The exact role of COPI <lb/>vesicles in the Golgi to ER transfer has been a matter of controversy mostly because much of <lb/>the information comes from use of the secretory pathway inhibitor BFA, which affects also <lb/>the ER to Golgi pathway. No data is available about the importance of this COPI and COPII <lb/>trafficking on the lipid distribution in the cell. <lb/> 4.1.2. Transfer to the vacuoles <lb/> In plants, two types of vacuoles exist. On one hand, the storage vacuole is present in the <lb/>storage tissues, like cotyledons and endosperm. It is characterised by a neutral pH and by the <lb/>
			
			<page>15 <lb/></page>
			
			presence of񮽙񮽙-TIP (tonoplast integral protein) and storage proteins, like prolamins and <lb/>globulins. On the other hand, the lytic vacuole of vegetative tissues is characterised by an <lb/>acidic pH and presence of 񮽙-TIP and lumenal proteins. Theses two vacuoles have different <lb/>protein-sorting mechanisms [44], and little is known about their lipid sorting. <lb/>Although the storage vacuole lipid composition is not yet characterised, different mechanisms <lb/>of transfers are identified depending on tissues and plant species. Two types of vesicles are <lb/>possibly present: the first type originating from the ER, corresponds to the so-called <lb/> &quot; precursor-accumulating compartment &quot; that contains prolamins; the other type (deriving from <lb/>the Golgi), corresponds to dense vesicles that contain globulins [51]. Altogether, proteins <lb/>destined for the storage vacuole have an addressing domain in their C-terminal and their <lb/>transfer involves the activation by PI-4P phosphoinositide since this trafficking is sensitive to <lb/>Wortmaninn, a PI-kinase inhibitor [52]. <lb/>The lytic vacuole can be compared to animal lysosomes. Lipids from clathrin-coated vesicles <lb/>are transferred from the Golgi to a prevacuolar compartment, with the intervention of the actin <lb/>cytoskeleton and dynamin [45]. Transfer between the prevacuolar compartment and the lytic <lb/>vacuole is not yet characterised. PI-3P is involved in the vesicular transfer from the Golgi to <lb/>the lytic vacuole. In animals and yeast, a protein called EEA (Early Endosome Antigen) binds <lb/>PI-3P with the participation of RabF GTPase and drives to the endosome fusion. The <lb/>overexpression of the EEA PI-3P binding domain in Arabidopsis showed that this domain <lb/>was sorted gradually from the Golgi to the lytic vacuole via the prevacuolar compartment. By <lb/>competition mechanism, this overexpression inhibited the trafficking of vacuole proteins <lb/>while trapping free PI-3P [53]. The plant ADL6 dynamin, that binds adaptatin and actin, has a <lb/>PI-3P specific PH domain (phosphoinositide recognition domain) and its mutation abolished <lb/>the trafficking of vacuole proteins. ADL6 is therefore an important protein that connects PI-<lb/>
			
			<page>16 <lb/></page>
			
			3P local concentration and sorting to the vacuole [54]. However, nothing is known about the <lb/>lipid composition and the lipid selectivity of all these vesicles. <lb/> 4.1.3. Transfer to the plasma membrane <lb/> The plant cell plasma membrane is not homogenous and domains are detected. A domain is a <lb/>membrane area, organised or not, whose lipid and/or protein composition differs from the <lb/>bulk membrane composition. For example, rafts are membrane domains that resist detergent <lb/>solubilization due to a special lipid/protein local composition. Lipid rafts were recently <lb/>characterised in Tobacco and Arabidopsis [55, 56]. Rafts are enriched in sterols and <lb/>sphingolipids and recruit a pool of specific proteins. Some other plant plasma membrane <lb/>domains have been characterized by their divergent protein composition and their position in <lb/>the cell: for example, in vascular cells, the auxin efflux transporter, PIN1, is localised in the <lb/>basal pole whereas the auxin influx transporter is found at the apical pole [46]. <lb/>The plasma membrane derives from uncharacterized Golgi vesicles. Lipid trafficking from the <lb/>Golgi to the plasma membrane occurs partly through these transport vesicles. The nature of <lb/>the vesicles is not yet identified although the following data support their existence. It has <lb/>been recently shown by live imaging of animal cells that transport vesicles from the Golgi <lb/>directly fuse with the plasma membrane [57]. Consistently, in plant, monensin, a secretory <lb/>pathway inhibitor, was shown to cause accumulation of part of the plasma membrane lipids in <lb/>the Golgi [1]. This pathway is actin dependent [45]. The addressing of proteins to the plasma <lb/>membrane seems to be controlled by the size and number of their hydrophobic domains [58]. <lb/>Thus, preferential interactions between lipids and transmembrane proteins were proposed to <lb/>manage protein sorting in the Golgi. In the future, it will be important to define the precise <lb/>origins and fusion sites of vesicles in order to understand the general formation of the plasma <lb/>membrane and the genesis of particular microdomains. Concerning rafts, one can suggest that, <lb/>
			
			<page>17 <lb/></page>
			
			according to animal cell data, domains may be organized in the Golgi and subsequently <lb/>exported to the plasma membrane [59]. <lb/>PIP 2 plays a role in the transport to the plasma membrane [60]. A PI transfer protein (PI-TP) <lb/>was identified in Arabidopsis and was shown to be a SEC14 homolog allowing the <lb/>complementation of a yeast sec14 mutant. In yeast, the inactivation of SEC14 impedes protein <lb/>secretion at the Golgi level. Interestingly, mutations in genes involved in the nucleotidic <lb/>pathway for PC biosynthesis abolish the effect of the sec14 mutation. In fact, SEC14 binds <lb/>both PC and PI and is a phosphocholine:CTP cytidylyltransferase inhibitor. It has been <lb/>proposed that SEC14 was a &quot; sensor &quot; of the plasma membrane lipid composition and could <lb/>inhibit PC biosynthesis when PC is abundant. This hypothetical role has not been confirmed <lb/> in planta [61]. Another PI-TP, AtSfh1p, belonging to the SEC14-nodulin family, was <lb/>identified in Arabidopsis. AtSfh1p is likely a regulator of the intracellular trafficking in root <lb/>hair by moving PIP 2 to the areas of the plasma membrane where vesicles fuse [62]. <lb/>By using monensin, Moreau et al. [1] tried to determine which lipid classes were transferred <lb/>to plant plasma membrane via the vesicular pathway. When monensin was added, these <lb/>authors observed in the plasma membrane the absence of PS, whereas the PI content was not <lb/>affected, and PE and PC amounts were half reduced. Based on these results, they concluded <lb/>that PS was exclusively transferred to the plasma membrane by vesicular pathway, PE and PC <lb/>were partly transferred by the vesicular pathway and PI was transferred by another process. <lb/>However Vincent et al. [63] observed that PS could also be synthesised directly in the plasma <lb/>membrane by polar head exchange. The balance between PS from Golgi vesicles and PS <lb/>generated by plasma membrane polar head exchange is unknown. <lb/> 4.1.4. Endocytosis and exocytosis <lb/> Plant endocytosis was questioned for long due to the turgid pressure and cell wall rigidity that <lb/>were supposed to prevent its existence. It is now well established that brefeldin A, an <lb/>
			
			<page>18 <lb/></page>
			
			exocytosis inhibitor, induces the internalisation of plasma membrane proteins, like the auxin-<lb/>carrier proteins AUX1 and PIN1, in a compartment called the endosome [45]. The distinction <lb/>between the endosome and prevacuolar compartments is not clear [64] because the fate of <lb/>internalised proteins divides in two parts: a part is recycled to the plasma membrane and the <lb/>other destined for the lytic vacuole. <lb/>Plant endocytosis implies at least two pathways: one is catalysed by clathrin-coated vesicles <lb/>that are transported by the actin cytoskeleton and moved by myosin VIII [45]; another one, <lb/>like the PIN endocytosis, depends on presence of sterols and of rafts [65]. In plants, no <lb/>receptor for addressing sequences to clathrin-coated vesicles has been identified despite <lb/>pointed homologies with some yeast receptors in the Arabidopsis genome [64]. However, two <lb/>subunits of the AP2 adaptatin complex, 񮽙C-adaptatin and AP180, were characterised in <lb/> Arabidopsis. AP180 catalyses clathrin assembly and񮽙񮽙C-adaptatin binds to AP180 and to a <lb/>dynamin like protein, probably ADL1 [66]. <lb/>The transfer from endosome/prevacuolar compartment to lytic vacuole is not characterized <lb/>besides a PI-3P control [46]. In contrast, the mechanism of vesicle recycling to plasma <lb/>membrane is partially characterized. The recycling machinery is actin-dependent and involves <lb/>Arf1, GNOM and PIN since brefeldin A, an exocytosis inhibitor, aborts the recycling of the <lb/>PIN auxin efflux facilitators to plasma membrane by inhibiting GNOM activity, i.e. GDP-<lb/>GTP exchange on Arf1, a small GTPase. This pathway is involved in the transfer of other <lb/>proteins than PIN such as AUX1 and some ATPases. <lb/>To conclude, very few studies concern glycerolipid trafficking through the secretory pathway. <lb/>Altogether data indicate the following general features: a) ER-Golgi trafficking has no <lb/>glycerolipid specificity whereas b) there is some selectivity concerning trafficking to the <lb/>plasma membrane from the Golgi apparatus. In this case, PS is mainly transported by vesicles, <lb/>
			
			<page>19 <lb/></page>
			
			PE and PC are partially transferred by this route and PI is moved by another method <lb/>(independent of the secretory pathway). Moreover, PI has an additional role in the regulation <lb/>of trafficking. Different phosphorylated forms of PI favour sorting of vesicles to distinct <lb/>compartments: PI-4P to storage vacuole, PI-3P to lytic vacuole and PIP 2 to plasma membrane. <lb/> 4.2. Transfer from the plastid envelope to the thylakoids <lb/> Glycerolipids i.e. MGDG, DGDG, PG and sulfolipid, synthesised in the plastid envelope [for <lb/>review see 2] are selectively transported from the envelope inner membrane to the thylakoids <lb/>[67, 25]. Our knowledge about this lipid transfer mechanism is very imprecise but there are <lb/>some indications supporting vesicular trafficking. Vesicle budding from the plastid envelope <lb/>inner membrane was observed by electronic microscopy [68, 69]. An Arabidopsis thaliana <lb/> thylakoid formation 1 (Thf 1) gene product was shown to control a step required for the <lb/>organization of vesicles derived from the envelope inner membrane into mature thylakoid <lb/>stacks [70]. Bioinformatic studies suggest that a system similar to the COPII vesicular <lb/>pathway is present in plastids [71]. The plastid vesicular pathway is dependent on ATP and <lb/>stromal proteins [72, 73]. Some stromal proteins involved in this trafficking have been <lb/>identified: a NSF homolog protein [74], a dynamin-like protein [75] and a vesicle inducing <lb/>protein (VIPP1) [76]. In vipp1 (a VIPP -Vesicle Inducing Protein in Plastid 1-deleted mutant), <lb/>thylakoid membrane formation and chloroplast vesicle transport are abolished, indicating that <lb/>VIPP1 is essential for thylakoid maintenance by a vesicular pathway. Recent data demonstrate <lb/>that VIPP1 organizes in a high molecular mass complex closely associated with the inner <lb/>envelope membrane and suggest that the C-terminus of the protein protrudes from the <lb/>complex into the stroma of chloroplasts possibly for interaction with some other proteins <lb/>[77]. Accordingly, soluble VIPP1 interacts with a HSP70B/CDJ2 chaperone pair [78]. By <lb/>analogy with the action of the auxilin/Hsc70 chaperone pair with clathrin on clathrin-coated <lb/>
			
			<page>20 <lb/></page>
			
			vesicles, HSP70B/CDJ2 might disassemble and/or assemble VIPP1 oligomers to recycle the <lb/>system for another turn of vesicle formation/transport [78]. <lb/> 5. Transfer by membrane contact <lb/> Whereas vesicular pathways are involved in the lipid provisioning for thylakoids and <lb/>organelles of the secretory pathway, this process does not provide every necessary lipid for <lb/>the plasma membrane. In addition, the secretory pathway is apparently not involved in the <lb/>important lipid transfer from ER to plastids and from ER to mitochondria since no isolated <lb/>vesicle has been clearly detected between ER and these semi autonomous organelles. Another <lb/>type of lipid transfer has been proposed involving membrane contact between two organelles <lb/>[79]. By contrast with vesicular trafficking, transfer by contact does not involve a transfer of a <lb/>portion of a bilayer as such but a selective transfer of some components of the membrane. In <lb/>plants, some indications of a lipid transfer by membrane contact between plastid envelope and <lb/>mitochondria were recently reported [9]. <lb/> 5.1. Membrane contact sites <lb/> In a topological plan at the cell scale, ER has many specialised sub domains that interact with <lb/>other organelles such as mitochondria, vacuole, plasma membrane or plastids [44] (Figure 4). <lb/>At a membrane contact site, membranes are typically separated by less than 10 nm [10]. The <lb/>best-characterized membrane contact site was described in yeast between ER and <lb/>mitochondria [19] during a study of the mechanisms for PE biosynthesis in mitochondria [80]. <lb/>PE biosynthesis in mitochondria occurs by decarboxylation of PS and is dependent on PS <lb/>supply by ER [79]. Specific ER domains called MAM (Mitochondria Associated Membranes) <lb/>are enriched in PS synthase, supporting PS supply to mitochondria. The PS transfer from ER <lb/>to the mitochondria outer membrane is not completely characterized. Data indicate ATP <lb/>dependence of PS transfer, Ca2+ and Mg2+ stimulation, participation of a S100B protein <lb/>
			
			<page>21 <lb/></page>
			
			(Ca2+-modulated protein of the EF-hand type) that binds calcium and can interact with <lb/>annexin, and existence of a regulatory system involving a SCF (Skp1/Cul1/F-box protein) <lb/>ubiquitin ligase [19]. PS is finally transported to the mitochondria inner membrane by an <lb/>unknown mechanism, maybe going through contact sites between the inner and outer <lb/>membranes of mitochondria [81]. PS is decarboxylated in the mitochondria inner membrane <lb/>to form PE before a retro-transfer to ER probably going also through MAM [79]. Plants are <lb/>known to synthesize ethanolamine moieties of PE mainly by decarboxylation of free serine, <lb/>but there is also some evidence for PS decarboxylation, with both mitochondrial and <lb/>extramitochondrial PS decarboxylases [82, 83]. It is very likely that, in plants, the same kind <lb/>of PS transfer through MAM occurs for synthesis of some part of the mitochondrial PE. In <lb/>addition, MAM are also possibly involved in transfer of other mitochondrial phospholipids <lb/>synthesized in ER such as PC and PE. <lb/>Concerning transfer from ER to plasma membranes, it is believed, based on yeast studies, that <lb/>PE is transferred by a similar kind of system involving PAM (Plasma membrane Associated <lb/>Membrane) domains [10]. In plant, PAM-plasma membrane interactions contain actin <lb/>cytoskeleton elements and are sensitive to cell wall digestion [84]. <lb/>Finally, similar interactions by membrane contacts were observed between ER and vacuoles. <lb/>The ER anchoring to vacuole or to plasma membrane may serve as semi-immobile platforms <lb/>to which actin filaments attach to drive endoplasmic streaming [44]. These contact sites <lb/>possibly participate in the monensin insensitive transfer of PE, PC and PI, previously <lb/>described, with the involvement of LTPs (see below). <lb/>By analogy with MAM, PLAM (PLastid Associated Membrane) are supposed to be present at <lb/>the periphery of the chloroplast [85]. PLAM could contribute to the transfer of eukaryotic <lb/>DAG backbone from ER to plastids as described above. They could also facilitate the transfer <lb/>
			
			<page>22 <lb/></page>
			
			of PC from the ER to the outer membrane of the chloroplast envelope (Figure 2). Actually, <lb/>partial hydrolysis of PC to LysoPC in the ER was proposed to favour PC transfer between ER <lb/>and chloroplast since amphiphilic lysoPC can move easily through the cytosol [86]. In support <lb/>to this hypothesis, a lysoPC acyltransferase activity was detected in the chloroplast envelope <lb/>[86]. <lb/>Plant organelles are mobile inside the cell. Therefore, they can create membrane contact sites <lb/>adapted to physiological need. Each organelle has its own mechanism for location within the <lb/>cell and all organelle positions are coordinated in order to let each organelle fulfil its function <lb/>[87]. These movements are mainly actin-dependent in vegetative cells and this mobility <lb/>supports formation of organelle contact sites. <lb/>Plastids produce also very dynamic tubular structures called stromules that are able to interact <lb/>with other plastids and even with other type of organelles (Figure 4). Stromules are highly <lb/>dynamic structures involving both membranes of the plastid envelope and containing stroma <lb/>[for review, see 88]. In different tissues of tobacco and Arabidopsis, stromules interact with <lb/>the nucleus, the plasma membrane and mitochondria. They possibly support transfers such as <lb/>DAG, PC or DGDG transfers, although this role of stromules has never been demonstrated <lb/>[89, 90]. Other plastid envelope structures have been visualised to resemble myelin. These <lb/>structures were proposed to favour transfer of substances from plastid to vacuoles [91]. <lb/> 5.2. Lipid transfer protein or LTP <lb/> Lipid-transfer proteins that shuttle across cytosolic gaps mediate the trafficking of particular <lb/>lipids between organelles [10]. These proteins have to target both donor and acceptor <lb/>membranes and, indeed, some LTP have been localized at membrane contact sites where two <lb/>membranes were in close proximity [92]. For instance, LTPs of the Osh multigenic family <lb/>(Osh1, 2 and 3) were localised at reticulum contact sites in yeast. Osh LTPs belong to the <lb/>
			
			<page>23 <lb/></page>
			
			oxysterol binding protein (OSBP) family and are presumably involved in the movement of <lb/>sterol among cellular compartments, as was recently demonstrated for Osh4p [93]. In <lb/> Arabidopsis, twelve homologs of OSBP were identified but none has been studied yet (Table <lb/>2). Some LTPs have two targeting domains, one for the lipid donor membrane and the other <lb/>for the lipid receptor membrane. Consequently, LTPs can either move from one membrane to <lb/>another or bind to both membranes at the same time [10]. Holthuis and Levine pointed that <lb/>simultaneous binding to both membranes should promote lipid transport. Since the absence of <lb/>membrane fusion is a characteristic of membrane contact sites, one can question which <lb/>proteins are involved for the stabilisation of the membrane contact sites and whether LTP may <lb/>contribute to such stabilization. <lb/>To date, only one protein &quot; bridge &quot; between two organelles has been characterized between <lb/>the nucleus and the vacuole in yeast [94]. This &quot; bridge &quot; contains one nuclear envelope outer <lb/>membrane protein (Nvj1p) that docks to a vacuole surface protein (Vac8p). This binding <lb/>supports the formation of membrane contact sites between these two organelles without <lb/>membrane fusion. <lb/>Other LTP families were characterised without any information concerning their possible <lb/>localization to membrane contact sites. StART (Steroidogenic-Acute-Response protein related <lb/>lipid Transfer protein) proteins have a conserved domain around 200 amino acids involved in <lb/>lipid or sterol binding. A protein of the StART family, CERT (CEramide Related Transfer <lb/>protein), was recently characterised in mammalian cells [95]. CERT has a reticulum and a <lb/>Golgi binding domain and transfers ceramide from the reticulum to the Golgi. <lb/>Thirty-five proteins containing StART domains were identified in Arabidopsis. No CERT <lb/>close homolog was found in plants, but six proteins are homologues to StARD2, a PC-binding <lb/>protein [96]. The in silico studies of StARD2 homolog genes suggest that their products are <lb/>
			
			<page>24 <lb/></page>
			
			addressed either to mitochondria, or to plastids or to the secretory pathway (Table 2). These <lb/>proteins are possible candidates for the vesicular independent trafficking of PC, the eukaryotic <lb/>DAG backbone or of the minus Pi-induced mitochondrial DGDG. <lb/>The GLTP (GLycolipid Transfer Protein) family includes proteins involved mainly in <lb/>glycosphingolipid transfer; this family contains four genes in the Arabidopsis genome (Table <lb/>2). The Arabidopsis ACD11 protein is involved in the cell death mechanism and, by contrast <lb/>with the mammalian protein, it transfers only sphingosine [97]. No evidence was found of the <lb/>GLTP involvement in galactolipid transfer in plants but because of some similarities of <lb/>galactocerebroside to the glycosylglycerides, this hypothesis remains possible. <lb/>In plants, some PI-TPs are also present. SEC14 and AtSfh1, previously described, are some <lb/>examples. There are probably other PI-TP types although not yet known [62] (Table 2). <lb/>Finally, a SCP2 (Sterol Carrier Protein 2) was identified in Arabidopsis, transferring sterols as <lb/>well as phospholipids (Table 2). SCP2 is involved in the lipid transfer to the peroxysome for <lb/>the lipid catabolism [98]. <lb/>In plants, a large family of small soluble LTPs has been very well characterised genetically <lb/>and structurally [for reviews, see 99, 100]. The proteins transfer lipids in vitro between two <lb/>membranes and have no specificity for their lipid substrate. Sixty-seven genes were identified <lb/>in Arabidopsis (Table 2), among which most of them have a secretory peptide, indicating that <lb/>these proteins are excreted. The biological role of these proteins is unknown. They seem to be <lb/>involved in embryogenesis, cell wall formation and pathogen resistance [101]. <lb/> 6. Conclusion <lb/> Although requiring fatty acid delivery from the chloroplast, the plant ER is considered as a <lb/>lipid autonomous organelle because most of the phospholipid biosynthesis occurs there. The <lb/>nucleus and the Golgi are connected to the reticulum without any glycerolipid selection either <lb/>
			
			<page>25 <lb/></page>
			
			by membrane continuity or by dynamic vesicle exchanges. Vacuoles have vesicular <lb/>connection to the ER and the plasma membrane via the prevacuolar compartment but nothing <lb/>is known about the lipid delivery. More information is available concerning the lipids in the <lb/>plasma membrane. In particular, PS and a part of PE and PC are known to derive from the <lb/>Golgi by vesicular pathway. PI and part of PE and PC may come from the ER through PAM <lb/>and the plasma membrane DGDG, induced upon phosphate deprivation, could derive from <lb/>plastids either via direct contact with plastids possibly involving stromules, or via the ER. <lb/>Semi-autonomous organelles such as mitochondria and plastids are not connected to the ER <lb/>via vesicles. Lipid supply to mitochondria seems to occur exclusively through membrane <lb/>contact sites. Besides the DPG that is synthesised de novo in mitochondria, phospholipids are <lb/>transported from ER via MAM and, under phosphate deprivation, DGDG arrives through the <lb/>plastid envelope-mitochondria contact sites. Plastids are relatively independent for their lipid <lb/>synthesis due to the several lipid synthetic activities present in the envelope, but they need a <lb/>supply of a diacylglycerol source from the ER for formation of their eukaryotic glycerolipids. <lb/>This transfer is likely achieved via PLAM through a direct transfer of DAG molecules. <lb/>However phosphatidate derived from reticulum PC plays also some role in plastid envelope <lb/>galactolipid synthesis and the ABC protein TGD1 contributes to its transport to the inner <lb/>envelope membrane. Contact sites between the two envelope membranes may be involved in <lb/>the transfer since there is an intricate contribution of enzymatic activities of either the outer <lb/>envelope membrane or the inner envelope membrane (for instance, for the synthesis of <lb/>DGDG). In addition, plastids cannot achieve PC synthesis and need to import PC or LysoPC <lb/>from the ER. Inside chloroplasts, MGDG, DGDG, PG and sulfolipid are transferred from the <lb/>inner envelope membrane to the thylakoids by a vesicular transport that involves the VIPP1 <lb/>protein. <lb/>
			
			<page>26 <lb/></page>
			
			Altogether, the building of each type of membranes in plant cells requires an intricate <lb/>relationship between lipid synthesis and lipid transfer. Nothing is known whether the final <lb/>organisation of membranes is dependent or not on an original membrane pattern. Recent <lb/>progress concerns lipid transfers but the molecular mechanisms of the transfer are still very <lb/>elusive. Although some proteins have been identified, many candidates for lipid transfer <lb/>proteins remain to be identified. One expects that analysis of gene expression under <lb/>conditions such as phosphate deprivation which can affect lipid distribution should provide <lb/>new candidate proteins for these transfers and their regulation. Since all lipid trafficking <lb/>occurs in highly dynamic cells with mobile organelles, it is likely that cytoskeleton proteins <lb/>and molecular motors are essential and closely related to the transport. An important point <lb/>will be to understand how the lipid to be transferred are selected and when they are selected <lb/>related to the transfer. Organisation of lipid domains in membranes is likely to be important <lb/>but selection is expected to be also dependent on affinity of lipid transfer proteins for specific <lb/>lipids. Finally, dissection of these mechanisms of transfer will be an important challenge for <lb/>the future. <lb/> 
			</body>
			
			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements: <lb/> We thank Jacques Joyard and Roland Douce for their reading of our manuscript and <lb/>constructive criticism. We acknowledge Barbara Baldan (University of Padova, Italy) for the <lb/>electron micrograph presented in figure 4. <lb/></div>
			
			<listBibl>References <lb/> [1] Moreau P., Bessoule J.-J., Mongrand S., Testet E., Vincent P., Cassagne C. Lipid <lb/>trafficking in plant cells. Prog Lipid Res 1998;37:371-91. <lb/>[2] Block M.A., Maréchal E., Joyard J. Role of the plastid envelope in the biogenesis of <lb/>chloroplast lipids. In: Aro M., Andersson B., editors. Advances in Photosynthesis and <lb/>Respiration -Regulation of Photosynthesis. Dordrecht: Kluwer Academic, 2001;11:195-218. <lb/>
			
			<page>27 <lb/></page>
			
			[3] Hartel H., Essigmann B., Lokstein H., Hoffmann-Benning S., Peters-Kottig M., Benning <lb/>C. The phospholipid-deficient pho1 mutant of Arabidopsis thaliana is affected in the <lb/>organization, but not in the light acclimation, of the thylakoid membrane. Biochim Biophys <lb/>Acta 1998;1415:205-18. <lb/>[4] Hartel H., Dormann P., Benning C. DGD1-independent biosynthesis of extraplastidic <lb/>galactolipids after phosphate deprivation in Arabidopsis. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A <lb/>2000;97:10649-54. <lb/>[5] Klaus D., Hartel H., Fitzpatrick L.M., Froehlich J.E., Hubert J., Benning C., Dormann P. <lb/>Digalactosyldiacylglycerol synthesis in chloroplasts of the Arabidopsis dgd1 mutant. Plant <lb/>Physiol 2002;128:885-95. <lb/>[6] Jouhet J., Maréchal E., Bligny R., Joyard J., Block M.A. Transient increase of <lb/>phosphatidylcholine in plant cells in response to phosphate deprivation. FEBS Lett <lb/>2003;544:63-8. <lb/>[7] Andersson M.X., Stridh M.H., Larsson K.E., Liljenberg C., Sandelius A.S. Phosphate-<lb/>deficient oat replaces a major portion of the plasma membrane phospholipids with the <lb/>galactolipid digalactosyldiacylglycerol. FEBS Lett 2003;537:128-32. <lb/>[8] Andersson M.X., Larsson K.E., Tjellstrom H., Liljenberg C., Sandelius A.S. The plasma <lb/>membrane and the tonoplast as major targets for phospholipid-to-glycolipid replacement and <lb/>stimulation of phospholipases in the plasma membrane. J Biol Chem 2005;280:27578-86. <lb/>[9] Jouhet J., Maréchal E., Baldan B., Bligny R., Joyard J., Block M.A. Phosphate deprivation <lb/>induces transfer of DGDG galactolipid from chloroplast to mitochondria. J Cell Biol <lb/>2004;167:863-74. <lb/>[10] Holthuis J.C.M, Levine T.P. . Lipid traffic: floppy drives and a superhighway. Nat Rev <lb/>Mol Cell Biol 2005;6:209-20. <lb/>
			
			<page>28 <lb/></page>
			
			[11] Vaz W.L.C., Goodsaid-Zalduondo F., Jacobson K. Lateral diffusion of lipids and <lb/>proteins in bilayer membranes. FEBS Lett 1984;174:199-207. <lb/>[12] Bai J., Pagano R.E. Measurement of spontaneous transfer and transbilayer movement of <lb/>BODIPY-labeled lipids in lipid vesicles. Biochemistry 1997;36:8840-8. <lb/>[13] McLean L.R., Phillips M.C. Kinetics of phosphatidylcholine and <lb/>lysophosphatidylcholine exchange between unilamellar vesicles. Biochemistry 1984;23:4624-<lb/>30. <lb/>[14] Pomorski T., Holthuis J.C., Herrmann A., van Meer G. Tracking down lipid flippases <lb/>and their biological functions. J Cell Sci 2004;117:805-13. <lb/>[15] Kol M.A., de Kruijff B., de Kroon A.I. Phospholipid flip-flop in biogenic membranes: <lb/>what is needed to connect opposite sides. Semin Cell Dev Biol 2002;13:163-70. <lb/>[16] Seigneuret M., Devaux P.F. ATP-dependent asymmetric distribution of spin-labeled <lb/>phospholipids in the erythrocyte membrane: relation to shape changes. Proc Natl Acad Sci U <lb/>S A 1984 ;81:3751-5. <lb/>[17] Bell R.M., Ballas L.M., Coleman R.A. Lipid topogenesis. J Lipid Res 1981;22:391-403. <lb/>[18] Kol M.A., van Laak A.N., Rijkers D.T., Killian J.A., de Kroon A.I., de Kruijff B. <lb/>Phospholipid flop induced by transmembrane peptides in model membranes is modulated by <lb/>lipid composition. Biochemistry 2003;42:231-7. <lb/>[19] Voelker D.R. New perspectives on the regulation of intermembrane glycerophospholipid <lb/>traffic. J Lipid Res 2003;44:441-9. <lb/>[20] Helenius J., Ng D.T., Marolda C.L., Walter P., Valvano M.A., Aebi M. Translocation of <lb/>lipid-linked oligosaccharides across the ER membrane requires Rft1 protein. Nature <lb/>2002;415:447-50. <lb/>
			
			<page>29 <lb/></page>
			
			[21] Zhou Q., Zhao J., Stout J.G., Luhm R.A., Wiedmer T., Sims P.J. Molecular cloning of <lb/>human plasma membrane phospholipid scramblase. A protein mediating transbilayer <lb/>movement of plasma membrane phospholipids. J Biol Chem 1997;272:18240-4. <lb/>[22] O&apos;Brien I.E.W., Reutelingsperger C.P.M., Holdaway K.M. Annexin-V and TUNEL use <lb/>in monitoring the progression of apoptosis in plants. Cytometry 1997;29:28–33. <lb/>[23] Rawyler A., Unitt M.D., Giroud C., Davies H., Mayor J.P., Harwood J.L., Siegenthaler <lb/>P.A. The transmembrane distribution of galactolipids in chloroplast thylakoids is universal in <lb/>a wide variety of temperate climate plants. Photosynthesis Research 1987;11:3-13. <lb/>[24] Tremolières A., Dainese P., Bassi R., Heterogenous lipid distribution among chlorophyll-<lb/>binding proteins of photosystem II in maize mesophyll chloroplasts 1994;221:721-30. <lb/>[25] Rawyler A., Meylan-Bettex M., Siegenthaler P.A. (Galacto) lipid export from envelope <lb/>to thylakoid membranes in intact chloroplasts. II. A general process with a key role for the <lb/>envelope in the establishment of lipid asymmetry in thylakoid membranes. Biochim Biophys <lb/>Acta 1995;1233:123-33. <lb/>[26] Dorne A.J., Joyard J., Block M.A., Douce R. Localization of phosphatidylcholine in <lb/>outer envelope membrane of spinach chloroplasts. J Cell Biol 1985;100:1690-7. <lb/>[27] Tavernier E., Pugin A. Lipid composition of the vacuolar membrane of Acer <lb/>pseudoplatanus cultured cells. Biochimie 1995;77:174-81. <lb/>[28] Tang X., Halleck M.S., Schlegel R.A., Williamson P. A subfamily of P-type ATPases <lb/>with aminophospholipid transporting activity. Science 1996;272:1495-7. <lb/>[29] Gomès E., Jakobsen M.K., Axelsen K.B., Geisler M., Palmgren M.G. Chilling tolerance <lb/>in Arabidopsis involves ALA1, a member of a new family of putative aminophospholipid <lb/>translocases. Plant Cell 2000;12:2441-54. <lb/>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			[30] Raggers R.J., Pomorski T., Holthuis J.C., Kalin N., van Meer G. Lipid traffic: the ABC <lb/>of transbilayer movement. Traffic 2000;1:226-34. <lb/>[31] Pohl A., Devaux P.F., Herrmann A. Function of prokaryotic and eukaryotic ABC <lb/>proteins in lipid transport. Biochim Biophys Acta 2005;1733:29-52. <lb/>[32] Sanchez-Fernandez R., Davies T.G., Coleman J.O., Rea P.A. The Arabidopsis thaliana <lb/>ABC protein superfamily, a complete inventory. J Biol Chem 2001;276:30231-44. <lb/>[33] Martinoia E., Klein M., Geisler M., Bovet L., Forestier C., Kolukisaoglu U., Muller-<lb/>Rober B., Schulz B. Multifunctionality of plant ABC transporters--more than just detoxifiers. <lb/>Planta 2002;214:345-55. <lb/>[34] Beisson F., Koo A.J., Ruuska S., Schwender J., Pollard M., Thelen J.J., Paddock T., <lb/>Salas J.J., Savage L., Milcamps A., Mhaske V.B., Cho Y., Ohlrogge J.B. Arabidopsis genes <lb/>involved in acyl lipid metabolism. A 2003 census of the candidates, a study of the distribution <lb/>of expressed sequence tags in organs, and a web-based database. Plant Physiol 2003;132:681-<lb/>97. <lb/>[35] Koo A.J.K., Ohlrogge J.B., Pollard M. On the export of fatty acids from the chloroplast. <lb/>Journal of Biological Chemistry. J Biol Chem 2004;279:16101-10. <lb/>[36] Xu C.C., Fan J.L., Riekhof W., Froehlich J.E., Benning C. A permease-like protein <lb/>involved in ER to thylakoid lipid transfer in Arabidopsis. Embo J 2003;22:2370-9. <lb/>[37] Xu C., Fan J., Froehlich J.E., Awai K., Benning C. Mutation of the TGD1 chloroplast <lb/>envelope protein affects phosphatidate metabolism in Arabidopsis. Plant Cell 2005;17:3094-<lb/>110. <lb/>[38] Heinz E. Enzymatic reactions in galactolipid biosynthesis. In: Tevini M., Lichtenthaler <lb/>H.K., editors. Lipids and Lipid Polymers. Berlin: Springer Verlag 1977;102-20. <lb/>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			[39] Slack C.R., Roughan P.G., Balasingham N. Labelling studies in vivo on the metabolism <lb/>of the acyl and glycerol moieties of the glycerolipids in the developing maize leaf. Biochem J <lb/>1977;162:289-96. <lb/>[40] Okuley J., Lightner J., Feldmann K., Yadav N., Lark E., Browse J. Arabidopsis FAD2 <lb/>gene encodes the enzyme that is essential for polyunsaturated lipid synthesis. Plant Cell <lb/>1994;6:147-58. <lb/>[41] Nakamura Y., Awai K., Masuda T., Yoshioka Y., Takamiya K., Ohta H. A novel <lb/>phosphatidylcholine-hydrolyzing phospholipase C induced by phosphate starvation in <lb/>Arabidopsis. J Biol Chem 2005;280:7469-76. <lb/>[42] Misson J., Raghothama K.G., Jain A., Jouhet J., Block M.A., Bligny R., Ortet P., Creff <lb/>A., Somerville S., Rolland N., Doumas P., Nacry P., Herrerra-Estrella L., Nussaume L., <lb/>Thibaud M.C. A genome-wide transcriptional analysis using Arabidopsis thaliana Affymetrix <lb/>gene chips determined plant responses to phosphate deprivation. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A <lb/>2005;102:11934-9. <lb/>[43] Li M., Qin C., Welti R., Wang X. Double Knockouts of Phospholipases D{zeta}1 and <lb/>D{zeta}2 in Arabidopsis Affect Root Elongation during Phosphate-Limited Growth But Do <lb/>Not Affect Root Hair Patterning. Plant Physiol 2006;140:761-70. <lb/>[44] Staehelin L.A. The plant ER: a dynamic organelle composed of a large number of <lb/>discrete functional domains. Plant J 1997;11:1151-65. <lb/>[45] Samaj J., Baluska F., Voigt B., Schlicht M., Volkmann D., Menzel D. Endocytosis, actin <lb/>cytoskeleton, and signaling. Plant Physiol 2004;35:1150-61. <lb/>[46] Jürgens G. Membrane trafficking in plants. Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol 2004;20:481-504. <lb/>[47] Nebenfuhr A. Vesicle traffic in the endomembrane system: a tale of COPs, Rabs and <lb/>SNAREs. Curr Opin Plant Biol 2002;5:507-12. <lb/>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			[48] Hawes C. Cell biology of the plant Golgi apparatus. New Phytol 2005;165:29-44. <lb/>[49] Hawes C., Satiat-Jeunemaitre B. The plant Golgi apparatus--going with the flow. <lb/>Biochim Biophys Acta 2005;1744:466-80. <lb/>[50] Brandizzi F., Snapp E.L., Roberts A.G., Lippincott-Schwartz J., Hawes C. Membrane <lb/>protein transport between the endoplasmic reticulum and the Golgi in tobacco leaves is energy <lb/>dependent but cytoskeleton independent: evidence from selective photobleaching. Plant Cell <lb/>2002;14:1293-309. <lb/>[51] Matsuoka K., Bednarek S.Y. Protein transport within the plant cell endomembrane <lb/>system: an update. Curr Opin Plant Biol 1998;1:463-9. <lb/>[52] Matsuoka K., Bassham D.C., Raikhel N.V., Nakamura K. Different sensitivity to <lb/>wortmannin of two vacuolar sorting signals indicates the presence of distinct sorting <lb/>machineries in tobacco cells. J Cell Biol 1995;130:1307-18. <lb/>[53] Kim D.H., Eu Y.J., Yoo C.M., Kim Y.W., Pih K.T., Jin J.B., Kim S.J., Stenmark H., <lb/>Hwang I. Trafficking of phosphatidylinositol 3-phosphate from the trans-Golgi network to the <lb/>lumen of the central vacuole in plant cells. Plant Cell 2001;13:287-301. <lb/>[54] Lee S.H., Jin J.B., Song J., Min M.K., Park D.S., Kim Y.W., Hwang I. The <lb/>intermolecular interaction between the PH domain and the C-terminal domain of Arabidopsis <lb/>dynamin-like 6 determines lipid binding specificity. J Biol Chem 2002;277:31842-9. <lb/>[55] Mongrand S., Morel J., Laroche J., Claverol S., Carde J.P., Hartmann M.A., Bonneu M., <lb/>Simon-Plas F., Lessire R., Bessoule J.J. Lipid rafts in higher plant cells: purification and <lb/>characterization of Triton X-100-insoluble microdomains from tobacco plasma membrane. J <lb/>Biol Chem 2004;279:36277-86. <lb/>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			[56] Borner G.H., Sherrier D.J., Weimar T., Michaelson L.V., Hawkins N.D., Macaskill A., <lb/>Napier J.A., Beale M.H., Lilley K.S., Dupree P. Analysis of detergent-resistant membranes in <lb/>Arabidopsis. Evidence for plasma membrane lipid rafts. Plant Physiol 2005;137:104-16. <lb/>[57] Keller P., Toomre D., Diaz E., White J., Simons K. Multicolour imaging of post-Golgi <lb/>sorting and trafficking in live cells. Nat Cell Biol 2001;3:140-9. <lb/>[58] Bretscher M.S., Munro S. Cholesterol and the Golgi apparatus. Science 1993;261:1280-<lb/>1. <lb/>[59] Ikonen E. Roles of lipid rafts in membrane transport. Curr Opin Cell Biol 2001;13:470-7. <lb/>[60] Meijer H.J., Munnik T. Phospholipid-based signaling in plants. Annu Rev Plant Biol <lb/>2003;54:265-306. <lb/>[61] Jouannic N., Lepetit M., Vergnolle C., Cantrel C., Gardies A.M., Kader J.C., Arondel V. <lb/>Isolation of a cDNA from Arabidopsis thaliana that complements the sec14 mutant of yeast. <lb/>Eur J Biochem 1998;258:402-10. <lb/>[62] Vincent P., Chua M., Nogue F., Fairbrother A., Mekeel H., Xu Y., Allen N., Bibikova <lb/>T.N., Gilroy S., Bankaitis V.A. A Sec14p-nodulin domain phosphatidylinositol transfer <lb/>protein polarizes membrane growth of Arabidopsis thaliana root hairs. J Cell Biol <lb/>2005;168:801-12. <lb/>[63] Vincent P., Maneta-Peyret L., Sturbois-Balcerzak B., Duvert M., Cassagne C., Moreau P. <lb/>One of the origins of plasma membrane phosphatidylserine in plant cells is a local synthesis <lb/>by a serine exchange activity. FEBS Lett 1999;464:80-4. <lb/>[64] Holstein S. Clathrin and plant endocytosis. Traffic 2002;3:614-20. <lb/>[65] Murphy A.S., Bandyopadhyay A., Holstein S.E., Peer W.A. Endocytotic cycling of PM <lb/>proteins. Annu Rev Plant Biol 2005;56:221-51. <lb/>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			[66] Barth M., Holstein S.E. Identification and functional characterization of Arabidopsis <lb/>AP180, a binding partner of plant alphaC-adaptin. J Cell Sci. 2004;117:2051-62. <lb/>[67] Joyard J., Douce R., Siebertz H.P., Heinz E. Distribution of radioactive lipids between <lb/>envelopes and thylakoids from chloroplasts labelled in vivo. Eur J Biochem 1980;108:171-<lb/>176. <lb/>[68] Carde J.P., Joyard J., Douce R. Electron microscopic studies of envelope membranes <lb/>from spinach plastids. Biol Cell 1982;44:315-24. <lb/>[69] Morré D.J., Seldén G., Sundqvist S., Sandelius A.S. Stromal low temperature <lb/>compartment derived from the inner membrane of the envelope. Plant Physiol 1991;97:1558-<lb/>67. <lb/>[70] Wang Q., Sullivan R.W., Kight A., Henry R.L., Huang J., Jones A.M., Korth K.L. <lb/>Deletion of the chloroplast-localized Thylakoid formation1 gene product in Arabidopsis leads <lb/>to deficient thylakoid formation and variegated leaves. Plant Physiol 2004;136: 3594-604. <lb/>[71] Andersson M.X., Sandelius A.S. A chloroplast-localized vesicular transport system: a <lb/>bio-informatics approach. BMC Genomics 2004;5:40. <lb/>[72] Morré D.J., Morre J.T., Morre S.R., Sundqvist C., Sandelius A.S. Chloroplast biogenesis. <lb/>Cell-free transfer of envelope monogalactosylglycerides to thylakoids. Biochim Biophys Acta <lb/>1991;1070:437-45. <lb/>[73] Räntfors M, Everstsson I., Kjellberg J.M., Sandelius A.S. Intraplastidial lipid trafficking: <lb/>Regulation of galactolipid release from isolated chloroplast envelope. Physiol Plant <lb/>2000;110:262-70. <lb/>[74] Hugueney P., Bouvier F., Badillo A., d&apos;Harlingue A., Kuntz M., Camara B. Identification <lb/>of a plastid protein involved in vesicle fusion and/or membrane protein translocation. Proc <lb/>Natl Acad Sci U S A 1995;92:5630-4. <lb/>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			[75] Park J.M., Cho J.H., Kang S.G., Jang H.J., Pih K.T., Piao H.L., Cho M.J., Hwang I. A <lb/>dynamin-like protein in Arabidopsis thaliana is involved in biogenesis of thylakoid <lb/>membranes. Embo J 1998;17:859-67. <lb/>[76] Kroll D., Meierhoff K., Bechtold N., Kinoshita M., Westphal S., Vothknecht U.C., Soll <lb/>J., Westhoff P. VIPP1, a nuclear gene of Arabidopsis thaliana essential for thylakoid <lb/>membrane formation. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 2001;98:4238-42. <lb/>[77] Aseeva E., Ossenbuhl F., Eichacker L.A., Wanner G., Soll J., Vothknecht U.C. Complex <lb/>formation of Vipp1 depends on its alpha-helical PspA-like domain. J Biol Chem <lb/>2004;279:35535-41. <lb/>[78] Liu C.M., Willmund F., Whitelegge J.P., Hawat S., Knapp B., Lodha M., Schroda M. J-<lb/>Domain Protein CDJ2 and HSP70B Are a Plastidic Chaperone Pair That Interacts with <lb/>Vesicle-Inducing Protein in Plastids 1. Mol Biol Cell 2005;16:1165-77. <lb/>[79] Voelker D.R. Interorganelle transport of aminoglycerophospholipids. Biochim Biophys <lb/>Acta. Biochim Biophys Acta. 2000;1486:97-107. <lb/>[80] Vance J.E. Newly made phosphatidylserine and phosphatidylethanolamine are <lb/>preferentially translocated between rat liver mitochondria and endoplasmic reticulum. J Biol <lb/>Chem 1991;266:89-97. <lb/>[81] Reichert A.S., Neupert W. Contact sites between the outer and inner membrane of <lb/>mitochondria – role in protein transport. Biochim Biophys Acta 2002;1592:41-9. <lb/>[82] Rontein D., Rhodes D., Hanson A.D. Evidence from engineering that decarboxylation of <lb/>free serine is the major source of ethanolamine moieties in plants. Plant Cell Physiol <lb/>2003;44:1185-91. <lb/>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			[83] Rontein D., Wu W.I., Voelker D.R., Hanson A.D. Mitochondrial phosphatidylserine <lb/>decarboxylase from higher plants. Functional complementation in yeast, localization in plants, <lb/>and overexpression in Arabidopsis. Plant Physiol 2003;132:1678-87. <lb/>[84] Kunst L., Samuels A.L. Biosynthesis and secretion of plant cuticular wax. Prog Lipid <lb/>Res 2003;42:51-80. <lb/>[85] Kjellberg J.M., Trimborn M., Anderson M., Sandelius A.S. Acyl-CoA dependent <lb/>acylation of phospholipids in the chloroplast envelope. Biochim Biophys Acta 2000, <lb/>1485:100-10. <lb/>[86] Bessoule J.J., Testet E., Cassagne C. Synthesis of phosphatidylcholine in the chloroplast <lb/>envelope after import of lysophosphatidylcholine from endoplasmic reticulum membranes. <lb/>Eur J Biochem 1995 ;228:490-7. <lb/>[87] Wada M., Suetsugu N. Plant organelle positioning. Curr Opin Plant Biol 2004;7:626-31. <lb/>[88] Natesan S.K., Sullivan J.A., Gray J.C. Stromules: a characteristic cell-specific feature of <lb/>plastid morphology. J Exp Bot 2005;56:787-97. <lb/>[89] Kwok E.Y., Hanson M.R. Plastids and stromules interact with the nucleus and cell <lb/>membrane in vascular plants. Plant Cell Rep 2004;23:188-95. <lb/>[90] Kwok E.Y., Hanson M.R. In vivo analysis of interactions between GFP-labeled <lb/>microfilaments and plastid stromules. BMC Plant Biol 2004;4: 2. <lb/>[91] Vaughn K.C., Duke S.O. Evaginations from the plastid envelope: a method for transfer <lb/>of substances from plastid to vacuole. Cytobios 1981;32:89-95. <lb/>[92] Loewen C.J., Roy A., Levine T.P. A conserved ER targeting motif in three families of <lb/>lipid binding proteins and in Opi1p binds VAP. Embo J 2003;22:2025-35. <lb/>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			[93] Raychaudhuri S., Im Y.J., Hurley J.H., Prinz W.A. Nonvesicular sterol movement from <lb/>plasma membrane to ER requires oxysterol-binding protein-related proteins and <lb/>phosphoinositides. J Cell Biol 2006;173:107-19. <lb/>[94] Pan X., Roberts P., Chen Y., Kvam E., Shulga N., Huang K., Lemmon S., Goldfarb D.S. <lb/>Nucleus-vacuole junctions in Saccharomyces cerevisiae are formed through the direct <lb/>interaction of Vac8p with Nvj1p. Mol Biol Cell 2000;11:2445-57. <lb/>[95] Hanada K., Kumagai K., Yasuda S., Miura Y., Kawano M., Fukasawa M., Nishijima M. <lb/>Molecular machinery for non-vesicular trafficking of ceramide. Nature 2003;426:803-9. <lb/>[96] Schrick K., Nguyen D., Karlowski W.M., Mayer K.F. START lipid/sterol-binding <lb/>domains are amplified in plants and are predominantly associated with homeodomain <lb/>transcription factors. Genome Biol 2004;5:R41. <lb/>[97] Brodersen P., Petersen M., Pike H.M., Olszak B., Skov S., Odum N., Jorgensen L.B., <lb/>Brown R.E., Mundy J. Knockout of Arabidopsis accelerated-cell-death11 encoding a <lb/>sphingosine transfer protein causes activation of programmed cell death and defense. Genes <lb/>Dev 2002;16:490-502. <lb/>[98] Edqvist J., Ronnberg E., Rosenquist S., Blomqvist K., Viitanen L., Salminen T.A., <lb/>Nylund M., Tuuf J., Mattjus P. Plants express a lipid transfer protein with high similarity to <lb/>mammalian sterol carrier protein-2. J Biol Chem 2004;279:53544-53. <lb/>[99] Kader J.C. Lipid-Transfer Proteins in Plants. Annu Rev Plant Physiol Plant Mol Biol <lb/>1996;47:627-54. <lb/>[100] Breiteneder H., Mills C. Nonspecific lipid-transfer proteins in plant foods and pollens: <lb/>an important allergen class. Curr Opin Allergy Clin Immunol 2005;5:275-9. <lb/>
			
			<page>38 <lb/></page>
			
			[101] Blein J.P., Coutos-Thevenot P., Marion D., Ponchet M. From elicitins to lipid-transfer <lb/>proteins: a new insight in cell signalling involved in plant defence mechanisms. Trends Plant <lb/>Sci 2002;7:293-6. <lb/>[102] Hartmann M.A., Benveniste P. Plant membrane sterols: isolation, identification and <lb/>biosynthesis. Methods Enzymol 1987;148:632-50. <lb/>[103] Tavernier E., Lê Quôc D., Lê Quôc K. Lipid composition of the vacuolar membrane of <lb/>Acer pseudoplatanus cultured cells. Biochim Biophys Acta 1993;1167:242-7. <lb/>[104] Bertho P., Moreau P., Morre D.J., Cassagne C. Monensin blocks the transfer of very <lb/>long chain fatty acid containing lipids to the plasma membrane of leek seedlings. Evidence for <lb/>lipid sorting based on fatty acyl chain length. Biochim Biophys Acta 1991;1070:127-34. <lb/>[105] Block M.A., Dorne A.J., Joyard J., Douce R. . 
			
			Preparation and characterization of <lb/>membrane fractions enriched in outer and inner envelope membranes from spinach <lb/>chloroplasts. II. Biochemical characterization. J Biol Chem 1983;258:13281-6. <lb/>[106] Douce R.. Mitochondria in higher plants: structure, function and biogenesis. New York: <lb/>Academic Press Inc., 1985;322. <lb/>[107] Emanuelsson O., Nielsen H., Brunak S., von Heijne G. Predicting subcellular <lb/>localization of proteins based on their N-terminal amino acid sequence. J Mol Biol <lb/>2000;300:1005-16. <lb/></listBibl> 
			
			<body>Table 1: Lipid composition of plant cell membranes according to [1]. Endomembrane <lb/>analyses are derived from [102], [103], and [104]. Plastid and mitochondria membrane <lb/>analyses were done respectively by [105] and [106]. <lb/>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			Table 2: Arabidopsis thaliana genes potentially involved in lipid trafficking. Protein <lb/>localization determined by TargetP [107] is indicated by P letter for plastid, M for <lb/>mitochondria and S for secretory peptide presence. Protein localizations reported between <lb/>brackets were obtained by biochemical experiments [62, 98]. TM: transmembrane domain <lb/>number. <lb/> LTP <lb/> Bound lipid Arabidopsis locus Protein <lb/>Evidence <lb/>TM Localization <lb/> Flippase <lb/> RFT1 <lb/>? <lb/>At5g07630 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>9 <lb/>-<lb/>scramblase <lb/>? <lb/>At2g04940 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>M <lb/>P-type ATPase <lb/>Aminophospholipid translocase <lb/> PS, PE <lb/>At5g04930 <lb/>ALA1 <lb/>Functional complementation <lb/>10 <lb/>-<lb/>Aminophospholipid translocase <lb/>? <lb/>At5g44240 <lb/>ALA2 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>9 <lb/>-<lb/>Aminophospholipid translocase <lb/>? <lb/>At1g59820 <lb/>ALA3 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>8 <lb/>M <lb/>Aminophospholipid translocase <lb/>? <lb/>At1g17500 <lb/>ALA4 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>10 <lb/>M <lb/>Aminophospholipid translocase <lb/>? <lb/>At1g72700 <lb/>ALA5 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>10 <lb/>M <lb/>Aminophospholipid translocase <lb/>? <lb/>At1g54280 <lb/>ALA6 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>10 <lb/>M <lb/>Aminophospholipid translocase <lb/>? <lb/>At3g13900 <lb/>ALA7 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>10 <lb/>M <lb/>Aminophospholipid translocase <lb/>? <lb/>At3g27870 <lb/>ALA8 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>10 <lb/>M <lb/>Aminophospholipid translocase <lb/>? <lb/>At1g68710 <lb/>ALA9 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>10 <lb/>M <lb/>Aminophospholipid translocase <lb/>? <lb/>At3g25610 <lb/>ALA10 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>10 <lb/>M <lb/>Aminophospholipid translocase <lb/>? <lb/>At1g13210 <lb/>ALA11 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>10 <lb/>M <lb/>ABC transporter supposed to be involved in lipid translocation <lb/>ABC acyl transporter <lb/>? <lb/>At1g54350 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>5 <lb/>P <lb/>ABC transporter <lb/>? <lb/>At1g19800 <lb/>TGD1 <lb/>EMS mutant characterization <lb/>6 <lb/>P <lb/>Oxysterol binding protein <lb/>Oxysterol binding protein <lb/>? <lb/>At1g13170 <lb/>0sh3 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>0 <lb/>P <lb/>Oxysterol binding protein <lb/>? <lb/>At2g31020 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>P <lb/>Oxysterol binding protein <lb/>? <lb/>At2g31030 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>Oxysterol binding protein <lb/>? <lb/>At3g09300 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>P <lb/>Oxysterol binding protein <lb/>? <lb/>At4g08180 <lb/>OSBP <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>Oxysterol binding protein <lb/>? <lb/>At4g12460 <lb/>Osh1 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>Oxysterol binding protein <lb/>? <lb/>At4g22540 <lb/>Osh2 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>Oxysterol binding protein <lb/>? <lb/>At4g25850 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>Oxysterol binding protein <lb/>? <lb/>At4g25860 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>Oxysterol binding protein <lb/>? <lb/>At5g02100 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>P <lb/>Oxysterol binding protein <lb/>? <lb/>At5g57240 <lb/>KES1 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>Membranes <lb/>PC <lb/>PE <lb/>PG <lb/>PI <lb/>PS <lb/>DPG <lb/>MGDG <lb/>DGDG <lb/>SQDG <lb/>Sterols <lb/>Glyco-<lb/>sphingolipides <lb/>Endomembranes <lb/>Reticulum <lb/>+Golgi <lb/>43-48 <lb/>23-26 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 -1 5 <lb/>Tonoplast <lb/>15-28 <lb/>15-28 <lb/>2 <lb/>5-9 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 4 -4 3 <lb/>1 2 -1 7 <lb/>Plasma <lb/>membrane <lb/>8-36 <lb/>9-32 <lb/>1-5 <lb/>1-6 <lb/>1-10 <lb/>5 -6 0 <lb/>6 -3 0 <lb/>Chloroplasts <lb/>Outer <lb/>membrane <lb/>32 <lb/>10 <lb/>5 <lb/>17 <lb/>30 <lb/>6 <lb/>Inner <lb/>membrane <lb/>9 <lb/>1 <lb/>55 <lb/>30 <lb/>5 <lb/>Thylakoids <lb/>7 <lb/>1 <lb/>58 <lb/>27 <lb/>7 <lb/>Mitochondria <lb/>Outer <lb/>membrane <lb/>52 <lb/>22 <lb/>3 <lb/>10 <lb/>1 3 <lb/>Inner <lb/>membrane <lb/>37 <lb/>33 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>11 <lb/>1 3 <lb/>

			<page> 40 <lb/></page>

			LTP <lb/> Bound lipid Arabidopsis locus Protein <lb/>Evidence <lb/>TM Localization <lb/> Oxysterol binding protein <lb/>? <lb/>At5g59240 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>StARD2 homolog proteins <lb/>PC transfer protein <lb/>PC <lb/>At1g55960 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>1 <lb/>P <lb/>PC transfer protein <lb/>PC <lb/>At1g64720 <lb/>CP5 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>1 <lb/>S <lb/>PC transfer protein <lb/>PC <lb/>At3g13062 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>1 <lb/>M <lb/>PC transfer protein <lb/>PC <lb/>At3g23080 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>1 <lb/>-<lb/>PC transfer protein <lb/>PC <lb/>At4g14500 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>2 <lb/>-<lb/>PC transfer protein <lb/>PC <lb/>At5g54170 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>2 <lb/>S <lb/>CERT <lb/>ceramide <lb/>? <lb/>Glycolipid transfer protein <lb/>GLTP <lb/>sphingosine <lb/>At2g34690 <lb/>ACD11 <lb/>T-DNA mutant characterization, <lb/>functional complementation and <lb/> in vitro expression <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>GLTP <lb/>? <lb/>At4g39670 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>GLTP <lb/>? <lb/>At2g33470 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>GLTP <lb/>? <lb/>At3g21260 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>PITP <lb/>Type SEC14 <lb/>PI/PC <lb/>At1g55840 <lb/>SEC14 <lb/>Functional complementation <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>Type SEC14 <lb/>PI <lb/>At4g34580 <lb/>AtSfh1/ <lb/>COW1 <lb/>

			T-DNA mutant characterization <lb/>and functional complementation <lb/>1 <lb/>-(Golgi) <lb/>Sterol carrier protein <lb/>SCP <lb/>PL, stérol <lb/>At5g42890 <lb/>SCP2 <lb/> In vitro expression <lb/>0 <lb/>-(Perox) <lb/>Non specific lipid transfer protein <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 1 <lb/>-<lb/>At2g38540 <lb/>LTP1 <lb/> In vitro expression <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 1 <lb/>-<lb/>At2g38530 <lb/>LTP2 <lb/> In vitro expression <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 1 <lb/>-<lb/>At5g59320 <lb/>LTP3 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 1 <lb/>-<lb/>At5g59310 <lb/>LTP4 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>1 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 1 <lb/>-<lb/>At3g51600 <lb/>LTP5 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 1 <lb/>-<lb/>At3g08770 <lb/>LTP6 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 1 <lb/>-<lb/>At2g18370 <lb/>LTP7 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 1 <lb/>-<lb/>At2g15050 <lb/>LTP8 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 1 <lb/>-<lb/>At2g15325 <lb/>LTP9 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>1 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 1 <lb/>-<lb/>At5g01870 <lb/>LTP10 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 1 <lb/>-<lb/>At4g33555 <lb/>LTP11 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 1 <lb/>-<lb/>At3g51590 <lb/>LTP12 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 1 <lb/>-<lb/>At4g08530 <lb/>LTP15 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 2 <lb/>-<lb/>At1g48750 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>1 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 2 <lb/>-<lb/>At1g66850 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 2 <lb/>-<lb/>At1g73780 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 2 <lb/>-<lb/>At3g18280 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>1 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 2 <lb/>-<lb/>At3g57310 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 2 <lb/>-<lb/>At5g38160 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 2 <lb/>-<lb/>At5g38170 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>1 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 2 <lb/>-<lb/>At5g38180 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>1 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 3 <lb/>-<lb/>At1g32280 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 3 <lb/>-<lb/>At3g07450 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 3 <lb/>-<lb/>At3g52130 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>1 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 3 <lb/>-<lb/>At4g30880 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 3 <lb/>-<lb/>At4g33550 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 3 <lb/>-<lb/>At5g07230 <lb/>A9 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 3 <lb/>-<lb/>At5g48485 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>1 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 3 <lb/>-<lb/>At5g48490 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 3 <lb/>-<lb/>At5g52160 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>1 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 3 <lb/>-<lb/>At5g55410 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 3 <lb/>-<lb/>At5g55450 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 3 <lb/>-<lb/>At5g55460 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 3 <lb/>-<lb/>At5g56480 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 3 <lb/>-<lb/>At5g62080 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 4 <lb/>-<lb/>At3g53980 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 4 <lb/>-<lb/>At5g05960 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At1g18280 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At1g27950 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>2 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At1g36150 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>1 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At1g55260 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At1g62790 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>2 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At1g70240 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At1g73550 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>1 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At1g73560 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At1g73890 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>1 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At2g13820 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>

			<page> 41 <lb/></page>

			LTP <lb/> Bound lipid Arabidopsis locus Protein <lb/>Evidence <lb/>TM Localization <lb/> Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At2g27130 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>1 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At2g37870 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At2g44290 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>1 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At2g44300 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>2 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At2g48130 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>M <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At2g48140 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>_ <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At3g22570 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At3g22580 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>1 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At3g22600 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At3g22620 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At3g43720 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>2 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At4g08670 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>1 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At4g12360 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>2 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At4g14815 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>1 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At4g22630 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>2 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At4g22640 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>1 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At5g09370 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At5g13900 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 5 <lb/>-<lb/>At5g64080 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>2 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 6 <lb/>-<lb/>At4g22490 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 6 <lb/>-<lb/>At4g22520 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 7 <lb/>-<lb/>At3g58550 <lb/>S e q u e n c e s i m i l a r i t y <lb/>0 <lb/>S <lb/>Lipid Transfer Protein type 8 <lb/>-<lb/>At4g28395 <lb/>ATA7 <lb/>Sequence similarity <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>

			<page> 42 <lb/></page>

			Figure 1: Lipid diffusion inside and across lipid bilayers. The figure shows the half-times <lb/>(T½) for spontaneous interbilayer and transbilayer movement according to [12, 16]. Large <lb/>arrows indicate fast movement and dashed arrows indicate slower movement. P: phosphate, <lb/>Chol: choline, Gal: galactose. <lb/> Figure 2: Lipid transfers towards and outwards the chloroplast envelope. PC is present in <lb/>the outer leaflet of the outer envelope membrane but is synthesized in the ER, not in the <lb/>plastid. It may be transferred from ER to the envelope directly or through its conversion to <lb/>LysoPC. The main lipids of thylakoids i.e. galactolipids, PG and SQDG are formed in the <lb/>envelope. Whereas prokaryotic type galactolipids are issued from phosphatidate (PA P ) <lb/>synthesized in the chloroplast, formation of eukaryotic type galactolipids is dependent on the <lb/>supply to the envelope of some PC derivatives formed in the ER: either diacylglycerol <lb/>(DAG E) [6] or phosphatidate (PA E ) [37]. PAP converting PA to DAG is present in the <lb/>envelope but only in the inner membrane. Altogether, a number of lipid transfers noted by <lb/>dashed arrows are important to build plastid membranes. Under phosphate deprivation, <lb/>DGDG formation is stimulated corresponding to activation or stimulation of a part of the <lb/>galactolipid synthesis pathway indicated in red [42; 6; 9]. Under these conditions, DGDG is <lb/>transferred through membrane contact between chloroplast and mitochondria [9]. <lb/> Figure 3: Scheme of the plant secretory pathway according to [48]. This scheme <lb/>represents different routes starting from the ER and indicates key proteins involved in vesicle <lb/>trafficking. Phosphorylated forms of PI address vesicles to specific compartments: PI-4P to <lb/>the storage vacuole, PI-3P to the lytic vacuole and PIP2 to the plasma membrane. 1-Transfer <lb/>from ER to Golgi uses COPII type vesicle machinery. Identified proteins involved in this <lb/>transfer are the GTPase Sar1, the GTP exchanging factor Sec12, the coat complexes Sec13 <lb/>and Sec23, and the GTPase RabD. 2-Transfer from Golgi to ER uses a COPI type vesicle <lb/>

			<page>43 <lb/></page>

			machinery. Identified proteins involved in this transfer are the GTPase Arf1, interacting with <lb/>a transmembrane protein p23, the GTP exchanging factor Gea, H/KDEL motif receptor <lb/>responsible of protein retrograde traffic ERD2. This transfer is actin dependent. 3-Transfer <lb/>from ER and Golgi to storage vacuole with the intervention of dense vesicles is not yet <lb/>characterised. The only protein identified in this transfer is the storage vacuole addressing <lb/>receptor PV72. 4-Transfer from Golgi to lytic vacuole via prevacuolar compartment uses <lb/>clathrin vesicle machinery. Identified proteins involved in vesicle formation are the GTPase <lb/>Arf1, lytic vacuole addressing motif receptor BP80 able to recruit the adaptatin complex AP1 <lb/>and thus clathrin. Vesicle fusion to prevacuolar compartment involves the v-SNARE PEP12 <lb/>and VAM3, the t-SNARE SYP25 and VTI11, and the GTPases RabA and RabF. This transfer <lb/>is actin and dynamin ADL6 dependent. 5-Transfer from Golgi to plasma membrane is not yet <lb/>identified. Protein involved in vesicle formation or fusion are not known. Only two PI-TP, <lb/>Sec14 and Sfh1, were characterised. This transfer is actin dependent. 6-Endocytosis uses <lb/>clathrin coated vesicle machinery. Identified proteins involved in vesicle formation are the <lb/>adaptatin complex AP2 and clathrin. This transfer is actin and dynamin ADL1 dependent. <lb/>And 7-Exocytosis utilizes a vesicle machinery not yet characterised. Identified proteins <lb/>involved in vesicle formation are the GTPase Arf1 and the GTP exchanging factor GNOM. <lb/>Vesicle fusion to plasma membrane involves the t-SNARE KNOLLE and the v-SNARE <lb/>SNAP33. <lb/> Figure 4: Lipid transfer at membrane contact sites. A: Electron microscopy observation of <lb/> A. thaliana cells grown in suspension. Cells were grown for 3 days in minus P i medium. Bar: <lb/>1 µm. Arrows indicate position of contact between mitochondria and amylochloroplasts. B: <lb/>Schematic representation of membrane contact sites reported in the plant cell. Reticulum <lb/>44 <lb/>forms a network that facilitates lipid transfer between organelles. Plastids create envelope <lb/>extension in the form of stromules or of myelinic structures, marked with a star. <lb/>

			OH <lb/> P <lb/>Chol <lb/>Gal <lb/>P <lb/>100 h <lb/>2 min <lb/>60 h <lb/>100 h <lb/>0.1 s <lb/>25 h <lb/>10 h <lb/>5 h <lb/> Transbilayer <lb/> diffusion T 1/2 <lb/> Interbilayer <lb/>diffusion T 1/2 <lb/> DAG <lb/>LysoPC <lb/>PC <lb/>MGDG <lb/> Figure 1 <lb/> Chol <lb/> MGDG <lb/> PLD <lb/> PLC <lb/> PC <lb/>DAG E <lb/> PA E <lb/> PA E <lb/> PA E <lb/> MGDG <lb/> MGD1 <lb/>MGD2, MGD3 <lb/>PAP <lb/> Endomembrane <lb/> Plastid envelope <lb/>OM <lb/> PAP <lb/> Figure 2 <lb/> PA P <lb/> + <lb/>DGDG <lb/> DGD1, DGD2 <lb/> DGDG <lb/> Thylakoids <lb/> LysoPC <lb/> PLA 2 <lb/> LysoPC <lb/>PC <lb/> LysoPC <lb/>acyltransferase <lb/> IM <lb/> DAG E <lb/> PG <lb/> Mitochondria <lb/> SQDG <lb/>DAG E <lb/> DAG P <lb/> + <lb/> Storage vacuole <lb/>Lytic vacuole <lb/>Endosome <lb/>Endoplasmic reticulum <lb/>Plasma membrane <lb/> p23 <lb/> Arf1 <lb/>Gea <lb/>ERD2 <lb/> COPI <lb/> actin <lb/> PI-4P <lb/> PV72 <lb/> PI-3P <lb/>PI-3P <lb/>PIP2 <lb/> AP1 <lb/>Arf1 <lb/>ELP <lb/> Clathrin-coated <lb/>vesicle <lb/> ADL6 <lb/>actin <lb/>PEP12 <lb/>VAM3 <lb/>RabA <lb/>RabF <lb/>SYP25 <lb/>VTI11 <lb/>AtSfh1 <lb/>Sec14 <lb/> PS, PE, PC <lb/>AP2 <lb/>ADL1 <lb/>actin <lb/>Arf1 <lb/>GNOM <lb/>actin <lb/>KNOLLE <lb/>SNAP33 <lb/> Nucleus <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/> Actin <lb/>Myosin VIII <lb/> Clathrin-coated <lb/>vesicle <lb/> Golgi <lb/>Prevacuolar <lb/>compartment <lb/> Figure 3 <lb/> Sec12,Sar1 <lb/>RabD <lb/> COPII <lb/> Figure 4 <lb/> Nucleus <lb/> Endoplasmic reticulum <lb/>Lytic <lb/>vacuole <lb/>Mitochondria <lb/>Chloroplast <lb/>Plasma <lb/>membrane <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> B <lb/>A</body>


	</text>
</tei>
