<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>TBM <lb/>Stakeholder perspectives on implementing the National <lb/>Cancer Institute&apos;s patient-reported outcomes version <lb/>of the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events <lb/>(PRO-CTCAE) <lb/>Deborah Watkins Bruner, RN, PhD, FAAN, <lb/>1 Laura J Hanisch, PsyD, <lb/>2 Bryce B Reeve, PhD, <lb/>3 <lb/>Andy M Trotti, MD, <lb/>4 Deborah Schrag, MD, MPH, <lb/>5 Laura Sit, <lb/>6 Tito R Mendoza, PhD, MS, MEd, <lb/>7 <lb/>Lori Minasian, MD, <lb/>8 Ann O&apos;Mara, PhD, RN, FAAN, <lb/>9 Andrea M Denicoff, MS, RN, ANP, <lb/>10 <lb/>Julia H Rowland, PhD, <lb/>11 Michael Montello, PharmD, MBA, <lb/>12 Cindy Geoghegan, <lb/>13 Amy P Abernethy, MD, <lb/>14 <lb/>Steven B Clauser, PhD, <lb/>15 Kathleen Castro, RN, MS, AOCN, <lb/>16 Sandra A Mitchell, CRNP, PhD, <lb/>17 <lb/>Laurie Burke, RPh, MPH, <lb/>18 Ann Marie Trentacosti, MD, <lb/>19 Ethan M Basch, MD, MSc <lb/>20 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The National Cancer Institute (NCI) is developing a patient-<lb/>reported version of its Common Terminology Criteria for <lb/>Adverse Events, called the &quot; PRO-CTCAE. &quot; The PRO-CTCAE <lb/> consists of a library of patient-reported items which can be <lb/>administered in clinical trials to directly capture the patient <lb/>experience of adverse events during cancer treatment, as <lb/>well as a software platform for administering these items <lb/>via computer or telephone. In order to better understand <lb/>the impressions of stakeholders involved in cancer clinical <lb/>research about the potential value of the PRO-CTCAE <lb/>approach to capturing adverse event information in <lb/>clinical research, as well as their perspectives about <lb/>barriers and strategies for implementing the PRO-CTCAE in <lb/>NCI-sponsored cancer trials, a survey was conducted. A <lb/>survey including structured and open-ended questions <lb/>was developed to elicit perceptions about the use of <lb/>patient-reported outcomes (PROs) for adverse event <lb/>reporting, and to explore logistical considerations for <lb/>implementing the PRO-CTCAE in cancer trials. The survey <lb/>was distributed electronically and by paper to a <lb/>convenience sample of leadership and committee <lb/>members in the NCI&apos;s cooperative group network, <lb/>including principal investigators, clinical investigators, <lb/>research nurses, data managers, patient advocates, and <lb/>representatives of the NCI and Food and Drug <lb/>Administration. Between October, 2008 through February, <lb/>2009, 727 surveys were collected. Most respondents <lb/>(93%) agreed that patient reporting of adverse symptoms <lb/>would be useful for improving understanding of the patient <lb/>experience with treatment in cancer trials, and 88%, 80%, <lb/>and 76%, respectively, endorsed that administration of <lb/>PRO-CTCAE items in clinical trials would improve the <lb/>completeness, accuracy, and efficiency of symptom data <lb/>collection. More than three fourths believed that patient <lb/>reports would be useful for informing treatment dose <lb/>modifications and towards FDA regulatory evaluation of <lb/>drugs. Eighty-eight percent felt that patients in clinical trials <lb/> 1 School of Nursing, Abramson Cancer <lb/>Center, University of Pennsylvania, <lb/>Claire M. Fagin Hall, Room 330, 418 <lb/>Curie Boulevard, Philadelphia, PA <lb/>19104-4217, USA <lb/>2 <lb/>Cancer Control and Outcomes <lb/>Program, Abramson Cancer Center, <lb/>University of Pennsylvania, Claire <lb/>M. Fagin Hall, Room 330, 418 Curie <lb/>Boulevard, Philadelphia, PA 19104-<lb/>4217, USA <lb/>Implications <lb/>Policymakers: Patient self-reporting provides <lb/>essential information about the safety and effec-<lb/>tiveness of drugs and devices which can aid <lb/>setting treatment and reimbursement priorities. <lb/>3 <lb/>Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer <lb/>Center, Department of Health <lb/>Policy and Management, Gillings <lb/>School of Global Public Health, <lb/>University of North Carolina at <lb/>Chapel Hill, 1101-D McGavran-<lb/>Greenberg Building, 135 Dauer <lb/>Drive, CB 7411, Chapel Hill, NC <lb/>27599-7411, USA <lb/> Researchers: Patient-reported outcomes pro-<lb/>vide reliable and valid accounts of the symptoms <lb/>experienced by patients during treatment, which <lb/>can provide important study data and prompt <lb/>new research questions. <lb/>4 <lb/>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and <lb/>Research Institute, 12902 Magnolia <lb/>Drive, Tampa, FL 33612, USA <lb/>5 <lb/>Practitioners: Systems that allow patients to self-<lb/>report their own side effects in real-time to providers <lb/>have been demonstrated to improve symptom <lb/>control, patient satisfaction, patient-clinician com-<lb/>munication, and to aid in clinical decision-making. <lb/>would be willing to self-report adverse symptoms at clinic <lb/>visits via computer, and 68% felt patients would self-report <lb/>weekly from home via the internet or an automated <lb/>telephone system. Lack of computers and limited space and <lb/>personnel were seen as potential barriers to in-clinic self-<lb/>reporting, but these were judged to be surmountable with <lb/>adequate funding. The PRO-CTCAE items and software are <lb/>viewed by a majority of survey respondents as a means to <lb/>improve adverse event data quality and <lb/>comprehensiveness, enhance clinical decision-making, and <lb/>foster patient-clinician communication. Research is ongoing <lb/>to assess the measurement properties and feasibility of <lb/>implementing this measure in cancer clinical trials. <lb/> Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, <lb/>Gastrointestinal Cancer Center, 44 <lb/>Binney Street, SM 205, Boston, <lb/>MA 02115, USA <lb/>6 <lb/>Health Outcomes Group, <lb/>Department of Epidemiology <lb/>and Biostatistics, Memorial Sloan-<lb/>Kettering Cancer Center, 307 <lb/>E.63rd Street, 2nd floor, New York, <lb/>NY 10065, USA <lb/>7 <lb/>Department of Symptom <lb/>Research, The University of Texas <lb/>MD Anderson Cancer Center, 1400 <lb/>Pressler St Unit 1450, Room <lb/>Number: FCT11.5074, Houston, TX <lb/>77030, USA <lb/>8 <lb/>Keywords <lb/>Patient-reported outcomes, Symptoms, adverse <lb/>events, Oncology, Cancer, Clinical trials, Toxicity, <lb/>safety, Tolerability, Comparative effectiveness <lb/>research, Cooperative groups, National Cancer <lb/>Institute <lb/>Community Oncology and <lb/>Prevention Trials Research Group, <lb/>Division of Cancer Prevention, <lb/>National Cancer Institute, NIH, <lb/>6130 Executive Blvd, EPN, Room <lb/>2016, MSC-7340, Bethesda, MD <lb/>20892-7340, USA <lb/>Cite this as: TBM 2011;1:110–122 <lb/>doi: 10.1007/s13142-011-0025-3 <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">TBM <lb/></note>

			<page>page 110 of 122 <lb/></page>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>The Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse <lb/>Events (CTCAE) is a lexicon of individual items <lb/>maintained by the US National Cancer Institute <lb/>(NCI) in order to standardize documentation of <lb/>adverse events (AEs) in cancer clinical trials [1]. <lb/>Initially developed in 1984, it was substantially revised <lb/>in 2003 to expand anatomic site specificity and include <lb/>criteria for surgical effects, and was again revised in <lb/>2009 to harmonize terminology with the Medical <lb/>Dictionary for Regulatory Activities [2, 3]. <lb/>Each CTCAE item contains a term which repre-<lb/>sents a specific AE of interest and response options <lb/>anchored to discrete clinical criteria which yield a <lb/>severity grade between 1 and 5. As such, these items <lb/>are used in clinical trials to document both the <lb/>incidence and severity of AEs. Three general <lb/>categories of AEs are included in the CTCAE: those <lb/>based on laboratory reports (e.g., anemia); those <lb/>based on clinical observations (e.g., retinal tear); and <lb/>symptoms (e.g., dyspnea). All three categories of <lb/>items are currently reported by clinicians. <lb/>Based on mounting evidence that clinician reporting <lb/>of patients&apos; symptoms underestimates the prevalence <lb/>and severity of these symptoms [4–11], and recent <lb/>guidance from the FDA regarding standards for the <lb/>development of patient-reported outcomes measures <lb/>[12], in 2008, the NCI contracted to develop patient <lb/>versions of those items in the CTCAE which represent <lb/>symptoms, which collectively would be called the <lb/> &quot; Patient-Reported Outcomes version of the Common <lb/>terminology Criteria for Adverse Events &quot; or PRO-<lb/>CTCAE. In addition, the NCI contracted to develop a <lb/>software platform for administering these items in <lb/>clinical trials (although the ultimate intention of the <lb/>PRO-CTCAE initiative it to move towards electronic <lb/>administration of these items in clinical trials, paper <lb/>versions consisting of PRO-CTCAE items will also be <lb/>available). <lb/>As a part of the PRO-CTCAE initiative, the NCI <lb/>wished to ascertain the extent to which various stake-<lb/>holders involved in NCI-sponsored trials (particularly <lb/>within the NCI&apos;s cooperative group network) recog-<lb/>nize a need for such a library of patient-reported AE <lb/>items and administration software. Stakeholders of <lb/>interest included cooperative group committee lead-<lb/>ers, study chairs/principal investigators, clinical inves-<lb/>tigators, research nurses, research assistants/data <lb/>managers, patient advocates, and representatives of <lb/>the NCI and FDA. Of particular interest were <lb/>perceived barriers to implementing a system in clinical <lb/>trials for electronically collecting patient-reported <lb/>adverse symptom information and recommended <lb/>solutions for overcoming these barriers. <lb/>METHODS <lb/>Survey—An anonymous survey was developed to <lb/>capture impressions from various stakeholders <lb/>involved in the conduct of NCI-sponsored clinical <lb/>research about the perceived value, feasibility, and <lb/>potential barriers to implementing an electronic soft-<lb/>ware platform for capturing patient-reported adverse <lb/>symptom events in multicenter oncology trials. Back-<lb/>ground questions queried participants&apos; research role <lb/>(s), affiliation(s) with cooperative groups, and educa-<lb/>tional degree(s). Additional questions pertained to <lb/>barriers to PRO-CTCAE implementation at the <lb/>patient-level and site-level, as well as overall impres-<lb/>sions of the usefulness of such an approach to <lb/>capturing adverse event information. These questions <lb/>utilized a common response option format including <lb/>strongly agree, somewhat agree, neither agree nor disagree, <lb/>somewhat disagree, and strongly disagree. Two open-ended <lb/>questions invited general impressions and recommen-<lb/>dations for desirable system features. A copy of the <lb/>survey is included as an APPENDIX. <lb/>Participants—Individuals were eligible to partici-<lb/>pate if they were clinical investigators (based at <lb/>academic centers or community practices), data <lb/>managers, NCI staff, FDA staff, cooperative group <lb/>leadership, or patient advocates with direct involve-<lb/>ment in the development, conduct, or analysis of <lb/>cooperative group trials. Study recruitment targeted <lb/>investigators in community oncology practices par-<lb/>ticipating in NCI cooperative group research (i.e., <lb/>Community Clinical Oncology Program sites); <lb/>patient advocates registered with the NCI; investi-<lb/>gators, data managers, and leadership of the Cancer <lb/>and Leukemia Group B (CALGB) and Radiation <lb/>Therapy Oncology Group (RTOG); FDA reviewers <lb/>in the Office of Oncology Drug Products and Study <lb/>Endpoints and Labeling Development staff; and NCI <lb/>staff in the Division of Cancer Prevention (DCP) and <lb/>Cancer Therapy Evaluation Program (CTEP). <lb/>Procedure—The survey was uploaded to a secure <lb/>electronic distribution system, and an email soliciting <lb/>participation was sent to distribution lists of the <lb/>targeted participants. In addition, paper versions of <lb/>the survey were distributed when disease committees <lb/>convened at cooperative group meetings. Because <lb/>paper surveys were handed out at multiple coopera-<lb/>tive group meetings and were also circulated electroni-<lb/>cally, it is not possible to quantify the total number of <lb/>distributed surveys. The survey indicated to respond-<lb/>ents that it was anonymous, and no personally <lb/>identifying information was collected. Data were <lb/>collected between October, 2008 and February, 2009. <lb/>Analyses—Frequencies and proportions were com-<lb/>puted for all survey items. Associations between <lb/>participant role and various responses were examined <lb/>with chi-square analyses. Since some participants <lb/>endorsed more than one role, participants were catego-<lb/>rized into mutually exclusive groups as Researchers (i.e., <lb/>lead primary investigators, investigators), Research Staff <lb/>(i.e., research nurses and research assistants/data man-<lb/>agers), Patient Advocates, or Regulators (i.e., NCI and FDA <lb/>representatives). Likert responses for each item were <lb/>collapsed to create three response options (i.e., Agree, <lb/>Neither Agree nor Disagree, Disagree). <lb/></body>

			<front>9 <lb/>Palliative Care Research, <lb/>Community Oncology and <lb/>Prevention Trials Research Group, <lb/>Division of Cancer Prevention, <lb/>National Cancer Institute, 6130 <lb/>Executive Blvd., EPN 2010, <lb/>Bethesda, MD 20892, USA <lb/>10 <lb/>Clinical Investigations Branch, <lb/>CTEP, Division of Cancer Treatment <lb/>and Diagnosis, National Cancer <lb/>Institute, Bethesda, MD 20892-<lb/>7436, USA <lb/>11 Office of Cancer Survivorship, <lb/>Division of Cancer Control and <lb/>Population Sciences, National <lb/>Cancer Institute, NIH/DHHS, 6116 <lb/>Executive Blvd, Suite 404, MSC <lb/>8336, Bethesda, MD 20892-8336, <lb/>USA <lb/>12 <lb/>National Cancer Institute, Clinical <lb/>Trials Technology, 6130 Executive <lb/>Blvd., Suite 7025, Bethesda, MD <lb/>20892-7436, USA <lb/>13 <lb/>Breast Cancer Network of <lb/>Strength, 135 South LaSalle Street, <lb/>Chicago, IL 60603, USA <lb/>14 <lb/>Department of Medicine, Duke <lb/>University School of Medicine, <lb/>25165 Morris Building, Duke <lb/>University Medical Center , Box <lb/>3436, Durham, NC 27710, USA <lb/>15 <lb/>Outcomes Research Branch, <lb/>Applied Research Program, Division <lb/>of Cancer Control and Population <lb/>Sciences, National Cancer Institute, <lb/>6130 Executive Boulevard—MSC <lb/>7344, Bethesda, MD 20892-7344, <lb/>USA <lb/>16 <lb/>Outcomes Research Branch, <lb/>Applied Research Program, Division <lb/>of Cancer Control and Population <lb/>Sciences, National Cancer Institute, <lb/>6130 Executive Blvd, EPN 4091, <lb/>Bethesda, MD 20892, USA <lb/>17 <lb/>Outcomes Research Branch, <lb/>Applied Research Program, Division <lb/>of Cancer Control and Population <lb/>Sciences, National Cancer Institute, <lb/>6130 Executive Blvd., EPN 4088, <lb/>Bethesda, MD 20892, USA <lb/>18 <lb/>Study Endpoints and Label <lb/>Development, Office of New Drugs, <lb/>Center for Drug Evaluation and <lb/>Research, Food and Drug <lb/>Administration, Building 22 Room <lb/>6462, 10903 New Hampshire <lb/>Avenue, Silver Spring, MD 20993-<lb/>0002, USA <lb/>19 <lb/>Study Endpoints and Label <lb/>Development, Office of New Drugs, <lb/>Center for Drug Evaluation and <lb/>Research, Food and Drug <lb/>Administration, Building 22 Room <lb/>6411, 10903 New Hampshire <lb/>Avenue, Silver Spring, MD 20993-<lb/>0002, USA <lb/>20 Health Outcomes Group, <lb/>Department of Epidemiology and <lb/>Biostatistics, Memorial <lb/>Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, 307 <lb/>E.63rd Street, 2nd floor, New York, <lb/>NY 10065, USA <lb/>Correspondence to: E Basch <lb/>basche@mskcc.org <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">TBM <lb/></note>

			<page>page 111 of 122 <lb/></page>

			<body>Qualitative responses to the open-ended ques-<lb/>tions were evaluated in stages. First, responses were <lb/>reviewed for content analysis. Three main themes <lb/>were identified: general approval/disapproval of <lb/>patient reporting for adverse event monitoring; <lb/>concerns about a PRO-CTCAE system; and sugges-<lb/>tions for functions of a PRO-CTCAE system. Next, <lb/>responses were coded according to these major <lb/>themes and grouped into subordinate categories. <lb/>Finally, the frequencies of responses within catego-<lb/>ries were tabulated. <lb/> RESULTS <lb/>Participants—A total of 727 questionnaires were <lb/>collected between October, 2008 through February, <lb/>2009, with the distribution of respondents including <lb/>26% researchers, 44% research staff, 14% patient <lb/>advocates, and 16% regulators. Ten of the US NCI-<lb/>sponsored clinical trials cooperative groups were <lb/>included in the survey including the American <lb/>College of Surgeons Oncology Group (ACoSOG); <lb/>American College of Radiology Imaging Network <lb/>(ACRIN); Cancer and Leukemia Group B <lb/>(CALGB); Children&apos;s Oncology Group (COG); <lb/>Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG); <lb/>Gynecologic Oncology Group (GOG); National <lb/>Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project <lb/>(NSABP); North Central Clinical Trials Group <lb/>(NCCTG); Radiation Therapy Oncology Group <lb/>(RTOG); and Southwest Oncology Group (SWOG). <lb/>Among the cooperative groups, CALGB (41%) and <lb/>RTOG (34%) represented the largest number of <lb/>respondents. <lb/>Perceived usefulness—Table 1 summarizes survey <lb/>responses by participant role. There was strong <lb/>consensus (93% overall) that patient reporting of <lb/>adverse symptoms would be useful for improving <lb/>our understanding of the patient experience with <lb/>treatment in cancer clinical trials. The majority of <lb/>respondents endorsed that such an approach <lb/>would improve the completeness (88%), accuracy <lb/>(80%), and efficiency (80%) of symptom data <lb/>collection in clinical trials. More than three-<lb/>fourths of respondents indicated that patient <lb/>reports would be useful for informing treatment <lb/>dose modifications and towards FDA regulatory <lb/>evaluation of drugs. <lb/>Acceptability—Survey responses revealed that 89% <lb/>endorsed, with 64% strongly endorsing, the need <lb/>for a PRO-CTCAE approach to collect adverse <lb/>symptom assessments directly from patients in <lb/>clinical trials. Adverse symptom severity was <lb/>regarded by 68% to be better understood by <lb/>patients than clinicians, particularly among patient <lb/>advocates, while research staff disagreed the most, <lb/>χ <lb/>2 (6, N=624)=54.64, p&lt;.001. Conversely, 86% of <lb/>all respondents agreed that some symptoms may <lb/>be better understood by clinicians due to technical <lb/>training and expertise. Consistent with these <lb/>results, 88% agreed that adverse events in clinical <lb/>trials should be reported by both patients and <lb/>clinicians. <lb/>Implementation barriers—Although 88% of respond-<lb/>ents felt that patients in clinical trials would be <lb/>willing to self-report adverse symptoms at clinic <lb/>visits via computer, 88% believed that severe illness <lb/>could be a potential barrier. Inclusion of proxy <lb/>reporting by caregivers for patients too ill to self-<lb/>report received support by 68%, particularly among <lb/>patient advocates, χ <lb/>2 <lb/>(6, N=619)=15.08, p&lt;.020. A <lb/>belief that patients enrolled in clinical trials would <lb/>be willing and able to self-report weekly from home <lb/>via the internet or via an automated telephone <lb/>system was shared by 68%, but research staff were <lb/>the most skeptical χ <lb/>2 (6, N=625)=42.88, p&lt;.001. <lb/>Most participants agreed that a potential barrier to <lb/>patients self-reporting at clinic visits via computer is <lb/>the scarceness in the clinical setting of computers <lb/>that can be accessed by patients (70%). Other <lb/>perceived barriers to this approach included limited <lb/>time at clinic visits (58%), limited available person-<lb/>nel to assist patients (57%), and limited clinic space <lb/>(50%). However, compared with research staff, <lb/>fewer patient advocates thought that clinic time, <lb/>personnel, or space were barriers. With no signifi-<lb/>cant differences between groups, 43% of all respond-<lb/>ents agreed that their workload would increase if <lb/>patient reports were used for AEs while 42% neither <lb/>agreed nor disagreed. <lb/>Importantly, 79% of participants perceived that <lb/>all potential barriers were manageable if additional <lb/>funds could be obtained. Regarding the method of <lb/>patient reporting in clinic, 82% indicated that paper-<lb/>based reporting was feasible, and relative to elec-<lb/>tronic reporting, more respondents thought portable <lb/>devices (58%) were feasible compared with desktop <lb/>computers (39%). Researchers endorsed the use of <lb/>portable devices more than other groups, χ <lb/>2 (6, N= <lb/>565)=100.98, p&lt;.001. <lb/>Patient advocate respondents were more likely <lb/>than other respondent types to endorse that patients <lb/>would be willing to self-report from home between <lb/>visits. Advocates were also more open to an <lb/>approach in which caregivers reported on behalf of <lb/>those too ill to report for themselves. <lb/>Qualitative responses—Of the total sample of 727 <lb/>respondents, 292 respondents (40%) provided com-<lb/>ments to the open-ended questions. Of these, 24% <lb/>offered generally positive statements about a PRO-<lb/>CTCAE approach. For example, &quot; Self-reporting of <lb/>adverse symptoms is needed. This would improve the <lb/>understanding of patients&apos; reactions to new treatments or <lb/>drugs and avoid the problem of patients not telling <lb/>clinicians of problems because they do not want to &apos;bother&apos; <lb/>the doctor. It also makes the patient feel a part of the <lb/>research process and not just a &apos;guinea pig&apos; which is very <lb/>important. &quot; In comparison, only 3% wrote general <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">TBM <lb/></note>

			<page>page 112 of 122 <lb/></page>

			<body>negative statements, such as, &quot; There are already several <lb/>good systems for collecting data of this kind. I am not sure <lb/>why additional systems are needed. &quot; <lb/>Respondents also commented on potential imple-<lb/>mentation barriers and provided suggestions to guide <lb/>the optimal design of a system to capture patient-<lb/>reported adverse events (see Tables 2 and 3). The most <lb/>frequently reported potential barrier was a concern <lb/>that patient self-reports could introduce inaccuracies <lb/>into adverse event reporting because of reporting and <lb/>recall biases, and lack of knowledge. Other cited <lb/>potential barriers included unfamiliarity with elec-<lb/>tronic devices, lack of computer access at home, and <lb/>limited acceptance of and adherence to reporting <lb/>protocols by patients. Additional concerns were that <lb/>such an approach might be a burden to patients, might <lb/>generate &quot; needless &quot; data, diminish communication <lb/>between patients and doctors, and cause patients to <lb/>be overtreated for symptoms. <lb/>Multiple suggestions were offered to strengthen <lb/>the development of patient-reported AE items and <lb/>software, with representative examples shown in <lb/>Table 3. The most common recommendation was to <lb/>assure that any approach to patient self-reporting be <lb/>Table 1 | Responses to stakeholder survey, by respondent role subgroup (N=727) <lb/>All <lb/>respondents <lb/>Respondent role subgroups <lb/>p &lt; value <lb/>Researchers <lb/>a <lb/>(N=189) <lb/>Research <lb/>staff <lb/>b <lb/>(N=316) <lb/>Patient advocates <lb/>(N=104) <lb/>Regulators <lb/>c <lb/>(N=118) <lb/>In general, patients better understand the severity of their symptoms than clinicians <lb/>N <lb/>624 <lb/>178 <lb/>288 <lb/>86 <lb/>72 <lb/>.001 <lb/>Agree <lb/>68% <lb/>80% <lb/>54% <lb/>81% <lb/>76% <lb/>Neither <lb/>13% <lb/>12% <lb/>15% <lb/>7% <lb/>13% <lb/>Disagree <lb/>19% <lb/>8% <lb/>31% <lb/>12% <lb/>11% <lb/>Caregivers will be able to report on behalf of severely ill or debilitated patients <lb/>N <lb/>619 <lb/>175 <lb/>285 <lb/>86 <lb/>73 <lb/>.020 <lb/>Agree <lb/>67% <lb/>59% <lb/>68% <lb/>83% <lb/>66% <lb/>Neither <lb/>14% <lb/>18% <lb/>13% <lb/>7% <lb/>15% <lb/>Disagree <lb/>19% <lb/>23% <lb/>18% <lb/>11% <lb/>19% <lb/>Most patients in clinical trials would be willing to self-report symptoms from home on a weekly basis <lb/>N <lb/>625 <lb/>178 <lb/>287 <lb/>87 <lb/>73 <lb/>.001 <lb/>Agree <lb/>68% <lb/>76% <lb/>57% <lb/>85% <lb/>70% <lb/>Neither <lb/>14% <lb/>14% <lb/>15% <lb/>7% <lb/>19% <lb/>Disagree <lb/>18% <lb/>11% <lb/>28% <lb/>8% <lb/>11% <lb/>Limited space at my clinic site is a potential barrier to implementing a system for collecting data directly from patients <lb/>N <lb/>577 <lb/>174 <lb/>286 <lb/>65 <lb/>52 <lb/>.001 <lb/>Agree <lb/>50% <lb/>48% <lb/>58% <lb/>26% <lb/>40% <lb/>Neither <lb/>21% <lb/>13% <lb/>15% <lb/>54% <lb/>40% <lb/>Disagree <lb/>29% <lb/>39% <lb/>27% <lb/>20% <lb/>19% <lb/>Limited personnel at my clinic site is a potential barrier to implementing a system for collecting data directly from <lb/>patients <lb/>N <lb/>576 <lb/>173 <lb/>285 <lb/>64 <lb/>54 <lb/>.001 <lb/>Agree <lb/>57% <lb/>71% <lb/>53% <lb/>38% <lb/>58% <lb/>Neither <lb/>18% <lb/>7% <lb/>15% <lb/>52% <lb/>32% <lb/>Disagree <lb/>25% <lb/>23% <lb/>32% <lb/>11% <lb/>11% <lb/>Limited time at my clinic site is a potential barrier to implementing a system for collecting data directly from patients <lb/>N <lb/>577 <lb/>174 <lb/>285 <lb/>64 <lb/>54 <lb/>.001 <lb/>Agree <lb/>58% <lb/>69% <lb/>55% <lb/>44% <lb/>54% <lb/>Neither <lb/>19% <lb/>9% <lb/>17% <lb/>44% <lb/>28% <lb/>Disagree <lb/>23% <lb/>22% <lb/>27% <lb/>13% <lb/>19% <lb/>Wireless laptop/tablet computer-based patient self-reporting is feasible at my site <lb/>N <lb/>565 <lb/>170 <lb/>285 <lb/>60 <lb/>50 <lb/>.001 <lb/>Agree <lb/>58% <lb/>79% <lb/>55% <lb/>33% <lb/>32% <lb/>Neither <lb/>23% <lb/>8% <lb/>20% <lb/>58% <lb/>46% <lb/>Disagree <lb/>19% <lb/>13% <lb/>25% <lb/>8% <lb/>22% <lb/>a Includes cooperative group committee leaders, study chairs/principal investigators, and clinical investigators <lb/>b Includes research nurses and clinical research assistants/data managers <lb/>c Includes representatives of the national cancer institute and food and drug administration <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">TBM <lb/></note>

			<page>page 113 of 122 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 2 | Common qualitative responses regarding potential barriers to implementing a standardized system for capturing <lb/>patient-reported adverse events in cancer clinical trials (N=292) <lb/>Potential barriers <lb/>n <lb/>a <lb/>Examples <lb/>Patient-related <lb/>Inaccurate reporting <lb/>48 <lb/> &quot; Some under-report; others appear to over-report. &quot; <lb/> &quot; Patients may not give true statements due to <lb/>fear they may have to come off study medications. &quot; <lb/> &quot; Patients not trained to identify many adverse events. &quot; <lb/>Computer literacy <lb/>24 <lb/> &quot; Patients, especially elderly, are not computer literate. &quot; <lb/>Lack of computer and internet access <lb/>17 <lb/> &quot; The only reservation is the availability for our patient <lb/>access to computers at home and the physician office. &quot; <lb/>Acceptance/adherence <lb/>15 <lb/> &quot; Our patient population is a mixture of people who <lb/>would love to do this and others who would not want <lb/>to and be quite annoyed at the suggestion. &quot;  &quot; Worry <lb/>about compliance with patients. &quot; <lb/>Patient burden <lb/>12 <lb/> &quot; I would like to see this not to become patient&apos;s burden.&quot; <lb/>Reading literacy <lb/>7 <lb/> &quot; Please be aware of the literacy limitations of other cultures <lb/>and educational levels. &quot; <lb/>Appropriate for minorities <lb/>6 <lb/> &quot; We have a number of patients who have immigrated <lb/>to our community from other countries. Many need <lb/>one-on-one help in deciphering both the survey question <lb/>and how they should answer. &quot; <lb/>Unable/illness <lb/>5 <lb/> &quot; The most seriously ill patients may not report and only <lb/>those who are faring well in the trial may report, thus, <lb/>skewing the results.&quot; &quot; I don&apos;t feel that all patients would <lb/>be able to self report. &quot; <lb/>Inaccurate proxy report <lb/>5 <lb/> &quot; Caregivers can over-state the patient&apos;s condition <lb/>and even more frequently under-state the patient&apos;s <lb/>condition. &quot; <lb/>Site-related <lb/>Limited personnel <lb/>20 <lb/> &quot; I am concerned about the workload generated by <lb/>this type of system &quot; . &quot; Not enough time, staffing to <lb/>facilitate. &quot; <lb/>Limited space <lb/>6 <lb/> &quot; This is a great idea, but in our sites, space is a big issue. &quot; <lb/>Funding insufficient <lb/>6 <lb/> &quot; Funding will not overcome the barriers. &quot; <lb/>Regulatory approval <lb/>2 <lb/> &quot; Too many regulations to allow this process in my setting. &quot; <lb/>Study-related <lb/>Unnecessary data <lb/>8 <lb/> &quot; We have used a paper review of AEs. It has generated a lot <lb/>of spurious data. &quot;  &quot; Does the FDA truly want everything a <lb/>patient reports including something not related to any <lb/>treatment? &quot; <lb/>Data discrepancies <lb/>5 <lb/> &quot; I can see discrepancies between what a patient reports <lb/>versus what a clinician would report. &quot; <lb/>Procedural difficulties <lb/>4 <lb/> &quot; It would be yet another area where we would have <lb/>protocol deviations out of our control. &quot;  &quot; Electronic <lb/>devices can often be misplaced, forgotten, or patients <lb/>can forget to save the data. &quot; <lb/>Decline enrollment <lb/>3 <lb/> &quot; This self-reporting may be a factor that causes someone <lb/>not to consent to trial. &quot; <lb/>Treatment-related <lb/>Clinical relationship <lb/>6 <lb/> &quot; Patient self-reporting could be helpful but should not <lb/>replace communication between doctor and patient. <lb/>This tool can&apos;t be another reason for patients not to <lb/>talk with their doctors. &quot; <lb/>Treatment implications <lb/>5 <lb/> &quot; Not every symptom needs a medical treatment. &quot; <lb/> &quot; I would be concerned that it may increase the dose <lb/>modifications required. &quot; <lb/>Staff notification <lb/>2 <lb/> &quot; How does the clinician gain access to this information for <lb/>patient care and dose modifications? &quot; <lb/>a Some respondents identified more than one potential barrier <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">TBM <lb/></note>

			<page>page 114 of 122 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 3 | Suggestions by survey respondents for the design of a standardized system to capture patient-reported adverse <lb/>events in cancer clinical trials (N=292) <lb/>Suggestions <lb/>n <lb/>a <lb/>Examples <lb/>User friendly <lb/>Understandable <lb/>41 <lb/> &quot; Clear definition of the concept measured. &quot;  &quot; Give examples. &quot; <lb/> &quot; Include pictures. &quot;  &quot; Simple short concise verbiage. &quot; <lb/>Easy to complete <lb/>40 <lb/> &quot; Touch screen system. &quot;  &quot; Drop down menus. &quot;  &quot; Quick to complete. &quot; <lb/> &quot; Easy to navigate. &quot;  &quot; Error correction. &quot; <lb/>General comments <lb/>37 <lb/> &quot; User friendly. &quot; <lb/>Patient Education <lb/>23 <lb/> &quot; We need much better patient education so that they feel comfortable <lb/>reporting events. &quot;  &quot; Any reporting system has to be clear about the <lb/>reasons for reporting symptoms in order to make sure that patients <lb/>don&apos;t withhold things that might be relevant. &quot; <lb/>Readable <lb/>18 <lb/> &quot; Large font. &quot;  &quot; Minimal words per screen. &quot;  &quot; Instructions modified for <lb/>people with visual impairment or reading disability. &quot;  &quot; Available in <lb/>different languages. &quot; <lb/>Easy for administrators <lb/>13 <lb/> &quot; Easy to implement for sites. &quot;  &quot; Leveraging potential business of <lb/>practice incentives to their use may prove to be a way to <lb/>accelerate uptake. &quot; <lb/>Accessible/portable <lb/>12 <lb/> &quot; Development of portable electronic/tablet systems. &quot;  &quot; Accessibility <lb/>is important to avoid biases. &quot; <lb/>Help support <lb/>6 <lb/> &quot; Help function should be available. &quot; <lb/>Cues/Reminders <lb/>4 <lb/> &quot; Auto calls or email to remind patients to self report. &quot;  &quot; Prompt <lb/>when PRO measures are due and not obtained. &quot; <lb/>System features <lb/>Reporting options <lb/>40 <lb/> &quot; It would be nice if patients were given a choice of electronic <lb/>vs. paper. &quot;  &quot; There should be some open ended way for patients <lb/>to report. &quot;  &quot; The option to self-report daily or more than weekly <lb/>as needed. &quot; <lb/>Electronic reporting <lb/>32 <lb/> &quot; eTablets were used in a practice I worked in and greatly improved <lb/>the assessment of the patients&apos; symptoms and adjustment of <lb/>treatment as needed. &quot;  &quot; Should make such a survey a web form. &quot; <lb/> &quot; Wireless. &quot;  &quot; PDA &quot; <lb/>Involve clinician <lb/>27 <lb/> &quot; Best system is probably interactive between patients and staff. &quot; <lb/> &quot; Patient self-reporting should always be accompanied by clinician <lb/>assessment simultaneously. &quot; <lb/>Outside clinic reporting <lb/>17 <lb/> &quot; Reporting between appointments would be very helpful. &quot;  &quot; Favor <lb/>home reporting due to limited clinic time/space. &quot; <lb/>Data quality assurance <lb/>9 <lb/> &quot; Would also need to be reviewed by trials staff to ensure that patient <lb/>is reporting all symptoms and events. &quot; <lb/>(Differentiate) proxy reports <lb/>6 <lb/> &quot; Caregiver or proxy reporting might be useful to avoid burden to ill <lb/>patient or to avoid missing data however it would need to be coded <lb/>differently. &quot;  &quot; For a pediatric population, the system would have to <lb/>allow for parent reporting. &quot; <lb/>Patient privacy <lb/>4 <lb/> &quot; Assurance of privacy. &quot; <lb/>System development and implementation <lb/>Validate <lb/>29 <lb/> &quot; A system such as the one proposed must be validated to withstand <lb/>the highest level of scrutiny. &quot;  &quot; Use instruments that patients have <lb/>reviewed and provided qualitative feedback on. &quot; <lb/>Standardize assessment <lb/>14 <lb/> &quot; Good idea but devil is in the detail. There should be a standard <lb/>method of reporting. &quot;  &quot; Group common AE&apos;s together and do not <lb/>&quot;repeat&quot; similar questions/events. &quot; <lb/>Minimize recall period <lb/>10 <lb/> &quot; Record the information at the time the symptom occurred. &quot; <lb/>Obtain additional <lb/>information <lb/>7 <lb/> &quot; Include QOL and affective measures. &quot;  &quot; Include field to indicate <lb/>interventions for AEs. &quot; <lb/>Longitudinal assessment <lb/>6 <lb/> &quot; What is of interest is change over time since it is recognized that <lb/>some patients have poor baseline scores that are unrelated to <lb/>study treatment. &quot;  &quot; We really don&apos;t know much about long term <lb/>AE&apos;s. &quot; <lb/>Assess group/individual <lb/>differences <lb/>6 <lb/> &quot; More work needs to be done to examine how different types of <lb/>patients communicate with physicians or cancer care teams. &quot; <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">TBM <lb/></note>

			<page>page 115 of 122 <lb/></page>

			<body>user-friendly. Patient reminders and feedback were <lb/>proposed to increase adherence, and to facilitate <lb/>patient care. Automated alerts to flag severe symp-<lb/>toms to research and clinical staff were deemed <lb/>important. Respondents advocated that any patient-<lb/>reported items and software should be appropriate <lb/>for use in a range of patient populations, including <lb/>minorities, pediatrics, disabled, non-English speak-<lb/>ing, and those with lower literacy and educational <lb/>levels. Similarly, system testing within a range of <lb/>community settings and not just at large university-<lb/>based clinics was encouraged. Respondents also <lb/>recommended research on the interpretation of <lb/>response choices as some felt that reporting differ-<lb/>ences may exist by treatment trajectory, symptom <lb/>tolerance, severity of illness, location (e.g., home vs. <lb/>clinic), cultural factors, and age (e.g., adolescents). <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>Diverse stakeholders involved with administration of <lb/>clinical trials in the NCI-sponsored cooperative group <lb/>network endorse development of a system to system-<lb/>atically collect patient-reported adverse event informa-<lb/>tion. Across several respondent subgroups (i.e., <lb/>cooperative group leadership, investigators, data man-<lb/>agers, patient advocates, regulators), the PRO-CTCAE <lb/>approach was viewed by most as a means to improve <lb/>data quality and comprehensiveness, enhance clinical <lb/>decision-making, and foster patient-clinician commu-<lb/>nication. Moreover, it was felt that patient-reported <lb/>adverse event information should be incorporated into <lb/>published study results and drug labels. <lb/>These findings reflect an overall movement in clinical <lb/>research and drug regulatory policy towards favoring <lb/>patient self-reports for those experiences best known to <lb/>the patient, such as symptoms [3–5, 13–18]. Of <lb/>particular note is the FDA&apos;s recent guidance for industry <lb/>on patient-reported outcomes measures in medical <lb/>product development to support labeling claims, in <lb/>which patient-reported outcomes (PROs) are advocated <lb/>for measuring subjective experiences of patients related <lb/>both to treatment benefit and risk [12, 19]. Most HRQL <lb/>and symptom instruments focus on treatment benefit, <lb/>but the patient perspective on tolerability is rarely <lb/>systematically captured. The availability of inexpensive <lb/>technologies for administering questionnaires to <lb/>patients (e.g., via computer, telephone, or other portable <lb/>device), and widespread patient familiarity with these <lb/>technologies, have made it feasible to collect informa-<lb/>tion directly from patients during cancer treatment [20, <lb/>21]. A recent report by the Institute of Medicine <lb/>highlights the need for data standardization and <lb/>efficiency within the cooperative groups and the <lb/>importance of engaging patients in the clinical trial <lb/>enterprise; the approach of the PRO-CTCAE is con-<lb/>sistent with this report&apos;s recommendations [22]. <lb/>The results of this survey are being used to inform <lb/>pilot feasibility studies of implementing PRO-<lb/>CTCAE in NCI-sponsored clinical trials within the <lb/>NCI&apos;s cooperative group network. In these pilot <lb/>studies, selected PRO-CTCAE items are being <lb/>administered electronically to patients enrolled in <lb/>several multicenter clinical trials. Outcomes of <lb/>interest include cost, logistical requirements for sites, <lb/>acceptance by clinical staff and patients, and added <lb/>value of collected information. <lb/>The PRO-CTCAE approach may yield benefits <lb/>beyond screening for and characterizing adverse <lb/>symptoms in clinical trials. Longer-term monitoring <lb/>of patients&apos; symptoms can be used to evaluate post-<lb/>treatment patterns and timeframes for resolution of <lb/>symptoms. It may also aid in symptom monitoring <lb/>and management during routine chemotherapy <lb/>care. <lb/>The stakeholder survey suggests that the largest <lb/>perceived barrier to adoption of PRO-CTCAE in <lb/>NCI-sponsored trials is the logistics around clinical <lb/>implementation. When asked what resources would <lb/>be necessary to facilitate computer-based adminis-<lb/>tration of PRO-CTCAE items at clinic visits (i.e., at <lb/>the point of care), many respondents suggested that <lb/>additional computers, staff, and space would be <lb/>necessary. This suggests that for an in-clinic elec-<lb/>tronic questionnaire administration model of PRO-<lb/>CTCAE implementation to be successful, additional <lb/>funds would be necessary to support site-level <lb/>infrastructure. Alternatively, a model could be <lb/>Table 3 (continued) <lb/>Funding <lb/>6 <lb/> &quot; Financial support. &quot; <lb/>User benefits <lb/>Improve communication to <lb/>site personnel <lb/>16 <lb/> &quot; Customized &apos;tell your doctor fields&apos; would add to value for busy <lb/>clinics and an automatic email and feedback to data mangers <lb/>and investigators on trials. &quot;  &quot; Real-time feedback to providers. &quot; <lb/>Clinically useful <lb/>14 <lb/> &quot; Include some diagnostic queries. &quot;  &quot; Ability of health care personnel <lb/>to access patient-reported symptoms to integrate these into <lb/>clinical evaluation. &quot; <lb/>Helpful for patients <lb/>11 <lb/> &quot; System to categorize the adverse events over time for a patient to <lb/>see a pattern or trend. &quot;  &quot; The system should be used to provide <lb/>24/7 coverage for patients. &quot; <lb/>a Some respondents identified more than one potential barrier <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">TBM <lb/></note>

			<page>page 116 of 122 <lb/></page>

			<body>developed in which patients do not rely on clinic-<lb/>based computers to report, but rather would report <lb/>between visits via home computers or an automated <lb/>telephone system. Although training and backup <lb/>data collection methods for non-respondents would <lb/>still be necessary, much of this could be centralized <lb/>or handled by site staff without requiring additional <lb/>equipment or physical space at sites. Most respond-<lb/>ents felt that such a remote-reporting model would <lb/>be feasible. <lb/>Research staff (research nurses, research study <lb/>assistants, data managers) generally had more con-<lb/>cerns than other stakeholders about the logistics and <lb/>resources necessary for adding this approach to the <lb/>already-complex conduct of clinical trials. These are <lb/>understandable concerns for this stakeholder group <lb/>given limited resources at study sites for current data <lb/>management needs and competing priorities in <lb/>clinical trials [23]. Therefore, successful implemen-<lb/>tation of the PRO-CTCAE in cancer trials requires <lb/>commitment of resources and education of research <lb/>staff regarding its value as a data collection tool to <lb/>improve the quality, comprehensiveness, and effi-<lb/>ciency of AE data collection. Notably, clinical staff <lb/>members who have actively participated in pilot <lb/>studies including patient-reported AE data have <lb/>highly endorsed its use [20]. <lb/>Of note, patient respondents were more likely <lb/>than other respondent types to feel that patients <lb/>would be willing to self-report weekly from home <lb/>between visits. This bodes well for the use of a <lb/>between-visit approach to monitoring patient symp-<lb/>toms. It also reveals that clinical staff may under-<lb/>estimate the level of patient willingness or <lb/>enthusiasm to self-report from home. <lb/>The success of broadly integrating use of the PRO-<lb/>CTCAE items and software in cancer clinical research <lb/>as tools for AE documentation and to enhance clinical <lb/>decision-making will likely also depend on their <lb/>integration with clinical workflow and in particular <lb/>with other electronic systems used to manage clinical <lb/>trials and electronic health records [24]. As such, an <lb/>emphasis of the PRO-CTCAE initiative is integration <lb/>with other clinical systems. [25] <lb/>To date, version 1.0 of the PRO-CTCAE items <lb/>has been developed, encompassing 78 of the 790 <lb/>items in CTCAE version 4. [26] Cognitive inter-<lb/>views have been conducted in a diverse sample of <lb/>patients to assess the content validity of the items, <lb/>[27] and a multi-center validation study to assess the <lb/>measurement properties of the items is currently <lb/>underway. [28] An online portal for administering <lb/>these items to patients has been developed [25]. <lb/>Prior work demonstrates the feasibility of collecting <lb/>adverse symptom information directly from patients <lb/>during cancer treatment [15, 20, 21], and additional <lb/>feasibility studies in the NCI cooperative group <lb/>network are ongoing. <lb/> In generalizing our findings, it should be recog-<lb/>nized that a nonresponder bias may exist since our <lb/>sampling procedures did not allow us to determine <lb/>the response rate, and respondents comprise a <lb/>convenience sample of those investigators, data <lb/>managers, patient advocates, and regulators who <lb/>were willing to participate. As a result, there may be <lb/>unaccounted-for differences between survey res-<lb/>ponders and nonresponders in their perceptions <lb/>about patient self-reporting of adverse events. How-<lb/>ever, given the size and diversity of our sample, we <lb/>speculate that the high levels of overall endorsement <lb/>observed in our study are comparable to the view-<lb/>points of a majority of stakeholders. <lb/>As most participating investigators were aca-<lb/>demics and community-based practitioners work-<lb/>ing within the NCI&apos;s cooperative group network, <lb/>their sentiments may not extend to industry, <lb/>where most preapproval drug development is <lb/>conducted. However, many academic investiga-<lb/>tors serve as thought-leaders and advisors to <lb/>industry. Nonetheless, ascertainment of sentiments <lb/>towards such systems among stakeholders in the <lb/>pharmaceutical industry would necessitate addi-<lb/>tional study. Notably, other research is being <lb/>conducted to evaluate the extent to which patient <lb/>self-reporting of would affect the frequency of <lb/>reporting of adverse symptoms in clinical trials <lb/>compared with the current clinician-reporting <lb/>approach. It has been hypothesized that the <lb/>frequency of adverse symptoms not attributable <lb/>to products being studied (e.g., related to comor-<lb/>bidities or &quot; noise &quot; ) would actually be reduced, <lb/>while the power to detect adverse symptoms <lb/>attributable to products themselves would be <lb/>increased. Such properties would be appealing to <lb/>sponsors and regulators, but these evaluations are <lb/>pending. <lb/>The overall goal of a clinical trial is to collect <lb/>valid and reliable data about the efficacy and <lb/>adverse event profile of an intervention. This <lb/>information is used by investigators to understand <lb/>the properties of that intervention; by regulators <lb/>to assess its overall value to the public; and by <lb/>clinicians and patients during informed decision-<lb/>making. It has become clear that the current <lb/>mechanism for collecting adverse symptom event <lb/>information in trials does not adequately represent <lb/>the patient subjective experience with treatment. <lb/>As a consequence, the information about toler-<lb/>ability that is available to investigators, regulators, <lb/>clinicians, and patients when making decisions is <lb/>incomplete. To alleviate this gap, an approach to <lb/>systematically and efficiently collect patient-<lb/>reported adverse symptom events is indicated, <lb/>and the PRO-CTCAE represents one such <lb/>approach. The ultimate goal of this work is to <lb/>enhance the quality of information about the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">TBM <lb/></note>

			<page>page 117 of 122 <lb/></page>

			<body>impact of treatment on patients, to better inform <lb/>decision-making and to improve patient safety. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments: This work was supported by the National Cancer <lb/>Institute under contract HHSN261200800043C awarded to Dr. Ethan <lb/>Basch, PI. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">APPENDIX <lb/>DATE: _____/_____/_____ <lb/>(v11) <lb/>PRO-CTCAE STAKEHOLDER SURVEY <lb/>NCI is developing a system for patients to report their own adverse symptoms in clinical <lb/>treatment trials, called the PRO-CTCAE. This system will allow patients to self-report <lb/>selected CTCAE symptoms electronically (by computer) or via paper forms at clinic <lb/>visits. Clinicians and investigators will have access to this information for treatment <lb/>decisions and/or documentation. We are seeking your input to assist us in <lb/>understanding potential barriers to implementing such a system in the multicenter clinical <lb/>trial setting. <lb/>1(a). What is your current role (check all that apply): <lb/>__Lead PI on treatment trial protocols <lb/>__Investigator on treatment trial protocols <lb/>__QOL/Symptom researcher <lb/>__CRA/RSA (Research Assistant) <lb/>__Research nurse <lb/>__Member of cooperative group committee <lb/>__Cooperative group leadership (Committee Chair, Executive Committee member, etc) <lb/>__NCI representative <lb/>__FDA representative <lb/>__Patient advocate <lb/>__Representative of industry sponsor <lb/>1(b). If you are affiliated with a clinical trials cooperative group, please check all <lb/>that apply: <lb/>__ACoSOG <lb/>__ACRIN <lb/>__CALGB <lb/>__COG <lb/>__ECOG <lb/>__GOG <lb/>__NSABP <lb/>__NCCTG <lb/>__RTOG <lb/>__SWOG <lb/>2. Professional training: <lb/>__MD <lb/>__RN/NP <lb/>__PhD <lb/>__RPh/PharmD <lb/>__MPH or other Master&apos;s <lb/>__BA or BS <lb/>3. Have you worked with cancer populations? <lb/>__Yes __No <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">TBM <lb/></note>

			<page>page 118 of 122 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Please indicate how you perceive potential barriers to implementing a system for <lb/>patient self-reporting of adverse events in the multicenter clinical trials context: <lb/>4. PATIENT-RELATED ISSUES <lb/>Strongly <lb/>Agree <lb/>Somewhat <lb/>Agree <lb/>Neither <lb/>Agree <lb/>nor <lb/>Disagree <lb/>Somewhat <lb/>Disagree <lb/>Strongly <lb/>Disagree <lb/>Most patients participating in clinical trials of <lb/>cancer treatment would be willing to self-report <lb/>adverse symptoms at clinic visits <lb/>Strongly <lb/>Agree <lb/>Somewhat <lb/>Agree <lb/>Neither <lb/>Agree <lb/>nor <lb/>Disagree <lb/>Somewhat <lb/>Disagree <lb/>Strongly <lb/>Disagree <lb/>4a <lb/>If patients feel well enough to attend a clinic visit, <lb/>they are likely able to self-report their symptom <lb/>burden <lb/>4b <lb/>Severe illness or debilitation is a potential barrier <lb/>to patient self-reporting <lb/>4c <lb/>Caregivers will be able to report on behalf of <lb/>severely ill or debilitated patients <lb/>4d <lb/>Caregivers should be allowed to report symptom <lb/>burden on behalf of severely ill or debilitated <lb/>patients <lb/>4e <lb/>Most patients in clinical trials would be willing to <lb/>self-report symptoms from home on a weekly <lb/>basis (ie, by computer, automated telephone <lb/>system, handheld device, etc) <lb/>4f <lb/>5. CLINIC/STUDY SITE ISSUES <lb/>Limited space at my clinic site is a potential barrier <lb/>to implementing a system for collecting data <lb/>directly from patients <lb/>5a <lb/>Limited personnel at my clinic site is a potential <lb/>barrier to implementing a system for collecting <lb/>data directly from patients <lb/>5b <lb/>Limited time at my clinic site is a potential barrier <lb/>to implementing a system for collecting data <lb/>directly from patients <lb/>5c <lb/>Lack of computers for patients to use for self-<lb/>reporting is a potential barrier at my clinic site <lb/>5d <lb/>The above potential barriers could be overcome <lb/>with adequate funding <lb/>5e <lb/>My clinic site has research staff who could likely <lb/>assist patients with self-reporting symptoms in <lb/>clinical trials if such a system were adopted <lb/>5f <lb/>There are areas at my clinic site that could be <lb/>configured for patient self-reporting <lb/>5g <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">TBM <lb/></note>

			<page>page 119 of 122 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Strongly <lb/>Agree <lb/>Somewhat <lb/>Agree <lb/>Neither <lb/>Agree <lb/>nor <lb/>Disagree <lb/>Somewhat <lb/>Disagree <lb/>Strongly <lb/>Disagree <lb/>My clinic site has computers that could likely be <lb/>adapted for use by patients to self-report <lb/>symptoms in clinical trials <lb/>5h <lb/>My site would need to acquire new computers for <lb/>patient-reporting if such a system were adopted <lb/>5i <lb/>Desktop computer-based patient self-reporting is <lb/>feasible at my site <lb/>5j <lb/>Wireless laptop/tablet computer-based patient <lb/>self-reporting is feasible at my site <lb/>5k <lb/>Paper-based patient self-reporting is feasible <lb/>at my site <lb/>5l <lb/>6. YOUR OVERALL IMPRESSIONS <lb/>Strongly <lb/>Agree <lb/>Somewhat <lb/>Agree <lb/>Neither <lb/>Agree <lb/>nor <lb/>Disagree <lb/>Somewhat <lb/>Disagree <lb/>Strongly <lb/>Disagree <lb/>Systems to efficiently collect patient self-reported <lb/>adverse events in clinical trials should be <lb/>developed <lb/>6a <lb/>In general, patients better understand the severity <lb/>of their symptoms than clinicians <lb/>6b <lb/>There are some symptoms which clinicians better <lb/>understand than patients <lb/>6c <lb/>In clinical trials, adverse symptoms should only be <lb/>reported by patients and should not be separately <lb/>reported by clinicians <lb/>6d <lb/>In clinical trials, adverse symptoms should only be <lb/>reported by clinicians and should not be separately <lb/>reported by patients <lb/>6e <lb/>In clinical trials, adverse symptom information <lb/>should be reported by both patients and clinicians <lb/>6f <lb/>Both patient-reported and clinician-reported <lb/>adverse symptom information should be reported <lb/>in clinical trial results, and in drug labels <lb/>6g <lb/>Patient self-reporting of adverse symptoms in trials <lb/>would decrease my workload <lb/>6h <lb/>Patient self-reporting of adverse symptoms in trials <lb/>would increase my workload <lb/>6i <lb/>Patient self-reporting of adverse symptoms from <lb/>home between visits could provide valuable data <lb/>for assessing drug toxicities in clinical trials <lb/>6j <lb/>If patient-reported adverse symptoms were <lb/>included in drug labels, clinicians would use this <lb/>information to help describe the consequences of <lb/>treatment to future patients, and to shape <lb/>treatment recommendations <lb/>6k <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">TBM <lb/></note>

			<page>page 120 of 122 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>1. National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, U.S. <lb/>Department of Health and Human Services. Common Terminol-<lb/>ogy Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) Version 4.0. NIH <lb/>publication # 09-7473. Published May 29, 2009; Revised <lb/>Version 4.02 September 15, 2009 (available at http://evs.nci. <lb/>nih.gov/ftp1/CTCAE/CTCAE_4.03_2010-06-14_QuickReferen <lb/>ce_5x7.pdf, last accessed December 30, 2010). <lb/>2. Trotti, A., Colevas, A. D., et al. (2003). CTCAE v3.0: development of a <lb/>comprehensive grading system for the adverse effects of cancer <lb/>treatment. Seminars in Radiation Oncology, 13(3), 176–181. <lb/>3. Trotti, A., Colevas, A. D., Setser, A., &amp; Basch, E. (2007). Patient-<lb/>reported outcomes and the evolution of adverse event reporting <lb/>in oncology. Journal of Clinical Oncology, 25(32), 5121–5127. <lb/>4. Fromme, E. K., Eilers, K. M., et al. (2004). How accurate is <lb/>clinician reporting of chemotherapy adverse effects? A compar-<lb/>ison with patient-reported symptoms from the quality-of-life <lb/>questionnaire C30. Journal of Clinical Oncology, 22(17), 3485– <lb/>3490. <lb/>5. Basch, E. (2010). The missing voice of patients in drug-safety <lb/>reporting. The New England Journal of Medicine, 362(10), 865–869. <lb/>6. Pakhomov, S. V., Jacobsen, S. J., Chute, C. G., &amp; Roger, V. L. <lb/>(2008). Agreement between patient-reported symptoms and <lb/>their documentation in the medical record. American Journal of <lb/>Managed Care, 14, 530–539. <lb/>7. Schnadig, I. D., Fromme, E. K., et al. (2008). Patient-physician <lb/>disagreement regarding performance status is associated with <lb/>worse survivorship in patients with advanced cancer. Cancer, <lb/>113(8), 2205–2214. <lb/>8. Parliament, M. B., Danjoux, C. E., et al. (1985). Is cancer <lb/>treatment toxicity accurately reported? International Journal of <lb/>Radiation Oncology, Biology, Physics, 11(3), 603–608. <lb/>9. Basch, E., Iasonos, A., McDonough, T., Barz, A., Culkin, A., Kris, <lb/>M. G., et al. (2006). Clinician versus patient self-reporting of <lb/>symptoms during cancer treatment: a paired analysis using the <lb/>national cancer institute&apos;s common terminology criteria for <lb/>adverse events (CTCAE). The Lancet Oncology, 7(10), 903–909. <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">7. Patient self-reporting of CTCAE adverse symptoms would be useful for: <lb/>Strongly <lb/>Agree <lb/>Somewhat <lb/>Agree <lb/>Neither <lb/>Agree <lb/>nor <lb/>Disagree <lb/>Somewhat <lb/>Disagree <lb/>Strongly <lb/>Disagree <lb/>Providing information to inform treatment dose <lb/>modifications in clinical trials <lb/>7a. <lb/>Improving efficiency of data gathering in clinical <lb/>trials <lb/>7b. <lb/>Improving the completeness of symptom data <lb/>collection in clinical trials <lb/>7c. <lb/>Improving the accuracy of adverse event <lb/>documentation in clinical trials <lb/>7d. <lb/>Providing information for FDA to use when <lb/>evaluating the toxicities of drugs <lb/>7e. <lb/>Providing toxicity information for use in drug labels <lb/>7f. <lb/>Improving our understanding of the patient <lb/>experience with treatment <lb/>7g. <lb/>8. General comments, suggestions, or feedback are welcome and encouraged: <lb/>9. What features would you want to see in a system for patient self-reporting of <lb/>adverse events in clinical trials? <lb/>Please feel free to email any additional comments, or interest to become involved <lb/>in this effort, to Laura Sit (sitl@mskcc.org). <lb/>Thank you for taking the time to share your viewpoints, which we hope to use to design <lb/>a useful and valuable system. <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">TBM <lb/></note>

			<page>page 121 of 122 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>10. Bruner, D. W., Scott, C., et al. (1995). RTOG&apos;s first quality of life <lb/>study–RTOG 90-20: a phase II trial of external beam radiation with <lb/>etanidazole for locally advanced prostate cancer. International <lb/>Journal of Radiation Oncology Biology and Physics, 33(4), 901–906. <lb/>11. Varricchio, C. G., &amp; Sloan, J. A. (2002). The need for and <lb/>characteristics of randomized, phase III trials to evaluate <lb/>symptom management in patients with cancer. Journal of the <lb/>National Cancer Institute, 94(16), 1184–1185. <lb/>12. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, Food and Drug <lb/>Administration. Guidance for industry: Patient-reported out-<lb/>comes measures: Use in medical product development to <lb/>support labeling claims. Issued December 2009 (available at <lb/>http://www.fda.gov/downloads/Drugs/GuidanceComplianceRe <lb/>gulatoryInformation/Guidances/UCM193282.pdf, last accessed <lb/>February 9, 2011). <lb/>13. Willke, R. J., Burke, L. B., et al. (2004). Measuring treatment <lb/>impact: a review of patient-reported outcomes and other efficacy <lb/>endpoints in approved product labels. Controlled Clinical Trials, <lb/>25(6), 535–552. <lb/>14. Bruner, D. W., Bryan, C. J., Aaronson, N., Blackmore, C. C., <lb/>Brundage, M., Cella, D., et al. (2007). Issues and challenges with <lb/>integrating patient-reported outcomes in clinical trials supported <lb/>by the national cancer institute-sponsored clinical trials network. <lb/>Journal of Clinical Oncology, 25(32), 5051–5057. <lb/>15. Velikova, G. L., Booth, et al. (2004). Measuring quality of life in <lb/>routine oncology practice improves communication and patient <lb/>well-being: a randomized controlled trial. Journal of Clinical <lb/>Oncology, 22(4), 714–724. <lb/>16. Sloan, J. A., Cella, D., et al. (2005). Clinical significance of <lb/>patient-reported questionnaire data: another step toward con-<lb/>sensus. Journal of Clinical Epidemiology, 58(12), 1217–1219. <lb/>17. Lipscomb, J., Reeve, B. B., et al. (2007). Patient-reported <lb/>outcomes assessment in cancer trials: taking stock, moving <lb/>forward. Journal of Clinical Oncology, 25(32), 5133–5140. <lb/>18. Patrick, D. L., Ferketich, S. L., et al. (2003). National institutes of <lb/>health state-of-the-science conference statement: symptom man-<lb/>agement in cancer: pain, depression, and fatigue, July 15–17, 2002. <lb/>Journal of the National Cancer Institute, 95(15), 1110–1117. <lb/>19. Rock, E. P., Kennedy, D. L., et al. (2007). Patient-reported <lb/>outcomes supporting anticancer product approvals. Journal of <lb/>Clinical Oncology, 25(32), 5094–5099. <lb/>20. Basch, E., Artz, D., Dulko, D., Scher, K., Sabbatini, P., Hensley, <lb/>M., et al. (2005). Patient online self-reporting of toxicity <lb/>symptoms during chemotherapy. Journal of Clinical Oncology, <lb/>23(15), 3552–3561. <lb/>21. Abernethy, A. P., Ahmad, A., Zafar, S. Y., Wheeler, J. L., Reese, J. <lb/>B., &amp; Lyerly, H. K. (2010). Electronic patient-reported data <lb/>capture as a foundation of rapid learning cancer care. Medical <lb/>Care, 48(6 Suppl), S32–S38. <lb/>22. Committee on Cancer Clinical Trials and the NCI Cooperative <lb/>Group Program, Institute of Medicine. (2010). A national cancer <lb/>clinical trials system for the 21st century: reinvigorating the NCI <lb/>Cooperative group program. Washington: Institute of Medicine of <lb/>the National Academies. <lb/>23. Institute of Medicine, National Academy of Sciences. (2010). A <lb/>national cancer clinical trials system for the 21st century: reinvigorat-<lb/>ing the NCI cooperative group program. Washington, DC: National <lb/>Academies Press. <lb/>24. Buetow, K. H. (2009). An infrastructure for interconnecting <lb/>research institutions. Drug Discovery Today, 14(11–12), 605– <lb/>610. <lb/>25. Chilukuri, R., Gulati, M., Agarwal, H., Baumgartner, P., Reeve, B., <lb/>Sit, L., et al. (2009). Software system for administering the <lb/>Patient-Reported Outcomes version of the CTCAE (PRO-CTCAE). <lb/>Presented at the National Cancer Institute caBIG Annual Meeting, <lb/>Washington, DC. <lb/>26. Basch, E., Reeve, B. B., Cleeland, C. S., Sloan, J. A., Mendoza, T. <lb/>R., Abernethy, A. P., et al. (2010). Development of the patient-<lb/>reported version of the common terminology criteria for adverse <lb/>events (PRO-CTCAE). Presented at 2010 ASCO Annual Meeting, <lb/>Chicago, IL. J Clin Oncol 28 (suppl; abstr e19605). <lb/>27. Hay, J., Atkinson, T. M., Mendoza, T. R., Reeve, B. B., Willis, G., <lb/>Gagne, J. J., et al. (2010). Refinement of the patient-reported <lb/>outcomes version of the common terminology criteria for adverse <lb/>events (PRO-CTCAE) via cognitive interviewing. Presented at <lb/>2010 ASCO Annual Meeting, Chicago, IL. J Clin Oncol 28:15s <lb/>(suppl; abstr 9060). <lb/>28. Dueck, A. C., Mendoza, T. R., Reeve, B. B., Sloan, J. A., Cleeland, <lb/>C. S., Hay, J., et al. (2010) Validation study of the patient-<lb/>reported outcomes version of the common terminology criteria <lb/>for adverse events (PRO-CTCAE). Presented at 2010 ASCO Annual <lb/>Meeting, Chicago, IL. J Clin Oncol 28:15s (suppl; abstr TPS274). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">TBM <lb/></note>

			<page>page 122 of 122 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
