<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>Germ cell connectivity enhances cell death in response to DNA damage in Drosophila testis. <lb/>Kevin L. Lu 1,2,3 , Yukiko M. Yamashita 1,2,4,5 <lb/>1 Life Sciences Institute, 2 Cellular and Molecular Biology Program, 3 Medical Scientist Training <lb/>Program, 4 Department of Cell and Developmental Biology, 5 Howard Hughes Medical Institute, <lb/>University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI 48109 <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>Abstract <lb/>Two broadly known characteristics of germ cells in many organisms are their development as a <lb/>&apos;cyst&apos; of interconnected cells and their high sensitivity to DNA damage. Here we provide <lb/>evidence that these characteristics are linked, and that interconnectivity is a mechanism that <lb/>confers to the Drosophila testis a high sensitivity to DNA damage. We show that all germ cells <lb/>within a cyst die simultaneously even when only a subset of them exhibit detectable DNA <lb/>damage. Compromising connectivity results in cysts in which only a subset of germ cells die <lb/>upon DNA damage, lowering overall germ cell death. Our data indicate that a death-promoting <lb/>signal is shared through the intercellular connections of germ cells. Taken together, we propose <lb/>that intercellular connectivity is a mechanism that uniquely increases the sensitivity of the <lb/>germline to DNA damage, thereby protecting the integrity of gamete genomes that are passed on <lb/>to the next generation. <lb/></front>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>A prevalent feature of germ cell development across species is their proliferation as an <lb/>interconnected cluster of cells, widely known as a germ cell cyst. In many organisms from <lb/>insects to humans, germ cells divide with incomplete cytokinesis that results in interconnected <lb/>cells with shared cytoplasm, leading to cyst formation (Greenbaum, Iwamori, Buchold, &amp; <lb/>Matzuk, 2011; Haglund, Nezis, &amp; Stenmark, 2011; Pepling, de Cuevas, &amp; Spradling, 1999). <lb/>During oogenesis, this intercellular connectivity is critical for the process of oocyte specification, <lb/>allowing only some of the developing germ cells to become oocytes while the others adopt a <lb/>supportive role (de Cuevas, Lilly, &amp; Spradling, 1997; Lei &amp; Spradling, 2016; Pepling et al., <lb/>1999). For example, in the Drosophila ovary, four rounds of germ cell divisions with incomplete <lb/>cytokinesis results in a cyst of 16 interconnected germ cells, where only one becomes an oocyte <lb/>while the remaining 15 germ cells become nurse cells. During this process, nurse cells support <lb/>oocyte development by providing their cytoplasmic contents to oocytes via intercellular <lb/>trafficking (Cox, 2003; de Cuevas et al., 1997; Huynh &amp; St Johnston, 2004). In contrast to <lb/>oogenesis, where cytoplasmic connectivity has a clear developmental role in oocyte <lb/>determination, spermatogenesis is a process where all germ cells within a cyst are considered to <lb/>be equivalent and become mature gametes (Fuller, 1993; Yoshida, 2016). Despite the lack of a <lb/>&apos;nursing mechanism&apos; during spermatogenesis, intercellular connectivity is widely observed in <lb/>spermatogenesis from insects to humans (Greenbaum et al., 2011; Yoshida, 2016). While a <lb/>function for this connectivity has been proposed in post-meiotic spermatids (Braun, Behringer, <lb/>Peschon, Brinster, &amp; Palmiter, 1989), the biological significance of male germ cell connectivity <lb/>during pre-meiotic stages of spermatogenesis remains unknown. <lb/>Another well-known characteristic of the germline is its extreme sensitivity to DNA <lb/>damage compared to the soma, with clinical interventions such as radiation or chemotherapy <lb/>often resulting in impaired fertility (Arnon, Meirow, Lewis-Roness, &amp; Ornoy, 2001; Meistrich, <lb/>2013; Oakberg, 1955). It has been postulated that the high sensitivity of the germline to DNA <lb/>damage is part of a quality control mechanism for the germ cell genome, which is passed on to <lb/>the next generation (Gunes, Al-Sadaan, &amp; Agarwal, 2015). However, the means by which the <lb/>germline achieves such a high sensitivity to DNA damage remains unclear. <lb/>Here we provide evidence that germ cell connectivity serves as a mechanism to sensitize <lb/>the germline in response to DNA damage, inducing cell death in the Drosophila testis. We show <lb/>that an entire germ cell cyst undergoes synchronized cell death as a unit even when only a subset <lb/>of cells within the cyst exhibit detectable DNA damage. Disruption of germ cell connectivity in <lb/>mutants of the fusome, an organelle that connects the germ cells within a cyst, leads to death of <lb/>individual germ cells within a cyst in response to DNA damage, reducing overall germ cell <lb/>death. The sensitivity of a germ cell cyst to DNA damage increases as the number of <lb/>interconnected germ cells within increases, demonstrating that connectivity serves as a <lb/>mechanism to confer higher sensitivity to DNA damage. Taken together, we propose that germ <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>cell cyst formation serves as a mechanism to increase the sensitivity of genome surveillance, <lb/>ensuring the quality of the genome that is passed on to the next generation. <lb/>Results <lb/>Ionizing radiation induces spermatogonial death preferentially at the 16-cell stage. <lb/>The Drosophila testis serves as an excellent model to study germ cell development owing <lb/>to its well-defined spatiotemporal organization, with spermatogenesis proceeding from the apical <lb/>tip down the length of the testis. Germline stem cells (GSCs) divide to produce gonialblasts <lb/>(GBs), which undergo transit-amplifying divisions to become a cyst of 16 interconnected <lb/>spermatogonia (16-SG) before entering meiosis (Fig. 1A). In our previous study we showed that <lb/>protein starvation induces SG death, predominantly at the early stages (~4-SG stage) of SG <lb/>development (Yang &amp; Yamashita, 2015) (Fig. 1A). Starvation-induced SG death is mediated by <lb/>apoptosis of somatic cyst cells encapsulating the SGs (Yang &amp; Yamashita, 2015), which breaks <lb/>the &apos;blood-testis-barrier&apos; and leads to SG death (Fairchild, Smendziuk, &amp; Tanentzapf, 2015; Lim <lb/>&amp; Fuller, 2012). Though we also noted significant SG death at the 16-SG stage in the course of <lb/>our previous work, it was independent of nutrient conditions and thus was not the focus of the <lb/>study (Yang &amp; Yamashita, 2015). <lb/>In search of the cause of this 16-SG death, we discovered that it can be induced by <lb/>ionizing radiation (see methods). When adult flies were exposed to ionizing radiation that causes <lb/>DNA double strand breaks (DSBs), a dramatic induction of SG death was observed (Fig. 1B, C). <lb/>Dying SGs induced by ionizing radiation were detected by Lysotracker staining, which marks <lb/>acidified compartments, a hallmark of germ cell death (Yacobi-Sharon, Namdar, &amp; Arama, <lb/>2013; Yang &amp; Yamashita, 2015). SG death in control and irradiated flies proceeded in the same <lb/>manner, where all of the SGs within a cyst die simultaneously by becoming Lysotracker-positive <lb/>(Fig. 1B). Importantly, in contrast to starvation-induced SG death, which was dependent on <lb/>somatic cyst cell apoptosis, radiation-induced SG death was not suppressed by inhibiting cyst <lb/>cell apoptosis (Fig. 1 -Figure supplement 1), suggesting that radiation-induced SG death is a <lb/>germ cell-intrinsic response. <lb/>The frequency of dying SG cysts peaked around 3 to 6 hours after irradiation and <lb/>decreased by 24 hours post-irradiation (Fig. 1C). Interestingly, we found that ionizing radiation <lb/>robustly induces cell death at the 16-SG stage, although death of other stages (2-, 4-, 8-cell SGs) <lb/>was also induced (Fig. 1C and see below). This pattern of SG death held true regardless of the <lb/>ionizing radiation dose (Fig. 1 -Figure supplement 2). While testing multiple doses of ionizing <lb/>radiation, we noticed that even exposure to a very low dose of ionizing radiation could <lb/>dramatically induce death of 16-SGs. By measuring dose-dependent death of 16-SGs at six hours <lb/>post-irradiation, we found that the 16-SG death induced by increasing radiation was a distinctly <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>non-linear response, quickly reaching a plateau of ~3 dying 16-SG cysts per testis (Fig. 1D). In <lb/>comparison, somatic cell death in a defined area of the irradiated wing imaginal disc (Fig. 1 -<lb/>Figure supplement 3) followed a linear dose-response relationship where an increase in radiation <lb/>resulted in a proportional increase in cell death (Fig. 1D). These results demonstrate a <lb/>remarkable sensitivity of 16-SGs to ionizing radiation, compared to somatic cells from imaginal <lb/>discs. <lb/>All SGs within a cyst die even when only a subset of cells exhibit detectable DNA damage. <lb/>To gain insight into the cause of the unusual sensitivity of 16-SGs to DNA damage, we <lb/>evaluated the response of SGs to ionizing radiation at a cell biological level. DSBs result in <lb/>phosphorylation of the histone H2A variant (γ-H2Av), the Drosophila equivalent of mammalian <lb/>γ-H2AX, reflecting the very early cellular response to DSBs (Madigan, Chotkowski, &amp; Glaser, <lb/>2002). Using an anti-γ-H2Av antibody (pS137), we confirmed that γ-H2Av can be robustly <lb/>detected in SGs following a high dose of ionizing radiation (Fig. 2 -Figure supplement 1). When <lb/>a low dose of ionizing radiation was used, we frequently observed 16-SG cysts in which only a <lb/>subset of cells within the cyst possessed detectable γ-H2Av signal but all 16 cells were <lb/>Lysotracker-positive and dying (Fig. 2A). <lb/>The fraction of γ-H2Av-positive SGs within each cyst increased gradually with <lb/>increasing radiation dose irrespective of SG stage (Fig. 2B and Fig. 2 -Figure supplement 2), <lb/>consistent with the linear nature of ionizing radiation damaging DNA molecules (Ulsh, 2010). <lb/>However, Lysotracker staining showed that SGs within a cyst were always either all <lb/>Lysotracker-positive or -negative (Fig. 2C). These results suggest that while DNA damage is <lb/>induced in individual SGs within a cyst proportional to the dose of radiation, cell death is <lb/>induced in all of the SGs within the entire cyst, leading to elevated SG death that follows a non-<lb/>linear response with increasing dose. <lb/>The fusome is required for synchronized all-or-none SG death within the cysts. <lb/>The above results led us to hypothesize that all SGs within a cyst might be triggered to <lb/>die together even when only a subset of SGs within the cyst have detectable DNA damage, <lb/>explaining the extremely high sensitivity of the germline to DNA damage. In Drosophila and <lb/>other insects, the fusome is a germline-specific membranous organelle that connects the <lb/>cytoplasm of germ cells within a cyst and mediates intracyst signaling amongst germ cells (Lilly, <lb/>de Cuevas, &amp; Spradling, 2000; Lin, Yue, &amp; Spradling, 1994). We speculated that if germ cell <lb/>cysts undergo synchronized cell death by sharing the decision to die, the fusome might mediate <lb/>the &apos;all-or-none&apos; mode of SG death upon DNA damage. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>To examine the role of the fusome in all-or-none SG death upon irradiation, we used <lb/>RNAi-mediated knockdown of α-spectrin and a mutant of hts, core components of the fusome <lb/>(de Cuevas, Lee, &amp; Spradling, 1996; Lilly et al., 2000; Lin et al., 1994) (Fig. 3 -Figure <lb/>supplement 1). Mutant and control flies were irradiated and their testes were stained with <lb/>Lysotracker to identify dying SGs in combination with the lipophilic dye FM 4-64 to mark cyst <lb/>cell membranes, demarcating the boundaries of SG cysts (see methods) (Chiang, Yang, &amp; <lb/>Yamashita, 2017). In control testes, 16-SG cysts were almost always found to be either <lb/>completely Lysotracker-positive or -negative under all conditions tested as described above, <lb/>indicating that 16-SG cysts make an all-or-none death decision (Fig. 3A, B, E, F). Of particular <lb/>importance, even at a lower dose of radiation (e.g. 100 rad) where only a subset of germ cells <lb/>exhibit visible γ-H2Av staining (Fig. 2B), the 16-SG cyst was either entirely Lysotracker-<lb/>negative or -positive. In contrast, α-spectrin RNAi and hts mutant testes frequently contained 16-<lb/>SG cysts with a mixture of individual Lysotracker-positive and -negative SGs (Fig. 3C, D, G, H), <lb/>suggesting that the all-or-none mode of SG death was compromised. Importantly, the mean <lb/>fraction of 16-SG that died in response to radiation exposure at any dose was significantly <lb/>reduced when the fusome was disrupted (Fig. 3B, D, F, H, see Supplementary Table S1 for <lb/>statistics). These data show that the fusome is required for the coordinated death of all SGs <lb/>within a cyst, and suggests that connectivity of SGs increases overall SG death in response to <lb/>radiation-induced DNA damage. Moreover, the fact that loss of germ cell connectivity in fusome <lb/>mutants allows for the survival of some SGs strongly argues against the possibility that SGs <lb/>without cytologically detectable γ-H2Av are sufficiently damaged to trigger cell death on their <lb/>own, and that SGs are individually dying. Instead, the death of SGs without detectable γ-H2Av <lb/>in wild type/control can likely be attributed to a shared signal from other cells, as blockade of <lb/>intercellular communication in fusome mutants allows for their survival. <lb/>The mitochondrial protease HtrA2/Omi is required for all-or-none SG death <lb/>The above results suggest that intercellular connectivity mediated by the fusome plays a <lb/>critical role in allowing for all-or-none commitment of SGs to death or survival. Based on these <lb/>results, we hypothesized that a signal to promote cell death exists that is rapidly transmitted from <lb/>damaged SGs to others via their intercellular connections. <lb/>It has previously been shown that germ cell death in the Drosophila testis depends on <lb/>mitochondria-associated factors rather than effector caspases (Yacobi-Sharon et al., 2013). In <lb/>response to nuclear DNA damage, the Drosophila homolog of the mitochondrial serine protease <lb/>HtrA2/Omi is cleaved and released from the mitochondrial compartment as part of the <lb/>mitochondria-associated death pathway, and interacts with components of the apoptotic <lb/>machinery in the cytoplasm to promote cell death (Igaki et al., 2007; Khan et al., 2008; Tain et <lb/>al., 2009; Vande Walle, Lamkanfi, &amp; Vandenabeele, 2008). <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>In HtrA2/Omi mutant flies, we frequently observed a mix of Lysotracker-positive and -<lb/>negative SGs within a single cyst, similar to what was seen in fusome mutants (Fig. 4A). <lb/>Disruption of the all-or-none mode of SG death within the cyst was observed at any dose of <lb/>radiation tested (Fig. 4B). Disrupted all-or-none SG death occurred in both heterozygous <lb/>(Omi Δ1 /+) and transheterozygous (Omi Δ1 /Omi Df1 ) conditions, consistent with the previous report <lb/>that heterozygous conditions exhibit haploinsufficiency in inducing SG death (Yacobi-Sharon et <lb/>al., 2013). In contrast, wild type control 16-SG cysts maintained their all-or-none mode of SG <lb/>death (Fig. 4B). Taken together, these data show that HtrA2/Omi is critical for all-or-none SG <lb/>death within a cyst, and imply a role for HtrA2/Omi in propagating the signal to initiate germ <lb/>cell death within a SG cyst, possibly through its cycle of cleavage and release from <lb/>mitochondria. <lb/>p53 and mnk/chk2 do not regulate the all-or-none mode of SG death <lb/>The DNA damage response is a highly conserved pathway controlling cell death and <lb/>DNA repair (Ciccia &amp; Elledge, 2010; Song, 2005). We thus examined the potential involvement <lb/>in radiation-induced SG death of the universal DNA damage response pathway components, <lb/>mnk/chk2 and p53, whose conserved function in DNA damage response in Drosophila has been <lb/>shown (Brodsky et al., 2004; Peters et al., 2002). By using well-characterized loss-of-function <lb/>alleles (mnk 6006 and p53 5A-1-4 ) (Takada, Kelkar, &amp; Theurkauf, 2003; Wichmann, Jaklevic, &amp; Su, <lb/>2006; Xie &amp; Golic, 2004), we found that these mutants broadly suppress SG death at high and <lb/>low doses of radiation (Fig. 5D). However, SG death in these mutants maintained an all-or-none <lb/>pattern (Fig. 5A-C, E). These results suggest that while p53 and mnk/chk2 may contribute to SG <lb/>death via their general role in controlling the DNA damage response as has been described in <lb/>somatic cells, they do not play a role in mediating the all-or-none pattern of SG death within a <lb/>cyst that is unique to interconnected germ cells. <lb/>Consistent with the idea that neither mnk/chk2 or p53 is responsible for a germline-<lb/>specific DNA damage response, Mnk/Chk2 or p53 was not upregulated in the germline in <lb/>response to a low dose of radiation (100 rad), which is normally sufficient to induce robust SG <lb/>death. Using a polyclonal anti-Mnk/Chk2 antibody (Takada, Collins, &amp; Kurahashi, 2015), we <lb/>were unable to detect induction of Mnk/Chk2 at a low radiation dose, and even at a high dose <lb/>Mnk/Chk2 staining was mostly limited to somatic cells (Fig. 5 -Figure supplement 1). Likewise, <lb/>a p53 transcriptional reporter (Wylie et al., 2014) was not upregulated in response to a low dose <lb/>of radiation (Fig. 5 -Figure supplement 2). Even at a high dose, the reporter expression was <lb/>observed only at 24 hours after irradiation, much later than the peak of SG death, which typically <lb/>happens within a few hours. Collectively, these data indicate that differential expression of p53 <lb/>or Mnk/Chk2 in SGs is unlikely to account for the high sensitivity of the germline to DNA <lb/>damage. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Increasing connectivity of SGs inherently increases sensitivity to DNA damage <lb/>The above results suggest that the robust ability of SGs to trigger cell death in response to <lb/>DNA damage is facilitated by the sharing of signals to die amongst SGs within a cyst, killing <lb/>SGs that are not sufficiently damaged to commit to cell death on their own. This sharing of death <lb/>signals is mediated by and dependent on germ cell connectivity. If this is the case, it would be <lb/>predicted that increasing the connectivity of a SG cyst (the number of interconnected SGs within <lb/>the cyst) would increase its sensitivity to DNA damage. Indeed, as mentioned above, we <lb/>observed a trend of 16-SG cysts dying more frequently than 2-, 4-, or 8-SGs (Fig. 1C, Fig 1 -<lb/>Figure supplement 2). By plotting cell death frequency of all SG stages as a function of <lb/>increasing radiation dose (Fig. 6A), it becomes clear that the sensitivity of SG cysts correlates <lb/>with their connectivity, where 8-SGs are less sensitive than 16-SGs but more sensitive than 4-<lb/>SGs and so on. Interestingly, single-celled GBs, the immediate daughter of GSCs that have not <lb/>formed any intercellular connections, exhibited an essentially linear increase in death in response <lb/>to radiation dose, which is reminiscent of somatic imaginal disc cells (Fig. 1D). These results <lb/>further support the idea that germ cell connectivity plays a key role in increasing the sensitivity <lb/>of the germline to DNA damage. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Our present study may provide a link between two long-standing observations in germ <lb/>cell biology: 1) the broad conservation of intercellular connectivity (cyst formation) of germ <lb/>cells and 2) the increased sensitivity of the germline to DNA damage compared to the soma. Our <lb/>study shows that the connectivity of germ cells is a key mechanism for their ability to robustly <lb/>induce cell death. We propose that connectivity allows for the sharing of signals that leads to cell <lb/>death (Fig. 6B). We imagine two possibilities to explain how the signals are shared leading to <lb/>cell death: when one SG within a cyst decides to die, this &apos;decision of death&apos; might be sent to all <lb/>the other SGs within the cyst, leading to all-or-none SG death. Alternatively, the signal shared <lb/>among SGs may be &apos;additive&apos; in nature. In such a scenario, even when none of the individual <lb/>SGs have sufficient DNA damage to trigger cell death on its own, addition of all damage <lb/>signaling within the cyst might reach a level sufficient to cause activation of an intracellular <lb/>cascade that induces cell death. Such a response would effectively lower the threshold of DNA <lb/>damage needed per cell to trigger germ cell death. Either way, the sharing of signals between <lb/>SGs through intercellular connections increases their likelihood to die following DNA damage, <lb/>explaining the unusually high sensitivity of the germline to DNA damage. <lb/>According to this model, higher connectivity would confer higher sensitivity to DNA <lb/>damage: as the connectivity increases, more cells would contribute to detecting any DNA <lb/>damage the germline may be experiencing. Indeed, our data show a direct correlation between <lb/>sensitivity to radiation and the increasing connectivity of SG cysts (Fig. 6A). Remarkably, the <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>fact that single-celled, unconnected GBs exhibit an essentially linear death response to increasing <lb/>radiation suggests that individual germ cells do not have an intrinsically different DNA damage <lb/>response that accounts for their high sensitivity to DNA damage (Fig. 6A). <lb/>A connectivity-based increase in sensitivity to DNA damage also has an important <lb/>implication in the development of multicellular organisms. To pass on genomes to the next <lb/>generation, it is critically important for germ cells to have the most stringent mechanisms to <lb/>prevent deleterious mutations. However, as genome size increases in multicellular organisms, <lb/>ubiquitously increasing the stringency of genome quality control would result in a high rate of <lb/>cell death in all tissues, which could compromise the development or survival of organisms. <lb/>Thus, a multicellular organism would require differential sensitivities to DNA damage between <lb/>the soma and the germline. The germline would require a more sensitive genome surveillance <lb/>mechanism to produce gametes with the highest genome quality, whereas the priority of the <lb/>soma shifts toward survival in order to support development and maintenance of somatic organs. <lb/>A connectivity-based increase in sensitivity to DNA damage would be a simple method for <lb/>multicellular organisms to achieve drastically different sensitivities to DNA damage between the <lb/>soma and germline without having to alter intrinsic damage response pathways. Thus, we <lb/>speculate that one reason germ cell connectivity has arisen during evolution might be to confer <lb/>higher sensitivity to DNA damage specifically in the germline. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We thank Drs. Saeko Takada, William Theurkauf, Eli Arama, and John Abrams for reagents. <lb/>Bloomington Stock Center, the Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank for reagents, the <lb/>University of Michigan Experimental Irradiation Core for radiation experiments, Lei Lei, Sue <lb/>Hammoud and Yamashita lab members for comments on the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions <lb/>K.L. conducted all experiments. K.L. and Y.Y. designed experiments, interpreted results, <lb/>analyzed the data and wrote the manuscript. <lb/>This work was supported the University of Michigan Medical Scientist Training Program, by the <lb/>University of Michigan Career Training in Reproductive Biology training grant [T32 <lb/>HD079342] and by NIH Fellowship [F30 AG050398-01] to K.L. The research in the Yamashita <lb/>laboratory is supported by the Howard Hughes Medical Institute. Y.M.Y. is supported by the <lb/>MacArthur Foundation. Deposited in PMC for release after 6 months. <lb/></div>

			<body>Materials and methods <lb/>Fly husbandry and strains: <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>All fly stocks were raised on standard Bloomington medium at 25°C, and young flies (0 <lb/>to 2-day old adults) were used for all experiments unless otherwise noted. The following fly <lb/>stocks were used: hts 01103 (Yuan, Chiang, Cheng, Salzmann, &amp; Yamashita, 2012), nos-gal4 (Van <lb/>Doren, Williamson, &amp; Lehmann, 1998), UAS-α-spectrin RNAi (TRiP.HMC04371), c587-gal4 <lb/>(Decotto &amp; Spradling, 2005), UAS-Diap1 (obtained from the Bloomington Stock Center), p53 5A-<lb/>1-4 (Wichmann et al., 2006; Xie &amp; Golic, 2004), Df(2R)BSC26, Df(3R)ED6096, Df(2L)Exel7077 <lb/>(obtained from the Bloomington Stock Center), p53RE-GFP-nls reporter (Wylie et al., 2014) (a <lb/>gift of John Abrams, University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center), Omi Δ1 , Omi Df1 (Tain et <lb/>al., 2009; Yacobi-Sharon et al., 2013) (a gift of Eli Arama, Weizmann Institute of Science), <lb/>mnk 6006 (Takada et al., 2003) (a gift of William Theurkauf, University of Massachusetts Medical <lb/>School). <lb/>Immunofluorescence staining and microscopy: <lb/>Immunofluorescence staining of testes was performed as described previously (Cheng et <lb/>al., 2008). Briefly, testes were dissected in PBS, transferred to 4% formaldehyde in PBS and <lb/>fixed for 30 minutes. Testes were then washed in PBS-T (PBS containing 0.1% Triton-X) for at <lb/>least 60 minutes, followed by incubation with primary antibody in 3% bovine serum albumin <lb/>(BSA) in PBS-T at 4°C overnight. Samples were washed for 60 minutes (three 20-minute <lb/>washes) in PBS-T, incubated with secondary antibody in 3% BSA in PBS-T at 4°C overnight, <lb/>washed as above, and mounted in VECTASHIELD with DAPI (Vector Labs). The following <lb/>primary antibodies were used: mouse anti-Adducin-like 1B1 (hu-li tai shao -Fly Base) [1:20; <lb/>Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank (DSHB); developed by H.D. Lipshitz]; mouse anti-<lb/>alpha-spectrin 3A9 (1:20; DSHB; developed by R. Dubreuil, T. Byers); rat anti-vasa (1:50; <lb/>DSHB; developed by A. Spradling), rabbit anti-vasa (1:200; d-26; Santa Cruz Biotechnology), <lb/>mouse anti-Fasciclin III (1:200; DSHB; developed by C. Goodman), anti-LaminDm0 (1:200; <lb/>DSHB; developed by P. A. Fisher), rabbit anti-γ-H2AvD pS137 (1:100;Rockland), rabbit anti-<lb/>mnk (1:100; courtesy of Saeko Takada). Images were taken using a Leica TCS SP8 confocal <lb/>microscope with 63x oil-immersion objectives (NA=1.4) and processed using Adobe Photoshop <lb/>software. For detection of germ cell death, testes were stained with Lysotracker Red DND-99 in <lb/>PBS (1:1000) for 30 minutes prior to formaldehyde fixation. Stages (GB, 2-, 4-, 8-, and 16-SGs) <lb/>of dying SGs were identified by counting the number of nuclei within the cyst visualized by <lb/>Lamin Dm0 and DAPI (Chiang et al., 2017). Note that the number of &apos;stageable&apos; dying SGs <lb/>underrepresents the total population of dying SGs, because nuclear structures disintegrate during <lb/>later phases of cell death and make it impossible to count the number of SGs within a dying cyst <lb/>(Chiang et al., 2017). Such &apos;unstageable&apos; SGs were not included in the scoring in this study. <lb/>For observation of unfixed samples, testes were dissected directly into PBS and incubated <lb/>in the dark with the desired dyes for 5 minutes, mounted on slides with PBS and imaged within <lb/>10 minutes of dissection. The dyes used in live imaging are: Lysotracker Red DND-99 (1:200) or <lb/>Lysotracker Green DND-26 (1:200) (Thermo Fisher Scientific), Hoechst 33342 (1:200), and <lb/>FM4-64FX in PBS (1:200) (Thermo Fisher Scientific). SG stage (2-, 4-, 8-, or 16-SG) was <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>assessed by number of Hoechst-stained nuclei only when using unfixed samples. Note that the <lb/>scoring of dying SGs is not directly comparable between fixed and unfixed samples (for <lb/>example, results shown in Fig. 1 vs. Fig. 2), due to the difference in the method of SG staging <lb/>and timing. In unfixed samples, SG cysts were staged by the number of Hoechst 33342-positive <lb/>nuclei per cyst marked by FM4-64FX, whereas in fixed samples SG cysts were staged by the <lb/>number of Lamin Dm0-positive nuclei per cyst. <lb/>Ionizing radiation <lb/>For radiation doses of 25-250 rad, a 137 Cs source was used with a dose rate of <lb/>approximately 100 rad per minute. Additionally, for radiation doses 100 rad and above, a Philips <lb/>RT250 model or Kimtron Medical IC-320 orthovoltage unit was used (dose rates of 200 and 400 <lb/>rad per minute respectively). Dosimetry was carried out using an ionization chamber connected <lb/>to an electrometer system directly traceable to National Institute of Standards and Technology <lb/>calibration. The relative biological effectiveness of 137 Cs and x-ray sources is comparable at <lb/>lower doses (Fu, Phillips, Heilbron, Ross, &amp; Kane, 1979), and experiments were repeated with <lb/>both sources for 100-250 rad, which yielded essentially the same results irrespective of radiation <lb/>source. <lb/>TUNEL Assay <lb/>Larval heads with imaginal discs attached were dissected from third instar larvae into <lb/>PBS, then fixed in 4% formaldehyde in PBS for 30 minutes. Samples were then washed in PBS-<lb/>T (PBS containing 0.1% Triton-X) for at least 20 minutes, transferred to 100% methanol for 6 <lb/>minutes with rocking, and washed again for at least 20 minutes in PBS-T. TUNEL assay was <lb/>then carried out according to manufacturer&apos;s instructions using a Millipore ApopTag Red In Situ <lb/>Apoptosis Detection Kit (S7165). Following washes with PBS-T for 20 minutes, wing imaginal <lb/>discs were dissected from larval heads and mounted in VECTASHIELD with DAPI (Vector <lb/>Labs). <lb/>Dose-response best fit regressions <lb/>Best fit functions and lines for radiation dose-cell death response curves were generated <lb/>by using GraphPad Prism 7 and the means-only values at all doses. Non-linear regressions were <lb/>determined using a four-parameter logistic curve with no constraints on bottom, top, or hillslope <lb/>and &gt;1500 iterations. Standard linear regression was performed using cell death as a function of <lb/>radiation dose. Goodness of fit, unadjusted R 2 value, was determined by 1.0 less the ratio of the <lb/>regression sum of squares to the total sum of squares, 1 -SS reg /SS tot. <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure legends: <lb/>Figure 1. A high level of SG death in response to ionizing radiation. <lb/>(A) Illustration of SG development and germ cell death in the Drosophila testis. <lb/>(B) An example of the testis apical tip (left panels) with dying SGs marked by Lysotracker <lb/>staining in control and irradiated flies. High magnification images of dying 16-SGs (dotted <lb/>outline) are shown in right panels. Lysotracker (red), Vasa (white), FasIII and Lamin Dm0 <lb/>(green), and DAPI (blue). Bars: 25µm (left panels), 5 μm (right panels). <lb/>(C) Quantification of dying SG cysts by stage from 3 to 24 hours after 3000 rad (Mean ± SD). <lb/>Testes sample n ≥ 17, repeated in triplicate. <lb/>(D) Number of Lysotracker-positive 16-SG cysts (red) and TUNEL-positive wing imaginal disc <lb/>cells (black) 6 hours post-irradiation as a function of radiation dose (Mean ± SD). Testes n ≥ 17 <lb/>and wing disc n ≥ 3, repeated in triplicate. Best fit lines shown determined by non-linear <lb/>regression. <lb/>Fig. 1 -Figure supplement 1. Radiation-induced SG cyst death is independent of somatic <lb/>cyst cell apoptosis. <lb/>(A) Representative images of testes apical tips from wild type, c587-gal4&gt;UAS-Diap1, and nos-<lb/>gal4&gt;UAS-Diap1 expressing flies six hours after 2000 rad. Lysotracker (red), Vasa (white), <lb/>FasIII and Lamin Dm0 (green), DAPI (blue). Bars: 25 µm. <lb/>(B) Quantification of dying SG cysts by stage from above (Mean ± SD), testes sample n ≥ 15 <lb/>repeated in triplicate for each. No significant differences at any SG stage between WT vs. <lb/>c587&gt;Diap1 or nos&gt;Diap1 (p-value * &lt;0.05 t-test). <lb/>Fig. 1 -Figure supplement 2. SG death in response to ionizing radiation. <lb/>Quantification of SG death by stage and time following varying doses of ionizing radiation. (A) <lb/>25 rad (n = 66), (B) 2000 rad (n = 84), (C) 4000 rad (n = 68). <lb/>Fig. 1 -Figure supplement 3. TUNEL staining to detect somatic cell death in response to <lb/>ionizing radiation. <lb/>TUNEL-positive foci were quantified in a defined 50 μm 2 field (dotted square) through entire z-<lb/>sections in the anterior-ventral compartment of the wing imaginal discs from L3 larvae. <lb/>Figure 2. All SGs within a cyst die even when only a fraction of cells exhibit detectable <lb/>DNA damage. <lb/>(A) An example of a dying 16-SG cyst (yellow dotted outline) with only a subset of SGs <lb/>containing detectable DNA damage (arrowhead). γ-H2Av (green), Lysotracker (red), Vasa <lb/>(white). Bar: 5 µm. <lb/>(B) Number of γ-H2Av-positive cells within each 16-SG cyst at various radiation doses. Blue <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>circles, individual data points. Red line, mean. <lb/>(C) Number of Lysotracker-positive cells within each 16-SG cyst. Blue circles, individual data <lb/>points. Red line, mean. <lb/>Fig. 2 -Figure supplement 1. γ-H2Av can be strongly detected in germ cells following <lb/>irradiation. <lb/>Representative images of testes apical tips from unirradiated and irradiated flies. Vasa (white), <lb/>FasIII and γ-H2Av (green). Bar: 25 µm. <lb/>Fig. 2 -Figure supplement 2. All SG stages show gradual accumulation of γ-H2Av-positive <lb/>cells with increasing radiation. <lb/>Number of γ-H2Av-positive cells per cyst at increasing radiation doses in (A) germline stem <lb/>cells (B) gonialblasts (C) 2-SG (D) 4-SG (E) 8-SG. Red line, mean. <lb/>Figure 3. The fusome is required for synchronized all-or-none SG death within a cyst. <lb/>(A) A Lysotracker-positive 16-SG cyst (green, dotted outline) in unfixed control testes, with cyst <lb/>borders marked by FM 4-64 (red) and SG nuclei marked by Hoechst 33342 (blue). Bar: 7.5 µm. <lb/>(B) Number of Lysotracker-positive cells within each 16-SG cyst of control testes at varying <lb/>radiation doses. Black line, mean. <lb/>(C) A 16-SG cyst (dotted outline) in nos-gal4&gt;UAS-α-spectrin RNAi testes containing a single <lb/>Lysotracker-positive SG (arrowhead). Bar: 10 μm. <lb/>(D) Number of Lysotracker-positive cells within each 16-SG cyst of nos-gal4&gt;UAS-α-<lb/>spectrin RNAi testes at varying radiation doses. Black line, mean. <lb/>(E, F) hts 01103 /+ control testes. Bar: 5 μm. <lb/>(G, H) hts 01103 /Df(2R)BSC26 mutant testes. Bar: 7.5 μm. <lb/>Fig. 3 -Figure supplement 1. Validation of fusome elimination in hts mutant and α-<lb/>spectrin RNAi testes. <lb/>(A, B) Hts/Adducin staining (red) in control (A) and hts 01103 /Df(2R)BSC26 mutant (B) testes. <lb/>Red: Hts/Add and FasIII. Green: Vasa (germ cells). Bars: 25 µm. Note that hts mutation <lb/>eliminates fusome staining (leaving FasIII staining of the hub cells). <lb/>(C, D) α-Spectrin staining (red) in control (C) and nos-gal4&gt;UAS-spectrin RNAi (D) testes. α-<lb/>Spectrin and FasIII (red). Green: Vasa. Blue: DAPI. <lb/>Figure 4. The mitochondrial protease HtrA2/Omi is required for all-or-none SG death. <lb/>(A) SG cysts (dotted outlines) in Omi Δ1 /Omi Df1 mutant testes containing individual Lysotracker-<lb/>positive SG (arrows). Hoechst 33342 (blue), FM 4-64 (red), Lysotracker (green). Bar: 10 µm. <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>(B) Number of Lysotracker-positive SG in each 16-SG cyst in Omi Δ1 /Omi Df1 , Omi Δ1 /+, and wild <lb/>type testes. Black line, mean. <lb/>Figure 5. p53 and Chk2/mnk supress SG death but do not regulate the all-or-none mode of <lb/>SG death. <lb/>(A-C) Examples of dying 16-SGs (dotted outline) in wild-type (A), mnk 6006 /Df(2L)Exel7077 <lb/>mutant (B), and p53 5A-1-4 /Df(3R)ED6096 mutant (C) testes. Lysotracker (red), Lamin Dm0 <lb/>(green), DAPI (blue) and Vasa (white). Bars: 5 µm. <lb/>(D-G) SG cyst death by stage in mnk/chk2 (D, F) and p53 (E, G) mutants 6 hours after irradiation <lb/>with 100 rad (D, E) and 2000 rad (F, G) (Mean ± SD, p-value * &lt;0.05 t-test). Fixed, stained <lb/>samples were used for scoring. Testes sample n ≥ 11 for each genotype, repeated in triplicate. <lb/>(H) Number of Lysotracker-positive SG per 16-SG cyst in mnk/chk2 and p53 mutants following <lb/>100 rad. Red line, mean. Unfixed samples stained with Lysotracker, FM 4-64, and Hoechst <lb/>33342 were used for scoring. <lb/>Fig. 5 -Figure supplement 1. Expression of Mnk/Chk2 in response to ionizing radiation. <lb/>Testes from unirradiated flies (A), flies irradiated with 100 rad (B-D), or with 4000 rad (E-G), <lb/>stained for Mnk/Chk2 (red), Vasa (white), Hts (green), and DAPI (blue). Bars: 25 µm. <lb/>Mnk/Chk2 was detected only after a high dose of radiation, predominantly in the somatic cyst <lb/>cells surrounding the Vasa-positive germ cells. <lb/>Fig. 5 -Figure supplement 2. Expression of p53 reporter in response to ionizing radiation. <lb/>Testes from unirradiated flies (A), flies irradiated with 100 rad (B-D), or with 4000 rad (E-G), <lb/>stained for p53RE-GFPnls (green), Vasa (blue), Hts/Adducin and FasIII (red). Bars: 25 µm. <lb/>p53RE-GFPnls was only detectable 24 hours following irradiation at a high dose (4000 rad). <lb/>Figure 6. Increasing connectivity confers higher sensitivity to DNA damage <lb/>(A) Dose-dependent SG death in 2-, 4-, 8-, and 16-SG cysts (Mean ± SD). Best fit lines shown <lb/>determined by non-linear regression. Testes n ≥ 17, repeated in triplicate. <lb/>(B) Model of SG death enhanced by connectivity. <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Dose (rad) <lb/>Control <lb/>95% CI <lb/>α-Spectrin RNAi <lb/>95% CI <lb/>Kolmogorov-<lb/>Smirnov <lb/>p-value <lb/>100 <lb/>5.961 3.763&lt;μ&lt;8.158 <lb/>0.7647 0.0453&lt;μ&lt;1.484 <lb/>0.0035 <lb/>500 <lb/>5.073 3.427&lt;μ&lt;6.719 <lb/>2.316 1.049&lt;μ&lt;3.583 <lb/>0.0582 <lb/>1000 <lb/>7.442 4.957&lt;μ&lt;9.927 <lb/>2.722 0.8946&lt;μ&lt;4.55 <lb/>0.0147 <lb/>2000 <lb/>7.309 5.143&lt;μ&lt;9.475 <lb/>2.578 0.9354&lt;μ&lt;4.22 <lb/>0.0121 <lb/>3000 <lb/>5.517 2.573&lt;μ&lt;8.461 <lb/>2.955 0.1622&lt;μ&lt;5.747 <lb/>0.8397 <lb/>Dose (rad) <lb/>hts Control <lb/>95% CI <lb/>hts mutant <lb/>95% CI <lb/>Kolmogorov-<lb/>Smirnov <lb/>p-value <lb/>100 <lb/>2.5 1.317&lt;μ&lt;3.683 <lb/>0.5205 <lb/>0&lt;μ&lt;1.137 <lb/>0.4966 <lb/>500 <lb/>2.282 0.956&lt;μ&lt;3.607 <lb/>0.6727 0.019&lt;μ&lt;1.327 <lb/>0.7395 <lb/>1000 <lb/>4.14 1.972&lt;μ&lt;6.307 <lb/>0.575 <lb/>0&lt;μ&lt;1.407 <lb/>0.2195 <lb/>2000 <lb/>6 3.491&lt;μ&lt;8.509 <lb/>1.211 <lb/>0&lt;μ&lt;2.445 <lb/>0.0348 <lb/>3000 <lb/>3.646 2.133&lt;μ&lt;5.158 <lb/>1.578 0.3153&lt;μ&lt;2.84 <lb/>0.4457 <lb/>
			Supplementary Table S1. Fraction of 16-SG dying in fusome mutants. <lb/>Statistics for mean number of dying cells per 16-SG cyst from Fig. 3 in control and fusome <lb/>mutants. Kolmogrov-Smirnov test for comparing the distribution of two data sets at a given dose <lb/>of radiation. <lb/></div>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Arnon, J., Meirow, D., Lewis-Roness, H., &amp; Ornoy, A. (2001). Genetic and teratogenic effects of <lb/>cancer treatments on gametes and embryos. Human Reproduction Update, 7(4), 394-403. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1093/HUMUPD/7.4.394 <lb/>Braun, R. E., Behringer, R. R., Peschon, J. J., Brinster, R. L., &amp; Palmiter, R. D. (1989). <lb/>Genetically haploid spermatids are phenotypically diploid. Nature, 337(6205), 373-6. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1038/337373a0 <lb/>Brodsky, M. H., Weinert, B. T., Tsang, G., Rong, Y. S., McGinnis, N. M., Golic, K. G., … <lb/>Rubin, G. M. (2004). Drosophila melanogaster MNK/Chk2 and p53 regulate multiple DNA <lb/>repair and apoptotic pathways following DNA damage. Molecular and Cellular Biology, <lb/>24(3), 1219-31. Retrieved from http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/14729967 <lb/>Cheng, J., Türkel, N., Hemati, N., Fuller, M. T., Hunt, A. J., &amp; Yamashita, Y. M. (2008). <lb/>Centrosome misorientation reduces stem cell division during ageing. Nature, 456(7222), <lb/>599-604. http://doi.org/10.1038/nature07386 <lb/>Chiang, A. C.-Y., Yang, H., &amp; Yamashita, Y. M. (2017). spict, a cyst cell-specific gene, <lb/>regulates starvation-induced spermatogonial cell death in the Drosophila testis. Scientific <lb/>Reports, 7, 40245. http://doi.org/10.1038/srep40245 <lb/>Ciccia, A., &amp; Elledge, S. J. (2010). The DNA Damage Response: Making It Safe to Play with <lb/>Knives. Molecular Cell, 40(2), 179-204. http://doi.org/10.1016/j.molcel.2010.09.019 <lb/>Cox, R. T. (2003). A Balbiani body and the fusome mediate mitochondrial inheritance during <lb/>Drosophila oogenesis. Development, 130(8), 1579-1590. http://doi.org/10.1242/dev.00365 <lb/>de Cuevas, M., Lee, J. K., &amp; Spradling, A. C. (1996). alpha-spectrin is required for germline cell <lb/>division and differentiation in the Drosophila ovary. Development, 122(12). <lb/>de Cuevas, M., Lilly, M., &amp; Spradling, A. (1997). GERMLINE CYST FORMATION IN <lb/>DROSOPHILA. Annual Review of Genetics, 31(1), 405-428. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.genet.31.1.405 <lb/>Decotto, E., &amp; Spradling, A. C. (2005). The Drosophila Ovarian and Testis Stem Cell Niches: <lb/>Similar Somatic Stem Cells and Signals. Developmental Cell, 9(4), 501-510. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1016/j.devcel.2005.08.012 <lb/>Fairchild, M. J., Smendziuk, C. M., &amp; Tanentzapf, G. (2015). A somatic permeability barrier <lb/>around the germline is essential for Drosophila spermatogenesis. Development, 142(2), <lb/>268-281. http://doi.org/10.1242/dev.114967 <lb/>Fu, K. K., Phillips, T. L., Heilbron, D. C., Ross, G., &amp; Kane, L. J. (1979). Relative Biological <lb/>Effectiveness of Low-and High-LET Radiotherapy Beams for Jejunal Crypt Cell Survival <lb/>at Low Doses Per Fraction. Radiology, 132(1), 205-209. http://doi.org/10.1148/132.1.205 <lb/>Fuller, M. T. (1993). Spermatogenesis. In The Development of Drosophila melanogaster. In The <lb/>Development of Drosophila melanogaster (Vol. 1, pp. 71-147). New York: Cold Spring <lb/>Harbor Laboratory Press. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Greenbaum, M. P., Iwamori, T., Buchold, G. M., &amp; Matzuk, M. M. (2011). Germ cell <lb/>intercellular bridges. Cold Spring Harbor Perspectives in Biology, 3(8), a005850. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1101/cshperspect.a005850 <lb/>Gunes, S., Al-Sadaan, M., &amp; Agarwal, A. (2015). Spermatogenesis, DNA damage and DNA <lb/>repair mechanisms in male infertility. Reproductive BioMedicine Online, 31(3), 309-319. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1016/j.rbmo.2015.06.010 <lb/>Haglund, K., Nezis, I. P., &amp; Stenmark, H. (2011). Structure and functions of stable intercellular <lb/>bridges formed by incomplete cytokinesis during development. Communicative &amp; <lb/>Integrative Biology, 4(1), 1-9. http://doi.org/10.4161/cib.4.1.13550 <lb/>Huynh, J.-R., &amp; St Johnston, D. (2004). The Origin of Asymmetry: Early Polarisation of the <lb/>Drosophila Germline Cyst and Oocyte. Current Biology, 14(11), R438-R449. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2004.05.040 <lb/>Igaki, T., Suzuki, Y., Tokushige, N., Aonuma, H., Takahashi, R., &amp; Miura, M. (2007). Evolution <lb/>of mitochondrial cell death pathway: Proapoptotic role of HtrA2/Omi in Drosophila. <lb/>Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications, 356(4), 993-997. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbrc.2007.03.079 <lb/>Khan, F. S., Fujioka, M., Datta, P., Fernandes-Alnemri, T., Jaynes, J. B., &amp; Alnemri, E. S. <lb/>(2008). The interaction of DIAP1 with dOmi/HtrA2 regulates cell death in Drosophila. Cell <lb/>Death and Differentiation, 15(6), 1073-83. http://doi.org/10.1038/cdd.2008.19 <lb/>Lei, L., &amp; Spradling, A. C. (2016). Mouse oocytes differentiate through organelle enrichment <lb/>from sister cyst germ cells. Science, 352(6281), 95-99. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1126/science.aad2156 <lb/>Lilly, M. A., de Cuevas, M., &amp; Spradling, A. C. (2000). Cyclin A Associates with the Fusome <lb/>during Germline Cyst Formation in the Drosophila Ovary. Developmental Biology, 218(1), <lb/>53-63. http://doi.org/10.1006/dbio.1999.9570 <lb/>Lim, J. G. Y., &amp; Fuller, M. T. (2012). Somatic cell lineage is required for differentiation and not <lb/>maintenance of germline stem cells in Drosophila testes. Proceedings of the National <lb/>Academy of Sciences, 109(45), 18477-18481. http://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1215516109 <lb/>Lin, H., Yue, L., &amp; Spradling, A. C. (1994). The Drosophila fusome, a germline-specific <lb/>organelle, contains membrane skeletal proteins and functions in cyst formation. <lb/>Development (Cambridge, England), 120(4), 947-56. Retrieved from <lb/>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/7600970 <lb/>Madigan, J. P., Chotkowski, H. L., &amp; Glaser, R. L. (2002). DNA double-strand break-induced <lb/>phosphorylation of Drosophila histone variant H2Av helps prevent radiation-induced <lb/>apoptosis. Nucleic Acids Research, 30(17), 3698-705. Retrieved from <lb/>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12202754 <lb/>Meistrich, M. L. (2013). Effects of chemotherapy and radiotherapy on spermatogenesis in <lb/>humans. Fertility and Sterility, 100(5), 1180-1186. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1016/j.fertnstert.2013.08.010 <lb/>Oakberg, E. F. (1955). Sensitivity and Time of Degeneration of Spermatogenic Cells Irradiated <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>in Various Stages of Maturation in the Mouse Sensitivity and Time of Degeneration of <lb/>Spermatogenic Cells Irradiated in Various Stages of Maturation in the Mouse&quot;&apos;2. <lb/>Source: Radiation Research, 2(4), 369-391. Retrieved from <lb/>http://www.jstor.org/stable/3570245 <lb/>Pepling, M. E., de Cuevas, M., &amp; Spradling, A. C. (1999). Germline cysts: a conserved phase of <lb/>germ cell development? Trends in Cell Biology, 9(7), 257-62. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1016/S0962-8924(99)01594-9 <lb/>Peters, M., DeLuca, C., Hirao, A., Stambolic, V., Potter, J., Zhou, L., … Mak, T. W. (2002). <lb/>Chk2 regulates irradiation-induced, p53-mediated apoptosis in Drosophila. Proceedings of <lb/>the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 99(17), 11305-10. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.172382899 <lb/>Song, Y.-H. (2005). Drosophila melanogaster: a model for the study of DNA damage checkpoint <lb/>response. Molecules and Cells, 19(2), 167-79. Retrieved from <lb/>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15879698 <lb/>Tain, L. S., Chowdhury, R. B., Tao, R. N., Plun-Favreau, H., Moisoi, N., Martins, L. M., … <lb/>Tapon, N. (2009). Drosophila HtrA2 is dispensable for apoptosis but acts downstream of <lb/>PINK1 independently from Parkin. Cell Death and Differentiation, 16(8), 1118-1125. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1038/cdd.2009.23 <lb/>Takada, S., Collins, E. R., &amp; Kurahashi, K. (2015). The FHA domain determines Drosophila <lb/>Chk2/Mnk localization to key mitotic structures and is essential for early embryonic DNA <lb/>damage responses. Molecular Biology of the Cell, 26(10), 1811-28. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1091/mbc.E14-07-1238 <lb/>Takada, S., Kelkar, A., &amp; Theurkauf, W. E. (2003). Drosophila Checkpoint Kinase 2 Couples <lb/>Centrosome Function and Spindle Assembly to Genomic Integrity. Cell, 113(1), 87-99. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1016/S0092-8674(03)00202-2 <lb/>Ulsh, B. A. (2010). CHECKING THE FOUNDATION: RECENT RADIOBIOLOGY AND <lb/>THE LINEAR NO-THRESHOLD THEORY. Health Physics, 99(6), 747-758. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1097/HP.0b013e3181e32477 <lb/>Van Doren, M., Williamson, A. L., &amp; Lehmann, R. (1998). Regulation of zygotic gene <lb/>expression in Drosophila primordial germ cells. Current Biology (Vol. 8). Retrieved from <lb/>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0960982298700910 <lb/>Vande Walle, L., Lamkanfi, M., &amp; Vandenabeele, P. (2008). The mitochondrial serine protease <lb/>HtrA2/Omi: an overview. Cell Death and Differentiation, 15(3), 453-460. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1038/sj.cdd.4402291 <lb/>Wichmann, A., Jaklevic, B., &amp; Su, T. T. (2006). Ionizing radiation induces caspase-dependent <lb/>but Chk2-and p53-independent cell death in Drosophila melanogaster. Proceedings of the <lb/>National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 103(26), 9952-7. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0510528103 <lb/>Wylie, A., Lu, W.-J., D&apos;Brot, A., Buszczak, M., Abrams, J. M., Abdu, U., … Xu, Y. (2014). p53 <lb/>activity is selectively licensed in the Drosophila stem cell compartment. eLife, 3, e01530. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>http://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.01530 <lb/>Xie, H. B., &amp; Golic, K. G. (2004). Gene deletions by ends-in targeting in Drosophila <lb/>melanogaster. Genetics, 168(3), 1477-89. http://doi.org/10.1534/genetics.104.030882 <lb/>Yacobi-Sharon, K., Namdar, Y., &amp; Arama, E. (2013). Alternative germ cell death pathway in <lb/>Drosophila involves HtrA2/Omi, lysosomes, and a caspase-9 counterpart. Developmental <lb/>Cell, 25(1), 29-42. http://doi.org/10.1016/j.devcel.2013.02.002 <lb/>Yang, H., &amp; Yamashita, Y. M. (2015). The regulated elimination of transit-amplifying cells <lb/>preserves tissue homeostasis during protein starvation in Drosophila testis. Development <lb/>(Cambridge, England), 142(10), 1756-66. http://doi.org/10.1242/dev.122663 <lb/>Yoshida, S. (2016). From cyst to tubule: innovations in vertebrate spermatogenesis. Wiley <lb/>Interdisciplinary Reviews: Developmental Biology, 5(1), 119-131. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1002/wdev.204 <lb/>Yuan, H., Chiang, C.-Y. A., Cheng, J., Salzmann, V., &amp; Yamashita, Y. M. (2012). Regulation of <lb/>cyclin A localization downstream of Par-1 function is critical for the centrosome orientation <lb/>checkpoint in Drosophila male germline stem cells. Developmental Biology, 361(1), 57-67. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1016/j.ydbio.2011.10.010 </listBibl>

	</text>
</tei>
