<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="footnote"> arXiv:0806.4793v1  [math-ph] 29 Jun 2008 <lb/></note>

			<front> A bi-Hamiltonian Supersymmetric Geodesic <lb/>Equation <lb/> J. Lenells <lb/> Department of Applied Mathematics and Theoretical Physics, University of Cambridge, <lb/>Cambridge CB3 0WA, United Kingdom <lb/> Abstract <lb/> A supersymmetric extension of the Hunter-Saxton equation is constructed. We <lb/>present its bi-Hamiltonian structure and show that it arises geometrically as a <lb/>geodesic equation on the space of superdiffeomorphisms of the circle that leave <lb/>a point fixed endowed with a right-invariant metric. <lb/> AMS Subject Classification (2000): 37K10, 17A70. <lb/> Keywords: Supersymmetry, integrable systems, Hunter-Saxton equation. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> Among all integrable systems, the KdV equation, indisputably, is the most well-<lb/>studied. Ever since its solution was presented by means of the inverse scattering <lb/>method [12], much effort has been put into finding other physical models amenable <lb/>to a similar analysis, and into developing a framework for a deeper understanding of <lb/>their integrability. Geometrically, one intriguing feature of the KdV and many other <lb/>integrable nonlinear evolution equations, is that they arise as Euler equations for the <lb/>geodesic flow on some manifold. Since geodesic flows are not integrable in general, <lb/>this raises the question of whether one may geometrically distinguish the integrable <lb/>flows from the nonintegrable ones. An important class of geodesic flows, which are <lb/>indeed integrable, are related to the group of diffeomorphisms of the circle, Diff(S  1  ), <lb/>or to its one-dimensional extension, the Virasoro group cf. [7]. Indeed, the KdV <lb/>equation describes the geodesic motion on the Virasoro group induced by the right-<lb/>invariant metric given at the identity by the L  2  -norm [25], while the H  1  -norm on the <lb/>same group gives rise [22, 27] to the Camassa-Holm (CH) equation [3]—a shallow <lb/>water equation which has attracted considerable interest in recent years as it exhibits <lb/>more general wave phenomena than the KdV equation, such as wave-breaking and <lb/>solitons with a peak at their crest cf. [1, 5, 6, 18]. <lb/>One trend in the study of integrable systems has been the appearance of fermionic <lb/>extensions of integrable equations. About the same time as supersymmetric methods <lb/>became widely used in quantum field theory, fermionic generalizations of classical <lb/>soliton equations also began to appear, two of the more well-known examples being the <lb/></body>

			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<body> so-called kuperKdV [17] and superKdV [20, 21] generalizations of the KdV equation <lb/>(see [4, 16, 23, 26] for other examples). While these extensions introduce new fields <lb/>in addition to the original bosonic variables, they normally also preserve most of the <lb/>structure of the original equation. For example, it was demonstrated in [25] that <lb/>the interpretation of the KdV equation as a geodesic equation carries over to the <lb/>kuperKdV system: it describes the geodesic flow on the superconformal group with <lb/>respect to an L  2  -type metric. In fact, it was shown recently [9] that taking a general <lb/>metric of L  2  -type on the superconformal group one obtains a one-parameter family <lb/>of geodesic equations which includes also the superKdV system. <lb/>While the hope is that the interrelationship between geometry and supersymmetry <lb/>would cast new light on the meaning of integrability, all the features of an integrable <lb/>equation are not always preserved by a fermionic extension. Let us comment on the <lb/>following properties of a fermionic generalization of an integrable equation: (a) it <lb/>admits a bi-Hamiltonian structure (b) it is supersymmetric (c) it arises geometrically <lb/>as an Euler equation for geodesic flow. <lb/>(a) One characteristic feature of integrable systems is the presence of two distinct, <lb/>but compatible, Hamiltonian formulations. However, while this is usually con-<lb/>sidered a sufficient criterion for the integrability of a system with fermions, it <lb/>appears not to be necessary. For example, only a single Hamiltonian formu-<lb/>lation in standard form is known for the superKdV system (see [24]). On the <lb/>other hand, the kuperKdV equation has a bi-Hamiltonian formulation, but it <lb/>is not supersymmetric. <lb/>(b) The main idea of supersymmetrization, which has its origin in quantum the-<lb/>ory, is to unify bosons and fermions: in addition to the original commuting <lb/>fields, new anti-commuting fields are introduced, the two kinds of variables <lb/>being related by supersymmetry. However, fermion fields can also be incorpo-<lb/>rated independently from the boson fields, giving generalizations that are not <lb/>always invariant under supersymmetric transformations. This is the case for <lb/>kuperKdV. <lb/>(c) Besides the geometric formulation of the kuperKdV system mentioned above, <lb/>the occurrence of fermionic extensions of the Camassa-Holm equation among <lb/>the geodesic equations induced by H  1  type metrics on the superconformal group <lb/>has also been investigated [9]. The equations describing the geodesic motion <lb/>with respect to H  1  type metrics define a large class of fermionic generalizations <lb/>of CH. Being geodesic equations, they automatically admit at least one Hamil-<lb/>tonian structure—the so-called Lie-Poisson structure with Hamiltonian given <lb/>by the H  1  metric. Moreover, within this family of H  1  geodesic equations, a <lb/>subclass also admit a second Hamiltonian structure. However, none of the bi-<lb/>Hamiltonian equations found in [9] is also supersymmetric. Hence, the superCH <lb/>system put forward in [9] is a geodesic equation, which is supersymmetric, but <lb/>for which only a single Hamiltonian formulation is known. <lb/>In addition to the Camassa-Holm equation, there recently appeared another non-<lb/>linear wave equation which also resembles the KdV equation in several respects. The <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body> Hunter-Saxton equation [13] <lb/>(1.1) <lb/> − u  txx  = 2u  x  u  xx  + uu  xxx  , t &gt; 0, x ∈ R, <lb/> models the propagation of orientation waves in liquid crystals, and is a bi-Hamiltonian, <lb/>completely integrable system with an infinite family of conserved quantities [14]. <lb/>Equation (1.1) also arises geometrically as a geodesic equation related to the group <lb/>Diff(S  1  ): it describes the geodesic flow on the quotient space Diff(S  1  )/S  1  of the group <lb/>Diff(S  1  ) of orientation-preserving diffeomorphisms of the unit circle S  1  modulo the <lb/>subgroup of rigid rotations, endowed with the ˙ <lb/> H  1  right-invariant metric given by <lb/> u, v = <lb/> u  x  v  x  dx for any two vectors u and v in the Lie algebra Vect(S  1  ) [15]. <lb/>In this note we investigate the equations describing the geodesic flow induced by <lb/>a super-analogue of the ˙ <lb/> H  1  metric. We show that the system <lb/>(1.2) <lb/> −u  txx  = 2u  x  u  xx  + uu  xxx  + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  ξ  x  ξ  xxx  , <lb/> −ξ  txx  = uξ  xxx  + <lb/> 3 <lb/>2  u  x  ξ  xx  + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  u  xx  ξ  x  , <lb/> where u(x, t) and ξ(x, t) are bosonic and fermionic fields, respectively, exhibits all <lb/>of the above mentioned properties: it is bi-Hamiltonian and supersymmetric, and <lb/>it arises geometrically as a geodesic equation on the space Super-Diff(S  1  )/S  1  of su-<lb/>perdiffeomorphisms of the circle that leave a point fixed. In sections 2-4 we consider <lb/>the geometric, bi-Hamiltonian, and supersymmetric structure of (1.2), respectively, <lb/>while Section 5 contains a derivation of a Lax pair. <lb/> 2 Geodesic flow <lb/> Define the Lie algebra g as the super-analogue of Vect(S  1  ), i.e. g consists of all <lb/>pairs (u(x), ϕ(x)), where u(x) and ϕ(x) are bosonic and fermionic fields, respectively. <lb/>Geometrically this is the superconformal algebra of contact vector fields on the 1|1-<lb/>dimensional supercircle S  1|1  . The Lie bracket is given by <lb/>(2.1) <lb/>[(u, ϕ), (v, ψ)] = <lb/> uv  x  − u  x  v + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ϕψ, uψ  x  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> u  x  ψ − ϕ  x  v + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ϕv  x <lb/> , <lb/> and we introduce the ˙ <lb/> H  1  inner product by <lb/>(2.2) <lb/> (u, ϕ), (v, ψ) = <lb/> dx (u  x  v  x  + ϕ  x  ψ) = <lb/> dx (uA  0  v + ϕA  1  ψ) , <lb/> where <lb/> A  0  = −∂ <lb/> 2 <lb/> x  , <lb/>A  1  = −∂  x  . <lb/> Defining the operator B : g × g → g by <lb/> U, [V, W ] = B(U, V ), W , <lb/></body>

			<page> 3 <lb/></page>

			<body> the geodesic equation can be written as U  t  = B(U, U ) cf. [2]. Let U = (u, ϕ) and <lb/> V = (v, ψ). Then B(U, V ) = (B  0  (U, V ), B  1  (U, V )), where <lb/> A  0  B  0  (U, V ) = − <lb/> 2v  x  A  0  u + vA  0  u  x  + <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/> ψ  x  A  1  ϕ + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ψA  1  ϕ  x <lb/> , <lb/> (2.3) <lb/> A  1  B  1  (U, V ) = − <lb/> 3 <lb/>2 <lb/> v  x  A  1  ϕ + vA  1  ϕ  x  + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ψA  0  u <lb/> , <lb/> (2.4) <lb/>and the geodesic equations are <lb/> A  0  u  t  = A  0  B  0  (U, V ), <lb/> A  1  ϕ  t  = A  1  B  1  (U, V ). <lb/>If we introduce ξ by ϕ = ξ  x  , these equations become (1.2). Note that upon setting <lb/> ξ = 0 in (1.2), the geometric formulation of equation (1.1) is recovered. <lb/> 3 Bi-Hamiltonian structure <lb/> Introducing the variables m = −u  xx  and η = −ξ  xx  , equation (1.2) admits the bi-<lb/>Hamiltonian formulation <lb/>(3.1) <lb/> m <lb/>η <lb/> t <lb/> = J  1 <lb/> δH  1 <lb/> δm <lb/>δH  1 <lb/> δη <lb/> = J  2 <lb/> δH  2 <lb/> δm <lb/>δH  2 <lb/> δη <lb/> , <lb/> where the Hamiltonian operators are <lb/> J  1  = <lb/> −∂  x  m − m∂  x <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  ∂  x  η + η∂  x <lb/> −∂  x  η − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  η∂  x <lb/> − <lb/> m <lb/> 2 <lb/> , <lb/>J  2  = <lb/> ∂  3 <lb/> x <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 ∂  2 <lb/> x <lb/> , <lb/> the first Hamiltonian is given by the ˙ <lb/> H  1  inner product according to <lb/> H  1  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> U, U  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> dx <lb/> u <lb/> 2 <lb/> x  + ξ  xx  ξ  x <lb/> , <lb/> and the second Hamiltonian is <lb/> H  2  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> dx <lb/> uu <lb/> 2 <lb/> x  − uξ  x  ξ  xx <lb/> . <lb/> Indeed, for a functional F , the variational derivatives <lb/> δF <lb/>δm  and <lb/> δF <lb/>δη  are defined by <lb/> d <lb/>dǫ <lb/> ǫ=0 <lb/> F [m + ǫδm, η + ǫδη] = <lb/> dx <lb/> δF <lb/>δm <lb/>δm + <lb/> δF <lb/>δη <lb/>δη <lb/> . <lb/> It follows from the definitions of m and η that <lb/> A  0 <lb/>  δF <lb/>δm <lb/>δF <lb/>δη <lb/> = <lb/>  δF <lb/>δu <lb/>δF <lb/>δξ <lb/> . <lb/></body>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<body> Hence, the formulation (3.1) is easily verified using that <lb/> δH  1 <lb/> δu <lb/>δH  1 <lb/> δξ <lb/> = A  0 <lb/> u <lb/>ξ  x <lb/> , <lb/> δH  2 <lb/> δu <lb/>δH  2 <lb/> δξ <lb/> = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> u  2 <lb/> x  + 2uu  xx  + ξ  x  ξ  xx <lb/> 2uξ  xxx  + 3u  x  ξ  xx  + u  xx  ξ  x <lb/> . <lb/> Notice that when ξ = 0, the bi-Hamiltonian structure reduces to that of the Hunter-<lb/>Saxton equation cf. [14]. Let us also point out that equation (1.2) has a Lagrangian <lb/>formulation corresponding to the Hamiltonian H  2  . It is the Euler-Lagrange equation <lb/>for the action <lb/> S = <lb/> dtdx <lb/> u  t  u  x  − ξ  t  ξ  xx  + uu <lb/> 2 <lb/> x  − uξ  x  ξ  xx <lb/> . <lb/> 4 Supersymmetry <lb/> A simple computation shows that equation (1.2) is invariant under the supersymmetry <lb/>transformation <lb/>(4.1) <lb/> δu = τ ξ  x  , <lb/>δξ = τ u, <lb/> where τ is an odd parameter. The supersymmetry can also be established by formu-<lb/>lating the calculations in Section 2 in terms of superfields. We define a superderivative <lb/> D by D = ∂  θ  +θ∂  x  , where θ is an odd coordinate. Letting U = u+θϕ and V = v+θψ, <lb/> the Lie bracket (2.1) can be written as <lb/>[U, V ] = U D <lb/> 2  V − V D <lb/> 2  U + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(DU )(DV ), <lb/>and the ˙ <lb/> H  1  inner product becomes <lb/> U, V  = <lb/> dxdθ(D <lb/> 2  U )(DV ). <lb/>The superspace bilinear operator <lb/> (U, V ) satisfies <lb/> −D <lb/> 3  ˆ <lb/> B(U, V ) = V (D <lb/> 5  U ) + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(DV )(D <lb/> 4  U ) + <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>(D <lb/> 2  V )(D <lb/> 3  U ). <lb/>Introducing a fermionic superfield M (x, θ) by M = −D  3  U = −ϕ  x  + θm, the geodesic <lb/>flow equation U  t  = ˆ <lb/> B(U, U ) is <lb/>(4.2) <lb/> M  t  = U (D <lb/> 5  U ) + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(DU )(D <lb/> 4  U ) + <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>(D <lb/> 2  U )(D <lb/> 3  U ). <lb/>This equation is by construction invariant under the supersymmetry transformation <lb/>(4.1). The component equations of (4.2) give back system (1.2). <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body> 5 Lax pair <lb/> A long but straightforward computation shows that equation (4.2) is the condition <lb/>of compatibility of the linear system <lb/>(5.1) <lb/> D  3  G = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2λ  M G, <lb/>G  t  = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  U  x  G − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  (DU )(DG) + (λ − U )G  x  . <lb/> where the even superfield G serves as an eigenfunction and λ ∈ C is a spectral <lb/>parameter. <lb/>Let us briefly indicate how the Lax pair (5.1) was derived. We first consider how <lb/>the existence of a recursion operator leads to a Lax pair in the purely bosonic case. <lb/>By definition, a recursion operator R for an evolution equation m  t  = K[m] satisfies <lb/>(5.2) <lb/> R  t  = [K <lb/> ′  , R], <lb/> where K  ′  [m] is the Frechét derivative of the operator K cf. [10]. Equation (5.2) is <lb/>the compatibility condition of <lb/>(5.3) <lb/> Rϕ = λϕ, <lb/>ϕ  t  = K  ′  · ϕ, <lb/> The system (5.3) provides a Lax pair for the evolution equation in terms of the <lb/>&apos;squared eigenfunction&apos; ϕ cf. [11]. We expect the existence of a simpler Lax pair <lb/>expressed in terms of an appropriate &apos;square root&apos; of ϕ. <lb/> This procedure can be applied to the Hunter-Saxton equation (1.1) as follows. <lb/>Since equation (1.1) admits the recursion operator R = (m∂  x  + ∂  x  m)∂  −3 <lb/> x  , where <lb/> m = −u  xx  (see [14]), we obtain an x-part of the form <lb/>(m∂  x  + ∂  x  m)∂ <lb/> −3 <lb/> x  ϕ = λϕ. <lb/> Moreover, letting ϕ = ∂  3 <lb/> x  (ψ  2  ), this equation is implied by the x-part of the standard <lb/>Lax pair for (1.1) given by <lb/>(5.4) <lb/> ψ  xx  = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2λ  mψ, <lb/>ψ  t  = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  u  x  ψ + (λ − u)ψ  x  . <lb/> We now show how (5.1) can be derived by following analogous steps in the presence <lb/>of supersymmetry.  1  In terms of M , the bi-Hamiltonian formulation (3.1) reads <lb/> M  t  = K  1 <lb/> δH  1 <lb/> δM <lb/> = K  2 <lb/> δH  2 <lb/> δM <lb/>, <lb/> where <lb/> H  1  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> dxdθ(U M ), <lb/> H  2  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> dxdθ(D <lb/> 2  U )(DU )U, <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 1  An alternative approach would be to start with the bosonic Lax pair (5.4) and simply search for <lb/>the most general fermionic extension compatible with supersymmetry. The current method is more <lb/>systematic and provides additional guidance. <lb/></note>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<body> and <lb/> K  1  = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>[M ∂  x  + 2∂  x  M + (DM )D] , <lb/>K  2  = D <lb/> 5  . <lb/> We consider the recursion operator <lb/> R = −K  1  K <lb/> −1 <lb/> 2  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>[M ∂  x  + 2∂  x  M + (DM )D] D <lb/> −5  . <lb/> In analogy to the above bosonic case, we expect <lb/>(5.5) <lb/> RF = λF, <lb/> to be the x-part for a Lax pair of (4.2). The even superfield F serves as a &apos;squared <lb/>eigenfunction&apos;. Letting F = D  5  (G  2  ), we find that the equation <lb/>(5.6) <lb/> D <lb/> 3  G = <lb/>1 <lb/>2λ <lb/> M G, <lb/> implies (5.5). This suggests that equation (5.6) is an appropriate x-part. In compo-<lb/>nents, with G = g + θν and M = −ϕ  x  + θm, (5.6) reads <lb/>(5.7) <lb/> g  xx  = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2λ  (mg + ϕ  x  ν) <lb/>ν  x  = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2λ  ϕ  x  g, <lb/> which agrees with the x-part of (5.4) when the fermionic fields are set to zero. <lb/>In order to find the corresponding t-part, we seek a Lax pair of the form <lb/>(5.8) <lb/> D  3  G = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2λ  M G <lb/>G  t  = AG + BDG + CG  x  , <lb/> where A, C are even superfields and B is an odd superfield to be determined. The <lb/>compatibility condition of (5.8) is <lb/> 1 <lb/>2λ <lb/> M G <lb/> t <lb/> = D <lb/> 3  (AG + BDG + CG  x  ) . <lb/> We expand the derivatives, use (5.8) to replace all occurences of G  t  and D  3  G, and <lb/>identify coefficients of G, DG, and G  x  , to arrive at the three equations <lb/> M  t  =2λ(DA  x  ) + (DB)M + (DC)(DM ) + C  x  M − B(DM ) + CM  x  , <lb/> (5.9) <lb/>0 =DB  x  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2λ <lb/>(DC)M + A  x  + <lb/>1 <lb/> λ <lb/>BM, <lb/> (5.10) <lb/>0 =DC  x  + DA − B  x  . <lb/> (5.11) <lb/>Letting <lb/> A = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> U  x  , <lb/>B = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> DU, <lb/>C = λ − U, <lb/> equations (5.10) and (5.11) are identically satisfied, while equation (5.9) is equivalent <lb/>to (4.2). <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body> 6 Concluding remarks <lb/> We have constructed a supersymmetric, bi-Hamiltonian extension of equation (1.1) <lb/>and shown that it arises geometrically as the geodesic equation with respect to the ˙ <lb/> H  1 <lb/> metric (2.2) on Super-Diff(S  1  )/S  1  . Later, the bi-Hamiltonian structure has been used <lb/>to derive a Lax pair. The equation sets itself apart from the super-geodesic equations <lb/>previously obtained using the L  2  and H  1  metrics in that it is both supersymmetric and <lb/>bi-Hamiltonian: the kuperKdV system which is induced by the L  2  metric [25] is not <lb/>supersymmetric [8], while the superCH system put forward in [9] is supersymmetric <lb/>but appears not to be bi-Hamiltonian. <lb/>Finally, let us point out that the geometric interpretation of equation (1.1) is <lb/>particularly simple in that the underlying space Diff(S  1  )/S  1  is isometric to an open <lb/>subset of an infinite-dimensional L  2  -sphere, so that the geodesics are simply segments <lb/>of the big circles on the sphere [19]. It would be interesting to investigate whether <lb/>this point of view has an extension to the supersymmetric system (1.2). <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgement The author thanks Professor O. Lechtenfeld for helpful discus-<lb/>sions. This work was carried out while the author was supported by a Marie Curie <lb/>Intra-European Fellowship. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] M. Alber, R. Camassa, D. D. Holm and J. E. Marsden, The geometry of peaked solitons <lb/>and billiard solutions of a class of integrable PDE&apos;s, Lett. Math. Phys. 32 (1994) 137–151. <lb/>[2] V. Arnold, Sur la géometrie différentielle des groupes de Lie de dimension infinie et ses <lb/>applicationà l&apos;hydrodynamique des fluides parfaits, Ann. Inst. Fourier (Grenoble) 16 <lb/> (1966), 319–361. <lb/>[3] R. Camassa and D. D. Holm, An integrable shallow water equation with peaked solitons, <lb/> Phys. Rev. Lett. 71 (1993), 1661–1664. <lb/>[4] M. Chaichian and P. P. Kulish, On the method of inverse scattering problem and <lb/>Bäcklund transformations for supersymmetric equations, Phys. Lett. B 78 (1978), 413– <lb/>417. <lb/>[5] A. Constantin and J. Escher, Global existence and blow-up for a shallow water equation, <lb/> Annali Sc. Norm. Sup. Pisa 26 (1998), 303–328. <lb/>[6] A. Constantin, V. S. Gerdjikov, and R. I. Ivanov, Inverse scattering transform for the <lb/>Camassa-Holm equation, Inverse Problems 22 (2006), 2197–2207. <lb/>[7] A. Constantin and B. Kolev, On the geometric approach to the motion of inertial me-<lb/>chanical systems, J. Phys. A 35 (2002), R51–R79. <lb/>[8] D. A. Depireux and P. Mathieu, Integrable supersymmetry breaking perturbations of <lb/> N = 1, 2 superconformal minimal models, Phys. Lett. B 308 (1993), 272–278. <lb/>[9] C. Devchand and J. Schiff, The supersymmetric Camassa-Holm equation and geodesic <lb/>flow on the superconformal group, J. Math. Phys. 42 (2001), 260–273. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [10] A. S. Fokas, Symmetries and integrability, Stud. Appl. Math. 77 (1987), 253–299. <lb/>[11] A. S. Fokas and R. L. Anderson, On the use of isospectral eigenvalue problems for <lb/>obtaining hereditary symmetries for Hamiltonian systems, J. Math. Phys. 23 (1982), <lb/>1066–1073. <lb/>[12] C. S. Gardner, J. M. Greene, M. D. Kruskal, and R. M. Miura, Method for solving the <lb/>Korteweg-de Vries equation, Phys. Rev. Lett. 19 (1967), 1095–1097. <lb/>[13] J. K. Hunter and R. Saxton, Dynamics of director fields, SIAM J. Appl. Math. 51 (1991), <lb/>1498–1521. <lb/>[14] J. K. Hunter and Y. Zheng, On a completely integrable nonlinear hyperbolic variational <lb/>equation, Physica D 79 (1994), 361–386. <lb/>[15] B. Khesin and G. Misio lek, Euler equations on homogeneous spaces and Virasoro orbits, <lb/> Adv. Math. 176 (2003), 116–144. <lb/>[16] P. P. Kulish, Quantum OSP-invariant nonlinear Schrödinger equation, Lett. Math. Phys. <lb/> 10 (1985), 87–93. <lb/>[17] B. A. Kupershmidt, A super Korteweg-de Vries equation: an integrable system, Phys. <lb/>Lett. A 102 (1984), 213–215. <lb/>[18] J. Lenells, Traveling wave solutions of the Camassa-Holm equation, J. Diff. Eq. 217 <lb/> (2005), 393–430. <lb/>[19] J. Lenells, The Hunter-Saxton equation describes the geodesic flow on a sphere, J. Geom. <lb/>Phys. 57 (2007), 2049–2064. <lb/>[20] Y. I. Manin and A. O. Radul, A supersymmetric extension of the Kadomtsev-Petviashvili <lb/>hierarchy, Comm. Math. Phys. 98 (1988), 65–77. <lb/>[21] P. Mathieu, Supersymmetric extension of the Korteweg-de Vries equation, J. Math. <lb/>Phys. 29 (1988), 2499–2506. <lb/>[22] G. Misio lek, A shallow water equation as a geodesic flow on the Bott-Virasoro group, J. <lb/>Geom. Phys. 24 (1998), 203–208. <lb/>[23] C. Morosi and L. Pizzocchero, osp(3, 2) and gl(3, 3) supersymmetric KdV hierarchies, <lb/> Phys. Lett. A 185 (1994), 241–252. <lb/>[24] W. Oevel and Z. Popowicz, The bi-Hamiltonian structure of fully supersymmetric <lb/>Korteweg-de Vries systems, Comm. Math. Phys. 139 (1991), 441–460. <lb/>[25] V. Ovsienko and B. Khesin, The (super) KdV equation as an Euler equation, Funct. <lb/>Anal. Appl. 21:4 (1987), 81–82. <lb/>[26] G. H. M. Roelofs and P. H. M. Kersten, Supersymmetric extensions of the nonlinear <lb/>Schrödinger equation: symmetries and coverings, J. Math. Phys. 33 (1992), 2185–2206. <lb/>[27] S. Shkoller, Geometry and curvature of diffeomorphism groups with H <lb/> 1  metric and mean <lb/>hydrodynamics, J. Funct. Anal. 160 (1998), 337–365. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 9 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
