<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Linear Algebra and its Applications 434 (2011) 1200–1214 <lb/> Contents lists available at ScienceDirect <lb/> Linear Algebra and its Applications <lb/> journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/laa <lb/> Maximal linear subspaces of strong self-dual 2-forms and the <lb/>Bonan 4-form <lb/> Ay se Hümeyra Bilge <lb/> a, *  , Tekin Dereli <lb/> b , ¸ <lb/>Sahin Koçak <lb/> c <lb/> a  Faculty of Sciences and Letters, Kadir Has University, Cibali, Istanbul, Turkey <lb/> b  Department of Physics, Koç University, Sarıyer, Istanbul, Turkey <lb/> c  Department of Mathematics, Anadolu University, Eski sehir, Turkey <lb/> A R T I C L E I N F O <lb/>A B S T R A C T <lb/> Article history: <lb/> Received 21 August 2009 <lb/>Accepted 1 November 2010 <lb/>Available online 3 December 2010 <lb/>Submitted by V. Sergeichuk <lb/> AMS classification: <lb/> 11E76 <lb/>15A66 <lb/> Keywords: <lb/> Bonan form <lb/>Self-duality <lb/>Eight manifolds <lb/> The notion of self-duality of 2-forms in 4-dimensions plays an em-<lb/>inent role in many areas of mathematics and physics, but although <lb/>the 2-forms have a genuine meaning related to curvature and gauge-<lb/>field-strength in higher dimensions also, their &quot; self-duality&quot; is some-<lb/>thing which is almost avoided above 4-dimensions. We show that <lb/>self-duality of 2-forms is a very natural notion in higher (even) di-<lb/>mensions also and we prove the equivalence of some scattered and <lb/>rarely used definitions in the literature. We demonstrate the useful-<lb/>ness of this higher self-duality by studying it in 8-dimensions and <lb/>we derive a natural expression for the Bonan form in terms of self-<lb/>dual 2-forms and we give an explicit expression of the local action <lb/>of SO(8) on the Bonan form. <lb/>© 2010 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> Let M be a 4-dimensional, oriented Riemannian manifold and let e <lb/> i  , i  =  1,  . . . ,  4 be a local, posi-<lb/>tively oriented, orthonormal basis for the cotangent bundle T  *  M of M. The local expression of a 2-form <lb/>is given by <lb/> ω = <lb/> i&lt;j <lb/> ω  ij e <lb/> i <lb/> ∧  e <lb/> j <lb/> . <lb/> (We will use e <lb/> ij  for e <lb/> i <lb/> ∧  e <lb/> j  .) In 4-dimensions,  ω  is Hodge self-dual if  * ω = ω  while it is Hodge anti-<lb/>self-dual if  * ω = −ω.  For any p-form on an n-dimensional manifold, we have  * * = (−1) <lb/> p(n−p)  . In <lb/></body>

			<front> *  Corresponding author. <lb/> E-mail addresses: ayse.bilge@khas.edu.tr (A.H. Bilge), tdereli@ku.edu.tr (T. Dereli), skocak@anadolu.edu.tr (S. Koçak). <lb/>0024-3795/$ -see front matter © 2010 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.laa.2010.11.002 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote"> A.H. Bilge et al. / Linear Algebra and its Applications 434 (2011) 1200–1214 <lb/></note>

			<page> 1201 <lb/></page>

			<body> particular for n  =  4 and p  =  2,  * * =  1 and therefore  *  has eigenvalues  ±1.  Hence in 4-dimensions, the <lb/>6-dimensional linear space of 2-forms is the orthogonal direct sum of the 3-dimensional eigenspaces <lb/>of the Hodge map. This construction fails in higher dimensions as the Hodge dual of a 2-form is no <lb/>longer a 2-form. There are various definitions of self-duality of 2-forms in higher dimensions, each <lb/>with some type of a drawback or restrictions. In previous papers [1–3], we have proposed the notion <lb/>of &quot; strong self-duality&quot; which unifies most of the existing definitions in the literature. In this report we <lb/>recall some of these results and apply them to obtain new results on the relation of linear subspaces of <lb/>strong self-dual 2-forms and the Bonan form in 8-dimensions [4], whereby we construct new natural <lb/>expressions for the Bonan form. This construction allows a very convenient way of obtaining the <lb/>expression of the action of SO(8) on the Bonan form. <lb/>The  ω  ij  &apos;s form a skew-symmetric matrix whose eigenvalues are pure imaginary and occur in con-<lb/>jugate pairs. If these are denoted in 4-dimensions as  ±iλ  1 and  ±iλ  2 , it can be seen that they satisfy <lb/> λ <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + λ <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  = ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>12  + ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>13  + ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>14  + ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>23  + ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>24  + ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>34  , <lb/>λ <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  λ <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  = (ω  12  ω  34  − ω  13  ω  24  + ω  14  ω  23  ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> . <lb/> Hence <lb/> λ  1  ∓ λ  2  = <lb/> (ω  12  ∓ ω  34  )  2  + (ω  13  ± ω  24  )  2  + (ω  14  ∓ ω  23  )  2  . <lb/> Thus for self-duality <lb/> λ  1  = λ  2  , <lb/> while for anti-self-duality <lb/> λ  1  = −λ  2  . <lb/> In both cases the absolute values of the eigenvalues are equal. Two cases are distinguished by the sign <lb/>of the Pfaffian of  ω: <lb/> Pf  (ω) = ω  12  ω  34  − ω  13  ω  24  + ω  14  ω  23  . <lb/> Thus in 4-dimensions, the equality of the absolute values of the eigenvalues gives the usual notion <lb/>of self-duality in the Hodge sense. <lb/>This crucial remark is the starting point of our work on strong self-duality. We declare a 2-form <lb/>in 2n-dimensions to be strong self-dual or strong anti-self-dual, if the eigenvalues of its matrix with <lb/>respect to some local orthonormal basis  {e <lb/> 1 <lb/> , . . . ,  e <lb/> 2n <lb/> }  are equal in absolute value and nonzero. The <lb/>two cases are again distinguished by the sign of the Pfaffian, or more simply, by the sign of  * (ω <lb/> n <lb/> ).  We <lb/>also note that odd dimensional manifolds can be ignored because the 2-forms on them are degenerate. <lb/>Denoting the 2-form and its matrix with respect to some orthonormal basis by the same symbol  ω, <lb/> strong self-duality or anti self-duality can also be expressed by the minimal polynomial requirement <lb/> ω <lb/> 2 <lb/> + λ <lb/> 2  I  =  0, <lb/>where <lb/> λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2n <lb/>Tr  ω <lb/> 2 <lb/> . <lb/> 2. Strong self-duality in higher dimensions <lb/> In Section 2.1 we recall the definition of strong self-duality and anti-self-duality in terms of the <lb/>associated anti-symmetric matrices, in Section 2.2 we discuss some useful inequalities and in Section <lb/>2.3 we prove the equivalence of various self-duality notions for 2-forms. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1202 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A.H. Bilge et al. / Linear Algebra and its Applications 434 (2011) 1200–1214 <lb/></note>

			<body> 2.1. Strong self-duality (SD) and anti-self-duality (ASD) of 2-forms as an eigenvalue criterion <lb/> Let  ω  be a 2-form on a 2n-dimensional oriented real vector space with an inner-product. We denote <lb/>the 2-form  ω  and the corresponding skew-symmetric matrix consisting of its components with respect <lb/>to some orthonormal basis by the same symbol. The distinction between the wedge product of forms <lb/>and the matrix multiplication should be made from the context. Since  ω  is a 2n  ×  2n skew-symmetric <lb/>matrix, its eigenvalues are pure imaginary and pairwise conjugate, i.e.  ±iλ  1  , . . . , ±iλ  n  . Thus there is <lb/>an orthonormal basis  {X  k  ,  Y k  }  such that <lb/> ωX  k  = −λ  k Y k  , ωY  k  = λ  k X k <lb/> and  ω  takes the block-diagonal form <lb/> ω = <lb/> ⎛ <lb/> ⎜ <lb/>⎜ <lb/>⎜ <lb/>⎜ <lb/>⎜ <lb/>⎜ <lb/>⎜ <lb/>⎜ <lb/>⎜ <lb/>⎜ <lb/>⎜ <lb/>⎜ <lb/>⎝ <lb/> 0  λ  1 <lb/> −λ  1 0 <lb/> . <lb/>. <lb/>. <lb/> 0  λ  n <lb/> −λ  n  0 <lb/> ⎞ <lb/>⎟ <lb/>⎟ <lb/>⎟ <lb/>⎟ <lb/>⎟ <lb/>⎟ <lb/>⎟ <lb/>⎟ <lb/>⎟ <lb/>⎟ <lb/>⎟ <lb/>⎟ <lb/>⎠ <lb/> . <lb/> We define strong self-duality and anti-self-duality as follows (see [1]): <lb/> Definition 1. Let  ω  be a real 2-form on a 2n-dimensional oriented real vector space with an inner <lb/>product and denote the corresponding 2n  ×  2n skew-symmetric matrix with respect to some ortho-<lb/>normal basis by the same symbol. Let  ±iλ  1  , . . . , ±iλ  n  be the eigenvalues of  ω.  Then  ω  is said to be <lb/>strong self-dual (respectively, strong anti-self-dual) if <lb/> |λ  1  | = |λ  2  | = · · · = |λ  n  | <lb/> (1) <lb/>and  * ω <lb/> n <lb/> &gt;  0 (respectively,  * ω <lb/> n <lb/> &lt;  0). <lb/>Note that this is equivalent to the statement that the distinction is based on the sign of the Pfaffian <lb/>of  ω  with respect to a positively oriented orthonormal basis. <lb/>If  ω  is strong self-dual, its matrix with respect to a positively oriented orthonormal basis can be <lb/>brought to a block diagonal form K  λ  =  I  ⊗  λ  where  λ  = <lb/> ⎛ <lb/>⎝ <lb/> 0  λ <lb/> −λ  0 <lb/> ⎞ <lb/>⎠ , by an orientation preserv-<lb/>ing orthogonal transformation, while if it is strong anti-self-dual, the same K  λ  can be realized by an <lb/>orientation reversing transformation. <lb/>The strong self-duality condition is equivalent to the matrix equation <lb/> ω <lb/> 2 <lb/> + λ <lb/> 2  I  =  0, <lb/>where I is the identity matrix, and  λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2n <lb/> Tr  ω <lb/> 2 . This definition gives quadratic equations for the <lb/> ω  ij  &apos;s, hence the strong self-duality condition determines an algebraic variety. This algebraic variety <lb/>will be denoted by S  2n . <lb/>In 4-dimensions, the strong self-duality coincides with usual Hodge duality. More precisely, the <lb/>matrices satisfying  ω <lb/> 2 <lb/> + λ <lb/> 2  I  =  0 consist of the union of the usual self-dual and anti-self-dual 2-forms <lb/>(including the zero form). Thus the algebraic variety consists of the union of two linear spaces. <lb/> 2.2. Eigenvalue inequalities <lb/> In this section we shall use the well known inequalities between elementary symmetric functions <lb/>of the eigenvalues of a skew symmetric matrix to obtain inequalities between the norms of the powers <lb/>of a 2-form. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> A.H. Bilge et al. / Linear Algebra and its Applications 434 (2011) 1200–1214 <lb/></note>

			<page> 1203 <lb/></page>

			<body> Lemma 1 [6]. Let s k be the kth elementary symmetric function of the numbers  {α  1  , α  2  , . . . , α  n  },  with <lb/> α  i  ∈  R and let the weighted elementary symmetric polynomials, q k &apos;s, be defined by <lb/> n <lb/>k <lb/> q k  =  s k  . <lb/> (2) <lb/> Then <lb/>q  1  ≥  q <lb/> 1/2 <lb/>2 <lb/> ≥  q <lb/> 1/3 <lb/>3 <lb/> ≥ · · · ≥  q <lb/> 1/n <lb/> n  , <lb/> (3) <lb/> q r−1 q r+1  ≤  q <lb/> 2 <lb/> r  ,  1  ≤  r  &lt;  n. <lb/> (4) <lb/> If all  α  i &apos;s are equal, then the equalities hold and if any single equality holds, then all  α  i &apos;s are equal. <lb/> Although the inequalites (4) are more convenient to use, the inequalites (3) are more refined in the <lb/>sense that (4) implies (3). <lb/> Remark 1. If A is diagonalizable with eigenvalues  λ  1  , λ  2  , . . . , λ  n  , then <lb/>det(I  +  tA)  = <lb/> n <lb/> k=0 <lb/> σ  k t <lb/> k <lb/> = <lb/> n <lb/> k=1 <lb/> (1 +  tλ k  ), <lb/> (5) <lb/>where  σ  k  is just the kth elementary symmetric function of the eigenvalues. <lb/>If A is a real skew-symmetric 2n  ×  2n matrix, then the eigenvalues of A are  ±iλ  k  , k  =  1, 2,  . . . ,  n. <lb/> It can be seen that, in this case  σ  2k+1  =  0 while the  σ  2k &apos;s are kth elementary symmetric functions of <lb/> {λ <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  , λ <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  , . . . , λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> n  },  i.e. <lb/> σ  2  = λ <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + λ <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  + · · · + λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> n  , <lb/>σ  4  = λ <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  λ <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  + λ <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  λ <lb/> 2 <lb/>3  + · · · + λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> n−1  λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> n  , <lb/>σ  6  = λ <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  λ <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  λ <lb/> 2 <lb/>3  + λ <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  λ <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  λ <lb/> 2 <lb/>4  + · · · + λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> n−2  λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> n−1  λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> n  , <lb/> (6) <lb/> . . . <lb/>σ  2n  = λ <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  λ <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  · · · λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> n  . <lb/> Thus for a skew-symmetric matrix, using (2), we can express  σ  2k &apos;s as <lb/> σ  2k  = <lb/> n! <lb/>k!(n  −  k)! <lb/>q k  . <lb/> (7) <lb/>On the other hand, the  σ  2k &apos;s are related to the norms of the kth powers of  ω  as <lb/> σ  2k  = <lb/> 1 <lb/> (k!)  2  (ω <lb/> k <lb/> , ω <lb/> k <lb/> ), <lb/> (8) <lb/>where the brackets (,) denote the inner product. <lb/>Combining these we have the relations <lb/> σ  2  = (ω, ω) =  nq  1  , <lb/>σ  4  = <lb/> 1 <lb/> (2!)  2  (ω <lb/> 2 <lb/> , ω <lb/> 2 <lb/> ) = <lb/> n(n  −  1) <lb/>2 <lb/> q  2  , <lb/>σ  6  = <lb/> 1 <lb/> (3!)  2  (ω <lb/> 3 <lb/> , ω <lb/> 3 <lb/> ) = <lb/> n(n  −  1)(n  −  2) <lb/>6 <lb/> q  3  , <lb/></body>

			<page> 1204 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A.H. Bilge et al. / Linear Algebra and its Applications 434 (2011) 1200–1214 <lb/></note>

			<body> . . . <lb/>σ  2k  = <lb/> 1 <lb/> (k!)  2  (ω <lb/> k <lb/> , ω <lb/> k <lb/> ) = <lb/> n! <lb/>k!(n  −  k)! <lb/>q k  , <lb/>. . . <lb/>σ  2n  = <lb/> 1 <lb/> (n!)  2  (ω <lb/> n <lb/> , ω <lb/> n <lb/> ) = <lb/> 1 <lb/> (n!)  2  | * ω <lb/> n <lb/> | <lb/> 2 <lb/> =  q n  . <lb/> Thus <lb/> (ω <lb/> k <lb/> , ω <lb/> k <lb/> ) = <lb/> n!k! <lb/> (n −  k)! <lb/>q k <lb/> (9) <lb/>or <lb/> q k  = <lb/> (n −  k)! <lb/>n!k! <lb/> (ω <lb/> k <lb/> , ω <lb/> k <lb/> ). <lb/> (10) <lb/>From the inequalities (3), <lb/> (ω <lb/> k <lb/> , ω <lb/> k <lb/> ) ≤ <lb/> n!k! <lb/>n k  (n −  k)! <lb/> (ω, ω) <lb/> k <lb/> (11) <lb/>and in the case of the equality of the eigenvalues <lb/> (ω <lb/> k <lb/> , ω <lb/> k <lb/> ) = <lb/> n!k! <lb/>n k  (n −  k)! <lb/> (ω, ω) <lb/> k <lb/> . <lb/> (12) <lb/>For k  =  n this formula gives for a strong SD/ASD form in 2n-dimensions <lb/> (ω <lb/> n <lb/> , ω <lb/> n <lb/> ) = <lb/> (n!) <lb/> 2 <lb/> n n <lb/> (ω, ω) <lb/> n <lb/> (13) <lb/>or <lb/> | * ω <lb/> n <lb/> | = <lb/> n! <lb/>n <lb/> n <lb/> 2 <lb/> |ω| <lb/> n <lb/> . <lb/> (14) <lb/> 2.3. Equivalence of strong self-duality with previous definitions of self-duality <lb/> We defined the strong SD/ASD of a 2-form as the equality of the absolute values of the eigenvalues <lb/>of the corresponding matrix. Now we will show that (i) a 2-form  ω  in 2n-dimensions is strong SD if <lb/>and only if  ω <lb/> n−1  is proportional to the Hodge dual of  ω  and (ii) a 2-form  ω  in 4n-dimensions is strong <lb/>SD if  ω <lb/> n  is SD in the Hodge sense. The first condition has been proposed as a definition of self-duality <lb/>by Trautman [11] while the second one appears in the work of Grossman et al. [7]. We start with the <lb/>second result which is easier to prove. <lb/> Theorem 2. Let  ω  be a (non-degenerate) 2-form in 4n-dimensions. Then  ω  is strong self-dual (anti self-<lb/>dual) if and only if  ω <lb/> n is self-dual (anti self-dual) in the Hodge sense, that is  * ω <lb/> n <lb/> = ω <lb/> n ( * ω <lb/> n <lb/> = −ω <lb/> n ). <lb/> Proof. If  ω  is strong SD, we can choose a positive orthonormal basis such that  ω = λ(e <lb/> 12 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 34 <lb/> + <lb/>· · · +  e <lb/> 4n−1,4n <lb/> )  with respect to this basis and it can be seen that  * ω <lb/> n <lb/> = ω <lb/> n  . For the ASD case we can <lb/>choose  ω = λ(−e <lb/> 12 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 34 <lb/> + · · · +  e <lb/> 4n−1,4n <lb/> )  giving  * ω <lb/> n <lb/> = −ω <lb/> n  . <lb/>Conversely, if  * ω <lb/> n <lb/> = ω <lb/> n  holds, then <lb/>  * ω <lb/> 2n <lb/> = * (ω <lb/> n <lb/> ∧ ω <lb/> n <lb/> ) = * (ω <lb/> n <lb/> ∧ * ω <lb/> n <lb/> ) = (ω <lb/> n <lb/> , ω <lb/> n <lb/> ). <lb/> (15) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> A.H. Bilge et al. / Linear Algebra and its Applications 434 (2011) 1200–1214 <lb/></note>

			<page> 1205 <lb/></page>

			<body> By the inequalities (2) we have for k  =  n in 4n-dimensions, q <lb/> 1/n <lb/> n <lb/> ≥  q <lb/> 1/2n <lb/>2n , i.e. q <lb/> 2 <lb/> n  ≥  q  2n . As q n  = <lb/> 1 <lb/> (2n)!  (ω <lb/> n <lb/> , ω <lb/> n <lb/> )  and q  2n  = <lb/> 1 <lb/> (2n)!  2  (ω <lb/> 2n <lb/> , ω <lb/> 2n <lb/> )  this gives  (ω <lb/> n <lb/> , ω <lb/> n <lb/> ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> ≥ (ω <lb/> 2n <lb/> , ω <lb/> 2n <lb/> ) = | * ω <lb/> 2n <lb/> | <lb/> 2 <lb/> .  Thus this <lb/>inequality is saturated by Eq. (15) and  ω  is strong SD. <lb/>If  * ω <lb/> n <lb/> = −ω <lb/> n  , then  * ω <lb/> 2n <lb/> = −(ω <lb/> n <lb/> , ω <lb/> n <lb/> ),  * ω <lb/> 2n <lb/> &lt;  0 and the same saturation argument shows that <lb/> ω  is strong ASD.  <lb/> We will now show that the strong self-duality condition is also equivalent to the self-duality defi-<lb/>nition used by Trautman [11]. <lb/> Theorem 3. Let  ω  be a strong SD (ASD) 2-form in 2n-dimensions. Then <lb/> ω <lb/> n−1 <lb/> = <lb/> n! <lb/>n n/2 <lb/> (ω, ω) <lb/> n <lb/> 2 <lb/> −1 <lb/> *  ω <lb/> ω <lb/> n−1 <lb/> = − <lb/> n! <lb/>n n/2 <lb/> (ω, ω) <lb/> n <lb/> 2 <lb/> −1 <lb/> *  ω <lb/> . <lb/> (16) <lb/> Conversely, if for a (non-degenerate) 2-form  ω  the equality  ω <lb/> n−1 <lb/> =  k  *  ω  holds, then k  = ± <lb/> n! <lb/>n n/2  (ω, ω) <lb/> n <lb/> 2 <lb/> −1 <lb/> and  ω  is strong SD (ASD) for positive (negative) k. <lb/> Proof. If  ω  is strong SD, we can choose a positive orthonormal basis such that  ω = λ(e <lb/> 12 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 34 <lb/> + · · · + <lb/> e <lb/> 4n−1,4n <lb/> )  with respect to this basis. Then  (ω, ω) =  nλ <lb/> 2 and it is not difficult to see that  ω <lb/> n−1  consists <lb/>of the products of 2n  −  2 distinct e <lb/> i  &apos;s, with coefficient  (n −  1)!. Thus  ω <lb/> n−1 <lb/> = λ <lb/> n−2 <lb/> (n −  1)!  *  ω  and <lb/>the result follows by inserting  λ = <lb/> (ω,ω) <lb/> 1/2 <lb/> n  1/2 . If  ω  is strong ASD, then we can take  ω = λ(−e <lb/> 12 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 34 <lb/> + <lb/>· · · +  e <lb/> 4n−1,4n <lb/> ). <lb/> Conversely, if  ω <lb/> n−1 <lb/> =  k  *  ω  holds, then multiplying it with  ω  and taking Hodge duals, we obtain, <lb/>  * ω <lb/> n <lb/> =  k(ω,  ω).  Since  (ω, ω) = σ  2  =  nq  1 and  | * ω <lb/> n <lb/> |=  n!σ <lb/> 1/2 <lb/>2n  =  n!q <lb/> 1/2 <lb/> n  , we obtain k  = (n − <lb/> 1)!q <lb/> 1/2 <lb/> n  /q  1 . Then taking inner products of both sides of  ω <lb/> n−1 <lb/> =  k  *  ω  with themselves, we obtain <lb/> (ω <lb/> n−1 <lb/> , ω <lb/> n−1 <lb/> ) =  k <lb/> 2 <lb/> ( * ω,  * ω) =  k <lb/> 2 <lb/> (ω, ω).  Substituting the value of k obtained above, and using <lb/> (ω <lb/> n−1 <lb/> , ω <lb/> n−1 <lb/> ) = <lb/>  (n −  1)! <lb/>  2  nq n−1  , we obtain q n  =  q n−1 q  1 . But since q  1  ≥  q <lb/> 1/n <lb/> n  , we have q n  ≥ <lb/> q n−1 q <lb/> 1/n <lb/> n  , which leads to q <lb/> n−1 <lb/>n <lb/> ≥  q <lb/> n <lb/>n−1  . This is just the reverse of the weighted elementary symmetric <lb/>polynomials q k  &apos;s inequality in Section 2.2, hence equality must hold, and all eigenvalues of  ω  are equal <lb/>in absolute value. Thus  ω  is strong SD/ASD.  * ω <lb/> n <lb/> =  k(ω,  ω)  and the Eq. (14) gives  |k| = <lb/> n! <lb/>n n/2  (ω, ω) <lb/> n <lb/> 2 <lb/> −1 <lb/> . <lb/> For positive (negative) k we have  * ω <lb/> n <lb/> &gt;  0 ( * ω <lb/> n <lb/> ≤  0), thus  ω  is strong SD (ASD).  <lb/> 3. Geometry of 2-forms <lb/> In Section 3.1 we recall the manifold structure of strong SD/ASD 2-forms, in Section 3.2 we recall <lb/>some basics from Clifford algebras, in Section 3.3 we discuss the maximal linear subspaces of strong <lb/>SD/ASD 2-forms and in Section 3.4 we specialize to 8-dimensions where possibly the richest structures <lb/>are encountered. <lb/> 3.1. Manifold structure of strong SD/ASD 2-forms <lb/> In this section we describe the geometrical structure of strong self-dual and anti-self-dual 2-forms <lb/>in arbitrary even dimensions. Let S  2n be the set of SD/ASD 2-forms in 2n-dimensions. Taking as vector <lb/>space the standard  R <lb/> 2n (with the usual metric and orientation) this set can be equivalently defined in <lb/>terms of skew symmetric matrices as follows. <lb/> Definition 2. Let A  2n be the set of anti-symmetric matrices in 2n-dimensions. Then S  2n  = {A ∈  A  2n  | <lb/> A <lb/> 2 <lb/> + λ <lb/> 2  I  =  0,  λ ∈ R, λ =  0}. <lb/>Including the zero matrix, we denote the closure of S  2n by S  2n . Note that at each A, S  2n contains the <lb/>line through A, i.e. if A  ∈  S  2n , then  λA ∈  S  2n for  λ ∈ R  and hence the existence of 1-dimensional linear <lb/></body>

			<page> 1206 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A.H. Bilge et al. / Linear Algebra and its Applications 434 (2011) 1200–1214 <lb/></note>

			<body> subspaces of the closure is trivial. In the next section we will determine the dimension of maximal <lb/>linear spaces of S  2n . <lb/>We recall now the manifold structure of S  2n . <lb/> Proposition 1. S  2n  is diffeomorphic to <lb/> O(2n)  ∩  A  2n <lb/>  × R  +  . <lb/> Proof. <lb/> φ :  S  2n  −→ <lb/> O(2n)  ∩  A  2n <lb/>  × R <lb/> + <lb/> given by  φ(A) = <lb/> 1 <lb/> κ  A,  κ <lb/> with  κ = <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2n <lb/> Tr A <lb/> 2 <lb/>  1/2 <lb/> is a diffeomorphism [2].  <lb/> There is another useful description of S  2n : <lb/> Proposition 2. S  2n  is diffeomorphic to the homogeneous manifold <lb/> O(2n)  × R  +  <lb/> /U(n) × {1}  (where <lb/> R  +  is considered as a multiplicative group), and dimS  2n  =  n <lb/> 2 <lb/> −  n  +  1. <lb/> Proof. O(2n)  × R  +  acts on S  2n transitively by  (P, α)A = αP <lb/> t AP (where P  ∈  O(2n),  α ∈ R  +  , and <lb/> A  ∈  S  2n ) with isotropy group U(n) [2].  <lb/> In particular, in 8-dimensions, S  8 is a 13 dimensional manifold (with two connected components, <lb/>one of them containing  ω =  e <lb/> 12 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 34 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 56 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 78 and all strongly SD 2-forms, the other containing <lb/> ω = −e <lb/> 12 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 34 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 56 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 78 and all strongly ASD 2-forms). <lb/> 3.2. Clifford algebras <lb/> We recall very briefly the notion of a (real) Clifford algebra. Let V be a real vector space and q be <lb/>a (real) quadratic form on V . The Clifford algebra Cl(V  ,  q) associated to V and q is a real associative <lb/>algebra with identity 1, generated by the vector space V and by the identity, subject to the relations <lb/> v  ·  v  = −q(v)1  for any vector v in V . The map  α(v) = −v  for v  ∈  V extends to an involution of <lb/>the Clifford algebra Cl(V  ,  q) and its  ±1  eigenspaces are called, respectively, the even and odd parts, <lb/>denoted by Cl <lb/> ev <lb/> (V,  q) and Cl <lb/> odd <lb/> (V,  q). A representation of a Clifford algebra Cl(V  ,  q) on a real vector <lb/>space W is a homomorphism from Cl(V  ,  q) to Hom(W  ,  W  ). <lb/> The real Clifford algebra associated to V  = R <lb/> n  and to the quadratic form q(x)  =  x <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + · · · +  x <lb/> 2 <lb/> n  ,  is <lb/>denoted by Cl(n). <lb/> If  {e  1  ,  e  2  , . . . ,  e n  }  is an orthonormal basis for V , the real Clifford algebra Cl(n) is generated by the <lb/> {e  i  }&apos;s,  subject to the relations, <lb/> e <lb/> 2 <lb/> i  = −1,  i  =  1,  . . . ,  n e i e j  +  e j e i  =  0, i  =  j, <lb/> and it is a 2 <lb/> n  -dimensional vector space spanned by the set <lb/> {1,  e  1  ,  e  2  , . . . ,  e  1  e  2  , . . . ,  e  1  e  2  e  3  , . . . ,  e  1  e  2  e  3  , . . . ,  e n  }. <lb/> There is a transpose-antiinvolution on Cl(n), given by reversing the order of generators: e i  1  e i  2  . . .e  i k  → <lb/> e i k e i k−1  . . .e  i  1  .  We denote the image of an element u  ∈  Cl(n) by u <lb/> t <lb/> . <lb/> The spin groups are defined by <lb/> Spin(n)  = {u ∈  Cl <lb/> ev <lb/> (n) |  uxu <lb/> −1 <lb/> ∈  V for x  ∈  V and uu <lb/> t <lb/> =  1}. <lb/>(17) <lb/>Clifford algebras have the following fundamental property: if f  :  V  →  A is a linear map into an <lb/>associative algebra with unit such that f  (v) <lb/> 2 <lb/> = −q(v) ·  1 holds for all v  ∈  V , then f can be uniquely <lb/>extended to an algebra homomorphism from Cl(V  ,  q) to A. <lb/> To give an example relevant for us, let V  = R <lb/> 7 with the standard quadratic form and A  =  End  R  (O)⊕ <lb/> End  R  (O)  where  O  denotes the octonions. To give a map f  :  V  →  A, we understand  R <lb/> 7 as Im(O) <lb/> (imaginary octonions) and define f  (v) = (R  v  , −R  v  )  where R v  denotes the octonion multiplication <lb/>from the right with the imaginary octonion v. This map can be seen to possess the required property <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> A.H. Bilge et al. / Linear Algebra and its Applications 434 (2011) 1200–1214 <lb/></note>

			<page> 1207 <lb/></page>

			<body> and thus extends to an algebra homomorphism Cl(7)  →  End  R  (O) ⊕  End  R  (O),  which can be seen to <lb/>be an isomorphism (for this and generally for Clifford algebras we refer to [8,10]). <lb/>Under this isomorphism Cl <lb/> ev <lb/> (7)  is embedded as the diagonal of End  R  (O) ⊕  End  R  (O),  Spin(7)  ⊂ <lb/> Cl <lb/> ev <lb/> (7)  is embedded diagonally into O(8)  ⊕  O(8) and we can also understand Spin(7) as a subgroup of <lb/> O(8) (in fact, SO(8)) by projecting into a factor; it can be shown that Spin(7) is the subgroup generated <lb/>by the right-multiplication maps R v  for v  ∈  Im(O),  v =  1. We note for later reference, that in this <lb/>model and according to the Eq. (17), Spin(7) consists exactly of those elements P  ∈  O(8) for which <lb/>any R v  (v ∈  Im(O)) is transformed under PR v P  −1  into another right-multiplication map for some <lb/> w  ∈  Im(O): PR v P  −1 =  R w  . <lb/> 3.3. Maximal linear subspaces of S  2n <lb/> In this section we will show that the dimension of maximal linear subspaces of S  2n is equal to <lb/>the number of linearly independent vector fields on S <lb/> 2n−1 . The maximal number of pointwise linearly <lb/>independent vector fields on the sphere S <lb/> N  is given by the Radon–Hurwitz number associated to N  +1: <lb/> If N  +  1  = (2a +  1)2 <lb/> 4d+c with c  =  0, 1, 2 or 3, then the R–H-number associated to N  +  1 equals <lb/>8d  +  2 <lb/> c <lb/> −  1 [10]. <lb/>Using this formula it can be seen that there are three pointwise linearly independent vector fields on <lb/> S <lb/> 3 , seven on S <lb/> 7 , three on S <lb/> 11 and so on. In particular this number is one for the spheres S <lb/> 2n−1 for odd n. <lb/>Let L <lb/> k <lb/> 2n be a k-dimensional linear subspace of S  2n . We will show that the maximum of the numbers <lb/> k is equal to the Radon–Hurwitz number associated to 2n. <lb/> Proposition 3. The dimension of the maximal linear subspaces of S  2n  is equal to the number of linearly <lb/>independent vector fields on S <lb/> 2n−1  . <lb/> Proof. Let L <lb/> k <lb/> 2n be a k-dimensional linear subspace of S  2n , and choose an orthogonal basis  {A  1  ,  A  2  , . . . , <lb/> A k  }  consisting of orthogonal and anti-symmetric matrices for this linear subspace (note that a suitable <lb/>multiple of any nonzero matrix in S  2n is orthogonal). As  (A  i  +  A j  ) ∈  L <lb/> k <lb/> 2n ,  (A  i  +  A j  ) <lb/> 2 is a scalar matrix, <lb/>consequently A i A j  +  A j A i  is a scalar matrix and  (A  i  ,  A j  ) =  Tr(A <lb/> t <lb/>i A j  ) =  0 implies that A i A j  +  A j A i  =  0. <lb/>This means that the assignment e i  →  A i  (i =  1, 2  . . . ,  k) gives a representation of Cl(k) on  R <lb/> 2n . <lb/>Conversely, if for some k, there is a representation of Cl(k) on  R <lb/> 2n , then there is an orthogonal <lb/>representation also and the relations e <lb/> 2 <lb/> i  = −1,  e i e j  +  e j e i  =  0 imply that the images A i  of e i  under this <lb/>representation are anti-symmetric and anti-commuting. This means that the matrices  {A  1  ,  A  2  , . . . ,  A k  } <lb/> span a k-dimensional linear subspace of S  2n . <lb/>Thus, the maximal dimension of a linear subspace of S  2n is the maximal k, for which Cl(k) acts on <lb/> R <lb/> 2n . This the Radon–Hurwitz number associated to 2n [10].  <lb/> This property shows that there is an intimate relationship between strong self-duality and Clifford-<lb/>algebras. Namely, S  2n admits a k-dimensional linear subspace (i.e. including the zero-form, there exists <lb/>a k-dimensional linear space of strongly SD/ASD 2-forms on  R <lb/> 2n ) if and only if there is a representation <lb/>of Cl(k) on  R <lb/> 2n . <lb/> Remark 2. The 7-dimensional plane of 2-forms on  R <lb/> 8 given by the linear self-duality equations of <lb/>Corrigan et al. [5] is one of these planes in S  8 . <lb/>We now prove directly that for odd n there are no linear subspaces other than the 1-dimensional <lb/>ones. <lb/> Proposition 4. Let L  = {A ∈  S  2n  | (A +  J)  ∈  S  2n  }  where J  =  1  ⊗  I is a reference matrix. Then <lb/>L  = {kJ |  k  ∈ R}  for odd n. <lb/> Proof. Let A  = <lb/> ⎛ <lb/> ⎝ <lb/> A  11  A  12 <lb/> −A <lb/> t <lb/> 12  A  22 <lb/> ⎞ <lb/>⎠ , where A  11  +  A <lb/> t <lb/> 11  =  0, A  22  +  A <lb/> t <lb/> 22  =  0. Since  (A +  J)  ∈  S  2n , AJ  +  JA is <lb/>proportional to the identity. This gives A  11  +  A  22  =  0 and the symmetric part of A  12 is proportional <lb/></body>

			<page> 1208 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A.H. Bilge et al. / Linear Algebra and its Applications 434 (2011) 1200–1214 <lb/></note>

			<body> to identity. Therefore A  =  kJ  + <lb/> ⎛ <lb/> ⎝ <lb/> A  11  A  12o <lb/> A  12o  −A  11 <lb/> ⎞ <lb/>⎠ , where A  12o denotes the antisymmetric part of A  12 and <lb/> k  ∈ R.  Then the requirement that A  ∈  S  2n gives <lb/> [A  11  ,  A  12o  ] =  0, A <lb/> 2 <lb/>11  +  A <lb/> 2 <lb/>12o  +  k <lb/>  I  =  0, k <lb/> ∈ R. <lb/> As A  11 and A  12o commute, they can be simultaneously diagonalised, hence for odd n they can be <lb/>brought to the form <lb/> A  11  =  diag(λ 1  , . . . , λ (n−1)/2 ,  0), <lb/> A  12o  =  diag(μ 1  , . . . , μ (n−1)/2 ,  0), <lb/>up to the permutation of blocks, where  =  1  = <lb/> ⎛ <lb/>⎝ <lb/> 0 1 <lb/> −1  0 <lb/> ⎞ <lb/>⎠ , and 0 denotes a 1  ×  1 block. If the blocks <lb/>occur as shown, clearly A <lb/> 2 <lb/>11  +  A <lb/> 2 <lb/>12o cannot be proportional to the identity unless  λ  i  = μ  i  =  0 for all i. <lb/> It can also be seen that the same is the case for any permutation of the blocks.  <lb/> Note that these structures refer to local constructions on a manifold. Existence of k-dimensional <lb/> strong SD/ASD sub-bundles of the bundle of 2-forms is another matter. If there exists a section  ω  of <lb/>strong SD/ASD 2-forms on the manifold, then  ω  can be normalized to have constant norm and it defines <lb/>an almost complex structure. Conversely, almost complex manifolds provide examples of manifolds <lb/>admitting a (global) section of strong self-dual 2-forms. In this case  * ω = κω <lb/> n−1  , where  κ  is constant. <lb/>Then if dω  =  0 it follows that d  *  ω =  0, hence if  ω  is closed and has constant norm, then  ω  is <lb/>harmonic. <lb/> 3.4. Maximal linear spaces of strong AS/ASD 2-forms in 8-dimensions <lb/> By Theorem 3, the maximal linear spaces of strong SD/ASD 2-forms on  R <lb/> 8 are 7-dimensional. By <lb/>the proof of Theorem 3, to produce one such space, it is enough to take a representation of Cl(7) on <lb/> R <lb/> 8 <lb/> = O  and take the span of the images of the generators e  1  ,  e  2  , . . . ,  e  7 of Cl(7). <lb/> Let us take the representation (implicit in Section 3.2) given by e i  →  R e i  .  The corresponding strong <lb/>SD 2-forms are the following (see the Appendix for the multiplication table we use): <lb/> ω  1  = −e <lb/> 12 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 34 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 56 <lb/> −  e <lb/> 78 <lb/> , <lb/>ω  2  = −e <lb/> 13 <lb/> −  e <lb/> 24 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 57 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 68 <lb/> , <lb/>ω  3  = −e <lb/> 14 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 23 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 58 <lb/> −  e <lb/> 67 <lb/> , <lb/>ω  4  = −e <lb/> 15 <lb/> −  e <lb/> 26 <lb/> −  e <lb/> 37 <lb/> −  e <lb/> 48 <lb/> , <lb/>ω  5  = −e <lb/> 16 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 25 <lb/> −  e <lb/> 38 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 47 <lb/> , <lb/>ω  6  = −e <lb/> 17 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 28 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 35 <lb/> −  e <lb/> 46 <lb/> , <lb/>ω  7  = −e <lb/> 18 <lb/> −  e <lb/> 27 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 36 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 45 <lb/> . <lb/> (18) <lb/>We will denote the span of these 2-forms by  L <lb/> 7 and use it as a reference 7-plane inside S  8  ⊂ <lb/> End  R  (O) =  End(R <lb/> 8 <lb/> ). L <lb/> 7 is the first projection of the image of  R <lb/> 7 <lb/> =  Im(O) under the map f  : <lb/> Im(O)  →  End  R  (O) ⊕  End  R  (O),  f  (v) = (R  v  , −R  v  ). L <lb/> 7 is invariant under the matrix-conjugation <lb/>action of Spin(7). <lb/> Let us denote the set of maximal (7-dimensional) linear subspaces of S  8 by L <lb/> 7 <lb/>8 . O(8) acts on L <lb/> 7 <lb/>8 (by <lb/>conjugation on the level of elements, which maps a maximal plane onto another maximal plane) and <lb/>we now show that this action is transitive: <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> A.H. Bilge et al. / Linear Algebra and its Applications 434 (2011) 1200–1214 <lb/></note>

			<page> 1209 <lb/></page>

			<body> Lemma 4. The conjugation action of O(8) on L <lb/> 7 <lb/>8  is transitive. <lb/> Proof. Let L <lb/> 7 and L  7  ∈  L <lb/> 7 <lb/>8 be given and choose matrices A i  ∈  L <lb/> 7 , B i  ∈  L   7  (i =  1,  . . . ,  7) with <lb/> A <lb/> 2 <lb/> i  = −I,  A i A j  +  A j A i  =  0, B <lb/> 2 <lb/> i  = −I,  B i B j  +  B j B i  =  0. The assignments e i  →  A i  and e i  →  B i <lb/> determine two representations  ρ  and  σ  of Cl(7) on  R <lb/> 8 <lb/> .  The assignment e i  → −A  i  determines another <lb/>representation  ρ  −  of Cl(7) on  R <lb/> 8 , which is inequivalent to  ρ.  It is a fact that [10] there are exactly two <lb/>inequivalent representations of Cl(7) on  R <lb/> 8 , so  σ  is either equivalent to  ρ  or to  ρ  −  . Let us assume  σ  to <lb/>be equivalent to  ρ  (the other case being similar) which means that for a certain P  ∈  GL(R, 8) it holds <lb/> B i  =  PA i P  −1  . Anti-symmetry of A i  and B i  gives P <lb/> t PA i  =  A i P <lb/> t P, which necessitates P <lb/> t P to be a scalar <lb/>matrix, since it commutes with all A i  (and the A i  generate the algebra End(R <lb/> 8 <lb/> )).  So, if P <lb/> t P  = λI,  then <lb/> Q  = <lb/> 1 <lb/> √ λ <lb/> P is orthogonal and B i  =  QA i Q  −1  . Thus L   7 is obtained from L <lb/> 7 by the action of Q  ∈  O(8).  <lb/> Remark 3. Spin(7) is the isotropy group of  L <lb/> 7 under this action of O(8) on L <lb/> 7 <lb/>8 . <lb/> Remark 4. All planes L <lb/> 7 <lb/> ∈  L <lb/> 7 <lb/>8 are &quot; pure&quot; in the sense that, the non-zero 2-forms in a plane are either <lb/>all strong SD, or all strong ASD, because  L <lb/> 7 is pure (SD), so any other is pure (SD or ASD) depending on <lb/>whether the conjugation is by matrix from SO(8) or O(8)\SO(8). (This could be seen by a connectivity <lb/>argument also.) <lb/> Remark 5. If  ω  is a 2-form with the associated matrix A and P  ∈  End(R <lb/> 8 <lb/> ),  then the pull-back  η =  P  *  ω <lb/> has the matrix B  =  P <lb/> t AP, so if P  ∈  O(8) then B  =  P  −1  AP, the conjugation by P  −1  . <lb/>Before describing the Bonan form we want to note a few useful properties in 8-dimensions. The <lb/>basic eigenvalue inequalities reduce to <lb/> (ω, ω) <lb/> 2 <lb/> ≥ <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/> (ω <lb/> 2 <lb/> , ω <lb/> 2 <lb/> ) ≥ <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/> | *  ω <lb/> 4 <lb/> |. <lb/> (19) <lb/>When  ω  is strong self-dual we have the equalities <lb/> (ω, ω) <lb/> 2 <lb/> = <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/> (ω <lb/> 2 <lb/> , ω <lb/> 2 <lb/> ) = <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/>  *  ω <lb/> 4 <lb/> , ω <lb/> 3 <lb/> = <lb/> 3 <lb/>2 <lb/> (ω, ω)  *  ω, <lb/> (20) <lb/>while when  ω  is strongly anti self-dual <lb/> (ω, ω) <lb/> 2 <lb/> = <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/> (ω <lb/> 2 <lb/> , ω <lb/> 2 <lb/> ) = − <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/>  *  ω <lb/> 4 <lb/> , ω <lb/> 3 <lb/> = − <lb/> 3 <lb/>2 <lb/> (ω, ω)  *  ω. <lb/> (21) <lb/> Lemma 5. Let  ω  and  η  be two orthogonal strong SD/ASD 2-forms with commuting matrices. Then <lb/> ω <lb/> 2 <lb/> η = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> (ω, ω)  *  η. <lb/> (22) <lb/> Proof. Since the matrices of  ω  and  η  are commuting, they can be simultaneously diagonalized and <lb/>without loss of generality we can choose <lb/> ω =  e  12  +  e  34  +  e  56  +  e  78  , η =  e  12  +  e  34  −  e  56  −  e  78  . <lb/> The result follows by simple computation.  <lb/> Lemma 6. Let  ω  and  η  be two orthogonal strong SD/ASD 2-forms whose matrices anti-commute. Then <lb/> ω <lb/> 2 <lb/> η = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> (ω, ω)  *  η. <lb/> (23) <lb/> Proof. By anti-commutativity  ω ± η  are also strong SD/ASD and by connectivity reasons all are SD or <lb/>ASD. Applying (19) for the SD-case and (20) for the-ASD case to both  ω ± η  and using orthogonality <lb/>gives the result by simple computation.  <lb/></body>

			<page> 1210 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A.H. Bilge et al. / Linear Algebra and its Applications 434 (2011) 1200–1214 <lb/></note>

			<body> 4. The Bonan-form <lb/> In Section 4.1 we give an expression for the Bonan-form in terms of strong self-dual 2-forms and in <lb/>Section 4.2 we compute explicitly the eigenvalues and eigenspaces of the self-adjoint map on 2-forms <lb/>associated with the Bonan-form. <lb/> 4.1. The relationship of the Bonan-form with strong self-duality <lb/> The Bonan-form, which is a Spin(7)-invariant 4-form in 8-dimensions [4,10,9], and which plays <lb/>an important role in special Spin-geometry, can be constructed in an elegant way in terms of strong <lb/>self-dual 2-forms. <lb/>Consider the 7-plane  L <lb/> 7 <lb/> ∈  L <lb/> 7 <lb/>8 with an orthonormal basis  {η  1  , η  2  , . . . , η  7  }  and define <lb/> Φ  = η <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + η <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  + · · · + η <lb/> 2 <lb/>7  ∈  Λ <lb/> 4 <lb/> (R <lb/> 8 <lb/> ) <lb/>  * <lb/> . <lb/> (24) <lb/>If  {θ  1  , θ  2  , . . . , θ  7  }  is another orthonormal basis of  L <lb/> 7 it is easily seen that <lb/> η <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + η <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  + · · · + η <lb/> 2 <lb/>7  = θ <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + θ <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  + · · · + θ <lb/> 2 <lb/>7  . <lb/> The operation of pullback of a 2-form  η ∈ L <lb/> 7 by an element P  ∈  Spin(7) is expressed at the matrix <lb/>level by the operation of conjugation by P  −1  , so the map  L <lb/> 7 <lb/> → L <lb/> 7 ,  η →  P  *  η  is orthogonal and <lb/>consequently, <lb/> P <lb/>  *  Φ  = (P <lb/>  * <lb/> η  1  ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> + (P <lb/>  * <lb/> η  2  ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> + · · · + (P <lb/>  * <lb/> η  7  ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> =  Φ, <lb/> (25) <lb/>i.e. the 4-form  Φ  (which is self-dual by Theorem 1) is Spin(7)-invariant. Thus, the Bonan-form is <lb/>expressed in terms of strong self-dual 2-forms. <lb/>To give an explicit expression we can use the ortonormal basis <lb/> η  1  = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ω  1  , η  2  = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ω  2  , . . . , η  7  = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ω  7 <lb/> , <lb/> (26) <lb/>where the  ω  i  &apos;s are given by Eq. (18) and find <lb/> Φ  = − <lb/> 3 <lb/>2 <lb/> (e <lb/> 1234 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 1256 <lb/> −  e <lb/> 1278 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 1357 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 1368 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 1458 <lb/> −  e <lb/> 1467 <lb/> −e <lb/> 2358 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 2367 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 2457 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 2468 <lb/> −  e <lb/> 3456 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 3478 <lb/> +  e <lb/> 5678 <lb/> ). <lb/> (27) <lb/>The same construction can naturally be applied to any L <lb/> 7 <lb/> ∈  L <lb/> 7 <lb/>8 and in this way a Bonan-form  Φ  L <lb/> is associated with every maximal 7-plane of strong SD/ASD 2-forms. If Q  ∈  O(8), then Q  *  Φ  is the <lb/>Bonan-form associated with the plane Q  −1  L <lb/> 7  Q and the isotropy group of Q  *  Φ  is Q  −1  Spin(7)Q  . <lb/> 4.2. Eigenspaces of the Bonan-form <lb/> We want to compute the eigenspaces and eigenvalues of the self-adjoint map T  Φ  on  Λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> (R <lb/> 8 <lb/> )  * <lb/> defined by T  Φ (η) = * (Φη).  (The method explained below works for any  Φ  L  .) We start with an <lb/>orthonormal basis of  L <lb/> 7 and denote it by  {ω  12  , ω  13  , . . . , ω  18  }  (We abuse the notation: double-indices <lb/>denote no more the coefficients of a 2-form, but a 2-form itself; it will be convenient in the sequel.) <lb/>Let A  1i  (i =  2,  . . . ,  8) denote the matrices corresponding to  ω  1i  .  Let A ij  =  A  1i  A  1j for 1  &lt;  i  &lt;  j. The <lb/>matrices A ij  for i  &lt;  j will constitute a basis for skew-symmetric matrices in End(R <lb/> 8 <lb/> )  and will represent <lb/>strong SD/ASD forms (their squares are scalar matrices). Now, it can easily be seen that two distinct A ij <lb/> and A kl  commute iff  {i,  j} and  {k,  l} are disjoint; A ij  and A kl  anti-commute iff  {i,  j} and  {k,  l} have one <lb/>index common. We denote the 2-form corresponding to A ij  by  ω  ij  . The set  {ω  12  , . . . , ω  78  }  is a basis of <lb/>2-forms. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> A.H. Bilge et al. / Linear Algebra and its Applications 434 (2011) 1200–1214 <lb/></note>

			<page> 1211 <lb/></page>

			<body> Let <lb/> Φ  = ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>12  + · · · + ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>18  , Φ <lb/> = ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>23  + · · · + ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>78  . <lb/> By symbolic computation with REDUCE, it can be seen that  Φ  = −Φ,  hence the sum of the squares <lb/>of the basis elements is zero. Since  {ω  12  , . . . , ω  18  }  is an orthogonal basis of a 7-plane  L <lb/> 7 ,  Φ  is a Bonan <lb/>form. We will show that the linear maps T  Φ  and T  Φ   have both 7-and 21-dimensional eigenspaces with <lb/>eigenvalues  ±3  and  ∓1  (after scaling), and  L  is the eigenspace corresponding to the eigenvalue  ±3. <lb/> Thus each Bonan form determines an  L.  Hence maximal linear subspaces of strong self-dual 2-forms <lb/>and the Bonan forms are in 1–1 correspondence. <lb/> Proposition 5. T  Φ  :  Λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> (R <lb/> 8 <lb/> )  *  →  Λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> (R <lb/> 8 <lb/> )  *  defined by T  Φ (η) = * (Φη)  where  Φ  = ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>12  + · · · + ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>18  , <lb/>has eigenvalues 9/2 and  −3/2,  with 7- and 21-dimensional eigenspaces, respectively. (Scaling  Φ  we can <lb/>get eigenvalues 3 and  −1.) <lb/> Proof. Applying the Lemmas 3 and 4, one gets, <lb/> T  Φ (ω  1j  ) =  T  ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>1j <lb/> (ω  1j  ) + <lb/> k  =j <lb/> T  ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>1k <lb/> (ω  1j  ) = <lb/> 3 <lb/>2 <lb/> ω  1j  +  6  × <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ω  1j  . <lb/> T  Φ (ω  jk  ) =  T  ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>1j <lb/> (ω  jk  ) +  T  ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>1k <lb/> (ω  jk  ) + <lb/> l  =j,k <lb/> T  ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>1l <lb/> (ω  jk  ) =  2  × <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ω  jk  −  5  × <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ω  jk  . <lb/> We will now show that  Φ   has eigenvalues  −9/2  and 3/2 with, respectively, 7-and 21-dimensional <lb/>eigenspaces, hence prove that it is equal to  −Φ. <lb/> Proposition 6. T  Φ  :  Λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> (R <lb/> 8 <lb/> )  *  →  Λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> (R <lb/> 8 <lb/> )  *  defined by T  Φ   (η) = * (Φ  η)  where  Φ  = ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>23  +· · ·+ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>28  , <lb/>has eigenvalues  −9/2  and 3/2, with 7- and 21-dimensional eigenspaces, respectively. (Scaling  Φ   we can <lb/>get eigenvalues  −3  and 1.) <lb/> Proof. We start by computing T  Φ   on  ω  1k .  Φ   is a sum of 21 terms and there are exactly 6 terms  ω <lb/> 2 <lb/> ij <lb/> where i  =  k or j  =  k and 15 terms with i  =  k and j  =  k. By Lemmas 4 and 3, these first and the <lb/>second group of terms lead to positive and negative contributions, hence <lb/> T  Φ   (ω  1k  ) =  T  ω <lb/> 2 <lb/> ik <lb/> (ω  1k  ) + <lb/> i,j  =k <lb/> T  ω  ij  (ω  1k  ) =  6  × <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ω  1k  −  15  × <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ω  1k  = − <lb/> 9 <lb/>2 <lb/> ω  1k  . <lb/> By similar counting arguments, <lb/> T  φ   (ω  jk  ) = <lb/>  3 <lb/>2 <lb/> + (5 +  5)  × <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> − (5 +  5)  × <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ω  jk  = <lb/> 3 <lb/>2 <lb/> . <lb/> We have thus seen that any maximal linear subspace  L <lb/> 7 of strong self-dual 2-forms determines <lb/>a Bonan form as the sum of squares of any orthogonal basis and conversely, given a Bonan form  Φ, <lb/> an  L <lb/> 7 is determined as a 7-dimensional eigenspace of the linear map T  Φ  determined by  Φ.  We will <lb/>now show that given an  L <lb/> 7 , the Bonan form is uniquely determined by a linear transformation that <lb/>acts as identity on  L <lb/> 7 . The following proposition is proved by directly checking the claim by symbolic <lb/>computation with REDUCE. <lb/> Proposition 7. Let  Ψ  be a 4-form such that <lb/>T  Ψ (ω  1i  ) =  kω  1i  ,  i  =  2,  . . . ,  8. <lb/> Then <lb/> Ψ  =  k <lb/> 2 <lb/>9 <lb/> Φ. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1212 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A.H. Bilge et al. / Linear Algebra and its Applications 434 (2011) 1200–1214 <lb/></note>

			<body> We note that in the characterization above,  Ψ  is not assumed to be self-dual, but its self-duality <lb/>follows from the invariance of the  ω  1i &apos;s. Furthermore, if an  L <lb/> 7 has a basis  ω  1i with anti self-dual  ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>1i &apos;s, <lb/>then the form  Ψ  defined above is anti self-dual. <lb/> 4.3. The SO(8) action on the Bonan form <lb/> In this section we give the explicit expression of the Bonan form under the action of SO(8). Let  ω  ij <lb/> be as in the previous section and let A ij  be the corresponding matrix. Thus the A ij  &apos;s span the Lie algebra <lb/>of SO(8). It is easy to see that the exponential of matrix A ij  is <lb/> e <lb/> tA ij  =  cos(t)I  +  sin(t)A ij  . <lb/> The action of SO(8) on 2-forms is obtained by its action on matrices by conjugation. If R  ∈  SO(8), <lb/> and R  · ω  denotes its action on the 2-form  ω,  then <lb/> R  · ω =  RAR <lb/> t <lb/> . <lb/> We will show that e <lb/> tA ij  for i  ≥  2 leaves the Bonan form invariant. For simplicity of notation let <lb/> t ij  =  e <lb/> tA ij  = (cI +  sA ij  ), <lb/> where <lb/> c  =  cos(t), s  =  sin(t). <lb/>The 2-form t ij  · ω  1k is the 2-form corresponding to the matrix  (cI +  sA ij  )A  1k  (cI −  sA ij  ).  Then, <lb/> t ij  · ω  1i  = (c <lb/> 2 <lb/> −  s <lb/> 2 <lb/> )ω  1i  +  2csω 1j  , <lb/> t ij  · ω  1j  = (c <lb/> 2 <lb/> −  s <lb/> 2 <lb/> )ω  1j  −  2csω 1i  , <lb/> t ij  · ω  1k  = ω  ik  ,  k  =  i, j. <lb/> (28) <lb/>It is easy to see that <lb/> (t  ij  · ω  1i  ) ∧  t ij  · ω  1i  + (t  ij  · ω  1j  ) ∧  t ij  · ω  1j  = ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>1i  + ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>1j  . <lb/> It follows that t ij  leaves the Bonan form invariant hence generate Spin(7). <lb/> Identifying the Lie algebra of SO(8) with 2-forms, if X is any vector in SO(8), <lb/>e <lb/> tX <lb/> ·  Φ  =  e <lb/> tY <lb/> ·  Φ, <lb/> where Y belongs to the span of the A1i&apos;s. Thus the orbit of the Bonan form is locally generated by t  1j , <lb/>for j  =  2,  . . . ,  8. Let y i  (t),  i  =  1,  . . . ,  8 be a 1-parameter family of functions such that <lb/> y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>3  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>4  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>5  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>6  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>7  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>8  =  1. <lb/>Then the matrix R defined by <lb/> R  =  y  1  I  +  y  2  ω  12  +  y  3  ω  13  +  y  4  ω  14  +  y  5  ω  15  +  y  6  ω  16  +  y  7  ω  17  +  y  8  ω  18 <lb/> is a one parameter family of orthogonal matrices. The image of the Bonan form  Φ  under the action of <lb/> R is obtained by taking the wedge products of the images of the 2-forms  ω  1j &apos;s and summing up. The <lb/>result is <lb/>   = <lb/> i&lt;j&lt;k <lb/> c ijk  (e <lb/> 1ijk <lb/> + * e <lb/> 1ijk <lb/> ), <lb/> where <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> A.H. Bilge et al. / Linear Algebra and its Applications 434 (2011) 1200–1214 <lb/></note>

			<page> 1213 <lb/></page>

			<body> c  234  =  1  −  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1 <lb/> y <lb/> 2 <lb/>5  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>6  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>7  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>8 <lb/> , <lb/> c  256  =  1  −  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1 <lb/> y <lb/> 2 <lb/>3  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>4  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>7  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>8 <lb/> , <lb/> c  278  = −1 +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1 <lb/> y <lb/> 2 <lb/>3  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>4  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>5  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>6 <lb/> , <lb/> c  357  =  1  −  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1 <lb/> y <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>4  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>6  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>8 <lb/> , <lb/> c  368  =  1  −  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1 <lb/> y <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>4  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>5  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>7 <lb/> , <lb/> c  458  =  1  −  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1 <lb/> y <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>3  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>6  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>7 <lb/> , <lb/> c  467  = −1 +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1 <lb/> y <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>3  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>5  +  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>8 <lb/> , <lb/> (29) <lb/> c  235  = −4y  1  y  8  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (y  1  y  8  +  y  2  y  7  −  y  3  y  6  +  y  4  y  5  ), <lb/> c  246  =  4y 1  y  8  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (−y  1  y  8  −  y  2  y  7  −  y  3  y  6  +  y  4  y  5  ), <lb/> c  347  =  4y 1  y  8  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (−y  1  y  8  +  y  2  y  7  +  y  3  y  6  +  y  4  y  5  ), <lb/> c  567  =  4y 1  y  8  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (−y  1  y  8  +  y  2  y  7  −  y  3  y  6  −  y  4  y  5  ), <lb/> (30) <lb/> c  236  =  4y 1  y  7  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (−y  1  y  7  +  y  2  y  8  +  y  3  y  5  +  y  4  y  6  ), <lb/> c  245  =  4y 1  y  7  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (−y  1  y  7  +  y  2  y  8  −  y  3  y  5  −  y  4  y  6  ), <lb/> c  348  = −4y  1  y  7  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (y  1  y  7  +  y  2  y  8  −  y  3  y  5  +  y  4  y  6  ), <lb/> c  568  = −4y  1  y  7  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (y  1  y  7  +  y  2  y  8  +  y  3  y  5  −  y  4  y  6  ), <lb/> (31) <lb/> c  237  = −4y  1  y  6  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (y  1  y  6  −  y  2  y  5  +  y  3  y  8  +  y  4  y  7  ), <lb/> c  248  = −4y  1  y  6  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (y  1  y  6  −  y  2  y  5  −  y  3  y  8  −  y  4  y  7  ), <lb/> c  345  = −4y  1  y  6  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (y  1  y  6  +  y  2  y  5  +  y  3  y  8  −  y  4  y  7  ), <lb/> c  578  =  4y 1  y  6  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (−y  1  y  6  −  y  2  y  5  +  y  3  y  8  −  y  4  y  7  ), <lb/> (32) <lb/> c  238  =  4y 1  y  5  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (−y  1  y  5  −  y  2  y  6  −  y  3  y  7  +  y  4  y  8  ), <lb/> c  247  = −4y  1  y  5  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (y  1  y  5  +  y  2  y  6  −  y  3  y  7  +  y  4  y  8  ), <lb/> c  346  =  4y 1  y  5  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (−y  1  y  5  +  y  2  y  6  −  y  3  y  7  −  y  4  y  8  ), <lb/> c  678  = −4y  1  y  5  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (y  1  y  5  −  y  2  y  6  −  y  3  y  7  −  y  4  y  8  ), <lb/> (33) <lb/> c  257  =  4y 1  y  4  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (−y  1  y  4  +  y  2  y  3  +  y  5  y  8  +  y  6  y  7  ), <lb/> c  268  =  4y 1  y  4  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (−y  1  y  4  +  y  2  y  3  −  y  5  y  8  −  y  6  y  7  ), <lb/> c  356  = −4y  1  y  4  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (y  1  y  4  +  y  2  y  3  −  y  5  y  8  +  y  6  y  7  ), <lb/> c  378  =  4y 1  y  4  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (−y  1  y  4  −  y  2  y  3  −  y  5  y  8  +  y  6  y  7  ), <lb/> (34) <lb/> c  258  = −4y  1  y  3  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (y  1  y  3  +  y  2  y  4  −  y  5  y  7  +  y  6  y  8  ), <lb/> c  267  =  4y 1  y  3  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (−y  1  y  3  −  y  2  y  4  −  y  5  y  7  +  y  6  y  8  ), <lb/> c  456  =  4y 1  y  3  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (−y  1  y  3  +  y  2  y  4  +  y  5  y  7  +  y  6  y  8  ), <lb/> c  478  = −4y  1  y  3  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (y  1  y  3  −  y  2  y  4  +  y  5  y  7  +  y  6  y  8  ), <lb/> (35) <lb/></body>

			<page> 1214 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A.H. Bilge et al. / Linear Algebra and its Applications 434 (2011) 1200–1214 <lb/></note>

			<body> c  358  =  4y 1  y  2  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (−y  1  y  2  +  y  3  y  4  +  y  5  y  6  +  y  7  y  8  ), <lb/> c  367  = −4y  1  y  2  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (y  1  y  2  −  y  3  y  4  +  y  5  y  6  +  y  7  y  8  ), <lb/> c  457  = −4y  1  y  2  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (y  1  y  2  +  y  3  y  4  −  y  5  y  6  +  y  7  y  8  ), <lb/> c  468  = −4y  1  y  2  +  8y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (y  1  y  2  +  y  3  y  4  +  y  5  y  6  −  y  7  y  8  ). <lb/> (36) <lb/> 5. Conclusion <lb/> In order to conclude, we wish to re-emphasize that a Bonan 4-form is associated with every maximal <lb/>7-plane of strongly self-dual (or anti-self-dual) 2-forms. The square of any strong self-dual 2-form in <lb/>8-dimensions as given above yields a Bonan 4-form that is a Spin(7) invariant form and plays an <lb/>important role in the construction of special spin geometries [11]. We also give explicitly the action of <lb/> SO(8) on a given Bonan 4-form. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgements <lb/> This work is supported by TUBITAK (The Scientific and Technological Research Council of Turkey) <lb/>through Project No. TBAG/107T553. T.D. is supported in part by the Turkish Academy of Sciences (TUBA). </div>

			<div type="annex"> <lb/> Appendix <lb/> We use the following multiplication table for the octonions: <lb/>1 <lb/> e  1 <lb/> e  2 <lb/> e  3 <lb/> e  4 <lb/> e  5 <lb/> e  6 <lb/> e  7 <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 <lb/> e  1 <lb/> e  2 <lb/> e  3 <lb/> e  4 <lb/> e  5 <lb/> e  6 <lb/> e  7 <lb/> e  1 <lb/> e  1 <lb/> −1 <lb/> e  3 <lb/> −e  2 <lb/> e  5 <lb/> −e  4  −e  7 <lb/> e  6 <lb/> e  2 <lb/> e  2 <lb/> −e  3  −1 <lb/> e  1 <lb/> e  6 <lb/> e  7 <lb/> −e  4  −e  5 <lb/> e  3 <lb/> e  3 <lb/> e  2 <lb/> −e  1  −1 <lb/> e  7 <lb/> −e  6 <lb/> e  5 <lb/> −e  4 <lb/> e  4 <lb/> e  4 <lb/> −e  5  −e  6  −e  7  −1 <lb/> e  1 <lb/> e  2 <lb/> e  3 <lb/> e  5 <lb/> e  5 <lb/> e  4 <lb/> −e  7 <lb/> e  6 <lb/> −e  1  −1 −e  3 <lb/> e  2 <lb/> e  6 <lb/> e  6 <lb/> e  7 <lb/> e  4 <lb/> −e  5  −e  2 <lb/> e  3 <lb/> −1 −e  1 <lb/> e  7 <lb/> e  7 <lb/> −e  6 <lb/> e  5 <lb/> e  4 <lb/> −e  3  −e  2 <lb/> e  1 <lb/> −1 <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] A.H. Bilge, T. Dereli, ¸ <lb/>S. Koçak, Self-dual Yang–Mills fields in eight dimensions, Lett. Math. Phys. 36 (1996) 301–309. <lb/>[2] A.H. Bilge, T. Dereli, ¸ <lb/>S. Koçak, The geometry of self-dual two-forms, J. Math. Phys. 38 (1997) 4804–4814. <lb/>[3] A.H. Bilge, T. Dereli, ¸ <lb/>S. Koçak, The geometry of self-dual gauge fields, in: J. Lukierski, M. Mozrzymas (Eds.), IX. Max Born Sym-<lb/>posium: New Symmetries in the Theories of Fundamental Interactions, Polish Scientific Publishers PWN, Warszawa, 1997, <lb/>pp.277-288. <lb/>[4] E. Bonan, Sur les varieties riemanniennes a groupe d&apos;holonomie G  2 ou Spin(7), C.R. Acad. Sci. Paris 262 (1966) 127–129. <lb/>[5] E. Corrigan, C. Devchand, D. Fairlie, J. Nuyts, First order equations for gauge fields in spaces of dimensions greater than four, <lb/>Nucl. Phys. B 214 (1983) 452–464. <lb/>[6] M. Marcus, H. Minc, A Survey of Matrix Theory and Matrix Inequalities, Ally and Bacon, 1964. <lb/>[7] B. Grossman, T.W. Kephart, J.D. Statsheff, Solutions to Yang–Mills field equations in eight dimensions and the last Hopf map, <lb/>Comm. Math. Phys. 96 (1984) 431–437. <lb/>[8] F.R. Harvey, Spinors and Calibrations, Academic Press, New York, 1990. <lb/>[9] D. Joyce, Compact Manifolds with Special Holonomy, Oxford University Press, 2000. <lb/>[10] H.B. Lawson Jr., M.L. Michelsson, Spin Geometry, Princeton University Press, 1989. <lb/>[11] A. Trautman, Solutions of the Maxwell and Yang–Mills equations associated with Hopf fiberings, Int. J. Theor. Phys. 16 (1977) <lb/>561–565. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
