<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage> CDF Note 5147 <lb/>October 14, 1999 <lb/> Fragmentation of CDF jets: perturbative or <lb/>non-perturbative? <lb/> Alexei N. Safonov <lb/>For CDF Collaboration <lb/>University of Florida <lb/> Abstract <lb/> Proceedings. International Euroconference in Quantum Chromodynamics 7-13 July 1999, <lb/>Montpellier, France <lb/> </titlePage>

			<front> Fragmentation of CDF jets: perturbative or non-perturbative? <lb/> Alexei Safonov <lb/>Department of Physics, University of Florida, <lb/>Gainesville FL32611-8440, USA <lb/>For CDF Collaboration <lb/>Presented are the most recent jet fragmentation results from CDF: inclusive distributions of charged particle <lb/>momenta and their k T in jets; average track multiplicities, as well as angular distributions of multiplicity flow, <lb/>for a wide range of jet energies with E T from 40 to 300 GeV. The results are compared with Monte-Carlo and, <lb/>when possible, analytical calculations performed in resummed perturbative QCD approximations (MLLA). <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. INTRODUCTION <lb/> Fig. 1 gives a symbolic depiction of the jet <lb/>fragmentation, in which one can distinguish the <lb/>stage governed by perturbative QCD and the stage <lb/>of phenomenological hadronization. The fuzzy <lb/>boundary between the stages is usually associated <lb/>with a k T cut-off scale Q 0 . To proceed with <lb/>perturbative calculations, one has to set Q 0 »Λ QCD so <lb/>that α s, which is also effectively enlarged by a <lb/>double log term that comes from soft (dk/k) and <lb/>collinear (dk T /k T) divergences, remains small. <lb/> Two Stages of jet evolution: <lb/>I -perturbative QCD (k T &gt;Q 0 ) <lb/>II -phenomenological hadronization <lb/> R ~ 1/M JJ <lb/>R ~ 1/Q 0 <lb/>R ~ 1 fm ~ 1/m π <lb/> Figure 1. Symbolic depiction of the jet <lb/>fragmentation. <lb/> Cone 0.280 <lb/>M JJ =82 GeV (lower set) <lb/>M JJ =628 GeV (upper set) <lb/>M JJ =229 GeV (middle set) <lb/>DATA (points) vs Herwig/QFL(line) <lb/>CDF Preliminary <lb/> dN/dk T <lb/> k T (GeV) <lb/> Figure 2. dN/dk T distribution for tracks within cone <lb/>0.28 around the jet axis. Dijet events. Herwig 5.6 <lb/>scaled by 0.89. <lb/>From Fig. 2, one can easily see that within <lb/>&quot;straightforward&quot; perturbative QCD (cut-off scale of <lb/>the order of 1 GeV) there is no chance to coherently <lb/>describe the jet fragmentation, as the vast majority <lb/>of hadrons within jets has k T well below 1 GeV <lb/>scale. Therefore, perturbative methods may seem to <lb/>be insufficient for predicting the characteristics of jet <lb/>hadrons and one needs to rely heavily on the <lb/>hadronization models. <lb/> In order to make perturbative methods usable to <lb/>describe jet fragmentation, two requirements have to <lb/>be fulfilled: first, final hadrons have to &quot;remember&quot; <lb/>properties of partons and, second, perturbative <lb/>calculations have to include partons with sufficiently <lb/>low k T . In other words, the cut-off scale needs to be <lb/>pushed down below 1 GeV. <lb/>Possible perturbative dominance scenario <lb/>satisfying the requirements listed above, can be <lb/>realized by taking perturbative calculations carried <lb/>out in the framework of Modified Leading Log <lb/>Approximation (MLLA) [1] together with the <lb/>hypothesis of Local Parton-Hadron Duality (LPHD) <lb/>[2]. <lb/>MLLA calculations (at least, those related to <lb/>momentum distributions) are infrared stable, which <lb/>allows one to push the cut-off scale Q  eff  all the way <lb/>down to Λ  QCD . In this way, soft partons are <lb/>accounted for, and the cut-off parameter Q eff  has to <lb/>be obtained from data. <lb/>LPHD assumess that hadronization happens <lb/>locally in the very last moment, so that properties of <lb/>final hadrons resemble those of initial partons. Thus, <lb/>hadron distributions are related to parton ones. <lb/>Parameter Const, which basically relates the number <lb/>of final hadrons and initial partons becomes another <lb/>free parameter: <lb/> partons <lb/>hadrons <lb/> N <lb/>N <lb/>Const = <lb/> As a result, we have a perturbative model, which <lb/>potentially may describe jet fragmentation with only <lb/>two free parameters - Const and Q eff  . <lb/> 2. THEORETICAL PREDICTIONS <lb/> MLLA+LPHD gives a number of very firm <lb/>predictions, which can be compared to the <lb/>experimental data. <lb/>Here, when comparing data to the MLLA <lb/>calculations, we will be concentrating mostly on <lb/>inclusive multiplicity of charged hadrons in jets, the <lb/>inclusive momentum distribution shape and its peak <lb/>position. <lb/>The MLLA parton momentum spectrum for a <lb/>gluon jet is given by [1,3]: <lb/>, <lb/>1 <lb/> ) <lb/>sinh <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>( <lb/>(cosh <lb/>sinh <lb/>4 <lb/>sinh <lb/>4 <lb/>sinh <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>( <lb/>cosh <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>4 <lb/> 2 <lb/>/ <lb/>2 <lb/>/ <lb/>2 <lb/>/ <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>× <lb/>× <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>= <lb/> − <lb/>+ <lb/>− <lb/>+ <lb/>Γ <lb/> − <lb/>+ <lb/>− <lb/> ∫ <lb/> α <lb/>ζ <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/>ζ <lb/>α <lb/> α <lb/>π <lb/>π <lb/> π <lb/>τ <lb/>ξ <lb/>σ <lb/>σ <lb/> Y <lb/>b <lb/>Nc <lb/>Y <lb/>b <lb/>Nc <lb/>B <lb/>b <lb/>Nc <lb/> B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/> I <lb/>e <lb/>d <lb/>d <lb/>d <lb/> with important variables: <lb/>, <lb/>ln <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/>1 <lb/>ln <lb/> eff <lb/>cone <lb/>jet <lb/>jet <lb/> Q <lb/>E <lb/>Y <lb/>E <lb/>p <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> θ <lb/>ξ <lb/> = <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/> and some secondary ones: <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>tanh <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/>1 <lb/> − <lb/>= <lb/>+ <lb/>= <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/> ζ <lb/>α <lb/>τ <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/>ξ <lb/>ζ <lb/> o <lb/>o i <lb/>Y <lb/> It should be pointed out that MLLA calculations <lb/>are carried out using the assumption x©1. On the <lb/>other side of the spectrum, still one has to stay above <lb/>p=0.5 GeV to avoid the finite mass effects since <lb/>MLLA deals with massless partons, not hadrons. <lb/>Although the curve should go to zero at ξ=0, the <lb/>exact shape of the descending is not controlled in the <lb/>calculation. <lb/>The peak position of the momentum spectrum is <lb/>given by [3]: <lb/>3 <lb/>29 <lb/>. <lb/>0 <lb/>, <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/> = <lb/>= <lb/>− <lb/>+ <lb/>= <lb/> f <lb/>o <lb/> n <lb/>for <lb/>c <lb/>where <lb/>c <lb/>cY <lb/>Y <lb/> ξ <lb/> The value of the third term in the equation above, <lb/>the constant, is determined by the MLLA spectrum <lb/>function. Though, strictly speaking, next-to-MLLA <lb/>terms may contribute to the peak position at this <lb/>level. <lb/>Multiplicity of partons in a gluon jet in MLLA is <lb/>given by [3]: <lb/> b <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>z <lb/>where <lb/>z <lb/>I <lb/>z <lb/>B <lb/>N <lb/> c <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>g <lb/> / <lb/>16 <lb/>), <lb/>( <lb/>2 <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 <lb/> = <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>Γ <lb/>= <lb/> + <lb/>+ <lb/>− <lb/> It is also very important to mention that in <lb/>MLLA, gluon and quark jets are identical apart from <lb/>a numerical factor r, ratio of multiplicities: <lb/> For the range of CDF jet energies, the theoretical <lb/>value of r is almost constant. In MLLA r=9/4 [3] <lb/>(ratio of gluon and quark color charges), in the next-<lb/>to-MLLA calculations r=2.05 [4], and in the next-to-<lb/>next-to-MLLA order two different values were <lb/>reported: r=2.0 [5] and r=1.85 [6]. Experimental <lb/>e+e-data suggests that this ratio r is somewhere <lb/>between 1.0 and 1.5 [7], and may be energy <lb/>dependent. <lb/> 3. ANALYSIS AT CDF <lb/> The following results are based on approximately <lb/>100,000 dijet events taken in 1994-96 at CDF. <lb/>Selected events were required to have two high E T <lb/> well-balanced jets in the central region of the <lb/>detector. Events with three or four jets were also <lb/>allowed if the additional jets were sufficiently soft <lb/>(E T sum of the third and fourth jets less than 15% of <lb/>total event E T ). <lb/>One of the significant advantages of high energy <lb/>hadron machines, such as Tevatron, is that the range <lb/>of dijet masses one can look at is rather wide. In this <lb/>analysis, the masses of the dijet events range <lb/>between 72 and 740 GeV, and the events were <lb/>subdivided in 9 sub-samples, as shown in Table 1. <lb/>072 &lt; M jj &lt; 094 <lb/>&lt;M jj &gt; = 81.8 <lb/>094 &lt; M jj &lt; 120 <lb/>&lt;M jj &gt; = 105.1 <lb/>120 &lt; M jj &lt; 154 <lb/>&lt;M jj &gt; = 140.4 <lb/>154 &lt; M jj &lt; 200 <lb/>&lt;M jj &gt; = 182.7 <lb/>200 &lt; M jj &lt; 260 <lb/>&lt;M jj &gt; = 228.9 <lb/>260 &lt; M jj &lt; 340 <lb/>&lt;M jj &gt; = 292.5 <lb/>340 &lt; M jj &lt; 440 <lb/>&lt;M jj &gt; = 378.0 <lb/>440 &lt; M jj &lt; 570 <lb/>&lt;M jj &gt; = 487.9 <lb/>570 &lt; M jj &lt; 740 <lb/>&lt;M jj &gt; = 628.0 <lb/>Table 1. Dijet masses (GeV) of the 9 sub-samples. <lb/>It is important that MLLA predictions have <lb/>angular dependence. In other words, one can look at <lb/>distributions of hadrons within fixed opening angle <lb/>around the jet axis and compare experimental data <lb/>with the predictions. In our analysis, we chose 5 <lb/>such restricted cone-sizes: 0.168, 0.217, 0.280, 0.361 <lb/>and 0.466. Angle is defined as the angle between the <lb/>jet direction and the cone side. <lb/>Unlike e+e-experiments, in our data we have a <lb/>mixture of quark and gluon jets, which can not be <lb/>separated from each other without further <lb/>investigation. We plan to carry out an analysis <lb/>similar to this one for γ-jet sample, which is enriched <lb/>with quark jets and, in this way, to separate those <lb/>contributions. <lb/>In our case, the formulas from the previous <lb/>chapter have to be modified somewhat to take into <lb/>account the presence of both kinds of jets: <lb/>), <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/> q <lb/> q <lb/>g <lb/>g <lb/>hadrons <lb/> N <lb/>N <lb/>Const <lb/>N <lb/> ε <lb/>ξ <lb/>ε <lb/>ξ <lb/>ξ <lb/> + <lb/>= <lb/> where N g and N q are the gluon and quark jet spectra. <lb/>In MLLA, N g (ξ) and N q (ξ) are different by a single <lb/>factor r, therefore: <lb/>) <lb/>/ <lb/>1 <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>/ <lb/>1 <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/> , <lb/>, <lb/> q <lb/>g <lb/>g <lb/>hadrons <lb/>or <lb/>g <lb/>q <lb/>g <lb/>hadrons <lb/> r <lb/>Const <lb/>K <lb/>N <lb/>K <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>r <lb/>Const <lb/>N <lb/> ε <lb/>ε <lb/>ξ <lb/>ε <lb/>ε <lb/>ξ <lb/> + <lb/>= <lb/>⋅ <lb/>= <lb/>⋅ <lb/>+ <lb/>= <lb/> Note, that K depends on energy only (via the <lb/>energy dependence of ε  q and ε  g -the quark and <lb/>gluon jet fractions in the sample). <lb/>All data distributions were fitted with MLLA <lb/>gluon spectrum functions. In this work, we report <lb/>extracted values of K instead of the true MLLA <lb/>parameter Const. <lb/> 4. RESULTS <lb/> Below we present our findings on inclusive <lb/>multiplicity of charged particles in dijet events (i.e. <lb/>doubled jet multiplicity), and results of fits of <lb/>inclusive momentum spectrum of charged particles <lb/>with MLLA theoretical predictions. Results of the <lb/>fits are represented in terms of peak position of the <lb/>distribution, and MLLA parameters Q eff  and K, we <lb/>also present the results on multiplicity flow, standard <lb/>dN/dx fragmentation function and dN/dk T <lb/> distributions. Analysis of systematics for these <lb/>results is yet to be carried out. <lb/> 4.1. <lb/> Charged Multiplicity <lb/> In the next plot, we compare our results for <lb/>charged particle multiplicity within a restricted cone <lb/>0.466 around the jet axis to the predictions of <lb/>Monte-Carlo (Herwig 5.6 + Detector simulation) and <lb/>to MLLA predictions corresponding to different <lb/>values of ratio r. Data errors are completely <lb/>dominated by correlated systematic uncertainties. <lb/>Range of values r goes from r=1, which <lb/>corresponds to the case when quark and gluon jets <lb/>are indistinguishable, to r=9/4 (the classic MLLA <lb/>case). Next-to-MLLA and next-to-next-to-MLLA <lb/>order predictions range between these extreme cases. <lb/>Next-to-next-to-MLLA calculations predict r to <lb/>be either 1.85 or 2.0, while experimental e+e-results <lb/>give r in the range of 1.0-1.5. Our data suggests that <lb/>the quark-gluon jet&apos;s multiplicity ratio r, defined as <lb/>described in chapter 3, is somewhere between 1.4 <lb/>and 2. <lb/>Note that Herwig 5.6 predictions were scaled by <lb/>a factor 0.89 to match the data. However, given the <lb/>systematic errors, this difference is not very <lb/>significant (about 2 sigma). <lb/>Throughout our analysis, Herwig 5.6 predictions <lb/>were always scaled by the same factor 0.89. <lb/>Table 2 presents numerical results for <lb/>multiplicities for all 5 restricted cone-sizes along <lb/>with both statistical and systematical uncertainties. <lb/>One can see that the errors are completely dominated <lb/>by systematics. <lb/> Dijet Mass, GeV <lb/> 100 <lb/> Multiplicity <lb/> 0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>MLLA with r=1.0 <lb/>MLLA with r=1.2 <lb/>MLLA with r=1.4 <lb/>MLLA with r=1.6 <lb/>MLLA with r=1.8 <lb/>MLLA with r=2.0 <lb/>MLLA with r=2.25 <lb/>Data <lb/>Herwig 5.6 normalized to data (x 0.89) <lb/> CDF Preliminary <lb/> Figure 3. Charged multiplicity within cone 0.466 <lb/>around the jet axis. Data compared to Monte-Carlo <lb/>and MLLA predictions with r =1.0 -2.25. <lb/>Fig. 4 allows us to compare the data with Herwig <lb/>predictions. This plot presents charged multiplicity <lb/>of particles within 3 restricted cones: 0.168, 0.280, <lb/>0.466. One can see that the agreement is very <lb/>reasonable, apart from the fact that we had to scale <lb/>Herwig predictions. <lb/> Energy <lb/> (GeV) <lb/>Cone 0.168 <lb/>Cone 0.217 <lb/>Cone 0.280 <lb/>Cone 0.361 <lb/>Cone 0.466 <lb/>81.81 5.56±0.06±0.65 <lb/>7.27±0.09±0.73 <lb/>8.85±0.07±0.88 <lb/>10.45±0.08±1.06 11.96±0.09±1.27 <lb/>105.10 6.52±0.09±0.78 <lb/>8.24±0.09±0.84 <lb/>10.08±0.10±1.01 11.73±0.11±1.21 13.53±0.12±1.43 <lb/>140.40 7.57±0.08±0.92 <lb/>9.69±0.09±0.98 <lb/>11.47±0.09±1.16 13.10±0.09±1.36 14.68±0.99±1.57 <lb/>182.70 8.76±0.08±1.07 <lb/>11.31±0.15±1.14 13.27±0.08±1.31 15.17±0.09±1.54 17.01±0.09±1.80 <lb/>228.90 10.14±0.07±1.16 12.19±0.09±1.24 14.36±0.08±1.44 16.28±0.08±1.69 18.36±0.11±1.97 <lb/>292.50 11.71±0.10±1.34 13.70±0.10±1.39 16.06±0.09±1.61 18.03±0.10±1.87 20.16±0.10±2.16 <lb/>378.00 13.01±0.12±1.48 15.21±0.13±1.53 17.56±0.13±1.76 20.07±0.14±2.06 22.22±0.17±2.37 <lb/>487.90 14.63±0.17±1.59 16.41±0.18±1.66 18.56±0.18±1.86 20.80±0.19±2.15 23.30±0.20±2.49 <lb/>628.00 15.69±0.29±1.64 16.48±0.31±1.68 19.10±0.32±1.93 21.52±0.35±2.25 23.95±0.36±2.60 <lb/> Table 2. Inclusive charged particle multiplicity in dijet events in cones 0.168, 0.217, 0.280, 0.361 and 0.466 with <lb/>corresponding statistical and systematical errors. <lb/>CDF Preliminary <lb/> Dijet Mass M jj , GeV <lb/> 100 <lb/> Charged <lb/> multiplicity <lb/> 0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>Cone 0.168 <lb/>Cone 0.280 <lb/>Cone 0.466 <lb/>Herwig v5.6, cone 0.168 (x 0.89) <lb/>Herwig v5.6, cone 0.280 (x 0.89) <lb/>Herwig v5.6, cone 0.466 (x 0.89) <lb/> CDF Preliminary <lb/> Figure 4. Charged multiplicity of particles within <lb/>cones 0.168, 0.280, 0.466. Herwig is scaled by a <lb/>factor 0.89. <lb/> 4.2. <lb/> Inclusive momentum distribution <lb/> Fig.5 presents 9 plots corresponding to 9 dijet <lb/>mass sub-samples for inclusive momentum <lb/>distribution of charged particles within cone 0.168 <lb/>around the jet axis. Data is fitted with the MLLA <lb/>limiting spectrum function. Fig. 6 presents a similar <lb/>set of plots but for the largest available cone-size <lb/>0.466. <lb/>We fitted 45 distributions -all possible <lb/>combinations -9 dijet mass sub-samples times 5 <lb/>cone-sizes. Fitted values for Q  eff  are presented in <lb/>Table 3, and the results for the parameter K can be <lb/>found in Table 4. In Table 5, corresponding fit <lb/>values of χ  2  are shown. <lb/> Mass=82 GeV <lb/>Mass=105 GeV <lb/>Mass=140 GeV <lb/>Mass=183 GeV <lb/>Mass=229 GeV <lb/>Mass=293 GeV <lb/>Mass=378 GeV <lb/>Mass=488 GeV <lb/>Mass=628 GeV <lb/> x=log(  ) <lb/>_ <lb/>x <lb/>1 <lb/> x=log(  ) <lb/>_ <lb/>x <lb/>1 <lb/> x=log(  ) <lb/>_ <lb/>x <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>d N <lb/>dx <lb/>N event <lb/> 1 <lb/>d N <lb/>dx <lb/>N event <lb/> 1 <lb/>d N <lb/>dx <lb/>N event <lb/> Figure 5. Inclusive momentum distribution of <lb/>charged particles within cone 0.168 fitted with <lb/>MLLA function. All available dijet mass samples. <lb/>Results of the fits are in Tables 3 -5. <lb/>One can clearly see that, for both parameters, the <lb/>effects of systematics dominate over statistical <lb/>fluctuations. Though the general agreement between <lb/>the data and MLLA predictions is rather striking, <lb/>one can see a clear small excess of data over the <lb/>MLLA predictions to the left of the peak of the <lb/>distribution. This is especially visible in the case of <lb/>high-statistics dijet mass sub-samples. <lb/> Energy <lb/> (GeV) <lb/>Cone 0.168 <lb/>Cone 0.217 <lb/>Cone 0.280 <lb/>Cone 0.361 <lb/>Cone 0.466 <lb/> 81.81 <lb/>0.246±0.001±0.039 <lb/>0.263±0.001±0.042 <lb/>0.250±0.005±0.041 <lb/>0.262±0.001±0.045 <lb/>0.280±0.003±0.045 <lb/>105.10 <lb/>0.245±0.003±0.039 <lb/>0.221±0.002±0.036 <lb/>0.247±0.001±0.041 <lb/>0.261±0.002±0.044 <lb/>0.279±0.001±0.044 <lb/>140.40 <lb/>0.222±0.002±0.035 <lb/>0.252±0.001±0.041 <lb/>0.256±0.001±0.042 <lb/>0.247±0.001±0.042 <lb/>0.265±0.001±0.042 <lb/>182.70 <lb/>0.214±0.004±0.034 <lb/>0.224±0.002±0.036 <lb/>0.237±0.003±0.039 <lb/>0.243±0.001±0.041 <lb/>0.260±0.003±0.041 <lb/>228.90 <lb/>0.210±0.003±0.033 <lb/>0.220±0.003±0.036 <lb/>0.226±0.001±0.037 <lb/>0.236±0.001±0.040 <lb/>0.251±0.002±0.040 <lb/>292.50 <lb/>0.237±0.004±0.038 <lb/>0.227±0.001±0.037 <lb/>0.230±0.003±0.038 <lb/>0.244±0.002±0.041 <lb/>0.250±0.002±0.040 <lb/>378.00 <lb/>0.221±0.003±0.035 <lb/>0.222±0.004±0.036 <lb/>0.230±0.003±0.038 <lb/>0.227±0.002±0.039 <lb/>0.245±0.004±0.039 <lb/>487.90 <lb/>0.203±0.004±0.032 <lb/>0.200±0.002±0.032 <lb/>0.212±0.004±0.035 <lb/>0.227±0.002±0.039 <lb/>0.241±0.005±0.038 <lb/>628.00 <lb/>0.180±0.011±0.029 <lb/>0.191±0.005±0.031 <lb/>0.199±0.009±0.033 <lb/>0.206±0.009±0.035 <lb/>0.227±0.008±0.036 <lb/> Table 3. Fitted values for MLLA parameter Q eff  along with statistical and systematical errors. <lb/>CDF Preliminary <lb/>CDF Preliminary <lb/> Energy <lb/> (GeV) <lb/>Cone 0.168 <lb/>Cone 0.217 <lb/>Cone 0.280 <lb/>Cone 0.361 <lb/>Cone 0.466 <lb/> 81.81 <lb/>0.490±0.006±0.060 0.557±0.006±0.062 0.590±0.007±0.057 0.632±0.005±0.061 0.661±0.005±0.065 <lb/>105.10 <lb/>0.515±0.007±0.063 0.528±0.008±0.059 0.596±0.007±0.058 0.634±0.006±0.062 0.659±0.006±0.065 <lb/>140.40 <lb/>0.494±0.005±0.060 0.549±0.006±0.061 0.581±0.005±0.056 0.592±0.005±0.058 0.611±0.004±0.060 <lb/>182.70 <lb/>0.485±0.005±0.059 0.529±0.004±0.059 0.560±0.004±0.054 0.579±0.003±0.056 0.598±0.004±0.059 <lb/>228.90 <lb/>0.475±0.004±0.058 0.510±0.004±0.057 0.540±0.003±0.052 0.561±0.003±0.055 0.584±0.003±0.058 <lb/>292.50 <lb/>0.506±0.005±0.062 0.520±0.003±0.058 0.546±0.004±0.053 0.568±0.003±0.055 0.575±0.003±0.057 <lb/>378.00 <lb/>0.477±0.005±0.058 0.503±0.005±0.056 0.525±0.008±0.051 0.535±0.005±0.052 0.551±0.005±0.054 <lb/>487.90 <lb/>0.443±0.006±0.054 0.463±0.006±0.051 0.484±0.006±0.047 0.502±0.005±0.049 0.518±0.005±0.051 <lb/>628.00 <lb/>0.385±0.011±0.047 0.411±0.009±0.046 0.433±0.010±0.042 0.448±0.009±0.044 0.468±0.009±0.046 <lb/> Table 4. Fitted values for MLLA related parameter K along with statistical and systematical errors. <lb/>As it was already mentioned, the data was fitted <lb/>as if all jets were gluon jets. Within MLLA, the <lb/>quark and gluon jet distributions have almost the <lb/>same shape and differ by only a normalization <lb/>constant. As a consequence, the fitted parameter K, <lb/> though closely related, is not exactly the <lb/>MLLA+LPHD constant Const. <lb/> Mass=82 GeV <lb/>Mass=105 GeV <lb/>Mass=140 GeV <lb/>Mass=183 GeV <lb/>Mass=229 GeV <lb/>Mass=293 GeV <lb/>Mass=378 GeV <lb/>Mass=488 GeV <lb/>Mass=628 GeV <lb/> N=log( ) <lb/>_ <lb/>x <lb/>1 <lb/> N=log( ) <lb/>_ <lb/>x <lb/>1 <lb/> N=log( ) <lb/>_ <lb/>x <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>d N <lb/>dN <lb/>N event <lb/> 1 <lb/>d N <lb/>dN <lb/>N event <lb/> 1 <lb/>d N <lb/>dN <lb/>N event <lb/> Figure 6. Inclusive momentum distribution of <lb/>charged particles within cone 0.466 fitted with <lb/>MLLA function. All available dijet mass samples. <lb/>Therefore, our fits are valid, but the <lb/>interpretation of the constant K can be done only if <lb/>the ratio of normalization constants for quark and <lb/>gluon jets is known. <lb/>If quark jets have smaller multiplicity as <lb/>predicted by MLLA (see discussion of results on <lb/>multiplicity), then the constant K should fall with jet <lb/>energy, and it does. <lb/>Unlike K, parameter Q eff can be analyzed <lb/>directly, in MLLA Q eff must be a constant. Still, <lb/>some systematic trends in the behavior of Q eff are <lb/>visible: it tends to become smaller for larger jet <lb/>energies. <lb/> 0.10 <lb/> 0.12 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.18 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>0.34 <lb/> MLLA parameter Q eff <lb/> Figure 7. Fitted values for Q eff corresponding to 45 <lb/>(5 cones x 9 dijet mass cuts) possible combinations. <lb/>Five series of data points correspond to five cone <lb/>sizes, 9 data points within each cone size series <lb/>correspond to different dijet masses (lowest at left). <lb/> Q eff = 240 ±40 MeV. <lb/>CDF Preliminary <lb/>CDF Preliminary <lb/>CDF Preliminary <lb/> As far as parameter K concerned, it was shown <lb/>that K depends on energy only. Thus, for the same <lb/>dijet mass sample, K should stay constant for all <lb/>cone-sizes. <lb/>Data in Table 4 indicates that this is violated. <lb/>The plot presented on Fig. 8 makes this observation <lb/>apparent. We plotted and fitted momentum <lb/>distributions, corresponding to three different cone-<lb/>sizes, corresponding to the same dijet mass M JJ =378 <lb/>GeV. <lb/> 1 <lb/> dN <lb/>d <lb/>N event <lb/> =log( ) <lb/>_ <lb/>x <lb/>1 <lb/> + <lb/> -<lb/> + <lb/> -<lb/> + <lb/> -<lb/> K = 0.525 0.004 0.051 <lb/>Qeff = 0.2300 0.0026 0.0379 <lb/>ndf = 130.4 / 36 <lb/> + <lb/> -<lb/> K = 0.477 0.005 0.058 <lb/>Qeff = 0.2207 0.0022 0.0350 <lb/>ndf = 157.7 / 31 <lb/> + <lb/> - + <lb/> -<lb/> + <lb/> -<lb/> + <lb/> -<lb/> K = 0.542 0.004 0.054 <lb/>Qeff = 0.2405 0.0006 0.0388 <lb/>ndf = 117.9 / 41 <lb/> + <lb/> - + <lb/> - + <lb/> -<lb/> + <lb/> -<lb/> Figure 8. Inclusive momentum distribution of <lb/>charged particles within cones 0.168, 0.280 and <lb/>0.468 fitted with MLLA function. Dijet mass 378 <lb/>GeV. <lb/>However, the assumption that r is energy <lb/>independent may be incorrect as indicated by LEP <lb/>experiments. In this case one needs to do a more <lb/>thorough analysis that would include the γ(Z/W)-jet <lb/> sample. This will allow for direct measurement of <lb/>the ratio r and unambiguous extraction of the MLLA <lb/> Const from the fit parameter K. <lb/> 4.3. <lb/> Peak position of the <lb/>inclusive <lb/>momentum distribution <lb/> Fig. 9 shows the peak position of the inclusive <lb/>momentum distributions plotted against M jj sinθ (θ -<lb/>opening angle). <lb/> CDF Preliminary <lb/> Figure 9. Peak position of the inclusive momentum <lb/>distributions plotted against M jj sinθ. <lb/> χ 2 <lb/> Energy <lb/> (GeV) <lb/>Cone 0.168 <lb/>Cone 0.217 <lb/>Cone 0.280 <lb/>Cone 0.361 <lb/>Cone 0.466 <lb/>81.81 <lb/>37.27 / 16 <lb/>50.86 / 18 <lb/>84.58 / 21 <lb/>85.29 / 23 <lb/>128.1 / 26 <lb/>105.10 <lb/>19.49 / 18 <lb/>69.31 / 23 <lb/>41.61 / 23 <lb/>47.23 / 26 <lb/>56.63 / 28 <lb/>140.40 <lb/>86.03 / 23 <lb/>98.97 / 24 <lb/>94.49 / 26 <lb/>101.4 / 29 <lb/>85.85 / 31 <lb/>182.70 <lb/>112.5 / 24 <lb/>150.6 / 26 <lb/>219.7 / 29 <lb/>228.7 / 31 <lb/>272.2 / 34 <lb/>228.90 <lb/>48.62 / 26 <lb/>91.56 / 28 <lb/>174.8 / 31 <lb/>257.8 / 34 <lb/>230.6 / 36 <lb/>292.50 <lb/>184.1 / 28 <lb/>153.5 / 31 <lb/>227.1 / 33 <lb/>182.1 / 36 <lb/>268.8 / 39 <lb/>378.00 <lb/>157.7 / 31 <lb/>117.0 / 34 <lb/>130.4 / 36 <lb/>116.5 / 39 <lb/>117.9 / 41 <lb/>487.90 <lb/>57.99 / 33 <lb/>59.89 / 36 <lb/>64.92 / 39 <lb/>73.39 / 41 <lb/>74.14 / 44 <lb/>628.00 <lb/>74.53 / 36 <lb/>76.82 / 39 <lb/>82.20 / 41 <lb/>89.31 / 44 <lb/>82.86 / 46 <lb/> Table 5. Account of values of χ 2 obtained for the fits of the inclusive momentum distributions. <lb/>CDF Preliminary <lb/>CDF Preliminary <lb/>The MLLA fit gives Q  eff  = 235 ± 40 MeV. The <lb/>error is completely dominated by systematic errors <lb/>in determination of the peak position. This <lb/>remarkable agreement with the theoretical <lb/>expectations in the framework of MLLA is also <lb/>supported by e+e-and ep data (empty circles).For <lb/>reference, The Leading Log prediction is also plotted <lb/>on the same graph, as well as the prediction in the <lb/>case of fragmentation without color coherence <lb/>effects <lb/> 4.4. <lb/> dN/dlogp distribution <lb/> When plotted as dN/dln(p), Fig. 10, the MLLA <lb/>inclusive momentum distributions reveal an <lb/>interesting feature: the multiplicity of soft tracks in a <lb/>jet is almost jet energy independent. This is a direct <lb/>consequence of the color interference. To understand <lb/>this, first it is important to remember that the <lb/>probability of a soft gluon emission does not depend <lb/>directly on the jet energy. Second, one needs to <lb/>recall that the color interference can be effectively <lb/>accounted for as an angular ordering of emissions: <lb/>emissions should occur at subsequently decreasing <lb/>angles. <lb/>So, even if all emissions occur at the minimum <lb/>k T (it is natural to assume that the minimum k T is of <lb/>the order of Q eff  = Λ  QCD ), then all further emitted <lb/>gluons would have to have larger and larger <lb/>energies. Eventually, such emissions are terminated <lb/>as the result of phase space limitations and energy <lb/>conservation. The larger the jet energy is, the farther <lb/>away those limits are. <lb/> Cone 0.466 <lb/>M JJ =140 GeV <lb/>M JJ =488 GeV (upper) <lb/>M JJ =229 GeV <lb/>CDF Preliminary <lb/> dN/Log(p) <lb/> Log (p) <lb/>M JJ =82 GeV (lower set) <lb/> Figure 10. dN/dlog(p) distribution (4 dijet mass <lb/>samples, cone 0.466). <lb/>Thus, as jet energy increases, the multiplicity <lb/>grows mostly due to partons with increasingly <lb/>higher momentum flying out at decreasingly smaller <lb/>angles. <lb/>Fig. 10 shows the dN/dln(p) distribution for the <lb/>data. One can see that the low momentum region of <lb/>the spectrum (p&lt;1 GeV) is indeed almost energy <lb/>independent. <lb/> Energy <lb/>(GeV) <lb/>Cone 0.168 <lb/>Cone 0.217 <lb/>Cone 0.280 <lb/>Cone 0.361 <lb/>Cone 0.466 <lb/>81.81 <lb/>2.39±0.02±0.07 2.50±0.01±0.09 2.63±0.02±0.09 2.78±0.01±0.11 2.90±0.01±0.09 <lb/>105.10 <lb/>2.55±0.02±0.08 2.68±0.01±0.09 2.84±0.02±0.09 2.97±0.02±0.12 3.07±0.01±0.09 <lb/>140.40 <lb/>2.70±0.01±0.08 2.86±0.01±0.10 2.99±0.01±0.10 3.13±0.01±0.13 3.25±0.01±0.10 <lb/>182.70 <lb/>2.94±0.01±0.09 3.04±0.01±0.11 3.19±0.01±0.11 3.31±0.01±0.13 3.44±0.01±0.10 <lb/>228.90 <lb/>3.07±0.01±0.09 3.21±0.01±0.11 3.35±0.01±0.11 3.49±0.01±0.14 3.60±0.01±0.11 <lb/>292.50 <lb/>3.20±0.01±0.10 3.33±0.01±0.12 3.49±0.01±0.12 3.62±0.01±0.15 3.72±0.01±0.11 <lb/>378.00 <lb/>3.38±0.01±0.10 3.53±0.01±0.12 3.65±0.01±0.12 3.82±0.02±0.15 3.91±0.01±0.12 <lb/>487.90 <lb/>3.59±0.02±0.11 3.75±0.02±0.13 3.88±0.02±0.13 4.00±0.02±0.16 4.10±0.02±0.12 <lb/>628.00 <lb/>3.80±0.03±0.12 3.91±0.03±0.14 4.05±0.04±0.13 4.18±0.04±0.17 4.31±0.03±0.13 <lb/> Table 6. Account of systematic errors for Peak Position of the inclusive momentum distribution. <lb/>CDF Preliminary <lb/> 4.5. <lb/> Multiplicity flow <lb/> Fig. 11 shows the differential dN/dθ distribution <lb/>of charged particles in the jet compared to Monte-<lb/>Carlo predictions (Herwig 5.6 along with the <lb/>detector simulation). One can see that agreement is <lb/>very reasonable. <lb/> dN/d <lb/> angle between track and jet (rad) <lb/>M JJ =82 GeV (lower set) <lb/>M JJ =628 GeV (upper set) <lb/>M JJ =229 GeV (middle set) <lb/>Cone 0.466 <lb/> DATA + Herwig/QFL <lb/> CDF Preliminary <lb/> Figure 11. dN/dθ distribution of charged particles in <lb/>dijets compared to Monte-Carlo (Herwig 5.6 scaled <lb/>by 0.89 along with the detector simulation). <lb/> 4.6. <lb/>dN/dx distribution <lb/> So far we have been analyzing the jet <lb/>fragmentation with the emphasis on the soft <lb/>momentum tracks. Fig. 12 shows the standard <lb/>dN/dx p fragmentation function for three different di-<lb/>jet masses (tracks are from the cone θ  cone =0.47). <lb/>It is interesting to compare these results to the <lb/>e+e-fragmentation functions. Fig. 13 shows the <lb/>CDF M jj =82 GeV data (same data points as in Fig. <lb/>12) plotted together with TASSO [8] and DELPHI <lb/>[9] data points. <lb/>One should not compare the curves on Fig. 13 at <lb/>very low x p -CDF data are from restricted cones <lb/>around the jet axis and, therefore, are bound to lack <lb/>soft tracks compared to the e+e-data, where tracks <lb/>from the full solid angle are included in the plots. <lb/> dN/dx <lb/> M JJ =82 GeV <lb/>M JJ =628 GeV <lb/>M JJ =229 GeV <lb/>Cone 0.466 <lb/>CDF Preliminary <lb/> x=p/E jet <lb/> Figure 12. Standard dN/dx distribution compared to <lb/>Monte-Carlo predictions. <lb/> X  p <lb/> 0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/> dN/dx p <lb/> 0.1 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>100 <lb/>1000 <lb/>CDF M JJ =82 GeV (cone 0.466) <lb/>TASSO M JJ =34 GeV <lb/>DELPHI M JJ =91 GeV <lb/> CDF Preliminary <lb/> Figure 13. Fragmentation function dN/dx. <lb/>Comparison of the CDF data to TASSO [8] and <lb/>DELPHI [9] results. <lb/> On the other hand, the points at larger x can be <lb/>compared (the high momentum tracks mostly come <lb/>from the very collimated region around the jet <lb/>axis).From the QCD scaling violation, one expects <lb/>that at the domain of larger x, the curves should go <lb/>lower as the jet energy increases (cf. TASSO and <lb/>DELPHI results). However, one can see that at <lb/>larger x, CDF data points tend to go lower than the <lb/>DELPHI points, although the CDF dijet data sample <lb/>plotted here has slightly lower energy. <lb/>The reason for this observation may be twofold. <lb/>First, the CDF jets at Mjj=82 GeV are <lb/>predominantly (~75%) gluon jets, while the e+e-jets <lb/>are quark jets. As was discussed above, the gluon <lb/>jets should yield higher multiplicity in the low-x <lb/>region. From energy conservation, this immediately <lb/>implies that the high-x region should be somewhat <lb/>depleted. Second, the e+e-analysis is done for all <lb/>tracks from the full solid angle, which will include <lb/>all multi-jet events. Those will contribute a certain <lb/>number of hard tracks. <lb/>Cross-comparison of γ-jet and jet-jet events will <lb/>shed more light on differences in quark and gluon <lb/>jets. Meanwhile, Fig. 12 shows that the data and <lb/>Herwig/QFL are in very good agreement (apart from <lb/>the overall normalization 0.89 used for Monte-<lb/>Carlo). <lb/> 5. CONCLUSIONS <lb/> Our findings can be briefly summarized as <lb/>follows: <lb/> • MLLA gives reasonable agreement with data <lb/>(multiplicity N, dN/dξ distribution and the peak <lb/>position evolution). For the cut-off parameter, <lb/>we report value Q  eff  =240±40 MeV. <lb/> • Indirectly measured gluon/quark jet multiplicity <lb/>ratio r, defined assuming that quark and gluon <lb/>jets have the same shape (as in MLLA), seems <lb/>to be between 1.4 and 2.0. Future jet-jet vs γ-jet <lb/> analysis will allow for direct measurement of r, <lb/>and is in progress. <lb/> • Herwig 5.6 was found to be in a good <lb/>agreement with data (apart from a scaling factor <lb/>0.89, which is not very significant given the <lb/>systematic uncertainties) over the wide range of <lb/>analyzed distributions of hadrons in jets. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> REFERENCES <lb/> [1] Yu. Dokshitzer, S. Troyan, XIX Winter <lb/>School of LNPI, vol. 1, p. 144; A. Mueller, <lb/>Nucl. Phys. B213 (1983) 85; Erratum quoted <lb/>ibid., B241 (1984) 141. <lb/>[2] Ya. I. Azimov, Yu. Dokshitzer, V. Khoze, and <lb/>S.troyan, Z. Phys. C27 (1985) 65 and C31 <lb/>(1986) 213. <lb/>[3] Yu. Dokshitzer, V. Khoze, A.H. Mueller, S. <lb/>Troyan, Basics of Perturbative QCD, 1991, <lb/>Editions Frontiers, France <lb/>[4] A.H. Mueller, Nucl. Phys. B241 (1984),141; <lb/>E.D. Malaza, Z. Phys. C31 (1986), 143 <lb/> [5] J. B. Gaffney and A.H. Mueller, Nucl. Phys. <lb/>B250 (1985) 109 <lb/>[6] I.M. Dremin, V.A. Nechitailo, Modern Phys. <lb/>Letters A, vol. 9, No. 16 (1994) 147 <lb/>[7] OPAL Collaboration, CERN-PPE/95-075 <lb/>[8] TASSO Collaboration, Z. Phys. C47 (1990) <lb/>187, Z.Phys. C22 (1984) 307 <lb/> [9] DELPHI Collab., Phys. Lett. B275 (1992) <lb/>231, Z.Phys. C70 (1996) 179, Physics Lett. <lb/>B311 (1993) 408 <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex"> QUESTIONS <lb/> R. Peschanski, Saclay: <lb/> To which extent there is a correlation between <lb/>using MLLA for the perturbative calculation and the <lb/>determination of the quark/gluon multiplicity ratio r? <lb/> A. Safonov: <lb/> Our definition of r heavily relies on MLLA <lb/>calculations. Basic assumption used was that quark <lb/>and gluon inclusive momentum spectra have the <lb/>same shape and only differ by a normalization <lb/>factor. </div>


	</text>
</tei>
