<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="footnote"> arXiv:1411.5583v3  [math-ph] 2 Feb 2015 <lb/></note>

			<front> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD <lb/>THEORY <lb/> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/> Abstract. In [BBK10] it was shown how so-called wonderful compactifica-<lb/>tions can be used for renormalization in the position space formulation of <lb/>quantum field theory. This article aims to continue this idea, using a slightly <lb/>different approach; instead of the subspaces in the arrangement of divergent <lb/>loci, we use the poset of divergent subgraphs as the main tool to describe the <lb/>whole renormalization process. This is based on [Fei05] where wonderful mod-<lb/>els were studied from a purely combinatorial viewpoint. The main motivation <lb/>for this approach is the fact that both, renormalization and the model con-<lb/>struction, are governed by the combinatorics of this poset. Not only simplifies <lb/>this the exposition considerably, but also allows to study the renormalization <lb/>operators in more detail. Moreover, we explore the renormalization group in <lb/>this setting by studying how the renormalized distributions behave under a <lb/>change of renormalization points. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> Quantum field theory (QFT), the unification of quantum mechanics and special <lb/>relativity, is the last century&apos;s most successful physical theory. Although plagued <lb/>with infinities and ill-defined quantities all over the place, it is in astonishing agree-<lb/>ment with data obtained from particle physics experiments. At first this seems <lb/>very awkward since up until now no one has been able to prove the existence of <lb/>interacting quantum fields satisfying a reasonable set of physical axioms. Instead, <lb/>these &quot; real &quot; fields are approximated as perturbations of their free, non-interacting <lb/>counterparts. Although this perturbative world contains a lot of mathematical <lb/>monsters, the theory predicts the outcome of particle physics experiments with <lb/>great accuracy. The art of taming these monster, i.e. treating the infinities arising <lb/>in perturbative calculations, is called renormalization. Over the years it has turned <lb/>from a &quot; black magic cooking recipe &quot; into a well-established and rigorous formu-<lb/>lated theory, at the latest since the 90&apos;s when Kreimer discovered a Hopf algebra <lb/>structure underlying renormalization. The main implication is that (perturbative) <lb/>QFT is governed by the combinatorics of Feynman diagrams. This has proven to <lb/>be a very powerful tool, both in computational problems as well as in improving <lb/>our understanding of QFT in general. In addition, it has revealed surprising con-<lb/>nections to deep questions in pure mathematics, for example in number theory and <lb/>algebraic geometry. For more on the Hopf algebraic formulation of renormalization <lb/>and its connection to other fields we refer to the exposition in [Kre13]. <lb/>The mathematical reason for divergences arising in perturbative calculations is <lb/>that quantum fields are modeled by operator-valued distributions for which prod-<lb/>ucts are in general not well-defined. In the position space formulation of QFT <lb/>renormalization translates directly into the problem of extending distributions as <lb/></body>

			<page> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> shown by Epstein and Glaser in [EG73]. Although they formulated and solved <lb/>the renormalization problem already in the early 70&apos;s, since then no real progress <lb/>has been made in this direction. This is mainly due to two reasons: Firstly, their <lb/>approach was mathematical precise but conceptually difficult. It involved a lot of <lb/>functional analysis, in some sense disguising the beauty and simplicity of the idea. <lb/>Secondly, it is not applicable to calculations at all. Only recently, in a first ap-<lb/>proximation to quantum gravity, physicists have started to study quantum fields <lb/>on general spacetimes and in this setting one is naturally forced to work in position <lb/>space [BF00]. <lb/>In [BBK10] another, more geometric approach to this problem was presented. <lb/>In position space the Feynman rules associate to a graph G a pair (X <lb/> G  , v  G  ) where <lb/> X <lb/> G  is a product of the underlying spacetime and v  G  : X <lb/> G  → R a rational function. <lb/>One would like to evaluate this to <lb/>(X <lb/> G  , v  G  ) = <lb/> X  G <lb/> v  G  , <lb/> but this fails in general as the integrand need not be an element of L <lb/> 1  (X <lb/> G  ). If v  G <lb/> does not vanish fast enough at infinity this is called an infrared divergence. The <lb/>problem is circumvented by viewing v  G  as a distribution on the space of compactly <lb/>supported test functions. On the other hand, ultraviolet divergences arise from v  G <lb/> having poles along certain subspaces of X <lb/> G  . These subspaces are determined by D, <lb/> the set of (ultraviolet-)divergent subgraphs of G, and form the divergent arrange-<lb/>ment X <lb/> G <lb/> D  . In this setting renormalization translates into the problem of finding <lb/>an extension of v  G  onto X <lb/> G <lb/> D  . In [BBK10] this is solved with a geometric ansatz: <lb/>The idea is to resolve the divergent arrangement into a normal crossing divisor and <lb/>then define canonical renormalization operators that extend v  G  to a distribution <lb/>defined on the whole space X <lb/> G  . Such a model, also called a compactification of the <lb/>complement of X <lb/> G <lb/> D  , is provided by the wonderful model construction by DeConcini <lb/>and Procesi [CP95], based on techniques from Fulton and MacPherson&apos;s seminal <lb/>paper [FM94]. What makes it so well-suited for renormalization is that the whole <lb/>construction is governed by the combinatorics of the arrangement which translates <lb/>directly into the subgraph structure of G. <lb/> The idea of employing a resolution of singularities to extend distributions is <lb/>not new. It is based on a paper by Atiyah [Ati70] that highlighted the usefulness <lb/>of Hironaka&apos;s famous theorem in seemingly unrelated areas of mathematics. In <lb/>addition, the same technique was applied in Chern-Simons perturbation theory in-<lb/>dependently by Kontsevich [Kon94] as well as Axelrod and Singer [AS94]. For an <lb/>application of this idea to renormalization in parametric space see [BEK06]. <lb/>The present article aims to continue the work of [BBK10] emphasizing a slightly <lb/>different point of view. We use another language to formulate the wonderful con-<lb/>struction and the renormalization process; instead of the subspaces in the diver-<lb/>gent arrangement we express the central notions in terms of the poset D, formed <lb/>by all divergent subgraphs of G, partially ordered by inclusion. This is inspired <lb/>by [Fei05] where the wonderful model construction is studied from a combinatorial <lb/>point of view. Not only does this simplify the definitions and proofs immensely, it <lb/>also highlights the combinatorial flavour in the construction of both, the wonder-<lb/>ful models and the renormalization operators. In addition, instead of the vertex <lb/>set of G we use adapted spanning trees t to define coordinates on X <lb/> G  , naturally <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body> suited to the problem. This is also mentioned in [BBK10], but not used to its full <lb/>extent. The main point is that such spanning trees are stable under certain graph <lb/>theoretic operations like contraction of divergent subgraphs and therefore provide <lb/>a convenient tool to formulate the wonderful construction. It allows to treat the <lb/>definition of the renormalization operators in more detail ([BBK10] focuses mainly <lb/>on the model construction for arrangements coming from graphs) and to study <lb/>the renormalization group, a powerful tool (not only) in QFT, that allows even for <lb/>statements beyond perturbation theory. The main result is a formula for the change <lb/>of renormalization points, the parameters involved in defining the renormalization <lb/>operators. It relates a so-called finite renormalization of the renormalized distri-<lb/>bution R[v  G  ] to a sum of distributions determined by the divergent subgraphs of G. <lb/> The presentation is organized as follows. In the next section we cover some <lb/>topics of distribution theory that will be needed later; it finishes with a definition <lb/>of Feynman rules, i.e. how QFT associates distributions to Feynman diagrams, <lb/>and an analysis of the divergent loci of these distributions. The next sections is <lb/>devoted to the two other central objects in this article, smooth models and posets. <lb/>It starts with an exposition of the wonderful model construction as in [CP95], then, <lb/>following [Fei05], we introduce the necessary combinatorial language to review this <lb/>construction from a purely combinatorial viewpoint; special emphasis is given to the <lb/>case of arrangements coming from graphs via Feynman rules. After these mostly <lb/>preliminary steps we come to the main part, the wonderful renormalization process. <lb/>We first study the pole structure of the pull-back of a Feynman distribution onto an <lb/>associated wonderful model and then define two renormalization operators. This <lb/>definition requires some choices to be made and a natural question, considered in <lb/>Section 5, is to ask what happens if one varies these parameters. We derive and <lb/>proof a formula for these so-called finite renormalizations. The last section finishes <lb/>the wonderful renormalization process by showing that it is physical reasonable, i.e. <lb/>it satisfies the Epstein-Glaser recursion principle, in other contexts known as locality <lb/>of counterterms. After that we discuss the connection between the renormalization <lb/>operation for single graphs presented here and the Epstein-Glaser method. We <lb/>finish with an outlook to further studies: The treatment of amplitudes and the role <lb/>of Fulton-MacPherson compactifications in this setting, and the Hopf algebraic <lb/>formulation of wonderful renormalization. <lb/>2. Distributions <lb/> In this section we collect some preliminary material about distributions. Al-<lb/>though crucial in the definition of QFT (see for example [SW00]), in most textbooks <lb/>the distributional character of the theory is largely neglected. This is ok as long <lb/>as one works in momentum space, but in position space they play a central role in <lb/>every aspect. We start by defining distributions on manifolds. Then we state the <lb/>extension problem and study its solution in a toy model case. The section finishes <lb/>with a definition of Feynman distributions, i.e. distributions associated to graphs <lb/>via Feynman rules, and an analysis of the corresponding divergent loci. <lb/>Let X ⊆ R <lb/> d  be open and denote by D(X) := C <lb/> ∞ <lb/> 0  (X) the space of compactly <lb/>supported smooth functions on X. We write D <lb/> ′  (X) for the space of continuous <lb/>linear functionals on D(X) and u|ϕ for the value of u ∈ D <lb/> ′  (X) at ϕ ∈ D(X). <lb/></body>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> By (the usual) abuse of notation we use the same symbol f for a function and the <lb/>functional u  f  it represents. In the latter case we refer to f as the kernel of u  f  . The <lb/>locus where u cannot be given by a function is called the singular support of u. <lb/> Now let X be a d-dimensional smooth manifold. For X ⊆ R <lb/> d  open it seems <lb/>natural to define the space of distributions as above, D <lb/> ′  (X) := (D(X)) <lb/>  *  . To gen-<lb/>eralize this to the manifold case there are two possibilities, depending on whether <lb/>distributions should generalize functions or measures (cf. [Hö90]). In the following <lb/>let {ψ  i  : U  i  → ˜ <lb/> U  i  ⊆ R <lb/> d  }  i∈I  be an atlas for X. <lb/> Definition 2.1. A distribution u on X is given by a collection of distributions <lb/> {u  i  ∈ D <lb/> ′  ( ˜ <lb/> U  i  )}  i∈I  such that for all i, j ∈ I <lb/>u  j  = (ψ  i  • ψ <lb/> −1 <lb/> j  ) <lb/>  *  u  i  in ψ  j  (U  i  ∩ U  j  ). <lb/>The space of distributions on X is denoted by D <lb/> ′  (X). <lb/>This is the way to define distributions as generalized functions on X (every <lb/> u ∈ C <lb/> 0  (X) defines a distribution by setting u  i  := u • ψ <lb/> −1 <lb/> i  ). If we start from <lb/>the point of view that they are continuous linear forms on D(X), we arrive at <lb/>generalized measures on X, also called distribution densities: <lb/> Definition 2.2. A distribution density  <lb/>  on X is a collection of distributions <lb/> {˜   i  ∈ D <lb/> ′  ( ˜ <lb/> U  i  )}  i∈I  such that for all i, j ∈ I <lb/> ˜ <lb/> u  j  = |det D(ψ  i  • ψ <lb/> −1 <lb/> j  )|(ψ  i  • ψ <lb/> −1 <lb/> j  ) <lb/>  *  ˜ <lb/> u  i  in ψ  j  (U  i  ∩ U  j  ). <lb/>The space of distribution densities on X is denoted by <lb/> ′  (X). <lb/>Because of their transformation properties, distribution densities are also called <lb/> pseudoforms. They generalize differential forms in the sense that they can be inte-<lb/>grated even on non-orientable manifolds. For more on pseudoforms and integration <lb/>on non-orientable manifolds we refer to [Nic07]. Note that if X is orientable, there <lb/>is an isomorphism D <lb/> ′  (X) ∼ = ˜ <lb/> D <lb/> ′  (X) via u → uν for ν a strictly positive density (i.e. <lb/>a volume form) on X. In particular, on R <lb/> d  such a density is given by the Lebesgue <lb/>measure ν = |dx| and we write <lb/>  for u|dx| with u ∈ D <lb/> ′  (R <lb/> d  ). <lb/>For later purposes we introduce two operations on distributions and densities, <lb/>the pullback and pushforward along a smooth map f : X → X <lb/> ′  . <lb/> Definition 2.3 (Pushforward). Let X ⊆ R <lb/> m  and X <lb/> ′  ⊆ R <lb/> n  be open and f : X → X <lb/> ′ <lb/> be surjective and proper (if u is compactly supported this requirement can be <lb/>dropped). For a distribution u on X the pushforward f  *  u ∈ D <lb/> ′  (X <lb/> ′  ) is defined by <lb/> f  *  u|ϕ = u|f <lb/>  *  ϕ for all ϕ ∈ D(X <lb/> ′  ). <lb/>For X and X <lb/> ′  manifolds with atlantes (ψ  i  , U  i  )  i∈I  and (ψ <lb/> ′ <lb/> j  , U <lb/> ′ <lb/> j  )  j∈J  we define the <lb/>pushforward f  *  ˜ <lb/> u ∈ ˜ <lb/> D <lb/> ′  (X <lb/> ′  ) of <lb/>  ∈ ˜ <lb/> D <lb/> ′  (X) by <lb/>(f  *  u)  j  := (ψ <lb/> ′ <lb/> j  • f • ψ <lb/> −1 <lb/> i  )  *  u  i  in U <lb/> ′ <lb/> j  ∩ (ψ <lb/> ′ <lb/> j  • f • ψ <lb/> −1 <lb/> i  )(U  i  ). <lb/>The question under what conditions the pullback of distributions is defined is <lb/>more delicate, see [Hö90] for a detailed exposition. We state only one special case <lb/>where it is possible to define a pullback: Let X and X be open subsets of R <lb/> n  and <lb/> f : X → X <lb/> ′  a smooth submersion. Then there exists a unique linear operator <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body> f <lb/>  *  : D <lb/> ′  (X <lb/> ′  ) → D <lb/> ′  (X) such that f <lb/>  *  u = u • f if u ∈ C <lb/> 0  (X <lb/> ′  ). If X and X <lb/> ′  are <lb/>manifolds and <lb/>  is a density on X <lb/> ′  then f <lb/>  *  ˜ <lb/> u ∈ ˜ <lb/> D <lb/> ′  (X) is defined by <lb/>(f <lb/>  *  u)  i  := (ψ <lb/> ′ <lb/> j  • f • ψ <lb/> −1 <lb/> i  ) <lb/>  *  u  j  in U <lb/> ′ <lb/> j  ∩ (ψ <lb/> ′ <lb/> j  f ψ <lb/> −1 <lb/> i  )(U  i  ). <lb/>2.1. Extension of distributions. In this section we present the theory of extend-<lb/>ing distributions. We study a toy model, distributions on R \ {0} given by kernels <lb/>having an algebraic singularity at 0. We follow the exposition in [GS64]. Applying <lb/>this toy model to the extension problem for Feynman distributions is precisely the <lb/>idea behind the geometric approach to renormalization presented here. <lb/>The extension problem for distribution densities is formulated as follows: <lb/> Definition 2.4 (Extension problem). Let X be a smooth manifold and Y ⊆ X an <lb/>immersed submanifold. Given a density <lb/>  ∈ ˜ <lb/> D <lb/> ′  (X \ Y ) find an extension of <lb/>  onto <lb/> X, i.e. find a density <lb/>  ext  ∈ ˜ <lb/> D <lb/> ′  (X) with <lb/>   ext  |ϕ = ˜ u|ϕ for all ϕ ∈ D(X \ Y ). <lb/>In this very general formulation the problem is not always solvable. Moreover, if <lb/>there is a solution, it need not be unique since by definition two extension may differ <lb/>by a distribution supported on Y . Therefore additional conditions are sometimes <lb/>formulated to confine the space of solutions. Usually one demands that the exten-<lb/>sion should have the same properties as u, for example scaling behaviour, Poincare <lb/>covariance or solving certain differential equations. <lb/>2.1.1. A toy model. Let u ∈ D <lb/> ′  (R \ {0}) be defined by the kernel x → <lb/> 1 <lb/> |x|  . A priori <lb/> u is only defined as a distribution on the space of test functions vanishing at 0. <lb/>The first step in the process of extending u is to regularize it by introducing a <lb/>complex parameter s ∈ C. Raising u to a complex power u <lb/> s  is known as analytic <lb/>regularization. It justifies the following calculations: <lb/> u <lb/> s  |ϕ = <lb/> R <lb/> dx <lb/> 1 <lb/> |x|  s  ϕ(x) <lb/> = <lb/> [−1,1] <lb/> dx <lb/>ϕ(x) − ϕ(0) <lb/> |x|  s <lb/> + ϕ(0) <lb/> [−1,1] <lb/> dx <lb/> 1 <lb/> |x|  s  + <lb/> R\[−1,1] <lb/> dx <lb/>ϕ(x) <lb/> |x|  s <lb/> = <lb/> [−1,1] <lb/> dx <lb/>ϕ(x) − ϕ(0) <lb/> |x|  s <lb/> + <lb/>2ϕ(0) <lb/>1 − s <lb/> + <lb/> R\[−1,1] <lb/> dx <lb/>ϕ(x) <lb/> |x|  s  . <lb/> The last term is defined for all s ∈ C, the second term for s  = 1 and the first one <lb/>for Re(s) &lt; 3. <lb/>Thus, we have found a way to split the regularized distribution u <lb/> s  = u  ∞  (s, ·) + <lb/> u  ♥  (s, ·) into a divergent and a convergent part. The divergent part is the principal <lb/>part of the Laurent expansion of the meromorphic distribution-valued function <lb/> s → u <lb/> s  in a punctured disc around 1 in C: <lb/> u  ∞  (s, ·)|ϕ = <lb/>2ϕ(0) <lb/>1 − s <lb/>, <lb/> u  ♥  (s, ·)|ϕ = <lb/> R <lb/> dx <lb/>ϕ(x) − θ(1 − |x|)ϕ(0) <lb/>|x|  s <lb/> . <lb/> To continue the process of extending u we have to get rid of the divergent part in <lb/>some sensible way (in physics this is the choice of a renormalization scheme) and <lb/></body>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> take the limit s → 1. The most straightforward way to do so is by subtracting the <lb/>pole (minimal subtraction) and set <lb/>ˆ <lb/> u = r  1  [u <lb/> s  ]|  s=1  := (u <lb/> s  − <lb/> 2δ <lb/>1 − s <lb/> )|  s=1  = u  ♥  (1, ·). <lb/> The map r  1  is called a renormalization operator. Obviously this technique can be <lb/>generalized to extend distributions u with higher negative powers of |x| -one simply <lb/>subtracts a higher order Taylor polynomial from ϕ. <lb/> Another renormalization scheme, subtraction at fixed conditions, is given by <lb/> r  ν  [u <lb/> s  ]|ϕ := u <lb/> s  |ϕ − u <lb/> s  |ϕ(0)ν <lb/> with ν ∈ D(R) a smooth cutoff function with ν(0) = 1. Another way to formulate <lb/>the subtracted distribution is <lb/> u <lb/> s  |ϕ(0)ν = (p  0  )  *  (νu <lb/> s  )|δ  0  [ϕ]. <lb/>Here p  0  : R → {0} is the projection onto the divergent locus and δ  0  is interpreted <lb/>as an operator D(R) → D(0) mapping test functions on R onto test functions <lb/>supported on the divergent locus. From this it is also clear that the difference <lb/>between two such renormalization operators R  ν  and R  ν  ′  is given by a distribution <lb/>supported on {0}, i.e. a linear combination of δ and its derivatives. <lb/>This formulation will be very useful later. The tricky part in applying these <lb/>renormalization techniques to densities coming from Feynman graphs is the fact <lb/>that they are products of divergent and smooth functions. Therefore the renormal-<lb/>ization operators act on the divergent part only, while the smooth part is treated <lb/>like a test function -this makes it hard to find a globally consistent notation for <lb/>the renormalized densities. <lb/>A nice feature of these renormalization operators r is that they commute with <lb/>multiplication by smooth functions, r[f u] = f r[u] for f ∈ C <lb/> ∞  (R). In addition, r <lb/> belongs to the class of Rota-Baxter operators, a fact extensively used in the Hopf <lb/>algebraic formulation of renormalization (see for example [EFG07]). <lb/>Later we will work with distributions given by kernels <lb/> u <lb/> s  (x) = <lb/>1 <lb/> |x|  1+d(s−1)  . <lb/> In this case u <lb/> s  splits into <lb/>(1) <lb/> u <lb/> s  = − <lb/> 2 <lb/> d <lb/>δ  0 <lb/> s − 1 <lb/>+ u  ♥  (s) <lb/>with u  ♥  (s) holomorphic for Re(s) &lt; <lb/> 2+d <lb/> d  . <lb/>2.2. Feynman distributions. Feynman diagrams are convenient book-keeping <lb/>devices for the terms in the perturbative expansion of physical quantities. The map <lb/>that assigns to every Feynman diagram its corresponding analytical expression is <lb/>called Feynman rules and denoted by Φ. In position space the map Φ assigns to <lb/>every diagram G a pair (X <lb/> G  , ˜ <lb/> v  G  ) where <lb/>  G  is a differential form on the space X <lb/> G  , <lb/>a cartesian product of the underlying spacetime M . We would like to evaluate <lb/>(X <lb/> G  , ˜ <lb/> v  G  ) −→ <lb/> X  G <lb/> ˜ <lb/> v  G  , <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body> but this is in general not possible due to the problem of ultraviolet and infrared <lb/>divergences. While we avoid the infrared problem by viewing <lb/>  G  as a distribution <lb/>density, the ultraviolet problem translates into an extension problem for <lb/>  G  . The <lb/>ultraviolet divergences of <lb/>  G  are assembled in a certain subspace arrangement that <lb/>we will describe at the end of this section, after the definition of Φ. <lb/>We consider a massless scalar quantum field in d-dimensional Euclidean space-<lb/>time M := R <lb/> d  . The case of fields with higher spin differs only by notational com-<lb/>plexity. On the other hand, the massive case is much harder because already the <lb/>simplest examples have special functions arising as propagators of the free theory. <lb/>Working in the Euclidean metric is justified by the technique of Wick rotation (see <lb/>[Wei96]) that allows one to do calculations in M and transform the results back to <lb/>Minkoswki spacetime. The position space propagator of a massless scalar field is <lb/>given by the Fourier transform of the momentum space propagator, <lb/> △(x) = F (k → <lb/> 1 <lb/> k  2  )(x) = <lb/>1 <lb/> x  d−2  , x ∈ M. <lb/> Let G be a connected graph. By a graph we mean the following combinatorial <lb/>object: <lb/> Definition 2.5. A graph G is an ordered pair G = (V, E) of a set V of vertices and <lb/>a multiset E of unordered distinct (we do not allow loop edges, i.e. edges connecting <lb/>a vertex with itself) pairs of elements of V . <lb/> Example. The dunce&apos;s cap graph (Figure 1) will serve as main example later <lb/>throughout the text. Here V = {v  1  , v  2  , v  3  } and E = {e  1  = (v  1  , v  2  ), e  2  = (v  1  , v  3  ), e  3  = <lb/>(v  2  , v  3  ), e  4  = (v  2  , v  3  )} <lb/> v  1 <lb/> v  2 <lb/> v  3 <lb/> e  1 <lb/> e  2 <lb/> e  3  e  4 <lb/> Figure 1. Dunce&apos;s cap <lb/> Definition 2.6. A subgraph g of G, denoted by g ⊆ G, is determined by a subset <lb/> E(g) ⊆ E(G). Usually one defines the vertex set of g to be the set of vertices of <lb/> V (G) that are connected to edges of g, so that g is a graph itself, g = (V (g), E(g)). <lb/> For our purposes it is more convenient to allow also for isolated vertices. Therefore <lb/>we define a subgraph g ⊆ G to be an equivalence class under the relation <lb/> g ∼ g <lb/> ′  ⇐⇒ E(g <lb/> ′  ) = E(g). <lb/> For subgraphs g, h ⊆ G we introduce the following operations: <lb/>(1) Union and intersection: g ∪ h and g ∩ h are the subgraphs of G defined by <lb/>the corresponding operations on the edge sets of g and h. <lb/> (2) Deletion: For g ⊆ h the deletion h \ g is the graph h with all edges of g <lb/> removed. <lb/></body>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> (3) Contraction: For g ⊆ h the contraction h/g is the graph h with all edges <lb/> e in E(g) removed and for every e ∈ E(g) the two vertices connected to e <lb/> identified. <lb/>As shown in [BBK10], Feynman rules are determined by the topology of G as <lb/>follows: <lb/>Pick a labelling V = {v  0  , . . . , v  n  } of the vertices of G and an orientation on the <lb/>edges of G. For a finite set F let R <lb/> F  denote the vector space with (fixed) basis the <lb/>elements of F . The cohomology of the simplicial complex G = (V, E) gives rise to <lb/>an exact sequence <lb/>0 −→ R <lb/> σ <lb/> −→ R <lb/> V <lb/>δ <lb/> −→ R <lb/> E  −→ H <lb/> 1  (G, R) −→ 0. <lb/>Here the map σ sends 1 to v  0  + · · · + v  n  and δ is given by δ(v) = <lb/> e∈E  (v : e)e with <lb/>(v : e) = ±1 if e starts/ends at v and 0 otherwise. Fix a basis of coker(σ) by an <lb/>isomorphism ϕ : V <lb/> ′  := V \ {v  0  } → coker(σ). This defines an inclusion ι : R <lb/> V <lb/> ′  ∼ = <lb/>cokerc ֒→ R <lb/> E  . Doing this component-wise on the space X <lb/> G  := M <lb/> V <lb/> ′  = (R <lb/> d  ) <lb/> V <lb/> ′  we <lb/>obtain an inclusion I := ι <lb/> ⊕d  : X <lb/> G  ֒→ M <lb/> E  and define v  G  : X <lb/> G  → R by <lb/> v  G  : <lb/> v∈V  ′ <lb/> x  v  v −→ <lb/> e∈E(G) <lb/> △( <lb/> v∈V  ′ <lb/> (v : e)x  v  ). <lb/>Moreover, every edge e ∈ E defines a linear form ω  e  := e <lb/>  *  • ι on R <lb/> V <lb/> ′  and a linear <lb/>subspace of (X <lb/> G  ) <lb/>  *  by <lb/> A  e  :=&lt; ω  e  &gt; <lb/> ⊕d  = <lb/> (x  1  , . . . , x  n  ) → <lb/> d <lb/> i=1 <lb/> α  i  ω  e  (x <lb/> i <lb/> 1  , . . . , x <lb/> i <lb/>n  ), α  i  ∈ R <lb/> . <lb/> For a subgraph g ⊆ G we define A  g  := <lb/> e∈E(g)  A  e  . Families P of subgraphs of G <lb/> give then rise to subspace arrangements in (X <lb/> G  ) <lb/>  *  , <lb/> A  P  := {A  g  | g ∈ P}. <lb/> Note that two subgraphs g, h ⊆ G may define the same subspace, A  g  = A  h  . There-<lb/>fore we will consider only subfamilies of G, the set of saturated subgraphs of G. <lb/> Saturated subgraphs are maximal with respect to the property of defining their <lb/>corresponding subspaces A  g  . A precise definition is given in Section 3.13. <lb/>Two arrangements are especially important for our purposes. The singular ar-<lb/>rangement <lb/> A  G  := {A  g  | g ⊆ G is saturated}, <lb/>and the arrangement coming from the family D of divergent subgraphs of G, <lb/> A  D  = {A  g  | g ⊆ G is divergent}. <lb/> Definition 2.7. Let h  1  (·) denote the first Betti number. Define the superficial <lb/>degree of divergence ω of G by <lb/> ω(G) := dh  1  (G) − 2|E(G)|. <lb/>Then G is called divergent if ω(G) ≥ 0. G is at most logarithmic if ω(g) ≤ 0 holds <lb/>for all g ⊆ G. If D = {∅, G}, then G is called primitive. <lb/> Lemma 2.8. Let G be at most logarithmic and d &gt; 2. Then <lb/> g ∈ D =⇒ g is saturated. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body> Proof. Suppose A  g  = A  g∪e  for some e ∈ E(G \ g). From this follows that V (g) = <lb/> V (g ∪ e) because A  g  ⊆ (M <lb/> V <lb/> ′  ) <lb/>  *  . But then adding e to g must produce a cycle, so <lb/> h  1  (g ∪ e) = h  1  (g) + 1. Thus, ω(g ∪ e) = ω(g) + d − 2 &gt; 0, a contradiction to G at <lb/>most logarithmic. <lb/> As shown in the next proposition, the divergent arrangement A  D  describes ex-<lb/>actly the locus where extension is necessary. <lb/> Proposition 2.9. Let G be connected and at most logarithmic. Set <lb/> X  s  := <lb/> e∈E <lb/> A <lb/> ⊥ <lb/> e  and X  D  := <lb/> g∈D <lb/> A <lb/> ⊥ <lb/> g  . <lb/> Then v  G  is a well defined distribution on X \ X  D  and the singular support of v  G  is <lb/>given by the complement X  s  \ X  D  . <lb/>Proof. Let V = {v  0  , . . . , v  n  }. Wherever defined, v  G  can be written as <lb/> v  G  (x  1  , . . . , x  n  ) = I <lb/>  * <lb/> △ <lb/> ⊗|E| <lb/> (x  1  , . . . , x  n  ) = <lb/> e∈E <lb/> △ <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (v  i  : e)x  i <lb/> . <lb/> Since sing supp(△) = {0}, the singular support of △ <lb/> ⊗E  is the set where at least <lb/>one x  e  ∈ M vanishes. But this is precisely the image of A <lb/> ⊥ <lb/> e  under I. Thus, sing <lb/>supp(v  G  ) ⊆ X  s  . <lb/>For K ⊆ X compact and χ  K  the (smooth approximation of the) characteristic <lb/>function of K we need to show that v  G  |χ  K  = <lb/> K  dx v(x) &lt; ∞ as long as K is <lb/>disjoint from X  D  . Assume the contrary, K ∩ X  D  = ∅; more precisely, K intersects <lb/> A <lb/> ⊥ <lb/> g  for some g ∈ D, but no other divergent loci. Moreover, assume that g is <lb/>connected -otherwise A <lb/> ⊥ <lb/> g  = A <lb/> ⊥ <lb/> g1  ∪ A <lb/> ⊥ <lb/> g2  and a smaller K will intersect only one of <lb/>these subspaces. Then v  G  splits into two factors <lb/> v  G  (x) = <lb/> e∈E(g) <lb/> △ <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (v  i  : e)x  i <lb/> e∈E\E(g) <lb/> △ <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (v  i  : e)x  i <lb/> , <lb/> with the second factor being smooth on A <lb/> ⊥ <lb/> g  \ <lb/> gg  ′  A <lb/> ⊥ <lb/> g  ′  . <lb/>Now we need some power counting: The integral <lb/> K  dx v  G  (x) is over a dn-<lb/> dimensional space. Since A  g  is the sum over all A  e  with e ∈ E(g), it is al-<lb/>ready spanned by the edges in a spanning tree t of g (a spanning tree is a sub-<lb/>graph without loops meeting every vertex exactly once -see Definition 3.29). A <lb/>spanning tree of a connected graph with n vertices has necessarily n − 1 edges, <lb/>therefore dim A  g  = d(|V (g)| − 1). Adding an edge to t produces a cycle, so that <lb/> h  1  (g) = |E(g)| − |V (g)| + 1. We conclude that dim A  g  = d(|E(g)| − h  1  (g)). Each <lb/> △(x) is of order  O(x <lb/> 2−d  )  as x → 0 and there are |E(g)| products in the first factor <lb/>expressing v  G  . Thus, the whole product scales as (2 − d)|E(g)| as x approaches A <lb/> ⊥ <lb/> g <lb/> in X <lb/> G  : <lb/> dx v  G  (x) ∝ <lb/> dr r <lb/> dim Ag−1+(2−d)|E(g)| <lb/> and the integral converges if and only if <lb/>dim A  g  + (2 − d)|E(g)| &gt; 0 ⇐⇒ d(|E(g)| − h  1  (g)) + (2 − d)|E(g)| &gt; 0 <lb/> ⇐⇒ ω(g) &lt; 0 <lb/> ⇐⇒ g / <lb/> ∈ D. <lb/></body>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> In Section 3.2 we will employ a more practical point of view. We use coordinates <lb/>on X <lb/> G  not given by the vertex set V <lb/> ′  , but on the edges of an adapted spanning <lb/>spanning tree t. Since every spanning tree of G must have |V | − 1 vertices, refor-<lb/>mulating everything in coordinates given by edges of t is just a change of basis for <lb/> M <lb/> V <lb/> ′  . The point here is that although it might seem to be more intuitive and &quot; posi-<lb/>tional &quot; to work with the vertex set of G, the formulation with t is more convenient <lb/>because the combinatorics of renormalization show up in the subgraph structure of <lb/> G and subgraphs are determined by subsets of E, not of V . <lb/>3. Compactifications <lb/> To systematically renormalize distributions v = v  G  (from now on we drop the <lb/>index G) coming from Feynman diagrams we want to arrange the loci of diver-<lb/>gences in a &quot; nice &quot; way by resolving their singularities. This means, we are looking <lb/>for a compactification of X \ X  D  , or, in other words, a smooth model for the di-<lb/>vergent arrangement in X <lb/> G  . This section consists of two parts: First we study <lb/>compactifications from a geometric point of view, then we focus on the underlying <lb/>combinatorics. <lb/>3.1. Geometry. The problem of resolving singularities has been a major topic in <lb/>algebraic geometry since the time of Newton who solved the problem of resolving <lb/>curves in the complex plane. In its most basic form the problem can be formulated <lb/>as follows. <lb/> Definition 3.1. Let X be an algebraic variety over a field k. Then a non-singular <lb/>variety Y is a resolution for X if there exists a proper and surjective rational map <lb/> β : Y −→ X. <lb/> There are various types of resolutions, depending on additional conditions on <lb/> Y and β. Here we demand that β is the composition of blow-ups along smooth <lb/>subvarieties of X. This allows for an explicit description of the manifold Y . <lb/>Hironaka showed in his celebrated work [Hir64] that for fields of characteristic <lb/>zero a resolution always exists; for fields of non-trivial characteristic this is still <lb/>an open problem. He gave a constructive proof using a sequence of blow-ups. The <lb/>difficulty lies in the fact that one cannot proceed by just blowing up all singularities <lb/>in X, but must choose a specific order in doing so. For an extensive treatment of <lb/>this topic, including a comparison of different resolutions, we refer to [Kol07]. Since <lb/>we will use the same method to resolve the singularities of a Feynman distribution, <lb/>we start with a general introduction to blow-ups. <lb/>3.1.1. Blow-ups. What is meant by blowing up a subvariety of a variety X? First, <lb/>we define the blow up of the origin in X = R <lb/> n  , following [GH94]. The idea is <lb/>to replace the origin by the space of all possible directions entering it, in such a <lb/>way that all directions are disjoint. To do so set E := P(X) with homogeneous <lb/>coordinates [y  1  : . . . : y  n  ] and define Y ⊆ X × E by <lb/> Y := <lb/> x  1  , . . . , x  n  , [y  1  : . . . : y  n  ] <lb/> | x  i  y  j  = x  j  y  i  for all i  = j <lb/> . <lb/> The map β : Y → X is then simply the projection onto the first factor. Since the <lb/>defining equations are smooth, Y is a smooth submanifold of X × E. To define an <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body> atlas for Y let for i = 1, . . . , n the maps ρ  i  : R <lb/> n  → X × E be given by <lb/>(x  1  , . . . , x  n  ) → (y  1  , . . . , y  n  , [y  1  : . . . : y  n  ]) <lb/>where <lb/> y  k  = <lb/> x  i <lb/> if k = i, <lb/>x  i  x  k  if k  = i. <lb/> Set U  i  = ρ  i  (R <lb/> n  ) and κ  i  := ρ <lb/> −1 <lb/> i  . Then the collection of charts (U  i  , κ  i  )  i∈{1,...,n}  forms <lb/>an atlas for Y . The submanifold E, called the exceptional divisor, is locally given <lb/>by {x  i  = 0} and covered by induced charts (V  i  , φ  i  )  i∈{1,...,n}  where V  i  := ˆ <lb/> ρ  i  (R <lb/> n−1  ) <lb/>and φ  i  := ˆ <lb/> ρ <lb/> −1 <lb/> i <lb/> with <lb/>ˆ <lb/> ρ  i  := ρ  i  |  xi=0  : R <lb/> n−1  −→ {0} × E ⊆ Y. <lb/> Blowing up along a submanifold S of R <lb/> n  is done similarly by replacing S by <lb/>the projectivization of its normal bundle. More precisely, if S is locally given by <lb/> {x  1  = . . . = x  k  = 0}, then one proceeds as above but restricts the defining equation <lb/>to these coordinates, <lb/> Y := <lb/> x  1  , . . . , x  n  , [y  1  : . . . : y  k  ] <lb/> | x  i  y  j  = x  j  y  i  for all i  = j ∈ {1, . . . , k} <lb/> . <lb/> Note that this construction is independent of the chosen coordinates. It can be <lb/>generalized to the case where S is a subvariety of a smooth variety X: Blow up <lb/>locally, then globalize by patching together the local blow-ups. <lb/>If S <lb/> ′  ⊆ X is another submanifold that is distinct from S, then S <lb/> ′  is essentially <lb/>unaffected by the blow-up process. However, if it has a nonempty intersection with <lb/> S, then S <lb/> ′  has two &quot; preimages &quot; in Y : The strict transform of S <lb/> ′  is defined as the <lb/>closure of β <lb/> −1  (S <lb/> ′  \ S) in Y , while the preimage β <lb/> −1  (S <lb/> ′  ) is called the total transform <lb/> of S <lb/> ′  . Loosely speaking, the blow-up makes degenerate intersections transversal <lb/>and transversal ones disjoint. Therefore, if building a resolution consists of multiple <lb/>blow-ups, the order of blowing up is important -we will get back to this point later. <lb/>We introduced here the algebro-geometric version of blowing up. There is also <lb/>a differential-geometric equivalent, where one replaces the locus to be blown up by <lb/>its normal spherebundle (as used in [AS94]). Both cases have drawbacks: Using <lb/>the projective normal bundles leads to Y being non-orientable in general, while the <lb/>differential-geometric blow-up produces a manifold with boundary. <lb/>3.1.2. Wonderful models. The general setup is the following: Let X be a finite <lb/>dimensional smooth variety over a field k of characteristic zero. An arrangement <lb/> A in X is a finite family of smooth subvarieties of X. Let M (A) denote the <lb/>complement of the arrangement, M (A) = X \ ∪  A∈A  A. <lb/> Definition 3.2. A smooth model for the arrangement A is a pair (Y  A  , β), where <lb/> Y  A  is a smooth variety and β : Y  A  −→ X is a proper surjective map with the <lb/>following properties: <lb/>(1) β is an isomorphism outside of E := β <lb/> −1  (X \ M (A)). <lb/>(2) E is a normal crossing divisor, i.e. there exist local coordinates such that it <lb/>is given by E = {(x  1  , . . . , x  n  ) | x  1  · . . . · x  k  = 0}. <lb/>(3) β is a composition of blowups along smooth centers. <lb/>Recall, that β is proper if and only if β <lb/> −1  (K) is compact for all compact sets <lb/> K ⊆ X; this is why smooth models are sometimes also called compactifications. <lb/>From [Hir64] we know that such a model always exists, actually in way more general <lb/></body>

			<page> 12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> situations. In their seminal paper [FM94] Fulton and MacPherson constructed a <lb/>compactification of the configuration space <lb/> F  n  (X) := {(x  1  , . . . , x  n  ) ∈ X <lb/> n  | x  i  = x  j  for all i  = j} <lb/> for a non-singular variety X. This is just an example of a smooth model for the <lb/>arrangement given by all diagonals D  I  in X <lb/> n  , <lb/> A = {D  I  | I ⊆ {1, . . . , n}} where D  I  = {x  i  = x  j  | ∀i, j ∈ I}. <lb/> Inspired by the techniques used in [FM94], DeConcini and Procesi developed a <lb/>systematic way to construct smooth models for general linear arrangements. Since <lb/>their technique is local, it can be generalized to arrangements in smooth varieties <lb/>(see [Li09]), but we do not need this here and stick to the notation of [CP95]. <lb/>Let V be a finite dimensional k-vector space (here k = R) and A be a linear <lb/>arrangement in the dual V <lb/>  *  , i.e. a finite family {A  1  , . . . , A  k  } of linear subspaces of <lb/> V <lb/>  *  (for the construction of DeConcini and Procesi it is more convenient to work in <lb/>the dual). We first give an abstract definition of a smooth model Y  A  for A, then <lb/>we construct it explicitly. <lb/> Definition 3.3 (Wonderful definition I). Let A be a linear arrangement in V <lb/>  *  . <lb/>For every A ∈ A the projection π  A  : V −→ V /A <lb/> ⊥  −→ P(V /A <lb/> ⊥  ) is a well defined <lb/>map outside of A <lb/> ⊥  . Doing this for every element in the arrangement, we obtain a <lb/>rational map <lb/> π  A  : M (A) −→ <lb/> A∈A <lb/> P(V /A <lb/> ⊥  ). <lb/>The graph Γ(π  A  ) of this map, a closed subset of M (A) × <lb/> A∈A  P(V /A <lb/> ⊥  ), embeds <lb/>openly into V × <lb/> A∈A  P(V /A <lb/> ⊥  ). The wonderful model Y  A  is defined as the closure <lb/>of the image of this embedding. <lb/>The second way of defining Y  A  is to explicitly construct it by a sequence of blow-<lb/>ups. This sequence is actually completely determined by the combinatorics of the <lb/> intersection poset P (A), a point we will use extensively in the following sections. <lb/>For the wonderful construction we need to introduce some terminology. The first <lb/>notion is based on the fact that Y  A  is also a wonderful model for arrangements A <lb/> ′  , as <lb/>long as A ⊆ A <lb/> ′  is a building set for A <lb/> ′  . The idea is that an arrangement may carry <lb/>too much information and in this case one needs only a subfamily B ⊆ A to encode <lb/>this information. While the choice of a building set controls the geometry of the <lb/>wonderful model, more precisely of the exceptional divisor E, certain subsets of B, <lb/> the B-nested sets, and the choice of a B-adapted basis of V are the crucial elements <lb/>in the explicit construction of an atlas for Y  A  . We cite the main definitions and <lb/>results from DeConcini and Procesi; for the proofs we refer the reader to [CP95]. <lb/> Definition 3.4 (Building sets). Let A be an arrangement in V <lb/>  *  . A subfamily <lb/> B ⊆ A is a building set for A if <lb/>(1) Every A ∈ A is the direct sum A = B  1  ⊕ · · · ⊕ B  k  of the maximal elements <lb/>of B contained in A. <lb/> (2) This decomposition property holds also for all A <lb/> ′  ∈ A with A <lb/> ′  ⊆ A, i.e. <lb/> A <lb/> ′  = (B  1  ∩ A <lb/> ′  ) ⊕ · · · ⊕ (B  k  ∩ A <lb/> ′  ). <lb/>There are two important building sets for any arrangement A, the maximal <lb/>building set, given by all elements of A, and the minimal building set I(A). The <lb/>latter consists of all A ∈ A that do not allow for a non-trivial decomposition. Note <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body> that every other building set B satisfies I(A) ⊆ B ⊆ A. In [CP95] it is shown <lb/>that for every building set B ⊆ A the variety Y  B  as defined above is a smooth <lb/>model for A. Moreover, the exceptional divisor E is the union of smooth irreducible <lb/>components E  B  , one for each B ∈ B. <lb/> Now we turn to the explicit description of Y  B  . <lb/> Definition 3.5 (Nested sets). Let B be a building set. N ⊆ B is B-nested if <lb/>the following holds: For all subsets {A  1  , . . . , A  k  } ⊆ N of pairwise incomparable <lb/>elements their direct sum does not belong to B. <lb/> Nested sets are one main ingredient in the description of Y  B  , the second one being <lb/>markings of an adapted basis of V <lb/>  *  . While nested sets reflect the combinatorics of <lb/>the stratification of E, the markings are related to the dimension of each submanifold <lb/>in this stratification. Together they describe all components of the exceptional <lb/>divisor. <lb/> Definition 3.6 (Adapted bases). A basis B of V <lb/>  *  is N -adapted if for all A ∈ N <lb/> the set B ∩ A generates A. A marking of an N -adapted basis is for every A ∈ N <lb/> the choice of an element b  A  ∈ B with p(b  A  ) = A. Here p = p  N  is the map assigning <lb/>to x ∈ V <lb/>  *  \ {0} the minimal element of N ∪ {V <lb/>  *  } containing x (it exists because <lb/> N is nested). <lb/>The map p and a marking define a partial order on B, <lb/>b  b <lb/> ′  ⇐⇒ p(b) ⊆ p(b <lb/> ′  ) and b <lb/> ′  is marked. <lb/>This partial order defines a map ρ = ρ  N ,B  : R <lb/> B  → V as follows. For every <lb/> x = <lb/> b∈B  x  b  b ∈ R <lb/> B  the image ρ(x) is an element of V = hom(V <lb/>  *  , R) given by <lb/> B ∋ b → <lb/> p(b)⊆A  x  bA <lb/> if b is marked, <lb/> x  b <lb/> p(b)⊆A  x  bA  else. <lb/>Viewing the elements of B as nonlinear coordinates on V and with x  A  := x  bA  , we <lb/>can write ρ as <lb/> ρ(x)  b  = ρ(x)(b) = <lb/> p(b)⊆A  x  A <lb/> if b is marked, <lb/> x  b <lb/> p(b)⊆A  x  A  else. <lb/>The next proposition shows that the map ρ has all the properties of a local descrip-<lb/>tion of a composition of blow-ups. <lb/> Proposition 3.7. For every nested set N and an adapted and marked basis B the <lb/>map ρ = ρ  N ,B  is a birational morphism with the following properties: <lb/>It maps the subspace defined by x  A  = 0 onto A <lb/> ⊥  and it restricts to an isomor-<lb/>phism <lb/> V \ <lb/> A∈N <lb/> {x  A  = 0} <lb/> ∼ = <lb/> −→ V \ <lb/> A∈N <lb/> A <lb/> ⊥  . <lb/> Furthermore, every v in V <lb/>  *  \ {0} with p(v) = A ∈ N is mapped by ρ(x) to <lb/> ρ(x)(v) = P  v  (x) <lb/> bA b <lb/> v  b  x  b <lb/> where P  v  is a polynomial, depending only on {x  b  }  b≺bA  and linear in each variable. <lb/></body>

			<page> 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> Definition 3.8 (Wonderful definition II). Let N be a B-nested set for a building set <lb/> B ⊆ A and B an adapted, marked basis. Define Z  A  ⊆ R <lb/> B  by Z  A  = {P  v  = 0, v ∈ A}, <lb/> the vanishing locus of all P  v  for v ∈ A. Then for every A ∈ B the composition of ρ <lb/> with the projection π  A  : V \ A <lb/> ⊥  → P(V /A <lb/> ⊥  ) is well-defined outside of Z  A  . <lb/>Composing the map ρ with Γ(π  B  ) : M (B) → V × <lb/> A∈B  P(V /A <lb/> ⊥  ) defines an <lb/>open embedding <lb/>(Γ(π  B  ) • ρ)  N ,B  : R <lb/> B  \ <lb/> A∈B <lb/> Z  A  −→ Y  B  . <lb/> Set U  N ,B  := im <lb/> (Γ(π  B  ) • ρ)  N ,B <lb/> and κ  N ,B  := (Γ(π  B  ) • ρ) <lb/> −1 <lb/>N ,B  . Varying over all <lb/> B-nested sets N and adapted, marked bases B, we obtain an atlas (U  N ,B  , κ  N ,B  ) <lb/>for the wonderful model Y  B  . The map β is just the projection onto the first factor, <lb/>in local coordinates given by ρ. <lb/> That this really defines a smooth model for the arrangement A follows from the <lb/>next proposition. <lb/> Theorem 3.9 (Geometry of the wonderful model). Let B be a building set for A. <lb/> The wonderful model Y  B  has the following properties: <lb/> (1) The exceptional divisor E is normal crossing, i.e. <lb/> E := β <lb/> −1  ( <lb/> A∈B <lb/> A <lb/> ⊥  ) <lb/> loc. <lb/> = { <lb/> A∈N <lb/> x  A  = 0}. <lb/>(2) E is the union of smooth irreducible components E  A  where A ∈ B and <lb/> β(E  A  ) = A <lb/> ⊥  . A family of these components E  A1  , . . . , E  A  k  has non-empty <lb/>intersection if and only if {A  1  , . . . , A  k  } is a B-nested set. In this case the <lb/>intersection is transversal and irreducible. <lb/> (3) For A minimal in B \ I(A) let A = A  1  ⊕ . . . ⊕ A  k  be its irreducible decom-<lb/>position. Set B <lb/> ′  = B \ {A}. Then Y  B  is obtained from Y  B  ′  by blowing up <lb/> E  A  = E  A1  ∩ . . . ∩ E  A  k  . <lb/> (4) For A minimal in B = I(A) set B <lb/> ′  = B \ {A}. Then Y  B  is obtained from <lb/> Y  B  ′  by blowing up the proper transform of A <lb/> ⊥  . <lb/> As stated before, the most famous example of a wonderful model is the Fulton-<lb/>MacPherson compactification of the configuration space F  n  (X) in the case where <lb/> X is a linear space. It is the minimal wonderful model for the arrangement of all <lb/>(poly-)diagonals in X <lb/> n  , <lb/> A = {D  π  | π is a partition of {1, . . . , n}}, <lb/>D  π  = {x  i  = x  j  | i, j lie in the same partition block of π }. <lb/> Here the minimal building set consists of all simple diagonals in the n-fold product <lb/>of X. The wonderful model for the maximal building set was studied by Ulyanov <lb/>in [Uly02] and called a polydiagonal compactification of configuration space. The <lb/>main difference, apart from the geometry of the exceptional divisor, is the blowup <lb/>sequence in the construction. In [Uly02] the model is obtained by successively <lb/>blowing up (the strict transforms of) all elements of the building set by increas-<lb/>ing dimension, but in the minimal case one has to proceed with care; some strict <lb/>transforms of diagonals to be blown up in the next step might still have nonempty <lb/>intersection and in this case the result depends on the order of blowups. To sep-<lb/>arate them before proceeding requires additional blow-ups, exactly those given by <lb/>the additional elements in the maximal building set. These are the polydiagonals, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body> obtained by intersecting simple diagonals. The interested reader is encouraged to <lb/>study the example F  n  (X) for X = R and n &gt; 3 (for smaller n minimal and maximal <lb/>models coincide). It is a well studied object, the real rank n − 1 braid arrangement, <lb/> see for example [Fei05]. <lb/>The next step is to adapt this construction to the case of the divergent arrange-<lb/>ment associated to a Feynman graph G. In [BBK10] this is done by examining the <lb/>special structure of the elements of the arrangement A = {A  g  | g ⊆ G divergent}. <lb/>These properties of A can be directly formulated in graph theoretical terms. Here <lb/>we will focus even more on this combinatorial flavour of QFT and formulate every-<lb/>thing with the help of the poset of divergent subgraphs of G. In the next section we <lb/>will express all central notions of the wonderful construction, building sets, nested <lb/>sets and adapted, marked bases in terms of this poset. <lb/>3.2. Combinatorics. In the application to graphs and the renormalization pro-<lb/>gram to be presented here, combinatorics play a major role and therefore we re-<lb/>formulate the central objects of the last section in terms of a poset associated to <lb/> A. We focus on arrangements coming from graphs via Feynman rules, but note <lb/>that from every given arrangement we can form the intersection poset to study its <lb/>combinatorics. <lb/> Definition 3.10. A poset (P, ≤) is a finite set P (we consider here only finite <lb/>graphs and posets) endowed with a partial order ≤. <lb/> We say that p covers q if p &gt; q and there is no r ∈ P with p &gt; r &gt; q. The closed <lb/>interval [p, q] = P  [p,q]  is defined as the set of elements r ∈ P satisfying p ≤ r ≤ q . <lb/>The open interval (p, q) = P  (p,q)  and the subsets P  &lt;p  , P  ≤p  , P  &gt;p  , P  ≥p  are defined <lb/>similarly. We denote by  and  the unique minimal and maximal elements of P if <lb/>they exist. <lb/>A poset is best visualized by drawing its Hasse diagram, a directed graph with <lb/>its vertices given by the elements of P and edges between every pair of elements <lb/> p, q ∈ P such that p covers q. Another way to encode the data of P is the order <lb/>complex ∆(P). It is the abstract simplicial complex defined by its k-faces being <lb/>the linearly ordered k + 1-element subsets of P. The order complex stores all the <lb/>combinatorial information of P as is demonstrated by the following theorem taken <lb/>from [GM87]. <lb/> Definition 3.11 (Intersection lattice). Let V be an n-dimensional real vector space <lb/>and let A := {A  1  , . . . , A  m  } be an arrangement in V . Every arrangement gives rise <lb/>to a poset (actually a lattice, defined below) with its underlying set consisting of <lb/>all possible intersections of elements in A, <lb/>P = P(A) = { <lb/> i∈I <lb/> A  i  | I ⊆ {1, . . . , m}}, <lb/> partially ordered by reverse inclusion. It is called the intersection poset/lattice of <lb/> A. <lb/> In addition, P(A) is equipped with a ranking, i.e. a map r : P(A) → N mapping <lb/>each element of P(A) to the codimension of the corresponding intersection in V . <lb/>Let M (A) := V \ <lb/>  m <lb/>i=1  A  i  denote the complement of the arrangement. Then the <lb/>homology of M (A) is encoded in ∆(P(A)). <lb/></body>

			<page> 16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> Theorem 3.12. (Goresky, MacPherson) Let H denote the (singular) homology <lb/>functor. Let A be an arrangement in V and let M (A) denote the complement. <lb/>Then <lb/> H  k  (M (A), Z) ∼ = <lb/> A∈P(A) <lb/> G  k  (A), <lb/> where <lb/> (2) <lb/> G  k  (A) = <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> H <lb/> −k  (point, Z) <lb/> if A = ˆ 0, <lb/> H <lb/> r(A)−k−1  (point, Z) <lb/> if A covers  , <lb/>˜ <lb/> H <lb/> r(A)−k−2  (∆(P  ( ˆ 0,A)  ), Z) otherwise. <lb/> Recall from Section 2 the definition of the singular and divergent arrangements <lb/>of a graph G. They give rise to corresponding intersection posets, but we can also <lb/>define them directly in terms of G. <lb/> Definition 3.13. To a graph G we associate the (saturated) graph poset (G, ⊆) <lb/> consisting of the set of all saturated subgraphs of G, partially ordered by inclusion. <lb/>A connected subgraph g ⊆ G is saturated if the following holds <lb/> ∀t span. tree of g : ∀e ∈ E(G \ g) : t is not a spanning for g ∪ e. <lb/> If g has more than one connected components, it is saturated if every component <lb/>is. <lb/>In terms of the singular arrangement a saturated subgraph g is the maximal <lb/>subgraph of G defining A  g  ∈ A  G  . This means, that adding an edge to a saturated <lb/>graph necessarily changes the space A  g  , while removing an edge might still define <lb/>the same subspace of (X <lb/> G  ) <lb/>  *  . <lb/> Example. Let K  3  be the complete graph on 3 vertices. The saturated subgraphs <lb/>are the three single-edged subgraphs and K  3  itself. <lb/> a <lb/>c <lb/>b <lb/>a <lb/>o <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>K  3 <lb/> Figure 2. K  3  and the Hasse diagram of G(K  3  ) <lb/> Definition 3.14. The divergent graph poset D is given by the subset of G formed <lb/>by all divergent subgraphs, partially ordered by inclusion. <lb/>Of course we can do the same for other subsets of G, but for our purposes only G <lb/> and D (and special subsets thereof) will be important. As already seen in Proposi-<lb/>tion 2.9 they carry all the information necessary for renormalization. Note that all <lb/>subsets of G have an unique minimal element, the empty graph, which we denote <lb/>by o. In our convention o is defined by E(o) = ∅. <lb/> For the divergent arrangement of a connected and at most logarithmic graph G, <lb/> Theorem 3.12 allows us to compute the homology of M (X <lb/> G <lb/> D  ), the complement of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body> the divergent loci in X <lb/> G  . It is determined by the set of atoms of D, the minimal <lb/>elements in D  &gt;o  . These elements are precisely the primitive subgraphs of G. <lb/> Proposition 3.15. Let G be connected and at most logarithmic. Define n  i  to be <lb/>the number of atoms g ∈ D with r(g) = dim A  g  = di (i.e. the primitive subgraphs <lb/>on i + 1 vertices). Let α ∈ N <lb/> l  be a multi index with α  i  ≥ α  j  for 1 ≤ i &lt; j ≤ l and <lb/> ||α||  1  = l. The homology of M (X <lb/> G <lb/> D  ) is then given by <lb/> (3) <lb/> H  k  (M (X <lb/> G <lb/> D  ), Z) ∼ = <lb/>  <lb/>             <lb/>            <lb/> Z <lb/> if k = 0, <lb/> Z <lb/> ni <lb/> if k = di − 1, <lb/> Z ( <lb/> n i <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> if k = 2di − 2, <lb/> Z <lb/> ni  1  ni  2 <lb/> if k = d(i  1  + i  2  ) − 2, <lb/> . . . <lb/> Z <lb/>  l <lb/>j=1  ( <lb/> n i j <lb/>α j <lb/> ) if k = d <lb/>  l <lb/>j=1  α  j  i  j  − l, <lb/>. . . <lb/> Proof. The atoms of D determine the topology of the complement because the <lb/>corresponding subspaces A <lb/> ⊥ <lb/> g  contain all other divergent subspaces. <lb/>Abbreviate H  k  (M (X <lb/> G <lb/> D  ), Z) by H  k  . Using Theorem 3.12 we have H  0  = Z. More-<lb/>over, there is a generator in H  k  with k = r(g)−1 = di−1 for every atom g such that <lb/> r(g) = di. For an element γ that is given by the union of atoms we have to use the <lb/>third row in Equation (2): If γ is the union of two atoms g and h, the subcomplex <lb/>∆(D  (o,γ)  ) consists of 2 disconnected points (representing the two atoms). Therefore <lb/>we have <lb/>  ni <lb/> 2 <lb/> generators in dimension k = 2di − 2 if r(g) = r(h) = di and n  i1  n  i2 <lb/> generators in dimension k = d(i  1  + i  2  ) − 2 if r(g) = di  1  and r(h) = di  2  . If γ is <lb/>the union of l &gt; 2 atoms, the interval (o, γ) consists of these atoms and all unions <lb/>thereof. It is the face poset of the standard (l − 1)-simplex △ <lb/> l−1  with interior re-<lb/>moved. Thus, ∆(D  (o,γ)  ) = ∆(F (∂△ <lb/> l−1  )) ∼ = ∂△ <lb/> l−1  ∼ = S <lb/> l−2  . Since <lb/> k  (S <lb/> l−2  ) equals <lb/> Z if k = l − 2 and is trivial else, we conclude that there are generators in H  k  coming <lb/>from such elements γ if k = r(γ) − l. Let α ∈ N <lb/> l  with α  i  ≥ α  j  for 1 ≤ i &lt; j ≤ l <lb/> and ||α||  1  = l. If r(γ) = d <lb/>  l <lb/>j=1  α  j  i  j  then such γ can be formed out of l atoms in <lb/>  l <lb/>j=1 <lb/>  ni  j <lb/> αj <lb/> possible ways and (3) follows. <lb/> 3.2.1. The divergent graph lattice. From now on let G always be connected. We <lb/>continue studying the graph poset G in more detail. As it turns out it has extra <lb/>structure, it is a lattice. <lb/> Definition 3.16 (Lattices). Let (P, ≤) be a poset and p, q ∈ P. A least upper <lb/>bound or join of p and q is an upper bound r for both elements such that every <lb/>other upper bound s satifies r ≤ s. If the join of p and q exists, it is unique and <lb/>denoted by p ∨ q. <lb/> Dually one defines a greatest lower bound or meet of two elements p and q in P, <lb/> denoted by p ∧ q. <lb/> P is called a join-semilattice (meet-semilattice) if for all p, q ∈ P the join p ∨ q <lb/> (the meet p∧q) exists. P is called a lattice if it is both a join-and a meet-semilattice. <lb/>For any arrangement A the intersection poset P(A) is a lattice: If one orders the <lb/>elements of P(A) by reverse inclusion then the join operation is just given by set <lb/>theoretic intersection. The statement then follows from the fact that every finite <lb/></body>

			<page> 18 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> join-semilattice with  (represented by the empty intersection, the ambient space <lb/> V ) is a lattice (Proposition 3.3.1 in [Sta97]). <lb/>Regarding the definition of the partial order by inclusion or reverse inclusion <lb/>there are different conventions used in the literature. Both have their advantages <lb/>and can be converted into the other since the dual of any lattice, i.e. the lattice with <lb/>reversed order, is a lattice as well. We use reverse inclusion because it matches the <lb/>convention in [CP95] using arrangements in the dual and it fits with the natural <lb/>partial order on subgraphs. <lb/>Since G is the intersection poset of the (dual) singular arrangement A  G  in X <lb/> G  , <lb/>it is a lattice. Clearly, if P ⊆ G is closed under union and intersection, it is the <lb/>intersection lattice of some corresponding arrangement. This is the case for the set <lb/>of divergent subgraphs: <lb/> Proposition 3.17. Let G be at most logarithmic. Then (D, ⊆) is a lattice. <lb/>Proof. For g, h ⊆ G divergent subgraphs we define the join and meet operations in <lb/> D by <lb/> g ∨ h := g ∪ h <lb/>g ∧ h := g ∩ h <lb/> Suppose g and h have k shared edges and l shared cycles. Moreover, assume that <lb/> m new cycles are created by uniting g and h. In formulae: <lb/> h  1  (g ∪ h) = h  1  (g) + h  1  (h) + m − l <lb/>E(g ∪ h) = E(g) + E(h) − k. <lb/> From this we conclude that the superficial degree of divergence of g ∪ h is given by <lb/> ω(g ∪ h) = d(h  1  (g) + h  1  (h) + m − l) − 2(E(g) + E(h) − k) <lb/> = d(m − l) + 2k <lb/> ! <lb/> ≤ 0. <lb/>Split k = k  l  + k  0  into edges in the shared cycles and those that are not. Then <lb/> dl ≤ 2k  l  and we conclude <lb/> ω(g ∪ h) ≥ dm + 2k  0  ≥ 0 <lb/>Thus m = k  0  = 0 and <lb/>0 ≥ ω(g ∪ h) = dl − 2k  l  = ω(g ∩ h) ≤ 0. <lb/>Therefore g ∪ h and g ∩ h are both divergent subgraphs of G. Clearly, they are the <lb/>minimal (maximal) elements of D bounding g and h from above (below). <lb/> With the methods used in the above proof we are able to show another property <lb/>of G and D. They are graded lattices. <lb/> Definition 3.18. A poset (P, ≤) is graded if it is equipped with a map τ : P → N <lb/> that has the following two properties: τ is order preserving with respect to the <lb/>natural order on N and if there are p, q ∈ P with p covering q, then τ (p) = τ (q) + 1. <lb/> Proposition 3.19. For any connected graph G the graph lattice G is graded. <lb/>Proof. The map τ associates to every saturated subgraph g ⊆ G the value d <lb/> −1  dim A  g  = <lb/> V (g) − c  g  (c  g  denoting the number of connected components of g, cf. the proof of <lb/>Proposition 2.9). Clearly, τ is order preserving and τ (p) = τ (q) + 1 for p covering <lb/> q holds because of the saturated condition. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body> Proposition 3.20. Let G be at most logarithmic. Then D is a graded lattice. <lb/> To prove this we use Proposition 3.3.2 from [Sta97]. <lb/> Proposition 3.21. Let L be a finite lattice. The following two conditions are <lb/>equivalent: <lb/>1. L is graded and the map τ satisfies τ (x) + τ (y) ≥ τ (x ∧ y) + τ (x ∨ y) for all <lb/> x, y ∈ L. <lb/> 2. If x and y both cover x ∧ y, then x ∨ y covers both x and y. <lb/> Proof of Proposition 3.20 . We argue by contradiction: Let g, h ⊆ G be divergent <lb/>and suppose there is a γ ∈ D with g &lt; γ &lt; g ∨h, i.e. g ∨h does not cover both g and <lb/> h. First, note that γ ∩ h  = ∅ because otherwise γ would not be a subgraph of g ∨ h. <lb/> From Proposition 3.17 we know that γ ∩h is divergent. But then g∧h &lt; γ ∧h &lt; h, <lb/> which means h is not covering g ∧ h. <lb/> We will not use this here but for the sake of completeness we mention one <lb/>additional property of D. From a combinatorial viewpoint distributive lattices are <lb/>important because this extra structure allows one to prove many powerful theorems, <lb/>for example Birkhoff&apos;s famous representation theorem [Bir67]. <lb/> Proposition 3.22. Let G be at most logarithmic. Then D is a distributive lattice, <lb/>i.e. <lb/> f ∨ (g ∧ h) =(f ∨ g) ∧ (f ∨ h), <lb/>f ∧ (g ∨ h) =(f ∧ g) ∨ (f ∧ h), <lb/> for all f, g, h in D. <lb/> Proof. Since one of the properties implies the other ,we will only proof the first one. <lb/>Moreover, the proof works exactly the same in the second case. <lb/>Let f, g, h ⊆ G be divergent. Compare the edge set of the graphs on the left and <lb/>the right: <lb/> E <lb/> f ∨ (g ∧ h) <lb/> =E <lb/> f ∪ (g ∩ h) <lb/> = E(f ) ∪ E(g ∩ h) <lb/> = <lb/> E(f ) ∪ E(g) <lb/> ∩ <lb/> E(f ) ∪ E(h) <lb/> =E(f ∪ g) ∩ E(f ∪ h) = E <lb/> (f ∪ g) ∩ (f ∪ h) <lb/> =E <lb/> (f ∨ g) ∧ (f ∨ h) <lb/> . <lb/> 3.2.2. Wonderful models revisited. We reformulate wonderful models in terms of <lb/>the graph lattice G. This is based on [Fei05] where a combinatorial version of the <lb/>wonderful model construction is developed for any (finite) lattice L. In general we <lb/>can associate to every arrangement the corresponding intersection lattice defined <lb/>in the previous section. It is the combinatorics of this lattice that reflect the topo-<lb/>logical properties of the wonderful models as seen for example in Theorem 3.12. <lb/>Another example is the following theorem by Feichtner that relates combinatorial <lb/>and geometric wonderful models via a combinatorial blow-up (Definition 3.5 and <lb/>Theorem 3.6 in [Fei05]). <lb/> Theorem 3.23. Let L be an intersection lattice, B a combinatorial building set <lb/>in L, and B  1  , . . . , B  t  a linear order on B that is non-increasing with respect to the <lb/></body>

			<page> 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> partial order on L. Then consecutive combinatorial blowups in B  1  , . . . , B  t  result in <lb/>the face poset of the nested set complex ∆  N  (L, B), <lb/> Bl  Gt  (. . . (Bl  G2  (Bl  G1  ))) = F (∆  N  (L, B)) . <lb/> Although the following definitions apply to any lattice L, to connect with Sec-<lb/>tion 2.2 think of L as being given by the singular or divergent arrangement of <lb/>a connected and at most logarithmic graph G. We define the central notions of <lb/>the wonderful construction in combinatorial language following [Fei05] where the <lb/>interested reader finds a thorough exposition of the wonderful models from a combi-<lb/>natorial geometer&apos;s viewpoint. In this case building sets and nested sets are certain <lb/>subposets of L (a subposet of a poset (P, ≤) is a subset of P with the induced <lb/>partial order). In some cases these subsets are even lattices, although not neces-<lb/>sarily sublattices since the meet and join operations need not be induced by the <lb/>corresponding operations on L. <lb/> Definition 3.24 (Combinatorial building sets). Let L be a lattice. A non-empty <lb/>subset B of L is a combinatorial building set for L if the following holds: For all <lb/> p ∈ L  &gt; ˆ 0  and {q  1  , . . . , q  k  } = max B  ≤p  there is an isomorphism of posets <lb/>(4) <lb/> ϕ  p  : <lb/> k <lb/> i=1 <lb/> [ ˆ 0, q  i  ] −→ [ ˆ 0, p] <lb/> with ϕ  p  ( ˆ 0, . . . , q  j  , . . . , ˆ 0) = q  j  for j = 1, . . . , k. <lb/> This defines combinatorial building sets which are more general than the build-<lb/>ing sets introduced in Section 3.1. To get the notion of a geometric building set <lb/> according to the construction of DeConcini and Procesi we have to demand an <lb/>additional geometric compatibility condition. <lb/> Definition 3.25 (Geometric building sets). We call B a geometric building set for <lb/> L if it is a combinatorial building set and <lb/>dim A  p  = <lb/> k <lb/> i=1 <lb/> dim A  qi  . <lb/> Note that if L ⊆ G, since dim A  g  = d(|V (g)| − 1) (or d(|E(g)| − h  1  (g)) if g is <lb/>divergent), we can express this geometric condition also purely in graph theoretic <lb/>terms. <lb/> Example. For every lattice L itself is a building set, the maximal building set. The <lb/> minimal building set is given by the irreducible elements of L. It is formed by all <lb/> p ∈ L for which there is no product decomposition as in (4) of the interval [ ˆ 0, p]. <lb/> We denote this building set by I(L). <lb/> The geometric condition gives a handy criterion to check whether a given element <lb/>is irreducible or not. <lb/> Lemma 3.26. Let L ⊆ G be a lattice. Let g ∈ L be the union of irreducible <lb/>subgraphs g = g  1  ∪ · · · ∪ g  k  with non-empty overlap h = g  1  ∩ · · · ∩ g  k  . W.l.o.g. <lb/>assume that the g  i  are maximal with this property. Then g is irreducible. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body> Vice versa, for every reducible element g ∈ L \ I(L) we have that g is the union <lb/>of some g  1  , . . . , g  k  ∈ I(L) with <lb/> k <lb/> i=1 <lb/> g  i  = <lb/> v∈V  ′ <lb/> v ∼ o <lb/> for some vertex set V <lb/> ′  ⊆ V (G). <lb/> Proof. Write d(g) for dim A  g  . If g would be reducible, then d(g) = <lb/>  k <lb/>i=1  d(g  i  ) <lb/>because the g  i  form the set max I(L)  ≤g  . On the other hand, d(g) = <lb/>  k <lb/>i=1  d(g  i  ) − <lb/> d(h) -the sum can not be direct because of the overlap h. Thus, d(h) = 0, i.e. <lb/> A  h  = {0} which means h = o. <lb/> The second statement follows from the same argument. The geometric condition <lb/>for reducibility d(g) = <lb/>  k <lb/>i=1  d(g  i  ) cannot hold if the g  i  have common edges. <lb/> Recall that the choice of a building set B determines the structure of the ex-<lb/>ceptional divisor E in the wonderful model; the elements of B control the number <lb/>of components of E and how they intersect. To construct Y  B  explicitly we need <lb/>another family of sub(po)sets of B, the B-nested sets. <lb/> Definition 3.27 (Nested sets). Let B be a building set in a lattice L. A subset <lb/> N ⊆ B is B-nested if for all subsets {p  1  , . . . , p  k  } ⊆ N of pairwise incomparable <lb/>elements the join (in L!) p  1  ∨ . . . ∨ p  k  exists and does not belong to B. <lb/> With nested sets we can build another abstract simplicial complex, the nested <lb/>set complex ∆  N  (L, B). Its k-faces consist of the B-nested sets with k + 1 elements. <lb/>It is the generalization of the order complex for non-maximal building sets. For the <lb/>maximal building set B = L a subset is nested if and only if it is linearly ordered <lb/>in B, so that in this case we have ∆(L) = ∆  N  (L, B). By Theorem 3.9 it contains <lb/>all the information about the stratification of the exceptional divisor E in Y  B  . <lb/>Since D is a graded lattice, we have proven here a little conjecture (in the case G <lb/> at most logarithmic) that appears in many texts on Hopf algebraic renormalization <lb/>(for example [BK08]): <lb/> Corollary 3.28. Every maximal forest of a graph G has the same cardinality. <lb/>Proof. In the language of posets this translates into the fact that every maximal <lb/>nested set has equal cardinality. But this is equivalent to D being graded because <lb/>the grading map τ forbids maximal linearly ordered subsets of different length. <lb/> Example. Here are some examples, all in d = 4: <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>5 <lb/>4 <lb/>2n − 3 <lb/>2n − 4 2n − 1 <lb/>2n − 2 <lb/> Figure 3. The n-bubble graph <lb/>(1) Let G <lb/> n  be the graph in Figure 3. Here the index n stands for the number <lb/>of atoms, the one-loop fish subgraphs on two edges, and the numbering <lb/></body>

			<page> 22 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> of vertices is chosen to match the most &quot; natural &quot; choice of an adapted <lb/>spanning tree t (see Definition 3.30). <lb/>Let g <lb/> k <lb/> l  denote the full subgraph of G <lb/> n  given by the vertex set V (g <lb/> k <lb/>l  ) = <lb/> {2l − 2, . . . , 2l − 2 + 2k − 1}. From the fact that D(G <lb/> n+1  ) contains two <lb/>copies of D(G <lb/> n  ), given by the intervalls [o, g <lb/> n <lb/> 1  ] and [o, g <lb/> n <lb/> 2  ], and Lemma 3.26, <lb/>it follows by induction that <lb/> I(D(G <lb/> n  )) = {g <lb/> k <lb/>l  ⊆ G <lb/> n  | k = 1, . . . , n and l = 1, . . . , n − k + 1}. <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>5 <lb/>4 <lb/> n − 2 <lb/> n − 1 <lb/> n <lb/> Figure 4. The n-insertions graph <lb/>(2) Next we look at the graph G  n  , depicted in Figure 4, constructed by a <lb/>sequence of n insertions of the fish into itself. Here minimal and maximal <lb/>building set coincide because all divergent subgraphs are nested into each <lb/>other: <lb/> D(G  n  ) = I(D(G  n  )) = {g  1  , g  2  , . . . , g  n  = G  n  } <lb/> where g  i  is the full subgraph of G <lb/> n  corresponding to the vertex set {0, . . . , i}. <lb/> The partial order is a total order. Thus, the D(G  n  )-nested sets are all non-<lb/>empty subsets of the power set P (D(G <lb/> n  )). <lb/>(3) Let G <lb/> n,m  be the graph obtained by inserting n bubbles on the left and m <lb/> bubbles on the right into the fish graph (Figure 5). Here <lb/> I(D(G <lb/> n,m  )) = {g  1  , . . . , g  n  , h  1  . . . , h  m  , G <lb/> n,m  } <lb/> where g  i  is the fish subgraph on the vertex set {i−1, i} for i ∈ {1, . . . , n} and <lb/> h  j  is the fish subgraph on the vertex set {n+j, n+j +1} for j ∈ {1, . . . , m}. <lb/> All subgraphs in I(D(G <lb/> n,m  )) \ {G <lb/> n,m  } have disjoint edge sets. Therefore, <lb/>as in the previous example, the I(D(G <lb/> n,m  ))-nested sets are all non-empty <lb/>subsets of P (I(D(G <lb/> n,m  ))). <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> n − 1 <lb/> n <lb/>n + m + 1 <lb/> n + m <lb/>n + 2 <lb/> n + 1 <lb/> Figure 5. The n, m-bubble graph <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body> (4) For n &gt; 0 let G = K  n+1  be the complete graph on n + 1 vertices. By <lb/>induction it follows that saturated subgraphs are either disjoint unions or <lb/>complete subgraphs on their respective vertex set. Thus, if n = 2 then <lb/> G = I(G). For n = 3 (Figure 6) the three subgraphs given by the disjoint <lb/>union of edges a ˙ <lb/> ∪ c, b ˙ <lb/> ∪ d and e ˙ <lb/> ∪ f are reducible while the four embeddings <lb/>of K  3  given by a ∪ b ∪ f etc. are irreducible (|[o, a ∪ b ∪ f ]| = 5 is not divisible <lb/>by two). <lb/>In general, I(G(K  n+1  )) consists of all subgraphs that are embeddings of <lb/> K  i  into K  n+1  for i = 1, . . . , n while the reducible subgraphs are the disjoint <lb/>unions of embeddings of K  i  and K  j  for i + j ≤ n + 1. These disjoint <lb/>unions represent the polydiagonals that make the difference in the blow-up <lb/>sequence of the Fulton-MacPherson compactification M [n] and Ulyanov&apos;s <lb/>polydiagonal compactification M n. <lb/> a <lb/>d <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>e <lb/>f <lb/> Figure 6. K  4 <lb/> It remains to define the combinatorial version of adapted bases. For this we need <lb/> adapted spanning trees. <lb/> Definition 3.29. Let G be a connected graph. A spanning tree for G is a simply-<lb/>connected subgraph t ⊆ G with V (t) = V (G). If G is not connected, G = G  1  ˙ <lb/> ∪ . . . ˙ <lb/> ∪ <lb/> G  n  , a spanning n-forest for G is the disjoint union t = t  1  ˙ <lb/> ∪ . . . ˙ <lb/> ∪ t  n  of n spanning <lb/>trees t  i  for G  i  . <lb/> Definition 3.30 (Adapted spanning trees). Let G be a graph and P ⊆ G a family <lb/>of subgraphs of G. A spanning tree t of G is P-adapted if for each g ∈ P the graph <lb/> t  g  , defined by E(t  g  ) := E(t) ∩ E(g) is a spanning tree for g. More precisely, if g is <lb/>not connected, then we demand t  g  to be a spanning forest for g. <lb/> Example. For dunce&apos;s cap an D-adapted spanning tree (d = 4) is given by E(t) = <lb/> {e  1  , e  3  } or E(t) = {e  2  , e  4  }, while t with E(t) = {e  1  , e  2  } is spanning but not adapted. <lb/> Proposition 3.31. A D-adapted spanning tree always exists for G at most loga-<lb/>rithmic. <lb/>Proof. We construct t using the fact that divergent graphs can be built from prim-<lb/>itive ones using the insertion operation. Moreover, this process is reversible, i.e. in <lb/>the dual process of contracting subgraphs no information is lost. <lb/>Start with the primitive subgraphs of G and let G  1  be the graph obtained from <lb/> G by contracting all these primitive subgraphs. G  1  might have primitive subgraphs <lb/>itself (the g ∈ D with coradical degree equal to two, cf. [Kre13]). Repeat the <lb/>process. After a finite number of steps G  k  will be free of subdivergences. Now <lb/>choose a spanning tree t  1  for G  k  and spanning trees for all subgraphs contracted in <lb/>the step from G  k−1  to G  k  . Then t  2  , the union of all these spanning trees, is a tree <lb/></body>

			<page> 24 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> in G  k−1  visiting every vertex exactly once. Thus, it is a spanning tree for G  k−1  . <lb/>Repeat this process until after k steps we have an D-adapted spanning tree t = t  k <lb/> of G. <lb/> Remark. An interesting question arising here is the following: For which families <lb/> P ⊆ G does such a P-adapted spanning tree exist? For a counterexample just take <lb/> P = G or I(G): In the first case every edge of G lies in G, so there cannot exist <lb/>a G-adapted spanning tree. For the second case consider the example K  4  ; there is <lb/>no spanning tree that generates all four irreducible &quot; triangle &quot; subgraphs. Another <lb/>question is for which class of graphs this holds, i.e. if the assumption of G being at <lb/>most logarithmic can be dropped. <lb/>With adapted spanning trees we are able to define N -adapted bases of (X <lb/> G  ) <lb/>  *  in <lb/>combinatorial terms. If the divergent lattice is considered, a D-adapted spanning <lb/>tree will automatically be N -adapted for any nested set of any building set in D. <lb/> This allows us to fix a convenient basis from the beginning on. Every spanning <lb/>tree t of G has |V | − 1 edges (otherwise it would contain a loop, contradicting <lb/>simply-connectedness). Therefore, for every spanning tree t of G (with the same <lb/>orientation) we have a linear map ψ  t  : M <lb/> E(t)  → M <lb/> V <lb/> ′  defined by <lb/>(5) <lb/> e → <lb/> v  j  − v  i  if e starts at v  i  and ends v  j  , <lb/> ±v  k <lb/> if e connects v  0  to v  k  . <lb/>Pulling back v  G  along ψ  t  amounts to a linear change of coordinates on X <lb/> G  (as well <lb/>as altering the numbering of the vertices of G, its orientation or the choice of a <lb/>different (adapted) spanning tree). Any automorphism of X <lb/> G  will not change the <lb/>topology of the arrangement and, as is shown in [CP95], induces an isomorphism <lb/>on the corresponding wonderful models. Therefore the wonderful construction and <lb/>renormalization do not depend on these choices and we can work in a convenient <lb/>basis given by an adapted spanning tree. <lb/>In this basis v  G  is given by <lb/> v  G  ({x  e  }  e∈E(t)  ) = <lb/> e∈E(t) <lb/> △(x  e  ) <lb/> e∈E(G\t) <lb/> △( <lb/> e  ′  ∈E(te) <lb/> σ  t  (e <lb/> ′  )x  e  ′  ) <lb/>where t  e  is the path in t connecting the source and target vertices of e and σ  t  : <lb/> E(t) → {−1, +1} is determined by the chosen orientation of G. The point is that <lb/>for the divergent poset D in these coordinates x = <lb/> e∈E(t)  x  e  e we have A <lb/> ⊥ <lb/> g  = {x  e  = <lb/>0 | e ∈ E(t  g  )} for all g ∈ D. Dually this means that the elements in B|  e∈E(tg )  , <lb/>defined below, form a basis of A  g  . In other words, we have an adapted basis in the <lb/>sense of DeConcini-Procesi! <lb/>By duality B also defines a basis of X <lb/> G  . By abuse of notation we will denote <lb/>both bases by B -the meaning should always be clear from the context. This choice <lb/>of basis will be important when we study the pullback of v  G  onto the wonderful <lb/>model in the next section. <lb/>For G and other lattices there need not be an adapted spanning tree, but we can <lb/>always find an N -adapted spanning tree for any nested set. <lb/> Proposition 3.32. Let N be nested for some building set B in some lattice L ⊆ G. <lb/> Then there exists an N -adapted spanning tree. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body> Proof. The idea is the same as in Proposition 3.31. Start with the set M of maximal <lb/>elements in N and contract all other elements. Pick a spanning tree for the resulting <lb/>graphs. Proceed in the same manner with N \ M and repeat the process until all <lb/>of N has been exhausted. This produces a spanning forest t for ∪  γ∈N  γ, except if <lb/>there are g, h in N that are non-comparable and have non-empty intersection. In <lb/>this case we argue like in the proof of Lemma 3.26 to see that the join g ∨ h must <lb/>also be in B. But this is impossible since N is B-nested. In a last step contract all <lb/>elements of N in G and pick a spanning tree t <lb/> ′  for the resulting graph. The union <lb/> t ∪ t <lb/> ′  is then an N -adapted spanning tree for G. <lb/> Definition 3.33. Let G be at most logarithmic and N a B-nested set for some <lb/>building set B in a lattice L ⊆ G. Given an N -adapted spanning tree t define the <lb/>map ψ  t  as in Equation 5. Together with the linear forms ω  e  introduced in Section <lb/>2.2 we define an N -adapted basis of (X <lb/> G  ) <lb/>  *  by <lb/> B := {b <lb/> i <lb/>e  := (ω  e  • ψ  t  ) <lb/> i  | e ∈ E(t), i = 1, . . . , d}. <lb/> In such a basis the map p : (X <lb/> G  ) <lb/>  *  → N ∪ {G} from Definition 3.6 is then given by <lb/> p : x = <lb/> e∈E(t) <lb/>i=1,...,d <lb/> x <lb/> i <lb/>e  b <lb/> i <lb/>e  −→ min{g ∈ N ∪ {G} | x <lb/> i <lb/>e  = 0 for all e ∈ E(t \ t  g  )}. <lb/>A marking of an adapted basis is for every g ∈ N the choice of a b <lb/> ig <lb/>g  ∈ B with <lb/> p(b <lb/> ig <lb/>g  ) = g. Equivalently, we can view it as a labelling on the elements of N : <lb/> g −→ b <lb/> j <lb/>e  for e ∈ E(t ∩ (g \ N  &lt;g  )) and some j ∈ {1, . . . , d} <lb/> where g \ N  &lt;g  := g \ (h  1  ∪ · · · ∪ h  k  ) for {h  1  , . . . , h  k  } = {h ∈ N | h &lt; g} denotes the <lb/>graph g with all its lower bounds in N removed. <lb/>Finally, the partial order  on B that determines the local blow-up ρ  N ,B  is given <lb/>by <lb/> b <lb/> i <lb/>e  b <lb/> j <lb/>e  ′  ⇐⇒ e ∈ E(t  g  ), e <lb/> ′  ∈ E(t  g  ′  ) with g ⊆ g <lb/> ′  and b <lb/> j <lb/>e  ′  is marked. <lb/>This finishes all necessary definitions and from here on we could repeat the <lb/>construction of a wonderful model in purely combinatorial terms. In the divergent <lb/>case, A = D, we thus conclude that all ingredients are already determined by the <lb/>topology and subgraph structure of G. Therefore there is really no need for purely <lb/>geometric data to build an atlas for Y  B  . However obtained, now after the planting <lb/>has been done, it is time to reap the fruits and see what a wonderful model can do <lb/>for us. <lb/>4. Wonderful renormalization <lb/> Having constructed the wonderful models (Y  A  , β) for general arrangements A, we <lb/>now focus on the divergent and singular arrangements A = A  D  , A  G  of a connected <lb/>and at most logarithmic graph G. We study the pullback of v  G  onto the model <lb/>and the pole structure of its Laurent expansion, then define (local) renormalization <lb/>operators. Since Y  A  is non-orientable, we work from now on with distribution <lb/>densities. <lb/>Throughout this section let G be connected and at most logarithmic. To keep <lb/>the notation from exploding we drop the indices where possible. We write x = <lb/>(x  1  , . . . , x  n  ) for a point in X = M <lb/> n  where x  i  = (x <lb/> 1 <lb/> i  , . . . , x <lb/> d <lb/>i  ). The marking of <lb/>an adapted basis assigns individual coordinates to the elements of a nested set of <lb/></body>

			<page> 26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> graphs. We denote the marked elements by N ∋ g → x <lb/> ig <lb/> g  . If a vector x  g  ∈ M is <lb/>marked in this way, let <lb/>  g  denote the vector <lb/>ˆ <lb/> x  g  = (x <lb/> 1 <lb/> g  , . . . , x <lb/> i−1 <lb/>g  , 1, x <lb/> i+1 <lb/>g  , . . . , x <lb/> d <lb/>g  ) ∈ M. <lb/> The first two sections follow the exposition in [BBK10], especially the proofs <lb/>of Proposition 4.1 and Theorem 4.4. The difference lies in the emphasis on the <lb/>combinatorics of D and the role of adapted spanning trees in our formulation. In <lb/>addition, we correct some minor flaws and fill out missing details in the proofs. <lb/>4.1. The pullback of v  G  onto the wonderful model. Let (Y, β) be a wonderful <lb/>model and v = v  G  the Feynman distribution associated to a graph G. We start the <lb/>renormalization program by disassembling the pullback of v onto Y into a regular <lb/>and a singular part. <lb/> Proposition 4.1. Let N be B-nested for a building set B of D (or G) and B an <lb/>adapted, marked basis. In local coordinates on U  N ,B  the pullback of  <lb/> s  := v <lb/> s  |dx| <lb/> along β is given by <lb/> (6) <lb/>( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  N ,B  := (β <lb/>  *  ˜ <lb/> v <lb/> s  )  N ,B  = f <lb/> s <lb/> N ,B <lb/> g∈N <lb/> u <lb/> −1+dg+s(2−d)|E(g)| <lb/> g <lb/> |dx| <lb/> where u  g  (x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  ) = |x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  | <lb/> −1  and d  g  := dim A  g  = d(|E(g)| − h  1  (g)). <lb/> The map f  N ,B  : κ  N ,B  (U  N ,B  ) −→ R is in L <lb/> 1 <lb/> loc  (κ  N ,B  (U  N ,B  )) (or in C <lb/> ∞  (κ  N ,B  (U  N ,B  )) <lb/> if the singular arrangement is considered) but smooth in the variables x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  , g ∈ N . <lb/> As mentioned above, we drop indices to keep the notation minimal. Therefore, <lb/>and because we always work in local coordinates, from now on we do not indicate <lb/>local expressions by the subscript N , B. In addition, local coordinates are always <lb/>given by an adapted spanning tree t. <lb/> Proof. The crucial point here is that locally β is given by the map <lb/> ρ : X −→ X, <lb/> d <lb/> i=1 <lb/> e∈E(t) <lb/> x <lb/> i <lb/>e  b <lb/> i <lb/>e  → <lb/> d <lb/> i=1 <lb/> e∈E(t) <lb/> x  i <lb/> e  x  k <lb/>e ′ <lb/> x <lb/> k <lb/>e  ′  b <lb/> i <lb/>e  . <lb/> Recall the choice of coordinates given by t (Equation 5). In these coordinates <lb/> β <lb/>  *  v <lb/> s  (x) = v <lb/> s  (ρ(x)) = <lb/> ρ <lb/>  * <lb/> I <lb/>  *  △ <lb/> s⊗|E(G)| <lb/> (x) <lb/>= ρ <lb/>  * <lb/> e∈E(t) <lb/> △ <lb/> s  (x  e  ) <lb/> e∈E(G\t) <lb/> △ <lb/> s  ( <lb/> e  ′  ∈E(te) <lb/> σ  t  (e <lb/> ′  )x  e  ′  ) <lb/> = <lb/> e∈E(t) <lb/> △ <lb/> s  ( <lb/> p(xe)⊆g <lb/> x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  ˆ <lb/> x  e  ) <lb/> e∈E(G\t) <lb/> △ <lb/> s  ( <lb/> e  ′  ∈E(te) <lb/> p(x  e ′  )⊆g <lb/> x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  σ  t  (e <lb/> ′  )ˆ x  e  ′  ) <lb/>wherê <lb/> x  e  := (x <lb/> 1 <lb/> e  , . . . , <lb/> ig <lb/> 1 , . . . , x <lb/> d <lb/>e  ) if x  e  has a marked component. Since △ is homo-<lb/>geneous of degree (2 − d), we can pull out all the factors x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  in the first product of <lb/> △&apos;s, so that the kernel of <lb/> s  (x) is given by <lb/> e∈E(t) <lb/> ( <lb/> p(xe)⊆g <lb/> x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  ) <lb/> s(2−d)  △ <lb/> s  (ˆ x  e  ) <lb/> e∈E(G\t) <lb/> △ <lb/> s  ( <lb/> e  ′  ∈E(te) <lb/> p(x  e ′  )⊆g <lb/> x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  σ  t  (e <lb/> ′  )ˆ x  e  ′  ). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body> In the second factor we can pull out a factor x <lb/> ig <lb/> g  if it appears in every term in the <lb/>sum, i.e. if t  e  is a subgraph of some g ∈ N . But this is equivalent to e ∈ E(g) <lb/> because t is an adapted spanning tree. Thus, x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  appears exactly |E(g)|-times and <lb/>we conclude <lb/> w <lb/> s  (x) = f <lb/> s  (x) <lb/> g∈N <lb/> (x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  ) <lb/> s(2−d)|E(g)|  . <lb/> Under the coordinate transformation ρ every dx  e  = <lb/> i=1,...,d  dx <lb/> i <lb/>e  transforms into <lb/> ρ <lb/>  *  dx  e  = <lb/> (x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  ) <lb/> d−1  dx  e  if x  e  contains a marked component, <lb/>(x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  ) <lb/> d  dx  e <lb/> if x  e  has no marked component. <lb/>How many x  e  are scaled by the same x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  ? As many as there are edges in E(g). <lb/> Therefore, there are in total (dim A  g  − 1) factors and the measure <lb/> |dx| = | <lb/> e∈E(t),i=1,...,d <lb/> dx <lb/> i <lb/>e  | <lb/> tranforms into <lb/> ρ <lb/>  *  |dx| = <lb/> g∈N <lb/> |x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  | <lb/> dim Ag −1  |dx|. <lb/> Putting everything together we conclude <lb/>˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  (x) = f <lb/> s  (x) <lb/> g∈N <lb/> |x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  | <lb/> −1+dg+s(2−d)|E(g)|  |dx|. <lb/> For the divergent lattice the exponents of |x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  | are given by −1 + d  g  (s − 1) because <lb/> d|h  1  (g)| = 2|E(g)| and d  g  = dim A  g  = d(|E(g)|−h  1  (g)) (cf. the proof of Proposition <lb/>2.9). <lb/>It remains to show that f ∈ L <lb/> 1 <lb/>loc  (κ(U )) or C <lb/> ∞  (κ(U )), respectively. Recall the <lb/>definition of U = U  N ,B  = X \ ∪  γ∈B  Z  γ  where Z  γ  is the vanishing locus of the <lb/>polynomials P  v  for v ∈ X <lb/>  *  such that p(v) = γ. For the singular arrangement <lb/>every building set B must contain all subgraphs consisting of a single edge. But <lb/>for these elements of B the Z  γ  = Z  e  are precisely the sets where an entire sum <lb/> e  ′  ∈E(te)  σ  t  (e <lb/> ′  )x  e  ′  expressing an edge e of G vanishes. Since all functions △ are <lb/>smooth off the origin it follows that f is a smooth function. The same reasoning <lb/>works for the divergent arrangement. Every building set of D must contain all <lb/>irreducible subgraphs. In addition, every element of D is built out of elements of <lb/> I(D) by the join operation (i.e. using ∪). Therefore, as in the singular case, it <lb/>follows that linear combinations expressing edges in any divergent subgraph can <lb/>not vanish on U . The map f fails to be smooth only at propagators of edges that <lb/>do not lie in some element of B. But by the proof of Proposition 2.9 we know <lb/>that there f is still locally integrable, hence f ∈ L <lb/> 1 <lb/>loc  (κ(U )). Smoothness in the <lb/>marked elements x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  , g ∈ N , follows from the simple fact that in the definition <lb/>of f already all marked elements have been pulled out of the linear combinations <lb/>expressing edges in G. If one such expression would vanish at x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  = 0, then all x  e  ′ <lb/> were scaled by x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  and this factor would have been absorbed into the exponent of <lb/> u  g  . Therefore no argument in the product of △&apos;s can vanish at x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  = 0. <lb/></body>

			<page> 28 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> 4.2. Laurent expansion. From now on we will consider the divergent lattice D <lb/> only. In this case we define u <lb/> s <lb/> g  (x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  ) := |x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  | <lb/> −1+dg(1−s)  and for a finite product of <lb/>maps F  i  , i ∈ I, we write F  I  := <lb/> i∈I  F  i  . Then we have under the assumptions of <lb/>Proposition 4.1 <lb/>˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  = f <lb/> s <lb/> g∈N <lb/> u <lb/> s <lb/>g  |dx| = f <lb/> s  u <lb/> s <lb/> N  |dx|. <lb/> To define local renormalization operators we need a better understanding of the <lb/>pole structure of <lb/> s  . As it turns out, this structure is already encoded in the geom-<lb/>etry of the exceptional divisor E and reflects the structure of the divergent lattice D. <lb/> It will be useful to consider first the case of primitive graphs. In this case Y <lb/> is the blow-up of the origin in X, covered by charts U  i  where i runs from 1 to dn <lb/> (corresponding to all possible markings of an adapted basis). We already know from <lb/>the extension theory for distributions that the Laurent expansion around s = 1 of <lb/> s  has a simple pole with its residue given by <lb/>˜ <lb/> a  −1  = − <lb/> 2 <lb/> d  G <lb/> f δ  E  . <lb/> Here δ  E  is a density on Y , the delta distribution centered on E (cf. [GS64]), locally <lb/>in U  i  given by the delta distribution in the marked coordinate x <lb/> i  , i.e. <lb/> δ  E  |ϕ <lb/> loc. <lb/> = <lb/> dx δ(x  i  )ϕ(x). <lb/>Pairing ã  −1  with the characteristic function χ of Y produces a projective integral <lb/> ã  −1  |χ = − <lb/> 2 <lb/> d  G <lb/> E <lb/> f. <lb/> Recall from Section 3.1.1 the definition of induced charts (V  i  , φ  i  ) for E. Since any <lb/>such chart covers E up to a set of measure zero, it suffices to do this integral in one <lb/>of them. Thus, <lb/> E <lb/> f = <lb/> dˆ f (ˆ x) <lb/> where dˆ  = dx <lb/> 1  ∧ · · · ∧ <lb/> dx  i  ∧ · · · ∧ dx <lb/> nd  for some i ∈ {1, . . . , dn}. <lb/> Definition 4.2 (Period of a primitive graph). Let G be primitive. The period <lb/> P(G) of G is defined as the projective integral <lb/> P(G) := ˜ a  −1  |χ = − <lb/> 2 <lb/> d  G <lb/> E <lb/> f. <lb/> For more on periods see the overview in [Sch10]. Until recently it was believed <lb/>that all periods in massless φ <lb/> 4  -theory (i.e. d = 4 and all vertices of the Feynman <lb/>diagram corresponding to G are 4-valent) are rational combinations of multiple <lb/>zeta values. But counterexamples [BD13] have proven this false, relating a better <lb/>understanding of these periods to deep questions in algebraic geometry [Bro10]. <lb/>In the Laurent expansion of <lb/> s  for non-primitive G terms corresponding to <lb/>contracted graphs will appear. Since we work in local coordinates indexed by B-<lb/> nested sets, we need a more sophisticated (local) contraction operation on graphs: <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body> Definition 4.3. Let g ⊆ G and P ⊆ D. The contraction relative to P is defined as <lb/> g//P := <lb/> g/( <lb/> γ∈P&lt;g  γ) <lb/> if g ∈ P, <lb/> g/(g ∩ <lb/> γ∈P&lt;g  γ) else. <lb/>Especially important will be the contraction relative to nested sets. The reader <lb/>should think of it as a local version of the contraction in the definition of the <lb/>coproduct in the Hopf algebra of Feynman graphs. It will show up in all formulas <lb/>that include the coproduct in their usual formulation, say in momentum space. <lb/>Note that for g ⊆ G the &quot; normal &quot; contraction G/g is included in this definition <lb/>as contraction of G with respect to the nested set N = {g, G}. Moreover, if N is <lb/>nested and g ∈ N or all elements of N are contained in g, then g//N is at most <lb/>logarithmic as well. For a general discussion of which classes of graphs are closed <lb/>under contraction we refer the reader to [BK08]. <lb/> Theorem 4.4. Let Y be a wonderful model for some building set B of D. Let <lb/> s  = β <lb/>  *  ˜ <lb/> v <lb/> s  be the pullback of the density  <lb/> s  ∈ ˜ <lb/> D <lb/> ′  (X) onto Y . Then: <lb/> (1) The Laurent expansion of  <lb/> s  at s = 1 has a pole of order N where N is <lb/>the cardinality of the largest B-nested set. <lb/> (2) The coefficients  ã  k  in the principal part of the Laurent expansion <lb/>ñ <lb/> w <lb/> s  = <lb/> −N ≤k <lb/>  ã  k  (s − 1) <lb/> k <lb/> are densities with (k ≤ −1) <lb/> supp  ã  k  = <lb/> |N |=−k <lb/> E  N  . <lb/> (3) Consider the irreducible elements I(D) as building set. Assume G ∈ I(D). <lb/> Let N be a maximal nested set and denote by χ the constant function on <lb/>the wonderful model Y  I(D)  . Then for N = |N | <lb/>˜ a  −N  |χ = <lb/> |M|=N <lb/> γ∈M <lb/> P(γ//M). <lb/> Proof. 1. This follows from the local expression for <lb/> s  . Using Formula (1) we have <lb/>˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s loc. <lb/> = f <lb/> s  u <lb/> s <lb/> N  |dx| = f <lb/> s <lb/> g∈N <lb/> − <lb/> 2 <lb/> d  g <lb/> δ  g  (s − 1) <lb/> −1  + u <lb/> s <lb/>g♥ <lb/> |dx|. <lb/> Since u <lb/> s <lb/>g♥  is regular in s, the highest pole order is given by |N |. <lb/> 2. Expand u <lb/> s <lb/> ♥  ∈ D <lb/> ′  (R) into a Taylor series at s = 1, <lb/> u <lb/> s <lb/> ♥  = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=0 <lb/> u  k  (s − 1) <lb/> k <lb/> where the distributions u  k  are given by <lb/>(7) <lb/> u  k  : ϕ → <lb/> dx |x| <lb/> −1  log <lb/> k  (|x|) <lb/> ϕ(x) − θ(1 − |x|)ϕ(0) <lb/> . <lb/></body>

			<page> 30 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> In the following we write θ  g  for the map x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  → θ <lb/> 1 − |x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  | <lb/> in all coefficients of the <lb/>expansion of the regular part of u <lb/> s <lb/>g  . Expanding f <lb/> s  gives <lb/> f <lb/> s  = exp(log(f <lb/> s  )) = f exp <lb/> (s − 1) log(f ) <lb/> = f <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=0 <lb/> log <lb/> k  (f ) <lb/> k! <lb/> (s − 1) <lb/> k  . <lb/> Fix a B-nested set N . To determine the lower pole parts in the local expression for <lb/> s  we multiply all series u <lb/> s <lb/>g♥  for g ∈ N and reorder the sum. Denote by (u  g  )  l  the <lb/> l-th order coefficient of the expansion of u <lb/> s <lb/>g  . Then for i in {1, . . . , N } the kernel of <lb/> ã  −i  is given by <lb/> N −i−1 <lb/> k=0 <lb/> f log <lb/> k  (f ) <lb/> k! <lb/>  N −i−1 <lb/> j=k <lb/> L⊆N <lb/>|L|=i+j <lb/> γ∈L <lb/> (− <lb/>2 <lb/> d  γ <lb/> )δ  γ <lb/> η∈N \L <lb/>{lη∈N| <lb/> η∈N \L  lη =j−k} <lb/> (u  η  )  lη <lb/> (8) <lb/>+ <lb/> f log <lb/> N −i  (f ) <lb/>(N − i)! <lb/> γ∈N <lb/> (− <lb/>2 <lb/> d  γ <lb/> )δ  γ  . <lb/> Recall that locally E  g  is given by x <lb/> ιg <lb/>g  = 0 and E  I  ⊆ E  J  for J ⊆ I ⊆ N . Therefore <lb/>the support of ã  −i  is given by the (k = j = 0)-summand in (8), carrying the product <lb/>of i δ-distributions in the marked coordinates of an i-element subset of N . Varying <lb/>over all B-nested sets N (and the marking of B) the same holds for all i-element <lb/> subsets of any nested set. Thus, from the expansion formula (8) we conclude that <lb/>the densities ã  −i  are supported on <lb/> |N |=i <lb/> γ∈N <lb/> E  γ <lb/> = <lb/> |N |=i <lb/> E  N  . <lb/> 3. This follows essentially from two assertions: First, if we view the pairing of a <lb/>product of delta distributions (δ  g  := δ(x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  )) with a function ϕ as an operator δ  N  , <lb/>locally given by <lb/> δ  N  : ϕ ∈ L <lb/> 1 <lb/> loc  (κ(U )) −→ <lb/> γ∈N <lb/> δ  γ  [ϕ] ∈ L <lb/> 1 <lb/> loc  (κ(U ∩ E  N  )), <lb/>then for f the regular part of the pullback of v <lb/> s  we have <lb/>(9) <lb/> δ  N  [f ] = <lb/> γ∈N <lb/> f  γ//N  . <lb/> Here f  g//N  is obtained from f by setting all marked elements corresponding to <lb/>graphs in N  &lt;g  to zero. It equals the regular part of the local pullback of v <lb/> s <lb/>g//N <lb/> onto the wonderful model for the graph g//N in the nested set N <lb/> ′  = {g//N } <lb/> (g//N is primitive!). For a precise definition and the proof of this assertion we <lb/>refer to Section 5, Theorem 5.3, where this is elaborated in a much more general <lb/>case. The important point here is that δ  N  [f ] is a product of maps f  g//N  , each one <lb/>depending only on the set of variables {x  e  } with e in E(t  g  ) \ E(N  &lt;g  ), minus all <lb/>marked elements. <lb/>The second assertion is that in every maximal I(D)-nested set all contracted <lb/>graphs g//N are primitive. Note that if G is divergent and irreducible, it must <lb/>be contained in every maximal nested set. To prove the assertion let g ∈ N and <lb/>assume g//N is not primitive. This means there is an h ∈ D with either h ⊆ g//N <lb/> or h//N ⊆ g//N . In both cases we can assume that h is irreducible (if not, then <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body> h is the union of irreducible elements and we do the following for every irreducible <lb/>component of h). Then the set N <lb/> ′  = N ∪{h} is also nested if h satisfies the following <lb/>property: For all g <lb/> ′  in N that are incomparable to g the join h∨g <lb/> ′  = h∪g <lb/> ′  must not <lb/>lie in I(D). But if there is g <lb/> ′  ∈ N , incomparable to g, with h ≤ g <lb/> ′  then g and g <lb/> ′  have <lb/>both h as common subgraph. By Lemma 3.26 this implies that g ∨ g <lb/> ′  is irreducible, <lb/>showing that g and g <lb/> ′  cannot both lie in N because N is I(D)-nested. If g//N <lb/> ′ <lb/> is still not primitive, repeat the process until all contracted graphs are primitive. <lb/>The resulting nested set N <lb/> ′  is then really maximal: If adding another graph would <lb/>not violate the property of being nested, then it must necessarily be disjoint from <lb/>all g ∈ N <lb/> ′  (otherwise some g//N is not primitive) and this is impossible due to G <lb/> being in N <lb/> ′  . <lb/>For G ∈ I(D) all edges of G lie in some divergent subgraph (if not, say for one <lb/>edge e, then contract all divergent subgraphs. The resulting graph is primitively <lb/>divergent and contains e). Thus, in every maximal nested set N all edges of an <lb/>adapted spanning tree t correspond to some element of N and by Definition 3.8 we <lb/>have U  N ,B  = X for all maximal nested sets N . Let N be such a maximal nested <lb/>set. Using 2. and the first assertion we have locally in U <lb/> ˜ a  −N  |χ <lb/> loc. <lb/> = <lb/> κ(U) <lb/> dx <lb/> γ∈N <lb/> (− <lb/>2 <lb/> d  γ <lb/> )δ  γ  [f ] = <lb/> γ∈N <lb/> (− <lb/>2 <lb/> d  γ <lb/> ) <lb/> κ(V ) <lb/> dˆ δ  N  [f ] <lb/>= <lb/> κ(V ) <lb/> dˆ <lb/> γ∈N <lb/> (− <lb/>2 <lb/> d  γ <lb/> )f  γ//N  . <lb/> Herê <lb/> x denotes {x  e  }  e∈E(t)  minus all marked elements and V = V  N ,B  is the chart <lb/>domain for local coordinates on E  N  , obtained by restriction of the chart κ (cf. <lb/>Section 3.1.1). Since it covers E  N  up to a set of measure zero (cf. Definition 4.2), <lb/>integration in a single chart suffices. Moreover, two components of the exceptional <lb/>divisor E  N  and E  M  have non-empty intersection if and only if N ∪M is nested. But <lb/>this is impossible due to maximality of N . Therefore we can sum the contributions <lb/>from charts given by different maximal nested sets to obtain the global result <lb/> ã  −N  |χ = <lb/> N <lb/> κ(V ) <lb/> dˆ <lb/> γ∈N <lb/> (− <lb/>2 <lb/> d  γ <lb/> )f  γ//N <lb/> where the sum is over all maximal nested sets. <lb/>Finally, since all f  γ//N  depend on mutually disjoint sets of variables, the integral <lb/>factorizes and since restricting κ|  V  further to {ˆ   e  }  e∈E(tγ )  is a local chart for E  γ//N  , <lb/>we conclude that <lb/> N <lb/> κ(V ) <lb/> dˆ <lb/> γ∈N <lb/> (− <lb/>2 <lb/> d  γ <lb/> )f  γ//N  = <lb/> N <lb/> γ∈N <lb/> E  γ//N <lb/> (− <lb/>2 <lb/> d  γ <lb/> )f  γ//N  = <lb/> N <lb/> γ∈N <lb/> P(γ//N ). <lb/> This theorem is a first hint at the Hopf algebraic formulation of the renormal-<lb/>ization group (see [Kre13], [CK01]). It shows that the poles of <lb/> s  are not arbitrary <lb/>densities but reflect the combinatorics of D in a special way. The highest order <lb/>pole is completely determined by the structure of D. For the poles of lower order <lb/>the same holds in a weaker version; they are supported on components of E whose <lb/>stratification is given by the combinatorial structure of D as well. <lb/></body>

			<page> 32 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> 4.3. Renormalization. With the main result of the previous section we are now <lb/>able to tackle the renormalization problem. Since all poles of <lb/> s  live on the com-<lb/>ponents of the exceptional divisor, we can get rid of them using local subtractions <lb/>depending on the direction such a pole is approached. These directions are encoded <lb/>by nested sets, so that we will employ local versions of the previously defined renor-<lb/>malization maps r  1  and r  ν  , depending on the chosen coordinate system given by <lb/> B-nested sets and markings of an adapted basis B. From now on we consider only <lb/>the minimal or maximal building sets in the divergent lattice D. <lb/> Definition 4.5 ((Local) minimal subtraction). Let R  1  denote the collection of <lb/>renormalization maps {R <lb/> N ,B <lb/> 1 <lb/> } for N a B-nested set and B an adapted basis (more <lb/>precisely, the marking since the basis is fixed). R <lb/> N ,B <lb/> 1 <lb/> removes the poles in the <lb/>coordinates associated to the marked elements, i.e. <lb/> R  1  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ] <lb/> loc. <lb/> = R <lb/> N ,B <lb/> 1 <lb/> [f <lb/> s  ˜ <lb/> u <lb/> s <lb/> N  ] := f <lb/> s <lb/> g∈N <lb/> r  1  [u <lb/> s <lb/>g  ]|dx|. <lb/>Recall from Section 2 that r  1  [u <lb/> s <lb/>g  ] = (u <lb/> s <lb/>g  )  ♥  , so there are no poles anymore and we <lb/>can take the limit s → 1 to obtain a well defined density on Y . <lb/>The next definition introduces a renormalization operator that produces a den-<lb/>sity for s in a complex neighborhood of 1. It should be thought of as a smooth <lb/>version of minimal subtraction. <lb/> Definition 4.6 ((Local) subtraction at fixed conditions). Let R  ν  denote the col-<lb/>lection of renormalization maps {R <lb/> N ,B <lb/>ν <lb/> } where N is a B-nested sets and B marked. <lb/>The symbol ν = {ν <lb/> N ,B <lb/>g <lb/> }  g∈N  stands for a collection of smooth functions on κ(U ). <lb/>Each ν <lb/> N ,B <lb/>g <lb/> depends only on the coordinates x  e  with e ∈ E(t) ∩ E(g \ N  &lt;g  ) and <lb/>satisfies <lb/> ν <lb/> N ,B <lb/>g <lb/> |  x <lb/> ig <lb/> g  =0 <lb/> = 1. <lb/>Furthermore, it is compactly supported in all other directions. <lb/>Similarly to R  1  the operator R  ν  is defined by <lb/> R  ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ] <lb/> loc. <lb/> = R <lb/> N ,B <lb/>ν <lb/> [f <lb/> s  ˜ <lb/> u <lb/> s <lb/> N  ] := f <lb/> s <lb/> g∈N <lb/> r  ν <lb/> N ,B <lb/>g <lb/> [u <lb/> s <lb/>g  ]|dx|. <lb/> Remark. In contrast to the definition of r  ν  given in Section 2 the maps ν  g  (we <lb/>drop the index (N , B) from here on, as well as the dependence of the opera-<lb/>tors R on B) are not only test functions in the marked coordinate x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  , but in <lb/>all {x  e  }  e∈E(t)∩E(g\N&lt;g )  . This is to ensure that the counterterms are really well-<lb/>defined densities in a neighborhood of s = 1. There is some ambivalence in defining <lb/>them, so it pays of to be careful at this point. <lb/>We introduce another useful expression for R  ν  : For K ⊆ N write ν  K  for the <lb/>product <lb/> γ∈K  ν  γ  . In a chart U the operators R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  act oñ <lb/> w <lb/> s  by <lb/> R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ] = <lb/> K⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K|  ν  K  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  EK <lb/> where E  K  = <lb/> γ∈K  E  γ  ⊆ E is the component of the exceptional divisor associated <lb/>to the nested set K ⊆ N . This is to be understood in the following way. First <lb/>restrict the regular part f <lb/> s  of <lb/> s  and the test function ϕ to κ(U ∩ E  K  ), then pull <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body> this product back onto U , then multiply by u <lb/> s <lb/> N  and ν  K  and finally integrate, in <lb/>formulae <lb/> ν  K  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  EK  |ϕ = (p  K  )  *  (ν  K  u <lb/> s <lb/> N  |dx|)|δ  K  [f <lb/> s  ϕ]. <lb/> Here p  K  is the local expression of the canonical projection π : Y → E  K  and δ  K  is <lb/>the corresponding map D(Y ) → D(E  K  ). For K = {g  1  , . . . , g  k  } both are given by <lb/> p  g1,...,g  k  : x → (x <lb/> 1 <lb/>1  , . . . , x <lb/> ig  1 <lb/> g1  , . . . , x <lb/> ig  k <lb/> g  k  , . . . , x <lb/> d <lb/>n  )|  x <lb/> ig 1 <lb/> g 1 <lb/> ,...,x <lb/> ig <lb/>k <lb/>g k <lb/> =0 <lb/> , <lb/>δ  g1,...,g  k  : ϕ → ϕ|  x <lb/> ig 1 <lb/> g 1 <lb/> ,...,x <lb/> ig <lb/>k <lb/>g k <lb/> =0 <lb/> . <lb/> Note that δ  K  [f <lb/> s  ϕ] remains compactly supported in the coordinates associated to <lb/> G \ ∪  γ∈K  N  &lt;γ  . On the other hand, ν  K  is compactly supported in the coordinates <lb/>associated to G ∩ (∪  γ∈K  (γ \ N  &lt;γ  )). But these sets cover G and therefore the coun-<lb/>terterms ν  K  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  EK  are well defined densities in all coordinates except the marked <lb/>elements (cf. the proof of Theorem 11). The notation is chosen to suggest that <lb/>( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  EK  can be thought of as the &quot; restriction &quot; of <lb/> s  onto E  K  and the symbol &quot; · &quot; in <lb/> ν  K  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  EK  is used to highlight the fact that this expression differs from the usual <lb/>product of distributions and smooth functions. We call it &quot; product &quot; because it is <lb/>linear and multiplicative in ν. Although this notation might seem awkward, it will <lb/>turn out be very useful in the next section! <lb/>The following lemma will be needed to compare the renormalized densities ob-<lb/>tained by choosing different maps ν. <lb/> Lemma 4.7. Let g, h ∈ D. The maps p  g,h  and δ  g,h  both fulfill the following &quot; com-<lb/>mutation rules &quot; : <lb/> p  g,h  = p <lb/> g <lb/>g,h  • p  g  = p <lb/> h <lb/>g,h  • p  h  , <lb/>δ  g,h  = δ <lb/> g <lb/>g,h  • δ  g  = δ <lb/> h <lb/>g,h  • δ  h  , <lb/> where locally p <lb/> g <lb/>g,h  : κ(U ∩ E  g  ) −→ κ(U ∩ E  g,h  ) is defined by <lb/> (x <lb/> 1 <lb/>1  , . . . , ˆ <lb/> x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  , . . . , x <lb/> d <lb/>n  ) → (x <lb/> 1 <lb/>1  , . . . , ˆ <lb/> x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  , . . . , ˆ <lb/> x <lb/> i  h <lb/> h  , . . . , x <lb/> d <lb/>n  ) <lb/> and δ <lb/> g <lb/>g,h  : D(κ(U ∩ E  g  )) → D(κ(U ∩ E  g,h  )) by <lb/> ϕ |  x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  =0 <lb/> → ϕ |  x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  =x <lb/> i h <lb/>h <lb/> =0 <lb/> . <lb/> Proof. Clear from the definition of both maps. <lb/> Obviously this property generalizes to the case where instead of {g, h} a finite <lb/>subset of a nested set is considered, e.g. <lb/> p  g1,...,g  k  = p <lb/> g1,...,g  k−1 <lb/> g1,...,g  k <lb/> • · · · • p <lb/> g1 <lb/>g1,g2  • p  g1 <lb/> and similarly for δ  g1,...,g  k  . <lb/>Both renormalization operations produce well-defined densities at s = 1 as is <lb/>shown in the next proposition. <lb/> Proposition 4.8. Let (Y, β) be the minimal or maximal wonderful model for the <lb/>divergent lattice D. Then R  1  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ]|  s=1  defines a density on Y , while R  ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ] is a <lb/>density-valued holomorphic function for all s in a neighborhood of 1 in C. <lb/></body>

			<page> 34 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> Proof. Note that from the proof of Theorem 4.4 it follows in particular that <lb/> s  is <lb/>really a density on Y . By the same argumentation we are able to conclude from <lb/>expression (4.3) for the counterterms in R  ν  that they are all densities for s in a <lb/>neighborhood of 1: Every subtraction term has the same combination of u <lb/> s <lb/> N  and f <lb/> s  , <lb/>transforming under a change of coordinates according to the definition of densities. <lb/>In the case of minimal subtraction, by Theorem 4.4 and the definition of r  1  , all <lb/>poles of <lb/> s  have been discarded. Therefore, R  1  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ]|  s=1  is a finite density. From the <lb/>Taylor expansion of u <lb/> s <lb/> ♥  (Equation (7)) it follows that R  1  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ] fails to be a density <lb/>for s  = 1 because the u <lb/> s <lb/>g  do not transform correctly under a change of coordinates. <lb/>It remains to show the finiteness of R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ] for all B-nested sets N . We argue <lb/>by induction on the cardinality of |N |. First consider the case where the nested set <lb/>consists of a single graph, N = {g} for some g ⊆ G. Let x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  denote the marked <lb/>element, otherwise we drop all indices. Then by Definition 4.6 <lb/> R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ]|ϕ =  ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  |ϕ − ν · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  Eg  |ϕ, <lb/> ν = ν  g  depending on all x  e  with e ∈ E(t  g  ). We expand both summands into their <lb/>Laurent series (focusing on the principle part only) to get <lb/> s  |ϕ = <lb/> dx |x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  | <lb/> −1+dg (1−s)  f <lb/> s  (x)ϕ(x) <lb/>= <lb/> dx <lb/> ig <lb/>g  |x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  | <lb/> −1+dg(1−s) <lb/> dˆ f <lb/> s  (x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  , ˆ <lb/> x)ϕ(x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  , ˆ <lb/> x) <lb/> =: <lb/> dx <lb/> ig <lb/>g  |x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  | <lb/> −1+dg (1−s)  F (s, x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  ). <lb/>Using Formula (1) from Section 2, <lb/> ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  |ϕ = − <lb/> 2 <lb/> d  g <lb/> F (s, 0)(s − 1) <lb/> −1 <lb/> + <lb/> dx <lb/> ig <lb/>g  |x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  | <lb/> −1+dg(1−s) <lb/> F (s, x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  ) − θ  g  (x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  )F (s, 0) <lb/> . <lb/> For the counterterm we have <lb/> ν · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  Eg  |ϕ = <lb/> dx |x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  | <lb/> −1+dg (1−s)  ν(x  tg  ) <lb/> f <lb/> s  (x)ϕ(x) <lb/> |  x <lb/> ig <lb/> g  =0 <lb/> = <lb/> dx <lb/> ig <lb/>g  |x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  | <lb/> −1+dg(1−s) <lb/> dˆ ν(x  tg  )f <lb/> s  (0, ˆ <lb/> x)ϕ(0, ˆ <lb/> x) <lb/> =: <lb/> dx <lb/> ig <lb/>g  |x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  | <lb/> −1+dg(1−s)  G  ν  (s, x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  ). <lb/>In the same way as above we get <lb/> ν · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  Eg  |ϕ = − <lb/> 2 <lb/> d  g <lb/> G  ν  (s, 0)(s − 1) <lb/> −1 <lb/> + <lb/> dx <lb/> ig <lb/>g  |x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  | <lb/> −1+dg(1−s)  (G  ν  (s, x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  ) − θ  g  (x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  )G  ν  (s, 0)). <lb/>Since ν(x  tg  )|  x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  =0 <lb/> = 1, F (s, 0) = G(s, 0) and the pole cancels in the difference. <lb/>Therefore, R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ]|ϕ is finite for all ϕ ∈ D(κ(U )). <lb/>Now let N be nested and h ⊆ G such that N <lb/> ′  := N ∪ {h} is also nested. For <lb/> K ⊆ N set K <lb/> ′  := K ∪ {h}. Assume h to be minimal in N <lb/> ′  (if not choose another <lb/>minimal element). We want to show finiteness of <lb/> s  in κ <lb/> ′  (U <lb/> ′  ) for U <lb/> ′  = U  N  ′  ,B  with <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body> B marked for N plus an additional marking for the element h (since h is minimal, all <lb/>markings of N <lb/> ′  are of this form). By induction hypothesis R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ] is a well-defined <lb/>density on κ(U ) for all s in a neighborhood of 1 in C. In [CP95] it is shown that <lb/> U <lb/> ′  is the blow-up of the proper transform of A <lb/> ⊥ <lb/> h  in U  N ,B  . By minimality of h this <lb/>blow-up β  h  is locally given by ρ  h  scaling all {x  e  }  e∈E(t  h  )  with x <lb/> i  h <lb/> h  . Moreover, the <lb/>chart κ <lb/> ′  is just the inverse of the composition of ρ  h  with Γ(π  B  ) • ρ  N  . The pullback <lb/>of the density R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ] along this blow-up has now an additional divergence in the <lb/>coordinate x <lb/> i  h <lb/> h  . Therefore one more subtraction is needed to obtain a finite density <lb/>on U <lb/> ′  (the index N stands for the local expression in U ), <lb/> R  ν  h <lb/> β <lb/>  * <lb/> h  R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/> N  ] <lb/> = R  ν  h <lb/>  <lb/> β <lb/>  * <lb/> h <lb/> K⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K|  ν  K  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/> N  )  EK <lb/>  <lb/> =  * <lb/> We compute the pullbacks locally in U , the power counting that produces u <lb/> s <lb/>h  works <lb/>exactly like in the proof of Proposition 4.1. <lb/> ρ <lb/>  * <lb/> h  (ν  K  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/> N  )  EK  )|ϕ = <lb/> (ρ <lb/>  * <lb/> h  dx)(ν  K  • ρ  h  )(u <lb/> s <lb/> N  • ρ  h  )p <lb/>  * <lb/>K  δ  K  [(f <lb/> s <lb/> N  • ρ  h  )ϕ] <lb/>= <lb/> dx ν  K  u <lb/> s <lb/> N  u <lb/> s <lb/>h  p <lb/>  * <lb/>K  δ  K  [(f <lb/> s <lb/> N  ′  )ϕ] <lb/>=ν  K  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/> N  ′  )  EK  |ϕ. <lb/> Thus, <lb/> *  = <lb/> K⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K|  ν  K  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/> N  ′  )  EK  − ν  h  · <lb/> K⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K|  ν  K  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/> N  ′  )  E  K∪{h} <lb/> = <lb/> K⊆N  ′ <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K|  ν  K  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/> N  ′  )  EK <lb/> =R <lb/> N <lb/> ′ <lb/> ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/> N  ′  ] <lb/>where we have used minimality of h again, <lb/> ν  h  · (ν  K  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  EK  )  E  h  |ϕ = <lb/> dx u <lb/> s <lb/> N  ν  h  ν  K  |  x <lb/> i h <lb/>h  =0 <lb/> (f <lb/> s  ϕ) |  x <lb/> i K <lb/>K  =x <lb/> i h <lb/>h  =0 <lb/> = <lb/> dx u <lb/> s <lb/> N  ν  K  ′  (f <lb/> s  ϕ) |  x <lb/> i K <lb/>K  =x <lb/> i h <lb/>h  =0 <lb/> = (ν  K  ′  ) · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  E  K ′  |ϕ. <lb/> We see that both densities coincide and the proposition is proven. <lb/> Both renormalization operators have another property that every sensible renor-<lb/>malization should have; they commute with multiplication by smooth functions. <lb/> Lemma 4.9. Let f ∈ C <lb/> ∞  (κ(U )), then <lb/> R <lb/> N <lb/> 0  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/> N  f ] = f R <lb/> N <lb/> 0  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/> N  ] <lb/> R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/> N  f ] = f R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/> N  ]. <lb/> Proof. Clear from the definition of both operators. Under the renormalization <lb/>operation the regular part of the density is treated as a test function which is also <lb/>the definition of the product of smooth functions and densities. <lb/> Finally, we are able to state a solution of the renormalization problem. <lb/></body>

			<page> 36 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> Definition 4.10 (Renormalized Feynman rules). Let R denote one of the renor-<lb/>malization operators R  1  or R  ν  on the wonderful model (Y  B  , β) for B = I(D) or D. <lb/> Define the renormalized Feynman distribution by <lb/> R[v  G  ] := β  *  R[ ˜ <lb/> w  G  ]|  s=1  . <lb/> Then the renormalized Feynman rules are given by the map <lb/>Φ  R  : G −→ (X <lb/> G  , R(v  G  )). <lb/>The pair (X <lb/> G  , R(v  G  )) can now be evaluated at ϕ ∈ D(X), <lb/> (eval  ϕ  • Φ  R  ) (G) = R[v  G  ]|ϕ <lb/>= β  *  R[ ˜ <lb/> w  G  ]|  s=1  | ϕ <lb/> = R[ ˜ <lb/> w  G  ]|  s=1  | β <lb/>  *  ϕ. <lb/> To carry out the evaluation at ϕ we choose a partition of unity {χ  i  }  i∈{(N ,B)}  on <lb/> Y  B  , subordinate to the covering {U  i  }  i∈{(N .B)}  . Write π  i  for χ  i  • κ <lb/> −1 <lb/> i  . Then <lb/> R[ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/>G  ]|  s=1  | β <lb/>  *  ϕ = <lb/> i <lb/> π  i  (R[ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/>G  ])  i  |  s=1  | ϕ • ρ  i  . <lb/> To see that this definition does not depend on the chosen partition of unity let {χ <lb/> ′ <lb/> j  } <lb/> denote another partition, also subordinate to the {U  j  }  j∈{(N ,B)}  . Then <lb/> i <lb/> π  i  (R[ ˜ <lb/> w  G  ])  i  |  s=1  | ϕ • ρ  i  <lb/> = <lb/> i <lb/> supp(πi) <lb/> dx <lb/> K⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K|  u  N  ν  K  δ  K  [f  i  (ϕ • ρ  i  )π  i  ] <lb/>= <lb/> i <lb/> supp(πi) <lb/> dx <lb/> K⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K|  u  N  ν  K  δ  K  [f  i  (ϕ • ρ  i  )π  i <lb/> j <lb/> π <lb/> ′ <lb/> j  ] <lb/>= <lb/> i <lb/> j <lb/> supp(πi)∩supp(π  ′ <lb/> j  ) <lb/> dx <lb/> K⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K|  u  N  ν  K  δ  K  [f  i  (ϕ • ρ  i  )π  i  π <lb/> ′ <lb/> j  ] <lb/>= <lb/> j <lb/> supp(π <lb/> ′ <lb/> j  ) <lb/> dx <lb/> K⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K|  u  N  ν  K  δ  K  [f  j  (ϕ • ρ  j  )π <lb/> ′ <lb/> j <lb/> i <lb/> π  i  ] <lb/>= <lb/> j <lb/> π <lb/> ′ <lb/> j  (R[ ˜ <lb/> w  G  ])  j  |  s=1  | ϕ • ρ  j  . <lb/> This finishes the process of wonderful renormalization. From a mathematical <lb/>point of view we are done, but for a physicist it is not clear yet that we have con-<lb/>structed a reasonable renormalization. In addition to producing finite distributions <lb/>both schemes have to fulfill another condition that is dictated by physics. It is <lb/>called the locality principle (see [EG73]) and, roughly speaking, assures that the <lb/>renormalized distributions still obey the laws of physics. There are various equiva-<lb/>lent formulations of this; we will use a version for single graphs from [BBK10], more <lb/>about this in Section 6. Before that we turn our attention to the dependence of the <lb/>operators R on the renormalization points, i.e. we study what happens if we change <lb/>the collection of maps {ν} or the cutoff in the definition of u <lb/> s <lb/> ♥  , respectively. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<body> 5. Renormalization group <lb/> In this section we take a closer look at the renormalized distribution densities. <lb/>First we consider (local) subtraction at fixed conditions. The case of minimal <lb/>subtraction then follows by similar arguments since it can be thought of as a &quot; non-<lb/>smooth &quot; version of the former. <lb/>What happens if we change the cutoff functions ν  g  in the definition of the oper-<lb/>ator R  ν  ? Clearly, for primitive graphs the difference is a density supported on the <lb/>exceptional divisor E and after blowing down the renormalized density it becomes <lb/>a density supported on {0} ∈ X. To get an idea what happens in the general case <lb/>it is useful to start with an example. <lb/> Example. Let G be the dunce cap graph (Figure 1). Locally (in d = 4 dimensions <lb/>and N = {g, G}, g denoting the divergent one loop subgraph) we have for ϕ ∈ <lb/>D(κ(U )) <lb/> R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ]|ϕ = <lb/> K⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K|  ν  K  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  EK  |ϕ <lb/> =  ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  |ϕ − (p  G  )  *  (ν  G  u <lb/> s <lb/> N  |dx|)|δ  G  [f <lb/> s  ϕ] <lb/> − (p  g  )  *  (ν  g  u <lb/> s <lb/> N  |dx|)|δ  g  [f <lb/> s  ϕ] <lb/> + (p  g,G  )  *  (ν  g  ν  G  u <lb/> s <lb/> N  |dx|)|δ  g,G  [f <lb/> s  ϕ]. <lb/> Changing the renormalization point, i.e. the collection of test functions {ν}, by <lb/>linearity the difference of the two renormalized expressions is again a sum of this <lb/>form. However, it will contain a mixture of ν and ν <lb/> ′  as renormalization points. But <lb/>we can express the terms with ν <lb/> ′  again by ν-terms only and obtain a finite sum of <lb/> ν-renormalized expressions. Another way to see this is by Taylor expansion using <lb/>the calculus of variations, <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> |  t=0  R  ν+tµ  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ]|ϕ = −(p  g  )  *  (µ  g  u <lb/> s <lb/> N  |dx|)|δ  g  [f <lb/> s  ϕ] <lb/> − (p  G  )  *  (µ  G  u <lb/> s <lb/> N  |dx|)|δ  G  [f <lb/> s  ϕ] <lb/> + (p  g,G  )  * <lb/> (ν  g  µ  G  + ν  G  µ  g  )u <lb/> s <lb/> N  |dx| <lb/> |δ  g,G  [f <lb/> s  ϕ], <lb/>d <lb/> 2 <lb/> dt  2  |  t=0  R  ν+tµ  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ]|ϕ = 2(p  g,G  )  *  (ν  g  ν  G  u <lb/> s <lb/> N  |dx|)|δ  g,G  [f <lb/> s  ϕ], <lb/>d <lb/> k <lb/> dt  k  |  t=0  R  ν+tµ  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ]|ϕ = 0 for all k &gt; 2. <lb/>Thus, for µ  γ  := ν <lb/> ′ <lb/> γ  − ν  γ  , γ ∈ {g, G}, using Lemma 4.7, <lb/> R  ν  ′  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ] − R  ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ]|ϕ = − R  νG  [µ  g  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  Eg  ]|ϕ − R  νg  [µ  G  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  EG  ]|ϕ <lb/>+ ν  g  ν  G  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  Eg,G  |ϕ. <lb/> We see, as expected, that the difference is a sum of densities supported on the <lb/>components of the exceptional divisor, given by subsets of the nested set N . Since <lb/> µ  γ  = 0 for x <lb/> iγ <lb/>γ  = 0, they are finite, except if a point approaches the intersection of <lb/>two components E  J  ∩ E  K  for J , K ⊆ N . But in this case the necessary subtractions <lb/>are already provided by the counterterms associated to the set J ∪ K. <lb/> We first state this property in the general case, then dive deeper into the structure <lb/>of these densities by studying their form more closely. <lb/></body>

			<page> 38 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> Proposition 5.1. Let N be a nested set for the building set I(D) or D and let B <lb/> be marked accordingly. For two collections of renormalization points {ν} and {ν <lb/> ′  } <lb/> set µ  γ  := ν <lb/> ′ <lb/> γ  − ν  γ  for γ ∈ N . Locally in U the difference between the operators R  ν  ′ <lb/> and R  ν  acting onñ <lb/> w <lb/> s  is given by <lb/> (R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  ′  − R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  )[ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ] = <lb/> ∅∅ =K⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K|  R <lb/> N \K <lb/> ν <lb/> [µ  K  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  EK  ] <lb/> with R <lb/> ∅ <lb/> ν  := id  <lb/>  ′  (κ(U))  . <lb/>Proof. Induction on n = |N |. The statement holds in the cases n = 1 and 2 (see <lb/>example above). Let N be a nested set of cardinality n and h / <lb/> ∈ N an additional <lb/>divergent subgraph such that N <lb/> ′  = N ∪ {h} is also nested. For K ⊆ N set K <lb/> ′  := <lb/> K ∪ {h}. <lb/> (R <lb/> N <lb/> ′ <lb/> ν  ′  − R <lb/> N <lb/> ′ <lb/> ν  )[ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ] = <lb/> ∅∅ =K⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K|  (ν <lb/> ′ <lb/>K  − ν  K  ) · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  EK <lb/> + <lb/> K⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K <lb/> ′  |  (ν <lb/> ′ <lb/>K  ′  − ν  K  ′  ) · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  E  K ′ <lb/> =: A + B. <lb/> By induction hypothesis <lb/> A = <lb/> ∅∅ =K⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K|  R <lb/> N \K <lb/> ν <lb/> [µ  K  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  EK  ]. <lb/>Using <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (a  i  + b  i  ) − <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> a  i  = <lb/> ∅∅ =J⊆{1,...,n} <lb/> b  J  a  {1,...,n}\J <lb/> we expand B into two parts, depending on whether ν or µ carries an index h, <lb/>B = B  1  + B  2  = <lb/> K⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K <lb/> ′  | <lb/> J ⊆K <lb/> µ  J  ′  ν  K\J  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  E  K ′ <lb/> + <lb/> ∅∅ =K⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K <lb/> ′  | <lb/> ∅∅ =J ⊆K <lb/> µ  J  ν  K  ′  \J  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  E  K ′  . <lb/> Note that in A all densities µ  L  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  EL  have an additional, not yet renormalized, <lb/>divergence corresponding to the subgraph h ∈ N <lb/> ′  . In order to renormalize them <lb/>we have to add the counterterms associated to h, i.e. all terms in B containing ν  h  . <lb/>For non-empty L ⊆ N fixed <lb/>(−1) <lb/> |L|  R <lb/> N \L <lb/> ν <lb/> [µ  L  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  EL  ] + <lb/> L⊆J ⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |J <lb/> ′  |  µ  L  ν  J  ′  \L  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  E  J ′ <lb/> = (−1) <lb/> |L| <lb/> I⊆N \L <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |I| <lb/> µ  L  ν  I  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  EL∪I  − µ  L  ν  I  ′  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  E  L∪I ′ <lb/> = (−1) <lb/> |L| <lb/> I⊆N  ′  \L <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |I|  µ  L  ν  I  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  EL∪I  = (−1) <lb/> |L|  R <lb/> N <lb/> ′  \L <lb/> ν <lb/> [µ  L  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  EL  ] <lb/>is then a finite expression. Doing this for every non-empty L ⊆ N covers the whole <lb/>sum B  2  because every term µ  L  ν  I  ′  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  E  L∪I ′  appears exactly once and the signs <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<body> match since <lb/> I⊆N \L <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |L|+|I|+1  µ  L  ν  I  ′  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  E  L∪I ′  = <lb/> ∅∅ =K⊆N ,L⊆K <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K <lb/> ′  |  µ  L  ν  K  ′  \L  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  E  K ′  . <lb/> The same argumentation works for B  1  . Fix L ⊆ N and consider all terms in B  1 <lb/> containing µ  L  ′  : <lb/> K⊆N ,L⊆K <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K <lb/> ′  |  µ  L  ′  ν  K\L  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  E  K ′  = <lb/> I⊆N \L <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |L <lb/> ′  |+|I|  µ  L  ′  ν  I  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  E  L ′ ∪I <lb/> = (−1) <lb/> |L <lb/> ′  |  R <lb/> N <lb/> ′  \L <lb/> ′ <lb/> ν <lb/> [µ  L  ′  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  E  L ′  ]. <lb/>Putting everything together we have shown that locally the difference between <lb/>two renormalization operators R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  ′  and R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  is expressible as a sum of densities, <lb/>supported on the components E  K  for K ⊆ N and renormalized in the remaining <lb/>directions according to subsets of N \ K. <lb/> This is a nice formula showing that a finite renormalization (i.e. changing the <lb/>renormalization point {ν}) amounts to adding a density supported on the excep-<lb/>tional divisor, like expected from the toy model case on R (or R <lb/> d  for homogeneous <lb/>distributions). But we can do even better and physics tells us what to expect: The <lb/>Hopf algebraic formulation of the renormalization group predicts that the densities <lb/>appearing in (R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  ′  −R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  )[ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ] should correspond to graphs showing up in the coprod-<lb/>uct of G (for more on this we refer to [CK01] and [Kre13]). In the local formulation <lb/>presented here the coproduct translates into local contractions, i.e. contractions <lb/>with respect to nested sets N . <lb/> Example. Turning back to the example at the beginning of this section where we <lb/>calculated R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  ′  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ] − R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ]|ϕ to be <lb/> −R  νG  [µ  g  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  Eg  ]|ϕ − R  νg  [µ  G  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  EG  ]|ϕ + ν  g  ν  G  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  Eg,G  |ϕ, <lb/> we now examine the individual terms in more detail. Eventually we are interested <lb/>in the pairing with test functions ϕ that are pullbacks of test functions on X. <lb/> Recall that such ϕ are then locally given by ϕ = β <lb/>  *  ψ = ψ • ρ for ψ ∈ D(β(U )). In <lb/> κ(U ) = X <lb/> G  = M <lb/> 2  , corresponding to N = {g, G}, an adapted spanning tree chosen <lb/>as in the example in Section 3.2.2 and marked elements x  G  , y  g  (x, y ∈ R <lb/> 4  ), <lb/> R  νG  [µ  g  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  Eg  ]|ϕ = <lb/> M  2 <lb/> d <lb/> 4  xd <lb/> 4  y µ  g  |x  G  | <lb/> 7−8s  |y  g  | <lb/> 3−4s  (δ  g  [f <lb/> s  ϕ] − ν  G  δ  g,G  [f <lb/> s  ϕ]) <lb/> = c  g <lb/> M <lb/> d <lb/> 4  x |x  G  | <lb/> 7−8s <lb/>  ψ(x  G  ˆ <lb/> x, 0) <lb/>ˆ <lb/> x  4s <lb/> − <lb/> ν  G  (x)ψ(0, 0) <lb/>ˆ <lb/> x  4s <lb/> = c  g  R  νG  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/>G/g  ]|δ  g  [ϕ]. <lb/>Here <lb/> s <lb/>G/g  is the density associated to the contracted graph G/g (more precise, its <lb/>local expression in U  B  ′  ,N  ′  with B <lb/> ′  spanned by x = {x <lb/> i <lb/>e  }  e∈E(t)\E(g)  and N <lb/> ′  = {G/g} <lb/> -the exponent 7 − 8s in |x  G  | does not match but we neglect this little technical <lb/>problem here; see below for the general argument). The coefficient c  g  is given by <lb/> c  g  = <lb/> M <lb/> d <lb/> 4  y <lb/> |y  g  | <lb/> 3−4s <lb/>  4s <lb/> ν <lb/> ′ <lb/> g  (y) − ν  g  (y) <lb/> = R  νg  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/>g  ]|ν <lb/> ′ <lb/> g  <lb/> because ν <lb/> ′ <lb/> g  |  yg =0  = 1. In the same manner we calculate <lb/> R  νg  [µ  G  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  EG  ]|ϕ = c  G  ψ(0, 0) = c  G  δ  G  |ϕ <lb/></body>

			<page> 40 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> with <lb/> c  G  = <lb/> M  2 <lb/> d <lb/> 4  xd <lb/> 4  y µ  G  |x  G  | <lb/> 7−8s  |y  g  | <lb/> 3−4s <lb/> 1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> x  2s  <lb/>  4s  (ˆ x + y  g  ˆ <lb/> y)  2s  − <lb/> ν  g  (y) <lb/>ˆ <lb/> x  4s  <lb/>  4s <lb/> = R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/>G  ] |ν <lb/> ′ <lb/> G  . <lb/> The last term [ν  g  ν  G  · ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ]  Eg,G  |ϕ evaluates to c  g,G  ψ(0, 0) with <lb/> c  g,G  = R  νg  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/>g  ]|ν <lb/> ′ <lb/> g  R  νG  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/>G/g  ]|ν <lb/> ′ <lb/> G  . <lb/> To formulate this in the general case it will be useful to define the contraction <lb/>operation // not only on single graphs but also on nested sets. <lb/> Definition 5.2. Let N be a nested set for some building set B ⊆ D and let J ⊆ N . <lb/>The contraction N //J is defined as the poset with underlying set <lb/> N //J := {g//J | g ∈ N }, <lb/> partially ordered by inclusion. Since the inclusion operation differs from the one <lb/>in N (contracted graphs may not be subgraphs of G anymore, although we can <lb/>identify them with subgraphs via their edge sets), we denote this partial order by <lb/> ⊑. <lb/> The partial order ⊑ is most easily understood by looking at the Hasse diagram <lb/>of N . Replace every g ∈ N by g//J , remove all lines that connect elements of J <lb/> to &quot; above &quot; and draw a new line from o to every element that became disconnected <lb/>in the process. Note that in particular all elements of J have become maximal in <lb/> N //J . <lb/>In addition, we denote by abuse of notation the corresponding contractions on <lb/>adapted spanning trees by the same symbol, i.e. we define <lb/> t//J := t/t  J  where t  J  := <lb/> γ∈J <lb/> t  γ  , <lb/>t  g  //J := t  g  //J  &lt;g  . <lb/> Example. Let G be the graph shown in Figure 7. Denote by γ  1  , γ  2  and γ  3  the <lb/>three fish subgraphs from left to right, and let g and h be the full subgraphs on <lb/>the vertex set V (g) = {0, 1, 2, 3} and V (h) = {2, 3, 4, 5}. In Figure 8 we depict an <lb/> I(D(G))-nested set N and the poset (N //J , ⊑) for J = {γ  1  , γ  3  , g}. <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>5 <lb/>4 <lb/> Figure 7. The graph G <lb/> In the general case we have the following structure for finite renormalizations: <lb/> Theorem 5.3. Consider the collection of renormalization operators R  ν  for two <lb/>sets of subtraction points {ν <lb/> ′  } and {ν}. Let N be a nested set for the building set <lb/> D or I(D) and B be an adapted, marked basis. Then the local expression for the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>41 <lb/></page>

			<body> o <lb/> γ  1 <lb/> γ  2 <lb/> γ  3 <lb/> g <lb/>G <lb/>o <lb/>γ  1 <lb/> γ  2  γ  3 <lb/> G//J <lb/>g//J <lb/> Figure 8. The posets N and (N //J , ⊑) <lb/> difference (R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  ′  − R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  )[ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ] applied on a test function ϕ = β <lb/>  *  ψ for ψ ∈ D(β(U )) is <lb/>given by <lb/> (10) <lb/> (R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  ′  − R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  )[ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ]|ϕ = <lb/> ∅∅ =K⊆N <lb/> c  K  R  ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/>G//K  ]|δ  K  [ϕ] <lb/> where <lb/> (11) <lb/> c  K  = <lb/> γ∈K <lb/> R  ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/>γ//K  ] | ν <lb/> ′ <lb/> γ  <lb/> and R  ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/> ∅  ]|δ  G  [ϕ] is to be understood as δ|ψ = ψ(0). <lb/> We have dropped the indices in R  ν  for simplicity. Define H := ∪  γ∈K  H  γ  with <lb/> H  γ  := {h ∈ N | h//K ∈ (N //K)  ⊏γ//K  }. Then it is shown below that in (10) the <lb/>index is given by N \ (K ∪ H). Likewise, in (11) H  γ  ∪ {γ} is the index in the factor <lb/>associated to γ ∈ K. <lb/> Proof. Using Proposition 5.1 we examine all terms in (R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  ′  −R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  )[ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ]|ϕ separately. <lb/>The proof consists of two steps. First we study how δ  K  acts on the maps f and <lb/> ϕ = β <lb/>  *  ψ. This allows then in the second step to show that the integral arising in <lb/>the evaluation of (R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  ′  −R <lb/> N <lb/> ν  )[ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ]|ϕ factorizes into a product of integrals according <lb/>to (10) and (11). <lb/>Recall that B is given by an D-adapted spanning tree t and <lb/> s  = u <lb/> s <lb/> N  f <lb/> s  |dx|. <lb/> Claim: For J ⊆ N the map δ  J  operates on f and ϕ = β <lb/>  *  ψ <lb/> loc. <lb/> = ψ • ρ by <lb/> ϕ → δ  J  [ϕ] = ϕ|  xJ =0  , <lb/>f → δ  J  [f ] = <lb/> γ∈J ∪{G} <lb/> f  γ//J  . <lb/> Here f  g//J  is defined as follows: Contracting t  g  with respect to J defines an adapted <lb/>spanning tree for g//J (contracting graphs in N and t accordingly does not change <lb/>the properties of t being spanning and adapted -cf. the construction in Proposition <lb/>3.31). Define <lb/>(12) <lb/> X <lb/> g//J  := {(x  e1  , . . . , x  e  k  ) | {e  1  , . . . , e  k  } = E(t  g  //J )} <lb/>with adapted basis B <lb/> ′  = B|  e∈E(tg //J )  . The set N <lb/> ′  = N //J  ⊑g//J  is nested for the <lb/>minimal building set I(D(g//J )) in the divergent arrangement of g//J . Mimicing <lb/>the construction of the wonderful models for this case, we obtain an open set U  N  ′  ,B  ′ <lb/> that is a local piece of the (minimal) wonderful model for the graph g//J . The <lb/>function f <lb/> s <lb/>g//J  is then the regular part of the local pullback of <lb/> s <lb/>g//J  onto this model. <lb/></body>

			<page> 42 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> The factor f  G//J  collects all the remaining parts and is defined in the same way, <lb/>except for one special case: If G does not lie in N , or even not in D (locally in <lb/> U  N ,B  this is the same!), and G//J is primitive, then N <lb/> ′  = ∅ and we do not have <lb/>a local model to pullback <lb/> s <lb/>G//J  onto. But in this case v  G//J  = f  G//J  is already <lb/>regular and no model is required. Also note that if G ∈ N , the operation δ  G  does <lb/>not alter f since it does not depend on the variable x <lb/> iG <lb/>G  . <lb/>Recall that in coordinates given by an adapted spanning tree the distribution <lb/>kernel v is a product of factors (y  e  ) <lb/> 2−d  with e ∈ E(G) and <lb/> y  e  = <lb/> x  e <lb/> if e is an edge of t, <lb/> e  ′  ∈E(te)  σ  t  (e <lb/> ′  )x  e  ′  if e is an edge in G \ t. <lb/> Moreover, the pullback under β onto the wonderful model Y is locally given by the <lb/>map ρ = ρ  N ,B  that scales all x  e  with e ∈ E(t  g  ) and g ∈ N by x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  . <lb/>To prove the claimed properties of δ  J  we argue in the same manner as in the <lb/>proof of Theorem 4.4: <lb/>1. Since ϕ = ψ • ρ, we have that δ  J  [ϕ] is equivalent to ϕ|  {x <lb/> i h <lb/>h  =0} <lb/> for h in max J , <lb/>the set of maximal elements of J . This means that the resulting map only depends <lb/>on the variables x  e  with e ∈ E(t ∩ N  &gt;max J  ). All other vectors are scaled by the <lb/> x <lb/> i  h <lb/> h  and therefore vanish after δ  J  is applied. Another way to put this is that δ  J  [ϕ] <lb/>depends only on the x  e  with e ∈ E(t//J ). In particular, if G ∈ J then δ  J  [ϕ] is <lb/>just a constant, δ  J  [ϕ] = δ|ψ = ψ(0). <lb/> 2. For the second claim start with J = {g} consisting only of a single subgraph <lb/> g  G. The part of f that depends only on the vectors associated to edges of g is <lb/>unaffected by setting x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  = 0 because all x  e  with e ∈ E(t  g  ) get scaled and so the <lb/>factor x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  pulls out (it is already absorbed into the definition of u <lb/> s <lb/>g  ). On the other <lb/>hand, the remaining part of f depends on x  e  with e ∈ E(t  g  ) only through special <lb/>linear combinations. These linear combinations express vectors representing edges <lb/> e <lb/> ′  that do not lie in g but are connected to a vertex of g such that E(t  e  ′  )∩E(t  g  )  = ∅. <lb/> They become independent of x  e  after setting x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  to zero. Therefore, δ  J  [f ] splits into <lb/>a product of two factors depending on the mutual disjoint sets of vectors {x  e  }  e∈E(tg) <lb/> or {x  e  }  e∈E(t/tg)  , i.e. <lb/> δ  g  [f ] = f  g  f  G/g  = f  g//J  f  G//J  . <lb/> Adding another graph h  = G from N to J and using Lemma 4.7 we can express <lb/> δ  J  as <lb/> δ  J  [f ] = δ <lb/> g <lb/>g,h  [δ  g  [f ]] = δ  h  [f  g  f  G/g  ]. <lb/>There are three possible cases (due to Lemma 3.26 there cannot be two incompa-<lb/>rable g, h with non-empty overlap in an I(D)-nested set; if the maximal building <lb/>set D is considered only case 2 and 3 are possible): <lb/>(1) g and h are incomparable. Then f  g  does not depend on any x  e  with e ∈ <lb/> E(t  h  ) and <lb/> δ  h  [f  g  f  G/g  ] = f  g  δ  h  [f  G/g  ] = f  g//J  δ  h  [f  G/g  ]. <lb/>(2) h is contained in g, h  g. Then all {x  e  }  e∈E(t  h  )  are scaled by x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  and f  G/g <lb/> is independent of these. Thus, only f  g  is affected by contracting h, <lb/>δ  h  [f  g  f  G/g  ] = δ  h  [f  g  ]f  G/g  = δ  h  [f  g  ]f  G//J  . <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>43 <lb/></page>

			<body> (3) h contains g, g  h. Then all {x  e  }  e∈E(tg)  are scaled by x <lb/> i  h <lb/> h  and f  g  is not <lb/>affected by setting x <lb/> i  h <lb/> h  = 0. Therefore <lb/> δ  h  [f  g  f  G/g  ] = f  g  δ  h  [f  G/g  ] = f  g//J  δ  h  [f  G/g  ]. <lb/>In all three cases we argue like in the first step to carry out the operation of δ  h  and <lb/>conclude <lb/> δ  J  [f ] = f  g//J  f  h//J  f  G//J  . <lb/> For general J ⊆ N we repeat this procedure for a finite number of steps to show <lb/> δ  J  [f ] = <lb/> γ∈J ∪{G} <lb/> f  γ//J  . <lb/> With the help of these two assertions we are now able to examine the integrals <lb/>(13) <lb/> R <lb/> N \K <lb/> ν <lb/> [µ  K  · (w <lb/> s  )  EK  ]|ϕ = <lb/> κ(U) <lb/> dxu <lb/> s <lb/> N  µ  K <lb/> J ⊆N \K <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |J |  ν  J  δ  K∪J  [f <lb/> s  ϕ] <lb/> in detail. Note that f  g//J  depends only on the variables x  e  associated to edges <lb/>of E(t  g  \ t  h1∪...∪h  k  ) with {h  1  , . . . , h  k  } = max J  &lt;g  (not on the marked element x <lb/> ig <lb/>g <lb/> though!). This is exactly the set of coordinates on which the maps ν  g  depend. <lb/>Therefore divergences corresponding to elements g//J are also renormalized by the <lb/>subtraction points ν  g  associated to g. <lb/> To make the following calculations more readable we simplify the notation: For <lb/> K ⊆ N write <lb/>  for the K-contracted graph g//K. Let K = {g  1  , . . . , g  n  } (if G ∈ K <lb/> assume g  n  = G) and define the subsets H  i  ⊆ N by <lb/> H  i  := {h | ˜ <lb/> h ⊏ ˜ <lb/> g  i  } for i = 1, . . . , n. <lb/> We want to show that the integral <lb/> κ(U) <lb/> dx u <lb/> s <lb/> N <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (ν <lb/> ′ <lb/> gi  − ν  gi  ) <lb/> J ⊆N \K <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |J |  ν  J <lb/> γ∈K∪J ∪{G} <lb/> f <lb/> s <lb/> ˜ <lb/> γ//J  δ  K∪J  [ϕ] <lb/>factorizes into a product of integrals according to (10) and (11). To see this split <lb/>the sum into two parts, the first one summing over subsets I ⊆ N \ K that contain <lb/>an element of H  1  , i.e. I ∩ H  1  = ∅, the second one over subsets J ⊆ N \ K with <lb/> J ∩ H  1  = ∅. The first sum can then be written as <lb/> J ⊆N \K <lb/>J ∩H1=∅ <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |J | <lb/> ∅∅ =L⊆H1 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |L|  ν  J  ν  L  δ  K∪J ∪L  [f <lb/> s  ]δ  K∪J ∪L  [ϕ]. <lb/>Now <lb/> δ  K∪J ∪L  [ϕ] = δ  K∪J  [ϕ], <lb/>because all g ∈ L satisfy <lb/>  ⊏ ˜ <lb/> g  1  and from this follows g ≤ g  1  for the partial order <lb/>on N . Therefore all g ∈ L are scaled by x <lb/> ig  1 <lb/> g1  which is set to zero by δ  K  . Again, <lb/></body>

			<page> 44 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> since all elements of L are smaller than g  1  , <lb/> δ  K∪J ∪L  [f <lb/> s  ] = f  ˜ <lb/> G//J ∪L <lb/> γ∈(K∪J ∪L)\{G} <lb/> f  ˜ <lb/> γ//J ∪L <lb/> = f  ˜ <lb/> G//J <lb/> γ∈K\{G} <lb/> f  ˜ <lb/> γ//J ∪L <lb/> ξ∈J \{G} <lb/> f  ˜ <lb/> ξ//J ∪L <lb/> η∈L\{G} <lb/> f  ˜ <lb/> η//J ∪L <lb/> = f  ˜ <lb/> G//J  f  ˜ <lb/> g1//L <lb/> γ∈K\{g1,G} <lb/> f  ˜ <lb/> γ//J <lb/> ξ∈J \{G} <lb/> f  ˜ <lb/> ξ//J <lb/> η∈L\{G} <lb/> f  ˜ <lb/> η//L  . <lb/> In the last line we have used that <lb/>  1  is immune to contraction by elements lying <lb/>outside of H  1  . <lb/>Thus, the factor <lb/> ∅∅ =L⊆H1 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |L|  ν  L  f  ˜ <lb/> g1//L <lb/> η∈L\{G} <lb/> f <lb/> s <lb/> ˜ <lb/> η//L <lb/> can be pulled out of the first sum. <lb/>In the second sum over the subsets J ⊆ N \ K with J ∩ H  1  = ∅ the factor <lb/> f <lb/> s <lb/> ˜ <lb/> g1  appears in every summand because <lb/>  1  is not affected by δ  J  . Recall that δ  K  [ϕ] <lb/>depends only on the coordinates {x  e  }  e∈E(t//K)  to conclude that <lb/> κ(U) <lb/> dx u <lb/> s <lb/> N <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (ν <lb/> ′ <lb/> gi  − ν  gi  ) <lb/> J ⊆N \K <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |J |  ν  J  δ  K∪J  [f <lb/> s  ] δ  K∪J  [ϕ] <lb/>= <lb/> V1 <lb/> dx u <lb/> s <lb/>g1  u <lb/> s <lb/> H1  (ν <lb/> ′ <lb/> g1  − ν  g1  ) <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> ∅∅ =L⊆H1 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |L|  ν  L <lb/> η∈L\{G} <lb/> f <lb/> s <lb/> ˜ <lb/> η//L  f <lb/> s <lb/> ˜ <lb/> g1//L  + f <lb/> s <lb/> ˜ <lb/> g1 <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> × <lb/> V2 <lb/> dx u <lb/> s <lb/> N \(H1∪{g1}) <lb/> n <lb/> i=2 <lb/> (ν <lb/> ′ <lb/> gi  − ν  gi  ) <lb/> J ⊆N \K <lb/>J ∩H1=∅ <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |J |  ν  J  δ  K\{g1}∪J  [f <lb/> s  ] δ  K∪J  [ϕ] <lb/>= R  ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w  g1//K  ]|ν <lb/> ′ <lb/> g1  <lb/> · · · . <lb/> Here we have changed the domain of integration from κ(U ) to V  1  × V  2  with <lb/> V  i  constructed as follows: Pick a linear extension of the partial order on K = <lb/> {g  1  , . . . , g  n  } and let g  1  = ˜ <lb/> g  1  be the minimal element (the proof works also without <lb/>this assumption, but this simplifies it considerably). Define X <lb/> ˜ <lb/> g1  as in Equation <lb/>(12) and X <lb/> G <lb/> ′  similarly for G <lb/> ′  := G/˜ g  1  . Recall the wonderful construction from <lb/>Definition 3.8 and set for every g in the minimal or maximal building set B <lb/> Z <lb/> 1 <lb/> g  := Z  g  ∩ (X <lb/> ˜ <lb/> g1  × {0}) and Z <lb/> 2 <lb/> g  := Z  g  ∩ ({0} × X <lb/> G <lb/> ′  ). <lb/>Define V  1  := X <lb/> ˜ <lb/> g1  \ ∪  γ∈B  Z <lb/> 1 <lb/> γ  and V  2  := X <lb/> G <lb/> ′  \ ∪  γ∈B  Z <lb/> 2 <lb/> γ  . Then V  1  is a local chart <lb/>domain for the wonderful model for <lb/>  1  with respect to the nested set H  1  ∪ {g  1  } and <lb/>adapted basis B|  E(t˜   1  )  . The same holds for G <lb/> ′  with respect to N \ (H  1  ∪ {g  1  }) and <lb/> B|  E(t  G/˜ g 1  )  . For the original chart on Y we have <lb/> κ(U ) = X <lb/> G  \ (∪  γ∈B  Z  γ  ) ⊆ V  1  × V  2  , <lb/> and the difference is an union of linear subspaces, i.e a set of measure zero. More-<lb/>over, the integrand is finite because all divergences associated to the elements of <lb/> K get &quot; damped &quot; by µ  K  , the remaining divergences coming from elements of N \ K <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>45 <lb/></page>

			<body> are renormalized and ψ ∈ D(β(U  N ,B  )) vanishes in a neighborhood of all Z  γ  , which <lb/>covers the divergences of B \ N . Thus, changing the domain is justified and by <lb/>Fubini&apos;s theorem the integral factorizes into the desired product. The last equality <lb/>holds because of <lb/>(ν <lb/> ′ <lb/> g1  − ν  g1  ) <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> ∅∅ =L⊆H1 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |L|  ν  L <lb/> η∈L <lb/> f <lb/> s <lb/> ˜ <lb/> η//L  f <lb/> s <lb/> ˜ <lb/> g1//L  + f <lb/> s <lb/> ˜ <lb/> g1 <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> = f <lb/> s <lb/> ˜ <lb/> g1  ν <lb/> ′ <lb/> g1  − ν  g1  (f <lb/> s <lb/> ˜ <lb/> g1  ν <lb/> ′ <lb/> g1  )|  x <lb/> ig 1 <lb/> g 1 <lb/> =0 <lb/> + <lb/> ∅∅ =L⊆H1 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |L|  ν  L <lb/> η∈L∪{g1} <lb/> f <lb/> s <lb/> ˜ <lb/> η//L  ν <lb/> ′ <lb/> g1 <lb/> − <lb/> ∅∅ =L⊆H1 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |L|  ν  L  ν  g1  ( <lb/> η∈L∪{g1} <lb/> f <lb/> s <lb/> ˜ <lb/> η//L  ν <lb/> ′ <lb/> g1  )|  x <lb/> ig 1 <lb/> g 1 <lb/> =0 <lb/> = f <lb/> s <lb/> ˜ <lb/> g1  ν <lb/> ′ <lb/> g1  + <lb/> ∅∅ =L⊆H1∪{g1} <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |L|  ν  L  δ  L  [f <lb/> s <lb/> ˜ <lb/> g1  ν <lb/> ′ <lb/> g1  ]. <lb/>A technical detail: If g  1  had another divergent subgraph h ∈ B \ N , the renor-<lb/>malization by R  ν  would not take care of this and the integral would still diverge. <lb/>But in this case all variables {x  e  }  e∈E(t  h  )  are set to zero by δ  K  . Then the whole <lb/>summand associated to K in Formula (10) vanishes because δ  K  [ϕ] = δ  K  [ψ • ρ] = 0 <lb/>since supp(ψ) ⊆ κ(U ) is disjoint from {x  e  = 0 | e ∈ E(t  h  )}. <lb/>The remaining integral is of the same structure as the one we started with, so we <lb/>can repeat the process for g  2  ∈ K (notice how this relies heavily on K ⊆ N being <lb/>nested and the stability of t under contractions). After a finite number of steps we <lb/>obtain a product of renormalized densities, each factor representing an element of <lb/> K, possibly times a last remaining factor, <lb/> V2 <lb/> dz u <lb/> s <lb/> N \(∪  n <lb/>i=1  Hi∪{gi}) <lb/> J ⊆N \K <lb/>J ∩(∪iHi)=∅ <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |J |  ν  J  f <lb/> s <lb/> ˜ <lb/> G//J <lb/> γ∈J \{G} <lb/> f <lb/> s <lb/> ˜ <lb/> γ//J  δ  K∪J  [ϕ]. <lb/>If G lies in K, then δ  K  [ϕ] = ψ(0) is constant and the procedure ends before this <lb/>last step since the H  i  cover N . If G is not in K, then G//K could have remaining <lb/>divergences, given by elements of N \ (K ∪ H  1  ∪ . . . ∪ H  n  ); then this last integral is <lb/>just the renormalized expression for <lb/> s <lb/>G//K  , applied to the test function δ  K  [ϕ], <lb/> J ⊆N \K <lb/>J ∩(∪iHi)=∅ <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |J |  ν  J  f <lb/> s <lb/> ˜ <lb/> G//J <lb/> γ∈J \{G} <lb/> f <lb/> s <lb/> ˜ <lb/> γ//J  δ  K∪J  [ϕ] <lb/>= <lb/> J ⊆N \(K∪H1∪...∪Hn) <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |J |  ν  J  δ  J  [f <lb/> s <lb/>G//K  δ  K  [ϕ]] <lb/>= R  ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/>G//K  ]|δ  K  [ϕ]. <lb/>Last but not least, there remains one technical detail to take care of: The exponents <lb/>in u <lb/> s <lb/>g  do not match the ones provided by the definition of <lb/> s <lb/>G/K  and <lb/> s <lb/>g//K  . This <lb/>would not happen if we had defined subgraphs g ⊆ G as given by there edge <lb/>set E(g) ⊆ E(G) but with V (g) = V (G) (we chose not to do so because in the <lb/>formulation presented here, X is spanned by variables associated to edges of an <lb/>adapted spanning tree, not by the elements of V <lb/> ′  like in [BBK10]). However, we <lb/>can also just rescale the complex regularization parameter s = 1 − <lb/> d˜  <lb/> dg  (1 − ˜ <lb/> s) without <lb/>affecting the whole construction to obtain the correct exponent in u <lb/> s <lb/> ˜ <lb/> g  . On the other <lb/></body>

			<page> 46 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> hand, this discrepancy does not show up in the limit s → 1 which we are allowed <lb/>to take because this proof shows that every term in (10) and (11) is well-defined at <lb/> s = 1. Putting everything together we arrive at the desired formula. <lb/> Now we consider minimal subtraction. It will turn out to work in exactly the <lb/>same manner as the case above. This is already clear if we think of R  1  as a non-<lb/>smooth version of R  ν  by making the (forbidden) substitution ν  g  (x  g  ) = θ(1 − |x <lb/> ig <lb/>g  |). <lb/> Let N be a nested set for the building set I(D) or D. Locally in U the minimal <lb/>subtraction operator R  1  is given by <lb/>˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  (x) = <lb/> γ∈N <lb/> u <lb/> s <lb/>γ  (x <lb/> iγ <lb/>γ  )f <lb/> s  (x)|dx| <lb/> R1 <lb/> −→ <lb/> γ∈N <lb/> u <lb/> s <lb/>γ  (x <lb/> iγ <lb/>γ  ) <lb/> ♥ <lb/> f <lb/> s  (x)|dx|, <lb/>where (. . .)  ♥  denotes the regular part <lb/> u <lb/> s <lb/>g <lb/> ♥ <lb/> |ϕ := <lb/> dx |x| <lb/> −1+dg (1−s) <lb/> ϕ(x) − θ(1 − |x|)ϕ(0) <lb/> and the factor f <lb/> s  is treated as test function. If instead θ <lb/> c  (x) := θ(c − |x|) with <lb/> c &gt; 0 is used as cutoff, the principal part of the Laurent expansion does not change <lb/>while the regular part (u <lb/> s <lb/>g  )  ♥c  gets an additional δ-term <lb/> 2 <lb/> k≥0 <lb/> d <lb/> k <lb/>g  log <lb/> k+1  (c) <lb/> k + 1! <lb/>(s − 1) <lb/> k  δ. <lb/> Therefore the whole Laurent series for u <lb/> s <lb/>g  is given by <lb/> u <lb/> s <lb/>g  |ϕ = <lb/>2 <lb/> d  g <lb/> δ|ϕ(1 − s) <lb/> −1  + <lb/> k≥0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> k! <lb/> |x| <lb/> −1  log <lb/> k  (|x|) <lb/> ♥c <lb/> |ϕ(1 − s) <lb/> k <lb/> = <lb/>2 <lb/> d  g <lb/> δ|ϕ(1 − s) <lb/> −1  + <lb/> k≥0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> k! <lb/> |x| <lb/> −1  log <lb/> k  (|x|) <lb/> ♥ <lb/> |ϕ(1 − s) <lb/> k <lb/> + <lb/> k≥0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> k + 1! <lb/> d <lb/> k <lb/>g  log <lb/> k+1  (c)δ|ϕ(1 − s) <lb/> k  . <lb/> Write N = {g  1  , . . . , g  n  } and for k ∈ {1, . . . , n} let x <lb/> i  k <lb/> k  denote the associated marked <lb/>element. Writê <lb/> x for the collection of all other coordinates. For a test function <lb/> ϕ ∈ D(κ(U )) set <lb/> φ  s  (x <lb/> i1 <lb/> 1  , . . . , x <lb/> in <lb/>n  ) := <lb/> dˆ f <lb/> s  (x)ϕ(x). <lb/>By expanding the successive application of the regular parts (u <lb/> s <lb/>g  )  ♥  and reordering <lb/>the sum we see that R  1  is expressed by a formula similar to the one for subtraction <lb/>at fixed conditions: <lb/> R <lb/> N <lb/> 1  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ]|ϕ = (u <lb/> s <lb/>g1  )  ♥  ||(u <lb/> s <lb/>g2  )  ♥  | . . . (u <lb/> s <lb/>gn  )  ♥  |φ  s  . . . <lb/> = (u <lb/> s <lb/>g1  )  ♥  ||(u <lb/> s <lb/>g2  )  ♥  | . . . <lb/> dx <lb/> in <lb/>n  |x <lb/> in <lb/>n  | <lb/> −1+dn(s−1) <lb/> × <lb/> φ  s  (x <lb/> i1 <lb/> 1  , . . . , x <lb/> in <lb/>n  ) − θ <lb/> 1  (x <lb/> in <lb/>n  )φ  s  (x <lb/> i1 <lb/> 1  , . . . , x <lb/> in−1 <lb/>n−1  , 0) <lb/> . . . <lb/> = <lb/> K⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K| <lb/> dx <lb/> n <lb/> j=1 <lb/> u <lb/> s <lb/>gj  (x <lb/> ij <lb/>j  ) <lb/> γ∈K <lb/> θ  γ  (x <lb/> iγ <lb/>γ  ) δ  K  [f <lb/> s  ϕ](x). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>47 <lb/></page>

			<body> We do the same for the regular parts obtained by cutting off at c, <lb/> R <lb/> N <lb/> c  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ]|ϕ = <lb/> K⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K| <lb/> dx <lb/> n <lb/> j=1 <lb/> u <lb/> s <lb/>gj  (x <lb/> ij <lb/>j  ) <lb/> γ∈K <lb/> θ <lb/> c <lb/>γ  (x <lb/> iγ <lb/>γ  ) δ  K  [f <lb/> s  ϕ](x), <lb/> and write θ <lb/> c <lb/> ′  (x) = θ <lb/> c  (x) + ϑ <lb/> c,c <lb/> ′  (x) with <lb/> ϑ <lb/> c,c <lb/> ′  (x) = <lb/> 1 for c &lt; |x| &lt; c <lb/> ′  , <lb/> 0 else. <lb/>Then we can express the difference between two minimal subtraction operators R <lb/> N <lb/> c  ′ <lb/> and R <lb/> N <lb/> c  , applied tõ <lb/> w <lb/> s  , by the density <lb/> ϕ −→ <lb/> ∅∅ =K⊂N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K| <lb/> dx u <lb/> s <lb/> N  Θ <lb/> c <lb/> ′  ,c <lb/> K  δ  K  [f <lb/> s  ϕ]. <lb/> Here Θ <lb/> c <lb/> ′  ,c <lb/> K <lb/> := <lb/> γ∈K  θ <lb/> c <lb/> ′  (x <lb/> iγ <lb/>γ  ) − <lb/> γ∈K  θ <lb/> c  (x <lb/> iγ <lb/>γ  ) is a &quot; multidimensional cutoff &quot; , sup-<lb/>ported on <lb/> {x ∈ R <lb/> |K|  | c &lt; |x  i  | &lt; c <lb/> ′  for all i ∈ {1, . . . , |K|}}. <lb/> Expanding Θ <lb/> c,c <lb/> ′ <lb/> K  and reordering the sum, we have <lb/>Θ <lb/> c <lb/> ′  ,c <lb/> K  = <lb/> γ∈K <lb/> (θ <lb/> c <lb/>γ  + ϑ <lb/> c,c <lb/> ′ <lb/> γ  ) − <lb/> γ∈K <lb/> θ <lb/> c <lb/>γ  = <lb/> ∅∅ =J ⊆K <lb/> ( <lb/> γ∈J <lb/> ϑ <lb/> c,c <lb/> ′ <lb/> γ  )( <lb/> η∈K\J <lb/> θ <lb/> c <lb/>η  ) = <lb/> ∅∅ =J ⊆K <lb/> ϑ <lb/> c,c <lb/> ′ <lb/> J  θ <lb/> c <lb/> K\J  . <lb/> Putting everything together, we find that a change of the renormalization point c is <lb/>expressed by a sum of densities supported on components of the exceptional divisor <lb/>given by subsets K ⊆ N , <lb/> (R <lb/> N <lb/> c  ′  − R <lb/> N <lb/> c  )[ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ]|ϕ = <lb/> ∅∅ =K⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K| <lb/> ∅∅ =J ⊆K <lb/> dx u <lb/> s <lb/> N  ϑ <lb/> c,c <lb/> ′ <lb/> J  θ <lb/> c <lb/> K\J  δ  K  [f <lb/> s  ϕ]. <lb/> We can repeat the argumentation from the case of subtraction at fixed conditions <lb/>to arrive at the formulae of Proposition 5.1 and Theorem 5.3: <lb/> (R <lb/> N <lb/> c  ′  − R <lb/> N <lb/> c  )[ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ]|ϕ = <lb/> ∅∅ =K⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K|  R <lb/> N \K <lb/> c <lb/> [ϑ <lb/> c,c <lb/> ′ <lb/> K  · ( ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  )  EK  ]|ϕ, <lb/> (R <lb/> N <lb/> c  ′  − R <lb/> N <lb/> c  )[ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s  ]|ϕ = <lb/> ∅∅ =K⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K|  c  K  R  c  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/>G/K  ]|δ  K  [ϕ]. <lb/>Viewing the maps θ <lb/> c <lb/> ′ <lb/> γ  as test functions, the constants c  K  are exactly the same as <lb/>in (11). They are given by densities of K-contracted graphs, evaluated at their <lb/>respective renormalization points, c  γ  = <lb/> γ∈K  R  c  [ ˜ <lb/> w <lb/> s <lb/>γ//K  ]|θ <lb/> c <lb/> ′ <lb/> γ  . <lb/> Eventually one would like to apply the formulae presented here not on distri-<lb/>butions given by single graphs but on the formal sum of all graphs expressing a <lb/>given interaction (an amplitude). The study of the behaviour of amplitudes under <lb/>a change of renormalization points allows in the best cases even to make non-<lb/>perturbative statements; the main idea is that physical observables do not depend <lb/>on the choices made in fixing a renormalization scheme. This leads to a differential <lb/>equation, the renormalization group equation (cf. [Col84]). In the language of the <lb/>renormalization Hopf algebra this translates to (combinatorial) Dyson-Schwinger <lb/>equations (cf. [Kre13]). So far we have not used any differential methods, but to <lb/></body>

			<page> 48 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> explore these objects within the wonderful framework it seems that subtraction at <lb/>fixed conditions is then the way to go. This is reserved for future work. <lb/>6. Back to Physics <lb/> This section connects the geometric method of extending distributions presented <lb/>in this thesis to physics. We show that renormalization on wonderful models satisfies <lb/>the locality principle of Epstein and Glaser [EG73]. After that we finish with an <lb/>outlook of how to relate our approach to the method of Epstein-Glaser, i.e. to the <lb/>renormalization of amplitudes, and how Hopf algebras can be utilized to describe <lb/>the wonderful renormalization process. <lb/>6.1. Connection to the Epstein-Glaser method. The Epstein-Glaser locality <lb/>principle is the position space analog of locality of counterterms. It decides whether <lb/>a given theory is renormalizable, i.e. if adding counterterms to renormalize the <lb/>Lagrangian keep its form invariant. <lb/>In [BBK10] this principle is formulated in a version for single graphs. <lb/> Definition 6.1 (Locality principle). Let G be a connected graph. Let R denote a <lb/>renormalization operator. R satisfies the locality principle of Epstein and Glaser if <lb/>(14) <lb/> R[v  G  ] = R[v  g  ]R[v  h  ]v  G\(g∪h)  on X <lb/> G  \ X <lb/> G\(g∪h) <lb/>s <lb/> holds for all disjoint pairs g, h of connected and divergent subgraphs of G. <lb/> This is to be understood in the sense of distributions. For all test functions <lb/> ϕ ∈ D(X <lb/> G  ) with support disjoint from X <lb/> G\(g∪h) <lb/>s <lb/> the renormalization of v  G  is <lb/>already determined by the renormalized distributions v  g  and v  h  . Note that v  g  and <lb/> v  h  depend on disjoint sets of variables and v  G\(g∪h)  is regular on X <lb/> G  \ X <lb/> G\(g∪h) <lb/>s <lb/> . <lb/>Therefore the product on the right hand side of Equation (14) is well-defined. <lb/>Another way to formulate the locality principle is that for causal disconnected <lb/>regions (g and h are disjoint) the renormalized distribution is given by &quot; lower order &quot; <lb/>(i.e. subgraph-) distributions. In the recursive procedure of Epstein and Glaser this <lb/>is one of the main ingredients in the construction; it allows to recursively construct <lb/>the n-th order term T <lb/> n  in the formal series for the S-matrix up to the small diagonal <lb/>in M <lb/> n  . <lb/> Theorem 6.2. Let R be given by minimal subtraction or subtraction at fixed condi-<lb/>tions on the minimal wonderful model for the divergent arrangement of a connected <lb/>and at most logarithmic graph. <lb/>In both cases R satisfies the locality principle (14). <lb/> Proof. We follow the lines of [BBK10] but correct the proof by adding some essential <lb/>details missing there. <lb/>Let Y  g  , Y  h  and Y denote minimal wonderful models for g, h and G. For G <lb/>  *  := <lb/> G \ (g ∪ h) define X <lb/> −  := X <lb/> G <lb/>  *  as in (12). In the language of wonderful models the <lb/>theorem states that Y <lb/> ′  = Y  g  × Y  h  × X <lb/> −  is a (minimal) wonderful model for the <lb/>divergent arrangement of the graph g ∪ h in S := supp(ϕ) ⊆ X. <lb/> Let B denote the minimal building set in the divergent arrangement. The proof <lb/>is based on two claims: Every B(g ∪ h)-nested set is given by a disjoint union <lb/> N  g  ˙ <lb/> ∪ N  h  of B(g)- and B(h)-nested sets (one of them possibly empty). Secondly, <lb/> Y \ β <lb/> −1  (X <lb/> −  ) is covered by the open sets U  N ,B  where N is a disjoint union of N  g <lb/> and N  h  as above, both non-empty. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>49 <lb/></page>

			<body> Proof of first claim: Since g and h are disjoint, Lemma 3.26 implies B(g ∪ h) = <lb/> B(g) ∪ B(h). This shows that if N  g  and N  h  are nested with respect to B(g) and <lb/> B(h), then N  g  ∪ N  h  is B(g ∪ h)-nested. On the other hand, every subset of a nested <lb/>set is nested itself. With B(g ∪ h) = B(g) ∪ B(h) the claim follows. <lb/>Proof of second claim: If γ is an element of B(G) \ B(g ∪ h), then it must contain <lb/>an edge e in E(t  γ  \ t  g  ) for t an adapted spanning tree. From <lb/> A <lb/> ⊥ <lb/> γ  = <lb/> e  ′  ∈E(tγ ) <lb/> A <lb/> ⊥ <lb/> e  ⊆ A <lb/> ⊥ <lb/> e <lb/> and e ∈ E(G <lb/>  *  ) it follows that <lb/> E  γ  = β <lb/> −1  (A <lb/> ⊥ <lb/> γ  ) ⊆ β <lb/> −1  (X <lb/> −  ). <lb/>Now consider the open sets U  N ,B  ⊆ Y where N = N  g  ˙ <lb/> ∪ N  h  is I(g ∪ h)-nested and B <lb/> marked accordingly. We need to show that local charts of this type cover every E  γ <lb/> for γ ∈ B(g ∪h) and that every x ∈ X \ X <lb/> −  is the preimage of some y ∈ U  N ,B  under <lb/>the map β: W.l.o.g. assume γ ⊆ g and pick η ∈ B(h). Then N := {γ, η} is B(G)-<lb/> nested. Let B be marked accordingly and let <lb/>  γ  and <lb/>  η  denote the collection of <lb/>coordinates {x  e  }  e∈E(tγ )  and {x  e  }  e∈E(tη)  where the marked elements x <lb/> iγ <lb/>γ  and x <lb/> iη <lb/>η  are <lb/>set to 1. The map ρ  N ,B  scales <lb/>  γ  by x <lb/> iγ <lb/>γ  , ˆ <lb/> x  η  by x <lb/> iη <lb/>η  and leaves all other coordinates <lb/>unaltered -it does not &quot; mix &quot; coordinates because g and h are disjoint. Recall that <lb/> ρ  N ,B  is the essential part in the definition of the chart <lb/> κ <lb/> −1 <lb/>N ,B  : X \ <lb/> ξ∈B(G) <lb/> Z  ξ  −→ U  N ,B  ⊆ Y, <lb/>x −→ <lb/> x <lb/> iγ <lb/>γ  ˆ <lb/> x  γ  , . . . , x <lb/> iη <lb/>η  ˆ <lb/> x  η  ; [ˆ x  γ  ], . . . , [ˆ x  η  ] <lb/> . <lb/> If ξ is in B(G) \ B(g ∪ h), the Z  ξ  are given by {x  e  = 0 | e ∈ E(t  ξ  )} which is <lb/>a subset of X <lb/> −  . Similarly, for ξ ∈ B(g ∪ h) with either ξ &lt; γ or ξ &lt; η we <lb/>have Z  ξ  = {x  e  = 0 | e ∈ E(t  ξ  )}. If ξ ∈ B(g ∪ h) and either ξ &gt; γ or ξ &gt; η, <lb/> then Z  ξ  = {x <lb/> iγ <lb/>γ  = 0, x  e  = 0 | e ∈ E(t  ξ  \ t  γ  )} or with γ replaced by η. Finally, <lb/> Z  γ  = Z  η  = ∅. From this description it is clear that as the marking of B varies, the <lb/>sets U  N ,B  cover E  γ  (and E  η  as well). Additionally, as we vary over B(g ∪ h)-nested <lb/> sets of the form N  g  ˙ <lb/> ∪ N  h  and markings of B, we find preimages y ∈ Y in U  N ,B  for <lb/>every x ∈ X \ X <lb/> −  by solving a system of linear equations (after fixing the marked <lb/>elements the system is trivial; if the marked elements are required to be zero, we <lb/>switch to another chart). <lb/>The previous discussion shows also that for such nested sets N = N  g  ˙ <lb/> ∪ N  h  and <lb/>marked bases B = B  g  ˙ <lb/> ∪ B  h  we have <lb/> U  N ,B  = U  Ng ,Bg  × U  N  h  ,B  h  × (X <lb/> G <lb/>  *  \ <lb/> γ∈B(G)\B(g∪h) <lb/> Z  γ  ), <lb/>where U  Ng ,Bg  and U  N  h  ,B  h  are chart domains for Y  g  and Y  h  . A similar decomposition <lb/>holds for the charts κ  N ,B  = κ  Ng ,Bg  × κ  N  h  ,B  h  × id and for the blowdown β, locally <lb/>given by ρ  N ,B  = ρ  Ng ,Bg  × ρ  N  h  ,B  h  × id. Thus, outside of β <lb/> −1  (X <lb/> −  ) both models <lb/> Y and Y <lb/> ′  look locally the same and we can find a partition of unity χ  N ,B  = <lb/> χ  Ng ,Bg  × χ  N  h  ,B  h  × id, subordinate to the sets U  N ,B  ∩ β <lb/> −1  (S) where N = N  g  ˙ <lb/> ∪ N  h <lb/> and B = B  g  ˙ <lb/> ∪ B  h  . With the notation introduced in the proof of Theorem 5.3 we <lb/></body>

			<page> 50 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> have f = f  g  f  h  f  G  *  . Then in every such U  N ,B <lb/> R  ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w  G  ]|ψ = <lb/> K⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K|  ν  K  · ( ˜ <lb/> w  G  )  EK  |ψ <lb/> = <lb/> ∅∅ =Kg⊆Ng <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |Kg| <lb/> dx u  N  ν  Kg  δ  Kg  [f ψ] <lb/> + <lb/> ∅∅ =K  h  ⊆N  h <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K  h  | <lb/> dx u  N  ν  K  h  δ  K  h  [f ψ] <lb/> + <lb/> Kg ˙ <lb/> ∪K  h  ⊆N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |Kg|+|K  h  | <lb/> dx u  N  ν  Kg  ν  K  h  δ  Kg ˙ <lb/> ∪K  h  [f ψ] <lb/> = <lb/> ∅∅ =Kg⊆Ng <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |Kg| <lb/> dx u  N  ν  Kg  δ  Kg  [f  g  ] <lb/> f  h  δ  Kg  [f  G  *  ]δ  Kg  [ψ] <lb/>+ <lb/> ∅∅ =K  h  ⊆N  h <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K  h  |  ν  K  h  δ  K  h  [f  h  ]δ  Kg ˙ <lb/> ∪K  h  [f  G  *  ]δ  Kg ˙ <lb/> ∪K  h  [ψ] <lb/> + <lb/> K  h  ⊆N  h <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |K  h  | <lb/> dx u  N  ν  K  h  δ  K  h  [f  h  ]δ  K  h  [f  G  *  ] f  g  δ  K  h  [ψ] <lb/>= <lb/> Kg ⊆Ng <lb/>K  h  ⊆N  h <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |Kg|+|K  h  | <lb/> dx u  N  ν  Kg  ν  K  h  δ  Kg  [f  g  ]δ  K  h  [f  h  ] <lb/> × δ  Kg ˙ <lb/> ∪K  h  [f  G  *  ]δ  Kg ˙ <lb/> ∪K  h  [ψ] <lb/>= <lb/> R  ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w  g  ] ⊗ R  ν  [ ˜ <lb/> w  h  ] | ˜ <lb/> w  G  *  |ψ <lb/> . <lb/> Applying this to ψ = (χ  N ,B  • κ <lb/> −1 <lb/>N ,B  )β <lb/>  *  ϕ and summing over all nested sets and <lb/>corresponding markings shows (14). The case of minimal subtraction works in the <lb/>same way (cf. the discussion in Section 5). This finishes the proof. <lb/> To connect the graph by graph method presented in this thesis with the Epstein-<lb/>Glaser construction we need to renormalize the sum of all graphs with a fixed vertex <lb/>order. Thus, we need a space that serves as a universal wonderful model for all <lb/>at most logarithmic graphs on n vertices. There are two obvious candidates, the <lb/>minimal and the maximal wonderful models of the graph lattice G for the complete <lb/>graph K  n  . Since every divergent subgraph of a graph is saturated, the set G(K  n  ) <lb/>contains all possible divergences of such a graph. In other words, these two models <lb/>are universal in the sense that for every graph G on n vertices there exist canonical <lb/>proper projections <lb/> p <lb/> G <lb/> max  : Y  G(Kn)  −→ Y  D(G)  , <lb/> (15) <lb/> p <lb/> G <lb/> min  : Y  I(G(Kn))  −→ Y  I(D(G))  . <lb/> (16) <lb/>This follows from Definition 3.3. The theorem above suggests to focus on minimal <lb/>building sets. Let Y denote Y  I(G(Kn))  and G be a connected and at most logarithmic <lb/>graph on n vertices. The idea is to compose the projection p <lb/> G <lb/> min  with the blowdown <lb/> β of the wonderful model Y  I(D(G))  and consider the pullback <lb/>  G  of v  G  under this <lb/>map. In the additional charts that cover the components of E ⊆ Y not correspond-<lb/>ing to elements of I(D(G)) we set the local densities <lb/>  G  to zero. Then we proceed <lb/>as before to obtain a renormalized density on Y . A detailed description is left for <lb/> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/>51 <lb/> future work, but we make one further observation that highlights the connection <lb/>between wonderful renormalization and the Epstein-Glaser method. Recall that the <lb/>wonderful model Y  I(G(Kn))  is equivalent to the Fulton-MacPherson compactification <lb/>of the configuration space F  n  (M ), for which the structure of I(G(K  n  ))-nested sets <lb/>is encoded by rooted trees [FM94]. As shown in [BK04], Epstein-Glaser renormal-<lb/>ization can also be formulated in terms of rooted trees. On the other hand, the Hopf <lb/>algebra of rooted trees H  rt  satisfies an universal property in the category of renor-<lb/>malization Hopf algebras [Kre13], as does the Fulton-MacPherson compactification <lb/>in the category of (minimal) wonderful models (cf. Equation (15))! <lb/>6.2. Connection to renormalization Hopf algebras. As shown in [BBK10], <lb/>the renormalization Hopf algebra of Feynman graphs is encoded in the stratification <lb/>of the exceptional divisor E of a wonderful model associated to a graph G. We <lb/>sketch the arguments and finish with a discussion of a Hopf algebraic formulation <lb/>of wonderful renormalization. <lb/>Let H be the free algebra on the vector space spanned by (isomorphism classes) <lb/>of connected, divergent (at most logarithmic) graphs. The multiplication on H is <lb/>given by disjoint union, the empty graph being the unit element. In [BK08] it is <lb/>shown that H endowed with a coproduct ∆ given by <lb/>∆(G) := <lb/> γ∈D <lb/> γ ⊗ G//γ <lb/> is indeed a Hopf algebra. To cope with the case of minimal building sets, i.e. <lb/>irreducible graphs, we can mod out by the ideal I generated by all irreducible <lb/>decompositions as defined in Section 3.2. Oñ <lb/> H := H/I it is the antipode S : <lb/>˜ <lb/> H → ˜ <lb/> H that disassembles G into parts determined by its irreducible divergent <lb/>subgraphs and prepares so the renormalization process. In terms of contraction <lb/>relative to nested sets S is given by <lb/> S(G) = <lb/> N <lb/> (−1) <lb/> |N | <lb/> γ∈N <lb/> γ//N <lb/> where the sum is over I(D(G))-nested sets. This is the starting point of Hopf al-<lb/>gebraic renormalization. The goal is then to formulate the whole wonderful renor-<lb/>malization process in terms of the convolution product of a twisted antipode with <lb/>Feynman rules, similar to renormalization in momentum or parametric space. This <lb/>is not straightforward due to the local formulation of the renormalization operators, <lb/>but motivated by another, more direct approach. The combinatorial character of <lb/>Zimmermann&apos;s forest formula is a first hint at a Hopf algebra structure underlying <lb/>renormalization. The locally defined wonderful renormalization operators resemble <lb/>the classical formula for subtracting divergences only in certain charts. To connect <lb/>with the forest formula and translate it into Hopf algebraic terms we could use the <lb/>following idea. It is based on the fact that if a graph has only subdivergences that <lb/>are nested into each other, then local subtractions resemble the forest formula cor-<lb/>rectly. Working modulo primitive elements of H, or <lb/> , every graph can be written <lb/>as a sum of graphs that behaves like an element with purely nested subdivergences <lb/>[BK08]. This shows that in principle wonderful renormalization fits into the Hopf <lb/>algebraic framework. Of course, it is worthwhile to establish the connection on a <lb/>more abstract level using geometrical methods. Once this is achieved, the whole <lb/></body>

			<page> 52 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> MARKO BERGHOFF <lb/></note>

			<body> world of renormalization Hopf algebras can be explored and used in the position <lb/>space setting. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [AS94] S. Axelrod and I. M. Singer. Chern-simons perturbation theory II. J. Diff. Geom., 39, <lb/>1994. <lb/>[Ati70] M. Atiyah. Resolution of singularities and division of distributions. Comm. Pure Appl. <lb/>Math., XXIII, 1970. <lb/>[BBK10] C. Bergbauer, R. Brunetti, and D. Kreimer. Renormalization and resolution of singu-<lb/>larities. arXiv:0908.0633, 2010. <lb/>[BD13] F. Brown and D. Doryn. Framings for graph hypersurfaces. arXiv:1301.3056v1, 2013. <lb/>[BEK06] S. Bloch, H. Esnault, and D. Kreimer. On motives associated to graph polynomials. <lb/> Commun. Math. Phys., 267, 2006. <lb/>[BF00] R. Brunetti and K. Fredenhagen. Microlocal analysis and interacting quantum field <lb/>theories: Renormalization on physical backgrounds. Commun. Math. Phys., 208, 2000. <lb/>[Bir67] G. Birkhoff. Lattice Theory. Colloquium Publications Vol. XXV. American Mathemati-<lb/>cal Society, 1967. <lb/>[BK04] C. Bergbauer and D. Kreimer. The hopf algebra of rooted trees in epstein-glaser renor-<lb/>malization. Ann. Henri Poincaré, 6, 2004. <lb/>[BK08] S. Bloch and D. Kreimer. Mixed hodge structures and renormalization in physics. Com-<lb/>mun. Numb. Theory and Phys., 2(4), 2008. <lb/>[Bro10] F. Brown. On the periods of some feynman integrals. arXiv:0910.0114v2, 2010. <lb/>[CK01] A. Connes and D. Kreimer. Renormalization in quantum field theory and the riemann-<lb/>hilbert problem II: the β-funcion, diffeomorphisms and the renormalization group. Com-<lb/>mun. Math. Phys., 216, 2001. <lb/>[Col84] J. Collins. Renormalization: An Introduction to Renormalization, the Renormalization <lb/>Group and the Operator Product Expansion. Cambridge Monographs on Mathematical <lb/>Physics. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, 1984. <lb/>[CP95] C. De Concini and C. Procesi. Wonderful models of subspace arrangements. Selecta <lb/>Math. (N.S.), 1(3), 1995. <lb/>[EFG07] K. Ebrahimi-Fard and L. Guo. Rota-baxter algebras in renormalization of perturbative <lb/>quantum field theory. Fields Inst. Commun., 50, 2007. <lb/>[EG73] H. Epstein and V. Glaser. The role of locality in perturbation theory. Ann. Poincare <lb/>Phys. Theor., A19, 1973. <lb/>[Fei05] E. M. Feichtner. De concini-procesi wonderful arrangement models: A discrete geome-<lb/>ter&apos;s point of view. Combinatorial and Computational Geometry, 52, 2005. <lb/>[FM94] W. Fulton and R. MacPherson. A compactification of configuration spaces. Ann. Math., <lb/> 139, 1994. <lb/>[GH94] P. Griffiths and J. Harris. Principles of Algebraic Geometry. Wiley Classics Library. <lb/>John Wiley &amp; Sons, 1994. <lb/>[GM87] M. Goresky and R. MacPherson. Stratified Morse Theory. Ergebnisse der Mathematik <lb/>und ihrer Grenzgebiete, Vol. 14. Springer, New York, 1987. <lb/>[GS64] I. M. Gelfand and G. E. Shilov. Generalized Functions I. Academic Press, New York, <lb/>1964. <lb/>[Hir64] H. Hironaka. Resolution of singularities of an algebraic variety over a field of character-<lb/>istic zero: I,II. Ann. of Math., 79(1,2), 1964. <lb/>[Hö90] <lb/>L. Hörmander. The Analysis of Linear Partial Differential Operators I, Distribution <lb/>Theory and Fourier Analysis. Classics in Mathematics. Springer, Berlin, second edition, <lb/>1990. <lb/>[Kol07] J. Kollár. Lectures on Resolution of Singularities. Annals of Mathematics Studies, 166. <lb/>Princeton University Press, 2007. <lb/>[Kon94] M. Kontsevich. Feynman diagrams and low-dimensional topology, in: First European <lb/>Congress of Math. (Paris 1992), Vol. II. Progress in Mathematics, 120. Birkhäuser, <lb/>1994. <lb/>[Kre13] D. Kreimer. Renormalization &amp; renormalization group. Unpublished lecture notes by L. <lb/>Klaczynski, 2013. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> WONDERFUL COMPACIFICATIONS IN QUANTUM FIELD THEORY <lb/></note>

			<page>53 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [Li09] <lb/> L. Li. Wonderful compactification of an arrangement of subvarieties. Michigan Math. <lb/>J., 58(2), 2009. <lb/>[Nic07] L. I. Nicolaescu. Lectures on the Geometry of Manifolds. World Scientific Publishing <lb/>Company, second edition, 2007. <lb/>[Sch10] O. Schnetz. Quantum periods: A census of φ  4  transcendentals. Commun. Numb. Theory <lb/>and Phys., 4(1), 2010. <lb/>[Sta97] R. P. Stanley. Enumerative Combinatorics I. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, <lb/>second edition, 1997. <lb/>[SW00] R.F. Streater and A.S. Wightman. PCT, Spin and Statistics, and All That. Landmarks <lb/>in Physics. Princeton University Press, 2000. <lb/>[Uly02] A. P. Ulyanov. Polydiagonal compactification of configuration spaces. J. Algebraic <lb/>Geom., 11(1), 2002. <lb/>[Wei96] S. Weinberg. The Quantum Theory of Fields I. Cambridge University Press, second <lb/>edition, 1996. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
