<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> ANALYSIS OF HIGH ORDER MODES DAMPING TECHNIQUES FOR 800 <lb/>MHZ SINGLE CELL SUPERCONDUCTING CAVITIES* <lb/> Ya.V. Shashkov, N.P. Sobenin, National Research Nuclear University MEPhI <lb/>(Moscow Engineering Physics Institute), Moscow, Russia <lb/>M.M. Zobov, LNF-INFN, Frascati (Rome), Italy <lb/> Abstract <lb/> The High Luminosity LHC upgrade program foresees a <lb/>possibility of using the second harmonic cavities working <lb/>at 800 MHz for the collider bunch length variation. Such <lb/>harmonic cavities should provide an opportunity to vary <lb/>the length of colliding bunches. In order to supply the <lb/>required harmonic voltage several single cell <lb/>superconducting cavities are to be used. Different cavity <lb/>designs and several higher order mode (HOM) damping <lb/>techniques are being studied in order to reduce the cavity <lb/>HOM impact on the beam stability and to minimize <lb/>parasitic power losses. In this paper we analyze and <lb/>compare the HOM electromagnetic characteristics and <lb/>respective wake potential decay rates for cavities with <lb/>grooves, fluted and ridged beam pipes. The problem of <lb/>Lorentz force detuning is also addressed. <lb/></front>

			<body> INTRODUCTION <lb/> At present the project aimed at Large Hadron Collider <lb/>luminosity upgrade (HL-LHC) is being developed at <lb/>CERN [1]. The luminosity increase is expected to be <lb/>accomplished by increasing the currents of circulating <lb/>beams, by reducing transverse beam sizes at the <lb/>interaction points (applying smaller betatron functions) <lb/>and using crab cavities to compensate the geometric <lb/>luminosity loss in beam collisions [2]. <lb/>The project considers also a possible implementation of <lb/>harmonic cavities in addition to the main accelerating <lb/>cavities working at 400 MHz to increase or to shorten the <lb/>bunches [3-7]. In order to achieve the desired results a <lb/>combination of the existing main RF cavities and <lb/>harmonic cavities operating at 800 MHz is being studied. <lb/>In this paper we study electromagnetic characteristics of <lb/>HOMs for a single cell 800 MHz superconducting cavity. <lb/>Different techniques for the HOM damping such as beam <lb/>pipe grooves, fluted beam pipes, ridged beam pipes etc. <lb/>are investigated and compared. <lb/> HIGHER ORDER MODES DAMPING <lb/> Basic Design <lb/> An initial design of the harmonic cavity has been <lb/>obtained by scaling (reducing) all the sizes of the LHC <lb/>accelerating cavity operating at 400 MHz by a factor of 2 <lb/>[8]. The cavity view is shown in Fig. 1. It is assumed in <lb/>[8] that higher order modes damping is carried out, as in <lb/>the case of the LHC accelerating cavity, with four <lb/>couplers: two dipole and two broadband couplers. These <lb/>couplers break the cylindrical symmetry of the <lb/>electromagnetic field in the structure which gives rise to <lb/>the transverse component of the electric field (kick-factor) <lb/>causing a negative impact on the performance of the <lb/>accelerated beam. Besides, the transient beam loading <lb/>compensation in LHC requires a very high power main <lb/>coupler [9]. Placing the robust main coupler and the <lb/>HOM couplers on the same beam pipe may complicate <lb/>the final design. That&apos;s why different HOM damping <lb/>techniques were investigated. <lb/>Figure 1: Accelerating <lb/>cavity. <lb/>Figure 2: Cavity with <lb/>grooved beam pipes. <lb/>We started our analysis by calculating the resonance <lb/>frequency and the effective resistance to quality factor Q <lb/>ratio (parameter R/Q 0 ) for the cavity shown in Fig. 1 by <lb/>varying the drift tube radius. It was found that the most <lb/>dangerous dipole HOM are TE 111 and TM 110 . The <lb/>frequency of these dipole HOMs lie below the cut-off <lb/>frequency of the TE 11 wave and therefore cannot <lb/>propagate along the drift tube [10]. HOMs couplers <lb/>should be placed as close as possible to the accelerating <lb/>cavity for the effective damping of such trapped modes. <lb/> Beam Pipe with Grooves <lb/> Another way to damp the HOMs is to cover the inner <lb/>surface of the drift tubes with a dissipative material and <lb/>let the HOMs propagate toward the absorbing load. This <lb/>method is effective if the higher order mode frequencies <lb/>become lower than the beam pipe cut-off frequency. Such <lb/>a task can be accomplished by using grooved structures <lb/>[11], i.e. cavities with grooves, as shown in Fig. 2. <lb/>The main advantage of the grooved structure is its <lb/>cylindrical symmetry providing the same level of <lb/>effective damping of HOMs with different polarizations. <lb/>The absence of HOM couplers makes the design simpler <lb/>and eliminates eventual negative impact of the couplers <lb/>on beam dynamics due to the field distortion at their <lb/>locations. <lb/>The results of simulations with ABCI code [12] clearly <lb/>demonstrate that by choosing the beam pipe radius and <lb/>the groove geometry in a proper way we have managed to <lb/>obtain a truly &quot; single mode &quot; cavity. Figure 3a shows the <lb/>simulated cavity shape, while Figs 3b shows respectively <lb/></body>

			<front> ___________________________________________ <lb/> *Work supported by RFBR grant 13-02-00562/14 and by the EU FP7 <lb/>HiLumi LHC -Grant Agreement 284404 <lb/> </front>

			<note place="headnote"> Proceedings of RuPAC2014, Obninsk, Kaluga Region, Russia <lb/>THPSC16 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> 09 Superconducting accelerators and cryogenics <lb/>ISBN 978-3-95450-170-0 <lb/></note>

			<page>353 <lb/></page>

			<front>Copyright © 2014 CC-BY-3.0 and by the respective authors <lb/></front>

			<body> the dipole wake potential. We should not expect <lb/>multibunch instabilities since the wake field decays <lb/>completely at the distance of 15 m that corresponds to the <lb/>actual bunch separation of 50 ns in LHC. <lb/>Figure 3: Wakefield results for the structure with grooved <lb/>beam pipe (a. Structure profile, b. Wake potential, c. <lb/>Monopole impedance). <lb/> Fluted Beam Pipe <lb/> Structure with fluted beam pipes [13] is demonstrated <lb/>in Figure 4. <lb/>Figure 4: Structure with 4 (a) and 3 (b) flutes. <lb/>The effect of the fluted beam pipe size on cutoff <lb/>frequencies of the TM 01 , TE 11 , TE 21 waves was <lb/>investigated with MWS program [14]. It was found that <lb/>the sizes of the edges do not change the cutoff frequency <lb/>of the wave TM 01 but have a strong influence on the <lb/>cutoff frequency of TE 11 and TE 21 waves and hence the <lb/>damping of the TE 111 , TM 110 , TE 211 , TM 210 modes. It was <lb/>found that the configuration with 3 flutes instead of 4, as <lb/>in [13], has higher damping efficiency for quadrupole <lb/>modes. <lb/>Fig 5. Wakefield results for the structure with fluted beam <lb/>pipe (a. Dipole Wake potential, b. Monopole impedance, <lb/>c. Dipole impedance). <lb/>In this structure Q ext are below 100 for all HOMs except <lb/>for a few modes with low R/Q ratio and the wake <lb/>potential decays very fast (fig 5a). Respectively there are <lb/>no sharp peaks on monopole (fig 5b) and dipole (fig 5c) <lb/>impedance graphs except the one corresponding to the <lb/>operating mode. <lb/> Ridged Beam Pipe <lb/> The fluted beam pipe damping efficiency could be <lb/>improved if we reverse flutes inward the beam pipe (fig <lb/>6). In this case the cut off frequencies for quadrupole and <lb/>dipole modes decrease and this allows reducing the beam <lb/>pipe radius. The calculated wake field decays for this <lb/>structure is presented in fig 7a. <lb/> Figure 6: Structure <lb/>with ridged beam <lb/>pipe. <lb/>Figure 7a. Wake potential. <lb/>Fig 7b-c. Wakefield results for the structure with <lb/>ridged beam pipe (7b. Monopole impedance, 7c. <lb/>Dipole impedance). <lb/> As it can be seen the wake potential decays very fast <lb/>also in this case. On the other hand, the cut-off frequency <lb/>of E 010 mode is also lower for this configuration which <lb/>can lead to a deeper penetration of the working mode <lb/>towards the load. To prevent decreasing Q 0 of the <lb/>working mode beam pipe length can be chosen longer <lb/>than that in fluted bam pipe case. Sharp peaks on the <lb/>HOM monopole (fig 7b) and dipole (fig 7c) impedance <lb/>graphs are not observed. <lb/> LORENZ FORCE DETUNING <lb/> Lorenz force frequency detuning was investigated for <lb/>the discussed HOMs damping methods. As an example <lb/>deformations of the grooved structure due to the influence <lb/>of the Lorentz force are shown in Figure 8. <lb/>Figure 8: Grooved structure <lb/>deformations due to the <lb/>influence of the Lorentz force <lb/>(dotted line – structure, solid <lb/>line– deformed structure). <lb/>Figure 9: Structure with <lb/>grooves and stiffeners. <lb/>The ratio of frequency detuning to the square of the <lb/>electric field strength can be considered as a quality <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> THPSC16 <lb/> Proceedings of RuPAC2014, Obninsk, Kaluga Region, Russia <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">ISBN 978-3-95450-170-0 <lb/></note>

			<page>354 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Copyright © 2014 CC-BY-3.0 and by the respective authors <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> 09 Superconducting accelerators and cryogenics <lb/></note>

			<body> criterion for the influence of the Lorentz force on the <lb/>structure. The Lorentz force sensitivity can be decreased <lb/>by increasing the cavity wall thickness or by adding of <lb/>specific stiffeners schematically depicted in Fig. 9 to the <lb/>structure design [15]. <lb/>The calculations were carried out for the structure <lb/>consisting of copper with Young&apos;s coefficients 120 <lb/>kN/mm <lb/> 2 (Table 1). One end of the cavity beam pipe is <lb/>considered rigidly fixed during the calculations of <lb/>frequency detuning. <lb/>Table 1. Lorenz force frequency detuning <lb/>Structure type (beam pipe/beam pipe <lb/>outer radius, mm) <lb/>Copper structure <lb/> Δf/ΔE <lb/> 2  , Hz <lb/>Smooth structure(75) <lb/>-6.3 <lb/>Grooved structure(75/105) <lb/>-6.3 <lb/>Grooved structure with stiffners <lb/>(75/105) <lb/>0.2 <lb/>Fluted beam pipe structure (75/120) <lb/>-6.1 <lb/>Table 1 shows that the Δf/ΔE <lb/> 2 ratio is smallest for the <lb/>structure with grooves and stiffening ribs. <lb/> COMPARISON OF DESIGN SOLUTIONS <lb/> Table 2 shows that each of the considered methods of <lb/>HOMs damping has its own advantages and <lb/>disadvantages. <lb/>Table 2. Comparison of characteristics of calculated <lb/>structures <lb/>Grooved <lb/>structure <lb/>Fluted <lb/>beam pipe <lb/>structure <lb/>Ridged <lb/>beam pipe <lb/>Q ext in single <lb/>cell cavity <lb/>&lt;10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> &lt;10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> &lt;10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> Lorenz force <lb/>detuning <lb/> Δf/ΔE <lb/> 2 , Hz <lb/>0.2 <lb/>-6.8 <lb/>-6.8 <lb/>Symmetrical <lb/>structure <lb/>Yes <lb/>No <lb/>No <lb/>Additional <lb/>Easy in <lb/>manufac-<lb/>turing <lb/>Quadrupo <lb/>le modes <lb/>damping <lb/>Quadrupo <lb/>le modes <lb/>damping <lb/>In our opinion, the structure with grooves seems to be a <lb/>more suitable candidate for the 800 MHz cavity design <lb/>since: a) it has simplest azimuthally symmetric geometry; <lb/>b) there are no dangerous HOM created in the structure; <lb/>c) no dedicated HOM couplers are required; d) an <lb/>eventual multipacting discharge in the equatorial region at <lb/>rather low accelerating gradients can be cured by an <lb/>additional purification of the cavity surface and <lb/>subsequent training; e) the Lorentz force detuning can be <lb/>significantly reduced by inserted ring stiffeners in the <lb/>grooves. <lb/>In the following we also consider a possibility to <lb/>combine several such structures in a chain of non-<lb/>communicating cavities in order to place them in a single <lb/>cryostat. <lb/> CONCLUSION <lb/> We have compared four different HOM damping <lb/>techniques for the 800 MHz harmonic cavity. In our <lb/>opinion, the solution with grooves is preferable due to its <lb/>cylindrical symmetry, design simplicity and absence of <lb/>dangerous HOMs. We have also proposed to combine two <lb/>such cavities connected by smaller radius beam pipe in a <lb/>single cryostat [16]. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> REFERENCES <lb/> [1] L. Rossi, LHC upgrade plans: options and strategy, <lb/>IPAC2011, p.908. <lb/>[2] O.Bruning, F.Zimmermann, Parameter space for the <lb/>LHC luminosity upgrade, IPAC2012, p. 127. <lb/>[3] O. Bruning et al., LHC Luminosity and Energy <lb/>Upgrade: A Feasibility Study, LHC Project Report <lb/>626, 2002. <lb/>[4] F. Ruggiero and F. Zimmermann, Luminosity <lb/>Optimisation near the Beam-Beam Limit by <lb/>Increasing the Bunch Length or Crossing Angle, <lb/>CERN-SL-2002-005-REV (AP), 2002. <lb/>[5] F. Ruggiero and F. Zimmermann, Possible Scenario <lb/>for an LHC Upgrade &quot; , CARE-Conf-05-002-HHH, <lb/>Proc. of the HHH 2004 Workshop, Geneva, <lb/>November 2004. <lb/>[6] T. Linnecar and E. Shaposhnikova, An RF System <lb/>for Landau Damping in the LHC, LHC Project Note <lb/>394, 2007. <lb/>[7] D. Shatilov, M. Zobov, On the Possibility of <lb/>Utilizing Flat Longitudinal Beam Profiles to <lb/>Increase the Luminosity in Collisions with Large <lb/>Piwinski Angle, 14/04/2012 (unpublished) <lb/>[8] Ficcadenti F. et al., LHC Landau Cavity Design // <lb/>BE-RF CERN, BR section meeting, March 29, 2012 <lb/>[9] P. Baudrenghien, T. Mastoridis, Power requirement <lb/>for the harmonic cavities in the full-detuning <lb/>scheme, CERN BE-RF 2nd LHC Harmonic Cavity <lb/>meeting, May 27 <lb/> th ,2013. <lb/>[10] N.Sobenin, B.Zverev, ElectrodynamicCharacte-<lb/>ristics of Accelerating Cavities, Foundation for <lb/>International Scientific and Education Cooperation. <lb/>Gordon and Breach Science Publishers S.A. 1999 <lb/>[11] S. Kurokawa, Present Status of KEK-B Project, <lb/>EPAC, p. 448 (1996). <lb/>[12] http://abci.kek.jp/ <lb/>[13] H. Padamsee et al., Accelerating Cavity <lb/>Development for the Cornell B-Factory, CESR-B, <lb/>Accelerator Science and Technology. vol. 2, 1991, <lb/> р. 786 – 788. <lb/>[14] https://www.cst.com/ <lb/>[15] R.Mitchell,K.Matsumoto,G.Ciovati,etal.,Lorentzforc <lb/>edetuning for the SNS cavities,LLRFWorkshop, <lb/>2001. <lb/>[16] Ya. Shashkov et al., Comparison of higher order <lb/>modes damping techniques for array of single cell <lb/>cavities, this proceedings, This Proceedings. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> Proceedings of RuPAC2014, Obninsk, Kaluga Region, Russia <lb/>THPSC16 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> 09 Superconducting accelerators and cryogenics <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">ISBN 978-3-95450-170-0 <lb/></note>

			<page>355 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Copyright © 2014 CC-BY-3.0 and by the respective authors </note>


	</text>
</tei>
