<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Umbral Moonshine and Linear Codes <lb/> John F. R. Duncan <lb/>  * <lb/> 7 June 2013 <lb/> Abstract <lb/> We exhibit each of the finite groups of umbral moonshine as a distinguished subgroup of <lb/>the automorphism group of a distinguished linear code, each code being defined over a different <lb/>quotient of the ring of integers. These code constructions entail permutation representations <lb/>which we use to give a description of the multiplier systems of the vector-valued mock modular <lb/>forms attached to the conjugacy classes of the umbral groups by umbral moonshine. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> In 2010 Eguchi–Ooguri–Tachikawa made a remarkable observation [1] relating the elliptic genus <lb/>of a K3 surface to the largest Mathieu group M  24  via a decomposition of the former into a linear <lb/>combination of characters of irreducible representations of the small N = 4 superconformal <lb/>algebra. The elliptic genus is a topological invariant and for any K3 surface it is given by the <lb/>weak Jacobi form <lb/> Z  K3  (τ, z) = 8 <lb/> θ  2  (τ, z) <lb/>θ  2  (τ, 0) <lb/>  2 <lb/> + <lb/> θ  3  (τ, z) <lb/>θ  3  (τ, 0) <lb/>  2 <lb/> + <lb/> θ  4  (τ, z) <lb/>θ  4  (τ, 0) <lb/>  2 <lb/> (1.1) <lb/>of weight 0 and index 1. The θ  i  here denote Jacobi theta functions (cf. (B.3)). The decompo-<lb/>sition into N = 4 characters leads to an expression <lb/> Z  K3  (τ, z) = <lb/> θ  1  (τ, z) <lb/> 2 <lb/> η(τ )  3 <lb/> 24 µ(τ, z) + q <lb/> −1/8  <lb/> − 2 + <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=1 <lb/> t  n  q <lb/> n  <lb/> (1.2) <lb/>for some t  n  ∈ Z (cf. [2]) where θ  1  (τ, z) and µ(τ, z) are defined in (B.3-B.4). By inspection, the <lb/>first five t  n  are given by t  1  = 90, t  2  = 462, t  3  = 1540, t  4  = 4554, and t  5  = 11592; the observation <lb/></body>

			<front>  *  Department of Mathematics, Case Western Reserve University, Cleveland, OH 44106, U.S.A. <lb/> E-mail: john.duncan@case.edu <lb/></front>

			<page> 1 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Umbral Moonshine and Linear Codes <lb/></note>

			<page> 2 <lb/></page>

			<body> of [1] is that each of these t  n  is twice the dimension of an irreducible representation of M  24  (cf. <lb/>[3]). <lb/>Experience with monstrous moonshine [4, 5, 6], for example, leads us to conjecture that every <lb/> t  n  may be interpreted as the dimension of an M  24  -module K <lb/> (2) <lb/> n−1/8  , and that, assuming such a <lb/>module structure to be known, we may obtain interesting functions by replacing t  n  = tr|  K <lb/> (2) <lb/> n−1/8 <lb/> 1 <lb/>with tr|  K <lb/> (2) <lb/> n−1/8 <lb/> g for non-identity elements g ∈ M  24  . If we define H <lb/> (2)  (τ ) by requiring <lb/> Z  K3  (τ, z)η(τ ) <lb/> 3  = θ  1  (τ, z) <lb/> 2  (aµ(τ, z) + H <lb/> (2)  (τ )), <lb/>(1.3) <lb/>then a = 24 and <lb/> H <lb/> (2)  (τ ) = q <lb/> −1/8 <lb/> −2 + <lb/> n&gt;0 <lb/> t  n  q <lb/> n <lb/> (1.4) <lb/>is a slight modification of the generating function of the t  n  . The inclusion of the term −2 and <lb/>the factor q <lb/> −1/8  = e <lb/> −2πiτ /8  has the effect of improving the modularity: H <lb/> (2)  (τ ) is a (weak) <lb/> mock modular form for SL  2  (Z) with multiplier <lb/> −3  (cf. (B.2)), weight 1/2, and shadow 24η <lb/> 3  (cf. <lb/>(B.1)), meaning that if we define the completion  <lb/> (2)  (τ ) of the holomorphic function H <lb/> (2)  (τ ) <lb/>by setting <lb/> (2)  (τ ) = H <lb/> (2)  (τ ) + 24 (4i) <lb/> −1/2 <lb/>  ∞ <lb/>−¯ τ <lb/> (z + τ ) <lb/> −1/2  η(−¯ z)  3  dz, <lb/>(1.5) <lb/>then <lb/> (2)  (τ ) transforms as a modular form of weight 1/2 on SL  2  (Z) with multiplier system <lb/>conjugate to that of η(τ ) <lb/> 3  , so that we have <lb/> (γ) <lb/> −3  <lb/> (2)  (γτ )j(γ, τ ) <lb/> 1/2  = ˆ <lb/> H <lb/> (2)  (τ ) <lb/>for γ ∈ SL  2  (Z) where j(γ, τ ) = (cτ + d) <lb/> −1  when (c, d) is the lower row of γ. <lb/> The McKay–Thompson series H <lb/> (2) <lb/> g <lb/> for g ∈ M  24  is now defined—assuming knowledge of the <lb/> M  24  -module structure on K <lb/> (2)  = <lb/> n  K <lb/> (2) <lb/> n−1/8  —by setting <lb/> H <lb/> (2) <lb/> g  (τ ) = −2q <lb/> −1/8  + <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=1 <lb/> tr|  K  n−1/8  (g)q <lb/> n−1/8 <lb/> (1.6) <lb/>where q = e(τ ) = e <lb/> 2πiτ  . Actually the functions H <lb/> (2) <lb/> g <lb/> are more accessible than M  24  -module K <lb/> (2) <lb/> (for which no concrete construction is yet known) since one only needs to know tr|  K  n−1/8  g for <lb/>a few values of n if one assumes the function H <lb/> (2) <lb/> g <lb/> to have good modular properties. Concrete <lb/>proposals made in [7, 8, 9, 10] entail the prediction that H <lb/> (2) <lb/> g <lb/> should be a certain concretely <lb/>defined (cf. [2]) mock modular form of weight 1/2 for Γ  0  (n  g  ) with shadow proportional to <lb/> −3 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Umbral Moonshine and Linear Codes <lb/></note>

			<page> 3 <lb/></page>

			<body> where n  g  is the order of g ∈ M  24  , and the existence of a compatible M  24  -module K <lb/> (2)  has now <lb/>been established by Gannon [11]. <lb/>In [12] it was shown that the observation of Eguchi–Ooguri–Tachikawa belongs to a family of <lb/>relationships—umbral moonshine—between finite groups G <lb/> ()  and vector-valued mock modular <lb/>forms H <lb/> () <lb/> g  = (H <lb/> () <lb/> g,1  , . . . , H <lb/> () <lb/> g,,−1  ) for g ∈ G <lb/> ()  , that support the existence of infinite-dimensional <lb/>bi-graded G <lb/> ()  -modules <lb/> K <lb/> ()  = <lb/> 0&lt;r&lt;&lt; <lb/> n <lb/> K <lb/> () <lb/> r,n−r  2  /4  , <lb/> (1.7) <lb/>where the G <lb/> ()  -module structure on K <lb/> ()  is conjectured to be related to the vector-valued mock <lb/>modular form H <lb/> () <lb/> g  = (H <lb/> () <lb/> g,r  ) via <lb/> H <lb/> () <lb/> g,r  (τ ) = −2δ  r,1  q <lb/> −1/4  + <lb/> n∈Z <lb/>r <lb/> 2  −4nn&lt;0 <lb/> tr|  K <lb/> () <lb/> r,n−r 2 /4 <lb/> (g)q <lb/> n−r <lb/> 2  /4  . <lb/> (1.8) <lb/>The cases of umbral moonshine presented in [12] are indexed by the positive integers <lb/> such that  − 1 divides 12. In this note we give constructions of the umbral groups G <lb/> ()  as <lb/>automorphisms of linear codes over rings Z//, and we show, as an application, how to use the <lb/>resulting permutation representations to describe the multiplier systems of the umbral McKay– <lb/>Thompson series H <lb/> () <lb/> g  . <lb/> Table 1: The groups of umbral moonshine. <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>7 <lb/>13 <lb/> G  ()  M  24  2.M  12  2.AGL  3  (2) GL  2  (5)/2 SL  2  (3) Z/4Z <lb/> It is striking that the codes arising all appear in the article [13] written in connection with <lb/>the Leech lattice. One consequence is that each of the umbral groups G <lb/> ()  may be regarded <lb/>as a subgroup of the Conway group Co  0  , this being the automorphism group of the Leech <lb/>lattice. Another consequence is the suggestion that there might be analogous cases of umbral <lb/>moonshine for the remaining 17 codes (or equivalently, Niemeier root systems) appearing in [13]. <lb/>Confirmation of this suggestion will be demonstrated in a forthcoming article [14]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Umbral Moonshine and Linear Codes <lb/></note>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<body> 2 Codes <lb/> In this section we review the notion of linear code over a ring Z/m and define a distinguished <lb/>linear code G <lb/> ()  over Z// for each  such that  − 1 divides 12. <lb/>A (linear) code over Z/m of length n is a Z/m-submodule of (Z/m) <lb/> n  . Let {e  i  | i ∈ Ω} <lb/>denote the standard basis for (Z/m) <lb/> n  , the index set Ω having cardinality n. We equip (Z/m) <lb/> n <lb/> with a Z/m-valued Z/m-bilinear form by setting (C, C <lb/>  ) = <lb/> i∈Ω  c  i  c <lb/> i  in case C = <lb/> i∈Ω  c  i  e  i  and <lb/> C <lb/>  = <lb/> i∈Ω  c <lb/> i  e  i  , and given S ⊂ (Z/m) <lb/> n  we define S <lb/> ⊥  = {D ∈ (Z/m) <lb/> n  | (C, D) = 0, ∀C ∈ S}. <lb/> We say that a code C &lt; (Z/m) <lb/> n  is self-orthogonal in case C ⊂ C <lb/> ⊥  and we say that C is self-dual if <lb/>it is maximally self-orthogonal, meaning that C = C <lb/> ⊥  . Given a code C of length n over Z/m we <lb/>define Aut(C) to be the subgroup of GL  n  (Z/m) that stabilizes the subspace C &lt; (Z/m) <lb/> n  , and <lb/>we define Aut <lb/> ±  (C) to be the subgroup of Aut(C) consisting of signed coordinate permutations, <lb/>meaning that <lb/>Aut <lb/> ±  (C) = {γ ∈ GL  n  (Z/m) | γ(C) ⊂ C and γ(B) ⊂ B} <lb/> (2.1) <lb/>where B denotes the set {±e  i  | i ∈ Ω}. Observe that Aut(C) and Aut <lb/> ±  (C) coincide when <lb/> m ∈ {2, 3, 4}, but are generally different otherwise. <lb/>We now identify a distinguished linear code G <lb/> ()  over Z// for each  such that  − 1 divides <lb/>12. The code G <lb/> ()  will have length 24/( − 1) and the construction we give will be either a <lb/>rephrasing or direct reproduction of a construction given (much earlier) in [13]. In particular, it <lb/>will develop that G <lb/> (2)  is the extended binary Golay code and G <lb/> (3)  is the extended ternary Golay <lb/>code. The remaining G <lb/> ()  are visible, in a certain sense, inside the Leech lattice (cf. [13]) and <lb/>may be regarded as natural analogues of the extended binary and ternary Golay codes defined <lb/>over larger quotients of the ring of integers. <lb/>To define G <lb/> (2)  equip (Z/2) <lb/> 24  with the standard basis {e  i  } and index this basis with the set <lb/>Ω <lb/> (2)  = {∞} ∪ Z/23. Let N be the subset of Ω <lb/> (2)  consisting of the elements of Z/23 that are not <lb/>squares in Z/23, so that N = {5, 7, 10, 11, 14, 15, 17, 19, 20, 21, 22}, and define <lb/> C  i  = e  ∞  + <lb/> n∈N <lb/> e  n+i  ∈ (Z/2) <lb/> 24 <lb/> (2.2) <lb/>for i ∈ Z/23. Then the subspace of (Z/2) <lb/> 24  generated by the set {C  i  | i ∈ Z/23} is a self-dual <lb/>linear code over Z/2 of length 24 which we denote G <lb/> (2)  . In fact, G <lb/> (2)  is a copy of the extended <lb/>binary Golay code (see various chapters in [15] for more details) and the automorphism group <lb/>of G <lb/> (2)  is isomorphic to the largest Mathieu group, M  24  . The group G <lb/> (2)  defined in [12] is also <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Umbral Moonshine and Linear Codes <lb/></note>

			<page> 5 <lb/></page>

			<body> isomorphic to M  24  so we have Aut <lb/> ±  (G <lb/> (2)  ) = Aut(G <lb/> (2)  )  G <lb/> (2)  . <lb/>To define G <lb/> (3)  equip (Z/3) <lb/> 12  with the standard basis {e  i  } and take the index set to be <lb/>Ω <lb/> (3)  = {∞} ∪ Z/11. The set of non-squares in Z/11 is N = {2, 6, 7, 8, 10}. Let Q be the <lb/>complement of N in Z/11, so that Q = {0, 1, 3, 4, 5, 9}, and define C  i  ∈ (Z/3) <lb/> 12  for i ∈ Z/11 by <lb/>setting <lb/> C  i  = 2e  ∞  + <lb/> n∈N <lb/> 2e  n+i  + <lb/> n∈Q <lb/> e  n+i  ∈ (Z/3) <lb/> 12  . <lb/> (2.3) <lb/>Then the code G <lb/> (3)  generated by the C  i  is a copy of the extended ternary Golay code (cf. <lb/>[15]) and the automorphism group of G <lb/> (3)  is isomorphic to a group 2.M  12  , being the unique <lb/>(up to isomorphism) non-trivial double cover of the Mathieu group M  12  (cf. [3]). Again we <lb/>have Aut <lb/> ±  (G <lb/> (3)  ) = Aut(G <lb/> (3)  ) and the group G <lb/> (3)  defined in [12] is also isomorphic to 2.M  12  , so <lb/>Aut <lb/> ±  (G <lb/> (3)  )  G <lb/> (3)  . <lb/>For  = 4 equip (Z/4) <lb/> 8  with the standard basis, indexed by Ω  (4)  = {∞} ∪ Z/7, let N denote <lb/>the set {3, 5, 6} of non-squares in Z/7, and define C  i  ∈ (Z/4) <lb/> 8  for i ∈ Z/7 by setting <lb/> C  i  = 3e  ∞  + 2e  i  + <lb/> n∈N <lb/> e  n+i  ∈ (Z/4) <lb/> 8  . <lb/> (2.4) <lb/>Define G <lb/> (4)  to be the Z/4-submodule of (Z/4) <lb/> 8  generated by the set {C  i  | i ∈ Z/7}. Then G <lb/> (4) <lb/> is a copy of the octacode [16] (see also [17,  §3.2]). The automorphism group of G <lb/> (4)  has a central <lb/>subgroup of order 2, generated by the symmetry C = (c  i  ) → (−c  i  ), and modulo this central <lb/>subgroup we obtain the affine general linear group of degree 3 over a field with 2 elements, which <lb/>is the same as the stabilizer in GL  4  (2) of a line in (Z/2) <lb/> 4  . Comparing with the definition of <lb/> G <lb/> (4)  given in [12] we find that Aut <lb/> ±  (G <lb/> (4)  ) = Aut(G <lb/> (4)  )  G <lb/> (4)  . <lb/>Now consider the case that  = 5. Index the standard basis of (Z/5) <lb/> 6  with the set Ω <lb/> (5)  = <lb/> {∞} ∪ {0, 1, 2, 3, 4} and define <lb/> C  i  = e  ∞  + e  1+i  + 4e  2+i  + 4e  3+i  + e  4+i  ∈ (Z/5) <lb/> 6 <lb/> (2.5) <lb/>for i ∈ Z/5. Then the C  i  generate a self-dual code G <lb/> (5)  &lt; (Z/5) <lb/> 6  . We see that Aut <lb/> ±  (G <lb/> (5)  ) is a <lb/>proper subgroup of Aut(G <lb/> (5)  ) since the latter contains the central element e  i  → 2e  i  , for example, <lb/>which does not preserve B = {±e  i  }. The group Aut <lb/> ±  (G <lb/> (5)  ) is a double cover of S  5  , regarded <lb/>as a permutation group on 6 points via the isomorphism S  5  PGL  2  (5). The particular double <lb/>cover arising is perhaps a little unfamiliar in that it does not contain the Schur double cover of <lb/> A  5  as a subgroup; it can be realized explicitly as the quotient of GL  2  (5) by its unique central <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Umbral Moonshine and Linear Codes <lb/></note>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<body> subgroup of order 2. (Note that the centre of GL  2  (5) is cyclic of order 4.) Upon comparison <lb/>with [12] we conclude that Aut <lb/> ±  (G <lb/> (5)  )  G <lb/> (5)  . <lb/>For  = 7 we take Ω <lb/> (7)  = {∞} ∪ Z/3 as an index set for the standard basis of (Z/7) <lb/> 4  and we <lb/>define C  i  ∈ (Z/7) <lb/> 4  by setting <lb/> C  i  = e  ∞  + 2e  i  + e  1+i  + 6e  2+i  ∈ (Z/7) <lb/> 4 <lb/> (2.6) <lb/>for i ∈ Z/3. We define G <lb/> (7)  to be the Z/7-submodule generated by the C  i  for i ∈ Z/3 and <lb/>observe that G <lb/> (7)  is a self-dual code over Z/7 with Aut <lb/> ±  (G <lb/> (7)  ) a double cover of PSL  2  (3)  A  4  . <lb/>In fact the double cover arising is SL  2  (3) and we have Aut <lb/> ±  (G <lb/> (7)  )  G <lb/> (7)  . <lb/>The remaining code is G <lb/> (13)  which has length 2 = 24/(13 − 1) and which we may take to <lb/>be generated by e  ∞  + 5e  0  ∈ (Z/13) <lb/> 2  . (In this case we set Ω <lb/> (13)  = {∞} ∪ Z/1.) The code <lb/> G <lb/> (13)  is self-dual (since 1 <lb/> 2  + 5 <lb/> 2  ≡ 0 (mod 13)) and Aut <lb/> ±  (G <lb/> (13)  ) is cyclic of order 4, generated <lb/>explicitly by (c  ∞  , c  0  ) → (c  0  , −c  ∞  ). Once again we find Aut <lb/> ±  (G <lb/> (13)  )  G <lb/> (13)  and we conclude <lb/>that Aut <lb/> ±  (G <lb/> ()  )  G <lb/> ()  for all  (such that  − 1 divides 12). <lb/> 3 Automorphy <lb/> We now take G <lb/> ()  = Aut <lb/> ±  (G <lb/> ()  ) for  ∈ {2, 3, 4, 5, 7, 13} and give an explanation of how these <lb/>constructions may be used to describe the automorphy of the vector-valued mock modular forms <lb/> H <lb/> () <lb/> g  attached (in [12]) to the elements of G <lb/> ()  via umbral moonshine. <lb/>Observe that G <lb/> ()  is a code of length 24/( − 1) over Z// for each . Thus we obtain a <lb/>permutation representation of degree 24 for G <lb/> ()  by considering its action on the set <lb/> {ce  i  | i ∈ Ω <lb/> ()  , c ∈ Z//, c  = 0} <lb/>(3.1) <lb/>of non-zero multiplies of the basis vectors e  i  . Write <lb/>  g  for the cycle shape attached to g ∈ G <lb/> () <lb/> arising from this permutation representation and write g → ˜ <lb/> χ  g  for the corresponding character <lb/>of G <lb/> ()  . Then, for example, ˜ <lb/>Π  g  = 2 <lb/> 12  if g is the central involution in G <lb/> ()  and  = 4. (For each <lb/> the group G <lb/> ()  contains the transformation e  i  → −e  i  , which is the unique central involution of <lb/> G <lb/> ()  if &gt; 2.) In the case that  = 4 and g is the central involution of G <lb/> (4)  we have <lb/>  g  = 1 <lb/> 8  2 <lb/> 8  . <lb/>Define a second permutation representation of degree 24/( − 1) for G <lb/> ()  by considering the <lb/>action of G <lb/> ()  on the sets E  i  = {ce  i  | c ∈ Z//, c  = 0} for i ∈ Ω <lb/> ()  , which constitute a system of <lb/>imprimitivity for the degree 24 permutation representation of G <lb/> ()  just defined. Write ¯ <lb/>Π  g  for <lb/>the corresponding cycle shapes and g → ¯ <lb/> χ  g  for the character, and observe that this permutation <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Umbral Moonshine and Linear Codes <lb/></note>

			<page> 7 <lb/></page>

			<body> representation is generally not faithful, for the central involution e  i  → −e  i  acts trivially. We <lb/>write g → ¯ <lb/> g for the natural map from G <lb/> ()  to its quotient ¯ <lb/> G <lb/> ()  by the central subgroup generated <lb/>by e  i  → −e  i  . (We have G <lb/> ()  ¯ <lb/> G <lb/> ()  when  = 2 since e  i  = −e  i  for i ∈ Ω <lb/> (2)  .) <lb/>Observe that the smaller permutation representation ¯ <lb/> χ is an irreducible constituent of the <lb/>larger one <lb/> . Indeed, the latter contains /2 copies of the former, and ( − 1)/2 copies of <lb/>a faithful representation of degree 24/( − 1), whose character we denote g → χ  g  , which is just <lb/>that which you obtain by taking the matrices representing the action of G <lb/> ()  = Aut <lb/> ±  (G <lb/> ()  ) as <lb/>elements of GL  n  (Z//)—these matrices having exactly one non zero entry ±1 in each row and <lb/>column—and regarding them as elements of GL  n  (C). (Here n = 24/( − 1).) <lb/>˜ <lb/> χ  g  = /2 ¯ <lb/> χ  g  + ( − 1)/2χ  g <lb/> (3.2) <lb/>It is now easy to describe the shadow of the vector-valued mock modular form H <lb/> () <lb/> g  = (H <lb/> () <lb/> g,r  ), <lb/>for it is given by S <lb/> () <lb/> g <lb/> = (S <lb/> () <lb/> g,r  ) where S <lb/> () <lb/> g,r  = ¯ <lb/> χ  g  S  ,r  for r odd, and S <lb/> () <lb/> g,r  = χ  g  S  ,r  for r even, <lb/>where S  m,r  denotes the unary theta series <lb/> S  m,r  (τ ) = <lb/> k∈Z <lb/> (2km + r)q <lb/> (2km+r) <lb/> 2  /4m  . <lb/> (3.3) <lb/>Note that S  m  = (S  m,r  ) is a vector-valued cusp form of weight 3/2 for the modular group SL  2  (Z). <lb/>Given a cycle shape Π = m <lb/> n1 <lb/> 1  · · · m <lb/> n  k <lb/> k  with n  i  &gt; 0 for 1 ≤ i ≤ k and m  1  &lt; m  2  &lt; · · · &lt; m  k <lb/> call m  k  the largest factor of Π and call m  1  the smallest factor. For each g ∈ G <lb/> ()  define n  g  to <lb/>be the largest factor of ¯ <lb/>Π  g  (this turns out to be the same as the order of ¯ <lb/> g) and define N  g  to <lb/>be the product of the smallest and largest factors of <lb/>  g  . The significance of these values for <lb/>the automorphy of H <lb/> () <lb/> g <lb/> is that n  g  is the level of H <lb/> () <lb/> g  —i.e., the smallest positive integer such <lb/>that the vector-valued mock modular form H <lb/> () <lb/> g <lb/> is a mock modular form for Γ  0  (n  g  )—and N  g <lb/> is the smallest positive integer such that the multiplier system for H <lb/> () <lb/> g <lb/> coincides with that of <lb/> S   = (S  ,r  ) when restricted to Γ  0  (N  g  ). <lb/>The expression for S <lb/> () <lb/> g  just given determines the multiplier system of H <lb/> () <lb/> g  —since the mul-<lb/>tiplier system of a mock modular form is the inverse of the multiplier system of its shadow (cf. <lb/>[18])—in the case that ¯ <lb/> χ  g  and χ  g  are both non-zero. The multiplier system of H <lb/> () <lb/> g <lb/> may be <lb/>described as follows in the case that ¯ <lb/> χ  g  χ  g  = 0. <lb/>Define v <lb/> ()  =  + 2 in case  is odd (i.e.  ∈ {3, 5, 7, 13}), and set v <lb/> ()  =  − 1 when  is even <lb/>(i.e.  ∈ {2, 4}). Let σ <lb/> ()  denote the inverse of the multiplier system of the cusp form S   = (S  ,r  ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Umbral Moonshine and Linear Codes <lb/></note>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<body> and define ψ <lb/> () <lb/> n|h  : Γ  0  (n) → GL  −1  (C) for positive integers n and h by setting <lb/> ψ <lb/> () <lb/> n|h <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> a b <lb/>c d <lb/>  <lb/> = e <lb/> −v <lb/> ()  cd <lb/>nh <lb/> σ <lb/> () <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> a b <lb/>c d <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> (3.4) <lb/>in case h divides n, and otherwise <lb/> ψ <lb/> () <lb/> n|h <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> a b <lb/>c d <lb/>  <lb/> = e <lb/> −v <lb/> ()  cd <lb/>nh <lb/> (n, h) <lb/>n <lb/> σ <lb/> () <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> a b <lb/>c d <lb/>  <lb/> J <lb/> c(d+1)/n  K <lb/> c/n <lb/> (3.5) <lb/>where J is the diagonal matrix J = diag(1, −1, 1, · · · ) with alternating ±1 along the diagonal, <lb/>and K is the &quot; reverse shuffle &quot; permutation matrix corresponding to the permutation <lb/>(1,  − 1)(2,  − 2)(3,  − 3) · · · <lb/> (3.6) <lb/>of the standard basis {e  1  , . . . , e  −1  } of C <lb/> −1  . Now the multiplier system of H <lb/> () <lb/> g  is given by ψ <lb/> () <lb/> n|h <lb/> for n = n  g  and h = h  g  = N  g  /n  g  when ¯ <lb/> χ  g  χ  g  = 0. <lb/>Note that the factor (n, h)/n can usually be ignored in practice, for there is just one case in <lb/>which ¯ <lb/> χ  g  χ  g  = 0 and h = h  g  does not divide n = n  g  and (n, h)  = n; viz., the case that  = 3 <lb/>and g ∈ G <lb/> (3)  satisfies ¯ <lb/>Π  g  = 2 <lb/> 1  10 <lb/> 1  and <lb/>  g  = 4 <lb/> 1  20 <lb/> 1  . <lb/>  </body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"><lb/> The author thanks RIMS and the organizers of the RIMS workshop Research on finite groups <lb/>and their representations, vertex operator algebras, and algebraic combinatorics, Kyoto, Japan, <lb/>January 2013, for support and hospitality. The author&apos;s understanding of umbral moonshine, <lb/>and the content of this note in particular, has developed from many conversations with many <lb/>people, but the greatest burden has fallen upon his coauthors Miranda Cheng and Jeffrey Harvey, <lb/>to whom the author is extremely grateful. We are indebted to George Glauberman for the <lb/>observation that the groups of umbral moonshine are related to deep holes in the Leech lattice. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote"> Umbral Moonshine and Linear Codes <lb/></note>

			<page> 9 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex"> A  Characters <lb/> The tables in this section describe the character values ¯ <lb/> χ <lb/> g  , and  χ <lb/> g  , as well as the cycle shapes  <lb/> g  and ¯ <lb/> Π <lb/> g  , and also the <lb/> symbols  n <lb/> g  |h <lb/> g  for each  g  ∈  G  () <lb/> , for each  ∈ {2,  3, 4, 5, 7, 13}. In case  = 2 we have  <lb/>   = ¯ <lb/> χ  =  χ,  so we just give the ¯ <lb/> χ <lb/> g  and <lb/> ¯ <lb/> Π <lb/> g  . The conjugacy class names are chosen to coincide with those of [12]. <lb/> Table 2: Characters and cycle shapes at  = 2 <lb/> [g] <lb/> 1A <lb/> 2A <lb/> 2B 3A <lb/> 3B <lb/> 4A <lb/> 4B <lb/> 4C <lb/> 5A <lb/> 6A <lb/> 6B <lb/> n <lb/> g  |h <lb/> g <lb/> 1|1 <lb/> 2|1 <lb/> 2|2 3|1 <lb/> 3|3 <lb/> 4|2 <lb/> 4|1 <lb/> 4|4 <lb/> 5|1 <lb/> 6|1 <lb/> 6|6 <lb/> ¯ <lb/> χ <lb/> g <lb/> 24 <lb/> 8 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 6 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 0 <lb/> ¯ <lb/> Π <lb/> g <lb/> 1  24 <lb/> 1  8 <lb/> 2  8 <lb/> 2  12 <lb/> 1  6 <lb/> 3  6 <lb/> 3  8 <lb/> 2  4 <lb/> 4  4 <lb/> 1  4 <lb/> 2  2 <lb/> 4  4 <lb/> 4  6 <lb/> 1  4 <lb/> 5  4 <lb/> 1  2 <lb/> 2  2 <lb/> 3  2 <lb/> 6  2 <lb/> 6  4 <lb/> [g] 7AB <lb/> 8A <lb/> 10A 11A <lb/> 12A <lb/> 12B <lb/> 14AB <lb/> 15AB 21AB 23AB <lb/> n <lb/> g  |h <lb/> g <lb/> 7|1 <lb/> 8|1 <lb/> 10|2 11|1 <lb/> 12|2 <lb/> 12|12 <lb/> 14|1 <lb/> 15|1 <lb/> 21|3 <lb/> 23|1 <lb/> ¯ <lb/> χ <lb/> g <lb/> 3 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> ¯ <lb/> Π <lb/> g <lb/> 1  3 <lb/> 7  3 <lb/> 1  2 <lb/> 2  1 <lb/> 4  1 <lb/> 8  2 <lb/> 2  2 <lb/> 10  2 <lb/> 1  2 <lb/> 11  2 <lb/> 2  1 <lb/> 4  1 <lb/> 6  1 <lb/> 12  1 <lb/> 12  2 <lb/> 1  1 <lb/> 2  1 <lb/> 7  1 <lb/> 14  1 <lb/> 1  1 <lb/> 3  1 <lb/> 5  1 <lb/> 15  1 <lb/> 3  1 <lb/> 21  1 <lb/> 1  1 <lb/> 23  1 <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote"> Umbral Moonshine and Linear Codes <lb/></note>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>
			<div type="annex"> 
			  Table 3: Characters and cycle shapes at  = 3 <lb/> [g] 1A 2A 4A 2B 2C 3A 6A 3B 6B 4B 4C 5A 10A 12A 6C <lb/> 6D 8AB 8CD 20AB 11AB 22AB <lb/> n <lb/> g  |h <lb/> g <lb/> 1 1|4 2|8 2 2|2 3 3|4 3|3 3|12 4|2 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 5 5|4 6|24 <lb/> 6 <lb/> 6|2 <lb/> 8|4 <lb/> 8 <lb/> 10|8 11 11|4 <lb/> ¯ <lb/> χ <lb/> g <lb/> 12 12 0 4 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 3 0 0 0 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> χ <lb/> g <lb/> 12  −12  0 4  −4  3  −3  0 0 0 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 2  −2  0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> −1 <lb/> ¯ <lb/> Π <lb/> g <lb/> 1  12 <lb/> 1  12 <lb/> 2  6 <lb/> 1  4 <lb/> 2  4 <lb/> 1  4 <lb/> 2  4 <lb/> 1  3 <lb/> 3  3 <lb/> 1  3 <lb/> 3  3 <lb/> 3  4 <lb/> 3  4 <lb/> 2  2 <lb/> 4  2 <lb/> 1  4 <lb/> 4  2 <lb/> 1  2 <lb/> 5  2 <lb/> 1  2 <lb/> 5  2 <lb/> 6  2 <lb/> 1  1 <lb/> 2  1 <lb/> 3  1 <lb/> 6  1 <lb/> 1  1 <lb/> 2  1 <lb/> 3  1 <lb/> 6  1 <lb/> 4  1 <lb/> 8  1 <lb/> 1  2 <lb/> 2  1 <lb/> 8  1 <lb/> 2  1 <lb/> 10  1 <lb/> 1  1 <lb/> 11  1 <lb/> 1  1 <lb/> 11  1 <lb/> ˜ <lb/> Π <lb/> g <lb/> 1  24 <lb/> 2  12 <lb/> 4  6 <lb/> 1  8 <lb/> 2  8 <lb/> 2  12 <lb/> 1  6 <lb/> 3  6 <lb/> 2  3 <lb/> 6  3 <lb/> 3  8 <lb/> 6  4 <lb/> 2  4 <lb/> 4  4 <lb/> 1  4 <lb/> 2  2 <lb/> 4  4 <lb/> 1  4 <lb/> 5  4 <lb/> 2  2 <lb/> 10  2 <lb/> 12  2 <lb/> 1  2 <lb/> 2  2 <lb/> 3  2 <lb/> 6  2 <lb/> 2  2 <lb/> 6  2 <lb/> 4  2 <lb/> 8  2 <lb/> 1  2 <lb/> 2  1 <lb/> 4  1 <lb/> 8  2 <lb/> 4  1 <lb/> 20  1 <lb/> 1  2 <lb/> 11  2 <lb/> 2  1 <lb/> 22  1 <lb/> Table 4: Characters and cycle shapes at  = 4 <lb/> [g] 1A 2A 2B 4A 4B 2C 3A <lb/> 6A <lb/> 6BC 8A <lb/> 4C 7AB 14AB <lb/> n <lb/> g  |h <lb/> g  1|1 1|2 2|2 2|4 4|4 2|1 3|1 <lb/> 3|2 <lb/> 6|2 4|8 <lb/> 4|1 <lb/> 7|1 <lb/> 7|2 <lb/> ¯ <lb/> χ <lb/> g <lb/> 8 <lb/> 8 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> χ <lb/> g <lb/> 8  −8  0 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 2 <lb/> −2 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> −1 <lb/> ¯ <lb/> Π <lb/> g <lb/> 1  8 <lb/> 1  8 <lb/> 2  4 <lb/> 2  4 <lb/> 4  2 <lb/> 1  4 <lb/> 2  2 <lb/> 1  2 <lb/> 3  2 <lb/> 1  2 <lb/> 3  2 <lb/> 2  1 <lb/> 6  1 <lb/> 4  2 <lb/> 1  2 <lb/> 2  1 <lb/> 4  1 <lb/> 1  1 <lb/> 7  1 <lb/> 1  1 <lb/> 7  1 <lb/> ˜ <lb/> Π <lb/> g <lb/> 1  24 <lb/> 1  8 <lb/> 2  8 <lb/> 2  12 <lb/> 2  4 <lb/> 4  4 <lb/> 4  6 <lb/> 1  8 <lb/> 2  8 <lb/> 1  6 <lb/> 3  6 <lb/> 1  2 <lb/> 2  2 <lb/> 3  2 <lb/> 6  2 <lb/> 2  3 <lb/> 6  3 <lb/> 4  2 <lb/> 8  2 <lb/> 1  4 <lb/> 2  2 <lb/> 4  4 <lb/> 1  3 <lb/> 7  3 <lb/> 1  1 <lb/> 2  1 <lb/> 7  1 <lb/></div>

			<page> 14  1 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Umbral Moonshine and Linear Codes <lb/></note>

			<page> 11 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex"> Table 5: Characters and cycle shapes at  = 5 <lb/>[g] 1A 2A 2B 2C 3A 6A 5A 10A 4AB 4CD 12AB <lb/> n  g  |h  g  1|1 1|4 2|2 2|1 3|3 3|12 5|1 5|4 2|8 <lb/>4|1 <lb/>6|24 <lb/>¯ <lb/> χ  g <lb/> 6 6 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/> χ  g <lb/> 6 −6 −2 2 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>¯ <lb/>Π  g <lb/> 1  6  1  6  1  2  2  2  1  2  2  2  3  2  3  2  1  1  5  1  1  1  5  1  2  3 <lb/> 1  2  4  1 <lb/> 6  1 <lb/> ˜ <lb/>Π  g  1  24  2  12  2  12  1  8  2  8  3  2  6  4  1  4  5  4  2  2  10  2  4  6  1  4  2  2  4  4  12  2 <lb/> Table 6: Characters and cycle shapes at  = 7 <lb/>[g] <lb/>1A 2A 4A 3AB 6AB <lb/> n  g  |h  g <lb/> 1 <lb/>1|4 2|8 <lb/>3 <lb/>3|4 <lb/>¯ <lb/> χ  g <lb/> 4 <lb/>4 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/> χ  g <lb/> 4 <lb/>-4 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>-1 <lb/>¯ <lb/>Π  g <lb/> 1  4 <lb/> 1  4 <lb/> 2  2  1  1  3  1  1  1  3  1 <lb/> ˜ <lb/>Π  g <lb/> 1  24  2  12  4  6  1  6  3  6  2  3  6  3 <lb/> Table 7: Characters and cycle shapes at  = 13 <lb/>[g] 1A 2A 4AB <lb/> n  g  |h  g <lb/> 1 1|4 <lb/>2|8 <lb/>¯ <lb/> χ  g <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/> χ  g <lb/> 2 <lb/>-2 <lb/>0 <lb/>¯ <lb/>Π  g <lb/> 1  2 <lb/> 1  2 <lb/> 2  1 <lb/> ˜ <lb/>Π  g  1  24  2  12 <lb/> 4  6 <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote"> Umbral Moonshine and Linear Codes <lb/></note>

			<page> 12 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex"> B Special Functions <lb/> The Dedekind eta function, denoted η(τ ), is a holomorphic function on the upper half-plane <lb/>defined by the infinite product <lb/> η(τ ) = q <lb/> 1/24 <lb/> n&gt;0 <lb/> (1 − q <lb/> n  ) <lb/>(B.1) <lb/>where q = e(τ ) = e <lb/> 2πiτ  . It is a modular form of weight 1/2 for the modular group SL  2  (Z) with <lb/>multiplier  : SL  2  (Z) → C so that <lb/> η(γτ )(γ) j(γ, τ ) <lb/> 1/2  = η(τ ) <lb/>(B.2) <lb/>for all γ ∈ SL  2  (Z), where j(γ, τ ) = (cτ + d) <lb/> −1  in case (c, d) is the lower row of γ. <lb/> Setting q = e(τ ) and y = e(z) we use the following conventions for the four standard Jacobi <lb/>theta functions. <lb/> θ  1  (τ, z) = −iq <lb/> 1/8  y <lb/> 1/2 <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=1 <lb/> (1 − q <lb/> n  )(1 − yq <lb/> n  )(1 − y <lb/> −1  q <lb/> n−1  ) <lb/> θ  2  (τ, z) = q <lb/> 1/8  y <lb/> 1/2 <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=1 <lb/> (1 − q <lb/> n  )(1 + yq <lb/> n  )(1 + y <lb/> −1  q <lb/> n−1  ) <lb/> θ  3  (τ, z) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=1 <lb/> (1 − q <lb/> n  )(1 + y q <lb/> n−1/2  )(1 + y <lb/> −1  q <lb/> n−1/2  ) <lb/> θ  4  (τ, z) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=1 <lb/> (1 − q <lb/> n  )(1 − y q <lb/> n−1/2  )(1 − y <lb/> −1  q <lb/> n−1/2  ) <lb/>(B.3) <lb/>We write µ(τ, z) for the Appell-Lerch sum defined by setting <lb/> µ(τ, z) = <lb/> −iy <lb/> 1/2 <lb/> θ  1  (τ, z) <lb/> ∈Z <lb/> (−1) <lb/>  y <lb/> n  q <lb/> (+1)/2 <lb/> 1 − yq  <lb/> . <lb/> (B.4) <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote"> Umbral Moonshine and Linear Codes <lb/></note>

			<page> 13 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] T. Eguchi, H. Ooguri, and Y. Tachikawa, &quot; Notes on the K3 Surface and the Mathieu <lb/>group M  24  , &quot;  Exper.Math. 20 (2011) 91–96, arXiv:1004.0956 [hep-th]. <lb/> [2] M. C. N. Cheng and J. F. R. Duncan, &quot; The Largest Mathieu Group and (Mock) <lb/>Automorphic Forms, &quot;  1201.4140. <lb/> [3] J. Conway, R. Curtis, S. Norton, R. Parker, and R. Wilson, Atlas of finite groups. <lb/>Maximal subgroups and ordinary characters for simple groups. With comput. assist. from <lb/>J. G. Thackray. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1985. <lb/>[4] J. H. Conway and S. P. Norton, &quot; Monstrous Moonshine, &quot;  Bull. London Math. Soc. 11 <lb/> (1979) 308 339. <lb/>[5] J. G. Thompson, &quot; Finite groups and modular functions, &quot;  Bull. London Math. Soc. 11 <lb/> (1979) no. 3, 347–351. <lb/>[6] J. G. Thompson, &quot; Some numerology between the Fischer-Griess Monster and the elliptic <lb/>modular function, &quot;  Bull. London Math. Soc. 11 (1979) no. 3, 352–353. <lb/>[7] M. C. N. Cheng, &quot; K3 Surfaces, N = 4 Dyons, and the Mathieu Group M  24  , &quot;  1005.5415. <lb/> [8] M. R. Gaberdiel, S. Hohenegger, and R. Volpato, &quot; Mathieu twining characters for K3, &quot; <lb/> JHEP 1009 (2010) 058, arXiv:1006.0221 [hep-th]. 19 pages. <lb/>[9] M. R. Gaberdiel, S. Hohenegger, and R. Volpato, &quot; Mathieu Moonshine in the elliptic <lb/>genus of K3, &quot;  JHEP 1010 (2010) 062, arXiv:1008.3778 [hep-th]. <lb/> [10] T. Eguchi and K. Hikami, &quot; Note on Twisted Elliptic Genus of K3 Surface, &quot;  Phys.Lett. <lb/> B694 (2011) 446–455, arXiv:1008.4924 [hep-th]. <lb/> [11] T. Gannon, &quot; Much ado about Mathieu, &quot; November, 2012. <lb/>[12] M. C. N. Cheng, J. F. R. Duncan, and J. A. Harvey, &quot; Umbral Moonshine, &quot; <lb/> arXiv:1204.2779 [math.RT]. <lb/> [13] J. H. Conway and N. J. A. Sloane, &quot; Twenty-three constructions for the Leech lattice, &quot; <lb/> Proc. Roy. Soc. London Ser. A 381 (1982) no. 1781, 275–283. <lb/> http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rspa.1982.0071. <lb/> [14] M. C. N. Cheng, J. F. R. Duncan, and J. A. Harvey, &quot; Umbral Moonshine and the <lb/>Niemeier Lattices, &quot; . <lb/>[15] J. H. Conway and N. J. A. Sloane, Sphere Packings, Lattices and Groups. <lb/> Springer-Verlag, 1999. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> Umbral Moonshine and Linear Codes <lb/></note>

			<page> 14 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [16] J. H. Conway and N. J. A. Sloane, &quot; Self-dual codes over the integers modulo 4, &quot;  J. <lb/> Combin. Theory Ser. A 62 (1993) no. 1, 30–45. <lb/> http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0097-3165(93)90070-O. <lb/> [17] E. M. Rains and N. J. A. Sloane, &quot; Self-dual codes, &quot; in Handbook of coding theory, Vol. I, <lb/>II, pp. 177–294. North-Holland, Amsterdam, 1998. <lb/>[18] M. C. Cheng and J. F. Duncan, &quot; Rademacher Sums and Rademacher Series, &quot; <lb/> arXiv:1210.3066 [math.NT]. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
