<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Recent Results from the ATLAS Experiment <lb/> Paul D. Jackson 1,2 on behalf of the ATLAS Collaboration <lb/> 1  University of Adelaide, School of Chemistry and Physics, Adelaide, SA 5005, Australia, <lb/> 2  ARC Centre of Excellence for Particle Physics at the Tera-scale, University of Adelaide <lb/>E-mail: p.jackson@adelaide.edu.au <lb/> (Received July 31, 2013) <lb/>The ATLAS experiment [1] at the Large Hadron Collider at CERN is a general purpose detector <lb/>for studying proton-proton collisions at TeV energies. This talk presents the latest ATLAS physics <lb/>results, based on the data collected in 2011 and 2012, summing to over 20 fb <lb/> −1  . The latest measure-<lb/>ments of the Higgs boson, and studies of its properties are described. Recent searches for processes <lb/>beyond the Standard Model such as Supersymmetry, and other Exotica, are also covered. <lb/> KEYWORDS: ATLAS, LHC, Higgs, SUSY, Exotics <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> The ATLAS experiment has been collecting data from proton-proton collisions at the CERN <lb/>Large Hadron Collider (LHC) since late 2009. Data samples at centre-of mass collision energies of <lb/>7 TeV and 8 TeV were recorded in 2010-11 and 2012 respectively with samples of 4.7 fb  −1  and <lb/>20.7 fb  −1  now stored on tape. These samples have permitted precision tests of the Standard Model at <lb/>the highest achieved energies to date and measurements of the cross-sections of vector boson (with <lb/>and without associated jets), di-boson, single top and t ¯ <lb/> t have withstood experimental scrutiny to <lb/>uphold the Standard Model. These measurements, along with accurate luminosity determination, ex-<lb/>cellent detector performance and detailed Monte Carlo studies form the basis for searches for physics <lb/>beyond the Standard Model. Furthermore, knowledge of the Standard Model background is criti-<lb/>cal to enable ATLAS to perform searches for the Higgs boson, and all subsequent measurements to <lb/>determine it&apos;s properties. <lb/> 2. The Higgs Boson <lb/> The announcement of the discovery of a new particle in the search for the Higgs boson occurred <lb/>on July 4 th , 2012 [2]. Since then, the ATLAS experiment has collected over 20.7 fb  −1  of collision <lb/>data at a pp centre of mass collision energy of 8 TeV. These data have been analysed further with the <lb/>purpose of improving the sensitivity to the new particle&apos;s mass, and comparing it&apos;s properties to those <lb/>expected from the Standard Model Higgs boson. <lb/> 2.1 Mass determination and signal strength <lb/> The combined significance of the local probability of the Higgs boson measurement is now more <lb/>than 10 sigma, mostly arising from the H → γγ, ZZ  ( * )  → 4, W  ±  W  ( * )∓  → νν observations. The <lb/>central value for the mass is measured to be m H  = 125.5 ± 0.3(stat.) ± 0.5(syst.) GeV. Figure 1 shows <lb/>the fitted signal for the H → γγ and H → ZZ  ( * )  → 4 channels with the signal clearly evident. <lb/>The signal strength the di-boson measurement is summarised in Figure 2 (left). The combined µ <lb/> value, the ratio of measured cross section to that expected from a Standard Model Higgs boson with <lb/>a mass of 125.5 GeV, is in excellent agreement with unity [3]. <lb/> 1 <lb/>% % % <lb/></body>

			<front> JPS Conf. Proc. , 013001 (2014) <lb/>©2014 The Physical Society of Japan <lb/> 1 <lb/> Proceedings of the 12th Asia Pacific Physics Conference <lb/></front>

			<page> 013001-1 <lb/></page>

			<body> 100 <lb/> 110 <lb/>120 <lb/>130 <lb/>140 <lb/>150 <lb/>160 <lb/> Events / 2 GeV <lb/> 2000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>6000 <lb/>8000 <lb/>10000 <lb/> γ <lb/> γ <lb/>→ <lb/> H <lb/> -1 <lb/> Ldt = 4.8 fb <lb/> ∫ <lb/> = 7 TeV <lb/>s <lb/> -1 <lb/> Ldt = 20.7 fb <lb/> ∫ <lb/> = 8 TeV <lb/>s <lb/> ATLAS <lb/> Data 2011+2012 <lb/>=126.8 GeV (fit) <lb/> H <lb/> SM Higgs boson m <lb/>Bkg (4th order polynomial) <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> γ <lb/>γ <lb/> m <lb/> 100 <lb/>110 <lb/>120 <lb/>130 <lb/>140 <lb/>150 <lb/>160 <lb/> Events - Fitted bkg <lb/> -200 <lb/>-100 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> 4l <lb/> m <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>Events/5 GeV <lb/> 0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>35 <lb/>40 <lb/> -1 <lb/> Ldt = 4.6 fb <lb/> ∫ <lb/> = 7 TeV <lb/>s <lb/> -1 <lb/> Ldt = 20.7 fb <lb/> ∫ <lb/> = 8 TeV <lb/>s <lb/> 4l <lb/> → <lb/> ZZ* <lb/> → <lb/> H <lb/> Data 2011+ 2012 <lb/>SM Higgs Boson <lb/>=124.3 GeV (fit) <lb/> H <lb/> m <lb/>Background Z, ZZ* <lb/>t <lb/>Background Z+jets, t <lb/>Syst.Unc. <lb/> ATLAS <lb/> Fig. 1. Invariant mass of the two-photon (left) and ZZ <lb/> ( * ) <lb/> → 4 (right) channels. Details can be found else-<lb/>where [3]. <lb/> 2.2 Higgs Properties: Spin and Parity <lb/> In order to show consistency with the expectation of the Standard Model Higgs boson the spin <lb/>and parity of the new boson should be measured. The Higgs boson has unique properties in the <lb/>Standard Model, corresponding to a particle with J P  = 0  +  . In order to test this hypothesis other <lb/>possible J P  assignments are scrutinised with the results summarised in Figure 2 [4]. These spin and <lb/>parity hypotheses can be tested with the suite of di-boson final state measurements of the Higgs decay. <lb/> H → ZZ  ( * ) is used to test all spin hypotheses and both odd and even parity; H → WW  ( * ) compares <lb/>all spin possibilities, while H → γγ compares spin-0 to spin-2, neither of the latter channels has <lb/>sensitivity to parity. All results show consistency with the Standard Model expectation for J P  = 0  + <lb/> with alternative hypotheses ruled out at the 2-3 sigma level [4]. <lb/> 2.3 Summary <lb/> Since the first observation of the Higgs boson, a year of concerted effort has yielded impressive <lb/>results. Precision measurements of the Higgs boson have now been presented with the first evidence <lb/>of its properties being shown in July 2013. More data will yield even greater precision on these <lb/>measurements and we are already entering the realm of detailed Higgs boson studies. <lb/> 3. Supersymmetry <lb/> Supersymmetry (SUSY) [5–13] is the most studied extension to the Standard Model. The liter-<lb/>ature contains many scenarios, often modelled in great detail, which make predictions that SUSY <lb/>particles should be observable at the LHC, with masses in the region of 1 TeV, and these predictions <lb/>have been tested by many analyses. <lb/>There are many reasons to believe that SUSY might be relevant to physics in the TeV energy <lb/>range. We already have evidence of physics beyond the Standard Model, from astrophysical obser-<lb/>vations consistent with dark matter. R-parity conserving (RPC) SUSY [14, 15] offers a heavy weakly <lb/>interacting particle which is a natural dark matter candidate. We also now have a Higgs boson, at a <lb/>mass close of 125 GeV, and the stability of its mass can be protected from quantum loop effects by <lb/>SUSY partners [16–21]. The theoretical motivations for SUSY models remain as strong as ever, and <lb/> 2 <lb/>% % % <lb/></body>

			<page> 013001-2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> JPS Conf. Proc. , 013001 (2014) <lb/></note>

			<body> 1 <lb/> ) <lb/> µ <lb/> Signal strength ( <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/> ATLAS <lb/> -1 <lb/> Ldt = 4.6-4.8 fb <lb/> ∫ <lb/> = 7 TeV <lb/>s <lb/> -1 <lb/> Ldt = 20.7 fb <lb/> ∫ <lb/> = 8 TeV <lb/>s <lb/> = 125.5 GeV <lb/> H <lb/> m <lb/> 0.28 <lb/> -<lb/> 0.33 <lb/> + <lb/> = 1.55 <lb/> µ <lb/> γ <lb/>γ <lb/>→ <lb/> H <lb/> 0.15 <lb/> ± <lb/> 0.15 <lb/> ± <lb/> 0.23 <lb/> ± <lb/> 0.4 <lb/> -<lb/> 0.5 <lb/> + <lb/> = 1.6 <lb/> µ <lb/> Tt <lb/> Low p <lb/>0.3 <lb/> ± <lb/> 0.6 <lb/> -<lb/> 0.7 <lb/> + <lb/> = 1.7 <lb/> µ <lb/> Tt <lb/> High p <lb/>0.5 <lb/> ± <lb/> 0.6 <lb/> -<lb/> 0.8 <lb/> + <lb/> = 1.9 <lb/> µ <lb/> mass (VBF) <lb/>2 jet high <lb/> 0.6 <lb/> ± <lb/> 1.1 <lb/> -<lb/> 1.2 <lb/> + <lb/> = 1.3 <lb/> µ <lb/> VH categories <lb/>0.9 <lb/> ± <lb/> 0.35 <lb/> -<lb/> 0.40 <lb/> + <lb/> = 1.43 <lb/> µ <lb/> 4l <lb/> → <lb/> ZZ* <lb/> → <lb/> H <lb/> 0.14 <lb/> ± <lb/> 0.17 <lb/> ± <lb/> 0.33 <lb/> ± <lb/> 0.9 <lb/> -<lb/> 1.6 <lb/> + <lb/> = 1.2 <lb/> µ <lb/> categories <lb/>VBF+VH-like <lb/> 0.9 <lb/> -<lb/> 1.6 <lb/> + <lb/> 0.36 <lb/> -<lb/> 0.43 <lb/> + <lb/> = 1.45 <lb/> µ <lb/> categories <lb/>Other <lb/> 0.35 <lb/> ± <lb/> 0.28 <lb/> -<lb/> 0.31 <lb/> + <lb/> = 0.99 <lb/> µ <lb/> ν <lb/> l <lb/> ν <lb/> l <lb/> → <lb/> WW* <lb/> → <lb/> H <lb/> 0.12 <lb/> ± <lb/> 0.21 <lb/> ± <lb/> 0.21 <lb/> ± <lb/> 0.32 <lb/> -<lb/> 0.33 <lb/> + <lb/> = 0.82 <lb/> µ <lb/> 0+1 jet <lb/>0.22 <lb/> ± <lb/> 0.6 <lb/> -<lb/> 0.7 <lb/> + <lb/> = 1.4 <lb/> µ <lb/> 2 jet VBF <lb/>0.5 <lb/> ± <lb/> 0.18 <lb/> -<lb/> 0.21 <lb/> + <lb/> = 1.33 <lb/> µ <lb/> , ZZ*, WW* <lb/> γ <lb/>γ <lb/>→ <lb/> Comb. H <lb/> 0.11 <lb/> ± <lb/> 0.15 <lb/> ± <lb/> 0.14 <lb/> ± <lb/> Total uncertainty <lb/> µ <lb/> on <lb/> σ <lb/> 1 <lb/> ± <lb/> (stat) <lb/> σ <lb/> (sys) <lb/> σ <lb/> (theo) <lb/> σ <lb/> -<lb/> = 0 <lb/> P <lb/> J <lb/> + <lb/> = 1 <lb/> P <lb/> J <lb/> -<lb/> = 1 <lb/> P <lb/> J <lb/> m <lb/>+ <lb/> = 2 <lb/> P <lb/> J <lb/> ATLAS <lb/> 4l <lb/> → <lb/> ZZ* <lb/> → <lb/> H <lb/> -1 <lb/> Ldt = 4.6 fb <lb/> ∫ <lb/> = 7 TeV <lb/>s <lb/> -1 <lb/> Ldt = 20.7 fb <lb/> ∫ <lb/> = 8 TeV <lb/>s <lb/> γ <lb/>γ <lb/>→ <lb/> H <lb/> -1 <lb/> Ldt = 20.7 fb <lb/> ∫ <lb/> = 8 TeV <lb/>s <lb/> ν <lb/> e <lb/> ν <lb/>µ <lb/> / <lb/> ν <lb/>µ <lb/>ν <lb/> e <lb/> → <lb/> WW* <lb/> → <lb/> H <lb/> -1 <lb/> Ldt = 20.7 fb <lb/> ∫ <lb/> = 8 TeV <lb/>s <lb/> σ <lb/> 1 <lb/> σ <lb/> 2 <lb/> σ <lb/> 3 <lb/> σ <lb/> 4 <lb/> Data <lb/>expected <lb/> s <lb/> CL <lb/> + <lb/> = 0 <lb/> P <lb/> assuming J <lb/> σ <lb/> 1 <lb/> ± <lb/> ) <lb/> alt <lb/> P <lb/> ( J <lb/> s <lb/> CL <lb/> -6 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/> Fig. 2. (Left) The measured production strengths for a Higgs boson of mass mH =125.5 GeV, normalised to <lb/>the SM expectations, for di-boson final states and their combination. (Right) Expected (blue triangles/dashed <lb/>lines) and observed (black circles/solid lines) confidence level CLs for alternative spin–parity hypotheses as-<lb/>suming a 0 <lb/> +  signal. The green band represents the 68% CLs(J <lb/> p <lb/> alt  ) expected exclusion range for a signal with <lb/>assumed 0 <lb/> +  . For the spin-2 hypothesis, the results for the specific 2 <lb/> + <lb/> m  model, are shown. More details can be <lb/>found elsewhere [4]. <lb/> so we should complete all searches before concluding that SUSY is a figment of our imagination. <lb/>The sensitivity of the current searches depends strongly on which processes are most accessible. The <lb/>highest reach is achieved for gluinos and for first and second generation squarks, while, for example, <lb/>stops and charginos have lower cross-sections and are harder to detect, and the search limits are less <lb/>stringent. <lb/>SUSY remains the most promising theory of physics beyond the Standard Model being probed <lb/>by the LHC experiments. If realised in nature, the theory must be broken and the mechanism by <lb/>which this occur can give rise to varied particle spectra, which more than double the elementary <lb/>particles of the Standard Model leading to rich structure for experimentalists and theorists alike to <lb/>explore. Signatures at the LHC generally require high p  T  objects (jets and charged leptons) produced <lb/>in association with large missing transverse momentum. <lb/> 3.1 SUSY: strong production <lb/> The most powerful of the existing searches are based on all-hadronic final states with missing <lb/>transverse momentum (E miss <lb/> T  ). To complement this, ATLAS recently updated a search for squark and <lb/>gluino production in a final state with one or two leptons [22]. The events are categorised by whether <lb/>the leptons have higher or lower momentum and are referred to as the &quot; hard &quot; and &quot; soft &quot; lepton <lb/>channels respectively. Leptons in the soft category satisfy 6, 10 &lt; p  T  &lt; 25 GeV (µ, e) and such events <lb/>are triggered by sufficient E  miss <lb/> T  . Hard leptons pass p  T  &gt; 25 GeV and are seeded with both lepton and <lb/> 3 <lb/>% % % <lb/></body>

			<page> 013001-3 <lb/></page>
			<note place="headnote"> JPS Conf. Proc. , 013001 (2014) <lb/></note>

			<body> 1 <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> g <lb/>~ <lb/> m <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1200 <lb/>1400 <lb/>[GeV] <lb/> 1 <lb/> 0 <lb/> χ  ∼ <lb/> m <lb/> 100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>700 <lb/>800 <lb/>900 <lb/>1000 <lb/> , x=1/2 <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/> χ ∼ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/> χ ∼ <lb/> qqqqWW <lb/> → <lb/> g <lb/>~ <lb/>-<lb/>g <lb/>~ <lb/> ) <lb/> theory <lb/>SUSY <lb/> σ <lb/> 1 <lb/> ± <lb/> Observed limit ( <lb/>) <lb/> exp <lb/> σ <lb/> 1 <lb/> ± <lb/> Expected limit ( <lb/> =8 TeV <lb/>s <lb/>, <lb/> -1 <lb/> L dt = 20.3 fb <lb/> ∫ <lb/> miss <lb/>T <lb/> 1-lepton + jets + E <lb/> 1 <lb/>0 <lb/> χ <lb/>∼ <lb/> &lt; <lb/>m <lb/> g <lb/>~ <lb/> m <lb/>PRD 86 (2012) 092002 <lb/>Observed limit (hard lepton) <lb/>Expected limit (hard lepton) <lb/>Observed limit (soft lepton) <lb/>Expected limit (soft lepton) <lb/>All limits at 95% CL <lb/> ATLAS Preliminary <lb/> 0.04 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.42 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>25 <lb/>72 <lb/>345 <lb/>7 <lb/>129 <lb/>17 <lb/>13 <lb/>15 <lb/>247 <lb/>16 <lb/>3 <lb/>23 <lb/>3 <lb/>21 <lb/>20 <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.77 <lb/>0.36 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>0.72 <lb/>0.52 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.46 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.69 <lb/>0.98 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.33 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 0.51 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>0.98 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.36 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.43 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.19 <lb/>0.45 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 0.43 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.61 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.34 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.07 <lb/> Numbers give 95% CL excluded model cross sections [pb] <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> g <lb/>~ <lb/> m <lb/> 600 700 800 900 1000 1100 1200 1300 1400 1500 1600 <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> 1 <lb/> 0 <lb/> χ  ∼ <lb/> m <lb/> 200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1200 <lb/> fo <lb/>rb <lb/>id <lb/>d e n <lb/> 1 <lb/>0 <lb/> χ <lb/>∼ <lb/> t <lb/>t <lb/> → <lb/> g <lb/>~ <lb/> = 8 TeV <lb/>s <lb/>), <lb/>g <lb/>~ <lb/>) &gt;&gt; m( <lb/>q <lb/>~ <lb/>, m( <lb/> 1 <lb/>0 <lb/> χ ∼ <lb/> t <lb/>t <lb/> → <lb/> g <lb/>~ <lb/>production, <lb/>g <lb/>~ <lb/>g <lb/>~ <lb/>Lepton &amp; Photon 2013 <lb/> ATLAS <lb/> Preliminary <lb/> Expected <lb/>Observed <lb/>Expected <lb/>Observed <lb/>Expected <lb/>Observed <lb/>Expected <lb/>Observed <lb/>10 jets <lb/> ≥ <lb/> 0-lepton, 7 -<lb/>3 b-jets <lb/> ≥ <lb/> 0-1 lepton, <lb/>4 jets <lb/> ≥ <lb/> 3-leptons, <lb/>3 b-jets <lb/> ≥ <lb/> 2-SS-leptons, 0 -<lb/> ATLAS-CONF-2013-054 <lb/>ATLAS-CONF-2013-061 <lb/>ATLAS-CONF-2012-151 <lb/>ATLAS-CONF-2013-007 <lb/> ] <lb/> -1 <lb/> = 20.3 fb <lb/> int <lb/> [L <lb/>] <lb/> -1 <lb/> = 20.1 fb <lb/> int <lb/> [L <lb/>] <lb/> -1 <lb/> = 12.8 fb <lb/> int <lb/> [L <lb/>] <lb/> -1 <lb/> = 20.7 fb <lb/> int <lb/> [L <lb/> not included. <lb/> theory <lb/>SUSY <lb/> σ <lb/> 95% CL limits. <lb/> Fig. 3. SUSY exclusions for strong production with leptons (left) The dark grey dashed line shows the ex-<lb/>pected limits at 95% CL, with the light (yellow) bands indicating the ±1σ variation on the median expected <lb/>limit due to the experimental and background-theory uncertainties. The observed nominal limit is indicated by <lb/>a solid dark red line with the dark red dotted lines being obtained by varying the signal cross section by the <lb/>scale and PDF uncertainties. The observed limit set by the previous ATLAS analysis using 7 TeV data is shown <lb/>as a grey area. The light blue and purple full (dashed) lines show the observed (expected) exclusion obtained <lb/>by the soft and hard-lepton analyses, respectively. The grey numbers show the upper limit on the production <lb/>cross section, in pb, obtained for each point of the grids. More details elsewhere [22]. <lb/>Gluino-mediated third generation production (right). The exclusion in the m  ˜ <lb/> g  vs m  ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/> plane is for the Gtt model. <lb/>The dashed/solid lines show the 95% CL expected/observed limits respectively, including all uncertainties <lb/>except the theoretical signal cross-section uncertainty. More details elsewhere [23]. <lb/> E  miss <lb/> T <lb/> triggers. Figure 3 (right) shows the reach of the single lepton channel and demonstrates how the <lb/>soft and hard lepton analyses provide excellent coverage across the m  ˜ <lb/> g  vs m  ˜ <lb/> χ  0 <lb/>1 <lb/> plane. <lb/>If the gluino mass is sufficiently high they are expected to preferentially decay through direct <lb/>production of third generation quarks (top and bottom) leading to distinctive signatures. The most <lb/>sensitive analysis performed by ATLAS searches for final states with 3 b-jets, E  miss <lb/> T <lb/> and either 0 or 1 <lb/>lepton. The resulting exclusion from this analysis in the m  ˜ <lb/> g  vs m  ˜ <lb/> χ  0 <lb/>1 <lb/> plane extends beyond the reach of <lb/>other comparable channels and excludes gluino masses up to 1.4 TeV for certain model assumptions. <lb/>The results of this search are summarised in Figure 3 and in [23]. <lb/> 3.2 SUSY: 3  rd  generation <lb/> The argument that SUSY cancels the divergences in the Higgs mass requires the SUSY particles <lb/>be close to the TeV scale to avoid large fine-tuning of the theory parameters. The dominant term <lb/>in the Higgs mass correction comes from the top quark loop and therefore it is only necessary for <lb/>the stop to be in the TeV range in order to stabilise the Higgs mass. For this reason, direct searches <lb/>for third generation squarks have become a priority. Details of the studies performed by the ATLAS <lb/>experiment are summarised in Figure 4. A suite of channels have been considered, depending on the <lb/>topologies allowed and the exclusions generally come with some assumptions driven by the short <lb/>comings of the techniques and variables used, such as the requirement of 100% branching ratios into <lb/>a particular signal decay mode. <lb/> 4 <lb/>% % % <lb/></body>

			<page> 013001-4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> JPS Conf. Proc. , 013001 (2014) <lb/></note>

			<body> 1 <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/>~ <lb/> m <lb/> 100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>700 <lb/> 1 <lb/> 0 <lb/> χ∼ <lb/> + m <lb/> t <lb/> &lt; <lb/> m 1 <lb/> t <lb/> ~ <lb/> m <lb/> 1 <lb/> 0 <lb/> χ <lb/> ∼ <lb/> + <lb/> m <lb/> W <lb/> + <lb/> m <lb/> b <lb/> &lt; <lb/> m 1 <lb/> t <lb/> ~ <lb/> m <lb/> 200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/> ) <lb/> 1 <lb/>0 <lb/> χ <lb/>∼ <lb/> m <lb/> × <lb/> = 2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> ± <lb/> χ <lb/>∼ <lb/> ( m <lb/> 1 <lb/> ± <lb/> χ <lb/>∼ <lb/> + m <lb/> b <lb/> &lt; m <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/>~ <lb/> m <lb/>&lt; 106 GeV <lb/> 1 <lb/> ± <lb/> χ ∼ <lb/> m <lb/>+ 5 <lb/> G <lb/> e V ) <lb/> 1 <lb/> 0 <lb/> χ∼ <lb/> = <lb/> m <lb/> 1 <lb/> ± <lb/> χ∼ <lb/> ( m <lb/> 1 <lb/> ± <lb/> χ∼ <lb/> + m <lb/> b <lb/> &lt; <lb/> m <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/> ~ <lb/> m <lb/> &lt; 103.5 GeV <lb/> 1 <lb/> ± <lb/> χ ∼ <lb/> m <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> 1 <lb/> 0 <lb/> χ ∼ <lb/> m <lb/> 0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/> Observed limits <lb/>) <lb/> theo <lb/> σ <lb/> Observed limits (-1 <lb/>Expected limits <lb/> 1 <lb/>0 <lb/> χ <lb/>∼ <lb/> m <lb/> × <lb/> = 2 <lb/> ± <lb/> 1 <lb/> χ <lb/> m <lb/> -1 <lb/> = 20-21 fb <lb/> int <lb/> L <lb/>-10 GeV <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/>~ <lb/> = m <lb/> ± <lb/> 1 <lb/> χ <lb/> m <lb/> -1 <lb/> = 20.3 fb <lb/> int <lb/> L <lb/>= 150 GeV <lb/> ± <lb/> 1 <lb/> χ <lb/> m <lb/> -1 <lb/> = 20.7 fb <lb/> int <lb/> L <lb/>= 106 GeV <lb/> ± <lb/> 1 <lb/> χ <lb/> m <lb/> -1 <lb/> = 4.7 fb <lb/> int <lb/> L <lb/>+ 5 GeV <lb/> 1 <lb/>0 <lb/> χ <lb/>∼ <lb/> = m <lb/> ± <lb/> 1 <lb/> χ <lb/> m <lb/> -1 <lb/> = 20.1 fb <lb/> int <lb/> L <lb/> -1 <lb/> = 4.7 fb <lb/> int <lb/> L <lb/> -1 <lb/> 21 fb <lb/> ≈ <lb/> int <lb/> L <lb/> 1 <lb/>0 <lb/> χ ∼ <lb/> W b <lb/> -1 <lb/> = 20 fb <lb/> int <lb/> L <lb/> ATLAS Preliminary <lb/> production <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/>~ <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/>~ <lb/> Status: LHCP 2013 <lb/>=8 TeV <lb/>s <lb/> -1 <lb/> = 20 -21 fb <lb/> int <lb/> L <lb/>=7 TeV <lb/>s <lb/> -1 <lb/> = 4.7 fb <lb/> int <lb/> L <lb/> 0L ATLAS-CONF-2013-024 <lb/>1L ATLAS-CONF-2013-037 <lb/>-<lb/>2L ATLAS-CONF-2013-048 <lb/>0L ATLAS-CONF-2013-053 <lb/>-<lb/>1L ATLAS-CONF-2013-037 <lb/>2L ATLAS-CONF-2013-048 <lb/>1L CONF-2013-037, 2L CONF-2013-048 <lb/>0L [1208.1447] <lb/>1L [1208.2590] <lb/>2L [1209.4186] <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>2L [1208.4305], 1-2L [1209.2102] <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1-2L [1209.2102] <lb/> 1 <lb/>0 <lb/> χ ∼ <lb/> (*) <lb/> W <lb/> → <lb/> 1 <lb/> ± <lb/> χ ∼ <lb/> , <lb/> 1 <lb/> ± <lb/> χ ∼ <lb/> b <lb/> → <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/>~ <lb/> 1 <lb/>0 <lb/> χ ∼ <lb/> W b <lb/> → <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/>~ <lb/>/ <lb/> 1 <lb/>0 <lb/> χ ∼ <lb/> t <lb/> → <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/>~ <lb/> 1 <lb/>0 <lb/> χ <lb/>∼ <lb/> t <lb/> → <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/>~ <lb/>0L, <lb/> 1 <lb/>0 <lb/> χ <lb/>∼ <lb/> t <lb/> → <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/>~ <lb/>1L, <lb/> 1 <lb/>0 <lb/> χ <lb/>∼ <lb/> t <lb/> → <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/>~ <lb/>2L, <lb/> 1 <lb/>0 <lb/> χ <lb/>∼ <lb/> W b <lb/> → <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/>~ <lb/>2L, <lb/>+ 5 GeV <lb/> 1 <lb/>0 <lb/> χ <lb/>∼ <lb/> = m <lb/> ± <lb/> 1 <lb/> χ <lb/> 0L, m <lb/>= 106 GeV <lb/> ± <lb/> 1 <lb/> χ <lb/> , m <lb/> 1 <lb/> ± <lb/> χ <lb/>∼ <lb/> b <lb/> → <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/>~ <lb/>1-2L, <lb/>= 150 GeV <lb/> ± <lb/> 1 <lb/> χ <lb/> , m <lb/> 1 <lb/> ± <lb/> χ <lb/>∼ <lb/> b <lb/> → <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/>~ <lb/>1L, <lb/>-10 GeV <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/>~ <lb/> = m <lb/> ± <lb/> 1 <lb/> χ <lb/> , m <lb/> 1 <lb/> ± <lb/> χ <lb/>∼ <lb/> b <lb/> → <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/>~ <lb/>2L, <lb/> 1 <lb/>0 <lb/> χ <lb/>∼ <lb/> m <lb/> × <lb/> = 2 <lb/> ± <lb/> 1 <lb/> χ <lb/> , m <lb/> 1 <lb/> ± <lb/> χ <lb/>∼ <lb/> b <lb/> → <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/>~ <lb/>1-2L, <lb/> Fig. 4. Summary of the dedicated ATLAS searches for top squark (stop) pair production based on 20 fb <lb/> 1 <lb/> of pp collision data taken at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 8 TeV. Exclusion limits at 95% CL are shown in the (stop,neutralino) <lb/>mass plane. The dashed and solid lines show the expected and observed limits, respectively, including all <lb/>uncertainties except the theoretical signal cross section uncertainty (PDF and scale). The dotted lines represent <lb/>the results obtained when reducing the nominal signal cross section by 1s of its theoretical uncertainty. For <lb/>stop masses below 200 GeV, the decay <lb/>  1  → b ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> ± <lb/> 1  , ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> ± <lb/> 1  → W <lb/> ( * ) ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 is assumed in all cases, with five hypotheses <lb/>on the <lb/> ± <lb/> 1  , ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 mass hierarchy. For stop masses above 200 GeV, the decay <lb/>  1  → tχ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 is assumed to dominate. <lb/> 3.3 Summary <lb/> The data are putting pressure on SUSY models from many directions. With the increasing energy <lb/>and luminosity of this magnificent machine, the experiments will remain busy searching for SUSY <lb/>for some years to come. New ideas and techniques on the horizon should improve the sensitivity of <lb/>the ATLAS experiment to SUSY signatures and so exciting times lie ahead of us. <lb/> 4. Outlook and Conclusion <lb/> The LHC has provided a wonderful dataset to be probed by the experiments it serves. These data <lb/>are rich and present considerable challenges to unravel the details of their make-up. Run 1 of the <lb/>LHC will be remembered by the discovery of the new boson that looks increasingly like the Standard <lb/>Model Higgs boson. The ATLAS collaboration have exploited their significant signal in decays of <lb/>the Higgs to vector bosons to establish first evidence of the spin-0 nature of this boson. In searching <lb/>for physics beyond the Standard Model many possibilities have been considered. Among the leading <lb/>candidates SUSY remains the most viable option and ATLAS have presented a thorough plan to <lb/>probe potential SUSY breaking scenarios and final states. As yet, there has been no signal to excite <lb/>the community but evidence of new physics processes may lurk around any corner so our exhaustive <lb/>physics program must continue. <lb/> 5 <lb/>% % % <lb/></body>

			<page> 013001-5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> JPS Conf. Proc. , 013001 (2014) <lb/> 1 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] http://atlas.web.cern.ch/Atlas/Collaboration/ <lb/>[2] ATLAS Collaboration, Observation of a new particle in the search for the Standard Model Higgs boson <lb/>with the ATLAS detector at the LHC, Phys. Lett. B 716 (2012) 1, arXiv:1207.7214. <lb/>[3] ATLAS Collaboration, Measurements of Higgs boson production and couplings in di-boson final states <lb/>with the ATLAS detector at the LHC, submitted to Physics Letters B, arXiv:1307.1427. <lb/>[4] ATLAS Collaboration, Evidence for the spin-0 nature of the Higgs boson using ATLAS data, submitted to <lb/>Physics Letters B, arXiv:1307.1432. <lb/>[5] H. Miyazawa, Baryon Number Changing Currents, Prog. Theor. Phys. 36 (6) (1966) 1266. <lb/>[6] P. Ramond, Dual Theory for Free Fermions, Phys. Rev. D 3 (1971) 2415. <lb/>[7] Y. A. Golfand and E. P. Likhtman, Extension of the Algebra of Poincare Group Generators and Violbation <lb/>of p Invariance, JETP Lett. 13 (1971) 323. [Pisma Zh. Eksp. Teor. Fiz. 13 (1971) 452-455]. <lb/>[8] A. Neveu and J. H. Schwarz, Factorizable dual model of pions, Nucl. Phys. B 31 (1971) 86. <lb/>[9] A. Neveu and J. H. Schwarz, Quark Model of Dual Pions, Phys. Rev. D 4 (1971) 1109. <lb/>[10] J. Gervais and B. Sakita, Field theory interpretation of supergauges in dual models, Nucl. Phys. B 34 <lb/>(1971) 632. <lb/>[11] D. V. Volkov and V. P. Akulov, Is the Neutrino a Goldstone Particle?, Phys. Lett. B 46 (1973) 109. <lb/>[12] J. Wess and B. Zumino, A Lagrangian Model Invariant Under Supergauge Transformations, Phys. Lett. <lb/>B 49 (1974) 52. <lb/>[13] J. Wess and B. Zumino, Supergauge Transformations in Four-Dimensions, Nucl. Phys. B 70 (1974) 39. <lb/>[14] H. Goldberg, Constraint on the photino mass from cosmology, Phys. Rev. Lett. 50 (1983) 1419. <lb/>[15] J. Ellis, J. Hagelin, D. Nanopoulos, K. Olive, and M. Srednicki, Supersymmetric relics from the big bang, <lb/>Nucl. Phys. B238 (1984) 453476. <lb/>[16] S. Dimopoulos and H. Georgi, Softly Broken Supersymmetry and SU(5), Nucl. Phys. B 193 (1981) 150. <lb/>[17] E. Witten, Dynamical Breaking of Supersymmetry, Nucl. Phys. B188 (1981) 513. <lb/>[18] M. Dine, W. Fischler, and M. Srednicki, Supersymmetric Technicolor, Nucl. Phys. B189 (1981) 575593. <lb/>[19] S. Dimopoulos and S. Raby, Supercolor, Nucl. Phys. B192 (1981) 353. <lb/>[20] N. Sakai, Naturalness in Supersymmetric Guts, Zeit. Phys. C11 (1981) 153. <lb/>[21] R. Kaul and P. Majumdar, Cancellation of quadratically divergent mass corrections in globally supersym-<lb/>metric spontaneously broken gauge theories, Nucl. Phys. B199 (1982) 36. <lb/>[22] ATLAS Collaboration, Search for squarks and gluinos in events with isolated leptons, jets and missing <lb/> transverse momentum at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 8 TeV with the ATLAS detector, ATLAS-CONF-2013-062. <lb/>[23] ATLAS Collaboration, Search for strong production of supersymmetric particles in final states with miss-<lb/>ing transverse momentum and at least three b-jets using 20.1 fb <lb/> 1 of pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 8 TeV with the <lb/>ATLAS Detector, ATLAS-CONF-2013-061. <lb/>6 <lb/>% % % <lb/> 013001-6 <lb/> JPS Conf. Proc. , 013001 (2014) <lb/> 1 </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
