<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Lie superalgebras of Krichever–Novikov type <lb/> Martin Schlichenmaier <lb/> Abstract. Classically, starting from the Witt and Virasoro algebra im-<lb/>portant examples of Lie superalgebras were constructed. In this write-up <lb/>of a talk presented at the Biaa lowie˙ za meetings we report on results on <lb/>Lie superalgebras of Krichever-Novikov type. These algebras are multi-<lb/>point and higher genus equivalents of the classical algebras. The grading <lb/>in the classical case is replaced by an almost-grading. It is induced by <lb/>a splitting of the set of points, were poles are allowed, into two disjoint <lb/>subsets. With respect to a fixed splitting, or equivalently with respect <lb/>to a fixed almost-grading, it is shown that there is up to rescaling and <lb/>equivalence a unique non-trivial central extension of the Lie superalge-<lb/>bra of Krichever–Novikov type. It is given explicitly. <lb/> Mathematics Subject Classification (2010). Primary: 17B56; Secondary: <lb/>17B68, 17B65, 17B66, 14H99, 81R10, 81T40. <lb/> Keywords. Superalgebra; Krichever–Novikov type algebra; central ex-<lb/>tensions; Witt algebra; Virasoro algebra; Lie algebra cohomology; con-<lb/>formal field theory. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> In the context of conformal field theory (CFT) the Witt algebra and its <lb/>universal central extension, the Virasoro algebra, play an important role. <lb/>These algebras encode conformal symmetry. To incorporate superconformal <lb/>symmetry one is forced to extend the algebras to Lie superalgebras. Examples <lb/>of them are the Neveu–Schwarz and the Ramond type superalgebras. <lb/>These algebras we call the classical algebras. They correspond to the <lb/>genus zero situation. Krichever–Novikov algebras are higher genus and multi-<lb/>point analogs of them. For higher genus, but still only for two points where <lb/>poles are allowed, some of the algebras were generalised in 1986 by Krichever <lb/>and Novikov [9], [10], [11]. In 1990 the author [15], [16], [17], [18] extended <lb/></body>

			<front> Partial support by the Internal Research Project GEOMQ11, University of Luxembourg, <lb/>and by the OPEN scheme of the Fonds National de la Recherche (FNR) with the project <lb/>QUANTMOD O13/5707106 is acknowledged. <lb/></front>

			<page> 2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Martin Schlichenmaier <lb/></note>

			<body>the approach further to the general multi-point case. These extensions were <lb/>not straight-forward generalizations. The crucial point was to introduce a <lb/>replacement of the graded algebra structure present in the &quot; classical &quot; case. <lb/>Krichever and Novikov found that an almost-grading, see Definition 6, will <lb/>be enough to allow constructions in representation theory, like triangular de-<lb/>compositions, highest weight modules, Verma modules and so on. In [17], [18] <lb/>it was realized that a splitting of the set A of points where poles are allowed <lb/>into two disjoint non-empty subsets A = I ∪ O is crucial for introducing an <lb/>almost-grading. For every such splitting the corresponding almost-grading <lb/>was given. Essentially different splittings (not just corresponding to inter-<lb/>changing of I and O) will yield essentially different almost-gradings. For the <lb/>general theory (including the classical case) see the recent monograph [22]. <lb/>In the context of conformal field theory and string theory the Neveu-<lb/>Schwarz and the Ramond type superalgebras appear as superextensions of the <lb/>classical algebras. Some physicists also studied superanalogs of the algebra <lb/>of Krichever-Novikov type, but still only with two points where poles are <lb/>allowed, e.g. [1], [2], [3], [4], [23]. The multi-point case was developed by the <lb/>author some time ago and recently published in [21]. See also [22]. <lb/>Starting from Krichever–Novikov type superalgebras interesting explicite <lb/>infinite dimensional examples of Jordan superalgebras and antialgebras can <lb/>be constructed. In this respect, see the work of Leidwanger and Morier-<lb/>Genoud [12], [13], and Kreusch [8]. <lb/>In this write-up we will recall the construction of the Krichever–Novikov <lb/>(KN) type algebras for the multi-point situation and for arbitrary genus. The <lb/>classical situation will be a special case. In particular, the construction of the <lb/>Lie superalgebra is recalled. Its almost-graded structure, induced by a fixed <lb/>splitting A = I ∪ O, is given. <lb/>The main result presented here is the fact that up to rescaling the central <lb/>element and equivalence of extension, there is only one non-trivial almost-<lb/>graded central extension of the Lie superalgebra of KN type with even central <lb/>element. We stress the fact, that this does not mean that there is essentially <lb/>only one central extension. For an essentially different splitting we get an <lb/>essentially different central extension. For higher genus there are even central <lb/>extensions not related to any splitting. In the classical situation in this way <lb/>uniqueness of the non-trivial central extension is again obtained. Recall that <lb/> &quot; classical &quot; means genus zero and two points where poles are allowed. <lb/>We will give a geometric description for the defining cocycle, see (43). <lb/>For the two-point case the form of the cocycle was given by Bryant in [4], <lb/>correcting some ommission in [1]. <lb/>In the case of odd central elements we obtained that the corresponding <lb/>central extension of the Lie superalgebra will split. For the proofs we have to <lb/>refer to the original article [21], respectively to [22]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Lie superalgebras of Krichever–Novikov type <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body> 2. The Classical Lie Superalgebra <lb/> For the convenience of the reader we start with recalling the definition of a <lb/>Lie superalgebra. Let S be a vector space which is decomposed into even and <lb/>odd elements S = S¯  0  ⊕ S¯  1  , i.e. S is a Z/2Z-graded vector space. Furthermore, <lb/>let [., .] be a Z/2Z-graded bilinear map S × S → S such that for elements x, y <lb/> of pure parity <lb/>[x, y] = −(−1) <lb/> ¯ <lb/> x¯ y  [y, x]. <lb/> (1) <lb/>This says that <lb/>[S¯  0  , S¯  0  ] ⊆ S¯  0  , <lb/> [S¯  0  , S¯  1  ] ⊆ S¯  1  , <lb/> [S¯  1  , S¯  1  ] ⊆ S¯  0  , <lb/> (2) <lb/>and [x, y] is symmetric for x and y odd, otherwise anti-symmetric. Further-<lb/>more, S is a Lie superalgebra if in addition the super-Jacobi identity (x, y, z <lb/> of pure parity) <lb/>(−1) <lb/> ¯ <lb/> x¯ z  [x, [y, z]] + (−1) <lb/> ¯ <lb/> y ¯ <lb/> x  [y, [z, x]] + (−1) <lb/> ¯ <lb/> z ¯ <lb/> y  [z, [x, y]] = 0 <lb/>(3) <lb/>is valid. As long as the type of the arguments is different from (even, odd, <lb/>odd) all signs can be put to +1 and we obtain the form of the usual Jacobi <lb/>identity. In the remaining case we get <lb/>[x, [y, z]] + [y, [z, x]] − [z, [x, y]] = 0. <lb/>(4) <lb/>By the very definitions S  0  is a Lie algebra. <lb/>In purely algebraic terms the Virasoro algebra V is given by generators <lb/> {e  n  (n ∈ Z), t} with relations <lb/>[e  n  , e  m  ] = (m − n)e  n+m  + <lb/>1 <lb/>12 <lb/>(n <lb/> 3  − n)δ <lb/> −m <lb/> n <lb/> · t, <lb/> [t, e  n  ] = 0 . <lb/> (5) <lb/>Without the central term t we obtain the Witt algebra W. <lb/> For the classical (Neveu–Schwarz) Lie superalgebra we add an additional <lb/>set of generators {ϕ  m  | m ∈ Z + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  } and complete the relations to <lb/>[e  n  , e  m  ] = (m − n)e  m+n  + <lb/>1 <lb/>12 <lb/>(n <lb/> 3  − n) δ <lb/> −m <lb/> n <lb/> t, <lb/> [e  n  , ϕ  m  ] = (m − <lb/> n <lb/> 2 <lb/>) ϕ  m+n  , <lb/> [ϕ  n  , ϕ  m  ] = e  n+m  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>6 <lb/>(n <lb/> 2  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>4 <lb/>) δ <lb/> −m <lb/> n <lb/> t, <lb/> [t, e  n  ] = [t, ϕ  m  ] = 0 . <lb/> (6) <lb/>These algebras can be realized in a geometric manner by considering vector <lb/>fields and forms of weight −1/2 (see below) on the Riemann sphere S <lb/> 2  (i.e. <lb/>the Riemann surface of genus zero). If we take the vector fields e  n  = z <lb/> n+1 d <lb/>dz  , <lb/>the forms of weight −1/2 given by ϕ  m  = z <lb/> m+1/2  (dz) <lb/> −1/2  , let the vector <lb/>field e  n  act by taking the Lie derivative, and set [ϕ  m  , ϕ  n  ] = ϕ  m  · ϕ  n  then <lb/>we obtain the relations above without central terms. The element t is an <lb/>additional element and the factors in front of it seem to be rather ad-hoc for <lb/></body>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Martin Schlichenmaier <lb/></note>

			<body>the moment <lb/> 1  . One verifies by direct calculations that by our prescription we <lb/>obtain indeed a Lie superalgebra. <lb/> 3. Higher genus generalization <lb/> Starting from the geometric realization above we can extend this to arbi-<lb/>trary genus. For the whole contribution let Σ be a compact Riemann surface <lb/>(without boundary). We do not put any restriction on the genus g = g(Σ). <lb/> Furthermore, let A be a finite subset of Σ. Later we will need a splitting of A <lb/> into two non-empty disjoint subsets I and O, i.e. A = I ∪ O. Set N := #A, <lb/> K := #I, M := #O, with N = K + M . More precisely, let <lb/> I = (P  1  , . . . , P  K  ), and O = (Q  1  , . . . , Q  M  ) <lb/>(7) <lb/>be disjoint ordered tuples of distinct points ( &quot; marked points &quot; , &quot; punctures &quot; ) <lb/>on the Riemann surface. In particular, we assume P  i  = Q  j  for every pair <lb/>(i, j). The points in I are called the in-points, the points in O the out-points. <lb/> Sometimes we consider I and O simply as sets. <lb/>Our objects, algebras, structures, ... will be meromorphic objects de-<lb/>fined on Σ which are holomorphic outside the points in A. To introduce them <lb/>let K = K  Σ  be the canonical line bundle of Σ, respectively. the locally free <lb/>canonically sheaf. The local sections of the bundle are the local holomor-<lb/>phic differentials. If P ∈ Σ is a point and z a local holomorphic coordinate <lb/>at P then a local holomorphic differential can be written as f (z)dz with <lb/>a local holomorphic function f defined in a neighbourhood of P . A global <lb/>holomorphic section can be described locally for a covering by coordinate <lb/>charts (U  i  , z  i  )  i∈J  by a system of local holomorphic functions (f  i  )  i∈J  , which <lb/>are related by the transformation rule induced by the coordinate change map <lb/> z  j  = z  j  (z  i  ) and the condition f  i  dz  i  = f  j  dz  j  . This says <lb/> f  j  = f  i  · <lb/> dz  j <lb/> dz  i <lb/>  −1 <lb/> . <lb/> (8) <lb/>With respect to a coordinate covering a meromorphic section of K is given <lb/>as a collection of local meromorphic functions (h  i  )  i∈J  for which the transfor-<lb/>mation law (8) is true. <lb/>In the following λ is either an integer or a half-integer. If λ is an integer <lb/>then <lb/>(1) K <lb/> λ  = K <lb/> ⊗λ  for λ &gt; 0, <lb/>(2) K <lb/> 0  = O, the trivial line bundle, and <lb/>(3) K <lb/> λ  = (K <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> ⊗(−λ)  for λ &lt; 0. <lb/>Here as usual K <lb/>  *  denotes the dual line bundle to the canonical line bundle. <lb/>The dual line bundle is the holomorphic tangent line bundle, whose local <lb/>sections are the holomorphic tangent vector fields f (z)(d/dz). If λ is a half-<lb/>integer, then we first have to fix a &quot; square root &quot; of the canonical line bundle, <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 1  Below we will give for the factors a geometric expression. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Lie superalgebras of Krichever–Novikov type <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>sometimes called a theta-characteristics. This means we fix a line bundle L <lb/> for which L <lb/> ⊗2  = K. <lb/> After such a choice of L is done we set K <lb/> λ  = K <lb/> λ <lb/>L  = L <lb/> ⊗2λ  . In most cases <lb/>we will drop mentioning L, but we have to keep the choice in mind. Also the <lb/>structure of the algebras we are about to define will depend on the choice. <lb/>But the main properties will remain the same. <lb/> Remark. A Riemann surface of genus g has exactly 2 <lb/> 2g  non-isomorphic square <lb/>roots of K. For g = 0 we have K = O(−2) and L = O(−1), the tautological <lb/>bundle which is the unique square root. Already for g = 1 we have 4 non-<lb/>isomorphic ones. As in this case K = O one solution is L  0  = O. But we have <lb/>also the other bundles L  i  , i = 1, 2, 3. <lb/>As above we can talk about holomorphic and meromorphic sections of <lb/> K <lb/> λ  . In local coordinates z  i  we can write such sections as f  i  dz <lb/> λ <lb/>i  , with f  i  being <lb/>a local holomorphic, respectively meromorphic function. <lb/>We set <lb/> F <lb/> λ  := F <lb/> λ  (A) := {f is a global meromorphic section of K <lb/> λ  | <lb/> such that f is holomorphic over Σ \ A}. <lb/> (9) <lb/>Here the set of A is fixed and we drop it in the notation. Obviously, F <lb/> λ  is <lb/>an infinite dimensional C-vector space. Recall that in the case of half-integer <lb/> λ everything depends on the theta characteristic L. We call the elements <lb/>of the space F <lb/> λ  meromorphic forms of weight λ (with respect to the theta <lb/>characteristic L). Altogether we set <lb/> F := <lb/> λ∈ <lb/> 1 <lb/> 2  Z <lb/> F <lb/> λ  . <lb/> (10) <lb/> 4. Algebraic Structure <lb/> 4.1. Associative Multiplication <lb/> The natural map of the locally free sheaves of rank one <lb/> K <lb/> λ  × K <lb/> ν  → K <lb/> λ  ⊗ K <lb/> ν  ∼ = K <lb/> λ+ν  , (s, t) → s ⊗ t, <lb/> (11) <lb/>defines a bilinear map <lb/> · : F <lb/> λ  × F <lb/> ν  → F <lb/> λ+ν  . <lb/> (12) <lb/>With respect to local trivialisations this corresponds to the multiplication of <lb/>the local representing meromorphic functions <lb/>(s dz <lb/> λ  , t dz <lb/> ν  ) → s dz <lb/> λ  · t dz <lb/> ν  = s · t dz <lb/> λ+ν  . <lb/> (13) <lb/>If there is no danger of confusion then we will mostly use the same symbol <lb/>for the section and for the local representing function. <lb/>The following is obvious <lb/> Proposition 1. The vector space F with operation · is an associative and <lb/>commutative graded (over <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  Z) algebra. Moreover, F <lb/> 0  is a subalgebra. <lb/></body>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">  Martin Schlichenmaier <lb/></note>

			<body>We also use A := F <lb/> 0  . Of course, it is the algebra of meromorphic func-<lb/>tions on Σ which are holomorphic outside of A. The spaces F <lb/> λ  are modules <lb/>over A. <lb/> 4.2. Lie algebra structure <lb/> Next we define a Lie algebra structure on the space F. The structure is <lb/>induced by the map <lb/> F <lb/> λ  × F <lb/> ν  → F <lb/> λ+ν+1  , <lb/> (s, t) → [s, t], <lb/> (14) <lb/>which is defined in local representatives of the sections by <lb/>(s dz <lb/> λ  , t dz <lb/> ν  ) → [s dz <lb/> λ  , t dz <lb/> ν  ] := <lb/> (−λ)s <lb/> dt <lb/>dz <lb/> + ν t <lb/>ds <lb/>dz <lb/> dz <lb/> λ+ν+1  , <lb/> (15) <lb/>and bilinearly extended to F. <lb/> Proposition 2. (a) The bilinear map [., .] defines a Lie algebra structure on <lb/> F. <lb/> (b) The space F with respect to · and [., .] is a Poisson algebra. <lb/>Proof. This is done by local calculations. For details see [19], [22]. <lb/> Proposition 3. The subspace L := F <lb/> −1  is a Lie subalgebra with respect to the <lb/>operation [ ., . ], and the F <lb/> λ  &apos;s are Lie modules over L. <lb/> As forms of weight −1 are vector fields, L could also be defined directly <lb/>as the Lie algebra of those meromorphic vector fields on the Riemann surface <lb/>Σ which are holomorphic outside of A. The product (15) gives the usual Lie <lb/>bracket of vector fields and the Lie derivative for their actions on forms: <lb/>[e, f ]  |  (z) = [e(z) <lb/> d <lb/>dz <lb/>, f (z) <lb/> d <lb/>dz <lb/> ] = <lb/> e(z) <lb/>df <lb/>dz <lb/> (z) − f (z) <lb/> de <lb/>dz <lb/> (z) <lb/> d <lb/>dz <lb/>, <lb/> (16) <lb/> ∇  e  (f )  |  (z) = L  e  (f )  |  = e . f  |  = <lb/> e(z) <lb/>df <lb/>dz <lb/> (z) + λf (z) <lb/> de <lb/>dz <lb/> (z) <lb/> d <lb/>dz <lb/>. <lb/> (17) <lb/> 4.3. Superalgebra of half forms <lb/> Next we consider the associative product <lb/> · F <lb/> −1/2  × F <lb/> −1/2  → F <lb/> −1  = L, <lb/> (18) <lb/>and introduce the vector space and the product <lb/> S := L ⊕ F <lb/> −1/2  , [(e, ϕ), (f, ψ)] := ([e, f ] + ϕ · ψ, e . ϕ − f . ψ). <lb/> (19) <lb/>Usually we will denote the elements of L by e, f, . . . , and the elements of <lb/> F <lb/> −1/2  by ϕ, ψ, . . .. <lb/> Definition (19) can be reformulated as an extension of [., .] on L to a <lb/> &quot; super-bracket &quot; (denoted by the same symbol) on S by setting <lb/>[e, ϕ] := −[ϕ, e] := e . ϕ =  |  (e <lb/> dϕ <lb/>dz <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ϕ <lb/>de <lb/>dz <lb/> )(dz) <lb/> −1/2  , <lb/> (20) <lb/>and <lb/>[ϕ, ψ] = ϕ · ψ. <lb/> (21) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Lie superalgebras of Krichever–Novikov type <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>We call the elements of L elements of even parity, and the elements of F <lb/> −1/2 <lb/> elements of odd parity. For such elements x we denote by ¯ <lb/> x ∈ { ¯ 0, ¯ 1} their <lb/>parity. <lb/>The sum (19) can be described as S = S¯  0  ⊕ S¯  1  , where S¯  i  is the subspace <lb/>of elements of parity ¯ i. <lb/> Proposition 4. [21, Prop. 2.5] The space S with the above introduced parity <lb/>and product is a Lie superalgebra. <lb/> Definition 5. The algebra S is the Lie superalgebra of Krichever–Novikov <lb/>type. <lb/> Remark. The introduced Lie superalgebra corresponds classically to the Neveu-<lb/>Schwarz superalgebra. In string theory physicists considered also the Ramond <lb/>superalgebra as string algebra (in the two-point case). The elements of the <lb/>Ramond superalgebra do not correspond to sections of the dual theta char-<lb/>acteristics. They are only defined on a 2-sheeted branched covering of Σ, see <lb/>e.g. [1], [3]. Hence, the elements are only multi-valued sections. As here we <lb/>only consider honest sections of half-integer powers of the canonical bundle, <lb/>we do not deal with the Ramond algebra. <lb/>The choice of the theta characteristics corresponds to choosing a spin <lb/>structure on Σ. Furthermore, this bundle is related to graded Riemann sur-<lb/>faces. See Bryant [4] for more details on this aspect. <lb/> 5. Almost-Graded Structure <lb/> Recall the classical situation. This is the Riemann surface P <lb/> 1  (C) = S <lb/> 2  , i.e. <lb/>the Riemann surface of genus zero, and the points where poles are allowed <lb/>are {0, ∞}. In this case the algebras introduced in the last chapter are graded <lb/>algebras. In the higher genus case and even in the genus zero case with <lb/>more than two points where poles are allowed there is no non-trivial grading <lb/>anymore. As realized by Krichever and Novikov [9] there is a weaker concept, <lb/>called an almost-grading which to a large extend is a valuable replacement <lb/>of a honest grading. Such an almost-grading is induced by a splitting of the <lb/>set A into two non-empty and disjoint sets I and O. The (almost-)grading is <lb/>fixed by exhibiting certain basis elements in the spaces F <lb/> λ  as homogeneous. <lb/> Definition 6. Let L be a Lie or an associative algebra such that L = ⊕  n∈Z  L  n <lb/> is a vector space direct sum, then L is called an almost-graded (Lie-) algebra <lb/>if <lb/>(i) dim L  n  &lt; ∞, <lb/> (ii) There exist constants L  1  , L  2  ∈ Z such that <lb/> L  n  · L  m  ⊆ <lb/> n+m+L2 <lb/> h=n+m−L1 <lb/> L  h  , <lb/> ∀n, m ∈ Z. <lb/> (22) <lb/>Elements in L  n  are called homogeneous elements of degree n, and L  n  is called <lb/>homogeneous subspace of degree n. <lb/></body>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Martin Schlichenmaier <lb/></note>

			<body>In a similar manner almost-graded modules over almost-graded algebras <lb/>are defined. Of course, we can extend in an obvious way the definition to <lb/>superalgebras, respectively even to more general algebraic structures. This <lb/>definition makes complete sense also for more general index sets J. In fact <lb/>we will consider the index set J = (1/2)Z for our superalgebra. The even <lb/>elements (with respect to the super-grading) will have integer degree, the <lb/>odd elements half-integer degree. <lb/>As already mentioned above the almost-grading for F <lb/> λ  is introduced by <lb/>exhibiting certain elements f <lb/> λ <lb/>m,p  ∈ F <lb/> λ  , p = 1, . . . , K which constitute a basis <lb/>of the subspace F <lb/> λ <lb/>m  of homogeneous elements of degree m. Here m ∈ J  λ  with <lb/> J  λ  = Z (for λ integer) or J  λ  = Z+1/2 (for λ half-integer). The basis elements <lb/> f <lb/> λ <lb/>m,p  of degree m are required to have order <lb/>ord  Pi  (f <lb/> λ <lb/>m,p  ) = (n + 1 − λ) − δ <lb/> p <lb/>i <lb/> at the point P  i  ∈ I, i = 1, . . . , K. The prescription at the points in O is made <lb/>in such a way that the element f <lb/> λ <lb/>m,p  is essentially uniquely given. For more <lb/>details on the prescription see [22, Chapter 4] or the original article [16]. In <lb/>the classical case we have deg(e  n  ) = n and deg(ϕ  m  ) = m. Warning: The <lb/>spaces F <lb/> λ <lb/>m  depend on the splitting of A. <lb/> For the property of being almost-graded the following result is crucial. <lb/>It is obtained by calculating residues and estimating orders. <lb/> Proposition 7. [22, Thm. 3.8] There exist constants R  1  and R  2  (depending on <lb/>the number and splitting of the points in A and of the genus g) independent <lb/>of n, m ∈ J and λ and ν such that for the basis elements <lb/> f <lb/> λ <lb/>n,p  · f <lb/> ν <lb/>m,r  = f <lb/> λ+ν <lb/>n+m,r  δ <lb/> r <lb/>p <lb/> + <lb/> n+m+R1 <lb/> h=n+m+1 <lb/>K <lb/> s=1 <lb/> a <lb/> (h,s) <lb/>(n,p)(m,r)  f <lb/> λ+ν <lb/>h,s  , a <lb/> (h,s) <lb/>(n,p)(m,r)  ∈ C, <lb/> [f <lb/> λ <lb/>n,p  , f <lb/> ν <lb/>m,r  ] = (−λm + νn) f <lb/> λ+ν+1 <lb/>n+m,r  δ <lb/> r <lb/>p <lb/> + <lb/> n+m+R2 <lb/> h=n+m+1 <lb/>K <lb/> s=1 <lb/> b <lb/> (h,s) <lb/>(n,p)(m,r)  f <lb/> λ+ν+1 <lb/>h,s <lb/> , b <lb/> (h,s) <lb/>(n,p)(m,r)  ∈ C. <lb/> (23) <lb/>The constants R  i  can be explicitly calculated (if needed). <lb/>As a direct consequence we obtain <lb/> Theorem 8. The algebras L and S are almost-graded Lie, respectively Lie <lb/>superalgebras. The almost-grading depends on the splitting of the set A into <lb/> I and O. More precisely, <lb/> F <lb/> λ  = <lb/> m∈J  λ <lb/> F <lb/> λ <lb/>m  , <lb/> with dim F <lb/> λ <lb/>m  = K. <lb/> (24) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Lie superalgebras of Krichever–Novikov type <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body> and there exist R  2  , R  3  (independent of n and m) such that <lb/> [L  n  , L  m  ] ⊆ <lb/> n+m+R2 <lb/> h=n+m <lb/> L  h  , <lb/> [S  n  , S  m  ] ⊆ <lb/> n+m+R3 <lb/> h=n+m <lb/> S  h  . <lb/> Also from (23) we directly conclude <lb/> Proposition 9. For all m, n ∈ J  λ  and r, p = 1, . . . , K we have <lb/> [e  n,p  , e  m,r  ] = (m − n) · e  n+m,r  δ <lb/> p <lb/>r  + h.d.t. <lb/> e  n,p  . ϕ  m,r  = (m − <lb/> n <lb/> 2 <lb/>) · ϕ  n+m,r  δ <lb/> p <lb/>r  + h.d.t. <lb/> ϕ  n,p  · ϕ  m,r  = e  n+m,r  δ <lb/> p <lb/>r  + h.d.t. <lb/> (25) <lb/> Here h.d.t. denote linear combinations of basis elements of degree between <lb/> n + m + 1 and n + m + R  i  . <lb/> See (6) for an example in the classical case (by ignoring the central <lb/>extension appearing there for the moment). <lb/> Remark. Leidwanger and Morier-Genoux introduced in [12] also a Jordan <lb/>superalgebra based on the Krichever-Novikov objects given by <lb/> J := F <lb/> 0  ⊕ F <lb/> −1/2  = J¯  0  ⊕ J¯  1  . <lb/> (26) <lb/>Recall that F <lb/> 0  is the associative algebra of meromorphic functions. The (Jor-<lb/>dan) product is defined via the algebra structure for the spaces F <lb/> λ  by <lb/> f • g := f · g ∈ F <lb/> 0  , <lb/>f • ϕ := f · ϕ ∈ F <lb/> −1/2  , <lb/>ϕ • ψ := [ϕ, ψ] ∈ F <lb/> 0  . <lb/> (27) <lb/>By rescaling the second definition with the factor 1/2 one obtains a Lie an-<lb/>tialgebra. See [12] for more details and additional results on representations. <lb/>Using the results presented here one obtains an almost-grading (depending <lb/>on a splitting A = I ∪ O) of the Jordan superalgebra <lb/> J = <lb/> m∈1/2Z <lb/> J  m  . <lb/> (28) <lb/>Hence, it makes sense to call it a Jordan superalgebra of KN type. Calculated <lb/>for the introduced basis elements we get (using Proposition 7) <lb/> A  n,p  • A  m,r  = A  n+m,r  δ <lb/> p <lb/>r  + h.d.t. <lb/> A  n,p  • ϕ  m,r  = ϕ  n+m,r  δ <lb/> p <lb/>r  + h.d.t. <lb/> ϕ  n,p  • ϕ  m,r  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(m − n)A  n+m,r  δ <lb/> p <lb/>r  + h.d.t. <lb/>(29) <lb/></body>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Martin Schlichenmaier <lb/></note>

			<body>6. Central Extensions <lb/> A central extension of a Lie algebra W is defined on the vector space direct <lb/>sum <lb/> W = C ⊕ W . If we denotê <lb/> x := (0, x) and t := (1, 0) its Lie structure is <lb/>given by <lb/>[ˆ x, ˆ <lb/> y] = <lb/> [x, y] + Φ(x, y) · t, [t, <lb/> W ] = 0, x, y ∈ W. <lb/> (30) <lb/>Then <lb/> W will be a Lie algebra, e.g. fulfill the Jacobi identity, if and only if Φ <lb/>is antisymmetric and fulfills the Lie algebra 2-cocycle condition <lb/>0 = d  2  Φ(x, y, z) := Φ([x, y], z) + Φ([y, z], x) + Φ([z, x], y). <lb/> (31) <lb/>There is the notion of equivalence of central extensions. It turns out that two <lb/>central extensions are equivalent if and only if the difference of their defining <lb/>2-cocycles Φ and Φ <lb/>  is a coboundary, i.e. there exists a φ : W → C such that <lb/>Φ(x, y) − Φ <lb/>  (x, y) = d  1  φ(x, y) = φ([x, y]). <lb/> (32) <lb/>In this way the second Lie algebra cohomology H <lb/> 2  (W, C) of W with values <lb/>in the trivial module C classifies equivalence classes of central extensions. <lb/>The class [0] corresponds to the trivial (i.e. split) central extension. Hence, <lb/>to construct central extensions of our Lie algebras we have to find such Lie <lb/>algebra 2-cocycles. <lb/>For the superalgebra case central extension are obtained with the help <lb/>of a bilinear map <lb/>Φ : S × S → C <lb/> (33) <lb/>via an expression completely analogous to (30). Additional conditions for Φ <lb/>follow from the fact that the resulting extension should be again a superal-<lb/>gebra. This implies that for homogeneous elements x, y, z ∈ S (S might be <lb/>an arbitrary Lie superalgebra) we need <lb/>Φ(x, y) = −(−1) <lb/> ¯ <lb/> x¯ y  Φ(x, y). <lb/> (34) <lb/>If x and y are odd then the bilinear map Φ will be symmetric, otherwise it <lb/>will be antisymmetric. The super-cocycle condition reads in complete analogy <lb/>with the super-Jacobi relation as <lb/>(−1) <lb/> ¯ <lb/> x¯ z  Φ(x, [y, z]) + (−1) <lb/> ¯ <lb/> y ¯ <lb/> x  Φ(y, [z, x]) + (−1) <lb/> ¯ <lb/> z ¯ <lb/> y  Φ(z, [x, y]) = 0. <lb/>(35) <lb/>As we will need it anyway, I will write it out for the different type of argu-<lb/>ments. For (even,even,even), (even,even, odd), and (odd,odd,odd) it will be <lb/>of the &quot; usual form &quot; of the cocycle condition <lb/>Φ(x, [y, z]) + Φ(y, [z, x]) + Φ(z, [x, y]) = 0. <lb/>(36) <lb/>For (even,odd,odd) we obtain <lb/>Φ(x, [y, z]) + Φ(y, [z, x]) − Φ(z, [x, y]) = 0. <lb/>(37) <lb/>Now we have to decide which parity our central element should have. In <lb/>our context, as we want to extend the central extension of the vector field <lb/>algebra to the superalgebra, the natural choice is that the central element <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Lie superalgebras of Krichever–Novikov type <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>should be even. This implies that our bilinear form Φ has to be an even form. <lb/>Consequently, <lb/>Φ(x, y) = Φ(y, x) = 0, for ¯ <lb/> x = 0, ¯ <lb/> y = 1. <lb/>(38) <lb/>In this case only (37) for the (even,odd,odd) and (36) for the (even,even,even) <lb/> case will give relations which are not trivially zero. <lb/>Given a linear form φ : S → C we assign to it <lb/> δ  1  φ(x, y) = φ([x, y]). <lb/> (39) <lb/>As in the classical case δ  1  φ will be a super-cocycle. A super-cocycle Φ will <lb/>be a coboundary if and only if there exists a linear form φ : S → C such <lb/>that Φ = δ  1  φ. As φ is a linear form it can be written as φ = φ¯  0  ⊕ φ¯  1  where <lb/> φ¯  0  : S¯  0  → C and φ¯  1  : S¯  1  → C. Again we have the two cases of the parity <lb/>of the central element. Let Φ be a coboundary δ  1  φ. If the central element is <lb/>even then Φ will also be a coboundary with respect to a φ with φ¯  1  = 0. In <lb/>other words this φ is even. In the odd case we can take φ¯  0  = 0 and φ is odd. <lb/>After fixing a parity of the central element we consider the quotient <lb/>spaces <lb/>H <lb/> 2 <lb/>¯ 0  (S, C) := {even cocycles}/{even coboundaries}, <lb/>(40) <lb/>H <lb/> 2 <lb/>¯ 1  (S, C) := {odd cocycles}/{odd coboundaries}. <lb/>(41) <lb/>These cohomology spaces classify central extensions of S with even (respec-<lb/>tively odd) central elements up to equivalence. Equivalence is defined as in <lb/>the non-super setting. <lb/>To define a super-cocycle we have to introduce the following objects. <lb/> Definition 10. Let (U  α  , z  α  )  α∈J  be a covering of the Riemann surface by <lb/>holomorphic coordinates, with transition functions z  β  = f  βα  (z  α  ). A system of <lb/>local holomorphic functions R = (R  α  (z  α  )) is called a holomorphic projective <lb/>connection if it transforms as <lb/> R  β  (z  β  ) · (f <lb/> β,α  ) <lb/> 2  = R  α  (z  α  ) + S(f  β,α  ), <lb/>with S(h) = <lb/> h <lb/> h   − <lb/> 3 <lb/>2 <lb/> h <lb/> h  <lb/>  2 <lb/> , <lb/> (42) <lb/>the Schwartzian derivative. Here <lb/>  means differentiation with respect to the <lb/>coordinate z  α  . <lb/>It is a classical result [6], [5] that every Riemann surface admits a holo-<lb/>morphic projective connection R. From the definition it follows that the differ-<lb/>ence of two projective connections is a quadratic differential. In fact starting <lb/>from one projective connection we will obtain all of them by adding quadratic <lb/>differentials to it. <lb/>If we have a cocycle Φ for the algebra S we obtain by restriction a <lb/>cocycle for the algebra L. For arguments with mixed parity we know that <lb/>Φ(e, ψ) = 0. A naive try to put just anything for Φ(ϕ, ψ) will not work as <lb/>(37) relates the restriction of the cocycle on L with its values on F <lb/> −1/2  . <lb/></body>

			<page> 12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Martin Schlichenmaier <lb/></note>

			<body>Proposition 11. [21, Prop. 5.1] Let C be any closed (differentiable) curve on <lb/> Σ not meeting the points in A, and let R be any (holomorphic) projective <lb/>connection, then the bilinear extension of <lb/> Φ  C,R  (e, f ) := <lb/>1 <lb/>24πi <lb/> C <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(e <lb/>  f − ef <lb/>  ) − R · (e <lb/>  f − ef <lb/>  ) <lb/> dz <lb/> Φ  C,R  (ϕ, ψ) := − <lb/> 1 <lb/>24πi <lb/> C <lb/> (ϕ <lb/>  · ψ + ϕ · ψ <lb/>  − R · ϕ · ψ) dz <lb/> Φ  C,R  (e, ϕ) := 0 <lb/>(43) <lb/> gives a Lie superalgebra cocycle for S, hence defines a central extension of S. <lb/> The cocycle class does not depend on the chosen connection R. <lb/> A similar formula was given by Bryant in [4]. By adding the projective <lb/>connection in the second part of (43) he corrected some formula appearing <lb/>in [1]. He only considered the two-point case and only the integration over <lb/>a separating cycle. See also [8] for the multi-point case, where still only the <lb/>integration over a separating cycle is considered. <lb/>The following remarks are in order. For the proof of the claims see [21]. <lb/>1. Adding the projective connection is necessary to make the integrand a <lb/>well-defined differential. <lb/>2. Different R will yield cohomologous cocycles. <lb/>3. With respect to the curve C only its homology class in H  1  (Σ \ A, Z) is <lb/>relevant for the cocycle. <lb/>But a different cycle class will change the cocycle in an essential manner. <lb/>We cannot expect uniqueness if g &gt; 0 or N &gt; 2. We should not forget, that <lb/>we want to extend our almost-grading of S to the centrally extended Lie <lb/>superalgebra by assigning a degree to the central element. This only works <lb/>if our cocycle is &quot; local &quot; [9] in the following sense: There exists M  1  , M  2  ∈ Z <lb/> such that <lb/> ∀n, m : ψ(W  n  , W  m  )  = 0 =⇒ M  1  ≤ n + m ≤ M  2  . <lb/> What is local is defined in terms of the almost-grading and hence depends <lb/>on the splitting A = I ∪ O. <lb/> If the integration path C in (43) is a separating cycle C  S  , i.e. a cycle <lb/>which separates the points in I from the points in O, then the cocycle Φ  C  S  ,R <lb/> is local. A special choice for C  S  is the collection of circles around the points <lb/>in I. This shows that in this case the cocycle can be calculated via residues. <lb/>How about the opposite direction? Given a local cocycle, can it be de-<lb/>scribed as such a geometric cocycle? The answer is yes and this is the main <lb/>result which we present. <lb/> Theorem 12. [21, Thm. 5.5] Given a local (even) cocycle for the Lie superal-<lb/>gebra S of Krichever–Novikov type then up to coboundary it is a multiple of <lb/> Φ  C  S  ,R  . Hence, up to rescaling and equivalence there is a unique non-trivial <lb/>almost-graded central extension of S. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Lie superalgebras of Krichever–Novikov type <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Recall that the almost-grading is fixed by the splitting. We will only <lb/>give some general remarks on the proof. <lb/>1. We start with a local cocycle for S and restrict it to L, the vector field <lb/>subalgebra. <lb/>2. This gives a local cocycle for the vector field algebra L. <lb/> 3. For such local cocycles my earlier classification results [20] show that it <lb/>is unique (in the above sense) and can by given by an expression of the <lb/>type Φ  C  S  ,R  for L. <lb/> 4. This expression we extend to S by using the full expression of Φ  C  S  ,R  . <lb/>5. The difference between the initial cocycle and the extended one vanishes <lb/>if restricted to L. <lb/> 6. Next we show that each local cocycle of S which vanishes on L van-<lb/>ishes in total. This is done by some induction process using the almost-<lb/>gradedness and the locality (more precisely, the boundedness from above <lb/>is enough). <lb/> Theorem 13. [21, Thm. 5.6] All local cocycles of odd type are coboundaries. <lb/>Hence, there does not exist non-trivial almost-graded odd central extensions <lb/>of S. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] Bonora, L., Martellini, M., Rinaldi, M., Russo, J., Neveu-Schwarz- and <lb/>Ramond-type Superalgebras on genus g Riemann surfaces, Phys. Lett. B, 206(3) <lb/>(1988), 444–450. <lb/>[2] Bonora, L., Lugo, A., Matone, M., Russo, J., A global operator formalism on <lb/>higher genus Riemann surfaces: b − c systems, Comm. Math. Phys. 123 (1989), <lb/>329–352. <lb/>[3] Bonora, L., Matone, M., Toppan, F., Wu, K., Real weight b − c systems and <lb/>conformal field theories in higher genus, Nuclear Phys. B 334 (1990), no. 3, <lb/>717–744. <lb/>[4] Bryant, P., Graded Riemann surfaces and Krichever-Novikov algebras, Lett. <lb/>Math. Phys., 19 (1990), 97–108. <lb/>[5] Gunning, R.C., Lectures on Riemann surfaces, Princeton Math. Notes, N.J. <lb/>1966. <lb/>[6] Hawley, N.S., Schiffer, M., Half-order differentials on Riemann surfaces, Acta <lb/>Math. 115 (1966), 199–236. <lb/>[7] Kac, V.G., Infinite dimensional Lie algebras. Cambridge Univ. Press, Cam-<lb/>bridge, 1990. <lb/>[8] Kreusch, M., Extensions of superalgebras of Krichever-Novikov type, Lett. <lb/>Math. Phys. 103 (11), (2013), 1171–269. arXiv:1204.4338v2. <lb/>[9] Krichever, I.M., Novikov, S.P., Algebras of Virasoro type, Riemann surfaces <lb/>and structures of the theory of solitons. Funktional Anal. i. Prilozhen. 21, No.2 <lb/>(1987), 46-63. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Martin Schlichenmaier <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> [10] Krichever, I.M., Novikov, S.P., Virasoro type algebras, Riemann surfaces and <lb/>strings in Minkowski space. Funktional Anal. i. Prilozhen. 21, No.4 (1987), <lb/>47-61. <lb/>[11] Krichever, I.M., Novikov, S.P., Algebras of Virasoro type, energy-momentum <lb/>tensors and decompositions of operators on Riemann surfaces. Funktional Anal. <lb/>i. Prilozhen. 23, No.1 (1989), 46-63. <lb/>[12] Leidwanger, S., Morier-Genoud, S., Superalgebras associated to Riemann sur-<lb/>faces: Jordan algebras of Krichever-Novikov type, Int. Math. Res. Notices, <lb/>doi:10.1093/imrn/rnr196 <lb/>[13] Leidwanger, S., Morier-Genoud, S., Universal enveloping algebras of Lie an-<lb/>tialgebras, Algebras and Representation Theory 15(1) (2012), 1–27 <lb/>[14] Ovsienko, V., Lie antialgebras: prémices, J. of Algebra 325 (1) (2011), 216–247 <lb/>[15] Schlichenmaier, M., Krichever-Novikov algebras for more than two points. Lett. <lb/>Math. Phys. 19 (1990), 151-165. <lb/>[16] Schlichenmaier, M., Krichever-Novikov algebras for more than two points: ex-<lb/>plicit generators. Lett. Math. Phys. 19 (1990), 327-336. <lb/>[17] Schlichenmaier, M., Central extensions and semi-infinite wedge representations <lb/>of Krichever-Novikov algebras for more than two points. Letters in Mathemat-<lb/>ical Physics 20 (1990), 33-46. <lb/>[18] Schlichenmaier, M.,Verallgemeinerte Krichever -Novikov Algebren und deren <lb/>Darstellungen. Ph.D. thesis, Universität Mannheim, 1990. <lb/>[19] Schlichenmaier, M., Zwei Anwendungen algebraisch-geometrischer Methoden in <lb/>der theoretischen Physik: Berezin-Toeplitz-Quantisierung und globale Algebren <lb/>der zweidimensionalen konformen Feldtheorie &quot; , Habilitation Thesis, University <lb/>of Mannheim, June 1996. <lb/>[20] Schlichenmaier, M., Local cocycles and central extensions for multi-point al-<lb/>gebras of Krichever-Novikov type. J. Reine und Angewandte Mathematik 559 <lb/>(2003), 53–94. <lb/>[21] Schlichenmaier, M., Lie superalgebras of Krichever–Novikov type and their <lb/>central extensions. Analysis and Math. Phys. 3(3) 2013, 235–261, DOI <lb/>10.1007/s13324-013-0056-7. <lb/>[22] Schlichenmaier, M., Krichever-Novikov algebras. Theory and Applications, <lb/> Studies in Mathematics 53, DeGruyter, 2014. <lb/>[23] Zachos, C.K., Fermionic center in the superconformal algebra on the supertorus, <lb/> Nucl. Phys. B (Proc. Suppl.) 11 (1989), 414–424. <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">Martin Schlichenmaier <lb/>University of Luxembourg <lb/>Mathematics Research Unit, FSTC <lb/>Campus Kirchberg, 6, rue Coudenhove-Kalergi <lb/>L-1359 Luxembourg-Kirchberg, Luxembourg <lb/>e-mail: martin.schlichenmaier@uni.lu</div>

	</text>
</tei>
