<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> International Journal of Theoretical and Mathematical Physics 2011; 1(1): 1-11 <lb/>DOI: 10.5923/j.ijtmp.20110101.01 <lb/> Quantum Theory at Planck Scale, Dynamical <lb/>Cosmological Term and Deformed Gravity <lb/> A. E. Shalyt-Margolin <lb/> National Centre of Particles and High Energy Physics, Bogdanovich Str. 153, Minsk, 220040, Belarus <lb/> Abstract  The dark energy problem is analyzed from the viewpoint of the time-varying cosmological term. It is demon-<lb/>strated that, at least within the scope of the holographic principle, an experimental value of the vacuum energy density may be <lb/>derived and may be tested quite well with a new small parameter arising in a quantum theory with the fundamental length on <lb/>the order of Planck&apos;s length. Besides, within a theory proclaiming the existence of such fundamental length a high-energy <lb/>deformation of the General Relativity for the space with horizon has been constructed. The obtained results have been applied <lb/>to solving of the dark energy problem, making it possible to frame the following hypothesis: a dynamic cosmological term is <lb/>a measure of deviation from a thermodynamic identity (the first law of thermodynamics) of the high-energy (Planck&apos;s) de-<lb/>formation of Einstein equations for horizon spaces in their thermodynamic interpretation. <lb/> Keywords  Dark Energy, Fundamental Length, Deformation Parameter <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> The cosmological constant  Λ  is presently the most <lb/>probable candidate for a role of dark energy. However, more <lb/>and more researchers arrive at the idea that  Λ  is a dynamic <lb/>quantity <lb/> ( ) <lb/> t <lb/> Λ = Λ  [1–3] rather than a constant. The idea is <lb/>also supported by the inflation models pointing to the fact <lb/>that in the early Universe the quantity was enormous[4], <lb/>whereas this is evidently not so for the present-day Universe. <lb/>If this is really the case, we have to appreciate time variations <lb/>of this quantity and to realize why its current value conforms <lb/>to the observable. <lb/>It should be recalled that in the initial calculations of  Λ <lb/> with the use of a quantum field theory (QFT) it was cut-off at <lb/>large (Planck) momenta[5,6] and, actually, implicitly it was <lb/>QFT with the fundamental length on the order of Planck&apos;s <lb/> p <lb/> l  . <lb/>On the other hand, in the last decade numerous works <lb/>devoted to a Quantum Field Theory (QFT) at Planck&apos;s <lb/>scale[7–9] have been published(of course, the author has no <lb/>pretensions of being exhaustive in his references). This in-<lb/>terest stems from the facts that (i) at these scales it is ex-<lb/>pected to reveal the effects of a Quantum Gravity (QG), and <lb/>this still unresolved theory is intriguing all the researchers <lb/>engaged in the field of theoretical physics; (ii) modern ac-<lb/>celerators, in particular LHC, have the capacity of achieving <lb/>the energies at which some QG effects may be exhibited. <lb/></body>

			<front> * Corresponding author: <lb/>a.shalyt@mail.ru (A. E. Shalyt-Margolin) <lb/>Published online at http://journal.sapub.org/ijtmp <lb/>Copyright © 2011 Scientific &amp; Academic Publishing. All Rights Reserved <lb/></front>

			<body> Planck&apos;s scales undergoes changes associated with the <lb/>appearance of additional parameters related to a minimal <lb/>length (on the order of the Planck&apos;s length). As this takes <lb/>place, the corresponding parameters are naturally considered <lb/>as deformation parameters, i.e. the related quantum theories <lb/>are considered as a high-energy deformation (at Planck&apos;s <lb/>scales) of the well-known quantum field theory. The de-<lb/>formation is understood as an extension of a particular theory <lb/>by inclusion of one or several additional parameters in such a <lb/>way that the initial theory appears in the limiting transi-<lb/>tion[10]. <lb/>The present work is a natural continuation of the previous <lb/>papers of the author. The idea that a quantum theory at the <lb/>Planck scales must involve the fundamental length has been <lb/>put forward in the works devoted to a string theory fairly a <lb/>long time ago[11]. But since it is still considered to be a <lb/>tentative theory, some other indications have been required. <lb/>Fortunately, by the present time numerous publications have <lb/>suggested the appearance of the fundamental length in the <lb/>Early Universe with the use of various approaches[12–15]. <lb/>Of particular importance is the work[12], where on the basis <lb/>of a simple gedanken experiment it is demonstrated that, <lb/>with regard to the gravitational interactions (Planck&apos;s scales) <lb/>exhibited in the Early Universe only, the Heisenberg Un-<lb/>certainty Principle should be extended to the Generalized <lb/>Uncertainty Principle[11–15]that in turn is bound to bring <lb/>forth the fundamental length on the order of Planck&apos;s length. <lb/>The advent of novel theories in physics of the Early Universe <lb/>is associated with the introduction of new parameters, i.e. <lb/>with a deformation of the well-known theories. Of course, in <lb/>this case Heisenberg Algebra is subjected to the corre-<lb/>sponding deformation too. Such a deformation may be based <lb/></body>

			<page> 2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A.E.Shalyt-Margolin: Quantum Theory at Planck Scale, Dynamical Cosmological Term and Deformed Gravity <lb/></note>

			<body> on the Generalized Uncertainty Principle (GUP)[16–18] as <lb/>well as on the density matrix deformation[19–29]. <lb/>At the same time, the above-mentioned new deformation <lb/>parameters so far have not appeared in gravity despite the <lb/>idea that they should. The situation is that no evident efforts <lb/>have been undertaken to develop the high-energy (Planck&apos;s <lb/>scale) gravity deformations including the deformation pa-<lb/>rameters introduced in a Quantum Theory of the Early <lb/>Universe. <lb/>In this paper, with GUP held true, the possibility for the <lb/>high-energy gravity deformation is considered for a specific <lb/>case of Einstein&apos;s equations. As this takes place, the pa-<lb/>rameter  α  appearing in the Quantum Field Theory (QFT) <lb/>with the UV cut off (fundamental length) produced by the <lb/>density matrix deformation is used. There is no discrepancy <lb/>of any kind as the deformation parameter in the GUP-pro-<lb/>duced Heisenberg algebra deformation is quite naturally <lb/>expressed in terms of  α  , and this will be shown later (Sec-<lb/>tion 3). Besides, by its nature,  α  is better applicable to <lb/>study the high-energy deformation of General Relativity <lb/>because it is small, dimensionless (making series expansion <lb/>more natural), and the corresponding representation of the <lb/>Einstein&apos;s equations in its terms or its deformation appear <lb/>simple. Structurally, the paper is as follows. Section 2 pre-<lb/>sents a short discussion o the notion of a dynamic cosmo-<lb/>logical term and also the general problem statement associ-<lb/>ated with its connection to the dark energy problem. In Sec-<lb/>tion 3 the approaches to the deformation of a quantum theory <lb/>at the Planck scales are briefly reviewed. In Section 4 the <lb/>possibilities for derivation of a modern value of the dark <lb/>energy in the assumption of the existing dynamic cosmo-<lb/>logical term ( ) <lb/> t <lb/> Λ <lb/> are analyzed using the standard approach <lb/>to the cosmological constant  Λ  [5,6]. It is shown that only <lb/>the validity of the holographic principle gives the required <lb/>result. This Section is mainly based on the author&apos;s re-<lb/>sults[30,31]. In Section 5 it is shown how to interpret quan-<lb/>tum corrections for the thermodynamic characteristics of <lb/>black holes considering the deformation of a theory with the <lb/>fundamental length[31]. Essentially new results are pre-<lb/>sented in Sections 5 and 6. A thermodynamic description of <lb/>the General Relativity is used. The possibility for the high <lb/>energy deformation of Einstein&apos;s equations is discussed <lb/>within the scope of both equilibrium thermodynamics and <lb/>non-equilibrium thermodynamics. In the latter case the ap-<lb/>proach is contemplated only in terms of a nature of the <lb/>cosmological term. Moreover, in this case a more precise <lb/>definition for the dependence of this term on the deformation <lb/>parameter is possible. In Section 7 the derived results are <lb/>applied to solve the dark energy problem. Based on the re-<lb/>sults obtained, in Conclusion the following hypothesis is <lb/>framed: a dynamic cosmological term is a measure of de-<lb/>viation from the thermodynamic identity (the first law of <lb/>thermodynamics) of the high-energy (Planck&apos;s) deformation <lb/>of Einstein equations for horizon spaces in their thermody-<lb/>namic interpretation. <lb/> 2. Dark Energy and Dynamical <lb/>Cosmological Term <lb/> The dark matter problem[32], along with the dark energy <lb/>problem[33], is presently the basic problem in modern fun-<lb/>damental physics, astrophysics, and cosmology. Whereas for <lb/>a nature of the first real hypotheses have been accepted al-<lb/>ready[34], the dark energy still remains enigmatic[35–38]. <lb/>But it is the opinion of most researchers that dark energy <lb/>represents the energy of the cosmic vacuum, its density being <lb/>associated with the cosmological term  Λ  in Einstein&apos;s <lb/>equation[5,6,39]. In this respect an important reservation <lb/>must be made – the point is that most common is the term <lb/>cosmological constant. Actually, due to the Bianchi identi-<lb/>ties[40] <lb/> 0 <lb/> G <lb/> µ <lb/>µ <lb/>ν <lb/> ∇ <lb/>= <lb/> (1) <lb/>where  G <lb/> µ <lb/>ν  – Einstein equations <lb/> 4 <lb/>4 <lb/> 1 <lb/>8 <lb/>2 <lb/>8 <lb/> G <lb/>c <lb/>G <lb/>R <lb/>R <lb/>T <lb/>c <lb/>G <lb/> µ <lb/>µ <lb/>µ <lb/>µ <lb/>µ <lb/>ν <lb/>ν <lb/>ν <lb/>ν <lb/>ν <lb/> π <lb/>δ <lb/>δ <lb/>π <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> Λ <lb/>≡ <lb/>− = <lb/>+ <lb/> (2) <lb/>the energy-momentum tensor  T <lb/> µ <lb/>ν <lb/> (energy-momentum <lb/>density tensor) remains covariantly valid <lb/> 0 <lb/> T <lb/> µ <lb/>µ <lb/>ν <lb/> ∇ <lb/>= <lb/> (3) <lb/>From whence it directly follows that the cosmological <lb/>term  Λ  is a constant. <lb/>But, as has been rightly noted in several publications <lb/>(e.g.,[1–3]), conservation laws (3) are only regulating the <lb/>energy-momentum exchange between the field sources and <lb/>gravitational field and are liable to be violated if an inde-<lb/>pendent energy source is existent in the Universe. Such a <lb/>source may be associated with a time-varying cosmological <lb/>term. So, in this case it is reasonable to consider <lb/> ( ) <lb/> t <lb/> Λ = Λ  . <lb/>Then the Bianchi identity (1) is replaced by the &quot;general-<lb/>ized Bianchi identity&quot;[2] <lb/> 0 <lb/> T <lb/> µ <lb/>µ <lb/>µ <lb/>ν <lb/>ν <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> ∇ <lb/>+ Λ = <lb/> (4) <lb/>where <lb/> µ <lb/>µ <lb/>ν <lb/>ν <lb/> ε δ <lb/> Λ <lb/> Λ = <lb/> is some energy-momentum tensor <lb/>(referred to as the dark energy-momentum tensor [2]) related <lb/>to the cosmological term, where <lb/> 4 <lb/> 8 <lb/> c <lb/>G <lb/> ε <lb/>π <lb/> Λ <lb/> Λ <lb/>= <lb/> (5) <lb/>is the corresponding energy density. <lb/>We are not interested in a diversity of the cosmological <lb/>models involving the dynamic cosmological term <lb/> ( ) <lb/> t <lb/> Λ = Λ <lb/> and different relationships between  Λ  and  t  . Rather de-<lb/>tailed references to such models have been made in the the-<lb/>siswork[41]. Of interest is the problem: how can we obtain <lb/>the observable value of <lb/> observ <lb/> Λ = Λ <lb/> knowing that  Λ  is de-<lb/>pendent on  t  . <lb/> 3. Quantum Theory at Planck&apos;s Scale <lb/>and Universal Deformation <lb/>Parameter <lb/> In the last twenty years the researchers have come to the <lb/>understanding that studies of the Early Universe physics <lb/>(extremely high – Planck&apos;s energies) necessitate changes in <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> International Journal of Theoretical and Mathematical Physics 2011; 1(1): 1-11 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body> the fundamental physical theories, specifically quantum <lb/>mechanics and quantum field theory. Inevitably a funda-<lb/>mental length should be involved in these theories[14–17]. <lb/>This idea has been first suggested by a string theory[11]. But <lb/>it is still considered to be a tentative theory without the ex-<lb/>perimental status and merely an attractive model. However, <lb/>the fundamental length has been involved subsequently in <lb/>more simple and natural considerations[12]. <lb/>The main approach to framing of Quantum Mechanics <lb/>with fundamental length (QMFL) and Quantum Field The-<lb/>ory with fundamental length (QFTFL) (or with Ultraviolet <lb/>(UV) cutoff) is that associated with the Generalized Uncer-<lb/>tainty Principle (GUP)[11–18]: <lb/> 2 <lb/> p <lb/> p <lb/>x <lb/>l <lb/>p <lb/> α <lb/> ′ <lb/> ≥ <lb/>+ <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> (6) <lb/>with the corresponding Heisenberg algebra deformation <lb/>produced by this principle[16–18]. <lb/>Besides, in the works by the author[19–28] an approach to <lb/>the construction of QMFL has been developed with the help <lb/>of the deformed density matrix, the density matrix deforma-<lb/>tion in QMFL being a starting object called the density <lb/>pro-matrix ( )3 <lb/> ρ α  and deformation parameter (additional <lb/>parameter) <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 <lb/> min <lb/> l <lb/>x <lb/> α <lb/> = <lb/>/ <lb/> (7) <lb/>where  x  is the measuring scale,  min <lb/>p <lb/> l <lb/>l <lb/>  <lb/> and <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 4 <lb/> α <lb/> &lt; ≤ /  [19–25]. <lb/>The explicit form of the above-mentioned deformation <lb/>gives the exponential ansatz <lb/> ( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/> i <lb/>i <lb/> exp <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/> ρ α <lb/>α <lb/>ω <lb/> * <lb/> = <lb/>− <lb/>| &gt;&lt; | <lb/> ∑ <lb/> (8) <lb/>where all <lb/> 0 <lb/> i <lb/> ω &gt;  are independent of  α  and their sum is <lb/>equal to 1. <lb/>In the corresponding deformed Quantum Theory (denoted <lb/>as  QFT <lb/> α <lb/> ) for average values we have <lb/> ( ) <lb/> B <lb/>exp <lb/>B <lb/> α <lb/> α <lb/> &lt; &gt; = <lb/>− &lt; &gt; <lb/> (9) <lb/>where  B <lb/> &lt; &gt;  -average in well-known QFT[24,25]. All <lb/>the variables associated with the considered  α  -deformed <lb/>quantum field theory are hereinafter marked with the upper <lb/>index <lb/> α <lb/> . <lb/>Note that the deformation parameter  α  is absolutely <lb/>naturally represented as a ratio between the squared UV and <lb/>IR limits <lb/> 2 <lb/> ( <lb/>) <lb/> UV <lb/>IR <lb/> α = <lb/> (10) <lb/>where UV is fixed and IR is varying. <lb/>It should be noted[29] that in a series of the author&apos;s <lb/>works[19–28] a minimal  α  -deformation of QFT has been <lb/>formed. By &quot; minimal &quot; it is meant that no space-time non-<lb/>commutativity was required, i.e. there was no requirement <lb/>for noncommutative operators associated with different <lb/>spatial coordinates <lb/> [ <lb/>] 0 <lb/> i <lb/>j <lb/> X X <lb/>i j <lb/> , <lb/>≠ , ≠ <lb/> (11) <lb/>However, all the well-known deformations of QFT asso-<lb/>ciated with GUP (for example[16–18]) contain (11) as an <lb/>element of the corresponding deformed Heisenberg algebra. <lb/>Because of this, it is necessary to extend (or modify) the <lb/>above-mentioned minimal  α  -deformation of QFT –  QFT <lb/> α <lb/> [19-28] to some new deformation   <lb/> QFT <lb/> α  compatible with <lb/>GUP, as it has been noted in[29]. We can easily show that <lb/>QFT parameter of deformations associated with GUP may be <lb/>expressed in terms of the parameter  α  that has been intro-<lb/>duced in the approach associated with the density matrix <lb/>deformation[30,31]. Here the notation of[42] is used. Then <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 <lb/> [ <lb/>] <lb/>(1 <lb/>) <lb/> x p i <lb/>p <lb/> β <lb/> , = <lb/>+ <lb/>+ ... <lb/>   <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> (12) <lb/>and <lb/> min <lb/> p <lb/> x <lb/>l <lb/> β <lb/> ∆ <lb/>≈ <lb/>  <lb/> (13) <lb/>Then from (12), (13) it follows that <lb/> 2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> β <lb/> / p <lb/>  <lb/> , and for <lb/> min <lb/> p <lb/> x <lb/>l <lb/>   ,  β  corresponding to min <lb/> x <lb/> is nothing else but <lb/> 2 <lb/> 1  pl <lb/> P <lb/> β <lb/> / <lb/>  <lb/> (14) <lb/>where  pl <lb/> P  is Planck&apos;s momentum:  pl <lb/>p <lb/> P <lb/>l <lb/> = <lb/>/ <lb/>  <lb/> . <lb/>In this way  β  is changing over the following interval: <lb/> 2 <lb/> pl <lb/> P <lb/> λ <lb/>β <lb/> / <lb/>≤ &lt; ∞ <lb/> (15) <lb/>where  λ  is a numerical factor and the second member in <lb/>(12) is accurately reproduced in momentum representation <lb/>(up to the numerical factor) by <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/> min <lb/>p <lb/>pl <lb/> l <lb/>l <lb/>l l <lb/>p P <lb/> α = <lb/>/ <lb/>/ = <lb/>/ <lb/>  <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> [ <lb/>] <lb/>(1 <lb/>) <lb/>(1 <lb/>) <lb/> x p i <lb/>i <lb/>a <lb/>a <lb/>p <lb/> β <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/> , = <lb/>+ <lb/>+ ... <lb/>= = <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ ... <lb/>   <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> (16) <lb/> 4. Dynamical Cosmological Term and Its <lb/>Modern Value <lb/> As is known, a direct calculation of the vacuum energy <lb/>density  vac <lb/> ρ  results in the value that is higher than the ex-<lb/>perimental one by a factor of <lb/> 122 <lb/> 10 . According to the typical <lb/>reasoning that is already &quot; canonical &quot; we have[5,6,43]: <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/> 4 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>(2 ) <lb/> max <lb/> p <lb/>vac <lb/> p <lb/>dp <lb/> π <lb/>ω <lb/>ρ <lb/>π <lb/> &lt; <lb/>&gt;= ∫ <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> (17) <lb/>where  max <lb/>pl <lb/> p <lb/>P <lb/>  <lb/> is the momentum cut-off at Planck <lb/>scales, because the General Relativity is valid right up to the <lb/>Planck scales. Proceeding from <lb/> ( <lb/>) <lb/> p <lb/>c <lb/> ω <lb/> = <lb/>/ <lb/>  <lb/> , we can ob-<lb/>tain[43] <lb/> 4 <lb/>2 3 <lb/> 8 <lb/> vac <lb/> c <lb/> ρ <lb/>π <lb/> Ω <lb/>&lt; <lb/>&gt;= <lb/>  <lb/> (18) <lb/>And then  Ω  is given by  p <lb/> Ω  , where <lb/> 1 2 <lb/>5 <lb/> p <lb/>p <lb/> c <lb/>E <lb/>G <lb/> / <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/>Ω = <lb/>=  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> (19) <lb/>But it is known that <lb/> p <lb/> ρ <lb/> &lt; <lb/>&gt;  is higher than the observable <lb/>value <lb/> obs <lb/>vac <lb/> ρ  [6,43] approximately by a factor of <lb/> 122 <lb/> 10 . <lb/>Yet, taking the cosmological term as a dynamic quantity, <lb/>we can write (17) as <lb/> 2 <lb/>( ) <lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/> 4 <lb/>( ) <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>(2 ) <lb/> p t <lb/>vac <lb/> p <lb/>t <lb/>dp <lb/> π <lb/>ω <lb/>ρ <lb/>π <lb/> &lt; <lb/>&gt;= ∫ <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> (20) <lb/></body>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A.E.Shalyt-Margolin: Quantum Theory at Planck Scale, Dynamical Cosmological Term and Deformed Gravity <lb/></note>

			<body> that in the very early Universe, at the time close to the <lb/>Planck&apos;s time  p <lb/> t  , turns to (17) as follows: <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/> 4 <lb/>( ) <lb/>2 <lb/>(2 ) <lb/>2 <lb/> pl <lb/> P <lb/>vac <lb/>p <lb/> p <lb/>t <lb/>dp <lb/> π <lb/> ω <lb/>ρ <lb/>π <lb/> &lt; <lb/>&gt;= ∫ <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> (21) <lb/>However, it is known that the experimental value <lb/> obs <lb/>vac <lb/> ρ <lb/> is <lb/>sooner determined by low momenta and energies (corre-<lb/>sponding to large scales) and also by the infrared limit that is <lb/>given by a radius of the measurable part of the Universe <lb/> 28 <lb/> 10 <lb/> Univ <lb/> R <lb/>cm <lb/> = <lb/> . For such momenta by the uncertainty princi-<lb/>ple (17) we have <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/> 4 <lb/>( ) <lb/>2 <lb/>(2 ) 2 <lb/> min <lb/> p <lb/>vac Univ <lb/> p <lb/>t <lb/>dp <lb/> π <lb/>ω <lb/>ρ <lb/>π <lb/> &lt; <lb/>&gt;= ∫ <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> (22) <lb/>where  Univ <lb/> t <lb/> –Universe life-time,  min <lb/> p <lb/> –&quot;minimal&quot; mo-<lb/>mentum. <lb/>As <lb/> 61 <lb/> 10 <lb/> Univ <lb/>p <lb/>pl <lb/>min <lb/> R <lb/>l <lb/>P p <lb/> / = <lb/>/ <lb/>= <lb/> , then by analogy (18)and in <lb/>the infrared limit <lb/> 4 <lb/>2 3 <lb/> ( ) <lb/>8 <lb/> min <lb/>vac Univ <lb/> t <lb/>c <lb/> ρ <lb/>π <lb/> Ω <lb/>&lt; <lb/>&gt;= <lb/>  <lb/> (23) <lb/>where <lb/> min <lb/>min <lb/> E <lb/> Ω = <lb/>  <lb/> (24) <lb/>But in this case <lb/> ( ) <lb/> vac Univ <lb/> t <lb/> ρ <lb/> is lower than  vac <lb/> ρ  calculated <lb/>from(17) by a factor of <lb/> 244 <lb/> 10 rather than by a factor of <lb/> 122 <lb/> 10 . <lb/>This result is easily obtained using the Uncertainty Prin-<lb/>ciple for the pair of conjugate variables ( <lb/>) <lb/> V <lb/> Λ,  ,[44–47]: <lb/> V <lb/> ∆ ≈ ∆Λ <lb/>  <lb/> (25) <lb/>where  Λ  is the dynamic cosmological term,  V  is the <lb/>space-time volume. And  V  results from the Einstein-Hil-<lb/>bert action  EH <lb/> S  [45]: <lb/> 4 <lb/> d x g <lb/>V <lb/> Λ <lb/>− = Λ <lb/> ∫ <lb/> (26) <lb/>where (26) is the term in  EH <lb/> S  . <lb/>In[30,31] the Uncertainty Principle (25) has been gener-<lb/>alized at Planck scales up to the Generalized Uncertainty <lb/>Principle <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 <lb/> p <lb/> V <lb/>t V <lb/> α <lb/> ′ <lb/> ∆Λ <lb/>∆ ≈ <lb/>+ <lb/>∆Λ <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> (27) <lb/>where  V  -spatial part  V  that, as is assumed, may be <lb/>extracted explicitly. <lb/>(27) is of interest from the viewpoint of two limits[30,31]: <lb/>1) IR -limit:  t → ∞ <lb/> 2) UV -limit: <lb/> min <lb/> t t <lb/> → <lb/> . <lb/>In the case of IR-limit we have large volumes  V  and  V <lb/> at low  ∆Λ  . Because of this, the main contribution on the <lb/>right-hand side of (27) is made by the first term, as great  V <lb/> in the second term is damped by small  p <lb/> t  and  ∆Λ  . Thus, <lb/>we derive at <lb/> lim <lb/> t <lb/> V <lb/> →∞ <lb/> ∆ ≈ ∆Λ <lb/>  <lb/> (28) <lb/>in accordance with (25) and  Λ  is a dynamic value fluc-<lb/>tuating around zero. <lb/>And for the case 2)  ∆Λ  becomes significant <lb/> 3 <lb/>3 <lb/> lim <lb/>lim <lb/> min <lb/>min <lb/> p <lb/>min <lb/>p <lb/>p p <lb/>min <lb/>p <lb/>t t <lb/>t t <lb/> V <lb/>l <lb/>V V <lb/>V l t <lb/>V <lb/>V <lb/> → <lb/>→ <lb/> = <lb/>= ; <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> (29) <lb/>As a result, we have <lb/> 2 <lb/> lim <lb/> min <lb/> p <lb/>t t <lb/> V <lb/>V <lb/> α Λ <lb/>→ <lb/> ∆Λ <lb/>∆ = <lb/>+ <lb/>∆Λ <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> (30) <lb/>where the parameter  α Λ  absorbs all the above-mentioned <lb/>proportionality coefficients. <lb/>For (30), <lb/> p <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/> V <lb/>E V <lb/> ∆Λ Λ ≡ / = <lb/>/ <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> . <lb/>It is easily seen that in this case <lb/> 4 <lb/> p <lb/> m <lb/> Λ  <lb/> , in agreement <lb/>with the value obtained using a standard (i.e. without su-<lb/>per-symmetry and the like) quantum field theory[6,5]. De-<lb/>spite the fact that  Λ  at Planck&apos;s scales (referred to as  UV <lb/> Λ  ) <lb/>(30) is also a dynamic quantity, it is not directly related to <lb/>well-known  Λ  (25),(28) (called  IR <lb/> Λ  ) because the latter, as <lb/>opposed to the first one, is derived from Einstein&apos;s equations <lb/> 1 <lb/>8 <lb/>2 <lb/> N <lb/> R <lb/>g R <lb/>G <lb/>g <lb/>T <lb/> µν <lb/>µν <lb/>µν <lb/>µν <lb/> π <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> − = <lb/>−Λ <lb/>+ <lb/> (31) <lb/>However, Einstein&apos;s equations (31) are not valid at the <lb/>Planck scales and hence  UV <lb/> Λ  may be considered as some <lb/>high-energy generalization of the conventional cosmological <lb/>constant, leading to  IR <lb/> Λ  in the low-energy limit. <lb/>As <lb/> 3 <lb/>4 <lb/> V l l <lb/> t <lb/>    , where  l  -characteristic linear dimension  V  , <lb/>it is directly inferred that in the infrared region  IR <lb/> Λ  calcu-<lb/>lated for <lb/> Univ <lb/> l R <lb/> = <lb/> is lower than  UV <lb/> Λ <lb/> in <lb/> 4 <lb/>4 <lb/>244 <lb/> 10 <lb/> Univ <lb/>p <lb/> R <lb/>l <lb/> / = <lb/>  <lb/> , <lb/>that is in a perfect agreement with the result obtained by the <lb/>direct calculations at the beginning of this Section. <lb/>In other words, a quantum field theory with UV-cutoff in <lb/>the assumption that  Λ  is a dynamic quantity gives no cor-<lb/>rect value for  observ <lb/> Λ <lb/> as well. <lb/>In this way, similar to[48,49], we obtain <lb/> DE <lb/>UR IR <lb/> Λ = Λ Λ <lb/> (32) <lb/>where  DE <lb/>observ <lb/> Λ = Λ <lb/> – cosmological term corresponding to <lb/>the observable value. <lb/>Now we demonstrate that the Holographic Princi-<lb/>ple[50–53] is helpful in the solution of this problem, the <lb/>deformation parameter  α  (7) &quot; testing &quot; variations of  vac <lb/> ρ  in <lb/>time and hence playing the critical role. <lb/>In terms of the deformation parameter  α  , the principal <lb/>values of the Vacuum Energy Problem may be simply and <lb/>clearly defined. Let us begin with the Schwarzschild black <lb/>holes, whose semiclassical entropy is given by <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/> Sch <lb/> Sch <lb/>p <lb/>Sch p <lb/>R <lb/> S <lb/>R <lb/>l <lb/>R m <lb/> π <lb/>π <lb/>πα <lb/> − <lb/> = <lb/>/ = <lb/>= <lb/> (33) <lb/>with the assumption that in the formula for  α  Sch <lb/> R <lb/>x <lb/> =  is <lb/>the measuring scale and <lb/> 1 <lb/> p <lb/>p <lb/> l <lb/>m <lb/> = / <lb/> . Here  Sch <lb/> R <lb/> is the ade-<lb/>quate Schwarzschild radius, and <lb/> Sch <lb/> R <lb/> α <lb/> is the value of  α <lb/> associated with this radius. Then, as it has been pointed out <lb/>in [55], in case the Fischler -Susskind cosmic holographic <lb/>conjecture[56] is valid, the entropy of the Universe is limited <lb/>by its &quot;surface&quot; measured in Planck units[55]: <lb/> 2 <lb/> 4 <lb/> p <lb/> A <lb/>S <lb/>m <lb/> ≤ <lb/> (34) <lb/>where the surface area <lb/> 2 <lb/> 4 <lb/> A <lb/>R <lb/> π <lb/> = <lb/> is defined in terms of <lb/>the apparent (Hubble) horizon <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> International Journal of Theoretical and Mathematical Physics 2011; 1(1): 1-11 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body> 2 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> R <lb/> H k a <lb/> = <lb/> + / <lb/> (35) <lb/>with curvature  k  and scale  a  factors. <lb/>Again, interpreting  R  from (35) as a measuring scale, <lb/>we directly obtain(34) in terms of  a  : <lb/> 1 <lb/> R <lb/> S  πα <lb/> − <lb/> ≤ <lb/> (36) <lb/>where <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 <lb/> R <lb/>p <lb/> l R <lb/> α = <lb/>/  . Therefore, the average entropy density <lb/>may be found as <lb/> 1 <lb/> R <lb/> S <lb/>V <lb/>V <lb/> πα <lb/> − <lb/> ≤ <lb/> (37) <lb/>Using further the reasoning line of[55] based on the results <lb/>of the holographic thermodynamics, we can relate the en-<lb/>tropy and energy of a holographic system[54]. Similarly, in <lb/>terms of the  α  parameter one can easily estimate the upper <lb/>limit for the energy density of the Universe (denoted here by <lb/> hol <lb/> ρ  ): <lb/> 2 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/> 3 <lb/>3 <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/> hol <lb/>p <lb/>R p <lb/> m <lb/>m <lb/>R <lb/> ρ <lb/>α <lb/>π <lb/>π <lb/> ≤ <lb/>= <lb/> (38) <lb/>that is drastically differing from the one obtained with <lb/>well-known QFT <lb/> 4 <lb/> QFT <lb/>p <lb/> m <lb/> ρ <lb/>  <lb/> (39) <lb/>Here by <lb/> QFT <lb/> ρ <lb/> we denote the energy vacuum density <lb/>calculated from well-known QFT (without UV cutoff)[5]. <lb/>Obviously, as  R <lb/> α  for  R  determined by (35) is very small, <lb/>actually approximating zero,  hol <lb/> ρ <lb/> is by several orders of <lb/>magnitude smaller than the value expected in QFT – <lb/> QFT <lb/> ρ  . <lb/>Since <lb/> 1 <lb/> p <lb/>p <lb/> m <lb/>l <lb/> / <lb/>  <lb/> , the right-hand side of (38) is actually <lb/>nothing else but the energy density in Holographic Dark <lb/>Energy Models[57–60]. Thus, in Holographic Dark Energy <lb/>Models the principal quantity, holographic energy density <lb/> ρ Λ  , may be estimated in terms of the deformation parameter <lb/> α  . <lb/>In fact, the upper limit of the right-hand side of (38) is <lb/>attainable, as it has been indicated in[55]. The &quot;overestima-<lb/>tion&quot; value of  r  for the energy density <lb/> QFT <lb/> ρ  , compared to <lb/> hol <lb/> ρ  , may be determined as <lb/> 2 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 8 <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/> QFT <lb/>hol <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/> R <lb/>S <lb/>r <lb/>S <lb/>l <lb/> ρ <lb/>π <lb/>π <lb/>π <lb/>α <lb/>ρ <lb/> − <lb/> = = <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/> R <lb/> (40) <lb/>where  p <lb/> S  is the entropy of the Plank mass and length for <lb/>the Schwarzschild black hole. It is clear that due to smallness <lb/>of  R <lb/> α  the value of <lb/> 1 <lb/> R <lb/> α <lb/> − <lb/> is on the contrary too large. It may <lb/>be easily calculated (e.g., see[55]) <lb/> 122 <lb/> 5 44 10 <lb/> r = . × <lb/> (41) <lb/>in a good agreement with the astrophysical data. <lb/>Naturally, on the assumption that the vacuum energy <lb/>density  vac <lb/> ρ  is involved in  ρ  as a term <lb/> M <lb/>vac <lb/> ρ ρ <lb/>ρ <lb/> = <lb/>+ <lb/> (42) <lb/>where  M <lb/> ρ  -average matter density, in case of  vac <lb/> ρ  we <lb/>can arrive to the same upper limit (right-hand side of the <lb/>formula (38)) as for  ρ  . <lb/>Average values of any quantity in QFT with UV-cutoff <lb/>may be expended in terms of the small parameter  α  (Sec-<lb/>tion 3). Specifically, for the vacuum energy density ( ) <lb/> t <lb/> ρ <lb/> in <lb/>the most general case we have <lb/> 2 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/> t <lb/>a a t a <lb/>t <lb/> ρ <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/> &lt; <lb/>&gt; <lb/>= <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/> (43) <lb/>In[48,49] a similar expansion was performed for <lb/> ( ) <lb/> IR <lb/> t <lb/> α <lb/>α <lb/> = <lb/> : <lb/> 2 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>vac <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/> 1 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 (1 <lb/>) <lb/> p <lb/>p <lb/>IR <lb/>IR <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/> l <lb/>l <lb/>l <lb/>l <lb/>l <lb/>l <lb/>l <lb/>l <lb/> ρ <lb/>α α <lb/> Λ <lb/>Λ <lb/>   <lb/>  <lb/>= <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ ... = <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ ... <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> (44) <lb/>Here vac <lb/> ρ <lb/> is understood as the quantity calculated for <lb/> IR <lb/>Univ <lb/> l l <lb/>R <lb/> Λ <lb/> = = <lb/> and  IR <lb/> α  corresponds to  IR <lb/> l  . <lb/>But as shown previously, if the holographic principle is <lb/>valid, this expansion has a more exact form <lb/> 2 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/> t <lb/>a t a <lb/>t <lb/> ρ <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/> &lt; <lb/>&gt; <lb/>= <lb/>+ <lb/>+ ... <lb/> (45) <lb/>and 1 0 <lb/> a ≠ . <lb/> 5. Gravitational Thermodynamics in <lb/>Low and High Energy and Deformed <lb/>Quantum Theory <lb/> In the last decade a number of very interesting works have <lb/>been published. We can primary name the works[61–70], <lb/>where gravitation, at least for the в spaces with horizon, is <lb/>directly associated with thermodynamics and the results <lb/>obtained demonstrate a holographic character of gravitation. <lb/>Of the greatest significance is a pioneer work[54]. For black <lb/>holes the association has been first revealed in[71,72], where <lb/>related the black-hole event horizon temperature to the sur-<lb/>face gravitation. In[69], has shown that this relation is not <lb/>accidental and may be generalized for the spaces with hori-<lb/>zon. As all the foregoing results have been obtained in a <lb/>semiclassical approximation, i.e. for sufficiently low ener-<lb/>gies, the problem arises: how these results are modified when <lb/>going to higher energies. In the context of this paper, the <lb/>problem may be stated as follows: since we have some infra-<lb/>red (IR) cutoff  max <lb/> l <lb/> and ultraviolet (UV) cutoff  min <lb/> l  , we <lb/>naturally have a problem how the above-mentioned results <lb/>on Gravitational Thermodynamics are changed for <lb/> min <lb/> l l <lb/> → <lb/> (46) <lb/>Sections 2 and 3 of this paper show that the results are <lb/>dependent on the deformation parameter  α  (33), (10) that <lb/>in the accepted notation is of the form <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 <lb/> min <lb/> l <lb/>l <lb/> α = <lb/> (47) <lb/>In fact, in several papers[73–80] it has been demonstrated <lb/>that thermodynamics and statistical mechanics of black holes <lb/>in the presence of GUP (i.e. at high energies) should be <lb/>modified. To illustrate, in[78] the Hawking temperature <lb/>modification has been computed in the asymptotically flat <lb/>space in this case in particular. It is easily seen that in this <lb/>case the deformation parameter  α  arises naturally. Indeed, <lb/>modification of the Hawking temperature is of the following <lb/></body>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A.E.Shalyt-Margolin: Quantum Theory at Planck Scale, Dynamical Cosmological Term and Deformed Gravity <lb/></note>

			<body> form[73,75,78]: <lb/> 2 2 <lb/>1 2 <lb/>2 2 <lb/>2 <lb/> 4 <lb/>3 <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>[1 (1 <lb/>) ] <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/> p <lb/> GUP <lb/>p <lb/> l <lb/>r <lb/>d <lb/>T <lb/>l <lb/>r <lb/> α <lb/> π <lb/>α <lb/> ′ <lb/>/ <lb/>+ <lb/>′ <lb/>+ <lb/> − <lb/>= <lb/>− − <lb/>  <lb/> (48) <lb/>where  d  is the space-time dimension, and  r  +  is the un-<lb/>certainty in the emitted particle position by the Hawking <lb/>effect, expressed as <lb/> i <lb/> x r  + <lb/> ∆ ≈ <lb/> (49) <lb/>and being nothing else but a radius of the event horizon; <lb/> α <lb/> ′ <lb/> – dimensionless constant from GUP. But as we have <lb/> 2  p min <lb/> l l <lb/> α <lb/> ′ <lb/> = <lb/> , in terms of  α  (48) may be written in a natural <lb/>way as follows: <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 2 <lb/> 3 <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>[1 (1 <lb/>) ] <lb/>4 <lb/> r <lb/>GUP <lb/>r <lb/>p <lb/> d <lb/>T <lb/>l <lb/> α <lb/>α <lb/>π α <lb/> + <lb/>+ <lb/> − <lb/>/ <lb/>′ <lb/> − <lb/>= <lb/>− − <lb/>  <lb/> (50) <lb/>where  r <lb/> α +  -parameter  α  associated with the IR-cutoff <lb/> r  +  . In such a manner  GUP <lb/> T <lb/> is only dependent on the con-<lb/>stants including the fundamental ones and on the deforma-<lb/>tion parameter  α  . <lb/>The dependence of the black hole entropy on  α  may be <lb/>derived in a similar way. For a semiclassical approximation <lb/>of the Bekenstein-Hawking formula[71,72] <lb/> 2 <lb/> 1 <lb/>4  p <lb/> A <lb/>S <lb/>l <lb/> = <lb/> (51) <lb/>where  A  – surface area of the event horizon, provided the <lb/>horizon event has radius  r  +  , then <lb/> 2 <lb/> A r  + <lb/>  <lb/> and (51) is clearly <lb/>of the form <lb/> 1 <lb/> r <lb/> S  σα + <lb/> − <lb/> = <lb/> (52) <lb/>where  σ  is some dimensionless denumerable factor. The <lb/>general formula for quantum corrections[77] given as <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/> ln <lb/>const <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/> n <lb/>GUP <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/> A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>S <lb/>c <lb/>l <lb/>l <lb/>l <lb/> πα <lb/> − <lb/>′ <lb/>∞ <lb/>= <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>= <lb/>− <lb/>+ + <lb/>+ <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> ∑ <lb/> (53) <lb/>where the expansion coefficients <lb/> 2( 1) <lb/> n <lb/>n <lb/> c  α <lb/> ′ <lb/>+ <lb/> ∝ <lb/> can always <lb/>be computed to any desired order of accuracy[77], may be <lb/>also written as a power series in <lb/> 1 <lb/> r <lb/> α + <lb/> − <lb/> (or Laurent series in <lb/> r <lb/> α +  ) <lb/> 2 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/> ln( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>const <lb/>4 <lb/> n <lb/>n <lb/>GUP <lb/>r <lb/>r <lb/>n <lb/>r <lb/>n <lb/> S <lb/>c <lb/> πα <lb/>σα <lb/>σα <lb/>σ α <lb/> + <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/> ′ <lb/>∞ <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/> = − <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/> ∑ <lb/> (54) <lb/>Note that here no consideration is given to the restrictions <lb/>on the IR-cutoff <lb/> max <lb/> l l <lb/> ≤ <lb/> (55) <lb/>and to those corresponding the extended uncertainty <lb/>principle (EUP)[78] or symmetric generalized uncertainty <lb/>principle (SGUP)[79] that leads to a minimal momentum. <lb/>A black hole is a specific example of the space with ho-<lb/>rizon. It is clear that for other horizon spaces[69] a similar <lb/>relationship between their thermodynamics and the defor-<lb/>mation parameter  α  should be exhibited. <lb/>Quite recently, in a series of papers, and specifically <lb/>in[61–67], it has been shown that Einstein equations may be <lb/>derived from the surface term of the GR Lagrangian, in fact <lb/>containing the same information as the bulk term. <lb/>It should be noted that Einstein&apos;s equations[at least for <lb/>space with horizon] may be obtained from the proportional-<lb/>ity of the entropy and horizon area together with the fun-<lb/>damental thermodynamic relation connecting heat, entropy, <lb/>and temperature[54]. In fact[61–68], this approach has been <lb/>extended and complemented by the demonstration of holo-<lb/>graphicity for the gravitational action (see also[69]).And in <lb/>the case of Einstein-Hilbert gravity, it is possible to interpret <lb/>Einstein&apos;s equations as the thermodynamic identity[70]: <lb/> TdS dE PdV <lb/> = <lb/>+ <lb/> (56) <lb/>The above-mentioned results have been obtained at low <lb/>energies, i.e. in a semiclassical approximation. Because of <lb/>this, the problem arises how these results are changed in the <lb/>case of high energies? Or more precisely, how the results <lb/>of[54,61–70] are generalized in the UV-limit? It is obvious <lb/>that, as in this case all the thermodynamic characteristics <lb/>become dependent on the deformation parameter  α  , all the <lb/>corresponding results should be modified (deformed) to meet <lb/>the following requirements: <lb/>(a) to be clearly dependent on the deformation parameter <lb/> α  at high energies; <lb/>(b) to be duplicated, with high precision, at low energies <lb/>due to the suitable limiting transition. <lb/>The problem may be more specific. As, according to[54, <lb/>69,70] and some other works, gravitation is greatly deter-<lb/>mined by thermodynamics, and at high energies the latter is a <lb/>&quot;deformation of the classical thermodynamics&quot;. Here &quot;high-<lb/>energy deformation of thermodynamics&quot; is understood as <lb/>some (meanwhile unknown) deformation of thermodynam-<lb/>ics in high energies. This theory is still unframed, though <lb/>several of its elements  GUP GUP <lb/> T <lb/>S <lb/> , <lb/> and the like[73–80] are <lb/>known already. It is interesting whether gravitation at high <lb/>energies (or what is the same, quantum gravity or Planck <lb/>scale) is being determined by the corresponding deformed <lb/>thermodynamics. The formulae (50) and (54) are elements of <lb/>the high-energy  α  -deformation in thermodynamics, a gen-<lb/>eral pattern of which still remains to be formed. Obviously, <lb/>these formulae should be involved in the general pattern <lb/>giving better insight into the quantum gravity, as they are <lb/>applicable to black mini-holes (Planck black holes) which <lb/>may be a significant element of such a pattern. But what <lb/>about other elements of this pattern? How can we generalize <lb/>the results[54,69,70]when the IR-cutoff tends to the UV-<lb/>cutoff (formula (46))? What are modifications of the ther-<lb/>modynamic identity (56) in a high-energy deformed ther-<lb/>modynamics and how is it applied in high-energy (quantum) <lb/>gravity? <lb/>By authors opinion, the methods developed to solve the <lb/>problem of point (c) and elucidation of other above-men-<lb/>tioned problems may form the basis for a new approach to <lb/>solution of the quantum gravity problem. And one of the <lb/>keys to the quantum gravity problem is a better insight into <lb/>the high-energy thermodynamics. <lb/> 6.  α  –Representation of Einstein&apos;s <lb/>Equations <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> International Journal of Theoretical and Mathematical Physics 2011; 1(1): 1-11 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body> Let us consider  α  -representation and high energy  α <lb/> -deformation of the Einstein&apos;s field equations for the specific <lb/>cases of horizon spaces (the point (c) of Section 4). In so <lb/>doing the results of the survey work[81] are used. Then, <lb/>specifically, for a static, spherically symmetric horizon in <lb/>space-time described by the metric <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/> ( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/> ds <lb/> f r c dt f r dr r d <lb/> − <lb/> = − <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>Ω <lb/> (57) <lb/>the horizon location will be given by simple zero of the <lb/>function ( ) <lb/> f r  , at  r a <lb/> =  . <lb/>It is known that for horizon spaces one can introduce the <lb/>temperature that can be identified with an analytic con-<lb/>tinuation to imaginary time. In the case under consideration <lb/>([81], eq.(116)) <lb/> ( ) <lb/>4 <lb/> B <lb/> cf a <lb/>k T <lb/> π <lb/> ′ <lb/>= <lb/>  <lb/> (58) <lb/>Therewith, the condition ( ) 0 <lb/> f a =  and ( ) 0 <lb/> f a <lb/> ′ ≠  must be <lb/>fulfilled. <lb/>Then at the horizon  r a <lb/> =  Einstein&apos;s field equations <lb/> 4 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>( ) <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/> c <lb/>f a a <lb/>Pa <lb/>G <lb/> π <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/>′ <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> (59) <lb/>may be written as the thermodynamic identity (56)([81] <lb/>formula (119)) <lb/> 3 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/> ( ) <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/> B <lb/> cf a c <lb/>c da <lb/>d <lb/>a <lb/>Pd <lb/>a <lb/>G <lb/>G <lb/>k T <lb/>dE <lb/>dS <lb/>P dV <lb/> π <lb/>π <lb/>π <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> ′ <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/>− <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/>   <lb/>   <lb/>   <lb/> <lb/> (60) <lb/>where <lb/> r <lb/>r <lb/> P T <lb/> = <lb/> is the trace of the momentum-energy ten-<lb/>sor and radial pressure. In the last equation  da  arises in the <lb/>infinitesimal consideration of Einstein&apos;s equations when <lb/>studying two horizons distinguished by this infinitesimal <lb/>quantity  a  and  a da <lb/> + <lb/> ([81] formula (118)). <lb/>Now we consider (60) in new notation expressing  a  in <lb/>terms of the corresponding deformation parameter  α  . Then <lb/>we have <lb/> 1 2 <lb/> min <lb/> a l  α <lb/> − / <lb/> = <lb/> (61) <lb/>Therefore, <lb/> 1 <lb/>3 2 <lb/> ( ) <lb/>2 <lb/>( ) <lb/> min <lb/> f a <lb/>l <lb/>f <lb/> α <lb/>α <lb/> − <lb/>/ <lb/> ′ <lb/>′ <lb/>= − <lb/> (62) <lb/>Substituting this into (59) or into (60), we obtain in the <lb/>considered case of Einstein&apos;s equations in the &quot;  α  -repre-<lb/>sentation&quot; the following: <lb/> 4 <lb/>1 2 <lb/> 1 <lb/>( <lb/>( ) <lb/>) 4 <lb/>2 <lb/> min <lb/> c <lb/>f <lb/>P l <lb/>G <lb/> α α <lb/>π α <lb/> − <lb/> ′ <lb/>− <lb/>− = <lb/> (63) <lb/>Multiplying the left-and right-hand sides of the last <lb/>equation by  α  , we get <lb/> 4 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 <lb/>( <lb/>( ) <lb/>) 4 <lb/>2 <lb/> min <lb/> c <lb/>f <lb/>Pl <lb/>G <lb/> α <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/>π <lb/> ′ <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/> (64) <lb/>But since usually  min p <lb/> l <lb/>l <lb/>  <lb/> (that is just the case if the <lb/>Generalized Uncertainty Principle (GUP) is satisfied), we <lb/>have <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/> min <lb/>p <lb/> l <lb/>l G c <lb/> = <lb/>/ <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> . When selecting a system of units, <lb/>where <lb/> 1 <lb/> c <lb/> = = <lb/>  <lb/> , we arrive at  min p <lb/> l <lb/>l <lb/>G <lb/> = √ <lb/>  <lb/> , and then (63) is <lb/>of the form <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 2 <lb/> 1 <lb/>( ) <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/> f <lb/>P G <lb/> α <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/>π ϑ <lb/> ′ <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/> (65) <lb/>where <lb/> min <lb/>p <lb/> l <lb/>l <lb/> ϑ <lb/> = <lb/>/  . L.h.s. of (65) is dependent on  α  . Be-<lb/>cause of this, r.h.s. of (65) must be dependent on  α  as well, <lb/>i. e. <lb/> ( ) <lb/> P P  α <lb/> = <lb/> . <lb/> Analysis of  α  -Representation of Einstein&apos;s Equations <lb/> Now let us get back to (60). In[81] the low-energy case has <lb/>been considered, for which ([81] formula (120)) <lb/> 1 2 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>(4 <lb/>) 4 <lb/>2 <lb/>16 <lb/>4 <lb/> H <lb/>H <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/> A <lb/>A <lb/>c <lb/>c <lb/>S <lb/>a <lb/>E <lb/>a <lb/>G <lb/>G <lb/>l <lb/>l <lb/> π <lb/>π <lb/> / <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>; = <lb/>= <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> (66) <lb/>where  H <lb/> A  is the horizon area. In our notation (66) may be <lb/>rewritten as <lb/> 1 2 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 2 <lb/> 1 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>16 <lb/>2 <lb/> H <lb/> A <lb/>c <lb/>c <lb/>S <lb/>E <lb/>a <lb/>G <lb/>G <lb/>G <lb/> ϑ <lb/>πα <lb/>α <lb/>π <lb/> / <lb/>− <lb/>/ <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/>= <lb/>; = <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>√ <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> (67) <lb/>We proceed to two entirely different cases: low energy <lb/>(LE) case and high energy (HE) case. In our notation these <lb/>are respectively given by <lb/>A) <lb/> 0 <lb/> α →  (LE), B) <lb/> 1 4 <lb/> α → /  (HE), <lb/>C)  α  complies with the familiar scales and energies. <lb/>The case of C) is of no particular importance as it may be <lb/>considered within the scope of the conventional General <lb/>Relativity. <lb/>Indeed, in point A) <lb/> 0 <lb/> α →  is not actually an exact limit as <lb/>a real scale of the Universe (Infrared (IR) -cutoff <lb/> 28 <lb/> 10 <lb/> max <lb/>Univ <lb/> l <lb/>R <lb/>cm <lb/> = <lb/>≈ <lb/> ), and then <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 <lb/>122 <lb/> 10 . <lb/> min <lb/>p <lb/>max <lb/> l l <lb/> α <lb/> − <lb/> / <lb/>≈ <lb/>  <lb/> In this way A) is replaced by A1) <lb/> min <lb/> α α <lb/> → <lb/> . In any case at <lb/>low energies the second term in the left-hand side (65) may <lb/>be neglected in the infrared limit. Consequently, at low en-<lb/>ergies (65) is written as <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 2 <lb/> ( ) 4 ( ) <lb/> f <lb/>P <lb/>G <lb/> α <lb/>α <lb/>π α ϑ <lb/> ′ <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/> (68) <lb/>Solution of the corresponding Einstein equation – finding <lb/>of the function ( ) <lb/>[ ( )] <lb/> f <lb/>f P <lb/> α <lb/>α <lb/> = <lb/> satisfying (68). In this case <lb/>formulae (66) are valid as at low energies a semiclassical <lb/>approximation is true. But from (68) it follows that <lb/> 2 2 <lb/>2 <lb/> ( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>4 <lb/> P <lb/>f <lb/>G <lb/>d <lb/> α <lb/>α <lb/>πϑ <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/> = − <lb/> ∫ <lb/> (69) <lb/>On the contrary, knowing <lb/> ( ) <lb/> f  α  , we can obtain <lb/> ( ) <lb/> r <lb/>r <lb/> P <lb/>T <lb/> α = <lb/>. <lb/> But it is noteworthy that, when studying the infrared <lb/>modified gravity[82-84], we have to make corrections for the <lb/>considerations of point A1). <lb/> 7. Possible High Energy  α  -Deformation <lb/>of General Relativity <lb/> Let us consider the high-energy case B). Here two variants <lb/>are possible. <lb/> I. First variant <lb/> In this case it is assumed that in the high-energy (Ultra-<lb/>violet (UV)) limit the thermodynamic identity (60) (or that is <lb/>the same (56) is retained but now all the quantities involved <lb/>in this identity become  α  -deformed. This means that they <lb/></body>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A.E.Shalyt-Margolin: Quantum Theory at Planck Scale, Dynamical Cosmological Term and Deformed Gravity <lb/></note>

			<body> appear in the  α  -representation with quantum corrections <lb/>and are considered at high values of the parameter  α  , i.e. at <lb/> α  close to 1/4. In particular, the temperature  T  from <lb/>equation (60) is changed by  GUP <lb/> T <lb/> (50), the entropy  S  from <lb/>the same equation given by semiclassical formula (66) is <lb/>changed by  GUP <lb/> S <lb/> (54), and so forth: <lb/> GUP <lb/>GUP <lb/> E <lb/>E <lb/>V <lb/>V <lb/> , <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> Then the high-energy  α  -deformation of equation (60) <lb/>takes the form <lb/> ( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/> B GUP <lb/>GUP <lb/>GUP <lb/>GUP <lb/> k T <lb/>dS <lb/>dE <lb/>P dV <lb/> α <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/> − <lb/>= <lb/> (70) <lb/>Substituting into (70) the corresponding quantities <lb/> ( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) ( ) <lb/> GUP <lb/>GUP <lb/>GUP <lb/>GUP <lb/> T <lb/>S <lb/>E <lb/>V <lb/>P <lb/> α <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/> , <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/> and expanding <lb/>them into a Laurent series in terms of  α  , close to high val-<lb/>ues of  α  , specifically close to <lb/> 1 4 <lb/> α = /  , we can derive a <lb/>solution for the high energy  α  -deformation of general rela-<lb/>tivity (70) as a function of ( ) <lb/> P  α  . As this takes place, pro-<lb/>vided at high energies the generalization of (60) to (70)is <lb/>possible, we can have the high-energy  α  -deformation of the <lb/>metric. Actually, as from (60) it follows that <lb/> 4 <lb/>( ) <lb/>4 <lb/> B <lb/>B <lb/> k <lb/>f a <lb/>T <lb/>k T <lb/>c <lb/> π <lb/>π <lb/> ′ <lb/>= = <lb/>  <lb/> (71) <lb/>(considering that we have assumed <lb/> 1 <lb/> c <lb/> = = <lb/>  <lb/> ), we get <lb/> ( ) 4 <lb/>( ) <lb/> B GUP <lb/>GUP a <lb/>k T <lb/>f <lb/> π <lb/>α <lb/> ′ <lb/>= <lb/> (72) <lb/>L.h.s. of (72) is directly obtained in the  α  -representation. <lb/>This means that, when  f T <lb/> ′   , we have <lb/> GUP <lb/>GUP <lb/> T <lb/>f ′  <lb/> with <lb/>the same factor of proportionality. In this case the function <lb/> GUP <lb/> f <lb/> determining the high-energy  α  -deformation of the <lb/>spherically symmetric metric may be in fact derived by the <lb/>expansion of  GUP <lb/> T  , that is known from (50), into a Laurent <lb/>series in terms of  α  close to high values of  α  (specifically <lb/>close to <lb/> 1 4 <lb/> α = /  ), and by the subsequent integration. <lb/>It might be well to remark on the following. <lb/>7.1 As on going to high energies we use (GUP),  ϑ  from <lb/>equation (65) is expressed in terms of  α <lb/> ′ <lb/> –dimensionless <lb/>constant from GUP (6), (50): <lb/> 2 <lb/> ϑ α <lb/> ′ <lb/> = <lb/>. <lb/> 7.2 Of course, in all the formulae including  p <lb/> l  this <lb/>quantity must be changed by <lb/> 1 2 <lb/> G <lb/> / <lb/> and hence  min <lb/> l <lb/> by <lb/> 1 2 <lb/>1 2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> G <lb/>G <lb/> ϑ <lb/>α <lb/> / <lb/>′ <lb/>/ <lb/> = <lb/>. <lb/> 7.3 As noted in the end of subsection 6.1, and in this case <lb/>also knowing all the high-energy deformed quantities <lb/> ( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/> GUP <lb/>GUP <lb/>GUP <lb/>GUP <lb/> T <lb/>S <lb/>E <lb/>V <lb/> α <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/> , <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/> , we can find ( ) <lb/> P  α  at  α <lb/> close to 1/4. <lb/>7.4 Here it is implicitly understood that the Ultraviolet <lb/>limit of Einstein&apos;s equations is independent of the starting <lb/>horizon space. This assumption is quite reasonable. Because <lb/>of this, we use the well-known formulae for the modification <lb/>of thermodynamics and statistical mechanics of black holes <lb/>in the presence of GUP[73–80] <lb/>7.5 The use of the thermodynamic identity (70) for the <lb/>description of the high energy deformation in General Rela-<lb/>tivity implies that on going to the UV-limit of Einstein&apos;s <lb/>equations for horizon spaces in the thermodynamic repre-<lb/>sentation (consideration) we are trying to remain within the <lb/>scope of equilibrium statistical mechanics[85] (equilibrium <lb/>thermodynamics)[86]. However, such an assumption seems <lb/>to be too strong. But some grounds to think so may be found <lb/>as well. Among other things, of interest is the result from[73] <lb/>that GUP may prevent black holes from their total evapora-<lb/>tion. In this case the Planck&apos;s remnants of black holes will be <lb/>stable, and when they are considered, in some approximation <lb/>the equilibrium thermodynamics should be valid. At the <lb/>same time, by author&apos;s opinion these arguments are rather <lb/>weak to think that the quantum gravitational effects in this <lb/>context have been described only within the scope of equi-<lb/>librium thermodynamics[86]. <lb/> II. Second variant <lb/> According to the remark of .5, it is assumed that the in-<lb/>terpretation of Einstein&apos;s equations as a thermodynamic <lb/>identity (60) is not retained on going to high energies <lb/>(UV–limit), i.e. at <lb/> 1 4 <lb/> α → /  , and the situation is adequately <lb/>described exclusively by non-equilibrium thermodynam-<lb/>ics[86,87]. Naturally, the question arises: which of the addi-<lb/>tional terms introduced in (60) at high energies may be <lb/>leading to such a description? <lb/>In the[30,31] it has been shown that in case the cosmo-<lb/>logical term  Λ  is a dynamic quantity, it is small at low <lb/>energies and may be sufficiently large at high energies. In the <lb/>right-hand side of (65) in the  α  –representation the addi-<lb/>tional term ( ( )) <lb/> G  α <lb/> Λ <lb/> is introduced: <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 2 <lb/> 1 <lb/>( ) <lb/>4 ( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>2 <lb/> f <lb/>P <lb/>G G <lb/> α <lb/>α <lb/>α π α ϑ <lb/>α <lb/> ′ <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/>− Λ <lb/> (73) <lb/>where ( ) <lb/> α <lb/> Λ <lb/> is the cosmological term depending from  α  . <lb/>Then its inclusion in the low-energy case (59)(or in the  α  -<lb/>representation (65)) has actually no effect on the thermo-<lb/>dynamic identity (60) validity, and consideration within the <lb/>scope of equilibrium thermodynamics still holds true. It is <lb/>well known that this is not the case at high energies as the  Λ <lb/> -term may contribute significantly to make the &quot;process&quot; <lb/>non-equilibrium in the end[86,87]. <lb/>Is this the only cause for violation of the thermodynamic <lb/>identity (60) as an interpretation of the high-energy gener-<lb/>alization of Einstein&apos;s equations? Further investigations are <lb/>required to answer this question. <lb/> 8. Conclusions <lb/> Thus, this work presents an analysis of the dark energy <lb/>problem on the assumption that it is the time-varying vac-<lb/>uum energy, that conforms to the dynamic cosmological <lb/>term ( ) <lb/> t <lb/> Λ  . Note that the question of the explicit relationship <lb/>between  Λ  and  t  is not touched, we have rather studied <lb/>the problem of deriving the currently observable value for <lb/> observ <lb/> Λ = Λ <lb/> . <lb/>As such a consideration inevitably involves the physics of <lb/>the early Universe (Planck scales) and hence QFT with the <lb/>fundamental length (on the order of Planck&apos;s  p <lb/> l  ), it is asso-<lb/>ciated with new parameters (deformation parameters) and, in <lb/>the limiting transition to low-energy, QFT with the funda-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> International Journal of Theoretical and Mathematical Physics 2011; 1(1): 1-11 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body> mental length turns to well-known QFT (without cutoff). By <lb/>the author&apos;s opinion,  α  (7) is the most optimal of the de-<lb/>formation parameters from the standpoint of the problems <lb/>considered in this work. <lb/>The results obtained in Sections 6 and 7 enable framing of <lb/>the following hypothesis: <lb/>a dynamic cosmological term is a measure of deviation <lb/>from the thermodynamic identity (the first law of thermo-<lb/>dynamics) of the high-energy (Planck&apos;s) deformation of <lb/>Einstein equations for horizon spaces in their thermody-<lb/>namic interpretation. <lb/>The dynamic cosmological term correlates well with in-<lb/>flation models[4] as the latter require a very high  Λ  at the <lb/>early stages of the Universe, and this is distinct from <lb/> exper <lb/> Λ = Λ <lb/> in the modern period. Of great interest is the re-<lb/>cent work[89], where a mechanism of the vacuum energy <lb/>decay in the de Sitter space is established to support a dy-<lb/>namic nature of  Λ  . <lb/>This work is a step to the incorporation of deformation <lb/>parameters involved in a quantum field theory at Planck&apos;s <lb/>scales into the high-energy deformation of the General <lb/>Relativity (GR). The corresponding calculations with the <lb/>adequate interpretation must follow next. It is interesting to <lb/>consider the high energy  α  -deformation of GR in a more <lb/>general case. The problem is how far a thermodynamic in-<lb/>terpretation of Einstein&apos;s equations may be extended? We <lb/>should remember that, as all the deformations considered <lb/>involve a minimal length at the Planck level  min p <lb/> l <lb/>l <lb/>   , a <lb/>minimal three-dimensional volume should also be the case <lb/> 3 <lb/> min <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/> V <lb/>V l <lb/> = <lb/>  <lb/> . And this is of particular importance for high <lb/>energy thermodynamics (some indications to this fact have <lb/>been demonstrated in[30,31]). <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> REFERENCES <lb/> [1] Mukohyama, S., Randall, L. A, 2004, Dynamical approach to <lb/>the cosmological constant., Phys.Rev.Lett., 92, 211302.; L.P. <lb/>Chimento and D. Pavon, 1998, Inhomogeneous Universe <lb/>Models with Varying Cosmological Term, Gen. Rel. Grav., <lb/>643--651; S. Carneiro,2003, Decaying Lambda cosmology <lb/>with varying G, arXiv:gr-qc/0307114 <lb/>[2] Aldrovandi, R. Beltran Almeida, J. P., Pereira, J. G., 2005, <lb/>Time-Varying Cosmological Term: Emergence and Fate of a <lb/>FRW Comments., Grav.Cosmol. 11, 277-283 <lb/>[3] Richard T., 2008, Hammond, Terry Pilling, Dark Entropy, <lb/>arXiv: 0806.1277 <lb/>[4] Kolb E., and Turner M., 1990, The Early Universe, Reading, <lb/>Addison Wesley; Baumann D.,2009, TASI Lectures on In-<lb/>flation , arXiv:0907.5424 <lb/>[5] Zel&apos;dovich,Y.B., 1968, Sov.Phys.Uspehi, 11, 381–393 <lb/>[6] Weinberg, S., 1989, the Cosmological Constant Problem. Rev. <lb/>Mod. Phys., 61 , 1–23 <lb/>[7] Klinkhamer F.R., 2007, Fundamental length scale of quantum <lb/>spacetime foam., JETPLett., 86, 2167-2180 <lb/>[8] Amelino-Camelia G. Smolin L., 2009, Prospects for con-<lb/>straining quantum gravity dispersion with near term obser-<lb/>vations., Phys.Rev.D ,80, 084017; Gubitosi G. et al., 2009, A <lb/>Constraint on Planck-scale Modifications to Electrodynamics <lb/>with CMB polarization data., JCAP,0908, 021; Amelino-<lb/>Camelia G., 2005, Building a case for a Planck-scale-de-<lb/>formed boost action: the Planck-scale particle-localization <lb/>limit., Int.J.Mod.Phys. D.,14, 2167-2180 <lb/>[9] Hossenfelder S. et al.,2003, Signatures in the Planck Regime., <lb/>Phys. Lett.B.,575, 85-99; Hossenfelder S., 2004, Running <lb/>coupling with minimal length, Phys.Rev.D., 70, 105003; <lb/>Hossenfelder S., 2006, Self-consistency in theories with a <lb/>minimal length, Class. Quant. Grav.,23, 1815-1821 <lb/>[10] Faddeev, L.,1989, Mathematical View on Evolution of <lb/>Physics., Priroda, 5, 11–18 <lb/>[11] Veneziano,G. A, 1986, Stringy Nature Needs Just Two Con-<lb/>stants.,Europhys. Lett., 2,199–211; Amati, D., Ciafaloni, M., <lb/>Veneziano,G.,1989, Can Space-Time Be Probed Below the <lb/>String Size? Phys.Lett.B, 216,41–47; E.Witten, 1996. Phys. <lb/>Today, 49, 24–28 <lb/>[12] Adler,R.J., and Santiago,D.I., 1999, On gravity and the un-<lb/>certainty principle., Mod. Phys. Lett. A ,14, 1371–1378 <lb/>[13] Scardigli,F.,1999, Generalized uncertainty principle in <lb/>quantum gravity from micro -black hole Gedanken experi-<lb/>ment., Phys. Lett. B., 452, 39–44; Bambi,C. A, 2008, Revi-<lb/>sion of the Generalized Uncertainty Principle., Class. Quant. <lb/>Grav, 25, 105003 <lb/>[14] Garay, L.,1995. Quantum gravity and minimum length. Int.J. <lb/>Mod.Phys.A, 10, 145–166 <lb/>[15] Ahluwalia, D.V., 2000, Wave particle duality at the Planck <lb/>scale: Freezing of neutrino oscillations., Phys.Lett, A., 275, <lb/>31–35; Ahluwalia,D.V., 2002, Interface of gravitational and <lb/>quantum realms., Mod.Phys.Lett., A. 17, 1135–1146 <lb/>[16] Maggiore, M. A., 1993, Generalized uncertainty principle in <lb/>quantum gravity., Phys.Lett, 304, 65–69 <lb/>[17] Maggiore, M.,1993, The Algebraic structure of the genera-<lb/>lized uncertainty principle, Phys.Lett.B, 319, 83–86 <lb/>[18] Kempf,A.; Mangano,G.; Mann,R.B.,1995, Hilbert space <lb/>representation of the minimal length uncertainty relation. <lb/>Phys.Rev.D, 52, 1108–1118 <lb/>[19] Shalyt-Margolin,A.E., and Suarez, J.G.,2003, Quantum <lb/>mechanics of the early universe and its limiting transition. <lb/>gr-qc/0302119, 16pp <lb/>[20] Shalyt-Margolin, A.E. and Suarez, J.G., 2003, Quantum <lb/>mechanics at Planck&apos;s scale and density matrix. Intern. Journ. <lb/>Mod. Phys D. ,12, 1265–1278 <lb/>[21] Shalyt-Margolin, A.E., and Tregubovich, A.Ya., 2004, De-<lb/>formed density matrix and generalized uncertainty relation in <lb/>thermodynamics., Mod. Phys.Lett. A., 19, 71–82 <lb/>[22] Shalyt-Margolin, A.E., 2004, Nonunitary and unitary transi-<lb/>tions in generalized quantum mechanics, new small parame-<lb/>ter and information problem solving., Mod. Phys. Lett. A, 19, <lb/>391–404 <lb/>[23] Shalyt-Margolin, A.E., 2004, Pure states, mixed states and <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A.E.Shalyt-Margolin: Quantum Theory at Planck Scale, Dynamical Cosmological Term and Deformed Gravity <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> Hawking problem in generalized quantum mechanics. Mod. <lb/>Phys. Lett. A, 19, 2037–2045 <lb/>[24] Shalyt-Margolin, A.E., 2004, The Universe as a nonuniform <lb/>lattice in finite volume hypercube. I. Fundamental definitions <lb/>and particular features., Intern. Journ. Mod.Phys D, 13, 853– <lb/>864 <lb/>[25] Shalyt-Margolin, A.E., 2005, The Universe as a nonuniform <lb/>lattice in the finite-dimensional hypercube. II. Simple cases of <lb/>symmetry breakdown and restoration. Intern.Journ.Mod. <lb/>Phys.A, 20, 4951–4964 <lb/>[26] Shalyt-Margolin, A.E. and Strazhev, V.I., 2006, The Density <lb/>Matrix Deformation in Quantum and Statistical Mechanics in <lb/>Early Universe., Proc. Sixth International Symposium <lb/>&quot;Frontiers of Fundamental and Computational Physics&quot;, <lb/>edited by B.G. Sidharth at al. Springer, 131–134 <lb/>[27] Shalyt-Margolin, A.E., 2005, The Density matrix deforma-<lb/>tion in physics of the early universe and some of its implica-<lb/>tions., Quantum Cosmology Research Trends,edited by A. <lb/>Reimer, Horizons in World Physics., Nova Science Publish-<lb/>ers, Inc., Hauppauge, 49–91 <lb/>[28] Shalyt-Margolin, A.E., 2006, Deformed density matrix and <lb/>quantum entropy of the black hole. Entropy,8, 31–43 <lb/>[29] Shalyt-Margolin, A.E., 2007, Entropy in the Present and <lb/>Early Universe, Symmetry, 18, 299–320 <lb/>[30] Shalyt-Margolin, A.E., 2010, Entropy in the Present and <lb/>Early Universe and Vacuum Energy, AIP Conference Pro-<lb/>ceedings, 1205, 160–167 <lb/>[31] Shalyt-Margolin, A.E.,2010, Entropy In The Present And <lb/>Early Universe: New Small Parameters And Dark Energy <lb/>Problem, Entropy ,12, 932-952 <lb/>[32] Sciama, D.W., 1984, Proc. R.Soc.Lond. A 394, 1—23; <lb/>Bowyer S., KorpelaE.J., Edelstein J., Lampton M., Morales <lb/>C., Perez-Mercader J., Gomez J.F., Trapero J., 1999, ApJ 526, <lb/>10--31, Turner, M.S., 1991, Phys. scr.,36, 167--179 <lb/>[33] Perlmutter, S. et al., 1999, Measurements of Omega and <lb/>Lambda from 42 high redshift supernovae., Astrophys. J ,517, <lb/>565–586; Riess A. G. et al.,1998, Observational evidence <lb/>from supernovae for an accelerating universe and a cosmo-<lb/>logical constant., Astron. J. ,116, 1009–1038; Riess A. G. et <lb/>al., 1999, BV RI light curves for 22 type Ia supernovae. As-<lb/>tron. J ,117, 707–724 <lb/>[34] Dan Hooper, 2009, TASI 2008 Lectures on Dark Matter, <lb/>ArXiv: 0901.4090 <lb/>[35] Ratra,B. and Peebles,J.,1988,Cosmological Consequences of <lb/>a Rolling Homogeneous Scalar Field., Phys. Rev. D,37, <lb/>3406–3422; Caldwell,R. R., Dave, R. and Steinhardt, P. J. <lb/>Cosmological imprint of an energy component with general <lb/>equation of state., 1998, Phys. Rev. Lett , 80, 1582–1585 <lb/>[36] Armendariz-Picaon, C., Damour,T.V., Mukhanov, V., 1999, <lb/>k -inflation., Phys. Lett. B, 458, 209–218; J. Garriga, and V. <lb/>Mukhanov, Perturbations in k-inflation., Phys. Lett. B,458, <lb/>219–225 <lb/>[37] Padmanabhan, T., 2002, Accelerated expansion of the un-<lb/>iverse driven by tachyonic matter. Phys. Rev. D,66, 021301; <lb/>Bagla, J. S. Jassal,H. K., Padmanabhan, T.,2003, Cosmology <lb/>with tachyon field as dark energy., Phys. Rev. D, 67,063504; <lb/>Abramo, L. R. W., and Finelli,F.,2003, Cosmological dy-<lb/>namics of the tachyon with an inverse power-law potential., <lb/>Phys. Lett. B , 575, 165–171 <lb/>[38] Sahni, V. and Shtanov, Y., 2003, Brane world models of dark <lb/>energy., JCAP,0311, 014--027; Elizalde, E., Nojiri, S., <lb/>Odintsov, S. D.,2004, Late-time cosmology in (phantom) <lb/>scalar-tensor theory: Dark energy and the cosmic speed-up. <lb/>Phys. Rev. D ,70, 043539 <lb/>[39] Gliner, E. B.,1965, Algebraic Properties of Energy-Mo-<lb/>mentum Tensor and vacuum-like state of the matter, ZHETF, <lb/>49, 542–549 <lb/>[40] Wald, Robert. M., 1984, General Relativity. The University <lb/>Chicago Press., Chicago and London 1984, 491 p.p <lb/>[41] Chakraborty, W.,2011, Acceleration Expantion of the Un-<lb/>iverse, ArXiv: 1105.1087 <lb/>[42] Kim,Yong-Wan, Lee,Hyung Won, Myung, Yun Soo,2009, <lb/>Entropy bound of local quantum field theory with generalized <lb/>uncertainty principle., Phys.Lett.B, 673,293-296 <lb/>[43] O&apos;Connell, R. F. ,2007, Phys.Lett.A, 366:177-178 <lb/>[44] Jejjala, V., Kavic, M., Minic, D., 2007, Time and M-theory. <lb/>Int. J. Mod. Phys. A ,22, 3317–3405 <lb/>[45] Jejjala, V., Kavic, M., Minic, D.,2007, Fine structure of dark <lb/>energy and new physics., Adv. High Energy Phys, 2007, <lb/>21586 <lb/>[46] Jejjala, V. and Minic, D.,2007, Why there is something so <lb/>close to nothing: Towards a fundamental theory of the cos-<lb/>mological constant., Int.J.Mod.Phys.A ,22, 1797-1818 <lb/>[47] Jejjala, V., Minic, D.,Tze, C-H., 2004, Toward a background <lb/>independent quantum theory of gravity. Int. J. Mod. Phys. D, <lb/>13, 2307–2314 <lb/>[48] Padmanabhan, T., 2005, Darker side of the universe. and the <lb/>crying need for some bright ideas! Proceedings of the 29th <lb/>International Cosmic Ray Conference, Pune, India, 47–62. <lb/>[49] Padmanabhan, T., 2006, Dark Energy: Mystery of the Mil-<lb/>lennium. Paris 2005, Albert Einstein&apos;s century, AIP Confe-<lb/>rence Proceedings 861, American Institute of Physics, New <lb/>York, 858–866 <lb/>[50] Hooft, G. &apos;T.,1993, Dimensional reduction in quantum grav-<lb/>ity.Essay dedicated to Abdus Salam gr-qc/9310026, 15pp <lb/>[51] Hooft, G. &apos;T., 2000, The Holographic Principle, hep-th/ <lb/>0003004, 15pp.; L.Susskind, 1995, The World as a hologram. <lb/>J. Math. Phys, 36, 6377–6396 <lb/>[52] Bousso, R. The Holographic principle, 2002, Rev. Mod. Phys , <lb/>74, 825–874 <lb/>[53] Bousso, R. A, 1999, Covariant entropy conjecture. JHEP ,007, <lb/>004--021 <lb/>[54] Jacobson, T.,1995, Thermodynamics of space-time: The <lb/>Einstein equation of state, Phys. Rev. Lett ,75, 1260–1263 <lb/>[55] Balazs,C. and Szapudi,I.,2006, Naturalness of the vacuum <lb/>energy in holographic theories., hep-th/0603133, 4pp <lb/>[56] Fischler,W. and Susskind, L.,1998, Holography and cos-<lb/>mology. hep-th/9806039, 7pp <lb/>[57] Cohen,A., Kaplan, D., Nelson, A.,1999, Effective field theory, <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> International Journal of Theoretical and Mathematical Physics 2011; 1(1): 1-11 <lb/></note>

			<page> 11 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> black holes, and the cosmological constant., Phys. Rev. <lb/>Lett ,82, 4971–4974 <lb/>[58] Myung,Y.S., 2005,Holographic principle and dark energy. <lb/>Phys. Lett. B,610, 18–22 <lb/>[59] Myung, Y. S. and Min-Gyun Seo, 2009, Origin of holo-<lb/>graphic dark energy models., Phys. Lett. B,617, 435–439 <lb/>[60] Sergio del Campo, Júlio.C. Fabris, Ramón Herrera, Winfried <lb/>Zimdahl,2011, On holographic dark-energy models, Phys. <lb/>Rev.D, 83, 123006 <lb/>[61] Padmanabhan, T.,2005, A New perspective on gravity and <lb/>the dynamics of spacetime. Int.Jorn.Mod.Phys. D, 14, 2263– <lb/>2270 <lb/>[62] Padmanabhan, T., 2002, The Holography of gravity encoded <lb/>in a relation between entropy, horizon area and action for <lb/>gravity., Gen.Rel.Grav , 34, 2029–2035 <lb/>[63] Padmanabhan,T.,2005, Holographic Gravity and the Surface <lb/>term in the Einstein-Hilbert Action., Braz.J.Phys, 35, <lb/>362–372 <lb/>[64] Padmanabhan, T., 2006, Gravity: A New holographic pers-<lb/>pective. Int.J.Mod.Phys.D, 15, 1659–1676 <lb/>[65] Mukhopadhyay,A. and Padmanabhan,T.,2006, Holography <lb/>of gravitational action functionals, Phys.Rev.D, 74, 124023 <lb/>[66] Padmanabhan, T., 2008, Dark energy and gravity, Gen.Rel. <lb/>Grav, 40, 529–564 <lb/>[67] Padmanabhan,T. and Paranjape,A.,2007, Entropy of null <lb/>surfaces and dynamics of spacetime, Phys.Rev.D.,75, 064004 <lb/>[68] Padmanabhan, T., 2007,Gravity as an emergent phenomenon: <lb/>A conceptual description. International Workshop and at on <lb/>Theoretical High Energy Physics (IWTHEP 2007), AIP <lb/>Conference Proceedings 939, American Institute of Physics, <lb/>New York, 114–123 <lb/>[69] Padmanabhan, T., 2005, Gravity and the thermodynamics of <lb/>horizons, Phys.Rept , 406, 49–125 <lb/>[70] Paranjape, A., Sarkar, S.; Padmanabhan, T.,2006, Thermo-<lb/>dynamic route to field equations in Lancos-Lovelock gravity, <lb/>Phys.Rev. D, 74, 104015 <lb/>[71] Bekenstein, J.D., 1973, Black Holes and Entropy. Phys. Rev. <lb/>D.7, 2333–2345 <lb/>[72] Hawking, S., 1976, Black Holes and Thermodynamics, Phys. <lb/>Rev.D, 13,191–204 <lb/>[73] Adler, R. J., Chen,P., Santiago, D. I.,2001, The generalized <lb/>uncertainty principle and black hole remnants, Gen.Rel. <lb/>Grav., 13, 2101-2108 <lb/>[74] Custodio, P. S. and Horvath, J. E.,2003, The Generalized <lb/>uncertainty principle, entropy bounds and black hole <lb/>(non)evaporation in a thermal bath, Class.Quant.Grav.,20, <lb/>L197-L203 <lb/>[75] Cavaglia, M. and Das, S., 2004, How classical are TeV scale <lb/>black holes? Class.Quant.Grav., 21, 4511–4523 <lb/>[76] Bolen, B., and Cavaglia,M., 2005,(Anti-)de Sitter black hole <lb/>thermodynamics and the generalized uncertainty principle., <lb/>Gen.Rel.Grav.,37, 1255–1263 <lb/>[77] Medved, A.J.M. and Vagenas, E.C., 2004, When conceptual <lb/>worlds collide: The GUP and the BH entropy. Phys. Rev. <lb/>D ,70, 124021 <lb/>[78] Park, M.-I.,2008, The Generalized Uncertainty Principle in <lb/>(A)dS Space and the Modification of Hawking Temperature <lb/>from the Minimal Length., Phys.Lett.B , 659, 698–702 <lb/>[79] Kim,Wontae. and Son,Edwin J., 2008, Yoon, Myungseok. <lb/>Thermodynamics of a black hole based on a generalized un-<lb/>certainty principle. JHEP,08, 035--043 <lb/>[80] Nouicer,K,2007,Quantum-corrected black hole thermody-<lb/>namics to all orders in the Planck length , Phys.Lett B,647, <lb/>63--71 <lb/>[81] Padmanabhan,T.,2010, Thermodynamical Aspects of Gravity: <lb/>New insights.Rep. Prog. Phys. 73, 046901 <lb/>[82] Patil, S.P., 009, Degravitation, Inflation and the Cosmologi-<lb/>cal Constant as an Afterglow. JCAP,0901, 017--035 <lb/>[83] Park, Mu-in., 2009, The Black Hole and Cosmological Solu-<lb/>tions in IR modified Horava Gravity. JHEP,0909, 123--142 <lb/>[84] Rubakov, V. A., and Tinyakov,P. G., 2008, Infrared-modified <lb/>gravities and massive gravitons. Phys.Usp, 123., 759-792; <lb/>Nikiforova,V.; Randjbar-Daemi, S.; Rubakov V., 2009, <lb/>Infrared Modified Gravity with Dynamical Torsion. Phys. <lb/>Rev. D , 80, 124050 <lb/>[85] Balesku, R.,1975 Equilibruim and Nonequilibruim Statistical <lb/>Mechanics, v.1, A Wiley Interscience Publications, New <lb/>York-London-Sydney-Toronto <lb/>[86] Bazarov, I.P., 1991, Thermodynamics, Moskow, Press &quot;Hi-<lb/>gher School&quot; <lb/>[87] Gyarmati, I., 1974, Non-Equilibruim Thermodynamics. Field <lb/>Theory and Varitional Principles, Springer-Verlag, Berlin-<lb/>Heidelberg-New York <lb/>[88] Cai,R.-G, and Kim,S.P, 2005, First law of thermodynamics <lb/>and Friedmann equations of Friedmann-Robertson-Walker <lb/>universe. JHEP, 02, 050 – 067 <lb/>[89] Polyakov, A. M., 2010, Decay of Vacuum Energy. Nucl. Phys. <lb/>B., 834, 316–329. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
