<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Ann. Henri Poincaré 7 (2006), 975–1011 <lb/>c <lb/> 2006 Birkhäuser Verlag Basel/Switzerland <lb/>1424-0637/050975-37, published online 2006-08-08 <lb/>DOI 10.1007/s00023-006-0273-9 <lb/> Annales Henri Poincaré <lb/> Positive Energy-Momentum Theorem for <lb/>AdS-Asymptotically Hyperbolic Manifolds <lb/> Daniel Maerten <lb/> Abstract. The aim of this paper is to prove a positive energy-momentum the-<lb/>orem under the (well known in general relativity) dominant energy condition, <lb/>for AdS-asymptotically hyperbolic manifolds. These manifolds are by defi-<lb/>nition endowed with a Riemannian metric and a symmetric 2-tensor which <lb/>respectively tend to the metric and second fundamental form of a standard <lb/>hyperbolic slice in Anti-de Sitter space-time. There exists a positive mass <lb/>theorem for asymptotically hyperbolic spin Riemannian manifolds (with zero <lb/>extrinsic curvature), and we present an extension of this result for the non <lb/>zero extrinsic curvature case. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. The energy-momentum <lb/> 1.1. Introduction <lb/> This paper proves a positive energy-momentum theorem under the (well known in <lb/>general relativity) dominant energy condition, for AdS-asymptotically hyperbolic <lb/>manifolds. An AdS-asymptotically hyperbolic manifold is by definition a manifold <lb/>(M, g, k) such that at infinity, the Riemannian metric g and the symmetric 2-ten-<lb/>sor k tend respectively to the metric and second fundamental form of a standard <lb/>hyperbolic slice of Anti-de Sitter (AdS). <lb/>Chru´ ciel and Nagy [19] recently defined the notion of energy-momentum of <lb/>an asymptotically hyperbolic manifold, which generalizes the analogous notion in <lb/>the asymptotically flat case. Besides Chru´ ciel and Herzlich [15] recently proved a <lb/>positive mass theorem for asymptotically hyperbolic spin Riemannian manifolds <lb/>(with zero extrinsic curvature). <lb/>The aim of the present paper is to extend this result to the non-zero extrinsic <lb/>curvature case. <lb/> 1.2. Some definitions and notations <lb/> In the whole paper, we consider a spacelike hypersurface M in a (locally defined) <lb/>Lorentzian manifold N . Using geodesic coordinates along M , we shall write a <lb/>neighbourhood of M in N as a subset of ]−, [ × M , endowed with the metric <lb/></body>

			<page> 976 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> D. Maerten <lb/>Ann. Henri Poincaré <lb/></note>

			<body> γ = −dt <lb/> 2  + g  t  . The Riemannian n-manifold M has induced metric g  0  = g and <lb/>second fundamental form k := (− <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>d <lb/>dt  g  t  )  |t=0  . We assume that (M, g, k) is AdS-<lb/>asymptotically hyperbolic that is to say, the metric g and the second fundamental <lb/>form k are asymptotic at infinity to the metric and the second fundamental form <lb/>of a standard hyperbolic slice in AdS. More precisely we adopt the following <lb/> Definition 1.1. (M, g, k) is said to be AdS-asymptotically hyperbolic if there exists <lb/>some compact K, a positive number R and a homeomorphism called a chart at <lb/>infinity M  K −→ R <lb/> n <lb/>  B(0, R) such that in this chart we have <lb/> e := g − b = O(e <lb/> −τr  ), ∂e = O(e <lb/> −τr  ), ∂ <lb/> 2  e = O(e <lb/> −τr  ), <lb/> k = O(e <lb/> −τr  ), <lb/> ∂ k= O(e <lb/> −τr  ), <lb/> for τ &gt; n/2 and where ∂ is taken with respect to the hyperbolic metric b = dr <lb/> 2  + <lb/>sinh <lb/> 2  rg  S  n−1  with g  S  n−1  the standard metric of S <lb/> n−1  . <lb/> The model case is merely the standard embedding of the hyperbolic space (H <lb/> n  , b, 0) <lb/>in AdS space time, which will be denoted by (R <lb/> n+1  , β = −dt <lb/> 2  + b  t  ). <lb/>The motivation for the definition of the energy-momentum comes from the <lb/>study of the constraints map which by definition is <lb/>Φ : M × Γ(S <lb/> 2  T <lb/>  *  M ) −→ <lb/> C <lb/> ∞  (M ) × Γ(T <lb/>  *  M ) <lb/>(h, p) <lb/> −→ <lb/> Scal <lb/> h  +(tr  h  p) <lb/> 2 <lb/> − |p| <lb/> 2 <lb/> h <lb/> 2 (δ  h  p + dtr  h  p) <lb/> , <lb/> where M is the set of Riemannian metrics on the manifold M . Let us denote <lb/>by ( ˙ <lb/> h, ˙ <lb/> p) an infinitesimal deformation of (h, p). Now if we take a couple (f, α) ∈ <lb/> C <lb/> ∞  (M ) × Γ(T <lb/>  *  M ) then we compute <lb/> (f, α), (Φ(h + ˙ <lb/> h, p + ˙ <lb/> p) − Φ(h, p)) <lb/> = δ(f (δ ˙ <lb/> h + dtr ˙ <lb/> h) + i  ∇f  ˙ <lb/> h − (tr ˙ <lb/> h)df + 2i  α  ˙ <lb/> p − 2(tr ˙ <lb/> p)α) <lb/> + δ(&lt;p, ˙ <lb/> h&gt;α + &lt;h, ˙ <lb/> h&gt;i  α  p − 2i  iαp  ˙ <lb/> h) <lb/> + <lb/> dΦ <lb/>  * <lb/> (h,p)  (f, α), ( ˙ <lb/> h, ˙ <lb/> p) <lb/> + Q(f, α, h, p, ˙ <lb/> h, ˙ <lb/> p), <lb/> where &lt; , &gt; is the metric extended to all tensors, δ is the h-divergence operator, <lb/>dΦ <lb/>  * <lb/> (h,p)  is the formal adjoint of the linearized constraints map at the point (h, p), <lb/> traces are taken with respect to h and Q(f, α, h, p, ˙ <lb/> h, ˙ <lb/> p) is a remainder which is <lb/>linear with respect to (f, α) and at least quadratic with respect to ( ˙ <lb/> h, ˙ <lb/> p). Now <lb/>considering the constraints map along the hyperbolic space embedded in AdS, <lb/>that is to say (h, p) = (b, 0) and ( ˙ <lb/> h, ˙ <lb/> p) = (g − b = e, k) one finds <lb/> (f, α), (Φ(g, k) − Φ(b, 0)) = δ(f (δe + dtr e) + i  ∇f  e − (tr e)df + 2i  α  k − 2(tr k)α) <lb/> + <lb/> dΦ <lb/>  * <lb/> (b,0)  (f, α), (e, k) <lb/> + Q(f, α, b, k, e). <lb/> As a consequence if we assume that (M, g, k) is AdS-asymptotically hyperbolic <lb/>and if the function (f, α), (Φ(g, k) − Φ(b, 0)) is integrable on M with respect to <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vol. 7 (2006) <lb/>Positive Energy Theorem <lb/></note>

			<page> 977 <lb/></page>

			<body> the measure dVol  b  , then the energy-momentum H can be defined as a linear form <lb/>on Ker dΦ <lb/>  * <lb/> (b,0) <lb/> H : (f, α) −→ lim <lb/> r→∞ <lb/> Sr(b) <lb/> −f (δ  b  e + dtr  b  e) − i  ∇  b  f  e + (tr  b  e)df − 2i  α   k + 2(tr  b  k)α. <lb/> The integrand in the formula of H is in index notation <lb/> f (e <lb/> i <lb/>j,i  − e <lb/> i <lb/>i,j  ) − f <lb/> ,i  e  ij  + (e <lb/> i <lb/>i  )f  ,j  − 2α <lb/> i  k  ij  + 2(k <lb/> i <lb/>i  )α  j  , <lb/> where &quot; , &quot; stands for the b-derivatives and where h <lb/> i  = b <lb/> ij  h  j  for any tensor h. This <lb/>integrand is the same as the one of Chru´ ciel and Nagy [19] since each Killing <lb/>vector fields on AdS is decomposable into the sum of some normal and tangential <lb/>components (with respect to a standard hyperbolic slice) which are in our case <lb/>given by the couple (f, α) (see also [22]). More precisely, one can show, using <lb/>Moncrief argument [26], that Ker dΦ <lb/>  * <lb/> (b,0) <lb/> ∼ = Kill(AdS) where Kill(AdS) denotes the <lb/>Lie algebra of Killing vector fields on AdS, since it satisfies the Einstein equations <lb/>with a (negative) cosmological constant. The isometry group of AdS is O(n, 2), and <lb/>thereby Kill(AdS) ∼ = so(n, 2) ∼ = N  b  ⊕ so(n, 1) ∼ = N  b  ⊕ Kill(H <lb/> n  ), where we have set <lb/> N  b  = {f ∈ C <lb/> ∞  (M ) | Hess f = fb}. It is well known [19], [15] that the application <lb/> R <lb/> n,1 <lb/> −→ N  b <lb/> y  k  −→ x  k  := y  k|H  n  , <lb/> (where (y  k  ) <lb/> n <lb/>k=0  are the standard coordinates) is an isometry, and the mass part <lb/>of the energy-momentum is a linear form on N  b  which is causal and positively <lb/>oriented as soon as Scal <lb/> g <lb/> ≥ −n(n − 1) = Scal <lb/> b  . Remark that the sharpest in-<lb/>tegrability conditions in order to make H well defined and invariant under as-<lb/>ymptotic isometries have been found by Chru´ ciel and Nagy still in [19]. How-<lb/>ever for the sake of simplicity one can use instead of the integrability condition <lb/> (f, α), (Φ(g, k) − Φ(b, 0)) ∈ L <lb/> 1  (M, dVol  b  ), the less general but more convenient <lb/>condition |Φ(g, k) − Φ(b, 0)| e <lb/> r <lb/> ∈ L <lb/> 1  (M, dVol  b  ). <lb/> Remark 1.2. In the asymptotically flat situation, the energy-momentum is also a <lb/>linear form on R <lb/> n,1 <lb/> ⊕ so(n, 1) where the first component corresponds to transla-<lb/>tional isometries (if a normal vector to the hypersurface is given, the normal com-<lb/>ponent in the R <lb/> n,1  part is nothing but the mass) and the second one to rotations. <lb/>This interpretation gave rise to the respective terminology of linear and angular <lb/>momentum. In the AdS-asymptotically hyperbolic situation, one cannot identify <lb/>some linear momentum in the decomposition so(n, 2) ∼ = R <lb/> n,1 <lb/> ⊕ so(n, 1), since the <lb/>first component R <lb/> n,1  in so(n, 2) is not of translational nature. This whole first com-<lb/>ponent of the energy is then called the mass functional and it only remains some <lb/> angular momentum. Moreover physicists often call the limit of integrals H(f, α) <lb/> global charges and so the positive energy-momentum theorem could be consequently <lb/>renamed global inequalities theorem. Some supplementary details on the physical <lb/>interpretation of our result can be found in the forthcoming note by Chru´ ciel and <lb/>the author [17]. <lb/></body>

			<page> 978 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> D. Maerten <lb/>Ann. Henri Poincaré <lb/></note>

			<body> 1.3. Statement of the theorems and comments <lb/> As we have seen, given a chart at infinity, H can be considered as a vector of <lb/> R <lb/> n,1 <lb/> ⊕ so(n, 1) and will be denoted by M ⊕ Ξ. The vector M is the mass part [15] <lb/>of H, and Ξ is the angular momentum. We will prove the existence of a Hermitian <lb/>quadratic application <lb/> Q : C <lb/> d <lb/> K  / / R <lb/> n,1 <lb/> ⊕ so(n, 1) <lb/> H  / / R , <lb/> which is nonetheless quite difficult to explicit in general. <lb/>We will also treat the case where the slice M has a compact inner bound-<lb/>ary ∂M whose induced metric and second fundamental form are respectively de-<lb/>noted by ˘ <lb/> g and ˘ <lb/> k. To this end, we have to define the vector field k := (− tr ˘ <lb/> k + <lb/>(n − 1))e  0  + k(ν) along the boundary ∂M . We can now state the first main result <lb/>of this paper. <lb/> Theorem 1.3 (Positive energy-momentum). Let (M <lb/> n  , g, k) be an AdS-asymptoti-<lb/>cally hyperbolic spin Riemannian manifold satisfying the decay conditions stated <lb/>in Section 1.2 and the following conditions <lb/> (i) (f, α), (Φ(g, k) − Φ(b, 0)) ∈ L <lb/> 1  (M, dVol  b  ) for every (f, α) ∈ N  b  ⊕ Kill(M, b), <lb/> (ii) the relative version of the dominant energy condition (cf. Section 2.2) holds, <lb/>that is to say (Φ(g, k) − Φ(b, 0)) is a positively oriented causal (n + 1)-vector <lb/> along M , <lb/> (iii) in the case where M has a compact boundary ∂M , we assume moreover that <lb/> k is causal and positively oriented along ∂M . <lb/>Then there exists a (hardly explicitable) map R <lb/> n,1 <lb/> ⊕ so(n, 1) −→ Herm(C <lb/> d  ) which <lb/>sends, under the assumptions (i)–(iii), the energy-momentum on a non-negative <lb/>Hermitian quadratic form Q. <lb/> Moreover, in dimension n = 3, we can be more specific giving the explicit <lb/>formula of Q in terms of the components M ∈ M ⊂ M(2, C) (cf. Section 2.4 for <lb/>the definition of M) and Ξ ∈ sl(2, C) of the energy-momentum H. More precisely, <lb/> Q = 2 <lb/> M Ξ <lb/>Ξ <lb/>  * <lb/> M <lb/> , <lb/> where <lb/> M is the transposed comatrix of M . <lb/> In dimension n = 3, classical algebra results give the non-negativity of each prin-<lb/>cipal minors of Q which provide a set of inequalities on the coefficients of H that <lb/>are explicitly written in the appendix (cf. Section 5.1). <lb/>This result is new (even though many formal arguments where given by <lb/>Gibbons, Hull and Warner in [20]) and based on the recent global charge defini-<lb/>tion of Chru´ ciel and Nagy for AdS-asymptotically hyperbolic manifolds, which <lb/>comes from the Hamiltonian description of General Relativity. Our approach is <lb/>purely Riemannian, the Lorentzian connection and manifold introduced are auxil-<lb/>iary since everything is restricted to the Riemannian slice M (oppositely to [20]). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vol. 7 (2006) <lb/>Positive Energy Theorem <lb/></note>

			<page> 979 <lb/></page>

			<body> In the other hand, the positive mass theorem for Minkowski-asymptotically hy-<lb/>perbolic initial data sets of Chru´ ciel, Jezierski and <lb/>L¸ ski [16] is also different <lb/>from ours, since their Riemannian hypersurface is supposed to be asymptotic at <lb/>infinity to a standard hyperbolic slice of Minkowski space-time (in that case the <lb/>extrinsic curvature does not tend to 0). Then considering the translational Killing <lb/>vector fields of Minkowski, they defined a hyperbolic 4-momentum (usually called <lb/> Trautman-Bondi mass) and proved that it is timelike and future directed under <lb/>the dominant energy condition (and some other technical assumptions). <lb/>Remark finally that our result extends the positive mass theorem of Chru´ ciel <lb/>and Herzlich [15] in dimension n, since if one supposes that k = 0 then we recover <lb/>their result: the mass functional M has to be time-like future directed. <lb/>As regards the rigidity part we have the <lb/> Theorem 1.4 (Rigidity). Under the assumptions of the positive energy-momentum <lb/>theorem, Q = 0 implies that (M, g, k) is isometrically embeddable in AdS <lb/> n,1  . <lb/> This result is optimal in the sense that one could not reasonably hope better than <lb/>being able to embbed isometrically our triple (M, g, k) in AdS. <lb/>Some additional but partial results will be proved (also for the Trautman-<lb/>Bondi 4-momentum) in order to weaken the defining condition of rigidity (cf. <lb/>Section 4). <lb/> 1.4. Organisation of the paper <lb/> In Section 2, we give the necessary geometric background by recalling some basic <lb/>facts on spinors and defining the Killing connection used in the remainder of the <lb/>paper. We also prove the Bochner-Lichnerowicz-Weitzenbök-Witten formula with <lb/>respect to our Killing connection and deduce an integration formula. <lb/>In Section 3, we prove the positive energy-momentum theorem: we remark <lb/>that the boundary contribution of the integrated Bochner-Lichnerowicz-Weitzen-<lb/>bök-Witten formula can be identified to the global charges H(f, α), for some choices <lb/>of (f, α). This can be done using the same ideas as in [15] but in a Lorentzian <lb/>situation, and extends the quite technical computations of [15] in a non-trivial <lb/>way, since the algebraic structures are different (spinors, Hermitian scalar product, <lb/>gauge etc...) and since new terms (involving the extrinsic curvature) appeared and <lb/>had to be identified. We then make the analysis of the Dirac operator (we also <lb/>treat the case where M has a compact boundary) which gives the non-negativity of <lb/>the global charges H(f, α) when the couple (f, α) comes from an imaginary Killing <lb/>spinor of AdS <lb/> n,1  . Then we restrict to dimension n = 3, and completely study the <lb/>imaginary Killing spinors of AdS <lb/> 3,1  in order to interpret the non-negativity of the <lb/> global charges as the non-negativity of the Hermitian matrix Q on C <lb/> 4  . <lb/>Section 4 is devoted to the proof of the rigidity results. <lb/> The last section is an appendix which gives the non-negativity of Q in di-<lb/>mension n = 3 seen through its coefficients, and proves some rigidity results for <lb/>the Trautman-Bondi mass [16]. <lb/></body>

			<page> 980 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> D. Maerten <lb/>Ann. Henri Poincaré <lb/></note>

			<body> 2. Geometric background <lb/> All the definitions and conventions of this section will be stated for any n ≥ 3, <lb/>where n is the dimension of the AdS-asymptotically hyperbolic slice (M, g, k), <lb/> except if the dimension is explicitly mentioned to be 3. Recall that β denotes the <lb/>AdS background metric. <lb/> 2.1. Connections and curvatures <lb/> Let ∇, ∇ denote respectively the Levi-Civita connections of γ and g. Let us take <lb/>a spinor field ψ ∈ Γ(Σ) (where Σ := ΣN  |M  ) and a vector field X ∈ Γ(T M), then <lb/> ∇  X  ψ <lb/> = ∇  X  ψ − <lb/> 1 <lb/> 2  k(X) · e  0  · ψ <lb/> k(X), Y  γ  = ∇  X  Y, e  0   γ  . <lb/> In these formulae · denotes the Clifford action with respect to the metric γ, and <lb/> e  0  = ∂  t  . We will use different notations when we have to make the difference <lb/>between the Clifford action with respect to the metric γ or β. <lb/> Definition 2.1. The Killing equation on a spinor field τ ∈ Γ(Σ) is <lb/> D  X  τ := D  X  τ + <lb/> i <lb/> 2 <lb/> X ·  β  τ = 0 ∀X ∈ Γ(T M), <lb/> where D denotes the Levi-Civita connection of AdS along M . Such a <lb/> D-parallel <lb/> spinor field is called a β-imaginary Killing spinor and we denote τ ∈ IKS (Σ). In <lb/>the same way, a <lb/> ∇-parallel spinor field (where <lb/> ∇  X  := ∇  X  + <lb/> i <lb/> 2  X·  γ  ) is called a <lb/> γ-imaginary Killing spinor. <lb/> Notice that the equation <lb/> Dτ = 0 is neither the Killing equation in AdS nor in H <lb/> n  , <lb/>but the Killing equation in AdS along H <lb/> n  (in particular the imaginary Killing <lb/>spinors considered here are not the one of [3], [15]). <lb/>Now if R, <lb/> R are the respective curvatures of ∇ and <lb/> ∇, we have the relation <lb/> R  X,Y  = R  X,Y  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>4 <lb/>(X · Y − Y · X)· , <lb/> where we use the convention of [24] for the curvature. <lb/> 2.2. Bochner-Lichnerowicz-Weitzenbök-Witten formula and the dominant <lb/>energy condition <lb/> From now on (e  k  ) <lb/> n <lb/>k=0  is an orthonormal basis at the point with respect to the <lb/>metric γ. We define the Dirac-Witten operators <lb/> Dψ = <lb/> n <lb/> k=1 <lb/> e  k  · ∇  e  k  ψ, <lb/> Dψ = <lb/> n <lb/> k=1 <lb/> e  k  · <lb/> ∇  e  k  ψ, <lb/> where n is the dimension of the spacelike slice. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vol. 7 (2006) <lb/>Positive Energy Theorem <lb/></note>

			<page>981 <lb/></page>

			<body> Lemma 2.2 (Bochner-Lichnerowicz-Weitzenbök-Witten formula). <lb/> D <lb/>  *  <lb/> D = <lb/> ∇ <lb/>  *  <lb/> ∇ + <lb/> R, <lb/> where <lb/> R := <lb/> 1 <lb/> 4  (Scal <lb/> γ  + n(n − 1) + 4 Ric <lb/> γ  (e  0  , e  0  ) + 2e  0  · Ric <lb/> γ  (e  0  )). <lb/> Proof. The Dirac-Witten operator D is clearly formally self adjoint, and we have <lb/>the classical Bochner-Lichnerowicz-Weitzenbök formula (cf. [23], [28] for instance) <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> D = D <lb/> 2  = ∇ <lb/>  * <lb/> ∇ + R, where R := <lb/> 1 <lb/>4  (Scal <lb/> γ  + 4 Ric <lb/> γ  (e  0  , e  0  ) + 2e  0  · Ric <lb/> γ  (e  0  )). We <lb/>also know that <lb/> D = D − i <lb/> n <lb/> 2  and so we get <lb/> D <lb/>  *  <lb/> D = ∇ <lb/>  * <lb/> ∇ + R + <lb/> n <lb/> 2 <lb/> 4 <lb/> , <lb/> but finally remarking that <lb/> ∇ <lb/>  *  <lb/> ∇ = ∇ <lb/>  * <lb/> ∇ + <lb/> n <lb/> 4  , we obtain our formula. <lb/> We derive an integration formula from the Bochner-Lichnerowicz-Weitzen-<lb/>bök-Witten identity considering the 1-form θ on M defined by θ(X) = <lb/> ∇  X  ψ + <lb/> X · <lb/> Dψ, ψ <lb/> γ <lb/> , where ψ is a spinor field. Straightforward computations lead to the <lb/>following g-divergence formula <lb/>div θ = <lb/> Dψ, <lb/> Dψ <lb/> γ <lb/> − <lb/> Rψ, ψ <lb/> γ <lb/> − <lb/> ∇ψ, <lb/> ∇ψ <lb/> γ <lb/> . <lb/> Let S  r  the g-geodesic sphere of radius r and centered in a point of M . The radius r <lb/> is supposed to be as large as necessary. We denote by M  r  the interior domain of S  r <lb/> and ν  r  the (pointing outside) unit normal. Integrating our divergence formula over <lb/> M  r  and using Stokes theorem, we get <lb/> Mr <lb/> Dψ <lb/> 2 <lb/> γ <lb/> = <lb/> Mr <lb/> ∇ψ <lb/> 2 <lb/> γ <lb/> + <lb/> Rψ, ψ <lb/> γ <lb/> − <lb/> Sr <lb/> ∇  νr  ψ + ν  r  · <lb/> Dψ, ψ <lb/> γ <lb/> dVol  Sr  . <lb/> Let us now consider the Einstein tensor G = Ric <lb/> γ <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  Scal <lb/> γ  γ with respect to the <lb/>metric γ. The dominant energy condition [33] says that the speed of energy flow <lb/>of matter is always less than the speed of light. More precisely, for every positively <lb/>oriented time-like vector field v, the energy-momentum current of density of matter <lb/> −G(v, .) <lb/>  must be time-like or null, with the same orientation as v. The assumption <lb/>we make in order to prove the positive energy-momentum theorem is a relative <lb/>version of the dominant energy condition: − <lb/> G − <lb/> n(n−1) <lb/> 2 <lb/> γ <lb/> (e  0  ) is a positively <lb/>oriented time-like or null vector along M . Some easy computations give <lb/>Scal <lb/> γ  = 2(G(e  0  , e  0  ) − Ric <lb/> γ  (e  0  , e  0  )) <lb/> e  0  · Ric <lb/> γ  (e  0  ) = e  0  · G  |T M  (e  0  ) − Ric <lb/> γ  (e  0  , e  0  ), <lb/></body>

			<page> 982 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> D. Maerten <lb/>Ann. Henri Poincaré <lb/></note>

			<body> where G  |T M  (e  0  ) = <lb/>  3 <lb/> k=1  G(e  0  , e  k  )e  k  . Thereby <lb/> R = <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/> 2G(e  0  , e  0  ) + (n(n − 1)) + 2e  0  · G  |T M  (e  0  ) <lb/> · <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> G(e  0  , e  0  ) + <lb/> n(n − 1) <lb/>2 <lb/> e  0  − G  |T M  (e  0  ) <lb/> · e  0  · <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> G(e  0  , e  0  ) − <lb/> n(n − 1) <lb/>2 <lb/> γ(e  0  , e  0  ) <lb/> e  0  − G  |T M  (e  0  ) <lb/> · e  0  · <lb/> = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> G − <lb/> n(n − 1) <lb/>2 <lb/> γ <lb/> (e  0  ) · e  0  · . <lb/> Our assumption gives the non negativity of the spinorial endomorphism <lb/> R that is <lb/>to say <lb/> Rψ, ψ <lb/> ≥ 0 for every spinor field ψ. <lb/> Remark 2.3. We can express the dominant energy condition in terms of the con-<lb/>straints as in Section 1.3 since <lb/> − <lb/> G − <lb/> n(n − 1) <lb/>2 <lb/> γ <lb/> (e  0  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(Φ(g, k) − Φ(b, 0)) . <lb/> 2.3. Spinorial gauge <lb/> In the same way as Andersson and Dahl [3], but in a Lorentzian situation, we <lb/>compare spinors in Σ (along M ) with respect to the two different metrics β and γ. <lb/> This can be done according to [13] as soon as the tubular neighbourhood of M <lb/> in N is small enough. Consequently we suppose that both metrics are written in <lb/>Gaussian coordinates β = −dt <lb/> 2  + g  t  , γ = −dt <lb/> 2  + b  t  on ]−, +[ × M for  small <lb/>enough. We define the spinorial gauge A ∈ Γ(End(T)) with the relations <lb/> γ(AX, AY ) = β(X, Y ) <lb/> γ(AX, Y ) = γ(X, AY ) , <lb/> where T is T N restricted to M . The first relation says that A sends β-orthonormal <lb/> frames on γ-orthonormal frames whereas the second one means that the endomor-<lb/>phism A is symmetric. We notice that these relations are only satisfied along <lb/> M = {t = 0} and can also be written in the following way <lb/> ⎧ <lb/>⎨ <lb/>⎩ <lb/> Ae  0  = e  0 <lb/> g(AX, AY ) = b(X, Y ) <lb/> g(AX, Y ) = g(X, AY ) . <lb/> Consequently A is an application P  SO  0  (n,1)  (β)  |M  → P  SO  0  (n,1)  (γ)  |M  , which can be <lb/>covered by an application still denoted by A : P  Spin  0  (n,1)  (β)  |M  → P  Spin  0  (n,1)  (γ)  |M  . <lb/>This application carries β-spinors on γ-spinors so that we have the compatibility <lb/>relation about the Clifford actions of β and γ <lb/> A(X ·  β  σ) = (AX) ·  γ  (Aσ), <lb/>for every X ∈ Γ(T), σ ∈ Γ(Σ) and where ·  β  , ·  γ  denotes the Clifford actions respec-<lb/>tively of β and γ. Remark that our gauge is more sophisticated that the one of [3] <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vol. 7 (2006) <lb/>Positive Energy Theorem <lb/></note>

			<page> 983 <lb/></page>

			<body> since it deals with the trace of Lorentzian structures (metrics, spinors, Hermitian <lb/>scalar product etc...) along the spacelike slice M . <lb/>We define a new connection <lb/> ∇X = A(DA <lb/> −1  X) along M . It is easy to check <lb/>that <lb/> ∇ is g-metric and has torsion <lb/> T (X, Y ) = −((D  X  A)A <lb/> −1  Y − (D  Y  A)A <lb/> −1  X). <lb/> We extract some formulae for later use <lb/>2g <lb/> ∇  X  Y − ∇  X  Y, Z <lb/> = g <lb/> T (X, Y ), Z <lb/> − g <lb/> T (X, Z), Y <lb/> − g <lb/> T (Y, Z), X <lb/> . <lb/> Now we intend to compare the connections ∇ and <lb/> ∇ on Σ. (σ  s  )  s  denotes the <lb/>spinorial frame corresponding to the orthonormal frame (e  k  ) <lb/> n <lb/>k=0  , and ω, <lb/> ω are the <lb/>connection 1-forms respectively of ∇ and <lb/> ∇ <lb/> ω  ij  = g(∇e  i  , e  j  ) <lb/> ω  ij  = g( <lb/> ∇e  i  , e  j  ) , <lb/> and if we take a general spinor ϕ = ϕ <lb/> s  σ  s  , their derivatives are given by <lb/> ∇ϕ = dϕ <lb/> s <lb/> ⊗ σ  s  + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> i&lt;j <lb/> ω  ij  ⊗ e  i  ·  γ  e  j  ·  γ  ϕ <lb/> ∇ϕ = dϕ <lb/> s <lb/> ⊗ σ  s  + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> i&lt;j <lb/> ω  ij  ⊗ e  i  ·  γ  e  j  ·  γ  ϕ , <lb/> and as a consequence <lb/>(∇ − <lb/> ∇)ϕ = <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/> n <lb/> i,j=0 <lb/> (ω  ij  − <lb/> ω  ij  ) ⊗ e  i  ·  γ  e  j  ·  γ  ϕ . <lb/> 2.4. Tangent and spinor bundles <lb/> In this paper, the model spaces AdS <lb/> n,1  and H <lb/> n  are considered as symmetric spaces: <lb/> H <lb/> n  = Spin  0  (n, 1)/ Spin(n) <lb/>  <lb/> / / AdS <lb/> n,1  = Spin  0  (n, 2)/ Spin  0  (n, 1) , <lb/> so that every section of the spinor bundle Σ of AdS restricted to H <lb/> n  , can be seen <lb/>as a function Spin  0  (n, 1) −→ C <lb/> d  which is Spin(n)-equivariant (with d depending <lb/>upon n). We can be more explicit when we take n = 3 (this fact is due to the <lb/>exceptional isomorphisms of Lie groups below) <lb/> H <lb/> 3  = SL(2, C)/ SU(2) <lb/>  <lb/> / / AdS <lb/> 3,1  = Spin  0  (3, 2)/ Spin  0  (3, 1) , <lb/> with SU(2) ∼ = Spin(3) and SL(2, C) ∼ = Spin  0  (3, 1). <lb/>The spinor bundle of AdS is Σ  AdS  = Spin  0  (3, 2) ×  ˜ <lb/> ρ  C <lb/> 4  , where Spin  0  (3, 2) is <lb/>the bundle of the Spin  0  (3, 1)-frames in AdS, and <lb/>  is the standard representation <lb/>of SL(2, C) on C <lb/> 4  ∼ = C <lb/> 2 <lb/> ⊕ C  2 <lb/>  . In other words <lb/>˜ <lb/> ρ : SL(2, C) −→ M  4  (C) <lb/>˜ <lb/> g <lb/> −→ <lb/>  0 <lb/>0 (˜ g <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> −1 <lb/> , <lb/></body>

			<page> 984 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> D. Maerten <lb/>Ann. Henri Poincaré <lb/></note>

			<body> where A <lb/>  *  = <lb/> t  A, A ∈ M  2  (C). When we restrict this bundle to the hypersurface H <lb/> 3 <lb/> we have Σ = SL(2, C) ×  ˜ <lb/> ρ  | SU(2)  C <lb/> 4  . <lb/> Proposition 2.4. Σ and H <lb/> 3 <lb/> × C <lb/> 4  are isomorphic thanks to the following trivialisa-<lb/>tion: <lb/> T : <lb/>Σ −→ H <lb/> 3 <lb/> × C <lb/> 4 <lb/> {˜ , w} −→ ([˜ e], ˜ <lb/> ρ(˜ e)w) , <lb/> where {˜ , w} denotes the class of (˜ e, w) ∈ SL(2, C) × C <lb/> 4  in Σ, and [˜ e] denotes the <lb/>class of  <lb/>  ∈ SL(2, C) in H <lb/> 3  = SL(2, C)/ SU(2). <lb/>The construction of T  AdS  , the tangent bundle of AdS, is quite similar to the con-<lb/>struction of the spinor bundle. Still noticing that the principal bundle of SO  0  (3, 1)-<lb/>frames in AdS is isomorphic to SO  0  (3, 2), we write T  AdS  = SO  0  (3, 2) ×  ρ  R <lb/> 4  , where <lb/> ρ is the standard representation of SO  0  (3, 1) on R <lb/> 4  . By restriction to the hyper-<lb/>surface H <lb/> 3  , we obtain T = SO  0  (3, 1) ×  ρ  | SO(3)  R <lb/> 4  , where SO(3) is by definition the <lb/>isotropy group of f  0  if (f  k  ) <lb/> 3 <lb/> k=0  denotes the canonical basis of R <lb/> 4  . <lb/> Proposition 2.5. T and H <lb/> 3 <lb/> × R <lb/> 4  are isomorphic thanks to the following trivialisa-<lb/>tion: <lb/> T : <lb/> T −→ H <lb/> 3 <lb/> × R <lb/> 4 <lb/> {e, u} −→ ([e], ρ(e)u) , <lb/> where {e, u} denotes the class of (e, u) ∈ SO  0  (3, 1) × R <lb/> 4  in T, and [e] denotes the <lb/>class of e ∈ SO  0  (3, 1) in H <lb/> 3  = SO  0  (3, 1)/ SO(3). <lb/>We are going to define the Clifford action on Σ, in the same way as in [28]. To <lb/>this end, we denote by (R <lb/> 4  , q) the Minkowski space-time of signature (3,1), where <lb/> q = −dy <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  + dy <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + dy <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  + dy <lb/> 2 <lb/>3  . This space is isometric to a subspace of M  2  (C) via <lb/>Λ: <lb/>(R <lb/> 4  , q) −→ M := ({A ∈ M  2  (C) | A <lb/>  *  = A} , − det) <lb/> y = (y  i  ) <lb/> 3 <lb/> i=0  −→ <lb/> y  0  + y  1  y  2  + iy  3 <lb/> y  2  − iy  3  y  0  − y  1 <lb/> . <lb/> We have thus the following real vector space isomorphisms: <lb/>M  2  (C) ∼ = u(2) ⊕ M <lb/>sl  2  (C) ∼ = su(2) ⊕ (M ∩ sl  2  (C)) <lb/> ∼ = su(2) ⊕ G , <lb/> and G ∼ = R <lb/> 3  . In order to make the value of the sectional curvature of H <lb/> 3  equal <lb/>to −1, when we consider H <lb/> 3  = SL(2, C)/ SU(2) as a symmetric space, we have to <lb/>consider R <lb/> 4  endowed with 4q and not q, and consequently the embedding of the <lb/>Clifford algebra C  3,1  in M  4  (C) becomes <lb/>Θ: X ∈ M −→ <lb/> 0 2X <lb/>2 <lb/> X <lb/> 0 <lb/> , <lb/> where <lb/> X means the transposed comatrix of X. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vol. 7 (2006) <lb/>Positive Energy Theorem <lb/></note>

			<page> 985 <lb/></page>

			<body> It will be convenient to see T as SL(2, C) ×  μ  M, where μ is the universal <lb/>covering of SO  0  (3, 1) by SL(2, C), which is given by: <lb/> μ : SL(2, C) −→ <lb/> SO  0  (3, 1) <lb/>˜ <lb/> g <lb/> −→ (˜ g : X ∈ M → ˜ <lb/> gX  <lb/>  *  ) . <lb/> We can now define the Clifford action. Let us take e ∈ SO  0  (3, 1) and <lb/>  ∈ SL(2, C) <lb/> such that e = μ( e). A vector X = X[e] tangent at the point [e] = [˜ e] ∈ H <lb/> 3  , is a <lb/>class {e, u} ∈ T. A spinor σ = σ[˜ e] at the same point is likewise a class {˜ , w} ∈ Σ. <lb/>The result of the Clifford action of X on σ is the spinor (X ·σ)[˜ e] = {e, u}·{˜ , w} = <lb/> {˜ , Θ(u)w}. We define a sesquilinear inner product (not definite positive) (·, ·) on <lb/> C <lb/> 4  ∼ = C <lb/> 2 <lb/> ⊕ C  2 <lb/>  as in [28] (ξ, η) := ξ  1  , η  2   C  2  + ξ  2  , η  1   C  2  , where ξ = <lb/>  ξ1 <lb/>ξ2 <lb/> , η = <lb/>  η1 <lb/>η2 <lb/> ∈ C <lb/> 4  and where ·, ··  C  2  is the standard Hermitian product on C <lb/> 2  . This induces a <lb/>sesquilinear product on Σ by ({˜ , ξ}, {˜ , η}) := (ξ, η). In the same way we define a <lb/>scalar product on Σ setting <lb/> {˜ , ξ}, {˜ , η}} := <lb/>  1 <lb/>2  f  0  · {˜ , ξ}, {˜ , η} <lb/> = ({˜ , <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  Θ(f  0  )ξ}, {˜ , η}) <lb/> = ξ, η  C  4  , <lb/> where ·, ··  C  4  denotes the standard Hermitian product on C <lb/> 4  . <lb/>Since SL(2, C) is the 2-sheeted covering of SO  0  (3, 1), there exists a natural <lb/>(left) action of SL(2, C) on Σ which is derived from the natural (left) action of <lb/>SO  0  (3, 1) on T: the action of the group of the isometries of AdS preserving the <lb/>slice H <lb/> 3  that is <lb/>  * {˜ , w} = {˜ ˜ , w}, with <lb/>  ∈ SL(2, C) and σ[˜ e] = {˜ , w} a spinor at <lb/>[˜ e]. To have the action on a section σ ∈ Γ(Σ) we set as usual (˜ g  * σ)[˜ e] = ˜ <lb/> g  * σ(˜ g <lb/> −1  <lb/> ). <lb/> 3. Positive energy-momentum theorem <lb/> In this section, the dimension will be n ≥ 3 expect if n is explicitly mentioned to <lb/>be 3. <lb/>Moreover f will denote a smooth cutoff function which is 0 on M except on <lb/>a small neighbourhood of the infinity boundary of M where f ≡ 1, and H(a), <lb/>H  −  (a) are Hilbert spaces of spinor fields defined in the subsections below. We will <lb/>prove the <lb/> Proposition 3.1. For every β-imaginary Killing spinor σ ∈ IKS (Σ) there exists a <lb/>unique γ-spinor field ξ  0  ∈ H(a) (resp. ∈ H  −  (a) if M has a boundary) such that <lb/> ξ = f Aσ + ξ  0  ∈ Ker <lb/> D (resp. ∈ Ker <lb/> D ∩ H  −  (a)) and H(V  σ  , α  σ  ) ≥ 0, <lb/> where V  σ  = σ, σ and α  σ  (X) = X · e  0  · σ, σ. <lb/> In Section 3.3, it will proved that the couple (V  σ  , α  σ  ) belongs to N  b  ⊕ Kill(H <lb/> n  ) so <lb/>that H(V  σ  , α  σ  ) is actually well defined. <lb/>The computations we will make in Section 3.1 prove that if we integrate the <lb/>Bochner-Lichnerowicz-Weitzenbök-Witten formula with an asymptotically imagi-<lb/>nary Killing spinor f Aσ, then the boundary integrals tend to some global charge <lb/></body>

			<page> 986 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> D. Maerten <lb/>Ann. Henri Poincaré <lb/></note>

			<body> H(V  σ  , α  σ  ), when r goes to infinity. In fact it is still true if we perturb f Aσ with a <lb/>smooth compactly supported spinor field ξ  0  (that is to say if we consider f Aσ + ξ  0 <lb/> instead of f Aσ). Actually we will show in Section 3.2 that we can find a pertur-<lb/>bation ξ  0  in a relevant Hilbert space such that ξ  0  has no contribution at infinity, <lb/>and f Aσ + ξ  0  belongs to the kernel of <lb/> D. <lb/> This will naturally imply the non-negativity of H(V  σ  , α  σ  ) when σ is a β-imag-<lb/> inary Killing spinor. This is the reason why we focus on the study of the Killing <lb/>equation in Section 3.3 so as to interpret the non-negativity of the H(V  σ  , α  σ  ). <lb/> 3.1. Energy-momentum and imaginary Killing spinors <lb/> The aim of this section is to show the <lb/> Proposition 3.2. Let ξ = f Aσ + ξ  0  , where σ ∈ IKS (Σ) and ξ  0  is a compactly <lb/>supported spinor field. Then we have <lb/> H(V  σ  , α  σ  ) = 4 lim <lb/> r→+∞ <lb/> Sr <lb/> ∇  Aνr  ξ + Aν  r  · <lb/> Dξ, ξ <lb/> γ <lb/> = 4 <lb/> M <lb/> ∇ξ <lb/> 2 <lb/> γ <lb/> + <lb/> Rξ, ξ <lb/> γ <lb/> − 4 <lb/> M <lb/> Dξ <lb/> 2 <lb/> γ <lb/> . <lb/> Remark that the only important data is the exact β-imaginary Killing spinor σ <lb/> involved in the definition of the couple (V  σ  , α  σ  ). <lb/> Proof. Remember that <lb/> Mr <lb/> Dψ <lb/> 2 <lb/> γ <lb/> = <lb/> Mr <lb/> ∇ψ <lb/> 2 <lb/> γ <lb/> + <lb/> Rψ, ψ <lb/> γ <lb/> − <lb/> Sr <lb/> ∇  Aνr  ψ + Aν  r  ·  γ  <lb/> Dψ, ψ <lb/> γ <lb/> dVol  Sr  , <lb/> where ν  r  denotes the b-normal of S  r  , e  0  = ∂  t  and we set e  1  = Aν  r  for the remainder <lb/>of the proof. <lb/>We have to work on the expression <lb/> ∇  Aνr  ψ + Aν  r  ·  γ  <lb/> Dψ, ψ <lb/> γ <lb/> in order to <lb/>identify the integrand used to compute the energy-momentum for some couple <lb/>(f, α). We start with noticing that e  1  ·  γ  e  1  ·  γ  <lb/> ∇  e1  = − <lb/> ∇  e1  = − <lb/> ∇  Aνr  so that <lb/> ∇  Aνr  ψ + Aν  r  ·  γ  <lb/> Dψ = Aν  r  ·  γ <lb/> ⎛ <lb/>⎝ <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> e  j  ·  γ  <lb/> ∇  ej <lb/> ⎞ <lb/>⎠ ψ. <lb/> From now on we work on <lb/> Aν  r  ·  γ <lb/> ⎛ <lb/>⎝ <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> e  j  ·  γ  <lb/> ∇  ej <lb/> ⎞ <lb/>⎠ ·  γ  Aσ, Aσ <lb/> γ <lb/> . <lb/> Let us take σ a β-imaginary Killing spinor, that is to say a spinor field solution, <lb/>by definition, of <lb/> D  X  σ = D  X  σ + <lb/> i <lb/> 2  X ·  β  σ = 0, for every vector field X ∈ Γ(T M). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vol. 7 (2006) <lb/>Positive Energy Theorem <lb/></note>

			<page> 987 <lb/></page>

			<body> Consider f a smooth cutoff function which is 0 on M except on a compact neigh-<lb/>bourhood of the infinity boundary of M where f ≡ 1. Then we have <lb/> ∇  X  (f Aσ) = df (X)Aσ + f <lb/> ∇  X  (Aσ) <lb/>= df (X)Aσ + f (∇  X  − <lb/> ∇  X  )(Aσ) <lb/>+ f <lb/> ∇  X  + <lb/> i <lb/> 2  ·  γ  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  k(X) ·  γ  e  0  ·  γ <lb/> (Aσ), <lb/>but since <lb/> ∇  X  (Aσ) = AD  X  σ = − <lb/> i <lb/> 2  A(X ·  β  σ) = − <lb/> i <lb/> 2  (AX) ·  γ  (Aσ), we obtain <lb/> ∇  X  (f Aσ) = df (X)Aσ+f (∇  X  − <lb/> ∇  X  )(Aσ)− <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> f (k(X) ·  γ  e  0  + i(A − Id )X)·  γ  (Aσ), <lb/>that we restrict to the neighbourhood where f ≡ 1 <lb/> ∇  X  (Aσ) = (∇  X  − <lb/> ∇  X  )(Aσ) − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(k(X) ·  γ  e  0  + i(A − Id )X) ·  γ  (Aσ). <lb/>As a consequence our boundary term becomes for r great enough <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> Aν  r  ·  γ  e  j  ·  γ <lb/> (∇  ej  − <lb/> ∇  ej  ) − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(k(e  j  ) ·  γ  e  0  + i(A − Id )e  j  )·  γ <lb/> (Aσ), Aσ <lb/> γ <lb/> . <lb/> We will estimate this boundary term in several steps. From the decay assumptions <lb/>stated in Section 1.2, the gauge is supposed to be of the form A = Id +B +O(|B| <lb/> 2  ), <lb/>where B has the same decay to 0 as e = g − b. In the following (  j  = A <lb/> −1  e  j  ) <lb/> n <lb/>j=0 <lb/> is a β-orthonormal frame. <lb/>We begin with the easiest term <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> Aν  r  ·  γ  e  j  ·  γ  k(e  j  ) ·  γ  e  0  ·  γ  (Aσ), Aσ  γ <lb/> = <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> Aν  r  ·  γ  A  j  ·  γ  k(A  j  ) ·  γ  A  0  ·  γ  (Aσ), Aσ  γ <lb/> = <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> ν  r  ·  β   j  ·  β  A <lb/> −1 <lb/> • k • A(  j  ) ·  β   0  ·  β  σ, σ <lb/> β <lb/> . <lb/> But we note that A <lb/> −1 <lb/> • k • A = k − B • k + k • B + O(|B| <lb/> 2  ). Now B has the same <lb/>decay as k so B • k + k • B = O(|B| <lb/> 2  ), terms that we can neglect since the energy-<lb/>momentum is computed by a limit procedure of integrals over large spheres. We <lb/>conclude that A <lb/> −1 <lb/> • k • A ≈ k, where for convenience the relation ≈  means <lb/>that | | −  | is at least a O(e <lb/> −2τr  ) when r goes to infinity. Moreover <lb/> ν  r  ·  β <lb/>n <lb/> j=2 <lb/>  j  ·  β  k(  j  ) =  1  ·  β <lb/> ⎛ <lb/>⎝ <lb/> n <lb/> j=1 <lb/>  j  ·  β  k(  j  ) −  1  ·  β  k(  1  ) <lb/> ⎞ <lb/>⎠ <lb/> = k(ν  r  ) − (tr  b  k)ν  r  , <lb/> 988 <lb/> D. Maerten <lb/>Ann. Henri Poincaré <lb/> which implies <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> Aν  r  ·  γ  e  j  ·  γ  k(e  j  ) ·  γ  e  0  ·  γ  (Aσ), Aσ  γ  ≈ ≈k(ν  r  ) − (tr  b  k)ν  r  ·  β   0  ·  β  σ, σ  β <lb/> = (i  ασ  k − (tr  b  k)α  σ  ) (ν  r  ), <lb/>where α  σ  (X) = X ·  β   0  ·  β  σ, σ  β  . <lb/>The second term we study is <lb/> i <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> Aν  r  ·  γ  e  j  ·  γ  (A − Id )(e  j  ) ·  γ  (Aσ), Aσ  γ <lb/> = i <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> Aν  r  ·  γ  A  j  ·  γ  (A − Id )(A  j  ) ·  γ  (Aσ), Aσ  γ <lb/> = i <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> ν  r  ·  β   j  ·  β  A <lb/> −1 <lb/> • (A − Id ) • A(  j  ) ·  β  σ, σ <lb/> β <lb/> ≈ i <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> ν  r  ·  β   j  ·  β  B(  j  ) ·  β  σ, σ  β  , <lb/> but thanks to the same property as above <lb/> ν  r  ·  β <lb/>n <lb/> j=2 <lb/>  j  ·  β  B(  j  ) = B(ν  r  ) − (tr  b  B)ν  r  , <lb/> which induces <lb/> i <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> Aν  r  ·  γ  e  j  ·  γ  (A − Id )(e  j  ) ·  γ  (Aσ), Aσ  γ  ≈ i B(ν  r  ) − (tr  b  B)ν  r  ·  β  σ, σ  β <lb/> = (i  ∇Vσ  B − (tr  b  B)dV  σ  ) (ν  r  ), <lb/>where dV  σ  (X) = i X ·  β  σ, σ  β  . <lb/>The last term we have to study is certainly the most difficult (summation conven-<lb/>tion k ∈ {2, 3, . . . , n}, l ∈ {1, 2, . . . , n}, m ∈ {1, 2, . . . , n}) <lb/> Aν  r  ·  γ  e  k  ·  γ  (∇  e  k  − <lb/> ∇  e  k  )(Aσ), Aσ <lb/> γ <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/> (ω  lm  − <lb/> ω  lm  )(e  k  )Aν  r  ·  γ  e  k  ·  γ  e  l  ·  γ  e  m  ·  γ  (Aσ), Aσ  γ <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/> (ω  lm  − <lb/> ω  lm  ) • A(  k  )ν  r  ·  β   k  ·  β   l  ·  β   m  ·  β  σ, σ  β <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/> S <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vol. 7 (2006) <lb/>Positive Energy Theorem <lb/></note>
			<page> 989 <lb/></page>

			<body> S = <lb/> n <lb/> k,l,m=2 <lb/> (ω  lm  − <lb/> ω  lm  )(e  k  )Aν  r  ·  γ  e  k  ·  γ  e  l  ·  γ  e  m  ·  γ  (Aσ), Aσ  γ <lb/> + 2 <lb/> n <lb/> k,l=2 <lb/> (ω  1l  − <lb/> ω  1l  )(e  k  )Aν  r  ·  γ  e  k  ·  γ  e  1  ·  γ  e  l  ·  γ  (Aσ), Aσ  γ <lb/> = S  1  + 2S  2  . <lb/> We will give estimates of each S  k  , keeping in mind that they are real and that every <lb/>term that is at least O(|B| <lb/> 2  ) can be neglected when r → +∞ for the computations <lb/>of the global charge integrals. <lb/> Estimate of S  1 <lb/> S  1  = <lb/> n <lb/> k,l,m=2 <lb/> (ω  lm  − <lb/> ω  lm  )(e  k  )Aν  r  ·  γ  e  k  ·  γ  e  l  ·  γ  e  m  ·  γ  (Aσ), Aσ  γ  . <lb/> We can keep only the subscripts l  = m because of the skew-symmetry of (ω − <lb/> ω). <lb/> Besides if we suppose that k = l, we have terms like Aν  r  ·  γ  e  m  ·  γ  (Aσ), Aσ  γ <lb/> which belong to iR. So we can sum over k, l, m distinct subscripts without any loss <lb/>of generality. On the other hand <lb/>(ω  lm  − <lb/> ω  lm  )(e  k  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> −g( <lb/> T (e  k  , e  l  ), e  m  ) + g( <lb/> T (e  k  , e  m  ), e  l  ) + g( <lb/> T (e  l  , e  m  ), e  k  ) <lb/> where the two last terms of the right-hand side member are symmetric with respect <lb/>to (l, k), so they vanish when we sum over k and l distinct. Consequently <lb/>(ω  lm  − <lb/> ω  lm  )(e  k  )  k  ·  β   l  ·  β   m <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> b <lb/> A <lb/> −1  (D  e  k  A)  l  − A <lb/> −1  (D  e  l  A)  k  , ,  m <lb/>  k  ·  β   l  ·  β   m <lb/> = b <lb/> A <lb/> −1  (D  e  k  A)  l  , ,  m <lb/>  k  ·  β   l  ·  β   m  , <lb/> but <lb/> b(A <lb/> −1  (D  e  k  A)  l  , ,  m  ) = b(A <lb/> −1  (D  e  k  (A  l  ) − AD  e  k   l  ), ,  m  ) <lb/> ≈ b(D   k  (BB  l  ) − B(D   k   l  ), ,  m  ) <lb/>= b((D   k  B)  l  , ,  m  ), <lb/>expression which is symmetric with respect to (l, m), since DB is a symmetric <lb/>endomorphism. Consequently <lb/> k,l,m distinct <lb/> (ω  lm  − <lb/> ω  lm  )(e  k  )  k  ·  β   l  ·  β   m  ≈ 0, <lb/>when r → +∞. <lb/></body>

			<page> 990 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> D. Maerten <lb/>Ann. Henri Poincaré <lb/></note>

			<body> Estimate of S  2 <lb/> S  2  = <lb/> n <lb/> k,l=2 <lb/> (ω  1l  − <lb/> ω  1l  )(e  k  )Aν  r  ·  γ  e  k  ·  γ  e  1  ·  γ  e  l  ·  γ  (Aσ), Aσ  γ <lb/> = − <lb/> n <lb/> k=2 <lb/> (ω  1k  − <lb/> ω  1k  )(e  k  )σ, σ  β <lb/> + <lb/> k =l <lb/> (ω  1l  − <lb/> ω  1l  )(e  k  )e  k  ·  γ  e  l  ·  γ  (Aσ), Aσ  γ  , <lb/> but the second sum is in iR, so it remains <lb/> e(S  2  ) = − <lb/>  n <lb/> k=1 <lb/> (ω  1k  − <lb/> ω  1k  )(e  k  ) <lb/> V  σ  . <lb/> We only have to compute <lb/> − <lb/> n <lb/> k=1 <lb/> (ω  1k  − <lb/> ω  1k  )(e  k  ) = <lb/> n <lb/> k=1 <lb/> g((D  e1  A)A <lb/> −1  e  k  , e  k  − (D  e  k  A)A <lb/> −1  e  1  , e  k  ) <lb/>= S <lb/> 2  − S <lb/> 2  . <lb/> We focus on <lb/> S <lb/> 2  = <lb/> n <lb/> k=1 <lb/> g((D  e  k  A)A <lb/> −1  e  1  , e  k  ) <lb/>= <lb/> n <lb/> k=1 <lb/> b(A <lb/> −1  (D  e  k  A)  1  , ,  k  ) <lb/>= <lb/> n <lb/> k=1 <lb/> b(A <lb/> −1  D  e  k  (A  1  ) − D  e  k   1  , ,  k  ) <lb/> ≈ <lb/> n <lb/> k=1 <lb/> b((D  e  k  B)  1  , ,  k  ) <lb/> ≈ <lb/> n <lb/> k=1 <lb/> b(  1  , (D   k  B)  k  ) <lb/>= − div  b  B(ν  r  ). <lb/>As regards the first term S <lb/> 2  , we decompose the gauge endomorphism A as follows: <lb/> A  i  = <lb/>  n <lb/>k=0  A <lb/> k <lb/>i   k  . We remind that A  0  =  0  , A(T M) ⊂ T M and so we have <lb/> A <lb/> k <lb/> 0  = A <lb/> 0 <lb/> k  = 0, k ≥ 1. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vol. 7 (2006) <lb/>Positive Energy Theorem <lb/></note>

			<page> 991 <lb/></page>

			<body> S <lb/> 2  = <lb/> n <lb/> k=1 <lb/> g((D  e1  A)A <lb/> −1  e  k  , e  k  ) <lb/>= <lb/> n <lb/> k=1 <lb/> b((A <lb/> −1  D  e1  A)  k  , ,  k  ) <lb/>= <lb/> n <lb/> k=1 <lb/> b(A <lb/> −1  D  e1  (A  k  ) − D  e1   k  , ,  k  ) <lb/> ≈ <lb/> n <lb/> k,l=1 <lb/> (e  1  · A <lb/> l <lb/>k  ) {b(  l  , ,  k  ) − b(BB  l  , ,  k  )} − <lb/> n <lb/> k=1 <lb/> b(D  e1   k  , ,  k  ) <lb/>+ <lb/> n <lb/> k,l=1 <lb/> A <lb/> l <lb/>k <lb/> b(D  e1   l  , ,  k  ) − b(BD  e1   l  , ,  k  ) <lb/> ≈ (  1  · tr  b  B) − <lb/> n <lb/> k=1 <lb/> b(D  e1   k  , ,  k  ) <lb/>+ <lb/> n <lb/> k,l=1 <lb/> (δ <lb/> k <lb/>l  + B <lb/> l <lb/>k  ) <lb/> b(D  e1   l  , ,  k  ) − b(BD  e1   l  , ,  k  ) <lb/> ≈ (  1  · tr  b  B) − <lb/> n <lb/> k=1 <lb/> b(BD  e1   k  , ,  k  ) − b(D  e1   k  , B  k  ) <lb/> = d(tr  b  B)(ν  r  ), <lb/>that entails <lb/> e(S  2  ) ≈ V  σ  (d(tr  b  B) + div  b  B)(ν  r  ). <lb/>We can conclude, taking B = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  e, that the real part of our boundary integrand <lb/>is nothing but <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/> −V  σ  (δ  b  e + d tr  b  e) − i  ∇  b  Vσ  e + (tr  b  e)dV  σ  − 2i  α <lb/>σ <lb/> k + 2(tr  b  k)α  σ <lb/> (ν  r  ), <lb/>what achieves the proof. <lb/> 3.2. Analysis of <lb/> D <lb/> This section is devoted to the study of the analytical properties of <lb/> D. The first <lb/>paragraph deals with the case where M has no boundary whereas the second one <lb/>deals with the case where M has a compact and connected boundary denoted as <lb/>usual by ∂M . <lb/> 3.2.1. The boundaryless case. <lb/>Proposition 3.3. For every σ ∈ IKS (Σ), there exists a unique ξ  0  ∈ H(a) such that <lb/> ξ = f Aσ+ξ  0  ∈ Ker <lb/> D and <lb/> H(V  σ  , α  σ  ) = lim <lb/> r→+∞ <lb/> Sr <lb/> ∇  Aνr  ξ + Aν  r  · <lb/> Dξ, ξ <lb/> γ <lb/> = 4 <lb/> M <lb/> ∇ξ <lb/> 2 <lb/> γ <lb/> + <lb/> Rξ, ξ <lb/> γ <lb/> ≥ 0. <lb/></body>

			<page> 992 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> D. Maerten <lb/>Ann. Henri Poincaré <lb/></note>

			<body> Proof. We study in a usual way the analytical properties of <lb/> D. Let us consider <lb/> C <lb/> ∞ <lb/> 0  (Σ) = C <lb/> ∞ <lb/> 0  the space of smooth and compactly supported spinors. We define a <lb/>sesquilinear form on C <lb/> ∞ <lb/> 0  by <lb/> a(ϕ, ψ) = <lb/> M <lb/> Dϕ, <lb/> Dψ <lb/> γ <lb/> dμ  g  , <lb/> where dμ  g  denotes the standard volume form of the metric g. The form a is clearly <lb/>bounded and non-negative on C <lb/> ∞ <lb/> 0  . We define the usual Sobolev space <lb/> H <lb/> 1  (Σ) = <lb/> ψ ∈ Σ <lb/> M <lb/> |ψ| <lb/> 2 <lb/> γ  + |∇ψ| <lb/> 2 <lb/> γ  &lt; ∞ <lb/> . <lb/> Definition 3.4. We set H(a) := C  ∞ <lb/> 0 <lb/> a  . <lb/> Remark 3.5 (Weighted Poincaré inequality). <lb/> ∃ω ∈ L <lb/> 1 <lb/>loc  (M, dVol  g  ) ess  M  inf ω &gt; 0 ∀u ∈ C <lb/> 1 <lb/>0 <lb/> M <lb/> ω|u| <lb/> 2  dVol  g  ≤ <lb/> M <lb/> | <lb/> ∇u| <lb/> 2  dVol  g  . <lb/> The symmetric part of the connection <lb/> ∇ is given by Γ  X  = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  {k(X) · e  0  − iX} ·, <lb/> and so satisfies the conditions (cf. [7]) in order to have the existence of a weighted <lb/>Poincaré inequality that is to say Γ ∈ L <lb/> n <lb/> loc  (M ) and lim sup  x→0  |xΓ  x  | &lt; <lb/> n−1 <lb/> 2  . <lb/>Such a weighted Poincaré inequality insures the continuity of the embedding of <lb/> H(a) <lb/>  <lb/> / / H <lb/> 1 <lb/> loc  . This claim is true even when M has a compact boundary so that <lb/>we will make its proof when there is a boundary. Indeed consider (ψ  k  )  k∈N  ∈ (C <lb/> ∞ <lb/> 0  ) <lb/> N <lb/> a Cauchy sequence with respect to the form a whose elements satisfy the boundary <lb/>condition F (ψ  k  ) = −ψ  k  (cf. next section for the definition of the boundary en-<lb/>domorphism F ). Then we have (the vector field k will also be defined in the next <lb/>section) <lb/> M <lb/> Dψ  k <lb/> 2 <lb/> γ <lb/> = <lb/> ∇ψ  k <lb/> 2 <lb/> γ <lb/> + <lb/> Rψ  k  , ψ  k <lb/> γ <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ∂M <lb/> e  0  · k · ψ  k  , ψ  k <lb/> , <lb/> and thus thanks to the weighted Poincaré inequality <lb/> ∀Ω ⊂ M |Ω| &lt; ∞ ψ  k <lb/>L <lb/> 2  (Ω)  / / ψ and <lb/> ∇ψ  k <lb/>L <lb/> 2  (M )  / / ρ. <lb/> Now let us take a ϕ ∈ C <lb/> 1 <lb/>0  such that Supp ϕ ⊂ K ⊂ (M \ ∂M ) (K compact without <lb/>boundary) and then <lb/> K <lb/> ∇ <lb/>  *  ϕ, ψ  k <lb/> k→∞ <lb/> K <lb/> ϕ, <lb/> ∇ψ  k <lb/> k→∞ <lb/> K <lb/> ∇ <lb/>  *  ϕ, ψ <lb/> K <lb/> ϕ, ρ <lb/>, <lb/> and therefore ρ = <lb/> ∇ψ in the distributional sense. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vol. 7 (2006) <lb/> Positive Energy Theorem <lb/></note>

			<page> 993 <lb/></page>

			<body> We notice that for r great enough and for σ ∈ IKS (Σ) <lb/> ∇  X  (Aσ) = ∇  X  (Aσ) + <lb/> i <lb/> 2 <lb/> X ·  γ  (Aσ) <lb/>= (∇  X  − <lb/> ∇  X  )(Aσ) − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(k(X) ·  γ  e  0  + i(A − Id )X) ·  γ  (Aσ). <lb/>But the relations <lb/> T (X, Y ) = −((D  X  A)A <lb/> −1  Y − (D  Y  A)A <lb/> −1  X) <lb/> 2g( <lb/> ∇  X  Y − ∇  X  Y, Z) = g( <lb/> T (X, Y ), Z) − g( <lb/> T (X, Z), Y ) − g( <lb/> T (Y, Z), X) <lb/> tell us that |(ω  ij  − <lb/> ω  ij  )(e  k  )| ≤ C|A <lb/> −1 <lb/> ||DA|. We get an estimate <lb/> | <lb/> D(Aσ)| ≤ C|A|(|DA| + |A − Id | + |k|)|σ| ∈ L <lb/> 2  (M, dμ  g  ), <lb/>which infers that <lb/> D(f Aσ) ∈ L <lb/> 2  (M, dμ  g  ). We now consider the linear form l <lb/> on H(a) defined by <lb/> l(ψ) = <lb/> M <lb/> D(f Aσ), <lb/> Dψ <lb/> γ <lb/> dμ  g  . <lb/> Thanks to our estimate above we get |l(ψ)| <lb/> 2 <lb/> ≤ <lb/> D(f Aσ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> L  2 <lb/> a(ψ, ψ), that gives <lb/>the continuity of l in H(a). We can claim, thanks to Lax-Milgram theorem, that <lb/>there exists a unique ξ  0  ∈ H(a) such that l = a(−ξ  0  , ·). In other words <lb/> M <lb/> ( <lb/> D) <lb/>  *  <lb/> D(f Aσ + ξ  0  ), ψ <lb/> γ <lb/> = 0. <lb/>Since <lb/> D <lb/>  *  = <lb/> D + in, we have in the distributional sense ( <lb/> D + in) <lb/> Dξ = 0, where we <lb/>have set ξ = f Aσ + ξ  0  . By an elliptic regularity argument, <lb/> Dξ is in fact smooth <lb/>and ( <lb/> D) <lb/> k  ξ are L <lb/> 2  , for every k ∈ N. It follows <lb/> M <lb/> ( <lb/> D) <lb/> 2  ξ, ( <lb/> D) <lb/> 2  ξ <lb/> γ <lb/> = <lb/> M <lb/> ( <lb/> D + in)( <lb/> D) <lb/> 2  ξ, <lb/> Dξ <lb/> γ <lb/> = <lb/> M <lb/> D( <lb/> D + in) <lb/> Dξ, <lb/> Dξ <lb/> γ <lb/> = 0, <lb/>that implies ( <lb/> D) <lb/> 2  ξ = 0, but we already know that ( <lb/> D + in) <lb/> Dξ = 0, and thereby <lb/> Dξ = 0. We now apply our integration formula to ξ <lb/> H(V  σ  , α  σ  ) = lim <lb/> r→+∞ <lb/> Sr <lb/> ∇  Aνr  ξ + Aν  r  · <lb/> Dξ, ξ <lb/> γ <lb/> = 4 <lb/> M <lb/> ∇ξ <lb/> 2 <lb/> γ <lb/> + <lb/> Rξ, ξ <lb/> γ <lb/> − 4 <lb/> M <lb/> Dξ <lb/> 2 <lb/> γ <lb/> = 4 <lb/> M <lb/> ∇ξ <lb/> 2 <lb/> γ <lb/> + <lb/> Rξ, ξ <lb/> γ <lb/> ≥ 0, <lb/>and the proof is complete. <lb/></body>

			<page> 994 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> D. Maerten <lb/>Ann. Henri Poincaré <lb/></note>

			<body> 3.2.2. The non-empty boundary case. We will consider, in this section, a Riemann-<lb/>ian slice M that has a non-empty inner compact boundary ∂M . ˘ <lb/> g, <lb/> ∇, ˘ <lb/> k will denote <lb/>respectively the induced metric, the connection and the second fundamental form <lb/>which is defined by <lb/> ∇  X  Y = <lb/> ∇X Y − ˘ <lb/> k(X, Y )ν <lb/> ∇  X  ψ = <lb/> ∇X ψ − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>˘ <lb/> k(X) · ν · ψ, <lb/> where ν is the normal to ∂M pointing toward infinity (that is to say pointing <lb/>inside), and · still denotes the Clifford action with respect to the metric γ. Conse-<lb/>quently our integration formula has another boundary term <lb/> Mr <lb/> Dψ <lb/> 2 <lb/> γ <lb/> = <lb/> Mr <lb/> ∇ψ <lb/> 2 <lb/> γ <lb/> + <lb/> Rψ, ψ <lb/> γ <lb/> − <lb/> Sr <lb/> ∇  Aνr  ψ + Aν  r  · <lb/> Dψ, ψ <lb/> γ <lb/> + <lb/> ∂M <lb/> ∇  ν  ψ + ν · <lb/> Dψ, ψ <lb/> γ <lb/> . <lb/> But if ψ is a compactly supported smooth spinor field then, making r → ∞ one <lb/>finds <lb/> M <lb/> Dψ <lb/> 2 <lb/> γ <lb/> = <lb/> M <lb/> ∇ψ <lb/> 2 <lb/> γ <lb/> + <lb/> Rψ, ψ <lb/> γ <lb/> + <lb/> ∂M <lb/> ∇  ν  ψ + ν · <lb/> Dψ, ψ <lb/> γ <lb/> . <lb/> We then have to estimate the boundary integrand <lb/> ∇  ν  ψ + ν · <lb/> Dψ, ψ <lb/> . <lb/> Lemma 3.6. If (ν = e  1  , e  2  , . . . , e  n  ) is a local orthonormal frame of T M  |∂M  then <lb/> ∇  ν  ψ + ν · <lb/> Dψ = ν · <lb/> n <lb/> k=2 <lb/> ∇  e  k  ψ . <lb/> Proof. Just remark that <lb/> ∇  ν  ψ = −e  1  · e  1  · <lb/> ∇  e1  ψ. <lb/> Lemma 3.7. Keeping our orthonormal frame (ν = e  1  , e  2  , . . . , e  n  ), we have <lb/> ∇  ν  ψ + ν · <lb/> Dψ = <lb/> n <lb/> k=2 <lb/> ν · e  k  · <lb/> ∇e  k  ψ + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> − tr ˘ <lb/> k − (n − 1)iν + (tr k)ν · e  0  − k(ν) · e  0 <lb/> · ψ . <lb/> Proof. Using the formula above, we then express <lb/> ∇ in term of the (n − 1)-dimen-<lb/>sional connection and second form, and the n-dimensional second form. <lb/> Let us define F ∈ End(Σ  |∂M  ) by F (ψ) = iν · ψ. We sum up some basic properties <lb/>of F in the following <lb/> Proposition 3.8. The endomorphism F is symmetric, isometric with respect to ·, ··, <lb/> commutes to the action of ν· and anticommutes to each e  k  ·, (k  = 1). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vol. 7 (2006) <lb/>Positive Energy Theorem <lb/></note>

			<page>995 <lb/></page>

			<body> Lemma 3.9. If F (ψ) = −ψ then <lb/> ∇  ν  ψ + ν · <lb/> Dψ, ψ <lb/> |∂M <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> e  0  · <lb/> (− tr ˘ <lb/> k + (n − 1))e  0  + k(ν) <lb/> · ψ, ψ <lb/> . <lb/> Proof. Using the proposition above we know that ν · e  k  (k  = 1) anticommutes <lb/>with F and the formula follows since F respects ·, ··. <lb/> Assumption. Let us suppose that the 4-vector k := (− tr ˘ <lb/> k + (n − 1))e  0  + k(ν) is <lb/>causal and positively oriented, that is to say γ( k, k) ≤ 0 and tr ˘ <lb/> k ≤ (n − 1). <lb/>This assumption (which is exactly the same as for <lb/> R) guarantees the non-negativity <lb/>of the boundary integrand term <lb/> ∇  ν  ψ + ν · <lb/> Dψ, ψ <lb/> |∂M <lb/> = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> e  0  · k · ψ, ψ <lb/> , when-<lb/>ever the boundary condition F (ψ) = −ψ is satisfied. Although this assumption is <lb/>vectorial, it clearly extends the one given in [15]. <lb/>Let us define H  −  (a) = {ψ ∈ H(a) | F (ψ) = −ψ} where H(a) has been defined <lb/>in Section 3.6.1. Still taking ψ a compactly supported smooth spinor field in H  −  (a), <lb/>we have <lb/> a(ψ, ψ) = <lb/> M <lb/> ∇ψ <lb/> 2 <lb/> γ <lb/> + <lb/> Rψ, ψ <lb/> γ <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ∂M <lb/> e  0  · k · ψ, ψ <lb/> , <lb/> whose each single term is non-negative tanks to our assumption. <lb/>We consider the linear form l on H  −  (a) defined by <lb/> l(ψ) = <lb/> M <lb/> D(f Aσ), <lb/> Dψ <lb/> γ <lb/> dμ  g  . <lb/> It still is a continuous linear form on the Hilbert space H  −  (a) (it is complete since <lb/>the condition F (ψ) = −ψ is closed) and applying again Lax-Milgram theorem we <lb/>get the existence of a unique ξ  0  ∈ H(a) such that l = a(−ξ  0  , ·). In other words <lb/> ∀ψ ∈ H  −  (a) <lb/> M <lb/> χ, <lb/> Dψ <lb/> = 0, <lb/>where we have set ξ = f Aσ + ξ  0  and χ = <lb/> Dξ. <lb/> For any ψ ∈ C <lb/> 1 <lb/>0  we have <lb/> M <lb/> χ, <lb/> Dψ <lb/> = 0 = <lb/> M <lb/> D <lb/>  *  χ, ψ <lb/> + <lb/> ∂M <lb/> ν · χ, ψ . <lb/> But remembering that C <lb/> ∞ <lb/> 0  (M \ ∂M ) the space of smooth spinor fields compactly <lb/>supported in M \ ∂M is dense in L <lb/> 2  (M ) then we obtain that <lb/> D <lb/>  *  χ = 0 and χ ∈ <lb/> H  +  (a) = {ψ ∈ H(a) | F (ψ) = +ψ}. By ellipticity χ is smooth and <lb/> D <lb/> k  χ ∈ L <lb/> 2  (M ) <lb/></body>

			<page> 996 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> D. Maerten <lb/>Ann. Henri Poincaré <lb/></note>

			<body> for every k ∈ N. Finally we notice that <lb/> M <lb/> Dχ <lb/> 2 <lb/> = <lb/> M <lb/> D <lb/>  *  <lb/> Dχ, χ <lb/> + <lb/> ∂M <lb/> ν · <lb/> Dχ, χ <lb/> = 0 + <lb/> ∂M <lb/> −inν · χ, χ <lb/> = −n <lb/> ∂M <lb/> |χ| <lb/> 2  , <lb/> and therefore <lb/> Dχ = 0 which implies that χ = 0. We can conclude with the <lb/> Proposition 3.10. For every σ ∈ IKS (Σ) there exists a unique ξ  0  ∈ H  −  (a) such <lb/>that ξ = f Aσ + ξ  0  ∈ Ker <lb/> D ∩ H  −  (a) and <lb/> H(V  σ  , α  σ  ) = lim <lb/> r→+∞ <lb/> Sr <lb/> ∇  Aνr  ξ + Aν  r  · <lb/> Dξ, ξ <lb/> γ <lb/> = 4 <lb/> M <lb/> ∇ξ <lb/> 2 <lb/> γ <lb/> + <lb/> Rξ, ξ <lb/> γ <lb/> + 2 <lb/> ∂M <lb/> e  0  · k · ψ, ψ <lb/> ≥ 0. <lb/> 3.3. Imaginary Killing spinors <lb/> In general (that is to say whatever the dimension), the spinor bundle under con-<lb/>sideration is Σ = Spin  0  (n, 1)/ Spin(n)×  ρ  C <lb/> d  for a certain spinorial representation ρ <lb/> and some integer d depending upon n + 1. It is known that Σ is trivialized by the <lb/>space of imaginary Killing spinors of AdS <lb/> n,1  along H <lb/> n  (cf. [14] for instance). Now <lb/>consider some σ ∈ IKS (Σ), and define the function V  σ  = σ, σ and the real 1-form <lb/> α  σ  (X) = X · e  0  · σ, σ. We can easily compute the first derivative of α  σ <lb/> D  X  α  σ  (Y ) = <lb/> i <lb/> 2 <lb/> (X · Y − Y · X) · e  0  · σ, σ , <lb/> which is a real skew symmetric 2-form and hence α  σ  is a Killing form on H <lb/> n  . <lb/>Furthermore, it is clear that V  σ  ∈ N  b  ∼ = R <lb/> n,1  [15]. By this way, we merely define a <lb/>quadratic application <lb/> IKS (Σ) <lb/> / / R <lb/> n,1 <lb/> ⊕ so(n, 1) . <lb/> Now the complex isomorphism C <lb/> d <lb/> ∼  / / IKS (Σ) is quite difficult to explicit (it <lb/>may be possible by the means of harmonic analysis, and it will be the aim of a <lb/>future paper) because of the non-explicit character of the Clifford action when the <lb/>dimension is arbitrary. However we have a formal Hermitian quadratic application <lb/> K : C <lb/> d <lb/> / / IKS (Σ) <lb/> / / R <lb/> n,1 <lb/> ⊕ so(n, 1) , <lb/> that we will explicit when the dimension of the slice is n = 3 (because of exceptional <lb/>isomorphisms of Lie groups). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vol. 7 (2006) <lb/>Positive Energy Theorem <lb/></note>

			<page> 997 <lb/></page>

			<body> The 3-dimensional case <lb/> The aim of this section is to solve explicitly the Killing equation of Section 2.2. <lb/>As a matter of fact, representation theory provides us good candidates for the <lb/>imaginary Killing spinors. Thanks to Schur&apos;s lemma, we have an isomorphism <lb/> C <lb/> 2 <lb/> −→ Hom <lb/> SU(2)  (C <lb/> 2  , C <lb/> 2 <lb/> ⊕ C <lb/> 2  ) <lb/>  z1 <lb/> z2 <lb/>  −→ <lb/>  z1I2 <lb/>z2I2 <lb/> . <lb/> We are now considering two families of spinors which are derived from represen-<lb/>tation theory. To this end, we will denote w ⊗ z ∈ C <lb/> 2 <lb/> ⊗ Hom <lb/> SU(2)  (C <lb/> 2  , C <lb/> 2 <lb/> ⊕ C <lb/> 2  ) <lb/>thanks to the isomorphism above. <lb/> Definition 3.11. Let w ⊗ z ∈ C <lb/> 2 <lb/> ⊗ C <lb/> 2  and set σ <lb/> −1 <lb/> w⊗z  [˜ g] = <lb/> ˜ <lb/> g, z(˜ g <lb/> −1  w) <lb/> , σ <lb/>  * <lb/> w⊗z  [˜ g] = <lb/> {˜ , z(˜ g <lb/>  *  w)}. <lb/> Let us consider a spinor field τ ∈ Γ(Σ) and a vector field X ∈ Γ(T) tangent to H <lb/> 3  . <lb/>We can write τ [˜ g] = {˜ , v(˜ g)} and X[g] = {g, ζ(g)}, where v : H <lb/> 3 <lb/> −→ C <lb/> 4  and <lb/> ζ : H <lb/> 3 <lb/> −→ G are respectively SO(3) and SU(2)-equivariant functions. We can now <lb/>differentiate τ in the direction of X and write down <lb/>(D  X  τ )[˜ g] = {˜ , v  *  (X)  [˜ g]  + ˜ <lb/> ρ  *  • s <lb/>  *  θ(ζ)  [˜ g]  v[˜ g]}, <lb/> where θ is the connection 1-form of the bundle of SL(2, C)-frames, restricted to H <lb/> 3  . <lb/>If one remembers that θ is only the projection on the first factor in the decompo-<lb/>sition sl  2  (C) ∼ = su(2) ⊕ G, we can conclude that <lb/>   *  • s <lb/>  *  θ(ζ)  [˜ g]  v[˜ g] vanishes. Besides <lb/>we will apply this formula to spinors in <lb/> σ <lb/> −1 <lb/> w⊗z  , σ <lb/>  * <lb/> u⊗z  , w, u ∈ C <lb/> 2 <lb/> so that we can <lb/>only derive at the point <lb/>  = 1 unity in SL(2, C) since we have the <lb/> Proposition 3.12. The set <lb/> σ <lb/> −1 <lb/> w⊗z  , σ <lb/>  * <lb/> u⊗z  , w, u ∈ C <lb/> 2 <lb/> is stable under the SL(2, C) <lb/> action. More precisely for every  <lb/>  ∈ SL(2, C) we have  <lb/>  *  σ <lb/> −1 <lb/> w⊗z  = σ <lb/> −1 <lb/> w⊗z  and <lb/>  *  σ <lb/>  * <lb/> u⊗z  = σ <lb/>  * <lb/> (˜ e  *  )  −1  u⊗z  . <lb/> We obtain <lb/> (D  X  σ <lb/> −1 <lb/> w⊗z  )[1] = {1, −z(ζw)} <lb/> (D  X  σ <lb/>  * <lb/> u⊗z  )[1] = {1, z(ζu)} , <lb/> where ζ = ζ(1). We also compute the Clifford action of X on σ <lb/> −1 <lb/> w⊗z  , σ <lb/>  * <lb/> u⊗z  at the <lb/>point 1: <lb/> X · σ <lb/> −1 <lb/> w⊗z  [1] = {1, Θ(ζ)z(w)} <lb/> X · σ <lb/>  * <lb/> u⊗z  [1] = {1, Θ(ζ)z(u)} . <lb/> We must precise Θ  |G  : ζ −→ <lb/> 0 <lb/>2ζ <lb/> −2ζ 0 <lb/> , and if we introduce the sections σ <lb/> −1 <lb/> w⊗( <lb/> 1 <lb/> −i  ) <lb/>and σ <lb/>  * <lb/> w⊗( <lb/> 1 <lb/> i  ) <lb/>, for any w ∈ C <lb/> 2  , we have on one hand <lb/> ⎧ <lb/>⎨ <lb/>⎩ <lb/> − <lb/> i <lb/> 2  X · σ <lb/> −1 <lb/> w⊗( <lb/> 1 <lb/> −i  ) <lb/>[1] = −i {1, −iζw ⊕ −ζw} = {1, −ζw ⊕ iζw} <lb/> − <lb/> i <lb/> 2  X · σ <lb/>  * <lb/> u⊗( <lb/> 1 <lb/> i  ) <lb/>[1] = −i {1, iζu ⊕ −ζu} = {1, ζu ⊕ iζu} , <lb/></body>

			<page> 998 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> D. Maerten <lb/>Ann. Henri Poincaré <lb/></note>

			<body> and on the other hand <lb/> ⎧ <lb/> ⎪ ⎪ ⎨ <lb/>⎪ ⎪ ⎩ <lb/> D  X  σ <lb/> −1 <lb/> w⊗( <lb/> 1 <lb/> −i  ) <lb/> [1] = {1, −ζw ⊕ iζw} <lb/> D  X  σ <lb/>  * <lb/> u⊗( <lb/> 1 <lb/> i  ) <lb/> [1] = {1, ζu ⊕ iζu} . <lb/> Since <lb/> σ <lb/> −1 <lb/> w⊗( <lb/> 1 <lb/> −i  ) <lb/>+ σ <lb/>  * <lb/> u⊗( <lb/> 1 <lb/> i  ) <lb/> w, u ∈ C <lb/> 2 <lb/> is a 4-dimensional complex vector space, <lb/>we obviously obtain the <lb/> Proposition 3.13. The space of imaginary Killing spinors denoted by IKS (Σ) is <lb/>generated by <lb/> σ <lb/> −1 <lb/> w⊗( <lb/> 1 <lb/> −i  ) <lb/> , σ <lb/>  * <lb/> u⊗( <lb/> 1 <lb/> i  ) , w, u ∈ C <lb/> 2 <lb/> . <lb/> Let σ an imaginary Killing spinor and set V  σ  := &lt;σ, σ&gt; which is a function on H <lb/> 3  , <lb/>and if e  0  denotes a unit normal of H <lb/> 3  in AdS, we set α  σ  (Y ) := Y · e  0  · σ, σ which <lb/>is a real 1-form on H <lb/> 3  . The goal of the two next paragraphs is to define some <lb/>SL(2, C)-equivariant application <lb/> K : IKS (Σ) ∼ = C <lb/> 2 <lb/> ⊕ C <lb/> 2 <lb/> −→ (M ⊕ sl  2  (C)) <lb/>  * R <lb/> w ⊕ u −→ K  w⊕u  := (V  w⊕u  ⊕ α  w⊕u  ) . <lb/> The functions V  σ  when n = 3 <lb/> We compute the functions V  σ  which are by definition <lb/> V  σ  [˜ g] = <lb/> σ <lb/> −1 <lb/> w⊗( <lb/> 1 <lb/> −i  ) <lb/>[˜ g] <lb/> 2 <lb/> C  4 <lb/> + <lb/> σ <lb/>  * <lb/> u⊗( <lb/> 1 <lb/> i  ) <lb/>[˜ g] <lb/> 2 <lb/> C  4 <lb/> + 2e <lb/> σ <lb/> −1 <lb/> w⊗( <lb/> 1 <lb/> −i  ) <lb/>[˜ g], σ <lb/>  * <lb/> u⊗( <lb/> 1 <lb/> i  ) <lb/>[˜ g] <lb/> C  4 <lb/> = 2 <lb/> ˜ <lb/> g <lb/> −1  w <lb/> 2 <lb/> C  2  + 2 |˜  <lb/>  *  u| <lb/> 2 <lb/> C  2  . <lb/> Remark 3.14. σ <lb/> −1 <lb/> w⊗( <lb/> 1 <lb/> −i  ) <lb/> and σ <lb/>  * <lb/> u⊗( <lb/> 1 <lb/> i  ) <lb/> are orthogonal spinors for every u, w ∈ C <lb/> 2  . <lb/> If <lb/>  ∈ SL(2, C), the corresponding base point is <lb/> ˜ <lb/>  * <lb/> ∈ H <lb/> 3 <lb/> ⊂ M ∼ = R <lb/> 3,1  whose <lb/>coordinates are given by (x  k  ) <lb/> 3 <lb/> k=0  = Λ <lb/> −1  (˜ g˜ <lb/>  *  ). <lb/> Proposition 3.15. V  σ  is a causal element of N  b  . <lb/>Proof. Let U = <lb/>  u1 <lb/> −w2 <lb/>  ∈ C <lb/> 2  , V = <lb/>  u2 <lb/>w1 <lb/>  ∈ C <lb/> 2  . We notice that <lb/> V  σ  [˜ g] = x  0  (|U | <lb/> 2  + |V | <lb/> 2  ) + x  1  (|U | <lb/> 2 <lb/> − |V | <lb/> 2  ) + 2x  2  e(&lt;U, V &gt;) − 2x  3  m(&lt;U, V &gt;), <lb/> so that the norm of V  σ  is |V  σ  [˜ g]| <lb/> 2  = 4 <lb/> |&lt;U, V &gt;| <lb/> 2 <lb/> − |U | <lb/> 2 <lb/> |V | <lb/> 2 <lb/>  ≤ 0, thanks to the <lb/>Cauchy-Schwarz inequality for the standard Hermitian form on C <lb/> 2  . <lb/> More conceptually we see that V  σ  [˜ g] = 2(w <lb/>  *  <lb/> W w + u <lb/>  *  W u), where we have set <lb/> W := ˜ <lb/> g˜ <lb/>  * <lb/> ∈ H <lb/> 3 <lb/> ⊂ M. Thereby we can define by extension an application <lb/> C <lb/> 2 <lb/> ⊕ C <lb/> 2 <lb/> −→ M <lb/>  * <lb/> w ⊕ u −→ <lb/> V  w⊕u  : W → 2(w <lb/>  *  <lb/> W w + u <lb/>  *  W u) <lb/> . <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vol. 7 (2006) <lb/>Positive Energy Theorem <lb/></note>

			<page> 999 <lb/></page>

			<body> The 1-forms α  σ  when n = 3 <lb/> The positively oriented unit normal of H <lb/> 3  in AdS is given by e  0  [˜ g] = <lb/> ˜ <lb/> g, <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  μ(˜ g)I  2 <lb/> and for any ξ ∈ G satisfying − det ξ = 1 we set X <lb/> ξ  [˜ g] = <lb/> ˜ <lb/> g, <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  μ(˜ g)ξ <lb/> . Just remem-<lb/>ber that α  σ  (X <lb/> ξ  )  [˜ g]  := <lb/> X <lb/> ξ <lb/> · e  0  · σ, σ <lb/> [˜ g] <lb/> . As we suppose that σ ∈ IKS (Σ), we can <lb/>easily compute the first derivative of α  σ <lb/> D  X  η  α  σ  (X <lb/> ξ  )  [˜ g]  = <lb/> i <lb/> 2 <lb/> (X <lb/> η <lb/> · X <lb/> ξ <lb/> − X <lb/> ξ <lb/> · X <lb/> η  ) · e  0  · σ, σ <lb/> [˜ g] <lb/> , <lb/> which is a real skew symmetric 2-form and hence α  σ  is a Killing form on H <lb/> 3  . From <lb/>now on we set α  σ  = (α  σ  )  1  and Dα  σ  = (Dα  σ  )  1  , that we will write as function of <lb/> w ⊕ u. After some computations we find <lb/> α  σ  (ξ) <lb/>=2(w <lb/>  *  ξu + u <lb/>  *  ξw) <lb/>Dα  σ  (η, ξ) = (w <lb/>  *  (ξη − ηξ)u − u <lb/>  *  (ξη − ηξ)w) . <lb/> We have to notice that ξη − ηξ ∈ iG so that Dα  σ  is naturally a linear form <lb/>on iG. As a consequence we define, thanks to the Killing 1-form α  σ  , the following <lb/>application <lb/> C <lb/> 2 <lb/> ⊕ C <lb/> 2 <lb/> −→ sl  2  (C) <lb/>  * R <lb/> w ⊕ u −→ (α  w⊕u  : ξ → 2(w <lb/>  *  ξu + u <lb/>  *  ξ <lb/>  *  w)) , <lb/> where <lb/>  * R  stands for the duality with respect to the reals. We then define <lb/> K  w⊕u  = V  w⊕u  ⊕ α  w⊕u <lb/> and conclude with the <lb/> Proposition 3.16. The application K is SL(2, C)-equivariant. More precisely, for <lb/>every  <lb/>  ∈ SL(2, C) <lb/> K  ˜ <lb/> e * (w⊕u)  = <lb/> V  w⊕u  • μ(˜ e <lb/> −1  ) <lb/> ⊕ (α  w⊕u  • Ad(˜ e <lb/>  *  )) . <lb/> Proof. We must compute for every W ∈ M and ξ ∈ sl  2  (C) <lb/> K  ˜ <lb/> e * (w⊕u)  (W, ξ) = K  ˜ <lb/> ew⊕(˜ e  *  )  −1  u  (W, ξ) <lb/> = 2(w <lb/>  *  ˜ <lb/> e <lb/>  *  <lb/> W ˜ <lb/> ew + u <lb/>  *  ˜ <lb/> e <lb/> −1  W (˜ e <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> −1  u + w <lb/>  *  ˜ <lb/> e <lb/>  *  ξ(˜ e <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> −1  u + u <lb/>  *  ˜ <lb/> e <lb/> −1  ξ <lb/>  *  ˜ <lb/> ew) <lb/> = V  w⊕u  • μ(˜ e <lb/> −1  )(W ) ⊕ α  w⊕u  • Ad(˜ e <lb/>  *  )(ξ). <lb/> Remark 3.17 (The norm of imaginary Killing spinors). Classical considerations <lb/>on Lie algebras show that so(3, 2) endowed with its Killing form, is isometric to <lb/> (M, − det) ⊕ (sl  2  (C), −−e(det)) which is a 10-dimensional real vector space of <lb/>signature (6,4). The norm of K(w ⊕ u) with respect to the Killing form is, up to a <lb/>multiplicative and positive constant |K(w ⊕ u)| <lb/> 2  = |&lt;U, V &gt;| <lb/> 2 <lb/> − |U | <lb/> 2 <lb/> |V | <lb/> 2  + e(χ <lb/> 2  ), <lb/> where we have set χ = u  1  w  1  + u  2  w  2  . Besides, if V  w⊕u  is isotropic in M then α  w⊕u <lb/> and K(w ⊕ u) are also isotropic respectively in sl  2  (C) <lb/>  *  and (M ⊕ sl  2  (C)) <lb/>  *  . Indeed <lb/>the equality case in the Cauchy-Schwarz inequality occurs if and only if U and V <lb/> satisfy det  C  2  (U, V ) = ¯ <lb/> χ = 0. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1000 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> D. Maerten <lb/>Ann. Henri Poincaré <lb/></note>

			<body> 3.4. End of the proof <lb/> Whatever the dimension is, we obtain a Hermitian quadratic application <lb/> Q : C <lb/> d <lb/> K  / / R <lb/> n,1 <lb/> ⊕ so(n, 1) <lb/> H  / / R , <lb/> which has to be non-negative in vertue of the non-negativity results of Sections <lb/>3.2.1 and 3.2.2. This completes the proof of the first part of the (positivity) Theo-<lb/>rem 1.3. It is also important to notice that in the zero extrinsic curvature case, that <lb/>is k ≡ 0, then H(f, α) = H(f, 0) which is merely the hyperbolic mass functional, <lb/>and thereby we recover the result of [15]. <lb/>In dimension n = 3, we can be more specific giving the explicit formula of Q <lb/> in terms of the components of the energy-momentum H. More precisely, on one <lb/>hand we have found a quadratic application <lb/> K : IKS (Σ) ∼ = C <lb/> 2 <lb/> ⊕ C <lb/> 2 <lb/> −→ (M ⊕ sl  2  (C)) <lb/>  * R  ∼ = Ker dΦ <lb/>  * <lb/> (b,0) <lb/> w ⊕ u −→ (V  w⊕u  ⊕ α  w⊕u  ) , <lb/> which is SL(2, C)-equivariant. On the other hand we know that the energy-momen-<lb/>tum functional H can be seen as a real linear form on (M ⊕ sl  2  (C)) <lb/>  * R  that is to say, <lb/>as a vector H = M ⊕ Ξ ∈ M ⊕ sl  2  (C). In the following, we will adopt the notations <lb/>Ξ = N ⊕ iR ∈ G ⊕ iG, and M = Λ(m  0  , m), N = Λ(0, n), R = Λ(0, r), where Λ is <lb/>the isomorphism defined in Section 2.4. Now applying the non-negativity results <lb/>of Section 3.2.1 or 3.2.2, we know that (even if our AdS-asymptotically hyperbolic <lb/>manifold has a compact boundary such that k is causal and positively oriented) <lb/> ∀σ ∈ IKS (Σ) H(V  σ  , α  σ  ) ≥ 0. <lb/>In other words, for each w ⊕ u ∈ C <lb/> 4  , we have H(K  w⊕u  ) ≥ 0. But the complete <lb/>study of IKS (Σ) of Section 3.3 implies that actually <lb/> H(K  w⊕u  ) = V  w⊕u  (M ) + α  w⊕u  (Ξ) <lb/>= 2(w <lb/>  *  <lb/> Mw + u <lb/>  *  Mu) + 2(w <lb/>  *  Ξu + u <lb/>  *  Ξ <lb/>  *  w), <lb/> and consequently the application w ⊕ u −→ H(K  w⊕u  ) is a Hermitian form on <lb/> C <lb/> 2 <lb/> ⊕ C <lb/> 2  whose matrix is <lb/> Q = 2 <lb/> M Ξ <lb/>Ξ <lb/>  * <lb/> M <lb/> = 2 <lb/> Λ(m  0  , −m) <lb/> Λ(0, n) + iΛ(0, r) <lb/> Λ(0, n) − iΛ(0, r) <lb/> Λ(m  0  , m) <lb/> . <lb/> It is easy to conclude since we have the identity <lb/> ∀w ⊕ u ∈ C <lb/> 4 <lb/> H(V  w⊕u  ⊕ α  w⊕u  ) = Q(w ⊕ u, w ⊕ u) ≥ 0, <lb/>which ends the proof of <lb/> Theorem 1.3 Let (M <lb/> n  , g, k) be an AdS-asymptotically hyperbolic spin Riemannian <lb/>manifold satisfying the decay conditions stated in Section 1.2 and the following <lb/>conditions <lb/> (i) (f, α), (Φ(g, k) − Φ(b, 0)) ∈ L <lb/> 1  (M, dVol  b  ) for every (f, α) ∈ N  b  ⊕ Kill(M, b), <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vol. 7 (2006) <lb/>Positive Energy Theorem <lb/></note>

			<page>1001 <lb/></page>

			<body> (ii) the relative version of the dominant energy condition (cf. Section 2.2) holds, <lb/>that is to say (Φ(g, k) − Φ(b, 0)) is a positively oriented causal (n + 1)-vector <lb/> along M , <lb/>(iii) in the case where M has a compact boundary ∂M , we assume moreover that <lb/> k is causal and positively oriented along ∂M . <lb/> Then there exists a (hardly explicitable) map R <lb/> n,1 <lb/> ⊕ so(n, 1) −→ Herm(C <lb/> d  ) which <lb/>sends, under the assumptions (i)–(iii), the energy-momentum on a non-negative <lb/>Hermitian form Q. <lb/>Moreover, when n = 3, we can explicit Q in terms of the components of the <lb/>energy-momentum as described above. <lb/> The end of this section is devoted to the 3-dimensional case. <lb/>As the invariance of the energy-momentum under asymptotic hyperbolic <lb/>isometries was proved in [19], one can be interested in the description of the orbit <lb/>of Q under the action of SL(2, C). <lb/> Proposition 3.18. If M is timelike, there exists a (non-unique) representative el-<lb/>ement of the orbit of H = M ⊕ Ξ under the natural action (cf. Section 3.3) of <lb/> SL(2, C) on M ⊕ sl  2  (C) which can be written <lb/> m  0 <lb/> 1 0 <lb/>0 1 <lb/> ⊕ n  1 <lb/> 1 0 <lb/>0 −1 <lb/> ⊕ i <lb/> r  1  r  2 <lb/> r  2  −r  1 <lb/> , m  0  , n  1  , r  1  , r  2  ∈ R. <lb/> The positive energy-momentum theorem then reduces to m  0  ≥ <lb/> (|n  1  | + |r  2  |)  2  + r  2 <lb/>1  . <lb/>Proof. Let us suppose that M ∈ M is timelike. Thus considering the action of <lb/>SL(2, C) on M ⊕ sl  2  (C) (cf. Section 3.3), then there exists an element in the orbit <lb/>of H that can be written m  0 <lb/> 1 0 <lb/>0 1 <lb/> ⊕ Ξ <lb/>  . Since the isotropy group of <lb/> 1 0 <lb/>0 1 <lb/> is <lb/>SU(2) whose action on G is transitive, then there exists an element in the orbit <lb/>of H that can be written m  0 <lb/> 1 0 <lb/>0 1 <lb/> ⊕ n  1 <lb/> 1 0 <lb/>0 −1 <lb/> ⊕ iR <lb/>  . But the isotropy group <lb/>of <lb/> 1 0 <lb/>0 −1 <lb/> is the one parameter group <lb/> e <lb/> iθ <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 e <lb/> −iθ <lb/> , θ ∈ R <lb/> . Finally there ex-<lb/>ists an element (not unique since the isotropy group of <lb/> 0 1 <lb/>1 0 <lb/> is isomorphic <lb/>to Z  2  ) in the orbit of H that can be written as announced in the proposition. The <lb/>corresponding Hermitian matrix is <lb/> Q = 2 <lb/> ⎛ <lb/>⎜ <lb/>⎜ <lb/>⎝ <lb/> m  0 <lb/> 0 <lb/> n  1  + ir  1 <lb/> ir  2 <lb/> 0 <lb/> m  0 <lb/> ir  2 <lb/> −n  1  − ir  1 <lb/> n  1  − ir  1 <lb/> −ir  2 <lb/> m  0 <lb/> 0 <lb/> −ir  2 <lb/> −n  1  + ir  1 <lb/> 0 <lb/> m  0 <lb/> ⎞ <lb/>⎟ <lb/>⎟ <lb/>⎠ . <lb/></body>

			<page> 1002 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> D. Maerten <lb/>Ann. Henri Poincaré <lb/></note>

			<body> Since Q is non negative we have <lb/> m  0  ≥ 0 <lb/> m  0  (m <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  − (n <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + r <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + r <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  )) ≥ 0 <lb/>(m <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  − (n <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + r <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + r <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  )) <lb/> 2 <lb/> ≥ 4(n  1  r  2  ) <lb/> 2  , <lb/> which can be summarized with m  0  ≥ <lb/> (|n  1  | + |r  2  |)  2  + r  2 <lb/>1  . <lb/> Remark 3.19. The {t = t  0  } slices of the Kerr-AdS metrics are AdS-asymptotically <lb/>hyperbolic and parametrized by 2 real parameters: the mass and the angular mo-<lb/>mentum. The proposition above then shows that there exists some energy-momenta <lb/>that could not be obtained by the action of SL(2, C) on a Kerr-AdS solution. As <lb/>a consequence, an interesting question would be to find some (new ) AdS-asymp-<lb/>totically hyperbolic metrics which have an energy-momentum of the form given in <lb/>the proposition above with non-zero coefficients m  0  , n  1  , r  1  , r  2  , and which satisfy the <lb/>dominant energy condition or the (stronger ) cosmological vacuum constraints. <lb/> 4. Rigidity theorems <lb/> Theorem 1.4 Under the assumptions of the positive energy-momentum theorem, <lb/> Q = 0 implies that (M, g, k) is isometrically embeddable in AdS <lb/> n,1  . <lb/> Proof. The vanishing of Q implies that our spinor bundle Σ is trivialized by a basis <lb/>of γ-imaginary Killing spinors. We denote by ξ any γ-imaginary Killing spinors <lb/> of this basis. We will need the following spinorial Gauss-Codazzi equation. <lb/> Proposition 4.1. For every X, Y ∈ Γ(T M) we have <lb/> R <lb/> γ <lb/>X,Y  = R <lb/> g <lb/>X,Y  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> d <lb/> ∇  k(X, Y ) · e  0  + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> k(X) · k(Y ) − k(Y ) · k(X) <lb/> · , <lb/> where · denotes the Clifford action with respect to the metric γ. <lb/> Proof of the proposition. It is a straightforward computation where we use vector <lb/>fields X, Y satisfying at the point ∇  X  Y = ∇  Y  X = 0. <lb/> ∇  X  ∇  Y  = ∇  X <lb/> ∇  Y  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> k(Y ) · e  0  · <lb/> = ∇  X  ∇  Y  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> k(X) · e  0  · ∇  Y <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(∇  X  k(Y ) · e  0  · +k(Y ) · (∇  X  e  0  ) · +k(Y ) · e  0  · ∇  X  ) <lb/>= ∇  X  ∇  Y  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> k(X) · e  0  · ∇  Y  + k(Y ) · e  0  · ∇  X  − k • k(X, Y )e  0  · <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ∇  X  k(Y ) · e  0  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>4 <lb/> k(Y ) · k(X) <lb/> · , <lb/> and the curvature formula above follows. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vol. 7 (2006) <lb/>Positive Energy Theorem <lb/></note>

			<page> 1003 <lb/></page>

			<body> Using the fact that ξ is a γ-imaginary Killing spinor one gets <lb/> R <lb/> g <lb/> X,Y  ξ − <lb/> 1 <lb/>4 <lb/> X · Y − Y · X + k(X) · k(Y ) − k(Y ) · k(X) <lb/> · ξ, ξ <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> d <lb/> ∇  k(X, Y ) · e  0  · ξ, ξ <lb/> , <lb/> where <lb/> R <lb/> g <lb/>X,Y  ξ, ξ <lb/> and <lb/> X · Y − Y · X + k(X) · k(Y ) − k(Y ) · k(X) <lb/> · ξ, ξ <lb/> are <lb/>purely imaginary terms whereas <lb/> d <lb/> ∇  k(X, Y ) · e  0  · ξ, ξ <lb/> is real. As a consequence <lb/> d <lb/> ∇  k(X, Y ) · e  0  · ξ, ξ <lb/> = 0 for any ξ of our γ-imaginary Killing spinor basis and <lb/>so d <lb/> ∇  k = 0. This implies <lb/> R <lb/> g <lb/>X,Y  = <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/> X · Y − Y · X + k(X) · k(Y ) − k(Y ) · k(X) <lb/> · , <lb/> and using the natural isomorphism between C  0  (R <lb/> 3,1  ) and Λ <lb/> 2  (R <lb/> 3,1  ) (cf. [24] propo-<lb/>sition 6.2) we get that <lb/> R <lb/> g  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> g  g + k  k <lb/> d <lb/> ∇  k = 0. <lb/>Let us denote by V the function &lt;ξ, ξ&gt;, α the real 1-form defined by α(Y ) = <lb/> Y · e  0  · ξ, ξ. Then the couple (V, W ) := (V, −α <lb/>  ) is a Killing Initial Data (KID) <lb/>[10]. If we consider ( <lb/> M, ˜ <lb/> g, ˜ <lb/> k) the universal Riemannian covering of (M, g, k), <lb/> then we can make the Killing development of ( <lb/> M, ˜ <lb/> g, ˜ <lb/> k) with respect to the KID <lb/>( <lb/> V , <lb/> W ) which by definition is R × <lb/> M endowed with the Lorentzian metric <lb/>  = <lb/> − <lb/> V <lb/> 2  + | <lb/> W | <lb/> 2 <lb/> du <lb/> 2  +2 <lb/> W <lb/>  du + ˜ <lb/> g. By construction, <lb/> M is embedded in (R × <lb/> M, ˜ <lb/> γ) <lb/> with induced metric <lb/>  and second fundamental form <lb/> . Besides R × <lb/> M is the uni-<lb/>versal covering of N , and <lb/>  which has sectional curvature −1, is a stationary <lb/>solution of the vacuum Einstein equations with cosmological constant that is to <lb/>say G <lb/> ˜ <lb/> γ  = <lb/> n(n−1) <lb/> 2 <lb/> ˜ <lb/> γ. But ( <lb/> M, ˜ <lb/> g) is complete since (M, g) is complete and there-<lb/>fore [1] (R × <lb/> M, ˜ <lb/> γ) is geodesically complete. It follows that (R × <lb/> M, ˜ <lb/> γ) is AdS <lb/> n,1 <lb/> (in vertue of Proposition 23 [p. 227] of [27]). It only remains to show that M is <lb/>simply connected. We know that R × <lb/> M ∼ = R <lb/> n+1  and thereby using the following <lb/>compactly supported de Rham cohomology isomorphisms {0} = H <lb/> 2 <lb/> dR,c  (R × <lb/> M ) = <lb/> H <lb/> 2 <lb/> dR,c  (R <lb/> n+1  ) = H <lb/> 1 <lb/> dR,c  ( <lb/> M ) (cf. Proposition 4.7 and Corollary 4.7.1 [p. 39] of [12] <lb/>for instance), we obtain that <lb/> M has only one asymptotic end. This last fact com-<lb/>pels the universal covering map <lb/> M → M to be trivial and as a consequence <lb/>(M, g, k) ≡ ( <lb/> M, ˜ <lb/> g, ˜ <lb/> k) is isometrically embedded in AdS <lb/> n,1 <lb/> ≡ ( <lb/> N, ˜ <lb/> γ). This com-<lb/>pletes the proof of the theorem. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1004 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> D. Maerten <lb/>Ann. Henri Poincaré <lb/></note>

			<body> A natural and less restriction on Q is to assume that it is degenerate, and one can <lb/>wonder whether this implies rigidity. The end of this section is devoted to a study <lb/>of the rigidity case in dimension n = 3. Namely we prove the following <lb/> Theorem 4.2. Let us suppose that (M <lb/> 3  , g, k) satisfies the assumptions of the posi-<lb/>tive energy-momentum theorem and that the matrix Q is degenerate. Then there ex-<lb/>ists some <lb/> ∇-parallel spinor field ξ such that <lb/> Rξ, ξ <lb/> = 0 and consequently (M, g, k) <lb/> is isometrically embeddable in a stationary pp-wave space-time. <lb/>If furthermore the constant function (ξ, ξ) is non-zero then (M, g, k) admits <lb/>a vacuum Killing development which is a solution of the Einstein equations (with <lb/> the cosmological constant −3). <lb/> Remark 4.3. A pp-wave space-time is a Lorentzian manifolds such that its stress-<lb/>energy tensor satisfies T  μν  = λZ  μ  ⊗ Z  ν  where Z <lb/> μ  is an isotropic Killing vector <lb/>field and λ a function on the manifold. Some results were also proved by Siklos in <lb/> [32] and by Leitner in [25] for Lorentzian manifolds admitting a Killing spinor. <lb/>Proof. The degenerate character of Q implies the existence of a non-zero w⊕u ∈ C <lb/> 4 <lb/> and a unique ξ  0  such that ξ = f Aσ  w⊕u  + ξ  0  satisfies the conditions <lb/> ∇ξ = 0 <lb/> Rξ, ξ <lb/> = 0. <lb/>By the same argument as above we get that <lb/> d <lb/> ∇  k(X, Y ) · e  0  · ξ, ξ <lb/> = 0 (which can <lb/>also be thought as ∇  X  k(Y, α) = ∇  Y  k(X, α)). Now since ξ is <lb/> ∇-parallel we get <lb/> e <lb/>  3 <lb/> k=1 <lb/> e  k  · R <lb/> γ <lb/>X,e  k <lb/> ξ, Y · ξ <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/> e <lb/>  3 <lb/> k=1 <lb/> e  k  · (X · e  k  − e  k  · X) · ξ, Y · ξ <lb/> = X, Y <lb/>∀X, Y ∈ Γ(T M). <lb/> On the other hand a direct computation leads to <lb/> 3 <lb/> k=1 <lb/> e  k  · R <lb/> γ <lb/>X,e  k <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 3 <lb/> l,m=1 <lb/> d <lb/> ∇  k(X, e  l  , e  m  )e  l  · e  0  · e  m  · + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 3 <lb/> l,m=1 <lb/> R <lb/> γ  (X, e  l  , e  l  , e  m  )e  l  · e  l  · e  m  · <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 3 <lb/> l,m=1 <lb/> d <lb/> ∇  k(X, e  l  , e  m  )e  l  · e  0  · e  m  · <lb/>− <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 3 <lb/> l,m=1 <lb/> {R <lb/> g  (X, e  l  , e  l  , e  m  ) − k(X, e  l  )k(e  l  , e  m  ) + k(X, e  m  )k(e  l  , e  l  )} · e  m  · <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vol. 7 (2006) <lb/>Positive Energy Theorem <lb/></note>
			<page> 1005 <lb/></page>

			<body> = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 3 <lb/> l,m=1 <lb/> d <lb/> ∇  k(X, e  l  , e  m  )e  l  · e  0  · e  m  · − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(E(X) − 2X)· , <lb/> where we have set E = Ric <lb/> g  +2g + (tr k)k − k • k. It is then clear that <lb/> e <lb/>  3 <lb/> k,l=1 <lb/> d <lb/> ∇  k(X, e  l  , e  m  )e  l  · e  0  · e  m  · ψ, Y · ψ <lb/> = V E(X, Y ). <lb/>In the following computation we will set Y = e  s  . We recall that <lb/> e <lb/>  3 <lb/> l,m=1 <lb/> d <lb/> ∇  k(X, e  l  , e  m  )e  l  · e  0  · e  m  · ψ, e  s  · ψ <lb/> = <lb/> 3 <lb/> l,m=1 <lb/> d <lb/> ∇  k(X, e  l  , e  m  )e e  l  · e  0  · e  m  · ψ, e  s  · ψ <lb/> = <lb/> 3 <lb/> l=1 <lb/> d <lb/> ∇  k(X, e  l  , e  l  )e e  l  · e  0  · e  l  · ψ, e  s  · ψ <lb/> + <lb/> l =m <lb/> d <lb/> ∇  k(X, e  l  , e  m  )e e  l  · e  0  · e  m  · ψ, e  s  · ψ <lb/> = (I + II)(X, e  s  ), <lb/>and we will treat I and II separately for convenience. The easiest one is <lb/> I(X, e  s  ) = − −e  s  · e  0  · ψ, ·ψ <lb/> 3 <lb/> l=1 <lb/> ∇  X  k(e  l  , e  l  ) − ∇  e  l  k(X, e  l  ) <lb/> = − <lb/> (δ  g  k + dtr  g  k) ⊗ α <lb/> (X, e  s  ). <lb/>Thereby we can conclude that I = −(δ  g  k +dtr  g  k)⊗α. We compute now II(X, e  s  ). <lb/> II(X, e  s  ) = <lb/> l =s <lb/> d <lb/> ∇  k(X, e  l  , e  s  )e e  l  · e  0  · e  s  · ψ, e  s  · ψ <lb/> + <lb/> m =s <lb/> d <lb/> ∇  k(X, e  s  , e  m  )e e  s  · e  0  · e  m  · ψ, e  s  · ψ <lb/> + <lb/> l =m, l =s, m =s <lb/> d <lb/> ∇  k(X, e  l  , e  m  )e e  l  · e  0  · e  m  · ψ, e  s  · ψ , <lb/> but the last sum is zero since e  k  · e  0  · e  m  · ψ, e  s  · ψ is purely imaginary whenever <lb/> k, m, s are distinct indices. Thereby it comes out that II(X, e  s  ) = <lb/> ∇  es  k(X, α) − <lb/>∇  α  k(X, e  s  ) <lb/> , so that we can conclude <lb/> II(X, Y ) = ∇  Y  k(X, α) − ∇  α  k(X, Y ), <lb/></body>

			<page> 1006 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> D. Maerten <lb/>Ann. Henri Poincaré <lb/></note>

			<body> and consequently <lb/> V <lb/> Ric <lb/> g  + 2g + (tr  g  k)k − k • k <lb/> (X, Y ) = − <lb/> (δ  g  k + dtr  g  k) ⊗ α <lb/> (X, Y ) <lb/>+ <lb/> ∇  Y  k(X, α) − ∇  α  k(X, Y ) <lb/> . <lb/> Moreover the couple (V, α) satisfies the following differential equations <lb/> ∇  X  α(Y ) = V k(X, Y ) + <lb/> i <lb/> 2 <lb/> (X · Y − Y · X) · ξ, ξ <lb/> δ <lb/>  * <lb/> g  α = V k <lb/> dV (X) = k(X, α) + i X · ψ, ψ <lb/> and <lb/>(Hess <lb/> g  V )(X, Y ) <lb/>= ∇  Y  k(X, α) − V (k • k)(X, Y ) + V g(X, Y ) + ∇  X  α(k(Y )) + ∇  Y  α(k(X)) <lb/> = ∇  Y  k(X, α) − ∇  α  k(X, Y ) − V (k • k)(X, Y ) + V g(X, Y ) + L  α  k(Y, X) <lb/> = V <lb/> Ric <lb/> g  + 3g + (tr  g  k)k − 2(k • k) <lb/> (X, Y ) <lb/>+ <lb/> (δ  g  k + dtr  g  k) ⊗ α <lb/> (X, Y ) + L  α  k(Y, X) . <lb/> It is clear that the couple (V, W ) := (V, −α <lb/>  ) satisfies the first KID equation [10], <lb/>and using the second KID equation for defining the symmetric tensor τ of [10], <lb/>namely <lb/> V <lb/> τ − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(tr  g  τ − ρ)g <lb/> = V <lb/> Ric <lb/> g  + (tr  g  k)k − 2(k • k) <lb/> − L  W  k − (Hess <lb/> g  V ) <lb/>= <lb/> (δ  g  k + dtr  g  k) ⊗ W <lb/> − 3V g, <lb/> where 2ρ := Scal <lb/> g  +(tr k) <lb/> 2 <lb/> − |k| <lb/> 2  . Taking the trace of last equation one gets <lb/>tr  g  τ − ρ = 12 and consequently <lb/> V τ = <lb/> (δ  g  k + dtr  g  k) ⊗ W <lb/> + 3V g. <lb/> Now the equation  <lb/> Rξ, ξ = 0 implies <lb/> Scal <lb/> g  +6+(tr  g  k) <lb/> 2 <lb/> −|k| <lb/> 2 <lb/> g <lb/> = 2 |δ  g  k + dtr  g  k|. <lb/> We also know that V <lb/> Scal <lb/> g  + 6 + (tr  g  k) <lb/> 2 <lb/> − |k| <lb/> 2 <lb/> g <lb/> = 2 <lb/> (δ  g  k + dtr  g  k), W <lb/> , and <lb/>thereby it is clear that there exists some function on M denoted by ϑ such that <lb/> W = ϑ(δ  g  k + dtr  g  k) and so <lb/> V <lb/> Scal <lb/> g  + 6 + (tr  g  k) <lb/> 2 <lb/> − |k| <lb/> 2 <lb/> g <lb/> = 2 |ϑ| |δ  g  k + dtr  g  k| <lb/> 2 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vol. 7 (2006) <lb/> Positive Energy Theorem <lb/></note>

			<page> 1007 <lb/></page>

			<body> and therefore <lb/>2V |δ  g  k + dtr  g  k| = <lb/> 2ρ + 6 <lb/> |W | , <lb/> which shows that in the Killing development the Killing vector field (V, W ) will <lb/>be colinear to the cosmological constraints 4-vector (2ρ + 6, 2(δ  g  k + dtr  g  k)) which <lb/>is isotropic. It follows that the Killing vector field (N, W ) is also isotropic in the <lb/>Killing development. We finally obtain the relation V <lb/> 2  (τ −3g) = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  (2ρ+6)W <lb/> ⊗W <lb/> which means that the Killing development is a stationary pp-wave space-time. <lb/>Supposing furthermore that the constant function (ξ, ξ) is non-zero, we get <lb/>(δ  g  k + dtr  g  k)(ξ, ξ) = 0 and so (δ  g  k + dtr  g  k) = 0 by tracing the equation <lb/> d <lb/> ∇  k(X, Y ) · e  0  · ξ, ξ <lb/> = 0. It follows by the dominant energy condition that <lb/>Scal <lb/> g  +(tr k) <lb/> 2 <lb/> − |k| <lb/> 2  = −6, and we obtain finally that τ = 3g. Thereby the couple <lb/>(V, W ) is a cosmological vacuum KID. It is known [10] that in that case (M, g, k) <lb/> has a cosmological vacuum Killing development denoted by (N, γ) which is a sta-<lb/>tionary 4-dimensional Lorentzian manifold satisfying G <lb/> γ  = 3γ and carrying a <lb/>Killing vector field which is the natural extension of the KID (V, W ). <lb/> Remark 4.4. It is clear that expecting m  0  = 0 so as to define the rigidity situation <lb/>is much stronger than expecting the degenerate character of Q. A good issue would <lb/>certainly be to use the geometry at infinity in the same way as in [18] but in <lb/>the AdS-asymptotically hyperbolic context, in order to prove under the degenerate <lb/>character of Q the existence of an isometric embedding of (M, g, k) in AdS. <lb/> 5. Appendix <lb/> 5.1. Non-negativity of Q seen through its coefficients when n = 3 <lb/>Classical linear algebra results state that every principal minor of Q must be non-<lb/>negative which give rise to a set of inequalities on the coefficients of H. <lb/> m  0  + m  1  ≥ 0 <lb/> m  0  − m  1  ≥ 0 <lb/> m <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  − |m| <lb/> 2 <lb/> ≥ 0 <lb/>(m  0  + m  1  ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> − (n  2  + r  3  ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> − (r  2  − n  3  ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> ≥ 0 <lb/>(m  0  − m  1  ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> − (n  2  − r  3  ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> − (r  2  + n  3  ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> ≥ 0 <lb/> m <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  − m <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  − n <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  − r <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  ≥ 0 <lb/>(m  0  + m  1  )(m <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  − (|m| <lb/> 2  + n <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + r <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  )) − (m  0  − m  1  )((n  2  + r  3  ) <lb/> 2  + (n  3  − r  2  ) <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> − 2((n  2  + r  3  )(m  2  n  1  + m  3  r  1  ) + (−n  3  + r  2  )(m  2  r  1  − m  3  n  1  ) ≥ 0 <lb/>(m  0  − m  1  )(m <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  − (|m| <lb/> 2  + n <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + r <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  )) − (m  0  + m  1  )((n  2  − r  3  ) <lb/> 2  + (n  3  + r  2  ) <lb/> 2  ) <lb/>+ 2((n  2  − r  3  )(m  2  n  1  − m  3  r  1  ) + (n  3  + r  2  )(m  2  r  1  + m  3  n  1  ) ≥ 0 <lb/>(m <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  − (|m| <lb/> 2  + |n| <lb/> 2  + |r| <lb/> 2  )) <lb/> 2 <lb/> − 4(|m| <lb/> 2 <lb/> |n| <lb/> 2  + |m| <lb/> 2 <lb/> |r| <lb/> 2  + |n| <lb/> 2 <lb/> |r| <lb/> 2  ) <lb/>+ 4(&lt;m, n&gt; <lb/> 2  + &lt;m, r&gt; <lb/> 2  + &lt;n, r&gt; <lb/> 2  ) + 8m  0  det  R  3  (m, n, r) <lb/> ≥ 0. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1008 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> D. Maerten <lb/>Ann. Henri Poincaré <lb/></note>

			<body> 5.2. Rigidity results for the Trautman-Bondi mass <lb/> Oppositely to the rest of the paper, we consider here the situation of the Trautman-<lb/> Bondi mass [16], namely (M, g, k) is assumed to be Minkowski-asymptotically <lb/>hyperbolic which means that the triple (M, g, k) is asymptotic at infinity to a <lb/>standard hyperbolic slice of Minkowski space-time. It has been proved (cf. The-<lb/>orem 5.4 of [16]) that the Trautman-Bondi four-momentum p  μ  is timelike and <lb/>future directed under the dominant energy condition (and some other technical <lb/>assumptions). The aim of this section is to prove some rigidity results for the <lb/> Trautman-Bondi four-momentum which are analogous to the statements of Sec-<lb/>tion 4. More precisely <lb/> Theorem 5.1. Under the assumptions of Theorem 5.4 of [16], and if the compo-<lb/>nent p  0  of the Trautman-Bondi four-momentum p  μ  vanishes, then (M, g, k) can <lb/>be isometrically embedded in Minkowski space-time. <lb/>Proof. This can be done in the same way as our rigidity theorem: since p  μ  is <lb/>timelike, the condition p  0  = 0 implies that p  μ  actually vanishes. Consequently there <lb/>exists a basis of ∇-parallel spinor fields on M , where ∇ is the connection on some <lb/>cylinder ]−, +[ × M endowed with some Lorentzian metric γ = −dt <lb/> 2  + g  t  (such <lb/>that M has induced metric g and extrinsic curvature k satisfying the conditions <lb/>of [16]). Now if ∇ denotes the Levi-Civita connection of g = g  0  , we still have the <lb/>relation ∇  X  ξ = ∇  X  ξ − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  k(X) · e  0  · ξ where · is the Clifford action with respect <lb/>to γ. Our spinorial Gauss-Codazzi formula is still valid, that is <lb/> R <lb/> γ <lb/>X,Y  = R <lb/> g <lb/>X,Y  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> d <lb/> ∇  k(X, Y ) · e  0  + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> k(X) · k(Y ) − k(Y ) · k(X) <lb/> · = 0 , <lb/> and so <lb/> R <lb/> g  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> k  k <lb/> d <lb/> ∇  k = 0. <lb/>Furthermore, the couple (V, W ) := (V, −α <lb/>  ) is a vacuum KID if one defines V = <lb/> &lt;ξ, ξ&gt; and the real 1-form α by α(Y ) = Y · e  0  · ξ, ξ. We consider again the <lb/>Killing development of ( <lb/> M, <lb/> g,  k) with respect to ( <lb/> V , <lb/> W ), and observe that it must <lb/>be a geodesically complete stationary solution of vacuum Einstein equations of zero <lb/>sectional curvature and thereby must be Minkowski space-time (cf. Proposition 23 <lb/>[p. 227] of [27]). Now the same cohomological arguments give ( <lb/> M, <lb/> g,  k) = (M, g, k) <lb/> which is by construction embedded in its Killing development that is Minkowski. <lb/> Theorem 5.2. Let us suppose that (M, g, k) satisfies the assumptions of Theorem <lb/> 5.4 of [16] and that p  μ  is null. Then there exists some ∇-parallel spinor field ξ <lb/> such that Rξ, ξ = 0 and consequently (M, g, k) is isometrically embeddable in a <lb/>stationary pp-wave space-time. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vol. 7 (2006) <lb/>Positive Energy Theorem <lb/></note>

			<page> 1009 <lb/></page>

			<body> If furthermore the constant function (ξ, ξ) is non-zero then (M, g, k) admits <lb/>a vacuum Killing development which is a stationary solution of the Einstein equa-<lb/>tions. <lb/>Proof. p  μ  is null implies the existence of a spinor field ξ satisfying the conditions <lb/> ∇ξ = 0 <lb/> Rξ, ξ = 0. <lb/>Then in the same way as in the last Theorem of Section 4, but defining here the <lb/>2-tensor E =: Ric <lb/> g  +(tr k)k − k • k we obtain that the couple (V, W ) is a vacuum <lb/>KID and the corresponding Killing development satisfies V <lb/> 2  τ = ρ(W <lb/> ⊗W <lb/>  ) which <lb/>means that it is a stationary pp-wave space-time. <lb/>Still using the same computations as in the last Theorem of Section 4 and <lb/>assuming that the constant function (ξ, ξ) is non-zero we find that the constraints <lb/>equations are satisfied (because of the dominant energy condition) and that τ = 0. <lb/>Thereby (V, W ) is a vacuum KID and it is known that in this case (M, g, k) has a <lb/>stationary vacuum Killing development. <lb/> Remark 5.3. It is clear that expecting p  0  = 0 so as to define the rigidity situation <lb/>is much stronger than expecting the null character of p  μ  . As in our situation (cf. <lb/> the remark at the end of Section 4), a good issue would certainly be to use the <lb/> geometry at infinity in the same way as in [18] but in the Minkowski-asymptotically <lb/>hyperbolic context, in order to prove under the equality case of Theorem 5.4 of [16], <lb/> the existence of an isometric embedding of (M, g, k) in Minkowski. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments <lb/> I wish to thank M. Herzlich for his helpful comments as regard the redaction of <lb/>this text. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] M.T. Anderson, On stationary vacuum solutions to the Einstein equations, Ann. <lb/>Henri Poincaré, 1 (2000) 5, 977–994. <lb/>[2] M.T. Anderson, On the structure of solutions to the static vacuum Einstein equations, <lb/> Ann. Henri Poincaré, 1 (2000) 6, 995–1042. <lb/>[3] L. Andersson, M. Dahl, Scalar curvature rigidity for asymptotically locally hyperbolic <lb/>manifolds, Ann. Global Anal. Geom., 16 (1998), 1–27. <lb/>[4] C. Bär, Real spinors and holonomy, Commun. Math. Phys., 154 (1993), 509–521. <lb/>[5] C. Bär, P. Gauduchon, A. Moroianu, Generalized cylinders in semi-Riemannian and <lb/>spin geometry, arXiv:math.DG/0303095 v1. <lb/>[6] R. Bartnik, The mass of an asymptotically flat manifold, Comm. Pure Appl. Math., <lb/> 39 (1986), 661–693. <lb/>[7] R. Bartnik, P.T. Chru´ ciel, Boundary value problems for Dirac-type equations, with <lb/>applications, arXiv:math.DG/0307278v1, 21 Jul 2003. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 1010 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> D. Maerten <lb/>Ann. Henri Poincaré <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> [8] H. Baum, Complete Riemannian manifolds with imaginary Killing spinors, Ann. <lb/>Global Anal. Geom., 7 (1989) 4, 205–226. <lb/>[9] H. Baum, Odd-dimensionnal Riemannian manifolds with imaginary Killing spinors, <lb/> Ann. Global Anal. Geom., 7 (1989) 2, 141–154. <lb/>[10] R. Beig, P.T. Chru´ ciel, Killing Initial Data, Class. Quantum Gravity, 14 (1997) 1.A, <lb/>A83-A92. <lb/>[11] A.L. Besse, Einstein manifolds, Springer. <lb/>[12] R. Boot, L.W. Tu, Differential Forms in Algebraic Topology, Graduate Texts in <lb/>Mathematics, Springer. <lb/>[13] J.P. Bourguignon, P. Gauduchon, Spineurs, opérateurs de Dirac et variations de <lb/>métriques, Comm. Math. Phys., 144 (1992) n 3, 581–599. <lb/>[14] M. Cahen, S. Gutt, L. Lemaire, P. Spindel, Killing Spinors, Bull. Soc. Math. Belg., <lb/>Ser. A 38 (1986) 2, 75–102. <lb/>[15] P.T. Chru´ ciel, M. Herzlich, The mass of asymptotically hyperbolic Riemannian man-<lb/>ifolds, Pacific Journal of Mathematics, 212 (2003) 2, 231–264. <lb/>[16] P.T. Chru´ ciel, J. Jezierski, S. <lb/>L¸ ski, The Trautman-Bondi mass of hyperboloidal <lb/>initial data sets, Adv. Theor. Math. Phys., 8 (2004), 83–139. <lb/>[17] P.T. Chru´ ciel, D. Maerten, An upper bound for angular momentum for asymptoti-<lb/>cally anti-de Sitter space-times, to appear. <lb/>[18] P.T. Chru´ ciel, D. Maerten, Killing vectors in asymptotically flat space-times: II. <lb/>Asymptotically translational Killing vectors and the rigid positive energy theorem in <lb/>higher dimensions, to appear. <lb/>[19] P.T. Chru´ ciel, G. Nagy, The mass of spacelike hypersurfaces in asymptotically anti-<lb/>de Sitter space-times, Adv. Theor. Math. Phys., 19 (2001) 4, 697–754. <lb/>[20] G.W. Gibbons, C.M. Hull, N.P. Warner, The stability of gauged supergravity, Nuclear <lb/>Phys. B, 218 (1983) n 1, 173–190. <lb/>[21] S.W. Hawking, G.F.R. Ellis, The large scale structure of space-time, Cambridge Uni-<lb/>versity Press. <lb/>[22] M. Henneaux, C. Teitelboim, Asymptotically Anti-de-Sitter Spaces, Commun. Math. <lb/>Phys., 98 (1985), 391–424. <lb/>[23] M. Herzlich, The positive mass theorem for black holes revisited, J. Geom. Phys., 26 <lb/> (1998), 97–111. <lb/>[24] H.B. Lawson, M.L. Michelson, Spin Geometry, Princeton. <lb/>[25] F. Leitner, Imaginary Killing Spinors in Lorentzian Geometry, J. of Math. Phys., 44 <lb/> (2003) no. 10, 4795–4806. <lb/>[26] V. Moncrief, Space-time symmetries and linearization stability of the Einstein equa-<lb/>tions, J. of Math. Phys., 16, 493–498. <lb/>[27] B. O&apos;Neill, Semi-Riemannian Geometry, with applications to Relativity, Academic <lb/>Press. <lb/>[28] T. Parker, C. Taubes, On Witten&apos;s proof of the positive energy theorem, Commun. <lb/>Math. Phys., 84 (1982), 223–238. <lb/>[29] R. Schoen, S.-T. Yau, On the proof of the positive mass conjecture in general rela-<lb/>tivity, Commun. Math. Phys., 65 (1979), 45–76. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> Vol. 7 (2006) <lb/>Positive Energy Theorem <lb/></note>

			<page> 1011 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [30] R. Schoen, S.-T. Yau, The energy and the linear momentum of space-times in general <lb/>relativity, Commun. Math. Phys., 79 (1981), 47–51. <lb/>[31] R. Schoen, S.-T. Yau, Proof of the positive mass theorem II, Commun. Math. Phys., <lb/> 79 (1981), 231–260. <lb/>[32] S.T.C. Siklos, Lobatchevsky Plane Gravitational Waves, S.T.C. Siklos, in Galaxies, <lb/>axisymmetric systems and relativity ed. M.A.H. MacCallum, Cambridge University <lb/>Press, 1985. <lb/>[33] R. Wald, General relativity, University press of Chicago. <lb/>[34] X. Wang, Mass for asymptotically hyperbolic manifolds, J. Differential Geom., 57 <lb/> (2001), 273–299. <lb/>[35] E. Witten, A simple proof of the positive energy theorem, Commun. Math. Phys., 80 <lb/> (1981), 381–402. <lb/>[36] X. Zhang, Angular momentum and positive mass theorem, Commun. Math. Phys., <lb/> 206 (1999), 137–155. <lb/>[37] X. Zhang, A definition of total energy-momenta and the positive mass theorem on <lb/>asymptotically hyperbolic manifolds, Commun. Math. Phys., 249 (2004), 529–548. <lb/></listBibl>

			<front>Daniel Maerten <lb/>Institut de Mathématiques et de Modélisation de Montpellier (I3M) <lb/>Université Montpellier II <lb/>UMR 5149 CNRS <lb/>Place Euène Bataillon <lb/>F-34095 Montpellier <lb/>France <lb/>e-mail: maerten@math.univ-montp2.fr <lb/> Communicated by Sergiu Klainerman <lb/>Submitted: January 15, 2006 <lb/>Accepted: January 15, 2006 <lb/> To access this journal online: <lb/>http://www.birkhauser.ch </front>


	</text>
</tei>
