<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage> This content has been downloaded from IOPscience. Please scroll down to see the full text. <lb/>Download details: <lb/>IP Address: 137.138.124.224 <lb/>This content was downloaded on 13/04/2015 at 18:46 <lb/>Please note that terms and conditions apply. <lb/> Two potential solution for an Abelian dyon in Born Infeld theory <lb/> View the table of contents for this issue, or go to the journal homepage for more <lb/>1992 Phys. Scr. 46 385 <lb/>(http://iopscience.iop.org/1402-4896/46/5/001) <lb/>Home Search Collections Journals About Contact us My IOPscience <lb/></titlePage>


			<front> Physica Scripta. Vol.  46,  385-388, 1992. <lb/> Two Potential Solution for an Abelian Dyon in Born lnfeld <lb/>Theory <lb/> c. Wolf <lb/> Department of Physics, North Adams State College, North Adams, MA 01247, U.S.A. <lb/> Received April 1,1992; accepted May 25,1992 <lb/> Abstract <lb/> By introducing two potentials to describe the electromagnetic field we <lb/>arrive at a symmetric solution for the field of an Abelian dyon in Born <lb/>Infeld theory. A discussion is given regarding the difference between a two <lb/>potential theory and a one potential theory in the case of an Abelian dyon. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1.  Introduction <lb/> The existence of monopole and dyon solutions in both <lb/>Abelian and non-Abelian gauge theory suggest topological <lb/>properties of field configurations that have far ranging con-<lb/>sequences in particle theory and early universe cosmology in <lb/>that monopoles can serve as seeds to large scale structures <lb/>as well as serving as a catalyst for proton decay  [l, 21.  The <lb/>monopole was long ago discussed by Dirac in his search to <lb/>find a fundamental reason for electric charge quantization <lb/> [3].  Schwinger  [4]  later discussed the electromagnetic <lb/>properties of a two dyon solution in electrodynamics (a <lb/>dyon being a monopole with electric charge) and Witten has <lb/>pointed out that the electric charge of a dyon need not be <lb/>quantized in the presence of C P violating interactions  [SI. <lb/> Building upon this fact, Fischler and Preskill  [6]  have <lb/>shown how a monopole interacting with an axion cloud can <lb/>serve to diminish the axion density to acceptable levels in <lb/>the early universe, the monopole acquires a non-integral <lb/>electric charge through the C P violating coupling between <lb/>the electromagnetic field and the axion field and thus <lb/>becomes a dyon. The topological properties of non-Abelian <lb/>monopoles and dyons have been discussed by Prasad-<lb/>Sommerfield (Ref. [l]) with the magnetic charge having dis-<lb/>tinct homotophy characteristics. In a very profound study, <lb/>Vinciarelli  [7]  pointed out that only four dimensional <lb/>space-time can support the dual symmetry of Maxwell&apos;s <lb/>equations, this fact suggests that the symmetry between elec-<lb/>tric and magnetic charge might be a feature enjoyed by four <lb/>space-time dimensions alone and electric and magnetic <lb/>charge structures might be present only after compact-<lb/>ification from higher dimensions. On the scale of elementary <lb/>particle phenomena, Olsen and Osland  [8]  have studied the <lb/>bound states of vector particles in the field of a monopole <lb/>with stable bound states resulting. In an external magnetic <lb/>field Tolkachev  et al. [9]  have studied the Zeeman splitting <lb/>of a dyogen atom (dyon  +  electric charge) and have shown <lb/>how the splitting of the energy levels is due to the parity <lb/>violating properties of the dyon. With regard to non-<lb/>Abelian dyons Gal&apos;tsov and Ershov  [lo]  have studied the <lb/>bound states of a scalar particle in the field of an SU(2) <lb/>dyon. Most recently Frampton  et  al. [11]  and Zhang  [12] <lb/> have studied the bound state spectra of a fermion in the field <lb/>of an Abelian dyon and arrived at selection rules for parity <lb/>violating transitions. With regard to the fundamental origin <lb/>of CP violation Zhang-Jian-zu  [13]  has discussed the CP <lb/>violating electric and magnetic dipole moments of a dyon-<lb/>fermion system which might suggest that composite fer-<lb/>mions might contain a fermion-dyon bound state to serve as <lb/>a source to phenomenological C P violation. <lb/>The intent of this note is to study the properties of an <lb/>Abelian dyon within the context of non-linear electro-<lb/>dynamics when a two potential theory is used, it turns out <lb/>that the two potential theory leads to a symmetry between <lb/>electric and magnetic charge which is not present in the one <lb/>potential theory when a non-linear electromagnetic lagrang-<lb/>ian is studied. There have been two separate approaches to <lb/>non-linear electrodynamics, the first is the Euler-Heisenberg <lb/>approach which is an effective non-linear electromagnetic <lb/>theory obtained after the fermions are integrated out of the <lb/>lagrangian  [14, 151,  the second which we study in this note <lb/>is the historical approach of Born-Infeld that seeks to <lb/>obtain a purely finite electromagnetic theory by altering the <lb/>Maxwell lagrangian  [  161.  When magnetic charge is present <lb/>in Maxwell&apos;s theory, it turns out that outside the region of <lb/>magnetic charge a potential can be defined and a solution <lb/>for the electric and magnetic field of a dyon can be obtained <lb/>that is symmetric in the electric and magnetic charge. <lb/>However, as mentioned in Born-Infeld theory for a one <lb/>potential theory, there is no symmetry between electric and <lb/>magnetic charge. Our analysis might serve to suggest how <lb/>to treat Abelian gauge fields when a highly non-linear elec-<lb/>tromagnetic structure is present. We may view the non-<lb/>linearity as an effect generated by integrating out the heavy <lb/>field degrees of freedom with the gauge field remaining. Cer-<lb/>tainly close to the dyon core the non-linear terms are <lb/>important and we will discuss both the near-electric, mag-<lb/>netic and gravitational field as well as the far fields. <lb/>On an astrophysical scale recently Dimopoulous  et  al. <lb/>[17]  and De Rujula  et  al. [18]  have suggested the presence <lb/>of CHAMPS (charged massive particles between  20  and <lb/>1OOOTeV) to explain the presence of dark matter in galatic <lb/>halos. These particles are predicted by G.U.T. theory and if <lb/> they were to be localized near a monopole created around <lb/>the time of nucleosynthesis  [19]  we would have the com-<lb/>ponents of a macroscopic dyon that could very well have a <lb/>highly non-linear structure. Such a dyon would effect local <lb/>phenomena such as plasma oscillations or density fluctua-<lb/>tions to seed large scale structure and thus the details of <lb/>dyon field would be of utmost interest. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> Physica Scripta 46 <lb/></note>

			<page> 386 </page>

			<note place="headnote"> C.  Wolf <lb/></note>

			<body> As a problem in classical field theory as well as a sugges-<lb/>tion of how a non-linear dyon field configuration might <lb/>look we embark on the study of a non-linear dyon in a two <lb/>potential theory of Cabibbo and Ferrari [20]. Our results <lb/>through classical should serve as a model to study more <lb/>elaborate quantum configurations when the quanta of the <lb/>heavy fields cannot be integrated out of the theory. <lb/>and for the  (3  Einstein equation we have <lb/>Since T i  =  TZ for the electromagnetic field of the dyon we <lb/>may subtract the (i) and  ( <lb/>: <lb/>)  Einstein equations to obtain <lb/> +  v&apos;)  = 0 <lb/> or <lb/> 2. Two potential solution for an Abelian dyon in born-infeld <lb/> We begin by writing the lagrangian of electromagnetism <lb/>and gravity in a two potential theory  (A,, BJ  (Ref. [20]) <lb/> with a non-linear B.E. electromagnetic structure <lb/> theory <lb/> I + v = C <lb/> By rescaling the time coordinant it is always possible to <lb/>choose  C  =  0, thus  A  +  v  =  0 for the dyon metric. <lb/>Equation (2.3) and eq. (2.4) give using the definitions of <lb/> F14, F,, and the condition  A  +  v  = 0 <lb/> L=- c4  R&amp; <lb/> - (J1+  5  - 1) <lb/>16nG <lb/> 8n <lb/> (b  =  constant). <lb/>or <lb/> L  =  L,  +  LE,  - J ~ A , &amp;  +  J G B , ~ ~ <lb/> Here  J ;  =  electric four current,  J&amp;  =  magnetic four current, <lb/> J  =  F,, F&quot;&apos; . The electromagnetic field tensor in this two <lb/>potential theory is (Ref. [20]). <lb/> after integrating <lb/> .&apos;E. <lb/> e <lb/> 4n  J T = G <lb/> l+---<lb/> r&apos;B. <lb/> a <lb/> where <lb/> 4n  J &apos; p = z <lb/> 1+---<lb/> (e,  q  =  electric and magnetic charge of dyon.) <lb/>Solving eq. (2.8) and eq. (2.9) for E,, B, gives <lb/> =  tensor density),  A,,  =  electric-like ,dur potential, <lb/>If we vary eq. (2.1) with respect to  A,, B,  respectively we <lb/> B,  =  magnetic-like four potential. <lb/>have <lb/> (2.3) <lb/>(2.10) <lb/> e <lb/> E,  = <lb/> (2.1 1) <lb/>(2.4) <lb/> For the energy momentum tensor of the electromagnetic <lb/>field we have from eq. (2.1) <lb/>(2.12) <lb/>1 F,F: <lb/> =  8n  [Pi  - 1Igrv  --<lb/> (the dual to FJ. We consider a central dyon of electric and <lb/>magnetic charge  e,  q,  with F,,  =  E,, F,,  =  r &apos;  sin  OB,  also <lb/> . I { =  J&amp;  =  0 for  r  &gt;  0. Also we employ the spherically sym-<lb/>metric metric. <lb/>(ds)&apos;  =  e&apos;(dx4)&apos;  - e&apos; ((dr)&apos;  - r2(dO)Z  - t 2  sin&apos; (d4)&apos; <lb/> (2.5) <lb/> For the (i) Einstein equation we have <lb/> E&apos; <lb/> (2.13) <lb/> -<lb/> Physica Scripta 46 <lb/> Two  Potential Solution for an Abelian Dyon in  Born  Infeld Theory 387 <lb/> We first study the behavior of the metric for small  r,  from <lb/>eq.  (2.10),  eq.  (2.11)  and eq.  (2.13)  we have for small  r  (where <lb/>we restrict the charges to obey  e  &gt;  q so  as not to allow the <lb/>quantity under the square root to become negative) <lb/> Ti  E L  [L  (1  - f) - 1 1  + - e&apos;  (1  - G) <lb/> 8n <lb/> 4nr2~&apos;/&apos; <lb/> with <lb/> 2e2 2q2 <lb/> X = b -b <lb/> From the  (2)  Einstein equation we have for small  r <lb/> re  ) -<lb/> )(f) <lb/> d <lb/>dr <lb/> c4  8 1 1 ~ &apos; / ~  871 <lb/> 811 <lb/> 47q1/&apos;  8nx3l2 <lb/> br2 <lb/> e&apos; <lb/> --+---<lb/> 8nG  [  br4 b  (  r4 <lb/> -( <lb/> -A -1 --<lb/> -_-<lb/> -<lb/> or upon integration <lb/> e2r4  1 <lb/> br2 <lb/> e&apos; <lb/> --+---<lb/> 24n 4 n ~ &apos; &quot;  4 0 n ~ &apos; / ~ <lb/> Rewriting eq.  (2.17)  gives <lb/> 2GM 2Ge2 1Gbr2 <lb/> e-1  E  1  ----<lb/> rc2 <lb/> Gr4  (  b <lb/> x  112  c  4  +  3c4 <lb/> e&apos;  ) <lb/> + <lb/> Gr8  (  b  ) <lb/> ---_ -<lb/> --<lb/> 5c4  X I / ~ ~ 3 1 2 <lb/> 1 8 ~ 4  XJIZ <lb/> (2.14) <lb/>(2.15) <lb/>(2.16) <lb/>(2.17) <lb/>(2.18) <lb/> In the above expression for the metric near  r  =  0 we have <lb/>identified  a  as a mass parameter which is not the mass of <lb/>the particle since we are not in the asymptotic region  r  +  W. <lb/> If <lb/> Ge2 <lb/> X l / 2 c 4  &lt; <lb/> we see that the metric has an horizon for <lb/> 2GM 1 Gbr2 <lb/> 1 --<lb/> +--=o <lb/> rc4 <lb/> 3  c4 <lb/> (2.19) <lb/> (neglecting  r4,  r8  terms). <lb/>However, it will have other horizons since the  r4  term <lb/>decreases e-* after  r2  increases it. To obtain the precise <lb/>horizon properties of e-&apos; eq.  (2.16)  would have to be inte-<lb/>grated exactly using eq.  (2.13),  however the exact integral of <lb/>eq.  (2.16)  using eq.  (2.13)  cannot be found in closed form <lb/>thus making the solution a problem in numerical integra-<lb/>tion. <lb/>For large  r <lb/> - 2E,&apos; -41)  2B,&apos; <lb/> b y b <lb/> Also for large  r <lb/> from eq.  (2.10),  eq.  (2.11). <lb/> The  (2)  component of the Einstein equations is for large  r <lb/> d <lb/>dr <lb/> 2GM Ge2  Gq2 <lb/> +-+-<lb/> e-2  =  1  - -<lb/> re2 <lb/> r2c4 r2c4 <lb/> (2.21) <lb/> for large  r,  here  M  =  mass of central dyon. <lb/>Equation  (2.21)  is symmetric in e,  q  and represents the far <lb/>field Reissner Nordstrom metric for an Abelian dyon in the <lb/>two potential theory. The fact that the horizon structure of <lb/>a Born-Infeld dyon is different from that of the usual Reiss-<lb/>ner Nordstrom solution suggests that, both astrophysical <lb/>phenomena as well as Hawking radiative effects would have <lb/>unique characteristics associated with the Born-Infeld solu-<lb/>tion. <lb/>To demonstrate the difference between the one potential <lb/>solution for a dyon and the two potential solution we first <lb/>note that the bare E.M. lagrangian for the one potential <lb/>theory is the same as in eq.  (2.1)  for a two potential theory, <lb/>(excluding the  J&amp; B,&amp;  term), the field equations for F,, in <lb/>the one potential theory exterior to magnetic charge are <lb/>from eq.  (2.1)  upon varying with respect to A,, <lb/> (2.22) <lb/> Also we have the antisymmetric condition exterior to mag-<lb/>netic charge which is a statement of the existence of A,  , <lb/> (2.23) <lb/> Using  F,,  =  E,,  F2,  =  r2  sin OB,, eq.  (2.22)  and eq.  (2.23) <lb/> along with  1  +  v  =  0 (since  Ti  =  T i  for the one potential <lb/>theory) gives <lb/> a <lb/> ar <lb/> - (r2B,)  = 0 <lb/> giving <lb/> r2E. <lb/> e <lb/>(2.24) <lb/>(2.25) <lb/>(2.26) <lb/>(2.27) <lb/> 4 <lb/> r2B,  =  q, B,  = ; i <lb/> (e,  q  =  electric and magnetic charge of dyon). <lb/>substituted into the energy momentum tensor <lb/>When the solutions for E, B in eq.  (2.26)  and eq.  (2.27)  are <lb/>Equation  (2.13)  gives <lb/> (2.20) <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> Physica Scripta 46 <lb/></note>

			<page> 388 </page>

			<note place="headnote"> C.  Wolf <lb/></note>

			<body> and the  (2)  Einstein equation is integrated we obtain a soh-<lb/> r,  eq. (2.26) and eq. (2.27) give <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgement <lb/> University for the use of their facilities. <lb/> tion different than that Of eq* (2*18) for <lb/> &quot; <lb/> for large I&apos;d like to thank the physics departments at Williams College and Haward <lb/></div>

			<body> which would generate the Reissner Nordstrom solution for <lb/>large  r.  Thus the two potential theory and the one potential <lb/>theory generate identical far field metrics but different <lb/>metrics for small  r  and intermediate  r. <lb/> Conclusion <lb/> We have seen from our analysis that both the one potential <lb/>electrodynamics and the two potential electrodynamics yield <lb/>identical far field E , , B,  and metrics for a central dyon. <lb/>However for short distances, the two different formulations <lb/>would yield different results for both the electromagnetic <lb/>field and the metric in the case of non-linear electro-<lb/>dynamics. We might point out here that in addition to being <lb/>an interesting phenomenological lagrangian the Born Infeld <lb/>lagrangian has been shown to be a low energy effective <lb/>lagrangian for the electromagnetic field derived from a <lb/>string theory in the field theory limit [21].  This  fact encour-<lb/>ages us further to look for dyon solutions in such a theory. <lb/>Looking for dyons in an astrophysical setting has been sug-<lb/>gested by Frampton et al. (Ref. Ell]) where emissions from <lb/>condensed objects might reveal a fermion dyon bound state <lb/>with characteristic spectrum differing from the hydrogen <lb/>spectrum. If any such anomalous spectra were found, the <lb/>details of it might provide information to differentiate <lb/>between the one potential and two potential model for a <lb/>theory of electric and magnetic charge as well as serving as <lb/>a probe for non-linearities in the field configuration of an <lb/>Abelian dyon. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1.  Prasad, M.  K.  and Sommeriield, C. M., Phys. Rev. Lett.  35, (12), 760 <lb/>(1975). <lb/>2.  Callan, C. G., Phys. Rev.  D28,2058 (1982). <lb/> 3.  Dirac,  P.  A. M., Proc. of Roy. Society  A133,60 (1931). <lb/>4.  Schwinger, J., Phys. Rev.  144,1087 (1966). <lb/> 5.  Witten, E., Phys. Lett.  B86, 287 (1979). <lb/>6.  Fischler, W. and Preskill, J., Phys. Lett.  B125, 165 (1983). <lb/>7.  Vinciarelli, D., Proc. of  1976  Int. School of Subnuclear Physics, Erice <lb/>(Plenum Press, New York  1978). <lb/> 8.  Olsen, H. A. and Osland, P., Ark. Fys. Semin. Trondheim (Norway) <lb/> 11, l(1989). <lb/>9.  Tokachev, E. A., Tomil&apos;Chik, L. M. and Shnir, Ya. M., Sov. J. Nucl. <lb/>Phys. (U.S.A.)  SO,  (2), 275 (1989). <lb/>10.  Gal&apos;tov, D. V. and Ershov, A. A., Mosc. Univ. Phys. Bull. (U.S.A.)  43, <lb/>(4), 40 (1988). <lb/> 11.  Frampton, P. H., Zhang Jian-zu and Qi Yong-chang, Phys. Rev.  D40, <lb/>3533 (1989). <lb/>12.  Zhang Jian-zu, Phys. Rev.  D41,1280 (1990). <lb/>13.  Zhang Jian-zu, J. Phys. G. (Nucl. and Part. Phys)  16, 195 (1990). <lb/>14.  Euler, A. and Heisenberg, W., Zeitschrift fiir Physics  98,714 (1936). <lb/>15.  Adler,  S.  A., Annals of Physics  67, 599 (1971). <lb/>16.  Born, M. and Infeld, L., Proc. of Roy. Soc. of London  147,552 (1934). <lb/>17.  Dimopoulous,  S.,  Eichler,  B.,  Esmaelzadeh, R. and Starkman, C. D., <lb/> Phys. Rev.  D41,2388 (1990). <lb/>18.  De Rujula, A., Glashow,  S.  L. and Sand, U., Nucl. Phys.  B133, 173 <lb/>(1990). <lb/>19.  Hill. C. T., Proc. of N.A.T.O. Advanced Study Inst. on Magnetic <lb/>Monopoles, Oct.  14-17 (1982),  Wingspread, Wisconsin (Plenum Press, <lb/>New York  1983),  p.  175. <lb/> 20. Cabibbo, C. and Ferran, E., I11 Nuovo Cimento  23, 1147 (1962). <lb/>21.  Nappi, C. H., Proc. of XXIII Int. Cod. on High Energy Physics, July <lb/> 16-23 (1986),  Berkley, CA (World Scientific, Singapore  1987),  p.  530. <lb/> Physica  Scripta  46 </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
