<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> ELECTRON AND POSITRON BEAMS TRANSPORTATION CHANNELS <lb/>TO BINP COLLIDERS* <lb/> I.M. Zemlyansky <lb/> # <lb/> , D.E. Berkaev, V.A. Kiselev, I.A. Koop, A.V. Otboev, A.M. Semenov, <lb/>A.A. Starostenko, Budker Institute of Nuclear Physics, Novosibirsk, Russia <lb/> Abstract <lb/> There are two accelerator complexes VEPP-2000 and <lb/>VEPP-4M in BINP. There is preparatory work for <lb/>building of new accelerator – Super Charm-Tau Factory. <lb/>As an injector of positrons for Super c-t Factory the <lb/>existing injection complex VEPP-5 will be used. <lb/>Existence of the powerful injection complex provokes the <lb/>desire to use it for needs of the working accelerator <lb/>complexes VEPP-2000 and VEPP-4M. Replacement of <lb/>the existing injection subsystems with the injection <lb/>complex VEPP-5 will allow us to increase the speed of <lb/>accumulation of positrons at the accelerator complexes <lb/>VEPP-2000 and VEPP-4M in 1000 and 100 times <lb/>respectively. For VEPP-2000 this improvement has a <lb/>great significance as the existing conversion system <lb/>doesn&apos;t provide the demanded quantity of positrons for <lb/>designed luminosity of a collider 1x10 <lb/> 32  сm <lb/> -2 s <lb/> -1 . <lb/>In the article the short review of transportation channels <lb/>from the injection complex VEPP-5 to the accelerator <lb/>complexes VEPP-2000 and VEPP-4M, time sequence of <lb/>an injector&apos;s work for both complexes are given. The <lb/>transportation channel from the injection complex VEPP-<lb/>5 to the booster ring BEP of the accelerator complex <lb/>VEPP-2000 is described in details. <lb/></front>

			<body> BINP COLLIDERS AND INJECTION <lb/>COMPLEX <lb/> Figure 1: Colliders and Injection Complex in BINP. <lb/>In Figure 1 the arrangement of colliders and the <lb/>injection complex in the territory of BINP is shown. Their <lb/>detailed schemes are submitted in Figures 2-4. <lb/>The existing injection system of VEPP-2000 provides <lb/>2x10 <lb/> 7 positrons per second that allows us to reach <lb/>luminosity 5x10 <lb/> 30  сm <lb/> -2 s <lb/> -1 at energy 1GeV in one bunch. <lb/>Achievement of designed luminosity 1x10 <lb/> 32  сm <lb/> -2 s <lb/> -1 <lb/> requires 1x10 <lb/> 8 positrons per second. <lb/>Figure 2: Accelerator Complex VEPP-2000. <lb/>Figure 3: Accelerator Complex VEPP-4M. <lb/>Figure 4: Super Charm-Tau Factory and Injection <lb/>Complex VEPP-5. <lb/>The existing injection system of VEPP-4M makes <lb/>2x10 <lb/> 8 positrons per second that allows us to reach <lb/>luminosity 2x10 <lb/> 30  сm <lb/> -2 s <lb/> -1 at energy 1.8 GeV in one bunch. <lb/>Achievement of the future designed luminosity 8x10 <lb/> 31 <lb/> сm <lb/> -2 s <lb/> -1 at energy 5.5 GeV in one bunch requires 2x10 <lb/> 10 <lb/> positrons per second. <lb/></body>

			<front> ___________________________________________ <lb/> *Work supported by the Ministry of Education and Science of the <lb/>Russian Federation, NSh-4860.2014.2 <lb/>#I.M.Zemlyansky@inp.nsk.su <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote"> FRCA03 <lb/> Proceedings of RuPAC2014, Obninsk, Kaluga Region, Russia <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> ISBN 978-3-95450-170-0 <lb/></note>

			<page> 462 <lb/></page>

			<front> Copyright © 2014 CC-BY-3.0 and by the respective authors <lb/> 02 Colliders <lb/></front>

			<body> For future Super c-t Factory with designed luminosity <lb/>1x10 <lb/> 35  сm <lb/> -2 s <lb/> -1 6x10 <lb/> 11 positrons per second will be <lb/>required. <lb/>The Injection complex VEPP-5 parameters are: energy <lb/>510 MeV, number of positrons 2x10 <lb/> 10 per second, energy <lb/>spread 5.1x10 <lb/> -4 <lb/> , emittances e  x 2.3x10 <lb/> -6 cm·rad e  z 5х10 <lb/> -7 <lb/> cm·rad. These are enough for needs of VEPP-2000 and <lb/>VEPP-4M. Super c-t Factory requires more productivity <lb/>of the injector. Improvement of the injection complex will <lb/>be made along with construction of Super c-t Factory. <lb/> OPERATION: INJECTOR VEPP-5 FOR <lb/>VEPP-2000 &amp; VEPP-4M <lb/> Work at VEPP-4M: accumulation of electrons in a <lb/>booster ring VEPP-3 to current 200 мА in one minute; <lb/>energy rise to 1.8 GeV in 10 minutes; transportation of <lb/>electrons to collider VEPP-4M; a polarity reversal of <lb/>booster ring VEPP-3 in 2 minutes; accumulation of <lb/>positrons to 200 мА; transportation to VEPP-4M collider, <lb/>once again electrons and positrons. After injection to the <lb/>collider of two bunches of electrons and two bunches of <lb/>positrons, there is a rise to the energy of experiment from <lb/>1 to 5.5 GeV per bunch. Receiving four bunches and <lb/>energy rise takes 1 hour. After that experiment runs 3 <lb/>hours. <lb/>Work of the accelerator complex VEPP-2000 differs <lb/>from VEPP-4M. The collider of VEPP-2000 can work for <lb/>experiment constantly as its booster ring BEP is capable <lb/>to change the energy in all range of experiments from <lb/>0.16 to 1 GeV per bunch. After receiving electrons, BEP <lb/>boost them to the energy of experiment in 10 seconds. <lb/>After transportation of electrons to VEPP-2000 collider, <lb/>the booster reverses polarity in 20 seconds. Then BEP <lb/>takes positrons, increases their energy, transports to <lb/>collider ring, reverses polarity and so on. <lb/> TRANSPORTATION CHANNEL FROM <lb/>INJECTIOR VEPP-5 TO BOOSTER BEP <lb/> Geometry and optics <lb/> Figure 5: Location of the transportation channel in the <lb/>BINP. <lb/>The transportation channel layout is presented in <lb/>Figure 5. The detailed geometry and lattice functions are <lb/>shown in Figures 6-13. <lb/>Figure 6: Descent from the storage ring of VEPP-5. <lb/>Figure 7: Lattice functions of descent. <lb/>Figure 8: First horizontal bend. <lb/>Figure 9: Lattice functions of first horizontal bend in <lb/>regular part. <lb/>Figure 10: Second horizontal bend. <lb/>Figure 11: Lattice functions of second horizontal bend in <lb/>regular part.</body>

			<note place="headnote"> <lb/> Proceedings of RuPAC2014, Obninsk, Kaluga Region, Russia <lb/>FRCA03 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> 02 Colliders <lb/>ISBN 978-3-95450-170-0 <lb/></note>

			<page>463 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Copyright © 2014 CC-BY-3.0 and by the respective authors <lb/></note>

			<body> Figure 12: Ascent to booster BEP. <lb/>Figure 13: Lattice functions of ascent. <lb/> Beam Diagnostics and Vacuum <lb/> For beam diagnostics two types of sensors are used: 12 <lb/>luminophor probes and 23 image current monitors. Probes <lb/>used for the first beam-pass, they are not transparent for <lb/>the beam. Monitors are used for supervision of bunches at <lb/>the time of the beam-pass. They are located after the <lb/>dipole correctors with betatron phase advance of 2/3p. It <lb/>allows us to observe effectively the influence of dipole <lb/>correctors on a bunch trajectory. <lb/>At present the vacuum is 10 <lb/> -8 Torr, for this purpose 8 <lb/>pumps NMD-016 are installed. <lb/> Magnets and Power Supply <lb/> Magnets and power supplies of the transportation <lb/>channel are listed in Table 1. The first three power <lb/>supplies are in production. Other power supplies and all <lb/>magnets are already manufactured. <lb/> PERSPECTIVE <lb/> Work of beam-pass from Injection complex VEPP-5 to <lb/>the booster BEP is planned to carry out from December, <lb/>2014 to March, 2015. Experiment on collider VEPP-2000 <lb/>is planned to begin in May, 2014. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> ACKNOWLEDGMENT <lb/> Thanks to V.V. Anashin, L.N. Arapov, A.M. Batrakov, <lb/>O.V. Belikov, D.B. Burenkov, A.S. Churkin, <lb/>B.A. Dovzhenko, K.V. Dyakov, Yu.I. Koysin, <lb/>I.E. Korenev, <lb/>A.A. <lb/>Krasnov, <lb/>N.N. <lb/>Lebedev, <lb/>E.B. Levichev, <lb/>P.V. <lb/>Logatchev, <lb/>S.A. <lb/>Mishin, <lb/>M.I. Nepomnyaschykh, A.A. Novikov, A.V. Pavlenko, <lb/>A.V. Polyansky, R.Z. Pronik, V.P. Prosvetov, <lb/>O.A. Proskurina, V.V. Rashenko, A.L. Romanov, <lb/>S.I. Ruvinsky, <lb/>S.V. Seleznev, <lb/>L.E. <lb/>Serdakov, <lb/>A.N. Skrinsky, V.P. Cherepanov, Yu.M. Shatunov, <lb/>V.A. Shishkin, <lb/>D.B. Shwartz, <lb/>G.G. <lb/>Shumakov, <lb/>V.D. Yudin, Yu.M. Zharinov, V.K. Zhurba. <lb/>Table 1: Magnets and Power supplies <lb/> Element <lb/>Parameters <lb/>Power supply <lb/> 2 horizontal magnets, 1-st <lb/>bend <lb/>H=0.08T, <lb/>L=0.5m <lb/>1 DC, UM-20, <lb/>I=20A <lb/>2 horizontal magnets, 2-<lb/>nd bend <lb/>H=0.08T, <lb/>L=1.5m <lb/>1 DC, UM-20, <lb/>I=20A <lb/>4 vertical magnets of the <lb/>ascent to the booster BEP <lb/>H=0.7T, <lb/>L=1m <lb/>1 AC, GID-<lb/>3000, W=3kJ <lb/>1 horizontal magnet <lb/>before the septum magnet <lb/>in the booster BEP <lb/>H=1.7T, <lb/>L=0.3m <lb/>1 AC, <lb/>W=2.4kJ <lb/>1 septum magnet of the <lb/>booster BEP <lb/>H=1.7T, <lb/>L=0.4m <lb/>1 AC, <lb/>W=2.4kJ <lb/>42 lenses of regular part <lb/>G=2.5T/m, <lb/>L=0.2m <lb/>8 AC, GID-<lb/>25, W=25J <lb/>17 lenses of matching <lb/>parts <lb/>G=10-20T/m, <lb/>L=0.2m <lb/>17 AC, GID-<lb/>25, W=25J <lb/>12 dipole correctors in 12 <lb/>lenses <lb/>Hmax=0.2T, <lb/>L=0.1m <lb/>12 AC, GID-<lb/>25, W=25J <lb/>27 dipole correctors <lb/>Hmax=0.2T, <lb/>L=0.1m <lb/>27 DC, PS-3-<lb/>A, I=3A <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> REFERENCES <lb/> [1] Yu. Rogovsky et al., &quot; Status and Perspectives of the VEPP-<lb/>2000 Complex, &quot; TUY01, these proceedings. <lb/>[2] V.A. Kiselev et al., &quot; Particle and Accelerator Physics at the <lb/>VEPP-4M Collider, &quot; TUZ01, these proceedings. <lb/>[3] A.E. Bondar et al., &quot; Project of a Super Charm-Tau factory <lb/>at the Budker Institute of Nuclear Physics in Novosibirsk, &quot; <lb/>Physics of Atomic Nuclei, Volume 76 (September 2013), <lb/>Issue 9, pp 1072-1085. <lb/>[4] A. Starostenko et al., &quot; Status of Injection Complex VEPP-<lb/>5, &quot; TUY02, these proceedings. <lb/>[5] A.P. Lysenko et al., &quot; Program of numerical simulation of <lb/>accelerator structures RING, &quot; BINP, Novosibirsk. <lb/>[6] A.N. Dubrovin, &quot; Program of magnetic calculations <lb/>MERMAID, &quot; BINP, Novosibirsk. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> FRCA03 <lb/> Proceedings of RuPAC2014, Obninsk, Kaluga Region, Russia <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> ISBN 978-3-95450-170-0 <lb/></note>

			<page> 464 <lb/></page> 

			<note place="footnote"> Copyright © 2014 CC-BY-3.0 and by the respective authors <lb/> 02 Colliders <lb/></note>

	</text>
</tei>
