<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Gravity on All the Energy Steps. The Contours of a Future <lb/>Building <lb/> A.E.Shalyt-Margolin <lb/> 1 <lb/> National Centre of Particles and High Energy Physics, Pervomaiskaya Str. <lb/>18, Minsk 220088, Belarus <lb/> PACS: 03.65, 05.20 <lb/>Keywords:gravity,fundamental length,discrete parameters <lb/> Abstract <lb/> At the present time a theory of gravity is subdivided into two ab-<lb/>solutely different parts: low-energy theory represented by the Gen-<lb/>eral Relativity (GR) and hypothetical high-energy theory – Quan-<lb/>tum Gravity (QG) – that is still unresolved. In this way there is <lb/>a certain dichotomy in gravity considered as a unified theory. This <lb/>paper is an effort to reveal the main causes for such a dichotomy; <lb/>the means for departure from this dichotomy are proposed. By one <lb/>of the approaches gravity is considered at low and at high ener-<lb/>gies as a single whole dependent on the same parameters, which are <lb/>discrete for the fundamental length if present.There are grounds to <lb/>believe that in this case the mathematical formalism must be modi-<lb/>fied – all infinitesimal space-time quantities must be replaced by the <lb/>corresponding finite quantities dependent on the existent energies. <lb/>Possible approaches to this problem are proposed with the proper <lb/>illustrations. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1 Introduction. Gravity at Low and High <lb/>Energies and Main Problems. <lb/> At the present time a theory of gravity is subdivided into two absolutely <lb/>different parts: low-energy theory represented by the General Relativity <lb/></body>

			<front> 1  E-mail: a.shalyt@mail.ru; alexm@hep.by <lb/></front>

			<page> 1 <lb/></page>

			<body> (GR) that has been brilliantly verified by experiment and hypothetical high-<lb/>energy theory – Quantum Gravity (QG) – that is still unresolved. <lb/>The General Relativity (GR) is one of the most basic and beautiful phys-<lb/>ical theories advanced and accepted during the whole history of physical <lb/>science. It has been convincingly verified by the experiments (for example, <lb/>[1]). Nevertheless, some problems associated with GR still must be tackled. <lb/>The primary problem concerns extension of GR for high energies i.e. the <lb/>gravity quantization problem [2]–[6]. According to the generally recognized <lb/>viewpoint, the quantum effects in gravity are introduced at the Planck&apos;s <lb/>length scales l  P  = (G/c <lb/> 3  ) <lb/> 1/2 <lb/> ≈ 10 <lb/> −33  cm [5],[6]. <lb/>The majority of researchers agree that in the high-energy (quantum) limit <lb/>of gravity the minimal length l  min  appears inevitably and this length most <lb/>likely but (not necessarily!) is on the order of the Planck length l  min  ∝ <lb/> l  P  ,[2]–[6]. <lb/>Just with this point there is a discrepancy between the two above-mentioned <lb/>parts of gravity or, more precisely, between the mathematical apparatus <lb/>(instruments) of GR and of hypothetical QG. Starting from the highest <lb/>(Planck) energies E  P  and from a minimal length l  min  ∝ l  P  in QG and <lb/> ≪  coming down the energy steps  ≫  , in GR we, in accordance with the Heisen-<lb/>berg Uncertainty Principle (HUP), should have arrived at the length scales <lb/>considerably exceeding l  min  but, quite the contrary, all the mathematical <lb/>apparatus of GR is based on the notion of infinitesimal variations in the <lb/>space-time quantities. <lb/>Really, the current mathematical formalism of the theory [8] is utterly in-<lb/>compatible with the HUP [9]: <lb/>∆x  i  ∆p  i  ≥ <lb/> 2 <lb/> . <lb/> (1) <lb/>Or for the pair energy -time we have <lb/>∆E∆t ≥ <lb/> 2 <lb/> . <lb/> (2) <lb/>The explanation is that the mathematical formalism of GR is based on the <lb/>concept of infinitesimal variations in the space-time quantities ds, dx  µ  , ..., <lb/> which for a probe particle, in accordance with (1),(2), will inevitably result <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body> in the infinitely large momentum and energy fluctuations <lb/>∆p  i  → ∞; ∆E → ∞. <lb/> (3) <lb/>But then, if measurable quantities are concerned, (3) is in conflict with GR <lb/>because, as immediately follows from (3), when measuring the character-<lb/>istics for variations in the probe particle positions within the scope of GR <lb/>and, actually, being at low energies, we can derive the momentum and en-<lb/>ergy characteristic for the scales of Quantum Gravity (QG)! In other words, <lb/>by this procedure GR, in fact, exceeds its own limits. As a consequence, <lb/>the theory becomes nonclosed (at least with respect to HUP) but it should <lb/>not be. It is clear that this nonclosure arises from the <lb/> mathematical formalism of GR admitting the existence of in-<lb/>finitesimal variations in the space-time quantities . <lb/> The apparent incompatibility of the mathematical apparatus (in-<lb/>struments) used in GR and HUP is the main cause (problem) of <lb/> dichotomy between GR and QG, provided we suppose that the <lb/>fundamental quantities involved in the theory are measurable. <lb/> It is clear that gravity as a unified theory considered independent of the <lb/>energies should be saved from this limitation. Then it is clear that in a <lb/>future gravity theory, valid for any energy (low or high), GR should arise <lb/>in the low-energy limit to a high degree of accuracy. In other words, the <lb/>future Quantum Gravity that at low energies would become GR to a high <lb/>accuracy should be built as a high-energy deformation of the latter. <lb/> The deformation is understood as an extension of a particular the-<lb/>ory by inclusion of one or several additional parameters in such a <lb/>way that the initial theory appears in the limiting transition [7]. <lb/>What are the parameters of interest in the case under study? Proceeding <lb/>from the above, the parameters must be inevitably associated with l  min <lb/> (probably with l  min  ∝ l  P  )and hence E  P  . <lb/> This means that in a high-energy gravitation theory the energy-<lb/>or, what is the same, measuring scales-dependent parameters should <lb/>be necessarily introduced. <lb/> But, on the other hand, these parameters could hardly disappear totally <lb/>at low energies, i.e. for GR too. However, since the well-known canonical <lb/>(and in essence the classical) statement of GR has no such parameters [8], <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body> the inference is as follows: their influence at low energies is so small that it <lb/>may be disregarded at the modern stage in evolution of the theory and of <lb/>the experiment. <lb/> Still this does not imply that they should be ignored in future evo-<lb/>lution of the theory, especially on going to its high-energy limit. <lb/> This is one more (implicit) problem of the above-mentioned dichotomy be-<lb/>tween GR and QG. <lb/> The problem in the explicit form may be stated as follows: <lb/> what (latent) parameters exist in GR considering the minimal <lb/>length l  min  ? <lb/>This work is motivated by a search for the unifying principles <lb/>for GR and QG aimed at elimination of the above-indicated di-<lb/>chotomy between them. More exactly, we look for the identical <lb/>parameters, possibly unifying both theories but varying for each <lb/>of them in different domains, which will allow for the solution of <lb/>the above-stated problems. <lb/> Clearly, for solution of the first problem, the mathematical formalism presently <lb/>used for the General Relativity should be revised if we want to derive a the-<lb/>ory measurable from the viewpoint of Quantum Mechanics, (i.e., at least <lb/>compatible with HUP). <lb/> All the infinitesimal space-time quantities ds, dx  µ  , ... in General <lb/>Relativity should be replaced by the finite quantities dependent <lb/>on the measuring scales l (energies E ∼ 1/l): <lb/> ds <lb/> 2 <lb/> → τ s <lb/> 2  (l); dx  µ  → τ x  µ  (l), ... <lb/> (4) <lb/>With such a problem stating, the deformation parameters mentioned in the <lb/>first part of this Introduction will be introduced quite naturally both in <lb/>the low-energy and high-energy, quantum, domain of this theory. And only <lb/>on going from one domain to the other their values, perhaps their physical <lb/>meaning, will be changed, possibly leading to a solution of the second <lb/>problem at hand. <lb/> It seems expedient to emphasize once more that in this case the matter <lb/>concerns modification of the mathematical formalism in accordance with <lb/>the above arguments (appearing logical, consistent, and convincing) rather <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body> than GR itself. In what follows one of the approaches to solving of the <lb/>problem at hand is be proposed. <lb/>This work is a continuation of the paper [10] and, because of this it is <lb/>somewhat intertwined with it. <lb/> 2 Quantum Fluctuations of Space-Time and <lb/>New Parameters in Gravity <lb/> To solve the above-mentioned problems, initially we can use the Space-<lb/>Time Quantum Fluctuations (STQF) imposing considerable constraints on <lb/>HUP with regard to gravity. The definition (STQF) is closely connected to <lb/>the notion of &quot; space-time foam &quot; . <lb/>The notion &quot; space-time foam &quot; , introduced by J. A. Wheeler about 60 years <lb/>ago for the description and investigation of physics at Planck&apos;s scales (Early <lb/>Universe) [11],[12], is fairly settled. Despite the fact that in the last decade <lb/>numerous works have been devoted to physics at Planck&apos;s scales within the <lb/>scope of this notion, for example [13]–[32], by this time still their no clear <lb/>understanding of the &quot; space-time foam &quot; as it is. <lb/>On the other hand, it is undoubtful that a quantum theory of the Early <lb/>Universe should be a deformation of the well-known quantum theory. <lb/>In my works with the colleagues [33]–[41] I has put forward one of the pos-<lb/>sible approaches to resolution of a quantum theory at Planck&apos;s scales on the <lb/>basis of the density matrix deformation. <lb/>In accordance with the modern concepts, the space-time foam [12] notion <lb/>forms the basis for space-time at Planck&apos;s scales (Big Bang). This object <lb/>is associated with the quantum fluctuations generated by uncertainties in <lb/>measurements of the fundamental quantities, inducing uncertainties in any <lb/>distance measurement. A precise description of the space-time foam is still <lb/>lacking along with an adequate quantum gravity theory. But for the de-<lb/>scription of quantum fluctuations we have a number of interesting methods <lb/>(for example, [42],[22]-[32]). <lb/>In what follows, we use the terms and symbols from [24]. Then for the <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body> fluctuations <lb/> δl of the distance l we have the following estimate: <lb/> δl ∼ &gt; l <lb/> γ <lb/> P  l <lb/> 1−γ  = l  P  ( <lb/> l <lb/>l  P <lb/> ) <lb/> 1−γ  = l( <lb/>l  P <lb/> l <lb/> ) <lb/> γ  , <lb/> (5) <lb/>where 0 ≤ γ ≤ 1. <lb/>At the present time three principal models associated with different values <lb/>of the parameter γ are considered: <lb/>A) γ = 1 that conforms to the initial (canonical) model from [11],[12] <lb/> δl ∼ &gt; l  P  ; <lb/>(6) <lb/>B) γ = 2/3 that conforms to the Salecker -Wigner model (inequalities) <lb/>[42],[24] compatible with the holographic principle [43]–[47] <lb/> δl ∼ &gt; (ll <lb/> 2 <lb/> P  ) <lb/> 1/3  = l  P <lb/> ( <lb/> l <lb/>l  P <lb/> )  1/3 <lb/> ; <lb/>(7) <lb/>C) γ = 1/2 -random-walk model [31] [32] <lb/> δl ∼ &gt; (ll  P  ) <lb/> 1/2  = l  P <lb/> ( <lb/> l <lb/>l  P <lb/> )  1/2 <lb/> . <lb/> (8) <lb/>But, because of the experimental data obtained with the help of the Hub-<lb/>ble Space Telescope [48], a random-walk model C) may be excluded from <lb/>consideration (for example, see [29]) and is omitted in this work. <lb/>Moreover, in fact it is clear that at Planck&apos;s scales, i.e. for <lb/> l →∝ l  P <lb/> (9) <lb/> models A) are B) are coincident. <lb/> Using (6)–(8), we can derive the quantum fluctuations for all the primary <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body> characteristics, specifically for the time <lb/> δt, energy <lb/> δE, and metrics <lb/> δg  µν  . In <lb/>particular, for <lb/> δg  µν  we can use formula (10) in [24] <lb/> δg  µν  ∼ &gt; (l  P  /l) <lb/> γ  . <lb/> (10) <lb/>Let us denote the parameter l  P  /l in terms of λ as follows: <lb/> λ  l  ≡ <lb/> l  P <lb/> l <lb/>. <lb/> (11) <lb/>What is the principal meaning of STQF? It is important that with al-<lb/>lowance for the gravitational interactions they impose hard constraints on <lb/>the quantities ∆x  i  , ∆p  i  , ∆E, ∆t..., ... and hence on HUP depending on <lb/>the existing scales and energies. The energies will have nonzero minimal <lb/>(and correspondingly maximal) values which depend on the existent ener-<lb/>gies (measuring scale) and Planck&apos;s energies. <lb/>As mentioned in the previous Section, there are no infinitesimal variations <lb/>in space-time quantities and no infinitely large variations of momenta and <lb/>energies. <lb/>The Generalized Uncertainty Principle (GUP) that is an extension of HUP <lb/>for Planck&apos;s energies, where gravity must be taken into consideration [49]– <lb/>[56], conveys the same, namely: <lb/> △x ≥ <lb/> △p <lb/> + α <lb/> ′  l <lb/> 2 <lb/> P <lb/> △p <lb/> , <lb/> (12) <lb/>where α <lb/> ′  is the model-dependent dimensionless numerical factor. <lb/>(12) leads to the minimal length l  min  ∝ l  P  . But this minimum is global as <lb/>it is dependent only on l  P  and model parameters of GUP, being independent <lb/>of the measuring scale l. <lb/> GUP (12) leads to the same minimal boundary l  min  ∝ l  P  for the measuring <lb/>scale l as the heuristic model A)(6). However, even J. A. Wheeler has used <lb/>(6) not over the whole energy range but at Planck&apos;s scales only. Because <lb/>of this, the model for STQF governed by (6) is limited, in essence being <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body> a particular case of the Salecker -Wigner model B) but on going to the <lb/>Planck scales. <lb/>In what follows we assume the presence of a minimal length on the or-<lb/>der of the Planck length l  min  ∝ l  P  . This fact may be inferred from GUP or <lb/>may be taken independently without regard to GUP. <lb/>Then it is obvious that any quantity having the dimensions of length is <lb/>quantized, i.e. is determined by a discrete set of values as follows from the <lb/>obvious statement: <lb/> Provided some quantity has a minimal measuring unit, values of <lb/>this quantity are multiples of this unit. <lb/> Naturally, any quantity having a minimal measuring unit is uniformly dis-<lb/>crete. <lb/>The latter property is not met, in particular, by the energy E. <lb/> As E ∼ 1/l, where l – measurable scale, <lb/> the energy E is a discrete quantity but the nonuniformly discrete <lb/>one. <lb/> It is clear that the difference between the adjacent values of E is the less <lb/>the lower E. In other words, for <lb/> E ≪ E  P <lb/> (13) <lb/> E becomes a practically continuous quantity. <lb/>Note that all the above-mentioned models of STQF A)–C) are actually de-<lb/>pendent on one and the same dimensionless parameter λ  l  and on the Planck <lb/>quantities l  P  , E  P  ...). Since l  min  ∝ l  P  with the constant proportionality fac-<lb/>tor (in a particular case of GUP this is the model-dependent quantity α <lb/> ′ <lb/> (12)), this parameter may be represented by l  min  /l or (at least within the <lb/>scope of HUP or of a linear variant of GUP [57],[58]) by E/E  max  ∝ E/E  P  . <lb/>In the above notation (5) takes the form <lb/>( <lb/> δl)  min  = βl <lb/> γ <lb/>P  l <lb/> 1−γ  = βl  P  ( <lb/> l <lb/>l  P <lb/> ) <lb/> 1−γ  = βlλ <lb/> γ <lb/>l  , <lb/> (14) <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body> where 1/2 &lt; γ &lt; 1 and β is a numerical factor on the order of unity [59]. <lb/>Obviously, we get <lb/>( <lb/> δt)  min  = c <lb/> −1  ( <lb/> δl)  min  . <lb/> (15) <lb/>And then in formula (4) the corresponding substitution may be as follows: <lb/> ds <lb/> 2 <lb/>  → τ s <lb/> 2  (l) ∼ ( <lb/> δl) <lb/> 2 <lb/> min  = β <lb/> 2  l <lb/> 2  λ <lb/> 2γ <lb/> l  , <lb/>dx  µ  → τ x  µ  (l) ∼ l. <lb/> (16) <lb/>Now it is clear that for the metric g  µν  (x) there is a dependence on l (or on <lb/>the corresponding energy E) <lb/>g  µν  (x) → g  µν  (x, l) = g  µν  (x, λ <lb/> γ <lb/>l  ). <lb/>(17) <lb/>As l is quantized in units of l  min  ∝ l  P  , we obtain (16) in terms of Planck&apos;s <lb/>quantities and of the natural parameter k  l  in the following way: <lb/> τ s <lb/> 2  (l) ∼ ( <lb/> δl) <lb/> 2 <lb/> min  = <lb/> βk <lb/> 2−2γ <lb/> l <lb/> l <lb/> 2 <lb/> P  , <lb/> (18) <lb/>where k  l  = l/l  min  and <lb/> β has the factor β and the corresponding factor due <lb/>to the ratio l  min  /l  P  . <lb/>Note that at low energies the flat metric (1, −1, −1, −1), with a high degree <lb/>of accuracy, gives the ansatz: <lb/> g  µν  (x) = (±δ  µν  exp(±λ <lb/> γ <lb/>l  )), <lb/>where the sign + before δ  µν  corresponds to the case µ = ν = 0 only. <lb/>Thus, from the start, we obtain some discrete set of the initial data whose <lb/>variations are governed by the nonuniformly discrete parameter λ  l  . At low <lb/>energies E ≪ E  P  , i.e. for k  l  ≫ 1, its variation is almost continuous because <lb/>the intervals between the adjacent points λ  l  will be constantly reducing as <lb/> E is decreased(or similarly as l is increased) and a practically continuous <lb/>theory arises in the limit E → 0. <lb/>At high energies, with E ≈ E  P  or k  l  → 1, it will be really discrete. Ob-<lb/>viously, in this case it is responsible for great fluctuations of the metric <lb/>(17). <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body> 3 Dimensionless Parameter λ l  and Thermo-<lb/>dynamic Approach to Gravity. Some Il-<lb/>lustrations. <lb/> Note also that, in fact, the nonuniformly discrete parameter λ  l  (11) is in-<lb/>troduced as a deformation parameter on going from the well-known quan-<lb/>tum mechanics (QM) to a quantum mechanics with the fundamental length <lb/>(QMFL), provided this length l  min  is on the order of Planck&apos;s length l  min  ∝ <lb/> l  P  , as revealed by the author in the works written with his colleagues [33] <lb/>–[41]. The main concept of these works is a high-energy (Planck&apos;s) defor-<lb/>mation of the well-known quantum-mechanical density matrix ρ. <lb/> Yet it should be noted that actually in works [33] –[41] the author has used <lb/>the parameter λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> l <lb/> α  l  = l <lb/> 2 <lb/> min  /l <lb/> 2 <lb/> ∝ λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> l  . <lb/> (19) <lb/>This parameter up to a factor is variable within the interval <lb/>0 &lt; α  l  ≤ 1/4, <lb/>(20) <lb/>whereas the density matrix in QMFL becomes deformed and dependent on <lb/> α  l  : ρ = ρ(α  l  ), and we get <lb/>lim <lb/> α  l  →0 <lb/> ρ(α  l  ) → ρ, <lb/> (21) <lb/>where ρ – known density matrix from QM. <lb/>In this way the condition (20) naturally resultant from the procedure giving <lb/>rise to the deformed density matrix ρ(α  l  ) imposes a natural constraint on <lb/> λ due to l ≥ 2l  min  . <lb/>In the last few years new very interesting approaches to gravity studies <lb/>have been proposed, which may be divided into &quot; thermodynamical &quot; and <lb/> &quot; theoretical-informational &quot; approaches. The approach suggested in the pi-<lb/>oneer work by T. Jacobson [60] has been considerably extended in a series <lb/>of remarkable papers by T.Padmanabhan [61]–[72]. <lb/>As shown in [71], the Einstein Equation for several cases of horizon spaces <lb/>may be written as a thermodynamic identity (the first principle of thermo-<lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body> dynamics): ([71], formula (119)) <lb/> cf <lb/> ′  (a) <lb/>4π <lb/> k  B  T <lb/>c <lb/> 3 <lb/> G <lb/>d <lb/> ( <lb/> 1 <lb/>4 <lb/>4πa <lb/> 2 <lb/> ) <lb/> dS <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> c <lb/> 4  da <lb/>G <lb/> −dE <lb/> = P d <lb/> ( <lb/> 4π <lb/>3 <lb/> a <lb/> 3 <lb/> ) <lb/> P dV <lb/>, <lb/> (22) <lb/>where a static, spherically symmetric horizon in space-time is described by <lb/>the metric <lb/> ds <lb/> 2  = −f (r)c <lb/> 2  dt <lb/> 2  + f <lb/> −1  (r)dr <lb/> 2  + r <lb/> 2  dΩ <lb/> 2  , <lb/> (23) <lb/>and the horizon location will be given by simple zero of the function f (r) <lb/>(f (a) = 0, f <lb/> ′  (a) ̸ = 0) at r = a.( Here r = a is the radius of a sphere.) And <lb/> P = T <lb/> r <lb/>r  is the trace of the momentum-energy tensor and radial pressure. <lb/>In Sections 5 and 6 of [73] first the Einstein Equations on horizon (22) have <lb/>been written in terms of the parameter α  a  , next the high-energy (α  a  → 1/4), <lb/> α  a  – deformation of these equations has been derived in two different cases: <lb/>equilibrium and nonequilibrium thermodynamics. <lb/>The latter case is distinguished from the first one by the dynamic cosmo-<lb/>logical term dependent on α  a  , appearing with the corresponding factor in <lb/>the right side of high-energy deformed (22) as follows: <lb/>Λ = Λ[α  a  ]. <lb/>(24) <lb/>It is evident that by virtue of (19) the α  a  – deformation of these equations <lb/>is equivalent to their λ  a  – deformation, and we have <lb/>Λ = Λ[α  a  ] = Λ[λ  a  ]. <lb/>(25) <lb/>Also, it is noteworthy that the parameter λ  l  (11) is implicitly introduced in <lb/>the noted work by E. Verlinde [74], where gravity is considered as an &quot; En-<lb/>tropic Force &quot; . But, since for R ≫ l  P  , where R – radius of a holographic <lb/>screen, its value is close to zero λ  R  ≈ 0 and varies very smoothly, it is <lb/>omitted in the final formulae at low energies [74]. <lb/>However, at high (Planck&apos;s) energies on going to the GUP-correction and <lb/>further on to the high-energy deformation of Einstein equations it is in-<lb/>evitable as shown in the latest works [75](evidently in formulae ((27)– <lb/>(39),[76] (and in the implicit form in (32)–(36)). <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body> So, at least for horizon spaces the parameter λ  R  is just the la-<lb/>tent parameter of GR mentioned in Section 1, infinitesimal at <lb/>low energies λ  R  ≈ 0 but turning to λ  R  → 1/2 on going to high <lb/>(Planck&apos;s) energies (i.e., to QG). <lb/> This parameter in the &quot; energy representation &quot;  ∼ E/E  P  is directly or in-<lb/>directly introduced in all the formulae of the noted review on Quantum-<lb/>Spacetime Phenomenology [2]. <lb/> 4 Conclusion <lb/> Thus, provided the main concept of this work is realized, at all energy <lb/>levels gravity may be governed by the same set of discrete param-<lb/>eterswhich still have different variation rates and differing values in the <lb/>low-and high-energy regions. The transfer from low energies (GR) to high <lb/>(Planck) energies (QG) may be schematically represented as <lb/> GR[k  l  ≫ 1, λ ≈ 0, ...] → QG[k  l  → 1, λ → 1, ...]. <lb/> (26) <lb/>However, as noted in [7], in nature the direction was opposite – from high <lb/>to low energies. Because of this, it seems more natural to consider the <lb/>transition opposite to (26), in [7] referred to as the  ≪  dequantization  ≫  : <lb/> QG[k  l  → 1, λ → 1, ...] → GR[k  l  ≫ 1, λ ≈ 0, ...] <lb/> (27) <lb/>The parameter set in the left and right sides of (26),(27) is the same. The <lb/>dots in parenthesis are given for additional parameters which may arise in <lb/>the process of a theory resolution. <lb/>It is important that in this case gravity could be considered as a single <lb/>whole without its subdivision into the Classical Gravity (GR) and <lb/>Quantum Gravity (QG). <lb/> Of course, the dependence of the principal space-time quantities on the <lb/>measuring scale l (existing energy E) that is based on STQF and suggested <lb/>in (16)–(18) is very tentative and may vary in the process of the theory evo-<lb/>lution. Still, by author&apos;s opinion, a set of the principal discrete parameters <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body> in (26) will be invariant with respect to these variations. <lb/>The primary criterion for resolution of a future theory must be the Con-<lb/> formity Principle: <lb/> on going to low energies GR must be reproduced to a high degree of accu-<lb/>racy, at least its experimentally verified part. <lb/>The title of this work is not chosen by chance as gravity by this ap-<lb/>proach for all the energy levels is treated as a single whole (one <lb/>building), where the descent from the upper levels (steps) to the <lb/>lower ones by the energy steps is governed by a single discrete <lb/>parameter λ  l  , the step height being steadily reduced as we descend <lb/>lower and lower, whereas their length ∼ l will be ever increasing . <lb/>The proposed concept is rather important for better understanding and <lb/>investigation of the cosmological term Λ, especially in view of the Dark <lb/>Energy Problem [77]–[81]. In principle, they may be used to answer the <lb/>question whether Λ = const or Λ = Λ(t) is a time-variable quantity. <lb/>Despite the fact that the works taking Λ as Λ(t), i.e. as a dynamic quan-<lb/>tity, are numerous(for example, [82]– [85]) quite forceful arguments are given <lb/>against this point of view (for example, [86]). <lb/>Indeed, according to the General Relativity, the cosmological term Λ has <lb/>been considered constant Λ = const as, due to the Bianchi identities [8], <lb/> ∇ <lb/> µ  G  µν  = 0. <lb/>(28) <lb/>But in this work it has been demonstrated that, actually, Bianchi identities <lb/>(28) are introduced at the low-energy limit only <lb/>lim <lb/> λ  l  →0 <lb/> ∇ <lb/> µ  G <lb/> [λ  l  ] <lb/> µν  = ∇ <lb/> µ  G  µν  = 0. <lb/>(29) <lb/>Because of this, the really measured cosmological term Λ in fact is dynamic <lb/>Λ = Λ[λ  l  (t)], practically invariable in the modern epoch, i.e. at low energies, <lb/>due to slow variations of the deformation parameter λ  l  (t) at low energies <lb/>and due to its very small value. <lb/>In the works [87]–[89] a behavior of the term Λ has been studied reasoning <lb/>from α  l  (t) on the assumption that it is dynamic, similar to the case proven <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body> in [87] GUP for the pair of conjugate variables (Λ, V ), where V is the space-<lb/>time volume, as with the holographic principle applied to the whole Universe <lb/>[90], where α  l  ∝ λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> l  because of (19),(20) of the Section 3. And as noted in <lb/>(25) α  l  -deformation theory is equivalent to its λ  l  -deformation, (in fact to <lb/>its λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> l  -deformation). <lb/>Then the main difference of these two different cases, examined in [87]–[89] <lb/>is in the leading order of expansion Λ[λ] in terms of λ. In the first case it is <lb/>the second <lb/>Λ <lb/> GU P  (λ) ∝ (λ <lb/> 4  + η  1  λ <lb/> 6  + ...)Λ  p  , <lb/> (30) <lb/>whereas in the second case it is the first <lb/>Λ <lb/> Hol  (λ) ∝ (λ <lb/> 2  + ξ  1  λ <lb/> 4  + ...)Λ  p  , <lb/> (31) <lb/>where Λ  p  = Λ  λ→1/2  – cosmological term at Planck&apos;s scales. <lb/>As Λ <lb/> Hol  is practically coincident with the experimental value of the cosmo-<lb/>logical term Λ  exper  , a holographic model is preferable – model B) of Section <lb/>2 developed for quantum fluctuations is supported experimentally. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] R.Penrose,Quantum Theory and Space-Time, Fourth Lecture in Stephen <lb/>Hawking and Roger Penrose, The Nature of Space and Time, Prinseton <lb/>University Press, 1996. <lb/>[2] G. Amelino-Camelia,Living Rev.Rel.16 (2013) 5; <lb/>arXiv:gr-<lb/>qc/0806.0339. <lb/>[3] L. Garay, Int.J.Mod.Phys.A. 10 (1995) 145. <lb/>[4] G. Amelino-Camelia, L. Smolin, Phys.Rev.D. 80 2009 (2009) 084017; <lb/>G.Gubitosi G. et al., JCAP. 0908, (2009), 021; G. Amelino-Camelia, <lb/>Int.J.Mod.Phys.D. 14, (2005) 2167. <lb/>[5] S. Hossenfelder, Phys. Lett.B. 575 (2003), 85; S. Hossenfelder, <lb/>Phys.Rev.D. 70 (2004) 105003; S. Hossenfelder, Class. Quant. Grav. 23 <lb/> (2006) 1815. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [6] S. Hossenfelder, Living Rev.Rel. 16 (2013) 2; arXiv:gr-qc/1203.6191. <lb/>[7] L.Faddeev, Priroda. 5 (1989) 11. <lb/>[8] Robert. M. Wald, General Relativity, The University Chicago Press <lb/>Chicago and London (1984). <lb/>[9] W. Heisenberg, Zeitschrift fur Physik. 43 (1927) 172. English transla-<lb/>tion: J. A. Wheeler and H. Zurek, Quantum Theory and Measurement <lb/>Princeton Univ. Press, 1983, pp. 62-84. <lb/>[10] A.E.Shalyt-Margolin,Spacetime Quantum Fluctuations, Minimal <lb/>Length and Einstein Equations,arXiv:1306.1143 <lb/>[11] J. A. Wheeler,Geometrodynamics (Academic Press, New York and Lon-<lb/>don, 1962). <lb/>[12] C. W. Misner, K. S. Thorne, and J. A. Wheeler, Gravitation Freeman, <lb/>San Francisco, (1973). <lb/>[13] Remo Garattini, Int. J. Mod. Phys. D. 4 (2002) 635. <lb/>[14] Remo Garattini, Entropy. 2 (2000) 26. <lb/>[15] Remo Garattini, Nucl.Phys.Proc.Suppl. 88 (2000) 297. <lb/>[16] Remo Garattini, Phys.Lett.B. 459 (1999) 461. <lb/>[17] Fabio Scardigli, Class.Quant.Grav. 14 (1997) 1781. <lb/>[18] Fabio Scardigli, Phys.Lett.B. 452 (1999) 39. <lb/>[19] Fabio Scardigli, Nucl.Phys.Proc.Suppl. 88 (2000) 291. <lb/>[20] Luis J. Garay, Phys.Rev. D. 58 (1998) 124015. <lb/>[21] Luis J. Garay, Phys.Rev.Lett. 80 (1998) 2508. <lb/>[22] Y. J. Ng, H. van Dam, Found. Phys. 30 (2000) 795. <lb/>[23] Y. J. Ng, Int. J. Mod. Phys. D. 11 (2002) 1585. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [24] Y. J. Ng, Mod.Phys.Lett.A. 18 (2003) 1073 <lb/>[25] Y. J. Ng, gr-qc/0401015. <lb/>[26] Y. J. Ng, H. van Dam, Int.J.Mod.Phys.A. 20 (2005) 1328. <lb/>[27] W.A. Christiansen, Y. Jack Ng and H. van Dam, Phys.Rev.Lett. 96 <lb/> (2006) 051301. <lb/>[28] Y. Jack Ng, Phys.Lett.B. 657 (2007) 10. <lb/>[29] Y. Jack Ng, AIP Conf.Proc. 1115 (2009) 74. <lb/>[30] A. Wayne Christiansen, David J. E. Floyd, Y. Jack Ng, Eric S. Perlman, <lb/>Phys.Rev.D. 83 (2011) 084003. <lb/>[31] G. Amelino-Camelia, Nature. 398 (1999) 216. <lb/>[32] L. Diosi and B. Lukacs, Phys. Lett. A142 (1989) 331. <lb/>[33] A.E. Shalyt-Margolin and J.G. Suarez, gr-qc/0302119. <lb/>[34] A.E. Shalyt-Margolin and J.G. Suarez, Intern. Journ. Mod. Phys. D. <lb/> 12 (2003) 1265. <lb/>[35] A.E. Shalyt-Margolin and A.Ya. Tregubovich, Mod. Phys.Lett. A. 19 <lb/> (2004) 71. <lb/>[36] A.E. Shalyt-Margolin, Mod. Phys. Lett. A. 19 (2004) 391. <lb/>[37] A.E. Shalyt-Margolin, Mod. Phys. Lett. A. 19 (2004) 2037. <lb/>[38] A.E. Shalyt-Margolin, Intern. Journ. Mod.Phys. D. 13 (2004) 853. <lb/>[39] A.E. Shalyt-Margolin, Intern.Journ.Mod.Phys.A. 20 (2005) 4951. <lb/>[40] A.E. Shalyt-Margolin, V.I. Strazhev, Proc. Sixth International Sym-<lb/>posium &quot; Frontiers of Fundamental and Computational Physics &quot; ,ed. B.G. <lb/>Sidharth, Springer (2006) p. 131. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [41] A.E. Shalyt-Margolin, Quantum Cosmology Research Trends,ed. A. <lb/>Reimer (Horizons in World Physics. 246, Nova Science Publishers, Inc., <lb/>Hauppauge, NY, (2005) p. 49. <lb/>[42] E.P. Wigner, Rev. Mod. Phys. 29 (1957) 255; H. Salecker, E.P. Wigner, <lb/>Phys. Rev. 109 (1958) 571. <lb/>[43] G. &apos;T. Hooft, gr-qc/9310026. <lb/> [44] G. &apos;T. Hooft, hep-th/0003004 ; <lb/>[45] L.Susskind, J. Math. Phys. 36 (1995) 6377. <lb/>[46] R. Bousso, Rev. Mod. Phys. 74 (2002) 825. <lb/>[47] R. Bousso, JHEP. 07 (1999) 004. <lb/>[48] E. S. Perlman et al., Astron. J. 124, 2401–2412 (2002) <lb/>[49] G. A. Veneziano, Europhys.Lett. 2 (1986) 199. <lb/>[50] D. Amati, M. Ciafaloni, and G. A. Veneziano, Phys.Lett.B. 216 (1989) <lb/>41. <lb/>[51] E.Witten, Phys.Today. 49 (1996) 24. <lb/>[52] R. J. Adler,D. I. Santiago, Mod. Phys. Lett. A. 14 (1999) 1371. <lb/>[53] D.V.Ahluwalia, Phys.Lett. A275 (2000) 31. <lb/>[54] D.V.Ahluwalia, Mod.Phys.Lett. A17 (2002) 1135. <lb/>[55] M. Maggiore, Phys.Lett. B. 319 (1993) 83. <lb/>[56] A. Kempf, G. Mangano and R.B. Mann, Phys.Rev.D. 52 (1995) 1108. <lb/>[57] S. Das, E. C. Vagenas and A. F. Ali, PhysLett.B. 690, (2010) 407, <lb/>arXiv:1005.3368 [hep-th]. <lb/>[58] A. Tawfik,JCAP. 07 (2013) 040, arXiv:1307.1894. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [59] M. Maziashvili,Phys. Rev. D. 86 (2012) 104066,arXiv:1206.4388. <lb/>[60] T. Jacobson, Phys. Rev. Lett. 75 (1995) 1260. <lb/>[61] T. Padmanabhan, Int.Jorn.Mod.Phys. D14 (2005) 2263. <lb/>[62] T. Padmanabhan, Gen.Rel.Grav. 34,(2002) 2029. <lb/>[63] T. Padmanabhan, Braz.J.Phys. 35 (2005) 362. <lb/>[64] T. Padmanabhan, Int.J.Mod.Phys.D. 15 (2006) 1659. <lb/>[65] A.Mukhopadhyay, T. Padmanabhan, Phys.Rev.D. 74 (2006) 124023. <lb/>[66] T. Padmanabhan, Gen.Rel.Grav. 40 (2008) 529. <lb/>[67] T. Padmanabhan, A. Paranjape, Phys.Rev.D. 75 (2007) 064004. <lb/>[68] T. Padmanabhan, AIP Conference Proceedings. 939 (2007) 114. <lb/>[69] T. Padmanabhan, Phys.Rept. 406 (2005) 49. <lb/>[70] A. Paranjape, S.Sarkar and T. Padmanabhan, Phys.Rev.D. 74 (2006) <lb/>104015. <lb/>[71] T. Padmanabhan, Rep. Prog. Phys. 74 (2010) 046901. <lb/>[72] T. Padmanabhan, Mod.Phys.Lett.A. 25 (2010) 1129. <lb/>[73] A.E. Shalyt-Margolin, Intern. J. Mod. Phys. D. 21 (2012) 1250013. <lb/>[74] E. Verlinde, JHEP. 1104 (2011) 029. <lb/>[75] A. E. Shalyt-Margolin, Advances in High Energy Physics, 2013 (2013) <lb/>384084, arXiv:1205.6988. <lb/>[76] Barun Majumder, Advances in High Energy Physics. 2013 (2013) <lb/>296836, arXiv:1310.1165. <lb/>[77] S.Perlmutter et al., Astrophys. J. 517 (1999) 565. <lb/>[78] A. G. Riess et al., Astron. J. 116 (1998) 1009. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [79] A. G.Riess et al., Astron. J. 117 (1999) 707. <lb/>[80] V. Sahni and A. A. Starobinsky, Int. J. Mod. Phys. D. 9 (2000) 373. <lb/>[81] S. M. Carroll, Living Rev. Rel. 4 (2001) 1. <lb/>[82] O. Bertolami, N. Cim. B. 93 (1986) 36. <lb/>[83] J.C. Carvalho,J.A.S Lima and I. Waga, Phys. Rev. D. 46 (1992) 2404. <lb/>[84] L.P. Chimento and D. Pavon, Gen. Rel. Grav. 30 (1998) 643. <lb/>[85] T. Harco and M.K. Mak, Gen. Rel. Grav. 31 (1999) 849. <lb/>[86] A.D. Dolgov, Phys.Atom.Nucl. 71 (2008) 651. <lb/>[87] A.E. Shalyt-Margolin, Entropy. 12 (2010) 932. <lb/>[88] A.E. Shalyt-Margolin, Intern. J. Theor. Math. Phys. 1 (2011) 1. <lb/>[89] A.E. Shalyt-Margolin, Entropy. 14 (2012) 2143. <lb/>[90] W. Fischler and L. Susskind, hep-th/9806039. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 19 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
