<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Exactly solvable deformations of the oscillator and Coulomb <lb/>systems and their generalization <lb/> ngel Ballesteros  a  , Alberto Enciso  b  , Francisco J. Herranz  a,1 <lb/> Orlando Ragnisco  c  and Danilo Riglioni  d <lb/>a  Departamento de Física, Universidad de Burgos, E-09001 Burgos, Spain <lb/> b  Instituto de Ciencias Matemáticas, CSIC, Nicolás Cabrera 13-15, E-28049 Madrid, Spain <lb/> c  Dipartimento di Matematica e Fisica, Universià di Roma Tre and Istituto Nazionale di Fisica <lb/>Nucleare sezione di Roma Tre, Via Vasca Navale 84, I-00146 Roma, Italy <lb/> d  Centre de Recherches Mathématiques, Université de Montréal, H3T 1J4 2920 Chemin de la <lb/>tour, Montreal, Canada <lb/>E-mail: angelb@ubu.es, aenciso@icmat.es, fjherranz@ubu.es, <lb/>ragnisco@fis.uniroma3.it, riglioni@crm.umontreal.ca <lb/> Abstract <lb/> We present two maximally superintegrable Hamiltonian systems H  λ  and H  η  that are defined, <lb/>respectively, on an N -dimensional spherically symmetric generalization of the Darboux sur-<lb/>face of type III and on an N -dimensional Taub–NUT space. Afterwards, we show that the <lb/>quantization of H  λ  and H  η  leads, respectively, to exactly solvable deformations (with pa-<lb/>rameters λ and η) of the two basic quantum mechanical systems: the harmonic oscillator <lb/>and the Coulomb problem. In both cases the quantization is performed in such a way that <lb/>the maximal superintegrability of the classical Hamiltonian is fully preserved. In particular, <lb/>we prove that this strong condition is fulfilled by applying the so-called conformal Laplace– <lb/>Beltrami quantization prescription, where the conformal Laplacian operator contains the <lb/>usual Laplace–Beltrami operator on the underlying manifold plus a term proportional to its <lb/>scalar curvature (which in both cases has non-constant value). In this way, the eigenvalue <lb/>problems for the quantum counterparts of H  λ  and H  η  can be rigorously solved, and it is <lb/>found that their discrete spectrum is just a smooth deformation (in terms of the parameters <lb/> λ and η) of the oscillator and Coulomb spectrum, respectively. Moreover, it turns out that <lb/>the maximal degeneracy of both systems is preserved under deformation. Finally, new fur-<lb/>ther multiparametric generalizations of both systems that preserve their superintegrability <lb/>are envisaged. <lb/> 1  Based on the contribution presented at &quot; The 30th International Colloquium on Group Theoretical Methods <lb/>in Physics &quot; , July 14–18, 2014, Ghent, Belgium. <lb/> arXiv:1411.7569v1  [quant-ph] 27 Nov 2014 <lb/></front>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> It is well known that if we consider a natural classical Hamiltonian system on the N -dimensional <lb/>(N D) Euclidean space <lb/> H = T (p) + U(q), <lb/> (1) <lb/>the harmonic oscillator potential U(q) = ω  2  q  2  and the Coulomb potential U(q) = −k/|q| define <lb/>two maximally superintegrable (MS) systems (in the Liouville sense), since both systems are <lb/>endowed with (2N − 1) functionally independent and globally defined integrals of the motion. In <lb/>the first case such integrals are provided by the components of the Demkov–Fradkin tensor [1, 2], <lb/>and in the second one by the angular momenta together with the N components of the Runge– <lb/>Lenz vector (see e.g. [3] and references therein). At the classical dynamical level, the footprint <lb/>of superintegrability consists in the fact that all bounded trajectories of these two systems are <lb/>closed ones, a fact which is diretly related with Bertrand&apos;s theorem [4]. Moreover, when the <lb/>quantization of these systems is performed it is found that such superintegrability implies that <lb/>their spectrum exhibits maximal degeneracy due to a superabundance of quantum integrals of <lb/>the motion. <lb/>In this paper we review two spherically symmetric deformations of the oscillator and Coulomb <lb/>systems that define two new MS systems [5, 6]. As a consequence, their quantization [7, 8, <lb/>9] is shown to present maximal degeneracy in the spectra. At a first sight, the existence of <lb/>such deformations could seem impossible since the only spherically symmetric potentials on <lb/>the Euclidean space that are MS are just the oscillator and the Coulomb ones. Therefore, <lb/>the addition of any radial perturbation on these systems leads to superintegrability breaking <lb/>and thus to a lack of maximal degeneracy in the spectra, a fact that is very well known in <lb/>quantum perturbation theory. However, as we shall see, such superintegrable perturbations can <lb/>be obtained if both the potential and the kinetic energy are simultaneously deformed in a very <lb/>precise way. Explicitly, the Hamiltonian (1) will be smoothly deformed into <lb/> H  µ  (q, p) = T  µ  (q, p) + U  µ  (q), <lb/>(2) <lb/>where µ can be regarded as a (generic) deformation parameter in such a manner that we will be <lb/>no longer working on the flat Euclidean space, but on a suitable curved space with metric and <lb/>kinetic energy given by <lb/>ds <lb/> 2 <lb/> µ  = <lb/> N <lb/> i,j=1 <lb/> g  ij  (q)dq  i  dq  j  , T  µ  (q, p) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> N <lb/> i,j=1 <lb/> g <lb/> ij  (q)p  i  p  j  . <lb/> This fact will provide additional interesting geometric features to the systems we will deal with. <lb/>In particular, we will see that the curved/deformed generalization of the Demkov–Fradkin tensor <lb/>and of the Runge–Lenz vector do exist, and will be the essential tool to prove the MS property <lb/>of the deformed systems. <lb/>We recall that the quantization problem on curved spaces is clearly a non-trivial one, since <lb/>the kinetic energy term T  µ  (q, p) is a function of both positions and momenta that creates <lb/>severe ordering ambiguities. Nevertheless, we shall explicitly show that a quantization of H  µ <lb/> (2) that preserves the MS property is achieved through the conformal Laplacian quantization <lb/> (see [8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13] and references therein): <lb/>ˆ <lb/> H  c,µ  = ˆ <lb/> T  c,µ  + U  µ  = − <lb/>  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/>∆  c,µ  + U  µ  = − <lb/>  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> ∆  LB,µ  − <lb/> (N − 2) <lb/>4(N − 1) <lb/> R  µ <lb/> + U  µ  , <lb/> (3) <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body> where R  µ  is the scalar curvature on the underlying N D curved manifold M  µ  , the operator ∆  c,µ <lb/> is the conformal Laplacian [14] and ∆  LB,µ  is the usual Laplace–Beltrami operator on M  µ  , i.e., <lb/> ∆  LB,µ  = <lb/> N <lb/> i,j=1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> √ g <lb/>∂  i <lb/> √ gg <lb/> ij  ∂  j  , <lb/> where g  ij  is the inverse of the metric tensor g  ij  and g is the corresponding determinant. The <lb/>limit µ → 0 gives rise to the quantization of the flat Hamiltonian (1) with ds  2  = dq  2  since <lb/>lim <lb/> µ→0 <lb/> R  µ  = 0, <lb/>lim <lb/> µ→0 <lb/> ∆  c,µ  = lim <lb/> µ→0 <lb/> ∆  LB,µ  = ∆ = ∇ <lb/> 2  , <lb/> lim <lb/> µ→0 <lb/>  c,µ  = − <lb/>  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> ∇ <lb/> 2  + U . <lb/> We also recall that the quantization (3) can be related through a similarity transformation to <lb/>the Hamiltonian obtained by means of the so-called direct Schrödinger quantization prescription <lb/>on conformally flat spaces [7, 8] <lb/>ˆ <lb/> H  µ  = ˆ <lb/> T  µ  + U  µ  = − <lb/>  2 <lb/> 2f  µ  (r)  2  ∆ + U  µ  , <lb/> where f  µ  (r) = f  µ  (|q|) is the conformal factor of the metric on M  µ  written as ds  2 <lb/> µ  = f  µ  (r)  2  dq  2  . <lb/>In this case, the scalar curvature reads <lb/> R = −(N − 1) <lb/> (N − 4)f  <lb/> µ  (r)  2  + f  µ  (r) <lb/> 2f  <lb/> µ  (r) + 2(N − 1)r  −1  f  <lb/> µ  (r) <lb/> f  µ  (r)  4 <lb/> . <lb/> (4) <lb/>In the next two sections, we review the exactly solvable deformations of the N D isotropic <lb/>oscillator <lb/>  c,λ  [8] and the Coulomb system <lb/>  c,η  [9], correspondingly. New results are sketched in <lb/>the last section by presenting the only possible multiparametric spherically symmetric general-<lb/>izations of the above systems which are MS with quadratic integrals of motion, that is, the most <lb/>generic deformations that can be endowed, respectively, with a generalized Demkov–Fradkin <lb/>tensor and with a Runge–Lenz N -vector. <lb/> 2 An exactly solvable deformation of the oscillator system <lb/> The N D classical Hamiltonian system given by <lb/> H  λ  (q, p) = T  λ  (q, p) + U  λ  (q) = <lb/> p  2 <lb/> 2(1 + λq  2  ) <lb/>+ <lb/> ω  2  q  2 <lb/> 2(1 + λq  2  ) <lb/> , <lb/> (5) <lb/>where λ and ω are real parameters and q, p ∈ R  N  are canonical coordinates and momenta, was <lb/>proven in [5] to be MS. The kinetic energy T  λ  (q, p) can be interpreted as the one generating <lb/>the geodesic motion of a particle with unit mass on a conformally flat space with metric and <lb/>(non-constant) scalar curvature (4) given by <lb/>ds <lb/> 2 <lb/> λ  = (1 + λq <lb/> 2  )dq <lb/> 2  , <lb/>R  λ  (q) = −λ <lb/> (N − 1) <lb/> 2N + 3λ(N − 2)q  2  <lb/> (1 + λq  2  )  3 <lb/> . <lb/> Such a curved space is, in fact, an N D spherically symmetric generalization M  λ  [15, 16] of the <lb/>Darboux surface of type III [17, 18, 19]. The limit λ → 0 of the above expressions leads to the <lb/>well known results concerning the (flat) N D isotropic harmonic oscillator with frequency ω: <lb/> H = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> p <lb/> 2  + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ω <lb/> 2  q <lb/> 2  , <lb/> ds <lb/> 2  = dq <lb/> 2  , <lb/>R = 0. <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body> The remarkable point is that H  λ  is a MS Hamiltonian, a fact that can be stated as follows. <lb/> Proposition 1. [5, 6] (i) The Hamiltonian H  λ  (5) is endowed with the following constants of <lb/>motion (m = 2, . . . , N ): <lb/> • (2N − 3) angular momentum integrals: <lb/> C <lb/> (m)  = <lb/> 1≤i&lt;j≤m <lb/> (q  i  p  j  − q  j  p  i  ) <lb/> 2  , <lb/>C  (m)  = <lb/> N −m&lt;i&lt;j≤N <lb/> (q  i  p  j  − q  j  p  i  ) <lb/> 2  , <lb/>C <lb/> (N )  = C  (N )  . <lb/> (6) <lb/> • N  2  integrals which form the ND curved/deformed Demkov–Fradkin tensor (i, j = 1, . . . , N ): <lb/> I  λ,ij  = p  i  p  j  − <lb/> 2λH  λ  (q, p) − ω <lb/> 2  <lb/> q  i  q  j  , <lb/> H  λ  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> N <lb/> i=1 <lb/> I  λ,ii  . <lb/> (ii) Each of the three sets {H  λ  , C  (m)  }, {H  λ  , C  (m)  } (m = 2, . . . , N ) and {I  λ,ii  } (i = 1, . . . , N ) is <lb/>formed by N functionally independent functions in involution. <lb/>(iii) The set {H  λ  , C  (m)  , C  (m)  , I  λ,ii  } for m = 2, . . . , N with a fixed index i is constituted by <lb/> (2N − 1) functionally independent functions. <lb/> Let us now consider the standard definitions for the quantum positions <lb/>  = (ˆ q  1  , . . . , ˆ <lb/> q  N  ), <lb/>momentâ <lb/> p = (ˆ p  1  , . . . , ˆ <lb/> p  N  ) and ∇ = ( <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂q  1 <lb/> , . . . , <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂q  N <lb/> ) operators (i, j = 1, . . . , N ): <lb/>ˆ <lb/> q  i  ψ(q) = q  i  ψ(q), <lb/> ˆ <lb/> p  i  ψ(q) = −i <lb/> ∂ ψ(q) <lb/>∂q  i <lb/> , <lb/> [ˆ q  i  , ˆ <lb/> p  j  ] = i δ  ij  , <lb/> q · ∇ = <lb/> N <lb/> i=1 <lb/> q  i <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂q  i <lb/> . <lb/> If we now apply the conformal Laplacian quantization prescription (3) to H  λ  (5) we find: <lb/> Proposition 2. [8] Let  <lb/>  c,λ  be the quantum Hamiltonian given by <lb/>  c,λ  = − <lb/>  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/>∆  LB,λ  + <lb/> ω  2  q  2 <lb/> 2(1 + λq  2  ) <lb/> − <lb/> 2  λ(N − 2) <lb/> 2N + 3λ(N − 2)q  2 <lb/> 8(1 + λq  2  )  3 <lb/> , <lb/> with <lb/> ∆  LB,λ  = <lb/>1 <lb/>(1 + λq  2  ) <lb/>∆ + <lb/> λ(N − 2) <lb/>(1 + λq  2  )  2  (q · ∇) . <lb/> (7) <lb/> (i) ˆ <lb/> H  c,λ  commutes with the (2N − 3) quantum angular momentum operators (m = 2, . . . , N ) <lb/>ˆ <lb/> C <lb/> (m)  = <lb/> 1≤i&lt;j≤m <lb/> (ˆ q  i  ˆ <lb/> p  j  − ˆ <lb/> q  j  ˆ <lb/> p  i  ) <lb/> 2  , <lb/> ˆ <lb/> C  (m)  = <lb/> N −m&lt;i&lt;j≤N <lb/> (ˆ q  i  ˆ <lb/> p  j  − ˆ <lb/> q  j  ˆ <lb/> p  i  ) <lb/> 2  , <lb/> ˆ <lb/> C <lb/> (N )  = ˆ <lb/> C  (N )  , <lb/> (8) <lb/> as well as with the N  2  curved/deformed Demkov–Fradkin operators given by <lb/>  c,λ,ij  = ˆ <lb/> p  i  ˆ <lb/> p  j  − (N − 2) <lb/>iλ <lb/>2(1 + λˆ   2  ) <lb/>(ˆ q  i  ˆ <lb/> p  j  + ˆ <lb/> q  j  ˆ <lb/> p  i  ) + <lb/>(N − 2)  2  λ  2  ˆ <lb/> q  i  ˆ <lb/> q  j <lb/> (1 + λˆ   2  )  2 <lb/> 1 − <lb/> N − 2 <lb/>4 <lb/> − <lb/> (N − 2)  2  λ <lb/> 2(1 + λˆ   2  ) <lb/> δ  ij  − 2λˆ   i  ˆ <lb/> q  j  ˆ <lb/> H  c,λ  (ˆ q, ˆ <lb/> p) + ω <lb/> 2  ˆ <lb/> q  i  ˆ <lb/> q  j  , <lb/> with i, j = 1, . . . , N and such that  <lb/>  c,λ  = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>  N <lb/>i=1 <lb/>  c,λ,ii  . <lb/>(ii) Each of the three sets { ˆ <lb/> H  c,λ  , ˆ <lb/> C  (m)  }, { ˆ <lb/> H  c,λ  , ˆ <lb/> C  (m)  } (m = 2, . . . , N ) and { ˆ <lb/> I  c,λ,ii  } (i = 1, . . . , N ) <lb/>is formed by N algebraically independent commuting observables. <lb/></body>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<body> (iii) The set { ˆ <lb/> H  c,λ  , ˆ <lb/> C  (m)  , ˆ <lb/> C  (m)  , ˆ <lb/> I  c,λ,ii  } for m = 2, . . . , N with a fixed index i is formed by (2N −1) <lb/> algebraically independent observables. <lb/>(iv) ˆ <lb/> H  c,λ  is formally self-adjoint on the space L  2  (M  λ  ), associated with the underlying Darboux <lb/>III space, defined by <lb/> Ψ|Φ  c,λ  = <lb/> M  λ <lb/> Ψ(q) Φ(q) (1 + λq <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> N/2  dq. <lb/>The complete solution to the eigenvalue problem along with the corresponding eigenfunctions <lb/>for the case of positive deformation parameter λ is summarized in the following statement. <lb/> Theorem 3. [8] Let  <lb/>  c,λ  be the quantum Hamiltonian (7) with λ &gt; 0. Then: <lb/>(i) The continuous spectrum of  <lb/>  c,λ  is given by [ <lb/> ω  2 <lb/> 2λ  , ∞). There are no embedded eigenvalues <lb/>and its singular spectrum is empty. <lb/>(ii) ˆ <lb/> H  c,λ  has an infinite number of eigenvalues, all of which are contained in (0, <lb/> ω  2 <lb/> 2λ  ). Their only <lb/>accumulation point is <lb/> ω  2 <lb/> 2λ  which is the bottom of the continuous spectrum. <lb/>(iii) All the discrete eigenvalues of  <lb/>  c,λ  are of the form <lb/> E  λ,n  = −λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> n + <lb/> N <lb/> 2 <lb/>  2 <lb/> + <lb/> n + <lb/> N <lb/> 2 <lb/>  2  λ  2 <lb/> n + <lb/> N <lb/> 2 <lb/>  2 <lb/> + ω  2  , <lb/>n ∈ N . <lb/> (9) <lb/> (iv) The eigenfunction Ψ  c,λ  of  <lb/>  c,λ  with eigenvalue E  λ,n  is given by <lb/> Ψ  c,λ  (q) = (1 + λq <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> (2−N )/4 <lb/> N <lb/> i=1 <lb/> exp{−β <lb/> 2  q <lb/> 2 <lb/> i  /2}H  n  i  (βq  i  ), β = <lb/> Ω <lb/> , <lb/> Ω = <lb/> ω  2  − 2λE, <lb/> where H  n  i  are Hermite polynomials, with n  i  ∈ N and n  1  + · · · + n  N  = n. <lb/> The maximal degeneracy of the spectrum clearly arises from the expression (9). Moreover, <lb/>the bound states of this system satisfy <lb/> E  λ,∞  = lim <lb/> n→∞ <lb/> E  λ,n  = <lb/> ω  2 <lb/> 2λ <lb/> , <lb/> lim <lb/> n→∞ <lb/> (E  λ,n+1  − E  λ,n  ) = 0. <lb/>The discrete spectrum (9) is depicted in figure 1 as a function of n for several values of λ. <lb/> 3 An exactly solvable deformation of the Coulomb system <lb/> Now we consider the N D Hamiltonian system given by <lb/> H  η  = T  η  (q, p) + U  η  (q) = <lb/> |q| <lb/> 2(η + |q|) <lb/> p <lb/> 2  − <lb/> k <lb/>η + |q| <lb/> , <lb/> (10) <lb/>where η and k are real parameters. The metric and scalar curvature of the underlying manifold <lb/> M  η  turns out to be <lb/>ds <lb/> 2 <lb/> η  = <lb/> 1 + <lb/> η <lb/> |q| <lb/> dq <lb/> 2  , <lb/>R  η  = η(N − 1) <lb/>4(N − 3)r + 3η(N − 2) <lb/>4r(η + r)  3 <lb/> , <lb/>r = |q| = <lb/> q  2  . <lb/> We remark that the system (10) is directly related to a reduction [20] of the geodesic motion <lb/>on the Taub–NUT space [21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31]. In fact, this system can be <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body> 5 <lb/> 10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/> n <lb/> 5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/> E n <lb/> Figure 1: The discrete spectrum E  λ,n  (9) for 0 ≤ n ≤ 25, N = 3,  = ω = 1 and λ = <lb/> {0, 0.01, 0.02, 0.04} starting from the upper dot (straight) line corresponding to the isotropic <lb/>harmonic oscillator with λ = 0, that is, E  0,n  . In the same order, E  λ,0  = {1.5, 1.48, 1.46, 1.41} <lb/>and E  λ,∞  = {∞, 50, 25, 12.5}. <lb/>regarded as an η-deformation of the N D Euclidean Coulomb problem with coupling constant k, <lb/> since the limit η → 0 yields <lb/> H = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> p <lb/> 2  − <lb/> k <lb/> |q| <lb/> , <lb/> ds <lb/> 2  = dq <lb/> 2  , <lb/>R = 0. <lb/>Remarkably enough, the Hamiltonian H  η  turns out to be a MS classical system, and this <lb/>result can be summarized as follows. <lb/> Proposition 4. [6] (i) The Hamiltonian H  η  (10) is endowed with the (2N − 3) angular mo-<lb/>mentum integrals (6) and Poisson-commutes with the R  η,i  components (i = 1, . . . , N ) of the <lb/>Runge–Lenz N -vector given by <lb/> R  η,i  = <lb/> N <lb/> j=1 <lb/> p  j  (q  j  p  i  − q  i  p  j  ) + <lb/> q  i <lb/> |q| <lb/> (ηH  η  (q, p) + k) . <lb/> (ii) The set {H  η  , C  (m)  , C  (m)  , R  η.i  } with m = 2, . . . , N and a fixed index i is formed by (2N − 1) <lb/> functionally independent functions. <lb/> We also recall that the classical system H  η  has been fully solved in [32]. Next the quantum <lb/>counterpart of (10) can be obtained by applying (3), and reads: <lb/> Proposition 5. [9] (i) The quantum Hamiltonian  <lb/>  c,η  given by <lb/>  c,η  = − <lb/>  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/>∆  LB,η  − <lb/> k <lb/>η + |q| <lb/> + <lb/> 2  η(N − 2) <lb/>4(N − 3)|q| + 3η(N − 2) <lb/>32|q|(η + |q|)  3 <lb/> , <lb/> with <lb/> ∆  LB,η  = <lb/> |q| <lb/> η + |q| <lb/> ∆ − <lb/> η(N − 2) <lb/>2|q|(|q| + η)  2  (q · ∇) , <lb/> (11) <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body> commutes with the (2N − 3) quantum angular momentum operators (8) as well as with the <lb/>following N Runge–Lenz operators (i = 1, . . . , N ): <lb/>ˆ <lb/> R  c,η,i  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> N <lb/> j=1 <lb/>  j  + i η <lb/> (N − 2)ˆ q  j <lb/> 4(η + |ˆ |) ˆ <lb/> q  2 <lb/> (ˆ q  j  ˆ <lb/> p  i  − ˆ <lb/> q  i  ˆ <lb/> p  j  ) <lb/>+ <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> N <lb/> j=1 <lb/> (ˆ q  j  ˆ <lb/> p  i  − ˆ <lb/> q  i  ˆ <lb/> p  j  ) <lb/> ˆ <lb/> p  j  + i η <lb/> (N − 2)ˆ q  j <lb/> 4(η + |ˆ |) ˆ <lb/> q  2 <lb/> + <lb/>ˆ <lb/> q  i <lb/> |ˆ | <lb/> η ˆ <lb/> H  c,η  (q, p) + k <lb/> . <lb/> (ii) Each of the three sets { ˆ <lb/> H  c,η  , ˆ <lb/> C  (m)  }, { ˆ <lb/> H  c,η  , ˆ <lb/> C  (m)  } (m = 2, . . . , N ) and { ˆ <lb/> R  c,η,i  } (i = 1, . . . , N ) <lb/>is formed by N algebraically independent commuting operators. <lb/>(iii) The set { ˆ <lb/> H  c,η  , ˆ <lb/> C  (m)  , ˆ <lb/> C  (m)  , ˆ <lb/> R  c,η,i  } for m = 2, . . . , N with a fixed index i is formed by (2N −1) <lb/> algebraically independent operators. <lb/>(iv) ˆ <lb/> H  c,η  is formally self-adjoint on the Hilbert space L  2  (M  η  ) with the scalar product <lb/> Ψ|Φ  c,η  = <lb/> Mη <lb/> Ψ(q) Φ(q) <lb/> 1 + <lb/> η <lb/> |q| <lb/>  N/2 <lb/> dq. <lb/>For a positive value of the deformation parameter η, the complete solution of the eigenvalue <lb/>problem for this quantum mechanical deformed Coulomb problem is the following. <lb/> Theorem 6. [9] Let  <lb/>  c,η  be the quantum Hamiltonian (11) with k &gt; 0 and η &gt; 0. Then: <lb/>(i) The continuous spectrum of  <lb/>  c,η  is given by [0, ∞). There are no embedded eigenvalues and <lb/>the singular spectrum is empty. <lb/>(ii) ˆ <lb/> H  c,η  has an infinite number of eigenvalues E  η,n,l  , depending only on the sum (n + l) and <lb/>accumulating at 0. <lb/> (iii) The eigenvalues E  η,n,l  of  <lb/>  c,η  are of the form <lb/> E  η,n,l  = <lb/> −k  2 <lb/>  2 <lb/> n + l + <lb/> N −1 <lb/> 2 <lb/>  2  + kη + <lb/>  4 <lb/> n + l + <lb/> N −1 <lb/> 2 <lb/>  4  + 2  2  kη <lb/> n + l + <lb/> N −1 <lb/> 2 <lb/>  2 <lb/> , <lb/> such that the radial eigenfunction Φ  c,η  (r) of  <lb/>  c,η  with eigenvalue E  η,n,l  reads <lb/> Φ  c,η  (r) = <lb/> 1 + <lb/> η <lb/>r <lb/>  2−N <lb/> 4 <lb/> r <lb/> l  exp <lb/> − <lb/> Kr <lb/>  2 <lb/> n + l + <lb/> N −1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> L <lb/> 2l+N −2 <lb/> n <lb/> 2Kr <lb/>  2 <lb/> n + l + <lb/> N −1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> , <lb/> where L  α <lb/>n  are generalized Laguerre polynomials and the deformed coupling constant K reads <lb/> K = k + η E  η,n,l  . <lb/> Sincê <lb/> H  c,η  is a Hamiltonian with radial symmetry, its complete eigenfunction is so given by <lb/>Ψ  c,η  = Φ  c,η  (r)Y (θ) where Y (θ) denotes the usual hyperspherical harmonics. Notice also that <lb/>the bound states of this system satisfy <lb/>lim <lb/> n,l→∞ <lb/> E  η,n,l  = 0, <lb/>lim <lb/> n→∞ <lb/> (E  η,n+1  − E  η,n)  = 0, <lb/> n = n + l. <lb/></body>

			<page> 7 <lb/></page>

			<body> 1 <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/> nlN12 <lb/> 0.5 <lb/> 0.4 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.1 <lb/> E n,l <lb/> Figure 2: Discrete spectrum for the fundamental and the three first excited states of the Hamil-<lb/>tonian <lb/>  c,η  (11) when η = {0, 0.2, 0.4, 0.6, 1} with  = k = 1 and N ≥ 3. Note that the effect <lb/>of the η deformation is quite strong for the fundamental state, since it comes from the shift <lb/> r → r + η in the usual Coulomb potential. <lb/>As expected, the limit η → 0 of E  η,n,l  provides the well known formula for the standard Coulomb <lb/>eigenvalues E  0,n,l <lb/> E  0,n,l  = − <lb/> k  2 <lb/> 2  2 <lb/> n + l + <lb/> N −1 <lb/> 2 <lb/>  2  . <lb/> And we find that the perturbative series for the eigenvalues of the deformed system <lb/>  c,η  (11) <lb/>reads <lb/> E  η,n,l  = E  0,n,l  + η <lb/>k  3 <lb/> 2  4 <lb/> n + l + <lb/> N −1 <lb/> 2 <lb/>  4  − η <lb/> 2 <lb/> 5k  4 <lb/> 8  6 <lb/> n + l + <lb/> N −1 <lb/> 2 <lb/>  6  + O(η <lb/> 3  ). <lb/>In figure 2 the eigenvalues of the fundamental and of the first three excited states are plotted <lb/>for different values of the deformation parameter η. <lb/> 4 Generalization <lb/> So far we have reviewed some specific exactly solvable deformations of the oscillator and Coulomb <lb/>potentials, which can be regarded as the most natural MS deformations beyond constant curva-<lb/>ture. Nevertheless, there are more possible generalizations within this framework that preserves <lb/>the classical MS property and that would lead to other exactly solvable deformed oscillator and <lb/>Coulomb systems. These arise within the classification of Bertrand Hamiltonians formerly intro-<lb/>duced in [33] and further developed in [34, 35, 36]. Such systems are MS and their underlying <lb/>Bertrand spaces are spherically symmetric ones. If we require to keep quadratic integrals of <lb/>motion, so generalizing the Demkov–Fradkin tensor and the Runge–Lenz N -vector, it can be <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body> shown that there only exists one possible generalization of the deformations of the oscillator and <lb/>Coulomb systems here studied that depends on two deformation parameters. <lb/>In particular, the two-parameter MS deformation of the oscillator system turns out to be <lb/> H  λ,ξ  (q, p) = T  λ,ξ  (q, p) + U  λ,ξ  (q) = <lb/>(1 − ξq  4  )  2  p  2 <lb/> 2(1 + λq  2  + ξq  4  ) <lb/>+ <lb/> ω  2  q  2 <lb/> 2(1 + λq  2  + ξq  4  ) <lb/> , <lb/> where ξ is a real parameter. Obviously, the limit ξ → 0 gives rise to the Hamiltonian H  λ  (5) <lb/>The underlying manifold M  λ,ξ  is endowed with a conformally flat metric given by <lb/>ds <lb/> 2 <lb/> λ,ξ  = <lb/>(1 + λq  2  + ξq  4  ) <lb/>(1 − ξq  4  )  2 <lb/> dq <lb/> 2  . <lb/> And the corresponding scalar curvature (4) reads <lb/> R  λ,ξ  (r) = − <lb/> (N − 1) <lb/>(1 + λr  2  + ξr  4  )  3 <lb/> N <lb/> 2 + 3λr <lb/> 2  + 6ξr <lb/> 4  + λξr <lb/> 6  <lb/> λ + 3λξr <lb/> 4  + 2ξr <lb/> 2  (3 + ξr <lb/> 4  ) <lb/> −6r <lb/> 2  (λ <lb/> 2  − 4ξ)(1 − ξr <lb/> 4  ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> , <lb/> where recall that r = |q| = <lb/> q  2  . <lb/>As far as the Coulomb system is concerned, the resulting two-parameter MS deformation is <lb/>given by <lb/> H  η,ζ  = T  η,ζ  (q, p) + U  η,ζ  (q) = <lb/>(1 − ζq  2  )  2  |q| <lb/> 2(η + |q| + ηζq  2  ) <lb/> p <lb/> 2  − <lb/> k(1 + ζq  2  ) <lb/>(η + |q| + ηζq  2  ) <lb/> , <lb/> which generalizes the one-parameter Hamiltonian H  η  (10). Hence the metric of the underlying <lb/>spherically symmetric space M  η,ζ  and its scalar curvature are found to be <lb/>ds <lb/> 2 <lb/> η,ζ  = <lb/>(η + |q| + ηζq  2  ) <lb/>(1 − ζq  2  )  2  |q| <lb/> dq <lb/> 2  , <lb/>R  η,ζ  (r) = − <lb/> (N − 1) <lb/>4r(η + r + ηζr  2  )  3 <lb/> 6η(1 − ζr <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> 2  <lb/> η + r(2 + ζr(6η + r[2 + ηζr]) <lb/> −N <lb/> 3η + r(4 + ηζr(6 − ζr <lb/> 2  <lb/> η − ζr <lb/> 2  (6η + r[4 + 3ηζr]) <lb/> . <lb/> It is worth stressing that M  η,ζ  turns out to be the N D spherically symmetric generalization of <lb/>the Darboux surface of type IV [17, 18, 19] constructed in [15, 16]. <lb/>Consequently, by applying the conformal Laplacian quantization (3) to the above two-<lb/>parameter Hamiltonians, new exactly solvable systems, ˆ <lb/> H  c,λ,ξ  and <lb/>  c,η,ζ  , would be obtained <lb/>as deformations of the oscillator and Coulomb systems. Their solution would generalize the <lb/>results presented in theorems 3 and 6. Work on this line is currently in progress. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments <lb/> This work was partially supported by the Spanish MINECO through the Ramón y Cajal program <lb/>(A.E.) and under grants MTM2013-43820 (A.B and F.J.H.) and FIS2011-22566 (A.E.), by the <lb/>Spanish Junta de Castilla y León under grant BU278U14 (A.B., A.E. and F.J.H.), by the <lb/>ICMAT Severo Ochoa under grant SEV-2011-0087 (A.E.), and by a postdoctoral fellowship <lb/>from the Laboratory of Mathematical Physics of the CRM, Université de Montréal (D.R.). <lb/></div>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] Demkov Y N 1959 Soviet Phys. JETP 9 63 <lb/>[2] Fradkin D M 1965 Amer. J. Phys. 33 207 <lb/>[3] Ballesteros A, Enciso A, Herranz F J and Ragnisco O 2009 Commun. Math. Phys. 290 1033 <lb/>[4] Bertrand J 1873 C.R. Acad. Sci. Paris 77 849 <lb/>[5] Ballesteros A, Enciso A, Herranz F J and Ragnisco O 2008 Physica D 237 505 <lb/>[6] Ballesteros A, Enciso A, Herranz F J, Ragnisco O and Riglioni D 2011 SIGMA 7 048 <lb/>[7] Ballesteros A, Enciso A, Herranz F J, Ragnisco O and Riglioni D 2011 Phys. Lett. A 375 <lb/> 1431 <lb/>[8] Ballesteros A, Enciso A, Herranz F J, Ragnisco O and Riglioni D 2011 Ann. Phys. 326 2053 <lb/>[9] Ballesteros A, Enciso A, Herranz F J, Ragnisco O and Riglioni D 2014 Ann. Phys. 351 540 <lb/>[10] Wald R M 1984 General Relativity (Chicago: The University of Chicago Press) <lb/>[11] Liu Z J and Qian M 1992 Trans. Amer. Math. Soc. 331 321 <lb/>[12] Landsman N P 1998 Mathematical Topics Between Classical and Quantum Mechanics (New <lb/>York: Springer) <lb/>[13] Michel J P, Radoux F and Silhan J 2014 SIGMA 10 016 <lb/>[14] Baer C and Dahl M 2003 Geom. Funct. Anal. 13 483 <lb/>[15] Ballesteros A, Herranz F J and Ragnisco O 2007 Phys. Lett. B 652 376 <lb/>[16] Ballesteros A, Enciso A, Herranz F J and Ragnisco O 2009 Ann. Phys. 324 1219 <lb/>[17] Koenigs G 1972 Leçons sur la tèorie g` eèrale des surfaces vol 4 ed G Darboux (New York: <lb/>Chelsea) p 368 <lb/>[18] Kalnins E G, Kress J M, Miller W Jr and Winternitz P 2003 J. Math. Phys. 44 5811 <lb/>[19] Grosche C, Pogosyan G S and Sissakian A N 2007 Phys. Part. Nuclei 38 525 <lb/>[20] Iwai T and Katayama N 1994 J. Phys. A: Math. Gen. 27 3179 <lb/>[21] Manton N S 1982 Phys. Lett. B 110 54 <lb/>[22] Atiyah M F and Hitchin N J 1985 Phys. Lett. A 107 21 <lb/>[23] Gibbons G W and Manton N S 1986 Nucl. Phys. B 274 183 <lb/>[24] Fehér L G and Horváthy P A 1987 Phys. Lett. B 183 182 <lb/>[25] Gibbons G W and Ruback P J 1988 Comm. Math. Phys. 115 267 <lb/>[26] Iwai T and Katayama N 1995 J. Math. Phys. 36 1790 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [27] Iwai T, Uwano Y and Katayama N 1996 J. Math. Phys. 37 608 <lb/>[28] Bini D, Cherubini C and Jantzen R T 2002 Class. Quantum Grav. 19 5481 <lb/>[29] Bini D, Cherubini C, Jantzen R T and Mashhoon B 2003 Class. Quantum Grav. 20 457 <lb/>[30] Gibbons G W and Warnick C M 2007 J. Geom. Phys. 57 2286 <lb/>[31] Jezierski J and Lukasik M 2007 Class. Quantum Grav. 24 1331 <lb/>[32] Latini D and Ragnisco O 2014 preprint arXiv:1411.3571 <lb/>[33] Perlick V 1992 Class. Quantum Grav. 9 1009 <lb/>[34] Ballesteros A, Enciso A, Herranz F J and Ragnisco O 2008 Class. Quantum Grav. 25 165005 <lb/>[35] Riglioni D 2013 J. Phys. A: Math. Theor. 46 265207 <lb/>[36] Post S and Riglioni D 2014 preprint arXiv:1410.4495 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>11 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
