<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage> This content has been downloaded from IOPscience. Please scroll down to see the full text. <lb/>Download details: <lb/>IP Address: 188.184.3.52 <lb/>This content was downloaded on 23/12/2014 at 08:44 <lb/>Please note that terms and conditions apply. <lb/> First non-intercepting emittance measurement by means of optical diffraction radiation <lb/>interference <lb/> View the table of contents for this issue, or go to the journal homepage for more <lb/>2014 New J. Phys. 16 113029 <lb/>(http://iopscience.iop.org/1367-2630/16/11/113029) <lb/>Home Search Collections Journals About Contact us My IOPscience <lb/></titlePage>

			<front> First non-intercepting emittance measurement by <lb/>means of optical diffraction radiation interference <lb/> A Cianchi <lb/> 1 <lb/> , V Balandin <lb/> 2 <lb/> , M Castellano <lb/> 3 <lb/> , E Chiadroni <lb/> 3 <lb/> , L Catani <lb/> 4 <lb/> , <lb/>N Golubeva <lb/> 2 <lb/> , K Honkavaara <lb/> 2 <lb/> , G Kube <lb/> 2  and M Migliorati <lb/> 5 <lb/> 1 INFN-Roma Tor Vergata &amp; University of Rome &apos;Tor Vergata&apos;, Via della Ricerca Scientifica, <lb/>1-00133 Rome, Italy <lb/> 2 DESY, Notkestrasse 85, 22607 Hamburg, Germany <lb/> 3 INFN-LNF, Via E. Fermi, 40-00044 Frascati, Rome, Italy <lb/> 4 INFN-Roma &apos;Tor Vergata&apos;, Via della Ricerca Scientifica, 1-00133 Rome, Italy <lb/> 5 Dept. SBAI, Sapienza University of Rome, Via A. Scarpa 16, 00161 Roma, Italy <lb/>E-mail: alessandro.cianchi@roma2.infn.it <lb/>Received 18 May 2014, revised 29 August 2014 <lb/>Accepted for publication 4 September 2014 <lb/>Published 11 November 2014 <lb/> New Journal of Physics 16 (2014) 113029 <lb/>doi:10.1088/1367-2630/16/11/113029 <lb/> Abstract <lb/> Transverse electron beam size measurements are required in order to determine <lb/>the transverse emittance. In the case of high brightness electron beams produced <lb/>by high repetition rate linear accelerators, conventional invasive diagnostics <lb/>cannot sustain the intense power dissipated in intercepting devices. The analysis <lb/>of the angular distribution of diffraction radiation has been proven to be a <lb/>competent candidate for non-intercepting measurements of electron beam <lb/>parameters. In addition, optical diffraction radiation interference (ODRI) has <lb/>been demonstrated to be superior to the single slit ODR due to its shielding <lb/>capability against the synchrotron radiation background and the possibility of <lb/>avoiding complementary diagnostics. This paper reports the first transverse <lb/>emittance measurement ever performed with the ODRI technique. In addition, <lb/>the intrinsic non-intercepting and non-disturbing feature of the ODRI method <lb/>has been checked in our experimental conditions by wakefield calculations. <lb/>Keywords: diffraction radiation, high brightness beam, emittance measurement <lb/> Content from this work may be used under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 licence. <lb/>Any further distribution of this work must maintain attribution to the author(s) and the title of the work, journal <lb/>citation and DOI. <lb/> New Journal of Physics 16 (2014) 113029 <lb/>1367-2630/14/113029+12$33.00 <lb/>© 2014 IOP Publishing Ltd and Deutsche Physikalische Gesellschaft <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> High brightness or high repetition rate electron beams, mainly destined to serve as advanced <lb/>radiation sources, are currently produced at several accelerator facilities worldwide, and more <lb/>are foreseen in the near future. The transverse emittance measurement is of paramount <lb/>importance in order to achieve the required high beam quality. Emittance measurements are <lb/>usually based on the quadrupole scan or multiple screens technique [1]. Conventional <lb/>intercepting devices, such as screens, mainly using optical transition radiation (OTR), or wire <lb/>scanners, are widely used to measure the beam size in order to determine the emittance value. <lb/>However, in the case of high brightness beams having small transverse dimensions—typically <lb/>below 100 μm—or high repetition rate in the order of MHz, the energy deposited in the <lb/>intercepting devices makes their use unfeasible. <lb/>The laser wire [2, 3] provides an attractive option; however it faces tight mechanical and <lb/>optical requirements. Our approach is to use the angular distribution of far-field ODR, produced <lb/>by an electron bunch passing through a rectangular aperture in a screen. This technique was <lb/>proposed several years ago [4] as a non-intercepting device for beam size measurements. When <lb/>the radial extension of the electromagnetic field (in the order of γλ, where γ is the Lorentz factor <lb/>and λ the wavelength of observation) is larger than the aperture size, the field interacts with the <lb/>screen resulting in the emission of ODR. The use of a rectangular slit instead of a circular hole <lb/>[5] has several advantages: it simplifies the mathematical treatment and eases the mechanical <lb/>machining of the slit. The physics of the diffraction radiation emission, as well as the effects of <lb/>the used geometry on the angular distribution of the emitted radiation has been described in [6] <lb/>and later extensively treated in several papers, e.g. [7, 8], and in a recent book [9]. The first <lb/> measurement of the beam size using ODR has been performed at KEK [10], demonstrating the <lb/>potential of this technique but also highlighting some unwanted problems. For example, the <lb/>synchrotron radiation (SR), mainly produced by the magnetic elements upstream of the beam <lb/>size measurement location, is scattered around the beam pipe, distorting the low intensity signal <lb/>produced by ODR. Furthermore, in order to avoid a systematic error in beam size measurements <lb/>[4], standard ODR-based techniques require complementary diagnostics to align the electron <lb/>beam into the center of the slit. The ODRI technique has been developed in order to overcome <lb/>both problems. Standard emittance measurements using OTR imaging or wire scanners are, <lb/>nevertheless, more easily implemented as measurements based on ODR, and therefore <lb/>preferable when beam parameters allow them. <lb/>A detailed description of the ODRI physics including the used formulas and <lb/>approximations can be found in [11]. We recall here only some basic features. In the <lb/>traditional DR-based diagnostics, the angular distribution of the diffraction radiation, which is <lb/>emitted when a charged particle beam passes a slit aperture, is detected. For ODRI <lb/>measurements, an additional slit aperture with different size is used (see figure 1). The distance <lb/>between the screens is shorter than the radiation formation length. The ODR emitted in the <lb/>forward direction at the first slit interferes with the backward radiation produced at the second <lb/>slit. Different slit apertures are needed in order to avoid signal cancellation due to destructive <lb/>interference between the emitted fields. The interference pattern contains valuable information <lb/>regarding the beam parameters: transverse size, angular divergence and relative position inside <lb/>the slits can be retrieved from it. When using a single slit setup, it is not possible to distinguish <lb/>the beam size and the beam position inside the slit, and a complementary diagnostic is needed in <lb/>order to separate these two contributions. We have demonstrated in [11] that this is not the case <lb/></body>

			<page> 2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> New J. Phys. 16 (2014) 113029 <lb/>A Cianchi et al <lb/></note>

			<body> when using ODRI with non-collinear slits. This is an important difference because in our case <lb/>we do not need any additional diagnostics to retrieve the beam position inside the slit, and also <lb/>the contributions to the angular distribution of beam position and beam size are separated from <lb/>each other. A more detailed analysis of the near fields in a real experimental geometry and the <lb/>effects on the radiation angular distribution has recently been studied, demonstrating that our far <lb/> field approximation is accurate if the misalignment of the slit centers is within 50 μm [12], <lb/>consistent with our measurement setup. This result confirms the very good agreement between <lb/>data and theoretical model shown in [11]. <lb/>Another significant advantage of ODRI compared to ODR concerns the better efficiency in <lb/>shielding against the SR background. The first screen acts as a mask, effectively reducing the <lb/>SR background. <lb/> 2. Experimental setup <lb/> A sketch of the used ODRI setup is shown in figure 1. <lb/>The first slit, 1 mm wide and normal to the beam direction, acts as a shield against the SR <lb/>background. In addition, the forward ODR (FDR) produced by this slit interferes with the <lb/>backward ODR (BDR) at the second interface, where an aperture of 0.5 mm is placed. The <lb/>distance between the two screens is about 2 cm, much shorter than the formation length (in the <lb/>order of γ <lb/> 2 <lb/> λ) in the case of optical wavelengths and at 1 GeV electron beam energy. The <lb/>difference in the aperture sizes prevents the complete cancellation of the fields, resulting in a <lb/>clear interference pattern. <lb/>The experimental setup consists of an in-vacuum actuator used to insert an aluminum <lb/>coated silicon screen into a precise position with respect to the electron beam axis. The screen <lb/>holder is shown in figure 2. The 1 mm wide slit can also be moved using a dedicated second <lb/>movable actuator allowing a remote control of the relative vertical position between the slits. <lb/>The 0.5 mm slit aperture on the screen is opened by means of a lithographic technique using <lb/>anisotropic etching in a KOH solution, allowing the creation of clean and very sharp edges. The <lb/>manufacturing procedure has been described in [13]. With respect to our screen, the only <lb/>difference from the one in [13] is the use of the silicon nitride as mask etching instead of silicon <lb/>oxide, allowing a more uniform and slower etching rate. <lb/> Figure 1.  Sketch of the two-slit setup. Dimension a is the aperture size of the first slit; b <lb/> is the size of the second slit. The FDR produced at the first interface is reflected and <lb/>interferes with the BDR from the second surface. An optical system, described later in <lb/>the paper, images the radiation onto a CCD device. <lb/></body>

			<page> 3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> New J. Phys. 16 (2014) 113029 <lb/>A Cianchi et al <lb/></note>

			<body> Since the first slit can be moved vertically with respect to the second one, it is possible to <lb/>measure ODRI angular distributions in the same experimental conditions with only one <lb/>parameter, i.e. the offset of the electron beam with respect to the center of the first slit, changed <lb/>in a controlled way. In addition, since the middle part of the second screen can be used as a <lb/>conventional OTR screen, the ODRI results can be directly compared with those from OTR <lb/>measurements. <lb/>The emitted radiation is extracted out of the beam pipe through a window, reflected by a <lb/>mirror and guided into an optical system which can be moved remotely with respect to the <lb/>optical axis. An achromatic doublet with focal length f = 250 mm is used to image the beam, <lb/>while a custom apochromatic lens (f = 531 mm), designed to reduce the influence of the <lb/>chromatic aberration, is implemented to obtain the ODRI angular distribution. Several narrow <lb/>band interferential filters are mounted onto a filter wheel to select the observation wavelength. <lb/>A second wheel is equipped with two Glan–Thomson polarizers to select vertical or horizontal <lb/>polarization. The polarizer lengthens the optical path, thus increasing the focal length. This <lb/>variation can be corrected by changing slightly the longitudinal camera position. The detector <lb/>used is a cooled, high sensitivity, 16-bit CCD camera (Hamamatsu ORCA II-BT-512G model <lb/>type C4742–98-26LAG2). The main advantages of this kind of camera are the very high <lb/>quantum efficiency, 80% even at 800 nm, and the negligible thermal noise. The distance <lb/>between the screen and the camera is about 1 meter. All components of the optical system can <lb/>be inserted and remotely moved out from the optical axis using a remote control. <lb/> 3. Emittance measurements <lb/> The measurements were performed at the FLASH free-electron laser user facility [14] at DESY <lb/>(Hamburg). FLASH consists of an electron source to produce a high quality electron beam, <lb/>followed by a superconducting linac with TESLA-type accelerating modules, and an undulator <lb/>section to produce FEL radiation. Our experimental station was located in a beam line thus <lb/>bypassing the undulators. During our measurements the electron beam energy was 1 GeV. The <lb/> Figure 2.  A picture of the screen holder. The movable 1 mm wide slit acts as SR <lb/>shielding and an FDR target. The BDR generating screen has a 0.5 mm wide slit. A <lb/>calibration pattern is visible on the bottom part of the frame. The central part can be <lb/>used as a standard OTR screen. <lb/></body>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> New J. Phys. 16 (2014) 113029 <lb/>A Cianchi et al <lb/></note>

			<body> electron bunch train repetition rate was 10 Hz with typically 20 bunches per train. In our <lb/>experiment, we used an electron bunch charge of 0.2 nC, and a CCD integration time of 2 <lb/>seconds resulting in a total integrated charge of 80 nC. The complementary OTR measurements <lb/>were carried out with a single 0.2 nC bunch to avoid damages on the conventional aluminum <lb/>coated OTR screen. <lb/> 3.1. Data analysis <lb/> The data analysis consists of multiple steps. The effects of the electron beam parameters were <lb/>taken into account through the convolution of the ODRI angular distribution, as produced by a <lb/>single particle, with two Gaussian distributions, one for the beam size and the other one for the <lb/>angular spread. The whole beam was simulated by adding 5000 randomly generated <lb/>distributions produced by single particles each one with different vertical position and incident <lb/>angle. The chosen random distribution was a normal one, since it corresponds to the most likely <lb/>one for an electron beam properly matched and tuned in a high energy linac. This assumption <lb/>has been verified experimentally for the transverse profile. A Monte Carlo approach was then <lb/>used to numerically solve the resulting expression which cannot be solved analytically. The <lb/>obtained results were entered into the Minuit [15] routine. New distributions were generated <lb/>through the Monte Carlo code; each time the fitting procedure changes the starting parameters. <lb/>We fit seven parameters: the beam size and divergence, a constant background, the distribution <lb/>center, the relative position of the beam inside the first and the second slit and the focal length <lb/>of the optical system. <lb/>As we already mentioned, our model uses the far field approximation for the angular <lb/>distribution. This approximation is valid when the slitʼs displacement is very small (about 25 <lb/> μm), as was the case in our experiment. To test the validity of our analysis we measured several <lb/>ODRI angular distributions with different observation wavelengths and radiation polariza-<lb/>tions [16]. <lb/>Figure 3 shows an example of a measured profile of the ODRI angular distribution <lb/>superimposed with a fit, showing an excellent agreement between the model and the <lb/>measurement data. This data is recorded during the quadrupole scan reported below and it refers <lb/> Figure 3.  Measured ODRI angular distribution (black points) with a superimposed fit <lb/> (red line). A value of beam size larger than 10 μm is shown in blue, while a beam <lb/>smaller than 10 μm is shown in green. The cut on the left is due to a stray light <lb/>background. <lb/></body>

			<page> 5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> New J. Phys. 16 (2014) 113029 <lb/>A Cianchi et al <lb/></note>

			<body> to the current value of −35.7 A in figure 4. In addition, simulations of the angular distributions, <lb/>having different sizes of ±10 μm with respect to the nominal value, are shown in figure 3. <lb/>We use as an error estimate the Poisson noise of emitted ODRI photons after background <lb/>subtraction, assuming that the CCD was operated in the photon counting regime as it was the <lb/>case in our experiment. The cut in the left hand side of the profile is caused by the stray light <lb/>background. <lb/> 3.2. Measurement results <lb/> The transverse emittance was measured by means of the quadrupole scan technique [1], using <lb/>the last quadrupole upstream of the experimental set-up. In order to validate the ODRI results, <lb/>the quadrupole scan was also performed using conventional OTR imaging. <lb/>The two quadrupole scans are compared in figure 4. In the appendix, we show for each <lb/>data point of figure 4 the 2D ODRI data images and the fit results as well as the beam spots <lb/>obtained by OTR imaging. <lb/>For each value of the quadrupole current, we collected two ODRI angular distribution <lb/>patterns. The two measurements differ only in the position of the first slit, which was moved by <lb/>25 μm with respect to the second one. In this way we obtained two data sets with only one <lb/>parameter changed, i.e. the offset of the electron beam with respect to the center of the first slit. <lb/>This constraint on the fit improves the confidence in the results. All ODRI distributions <lb/>presented in this publication have been collected using the vertical polarizer and an <lb/>interferential filter at 500 nm. <lb/>The standard deviation of the rms (root mean square) beam size has been used as the <lb/>measurement error for the OTR data. In the ODRI case the error analysis is more complicated. <lb/>Due to the stochastic nature of the fitting routine, Minuit is unable to perform a correct error <lb/>analysis. Therefore, in order to have an error estimation for the ODRI measurements, we <lb/>calculated the normalized χ <lb/> 2 value of the fit and we varied the beam size parameter until the χ <lb/> 2 <lb/> changed by one unit. The change of the beam size causing one unit change of χ <lb/> 2 is then used as <lb/>an estimate for the beam size error in the ODRI measurements [17]. <lb/> Figure 4.  Comparison between quadrupole scans obtained by imaging a single electron <lb/>bunch using the OTR screen and using the ODRI angular distribution produced by a <lb/>long train of bunches going through the slits. <lb/></body>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> New J. Phys. 16 (2014) 113029 <lb/>A Cianchi et al <lb/></note>

			<body> The resulting emittance is  ϵ = <lb/> ± <lb/> (2.3 0.4) mm  mrad for the ODRI measurements and <lb/> ϵ = <lb/>± <lb/> (2.4 0.4) mm  mrad for the OTR measurements. The agreement between the two <lb/>techniques is excellent, concerning both the measured emittance as well as the shape of the <lb/>quadrupole scan curve (figure 4). The measurement error above, both for the ODRI and OTR <lb/>measurements, is the RMS statistical error due to a shot-to-shot instability of the electron beam <lb/>size and position. Since our experiment is located downstream of a complicated dogleg-like <lb/>bend, we believe that this instability is mainly caused by only partially closed dispersion. <lb/>The resolution, independent of the measurement method, is an important issue when <lb/>measuring small emittances with beam sizes down to 10 μm. The achievable ODRI resolution <lb/>depends on several parameters such as the electron beam energy, the observation wavelength <lb/>and the slit dimension. As a rule of thumb, the stronger the diffraction effect, i.e. the more the <lb/>ODRI angular distribution differs from the OTR angular distribution, the better the resolution. <lb/>The authors of [10] showed that for their experimental conditions (energy = 1.28 GeV, slit <lb/>aperture = 260 μm, wavelength = 530 nm), they were able to measure a 10 μm beam size. They <lb/>found a good agreement with independent measurements from a wire scanner at the same <lb/>experimental location. Since a larger slit aperture improves the resolution, while a longer <lb/>wavelength degrades it, we can assume that the resolution of our ODRI setup is of the same <lb/>order of magnitude as measurements reported in [10]. <lb/> 4. Wakefieldʼs calculation <lb/> In order to verify that the ODRI based diagnostics is not only non-intercepting but also non-<lb/>disturbing, we have calculated the transverse and longitudinal wakefields using CST Particle <lb/>Studio [18] and their effects on the electron bunch under our experimental conditions by <lb/>analytical methods. <lb/>The 3D electromagnetic code solves the Maxwellʼs equations in a given structure taking a <lb/>Gaussian beam as the source of the fields. This means that we cannot determine the wakefield <lb/>generated by a point charge, called as the Greenʼs function of the structure, but only the wake <lb/>potential of the entire bunch instead. However, in our situation this is not a limitation because <lb/>we can still determine the effects of the induced electromagnetic fields on the beam dynamics <lb/>by directly using the wake potential, since we can assume that the longitudinal bunch <lb/>distribution does not change when passing through the slit structure. <lb/>Due to the asymmetry of our set-up, we cannot obtain the transverse wake potential per <lb/>unit of displacement (dipole wakefield with an off-axis source and an on-axis test charge [19]), <lb/>but instead we have simulated an on-axis bunch and evaluated the transverse electromagnetic <lb/> fields on the bunch itself. <lb/>We have verified that the longitudinal wake potential is independent on the displacement <lb/>between the two slits. An energy loss and an induced energy spread are the effects of the <lb/>longitudinal wake potential on the bunch. <lb/>A Gaussian bunch shape with rms length of 7 ps and a charge of 200 pC at an energy of <lb/>1 GeV was used. The total energy loss and the energy spread have been evaluated with the use <lb/>of the longitudinal wake potential given by CST and the Gaussian distribution. The results give <lb/>an energy loss of 2.7 keV with an additional energy spread of 1.6 keV, which corresponds to a <lb/>relative energy spread of 1.6 10 <lb/> −6 <lb/> , at 1 GeV. This is negligible compared to the usual <lb/>uncorrelated energy spread of the 1 GeV beam (in the order of 100 keV). <lb/></body>

			<page> 7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> New J. Phys. 16 (2014) 113029 <lb/>A Cianchi et al <lb/></note>

			<body> The expected effect of the transverse wake potential is to deflect the electrons inside the <lb/>bunch. The evaluation of the deflection angle has been performed in [20] and [21] starting from <lb/>the spectral angular distribution of an ultrarelativistic electron passing through a circular disk. <lb/>As our geometry is more complicated with respect to the one investigated in the aforementioned <lb/>references, with two slits tilted 45 degrees relative to one another, and also taking into account <lb/>the interference at the two interfaces, we have resorted to the transverse wake potential given by <lb/>CST, since both the papers state that their approaches agree with results obtained from the <lb/>geometric wakefield model. <lb/>The average deflection, corresponding to an average kick received by the bunch when it <lb/>crosses the slit system, results in a divergence of 3.610 <lb/> −7  rad for the horizontal case, and 1.3 <lb/>10 <lb/> −7  rad for the vertical one. The latter is evaluated for a 50 μm slit displacement. The <lb/>divergence spread due to the dependence of the transverse wake on the longitudinal position <lb/>along the bunch is 1.410 <lb/> −7  rad for the horizontal plane, and 5 10 <lb/> −8  rad for the vertical one (50 <lb/> μm misalignment). <lb/>From the performed wakefield study we can conclude that, for all cases in our <lb/>experimental scenario, the longitudinal and transverse wake potentials cause only a negligible <lb/>contribution to energy spread and beam divergence. We would like, however, to point out that <lb/>this is not a general result, but applies only to our experimental situation. For each new <lb/>experiment, the wakefield effects should be evaluated taking into account the characteristics of <lb/>the experiment. If required, the slit geometry may be modified such that the wakefield effects <lb/>can be neglected. In addition, in order to keep the non-intercepting feature of the device and to <lb/>ensure a large enough ODRI signal, the geometry (slit apertures and relative distance) must be <lb/>customized for each experiment according to the expected electron beam parameters. <lb/> 5. Conclusions <lb/> The angular distribution of the optical diffraction radiation interference has been used for the <lb/> first time to measure the transverse emittance in a non-intercepting way. The ODRI <lb/>measurements were compared with measurements performed using standard intercepting OTR <lb/>imaging. The agreement between the results obtained with these two techniques was excellent. <lb/>In addition, an estimation of the wakefields has been included in our analysis showing that, in <lb/>our experimental scenario, their effect on beam parameters can be neglected. In this case, ODRI <lb/>diagnostics is not only non-intercepting but also non-disturbing. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgements <lb/> We thank DESY for the opportunity to perform our experiment at the FLASH facility. Special <lb/>thanks are given to the FLASH operators for their help, to Christian Wiebers for his important <lb/>contribution to the mechanical construction of the experimental setup and to Hans-Christian <lb/>Schroeder for the design of the apochromatic lens. We also thank V Foglietti of IFN-CNR for <lb/>the realization of the slit with a lithographic technique, and R Sorchetti and L Cacciotti for their <lb/>qualified and fundamental technical support in the development of this diagnostic. <lb/></div>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> New J. Phys. 16 (2014) 113029 <lb/>A Cianchi et al <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex"> Appendix <lb/> We present here the experimental data for each point of the quadrupole scan in figure 4. <lb/>Figures A1 –A6 show the line profile of ODRI angular distribution along the central line. <lb/>Figure A7 shows the beam spots obtained by single shot OTR imaging (please notice that due <lb/>to a rotation of the camera the vertical dimension here is the horizontal one). The used <lb/>quadrupole current and the measured rms beam size for each data point are given in the figure <lb/> captions. The 2D raw data images are given for comparison as well. <lb/> Figure A2.  Top: angular distribution of the ODRI radiation at 500 nm with <lb/>superimposed fit of data points, quadrupole current  = −35.4A.  Fit results: σ  y = 70.7 <lb/> μm. Bottom: 2D angular distribution raw data. <lb/> Figure A1.  Top: angular distribution of the ODRI radiation at 500 nm with <lb/>superimposed fit of data points; quadrupole current  = −34.9A.  Fit results: σ  y = 95.4 <lb/> μm. Bottom: 2D angular distribution raw data. <lb/></div>

			<page> 9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> New J. Phys. 16 (2014) 113029 <lb/>A Cianchi et al <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex"> Figure A4.  Top: angular distribution of the ODRI radiation at 500 nm with <lb/>superimposed fit of data points, quadrupole current  = −36.0A.  Fit results: σ  y = 31.3 <lb/> μm. Bottom: 2D angular distribution raw data. <lb/> Figure A3.  Top: angular distribution of the ODRI radiation at 500 nm with <lb/>superimposed fit of data points, quadrupole current  = −35.7A.  Fit results: σ  y = 46.0 <lb/> μm. Bottom: 2D angular distribution raw data. <lb/></div>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> New J. Phys. 16 (2014) 113029 <lb/>A Cianchi et al <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex"> Figure A6.  Top: angular distribution of the ODRI radiation at 500 nm with <lb/>superimposed fit of data points, quadrupole current  = −37.2A.  Fit results: σ  y = 88.7 <lb/> μm. Bottom: 2D angular distribution raw data. <lb/> Figure A5.  Top: angular distribution of the ODRI radiation at 500 nm with <lb/>superimposed fit of data points, quadrupole current  = −36.6A.  Fit results: σ  y = 63.8 <lb/> μm. Bottom: 2D angular distribution raw data. <lb/></div>

			<page> 11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> New J. Phys. 16 (2014) 113029 <lb/>A Cianchi et al <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] Minty M G and Zimmermann F 2003 Measurement and Control of Charged Particle Beams (Berlin: <lb/>Springer) <lb/>[2] Ross M 2003 Proc. Particle Accelerator Conf. (Piscataway, NJ: IEEE) 1 pp 503–7 <lb/>[3] Tenenbaum P and Shintake T 1999 Annu. Rev. Nucl. Part. Sci. 49 125 <lb/>[4] Castellano M 1997 Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res. A 394 275 <lb/>[5] Rule D, Fiorito R and Kimura W 1997 AIP Conf. Proc. 390 510 <lb/>[6] Ter-Mikaelian M L 1972 High-energy Electromagnetic Processes in Condensed Media (New York: Wiley) <lb/>[7] Potylitsyn A 1998 Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res. 145 169 <lb/>[8] Potylitsina-Kube N and Artru X 2003 Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res. 201 172 <lb/>[9] Potylitsyn A P, Ryazanov M I, Strikhanov M N and Tishchenko A A 2010 Diffraction Radiation from <lb/>Relativistic Particles vol 239 (Berlin: Springer) <lb/>[10] Karataev P, Araki S, Hamatsu R, Hayano H, Muto T, Naumenko G, Potylitsyn A, Terunuma N and <lb/>Urakawa J 2004 Phys. Rev. Lett. 93 244802 <lb/>[11] Cianchi A, Castellano M, Catani L, Chiadroni E, Honkavaara K and Kube G 2011 Phys. Rev. ST Accel. <lb/>Beams 14 102803 <lb/>[12] Shpakov V and Dabagov S B 2012 Tech. Rep. INFN-12-02/LNF (arXiv:1408.5758) <lb/>[13] Cianci E, Notargiacomo A, Cianchi A and Foglietti V 2001 Proc. SPIE 4557 242–9 <lb/>[14] Vogt M, Faatz B, Feldhaus J, Honkavaara K, Schreiber S and Treusch R 2014 Status of the free electron laser <lb/>user facility FLASH Proc. 5th Int. Particle Accelerator Conf. (Dresden, Germany, 2014) p 938 <lb/>[15] James F 1994 CERN Program Library Long Writeup D506 (http://hep.fi.infn.it/minuit.pdf) <lb/>[16] Cianchi A, Balandin V, Castellano M, Catani L, Chiadroni E, Gatti G, Golubeva N, Honkavaara K and <lb/>Kube G 2012 J. Phys.: Conf. Ser. 357 012019 <lb/>[17] Hughes I and HASE T 2010 Measurements and their Uncertainties (Oxford: Oxford University Press) <lb/>pp 74–9 <lb/>[18] CST AG, Darmstadt, Germany, http://cst.com <lb/>[19] Palumbo L, Vaccaro V G and Zobov M 1995 Proc. CERN Accelerator School: Advanced Accelerator <lb/>Physics Course No. 95-06 ed S Turner (Geneva, Switzerland) <lb/>[20] Potylitsyn A et al 2005 Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res. B 227 170 <lb/>[21] Xiang D and Huang W 2007 Phys. Rev. ST Accel. Beams 10 12801 <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex"> 1 <lb/> 2 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>3 <lb/> Figure A7.  1: Quad current  = −34.9A,  σ  y = 112.7 μm. 2: Quad current  = −35.4A, <lb/> σ  y = 69.2 μm. 3: Quad current  = −35.7A,  σ  y = 45.8 μm. 4: Quad current  = −36.0A, <lb/> σ  y = 31.5 μm. 5: Quad current  = −36.6A,  σ  y = 59.7 μm. 6: Quad current  = −37.2A, <lb/> σ  y = 88.7 μm. <lb/> </div>

			<page> 12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> New J. Phys. 16 (2014) 113029 <lb/>A Cianchi et al</note>


	</text>
</tei>
