<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="footnote"> arXiv:1503.06645v1  [physics.gen-ph] 12 Feb 2015 <lb/></note>

			<front> A Bound System in the Expanding Universe with Modified <lb/>Holographic Ricci Dark Energy and Dark Matter <lb/> En-Kun Li, <lb/> a  Yu Zhang, <lb/> a, * <lb/> Jin-Ling Geng <lb/> a  , Peng-Fei Duan <lb/> b <lb/>a  Faculty of Science, Kunming University of Science and Technology, <lb/>Kunming 650500, China. <lb/> b  City College, Kunming University of Science and Technology, <lb/>Kunming 650051, China <lb/> Abstract <lb/> The evolution of a bound system in the expanding background has been investigated in this paper. <lb/>The background is described by a FRW universe with the modified holographic dark energy model, <lb/>whose equation of state parameter changes with time and can cross the phantom boundary. To study <lb/>the evolution of the bound system, an interpolating metric is considered, and on this basis the geodesics <lb/>of a test particle are given. The equation of motion and the effective potential are also derived from the <lb/>geodesics. By studying the the effective potential and the evolution of the radius of a test particle in the <lb/>bound system of the Milky Way galaxy, we have found that the galaxy would go through three stages: <lb/>expands from a singular point; stays in a discoid for a period of time; big rip in the future. With the help <lb/>of analysing the critical angular momentum, we find that the test particle needs less angular momentum <lb/>to escape from the center mass as time passes. <lb/> keywords: bound system; expanding background; modified holographic dark energy <lb/></front>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> There is a great deal of observational evidence to prove that our universe is undergoing an accelerating <lb/>expansion phase [1, 2, 3, 4, 5]. To explain this phenomenon, a large number of theoretical models have <lb/>been put forward, and among these models the dark energy models have attracted a lot of attention [6, <lb/>7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12]. Although numerous dark energy models have been proposed, the nature of it is still <lb/>very largely in the dark. Among these dark energy models, the so called holographic dark energy, which <lb/>arises from the holographic principle [13, 14, 15, 16], seems to provide a more simple and reasonable frame <lb/>to investigate the problem of dark energy [17, 18]. According to the holographic principle, the energy <lb/>density of the holographic dark energy is written as ρ  x  = 3c <lb/> 2  M <lb/> 2 <lb/> p  L <lb/> −2  , where c is a numerical constant, and <lb/> M  p  = 1/ <lb/> √ <lb/> 8πG is the reduced Planck mass and L is the largest IR cutoff. Until now, various types of <lb/>IR cutoff have been considered to solve the dark energy problems, such as the Hubble radius [19, 20, 21], <lb/>the particle horizon [15, 22], the future event horizon [23, 24], the cosmological conformal time [25, 26], or <lb/>other generalized IR cutoff [27, 28, 29, 30, 31, 32, 33, 34]. Nowadays, the researches on the holographic <lb/>dark energy have attracted so many scientists, and lots of remarkable works have been done in this field <lb/>[35, 36, 37, 38, 39, 40, 41, 42, 43, 44]. <lb/>However, the current accelerating expansion can not be derived from the holographic dark energy models <lb/>with Hubble horizon or particle horizon as the IR cutoff [12, 45]. Meanwhile, Setare et al. [41, 46] proved <lb/>that the holographic dark energy model in the non-flat universe enclosed by the event horizon cannot cross <lb/>the phantom divide line. To solve these problems, Gao, et al. [47] raised a new holographic Ricci dark energy <lb/>model, where the length scale is given by L ∼ |R| <lb/> −1/2  , and R is the Ricci curvature scalar. Granda, et al. <lb/>[48, 49] proposed a new form of IR cutoff for the holographic dark energy, which is a linear combination of <lb/>˙ <lb/> H and H <lb/> 2  , i.e., ρ  x  ∝ αH <lb/> 2  + β ˙ <lb/> H. This model could avoid the causality problem, which appears when using <lb/>the event horizon area as the IR cutoff, meanwhile, the fine tuning problem and the coincidence problem <lb/></body>

			<front>  *  Email: zhangyu 128@126.com <lb/></front>

			<page> 1 <lb/></page>

			<body> can also be solved effectively. Recently, Chimento, et al. [50] proposed a modified form of holographic Ricci <lb/>dark energy model, it is <lb/> ρ  x  = <lb/> 2 <lb/> α−β <lb/> ˙ <lb/> H + <lb/> 3 <lb/>2  αH <lb/> 2 <lb/> , <lb/> (1) <lb/>where α and β are free constants. After their work, the modified holographic Ricci dark energy (MHRDE) is <lb/>studied in connection with the interacting dark matter in many papers, and more information can be found <lb/>in [51, 52, 53, 54]. <lb/>In modern physics, the relation between cosmic expansion and local physics is a problem of principle in <lb/>general relativity which still awaits a definitive answer [55, 56, 57, 58]. The physics of a bound system in <lb/>the expanding universe is an immediate approach for this problem. A great deal of attention have been put <lb/>on the effects of the universe&apos;s expansion on gravitationally bound system such as planetary, galaxies and <lb/>cluster systems [59, 60, 61, 62, 63, 64, 65]. Among them, Nesseris, et al. [65] have studied different bound <lb/>systems in the phantom and quintessence universe, and they also gave the numerical reconstruction of the <lb/>dissociating bound orbits. In their work, they found that the bound system got unbounded at the time when <lb/>the minimum of the time-dependent effective potential disappeared. This is not the time when the phantom <lb/>energy gravitational potential, which is due to the average (ρ + 3p), balance the attractive gravitational <lb/>potential of the mass M of the system. In the present paper, we would like to examine a bound system in an <lb/>expanding universe filled with dark matter and MHRDE. In such a model, the equation of state parameter <lb/>of MHRDE is time-depending. <lb/>This paper is organized as follows: In Sec. 2, we give a brief review of the MHRDE model and the <lb/>evolution of its equation of state parameter. The evolution of energy densities for dark matter and dark <lb/>energy are studied next. In Sec. 3, using an interpolating metric, which is Schwarzschild like in small <lb/>scales and a general time-depending FRW universe in large scales, we give the test particle&apos;s radial equation <lb/>of motion. Based on this motion equation, the effective potential is given, too. Then, the bound system <lb/>corresponding to the Milky Way galaxy is studied by discussing the evolution of the effective potential and <lb/>the change of the circular orbits. The conclusions are given in Sec. 4. In this work, we assume today&apos;s scale <lb/>factor a  0  → 1, far future a → ∞, and the unit 8πG = 1. <lb/> 2 A brief review of the universe with the MHRDE model <lb/> Now, considering that there are only two components, i.e., the pressureless dark matter and the negative <lb/>pressure dark energy. Then the Friedmann equation describing the evolution of the FRW universe can be <lb/>written as <lb/> H <lb/> 2  = <lb/> 1 <lb/>3  (ρ  m  + ρ  x  ) , <lb/> (2) <lb/>where ρ  m  and ρ  x  are the energy densities of dark matter and dark energy, H = ˙ <lb/> a/a is the Hubble parameter <lb/>and a is the scale factor. The total energy density must satisfies the following conservation law: <lb/>˙ <lb/> ρ  m  + ˙ <lb/> ρ  x  + 3H(ρ  m  + ρ  x  + p  x  ) = 0. <lb/>(3) <lb/>Since we suppose that there is no interaction between dark matter and dark energy, the conservation law <lb/>would be written in the following two separate equations <lb/>˙ <lb/> ρ  m  + 3Hρ  m  = 0, <lb/>(4) <lb/>˙ <lb/> ρ  x  + 3H(ρ  x  + p  x  ) = 0. <lb/>(5) <lb/>Let&apos;s define that, <lb/> h = <lb/> H <lb/>H0  , ˜ <lb/> ρ  m  = <lb/> ρm <lb/> 3H  2 <lb/> 0 <lb/> , ˜ <lb/> ρ  x  = <lb/> ρx <lb/> 3H  2 <lb/>0 <lb/> , <lb/> (6) <lb/>where H  0  is the present value of the Hubble parameter. Substituting Eq. (6) into Eq. (4), we obtain the <lb/>equation for conformal density of dark matter as <lb/>˜ <lb/> ρ  m  = Ω  m0  a <lb/> −3  , <lb/> (7) <lb/>where Ω  m0  = ρ  m0  /3H <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  is the present density of dark matter. Using Eqs. (1), (6) and (7), the Friedmann <lb/>equation can be written in the following conformal form <lb/> h <lb/> 2  = Ω  m0  a <lb/> −3  + <lb/> 1 <lb/>3(α−β) <lb/> dh <lb/> 2 <lb/> d ln a  + 3αh <lb/> 2 <lb/> . <lb/> (8) <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body> The general solution of the above differential equation is given by <lb/> h <lb/> 2  = <lb/> α−β <lb/> 1−β  Ω  m0  a <lb/> −3  + Ca <lb/> −3β  , <lb/> (9) <lb/>where C is a constant and can be determined by the initial condition h <lb/> 2  |  x=0  = 1. Using the initial condition <lb/>one can obtain C = 1 − <lb/> α−β <lb/> 1−β  Ω  m0  . Now, the conformal density of the MHRDE can be identified as <lb/>˜ <lb/> ρ  x  = <lb/> α−1 <lb/> 1−β  Ω  m0  a <lb/> −3  + <lb/> 1 − <lb/> α−β <lb/> 1−β  Ω  m0 <lb/> a <lb/> −3β  , <lb/> (10) <lb/>and the conformal Hubble parameter is <lb/> h <lb/> 2  = Ω  m0  a <lb/> −3  + <lb/> α − 1 <lb/>1 − β <lb/> Ω  m0  a <lb/> −3 <lb/> + <lb/> 1 − <lb/> α − β <lb/> 1 − β <lb/> Ω  m0 <lb/> a <lb/> −3β  . <lb/> (11) <lb/>Using Eqs. (5) and (10), the equation of state parameter for the MHRDE can be written as <lb/> w  x  = −1 + <lb/> (α−1)Ωm0+β[1−β−(α−β)Ωm0]a <lb/> 3(1−β) <lb/> (α−1)Ωm0+[1−β−(α−β)Ωm0]a  3(1−β)  . <lb/> (12) <lb/>From Eq. (12), one can find that the equation of state parameter provides the possibility of transition from <lb/> w  x  &gt; −1 to w  x  &lt; −1, which corresponds to the quintom model. If we consider a universe dominated by <lb/>MHRDE, where the contribution from the DM is negligible, then Eq. (12) becomes w  x  = −1 + β. So if <lb/> β &lt; 0, w  x  can cross the phantom divide. <lb/>However, from the above equations one can find that there are two free parameters that need to be <lb/>determined. To determine one of them, we will take a special condition into consideration. The derivative of <lb/> H with respect to time is given by ˙ <lb/> H = − <lb/> 3 <lb/>2 <lb/>1+wx+u <lb/>1+u  H <lb/> 2  , where u = ˜ <lb/> ρ  m  / ˜ <lb/> ρ  x  is the ratio between dark matter <lb/>and MHRDE, then Eq. (11) would be written in the following term <lb/> h <lb/> 2  = <lb/> 1+u <lb/> α−β <lb/> αh <lb/> 2  − <lb/> 1+wx+u <lb/>1+u  h <lb/> 2 <lb/> . <lb/> (13) <lb/>From this equation we obtain that the value of β given in terms of the free parameter α as β = u(1 − α) + <lb/>(1 + w  x  ). Taking the boundary conditions and the ratio between dark matter and MHRDE, i.e., <lb/> w  x0  = −1, u  0  = <lb/> ρ  m0 <lb/> ρ  x0 <lb/> = <lb/>Ω  m0 <lb/> 1 − Ω  m0 <lb/> into consideration, one can obtain <lb/> β = <lb/> Ωm0 <lb/>1−Ωm0  (1 − α). <lb/> (14) <lb/>From Eq. (14), it is easy to find that β decreases as α increases. Now, the free parameters have been reduced <lb/>to one, and for α = 1 we have β = 0. <lb/> Α1.0 <lb/> Α1.1 <lb/>Α1.2 <lb/>Α43 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1.0 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.2 <lb/> 0.0 <lb/>lna <lb/> wx <lb/> Figure 1: The evolution of the state parameter of MHRDE with respect to ln a, we choose Ω  m0  = 0.3. <lb/>The evolutions of the state parameter of MHRDE and the densities of dark matter and MHRDE are <lb/>plotted in Figs. 1 and 2, respectively. Combining the two figures, one can easily find that the future of the <lb/>universe would be MHRDE dominated. When α = 1, as shown in Fig. 1, the equation of state parameter <lb/>of MHRDE is w  x  = −1, and as shown in Fig. 2, its energy density is a constant, which indicates that the <lb/>MHRDE is ΛCDM like when α = 1. <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body> Α1.0 <lb/> Α1.1 <lb/>Α1.2 <lb/>Α43 <lb/>Ρm <lb/>Ρx <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 2 <lb/>4 <lb/> 15 <lb/>10 <lb/>5 <lb/> 0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>lna <lb/>lnΡ <lb/> Figure 2: The evolution of the energy density of dark matter and MHRDE, we choose Ω  m0  = 0.3. <lb/> 3 Evolution of the bound system <lb/> In order to study the bound system in the expanding universe, one needs the geodesics of a test particle <lb/>in the expanding universe. Now, let&apos;s consider an appropriate metric that satisfies the static Schwarzschild <lb/>metric at small distance and a time-depending FRW space time at large distances. Following most authors <lb/>[62, 65, 66], we consider such an interpolating metric, which is under the Newtonian limit (weak field, low <lb/>velocities), takeing the form [65]: <lb/> ds <lb/> 2  = <lb/> 1 − <lb/> 2GM <lb/> a(t)ρ <lb/> · dt <lb/> 2  − a(t) <lb/> 2  · [dρ <lb/> 2 <lb/> +ρ <lb/> 2  · (dθ <lb/> 2  + sin <lb/> 2  θdϕ <lb/> 2  )], <lb/>(15) <lb/>where ρ is the comoving radial coordinate. Using r = a(t)ρ, one can obtain the geodesics <lb/> − <lb/> ¨ <lb/> r − <lb/> ¨ <lb/> a <lb/>a  r <lb/> − <lb/> GM <lb/>r  2  + r ˙ <lb/> ϕ <lb/> 2  = 0, <lb/>(16) <lb/> r <lb/> 2  ˙ <lb/> ϕ = L, <lb/> (17) <lb/>where L is the constant angular momentum per unit mass. Then, the radial equation of motion for a test <lb/>particle in the Newtonian limit would be <lb/>¨ <lb/> r = − <lb/> GM <lb/>r  2  + <lb/> L <lb/> 2 <lb/> r  3  + <lb/> ¨ <lb/> a <lb/>a  r. <lb/> (18) <lb/>From this equation one can obtain the effective potential, which determines the dynamics of the bound <lb/>system, by <lb/>  = −∂V /∂r. Integrating it with respect to r and ignoring the arbitrary integration function of <lb/>time, one can obtain the effective potential <lb/> V  ef f  (t, r) = − <lb/> GM <lb/>r  + <lb/> L <lb/> 2 <lb/> 2r  2  − <lb/> ¨ <lb/> a <lb/> 2a  r <lb/> 2  . <lb/> (19) <lb/>Here, taking <lb/> d <lb/>dt  = H <lb/> d <lb/>d ln a  into consideration, we can obtain <lb/>˙ <lb/> r = <lb/> dr <lb/>dt  = Hr <lb/> ′  , <lb/> (20) <lb/>where r <lb/> ′  = dr/d ln a, then for <lb/>  one has <lb/>¨ <lb/> r = <lb/> d ˙ <lb/> r <lb/>dt  = <lb/> d(Hr <lb/> ′  ) <lb/> d ln a <lb/>d ln a <lb/>dt  = H <lb/> 2  r <lb/> ′′  + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  (H <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> ′  r <lb/> ′  . <lb/> (21) <lb/>We also takë <lb/> a/a = ˙ <lb/> H + H <lb/> 2  into account and use Eq. (21), then, Eq. (18) would be <lb/> H <lb/> 2  r <lb/> ′′  + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  (H <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> ′  r <lb/> ′  = − <lb/> GM <lb/>r  2  + <lb/> L <lb/> 2 <lb/> r  3 <lb/> +[ <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(H <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> ′  + H <lb/> 2  ] · r. <lb/> (22) <lb/>Similarly, one can obtain the effective potential in terms of H as <lb/> V  ef f  = − <lb/> GM <lb/>r  + <lb/> L <lb/> 2 <lb/> 2r  2  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  [ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  (H <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> ′  + H <lb/> 2  ]r <lb/> 2  . <lb/> (23) <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body> In what follows, we will focus on the evolution of a two body bound system in the expanding unverse. <lb/>Let us assume that at the present time, i.e., a = a  0  , a test particle moves on a circular orbit with radius r  0  , <lb/>and ˙ <lb/> ϕ(t  0  ) <lb/> 2  = ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  = GM/r <lb/> 3 <lb/>0  . Taking the following conformal forms into consideration <lb/> ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  = <lb/> GM <lb/> r  3 <lb/> 0  H  2 <lb/>0 <lb/> , r = r/r  0  , V  ef f  = V  ef f  /(H <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  r <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  ), <lb/>(24) <lb/>Eqs. (22) and (23) could be written in the following forms <lb/> h <lb/> 2  r <lb/> ′′  + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  (h <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> ′  r <lb/> ′  = − <lb/> ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0 <lb/> r  2  + <lb/> ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0 <lb/> r  3  + λ(a) <lb/> 2  r, <lb/> (25) <lb/> V  ef f  = − <lb/> ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0 <lb/> r  + <lb/> ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0 <lb/> 2r  2  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  λ(a) <lb/> 2  r <lb/> 2  , <lb/> (26) <lb/>where <lb/> λ(a) <lb/> 2  = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  (h <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> ′  + h <lb/> 2  . <lb/> (27) <lb/>By analysing the effective potential, one could find the radius of the circular orbit is given by the minimum <lb/> r  min  (a) of the effective potential. From Eq. (26), we know that the location of r  min  (a) is depending on the <lb/>scale factor. Radius of the circular orbit is given by solving the following equation <lb/> λ(a) <lb/> 2 <lb/> ω  2 <lb/>0 <lb/> r <lb/> 4 <lb/> min  − r  min  + 1 = 0. <lb/>(28) <lb/>In fact, Eq. (28) has a solution only for λ(a) <lb/> 2  ≤ 27ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  /256 [65]. Therefore, when λ(a) <lb/> 2  = 27ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  /256, the <lb/>minimum of the effective potential disappears, then, the system becomes unbound. Here, we define that the <lb/>solution of equation λ(a) <lb/> 2  = 27ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  /256 as a = a  rip  , which means the big rip occurs at the trip time a  rip  . <lb/>To investigate the future radial evolution of a bound gravitational system, we will take a specific bound <lb/>system — the Milky Way galasy (M = 2 × 10 <lb/> 45  gr, r  0  = 5 × 10 <lb/> 22  cm, ω  0  = 182) — into consideration. The <lb/>numerical evolution of the radius for different α is shown in Fig. 3. As shown in Fig. 3, it is easy to find that <lb/>all the curves have two turning point, one occurs at small a, which means the early universe, and another <lb/>occurs at big a, which means the future universe. According to Fig. 3, we find that r &lt; r  0  occurs before the <lb/>first turning point, and r &gt; r  0  occurs after the second turning point. From this we can say that the Milky <lb/>Way galaxy would go through three stages: the first stage is the expanding stage: from a very small radius <lb/>to today&apos;s size; the second is the steady stage: the radius changes little and the galaxy stays in a discoid; the <lb/>third is the rip stage: the radius of the galaxy becomes bigger and bigger that the galaxy would be ripped. <lb/>From Fig. 3, one can also find that as α increases the values of a  rip  decreases, which means that the big rip <lb/>occurs more early. The two body bound system corresponding to the Milky Way galaxy is plotted in Fig. <lb/>4. From Fig. 4, it is more easy to find that the galaxy comes from a singular point, stays in discoid for a <lb/>period of time, and will be ripped finally. <lb/> 50 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>lnaa 0  <lb/> lnr <lb/> Figure 3: The numerical evolution of the radius for the Milky Way galaxy is plotted under different cases: <lb/>continuous line for α = 1.1, dashed line for α = 1.2 and dotted line for α = 4/3. Here we choose Ω  m0  = 0.3. <lb/>The evolution of the effective potential around the trip time a  rip  is shown in Fig. 5. As a contrast, the <lb/>effective potential of the present time is also plotted in Fig. 5. As we know, the stability of a bound system <lb/>depends on whether the effective potential has a minimum. From Fig. 5, one can find that when a &lt; a  rip  , <lb/>as the radius r increases the effective potential curves decreases to a minimum first, then increases to a <lb/>maximum and finally decreases to −∞, and its maximum decreases as the scale factor increases. Then we <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body> Milky Way Galaxy Orbits <lb/> a  end  a  rip <lb/> 1.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/> 0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/> 1.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/> 0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>xr0 <lb/>yr0 <lb/> Figure 4: The evolution of the system of the Milky Way galaxy until the potential minimum disappears. <lb/>Here, we choose α = 1.2 and Ω  m0  = 0.3. <lb/>know that the effective potential curves have a minimum, which indicates the possibility of bound orbits for <lb/>the test particle. However, as we can see from Fig. 5, when a = a  rip  , the effective potential curve has only <lb/>one inflection point and when a &gt; a  rip  there is no inflection point. Then, we can say that when the scale <lb/>factor a ≥ a  rip  , the gravitational force can not bound the test particle any longer, they will fly to distant <lb/>area under the negative pressure force of the MHRDE. <lb/> aa 0 <lb/> a0.9a rip <lb/> aa rip <lb/> a1.1a rip <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/> 1 10 <lb/> 6 <lb/> 500 000 <lb/>0 <lb/>500 000 <lb/>rr 0 <lb/> Vrr <lb/> 0  H <lb/> 0 <lb/> 2 <lb/> r <lb/> 0 <lb/> 2 <lb/> Figure 5: The evolution of the effective potential corresponding to different scale factor a with respect to <lb/>the dimensionless radius r/r  0  , and we choose α = 1.2, Ω  m0  = 0.3. <lb/>We have studied the test particle at a circular orbit above, where we assume that ˙ <lb/> ϕ(t  0  ) <lb/> 2  = ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  = GM/r <lb/> 3 <lb/>0  . <lb/>Now, let&apos;s consider a different case that the test particle has different angular momentums. Eq. (26) could <lb/>be written in the following form <lb/> V  ef f  = − <lb/> ω <lb/> 2 <lb/> 0 <lb/> r  + <lb/> ˜ <lb/> L <lb/> 2 <lb/> 2r  2  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  λ(a) <lb/> 2  r <lb/> 2  , <lb/> (29) <lb/>where <lb/> 2  = L <lb/> 2  /(H <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  r <lb/> 4 <lb/>0  ). From Eq. (29) one can find that wheñ <lb/> L <lb/> 2  = ˜ <lb/> L <lb/> 2 <lb/> c  = <lb/> 3 <lb/>4  ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  [ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  /(4λ(a) <lb/> 2  )] <lb/> 1 <lb/>3  , the effective <lb/>potential curves have no extremum. The critical angular momentum <lb/>  c  with respect to ln a is plotted in Fig. <lb/>6. From Fig. 6, one can obtain that the critical angular momentum decreases as ln a increases, which means <lb/>with the passage of time, the test particle would need less angular momentum to escape the gravitational <lb/>force from the center mass. <lb/>In order to make this more clear, the effective potential curves for the test particle with different angular <lb/>momentums are shown in Fig. 7. From Fig. 7 (a), one can find that the critical angular momentum <lb/>  is <lb/>more big than ω  0  , i.e., ˜ <lb/> L <lb/> 2 <lb/> c  &gt;&gt; ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  . Fig. 7 (b) shows that <lb/> 2 <lb/> c  = ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  . As we all know, when the effective <lb/>potential has no extremum, the test particle could not be bounded together. Then, with the help of the <lb/>two graphics in Fig. 7, we can say that the test particle would need less angular momentum to escape the <lb/>immense pull from the center mass with the passing of time. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body> 0 <lb/> 20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>1  10 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 5  10 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 1  10 <lb/> 5 <lb/> 5  10 <lb/> 5 <lb/> 1  10 <lb/> 6 <lb/> 5  10 <lb/> 6 <lb/> 1  10 <lb/> 7 <lb/> lna <lb/>lnLcr0 <lb/> 4 <lb/> Figure 6: The critical angular momentum <lb/>  c  with respect to ln a. Here, we choose α = 1.2 and Ω  m0  = 0.3. <lb/> L <lb/>  2 <lb/> 0.2Ω0 <lb/> 2 <lb/> L <lb/>  2 <lb/> L <lb/> c <lb/> L <lb/>  2 <lb/> Ω0 <lb/> 2 <lb/> L <lb/>  2 <lb/> 2Ω0 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/> 600 000 <lb/> 400 000 <lb/> 200 000 <lb/>0 <lb/>200 000 <lb/>400 000 <lb/>600 000 <lb/>800 000 <lb/>rr0 <lb/>Vrr0H0 <lb/> 2 <lb/> r0 <lb/> 2 <lb/> a <lb/> L <lb/>  2 <lb/> 0.2Ω0 <lb/> 2 <lb/> L <lb/>  2 <lb/> L <lb/> c <lb/> L <lb/>  2 <lb/> Ω0 <lb/> 2 <lb/> L <lb/>  2 <lb/> 2Ω0 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/> 600 000 <lb/> 400 000 <lb/> 200 000 <lb/>0 <lb/>200 000 <lb/>400 000 <lb/>600 000 <lb/>800 000 <lb/>rr0 <lb/>Vrr0H0 <lb/> 2 <lb/> r0 <lb/> 2 <lb/> a <lb/> Figure 7: The evolution of the effective potential with respect to ln a under different angular momentum. <lb/>In figure (a), we choose the scale factor as a = a  0  and in figure (b) we choose a = a  rip  . Here, we choose <lb/> α = 1.2 and Ω  m0  = 0.3. <lb/> 4 Conclusion <lb/> In this paper, we have investigated the evolution of a bound system in the expanding universe, the universe <lb/>is described by the FRW universe with only two cosmic components: dark matter and dark energy. In the <lb/>present paper the dark energy is considered as the MHRDE, whose density is ρ  x  = <lb/> 2 <lb/> α−β  ( ˙ <lb/> H + <lb/> 3 <lb/>2  H <lb/> 2  ) and the <lb/>equation of state parameter of it is time-depending. From Sec. 2 one can find that the MHRDE behaves <lb/>like the quintom. <lb/>To investigate the bound system in the expanding universe, we have considered an interpolating metric <lb/>which can reduce to the static Schwarzschild metric at small scales but FRW metric at large scales. The <lb/>geodesics of a test particle are derived by this metric and using the geodesics we get the radial equation of <lb/>motion for a two body bound system. The test particle&apos;s motion in the Milky Way galaxy is examined by <lb/>analysing the equation of motion and the effective potential. We have found that the the galaxy would go <lb/>through three stages: the first stage is expanding from a singular point, then it will stay in a discoid for a <lb/>period of time, and it will be ripped owing to the negative pressure of the MHRDE finally. <lb/>Moreover, by studying the evolution of the critical angular momentum with respect to the scale factor <lb/> a, we find that with the passage of time, the test particle would need less angular momentum to escape the <lb/>immense pull of the center mass. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments <lb/> This work was supported in part by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Grants No. 11347101, <lb/>No. 11405076), the Science Foundation of the Education Department of Yunnan Province (Grant No. <lb/>2014Y066), and the Talent Cultivation Foundation of Kunming University of Science and Technology (Grants <lb/>No. KKSY201207053, No. KKSY201356060). Yu Zhang would like to acknowledge the support of the <lb/>working Funds of the Introduced High-level Talents of Yunnan Province from the Department of Human <lb/>Resources and Social Security of Yunnan Province. <lb/></div>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] Riess, A. G., et al.: Astron. J. 116, 1009 (1998) <lb/>[2] Perlmutter, S., et al.: Astrophys. J. 517, 565 (1999) <lb/>[3] Knop, R. A., et al.: Astrophys.J. 598, 102 (2003) <lb/>[4] Tonry, J. L., et al.: Astrophys. J. 594, 1 (2003) <lb/>[5] Riess, A. G., et al.: Astrophys. J. 607, 665 (2004) <lb/>[6] Sahni, V. and Starobinsky, A. A.: Int. J. Mod. Phys. D 09, 373 (2000) <lb/>[7] Padmanabhan, T.: Phys. Rep. 380, 235 (2003) <lb/>[8] Peebles, P. J. E. and Ratra, B.: Rev. Mod. Phys. 75, 559 (2003) <lb/>[9] Sahni, V. and Starobinsky, A.: Int. J. Mod. Phys. D 15, 2105 (2006) <lb/>[10] Copeland, E. J., Sami, M. and Tsujikawa, S.: Int. J. Mod. Phys. D 15, 1753 (2006) <lb/>[11] Frieman, J., Turner, M. and Huterer, D.: Annu. Rev. Astron. Astrophys. 46, 385 (2008) <lb/>[12] Li, M., Li, X. D., Wang, S. and Wang, Y.: Commun. Theor. Phys. 56, 525 (2011) <lb/>[13] &apos;t Hooft, G.: arXiv:gr-qc/9310026 (1993) <lb/>[14] Susskind, L.: J. Math. Phys. 36, 6377 (1995) <lb/>[15] Fischler, W. and Susskind, L.: arXiv:hep-th/9806039 (1998) <lb/>[16] Bousso, R.: Rev. Mod. Phys. 74, 825C874 (2002) <lb/>[17] Setare, M. R.: Phys. Lett. B 642, 1-4 (2006) <lb/>[18] Sheykhi, A.: Phys. Lett. B 680, 2 (2009) <lb/>[19] Cohen, A. G., Kaplan, D. B. and Nelson, A. E.: Phys. Rev. Lett. 82, 4971 (1999) <lb/>[20] Horava, P., Minic, D.: Phys. Rev. Lett. 85, 1610 (2000) <lb/>[21] Thomas, S.: Phys. Rev. Lett. 89, 081301 (2002) <lb/>[22] Bousso, R.: J. High Energy Phys. 07, 004 (1999) <lb/>[23] Huang, Q. G. and Li, M.: JCAP 0408, 013 (2004) <lb/>[24] Li, M.: Phys. Lett. B 603, 1 (2004) <lb/>[25] Cai, R. G.: Phys. Lett. B 657, 228 (2007) <lb/>[26] Wei, H. and Cai, R. G.: Phys. Lett. B 660, 113 (2008) <lb/>[27] Chen, S. and Jing, J.: Phys. Lett. B 679, 144 (2009) <lb/>[28] Cai, R. G., Hu, B. and Zhang, Y.: Commun. Theor. Phys. 51, 954 (2009) <lb/>[29] Durán, I. and Pavón, D.: Phys. Rev. D 83, 023504 (2011) <lb/>[30] Wang, Y. and Xu, L.: Phys. Rev. D 81, 083523 (2010) <lb/>[31] Xu, L., Li, W. and Lu, J.: Eur. Phys. J. C 60, 135-140 (2009) <lb/>[32] Xu, L., Lu, J. and Li, W.: Eur. Phys. J. C 64, 89-95 (2009) <lb/>[33] Xu, L. and Wang, Y.: JCAP 6, 002 (2010) <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [34] Zhang, M. J., Ma, C., Zhang, Z. S., Zhai, Z. X. and Zhang, T. J.: Phys. Rev. D 88, 063534 (2013) <lb/>[35] Bouhmadi-López, M. and Tavakoli, Y.: Phys. Rev. D 87, 023515 (2013) <lb/>[36] Cai, Y. F., Saridakis, E. N., Setare, M. R. and Xia, J. Q.: Phys. Rep. 493, 1C60 (2010) <lb/>[37] del Campo, S., Fabris, J. C., Herrera, R. and Zimdahl, W.: Phys. Rev. D 87, 123002 (2013) <lb/>[38] Ghaffari, S., Dehghani, M. H. and Sheykhi, A.: Phys. Rev. D 89, 123009 (2014) <lb/>[39] Li, M., Li, X. D., Meng, J. and Zhang, Z.: Phys. Rev. D 88, 023503 (2013) <lb/>[40] Setare, M. R. and Vagenas, E. C.: Int. J. Mod. Phys. D 18, 147 (2009) <lb/>[41] Setare, M. R.: Phys. Lett. B 644, 99-103 (2007) <lb/>[42] Setare, M. R.: Eur. Phys. J. C 50, 991-998 (2007) <lb/>[43] Setare, M. R.: Int. J. Mod. Phys. D 17, 2219 (2008) <lb/>[44] Xu, L.: Phys. Rev. D 87, 043525 (2013) <lb/>[45] Hsu, S. D. H.: Phys. Lett. B 594, 13 (2004) <lb/>[46] Setare, M. R.: Phys. Lett. B 642, 421-425 (2006) <lb/>[47] Gao, C., Wu, F., Chen, X. and Shen, Y. G.: Phys. Rev. D 79, 043511 (2009) <lb/>[48] Granda, L. N. and Oliveros, A.: Phys. Lett. B 669, 275 (2008) <lb/>[49] Granda, L. N. and Oliveros, A.: Phys. Lett. B 671, 199-202 (2009) <lb/>[50] Chimento, L. P. and Richarte, M. G.: Phys. Rev. D 84, 123507 (2011) <lb/>[51] Chattopadhyay, S. and Pasqua, A.: Indian J. Phys. 87, 1053-1057 (2013) <lb/>[52] Chimento, L. P. and Richarte, M. G.: Phys. Rev. D 85, 127301 (2012) <lb/>[53] Chimento, L. P., Forte, M. and Richarte, M. G.: Eur. Phys. J. C 73, 2285 (2013) <lb/>[54] Chimento, L. P., Forte, M. and Richarte, M. G.: Eur. Phys. J. C 73, 2352 (2013) <lb/>[55] Bars, I., Steinhardt, P. and Turok, N.: Phys. Rev. D 89, 043515 (2014) <lb/>[56] Faraoni, V. and Jacques, A.: Phys. Rev. D 76, 063510 (2007) <lb/>[57] Gao, C., Chen, X., Faraoni, V. and Shen, Y. G.: Phys. Rev. D 78, 024008 (2008) <lb/>[58] Gao, C., Chen, X., Shen, Y. G. and Faraoni, V.: Phys. Rev. D 84, 104047 (2011) <lb/>[59] Bona, C. and Stela, J.: Phys. Rev. D 36, 2915 (1987) <lb/>[60] Bonnor, W. B.: Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc. 282, 1467 (1996) <lb/>[61] Cooperstock, F. I., Faraoni, V. and Vollick, D. N.: Astrophys. J. 503, 61 (1998) <lb/>[62] Einstein, A. and Straus, E. G.: Rev. Mod. Phys. 18, 148 (1946) <lb/>[63] Gonzalez-Diaz, P. F. and Siguenza, C. L.: Phys. Lett. B 589, 78 (2004) <lb/>[64] Stefancic, H.: Phys. Lett. B 595, 9 (2004) <lb/>[65] Nesseris, S. and Perivolaropoulos, L.: Phys. Rev. D 70, 123529 (2004) <lb/>[66] McVittie, G. C.: Mon. Not. R. Astron. Soc. 93, 325 (1933) <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>9 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
