<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> arXiv:1410.1182v1  [math.AG] 5 Oct 2014 <lb/> A GENERALIZED QUOT SCHEME AND MEROMORPHIC VORTICES <lb/> INDRANIL BISWAS, AJNEET DHILLON, JACQUES HURTUBISE, <lb/>AND RICHARD A. WENTWORTH <lb/> Abstract. Let X be a compact connected Riemann surface. Fix a positive integer r <lb/> and two nonnegative integers d  p  and d  z  . Consider all pairs of the form (F , f ), where F <lb/> is a holomorphic vector bundle on X of rank r and degree d  z  − d  p  , and <lb/> f : O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  −→ F <lb/> is a meromorphic homomorphism which an isomorphism outside a finite subset of X <lb/> and has pole (respectively, zero) of total degree d  p  (respectively, d  z  ). Two such pairs <lb/>(F  1  , f  1  ) and (F  2  , f  2  ) are called isomorphic if there is a holomorphic isomorphism of F  1 <lb/> with F  2  over X that takes f  1  to f  2  . We construct a natural compactification of the <lb/>moduli space equivalence classes pairs of the above type. The Poincaré polynomial of <lb/>this compactification is computed. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> Take a compact connected Riemann surface X. Fix positive integers r and d. Consider <lb/>pairs of the form (E , f ), where E is a holomorphic vector bundle on X of rank r and <lb/>degree d, and <lb/> f : O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  −→ E <lb/> is an O  X  –linear homomorphism which is an isomorphism outside a finite subset of X. <lb/> This implies that the total degree of zeros of f is d. Two such pairs (E  1  , f  1  ) and (E  2  , f  2  ) <lb/>are called equivalent if there is a holomorphic isomorphism <lb/> φ : E  1  −→ E  2 <lb/> such that φ • f  1  = f  2  . Such pairs are examples of vortices [BDW], [Br], [BR], [Ba], <lb/>[EINOS]. <lb/>For any pair (E , f ) of the above type, consider the dual homomorphism <lb/> f <lb/>  *  : E <lb/>  *  −→ (O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  ) <lb/>  *  = O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  . <lb/> The quotient O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  /image(f <lb/>  *  ) is an element of the Quot scheme Quot(r, d) that parametrizes <lb/>all torsion quotients of O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  of degree d. Conversely, given any torsion quotient <lb/> O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X <lb/>ψ <lb/> −→ T <lb/> of degree d, consider the homomorphism <lb/> O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  = (O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  ) <lb/>  *  ψ  ′ <lb/> −→ kernel(ψ) <lb/>* <lb/></body>

			<front> 2000 Mathematics Subject Classification. 14H60, 14D21, 14D23. <lb/> Key words and phrases. Generalized Quot scheme, meromorphic vortices, moduli space, Poincaré <lb/>polynomial. <lb/></front>

			<page> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> I. BISWAS, A. DHILLON, J. HURTUBISE, AND R. A. WENTWORTH <lb/></note>

			<body> induced by the inclusion kernel(ψ) ֒→ O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  . The pair (kernel(ψ) <lb/>  *  , ψ <lb/> ′  ) is clearly of the <lb/>above type. Therefore, the moduli space of equivalence classes of pairs (E , f ) is identified <lb/>with the Quot scheme Quot(r, d). <lb/> Here we consider pairs of the form (E , f ), where E is a holomorphic vector bundle on <lb/> X of rank r and degree d, and <lb/> f : O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  −→ E <lb/> is an O  X  –linear meromorphic homomorphism which is an isomorphism outside a finite <lb/>subset of X. We assume that the total degree of the poles of the meromorphic homo-<lb/>morphism is d  p  . This implies that the total degree of the zeros of the meromorphic <lb/>homomorphism is d + d  p  . As before, two such pairs (E  1  , f  1  ) and (E  2  , f  2  ) will be called <lb/>equivalent if there is a holomorphic isomorphism <lb/> φ : E  1  −→ E  2 <lb/> such that φ • f  1  = f  2  . The equivalence classes of pairs can be considered as examples of <lb/>meromorphic vortices. <lb/>We construct a natural compactification of the moduli space of these meromorphic <lb/>vortices. We compute the Poincaré polynomial of this compactification. <lb/>2. Preliminaries <lb/> Let S be a scheme and Y −→ S a smooth projective morphism. Given a coherent sheaf <lb/> F on Y flat over S and a numerical polynomial r(t), we denote by Quot(F /S, r(t)) the <lb/>Grothendieck Quot scheme over S parametrizing quotients of F with Hilbert polynomial <lb/> r(t) [Gr]. There is a universal exact sequence on Quot(F /S, r(t)) ×  S  Y <lb/> 0 −→ K <lb/> univ <lb/>Quot(F /S,r(t))  −→ π <lb/>  * <lb/> Y  F −→ Q <lb/> univ <lb/>Quot(F /S,r(t))  −→ 0 , <lb/> where π  Y  : Quot(F /S, r(t)) ×  S  Y −→ Y is the natural projection. Often we will just <lb/>drop the subscripts and write K <lb/> univ  or Q <lb/> univ  instead. This construction is well behaved <lb/>with respect to pull-backs, so let us record the following: <lb/> Lemma 2.1. For any morphism g : T −→ S, the base change <lb/> Quot(g <lb/>  *  F /T, r(t)) ∼ = Quot(F /S, r(t)) ×  S  T <lb/> holds. <lb/>Proof. This follows by examining the corresponding representable functors. <lb/> We will mostly be interested in the case where Y −→ S is a smooth, connected and of <lb/>relative dimension one, that is a relative curve, and F is locally free of rank r. Further, <lb/>we will only consider torsion quotients of rank zero and degree d. This Quot scheme will <lb/>be denoted by Quot(F /S, d). When r = 1 and S is a point, then <lb/>Quot(O, d) = Sym <lb/> d  (Y ) , <lb/> the d-th symmetric power of Y . <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> A GENERALIZED QUOT SCHEME AND MEROMORPHIC VORTICES <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body> Given an positive integer d by a partition of length k &gt; 0 of d we mean a sequence <lb/> P = (p  1  , p  2  , · · · , p  k  ) of non-negative integers with <lb/>  k <lb/>i=1  p  i  = d. For such a partition <lb/>define d(P) := <lb/>  k <lb/>i=1  (i − 1)p  i  . We will write <lb/>Sym <lb/> P  (Y ) = Sym <lb/> p  1  (Y ) × · · · × Sym <lb/> pr  (Y ) . <lb/> 3. A relative Quot scheme <lb/> Let X be a compact connected Riemann surface. Let E and F be two holomorphic <lb/>vector bundles on X of common rank r. Take a dense open subset U ⊂ X, such that <lb/>the complement S := X \ U is a finite set, and take an isomorphism of coherent analytic <lb/>sheaves <lb/> f : E|  U  −→ F |  U <lb/> over U. This homomorphism f will be called meromorphic if there is a positive integer n <lb/> such that f extends to a homomorphism of coherent analytic sheaves <lb/> f : E −→ F ⊗ O  X  (nS) ⊃ F <lb/> over X, where S is the reduced divisor defined by the finite subset S. Note that since <lb/>the divisor S is effective, we have F ⊂ F ⊗ O  X  (nS). Therefore, f is meromorphic if and <lb/>only if the homomorphism f is algebraic with respect to the algebraic structures on E|  U <lb/> and F |  U  given by the algebraic structures on E and F respectively. <lb/>Take a meromorphic homomorphism f as above. We note that the extension <lb/> f is <lb/>uniquely determined by f because f and <lb/> f coincide over U. The inverse image <lb/> E(f ) := <lb/> f <lb/> −1  (F ) ⊂ E <lb/> (recall that F ⊂ F ⊗ O  X  (nS)) is clearly independent of the choice of n. We note that <lb/>both E(f ) and <lb/> f (E(f )) are holomorphic vector bundles on X because they are coherent <lb/>analytic subsheaves of holomorphic vector bundles. Both of then are of rank r, and the <lb/>restriction <lb/>(3.1) <lb/> f |  E(f )  : E(f ) −→ <lb/> f (E(f )) <lb/>is an isomorphism of holomorphic vector bundles. Define <lb/>(3.2) <lb/> Q  p  (f ) := E/E(f ) and Q  z  (f ) := F /( <lb/> f (E(f ))) <lb/>(the subscripts &quot; p &quot; and &quot; z &quot; stand for &quot; pole &quot; and &quot; zero &quot; respectively). We note that both <lb/> Q  p  (f ) and Q  z  (f ) are torsion coherent analytic sheaves on X. In particular, their supports <lb/>are finite subsets of X. From (3.2) it follows that <lb/>(3.3) <lb/>degree(Q  p  (f )) = degree(E) − degree(E(f )) and <lb/>degree(Q  z  (f )) = degree(F ) − degree( <lb/> f (E(f ))) . <lb/> Fix positive integers r, d  p  and d  z  . Set the domain E to be the trivial vector bundle O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X <lb/> of rank r. Consider all triples of the form (F , U , f ), where <lb/> • F is a holomorphic vector bundle on X of rank r, <lb/> • U is the complement of a finite subset of X, and <lb/> • f : O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  |  U  = O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> U  −→ F |  U  is a meromorphic homomorphism such that <lb/>degree(Q  p  (f )) = d  p  and degree(Q  z  (f )) = d  z  . <lb/></body>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> I. BISWAS, A. DHILLON, J. HURTUBISE, AND R. A. WENTWORTH <lb/></note>

			<body> Since <lb/> f |  E(f )  in (3.1) is an isomorphism, from (3.3) we conclude that <lb/>(3.4) <lb/>degree(F ) = d  z  − d  p  + degree(O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  ) = d  z  − d  p  . <lb/> Two such triples (F  1  , U  1  , f  1  ) and (F  2  , U  2  , f  2  ) will be called equivalent if there is a holo-<lb/>morphic isomorphism of vector bundles over X <lb/>β : F  1  −→ F  2 <lb/> such that <lb/> β • (f  1  |  U  1  ∩U  2  ) = f  2  |  U  1  ∩U  2  . <lb/> Therefore, the equivalence class of (F , U , f ) depends only on (F , f ) and it is independent <lb/>of U. More precisely, (F , U , f ) is equivalent to (F , W , f |  W  ) for every W ⊂ U such that <lb/>the complement U \ W is a finite set. <lb/>Let <lb/>(3.5) <lb/>Q <lb/> 0  = Q <lb/> 0 <lb/> X  (r, d  p  , d  z  ) <lb/>be the space of all equivalence classes of triples of the above form. We will embed Q <lb/> 0  as <lb/>a Zariski open subset of a smooth complex projective variety. <lb/>Take any triple (F , U , f ) as above that is represented by a point of Q <lb/> 0  . Consider the <lb/>short exact sequence <lb/>(3.6) <lb/>0 −→ E(f ) := kernel(q  p  ) −→ E = O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X <lb/>qp <lb/> −→ Q  p  (f ) −→ 0 , <lb/> where q  p  denotes the projection to the quotient in (3.2). We also have <lb/> E(f ) = <lb/> f (E(f )) ֒→ F <lb/> (recall that <lb/> f |  E(f )  in (3.1) is an isomorphism). Let <lb/>(3.7) <lb/>0 −→ F <lb/>  *  −→ E(f ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">  * <lb/> be the dual of the above inclusion of E(f ) in F . From (3.6) we have degree(E(f ) <lb/>  *  ) = <lb/>degree(Q  p  (f )) = d  p  . Therefore, from (3.4) it follows that <lb/>degree(E(f ) <lb/>  *  /F <lb/>  *  ) = degree(E(f ) <lb/>  *  ) − degree(F <lb/>  *  ) = d  p  + d  z  − d  p  = d  z <lb/> as degree(F <lb/>  *  ) = −degree(F ). These imply that we can recover the equivalence class of <lb/>(F , f ) once we know the following two: <lb/> • the torsion quotient Q  p  (f ) of O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  of degree d  p  , and <lb/> • the torsion quotient E(f ) <lb/>  *  /F <lb/>  *  of E(f ) <lb/>  *  of degree d  z  . <lb/>(It should be clarified that &quot; knowing the torsion quotient Q  p  (f ) &quot; means knowing the sheaf <lb/> Q  p  (f ) along with the surjective homomorphism O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  −→ Q  p  (f ); similarly &quot; knowing the <lb/>torsion quotient E(f ) <lb/>  *  /F <lb/>  *   &quot; means knowing the sheaf E(f ) <lb/>  *  /F <lb/>  *  along with the surjective <lb/>homomorphism from E(f ) <lb/>  *  to it.) Indeed, once we know Q  p  (f ), we know the kernel E(f ) <lb/>and hence know E(f ) <lb/>  *  ; if we know the quotient E(f ) <lb/>  *  /F <lb/>  *  , then we know the subsheaf F <lb/>  * <lb/> of E(f ) <lb/>  *  . The dual of this inclusion F <lb/>  *  ֒→ E(f ) <lb/>  *  , namely the homomorphism <lb/> E(f ) −→ F , <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A GENERALIZED QUOT SCHEME AND MEROMORPHIC VORTICES <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body> gives the meromorphic homomorphism f . In other words, we have the diagram <lb/>0 <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> 0 −→ E(f ) −→ O <lb/> ⊕r  −→ Q  p  −→ 0 <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> f <lb/> F  <lb/> <lb/> Q  z <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> 0 <lb/>Let Quot(r, d  p  ) be the Quot scheme parametrizing the torsion quotients of O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  of <lb/>degree d  p  . We have the tautological short exact sequence of coherent analytic sheaves on <lb/> X × Q(r, d  p  ) <lb/>(3.8) <lb/>0 −→ K <lb/> univ  −→ p <lb/>  * <lb/> X  O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  −→ Q <lb/> univ  −→ 0 , <lb/> where p  X  is the projection of X × Quot(r, d  p  ) to X. We write K = K <lb/> univ  . Now consider <lb/>the dual vector bundle <lb/> K <lb/>  *  −→ X × Quot(r, d  p  ) <lb/> p  Q <lb/> −→ Quot(r, d  p  ) , <lb/> where p  Q  is the natural projection. Using p  Q  , we will consider K <lb/>  *  as a family of vector <lb/>bundles on X parametrized by Quot(r, d  p  ). For any point y ∈ Quot(r, d  p  ), the vector <lb/>bundle K <lb/>  *  |  X×{y}  over X will be denoted by K <lb/>  * <lb/>|y  . Let <lb/>(3.9) <lb/> ϕ : Quot(r, d  p  , d  z  ) := Quot(K <lb/>  *  / Quot(r, d  p  ), d  z  ) −→ Q(r, d  p  ) <lb/>be the relative Quot scheme over Quot(r, d  p  ), for the family K <lb/>  *  , parametrizing the torsion <lb/>quotients of degree d  z  . Therefore, for any point y ∈ Quot(r, d  p  ), the fiber ϕ <lb/> −1  (y) is the <lb/>Quot scheme parametrizing the torsion quotients of degree d  z  of the vector bundle K <lb/>  * <lb/>|y  . <lb/>Both Quot(r, d  p  ) and the fibers of ϕ are irreducible smooth projective varieties. The <lb/>morphism ϕ is smooth. Therefore, the projective variety Quot(r, d  p  , d  z  ) is irreducible and <lb/>smooth. <lb/>Consider Q <lb/> 0  defined in (3.5). We have a map <lb/> η <lb/> ′  : Q <lb/> 0  −→ Quot(r, d  p  ) <lb/>that sends any triple (F , U , f ) ∈ Q  0  to the point representing the quotient Q  p  (f ) in <lb/>(3.6). Let <lb/>(3.10) <lb/> η : Q <lb/> 0  −→ Quot(K <lb/>  *  , d  z  ) = Quot(r, d  p  , d  z  ) <lb/>be the map that sends any point α = (F , U , f ) ∈ Q  0  to the point of ϕ <lb/> −1  (η <lb/> ′  (α)) that <lb/>represents the quotient E(f ) <lb/>  *  /F <lb/>  *  in (3.7). This map η is injective because, as observed <lb/>earlier, the equivalence class of the pair (F , f ) can be recovered from the quotient Q  p  (f ) <lb/>of O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  and the quotient E(f ) <lb/>  *  /F <lb/>  *  of E(f ) <lb/>  *  . The image of η is clearly a Zariski open <lb/>subset of Quot(r, d  p  , d  z  ). <lb/></body>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> I. BISWAS, A. DHILLON, J. HURTUBISE, AND R. A. WENTWORTH <lb/></note>

			<body> Let <lb/>  r  K −→ <lb/>  r  p <lb/>  * <lb/> X  O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  = p <lb/>  * <lb/> X  O  X  be the r-th exterior power of the homomorphism <lb/>in (3.8). Considering it as a family of subsheaves of O  X  of degree −d  p  parametrized by <lb/>Quot(r, d  p  ), we have the corresponding classifying morphism <lb/> δ <lb/> ′ <lb/> 1  : Quot(r, d  p  ) −→ Quot(1, d  p  ) = Sym <lb/> dp  (X) . <lb/> Let <lb/>(3.11) <lb/> δ  1  := δ <lb/> ′ <lb/> 1  • ϕ : Quot(r, d  p  , d  z  ) =: Q −→ Sym <lb/> dp  (X) <lb/>be the composition, where ϕ is constructed in (3.9). Next, consider the tautological <lb/>subsheaf <lb/> S ֒→ (Id  X  × ϕ) <lb/>  *  K <lb/>  * <lb/> on X ×Q. Let <lb/>  r  S ֒→ <lb/>  r  (Id  X  ×ϕ) <lb/>  *  K <lb/>  *  be the r-th exterior power of the above inclusion. <lb/>Let <lb/>(3.12) <lb/> δ  2  : Q −→ Sym <lb/> dz  (X) <lb/>be the morphism that sends any y ∈ Q to the scheme theoretic support of the quotient <lb/>sheaf <lb/>( <lb/>  r <lb/> (Id  X  × ϕ) <lb/>  *  K <lb/>  * <lb/>|ϕ(y)  )/( <lb/>  r <lb/> S|  X×{y}  ) −→ X . <lb/> Now define the morphism <lb/>(3.13) <lb/> δ := (δ  1  , δ  2  ) : Quot(r, d  p  , d  q  ) = Q −→ Sym <lb/> dp  (X) × Sym <lb/> dz  (X) , <lb/> where δ  1  and δ  2  are constructed in (3.11) and (3.12) respectively. It can be shown that δ <lb/> is surjective. In fact, in Section 4 we will construct, and use, a section of δ. <lb/> Remark 3.1. Let M  X  (r, d  z  − d  p  ) denote the moduli stack of vector bundles on X of rank <lb/> r and degree d  z  − d  p  . Since there is a universal bundle over X × Quot(r, d  p  , d  q  ), we get a <lb/>morphism <lb/>Quot(r, d  p  , d  q  ) −→ M  X  (r, d  z  − d  p  ) . <lb/> 4. Fundamental group of Quot(r, d  p  , d  z  ) <lb/> Proposition 4.1. The homomorphism between fundamental groups induced by the mor-<lb/>phism δ in (3.13) is an isomorphism. <lb/>Proof. We will first construct a section of δ. Let <lb/> D(d  p  ) ⊂ X × Sym <lb/> dp  (X) <lb/>be the divisor consisting of all (x , {y  1  , · · · , y  dp  }) such that x ∈ {y  1  , · · · , y  dp  }. Then the <lb/>subsheaf <lb/> O  X×Sym <lb/> dp  (X)  (−D(d  p  )) ⊕ O <lb/> ⊕r−1 <lb/> X×Sym <lb/> dp  (X) <lb/> ⊂ O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X×Sym <lb/> dp  (X) <lb/> produces a classifying morphism <lb/>(4.1) <lb/> θ  1  : Sym <lb/> dp  (X) −→ Quot(r, d  p  ) . <lb/> Let ξ  1  (respectively, ξ  2  ) denote the projection of Sym <lb/> dp  (X) × Sym <lb/> dz  (X) to Sym <lb/> dp  (X) <lb/>(respectively, Sym <lb/> dz  (X)). Like before, D(d  z  ) ⊂ X × Sym <lb/> dp  (X) be the divisor consisting <lb/>of all (x , {y  1  , · · · , y  dz  }) such that x ∈ {y  1  , · · · , y  dz  }. The subsheaf <lb/>((Id  X  × ξ  1  ) <lb/>  *  (O  X×Sym <lb/> dp  (X)  (D(d  p  ))) ⊗ (Id  X  × ξ  2  ) <lb/>  *  (O  X×Sym <lb/> dz  (X)  (−D(d  z  )))) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> A GENERALIZED QUOT SCHEME AND MEROMORPHIC VORTICES <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body> ⊕(O <lb/> ⊕r−1 <lb/> X×Sym <lb/> dp  (X)Sym <lb/> dz  (X) <lb/> ) <lb/>  *  ⊂ (Id  X  × ξ  1  ) <lb/>  *  (O  X×Sym <lb/> dp  (X)  (−D(d  p  )) ⊕ O <lb/> ⊕r−1 <lb/> X×Sym <lb/> dp  (X) <lb/> ) <lb/>  * <lb/> produces a classifying morphism <lb/>(4.2) <lb/> θ : Sym <lb/> dp  (X) × Sym <lb/> dz  (X) −→ Quot(r, d  p  , d  q  ) . <lb/> We note that ϕ • θ = θ  1  , where ϕ and θ  1  are the morphisms constructed in (3.9) and <lb/>(4.1) respectively. <lb/>It is straightforward to check that <lb/>(4.3) <lb/> δ • θ = Id  Sym <lb/> dp  (X)×Sym <lb/> dz  (X)  , <lb/> where δ is constructed in (3.13). In view of this section θ, we conclude that the induced <lb/>homomorphism between fundamental groups <lb/> δ  *  : π  1  (Quot(r, d  p  , d  q  )) −→ π  1  (Sym <lb/> dp  (X) × Sym <lb/> dz  (X)) <lb/>is surjective (the base points of fundamental groups are suppressed in the notation). <lb/>Let <lb/>(4.4) <lb/> U ⊂ Sym <lb/> dp  (X) × Sym <lb/> dz  (X)) <lb/>be the Zariski open subset consisting of all <lb/>(x , y) = ({x  1  , · · · , x  dp  } , {y  1  , · · · , y  dz  }) ∈ Sym <lb/> dp  (X) × Sym <lb/> dz  (X)) <lb/>such that the d  p  + d  z  points {x  1  , · · · , x  dp  , y  1  , · · · , y  dz  } are all distinct, equivalently, the <lb/>effective divisor x + y is reduced. Let <lb/>(4.5) <lb/> θ  0  := θ|  U  : U −→ Quot(r, d  p  , d  z  ) <lb/>be the restriction of the map θ in (4.2). Also, consider the restriction <lb/>(4.6) <lb/> δ  0  := δ|  δ  −1  (U )  : δ <lb/> −1  (U) −→ U . <lb/> Every fiber of δ  0  is identified with (P <lb/> r−1 <lb/> C  ) <lb/> dp  × (P <lb/> r−1 <lb/> C  ) <lb/> dz  , where P <lb/> r−1 <lb/> C <lb/> is the projective space <lb/>parametrizing the hyperplanes in C <lb/> r  and P <lb/> r−1 <lb/> C <lb/> is the projective space parametrizing the <lb/>lines in C <lb/> r  (so P <lb/> r−1 <lb/> C <lb/> parametrizes the hyperplanes in (C <lb/> r  ) <lb/>  *  ). From the homotopy exact <lb/>sequence associated to δ  0  it follows that the induced homomorphism of fundamental groups <lb/> δ  0, *  : π  1  (δ <lb/> −1  (U)) −→ π  1  (U) <lb/>is an isomorphism. The variety Quot(r, d  p  , d  z  ) is smooth, and δ <lb/> −1  (U) is a nonempty <lb/>Zariski open subset of it. Therefore, the homomorphism <lb/> ι  *  : π  1  (δ <lb/> −1  (U)) −→ π  1  (Quot(r, d  p  , d  z  )) <lb/>induced by the inclusion ι : ϕ <lb/> −1  (U) ֒→ Quot(r, d  p  , d  z  ) is surjective. Since δ  0, *  is an <lb/>isomorphism, this implies that the homomorphism <lb/> θ  0, *  : π  1  (U) −→ π  1  (Quot(r, d  p  , d  z  )) <lb/>induced in θ  0  in (4.5) is surjective. Since θ  0  extends to θ, this immediately implies that <lb/>the homomorphism <lb/> θ  *  : π  1  (Sym <lb/> dp  (X) × Sym <lb/> dz  (X)) −→ π  1  (Quot(r, d  p  , d  z  ) <lb/>induced in θ in (4.2) is surjective. Since θ  *  is surjective, and the composition δ  *  • θ  *  is <lb/>injective (see (4.3)) we conclude that δ  *  is also injective. <lb/></body>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> I. BISWAS, A. DHILLON, J. HURTUBISE, AND R. A. WENTWORTH <lb/></note>

			<body> 5. Cohomology of Quot(r, d  p  , d  z  ) <lb/>5.1. Generalization of a theorem of Bifet. Let S  1  , S  2  , · · · , S  k  be a smooth connected <lb/>projective varieties over C. Fix some line bundles L  i  on S  i  × X of relative degree d  i  over <lb/> S  i  . In other words <lb/>deg(L  i  |  s×X  ) = d  i <lb/> for each point s ∈ S  i  . Set S = S  1  × · · · × S  k  . Let <lb/> π  S  i  ×X  : S × X −→ S  i  × X <lb/> be the natural projection. Define <lb/> L  i  := π <lb/>  * <lb/> S  i  ×X  L  i  . <lb/> Let <lb/> φ : Quot(⊕  i  <lb/> L  i  /S, d) −→ S <lb/> be the relative Quot scheme that parametrizes the torsion quotients of degree d. So <lb/>for any s = (s  1  , · · · , s  k  ) ∈ S, the fiber φ <lb/> −1  (s) parametrizes the torsion quotients of <lb/> ⊕ <lb/> k <lb/>i=1  L  i  |  s  i  ×X  of degree d. By deformation theory, φ is a smooth morphism of relative <lb/>dimension kd, so Quot(⊕  i  <lb/> L  i  /S, d) is smooth of dimension dim(S) + kd. The torus G <lb/> k <lb/>m <lb/> acts on Quot(⊕  i  <lb/> L  i  /S, d) via its action on <lb/>  k <lb/>i=1 <lb/> L  i  . <lb/>For any positive integer p, let Quot(L  i  /S  i  , p) −→ S  i  denote the relative Quot scheme <lb/>parametrizing the torsion quotients of L  i  /S  i  of degree p. So the fiber of Quot(L  i  /S  i  , p) <lb/> over any s ∈ S  i  parametrizes the torsion quotients of L  i  |  s×X  of degree p. <lb/> Proposition 5.1. There is a bijection between the partitions P = (p  1  , p  2  , · · · , p  k  ) of <lb/> d of length k and the connected components of the fixed point loci of the G <lb/> k <lb/>m  action on <lb/> Quot(⊕  i  <lb/> L  i  /S, d). The component corresponding to the partition <lb/>  k <lb/>i=1  p  i  = d is the prod-<lb/>uct of Quot schemes <lb/> Quot(L  •  /S, P) := Quot(L  1  /S  1  , p  1  ) × Quot(L  2  /S  2  , p  2  ) × . . . × Quot(L  k  /S  k  , p  k  ) <lb/> with the obvious structure morphism to S. <lb/> Proof. On applies the argument used to prove Lemme 1 in [Bif]. <lb/> As all schemes and morphisms are assumed to be projective it is possible to choose a <lb/>one parameter subgroup <lb/> G  m  ֒→ G <lb/> k <lb/>m <lb/> so that <lb/>Quot(⊕  i  <lb/> L  i  /S, d) <lb/> Gm  = Quot(⊕  i  <lb/> L  i  /S, d) <lb/> G  k <lb/>m <lb/> . <lb/> Further, the above one-parameter subgroup can be chosen to be given by an increasing <lb/>sequence of weights λ  1  &lt; λ  2  &lt; . . . &lt; λ  k  . <lb/>There is an induced action of G  m  on the tangent space at a fixed point x. The action <lb/>preserves the normal space to the fixed point locus and we wish to describe the subspace <lb/>of positive weights. <lb/>Take a partition P = (p  1  , · · · , p  k  ) of D. As before, let <lb/>Quot(L  •  /S, P) ⊂ Quot(⊕  i  <lb/> L  i  /S, d) <lb/> G  k <lb/>m <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> A GENERALIZED QUOT SCHEME AND MEROMORPHIC VORTICES <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body> be the connected component corresponding to P. For a point x ∈ Quot(L  •  /S, P), its <lb/>image in S  i  will be denoted by x  i  . The line bundle L  i  |  x  i  ×X  on X will be denoted by L <lb/> x <lb/>i  . <lb/>The point x  i  is given by the exact sequence <lb/>0 −→ L <lb/> x <lb/>i  ⊗ O  X  (−D  i  ) −→ L <lb/> x <lb/>i  −→ O  D  i  −→ 0 <lb/>where D  i  is an effective divisor on X with deg D  i  = p  i  . The relative tangent bundle for <lb/>the projection φ is <lb/> T  x  Quot(⊕  i  <lb/> L  i  /S, d)/S = <lb/> k <lb/> i,j=1 <lb/> Hom(L <lb/> x <lb/>i  ⊗ O  X  (−D  i  ) , O  D  j  ) . <lb/> On the other hand, the relative tangent space to the fixed point locus Quot(L  •  /S, P) is <lb/> T  x  Quot(L  •  /S, P)/S = <lb/> k <lb/> i=1 <lb/> Hom(L <lb/> x <lb/>i  ⊗ O  X  (−D  i  ) , O  D  i  ) . <lb/> Consequently, the normal bundle N to Quot(L  •  /S, P) ⊂ Quot(⊕  i  <lb/> L  i  /S, d) is <lb/> N  x  = <lb/> i =j <lb/> Hom(L <lb/> x <lb/>i  ⊗ O  X  (−D  i  , O  D  j  ) . <lb/> Also, the subspace of positive weights is <lb/> N <lb/> + <lb/> x  = <lb/> i&lt;j <lb/> Hom(L <lb/> x <lb/>i  ⊗ O  X  (−D  i  , O  D  j  ) <lb/>because the torus acts on Hom(L <lb/> x <lb/>i  ⊗ O  X  (−D  i  , O  D  j  ) with weight λ  j  − λ  i  . It follows that <lb/> d(P) := dim N <lb/> + <lb/> x  = <lb/> k <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (i − 1)p  i  . <lb/> Proposition 5.2. The Quot schemes for line bundles <lb/> Quot(L  i  /S  i  , p  i  ) = Quot(O/S  i  , p  i  ) = Sym <lb/> p  i  (X) × S  i  . <lb/> The Poincaré polynomial of Quot(⊕  i  <lb/> L  i  /S, d) is given by <lb/> P (Quot(⊕  i  <lb/> L  i  /S, d), t) = <lb/> P <lb/> t <lb/> 2d(P)  P (Quot(L  i  /S  i  , p  i  ), t) <lb/> = <lb/> P <lb/> t <lb/> 2d(P)  P (S  i  , t)P (Sym <lb/> p  i  (X), t) , <lb/> where the sum is over all partitions of d of length k. <lb/> Proof. The isomorphism Quot(O/S  i  , p  i  ) <lb/> ∼ <lb/> −→ Quot(L  i  /S  i  , p  i  ) is by tensoring exact se-<lb/>quences with L  i  . The second equality is via (2.1). <lb/>We need to recall the theorems of [Bia] and [Ki] in our present context. The torus action <lb/>determines two stratifications of the variety Quot(⊕  i  <lb/> L  i  /S, d). The strata are in bijection <lb/>with connected components of the fixed point locus which are in turn in bijection with <lb/>partitions of d of length k. Given such a partition P, its corresponding strata are <lb/>Quot(L  •  /S, P) <lb/> +  := {x | lim <lb/> t→0 <lb/> t.x ∈ Quot(L  •  /S, P)} <lb/></body>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> I. BISWAS, A. DHILLON, J. HURTUBISE, AND R. A. WENTWORTH <lb/></note>

			<body> and <lb/> Quot(L  •  /S, P) <lb/> −  := {x | lim <lb/> t→∞ <lb/> t.x ∈ Quot(L  •  /S, P)} . <lb/> Both of these stratifications are known to be perfect. There are affine fibrations <lb/>Quot(L  •  /S, P) <lb/> +  −→ Quot(L  •  /S, P) and Quot(L  •  /S, P) <lb/> −  −→ Quot(L  •  /S, P) <lb/> of relative dimensions dim N <lb/> + <lb/> x  and dim N <lb/> − <lb/> x  respectively, where x ∈ Quot(L  •  /S, P) is <lb/>an arbitrary closed point. It follows that the codimension of Quot(L  •  /S, P) <lb/> −  is dim N <lb/> + <lb/> x <lb/> which gives the above formula for the Poincare polynomial. <lb/> 5.2. The cohomology of Quot(r, d  p  , d  z  ). In this subsection we describe the Poincaré <lb/>polynomial of Quot(r, d  p  , d  z  ). Consider the morphism ϕ in (3.9). There is a natural <lb/>action of the torus G <lb/> r <lb/>m  on the target Quot(O <lb/> r  , d  p  ) = Q(r, d  p  ). This action clearly lifts to <lb/>the domain Quot(r, d  p  , d  z  ) for ϕ. <lb/> The previous subsection provides us with a decomposition and an induced formula for <lb/>the Poincaré polynomial of Quot(r, d  p  , d  z  ). Let us recall it quickly in the present context. <lb/>There is a bijection between connected components of fixed point locus and partitions of <lb/> d  p  of length r. Given a partition P = (p  1  , p  2  , · · · , p  r  ), the corresponding component of <lb/>Quot(O <lb/> r  , d  p  ) <lb/> Gm  is <lb/>Quot(O, p  1  ) × · · · × Quot(O, p  r  ) = Sym <lb/> p  1  (X) × · · · × Sym <lb/> pr  (X) <lb/>= Sym <lb/> P  X. <lb/> There are universal divisors D <lb/> univ <lb/> p  i <lb/> inside Sym <lb/> p  i  (X)×X. The component of Quot(r, d  p  , d  z  ) <lb/> G  r <lb/>m <lb/> corresponding to P, that is <lb/> φ <lb/> −1  (Sym <lb/> p  1  (X) × Sym <lb/> p  2  (X) × · · · × Sym <lb/> pr  (X)) <lb/>is then identified with Quot(⊕  i  O  Sym  p i  (X)×X  (D <lb/> univ <lb/> p  i <lb/> )/ Sym <lb/> p  i  (X), d  z  ). As the morphism ϕ <lb/> in (3.9) is smooth, and smooth morphisms preserve codimension, we obtain the following <lb/>formula for the Poincaré polynomial: <lb/>(5.1) P (Quot(r, d  p  , d  z  ), t) = <lb/> P <lb/> t <lb/> 2d(P)  P (Quot(⊕  i  O  Sym <lb/> p i  (X)×X  (D <lb/> univ <lb/> p  i <lb/> )/ Sym <lb/> p  i  (X), d  z  ), t). <lb/> To complete the calculation we need to compute the Poincaré polynomials of <lb/>Quot(⊕  i  O  Sym  p i  (X)×X  (D <lb/> univ <lb/> p  i <lb/> )/ Sym <lb/> P  (X), d  z  ) . <lb/> Once again Proposition 5.2 applies. The connected components of the fixed point loci <lb/>are in bijection with partitions of d  z  of length r. Given a partition Q = (q  1  , · · · , q  r  ), the <lb/>corresponding connected component is <lb/>Quot(O  Sym  p 1  (X)×X  (−D  p  1  )/ Sym <lb/> p  1  (X), q  1  )×· · ·×Quot(O  Sym  pr  (X)×X  (−D  pr  )/ Sym <lb/> pr  (X), q  r  ) <lb/>which is canonically isomorphic to <lb/>Sym <lb/> P,Q  X := Sym <lb/> p  1  (X) × · · · × Sym <lb/> pr  (X) × Sym <lb/> q  1  (X) × · · · × Sym <lb/> qr  (X) . <lb/> We obtain the following formula: <lb/> P (Quot(⊕  i  OSym <lb/> p  i  (X) × X(D <lb/> univ <lb/> p  i <lb/> )/ Sym <lb/> P  (X), d  z  )) = <lb/> Q <lb/> t <lb/> 2d(Q)  P (Sym <lb/> P,Q  (X), t) . <lb/> Putting this all together we obtain the following: <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> A GENERALIZED QUOT SCHEME AND MEROMORPHIC VORTICES <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body> Theorem 5.3. The Poincaré polynomial for Quot(r, d  p  , d  z  ) is <lb/> P (Quot(r, d  p  , d  z  ), t) = <lb/> P <lb/> Q <lb/> t <lb/> 2[d(P)+d(Q)]  P (Sym <lb/> P  (X), t)P (Sym <lb/> Q  (X), t) , <lb/> where P varies over all partitions of d  p  of length r and Q varies over all partitions of d  z <lb/> of length r. <lb/> Poincaré polynomial of Sym <lb/> n  (X) is the coefficient of t <lb/> n  in <lb/>(1 + tx) <lb/> 2g  X <lb/> (1 − t)(1 − tx  2  ) <lb/> , <lb/> where g  X  is the genus of X [Ma, p. 322, (4.3)]. Using this and Theorem 5.3 we get an <lb/>explicit expression for P (Quot(r, d  p  , d  z  ), t). <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgements <lb/> We thank the National University of Singapore for its hospitality. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [Ba] <lb/> J.M. Baptista, On the L <lb/> 2  -metric of vortex moduli spaces, Nucl. Phys. B 844 (2011), 308–333. <lb/>[BDW] <lb/>A. Bertram, G. Daskalopoulos and R. Wentworth, Gromov invariants for holomorphic maps <lb/>from Riemann surfaces to Grassmannians, Jour. Amer. Math. Soc. 9 (1996) 529–571. <lb/>[Bia] <lb/>A. Bia lynicki-Birula, Some theorems on actions of algebraic groups, Ann. of Math. 98 (1973), <lb/>480–497. <lb/>[Bif] <lb/>E. Bifet, Sur les points fixes schéma Quot  OX /X,k  sous l&apos;action du tore G <lb/> r <lb/>m,k  , Com. Ren. Math. <lb/>Acad. Sci. Paris 309 (1989), 609–612. <lb/>[BR] <lb/>I. Biswas and N. M. Romão, Moduli of vortices and Grassmann manifolds, Comm. Math. Phy. <lb/> 320 (2013), 1–20. <lb/>[Br] <lb/>S. Bradlow, Vortices in holomorphic line bundles over closed Kähler manifolds, Commun. <lb/>Math. Phys. 135 (1990), 1–17. <lb/>[EINOS] M. Eto, Y. Isozumi, M. Nitta, K. Ohashi and N. Sakai, Solitons in the Higgs phase: the moduli <lb/>matrix approach, J. Phys. A: Math. Gen. 39 (2006), 315–392. <lb/>[Gr] <lb/>A. Grothendieck, Techniques de construction et théoèmes d&apos;existence en géométrie algébrique. <lb/>IV. Les schémas de Hilbert, Séminaire Bourbaki, Vol. 6, Exp. No. 221, 249–276. <lb/>[Ki] <lb/>F. Kirwan, Intersection homology and torus actions, Jour. Amer. Math. Soc. 1 (1988), 385– <lb/>400. <lb/>[Ma] <lb/>I. G. Macdonald, Symmetric products of an algebraic curve, Topology 1 (1962), 319–343. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> I. BISWAS, A. DHILLON, J. HURTUBISE, AND R. A. WENTWORTH <lb/></note>

			<front> School of Mathematics, Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Homi Bhabha Road, <lb/>Bombay 400005, India <lb/> E-mail address: indranil@math.tifr.res.in <lb/> Department of Mathematics, Middlesex College, University of Western Ontario, Lon-<lb/>don, ON N6A 5B7, Canada <lb/> E-mail address: adhill3@uwo.ca <lb/> Department of Mathematics, McGill University, Burnside Hall, 805 Sherbrooke St. <lb/>W., Montreal, Que. H3A 0B9, Canada <lb/> E-mail address: jacques.hurtubise@mcgill.ca <lb/> Department of Mathematics, University of Maryland, College Park, MD 20742, USA <lb/> E-mail address: raw@umd.edu </front>


	</text>
</tei>
