<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> THE SPECTRAL CURVE OF THE EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION VIA <lb/>THE LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/> OLIVIA DUMITRESCU, MOTOHICO MULASE, BRAD SAFNUK, AND ADAM SORKIN <lb/> Abstract. The Eynard-Orantin recursion formula provides an effective tool for certain enumer-<lb/>ation problems in geometry. The formula requires a spectral curve and the recursion kernel. We <lb/>present a uniform construction of the spectral curve and the recursion kernel from the unstable <lb/>geometries of the original counting problem. We examine this construction using four concrete ex-<lb/>amples: Grothendieck&apos;s dessins d&apos;enfants (or higher-genus analogue of the Catalan numbers), the <lb/>intersection numbers of tautological cotangent classes on the moduli stack of stable pointed curves, <lb/>single Hurwitz numbers, and the stationary Gromov-Witten invariants of the complex projective <lb/>line. <lb/></front>

			<body> Contents <lb/> 1. Introduction <lb/>1 <lb/>2. The Eynard-Orantin differential forms and the topological recursion <lb/>6 <lb/>3. Counting Grothendieck&apos;s dessins d&apos;enfants <lb/>7 <lb/>4. The Laplace transform of the number of dessins and ribbon graphs <lb/>13 <lb/>5. The ψ-class interaction numbers on M  g,n <lb/> 20 <lb/>6. Single Hurwitz numbers <lb/>24 <lb/>7. The stationary Gromov-Witten invariants of P  1 <lb/> 33 <lb/>Appendix A. Calculation of the Laplace transform <lb/>43 <lb/>References <lb/>46 <lb/>1. Introduction <lb/> What is the mirror dual object of the Catalan numbers? We wish to make sense of <lb/>this question in the present paper. Since the homological mirror symmetry is a categorial <lb/>equivalence, it does not require the existence of underlying spaces to which the categories <lb/>are associated. By identifying the Catalan numbers with a counting problem similar to <lb/>Gromov-Witten theory, we come up with an equation <lb/> (1.1) <lb/> x = z + <lb/>1 <lb/> z <lb/> as their mirror dual. It is not a coincidence that (1.1) is the Landau-Ginzburg model in one <lb/>variable [2, 40]. Once the mirror dual object is identified, we can calculate the higher-genus <lb/>analogue of the Catalan numbers using the Eynard-Orantin topological recursion formula. <lb/> This recursion therefore provides a mechanism of calculating the higher-order quantum <lb/>corrections term by term. <lb/>The purpose of this paper is to present a systematic construction of genus 0 spectral curves <lb/>of the Eynard-Orantin recursion formula [25, 27]. Suppose we have a symplectic space X <lb/> on the A-model side. If the Gromov-Witten theory of X is controlled by an integrable <lb/></body>

			<front> 2000 Mathematics Subject Classification. Primary: 14H15, 14N35, 05C30, 11P21; Secondary: 81T30. <lb/> 1 <lb/> arXiv:1202.1159v1  [math.AG] 6 Feb 2012 <lb/></front>

			<page> 2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> system, then the homological mirror dual of X is expected to be a family of spectral curves <lb/> Σ. Let us consider the descendant Gromov-Witten invariants of X as a function in integer <lb/>variables. The Laplace transform of these functions are symmetric meromorphic functions <lb/>defined on the products of Σ. We expect that they satisfy the Eynard-Orantin topological <lb/>recursion on the B-model side defined on the curve Σ. <lb/>More specifically, we construct the spectral curve using the Laplace transform of the <lb/>descendant Gromov-Witten type invariants for the unstable geometries (g, n) = (0, 1) and <lb/>(0, 2). We give four concrete examples in this paper: <lb/> • The number of dessins d&apos;enfants of Grothendieck, which can be thought of as higher-<lb/>genus analogue of the Catalan numbers. <lb/> • The ψ-class intersection numbers τ  d  1  · · · τ  dn   g,n  on the moduli space M  g,n  of pointed <lb/>stable curves [10, 15, 25, 46, 78]. <lb/> • Single Hurwitz numbers [7, 24, 56]. <lb/> • The stationary Gromov-Witten invariants of P  1  [62, 66]. <lb/>The spectral curves we construct are listed in Table 1. The Eynard-Orantin recursion <lb/>formula for the single Hurwitz numbers [4, 7, 24, 57] and the ψ-class intersection numbers <lb/>[25] are known. Norbury and Scott conjecture that the stationary Gromov-Witten invariants <lb/>of P  1  also satisfy the Eynard-Orantin recursion [62]. A similar statement for the number of <lb/>dessins d&apos;enfants does not seem to be known. We give a full proof of this fact in this paper. <lb/>Grothendieck&apos;s Dessins <lb/> x = z + <lb/> 1 <lb/> z <lb/> y = −z <lb/>τ  d  1  · · · τ  dn   g,n <lb/> x = z  2 <lb/> y = −z <lb/> Single Hurwitz Numbers <lb/> x = ze  1−z <lb/> y = e  z−1 <lb/> Stationary GW Invariants of P  1 <lb/> x = z + <lb/> 1 <lb/> z <lb/> y = − log(1 + z  2  ) <lb/> Table 1. Examples of spectral curves. <lb/> Let D  g,n  (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  ) denote the weighted count of clean Belyi morphisms of smooth <lb/>connected algebraic curves of genus g with n poles of order (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  ). We first prove <lb/> Theorem 1.1. For 2g −2+n ≥ 0 and n ≥ 1, the number of clean Belyi morphisms satisfies <lb/>the following equation: <lb/> (1.2) µ  1  D  g,n  (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  ) = <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> (µ  1  + µ  j  − 2)D  g,n−1  (µ  1  + µ  j  − 2, µ  [n]\{1,j}  ) <lb/>+ <lb/> α+β=µ  1  −2 <lb/> αβ <lb/> D  g−1,n+1  (α, β, µ  [n]\{1}  ) + <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> IJ={2,...,n} <lb/> D  g  1  ,|I|+1  (α, µ  I  )D  g  2  ,|J|+1  (β, µ  J  ) <lb/> , <lb/> where µ  I  = (µ  i  )  i∈I  for a subset I ⊂ [n] = {1, 2, . . . , n}. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body> The simplest case <lb/> D  0,1  (2m) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2m <lb/> C  m <lb/> is given by the Catalan number C  m  = <lb/> 1 <lb/> m+1 <lb/>  2m <lb/> m <lb/> . The next case D  0,2  (µ  1  , µ  2  ) is calculated in <lb/>[44, 45]. Note that the (g, n)-terms appears also on the right-hand side of (1.2). Therefore, <lb/>this is merely an equation, not an effective recursion formula. <lb/>Define the Eynard-Orantin differential form by <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) = d  1  · · · d  n <lb/> µ  1  ,...,µn&gt;0 <lb/> D  g,n  (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  )e <lb/> −(µ  1  w  1  +···+µnwn)  , <lb/> where the w  j  -coordinates and t  j  -coordinates are related by <lb/> e <lb/> w  j  = <lb/> t  j  + 1 <lb/> t  j  − 1 <lb/>+ <lb/> t  j  − 1 <lb/> t  j  + 1 <lb/> . <lb/> Then <lb/> Theorem 1.2. The Eynard-Orantin differential forms for 2g−2+n &gt; 0 satisfy the following <lb/>topological recursion formula <lb/> (1.3) W <lb/> D <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/>= − <lb/> 1 <lb/>64 <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ <lb/> 1 <lb/> t + t  1 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> t − t  1 <lb/> (t  2  − 1)  3 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> · <lb/> 1 <lb/> dt <lb/> · dt  1 <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/>g−1,n+1  (t, −t, t  2  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/>+ <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/> 0,2  (t, t  j  )W  g,n−1  (−t, t  2  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) + W <lb/> D <lb/> 0,2  (−t, t  j  )W  g,n−1  (t, t  2  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/> + <lb/> stable <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> IJ={2,3,...,n} <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/>g  1  ,|I|+1  (t, t  I  )W <lb/> D <lb/>g  2  ,|J|+1  (−t, t  J  ) <lb/> . <lb/> This is now a recursion formula, since the topological type (g   , n   ) of the Belyi morphisms <lb/>appearing on the right-hand side satisfies <lb/>2g <lb/>  − 2 + n <lb/>  = (2g − 2 + n) − 1, <lb/>counting the contributions from the disjoint union of the domain curves additively. A <lb/>corollary to the recursion formula is a combinatorial identity between the number of clean <lb/>Belyi morphisms and the number of lattice points on the moduli space M  g,n  that has been <lb/>studied in [10, 55, 59, 60, 61]. <lb/> Corollary 1.3. <lb/> (1.4) D  g,n  (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  ) = <lb/>  1  &gt; <lb/> µ 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> · · · <lb/> n&gt; <lb/> µn <lb/> 2 <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> 2  i  − µ  i <lb/> µ  i <lb/> µ  i <lb/>  i <lb/> N  g,n  (2  1  − µ  i  , · · · , 2  n  − µ  n  ), <lb/> where N  g,n  (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  ) is defined by (4.18). <lb/> The recursion formula (1.3) is a typical example of the Eynard-Orantin recursion we <lb/>discuss in this paper. We establish this theorem by taking the Laplace transform of (1.2). <lb/>This is indeed a general theme. For every known case of the Eynard-Orantin recursion, <lb/>we establish its proof by taking the Laplace transform of the counting formula like (1.2). <lb/>For example, for the cases of single Hurwitz numbers [24, 57] and open Gromov-Witten <lb/></body>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> invariants of C  3  [81, 82], the counting formulas similar to (1.2) are called the cut-and-join <lb/> equations [29, 77, 49, 79, 80]. <lb/>The Laplace transform plays a mysterious role in Gromov-Witten theory. We notice its <lb/>appearance in Kontsevich&apos;s work [46] that relates the Euclidean volume of M  g,n  and the <lb/>intersection numbers on M  g,n  , and also in the work of Okounkov-Pandharipande [65] that <lb/>relates the single Hurwitz numbers and the enumeration of topological graphs. It has been <lb/>proved that in these two cases the Laplace transform of the quantities in question satisfies <lb/>the Eynard-Orantin recursion [10, 24, 26, 55, 57] for a particular choice of the spectral curve. <lb/> Then what is the role of the Laplace transform here? The answer we propose in this <lb/>paper is that the Laplace transform defines the spectral curve. Since the spectral curve is a <lb/>B-model object, the Laplace transform plays the role of mirror symmetry. <lb/> The Eynard-Orantin recursion formula is an effective tool in certain geometric enumer-<lb/>ation. The formula is originated in random matrix theory as a machinery to compute the <lb/>expectation value of a product of the resolvent of random matrices ([1], [21]). In [25, 27] Ey-<lb/>nard and Orantin propose a novel point of view, considering the recursion as a mechanism <lb/>of defining meromorphic symmetric differential forms W  g,n  on the product Σ  n  of a Riemann <lb/>surface Σ for every g ≥ 0 and n &gt; 0. They derive in [25, 27] many beautiful properties that <lb/>these quantities satisfy, including modularity and relations to integrable systems. <lb/>The effectiveness of the topological recursion in string theory is immediately noticed <lb/>[14, 23, 51, 70]. A remarkable discovery, connecting the recursion formula and geometry, is <lb/>made by Mariño [51] and Bouchard, Klemm, Mariño and Pasquetti [6]. It is formulated as <lb/>the Remodeling Conjecture. This conjecture covers many aspects of both closed and open <lb/>Gromov-Witten invariants of arbitrary toric Calabi-Yau threefolds. One of their statements <lb/>says the following. Let X be an arbitrary toric Calabi-Yau threefold, and Σ its mirror curve. <lb/>Apply the Eynard-Orantin recursion formula to Σ. Then W  g,n  calculates the open Gromov-<lb/>Witten invariants of X. The validity of the topological recursion of [25, 27] is not limited to <lb/>Gromov-Witten invariants. It has been applied to the HOMFLY polynomials of torus knots <lb/>[9], and understanding the role of quantum Riemann surfaces and certain Seiberg-Witten <lb/>invariants [35]. A speculation also suggests its relation to colored Jones polynomials and <lb/>the hyperbolic volume conjecture of knot complements [13]. <lb/>From the very beginning, effectiveness of the Eynard-Orantin recursion in enumerative <lb/>geometry was suggested by physicists. Bouchard and Mariño conjecture in [7] that particu-<lb/>lar generating functions of single Hurwitz numbers satisfy the Eynard-Orantin topological <lb/>recursion. They have come up to this conjecture as the limiting case of the remodeling con-<lb/>jecture for C  3  when the framing parameter tends to ∞. The spectral curve for this scenario <lb/>is the Lambert curve x = ye  −y  . The Bouchard-Mariño conjecture is solved in [4, 24, 57]. <lb/>The work [24] also influenced the solutions to the remodeling conjecture for C  3  itself. The <lb/>statement on the open Gromov-Witten invariants was proved in [11, 81, 82], and the closed <lb/>case was proved in [5, 83]. <lb/>The Eynard-Orantin topological recursion starts with a spectral curve Σ. Thus it is <lb/>reasonable to propose the recursion formalism whenever there is a natural curve in the <lb/>problem we study. Such curves may include the mirror curve of a toric Calabi-Yau threefold <lb/>[6, 51], the zero locus of an A-polynomial [13, 35], the Seiberg-Witten curves [35], the torus <lb/>on which a knot is drawn [9], and the character variety of the fundamental group of a knot <lb/>complement relative to SL(2, C) [13]. Now we ask the opposite question. <lb/> Question 1.4. If an enumerative geometry problem is given, then how do we find the <lb/>spectral curve, with which the Eynard-Orantin formalism may provide a solution? <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body> In every work of [5, 10, 11, 24, 25, 26, 27, 55, 57, 60, 62, 81, 82], the spectral curve is <lb/>considered to be given. How do we know that the particular choice of the spectral curve <lb/>is correct? Our proposal provides an answer to this question: the Laplace transform of <lb/>the unstable geometries (g, n) = (0, 1) and (0, 2) determines the spectral curve, and the <lb/>topological recursion formula itself. The key ingredients of the topological recursion are the <lb/>spectral curve and the recursion kernel that is determined by the differential forms W  0,1 <lb/> and W  0,2  . In the literature starting from [25], the word &quot; Bergman kernel &quot; is used for the <lb/>differential form W  0,2  . But it has indeed nothing to do with the classical Bergman kernel <lb/> in complex analysis. It is also treated as the universally given 2-form depending only on <lb/>the geometry of the spectral curve. We would rather emphasize in this paper that this <lb/> &quot; kernel &quot; is the Laplace transform of the annulus amplitude, which should be determined <lb/>by the counting problem we start with. <lb/>Although it is still vague, our proposal is the following <lb/> Conjecture 1.5 (The Laplace transform conjecture). If the unstable geometries (g, n) = <lb/>(0, 1) and (0, 2) make sense in a counting problem on the A-model side, then the Laplace <lb/>transform of the solution to these cases determines the spectral curve and the recursion <lb/>kernel of the Eynard-Orantin formalism, which is a B-model theory. Thus the Laplace <lb/>transform plays a role of mirror symmetry. The recursion then determines the solution to <lb/>the original counting problem for all (g, n). <lb/> The Eynard-Orantin recursion is a process of quantization [9, 35]. Thus the implication of <lb/>the conjecture is that quantum invariants are uniquely determined by the disk and annulus <lb/>amplitudes. For example, single Hurwitz numbers h  g,µ  are all determined by the first two <lb/>cases h  0,(µ  1  )  and h  0,(µ  1  ,µ  2  )  . The present paper and our previous work [24, 57] establish this <lb/>fact. The Lambert curve is the mirror dual of the number of trees. <lb/>The organization of this paper is the following. In Section 2 we present the Eynard-<lb/>Orantin recursion formalism for the case of genus 0 spectral curve. Higher genus situ-<lb/>ations will be discussed elsewhere. Sections 3 and 4 deal with the counting problem of <lb/>Grothendieck&apos;s dessins d&apos;enfants. We present our new results on this problem, which are <lb/>Theorem 1.1 and Theorem 1.2. We are inspired by Kodama&apos;s beautiful talk [44] (that is <lb/>based on [45]) to come up with the generating function of the Catalan numbers as the spec-<lb/>tral curve for this problem. We are grateful to G. Gliner for drawing our attention to [44]. <lb/>The counting problem of the lattice points on M  g,n  of [10, 55, 59, 60] is closely related to <lb/>the counting of dessins, which is also treated in Section 4. The Eynard-Orantin recursion <lb/>becomes identical to the Virasoro constraint condition for the ψ-class intersection numbers <lb/>on M  g,n  . We discuss this relation in Section 5, using Kontsevich&apos;s idea that the intersection <lb/>numbers on M  g,n  are essentially the same as Euclidean volume of M  g,n  . Section 6 is de-<lb/>voted to single Hurwitz numbers. In our earlier work [24, 57] we used the Lambert curve as <lb/>given. Here we reexamine the Hurwitz counting problem and derive the Lambert curve from <lb/>the unstable geometries. We then consider the Norbury-Scott conjecture [62] in Section 7, <lb/>which states that the generating functions of stationary Gromov-Witten invariants of P  1 <lb/> satisfy the Eynard-Orantin recursion. We are unable to prove this conjecture. What we <lb/>establish in this section is why the spectral curve of [62] is the right choice for this problem. <lb/>The subject of this paper is closely related to random matrix theory. Since the matrix <lb/>model side of the story has been extensively discussed by the original authors [27], we do <lb/>not deal with that aspect in the current paper. <lb/></body>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> 2. The Eynard-Orantin differential forms and the topological recursion <lb/> We use the following mathematical definition for the topological recursion of Eynard-<lb/>Orantin for a genus 0 spectral curve. The differences between our definition and the original <lb/>formulation found in [25, 27] are of the philosophical nature. Indeed, the original formula <lb/>and ours produce the exact same answer in all examples we examine in this paper. <lb/> Definition 2.1. We start with P  1  with a preferred coordinate t. Let S ⊂ P  1  be a finite <lb/>collection of points and compact real curves such that the complement Σ = P  1  \ S is <lb/>connected. The spectral curve of genus 0 is the data (Σ, π) consisting of a Riemann surface <lb/>Σ and a simply ramified holomorphic map <lb/>(2.1) <lb/> π : Σ  t −→ π(t) = x ∈ P <lb/> 1 <lb/> so that its differential dx has only simple zeros. Let us denote by R = {p  1  , . . . , p  r  } ⊂ Σ the <lb/>ramification points, and by <lb/> U = <lb/> r <lb/>j=1  U  j <lb/> the disjoint union of small neighborhood U  j  around each p  j  such that π : U  j  → π(U  j  ) ⊂ P  1 <lb/> is a double-sheeted covering ramified only at p  j  . We denote by ¯ <lb/> t = s(t) the local Galois <lb/>conjugate of t ∈ U  j  . The canonical sheaf of Σ is denoted by K. Because of our choice <lb/>of the preferred coordinate t, we have a preferred basis dt for K and ∂/∂t for K  −1  . The <lb/>meromorphic differential forms W  g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ), g = 0, 1, 2, . . . , n = 1, 2, 3, . . . , are said <lb/>to satisfy the Eynard-Orantin topological recursion if the following conditions are <lb/>satisfied: <lb/>(1) W  0,1  (t) ∈ H  0  (Σ, K). <lb/> (2) W  0,2  (t  1  , t  2  ) = <lb/> dt  1  ·dt  2 <lb/> (t  1  −t  2  )  2  − π  *  dx  1  ·dx  2 <lb/> (x  1  −x  2  )  2  ∈ H  0  (Σ × Σ, K  ⊗2  (2∆)), where ∆ is the diagonal <lb/>of Σ × Σ. <lb/>(3) The recursion kernel K  j  (t, t  1  ) ∈ H  0  (U  j  × C, (K <lb/> −1 <lb/> U  j <lb/> ⊗ K)(∆)) for t ∈ U  j  and t  1  ∈ C is <lb/>defined by <lb/>(2.2) <lb/> K  j  (t, t  1  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>  ¯ <lb/> t <lb/>t  W  0,2  (·, t  1  ) <lb/> W  0,1  ( ¯ <lb/> t) − W  0,1  (t) <lb/> . <lb/> The kernel is an algebraic operator that multiplies dt  1  while contracts dt. <lb/> (4) The general differential forms W  g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) ∈ H  0  (Σ  n  , K( * R)  ⊗n  ) are meromorphic <lb/>symmetric differential forms with poles only at the ramification points R for 2g − <lb/> 2 + n &gt; 0, and are given by the recursion formula <lb/>(2.3) W  g,n  (t  1  , t  2  , . . . , t  n  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> r <lb/> j=1 <lb/> U  j <lb/> K  j  (t, t  1  ) <lb/> W  g−1,n+1  (t, ¯ <lb/> t, t  2  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/>+ <lb/> No (0, 1) terns <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> IJ={2,3,...,n} <lb/> W  g  1  ,|I|+1  (t, t  I  )W  g  2  ,|J|+1  ( ¯ <lb/> t, t  J  ) <lb/> . <lb/> Here the integration is taken with respect to t ∈ U  j  along a positively oriented simple <lb/>closed loop around p  j  , and t  I  = (t  i  )  i∈I  for a subset I ⊂ {1, 2, . . . , n}. <lb/> (5) The differential form W  1,1  (t  1  ) requires a separate treatment because W  0,2  (t  1  , t  2  ) is <lb/>regular at the ramification points but has poles elsewhere. <lb/>(2.4) <lb/> W  1,1  (t  1  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> r <lb/> j=1 <lb/> U  j <lb/> K  j  (t, t  1  ) <lb/> W  0,2  (u, v) + π <lb/>  *  dx(u) · dx(v) <lb/> (x(u) − x(v))  2 <lb/> u=t <lb/>v= ¯ <lb/> t <lb/> . <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body> Let y : Σ−→C be a holomorphic function defined by the equation <lb/>(2.5) <lb/> W  0,1  (t) = y(t)dx(t). <lb/> Equivalently, we can define the function by contraction y = i  X  W  0,1  , where X is the <lb/>vector field on Σ dual to dx(t) with respect to the coordinate t. Then we have an <lb/>embedding <lb/>Σ  t −→ (x(t), y(t)) ∈ C <lb/> 2  . <lb/> Remark 2.2. The recursion (2.3) also applies to (g, n) = (0, 3), which gives W  0,3  in terms <lb/>of W  0,2  . In [25, Theorem 4.1] an equivalent but often more useful formula for W  0,3  is given: <lb/>(2.6) <lb/> W  0,3  (t  1  , t  2  , t  3  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> r <lb/> j=1 <lb/> U  j <lb/> W  0,2  (t, t  1  )W  0,2  (t, t  2  )W  0,2  (t, t  3  ) <lb/> dx(t) · dy(t) <lb/>. <lb/> 3. Counting Grothendieck&apos;s dessins d&apos;enfants <lb/> The A-model side of the problem we consider in this section is the counting problem of <lb/>Grothendieck&apos;s dessins d&apos;enfants (see for example, [71, 72]) for a fixed topological type of <lb/>Belyi morphisms [3]. Gromov-Witten theory of an algebraic variety X is an intersection <lb/>theory of naturally defined divisors on the moduli stack M  g,n  (X) of stable morphisms from <lb/> n-pointed algebraic curves of genus g to the target variety X. Since we are considering <lb/>tautological divisors, their 0-dimensional intersection points are also natural. These points <lb/>determine a finite set on M  g,n  via the stabilization morphism. If we expect that the <lb/>Gromov-Witten theory of X satisfies the Eynard-Orantin recursion, then we should also <lb/>expect that the counting problem of naturally defined finite sets of points on M  g,n  may <lb/>satisfy the Eynard-Orantin recursion. <lb/>Pointed curves defined over Q form a dense subset of M  g,n  . To specify n, we need to <lb/>use Belyi morphisms. When we identify a curve over Q with a Belyi morphism, a natural <lb/>counting problem arises by considering the profile of the Balyi morphism at the branched <lb/>points. In this way we arrive at canonically defined finite sets of points on M  g,n  . <lb/>More specifically, consider a Belyi morphism <lb/>(3.1) <lb/> b : C−→P <lb/> 1 <lb/> of a smooth algebraic curve C of genus g. This means b is branched only over 0, 1, ∞ ∈ <lb/> P  1  . By Belyi&apos;s Theorem [3], C is defined over Q. Let q  1  , . . . , q  n  be poles of b of orders <lb/>(µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  ) ∈ Z  n <lb/> +  . This vector of positive integers is the profile of b at ∞. In our enumera-<lb/>tion we label all poles of b. Therefore, an automorphism of a Balyi morphism preserves the <lb/>set of poles point-wise. <lb/>A clean Belyi morphism is a special class of Belyi morphism of even degree that has profile <lb/>(2, 2, . . . , 2) over the branch point 1 ∈ P  1  . We note that a complex algebraic curve is defined <lb/>over Q if and only if it admits a clean Belyi morphism. Let us denote by D  g,n  (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  ) <lb/>the number of genus g clean Belyi morphisms of profile (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  ) at ∞ ∈ P  1  . This is the <lb/>number we study in this section. <lb/>We first derive a recursion equation among D  g,n  (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  ) for all (g, n). This relation <lb/>does not provide an effective recursion formula, because D  g,n  (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  ) appears in the <lb/>equation in a complicated manner. We then compute the Laplace transform <lb/> F <lb/> D <lb/>g,n  (w  1  , . . . , w  n  ) = <lb/> µ  1  ,...,µn&gt;0 <lb/> D  g,n  (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  ) e <lb/> −(µ  1  w  1  +···+µnwn)  , <lb/></body>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> and rewrite the recursion equation in terms of the Laplace transformed functions. We then <lb/>show that the symmetric differential forms <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/> g,n  = d  1  · · · d  n  F <lb/> D <lb/>g,n <lb/> satisfy the Eynard-Orantin recursion formula. This time it is an effective recursion formula <lb/>for the generating functions W  D <lb/>g,n  of the number D  g,n  (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  ) of clean Belyi morphisms. <lb/>Grothendieck visualized the clean Belyi morphism by considering the inverse image <lb/>(3.2) <lb/>Γ = b <lb/> −1  ([0, 1]) <lb/>of the closed interval [0, 1] ⊂ P  1  by b (see his &quot; Esquisse d&apos;un programme &quot; reprinted in [72]). <lb/>This is what we call dessin d&apos;enfant. It is a topological graph drawn on the algebraic curve <lb/> C being considered as a Riemann surface. We call each pre-image of 0 ∈ P  1  by b a vertex <lb/> of Γ. Since b has profile (2, . . . , 2) over 1 ∈ P  1  , a pre-image of 1 is the midpoint of an edge <lb/> of Γ. The complement C \ Γ of Γ in C is the disjoint union of n disks centered at each q  i  . <lb/>By abuse of terminology we call each disk a face of Γ. Then by Euler&apos;s formula we have <lb/>2 − 2g = |b <lb/> −1  (0)| − |b <lb/> −1  (1)| + n. <lb/> A dessin is a special kind of metric ribbon graph. A ribbon graph of topological type (g, n) <lb/> is the 1-skeleton of a cell-decomposition of a closed oriented topological surface C of genus g <lb/> that decomposes the surface into a disjoint union of 0-cells, 1-cells, and 2-cells. The number <lb/>of 2-cells is n. Alternatively, a ribbon graph can be defined as a graph with a cyclic order <lb/>assigned to the incident half-edges at each vertex. When a positive real number, the length, <lb/>is assigned to each edge of a ribbon graph, we call it a metric ribbon graph. A dessin is <lb/>thus a metric ribbon graph with the same length given to each edge. We usually consider <lb/>this length to be 1, so the distance between 0 and 1 on P  1  is measured as <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  . <lb/>The concrete construction of [54] gives a Belyi morphism to any given dessin. Thus the <lb/>enumeration of clean Belyi morphism is equivalent to the enumeration of ribbon graphs, <lb/>where we assign length 1 to every edge. The original interest of dessins lies in the fact that <lb/>the absolute Galois group Gal(Q/Q) acts faithfully on the set of dessins. <lb/>An alternative description of a Belyi morphism is to use the dual graph <lb/>(3.3) <lb/>ˇ <lb/>Γ = b <lb/> −1  ([1, i∞]), <lb/> where <lb/>[1, i∞] = {1 + iy | 0 ≤ y ≤ ∞} ⊂ P <lb/> 1 <lb/> is the vertical half-line on P  1  with real part 1. This time the graph <lb/> has n labeled vertices <lb/>of degrees (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  ). Since we consider ribbon graphs in the context of canonical cell-<lb/>decomposition of the moduli space M  g,n  , we use the terminology dessin for a graph <lb/> dual <lb/>to a ribbon graph Γ. This distinction is important, because when we count the number of <lb/>ribbon graphs, we consider the automorphism of a graph that preserves each face, while <lb/>the automorphism group of the dual graph, i.e., a dessin, preserves each vertex point-wise, <lb/>but can permute faces. In this dual picture, we define the number of dessins with the <lb/>automorphism factor by <lb/>(3.4) <lb/> D  g,n  (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  ) = <lb/> ˇ <lb/>Γ dessin of <lb/>type (g,n) <lb/> 1 <lb/> |Aut  D  ( ˇ <lb/>Γ)| <lb/> , <lb/> wherě <lb/>Γ is a dessin of genus g with n labeled vertices with prescribed degrees (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  ), <lb/>and Aut  D  ( ˇ <lb/>Γ) is the automorphism of <lb/> preserving each vertex point-wise. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body> Our theme is to find the spectral curve of the theory by looking at the problem for <lb/>unstable curves (g, n) = (0, 1) and (0, 2). The dessins counted in D  0,1  (µ) for an integer <lb/> µ ∈ Z  +  are spherical graphs that contain only one vertex of degree µ. Since any edge of <lb/>this graph has to start and end with the same vertex, it is a loop, and thus µ is even. So let <lb/>us put µ = 2m. Each graph contributes with the weight 1/|Aut  D  ( ˇ <lb/>Γ)| in the enumeration of <lb/>the number D  0,1  (µ). This automorphism factor makes counting more difficult. Note that <lb/>the automorphism group of a spherical dessin with a single vertex is a subgroup of Z/(2m)Z <lb/> that preserves the graph. If we place an outgoing arrow to one of the 2m half-edges incident <lb/>to the unique vertex (see Figure 3.1), then we can kill the automorphism altogether. Since <lb/>there are 2m choices of placing such an arrow, the number of arrowed graphs is 2mD  0,1  (2m). <lb/>This is now an integer. By a simple bijection argument with the number of arrangements <lb/>of m pairs of parentheses, we see that <lb/>(3.5) <lb/>2mD  0,1  (2m) = C  m  = <lb/>1 <lb/> m + 1 <lb/> 2m <lb/> m <lb/> , <lb/> where C  m  is the m-th Catalan number. We note that the Catalan numbers appear in the <lb/>same context of counting graphs in [37]. <lb/> Figure 3.1. An arrowed dessin d&apos;enfant of genus 0 with one vertex. <lb/> Define the Laplace transform of D  0,1  (µ) by <lb/>(3.6) <lb/> F <lb/> D <lb/> 0,1  = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> m=1 <lb/> D  0,1  (2m)e <lb/> −2mw  . <lb/> Then the Eynard-Orantin differential <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/> 0,1  = d <lb/> F <lb/> D <lb/> 0,1  = − <lb/> ∞ <lb/> m=1 <lb/> 2mD  0,1  (2m)e <lb/> −2mw  dw = − <lb/> ∞ <lb/> m=1 <lb/> C  m  e <lb/> −2mw  dw <lb/> is a generating function of the Catalan numbers. Actually a better choice is (see [44, 45]) <lb/>(3.7) <lb/> z(x) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> m=0 <lb/> C  m <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  2m+1  = <lb/>1 <lb/> x <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> x  3  + <lb/>2 <lb/> x  5  + <lb/>5 <lb/> x  7  + <lb/>14 <lb/> x  9  + <lb/>42 <lb/> x  11  + · · · . <lb/> The radius of convergence of this infinite Laurent series is 2, hence the series converges <lb/>absolutely for |x| &gt; 2. The inverse function of z = z(x) near (x, z) = (∞, 0) is given by <lb/>(3.8) <lb/> x = z + <lb/>1 <lb/> z <lb/>. <lb/> This can be easily seen by solving the quadratic equation z  2  − xz + 1 = 0 with respect to <lb/> z, which is equivalent to the quadratic recursion <lb/> C  m+1  = <lb/> i+j=m <lb/> C  i  · C  j <lb/></body>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> of Catalan numbers. To take advantage of these simple formulas, let us define <lb/> (3.9) <lb/> x = e <lb/> w <lb/> and allow the m = 0 term in the Eynard-Orantin differential: <lb/>(3.10) <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/> 0,1  = − <lb/> ∞ <lb/> m=0 <lb/> C  m <lb/> dx <lb/>x  2m+1  . <lb/> Accordingly the Laplace transform of D  0,1  (2m) needs to be modified: <lb/>(3.11) <lb/> F <lb/> D <lb/> 0,1  = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> m=1 <lb/> D  0,1  (2m) e <lb/> −2mw  − w = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> m=1 <lb/> D  0,1  (2m) <lb/>1 <lb/> x  2m  − log x. <lb/> Although numerically D  0,1  (0) = 0, its infinitesimal behavior is given by <lb/>lim <lb/> m→0 <lb/> D  0,1  (2m) <lb/> x  2m <lb/> = − log x, <lb/> which is consistent with <lb/>lim <lb/> m→0 <lb/> 2mD  0,1  (2m) = C  0  = 1. <lb/>From (3.7) and (3.12), we obtain <lb/>(3.12) <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/> 0,1  = −z(x) dx. <lb/> In light of (2.5), we have identified the spectral curve for the counting problem of dessins <lb/> D  g,n  (µ). It is given by <lb/>(3.13) <lb/> x = z + <lb/> 1 <lb/> z <lb/> y = −z <lb/> . <lb/> To compute the recursion kernel of (2.2), we need to identify D  0,2  (µ  1  , µ  2  ) for the other <lb/>unstable geometry (g, n) = (0, 2). In the dual graph picture, D  0,2  (µ  1  , µ  2  ) counts the number <lb/>of spherical dessinš <lb/>Γ with two vertices of degree µ  1  and µ  2  , counted with the weight of <lb/>1/|Aut  D  ( ˇ <lb/>Γ)|. The computation was done by Kodama and Pierce in [45, Theorem 3.1]. We <lb/>also refer to a beautiful lecture by Kodama [44]. <lb/> Proposition 3.1 ([45]). The number of spherical dessinssš <lb/>Γ with two vertices of degrees j <lb/> and k, counted with the weight of 1/|Aut  D  ( ˇ <lb/>Γ)|, is given by the following formula. <lb/> (3.14) <lb/> D  0,2  (µ  1  , µ  2  ) = <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> 1 <lb/>2k <lb/>  2k <lb/> k <lb/> µ  1  = 0, µ  2  = 2k  = 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/>4 <lb/>1 <lb/> j+k <lb/>  2j <lb/> j <lb/>  2k <lb/> k <lb/> µ  1  = 2j  = 0, µ  2  = 2k  = 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> j+k+1 <lb/>  2j <lb/> j <lb/>  2k <lb/> k <lb/> µ  1  = 2j + 1, µ  2  = 2k + 1 <lb/> . <lb/> All other cases D  0,2  (µ  1  , µ  2  ) = 0. Here the automorphism group Aut  D  ( ˇ <lb/>Γ) is the topological <lb/>graph automorphisms that fix each vertex, but may permute faces. <lb/> Remark 3.2. The first case is irregular. For µ  1  = 0, the second vertex has an even degree, <lb/>and hence we have C  k  /(2k) graphs. Note that this graph has k + 1 faces due to Euler&apos;s <lb/>formula 2 = 1 − k + (k + 1). The degree 0 vertex has to be placed in one of these faces, <lb/>which makes the total number of graphs <lb/> k + 1 <lb/>2k <lb/> C  k  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2k <lb/> 2k <lb/> k <lb/> . <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body> However, we are counting only connected graphs. Hence degree 0 vertices are not allowed <lb/>in our counting. <lb/>In general the number of dessins satisfies the following: <lb/> Theorem 3.3. For g ≥ 0 and n ≥ 1 subject to 2g − 2 + n ≥ 0, the number of dessins (3.4) <lb/>satisfies a recursion equation <lb/> (3.15) µ  1  D  g,n  (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  ) = <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> (µ  1  + µ  j  − 2)D  g,n−1 <lb/> µ  1  + µ  j  − 2, µ  [n]\{1,j} <lb/> + <lb/> α+β=µ  1  −2 <lb/> αβ <lb/> D  g−1,n+1  (α, β, µ  [n]\{1}  ) + <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> IJ={2,...,n} <lb/> D  g  1  ,|I|+1  (α, µ  I  )D  g  2  ,|J|+1  (β, µ  J  ) <lb/> , <lb/> where µ  I  = (µ  i  )  i∈I  for a subset I ⊂ [n] = {1, 2, . . . , n}. The last sum is over all partitions <lb/>of the genus g and the index set {2, 3, . . . , n} into two pieces. <lb/> Remark 3.4. Note that when g  1  = 0 and I = ∅, D  g,n  appears in the right-hand side of <lb/>(3.15). Therefore, this is an equation of the number of dessins, not a recursion formula. <lb/> Proof. Consider the collection of genus g dessins with n vertices labeled by the index set <lb/>[n] = {1, 2, . . . , n} and of degrees (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  ). The left-hand side of (3.15) is the number <lb/>of dessins with an outward arrow placed on one of the incident edges at the vertex 1. The <lb/>equation is based on the removal of this edge. There are two cases. <lb/> Case 1. The arrowed edge connects the vertex 1 and vertex j &gt; 1. We then remove the <lb/>edge and put the two vertices 1 and j together as shown in Figure 3.2. This operation is <lb/>better described as shrinking the arrowed edge to a point. The resulting dessin has one less <lb/>vertices, but the genus is the same as before. The degree of the newly created vertex is <lb/> µ  1  + µ  j  − 2, while the degrees of all other vertices are unaffected. <lb/> 1 <lb/> j <lb/> Figure 3.2. The operation that shrinks the arrowed edge to a point and joins two <lb/>vertices labeled by 1 and j together. <lb/> To make the bijection argument, we need to be able to reconstruct the original dessin from <lb/>the new one. Since both µ  1  and µ  j  are given as the input value, we have to specify which <lb/>edges go to vertex 1 and which go to j when we separate the vertex of degree µ  1  + µ  j  − 2. <lb/>For this purpose, what we need is a marker on one of the incident edges. We group the <lb/>marked edge and µ  i  − 2 edges following it according to the cyclic order. The rest of the <lb/> µ  j  − 1 incident edges are also grouped. Then we insert an edge and separate the vertex into <lb/>two vertices, 1 and j, so that the first group of edges are incident to vertex 1 and the second <lb/>group is incident to j, honoring their cyclic orders (see Figure 3.2). The contribution from <lb/>this case is therefore <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> (µ  1  + µ  j  − 2)D  g,n−1 <lb/> µ  1  + µ  j  − 2, µ  [n]\{1,j} <lb/> . <lb/></body>

			<page> 12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> Case 2. The arrowed edge forms a loop that is attached to vertex 1. We remove this loop <lb/>from the dessin, and separate the vertex into two vertices. The loop classifies all incident <lb/>half-edges, except for the loop itself, into two groups: the ones that follow the arrowed <lb/>half-edge in the cyclic order but before the incoming end of the loop, and all others (see <lb/>Figure 3.3). Let α be the number of half-edges in the first group, and β the rest. Then <lb/> α + β = µ  1  − 2, and we have created two vertices of degrees α and β. <lb/> To recover the original dessin from the new one, we need to mark a half-edge from each <lb/>vertex so that we can put the loop back to the original place. The number of choices of <lb/>these markings is αβ. <lb/> Figure 3.3. The operation that removes a loop, and separates the incident vertex <lb/>into two vertices. <lb/> The operation of the removal of the loop and the separation of the vertex into two vertices <lb/>certainly increases the number of vertices from n to n + 1. This operation also affects the <lb/>genus of the dessin. If the resulting dessin is connected, then g goes down to g − 1. If the <lb/>result is the disjoint union of two dessins of genera g  1  and g  2  , then we have g = g  1  + g  2  . <lb/>Altogether the contribution from this case is <lb/> α+β=µ  1  −2 <lb/> αβ <lb/> D  g−1,n+1  (α, β, µ  [n]\{1}  ) + <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> IJ={2,...,n} <lb/> D  g  1  ,|I|+1  (α, µ  I  )D  g  2  ,|J|+1  (β, µ  J  ) <lb/> . <lb/> Note that the outward arrow we place defines the two groups of incident half-edges uniquely, <lb/>since one is after and the other before the arrowed half-edge according to the cyclic order. <lb/>Thus we do not need to symmetrize α and β. Indeed, if the arrow is placed in the other <lb/>end of the loop, then α and β are interchanged. <lb/>The right-hand side of the equation (3.15) is the sum of the above two contributions. <lb/> Remark 3.5. The equation (3.15) is considerably simpler, compared to the recursion for-<lb/>mula for the number of ribbon graphs with integral edge lengths that is proved in [10, <lb/>Theorem 3.3]. The edge removal operation of [10] is the dual operation of the edge shrink-<lb/>ing operations of Case 1 and Case 2 above, and the placement of an arrow corresponds to <lb/>the ciliation of [10]. In the dual picture, the graphs enumerated in [10] are more restrictive <lb/>than arbitrary clean dessins, which makes the equation more complicated. We also note <lb/>that [10, Theorem 3.3] is a recursion formula, not just a mere relation like what we have in <lb/>(3.15). In this regard, (3.15) is indeed similar to the cut-and-join equation (6.28) of [29, 77]. <lb/>We will come back to this point in Section 6. <lb/>The relation (3.15) becomes an effective recursion formula after taking the Laplace trans-<lb/>form. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body> 4. The Laplace transform of the number of dessins and ribbon graphs <lb/> In this section we derive the Eynard-Orantin recursion formula for the generating func-<lb/>tions of the number of dessins. The key technique is the Laplace transform. <lb/>Since the projection x = z + 1/z of the spectral curve to the x-coordinate plane has <lb/>two ramification points z = ±1, it is natural to introduce a coordinate that has these <lb/>ramification points at 0 and ∞. So we define <lb/>(4.1) <lb/> z = <lb/> t + 1 <lb/> t − 1 <lb/> . <lb/> Proposition 4.1. The Laplace transform of D  0,2  (µ  1  , µ  2  ) is given by <lb/> (4.2) F <lb/> D <lb/> 0,2  (t  1  , t  2  ) <lb/> def <lb/> = <lb/> µ  1  ,µ  2  &gt;0 <lb/> D  0,2  (µ  1  , µ  2  ) e <lb/> −(µ  1  w  1  +µ  2  w  2  )  = − log <lb/> 1 − z(x  1  )z(x  2  ) <lb/> = log(t  1  − 1) + log(t  2  − 1) − log(−2(t  1  + t  2  )), <lb/> where z(x) is the generating function of the Catalan numbers (3.7), and the variables <lb/> t, w, x, z are related by (3.9), (3.13), and (4.1). We then have <lb/> (4.3) <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/> 0,2  (t  1  , t  2  ) = d  1  d  2  F <lb/> D <lb/> 0,2  (t  1  , t  2  ) = <lb/> dt  1  · dt  2 <lb/> (t  1  − t  2  )  2  − <lb/> dx  1  · dx  2 <lb/> (x  1  − x  2  )  2  = <lb/> dt  1  · dt  2 <lb/> (t  1  + t  2  )  2  . <lb/> Proof. In terms of x = e  w  , the Laplace transform (4.2) is given by <lb/>(4.4) <lb/> µ  1  ,µ  2  &gt;0 <lb/> D  0,2  (µ  1  , µ  2  ) e <lb/> −(µ  1  w  1  +µ  2  w  2  ) <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/> ∞ <lb/> j,k=1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> j + k <lb/> 2j <lb/> j <lb/> 2k <lb/> k <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2j <lb/>1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  2k <lb/>2 <lb/> + <lb/> ∞ <lb/> j,k=0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> j + k + 1 <lb/> 2j <lb/> j <lb/> 2k <lb/> k <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2j+1 <lb/>1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2k+1 <lb/>2 <lb/> . <lb/> Since <lb/>(4.5) <lb/> dx = <lb/> 1 − <lb/> 1 <lb/> z  2 <lb/> dz, <lb/> we have <lb/>(4.6) <lb/> x <lb/>d <lb/>dx <lb/> = <lb/> z + <lb/> 1 <lb/> z <lb/> 1 − <lb/> 1 <lb/> z  2 <lb/> d <lb/>dz <lb/> = <lb/> z(z  2  + 1) <lb/> z  2  − 1 <lb/> d <lb/>dz <lb/>. <lb/> To make the computation simpler, let us introduce <lb/>(4.7) <lb/> ξ  0  (x) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> m=0 <lb/> 2m <lb/> m <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  2m+1  . <lb/> This will also be used in Section 7. In terms of z and t we have <lb/>(4.8) ξ  0  (x) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 − x <lb/>d <lb/>dx <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> m=0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> m + 1 <lb/> 2m <lb/> m <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  2m+1 <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 − <lb/> z(z  2  + 1) <lb/> z  2  − 1 <lb/> d <lb/>dz <lb/> z = − <lb/> z <lb/>z  2  − 1 <lb/>= − <lb/> t  2  − 1 <lb/>4t <lb/> . <lb/> Note that <lb/> − <lb/> x  1 <lb/> d <lb/>dx  1 <lb/> + x  2 <lb/> d <lb/>dx  2 <lb/> 1 <lb/>4 <lb/> ∞ <lb/> j,k=1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> j + k <lb/> 2j <lb/> j <lb/> 2k <lb/> k <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2j <lb/>1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  2k <lb/>2 <lb/></body>

			<page> 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> + <lb/> ∞ <lb/> j,k=0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> j + k + 1 <lb/> 2j <lb/> j <lb/> 2k <lb/> k <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2j+1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2k+1 <lb/>2 <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(x  1  ξ  0  (x  1  ) − 1)(x  2  ξ  0  (x  2  ) − 1) + 2ξ  0  (x  1  )ξ  0  (x  2  ) <lb/>= 2z  1  z  2 <lb/> 1 + z  1  z  2 <lb/> (z  1 <lb/>1  − 1)(z  2 <lb/>2  − 1) <lb/>= − <lb/> z  1  (z  2 <lb/>1  + 1) <lb/> z  2 <lb/>1  − 1 <lb/> d <lb/>dz  1 <lb/> + <lb/> z  2  (z  2 <lb/>2  + 1) <lb/> z  2 <lb/>2  − 1 <lb/> d <lb/>dz  2 <lb/> (− log(1 − z  1  z  2  )) . <lb/> In other words, we have a partial differential equation <lb/> x  1 <lb/> d <lb/>dx  1 <lb/> + x  2 <lb/> d <lb/>dx  2 <lb/> F <lb/> D <lb/> 0,2  (t  1  , t  2  ) + log(1 − z  1  z  2  ) <lb/> = 0 <lb/>for a holomorphic function in x  1  and x  2  defined for |x  1  | &gt; &gt; 2 and |x  2  | &gt; &gt; 2. Since the first <lb/>few terms of the Laurent expansions of − log <lb/> 1 − z(x  1  )z(x  2  ) <lb/> using (3.7) agree with the <lb/>first few terms of the sums of (4.4), we have the initial condition for the above differential <lb/>equation. By the uniqueness of the solution to the Euler differential equation with the <lb/>initial condition, we obtain (4.2). Equation (4.3) follows from differentiation of (4.2). <lb/> In terms of the t-coordinate of (4.1), the Galois conjugate of t ∈ Σ under the projection <lb/> x : Σ−→C is −t. Therefore, the recursion kernel for counting of dessins is given by <lb/>(4.9) K <lb/> D  (t, t  1  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>  −t <lb/> t  W  D <lb/> 0,2  (·, t  1  ) <lb/> W  D <lb/> 0,1  (−t) − W  D <lb/> 0,1  (t) <lb/>= <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> t + t  1 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> t − t  1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> t+1 <lb/>t−1  − <lb/> t−1 <lb/>t+1 <lb/> · <lb/> 1 <lb/> dx <lb/> · dt  1 <lb/> = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>64 <lb/> 1 <lb/> t + t  1 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> t − t  1 <lb/> (t  2  − 1)  3 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> · <lb/> 1 <lb/> dt <lb/> · dt  1  . <lb/> One of the first two stable cases (2.4) gives us <lb/>(4.10) W <lb/> D <lb/> 1,1  (t  1  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ <lb/> K <lb/> D  (t, t  1  ) <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/> 0,2  (t, −t) + <lb/> dx · dx  1 <lb/> (x − x  1  )  2 <lb/> = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ <lb/> K <lb/> D  (t, t  1  ) <lb/> dt · dt <lb/> 4t  2  = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>128 <lb/>(t  2 <lb/>1  − 1)  3 <lb/> t  4 <lb/>1 <lb/> dt  1  , <lb/> where the integration contour γ consists of two concentric circles of a small radius and a <lb/>large radius centered around t = 0, with the inner circle positively and the outer circle <lb/>negatively oriented (Figure 4.1). The (g, n) = (0, 3) case is given by <lb/>(4.11) W <lb/> D <lb/> 0,3  (t  1  , t  2  , t  3  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ <lb/> W  D <lb/> 0,2  (t, t  1  )W  D <lb/> 0,2  (t, t  2  )W  D <lb/> 0,2  (t, t  3  ) <lb/> dx(t) · dy(t) <lb/> = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>16 <lb/> 1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ <lb/> (t  2  − 1)  2  (t − 1)  2 <lb/> (t + t  1  )  2  (t + t  2  )  2  (t + t  3  )  2  · <lb/> dt <lb/>t <lb/> dt  1  dt  2  dt  3 <lb/> = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>16 <lb/> 1 − <lb/> 1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1  t  2 <lb/>2  t  2 <lb/>3 <lb/> dt  1  dt  2  dt  3  . <lb/> Remark 4.2. The general formula (2.3) for (g, n) = (0, 3) also gives the same answer. This <lb/>is because W  D <lb/> 0,2  acts as the Cauchy differentiation kernel. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body> W <lb/> D <lb/> 0,3  (t  1  , t  2  , t  3  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ <lb/> K <lb/> D  (t, t  1  ) <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/> 0,2  (t, t  2  )W <lb/> D <lb/> 0,2  (−t, t  3  ) + W <lb/> D <lb/> 0,2  (t, t  3  )W <lb/> D <lb/> 0,2  (−t, t  2  ) <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>64 <lb/> 1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ <lb/> 1 <lb/> t + t  1 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> t − t  1 <lb/> (t  2  − 1)  3 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> 1 <lb/>(t + t  2  )  2  (t − t  3  )  2  + <lb/>1 <lb/>(t + t  3  )  2  (t − t  2  )  2 <lb/> dt <lb/> · dt  1  dt  2  dt  3 <lb/> = <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>32 <lb/>(t  2 <lb/>1  − 1)  3 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> 1 <lb/>(t  1  + t  2  )  2  (t  1  − t  3  )  2  + <lb/>1 <lb/>(t  1  + t  3  )  2  (t  1  − t  2  )  2 <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>16 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  2 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>2  − t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> (t  2 <lb/>2  − 1)  3 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 <lb/>(t  2  + t  3  )  2 <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>16 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  3 <lb/> t  3 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>3  − t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> (t  2 <lb/>3  − 1)  3 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>3 <lb/> 1 <lb/>(t  2  + t  3  )  2 <lb/> dt  1  dt  2  dt  3  = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>16 <lb/> 1 − <lb/> 1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1  t  2 <lb/>2  t  2 <lb/>3 <lb/> dt  1  dt  2  dt  3  . <lb/> t  1 <lb/> t  1 <lb/> t j <lb/> t j <lb/> t-plane <lb/>dt <lb/>r <lb/>r <lb/> Figure 4.1. The integration contour γ. This contour encloses an annulus bounded <lb/>by two concentric circles centered at the origin. The outer one has a large radius r &gt; <lb/> max  j∈N  |t  j  | and the negative orientation, and the inner one has an infinitesimally <lb/>small radius with the positive orientation. <lb/> Theorem 4.3. Let us define the Laplace transform of the number of Grothendieck&apos;s dessins <lb/>by <lb/> (4.12) <lb/> F <lb/> D <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) = <lb/> µ∈Z  n <lb/> + <lb/> D  g,n  (µ)e <lb/> −(µ  1  w  1  +···+µnwn)  , <lb/> where the coordinate t  i  is related to the Laplace conjugate coordinate w  j  by <lb/> e <lb/> w  j  = <lb/> t  j  + 1 <lb/> t  j  − 1 <lb/>+ <lb/> t  j  − 1 <lb/> t  j  + 1 <lb/> . <lb/> Then the differential forms <lb/> (4.13) <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) = d  1  · · · d  n  F <lb/> D <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/> satisfy the Eynard-Orantin topological recursion <lb/> (4.14) W <lb/> D <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/>= − <lb/> 1 <lb/>64 <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ <lb/> 1 <lb/> t + t  1 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> t − t  1 <lb/> (t  2  − 1)  3 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> · <lb/> 1 <lb/> dt <lb/> · dt  1 <lb/> × <lb/>  n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/> 0,2  (t, t  j  )W  g,n−1  (−t, t  2  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) + W <lb/> D <lb/> 0,2  (−t, t  j  )W  g,n−1  (t, t  2  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/></body>

			<page> 16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> + W <lb/> D <lb/> g−1,n+1  (t, −t, t  2  , . . . , t  n  ) + <lb/> stable <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> IJ={2,3,...,n} <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/>g  1  ,|I|+1  (t, t  I  )W <lb/> D <lb/>g  2  ,|J|+1  (−t, t  J  ) <lb/> . <lb/> The last sum is restricted to the stable geometries. In other words, the partition should <lb/>satisfies 2g  1  − 1 + |I| &gt; 0 and 2g  2  − 1 + |J|. The spectral curve Σ of the Eynard-Orantin <lb/>recursion is given by <lb/> x = z + <lb/> 1 <lb/> z <lb/> y = −z <lb/> with the preferred coordinate t given by <lb/> t = <lb/> z + 1 <lb/> z − 1 <lb/> . <lb/> We give the proof of this theorem in the appendix. <lb/>The problem of counting dessins is closely related to the counting problem of the lattice <lb/>points of the moduli space M  g,n  of smooth n-pointed algebraic curves of genus g studied <lb/>in [59, 60]. Let us briefly recall the combinatorial model for the moduli space M  g,n  due <lb/>to Thurston (see for example, [73]), Harer [36], Mumford [58], and Strebel [75], following <lb/>[54, 55]. For a given ribbon graph Γ with e = e(Γ) edges, the space of metric ribbon <lb/>graphs is R <lb/> e(Γ) <lb/> +  /Aut(Γ), where the automorphism group acts by permutations of edges (see <lb/>[54, Section 1]). When we consider ribbon graph automorphisms, we restrict ourselves that <lb/>Aut(Γ) fixes each 2-cell of the cell-decomposition. We also require that every vertex of a <lb/>ribbon graph has degree 3 or more. Using the canonical holomorphic coordinate system <lb/>on a topological surface of [54, Section 4] corresponding to a metric ribbon graph, and the <lb/>Strebel differentials [75], we have an isomorphism of topological orbifolds [36, 58] <lb/>(4.15) <lb/> M  g,n  × R <lb/> n <lb/> + <lb/> ∼ = R  g,n <lb/> for (g, n) in the stable range. Here <lb/> R  g,n  = <lb/> Γ ribbon graph <lb/>of type (g,n) <lb/> R <lb/> e(Γ) <lb/> + <lb/> Aut(Γ) <lb/>is an orbifold consisting of metric ribbon graphs of a given topological type (g, n). The <lb/>gluing of orbi-cells is done by making the length of a non-loop edge tend to 0. The space <lb/> R  g,n  is a smooth orbifold (see [54, Section 3] and [73]). We denote by π : R  g,n  −→ R  n <lb/> + <lb/> the natural projection via (4.15), which is the assignment of the perimeter length of each <lb/>boundary to a given metric ribbon graph. <lb/>Take a ribbon graph Γ. Since Aut(Γ) fixes every boundary component of Γ, they are <lb/>labeled by [n] = {1, 2 . . . , n}. For the moment let us give a label to each edge of Γ by an <lb/>index set [e] = {1, 2, . . . , e}. The edge-face incidence matrix is defined by <lb/>(4.16) <lb/> A  Γ  = <lb/> a  iη <lb/> i∈[n], η∈[e] <lb/> ; <lb/> a  iη  = the number of times edge η appears in face i. <lb/> Thus a  iη  = 0, 1, or 2, and the sum of the entries in each column is always 2. The Γ con-<lb/>tribution of the space π  −1  (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  ) = R  g,n  (µ) of metric ribbon graphs with a prescribed <lb/>perimeter µ = (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  ) ∈ R  n <lb/> +  is the orbifold polytope <lb/> {x ∈ R  e <lb/> +  | A  Γ  x = µ} <lb/> Aut(Γ) <lb/> , <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body> where x = (  1  , . . . ,  e  ) is the collection of edge lengths of the metric ribbon graph Γ. We <lb/>have <lb/>(4.17) <lb/> i∈[n] <lb/> µ  i  = <lb/> i∈[n] <lb/> η∈[e] <lb/> a  iη   η  = 2 <lb/> η∈[e] <lb/>  η  . <lb/> Now let µ ∈ Z  n <lb/> +  be a vector consisting of positive integers. The lattice point counting <lb/>function we consider is defined by <lb/>(4.18) <lb/> N  g,n  (µ) = <lb/> Γ ribbon graph <lb/>of type (g,n) <lb/> {x ∈ Z  n <lb/> +  | A  Γ  x = µ} <lb/> |Aut(Γ)| <lb/> for (g, n) in the stable range ([10, 55, 59, 60]). <lb/>To find the spectral curve for lattice point counting, we need to identify the unstable <lb/>moduli M  0,1  and the ribbon graph space R  0,1  . We recall that the orbifold isomorphism <lb/>(4.15) holds for (g, n) in the stable range by defining R  g,n  as the space of metric ribbon <lb/>graphs of type (g, n) without vertices of degrees 1 and 2. For (g, n) = (0, 1), there are no <lb/>ribbon graphs satisfying these conditions. Let v  j  denote the number of degree j vertices in <lb/>a ribbon graph Γ of type (g, n). Then we have <lb/> j≥1 <lb/> jv  j  = 2e, <lb/> j≥1 <lb/> v  j  = v, <lb/> where v is the total number of vertices of Γ. Hence <lb/>(4.19) <lb/>2(2g − 2 + n) = 2e − 2v = <lb/> j≥1 <lb/> (j − 2)v  j  = −v  1  + <lb/> j≥3 <lb/> (j − 2)v  j  . <lb/> It follows that the number of degree 1 vertices v  1  is positive when (g, n) = (0, 1). Thus we <lb/>conclude that there is no spectral curve for this counting problem. <lb/> Still we can consider the Laplace transform of the number (4.18) of lattice points of the <lb/>moduli space M  g,n  with a prescribed perimeter length. We define for every stable (g, n) <lb/> (4.20) <lb/> F <lb/> L <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) = <lb/> µ∈Z  n <lb/> + <lb/> N  g,n  (µ) <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> z <lb/> µ  i <lb/> i <lb/> , <lb/> and the Eynard-Orantin differential forms by <lb/>(4.21) <lb/> W <lb/> L <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) = d  1  · · · d  n  F <lb/> L <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ). <lb/>The following result is proved in [10], with inspiration from [60]. <lb/> Theorem 4.4 ([10]). The differential forms W  L <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) satisfy the Eynard-Orantin <lb/>topological recursion with respect to the same spectral curve (3.13) and the recursion kernel <lb/>(4.9), starting with exactly the same first two stable cases <lb/> (4.22) <lb/> W <lb/> L <lb/> 1,1  (t  1  ) = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>128 <lb/>(t  2 <lb/>1  − 1)  3 <lb/> t  4 <lb/>1 <lb/> dt  1  , <lb/> and <lb/> (4.23) <lb/> W <lb/> L <lb/> 0,3  (t  1  , t  2  , t  3  ) = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>16 <lb/> 1 − <lb/> 1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1  t  2 <lb/>2  t  2 <lb/>3 <lb/> dt  1  dt  2  dt  3  . <lb/> Remark 4.5. It is somewhat surprising, because the spectral curve (3.13) has nothing to <lb/>do with the lattice point counting problem. As we have mentioned, the (g, n) = (0, 1) and <lb/>(0, 2) considerations for this problem do not produce the spectral curve. <lb/></body>

			<page> 18 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> Corollary 4.6. For every (g, n) with 2g − 2 + n &gt; 0, we have the identity <lb/> (4.24) <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/> g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) = W <lb/> L <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ). <lb/> The differential form W  D <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) is a Laurent polynomial in t  2 <lb/>1  , . . . , t  2 <lb/> n  of degree 2(3g − <lb/> 3 + n), with a reciprocity property <lb/> (4.25) <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/>g,n  (1/t  1  , . . . , 1/t  n  ) = (−1) <lb/> n  t <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  · · · t <lb/> 2 <lb/> n  W <lb/> D <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ). <lb/> The numbers of dessins can be expressed in terms of the number of lattice points: <lb/> (4.26) D  g,n  (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  ) = <lb/>  1  &gt; <lb/> µ 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> · · · <lb/> n&gt; <lb/> µn <lb/> 2 <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> 2  i  − µ  i <lb/> µ  i <lb/> µ  i <lb/>  i <lb/> N  g,n  (2  1  − µ  i  , · · · , 2  n  − µ  n  ). <lb/> Remark 4.7. The relation (4.26) appears in [62, Section 2.1] for an abstract setting. <lb/> Proof. The Eynard-Orantin topological recursion uniquely determines the differential forms <lb/>for all (g, n). Since W  D <lb/> 1,1  (t) = W  L <lb/> 1,1  (t) and W  D <lb/> 0,3  (t  1  , t  2  , t  3  ) = W  L <lb/> 0,3  (t  1  , t  2  , t  3  ), we conclude that <lb/> W  D <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) = W  L <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) for 2g − 2 + n &gt; 0. <lb/>By induction on 2g − 2 + n we can show that W  D <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) is a Laurent polynomial <lb/>in t  2 <lb/>1  , . . . , t  2 <lb/> n  . The statement is true for the initial cases (4.10) and (4.11). The integral <lb/>transformation formula (4.14) is a residue calculation at t = 0 and t = ∞. By the induction <lb/>hypothesis, the right-hand side of (4.14) becomes <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>64 <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ <lb/> 1 <lb/> t + t  1 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> t − t  1 <lb/> (t  2  − 1)  3 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> · <lb/> 1 <lb/> dt <lb/> · dt  1 <lb/> × <lb/>  n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/> 0,2  (t, t  j  )W  g,n−1  (−t, t  2  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) + W <lb/> D <lb/> 0,2  (−t, t  j  )W  g,n−1  (t, t  2  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/> + W <lb/> D <lb/>g−1,n+1  (t, −t, t  2  , . . . , t  n  ) + <lb/> stable <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> IJ={2,3,...,n} <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/>g  1  ,|I|+1  (t, t  I  )W <lb/> D <lb/>g  2  ,|J|+1  (−t, t  J  ) <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>32 <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ <lb/> (t  2  − 1)  3 <lb/> t  2  − t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/> · <lb/> 1 <lb/> dt <lb/> · dt  1 <lb/>  n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> 2(t  2  + t  2 <lb/> j  ) <lb/>(t  2  − t  2 <lb/> j  )  2  W  g,n−1  (t, t  2  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) dt · dt  j <lb/> + W <lb/> D <lb/>g−1,n+1  (t, t, t  2  , . . . , t  n  ) + <lb/> stable <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> IJ={2,3,...,n} <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/>g  1  ,|I|+1  (t, t  I  )W <lb/> D <lb/>g  2  ,|J|+1  (t, t  J  ) <lb/> . <lb/> Clearly the residues at t = 0 and t = ∞ are Laurent polynomials in t  2 <lb/>1  , . . . , t  2 <lb/> n  . <lb/>Because of (4.24), we have <lb/>(4.27) <lb/> µ∈Z  n <lb/> + <lb/> D  g,n  (µ) <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> d <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> µ  i <lb/> i <lb/> = <lb/> ν∈Z  n <lb/> + <lb/> N  g,n  (ν) <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> d <lb/> 1 <lb/> z <lb/> ν  i <lb/> i <lb/> = (−1) <lb/> n <lb/> ν∈Z  n <lb/> + <lb/> N  g,n  (ν) <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> dz <lb/> ν  i <lb/> i  , <lb/> where x  i  = z  i  + 1/z  i  . The Galois conjugation t→ − t corresponds to z→1/z. Since <lb/> W <lb/> N <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) = (−1) <lb/> n  W <lb/> N <lb/>g,n  (−t  1  , . . . , −t  n  ), <lb/>the second equality of (4.27) follows. Take the residue of the left-hand side of (4.27) at <lb/> x  i  = ∞ for i = 1, . . . , n. On the right-hand side we take the residue at z  i  = 0 for every i. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body> Then for every (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  ) ∈ Z  n <lb/> +  we have <lb/>(4.28) <lb/> D  g,n  (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  )µ  1  · · · µ  n  = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2πi <lb/>  n  <lb/> |z  1  |= <lb/> · · · <lb/> |zn|= <lb/> x <lb/> µ  1 <lb/> 1  · · · x <lb/> µn <lb/>n <lb/> ν∈Z  n <lb/> + <lb/> N  g,n  (ν) <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> dz <lb/> ν  i <lb/> i  . <lb/> Since <lb/> z  i  + <lb/>1 <lb/> z  i <lb/>  µ  i <lb/> = <lb/> µ  i <lb/>  i  =0 <lb/> µ  i <lb/>  i <lb/> z <lb/> µ  i  −2  i <lb/> i <lb/> , <lb/> the residue of (4.28) comes from the term µ  i  − 2  i  + ν  i  = 0, and we have <lb/> D  g,n  (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  )µ  1  · · · µ  n <lb/> = <lb/>  1  &gt;µ  1  /2 <lb/> · · · <lb/> n&gt;µn/2 <lb/>n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (2  i  − µ  i  ) <lb/> µ  i <lb/>  i <lb/> N  g,n  (2  1  − µ  1  , . . . , 2  n  − µ  n  ). <lb/>The reciprocity relation, and the degree of the Laurent polynomial, is the consequence <lb/>of the following, which was established in [55]. <lb/> Theorem 4.8 ([55]). The functions F  L <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) of (4.20) for the stable range 2g−2+n &gt; <lb/> 0 are uniquely determined by the following differential recursion formula from the initial <lb/>values F  L <lb/> 0,3  (t  1  , t  2  , t  3  ) and F  L <lb/> 1,1  (t  1  ). <lb/>(4.29) F <lb/> L <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/>= − <lb/> 1 <lb/>16 <lb/>  t  1 <lb/> −1 <lb/>  n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> t  j <lb/> t  2  − t  2 <lb/> j <lb/> (t  2  − 1)  3 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t <lb/>F  g,n−1  L  (t, t  [n]\{1,j}  ) − <lb/> (t  2 <lb/> j  − 1)  3 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> j <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  j <lb/> F <lb/> L <lb/>g,n−1  (t  [n]\{1}  ) <lb/> + <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> (t  2  − 1)  2 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t <lb/>F <lb/> L <lb/>g,n−1  (t, t  [n]\{1,j}  ) <lb/>+ <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(t  2  − 1)  3 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> ∂  2 <lb/> ∂u  1  ∂u  2 <lb/> F <lb/> L <lb/>g−1,n+1  (u  1  , u  2  , t  [n]\{1}  ) <lb/>+ <lb/> stable <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> IJ=[n]\{1} <lb/> F <lb/> L <lb/>g  1  ,|I|+1  (u  1  , t  I  )F  g  2  ,|J|+1  (u  2  , t  J  ) <lb/> u  1  =u  2  =t <lb/> dt. <lb/> Here [n] = {1, 2, . . . , n} is an index set, and the last sum is taken over all partitions g  1  +g  2  = <lb/> g and set partitions I  J = [n] \ {1} subject to the stability conditions 2g  1  − 1 + |I| &gt; 0 and <lb/> 2g  2  − 1 + |J| &gt; 0. The initial values are given by <lb/> (4.30) <lb/> F <lb/> L <lb/> 1,1  (t  1  ) = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>384 <lb/>(t + 1)  4 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> t − 4 + <lb/>1 <lb/> t <lb/> and <lb/> (4.31) <lb/> F <lb/> L <lb/> 0,3  (t  1  , t  2  , t  3  ) = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>16 <lb/>(t  1  + 1)(t  2  + 1)(t  3  + 1) <lb/> 1 + <lb/>1 <lb/> t  1  t  2  t  3 <lb/> . <lb/> In the stable range F  L <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) is a Laurent polynomial of degree 3(2n − 2 + n) and <lb/>satisfies the reciprocity relation <lb/> (4.32) <lb/> F <lb/> L <lb/>g,n  (1/t  1  , . . . , 1/t  n  ) = F <lb/> L <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ). <lb/></body>

			<page> 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> The leading terms of F  L <lb/> g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) form a homogeneous polynomial of degree 3(2g −2+n), <lb/> and is given by <lb/> (4.33) <lb/> F <lb/> K <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/> def <lb/> = <lb/>(−1)  n <lb/> 2  2g−2+n <lb/> d  1  +···+dn <lb/>=3g−3+n <lb/> τ  d  1  · · · τ  dn   g,n <lb/>n <lb/> j=1 <lb/> (2d  j  − 1)!! <lb/> t  j <lb/> 2 <lb/>  2d  j  +1 <lb/> , <lb/> where <lb/> τ  d  1  · · · τ  dn   g,n  = <lb/> Mg,n <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  1 <lb/> 1  · · · ψ <lb/> dn <lb/>n <lb/> is the ψ-class intersection number (see Section 6 for more detail about intersection numbers). <lb/>The special value at t  i  = 1 gives <lb/> (4.34) <lb/> F <lb/> L <lb/>g,n  (1, 1, . . . , 1) = (−1) <lb/> n  χ (M  g,n  ). <lb/>This completes the proof of Corollary 4.6. <lb/> 5. The ψ-class interaction numbers on M  g,n <lb/> The crucial discovery of Konstevich [46] is the equality between the intersection numbers <lb/>on the compact moduli space M  g,n  and the Euclidean volume of the moduli space M  g,n <lb/> of smooth curves using the isomorphism (4.15). The Feynman diagram expansion of the <lb/>Kontsevich matrix integral relates the Euclidean volume with a τ -function of the KdV <lb/>equations. The Eyanrd-Orantin recursion for the ψ-class intersection numbers is precisely <lb/>the Dijkgraaf-Verlinde-Verlinde formula [15] of the intersection numbers. In this section we <lb/>identify the spectral curve and the recursion kernel for the ψ-class intersection numbers. <lb/>As we have noted, the derivative of the recursion formula (4.29) is not the Eynard-Orantin <lb/>recursion because the spectral curve is not defined by the unstable geometries. Indeed, we <lb/>have dF  L <lb/> 0,1  ≡ 0. However, when we associate the number of lattice points with the ψ-class <lb/> intersection numbers on M  g,n  , the unstable geometries do make sense. <lb/>Let us recall a computation in [55, Section 4]. <lb/>(5.1) <lb/> µ∈Z  n <lb/> + <lb/> N  g,n  (µ)e <lb/> −−µ,w  = <lb/> Γ ribbon graph <lb/>of type (g,n) <lb/> µ∈Z  n <lb/> + <lb/> 1 <lb/> |Aut(Γ)| <lb/> {x ∈ Z <lb/> e(Γ) <lb/> + <lb/> | A  Γ  x = µ} <lb/> e <lb/> −−µ,w <lb/> = <lb/> Γ ribbon graph <lb/>of type (g,n) <lb/> 1 <lb/> |Aut(Γ)| <lb/> x∈Z <lb/> e(Γ) <lb/> + <lb/> e <lb/> −−A  Γ  x,w <lb/> = <lb/> Γ ribbon graph <lb/>of type (g,n) <lb/> 1 <lb/> |Aut(Γ)| <lb/> η edge <lb/>of Γ <lb/> ∞ <lb/> η=1 <lb/> e <lb/> −−aη,wη <lb/> = <lb/> Γ ribbon graph <lb/>of type (g,n) <lb/> 1 <lb/> |Aut(Γ)| <lb/> η edge <lb/>of Γ <lb/> e  −−aη,w <lb/> 1 − e  −−aη,w  , <lb/> where A  Γ  is the incidence matrix of (4.16), a  η  is the η-th column of A  Γ  , and µ, w = <lb/> µ  1  w  1  + · · · + µ  n  w  n  . By comparing (4.20) and (5.1), we see that we are substituting e  w  i  = z  i <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body> in this computation. Therefore, we obtain <lb/>(5.2) <lb/> F <lb/> L <lb/> g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) = <lb/> Γ ribbon graph <lb/>of type (g,n) <lb/> 1 <lb/> |Aut(Γ)| <lb/> η edge <lb/>of Γ <lb/> 1 <lb/>  n <lb/>i=1  z <lb/> a  iη <lb/> i <lb/> − 1 <lb/> . <lb/> Thus the series (4.20) in z  i  converges for |z  i  | &gt; 1. Since z  i  = <lb/> t  i  +1 <lb/> t  1  −1  , the t  i  →∞ limit picks <lb/>up the limit of (4.20) as z  i  →1, and hence the information of N  g,n  (µ) as µ  i  →∞. Since the <lb/>orbifold isomorphism (4.15) is scale invariant under the action of R  +  , making the perimeter <lb/>length µ large is the same as making the mesh small in the lattice point counting. Hence at <lb/>the limit we obtain the Euclidean volume of M  g,n  considered by Kontsevich in [46]. This is <lb/>why we expect that (4.33) holds. Let us now consider the limit of the spectral curve (3.13) <lb/>as t→∞. First we have <lb/> x = z + <lb/>1 <lb/> z <lb/> = 2 + <lb/>4 <lb/> t  2  − 1 <lb/> y = −z = −1 − <lb/> 2 <lb/> t − 1 <lb/> . <lb/> Ignoring the constant shifts of x and y, we obtain for a large t <lb/> (5.3) <lb/> x = <lb/> 4 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> y = − <lb/> 2 <lb/> t  . <lb/> Hence the spectral curve is given by the equation x = y  2  . We use t as the preferred <lb/>coordinate. <lb/>We now compare the Eynard-Orantin recursion with respect to this spectral curve and <lb/>the Witten-Kontsevich theory. We use (4.33) and define <lb/>(5.4) <lb/> W <lb/> K <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) = d  1  · · · d  n  F <lb/> K <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/>= <lb/>(−1)  n <lb/> 2  2g−2+n <lb/> d  1  +···+dn <lb/>=3g−3+n <lb/> τ  d  1  · · · τ  dn   g,n <lb/>n <lb/> j=1 <lb/> (2d  j  + 1)!! <lb/> t  j <lb/> 2 <lb/>  2d  j <lb/> d <lb/> t  j <lb/> 2 <lb/> = <lb/>(−1)  n <lb/> 16  2g−2+n  w <lb/> K <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) dt  1  · · · dt  n  , <lb/> where w  K <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) is the coefficient of the Eynard-Orantin differential form normalized <lb/>by the constant factor <lb/> (−1)  n <lb/> 16  2g−2+n  . Note that w  K <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) is a polynomial in t  2 <lb/> i  &apos;s with <lb/>positive rational coefficients for (g, n) in the stable range. For (g, n) = (0, 1) and (0, 2), we <lb/>have <lb/> τ  k   0,1  = δ  k+2,0 <lb/> (5.5) <lb/> τ  k  1  τ  k  2   0,2  = (−1) <lb/> k  1  , <lb/>k  1  + k  2  = −1. <lb/> (5.6) <lb/>Therefore, <lb/>(5.7) <lb/> W <lb/> K <lb/> 0,1  (t) = <lb/> −1 <lb/> 16  −1  τ  −2  (−3)!! t <lb/> −4  dt = <lb/>16 <lb/> t  4  dt = ydx, <lb/> in agreement with the spectral curve x = y  2  (5.3). Similarly, we have <lb/>(5.8) F <lb/> K <lb/> 0,2  (t  1  , t  2  ) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> d=0 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> d  (2d − 1)!!(−2d − 3)!! <lb/> t  1 <lb/> 2 <lb/>  2d+1  <lb/> t  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/>  −2d−1 <lb/></body>

			<page> 22 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> = − <lb/> ∞ <lb/> d=0 <lb/> 1 <lb/>2d + 1 <lb/> t  1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>  2d+1 <lb/> = log <lb/> 1 − <lb/> t  1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>log <lb/> 1 − <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>2 <lb/> , <lb/> and hence <lb/>(5.9) <lb/> W <lb/> K <lb/> 0,2  (t  1  , t  2  ) = <lb/> dt  1  · dt  2 <lb/> (t  1  − t  2  )  2  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> dx  1  · dx  2 <lb/> (x  1  − x  2  )  2  . <lb/> As a consequence, the recursion kernel is given by <lb/>(5.10) <lb/> K <lb/> K  (t, t  1  ) = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> t + t  1 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> t − t  1 <lb/> t  4 <lb/> 32 <lb/>1 <lb/> dt <lb/>dt  1  , <lb/> since <lb/> dx  1  ·dx  2 <lb/> (x  1  −x  2  )  2  does not contribute to the kernel. The Eynard-Orantin recursion for the <lb/>Euclidean volume then becomes <lb/>(5.11) W <lb/> K <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/>= − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ∞ <lb/> 1 <lb/> t + t  1 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> t − t  1 <lb/> t  4 <lb/> 64 <lb/>1 <lb/> dt <lb/>dt  1 <lb/> W <lb/> K <lb/>g−1,n+1  (t, −t, t  2  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/>+ <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> dt · dt  j <lb/> (t − t  j  )  2  W <lb/> K <lb/>g,n−1  (−t, t  2  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/> − <lb/> dt · dt  j <lb/> (t + t  j  )  2  W <lb/> K <lb/>g,n−1  (t, t  2  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/> + <lb/> stable <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> IJ={2,...,n} <lb/> W <lb/> K <lb/>g  1  ,|I|+1  (t, t  I  )W <lb/> K <lb/>g  2  ,|J|+1  (−t, t  J  ) <lb/> , <lb/> where the integral is taken with respect to a large negatively oriented circle γ  ∞  that encloses <lb/>any of ±t  1  , . . . , ±t  n  . This is the larger circle of Figure 4.1. Here again <lb/> dx  1  ·dx  2 <lb/> (x  1  −x  2  )  2  does not <lb/>contribute in the formula. Since the coefficients w  K <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) in the stable range are <lb/>polynomials, the poles of the integrand of (5.11) in the integration coutour are at t = ±t  i  &apos;s. <lb/>Therefore, we can perform the integral in terms of the residue calculus at poles t = ±t  i  . <lb/>First let us get rid of the factor 1/16  2g−2+n  from (5.11). Since the recursion is an induction <lb/>on 2g−2+n, we have an overall factor 16 adjustment on the right-hand side. The integration <lb/>contour is negatively oriented, so the residue calculation at t = ±t  i  receives universally the <lb/>negative sign. This sign is exactly cancelled by the choice of the sign of w  K <lb/>g,n  in (5.4). Thus <lb/>the result of residue evaluation of (5.11) is <lb/>(5.12) w <lb/> K <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> t <lb/> 4 <lb/>1  w <lb/> K <lb/>g−1,n+1  (t  1  , t  1  , t  2  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/>+ <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> t <lb/> 4 <lb/>1 <lb/>stable <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> IJ={2,...,n} <lb/> w <lb/> K <lb/>g  1  ,|I|+1  (t  1  , t  I  )w <lb/> K <lb/>g  2  ,|J|+1  (t  1  , t  J  ) <lb/>+ t <lb/> 4 <lb/>1 <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1  + t  2 <lb/> j <lb/> (t  2 <lb/>1  − t  2 <lb/> j  )  2  w <lb/> K <lb/>g,n−1  (t  1  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body> + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> ∂ <lb/> ∂t <lb/> t=t  j <lb/> + <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t <lb/> t=−t  j <lb/> 1 <lb/> t  2  − t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> t <lb/> 5  w <lb/> K <lb/>g,n−1  (t, t  2  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> t <lb/> 4 <lb/>1 <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> w <lb/> K <lb/>g−1,n+1  (t  1  , t  1  , t  2  , . . . , t  n  ) + <lb/> stable <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> IJ={2,...,n} <lb/> w <lb/> K <lb/>g  1  ,|I|+1  (t  1  , t  I  )w <lb/> K <lb/>g  2  ,|J|+1  (t  1  , t  J  ) <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> + <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  j <lb/> t  j <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1  − t  2 <lb/> j <lb/> t <lb/> 4 <lb/>1  w <lb/> K <lb/>g,n−1  (t  [n]\{j}  ) − t <lb/> 4 <lb/> j  w <lb/> K <lb/>g,n−1  (t  [n]\{1}  ) <lb/> . <lb/> This is the same as [10, Theorem 5.2]. <lb/>Let us adopt the normalized notation <lb/>(5.13) <lb/> σ  d  1  · · · σ  dn   g,n  = τ  d  1  · · · τ  dn   g,n <lb/>n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (2d  i  + 1)!! <lb/>to make the formula shorter. Then <lb/>(5.14) <lb/> w <lb/> K <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) = <lb/> d  1  ,...,dn <lb/> σ  d  1  · · · σ  dn   g,n <lb/>n <lb/> j=1 <lb/> t <lb/> 2d  j <lb/> j  . <lb/> The DVV formula [15] for the Virasoro constraint condition on the ψ-class intersection <lb/>numbers on M  g,n  reads <lb/>(5.15) σ  k <lb/>n <lb/> i=2 <lb/> σ  d  i   g,n  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> a+b=k−2 <lb/> σ  a  σ  b <lb/>n <lb/> i=2 <lb/> σ  d  i   g−1,n+1 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> a+b=k−2 <lb/> stable <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> IJ={2,...,n} <lb/> σ  a <lb/> i∈I <lb/> σ  d  i   g  1  ,|I|+1  · σ  b <lb/> j∈J <lb/> σ  d  j   g  2  ,|J|+1 <lb/> + <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> (2d  j  + 1)σ  k+d  j  −1 <lb/> i =1,j <lb/> σ  d  i   g,n−1  . <lb/> We thus recover the discovery of [25]: <lb/> Theorem 5.1. The Eynard-Orantin recursion formula for the spectral curve x = y  2  is the <lb/>Dijkgraaf-Verlinde-Verlinde formula [15] for the intersection numbers τ  d  1  · · · τ  dn   g,n  on the <lb/>moduli space M  g,n  of pointed stable curves. <lb/>Proof. We extract the coefficient of <lb/>(5.16) <lb/> t <lb/> 2k <lb/>1 <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> t <lb/> 2d  j <lb/> j <lb/> in (5.12) and compare the result with (5.15). It is obvious that the fifth line of (5.12) <lb/>produces the first and second lines of (5.15). <lb/>To compare the last lines of (5.12) and (5.15), we consider the case |t  j  | &lt; |t  1  | for all j ≥ 2 <lb/>in (5.12). We then have the expansion <lb/>1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1  − t  2 <lb/> j <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 − <lb/> t  2 <lb/> j <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> ∞ <lb/> m=0 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> j <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/>  m <lb/> . <lb/></body>

			<page> 24 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> The (5.16)-term of the last line of (5.12) has two contributions. The first one comes from <lb/> ∂ <lb/> ∂t  j <lb/> t <lb/> 2 <lb/> 1  t  j <lb/> ∞ <lb/> m=0 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> j <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/>  m <lb/> w <lb/> K <lb/>g,n−1  (t  1  , t  2  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/> . <lb/> Since w  K <lb/>g,n−1  (t  1  , t  2  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) does not contain t  j  , we set m = d  j  to produce the right <lb/>power 2d  j  of t  j  . The power of t  1  has to be 2k. Thus from w  K <lb/>g,n−1  we take the term of <lb/> t <lb/> 2k+2d  j  −2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> , whose coefficient is σ  k+d  j  −1 <lb/> i =1,j  σ  d  i  . The total contribution from the first <lb/>kind comes from the differentiation, which gives 2m + 1 = 2d  j  + 1. <lb/>The second possible contribution for the (5.16)-term may come from <lb/> − <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  j <lb/> t  5 <lb/> j <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> ∞ <lb/> m=0 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> j <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/>  m <lb/> w <lb/> K <lb/>g,n−1  (t  2  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/> . <lb/> However, this term does not produce t  2k <lb/>1  , and hence does not contribute to the (5.16)-term. <lb/>This completes the proof of Theorem 5.1. <lb/> 6. Single Hurwitz numbers <lb/> What is the mirror dual of the number of trees? The answer we wish to present in this <lb/>section is that it is the Lambert curve. This analytic curve serves as the spectral curve for the <lb/>Hurwitz counting problem, and comes up from the the unstable geometries (g, n) = (0, 1) <lb/>and (0, 2) via Laplace transform. <lb/>A Hurwitz cover is a holomorphic mapping f : C → P  1  from a connected nonsingu-<lb/>lar projective algebraic curve C of genus g to the projective line P  1  with only simple <lb/>ramifications except for ∞ ∈ P  1  . Such a cover is further refined by specifying its pro-<lb/>file, which is a partition µ = (µ  1  ≥ µ  2  ≥ · · · ≥ µ  n  &gt; 0) of the degree of the covering <lb/> d = |µ| = µ  1  + · · · + µ  n  . The length (µ) = n of this partition is the number of points in the <lb/>inverse image f  −1  (∞) = {p  1  , . . . , p  n  } of ∞. Each part µ  i  gives a local description of the <lb/>map f , which is given by u −→ u  −µ  i  in terms of a local coordinate u of C around p  i  . The <lb/>number h  g,µ  of the topological types of Hurwitz covers of a given genus g and a profile µ, <lb/> counted with the weight factor 1/|Autf |, is the single Hurwitz number we shall deal with <lb/>in this section. <lb/>The deformations of a Hurwitz cover f are obtained by moving the branch points (i.e., <lb/>the image of the ramification points) on P  1  \ {∞}. Thus h  g,µ  counts the number of Hurwitz <lb/>covers with prescribed (i.e., fixed) and labeled branch points. On the other hand, the <lb/>preimages of ∞ on C are labeled only by the parts of µ. Therefore, a more natural count <lb/>of Hurwitz cover is <lb/>(6.1) <lb/> H  g  (µ) = <lb/> |Aut(µ)| <lb/> (2g − 2 + n + |µ|)! <lb/>· h  g,µ  . <lb/> Here, <lb/>(6.2) <lb/> r = r(g, µ) <lb/> def <lb/> = 2g − 2 + n + |µ| <lb/> is the number of simple ramification points of f by the Riemann-Hurwitz formula, and <lb/>Aut(µ) is the group of permutations of equal parts of the partition µ. <lb/> One reason that explains why single Hurwitz numbers are interesting is a remarkable <lb/>formula due to Ekedahl, Lando, Shapiro and Vainshtein [20, 33, 48, 65] that relates Hurwitz <lb/>numbers and Gromov-Witten invariants. For genus g ≥ 0 and a partition µ of length <lb/> (µ) = n subject to the stability condition 2g − 2 + n &gt; 0, the ELSV formula states that <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body> (6.3) H  g  (µ) = <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> µ <lb/> µ  i <lb/> i <lb/> µ  i  ! <lb/> Mg,n <lb/> Λ  ∨ <lb/> g  (1) <lb/>  n <lb/>i=1 <lb/> 1 − µ  i  ψ  i <lb/> = <lb/> g <lb/> j=0 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> j <lb/> k  1  ,...,kn≥0 <lb/> τ  k  1  · · · τ  kn  c  j  (E) <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> µ <lb/> µ  i  +k  i <lb/> i <lb/> µ  i  ! <lb/> , <lb/> where M  g,n  is the Deligne-Mumford moduli stack of stable algebraic curves of genus g with <lb/> n distinct smooth marked points, Λ  ∨ <lb/> g  (1) = 1−c  1  (E)+· · ·+(−1)  g  c  g  (E) is the alternating sum <lb/>of the Chern classes of the Hodge bundle E on M  g,n  , ψ  i  is the i-th tautological cotangent <lb/>class, and <lb/>(6.4) <lb/> τ  k  1  · · · τ  kn  c  j  (E) = <lb/> Mg,n <lb/> ψ <lb/> k  1 <lb/> 1  · · · ψ <lb/> kn <lb/> c  j  (E) <lb/>is the linear Hodge integral, which is 0 unless k  1  + · · · + k  n  + j = 3g − 3 + n. <lb/> The Deligne-Mumford stack M  g,n  is defined as the moduli space of stable curves satisfying <lb/>the stability condition 2 − 2g − n &lt; 0. However, single Hurwitz numbers are well defined <lb/>for unstable geometries (g, n) = (0, 1) and (0, 2), and their values are <lb/>(6.5) <lb/> H  0  ((d)) = <lb/> d  d−3 <lb/> (d − 1)! <lb/>= <lb/> d  d−2 <lb/> d! <lb/> and <lb/> H  0  ((µ  1  , µ  2  )) = <lb/>1 <lb/> µ  1  + µ  2 <lb/> · <lb/> µ <lb/> µ  1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> µ  1  ! <lb/> · <lb/> µ <lb/> µ  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> µ  2  ! <lb/> . <lb/> The ELSV formula remains valid for unstable cases by defining <lb/> M  0,1 <lb/> Λ  ∨ <lb/> 0  (1) <lb/>1 − dψ <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/> d  2  , <lb/> (6.6) <lb/> M  0,2 <lb/> Λ  ∨ <lb/> 0  (1) <lb/>(1 − µ  1  ψ  1  )(1 − µ  2  ψ  2  ) <lb/>= <lb/>1 <lb/> µ  1  + µ  2 <lb/> . <lb/> (6.7) <lb/>Let us examine the (g, n) = (0, 1) case. We wish to count the number of Hurwitz covers <lb/> f : P  1  −→P  1  of degree d with profile µ = (d). If d = 2, then f (u) = u  2  is the only map, <lb/>since r = 1 and the two ramification points can be placed at u = 0 and u = ∞. The <lb/>automorphism of this map is Z/2Z. We now consider the case when d ≥ 3. First we label <lb/>all branch points. One is ∞, so let us place all others, the images of simple ramification <lb/>points, at the r-th roots of unity. Here r = d − 1. We label these points with indices <lb/>[r] = {1, 2, . . . , r}. Connect each r-th root of unity with the origin by a straight line (see <lb/>Figure 6.1). Let  *  denote this star-like shape, which has one vertex at the center and r <lb/> half-edges. Then the inverse image f  −1  ( * ) is a tree-like shape with d vertices and rd half-<lb/>edges. Here we call each inverse image of 0 a vertex of f  −1  ( * ). If f is simply ramified at p, <lb/> then two half-edges are connected at p and form a real edge that is incident to two vertices. <lb/>Since f (p) is one of the r-th root of unity, we give the same label to p. Thus all simple <lb/>ramification points are labeled with the index set [r]. Now we remove all half-edges from <lb/> f  −1  ( * ) that are not made into an edge, and denote it by T . It is a tree on P  1  that has d <lb/> vertices and r = d − 1 edges. Note that except for the case d = 2, the edge labeling gives a <lb/>labeling of vertices. For example, if a vertex x is incident to edges i  1  &lt; i  2  &lt; · · · &lt; i  k  , then <lb/> x is labeled by i  1  i  2  · · · i  k  . <lb/>Conversely, suppose we are given a tree with d labeled vertices by the index set [d] = <lb/> {1, 2, . . . , d} and r = d − 1 edges. At each vertex we can give a cyclic order to incident edges <lb/>by aligning them in the increasing order of the labels of the other ends of the edges. Thus <lb/>the tree becomes a ribbon graph (see Section 3), and hence it can be placed on P  1  . Then <lb/>by choosing the midpoint of each edge as a simple ramification point and each vertex as a <lb/></body>

			<page> 26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> f <lb/> Figure 6.1. Counting the genus 0 single Hurwitz numbers with the total ramifi-<lb/>cation at ∞. <lb/> zero of f , we can construct a Hurwitz cover. Recall that the number of trees with d labeled <lb/>vertices is d  d−2  . Therefore, <lb/> H  0  ((d)) = <lb/> d  d−2 <lb/> d! <lb/> is the number of trees with d unlabeled vertices. <lb/>Fix an n ≥ 1, and consider a partition µ of length n as an n-dimensional vector <lb/> µ = (µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  ) ∈ Z <lb/> n <lb/> + <lb/> consisting of positive integers. The Laplace transform of H  g  (µ) as a function in µ, <lb/> (6.8) <lb/> H  g,n  (w  1  , . . . , w  n  ) = <lb/> µ∈Z  n <lb/> + <lb/> H  g  (µ)e <lb/> −(µ  1  (w  1  +1)+···+µn(wn+1))  , <lb/> is the function we wish to compute. Note that the automorphism group Aut(µ) acts trivially <lb/>on the function e  −(µ  1  (w  1  +1)+···+µn(wn+1))  , which explains its appearance in (6.1). The reason <lb/>for shifting the variables w  i  −→ w  i  + 1 is due to the asymptotic behavior <lb/> µ  µ+k <lb/> µ! <lb/>e <lb/> −µ  ∼ <lb/> 1 <lb/> √ <lb/> 2π <lb/> µ <lb/> k− <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> as µ approaches to ∞. This asymptotics also suggests that the holomorphic function <lb/> H  g,n  (w  1  , . . . , w  n  ) is actually defined on a double-sheeted overing on the w  i  -plane, since <lb/> √ w  i  behaves better as a holomorphic coordinate. <lb/>Following [24, 57], we introduce a series of polynomials <lb/>  n  (t) of degree 2n + 1 in t for <lb/> n ≥ 0 by the recursion formula <lb/>(6.9) <lb/>ˆ <lb/> ξ  n  (t) = t <lb/> 2  (t − 1) <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/>  n−1  (t) <lb/>with the initial condition <lb/>  0  (t) = t − 1. This differential operator appears in [31]. The <lb/>functions <lb/>  −1  (t) and <lb/>  0  (t) also appear as the two fundamental functions in [84] that generate <lb/>his algebra A. These polynomials are introduced to make the computation of the Laplace <lb/>transform (6.8) easier. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body> Proposition 6.1 ([12, 24]). Let us introduce new coordinates <lb/> (6.10) <lb/> x = e <lb/> −w  , <lb/>z = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> µ=1 <lb/> µ  µ−1 <lb/> µ! <lb/>e <lb/> −µ  x <lb/> µ  , <lb/>t − 1 = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> µ=1 <lb/> µ  µ <lb/> µ! <lb/>e <lb/> −µ  x <lb/> µ  . <lb/> Then the inverse function of z = z(x) is given by <lb/> (6.11) <lb/> x = ze <lb/> 1−z  , <lb/> and the variables z and t are related by <lb/> (6.12) <lb/> z = <lb/> t − 1 <lb/> t <lb/>. <lb/> Moreover, we have <lb/> (6.13) <lb/>ˆ <lb/> ξ  n  (t) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> µ=1 <lb/> µ  µ+n <lb/> µ! <lb/>e <lb/> −µ(w+1)  = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> µ=1 <lb/> µ  µ+n <lb/> µ! <lb/>e <lb/> −µ  x <lb/> µ <lb/> for n ≥ 0. <lb/> Proof. The infinite series (6.13) has the radius of convergence 1, and for |x| &lt; 1, we can <lb/>apply the Lagrange inversion formula to obtain (6.11). Since the application of <lb/> − <lb/> d <lb/>dw <lb/> = x <lb/>d <lb/>dx <lb/> = t <lb/> 2  (t − 1) <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/>n-times to <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> µ=1 <lb/>µ  µ <lb/> µ!  e  −µ(w+1)  produces <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> µ=1 <lb/>µ  µ+n <lb/> µ!  e  −µ(w+1)  , we obtain (6.9). If we extend <lb/>(6.13) formally to n = −1, then we have z = ˆ <lb/> ξ  −1  (t). To obtain the expression of z as a <lb/>function of t, we need to solve the differential equation <lb/> t <lb/> 2  (t − 1) <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> · z = t − 1. <lb/>Its solution is z = c − <lb/> 1 <lb/> t  . Since x = 0 ⇐⇒ z = 0 and x = 0 =⇒ t = 1, we conclude that the <lb/>constant of integration is c = 1. Thus z = 1 − 1/t. <lb/> Remark 6.2. The relation between our z as a function in x and the classical Lambert <lb/>W-function (see for example, [12]) is <lb/> z(x) = −W (−x/e). <lb/>Because of the ELSV formula (6.1), the Laplace transform of H  g  (µ) becomes a polynomial <lb/>in t  i  , . . . , t  n  for (g, n) in the stable range. The result is <lb/>(6.14) F <lb/> H <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) = H  g,n  (w(t  1  ), . . . , w(t  n  )) <lb/>= <lb/> µ∈Z  n <lb/> + <lb/> H  g  (µ)e <lb/> −(µ  1  (w  1  +1)+···+µn(wn+1)) <lb/> = <lb/> µ∈Z  n <lb/> + <lb/> k  1  +···+kn≤3g−3+n <lb/> τ  k  1  · · · τ  kn  Λ <lb/> ∨ <lb/> g  (1) <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> µ <lb/> µ  i  +k  i <lb/> i <lb/> µ  i  ! <lb/> e <lb/> −(µ  1  (w  1  +1)+···+µn(wn+1)) <lb/> = <lb/> k  1  +···+kn≤3g−3+n <lb/> τ  k  1  · · · τ  kn  Λ <lb/> ∨ <lb/> g  (1) <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/>  k  i  (t  i  ). <lb/>The Laplace transform (6.14) is no longer a polynomial for the unstable geometries (g, n) = <lb/>(0, 1) and (0, 2). Wel use (6.5) to calculate F  H <lb/> 0,1  and F  H <lb/> 0,2  . <lb/></body>

			<page> 28 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> Theorem 6.3. The Laplace transform of the unstable cases (g, n) = (0, 1) and (0, 2) are <lb/>given by <lb/> (6.15) <lb/> F <lb/> H <lb/> 0,1  (t) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 − <lb/> 1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> and <lb/> (6.16) <lb/> F <lb/> H <lb/> 0,2  (t  1  , t  2  ) = log <lb/> z  1  − z  2 <lb/> x  1  − x  2 <lb/> − (z  1  + z  2  ) + 1, <lb/> where t  i  , x  i  , z  i  are related by (6.11) and (6.12). <lb/>Proof. The (0, 1) case is a straightforward computation. <lb/> F <lb/> H <lb/> 0,1  (t) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=d <lb/> H  0  ((d)) e <lb/> −d  x <lb/> d  = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> d=1 <lb/> d  d−2 <lb/> d! <lb/>e <lb/> −d  x <lb/> d  = ˆ <lb/> ξ  −2  (t). <lb/>This is a solution to the differential equation <lb/> t <lb/> 2  (t − 1) <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/>  −2  (t) = ˆ <lb/> ξ  −1  (t) = z = <lb/> t − 1 <lb/> t <lb/>. <lb/> Therefore, ˆ <lb/> ξ  −2  (t) = c − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  2  for a constant of integration c. Here again we note <lb/> t = 1 =⇒ z = 0 =⇒ x = 0 =⇒ <lb/>  −2  (t) = 0. <lb/>This determines that c = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  . Thus we have established (6.15). <lb/>Since <lb/> F <lb/> H <lb/> 0,2  (t  1  , t  2  ) = <lb/> µ  1  ,µ  2  ≥1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> µ  1  + µ  2 <lb/> · <lb/> µ <lb/> µ  1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> µ  1  ! <lb/> e <lb/> −µ  1  · <lb/> µ <lb/> µ  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> µ  2  ! <lb/> e <lb/> −µ  2  · x <lb/> µ  1 <lb/> 1  x <lb/> µ  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> and since z = ˆ <lb/> ξ  −1  (t), (6.16) is equivalent to <lb/>(6.17) <lb/> µ  1  ,µ  2  ≥0 <lb/> (µ  1  ,µ  2  ) =(0,0) <lb/> 1 <lb/> µ  1  + µ  2 <lb/> · <lb/> µ <lb/> µ  1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> µ  1  ! <lb/> e <lb/> −µ  1  · <lb/> µ <lb/> µ  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> µ  2  ! <lb/> e <lb/> −µ  2  ·x <lb/> µ  1 <lb/> 1  x <lb/> µ  2 <lb/> 2  = log <lb/> e <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=1 <lb/> k  k−1 <lb/> k! <lb/>e <lb/> −k  · <lb/> x  k <lb/> 1  − x  k <lb/> 2 <lb/> x  1  − x  2 <lb/> , <lb/> where |x  1  | &lt; 1, |x  2  | &lt; 1, and 0 &lt; |x  1  − x  2  | &lt; 1 so that the formula is an equation of <lb/>holomorphic functions in x  1  and x  2  . Define <lb/> φ(x  1  , x  2  ) <lb/> def <lb/> = <lb/> µ  1  ,µ  2  ≥0 <lb/> (µ  1  ,µ  2  ) =(0,0) <lb/> 1 <lb/> µ  1  + µ  2 <lb/> · <lb/> µ <lb/> µ  1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> µ  1  ! <lb/> e <lb/> −µ  1  · <lb/> µ <lb/> µ  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> µ  2  ! <lb/> e <lb/> −µ  2  · x <lb/> µ  1 <lb/> 1  x <lb/> µ  2 <lb/> 2  − log <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> k=1 <lb/> k  k−1 <lb/> k! <lb/>e <lb/> 1−k  · <lb/> x  k <lb/> 1  − x  k <lb/> 2 <lb/> x  1  − x  2 <lb/> . <lb/> Then <lb/> φ(x, 0) = <lb/> µ  1  ≥1 <lb/> µ <lb/> µ  1  −1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> µ  1  ! <lb/> e <lb/> −µ  1  x <lb/> µ  1  − log <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> k=1 <lb/> k  k−1 <lb/> k! <lb/>e <lb/> −k  · x <lb/> k−1 <lb/> − 1 <lb/>= ˆ <lb/> ξ  −1  (t) − log <lb/>  −1  (t) <lb/> x <lb/> − 1 = 1 − <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/> − log <lb/> 1 − <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/> + log x − 1 <lb/>= − <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/> − log <lb/> 1 − <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/> − w = 0 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body> because <lb/> x = e <lb/> −w  = ze <lb/> 1−z  = <lb/> 1 − <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/> e <lb/> 1 <lb/> t  . <lb/> Here t is restricted on the domain Re(t) &gt; 1. Since <lb/> x  1 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂x  1 <lb/> log <lb/> e <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=1 <lb/> k  k−1 <lb/> k! <lb/>e <lb/> −k  · <lb/> x  k <lb/> 1  − x  k <lb/> 2 <lb/> x  1  − x  2 <lb/> = t <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (t  1  − 1) <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  1 <lb/> log <lb/>  −1  (t  1  ) − ˆ <lb/> ξ  −1  (t  2  ) <lb/> − x  1 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂x  1 <lb/> log(x  1  − x  2  ) <lb/>= t <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  (t  1  − 1) <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  1 <lb/> log <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/> t  1 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> − <lb/> x  1 <lb/> x  1  − x  2 <lb/> = <lb/> t  1  t  2  (t  1  − 1) <lb/> t  1  − t  2 <lb/> − <lb/> x  1 <lb/> x  1  − x  2 <lb/> , <lb/> we have <lb/> x  1 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂x  1 <lb/> + x  2 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂x  2 <lb/> log <lb/> e <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=1 <lb/> k  k−1 <lb/> k! <lb/>e <lb/> −k  · <lb/> x  k <lb/> 1  − x  k <lb/> 2 <lb/> x  1  − x  2 <lb/> = <lb/> t  1  t  2  (t  1  − 1) − t  1  t  2  (t  2  − 1) <lb/> t  1  − t  2 <lb/> − <lb/> x  1  − x  2 <lb/> x  1  − x  2 <lb/> = t  1  t  2  − 1 = ˆ <lb/> ξ  0  (t  1  ) ˆ <lb/> ξ  0  (t  2  ) + ˆ <lb/> ξ  0  (t  1  ) + ˆ <lb/> ξ  0  (t  2  ). <lb/>On the other hand, we also have <lb/> x  1 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂x  1 <lb/> + x  2 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂x  2 <lb/> µ  1  ,µ  2  ≥0 <lb/> (µ  1  ,µ  2  ) =(0,0) <lb/> 1 <lb/> µ  1  + µ  2 <lb/> · <lb/> µ <lb/> µ  1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> µ  1  ! <lb/> e <lb/> −µ  1  · <lb/> µ <lb/> µ  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> µ  2  ! <lb/> e <lb/> −µ  2  · x <lb/> µ  1 <lb/> 1  x <lb/> µ  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> = <lb/> µ  1  ,µ  2  ≥0 <lb/> (µ  1  ,µ  2  ) =(0,0) <lb/> µ  1  + µ  2 <lb/> µ  1  + µ  2 <lb/> · <lb/> µ <lb/> µ  1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> µ  1  ! <lb/> e <lb/> −µ  1  · <lb/> µ <lb/> µ  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> µ  2  ! <lb/> e <lb/> −µ  2  · x <lb/> µ  1 <lb/> 1  x <lb/> µ  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> = ˆ <lb/> ξ  0  (t  1  ) ˆ <lb/> ξ  0  (t  2  ) + ˆ <lb/> ξ  0  (t  1  ) + ˆ <lb/> ξ  0  (t  2  ). <lb/>Therefore, <lb/>(6.18) <lb/> x  1 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂x  1 <lb/> + x  2 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂x  2 <lb/> φ(x  1  , x  2  ) = 0. <lb/>Note that φ(x  1  , x  2  ) is a holomorphic function in x  1  and x  2  . Therefore, it has a series <lb/>expansion in homogeneous polynomials around (0, 0). Since a homogeneous polynomial in <lb/> x  1  and x  2  of degree n is an eigenvector of the differential operator x  1 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂x  1 <lb/> + x  2 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂x  2 <lb/> belonging <lb/>to the eigenvalue n, the only holomorphic solution to the Euler differential equation (6.18) <lb/>is a constant. But since φ(x  1  , 0) = 0, we conclude that φ(x  1  , x  2  ) = 0. This completes the <lb/>proof of (6.17), and hence the proposition. <lb/> Definition 6.4. We define the symmetric differential forms for all g ≥ 0 and n &gt; 0 by <lb/>(6.19) <lb/> W <lb/> H <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) = d  1  · · · d  n  F <lb/> H <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ), <lb/>and call them the Hurwitz differential forms. <lb/></body>

			<page> 30 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> The unstable cases are given by <lb/>(6.20) <lb/> W <lb/> H <lb/> 0,1  (t  1  ) = d  1  F <lb/> H <lb/> 0,1  (t  1  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/> t  3 <lb/>1 <lb/> dt  1  = <lb/> z <lb/>x <lb/>dx, <lb/> and <lb/>(6.21) W <lb/> H <lb/> 0,2  (t  1  , t  2  ) = d  1  d  2  F <lb/> H <lb/> 0,2  (t  1  , t  2  ) = d  1  d  2  [log (z  1  − z  2  ) − log(x  1  − x  2  )] <lb/>= d  1  d  2 <lb/> log <lb/> 1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/> t  1 <lb/> − log(x  1  − x  2  ) <lb/> = d  1  d  2  [log (t  1  − t  2  ) − log(x  1  − x  2  )] <lb/>= <lb/> dt  1  · dt  2 <lb/> (t  1  − t  2  )  2  − <lb/> dx  1  · dx  2 <lb/> (x  1  − x  2  )  2  . <lb/> We note that all quantities are expressible in terms of z, or equivalently, in t. Now Defini-<lb/>tion 2.1 tells us that the spectral curve Σ of the single Hurwitz number is <lb/>(6.22) <lb/> x = ze  1−z <lb/> y = <lb/> z <lb/>x  = e  z−1  . <lb/> The Lambert curve Σ defined by x = ze  1−z  , which is obtained by the Laplace transform <lb/>of the number of trees, is an analytic curve and its x-projection has a simple ramification <lb/>point at z = 1, since <lb/> dx = (1 − z)e <lb/> 1−z  dz. <lb/> The t-coordinate brings this ramification point to t = ∞. Let ¯ <lb/> z (resp. ¯ <lb/> t) denote the unique <lb/>local Galois conjugate of z (reps. t). We also use <lb/>(6.23) <lb/>¯ <lb/> t = s(t), <lb/> which is defined by the functional equation <lb/>(6.24) <lb/> 1 − <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/> e <lb/> 1 <lb/> t  = <lb/> 1 − <lb/> 1 <lb/> s(t) <lb/> e <lb/> 1 <lb/> s(t)  . <lb/> Although the Galois conjugate is only locally defined near the branched point t = ∞, we <lb/>consider s(t) as a global holomorphic function via analytic continuation. For Re(t) &gt; 1, <lb/>(6.24) implies <lb/> w(t) = − log x = − <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/> − <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> n <lb/> 1 <lb/> t  n <lb/> = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> t  n  . <lb/> When considered as a functional equation, (6.24) has exactly two solutions: t and <lb/>(6.25) <lb/> s(t) = −t + <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>+ <lb/>4 <lb/>135 <lb/> t <lb/> −2  + <lb/>8 <lb/>405 <lb/> t <lb/> −3  + <lb/>8 <lb/>567 <lb/> t <lb/> −4  + · · · . <lb/> This is the deck-transformation of the projection π : Σ → C near t = ∞ and satisfies the <lb/>involution equation s <lb/> s(t) <lb/> = t. It is analytic on C \ [0, 1] and has logarithmic singularities <lb/>at 0 and 1. <lb/>Let us calculate the recursion kernel. Since <lb/> dx <lb/>x <lb/> = <lb/>1 − z <lb/>z <lb/>dz = <lb/> dt <lb/>t  2  (t − 1) <lb/>= <lb/> s   (t)dt <lb/> s(t)  2  (s(t) − 1) <lb/> , <lb/> we have <lb/>(6.26) K <lb/> H  (t, t  1  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>  s(t) <lb/>t <lb/> W  H <lb/> 0,2  (·, t  1  ) <lb/> W  0,1  (s(t)) − W  0,1  (t) <lb/>= <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> t − t  1 <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/> s(t) − t  1 <lb/> t  2  (t − 1) <lb/> 1 <lb/> t  − <lb/> 1 <lb/> s(t) <lb/> · <lb/> 1 <lb/> dt <lb/> · dt  1 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body> = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> t − t  1 <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/> s(t) − t  1 <lb/> ts(t) <lb/>s(t) − t <lb/> · <lb/> t  2  (t − 1) <lb/> dt <lb/> · dt  1  . <lb/> Theorem 6.5 ([24, 57]). The Hurwitz differential forms (6.19) for 2g − 2 + n &gt; 0 satisfy <lb/>the Eynard-Orantin recursion: <lb/> (6.27) W <lb/> H <lb/> g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ∞ <lb/> K <lb/> H  (t, t  1  ) <lb/> W <lb/> H <lb/>g−1,n+1  (t, s(t), t  2  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/>+ <lb/> No (0, 1)-terms <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> IJ={2,...,n} <lb/> W <lb/> H <lb/>g  1  ,|I|+1  (t, t  I  )W <lb/> H <lb/>g  2  ,|J|+1  (s(t), t  J  ) <lb/> , <lb/> where γ  ∞  is a negatively oriented circle around ∞ whose radius is larger than any of |t  j  |&apos;s <lb/> and |s(t  j  )|&apos;s. <lb/> Remark 6.6. The recursion formula (6.27) was first conjectured by Bouchard and Mariño <lb/>in [7]. Its proofs appear in [4, 24, 57]. The method of [4] is to use a matrix integral <lb/>expression of the single Hurwitz numbers. The idea of [24, 57] is that the Laplace transform <lb/>of the cut-and-join equation of [29, 77] is the Eynard-Orantin recursion. The cut-and-join <lb/>equation takes the following form: <lb/>(6.28) r(g, µ)H  g  (µ) = <lb/> i&lt;j <lb/> (µ  i  + µ  j  )H  g <lb/> µ( ˆ i, ˆ j), µ  i  + µ  j <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> α+β=µ  i <lb/> αβ <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> H  g−1 <lb/> µ( ˆ i), α, β <lb/> + <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> ν  1  ν  2  =µ( ˆ i) <lb/> H  g  1  (ν  1  , α)H  g  2  (ν  2  , β) <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> . <lb/> Here µ is a partition of length n, and µ( ˆ i) and µ( ˆ i, ˆ j) indicate the partition obtained by <lb/>deleting parts of µ. <lb/> Remark 6.7. As we have seen above, Hurwitz numbers in (6.5) determine the shape of the <lb/>recursion formula (6.27). Since the recursion gives the Hurwitz numbers for all (g, n), we <lb/>have thus established that unstable (g, n) = (0, 1) and (0, 2) Hurwitz numbers determine <lb/>all other single Hurwitz numbers. <lb/>It is important to check if the formulas (2.4) and (2.6) agree with the geometry. From <lb/>the definition (6.14) we calculate <lb/> F <lb/> H <lb/> 0,3  (t  1  , t  2  , t  3  ) = τ  0  τ  0  τ  0   0,3 <lb/> ˆ <lb/> ξ  0  (t  1  ) ˆ <lb/> ξ  0  (t  2  ) ˆ <lb/> ξ  0  (t  3  ) = (t  1  − 1)(t  2  − 1)(t  3  − 1), <lb/>which yields <lb/>(6.29) <lb/> W <lb/> H <lb/> 0,3  (t  1  , t  2  , t  3  ) = dt  1  dt  2  dt  3  . <lb/> Since <lb/> dx(z) · dy(z) = (1 − z)dz · dz = <lb/> dt · dt <lb/>t  5 <lb/> from (6.22) and (6.11), the general formula (2.6) yields <lb/> W <lb/> H <lb/> 0,3  (t  1  , t  2  , t  3  ) = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ∞ <lb/> W  H <lb/> 0,2  (t, t  1  )W  H <lb/> 0,2  (t, t  2  )W  H <lb/> 0,2  (t, t  3  ) <lb/> dx(t) · dy(t) <lb/></body>

			<page> 32 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ∞ <lb/> t  5 <lb/> (t − t  1  )  2  (t − t  2  )  2  (t − t  3  )  2  dt <lb/> dt  1  dt  2  dt  3  = dt  1  dt  2  dt  3  , <lb/> in agreement with geometry. Here we calculate the residue at t = ∞. Although <lb/> W <lb/> H <lb/> 0,2  (t, t  i  ) = <lb/> dt · dt  i <lb/> (t − t  i  )  2  − <lb/> dx · dx  i <lb/> (x − x  i  )  2  , <lb/> the second term does not contribute to the integral. This is because as t→∞, we have x→1, <lb/> and dx · dx  i  /(x − x  i  )  2  has no pole at x = 1. <lb/>Similarly, <lb/> F <lb/> H <lb/> 1,1  (t  1  ) = τ  1   1,1 <lb/> ˆ <lb/> ξ  1  (t  1  ) − τ  0  λ  1   1,1 <lb/> ˆ <lb/> ξ  0  (t  1  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>24 <lb/>(t <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  − 1)(t  1  − 1), <lb/>and thus we have <lb/>(6.30) <lb/> W <lb/> H <lb/> 1,1  (t  1  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>24 <lb/>(t  1  − 1)(3t  1  + 1)dt  1  . <lb/> On the other hand, the general formula (2.4) gives <lb/> W <lb/> H <lb/> 1,1  (t  1  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ∞ <lb/> K <lb/> H  (t, t  1  ) <lb/> W <lb/> H <lb/> 0,2  (u, v) + <lb/> dx(u) · dx(v) <lb/> (x(u) − x(v))  2 <lb/> u=t <lb/>v=s(t) <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ∞ <lb/> K <lb/> H  (t, t  1  ) <lb/> dt · s   (t)dt <lb/>(t − s(t))  2 <lb/> = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ∞ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> t − t  1 <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/> s(t) − t  1 <lb/> ts(t) <lb/>s(t) − t <lb/>t <lb/> 2  (t − 1) <lb/> s   (t)dt <lb/>(t − s(t))  2 <lb/> dt  1 <lb/> = <lb/> t  1  s(t  1  ) <lb/>(t  1  − s(t  1  ))  3  s(t  1  ) <lb/> 2  (s(t  1  ) − 1) dt  1 <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ  [0,1] <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> t − t  1 <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/> s(t) − t  1 <lb/> ts(t) <lb/>s(t) − t <lb/>t <lb/> 2  (t − 1) <lb/> s   (t)dt <lb/>(t − s(t))  2 <lb/> dt  1  , <lb/> where γ  [0,1]  is a contour circling around the slit [0, 1] in the t-plane in the positive direction. <lb/> -2 <lb/> -1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>-2 <lb/>-1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> Figure 6.2. The contours of integration. The outer loop γ  ∞  is the circle of a large <lb/>radius oriented clock wise, and γ  [0,1]  is the thin loop surrounding the closed interval <lb/>[0, 1] in the positive direction. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body> Note that the integrand of the last integral is a holomorphic function in t on γ  [0,1]  , hence <lb/>it has a finite value. It is also clear that as t  1  →∞, this integral tends to 0, because γ  [0,1]  is <lb/>a compact space. Therefore, we conclude that <lb/> W <lb/> H <lb/> 1,1  (t  1  ) = <lb/> t  1  s(t  1  ) <lb/>(t  1  − s(t  1  ))  3  s(t  1  ) <lb/> 2  (s(t  1  ) − 1) dt  1  + O(1/t  1  ) <lb/>= <lb/> 1 <lb/>8 <lb/> t <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>12 <lb/> t  1  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>24 <lb/> dt  1  + O(1/t  1  ), <lb/>since s(t) = −t + 2/3 + O(1/t  2  ). It agrees with (6.30) because of the following <lb/> Lemma 6.8. A solution to the topological recursion (6.27) is a polynomial in t  1  . <lb/>Proof. The t  1  -dependence of W  H <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) only comes from the factor <lb/> 1 <lb/> t − t  1 <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/> s(t) − t  1 <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/> t <lb/> + + <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  2  + <lb/> t <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  − <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/> t  1  + <lb/>2 <lb/>9 <lb/> 1 <lb/> t  3  + <lb/> t <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  − <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/> t  1  + <lb/>22 <lb/>135 <lb/> 1 <lb/> t  4  + · · · <lb/> in the recursion kernel (6.26). Since each coefficient of the t-expansion of K  H  (t, t  1  ) is a <lb/>polynomial in t  1  , Lemma follows. <lb/> 7. The stationary Gromov-Witten invariants of P  1 <lb/> In this section we study the generating functions of stationary Gromov-Witten invariants <lb/>of P  1  . The conjectural relation between these invariants and the Eynard-Orantin topological <lb/>recursion was first formulated in [62]. We identify the spectral curve and the recursion kernel <lb/>using the unstable geometries. <lb/>Morally speaking, the space P  1  we are considering here appears as the zero section of a <lb/>Calabi-Yau threefold known as the resolved conifold X, which is the total space of the rank 2 <lb/>vector bundle O  P  1  (−1) ⊕ O  P  1  (−1) over P  1  . Let L ⊂ X be a special Lagrangian submanifold <lb/>[39, 42]. Then the intersection L ∩ P  1  of the special Lagrangian and the zero section is a <lb/>circle on P  1  . If we holomorphically embed a bordered Riemann surface with n boundary <lb/>components into X in a way that each boundary is mapped to a distinct circle on P  1  , then <lb/>the whole Riemann surface is necessarily mapped to P  1  . Thus we are considering open <lb/> Gromov-Witten invariants of P  1  . And if we make these circles on P  1  small and centered <lb/>around n distinct points of P  1  , then we are naturally led to the stationary Gromov-Witten <lb/>invariants of P  1  . <lb/>So our main object of this section is the Laplace transform of the stationary Gromov-<lb/>Witten invariants <lb/>(7.1) <lb/> F <lb/> P  1 <lb/> g,n  (x  1  , . . . , x  n  ) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> µ  1  ,...,µn=0 <lb/> τ  µ  1  (ω) · · · τ  µn  (ω)  g,n <lb/>n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> µ  i  ! <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  µ  i  +1  , <lb/> where ω ∈ A  0  (P  1  ) is the point class generator, and <lb/>(7.2) <lb/> τ  µ  1  (ω) · · · τ  µn  (ω)  g,n  = <lb/> [Mg,n(P  1  ,d)]  virt <lb/> ψ <lb/> µ  1 <lb/> 1  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> 1  (ω) · · · ψ <lb/> µn <lb/> 1  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> n  (ω) <lb/>is a stationary Gromov-Witten invariant of P  1  . More precisely, M  g,n  (P  1  , d) is the moduli <lb/>stack of stable morphisms from a connected n-pointed curve (C, p  1  , . . . , p  n  ) into P  1  of degree <lb/></body>

			<page> 34 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> d such that f (p  i  ), i = 1, . . . , n, are distinct, and ev  i  is the natural evaluation morphism <lb/> ev  i  : M  g,n  (P <lb/> 1  , d)  [f, (C, p  1  , . . . , p  n  )] −→ f (p  i  ) ∈ P <lb/> 1  . <lb/> The Gromov-Witten invariant (7.2) vanishes unless <lb/>(7.3) <lb/>2g − 2 + 2d = µ  1  + · · · + µ  n  . <lb/> The sum in (7.1) is the Laplace transform if we identity <lb/>(7.4) <lb/> x = e <lb/> w  . <lb/> The extra numerical factor <lb/>  n <lb/>i=1  µ  i  ! is included in (7.1) because of the polynomial growth <lb/>order of <lb/>(7.5) <lb/> τ  µ  1  (ω) · · · τ  µn  (ω)  g,n <lb/>n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> µ  i  ! <lb/>for large µ that is established in [66]. Indeed (7.5) is essentially a special type of Hurwitz <lb/> numbers that counts the number of certain coverings of P  1  . <lb/>To determine the spectral curve and the annulus amplitude, we need to consider unstable <lb/>geometries (g, n) = (0, 1) and (0, 2). From [66] we learn <lb/>(7.6) <lb/> τ  µ  1  (ω)  0,1  = τ  2d−2  (ω)  0,1  = <lb/> 1 <lb/> d! <lb/>  2 <lb/> . <lb/> To compute a closed formula for <lb/> F <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 0,1  (x) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> µ  1  =0 <lb/> τ  µ  1  (ω)  0,1  µ  1  ! <lb/>1 <lb/> x  µ  1  +1  = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> d=1 <lb/> (2d − 2)! <lb/> d!d! <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  2d−1  , <lb/> we notice that the generating function of Catalan numbers (3.5) <lb/> z(x) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> m=0 <lb/> C  m <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  2m+1 <lb/> provides again an effective tool. Thus we have <lb/>(7.7) <lb/> x <lb/>d <lb/>dx <lb/> − 1 <lb/> F <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 0,1  (x) = −2 <lb/> ∞ <lb/> d=1 <lb/> (2d − 2)! <lb/>(d − 1)!d! <lb/>1 <lb/> x  2d−1 <lb/> = −2 <lb/> ∞ <lb/> m=0 <lb/> (2m)! <lb/>(m + 1)!m! <lb/>1 <lb/> x  2m+1  = −2z(x). <lb/> The advantage of using the Catalan series z(x) is that we know its inverse function (3.8). <lb/>Using (4.6), we see that (7.7) is equivalent to <lb/>(7.8) <lb/> z  3  + z <lb/>z  2  − 1 <lb/> d <lb/>dz <lb/> − 1 <lb/> F <lb/> p  1 <lb/> 0,1  (z) = −2z. <lb/> The solution of (7.8) is given by <lb/> F <lb/> p  1 <lb/> 0,1  (z) = − <lb/> 2 <lb/> z <lb/> − <lb/> z + <lb/>1 <lb/> z <lb/> log(1 + z <lb/> 2  ) + c <lb/> z + <lb/>1 <lb/> z <lb/> , <lb/> with a constant of integration c. Since <lb/> z→0 =⇒ x→∞ =⇒ F <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 0,1  →0, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body> we conclude that c = 2. We thus obtain <lb/>(7.9) <lb/> F <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 0,1  (z) = 2z − <lb/> z + <lb/>1 <lb/> z <lb/> log(1 + z <lb/> 2  ), <lb/>and therefore, <lb/>(7.10) <lb/> W <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 0,1  (z) = dF <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 0,1  (z) = − log(1 + z <lb/> 2  ) d <lb/> z + <lb/>1 <lb/> z <lb/> . <lb/> Theorem 7.1. The spectral curve for the stationary Gromov-Witten invariants of P  1  is <lb/>given by <lb/> (7.11) <lb/> x = z + <lb/> 1 <lb/> z <lb/> y = − log(1 + z  2  ). <lb/> Remark 7.2. Since dx = 0 has two zeros at z = ±1, we also use as our preferred coordinate <lb/>(7.12) <lb/> t = <lb/> z + 1 <lb/> z − 1 <lb/> ⇐⇒ z = <lb/> t + 1 <lb/> t − 1 <lb/> . <lb/> The log singularity on the t-plane is the right semicircle of radius 1 connecting i to −i (see <lb/>Figure 7.1). The expression of W  P  1 <lb/> 0,1  in terms of the preferred coordinate is <lb/>(7.13) <lb/> W <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 0,1  (t) = <lb/>8t <lb/>(t  2  − 1)  2  log <lb/> 2(t  2  + 1) <lb/>(t − 1)  2 <lb/> dt. <lb/> 1.5 <lb/> 1.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/> 0.5 <lb/> 1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/> 1.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/> 0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/> Figure 7.1. The spectral curve for the stationary Gromov-Witten invariants of P <lb/> 1 <lb/> is the complex t-plane minus the semicircle. <lb/> Remark 7.3. The function x = z + <lb/> 1 <lb/> z  is expected here, since it is the Landau-Ginzburg <lb/>model that is homologically mirror dual to P  1  [2]. <lb/> Remark 7.4. The Galois conjugate of x = z + <lb/> 1 <lb/> z  is globally defined, and is given by <lb/>(7.14) <lb/> t −→ ¯ <lb/> t = −t. <lb/> Remark 7.5. Since <lb/>(7.15) <lb/>1 <lb/>1 − z(x) <lb/> = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=0 <lb/> z(x) <lb/> k  = 1 + <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=0 <lb/> n <lb/> n <lb/> 2  <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  n+1  , <lb/></body>

			<page> 36 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> we can express t in the branch near t = −1 as a function in x. The result is <lb/>(7.16) <lb/> t + 1 = <lb/> z(x) + 1 <lb/> z(x) − 1 <lb/>+ 1 = 2 − <lb/> 2 <lb/>1 − z(x) <lb/> = − <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=0 <lb/> 2 <lb/> n <lb/> n <lb/> 2  <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  n+1  , <lb/> which is also absolutely convergent for |x| &gt; 2. <lb/> Remark 7.6. We are using the normalized Gromov-Witten invariants (7.5) to compute <lb/>the Laplace transform (7.1). If we did not include the µ! factor in our computation of the <lb/>spectral curve, then we would have encountered with the modified Bessel function <lb/> I  0  (2x) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> m=1 <lb/> 1 <lb/>(m!)  2  x <lb/> 2m  , <lb/> instead of z(x), in computing (7.9). We note that I  0  (2x) appears in [18] in the exact same <lb/>context of computing the Gromov-Witten invariants of P  1  . We prefer the Catalan number <lb/>series z(x) over the modified Bessel function mainly because the inverse function of z(x) <lb/> takes a simple form x = z + <lb/> 1 <lb/> z  . <lb/>Motivated by the technique developed in [7, 24, 57] for single Hurwitz numbers, let us <lb/>define <lb/>(7.17) <lb/> ξ  n  (t) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=0 <lb/> 2k <lb/> k <lb/> k <lb/> n <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  2k+1  , <lb/>n ≥ 0, <lb/>and <lb/>(7.18) <lb/> η  n  (t) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=0 <lb/> 2k + 1 <lb/> k <lb/> k <lb/> n <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  2k+2  , <lb/>n ≥ 0. <lb/>We then have <lb/>(7.19) <lb/> ξ  n+1  (t) = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> x <lb/>d <lb/>dx <lb/> + 1 <lb/> ξ  n  (t) = <lb/> t  4  − 1 <lb/>8t <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ξ  n  (t) <lb/>and <lb/>(7.20) <lb/> η  n+1  (t) = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> x <lb/>d <lb/>dx <lb/> + 2 <lb/> η  n  (t) = <lb/> t  4  − 1 <lb/>8t <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> − 1 <lb/> η  n  (t). <lb/>The initial values are computed as follows: <lb/>(7.21) ξ  0  (t) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 − x <lb/>d <lb/>dx <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> m=0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> m + 1 <lb/> 2m <lb/> m <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  2m+1 <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 − <lb/> z(z  2  + 1) <lb/> z  2  − 1 <lb/> d <lb/>dz <lb/> z = − <lb/> z <lb/>z  2  − 1 <lb/>= − <lb/> t  2  − 1 <lb/>4t <lb/> , <lb/> and similarly <lb/>(7.22) <lb/> η  0  (t) = − <lb/> (t + 1)  2 <lb/> 4t <lb/> . <lb/> We note that ξ  n  (t) and η  n  (t) are Laurent polynomials of degree 2n + 1 for every n ≥ 0. <lb/>Since they are defined as functions in x, we have the reciprocity property <lb/>(7.23) <lb/> ξ  n  (1/t) = −ξ  n  (t) <lb/> η  n  (1/t) = η  n  (t). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<body> This follows from <lb/> t  −→ <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/> =⇒ x −→ −x. <lb/> The annulus amplitude requires (g, n) = (0, 2) Gromov-Witten invariants. They can be <lb/>calculated from the (g, n) = (0, 1) invariants using the Topological Recursion Relation [28]. <lb/>The results are <lb/>(7.24) τ  µ  1  (ω)τ  µ  2  (ω)  0,2  = <lb/> 1 <lb/>(m  1  !)  2  (m  2  !)  2 <lb/> 1 <lb/>(m  1  +m  2  +1) <lb/> µ  1  = 2m  1  , µ  2  = 2m  2 <lb/>1 <lb/>(m  1  !)  2  (m  2  !)  2 <lb/> 1 <lb/>(m  1  +m  2  +2) <lb/> µ  1  = 2m  1  + 1, µ  2  = 2m  2  + 1. <lb/> Theorem 7.7. The annulus amplitude is given by <lb/> (7.25) <lb/> F <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 0,2  (z  1  , z  2  ) = − log(1 − z  1  z  2  ). <lb/> Hence we have <lb/> (7.26) <lb/> W <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 0,2  (t  1  , t  2  ) = <lb/> dt  1  · dt  2 <lb/> (t  1  − t  2  )  2  − <lb/> dx  1  · dx  2 <lb/> (x  1  − x  2  )  2  = <lb/> dt  1  · dt  2 <lb/> (t  1  + t  2  )  2  . <lb/> Proof. From (7.24) we calculate <lb/> F <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 0,2  (z  1  , z  2  ) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> µ  1  ,µ  2  =0 <lb/> τ  µ  1  (ω)τ  µ  2  (ω)  0,2  µ  1  !µ  2  ! <lb/>1 <lb/> x <lb/> µ  1  +1 <lb/>1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> µ  2  +1 <lb/>2 <lb/> = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> m  1  ,m  2  =0 <lb/> 1 <lb/>(m  1  + m  2  + 1) <lb/> 2m  1 <lb/> m  1 <lb/> 2m  2 <lb/> m  2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m  1  +1 <lb/>1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m  2  +1 <lb/>2 <lb/> + <lb/> ∞ <lb/> m  1  ,m  2  =0 <lb/> 1 <lb/>(m  1  + m  2  + 2) <lb/>(2m  1  + 1)(2m  2  + 1) <lb/> 2m  1 <lb/> m  1 <lb/> 2m  2 <lb/> m  2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m  1  +2 <lb/>1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m  2  +2 <lb/>2 <lb/> . <lb/> Thus we have <lb/> x  1 <lb/> d <lb/>dx  1 <lb/> + x  2 <lb/> d <lb/>dx  2 <lb/> F <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 0,2  (z  1  , z  2  ) <lb/>= −2 <lb/> ∞ <lb/> m  1  ,m  2  =0 <lb/> 2m  1 <lb/> m  1 <lb/> 2m  2 <lb/> m  2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m  1  +1 <lb/>1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m  2  +1 <lb/>2 <lb/> − 2 <lb/> ∞ <lb/> m  1  ,m  2  =0 <lb/> (2m  1  + 1)(2m  2  + 1) <lb/> 2m  1 <lb/> m  1 <lb/> 2m  2 <lb/> m  2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m  1  +2 <lb/>1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m  2  +2 <lb/>2 <lb/> = −2ξ  0  (x  1  )ξ  0  (x  2  ) − 2z <lb/>  (x  1  )z <lb/>  (x  2  ) <lb/>= −2 <lb/> z  1 <lb/> z  2 <lb/>1  − 1 <lb/> z  2 <lb/> z  2 <lb/>2  − 1 <lb/> − 2 <lb/> z  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> z  2 <lb/>1  − 1 <lb/> z  2 <lb/>2 <lb/> z  2 <lb/>2  − 1 <lb/>= −2 <lb/> z  1  z  2  (1 + z  1  z  2  ) <lb/>(z  2 <lb/>1  − 1)(z  2 <lb/>2  − 1) <lb/> , <lb/> where ξ  0  (x) is calculated in (7.21), and from (4.6) we know <lb/> z <lb/>  (x) = <lb/> dz <lb/>dx <lb/> = <lb/> z  2 <lb/> z  2  − 1 <lb/> . <lb/> On the other hand, <lb/> x  1 <lb/> d <lb/>dx  1 <lb/> + x  2 <lb/> d <lb/>dx  2 <lb/> (− log(1 − z  1  z  2  )) <lb/>= <lb/> z  1  (z  2 <lb/>1  + 1) <lb/> z  2 <lb/>1  − 1 <lb/> d <lb/>dz  1 <lb/> + <lb/> z  2  (z  2 <lb/>2  + 1) <lb/> z  2 <lb/>2  − 1 <lb/> d <lb/>dz  2 <lb/> (− log(1 − z  1  z  2  )) <lb/></body>

			<page> 38 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> = <lb/> (z  2 <lb/> 1  + 1) <lb/> z  2 <lb/>1  − 1 <lb/>+ <lb/>(z  2 <lb/>2  + 1) <lb/> z  2 <lb/>2  − 1 <lb/> z  1  z  2 <lb/> 1 − z  1  z  2 <lb/> = −2 <lb/> z  1  z  2  (1 + z  1  z  2  ) <lb/>(z  2 <lb/>1  − 1)(z  2 <lb/>2  − 1) <lb/> . <lb/> Therefore, <lb/> x  1 <lb/> d <lb/>dx  1 <lb/> + x  2 <lb/> d <lb/>dx  2 <lb/> F <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 0,2  (z  1  , z  2  ) + log(1 − z  1  z  2  ) <lb/> = <lb/> x  1 <lb/> d <lb/>dx  1 <lb/> + x  2 <lb/> d <lb/>dx  2 <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> µ  1  ,µ  2  =0 <lb/> τ  µ  1  (ω)τ  µ  2  (ω)  0,2  µ  1  !µ  2  ! <lb/>1 <lb/> x <lb/> µ  1  +1 <lb/>1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> µ  2  +1 <lb/>2 <lb/> − <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> n <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> m=0 <lb/> C  m <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m+1 <lb/>1 <lb/> ∞ <lb/> m=0 <lb/> C  m <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m+1 <lb/>2 <lb/>  n  <lb/> = 0. <lb/>Since the kernel of the Euler differential operator is the constants, and since actual compu-<lb/>tation shows that the first few expansion terms of the Laurent series <lb/> ∞ <lb/> µ  1  ,µ  2  =0 <lb/> τ  µ  1  (ω)τ  µ  2  (ω)  0,2  µ  1  !µ  2  ! <lb/>1 <lb/> x <lb/> µ  1  +1 <lb/>1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> µ  2  +1 <lb/>2 <lb/> − <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> n <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> m=0 <lb/> C  m <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m+1 <lb/>1 <lb/> ∞ <lb/> m=0 <lb/> C  m <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m+1 <lb/>2 <lb/>  n <lb/> are 0, we complete the proof of (7.25). <lb/> Using ξ  n  (t) and η  n  (t) of (7.17) and (7.18) and the classical topological recursion relation <lb/>[28], we can systematically calculate the Laplace transform of stationary Gromov-Witten <lb/>invariants. First let us consider (g, n) = (0, 3). Since the sum of the descendant indices of <lb/> τ  µ  1  (ω)τ  µ  2  (ω)τ  µ  3  (ω)  0,3 <lb/> is even, we have <lb/>(7.27) <lb/> τ  2m  1  (ω)τ  2m  2  (ω)τ  2m  3  (ω)  0,3  = <lb/>1 <lb/> m  2 <lb/>1  m  2 <lb/>2  m  2 <lb/>3 <lb/> , <lb/> τ  2m  1  (ω)τ  2m  2  +1  (ω)τ  2m  3  +1  (ω)  0,3  = <lb/>(m  2  + 1)(m  3  + 1) <lb/> m  2 <lb/>1  (m  2  + 1)  2  (m  3  + 1)  2  . <lb/> The Laplace transform is therefore <lb/>(7.28) F <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 0,3  (t  1  , t  2  , t  3  ) = <lb/> µ  1  µ  2  µ  3  ≥0 <lb/> τ  µ  1  (ω)τ  µ  2  (ω)τ  µ  3  (ω)  0,3  µ  1  !µ  2  !µ  3  ! <lb/>1 <lb/> x <lb/> µ  1  +1 <lb/>1 <lb/> · <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> µ  2  +1 <lb/>2 <lb/> · <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> µ  3  +1 <lb/>3 <lb/> = <lb/> m  1  ,m  2  ,m  3  ≥0 <lb/> 2m  1 <lb/> m  1 <lb/> 2m  2 <lb/> m  2 <lb/> 2m  3 <lb/> m  3 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m  1  +1 <lb/>1 <lb/> · <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m  2  +1 <lb/>2 <lb/> · <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m  3  +1 <lb/>3 <lb/> + <lb/> m  1  ,m  2  ,m  3  ≥0 <lb/> 2m  1 <lb/> m  1 <lb/> 2m  2  + 1 <lb/> m  2 <lb/> 2m  3  + 1 <lb/> m  3 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m  1  +1 <lb/>1 <lb/> · <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m  2  +2 <lb/>2 <lb/> · <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m  3  +2 <lb/>3 <lb/> + <lb/> m  1  ,m  2  ,m  3  ≥0 <lb/> 2m  1  + 1 <lb/> m  1 <lb/> 2m  2 <lb/> m  2 <lb/> 2m  3  + 1 <lb/> m  3 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m  1  +2 <lb/>1 <lb/> · <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m  2  +1 <lb/>2 <lb/> · <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m  3  +2 <lb/>3 <lb/> + <lb/> m  1  ,m  2  ,m  3  ≥0 <lb/> 2m  1  + 1 <lb/> m  1 <lb/> 2m  2  + 1 <lb/> m  2 <lb/> 2m  3 <lb/> m  3 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m  1  +2 <lb/>1 <lb/> · <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m  2  +2 <lb/>2 <lb/> · <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2m  3  +1 <lb/>3 <lb/> = ξ  0  (t  1  )ξ  0  (t  2  )ξ  0  (t  3  ) + ξ  0  (t  1  )η  0  (t  2  )η  0  (t  3  ) + η  0  (t  1  )ξ  0  (t  2  )η  0  (t  3  ) + η  0  (t  1  )η  0  (t  2  )ξ  0  (t  3  ) <lb/>= − <lb/> 1 <lb/>16 <lb/>(t  1  + 1)(t  2  + 1)(t  3  + 1) <lb/> 1 − <lb/> 1 <lb/> t  1  t  2  t  3 <lb/> , <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page> 39 <lb/></page>

			<body> which is indeed a Laurent polynomial. Since it is an odd degree polynomial in ξ  n  (t)&apos;s, we <lb/>have the reciprocity <lb/> F <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 0,3  (1/t  1  , 1/t  2  , 1/t  3  ) = −F <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 0,3  (t  1  , t  2  , t  3  ). <lb/>The n = 1 stationary invariants are concretely calculated in [66]. We have <lb/>(7.29) <lb/> τ  2d   1,1  = <lb/>1 <lb/>24 <lb/> 1 <lb/> d! <lb/>  2 <lb/> (2d − 1) <lb/> τ  2d+2   2,1  = <lb/> 1 <lb/> d! <lb/>  2  <lb/> 1 <lb/>5! 4  2  (2d − 1) + <lb/>1 <lb/>24  2 <lb/> 2d − 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> τ  2g−2+2d   g,1  = <lb/> 1 <lb/> d! <lb/>  2 g <lb/> =1 <lb/> 2d − 1 <lb/> k  i  &gt;0 <lb/>k  1  +···+k   =g <lb/> i=1 <lb/> 1 <lb/>(2k  i  + 1)! 4  k  i <lb/> . <lb/> We thus obtain <lb/>(7.30) F <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 1,1  (t  1  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>24 <lb/> ∞ <lb/> d=0 <lb/> 2d <lb/> d <lb/> (2d − 1) <lb/>1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2d+1 <lb/>1 <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>24 <lb/>(2ξ  1  (t  1  ) − ξ  0  (t  1  )) <lb/>= − <lb/> 1 <lb/>384 <lb/> t <lb/> 3 <lb/>1  − 7t  1  + <lb/>7 <lb/> t  1 <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/> t  3 <lb/>1 <lb/> . <lb/> To calculate the g = 2 case we need to do the following. <lb/>(7.31) F <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 2,1  (t  1  ) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> d=0 <lb/> (2d + 2)! <lb/> d! d! <lb/> 1 <lb/>5! 4  2  (2d − 1) + <lb/>1 <lb/>24  2 <lb/> 2d − 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2d+3 <lb/>1 <lb/> = <lb/> d <lb/>dx  1 <lb/>  2 ∞ <lb/> d=0 <lb/> 2d <lb/> d <lb/> 1 <lb/>5! 4  2  (2d − 1) + <lb/>1 <lb/>24  2  (2d <lb/> 2  − 3d + 1) <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2d+1 <lb/>1 <lb/> = <lb/> − <lb/> (t  2  − 1)  2 <lb/> 8t <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/>  2  <lb/> 1 <lb/>5! 4  2  (2ξ  1  (t  1  ) − ξ  0  (t  1  )) + <lb/>1 <lb/>24  2  (2ξ  2  (t  1  ) − 3ξ  1  (t  1  ) + ξ  0  (t  1  )) <lb/> = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  19  · 3  2  · 5 <lb/>(t  2  − 1)  3 <lb/> t  9 <lb/> 525t <lb/> 12 <lb/>1  − 1470t <lb/> 10 <lb/>1  + 1107t <lb/> 8 <lb/>1  + 527t <lb/> 6 <lb/>1  + 1107t <lb/> 4 <lb/>1  − 1470t <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + 525 <lb/> . <lb/> Proposition 7.8. F  P  1 <lb/> g,1  (t  1  ) is a Laurent polynomial of degree 6g − 3 with the reciprocity <lb/> F <lb/> P  1 <lb/> g,1  (1/t  1  ) = −F <lb/> P  1 <lb/> g,1  (t  1  ). <lb/> Proof. First we calculate the binomial coefficient <lb/> 2d − 1 <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/> ! <lb/> (2d − 1)(2d − 2) · · · (2d − ) = <lb/>1 <lb/> ! <lb/> 2 <lb/>  d <lb/>  − <lb/> ( + 1) <lb/>2 <lb/> d <lb/> −1  + · · · + (−1) <lb/>  ! <lb/> as a polynomial in d, and then replace each d  i  with ξ  i  (t  1  ). The result is a linear combination <lb/>of ξ  0  (t  1  ), . . . , ξ   (t  1  ). Let Ξ   (t  1  ) denote the resulting Laurent polynomial of degree 2 + 1. <lb/>Then we have an expression <lb/>(7.32) F <lb/> P  1 <lb/> g,1  (t  1  ) = <lb/> d <lb/>dx  1 <lb/>  2g−2 ∞ <lb/> d=0 <lb/> 2d <lb/> d <lb/>  g <lb/> =1 <lb/> 2d − 1 <lb/> k  i  &gt;0 <lb/>k  1  +···+k   =g <lb/> i=1 <lb/> 1 <lb/>(2k  i  + 1)! 4  k  i <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> 2d+1 <lb/>1 <lb/></body>

			<page> 40 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> = <lb/> − <lb/> (t  2  − 1)  2 <lb/> 8t <lb/> d <lb/> dt <lb/>  2g−2 <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> g <lb/> =1 <lb/> Ξ   (t  1  ) <lb/> k  i  &gt;0 <lb/>k  1  +···+k   =g <lb/> i=1 <lb/> 1 <lb/>(2k  i  + 1)! 4  k  i <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> , <lb/> which is a Laurent polynomial of degree 2(2g −2)+2g +1 = 6g −3. The reciprocity property <lb/>follows from (7.23) and the x  1  expression of (7.32), where x  1  changes to −x  1  . In particular, <lb/>the even order differentiation in x  1  is not affected by this change. <lb/> The Eynard-Orantin recursion is for the differential forms W  P  1 <lb/> g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ). We need the <lb/>recursion kernel. From (7.13) and (7.26), we compute <lb/>(7.33) K <lb/> P  1  (t, t  1  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>  −t <lb/> t  W  P  1 <lb/> 0,2  (·, t  1  ) <lb/> W  P  1 <lb/> 0,1  (−t) − W  P  1 <lb/> 0,1  (t) <lb/>= <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> t + t  1 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> t − t  1 <lb/> 1 <lb/>log <lb/> 2(t  2  +1) <lb/>(t+1)  2 <lb/> − log <lb/> 2(t  +  1) <lb/>(t−1)  2 <lb/> (t  2  − 1)  2 <lb/> −8tdt <lb/>· dt  1 <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>16 <lb/> 1 <lb/> t + t  1 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> t − t  1 <lb/> 1 <lb/>log <lb/> (t−1)  2 <lb/> (t+1)  2 <lb/> (t  2  − 1)  2 <lb/> tdt <lb/> · dt  1  . <lb/> We note the reciprocity property of the kernel <lb/>(7.34) <lb/> K <lb/> P  1  (1/t, 1/t  1  ) = −K <lb/> P  1  (t, t  1  ). <lb/>The topological recursion (2.3) becomes <lb/>(7.35) W <lb/> P  1 <lb/> g,n  (t  1  , t  2  , . . . , t  n  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ <lb/> K <lb/> P  1  (t, t  1  ) <lb/> W <lb/> P  1 <lb/> g−1,n+1  (t, −t, t  2  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/>+ <lb/> No (0, 1) terns <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> IJ={2,3,...,n} <lb/> W <lb/> P  1 <lb/> g  1  ,|I|+1  (t, t  I  )W <lb/> P  1 <lb/> g  2  ,|J|+1  (−t, t  J  ) <lb/> , <lb/> where the residue calculation is taken along the integration contour γ (see Figure 4.1) <lb/>consisting of two concentric circles of radius  and 1// for a small  centered around t = 0, <lb/>with the inner circle positively oriented and the outer circle negatively oriented. Since <lb/>there is a log singularity in the complex t-plane, we cannot use the residue calculus method <lb/>to evaluate the integral at t = t  1  and t = −t  1  . Thus the residue calculation of (7.35) is <lb/>performed around the neighborhood of t = 0 and t = ∞. <lb/> So let us provide two expansion formulas for the kernel K  P  1  (t, t  1  ), assuming that t  1  ∈ C  * <lb/> is away from the log singularity of Figure 7.1. The transcendental factor of K  P  1  (t, t  1  ) has <lb/>an expansion <lb/>(7.36) <lb/>4 <lb/> t log <lb/> (t−1)  2 <lb/> (t+1)  2 <lb/>  = − <lb/> 1 <lb/> t  2  + <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>+ <lb/>4 <lb/>45 <lb/> t <lb/> 2  + <lb/>44 <lb/>945 <lb/> t <lb/> 4  + <lb/>428 <lb/>14175 <lb/> t <lb/> 6  + <lb/>10196 <lb/>467775 <lb/> t <lb/> 8  + · · · <lb/> around t = 0. The denominator of the coefficient of t  2k−2  is given by <lb/> 2k+1 <lb/> q=3, prime <lb/> q <lb/> 2k <lb/> q−1 <lb/> = 3 <lb/> k  · 5 <lb/> k <lb/> 2  · 7 <lb/> k <lb/> 3  · · · , <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>41 <lb/></page>

			<body> which is the same as µ(L  k  ) of [38, Lemma 1.5.2]. The expansion of <lb/> 1 <lb/> t+t  1 <lb/> + <lb/> 1 <lb/> t−t  1 <lb/> at t = 0 is <lb/>given by <lb/>1 <lb/> t + t  1 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> t − t  1 <lb/> = −2t <lb/> 1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 − <lb/> t  2 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> = −2 <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=0 <lb/> t  2n+1 <lb/> t <lb/> 2n+2 <lb/>1 <lb/> . <lb/> From the expression (7.33) and the above consideration, we know that around t = 0, <lb/> K  P  1  (t, t  1  ) starts from t  −1  , and that the coefficient of t  2n−1  is a Laurent polynomial in t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> starting from <lb/> 1 <lb/>32  t <lb/> −(2n+2) <lb/> 1 <lb/> up to t <lb/> −2 <lb/> 1  with rational coefficients. More concretely, we have <lb/>(7.37) K <lb/> P  1  (t, t  1  ) = <lb/> 1 <lb/> t <lb/> 1 <lb/>32 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> + t <lb/> 1 <lb/>32 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  4 <lb/>1 <lb/> − <lb/> 7 <lb/>96 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> + t <lb/> 3 <lb/> 1 <lb/>32 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  6 <lb/>1 <lb/> − <lb/> 7 <lb/>96 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  4 <lb/>1 <lb/> + <lb/>71 <lb/>1440 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> + t <lb/> 5 <lb/> 1 <lb/>32 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  8 <lb/>1 <lb/> − <lb/> 7 <lb/>96 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  6 <lb/>1 <lb/> + <lb/>71 <lb/>1440 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  4 <lb/>1 <lb/> − <lb/> 191 <lb/>30240 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> + t <lb/> 7 <lb/> 1 <lb/>32 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  10 <lb/>1 <lb/> − <lb/> 7 <lb/>96 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  8 <lb/>1 <lb/> + <lb/>71 <lb/>1440 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  6 <lb/>1 <lb/> − <lb/> 191 <lb/>30240 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  4 <lb/>1 <lb/> − <lb/> 23 <lb/>28350 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> + t <lb/> 9 <lb/> 1 <lb/>32 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  12 <lb/>1 <lb/> − <lb/> 7 <lb/>96 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  10 <lb/>1 <lb/> + <lb/>71 <lb/>1440 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  8 <lb/>1 <lb/> − <lb/> 191 <lb/>30240 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  6 <lb/>1 <lb/> − <lb/> 23 <lb/>28350 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  4 <lb/>1 <lb/> − <lb/> 233 <lb/>935550 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> + · · · <lb/> 1 <lb/> dt <lb/> · dt  1  . <lb/> Similarly, around t = ∞ we have <lb/>(7.38) K <lb/> P  1  (t, t  1  ) = <lb/> − t <lb/> 3  1 <lb/>32 <lb/>+ t <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>32 <lb/> t <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + <lb/>7 <lb/>96 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> t <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>32 <lb/> t <lb/> 4 <lb/>1  + <lb/>7 <lb/>96 <lb/> t <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  − <lb/> 71 <lb/>1440 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> t  3 <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>32 <lb/> t <lb/> 6 <lb/>1  + <lb/>7 <lb/>96 <lb/> t <lb/> 4 <lb/>1  − <lb/> 71 <lb/>1440 <lb/> t <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + <lb/>191 <lb/>30240 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> t  5 <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>32 <lb/> t <lb/> 8 <lb/>1  + <lb/>7 <lb/>96 <lb/> t <lb/> 6 <lb/>1  − <lb/> 71 <lb/>1440 <lb/> t <lb/> 4 <lb/>1  + <lb/>191 <lb/>30240 <lb/> t <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + <lb/>23 <lb/>28350 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> t  7 <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>32 <lb/> t <lb/> 10 <lb/>1  + <lb/>7 <lb/>96 <lb/> t <lb/> 8 <lb/>1  − <lb/> 71 <lb/>1440 <lb/> t <lb/> 6 <lb/>1  + <lb/>191 <lb/>30240 <lb/> t <lb/> 4 <lb/>1  + <lb/>23 <lb/>28350 <lb/> t <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + <lb/>233 <lb/>935550 <lb/> + · · · <lb/> 1 <lb/> dt <lb/> · dt  1  . <lb/> Theorem 7.9. The Eynard-Orantin differential form W  P  1 <lb/> g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) is a Laurent polyno-<lb/>mial in t  2 <lb/>1  , t  2 <lb/>2  , . . . , t  2 <lb/> n  of degree 2(3g − 3 + n) in the stable range 2g − 2 + n &gt; 0. It satisfies <lb/>the reciprocity property <lb/> (7.39) <lb/> W <lb/> P  1 <lb/> g,n  (1/t  1  , . . . , 1/t  n  ) = (−1) <lb/> n  W <lb/> P  1 <lb/> g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/> as a meromorphic symmetric n-form. The highest degree terms form a homogeneous poly-<lb/>nomial of degree 2(3g − 3 + n), which is given by <lb/> (7.40) <lb/> W <lb/> P  1 <lb/> g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) = <lb/>(−1)  n <lb/> 2  2g−2+2n <lb/> k  1  ,...,kn≥0 <lb/> τ  k  1  · · · τ  kn   g,n <lb/>n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (2k  1  + 1)!! <lb/> t  i <lb/> 2 <lb/>  2k  i <lb/> dt  i <lb/> . <lb/> Indeed it is the same as the generating function of the ψ-class intersection numbers (5.4). <lb/>Proof. The statement is proved by induction on 2g − 2 + n using the recursion (7.35). <lb/>The initial cases (g, n) = (1, 1) and (g, n) = (0, 3) are easily verified from the concrete <lb/>calculations below. Since we are expanding <lb/> 1 <lb/> t+t  1 <lb/> + <lb/> 1 <lb/> t−t  1 <lb/> around t = 0 and t = ∞, it is <lb/>obvious that the recursion produces a Laurent polynomial in t  2 <lb/>1  , t  2 <lb/>2  , . . . , t  2 <lb/> n  as the result. <lb/></body>

			<page> 42 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> The expression of (7.38) tells us that the residue calculation at infinity increases the <lb/>degree by 4. This is because the leading term of the coefficient of t  −(2n+1)  is t <lb/> 2n+4 <lb/> 1 <lb/> , and the <lb/>residue calculation picks up the term t  2n  . By the induction hypothesis, the right-hand side <lb/>of (7.35) without the kernel term has homogenous degree 2(3g − 3 + n) − 4. The reciprocity <lb/>property also follows by induction using (7.34). <lb/>The leading terms of W  P  1 <lb/> g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) satisfy a topological recursion themselves. We can <lb/>extract the terms in the kernel that produce the leading terms of the differential forms from <lb/>(7.36) or (7.38). The result is <lb/>(7.41) <lb/> K <lb/> WK  (t, t  1  ) = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>32 <lb/> t <lb/> 3 <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=0 <lb/> t  2n <lb/>1 <lb/> t  2n <lb/> 1 <lb/> dt <lb/> · dt  1  = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> t − t  1 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> t + t  1 <lb/> 1 <lb/>32 <lb/> t <lb/> 4  · <lb/> 1 <lb/> dt <lb/> · dt  1  , <lb/> which is identical to [10, Theorem 7.4], and also to (5.10). Since the topological recursion <lb/>uniquely determines all the differential forms from the initial condition, and again since the <lb/>(g, n) = (0, 3) and (1, 1) cases satisfy (7.40), by induction we obtain (7.40) for all stable <lb/>values of (g, n). <lb/> The (g, n) = (1, 1) Eynard-Orantin differential form is computed using (2.4). <lb/>(7.42) W <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 1,1  (t  1  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ <lb/> K <lb/> P  1  (t, t  1  ) <lb/> W <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 0,2  (t, −t) + <lb/> dx · dx  1 <lb/> (x − x  1  )  2 <lb/> = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ <lb/> K <lb/> P  1  (t, t  1  ) <lb/> dt · dt <lb/> 4t  2 <lb/> = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>64 <lb/>  <lb/> 1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ <lb/> 1 <lb/> t + t  1 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> t − t  1 <lb/> 1 <lb/>log <lb/> (t−1)  2 <lb/> (t+1)  2 <lb/> (t  2  − 1)  2 <lb/> t  3 <lb/> dt <lb/>  <lb/> dt  1 <lb/> = <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>128 <lb/> t <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + <lb/>7 <lb/>384 <lb/>+ <lb/>7 <lb/>384 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>128 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  4 <lb/>1 <lb/> dt  1  . <lb/> This is in agreement of W  P  1 <lb/> 1,1  (t  1  ) = dF  P  1 <lb/> 1,1  (t  1  ) and (7.30). From (7.35) we have <lb/>(7.43) W <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 0,3  (t  1  , t  2  , t  3  ) <lb/>= <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ <lb/> K <lb/> P  1  (t, t  1  ) <lb/> W <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 0,2  (t, t  2  )W <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 0,2  (−t, t  3  ) + W <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 0,2  (t, t  3  )W <lb/> P  1 <lb/> 0,2  (−t, t  2  ) <lb/> = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>16 <lb/> 1 + <lb/>1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1  t  2 <lb/>2  t  2 <lb/>3 <lb/> dt  1  dt  2  dt  3  . <lb/> It is also in agreement with (7.28). <lb/>Norbury and Scott conjecture the following <lb/> Conjecture 7.10 (Norbury-Scott Conjecture [62]). For (g, n) in the stable range we have <lb/> (7.44) <lb/> W <lb/> P  1 <lb/> g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) = d  1  · · · d  n  F <lb/> P  1 <lb/> g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ). <lb/>The conjecture is verified for g = 0 and g = 1 cases in [62]. We recall that the Eyanrd-<lb/>Orantin recursion for simple Hurwitz numbers is essentially the Laplace transform of the <lb/>cut-and-join equation [24]. For the case of the counting problem of clean Belyi morphisms <lb/>the recursion is the Laplace transform of the edge-contraction operation of Theorem 3.3. <lb/> Question 7.11. What is the equation among the stationary Gromov-Witten invariants of <lb/> P  1  whose Laplace transform is the Eynard-Orantin recursion (7.35)? <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>43 <lb/></page>

			<body> Appendix A. Calculation of the Laplace transform <lb/> In this appendix we give the proof of Theorem 4.3. <lb/> Proposition A.1. Let us use the x  j  -variables defined by x  j  = e  w  j  , and write <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) = w  g,n  (x  1  , . . . , x  n  ) dx  1  · · · dx  n  . <lb/> Then the Laplace transform of the recursion formula (3.15) is the following differential <lb/>recursion: <lb/> (A.1) − x  1  w  g,n  (x  1  , . . . , x  n  ) <lb/>= <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂x  j <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  j  − x  1 <lb/> (w  g,n−1  (x  2  , . . . , x  n  ) − w  g,n−1  (x  1  , x  2  , . . . , <lb/> x  j  , . . . , x  n  )) <lb/> + w  g−1,n+1  (x  1  , x  1  , x  2  , . . . , x  n  ) + <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> IJ={2,...,n} <lb/> w  g  1  ,|I|+1  (x  1  , x  I  )w  g  2  ,|J|+1  (x  1  , x  J  ). <lb/> Proof. The operation we wish to do is to apply <lb/>(−1) <lb/> n <lb/> µ  1  ,...,µn&gt;0 <lb/> µ  2  · · · µ  n <lb/>n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> µ  i  +1 <lb/> i <lb/> to each side of (3.15). Then by (4.13), the left-hand side becomes w  g,n  (x  1  , . . . , x  n  ). <lb/>The second line of (3.15) is straightforward. Let us just consider the first term, since the <lb/>computation of the second term is the same. <lb/>(−1) <lb/> n <lb/> µ  1  ,...,µn&gt;0 <lb/> µ  2  · · · µ  n <lb/>n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> µ  i  +1 <lb/> i <lb/> α+β=µ  1  −2 <lb/> αβD  g−1,n+1  (α, β, µ  2  , . . . , µ  n  ) <lb/>= − <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  1 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> n+1 <lb/> µ  2  ,...,µn&gt;0 <lb/> α,β&gt;0 <lb/> αβµ  2  · · · µ  n  D  g−1,n+1  (α, β, µ  2  . . . , µ  n  ) <lb/>1 <lb/> x <lb/> α+1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> · <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> β+1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> n <lb/> i=2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> µ  i  +1 <lb/> i <lb/> = − <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  1 <lb/> w  g−1,n+1  (x  1  , x  1  , x  2  , . . . , x  n  ). <lb/>Thus the second line of (3.15) produces <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  1 <lb/> w  g−1,n+1  (x  1  , x  1  , x  2  , . . . , x  n  ) + <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> IJ={2,...,n} <lb/> w  g  1  ,|I|+1  (x  1  , x  I  )w  g  2  ,|J|+1  (x  1  , x  J  ) <lb/> . <lb/> To calculate the operation on the first line of (3.15), let us fix j &gt; 1 and set ν = <lb/> µ  1  + µ  j  − 2 ≥ 0. Then <lb/>(A.2) (−1) <lb/> n <lb/> µ  1  ,...,µn&gt;0 <lb/> µ  2  · · · µ  n  (µ  1  + µ  j  − 2) <lb/> × D  g,n−1  (µ  1  + µ  j  − 2, µ  2  , . . . , <lb/> µ  j  , . . . , µ  n  ) <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> µ  i  +1 <lb/> i <lb/> = − <lb/> ∞ <lb/> ν=0 <lb/> µ  2  ,..., µ  j  ,...,µn&gt;0 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> n−1  νµ  2  · · · <lb/> µ  j  · · · µ  n <lb/></body>

			<page> 44 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> × D  g,n−1  (ν, µ  2  , . . . , <lb/> µ  j  , . . . , µ  n  ) <lb/>1 <lb/> x <lb/> ν+1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> i =1,j <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> µ  i  +1 <lb/> i <lb/>ν+1 <lb/> µ  j  =1 <lb/> µ  j  x <lb/> µ  j  −2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> µ  j  +1 <lb/> j <lb/> . <lb/> Assuming |x  1  | &lt; |x  j  |, we calculate <lb/>(A.3) <lb/> ν+1 <lb/> µ  j  =1 <lb/> µ  j  x <lb/> µ  j  −2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> µ  j  +1 <lb/> j <lb/> = − <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂x  j <lb/>ν+1 <lb/> µ  j  =0 <lb/> x  1 <lb/> x  j <lb/>  µ  j <lb/> = − <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂x  j <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 − <lb/> x  1 <lb/> x  j <lb/> − <lb/> x  1 <lb/> x  j <lb/>  ν+2 <lb/> 1 − <lb/> x  1 <lb/> x  j <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> = − <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂x  j <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 − <lb/> x  1 <lb/> x  j <lb/> + x <lb/> ν <lb/> 1 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂x  j <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  j  − x  1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> x <lb/> ν+1 <lb/>j <lb/> . <lb/> We then substitute (A.3) in (A.2) and obtain <lb/>(A.4) (A.2) = w  g,n−1  (x  1  , x  2  , . . . , <lb/> x  j  , . . . , x  n  ) <lb/>1 <lb/> x  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂x  j <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 − <lb/> x  1 <lb/> x  j <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  1 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂x  j <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  j  − x  1 <lb/> w  g,n−1  (x  2  , . . . , x  j  , . . . , x  n  ) <lb/> = − <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  1 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂x  j <lb/> 1 <lb/> x  j  − x  1 <lb/> (w  g,n−1  (x  2  , . . . , x  j  , . . . , x  n  ) − w  g,n−1  (x  1  , x  2  , . . . , <lb/> x  j  , . . . , x  n  )) <lb/> . <lb/> This completes the proof. <lb/> Proof of Theorem 4.3. When the curve is split into two pieces, the second term of the third <lb/>line of (A.1) contains contributions from unstable geometries (g, n) = (0, 1) and (0, 2). We <lb/>first separate them out. For g  1  = 0 and I = ∅, or g  2  = 0 and J = ∅, we have a contribution <lb/>of <lb/>2w  0,1  (x  1  )w  g,n  (x  1  , x  2  , . . . , x  n  ). <lb/>Similarly, for g  1  = 0 and I = {j}, or g  2  = 0 and J = {j}, we have <lb/>2 <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> w  0,2  (x  1  , x  j  )w  g,n−1  (x  1  , . . . , <lb/> x  j  , . . . , x  n  ). <lb/>Since W  D <lb/> 0,1  and W  D <lb/> 0,2  are defined on the spectral curve, it is time for us to switch to the <lb/>preferred coordinate t of (4.1) now. We thus introduce <lb/>(A.5) <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) = w <lb/> D <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) dt  1  · · · dt  n  = w  g,n  (x  1  , . . . , x  n  ) dx  1  · · · dx  n  . <lb/> Since w  0,1  (x) = −z(x), we have <lb/> w  0,1  (x) = − <lb/> t + 1 <lb/> t − 1 <lb/> w  0,2  (x  1  , x  2  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>(t  1  + t  2  )  2 <lb/> (t  2 <lb/>1  − 1)  2 <lb/> 8t  1 <lb/> (t  2 <lb/>2  − 1)  2 <lb/> 8t  2 <lb/> w  g,n  (x  1  , . . . , x  n  ) = (−1) <lb/> n  w <lb/> D <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (t  2 <lb/> i  − 1)  2 <lb/> 8t  i <lb/> . <lb/> Thus (A.1) is equivalent to <lb/>2 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1  + 1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1  − 1 <lb/> − <lb/> t  1  + 1 <lb/> t  1  − 1 <lb/> w <lb/> D <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>45 <lb/></page>

			<body> = <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> (t  2 <lb/> 1  − 1)  2  (t  2 <lb/> j  − 1)  2 <lb/> 16(t  2 <lb/>1  − t  2 <lb/> j  )  2 <lb/> 8t  j <lb/> (t  2 <lb/> j  − 1)  2  w <lb/> D <lb/>g,n−1  (t  1  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/>+ <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  j <lb/> (t  2 <lb/>1  − 1)(t  2 <lb/> j  − 1) <lb/>4(t  2 <lb/>1  − t  2 <lb/> j  ) <lb/>8t  1 <lb/> (t  2 <lb/>1  − 1)  2 <lb/> (t  2 <lb/> j  − 1)  2 <lb/> 8t  j <lb/> w <lb/> D <lb/>g,n−1  (t  2  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/> + <lb/>(t  2 <lb/>1  − 1)  2 <lb/> 8t  1 <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> w <lb/> D <lb/>g−1,n+1  (t  1  , t  1  , t  2  , . . . , t  n  ) + <lb/> stable <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> IJ={2,...,n} <lb/> w <lb/> D <lb/>g  1  ,|I|+1  (t  1  , t  I  )w <lb/> D <lb/>g  2  ,|J|+1  (t  1  , t  J  ) <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> + 2 <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> 1 <lb/>(t  1  + t  j  )  2 <lb/> (t  2 <lb/>1  − 1)  2 <lb/> 8t  1 <lb/> w <lb/> D <lb/>g,n−1  (t  1  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/>= <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> t  j  (t  2 <lb/>1  − 1)  2 <lb/> 2(t  2 <lb/>1  − t  2 <lb/> j  )  2  + <lb/>1 <lb/>(t  1  + t  j  )  2 <lb/> (t  2 <lb/>1  − 1)  2 <lb/> 4t  1 <lb/> w <lb/> D <lb/>g,n−1  (t  1  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/>+ <lb/> t  1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1  − 1 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  j <lb/> (t  2 <lb/> j  − 1)  3 <lb/> 4t  j  (t  2 <lb/>1  − t  2 <lb/> j  ) <lb/> w <lb/> D <lb/>g,n−1  (t  2  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/> + <lb/>(t  2 <lb/>1  − 1)  2 <lb/> 8t  1 <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> w <lb/> D <lb/>g−1,n+1  (t  1  , t  1  , t  2  , . . . , t  n  ) + <lb/> stable <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> IJ={2,...,n} <lb/> w <lb/> D <lb/>g  1  ,|I|+1  (t  1  , t  I  )w <lb/> D <lb/>g  2  ,|J|+1  (t  1  , t  J  ) <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> . <lb/> Since <lb/>2 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1  + 1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1  − 1 <lb/> − <lb/> t  1  + 1 <lb/> t  1  − 1 <lb/> = − <lb/> 4t  1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1  − 1 <lb/> , <lb/> we obtain <lb/>(A.6) w <lb/> D <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) = − <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  j <lb/> (t  2 <lb/> j  − 1)  3 <lb/> 16t  j  (t  2 <lb/>1  − t  2 <lb/> j  ) <lb/> w <lb/> D <lb/>g,n−1  (t  2  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/> + <lb/>(t  2 <lb/>1  − 1)  3 <lb/> 16t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/>1  + t  2 <lb/> j <lb/> (t  2 <lb/>1  − t  2 <lb/> j  )  2  w <lb/> D <lb/>g,n−1  (t  1  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/> − <lb/> (t  2 <lb/>1  − 1)  3 <lb/> 32t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> w <lb/> D <lb/>g−1,n+1  (t  1  , t  1  , t  2  , . . . , t  n  ) + <lb/> stable <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> IJ={2,...,n} <lb/> w <lb/> D <lb/>g  1  ,|I|+1  (t  1  , t  I  )w <lb/> D <lb/>g  2  ,|J|+1  (t  1  , t  J  ) <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> . <lb/> Now let us compute the integral <lb/>(A.7) W <lb/> D <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>64 <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ <lb/> 1 <lb/> t + t  1 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> t − t  1 <lb/> (t  2  − 1)  3 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> · <lb/> 1 <lb/> dt <lb/> · dt  1 <lb/> × <lb/>  n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/> 0,2  (t, t  j  )W  g,n−1  (−t, t  2  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) + W <lb/> D <lb/> 0,2  (−t, t  j  )W  g,n−1  (t, t  2  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/></body>

			<page> 46 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<body> + W <lb/> D <lb/> g−1,n+1  (t, −t, t  2  , . . . , t  n  ) + <lb/> stable <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> IJ={2,3,...,n} <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/>g  1  ,|I|+1  (t, t  I  )W <lb/> D <lb/>g  2  ,|J|+1  (−t, t  J  ) <lb/> . <lb/> Recall that For 2g−2+n &gt; 0, w  D <lb/>g,n  (t  1  , . . . , t  n  ) is a Laurent polynomial in t  2 <lb/>1  , . . . , t  2 <lb/> n  . Thus the <lb/>third line of (A.7) is immediately calculated because the integration contour γ of Figure 4.1 <lb/>encloses ±t  1  and contributes residues with the negative sign. The result is exactly the last <lb/>line of (A.6). Similarly, since <lb/> W <lb/> D <lb/> 0,2  (t, t  j  )W  g,n−1  (−t, t  2  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) + W <lb/> D <lb/> 0,2  (−t, t  j  )W  g,n−1  (t, t  2  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/>= − <lb/> 1 <lb/>(t + t  j  )  2  + <lb/>1 <lb/>(t − t  j  )  2 <lb/> w <lb/> D <lb/>g,n−1  (t, t  2  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) dt dt dt  2  · · · <lb/> dt  j  · · · dt  n  , <lb/> the residues at ±t  1  contributes <lb/> − <lb/> (t  2 <lb/>1  − 1)  3  (t  2 <lb/>1  + t  2 <lb/> j  ) <lb/>16t  2 <lb/>1  (t  2 <lb/>1  − t  2 <lb/> j  )  2  w <lb/> D <lb/>g,n−1  (t  1  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ). <lb/>This is the same as the second line of the right-hand side of (A.6). <lb/>Within the contour γ, there are second order poles at ±t  j  for each j ≥ 2 that come from <lb/> W  D <lb/> 0,2  (±t, t  j  ). Note that W  D <lb/> 0,2  (t, t  j  ) acts as the Cauchy differentiation kernel. We calculate <lb/>1 <lb/>64 <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ <lb/> 1 <lb/> t + t  1 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> t − t  1 <lb/> (t  2  − 1)  3 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> n <lb/> j=2 <lb/> w <lb/> D <lb/> 0,2  (t, t  j  )w <lb/> D <lb/>g,n−1  (−t, t  2  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/>+ w <lb/> D <lb/> 0,2  (−t, t  j  )w  g,n−1  (t, t  2  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/> = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>32 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  j <lb/> 1 <lb/> t  j  + t  1 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> t  j  − t  1 <lb/>  (t  2 <lb/> j  − 1)  3 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> j <lb/> w <lb/> D <lb/>g,n−1  (t  j  , t  2  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/> = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>16 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  j <lb/> 1 <lb/> t  2 <lb/> j  − t  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> (t  2 <lb/> j  − 1)  3 <lb/> t  j <lb/> w <lb/> D <lb/>g,n−1  (t  j  , t  2  , . . . , <lb/> t  j  , . . . , t  n  ) <lb/> . <lb/> This gives the first line of the right-hand side of (A.6). We have thus completes the proof <lb/>of Theorem 4.3. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgement. The authors thank G. Borot, V. Bouchard, A. Brini, K. Chap-<lb/>man, B. Eynard, D. Hernández Serrano, G. Gliner, M. Mariño, P. Norbury, R. Ohkawa, <lb/>M. Penkava, G. Shabat, S. Shadrin, R. Vakil, and D. Zagier for stimulating and useful <lb/>discussions. During the preparation of this paper, the authors received support from NSF <lb/>grants DMS-0905981, DMS-1104734 and DMS-1104751, and from the Banff International <lb/>Research Station. The research of M.M. was also partially supported by the University of <lb/>Geneva, the University of Grenoble, the University of Salamanca, the University of Amster-<lb/>dam, and the Max-Planck Institute for Mathematics in Bonn. B.S. also received a special <lb/>research support from the Central Michigan University. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] A. Alexandrov, A. Mironov and A. Morozov, Unified description of correlators in non-Gaussian phases of Her-<lb/>mitean matrix model, arXiv:hep-th/0412099 (2004). <lb/>[2] M. R. Ballard, Meet homological mirror symmetry, in &quot; Modular forms and string duality, &quot; Fields Inst. Commun., <lb/> 54, 191–224 (2008). <lb/>[3] G. V. Belyi, On galois extensions of a maximal cyclotomic fields, Math. U.S.S.R. Izvestija 14, 247–256 (1980). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>47 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [4] G. Borot, B. Eynard, M. Mulase and B. Safnuk, Hurwitz numbers, matrix models and topological recursion, <lb/> arXiv:0906.1206 [math.Ph] (2009). <lb/>[5] V. Bouchard, A. Catuneanu, O. Marchal and P. Suu lkowski, The remodeling conjecture and the Faber-<lb/>Pandharipande formula, arXiv:1108.2689 (2011). <lb/>[6] V. Bouchard, A. Klemm, M. Mariño, and S. Pasquetti, Remodeling the B-model, Commun. Math. Phys. 287, <lb/> 117–178 (2008). <lb/>[7] V. Bouchard and M. Mariño, Hurwitz numbers, matrix models and enumerative geometry, Proc. Symposia Pure <lb/>Math. 78, 263–283 (2008). <lb/>[8] A. Brini, The local Gromov-Witten theory of CP  1  and integrable hierarchies, arXiv:1002.0582v1 [math-ph]. <lb/>[9] A. Brini, B. Eynard, and M. Mariño, Torus knots and mirror symmetry arXiv:1105.2012. <lb/>[10] K. Chapman, M. Mulase, and B. Safnuk, Topological recursion and the Kontsevich constants for the volume of <lb/>the moduli of curves, Preprint (2010). <lb/>[11] L. Chen, Bouchard-Klemm-Marino-Pasquetti Conjecture for C  3  , arXiv:0910.3739 (2009). <lb/>[12] R.M. Corless, G.H. Gonnet, D.E.G. Hare, D.J. Jeffrey and D.E. Knuth, On the Lambert W-function, Adv. <lb/>Computational Math. 5, 329–359 (1996). <lb/>[13] R. Dijkgraaf, H. Fuji and M. Manabe, The volume conjecture, perturbative knot invariants, and recursion rela-<lb/>tions for topological strings, arXiv:1010.4542 [hep-th] (2010). <lb/>[14] R. Dijkgraaf and C. Vafa, Two Dimensional Kodaira-Spencer Theory and Three Dimensional Chern-Simons <lb/>Gravity, arXiv:0711.1932 [hep-th]. <lb/>[15] R. Dijkgraaf, E. Verlinde, and H. Verlinde, Loop equations and Virasoro constraints in non-perturbative two-<lb/>dimensional quantum gravity, Nucl. Phys. B348, 435–456 (1991). <lb/>[16] B. Dubrovin, Geometry of 2D topological field theories, in &quot; Integrable systems and quantum groups, &quot; Lecture <lb/>Notes in Math. 1620, 120–348 (1994). <lb/>[17] B. Dubrovin and Y. Zhang, Frobenius manifolds and Virasoro constraints, Selecta Mathematica, New Ser. 5, <lb/> 423–466 (1999). <lb/>[18] B. Dubrovin and Y. Zhang, Virasoro Symmetries of the Extended Toda Hierarchy, arXive:math/0308152 (2003). <lb/>[19] P. Dunin-Barkowski, A. Mironov, A. Morozov, A. Sleptsov, and A. Smirnov. Superpolynomials for toric knots <lb/>from evolution induced by cut-and-join operators , arXiv:1106.4305 [hep-th]. <lb/>[20] T. Ekedahl, S. Lando, M. Shapiro, A. Vainshtein, Hurwitz numbers and intersections on moduli spaces of curves, <lb/> Invent. Math. 146, 297–327 (2001). <lb/>[21] B. Eynard, Topological expansion for the 1-hermitian matrix model correlation functions, arXiv:hep-th/0407261. <lb/>[22] B. Eynard, Recursion between volumes of moduli spaces, arXiv:0706.4403 [math-ph]. <lb/>[23] B. Eynard, M. Mariño and N. Orantin, Holomorphic anomaly and matrix models, Journal of High Energy Physics <lb/> 06 058, (2007) [arXiv:hep-th/0702110]. <lb/>[24] B. Eynard, M. Mulase and B. Safnuk, The Laplace transform of the cut-and-join equation and the Bouchard-<lb/>Mariño conjecture on Hurwitz numbers, arXiv:0907.5224 math.AG (2009). <lb/>[25] B. Eynard and N. Orantin, Invariants of algebraic curves and topological expansion, Communications in Number <lb/>Theory and Physics 1, 347–452 (2007). <lb/>[26] B. Eynard and N. Orantin, Weil-Petersson volume of moduli spaces, Mirzakhani&apos;s recursion and matrix models, <lb/> arXiv:0705.3600 [math-ph] (2007). <lb/>[27] B. Eynard and N. Orantin, Algebraic methods in random matrices and enumerative geometry, arXiv:0811.3531 <lb/>[math-ph] (2008). <lb/>[28] E. Getzler, Topological recursion relations in genus 2, arXiv:math/9801003 (1998). <lb/>[29] I.P. Goulden and D.M. Jackson, Transitive factorisations into transpositions and holomorphic mappings on the <lb/>sphere, Proc. A.M.S., 125, 51–60 (1997). <lb/>[30] I.P. Goulden, D.M. Jackson and A. Vainshtein, The number of ramified coverings of the sphere by the torus and <lb/>surfaces of higher genera, Ann. of Comb. 4, 27–46 (2000). <lb/>[31] I.P. Goulden, D.M. Jackson and R. Vakil, The Gromov-Witten potential of a point, Hurwitz numbers, and Hodge <lb/>integrals, Proc. London Math. Soc. 83:3, 563–581 (2001). <lb/>[32] I.P. Goulden, D.M. Jackson and R. Vakil, A short proof of the λg-conjecture without Gromov-Witten theory: <lb/>Hurwitz theory and the moduli of curves, arXiv:math/0604297v1 [math.AG] (2006). <lb/>[33] T. Graber and R. Vakil, Hodge integrals and Hurwitz numbers via virtual localization, Compositio Math. 135, <lb/> 25–36 (2003). <lb/>[34] T. Graber and R. Vakil, Relative virtual localization and vanishing of tautological classes on moduli spaces of <lb/>curves, Duke Math. J. 130, 1–37 (2005). <lb/>[35] S. Gukov and P. Suu lkowski, A-polynomial, B-model, and quantization, arXiv:1108.0002v1 [hep-th]. <lb/>[36] J. L. Harer, The cohomology of the moduli space of curves, in Theory of Moduli, Montecatini Terme, 1985 <lb/>(Edoardo Sernesi, ed.), Springer-Verlag, 1988, pp. 138–221. <lb/>[37] J. L. Harer and D. Zagier, The Euler characteristic of the moduli space of curves, Inventiones Mathematicae 85, <lb/> 457–485 (1986). <lb/>[38] F. Hirzebruch, Topological methods in algebraic geometry, Third Edition, Springer -Verlag, 232 pages, 1966. <lb/>[39] N. Hitchin, Lectures on Special Lagrangian Submanifolds, math.DG/9907034 (1999). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 48 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> O. DUMITRESCU, M. MULASE, B. SAFNUK, AND A. SORKIN <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> [40] K. Hori, S. Katz, A. Klemm, R. Pandharipande, R. Thomas, C. Vafa, R. Vakil, and E. Zaslow, Mirror symmetry, <lb/> Clay Mathematics Monograph 1, 929 pages, American Mathematical Society, 2003. <lb/>[41] A. Hurwitz, ¨ <lb/>Uber Riemann&apos;sche Flächen mit gegebene Verzweigungspunkten, Mathematische Annalen 39, 1–66 <lb/>(1891). <lb/>[42] D. Joyce, Lectures on special Lagrangian geometry, math.DG/0111111 (2001). <lb/>[43] R. Kaufmann, Yu. Manin, and D. Zagier, Higher Weil-Petersson volume of moduli space of stable n-pointed <lb/> curves, ArXiv:alg-geom/9604001 (1996). <lb/>[44] Y. Kodama, Combinatorics of the dispersionless Toda hierarchy, Lecture delivered at the International Workshop <lb/>on Nonlinear and Modern Mathematical Physics, Beijing Xiedao Group, Beijing, China, July 15–21, 2009. <lb/>[45] Y. Kodama and V.U. Pierce, Combinatorics of dispersionless integrable systems and universality in random <lb/>matrix theory, arXiv:0811.0351 (2008). <lb/>[46] M. Kontsevich, Intersection theory on the moduli space of curves and the matrix Airy function, Communications <lb/>in Mathematical Physics 147, 1–23 (1992). <lb/>[47] M. Kontsevich, Homological algebra of mirror symmetry, arXiv:alg-geom/9411018 (1994). <lb/>[48] C.-C. M. Liu, Lectures on the ELSV formula, arXiv:1004.0853. In &quot; Transformation Groups and Moduli Spaces of <lb/>Curves, &quot; Adv. Lect. Math. (ALM) 16, 195–216, Higher Education Press and International Press, Beijing-Boston, <lb/>2010. <lb/>[49] C.-C. M. Liu, K. Liu, J. Zhou, A proof of a conjecture of Mariño-Vafa on Hodge Integrals, J. Differential Geom. <lb/> 65, no. 2, 289–340 (2003). <lb/>[50] M. Mariño, Chern-Simons theory, matrix models, and topological strings, Oxford University Press, 2005. <lb/>[51] M. Mariño, Open string amplitudes and large order behavior in topological string theory, JHEP 0803, 060 (2008). <lb/>[52] A. Mironov and A. Morozov, Virasoro constraints for Kontsevich-Hurwitz partition function, arXiv:0807.2843 <lb/>[hep-th] (2008). <lb/>[53] M. Mulase, Asymptotic analysis of a Hermitian matrix integral, International Journal of Mathematics 6, 881–892 <lb/>(1995). <lb/>[54] M. Mulase and M. Penkava, Ribbon graphs, quadratic differentials on Riemann surfaces, and algebraic curves <lb/>defined over Q, The Asian Journal of Mathematics 2 (4), 875–920 (1998). <lb/>[55] M. Mulase and M. Penkava, Topological recursion for the Poincaré polynomial of the combinatorial moduli space <lb/>of curves, Preprint arXiv:1009.2135 math.AG (2010). <lb/>[56] M. Mulase and B. Safnuk, Mirzakhani&apos;s recursion relations, Virasoro constraints and the KdV hierarchy, Indian <lb/>J. Math. 50, 189–228 (2008). <lb/>[57] M. Mulase and N. Zhang, Polynomial recursion formula for linear Hodge integrals, Communications in Number <lb/>Theory and Physics 4, (2010). <lb/>[58] D. Mumford, Towards an enumerative geometry of the moduli space of curves (1983), in &quot; Selected Papers of <lb/>David Mumford, &quot; 235–292 (2004). <lb/>[59] P. Norbury, Counting lattice points in the moduli space of curves, arXiv:0801.4590 (2008). <lb/>[60] P. Norbury, String and dilaton equations for counting lattice points in the moduli space of curves, arXiv:0905.4141 <lb/>(2009). <lb/>[61] P. Norbury and N. Scott, Polynomials representing Eynard-Orantin invariants, arXiv:1001.0449 (2010). <lb/>[62] P. Norbury and N. Scott, Gromov-Witten invariants of P  1  and Eynard-Orantin invariants, arXiv:1106.1337 <lb/>(2011). <lb/>[63] A. Okounkov, Random matrices and random perputations, International Mathematics Research Notices 2000, <lb/> 1043–1095 (2000). <lb/>[64] A. Okounkov, Toda equations for Hurwitz numbers, Math. Res. Lett. 7, 447 (2000) [arXiv:math.AG/0004128]. <lb/>[65] A. Okounkov and R. Pandharipande, Gromov-Witten theory, Hurwitz numbers, and matrix models, I, Proc. <lb/>Symposia Pure Math. 80, 325–414 (2009). <lb/>[66] A. Okounkov and R. Pandharipande, Gromov-Witten theory, Hurwitz theory, and completed cycles, Ann. Math. <lb/> 163, 517–560 (2006). <lb/>[67] A. Okounkov and R. Pandharipande, The equivariant Gromov-Witten theory of P  1  , arXiv:math/0207233 <lb/>[math.AG] (2002). <lb/>[68] A. Okounkov and R. Pandharipande, Virasoro constraints for target curves, arXiv:math/0308097 [math.AG] <lb/>(2003). <lb/>[69] A. Okounkov and R. Pandharipande, Hodge integrals and invariants of the unknot, Geom. Topol. 8, 675–699 <lb/>(2004). <lb/>[70] H. Ooguri, P. Sulkowski, M. Yamazaki, Wall Crossing As Seen By Matrix Models, arXiv:1005.1293 (2010). <lb/>[71] L. Schneps, Editor, The Grothendieck theory of dessins d&apos;enfants, London Mathematical Society Lecture Notes <lb/>Series 200, 368 pages, 1994. <lb/>[72] L. Schneps and P. Lochak, Editors, Geometric Galois actions 1, London Mathematical Society Lecture Notes <lb/>Series 242, 293 pages,1997. <lb/>[73] D. D. Sleator, R. E. Tarjan, and W. P. Thurston, Rotation distance, triangulations, and hyperbolic geometry, <lb/> Journal of the American Mathematical Society 1, 647–681 (1988). <lb/>[74] R. P. Stanley, Enumerative combinatorics volume 2, Cambridge University Press, 2001. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> SPECTRAL CURVE OF EYNARD-ORANTIN RECURSION AND LAPLACE TRANSFORM <lb/></note>

			<page>49 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [75] K. Strebel, Quadratic differentials, Springer-Verlag, 1984. <lb/>[76] G. &apos;t Hooft, A planer diagram theory for strong interactions, Nuclear Physics B 72, 461–473 (1974). <lb/>[77] R. Vakil, Harvard Thesis 1997. <lb/>[78] E. Witten, Two dimensional gravity and intersection theory on moduli space, Surveys in Differential Geometry <lb/> 1, 243–310 (1991). <lb/>[79] J. Zhou, Hodge integrals, Hurwitz numbers, and symmetric groups, preprint, arXiv:math/0308024 [math.AG] <lb/>(2003). <lb/>[80] J. Zhou, On computations of Hurwitz-Hodge integrals, arXiv:0710.1679 (2007). <lb/>[81] J. Zhou, Local Mirror Symmetry for One-Legged Topological Vertex, arXiv:0910.4320 (2009). <lb/>[82] J. Zhou, Local Mirror Symmetry for the Topological Vertex arXiv:0911.2343 (2009). <lb/>[83] S. Zhu, On a proof of the Bouchard-Suu lkowski conjecture, arXiv:1108.2831 (2011). <lb/>[84] D. Zvonkine, An algebra of power series arising in the intersection theory of moduli spaces of curves and in the <lb/>enumeration of ramified coverings of the sphere, arXiv:math.AG/0403092 (2004). <lb/></listBibl>

			<front> Department of Mathematics, University of California, Davis, CA 95616–8633, U.S.A. <lb/> E-mail address: dolivia@math.ucdavis.edu <lb/> Department of Mathematics, University of California, Davis, CA 95616–8633, U.S.A. <lb/> E-mail address: mulase@math.ucdavis.edu <lb/> Department of Mathematics, Central Michigan University, Mount Pleasant, MI 48859 <lb/> E-mail address: brad.safnuk@cmich.edu <lb/> Department of Mathematics, University of California, Davis, CA 95616–8633, U.S.A. <lb/> E-mail address: asorkin@math.ucdavis.edu </front>


	</text>
</tei>
