<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="footnote"> arXiv:1411.5717v1  [math-ph] 20 Nov 2014 <lb/></note>

			<front> The partition function of the extended r-reduced <lb/> Kadomtsev-Petviashvili hierarchy <lb/> Marco Bertola <lb/>  * , * * , †  , Di Yang <lb/>  † <lb/>  *  Centre de recherches mathématiques, Université de Montréal <lb/>C. P. 6128, succ. centre ville, Montréal, Québec, Canada H3C 3J7 <lb/>  * *  Department of Mathematics and Statistics, Concordia University, <lb/>1455 de Maisonneuve W., Montréal, Québec, Canada H3G 1M8 <lb/>  †  SISSA, via Bonomea 265, Trieste 34136, Italy <lb/> Abstract <lb/> We derive a particular solution of the extended r-reduced KP hierarchy, which is specified <lb/>by a generalized string equation. The work is a generalization to arbitrary r ≥ 2 of Buryak&apos;s <lb/>recent results of a solution to the extended open KdV hierarchy which corresponds to r = 2. <lb/> Mathematics Subject Classification (2010). 53D45; 37K10; 37K20. <lb/> Keywords. KP hierarchy; tau function; wave function; string equation. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1 Introduction and results <lb/> Recently Pandharipande, Solomon and Tessler conjectured an integrable equation for descendent <lb/>integrals for open and closed Riemann surfaces, called the open KdV equation [17] which has <lb/>attracted significant attention [5, 6, 15, 2]. In particular, Buryak [5, 6] constructed an extension <lb/>of this equation to a hierarchy of commuting flows, called the extended open KdV hierarchy; he <lb/>also derived an explicit formula for a particular solution of the extended open KdV hierarchy which <lb/>satisfies a generalized version of the string equation. <lb/>It is known that the partition function for r-spin structures of type A is a particular tau function <lb/>of the r-reduced KP hierarchy [19, 11, 12]. As far as we know, the open version of these invariants <lb/>(except r = 2, the open KdV case) has not been discovered or defined; however, we are going to <lb/>construct a particular solution of the so-called extended r-reduced KP hierarchy, for which we hope <lb/>it will play the role of the partition function for open r-spin structures of type A. In passing, we also <lb/>present some formulae which clarify certain series expansions of [6]. To present the result, consider <lb/>the differential operator L <lb/>L = ∂ <lb/> r  + <lb/> r−1 <lb/> α=1 <lb/> u  α  (x) ∂ <lb/> r−1−α  , ∂ := ∂  x  , r ≥ 2. <lb/>(1.1) <lb/>The (r − 1)-KdV hierarchy, also called the Gelfand-Dickey hierarchy or the r-reduced KP hierarchy, <lb/>is a hierarchy of evolutionary partial differential equations for the operator L in terms of infinitely <lb/></body>

			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<body> many auxiliary parameter t  m  (called customarily &quot; times &quot; ) <lb/> ∂L <lb/>∂t  m <lb/> = α  m <lb/> L <lb/> m <lb/> r <lb/> + <lb/> , L <lb/> , m ≥ 1. <lb/>(1.2) <lb/>This infinite system of evolution equations for L (namely the coefficients u  α  (x; t  1  , . . .)) is well–known <lb/>to be compatible [8]. Here the numbers α  m  are defined by <lb/> α  p+qr  = <lb/>1 <lb/>(p + qr)!  (r)  ! <lb/> , 1 ≤ p ≤ r, q ≥ 0 <lb/>(1.3) <lb/>and x and (p + qr)!  (r)  ! is the r  th  generalized double factorial defined by <lb/>(p + qr)!  (r)  ! := (p + qr) · (p + (q − 1)r) · ... · p <lb/> (1.4) <lb/>which reduces to the usual double factorial in the case r = 2; the following convention is used <lb/>0!  (r)  ! = (−1)!  (r)  ! = ... = (−(r − 1))!  (r)  ! := 1. <lb/>(1.5) <lb/>The m = 1 equation in (1.2) reads <lb/> ∂L <lb/>∂t1  = [∂, L], which means that t  1  simply acts by translations in <lb/>the variable x; therefore we can (and will) identify t  1  and x throughout the paper. Introduce the <lb/>notations: <lb/> t = (t  1  , ..., t  r−1  , t  r+1  , ..., t  2r−1  , ...), t  KP  = (t  1  , t  2  , t  3  , ...). <lb/> (1.6) <lb/>In other words, the infinite vector t is obtained from t  KP  by removing the variables with index which <lb/>is a multiple of r. Note that if m is a multiple of r, then the r.h.s. of (1.2) vanishes <lb/> 1  which implies <lb/>that the operator L and hence the functions u  α  (t) depend only on the reduced set of variables t (as <lb/>opposed to the extended set t  KP  ): <lb/> u  α  = u  α  (t), α = 1, ..., r − 1. <lb/>(1.7) <lb/>Consider now the flows of the usual wave vector of the r–reduced KP hierarchy (1.2), but allow <lb/>them to depend also on the &quot; trivial &quot; flow variables t  rp  , p ∈ N: <lb/> ∂Ψ <lb/>∂t  m <lb/> = α  m <lb/> L <lb/> m <lb/>r <lb/> + <lb/> Ψ, m ≥ 1. <lb/>(1.8) <lb/>The compatibility of the equations (1.2) , (1.8) is a standard result (see for example [8]): <lb/> ∂  tm  ∂  tn  L = ∂  tn  ∂  tm  L, <lb/>∂  tm  ∂  tn  Ψ = ∂  tn  ∂  tm  Ψ, ∀ m, n ≥ 1. <lb/>(1.9) <lb/>So equations (1.2) and equations (1.8) together form an integrable system. <lb/> Definition 1.1 The infinite system of compatible equations (1.2), (1.8) is called the extended r-<lb/> reduced KP hierarchy. <lb/> The case r = 2, coincides with the extended open KdV hierarchy [5, 6, 17]. We point out that we <lb/>are not imposing at this stage an additional spectral equation. <lb/>In this paper, we are going to introduce (in Theorem 1.2 below) a particular solution of the <lb/>extended r-reduced KP hierarchy of Def. 1.1 that satisfies a certain additional constraint in the <lb/>form of the string equation. It turns out that this solution is closely related to a pair of adjoint <lb/>ODE problems that are closely related to the Pearcey equation (see (3.29), (3.30)); the approach <lb/>also should shed light on certain objects that have appeared in the case r = 2 in [5]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 1  Indeed in this case the r.h.s is the commutator of L with an integer power of L itself. <lb/></note>

			<page> 2 <lb/></page>

			<body> Frobenius manifolds. Recall now that the Frobenius manifold corresponding to the r-reduced <lb/> KP hierarchy is the space of miniversal deformations of a simple singularity of type A  r−1  . Let Z(t) <lb/> denote the partition function [1, 10] of this Frobenius manifold. It is a particular tau function of <lb/>the r-reduced KP hierarchy (1.2) which is uniquely determined (up to a multplicative constant) by <lb/>the celebrated string equation [1] <lb/> L  −1  Z(t) = 0, <lb/>(1.10) <lb/>where <lb/> L  −1  := <lb/> p≥r+1,r∤p <lb/> t  p <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  p−r <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> r−1 <lb/> k=1 <lb/> t  k  t  r−k  − <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  1 <lb/> . <lb/> (1.11) <lb/>It can also be uniquely determined by using only the W  Ar−1  -constraints [1, 3, 16]. According to <lb/>Witten&apos;s r-spin conjecture [19], which was proved by Faber, Shadrin and Zvonkine in [11] and in <lb/>a more general setting by Fan, Jarvis and Ruan in [12], log Z is also the generating function of <lb/>intersection numbers over certain moduli space of r-spin structures of type A. <lb/> Our goal is to produce a solution of the extended r–reduced KP hierarchy which generalizes the <lb/>above (see Theorem 1.2) and the result of [6]. To this end and to introduce the necessary objects, <lb/>let us denote by ψ(t  KP  ; z) the following wave function associated to Z(t) <lb/>ψ(t  KP  ; z) = <lb/> Z(t − [z <lb/> −1  ]) <lb/> Z(t) <lb/>e <lb/> ξ(t  KP  ; z) <lb/> (1.12) <lb/>where we have used the shorthand notations <lb/>(t  KP  − [z <lb/> −1  ]) := <lb/> t  1  − <lb/> m  1 <lb/> z <lb/>, t  2  − <lb/> m  2 <lb/> z  2  , . . . <lb/> , <lb/> (1.13) <lb/> ξ(t  KP  ; z) := <lb/> k≥1 <lb/> α  k  t  k  z <lb/> k  , <lb/> (1.14) <lb/> m  p+qr  := (p + (q − 1)r)!  (r)  !, 1 ≤ p ≤ r − 1, q ≥ 0. <lb/>(1.15) <lb/>The unwieldy normalizations of the time flows are chosen to simplify the comparison with existing <lb/>results later on and it is also dictated by the application to the underlying geometric invariants. <lb/>The wave function ψ(t  KP  ; z) is the ordinary wave function with the spectral parameter z, namely it <lb/>satisfies <lb/> Lψ(t  KP  ; z) = z <lb/> r  ψ(t  KP  ; z). <lb/> (1.16) <lb/>While L is independent of the flows t  p  , t  2p  , t  3p  , . . ., the wave function ψ does depend on them, albeit <lb/>in a trivial exponential way as dictated by (1.12). In order to emphasize this additional dependence <lb/>we have used the subscript t  KP  to indicate the dependence on the complete set of KP flows. <lb/>Now we are ready to state the result of this paper. <lb/> Theorem 1.2 Let ω = e <lb/> iπ <lb/>r+1  and set <lb/> D(z; Γ) = − <lb/> iω <lb/> r+1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> √ <lb/> 2π <lb/> z <lb/> r+1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> exp <lb/> − <lb/> z <lb/> r+1 <lb/> r + 1 <lb/> ω  −1  Γ <lb/> w <lb/> −1  exp <lb/> − <lb/> w <lb/> r+1 <lb/> (r + 1)r <lb/>+ <lb/> w <lb/>r <lb/>z <lb/> r <lb/> dw <lb/> (1.17) <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body> where Γ = e <lb/> − <lb/> iπ <lb/> r+1  R  +  ∪ e <lb/> iπ <lb/>r+1  R  +  (traversed in the upward direction). It has the following asymptotic <lb/>expansion <lb/> D(z; Γ) ∼ 1 + <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=1 <lb/> d  k <lb/> z  (r+1)k  =: d(z), z → ∞, z ∈ S <lb/> ′ <lb/> (1.18) <lb/> where S <lb/> ′  = {− <lb/> π <lb/>r  − <lb/> π <lb/>r+1  &lt; arg(z) &lt; <lb/> π <lb/>r  − <lb/> π <lb/>r+1  } and d  k  are constants, and the contour has zero index <lb/>number relative to w = 0. Introduce the following function <lb/> Ψ(t  KP  ) := <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> z=∞ <lb/> d(z) ψ(t  KP  ; z) <lb/>dz <lb/>z <lb/> (1.19) <lb/> where the formal series d(z) is given in (1.18). Define also the partition function of the extended <lb/> r–reduced KP hierarchy by the formula <lb/> Z  E  (t  KP  ) := Z(t) Ψ(t  KP  ) <lb/>(1.20) <lb/> where Z(t) is the partition function of the A  r−1  Frobenius manifold satisfying the string equation <lb/>(1.10). Then we have <lb/> L <lb/> ext <lb/> −1  Z  E  (t  KP  ) = 0, <lb/>(1.21) <lb/>Ψ(t  KP  )|  t  KP ≥2  =0  ≡ 1 (∀ t  1  ) <lb/>(1.22) <lb/> where the operator L <lb/> ext <lb/> −1  is defined by <lb/> L <lb/> ext <lb/> −1  = <lb/> p≥r+1 <lb/> t  p <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  p−r <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> r−1 <lb/> k=1 <lb/> t  k  t  r−k  + t  r  − <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  1 <lb/> . <lb/> (1.23) <lb/> Furthermore, the solution Ψ(t  KP  ) of (1.8) and such that Z  E  (t  KP  ) := Z(t) · Ψ(t  KP  ) solves (1.21) is <lb/>unique up to a multiplicative constant. <lb/> The paper is organized as follows: In Section 2, we review the tau function of the (r-reduced) KP <lb/>hierarchy and the associated wave function and dual wave function. In Section 3, by applying the <lb/>string actions we study some properties of the wave function and the dual wave function associated <lb/>to the partition function of the r-spin structures of type A. In Section 4, we prove Theorem 1.2. <lb/> 2 Tau function and wave functions of the r-reduced KP hi-<lb/>erarchy <lb/> Let us consider solutions to the extended r-reduced KP hierarchy (1.2),(1.8). It is easy to see that <lb/>equations (1.2) and (1.8) are decoupled: we can first solve (1.2) and then solve (1.8). Equations <lb/>(1.2) have a class of well-known solutions corresponding to infinite Grassmannians. <lb/>Let u  1  (t), ..., u  r−1  (t) be any Grassmannian solution to the r-reduced KP hierarchy. It is known <lb/>that there exists a so-called Sato tau function τ (t  KP  ) of this solution, which satisfies the bilinear <lb/>identities <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> z=∞ <lb/> e <lb/> ξ(t  KP  −t <lb/> ′ <lb/> KP <lb/> ; z)  τ (t  KP  − [z <lb/> −1  ]) τ (t <lb/> ′ <lb/> KP <lb/> + [z <lb/> −1  ]) dz = 0, ∀ t  KP  , t <lb/> ′ <lb/> KP <lb/> . <lb/> (2.1) <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body> where ξ(t  KP  − t <lb/> ′ <lb/> KP <lb/> ; z) and t  KP  − [z <lb/> −1  ], t  KP  + [z <lb/> −1  ] are defined as in (1.14), (1.13). The tau function <lb/> τ is unique up to a factor of form <lb/>exp <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> k≥1 <lb/> c  k  t  k  + c  0 <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> (2.2) <lb/>where c  i  , are arbitrary constants. <lb/>Substituting the solution u  1  (t), ..., u  r−1  (t) into equations (1.8) we get a set of evolutionary linear <lb/>PDEs for Ψ. To solve them, let us introduce an auxiliary problem <lb/> Lψ(t  KP  ; z) = z <lb/> r  ψ(t  KP  ; z). <lb/> (2.3) <lb/>Together with the original PDEs (1.8) <lb/> ∂ψ <lb/>∂t  m <lb/> (t  KP  ; z) = α  m <lb/> L <lb/> m <lb/>r <lb/> + <lb/> ψ(z; t  KP  ), m ≥ 1 <lb/>(2.4) <lb/> ψ(t  KP  ; z) becomes the wave function of the solution with the spectral parameter z (also called the <lb/>Baker–Akhiezer function). Without loss of generality, we assume it is normalized in the following <lb/>way <lb/> ψ(t  KP  ; z) ∼ <lb/> 1 + O(z <lb/> −1  ) <lb/> e <lb/> ξ(t  KP  ;z)  , <lb/>z → ∞. <lb/> (2.5) <lb/>Note that the wave function is unique up to an arbitrary asymptotic series g(z) satisfying <lb/> g(z) ∼ 1 + <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=1 <lb/> g  k <lb/> z  k  , z → ∞ <lb/> (2.6) <lb/>where g  k  , k ≥ 1 are constants. The following lemma is well-known. <lb/> Lemma 2.1 ([7, 8]) For any Grassmannian solution u  1  (t), ..., u  r−1  (t) of the r-reduced KP hierar-<lb/>chy, let τ (t  KP  ) be any tau-function of this solution. Then <lb/> ψ(t  KP  ; z) = <lb/> τ (t  KP  − [z <lb/> −1  ]) <lb/> τ (t  KP  ) <lb/> e <lb/> ξ(t  KP  ; z)  . <lb/> (2.7) <lb/> is a wave function of the solution. <lb/> Similarly to the above construction, let us also recall the dual wave function ψ <lb/> ⋆  (t  KP  ; z) of a <lb/>solution u(t). It satisfies the following linear system: <lb/> L <lb/> ⋆  ψ <lb/>  *  = z <lb/> r  ψ <lb/>  *  , <lb/> (2.8) <lb/> ∂ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> ∂t  m <lb/> = −α  m <lb/> L <lb/> m/r <lb/>  ⋆ <lb/> + <lb/> ψ <lb/>  *  . <lb/> (2.9) <lb/>Here ⋆ denotes the formal adjoint operator. The dual wave function is also normalized such that <lb/> ψ <lb/>  *  (t  KP  ; z) = <lb/> 1 + O(z <lb/> −1  ) <lb/> e <lb/> −ξ(t  KP  ;z)  , <lb/>z → ∞. <lb/> (2.10) <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body> In terms of the tau function it is expressed by <lb/> ψ <lb/>  *  (t  KP  ; z) := <lb/> τ (t  KP  + [z <lb/> −1  ]) <lb/> τ (t  KP  ) <lb/> e <lb/> −ξ(t  KP  ; z)  . <lb/> (2.11) <lb/>The bilinear identities (2.1) read as follows <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> z=∞ <lb/> ψ(t  KP  ; z) ψ <lb/>  *  (t <lb/> ′ <lb/> KP <lb/> ; z) dz = 0, ∀ t  KP  , t <lb/> ′ <lb/> KP <lb/> . <lb/> (2.12) <lb/>Now we take a tau function τ (t) of the solution u  1  (t), ..., u  t−1  (t) without dependence in t  rp  , p ≥ <lb/> 1, and take g(z) any asymptotic series of form (2.6). Then solutions of equations (1.8) are given by <lb/>Ψ(t  KP  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> z=∞ <lb/> g(z) <lb/>τ (t − [z <lb/> −1  ]) <lb/> τ (t) <lb/> e <lb/> ξ(t  KP  ; z)  dz <lb/>z <lb/>. <lb/> (2.13) <lb/>Inspired by Buryak [6] we call <lb/> τ  E  (t  KP  ) := τ (t) Ψ(t  KP  ) <lb/>(2.14) <lb/>a tau function of the solution (u  1  (t), ..., u  r−1  (t), Ψ(t  KP  )) of the extended r-reduced KP hierarchy. <lb/>It is well-known that the r-reduced KP hierarchy is Miura equivalent to Dubrovin-Zhang&apos;s <lb/>integrable hierarchy of topological type associated to the A  r−1  Frobenius manifold. So we can <lb/>write the hierarchy (1.2) by using the normal coordinates w  1  , ..., w  r−1  [10, 9] <lb/> ∂w  α <lb/> ∂t  β,q  = η  αγ  ∂  x <lb/> δ ¯ <lb/> h  β,q <lb/> δw  γ  (x) <lb/> , q ≥ 0 <lb/>(2.15) <lb/>where η  αβ  = δ  α+β, r  , <lb/> δ <lb/>δwγ  denote the variational derivatives, ¯ h  β,q  = <lb/> h  β,q  dx are Hamiltonians <lb/>whose densities h  β,q  satisfy the tau-symmetry property <lb/> h  α,−1  = w  α  , <lb/>∂h  β,p−1 <lb/> ∂t  α,q  = <lb/> ∂h  β,q−1 <lb/> ∂t  α,p  , p, q ≥ 0. <lb/>(2.16) <lb/>In these notations, t <lb/> α,p  = t  α+pr  , p ≥ 0. Here and below free Greek indices always take values <lb/>1, ..., r − 1, the Einstein summation convention for repeated Greek indices with one-up and one-<lb/>down is always assumed, and we use η  αβ  and its inverse η <lb/> αβ  to lower and raise Greek indices. For <lb/>example, w <lb/> α  := η <lb/> αβ  w  β  . <lb/> The tau symmetry property allows us to define two-point functions [10] Ω  α,p;β,q  for an arbitrary <lb/>solution (w  1  (t), ..., w  r−1  (t)) <lb/>Ω  α,p;β,q  (w; w  x  , w  xx  , ...) = ∂ <lb/> −1 <lb/> x <lb/>  ∂h  β,p−1 <lb/> ∂t  α,q <lb/> , p, q ≥ 0. <lb/>(2.17) <lb/>It also implies the existence of a tau function τ of the solution such that <lb/> ∂ <lb/> 2  log τ <lb/>∂t  α,p  ∂t  β,q  = Ω  α,p;β,q  (w(t); w  x  (t), w  xx  (t), ...). <lb/> (2.18) <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body> We call this tau function the Dubrovin-Zhang tau function associated to the A  r−1  Frobenius mani-<lb/>fold. Note that Ω  α,p;β,q  are differential polynomials in w, and that log τ admits the genus expansion <lb/>log τ = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> g=0 <lb/> F  g  =: F , <lb/> (2.19) <lb/>where F  g  are genus g free energies and F is the free energy. In the particular example of the <lb/> r-reduced KP hierarchy (1.2) that we are considering, the normal coordinates w  α  as well as the <lb/>Hamiltonian densities h  α,p  are given by [7, 10] <lb/> w  α  = <lb/> h  α <lb/> α!  (r)  ! <lb/> , <lb/> (2.20) <lb/> h  α, p  = <lb/> h  α+(p+1)r <lb/> (α + (p + 1)r)!  (r)  ! <lb/>(2.21) <lb/>where <lb/> h  k  := Res L <lb/> k <lb/> r  , <lb/>k ≥ 1. <lb/>(2.22) <lb/>In the above formula, Res means taking the coefficient of ∂ <lb/> −1  . <lb/> For Grassmannian solutions, the Sato tau function and the Dubrovin-Zhang tau function coin-<lb/>cide [7, 10] modulo an arbitrary factor of form (2.2). <lb/> 3 Wave potentials, string actions and Pearcey integrals <lb/> Recall that the partition function Z(t) associated to the A  r−1  Frobenius manifold is a particular <lb/>tau function of the r-reduced KP hierarchy. Up to a multiplicative constant, this tau function is <lb/>uniquely specified by the string equation <lb/> L  −1  Z = 0 <lb/>(3.1) <lb/>where L  −1  is defined in (1.11). Write <lb/> τ  k1  ...τ  km  := <lb/> ∂ <lb/> m  log Z <lb/>∂t  k1  ...∂t  km <lb/> t=0 <lb/> . <lb/> (3.2) <lb/>Then according to [11, 16], we know that τ  k1  ...τ  km  vanishes unless there exists a non-negative <lb/>number g such that <lb/> k  1 <lb/> r <lb/> + ... + <lb/> k  m <lb/> r <lb/> = m + <lb/> r − 2 <lb/> r <lb/> − 3 <lb/> (1 − g). <lb/> (3.3) <lb/>This implies for r ≥ 3, Z(x, 0, 0, ...) = constant. As usual we normalize this constant to be 1. For <lb/> r = 2, it is known that Z(x, 0, 0, ...) = exp <lb/> x <lb/> 3  /6 <lb/> . <lb/> We denote by u  1  (t), ..., u  r−1  (t) the solution to the r-reduced KP hierarchy associated with the <lb/>tau function Z(t), in normal coordinates by w  1  (t), ..., w  r−1  (t). The string equation (3.1) implies of <lb/>the initial data <lb/> w  α  |  t  ≥2  =0  = <lb/> ∂ <lb/> 2  log Z <lb/>∂t  1  ∂t  α <lb/> t  ≥2  =0 <lb/> = δ  α, r−1  · x, α = 1, ..., r − 1. <lb/>(3.4) <lb/>Here δ  α, r−1  is the Kronecker delta function. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body> Lemma 3.1 The Miura transformation relating u to w is triangular and of form <lb/> w  α  = <lb/> 1 <lb/> r <lb/>u  α  + M  α  (u  1  , ..., u  α−1  ), <lb/>(3.5) <lb/> where M  α  are differential polynomials in u  1  , ..., u  α−1  . <lb/> Proof Let us introduce a grading on pseudo-differential operators: <lb/>deg u <lb/> (k) <lb/> α  := α + 1 + k, deg ∂ <lb/> m  := m, <lb/>k ≥ 0, m ∈ Z. <lb/> (3.6) <lb/>Then we find that L and L <lb/> 1 <lb/> r  are homogeneous operators with degree <lb/>deg L = r, deg L <lb/> 1 <lb/> r  = 1. <lb/>(3.7) <lb/>Recall due to (2.20), (2.22) that <lb/> w  α  = <lb/>1 <lb/> α!  (r)  ! <lb/> ResL <lb/> α <lb/>r  . <lb/> (3.8) <lb/>So we have <lb/>deg w  α  = α + 1. <lb/>(3.9) <lb/>The leading term <lb/> 1 <lb/> r  u  α  is an easy exercise: one can replace in L the operator ∂ with a parameter λ <lb/> and take the usual residue at λ = ∞. The lemma is proved. <lb/> The above Lemma implies <lb/> u  α  |  t  ≥2  =0  = <lb/>1 <lb/> r <lb/>δ  α,r−1  · x, α = 1, ..., r − 1. <lb/>(3.10) <lb/>In particular, we have <lb/> Lemma 3.2 The following initial values hold <lb/> u  α  |  t=0  = 0. <lb/>(3.11) <lb/>Denote by ψ(t  KP  ; z) and ψ <lb/>  *  (t  KP  ; z) the wave and the dual wave functions associated to Z(t), <lb/> respectively: <lb/> ψ(t  KP  ; z) = <lb/> Z(t − [z <lb/> −1  ]) <lb/> Z(t) <lb/>e <lb/> ξ(t  KP  ; z)  , ψ <lb/>  *  (t  KP  ; z) = <lb/> Z(t + [z <lb/> −1  ]) <lb/> Z(t) <lb/>e <lb/> −ξ(t  KP  ; z)  , <lb/> (3.12) <lb/>and introduce the following notations <lb/> K(t  KP  ; z) := Z(t) · ψ(t  KP  ; z), <lb/>K <lb/>  *  (t  KP  ; z) := Z(t) · ψ <lb/>  *  (t  KP  ; z), <lb/> (3.13) <lb/> f (x; z) := ψ(t  KP  ; z)|  t  ≥2  =0  , <lb/>f <lb/>  *  (x; z) := ψ <lb/>  *  (t  KP  ; z)|  t  ≥2  =0  . <lb/> (3.14) <lb/>We call K(t  KP  ; z) and K <lb/>  *  (t  KP  ; z) the wave potential and the dual wave potential associated to the <lb/>partition function Z(t). Let us consider the string actions on them. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body> Proposition 3.3 The following equalities hold true: <lb/> L <lb/> ext <lb/> −1  K(t  KP  ; z) = S  z  K(t  KP  ; z), <lb/> (3.15) <lb/> L <lb/> ext, * <lb/> −1  K <lb/>  *  (t  KP  ; z) = −S <lb/> ⋆ <lb/>z  K <lb/>  *  (t  KP  ; z). <lb/> (3.16) <lb/> Here S  z  is defined by <lb/> S  z  = z <lb/> −(r−1)/2  • ∂  z  • z <lb/> −(r−1)/2  − z = <lb/>1 <lb/> z  r−1  ∂  z  − <lb/> r − 1 <lb/>2 z  r  − z <lb/> (3.17) <lb/> and S <lb/> ⋆ <lb/>z  is the formal adjoint operator of S  z  which has the form <lb/> S <lb/> ⋆ <lb/>z  = z <lb/> −(r−1)/2  • ∂ <lb/> ⋆ <lb/>z  • z <lb/> −(r−1)/2  − z = − <lb/> 1 <lb/> z  r−1  ∂  z  + <lb/> r − 1 <lb/>2 z  r  − z, <lb/> (3.18) <lb/> and L <lb/> ext <lb/> −1  , L <lb/> ext, * <lb/> −1 <lb/> are defined by <lb/> L <lb/> ext <lb/> −1 <lb/> = <lb/> p≥r+1 <lb/> t  p <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  p−r <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> r−1 <lb/> k=1 <lb/> t  k  t  r−k  + t  r  − <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  1 <lb/> , <lb/> (3.19) <lb/> L <lb/> ext, * <lb/> −1 <lb/> = <lb/> p≥r+1 <lb/> t  p <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  p−r <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> r−1 <lb/> k=1 <lb/> t  k  t  r−k  − t  r  − <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  1 <lb/> . <lb/> (3.20) <lb/> Proof On one hand, by using the string equation (3.1) we find <lb/> L <lb/> ext <lb/> −1  K(t  KP  ; z) = <lb/> p≥r+1 <lb/> m  p <lb/> z  p <lb/> ∂Z(t − [z <lb/> −1  ]) <lb/> ∂t  p−r <lb/> e <lb/> ξ(t  KP  ;z)  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> r − 1 <lb/> z  r  K(t  KP  ; z) − zK(t  KP  ; z) <lb/> + <lb/> p≥r+1 <lb/> α  p−r  t  p  z <lb/> p−r  K(t  KP  ; z) + <lb/> r−1 <lb/> p=1 <lb/> m  r−p  t  p  z <lb/> p−r  K(t  KP  ; z) + t  r  K(t  KP  ; z). <lb/> (3.21) <lb/>On another hand from the chain rule it follows that <lb/>1 <lb/> z  r−1  ∂  z  K(t  KP  ; z) = <lb/> p≥r+1 <lb/> (p − r) <lb/>m  p−r <lb/> z  p <lb/> ∂Z(t − [z <lb/> −1  ]) <lb/> ∂t  p−r <lb/> e <lb/> ξ(t  KP  ;z)  + <lb/> p≥1 <lb/> p α  p  t  p  z <lb/> p−r  K(t  KP  ; z). (3.22) <lb/>Comparing the above two equalities we have <lb/> L <lb/> ext <lb/> −1  K(t  KP  ; z) = <lb/>1 <lb/> z  r−1  ∂  z  K(t  KP  ; z) − <lb/> r − 1 <lb/>2 z  r  K(t  KP  ; z) − zK(t  KP  ; z) = S  z  K(t  KP  ; z). <lb/> (3.23) <lb/>In a similar way we can prove (3.16). The lemma is proved. <lb/> Lemma 3.4 Let f, f <lb/>  *  as in (3.14). We have for any k ≥ 0, <lb/> ∂ <lb/> k <lb/>x  f (x; z) = (−1) <lb/> k  S <lb/> k <lb/>z  f (x; z), <lb/> (3.24) <lb/> ∂ <lb/> k <lb/>x  f <lb/>  *  (x; z) = (S <lb/> ⋆ <lb/>z  ) <lb/> k  f <lb/>  *  (x; z). <lb/> (3.25) <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body> Proof Note that in the case r = 2 we have Z(x, 0, 0, ...) = exp <lb/> x <lb/> 3 <lb/> 6 <lb/> and that in the case r ≥ 3 we <lb/>have Z(t  1  , 0, 0, ...) = 1. Taking t  2  = t  3  = .... = 0 in both sides of (3.15), we find <lb/> f  x  + S  z  f = 0 <lb/>(3.26) <lb/>which implies (3.24). Similarly, taking t  2  = t  3  = ... = 0 in both sides of (3.16), we obtain (3.25). <lb/> Lemma 3.5 Denote A(z) = f (0; z) and A <lb/>  *  (z) = f <lb/>  *  (0; z). Applying the Taylor expansion and <lb/>Lemma 3.4 we have <lb/> f (x; z) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=0 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> n <lb/> n! <lb/>S <lb/> n <lb/>z  A(z) x <lb/> n  , <lb/> (3.27) <lb/> f <lb/>  *  (x; z) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> n! <lb/>S <lb/> ⋆ <lb/>z <lb/>n  A <lb/>  *  (z) x <lb/> n  . <lb/> (3.28) <lb/> Lemma 3.6 The functions A(z), A <lb/>  *  (z) satisfy the following ODEs: <lb/> S <lb/> r <lb/>z  A(z) = (−z) <lb/> r  A(z), <lb/> (3.29) <lb/> S <lb/> ⋆ <lb/>z <lb/>r  A <lb/>  *  (z) = (−z) <lb/> r  A <lb/>  *  (z). <lb/>(3.30) <lb/> Proof Recall that the Lax equations for ψ(t  KP  ; z) and ψ <lb/>  *  (t  KP  ; z) read <lb/> Lψ = z <lb/> r  ψ, <lb/>L <lb/> ⋆  ψ <lb/>  *  = z <lb/> r  ψ <lb/>  *  . <lb/> (3.31) <lb/>Taking t = 0 in these two equations and using the initial data (3.11) we have <lb/> ∂ <lb/> r <lb/>x  f (x; z)|  x=0  = z <lb/> r  f (0; z), <lb/> (−1) <lb/> r  f <lb/>  *  (x; z)|  x=0  = z <lb/> r  f (0; z). <lb/> (3.32) <lb/>Finally by employing Lemma 3.4 we obtain <lb/>(−1) <lb/> r  S <lb/> r <lb/>z  f (x; z)|  x=0  = z <lb/> r  f (0; z), <lb/> (−1) <lb/> r  S <lb/>  * <lb/> z <lb/>r  f <lb/>  *  (x; z)|  x=0  = z <lb/> r  f <lb/>  *  (0; z). <lb/> (3.33) <lb/>The lemma is proved. <lb/> Note that (2.5), (2.10) require the (formal) boundary behaviour <lb/> A(z) = 1 + O(z <lb/> −1  ), <lb/> z → ∞, <lb/> (3.34) <lb/> A <lb/>  *  (z) = 1 + O(z <lb/> −1  ), <lb/> z → ∞. <lb/> (3.35) <lb/>In order to solve the ODEs (3.29), (3.30) let us introduce a change of variable η = z <lb/> r  and let <lb/> H(η) = η <lb/> r−1 <lb/> 2r  exp <lb/> 1 <lb/> r + 1 <lb/> η <lb/> r+1 <lb/>r <lb/> = z <lb/> r−1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> exp <lb/> z <lb/> r+1 <lb/> r + 1 <lb/> . <lb/> (3.36) <lb/>A straightforward computation shows that <lb/>1 <lb/> H <lb/> • S  z  • H = r ∂  η  , <lb/> (3.37) <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body> which allows to transform immediately the ODEs (3.29), (3.30) in a pair of adjoint Pearcey equa-<lb/>tions. Indeed, let us write A(z) = H(η) · ℓ(η): the above ODE (3.29) becomes <lb/>(r∂  η  ) <lb/> r  ℓ(η) = (−1) <lb/> r  η ℓ(η). <lb/> (3.38) <lb/>Its solutions are well known and are given in the form of a Fourier-Laplace integral representation <lb/> ℓ(η) = C  1 <lb/> Γ <lb/> exp <lb/> w <lb/> r+1 <lb/> (r + 1)r <lb/> − <lb/> w <lb/>r <lb/>η <lb/> dw <lb/> (3.39) <lb/>where the contour Γ is any contour extending to infinity along two different asymptotic directions <lb/>in the sectors where ℜ(w <lb/> r+1  ) tends to −∞, and C  1  is a constant. Applying a formal saddle point <lb/>method to meet the condition (3.34), we obtain <lb/> A(z; Γ) = <lb/> i <lb/> √ <lb/> 2π <lb/> z <lb/> r−1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> exp <lb/> z <lb/> r+1 <lb/> r + 1 <lb/> Γ <lb/> exp <lb/> w <lb/> r+1 <lb/> (r + 1)r <lb/> − <lb/> w <lb/>r <lb/>z <lb/> r <lb/> dw <lb/> (3.40) <lb/>where the contour Γ is any contour extending to infinity along two different asymptotic directions <lb/> R  j  := R  +  e <lb/> iπ <lb/>r+1  + <lb/> 2iπ <lb/> r+1  j  , j ≡ 0, . . . , r mod (r + 1). The integrals appearing in (3.40) (in the variable <lb/> ξ = z <lb/> r  ) are famously known as Pearcey integrals and generalize the usual integral representation of <lb/>Airy functions. A relatively straightforward steepest descent analysis shows that if Γ is the contour <lb/>originating at ∞ along R  −1  and ending at ∞ along R  0  then the function has the asymptotic <lb/>expansion <lb/> A(z; Γ) = 1 + O(1/z), |z| → ∞, z ∈ S  Γ  , <lb/> (3.41) <lb/>where S  Γ  = {|arg(z)| &lt; <lb/> π <lb/>r  }. More precisely the expansion contains only powers of z <lb/> −r−1  as stated <lb/>in the following lemma (whose proof is straightforward and thus omitted). <lb/> Lemma 3.7 A(z; Γ) admits the following asymptotic <lb/> A(z; Γ) ∼ 1 + <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=1 <lb/> a  k <lb/> z  (r+1)k  , <lb/>z → ∞, z ∈ S  Γ  , <lb/> (3.42) <lb/> where a  k  are constants. <lb/> Below we denote by a(z) = 1 + <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> k=1 <lb/>a  k <lb/> z  (r+1)k  the formal asymptotic series of A(z; Γ). <lb/> Lemma 3.8 With ω = e <lb/> iπ <lb/>r+1  , we have <lb/> S <lb/> ⋆ <lb/>z  = ω <lb/> −1  S  ωz  . <lb/> (3.43) <lb/> Proof <lb/> S  ωz  = <lb/>1 <lb/> ω  r  z  r−1  ∂  z  − <lb/> r − 1 <lb/>2 ω  r  z  r  − ωz = ω <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/> z  r−1  ∂  z  + <lb/> r − 1 <lb/>2 z  r  − z <lb/> = ω S <lb/> ⋆ <lb/>z  . <lb/> (3.44) <lb/></body>

			<page> 11 <lb/></page>

			<body> Lemma (3.8) implies <lb/> A <lb/>  *  (z; Γ) = A(ωz; Γ) <lb/>= <lb/> iω <lb/> r+1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> √ <lb/> 2π <lb/> z <lb/> r−1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> exp <lb/> − <lb/> z <lb/> r+1 <lb/> r + 1 <lb/> ω  −1  Γ <lb/> exp <lb/> −s <lb/> r+1 <lb/> (r + 1)r <lb/>+ <lb/> s <lb/>r <lb/>z <lb/> r <lb/> ds <lb/> (3.45) <lb/>which satisfies <lb/> A <lb/>  *  (z; Γ) = 1 + O(z <lb/> −1  ), <lb/> z → ∞, z ∈ ωS  Γ  . <lb/> (3.46) <lb/>We recall now that there exists a natural bilinear pairing between solutions of two adjoint equations <lb/>which is called the bilinear concomitant. In the present case, solutions of the two equations can <lb/>be represented in terms of Fourier–Laplace integrals along two relatively dual bases in a certain <lb/>homology of contours and the bilinear concomitant is simply a representation of the intersection <lb/>pairing. For more details (and in more general terms) see [4], Sect. 3. Let us call <lb/> B(z; ˆ <lb/>Γ) = Cz <lb/> r−1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> exp <lb/> − <lb/> z <lb/> r+1 <lb/> r + 1 <lb/> ˆ <lb/>Γ <lb/> exp <lb/> −s <lb/> r+1 <lb/> (r + 1)r <lb/>+ <lb/> s <lb/>r <lb/>z <lb/> r <lb/> ds, <lb/> (3.47) <lb/>wherê <lb/>Γ spans the dual homology of the contours spanned by Γ&apos;s. The concomitant reads: <lb/> B(A(z; Γ), B(z; ˆ <lb/>Γ)) = <lb/> Γ× <lb/> ds dw <lb/>w <lb/> r  − s <lb/> r <lb/> w − s <lb/> exp <lb/> w <lb/> r+1  − s <lb/> r+1 <lb/> r(r + 1) <lb/> − <lb/> w − s <lb/>r <lb/>η <lb/> . <lb/> (3.48) <lb/>Here η = z <lb/> r  . The result of this integral is the intersection number of Γ and <lb/>. Indeed <lb/> Γ× <lb/> ds dw <lb/>w <lb/> r  − s <lb/> r <lb/> w − s <lb/> exp <lb/> w <lb/> r+1  − s <lb/> r+1 <lb/> r(r + 1) <lb/> − <lb/> w − s <lb/>r <lb/>ξ <lb/> = <lb/> Γ× <lb/> ds dw (∂  s  + ∂  w  ) <lb/>exp <lb/> w <lb/> r+1  −s <lb/> r+1 <lb/> r(r+1) <lb/> − <lb/> w−s <lb/>r  ξ <lb/> w − s <lb/> = 2iπ link(Γ, ˆ <lb/>Γ). <lb/>(3.49) <lb/>The bilinear concomitant (3.48) can equivalently be written in terms of a bilinear expression in the <lb/>derivatives of the functions A(z; Γ) and B(z; ˆ <lb/>Γ) by expanding <lb/> w <lb/> r  −s <lb/> r <lb/> w−s  = <lb/>  r−1 <lb/>j=0  w <lb/> j  s <lb/> r−1−j  and thus <lb/>giving the following lemma: <lb/> Lemma 3.9 The following identities hold true: <lb/> r−1 <lb/> k=0 <lb/> S <lb/> ⋆ <lb/>z <lb/>r−1−k <lb/> A(ωz; ˆ <lb/>Γ) <lb/> S <lb/> k <lb/>z  A(z; Γ) = link(Γ, ˆ <lb/>Γ) · z <lb/> r−1  , z ∈ S  Γ  . <lb/> (3.50) <lb/> See Sect. 3 of [4]. <lb/> We remark that the analytic function A(z; Γ) that we have defined has different asymptotic be-<lb/>haviours at ∞ as the sector changes. This is called the Stokes phenomenon. <lb/>To end this section, let us solve the following ODE problem which will be useful for the next <lb/>section: <lb/> − S <lb/> ⋆ <lb/>z <lb/>  D(z) <lb/>z <lb/> = A(ωz) <lb/> (3.51) <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body> with the (formal) asymptotic boundary requirement <lb/> D(z) = 1 + O(z <lb/> −1  ), <lb/> z → ∞. <lb/> (3.52) <lb/>Using the representation (3.37) for the differential operator, it is immediate to verify that <lb/> D(z; Γ) = − <lb/> iω <lb/> r+1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> √ <lb/> 2π <lb/> z <lb/> r+1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> exp <lb/> − <lb/> z <lb/> r+1 <lb/> r + 1 <lb/> ω  −1  Γ <lb/> w <lb/> −1  exp <lb/> − <lb/> w <lb/> r+1 <lb/> (r + 1)r <lb/>+ <lb/> w <lb/>r <lb/>z <lb/> r <lb/> dw. <lb/> (3.53) <lb/>(which is (1.17)) indeed solves the equation. Of course the equation (3.51) only determines the <lb/>solution up to addition of the complementary solution of the associated homogeneous equation. <lb/>This arbitrariness is reflected in the choice of the contour in (3.53); indeed the integrand has a <lb/>simple pole at w = 0 and thus it is important to specify the index of the contour of integration <lb/>relative to w = 0. Now, the steepest descent analysis shows that (3.53) has the behaviour (3.52) <lb/> provided that the contour can be retracted onto the steepest descent path of the exponential phase. <lb/>The steepest descent path clearly recedes to infinity (the principal saddle point is at w = z). Thus <lb/>the contour must have index 0 relative to w = 0. <lb/> Remark 3.10 Another simple argument to determine the index of the integration contour relative <lb/>to w = 0 is that if the contour in (3.53) has index 1, then retracting the contour to the saddle yields <lb/>the residue at w = 0, which adds a multiple of <lb/> √ <lb/> 2πz <lb/> r+1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> exp <lb/> − <lb/> z <lb/> r+1 <lb/> r+1 <lb/> (the complementary solution), <lb/>which has necessarily an exponential growth within the sector S  Γ  , and thus violates the boundary <lb/>condition (3.52). <lb/> Applying the saddle point method one can obtain <lb/> Lemma 3.11 D(z; Γ) admits the following asymptotic <lb/> D(z; Γ) ∼ d(z) = 1 + <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=1 <lb/> d  k <lb/> z  (r+1)k  , z → ∞, z ∈ ω <lb/> −1  S  Γ  . <lb/> (3.54) <lb/> 4 A particular solution to the extended r-reduced KP hier-<lb/>archy <lb/> In this section we finally prove Theorem (1.2). Let us further introduce some useful notations and <lb/>lemmas. <lb/> Notations Denote the vector space of formal series with finitely many terms with positive powers <lb/>by: <lb/> A = <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> n≥−m <lb/> b  n <lb/> z  n <lb/> m ∈ Z, b  n  ∈ C <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> . <lb/> (4.1) <lb/>For any r ≥ 2, let θ = e <lb/> 2πi <lb/> r+1  and let <lb/> A <lb/> (k)  := <lb/> b(z) ∈ A <lb/> b(θz) = θ <lb/> k  b(z) <lb/> , k ∈ Z. <lb/> (4.2) <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body> We also use subscripts to denote the leading order term, for example <lb/> A <lb/> (0) <lb/> 1  = <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> 1 + <lb/> n≥1 <lb/> b  n <lb/> z  n(r+1) <lb/> b  n  ∈ C <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> , A <lb/> (1) <lb/>3z  m  = <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> 3z <lb/> m  + <lb/> n≥1 <lb/> b  n <lb/> z  n(r+1)−m <lb/> b  n  ∈ C <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> , etc. <lb/> Clearly A <lb/> (k)  = z <lb/> k  A <lb/> (0)  , A <lb/> (k)  = A <lb/> (k+r+1)  , ∀ k ∈ Z. <lb/> Lemma 4.1 For any k ∈ Z, S  z  A <lb/> (k)  = A <lb/> (k−r)  , S <lb/> ⋆ <lb/>z  A <lb/> (k)  = A <lb/> (k−r)  . <lb/> Proof It suffices to consider the action of S  z  on a monomial z <lb/> k  : <lb/> S  z  z <lb/> k  = <lb/> k − <lb/> r − 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> z <lb/> k−r  − z <lb/> k+1  = z <lb/> k−r <lb/>  2k − r + 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> − z <lb/> r+1 <lb/> . <lb/> (4.3) <lb/>Similarly for S <lb/> ⋆ <lb/>z  . <lb/> In the last section, we have defined a formal series a(z) as the asymptotic expansion of A(z; Γ) <lb/>in S  Γ  . <lb/> Lemma 4.2 a(z) is the unique formal solution in A  1  to the equation <lb/> S <lb/> r <lb/>z  a(z) = (−z) <lb/> r  a(z). <lb/> (4.4) <lb/> Proof The uniqueness follows from the recursive procedure given by the ODE. <lb/> Lemma (4.1) and Lemma (4.2) immediately imply <lb/> Lemma 4.3 For any n ≥ 0, S <lb/> n <lb/>z  a(z) ∈ A <lb/> (n) <lb/>(−1)  n  z  n  . <lb/> Remark 4.4 We know from Lemma (3.5) and the above lemmas that the point in Sato&apos;s (formal) <lb/>Grassmannian corresponding to Z(t) is given by <lb/> W = Span  C  {a(z), S  z  a(z), S <lb/> 2 <lb/> z  a(z), ...}. <lb/> (4.5) <lb/> This is actually well-known for example, in [14] and in [1]. <lb/> Lemma 4.5 The following identities hold true: <lb/> 1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> z=∞ <lb/> S <lb/> ⋆ <lb/>z <lb/>m  (a(ωz)) S <lb/> n <lb/>z  a(z) dz = 0, ∀ m, n ≥ 0. <lb/>(4.6) <lb/> If b(z) ∈ A  1  satisfies that for all n ≥ 0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> z=∞ <lb/> b(z) S <lb/> n <lb/>z  a(z) dz = 0, <lb/>(4.7) <lb/> then b(z) = a(ωz). <lb/> Proof Due to Lemma 3.5, the identity (4.6) is nothing but the bilinear identity (2.12) evaluated <lb/>at t|  KP,≥2  = t <lb/> ′  |  KP,≥2  = 0. Write <lb/> b(z) = 1 + <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=1 <lb/> b  k <lb/> z  k  ; <lb/>(4.8) <lb/>then b  1  , b  2  , b  3  , ... can be solved recursively from the relations (4.7) by taking n = 1, 2, 3, ... respec-<lb/>tively. <lb/> Before proceeding further, let us mention that Lemma 3.9 and Lemma 4.2 imply <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body> Lemma 4.6 The following identities hold true in A: <lb/> r−1 <lb/> k=0 <lb/> S <lb/> ⋆ <lb/>z <lb/>r−1−k  (a(ωz)) S <lb/> k <lb/>z  a(z) = (−1) <lb/> r−1  r z <lb/> r−1  . <lb/> (4.9) <lb/> Remark 4.7 In the case r = 2, the identity appearing in this lemma was observed in [18] and it <lb/>was used by Buryak [6] to prove the analog of Lemma 4.5 for r = 2. We point out here that, in <lb/>fact, this identity is a simple consequence of a classical object, the bilinear concomitant of adjoint <lb/>equations, introduced by Legendre [13]! <lb/> Lemma 4.8 The formal series d(z) defined in the previous section as the asymptotic expansion of <lb/> D(z; Γ) in ω <lb/> −1  S  Γ  is the unique formal solution in A  1  to the equation <lb/> − S <lb/> ⋆ <lb/>z <lb/>  d(z) <lb/>z <lb/> = a(ωz). <lb/> (4.10) <lb/> Proof The uniqueness of the solution in A  1  follows from recursive procedure given by the above <lb/>ODE. <lb/> Example 4.9 For r = 2 we have <lb/> a(z) = 1 − <lb/> 5 <lb/>24z  3  + <lb/>385 <lb/>1152z  6  − <lb/> 85085 <lb/>82944z  9  + <lb/>37182145 <lb/>7962624z  12  + O(z <lb/> −15  ), <lb/>(4.11) <lb/> d(z) = 1 + <lb/>41 <lb/>24z  3  + <lb/>9241 <lb/>1152z  6  + <lb/>5075225 <lb/>82944z  9  + <lb/>5153008945 <lb/>7962624z  12  + O(z <lb/> −15  ). <lb/>(4.12) <lb/> For r = 3 we have <lb/> a(z) = 1 − <lb/> 7 <lb/>12z  4  + <lb/>385 <lb/>288z  8  − <lb/> 39655 <lb/>10368z  12  + <lb/>665665 <lb/>497664z  16  + O(z <lb/> −20  ), <lb/>(4.13) <lb/> d(z) = 1 + <lb/>31 <lb/>12z  4  + <lb/>4849 <lb/>288z  8  + <lb/>1785295 <lb/>10368z  12  + <lb/>1200383905 <lb/>497664z  16  + O(z <lb/> −20  ). <lb/>(4.14) <lb/> For r = 4 we have <lb/> a(z) = 1 − <lb/> 9 <lb/>8z  5  + <lb/>441 <lb/>128z  10  − <lb/> 30303 <lb/>5120z  15  − <lb/> 25162137 <lb/>163840z  20  + O(z <lb/> −25  ), <lb/>(4.15) <lb/> d(z) = 1 + <lb/>29 <lb/>8z  5  + <lb/>3921 <lb/>128z  10  + <lb/>1990803 <lb/>5120z  15  + <lb/>1089687543 <lb/>163840z  20  + O(z <lb/> −25  ). <lb/>(4.16) <lb/> Theorem 4.10 Let <lb/> Z  E  (t  KP  ) = Z(t) Ψ(t  KP  ), <lb/>(4.17) <lb/> be the partition function of the extended r-reduced KP hierarchy, where Z(t) is the partition function <lb/>of the A  r−1  Frobenius manifold and <lb/> Ψ(t  KP  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> z=∞ <lb/> g(z) ψ(t  KP  ; z) <lb/>dz <lb/>z <lb/> (4.18) <lb/> with <lb/> g(z) = 1 + <lb/> k≥1 <lb/> g  k <lb/> z  k  . <lb/> (4.19) <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body> Then there exists a unique sequence of numbers g  1  , g  2  , g  3  , ... such that <lb/> L <lb/> ext <lb/> −1  Z  E  (t  KP  ) = 0. <lb/>(4.20) <lb/> And these numbers are given by <lb/> g  (r+1)k+p  = 0 (k ≥ 0, p = 1, 2, ..., r); g  (r+1)k  = d  k  , k ≥ 1. <lb/>(4.21) <lb/> Proof Let K(t  KP  ; z) denote the wave potential associated to Z(t). Then by definition <lb/> Z  E  (t  KP  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> z=∞ <lb/> g(z)K(t  KP  ; z) <lb/>dz <lb/>z <lb/>. <lb/> (4.22) <lb/>By using Lemma 3.3 we have <lb/>0 = L <lb/> ext <lb/> −1  Z  E  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> z=∞ <lb/> g(z)L <lb/> ext <lb/> −1  K(t  KP  ; z) <lb/>dz <lb/>z <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> z=∞ <lb/> g(z) S  z  (K(t  KP  ; z)) <lb/>dz <lb/>z <lb/> = <lb/> Z(t) <lb/> 2πi <lb/> z=∞ <lb/> g(z) S  z  (ψ(t  KP  ; z)) <lb/>dz <lb/>z <lb/>. <lb/> (4.23) <lb/>Taking t  1  = t  2  = ... = 0 in the above equation we obtain <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> z=∞ <lb/> g(z) S  z  f (x; z) <lb/>dz <lb/>z <lb/> = 0. <lb/>(4.24) <lb/>Substituting (3.27) in (4.24) we have <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=0 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> n <lb/> n! <lb/> 1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> z=∞ <lb/> S <lb/> ⋆ <lb/>z <lb/>  g(z) <lb/>z <lb/> S <lb/> n <lb/>z  a(z) dz x <lb/> n  = 0. <lb/>(4.25) <lb/>This is equivalent to <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> z=∞ <lb/> S <lb/> ⋆ <lb/>z <lb/>  g(z) <lb/>z <lb/> S <lb/> n <lb/>z  a(z) dz = 0, ∀ n ≥ 0. <lb/>(4.26) <lb/>Due to Lemma 4.5 and the requirement (4.19), we obtain <lb/> S <lb/> ⋆ <lb/>z <lb/>  g(z) <lb/>z <lb/> = −a(ωz). <lb/> (4.27) <lb/>Lemma 4.8 implies <lb/> g(z) = d(z). <lb/> (4.28) <lb/>Now if g(z) = d(z), then we know from Lemma 4.5 that (4.24) holds true. Since the wave function <lb/> ψ(t  KP  ; z) satisfies the linear evolutionary equations (1.8), we know that (4.24) also implies (4.23). <lb/>The theorem is proved. <lb/> Proposition 4.11 The function Ψ(t  KP  ) defined by (4.18) with g(z) = d(z) satisfies <lb/> Ψ(t  KP  )|  t  ≥2  =0  ≡ 1, ∀ t  1  . <lb/> (4.29) <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body> Proof Reminding the reader that t  1  = x, we have for all x <lb/> Ψ(t  KP  )|  t  ≥2  =0  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> z=∞ <lb/> d(z) f (x; z) <lb/>dz <lb/>z <lb/> (4.30) <lb/>= <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> z=∞ <lb/> d(z) <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=0 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> n <lb/> n! <lb/>S <lb/> n <lb/>z  a(z) x <lb/> n  dz <lb/>z <lb/> = 1. <lb/>(4.31) <lb/>The last equality follows from Lemma 4.8 together with Lemma 4.5 for the terms n ≥ 1, while for <lb/> n = 0 we use the fact that both d(z) and a(z) are of the form 1 + O(z <lb/> −r−1  ). The proposition is <lb/>proved. <lb/> Theorem (1.2) is then a combination of Theorem (4.10) and Proposition (4.11). <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgements We thank Ferenc Balogh and Thomas Bothner for helpful discussions. M. <lb/>B. acknowledges the support of the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada <lb/> and the Fonds de recherche du Québec -Nature et technologies. D. Y. wishes to thank Youjin Zhang <lb/>and Boris Dubrovin for their advises and helpful discussions. He acknowledges the support of <lb/>PRIN 2010-11 Grant &quot; Geometric and analytic theory of Hamiltonian systems in finite and infinite <lb/>dimensions &quot; of Italian Ministry of Universities and Researches, and the support of the Marie Curie <lb/>IRSES project RIMMP. He also wishes to thank the Centre de Recherches Mathémetiques and the <lb/>Department of Mathematics and Statistics at Concordia University for generous hospitality, where <lb/>the manuscript was completed. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] Adler, M., Van Moerbeke, P. (1992). A matrix integral solution to two-dimensional W  p  -gravity. <lb/>Communications in mathematical physics, 147 (1), 25–56. <lb/>[2] Alexandrov, A. (2014). Open intersection numbers, matrix models and MKP hierarchy. arXiv <lb/>preprint arXiv:1410.1820. <lb/>[3] Bakalov, B., Milanov, T. (2013). W-constraints for the total descendant potential of a simple <lb/>singularity. Compositio Mathematica, 149 (05), 840–888. <lb/>[4] Bertola, M. (2007). Biorthogonal polynomials for two-matrix models with semiclassical poten-<lb/>tials, J. Approx. Theory, 144 (2), 162–212. <lb/>[5] Buryak, A. (2014). Equivalence of the open KdV and the open Virasoro equations for the <lb/>moduli space of Riemann surfaces with boundary. arXiv preprint arXiv:1409.3888. <lb/>[6] Buryak, A. (2014). Open intersection numbers and the wave function of the KdV hierarchy. <lb/>arXiv preprint arXiv:1409.7957. <lb/>[7] Date, E., Jimbo, M., Kashiwara, M., Miwa, T. (1981). Transformation groups for soliton <lb/>equations, Proceedings of RIMS. <lb/>[8] Dickey, L. A. (2003). Soliton Equations and Hamiltonian Systems (Vol. 26). World Scientific. <lb/>[9] Dubrovin, B., Zhang, Y. (1998). Bi-Hamiltonian hierarchies in 2D topological field theory at <lb/>one-loop approximation, Comm. Math. Phys. 198, 311–361. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [10] Dubrovin, B., Zhang, Y. (2001). Normal forms of hierarchies of integrable PDEs, Frobenius <lb/>manifolds and Gromov-Witten invariants. arXiv preprint math/0108160. <lb/>[11] Faber, C., Shadrin, S., Zvonkine, D. (2010). Tautological relations and the r-spin Witten <lb/>conjecture. In Annales scientifiques de l&apos;Ecole normale suprieure (Vol. 43, No. 4, pp. 621–658). <lb/>Elsevier. <lb/>[12] Fan, H., Jarvis, T., Ruan, Y. (2013). The Witten equation, mirror symmetry and quantum <lb/>singularity theory. Ann. of Math.(2), 178(1), 1–106. <lb/>[13] Ince, E. L. (1944). Ordinary Differential Equations, Dover Publications, New York. <lb/>[14] Kac, V., Schwarz, A. (1991). Geometric interpretation of the partition function of 2D gravity. <lb/>Physics letters B, 257 (3), 329–334. <lb/>[15] Ke, H.-Z. (2014). On a conjectural solution to open KdV and Virasoro. arXiv preprint <lb/>arXiv:1409.7470. <lb/>[16] Liu, S.-Q., Yang, D., Zhang, Y. (2013). Uniqueness Theorem of W-Constraints for Simple <lb/>Singularities. Letters in Mathematical Physics, 103 (12), 1329–1345. <lb/>[17] Pandharipande, R., Solomon, J. P., Tessler, R. J. (2014). Intersection theory on moduli of <lb/>disks, open KdV and Virasoro. arXiv preprint arXiv:1409.2191. <lb/>[18] Pixton, A. (2012). Conjectural relations in the tautological ring of M  g,n  . arXiv preprint <lb/>arXiv:1207.1918. <lb/>[19] Witten, E. (1993). Algebraic geometry associated with matrix models of two-dimensional grav-<lb/>ity (pp. 235–269). Topological methods in modern mathematics (Stony Brook, NY, 1991), <lb/>Publish or Perish, Houston, TX. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>18 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
