<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Monte Carlo generators for central exclusive diffraction <lb/> Maarten Boonekamp, Creighton Hogg, James Monk, Andrew Pilkington &amp; Marek Tasevsky <lb/> Abstract <lb/> We review the three Monte Carlo generators that are available for simulating <lb/>the central exclusive reaction, pp → p + X + p. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1  Introduction <lb/> The central exclusive mechanism is defined as pp → p + X + p with no radiation emitted between the <lb/>intact outgoing beam hadrons and the central system X. The study of central exclusive Higgs boson <lb/>production has been aided with the recent development of Monte Carlo simulations to enable parton, <lb/>hadron and detector level simulation. The three generators that we shall examine here are DPEMC <lb/>[1], EDDE [2] and ExHuME [3]. From an experimental perspective, it is important to examine both <lb/>the similarities and differences between the models in order to assess the physics potential in terms of <lb/>forward proton tagging at the LHC [4]. <lb/>Each of the Monte Carlos implements a different model of central exclusive production that is <lb/>either perturbative or non-perturbative. ExHuME is an implementation of the perturbative calculation of <lb/>Khoze, Martin and Ryskin [5], the so-called &quot; Durham Model &quot; . In this calculation (depicted in fig 1(a)), <lb/>the two gluons couple perturbatively to the off-diagonal unintegrated gluon distribution in the proton. <lb/>The Durham approach includes a Sudakov factor to suppress radiation into the rapidity gap between the <lb/>central system and the outgoing protons and which renders the loop diagram infra-red safe. The bare <lb/>cross section is suppressed by a soft-survival probability, S  2  , that accounts for additional momentum <lb/>transfer between the proton lines that lead to particle production that could fill in the gap. The current <lb/>ExHuME default takes S  2  to be 0.03 at the LHC. <lb/>In contrast, DPEMC and EDDE treat the proton vertices non-perturbatively. This is acheived in the <lb/>context of Regge theory, by pomeron exchange from each of the proton lines. DPEMC follows the Bialas-<lb/>Landshoff approach [6] of parameterising the pomeron flux within the proton. DPEMC also sets the <lb/>default value of S  2  to 0.03 at the LHC. EDDE uses an improved Regge-eikonal approach [7] to calculate <lb/>the soft proton vertices and includes a Sudakov suppression factor to prohibit real gluon emission. There <lb/>is no explicit soft-survival factor present in EDDE: it is assumed that the Regge parameterisation includes <lb/>the effect of additional interactions between the proton lines. For further details of the calculations <lb/>underlying both DPEMC and ExHuME please refer to [8]. <lb/>The connection between the parton level process and the hadronic final state is not the same in <lb/>the three Monte Carlos. Both ExHuME and EDDE are linked to Pythia [9, 10] for final state parton <lb/>showering and hadronisation. DPEMC however, overrides the HERWIG [11] internal γγ interactions in <lb/> e  +  e  −  collisions to simulate double pomeron exchange. <lb/>The processes available are similar in each Monte Carlo. Perhaps the most interesting is Higgs <lb/>boson production with all subsequent decays. In addition, di-jet production is included in all three <lb/>generators. None of the Monte Carlos yet includes the next-to-leading order 3 jet process, which could <lb/>be an important, or even the dominant, background to the central exclusive H → b ¯ b search channel. <lb/>Finally, inclusive double pomeron exchange (shown in figure 1(b)) will also act as a backgound to <lb/>the exclusive process as there are 2 protons in the final state. These processes are always accompanied by <lb/>pomeron remnants in the central system and it may be a challenge experimentally to separate these from <lb/>the system of interest. Two models for these processes are the Cox-Forshaw model (CF), implemented in <lb/>POMWIG [12], and the Boonekamp-Peschanski-Royon model (BPR) [13] that is included in DPEMC. <lb/> ¯ <lb/> p <lb/> p <lb/>φ <lb/>ξ1 <lb/>ξ2 <lb/> ¯ <lb/> p <lb/> p <lb/> Fig. 1: The exclusive production process (a) and the inclusive (double pomeron) production process (b). <lb/> 2  Results <lb/> Unless otherwise stated, all plots shown here were produced by using each of the Monte Carlos as they <lb/>are distributed. constant soft survival factor, S  2  , of 0.03 was used in all three generators. In the case <lb/>of ExHuME, where a parton distribution set must be chosen, the default is the 2002 MRST set, usually <lb/>supplied via the LHAPDF library. <lb/>Using the default settings at the LHC energy of 14 TeV the total cross sections for production of a <lb/>120 GeV Higgs boson are 3.0 fb, 1.94 fb and 2.8 fb for DPEMC, EDDE and ExHuME respectively. How-<lb/>ever, despite these similar cross section predictions, the physics reach of the central exclusive process is <lb/>predicted to differ significantly between the Monte Carlos. Figure 2(a) shows that ExHuME and EDDE <lb/>predict that the cross section for exclusive Higgs boson production will fall much faster than DPEMC <lb/>with an increase in Higgs boson mass. This is a direct effect of the Sudakov suppression factors grow-<lb/>ing as the available phase space for gluon emission increases with the mass of the central system. The <lb/>different gluon momentum fraction, ξ, dependences lead to the differences in figure 2(b). With a fixed <lb/>central mass an increase in collision energy is identical to a decrease in ξ, and the flatter ξ distributions <lb/>of DPEMC and EDDE are reflected in the flatter <lb/> √ s dependence compared to ExHuME. <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> H <lb/> M <lb/> 50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>300 <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> H <lb/> M <lb/> 50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>300 <lb/> Higgs  production cross section [fb] <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/> ExHuMe 1.3 <lb/>DPEMC 2.4 <lb/>EDDE 1.2 <lb/> Exclusive DPE Higgs production <lb/>at LHC <lb/> [TeV] <lb/> pp <lb/> s <lb/> 4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/>16 <lb/>18 <lb/>20 <lb/> [TeV] <lb/> pp <lb/> s <lb/> 4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/>16 <lb/>18 <lb/>20 <lb/> Higgs production cross section [fb] <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/> ExHuMe 1.3 <lb/>DPEMC 2.4 <lb/>EDDE 1.2 <lb/> Exclusive DPE Higgs production <lb/>=120 GeV <lb/> H <lb/> for M <lb/> Fig. 2: (a) The left hand plot shows the higgs cross section as a function of higgs mass. (b) The right hand plot <lb/>shows the increase in cross section with the collision energy (fixed gap survival factor). <lb/> The physics potential is dependent not only on the total cross section, but also on the rapidity <lb/>distribution of the central system, which is shown in figure 3(b) together with the ξ distribution for the <lb/>gluons. The more central rapidity distribution of ExHuME is due to the gluon distributions falling more <lb/>sharply than the pomeron parameterisation present in DPEMC. <lb/> ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> ξ <lb/> , <lb/> 1 <lb/> ξ <lb/> max( <lb/> 0 0.02 0.04 0.06 0.08 0.1 0.12 0.14 <lb/> Nev <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> DPEMC 2.4 <lb/>ExHuMe 1.3 <lb/>EDDE 1.2 <lb/> Higgs rapidity <lb/> -4 -3 -2 -1 0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>0 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1200 <lb/>1400 <lb/>1600 <lb/> Fig. 3: The max(ξ  1  , ξ  2  )(a) and rapidity(b) of the 120 GeV Higgs. ExHuME predicts a steeper fall off in the <lb/>number of events at high ξ and hence favours a less broad rapidity distribution compared to the soft non-perturbative <lb/>models. Note that a cut is applied in DPEMC at ξ = 0.1, as required by the Bialas-Landshoff approach. <lb/> The acceptances of any forward proton taggers that might be installed at the LHC are sensitive <lb/>to the rapidity distributions of the central system. The differences seen in figure 3(b) are reflected in <lb/>different acceptance curves shown in figure 4. The predicted acceptances using taggers at 420 and 220 <lb/>metres as a function of the mass of the central system were obtained using a fast simulation of the <lb/>CMS detector. The fast simulation includes a parameterisation of the responses of the forward taggers <lb/>based on a detailed simulation of the detectors [14]. As seen in figure 4, as the mass of the central system <lb/>increases the combined acceptance using detectors at both 220 and 420 metres increases, with the relative <lb/>difference between the predictions from the three generators decreasing (from about 40% down to 15% <lb/>for the most extreme relative differences). For a Higgs boson of mass 120 GeV the acceptances are <lb/>predicted to be 46, 50 and 57% for EDDE, DPEMC and ExHuME respectively. <lb/>Changes from the default generator settings can have an effect on all of these distributions. As an <lb/>example Fig. 5(a) shows the rapidity distribution from ExHuME using the CTEQ6M set compared to the <lb/>MRST 2002 set of parton distribution functions. The CTEQ pdf has a flatter ξ dependence in the sensitive <lb/>region of Q  ⊥  3 GeV, which leads to a broader peak and sharper fall in the rapidity distribution and a <lb/>larger cross section of 3.75 fb. This in turn should improve the efficiency of the forward proton taggers <lb/>because not only are there more events, but there are more events at low rapidity. It is also possible <lb/>to change the DPEMC code to add a harder ξ dependence of the form (1 − ξ) <lb/> α <lb/> to the pomeron flux <lb/>parameterisation. This would favour a more central rapidity distribution, thus increasing the acceptance <lb/>in the forward pots. <lb/>In di-jet production the di-jet mass fraction, R  jj  is defined as R  jj  = M  jj  / <lb/> √ <lb/> ˆ <lb/> s, where M  jj  is the <lb/>mass of the di-jet system and <lb/> √ <lb/> ˆ <lb/> s is the total invariant mass of the central system. R  jj  should be large in a <lb/>central exclusive event. In current searches for central exclusive di-jet production at the Tevatron [15], the <lb/>CDF collaboration have experimentally defined exclusive events to be those where R  jj  &gt; 0.8. It should <lb/>be noted that M  jj  depends on the particular jet reconstruction algorithm used and the <lb/> √ <lb/> ˆ <lb/> s measurement <lb/>is dependent either on tagging the outgoing protons or on reconstructing the missing mass using the <lb/>calorimeter. In figure 6(a) we show the prediction for the R  jj  fraction in exclusive events at the LHC, <lb/>whilst in figure 6(b) we show two examples of the inclusive background with pomeron remnants from <lb/>Pomwig and DPEMC. It is clear that the R  jj  &gt; 0.8 definition for central exclusive production leads to <lb/>an overlap between the exclusive and inclusive regions for all of the Monte Carlo predictions. <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> H <lb/> M <lb/> 60 <lb/>80 100 120 140 160 180 200 <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> H <lb/> M <lb/> 60 <lb/>80 100 120 140 160 180 200 <lb/>Acceptance <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1 <lb/> ExHuMe 1.3 <lb/>ExHuMe 1.3 <lb/>DPEMC 2.4 <lb/>DPEMC 2.4 <lb/>EDDE 1.2 <lb/>EDDE 1.2 <lb/> 420+220m RP <lb/>420m RP <lb/> Fig. 4: The predicted acceptances for the proposed forward taggers at 420 metres and for a combination of taggers <lb/>at 220 and 420 metres from the central detector. <lb/> 4 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 2 <lb/>4 <lb/>Rapidity <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> Σ <lb/>y <lb/> CTEQ6M <lb/>MRST 2002 <lb/> Fig. 5: The ExHuME rapidity distributions for production of a 120 GeV Higgs using MRST 2002 pdfs and the <lb/>CTEQ6M pdfs. <lb/> miss.mass <lb/> /M <lb/> jj <lb/> M <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/> Nev <lb/> 0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>6000 <lb/> DPEMC 2.4 <lb/>ExHuMe 1.3 <lb/> JJ <lb/> R <lb/>0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1 <lb/> JJ <lb/> dR <lb/> dN <lb/> N <lb/> 1 <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/> CF <lb/> BPR <lb/> Fig. 6: R  jj  distributions for (a) exclusive di-jet production using DPEMC and ExHuME and (b) the background <lb/>inclusive di-jet production as predicted by the Cox-Forshaw (CF) and Boonekamp-Peschanski-Royon (BPR) mod-<lb/>els. <lb/> 3  Summary <lb/> At a Higgs boson mass of 120GeV, all three Monte Carlo simulations give similar predictions for the <lb/>cross section. However, the physics potential decreases for models that include Sudakov suppression, <lb/>which will limit Higgs boson searches. The differing rapidity distributions of the central system result <lb/>in different efficiencies for a forward proton tagging programme. In order to fully study the background <lb/>to the H → b ¯ b channel, future additions to the Monte Carlo programs should include the next to leading <lb/>order three jet process. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgements <lb/> We would like to thank Brian Cox, Jeff Forshaw, Valery Khoze, Misha Ryskin and Roman Ryutin for <lb/>discussion throughout the proceedings. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] M. Boonekamp and T. Kucs, Comput. Phys. Commun. 167 (2005). E-Print Archive: <lb/>hep-ph/0312273. <lb/>[2] R. Ryutin, Edde monte carlo event generator. E-Print Archive: hep-ph/0409180. <lb/>[3] J. Monk and A. Pilkington, Exhume: A monte carlo event generator for exclusive diffraction. <lb/> E-Print Archive: hep-ph/0502077. <lb/>[4] M. G. Albrow et al., CERN-LHCC 25 (2005). <lb/>[5] V. A. Khoze, A. D. Martin and M. G. Ryskin, Eur. Phys. J C23, 311 (2002). E-print Archive: <lb/>hep-ph/0111078. <lb/>[6] A. Bialas and P. V. Landshoff, Phys. Lett. B B256, 540 (1991). <lb/>[7] V. A. Petrov and R. Ryutin, Eur. Phys. Journ C36, 509 (2004). <lb/>[8] J. Forshaw, Diffractive higgs production: theory. These proceedings. <lb/>[9] T. Sjostrand, P. Eden, C. Friberg, L. Lonnblad, G. Miu, S. Mrenna and E. Norrbin, Comput. Phys. <lb/>Commun 135, 238 (2001). E-Print Archive: hep-ph/0010017. <lb/>[10] T. Sjostrand, L. Lonnblad, S. Mrenna and P. Skands, Pythia 6.3: Physics and manual. E-Print <lb/>Archive: hep-ph/0308153. <lb/>[11] G. Corcella, I. G. Knowles, G. Marchesini, S. Moretti, K. Odagiri, P. Richardson, M. H. Seymour <lb/>and B. R. Webber, JHEP 0101, 010 (2001). <lb/>[12] B. E. Cox and J. R. Forshaw, Comput. Phys. Commun 144, 104 (2002). E-Print Archive: <lb/>hep-ph/0010303. <lb/>[13] M. Boonekamp, R. Peschanski and C. Royon, Phys. Rev. Lett 87, 251806 (2001). <lb/>[14] V. Avati and K. Osterberg, Roman pot acceptances. These proceedings. <lb/>[15] T. Affolder et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 85, 4215 (2000). </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
