<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="footnote"> arXiv:math/0108100v2  [math.AG] 16 Oct 2001 <lb/></note>

			<front> GROMOV – WITTEN INVARIANTS AND QUANTIZATION OF <lb/>QUADRATIC HAMILTONIANS <lb/> ALEXANDER B. GIVENTAL <lb/> Abstract. We describe a formalism based on quantization of quadratic hamil-<lb/>tonians and symplectic actions of loop groups which provides a convenient <lb/>home for most of known general results and conjectures about Gromov-Witten <lb/>invariants of compact symplectic manifolds and, more generally, Frobenius <lb/>structures at higher genus. We state several results illustrating the formalism <lb/>and its use. In particular, we establish Virasoro constraints for semisimple <lb/>Frobenius structures and outline a proof of the Virasoro conjecture for Gro-<lb/>mov – Witten invariants of complex projective spaces and other Fano toric <lb/>manifolds. Details will be published elsewhere. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Gromov – Witten invariants. <lb/> Let X be a compact almost Kähler manifold of complex dimension D. Denote <lb/>by X  g,m,d  the moduli (orbi)space of degree d stable holomorphic maps to X of <lb/>genus g curves with m marked points [27, 3]. The degree d takes values in the <lb/>lattice H  2  (X). The moduli space is compact and can be equipped [2, 29, 36] <lb/>with a rational coefficient virtual fundamental cycle [X  g,m,d  ] of complex dimension <lb/> m + (1 − g)(D − 3) + <lb/> d  c  1  (T X). <lb/> The total descendent potential of X is defined as <lb/> D  X  := exp <lb/> g−1  F <lb/> g <lb/>X  , <lb/> where F <lb/> g <lb/>X  is the genus g descendent potential <lb/> m,d <lb/> Q <lb/> d <lb/> m! <lb/> [X  g,m,d  ] <lb/> ∧ <lb/> m <lb/>i=1  ( <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=0 <lb/> (ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  t  k  )ψ <lb/> k <lb/>i  ). <lb/>Here ψ <lb/> k <lb/>i  are the powers of the 1-st Chern class of the universal cotangent line bundle <lb/>over X  g,m,d  corresponding to the i-th marked point, ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  t  k  are pull-backs by the <lb/>evaluation map ev  i  : X  g,m,d  → X at the i-th marked point of the cohomology <lb/>classes t  0  , t  1  , ... ∈ H <lb/>  *  (X, Q), and Q <lb/> d  is the representative of d in the semigroup <lb/>ring of the semigroup of degrees of holomorphic curves in X. The genus g Gromov <lb/>– Witten potential of X is defined as the restriction F <lb/> g <lb/>X  (t) := F <lb/> g <lb/>X  |  t0=t, t1=t2=...=0  . <lb/>The genus g descendent potentials are considered as formal functions on the <lb/>super-space of vector Laurent polynomials t(z) = t  0  + t  1  z + t  2  z <lb/> 2  + ... in one indeter-<lb/>minate z with coefficients in H := H <lb/>  *  (X; Q[[Q]]), the cohomology space of X over <lb/>the Novikov ring. The latter is a suitable power series completion of the semigroup <lb/>ring of degrees. <lb/></body>

			<front> Date: April 12, 2001, revised on July 15 and August 14, 2001. <lb/>Research partially supported by NSF Grant DMS-0072658. <lb/></front>

			<page> 1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> </page>

			<note place="headnote"> ALEXANDER B. GIVENTAL <lb/></note>

			<body> 1.1. Remark. We will assume further on that H has no odd part and leave the <lb/>super-space generalization of the material of sections 2 – 5 to the reader. It is not <lb/>clear at the moment if the content of sections 6 – 10 admits such a generalization. <lb/> 1.2. Example. When X = point, the moduli spaces of stable maps coincide <lb/>with the Deligne – Mumford compactifications M  g,m  of moduli spaces of genus <lb/> g Riemann surfaces with m marked points. According to Witten&apos;s conjecture [38] <lb/>proved by Kontsevich [26], the total descendent potential in this case coincides with <lb/>the tau-function of the KdV-hierarchy satisfying the string equation [25]. We will <lb/>denote D  point  by τ (; t) and call it the Witten – Kontsevich tau-function. <lb/> Taylor coefficients of the Gromov – Witten and descendent potentials depend <lb/>only on the deformation class of the symplectic structure and are often referred to <lb/>respectively as Gromov – Witten invariants and their gravitational descendents. <lb/> 2. Quadratic hamiltonians and quantization. <lb/> Let H, (·, ·) be an N -dimensional vector space equipped with a non-degenerate <lb/>symmetric bilinear form. Let H be the space of Laurent polynomials in one inde-<lb/>terminate z with vector coefficients from H. We introduce a symplectic bilinear <lb/>form in H by <lb/>Ω(f, g) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> (f (−z), g(z))dz = −Ω(g, f ). <lb/>Let H = H  +  ⊕ H  −  correspond to the decomposition f (z, z <lb/> −1  ) = f  +  (z) + <lb/> f  −  (1/z)/z of the Laurent polynomials into polynomial and polar parts. The sub-<lb/>spaces H  ±  are Lagrangian. In particular the projection H → H  +  along H  −  defines <lb/>a polarization of (H, Ω). We quantize infinitesimal symplectic transformations L <lb/> on H to order ≤ 2 linear differential operators <lb/> . In a Darboux coordinate system <lb/> {p  α  , q  β  } compatible with our decomposition H = H  +  ⊕ H  −  we have <lb/>(p  α  p  β  )ˆ = ∂  qα  ∂  q  β  , (p  α  q  β  )ˆ = q  β  ∂  qα  , (q  α  q  β  )ˆ = q  α  q  β  /. <lb/> Note that [ ˆ <lb/> F , ˆ <lb/> G] = {F, G}ˆ  C(F, G) where the cocycle C satisfies <lb/> C(p <lb/> 2 <lb/> α  , q <lb/> 2 <lb/> α  ) = 2, C(p  α  p  β  , q  α  q  β  ) = 1 for α  = β, <lb/> and C = 0 for any other pairs of quadratic Darboux monomials. <lb/> 2.1. Remark: Fock spaces. The differential operators <lb/>  act on functions of  and <lb/> q = q  0  +q  1  z +q  2  z <lb/> 2  +... where q  0  , q  1  , q  2  , ... ∈ H. We will often refer to such functions <lb/>as elements of the Fock space. However we will be concerned with various functions <lb/>which belong to different formal series completions of the polynomial Fock space, <lb/>and we will not describe the completions explicitly in this paper. <lb/> 2.2. Dilaton shift. The total descendent potential D  X  will be considered as a <lb/>vector in the Fock space corresponding to the space H = H <lb/>  *  (X; Q[[Q]]) equipped <lb/>with the Poincaré intersection form (·, ·). More precisely, we introduce the dilaton <lb/>shift q(z) = t(z) − z which identifies the indeterminates t  0  , t  1  , ... in the descendent <lb/>potential with coordinates q  0  , q  1  , ... in H  +  . Slightly abusing notation we will always <lb/>identify functions of t with the functions of q ∈ H  +  obtained from them by the <lb/>dilaton shift. In particular, the genus g potentials F <lb/> g <lb/>X  are considered as formal <lb/>functions of t near the origin (0, 0, 0, ...) or, equivalently, as formal functions of q <lb/> near (0, −1, 0, ...). The same convention applies to the Witten – Kontsevich tau-<lb/>function τ = D  point  . <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> GROMOV – WITTEN INVARIANTS AND QUANTIZATION <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body> 3. The Witten – Kontsevich tau-function. <lb/> Denote D = z(d/dz)z and put L  m  = z <lb/> −1/2  D <lb/> m+1  z <lb/> −1/2  so that <lb/> L  −1  = 1/z, L  0  = z <lb/>d <lb/>dz <lb/> + 1/2, L  1  = z <lb/> 3  d <lb/> 2 <lb/> dz  2  + 3z <lb/> 2  d <lb/>dz <lb/> + <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/> z, <lb/>L  2  = z <lb/> 5  d <lb/> 3 <lb/> dz  3  + <lb/>15 <lb/>2 <lb/> z <lb/> 4  d <lb/> 2 <lb/> dz  2  + <lb/>45 <lb/>4 <lb/> z <lb/> 3  d <lb/>dz <lb/> + <lb/>15 <lb/>8 <lb/> z <lb/> 2  , ... <lb/> It is easy to check that Ω(Df, g) = Ω(f, Dg) and that Ω(z <lb/> −1/2  f, g) = −iΩ(f, z <lb/> −1/2  g) <lb/> (whatever it means). This implies Ω(L  m  f, g) = −Ω(f, L  m  g) and shows that the <lb/>operators L  m  are infinitesimal symplectic transformations on H. On the other <lb/>hand, D is conjugate to z <lb/> 2  d/dz = −d/dw where w = 1/z, and hence L  m  com-<lb/>mute as −wd <lb/> m+1  /dw <lb/> m+1  and therefore (via the Fourier transform) — as the vec-<lb/>tor fields −x <lb/> m+1  d/dx on the line. Thus the Poisson brackets satisfy {L  m  , L  n  } = <lb/>(m − n)L  m+n  , and we have a representation of the Lie algebra of vector fields on <lb/>the line to the Lie algebra of quadratic hamiltonians on H. <lb/> In the case of 1-dimensional H with the standard inner product, using the Dar-<lb/>boux coordinate system f = ... + p  1  /z <lb/> 2  − p  0  /z + q  0  + q  1  z + ... on H, we get (here <lb/> ∂  k  = ∂/∂q  k  ): <lb/>ˆ <lb/> L  −1  = q <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  /2 + <lb/> m≥0  q  m+1  ∂  m <lb/> ˆ <lb/> L  0  = <lb/> m≥0  (m + 1/2)q  m  ∂  m <lb/> ˆ <lb/> L  1  = ∂ <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  /8 + <lb/> m≥0  (m + 1/2)(m + 3/2)q  m  ∂  m+1 <lb/>  2  = 3∂  0  ∂  1  /4 + <lb/> m≥0  (m + 1/2)(m + 3/2)(m + 5/2)q  m  ∂  m+2  . <lb/> We have [ ˆ <lb/> L  m  , ˆ <lb/> L  n  ] = (m − n) ˆ <lb/> L  m+n  unless m, n = ±1, in which case: [ ˆ <lb/> L  1  , ˆ <lb/> L  −1  ] = <lb/>2[ ˆ <lb/> L  0  + 1/16]. Thus the operators <lb/>  m  + δ  m,0  /16 form a representation of the Lie <lb/>algebra of vector fields on the line. <lb/>Due to [25], the following result is a reformulation of the Kontsevich theorem <lb/>[26] confirming the Witten conjecture [38]. <lb/> 3.1. Theorem. The Witten – Kontsevich tau-function is annihilated by the <lb/>operators  <lb/>  m  + δ  m,0  /16, m = −1, 0, 1, 2, ..., and is completely characterized by this <lb/>property (up to a scalar factor). <lb/> 4. Hodge integrals. <lb/> Let E denote the Hodge bundle over the moduli space X  g,m,d  . By definition <lb/>the fiber of E over the point represented by a stable map Σ → X is the complex <lb/>space of dimension g dual to H <lb/> 1  (Σ, O  Σ  ). In fact E is the pull-back of by the <lb/> contraction map ct : X  g,m,d  → M  g,m  of the Hodge bundle over the Deligne – <lb/>Mumford space. It is known [32] that even components ch  2k  (E) of the Chern <lb/>character vanish. We define the total Hodge potential of X as an extension of <lb/>the total descendent potential depending on the sequence s = (s  1  , s  2  , ...) of new <lb/>variables and incorporating intersection indices with characteristic classes of the <lb/>Hodge bundles (as in [14]): <lb/> E  X  (; t; s) := exp <lb/> g <lb/> g−1 <lb/> m,d <lb/> Q <lb/> d <lb/> m! <lb/> [X  g,m,d  ] <lb/> e <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> k=1  s  k  ch  2k−1  (E)  ∧ <lb/> m <lb/>i=1  ( <lb/> k <lb/> (ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  t  k  )ψ <lb/> k <lb/>i  ). <lb/>We consider E  X  , subject to the dilaton shift, as a family of elements in the Fock <lb/>space depending on the parameters s. <lb/></body>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> ALEXANDER B. GIVENTAL <lb/></note>

			<body> On the other hand, it is obvious that multiplication by z <lb/> 2k−1  defines an in-<lb/>finitesimal symplectic transformation on (H, Ω), and we denote by (z <lb/> 2k−1  )ˆ the <lb/>corresponding quantization. <lb/> 4.1. Theorem. <lb/> E  X  = exp[ <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=1 <lb/> B  2k <lb/> (2k)! <lb/> s  k  (z <lb/> 2k−1  )ˆ] D  X <lb/> where B  2k  are Bernoulli numbers: x/(1 − e <lb/> −x  ) = 1 + x/2 + <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> k=1  B  2k  x <lb/> 2k  /(2k)!. <lb/> 4.2. Remark. The theorem is a reformulation of a result by Faber – Pandhari-<lb/>pande [14] which adjusts to arbitrary target spaces the famous Mumford&apos;s Riemann <lb/>– Roch – Grothendieck formula [32] expressing ch(E) via ψ  i  . <lb/> 5. Gravitational ancestors. <lb/> Consider the composition π : X  g,m+l,d  → M  g,m+l  → M  g,m  of the contraction <lb/>map with the operation of forgetting all marked points except the first m. Let <lb/>¯ <lb/> ψ  i  := π <lb/>  *  (ψ  i  ) denote pull-backs of the classes ψ  i  , i = 1, ..., m, from M  g,m  . We <lb/>introduce the total ancestor potential <lb/> A  t  (; t) := exp <lb/> ∞ <lb/> g=0 <lb/> g−1  ¯ <lb/> F <lb/> g <lb/>t  , <lb/> where the genus g ancestor potential ¯ <lb/> F <lb/> g <lb/>t  is defined by <lb/>¯ <lb/> F <lb/> g <lb/>t  := <lb/> m,l,d <lb/> Q <lb/> d <lb/> m!l! <lb/> [X  g,m+l,d  ] <lb/> ∧ <lb/> m <lb/>i=1  ( <lb/> k <lb/> (ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  t  k  ) ¯ <lb/> ψ <lb/> k <lb/>i  ) ∧ <lb/> m+l <lb/>i=m+1  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  t. <lb/> By definition the sum does not contain the terms with (g, m) = (0, 0), (0, 1), (0, 2) <lb/>and (1, 0). We treat A  t  subject to the dilaton shift q(z) = t(z) − z ∈ H  +  as an <lb/>element in the Fock space depending on the parameter t ∈ H. <lb/> Recall that F <lb/> 1  (t) denotes the genus 1 Gromov – Witten potential, i. e. F <lb/> 1 <lb/> X  (t) at <lb/> t  0  = t, t  1  = t  2  = ... = 0. <lb/>Let us introduce the operator S  t  on the Laurent 1/z-series completion of the <lb/>space H defined by <lb/>(a, S  t  b) := a, <lb/> b <lb/>z − ψ <lb/> := (a, b) + <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=0 <lb/> a, bψ <lb/> k  z <lb/> −1−k  . <lb/> The correlator notation here refers to the following 2-point gravitational descendent <lb/> in genus 0: <lb/> aψ <lb/> k  , bψ <lb/> l  := <lb/> m,d <lb/> Q <lb/> d <lb/> m! <lb/> [X  0,m+2,d  ] <lb/> (ev <lb/>  * <lb/> 1  a)ψ <lb/> k <lb/> 1  (∧ <lb/> m+1 <lb/>i=2  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  t ) (ev <lb/>  * <lb/> m+2  b) ψ <lb/> l <lb/>m+2  . <lb/> It is one of the basic facts of quantum cohomology theory (see the next section) <lb/>that S <lb/>  * <lb/> t  (−1/z)S  t  (1/z) = 1. (The asterisk here means transposition with respect to <lb/>the inner product (·, ·) on H.) In other words, on a suitable completion of (H, Ω), <lb/>the operator S  t  defines a symplectic transformation depending on the parameter <lb/> t ∈ H. We put <lb/>  t  := exp(ln S  t  )ˆ. <lb/> 5.1. Theorem. <lb/> D  X  = e <lb/> F <lb/> 1  (t)  ˆ <lb/> S <lb/> −1 <lb/> t <lb/> A  t  . <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> GROMOV – WITTEN INVARIANTS AND QUANTIZATION <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body> 5.2. Remark. The theorem is a reformulation of results by Kontsevich – Manin <lb/>[28] computing gravitational ancestors in terms of descendents and vice versa. <lb/>Moreover, using these results, Getzler [15] proves the 3g − 2-jet conjecture of <lb/>Eguchi – Xiong and Dubrovin about genus g descendent potential F <lb/> g <lb/> X  (we are not <lb/>going to formulate it here — see [13] for details) by showing that it is equivalent to <lb/>the following property of the genus g ancestor potentials: <lb/> ∂ <lb/> m <lb/> ∂t <lb/> α1 <lb/>k1+1  ...∂t <lb/> αm <lb/>km+1 <lb/> ( ¯ <lb/> F <lb/> g <lb/>t  )|  t0=0  = 0 if k  1  + ... + k  m  &gt; 3g − 3. <lb/>The latter property is obvious: ¯ <lb/> ψ <lb/> k1+1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> ... ¯ <lb/> ψ <lb/> km+1 <lb/>m <lb/> = 0 since dim M  g,m  = 3g − 3 + m. <lb/> In particular, ¯ <lb/> F <lb/> 0 <lb/> t  |  t0=0  = 0. One can use this property in order to extract the <lb/>genus 0 descendent potential F <lb/> 0  as follows. <lb/> 5.3. Proposition. Quantized symplectic operators of the form S(1/z) = 1 + <lb/> S  1  /z + S  2  /z <lb/> 2  + ... act on elements G of the Fock space as <lb/> ( ˆ <lb/> S <lb/> −1  G)(q) = e <lb/> W (q,q)/2  G([Sq]  +  ), <lb/> where [Sq]  +  is the power series truncation of S(z <lb/> −1  )q(z), and the quadratic form <lb/> W = <lb/> (W  kl  q  k  , q  l  ) is defined by <lb/> k,l≥0 <lb/> W  kl <lb/> w  k  z  l  := <lb/> S <lb/>  *  (w <lb/> −1  )S(z <lb/> −1  ) − 1 <lb/> w  −1  + z  −1 <lb/> . <lb/> In particular, F <lb/> 0 <lb/> X  (q) = W  t  (q, q)/2 if the parameter t in S  t  is set to make the <lb/>ancestor variable t  0  = 0. <lb/> 5.4. Corollary. The genus 0 descendent potential equals <lb/> F <lb/> 0 <lb/> X  (t) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> t(ψ) − ψ, t(ψ) − ψ |  t=t(t) <lb/> where t(t) is the critical point of the function 1, t(ψ) − ψ of t ∈ H depending on <lb/>the parameters t = (t  0  , t  1  , ...). <lb/> 5.5. Remarks. The corollary is the famous reconstruction results for genus 0 <lb/>gravitational descendents due to Dubrovin [6] and Dijkgraaf – Witten [5]. <lb/>The &quot; mysterious &quot; requirement that t = t(t) is the critical point of 1, t(ψ) − ψ <lb/> arises here simply to set the argument [S  t  q]  +  in the ancestor potential equal 0 at <lb/> z = 0. <lb/>We would like to mention the following heuristic observation (one can make on <lb/>the basis of 5.3, the dual proposition 7.3 and the theorems 4.1, 5.1 and underly-<lb/>ing geometry) about the nature of out formulas. It appears that their four basic <lb/>ingredients — symplectic transformations, quantization, dilaton shift and the cen-<lb/>tral charge — are governed by the four missing Deligne – Mumford spaces with <lb/>(g, m) = (0, 1), (0, 2), (0, 0) and (1, 0). <lb/> 6. Frobenius structures. <lb/> The operator series S  t  (1/z) introduced in the previous section is known to have <lb/>the following properties [19, 21, 30]. <lb/>The operator-valued 1-form A(t) := z (d  t  S  t  (1/z)) S <lb/> −1 <lb/> t  (1/z) does not depend <lb/>on z and thus defines a linear pencil of connections ∇  z  := d − z <lb/> −1  A(t)∧ on the <lb/>tangent bundle T H flat for all values of the parameter z <lb/> −1  . The flatness condition <lb/></body>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> ALEXANDER B. GIVENTAL <lb/></note>

			<body> thus reads A ∧ A = 0 and dA = 0. In coordinates t = <lb/> t <lb/> α  φ  α  the first condition <lb/>means commutativity A  α  A  β  = A  β  A  α  of the components of A = <lb/> A  α  (t)dt <lb/> α  . The <lb/>natural correspondence ∂  α  → A  α  (t) = i  ∂α  A defines commutative associative multi-<lb/>plications •  t  on the tangent spaces T  t  H called the quantum cup-product. Its struc-<lb/>ture constants (φ  α  •  t  φ  β  , φ  γ  ) actually coincide with the third directional derivatives <lb/> ∂  α  ∂  β  ∂  γ  F <lb/> 0 <lb/> X  (t) of the genus 0 Gromov – Witten potential F <lb/> 0 <lb/> X  . In particular, this ex-<lb/>plains why dA = 0 and also shows that A <lb/>  * <lb/> α  = A  α  so that the quantum cup-product <lb/>is Frobenius: (a • b, c) = (a, b • c). The quantum cup-product on T H is invariant <lb/>under the translations in the direction of the unit element 1 ∈ H = H <lb/>  *  (X; Q[[Q]]) <lb/> and 1•  t  = id. <lb/>The picture just described has been axiomatized [6] under the name Frobenius <lb/>structure. We refer to [6, 30, 19, 21, 22] for discussions of the following definition <lb/>and derivations of the properties reviewed below. <lb/> 6.1. Definition. A Frobenius structure on a manifold H consists of: <lb/>(i) a flat pseudo-Riemannian metric (·, ·), <lb/> (ii) a function F whose 3-rd covariant derivatives F  abc  are structure constants (a •  t <lb/> b, c) of a Frobenius algebra structure, i.e. associative commutative multiplication •  t <lb/> satisfying (a •  t  b, c) = (a, b •  t  c), on the tangent spaces T  t  H which depends smoothly <lb/>on t; <lb/> (iii) the vector field of unities 1 of the •  t  -product which has to be covariantly <lb/>constant and preserve the multiplication and the metric. <lb/>In the flat affine coordinates t = <lb/> t <lb/> α  φ  α  of the metric (·, ·), consider the de-<lb/>formation ∇  z  := d − z <lb/> −1 <lb/> (φ  α  •  t  ) dt  α  ∧ of the Levi-Civita connection. It fol-<lb/>lows from the definition that ∇ <lb/> 2 <lb/> z  = 0 for all z. Furthermore, one can construct <lb/>a fundamental solution to the system ∇  z  S = 0 in the form of a power series <lb/> S(1/z) = 1+S  1  /z +S  2  /z <lb/> 2  +... satisfying S <lb/>  *  (−1/z)S(1/z) = 1. Such S is unique up <lb/>to right multiplication by a constant operator series C(1/z) = 1+ C  1  /z + C  2  /z <lb/> 2  + ... <lb/> satisfying C <lb/>  *  (−1/z)C(1/z) = 1. We will call a Frobenius manifold equipped with <lb/>a choice of the solution S calibrated. <lb/> 6.3. The Euler field on a Frobenius manifold is a vector field E which in a flat <lb/>affine coordinate system on H has the form of a linear inhomogeneous vector field <lb/>and such that •, 1 and (·, ·) are eigenvectors of the Lie derivative along E with the <lb/>eigenvalues 0, −1 and 2 − D respectively. The Frobenius manifold equipped with <lb/>an Euler vector field is called conformal of conformal dimension D. We will require <lb/>that calibrations S of conformal Frobenius structures are homogeneous in the sense <lb/>that the bilinear form (a, S(1/z)b) on T H is an eigenvector of z∂  z  + E with the <lb/>eigenvalue 2 − D. This reduces the choice of S to finitely many constants, and we <lb/>refer to [7] for precise description of the ambiguity. <lb/>Following [7], we will assume the linear part of the Euler field semisimple. <lb/> 6.4. Examples. (a) According to K. Saito [34] orbit spaces of finite irreducible <lb/>Coxeter groups carry canonical conformal Frobenius structure. <lb/>(b) Miniversal deformations of isolated critical points of holomorphic functions <lb/>can be naturally equipped with conformal Frobenius structures [35] (see also [30, <lb/>18, 22]). <lb/>(c) Genus 0 Gromov – Witten invariants of a compact almost Kähler manifold X <lb/> define on H = H <lb/>  *  (X; Q[[Q]]) a formal structure of a calibrated conformal Frobenius <lb/>manifold of conformal dimension D = dim  C  X. In the coordinate system t = <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> GROMOV – WITTEN INVARIANTS AND QUANTIZATION <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>  t <lb/> α  φ  α  corresponding to a graded basis {φ  α  } in H <lb/>  *  (X, Q), the Euler field takes <lb/>on the form <lb/> E = <lb/> (1 − deg φ  a  /2)t  α  ∂  α  + ρ <lb/> where the constant part ρ ∈ H <lb/>  *  (X) is the 1-st Chern class of the tangent bundle <lb/> T X. <lb/> (d) In the section 9 we will deal with equivariant generalization [19, 37] of Gromov <lb/>– Witten theory in the case when X is equipped with a hamiltonian action of a <lb/>compact Lie group G. In this case equivariant genus 0 Gromov – Witten invariants <lb/>define on equivariant cohomology space H = H <lb/>  * <lb/> G  (X; Q[[Q]]) the structure of a <lb/>calibrated Frobenius manifold. It is not conformal though since the Euler field <lb/>defined by cohomology grading over Q[[Q]] is not a derivation over the coefficient <lb/>ring H <lb/>  * <lb/> G  (pt) = H <lb/>  *  (BG) of equivariant cohomology theory. <lb/> 6.5. Remark. We will apply our formalism of quantized quadratic hamiltonians <lb/>to the general problem of equipping Frobenius manifolds with all attributes of <lb/>higher genus Gromov – Witten theory. The function F from the definition 6.1 is <lb/>taken of course on the role of the genus 0 potential F <lb/> 0  . The calibration S is then <lb/>used to define the 1-point descendent a, b/(z − ψ) := (a, S(1/z)b). Then Corollary <lb/>5.4 yields Dubrovin&apos;s construction [6] of the genus 0 descendent potential F <lb/> 0  . <lb/>Below we give a construction of the total descendent potentials D in the case <lb/>when the Frobenius manifold is semisimple i. e. when Frobenius algebras (T  t  H, •  t  ) <lb/>are semisimple at generic t ∈ H. All Frobenius manifolds of Examples 6.4a, b are <lb/>semisimple as well as those in d when G is a torus acting on X with isolated fixed <lb/>points. Among examples 6.4c flag manifolds, toric Fano manifolds and probably <lb/>many other Fano manifolds yield semisimple Frobenius structures. <lb/> 6.6. Canonical coordinates. Let t = <lb/> t <lb/> α  φ  α  be a flat coordinate system on <lb/>the Frobenius manifold H. Let u ∈ H be a semisimple point so that the matrices <lb/> A  α  = φ  α  •  u  are simultaneously diagonalizable. Let Ψ be the transition matrix from <lb/>the basis {φ  α  } in T  u  H to the basis of common eigenvectors of A  α  normalized to the <lb/>unit lengths. Then Ψ <lb/> −1  A <lb/> 1  Ψ is a diagonal matrix of closed 1-forms and has locally <lb/>the form dU = diag(du <lb/> 1  , ..., du <lb/> N  ). The diagonal entries of the potential matrix <lb/> U = diag(u <lb/> 1  , ..., u <lb/> N  ) form a local coordinate system on H called canonical [6]. <lb/>Canonical coordinates are defined uniquely up to signs, permutations and additive <lb/>constants which are set to zero in the conformal case by the requirements Eu <lb/> i  = u  i  . <lb/> 6.7. Proposition [22, 21, 6]. (a) The equation ∇  z  S = 0 in a neighborhood <lb/>of a semisimple point u has a fundamental solution in the form: Ψ  u  R  u  (z)e <lb/> U/z  , <lb/>where R  u  (z) = 1 + R  1  z + R  2  z <lb/> 2  + ... is a formal matrix power series satisfying <lb/> R <lb/>  * <lb/> u  (−z)R  u  (z) = 1. <lb/> (b) The series R  u  (z) satisfying (a) is unique up to right multiplication by diagonal <lb/>matrices exp(a  1  z + a  2  z <lb/> 3  + a  3  z <lb/> 5  + ...) where a  k  = diag(a <lb/> 1 <lb/> k  , ..., a <lb/> N <lb/>k  ) are constant. <lb/>(c) In the case of conformal Frobenius structures the series R  u  (z) satisfying (a) <lb/>is uniquely determined by the homogeneity condition (z∂  z  + <lb/> u <lb/> i  ∂  u  i  )R  u  (z) = 0. <lb/>Let H be the space of Laurent polynomials in z with coefficients in the tangent <lb/>space T  u  H to the Frobenius manifold at a semisimple point u. Let H = H  +  ⊕ H  − <lb/> be the polarization of H described in section 2. For q(z) ∈ H  +  we write Ψ <lb/> −1 <lb/> u  q(z) = <lb/>(q <lb/> 1  (z), ..., q <lb/> N  (z)) and introduce the direct product T = τ (; q <lb/> 1  )...τ (; q <lb/> N  ) of N <lb/> copies of the Witten – Kontsevich tau-function as an element of the Fock space <lb/></body>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> ALEXANDER B. GIVENTAL <lb/></note>

			<body> of functions on H  +  . Next, the series R  u  (z) defines a symplectic transformation <lb/>on H, and we put <lb/>  u  = exp(ln R  u  )ˆ. Slightly abusing notation we denotê <lb/>Ψ  u  the <lb/>operator G(Ψ <lb/> −1  q) → G(q) identifying the Fock space with its coordinate version. <lb/>Finally, <lb/>  N <lb/>i=1  R <lb/> ii <lb/> 1  du <lb/> i  where R <lb/> ii <lb/> 1  are the diagonal entries of the matrix R  1  in the <lb/>series R  u  (z) = 1 + R  1  /z + ... is known to be closed as a 1-form on the Frobenius <lb/>manifold. We introduce the function C(u) = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>  u  R <lb/> ii <lb/> 1  du <lb/> i  of u defined up to an <lb/>additive constant. <lb/> 6.8. Definition. We define the total descendent potential of a semisimple Frobe-<lb/>nius manifold by the formula <lb/> D(; t) := e <lb/> C(u)  ˆ <lb/> S <lb/> −1 <lb/> u <lb/> ˆ <lb/>Ψ ˆ <lb/> R  u  e <lb/> (U/z)ˆ  T . <lb/> We introduce the total ancestor potential of a semisimple Frobenius manifold: <lb/> e <lb/> F <lb/> 1  (u)  A  u  (; t) := e <lb/> C(u)  ˆ <lb/>Ψ ˆ <lb/> R  u  e <lb/> (U/z)ˆ  T . <lb/> Since D and A  u  are related as in Theorem 5.1, these definitions automatically <lb/>agree with the reconstruction formula 5.4 for F <lb/> 0  . We keep the convention about <lb/>the dilaton shift 2.2 in these definitions. <lb/> 6.9. Remarks. (a) Both potentials depend on a choice of the asymptotical <lb/>series R  u  (z) (which is unambiguous in the conformal case) and are defined up to a <lb/>constant factor independent on u. In section 9 we will specify the choice of R  u  (z) <lb/>corresponding to equivariant Gromov – Witten theory. <lb/>(b) The factor exp(U/z)ˆ is redundant since the string operator (1/z)ˆ = ˆ <lb/> L  −1 <lb/> annihilates the (product of) Witten – Kontsevich tau-functions as it follows from <lb/>3.1 and is included only for future convenience. <lb/>(c) Quantizations of symplectic transformations S  u  (1/z) and R  u  (z) require dif-<lb/>ferent power series completion of the space H  +  so that their composition, strictly <lb/>speaking, is not defined. Nevertheless the formula for D makes sense (in particular <lb/>— due to some properties of the function T ) at least in the formal neighborhood <lb/>of the critical point locus u = t(t) described in 5.4. As a result of this subtlety, <lb/>the potentials of abstract Frobenius structures thus defined do not always extend <lb/>to non-semisimple values of t  0  = t(0). We are not going to stress this subtlety in <lb/>the rest of the text. <lb/> 7. Properties of the total descendent potential. <lb/> 7.1. Theorem. The total descendent potential D of a semisimple Frobenius <lb/>manifold defined in 6.8 does not depend on the choice of a semisimple point u. <lb/> This follows from the property of S  u  (1/z) and Ψ  u  R  u  (z) exp(U/z) to satisfy the <lb/>same differential equation ∇  z  S = 0 with coefficients rational in z. As a result of <lb/>this, derivatives of D in the directions of the parameter u vanish as if S <lb/> −1 <lb/> u <lb/> and <lb/>Ψ  u  R  u  exp(U/z) were inverse to each other. The factor e <lb/> C(u)  however is needed in <lb/>order to offset the effect of the cocycle C under quantization of this computation. <lb/> 7.2. Corollary. (a) The genus 1 Gromov – Witten potential F <lb/> 1  (t) of a semisim-<lb/>ple Frobenius manifold is given by the formula <lb/> F <lb/> 1  (t) = C(u) − <lb/> 1 <lb/>48 <lb/>ln det(∂  u  i  , ∂  u  j  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>  u  <lb/> R <lb/> ii <lb/> 1  du <lb/> i  + <lb/>1 <lb/>48 <lb/> ln ∆  i  , <lb/> where ∆ <lb/> −1 <lb/> i  (u) = (∂  u  i  , ∂  u  i  ) are inner squares of the canonical idempotents ∂  u  i  of the <lb/>semisimple Frobenius multiplication •  u  . <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> GROMOV – WITTEN INVARIANTS AND QUANTIZATION <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body> (b) The genus 1 descendent potential equals <lb/> F <lb/> 1 <lb/> X  (t) = F <lb/> 1  (t(t)) + <lb/>1 <lb/>24 <lb/>ln det[∂  t  α <lb/> 0 <lb/> ∂  t <lb/> β <lb/> 0 <lb/> ∂  t  0 <lb/>0 <lb/> F <lb/> 0 <lb/> X  (t)], <lb/> where the partial derivatives are taken with respect to coordinates of t <lb/> 0  = <lb/> t <lb/> α <lb/> 0  φ  α  . <lb/> The part (a) coincides with the conjectural formula for F <lb/> 1 <lb/> X  suggested in [21] and <lb/>proved in [8] in the conformal case. A similarly looking formula can be derived for <lb/>the genus 1 descendent potential. It is shown in [22], Example 8, how to reconcile <lb/>it with the well-known formula in part (b) which is due to Dijgraaf – Witten [5] <lb/>and does not require semisimplicity hypotheses. <lb/> 7.3. Proposition. Quantized symplectic operators of the form R(z) = 1 + <lb/> R  1  z + R  2  z <lb/> 2  + ... act on elements G of the Fock space as <lb/> ( ˆ <lb/> RG)(q) = [e <lb/> V (∂q,∂q)/2  G](R <lb/> −1  q), <lb/> where R <lb/> −1  q is defined as the product of z-series R <lb/> −1  (z)q(z), and the quadratic <lb/>form V = <lb/> (p  k  , V  kl  p  l  ) is defined by <lb/> k,l≥0 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> k+l  V  kl  w <lb/> k  z <lb/> l  = <lb/> R <lb/>  *  (w)R(z) − 1 <lb/> w + z <lb/>. <lb/> 7.4. Corollary. The total descendent potential D of a semisimple Frobenius <lb/>manifold satisfies the 3g − 2-jet conjecture of Eguchi – Xiong (see Remark 5.2). <lb/>This time the property of genus g ancestor potentials <lb/> ∂ <lb/> m <lb/> ∂  t <lb/> α 1 <lb/> k 1 +1 <lb/> ...∂  t <lb/> αm <lb/>km +1 <lb/> ( ¯ <lb/> F <lb/> g <lb/>u  )|  t0=0  = 0 if k  1  + ... + k  m  &gt; 3g − 3 <lb/>follows from the dimensional properties of the product T of Witten-Kontsevich <lb/>tau-functions and from the structure ( &quot; upper-triangular &quot; in some sense) of the <lb/>operators <lb/>  described in the proposition. <lb/>Propositions 5.3 and 7.3 together imply: <lb/> 7.5. Corollary. The definition 6.8 of the descendent potential of a semisimple <lb/>Frobenius manifold agrees with the construction of genus &gt; 1 (descendent) poten-<lb/>tials F <lb/> g  (t) (respectively F <lb/> g  (t)) suggested in [22]. <lb/> 7.6. Conjecture. D  X  = D: The total descendent potential D correspond-<lb/>ing to the calibrated conformal Frobenius structure on the cohomology space H = <lb/> H <lb/>  *  (X; Q[[Q]]) defined by genus 0 Gromov – Witten invariants of a compact almost <lb/>Kähler manifold X with generically semisimple quantum cup-product coincides with <lb/>the total descendent potential D  X  defined in the Gromov – Witten theory of X. <lb/> This conjecture is equivalent to Conjecture 2 in [22]. In sections 9, 10 we out-<lb/>line a proof of this conjecture for complex projective spaces and other toric Fano <lb/>manifolds. <lb/>The Virasoro operators <lb/>  m  +N δ  m,0  /16 from the section 3 annihilate the product <lb/> T of N Witten – Kontsevich tau-functions. Let us put formally <lb/> L  m  := ˆ <lb/> S <lb/> −1 <lb/> u <lb/> ˆ <lb/>Ψ  u  ˆ <lb/> R  u  ˆ <lb/> L  m  ˆ <lb/> R <lb/> −1 <lb/> u <lb/> ˆ <lb/>Ψ <lb/> −1 <lb/> u <lb/> ˆ <lb/> S  u  . <lb/> 7.7. Proposition. The operators L  m  + N δ  m,0  /16 satisfy the commutation re-<lb/>lations [L  m  , L  n  ] = (m − n)L  m+n  of the algebra of vector fields on the line and <lb/></body>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> ALEXANDER B. GIVENTAL <lb/></note>

			<body> annihilate the total descendent potential of the semisimple Frobenius manifold: <lb/> L  m  D = 0, m = −1, 0, 1, 2, .... <lb/> The formal Virasoro constraints described in the proposition will be computed <lb/>in the next section in the case of conformal Frobenius structures. <lb/> 8. Virasoro constraints. <lb/> Consider a Frobenius structure of conformal dimension D with the Euler vector <lb/>field which is the sum of a linear diagonalizable and a constant vector field. Then <lb/>in suitable flat coordinates of the metric it assumes the form <lb/> E = <lb/> (1 − d  α  )t <lb/> α  ∂  t  α  + <lb/> α: dα=1 <lb/> ρ  α  ∂  t  α  , <lb/> where the degree spectrum {d  α  } is confined on the interval [0, D] and is symmet-<lb/>ric about D/2. The homogeneity conditions for the calibration S(1/z) and the <lb/>asymptotical solution T = ΨR(z)e <lb/> U/z  read respectively: <lb/>(z∂  z  + E)S = µS + S(µ + ρ/z) <lb/>  *  , (z∂  z  + E)T = µT, <lb/> where µ = diag(d  1  − D/2, ..., d  N  − D/2) is anti-symmetric (µ = −µ <lb/>  *  ), and ρ = ρ <lb/>  * <lb/> is µ-nilpotent in the sense of [7]. In Gromov – Witten theory, µ is the Hodge <lb/>grading operator and ρ is the operator of multiplication by c  1  (T X) = <lb/> ρ  α  ∂  t  α  in <lb/>the classical cohomology algebra. <lb/> 8.1. Theorem. The Virasoro operators 7.7 are L  m  = ˆ <lb/> L <lb/> µ,ρ <lb/>m  + <lb/> δm,0 <lb/> 4  tr(µµ <lb/>  *  ), where <lb/> L <lb/> µ,ρ <lb/>m  are the infinitesimal symplectic transformations <lb/> L <lb/> µ,ρ <lb/>m  = z <lb/> µ  z <lb/> −ρ  L  m  z <lb/> ρ  z <lb/> −µ  = z <lb/> −1/2  (z <lb/> d <lb/>dz <lb/>z − µz + ρ) <lb/> m+1  z <lb/> −1/2  . <lb/> The Virasoro operators 8.1 actually coincide with those introduced in [9]. <lb/>Regardless of the validity of the conjecture 7.6, our definition of the total de-<lb/>scendent potential D reproduces correctly the formulas 5.4 and 5.5 + 7.2 for genus <lb/>0 and 1 descendent potentials in Gromov – Witten theory. As a consequence, we <lb/>obtain a new proof of the main result in [9]: <lb/> 8.2. Corollary. The genus 1 Virasoro constraints hold true for Gromov – <lb/>Witten invariants of almost Kähler manifolds with generically semisimple quantum <lb/>cup-product. <lb/> 8.3. Remarks. (a) Put w = 1/z. Given a connection operator D = d/dw + <lb/> A(w)/w where A = A  0  w + A  1  w <lb/> 2  + ..., A <lb/>  *  (−w) = −A(w), one can associate to <lb/>it a representation of the Lie algebra of vector fields on the line to the algebra of <lb/>quadratic hamiltonians on H by taking L <lb/> D <lb/>m  := w <lb/> 3/2  D <lb/> m+1  w <lb/> −1/2  . Quantization then <lb/>yields a representation in the Fock space. If two connections are conjugated by a <lb/>gauge transformation D → S <lb/> −1  DS where S(w) = S  0  + S  1  w + ..., S <lb/>  *  (−w)S(w) = 1, <lb/> then the corresponding representations are equivalent. According to [7], the classes <lb/>of gauge equivalence (in the case when the residue operator A  0  , A  0  = −A <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  , is <lb/>semisimple) are represented by the connections of the form d/dw + (µ − wρ)/w <lb/> where ρ is polynomial in w and is µ-nilpotent (see [7]). The representation in the <lb/>theorem corresponds to D in the normal form with constant ρ. <lb/> (b) In the case of conformal Frobenius structures the consistent PDE system <lb/> dΦ = z <lb/> −1  A(t)Φ on H can be completed, following [6], to a consistent PDE system <lb/>on C × H by adding the homogeneity equation (d/dw + µ/w − E•  t  )Φ = 0. The <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> GROMOV – WITTEN INVARIANTS AND QUANTIZATION <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body> latter equation can be considered as a family D  t  of connections on C depending on <lb/>the parameter t ∈ H and is isomonodromic. It is the role of the calibration S  t  (w) to <lb/>conjugate the connection operators D  t  to the normal form d/dw + µ/w − ρ with the <lb/>fundamental solution w <lb/> −µ  w <lb/> ρ  . In other words, Φ = S  t  (w)w <lb/> −µ  w <lb/> ρ  is a fundamental <lb/>solution to the PDE system on C × H. The key point in the proof of the theorem <lb/>8.1 is that the asymptotical solution T satisfies the same equations as Φ and thus <lb/> S <lb/> −1  T satisfies the same equations as w <lb/> −µ  w <lb/> ρ  . <lb/> 9. Equivariant Gromov – Witten theory. <lb/> Let the compact almost Kähler manifold X be equipped with a hamiltonian <lb/>Killing action of a compact Lie group G. Then the moduli spaces X  g,m,d  inherit the <lb/>action, and the evaluation, forgetting and contraction maps are G-equivariant. The <lb/>construction of the virtual fundamental class [X  g,m,d  ] admits an equivariant gener-<lb/>alization [33]. This allows one to introduce G-equivariant counterparts of Gromov <lb/>– Witten invariants, gravitational descendents and ancestors and of the generat-<lb/>ing functions F <lb/> g <lb/>X  , F <lb/> g <lb/>X  , D  X  , A  X  , etc. The invariants take values in H <lb/>  * <lb/> G  (point; Q) = <lb/> H <lb/>  *  (BG; Q), the coefficient ring of equivariant cohomology theory. They reduce to <lb/>their non-equivariant versions under the restriction homomorphism H <lb/>  *  (BG; Q) → <lb/> H <lb/>  *  (point; Q). <lb/> The genus 0 equivariant Gromov – Witten potential F <lb/> 0 <lb/> X  defines on the equi-<lb/>variant cohomology space H = H <lb/>  * <lb/> G  (X; Q[[Q]]) the structure of a formal Frobenius <lb/>manifold over the ground ring H <lb/>  * <lb/> G  (point; Q) (see [19]). <lb/>Let us consider the case when G is a torus (S <lb/> 1  ) <lb/> r  . The cohomology algebra of the <lb/>classifying space BG = (CP <lb/> ∞  ) <lb/> r  is isomorphic to Q[λ  1  , ..., λ  r  ]. Here λ  i  ∈ Lie <lb/>  *  G are <lb/>identified with a basis of infinitesimal characters of 1-dimensional representations <lb/>of (S <lb/> 1  ) <lb/> r  . The representations induce Hopf line bundles over (CP <lb/> ∞  ) <lb/> r  whose Chern <lb/>classes generate H <lb/>  *  (BG). <lb/>When the fixed points of the torus G action on X are isolated, the Frobenius <lb/>structure on H is semisimple. Indeed, even the classical equivariant cohomology <lb/>algebra of X with coefficients in the field of fractions Q(λ) of the ground ring <lb/> H <lb/>  * <lb/> G  (point; Q) is semisimple. Therefore the most of results of the previous sections <lb/>apply in equivariant Gromov – Witten theory. However, the Frobenius structure in <lb/>question is not conformal: the Euler vector field expressing dimensional properties <lb/>of Gromov – Witten invariants is a derivation over Q but, generally speaking, not <lb/>over the ground ring H <lb/>  * <lb/> G  (point; Q) since elements of this ring may have non-zero <lb/>degrees. As a consequence, the part (c) of Proposition 6.7 does not apply, i. e. <lb/>the construction 6.7(a) of the series R(z) is ambiguous, and the ambiguity is as <lb/>described in 6.7(b). <lb/>Let w  i  , i = 1, ..., N be the fixed points of the torus G action on X, and N <lb/> (i) <lb/> l <lb/> denote the Newton polynomial <lb/>  n <lb/>j=1  χ <lb/> −l <lb/> j  (w  i  ) of the inverse infinitesimal characters <lb/> χ <lb/> −1 <lb/> j  (w  i  ) of the torus G action on the cotangent space T <lb/>  * <lb/> wi  X at the fixed point. We <lb/>consider N <lb/> (i) <lb/> l <lb/> as an element of the ground field Q(λ  1  , ..., λ  r  ). <lb/> 9.1. Theorem. In the case of a torus G action with isolated fixed points, the <lb/>total ancestor potential in the equivariant Gromov – Witten theory on X coincides <lb/>with the total ancestor potential 6.8 of the semisimple Frobenius structure on H = <lb/> H <lb/>  * <lb/> G  (X; Q[[Q]]) (i. e. e <lb/> F <lb/> 1 <lb/> X  A  X  = e <lb/> C  ˆ <lb/>Ψ ˆ <lb/> RT ) provided that the series R(z) is normalized <lb/>by the condition that in the classical cohomology limit Q → 0 it takes on the form <lb/></body>

			<page> 12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> ALEXANDER B. GIVENTAL <lb/></note>

			<body> R(z)|  Q=0  = exp diag(b  1  , ..., b  N  ) where b  i  are the Bernoulli series <lb/> b  i  (z) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=1 <lb/> N <lb/> (i) <lb/>2k−1 <lb/> B  2k <lb/> 2k <lb/> z <lb/> 2k−1 <lb/> 2k − 1 <lb/> . <lb/> 9.2. Remarks. (a) The theorem is equivalent (due to 5.1) to the Theorem 2 in [22] <lb/>describing descendent potentials F <lb/> g <lb/>X  with g &gt; 1 (plus a similar result of [21] about <lb/> F <lb/> 1 <lb/> X  ). Both results are proved by fixed point localization in moduli spaces X  g,m,d <lb/> utilizing Kontsevich&apos;s technique of summations over graphs [27]. Justification of <lb/>fixed point localization formulas for virtual fundamental classes depends on the <lb/>results of [23] in the algebraic category and [37] in the general almost Kähler setting. <lb/>The Bernoulli series arise to offset the effect of Hodge integrals in localization <lb/>formulas by applying the theorem 4.1 for X = point. <lb/> (b) It is essential in the formulation 9.1 that indices of canonical coordinates <lb/>coincide with the labels i = 1, ..., N of fixed points. This is due to the phenomenon <lb/>[19, 21] of materialization of canonical coordinates in fixed point localization theory, <lb/>playing an essential role in the proofs [21, 22] otherwise too. The simplest instance <lb/>of it is related to the equality <lb/> u <lb/> i  = the total &quot; number &quot; of elliptic curves in X with given modulus. <lb/>In the computation of the &quot; number &quot; via the fixed point technique, we can single <lb/>out contributions v <lb/> i  of those fixed curves where the elliptic irreducible component <lb/>(with the required generic modulus) is mapped to the fixed point w  i  . It turns out <lb/>[19] that the equality <lb/> v <lb/> i  = <lb/> u <lb/> i  is termwise (which in particular establishes the <lb/>aforementioned correspondence). <lb/>(c) The ancestor potential A  X  specializes to its non-equivariant counterpart in <lb/>the non-equivariant limit λ = 0. It is not clear however how to derive from the <lb/>theorem its non-equivariant version. It would suffice to show that the series R(z) <lb/> tends to its non-equivariant counterpart (since all other ingredients of the formula <lb/>obviously do). Yet, if for some normalization of R(z) the limit exists, then it does <lb/>not exist for any other normalization. <lb/> 9.3. Conjecture. When X has generically semisimple non-equivariant quan-<lb/>tum cohomology, the series R(z) (normalized by the Bernoulli series as in 9.1) has <lb/>a non-equivariant limit at λ = 0 equal to the series R from 7.6. <lb/>In the next section we prove this conjecture in the case of complex projective <lb/>spaces. <lb/> 10. Mirrors of complex projective spaces. <lb/> According to the theorem 7.1 the total descendent potential D of a semisimple <lb/>Frobenius manifold is determined by the values of S, Ψ and R at any semisimple <lb/>point. We will exploit the property of projective spaces and their products to have <lb/>semisimple small quantum cohomology algebra. <lb/>Let G = T <lb/> n+1  be the torus of diagonal unitary transformations of the stan-<lb/>dard Hermitian space C <lb/> n+1  . We identify H <lb/>  *  (BG, Q) with C[λ  0  , ..., λ  n  ] and the <lb/>equivariant cohomology algebra H <lb/>  * <lb/> G  (CP <lb/> n  , Q) of the projectivized space — with <lb/> C[P, λ  0  , ..., λ  n  ]/((P − λ  0  )...(P − λ  n  ). Here −P denote the equivariant 1-st Chern <lb/>class of the Hopf line bundle over CP <lb/> n  . The multiplication table in the basis <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> GROMOV – WITTEN INVARIANTS AND QUANTIZATION <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body> 1, P, ..., P <lb/> n−1  in the small equivariant quantum cohomology algebra of CP <lb/> n  has <lb/>the following well-known description: <lb/>(P − λ  0  ) • ... • (P − λ  n  ) = Q, while P • P <lb/> k  = P <lb/> k+1  for k &lt; n. <lb/> Here the generator Q in the Novikov ring is identified with exp t where t is the <lb/>coordinate on the parameter space H <lb/> 2  (CP <lb/> n  , C) of the small quantum cohomology <lb/>algebra. (The identification is possible due to the divisor equation, see for instance <lb/>[19].) Respectively, the connection ∇  z  from 6.7 restricted to this parameter space <lb/>yields the following system of linear differential equations: <lb/> z <lb/>d <lb/>dt <lb/>I  k  = I  k+1  for k &lt; n, and (z <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> − λ  0  )...(z <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> − λ  n  ) I  0  = e <lb/> t  I  0  . <lb/> Introduce the complex oscillating integral <lb/> I = <lb/> Γ⊂{x0...xn=Q} <lb/> e <lb/> (x0+...+xn)/z  x <lb/> λ0/z <lb/> 0 <lb/> ... x <lb/> λn/z <lb/>n <lb/> dx  0  ∧ ... ∧ dx  n <lb/> d(x  0  ...dx  n  ) <lb/> . <lb/> The cycles Γ in the oscillating integrals of the form <lb/> Γ  e <lb/> F (x)/z  φ(x)dx may be non-<lb/>compact and are constructed by means of Morse theory for the functions Re(F/z). <lb/> 10.1. Theorem. (zQ <lb/> d <lb/>dQ  − λ  0  )...(zQ <lb/> d <lb/>dQ  − λ  n  ) I = Q I. <lb/> Proof. It is convenient to rewrite the integral in logarithmic coordinates: Q = <lb/> e <lb/> t  , x  i  = e <lb/> Ti  : <lb/> I = <lb/> Γ⊂{t= <lb/> Ti} <lb/> e <lb/> (e <lb/> T i  +λiTi)/z  dT  0  ∧ ... ∧ dT  n <lb/> d(T  0  + ... + T  n  ) <lb/> . <lb/> The projection (T  0  , ..., T  n  ) → t = T  0  + ... + T  n  maps each ∂  Ti  to ∂  t  . Using this we <lb/>conclude that application of zd/dt − λ  i  to the integral can be replaced by multipli-<lb/>cation of the integrand by e <lb/> Ti  . Doing this consecutively for i = 0, 1, ..., n we find <lb/>the integrand multiplied by e <lb/> T0  ...e <lb/> Tn  = e <lb/> t  . Thus (zd/dt − λ  0  )...(zd/dt − λ  n  )I = e <lb/> t  I. <lb/> 10.2. Remark. The result is an equivariant version of the mirror theorem for <lb/>complex projective spaces we reported in Summer 93 at seminars in Lyon, Stras-<lb/>bourg and Oberwolfach. Many mathematical results inspired by or predicted on <lb/>the basis of mirror theory have been proved since then. Yet the argument presently <lb/>discussed seems to be one of the first formal mathematical applications of a mirror <lb/>theorem. <lb/>An asymptotical solution T = ΨR(z) exp(U/z) to the system ∇  z  T = 0 can be <lb/>obtained from stationary phase asymptotics near the critical points of the phase <lb/>function of the integral I and its derivatives. <lb/> 10.3. Example. We illustrate the procedure of expanding a complex oscillating <lb/>integral near a non-degenerate critical point of the phase function with the critical <lb/>value u: <lb/> e <lb/> (u−x <lb/> 2  +αx <lb/> 3  +...)/z  (β + γx + ...)dx = <lb/> √ <lb/> ze <lb/> u/z <lb/> e <lb/> −y <lb/> 2  e <lb/> αy <lb/> √ <lb/> z+...  (β + γy <lb/> √ <lb/> z + ...)dy. <lb/> Discarding the dimensional factor <lb/> √ <lb/> z in front of the integral and computing mo-<lb/>menta of the Gaussian distribution yields an asymptotical expansion of the form <lb/> e <lb/> u/z  (a + bz + cz <lb/> 2  + ...). <lb/></body>

			<page> 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> ALEXANDER B. GIVENTAL <lb/></note>

			<body> In the oscillating integral I, the critical points of the phase function are con-<lb/>strained extrema of the function <lb/> e <lb/> T0  + ... + e <lb/> Tn  + λ  0  T  0  + ... + λ  n  T  n  − P (T  0  + ... + T  n  − t) <lb/> with the Lagrange multiplier P . They satisfy e <lb/> Tα  = P − λ  i  where (P − λ  0  )...(P − <lb/> λ  n  ) = Q. Near Q = 0 and generic λ, the n+1 roots P <lb/> (i)  (Q), i = 0, ..., n, to the latter <lb/>equation are distinguished by their values P <lb/> (i)  (0) = λ  i  . On the other hand the basis <lb/> {P <lb/> k  , k = 0, ..., n} in H <lb/>  *  (CP <lb/> n  ) corresponds to the basis of integrals I  k  = z(d/dt) <lb/> k  I <lb/> (since P <lb/> •k  = P <lb/> k  for k ≤ n). In the asymptotical solution ΨR(z) exp(U/z) the <lb/>diagonal matrix U consists of the critical values u <lb/> i  , and the matrix entries of ΨR(z) <lb/>are obtained from asymptotical expansions of I  k  near the critical point P <lb/> (i)  . <lb/>The asymptotical solution thus constructed automatically admits the non -equi-<lb/>variant limit λ = 0 when Q  = 0 since the phase functions, amplitudes and the <lb/>critical points in the oscillating integrals depend continuously on λ. For generic λ, <lb/> the solution depends continuously on Q up to Q = 0. <lb/>At Q = 0 the matrix Ψ describes the transition from the basis {P <lb/> k  } to the basis <lb/> L  j  (P ) = <lb/> α  (P − λ  α  )/(λ  j  − λ  α  ) <lb/> 1/2  of (suitably normalized) Lagrange interpolation <lb/>polynomials. Indeed, the Lagrange interpolation polynomials represent the basis <lb/>of delta-functions of of the fixed points w  j  , j = 0, ..., n, in the equivariant coho-<lb/>mology algebra of CP <lb/> n  and therefore coincide with the canonical idempotents of <lb/>the semisimple algebra (T  u  H, •  u  ) in the classical cohomology limit Q = 0. Thus <lb/>the matrix elements of the series R(z) at Q = 0 are extracted from asymptotical <lb/>expansions near the critical points P <lb/> (i)  of the integrals L  j  (zd/dt)I in this limit. <lb/>For symmetry reasons it suffices to consider only the critical point corresponding <lb/>to P <lb/> (0)  . Computing L  j  (zd/dt)I as in the proof of 10.1 we find an extra factor <lb/>proportional to Q/x  j  in the integrand of the oscillating integral I. We rewrite the <lb/>integral in the chart (x  1  , ..., x  n  ) where x  0  = Q/x  1  ...x  n  . It still contains P <lb/> (0)  in the <lb/>limit Q = 0 when x  0  = P <lb/> (0)  − λ  0  vanishes. We find L  j  (zd/dt)I proportional to <lb/> e <lb/> λ0 ln Q/z <lb/> e <lb/> [ <lb/> Q <lb/> x 1 ...xn  +x1+...+xn+(λ1−λ0) ln x1+...+(λn−λ1) ln xn]/z  Q <lb/>x  j <lb/> dx  1  ∧ ... ∧ dx  n <lb/> x  1  ...x  n <lb/> . <lb/> We see that the integral vanishes at Q = 0 unless j = 0. This agrees with the fact of <lb/>our general theory that R is diagonal at Q = 0. For j = 0 we have Q/x  0  = x  1  ...x  n  , <lb/>and the integral at Q = 0 factors into 1-dimensional ones: <lb/> e <lb/> ( <lb/>  n <lb/>i=1  xi+(λi−λ0) ln xi)/z  dx  1  ∧ ... ∧ dx  n  = <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> e <lb/> x/z  x <lb/> (λi−λ0)/z  dx. <lb/> The stationary phase asymptotics of the latter integral is the same as for the product <lb/>Γ(1 + (λ  1  − λ  0  )/z)...Γ(1 + (λ  n  − λ  0  )/z) of the gamma-functions as z → 0 since <lb/> e <lb/> x/z  x <lb/> λ/z  dx = (−z) <lb/> 1+λ/z <lb/> e <lb/> −v  v <lb/> λ/z  dv ∼ Γ(1 + <lb/> λ <lb/>z <lb/> ). <lb/> 10.4. Lemma. ln Γ(1 + s) ∼ s ln(s/e) + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  ln(2πs) + <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> k=1 <lb/>B  2k <lb/> 2k <lb/> s <lb/> 1−2k <lb/> 2k−1  . <lb/> Proof. This is well-known, see for instance [24]. <lb/>Subtracting the critical value (Stirling&apos;s approximation) we find that at Q = 0 <lb/>ln R <lb/> 00  = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=1 <lb/> B  2k <lb/> 2k <lb/> z <lb/> 2k−1 <lb/> 2k − 1 <lb/> α =0 <lb/> (λ  α  − λ  0  ) <lb/> 1−2k  . <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> GROMOV – WITTEN INVARIANTS AND QUANTIZATION <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body> This coincides with b  0  (z) in 9.1 since λ  α  −λ  0  are exactly the infinitesimal characters <lb/>of the torus G action on T <lb/>  * <lb/> w0  CP <lb/> n  . <lb/>Finally, our computation carries over without significant changes to arbitrary <lb/>Fano toric manifolds X. It is essential here that (i) Fano toric manifolds have <lb/>semisimple small quantum cohomology (as it follows from the explicit description <lb/>of such cohomology given by V. Batyrev [1]) and (ii) equivariant genus 0 GW-<lb/>invariants of Fano toric manifolds admit a mirror description [21] by complex os-<lb/>cillating integrals generalizing Theorem 10.1. <lb/>Combining the computation with 5.1 and 9.1 (or equivalently — with [22]) we <lb/>prove the conjecture 7.6. <lb/> 10.5. Theorem. The total descendent potential of a toric Fano manifold X is <lb/>given, up to a non-zero constant factor, by the formula D  X  = e <lb/> C(t)  ˆ <lb/> S  t  ˆ <lb/>Ψ  t  ˆ <lb/> R  t  T where <lb/> t ∈ H <lb/> 2  (X; C). <lb/>10.6. Corollary. The total descendent potential D  X  of a toric Fano manifold <lb/>satisfies (L  m  +N δ  m,0  /16)D  X  = 0 for m = −1, 0, 1, 2, ..., where L  m  are the Virasoro <lb/>operators 8.1. <lb/> 10.7. Remarks. (a) The corollary was conjectured by T. Eguchi, K. Hori, M. <lb/>Jinzenji, C.-S. Xiong and S. Katz [11, 12]. <lb/>(b) The so called λ  g  -conjecture and some other non-trivial properties of Hodge <lb/>integrals over Deligne – Mumford spaces were discovered by Getzler and Pandhari-<lb/>pande [16] on the basis of Virasoro conjecture for CP <lb/> 1  . The Corollary therefore <lb/>backs up the original arguments of [16] which appear to be more natural than the <lb/>proof of the properties found later by Faber and Pandharipande [14]. <lb/>(c) The role the gamma-function 10.4 plays in a general theorem 9.1 should <lb/>probably remind us about the relationship of quantum cohomology theory with its <lb/>heuristic roots [17, 18] — S <lb/> 1  -equivariant Floer theory on loop spaces. In fact the <lb/>gamma-function 10.4 will make a more systematic appearance in [4] in the context <lb/>of general &quot; quantum &quot; versions of the Riemann – Roch formula, Serre duality and <lb/>Lefschetz hyperplane section theorem. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments.  The author is thankful to H. Chang, T. Coates, Y.-P. <lb/>Lee and R. Pandharipande for numerous stimulating discussions and to J. Morava <lb/>for pointing at his notes [31] which indicate how the formalism of Fock spaces <lb/>discussed above emerges naturally from S <lb/> 1  -equivariant cobordism theory of loop <lb/>spaces. <lb/></div>

			<page> 16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> ALEXANDER B. GIVENTAL <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] V. Batyrev. Quantum cohomology rings of toric manifolds. Journes de Gomtrie Algbrique <lb/>d&apos;Orsay (Orsay, 1992). Astrisque No. 218 (1993), 9–34. <lb/>[2] K. Behrend, B. Fantechi. The intrinsic normal cone. Invent. Math. 128 (1997), 45 – 88. <lb/>[3] K. Behrend, Yu. Manin. Stacks of stable maps and Gromov-Witten invariants. Duke Math. <lb/>J. 85 (1996), 1 – 60. <lb/>[4] T. Coates, A. Givental. Quantum Riemann – Roch, Lefschetz and Serre. In preparation. <lb/>[5] R. Dijkgraaf, E. Witten. Mean field theory, topological field theory and multi-matrix models. <lb/> Nucl. Phys. B342 (1990), 486–522. <lb/>[6] B. Dubrovin. Geometry of 2D topological filed theories. In: Integrable Systems and Quantum <lb/>Groups. Springer Lecture Notes in Math. 1620 (1996), 120–348. <lb/>[7] B. Dubrovin. Painlevé transcendents and two-dimensional topological field theory. Preprint, <lb/>117 pp., math.AG/9803107 <lb/>[8] B. Dubrovin, Y. Zhang. Bihamiltonian hierarchies in 2D topological field theory at one-loop <lb/>approximation. Commun. Math. Phys. 198 (1998), 311–361. <lb/>[9] B. Dubrovin, Y. Zhang. Frobenius manifolds and Virasoro constraints. Selecta Math. (N.S.) <lb/>5 (1999), 423–466. <lb/>[10] T. Eguchi, E. Getzler, C.-S. Xiong. Topological gravity in genus 2 with two primary fields. <lb/> Preprint, hep-th/0007194. <lb/>[11] Eguchi, Hori, Xiong. Quantum cohomology and Virasoro algebra. Phys. Lett. B 402 (1997), <lb/>71 – 80. <lb/>[12] T. Eguchi, M. Jinzenji, C.-S. Xiong. Quantum cohomology and free field representations. <lb/> Nuclear Phys. B 510 (1998), 608 – 622. <lb/>[13] T. Eguchi, C.-S. Xiong. Quantum cohomology at higher genus: topological recursion rela-<lb/>tions and Virasoro conditions. Adv. Theor. Math. Phys. 2 (1998), 219 – 229. <lb/>[14] C. Faber, R. Pandharipande. Hodge integrals and Gromov – Witten theory. Invent. Math. <lb/>139 (2000), 173–199. <lb/>[15] E. Getzler. The jet space of a frobenius manifold and higher-genus Gromov – Witten in-<lb/>variants. Preprint, 2001. <lb/>[16] E. Getzler, R. Pandharipande. Virasoro constraints and the Chern classes of the Hodge <lb/>bundle. Nucl. Phys. B 530 (1998), 701 – 714. <lb/>[17] A. Givental. Homological geometry I: projective hypersurfaces. Selecta Math. (N. S.) 1 <lb/> (1995), 325 – 345. <lb/>[18] A. Givental. Homological geometry and mirror symmetry. In: Proceedings of ICM-94 Zürich. <lb/>Birkhäuser, Basel, 1995, 472–480. <lb/>[19] A. Givental. Equivariant Gromov – Witten invariants. IMRN, 1996, 613–663. <lb/>[20] A. Givental. A mirror theorem for toric complete intersections. In: Topological field theory, <lb/>primitive forms and related topics (Kyoto, 1996), 141–175, Progr. in Math., 160, Birkhäuser, <lb/>Boston, MA, 1998. <lb/>[21] A. Givental. Elliptic Gromov – Witten invariants and the generalized mirror conjecture. <lb/> In: Integrable Systems and Algebraic Geometry. World Sci. Publ., River Edge, NJ, 1998, <lb/>107–155. <lb/>[22] A. Givental. Semisimple Frobenius structures at higher genus. Preprint, math.AG/0008067. <lb/>To appear in IMRN. <lb/>[23] T. Graber, R. Pandharipande. Localization of virtual classes. Invent. Math. 135 (1999), 487 <lb/>– 518. <lb/>[24] E. Jahnke, F. Emde, F. Lösch. Tables of higher functions. Teubner Verlag., Stuttgart, 1966. <lb/>[25] V. Kac, A. Schwarz. Geometric interpretation of the partition function of 2D gravity. Phys. <lb/>Lett. B257 (1991), 329 – 334. <lb/>[26] M. Kontsevich Intersection theory on the moduli space of curves and the matrix Airy func-<lb/>tion. Commun. Math. Phys. 147 (1992), 1 – 23. <lb/>[27] M. Kontsevich. Enumeration of rational curves via toric actions. In: The Moduli Space of <lb/>Curves (R, Dijkgraaf, C. Faber, G. van der Geer, eds.) Progr. in Math. 129, Birkhäuser, <lb/>Boston, 1995, 335–368. <lb/>[28] M. Kontsevich, Yu. Manin. Relations between the correlators of the topological sigma-model <lb/>coupled to gravity. Commun. Math. Phys. 196 (1998), 385 – 398. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> GROMOV – WITTEN INVARIANTS AND QUANTIZATION <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [29] J. Li, G. Tian. Virtual Moduli cycles and Gromov-Witten invariants in general symplectic <lb/>manifolds. In: Topics in symplectic 4-manifolds (Irvine, CA, 1996), 47–83, First Int. Press <lb/>Lect. Ser., I, Internat. Press, Cambridge, MA, 1998. <lb/>[30] Yu. I. Manin. Frobenius manifolds, quantum cohomology, and moduli spaces. AMS Collo-<lb/>quium Publ. 47, Providence, RI, 1999, 303 pp. <lb/>[31] J. Morava. Tate cohomology of framed circle actions as a Heisenberg group. Preprint, <lb/>math.AT/0102132. <lb/>[32] D. Mumford. Towards enumerative geometry on the moduli space of curves. In: Arithmetics <lb/>and Geometry (M. Artin, J. Tate eds.), v.2, Birkhäuser, 1983, 271 – 328. <lb/>[33] Y. Ruan. Virtual neighborhoods of pseudo-holomorphic curves. Proceedings of 6th Gkova <lb/>Geometry-Topology Conference. Turkish J. Math. 23 (1999), no. 1, 161–231. <lb/>[34] K. Saito. On a linear structure of the quotient variety by a finite reflection group. Publ. Res. <lb/>Inst. Math. Sci. 29 (1993), no. 4, 535–579. <lb/>[35] K. Saito. On periods of primitive integrals, I. Preprint RIMS, 1982. <lb/>[36] B. Siebert Algebraic and symplectic Gromov-Witten invariants coincide. Ann. Inst. Fourier <lb/>(Grenoble) 49 (1999), no. 6, 1743–1795. <lb/>[37] B. Siebert. A lecture at the Workshop on Symplectic 4-Manifolds at Ecolé Polytechnique, <lb/>Lozere, June 2000. <lb/>[38] E. Witten. Two-dimensional gravity and intersection theory on moduli space. Surveys in <lb/>Diff. Geom. 1 (1991), 243–310. <lb/> UC Berkeley and Caltech </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
