<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="footnote"> arXiv:1407.5824v1  [math-ph] 22 Jul 2014 <lb/></note>

			<front> Symplectic field theory of a disk, quantum <lb/>integrable systems, and Schur polynomials <lb/> Boris Dubrovin <lb/> Abstract. We consider commuting operators obtained by quantization <lb/>of Hamiltonians of the Hopf (aka dispersionless KdV) hierarchy. Such op-<lb/>erators naturally arise in the setting of Symplectic Field Theory (SFT). <lb/>A complete set of common eigenvectors of these operators is given by <lb/>Schur polynomials. We use this result for computing the SFT potential <lb/>of a disk. <lb/> Keywords. Quantum integrable systems, Symplectic field theory, Schur <lb/>polynomials. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> 1.1. Hopf integrable hierarchy and its quantization <lb/> Hopf equation <lb/> u  t  + u u  x  = 0 <lb/>(1.1) <lb/>can be considered as the spatially one-dimensional analogue of the Euler <lb/>equations of motion of ideal incompressible fluid. It is perhaps the simplest <lb/>example of an integrable nonlinear PDE. In the community of experts in <lb/>integrable systems it is often called dispersionless Korteweg–de Vries (KdV) <lb/>equation; sometimes it is also called (inviscid) Burgers equation. Eq. (1.1) is <lb/>an infinite-dimensional analogue of a Hamiltonian dynamical system <lb/> u  t  + ∂  x <lb/> δH <lb/>δu(x) <lb/> = 0, H = <lb/>1 <lb/>2π <lb/>  2π <lb/> 0 <lb/> u <lb/> 3  (x) <lb/>6 <lb/> dx <lb/> (to be more specific let us consider (1.1) as a dynamical system on the space <lb/>of smooth 2π-periodic functions). It possesses a complete family of pairwise <lb/>commuting conservation laws <lb/> H  n  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2π <lb/>  2π <lb/>0 <lb/> u <lb/> n+2  (x) <lb/>(n + 2)! <lb/> dx, n ≥ −1 <lb/> (1.2) <lb/></body>

			<page> 2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> B. Dubrovin <lb/></note>

			<body> {H  n  , H  m  } := <lb/>1 <lb/>2π <lb/>  2π <lb/> 0 <lb/> δH  n <lb/> δu(x) <lb/>∂  x <lb/>  δH  m <lb/> δu(x) <lb/> dx <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>2π <lb/>  2π <lb/>0 <lb/> ∂  x <lb/> u <lb/> m+n+2  (x) <lb/>(n + 1)! m! (m + n + 2) <lb/> dx = 0. <lb/>The Hopf Hamiltonian coincides with the functional H  1  ; the Hamiltonian H  0 <lb/> generates spatial translations; the very first Hamiltonian H  −1  is a Casimir <lb/>of the degenerate Poisson bracket defined by the operator ∂  x  . A convenient <lb/>generating function of the commuting Hamiltonians can be chosen in the <lb/>form <lb/> H(z) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2π <lb/>  2π <lb/>0 <lb/> e <lb/> z u(x)  dx = 1 + <lb/> n≥−1 <lb/> H  n  z <lb/> n+2  . <lb/> (1.3) <lb/>In general the procedure of quantization of a Hamiltonian system on a <lb/>symplecic manifold converts functions on the manifold into operators acting <lb/>on a suitable space of states. It depends on the choice of canonical coordinates <lb/>on the phase space. <lb/>In our case one can use the Fourier coefficients of the 2π-periodic func-<lb/>tion <lb/> u(x) = <lb/> n∈Z <lb/> u  n  e <lb/> i n x <lb/> as coordinates on the phase space. Their Poisson brackets read <lb/> {u  n  , u  m  } = i n δ  m,−n  . <lb/> Thus one can choose positive Fourier coefficients as canonical coordinates on <lb/>the symplectic leaves u  0  = const <lb/> q  n  = u  n  , n ≥ 1. <lb/>Negative Fourier coefficients will be denoted <lb/> p  n  = u  −n  , n ≥ 1. <lb/>Their Poisson brackets have the canonical form up to a constant factor <lb/> {p  n  , q  m  } = −i n δ  mn  , {u  0  , q  n  } = {u  0  , p  n  } = 0. <lb/>(1.4) <lb/>After the quantization one has to replace the variables q  n  , p  m  by oper-<lb/>ators <lb/>  n  , ˆ <lb/> p  m  satisfying the commutation relations <lb/>[ˆ p  n  , ˆ <lb/> q  m  ] =  n δ  mn  . <lb/> (1.5) <lb/>Here  is an independent parameter of the quantization procedure called <lb/>Planck constant. <lb/>The operators <lb/>  k  , ˆ <lb/> p  k  admit the following realization on the space of <lb/>polynomials in the variables q  1  , q  2  , . . . <lb/>ˆ <lb/> q  k  f (q) = q  k  f (q), ˆ <lb/> p  k  f (q) =  k <lb/>∂ <lb/>∂q  k <lb/> f (q), k = 1, 2, . . . . <lb/> (1.6) <lb/>We can associate certain operators acting on the same space of poly-<lb/>nomials also with the Hamiltonians H  n  applying the procedure of normal <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SFT and Schur polynomials <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>ordering. That means that, in any monomial in the p- and q-variables all p  n  -<lb/>s must be written on the right and, then, replaced by operators <lb/>  n  =  n <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂qn  . <lb/>Denoteê <lb/> H <lb/> 0 <lb/> n  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2π <lb/>: <lb/>  2π <lb/>0 <lb/> u <lb/> n+2  (x) <lb/>(n + 2)! <lb/> dx : <lb/>(1.7) <lb/>the resulting normally ordered quantum operators. For example, <lb/>ˆ <lb/> H <lb/> 0 <lb/> −1  = u  0 <lb/> ˆ <lb/> H <lb/> 0 <lb/>0  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2π <lb/>: <lb/>  2π <lb/>0 <lb/> u <lb/> 2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> dx := <lb/> u <lb/> 2 <lb/>0 <lb/> 2 <lb/>+ <lb/> n≥1 <lb/>  n  ˆ <lb/> p  n <lb/> ˆ <lb/> H <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2π <lb/>: <lb/>  2π <lb/>0 <lb/> u <lb/> 3 <lb/> 6 <lb/> dx := <lb/> u <lb/> 3 <lb/>0 <lb/> 6 <lb/>+ u  0 <lb/> ˆ <lb/> q  k  ˆ <lb/> p  k  + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> i, j <lb/> (ˆ q  i  ˆ <lb/> q  j  ˆ <lb/> p  i+j  + ˆ <lb/> q  i+j  <lb/>  i  ˆ <lb/> p  j  ) <lb/>etc. In the semiclassical limit  → 0 the operators are replaced by their <lb/>symbols clearly coinciding with the original Hamiltonians H  n  . <lb/>However, these quantum operators do not commute any more; this can <lb/>be seen already in the commutator <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  , ˆ <lb/> H <lb/> 0 <lb/>2 <lb/> = <lb/> 2 <lb/> 8 <lb/> i j(i + j) (ˆ q  i+j  <lb/>  i  ˆ <lb/> p  j  − ˆ <lb/> q  i  ˆ <lb/> q  j  ˆ <lb/> p  i+j  )  = 0. <lb/>We arrive at the following quantization problem. <lb/> Definition 1.1. Quantization of the integrable system (1.1) is a family of <lb/>pairwise commuting operators <lb/>  n  , n ≥ −1, acting on the Fock space of <lb/>polynomials C[q  1  , q  2  , . . . ] and, in the semiclassical limit  → 0, coinciding <lb/>with H  n  given by (1.2) . <lb/>Such quantization problem <lb/> 1  was addressed in [19] where a recursion <lb/>procedure for constructing commuting quantum Hamiltonians has been de-<lb/>veloped. Independently a closed formula for the commuting quantum Hamil-<lb/>tonians was found by Y. Eliashberg [7], [8], see also [20], in the setting of <lb/>Symplectic Field Theory (see below). This formula plays the central role in <lb/>the present paper. <lb/> Proposition 1.2. The operators  <lb/>  n  , n ≥ −1 defined by their generating func-<lb/>tion <lb/> (z, u  0  , ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2π s <lb/>  1/2  z <lb/> : <lb/>  2π <lb/>0 <lb/> e <lb/> z s(i <lb/> 1/2  z∂x)u(x)  dx := 1 + <lb/> n≥−1 <lb/>  n  z <lb/> n+2 <lb/> (1.8) <lb/> where <lb/> u(x) = u  0  + <lb/> k≥1 <lb/>  k  e <lb/> ikx  + ˆ <lb/> p  k  e <lb/> −ikx  <lb/> 1  Quantization of the KdV equation equipped with the second Poisson bracket was first <lb/>considered in a series of papers by V. Bazhanov, S. Lukyanov and A. Zamolodchikov [4]. <lb/>More recently the problem of quantization of the intermediate long wave equation was <lb/>addressed in [5]. <lb/></body>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> B. Dubrovin <lb/></note>

			<body> and <lb/> s(t) = <lb/>sinh <lb/> t <lb/> 2 <lb/> t <lb/> 2 <lb/> commute pairwise <lb/> ê <lb/> H  n  , ˆ <lb/> H  m <lb/> = 0, n, m ≥ −1. <lb/> Remark 1.3. The commuting operators <lb/>  n  were recently rediscovered in es-<lb/>sentially equivalent form in [1], [11]. <lb/> 1.2. Schur polynomials and eigenvectors of the quantum Hamiltonians <lb/> Using the Taylor expansion of the function s(t) <lb/>s(t) = 1 + <lb/> n≥1 <lb/> t <lb/> 2n <lb/> 2  2n  (2n + 1)! <lb/>one can spell out the formula (1.8) as follows <lb/>ˆ <lb/> H(z, u  0  , ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2π s <lb/>  1/2  z <lb/> : <lb/>  2π <lb/>0 <lb/> e <lb/> z u− <lb/>  z 3 <lb/> 24  u <lb/> ′′  + <lb/>  2 z 5 <lb/>1920  u <lb/> (4)  −...  dx : <lb/>so, in the semiclassical limit  → 0, one returns to the Hamiltonians (1.2) <lb/>but, starting from <lb/>  2  there are nontrivial corrections <lb/>ˆ <lb/> H  −1  = u  0 <lb/> ˆ <lb/> H  0  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2π <lb/>: <lb/>  2π <lb/>0 <lb/> u <lb/> 2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> dx : − <lb/> 24 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> H  1  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2π <lb/>: <lb/>  2π <lb/>0 <lb/> u <lb/> 3 <lb/> 6 <lb/> dx : − <lb/> 24 <lb/> u  0 <lb/> ˆ <lb/> H  2  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2π <lb/>: <lb/>  2π <lb/>0 <lb/>  u <lb/> 4 <lb/> 24 <lb/>+ <lb/> 24 <lb/> u u <lb/> ′′  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> u <lb/> 2 <lb/> dx : + <lb/>7 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 5760 <lb/> . <lb/> Observe that, in the representation (1.6) the nontrivial part of <lb/>  0  coincides <lb/>with the degree operator, up to an additive constant, <lb/>ˆ <lb/> H  0  |  u0=0  = <lb/> n <lb/> n q  n <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂q  n <lb/> − <lb/> 24 <lb/>and <lb/>  1  with the cut-and-join operator <lb/>ˆ <lb/> H  1  |  u0=0  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> i, j <lb/> (i + j)q  i  q  j <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂q  i+j <lb/> + <lb/> 2  i j q  i+j <lb/> ∂ <lb/> 2 <lb/> ∂q  i  ∂q  j <lb/> . <lb/> It was observed in [13] that Schur polynomials are eigenvectors <lb/> 2  of the <lb/>cut-and-join operator. It turns out that the same is true for all commuting <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 2  It can also be deduced from the description [3] in terms of Jack polynomials of eigenstates <lb/>of the Calogero–Sutherland operator at the limit β → 1. I thank P. Wiegman for this <lb/>reference. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> SFT and Schur polynomials <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Hamiltonians (1.8). In order to formulate the precise statement <lb/> 3  let us remind <lb/>basic definitions of the theory of Schur polynomials. <lb/>Introduce polynomials h  k  (q) by <lb/> k≥0 <lb/> h  k  (q)z <lb/> k  = e <lb/> k≥1  q  k <lb/>z k <lb/>k  , h  k  = 0 for k &lt; 0. <lb/>(1.9) <lb/>For any Young tableau λ = (λ  1  ≥ λ  2  ≥ · · · ≥ λ  n  &gt; 0) (the number n for the <lb/>tableau λ will be denoted l(λ)) define a polynomial <lb/> s  λ  (q) = det (h  λi−i+j  (q))  1≤i, j≤l(λ)  . <lb/> They coincide with the standard Schur polynomials s  λ  (x), up to a normal-<lb/>ization of the independent variables x  k  = <lb/> q  k <lb/> k  . <lb/> Theorem 1.4. For any partition λ the polynomial s  λ <lb/>  q <lb/>  1/2 <lb/> is an eigenvector <lb/>of the operator (1.8) <lb/>ˆ <lb/> H(z, u  0  , )s  λ <lb/>  q <lb/>  1/2 <lb/> = E(z, λ, u  0  , )s  λ <lb/>  q <lb/>  1/2 <lb/> (1.10) <lb/> E(z, λ, u  0  , ) = <lb/> 1/2  z e <lb/> z u0 <lb/> ∞ <lb/> i=1 <lb/> e <lb/> z <lb/> 1/2  (λi−i+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  ) , Re z &gt; 0. <lb/>The sum in the right-hand side makes sense for any infinite sequence <lb/>of nonnegative integers λ  1  ≥ λ  2  ≥ . . . such that λ  i  = 0 for i ≫ 0. Observe <lb/>that the eigenvalue (1.10) essentially coincides with the Chern character of <lb/>the partition λ introduced in [15] <lb/> E(z, λ, u  0  ,  = 1) = z ch  λ  (u  0  , z). <lb/> All Schur polynomials s  λ  (q) of degree n = |λ| form a basis in the space <lb/> V  n  ⊂ C[q] of all graded homogeneous polynomials of degree n in the variables <lb/> q  1  , . . . , q  n  , where the degree is assigned according to the following rule <lb/>deg q  i  = i, i = 1, 2, . . . . <lb/> Thus, the theorem 1.4 provides us with a complete family of eigenstates of <lb/>the commuting quantum Hamiltonians. <lb/> 1.3. Applications to Symplectic Field Theory <lb/> Symplectic Field Theory (SFT) is an approach to constructing topological <lb/>invariants of contact manifolds and symplectic cobordisms between them by <lb/>enumeration of pseudoholomorphic maps of open Riemann surfaces with cer-<lb/>tain boundary conditions. It also provides one with a surgery tool in com-<lb/>puting Gromov–Witten (GW) invariants of closed symplectic manifolds by <lb/>gluing them from simple blocks. <lb/>With a compact contact <lb/> 4  manifold V the SFT associates a bosonic Fock <lb/>space F (V ) generated by closed Reeb orbits on V , assuming them to be all <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 3  A closely related result was recently announced in [1]. <lb/> 4  This assumption can be slightly relaxed, see [8] for details. <lb/></note>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> B. Dubrovin <lb/></note>

			<body> nodegenerate. Choosing a closed odd-dimensional differential form θ on V one <lb/>obtains an infinite sequence of pairwise commuting quantum Hamiltonians <lb/> V <lb/> k  acting on the Fock space. For the particular case V = S <lb/> 1  this gives [7, 8] <lb/>the quantum Hamiltonians (1.8), see more details in Section 3 below. <lb/>A symplectic cobordism W between two contact manifolds V  +  and V  −  , <lb/> ∂W = V  +  ∪ (−V  −  ) <lb/>defines an operator <lb/> Z <lb/> W <lb/> SFT  : F (V  +  ) → F (V  −  ) <lb/>(1.11) <lb/>called the total SFT potential of W . For a closed symplectic manifold W , <lb/> ∂W = ∅, the SFT potential coincides with the total Gromov–Witten (GW) <lb/>descendent potential of W . <lb/>In particular, to a symplectic manifold W with the boundary V the <lb/>total SFT potential of W defines a state Ψ <lb/> W <lb/> SFT  in the Fock space F (V ) (or <lb/>in its dual, depending on the orientation of V = ±∂W ). A suitable choice <lb/>of an even-dimensional closed differential form φ = θ ∧ dρ on W makes the <lb/>SFT potential Ψ <lb/> W <lb/> SFT  depend on an infinite number of coupling parameters t <lb/> φ <lb/>k  . <lb/>The dependence on these parameters is determined from a system of pairwise <lb/>commuting Schrödinger <lb/> 5  equations <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t <lb/> φ <lb/>k <lb/> Ψ <lb/> W <lb/> SFT  = ˆ <lb/> H <lb/> V <lb/>k  Ψ <lb/> W <lb/> SFT  , k = 0, 1, . . . . <lb/> Our goal is to compute this SFT potential for the simplest example V = S <lb/> 1  , <lb/> W =disk. <lb/>Denote <lb/> E(z, λ, u  0  , ) = 1 + <lb/> n≥−1 <lb/> E  n  (λ, u  0  , )z <lb/> n+2 <lb/> (1.12) <lb/>the Taylor expansion of the eigenvalues (1.10), see the explicit formula (2.13) <lb/>below. <lb/> Theorem 1.5. The total SFT potential of a disk ⊂ C is given by the following <lb/>formula <lb/> Ψ <lb/> disk <lb/>SFT  (u  0  , t, p; ) = <lb/> λ <lb/> − <lb/> |λ| <lb/> 2 <lb/> dim λ <lb/> |λ|! <lb/> e <lb/> 1 <lb/> k≥0  t  k  E  k  (u0,,λ)  s  λ <lb/>  p <lb/>  1/2 <lb/> . (1.13) <lb/>Collecting in (1.13) partitions of a given number n = |λ| one obtains a <lb/>part of the SFT potential corresponding to maps of Riemann surfaces with <lb/>cylindrical ends of a given degree n. For low degrees |λ| ≤ 3 keeping the <lb/>variables t  k  for k ≤ 3 one obtains (for simplicity we set u  0  = 0; recall that <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 5  Due to our normalization of canonical coordinates and Hamiltonians the <lb/> √ <lb/> −1 does not <lb/>appear in the equations. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> SFT and Schur polynomials <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>this parameter is responsible for adding punctures on the Riemann surface <lb/>with no cohomology classes inserted) <lb/>Ψ <lb/> disk <lb/> SFT  = e <lb/> − <lb/> t 0 <lb/> 24  + <lb/> 7 t 2 <lb/>5760 <lb/> 1 + <lb/>1 <lb/> e <lb/> t0+ <lb/>  t 2 <lb/>24  p  1 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/>2  2 <lb/> e <lb/> 2t0+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  t1+ <lb/> 7 t 2 <lb/>12  + <lb/> 5 <lb/>24  <lb/> 3 <lb/>2  t3  (p <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  p  2  ) + e <lb/> 2t0− <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  t1+ <lb/> 7 t 2 <lb/>12  − <lb/> 5 <lb/>24  <lb/> 3 <lb/>2  t3  (p <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  p  2  ) <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/>36  3 <lb/> e <lb/> 3t0+3 <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  t1+ <lb/> 21 <lb/>8  t2+ <lb/> 13 <lb/>8  <lb/> 3 <lb/>2  t3  (p <lb/> 3 <lb/>1  + 3 <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  p  1  p  2  + 2 p  3  ) + 4e <lb/> 3t0+ <lb/> 9 <lb/>8  t2  (p <lb/> 3 <lb/>1  −  p  3  ) <lb/>+e <lb/> 3t0−3 <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  t1+ <lb/> 21 <lb/>8  t2− <lb/> 13 <lb/>8  <lb/> 3 <lb/>2  t3  (p <lb/> 3 <lb/>1  − 3 <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  p  1  p  2  + 2 p  3  ) <lb/> + . . . <lb/> It is not difficult to see that the resulting expansion contains only integer <lb/>powers of Planck constant due to the following well known properties (see, <lb/>e.g., [14]) <lb/> s  λ  ′  (p) = (−1) <lb/> |λ|  s  λ  (−p) <lb/>dim λ <lb/> ′  = dim λ. <lb/> Here λ <lb/> ′  is the transposed Young tableau. <lb/> Remark 1.6. Setting in (1.13) t  k  = 0 for k &gt; 0, u  0  = 0, t  0  = β one obtains <lb/>the I.P. Goulden and D.M. Jackson generating function for Hurwitz numbers <lb/>[10] (see also [21]) in the representation of M. Kazarian and S. Lando [13]. <lb/> Corollary 1.7. The tau-function τ (p, ǫ) = Ψ <lb/> disk <lb/>SFT  (t, p, u  0  , ǫ <lb/> 2  ) for arbitrary val-<lb/>ues of the parameters u  0  and t = (t  0  , t  1  , . . . ) satisfies equations of the KP <lb/>hierarchy <lb/> j≥0 <lb/> h  j  (−2y)h  j+1  (ǫ ˜ <lb/> D)e <lb/> ǫ <lb/> k≥1  y  k  D  k  τ · τ = 0 for all y = (y  1  , y  2  , . . . ). (1.14) <lb/> Here <lb/> D = (D  1  , D  2  , . . . ) <lb/> are the Hirota bilinear operators, <lb/> D  k  τ · τ = <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂q <lb/>τ (p  k  + q)(τ (p  k  − q) <lb/> q=0 <lb/> , <lb/> ˜ <lb/> D = (D  1  , 2D  2  , 3D  3  , . . . ). <lb/>Recall that, expanding eqs. (1.14) with respect to the indeterminates y  1  , <lb/> y  2  , etc. one obtains an infinite family of bilinear equations for tau-function <lb/>of the KP hierarchy. E.g., the first two equations read <lb/>(12D <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  − 12D  1  D  3  +  D <lb/> 4 <lb/>1  ) τ · τ = 0 <lb/>(6D  2  D  3  − 6D  1  D  4  +  D <lb/> 3 <lb/>1  D  2  ) τ · τ = 0 <lb/>(recall: here and below ǫ <lb/> 2  = ). The second logarithmic derivative <lb/> u = ǫ <lb/> 2  ∂ <lb/> 2 <lb/> x  log τ <lb/></body>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> B. Dubrovin <lb/></note>

			<body> as function of x = p  1  , y = p  2  , t = p  3  satisfies the Kadomtsev–Petviashvili <lb/>equation <lb/> u  xt  = u  yy  + <lb/> u u  x  + <lb/> 12 <lb/> u  xxx <lb/> x <lb/> . <lb/> (1.15) <lb/>Following the general scheme of [9] one can use the SFT potential of the <lb/>disk for computation of the stationary sector (in the terminology of [18]) of <lb/>Gromov–Witten theory of projective line P <lb/> 1  . Namely, <lb/> Corollary 1.8. Denote M <lb/> • <lb/> g,n  (P <lb/> 1  , d) the space <lb/> 6  of degree d stable maps to P <lb/> 1 <lb/> of not necessarily connected algebraic curves of the total genus g with n punc-<lb/>tures. Let <lb/> χ : M <lb/> • <lb/> g,n  (P <lb/> 1  , d) → Z <lb/> be a locally constant function taking value χ = 2g − 2k on the subset of stable <lb/>maps of k-component curves. Then <lb/> Z <lb/> • <lb/> P  1  (t, z, ) := <lb/> g≥0 <lb/> d≥0 <lb/> z <lb/> d <lb/> m, n <lb/> u <lb/> m <lb/> 0 <lb/> m! <lb/> k1,...,kn <lb/> t  k1  . . . t  kn <lb/> n! <lb/> [M <lb/> • <lb/> g,n+m  (P  1  ,d)] <lb/> virt <lb/> χ <lb/> 2  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> 1  (ω) . . . ev <lb/>  * <lb/> n  (ω)ψ <lb/> k1 <lb/> 1  . . . ψ <lb/> kn <lb/>n <lb/> = <lb/> λ <lb/>  z <lb/>  |λ| <lb/>  dim λ <lb/> |λ|! <lb/>  2 <lb/> e <lb/> 1 <lb/> k≥0  t  k  E  k  (λ,u0,)  . <lb/> (1.16) <lb/>In this formula ω ∈ H <lb/> 2  (P <lb/> 1  ) is the area form normalized by <lb/> P  1 <lb/> ω = 1. <lb/>Specializing (1.16) at u  0  = 0,  = 1 and collecting the terms of degree d <lb/> one arrives at eq. (0.25) of the A. Okounkov and R. Pandharipande paper [18] <lb/>playing an important role in their analysis of GW/Hurwitz correspondence. <lb/>The paper is organised as follows. In Section 2 we recall basics about the <lb/>so-called boson-fermion correspondence. We apply this technique for proving <lb/>Theorem 1.4. In Section 3 we very briefly remind main definitions of Sym-<lb/>plectic Field Theory and prove Theorem 1.5 as well as Corollaries 1.7 and <lb/>1.8. <lb/> 2. Boson-fermion correspondence and proof of Theorem 1.4 <lb/> For simplicity let us do the calculations setting  = 1. The original normal-<lb/>ization will be restored at the end of the proof. <lb/>We will use the so-called boson-fermion correspondence. Let us briefly <lb/>remind the main step of this construction; the reader can find more details <lb/>in [16], [2]. By definition the algebra of free bosons has generators <lb/> 7  q  n  , p  n  , <lb/> n ≥ 1, satisfying commutation relations <lb/>[p  n  , q  m  ] = n δ  n,m  , [p  n  , p  m  ] = [q  n  , q  m  ] = 0. <lb/>(2.1) <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 6  Here we follow notations of [18]. <lb/> 7  Hats over the bosonic operators will be omitted in this section. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> SFT and Schur polynomials <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>It admits a natural representation on the bosonic Fock space <lb/> C[q  1  , q  2  , . . . ]ˆ= <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=0 <lb/> V  n <lb/> V  n  = {f ∈ C[q  1  , . . . , q  n  ] | deg f = n}, assuming deg q  i  = i. <lb/> where the generator q  n  acts by multiplication by q  n  and p  n  by derivation <lb/> p  n  = n <lb/>∂ <lb/>∂q  n <lb/> . <lb/> The algebra of free fermions has two infinite sequences of generators ψ  k  and <lb/> ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  labeled by half-integers. The defining relations are given in terms of anti-<lb/>commutators <lb/> {a, b} = ab + ba. <lb/> They read <lb/> {ψ  i  , ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> j  } = δ  ij  , {ψ  i  , ψ  j  } = {ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> i  , ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> j  } = 0. <lb/>(2.2) <lb/>Fermionic Fock space F is spanned by vectors obtained by action of finite <lb/>products of the generators on the vacuum vector | 0 &gt;. It is assumed that <lb/> ψ  −k  | 0 &gt;= 0, ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  | 0 &gt;= 0 for k &gt; 0. <lb/>The generators ψ  −k  and ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  for k &gt; 0 are called annihilation operators; <lb/>the generators ψ  k  and ψ <lb/>  * <lb/>−k  are creation operators. For any product of the <lb/>fermionic generators the normal order is defined by moving all annihilation <lb/>operators on the right. For example, the normal ordering of the product ψ  i  ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> i <lb/> is <lb/>: ψ  i  ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> i  := <lb/> ψ  i  ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> i  , i &gt; 0 <lb/> −ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> i  ψ  i  , i &lt; 0 <lb/> . <lb/> Vectors of charge zero in the fermionic Fock space can be written as <lb/>linear combinations of vectors of the form <lb/> ψ  i1  . . . ψ  in  ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> j1  . . . ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> jn  | 0 &gt; <lb/> for an arbitrary integer n ≥ 0. The subspace in the Fock space spanned by <lb/>these vectors will be denoted F  0  . The dual space F <lb/>  *  is obtained by a similar <lb/>action on the bra-vector &lt; 0 | assuming that <lb/>0 =&lt; 0 |ψ  k  , 0 =&lt; 0 |ψ <lb/>  * <lb/>−k <lb/> for k &gt; 0. <lb/>The pairing F <lb/>  *  × F → C is completely defined by the anticommutation <lb/>relations (2.2) along with the normalization <lb/> &lt; 0 | 0 &gt;= 1. <lb/>Boson-fermion correspondence is an isomorphism of linear spaces <lb/>Φ : F  0  → C[q  1  , q  2  , . . . ]ˆ <lb/>given by the formula <lb/>Φ(ξ | 0 &gt;) =&lt; 0 |e <lb/> K(q)  ξ | 0 &gt; <lb/> (2.3) <lb/> K(q) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=1 <lb/> q  n <lb/> n <lb/> j <lb/> : ψ  j  ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> j+n  : <lb/></body>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> B. Dubrovin <lb/></note>

			<body> for any state ξ | 0 &gt;∈ F  0  . <lb/>The following formulae hold true <lb/> e <lb/> K(q)  ψ  i  e <lb/> −K(q)  = ψ  i  + h  1  (q)ψ  i−1  + h  2  (q)ψ  i−2  + . . . <lb/> (2.4) <lb/> e <lb/> K(q)  ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> i  e <lb/> −K(q)  = ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> i  + h  1  (−q)ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> i+1  + h  2  (−q)ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> i+2  + . . . <lb/> Here h  k  (q) are elementary Schur polynomials defined in (1.9). <lb/>Due to the isomorphism (2.3) any operator on F  0  becomes an operator <lb/>on the bosonic Fock space C[q  1  , q  2  , . . . ]ˆ and vice versa. For example, the pull-<lb/>back of the operators q  n  and p  n  acting on the bosonic Fock space is given by <lb/>the following infinite sums <lb/>Φ <lb/> −1  q  n  Φ = <lb/> j∈Z+ <lb/> 1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> : ψ  j  ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> j−n  : <lb/>Φ <lb/> −1  p  n  Φ = <lb/> j∈Z+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> : ψ  j  ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> j+n  : <lb/>The following statement was proved by P. Rossi in [20]. <lb/> Proposition 2.1. The fermionic representation of the Hamiltonian (1.8) reads <lb/> Φ <lb/> −1  <lb/> (z, u  0  ,  = 1) Φ = e <lb/> z u0 <lb/>  <lb/> z <lb/> k∈Z+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> e <lb/> k z  : ψ  k  ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  : + <lb/>1 <lb/> s(z) <lb/>  <lb/> . <lb/> (2.5) <lb/>Following [2] construct a basis of the fermionic Fock space F  0  labeled <lb/>by partitions λ = (λ  1  ≥ λ  2  ≥ · · · ≥ λ  n  &gt; 0) of arbitrary length n ≥ 0. It is <lb/>convenient to use Frobenius notations for partitions <lb/> λ = (α  1  , . . . , α  d  | β  1  , . . . , β  d  ) <lb/>(2.6) <lb/>where d = d(λ) is the length of the diagonal of the Young tableau λ, the <lb/>numbers α  i  , β  i  are defined as follows <lb/> α  i  = λ  i  − i, β  i  = λ <lb/> ′ <lb/> i  − i, i = 1, . . . , d(λ). <lb/> Here λ <lb/> ′  is the transposed Young tableau. Define the state | λ &gt;∈ F  0  by <lb/> | λ &gt;= ψ  α1+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ψ  α2+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> . . . ψ  α  d(λ)  + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ψ <lb/>  * <lb/>−β  d(λ)  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> . . . ψ <lb/>  * <lb/>−β2− <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ψ <lb/>  * <lb/>−β1− <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> | 0 &gt; . (2.7) <lb/>For empty partition put | ∅ &gt;= | 0 &gt;. <lb/> The following statement readily follows from Proposition 2.10 of [2]. <lb/> Proposition 2.2. For any partition λ one has <lb/> Φ(| λ &gt;) = (−1) <lb/> b(λ)  s  λ  (q) <lb/>(2.8) <lb/> where <lb/> b(λ) = <lb/> d(λ) <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (β  i  + 1). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SFT and Schur polynomials <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>Denote <lb/> O(z) = <lb/> k∈Z+ <lb/> 1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> e <lb/> k z  : ψ  k  ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  : <lb/>(2.9) <lb/>the nontrivial part of the operator (2.5). <lb/> Lemma 2.3. The states | λ &gt; are eigenvectors of the Hamiltonian (2.9) <lb/> O(z)| λ &gt;= <lb/> d(λ) <lb/> i=1 <lb/> e <lb/> z(αi+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  ) − e <lb/> −z(βi+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  ) <lb/> | λ &gt; . <lb/> (2.10) <lb/> Here the partition λ is represented in the Frobenius form (2.6). <lb/> Proof. One has <lb/> O(z)| λ &gt;= <lb/> k&gt;0 <lb/> e <lb/> k z  ψ  k  ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  ψ  α1+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ψ  α2+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> . . . ψ  α  d(λ)  + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ψ <lb/>  * <lb/>−β  d(λ)  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> . . . ψ <lb/>  * <lb/>−β2− <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ψ <lb/>  * <lb/>−β1− <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> | 0 &gt; <lb/> − <lb/> k&gt;0 <lb/> e <lb/> −k z  ψ <lb/>  * <lb/>−k  ψ  −k  ψ  α1+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ψ  α2+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> . . . ψ  α  d(λ)  + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ψ <lb/>  * <lb/>−β  d(λ)  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> . . . ψ <lb/>  * <lb/>−β2− <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ψ <lb/>  * <lb/>−β1− <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> | 0 &gt; . <lb/> Since ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  annihilates the vacuum for k &gt; 0, in the first sum the only nonzero <lb/>terms are those for which k = α  i  + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  for some 1 ≤ i ≤ d(λ). So <lb/> k&gt;0 <lb/> e <lb/> k z  ψ  k  ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  ψ  α1+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ψ  α2+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> . . . ψ  α  d(λ)  + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ψ <lb/>  * <lb/>−β  d(λ)  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> . . . ψ <lb/>  * <lb/>−β2− <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ψ <lb/>  * <lb/>−β1− <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> | 0 &gt; <lb/> = <lb/> d(λ) <lb/> i=1 <lb/> e <lb/> z  (αi+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  ) |λ &gt; . <lb/> In a similar way in the second sum the nonzero terms come from k = β  i  + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  , <lb/>1 ≤ i ≤ d(λ). This gives the second half of eq. (2.10). <lb/> It is easy to see that <lb/> d(λ) <lb/> i=1 <lb/> e <lb/> z(αi+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  ) − e <lb/> −z(βi+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  ) <lb/> = <lb/> l(λ) <lb/> i=1 <lb/> e <lb/> z(λi−i+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  ) − e <lb/> z(−i+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  ) <lb/> . <lb/> (2.11) <lb/>So, to complete the proof of the theorem it remains to reinsert the Planck <lb/>constant. This can be done by rescaling <lb/> q  k  → <lb/> k−1 <lb/> 2  q  k  , z → <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  z. <lb/> The theorem is proved. <lb/> Corollary 2.4. For any partition λ = (λ  1  ≥ λ  2  ≥ · · · ≥ λ  l(λ)  &gt; 0) = <lb/>(α  1  , . . . , α  d(λ)  | β  1  , . . . , β  d(λ)  ) the polynomials s  λ <lb/>  q <lb/>  1/2 <lb/> are common eigenvec-<lb/>tors of the commuting operators  <lb/>  k <lb/> ˆ <lb/> H  k  s  λ <lb/>  q <lb/>  1/2 <lb/> = E  k  (λ, u  0  , )s  λ <lb/>  q <lb/>  1/2 <lb/> , k ≥ −1 <lb/> (2.12) <lb/></body>

			<page> 12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> B. Dubrovin <lb/></note>

			<body> with the eigenvalues given by one of the two equivalent expressions <lb/> E  k  (λ, u  0  , ) = c  k  (u  0  , ) <lb/> (2.13) <lb/>+ <lb/> 1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> l(λ) <lb/> i=1 <lb/> u  0  + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> λ  i  − i + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>  k+1 <lb/> − <lb/> u  0  + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> −i + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>  k+1 <lb/> (k + 1)! <lb/>= c  k  (u  0  , ) + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> d(λ) <lb/> i=1 <lb/> u  0  + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> α  i  + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>  k+1 <lb/> − <lb/> u  0  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> β  i  + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>  k+1 <lb/> (k + 1)! <lb/> where <lb/> c  k  (u  0  , ) = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>(k + 2)! <lb/> k+2 <lb/> j=0 <lb/> k + 2 <lb/> j <lb/> 1 − 2 <lb/> 1−j  <lb/> B  j  <lb/> j <lb/> 2  u <lb/> k−j+2 <lb/> 0 <lb/> , <lb/>B  j  are Bernoulli numbers. <lb/>Proof. With the help of an obvious formula <lb/> i≥1 <lb/> e <lb/> z  (−i+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/> z s(z) <lb/>, Re z &gt; 0 <lb/>the expressions (1.10) can be rewritten in the form <lb/> E(z, λ, u  0  , ) = e <lb/> z u0 <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> 1 <lb/> s <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  z <lb/> + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  z <lb/> l(λ) <lb/> i=1 <lb/> e <lb/> z <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  (λi−i+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  ) − e <lb/> z <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  (−i+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  ) <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> = e <lb/> z u0 <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> 1 <lb/> s <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  z <lb/> + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  z <lb/> d(λ) <lb/> i=1 <lb/> e <lb/> z <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  (αi+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  ) − e <lb/> −z <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  (βi+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  ) <lb/> <lb/> . <lb/> Expanding the right-hand side in z and using the Taylor expansion <lb/>1 <lb/> s(t) <lb/> = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=0 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 1−n  − 1 <lb/> B  n <lb/> n! <lb/>t <lb/> n <lb/> one arrives at the needed formula for the eigenvalues. <lb/> Remark 2.5. An alternative derivation [18] of the spectrum of the operator <lb/>(2.9) uses a realization of the fermionic algebra by operators acting on the <lb/>Sato infinite-dimensional Grassmannian. Let us briefly outline this construc-<lb/>tion that will be useful below. Introduce an infinite-dimensional space with <lb/>a basis e  k  , <lb/> V = <lb/> k∈Z+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> Ce  k  . <lb/> Denote <lb/>Λ <lb/> ∞ <lb/> 2  V = span (e  i1  ∧ e  i2  ∧ . . . | i  1  &gt; i  2  &gt; . . . , i  k  = −k for large k) , <lb/>e  j  ∧ e  i  = −e  i  ∧ e  j  . <lb/> (2.14) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SFT and Schur polynomials <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Action of the fermionic algebra is defined by adding or erasing a factor on <lb/>the left of a semi-infinite wedge product <lb/> ψ  k  = e  k  ∧ , ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  = <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂e  k <lb/> , k ∈ Z + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> . <lb/> (2.15) <lb/>The vacuum vector reads <lb/> | 0 &gt;= e  −1/2  ∧ e  −3/2  ∧ . . . . <lb/> For any partition λ = (λ  1  ≥ λ  2  ≥ · · · ≥ λ  l  &gt; 0) consider <lb/> v  λ  = e  λ1− <lb/> 1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> ∧ e  λ2− <lb/> 3 <lb/>2 <lb/> ∧ · · · ∧ e  λ  l  −l+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ∧ e  −l− <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ∧ · · · ∈ Λ <lb/> ∞ <lb/> 2  V. <lb/> (2.16) <lb/>The vectors of the form (2.16) span the fermionic phase space F  0  . According <lb/>to [18] it is an eigenvector of the operator (2.9) with the eigenvalue <lb/> l <lb/> i=1 <lb/> e <lb/> z(λi−i+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  ) − e <lb/> z(−i+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  ) <lb/> . <lb/> 3. SFT potential of a disk <lb/> Let us very briefly outline the main constructions of SFT; more details can <lb/>be found in [9], [6], [8]; see also [20]. <lb/>Let (V, α) be a contact manifold with a contact form α. Denote R the <lb/>Reeb vector field on V . Let P(V ) be the set of periodic orbits of R. For sim-<lb/>plicity assume that all periodic orbits are non-degenerate; in this case P(V ) <lb/>is a discrete set. The first playing character is the SFT Hamiltonian H <lb/> V  . <lb/>The construction uses intersection theory on the moduli spaces of pseudo-<lb/>holomorphic maps <lb/> f : (C  g  , x  1  , . . . , x  n  ; y <lb/> − <lb/> 1  , . . . , y <lb/> − <lb/> r−  ; y <lb/> + <lb/>1  , . . . , y <lb/> + <lb/> r+  ) → V × R <lb/> of Riemann surfaces of genus g with n marked points x  1  , . . . , x  n  , r  −  negative <lb/>punctures y <lb/> − <lb/> 1  , . . . , y <lb/> − <lb/> r−  ∈ C  g  and r  +  positive punctures y <lb/> + <lb/>1  , . . . , y <lb/> + <lb/> r+  ∈ C  g  . <lb/>One has to choose an almost complex structure J on the cylinder V × R <lb/> compatible with the symplectic form d (e <lb/> t  α) where t ∈ R. It must be invari-<lb/>ant with respect to t-translations and satisfy certain additional restrictions. <lb/>The boundary conditions for the pseudoholomorphic maps near the posi-<lb/>tive/negative punctures depend on a choice of suitably oriented Reeb orbits <lb/> γ <lb/> + <lb/>1  , . . . , γ <lb/> + <lb/> r+  and γ <lb/> − <lb/> 1  , . . . , γ <lb/> − <lb/> r−  in P(V ). Namely, the map f must be asymp-<lb/>totically cylindrical near the negative punctures y <lb/> − <lb/> 1  , . . . , y <lb/> − <lb/> r−  to the orbits <lb/> γ <lb/> − <lb/> 1  , . . . , γ <lb/> − <lb/> r−  at t → −∞ and to γ <lb/> + <lb/>1  , . . . , γ <lb/> + <lb/> r+  near the positive punctures y <lb/> + <lb/>1  , <lb/>. . . , y <lb/> + <lb/> r+  at t → +∞. Denote <lb/> M  g,n  (V ; γ <lb/> −  , γ <lb/> +  ), γ <lb/> +  = (γ <lb/> − <lb/> 1  , . . . , γ <lb/> − <lb/> r−  ), γ <lb/> −  = (γ <lb/> + <lb/>1  , . . . , γ <lb/> + <lb/> r+  ) <lb/>(3.1) <lb/>the moduli space of such maps. The group R acts on the moduli space by <lb/>translations. The quotient can be compactified by adding stable holomorphic <lb/>buildings [6]. Denote M  g,n  (V ; γ  −  , γ  +  )/R the compactified space. Choosing a <lb/>system of closed differential forms θ  1  , . . . , θ  N  on V define the so-called SFT <lb/></body>

			<page> 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> B. Dubrovin <lb/></note>

			<body> Hamiltonian H <lb/> V  = H <lb/> V  (t, q, p, ) as a generating function of the intersection <lb/>numbers on the moduli spaces as follows <lb/> 8 <lb/> H <lb/> V  = <lb/> g≥0 <lb/> g <lb/> n,r−,r+ <lb/> 0≤i1,...,in≤N <lb/>0≤k1,...,kn <lb/> γ <lb/> − <lb/> b 1 <lb/> ,...,γ <lb/> − <lb/> br − <lb/> γ <lb/> + <lb/> c 1 <lb/> ,...,γ <lb/> + <lb/> cr + <lb/> t <lb/> i1 <lb/>k1  . . . t <lb/> in <lb/>kn <lb/> n! <lb/>q  b1  . . . q  br  − <lb/> r  −  ! <lb/> p  c1  . . . p  cr  + <lb/> r  +  ! <lb/> × <lb/> Mg,n(V ;  γ  −  ,γ  +  )/R <lb/> ev <lb/>  * <lb/> 1  (θ  i1  )ψ <lb/> k1 <lb/> 1  ∧ · · · ∧ ev <lb/>  * <lb/> n  (θ  in  )ψ <lb/> kn <lb/>n <lb/> (3.2) <lb/>Here ev  i  are the evaluation maps <lb/>ev  i  : M  g,n  (V ; γ  −  , γ  +  )/R → V, f → f (x  i  ), i = 1, . . . , n, <lb/>ψ  i  = c  1  (L  i  ) are the Chern classes of the tautological line bundles over the <lb/>moduli spaces. All the independent variables in the formula are Z/2-graded. <lb/> In particular, the parity of the variables t <lb/> i <lb/>k  , i = 1, . . . , N , k = 0, 1, . . . is <lb/>determined by parity of the chosen differential forms θ  1  , . . . , θ  N  . The q- and <lb/> p-variables labeled by Reeb orbits belong to a Weyl (super)-algebra with the <lb/>commutation relations <lb/>[p  γ  , q  γ  ′  ]  ±  =  mult(γ)δ  γ γ  ′  . <lb/> As the moduli spaces M  g,n  (V ; γ  −  , γ  +  )/R are odd-dimensional, the generating <lb/>function is an odd element of the algebra. Expanding H <lb/> V  with respect to odd <lb/> variables t <lb/> i <lb/>k  and taking the cohomology class one obtains therefore infinite <lb/>families of commuting Hamiltonians <lb/>ˆ <lb/> H <lb/> V <lb/>i,k  (q, p, ) := <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  i <lb/>k <lb/> H <lb/> V  <lb/> t=0 <lb/> in the Weyl algebra. <lb/>In the simplest case V = S <lb/> 1  the above construction yields the commut-<lb/>ing quantum Hamiltonians (1.8). In this case the set of Reeb orbits is just the <lb/>set of integers. The moduli spaces (3.1) are nontrivial only for positive mul-<lb/>tiplicities. Thus one has independent variables q  n  , p  n  , n = 1, 2, . . . satisfying <lb/>the commutation relation (1.5). Choose θ  0  = 1, θ  1  = dϕ as two differential <lb/>forms on S <lb/> 1  (here ϕ is the angular coordinate on the circle). The SFT Hamil-<lb/>tonian H <lb/> S <lb/> 1  is an odd element of the Weyl algebra with generators p  n  , q  n  , <lb/> n ≥ 1 depending on even variables t <lb/> 0 <lb/> k  and odd variables t <lb/> 1 <lb/> k  , k ≥ 0. Taking <lb/>derivatives with respect to odd variables produces the commuting quantum <lb/>Hamiltonians according to the following procedure [8]. <lb/> Proposition 3.1. Restriction of the derivatives of H <lb/> S <lb/> 1  = H <lb/> S <lb/> 1  (t, q, p, ) onto <lb/>the locus t <lb/> 0 <lb/>0  = u  0  , t <lb/> 0 <lb/> k  = 0 for k &gt; 0, t <lb/> 1 <lb/> k  = 0 for all k yields the commuting <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 8  Our definition differs by a factor  from the one of [9], [8]. This factor will be restored <lb/>below, see the Schrödinger equation (3.9). <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> SFT and Schur polynomials <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body> Hamiltonians (1.8) <lb/> ∂ <lb/> ∂t  1 <lb/> n <lb/> H <lb/> S <lb/> 1  |  t  0 <lb/>0  =u0, t  0 <lb/> k  =0 for k&gt;0, t  1 <lb/> k  =0  = ˆ <lb/> H  n  (u  0  , ), n ≥ 0. <lb/>(3.3) <lb/>More generally, with a symplectic cobordism W between two contact <lb/>manifolds V  +  and V  −  , <lb/> ∂W = V  +  ∪ (−V  −  ) <lb/>one can associate a family of moduli spaces M  g,n  (W, γ <lb/> −  , γ <lb/> +  ) labeled by col-<lb/>lections of Reeb orbits γ <lb/> −  = (γ <lb/> − <lb/> 1  , . . . , γ <lb/> − <lb/> r−  ) on V  −  and γ <lb/> +  = (γ <lb/> + <lb/>1  , . . . , γ <lb/> + <lb/> r+  ) on <lb/> V  +  . To this end one has to consider pseudoholomorphic maps with cylindrical <lb/>ends of Riemann surfaces of genus g with r  −  negative and r  +  positive punc-<lb/>tures and also with n marked points x  1  , . . . , x  n  to the symplectic manifold <lb/> W ∪ (V  −  × (−∞, 0]) ∪ (V  +  × [0, +∞)) equipped with an appropriate almost <lb/>complex structure. Evaluation maps are defined <lb/>ev  i  : M  g,n  (W, γ <lb/> −  , γ <lb/> +  ) → W, i = 1, . . . , n <lb/> by taking images of the marked points. In this way one arrives at the SFT <lb/>potential <lb/> Z <lb/> W <lb/> SFT  (t, q, p, ) = e <lb/> 1 <lb/> g≥0  <lb/> g  F <lb/> SFT <lb/> g <lb/> (t,q,p)  . <lb/> (3.4) <lb/>Here the genus g part F <lb/> SFT <lb/> g <lb/> (t, q, p) is the generating function of numbers <lb/>obtained by integrating over the compactified moduli spaces M  g,n  (W, γ  −  , γ  +  ) <lb/>the pull-backs ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (φ) of differential forms φ on W along with ψ-classes. The <lb/>independent variables q = (q  γ  −  ) and p = (p  γ  +  ) are labeled by Reeb orbits <lb/>on V  −  and V  +  respectively. <lb/>If W is obtained by glueing together two symplectic cobordisms <lb/> W = W  1  ∪ W  2  , ∂W  1  = V ∪ (−V  −  ), ∂W  2  = V  +  ∪ (−V ) <lb/>between contact manifold V  −  and V and V and V  +  respectively then the SFT <lb/>potential of W can be obtained by applying the following glueing rules <lb/> Z <lb/> W  (q  −  , p  +  ) = Z <lb/> W1  <lb/> q  −  , − → p <lb/> Z <lb/> W2  (q, p  +  ) |  q=0 <lb/> (3.5) <lb/>= Z <lb/> W1  (q  −  , p) Z <lb/> W2  ← − <lb/> q , p  + <lb/> |  p=0  . <lb/> The variables q = (q  γ  ) and p = (p  γ  ) are labeled by Reeb orbits on V . The <lb/>left-acting operator − → p  γ  and right-acting operator ← − q  γ  are defined by <lb/> − → p  γ  =  mult(γ) <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂q  γ <lb/> , ← − q  γ  =  mult(γ) <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂p  γ <lb/> . <lb/> In the particular case of a symplectic manifold W with a boundary <lb/> V = V  −  the total SFT potential depends only on the canonical coordinates <lb/> q  γ  labeled by Reeb orbits on V . It can be considered as a state in the bosonic <lb/>Fock space generated by Reeb orbits on V . This state will be denoted by <lb/>Ψ <lb/> W <lb/> SFT  (t, q, ) := Z <lb/> W <lb/> SFT  (t, q, ). <lb/> In a similar way, for a symplectic manifold W with a boundary V = V  +  one <lb/>obtains a state in the dual Fock space <lb/>Ψ <lb/> W <lb/> SFT  (t, p, ) := Z <lb/> W <lb/> SFT  (t, p, ). <lb/></body>

			<page> 16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> B. Dubrovin <lb/></note>

			<body>Finally, for a closed symplectic manifold W the total SFT potential coincides <lb/>with the GW total descendent potential <lb/> Z <lb/> W <lb/> SFT  (t, ) = Z <lb/> W <lb/> GW  (t, ). <lb/> To insert pullbacks of cohomology classes of the form φ = θ ∧ dρ, θ ∈ <lb/> Ω <lb/> odd  (V  +  ), dρ ∈ Ω <lb/> 1 <lb/>comp  (R) along with their descendents one can use the SFT <lb/>Hamiltonians (3.2): <lb/> Z <lb/> W <lb/> SFT  (t, q  −  , p  +  , ) = <lb/> Z <lb/> W <lb/> SFT  (q  −  , p, ) e <lb/> 1 <lb/> k≥0  t <lb/> φ <lb/>k <lb/> ˆ <lb/> H <lb/> V + <lb/> k  ( ← − <lb/> q ,p+,) <lb/> p=0 <lb/> (3.6) <lb/>where the quantum Hamiltonians H <lb/> V+ <lb/>k <lb/> are defined in a way similar to (3.3), <lb/>ˆ <lb/> H <lb/> V+ <lb/>k  (q, p, ) = <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  θ <lb/>k <lb/> H <lb/> V+  (t, q, p, )|  t=0  , k ≥ 0. <lb/>In the calculations of this section the following two formulae from the <lb/>theory of Schur polynomials will be useful (see, e.g., the Macdonald book <lb/>[14]). <lb/> Proposition 3.2. The following formulae hold true <lb/> q <lb/> n <lb/> 1  = <lb/> |λ|=n <lb/> dim λ · s  λ  (q  1  , . . . , q  n  ) <lb/>(3.7) <lb/> s  λ  (q  1  , . . . , q  n  ) = <lb/>dim λ <lb/>n! <lb/>q <lb/> n <lb/> 1  + . . . , n = |λ| <lb/> (3.8) <lb/> where periods stand for monomials of lower degree in q  1  . <lb/> In these formulae dim λ is the dimension of the irreducible representa-<lb/>tion of the symmetric group S  n  associated with the Young tableau λ. Recall <lb/>that this dimension can be computed using the hook length formula <lb/>dim λ = <lb/> |λ|! <lb/> (i,j)∈λ  h(i, j) <lb/> (ibid.) <lb/>We are now ready to prove Theorem 1.5. <lb/> Proof. According to the prescription (3.6) one has to solve a system of pair-<lb/>wise commuting non-stationary Schrödinger equations for the wave function <lb/>Ψ = Ψ <lb/> disk <lb/>SFT <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  k <lb/> Ψ = Ψ <lb/> ← − <lb/> H  k  , k = 0, 1, 2, . . . <lb/> (3.9) <lb/>with the plane wave initial data <lb/>Ψ|  t=0  = e <lb/> p 1 <lb/>  . <lb/> Using eq. (3.7) one decomposes the initial condition in a linear combination <lb/>of common eigenvectors of the commuting Hamiltonians <lb/> e <lb/> p 1 <lb/>  = <lb/> λ <lb/> − <lb/> |λ| <lb/> 2 <lb/> dim λ <lb/> |λ|! <lb/> s  λ <lb/>  p <lb/>  1/2 <lb/> . <lb/> With the help of such a decomposition, using (2.13), one arrives at (1.13). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SFT and Schur polynomials <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>We will now prove Corollary 1.7 . <lb/> Proof. According to [16] tau-functions of the KP hierarchy correspond to <lb/>simple multivectors <lb/> τ (q  1  , q  2  , . . . ) = Φ <lb/> ϕ  − <lb/> 1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> ∧ ϕ  − <lb/> 3 <lb/>2 <lb/> ∧ . . . <lb/> , ϕ  ν  ∈ V, ν ∈ Z + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> , ν &lt; 0 <lb/>(for notations see Remark 2.5 above). Choosing <lb/> ϕ  ν  = <lb/> i≥0 <lb/> A  ν,i  e  ν+i <lb/> A  ν,i  = <lb/>1 <lb/> i! <lb/> exp <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> k≥0 <lb/> t  k <lb/> [u  0  + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  (ν + i)] <lb/> k+1  − [u  0  + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  ν] <lb/> k+1 <lb/> (k + 1)! <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> (cf. [12]) one obtains the expression (1.13). <lb/> Proof of Corollary 1.8. According to the above procedures to compute <lb/>the Gromov–Witten potential of P <lb/> 1  within the stationary sector one has <lb/>to apply the SFT potential of the disk to the potential of the cap without <lb/>insertions, i.e., <lb/> Z <lb/> • <lb/> P  1  (t, z, ) = Ψ <lb/> disk <lb/>SFT <lb/> u  0  , t, − → p ; <lb/> e <lb/> z q 1 <lb/>  |  q=0  . <lb/> Here the independent parameter z is added for convenience in order to sep-<lb/>arate terms of various degrees. Due to (3.8) one has <lb/> s  λ  ( − → p )q <lb/> n <lb/> 1  |  q=0  = <lb/> n  dim λ, |λ| = n <lb/> 0, <lb/>otherwise. <lb/>This completes the proof. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgment <lb/> I am indebted to Y. Eliashberg for introducing me into Symplectic Field <lb/>Theory. I also wish to thank G. Bonelli, A. Tanzini, and P. Wiegmann for <lb/>stimulating discussions. This work is partially supported by the PRIN 2010-<lb/>11 Grant &quot; Geometric and analytic theory of Hamiltonian systems in finite <lb/>and infinite dimensions &quot; of Italian Ministry of Universities and Researches <lb/>and by Russian Federation Government Grant No. 2010-220-01-077. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] A. Alexandrov, Matrix models for random partitions, Nucl. Phys. B 851 (2011) <lb/>620-650. <lb/>[2] A. Alexandrov, A. Zabrodin, Free fermions and tau-functions, J. Geom. Phys. <lb/> 67 (2013) 37-80. <lb/>[3] H. Awata, Y. Matsuo, S. Odake, J. Shiraishi, Collective field theory, Calogero– <lb/>Sutherland model and generalised matrix models, Phys. Lett. B 347 (1995) 49 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 18 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> B. Dubrovin <lb/> [4] V. Bazhanov, S. Lukyanov, A. Zamolodchikov, Integrable structure of conformal <lb/>field theory, quantum KdV theory and thermodynamic Bethe ansatz, Commun. <lb/> Math. Phys. 177 (1996) 381-398; <lb/>Integrable structure of conformal field theory II. Q-operator and DDV equation, <lb/> Commun. Math. Phys. 190 (1997) 247-278; <lb/>Integrable structure of conformal field theory III. The Yang–Baxter relation, <lb/> Commun. Math. Phys. 200 (1999) 297-324. <lb/>[5] G. Bonelli, A. Sciarappa, A. Tanzini, P. Vasko, Six-dimensional supersymmet-<lb/>ric gauge theories, quantum cohomology of instanton moduli spaces and gl(N ) <lb/>Quantum Intermediate Long Wave Hydrodynamics, arXiv:1403.6454. <lb/>[6] F. Bourgeois, Y. Eliashberg, H. Hofer, K. Wysocki, E. Zehnder, Compactness <lb/>results in Symplectic Field Theory. Geom. Topol. 7 (2003), 799-888. <lb/>[7] Y. Eliashberg, Private communication, 2002. <lb/>[8] Y. Eliashberg, Symplectic field theory and applications, Proceedings of ICM <lb/>2006, 217-246. <lb/>[9] Y. Eliashberg, A. Givental and H. Hofer, Introduction to Symplectic Field The-<lb/>ory, GAFA 2000 Visions in Mathematics special volume, part II, 560-673. <lb/>[10] I. P. Goulden and D. M. Jackson, Transitive factorisations into transpositions <lb/>and holomorphic mappings on the sphere, Proc. A.M.S. 125 (1997), 51-60. <lb/>[11] D. Karabali, A. Polychronakos, Exact operator Hamiltonians and interactions <lb/>in the droplet bosonization method, arXiv:1403.5967. <lb/>[12] M. Kazarian, KP hierarchy for Hodge integrals, Adv. Math. 221 (2009) 1-21. <lb/>[13] M. Kazarian, S. Lando, An algebro-geometric proof of Witten&apos;s conjecture, J. <lb/>Amer. Math. Soc. 20:4 (2007), 1079-1089. <lb/>[14] I.G. Macdonald, Symmetric Functions and Hall Polynomials, Oxford Mathe-<lb/>matical Monographs, 2nd edition, 1995. <lb/>[15] A. Marshakov, N. Nekrasov, Extended Seiberg–Witten theory and integrable <lb/>hierarchy, JHEP 0701:104,2007 <lb/>[16] T. Miwa, M. Jimbo, E. Date, Solitons: Differential Equations, Symmetries and <lb/>Infinite Dimensional Algebras, Cambridge University Press, 2000. <lb/>[17] A. Okounkov, Infinite wedge and random partitions, Selecta Math. 7 (2001) <lb/>57-81. <lb/>[18] A. Okounkov, R. Pandharipande, Gromov-Witten theory, Hurwitz theory, and <lb/>completed cycles, Annals of Math. (2) 163 (2006), 517-560. <lb/>[19] A. K. Pogrebkov, Boson-fermion correspondence and quantum integrable and <lb/>dispersionless models, Russian Math. Surveys, 58:5 (2003), 1003-1037 <lb/>[20] P. Rossi, Gromov–Witten invariants of target curves via Symplectic Field The-<lb/>ory, J. Geom. Phys. 58 (2008) 931-941. <lb/>[21] R. Vakil, Enumerative geometry of curves via degeneration methods, Harvard <lb/>Ph.D. thesis, 1997. <lb/> SFT and Schur polynomials <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 19 <lb/></page>

			<front>Boris Dubrovin <lb/> SISSA <lb/>Via Bonomea, 265 <lb/>I-34136 TRIESTE <lb/>ITALY <lb/>and N.N.Bogolyubov Laboratory of Geometrical Methods in Mathematical Physics, <lb/>Moscow State University, Moscow, RUSSIA <lb/>e-mail: dubrovin@sissa.it </front>


	</text>
</tei>
