<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Study of cosmic ray muons momentum and charge asymmetry spectra <lb/> V. Sharma <lb/> 1, <lb/> *, K. Saraswat, V. Singh <lb/> 1 and V. S. Subrahmanyam <lb/> 1 <lb/> 1 Department of Physics, Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi -221005, INDIA <lb/> .  * email:vivek.bhu.hep@gmail.com <lb/> In this article, we studied cosmic ray momentum and charge asymmetry spectra. Data were collected using India-based <lb/>Neutrino Observatory prototype Iron Calorimeter (ICAL) working at VECC in Kolkata. Results presented in this article <lb/>are drawn from the data taken during initial phase of the data taking. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> The VECC ICAL prototype is made for the <lb/>study of the behavior of resistive plate chamber <lb/>(RPC) detector using cosmic rays muons during <lb/>ON and OFF magnetic field having strength around <lb/>1.5 Tesla. This prototype consists of twelve layers <lb/>of RPC detectors including three layers of Bakelite <lb/>electrode and nine layers of glass electrode. Each <lb/>detector is sandwiched between layers of around 5 <lb/>cm thick iron sheet. Each RPC detectors having <lb/>read out crossed strips to locate the co-ordinate of <lb/>interaction point. Raw data from stack is used to <lb/>regenerate the track of passed charged particles. <lb/>This work is about the study of cosmic ray muons <lb/>charge ratio (µ <lb/> + <lb/> /µ <lb/> − <lb/> ) and its momentum spectrum by <lb/>reconstruction of tracks in the magnetic field <lb/>having 500 A current in the coils with layer 3, layer <lb/>9 and layer 11 RPC detectors as a trigger for any <lb/>event. <lb/> 2. VECC ICAL Detector <lb/> The ICAL Prototype detector has 12 RPCs <lb/>which are interleaved in the gap between 13 layers <lb/>of iron plates of dimension 2.4m x 2.17m x 0.05m <lb/>with 50 kton ICAL magnet. By applying a D.C. <lb/>high voltage to these electrodes, an electric field is <lb/>generated across the gas gap. A passing charged <lb/>particle creates an avalanche in the gas inside the <lb/>detector. High resistivity of the electrodes prevents <lb/>discharge to spread over entire gas volume. The <lb/>created electron and positive ion pairs while <lb/>traveling towards the respective electrodes induces <lb/>signal on the pickup strips placed over the electrode <lb/>plates. The generated charge is deposited on a small <lb/>region of the electrode plate and the spot is slowly <lb/>recharged by current flowing through the plate. If <lb/>the electric field is even more intense, a &apos;spark&apos; <lb/>breakdown can be initiated by the avalanche. In the <lb/>conventional single gap RPC for the avalanche <lb/>mode of operation, mixtures of tetrafluroethane (R-<lb/>134a) with 2-5% of isobutene are used. The single <lb/>gap RPC first developed has been replaced by its <lb/>variants, where electrode materials, gap thickness <lb/>and geometry have been changed. VECC-SINP <lb/>developed Bakelite RPCs and in this stack 8 glass <lb/>RPCs and 4 bakellite RPCs are used. Glass RPCs <lb/>are running in avalanche mode and here pulse <lb/>height is in ~mV order and requires amplification <lb/>using preamplifier. Bakellite RPCs are running in <lb/>streamer mode and here pulse height is few <lb/>hundreds mV, so no need for amplification. Each <lb/>RPC has 32 pick-up strips along x-and y-axis. Both <lb/>types of RPCs are using two separate gas mixing <lb/>and distribution systems. Each Iron layer is made of <lb/>&apos;C&apos; and &apos;T&apos; section. The whole tracking detectors <lb/>are kept inside a magnetic field and continue to be <lb/>in operation for last more than two years. A total of <lb/>4 coils, each having five turns and wound <lb/>perpendicular to the plane of the Iron plates make <lb/>up an electromagnet which can be magnetized up to <lb/>1.6 Tesla. The power supply has two current <lb/>sources and it is operated in master-slave mode [1]. <lb/> 3. Reconstruction of particle track <lb/> The processed raw tracks are consisting of <lb/>many garbage points due to noise generated by <lb/>electronics or some other means. Therefore, the <lb/>first step to reconstruct the track was to choose only <lb/>those tracks which have least noise. After this, such <lb/>tracks which are not fitted satisfactorily have to be <lb/>excluded by the assigned cuts to get better fitting. A <lb/>good fitting track is shown in Figure 1. <lb/> Fig. 1: An example of fitted track after employing <lb/>cuts. On X-axis strip number and on Y-axis RPC <lb/>detector numbers are plotted. <lb/>After getting a good fit for reconstructed <lb/>tracks, fitting parameters have to be taken in <lb/>account for further calculation of momentum and <lb/>muon charge ratio. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Proceedings of the DAE Symp. on Nucl. Phys. 58 (2013) <lb/></note>

			<page> 814 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Available online at www.sympnp.org/proceedings <lb/></note>

			<body> 4. Results of Analysis of VECC Data <lb/> We know that charged particles travel in <lb/>circular path in the uniform magnetic field. During <lb/>ON magnetic field, part of the charged particle <lb/>circular path takes place due to limited dimension <lb/>of the detector and the radius of curvature of the <lb/>track provides information about the momentum of <lb/>the charge particle. Therefore, when magnetic field <lb/>is on and uniform over the active volume of the <lb/>RPC detector stack, the passing charged particles <lb/>follow circular path and only part of that path will <lb/>be observed as a curved trajectory and with the help <lb/>of the curvature of trajectory muon momentum <lb/>could be derived. Comparison between final <lb/>momentum spectrum and momentum spectrum <lb/>before final cut is shown in Figure 2. <lb/> Fig 2: Comparison of final momentum with <lb/>momentum before final cut. <lb/> Fig 3: Comparison cosmic ray muons momentum <lb/>spectrum with the similar spectrum of CMS <lb/>experiment. <lb/>Comparison of final cosmic ray muons momentum <lb/>spectrum with similar spectrum observed by CMS <lb/>experiment [2] is shown in Figure 3. <lb/>The muon charge ratio with respect to cosmic <lb/>ray momentum is shown in Figure 4 along with the <lb/>spectrum observed by BESS, MINOS and L3C <lb/>experiments. <lb/> Fig 4: Comparisons of muon charge ratio spectrum <lb/>with other experimental results [3-5]. <lb/>Under ground and surface effects on cosmic ray <lb/>momentum and charge are observed. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments <lb/> The authors would like to thank the VECC <lb/>group for providing raw data and information about <lb/>experimental setup. Authors are also thankful to <lb/>the DST, New Delhi for providing financial <lb/>support. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] Nuclear Instruments and Methods in Physics <lb/>Research A 602 (2009) 784–787 <lb/>[2] CMS PAPER CFT-09-014 29 Jan 2010. <lb/>[3] S. Haino et al. (BESS Collaboration), Phys. <lb/>Lett. B 594, 35 (2004). <lb/>[4] P. Archard et al. (L3+C Collaboration), Phys. <lb/>Lett. B 598, 15 (2004). <lb/>[5] P. Adamson et al. (MINOS Collaboration), <lb/>Phys. <lb/>Rev. <lb/> D76, <lb/> 052003 <lb/>(2007). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> Proceedings of the DAE Symp. on Nucl. Phys. 58 (2013) <lb/></note>

			<page> 815 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Available online at www.sympnp.org/proceedings </note>


	</text>
</tei>
