<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="footnote"> arXiv:1007.2701v1  [nlin.SI] 16 Jul 2010 <lb/></note>

			<front> ADDITIONAL SYMMETRIES OF CONSTRAINED CKP AND BKP <lb/>HIERARCHIES <lb/> KELEI TIAN †, JINGSONG HE <lb/>  *   ‡, JIPENG CHENG † AND YI CHENG  † <lb/> † Department of Mathematics, University of Science and Technology of China, China <lb/> ‡ Department of Mathematics, Ningbo University, China <lb/> Abstract. The additional symmetries of the constrained CKP (cCKP) and BKP (cBKP) hi-<lb/>erarchies are given by their actions on the Lax operators, and their actions on the eigenfunction <lb/>and adjoint eigenfunction {Φ  i  , Ψ  i  } are presented explicitly. Furthermore, we show that acting <lb/>on the space of the wave operator, ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  forms new centerless W <lb/> cC <lb/> 1+∞  and W <lb/> cB <lb/> 1+∞  -subalgebra of <lb/>centerless W  1+∞  respectively. In order to define above symmetry flows ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  of the cCKP and <lb/>cBKP hierarchies, two vital operators Y  k  are introduced to revise the additional symmetry <lb/>flows of the CKP and BKP hierarchies. <lb/> PACS (2003). 02.30.Ik. <lb/>Mathematics Subject Classification (2000). 17B80, 37K05, 37K10. <lb/>Keywords. constrained CKP hierarchy, constrained BKP hierarchy, additional symmetry. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/> The research on Kadomtsev-Petviashvili (KP) hierarchy [1, 2] is one of the most important <lb/>topics in the development of the theory of integrable systems. A specific interesting aspect <lb/>on this topic is additional symmetry [3–8]. Additional symmetries are special symmetries <lb/>which are not contained in the KP hierarchy and do not commute with each other. The <lb/>additional symmetry flows of the KP hierarchy form an infinite dimensional algebra W  1+∞ <lb/> [5, 8]. More recently, there are several new results about partition function in the matrix <lb/>models and Seiberg-Witten theory associated with additional symmetries, string equation and <lb/>Virasoro constraints of the KP hierarchy [9–13]. In fact, there is a parallel research line on <lb/>additional symmetries of evolution equations and their Lie algebraic structures, particularly <lb/>for 1 + 1 dimensional integrable equations [14], and the corresponding symmetries are called τ <lb/> -symmetries and related Lax operators are constructed pretty systematically [15, 16]. <lb/>It is well known that we can get different sub-hierarchies of the KP by different reduction <lb/>conditions on Lax operator L. The first two important sub-hierarchies are CKP hierarchy [17] <lb/>through a restriction L <lb/>  *  = −L and BKP hierarchy [1] through a restriction L <lb/>  *  = −∂L∂ <lb/> −1  . So <lb/>the additional symmetries of the CKP (or BKP) hierarchy have been constructed [18–21] and <lb/>shown to be a new infinite dimensional algebra W <lb/> C <lb/> 1+∞  (or W <lb/> B <lb/> 1+∞  ), which is subalgebra of W  1+∞  . <lb/>The third sub-hierarchy is constrained KP (cKP) hierarchy [22–24], which is obtained by setting <lb/>a special form of Lax operator L = ∂ + <lb/>  m <lb/>i=1  Φ  i  ∂ <lb/> −i  Ψ  i  , where Φ  i  is the eigenfunction and Ψ  i  is <lb/>the adjoint eigenfunction of the cKP hierarchy. This is a relative new reduction condition and is <lb/>different from the reduction conditions of previous two sub-hierarchies. Hence it is very natural <lb/>to explore the additional symmetries of the cKP hierarchy. However, additional symmetry flows <lb/>of the KP hierarchy break the special form of the Lax operator for the cKP hierarchy, and so it <lb/></body>

			<front>  *  Corresponding author. email: hejingsong@nbu.edu.cn. <lb/></front>

			<page> 1 <lb/> 2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> KELEI TIAN †, JINGSONG HE <lb/>  *   ‡, JIPENG CHENG † AND YI CHENG  † <lb/></note>

			<body> is highly non-trivial to find a suitable form of additional symmetry flow for this sub-hierarchy. <lb/>To this end, it is well defined [25] by means of a crucial modification of the corresponding <lb/>additional symmetry flows of the KP hierarchy. Note that a new and complicated operator X  k <lb/> plays a very important role in this procedure. <lb/>Furthermore, the fourth sub-hierarchy and fifth sub-hierarchy are constrained CKP (cCKP) <lb/>[26] and constrained BKP (cBKP) hierarchy [27], which are obtained by putting the combination <lb/>of the previous mentioned reduction conditions, i.e., CKP and cKP conditions, BKP and cKP <lb/>conditions. Some results associated cCKP and cBKP hierarchies have already been reported, <lb/>for example, a Gramm-type τ -function [26] of the cCKP hierarchy and a Pfaffian-form τ -<lb/>function [27] of the cBKP are also constructed from the vacuum solution, the dimensional <lb/>reductions of the CKP and BKP hierarchies are presented in [28]. Moreover, determinant <lb/>representations of the τ function, which are generated by the the gauge transformations, of the <lb/>cCKP and cBKP hierarchies are obtained [29]. However, for our best knowledge, there is no <lb/>any results on the additional symmetries of the cBKP and cCKP hierarchies. So, we shall fill <lb/>the gap in this paper by constructing additional symmetries for the two new sub-hierarchies <lb/>and their actions on eigenfunctions and adjoint eigenfunctions. The basic idea is to revise the <lb/>additional symmetry flows of CKP and BKP hierarchies such that the new symmetry flows ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k <lb/> will preserve the form of Lax operator of the cKP hierarchy. This will be realized by introducing <lb/>two vital operators Y  k  in sequel. <lb/>The paper is organized as follows. We first recall some basic results of the KP hierarchy, <lb/>CKP hierarchy, BKP hierarchy and the constrained KP hierarchy in Section 2. The main <lb/>results are stated and proved in Sections 3 and 4, which are the additional symmetries and its <lb/>action on the eigenfunction and adjoint eigenfunction of the cCKP and cBKP hierarchies, and <lb/>we further show that acting on the space of the wave operator, ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  forms new centerless W <lb/> cC <lb/> 1+∞ <lb/> and W <lb/> cB <lb/> 1+∞  -subalgebra of centerless W  1+∞  respectively. Section 5 is devoted to conclusions and <lb/>discussions. <lb/>2. background on KP hierarchy <lb/> In this section we first give a brief introduction of KP hierarchy based on [1, 2]. Let the <lb/>pseudo-differential operator <lb/> L = ∂ + u  1  ∂ <lb/> −1  + u  2  ∂ <lb/> −2  + u  3  ∂ <lb/> −3  + · · · <lb/> (2.1) <lb/>be a Lax operator of the KP hierarchy, which is described by the associated Lax equations <lb/> ∂L <lb/>∂t  n <lb/> = [B  n  , L], n = 1, 2, 3, · · · , <lb/> (2.2) <lb/>where B  n  = (L <lb/> n  )  +  = <lb/> n <lb/> k=0 <lb/> a  k  ∂ <lb/> k  denotes the non-negative powers of ∂ in L <lb/> n  , ∂ = ∂/∂x, u  i  = <lb/> u  i  (x = t  1  , t  2  , t  3  , · · · ). The other notation L <lb/> n <lb/> −  = L <lb/> n  − L <lb/> n <lb/> +  will be used in the paper. The <lb/>Lax operator L in eq.(2.1) can be generated by dressing operator S = 1 + <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> k=1  s  k  ∂ <lb/> −k  in the <lb/>following way <lb/> L = S∂S <lb/> −1  . <lb/> (2.3) <lb/>The dressing operator S satisfies Sato equation <lb/> ∂S <lb/>∂t  n <lb/> = −(L <lb/> n  )  −  S, n = 1, 2, 3, · · · . <lb/> (2.4) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> ADDITIONAL SYMMETRIES OF CONSTRAINED CKP AND BKP HIERARCHIES <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body> The wave function w(t, z) of the KP hierarchy is defined by <lb/> w(t, z) = Se <lb/> ξ(t,z)  , <lb/> (2.5) <lb/>where ξ(t, z) = t  1  z + t  2  z <lb/> 2  + t  3  z <lb/> 3  + · · · + t  n  z <lb/> n  · · · . The wave function satisfies the equations <lb/> L <lb/> k  w(t, z) = z <lb/> k  w(t, z), <lb/>∂ <lb/>∂t  n <lb/> w = B  n  w, k ∈ Z, n ∈ N. <lb/> (2.6) <lb/>Moreover w(t, z) has a very simple expression by τ function of the KP hierarchy <lb/> w(t, z) = <lb/> τ (t  1  − <lb/> 1 <lb/> z <lb/> , t  2  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2z  2  , t  3  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>3z  3  , · · · ) <lb/> τ (t  1  , t  2  , t  3  , · · · ) <lb/> e <lb/> ξ(t,z)  . <lb/> (2.7) <lb/>Beside the existence of the Lax operator, wave function, τ function for the KP hierarchy, <lb/>another important property is the Zakharov-Shabat equation and associated linear equation. <lb/>In other words, KP hierarchy also has an alternative expression, i.e., <lb/> ∂B  m <lb/> ∂t  n <lb/> − <lb/> ∂B  n <lb/> ∂t  m <lb/> + [B  m  , B  n  ] = 0, <lb/> m, n = 1, 2, 3, · · · . <lb/> (2.8) <lb/>The eigenfunction Φ = Φ(t  1  , t  2  , t  3  , · · · ) and adjoint eigenfunction Ψ = Ψ(t  1  , t  2  , t  3  , · · · ) of KP <lb/>hierarchy associated to (2.8) are defined by <lb/> ∂Φ <lb/>∂t  n <lb/> = (B  n  Φ), <lb/> ∂Ψ <lb/>∂t  n <lb/> = −(B <lb/>  * <lb/> n  Ψ), <lb/>(2.9) <lb/>where the symbol  *  is the formal adjoint operation. For an arbitrary pseudo-differential operator <lb/> P = <lb/> i <lb/> p  i  ∂ <lb/> i  , P <lb/>  *  = <lb/> i <lb/> (−1) <lb/> i  ∂ <lb/> i  p  i  , and (AB) <lb/>  *  = B <lb/>  *  A <lb/>  *  for pseudo-differential operators A and B. <lb/> For example, ∂ <lb/>  *  = −∂, (∂ <lb/> −1  ) <lb/>  *  = −∂ <lb/> −1  . <lb/>To construct additional symmetries associated with the KP hierarchy, let us introduce Γ and <lb/>Orlov-Shulman&apos;s M operator as Γ = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> i=1 <lb/> it  i  ∂ <lb/> i−1  and M = SΓS <lb/> −1  . Dressing [∂  k  − ∂ <lb/> k  , Γ] = 0 gives <lb/>[∂  k  − B  k  , M] = 0, i.e. <lb/> ∂  k  M = [B  k  , M], <lb/> (2.10) <lb/>and then <lb/> ∂  k  (M <lb/> m  L <lb/> n  ) = [B  k  , M <lb/> m  L <lb/> n  ]. <lb/>(2.11) <lb/>Thus, the additional flows are defined by <lb/> ∂S <lb/>∂t  * <lb/> m,n <lb/> = −(M <lb/> m  L <lb/> n  )  −  S, <lb/> (2.12) <lb/>or equivalently <lb/> ∂L <lb/>∂t  * <lb/> m,n <lb/> = −[(M <lb/> m  L <lb/> n  )  −  , L]. <lb/> (2.13) <lb/>Here (M <lb/> m  L <lb/> n  )  −  serves as the generator of the additional flows along the new time variables t <lb/>  * <lb/> m,n  . <lb/>The additional flows ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> m,n  = <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  * <lb/> m,n <lb/> commute with the hierarchy, i.e. [∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> m,n  , ∂  k  ] = 0 but do not <lb/>commute with each other, they indeed determine symmetries. Therefore these flows ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> m,n  are <lb/>also called additional symmetry flows, and they forms a centerless W  1+∞  algebra [5, 8] acting <lb/>on the spaces of the Lax operator L and wave operator S. <lb/></body>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> KELEI TIAN †, JINGSONG HE <lb/>  *   ‡, JIPENG CHENG † AND YI CHENG  † <lb/></note>

			<body> The CKP hierarchy is a reduction of the KP hierarchy through the constraint on L given by <lb/>eq.(2.1) as <lb/> L <lb/>  *  = −L, <lb/> (2.14) <lb/>then L is called the Lax operator of the CKP hierarchy, and the associated Lax equation of the <lb/>CKP hierarchy is <lb/> ∂L <lb/>∂t  n <lb/> = [B  n  , L], n = 1, 3, 5, · · · . <lb/> (2.15) <lb/>which compresses all even flows, i.e. the Lax equation of the CKP hierarchy has only odd flows. <lb/>Additional symmetry flows [18] for the CKP hierarchy are defined as <lb/> ∂L <lb/>∂t <lb/>  * <lb/> m,l <lb/> = −[(A  m,l  )  −  , L], <lb/> (2.16) <lb/>where A  m,l  for the CKP hierarchy should satisfy <lb/> A <lb/>  * <lb/> m,l  = −A  m,l  , <lb/> (2.17) <lb/>we can assume A  m,l  be <lb/> A  m,l  = M <lb/> m  L <lb/> l  − (−1) <lb/> l  L <lb/> l  M <lb/> m  , <lb/> (2.18) <lb/>where <lb/> M = S( <lb/> ∞ <lb/> i=0 <lb/> (2i + 1)t  2i+1  ∂ <lb/> 2i  )S <lb/> −1  . <lb/> (2.19) <lb/>Acting on the space of the wave operator S, ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> m,l  of the CKP hierarchy forms a new centerless <lb/> W <lb/> C <lb/> 1+∞  -subalgebra of centerless W  1+∞  . <lb/>If Lax operator L given by eq.(2.1) satisfies <lb/> L <lb/>  *  = −∂L∂ <lb/> −1  , <lb/> (2.20) <lb/>then L is called the Lax operator of the BKP hierarchy, the Lax equation of the BKP hierarchy <lb/>also has only odd flows <lb/> ∂L <lb/>∂t  n <lb/> = [B  n  , L], n = 1, 3, 5, · · · . <lb/> (2.21) <lb/>Additional symmetry flows [19, 20] for the BKP hierarchy are given by <lb/> ∂L <lb/>∂t <lb/>  * <lb/> m,l <lb/> = −[(A  m,l  )  −  , L], <lb/> (2.22) <lb/>where A  m,l  for the BKP hierarchy should satisfy the constraint equation <lb/> A <lb/>  * <lb/> m,l  = −∂A  m,l  ∂ <lb/> −1  , <lb/> (2.23) <lb/>then A  m,l  for the BKP hierarchy could be chosen as <lb/> A  m,l  = M <lb/> m  L <lb/> l  − (−1) <lb/> l  L <lb/> l−1  M <lb/> m  L, <lb/> (2.24) <lb/>where <lb/> M = S( <lb/> ∞ <lb/> i=0 <lb/> (2i + 1)t  2i+1  ∂ <lb/> 2i  )S <lb/> −1  . <lb/> (2.25) <lb/>Acting on the space of the wave operator S, ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> m,l  of the BKP hierarchy forms another new <lb/>centerless W <lb/> B <lb/> 1+∞  -subalgebra of centerless W  1+∞  . <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> ADDITIONAL SYMMETRIES OF CONSTRAINED CKP AND BKP HIERARCHIES <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body> We now turn to the cKP hierarchy [22–24]. The Lax operator L of the constrained KP <lb/>hierarchy is given by <lb/> L = ∂ + <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> Φ  i  ∂ <lb/> −i  Ψ  i  , <lb/> (2.26) <lb/>where Φ  i  (Ψ  i  ) is the (adjoint) eigenfunctions of this hierarchy, and the corresponding Lax <lb/>equation is formulated as <lb/> ∂L <lb/>∂t  n <lb/> = [B  n  , L], n = 1, 2, 3, · · · . <lb/> (2.27) <lb/>In particular, we stress that eigenfunctions and adjoint eigenfunctions {Φ  i  , Ψ  i  } are important <lb/>dynamical variables in cKP hierarchy, so it is necessary to find the action of the correct ad-<lb/>ditional symmetry flows on them. Here the correct flow ∂  τ  means its action on L of the cKP <lb/>hierarchy should be the form of [25] <lb/>(∂  τ  L)  −  = <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ( ˜ <lb/> A∂ <lb/> −1  Ψ  i  + Φ  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  <lb/> ), <lb/> (2.28) <lb/>which will result in its action on (∂  τ  Φ  i  = ˜ <lb/> A) and (∂  τ  Ψ  i  = ˜ <lb/> B). However, in general, the <lb/>additional symmetry flows of the KP hierarchy acting on L of the cKP hierarchy are not the <lb/>form of eq.(2.28). In other words, these flows do not preserve the form of the Lax operator of <lb/>the cKP hierarchy, the fact shows additional symmetry of the KP hierarchy is not consistent <lb/>with cKP reduction condition automatically. Therefore, the additional symmetry flows have to <lb/>be revised according to the analysis above, and then the correct additional symmetry flows of <lb/>the cKP hierarchy are given by [25] <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  L = [−(ML <lb/> k  )  −  + X  k−1  , L], k = 0, 1, 2, 3, · · · , <lb/> (2.29) <lb/>where <lb/> X  k−1  = 0, k = 0, 1, 2 <lb/>and <lb/> X  k−1  = <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/>k−2 <lb/> j=0 <lb/> (j − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(k − 2))L <lb/> k−2−j  (Φ  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> j  (Ψ  i  ), k ≥ 3. <lb/>(2.30) <lb/>Furthermore [25], <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  Φ  i  = <lb/> k <lb/> 2 <lb/> L <lb/> k−1  (Φ  i  ) + X  k−1  (Φ  i  ) + (A  1,k  )  +  (Φ  i  ), <lb/>(2.31) <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  Ψ  i  = <lb/> k <lb/> 2 <lb/> L <lb/>  * (k−1)  (Ψ  i  ) − X <lb/>  * <lb/> k−1  (Ψ  i  ) − (A  1,k  ) <lb/>  * <lb/> +  (Ψ  i  ). <lb/>(2.32) <lb/>3. Additional symmetries of constrained CKP hierarchy <lb/> Let us consider the constrained CKP hierarchy, which is the C-type sub-hierarchy of cKP <lb/>hierarchy. The Lax operator L of the cCKP hierarchy [26] is given by <lb/> L = ∂ + <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (q  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  r  i  + r  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  q  i  ), <lb/>(3.1) <lb/>where q  i  and r  i  are eigenfunctions. The corresponding Lax equation of the cCKP hierarchy is <lb/>defined by <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 6 <lb/> KELEI TIAN †, JINGSONG HE <lb/>  *   ‡, JIPENG CHENG † AND YI CHENG  † <lb/></note>

			<body> ∂L <lb/> ∂t  n <lb/> = [B  n  , L], n = 1, 3, 5, · · · . <lb/> (3.2) <lb/>For k = 1, 3, 5, · · · , we first try to calculate the original additional symmetry flows of the <lb/>CKP hierarchy as <lb/> ∂L <lb/>∂t <lb/>  * <lb/> 1,k <lb/> = −[(A  1,k  )  −  , L], <lb/> (3.3) <lb/>where A  1,k  = ML <lb/> k  − (−1) <lb/> k  L <lb/> k  M. Thus <lb/>( <lb/> ∂L <lb/>∂t <lb/>  * <lb/> 1,k <lb/> )  −  = [(A  1,k  )  +  , L]  −  + 2(L <lb/> k  )  −  . <lb/> (3.4) <lb/>In order to get its action on q  i  and r  i  , we need the form of (L <lb/> k  )  −  . <lb/> Lemma 3.1. The Lax operator L of the constrained CKP hierarchy given by eq.(3.1) satisfies <lb/>the relation <lb/>(L <lb/> k  )  −  = <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/>k−1 <lb/> j=0 <lb/> (L <lb/> k−j−1  (q  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> j  (r  i  ) + L <lb/> k−j−1  (r  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> j  (q  i  )), k = 1, 3, 5, · · · <lb/> (3.5) <lb/>where <lb/> L(q  i  ) = L  +  (q  i  ) + <lb/> m <lb/> j=1 <lb/> (q  j  ∂ <lb/> −1 <lb/> x  (r  j  q  i  ) + r  j  ∂ <lb/> −1 <lb/> x  (q  j  q  i  )). <lb/>However, (L <lb/> k  )  −  is not in the form of <lb/>(∂  τ  L)  −  = <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ((∂  τ  q  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  r  i  + (∂  τ  r  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  q  i  + q  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  (∂  τ  r  i  ) + r  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  (∂  τ  q  i  )), <lb/>(3.6) <lb/>as we expected for a correct flows. Here correctness means we can get the actions on ∂  τ  q  i  and <lb/> ∂  τ  r  i  from eq.(3.6). This shows that eq.(3.4) can not imply its action on eigenfunctions ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> 1,k  q  i <lb/> and ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> 1,k  r  i  . <lb/>Therefore, in order to get correct additional flows of the cCKP hierarchy, we revise eq.(3.3) <lb/>and then define new flows by <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  L = [−(A  1,k  )  −  + Y  k  , L], k = 1, 3, 5, · · · , <lb/> (3.7) <lb/>where A  1,k  = ML <lb/> k  − (−1) <lb/> k  L <lb/> k  M and Y  k  is introduced such that the left hand side of eq.(3.7) <lb/>will be the form of eq.(3.6). Next, we shall prove new flows ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  are correct additional symmetry <lb/>flows of the cCKP hierarchy. First of all, Y  k  is discussed, which is crucial to our purpose. <lb/> Lemma 3.2. For the cCKP hierarchy, the CKP reduction condition infers a constraint on <lb/> Y  k  , <lb/> Y <lb/>  * <lb/> k  = −Y  k  , k = 1, 3, 5, · · · . <lb/> (3.8) <lb/>Proof. The action of the additional flows ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  on the adjoint Lax operator L <lb/>  *  of the constrained <lb/>CKP hierarchy can be obtained by two different ways. We first computet it by a formal adjoint <lb/>operation on both sides of eq. (3.7), i.e. <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  L <lb/>  *  = ([−(A  1,k  )  −  + Y  k  , L]) <lb/>  *  = [L <lb/>  *  , −(A  1,k  ) <lb/>  * <lb/>−  + Y <lb/>  * <lb/> k  ], k = 1, 3, 5, · · · . <lb/> (3.9) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> ADDITIONAL SYMMETRIES OF CONSTRAINED CKP AND BKP HIERARCHIES <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body> The another way is to do a derivative with respect to t <lb/>  * <lb/> k  on L <lb/>  *  and use CKP reduction condition <lb/> L <lb/>  *  = −L, then <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  L <lb/>  *  = −∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  L = −[−(A  1,k  )  −  + Y  k  , L] = [L <lb/>  *  , (A  1,k  )  −  − Y  k  ], k = 1, 3, 5, · · · . <lb/> (3.10) <lb/>Comparing eq.(3.9) and eq.(3.10), we have <lb/> Y <lb/>  * <lb/> k  = −Y  k  , k = 1, 3, 5, · · · , <lb/> with the help of A <lb/>  * <lb/> 1,k  = −A  1,k  . <lb/> Thus we set Y  k  as <lb/> Y  1  = 0, <lb/>(3.11) <lb/> Y  k  = <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/>k−2 <lb/> j=0 <lb/> (2j − (k − 2))(L <lb/> k−2−j  (q  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> j  (r  i  ) + L <lb/> k−2−j  (r  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> j  (q  i  )), k ≥ 3, (3.12) <lb/>and shall show Y  k  satisfy the constraint given by eq.(3.8) . <lb/> Lemma 3.3. <lb/> Y  k  = −Y <lb/>  * <lb/> k  . <lb/> (3.13) <lb/>Proof. Y <lb/>  * <lb/> 1  = Y  1  = 0 is obvious, for k = 3, 5, 7, · · · , we have <lb/> Y <lb/>  * <lb/> k  = <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/>k−2 <lb/> j=0 <lb/> (2j − (k − 2))(−(L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> j  (r  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  L <lb/> k−2−j  (q  i  ) − (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> j  (q  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  L <lb/> k−2−j  (r  i  )) <lb/>= <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/>k−2 <lb/> j=0 <lb/> (2j − (k − 2))(−(−1) <lb/> j  L <lb/> j  (r  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  (−1) <lb/> k−2−j  (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> k−2−j  (q  i  ) <lb/> − (−1) <lb/> j  L <lb/> j  (q  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  (−1) <lb/> k−2−j  (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> k−2−j  (r  i  )) <lb/>= <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/>k−2 <lb/> j=0 <lb/> (2j − (k − 2))(L <lb/> j  (r  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> k−2−j  (q  i  ) + L <lb/> j  (q  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> k−2−j  (r  i  )) <lb/>= − <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/>k−2 <lb/> l=0 <lb/> (2l − (k − 2))(L <lb/> k−2−l  (q  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> l  (r  i  ) + L <lb/> k−2−l  (r  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> l  (q  i  )) <lb/>= −Y  k <lb/> In the fourth step we let l = k − 2 − j. <lb/> Furthermore, in order to calculate [Y  k  , L] in the eq.(3.7), the following lemma is necessary. <lb/> Lemma 3.4. For the Lax operator L of the cCKP hierarchy in eq.(3.1) and a pseudo-different <lb/>operator X = <lb/>  l <lb/>k=1  M  k  ∂ <lb/> −1  N  k  , the equation <lb/>[X, L]  −  = <lb/> l <lb/> k=1 <lb/> (−L(M  k  )∂ <lb/> −1  N  k  + M  k  ∂ <lb/> −1  L <lb/>  *  (N  k  )) <lb/>+ <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (X(q  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  r  i  + X(r  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  q  i  − q  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  X <lb/>  *  (r  i  ) − r  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  X <lb/>  *  (q  i  )) <lb/>holds. <lb/></body>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> KELEI TIAN †, JINGSONG HE <lb/>  *   ‡, JIPENG CHENG † AND YI CHENG  † <lb/></note>

			<body> Based on the above lemma, we have <lb/>[Y  k  , L]  −  = −2(L <lb/> k  )  −  + k <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (L <lb/> k−1  (q  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  r  i  + L <lb/> k−1  (r  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  q  i  ) <lb/>+k <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (q  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  L <lb/>  * (k−1)  (r  i  ) + r  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  L <lb/>  * (k−1)  (q  i  )) <lb/>+ <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (Y  k  (q  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  r  i  + Y  k  (r  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  q  i  ) <lb/> − <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (q  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  Y <lb/>  * <lb/> k  (r  i  ) + r  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  Y <lb/>  * <lb/> k  (q  i  )). <lb/>(3.14) <lb/>We are now in a position to calculate the explicit form of the right hand side of the new <lb/>additional flow give by eq.(3.7). <lb/> Theorem 3.1. The additional flows acting on the eigenfunction q  i  and r  i  of the constrained <lb/>CKP hierarchy are <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  q  i  = kL <lb/> k−1  (q  i  ) + Y  k  (q  i  ) + (A  1,k  )  +  (q  i  ), k = 1, 3, 5, · · · <lb/> (3.15) <lb/>and <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  r  i  = kL <lb/> k−1  (r  i  ) + Y  k  (r  i  ) + (A  1,k  )  +  (r  i  ), k = 1, 3, 5, · · · . <lb/> (3.16) <lb/>Proof. From the revised definition of the additional symmetry flows in eq.(3.7) of the cCKP <lb/>hierarchy, by a short calculation, we have <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  L  −  = [−(A  1,k  )  −  + Y  k  , L]  −  = [(A  1,k  )  +  , L]  −  + 2(L <lb/> k  )  −  + [Y  k  , L]  −  . <lb/> Using eq.(3.14) and the technical identity [K, f ∂ <lb/> −1  g]  −  = K(f )∂ <lb/> −1  g − f ∂ <lb/> −1  K <lb/>  *  (g) (where f, g <lb/> are arbitrary functions and K is a purely differential operator), note that k = 1, 3, 5, · · · , it is <lb/>followed by <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  L  −  = <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ((kL <lb/> k−1  (q  i  ) + Y  k  (q  i  ) + (A  1,k  )  +  (q  i  ))∂ <lb/> −1  r  i <lb/> + (kL <lb/> k−1  (r  i  ) + Y  k  (r  i  ) + (A  1,k  )  +  (r  i  ))∂ <lb/> −1  q  i <lb/> + q  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  (k(L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> k−1  (r  i  ) − Y <lb/>  * <lb/> k  (r  i  ) − (A  1,k  ) <lb/>  * <lb/> +  (r  i  )) <lb/>+ r  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  (k(L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> k−1  (q  i  ) − Y <lb/>  * <lb/> k  (q  i  ) − (A  1,k  ) <lb/>  * <lb/> +  (q  i  )) <lb/>thus <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  q  i  = kL <lb/> k−1  (q  i  ) + Y  k  (q  i  ) + (A  1,k  )  +  (q  i  ) = k(L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> k−1  (q  i  ) − Y <lb/>  * <lb/> k  (q  i  ) − (A  1,k  ) <lb/>  * <lb/> +  (q  i  ), <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  r  i  is also obtained at the same time. <lb/> Corollary 3.1. The additional flows act on wave operator S of the constrained CKP hier-<lb/>archy as <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  S = (−(A  1,k  )  −  + Y  k  )S, k = 1, 3, 5, · · · . <lb/> (3.17) <lb/> Theorem 3.2. The additional flows ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  commute with the constrained CKP hierarchy flows <lb/> ∂  t  2n+1  = <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  2n+1 <lb/> , i.e. <lb/>[∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  , ∂  t  2n+1  ] = 0. <lb/>(3.18) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> ADDITIONAL SYMMETRIES OF CONSTRAINED CKP AND BKP HIERARCHIES <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body> Thus ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  (k = 1, 3, 5, · · · ) are indeed the additional symmetry flows of the cCKP hierarchy. <lb/>Proof. The proof starts with the definition <lb/>[∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  , ∂  t  2n+1  ]S = ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  (∂  t  2n+1  S) − ∂  t  2n+1  (∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  S), <lb/> and using the action of the additional flows, we get <lb/>[∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  , ∂  t  2n+1  ]S = −∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k <lb/> L <lb/> 2n+1 <lb/> − <lb/> S <lb/> + ∂  t  2n+1  (((A  1,k  )  −  − Y  k  )S) <lb/>= −(∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  L <lb/> 2n+1  )  −  S − (L <lb/> 2n+1  )  −  (∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  S) + ∂  t  2n+1  ((A  1,k  )  −  − Y  k  )S <lb/>+ ((A  1,k  )  −  − Y  k  )(∂  t  2n+1  S). <lb/> Taking eq.(3.17) of Corollary 1 into the above formula, it is not difficult to compute <lb/>[∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  , ∂  t  2n+1  ]S = [(A  1,k  )  −  − Y  k  , L <lb/> 2n+1  ]  −  S + (L <lb/> 2n+1  )  −  ((A  1,k  )  −  − Y  k  )S <lb/>+ [(L <lb/> 2n+1  )  +  , (A  1,k  )  −  − Y  k  ]  −  S − ((A  1,k  )  −  − Y  k  )(L <lb/> 2n+1  )  −  S <lb/> = [((A  1,k  )  −  − Y  k  ), L <lb/> 2n+1  ]  −  S − [(A  1,k  )  −  − Y  k  , L <lb/> 2n+1 <lb/>+ <lb/> ]  −  S + [L <lb/> 2n+1 <lb/> − <lb/> , (A  1,k  )  −  − Y  k  ]S <lb/>= [(A  1,k  )  −  − Y  k  , L <lb/> 2n+1 <lb/> − <lb/> ]  −  S + [L <lb/> 2n+1 <lb/> − <lb/> , (A  1,k  )  −  − Y  k  ]S = 0 <lb/>We have used the fact that [L <lb/> 2n+1 <lb/>+ <lb/> , (A  m,l  ) − Y  k  ]  −  = [L <lb/> 2n+1 <lb/>+ <lb/> , ((A  1,k  )  −  − Y  k  )]  −  in the second step <lb/>of the above derivation, since (Y  k  )  −  = Y  k  and [L <lb/> 2n+1 <lb/>+ <lb/> , (A  m,l  )  +  ]  −  = 0. The last equality holds by <lb/>virtue of (P  −  )  −  = P  −  for arbitrary pseduo-differential operator P . <lb/> Taking into account of Y <lb/>  * <lb/> k  = −Y  k  , k = 1, 3, 5, · · · , we can give the next theorem by a <lb/>straightforward and tedious calculation. <lb/> Theorem 3.3. Acting on the space of the wave operator S of the constrained CKP hierarchy, <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  forms a new centerless W <lb/> cC <lb/> 1+∞  -subalgebra of centerless W  1+∞  . <lb/>4. Additional symmetries of constrained BKP hierarchy <lb/> We now turn to the case of the constrained BKP hierarchy, this follows in a similar way <lb/>of the case of the constrained CKP hierarchy. The Lax operator L of the constrained BKP <lb/>hierarchy [27] is given by <lb/> L = ∂ + <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (q  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  r  i,x  − r  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  q  i,x  ), <lb/>(4.1) <lb/>where the q  i  and r  i  are eigenfunctions. The corresponding Lax equation of the constrained <lb/>BKP hierarchy is defined by <lb/> ∂L <lb/>∂t  n <lb/> = [B  n  , L], n = 1, 3, 5, · · · . <lb/> (4.2) <lb/>For k = 1, 3, 5, · · · , at first we calculate the original additional symmetry flows of the BKP <lb/>hierarchy as <lb/> ∂L <lb/>∂t <lb/>  * <lb/> 1,k <lb/> = −[(A  1,k  )  −  , L], <lb/> (4.3) <lb/>where A  1,k  = M <lb/> m  L <lb/> l  − (−1) <lb/> l  L <lb/> l−1  M <lb/> m  L. Thus <lb/>( <lb/> ∂L <lb/>∂t <lb/>  * <lb/> 1,k <lb/> )  −  = [(A  1,k  )  +  , L]  −  + 2(L <lb/> k  )  −  . <lb/> (4.4) <lb/></body>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> KELEI TIAN †, JINGSONG HE <lb/>  *   ‡, JIPENG CHENG † AND YI CHENG  † <lb/></note>

			<body> For the cBKP hierarchy, the action of one flow ∂  τ  on the eigenfunctions (∂  τ  q  i  ) and (∂  τ  r  i  ) may <lb/>be derived from its action on the L if <lb/>(∂  τ  L)  −  = <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ((∂  τ  q  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  r  i,x  − (∂  τ  r  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  q  i,x  + q  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  (∂  τ  r  i,x  ) − r  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  (∂  τ  q  i,x  )). <lb/>(4.5) <lb/>At the same time, (∂  τ  q  i,x  ) should be consistent with (∂  τ  q  i  ), (∂  τ  r  i,x  ) should be consistent with <lb/>(∂  τ  r  i  ). However, the following lemma shows that ∂  t  * <lb/> 1,k <lb/> is not the case due to the form of (L <lb/> k  )  −  . <lb/> Lemma 4.1. The Lax operator L of the constrained BKP hierarchy given by eq.(4.1) satisfies <lb/>the relation <lb/>(L <lb/> k  )  −  = <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/>k−1 <lb/> j=0 <lb/> (L <lb/> k−j−1  (q  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> j  (r  i,x  ) − L <lb/> k−j−1  (r  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> j  (q  i,x  )), k = 1, 3, 5, · · · (4.6) <lb/>where <lb/> L(q  i  ) = L  +  (q  i  ) + <lb/> m <lb/> j=1 <lb/> (q  j  ∂ <lb/> −1 <lb/> x  (r  j,x  q  i  ) − r  j  ∂ <lb/> −1 <lb/> x  (q  j,x  q  i  )). <lb/>According to the analysis above, we may revise the flows in eq.(4.3) to define a correct <lb/>additional symmetry flows of the cBKP hierarchy. Similar to the case of cCKP hierarchy, we <lb/>define a new additional flow <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  L = [−(A  1,k  )  −  + Y  k  , L], k = 1, 3, 5, · · · , <lb/> (4.7) <lb/>where A  1,k  = M <lb/> m  L <lb/> l  − (−1) <lb/> l  L <lb/> l−1  M <lb/> m  L is the generator of the additional symmetry of the BKP <lb/>hierarchy. We shall show in this section that ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  is a correct additional symmetry flow for the <lb/>cBKP hierarchy. First of all, by a similar discussion as the case of the cCKP hierarchy, we have <lb/>the following lemma. <lb/> Lemma 4.2. For the cBKP hierarchy, the BKP reduction condition infers a constraint on <lb/> Y  k  as <lb/> Y <lb/>  * <lb/> k  = −∂Y  k  ∂ <lb/> −1  , k = 1, 3, 5, · · · <lb/> (4.8) <lb/>Thus we can set <lb/> Y  1  = 0, <lb/>(4.9) <lb/> Y  k  = <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/>k−2 <lb/> j=0 <lb/> (2j − (k − 2))(L <lb/> k−2−j  (q  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> j  (r  i,x  ) − L <lb/> k−2−j  (r  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> j  (q  i,x  )), k ≥ 3. (4.10) <lb/>The following lemma shows that {Y  k  , k = 1, 3, 5, · · · } satisfy the property we need. <lb/> Lemma 4.3. <lb/> Y <lb/>  * <lb/> k  = −∂Y  k  ∂ <lb/> −1  . <lb/> (4.11) <lb/>Proof. Y <lb/>  * <lb/> 1  = Y  1  = 0 is trivial. For k = 3, 5, 7, · · · , we have <lb/> ∂Y  k  ∂ <lb/> −1  = <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/>k−2 <lb/> j=0 <lb/> (2j − (k − 2))(∂L <lb/> k−2−j  (q  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> j  (r  i,x  )∂ <lb/> −1  − ∂L <lb/> k−2−j  (r  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> j  (q  i,x  )∂ <lb/> −1  ) <lb/>= <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/>k−2 <lb/> j=0 <lb/> (2j − (k − 2))((−1) <lb/> k−2−j  (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> k−2−j  (q  i,x  )(−1) <lb/> j  (L <lb/> j  (r  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  − ∂ <lb/> −1  L <lb/> j  (r  i  )) <lb/> − (−1) <lb/> k−2−j  (−L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> k−2−j  (r  i,x  )(−1) <lb/> j  (L <lb/> j  (q  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  − ∂ <lb/> −1  L <lb/> j  (q  i  ))) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> ADDITIONAL SYMMETRIES OF CONSTRAINED CKP AND BKP HIERARCHIES <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body> = − <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/>k−2 <lb/> j=0 <lb/> (2j − (k − 2))((L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> k−2−j  (q  i,x  )L <lb/> j  (r  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  − (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> k−2−j  (q  i,x  )∂ <lb/> −1  L <lb/> j  (r  i  ) <lb/> − (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> k−2−j  (r  i,x  )L <lb/> j  (q  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  + (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> k−2−j  (r  i,x  )∂ <lb/> −1  L <lb/> j  (q  i  )) <lb/>= − <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/>k−2 <lb/> l=0 <lb/> (2l − (k − 2))(−(L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> l  (r  i,x  )∂ <lb/> −1  L <lb/> k−2−l  (q  i  ) + (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> l  (q  i,x  )∂ <lb/> −1  L <lb/> k−2−l  (r  i  )) <lb/> − <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/>k−2 <lb/> j=0 <lb/> (2j − (k − 2))(−1) <lb/> k−2−j  (∂L <lb/> k−2−j  (q  i  )L <lb/> j  (r  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  − ∂L <lb/> k−2−j  (r  i  )L <lb/> j  (q  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  ) <lb/>= −Y <lb/>  * <lb/> k <lb/> we have used the identity ∂ <lb/> −1  f  x  ∂ <lb/> −1  = f ∂ <lb/> −1  − ∂ <lb/> −1  f as f = (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> j  (r  i,x  ) and f = (L <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> j  (q  i,x  ) in <lb/>the derivation. <lb/> In order to get the explicit form of the right hand side of eq.(4.7), the following lemma is <lb/>necessary. <lb/> Lemma 4.4. For the Lax operator L of the cBKP hierarchy and X = <lb/>  l <lb/>k=1  M  k  ∂ <lb/> −1  N  k  , <lb/>[X, L]  −  = <lb/> l <lb/> k=1 <lb/> (−L(M  k  )∂ <lb/> −1  N  k  + M  k  ∂ <lb/> −1  L <lb/>  *  (N  k  )) <lb/>+ <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (X(q  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  r  i,x  − X(r  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  q  i,x  − q  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  X <lb/>  *  (r  i,x  ) + r  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  X <lb/>  *  (q  i,x  )) <lb/>holds. <lb/>Applying the above lemma we conclude that <lb/>[Y  k  , L]  −  = −2(L <lb/> k  )  −  + k <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (L <lb/> k−1  (q  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  r  i,x  − L <lb/> k−1  (r  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  q  i,x  ) <lb/>+k <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (q  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  L <lb/>  * (k−1)  (r  i,x  ) − r  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  L <lb/>  * (k−1)  (q  i,x  )) <lb/>+ <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (Y  k  (q  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  r  i,x  − Y  k  (r  i  )∂ <lb/> −1  q  i,x  ) <lb/> − <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (−q  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  Y <lb/>  * <lb/> k  (r  i,x  ) + r  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  Y <lb/>  * <lb/> k  (q  i,x  )). <lb/> Theorem 4.1. For the cBKP hierarchy, the additional flows defined by eq.(4.7) acting on <lb/>the eigenfunction q  i  and r  i  are <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  q  i  = kL <lb/> k−1  (q  i  ) + Y  k  (q  i  ) − (A  1,k  )  +  (q  i  ), <lb/>(4.12) <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  r  i  = kL <lb/> k−1  (r  i  ) + Y  k  (r  i  ) + (A  1,k  )  +  (r  i  ), <lb/>(4.13) <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  q  i,x  = −kL <lb/>  * (k−1)  (q  i,x  ) − Y <lb/>  * <lb/> k  (q  i,x  ) + (A  1,k  ) <lb/>  * <lb/> +  (q  i,x  ), <lb/>(4.14) <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  r  i,x  = −kL <lb/>  * (k−1)  (r  i,x  ) − Y <lb/>  * <lb/> k  (r  i,x  ) − (A  1,k  ) <lb/>  * <lb/> +  (r  i,x  ), k = 1, 3, 5, · · · . <lb/> (4.15) <lb/></body>

			<page> 12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> KELEI TIAN †, JINGSONG HE <lb/>  *   ‡, JIPENG CHENG † AND YI CHENG  † <lb/></note>

			<body> Proof. From the revised definition of the additional flows in eq.(4.7) of the cBKP hierarchy, by <lb/>a short calculation, we have <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  L  −  = [−(A  1,k  )  −  + Y  k  , L]  − <lb/> = [(A  1,k  )  +  , L]  −  + 2(L <lb/> k  )  −  + [Y  k  , L]  − <lb/> = <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (kL <lb/> k−1  (q  i  ) + Y  k  (q  i  ) − (A  1,k  )  +  (q  i  ))∂ <lb/> −1  r  i,x <lb/> − (kL <lb/> k−1  (r  i  ) + Y  k  (r  i  ) + (A  1,k  )  +  (r  i  ))∂ <lb/> −1  q  i,x <lb/> + q  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  (−kL <lb/>  * (k−1)  (r  i,x  ) − Y <lb/>  * <lb/> k  (r  i,x  ) − (A  1,k  ) <lb/>  * <lb/> +  (r  i,x  )) <lb/> − r  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  (−kL <lb/>  * (k−1)  (q  i,x  ) − Y <lb/>  * <lb/> k  (q  i,x  ) + (A  1,k  ) <lb/>  * <lb/> +  (q  i,x  )) <lb/>thus <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  q  i  = kL <lb/> k−1  (q  i  ) + Y  k  (q  i  ) − (A  1,k  )  +  (q  i  ), <lb/>the other three identities could be also obtained in the same way. <lb/> Remark 4.1. By a simple calculation, ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  q  i,x  and ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  r  i,x  are not essential and necessary, <lb/>because it can be obtained from ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  q  i  and ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  r  i  , respectively. <lb/> Corollary 4.1. The additional flows act on wave operator S of the constrained BKP hier-<lb/>archy as <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  S = (−(A  1,k  )  −  + Y  k  )S, k = 1, 3, 5, · · · . <lb/> (4.16) <lb/> Theorem 4.2. The additional flows ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  commute with constrained BKP hierarchy <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t  2n+1 <lb/> , <lb/>i.e. <lb/>[∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  , ∂  t  2n+1  ] = 0. <lb/>(4.17) <lb/>This theorem shows ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  (k = 1, 3, 5, · · · ) are indeed the additional symmetry flows of the cBKP <lb/>hierarchy. <lb/>Using the identity Y <lb/>  * <lb/> k  = −∂Y  k  ∂ <lb/> −1  , k = 1, 3, 5, · · · , we can present the next theorem omitting <lb/>the proof. <lb/> Theorem 4.3. Acting on the space of the wave operator S of the constrained BKP hierarchy, <lb/> ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  forms new centerless W <lb/> cB <lb/> 1+∞  -subalgebra of centerless W  1+∞  . <lb/>5. Conclusions and Discussions <lb/> To summarize, we have constructed the additional symmetries of the constrained CKP hi-<lb/>erarchy in eq.(3.7) and theorem 3.2. The additional flows action on the eigenfunction of the <lb/>cCKP hierarchy are given in theorem 3.1. Acting on the space of the wave operator S of the <lb/>cCKP hierarchy, ∂ <lb/>  * <lb/> k  forms a new centerless W <lb/> cC <lb/> 1+∞  -subalgebra of centerless W  1+∞  algebra in <lb/>theorem 3.3. Similarly, the conclusions for the constrained BKP hierarchy are obtained using <lb/>the analogous technique in the case of constrained CKP hierarchy. The main results of the <lb/>cBKP hierarchy are presented in eq.(4.7), theorem 4.1, 4.2 and 4.3. Our results show that the <lb/>cCKP and cBKP hierarchies have, indeed, some different properties for additional symmetry <lb/>comparing with the KP, BKP, CKP and constrained KP hierarchies. For example, the defini-<lb/>tions of additional symmetry flows for the cCKP and cBKP hierarchies are different from the <lb/>above hierarchies, the revised operators Y  k  of the cCKP and cBKP hierarchies are different <lb/>from the corresponding operator X  k  of the cKP hierarchy given in [25]. Moreover, we also <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> ADDITIONAL SYMMETRIES OF CONSTRAINED CKP AND BKP HIERARCHIES <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body> would like to point out that Y  k  of the cCKP and cBKP hierarchies are distinct. We can use the <lb/>similar technique without essential difficulty to construct additional symmetries of the case as <lb/> L <lb/> k  = B  k  + <lb/> q  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  r  i  + r  i  ∂ <lb/> −1  q  i  , k &gt; 1, the results will be given in the future. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation <lb/>of China (Grant No.10971109, 10971209), and the Program for New Century Excellent Talents <lb/>in University (Grant No.NCET-08-0515). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] Date E, Kashiwara M, Jimbo M, Miwa T. Nonlinear Integrable Systems-Classical and Quantum Theory. <lb/>Singapore: World Scientific, 1983, 39-119 <lb/>[2] Dickey L A. Soliton Equations and Hamiltonian Systems (2nd Edition). Singapore: World Scientific, 2003 <lb/>[3] Orlov A Yu, Schulman E I. Additional symmetries of integrable equations and conformal algebra reprensen-<lb/>taion, Lett Math Phys, 1986, 12: 171–179 <lb/>[4] Moerbke P Van. Integrable foundation of string theory, in Lectures on integrable systems, P.163-267. <lb/> Singapore: World Scientific, 1994 <lb/>[5] Adler M, Shiota T, Moerbeke P van. A Lax representation for the Vertex operator and the central extension. <lb/>Comm Math Phys, 1995, 171: 547–588 <lb/>[6] Adler M, Shiota T, Moerbke P Van. From the w  ∞  -algebra to its central extension: a τ -function approach, <lb/>Phys Lett A, 1994, 194: 33–43 <lb/>[7] Dickey L A. On additional symmetries of the KP hierarchy and Sato&apos;s Backlund transformation. Comm <lb/>Math Phys, 1995, 167: 227–233 <lb/>[8] Dickey L A. Additional symmetries of KP, Grassmannian, and the string equation. Mod Phys Lett A, 1993, <lb/>8: 1259–1272 <lb/>[9] Morozov A. Integrability and matrix models. Phys Usp, 1994, 37: 1–55 <lb/>[10] Mironov A. WDVV equations in Seiberg-Witten theory and associative algebras. Nuclear Phys B Proc <lb/>Suppl, 1998, 61A: 177–185 <lb/>[11] Alexandrov A, Mironov A, Morozov A. Solving Virasoro constraints in matrix models. Fortschr Phys, 2005, <lb/>53: 512–521 <lb/>[12] Mironov A, Morozov A. Virasoro constraints for Kontsevich-Hurwitz partition function. J High Ener Phys, <lb/>2009, 02: 024, 51pages <lb/>[13] Aratyn H, Gomes J F, Zimerman A H. Integrable hierarchy for multidimensional Toda equations and <lb/>topological-anti-topological fusion. J Geom Phys, 2003, 46: 21–47 <lb/>[14] Ma W X. K symmetries and τ symmetries of evolution equations and their Lie algebras. J Phys A: Math <lb/>Gen, 1990, 23: 2707–2716 <lb/>[15] Ma W X. K symmetries and τ symmetries of evolution equations and their Lie algebras. J Phys A: Math <lb/>Gen, 1992, 25: 5329–5343 <lb/>[16] Ma W X. Lax representations and Lax operator algebras of isospectral and nonisospectral hierarchies of <lb/>evolution equations. J Math Phys, 1992, 33: 2464–2476 <lb/>[17] Date E, Kashiwara M, Jimbo M, Miwa T. KP hierarchy of Orthogonal symplectic type–transformation <lb/>groups for soliton equations VI. J Phys Soc Japan, 1981, 50: 3813–3818 <lb/>[18] He J S, Tian K L, Foerster A, Ma W X. Additional symmetries and string equation of the CKP hierarchy. <lb/>Lett Math Phys, 2007, 81: 119–134 <lb/>[19] Takasaki K. Quasi-classical limit of BKP hierarchy and W-infity symmetries. Lett Math Phys, 1993, 28: <lb/>177–185 <lb/>[20] Tu M H. On the BKP hierarchy: Additional symmetries, Fay identity and Adler-Shiota-van Moerbeke <lb/>formula. Lett Math Phys, 2007 81: 91–105 <lb/>[21] Shen H F, Tu M H. On the string equation of the BKP hierarchy. Int J Mode Phys A, 2009, V24, 22: <lb/>4193–4208 <lb/>[22] Konopelchenko B G, Sidorenko J, Strampp W. (1 + 1)-dimensional integrable systems as symmetry con-<lb/>straints of (2 + 1)-dimensional systems. Phys Lett A, 1991, 157: 17–21 <lb/>[23] Cheng Y, Li Y S. The constraint of the Kadomtsev-Petviashvili equation and its special solutions. Phys <lb/>Lett A, 1991, 157: 22–26 <lb/>[24] Cheng Y. Constraints of the Kadomtsev-Petviashvili hierarchy. J Math Phys, 1992, 33: 3774–3782 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> KELEI TIAN †, JINGSONG HE <lb/>  *   ‡, JIPENG CHENG † AND YI CHENG  † <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> [25] Aratyn H, Nissimov E, Pacheva,S. Virasoro symmetry of constrained of constrained KP Hierarchies, Phys <lb/>Lett A, 1997, 228: 164–175 <lb/>[26] Loris I. On reduced CKP equations. Inverse Problems, 1999, 15: 1099–1109 <lb/>[27] Loris I. Symmetry reductions of the BKP hierarchy. J Math Phys, 1999, 40: 1420–1431 <lb/>[28] Loris I. Dimensional reductions of BKP and CKP hierarchies. J Phys A, 2001, 34: 3447–3459 <lb/>[29] He J S, Wu Z W, Cheng Y. Gauge transformations for the constrained CKP and BKP hierarchies. J Math <lb/>Phys, 2007, 48: 113519, 16pages </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
