<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="headnote"> Available; at: http://www.ictp.trieste. it/~pub_ off <lb/>IC/2000/182 <lb/></note>

			<front> United Nations Educational Scientific and Cultural Organization <lb/>and <lb/>International Atomic Energy Agency <lb/>THE ABDUS SALAM INTERNATIONAL CENTRE FOR THEORETICAL PHYSICS <lb/> AXINO PRODUCTION IN e+e&quot; AND 77 COLLISIONS <lb/> Hoang Ngoc Long <lb/> Institute of Physics, NCST, P.O. Box 429, Bo Ho, Hanoi 10000, Vietnam} <lb/>and <lb/>The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics, Trieste, Italy <lb/> and <lb/>Dang Van Soa <lb/> Department of Physics, Hanoi University of Mining and Geology, <lb/>Dong Ngac. Tu Liern. Hanoi, Vietnam <lb/> 1 <lb/> and <lb/>The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics, Trieste, Italy. <lb/> Abstract <lb/> Production of axinos and photinos in e <lb/> + e~ and 77 collisions is calculated and estimated. It <lb/>is shown that there is an upper limit of the cross section for the process e~e <lb/> + —&gt; orf dependent <lb/>only 011 the breaking scale. For the process 77 —»• «,a <lb/> c <lb/> , there is a special direction in which axinos <lb/>are mainly produced. Behaviour of cross section for this process is also analysed. Based 011 the <lb/>result a new constraint for FjN is derived: j^ &gt; 10 <lb/> 14 GeV. <lb/>MIRAMARE TRIESTE <lb/>December 2000 <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote"> 1 Permanent address. <lb/></note>

			<body> Axinos -supcrsymmctric partners of axions [1-3] arc predicted in low-energy supcrsym-<lb/>metry and the Peccei-Quimi (PQ) solution. The axino is an electrically and color neutral particle <lb/>with mass highly dependent of the models [4 6]. In a large class of supersymmetric axion mod-<lb/>els [5] the mass of axino is predicted in the region ma &lt; 0(1) keV, which is cosmologically <lb/>harmless [6] (if axinos are heavier than a few keV they have to decay fast enough not to upset <lb/>any standard prediction of big-bang cosmology). In these models the axino a is the lightest <lb/>supersymmetric particle (LSP), which is stable and may contribute to the present mass density <lb/>of the Universe, as dark matter. There are good reasons to suspect that most of the mass of the <lb/>Universe is in some exotic and hitherto unknown dark form (the dark matter and dark energy) <lb/>contribute about 80 =t 20% of the critical density [7]. Thus axinos are very strongly motivated. <lb/>The possible consequences of the presence of axino is a subject of this study. In this paper <lb/>we consider the processes in which the axinos are mainly produced in, namely in e <lb/> + e~ and in <lb/>77 collisions. In our opinion, the considered collision is one of the many promising processes <lb/>which can be studied in the exiting collider project CLIC designed at the CERN with operating <lb/>energy at a range of 3 TeV. <lb/>As usual, we star with a piece <lb/> {4&gt;w  Q w <lb/> a ) 00 + (4&gt;*w <lb/> &amp; w A ) ss , <lb/> (l) <lb/> where &lt;f&gt; = a + ia +  -\/2BCL  + 0 <lb/> 2 F,p. Here a denotes an axion. a a saxion, and a an axino. Then a <lb/>relevant Lagrangian of axino -photino -photon coupling is given [6,8] <lb/> aN -<lb/>Corn = ^ <lb/>[A 7 <lb/>M 7 <lb/> i/ (l -75)fiiV + h.c] , <lb/> (2) <lb/>where JV is a number of inoquivalcnt vacua [9] (for type I (KSVZ) models [2], JV = 1, while for <lb/>type II (DFSZ) models [3], N = 6) and F is the PQ breaking scale. Collider and astrophysics <lb/>constraints require roughly [10] <lb/> § &gt; 10 <lb/> 9 GeV. <lb/> (3) <lb/> The above couplings are valid at energy scales between the PQ symmetry breaking scale F and <lb/>the electroweak symmetry breaking scale. <lb/>From (2) we get an axino -photino -photon vertex as follows <lb/> 7 -\/w\/W <lb/> = ^ (^ -ft&quot;) (1 -75 <lb/>Figure 1: Axino -photino -photon vertex <lb/>With the help of this vertex, an axino can be produced in pair with an aiitiphotino (j <lb/> 0 ) <lb/> in the e <lb/> + e~ collision through ,s-chaimel photon exchange. A pair of axino -antiaxino (aa <lb/> c ) can <lb/>be produced in the 77 scattering via t-channel photino exchange. <lb/>Now let us first consider a process in which the initial state contains the clccton and the <lb/>positron and in the final state there are the axino and the aiitiphotino: <lb/> e~(pi) + e <lb/> + (p 2 ) -&gt;a(A;i)+7 <lb/> c (fe2), <lb/>(4) <lb/>in which the letters in parentheses stand for the momenta of the particles. This process proceeds <lb/>through the s-chaimel photon exchange. <lb/>Amplitude for this process is given by <lb/> where q = p-[ + p-\. <lb/> The straightforward calculation yields the following differential cross section (DCS) in the <lb/>ccnter-of-mass frame <lb/> dvmd <lb/> (mj, - ml)[E v -E 2 ) -s{E v E 2  + k <lb/> 2  cos <lb/> 2  6)  •  (6) <lb/> where 9 is the angle between p\ and k\, k = \ki\ = \k-2\-E,E\ and E2 are energy of the initial <lb/>electron and of the final axino and aiitiphotino, respectively. The value k can be expressed in <lb/>terms of the usual variable s = q <lb/> 2  as follows <lb/> ] <lb/> (7) <lb/> The momentum of outgoing particle vanishes at threshold <lb/> s c = (m^ + <lb/>ras) <lb/> 2 . <lb/>(8) <lb/>Therefore the considered process starts with the critical energy s c . <lb/> Figure 2: DCS for e e <lb/> +  —&gt; aY (the solid curve) and reduced e~e <lb/> +  -&gt; JJ, II <lb/> + in QED (the dashed <lb/>curve) as a function of cos 9 at y/s = 200 GeV <lb/> Photino mau = 100 QeV <lb/>Photino maws =200 QeV <lb/>Upper limit <lb/>300 <lb/>1000 <lb/> Figure 3: Cross section er(e e <lb/> + —&gt;• dj <lb/> c ) as a function of y/s. The solid curve refers to photino <lb/>mass equal to 100 GeV, the dashed curve -200 GeV. <lb/> For the sake of certainty, hereafter in our estimation, mass of the axino is assumed to be <lb/>0.5 GeV and £ = 10 <lb/> 10 GeV. In figure 2 we plot the DCS by cos# (the solid curve). To see <lb/>the difference, we also plot the reduced by 10 <lb/> 21 cross section for e~e <lb/> +  —&gt;• p,&quot;fj, <lb/> +  in the QED <lb/>framework (the dashed curve). As we can see from the figure, our curve is a downward parabola <lb/>(maximum at cos 9 = 0), while the QED value is an upward parabola (minimum at cos# = 0). <lb/>After integration over cos 0 the total cross section takes a form <lb/> k <lb/> &lt;r(e  e  e <lb/> + <lb/> (9) <lb/> It must be emphasized that if y/s tends to infinity the QED cross section tends to zero, while <lb/>from Eq. (9) we get an upper limit <lb/>lim a{e~e <lb/> +  -&gt; ~af) = <lb/> « 2.1 x 10&quot; <lb/> 6 bar for F/N = 10 <lb/> 10 GeV. <lb/>(10) <lb/>Behaviour of a(e~e <lb/> +  -^ a^ <lb/> c ) as a function of y/s is shown in figure 3. It should be noted <lb/>that when y/s tends to zero, the cross section tends to an upper limit but not zero as in the <lb/>QED. This upper limit is independent of both axino and photino masses. Taking into account of <lb/>negative searches and the present experimental limit (a <lb/> exp  = 5 x 10~ <lb/> 5  nb) based on the following <lb/> 0.1 0.2 0.3 &lt;M 0.S 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 <lb/>as 0.55 o.6 o.65 a.7 0.75 o.e a.85 0.3 0.95 1 <lb/> cos 9 <lb/> Figure 4: da(-y^ -» aa <lb/> c )/d cos 8 as a function of cos 9 at y/s = 100 GeV. The left figure refers <lb/> cos 9 €[0 + 0.93], the right figure for cos 9 £ [0 -^ lj. <lb/> data: luminosity ~ 10 <lb/> 31 (of LEP I), 5 events per year (1 year ~ 10 <lb/> 7  s). As we can see from <lb/>figure 3, in order to be consistent with present collider constraints the value ^ has to be bigger <lb/>than 10 <lb/> 14 GeV. With the CLIC luminosity designed to be 10 <lb/> 33 <lb/> , should the collidder experiment <lb/>show the negative result then F/N has to be bigger than 10 <lb/> 15 or so. <lb/>Now we turn to the second process <lb/>7(Pi) &quot; <lb/>Process (11) is mediated by a virtual photino in the ^-channel. <lb/>Amplitude for the process is given <lb/> 2 <lb/>i <lb/> (11) <lb/>(12) <lb/>where I = k\ - pi, and the transversality between momentum and polarization of the photons <lb/>is used. <lb/>The computation is long but straightforward and gives DCS in center-of-mass frame <lb/> 2 <lb/> (13) <lb/>cfcr(77 —&gt;• aa <lb/> c ) _ <lb/>a <lb/> 4 iV <lb/> 4 <lb/> rlrr\&lt;if) <lb/> ^1 9TT <lb/> 5  J?4 (12 _ 17)2^2 <lb/> \Jb \s\JCs \f <lb/>ij i_ £J f\ <lb/>J-<lb/>IV <lb/>ft V£. f <lb/> where t = |Aj | = |^| = (f — <lb/> rn \) <lb/> 1 ^ <lb/> m an absolute strength of momentum of the outgoing axino <lb/> r\f-\f\ 1 •&quot; — m&quot; I . /of•/• ^rto H <lb/>J£— ] <lb/> It is easy to see that the DCS (13) has a single pole at <lb/>(14) <lb/> s <lb/> From (14) it follows that if y^ tends to infinity the scattering angle 9 p  tends to zero. <lb/>In figure 4 we plot the DCS ^J^f <lb/> 1 <lb/> as a function of cos 9 at a value yfs = 100 GeV. The <lb/>solid curve corresponds to photino mass equal 100 GeV. As we can see from the figure, axinos <lb/>are produced mainly at the direction determined by (14), for example 8 ~ 0 for s &gt; m|, m\. <lb/> PlwUno man -100 GeV <lb/>Phoano mass = 120GeV -<lb/> Figure 5: Cross section (7(77 ~&gt; aa <lb/> c ) as a function of y/s (the left figure for y/s € [IGeV 4 <lb/>lOGeV], the right figure for y/s € [lOOGeV 4 400GeF]. The solid curve refers to photino mass <lb/>equal to 100 GeV, the dashed curve -120 GeV. <lb/> After taking intergation over cos 0, the total cross section looks as follows <lb/> + ym| -9(m? - m\f <lb/> 2 -m|) <lb/> 2 +4(m?-m|) <lb/> 3 ] <lb/> (15) <lb/>In figure 5 we plot (7(77 —v aa <lb/> c ) as a function of y/s at two values of the photino masses: <lb/>the solid curve refers to m^ — 100 GeV and the dashed curve -120 GeV. As we can see from the <lb/>left figure, the curves get peak at low energy region (around 2 GeV) go through the minimum <lb/>value, after that smoothly increase (see the right figure). <lb/>Due to smallness of the coupling constant it seems that the tree-graph expressions are <lb/>sufficient and appropriate. It is difficult to imagine practical laboratory experiments, however <lb/>the considered 77 collision may play an important role in cosmology. <lb/>In summary, we have calculated the testable production of the axino and the antiphotino <lb/>at high energy e <lb/> + e~ colliders. We have seen that when y/s tends to infinity the total cross <lb/>section has the upper bound dependent only on the value F/N. We have got the new limit <lb/>^ &gt; 10 <lb/> 14 GeV, which is higher than the present estimation. In principle the considered process <lb/>should be seen at the CLIC unless F/N &gt; 10 <lb/> 15 GeV. We have also considered 77 —&gt; aa <lb/> c  which <lb/>has an important role in cosmology. The total cross section for this process has maximum and <lb/>minimum at low energy after that increases monotonously. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> A c kn ow lodgments <lb/> The authors are grateful to Prof. A. Pukhov for information on the present experimental <lb/>data. They also thank the AS-ICTP for financial support and hospitality extended to them. One <lb/>of them (D. V. S.) thanks the INFN for financial help. He would like to thank Prof. A. Masicro <lb/>for very helpful discussions and warm hospitality at the SISSA. This work was supported in part <lb/>by the Natural Science Council of Vietnam. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] S. Weinberg, Phys. Rev. Lett. 40, 223 (1978): F. Wilczek, ibid, 40. 279 (1978). <lb/>[2] J. E. Kim, Phys. Rev. Lett., 43, 103 (1979); M. A. Shifman, V. I. Vainshtcin, and V. I. <lb/>Zakharov, Nucl. Phys. B166, 4933 (1980). <lb/>[3] M. Dine. W. Fischler, and M. Sredniki. Phys. Lett. B104, 199 (1981); A. P. Zhitnitskii, <lb/>Sov. J. Nucl. Phys. 31, 2(50 (1980). <lb/>[4] K. Tamvakis and D. Wyler, Phys. Lett. B112, 451 (1982): J. F. Nicvcs, Phys. Rev. D33, <lb/> 1762 (1986). <lb/>[5] J. E. Kim, Phys. Lett. B136, 378 (1984); P. Moxhay and K. Yamamoto. ibid. B151, 363 <lb/>(1985); T. Goto and M. Yamaguchi. ibid. B276, 103 (1992); E. J. Chun. J. E. Kim, and H. <lb/>P. Nilles, ibid. B287, 123 (1992); E. J. Chun and A. Lukas. ibid. B357, 43 (1995). <lb/>[6] K. Rajagopal, M. S. Turner, and F. Wilczek, Nucl. Phys. 358 :  447 (1991). <lb/>[7] M. S. Turner, Phys. Rep. 333 -334. 619 (2000); Invited talk given at, 4th Rencontres du <lb/>Vietnam, Hanoi July 19 24, 2000. <lb/>[8] J. E. Kim, A. Masiero, and D. V. Nanopoulos, Phys. Lett. B 139, 346 (1984); K. Choi, E. <lb/>J. Chun, and J. S. Lee, Phys. Rev. D55, R3924 (1997). <lb/>[9] P. Sikivie, Phys. Rev. Lett. 48, 1156 (1984). <lb/>[10] G. Raffelt, Nucl. Phys. B (Proc. Suppl.) 77, 456 (1999). </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
