<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> About Time <lb/> Vishnu Jejjala <lb/> 1 *  , Michael Kavic <lb/> 2 †  , Djordje Minic <lb/> 2 ‡  , Chia-Hsiung Tze <lb/> 2 § <lb/>1  Institut des Hautes Études Scientifiques <lb/>35, Route de Chartres <lb/>91440 Bures-sur-Yvette, France <lb/> 2  Institute for Particle, Nuclear, and Astronomical Sciences <lb/>Department of Physics, Virginia Tech <lb/>Blacksburg, VA 24061, U.S.A. <lb/> Abstract <lb/> We present a novel perspective on the problem of time in quantum gravity. Inspired <lb/>by Einstein&apos;s analysis of the concept of time and the equivalence principle and guided <lb/>by the geometric structure of quantum theory, we offer new insights into the nature <lb/>and the origin of time  ¶  . <lb/>  *  vishnu@ihes.fr <lb/>  †  kavic@vt.edu <lb/>  ‡  dminic@vt.edu <lb/>  §  kahong@vt.edu <lb/>  ¶  Essay submitted to the FQXi Inaugural Essay Contest on the Nature of Time. <lb/></front>

			<page>– 1 – <lb/></page>

			<body> I. Of spacetime and the river <lb/> The quest for a theory of quantum gravity is fundamentally an attempt to reconcile two <lb/>disparate notions of time. Einstein&apos;s theory of general relativity teaches us that time is <lb/>ultimately an illusion while quantum theory tells us that time evolution is an essential part <lb/>of Nature. Moreover, the failure to resolve the conflict between these competing notions is <lb/>at the heart of our inability to properly describe the earliest moment of our Universe, the <lb/>Big Bang. We will spell out in clear terms the nature of the discrepancy between these <lb/>competing views and lay out a new proposal for a theory of quantum gravity that provides <lb/>a clear resolution of the problem of time. <lb/>Time in quantum mechanics and time in gravity are very different things. In quantum <lb/>mechanics, time is the fundamental evolution parameter of the underlying unitary group. <lb/>The Hamiltonian operator of a given system generates translations of the initial state in <lb/>time. Unlike other conjugate quantities in the theory such as momentum and position, the <lb/>relation between time and energy, which is the observable associated to the Hamiltonian, <lb/>is distinguished. Time is not an observable in quantum theory in the sense that there <lb/>is no associated &quot; clock &quot; operator. In the Schrödinger equation time simply enters as a <lb/>parameter. This conception of time as a Newtonian construct that is global or absolute in <lb/>a post-Newtonian theory persists even when we promote quantum mechanics to relativistic <lb/>quantum field theory. An illustration is the microcausality condition requiring two field <lb/>operators to commute, namely, to have no effect on each other whenever their locations <lb/>cannot be connected by a light signal. <lb/>To grasp the notion of time in gravity, we first recall that measurements are also, by their <lb/>nature, different in quantum field theory and the general theory of relativity [1]. The special <lb/>theory of relativity and quantum mechanics, as well as their conflation, are formulated in <lb/>terms of particle trajectories, wavefunctions, or fields that are functions (functionals) of <lb/>positions or momenta. Coordinates, however, must be regarded as auxiliary constructs in <lb/>the general theory of relativity. In classical gravity, spacetime is simply an arena in which <lb/>events transpire. The coordinates — including time — that are assigned as labels to the <lb/>events are not in themselves especially meaningful due to the general covariance of Einstein&apos;s <lb/>theory of gravitation. To better understand the role time plays in general relativity we can <lb/>consider as an analogy wrapping a birthday present. There are many kinds of paper with <lb/>which to wrap a present just as there are many kinds of coordinates with which to label <lb/>events. As one of these coordinates, time is no more fundamental to the events than the <lb/>wrapping paper is to the present. However, as we have noted above, quantum theory is <lb/>ill-defined without time. If we attempt to discard it like so much used wrapping paper, we <lb/>lose the essence of the theory and our present is destroyed in the process. <lb/>Although general relativity is formulated as a local classical field theory, it has distinguish-<lb/>ing non-local features, as exemplified, for instance by the concept of gravitational energy [2]. <lb/>No local gauge invariant observables can exist within a theory of gravitation [3]. Rather, <lb/></body>

			<page>– 2 – <lb/></page>

			<body> the most natural observables are couched in terms of integrals over all of spacetime. Such <lb/>observables are manifestly diffeomorphism invariant, but the failure of locality is intrinsic to <lb/>their definition. The decoupling of scales familiar to local quantum field theories is simply <lb/>not tenable in gravity. A chief lesson then is that high energy physics mixes inextricably <lb/>with dynamics at low energies. <lb/>Measurements in a classical theory of gravitation are founded on the relational properties <lb/>among spacetime events. Timelike separation of events is measured by mechanical clocks, <lb/>whereas spacelike separation is determined more indirectly [4]. We might thus prescribe a <lb/>clock in Greenwich as a standard reference object and consider other events in spacetime <lb/>relative to it. Then, for example, the curvature invariant at an event specified relative to <lb/>the ticking of the clock in Greenwich is a quasilocal observable in the theory [5]. <lb/>By contrast within a quantum theory, events cannot themselves be localized to arbitrary <lb/>precision. Only for high energies does it even make sense to speak of a local region in <lb/>spacetime where an interaction takes place. This indeterminacy simply follows from the <lb/>energy-time uncertainty relation. However, the measurements that an observer makes within <lb/>a quantum theory of gravity are necessarily constrained. Experiments are performed in finite <lb/>duration and at finite distance scales. The interactions accessed in the laboratory also take <lb/>place in regions of low spacetime curvature. In local quantum field theory, we operate <lb/>successfully under the conceit that the light cone is rigid. With respect to the vacuum in flat <lb/>space, there is an approximate notion of a scattering amplitude, which is the unitary matrix <lb/>relating asymptotic initial and final states for an interaction of particles. Even in string <lb/>theory, computing such amplitudes proceeds through analytic continuation of Lorentzian <lb/>spacetimes into Euclidean spaces with fixed asymptotic conditions. On cosmological scales, <lb/>this procedure is of course a cheat. Light cones do tilt, and the causal structure is not static. <lb/>In general settings, no choice of coordinates will ensure the existence of a global timelike <lb/>direction throughout all of spacetime. Even if such a coordinate system were to exist, as <lb/>local observers we do not a priori know what the asymptotic behavior of the metric will be <lb/>at late times. The only data available about spacetime are events in the observer&apos;s past light <lb/>cone. Each observer has a different past light cone consistent with the histories of all the <lb/>other observers, and the future causal structure is partially inferred from these data. <lb/>In a quantum theory of gravity, the spacetime metric is expected to fluctuate. In con-<lb/>sequence, notions such as whether two events are spacelike separated become increasingly <lb/>blurred as fluctuations amplify. Indeed, Lorentzian metrics exist for almost all pairs of points <lb/>on a spacetime manifold such that the metric distance is not spacelike [6]. Clearly the no-<lb/>tion of time, even locally, becomes problematic in such quantum gravitational regimes. The <lb/>failure of microcausality means that the intuitions and techniques of quantum field theory <lb/>must be dramatically revised in any putative theory of quantum gravity. <lb/>Given the overwhelming success of local quantum field theory as the bedrock for our un-<lb/>derstanding of Nature in all its (albeit non-gravitational) quantum interactions, it is tempting <lb/>to retain its underlying precepts as we refine and deepen our analysis. But there is an in-<lb/></body>

			<page>– 3 – <lb/></page>

			<body> escapable puzzle here as well. Observational evidence points to a hot Big Bang event some <lb/>13.72 ± 0.12 billion years in the past [7]. While a precise model for the Big Bang in quan-<lb/>tum gravity is presently lacking, the Penrose–Hawking theorems point to the existence of an <lb/>initial singularity [8]. Under conservative assumptions, there exist geodesics that are only <lb/>finitely extendible into the past. The curvature of spacetime blows up at the singularity, <lb/>which is the terminus of the geodesics, and general relativity cannot reliably say anything <lb/>useful about physics anymore since the very notion of geometry breaks down. The origin of <lb/>the Universe also raises conceptual questions within the quantum theory itself. In particular, <lb/>if we uphold the canonical definition of unitary evolution with a globally defined evolution <lb/>parameter, what happens to that evolution as we approach the singularity? According to <lb/>quantum theory, this evolution is not supposed to terminate, and yet, both physical intuition <lb/>and general relativity tell us, it seemingly does end. <lb/>From the above, we see that the standard conceptions of time in quantum theory and in <lb/>classical general relativity are in extreme tension: time in the quantum theory is an absolute <lb/>evolution parameter along the real line whereas in general relativity there can be no such one <lb/>parameter evolution. What, then, is the nature and the origin of time in quantum gravity? <lb/> II. Time is but the stream I go a-fishing in <lb/> Developing a theory of quantum gravity which resolves the problem of time is a monumental <lb/>undertaking. One of the principal obstacles to overcome derives from the fact that the role of <lb/>time is intimately tied to the underlying structure of quantum theory, a foundation which, as <lb/>we shall describe, is rigidly fixed. We will propose a specific way of loosening this structure <lb/>ever so slightly and discover that following this prescription yields surprisingly profound <lb/>implications for quantum gravity and the problem of time. <lb/>In reconciling the identity of time in gravitation and canonical quantum mechanics, one <lb/>is immediately struck by the marked difference in the most commonly used formulations of <lb/>the two theories. General relativity is typically articulated in a geometric language while <lb/>quantum mechanics is most commonly thought of in terms of an operatorial, complex Hilbert <lb/>space formalism. Yet when quantum theory is examined in its less familiar geometric form, it <lb/>mimics general relativity in several essential aspects. In fact, these parallels provide a natural <lb/>way to graft gravity into the theory at the root quantum level. The geometric formulation <lb/>as well illuminates the nature and rigidity of time in quantum theory and points the way to <lb/>making time more elastic. As a prelude to such a generalization, we first sum up the key <lb/>features of geometric quantum mechanics. <lb/>In casting quantum mechanics within a geometric framework all the standard features of <lb/>the theory are present and acquire a geometric interpretation [9]. To begin, each physical <lb/>configuration of the system, its wavefunction, corresponds to a point in the quantum me-<lb/>chanical phase space. Typically, the phase space is parameterized in terms of coordinates <lb/></body>

			<page>– 4 – <lb/></page>

			<body> which are positions and momenta. Here these are, respectively, the real and imaginary parts <lb/>of the Fourier components of the wavefunction in some orthonormal basis. A phase space <lb/>has a natural symplectic structure ω which allows for the definition of a Poisson bracket or <lb/>commutator and hence provides an arena for Hamiltonian dynamics. Specifically, the phase <lb/>space of the canonical quantum mechanics is the complex projective space CP <lb/> n  , visualizable <lb/>as the set of complex lines through the origin in the Hilbert space, a complex Euclidean <lb/>space. The n denotes the dimension of the projective Hilbert space of the quantum theory; <lb/>it is typically infinite. The manifold CP <lb/> n  is highly symmetric; it is a compact, homoge-<lb/>neous, isotropic, and simply connected Einstein space with a constant holomorphic sectional <lb/>curvature equal to 2/. In the simplest case n = 1, CP <lb/> 1  is S <lb/> 2  , the round sphere in three <lb/>dimensions and is the state space of a two level quantum system or that of the qubit of <lb/>quantum computation. <lb/>It is important to observe that to have a theory of a quantum mechanical system, a key <lb/>ingredient is still missing: dynamics. Like classical mechanics, quantum mechanics is not so <lb/>much a theory as it is a general framework for it does not provide a specific Hamiltonian <lb/>but asks for one. With a given Hamiltonian, a physical system is thus defined along with its <lb/>associated variables, observables, etc. As each quantum state |ψ corresponds to a point in <lb/>phase space, the metrical distance between two nearby states is determined by the overlap <lb/>of the corresponding wavefunctions: g(|ψ, |ψ <lb/>  ) ∝ (1 − ||ψ|ψ <lb/>  | <lb/> 2  ). The metric g on CP <lb/> n  is <lb/>in fact the unique Fubini–Study metric, or the Fisher distance from information theory and <lb/>statistical geometry [10], and captures the Born rule for probabilities. In the classical limit, <lb/>for a point particle, this metric on the space of quantum states reduces to the spatial metric <lb/>in spacetime when the configuration space of the quantum system under consideration is <lb/>the physical space itself. Similarly, the corresponding symplectic form becomes the classical <lb/>Poisson bracket between the spatial position and momentum of the particle. This reduction <lb/>shows the path to the emergence of physical space from quantum mechanical degrees of <lb/>freedom, a property which will used subsequently. <lb/>The symplectic structure of phase space determines how wavefunctions, or more generally, <lb/>fields propagate. On CP <lb/> n  , this time evolution or the Schrödinger equation turns into a <lb/>geodesic equation with respect to the Fubini–Study metric for a point particle carrying a <lb/>non-Abelian charge, a disguised form of the Hamiltonian. The manifold CP <lb/> n  is curved, and <lb/>the dynamics are non-linear. The curvature of the space concerns the propagation of the <lb/>wavefunction. Thus, CP <lb/> n  tells the matter particle how to move but, unlike general relativity, <lb/>matter has yet to tell the state space how to curve. Realizing this backreaction on the phase <lb/>space will be the key feature of our model of quantum gravity. <lb/>In contrast to the classical phase space endowed only with a symplectic structure, the <lb/>quantum state space is threefold richer in structure. On the complex projective space <lb/>there are the metric g, the symplectic structure ω, and the almost complex structure J. <lb/> This final element is the mysterious i = <lb/> √ <lb/>−1 that appears in the Schrödinger equation, <lb/> J <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> |ψ(t) = H |ψ(t). These are the three pillars upon which geometric quantum mechan-<lb/></body>

			<page>– 5 – <lb/></page>

			<body> ics is constructed, and any pair of these will determine the third. Within this architecture, <lb/>the superposition principle is tied to viewing CP <lb/> n  as a collection of complex lines passing <lb/>through the origin. Entanglement arises from the embedding of the products of two complex <lb/>projective spaces into a higher dimensional one. The symplectic structure yields the geomet-<lb/>ric phase of the wavefunction. The speed with which the system moves through phase space <lb/>is related to the uncertainty in the energy, ∆E. Specifically, we can derive the Aharonov– <lb/>Anandan relation <lb/> 2 <lb/> ds = ∆E dt, which correlates the statistical distance in phase space as <lb/>given by the Fubini–Study metric to time in the canonical evolution [9]. This equation is <lb/>very telling in several respects. It says that time is statistical and quantum mechanical in <lb/>nature. It defines a quantum clock. It indicates that distance in quantum phase space is <lb/>linked in an exact fashion to time evolution. What the line element ds on CP <lb/> n  measures <lb/>is the optimal distinguishability of nearby pure states: if the states are hard to resolve ex-<lb/>perimentally, then they are close to each other in phase space [10]. (As we shall see, this <lb/>observation will be central to an understanding of the Big Bang.) Most importantly, recall <lb/>that the phase space geometry is fixed by the structure of quantum mechanics, and while the <lb/>space is curved, it is constrained to be a constant curvature manifold at every point. The <lb/>rigidity of the geometry, namely, the uniqueness and hence universality of the Fubini–Study <lb/>metric, enforces the constraint that time in quantum mechanics is a global coordinate that is <lb/>absolute. This is very much akin to the view of time in special relativity, whereas in general <lb/>relativity the metric is dynamical and time is local. It is this crucial difference that is at the <lb/>core of the tension between time in quantum theory and time in a gravitational context. <lb/>In light of the above discussion, we wish to develop a notion of time in quantum theory <lb/>that is manifestly local and which allows for a quantum phase space with a dynamical <lb/>metric. However, this is quite a challenge given the rigidity of quantum theory. To attack <lb/>this obstacle, let us return to the triadic nature of quantum mechanics: the metric, the <lb/>symplectic, and the complex structures. If quantum theory were a photographic tripod, <lb/>the triadic structure would be its three legs. Without all three, the theory cannot stand. <lb/>Once we have properly placed any two of the legs, the position and existence of the third <lb/>is implied. The structure of the tripod is rigid in the sense that if we move one of the legs <lb/>too far from its position, the system will collapse. Moreover, adjusting any one of the legs <lb/>will necessarily require adjustment of the other two in order to keep the tripod upright. The <lb/>equilibrium is a delicate balance. <lb/>Motivated by physical intuition, we must proceed to gently shift one of the three defining <lb/>structures such that we change the postulates of quantum mechanics in a minimal way. The <lb/>questions we must answer are: which leg to move first, how do we move it, and what the <lb/>effect will be on the other two legs. For the first question, we recall that we wish to tinker <lb/>with time in quantum theory and the leg most closely tied to time is the complex structure, <lb/>due to the role played by i in time evolution. Thus we propose changing this structure <lb/>from being globally complex to only locally complex or equivalently globally strictly almost <lb/>complex. This mathematically precise relaxation of the original rigidity will have remarkable <lb/></body>

			<page>– 6 – <lb/></page>

			<body> consequences. It allows for an extension of the governing symmetry of quantum theory while <lb/>ensuring that the symplectic and metric structures remain compatible with this change. Thus <lb/>we may extend the unitary group to the general covariance group, the symmetry group of <lb/>general relativity! We must bear in mind, however, that we are working not in spacetime but <lb/>on the space of states, the true arena of quantum dynamics. Thus the quantum phase space <lb/> CP <lb/> n  gives way to a newcomer in physics, the infinite dimensional non-linear Grassmannian <lb/>Gr(C <lb/> n+1  ) = Diff(C <lb/> n+1  )/Diff(C <lb/> n+1  , C <lb/> n  × {0}), in the n → ∞ limit [11, 12]. On the latter <lb/>space, which admits scores of metrics, the symplectic structure, the metric structure, and <lb/>hence also the almost complex structure become dynamical, and the global time of quantum <lb/>theory relaxes to be a more provincial, local time. Most importantly, the essential elements <lb/>of quantum theory are left intact, and our adjusted tripod is kept stable. <lb/>The requirement of general coordinate invariance places stringent constraints on the <lb/>quantum geometry. We must have a strictly (i.e., a non-integrable) almost complex structure <lb/>on a necessarily infinite dimensional generalized space of quantum events. It follows that <lb/>wavefunctions that label the event space, while already unobservable, are in fact irrelevant. <lb/>They are as meaningless as spacetime coordinates in general relativity; the physics remains <lb/>the same with a different choice of labels. Only individual quantum events make sense <lb/>observationally, and at the basic level, there are only dynamical correlations between these <lb/>quantum events. Observables are furnished by general coordinate invariant quantities in the <lb/>quantum phase space. A ready example is the distance, ds. <lb/>To be a bit more explicit, the equations for our model are formally the same as Einstein&apos;s <lb/>equations for spacetime geometry with gauge fields and matter present. However, the arena <lb/>of dynamics is not spacetime but the quantum phase space. As in the case of general <lb/>relativity, the non-linear geodesic Schrödinger equation is implied by the conservation of <lb/>energy-momentum. At last, we have the bootstrapping of matter and state space dynamics; <lb/>as Weyl and Wheeler would have put it, the curvature of the state space tells the matter <lb/>how to move while the matter tells the state space how to curve, and each feeds back into <lb/>the other. <lb/>Given the close parallels between our proposal and general relativity, we may ask whether <lb/>there is any relation between the phase space of the generalized quantum theory and space-<lb/>time. Indeed, as indicated above, such a connection exists. Just as in quantum mechanics, <lb/>our extension also requires the specification of a Hamiltonian with its defining variables. <lb/>The form of the Hamiltonian may be fixed by the requirement that it should describe a <lb/>canonical quantum mechanical system whose space of configurations is physical space and <lb/>whose dynamics defines a consistent quantum gravity in a flat background. This is the local <lb/>physics we are after. We know of only one example of a non-perturbative quantum mechan-<lb/>ics that satisfies this criterion: Matrix theory [13]. By promoting all of the coordinates to <lb/>matrices, spacetime is expected to emerge from the much less intuitive dynamical quantum <lb/>phase space. <lb/>It should be emphasized that our model is consistent with our goal of altering minimally <lb/></body>

			<page>– 7 – <lb/></page>

			<body> the basic structure of quantum theory. In particular, there is no loss of unitarity. To be more <lb/>precise, probabilities are conserved in the sense of the more general, dynamical probability <lb/>measure. In other words, the probabilities sum to one, but the group of transformations <lb/>of underlying quantum dynamics extends the unitary group and the Born rule is thereby <lb/>generalized. Much of the structure implied by this generalization of the canonical quantum <lb/>theory has yet to be worked out in its details (both conceptually and computationally), <lb/>but given the remarkable properties enumerated above, we believe the proposal offers great <lb/>promise, and has something profound to say about the nature of time. The message at the <lb/>heart of our model is that we must surrender the global notion of time at all scales while <lb/>retaining the central role that time evolution plays in Nature. <lb/> III. A long while ago the world began <lb/> Our Universe started out as an extreme environment, a hot, small, dense place. Thus un-<lb/>derstanding the Big Bang requires a grasp of physics at the smallest scales in the presence <lb/>of exceptionally strong gravitational fields. The Universe in the beginning was by its very <lb/>nature a crucible in which Einstein&apos;s general relativity and quantum theory mix. More-<lb/>over, because the Big Bang is the Universe&apos;s initial condition, it is inextricably linked to <lb/>understanding the nature of time. <lb/>The initial state of the Universe had a very low entropy meaning that it was a highly <lb/>ordered state. The entropy of the observed Universe today can be estimated by counting the <lb/>degrees of freedom at the causal horizon, S <lb/> R  H <lb/>  P <lb/>  2 <lb/>  10 <lb/> 123  , where R  H  is the Hubble radius <lb/>and  P  the Planck length. The number of microstates is then given by Boltzmann&apos;s formula <lb/>Ω = e <lb/> S  e <lb/> 10  123  , and the probability associated with the Big Bang is P ∼ 1/Ω  e <lb/> −10  123  . The <lb/>Big Bang therefore appears to be an exceptionally special point in phase space [14], a most <lb/>unlikely event. That the entropy increases irreversibly with the expansion of the Universe is <lb/>the so called cosmological arrow of time. <lb/> Within the framework of our model we examine the possible initial states of the Universe. <lb/>Refinements in the understanding of the non-linear Grassmannian, the phase space of the <lb/>quantum theory, provide a sharp, new insight in this direction. In particular, different metrics <lb/>may be associated to the space. Since Gr(C <lb/> n+1  ) is the diffeomorphism invariant counterpart <lb/>of CP <lb/> n  , the simplest and most natural topological metric to consider is the analog of the <lb/>Fubini–Study metric. It so happens that just such a situation was analyzed by Michor and <lb/>Mumford [15], who obtained the striking result that the generalized Fubini–Study metric <lb/>induces on Gr(C <lb/> n+1  ) a vanishing geodesic distance between any two points on the space. <lb/>The fluctuations of the space become wild and the curvature becomes unbounded. This <lb/>causes the space to wrap tightly on itself. <lb/>As an analogy, consider that a shirt may have two buttons on opposite cuffs which do <lb/>not touch when the shirt is worn but that can be brought into contact when it is folded. <lb/></body>

			<page>– 8 – <lb/></page>

			<body> In a very similar fashion, the points on the phase space of this quantum theory come into <lb/>contact with each other. With the choice of the analog Fubini–Study metric on Gr(C <lb/> n+1  ), <lb/>the folding of the phase space of the theory becomes so extreme as to bring every point <lb/>arbitrarily close to every other point. In other words, the space comes to exist, effectively, <lb/>as a single point. <lb/>A point in the phase space of the theory corresponds to a state of the quantum system <lb/>under consideration, which in this case is the entire Universe. The distance in phase space <lb/>between points corresponds to the ability to distinguish the different quantum states from <lb/>one another. Thus the result of employing the Fubini–Study metric on the non-linear Grass-<lb/>mannian is that the quantum state space assumes only one possible configuration. The <lb/>entropy, which is given by the logarithm of the number of possible quantum states, then <lb/>vanishes. This is precisely the type of configuration that describes the initial state of the <lb/>Universe. <lb/>While the system has entropy S = 0, the very high curvatures in Gr(C <lb/> n+1  ) signal a non-<lb/>equilibrium condition of dynamical instability. The system will flow toward differentiation, <lb/>which yields, through entropy production, distinguishable states in the quantum phase space. <lb/>The vanishing geodesic distance can be interpreted as the signature, or order parameter, of <lb/>a strong fluctuation induced transition from the low-entropy, high-temperature initial state <lb/>to the high-entropy, low-temperature Universe that we observe and inhabit at late times. <lb/>How can this occur? The space Gr(C <lb/> n+1  ) has, in principle, an infinite number of metrics, <lb/>a subset of which will solve the dynamical equations on the state space. Indeed, there is <lb/>an infinite one parameter family of non-zero geodesic distance metrics, of which the Fubini– <lb/>Study metric is a special case [15]. The dynamical evolution, according to the second law <lb/>of thermodynamics, is toward some higher entropy but stable configuration. During this <lb/>evolution, spacetime and canonical quantum mechanics will emerge. <lb/>Einstein&apos;s equations tell us that matter and energy react dynamically to the geometry <lb/>of spacetime and, conversely, spacetime responds to matter and energy by curving, and the <lb/>process continues. The model proposed here is a highly non-linear theory that emulates <lb/>general relativity in its structure. The quantum state space is also governed by non-linear <lb/>differential equations and will likewise experience backreaction. Because it is a far from <lb/>equilibrium system, the initial state will decay. The Big Bang is, in fact, very reminiscent <lb/>of a &quot; freezing by heating &quot; metastable phase [16]. As the configuration space of the Matrix <lb/>theory is spacetime, when the non-linear Grassmannian evolves away from the initial Big <lb/>Bang configuration the points of the state space differentiate and the Universe expands. This <lb/>type of phase transition away from the zero entropy Big Bang state yields the cosmological <lb/>evolution of the Universe. Thus the Universe is required to undergo cosmological evolution <lb/>and is naturally equipped with an arrow of time. This cosmological arrow of time is nothing <lb/>but the flow on the space of metrics on Gr(C <lb/> n+1  ). Because there are more possible configu-<lb/>rations of the quantum system when the metric distance between points on the phase space <lb/>is non-zero, the Universe consistently evolves to a state of higher entropy. <lb/></body>

			<page>– 9 – <lb/></page>

			<body> The geometric structure of the non-linear Grassmannian is remarkable. It addresses the <lb/>problem of time, the arrow of time, and the nature of the initial state of the Universe. <lb/>We have seen the profound discrepancy between time in quantum mechanics, where it is a <lb/>necessary parameter for describing the evolution of a system, and time in gravitation, where <lb/>it is a label with no special meaning. Treating quantum mechanics geometrically and then <lb/>altering the triadic structure of the theory in a consistent fashion provides a framework in <lb/>which the two different meanings of time find reconciliation. In his Fragments, Heraclitus <lb/>likens time to a child playing with dice [17]. His musings from so long ago find an echo in <lb/>our statistical view of time, that familiar stranger. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments: CHT thanks Cornelia Vizman for first alerting him to the key paper <lb/>by Michor and Mumford on vanishing geodesic distance and Mathieu Molitor for many <lb/>mathematical clarifications on non-linear Grassmannians. VJ expresses gratitude to the <lb/>LPTHE, Jussieu for generous hospitality. DM &amp; MK are supported in part by the U.S. <lb/>Department of Energy under contract DE-FG05-92ER40677. <lb/></div>

			<page> – 10 – <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] E. P. Wigner, Rev. Mod. Phys. 29, 255 (1957). <lb/>[2] C. W. Misner, K. S. Thorne, and J. A. Wheeler, Gravitation, New York: Freeman (1973). <lb/>[3] Interestingly, this was well known from the beginning: A. Einstein, Albert Einstein and Michele <lb/>Besso Correspondence, letter of 3 January 1916, ed. P. Speziali, Paris: Hermann (1972); <lb/> Relativity: The Special and General Theory, New York: Dover (2001). For a recent discussion <lb/>of these issues, see S. B. Giddings, D. Marolf, and J. B. Hartle, Phys. Rev. D 74, 064018 <lb/>(2006) [arXiv:hep-th/0512200]. <lb/>[4] H. Salecker and E. P. Wigner, Phys. Rev. 109, 571 (1958). <lb/>[5] B. DeWitt, in Gravitation: An Introduction to Current Research, ed. L. Witten, New York: <lb/>Wiley (1962); Phys. Rev. 160, 1113 (1967). <lb/>[6] K. Fredenhagen and R. Haag, Commun. Math. Phys. 108, 91 (1987). For a discussion, see <lb/>C. J. Isham, arXiv:gr-qc/9210011. <lb/>[7] G. Hinshaw, et al. [WMAP Collaboration], arXiv:0803.0732 [astro-ph]. <lb/>[8] S. Hawking and R. Penrose, The Nature of Space and Time, Princeton: University Press <lb/>(1996). <lb/>[9] A. Ashtekar and T. A. Schilling, gr-qc/9706069; J. Anandan and Y. Aharonov, Phys. Rev. <lb/>Lett. 65, 1697 (1990); J. Anandan, Found. Phys. 21, 1265 (1991). <lb/>[10] W. K. Wootters, Phys. Rev. D 23, 357 (1981). <lb/>[11] For a review and references to the original literature, see V. Jejjala, M. Kavic, and D. Minic, <lb/>Int. J. Mod. Phys. A 22, 3317 (2007) [arXiv:0706.2252 [hep-th]]. <lb/>[12] D. Minic and C.-H. Tze, Phys. Lett. B 581, 111 (2004) [arXiv:hep-th/0309239]; Phys. Rev. D <lb/> 68, 061501 (2003) [arXiv:hep-th/0305193]. <lb/>[13] T. Banks, W. Fischler, S. H. Shenker, and L. Susskind, Phys. Rev. D 55, 5112 (1997) <lb/>[arXiv:hep-th/9610043]. <lb/>[14] R. Penrose, The Emperor&apos;s New Mind, Oxford: University Press (1989). <lb/>[15] P. W. Michor and D. Mumford, Documenta Math. 10, 217 (2005) [arXiv:math/0409303 <lb/>[math.DG]]. <lb/>[16] V. Jejjala, M. Kavic, D. Minic, and C.-H. Tze, arXiv:0804.3598 [hep-th]. <lb/>[17] Heraclitus, Fragments: The Collected Wisdom of Heraclitus, New York: Viking (The Penguin <lb/>Group, Penguin Putnam, Inc.) <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> – 11 – </page>


	</text>
</tei>
