<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> DELPHI Collaboration <lb/> DELPHI 2000-011 CONF 332 <lb/>26 February 2000 <lb/> Search for Neutralinos and Sleptons in scenarios with <lb/>Gravitino LSP and Stau NLSP with the DELPHI <lb/>detector up to 202 GeV centre-of-mass energy <lb/> Preliminary <lb/> DELPHI Collaboration <lb/> R. Alemany <lb/> 1  , F.R. Cavallo <lb/> 2  , C. García <lb/> 3  , F.L. Navarria <lb/> 2  , G. Wolf <lb/> 1 <lb/> Abstract <lb/> Sleptons and neutralinos were searched for in the context of scenarios where the <lb/>lightest supersymmetric particle is the gravitino. It was assumed that the stau is the <lb/>next-to-lightest supersymmetric particle. Data collected with the DELPHI detector <lb/>at centre-of-mass energies of 192, 196, 200 and 202 GeV were analysed combining <lb/>the methods developed in previous searches at lower energies. No evidence for the <lb/>production of these supersymmetric particles was found. Hence, limits were derived <lb/>at 95% confidence level. <lb/> Paper submitted to the Moriond Conference 2000 <lb/> 1  CERN, CH-1211 Geneva 23, Switzerland <lb/> 2  INFN, Bologna, V. le Berti Pichat 6/2, I00126 Bologna, Italy <lb/> 3  IFIC, Avda. Dr. Molliner 50, Burjassot 46100, Valencia, Spain <lb/></front>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> Supersymmetry (SUSY) may be broken at a scale below the grand-unification scale M  GU T  , <lb/>with the ordinary gauge interactions acting as the messengers of supersymmetry breaking <lb/>[1, 2]. In the corresponding models (GMSB models), the gravitino, ˜ <lb/> G, turns out to be <lb/>the lightest supersymmetric particle (LSP) and is expected to be almost massless. The <lb/>next-to-lightest supersymmetric particle (NLSP) is therefore unstable and decays, under <lb/>the assumption of R-parity conservation, into its ordinary matter partner and an invisible <lb/>gravitino. <lb/>The number of generations of supersymmetry breaking messengers and the value of <lb/>tan β usually determine which supersymmetric particle is the NLSP [3, 4, 5, 6]. In the <lb/>majority of the GMSB space, the NLSP is a slepton, ˜ l. Moreover, depending on magnitude <lb/>of the mixing betweeñ <lb/> τ  R  and <lb/>  L  , there exist two possible scenarios. If the mixing is large <lb/> 4  , <lb/>˜ <lb/> τ  1  is the NLSP, but if the mixing is negligible, ˜ <lb/> τ  1  is mainly right-handed [7] and almost <lb/>mass degenerate with the other sleptons. In this case, the <lb/>  R  and <lb/>  R  three body decay <lb/>( ˜ l→  <lb/>  1  τ l with <lb/>  1  → τ ˜ <lb/> G), is very suppressed, and <lb/>  R  and <lb/>  R  decay directly into l ˜ <lb/> G. This <lb/>scenario is called   co-NLSP. Searches for supersymmetric particles within both these <lb/>scenarios are described in this article. <lb/>Due to the coupling of the NLSP tõ <lb/> G, its mean decay length can range from µm <lb/> to meters depending on the mass of the gravitino (m  ˜ <lb/> G  ), or equivalently, on the scale of <lb/>SUSY breaking, <lb/> √ <lb/> F : <lb/> L = 1.76 × 10 <lb/> −3 <lb/> E  ˜ l <lb/> m  ˜ l <lb/>  2 <lb/> − 1 <lb/> m  ˜ l <lb/> 100 GeV/c <lb/> 2 <lb/>  −5  m  ˜ <lb/> G <lb/> 1 eV/c  2 <lb/>  2 <lb/> cm, <lb/>(1) <lb/>For example, for m  ˜ <lb/> G  250 eV ( <lb/> √ <lb/> F  1000 TeV), the decay of the NLSP can take <lb/>place within the detector. This range of <lb/> √ <lb/> F is in fact consistent with astrophysical and <lb/>cosmological considerations [8, 9]. <lb/>The results of two searches are presented in this work. The first one looks for the <lb/>production of <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  pairs with either <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  decaying tõ <lb/> τ  1  τ and <lb/>  1  then decaying promptly <lb/>into τ ˜ <lb/> G, which is an update of the search presented in ref. [11], or <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  decaying tõ ll <lb/> with BR( ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  → ˜ ll) = 1/3 and   promptly decaying into l ˜ <lb/> G: e <lb/> +  e <lb/> −  → ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  → ˜ ll  <lb/>   l <lb/>  → <lb/> l ˜ <lb/> Gll <lb/> l <lb/>  . These two modes represent the two extremes in the range of possible decays of <lb/>the neutralino. In particular, a higgsino-like <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  would decay only tõ <lb/> τ  1  τ for all practical <lb/>purposes since the higgsino component of the <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  couples tõ l through Yukawa couplings. <lb/>On the other hand, the decays of a gaugino-like <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  are regulated only by phase space <lb/>considerations. Therefore, in the case of the <lb/>  1  -NLSP scenario, neutralino pair production <lb/>would mainly lead to a final state with four tau leptons and two gravitinos, while in the <lb/>case of a co-NLSP scenario, the final signature would contain two pairs of leptons with <lb/>possibly different flavour and two gravitinos. <lb/>The second search concerns   pair production followed by the decays   → l ˜ <lb/> G within <lb/>the detector volume. The signature of such an event will be at least one track of a charged <lb/>particle with a kink or a decay vertex when the   decays inside the tracking devices. If <lb/>the decay length is too short (small m  ˜ <lb/> G  ) to allow for the reconstruction of the   track, <lb/>only the corresponding lepton or its decay products will be seen in the detector, and the <lb/>search will then be based on track impact parameter. However, if the decay takes place <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 4  In GMSB models large mixing occurs generally in regions of tan β ≥ 10 or |µ| &gt; 500 GeV. <lb/></note>

			<page> 1 <lb/></page>

			<body> outside the tracking devices (large m  ˜ <lb/> G  ), the signature will be that of a heavy charged <lb/>particle already studied by DELPHI [12]. For very light gravitinos the limits from the <lb/>search for sleptons in gravity mediated (MSUGRA) models can be applied [13, 14]. <lb/>The data samples and event selections are respectively described in sections 2 and 3, <lb/>while the results and a model dependent interpretation are presented in section 4. <lb/> 2 Event sample and experimental procedure <lb/> All searches are based on data collected with the DELPHI detector during 1999 at the <lb/>centre-of-mass energies of 192, 196, 200 and 202 GeV. The total integrated luminosity <lb/>was 228.2 pb <lb/> −1  . A detailed description of the DELPHI detector can be found in [16] and <lb/>its performance in [17]. In all cases, the <lb/>  1  and  searches are updates to similar searches <lb/>carried out at lower centre-of-mass energies. <lb/>To evaluate the signal efficiencies and background contaminations, events were gene-<lb/>rated using different programs, all relying on JETSET 7.4 [18], tuned to LEP 1 data [19] for <lb/>quark fragmentation. The program SUSYGEN [20] was used to generate the neutralino pair <lb/>events and their subsequent decay products. In order to compute detection efficiencies, <lb/>a total of 90000 events were generated with masses 67 GeV/c <lb/> 2  ≤ m  ˜ <lb/> τ  1  + 2 GeV/c <lb/> 2  ≤ <lb/> m  ˜ <lb/> χ  0 <lb/>1 <lb/> ≤ <lb/>√ <lb/> s/2. Slepton pair samples of 99000 and 76500 events at 196 GeV and 202 GeV <lb/>respectively were produced with PYTHIA 5.7 [18] with staus having mean decay lengths <lb/>from 0.25 to 200 cm and masses from m  τ  to 98 GeV/c <lb/> 2  . Another sample of <lb/>  pair <lb/>was produced with SUSYGEN for the small impact parameter search with m  ˜ <lb/> τ  from 40 to <lb/>80 GeV/c <lb/> 2  . <lb/>The background process e <lb/> +  e <lb/> −  → q ¯ <lb/> q(nγ) was generated with PYTHIA 6.125, while <lb/> KORALZ 4.2 [21] were used for µ <lb/> +  µ <lb/> −  (γ) and τ <lb/> +  τ <lb/> −  (γ). The generator BHWIDE [22] was <lb/>used for e <lb/> +  e <lb/> −  → e <lb/> +  e <lb/> −  events. <lb/>Processes leading to four-fermion final states, were generated using EXCALIBUR <lb/>1.08 [23] and GRC4F [24]. <lb/>Two-photon interactions leading to hadronic final states were generated using <lb/> TWOGAM [25], separating the VDM, QPM and QCD components. The generators of <lb/>Berends, Daverveldt and Kleiss [26] were used for the leptonic final states. <lb/>The cosmic radiation background was studied using the data collected before the <lb/>beginning of the 1998 LEP run. <lb/>The generated signal and background events were passed through the detailed simu-<lb/>lation [17] of the DELPHI detector and then processed with the same reconstruction and <lb/>analysis programs used for real data. <lb/> 3 Data selection <lb/> 3.1 Neutralino pair production <lb/> The selection used in the search for the process e <lb/> +  e <lb/> −  → ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  → ˜ <lb/> τ  1  τ ˜ <lb/> τ  1  τ → τ ˜ <lb/> Gτ τ ˜ <lb/> Gτ has <lb/>been described in [10, 11]. A very similar selection was used in the general search for <lb/> e <lb/> +  e <lb/> −  → ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  → ˜ ll  <lb/>   l <lb/>  → l ˜ <lb/> Gll <lb/> l <lb/>  within the co-NLSP scenario, where BR( ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  → ˜ ll) = <lb/>1/3 for each leptonic flavour. The main two differences between these two cases comes <lb/>from the fact that the mean number of neutrinos carrying away undetected energy and <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body> momentum and the number of charged tracks per event is considerably bigger for the <lb/>  1  -NLSP scenario. <lb/>The pre-selection of events is common to both scenarios, and has been described <lb/>in [10], together with the selection of the search for <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  → ˜ <lb/> τ  1  τ . Only the details of the <lb/>search <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  → ˜ ll are presented in the following. Two sets of cuts were applied in order to <lb/>reduce the γγ and f ¯ f(γ) backgrounds and a third set of cuts to select events according to <lb/>their topology: <lb/>1-Cuts against γγ backgrounds: the transverse energy, E  T  , should be bigger than 4 <lb/>GeV. The energy in a cone of 30 <lb/> •  around the beam axis was further restricted to <lb/>be less than 60% of the total visible energy to avoid possible bias from the Monte <lb/>Carlo samples. The missing mass should be smaller than 0.88 <lb/> √ <lb/> s. The momentum <lb/>of the charged particle with largest momentum should be bigger than 8 GeV/c. <lb/>The transverse missing momentum, p  T  , should be bigger than 6 GeV/c. These <lb/>cuts reduced the γγ background by a factor of the order of 40. <lb/>2-Cuts against f ¯ f(γ) and 4-fermion backgrounds: the number of good tracks should <lb/>be smaller than 7. The maximum thrust was further reduced from 0.99 to 0.95. <lb/>Dividing each event into two jets with the Durham algorithm, its acoplanarity should <lb/>be bigger than 8 <lb/> •  . The missing mass of the events should be bigger than 0.2 <lb/> √ <lb/> s. <lb/> After these cuts, the f ¯ f(γ) and 4-fermion backgrounds were reduced by a factor of <lb/>the order of 30. <lb/>3-Cuts based on topology: signal events tend naturally to cluster into a 4-jet topology. <lb/>When events are forced into a 4-jet configuration, all jets should be at least 18 <lb/> • <lb/> away from the beam direction. When reduced by the jet algorithm into a 2-jet <lb/>configuration, the charged particles belonging to each of these jets should be in a <lb/>cone broader than 25 <lb/> •  . Finally, the axes of each of the four jets should be separated <lb/>from the others at least by 9 <lb/> •  . <lb/>6 events were observed to pass the search for neutralino pair production in the <lb/>  1  -<lb/>NLSP scenario, with 3.36±0.98 SM background events expected. 4 events pass the search <lb/>for neutralino pair production in the co-NLSP scenario, with 4.39±0.51 SM background <lb/>events expected. After these cuts, efficiencies between 20 and 44% were obtained for the <lb/>signal events. <lb/> 3.2 Slepton pair production <lb/> This section describes the update of the search for the process e <lb/> +  e <lb/> −  → ˜ <lb/> τ ˜ <lb/> τ → τ ˜ <lb/> Gτ  <lb/> already described in [10, 27, 11]. An additional 228.2 pb <lb/> −1  integrated luminosity collected <lb/>at the centre-of-mass energies of 192, 196, 200 and 202 GeV has been analysed using the <lb/>same procedure as for the data collected at 189 GeV, and using the same values for the data <lb/>selection cuts taking into account the necessary rescaling of some cuts with the energy. <lb/>The same selection cuts have been applied to the search for <lb/>  R  -pair production in the <lb/>framework of   co-NLSP scenario. Therefore, only results and efficiencies will be reported <lb/>in this section, since the details of the selection criteria can be found in [10, 27, 11]. <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body> 3.2.1 Search for secondary vertices <lb/> This analysis exploits a peculiarity of the   → l ˜ <lb/> G topology in the case of intermediate <lb/>gravitino masses (i.e. 0.5 eV/c <lb/> 2  m  ˜ <lb/> G  200 eV/c <lb/> 2  as dictated by eq. 1), namely, one <lb/>or two tracks coming from the interaction point and at least one of them with either a <lb/>secondary vertex or a kink. <lb/>Rather loose preselection cuts were imposed on the events in order to suppress the <lb/>low energy background (beam-gas, beam-wall, etc), γγ, e <lb/> +  e <lb/> −  and hadronic events. The <lb/>events that survived the preselection cuts underwent the search for secondary vertices or <lb/>kinks. <lb/>Fake decay vertices could be present amongst the reconstructed secondary vertices, <lb/>being produced by particles interacting in the detector material or by radiated photons <lb/>if the particle trajectory was reconstructed into two separated tracks. To eliminate these <lb/>classes of events, additional requirements were imposed: <lb/>-to reject hadronic interactions, any reconstructed hadronic interaction (secondary <lb/>vertices reconstructed in region where there is material) must be outside a cone of <lb/>half angle 5 <lb/> •  around the slepton direction; <lb/>-to reject segmented tracks, the angle between the tracks used to define a vertex had <lb/>to be larger than 6 <lb/> •  ; <lb/>-to reject photon radiation in the case of τ clusters with only one track, there had <lb/>to be no neutral particle in a 3 <lb/> •  cone around the direction defined by the difference <lb/>between the <lb/>  1  momentum and the momentum of the τ daughter calculated at the <lb/>crossing point. <lb/>If no pair of tracks was found to survive these conditions, the event was rejected. Fi-<lb/>gure 1 shows the distribution of these three quantities. The distributions compare real <lb/>data, expected Standard Model background simulation and simulated signal for m  ˜ <lb/> τ  1  = <lb/>60 GeV/c <lb/> 2  decaying with a mean decay length of 50 cm. All the samples are at 200 <lb/>GeV centre-of-mass energy. The excess of data in the first bins of fig. 1-b is due to an <lb/>underestimation in the simulation of mismatchings between the tracking devices. <lb/>Two events in real data were found to satisfy all the conditions described above, <lb/>while 1.00 <lb/> +0.49 <lb/> −0.16  were expected from SM backgrounds. One event was compatible with a <lb/> γγ → τ <lb/> +  τ <lb/> −  with a hadronic interaction in the ID detector. The other one was compatible <lb/>with a e <lb/> +  e <lb/> −  → τ <lb/> +  τ <lb/> −  event where one of the electrons (decay product of the τ ), after <lb/>radiating a photon, was reconstructed as two independent tracks. <lb/>The vertex reconstruction procedure was sensitive to radial decay lengths, R, between <lb/>20 cm and 90 cm. Within this region a vertex was reconstructed with an efficiency <lb/>of ∼53.0±2.0%. The VD (Vertex Detector) and the ID (Inner Detector) were needed to <lb/>reconstruct the <lb/>  track and the TPC (Time Projection Chamber) to reconstruct the decay <lb/>products. The shape of the efficiency distribution was essentially flat as a function of R, <lb/>going down when the <lb/>  decayed near the outer surface of the TPC, due to inefficiencies <lb/>in the reconstruction of the tracks coming from the desintegration products of the τ . <lb/>The search for vertices had an efficiency of the order of 45.0±2.0% for <lb/>  masses between <lb/>40 and 98 GeV/c <lb/> 2  with a mean decay length of 50 cm. The efficiencies decreased near the <lb/>kinematical limit due to a small boost that allowed for big angles to appear between the <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body> ˜ <lb/> τ and the desintegration products of the τ . For <lb/>  masses below 40 GeV/c <lb/> 2  , the efficiency <lb/>decreased gradually due to the cut that rejects segmented tracks. This happened because <lb/>the resulting big boost causes the angle betweeñ <lb/> τ and τ decay products to be very small. <lb/>As already said, the same selection criteria was applied to smuons. The efficiency for <lb/>smuons was 56.0±2.0% for m  ˜ <lb/> µ  R  between 40 to 98 GeV/c <lb/> 2  . <lb/> 3.2.2 Large impact parameter search <lb/> To investigate the region of lower gravitino masses the previous search was extended to <lb/>the case of sleptons with mean decay length between 0.25 cm and approximately 10 cm. In <lb/>this case the   track is not reconstructed and only the l (or the decay products in the case <lb/>of <lb/>  ) is detected. The impact parameter search was only applied to those events accepted <lb/>by the same general requirements as in the search for secondary vertices, and not selected <lb/>by the vertex analysis. The same selection criteria described in references [10, 27, 11] <lb/>were applied. <lb/>The efficiencies were derived for the different <lb/>  1  masses and decay lengths by applying <lb/>the same selection to the simulated signal events. The maximum efficiency was 29.0±2.0% <lb/>corresponding to a mean decay length of 2.5 cm. The efficiency decreased very fast for <lb/>lower decay lengths due to the cut on minimum impact parameter. For longer decay <lb/>lengths, the appearance of reconstructed <lb/>  tracks in combination with the cut on the <lb/>maximum amount of charged particle tracks caused the efficiency to decrease smoothly. <lb/>This decrease is compensated by a rising efficiency in the search for secondary vertices. For <lb/>masses above 30 GeV/c <lb/> 2  no dependence on the <lb/>  mass was found far from the kinematic <lb/>limit. <lb/>The same selection was applied to smuons. For smuons the efficiency increased to <lb/>60.0±2.0% for a mean decay length of 2.5 cm and masses over 30 GeV/c <lb/> 2  since the smuon <lb/>has always one prong decay. <lb/>Trigger efficiencies were studied simulating the DELPHI trigger response to the events <lb/>selected by the vertex search and by the large impact parameter analysis, and were found <lb/>to be around 99%. <lb/>One event in the real data sample was selected with the above criteria, while 1.02 <lb/> +0.96 <lb/> −0.12 <lb/> were expected from SM backgrounds. <lb/> 3.2.3 Small impact parameter search <lb/> The large impact parameter search can be extended further down to mean decay <lb/>lengths below 1 mm. Here we recall only the main points of the analysis and some changes <lb/>with respect to previous ones. In low multiplicity events two hemispheres were defined <lb/>using the thrust axis. The highest momentum, good quality (∆p/p &lt; 50%), tracks in <lb/>each hemisphere were labelled leading tracks. The impact parameters, b  1  and b  2  , of the <lb/>leading tracks in the Rφ plane were used to discriminate against SM backgrounds. The <lb/>same selection criteria described in reference [10, 11] was applied. However, some extra <lb/>selection was added in order to reduce the background from detector noise or failure. <lb/>In order to preserve the efficiency in the region of decay length  10 cm, where the <lb/>  can be observed as a track coming from the primary vertex and badly measured owing <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body> to its limited length, further requirements on the track quality were applied only to the <lb/>leading track having the maximum impact parameter. This track was required to have <lb/>a relative momentum error &lt; 30% and to be measured in the TPC or in all of the other <lb/>three track detectors in the barrel. <lb/>The efficiency of the search did not show any significant dependence on the <lb/>  mass <lb/>for masses over 40 GeV/c <lb/> 2  , and it could be parameterized as a function of the <lb/>  decay <lb/>length in the laboratory system. The maximum efficiency was ∼ 38% for a mean decay <lb/>length of ∼ 2 cm, the efficiency dropped at small decay lengths (∼ 10% at 0.6 mm). <lb/>The same selection criteria were used to search for smuons as reported in [10, 11]. <lb/>The maximum efficiency reached for the smuon search was 43% at 2 cm of mean decay <lb/>length. <lb/>With <lb/> b <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + b <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  &gt; 600µm the number of events selected in the data was 5 for the <lb/>  and <lb/>  search. 5.05±0.39 events were expected from the Standard Model background. Fig. 2 <lb/>shows the <lb/> b <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + b <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  distribution for data (dots) and simulated backgrounds (histogram) <lb/>after all other cuts. All of the selected candidates were compatible with Standard Model <lb/>events. <lb/> 4 Results and interpretation <lb/> Since no evidence for a signal was found in the data, limits on the cross-section of sparticle <lb/>pair production and on the masses of the particles searched for were derived. In what <lb/>follows, the model described in reference [4] will be used in order to derive limits. This <lb/>is a model which assumes radiatively broken electroweak symmetry and null trilinear <lb/>couplings at the messenger scale. The corresponding parameter space was scanned as <lb/>follows: 1 ≤ n ≤ 4, 5 TeV ≤ Λ ≤ 90 TeV, 1.1 ≤ M/Λ ≤ 10 <lb/> 9  , 1.1 ≤ tan β ≤ 50, and <lb/> sign(µ) = ±1, where n is the number of messenger generations in the model, Λ is the <lb/>ratio between the vacuum expectation values of the auxiliary component and the scalar <lb/>component of the superfield and M is the messenger mass scale. The parameters tan β <lb/> and µ are defined as for MSUGRA. <lb/> 4.1 Neutralino pair production <lb/> Limits on the cross-section for neutralino pair production were derived in the two scenarios <lb/>for each (m  ˜ <lb/> χ  0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> ,m  ˜ l  ) combination. For the <lb/>  1  -NLSP case, the combination took also into <lb/>account the results from the LEP runs from 1996 to 1999 [10, 11]. The limits for the <lb/>production cross-section allowed us to exclude some sectors of the (m  ˜ <lb/> χ  0 <lb/>1 <lb/> , m  ˜ l  ) space. In <lb/>order to achieve the maximum sensitivity, the results from two other analyses are taken <lb/>into account. The first is the search for slepton pair production in the context of gravity <lb/>mediated SUSY breaking models [13, 14]. In the case where the MSUGRA <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  is massless, <lb/>the kinematics corresponds to the case of   decaying into a lepton and a gravitino. The <lb/>second is the search for lightest neutralino pair production in the region of the mass space <lb/>where <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  is the NLSP [29, 30] (the region above the diagonal line in fig. 3, i.e. m  ˜ <lb/> τ  &gt; m  ˜ <lb/> χ  0 <lb/>1 <lb/> ). <lb/>Within this zone, the neutralino decays into a gravitino and a photon. <lb/>As an illustration, fig. 3 presents the 95% C.L. excluded areas for m  ˜ <lb/> G  &lt; 1 eV/c <lb/> 2 <lb/> in the m  ˜ <lb/> χ  0 <lb/>1 <lb/> vs. m  ˜ <lb/> τ  R  plane for the co-NLSP case. The positive-slope dashed area is <lb/>excluded by this analysis. The negative-slope dashed area is excluded by the analysis <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body> searching for neutralino pair production followed by the decay <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1  → ˜ <lb/> Gγ. The point-<lb/>hatched area is excluded by the direct search for slepton pair production within MSUGRA <lb/>scenarios [13, 14]. <lb/> 4.2 Slepton pair production <lb/> Since there was no evidence for the signal above the expected background, the number of <lb/>candidates in data and the expected number of background events were used to set upper <lb/>limits at 95% C.L. for the slepton pair-production cross-section and slepton masses. The <lb/>limits presented here are at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 202 GeV after combining the results of the searches at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 130-202 GeV with the likelihood ratio method [28]. The results are presented in <lb/>the (m  ˜ <lb/> G  ,m  ˜ l  ) plane combining the two impact parameter searches, the secondary vertex <lb/>analysis and the stable heavy lepton search [12] <lb/> 5  . <lb/>The <lb/>  1  pair production cross-section depends on the mixing in the stau sector. There-<lb/>fore, in order to put limits to the <lb/>  1  mass the mixing angle has to be fixed. The results <lb/>presented here corresponds to the case when there is no mixing between the <lb/>  R  and <lb/>  L  , <lb/>thus <lb/>  1  is a pure right-handed state (figure 4-a). The case which corresponds to a mix-<lb/>ing angle which gives the minimum <lb/>  1  pair production cross-section, which at the same <lb/>time maintains m <lb/> 2 <lb/>˜ <lb/> τ  1  &gt; 0, reduces the given limit by 1 GeV. The impact parameter and <lb/>secondary vertex analyses allow the exclusion of <lb/>  R  with a mass below 88 GeV/c <lb/> 2  for <lb/>gravitino masses between 20 and 300 eV/c <lb/> 2  at 95% C.L.. For m  ˜ <lb/> G  below a few eV/c <lb/> 2  , <lb/> m  ˜ <lb/> τ  1  &lt; 75 GeV/c <lb/> 2  were excluded by the search for <lb/>  1  in gravity mediated models [14]. <lb/>For m  ˜ <lb/> G  larger than 1000 eV/c <lb/> 2  the limit was 87 GeV/c <lb/> 2  , obtained from the stable heavy <lb/>lepton search [12]. <lb/>Within the sleptons co-NLSP scenario, the cross-section limits were used to derive <lb/>limits for <lb/>  R  (figure 4-b) mass at 95% C.L.. Therefore, within the co-NLSP scenario, the <lb/>impact parameter search and the secondary vertex search allow for the exclusion of <lb/>  R <lb/> masses below 91 GeV/c <lb/> 2  for gravitino masses between 40 and 200 eV/c <lb/> 2  . <lb/>Assuming mass degeneracy between the staus and smuons, (fig. 4-c), these searches <lb/>exclude at 95% C.L. ˜ l  R  masses below 93.5 GeV/c <lb/> 2  for <lb/>  masses between 30 and 250 eV/c <lb/> 2  . <lb/>For very short lifetimes only <lb/>  R  was considered since it is the best limit that can be <lb/>achieved in absence of slepton combination. <lb/>For <lb/>  larger than 1000 eV/c <lb/> 2  the limit was 87 GeV/c <lb/> 2  , obtained from the stable heavy <lb/>lepton search [12]. ˜ l  R  masses below 35 GeV/c <lb/> 2  are excluded from LEP 1 data [32]. In the <lb/>case of   R  degeneracy, this limit improves to 41 GeV/c <lb/> 2  . <lb/> 5 Summary <lb/> Lightest neutralino-and slepton-pair production were searched for in the context of light <lb/>gravitino scenarios. Two scenarios were explored: the <lb/>  1  NLSP and the   R  co-NLSP <lb/>scenarios. No evidence for signal production was found. Hence, the DELPHI collaboration <lb/>sets lower limits at 95% C.L. for the mass of the <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  at 86 GeV/c <lb/> 2  if m  ˜ <lb/> G  ≤ 1 eV/c <lb/> 2  , for <lb/>the mass of the <lb/>  R  at 88 GeV/c <lb/> 2  , for the mass of the <lb/>  R  at 91 GeV/c <lb/> 2  , and finally for the <lb/>mass of the   R  at 93.5 GeV/c <lb/> 2  for m  ˜ <lb/> G  in the range between 20 and 300 eV/c <lb/> 2  . <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 5  Only the slepton searches have been updated, therefore, the stable heavy lepton and MSUGRA <lb/>searches only cover up to 189 GeV <lb/></note>

			<page> 7 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] M. Dine, W. Fischler and M. Srednicki, Nucl. Phys. B189 (1981) 575 ; <lb/>S. Dimopoulos and S. Raby, Nucl. Phys. B192 (1981) 353 ; <lb/>M. Dine and W. Fischler, Phys. Lett. B110 (1982) 227 ; <lb/>M. Dine and M. Srednicki, Nucl. Phys. B202 (1982) 238 ; <lb/>L. Alvarez-Gaumé, M. Claudson and M. Wise, Nucl. Phys. B207 (1982) 96 ; <lb/>C. Nappi and B. Ovrut, Phys. Lett. B113 (1982) 175 . <lb/>[2] M. Dine and W. Fischler, Nucl. Phys. B204 (1982) 346 ; <lb/>S. Dimopoulos and S. Raby, Nucl. Phys. B219 (1983) 479. <lb/>[3] J. A. Bagger, K. Matchev, D. M. Pierce and R. Zhang, Phys. Rev. D55 (1997) 3188. <lb/>[4] D. A. Dicus, B. Dutta, S. Nandi, Phys. Rev. D56 (1997) 5748 ; <lb/>D. A. Dicus, B. Dutta, S. Nandi, Phys. Rev. Lett. 78 (1997) 3055 ; <lb/>K. Cheung, D. A. Dicus, B. Dutta, S. Nandi, Phys. Rev. D58 (1998) 015008 . <lb/>[5] F. Borzumati, On the Minimal Messenger Model, hep-ph/9702307 and WIS/96-50-<lb/>PH, Dec. 1996. <lb/>[6] G. F. Giudice, R. Rattazzi, Phys. Rep. 322 (1999) 419.. <lb/>[7] A. Bartl et. al., Z. Phys. C73 (1997) 469. <lb/>[8] S. Dimopoulos, M. Dine, S. Raby, S. Thomas and J. D. Wells, Nucl. Phys. Proc. <lb/>Suppl. A52 (1997) 38. <lb/>[9] E. Calzetta, A. Kandus, F. D. Mazzitelli and C. E. M. Wagner, CERN-TH/99-261 <lb/>and hep-ph/9908524. <lb/>[10] DELPHI Collaboration, P. Abreu et al., E. Phys.J. C7 (1999) 595. <lb/>[11] DELPHI Collaboration, P. Abreu et al., CERN-EP/2000-015, Submitted to <lb/>E. Phys.J. <lb/>[12] DELPHI Collaboration, P. Abreu et al., Phys. Lett. B444 (1998) 491; <lb/>DELPHI Collaboration, P. Abreu et al., CERN-EP-2000-020 submitted to <lb/>Phys. Lett. B. <lb/> [13] DELPHI Collaboration, P. Abreu et al.,  &quot; Searches for sleptons at <lb/> √ s = 183 and 189 <lb/>GeV &quot; , to be submitted to Phys. Lett. B. <lb/> [14] DELPHI Collaboration, P. Abreu et al., DELPHI 2000-012 CONF 333. <lb/>[15] DELPHI Collaboration, P. Abreu et al., Phys. Lett. B466 (1999) 61. <lb/>[16] DELPHI Collaboration, P. Aarnio et al., Nucl. Instr. and Meth. 303 (1991) 233. <lb/>[17] DELPHI Collaboration, P. Abreu et al., Nucl. Instr. and Meth. 378 (1996) 57. <lb/>[18] T. Sjöstrand, Comp. Phys. Comm. 39 (1986) 347; <lb/>T. Sjöstrand, PYTHIA 5.6 and JETSET 7.3, CERN-TH/6488-92. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [19] DELPHI Collaboration, P. Abreu et al., Z. Phys. C73 (1996) 11. <lb/>[20] SUSYGEN 2.20, S. Katsanevas and S. Melachroinos in Physics at LEP2, CERN 96-<lb/>01, Vol. 2, p. 328 and http://lyoinfo.in2p3.fr/susygen/susygen.html ; <lb/>S. Katsanevas and P. Moravitz, Comp. Phys. Com. 122 (1998) 227. <lb/>[21] S. Jadach, B.F.L. Ward and Z. Was, Comp. Phys. Comm. 79 (1994) 503. <lb/>[22] S. Jadach, W. Placzek, B.F.L. Ward, Comp. Phys. Comm. 79 (1994) 503. <lb/>[23] F.A. Berends, R. Pittau, R. Kleiss, Phys. Lett. B390 (1997) 298. <lb/>[24] J. Fujimoto et al., Comp. Phys. Comm. 100 (1997) 128. <lb/>[25] S. Nova, A. Olshevski, and T. Todorov, A Monte Carlo event generator for two <lb/>photon physics, DELPHI note 90-35 (1990). <lb/>[26] F.A. Berends, P.H. Daverveldt, R. Kleiss, Comp. Phys. Comm. 40 (1986) 271, <lb/>Comp. Phys. Comm. 40 (1986) 285, Comp. Phys. Comm. 40 (1986) 309. <lb/>[27] DELPHI Collaboration, P. Abreu et al., Eur. Phys. J. C6 (1999) 385. <lb/>[28] A.L. Read, Optimal statistical analysis of search results based on the likelihood ratio <lb/>and its application to the search for the MSM Higgs boson at <lb/> √ s = 161 and 172 GeV, <lb/> DELPHI 97-158 PHYS 737 (1997) and references therein. <lb/>[29] DELPHI Collaboration, P. Abreu et al., Eur. Phys. J.C6 (1999) 371; <lb/>DELPHI Collaboration, P. Abreu et al.,  &quot; Photons events with missing energy at <lb/>LEP 2 &quot; , CERN-EP-2000-021, submitted to Eur. Phys. J. C. <lb/> [30] DELPHI Collaboration, P. Abreu et al., DELPHI 2000-020 CONF 341. <lb/>[31] JADE Collaboration, W. Bartel et al., Phys. Lett. B152 (1985) 392. <lb/>[32] Particle Data Group, Eur. Phys. J. C3 (1998) 1. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex"> 10 <lb/> -2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 1 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 120 <lb/>140 <lb/>160 180 <lb/>Angle hadr. int.( <lb/> o <lb/> ) <lb/> Vertices/3.6 <lb/> o <lb/> Cut = 5 <lb/> o <lb/> (a) <lb/> 10 <lb/> -2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 1 <lb/>10 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 120 <lb/>140 <lb/>160 180 <lb/>Angle between tracks ( <lb/> o <lb/> ) <lb/> Vertices/3.6 <lb/> o <lb/> Cut = 6 <lb/> o <lb/> (b) <lb/> 10 <lb/> -2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 1 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 120 <lb/>140 <lb/>160 180 <lb/>Angle with shower ( <lb/> o <lb/> ) <lb/> Vertices/3.6 <lb/> o <lb/> Cut = 3 <lb/> o <lb/> (c) <lb/> Figure 1: (a) Angle between the directions defined by the hadronic vertex and the re-<lb/>constructed vertex, (b) angle between the tracks of the kink, and (c) angle between the <lb/>electromagnetic shower and the direction defined by the difference between the momenta <lb/>of the <lb/>  1  and its associated τ , defined at the crossing point for real data (dots), ex-<lb/>pected Standard Model background (cross-hatched histogram) and simulated signal for <lb/> m  ˜ <lb/> τ  1  = 60 GeV/c <lb/> 2  decaying with a mean distance of 50 cm (blank histogram). Events <lb/>that do not have hadronic interactions are not included in (a), and events without electro-<lb/>magnetic showers are not included in (b). All the samples are at 200 GeV centre-of-mass <lb/>energy. The arrows indicate the selection criteria imposed. <lb/></div>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex"> Figure 2: <lb/> b <lb/> 2 <lb/> 1  + b <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  distribution for data (dots) and simulated backgrounds (histogram) <lb/>after all other cuts applied by the small impact parameter search. <lb/></div>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex"> 70 <lb/> 75 <lb/>80 <lb/>85 <lb/>90 <lb/>95 <lb/>100 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>100 <lb/>70 <lb/>75 <lb/>80 <lb/>85 <lb/>90 <lb/>95 <lb/>100 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>100 <lb/>70 <lb/>75 <lb/>80 <lb/>85 <lb/>90 <lb/>95 <lb/>100 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>100 <lb/>70 <lb/>75 <lb/>80 <lb/>85 <lb/>90 <lb/>95 <lb/>100 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>100 <lb/> DELPHI PRELIMINARY <lb/>s = 161 -202 GeV <lb/> 1/2 <lb/> 70 <lb/>75 <lb/>80 <lb/>85 <lb/>90 <lb/>95 <lb/>100 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>100 <lb/>70 <lb/>75 <lb/>80 <lb/>85 <lb/>90 <lb/>95 <lb/>100 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>100 <lb/>70 <lb/>75 <lb/>80 <lb/>85 <lb/>90 <lb/>95 <lb/>100 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>100 <lb/>70 <lb/>75 <lb/>80 <lb/>85 <lb/>90 <lb/>95 <lb/>100 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>100 <lb/> γ <lb/> G <lb/>~ 0 <lb/>1 <lb/> χ <lb/> ~ <lb/> γ <lb/> G <lb/>~ 0 <lb/>1 <lb/> χ <lb/> ~ <lb/> γ <lb/> G <lb/>~ 0 <lb/>1 <lb/> χ <lb/> ~ <lb/> γ <lb/> G <lb/>~ 0 <lb/>1 <lb/> χ <lb/> ~ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/> ~ χ <lb/>τ <lb/>τ ~ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/> ~ χ <lb/>τ <lb/>τ ~ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/> ~ χ <lb/>τ <lb/>τ ~ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/> ~ χ <lb/>τ <lb/>τ ~ <lb/>~ τ <lb/>τ ~ <lb/>e e <lb/>~ τ <lb/>τ ~ <lb/>e e <lb/>~ τ <lb/>τ ~ <lb/>e e <lb/>~ τ <lb/>τ ~ <lb/>e e <lb/> n = 1 <lb/>n = 2 <lb/>n = 3 <lb/>n = 4 <lb/> m <lb/> τ <lb/> 1 <lb/> ~ <lb/> (GeV) <lb/> m <lb/> τ <lb/> 1 <lb/> ~ <lb/> (GeV) <lb/> m <lb/> τ <lb/> 1 <lb/> ~ <lb/> (GeV) <lb/> m <lb/> τ <lb/> 1 <lb/> ~ <lb/> (GeV) <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/> ~ χ <lb/> m <lb/>(GeV) <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/> ~ χ <lb/> m <lb/>(GeV) <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/> ~ χ <lb/> m <lb/>(GeV) <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/> ~ χ <lb/> m <lb/>(GeV) <lb/> Figure 3: Areas excluded at 95% C.L. with m  ˜ <lb/> G  &lt; 1 eV/c <lb/> 2  in the m  ˜ <lb/> χ  0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> vs. m  ˜ <lb/> τ  R  plane for <lb/> n =1 to 4. The positive-slope dashed area is excluded by this analysis. The negative-slope <lb/>dashed area is excluded by the search for <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  → γ ˜ <lb/> G, and the point-hatched area by the <lb/>direct search for stau pair production in the MSUGRA framework. <lb/></div>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex"> 40 <lb/> 50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> m G ˜ (eV/c 2 ) <lb/> m (GeV/c <lb/> 2 <lb/> ) <lb/> τ  ˜ <lb/> R <lb/> a. <lb/>PRELIMINARY <lb/> Vertex and IP <lb/>MSUGRA <lb/> τ ˜ R <lb/> Stable <lb/>Heavy <lb/>Lepton <lb/> √s=130-202 GeV -DELPHI <lb/> 40 <lb/> 50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> m G ˜ (eV/c 2 ) <lb/> m (GeV/c <lb/> 2 <lb/> ) <lb/> µ  ˜ <lb/> R <lb/> b. <lb/>PRELIMINARY <lb/> (a) <lb/> Vertex and IP <lb/>MSUGRA <lb/> µ ˜ R <lb/> SHL <lb/> √s=130-202 GeV -DELPHI <lb/> 40 <lb/> 50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> m G ˜ (eV/c 2 ) <lb/> m (GeV/c <lb/> 2 <lb/> ) <lb/> ˜ <lb/> R <lb/> l <lb/> c. <lb/>PRELIMINARY <lb/> MSUGRA <lb/> µ ˜ R <lb/> SHL <lb/>Vertex and IP <lb/> √s=130-202 GeV -DELPHI <lb/> Figure 4: Exclusion regions in the (m  ˜ <lb/> G  ,m  ˜ <lb/> τ  R  ) (a), (m  ˜ <lb/> G  ,m  ˜ <lb/> µ  R  ) (b) and (m  ˜ <lb/> G  ,m  ˜ l  R  ) (c) planes <lb/>at 95% C.L. for the present analyses combined with the stable heavy lepton search and <lb/>the search for <lb/>  R  in gravity mediated models, using all LEP2 data up to 202 GeV. The <lb/>positive-slope hatched area shows the region excluded by the combination of the impact <lb/>parameter and secondary vertex searches. The dashed line shows the expected limits. <lb/></div>

			<page>13 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
