<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="footnote"> 2nd  Reading <lb/> November 25, 2014 12:56 WSPC/S0218-2718 <lb/>142-IJMPD <lb/>1550007 <lb/></note>

			<front> International Journal of Modern Physics D <lb/>Vol. 24, No. 1 (2015) 1550007 (14 pages) <lb/>c <lb/> World Scientific Publishing Company <lb/>DOI: 10.1142/S0218271815500078 <lb/> Kerr–Newman solution in modified teleparallel <lb/>theory of gravity <lb/> Gamal G. L. Nashed  * <lb/> Centre for Theoretical Physics, <lb/>The British University in Egypt, <lb/>Sherouk City 11837, P.O. Box 43, Egypt <lb/>nashed@bue.edu.eg <lb/> Received 11 July 2014 <lb/>Revised 27 September 2014 <lb/>Accepted 28 October 2014 <lb/>Published 27 November 2014 <lb/>A nondiagonal tetrad field having six unknown functions plus an angle Φ, which is a <lb/>function of the radial coordinate r, azimuthal angle θ and the polar angle φ, is applied <lb/>to the charged field equations of modified teleparallel theory of gravity. A special non-<lb/>vacuum solution is derived with three constants of integration. The tetrad field of this <lb/>solution is axially symmetric and its scalar torsion is constant. The associated metric <lb/>of the derived solution gives Kerr–Newman spacetime. We have shown that the derived <lb/>solution can be described by a local Lorentz transformations plus a diagonal tetrad field <lb/>that is the square root of the Kerr–Newman metric. We show that any solution of general <lb/>relativity (GR) can be a solution in f (T ) under certain conditions. <lb/> Keywords: f (T ) Theories of gravity; charged axially symmetric solution; energy. <lb/>PACS Number(s): 04.50.Kd, 04.70.Bw, 04.20.Jb <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> Cosmological observations containing the cosmic microwave background, <lb/> 1,2  the <lb/>Hubble parameter, <lb/> 3  type Ia supernovae <lb/> 4  and baryon acoustic oscillations surveys, <lb/> 5 <lb/> suggest that our Universe is currently undergoing a phase of accelerated expansion. <lb/>The proposals that have been put to explain such discoveries can be classified into <lb/>two categories: One is to assume the cosmic speed-up might be caused within gen-<lb/>eral relativity (GR) by a cosmic fluid with negative pressure, which is called dark <lb/>energy (DE). However, the nature of DE is still unknown and is still one of the <lb/>hardest and unresolved problems in modern theoretical physics. <lb/> 6,7 <lb/></body>

			<front>  *  Address: Mathematics Department, Faculty of Science, Ain Shams University, Cairo, 11566, <lb/>Egypt. <lb/></front>

			<page> 1550007-1 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. D 2015.24. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> 2nd  Reading <lb/> November 25, 2014 12:56 WSPC/S0218-2718 <lb/>142-IJMPD <lb/>1550007 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> G. G. L. Nashed <lb/></note>

			<body> A possible equivalence between the equations of GR can be obtain consider-<lb/>ing a spacetime where the curvature contributions vanish and the unique non-null <lb/>contribution is coming from the antisymmetric part of the connection. This scenario <lb/>is called Weitzenbök spacetime. Through this equivalence, one analyzes the physical <lb/>phenomena of the gravitation and the cosmology, which until now are not clearly <lb/>known using the GR. Hence, we can try to understand the contribution of the <lb/>terms of higher-order in curvature, added to the Einstein–Hilbert term as can be <lb/>observed in the common theories, f (R), <lb/> 8  f (G), <lb/> 9  f (R, T ) <lb/> 10  and f (R, G). <lb/> 11  In the <lb/>case of the theory equivalent to the GR, the Teleparallel Equivalent of General <lb/>Relativity (TEGR), <lb/> 12  the attention is attached to the torsion scalar T which plays <lb/>an important role in constructing the action of the theory. Hence, as in the case of <lb/>GR, a generalization of the TEGR must contain terms of higher-order in T that we <lb/>call f (T ) gravitational theory, <lb/> 13  where f (T ) is an algebraic function of the torsion <lb/>scalar T . <lb/>Recently, special attention has been attached to the f (T ) gravity. Møller and <lb/>other authors undertook and developed the proposal for an analogy between the <lb/>teleparallel gravity and the GR. <lb/> 14  Models based on f (T ) gravity were investigated, <lb/>on one hand as an alternative to inflationary models <lb/> 15,16  and on the other hand, as <lb/>an alternative to dark energy models. <lb/> 17  Recently, still in the framework of f (T ) <lb/>gravity, new spherically symmetric solutions of black holes and wormholes are <lb/>obtained in Refs. 13–22. Power-law solutions of the scale factor are investigated <lb/>when the Universe enters a phantom phase and it is shown that such power-law <lb/>solutions may exist as cosmological model in the framework of f (T ) gravity. <lb/>The f (T ) gravity appears in cosmology as the source driving the inflation. <lb/> 15 <lb/> Also, it has been used as a theory that reproduces the acceleration of the Uni-<lb/>verse without the necessity of introducing dark energy. <lb/> 23  The contributions of the <lb/>cosmological perturbations of this theory have been studied. <lb/> 24  In gravitation, the <lb/>first model of black hole which has been analyzed was the BTZ. <lb/> 16  Recently, in the <lb/>framework of f (T ) gravity, several black holes and wormhole solutions with spher-<lb/>ical symmetry have been found in Refs. 25–40. Moreover, other analysis about <lb/>various themes are being investigated in the context of f (T ) gravity. <lb/> 41  Izumi et al. <lb/> have shown the existence of physical superluminal modes and a causality in the <lb/>Brans–Dicke type of extension of teleparallel gravity that includes f (T ) gravity <lb/>and teleparallel dark energy as special cases. <lb/> 42  Several examples from gauge field <lb/>theories to explain how such superluminal modes could arise have been provided. <lb/> 43 <lb/> It is the aim of the present work, within the framework of extended theory of <lb/>teleparallel gravity, f (T ), to find a charged axially symmetric solution. In Sec. 2, <lb/>a brief review of f (T ) theory is given. In Sec. 3, a tetrad field with six unknown <lb/>functions of the radial coordinate, r, and an azimuth angle θ is applied to the field <lb/>equation of TEGR, f (T ) = T . A solution to the field equation of TEGR is given <lb/>in Sec. 3. This solution is substituting into the tetrad and we generalize the angle <lb/> φ by an angle Φ which is a function of the radial coordinate r, azimuthal angle <lb/> θ and the polar angle φ, i.e. Φ = L(r, θ, φ) is provided. Application of the field <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550007-2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. D 2015.24. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> 2nd  Reading <lb/> November 25, 2014 12:56 WSPC/S0218-2718 <lb/>142-IJMPD <lb/>1550007 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Kerr–Newman solution in modified teleparallel theory of gravity <lb/></note>

			<body> equation of f (T ) to this tetrad, the one with generalized angle Φ, is given in Sec. 3. <lb/>A new nonvacuum, axially symmetric solution with three constants of integration <lb/>is derived in Sec. 3. In Sec. 4, we rewrite the derived solution as a local Lorentz <lb/>transformation, which depends on the generalized angle Φ, and a diagonal tetrad <lb/>of the Kerr–Newman spacetime. The final section is a summary of the results. <lb/> 2. Brief Review of f (T ) <lb/> In a spacetime having absolute parallelism the parallel vector field h  i <lb/> µ44  defines the <lb/>nonsymmetric affine connection: <lb/>Γ <lb/> µ <lb/>νρ <lb/> def. <lb/> = h  i <lb/>µ  h <lb/> i <lb/>ν, ρ  , <lb/> (1) <lb/>where <lb/> a  h  iµ, ν  = ∂  ν  h  iµ  = <lb/> ∂hiµ <lb/>∂x  ν  . <lb/>The curvature tensor defined by Γ <lb/> µ <lb/>νρ  , given by Eq. (1), is identically vanishing. <lb/>The metric tensor g  µν  is defined by: <lb/> g  µν <lb/> def. <lb/> = η  ij  h <lb/> i <lb/>µ  h <lb/> j <lb/>ν  , <lb/> (2) <lb/>with η  ij  = (−1, +1, +1, +1) is the metric of Minkowski spacetime. Defining the <lb/>torsion and the contortion components as: <lb/> T <lb/> µ <lb/>νρ <lb/> def. <lb/> = Γ <lb/> µ <lb/>ρν  − Γ <lb/> µ <lb/>νρ  = h  i <lb/>µ  (∂  ν  h <lb/> i <lb/>ρ  − ∂  ρ  h <lb/> i <lb/>ν  ), <lb/> K <lb/> µν <lb/>ρ <lb/> def. <lb/> = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(T <lb/> µν <lb/>ρ  − T <lb/> νµ <lb/>ρ  − T  ρ <lb/>µν  ), <lb/>(3) <lb/>where the contortion equal the difference between Weitzenböck and Levi-Civita <lb/>connection, i.e. K <lb/> µ <lb/>νρ  = Γ <lb/> µ <lb/>νρ  − { <lb/> µ <lb/>νρ  }. <lb/> The skew symmetric tensor S  µ <lb/>νρ  is defined as: <lb/> S  µ <lb/>νρ def. <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(K <lb/> νρ <lb/>µ  + δ <lb/> ν <lb/>µ  T <lb/> λρ <lb/>λ  − δ <lb/> ρ <lb/>µ  T <lb/> λν <lb/>λ  ). <lb/>(4) <lb/>The torsion scalar is defined as: <lb/> T <lb/> def. <lb/> = T <lb/> µ <lb/>νρ  S  µ <lb/>νρ  . <lb/> (5) <lb/>Similar to the f (R) theory, one can define the action of f (T ) theory as <lb/> L(h <lb/> a <lb/>µ  ) = <lb/> h <lb/> f (T ) <lb/>16π <lb/>+ L  em <lb/> d <lb/> 4  x, where h = <lb/> √ <lb/>−g = det(h <lb/> a <lb/>µ  ), <lb/> L  em  is the Lagrangian of electromagnetic field. (6) <lb/>We assume the relativistic units in which G = c = 1 and L  em  = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  F ∧ <lb/>  F = <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>4  g <lb/> µρ  g <lb/> νσ  F  µν  F  ρσ  is the Maxwell Lagrangian, while F = dA = (A  µ,ν  − A  ν,µ  )[dx <lb/> µ <lb/> ∧ <lb/> dx <lb/> ν  ], with A = A  µ  dx <lb/> µ  , is the electromagnetic potential 1-form. <lb/> 29  Similar to the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> a  We use the Latin indices i, j, . . . to label (co)frame components and the Greek indices α, β, . . . <lb/> for local holonomic spacetime coordinates. <lb/></note>

			<page> 1550007-3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. D 2015.24. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> 2nd  Reading <lb/>November 25, 2014 12:56 WSPC/S0218-2718 <lb/>142-IJMPD <lb/>1550007 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> G. G. L. Nashed <lb/></note>

			<body> f (R) theory, one can define the action of f (T ) theory as a function of the fields <lb/> h <lb/> a <lb/> µ  and by putting the variation of the function with respect to the field h <lb/> a <lb/>µ  to be <lb/>vanishing, one can obtain the following equations of motion <lb/> 17  : <lb/> S  µ <lb/>ρν  T  ,ρ  f (T )  T T  + [h <lb/> −1  h <lb/> a <lb/>µ  ∂  ρ  (hh  a <lb/>α  S  α <lb/>ρν  ) − T <lb/> α <lb/>λµ  S  α <lb/>νλ  ]f (T )  T  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>4 <lb/> δ <lb/> ν <lb/>µ  f (T ) <lb/>= −4πT <lb/> emν <lb/> µ  , <lb/> (7) <lb/> ∂  ν  ( <lb/> √ <lb/>−gF <lb/> µν  ) = 0, <lb/>(8) <lb/>where <lb/> T  ,ρ  = <lb/> ∂T <lb/>∂x  ρ  , f(T )  T  = <lb/> ∂f (T ) <lb/> ∂T <lb/>, f(T )  T T  = <lb/> ∂ <lb/> 2  f (T ) <lb/> ∂T  2 <lb/> and <lb/> T <lb/> emν <lb/> µ  = g  ρσ  F <lb/> µρ  F <lb/> νσ <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>4 <lb/> g <lb/> µν  g <lb/> λρ  g <lb/> σ  F  λλ  F  ρσ  , <lb/> is the energy-momentum tensor of electromagnetic field. <lb/>Now we are going to rewrite Eq. (7) in another form: The field equation (7) is <lb/>written in terms of the tetrad and its partial derivatives. This equation appears to <lb/>be different from Einstein&apos;s field equations. Following, <lb/> 32  one can obtain an equation <lb/>relating T with the Ricci scalar of the metric, R. These will make the equivalence <lb/>between teleparallel gravity and GR clear. On the other hand, the tetrad cannot <lb/>be eliminated completely in favor of the metric in Eq. (7), because of the lack <lb/>of local Lorentz symmetry. However, we will show that the latter can be brought <lb/>in a form that closely resembles Einstein&apos;s equation. This form is more suitable <lb/>for constructing analytic solutions in the f (T ) theory. To start writing the field <lb/>equations in a covariant version, we must replace partial derivatives in the tensors <lb/>by covariant derivatives compatible with the metric g  µν  , i.e. ∇  σ  where ∇  σ  g  µν  = 0. <lb/>Thus, Eq. (3) can be written as <lb/> T <lb/> µ <lb/>νρ  = h  a <lb/>µ  (∇  ν  h <lb/> a <lb/>ρ  − ∇  ρ  h <lb/> a <lb/>ν  ). <lb/>(9) <lb/>Using Eq. (9) in Eqs. (3) and (4) one obtain <lb/> K <lb/> µ <lb/>νρ  = h  a <lb/>µ <lb/> ∇  ρ  h <lb/> a <lb/>ν  , <lb/>S <lb/> µν <lb/>ρ  = η <lb/> ij  h  i <lb/>µ <lb/> ∇  ρ  h  j <lb/>ν  + δ <lb/> ν <lb/>ρ  η <lb/> ij  h  i <lb/>σ <lb/> ∇  σ  h  j <lb/>µ <lb/> − δ <lb/> µ <lb/>ρ  η <lb/> ij  h  i <lb/>σ <lb/> ∇  σ  h  j <lb/>ν  . <lb/> (10) <lb/>On the other hand, from the relation between Weitzenböck connection and the <lb/>Levi-Civita connection one can write the Riemann tensor of the Levi-Civita con-<lb/>nection, { <lb/> ρ <lb/>µν  }, in terms of the nonsymmetric connection, Γ <lb/> ρ <lb/>µν  , in the form <lb/> R <lb/> ρ <lb/>µλν  = ∂  λ  Γ <lb/> ρ <lb/>µν  − ∂  ν  Γ <lb/> ρ <lb/>µλ  + Γ <lb/> ρ <lb/>σλ  Γ <lb/> σ <lb/>µν  − Γ <lb/> ρ <lb/>σν  Γ <lb/> σ <lb/>µλ <lb/> = ∇  λ  K <lb/> ρ <lb/>µν  − ∇  ν  K <lb/> ρ <lb/>µλ  + K <lb/> ρ <lb/>σλ  K <lb/> σ <lb/>µν  − K <lb/> ρ <lb/>σν  K <lb/> σ <lb/>µλ  . <lb/> (11) <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550007-4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. D 2015.24. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> 2nd  Reading <lb/> November 25, 2014 12:56 WSPC/S0218-2718 <lb/>142-IJMPD <lb/>1550007 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Kerr–Newman solution in modified teleparallel theory of gravity <lb/></note>

			<body> The associated Ricci tensor can then be written as <lb/> R  µν  = ∇  ν  K <lb/> ρ <lb/>µρ  − ∇  ρ  K <lb/> ρ <lb/>µν  + K <lb/> ρ <lb/>σν  K <lb/> σ <lb/>µρ  − K <lb/> ρ <lb/>σρ  K <lb/> σ <lb/>µν  . <lb/> (12) <lb/>Now, by using K <lb/> σ <lb/>µν  given by Eq. (3) along with the relations K <lb/> (µν)σ  = T <lb/> µ(νσ)  = <lb/> S <lb/> µ(νσ)  = 0 and considering S <lb/> µ <lb/>ρµ  = 2K <lb/> µ <lb/>ρµ  = −T <lb/> µ <lb/>ρµ  one has <lb/> 32–46 <lb/> R  µν  = −∇ <lb/> λ  S  νλµ  − g  µν  ∇ <lb/> λ  T <lb/> ρ <lb/>λρ  − S <lb/> ρσ <lb/>µ  K  σρν  , <lb/>R = −T − 2∇ <lb/> µ  T <lb/> ρ <lb/>µρ  . <lb/> (13) <lb/>Equation (13) implies that the T and R differ only by a covariant divergence of a <lb/>spacetime vector. Therefore, the Einstein–Hilbert action and the teleparallel action <lb/>(i.e. L  TEGR  = <lb/> d <lb/> 4  x|e|T ) will both lead to the same field equations and are dynam-<lb/>ically equivalent theories. In Ref. 32, the authors have shown that this equivalence <lb/>is directly at the level of the field equations. By using the equations listed above <lb/>and after some algebraic manipulations, one obtain <lb/> G  µν  − <lb/> g  µν <lb/> 2 <lb/> T = −∇ <lb/> ρ  S  νρµ  − S <lb/> σρ <lb/>µ  K  ρσν  , <lb/> (14) <lb/>where G  µν  = R  µν  − <lb/> gµν <lb/> 2  R is the Einstein tensor. Finally, by using Eq. (14), the field <lb/>equations for f (T ) gravity, Eq. (7), can be rewritten in the form <lb/> f (T )  T  G  µν  + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(f (T ) − T f(T )  T  )g  µν  + S  µ <lb/>ρν  T  ,ρ  f (T )  T T  = 4πT <lb/> emν <lb/> µ  . <lb/> (15) <lb/>Equation (15) can be taken as the starting point of the f (T ) modified gravity <lb/>model, and it has a structure similar to the field equation of f (R) gravity. Note <lb/>that in the more general case with f (T )  = T the field equations are covariant form. <lb/>Nevertheless, the theory is not local Lorentz invariant. In case of f (T ) = T and <lb/>constant torsion, f (T  0  ), GR is recovered and field equations are covariant and the <lb/>theory is Lorentz invariant. <lb/> 3. Axially Symmetric Solution in f (T ) Gravity Theory <lb/> We assume that the manifold possesses six unknown functions has the form: <lb/> (h <lb/> i µ)  = <lb/> 0 <lb/> B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>@ <lb/> A  1  (r, θ) <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 <lb/> A  2  (r, θ) <lb/>A  3  (r, θ) sin θ sin φ <lb/>A  4  (r, θ) sin θ cos φ A  5  (r, θ) cos θ cos φ A  6  (r, θ, φ) sin φ sin θ <lb/> −A  3  (r, θ) sin θ cos φ A  4  (r, θ) sin θ sin φ A  5  (r, θ) cos θ sin φ −A  6  (r, θ) cos φ sin θ <lb/> 0 <lb/> A  4  (r, θ) cos θ <lb/> −A  5  (r, θ) sin θ <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>A <lb/> , <lb/> (16) <lb/>where A  i  (r, θ), i = 1, . . . , 6, are six unknown functions of the radial coordinate, r <lb/> and the azimuth coordinate θ. The origin of tetrad (16) comes from the fact: <lb/>(h <lb/> i <lb/>µ  ) = (Λ <lb/> i <lb/>j  )(h <lb/> j <lb/>µ  )  d  , <lb/> (17) <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550007-5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. D 2015.24. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> 2nd  Reading <lb/> November 25, 2014 12:56 WSPC/S0218-2718 <lb/>142-IJMPD <lb/>1550007 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> G. G. L. Nashed <lb/></note>

			<body> where <lb/>(h <lb/> i <lb/> µ  )  d  = <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> A  1  (r, θ) <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 <lb/> A  2  (r, θ) <lb/> 0 <lb/> A  4  (r, θ) <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/> A  5  (r, θ) <lb/> 0 <lb/> A  3  (r, θ) <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 <lb/> A  6  (r, θ) <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> , <lb/> (18) <lb/>is the diagonal tetrad of Eq. (16) and <lb/>(Λ <lb/> i <lb/>j  ) = <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> 1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 sinθ cos φ cos θ cos φ sin φ sin θ <lb/> 0 sinθ sin φ cos θ sin φ −cos φ sin θ <lb/> 0 <lb/>cosθ <lb/> −sin θ <lb/> 0 <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> , <lb/> (19) <lb/>is a rotation, i.e. so (3) and it satisfies <lb/>(Λ <lb/> i <lb/>j  )η  ik  (Λ <lb/> k <lb/>l  ) = η  jl  , <lb/> which is studied in Ref. 20. <lb/>The associated metric of tetrad (16) is given by <lb/> ds <lb/> 2  = −[A  1 <lb/>2  (r, θ) − A  3 <lb/>2  (r, θ) sin <lb/> 2  θ]dt <lb/> 2  + A  4 <lb/>2  (r, θ)dr <lb/> 2  + A  5 <lb/>2  (r, θ)dθ <lb/> 2 <lb/> + [A  6 <lb/>2  (r, θ) sin <lb/> 2  θ − A  2 <lb/>2  (r, θ)]dφ <lb/> 2 <lb/> + [A  3  (r, θ)A  6  (r, θ) sin <lb/> 2  θ − A  1  (r, θ)A  2  (r, θ)]dtdφ. <lb/> (20) <lb/>Applying tetrad field (16) to the field equations (15) when f (T ) ≡ T , we get a <lb/>solution in the form. <lb/> b,c <lb/> A  1  = <lb/>Σ <lb/> ρ <lb/>, A  2  = A  1  c  3  sin <lb/> 2  θ, A  3  = <lb/> c  3 <lb/> ρ <lb/>, <lb/>A  4  = <lb/>1 <lb/> A  1 <lb/> , A  5  = ρ, A  6  = <lb/> r <lb/> 2  + c  3 <lb/>2 <lb/> ρ <lb/>, <lb/> (21) <lb/>where Σ and ρ are defined by <lb/>Σ = <lb/> r  2  + c  1  r + c  2 <lb/>2  + c  3 <lb/>2  , ρ = <lb/> r  2  + c  3 <lb/>2  cos  2  θ, <lb/> (22) <lb/>where c  1  , c  2  and c  3  are three constants of integration. Using (21) in (20), we get <lb/> ds <lb/> 2  = αdt <lb/> 2 <lb/> − <lb/> ρ <lb/> 2 <lb/> Σ  2  dr <lb/> 2 <lb/> − ρ <lb/> 2  dθ <lb/> 2 <lb/> − α  1  dφ <lb/> 2 <lb/> − <lb/> [rc  1  − c  2 <lb/>2  ]c  3  sin <lb/> 2  θ <lb/>ρ  2 <lb/> dtdφ, <lb/> where α = 1 − <lb/> c  1  r − c  2 <lb/>2 <lb/> ρ  2 <lb/> and <lb/> α  1  = sin <lb/> 2  θ <lb/> r <lb/> 2  + c  3 <lb/>2 <lb/> − <lb/> 2[rc  1  − c  2 <lb/>2  ]c  3 <lb/>2  sin <lb/> 2  θ <lb/>ρ  2 <lb/> , (23) <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> b  For brevity we will write A  i  ≡ A  i  (r, θ). <lb/> c  The derivation of these calculations are checked by Maple &quot; 16 &quot; software. <lb/></note>

			<page> 1550007-6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. D 2015.24. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> 2nd  Reading <lb/> November 25, 2014 12:56 WSPC/S0218-2718 <lb/>142-IJMPD <lb/>1550007 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Kerr–Newman solution in modified teleparallel theory of gravity <lb/></note>

			<body> which is the Kerr–Newman spacetime <lb/> 47  provided that c  1  = 2M , c  2  = q and c  3  = a, <lb/> which are the gravitational mass, charge and rotation parameters, respectively. <lb/>Substituting Eq. (16), after using Eqs. (21) and (22), in Eq. (15) we get the following <lb/>nonvanishing components of the energy-momentum tensors <lb/>4πT <lb/> em0 <lb/>0  = −4πT <lb/> em3 <lb/>3  = − <lb/> c  2 <lb/>2  (r <lb/> 2  + c  3 <lb/>2  [2 − cos <lb/> 2  θ]) <lb/> 2ρ  6 <lb/> , 4πT <lb/> em1 <lb/>1  = − <lb/> c  2 <lb/>2 <lb/> 2ρ  4  , <lb/> 4πT <lb/> em2 <lb/>2  = <lb/> c  2 <lb/>2 <lb/> 2ρ  4  , 4πT <lb/> em3 <lb/>0  = <lb/> c  2 <lb/>2  c  3 <lb/> ρ  6  , 4πT <lb/> em0 <lb/>3  = − <lb/> c  2 <lb/>2  c  3  sin <lb/> 2  θ(r <lb/> 2  + c  3 <lb/>2  ) <lb/> ρ  6 <lb/> . <lb/> (24) <lb/>Equation (24) shows that the energy-momentum tensor depends on the constant <lb/> c  2  , i.e. charge parameter q and when it is vanishing the components of the energy-<lb/>momentum-tensor are also vanishing. <lb/>Solution (21) is a solution to TEGR, i.e. f (T ) = T but not for f (T ) theory. <lb/>Therefore, to find an analytic solution within f (T ) gravitational theories we need <lb/>to parameterize the angle φ, i.e. makes the angle φ function of the radial coordinate <lb/> r, azimuthal angle θ and the polar angle φ, L(r, θ, φ). Then we calculate the tor-<lb/>sion scalar which will be a partial differential equation of one unknown L(r, θ, φ). <lb/> From this differential equation, we can put a constraint on the scalar torsion to be <lb/>constant. Let us explain this procedure in detail: By substituting solution (21) in <lb/>the tetrad field (16) we get <lb/>(h <lb/> i <lb/> µ  )  1  = <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> Σ <lb/> ρ <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>Σc  3  sin <lb/> 2  θ <lb/>ρ <lb/>c  3  sin θ sin Φ <lb/> ρ <lb/>ρ sin θ cos Φ <lb/>Σ <lb/> ρ cos θ cos Φ <lb/>(r <lb/> 2  + c  3 <lb/>2  ) sin θ sin Φ <lb/> ρ <lb/> − <lb/> c  3  sin θ cos Φ <lb/> ρ <lb/>ρ sin θ sin Φ <lb/>Σ <lb/> ρ cos θ sin Φ − <lb/> (r <lb/> 2  + c  3 <lb/>2  ) sin θ cos Φ <lb/> ρ <lb/> 0 <lb/> − <lb/> ρ cos θ <lb/> Σ <lb/> ρ sin θ <lb/> 0 <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> , <lb/> (25) <lb/>where Φ is a generalized function of the coordinates r, θ and φ, i.e. Φ = L(r, θ, φ). <lb/> Using Eq. (25) in Eq. (5) we get <lb/> h = ρ <lb/> 2  sin θ, <lb/>T = <lb/>2 <lb/>Σρ  6 <lb/> L  φ  {ρ <lb/> 4  (c  1  − r + Σ)} + (r − c  1  )ρ <lb/> 4 <lb/> − Σ(ρ[r <lb/> 2 <lb/> − c  3 <lb/>2  cos <lb/> 2  θ] + r <lb/> 2  c  2 <lb/>2 <lb/> − c  3 <lb/>2  (4c  1  r − c  2 <lb/>2  ) cos <lb/> 2  θ) <lb/> . <lb/> (26) <lb/>Equation (26) shows that the scalar torsion depends on the radial coordinate r, <lb/> azimuthal angle θ and the polar angle φ, and therefore so does the derivatives of <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550007-7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. D 2015.24. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> 2nd  Reading <lb/> November 25, 2014 12:56 WSPC/S0218-2718 <lb/>142-IJMPD <lb/>1550007 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> G. G. L. Nashed <lb/></note>

			<body> the scalar torsion. These derivatives have the form: <lb/> T <lb/>  = <lb/> ∂T <lb/>∂r <lb/> = <lb/>2 <lb/>Σ  3  ρ  8  {4Σ <lb/> 3 <lb/> {rρ <lb/> 4  L  φ  + c  3 <lb/>4  cos <lb/> 4  θ(2c  1  − 3r) <lb/> − c  3 <lb/>2  cos <lb/> 2  θ(2r <lb/> 2  + 10c  1  r − 4c  2 <lb/>2  ) + 2r <lb/> 3  c  2 <lb/>2 <lb/> − r <lb/> 5 <lb/> } <lb/>− ρ <lb/> 4  (1 + L  φ  )(2c  3 <lb/>2  cos <lb/> 2  θ[c  1 <lb/>2 <lb/> − c  2 <lb/>2 <lb/> − c  3 <lb/>2  ] <lb/>+ 2r[2r <lb/> 3 <lb/> − 6c  1  r <lb/> 2  + r{c  1 <lb/>2  + c  2 <lb/>2  + c  3 <lb/>2 <lb/> } − 2c  1  (c  2 <lb/>2  + c  3 <lb/>2  )])}, <lb/> T  θ  = <lb/> ∂T <lb/>∂θ <lb/> = <lb/>2c  2 <lb/>2  sin 2θ <lb/>Σρ  8 <lb/> [Σ{ρ <lb/> L <lb/>φ  − c  3 <lb/>4  cos <lb/> 4  θ − 2c  3 <lb/>2  cos <lb/> 2  θ(4rc  1  − r <lb/> 2 <lb/> − c  2 <lb/>2  ) <lb/>+ r <lb/> 2  (3r <lb/> 2  + 4rc  1  − 4c  2 <lb/>2  )} + ρ <lb/> 4  (1 + L  φ  )(c  1  − r)], <lb/>T  φ  = <lb/> ∂T <lb/>∂φ <lb/> = <lb/>2L  φφ  (r − c  1  − Σ) <lb/>Σρ  2 <lb/> . <lb/> (27) <lb/>If the derivatives of the torsion scalar are vanishing then the last term in the left-<lb/>hand side of the field equation (15) is vanishing. Then from Eq. (27) we get <lb/> L(r, θ, φ) = − <lb/> φ <lb/> 4(c  1  − r + Σ)[c  3 <lb/>2  cos 2θ + 2r  2  + c  3 <lb/>2  ]  2 <lb/> × (Σ[c  3 <lb/>4  cos <lb/> 2  2θ{T  0  c  3 <lb/>2  [cos 2θ + 3] − 4 + 6r <lb/> 2  T  0  } <lb/> + c  3 <lb/>2  cos 2θ[3T  0  c  3 <lb/>4  + 4c  3 <lb/>2  (3T  0  r <lb/> 2 <lb/> − 2) <lb/>+ 4(3T  0  r <lb/> 4 <lb/> − 8c  1  r + 2c  2 <lb/>2  )] + c  3 <lb/>2  [c  3 <lb/>4  T  0  + 2(3T  0  r <lb/> 2 <lb/> − 2)c  3 <lb/>2 <lb/> + 4(3T  0  r <lb/> 4 <lb/> − 8c  1  r + 2c  2 <lb/>2  )] + 8r <lb/> 2  [r <lb/> 4  T  0  − 2c  2 <lb/>2  + 2r <lb/> 2  ]] <lb/>+ 8(c  1  − r)[c  3 <lb/>2  cos 2θ + r <lb/> 2  + c  3 <lb/>2  ] <lb/> 2  ), <lb/>(28) <lb/>where T  0  is a constant. Substituting the value of L(r, θ, φ) given by Eq. (28) in <lb/>Eq. (26), we get a constant value of the scalar torsion, T = T  0  and consequently <lb/>its derivatives are vanishing. Substituting Eq. (25), using Eq. (28), in Eq. (15) we <lb/>get the same nonvanishing components of the following energy-momentum tensors <lb/>given by Eq. (24) provided that <lb/> f (const.) = T  0  , f  T  (const.) = 1, f  T T  = 0. <lb/>(29) <lb/>The constraints given by Eq. (29) ensure that the field equation (15) coincides with <lb/>the GR field equations. The tetrad field (25) is axially symmetric, i.e. it is invariant <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550007-8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Int.  J. Mod. Phys. D 2015.24. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> 2nd  Reading <lb/> November 25, 2014 12:56 WSPC/S0218-2718 <lb/>142-IJMPD <lb/>1550007 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Kerr–Newman solution in modified teleparallel theory of gravity <lb/></note>

			<body> under the transformation: <lb/>¯ <lb/>Φ → Φ + δΦ, ¯ <lb/> h <lb/> 0 <lb/> i  → h <lb/> 0 <lb/> i  , ¯ <lb/> h <lb/> 1 <lb/> i  → h <lb/> 1 <lb/> i  cos δΦ − h <lb/> 2 <lb/> i  sin δΦ, <lb/> ¯ h <lb/> 2 <lb/> i  → h <lb/> 1 <lb/> i  sin δΦ + h <lb/> 2 <lb/> i  cos δΦ, ¯ <lb/> h <lb/> 3 <lb/> i  → h <lb/> 3 <lb/> i  . <lb/> (30) <lb/> 4. Decomposition of Derived Solution <lb/> In this section, we are going to study the internal properties of tetrad (25). <lb/>Now, we use Eq. (17), i.e. (h <lb/> i <lb/>µ  )  1  = (Λ <lb/> i <lb/>j  )  1  (h <lb/> j <lb/>µ  )  dd  , to rewrite tetrad field (25), <lb/>where <lb/>(Λ <lb/> i <lb/>j  )  1  = <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> Σ <lb/> r  2  − 2M + a  2  cos  2  θ + q  2 <lb/> 0 <lb/> −a sin θ sin Φ <lb/> r  2  − 2M + a  2  cos  2  θ + q  2 <lb/> − sin θ cos Φ <lb/> a sin θ cos Φ <lb/> r  2  − 2M + a  2  cos  2  θ + q  2 <lb/> sin θ sin Φ <lb/>0 <lb/>c o s θ <lb/> 0 <lb/> a sin θ(r <lb/> 2 <lb/> − 4M r + a <lb/> 2  cos <lb/> 2  θ + 2q <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> ρ  2 <lb/> r  2  − 2M + a  2  cos  2  θ + q  2 <lb/> cos θ cos Φ <lb/> −α  2  sin Φ <lb/> ρ  2  Σ <lb/> r  2  − 2M + a  2  cos  2  θ + q  2 <lb/> cos θ sin Φ <lb/> α  2  cos Φ <lb/> ρ  2  Σ <lb/> r  2  − 2M + a  2  cos  2  θ + q  2 <lb/> − sin θ <lb/> 0 <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> , (31) <lb/>and <lb/>(h <lb/> j <lb/>mu  )  dd <lb/> = <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> − <lb/> r  2  − 2M + a  2  cos  2  θ + q  2 <lb/> ρ <lb/> 0 0 <lb/> a(2M r − q <lb/> 2  ) sin <lb/> 2  θ <lb/>ρ <lb/> r  2  − 2M + a  2  cos  2  θ + q  2 <lb/> 0 <lb/> ρ <lb/> Σ <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 ρ <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 0 <lb/>sin θρΣ <lb/> r  2  − 2M + a  2  cos  2  θ + q  2 <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> , <lb/> (32) <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550007-9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. D 2015.24. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> 2nd  Reading <lb/> November 25, 2014 12:56 WSPC/S0218-2718 <lb/>142-IJMPD <lb/>1550007 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> G. G. L. Nashed <lb/></note>

			<body> where <lb/> α  2  = a <lb/> 2  ρ <lb/> 2 <lb/> − a <lb/> 2  (2M r − q <lb/> 2  )(1 + sin <lb/> 2  θ) + r <lb/> 2  Σ <lb/> 2  . <lb/> (33) <lb/>Equation (31) is a local Lorentz transformation. <lb/>Equation (32) has the same metric of tetrad field (25). We call Eq. (32) the <lb/>diagonal form of tetrad field (25). <lb/> 5. Main Results and Discussion <lb/> Modifications of gravitational theories succeeded partially in solving some recent <lb/>observational problems. Among these modifications is the f (T ) gravitational the-<lb/>ories. In the framework of such modification, it is not an easy task to derive ana-<lb/>lytical solutions. In this paper, we have studied the nonvacuum case of f (T ), i.e. <lb/> T <lb/> emν <lb/> mu  = 0. The field equations in the case f (T ) = T , have been applied to a <lb/>nondiagonal, axially symmetric, tetrad field having six unknown functions of radial <lb/>coordinate, r and azimuthal coordinate θ. The resulting nonlinear partial differential <lb/>equations are solved and we have derived an analytical solution whose associated <lb/>metric gave Kerr–Newman spacetime. This solution is not a solution to the f (T ) <lb/>field equations. Therefore, we have substituted the derived solution in the tetrad <lb/>field and rewrite this tetrad in terms of an angle Φ which is a function of the radial <lb/>coordinate r, azimuthal angle θ and the polar angle φ i.e., Φ = L(r, θ, φ). We have <lb/>applied this tetrad field, the one with the generalized angle φ, to the field equa-<lb/>tions of f (T ) and have calculated its scalar torsion T and its derivatives. To find a <lb/>solution to the field equations of f (T ) gravitational theory we have put the scalar <lb/>torsion equal constant, T = T  0  and have solved the differential equation. We have <lb/>obtained a value of L(r, θ, φ) which makes the torsion scalar equal constant. This <lb/>condition, T = T  0  , makes the term which contains f  T T  of the field equation of f (T ) <lb/>to be vanishing and therefore, we obtained a solution to the field equations of f (T ) <lb/>provided that Eq. (29) is satisfied. In addition, this solution has axial symmetry, <lb/>i.e. the components of its tetrad field are invariant under the change of the angle Φ. <lb/>The associated metric of the solutions of f (T ) = T or of f (T ) gave Kerr–Newman <lb/>spacetime. <lb/>To shed light on the internal construction of the derived solution we have written <lb/>it as a local Lorentz transformation and a diagonal tetrad <lb/> d  . The local Lorentz <lb/>transformation is related to so(3). This local Lorentz transformation depends on <lb/>the generalized angle Φ, rotation and charge parameters and it reduces to the one <lb/>studied in Refs. 19, 21 and 22 when these parameters vanished and Φ = φ. <lb/> The way of writing tetrad field (25) as a local Lorentz transformation and diag-<lb/>onal one as given by Eqs. (31) and (32) is not unique. For example: If the form of <lb/>tetrad field (32) is changed then the form of (31) changes. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> d  Diagonal means the square root of the metric. <lb/></note>

			<page> 1550007-10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. D 2015.24. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> 2nd  Reading <lb/> November 25, 2014 12:56 WSPC/S0218-2718 <lb/>142-IJMPD <lb/>1550007 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Kerr–Newman solution in modified teleparallel theory of gravity <lb/></note>

			<body> Let us explain this by rewriting tetrad (25) with the help of (17) in the form <lb/>(h <lb/> i <lb/> µ  )  1  = (Λ <lb/> α <lb/>β  )  2  (h <lb/> γ <lb/>i  )  ddd  , <lb/> (34) <lb/>where <lb/>(Λ <lb/> β <lb/>γ  )  2  = <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> r <lb/> 2  + a <lb/> 2 <lb/> α  3 <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 <lb/> a sin θΣ <lb/>α  3 <lb/> −aΣ sin θ sin Φ <lb/> α  3 <lb/> cos Φ sin θ cos θ cos Φ <lb/> −(r <lb/> 2  + a <lb/> 2  ) sin Φ <lb/> α  3 <lb/> aΣ sin θ cos Φ <lb/> α  3 <lb/> sin Φ sin θ cos θ sin Φ <lb/>(r <lb/> 2  + a <lb/> 2  ) cos Φ <lb/> α  3 <lb/> 0 <lb/>c o s θ <lb/> − sin θ <lb/> 0 <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> (35) <lb/>and <lb/>(h <lb/> j <lb/>µ  )  ddd  = <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> ρΣ <lb/>α  3 <lb/> 0 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/> ρ <lb/> Σ <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 ρ <lb/> 0 <lb/>(2M r − q <lb/> 2  )a sin θ <lb/>ρα  3 <lb/> 0 0 <lb/> α  3  sin θ <lb/>ρ <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> , <lb/> (36) <lb/>where <lb/> α  3  = <lb/> r  4  + a  2  (2M r − q  2  + r  2  ) + a  2  cos  2  θΣ  2  . <lb/> (37) <lb/>Equation (35) is local Lorentz transformations. <lb/>To sum up, solution (28) justifies that any GR solution remains valid in f (T ) <lb/>theories having f  T  (const.) = 1 whenever the geometry admits a tetrad field with <lb/>constant scalar torsion, T . <lb/> 16 <lb/> Appendix: Calculations of Torsion and Contortion Tensors of <lb/>Solution (9) <lb/> Using solution (9), the nonvanishing components of the torsion tensor have the <lb/>form: <lb/> T <lb/> 0 <lb/>01  = <lb/> M (a <lb/> 2 <lb/> − r <lb/> 2  ) + rq <lb/> 2 <lb/> ρ  2  Σ  2 <lb/> , <lb/>T <lb/> 0 <lb/>13  = − <lb/> a sin <lb/> 2  θ[r <lb/> 2  (r − M ) + r(2q <lb/> 2  + a <lb/> 2  ) + M a <lb/> 2 <lb/> − ρ <lb/> 2  Σ] <lb/> ρ  2  Σ  2 <lb/> , <lb/>T <lb/> 0 <lb/>23  = <lb/> a sin 2θ(ρ <lb/> 2  + r <lb/> 2  + a <lb/> 2  ) <lb/>2ρ  2 <lb/> , T <lb/> 1 <lb/>12  = <lb/> a <lb/> 2  sin 2θ <lb/>2ρ  2  , T <lb/> 1 <lb/>30  = <lb/> −a sin <lb/> 2  θΣ <lb/>ρ  2 <lb/> , <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550007-11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. D 2015.24. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> 2nd  Reading <lb/> November 25, 2014 12:56 WSPC/S0218-2718 <lb/>142-IJMPD <lb/>1550007 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> G. G. L. Nashed <lb/></note>

			<body> T <lb/> 2 <lb/> 12  = − <lb/> rΣ − ρ <lb/> 2 <lb/> ρ  2  Σ <lb/> , T <lb/> 2 <lb/>30  = <lb/> −a sin 2θ <lb/>2ρ  2  , <lb/>T <lb/> 3 <lb/>13  = <lb/> a <lb/> 2  (M − r) cos <lb/> 2  θ − rq <lb/> 2  + M r <lb/> 2 <lb/> − M a <lb/> 2 <lb/> − r <lb/> 3  + ρ <lb/> 2  Σ <lb/> ρ  2  Σ  2 <lb/> , <lb/>T <lb/> 3 <lb/>10  = − <lb/> a(M − r) <lb/> Σ  2  ρ  2  , T <lb/> 3 <lb/>20  = <lb/> a cot θ <lb/>ρ  2  . <lb/> (A.1) <lb/>The nonvanishing components of the contortion tensor have the form: <lb/> K <lb/> 01 <lb/>0  = <lb/>(r <lb/> 2  + a <lb/> 2  )(M r <lb/> 2 <lb/> − rq <lb/> 2 <lb/> − M a <lb/> 2  cos <lb/> 2  θ) <lb/>ρ  6 <lb/> , K <lb/> 02 <lb/>0  = − <lb/> a <lb/> 2  sin 2θ(2M r − q <lb/> 2  ) <lb/>2ρ  6 <lb/> , <lb/>K <lb/> 01 <lb/>3  = <lb/> a sin <lb/> 2  θ(a <lb/> 2  cos <lb/> 2  θ[a <lb/> 2  M − M r <lb/> 2  + rq <lb/> 2  ] <lb/> −r[M a <lb/> 2  r − 2r <lb/> 2  q <lb/> 2  + 3M r <lb/> 3 <lb/> − a <lb/> 2  q <lb/> 2  ] + ρ <lb/> 4  Σ) <lb/> ρ  6 <lb/> , <lb/>K <lb/> 02 <lb/>3  = <lb/> a sin 2θ(a <lb/> 2  cos <lb/> 2  θ[2r <lb/> 2  + q <lb/> 2 <lb/> − 2M r + +a <lb/> 2  cos <lb/> 2  θ] + r <lb/> 4  + [2M r − q <lb/> 2  ]a <lb/> 2  ) <lb/>2ρ  6 <lb/> , <lb/>K <lb/> 03 <lb/>1  = − <lb/> ar <lb/>ρ  2  Σ  2  , K <lb/> 03 <lb/>2  = <lb/> −a cot θ <lb/>ρ  2  , K <lb/> 12 <lb/>1  = − <lb/> a <lb/> 2  sin 2θ <lb/>2ρ  4  , <lb/>K <lb/> 12 <lb/>2  = <lb/>Σ[ρ <lb/> 2 <lb/> − rΣ] <lb/>ρ  4 <lb/> , <lb/>K <lb/> 13 <lb/>3  = <lb/> a <lb/> 2  cos <lb/> 2  θ[M r <lb/> 2 <lb/> − 2r <lb/> 3 <lb/> − a <lb/> 2  M + a <lb/> 2  cos <lb/> 2  θ(M − r)] <lb/> − r[r <lb/> 4 <lb/> − 2M r <lb/> 3  + r <lb/> 2  q <lb/> 2 <lb/> − M ra <lb/> 2  + a <lb/> 2  q <lb/> 2  ] + ρ <lb/> 4  Σ <lb/> ρ  6 <lb/> , <lb/>K <lb/> 13 <lb/>0  = − <lb/> a(rq <lb/> 2  + M [a <lb/> 2  cos <lb/> 2  θ − r <lb/> 2  ]) <lb/> ρ  6 <lb/> , K <lb/> 21 <lb/>1  = <lb/> a <lb/> 2  sin 2θ <lb/>2ρ  4  , <lb/>K <lb/> 23 <lb/>3  = <lb/> −a <lb/> 2  sin 2θ(2M r − q <lb/> 2  ) <lb/>2ρ  6 <lb/> , K <lb/> 23 <lb/>0  = − <lb/> a cot θ(2M r − q <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> ρ  6 <lb/> . <lb/> (A.2) <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgment <lb/> This work is partially supported by the Egyptian Ministry of Scientific Research <lb/>under project No. 24-2-12. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. WMAP Collab. (E. Komatsu et al.), Astrophys. J. Suppl. 192 (2011) 18; WMAP <lb/>Collab. (G. Hinshaw et al.), Astrophys. J. Suppl. 208 (2013) 19. <lb/>2. Planck Collab. (P. Ade et al.), Astron. Astrophys. 21 (2013) 1011, arXiv:1303.5076. <lb/>3. A. G. Riess et al., Astrophys. J. 699 (2009) 539. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 1550007-12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. D 2015.24. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> 2nd  Reading <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> November 25, 2014 12:56 WSPC/S0218-2718 <lb/>142-IJMPD <lb/>1550007 <lb/> Kerr–Newman solution in modified teleparallel theory of gravity <lb/> 4. Supernova Cosmology Project (M. Kowalski et al.), Astrophys. J. 686 (2008) 749. <lb/>5. H. Lampeitl et al., Mon. Not. Roy. Astron. Soc. 401 (2009) 2331. <lb/>6. T. Padmanabhan, Phys. Rep. 380 (2003) 235; P. J. E. Peebles and B. Ratra, Rev. <lb/>Mod. Phys. 75 (2003) 559; C. G. Tsagas, A. Challinor and R. Maartens, Phys. Rep. <lb/> 465 (2008) 61; M. Li, X. D. Li, S. Wang and Y. Wang, Commun. Theor. Phys. 56 <lb/> (2011) 525; K. Karami, T. Najafi and A. Abdolmaleki, arXiv:1401.7549v. <lb/>7. V. Sahni, Class. Quantum Grav. 19 (2002) 3435; E. J. Copeland, M. Sami and S. Tsu-<lb/>jikawa, Int. J. Mod. Phys. D 15 (2006) 1753; T. Padmanabhan, Gen. Relativ. Gravit. <lb/> 40 (2008) 529. <lb/>8. S. Nojiri and S. D. Odintsov, Phys. Rep. 505 (2011) 59; S. Nojiri and S. D. Odintsov, <lb/> ECONF C 0602061 (2006) 06; Int. J. Geom. Methods Mod. Phys. 4 (2007) 115. <lb/>9. G. Cognola, E. Elizalde, S. Nojiri, S. D. Odintsov and S. Zerbini, Phys. Rev. D 73 <lb/> (2006) 084007. <lb/>10. S. D. Odintsov, T. Harko, F. S. N. Lobo and S. Nojiri, Phys. Rev. D 84 (2011) 024020. <lb/>11. I. Antoniadis, J. Rizos and K. Tamvais, Nucl. Phys. B 415 (1994) 497. <lb/>12. V. C. de Andrade, L. C. T. Guillen and J. G. Pereira, arXiv:gr-qc/0011087. <lb/>13. M. H. Daouda, M. E. Rodrigues and M. J. S. Houndjo, Eur. Phys. J. C 72 (2012) <lb/>1890. <lb/>14. C. Møller, Mat. Fys. Skr. Dan. Vid. Selsk. 1 (1961) 10; C. Pellegrini and J. Plebanski, <lb/> Mat. Fys. Skr. Dan. Vid. Selsk. 2 (1963) 4; C. Møller, K. Dan. Vidensk. Selsk. Mat. <lb/>Fys. Skr. 89 (1978)13; K. Hayashi and T. Nakano, Prog. Theor. Phys. 38 (1967) 491; <lb/>K. Hayashi, Nuovo Cimento A 16 (1973) 639; K. Hayashi, Phys. Lett. B 69 (1977) <lb/>441; K. Hayashi and T. Shirafuji, Phys. Rev. D 19 (1979) 3524; T. Shirafuji, G. G. L. <lb/>Nashed and K. Hayashi, Prog. Theor. Phys. 95 (1996) 665; M. I. Wanas, Amer. Inst. <lb/>Phys. Conf. Ser. 1115 (2009) 218; M. I. Wanas, Adv. High Ener. Phys. 2012 (2012) <lb/>Article ID 752613; M. I. Wanas and H. A. Hassan, Int. J. Theoret. Phys. (2014) 1. <lb/>15. R. Ferraro and F. Fiorini, Phys. Rev. D 75 (2007) 084031; R. Ferraro and F. Fiorini, <lb/> Phys. Rev. D 78 (2008) 124019. <lb/>16. R. Ferraro and F. Fiorini, Int. J. Mod. Phys. Conf. Ser. 3 (2011) 227. <lb/>17. G. R. Bengochea and R. Ferraro, Phys. Rev. D 79 (2009) 124019. <lb/>18. M. H. Daouda, M. E. Rodrigues and M. J. S. Houndjo, Eur. Phys. J. C 71 (2011) <lb/>1817. <lb/>19. G. G. L. Nashed, Chin Phys. Lett. 29 (2012) 050402. <lb/>20. G. G. L. Nashed, Gen. Relativ. Gravit. 45 (2013) 1878. <lb/>21. C. G. Böhmer, A. Mussa and N. Tamanini, Class. Quantum Grav. 28 (2011) 245020. <lb/>22. G. G. L. Nashed, Phys. Rev. D 88 (2013) 104034. <lb/>23. E. V. Linder, Phys. Rev. D 81 (2010) 127301. <lb/>24. S.-H. Chen, J. B. Dent, S. Dutta and E. N. Saridakis, Phys. Rev. D 83 (2011) 023508. <lb/>25. T. Wang, Phys. Rev. D 84 (2011) 024042. <lb/>26. P. Wu and H. W. Yu, Eur. Phys. J. C 71 (2011) 1552. <lb/>27. K. Bamba, C.-Q. Geng, C.-C. Lee and L.-W. Luo, J. Cosmol. Astropart. Phys. 1101 <lb/> (2011) 021. <lb/>28. P. Wu and H. W. Yu, Phys. Lett. B 693 (2010) 415. <lb/>29. S. Capozziello, P. A. González, E. N. Saridakis and Y. Vásquez, J. High Energy Phys. <lb/> 1302 (2013) 039. <lb/>30. J. B. Dent, S. Dutta and E. N. Saridakis, J. Cosmol. Astropart. Phys. 1101 (2011) <lb/>009. <lb/>31. R. Zheng and Q.-G. Huang, J. Cosmol. Astropart. Phys. 1103 (2011) 002. <lb/>32. B. Li, T. P. Sotiriou and J. D. Barrow, Phys. Rev. D 83 (2011) 104017. <lb/>33. T. P. Sotiriou, B. Li and J. D. Barrow, Phys. Rev. D 83 (2011) 104030. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 1550007-13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. D 2015.24. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> 2nd  Reading <lb/> November 25, 2014 12:56 WSPC/S0218-2718 <lb/>142-IJMPD <lb/>1550007 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> G. G. L. Nashed <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> 34. B. Li, T. P. Sotiriou and J. D. Barrow, Phys. Rev. D 83 (2011) 064035. <lb/>35. K. Izumi and Y. Chin Ong, J. Cosmol. Astropart. Phys. 06 (2013) 029. <lb/>36. Y.-F. Cai, S.-H. Chen, J. B. Dent, S. Dutta and E. N. Saridakis, Class. Quantum <lb/>Grav. 28 (2011) 215011. <lb/>37. A. Einstein, Sitzungsber. Preuss. Akad. Wiss. Phys. Math. Kl. 217 (1930) 401. <lb/>38. R. Aldrovandi and J. G. Pereira, An Introduction to Teleparallel Gravity, Instituto de <lb/>Fisica Teorica, UNSEP, Sao Paulo, http://www.ift.unesp.br/gcg/tele.pdf. <lb/>39. M. H. Daouda, M. E. Rodrigues and M. J. S. Houndjo, Eur. Phys. J. C 72 (2012) <lb/>1890. <lb/>40. M. H. Daouda, M. E. Rodrigues and M. J. S. Houndjo, Phys. Lett. B 715 (2012) 241. <lb/>41. J. Yang, Y.-L. Li, Y. Zhong and Y. Li, Phys. Rev. D 85 (2012) 084033; K. Karami <lb/>and A. Abdolmaleki, JCAP 04 (2012) 007; K. Atazadeh and F. Darabi, Eur. Phys. <lb/>J. C 72 (2012) 2016; H. Wei, X.-J. G. and L.-F. Wang, Phys. Lett. B 707 (2012) 298; <lb/>K. Karami, A. Abdolmaleki, Phys. Rev. D 88 (2013) 084034; N. L. Youssef and A. M. <lb/>Sid-Ahmed, Rep. Math. Phys. 60 (2007) 39; N. L. Youssef and A. M. Sid-Ahmed, Int. <lb/>J. Geom. Meth. Mod. Phys. 5 (2008), 1109; M. I. Wanas, N. L. Youssef and A. M. <lb/>Sid-Ahmed, Class. Quant. Grav. 27 (2010) 045005; N. L. Youssef and W. A. Elsayed, <lb/> Rep. Math. Phys. 72 (2013) 1; P. A. Gonzalez, E. N. Saridakis and Y. Vasquez, JHEP <lb/> 2012 (2012) 53; S. Capozziello, V. F. Cardone, H. Farajollahi and A. Ravanpak, Phys. <lb/>Rev. D 84 (2011) 043527; R.-X. Miao, M. Li and Y.-G. Miao, JCAP 2011 (2011) 033; <lb/>X.-H. Meng and Y.-B. Wang, Eur. Phys. J. C 71 (2011) 1755; H. Wei, X.-P. Ma and <lb/>H.-Y. Qi, Phys. Lett. B 703 (2011) 74; M. Li, R.-X. Miao and Y.-G. Miao, JHEP <lb/> 1107 (2011) 108; S. Chattopadhyay and U. Debnath, Int. J. Mod. Phys. D 20 (2011) <lb/>1135; P. B. Khatua, S. Chakraborty and U. Debnath, arXiv:1105.3393; R.-J. Yang, <lb/> Europhys. Lett. 93 (2011) 60001; C. G. Böehmer, A. Mussa and N. Tamanini, Class. <lb/>Quant. Grav. 28 (2011) 245020. <lb/>42. K. Izumi, Je-Añ Gu and Y. Chin Ong, Phys. Rev. D 89 (2014) 084025. <lb/>43. Y. Chin Ong, K. Izumi, J. M. Nester and P. Chen, Phys. Rev. D 88 (2013) 024019. <lb/>44. R. Weitzenböck, Invariance Theorie, Nordhoff, Gronin-Gen (1923). <lb/>45. Di Liu and M. J. Reboucas, Phys. Rev. D 86 (2012) 083515. <lb/>46. K. Atazadeh and M. Mousavi, Eur. Phys. J. C 73 (2013) 2272. <lb/>47. G. G. L. Nashed, Mod. Phys. Lett. A 22 (2007) 1047. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 1550007-14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. D 2015.24. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. </note>


	</text>
</tei>
