<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> December 30, 2014 16:10 <lb/>MPLA <lb/>S0217732315500054 page 1 <lb/> Modern Physics Letters A <lb/>Vol. 30, No. 1 (2015) 1550005 (13 pages) <lb/>c <lb/> World Scientific Publishing Company <lb/>DOI: 10.1142/S0217732315500054 <lb/> Analysis on modified Chaplygin gas as dark energy model <lb/> Ya-Bo Wu  *  , Cheng-Yuan Zhang, Jian-Bo Lu, Jun-Wang Lu, Xue Zhang, <lb/>Qing-Mei Qi and Bi Fan <lb/> Department of Physics, Liaoning Normal University, Dalian 116029, P. R. China <lb/>  *  ybwu61@163.com <lb/> Received 26 September 2014 <lb/>Revised 4 November 2014 <lb/>Accepted 4 November 2014 <lb/>Published 2 January 2015 <lb/>In this paper, we will continue to study the modified Chaplygin gas (MCG) based on <lb/>Ref. 25. Concretely, we not only discuss both the change rates of the energy densities and <lb/>the Hubble parameter H(z) as a function of the model parameters, which is compared <lb/>and consistent with the related data in Ref. 27, but also perform the Om diagnostic <lb/>in order to geometrically differentiate the MCG model from the ΛCDM, GCG and CG <lb/>models. Moreover, we plot the evolutionary trajectories of MCG model with different <lb/>interaction terms in Om planes, and find that the coupling intensity b  2  plays an impor-<lb/>tant role in the MCG model. Furthermore, we also reconstruct the potential of MCG <lb/>scalar field as well as the dynamics of the scalar field according to the evolution of the <lb/>MCG dark energy. It is worth stressing that the results given by us can include the ones <lb/>without interaction as the special cases. <lb/> Keywords: Modified Chaplygin gas; dark energy; Om diagnostic. <lb/>PACS Nos.: 98.80.-k, 98.80.Jk <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> More recently, new evidence from astrophysics and cosmology has revealed a quite <lb/>unexpected picture of the universe. Precisely, the latest datasets such as type Ia <lb/>Supernovae and Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB) <lb/> 1–5  radiation strongly show <lb/>an accelerated expansion of the Universe. And the observations indicate that the <lb/>energy budget of the universe is as follows: ordinary baryonic matter is 4%, the <lb/>contribution of dark matter (DM) is 26%, and the dark energy (DE) with positive <lb/>energy density and negative pressure occupies about 70% of the total energy of the <lb/>universe, which is responsible for the accelerated expansion of universe. <lb/>Over the past decade there have been many theoretical models for mimicking <lb/>the dark energy, such as the simplest cosmological constant model, i.e. the ΛCDM <lb/></body>

			<page>1550005-1 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">  Mod.  Phys. Lett. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> December 30, 2014 16:10 <lb/>MPLA <lb/>S0217732315500054 page 2 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Y.-B. Wu et al. <lb/></note>

			<body> model, in which the equation of state (EoS) is independent of the cosmic time, and <lb/>it can fit the observations well. However, two problems arise from this scenario, <lb/>namely the &quot; fine-tuning &quot; and &quot; the cosmic coincidence &quot; problems. In order to solve <lb/>these two problems, many dynamical dark energy models were proposed, whose <lb/>EoS evolves with cosmic time. The scalar field or quintessence <lb/> 6–8  is one of the most <lb/>favored candidates of dark energy, which produces sufficient negative pressure to <lb/>drive acceleration. In order to alleviate the cosmological-constant problems and <lb/>explain the acceleration expansion, many dynamical dark energy models were con-<lb/>structed, such as Phantom, <lb/> 9,10  Quintom, <lb/> 11  Tachyon, <lb/> 12  K-essence, <lb/> 13  Chaplygin gas <lb/>model <lb/> 14,15  etc. Meanwhile, some other interacting dark energy models including the <lb/>modified Chaplygin gas model, <lb/> 16  braneworld model <lb/> 17  and holographic dark energy <lb/>model <lb/> 18  were also established. Recently, based on the principle of quantum gravity, <lb/>the agegraphic dark energy <lb/> 19  model has been put forward and further extended to <lb/>new agegraphic dark energy <lb/> 20  model. <lb/>As we know, the Chaplygin gas model can be used to unify the dark energy and <lb/>dark matter by allowing an EoS evolving with time. And the generalized Chaplygin <lb/>gas (GCG) model, <lb/> 21  described by the EoS p  GCG  = − <lb/> B <lb/> ρ  α <lb/> GCG <lb/> (0 &lt; α ≤ 1), behaves as <lb/>dust-like matter at early times and a cosmological constant at late stages. Moreover, <lb/>the GCG model can be extended to the modified Chaplygin gas (MCG) model, <lb/> 22,23 <lb/> which interpolates between standard fluid at high energy density and Chaplygin <lb/>gas fluid at low energy density. The EoS for the MCG model is p = Aρ − <lb/> B <lb/>ρ  α  . <lb/>Based on Ref. 25, in this paper we will continue to study the MCG model by <lb/>discussing the density gradient for dark matter and dark energy as well as the <lb/>Hubble parameter H(z) as a function of the model parameters in Sec. 2. The Om <lb/> diagnostic to differentiate the MCG model from the ΛCDM, GCG and CG models <lb/>is preformed in Sec. 3. Specifically, we plot the evolutionary trajectories of the MCG <lb/>model with different interaction terms in Om planes, and find that the coupling <lb/>intensity b <lb/> 2  , which is a constant denoting the transfer strength, plays an important <lb/>role in the MCG model. In Sec. 4, we reconstruct the potential of the MCG scalar <lb/>field as well as the dynamics of the scalar field according to the evolution of the <lb/>MCG dark energy, and the results given by us can reduce to the cases without <lb/>interaction. <lb/> 2. The Evolutions of Change Rates of the Dark Energy Densities <lb/> We consider a cosmological model with two components: the MCG and the baryon <lb/>fluid, i.e. the total energy density ρ  t  = ρ  MCG  + ρ  b  . As a unified model of two dark <lb/>sectors, we assume that the MCG fluid is made up of two components, namely DE <lb/>and DM, i.e. <lb/> ρ  MCG  = ρ  de  + ρ  dm  , <lb/> (1) <lb/> p  MCG  = p  de  . <lb/> (2) <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550005-2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Mod.  Phys. Lett. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> December 30, 2014 16:10 <lb/>MPLA <lb/>S0217732315500054 page 3 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Analysis on modified Chaplygin gas as dark energy model <lb/></note>

			<body> The MCG fluid obeys the EoS <lb/> 22 <lb/> p  MCG  = Aρ  MCG  − <lb/> B <lb/>ρ  α <lb/> MCG <lb/> , <lb/> (3) <lb/>where 0 &lt; α ≤ 1, A and B are constant. It follows that the EoS can be reduced <lb/>to the GCG scenario when A = 0, and if A = 0 and α = 1 the EoS can further be <lb/>reduced to the CG scenario. <lb/>In the framework of the FRW cosmology, by means of the energy conservation <lb/>equation, the energy density of the MCG <lb/> 24  is as follows: <lb/> ρ  MCG  = ρ  0MCG  [A  s  + (1 − A  s  )a <lb/> −3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> 1 <lb/> 1+α  , <lb/> (4) <lb/>where a is the scalar factor, ρ  0MCG  is the present value of the MCG energy density, <lb/> A  s  = <lb/> B <lb/> (1+A)ρ <lb/> 1+α <lb/>0 <lb/> since 0 ≤ A  s  ≤ 1. <lb/>In what follows, we study the change rates of the energy densities of DE and <lb/>DM. It is supposed that there is an interaction between DE with constant ω  de  and <lb/>DM in this model. According to Ref. 25, we can obtain <lb/> ρ  de  = ρ  0MCG <lb/> −A  s  + A(1 − A  s  )a <lb/> −3(1+A)(1+α) <lb/> ω  de  [A  s  + (1 − A  s  )a  −3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> α <lb/> 1+α <lb/> , <lb/> (5) <lb/> ρ  dm  = ρ  0MCG <lb/> A  s  − A(1 − A  s  )a <lb/> −3(1+A)(1+α)  + ω  de  [A  s  + (1 − A  s  )a <lb/> −3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> ω  de  [A  s  + (1 − A  s  )a  −3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> α <lb/> 1+α <lb/> . <lb/> (6) <lb/>Furthermore, we can give the expressions of the change rates of the energy <lb/>densities of DE and DM as follows: <lb/> dρ  de <lb/> dz <lb/> = 3ρ  0MCG  S , <lb/> (7) <lb/> dρ  dm <lb/> dz <lb/> = 3ρ  0MCG  P , <lb/> (8) <lb/>where <lb/> S = <lb/>(1 + A)(1 − A  s  )(1 + z) <lb/> 3(1+A)(1+α)−1 <lb/> ω  de  [A  s  + (1 − A  s  )(1 + z)  3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> α <lb/> 1+α <lb/> × <lb/> A(1 + α) − <lb/> α[−A  s  + A(1 − A  s  )(1 + z) <lb/> 3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> A  s  + (1 − A  s  )(1 + z)  3(1+A)(1+α) <lb/> , <lb/>P = <lb/>(1 + A)(1 − A  s  )(1 + z) <lb/> 3(1+A)(1+α)−1 <lb/> ω  de  [A  s  + (1 − A  s  )(1 + z)  3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> α <lb/> 1+α <lb/> × <lb/> (1 + α)(ω  de  − A) + αω  de  + <lb/> α[A  s  − A(1 − A  s  )(1 + z) <lb/> 3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> A  s  + (1 − A  s  )(1 + z)  3(1+A)(1+α) <lb/> . <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550005-3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">  Mod.  Phys. Lett. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> December 30, 2014 16:10 <lb/>MPLA <lb/>S0217732315500054 page 2 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Y.-B. Wu et al. <lb/></note>

			<body> 0 <lb/> 2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/> 0.6 <lb/> 0.5 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.1 <lb/> 0.0 <lb/>z <lb/>S <lb/> a <lb/> 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>z <lb/>P <lb/> b <lb/> Fig. 1. The factor S and P vs. the redshift z, where As = 0.74, α = 0.5, A = 0.012. <lb/> From Eq. (7), it is easy to see that the sign of the value of <lb/> dρ  de <lb/> dz  depends on the <lb/>factor S. Figure 1(a) shows not only the relation between factor S and the redshift z, <lb/> but also the evolutionary behavior of the change rate of the energy density from <lb/>the past to the future, from which we see that as the redshift z decreases, <lb/> dρ  de <lb/> dz <lb/> gradually increases to −0.08 at z = 1.95 and then decreases to −0.14 at z = 0.35, <lb/>after that it increases rapidly, and eventually tends to be relatively stable. When <lb/> z = −0.70, it approaches 0. The factor S is always less than zero in contrast with <lb/>the value of P , which means that with the decrease of the redshift z, the energy <lb/>density of DE increases all the time although its change rate is different. That is to <lb/>say, there is an energy transfer from DM to DE, which is in good agreement with <lb/>the one in Fig. 1(b). <lb/>Specially, for the case without interaction between DE and DM, by means of <lb/>the continuity equation, the energy densities of DM and DE read <lb/> ρ  dm  = ρ  0dm  (1 + z) <lb/> 3  , <lb/> (9) <lb/> ρ  de  = ρ  0MCG  [A  s  + (1 − A  s  )(1 + z) <lb/> 3(1+α)(1+A)  ] <lb/> 1 <lb/>1+α  − ρ  0dm  (1 + z) <lb/> 3  . <lb/> (10) <lb/>Thus, we can get the change rates of the energy densities of DE and DM, <lb/> dρ  de <lb/> dz <lb/> = 3ρ  0MCG  M , <lb/> (11) <lb/> dρ  dm <lb/> dz <lb/> = 3ρ  0dm  (1 + z) <lb/> 2  , <lb/> (12) <lb/>where M = (1 + z) <lb/> 2 <lb/> (1−As)(1+A)(1+z) <lb/> 3[A+α(1+A)] <lb/> [As+(1−As)(1+z)  3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> α <lb/> 1+α <lb/> − <lb/> Ω  0dm <lb/> 1−Ω  0b <lb/> and A  s  = <lb/> 1 <lb/>1+A <lb/> A − <lb/> Ω  0de  ω  0de <lb/> 1−Ω  0b <lb/> = 0.74 (the current parameters used in this study are Ω  0dm  = 0.25, <lb/>Ω  0de  = 0.7, Ω  0b  = 0.05). <lb/> 26  Evidently, the sign of the value of <lb/> dρ  de <lb/> dz  lies on M . Hence <lb/>the evolutional trend of DE density can be discussed by the factor M . <lb/>The evolutional trend of factor M and <lb/> dρ  dm <lb/> dz  are illustrated in Fig. 2, from which <lb/>we can see that as the redshift z decreases, <lb/> dρ  dm <lb/> dz  decreases faster than <lb/> dρ  de <lb/> dz  , and <lb/>similarly <lb/> dρ  dm <lb/> dz  (or <lb/> dρ  de <lb/> dz  ) decreases faster in the range of z &gt; 0.1 than one in the range <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550005-4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Mod.  Phys. Lett. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> December 30, 2014 16:10 <lb/>MPLA <lb/>S0217732315500054 page 3 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Analysis on modified Chaplygin gas as dark energy model <lb/></note>

			<body> 0 <lb/> 2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>z <lb/> a <lb/> M <lb/>dΡ dm <lb/> dz <lb/> 1.0 0.8 0.6 0.4 0.2 <lb/> 0.0 <lb/> 1.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/> 0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>z <lb/> b <lb/> M <lb/>dΡ dm <lb/> dz <lb/> Fig. 2. The factor M and <lb/> dρ  dm <lb/> dz <lb/> vs. the redshift −1 &lt; z &lt; 8 (a) and −1 &lt; z &lt; 0.1 (b), where <lb/> As = 0.74, α = 0.5, A = 0.012. <lb/> of −1 &lt; z &lt; 0.1. Moreover, when z = −1 they approach zero. When −1 &lt; z &lt; 0.1, <lb/>Fig. 2(b) shows that <lb/> dρ  dm <lb/> dz  decreases continuously with the increasing z. But for the <lb/>DE, the curve first declines, then in spite of the change in the amplitude the increase <lb/>is very small with the decreasing z, until both of them approach 0 at z = −1. <lb/> On the other hand, as we know, the Hubble parameter is defined by H = <lb/> ˙ <lb/> a <lb/>a  , <lb/>and a list of 28 independent H(z) measurements <lb/> 27  was compiled on the basis of the <lb/>detection of baryon acoustic oscillation and other techniques. Moreover, the related <lb/>cosmological parameters can be constrained by means of these measurements in <lb/>different dark energy models. For the MCG model in this paper, by using the <lb/>Friedmann equation H <lb/> 2  = <lb/> 8πGρ <lb/>3 <lb/> and Eq. (7), the Hubble parameter H(z) can be <lb/>expressed as a function of the model parameters <lb/> H <lb/> 2  (z) = H <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  [(1 − Ω  0b  )[A  s  + (1 − A  s  )(1 + z) <lb/> 3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> 1 <lb/>1+α  + Ω  0b  (1 + z) <lb/> 3  ] . (13) <lb/>In the following analysis, the Gaussian H  0  prior H  0  + σ  H0  = 68 ± <lb/> 2.8 km s <lb/> −1  Mpc <lb/> −1  is used, which comes from the median statistics analysis of <lb/>553 H  0  measurements <lb/> 28  and is consistent with the earlier estimates of Gott et al. <lb/> 29 <lb/> and Chen et al. <lb/> 30  Thus, for the MCG model, the four H(z) data points can be <lb/>obtained, i.e. H(z) = 72.2 ± 2.97 km s <lb/> −1  Mpc <lb/> −1  at z = 0.07, H(z) = 74.53 ± <lb/> 3.06 km s <lb/> −1  Mpc <lb/> −1  at z = 0.1, H(z) = 76.34 ± 3.16 km s <lb/> −1  Mpc <lb/> −1  at z = 0.12 <lb/>and H(z) = 385.45 ± 15.87 km s <lb/> −1  Mpc <lb/> −1  at z = 1, which can be compared with <lb/>the data determined by using a number of different techniques as in Ref. 27. Our <lb/>results show that the first three values of H(z) in the MCG model are compatible <lb/>with those listed in Ref. 27. <lb/> 3. Om Diagnostic <lb/> It is well known that Om diagnostic <lb/> 31  is constructed based on the Hubble parameter <lb/> H, which can geometrically differentiate the ΛCDM model from the CG, GCG and <lb/>MCG models. The Om diagnostic is defined as <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550005-5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">  Mod.  Phys. Lett. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> December 30, 2014 16:10 <lb/>MPLA <lb/>S0217732315500054 page 2 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Y.-B. Wu et al. <lb/></note>

			<body> Om(x) = <lb/> h <lb/> 2  (x) − 1 <lb/> x  3  − 1 <lb/> , <lb/>x= 1 + z , <lb/> (14) <lb/>where h <lb/> 2  (x) = <lb/> H <lb/> 2  (x) <lb/> H  2 <lb/>0 <lb/> . <lb/>For the ΛCDM model, Om(z) = Ω  0m  is a constant, which provides a null-test <lb/>of the cosmological constant. Meanwhile, we can rewrite the Hubble parameter for <lb/>the MCG model with interaction as follows: <lb/> H <lb/> 2  = H <lb/> 2 <lb/>0 <lb/> i <lb/> Ω  0i  (1 + z) <lb/> 3(1+ωi)  , <lb/> (15) <lb/>where Ω  0i  is the present value of the density parameter of some component in <lb/>universe (here i = de, dm, b). As we know, the whole MCG fluid satisfies the energy <lb/>conservation, but DE and DM components do not obey it separately because of <lb/>their interaction Γ. The equations of motion for DE and DM can be written as <lb/>˙ <lb/> ρ  de  + 3Hρ  de  (1 + ω  de  ) = Γ , <lb/> (16) <lb/>˙ <lb/> ρ  dm  + 3Hρ  dm  = −Γ . <lb/> (17) <lb/>Thus we can rewrite Eqs. (16) and (17) into the equivalent form as <lb/>˙ <lb/> ρ  de  + 3Hρ  de  (1 + ω <lb/> (e) <lb/>de  ) = 0 , <lb/> (18) <lb/>˙ <lb/> ρ  dm  + 3Hρ  dm  (1 + ω <lb/> (e) <lb/>dm  ) = 0 , <lb/> (19) <lb/>where ω <lb/> (e) <lb/>de  = ω  de  − <lb/> Γ <lb/>3Hρ  de <lb/> and ω <lb/> (e) <lb/>dm  = <lb/> Γ <lb/>3Hρ  dm <lb/> are the effective EoS of the MCG model <lb/>with interaction between DE and DM. Thus, Hubble parameter with interaction <lb/> H <lb/> 2  = H <lb/> 2 <lb/>0 <lb/> i <lb/> Ω  0i  e <lb/> 3 <lb/>  z <lb/> 0 <lb/>1+ω <lb/>(e) <lb/> i <lb/> 1+z  dz <lb/> (20) <lb/>and h <lb/> 2  (z) <lb/> h <lb/> 2  (z) = Ω  0de  e <lb/> 3 <lb/>  z <lb/> 0 <lb/>1+ω <lb/>(e) <lb/>de <lb/>1+z  dz <lb/> + Ω  0dm  e <lb/> 3 <lb/>  z <lb/> 0 <lb/>1+ω <lb/>(e) <lb/>dm <lb/>1+z  dz <lb/> + Ω  0b  (1 + z) <lb/> 3  . <lb/> (21) <lb/>When taking different interaction terms, the effective EoS of DE and DM are <lb/>rewritten as follows: <lb/>(1) Γ = 3b <lb/> 2  Hρ  MCG  , <lb/> ω <lb/> (e) <lb/> de  = ω  de  − <lb/> b  2  ω  de  [As + (1 − As)(1 + z)  3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> −As + A(1 − As)(1 + z)  3(1+A)(1+α)  , <lb/> (22) <lb/> ω <lb/> (e) <lb/>dm  = <lb/> b  2  ω  de  [As + (1 − As)(1 + z)  3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> As − A(1 − As)(1 + z)  3(1+A)(1+α)  + ω  de  [As + (1 − As)(1 + z)  3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> . <lb/> (23) <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550005-6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Mod.  Phys. Lett. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> December 30, 2014 16:10 <lb/>MPLA <lb/>S0217732315500054 page 3 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Analysis on modified Chaplygin gas as dark energy model <lb/></note>

			<body> (2) Γ = 3b <lb/> 2  Hρ  de  , <lb/> ω <lb/> (e) <lb/> de  = ω  de  − b  2  , <lb/> (24) <lb/> ω <lb/> (e) <lb/>dm  = <lb/> b  2  [−As + A(1 − As)(1 + z)  3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> As − A(1 − As)(1 + z)  3(1+A)(1+α)  + ω  de  [As + (1 − As)(1 + z)  3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> . <lb/> (25) <lb/>(3) Γ = 3b <lb/> 2  Hρ  dm  , <lb/> ω <lb/> (e) <lb/>de  = ω  de  − b  2  As − A(1 − As)(1 + z)  3(1+A)(1+α)  + ω  de  [As + (1 − As)(1 + z)  3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> −As + A(1 − As)(1 + z)  3(1+A)(1+α) <lb/> , <lb/> (26) <lb/> ω <lb/> (e) <lb/>dm  = b  2  . <lb/> (27) <lb/>Thus, according to Eq. (21), by taking Ω  0de  = 0.7, Ω  0dm  = 0.25, Ω  0b  = 0.05, <lb/>we can obtain the Om parameters of the MCG model corresponding to the above <lb/>different interaction terms, which are plotted in Fig. 3. <lb/>Figure 3(a) shows that for a fixed interaction term Γ = 3b <lb/> 2  Hρ  MCG  , different <lb/>coupling intensity b <lb/> 2  corresponds to the different evolutionary trajectories. More-<lb/>over, the constant b <lb/> 2  has greater influence on the trajectories in the past (near <lb/> z &gt; 0) than those in the present. What is more, the larger the value of b <lb/> 2  , the <lb/>more obvious the curves change. Ultimately, these curves approach to the ΛCDM <lb/>fixed point as z = 0, which implies that the model behaves as a ΛCDM model in <lb/>the future, and our universe will enter a de Sitter phase. Figure 3(b) indicates that <lb/>the evolutionary trends of the three curves are not only roughly the same, even <lb/>though with the different values of b <lb/> 2  , but also all nearly parallel to the one in the <lb/>ΛCDM model. In Fig. 3(c), with the interaction term Γ = 3b <lb/> 2  Hρ  dm  , a crossing <lb/>point arises at z = 2.4. However, all of the Om curves go from decreasing to in-<lb/>creasing gradually as the redshift z decreases, and their behaviors are completely <lb/>different from each other when 0 &lt; z &lt; 2.0. Based on the above three cases, it <lb/>follows that the constant b <lb/> 2  plays a very important role in the evolution of the <lb/>MCG model. Especially, when taking b <lb/> 2  = 0, expression (21) can be reduced to <lb/>the situation in the absence of interaction. Figure 3(d) illustrates the evolutions of <lb/> Om parameter corresponding to the three different interaction terms in the case of <lb/> b <lb/> 2  = 0.14. Taking Γ = 3b <lb/> 2  Hρ  de  and Γ = 3b <lb/> 2  Hρ  dm  , both the corresponding evolu-<lb/>tionary trends of Om parameters are basically the same. However, when we take <lb/>Γ = 3b <lb/> 2  Hρ  MCG  , the trajectory of curve deviates obviously from the ΛCDM model <lb/>as the redshift z increases. Furthermore, by using Om diagnostic approach, we can <lb/>also distinguish the MCG model from the other models clearly, and find that there <lb/>are great differences among them. Especially, in Fig. 3(e), the three curves represent <lb/>CG, GCG and MCG models with interaction are quite different from the ΛCDM <lb/>model when 0 &lt; z &lt; 1.9. To the contrary, they coincide together as z = 0 and <lb/> z &gt; 1.9. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550005-7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">  Mod.  Phys. Lett. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> December 30, 2014 16:10 <lb/>MPLA <lb/>S0217732315500054 page 2 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Y.-B. Wu et al. <lb/></note>

			<body> 0.0 <lb/> 0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>0.40 <lb/>0.45 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.60 <lb/>z <lb/> z <lb/> a <lb/> CDM <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.06 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.1 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.14 <lb/> 0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>z <lb/> z <lb/> b <lb/> CDM <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.06 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.1 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.14 <lb/> 0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>z <lb/> z <lb/> c <lb/> CDM <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.06 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.1 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.14 <lb/> 0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>z <lb/> z <lb/> d <lb/> CDM <lb/>3b <lb/> 2 HΡ dm <lb/> 3b <lb/> 2 HΡ de <lb/> 3b <lb/> 2 HΡ MCG <lb/> 0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3.0 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>z <lb/> z <lb/> e <lb/> CDM <lb/> MGCG <lb/>GCG <lb/>CG <lb/> Fig. 3. The Om evolutionary diagrams of the MCG model with interaction in different cases, <lb/>where Γ = 3b  2  Hρ  MCG  (a), Γ = 3b  2  Hρ  de  (b), Γ = 3b  2  Hρ  dm  (c), b  2  = 0.14 (d), while the curves <lb/>in (e) correspond to CG (dotted), GCG (dot-dashed), MCG (dashed), and ΛCDM (solid) models, <lb/>respectively. <lb/> In particular, if there is no interaction between DE and DM, in Eq. (14), h <lb/> 2  (x) = <lb/> H <lb/> 2  (x) <lb/> H  2 <lb/>0 <lb/> = (1 − Ω  0b  )[A  s  + (1 − A  s  )x <lb/> 3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> 1 <lb/>1+α  + Ω  0b  x <lb/> 3  , where x = 1 + z. Thus, <lb/>we obtain the expression of Om in the MCG model as a function of z <lb/>Om(z) = <lb/>1 <lb/>(1 + z)  3  − 1 <lb/> {(1−Ω  0b  )[A  s  +(1−A  s  )(1+z) <lb/> 3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> 1 <lb/>1+α  +Ω  0b  (1+z) <lb/> 3 <lb/> −1} <lb/> (28) <lb/>with A  s  = 0.74, ω  de  = −1, and plot the curves of Om(z) in Fig. 4. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550005-8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Mod.  Phys. Lett. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> December 30, 2014 16:10 <lb/>MPLA <lb/>S0217732315500054 page 3 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Analysis on modified Chaplygin gas as dark energy model <lb/></note>

			<body> 1 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>z <lb/> z <lb/> CDM <lb/> MGCG <lb/>GCG <lb/>CG <lb/> Fig. 4. Om evolution diagram versus the redshift (z) for the CG (dotted), GCG (dot-dashed), <lb/>MCG (dashed) and ΛCDM (solid) models, where Ω  0dm  = 0.25, Ω  0de  = 0.7, Ω  0b  = 0.05 and <lb/> As = 0.74. <lb/> For the convenience of comparison, we plot the evolutionary trajectories of CG, <lb/>GCG models as well as ΛCDM model represented by the horizontal solid line in <lb/>Fig. 4, from which we find that the evolutionary trend of MCG model is analogous <lb/>to that of GCG model, but appears slightly different in the early period. When <lb/> z &gt; 2, the evolutionary trajectory of the CG model is almost the same as the <lb/>GCG model, though corresponding to different values of Om. Furthermore, these <lb/>trajectories have an identical crossing point with horizontal solid line at present. It <lb/>follows that when taking different values of A and α, Eq. (28) can reduce to the <lb/> Om of CG, GCG and ΛCDM models. <lb/> 4. Reconstruction of the MCG Scalar Field of Dark Energy with <lb/>Interaction <lb/> At present it is believed that the current accelerated expansion is driven by a <lb/>dynamical scalar field φ with potential V (φ), related to the energy density and the <lb/>pressure of dark energy <lb/> 32–34  as <lb/> ρ  φ  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>˙ <lb/> φ <lb/> 2  + V (φ) , <lb/> (29) <lb/> p  φ  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>˙ <lb/> φ <lb/> 2 <lb/> − V (φ) . <lb/> (30) <lb/>Hence, we have <lb/>˙ <lb/> φ <lb/> 2  = ρ  φ  + p  φ  , <lb/> (31) <lb/> V (φ) = <lb/> ρ  φ  − p  φ <lb/> 2 <lb/> . <lb/> (32) <lb/>We will reconstruct the potential and the dynamics. To do this, we treat the MCG <lb/>as an ordinary scalar field φ. By means of ρ  φ  = ρ  de(MCG)  and p  φ  = p  de  , according <lb/>to Eqs. (3)–(5), the kinetic term can be rewritten as <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550005-9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">  Mod.  Phys. Lett. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> December 30, 2014 16:10 <lb/>MPLA <lb/>S0217732315500054 page 2 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Y.-B. Wu et al. <lb/></note>

			<body> ˙ <lb/> φ <lb/> 2  = ρ  0MCG <lb/> (1 + ω  de  )[−A  s  + A(1 − A  s  )a <lb/> −3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> ω  de  [A  s  + (1 − A  s  )a  −3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> α <lb/> 1+α <lb/> . <lb/> (33) <lb/>Then we have <lb/>˙ <lb/> φ = <lb/> ρ  0MCG <lb/> (1 + ω  de  )[−A  s  + A(1 − A  s  )a  −3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> ω  de  [A  s  + (1 − A  s  )a  −3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> α <lb/> 1+α <lb/> . <lb/> (34) <lb/>Taking into account y = ln a, we have <lb/>˙ <lb/> φ = φ <lb/>  H , <lb/> (35) <lb/>where the &quot; prime &quot; denotes differentiation with respect to the e-folding time param-<lb/>eter y, hence we obtain <lb/> φ <lb/>  = <lb/>1 <lb/> H <lb/> ρ  0MCG <lb/> (1 + ω  de  )[−A  s  + A(1 − A  s  )a  −3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> ω  de  [A  s  + (1 − A  s  )a  −3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> α <lb/> 1+α <lb/> , <lb/> (36) <lb/>and further read off <lb/> φ(a) − φ(a  0  ) = <lb/>  ln a <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> H <lb/> ρ  0MCG <lb/> (1 + ω  de  )[−A  s  + A(1 − A  s  )a  −3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> ω  de  [A  s  + (1 − A  s  )a  −3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> α <lb/> 1+α <lb/> dy , <lb/> (37) <lb/>where a  0  is the present value of the scale factor. By using φ(a  0  ) = 0, we have <lb/> φ(a) = <lb/>  ln a <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> H <lb/> ρ  0MCG <lb/> (1 + ω  de  )[−A  s  + A(1 − A  s  )a  −3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> ω  de  [A  s  + (1 − A  s  )a  −3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> α <lb/> 1+α <lb/> dy . <lb/> (38) <lb/>In addition, we reconstruct the potential of the MCG scalar field. When the in-<lb/>teraction terms are taken as Γ  1  = 3b <lb/> 2  Hρ  de  , Γ  2  = 3b <lb/> 2  Hρ  dm  and Γ  3  = 3b <lb/> 2  Hρ  MCG  , <lb/>respectively, the corresponding expressions of potential read <lb/> V  1  = <lb/> ρ  0MCG  (1 − ω  de  + b <lb/> 2  )[−A  s  + A(1 − A  s  )a <lb/> −3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/>2ω  de  [A  s  + (1 − A  s  )a  −3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> α <lb/> 1+α <lb/> , <lb/> (39) <lb/> V  2  = <lb/> ρ  0MCG <lb/> 2 <lb/> (1 − ω  de  − b <lb/> 2  )[−A  s  + A(1 − A  s  )a <lb/> −3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> ω  de  [A  s  + (1 − A  s  )a  −3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> α <lb/> 1+α <lb/> + b <lb/> 2  [A  s  + (1 − A  s  )a <lb/> −3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> 1 <lb/>1+α <lb/> , <lb/> (40) <lb/> V  3  = <lb/> ρ  0MCG <lb/> 2 <lb/> (1 − ω  de  )[−A  s  + A(1 − A  s  )a <lb/> −3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> ω  de  [A  s  + (1 − A  s  )a  −3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> α <lb/> 1+α <lb/> + b <lb/> 2  [A  s  + (1 − A  s  )a <lb/> −3(1+A)(1+α)  ] <lb/> 1 <lb/>1+α <lb/> . <lb/> (41) <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550005-10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Mod.  Phys. Lett. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> December 30, 2014 16:10 <lb/>MPLA <lb/>S0217732315500054 page 3 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Analysis on modified Chaplygin gas as dark energy model <lb/></note>

			<body> 1.0 <lb/> 0.8 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.2 <lb/> 0.0 <lb/> 1.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/> 0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/> Φ <lb/> V <lb/> a <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.15 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.10 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.06 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0 <lb/> 1.0 0.8 0.6 0.4 0.2 <lb/> 0.0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/> Φ <lb/> V <lb/> b <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.15 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.10 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.06 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0 <lb/> 1.0 0.8 0.6 0.4 0.2 <lb/> 0.0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/> Φ <lb/> V <lb/> c <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.15 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.10 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.06 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0 <lb/> Fig. 5. The reconstruction of the potential V for the interacting MCG with different coupling <lb/>intensity b  2  in the case of the fixed interaction terms Γ = 3b  2  Hρ  de  (a), 3b  2  Hρ  dm  (b) and <lb/>3b  2  Hρ  MCG  (c). <lb/> In particular, for b <lb/> 2  = 0, one gets <lb/> V  1  = V  2  = V  3  = V (φ) = <lb/>1 − ω  de <lb/> 2(1 + ω  de  ) <lb/>(φ <lb/>  H) <lb/> 2  . <lb/> (42) <lb/>In Fig. 5, we plot the reconstruction of the potential V concretely. Figure 5(a) <lb/>illustrates that the potential V increases with the increasing φ. However, by com-<lb/>paring Fig. 5(a) with (b) and (c), we find that there are many differences among <lb/>them, such as that the trends of (b) and (c) are diametrically opposed to (a) except <lb/>for the case of b <lb/> 2  = 0, and that V decreases sharply and then increases gradually <lb/>as φ increases, i.e. the weaker the interaction, the faster the potential V changes. <lb/>In addition, the evolutions of the scalar field φ(a) are also displayed in Fig. 6, from <lb/>which we see that φ(a) goes up as the scalar factor increases for the fixed value <lb/>of b <lb/> 2  . Moreover, with the evolution of the scale factor to today, the effects of the <lb/>interaction terms on the evolution of φ(a) are basically the same, and tend to an <lb/>identical value at a = 1. From Figs. 6(a) and (c), we also see that the evolutionary <lb/>curves corresponding to different interaction terms overlap, which means that the <lb/>values of b <lb/> 2  nearly have no effect on the evolutionary trajectories of φ(a). However, <lb/>Fig. 6(b) illustrates the faint effects of b <lb/> 2  on φ(a). <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550005-11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">  Mod.  Phys. Lett. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> December 30, 2014 16:10 <lb/>MPLA <lb/>S0217732315500054 page 2 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Y.-B. Wu et al. <lb/></note>

			<body> 0.3 0.4 0.5 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1.0 <lb/> 1.0 <lb/> 0.8 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.2 <lb/> 0.0 <lb/> a <lb/> Φa <lb/> a <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.15 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.10 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.06 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0 <lb/> 0.3 0.4 0.5 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1.0 <lb/> 1.0 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.2 <lb/> 0.0 <lb/> a <lb/> Φa <lb/> b <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.15 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.10 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.06 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0 <lb/> 0.3 0.4 0.5 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1.0 <lb/> 1.0 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.2 <lb/> 0.0 <lb/> a <lb/> Φa <lb/> c <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.15 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.10 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0.06 <lb/> b <lb/> 2  0 <lb/> Fig. 6. The evolutions of the scalar field φ(a) for interacting MCG with different coupling inten-<lb/>sity b  2  , corresponds to Γ = 3b  2  Hρ  de  (a), 3b  2  Hρ  dm  (b) and 3b  2  Hρ  MCG  (c), respectively. <lb/> 5. Conclusions <lb/> In summary, for the modified Chaplygin gas (MCG) model with interaction we have <lb/>discussed both the change rates of the energy densities and the Hubble parameter <lb/> H(z) as a function of the model parameters, which is compared and consistent <lb/>with the related data in Ref. 27. Moreover, we have performed the Om diagnostic <lb/>in order to geometrically differentiate the MCG model from ΛCDM, GCG and CG <lb/>models. Concretely, we plotted the evolutionary trajectories of the MCG model <lb/>with different interaction terms in Om planes. Furthermore, we have shown that <lb/>the coupling intensity b <lb/> 2  plays an important role in the MCG model. Also, we have <lb/>reconstructed the potential of the MCG scalar field as well as the dynamics of the <lb/>scalar field according to the evolution of the MCG dark energy. Different values <lb/>of b <lb/> 2  correspond to different evolutions of the potential V , and the stronger the <lb/>interaction, the slower the potential V changes with increasing φ. In particular, it <lb/>is worth mentioning that the results given by us can reduce to the cases without <lb/>interaction. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgment <lb/> The research work is supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of <lb/>China (Grant Nos. 11175077 and 11205078), the Joint Specialized Research Fund <lb/></div>

			<page> 1550005-12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Mod.  Phys. Lett. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> December 30, 2014 16:10 <lb/>MPLA <lb/>S0217732315500054 page 13 <lb/> Analysis on modified Chaplygin gas as dark energy model <lb/></note>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> for the Doctoral Program of Higher Education, Ministry of Education, China (Grant <lb/>No. 20122136110002) and in part by a grant from State Key Laboratory of Theo-<lb/>retical Physics, Institute of Theoretical Physics, Chinese Academy of Science. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. S. Perlmutter et al., Nature 391, 51 (1998). <lb/>2. A. G. Riess et al., Astron. J. 116, 1009 (1998). <lb/>3. A. G. Riess et al., Astron. J. 607, 665 (2004). <lb/>4. B. Boisseau et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 85, 2236 (2000). <lb/>5. D. N. Spergel et al., Astrophys. J. Suppl. Ser. 170, 377 (2007). <lb/>6. B. Ratra and P. J. E. Peebles, Phys. Rev. D 37, 321 (1988). <lb/>7. P. G. Ferreira and M. Joyce, Phys. Rev. Lett. 79, 4740 (1997). <lb/>8. P. G. Ferreira and M. Joyce, Phys. Rev. D 58, 023503 (1997). <lb/>9. R. R. Caldwell, R. Dave and P. J. Steinhardt, Phys. Rev. Lett. 80, 1582 (1998). <lb/>10. R. R. Caldwell, R. Dave and P. J. Steinhardt, Phys. Lett. B Vol. 545, 23 (2002). <lb/>11. B. Feng, X. L. Wang and X. M. Zhang, Phys. Lett. B 607, 35 (2005). <lb/>12. T. Padmanabhan, Phys. Rev. D 66, 021301 (2002). <lb/>13. R. J. Scherrer, Phys. Rev. Lett. 93, 011301 (2004). <lb/>14. A. Y. Kamenshchik, U. Moschellaand and V. Pasquier, Phys. Lett. B 511, 265 (2001). <lb/>15. M. C. Bento, O. Bertolami and A. A. Sen, Phys. Rev. D 66, 043507 (2002). <lb/>16. U. Debnath, A. Banerjee and S. Chakraborty, Class. Quantum Grav. 21, 5609 (2001). <lb/>17. V. Sahni and Y. Shtanov, J. Cosmol. Astropart. Phys. 0311, 014 (2003). <lb/>18. A. G. Cohen, D. B. Kaplan and A. E. Nelson, Phys. Rev. Lett. 82, 4971 (1999). <lb/>19. R. G. Cai, Phys. Lett. B 657, 228 (2007). <lb/>20. H. Wei and R. G. Cai, Phys. Lett. B 660, 113 (2008). <lb/>21. M. C. Bento, O. Bertolami and A. A. Sen, Phys. Rev. D 67, 063003 (2003). <lb/>22. U. Debnath, A. Banerjee and S. Chakraborty, Class. Quantum Grav. 21, 5609 (2004). <lb/>23. L. P. Chimento, Phys. Rev. D 69, 123517 (2004). <lb/>24. Y. B. Wu et al., Mod. Phys. Lett. A 22, 783 (2007). <lb/>25. Y. B. Wu et al., Gen. Relat. Gravit. 45, 1387 (2013). <lb/>26. J. Wang et al., Chin. Phys. Lett. 26, 089801 (2009). <lb/>27. O. Farooq and B. Ratra, Astrophys. J. 766, L7 (2013). <lb/>28. G. Chen and B. Ratra, Publ. Astron. Soc. Pac. 123, 1127 (2011). <lb/>29. J. R. Gott et al., Astrophys. J. 549, 1 (2001). <lb/>30. G. Chen and B. Ratra, Publ. Astron. Soc. Pac. 115, 1143 (2003). <lb/>31. V. Sahni, A. Shafieloo and A. A. Starobinsky, Phys. Rev. D 78, 103502 (2008). <lb/>32. L. Wang et al., Mod. Phys. Lett. A 26, 727 (2011). <lb/>33. W. Q. Yang et al., Mod. Phys. Lett. A 26, 191 (2011). <lb/>34. Y. B. Wu et al., Chin. Phys. Lett. 31, 029801 (2014). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 1550005-13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Mod.  Phys. Lett. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only.</note>


	</text>
</tei>
