<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="footnote"> arXiv:1403.5691v2  [math.RT] 12 Aug 2014 <lb/></note>

			<front> CLASSIFICATION OF SIMPLE WEIGHT MODULES <lb/>OVER THE 1-SPATIAL AGEING ALGEBRA <lb/> RENCAI L ¨ <lb/>U, VOLODYMYR MAZORCHUK AND KAIMING ZHAO <lb/> Abstract. In this paper we use Block&apos;s classification of simple <lb/>modules over the first Weyl algebra to obtain a complete classifi-<lb/>cation of simple weight modules, in particular, of Harish-Chandra <lb/>modules, over the 1-spatial ageing algebra age(1). Most of these <lb/>modules have infinite dimensional weight spaces and so far the al-<lb/>gebra age(1) is the only Lie algebra having simple weight modules <lb/>with infinite dimensional weight spaces for which such a classifica-<lb/>tion exists. As an application we classify all simple weight modules <lb/>over the (1 + 1)-dimensional space-time Schrödinger algebra S that <lb/>have a simple age(1)-submodule thus constructing many new sim-<lb/>ple weight S-modules. <lb/> Keywords: weight module, Schrödinger algebra, ageing <lb/>algebra, highest weight module <lb/> Mathematics Subject Classification 2010: 17B10, <lb/>17B30, 17B80 <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction and description of the results <lb/> Non-semisimple Lie algebras play an important role in physics where <lb/>they are frequently used to study various physical systems and ex-<lb/>plain diverse physical phenomena. For example one could mention <lb/>Schrödinger algebras and groups, see [DDM], conformal Galilei algebras <lb/>and groups, see [AI, AIK, CZ, GIl, GI2, HP, NOR, LMZ], and ageing <lb/>algebras, see [HP, H1, H2, H3, H4, HEP, HU, HS1, HS2, PH, HSSU]. <lb/>The representation theory of finite dimensional semisimple Lie alge-<lb/>bras is fairly well developed, see for example [Hu, Ja, M] and the ref-<lb/>erences therein. In contrast to this, many important methods of the <lb/>representation theory of semisimple algebra are either not available or <lb/>not yet developed or, at best, become much more complicated in the <lb/>non-semisimple case, confer e.g. [DLMZ]. As a consequence, much <lb/>less in known for non-semisimple case even for Lie algebras of rather <lb/>small dimension. Some recent results, see e.g. [WZ, D, DLMZ, LMZ], <lb/>make some progress in studying modules over certain non-semisimple <lb/>extensions of the Lie algebra sl  2  motivated by their applications in <lb/>physics. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> RENCAI L ¨ <lb/>U, VOLODYMYR MAZORCHUK AND KAIMING ZHAO <lb/></note>

			<body> The Schrödinger Lie group is the group of symmetries of the free par-<lb/>ticle Schrödinger equation. The classical Schr¨ödinger algebra is the Lie <lb/>algebra of this group. The main objects of study in this paper is the <lb/>extended Schrödinger algebra S in (1 + 1)-dimensional space-time and <lb/>its ageing subalgebra age(1), see precise definitions in Section 2. The <lb/>name of the latter algebra comes from its use as dynamical symme-<lb/>try in physical ageing, which can be observed in strongly interacting <lb/>many-body systems quenched from a disordered initial state to the co-<lb/>existence regime below the critical temperature T  c  &gt; 0 where several <lb/>equivalent equilibrium states exist, see [BR] for details. Various repre-<lb/>sentations of age(1) were constructed in the literature, see for example <lb/>[HS1, HS2, H1, H2, H3, H4, HU, PH, HSSU]. <lb/>Both S and age(1) have natural Cartan subalgebras which allow to <lb/>define the notion of weight modules, that is modules on which elements <lb/>of the Cartan subalgebra act diagonalizably. The main objective of the <lb/>present paper is to classify all simple weight modules over age(1). It <lb/>turns out that these modules have either all their weight spaces one-<lb/>dimensional, or all their weight spaces infinite dimensional. It seems <lb/>that the algebra age(1) is the first Lie algebra having simple weight <lb/>modules with infinite dimensional weight spaces for which classification <lb/>of simple weight modules is completed. As an application we classify all <lb/>simple weight S-modules that have a simple age(1)-submodule. This <lb/>provides many new examples of simple weight S-modules (for other <lb/>examples, see [D, LMZ]). <lb/>The paper is organized as follows. We start with some preliminaries in <lb/>Section 2. In Section 3, by embedding our algebras into the first Weyl <lb/>algebra we obtain a very good presentation for the centralizer U  0  of the <lb/>Cartan subalgebra in the universal enveloping algebra U(age(1)). This <lb/>is the key observation needed to classify all simple U  0  -modules. As a <lb/>consequence, we obtain our main result, Theorem 11, which provides <lb/>a classification of all simple weight modules over age(1). It turns out <lb/>that there are four classes of such simple modules, the first three classes <lb/>consist of certain weight modules with finite dimensional (in fact one-<lb/>dimensional) weight spaces, while the last class consists of modules for <lb/>which all non-zero weight spaces are infinite-dimensional. As a bonus, <lb/>in Section 4 we classify all simple weight S-modules that have a simple <lb/> age(1)-submodule, see Theorem 15. <lb/>2. Preliminaries <lb/> In this paper, we denote by Z, N, Z  +  and C the sets of integers, positive <lb/>integers, nonnegative integers and complex numbers, respectively. All <lb/>vector spaces and Lie algebras are over C. For a Lie algebra g we denote <lb/>by U(g) its universal enveloping algebra. We write ⊗ for ⊗  C  . <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SIMPLE WEIGHT MODULES OVER AGEING ALGEBRA <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body> The extended Schrödinger algebra S in (1+1)-dimensional space-time is <lb/>a complex Lie algebra with a basis {f, q, h, e, p, z} and the Lie bracket <lb/>given as follows: <lb/>(2.1) <lb/>[h, e] = 2e, [e, f ] = h, [h, f ] = −2f, <lb/> [e, q] = p, [e, p] = 0, [h, p] = p, <lb/> [f, p] = q, [f, q] = 0, [h, q] = −q, <lb/> [p, q] = z. [z, S] = 0. <lb/>It is easy to see that the subspace age(1) of S spanned by {e, h, p, q, z} <lb/> is a Lie subalgebra of S. This subalgebra is called the ageing algebra. <lb/> The elements h and z span a Cartan subalgebra h while the elements <lb/> p, q and z span a copy of the Heisenberg algebra H. We also denote <lb/>by n the subalgebra spanned by h, z, e and p. The subalgebra of S <lb/> spanned by e, f and h is isomorphic to the classical algebra sl  2  and <lb/>will be identified with the latter. <lb/>By Schur&apos;s lemma, the element z acts as a scalar on any simple module <lb/>over age(1) or S. Since we are concerned with simple modules only, we <lb/>will assume that z acts as a scalar ˙ <lb/> z on any module in this paper. For <lb/>a module V we denote by wt(V ) the set of h-eigenvalues on V and will <lb/>call these eigenvalues weights. All h-eigenvectors will be called weight <lb/>vectors. For a weight ˙ <lb/> h we denote by V  ˙ <lb/> h  the corresponding weight space, <lb/> that is the space of all h-eigenvectors with eigenvalue ˙ <lb/> h. If V is a simple <lb/>weight age(1)- or S-module, then, as usual, we have wt(V ) ⊂ ˙ <lb/> h + Z for <lb/>any ˙ <lb/> h ∈ wt(V ). <lb/>Let U  0  = {x ∈ U(age(1))|[h, x] = 0} be the centralizer of h in U(age(1)). <lb/> Then, as usual, for every simple weight age(1)-module V and any <lb/> λ ∈ wt(V ) the U  0  -module V  λ  is simple. <lb/>Each ( ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h) ∈ C <lb/> 2  defines the one-dimensional n-module Cw with the <lb/>action hw = ˙ <lb/> hw, zw = ˙ <lb/> zw and pw = ew = 0. Using it we define, as <lb/>usual, the Verma age(1)-module <lb/> M  age(1)  ( ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h) = Ind <lb/> age(1) <lb/>n <lb/> Cw. <lb/> Denote by ¯ <lb/> M  age(1)  ( ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h) the unique simple quotient of M  age(1)  ( ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h) (which <lb/>exists by standard arguments, see e.g. [Di, Chapter 7]). Similarly we <lb/>may define the Verma modules M  S  ( ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h), M  H  ( ˙ <lb/> z), M  sl  2  ( ˙ <lb/> h) and the corre-<lb/>sponding simple quotients ¯ <lb/> M  S  ( ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h), ¯ <lb/> M  H  ( ˙ <lb/> z), ¯ <lb/> M  sl  2  ( ˙ <lb/> h) over S, H, and sl  2  , <lb/>respectively. Analogously one defines the lowest weight Verma modules <lb/> M <lb/> − <lb/>S  ( ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h), M <lb/> − <lb/> age(1)  ( ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h), M <lb/> − <lb/>H  ( ˙ <lb/> z) and M <lb/> − <lb/> sl  2 <lb/> ( ˙ <lb/> h) and their corresponding <lb/>simple quotients ¯ <lb/> M <lb/> − <lb/>S  ( ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h), ¯ <lb/> M <lb/> − <lb/> age(1)  ( ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h), ¯ <lb/> M <lb/> − <lb/>H  ( ˙ <lb/> z) and ¯ <lb/> M <lb/> − <lb/> sl  2 <lb/> ( ˙ <lb/> h). <lb/></body>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> RENCAI L ¨ <lb/>U, VOLODYMYR MAZORCHUK AND KAIMING ZHAO <lb/></note>

			<body> 3. Simple weight modules over age(1) <lb/> We start by recalling some results from [B] adjusted to our setup. Let <lb/> K be the associative algebra C(t)[s] where st − ts = 1. The algebra K <lb/> is a non-commutative principal left and right ideal domain, in fact, it is <lb/>an Euclidean domain (both left and right). The space C(t) becomes a <lb/>faithful C(t)[s]-module by defining the action of C(t) via multiplication <lb/>and the action of s via <lb/> d <lb/> dt <lb/> . Consider the subalgebra R  0  of K generated <lb/>by t and t <lb/> 2  s, and the subalgebra R  1  of K generated by t and ts. For <lb/>convenience of later use we set R  ˙ <lb/> z  := R  1  for ˙ <lb/> z ∈ C <lb/>  *  . <lb/> Lemma 1. Let ˙ <lb/> z ∈ C. <lb/> (a) Let α = <lb/>  n <lb/>j=0  α  j  s <lb/> j  , where α  j  ∈ C(t) with α  0  = 1, be an irreducible <lb/>element in K. Then we have the following: <lb/> (i) If the rational function α  j  has a zero at 0 of order at least j+1, <lb/> then R  1  /(R  1  ∩Kα) is a simple R  1  -module. Up to isomorphism, <lb/>every C[t]-torsion-free simple R  1  -module arises in this way. <lb/> (ii) If the rational function α  j  has a zero at 0 of order at least <lb/> 2j + 1, then R  0  /(R  0  ∩ Kα) is a simple R  0  -module. Up to <lb/>isomorphism, every C[t]-torsion-free simple R  0  -module arises <lb/>in this way. <lb/> (b) Any simple quotient of the R  ˙ <lb/> z  -module R  ˙ <lb/> z  /R  ˙ <lb/> z  t is 1-dimensional. <lb/> (c) For any λ ∈ C <lb/>  *  , the R  dotz  -module R  ˙ <lb/> z  /R  ˙ <lb/> z  (t − λ) is simple. <lb/> (d) Let V be a simple C[t]-torsion-free R  ˙ <lb/> z  -module. Then t acts bijec-<lb/>tively on V . <lb/>Proof. Claim (ai) is [B, Theorem 2]. Claim (aii) follows from [B, The-<lb/>orem 4.3]. <lb/>To prove claim (b), note that R  ˙ <lb/> z  t is a two-sided ideal of R  ˙ <lb/> z  for any value <lb/>of ˙ <lb/> z. The algebra R  ˙ <lb/> z  /R  ˙ <lb/> z  t is easily checked to be the commutative <lb/>algebra C[ts] if ˙ <lb/> z  = 0. Similarly, if ˙ <lb/> z = 0, we have that R  ˙ <lb/> z  /R  ˙ <lb/> z  t ∼ = <lb/> C[t <lb/> 2  s]. All simple modules over the latter commutative algebras have <lb/>dimension one. <lb/>To prove claim (c), observe that {(ts) <lb/> i  |i ∈ Z  +  } is a basis in R  ˙ <lb/> z  /R  ˙ <lb/> z  (t−λ) <lb/>if ˙ <lb/> z  = 0. Moreover, if ˙ <lb/> z = 0, then {(t <lb/> 2  s) <lb/> i  |i ∈ Z  +  } is a basis in the <lb/>quotient R  ˙ <lb/> z  /R  ˙ <lb/> z  (t − λ). Using this it is easy to verify that the R  ˙ <lb/> z  -<lb/>module R  ˙ <lb/> z  /R  ˙ <lb/> z  (t − λ) is simple. <lb/>Claim (d) follows from the fact that tV is an R  ˙ <lb/> z  -submodule of V and <lb/>hence is equal to V . <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SIMPLE WEIGHT MODULES OVER AGEING ALGEBRA <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body> Next we characterize the associative algebra U  0  . Denote by A the first <lb/>Weyl algebra, which we realize as the unital subalgebra of the algebra <lb/>of all linear operators on C[t] generated by the linear operator <lb/> d <lb/> dt <lb/> and <lb/>the linear operator of multiplication by t (which we will denote simply <lb/>by t). Alternatively, one can also think of the algebra A as the unital <lb/>subalgebra of the algebra K generated by t and s. In particular, we <lb/>can view R  0  as a subalgebra of A generated by t and t <lb/> 2 d <lb/>dt <lb/> . Similarly, <lb/>we can view R  1  as a subalgebra of A generated by t and t <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> . <lb/> Lemma 2. <lb/> (a) The associative algebra U  0  is generated by eq <lb/> 2  , pq, h, and z and <lb/> {(eq <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> i  1  (pq) <lb/> i  2  h <lb/> i  3  z <lb/> i  4  |i  1  , i  2  , i  3  , i  4  ∈ Z  +  } <lb/> is a basis of U  0  . In particular, for any ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h ∈ C, the image of <lb/> {(eq <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> i  1  (pq) <lb/> i  2  |i  1  , i  2  ∈ Z  +  } in U  0  /h − ˙ <lb/> h, z − ˙ <lb/> z forms a basis there. <lb/> (b) For any ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h ∈ C, there is a unique homomorphism of associative <lb/>algebras ϕ  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  : U  0  → A such that ϕ  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  (z) = ˙ <lb/> z, ϕ  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  (h) = ˙ <lb/> h and <lb/> (i) ϕ  0, ˙ <lb/> h  (pq) = t, ϕ  0, ˙ <lb/> h  (eq <lb/> 2  ) = t <lb/> 2 d <lb/>dt <lb/> if ˙ <lb/> z = 0; <lb/>(ii) ϕ  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  (pq) = 2 ˙ <lb/> zt <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> , ϕ  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  (eq <lb/> 2  ) = t + ˙ <lb/> zt <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> + 2 ˙ <lb/> z(t <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> ) <lb/> 2  if ˙ <lb/> z  = 0. <lb/>(c) We have ϕ  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  (U  0  ) = R  ˙ <lb/> z  and U  0  /h − ˙ <lb/> h, z − ˙ <lb/> z ∼ = R  ˙ <lb/> z  . <lb/> (d) The isomorphism in (c) induces a natural bijection between isomor-<lb/>phism classes of simple U  0  -modules on which h acts as ˙ <lb/> h and z acts <lb/>as ˙ <lb/> z and isomorphism classes of simple R  ˙ <lb/> z  -modules. <lb/>Proof. To prove claim (a) we argue that, by the PBW Theorem, the <lb/>algebra U  0  has a basis <lb/> {e <lb/> i  1  q <lb/> 2i  1  +i  2  p <lb/> i  2  z <lb/> i  3  h <lb/> i  4  |i  1  , i  2  , i  3  , i  4  ∈ Z  +  } = <lb/> {(e <lb/> i  1  q <lb/> 2i  1  )(q <lb/> i  2  p <lb/> i  2  )z <lb/> i  3  h <lb/> i  4  |i  1  , i  2  , i  3  , i  4  ∈ Z  +  }. <lb/> Step 1: The element q <lb/> i  p <lb/> i  can be written as a linear combination of <lb/>elements of the form (pq) <lb/> j  z <lb/> i−j  for j ∈ Z  +  . <lb/>This follows by induction on i from the following computation: <lb/> q <lb/> i+1  p <lb/> i+1  = q <lb/> i+1  pp <lb/> i  = pqq <lb/> i  p <lb/> i  − (i + 1)q <lb/> i  p <lb/> i  z. <lb/> Step 2: The element e <lb/> i  q <lb/> 2i  can be written as a linear combination of <lb/>elements of the form (eq <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> k  (pq) <lb/> j  z <lb/> i−k−j  for k, j ∈ Z  +  with i ≥ k + j. <lb/> This follows by induction on i from the following computation: <lb/> e <lb/> i+1  q <lb/> 2(i+1)  = ee <lb/> i  qq <lb/> 2i+1  = eqe <lb/> i  q <lb/> 2i+1  + ie <lb/> i  pq <lb/> 2i+1  = <lb/> eq <lb/> 2  e <lb/> i  q <lb/> 2i  + 2ie <lb/> i  pq <lb/> 2i+1  = (eq <lb/> 2  )(e <lb/> i  q <lb/> 2i  ) + 2i((e <lb/> i  q <lb/> 2i  )(pq) + 2ie <lb/> i  q <lb/> 2i  z). <lb/></body>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> RENCAI L ¨ <lb/>U, VOLODYMYR MAZORCHUK AND KAIMING ZHAO <lb/></note>

			<body> Claim (a) follows easily from Steps 1 and 2. <lb/>To prove claim (b), we only need to check <lb/> ϕ  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  ([eq <lb/> 2  , pq]) = [ϕ  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  (eq <lb/> 2  ), ϕ  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  (pq)] <lb/>for any ˙ <lb/> z and ˙ <lb/> h. Note that <lb/>[eq <lb/> 2  , pq] = [eq <lb/> 2  , p]q + p[eq <lb/> 2  , q] <lb/> = −2zeq <lb/> 2  + p(pq)q <lb/> = −2zeq <lb/> 2  + zpq + (pq) <lb/> 2  . <lb/> Therefore we have [ϕ  0, ˙ <lb/> h  (eq <lb/> 2  ), ϕ  0, ˙ <lb/> h  (pq)] = [t <lb/> 2 d <lb/>dt <lb/> , t] = t <lb/> 2  while <lb/> ϕ  0, ˙ <lb/> h  ([eq <lb/> 2  , pq]) = ϕ  0, ˙ <lb/> h  (−2zeq <lb/> 2  + zpq + (pq) <lb/> 2  ) = t <lb/> 2  , <lb/> which implies (bi). <lb/>Similarly, for ˙ <lb/> z  = 0 we have <lb/> ϕ  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  ([eq <lb/> 2  , pq]) = ϕ  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  ((−2zeq <lb/> 2  + zpq + (pq) <lb/> 2  )) <lb/>= −2 ˙ <lb/> z(t + ˙ <lb/> zt <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> + 2 ˙ <lb/> z(t <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> ) <lb/> 2  ) + ˙ <lb/> z2 ˙ <lb/> zt <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> + (2 ˙ <lb/> zt <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> = −2 ˙ <lb/> zt, <lb/> while <lb/>[ϕ  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  (eq <lb/> 2  ), ϕ  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  (pq)] = [t + ˙ <lb/> zt <lb/>d <lb/>dt <lb/> + 2 ˙ <lb/> z(t <lb/>d <lb/>dt <lb/> ) <lb/> 2  , 2 ˙ <lb/> zt <lb/>d <lb/>dt <lb/> ] = −2 ˙ <lb/> zt, <lb/> which implies (bii). <lb/>Claim (c) follows from claims (a) and (b). Claim (d) follows from <lb/>claim (c). <lb/> Now we address the structure of Verma modules over age(1). <lb/> Lemma 3. <lb/> (a) Let ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h ∈ C. Then the age(1)-module M  age(1)  ( ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h) is simple if and <lb/>only if ˙ <lb/> z  = 0. <lb/>(b) Let ˙ <lb/> h ∈ C. Then we have dim ¯ <lb/> M  age(1)  (0, ˙ <lb/> h) = 1. <lb/> Proof. If ˙ <lb/> z  = 0, then the module M  age(1)  ( ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h) is obviously simple al-<lb/>ready as an H-module, which implies (a). If ˙ <lb/> z = 0, we have a simple <lb/> age(1)-module Cv with action ev = pv = qv = zv = 0 and hv = ˙ <lb/> hv. <lb/> By the universal property of Verma modules, M  age(1)  (0, ˙ <lb/> h) surjects onto <lb/> Cv and hence ¯ <lb/> M  age(1)  (0, ˙ <lb/> h) = Cv, which implies (b). <lb/> Remark 4. Lemma 3 describes all simple highest weight age(1)-mo-<lb/> dules. Let V be a simple highest weight age(1)-module. Consider the <lb/>decomposition V = ⊕  ˙ <lb/> h∈C  V  ˙ <lb/> h  and note that all V  ˙ <lb/> h  are finite dimensional. <lb/>As usual, the space V <lb/> ⋆  = ⊕  ˙ <lb/> h∈C  Hom  C  (V  ˙ <lb/> h  , C) has the natural structure <lb/>of an age(1)-module defied using the canonical involution x → −x, <lb/> x ∈ age(1). The module V <lb/> ⋆  is a simple lowest weight age(1)-module <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SIMPLE WEIGHT MODULES OVER AGEING ALGEBRA <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body> and the correspondence V  → V <lb/> ⋆  is a bijection between the sets of <lb/>isomorphism classes of simple highest weight and simple lowest weight <lb/>modules. <lb/>Before constructing some other weight age(1)-modules, we have to de-<lb/>fine some automorphisms of the associative algebras U  0  and R  ˙ <lb/> z  . <lb/> Lemma 5. For any i ∈ Z there is a unique τ  i  ∈ Aut(U  0  ) such that <lb/> τ  i  (pq) = pq + iz, τ  i  (h) = h − i, τ  i  (z) = z, <lb/>τ  i  (eq <lb/> 2  ) = eq <lb/> 2  + ipq + <lb/> i(i + 1) <lb/>2 <lb/> z. <lb/> Proof. From Lemma 2.1(a), we know that U  0  is a PBW-algebra on <lb/>the generating set {eq <lb/> 2  , pq, h, z}. One can find the concept of PBW-<lb/>algebras in [BTLC]. Then we need only to verify the relations on the <lb/>generating elements eq <lb/> 2  , pq, h, and z. We have <lb/>[τ  i  (eq <lb/> 2  ), τ  i  (pq)] = [eq <lb/> 2  + ipq + <lb/> i(i+1) <lb/> 2 <lb/> z, pq + iz] <lb/> = [eq <lb/> 2  , pq] <lb/> = −2zeq <lb/> 2  + zpq + (pq) <lb/> 2 <lb/> while <lb/> τ  i  ([eq <lb/> 2  , pq]) = τ  i  (−2zeq <lb/> 2  + zpq + (pq) <lb/> 2  ) <lb/>= −2z(eq <lb/> 2  + ipq + <lb/> i(i+1) <lb/> 2 <lb/> z) + z(pq + iz) + (pq + iz) <lb/> 2 <lb/> = −2zeq <lb/> 2  + zpq + (pq) <lb/> 2  . <lb/> Thus [τ  i  (eq <lb/> 2  ), τ  i  (pq)] = τ  i  ([eq <lb/> 2  , pq]). All other relations are checked <lb/>similarly. <lb/> The proof of the next lemma is a straightforward computation which <lb/>is left to the reader. Here we use the embedding of R  ˙ <lb/> z  in the first Weyl <lb/>algebra A as in the paragraph before Lemma 2. <lb/> Lemma 6. For any i ∈ Z and ˙ <lb/> z ∈ C there is a unique τ  i, ˙ <lb/> z  ∈ Aut(R  ˙ <lb/> z  ) <lb/> such that <lb/> τ  i,0  (t) = t, τ  i,0  (t <lb/> 2  d <lb/>dt <lb/> ) = t <lb/> 2  d <lb/>dt <lb/> + it if ˙ <lb/> z = 0; <lb/> τ  i, ˙ <lb/> z  (t) = t, τ  i, ˙ <lb/> z  (t <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> ) = t <lb/>d <lb/>dt <lb/> + <lb/> i <lb/> 2 <lb/> if ˙ <lb/> z  = 0. <lb/>The next step is to construct some weight age(1)-modules using R  ˙ <lb/> z  -<lb/>modules. From now on in this section N denotes an R  ˙ <lb/> z  -module. We <lb/>define the age(1)-module N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  as follows: as a vector space we set <lb/> N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  = N ⊗ C[x, x <lb/> −1  ] and then for v ∈ N define <lb/>(3.1) q(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = v ⊗ x <lb/> i+1  , p(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = (ϕ  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  (pq + (i − 1)z)v) ⊗ x <lb/> i−1  , <lb/></body>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> RENCAI L ¨ <lb/>U, VOLODYMYR MAZORCHUK AND KAIMING ZHAO <lb/></note>

			<body> (3.2) e(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = (ϕ  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  (eq <lb/> 2  + (i − 2)pq + <lb/>(i − 1)(i − 2) <lb/>2 <lb/> z)v) ⊗ x <lb/> i−2  , <lb/> (3.3) <lb/> h(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = (( ˙ <lb/> h − i)v) ⊗ x <lb/> i  , z(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = ( ˙ <lb/> zv) ⊗ x <lb/> i  . <lb/> By a straightforward computation we get the following: <lb/> Lemma 7. <lb/> (a) Formulae (3.1), (3.2) and (3.3) define on N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  the structure of an <lb/> age(1)-module. <lb/> (b) For ˙ <lb/> z = 0 the action in (3.1), (3.2) and (3.3) reads as follows <lb/> (3.4) <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> h(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = ( ˙ <lb/> h − i)v ⊗ x <lb/> i  , z(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = 0, <lb/> q(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = v ⊗ x <lb/> i+1  , p(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = (tv) ⊗ x <lb/> i−1  , <lb/>e(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = ((t <lb/> 2  d <lb/>dt <lb/> + (i − 2)t)v) ⊗ x <lb/> i−2  . <lb/> (c) For ˙ <lb/> z  = 0 the action in (3.1), (3.2) and (3.3) reads as follows <lb/> (3.5) <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> h(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = ( ˙ <lb/> h − i)v ⊗ x <lb/> i  , z(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = ˙ <lb/> zv ⊗ x <lb/> i  , <lb/>q(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = v ⊗ x <lb/> i+1  , p(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = ((2 ˙ <lb/> zt <lb/>d <lb/>dt <lb/> + (i − 1) ˙ <lb/> z)v) ⊗ x <lb/> i−1  , <lb/>e(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = ((t + (2i − 3) ˙ <lb/> zt <lb/>d <lb/>dt <lb/> + 2 ˙ <lb/> z(t <lb/>d <lb/>dt <lb/> ) <lb/> 2  + <lb/>(i − 1)(i − 2) <lb/>2 <lb/>˙ <lb/> z)v) ⊗ x <lb/> i−2  . <lb/> For an associative algebra A, an A-module V and σ ∈ Aut(A), we <lb/>denote by V <lb/> σ  the module obtained from V via twisting the action of <lb/> A by σ, that is a · v = σ(a)v for a ∈ A and v ∈ V . <lb/>For each i ∈ Z the space N ⊗ x <lb/> i  is naturally a U  0  -module. We may <lb/>even make N ⊗ x <lb/> i  into an R  ˙ <lb/> z  -module as follows: <lb/>If ˙ <lb/> z = 0, then for any v ∈ N, we set <lb/>(3.6) <lb/> t(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = (pq)(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = (tv) ⊗ x <lb/> i  , <lb/> (t <lb/> 2  d <lb/>dt <lb/> )(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = (eq <lb/> 2  )(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = ((t <lb/> 2  d <lb/>dt <lb/> + it)v) ⊗ x <lb/> i  . <lb/> If ˙ <lb/> z  = 0, then for any v ∈ N, we set <lb/>(3.7) <lb/> t(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = (eq <lb/> 2  − <lb/> pq <lb/> 2 <lb/> − 2 ˙ <lb/> z( <lb/>pq <lb/> 2 ˙ <lb/> z <lb/> ) <lb/> 2  )(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = (tv) ⊗ x <lb/> i  , <lb/> (t <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> )(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = ( <lb/> pq <lb/> 2 ˙ <lb/> z <lb/> )(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = ((t <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> + <lb/> i <lb/> 2 <lb/>)v) ⊗ x <lb/> i  . <lb/> The following standard result asserts that any simple weight module is <lb/>uniquely determined by any of its nonzero weight spaces. <lb/> Lemma 8. Let g be age(1) or S. Let V and W be simple weight g-<lb/> modules such that for some ˙ <lb/> h ∈ wt(V ) the U(g)  0  modules V  ˙ <lb/> h  and W  ˙ <lb/> h <lb/> are isomorphic. Then V ∼ = W . <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SIMPLE WEIGHT MODULES OVER AGEING ALGEBRA <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body> Proof. Set N = V  ˙ <lb/> h  = W  ˙ <lb/> h  and write <lb/> U(g) = <lb/> i∈Z <lb/> U  i  where U  i  = {x ∈ U(g)|[h, y] = iy}. <lb/> Every U  i  is a U(g)  0  -U(g)  0  -bimodule. Consider the induced module <lb/> M := Ind <lb/> U (g) <lb/> U (g)  0 <lb/> N = U(g) <lb/> U (g)  0 <lb/> N = <lb/> i∈Z <lb/> (U  i  ⊗  U (g)  0  N). <lb/> Then, by adjunction, both V and W are simple quotients of M. The <lb/>module M is, clearly, a weight g-module with M  ˙ <lb/> h <lb/> ∼ = N, the latter being <lb/>a simple U(g)  0  -module, which implies, using standard arguments, that <lb/> M has a unique maximal submodule K satisfying K  ˙ <lb/> h  = 0 and thus the <lb/>unique corresponding simple quotient M/K. As both V and W have <lb/>to be quotients of M/K by adjunction, we get V ∼ = W . <lb/> Now we list some properties of the age(1)-module N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  . <lb/> Lemma 9. <lb/> (a) For every i ∈ Z the U  0  -modules N ⊗ x <lb/> i  and N <lb/> τ  i  are isomorphic. <lb/> (b) The age(1)-module N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  is simple if and only if N is a simple R  ˙ <lb/> z  -<lb/>module and one of the following conditions is satisfied: <lb/> (i) ˙ <lb/> z = 0 and (Ct + Ct <lb/> 2 d <lb/>dt <lb/> )N  = 0; <lb/>(ii) ˙ <lb/> z  = 0 and τ  i, ˙ <lb/> z  (Ct + Ct <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> )N  = 0 for all i ∈ Z. <lb/> (c) Let ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h, ˙ <lb/> z <lb/> ′  , ˙ <lb/> h <lb/> ′  ∈ C. Let further N be an R  ˙ <lb/> z  -module and N <lb/> ′  be an <lb/> R  ˙ <lb/> z  ′  -module. Assume that N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  and N <lb/> ′ <lb/> ˙ <lb/> z  ′  , ˙ <lb/> h  ′  are simple. Then we have <lb/> N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h <lb/> ∼ = N <lb/> ′ <lb/> ˙ <lb/> z  ′  , ˙ <lb/> h  ′  if and only if ˙ <lb/> z = ˙ <lb/> z <lb/> ′  , i := ˙ <lb/> h − ˙ <lb/> h <lb/> ′  ∈ Z and N <lb/> ′  ∼ = N <lb/> τ  i, ˙ <lb/> z <lb/> as R  ˙ <lb/> z  -modules. <lb/>Proof. Let ψ : N ⊗ x <lb/> i  → N <lb/> τ  i  be the linear map defined as ψ(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = v <lb/> for all v ∈ A. It is straightforward to verify that <lb/> ψ(pq(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  )) = ψ(((pq + i ˙ <lb/> z)v) ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = (pq + iz)v = τ  i  (pq)v, <lb/> ψ((eq <lb/> 2  )(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  )) = ψ((eq <lb/> 2  + ipq + <lb/> i(i + 1) <lb/>2 <lb/>˙ <lb/> z)v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) <lb/>= (eq <lb/> 2  + ipq + <lb/> i(i + 1) <lb/>2 <lb/>˙ <lb/> z)v = τ  i  (eq <lb/> 2  )ψ(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ), <lb/> ψ(h(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  )) = ψ(( ˙ <lb/> h − i)v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = ( ˙ <lb/> h − i)v = τ  i  (h)ψ(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ), <lb/> ψ(z(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  )) = ψ( ˙ <lb/> zv ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = τ  i  (z)ψ(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ). <lb/>This implies claim (a). <lb/></body>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> RENCAI L ¨ <lb/>U, VOLODYMYR MAZORCHUK AND KAIMING ZHAO <lb/></note>

			<body> To prove claim (b), we observe that simplicity of N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  clearly requires <lb/>simplicity of N. Now suppose that N is a simple R  ˙ <lb/> z  -module. We study <lb/>simplicity of N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  using a case-by-case analysis. <lb/> Case 1. Assume ˙ <lb/> z = 0 and (Ct + Ct <lb/> 2 d <lb/>dt <lb/> )N = 0. <lb/>In this case, from (3.4) we get eN  0, ˙ <lb/> h  = pN  0, ˙ <lb/> h  = 0. Hence each nonzero <lb/>weight element of N  0, ˙ <lb/> h  generates a proper highest weight submodule. <lb/> Case 2. Assume ˙ <lb/> z = 0 and (Ct + Ct <lb/> 2 d <lb/>dt <lb/> )N  = 0. <lb/>Since N is a simple R  ˙ <lb/> z  -module, we have (Ct + Ct <lb/> 2 d <lb/>dt <lb/> )v  = 0 for any <lb/>nonzero v ∈ N. From (3.4) it follows that for each i ∈ Z we either have <lb/> p(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  )  = 0 or e(v ⊗ x <lb/> j  )  = 0. As the action of q on N  0, ˙ <lb/> h  is injective, <lb/>it follows that any nonzero submodule V of N  0, ˙ <lb/> h  has support ˙ <lb/> h + Z. <lb/> Now from claim (a) we get V = N  0, ˙ <lb/> h  , that is any nonzero submodule <lb/> V coincides with N  0, ˙ <lb/> h  and thus N  0, ˙ <lb/> h  is simple. <lb/> Case 3. Assume ˙ <lb/> z  = 0 and τ  i, ˙ <lb/> z  (Ct + Ct <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> )N = 0 for some i ∈ Z. <lb/> In this case, we have N = Cv with tv = 0, (t <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> )v = − <lb/> i <lb/> 2 <lb/> v. From (3.5), <lb/>we have p(v ⊗ x <lb/> i+1  ) = e(v ⊗ x <lb/> i+1  ) = 0 and hence v ⊗ x <lb/> i+1  generates a <lb/>proper highest weight submodule of N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  . Therefore N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  is not simple. <lb/> Case 4. Assume ˙ <lb/> z  = 0 and τ  i, ˙ <lb/> z  (Ct + Ct <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> )N  = 0 for all i ∈ Z. <lb/> Since N is a simple R  ˙ <lb/> z  -module, have τ  i, ˙ <lb/> z  (Ct + Ct <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> )v  = 0 for any <lb/>nonzero v ∈ N. From (3.5) it follows that for each i ∈ Z we have either <lb/> p(vx <lb/> i+1  )  = 0 or e(vx <lb/> i+2  )  = 0 for some v ∈ N. Similarly to Case 2 we <lb/>deduce that N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  is simple. This completes the proof of claim (b). <lb/>To prove claim (c), first assume N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h <lb/> ∼ = N <lb/> ′ <lb/> ˙ <lb/> z  ′  , ˙ <lb/> h  ′  . Then we have i = <lb/> h − h <lb/> ′  ∈ Z, ˙ <lb/> z = ˙ <lb/> z <lb/> ′  and N <lb/> ′  ∼ = N ⊗ x <lb/> i  as U  0  -modules. From (3.6) and <lb/>(3.7) it follows that A <lb/> ′  ∼ = N <lb/> τ  i, ˙ <lb/> z <lb/> as R  ˙ <lb/> z  -modules. <lb/>Now suppose that ˙ <lb/> z = ˙ <lb/> z <lb/> ′  , i = ˙ <lb/> h− ˙ <lb/> h <lb/> ′  ∈ Z and N <lb/> ′  ∼ = N <lb/> τ  i, ˙ <lb/> z <lb/> as R  ˙ <lb/> z  -modules. <lb/>From (3.6) and (3.7) it follows that N <lb/> ′  ∼ = N ⊗ x <lb/> i  as U  0  -modules. From <lb/>Lemma 8 we thus get N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h <lb/> ∼ = N <lb/> ′ <lb/> ˙ <lb/> z  ′  , ˙ <lb/> h  ′  . This completes the proof. <lb/> Remark 10. Let N be a simple R  ˙ <lb/> z  -module. If we have ˙ <lb/> z = 0 and <lb/>(Ct + Ct <lb/> 2 d <lb/>dt <lb/> )N = 0, then dim N = 1. If ˙ <lb/> z  = 0 and τ  i, ˙ <lb/> z  (Ct + Ct <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> )N = 0 <lb/>for some i ∈ Z, then dim N = 1. Thus, if N is an infinite dimensional <lb/>simple R  ˙ <lb/> z  -module, then N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  is a simple weight age(1)-module. <lb/> Now we are ready to prove our main result on classification of all simple <lb/>weight age(1)-modules. <lb/> Theorem 11. Each simple weight age(1)-module is isomorphic to one <lb/>of the following simple modules: <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SIMPLE WEIGHT MODULES OVER AGEING ALGEBRA <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body> (i) A simple highest or lowest weight module. <lb/> (ii) The module Q(λ, ˙ <lb/> h) = C[x, x <lb/> −1  ], where ˙ <lb/> h ∈ C and λ ∈ C <lb/>  *  , with <lb/>the action given by: <lb/> zx <lb/> i  = px <lb/> i  = 0, qx <lb/> i  = x <lb/> i+1  , ex <lb/> i  = λx <lb/> i−2  , hx <lb/> i  = ( ˙ <lb/> h − i)x <lb/> i  . <lb/> (iii) The module Q <lb/> ′  ( ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h, λ) = C[x, x <lb/> −1  ], where ˙ <lb/> h ∈ C, ˙ <lb/> z ∈ C <lb/>  *  and <lb/> λ ∈ C\Z, with the action given by: <lb/> qx <lb/> i  = x <lb/> i+1  , px <lb/> i  = ˙ <lb/> z(λ + i)x <lb/> i−1  , zx <lb/> i  = ˙ <lb/> zx <lb/> i  , <lb/>hx <lb/> i  = ( ˙ <lb/> h − i)x <lb/> i  , ex <lb/> i  = <lb/>˙ <lb/> z <lb/> 2 <lb/>(λ + i)(λ + i − 1)x <lb/> i−2  . <lb/> (iv) The module N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  , where N is an infinite dimensional simple R  ˙ <lb/> z  -<lb/>module. <lb/>Proof. It is straightforward to verify that Q(λ, ˙ <lb/> h) in (ii) and Q <lb/> ′  ( ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h, λ) <lb/> in (iii) are simple age(1)-modules. From Remark 10 we know that the <lb/>module N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  in (iv) is a simple age(1)-module. <lb/> Let V be any simple weight age(1)-module. Assume that ˙ <lb/> h ∈ wt(V ) <lb/>and that z acts on V as the scalar ˙ <lb/> z. Then V  ˙ <lb/> h  is both, a simple U  0  -<lb/>module and a simple R  ˙ <lb/> z  -module. By Lemma 1 we have that V  ˙ <lb/> h  either <lb/>is a one-dimensional module with tV  ˙ <lb/> h  = 0 or is an infinite dimensional <lb/>module with t acting bijectively on it. If N = V  ˙ <lb/> h  has infinite dimension, <lb/>then V ∼ = N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  by Lemma 8. Therefore it remains to consider the case <lb/>when all nontrivial weight spaces of V have dimension one. <lb/>If V has a nonzero element annihilated by q, then V is clearly a lowest <lb/>weight module. Therefore we may assume that q acts injectively on V . <lb/>Let 0  = w ∈ V  ˙ <lb/> h  and consider first the case ˙ <lb/> z = 0. <lb/>In this case, we have tw = pqw = 0 and hence pw = 0 since the action of <lb/> q is injective. This implies that the ideal Cp + Cz of age(1) annihilates <lb/> V . Let a = age(1)/(Cp + Cz). Then V is a simple a-module. Denote <lb/>by ¯ <lb/> x the image of x ∈ age(1) in a. Note that ¯ <lb/> e¯ q <lb/> 2  is a central element <lb/>in U(a). By Schur&apos;s lemma, ¯ <lb/> e¯ q <lb/> 2  acts on V as a scalar, say λ ∈ C. If <lb/> λ = 0, then e(q <lb/> 2  w) = 0 and V is a highest weight module. If λ  = 0, <lb/>then it is easy to check that V ∼ = Q(λ, ˙ <lb/> h). <lb/> Finally, consider the case ˙ <lb/> z  = 0. In this case, w generates an H-<lb/> submodule of V with nonzero central charge and one-dimensional weight <lb/>spaces. Consequently, V contains a simple Ch + H submodule M with <lb/>nonzero central charge. We make M into an age(1)-module by setting <lb/> ev = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 ˙ <lb/> z <lb/> p <lb/> 2  v and denote the resulting module by M <lb/> age(1)  . Let Cv be <lb/>the one-dimensional trivial Ch + H-module. Then [LZ1, Lemma 8 and <lb/></body>

			<page> 12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> RENCAI L ¨ <lb/>U, VOLODYMYR MAZORCHUK AND KAIMING ZHAO <lb/></note>

			<body> Theorem 7] yield that V is isomorphic to a simple quotient of <lb/>Ind <lb/> age(1) <lb/> Ch+H  (M ⊗ Cv) ∼ = M <lb/> age(1)  ⊗ Ind <lb/> age(1) <lb/> Ch+H Cv, <lb/> which is of the form M <lb/> age(1)  ⊗ X, where X is a simple quotient of <lb/>Ind <lb/> age(1) <lb/> Ch+H Cv. Since M <lb/> age(1)  ⊗ X is a weight module, we get that X is <lb/>the trivial module and hence V ∼ = M <lb/> age(1)  . This gives that V is either <lb/>a highest weight module or is isomorphic to Q <lb/> ′  ( ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h, λ) with λ ∈ C \ Z. <lb/> This completes the proof. <lb/> The following result is a direct consequence of Theorem 11. <lb/> Corollary 12. Let V be a simple weight age(1)-module and ˙ <lb/> h ∈ wt(V ). <lb/> Then either dim V  ˙ <lb/> h+i  ≤ 1 for all i ∈ Z or dim V  ˙ <lb/> h+i  = ∞ for all i ∈ Z. <lb/> Next we present a nontrivial example of a simple weight age(1)-module <lb/> with infinite dimensional weight spaces. <lb/> Example 13. Let α = 1 − t <lb/> 3  (t − 1) <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> ∈ K. It is easy to see that α <lb/> is irreducible in K. Then N = R  0  /(R  0  ∩ Kα) is a simple R  0  -module <lb/>such that t acts bijectively on N. This implies that N is also a simple <lb/> R  1  -module and a simple module over the localization of A at t. In fact, <lb/>we have N = (t − 1) <lb/> −1  C[t, t <lb/> −1  ] with the following action: <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> · g(t) = <lb/> dg(t) <lb/>dt <lb/> + <lb/> g(t) <lb/>t  3  (t − 1) <lb/> , t · g(t) = tg(t) for all g(t) ∈ N. <lb/> Thus we have the simple age(1)-module N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  = (t − 1) <lb/> −1  C[t, t <lb/> −1  , x, x <lb/> −1  ] <lb/>with the action <lb/> h := ˙ <lb/> h − ∂  x  , z := 0, q := x, p := tx <lb/> −1  , <lb/>e := x <lb/> −2  t∂  t  + <lb/>1 <lb/> t(t − 1)x  2  + tx <lb/> −2  ∂  x  − 2tx <lb/> −2  . <lb/> if ˙ <lb/> z = 0, and the action <lb/> h := ˙ <lb/> h − ∂  x  , z := ˙ <lb/> z, q := x, p := x <lb/> −1  ˙ <lb/> z(2∂  t  + <lb/>2 <lb/> t  2  (t − 1) <lb/>+ ∂  x  − 1), <lb/> e := ˙ <lb/> zx <lb/> −2 <lb/>  t <lb/> ˙ <lb/> z <lb/> + (2∂  x  − 3)(∂  t  + <lb/>1 <lb/> t  2  (t − 1) <lb/>) + 2∂ <lb/> 2 <lb/> t  + <lb/>4 <lb/> t  2  (t − 1) <lb/> ∂  t  − <lb/> 2 + 2t + 6t <lb/> 2 <lb/> t  4  (t − 1)  2  + <lb/>(∂  x  − 1)(∂  x  − 2) <lb/>2 <lb/> , <lb/> if ˙ <lb/> z  = 0 (here ∂  x  = x <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂x <lb/> and ∂  t  = t <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t <lb/> ). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SIMPLE WEIGHT MODULES OVER AGEING ALGEBRA <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body> 4. Simple weight S-modules having a simple <lb/> age(1)-submodule <lb/> In this section we classify all simple weight S-modules that have a <lb/>simple age(1)-submodule. <lb/> Let V be a simple weight age(1)-module. We have the induced weight <lb/> S-module H(V ) := Ind <lb/> S <lb/> age(1)  V which can be identified with C[f ] ⊗ V as <lb/>a vector space. In this section we classify all simple quotient S-modules <lb/> of H(V ). From [DLMZ, Corollary 8] we know that the center Z(U(S)) <lb/> of U(S) equals C[z, c], where <lb/>(4.1) <lb/> c := (f p <lb/> 2  − eq <lb/> 2  − hpq) − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(h <lb/> 2  + h + 4f e)z. <lb/> Recall some simple S-module constructed in [LMZ] and [D]. Let V be <lb/>any simple module over H with nonzero central charge ˙ <lb/> z. The module <lb/> V becomes an S-module by setting <lb/>(4.2) ev = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 ˙ <lb/> z <lb/>p <lb/> 2  v, f v = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 ˙ <lb/> z <lb/>q <lb/> 2  v, hv = (− <lb/> pq <lb/> ˙ <lb/> z <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>)v, where v ∈ V. <lb/> The resulting module will be denoted by V <lb/> S  . <lb/>Any simple sl  2  -module W becomes an S-module by setting HW = 0. <lb/>The resulting module will also be denoted by W <lb/> S  . <lb/>Next let us define a class of simple weight S-modules. Let N be an <lb/>infinite dimensional simple R  ˙ <lb/> z  -module. Let A  (t)  denote the localiza-<lb/>tion of A at powers of t, which is actually the differential operator <lb/>algebra C[t, t <lb/> −1  , <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> ]. Then N is also naturally an A  (t)  -module since t <lb/> acts bijectively on N, see Lemma 1(d). Let ˙ <lb/> c, ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h ∈ C. Then we have <lb/>the simple weight age(1)-module N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  given by Lemma 7. We extend <lb/>this age(1)-module N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  to an S-module N  ˙ <lb/> c, ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  as follows: For ˙ <lb/> z = 0 we <lb/>set: <lb/>(4.3) <lb/> h(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = ( ˙ <lb/> h − i)v ⊗ x <lb/> i  , z(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = 0, <lb/> q(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = v ⊗ x <lb/> i+1  , p(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = (tv)x <lb/> i−1  , <lb/>e(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = ((t <lb/> 2 d <lb/>dt <lb/> + (i − 2)t)v) ⊗ x <lb/> i−2  , <lb/>f (v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = (( <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> + ( ˙ <lb/> h − 2)t <lb/> −1  + ˙ <lb/> ct <lb/> −2  )v) ⊗ x <lb/> i+2  . <lb/> For ˙ <lb/> z  = 0 we set: <lb/>(4.4) <lb/> h(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = ( ˙ <lb/> h − i)v ⊗ x <lb/> i  , z(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = ˙ <lb/> zv ⊗ x <lb/> i  , <lb/>q(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = vx <lb/> i+1  , p(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = ((2 ˙ <lb/> zt <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> + (i − 1) ˙ <lb/> z)v) ⊗ x <lb/> i−1  , <lb/>e(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = ((t + (2i − 3) ˙ <lb/> zt <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> + 2 ˙ <lb/> z(t <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> ) <lb/> 2  + <lb/> (i−1)(i−2) <lb/>2 <lb/> ˙ <lb/> z)v) ⊗ x <lb/> i−2  , <lb/>f (v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = ((− <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 ˙ <lb/> z <lb/> − ( ˙ <lb/> h − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ) <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> − t( <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> ) <lb/> 2  − ( <lb/> ( ˙ <lb/> h−1)( ˙ <lb/> h−2) <lb/> 4 <lb/> + <lb/> ˙ <lb/> c <lb/> 2 ˙ <lb/> z <lb/> )t <lb/> −1  )v) ⊗ x <lb/> i+2  . <lb/> Lemma 14. Formulae (4.3) and (4.4) indeed define the structure of <lb/>an S-module, moreover, the element c acts on N  ˙ <lb/> c, ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  as the scalar ˙ <lb/> c. <lb/></body>

			<page> 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> RENCAI L ¨ <lb/>U, VOLODYMYR MAZORCHUK AND KAIMING ZHAO <lb/></note>

			<body> Proof. If ˙ <lb/> z = 0, then from (3.4) we know that p = tx <lb/> −1  which acts <lb/>bijectively on N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  . From (4.1) we obtain that f = (eq <lb/> 2  + hpq + ˙ <lb/> c)p <lb/> −2  , <lb/>that is f (v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = (( <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> + ( ˙ <lb/> h − 2)t <lb/> −1  + ˙ <lb/> ct <lb/> −2  )v) ⊗ x <lb/> i+2  . This indicates the <lb/>formulae for ˙ <lb/> z = 0 and they are checked by a (long but) straightforward <lb/>computation. <lb/>If ˙ <lb/> z  = 0, then from (3.5) we know that <lb/> p <lb/> 2  − 2ze =(x <lb/> −1  (2 ˙ <lb/> z∂  t  + (∂  x  − 1) ˙ <lb/> z)) <lb/> 2  − <lb/>− 2x <lb/> −2  ˙ <lb/> z <lb/> t + ˙ <lb/> z(2∂  x  − 3))∂  t  + 2 ˙ <lb/> z∂ <lb/> 2 <lb/> t  + <lb/>(∂  x  − 1)(∂  x  − 2) <lb/>2 <lb/>˙ <lb/> z <lb/> = − 2 ˙ <lb/> ztx <lb/> −2 <lb/> which is bijective on A  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  . From (4.1) we obtain that <lb/> f = (eq <lb/> 2  + hpq + z(h <lb/> 2  + h)/2 + ˙ <lb/> c)(p <lb/> 2  − 2ze) <lb/> −1  , <lb/> that is f (v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) equals <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/> 2 ˙ <lb/> z <lb/> − <lb/> ˙ <lb/> h − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> − t <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/>  2  − <lb/> ( ˙ <lb/> h − 1)( ˙ <lb/> h − 2) <lb/>4 <lb/>+ <lb/>˙ <lb/> c <lb/> 2 ˙ <lb/> z <lb/> t <lb/> −1 <lb/> v <lb/> ⊗ x <lb/> i+2  . <lb/> This indicates the formulae for ˙ <lb/> z  = 0 and they are checked by a (long <lb/>but) straightforward computation. <lb/> Let ˙ <lb/> z ∈ C <lb/>  *  and λ ∈ C\Z. For convenience, we define the simple <lb/> H-module G( ˙ <lb/> z, λ) = C[x, x <lb/> −1  ] as follows (see [LMZ]): <lb/> qx <lb/> i  = x <lb/> i+1  , px <lb/> i  = ˙ <lb/> z(λ + i)x <lb/> i−1  , zx <lb/> i  = ˙ <lb/> zx <lb/> i  . <lb/> Note that the H-module G( ˙ <lb/> z, λ) is an H-submodule of the simple <lb/> age(1)-module Q <lb/> ′  ( ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h, λ) for any ˙ <lb/> h ∈ C. <lb/> Now we can formulate the main result of this section. <lb/> Theorem 15. Let V be a simple weight age(1)-module. <lb/> (a) If V is a highest weight module over age(1), then H(V ) is a highest <lb/>weight S-module, which has a unique simple quotient. <lb/> (b) If V ∼ = ¯ <lb/> M <lb/> − <lb/> age(1)  ( ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h) with ˙ <lb/> z  = 0, then <lb/> H(V ) ∼ = M <lb/> − <lb/>H  ( ˙ <lb/> z) <lb/> S  ⊗ M  sl  2  ( ˙ <lb/> h − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>) <lb/> S  . <lb/> The latter module has a unique simple quotient and this simple <lb/>quotient is isomorphic to M <lb/> − <lb/>H  ( ˙ <lb/> z) <lb/> S  ⊗ ¯ <lb/> M  sl  2  ( ˙ <lb/> h − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ) <lb/> S  . <lb/> (c) If V ∼ = Q(λ, ˙ <lb/> h) for some ˙ <lb/> h ∈ C and λ ∈ C <lb/>  *  , then H(V ) is simple. <lb/> (d) If V ∼ = Q <lb/> ′  ( ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h, λ) for some ˙ <lb/> h ∈ C, ˙ <lb/> z ∈ C <lb/>  *  , λ ∈ C\Z, then <lb/> H(V ) ∼ = G( ˙ <lb/> z, λ) <lb/> S  ⊗ M  sl  2  (λ + ˙ <lb/> h + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>) <lb/> S  . <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SIMPLE WEIGHT MODULES OVER AGEING ALGEBRA <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body> The latter module has a unique simple quotient and this simple <lb/>quotient is isomorphic to G( ˙ <lb/> z, λ) <lb/> S  ⊗ ¯ <lb/> M  sl  2  (λ + ˙ <lb/> h + <lb/> 1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> ) <lb/> S  . <lb/> (e) If V ∼ = N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  , where N is an infinite dimensional simple R  ˙ <lb/> z  -module, <lb/>then any simple quotient of H(V ) is isomorphic to N  ˙ <lb/> c, ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  for some <lb/> ˙ <lb/> c ∈ C. <lb/> Proof. Claim (a) is clear. To prove claim (b), we note that the module <lb/> V = ¯ <lb/> M <lb/> − <lb/> age(1)  ( ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h) has a simple H-submodule M <lb/> − <lb/>H  ( ˙ <lb/> z). Then, using (4.2), <lb/>we can extend the action of H on M <lb/> − <lb/>H  ( ˙ <lb/> z) to a lowest weight age(1)-<lb/> module ¯ <lb/> M <lb/> − <lb/> age(1)  ( ˙ <lb/> z, −1/2). Let Cv be the 1-dimensional age(1)-module <lb/> given by ev = pv = qv = zv = 0 and hv = ( ˙ <lb/> h − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> )v. Then we have <lb/> V ∼ = Cv ⊗ ¯ <lb/> M <lb/> − <lb/> age(1)  ( ˙ <lb/> z, −1/2). From [LMZ, Theorem 3] we know that <lb/> H(V ) ∼ = M <lb/> − <lb/>H  ( ˙ <lb/> z) <lb/> S  ⊗ ¯ <lb/> M  sl  2  ( ˙ <lb/> h − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ) <lb/> S  . The rest of claim (b) now follows <lb/>easily. <lb/>Let M be a nonzero submodule of H(V ). Then M is a weight module. <lb/>Choose 0  = v  n  = <lb/>  k <lb/>i=0  c  i  f <lb/> i  ⊗ x <lb/> n−2i  ∈ M such that k is minimal. If <lb/> k &gt; 0, then 0  = pv  n  = − <lb/>  k <lb/>i=1  ic  i  f <lb/> i−1  ⊗ x <lb/> n−2i−1  ∈ M which contradicts <lb/>our choice of v  n  . Hence k = 0 and v  n  ∈ 1 ⊗ V . Now M has to coincide <lb/>with H(V ) since V is a simple age(1)-module. Claim (c) follows. <lb/>To prove claim (d), we note that V = Q <lb/> ′  ( ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h, λ) has a simple H-sub-<lb/> module G( ˙ <lb/> z, λ). Then we apply (4.2) to make G( ˙ <lb/> z, λ) into an age(1)-<lb/> module G( ˙ <lb/> z, λ) <lb/> age(1)  with h(x <lb/> i  ) = −(λ + i + 1/2)x <lb/> i  . Let Cv be the <lb/>one-dimensional age(1)-module given by ev = pv = qv = zv = 0 <lb/>and hv = ( ˙ <lb/> h + λ + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> )v. Then V ∼ = Cv ⊗ G( ˙ <lb/> z, λ)  age(1)  . From [LMZ, <lb/>Theorem 3] we know that H(V ) ∼ = C( ˙ <lb/> z, λ) <lb/> S  ⊗ M  sl  2  (λ + ˙ <lb/> h + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ) <lb/> S  . The <lb/>rest of claim (d) now follows easily. <lb/>Finally, we prove claim (e). During the proof of Lemma 14 we computed <lb/>that in the module N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  we have p <lb/> 2  (v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = (t <lb/> 2  v) ⊗ x <lb/> i−2  if ˙ <lb/> z = 0 and <lb/>(p <lb/> 2  − 2ez)(v ⊗ x <lb/> i  ) = (−2 ˙ <lb/> ztv) ⊗ x <lb/> i−2  if ˙ <lb/> z  = 0. Recall that t acts <lb/>bijectively on N since N is infinite dimensional. Thus p <lb/> 2  − 2ez, which <lb/>is the coefficient at f in c, acts bijectively on N  ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  in this case. Let <lb/> M be any simple quotient of H(V ). Then c acts as the scalar ˙ <lb/> c on <lb/> M. Now we have f (1 ⊗ V ) ⊂ 1 ⊗ V in M, and the action of f is <lb/>uniquely determined by ˙ <lb/> c. Thus we have M ∼ = N  ˙ <lb/> c, ˙ <lb/> z, ˙ <lb/> h  . This completes <lb/>the proof. <lb/> Let age(1) <lb/> op  be the parabolic subalgebra of S spanned by {f, h, p, q, z}, <lb/> which is isomorphic to age(1). There are actually many simple weight <lb/> S-modules that do not contain any simple age(1)-submodule or any <lb/>simple age(1) <lb/> op  -submodule. For example, if we take V to be a simple <lb/>weight sl  2  -module that is not highest or lowest weight module and <lb/></body>

			<page> 16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> RENCAI L ¨ <lb/>U, VOLODYMYR MAZORCHUK AND KAIMING ZHAO <lb/></note>

			<body> ˙ <lb/> c  = 0, then the simple S-module V <lb/> S  ⊗ M  H  ( ˙ <lb/> z) <lb/> S  contains neither simple <lb/> age(1)-submodules nor simple age(1) <lb/> op  -submodules. <lb/>Taking into account the results of this paper it is natural to ask whether <lb/>one can classify all simple weight S-modules or all simple age(1)-module. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments. The research presented in this paper was car-<lb/>ried out during the visit of the first author to University of Waterloo <lb/>and of the second author to Wilfrid Laurier University. The first au-<lb/>thor thanks professors Wentang Kuo and Kaiming Zhao for sponsoring <lb/>his visit, and University of Waterloo for providing excellent working <lb/>conditions. The second author thanks Wilfrid Laurier University for <lb/>hospitality. We thank the referee for helpful comments and nice sug-<lb/>gestions. <lb/>R.L. is partially supported by NSF of China (Grant 11371134) and <lb/>Jiangsu Government Scholarship for Overseas Studies (JS-2013-313). <lb/>V.M. is partially supported by the Swedish Research Council. <lb/>K.Z. is partially supported by NSF of China (Grant 11271109) and <lb/>NSERC. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [AI] <lb/> N. Aizawa, P. S. Isaac. On irreducible representations of the exotic con-<lb/>formal Galilei algebra. J. Phys. A: Math. Theor. 44 (2011), 035401. <lb/>[AIK] <lb/>N. Aizawa, P. S. Isaac, Y. Kimura. Highest weight representations and <lb/>Kac determinants for a class of conformal Galilei algebras with central <lb/>extension. International Journal of Mathematics 23 (2012), No. 11, 1–25. <lb/>[BTLC] J. L. Bueso, J. Gomez Torrecillas, F. J. Lobillo, F. J. Castro, An intro-<lb/>duction to effective calculus in quantum groups, in: Caenepeel, Stefaan <lb/>et al. (Eds.), Rings, Hopf algebras, and Brauer groups. Proceedings of <lb/>the Fourth Week on Algebra and Algebraic Geometry, SAGA-4, Antwerp <lb/>and Brussels, Belgium, September 12-17, 1996, Marcel Dekker, New York, <lb/>NY, Lect. Notes Pure Appl. Math. vol. 197 (1998), 55-83. <lb/>[B] <lb/>R. Block. The irreducible representations of the Lie algebra sl(2) and of <lb/>the Weyl algebra. Adv. in Math. 139 (1981), no. 1, 69–110. <lb/>[BR] <lb/>A.J. Bray, A.D. Rutenberg. Growth laws for phase-ordering. Phys. Rev. <lb/>E 49, R27, (1994). <lb/>[CZ] <lb/>L. Cagliero, F. Szechtman. The classification of uniserial sl(2) ⋊ V (m)-<lb/>modules and a new interpretation Racah-Wigner 6j-symbols. J. Algebra <lb/> 386 (2013), 142–175. <lb/>[Di] <lb/>J. Dixmier. Enveloping algebras. Graduate Studies in Mathematics, 11. <lb/> American Mathematical Society, Providence, RI, 1996. <lb/>[DDM] V.K. Dobrev, H.-D. Doebner and C. Mrugalla. A q-Schrödinger al-<lb/>gebra, its lowest weight representations and generalized q-deformed <lb/>heat/Schrödinger equations. J. Phys. A 29 (1996), 5909–5918. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> SIMPLE WEIGHT MODULES OVER AGEING ALGEBRA <lb/></note>

			<page> 17 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [D] <lb/> B. Dubsky. Classification of simple weight modules with finite-dimensional <lb/>weight spaces over the Schrödinger algebra, Lin. Algebra Appl. 443 <lb/> (2014), 204–214. <lb/>[DLMZ] B. Dubsky, R. Lü, V. Mazorchuk, K. Zhao. Category O for the Schrödinger <lb/>algebra, arXiv: 1402.0334. Linear Algebra Appl., 460 (2014), 17-50. <lb/>[GIl] <lb/>A. Galajinsky, I. Masterov. Dynamical realization of l -conformal Galilei <lb/>algebra and oscillators. Nuclear Phys. B 866 (2013), no. 2, 212–227. <lb/>[GI2] <lb/>A. Galajinsky, I. Masterov. Remarks on l -conformal extension of the <lb/>Newton-Hooke algebra. Phys. Lett. B 702 (2011), no. 4, 265–267. <lb/>[HP] <lb/>P. Havas and J. Plebanski. Conformal extensions of the Galilei group and <lb/>their relation to the Schrödinger group. J. Math. Phys. 19 (1978), 482– <lb/>488. <lb/>[H1] <lb/>M. Henkel. Schrodinger-invariance in strongly anisotropic critical systems. <lb/>J. Stat. Phys. 75, 1023 (1994). <lb/>[H2] <lb/>M. Henkel. Local scale invariance and strongly anisotropic equilibrium <lb/>critical systems. Phys. Rev. Lett. 78, 1940 (1997). <lb/>[H3] <lb/>M. Henkel. Phenomenology of local scale-invariance: from conformal in-<lb/>variance to dynamical scaling. Nucl. Phys. B 641, 405 (2002). <lb/>[H4] <lb/>M. Henkel. Causality from dynamical symmetry: an example from local <lb/>scale-invariance. Proceedings of the 7th AGMP conference 24-26 Oct. 2011 <lb/>at Mulhouse (France), in press (2013), arXiv:1205.5901 <lb/>[HEP] M. Henkel, T. Enss, M. Pleimling. On the identification of quasiprimary <lb/>operators in local scale-invariance. J. Phys. A Math. Gen. 39, L589 (2006). <lb/>[HU] <lb/>M. Henkel, J. Unterberger. Schrödinger invariance and space-time sym-<lb/>metries. Nucl. Phys. B 660, 407 (2003). <lb/>[HS1] <lb/>M. Henkel, S. Stoimenov. Physical ageing and new representations of some <lb/>Lie algebras of local scale-invariance. arXiv:1410.6086. <lb/>[HS2] <lb/>M. Henkel, S. Stoimenov. On non-local representations of the ageing al-<lb/>gebra, Nuclear Physics B 847 (2011), 612–627. <lb/>[HSSU] M. Henkel, B. Schott, S. Stoimenov, J. Unterberger. The Poincare algebra <lb/>in the context of ageing systems: Lie structure, representations, Apell <lb/>systems and coherent states. Confluentes Mathematici 4, No. 4 (2012), <lb/>1250006, 23pp. <lb/>[Hu] <lb/>J. E. Humphreys. Introduction to Lie Algebras and Representation The-<lb/>ory, Graduate Texts in Mathematics 9, Springer-Verlag, New York-Berlin, <lb/>1978. <lb/>[Ja] <lb/>N. Jacobson. Basic algebra. II. W. H. Freeman and Co., San Francisco, <lb/>Calif., 1980. <lb/>[LMZ] R. Lü, V. Mazorchuk, K. Zhao. On simple modules over conformal Galilei <lb/>algebras, J. Pure Appl. Algebra 218 (2014), 1885-1899. <lb/>[LZ1] <lb/>R. Lü, K. Zhao. Generalized oscillator representations of the twisted <lb/>Heisenberg-Virasoro algebra. Preprint arXiv:1308.6023v1. <lb/>[M] <lb/>O. Mathieu. Classification of irreducible weight modules. Ann. Inst. <lb/>Fourier 50 (2000), 537–592. <lb/>[NOR] J. Negro, M. A. del Olmo, A. Rodriguez-Marco. Nonrelativistic conformal <lb/>groups. J. Math. Phys. 38 (1997), 3786–3809. <lb/>[PH] <lb/>A. Picone, M. Henkel. Local scale-invariance and ageing in noisy systems. <lb/>Nucl. Phys. B 688 [FS], 217 (2004). <lb/>[WZ] <lb/>Y. Wu, L. Zhu. Simple weight modules for Schroinger algebra. Linear <lb/>Algebra Appl. 438 (2013), no. 1, 559–563. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 18 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> RENCAI L ¨ <lb/>U, VOLODYMYR MAZORCHUK AND KAIMING ZHAO <lb/></note>

			<front> R.L.: Department of Mathematics, Soochow University, Suzhou, P. R. <lb/>China; e-mail: rencail@amss.ac.cn <lb/>V.M.: Department of Mathematics, Uppsala University, Box 480, SE-<lb/>751 06, Uppsala, Sweden; e-mail: mazor@math.uu.se <lb/>K.Z.: Department of Mathematics, Wilfrid Laurier University, Water-<lb/>loo, Ontario, N2L 3C5, Canada; and College of Mathematics and In-<lb/>formation Science, Hebei Normal (Teachers) University, Shijiazhuang <lb/>050016, Hebei, P. R. China; e-mail: kzhao@wlu.ca </front>


	</text>
</tei>
