<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> SEARCHES FOR SIGNATURES FROM GAUGE MEDIATED <lb/>SUSY BREAKING <lb/> NAOKO KANAYA <lb/> University of Victoria, Physics and Astronomy <lb/>PO Box 3040 STN CSC Victoria BC V8W 3N7, CANADA <lb/>E-mail: nkanaya@uvic.ca <lb/> Gauge-mediated SUSY breaking is an attractive model both theoretically and ex-<lb/>perimentally. In this paper, gauge-mediated SUSY breaking signatures studied <lb/>with the OPAL experiment are summarized. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> The Standard Model (SM) of particle physics describes presently known phe-<lb/>nomena successfully, and no distinct deviations from the SM have been con-<lb/>firmed. We, however, expect the SM will be extended to explain phenomena <lb/>such as the electroweak symmetry breaking, baryon asymmetry and missing <lb/>mass of the universe. The successful supersymmetry (SUSY) not only solves <lb/>the above problems, but also provide consistent predictions with the existing <lb/>experimental results. It&apos;s essential to observe a SUSY particle expected in the <lb/>theories to verify the supersymmetry. <lb/>In the gauge-mediated SUSY breaking (GMSB) model <lb/> ?? <lb/> , our world con-<lb/>sists of three sectors, hidden sector responsible for SUSY breaking and visible <lb/>sector composed of the SM particle and their super partners, and the messen-<lb/>ger sector, which is responsible for the communication of the SUSY breaking <lb/>effects into the visible sector. The SUSY particle mass spectrum is controlled <lb/>by known gauge interactions. Consequently the first and second generation <lb/>particles are degenerate in their masses, and dangerous flavor changing neu-<lb/>tral currents can be avoided. <lb/>In the minimal case, the low-energy phenomenology can be described by <lb/>six parameters, <lb/> Λ, M, n, <lb/> √ <lb/> F , tan β, sign(µ) . <lb/> The effective SUSY breaking scale, Λ, determines the whole SUSY particle <lb/>mass scale. The SUSY particle masses depend on the messenger scale M only <lb/>logarithmically, and sfermions (gauginos) become light as M is small (large). <lb/>The parameter tan β affects the mixing between left-and right-handed <lb/></body>

			<front> cr494: submitted to World Scientific on June 16, 2002 <lb/></front>

			<page> 1 <lb/></page>

			<body> sfermions, and the case µ &lt; 0 gives a larger mixing than the case µ &gt; 0 <lb/>in the notation of positive trilinear terms. <lb/>One of the most important features of GMSB models is the fact that the <lb/>gravitino is very light and becomes the lightest supersymmetric particle (LSP) <lb/>while its coupling to the SUSY particle is enhanced. This is because the SUSY <lb/>breaking scale F is low, comparing to that of the gravity-mediated models, to <lb/>give m  soft  the right order of magnitude. The gravitino mass is given by <lb/> m  ˜ <lb/> G  = <lb/> F <lb/> √ <lb/> 3M  P <lb/> = <lb/> √ <lb/> F <lb/> 100 TeV <lb/>  2 <lb/> × 2.4 <lb/>eV, <lb/>where M  P  = 2.4 × 10 <lb/> 18 <lb/> GeV is reduced Planck mass. The decay length of the <lb/>next-to-LSP (NLSP) depends on the gravitino mass (SUSY breaking scale), <lb/> L = 1.76 × 10 <lb/> −3  × <lb/> m  ˜ <lb/> G <lb/> 1 eV <lb/>  2  m  NLSP <lb/> 100 GeV <lb/>  −5 <lb/> ( βγ )  NLSP <lb/> cm. <lb/>The κ  γ  is the bino component of neutralino and is unity for sleptons. Expected <lb/>experimental topologies are changed by the gravitino mass. The NLSP might <lb/>decay very close to the e <lb/> +  e <lb/> − <lb/> interaction point ( &quot; short lifetime &quot; ) or in tracking <lb/>detector volumes ( &quot; intermediate lifetime &quot; ) or outside of the detector ( &quot; long <lb/> lifetime &quot; ). <lb/> GMSB models provide some different collider signatures from those of the <lb/>gravity-mediated models. Various analyses sensitive to the GMSB signatures <lb/>have been performed by the LEP and Tevatron experiments <lb/> ?? <lb/> , but no indi-<lb/>cation has been observed in spite of their efforts. In this paper, the GMSB <lb/>topologies studied at the OPAL experiment are introduced briefly. Some de-<lb/>tails of analysis techniques and results have been published on Refs <lb/> ???? <lb/> . <lb/> 2 GMSB signatures at e <lb/> +  e <lb/> − <lb/> collider <lb/> The GMSB models have a very predictive mass spectrum, and the NLSP is <lb/>the lightest neutralino or sleptons in the most of parameter space. The masses <lb/>of the first and second generations are degenerate while the third generations <lb/>can be lighter than the others due to their large Yukawa couplings. Thus the <lb/>lightest stau can solely become the NLSP if tan β is enough large. Table ?? <lb/> shows expected signatures with the different NLSP type and its lifetime. <lb/>In the OPAL experiment, both the NLSP and the next-to-NLSP (NNLSP) <lb/>signatures are considered. The NNLSP production events usually have less <lb/> </body>

			<note place="footnote"> cr494: submitted to World Scientific on June 16, 2002 <lb/></note>

			<page> 2 <lb/></page>

			<body> Table 1. The expected signatures for the different NLSP types and lifetimes. The symbols <lb/> &quot; X &quot; indicates additional particles from the cascade decays if sparticles heavier than the <lb/>NLSP are produced. <lb/>neutralino NLSP <lb/>slepton NLSP <lb/>short lifetime <lb/> • acoplanar photons + X <lb/> • acoplanar leptons + X <lb/> intermediate lifetime <lb/> • non-pointing photons + X <lb/> • tracks with large impact parameters + X <lb/> • kinked tracks + X <lb/> long lifetime <lb/>————————————— • tracks with anomalous dE/dx + X <lb/> Table 2. The topologies studied in the OPAL experiment are shown with the production <lb/>and decay process for each NLSP. <lb/>production <lb/>decay <lb/>neutralino NLSP <lb/>slepton NLSP <lb/>˜ <lb/> χ  0 <lb/> 1  ˜ <lb/> χ  0 <lb/>1 <lb/> γγ  <lb/>  0 <lb/>1  ˜ <lb/> χ  0 <lb/>1  ℓ  +  ℓ  −  → ℓ  +  ℓ  −  ℓ  +  ℓ  −  ˜ <lb/> G ˜ <lb/> G <lb/>  ℓ  +   ℓ  − <lb/> ˜ <lb/> χ  0 <lb/>1  ˜ <lb/> χ  0 <lb/>1  ℓ  +  ℓ  −  → γγ  <lb/>  + ℓ  +  ℓ  − <lb/> ℓ  +  ℓ  −  ˜ <lb/> G ˜ <lb/> G <lb/> ℓ  +  ℓ  −  + ˜ <lb/> χ  0 <lb/>1  ˜ <lb/> χ  0 <lb/>1  → ℓ  +  ℓ  −  +   τ  +  τ  −   τ  −  τ  − <lb/> → ℓ  +  ℓ  −  τ  +  τ  −  τ  +  τ  −  ˜ <lb/> G ˜ <lb/> G <lb/> ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> + <lb/>1  ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/> ˜ <lb/> χ  0 <lb/>1  ˜ <lb/> χ  0 <lb/>1  W  +  W  −  → γγ  <lb/>  + f ¯ ff ¯ f <lb/>——————————————— <lb/>˜ <lb/> χ  0 <lb/>2  ˜ <lb/> χ  0 <lb/>1 <lb/> ˜ <lb/> χ  0 <lb/>1  ˜ <lb/> χ  0 <lb/>1  Z  0  → γγ  <lb/>  + f ¯ f <lb/>——————————————— <lb/> background than those of the NLSP, and especially higher discovery potential <lb/>in case of the NNLSP masses being close to the NLSP. <lb/> 2.1 NLSP productions <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1  ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  → γγ  <lb/> ℓ <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> ℓ <lb/> − <lb/> 1  → ℓ <lb/> +  ℓ <lb/> −  ˜ <lb/> G ˜ <lb/> G <lb/> In case of the NLSP with short lifetime, main background are ννγ(γ) and <lb/> ℓ <lb/> +  νℓ <lb/> −  ν for <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  and <lb/> ℓ <lb/> +  <lb/> ℓ <lb/> − <lb/> productions, respectively. The selection efficiency <lb/>becomes high due to the &quot; unbalanced &quot; event shape as the NLSP mass is close <lb/>to the beam energy (i.e. produced almost at rest). The <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  is produced <lb/>dominantly via t-channel <lb/> e <lb/> ± <lb/> i  exchange, which interferes with s-channel Z <lb/> 0 <lb/> ex-<lb/>change. The Z <lb/> 0 <lb/> exchange is possible only with higgsino components of <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> cr494: submitted to World Scientific on June 16, 2002 <lb/></note>

			<page> 3 <lb/></page>

			<body> which is usually small in the minimal case. The cross-section of <lb/> µ <lb/> + <lb/> 1  <lb/> µ <lb/> − <lb/> 1  pro-<lb/>duction ( τ <lb/> + <lb/>1  <lb/> τ <lb/> − <lb/> 1  if tan β is small) is almost independent of model parameters, <lb/>on the other hand, it depends oñ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/> i  mass as well as their components in <lb/>case of <lb/> e <lb/> + <lb/>1  <lb/> e <lb/> − <lb/> 1  production. If the NLSP has a measurable lifetime, one can ob-<lb/>serve unique final states, which have tracks with a large impact parameter or <lb/>kinked tracks. A faked signal arises from the SM particles with intermediate <lb/>lifetime (K <lb/> ±  → µ <lb/> ±  ν, π <lb/> −  π <lb/> 0 <lb/> and π <lb/> −  → µ <lb/> ±  ν) and the hadronic interaction with <lb/>the detector material. Hadronic interactions and two-photon backgrounds are <lb/>not well simulated, and are reduced by applying tight selections. In case of <lb/>the slepton decaying out of the detector, tracks with anomalous ionization <lb/>energy loss dE/dx can be observed. There is nearly zero background since <lb/>the variable, dE/dx, is very powerful to separate the signal from the SM back-<lb/>ground. The selection efficiency is kept around 80 %. Only one event with <lb/>anomalous dE/dx was observed with data of the luminosity ∼ 680pb <lb/> −1 <lb/> taken <lb/>at <lb/> √ s = 183–208 GeV. If neutralino is pair-produced and they decay outside <lb/>of the detector, nothing can be observed. The NNLSP productions might be <lb/>available in this case. For instance, the analysis of two leptons plus miss-<lb/>ing energy has a sensitivity for <lb/> ℓ <lb/> +  <lb/> ℓ <lb/> − <lb/> production with long lifetime neutralino <lb/>NLSP. <lb/> 2.2 NNLSP productions : neutralino NLSP <lb/> 0 <lb/>2  ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  → ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  Z <lb/> 0  → γγ  <lb/>  + f ¯ f <lb/>˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> + <lb/>1  ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> − <lb/> 1  → ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  W <lb/> + <lb/> W <lb/> −  → γγ  <lb/>  + f ¯ ff ¯ f <lb/> ℓ <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> ℓ <lb/> − <lb/> 1  → ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  ℓ <lb/> +  ℓ <lb/> −  → γγ  <lb/>  + ℓ <lb/> +  ℓ <lb/> − <lb/> When the above processes occur, two photons plus something (X) with <lb/>missing energy can be observed. Requiring the two energetic isolated photons <lb/>is very effective for distinguishing the signal from the background. Domi-<lb/>nant faked signal photons are initial and final state radiative photons, and <lb/>Bremsstrahlung photons. As the mass difference between the NNLSP and <lb/>NLSP, ∆M , is large, the sensitivity becomes low due to small photon energy <lb/>and missing energy. In the minimal GMSB, ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>2  and <lb/> ± <lb/> 1  form a degenerate <lb/> W -ino weak triplet and their mass differences from <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  are around 20–50 GeV <lb/>within NNLSP production limits at LEP. On the other hand, wide mass dif-<lb/>ference is possible for slepton NNLSP. Several analyses optimized to different <lb/> Xs and ∆M are adopted. The analyses do not restrict to the minimal case, <lb/>the mass difference of from 3 GeV up to the almost NNLSP mass are con-<lb/>sidered. The decay of <lb/> 0 <lb/>2  → ˜ <lb/> Gγ is apt to occur thañ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>2  → ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  Z <lb/> 0 <lb/> with small <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> cr494: submitted to World Scientific on June 16, 2002 <lb/></note>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<body> ∆M . But the signature is almost same tõ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1  ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  with <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  decaying intõ <lb/> Gγ. <lb/> If selectron should be very heavy and the resulting cross-section of <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  is <lb/>suppressed, some of these NNLSP productions might be effective. <lb/> 2.3 NNLSP productions : slepton NLSP <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  → <lb/> ℓ <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> ℓ <lb/> − <lb/> 1  ℓ <lb/> +  ℓ <lb/> −  → ℓ <lb/> +  ℓ <lb/> −  ℓ <lb/> +  ℓ <lb/> −  ˜ <lb/> G ˜ <lb/> G <lb/> ℓ <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> ℓ <lb/> − <lb/> 1  → ℓ <lb/> +  ℓ <lb/> − <lb/> ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  ˜ <lb/> χ <lb/> 0 <lb/>1  → ℓ <lb/> +  ℓ <lb/> −  τ <lb/> +  τ <lb/> −  τ <lb/> +  τ <lb/> −  ˜ <lb/> G ˜ <lb/> G <lb/> If the neutralino and sleptons (stau) are degenerate in their masses, the above <lb/>processes play an important role. The NNLSP particle predominantly decays <lb/>into the NLSP and its SM partner rather than decay into gravitino directly if <lb/>it is kinematically allowed. <lb/>The 4-lepton analysis has a good sensitivity if the mass difference between <lb/>neutralino and sleptons is roughly greater than 1 GeV <lb/> ? <lb/> . The 6-lepton final <lb/>state is possible in case of the stau sole-NLSP (i.e. <lb/> τ <lb/> ± <lb/> 1  &gt; <lb/> e <lb/> ± <lb/> 1  ∼ <lb/> µ <lb/> ± <lb/> 1  &gt; m  ˜ <lb/> χ  0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> ). <lb/>For the intermediated lifetime, the efficiency usually becomes lower than that <lb/>of the short lifetime NLSP because the selection is tighten to reduce much <lb/>two-photon and non-SM background. <lb/> 3 Summary <lb/> The gauge-mediated SUSY Breaking model is attractive at both theoretical <lb/>and experimental points. We have studied most of possible topologies and <lb/>kinematics in GMSB models using high energy data, although no significant <lb/>excess has been observed. All analyses and interpretation method has been <lb/>already established. The all final results and the interpretation within the <lb/>minimal GMSB model will be published. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments <lb/> I&apos;d like to thank to Dr. R. Keeler and Dr. R. Mcphersn for their useful com-<lb/>ments and advice. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. E.Gildener, Phys. Rev. D 14 (1976) 1667; <lb/> E.Gildener and S.Weinberg Phys. Rev. D 14 (1976) 3333. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote"> cr494: submitted to World Scientific on June 16, 2002 <lb/></note>

			<page> 5 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> 2. M.Dine, W.Fischler and M.Srednicki, Nucl. Phys. B189 (1981) 575; <lb/> S.Dimopoulos and S.Raby, Nucl. Phys. B192 (1981) 353. <lb/> 3. G.F.Giudice and R.Rattazzi, Phys. Rep. 322 (1999) 419 <lb/> 4. ALEPH Collaboration A. Heister et al. hep-ex/0203024, Submitted to <lb/>Eur. Phys. J. C; <lb/> DELPHI Collaboration P. Abreu et al. Phys. Lett. B503 (2001) 34-48; <lb/> OPAL Collaboration B. Abbiendi et al. Phys. Lett. B501 (2001) 12 <lb/> 5. CDF Collaboration T. Affolder et al. Phys. Rev. Lett. 85 (2000) 1378; <lb/> D0 Collaboration B. Abbott et al. Phys. Rev. Lett. 80 (1998) 442. <lb/> 6. OPAL Collaboration B. Abbiendi et al. Phys. Lett. B501 (2001) 12 <lb/> 7. OPAL Collaboration B. Abbiendi et al. Eur. Phys. J C14 (2000) 51 <lb/> 8. OPAL Collaboration B. Abbiendi et al. Eur.Phys.J.C18 (2000) 253 <lb/> 9. OPAL Collaboration, K. Ackerstaff et al. Phys. Lett. B433 (1998) 195 <lb/> 10. S.Ambrosanio, G.D.Kribs and S.P.Martin Nucl. Phys. B516 (1998) 55 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote"> cr494: submitted to World Scientific on June 16, 2002 <lb/></note>

			<page> 6 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
