<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> PAMELA: a Payload for Antimatter Matter <lb/>Exploration and Light-nuclei Astrophysics – status <lb/>and first results <lb/> M. Pearce, O. Adriani, M. Ambriola, G.C. Barbarino, A. Basili, G.A. Bazilevskaja, R. Bellotti, M. Boezio, E.A. <lb/>Bogomolov, L. Bonechi, M. Bongi, L. Bongiorno, V. Bonvicini, A. Bruno, F. Cafagna, D. Campana, P. Carlson, M. <lb/>Casolino, G. Castellini, M. P. De Pascale, G. De Rosa, V. Di Felice, D. Fedele, A. M. Galper, P. Hofverberg, S.V. <lb/>Koldashov, S.Y. Krutkov, A.N. Kvashnin, J. Lundquist, O. Maksumov, V. Malvezzi, L. Marcelli, W. Menn, V.V. <lb/>Mikhailov, M. Minori, S. Misin, E. Mocchiutti, A. Morselli, N.N. Nikonov, S. Orsi, G. Osteria, P. Papini, P. Picozza, <lb/>M. Ricci, S.B. Ricciarini, M.F. Runtso, S. Russo, M. Simon, R. Sparvoli, P. Spillantini, Y.I. Stozhkov, E. Taddei, A. <lb/>Vacchi, E. Vannuccini, G. Vasilyev, S.A. Voronov, Y.T. Yurkin, G. Zampa, N. Zampa, and V.G. Zverev <lb/> Abstract– PAMELA is a satellite-borne experiment designed <lb/>for precision studies of the charged cosmic radiation. The <lb/>primary scientific goal is the study of the antimatter component <lb/>of the cosmic radiation (antiprotons, 80 MeV -190 GeV; and <lb/>positrons, 50 MeV -270 GeV) in order to search for evidence of <lb/>dark matter particle annihilations. PAMELA will also search for <lb/>primordial antinuclei (in particular, anti-helium), and test <lb/>cosmic-ray propagation models through precise measurements of <lb/>the antiparticle energy spectrum and studies of light nuclei and <lb/>their isotopes. Concomitant goals include a study of solar physics <lb/>and solar modulation during the 24th solar minimum by <lb/>investigating low energy particles in the cosmic radiation; and a <lb/>reconstruction of the cosmic ray electron energy spectrum up to <lb/>several TeV thereby allowing a possible contribution from local <lb/> Manuscript received November 21, 2007. The PAMELA mission is <lb/>sponsored by the Italian National Institute of Nuclear Physics (INFN), the <lb/>Italian Space Agency (ASI), the Russian Space Agency (Roskosmos), the <lb/>Russian Academy of Science, the German Space Agency (DLR), the Swedish <lb/>National Space Board and the Swedish Research Council (VR). <lb/>M. Pearce, P. Carlson, P. Hofverberg are with the Department of Physics, <lb/>KTH, Stockholm, Sweden. (e-mail: pearce@kth.se). <lb/>O. Adriani, L. Bonechi, M. Bongi, D. Fedele, P. Papini, S.B. Riccardini, P. <lb/>Spillantini, E. Taddei, E. Vannuccini are with INFN, Structure of Florence <lb/>and Physics Department of University of Florence, Florence, Italy. <lb/>M. Ambriola, R. Bellotti, A Bruno, F. Cafagna are with INFN, Structure of <lb/>Bari and Physics Department of University of Bari, Bari, Italy. <lb/>G.C. Barbarino, D. Campana, D. De Rosa, G. Osteria, S. Russo are with <lb/>INFN, Structure of Naples and Physics Department of University of Naples <lb/>&apos;Federico II&apos;, Naples, Italy. <lb/>A. Basili, M. Casolino, M.P. De Pascale, V. Di Felice, V. Malvezzi, L. <lb/>Marcelli, M. Minori, A. Morselli, S. Orsi, P. Picozza, R. Sparvoli are with <lb/>INFN, Structure of Rome &apos;Tor Vergata&apos; and Physics Department of <lb/>University of Rome &apos;Tor Vergata&apos;, Rome, Italy. <lb/>G.A. Bazilevskaja, A.N. Kvashnin, O. Maksumov, S. Misin, Y.I. Stozhkov <lb/>are at Lebedev Physical Institute, Moscow, Russia. <lb/>M. Boezio, V. Bonvicini, J. Lundquist, E. Mocchiutti, A. Vacchi, G. <lb/>Zampa, N. Zampa are with INFN, Structure of Trieste, Trieste, Italy. <lb/>E.A. Bogomolov, S.Y. Krutkov, N.N. Nikonov, G. Vasilyev are at Ioffe <lb/>Physical Technical Institute, St. Petersburg, Russia. <lb/>L. Bongiorno, M. Ricci are with INFN, Laboratori Nazionali di Frascati, <lb/>Frascati, Italy. <lb/>G. Castellini is with IFAC, Sesto Fiorentino, Florence, Italy. <lb/>A.M. Galper, S.V. Koldashov, V.V. Mikhailov, M.F. Runtso, S.A. <lb/>Voronov, Y.T. Yurkin, V.G. Zverev are with Moscow Engineering and <lb/>Physics Institute, Moscow, Russia. <lb/>W. Menn, M. Simon are with Universität Siegen, Siegen, Germany. <lb/> sources to be studied. PAMELA is housed on-board the Russian <lb/>Resurs-DK1 satellite, which was launched on June 15th 2006 in <lb/>an elliptical (350-600 km altitude) orbit with an inclination of 70 <lb/>degrees. PAMELA consists of a permanent magnet spectrometer, <lb/>to provide rigidity and charge sign information; a Time-of-Flight <lb/>and trigger system, for velocity and charge determination; a <lb/>silicon-tungsten calorimeter, for lepton/hadron discrimination; <lb/>and a neutron detector. An anticoincidence system is used offline <lb/>to reject false triggers. In this article the PAMELA experiment <lb/>and its status are reviewed. A preliminary discussion of data <lb/>recorded in-orbit is also presented. </front>

			<body> I. INTRODUCTION <lb/>PAMELA (Payload for Antimatter Matter Exploration and <lb/>Light-nuclei Astrophysics) is a satellite-borne apparatus <lb/>designed to study charged particles in the cosmic radiation <lb/>with a particular focus on antiparticles (antiprotons and <lb/>positrons). PAMELA is installed inside a pressurized <lb/>container attached to a Russian Resurs-DK1 Earth-observation <lb/>satellite that was launched into Earth orbit by a Soyuz-U <lb/>rocket on June 15th 2006 from the Baikonur cosmodrome in <lb/>Kazakhstan. The satellite orbit is elliptical and semi-polar, <lb/>with an altitude varying between 350 km (north) and 600 km <lb/>(south), at an inclination of 70 degrees. The mission is <lb/>foreseen to last for at least three years. This article continues <lb/>with a review of the science goals of the PAMELA mission, a <lb/>description of the PAMELA instrument, operational <lb/>experience and in-orbit performance, and concludes with a <lb/>discussion of preliminary results. <lb/>II. PAMELA SCIENCE GOALS <lb/>The PAMELA mission focuses on the investigation of dark <lb/>matter, the baryon asymmetry in the Universe, cosmic ray <lb/>generation and propagation in our galaxy and the solar system, <lb/>and studies of solar modulation and the interaction of cosmic <lb/>rays with the Earth&apos;s magnetosphere. The primary scientific <lb/>goal is to study the antimatter component of the cosmic <lb/>radiation, with the following themes in mind: <lb/> • To search for evidence of dark matter particle <lb/>annihilations by precisely measuring the antiparticle <lb/>(antiproton and positron) energy spectra <lb/></body>

			<front> 2007 IEEE Nuclear Science Symposium Conference Record <lb/>N04-2 <lb/>1-4244-0923-3/07/$25.00 ©2007 IEEE. <lb/></front>

			<page>42 <lb/></page>

			<body> • To search for primordial antinuclei (e.g. antihelium) <lb/>and evidence for antistellar nucleosynthesis (e.g. <lb/>anticarbon) <lb/> • To test cosmic-ray propagation models through <lb/>precise measurements of the antiparticle energy <lb/>spectrum and precision studies of light nuclei and <lb/>their isotopes. <lb/>Concomitant goals include: <lb/> • A study of solar physics and solar modulation during <lb/>the 24 <lb/> th solar minimum by investigating low energy <lb/>particles in the cosmic radiation <lb/> • A reconstruction of the cosmic ray electron energy <lb/>spectrum up to several TeV thereby allowing a <lb/>possible contribution from local sources to be <lb/>studied. <lb/>Table I shows the nominal design goals for PAMELA <lb/>performance. The various cosmic-ray components and energy <lb/>ranges over which PAMELA will provide new results are <lb/>indicated. <lb/> TABLE I <lb/>PAMELA DESIGN GOALS. <lb/> Energy range <lb/>Statistics <lb/>(3 years) <lb/>Antiproton flux <lb/>80 MeV – 190 GeV <lb/>10 <lb/> 4 <lb/> Positron flux <lb/>50 MeV – 270 GeV <lb/>10 <lb/> 5 <lb/> Electron/positron <lb/>flux <lb/>Up to 2 TeV (from <lb/>calorimeter only) <lb/>Electron flux <lb/>Up to 400 GeV <lb/>10 <lb/> 6 <lb/> Proton flux <lb/>Up to 700 GeV <lb/>10 <lb/> 8 <lb/> Light nuclei (to <lb/>Z=6) <lb/>Up to 200 GeV/n <lb/>He / Be / C <lb/>10 <lb/> 7/4/5 <lb/> Antinuclei search <lb/>Sensitivity of O(10 <lb/> -8 ) for He-bar/He <lb/>Antiparticle measurements are the primary scientific goal, <lb/>and the precise determination of the antiproton and positron <lb/>energy spectra stand to provide important information <lb/>concerning cosmic-ray propagation and solar modulation. <lb/>Indications of charge dependent solar modulation effects have <lb/>been already seen in the antiproton to proton ratio data [1]. <lb/>Antiparticles may also be produced from exotic sources such <lb/>as primordial black holes [2] or the annihilation of <lb/>supersymmetric [3] or Kaluza-Klein [4], [5] dark matter <lb/>particles. Figs. 1 and 2 show the current status of cosmic-ray <lb/>antiproton and positron energy spectrum measurements, <lb/>respectively. Theoretical calculations for pure secondary <lb/>production [6], [7], [8], [9] and for pure primary production <lb/>due to the annihilation of supersymmetric dark matter particles <lb/>[10], [11] are also shown. Almost all data available to date <lb/>have been obtained by balloon-borne experiments. The short <lb/>data-taking time (~24 hours) and the presence of a residual <lb/>overburden of atmosphere (~5 g/cm <lb/> 2 ) above the detecting <lb/>apparatus limits the precision of such measurements. <lb/>PAMELA will be able to perform very precise measurements <lb/>with high statistics (~10 <lb/> 4 antiprotons and ~10 <lb/> 5 positrons per <lb/>year) and over a wider energy range than possible to date. For <lb/>high energy events (above ~10 GeV), one HEAT-PBAR <lb/>balloon flight corresponds to ~22 days of PAMELA <lb/>operations and one CAPRICE98 balloon flight corresponds to <lb/>~4 days of PAMELA operations, once live time, and <lb/>experimental acceptance are accounted for. <lb/> Fig. 1. Recent experimental antiproton spectra (see [12] for references) along <lb/>with theoretical calculations for pure antiproton secondary production (solid <lb/>lines: [6], dashed line: [7]) and for pure antiproton primary production (dotted <lb/>line: [10], assuming the annihilation of neutralinos of mass 964 GeV/c <lb/> 2 ). The <lb/>expected PAMELA performance, in case of a pure secondary component (full <lb/>boxes) and of an additional primary component (full circles), are indicated. <lb/>Only statistical errors are included in the expected PAMELA data. <lb/> The full boxes in figs. 1 and 2 indicate the expected PAMELA <lb/>performance (3 years) for a pure secondary antiproton and <lb/>positron component, respectively. In the same figures the full <lb/>circles show the expected performance for an additional <lb/>primary component due to dark matter neutralino annihilation. <lb/>The errors on the expected PAMELA data points only include <lb/>statistical uncertainties. An average PAMELA orbit has been <lb/>used to estimate the vertical geomagnetic cut-offs and, <lb/>consequently, the expected number of antiproton and positron <lb/>events at low energies [13]. <lb/></body>

			<page> 43 <lb/></page>

			<body> Fig. 2. The positron fraction as a function of energy measured by several <lb/>experiments (see [12] for references). The dashed [8] and the solid [9] lines <lb/>are calculations of the secondary positron fraction. The dotted line is a <lb/>possible contribution from annihilation of neutralinos of mass 336 GeV/c <lb/> 2 <lb/> [11]. The expected PAMELA performance, for a pure secondary component <lb/>(full boxes) and of an additional primary component (full circles), are <lb/>indicated. Only statistical errors are included in the expected PAMELA data. <lb/> III. THE PAMELA INSTRUMENT <lb/>PAMELA is built around a 0.43 Tesla permanent magnet <lb/>spectrometer equipped with 6 planes of double-sided silicon <lb/>detectors allowing the sign, absolute value of charge and <lb/>momentum of traversing charged particles to be determined. <lb/>The acceptance of the spectrometer (which also defines the <lb/>overall acceptance of the PAMELA experiment) is 21.5 cm <lb/> 2 <lb/> sr <lb/>and the maximum detectable rigidity (momentum / charge) is <lb/>found to be ~1 TV from tests with particle beams. Spillover <lb/>effects limit the upper detectable antiparticle momentum to <lb/>~190 GeV/c (~270 GeV/c) for antiprotons (positrons). The <lb/>spectrometer is surrounded by a plastic scintillator veto shield. <lb/>An electromagnetic calorimeter mounted below the <lb/>spectrometer measures the energy of incident electrons and <lb/>allows topological discrimination between electromagnetic <lb/>and hadronic showers, or non-interacting particles. Planes of <lb/>plastic scintillator mounted above and below the spectrometer <lb/>form a time-of-flight system which also provides the primary <lb/>experimental trigger. The timing resolution of the time-of-<lb/>flight system allows albedo particles to be identified and <lb/>proton-electron separation is also possible below ~1 GeV/c. <lb/>Ionising energy loss measurements in the time-of-flight <lb/>scintillator planes and the silicon planes of the magnetic <lb/>spectrometer allow the absolute charge of traversing particles <lb/>to be determined. The volume between the upper two time-of-<lb/>flight planes is bounded by an additional plastic scintillator <lb/>anticoincidence system. A plastic scintillator system mounted <lb/>beneath the calorimeter aids in the identification of high <lb/>energy electrons and is followed by a neutron detection system <lb/>for the selection of very high energy electrons (up to 2 TeV) <lb/>which shower in the calorimeter but do not necessarily pass <lb/>through the spectrometer. Fig. 3 shows the arrangement of the <lb/>PAMELA apparatus. A complete description of the <lb/>subdetector components can be found elsewhere [12]. <lb/>PAMELA is housed inside a pressurized container attached <lb/>to a Resurs-DK1 Earth observation satellite, as shown in fig. <lb/>4. The satellite is manufactured by the Russian space company <lb/>TsSKB Progress to perform multi-spectral remote sensing of <lb/>the Earth&apos;s surface and acquire high-quality images in near <lb/>real-time. The satellite has a mass of ~6.7 Tonnes and a height <lb/>of 7.4 m. The solar array spans ~14 m. The satellite is three-<lb/>axis stabilized with an axis orientation accuracy of 0.2 arcmin <lb/>and an angular velocity stabilization accuracy of 0.005 <lb/>degrees/s. During launch and orbital manoeuvers, the <lb/>pressurized container is secured against the body of the <lb/>satellite. During data-taking it is swung up to give PAMELA a <lb/>clear view into space. The container is cylindrical in shape and <lb/>has an inside diameter of about 105 cm, a semi-spherical <lb/>bottom and a conical top. It is made of an aluminium alloy, <lb/>with a thickness of 2 mm in the acceptance of PAMELA. <lb/>PAMELA points mainly to zenith during data-taking. During <lb/>remote sensing operations the satellite executes a rolling <lb/>movement around zenith. The maximum roll angle can reach <lb/>30 degrees. Information about the inclination is transmitted to <lb/>the PAMELA every 1.5 seconds with an accuracy of about <lb/>one degree. <lb/> Fig. 3. A schematic overview of the PAMELA apparatus, which is <lb/>approximately 1.3 m tall, and has a mass of 470 kg. The average power <lb/>consumption is 355 W. The magnetic field lines inside the spectrometer cavity <lb/>are orientated in the y direction. <lb/></body>

			<page> 44 <lb/></page>

			<body> Fig. 4. A photograph of PAMELA during integration with the Resurs-DK1 <lb/>satellite. PAMELA is mounted inside a pressure vessel (the lid is not shown in <lb/>this photograph) which is attached to the satellite body. In orbit, the pressure <lb/>vessel is swung away from the satellite giving PAMELA a clear view of the <lb/>heavens. Note that the satellite is shown inverted in this photograph. <lb/> IV. OPERATIONS AND PERFORMANCE IN-ORBIT <lb/>PAMELA was launched from the Baikonur Cosmodrome on <lb/>June 15th 2006 at 0800 UTC. The PAMELA pressure vessel <lb/>was swung up into data taking position and the instrument <lb/>powered up on June 21 <lb/> st 2006 at 0300 UTC. All detectors <lb/>were found to operate as expected post launch. The <lb/>commissioning phase ended on July 11 <lb/> th 2006, and since then <lb/>PAMELA has been in a standard data-taking mode. As of <lb/>November 2007, there have been more than 400 days of data <lb/>taking (with an average live time of 73%). Science data is <lb/>stored in the PAMELA mass memory (2 GBytes). Once full, <lb/>data is transferred to the Resurs-DK1 mass memory. This <lb/>typically occurs 7 times per days for an average data volume <lb/>of 14 GByte. This data is down-linked to ground in 2-3 <lb/>sessions per day with a bit error rate of less than 10 <lb/> -9 <lb/> . The <lb/>reception centre is located at The Research Centre for Earth <lb/>Operative Monitoring (&apos;NtsOMZ&apos;) in Moscow, Russia. Upon <lb/>arrival at NtsOMZ, the data is unpacked and a &apos;Quicklook&apos; <lb/>analysis performed in order to evaluate the performance of the <lb/>apparatus and check for error conditions. If needed, the <lb/>PAMELA configuration can be changed through data up-<lb/>links. After being committed to local storage, data are sent <lb/>through leased networks to MePHI (Moscow Engineering and <lb/>Physics Institute) and then onwards to CNAF, the INFN GRID <lb/>computing facility in Bologna, Italy. At this point, data <lb/>reduction and calibration takes place prior to distribution to <lb/>participating institutes. <lb/>The PAMELA orbit has an inclination of 70 degrees and is <lb/>elliptical (350 km -610 km altitude). The orbit crosses the <lb/>South Atlantic Anomaly several times per day as well as the <lb/>outer (electron) radiation belt in the vicinity of the South Pole. <lb/>After an initial commissioning period, PAMELA operations <lb/>have been relatively straight-forward. Web-based Quicklook <lb/>software allows the instrument status to be rapidly assessed <lb/>and error conditions trapped. Approximately 1 alarm is issued <lb/>per day usually as a result of an anomalous electronics <lb/>condition. A weak correlation to passages through the South <lb/>Atlantic Anomaly and radiation belts has been observed. The <lb/>majority of these alarms are dealt with automatically by <lb/>hardware resets and less than one per month requires the <lb/>instrument power supply to be cycled. Few up-link <lb/>interventions have been necessary. An example of the stability <lb/>of the instrument is shown in fig. 5 where the typical time <lb/>development of pedestal values from a section of the <lb/>calorimeter is shown over a period of 5 months. <lb/> Fig. 5. The time dependence of the pedestal value (ADC counts) for a typical <lb/>calorimeter channel, as measured during calibration runs at the equatorial <lb/>ascending node. The time on the x-axis corresponds to approximately 5 <lb/>months. A minimum ionizing particle registers a signal ~30 channels above <lb/>the pedestal. <lb/> The primary PAMELA trigger is formed by requiring <lb/>coincident energy deposits in the time-of-flight scintillator <lb/>planes. Each plane consists of two orthogonal layers of plastic <lb/>scintillator. The coincidence condition is chosen according to <lb/>the counting rate measured on the top-most scintillator plane <lb/>(S1 in fig. 3). In low rate equatorial regions, a coincidence is <lb/>required between all three scintillator planes with an &apos;OR&apos; <lb/>condition applied between the layers in a given plane. In high <lb/>rate regions such as the South Atlantic Anomaly or the <lb/>radiation belts, the top-most scintillator plane is not used in the <lb/>coincidence condition since it saturates. Furthermore, an <lb/>&apos;AND&apos; condition is applied between layers of a given plane. <lb/>The average trigger rate is ~25 Hz. The rate in equatorial <lb/>regions is ~20 Hz and ~30 Hz in polar regions. The trigger <lb/>rate as a function of orbital position is shown in fig. 6, and <lb/>many orbits are shown superimposed on a world map in fig. 7. <lb/>The location of the South Atlantic Anomaly is clearly evident. <lb/>It is noted that hardware parameters (e.g. high voltage settings <lb/></body>

			<page> 45 <lb/></page>

			<body> for photomultiliers) are not changed in high rate regions such <lb/>as the South Atlantic Anomaly or during solar particle event <lb/>alerts. <lb/>V. PRELIMINARY RESULTS <lb/>To date, several tens of thousands of events have been <lb/>identified as positrons and several thousands as antiprotons. <lb/>Figs. 8 and 9 show an example of a high energy antiproton and <lb/>positron, respectively. The lepton-hadron separation afforded <lb/>by the combination of the calorimeter and neutron detector is <lb/>evident. These events represent the highest energy antiparticle <lb/>events reconstructed to date in the cosmic radiation, and are of <lb/>particular interest in the search for dark matter particle <lb/>annihilations. <lb/>Through a combination of ionization energy loss <lb/>measurements in the scintillator planes of the time-of-flight <lb/>system, the silicon planes of the spectrometer and the first <lb/>calorimeter plane, PAMELA is also able to study light nuclei <lb/>at least up to Oxygen. As an example, fig. 10 shows the <lb/>average ionization energy loss measured as a function of <lb/>rigidity as a particle traversed the silicon planes of the <lb/>spectrometer. <lb/>PAMELA also has the ability to study solar particle events <lb/>over an unprecedented energy range for several particle types <lb/>(e.g. protons, nuclei, and positrons) simultaneously [14]. The <lb/>large solar particle event of 13 <lb/> th December 2006 was observed <lb/>by PAMELA and fig. 11 shows the observed increase in the <lb/>low energy proton flux compared to a solar quiet period. <lb/> Fig. 6. The evolution of the trigger rate (Hz) for two consecutive PAMELA <lb/>orbits. Each orbit has a period of ~94 minutes. A sinusoidal structure is <lb/>evident as PAMELA completes one orbit. The narrow spikes correspond to <lb/>passages through the South Atlantic Anomaly. The trigger rate drops to zero <lb/>as PAMELA crosses the equator on an ascending node due to the execution of <lb/>a calibration procedure. <lb/>Fig. 7. A large number of PAMELA orbits superimposed on a map of the <lb/>world. The colour code shows the trigger rate in Hertz. The trigger rate is seen <lb/>to increase as PAMELA approaches the polar regions due to the effect of the <lb/>Earth&apos;s geomagnetic cut-off. In the South Atlantic Anomaly the trigger rate <lb/>increases by a factor of ~5. The low trigger rate band at zero latitude <lb/>corresponds to periods when PAMELA is in calibration mode. <lb/>Fig. 8. The event display an ♥84 GV antiproton candidate interacting in the <lb/>calorimeter. The bending (x) and non-bending (y) views are shown on the left <lb/>and on the right, respectively. A plan view of PAMELA is shown in the <lb/>center. The signal as detected by PAMELA detectors are shown (plane 19 of <lb/>the calorimeter x-view was malfunctioning) along with the particle trajectory <lb/>(solid line) reconstructed by the fitting procedure of the tracking system. <lb/></body>

			<page> 46 <lb/></page>

			<body> Fig. 9. The event display an ♥92 GV positron candidate interacting in the <lb/>calorimeter. The bending (x) and non-bending (y) views are shown on the left <lb/>and on the right, respectively. A plan view of PAMELA is shown in the <lb/>center. The signal as detected by PAMELA detectors are shown (plane 19 of <lb/>the calorimeter x-view was malfunctioning) along with the particle trajectory <lb/>(solid line) reconstructed by the fitting procedure of the tracking system. <lb/>Fig. 10. The average ionization energy loss (dE/dx) measured as a particle <lb/>traverses the silicon planes of the spectrometer as a function of rigidity. The <lb/>curved bands correspond to nuclei of differing charge, as indicated. The flat <lb/>band starting at the lowest dE/dx values corresponds to minimum ionizing <lb/>particles. This information is combined with that from the time-of-flight <lb/>scintillators and the first silicon plane of the calorimeter to identify nuclei of <lb/>higher charge. <lb/> VI. SUMMARY <lb/>PAMELA is a general purpose charged particle detector <lb/>system which was launched into Earth orbit in June 2006. It <lb/>has been routinely collecting data once a short commissioning <lb/>period was completed. PAMELA will explore the antiparticle <lb/>component of the cosmic radiation with high statistics and <lb/>over a wide energy range. Data analysis is on-going and first <lb/>results will be published shortly. <lb/> Fig. 11. The proton energy spectrum measured during three hours of the large <lb/>solar particle event of 13 <lb/> th December 2006 (black) compared to a solar quiet <lb/>period (red). A significant increase in the flux of low energy protons (&lt; 3 <lb/>GeV) is associated with the solar particle event. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> REFERENCES <lb/> [1] Y. Asaoka et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 88 (2002) 051101; astro-ph/0109007 <lb/>(2001). <lb/>[2] K. Maki et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 76 (1996) 3474 <lb/>[3] L. Bergström et al., Phys. Rev. D 59 (1999) 43506. <lb/>[4] D. Hooper et al., Phys.Rev. D 71 (2005) 083503. <lb/>[5] T. Bringmann, JCAP 08 (2005) 006; astro-ph/0506219 (2005). <lb/>[6] M. Simon et al., Astrophys. J. 499 (1998) 250. <lb/>[7] L. Bergström and P. Ullio, private communication (1999). <lb/>[8] R.J. Protheroe, Astrophys. J. 254 (1982) 391. <lb/>[9] I.V. Moskalenko et al., Astrophys. J. 493 (1998) 694. <lb/>[10] P. Ullio, astro-ph/9904086 (1999). <lb/>[11] E.A. Baltz et al., Phys. Rev. D 59 (1999) 023511. <lb/>[12] P. Picozza et al., Astroparticle Physics 27 (2007) 296. <lb/>[13] J. Lund, &apos;Antiparticle Identification Studies for the PAMELA Satellite <lb/>Experiment&apos;, PhD thesis, KTH, Stockholm (2004). <lb/>[14] M. Casolino et al., &apos;Solar cosmic ray observations with PAMELA <lb/>experiment&apos; Proc. 30th International Cosmic Ray Conference, Mérida, <lb/>Mexico (2007). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 47 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
