<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> 29th International Cosmic Ray Conference Pune (2005) 3, 293–296 <lb/> The Space Experiment PAMELA <lb/> M. Boezio on behalf of the PAMELA Collaboration <lb/> INFN, Structure of Trieste, Via Valerio, 2 I -34127 Trieste, Italy <lb/> Presenter: M. Boezio (Mirko.Boezio@trieste.infn.it), ita-boezio-M-abs1-og15-oral <lb/>We present a status report of the space experiment PAMELA. PAMELA is a satellite-borne experiment which <lb/>aims primarily to measure the antiproton and positron spectra in the cosmic radiation over the largest energy <lb/>range ever achieved and to search for antinuclei with unprecedented sensitivity. In addition, it will measure the <lb/>light nuclear component of cosmic rays and investigate phenomena connected with Solar and Earth physics. <lb/>All detectors have been successfully integrated in the apparatus that has been installed on-board the polar <lb/>orbiting Resource DK1 satellite. Before the end of 2005 it will be launched from the Baikonur cosmodrome <lb/>in Kazakhstan, for a 3 year long mission. Details of the integration phase and detectors performances will be <lb/>presented along with results of ground data taking and expected scientific output from the mission. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> The PAMELA apparatus (a Payload for Antimatter Matter Exploration and Light-nuclei Astrophysics) is a <lb/>satellite-borne experiment designed to study charged particles in the cosmic radiation. It will be hosted in a <lb/>pressurized vessel attached to a Russian Earth-observation satellite, the Resource DK1, that will be launched <lb/>into space by a Soyuz TM2 rocket in 2005 from the Baikonur cosmodrome, in Kazakhstan. The orbit will be <lb/>elliptical and semi-polar, with an inclination of 70.4 <lb/> and an altitude varying between 350 km and 600 km. The <lb/>mission will last at least three years, during which time PAMELA will measure the cosmic-ray composition <lb/>and energy spectrum. <lb/>The main scientific goal of the experiment is the precise measurement of the cosmic-ray antiproton and <lb/>positron energy spectra. The satellite orbit and mechanical design of the apparatus will allow the iden-<lb/>tification of these particles in an unprecedented energy range (¡ <lb/> ¢ <lb/> ¤ £ <lb/> MeV – <lb/> ¡ <lb/> ¦ ¥ <lb/> ¨  § <lb/> £ <lb/> MeV for positrons and <lb/> ¡ <lb/> ¢ <lb/> © £ <lb/> MeV – <lb/> ¡ <lb/>£ <lb/> MeV for antiprotons) and with high statistics (¡ 10 <lb/> and <lb/> ¡ <lb/> 10 <lb/> per year). The impor-<lb/>tance of these measurements stems from the information that they can provide about solar modulation effects <lb/>(below a few GeV), cosmic-ray propagation and primary production from exotic sources such as: primordial <lb/>black holes (e.g. see [1]), annihilation of supersymmetric particles (e.g. see [2] or Kaluza-Klein particles <lb/>(e.g. see [3, 4]). Almost all data available so far have been obtained by balloon-borne experiments. The short <lb/>data-taking time (approximately 24 hours) and the presence of a residual overburden of atmosphere above the <lb/>detecting apparatus at the altitudes that a balloon can reach (around 40 km, <lb/> ¡ <lb/> 5 g/cm of residual atmosphere) <lb/>are the main limits of such kind of measurements. <lb/>Additionally, PAMELA will search for antimatter in the cosmic radiation (sensitivity to the the <lb/> ! <lb/> &quot; <lb/>$ # <lb/> % ! <lb/> &quot; <lb/> of <lb/> ¡ <lb/> 10&amp; <lb/> ( &apos; <lb/> ), it will measure the light nuclear component of cosmic rays and investigate phenomena connected <lb/>with Solar and Earth physics (e.g. see [5]). <lb/> 2. The PAMELA apparatus <lb/> The apparatus [6] is composed of the following subdetectors, arranged as in Figure 1, from top to bottom: <lb/>1. a time of flight system (ToF (S1,S2,S3)); <lb/></body>

			<page> 294 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> M. Boezio <lb/> The Space Experiment PAMELA <lb/></note>

			<page> 295 <lb/></page>

			<body> -0.5 <lb/> 21.5 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>21.5 <lb/> PALETTE <lb/>TOF, CALO, S4 [MIP]: <lb/>0 <lb/>0 -2 <lb/>2 -10 <lb/>10 -100 <lb/>100 -500 <lb/>&gt; 500 <lb/>ND [neutrons]: <lb/>0 <lb/>1 -2 <lb/>3 -6 <lb/>7 -14 <lb/>15 -30 <lb/>&gt; 30 <lb/>AC: <lb/>NOT HIT <lb/>HIT trigger <lb/> HIT background <lb/> CARD4 <lb/> CARD1 <lb/> CARD2 <lb/>CARD3 <lb/> CAS3 <lb/> CAS4 <lb/> CAS2 <lb/>CAS1 <lb/>CAT1 <lb/>CAT2 <lb/>CAT3 <lb/>CAT4 <lb/>CAS2 <lb/>CAS1 <lb/>CAS4 <lb/>CAS3 <lb/>CARD2 <lb/>CARD3 <lb/>CARD1 <lb/>CARD4 <lb/>CAT3 <lb/>CAT4 <lb/>CAT2 <lb/>CAT1 <lb/> Calorimeter <lb/> Calorimeter <lb/> Tracker <lb/> Tracker <lb/> ND <lb/> ND <lb/> S3 <lb/>S2 <lb/>S1 <lb/>S3 <lb/>S2 <lb/>S1 <lb/>S4 <lb/>S4 <lb/> CPU SIDE <lb/> CPU SIDE <lb/> VME SIDE <lb/> VME SIDE <lb/> CPU SIDE <lb/> z <lb/>x <lb/>y <lb/> X VIEW <lb/>Y VIEW <lb/> y <lb/>x <lb/>z <lb/>x <lb/>y <lb/>z <lb/> Figure 2. The event display of a 1.5 GeV/C <lb/> E D <lb/> G F <lb/> from ground data in the PAMELA apparatus. <lb/> incoming and acceptance tests and is going to be integrated with the satellite by August 2005. Subsequently, <lb/>PAMELA and the satellite will be transported to Baikonur for the launch into space foreseen for the end of <lb/>2005. <lb/> 3. Ground data <lb/> Prior to the delivery to Russia, the PAMELA apparatus was assembled at the INFN laboratories of RomaII, <lb/>Rome, Italy. Here the system has been tested with ground muons over a period of several months. Figure 2 <lb/>shows an event recorded in Rome. The event is a 1.5 GeV/H negatively charged particle, with high probability <lb/>of being a <lb/> I <lb/> &amp; <lb/> considering the clean non-interacting pattern in the calorimeter. All PAMELA detectors are <lb/>shown in the figure along with the signals produced by the particle in the detectors and derived information. It <lb/>can be clearly seen the highly detailed information provided for each cosmic-ray event. The solid line indicates <lb/>the track reconstructed by the fitting procedure of the tracking system. <lb/>From this information the muon charge ratio measured at ground in Rome (50 m a.s.l.) has been obtained and <lb/>shown in Figure 3. Muons were selected as non interacting particles in the calorimeter and charge one in the <lb/>ToF scintillators. Their momenta were determined by the tracking system. In the figure PAMELA data are <lb/>compared with other experimental results [11, 12, 13]. A good agreement can be seen. <lb/> 4. Conclusions <lb/> PAMELA is a powerful instrument that will give results of great scientific relevance in several fields of cosmic <lb/>ray research. The PAMELA flight model has been extensively tested on ground and shown to perform as <lb/>required to meet the scientific goals of the mission. The model was delivered to Russia for integration with the <lb/></body>

			<page> 296 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> M. Boezio <lb/></note>

			<body> momentum (GeV/c) <lb/> µ <lb/> + <lb/> / <lb/> µ <lb/> -<lb/> Hebbeker and Timmermans (world average 2002) <lb/>BESS-95 (Tsukuba, Japan) <lb/>BESS-97/98/99 (Lynn Lake, Canada) <lb/>CAPRICE-98 (Fort Sumner, New Mexico) <lb/>PAMELA preliminary (Rome, Italy) <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.25 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1.75 <lb/>2 <lb/>2.25 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 1 <lb/>10 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> Figure 3. The muon charge ratio at ground measured by PAMELA compared with the global fit of experimental data by <lb/>Hebbeker and Timmermans [11] and subsequent experimental results [12, 13]. <lb/> satellite in March 2005. Incoming and acceptance tests are underway and by end of Summer 2005, PAMELA <lb/>will be moved to Baikonur for the launch into space scheduled for the end of 2005. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] K. Maki, T. Mitsui, T., and S. Orito, Phys. Rev. Lett. 76, 3474 (1996). <lb/>[2] L. Bergström, J. Edsjö and P. Ullio, Phys. Rev. D 59, 43506 (1999). <lb/>[3] D. Hooper and J. Silk, Phys.Rev. D 71, 083503 (2005). <lb/>[4] T. Bringmann, astro-ph/0506219 (2005). <lb/>[5] M. Casolino et al., 35P <lb/> R Q <lb/> COSPAR Scientific Assembly Paris (2004), to appear in Advances in Space <lb/>Research. <lb/>[6] M. Bongi et al., IEEE Trans. Nucl. Sci. 51, 854 (2004). <lb/>[7] D. Campana et al., 28th ICRC, Tsukuba (2003), 2141. <lb/>[8] S. Orsi et al., 35P <lb/> R Q <lb/> COSPAR Scientific Assembly Paris (2004), to appear in Advances in Space Research. <lb/>[9] O. Adriani et al., Nucl. Instr. &amp; Meth. A 511, 72 (2003). <lb/>[10] J. Lundquist et al., &quot; The PAMELA Calorimeter Identification Capabilities &quot; , Proceedings of this Confer-<lb/>ence. <lb/>[11] T. Hebbeker and C. Timmermans, Astropart. Phys. 18, 107 (2002). <lb/>[12] M. Motoki et al., Astropart. Phys. 19, 113 (2003). <lb/>[13] M. Boezio et al., Phys. Rev. D 67, 072003 (2003). </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
