<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> 20th IMEKO TC4 International Symposium and <lb/>18th International Workshop on ADC Modelling and Testing <lb/>Research on Electric and Electronic Measurement for the Economic Upturn <lb/>Benevento, Italy, September 15-17, 2014 <lb/> Single-shot and non-destructive longitudinal <lb/>monitor by means of Electro-Optical Sampling <lb/>for future Plasma Wakefield Acceleration <lb/>experiments <lb/> R. Pompili <lb/> 1 <lb/> , M.P. Anania <lb/> 1 <lb/> , M. Bellaveglia <lb/> 1 <lb/> , M. Castellano <lb/> 1 <lb/> , E. Chiadroni <lb/> 1 <lb/> , A. Cianchi <lb/> 2 <lb/> , D. Di <lb/>Giovenale <lb/> 1 <lb/> , G. Di Pirro <lb/> 1 <lb/> , G. Gatti <lb/> 1 <lb/> , F. Giorgianni <lb/> 4 <lb/> , M. Ferrario <lb/> 1 <lb/> , F. Massimo <lb/> 4 <lb/> , A. Mostacci <lb/> 1 <lb/> , C. <lb/>Vaccarezza <lb/> 1 <lb/> , F. Villa <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 <lb/> INFN-LNF, Via E. Fermi 40, 00044 Frascati, Rome, Italy <lb/> 2 <lb/> Università di Roma &quot;Tor Vergata&quot;, Physics Department, Via della Ricerca Scientifica 1, 00133 <lb/>Rome, Italy <lb/> 3 <lb/> INFN Milano, Via Celoria 16, 20133 Milan, Italy <lb/> 4 <lb/> Università di Roma &quot;Sapienza&quot;, Physics Department, Via Aldo Moro 2, 00185 Rome, Italy <lb/> Abstract – At SPARC-LAB, we have installed an <lb/>Electro-Optic Sampling (EOS) experiment for single <lb/>shot, non-destructive measurements of the longitudinal <lb/>distribution charge of individual electron bunches. The <lb/>profile of the electron bunch field is electro-optically <lb/>encoded into a Ti:Sa laser, having 130 fs (rms) pulse <lb/>length, directly derived from the photocathode&apos;s laser. <lb/>The bunch profile information is spatially retrieved, <lb/>i.e., the laser crosses with an angle of 30 deg with re-<lb/>spect the normal to the surface of EO crystal (ZnTe, <lb/>GaP) and the bunch longitudinal profile is mapped into <lb/>the laser&apos;s transverse profile. In particular, we used <lb/>the EOS for a single-shot direct visualization of the <lb/>time profile of a comb-like electron beam, consisting of <lb/>two bunches, about 100 fs (rms) long, sub-picosecond <lb/>spaced with a total charge of 160 pC. The electro-optic <lb/>measurements (done with both ZnTe and GaP crystals) <lb/>have been validated with both RF Deflector (RFD) and <lb/>Michelson interferometer measurements. <lb/></front>

			<body>I. INTRODUCTION <lb/>Single-shot and non-intercepting bunch length measure-<lb/>ments with 50 fs order resolution are of high interest <lb/>for future plasma-based accelerators, in order to moni-<lb/>tor the beams to be injected in the plasma. In particular, <lb/>the particle-driven wakefield acceleration (PWFA) require <lb/>multi-bunches schemes where two or more subsequent <lb/>bunches, sub-100 fs long and sub-picosecond spaced, can <lb/>enhance the plasma transformer ratio R and generate the <lb/>proper accelerating field [1] able to accelerate the last one <lb/>with low energy spread [2]. <lb/>The technique of electro-optical sampling (EOS) [3] <lb/>provides the possibility to measure the longitudinal charge <lb/>distribution by means of nonlinear crystals placed near the <lb/>moving electron beams and it&apos;s able to reach high tempo-<lb/>ral resolutions, determined by the width of the optical laser <lb/>pulse and the EO crystal length. The working principle is <lb/>based on the induced birefringence in a nonlinear crystal <lb/>(like ZnTe and GaP) by the high electric fields of the rel-<lb/>ativistic electron bunch (with temporal profile E  bunch  (t)), <lb/> which propagate in the crystal like a THz-field (see fig. 1). <lb/>Since the crystal becomes anisotropic (biaxial), the elec-<lb/>tric field of a polarized laser passing in the crystal is de-<lb/>composed along the two optical axes, with characteristic <lb/>refractive indices n  i  = n  1  , n  2  . Because the two compo-<lb/>nents travel at different velocities v  i  = c/n  i  , at the end of <lb/>the crystal their relative phase delay Γ is <lb/> Γ(t) = <lb/> ωd <lb/>c <lb/> (n  1  − n  2  ) ∝ E  bunch  (t) , <lb/> (1) <lb/>where ω is the laser&apos;s pulse frequency and d is the crys-<lb/>tal thickness. Therefore the time information contained in <lb/> Γ(t) is a replica of E  bunch  (t). <lb/> At the SPARC-LAB facility [4] (see fig. 2) a Ti:Sa IR <lb/>laser (λ = 800 nm, 130 fs pulse length, rms) is used <lb/>to sample the birefringence which is induced in the non-<lb/>linear optical crystal by the co-moving electric field of a <lb/>110 MeV electron bunch. The laser is directly derived from <lb/>the photocathode&apos;s one, resulting in a natural synchroniza-<lb/>tion with the electron beam, having a repetition rate of <lb/>10 Hz. The initial linear polarization of the laser pulse <lb/>is converted into a slightly elliptical polarization which is <lb/>then converted into an intensity modulation by placing a <lb/>polarizer after the crystal, with its polarization axis rotated <lb/>by 90 deg with respect to the initial laser polarization. To <lb/>encode the bunch longitudinal profile into the laser, we <lb/>used the spatially encoding EOS technique [5], in which <lb/>the laser crosses the nonlinear crystal with an angle of <lb/> θ = 30 deg (see fig. 1). In such a way, being x the spa-<lb/>tial coordinate along the laser transverse profile and t the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> ISBN-14: 978-92-990073-2-7 <lb/></note>

			<page> 69 <lb/></page>

			<body> Fig. 2. SPARC-LAB layout. The EOS station is located at the end of the 2nd beamline. <lb/> Bunch <lb/> Electric field <lb/> Electron bunch <lb/> Birefringent Crystal <lb/> x <lb/>y <lb/>z <lb/> L a s e r W <lb/> a v e fr o n t <lb/> SPATIAL <lb/> ENCODING <lb/> CCD <lb/> Fig. 1. Spatial Decoding for the Electro-Optic Sampling. <lb/>The laser crosses the EO crystal with angle θ = 30 deg. <lb/>By inserting a polarizer whose axis is 90 deg respect to the <lb/>laser linear polarization, the longitudinal bunch profile is <lb/>directly retrieved on the CCD. <lb/> time coordinate for the longitudinal bunch profile, we have <lb/> t = <lb/> x <lb/>c <lb/> tan θ , <lb/> (2) <lb/>where c is the vacuum speed of the light. From eq. 2, the <lb/>total time window ∆t is directly proportional to the laser&apos;s <lb/>spot diameter d, i.e. ∆t = (d/c) tan θ. In the presented <lb/>measure, a 5 mm wide laser has been used, resulting in a <lb/>time window of about 10 ps. <lb/>Previous accelerator-related EOS experiments have <lb/>been carried out at FELIX [6], DESY [7] and SLAC [8], in <lb/>each of which the EOS has been tested on a single (short <lb/>or long) electron bunch. Here we report the recent results <lb/>achieved at SPARC-LAB measuring, for the first time, the <lb/>longitudinal profile of comb-like beams, consisting of two <lb/>bunches, about 100 fs (rms) long, sub-ps spaced with a to-<lb/>tal charge up to 160 pC. <lb/>II. TWO BUNCHES COMB-LIKE BEAM AT <lb/>SPARC-LAB <lb/>The comb-like beam consists of two approximately <lb/>equal electron bunch, generated by properly shaping trains <lb/>of UV laser pulses illuminating the metallic photo-cathode <lb/>in the RF gun [9]. A diagnostics transfer line allows <lb/>to fully characterize the accelerated beam by measur-<lb/>ing transverse emittance [10] and the longitudinal pro-<lb/>file through a Radio-Frequency Deflector (RFD) [11], lo-<lb/>cated at the linac exit. Fig. 3(a) shows the longitudi-<lb/>nal phase space of a 160 pC total charge beam. The <lb/>two consecutive bunches have lengths of 100 ± 12 fs and <lb/> 70 ± 17 fs (rms), with respective charges of 77 ± 6 pC and <lb/> 83 ± 7 pC, separated by 846 ± 15 fs with a mean energy of <lb/> 110.0 ± 0.1 MeV. <lb/>Because the EOS station is located at the end of a dog-<lb/>leg transfer line, we have to take care to the fact that the <lb/>longitudinal phase space evolution in the dogleg is dom-<lb/>inated by non-linearities given by high order chromatic <lb/>terms [12]. In order to evaluate the bunch properties after <lb/>this line, a Michelson interferometer, analyzing the coher-<lb/>ent transition radiation (CTR) from an aluminium coated <lb/>silicon screen, has been installed at the end of the dogleg <lb/>line just before the EOS station; CTR is produced when a <lb/></body>

			<page> 70 <lb/></page>

			<body> Fig. 3. (a) Longitudinal phase space retrieved by using a <lb/>RF Deflector (time) and a bending magnet (energy) of a <lb/>comb beam consisting of two consecutive bunches with a <lb/>mean energy of 110.0 ± 0.1 MeV, with a total charge of <lb/>160 pC (77 pC and 83 pC for each bunch). <lb/> relativistic charged particle crosses the interface between <lb/>two media of different dielectric properties (vacuum and <lb/>aluminium, in our case) and its frequency spectrum fol-<lb/>lows the electron bunch one <lb/> 1 <lb/> . The interferometer consists <lb/>in a 12 µm mylar sheet that splits the CTR radiation in <lb/>two arms, one of which can be changed in length by us-<lb/>ing a motorized translational stage. By recombining the <lb/>two radiations on a broadband (0.5 − 30 THz) pyroelec-<lb/>tric detector, the overall intensity modulation (sampled for <lb/>each position of the translational stage by steps of 10 µm) <lb/> is used to make the interferogram showed in fig. 4(a) and <lb/>determine the corresponding CTR form factor (fig. 4(b)), <lb/>i.e., the power spectrum of the electron beam [13]. Since <lb/>from the production to the detection point the CTR crosses <lb/>a quartz window whose characteristic cut-off frequency is <lb/>about 3.8 THz, the Michelson interferometer is able to re-<lb/>produce bunch spectra up to this frequency. In our mea-<lb/>surement we obtained a bunch distance of 830 ± 20 fs and <lb/>150 fs (rms) as the upper limit of the bunch lengths, results <lb/>that are comparable with the RFD data. <lb/>III. EOS EXPERIMENTAL SETUP <lb/>In our experiment we used ZnTe and GaP with thick-<lb/>nesses of 500 µm and 400 µm, respectively, both cut in the <lb/>(110) plane (Ingcrys Laser Systems, UK); therefore, in or-<lb/>der to have a net EO effect, their [−1, 1, 0] axes have to be <lb/>parallel to both the bunch and the laser electric fields [7]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 1 Except a strong suppression of the low frequencies side, due to the <lb/>effect of considering the finite size of the metal target and far-field ap-<lb/>proximation not completely fulfilled [12]. <lb/></note>

			<body> 60 <lb/> 50 <lb/>40 <lb/>30 <lb/>20 <lb/>Detector Signal (mV) <lb/> 1.2 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>Mirror Position (mm) <lb/> 1.0 <lb/> 0.8 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>Form Factor <lb/> 5 <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>Frequency (THz) <lb/> Experimental <lb/>Theoretical <lb/> Fig. 4. (a) Interferogram obtained by moving the transla-<lb/>tional stage at steps of 10 µm and (b) retrieved form factor <lb/>of the comb beam measured with the Michelson Interfer-<lb/>ometer after the dogleg line. The calculated bunch distance <lb/>is 830 ± 20 fs while the upper limit for the bunch lengths <lb/>is fixed to ∼ 150 fs (rms). <lb/> By doing so, the induced phase delay of eq. 1 becomes <lb/> Γ(t) = <lb/> ωn <lb/> 3 <lb/> 0  r  41  E  bunch  (t) <lb/> c <lb/>d , <lb/> (3) <lb/>being r  41  the electro-optic coefficient of the crystal. <lb/>The EOS optical setup is showed in fig. 5(a). The EO <lb/>crystals are positioned so that their [−1, 1, 0] axis is prop-<lb/>erly oriented, i.e., parallel to the bunch electric field. The <lb/>crystals are mounted on a remotely controlled actuator, <lb/>which also holds OTR and Ce:YAG screens to monitor <lb/>the electron beam position. By knowing such position, <lb/>it&apos;s possible to move the actuator in order to approach the <lb/>crystals to the beam up to several microns. The IR laser&apos;s <lb/>energy is adjusted by simply rotating an half-wave plate <lb/>placed between two polarizers. In the experiment, the laser <lb/>energy was 50 nJ. The synchronization between the laser <lb/>itself and the electron beam is automatically achieved since <lb/>the laser is the same that is used for the photocathode. A <lb/>fine adjustment is however possible by using an optical <lb/>delay line installed prior to the EO crystal. In order to <lb/>reach the synchronization between the travelling electron <lb/>bunch and the IR laser pulse, two arrival time monitor de-<lb/>vices are needed. For the laser we used a fast rise time <lb/>(30 ps) G4176 photodiode by Hamamatsu <lb/> TM <lb/> , while to re-<lb/></body>

			<page> 71 <lb/></page>

			<body> 1 <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/> Fig. 5. Optical layout before the EOS vacuum chamber. <lb/> trieve the electron bunch arrival time we looked directly <lb/>to the 5 GHz signals coming from a Cavity BPM installed <lb/>prior to the EOS station. Since both devices have broad-<lb/>band outputs, the signals are analyzed by a 20 GHz scope <lb/>by Tektronix <lb/> TM <lb/> . The EOS station with the Cavity BPM is <lb/>showed in fig. 6. <lb/>The Glan-laser polarizer located before the input win-<lb/>dow produce a horizontally polarized laser, necessary to <lb/>have its electric field parallel to the [−1, 1, 0] axis of the <lb/>crystal. After the crystal, another Glan-laser polarizer <lb/>(crossed respect to the previous one) is used, preceded by <lb/>a quarter-wave plate useful to reduce the residual birefrin-<lb/>gence (i.e. not coming from the EO effect) mainly due to <lb/>the induced stress caused by the high vacuum inside the <lb/>chamber in the input and exit fused silica windows. With <lb/>such a polarizer&apos;s setup, the output signal detected by the <lb/>CCD is <lb/> I  det  = I  laser  sin <lb/> 2 <lb/>  Γ <lb/>2 <lb/> ≈ I  laser <lb/>  ωn <lb/> 3 <lb/>0  r  41  E  bunch  (t) <lb/> c <lb/>d <lb/>  2 <lb/> , <lb/> (4) <lb/>where I  det  and I  laser  are, respectively, the signal and <lb/>laser&apos;s intensity and Γ is the relative phase delay induced <lb/>by electro-optic effect. Eq. 4 shows that the output signal <lb/>is proportional to the square of the field. At the end of the <lb/>setup, a PixelFly USB CCD camera by PCO <lb/> TM <lb/> , triggered <lb/>to the bunch emission rate at 10 Hz, is used to retrieve the <lb/>EO signals by looking at the laser&apos;s intensity modulation. <lb/>With a pixel dimension of 6.45 µm, and considering an <lb/>optical magnification M = 0.69 of the signal on the CCD, <lb/>according to eq. 2 the pixel time resolution is about 18 fs. <lb/>IV. EOS RESULTS <lb/>Two typical single-shot EO measurements are shown in <lb/>fig. 7(a) and 8(a), showing the output signal from ZnTe <lb/>and GaP, respectively; the time direction (i.e., the signal <lb/>longitudinal profile) is marked by a white arrow. Because <lb/> Fig. 6. EOS experimental station. A Cavity BPM is placed <lb/>before the EOS chamber to monitor the bunch arrival time. <lb/>The EOS chamber consists in two actuators, one for the EO <lb/>crystals and the beam screens and the other to move the <lb/>focus and the position of the top camera looking at these <lb/>screens. <lb/> the laser&apos;s intensity instability is about 8%, for a recon-<lb/>struction of the bunch profile, several screenshots with the <lb/>electron beam turned off are acquired in order to have an <lb/>averaged background screen-shot to substract to the sig-<lb/>nal&apos;s one; all background traces were taken with the same <lb/>laser and CCD camera settings that were used for the EO <lb/>measurements. <lb/>Fig. 7(b) shows a single shot EO signal after background <lb/>subtraction for ZnTe. A Gaussian fit has been calculated on <lb/>the experimental data, showing a sigma value of 434 ± 9 fs <lb/>(rms) for the first bunch and 331±6 fs (rms) for the second <lb/>one, with a distance between the two peaks equal to 921 ± <lb/> 7 fs. To take in account possible fluctuations on the bunch <lb/>lengths <lb/> 2 <lb/> , an average of 100 consecutive shoots has been <lb/>calculated, showing mean lengths of 444 ± 46 fs and 340 ± <lb/> 14 fs (rms) with a mean distance of 932 ± 27 fs. The same <lb/>computations have been done for the GaP crystal and the <lb/>result is shown in fig. 8(b); the Gaussian fit calculated on <lb/>the showed screen-shot of fig. 8(a) reports sigma values of <lb/> 329±18 fs and 336±11 fs (rms) for the two bunch lengths <lb/>and a distance of 931 ± 12 fs between the two peaks in the <lb/>trace. By making an average of 100 consecutive shots, the <lb/>average lengths of the two bunches are 461 ± 68 fs and <lb/> 346 ± 27 fs (rms) with a mean distance of 864 ± 58 fs. <lb/>The previous results obtained with a 500 µm ZnTe and <lb/>a 400 µm GaP show that the obtained bunch distance is <lb/>the same (inside the errors) for both crystals and its value <lb/>is compatible with the RFD data by assuming the over-<lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 2 E.g., due to the time jitter between the RF and the photocathode&apos;s <lb/>laser and RF peak power instabilities. <lb/></note>

			<page> 72 <lb/></page>

			<body> 1 <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>x 10 <lb/> −12 <lb/> 0 <lb/>250 <lb/>500 <lb/>750 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1250 <lb/>1500 <lb/>1750 <lb/>2000 <lb/>2250 <lb/>2500 <lb/>Time (sec) <lb/>Pixel Intensity <lb/> Data <lb/>Gaussian Fit <lb/> Fig. 7. (a) EOS single screen-shot for the comb beam re-<lb/>trieved by using the 500 µm ZnTe crystal. The time di-<lb/>rection is marked by the white arrow. (b) Projected pro-<lb/>file (along the time axis) with Gaussian fit, with calculated <lb/>sigma for the two main peaks of 434 ± 9 fs and 331 ± 6 fs <lb/>(rms), separated by 921 ± 7 fs. By making an average <lb/>of 100 consecutive shots, the average lengths of the two <lb/>bunches are 444 ± 46 fs and 340 ± 14 fs (rms) with an av-<lb/>erage distance of 932±27 fs. The signal (and the Gaussian <lb/>fit) is proportional the square of E  bunch  (eq. 4). <lb/> all transport in the dogleg line [12], while the calculated <lb/>bunch lengths are quite larger. This is an expected be-<lb/>haviour, first al all because the laser pulse length used in <lb/>the experiment is longer than the electron bunch lengths. <lb/>Then, one has to take into account the velocity mismatch <lb/>(between the propagating laser and the THz pulses) and <lb/>the phonon resonances (located at 5.3 THz for ZnTe and <lb/>10.98 THz for GaP) of the two crystals. The broadening <lb/>is proportional to the crystal&apos;s thickness since the different <lb/>frequencies of the THz pulse travel at different velocities <lb/> 3 <lb/> 3 Because the crystal refractive index is function of the frequency. <lb/> 1 <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>x 10 <lb/> −12 <lb/> 0 <lb/>70 <lb/>140 <lb/>210 <lb/>280 <lb/>350 <lb/>420 <lb/>490 <lb/>560 <lb/>630 <lb/>700 <lb/>Time (sec) <lb/>Pixel Intensity (counts) <lb/> Data <lb/>Gaussian Fit <lb/> Fig. 8. (a) EOS single screen-shot for the comb beam re-<lb/>trieved by using the 400 µm GaP crystal. The time di-<lb/>rection is marked by the white arrow. (b) Projected pro-<lb/>file (along the time axis) with Gaussian fit, with calculated <lb/>sigma for the two main peaks of 329±18 fs and 336±11 fs <lb/>(rms), separated by 931 ± 12 fs. By making an average <lb/>of 100 consecutive shots, the average lengths of the two <lb/>bunches are 461 ± 68 fs and 346 ± 27 fs (rms) with an av-<lb/>erage distance of 864±58 fs. The signal (and the Gaussian <lb/>fit) is proportional the square of E  bunch  (eq. 4). <lb/> respect to each other and respect to the laser; because of <lb/>this slippage, the THz pulse &quot;appears&quot; longer to the laser. <lb/>Moreover, the absorption and refractive indices of the crys-<lb/>tals grow rapidly for frequencies approaching the phonon&apos;s <lb/>resonances, therefore higher frequencies (corresponding to <lb/>shorter bunches) propagate slowly and the velocity mis-<lb/>match increases. As a conclusion, currently the crystal <lb/>thickness and the laser pulse length fix the EOS tempo-<lb/>ral resolution, that can be improved by reducing the thick-<lb/>ness itself (at the price of a lower EOS signal intensity) <lb/>while compressing the laser upto its transform limit (about <lb/></body>

			<page> 73 <lb/></page>

			<body>50 fs). In this sense 100 µm GaP crystals are able to mea-<lb/>sure bunch length of the order of 50 fs (rms), because in <lb/>this crystal the phonon resonance is localized at higher fre-<lb/>quencies respect to ZnTe. <lb/>V. CONCLUSION AND OUTLOOK <lb/>In this contribute, we used for the first time the electro-<lb/>optic sampling (EOS) technique to measure the longitudi-<lb/>nal profile of a comb-like beam consisting of two bunches. <lb/>The response of the electro-optic crystals, ZnTe and GaP in <lb/>our case, is the dominant temporal limitation in these mea-<lb/>surements. Simultaneous RFD and interferometric mea-<lb/>surements show a good agreement with EOS data regard-<lb/>ing the distance between the two bunches, while the calcu-<lb/>lated EOS single bunch lengths appear greater due to the <lb/>velocity mismatch between the THz and laser pulses inside <lb/>the crystal. With GaP thicnkesses of the order of 100 µm <lb/> a near crossed polarizer setup [7] should be used in order <lb/>to increase the signal on the camera while having a signal <lb/>dependence on beam electric field almost linear. By using <lb/>thinner crystals with a shorter laser pulse length, the time <lb/>resolution can reach about 50 fs. The non-invasive prop-<lb/>erty of the electro-optic measurement will allow it to be <lb/>used as an online monitor for electron beams to be injected <lb/>in future PWFA accelerators. <lb/>This work has been partially supported by the EU Com-<lb/>mission in the Seventh Framework Program, Grant Agree-<lb/>ment 312453-EuCARD-2 and the Italian Minister of Re-<lb/>search in the framework of FIRB -Fondo per gli Investi-<lb/>menti della Ricerca di Base, Project n. RBFR12NK5K. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>[1] E. Kallos, Plasma wakefield accelerators using mul-<lb/>tiple electron bunches, Ph.D. thesis, Faculty of the <lb/>Graduate School, University of Southern California <lb/>(August 2008). <lb/>[2] T. Katsouleas, C. Joshi, J. M. Dawson, F. F. Chen, <lb/>C. Clayton, W. B. Mori, C. Darrow, D. Um-<lb/>stadter, Plasma accelerators, in: American Institute <lb/>of Physics Conference Series, Vol. 130 of American <lb/>Institute of Physics Conference Series, 1985, pp. 63– <lb/>98. doi:10.1063/1.35293. <lb/> [3] S. Casalbuoni, H. Schlarb, B. Schmidt, B. Stef-<lb/>fen, P. Schmuser, A. Winter, Numerical studies on <lb/>the electro-optic sampling of relativistic electron <lb/>bunches, in: Particle Accelerator Conference, 2005. <lb/>PAC 2005. Proceedings of the, IEEE, 2005, pp. <lb/>3070–3072. <lb/>[4] D. Alesini, et al., The sparc project: a high-brightness <lb/>electron beam source at lnf to drive a sase-fel exper-<lb/>iment, Nuclear Instruments and Methods in Physics <lb/>Research Section A: Accelerators, Spectrometers, <lb/>Detectors and Associated Equipment 507 (1â ˘ <lb/>A ¸ <lb/>S2) <lb/>(2003) 345 – 349. doi:http://dx.doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/S0168-9002(03)00943-4. <lb/> [5] A. L. Cavalieri, D. Fritz, S. Lee, P. Bucksbaum, <lb/>D. Reis, J. Rudati, D. Mills, P. Fuoss, G. Stephenson, <lb/>C. Kao, et al., Clocking femtosecond x rays, Physical <lb/>review letters 94 (11) (2005) 114801. <lb/>[6] G. Berden, S. P. Jamison, A. M. MacLeod, W. Gille-<lb/>spie, B. Redlich, A. van der Meer, Electro-optic tech-<lb/>nique with improved time resolution for real-time, <lb/>nondestructive, single-shot measurements of fem-<lb/>tosecond electron bunch profiles, Physical review let-<lb/>ters 93 (11) (2004) 114802. <lb/>[7] B. Steffen, V. Arsov, G. Berden, W. Gillespie, <lb/>S. Jamison, A. M. MacLeod, A. Van Der Meer, <lb/>P. Phillips, H. Schlarb, B. Schmidt, et al., Electro-<lb/>optic time profile monitors for femtosecond elec-<lb/>tron bunches at the soft x-ray free-electron laser <lb/>flash, Physical Review Special Topics-Accelerators <lb/>and Beams 12 (3) (2009) 032802. <lb/>[8] A. L. Cavalieri, Electro-optic characterization of <lb/>femtosecond electron bunches, 2005. <lb/>[9] M. Ferrario, D. Alesini, A. Bacci, M. Bellaveglia, <lb/>R. Boni, M. Boscolo, P. Calvani, M. Castellano, <lb/>E. Chiadroni, A. Cianchi, et al., Laser comb with ve-<lb/>locity bunching: Preliminary results at sparc, Nuclear <lb/>Instruments and Methods in Physics Research Sec-<lb/>tion A: Accelerators, Spectrometers, Detectors and <lb/>Associated Equipment 637 (1) (2011) S43–S46. <lb/>[10] A. Mostacci, M. Bellaveglia, E. Chiadroni, <lb/>A. Cianchi, M. Ferrario, D. Filippetto, G. Gatti, <lb/>C. Ronsivalle, Chromatic effects in quadrupole scan <lb/>emittance measurements, Physical Review Special <lb/>Topics-Accelerators and Beams 15 (8) (2012) <lb/>082802. <lb/>[11] D. Filippetto, M. Bellaveglia, M. Castellano, E. Chi-<lb/>adroni, L. Cultrera, G. Di Pirro, M. Ferrario, L. Fic-<lb/>cadenti, A. Gallo, G. Gatti, et al., Phase space analy-<lb/>sis of velocity bunched beams, Physical Review Spe-<lb/>cial Topics-Accelerators and Beams 14 (9) (2011) <lb/>092804. <lb/>[12] E. Chiadroni, M. Bellaveglia, P. Calvani, M. Castel-<lb/>lano, L. Catani, A. Cianchi, G. Di Pirro, M. Ferrario, <lb/>G. Gatti, O. Limaj, et al., Characterization of the thz <lb/>radiation source at the frascati linear accelerator, Re-<lb/>view of Scientific Instruments 84 (2) (2013) 022703– <lb/>022703. <lb/>[13] E. Chiadroni, A. Bacci, M. Bellaveglia, M. Castel-<lb/>lano, G. Di Pirro, M. Ferrario, G. Gatti, E. Pace, <lb/>A. Rossi, C. Vaccarezza, et al., The thz radiation <lb/>source at the sparc facility, in: Journal of Physics: <lb/>Conference Series, Vol. 359, IOP Publishing, 2012, <lb/>p. 012018. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 74 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
