<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="footnote"> arXiv:1411.7293v1  [quant-ph] 26 Nov 2014 <lb/></note>

			<front> Information processing with Page–Wootters states <lb/> Stam Nicolis <lb/> 1 <lb/> CNRS–Laboratoire de Mathématiques et Physique Théorique (UMR 7350) <lb/>Fédération de Recherche &quot; Denis Poisson &quot; (FR 2964) <lb/>Département de Physique <lb/>Université &quot; François Rabelais &quot; de Tours <lb/>Parc Grandmont, Tours 37200, France <lb/> Abstract <lb/> In order to perceive that a physical system evolves in time, two requirements must be <lb/>met: (a) it must be possible to define a &quot; clock &quot; and (b) it must be possible to make a <lb/>copy of the state of the system, that can be reliably retrieved to make a comparison. We <lb/>investigate what constraints quantum mechanics poses on these issues, in light of recent <lb/>experiments with entangled photons. <lb/> 1  E-Mail: Stam.Nicolis@lmpt.univ-tours.fr <lb/></front>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> A focal point of the research of John Nicolis is information processing: his work contributed in <lb/>extending the scope of the concept from the purely engineering point of view to game theory, <lb/>the modeling of social phenomena and biological systems. In his latest work he was particularly <lb/>interested in how the quantum properties of matter and, in particular, how entangled states <lb/>could be relevant to information processing by systems such as proteins. In this contribution I <lb/>would like to present some results on a very simple model, that shed light on the questions he <lb/>liked to raise [1, 2]. <lb/>The problem we want to solve is the following: if we have a &quot; closed &quot; system, i.e. isolated <lb/>from its surroundings, under what circumstances can it &quot; tell &quot; time, i.e. define a clock? These <lb/>questions were framed in a particularly concrete way thirty years ago by Page and Wootters [3] <lb/>within the context of quantum gravity and, since then, the discussion has mainly been pursued <lb/>with these problems in mind [4]. On the other hand, the issues raised by Page and Wootters <lb/>are not limited to quantum gravity. In recent years technology has led to the possibility <lb/>of performing experiments on entangled photons, emulating some of the systems envisaged <lb/>in ref. [3], cf. for instance, ref. [5]. To understand the experiments it is useful to perform <lb/>simulations. This will be the main object of the present study. <lb/>It is important to realize that for an isolated system without any &quot; internal parts &quot; , it is <lb/>impossible to define what time (or space for that matter) is and thus what the corresponding <lb/>devices, such as &quot; clocks &quot; or &quot; rulers &quot; , could measure-indeed, by definition, there aren&apos;t any. To <lb/>be able to talk about time at all it&apos;s mandatory that the system either have &quot; internal parts &quot; <lb/>(subsystems or more than one states) that can eventually play the role of clocks, or be in <lb/>contact with another system, whose &quot; evolution &quot; can serve as reference. The movement of the <lb/>Earth with respect to the Sun or the Moon is a time–honored example. <lb/>This, however, is not sufficient: For the evolution to be observable it is, also, necessary <lb/>for a copy of the system&apos;s state(s) to be available: we need a copier and a retrieval device-an <lb/>indexation mechanism-a &quot; memory &quot; and a &quot; processing unit &quot; . Otherwise, it is not possible to <lb/>perceive any evolution at all-we &quot; see &quot; the system always in the same state, since we don&apos;t have <lb/>any means of comparison. In computer terms, we need a &quot; buffer &quot; . <lb/>These arguments are, of course, classical since the language we use describes classical no-<lb/>tions. Mathematical analysis allows us to describe quantum mechanical systems. It is here that <lb/>the subtleties of quantum information processing enter the picture [6]. <lb/>Let us, therefore, recall some features of classical information processing [1, 7] and comment <lb/>on the difference with quantum information processing. <lb/>In classical information processing the fundamental unit is the bit (binary unit), b, that can <lb/>take two possible values, 0 or 1. While modern digital computers use transistors–that work <lb/>by the principles of quantam mechanics–to realize the two possible voltage differences that are <lb/>mapped to the two possible values of a bit, the mapping itself is classical and the bits are <lb/>organized into bytes and words and manipulated according to the rules of Boolean logic using <lb/>transformations, called gates. There are two gates that can act on one bit: the identity and <lb/></body>

			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<body> the negation, that &quot; flips &quot; the bit, changing its value from 0 to 1 or vice versa. <lb/>Since we need a copy, b  2  , of the bit, b ≡ b  1  , we are interested in the transformations, that <lb/>act on two bits. We readily deduce that there are 2 <lb/> 2  = 4 possible inputs, so there exist four <lb/>possible transformations that map a state of two bits to that of two other bits. <lb/>In quantum information processing [6, 7] the fundamental unit is the qubit (quantum binary <lb/>unit), |b: This, too, can be in two possible states, | − 1 or |1. It, typically, describes the <lb/>polarization state of a photon or of an electron, in more complicated situations it describes the <lb/>intrinsic magnetic moment (spin) of an ion in a trap (and, then, can can be in more than two <lb/>possible states). But quantum mechanics only allows us to compute the probability for finding <lb/>the photon, for instance, in the polarization state |1 or the state | − 1, corresponding to its <lb/>helicity, or the spin component along any fixed axis of the electron. The general state of a qubit <lb/>is thus given by the following expression <lb/> |b = α|1 + β| − 1 <lb/>(1) <lb/>with α and β complex numbers such that |α| <lb/> 2  + |β| <lb/> 2  = 1. The probability to find the qubit, |b <lb/> in the state |1 is |1|b| <lb/> 2  = |α| <lb/> 2  and in the state | − 1 is |−1|b| <lb/> 2  = |β| <lb/> 2  . We deduce that the <lb/>space of all possible states a qubit can be found in is described by the equation <lb/> |α| <lb/> 2  + |β| <lb/> 2  = 1 <lb/>(2) <lb/>which is the equation of the 3–sphere S <lb/> 3  of unit radius. However only the relative phase of <lb/>the two complex numbers, α and β, is physically relevant: if we multiply both by the same <lb/>complex number, exp(iθ), of unit modulus, we get the same point on the sphere. Therefore <lb/>only two degrees of freedom remain: the space is S <lb/> 3  /U(1) = S <lb/> 2  , a 2–sphere, called the Bloch <lb/>sphere. The two poles of this sphere correspond to the possible states of the (classical) bit. <lb/>The time evolution of the single qubit should, also, respect this relation, expressing thereby <lb/>the fact that the qubit is, indeed, a closed system. <lb/>When we wish to couple qubits together, the quantum analogs of gates will be transforma-<lb/>tions on the space of qubits, in the same way that classical gates are transformations on the <lb/>space of bits. Whereas we can only flip the state of a single bit, through the negation, a qubit <lb/>has a much richer set of transformations, namely those that realize a motion of a point on the <lb/>unit 2–sphere and leave the origin fixed and the radius equal to unity, since it represents the <lb/>probability of finding the qubit in any possible state. <lb/>When we consider the analogs of the gates that realize transformations of two qubits we <lb/>therefore come to the conclusion that they, too, must obey such a constraint. We may write <lb/>the corresponding transformation as follows: <lb/> |ψ = |b <lb/> ′ <lb/> 1  |b <lb/> ′ <lb/> 2  = c  1  | − 1| − 1 + c  2  | − 1|1 + c  3  |1| − 1 + c  4  |1|1 <lb/> (3) <lb/>where the c  i  , i = 1, 2, 3, 4 are complex numbers, that satisfy |c  1  | <lb/> 2  + |c  2  | <lb/> 2  + |c  3  | <lb/> 2  + |c  4  | <lb/> 2  = 1. <lb/>Once more we remark that we may multiply all the c  i  by the same complex number, of unit <lb/>modulus, exp(iθ), without affecting this relation, that expresses, once more, conservation of <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body> probability. This describes a 7–sphere in an eight–dimensional space, but we must identify the <lb/>points that are related by a global phase, so the space of configurations of all possible pairs of <lb/>qubits is S <lb/> 7  /U(1), a much more complicated space to describe than the square, the space of <lb/>configurations of all possible pairs of bits. <lb/>The phase of the complex numbers c  i  is the relative phase of the two qubits. <lb/>Now that we have described the space of 2–qubit configurations, we can focus on the problem <lb/>of characterizing the transformations of this space. These can then be identified as one–step <lb/>evolution operators. We wish to classify those evolution operators that have the property that, <lb/>when they act on a 2–qubit state, the relative phases do not all change by the same amount. <lb/>This is how the system will be able to register the passage of time. <lb/>This is the subject of the next section, where we recall the idea underlying the proposal by <lb/>Page and Wootters and that of the experiment of ref. [5] and set them within this classification <lb/>scheme. <lb/>In section 3 we describe some simulations that highlight our approach. We close with our <lb/>conclusions and a discussion of directions of further inquiry. <lb/> 2 A generalized Page–Wootters framework for two pho-<lb/>tons <lb/> The analysis of ref. [3] considered a closed system of N spin−j particles. For simplicity we <lb/>will rather deal here with systems of two photons, considered in the experiment of ref. [5] The <lb/>states of the system are the product kets, |m  1  |m  2  , with m  I  = ±1, the helicities of the photons. <lb/>The system has four states in total so we can talk, meaningfully, about transition amplitudes <lb/>between them. <lb/>Since the system is closed the evolution operator, whose expectation values are the transition <lb/>amplitudes, must be a unitary operator [9]. A one-step evolution operator of this kind is given <lb/>by the following expression <lb/> U  k,l  = P  k,l <lb/> (4) <lb/>where P  k,l  = δ  k,l+1  is the one-step shift operator in the space of the four states. This simply <lb/>permutes the states and was used in ref. [5]. It has, of course, the property that U <lb/> 4  = I  4×4  . <lb/>But this operator is not the only one allowed. The most general unitary operator that <lb/>acts on the space of these four states can be constructed by introducing the operator Q  k,l  = <lb/>exp(2πik/4)δ  k,l  ≡ ω <lb/> k <lb/> 4  δ  k,l  , where ω  4  ≡ exp(2πi/4) is the fourth root of unity. Then the opera-<lb/>tor [12] <lb/> U(φ)  k,l  = c(φ) <lb/> 3 <lb/> r,s=0 <lb/> e <lb/> 2πiφr,s/4  ω <lb/> rs/2 <lb/> 4 <lb/> [P <lb/> r  Q <lb/> s  ]  k,l <lb/> (5) <lb/>with φ  r,s  real is a unitary operator. Since the operators P and Q do not commute, the action of <lb/> U(φ) on a state vector is not, simply, a permutation. Nonetheless, the system remains closed <lb/>and an &quot; outside observer &quot; , being unable to measure the global phase, observes a static system. <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body> The operator of eq. (5) also satisfies U(φ) <lb/> 4  = I  4×4  . Another, well–known, member of this <lb/>family is the Discrete Fourier Transform (DFT) for two qubits, <lb/> F  k,l  = <lb/> ω <lb/> kl <lb/> 4 <lb/> 2 <lb/>(6) <lb/>The property that will interest us here is that it doesn&apos;t commute with P , indeed its columns <lb/>are the eigenvectors of P : F P = QF . <lb/>The reason this property is desirable is that we want to use one photon as a clock for the <lb/>other. To achieve this we only have the relative phase of the two photons at our disposal and it <lb/>is easy to prove that, under U  k,l  = P  k,l  , the relative phase of the two photons does not change, <lb/>upon each application of the evolution operator. <lb/>We must thus introduce a mechanism to make the relative phases change. The experiments <lb/>done in ref. [5] use quartz slabs to induce a phase difference. The length of the slabs is the <lb/>proxy for the number of times the evolution operator acts. This defines the &quot; clock &quot; within the <lb/>two–photon system. (We remark that they thereby &quot; couple &quot; the, original, two-photon system <lb/>to an external device.) <lb/>One way to model this theoretically, while remaining within the two–photon system, is by <lb/>using the operator U(φ) under whose action the relative phases do not stay fixed, since P and <lb/> Q do not commute. Therefore, with the operator U(φ) as evolution operator we can define a <lb/>clock and the system will be able to &quot; tell &quot; time, by comparing the relative phases between the <lb/>states. <lb/>Let us show how the system can tell time, when we use U(φ) = F , the Discrete Fourier <lb/>Transform. <lb/> 3 Simulations <lb/> We start with the state <lb/> |ψ = c  1  | − 1| − 1 + c  2  | − 1|1 + c  3  |1| − 1 + c  4  |1|1 <lb/> (7) <lb/>normalized to unity, |ψ|ψ| <lb/> 2  = 1. Ref. [5], for instance, take c  2  = 0 = c  3  and c  1  = cos ω, c  4  = <lb/>sin ω, with ω some angle. We want to compute U(φ) <lb/> n  |ψ ≡ |ψ  n  and show that |ψ|ψ  n  | <lb/> 2  does <lb/>depend on the index n, therefore there does exist a relative phase between the two photons, <lb/>that is sensitive to the number of times the operator U(φ) has acted on the system as a whole. <lb/>Since U(φ) <lb/> 4  = I  4×4  , the physically interesting quantity is n mod 4 = 0, 1, 2, 3. <lb/>To provide a flavor, we shall choose as one-step evolution operator, U(φ) ≡ F , the Discrete <lb/>Fourier Transform of order 4. We may compute U <lb/> n  |ψ, by expanding |ψ on the eigenvectors <lb/>of F for instance [14]. For the case at hand we note that F <lb/> n  = F <lb/> 4m+k  = F <lb/> k  , with k = 0, 1, 2, 3. <lb/>So we just need to compute the action of F and of [F <lb/> 2  ]  k,l  = δ  k,−l  , which is the parity operator, <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body> on the initial vector. To do that we use the correspondence <lb/> | − 1| − 1 ↔ (1, 0, 0, 0) <lb/> T <lb/> | − 1|1 <lb/> ↔ (0, 1, 0, 0) <lb/> T <lb/> |1| − 1 <lb/> ↔ (0, 0, 1, 0) <lb/> T <lb/> |1|1 <lb/>↔ (0, 0, 0, 1) <lb/> T <lb/> (8) <lb/>to define how the one-step evolution operator acts on the states. <lb/>We find the following result, <lb/> |ψ  n  = F <lb/> n  |ψ = F <lb/> k  |ψ ≡ c  1  (k)| − 1| − 1 + c  2  (k)| − 1|1 + c  3  (k)|1| − 1 + c  4  (k)|1|1 (9) <lb/>where (c  1  (0) = cos ω ≡ c, c  2  (0) = 0 = c  3  (0), c  4  (0) = sin ω ≡ s) <lb/>c  1  (1) = (c + s)/2 c  1  (2) = c c  1  (3) = (c + s)/2 <lb/>c  2  (1) = e <lb/> −iω  /2 <lb/>c  2  (2) = s c  2  (3) = e <lb/> iω  /2 <lb/>c  3  (1) = (c − s)/2 c  3  (2) = 0 c  3  (3) = (c − s)/2 <lb/>c  4  (1) = e <lb/> iω  /2 <lb/>c  4  (2) = 0 c  4  (3) = e <lb/> −iω  /2 <lb/> (10) <lb/>Unitarity of the evolution operator implies that |c  1  (n)| <lb/> 2  + |c  2  (n)| <lb/> 2  + |c  3  (n)| <lb/> 2  + |c  4  (n)| <lb/> 2  = 1, <lb/>implying, also, that the system, as a whole, is perceived as &quot; static &quot; by an &quot; external &quot; observer. <lb/>Therefore the interesting quantities are the |c  i  (n)| <lb/> 2  . If these are independent of n, then we <lb/>cannot use the corresponding states to tell time. For example, if ω = π/4, then c = s = 1/ <lb/> √ <lb/> 2 <lb/>and |c  1  (n)| <lb/> 2  = 1/2. The relative phase of the two photons does not change with time in this <lb/>state. To tell time, therefore, if one photon&apos;s helicity is +1, the other&apos;s helicity must be −1, if <lb/> ω = π/4. In fig. 1 we display |c  1  (n)| <lb/> 2  = |−1|−1|ψ  n  | <lb/> 2  as a function of the time step n, for <lb/>different values of ω. For ω  = π/4 we find two lines, for ω = π/4 just one. The two values, <lb/>for ω  = π/4, indicate that the system can tell time and one, also, finds that the two values are <lb/>visited periodically. <lb/>Let us draw attention now to the following point: If we start with an initial qubit config-<lb/>uration, |ψ  0  and wish to compute |ψ  1  = F |ψ  0  , when we use the Fast Fourier Transform we <lb/>replace |ψ  0  by |ψ  1  . This precludes, therefore, the possibility of computing |ψ  0  |ψ  1  | <lb/> 2  . In order <lb/>to perform this calculation we must make a copy of |ψ  0  . <lb/> On a classical computer this isn&apos;t an issue of principle, but it does require allocating the <lb/>corresponding memory: Each qubit pair is represented classically by the array of complex <lb/>numbers c  i  , on which acts the evolution operator, a 4 × 4 matrix with complex entries. So <lb/>we just need to keep a copy of the initial vector and then exchange the current vector for the <lb/>previous one, for the evolution. <lb/>On a quantum computer, however, making a copy of |ψ  0  means finding a unitary operator, <lb/> C that performs the following operation [8] <lb/> C|ψ  0  = |ψ  0  |ψ  0  |c <lb/> (11) <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body> 0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>100 <lb/>&apos;c1_w=0.2.out&apos; <lb/>&apos;c1_w=0.25.out&apos; <lb/>&apos;c1_w=0.5.out&apos; <lb/> Figure 1: Plot of |c  1  (n)| <lb/> 2  vs. the time step n for ω/π = 0.2, 0.25, 0.5. For ω/π = 0.25 there is <lb/>just one line of points, for the others two. <lb/>where |c is the state of the copier, which must hold, of course, at least the qubit configuration <lb/>being copied. The &quot; no-cloning theorem &quot; [8] states that such an operator does not exist. What <lb/>can be constructed [8] is a copying operator that performs a copy with some finite precision, <lb/>which implies an accumulation of error in the copying with time, that certainly deserves to be <lb/>studied in detail. <lb/>We shall not enter into the details of the copying procedure, but refer to the paper [8] for <lb/>the technical details themselves. A detailed study will be presented in future work. <lb/>This is the result that does not take the entanglement due to copying into account. It does <lb/>illustrate that two photons can &quot; tell &quot; time, if their dynamics is rich enough, even though they <lb/>are a closed system. <lb/>The &quot; problem of time &quot; , in fact, is the &quot; problem of finding a copier &quot; . And this problem, at <lb/>the quantum level, while non-trivial, since the copier is not perfect, has a well-defined solution. <lb/>What we haven&apos;t had the opportunity to discuss is how to &quot; erase &quot; a copy, in order to replenish <lb/> the buffer. This raises a host of further issues that need to be brought together [13]. While the <lb/>problem of &quot; erasure &quot; is at the heart of quantum computing [15], the many, seemingly disparate, <lb/>issues remain to be brought into a broader synthesis, an element that was, also at the heart of <lb/>refs. [1, 2]. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body> 4 Conclusions <lb/> In conclusion we have presented an example of a closed system that can &quot; tell &quot; time operationally, <lb/>in a fully quantum mechanical way. The new feature that we needed, to do the job, was the <lb/>buffer memory. Quantum mechanics imposes severe constraints on its use, due to the non-<lb/>cloning theorem. Nonetheless, transition amplitudes between the finite number of states of the <lb/>system can be defined and we obtain, in this way, a simulation of the experiment presented in <lb/>ref. [5] that eliminates the need for many of the assumptions introduced there. In particular, we <lb/>remark that unitarity of evolution of the full system ensures that the &quot; center of mass energy &quot; <lb/>remains an unobservable, global phase–there is no need or way to set it to zero, once we have <lb/>defined the cocycle properly. We realize that we may use a much larger class of evolution <lb/>operators than hitherto considered and hope to expand on this in further work. <lb/>As a bonus we acquire some insights into the information processing capabilities of closed <lb/>quantum systems that may, also, serve as a starting point for investigating open quantum <lb/>systems. Such insights might, in particular, prove useful for understanding the quantum infor-<lb/>mation processing by black hole microstates [16]. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] J. S. Nicolis, &quot; Dynamics of Hierarchical Systems: An Evolutionary Approach &quot; , Springer <lb/>(1986). <lb/>[2] J. S. Nicolis, &quot; Chaos and Information Processing: A Heuristic Outline &quot; , World Scientific <lb/>(1991). <lb/>[3] D. N. Page and W. K. Wootters, &quot; Evolution Without Evolution: Dynamics Described By <lb/>Stationary Observables, &quot;  Phys. Rev. D27 (1983) 2885. <lb/>[4] E. Anderson, &quot; Beables/Observables in Classical and Quantum Gravity, &quot; arXiv:1312.6073 <lb/>[gr-qc]. <lb/>D. N. Page, &quot; Clock time and entropy, &quot; gr-qc/9303020. <lb/>C. J. Isham, &quot; Canonical quantum gravity and the problem of time, &quot; In Salamanca 1992, <lb/> Integrable systems, quantum groups, and quantum field theories 157-287, and London <lb/>Imp. Coll. -ICTP-91-92-25 (92/08,rec.Nov.) 124 p [gr-qc/9210011]. <lb/>W. G. Unruh and R. M. Wald, &quot; Time and the Interpretation of Canonical Quantum <lb/>Gravity, &quot;  Phys. Rev. D40 (1989) 2598. <lb/>[5] E. Moreva, G. Brida, M. Gramegna, V. Giovannetti, L. Maccone and M. Genovese, &quot; Time <lb/>from quantum entanglement: an experimental illustration, &quot; [arXiv:1310.4691 [quant-ph]]. <lb/>[6] A. Steane, &quot; Quantum computing, &quot;  Rept. Prog. Phys. 61 (1998) 117 [quant-ph/9708022]. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [7] R. P. Feynman and A. Hey, &quot; Feynman Lectures on Computation &quot; , Westview Press (2000). <lb/>[8] V. Buzek and M. Hillery, &quot; Quantum copying: Beyond the no cloning theorem, &quot;  Phys. Rev. <lb/> A54 (1996) 1844. [quant-ph/9607018]. <lb/>[9] J. Schwinger, &quot; Quantum Mechanics: Symbolism of Atomic Measurements &quot; , Springer <lb/>(2001). <lb/>[10] E. G. Floratos, &quot; The Heisenberg-Weyl Group on the Z  N  × Z  N  Discretized Torus Mem-<lb/>brane, &quot;  Phys. Lett. B228 (1989) 335. <lb/>[11] E. G. Floratos and S. Nicolis, &quot; Quantum mechanics on the hypercube, &quot; (2000) [hep-<lb/>th/0006006]. E. G. Floratos and S. Nicolis, &quot; Unitary evolution on the Z  2  n  × Z  2  n  phase <lb/>space, &quot; [hep-th/0505229]. (2005). <lb/>[12] R. Balian and C. Itzykson, &quot; Observations sur la mécanique quantique finie &quot; , Comptes-<lb/>Rendus de l&apos;Acadámie des Sciences Paris, Sér. I 303 (1986) 773. <lb/>[13] J. Distler and S. Paban, &quot; On Uncertainties in Successive Measurements &quot; ,Phys. Rev. A87 <lb/> (2013) 062112, [arXiv:1211.4169 [quant-ph]]. <lb/>[14] M. L. Mehta, &quot; Eigenvalues and eigenvectors of the Finite Fourier Transform &quot; , J. Math. <lb/>Phys. 28 (1987) 781. <lb/>[15] E. Weisz, H. K. Choi, I. Sivan, M. Heiblum, Y. Gefen, D. Mahalu, V. Umansky, &quot; An <lb/>Electronic Quantum Eraser &quot; , [arXiv:1309.2007 [cond-mat.mes-hall]] <lb/>[16] M. Axenides, E. G. Floratos and S. Nicolis, &quot; Modular discretization of the AdS  2  /CFT  1 <lb/> holography, &quot; JHEP (02)109 (2014). [arXiv:1306.5670 [hep-th]]. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>8 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
