<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Astron. Nachr. /AN 334, No. 6, 605 – 610 (2013) / DOI 10.1002/asna.201311906 <lb/> Large Hadron Collider and Dark Matter <lb/> L. Covi <lb/> Institut für theoretische Physik, Friedrich-Hund-Platz 1, D-37077 Göttingen, Germany <lb/>Received 2013 Apr 24, accepted 2013 Apr 29 <lb/>Published online 2013 Jul 1 <lb/> Key words Cosmology: theory – dark matter <lb/>We review shortly the scenarios of Weakly Interactive Massive Particle (WIMP) and Super-Weakly Interacting Massive <lb/>Particle (SuperWIMP) Dark Matter candidates and discuss the recent searches for Dark Matter candidates at the Large <lb/>Hadron Collider (LHC). <lb/> c <lb/> 2013 WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/></front>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> The simplest way to explain many cosmological observa-<lb/>tions at different length-scales, from the horizon scale to the <lb/>galactic one, (see e.g. Bertone et al. 2005, for a discussion), <lb/>is to introduce a new type of matter, the Dark Matter, which <lb/>has different properties than any particle seen in a labora-<lb/>tory so far. Indeed we know that it cannot carry baryonic <lb/>number, nor be electromagnetically charged, nor too light if <lb/>it is a thermal relic and that it has to be sufficiently stable on <lb/>cosmological timescales. Already these four simple require-<lb/>ments unfortunately exclude all the known particles of the <lb/>Standard Model as acceptable Dark Matter candidates and <lb/>oblige us to look at extensions of the model. So Dark Matter <lb/>is one of the strongest hints for new physics and the iden-<lb/>tification of a Dark Matter particle an important endeavour <lb/>both for particle physics and astronomy. <lb/>Even if such Dark Matter particle has not yet been seen <lb/>in a laboratory or in astrophysics (various hints instead <lb/>have appeared recently both in DM direct detection experi-<lb/>ment (Aalseth et al. 2011; Angloher et al. 2012; Bernabei et <lb/>al. 2008) and in indirect detection observations (Bringmann <lb/>et al. 2012; Goodenough &amp; Hooper 2009; Hooper &amp; Linden <lb/>2011; Weniger 2012), but none is yet completely convincing <lb/>or confirmed by another independent experiment or obser-<lb/>vation (Finkbeiner et al. 2013; Kelso et al. 2012; Kopp et <lb/>al 2012; Schwetz &amp; Zupan 2011)), there is still a strong <lb/>hope that it may be produced and observed at the Large <lb/>Hadron Collider (LHC), the collider with the highest centre-<lb/>of-mass energy and recently turned operational. Indeed the <lb/>LHC is finally exploring a new energy window above the <lb/>electroweak scale and seems to finally have seen evidence <lb/>of the Higgs boson, a first step in the exploration the elec-<lb/>troweak sector of any extension of the Standard Model. If <lb/>the Dark Matter is connected to the electroweak scale, as <lb/>implied by the WIMP mechanism, there is a justified hope <lb/>that the LHC should give us some information about it, if <lb/></body>  

			<front>Corresponding author: laura.covi@theorie.physik.uni-goettingen.de <lb/></front>

			<body> not produce it directly. On the other hand also in other type <lb/>of models, where the DM is not so directly connected to the <lb/>electroweak scale and could be also much lighter, e.g. the <lb/>SuperWIMP type of models, still the LHC collider can pro-<lb/>vide important constraints, and in the future perhaps even <lb/>find signals together with indirect searches. In this short re-<lb/>view we will concentrate on discussing these two generic <lb/>scenarios that are being probed at the LHC. We regret that <lb/>we will not be able to cover in detail all possible type of DM <lb/>candidates that have been proposed and point for that to the <lb/>extensive literature on the subject (see, e.g., Bertone 2010 <lb/>or the review Tait &amp; Hooper 2012). <lb/> 2 The Large Hadron Collider <lb/> The Large Hadron Collider (LHC) is a new proton-<lb/>proton ring accelerator constructed in the LEP tunnel at <lb/>CERN (Evans &amp; Bryant 2008). It has a circumference of 27 <lb/>km and it hosts 4 experiments at different interaction points <lb/>along the ring. For the quest for Dark Matter the relevant <lb/>experiments are the detectors ATLAS (Aad et al. 2008) and <lb/>CMS (Chatrchyan et al. 2008) (in alphabetical order . . . ), <lb/>which are &quot; general purpose &quot; detectors trying to measure any <lb/>possible signal of new physics. <lb/>Note that the LHC is a hadronic machine, i.e. the col-<lb/>liding particles are not fundamental, like electrons or pho-<lb/>tons, but are bound-states of different partons (each proton <lb/>has 3 valence quarks and a sea of other quarks and gluons). <lb/>In the high energy collision of two protons, only a single <lb/>parton of each proton is involved in the scattering, with an <lb/>initial energy that is not unique, but follows a probability <lb/>distribution (the partonic distribution function). Therefore <lb/>at LHC different centre-of-mass energies can be realized in <lb/>the single collisions so that one can say that it is possible <lb/>to &quot; scan &quot; energies up to the total centre-of mass energy of <lb/>the collider with a single collider. On the other hand, not <lb/>knowing exactly the initial energy of the two partons makes <lb/>the determination of any missing energy, carried away by <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> c <lb/> 2013 WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/></note>

			<page> 606 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> L. Covi: LHC and Dark Matter <lb/></note>

			<body> neutral stable particles like the neutrino, more difficult. In <lb/>practice one has to consider the conservation of momentum <lb/>in the transverse plane to the beam and then define quanti-<lb/>ties like the missing transverse momentum. <lb/>In 2011 LHC took data at 7 TeV centre-of-mass energy, <lb/>while last year the energy was increased to 8 TeV. At the <lb/>moment the collider is undergoing a shut-down and consol-<lb/>idation works, that should allow to reach the energy of 13 <lb/>or 14 TeV (Heuer 2012). <lb/>Another characteristic of hadronic machines is that the <lb/>colliding particles interact via the strong interaction as de-<lb/>scribed by the Standard Model and therefore most of the <lb/>time only &quot; boring &quot; SM, mostly QCD, scatterings happen in <lb/>the detector. The interesting events, involving e.g. electro-<lb/>weakly interacting particles like the Z, W or Higgs bosons, <lb/>happen at a much lower rate and have to be selected among <lb/>an orders of magnitude larger background. Actually due to <lb/>the limitation in the recording rate, most of the uninterest-<lb/>ing events have to be identified immediately and are not <lb/>recorded at all. How does an experiment like ATLAS and <lb/>CMS &quot; see &quot; a particle in such a complex environment? The <lb/>clearest signal is usually a peak in the invariant mass distri-<lb/>bution of the escaping SM particles, corresponding to an in-<lb/>termediate unstable state. In such way, the LHC has already <lb/>been able to measure known unstable particles, for example <lb/>the rho, eta, J/Psi, Ypsilon mesons and the Z-boson. Un-<lb/>fortunately the Dark Matter particle, which is in any case <lb/>neutral and stable on collider time-scales, is not visible in <lb/>this way and therefore the DM searches concentrate instead <lb/>on the missing momentum signature. But, as we will see <lb/>below, for non-WIMP candidates also other types of signal <lb/>could appear. <lb/> 3 The Higgs boson and Dark Matter <lb/> The Higgs boson is the particle connected to the scalar field <lb/>responsible for electroweak symmetry breaking. Such field <lb/>is the main ingredient of the Brout-Englert-Higgs mech-<lb/>anism (Englert &amp; Brout 1964; Higgs 1964a,b) which al-<lb/>lows to give mass to the W/Z bosons and break the elec-<lb/>troweak symmetry in a consistent way, retaining the renor-<lb/>malizability of the Standard Model. In the minimal case of <lb/>one doublet Higgs field only a single physical scalar parti-<lb/>cle is added to the Standard Model degrees of freedom and <lb/>such particle, called the Higgs boson, has very specific cou-<lb/>plings to the other states, mostly proportional to those par-<lb/>ticle&apos;s masses. This is due to the fact that the vacuum ex-<lb/>pectation value of the Higgs field itself give rise to particle <lb/>masses (but not to the masses of hadrons like the proton and <lb/>neutrons, which is instead generated by the QCD confin-<lb/>ing scale Λ  QCD  ). In this minimal case, the Standard Model <lb/>is very predictive and the only free and unknown param-<lb/>eter is the Higgs mass (Djouadi 2012). The Higgs boson <lb/>has been the missing block to complete the Standard Model <lb/>of particle physics for more than 40 years. Finally it seems <lb/>that the search is over: The ATLAS and CMS collaborations <lb/>presented on the 4th July 2012 the first evidence of a Higgs-<lb/>like boson, with a mass around 125 GeV (Aad et al. 2012; <lb/>Chatrchyan et al. 2012b). After that first observation, fur-<lb/>ther data on its production mechanisms and decay channels <lb/>seem to confirm that it is the Standard Model Higgs, but <lb/>more evidence (e.g. the experimental determination of its <lb/>spin and of the couplings) is needed to have certainty that <lb/>the model is just the Standard Model with a single Higgs. <lb/>It may appear that the presence of a Higgs field is com-<lb/>pletely independent from the question of Dark Matter, but it <lb/>is not so. On one side, there are very popular models where <lb/>the Dark Matter is part of an extended Higgs sector, like <lb/>the Inert DM model (Barbieri et al. 2006; Ma 2006), re-<lb/>cently compared to the LHC Higgs evidence in Goudelis et <lb/>al. (2013); on the other side, it is important to ask if the DM <lb/>couples to the Higgs field. In the last years the possibility <lb/>that the DM couples to the SM only via the Higgs fields has <lb/>been very thoroughly studied in the &quot; Higgs portal &quot; models <lb/>(Chu et al. 2012; Englert et al. 2011; Kanemura et al. 2010; <lb/>Lebedev et al. 2012; Lopez-Honorez et al. 2012; Mambrini <lb/>2011; McDonald 1994). In this type of scenarios, two ob-<lb/>servable signals of DM could be within reach soon: the di-<lb/>rect detection of a WIMP Dark Matter with scattering me-<lb/>diated by Higgs particle itself and the invisible decay of the <lb/>Higgs into Dark Matter particles (Djouadi et al. 2012a; He <lb/>&amp; Tandean 2011; Lebedev et al. 2012; Mambrini 2011). The <lb/>direct detection rate through a Higgs particle is in fact close <lb/>to the present experimental sensitivities for couplings of or-<lb/>der one as required by the WIMP mechanism (Djouadi et al. <lb/>2012a). Therefore such a scenario should come to be tested <lb/>very soon. Moreover, if the Dark Matter is lighter than ap-<lb/>proximately 63 GeV, an additional decay channel for the <lb/>Higgs should appear, corresponding to the decay into two <lb/>Dark Matter particles. Such channel is an invisible decay <lb/>at the LHC and can already be constrained by present data, <lb/>even if not very strongly (Djouadi et al. 2012b; Espinosa et <lb/>al. 2012a,b). <lb/> 4 WIMPs <lb/> As discussed in the introduction, we do not know the nature <lb/>of the Dark Matter particles, but a very important observa-<lb/>tion is that they could be naturally related to the electroweak <lb/>scale. In fact a very well-known paradigm in cosmology <lb/>is the Weakly Interacting Massive Particle (WIMP) mecha-<lb/>nism (Bertone et al. 2005). The mechanism relies in the de-<lb/>coupling or freezing out of stable thermal massive relics and <lb/>it is connected to the numerical miracle that a particle with <lb/>mass of about 100 GeV with electroweak cross-sections of <lb/>order G  F  has a relic energy density of the order of the crit-<lb/>ical energy density. Once an explicit model for the WIMP <lb/>interactions is given, the computation of the thermal decou-<lb/>pling can be made more precise and the parameters of the <lb/>model fixed to give the correct relic density. Realization of <lb/>the WIMP paradigm have been given in many different sce-<lb/>narios of physics beyond the Standard Model: from the case <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> c <lb/> 2013 WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/> www.an-journal.org <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Astron. Nachr. / AN 334, No. 6 (2013) <lb/></note>

			<page>607 <lb/></page>

			<body> of extended Higgs sectors (Lopez Honorez et al. 2007) to <lb/>supersymmetric models (Jungman et al. 1996), form mod-<lb/>els with extra dimensions (Kaluza-Klein Dark Matter) (Ser-<lb/>vant &amp; Tait 2003) to technicolor models (Foadi et al. 2009; <lb/>Nussinov 1985), etc. <lb/>In general WIMP candidates can give rise to a wealth of <lb/>signals: first of all they can still annihilate at the present time <lb/>where their density is large like at the centre of our galaxy <lb/>or other astrophysical objects, giving rise to measurable cos-<lb/>mic rays and or gamma-rays (Ibarra 2012). If the annihila-<lb/>tion produces also light charged particles also indirect radio <lb/>photons can be produced by synchrotron emission (Bertone <lb/>et al. 2009). This kind of signatures constitute the indirect <lb/> detection signals for a WIMP candidate and have recently <lb/>been very actively pursued (Bringmann &amp; Weniger 2012; <lb/>Ibarra 2012). Secondly the WIMP wind can scatter elasti-<lb/>cally against normal matter depositing a small amount of <lb/>energy (in the keV range since DM is not relativistic in our <lb/>halo) in a detector (Primack et al. 1988). This search strat-<lb/>egy is called direct detection and is also very active (Baudis <lb/>2012). Finally DM can be also produced at collider from the <lb/>annihilation of SM particles and this type of signatures will <lb/>be discussed in more detail in the next section. <lb/>Since the direct detection and indirect detection signals <lb/>can be quite similar in different WIMP models, the informa-<lb/>tion of colliders can be crucial to disentangle the different <lb/>possibilities. On the other hand, a DM candidate detection at <lb/>a collider is not sufficient to prove that the observed particle <lb/>is sufficiently stable and indeed makes up all the DM den-<lb/>sity in the Universe. It is therefore clear that only a multiple <lb/>signal of the same particle in possibly all three types detec-<lb/>tion will be needed to provide a strong case for a specific <lb/>WIMP DM candidate. <lb/> 5 Generic WIMP searches at the LHC <lb/> A very general search for WIMP Dark Matter at the LHC <lb/>is based direct production of Dark Matter particles in the <lb/>annihilation of two partons. In such process we expect two <lb/>DM particles to be produced, since the DM has to be stable <lb/>on cosmological scales. In fact if also a single DM particle <lb/>could be produced, by inverting the process this would im-<lb/>ply also a decay of the DM within much shorter time-scales. <lb/>After being produced, the DM, as a neutral stable particle, <lb/>would just escape the detector leaving unfortunately no ex-<lb/>perimental signature. <lb/>Fortunately it can also happen that the initial scattering <lb/>partons emit initial state radiation before annihilating, giv-<lb/>ing rise also to an additional visible particle. The emission <lb/>of radiation from an accelerated charge is a universal pro-<lb/>cess depending only on the initial state particle, so that the <lb/>production of invisible DM plus radiation is quite general <lb/>and has been suggested long time ago as a model indepen-<lb/>dent signal of WIMP DM (Birkedal et al. 2004). In the case <lb/>of LHC such radiation can take two different forms, i.e. that <lb/>of a gluon or a photon. Both particles are visible in the de-<lb/>tectors and provide a clear signal: a single jet or photon re-<lb/>coiling against nothing! This is what is called the monojet <lb/>or monophoton signature. <lb/>In order to give bounds on Dark Matter models, one <lb/>needs to model the interaction leading to Dark Matter pro-<lb/>duction. In the last couple of years great efforts have been <lb/>done in embedding such interactions in effective models for <lb/>WIMP Dark Matter and in comparing them with TeVatron <lb/>and LEP data (Bai et al. 2010; Fox et al. 2011; Goodman <lb/>et al. 2010, 2011) setting up the theoretical tools in prepa-<lb/>ration for the LHC. Already with the very first data in fact <lb/>theoretical groups were able to set the first constraints (Fox <lb/>et al. 2012; Rajamaran et al. 2011). <lb/>The effective field theory description is based on writing <lb/>down all the possible non-renormalizable operators between <lb/>two Dark Matter fields and the Standard Model particles up <lb/>to dimension six and classifying them according to the DM <lb/>particle type. In particular for a scalar DM field one has <lb/> L = <lb/> i <lb/> O <lb/> 2+n <lb/> i <lb/> (SM) <lb/> |χ| <lb/> 2 <lb/> Λ  n  , <lb/> (1) <lb/>where O <lb/> 2+n <lb/> i <lb/> (SM) are operators of mass dimension 2 + n <lb/> in the SM fields. We see here clearly that the lowest di-<lb/>mension operators can only involve the Higgs field, justify-<lb/>ing for example the study of scenario like the Higgs portal <lb/>one. Assuming that a single of these operators dominates, <lb/>the absence of a signal at the LHC can be translated into <lb/>a lower bound on the scale of the operator Λ. Moreover if <lb/>the same operator is also giving the main contribution to the <lb/>WIMP-nucleon elastic scattering, the LHC results can be <lb/>directly compared to the direct detection experiments (Bai <lb/>et al. 2010; Fox et al. 2011; Goodman et al. 2010, 2011). <lb/>The LHC collaborations have also searched for this <lb/>kind of signals, until now without evidence of any excess <lb/>above the background (Aad et al. 2013a,b; Chatrchyan et <lb/>al. 2012c). At the moment such exclusion regions are com-<lb/>parable to the ones from direct detection and are usually <lb/>stronger in the low DM mass region, which lies mostly be-<lb/>low the threshold of the direct detection experiments, and <lb/>for the case of spin-dependent interaction. It must never-<lb/>theless be mentioned that these constraints still contain a <lb/>model dependence in the specific non-renormalizable oper-<lb/>ator considered and not all the operators are bounded at the <lb/>same level. As it is to be expected, the LHC is mostly sensi-<lb/>tive to operators that couple DM to the colored sector of the <lb/>SM, in particular gluons and first generation quarks. Nev-<lb/>ertheless weaker bound on the leptonic operators have been <lb/>obtained also from LEP (Fox et al. 2011). <lb/> 6 Supersymmetric WIMP: the neutralino <lb/> Supersymmetry is one of the best theoretically motivated <lb/>symmetries for enlarging the Standard Model. It is a sym-<lb/>metry between bosons and fermions and requires to dou-<lb/>ble the SM spectrum adding for every particle a su-<lb/>perpartner with the same quantum numbers but different <lb/> www.an-journal.org <lb/> c <lb/> 2013 WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/></body>

			<page> 608 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> L. Covi: LHC and Dark Matter <lb/></note>

			<body> spin (Nilles 1984). In the minimal supersymmetric exten-<lb/>sion, the MSSM, a second Higgs field is needed as well, en-<lb/>larging also the Higgs sector of the theory and an additional <lb/>discrete symmetry R-parity, which forbids baryon and lep-<lb/>ton violating interactions keeping the proton stable. Within <lb/>the MSSM the lightest neutralino, one of the fermionic su-<lb/>perpartners of the neutral gauge and Higgs bosons, is a nat-<lb/>ural WIMP candidate as it was realized long ago (Jung-<lb/>man et al. 1996). In general the MSSM tends to point to <lb/>a Higgs mass value lower than the one observed at the LHC <lb/>and therefore probably more extended models are nowadays <lb/>preferred (Hall et al. 2012). <lb/>In the case of a supersymmetric model (or also any other <lb/>explicit WIMP model with colored states!), we expect at the <lb/>LHC much stronger production rates for colored superpar-<lb/>ticles than for the neutralino. The searches have therefore <lb/>mostly concentrated on gluinos (the superpartners of the <lb/>gluons, which are present in the proton) and first two gener-<lb/>ation squarks (the scalar superpartners of the quarks), with-<lb/>out success so far, pushing the bounds on these superparticle <lb/>masses above the TeV (see Aad et al. 2013b; Chatrchyan et <lb/>al. 2012d) for published results on the 7 TeV data of 2011, <lb/>but more recent ones have been presented in conference <lb/>notes or preprints, e.g. in ATLAS (2012) and in Chatrchyan <lb/>et al. (2013). Nevertheless, there are more general super-<lb/>symmetric models which allow to accommodate a heavier <lb/>spectrum and still a neutralino WIMP and DM (Arbey et al. <lb/>2012a,b; Cahill-Rowley et al. 2012a,b), so supersymmetry <lb/>is not yet excluded. In fact only recently the LHC collabo-<lb/>rations have started probing directly electroweakly charged <lb/>states like the charginos, superpartners of the charged Higgs <lb/>and W-bosons or supersymmetric models with R-parity vi-<lb/>olation, where instead the gravitino, the superpartner of the <lb/>graviton, could be DM instead. <lb/>Moreover there are regions of the parameter space, <lb/>where the signals of colored superparticles are less evident, <lb/>for example in case of compressed mass spectrum: in fact if <lb/>the mass difference between the superpartners is very small, <lb/>the SM particles arising from the chain decays into neu-<lb/>tralino may have such a low energy and momentum to be <lb/>effectively invisible. <lb/> 1 <lb/> In those scenarios, though, the monojet or monopho-<lb/>ton channels can again become useful. For example mono-<lb/>jet/monophoton bounds on the case of graviton production <lb/>in extra-dimensional scenarios and for Dark Matter produc-<lb/>tion at colliders given in (Aad et al. 2013c; Chatrchyan et <lb/>al. 2012c) have recently been reinterpreted for the case of a <lb/>degenerate gaugino spectrum, excluding gluino masses up <lb/>to 450–500 GeV (Dreiner &amp; Tattersall 2012). <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 1 One has to recall that in order to reduce the SM backgrounds, the <lb/>LHC collaborations require a minimal energy/momentum threshold for the <lb/>particles in the final state. <lb/></note>

			<body> 7 SuperWIMPs and decaying Dark Matter <lb/> Let us now consider another type of dark matter candi-<lb/>dates, i.e. particles that interact much more weakly than <lb/>the electroweak interaction. An example of this category is <lb/>the gravitino, the superpartner of the graviton, which has <lb/>spin 3/2 and interactions suppressed by the Planck scale <lb/>(Wess &amp; Bagger 1992). To be a Cold Dark Matter (CDM) <lb/>candidate, the gravitinos must be heavier than 100 keV <lb/>or so and remain out of thermal equilibrium. <lb/> 2 Scattering <lb/>processes in the primordial plasma can nevertheless pro-<lb/>duce a sufficiently large gravitino population, in particu-<lb/>lar those mediated by dimension 5 operators involving the <lb/>QCD gauge interactions (Bolz et al. 2001; Pradler &amp; Steffen <lb/>2007; Rychkov &amp; Strumia 2007). <lb/>Another population of gravitinos is also generated by <lb/>the decay of the Next-to-lightest Superparticle (NLSP), af-<lb/>ter it has frozen out, in the SuperWIMP mechanism (Feng <lb/>et al. 2003a,b), as <lb/> Ω  3/2  h <lb/> 2 <lb/> = <lb/> m  3/2 <lb/> m  WIMP <lb/> Ω  WIMP  h <lb/> 2 <lb/> , <lb/> (2) <lb/>where we are assuming the NLSP to be a WIMP particle. <lb/>But if such decay happens during or after nucleosynthe-<lb/>sis, the energy density of the NLSP is very strongly con-<lb/>strained (Jedamzik &amp; Pospelov 2009). An easy option to <lb/>avoid this problem is to allow for a small R-parity viola-<lb/>tion, so that the NLSP decays only to SM particles (long) <lb/>before nucleosynthesis (Buchmüller et al. 2007). In that <lb/>case also the gravitino is unstable, but it can have a life-<lb/>time much longer than the age of the Universe and remain <lb/>a good DM candidate. The requirement that the NLSP de-<lb/>cays early enough and for the lepton-or baryon-violating <lb/>processes connected to R-parity violation not to be in equi-<lb/>librium at the same time as the sphaleron processes (Dreiner <lb/>&amp; Ross 1993; Endo et al. 2010), singles out a particular win-<lb/>dow in the range of these couplings, 10 <lb/> −7  –10 <lb/> −12  . Of course <lb/>once R-parity is broken, the danger of too fast proton decay <lb/>reappears in the MSSM, but it can be avoided if e.g. only <lb/>the lepton number violating couplings or only the baryon <lb/>number violating ones are switched on. <lb/>If the R-parity breaking couplings are large enough, DM <lb/>decay could be observable today in different channels of in-<lb/>direct DM detection observations (Bertone et al. 2007; Bo-<lb/>brovskyi et al. 2010; Bomark et al. 2010; Buchmüller et <lb/>al. 2009; Choi et al. 2010; Covi et al. 2009; Ishiwata et al. <lb/>2008). At the moment the FERMI data set a lower bound on <lb/>the DM lifetime in photons of the order of 5×10 <lb/> 28  s (Abdo <lb/>et al. 2010; Vertongen &amp; Weniger 2011), already exclud-<lb/>ing part of the R-parity breaking parameter space. For par-<lb/>ticular gaugino masses and light gravitino, the DM decay <lb/>in gamma and neutrino can be suppressed (Restrepo et al. <lb/>2012), allowing for larger R-parity breaking couplings, able <lb/>to accommodate also the neutrino masses. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 2 If they reach thermal equilibrium, contrary to WIMPs, they decouple <lb/>as a relativistic species and therefore with a too large number density. <lb/> c <lb/> 2013 WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/> www.an-journal.org <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Astron. Nachr. / AN 334, No. 6 (2013) <lb/></note>

			<page>609 <lb/></page>

			<body> 8 Supersymmetric SuperWIMP: the <lb/>gravitino at the LHC <lb/> Supersymmetric models with gravitino Dark Matter (or in <lb/>general with SuperWIMPs DM . . . ) can give at the LHC <lb/>quite different signals than the neutralino WIMP scenarios. <lb/>In that case in fact, the role of the lightest supersymmetric <lb/>particle at the collider is effectively played by the Next-to-<lb/>lightest particle, that can be also a charged state and decays <lb/>into gravitinos only far away from the detector. Then the <lb/>charged tracks of such metastable particle would cross the <lb/>whole detector and be difficult to miss. The long lifetime <lb/>of a charged particle would then be the signal that a super-<lb/> weakly coupled particle is involved. In fact strong bounds <lb/>exist on charged relics and they do imply that any such <lb/>charged particle cannot be stable on cosmological scales. <lb/>The LHC collaborations have already performed searches <lb/>for exotic metastable particles, setting strong constraints on <lb/>metastable stop and gluino NLSP, reaching lower limits of <lb/>the order of about 800 and 1200 GeV respectively (Cha-<lb/>trchyan et al. 2012a). Weaker constraints apply on the other <lb/>hand to the s-tau NLSP as well as the other non-colored par-<lb/>ticles. <lb/>If the lifetime of the NLSP is shorter, then also the pos-<lb/>sibility of displaced vertices within the detector arises and <lb/>even a neutral NLSP could be visible. For the R-parity vi-<lb/>olating models discussed above, the LHC can then probe <lb/>the scenario of neutralino NLSP also beyond the parameter <lb/>space already excluded by FERMI (Bobrovskyi et al. 2011). <lb/>On the other hand, if the NLSP is neutral, it may become <lb/>difficult to disentangle the gravitino DM from a neutralino <lb/>WIMP only relying on collider data. In that case the pres-<lb/>ence or absence of detection in direct detection experiments <lb/>may be needed to distinguish the two models. <lb/> 9 Conclusions <lb/> The search for a DM particle is gaining momentum and con-<lb/>tinues on all fronts: at the LHC collider, in direct detection <lb/>experiments and in indirect detection observations! We do <lb/>not have convincing signals so far, but it is still early days. <lb/>The recent observation of a Higgs-like particle with <lb/>mass around 125 GeV is the first measurement on the Higgs <lb/>sector of our theory and already poses a few challenges for <lb/>the simplest supersymmetric models. But if the Dark Matter <lb/>is a WIMP that couples preferentially to the Higgs, a signal <lb/>should come very soon from direct detection. <lb/>Regarding general WIMPs, the monojet/monophoton <lb/>searches are providing independent tests of this paradigm, <lb/>complementary to the direct and indirect detection searches. <lb/>Such channels are actually also able to constrain other diffi-<lb/>cult scenarios like the case of small mass differences in the <lb/>new particle spectrum. Supersymmetric searches for col-<lb/>ored superpartners have reached the TeV scale and beyond <lb/>in the simpler cases, but the constraints on non-colored par-<lb/>ticles or third generation squarks are not yet as strong. There <lb/>is still room both for a neutralino WIMP or for a gravitino <lb/>SuperWIMP, let us hope that another signal, apart for the <lb/>Higgs boson, will appear soon! <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgements. The author would like to thank the Organiz-<lb/>ing Committee of the AG2012 Meeting for the invitation to give a <lb/>review talk and for the friendly atmosphere. The author acknowl-<lb/>edges partial financial support by the German-Israeli Foundation <lb/>for scientific research and development (GIF) and by the EU FP7 <lb/>ITN Invisibles (Marie Curie Actions, PITN-GA-2011-289442). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> Aad, G., Abat, E., Abdallah, J., et al. (ATLAS Collaboration) 2008, <lb/>Journal of Instrumentation, 3, S08003 <lb/>Aad, G., Abajyan, T., Abbott, B., et al. (ATLAS Collaboration) <lb/>2012, Phys. Lett. B, 716, 1 <lb/>Aad, G., et al. (ATLAS Collaboration) 2013a, Journal of High En-<lb/>ergy Physics, 1304, 075 <lb/>Aad, G., Abajyan, T., Abbott, B., et al. (ATLAS Collaboration) <lb/>2013b, The European Physical Journal C, 73, 2362 <lb/>Aad, G., Abajyan, T., Abbott, B., et al. (ATLAS Collaboration) <lb/>2013c, Phys. Rev. Lett., 110, 011802 <lb/>Aalseth, C.E., Barbeau, P.S., Bowden, N.S., et al. (CoGeNT col-<lb/>laboration) 2011, Phys. Rev. Lett., 106, 131301 <lb/>Abdo, A., Ackermann, M., Ajello, M., et al. 2010, Phys. Rev. Lett., <lb/>104, 091302 <lb/>Angloher, G., Bauer, M., Bavykina, I., et al. 2012, The European <lb/>Physical Journal C, 72, 1971 <lb/>Arbey, A., Battaglia, M., &amp; Mahmoudi, F. 2012a, The European <lb/>Physical Journal C, 72, 2169 <lb/>Arbey, A., Battaglia, M., Djouadi, A., &amp; Mahmoudi, F. 2012b, <lb/>Journal of High Energy Physics, 1209, 107 <lb/>ATLAS Collaboration 2012, Search for squarks and gluinos with <lb/>the atlas detector using final states with jets and missing trans-<lb/>verse momentum and 5.8 fb <lb/> −1  of <lb/> √ s=8 tev proton-proton colli-<lb/>sion data, Tech. Rep. ATLAS-CONF-2012-109 CERN Geneva <lb/>Bai, Y., Fox, P.J., &amp; Harnik, R. 2010, Journal of High Energy <lb/>Physics, 1012, 048 <lb/>Barbieri, R., Hall, L. J., &amp; Rychkov, V. S. 2006, Phys. Rev. D, 74, <lb/>015007 <lb/>Baudis, L. 2012, Physics of the Dark Universe, 1, 94 <lb/>Bernabei, R., Belli, P., Cappella, F., et al. (DAMA Collaboration) <lb/>2008, The European Physical Journal C, 56, 333 <lb/>Bertone, G., Hooper, D., &amp; Silk, J. 2005, Physics Reports, 405, <lb/>279 <lb/>Bertone, G., Buchmüller, W., Covi, L., &amp; Ibarra, A. 2007, Journal <lb/>of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics, 0711, 003 <lb/>Bertone, G., Cirelli, M., Strumia, A., &amp; Taoso, M. 2009, Journal <lb/>of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics, 0903, 009 <lb/>Bertone, G. 2010, Particle Dark Matter: Observations, Models and <lb/>Searches (Cambridge University Press, UK) <lb/>Birkedal, A., Matchev, K., &amp; Perelstein, M. 2004, Phys. Rev. D, <lb/>70, 077701 <lb/>Bobrovskyi, S., Buchmüller, W., Hajer, J., &amp; Schmidt, J. 2010, <lb/>Journal of High Energy Physics, 1010, 061 <lb/>Bobrovskyi, S., Buchmüller, W., Hajer, J., &amp; Schmidt, J. 2011, <lb/>Journal of High Energy Physics, 1109, 119 <lb/>Bolz, M., Brandenburg, A., &amp; Buchmüller, W. 2001, Nuclear <lb/>Physics B, 606, 518 <lb/>Bomark, N. E., Lola, S., Osland, P., &amp; Raklev, A. 2010, Phys. Lett. <lb/>B, 686, 152 <lb/> www.an-journal.org <lb/> c <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote"> 2013 WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/></note>

			<page> 610 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> L. Covi: LHC and Dark Matter <lb/>Bringmann, T., &amp; Weniger, C. 2012, Physics of the Dark Universe, <lb/>1, 194 <lb/>Bringmann, T., Huang, X., Ibarra, A., Vogl, S., &amp; Weniger, C. <lb/>2012, Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics, 1207, <lb/>054 <lb/>Buchmüller, W., Covi, L., Hamaguchi, K., Ibarra, A., &amp; Yanagida, <lb/>T. 2007, Journal of High Energy Physics, 0703, 037 <lb/>Buchmüller, W., Ibarra, A., Shindou, T., Takayama, F., &amp; Tran, D. <lb/>2009, Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics, 0909, <lb/>021 <lb/>Cahill-Rowley, M. W., Hewett, J. L., Hoeche, S., Ismail, A., &amp; <lb/>Rizzo, T. G. 2012a, The European Physical Journal C, 72, 2156 <lb/>Cahill-Rowley, M. W., Hewett, J. L., Ismail, A., &amp; Rizzo, T. G. <lb/>2012b, hep-ph/1211.1981 <lb/>Chatrchyan, S., Hmayakyan, G., Khachatryan, V., et al. (CMS Col-<lb/>laboration) 2008, Journal of Instrumentation, 3, S08004 <lb/>Chatrchyan, S., et al. (CMS Collaboration) 2012a, Phys. Lett. B, <lb/>713, 408 <lb/>Chatrchyan, S., et al. (CMS Collaboration) 2012b, Phys. Lett. B, <lb/>716, 30 <lb/>Chatrchyan, S. et al. (CMS Collaboration) 2012c, hep-<lb/>ex/1206.5663 <lb/>Chatrchyan, S., et al. (CMS Collaboration) 2012d, hep-<lb/>ex/1212.6961 <lb/>Chatrchyan, S., et al. (CMS Collaboration) 2013, hep-<lb/>ex/1303.2985 <lb/>Choi, K. Y., Lopez-Fogliani, D. E., Munoz, C., &amp; de Austri, R. R. <lb/>2010, Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics, 1003, <lb/>028 <lb/>Chu, X., Hambye, T., &amp; Tytgat, M. H. 2012, Journal of Cosmology <lb/>and Astroparticle Physics, 1205, 034 <lb/>Covi, L., Grefe, M., Ibarra, A., &amp; Tran, D. 2009, Journal of Cos-<lb/>mology and Astroparticle Physics, 0901, 029 <lb/>Djouadi, A. 2012, The Higgs Mechanism and the Origin of <lb/>Mass, in Progress in Theoretical Physics (ICPTP 2011), ed. <lb/>N. Mebarki, J. Mimouni, N. Belaloui, &amp; K. Ait Moussa, AIPC <lb/>1444 (AIP, Melville), 45 <lb/>Djouadi, A., Lebedev, O., Mambrini, Y., &amp; Quevillon, J. 2012a, <lb/>Phys. Lett. B, 709, 65 <lb/>Djouadi, A., Falkowski, A., Mambrini, Y., &amp; Quevillon, J. 2012b, <lb/>hep-ph/1205.3169 <lb/>Dreiner, H. K., &amp; Ross, G. G. 1993, Nuclear Physics B, 410, 188 <lb/>Dreiner, H. K., &amp; Tattersall, M. K. J. 2012, hep-ph/1207.1613 <lb/>Endo, M., Hamaguchi, K., &amp; Iwamoto, S. 2010, Journal of Cos-<lb/>mology and Astroparticle Physics, 1002, 032 <lb/>Englert, F., &amp; Brout, R. 1964, Phys. Rev. Lett., 13, 321 <lb/>Englert, C., Plehn, T., Zerwas, D., &amp; Zerwas, P. M. 2011, Phys. <lb/>Lett. B, 703, 298 <lb/>Espinosa, J. R., Mühlleitner, M., Grojean, C., &amp; Trott, M. 2012a, <lb/>Journal of High Energy Physics, 1209, 126 <lb/>Espinosa, J. R., Grojean, C., Mühlleitner, M., &amp; Trott, M. 2012b, <lb/>Journal of High Energy Physics, 1212, 045 <lb/>Evans, L., &amp; Bryant, P. 2008, Journal of Instrumentation, 3, <lb/>S08001 <lb/>Feng, J. L., Rajaraman, A., &amp; Takayama, F. 2003a, Phys. Rev. <lb/>Lett., 91, 011302 <lb/>Feng, J. L., Rajaraman, A., &amp; Takayama, F. 2003b, Phys. Rev. D, <lb/>68, 063504 <lb/>Finkbeiner, D. P., Su, M., &amp; Weniger, C. 2013, Journal of Cosmol-<lb/>ogy and Astroparticle Physics, 1301, 029 <lb/>Foadi, R., Frandsen, M. T., &amp; Sannino, F. 2009, Phys. Rev. D, 80, <lb/>037702 <lb/>Fox, P. J., Harnik, R., Kopp, J., &amp; Tsai, Y. 2011, Phys. Rev. D, 84, <lb/>014028 <lb/>Fox, P. J., Harnik, R., Kopp, J., &amp; Tsai, Y. 2012, Phys. Rev. D, 85, <lb/>056011 <lb/>Goodenough, L., &amp; Hooper, D. 2009, astro-ph/0910.2998 <lb/>Goodman, J., Ibe, M., Rajaraman, A., et al. 2010, Phys. Rev. D, <lb/>82, 116010 <lb/>Goodman, J., Ibe, M., Rajaraman, A., et al. 2011 Phys. Lett. B, <lb/>695, 185 <lb/>Goudelis, A., Herrmann, B., &amp; Stål, O. 2013, hep-ph/1303.3010 <lb/>Hall, L. J., Pinner, D., &amp; Ruderman, J. T. 2012, Journal of High <lb/>Energy Physics, 1204, 131 <lb/>He, X. G., &amp; Tandean, J. 2011, Phys. Rev. D, 84, 075018 <lb/>Heuer, R.-D. 2012 physics.acc-ph/1202.5860 <lb/>Higgs, P. W. 1964a, Phys. Lett., 12, 132 <lb/>Higgs, P. W. 1964b, Phys. Rev.Lett., 13, 508 <lb/>Hooper, D., &amp; Linden, T. 2011, Phys. Rev. D, 83, 083517 <lb/>Ibarra, A. 2012, Acta Physica Polonica B, 43, 2199 <lb/>Ishiwata, K., Matsumoto, S., &amp; Moroi, T. 2008, Phys. Rev. D, 78, <lb/>063505 <lb/>Jedamzik, K., &amp; Pospelov, M. 2009, New J. Phys., 11, 105028 <lb/>Jungman, G., Kamionkowski, M., &amp; Griest, K. 1996, Physics Re-<lb/>ports, 267, 195 <lb/>Kanemura, S., Matsumoto, S., Nabeshima, T., &amp; Okada, N. 2010, <lb/>Phys. Rev. D, 82, 055026 <lb/>Kelso, C., Hooper, D., &amp; Buckley, M. R. 2012, Phys. Rev. D, 85, <lb/>043515 <lb/>Kopp, J., Schwetz, T., &amp; Zupan, J. 2012 Journal of Cosmology and <lb/>Astroparticle Physics, 1203, 001 <lb/>Lebedev, O., Lee, H. M., &amp; Mambrini, Y. 2012, Phys. Lett. B, 707, <lb/>570 <lb/>Lopez Honorez, L., Nezri, E., Oliver, J. F., &amp; Tytgat, M. H. 2007, <lb/>Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics, 0702, 028 <lb/>Lopez-Honorez, L., Schwetz, T., &amp; Zupan, J. 2012, Phys. Lett. B, <lb/>716, 179 <lb/>Ma, E. 2006, Phys. Rev. D, 73, 077301 <lb/>Mambrini, Y. 2011, Phys. Rev. D, 84, 115017 <lb/>McDonald, J. 1994, Phys. Rev. D, 50, 3637 <lb/>Nilles, H. P. 1984, Physics Reports, 110, 1 <lb/>Nussinov, S. 1985, Phys. Lett. B, 165, 55 <lb/>Pradler, J., &amp; Steffen, F. D. 2007, Phys. Rev. D, 75, 023509 <lb/>Primack, J. R., Seckel, D., &amp; Sadoulet, B. 1988, Annual Review <lb/>of Nuclear and Particle Sciences, 38, 751 <lb/>Rajaraman, A., Shepherd, W., Tait, T. M., &amp; Wijangco, A. M. <lb/>2011, Phys. Rev. D, D84, 095013 <lb/>Restrepo, D., Taoso, M., Valle, J., &amp; Zapata, O. 2012, Phys. Rev. <lb/>D, 85, 023523 <lb/>Rychkov, V. S., &amp; Strumia, A. 2007, Phys. Rev. D, 75, 075011 <lb/>Schwetz, T., &amp; Zupan, J. 2011, Journal of Cosmology and As-<lb/>troparticle Physics, 1108, 008 <lb/>Servant, G., &amp; Tait, T. M. 2003, Nuclear Physics B, 650, 391 <lb/>Tait, T. M., &amp; Hooper, D. 2012, Comptes Rendus Physique, 13, <lb/>719 <lb/>Vertongen, G., &amp; Weniger, C. 2011, Journal of Cosmology and <lb/>Astroparticle Physics, 1105, 027 <lb/>Weniger, C. 2012, Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle <lb/>Physics, 1208, 007 <lb/>Wess, J., &amp; Bagger, J. 1992, Supersymmetry and Supergravity <lb/>(Princeton University Press) <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote"> c <lb/> 2013 WILEY-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/> www.an-journal.org </note>


	</text>
</tei>
