<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Tojdo~y Vol. 24. No. 1, pp. 89-95, 1985. <lb/>two-9383/85 53.00+ .oo <lb/>Printed m Great kitam <lb/>Pergamon Press Ltd. <lb/> SUPERCONNECTIONS <lb/> AND THE CHERN CHARACTER <lb/> DANIEL QUILLEN <lb/> (Received 14 February 1984) <lb/></front>

			<body> 41. INTRODUCI&apos;ION <lb/>LET ld:E &quot; +  El be  a homomorphism of complex vector bundles over a smooth manifold <lb/> M.  If u is an isomorphism over a subset A, then u determines a class in the relative K-group <lb/> K(M, A).  Many important classes in K-theory are obtained in this way [l]. <lb/>In this paper we present a new way to construct the Chem character in de Rham <lb/>cohomology of such a K-class. The construction involves a &apos;super&apos; or H,-graded variant of the <lb/>concept of connection as follows. Regard  E = E &quot; @El  as a super vector bundle and let D be a <lb/>connection on  E  preserving the grading. Let  L be  the odd degree endomorphism of  E <lb/>L=i <lb/>i i <lb/>( <lb/>&gt; <lb/> where u* is the adjoint of u relative to a given metric. Then  D + L,  suitably interpreted as an <lb/>operator on forms with values in  E,  is a superconnection. Its curvature F =  (D + L)&apos;  is an <lb/>even form with values in End  E.  One shows by standard arguments that the Chern character <lb/>form tr, eF, where tr, denotes the supertrace, is closed, and that its de Rham class is <lb/>independent of the choice of superconnection. <lb/>If we replace  L  by  tL  where t is a parameter, then we obtain a family of forms on  M <lb/>tr, #J + W&apos; = tr <lb/> s <lb/> ,t2L*+t[D, <lb/>L]+D&apos; <lb/> all of which represent the Chern character ch  E &quot;  -ch  E&apos;  in de Rham cohomology. On the <lb/>open set where u is invertible this character form goes to zero rapidly as t approaches infinity, <lb/>since  L2  is negative definite there. Therefore the character form for large t has a sort of <lb/>Gaussian shape sharply peaked along the set where u is singular. <lb/>The above construction was motivated by the problem of generalizing the heat kernel <lb/>proof of the Atiyah-Singer index theorem to prove a local index theorem for families of <lb/>elliptic operators. The essential difficulty in the problem consists in finding a suitable <lb/>representative for the Chern character of the index of the family as a differential form. The <lb/>above formula provides the desired differential form, but it must be applied to a map u <lb/>between infinite dimensional bundles. These matters will be treated elsewhere; here we <lb/>consider the finite dimensional case, where there are no analytical technicalities. <lb/> 52. SUPERCONNECHONS <lb/> Let V = V &quot; @ V  1  be a super (or Z,-graded) complex vector space. We use E to denote the <lb/>involution giving the grading: E(U) =  ( - l)dcsa u. The algebra End V of endomorphisms of V <lb/>is a superalgebra with the even (resp. odd) endomorphisms commuting (resp. anti-<lb/>commuting) with E. The supertrace <lb/>tr,: End l&apos;+ C, tr, X = tr EX <lb/>vanishes on odd endomorphisms, and for an even one it gives the difference of the traces on <lb/>V &quot; and C&apos; &apos;. The supertrace has the symmetry property <lb/>tr, X y =  ( -l)(dcg X) Meg u, tr, YX <lb/>(1) <lb/></body>

			<front> This  work is supported in part by the National Science Foundation <lb/></front>

			<page> 89 <lb/> 90 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Daniel Quillen <lb/></note>

			<body> so it vanishes on supercommutators: <lb/>[X, y-j = X y-( -l)cdes X)(dcs 0 yX. <lb/> . <lb/> Let  E = E &quot; @El  bea super vector bundle over the manifold M. Let R(M) = @G&apos;(M) be <lb/>the algebra of smooth differential forms with complex coefficients, and let <lb/>n (M, 4 = Q(M) &amp;-P(M) no (M, 4 <lb/>be the R(M)-module of forms with values in  E,  where $2&apos; (M,  E)  is the space of sections of  E. <lb/> Then R(M, E) has a grading with respect to Z x Z,, however we are primarily concerned with <lb/>its total Z,-grading, and so regard it as a supermodule over n(M). As R(M) is a commutative <lb/>superalgebra, R(M, E) can be viewed as both a left and right module over R(M). The relation <lb/>between left and right multiplication is <lb/>oa =  ( _ l)cdes 4 Meis a) ao <lb/> for o in R(M) and a in R(M,  E). <lb/> We will be working in the superalgebra of endomorphism valued forms <lb/>a = R(M, End JZ) = C~(M)@~O(~C~~(M, End I?). <lb/>Here @ denotes the tensor product in the sense of superalgebras, so <lb/>(WX) (fjy) =  ( - l)(dQ X1 Cdcs ql o?j XY <lb/>where we write WX instead of o@X. This algebra operates on R(M,  E)  on the left: <lb/>(uX) (qe) =  ( - l)cdes x, cdes 9) con Xe <lb/>The following is easily verified. <lb/> PROPOSITION 1. In the above way the algebra a can be identified with the algebra of <lb/>operators on R(M, E) which are Q(M)-linear in the sense that the even and odd components <lb/>satisfy <lb/>T(oa) = ( -l)Ch T) (deg 4 UT(~)_ <lb/> Note that if we use right multiplication, this formula becomes simply  T (ao) = T (a)o. <lb/> The supertrace on the fibres of the bundle End  E  furnishes a $I0 (M)-module map tr, from <lb/> R &quot; (M,  End E) to  Cl&apos;(M),  which then can be extended to a Q(M)-module map <lb/>tr,:  a = R(M,  End  E) + R(M) <lb/> tr,wX = utr, X. <lb/> (2) <lb/> This supertrace is of even degree since it vanishes on forms with values in (End E)&apos;. It satisfies <lb/>the same symmetry property (I) but for elements of  a, so  it kills supercommutators in  a. <lb/> We define a  superconnection  on  E  to be an operator  D  on  Q(M, E)  of odd degree satisfying <lb/>the derivation property <lb/> D (wa) =  (do) a +  ( - l)des w  Da <lb/> for CO in  Q(M)  and a in Q(M,  E).  For example, a connection in  E  preserving the grading, when <lb/>extended to an operator on  R(M, E)  in the usual way, determines a superconnection. Using <lb/>the proposition one sees that the difference of two superconnections is an odd element of  a. <lb/> For local calculations it is useful to describe superconnections when  E  is trivial, say  E <lb/>= M x V,  whence  a = R(M) @  End V. The most general superconnection is of the form  D <lb/>= d + 0,  where 8 is an odd element of  a.  We are mainly interested in the case where <lb/>8 = A+LER&apos;(M)@(E~~ <lb/>V)&apos;@Q&apos;(M)@(End <lb/>V)&apos;. <lb/>Here the superconnection is the sum of the connection  d + A  and the odd degree <lb/>endomorphism f.. <lb/>If  D  is a superconnection and Bea, then the supercommutator  [D, S]  as an operator on <lb/>!2(M, E) is linear over  Q(M),  hence is an element of 0 by the proposition. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SUPERCONNECTIONS <lb/> AND THE CHERN CHARACTER <lb/></note>
		
			<page> 91 <lb/></page>

			<body> PROPOSITION 2. One has d(tr,0) = tr,[D,  01. <lb/>As this is a local assertion, we can suppose E is trivial and write  D = d + 8  as above, and we <lb/>can suppose 0 = OX with X in End V. Then the result follows from <lb/>tr,[d+&amp; OX] = tr,(do.X+[&amp; <lb/>wX]) = tr,do.X <lb/>=  do tr, X = d (tr,wX) <lb/> since the supertrace vanishes on supercommutators. <lb/>We define the curvature of a superconnection D to be the even degree operator D2 on <lb/>R(A4, E). It is linear over Q(M) and hence can be identified with an even degree element of cI. <lb/>For example, if D =  d + 0,  then D2 =  de + t12. <lb/> From the curvature we construct the differential forms <lb/>tr,(D2) &quot; = tr,D&apos; &quot; in Q(M)evcn. <lb/>These are even forms, because the supertrace (2) preserves the grading. <lb/> THEOREM. Theform  tr, D2 &quot; is closed, and its de Rham cohomology class is independent of the <lb/>choice of the superconnection <lb/>D. <lb/> By proposition 2, d (tr,D&apos; &quot; ) = tr,  [D, D2 &quot; ] = 0,  since  D  commutes with  D2,  hence the form <lb/>is closed. In order to prove independence, suppose given two superconnections  Do  and  D,  . <lb/> Choose a one-parameter family of superconnections  D,  joining them, e.g. (1 -t)  D, + tD,  .  On <lb/>the bundle pr,  *E  over the product W x  M we  obtain a superconnection D = dt a, +  D,  whose <lb/>restriction to {t} x M is  D,.  In terms of a local trivialization of  E we  can describe D,  D  as <lb/>follows. Write  D , = dM + 8,,  where Br is a family of forms on  M  with values in End V, and let 8 <lb/>be the form on Iw x M not involving dt having the restriction8, on (t&gt; x M. Then  D = dy + 8 <lb/> and D = drd,+D =  (dtd,+d,)+e <lb/>= d,.,+e. <lb/> By the first part of the theorem we know trsB2 &quot; represents a de Rham class on Iw x  M <lb/> restricting to the class of tr,  Df &quot;  over {t} x M. By the homotopy property of de Rham <lb/>cohomology, it follows that the class of tr,  0: &quot;  is independent of t, finishing the proof. <lb/>For certain purposes it is useful to have explicit formulas which can be extracted from this <lb/>proof of independence. We have the formulas <lb/>D2 =  D* +-dtD <lb/> where (D), =  a,D, <lb/> D2n = D2 &quot; _t <lb/>1 <lb/>D2i &amp; LjD2i <lb/> i+j=n-1 <lb/> trsDZn = {trS  D2 &quot; } +  dt {n tr,  DZne2 D} = a +  dt B <lb/> O=d  axM(a+dt&amp; =  d,u.+dt(oi-dH/?), <lb/>so we  conclude that dc =  dMfl,  that is, <lb/>a,(tr,D,Z &quot; }  =d{ntr,D: &quot; -2d,}. <lb/> Integrating yields <lb/>s <lb/> 1 <lb/> tr D2 &quot; -tr  D&apos; &quot; =d <lb/> s 1 <lb/>s 0 <lb/> dtntr,D,Z &quot; -2D, <lb/> 0 <lb/> (3) <lb/>(4) <lb/> 43.  CHERN CHARACr&apos;ER FORMS <lb/>We now consider a superconnection of the form  D + tL,  where  D = Do + D&apos;  is a <lb/>connection in  E = E &quot; @El  preserving the grading, where  L  is an  odd degree endomorphism <lb/>of  E,  and where t is a parameter. The curvature of  D + tL  is  (D + tL)2 = t2 L2 + t [D, L] + D2, <lb/> where L2~Qo(iU,(EndE)&apos;), <lb/> t[Dv  L]~fi&apos;(M,(End <lb/>E)&apos;),andD&apos;~Q~(iV,(EndE)~).HereD~ <lb/>is the usual curvature of the connection  D,  and, as can be easily verified,  [D, L]  is  the usual <lb/>covariant derivative of the endomorphism  L  with respect to  D. <lb/></body>

			<page> 92 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Daniel Quillen <lb/></note>

			<body> The form <lb/>tr,(t&apos; L2 + t[D, L] + D2)n = t2 &quot; trs L2 &quot; + . . . . + tr, D2 &quot; <lb/> has components of degrees @,2, . . ,2n. According to the theorem in the previous section, its <lb/>de Rham cohomology class is independent oft. Hence the components in degrees less than 2n <lb/>are exact. (As a check, note that the degree zero term is zero, since L2 &quot;  is the supercommutator <lb/>of $L and L2 &quot; -&apos;.) <lb/> At t = 0 we get the 2n-form tr (D0)2n -tr (D1)2n which represents the Chern character class <lb/>n! {ch,EO -ch, E&apos;). (Note that the customary factor (i/2$ has been omitted. It has to be put <lb/>back in whenever we want the proper relation with integral cohomology, e.g. when we <lb/>integrate over a cycle.) <lb/>Apparently nothing has been gained by introducing superconnections, since all one <lb/>obtains are extra exact forms in degrees lower than the cohomologically interesting one. <lb/>However, the situation is quite different for the full Chern character form <lb/> tr <lb/> s <lb/> et&apos;L* + t[D, L] + D&apos; <lb/> = .zo i tr, (D + rL)2n <lb/> The series converges because (D + CL)&apos; is a section of a bundle of finite dimensional algebras <lb/>over M. We know that the de Rham class of this character form is independent oft, in fact <lb/>from (3) of the previous section we obtain the formula <lb/>,,tr~e~2Lz+t[D,LI+DZ = dtr,e&apos;2L2+t[D,4+D2~ <lb/>(2) <lb/>At  t = 0  the character form is the difference of the character forms for the bundles E &quot;  and <lb/>E&apos; calculated from the connections Do and D&apos;. Thus for any  t  the form (1) represents the class <lb/>ch E &quot;  -ch E&apos; in de Rham cohomology. <lb/>Suppose now that <lb/>where u: E &quot; + E&apos; is a homomorphism of vector bundles, and u* is its adjoint relative to a <lb/>given hermitian metric on E. Then L2 is negative definite, on the open set U where u is an <lb/>isomorphism. Over U, as  t + co,  the quadratic term in the exponent of the character form <lb/>dominates, and the form approaches zero. The necessary estimates to justify this will begiven <lb/>in the next section. <lb/>We next explain how all this provides a construction of the Chern character of the <lb/>difference element in K (M, U) associated to the map u. The de Rham cohomology of M <lb/> relative to U can be defined via the mapping cone complex of the restriction map from R(M) <lb/>to 0  (U).  A class is represented by a pair a E n(M), /I E R(U) such that da = 0, a  ( U =  d/3. Upon <lb/>integrating (2) from 0 to co, we see that such a pair is given by <lb/> a =  trseD2 = tr e(oY -tr e(D&apos;Y <lb/> dt tr, e&apos;= L2 + t CD. L] + D2 L. <lb/> We can use this pair to define the Chern character of the difference K-class. <lb/>The character form (1) for large  t  has a sort of Gaussian shape peaked sharply along the <lb/>set M -U where u is singular. It would be interesting to know when the character form has a <lb/>limit as a current on M as t goes to infinity. This current would have support in M -U and <lb/>would be a good representative for the character of the difference K-class. <lb/>Something like this occurs in the Grassmannian graph construction used in the modern <lb/>approach to the general Riemann-Roth theorem [3]. In fact both that construction and ours <lb/>use the device of multiplying a bundle homomorphism by a parameter and then letting the <lb/>parameter go to infinity. The two should be closely related. <lb/>e now compute the character form (1) in an important case. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SUPERCONNECTIONS <lb/> AND THE CHERN CHARACTER <lb/></note>

			<page>93 <lb/></page>

			<body> Example. Let M = UP &quot;  and let  E be  the trivial bundle  M x S,  where S is the space of 2n-<lb/>dimensional spinors. It is a super vector space of dimension 2 &quot; equipped with inner product <lb/>and anti-commuting hermitian involutions y&apos;,  . . . . , y2 &quot;  of odd degree. Moreover <lb/> tr, $1  . . . yip =0 ifp&lt;2n <lb/>tr,y1y2  . . . y2 &quot; =  (24 <lb/>(3) <lb/>Let  L be  the endomorphism of  E  whose value at x = (xp) is the operator iy &quot; xJ&apos; on the <lb/>spinors. For example, when n = 1, we have S = C @Q) with y&apos;, y2 and the grading E given by <lb/>the three Pauli matrices. Then  L = i (, &quot; z), z = x1 + ix2  is associated to the bundle map given <lb/>by multiplying by z on the trivial line bundle over d), which represents the element of K,  ( R2) <lb/> having degree -1 for the standard orientation. In general the bundle map given by  L <lb/> represents (-1) &quot; times the Bott generator of K,(W2 &quot; ) (see Cl]). <lb/>Finally we take the trivial connection  D = d  in  E.  Then <lb/> trse(d+tL)2 <lb/> = tr,e -?x&apos; <lb/> +udx&apos;y&apos; <lb/> =e  -r2xz tr, n (1 + itdx &quot; y&apos;) <lb/>r <lb/>=e -rzX2(it)2ntrsdx1 yi  . . .  dx2 &quot; yZn <lb/>=  (2i) &quot; e <lb/> -tzX&apos;t2ndxl <lb/> . . . dx2n <lb/> where we have used (3) and the fact that dx &quot; and yJ&apos; anti-commute in the algebra R(M)  @  End <lb/>S. <lb/>Integrating (i/27$ times this form over Iw2 &quot; with the standard orientation yields ( -1) &quot; as it <lb/>should. Note that the limit of the character form as t goes to infinity is a b-funotion current at <lb/>the origin. <lb/> $4. SOME ESTIMATES <lb/> In this section we show that, as t -+ co, the Chern character form (1) of 53 goes to zero in <lb/>the C &quot; topology over the open set U where  L2  is negative definite. We begin with some <lb/>estimates for elements  A, B  in a Banach algebra. <lb/>The first estimate, which follows immediately from Cauchy&apos;s formula <lb/>1 <lb/> et-4 = _ <lb/> 2rci <lb/>er&apos; (A -A)-&apos;  dl, <lb/>says that if the spectrum of  A  is contained in the half-plane Re(A) &lt;  a,  then <lb/>llerAIj 6  Me&apos; &quot;  for t 2 0 <lb/>(1) <lb/>with  M  a constant. We apply this to the expansion <lb/>s <lb/> 1 <lb/>eA+B= <lb/>eA+ <lb/>dte(l-r)ABetA <lb/>0 <lb/> and obtain <lb/> 1 <lb/>+ <lb/>s <lb/>s <lb/>11 <lb/>dtl <lb/>dt2e(l-&apos;I)ABe(&apos;l-&apos;z)ABe&apos;2A+ <lb/>. . <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/> s <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 <lb/> IjeA+BII s  Me &quot; + <lb/> drM2e &quot; IIBIj+ <lb/>dt, i&apos;dr2M3eY~IB~~2+  . . . <lb/> 0 <lb/>s <lb/>s <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/> or <lb/> Ile A+BlI $ MeQ+MIIBIl, <lb/> We now use these estimates to show that <lb/>er&apos;L&apos;+l[D.  Ll+D2 in Q(u, End E) <lb/> (2) <lb/></body>

			<page> 94 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Daniel Quillen <lb/></note>

			<body> goes to zero as t + co. Now n(U, End E) is a subalgebra of the algebra  R  of endomorphisms <lb/>of the bundle A  T* @ E.  The C &quot; topology on  R  can be described by a family of algebra <lb/>norms, each of which describes uniform convergence of derivatives up to order  k  on the <lb/>compact set K, for some  k  and K. Let 11 )I be such a norm and complete  R  with respect to it <lb/>to obtain a Banach algebra. Since the eigenvalues of  L2  on the fibres of  E  and <lb/>hence A  T* @E  are negative, it follows that the spectrum of  L2  in the Banach algebra is <lb/>contained in the negative real axis, hence  L2  satisfies (1) for some a c 0. Then from (2) we <lb/>have <lb/>lie <lb/> t&apos;L2+t[D, <lb/> L]+D&apos;,, <lb/>s M~~~LI+MIII[D, <lb/>L]+D&apos;(( <lb/>&lt; Mer2a+tb+c <lb/>= <lb/> and this goes to zero as t + co. <lb/> $5. THE ODD CASE <lb/> Let  F be  a vector bundle over  M,  and let u be an endomorphism of  F  which is self-adjoint <lb/>relative to a given metric on  F.  It is known that to u we can associate an element of K  1 (M, U), <lb/> where U is the open set where u is invertible. This follows readily from the fact that elements <lb/>of K&apos; (M, CJ) are represented by maps from M to the space of self-adjoint Fredholm operators <lb/>which carry U into invertible operators [2]. In this section we indicate how to modify our <lb/>previous constructions so as to obtain odd degree Chern character forms corresponding to <lb/>this odd degree K-class. <lb/>We will use the fact that vector bundles are equivalent to super vector bundles which are <lb/>modules over the Clifford algebra  C,  .  Here C, = C @ Q=a is the superalgebra with one <lb/>generator u of odd degree satisfying o2 = 1. Although commutative as an algebra, it is non-<lb/>commutative as a superalgebra. So one must be a little careful about left and right in order to <lb/>preserve the sign conventions of the super framework. <lb/>A supermodule over C, is isomorphic to one of the form V = IV@ C, =  W @ W,  where <lb/> W  is a vector space and <lb/> 0  1 <lb/>cr= 1 0 <lb/> ( 1 <lb/> flips the factors. We consider V as a right C,-module, whence endomorphisms  T  of V, even <lb/>those of odd degree, commute (strictly) with cr, as  T(v 6) = (Tu)(T  involves no change in order. <lb/>In particular rr itself is an odd endomorphism of I&apos;. Any endomorphism is of the form u + UC, <lb/>where u and u are degree zero endomorphisms, and hence can be identified with elements of <lb/>End  W.  Hence one has an isomorphism of superalgebras <lb/>End, V = (End  W)@C, <lb/> where End, I&apos; denotes the superalgebra of endomorphisms of V as a right C,-module. <lb/>The supertrace on End, V is defined to be the map <lb/>tr,: End, V -+ C, tr, (w + ua) = trwo. <lb/>This supertrace kills supercommutators and even degree endomorphisms. (From a general <lb/>viewpoint, the supertrace on a superalgebra is the map to the quotient by the subspace of <lb/>supercommutators. In the case of End, V, this quotient is the one-dimensional odd degree <lb/>subspace C,/[C,, C,], and so the supertrace can be identified with tr,.) <lb/>Given now the vector bundle  F we  form the super vector bundle <lb/> E = F@C, <lb/>= F@F <lb/> of right C,-modules and consider operators on  R(M, E) = Q(M, F)@C,  which commute <lb/>with right multiplication by 0. Those operators which are Q(M)-linear can be identified with <lb/>elements of the superalgebra <lb/>8, =  Q(M,  End  F)@C, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> SUPERCONNECTIONS <lb/> AND THE CHERN CHARACTER <lb/></note>

			<page> 95 <lb/></page>

			<body> and can be written a+  ba  with a,  b  in R(M, End F). The supertrace on u, is the map of odd <lb/>degree <lb/>tr,: CI, = R(A4, End F)@C, -+ R(M) <lb/>tr, (a +  ba) =  trFb. <lb/>Suppose we now consider only superconnections Don  E  which commute with ~7&apos;. Then the <lb/>curvature of 0, as well as the difference of two such superconnections, lies in a,. It is clear that <lb/>the arguments of $2 extend to show that the differential forms tr, Dzn and tr,eD2, which are <lb/>now of odd degree, are closed and have de Rham class independent of the choice of 0. <lb/>Next suppose we are given a connection  D  in F and an endomorphism u of F. Then D =  D <lb/>+ itua,  where t is a parameter, is a superconnection commuting with c. Its curvature is the <lb/>element of a, <lb/>o*=  -t*u*+D*+it[D, <lb/>u]a. <lb/> LEMMA.  Let a, b ER(M, End F) be of even and odd degree respectively. Then <lb/>tr, (a + iba) &quot; = i(tr (a + b) &quot; ) odd <lb/>trbea+iba = i(trea+b)odd <lb/>Proof:  Expanding (a +  iba) &quot; we  get terms of the form <lb/>tr,(.  . iba . .  iba  . . iba . .) <lb/> where the dots stand for powers of a. As a is of even degree, it commutes with a in a,, and <lb/>similarly  b  anti-commutes with a. Thus the factors  ia  cancel in pairs. Since tr, kills terms with <lb/>an even number of  a  factors, we are left with a sum of terms  itr (. . b. . b. . b. .)  with an odd <lb/>number of  b&apos;s,  which clearly gives the expansion of the right side. The second formula follows <lb/>from the first. <lb/>We apply this lemma to a =  -t*  uz +  D*  and  b = t [D, u]  and get the odd degree form <lb/>tr d <lb/>eBl = j(tre-&apos;zU1+r[D.U]+D2 <lb/> )  odd <lb/> This is closed and its de Rham class is independent oft. If u is self-adjoint, then as t goes to <lb/>infinity, this form goes to zero on the set where u is invertible. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> REFERENCES <lb/>1. M. F. ATIYAH, R. Barr and A. SHAPIRO: Clifford modules, Topology 3, Suppl. 1 (1964), 3-38. <lb/>2. M. F. ATIYAH and I. M. SINGER: Index theory for skew-adjoint Fredholm operators,  Pub/. Math. I.H.E.S. 37 <lb/>(1969). S-26. <lb/>3.  P.  BAUM. W. FULTON and R. MACPHERSON: Riemann-Roth  for singular varieties,  Pub/. Math.  I.H.E.S. 45 (1975). <lb/>101-145. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
