<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Hyperfine Interact (2012) 213:147–158 <lb/>DOI 10.1007/s10751-011-0397-2 <lb/> The PAMELA space mission for antimatter and dark <lb/>matter searches in space <lb/> M. Boezio · A. Bruno · O. Adriani · G. C. Barbarino · G. A. Bazilevskaya · <lb/> R. Bellotti · E. A. Bogomolov · M. Bongi · V. Bonvicini · S. Borisov · S. Bottai · <lb/> F. Cafagna · D. Campana · R. Carbone · P. Carlson · M. Casolino · G. Castellini · <lb/> L. Consiglio · M. P. De Pascale · C. De Santis · N. De Simone · V. Di Felice · <lb/> A. M. Galper · W. Gillard · L. Grishantseva · G. Jerse · A. V. Karelin · <lb/> M. D. Kheymits · S. V. Koldashov · S. Y. Krutkov · A. N. Kvashnin · A. Leonov · <lb/> V. Malakhov · L. Marcelli · A. G. Mayorov · W. Menn · V. V. Mikhailov · <lb/> E. Mocchiutti · A. Monaco · N. Mori · N. Nikonov · G. Osteria · F. Palma · P. Papini · <lb/> M. Pearce · P. Picozza · C. Pizzolotto · M. Ricci · S. B. Ricciarini · L. Rossetto · <lb/> R. Sarkar · M. Simon · R. Sparvoli · P. Spillantini · Y. I. Stozhkov · A. Vacchi · <lb/> E. Vannuccini · G. Vasilyev · S. A. Voronov · Y. T. Yurkin · J. Wu · G. Zampa · <lb/> N. Zampa · V. G. Zverev <lb/> Published online: 21 October 2011 <lb/>© Springer Science+Business Media B.V. 2011 <lb/>J. Wu was on leave from School of Mathematics and Physics, China University of Geosciences, <lb/>430074 Wuhan, China. <lb/>M. Boezio (B) · V. Bonvicini · G. Jerse · E. Mocchiutti · C. Pizzolotto · R. Sarkar · A. Vacchi · <lb/> G. Zampa · N. Zampa <lb/>Sezione di Trieste, INFN, 34149 Trieste, Italy <lb/>e-mail: Mirko.Boezio@ts.infn.it <lb/>A. Bruno · R. Bellotti · F. Cafagna · A. Monaco <lb/>Department of Physics, University of Bari, 70126 Bari, Italy <lb/>A. Bruno · R. Bellotti · A. Monaco <lb/>Sezione di Bari, INFN, 70126 Bari, Italy <lb/>A. Bruno <lb/>e-mail: Alessandro.Bruno@ba.infn.it <lb/>O. Adriani · N. Mori · P. Spillantini <lb/>Department of Physics, University of Florence, Sesto Fiorentino, 50019 Florence, Italy <lb/>O. Adriani · M. Bongi · S. Bottai · N. Mori · P. Papini · S. B. Ricciarini · P. Spillantini · <lb/> E. Vannuccini <lb/>Sezione di Florence, INFN, Sesto Fiorentino, 50019 Florence, Italy <lb/>G. C. Barbarino <lb/>Department of Physics, University of Naples &quot; Federico II &quot; , 80126 Naples, Italy <lb/>G. C. Barbarino · D. Campana · R. Carbone · L. Consiglio · G. Osteria <lb/>Sezione di Naples, INFN, 80126 Naples, Italy <lb/>G. A. Bazilevskaya · A. N. Kvashnin · Y. I. Stozhkov <lb/>Lebedev Physical Institute, 119991, Moscow, Russia <lb/></front>

			<page> 148 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headntoe"> M. Boezio et al. <lb/></note>

			<front> Abstract The PAMELA satellite-borne experiment has presented new results on <lb/>cosmic-ray antiparticles that can be interpreted in terms of DM annihilation or pulsar <lb/>contribution. The instrument was launched from the Baikonur cosmodrome and it <lb/>has been collecting data since July 2006. The combination of a permanent magnet <lb/>silicon strip spectrometer and a silicon-tungsten imaging calorimeter allows precision <lb/>studies of the charged cosmic radiation to be conducted over a wide energy range <lb/>with high statistics. The primary scientific goal is the measurement of the antiproton <lb/>and positron energy spectrum in order to search for exotic sources. PAMELA is also <lb/>searching for primordial antinuclei (anti-helium), and testing cosmic-ray propagation <lb/>models through precise measurements of the antiparticle energy spectrum and <lb/>precision studies of light nuclei and their isotopes. This talk illustrates the most recent <lb/>scientific results obtained by the PAMELA experiment. <lb/> Keywords Cosmic rays · Antimatter · Dark matter <lb/></front>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> PAMELA (a &quot; Payload for Antimatter Matter Exploration and Light-nuclei Astro-<lb/>physics &quot; [1]) is a satellite-borne experiment conceived to study charged particles in <lb/>the cosmic radiation. In particular, it has been designed and optimized to measure <lb/></body>

			<front> E. A. Bogomolov · S. Y. Krutkov · N. Nikonov · G. Vasilyev <lb/>Ioffe Physical Technical Institute, 194021 St. Petersburg, Russia <lb/>S. Borisov · M. Casolino · M. P. De Pascale · C. De Santis · N. De Simone · V. Di Felice · <lb/> L. Marcelli · N. Nikonov · F. Palma · P. Picozza · R. Sparvoli <lb/>Sezione di Rome &quot; Tor Vergata &quot; , INFN, 00133 Rome, Italy <lb/>S. Borisov · R. Carbone · M. P. De Pascale · C. De Santis · N. De Simone · N. Nikonov · <lb/> F. Palma · P. Picozza · R. Sparvoli <lb/>Department of Physics, University of Rome &quot; Tor Vergata &quot; , 00133 Rome, Italy <lb/>S. Borisov · A. M. Galper · L. Grishantseva · A. V. Karelin · M. D. Kheymits · S. V. Koldashov · <lb/> A. Leonov · V. Malakhov · A. G. Mayorov · V. V. Mikhailov · S. A. Voronov · Y. T. Yurkin · <lb/> V. G. Zverev <lb/>NRNU MEPhI, 115409 Moscow, Russia <lb/>P. Carlson · W. Gillard · M. Pearce · L. Rossetto · J. Wu <lb/>Department of Physics, and the Oskar Klein Centre for Cosmoparticle Physics, KTH, <lb/>AlbaNova University Centre, 10691 Stockholm, Sweden <lb/>G. Castellini <lb/>IFAC, Sesto Fiorentino, 50019 Florence, Italy <lb/>G. Jerse <lb/>Department of Physics, University of Trieste, 34147 Trieste, Italy <lb/>W. Menn · M. Simon <lb/>Department of Physics, Universitat Siegen, 57068 Siegen, Germany <lb/>M. Ricci <lb/>Laboratori Nazionali di Frascati, INFN, Via Enrico Fermi 40, 00044 Frascati, Italy <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote"> The PAMELA space mission for antimatter and dark matter searches in space <lb/></note>

			<page>149 <lb/></page>

			<body> the rare antimatter component in a wide energy interval, ranging from several tens <lb/>of MeV to some hundreds of GeV, and with unprecedented precision and sensitivity. <lb/>Antiprotons and positrons, expected to be created mostly in the interaction of <lb/>cosmic-rays (CR) with the interstellar medium (ISM), are fundamental in studies <lb/>of production and propagation of CR in the Galaxy, providing complementary <lb/>information to light nuclei, originated through spallation reactions of heavier nuclei. <lb/>Differently, the antiproton production is characterized by a relatively high kinematic <lb/>threshold, and reflects the propagation history of the dominant proton component <lb/>of the cosmic radiation. Additionally, the propagation of electrons and positrons is <lb/>governed by mechanisms different from those of CR nuclei, allowing the electromag-<lb/>netic conditions encountered during the transport in the Galaxy to be studied. <lb/>Moreover, CR antiparticle measurements have been long considered as one of <lb/>the most promising tools for indirect dark matter (DM) searches, since DM particles <lb/>should annihilate or decay into products as neutrinos, photons, protons, antiprotons, <lb/>electrons and positrons. Predicted DM antiproton and positron fluxes could be <lb/>detectable above the background from nuclear interactions through a distortion of <lb/>the measured spectra, and such excess of cosmic antimatter may be detected in space-<lb/>based or balloon-borne experiments. <lb/>Indeed, the observation of CR antiparticles allows the investigation of the global <lb/>matter/antimatter symmetry of the Universe. In case of existence of antigalaxies, <lb/>signals of antimatter could be detected in the extragalactic component of the cosmic <lb/>radiation. While CR antiprotons can be used to probe some intrinsic properties of <lb/>antimatter (lower limit on the decay lifetime [2]), only the detection of antinuclei <lb/>with Z≥2 would provide direct evidence of the existence of antimatter domains in <lb/>the Universe. PAMELA design sensitivity allows to accurately measure the ¯ <lb/> He/He <lb/> flux ratio in a large rigidity interval. <lb/>Finally, concomitant scientific goals of the PAMELA experiment concern the <lb/>study of solar modulation, by investigating low energy (anti)particles in the cosmic <lb/>radiation during the 24 <lb/> th  solar minimum, and the study of CR interaction with the <lb/>Earth&apos;s magnetosphere. <lb/> 2 The PAMELA experiment <lb/> PAMELA is in orbit since 15 June 2006, when it was launched from the Baikonur <lb/>cosmodrome on board the &quot; Resurs-DK1 &quot; satellite. The apparatus is housed inside <lb/>an aluminum pressurized container, with a maximum thickness of 2 mm in corre-<lb/>spondence of the PAMELA acceptance window. PAMELA comprises a number of <lb/>sub-detectors with specific tasks (see Fig. 1), in order to identify antiparticles with <lb/>high accuracy, over the large background from the most abundant CR components. <lb/>The central part of the instrument is the magnetic spectrometer, which allows a <lb/>precise determination of the sign, absolute value of charge Z and rigidity (R = pc/Ze) <lb/>of incident particles. It consists of a hollow 0.43 T permanent magnet (Nd-Fe-B) and <lb/>of a set of six silicon microstrip sensor planes, uniformly positioned along the cavity. <lb/>These detectors are provided with a sensitive layer on both upper (X or bending <lb/>view) and lower side (Y or not-bending view), with the implanted strips of one side <lb/>orthogonal to those of the other, allowing the independent measurement of both the <lb/>X and Y coordinates of the crossing point of an incident ionizing particle, with a <lb/></body>

			<page> 150 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> M. Boezio et al. <lb/></note>

			<body> Fig. 1 Schematic drawing of <lb/>the PAMELA apparatus, <lb/>showing sensitive areas of the <lb/>various subdetectors to scale, <lb/>in a longitudinal section. The <lb/>detector is approximately <lb/>1.3 m high, has a mass of <lb/>470 kg and an average power <lb/>consumption of 355 W. The <lb/>magnetic field inside the <lb/>spectrometer cavity is oriented <lb/>along the Y-direction, with an <lb/>average value of 0.43 T <lb/> spatial resolution of 3.0 ± 0.1 μm and of 11.5 ± 0.6 μm, respectively. The PAMELA <lb/>spectrometer has a 21.5 cm <lb/> 2  sr geometric factor, and it has been designed to achieve <lb/>a Maximum Detectable Rigidity (MDR, defined as the value for which the relative <lb/>uncertainty is 100%) of about 1 TV. <lb/>An electromagnetic calorimeter, located below the spectrometer, provides sepa-<lb/>ration of hadrons and leptons by means of their interaction pattern when traversing <lb/>the detector. It consists of 22 planes, each made up of a central tungsten absorber <lb/>of thickness 2.6 mm sandwiched between two 380 μm thick silicon detectors. The <lb/>spatial development of a shower is reconstructed by the layers of silicon detectors <lb/>which are divided into strips in alternating directions for each plane. The total depth <lb/>of the calorimeter amounts to 16.3 radiation lengths (0.6 nuclear interaction lengths), <lb/>so both electrons and positrons develop a well-contained electromagnetic shower <lb/>below some hundreds of GeV. <lb/>A time-of-flight (TOF) measurement is performed by a set of fast plastic scintilla-<lb/>tors arranged in three planes (S1, S2 and S3), with alternate layers placed orthogonal <lb/>to each other. The measured TOF resolution of ∼300 ps allows particle identification <lb/>below 1 GV, and the rejection of albedo particles with a significance of ∼30 standard <lb/>deviations. Indeed, it is used to determine the absolute value of charge Z of incident <lb/>particles through the multiple measurement of energy loss dE/dx in the scintillator <lb/>counters. Moreover, it provides a fast signal for triggering data acquisition in the <lb/>whole instrument. <lb/>A further scintillator plane (S4) is placed below the calorimeter, and it is used <lb/>both to detect showers not contained in the calorimeter and to detect high energy <lb/>(&gt;100 GeV) out-of-acceptance electrons together with the calorimeter information. <lb/>The electron-hadron discrimination capabilities of the calorimeter are comple-<lb/>mented by a neutron detector (ND), which exploits the much larger neutron pro-<lb/>duction originated in the hadronic showers respect to the electromagnetic showers. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> The PAMELA space mission for antimatter and dark matter searches in space <lb/></note>

			<page>151 <lb/></page>

			<body> It is made up of of 36 proportional counters filled with <lb/> 3  He and surrounded by a <lb/>polyethylene moderator enveloped in a thin cadmium layer. <lb/>Finally, PAMELA is equipped with an anticounter system composed of three <lb/>sets of plastic scintillators: the CARD, which consists of four lateral detectors <lb/>surrounding the volume between S1 and S2; the CAT, formed by a single top detector <lb/>placed around S2; and the CAS, composed by four lateral detectors covering the sides <lb/>of the spectrometer. They delimit the apparatus geometric acceptance and are used <lb/>to identify false triggers, generated by secondary particles produced in the apparatus. <lb/> 3 Identification capabilities <lb/> The particle identification with the PAMELA experiment is based on a good track <lb/>determination provided by the tracking system, fundamental to achieve a reliable <lb/>charge sign separation and a precise estimate of the particle rigidity, in order to <lb/>separate antiparticles from the much more abundant flux of protons, electrons and <lb/>light nuclei. Strict conditions were applied on the number of position measurements <lb/>from the tracker and on the χ <lb/> 2  associated to the tracking fit procedure, in order <lb/>to reject events which were wrongly reconstructed due to scattering, minimizing <lb/>uncertainties on the rigidity measurement. <lb/>The analysis of the interaction topology in the calorimeter is crucial to allow <lb/>hadron/lepton discrimination. The used criteria are based on several features describ-<lb/>ing an electromagnetic shower development in the calorimeter which, combined with <lb/> dE/dx measurements from the individual silicon strips, allow electrons and positrons <lb/>to be identified with high precision and efficiency. The residual proton contamination <lb/>in the positron sample was estimated with statistical methods [3, 4]. <lb/>Strong constraints on the combined information from several detectors of <lb/>PAMELA were used in order to get a clean antiparticle sample from the recorded <lb/>data. Secondary particles produced by CR interacting in the Al vessel or at the <lb/>support structures in the upper parts of the apparatus were rejected by exploiting <lb/>the TOF and the tracking systems segmentation, and by requiring no activity in <lb/>the anticoincidence scintillators. In the case of antiprotons, the particle velocity <lb/>measurement provided by the TOF and the ionization loss in both the tracker and <lb/>the TOF planes were used to reject electrons, wrongly reconstructed protons and <lb/>locally produced particles (mostly π <lb/> −  ). The residual contamination was estimated <lb/>with simulations to be about 10% in the rigidity range 1÷3 GV and negligible <lb/>elsewhere [5, 6]. <lb/>Because of the finite spectrometer resolution (MDR ∼ 1 TV), high rigidity protons <lb/>may be assigned the wrong sign of curvature. Such &quot; spillover &quot; protons determine the <lb/>highest energy at which antiprotons can be unambiguously measured by PAMELA. <lb/>To reduce this background, strict requirements were applied on the quality of the <lb/>tracks reconstructed in the spectrometer. In particular, the MDR related to each <lb/>track, evaluated on an event-by-event basis by propagating the estimated coordinate <lb/>errors and taking into account the track topology, was required to be six times larger <lb/>than the measured rigidity. This allowed the antiproton measurement to be extended <lb/>up to 180 GV with a small contamination from spillover protons [6]. <lb/>The selected data samples were corrected by means of simulations to take into <lb/>account losses in the apparatus due to hadronic interactions, multiple scattering and <lb/></body>

			<page> 152 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> M. Boezio et al. <lb/></note>

			<body> kinetic energy [GeV] <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/>antiproton flux [GeV m 2 <lb/> s sr 2 <lb/> ] -1 <lb/> -6 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/> AMS (M. Aguilar et al.) <lb/>BESS-polar04 (K. Abe et al.) <lb/>BESS1995-97 (S. Orito et al.) <lb/>CAPRICE1998 (M. Boezio et al.) <lb/>CAPRICE1994 (M. Boezio et al.) <lb/>PAMELA <lb/>Donato et al. 2001 <lb/>Ptuskin et al. 2006 <lb/> kinetic energy [GeV] <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/>antiproton-to-proton flux ratio <lb/> -6 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> BESS 95-97 (S. Orito et al.) <lb/>BESS-polar 2004 (K. Abe et al.) <lb/>CAPRICE 1994 (M. Boezio et al.) <lb/>CAPRICE 1998 (M. Boezio et al.) <lb/>HEAT-pbar 2000 (Y. Asaoka et al.) <lb/>PAMELA <lb/>Donato et al. 2009 <lb/>Ptuskin et al. 2006 <lb/> Fig. 2 The ¯ <lb/> p spectrum (left) and the ¯ <lb/> p/ p flux ratio (right) measured by PAMELA [6], compared <lb/>with data from other contemporary experiments [8–13] and theoretical calculations for purely <lb/>secondary production of antiprotons in the Galaxy [14–16] <lb/> ionization. Selection efficiencies were determined using flight data, which naturally <lb/>include detectors performances, while test beam and simulation data were used to <lb/>support and cross-check the estimation [6, 7]. <lb/> 4 Results <lb/> 4.1 Antiprotons <lb/>The PAMELA collaboration has recently published its antiproton flux and its <lb/>updated antiproton-to-proton flux ratio measurements in the kinetic energy range <lb/>60 MeV ÷ 180 GeV [5, 6]. They significantly improve data by previous experiments, <lb/>thanks to the high statistical significance and the large explored interval, with the <lb/>extension of antiproton measurements to high energies (above 50 GeV). <lb/>The ¯ <lb/> p flux and the ¯ <lb/> p/ p ratio are shown respectively on the left and on the right <lb/>panel of Fig. 2, where they are compared with data from contemporary experiments <lb/>[8–13] and some theoretical calculations for a pure secondary production of antipro-<lb/>tons during the propagation of CR in the Galaxy [14–16]. PAMELA data reproduce <lb/>the expected peak around ∼2 GeV in the antiproton spectrum and appear to be <lb/>consistent with pure secondary calculations, excluding an appreciable contribution <lb/>from exotic processes in that energy range. <lb/>4.2 Positrons <lb/>The positron fraction e <lb/> + <lb/> /(e <lb/> + <lb/> + e <lb/> − <lb/> ) measured by PAMELA [3, 4] is shown in the <lb/>left panel of Fig. 3. PAMELA data cover a large kinetic interval (1.5÷100 GeV), <lb/>with a considerably improved statistical precision. Measurements from other recent <lb/>experiments [17–24] are also reported, together with a calculation for pure secondary <lb/>production of positrons during the propagation of CR in the Galaxy without re-<lb/>acceleration processes [25]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> The PAMELA space mission for antimatter and dark matter searches in space <lb/></note>

			<page>153 <lb/></page>

			<body> Energy [GeV] <lb/>Energy [GeV] <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> ) ) <lb/> -<lb/> (e <lb/> f <lb/> ) + <lb/> + <lb/> (e <lb/> f <lb/> ) / ( <lb/> + <lb/> (e <lb/> f <lb/> Positron fraction <lb/> 0.005 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/> PAMELA <lb/>Clem &amp; Evenson 2007 <lb/>HEAT00 <lb/>AMS <lb/>CAPRICE94 <lb/>HEAT94+95 <lb/>TS93 <lb/>MASS89 <lb/>Muller &amp; Tang 1987 <lb/> 1 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> GeV <lb/> -2 <lb/> m <lb/> -1 <lb/> sr <lb/> -1 <lb/> (s <lb/> 3 <lb/> E <lb/> ¥ <lb/> Flux <lb/> 1 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> PAMELA <lb/>CAPRICE94 <lb/>MASS91 <lb/>HEAT94+95 <lb/>AMS <lb/>ATIC <lb/>Kobayashi <lb/>BETS <lb/>Fermi <lb/>HESS <lb/> Fig. 3 Left panel: The PAMELA positron fraction (e  +  /(e  + + e  −  )) [4] compared with other <lb/>experimental data [17–24] and with predictions of a secondary production model (solid line) [25]. <lb/> Right panel: The PAMELA electron (e  −  ) spectrum [7] compared with recent electron, and electron <lb/>plus positron (e  − + e  +  ) data [21, 26–34] <lb/> The discrepancy between PAMELA and previous experimental data at low <lb/>energy (&lt;5 GeV) can be interpreted as a consequence of charge dependent solar <lb/>modulation effects, affecting positrons and electrons differently. The same suppres-<lb/>sion in the positron fraction, but with large statistical uncertainties, has been also <lb/>observed by a contemporary balloon-borne experiment by Clem et al. [24]. <lb/>Above ∼5 GeV the measured positron fraction significantly deviates from predic-<lb/>tions from secondary production models, increasing with energy. Other experimental <lb/>data in this range [19, 20, 22], while affected by uncertainties too large to draw any <lb/>meaningful conclusions, are consistent with the excess which is clearly shown by <lb/>PAMELA. As discussed below, the secondary production of these positrons seems <lb/>unlikely, even if theoretical uncertainties are still large. <lb/>The electron (e <lb/> −  ) spectrum measured by PAMELA in the kinetic energy interval <lb/>1 ÷ 625 GeV [7] is shown in the right panel of Fig. 3, together with other recent <lb/>experimental measurements of the electron, and the electron plus positron (e <lb/> − <lb/> + e <lb/> +  ) <lb/>flux [21, 26–34]. PAMELA data do not show any significant spectral features and <lb/>can be interpreted in terms of conventional diffusive propagation models. However, <lb/>they are also consistent with models including new CR sources that could explain the <lb/>positron excess. <lb/>4.3 Anti-helium <lb/>PAMELA is also placing constraints on the existence of cosmologically significant <lb/>amounts of antimatter, by searching for anti-Helium nuclei in the cosmic radiation. <lb/>Their measurement is commonly expressed in terms of the ratio ¯ <lb/> He/He. Up to now <lb/>no CR antinucleus has been detected, and only upper limits on the flux ratio have <lb/>been measured in various rigidity ranges, by different experiments. PAMELA is <lb/>able to investigate the ¯ <lb/> He/He ratio in the largest rigidity interval ever achieved, <lb/>extending the measurement up to several hundreds of GV. This is particular relevant, <lb/>since the predicted ¯ <lb/> He flux is expected to be strongly suppressed below a few GV, <lb/>where most of the measurements were taken. Preliminary results in the rigidity range <lb/></body>

			<page> 154 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">M. Boezio et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>  kinetic energy [GeV] <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>kinetic energy [GeV] <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> s sr] <lb/> 2 <lb/> antiproton flux [GeV m <lb/> -4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> SAA <lb/>GCR <lb/>sub-cutoff <lb/>Selesnick et al. 2007 <lb/> antiproton-to-proton ratio <lb/> -7 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -6 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> SAA <lb/>GCR <lb/>Selesnick et al. 2007 <lb/> Fig. 4 The geomagnetically trapped ¯ <lb/> p spectrum (left) and ¯ <lb/> p/ p flux ratio (right) measured by <lb/>PAMELA in the SAA region (red circles) [37], together with a trapped antiproton calculation <lb/>for the PAMELA satellite orbit (solid line) [36]. For comparison, the mean atmospheric under-<lb/>cutoff antiproton spectrum outside radiation belts (blue triangles), and results about galactic CR <lb/>antiprotons (black squares) measured by PAMELA [6] are also shown <lb/> 0.6 ÷ 600 GV have been provided, allowing an upper limit of 10 <lb/> −7 <lb/> ÷ 10 <lb/> −6  to be put <lb/>on the ¯ <lb/> He/He ratio. <lb/>4.4 Geomagnetically trapped antiprotons <lb/>The satellite orbit (70 <lb/> •  inclination and 350÷610 km altitude) allows a very detailed <lb/>measurement of the cosmic radiation in different regions of the terrestrial magne-<lb/>tosphere to be performed by PAMELA, including information about the nature <lb/>and energy spectra of under-cutoff <lb/> 1 particles [35]. In particular, the spacecraft orbit <lb/>passes through the South Atlantic Anomaly (SAA), allowing the observation of <lb/>geomagnetically trapped particles from the inner radiation belt. <lb/>Antiprotons are created in reactions of energetic CR with the Earth&apos;s atmosphere. <lb/>Part of these particles are captured by the geomagnetic field allowing the forma-<lb/>tion of an antiproton radiation belt around the Earth. In particular, a dominant <lb/>contribution from decay of albedo antineutrons has been hypothesized [36]. The <lb/>geomagnetically trapped antiproton population has been observed for the first time <lb/>by the PAMELA experiment [37]. The data show the existence of a significant <lb/>antiproton flux in the SAA below ∼1 GeV in kinetic energy: at the current solar <lb/>minimum, the trapped flux exceeds the galactic CR antiproton flux and the mean <lb/>atmospheric (under-cutoff) antiproton spectrum outside radiation belts by three <lb/>and four orders of magnitude respectively, thereby constituting the most abundant <lb/>antiproton source near the Earth. Results are reported in Fig. 4. PAMELA data <lb/>allow CR transport models to be tested in the terrestrial atmosphere and significantly <lb/>constrain predictions from trapped antiproton models. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 1 The cutoff rigidity is the lowest rigidity for which a particle arriving from the space can access a <lb/>given location within the geomagnetic field. Under-cutoff particles do not have an extraterrestrial <lb/>origin but rather are the product of CR interactions with Earth&apos;s atmosphere. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The PAMELA space mission for antimatter and dark matter searches in space <lb/></note>

			<page>155 <lb/></page>

			<body> 5 Theoretical interpretations of PAMELA ¯ <lb/> p and e <lb/> +  data <lb/> The unexpected rising positron fraction measured by the PAMELA experiment has <lb/>triggered a considerable amount of possible interpretations based on the existence of <lb/>some standard or exotic primary sources. These models are significantly constrained <lb/>by antiproton data which, contrarily, appear to be in agreement with predictions <lb/>of a purely secondary production. Further limits are provided by the measurement <lb/>of diffuse gamma rays. In addition, calculations of the positron fraction suffer from <lb/>large theoretical uncertainties, which have to be taken into account to estimate the <lb/>significance of proposed mechanisms. <lb/>5.1 Theoretical uncertainties on &quot; standard &quot; positron fraction <lb/>Secondary positrons are created by spallation reactions of CR nuclei on interstellar <lb/>gas and propagate in a diffusive mode under the influence of the turbulent com-<lb/>ponent of the galactic magnetic field. Consequently, estimates are strongly affected <lb/>by uncertainties about cosmic nuclei spectra, nuclear cross sections involved in <lb/>the positron production mechanism and propagation parameters involved in the <lb/>diffusion equation. Indeed, the secondary positron production depends on the spatial <lb/>distribution of CR nuclei and of the ISM, and fluctuations of the local injection rate <lb/>can influence some features in the measured spectrum. Moreover, a crucial ingredi-<lb/>ent for the calculation is given by the electron flux [38], with further complications <lb/>arising from the lack of knowledge about different spectral contributions, including <lb/>primary electrons from astrophysical sources, and about solar modulation effects. <lb/>5.2 Astrophysical sources <lb/>Regardless of theoretical uncertainties, the presence of an excess appears manifest <lb/>and consistent. As already proposed several years ago [39], a possible enhancement <lb/>of the e <lb/> ±  flux could be explained by astrophysical sources like nearby pulsars <lb/>[40, 41] (see left panel of Fig. 5). In this scenario, electrons are believed to be <lb/>initially extracted from the surface of the star by the intense rotation induced <lb/>electric fields and later to produce e <lb/> ±  pairs via electromagnetic showers inside the <lb/>magnetosphere; in addition, e <lb/> ±  are possibly re-accelerated by the pulsar winds or <lb/>in the supernova remnant shocks and released in the ISM [39, 42, 43]. Hence, no <lb/>sizeable contribution from antiprotons is predicted, while counterparts in γ -rays are <lb/>expected. In particular, magnetars are thought to generate a large amount of e <lb/> ±  pairs, <lb/>giving an important contribution despite their relatively low abundance [44]. Other <lb/>possible sources are given by nearby gamma-ray burst (GRB), GRB-like pulsars and <lb/>microquasar [45]. <lb/>Alternatively, positrons can be created as secondary products of hadronic inter-<lb/>actions inside supernova remnants (SNRs). The secondary production takes place <lb/>in the same region where CR are being accelerated: secondary e <lb/> ±  participate in the <lb/>acceleration process and result in a very flat spectrum at high energy, thus providing a <lb/>natural explanation for the observed positron excess, after propagation in the Galaxy <lb/>has been taken into account. In particular, old SNRs appear the best candidates [46] <lb/>(see right panel of Fig. 5). On the other hand, counterparts in γ -rays and possibly <lb/>in the antiproton channel as well are expected [47]. The predicted antiproton flux, <lb/></body>

			<page> 156 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> M. Boezio et al. <lb/></note>

			<body> Fig. 5 On the left: Experimental data on positron fraction [3, 20–22] compared with predicted <lb/>contribution from all nearby pulsars in the ATNF catalogue [40]. On the right: PAMELA data [3] <lb/>compared with predictions for a secondary production at astrophysical sources (SNRs) [46] <lb/> Fig. 6 On the left: The ¯ <lb/> p/ p ratio by PAMELA compared with theoretical calculations. The dotted <lb/>lines show the upper and lower limits calculated for a pure secondary production of antiprotons [16]. <lb/>The dashed line is a calculation including both a primary ¯ <lb/> p component from annihilation of 180 GeV <lb/>wino-like neutralinos and secondary antiprotons (dashed-dotted line) [53]. The solid line shows the <lb/>calculation for secondary antiprotons including an additional component produced and accelerated <lb/>at CR sources [47]. On the right: The positron fraction by PAMELA compared with predictions, <lb/>including a primary component from annihilation of 180 GeV wino-like neutralinos [53] <lb/> compatible with present data, should result in a harder component emerging at <lb/>high energies (&gt;100 GeV, see solid line in the left panel of Fig. 6). Moreover, <lb/>according to this scenario, an increase with energy of the Boron/Carbon ratio is also <lb/>expected [48]. <lb/>5.3 Dark matter annihilation or decay <lb/>The DM possibility, with annihilations in the halo of the Milky Way providing the <lb/>anomalous antiparticle flux, is of great interest from the particle physics viewpoint. <lb/>Minimal DM models can give a reasonably good fit to the PAMELA positron <lb/>data, while antiprotons data put strong constraints on DM annihilations, disfavoring <lb/>channels with gauge bosons, Higgs bosons or quarks. Nevertheless, the required hard <lb/>spectrum would result by combining a very high DM particle mass (∼10 TeV) and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> The PAMELA space mission for antimatter and dark matter searches in space <lb/></note>

			<page>157 <lb/></page>

			<body> a very efficient enhancement mechanism for the annihilation into charged gauge <lb/>bosons [49]. In particular, annihilating DM particles with ∼1 TeV mass or heavier <lb/>have been proposed in order to accommodate the observations of Fermi [29] and <lb/>provide the PAMELA positron excess. Super-heavy DM candidates would also <lb/>result in correct thermal relic abundance [50]. <lb/>Alternatively, DM models assuming a dominant leptonic channel can fit <lb/>PAMELA positron and antiproton measurements as well [40, 49]. In pure e <lb/> ±  models <lb/>the DM annihilation yields a pair of monochromatic e <lb/> ±  , with injection energies equal <lb/>to the mass of the annihilating DM particle. &quot; Lepto-philic &quot; models assume an equal <lb/>pair-annihilation branching ratio into each charged lepton species. Indeed, multistate <lb/>DM models with small mass splittings and couplings to light hidden sector bosons <lb/>have been proposed as an explanation for the high energy lepton excesses [51, 52]. <lb/>Provided some modifications concerning underlying distribution of the DM or the <lb/>propagation of its annihilation products, and given the inherent astrophysical un-<lb/>certainties, a wino-like neutralino of mass about 200 GeV, non-thermally produced, <lb/>normalized to the local relic density, and annihilating mainly into W-bosons, appears <lb/>to be a plausible candidate [53], consistent with existing positron, antiproton and γ -<lb/>ray data (see Fig. 6). Neutralinos with much larger mass do not fit to the PAMELA <lb/>results unless very large astrophysical boost factors are employed [54]. <lb/>Another possibility is offered by Kaluza-Klein models with one universal extra <lb/>dimension [55]. The DM particles annihilate largely to charged leptons, which <lb/>enables them to produce a spectrum of CR electrons and positrons consistent with <lb/>the PAMELA and ATIC [30] measurements, regardless of large boost factors and <lb/>significant annihilation to hadronic modes. Corresponding masses are limited to <lb/>approximately 600 ÷ 900 GeV by relic abundance arguments. <lb/>Radiative corrections may considerably enhance the DM induced positron yield <lb/>and result in a pronounced spectral signature, a rising positron to electron ratio and a <lb/>sharp cutoff in the positron spectrum at the neutralino mass. Again, very large boost <lb/>factors have to be invoked to obtain such a spectral feature [56]. <lb/> 6 Conclusions <lb/> The recently released PAMELA antiparticle data have significant implications in the <lb/>fields of astrophysics, particle physics and cosmology, putting strong constraints for <lb/>theoretical models of CR production and propagation and for the existence of exotic <lb/>processes. In contrast with antiproton measurements, the observed unambiguous <lb/>positron excess appears inconsistent with the predictions of the standard model for <lb/>the origin and propagation of CR in the Galaxy, regardless of theoretical uncertain-<lb/>ties affecting calculations. In the attempt to account for such excess, several scenarios <lb/>have been put forward, with the most exciting possibility involving DM particles <lb/>annihilation or decay. Alternatively, the pulsars/SNRs hypothesis encompases the <lb/>positron fraction data with conservative assumptions. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. Picozza, P., et al.: Astropart. Phys. 27, 296 (2007) <lb/>2. Geer, S.H., Kennedy, D.C.: LANL astro-ph/9809101; Astrophys. J. 532, 648 (2000) <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 158 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> M. Boezio et al. <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> 3. Adriani, O., et al.: Nature 458, 607–609 (2009) <lb/>4. Adriani, O., et al.: Astropart. Phys. 34, 1–11 (2010) <lb/>5. Adriani, O., et al.: Phys. Rev. Lett. 102, 051101 (2009) <lb/>6. Adriani, O., et al.: Phys. Rev. Lett. 105, 121101 (2010) <lb/>7. Adriani, O., et al.: Phys. Rev. Lett. 106, 201101 (2011) <lb/>8. Boezio, M., et al.: Astrophys. J. 487, 415 (1997) <lb/>9. Boezio, M., et al.: Astrophys. J. 561, 787 (2001) <lb/>10. Aguilar, M., et al.: Phys. Rep. 366, 331 (2002) <lb/>11. Orito, S., et al.: Phys. Rev. Lett. 84, 1078 (2000) <lb/>12. Abe, K., et al.: Phys. Lett. B 670, 103 (2008) <lb/>13. Beach, A.S., et al.: Phys. Rev. Lett. 87, 271101 (2001) <lb/>14. Donato, F., et al.: Astrophys. J. 563, 172 (2001) <lb/>15. Ptuskin, V.S., et al.: Astrophys. J. 642, 902 (2006) <lb/>16. Donato, F., et al.: Phys. Rev. Lett. 102, 071301 (2009) <lb/>17. Müller, D., Tang, K.K.: Astrophys. J. 312, 183–194 (1987) <lb/>18. Golden, R.L., et al.: Astrophys. J. 436, 769–775 (1994) <lb/>19. Golden, R.L., et al.: Astrophys. J. 457, L103–L106 (1996) <lb/>20. Barwick, S.W., et al.: Astrophys. J. 482, L191–194 (1997) <lb/>21. Boezio, M., et al.: Astrophys. J. 532, 653–669 (2000) <lb/>22. Aguilar, M., et al.: Phys. Lett. B 646, 145 (2007) <lb/>23. Beatty, J.J., et al.: Phys. Rev. Lett. 93, 241102–241105 (2004) <lb/>24. Clem, J., Evenson, P.: In: Caballero, R., et al. (eds.) Proc. 30th Intl Cosmic Ray Conf., vol. 1, <lb/>pp. 477–480. Universidad Nacional Autonoma de Mexico (2008) <lb/>25. Moskalenko, I.V., Strong, A.W.: Astrophys. J. 493, 694–707 (1998) <lb/>26. Kobayashi, T., et al.: In: Proc. 26th Int. Cosmic Ray Conf. (Salt Lake City), vol. 3, p. 61 (1999) <lb/>27. Torii, S., et al.: Astrophys. J. 559, 973 (2001) <lb/>28. Aharonian, F., et al.: Phys. Rev. Lett. 101, 261104 (2008) <lb/>29. Abdo, A.A., et al. (The Fermi LAT): arXiv:0905.0025 (2009) <lb/>30. Chang, J., et al.: Nature 456, 362 (2008) <lb/>31. Alcaraz, J., et al.: Phys. Lett. B 484, 10–22 (2000) <lb/>32. Barwick, S.W., et al.: Astrophys. J. 498, 779 (1998) <lb/>33. DuVernois, M.A., et al.: Astrophys. J. 559, 296 (2001) <lb/>34. Grimani, C., et al.: Astron. Astrophys. 392, 287–294 (2002) <lb/>35. Adriani, O., et al.: J. Geophys. Res. 114, A12218 (2009) <lb/>36. Selesnick, R.S., et al.: Geophys. Res. Lett. 34, 20 (2007) <lb/>37. Adriani, O., et al.: Astrophys. J. 737, L29 (2011) <lb/>38. Delahaye, T., et al.: Astron. Astrophys. 501, 821–833 (2009). arXiv:0809.5268v6 <lb/>39. Boulares, A., et al.: Astrophys. J. 342, 807–813 (1989); Atoyan, A.M., et al.: Phys. Rev. D 52(6), <lb/> 3265–3275 (1995) <lb/>40. Grasso, D., et al.: Astropart. Phys. 32, 140–151 (2009) <lb/>41. Hooper, D., Blasi, P., Serpico, P.: JCAP 1, 25 (2009) <lb/>42. Profumo, S.: arXiv:0812.4457 (2008) <lb/>43. Malyshev, D., Cholis, I., Gelfand, J.: Phys. Rev. D 80, 063005 (2009) <lb/>44. Heyl, J.S., Gill, R., Hernquist, L.: arXiv:1005.1003 (2010) <lb/>45. Ioka, K.: Prog. Theor. Phys. 123, 743–755 (2010). arXiv:0812.4851v4 <lb/>46. Blasi, P.: Phys. Rev. Lett. 103, 051104 (2009). arXiv:0903.2794 <lb/>47. Blasi, P., Serpico, P.D.: Phys. Rev. Lett. 103, 081103 (2009) <lb/>48. Mertsch, P., Sarkar, S.: Phys. Rev. Lett. 103, 081104 (2009) <lb/>49. Cirelli, M., et al.: Nucl. Phys. B 800, 204 (2008); Cirelli, M., et al.: Nucl. Phys. B 813, 1 (2009) <lb/>50. Profumo, S.: Phys. Rev. D 72, 103521 (2005) <lb/>51. Cholis, I., et al.: Phys. Rev. D 80, 123518 (2009) <lb/>52. Cirelli, M., Cline, J.M.: arXiv:1005.1779v2 (2010) <lb/>53. Kane, G., Lu, R., Watson, S.: Phys. Lett. B 681, 151 (2009) <lb/>54. Hooper, D., Stebbins, A., Zurek, K.M.: Phys. Rev. D 79, 103513 (2009). arXiv:0812.3202 <lb/>55. Hooper, D., Zurek, K.M.: Phys. Rev. D 79, 103529 (2009). arXiv:0902.0593 <lb/>56. Bergstrom, L., Bringmann, T., Edsjo, J.: Phys. Rev. D 78, 103520 (2008) </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
