<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage> PUBLICATIONS  MATHÉMATIQUES DE L&apos;I.H.É.S. <lb/> GRAEME SEGAL <lb/>GEORGE WILSON <lb/> Loop groups and equations of KdV type <lb/> Publications mathématiques de l&apos;I.H.É.S., tome 61 (1985), p. 5-65. <lb/> &lt;http://www.numdam.org/item?id=PMIHES_1985__61__5_0&gt; <lb/>© Publications mathématiques de l&apos;I.H.É.S., 1985, tous droits réservés. <lb/>L&apos;accès aux archives de la revue « Publications mathématiques de l&apos;I.H.É.S. » (http://www. <lb/> ihes.fr/IHES/Publications/Publications.html),  implique l&apos;accord avec les conditions générales <lb/>d&apos;utilisation (http://www.numdam.org/legal.php). Toute utilisation commerciale ou impression <lb/>systématique est constitutive d&apos;une infraction pénale. Toute copie ou impression de ce fi-<lb/>chier doit contenir la présente mention de copyright. <lb/> Article numérisé dans le cadre du programme <lb/>Numérisation de documents anciens mathématiques <lb/> http://www.numdam.org/ <lb/></titlePage>

			<front> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/> by GRAEME SEGAL and GEORGE WILSON <lb/></front>

			<body>The purpose of this paper is to work out some of the implications of recent ideas <lb/>of M. and Y. Sato about the Korteweg-de Vries (KdV) equation and related non-linear <lb/>partial differential equations. We learned of these ideas from the papers [5] of Date, <lb/>Jimbo, Kashiwara and Miwa (the original work ofM. and Y. Sato appears to be available <lb/>only in Japanese). We shall describe a construction which assigns a solution of the <lb/>KdV equation to each point of a certain infinite dimensional Grassmannian. The class <lb/>of solutions obtained in this way, which is misleadingly referred to as <lb/> &lt;( the general <lb/>solution &quot; in [5], includes the explicit algebro-geometric solutions ofKrichever [10, n]; <lb/>among these are the well known <lb/> c&lt; n-soliton &quot; and rational solutions. <lb/> Our main aims are to determine what class of solutions is obtained by the method, <lb/>to illustrate in detail how the geometry of the Grassmannian is reflected in properties <lb/>of the solutions, and to show how the algebro-geometric solutions fit into the picture. <lb/>We have also tried to explain the geometric meaning of the &quot; r-function &quot;, which plays <lb/>a fundamental role in the papers [5]. But above all we have endeavoured to present <lb/>a clear and self-contained account of the theory, and hope to have elucidated a number <lb/>of points left obscure in the literature. <lb/> i. Introduction <lb/> The KdV equation <lb/> 8u __ fflu <lb/>9u <lb/> a^a^ <lb/> 34 &quot; <lb/> U 8x <lb/> describes the time-evolution of a function u of the variable x: we think of the equation <lb/>geometrically as defining a flow on a suitable space of functions u. It is well known <lb/>that the theory of the equation is closely connected with that of the linear differential <lb/>operator L^ == D <lb/> 2 + u, where D = 819x, which is to be regarded as an operator on <lb/>functions of x which varies with time. In fact the KdV equation can be written in <lb/>the <lb/> c&lt; Lax form &quot; <lb/>^=4[P^LJ, <lb/>where P^ is the operator D <lb/> 3  + <lb/> 3 (^D + Du). <lb/> 4 <lb/></body>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEME SEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> The operator P^ is almost characterized by the fact that—for any function u—the <lb/> commutator [P^, LJ is a multiplication operator. More precisely, for given L^ there <lb/>is a canonical sequence of operators <lb/> P^=D <lb/> fe +A2D <lb/> fc -<lb/> 2 + ... +^ <lb/> such that each [P^, LJ is a multiplication operator, and any operator P with the same <lb/>property is a constant linear combination of the P^. It turns out that the coefficients <lb/>of such an operator P must be differential polynomials in u, i.e. polynomials in u and <lb/>its ^-derivatives ^u\W. For each k the equation <lb/> (x.r) <lb/>^[P^LJ <lb/> defines a flow on the space of functions of A;. These flows are called the &quot; KdV hierarchy <lb/> 5? . <lb/>The case k = 3 is the original KdV equation (apart from the factor 4). When k = i <lb/>we have P^ == D, and the corresponding flow is just uniform translation of u. When <lb/> k is even we have P^ = (LJ^ <lb/> 2 <lb/> , so that the corresponding flow is stationary. It is <lb/>a fundamental theorem of the subject that the flows given by (i. i) for various k commute <lb/> among themselves. <lb/>In this paper we shall describe the KdV flows on a certain class ^ of functions u. <lb/> Our approach is in terms of the geometry of an infinite dimensional manifold which is <lb/>of considerable interest in its own right. It has two alternative descriptions. The <lb/>first is as the space QUg of loops in the unitary group Ug. The second, more immedia-<lb/>tely relevant, description is as the Grassmannian Gr^ of all closed subspaces W of the <lb/>Hilbert space H = L^S <lb/> 1 <lb/> ) of square-summable complex-valued functions on the <lb/>circle S <lb/> 1 ^^,^^!^]^!} which satisfy the two conditions <lb/>(i) ^WCW, and <lb/>(ii) W is comparable with H^.. <lb/>Here z denotes the operator H —^H given by multiplication by the function z <lb/> on S <lb/> 1 <lb/> , and H^_ is the closed subspace ofH spanned by {z <lb/> k <lb/> } for k ^ o, i.e. the boundary <lb/>values ofholomorphic functions in [ z \ &lt; i. The meaning of&quot; comparable &quot; is explained <lb/>in § 2. <lb/> Our basic construction associates to each point W in a connected component <lb/>ofGr^ a meromorphic function u^ on the line, belonging to the class ^ <lb/> (2) <lb/> . The group I\ <lb/>of holomorphic maps DQ -&gt; C <lb/> x <lb/> , where Dp is the disc {z e C : z &lt; i }, acts by multi-<lb/>plication operators on H, and hence acts on Gr^. The action of I\ induces the KdV <lb/>flows on ^^ in the following sense: if <lb/> g== exp2;^el\, <lb/>where (^, ^, ...) are real numbers almost all zero, then Ug^ is the function obtained <lb/>from u^ by letting it flow for time ^ along the k-th KdV flow, for each A. (This makes <lb/>sense precisely because the KdV flows commute.) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body> The meromorphic function u^ is obtained from the so-called &quot; T-function &quot; T^ <lb/>of W by the formula <lb/> / d\ <lb/> 2 <lb/> U^{X) = 2 ( , <lb/> logTwW; <lb/> \UX/ <lb/> T^(^) is the determinant of the orthogonal projection ^&quot;^W -&gt;H_^. Of course the <lb/>determinant needs to be suitably interpreted. To define it one must choose bases in W <lb/>and H^., and accordingly T^(A:) is defined only up to a multiplier independent of x. <lb/> The determinant T^(A?) vanishes, and hence u^{x) has a pole, precisely when e~ <lb/> x^ <lb/> &apos;W <lb/> intersects H^:. <lb/>For certain particular subspaces W belonging to the Grassmannian it turns out <lb/>that the r-function is a Schur function. This was discovered by Sato, and it was, we <lb/>have been told, the observation that led him to develop his theory. In general a point <lb/>of the Grassmannian can be described by its Pliicker coordinates, and (as we shall prove <lb/>in § 8) the corresponding r-function is an infinite linear combination of Schur functions <lb/>with the Pliicker coordinates as coefficients. <lb/>It is not practical, however, in developing the theory, to pass directly from the <lb/>T-function to the function u^. Instead, one introduces an intermediate object, the <lb/> Baker function ^. This is an eigenfunction of the operator D <lb/> 2 + u^\ <lb/> (D <lb/> 2 + ^y) ^(^ 0 = ^ +w(^ 0; <lb/>on the other hand for each fixed x it is the unique element of W which is of the form <lb/> (1.2) <lb/> ^(i + ^iW z-<lb/> 1  + ^) z-<lb/> 2  +...). <lb/> Finding the formula ((5.14) below) for the Baker function in terms of the r-function <lb/>was one of the most important contributions of the Japanese school. The formula is a <lb/>precise analogue of a formula known earlier, in the case of solutions arising from an <lb/>algebraic curve, expressing the Baker function in terms of 6-functions. <lb/>At this point we should say something about the class ^ <lb/> (2) of solutions u^ which <lb/>we obtain. Suppose to begin with that u is a G°° function defined in an interval of R. <lb/>Then the eigenvalue problem 1^4&apos; == ^ ^ has ^.formal solution of the form (1.2). <lb/>The coefficients ^ in the formal series are G°° functions determined recursively by <lb/>— 2a, = L^_i, <lb/>with OQ == i. Each successive ^ involves a new constant of integration: this means <lb/>that ^ is determined up to multiplication by an arbitrary power series in z~ <lb/> 1  with <lb/>constant coefficients. The series (1.2) will usually not converge for any values of z. <lb/> The class of functions ^ <lb/> (2) is, roughly speaking, those such that it can be chosen conver-<lb/>gent in a neighbourhood of z == oo. To see how restrictive this is, consider the case <lb/>of functions u which are rapidly decreasing as x -&gt; ± oo. Then there are unique genuine <lb/></body>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEME SEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> solutions ^^.{x, z) and ^_{x, z) of Lyip == ^ &lt;}/, defined and holomorphic in z for <lb/> ~R.e{z) &gt; o and Re{z) &lt; o respectively, characterized by the properties <lb/> ^+(^5 z) ^ e^ as x -&gt; — oo, <lb/>^-(^, ^) ^ ^ as A: -^ + oo. <lb/> These solutions both extend to the axis Re{z) == o, but unless u belongs to the excep-<lb/>tional class of so-called &quot; reflectionless potentials &quot; or <lb/> &lt;( multisolitons &quot; they will be <lb/>linearly independent functions of x, and then no genuine solution of the form (1.2) <lb/>can exist. The situation is similar if we consider the case where u is a real C <lb/> 00  periodic <lb/>function: of these, our class ^ <lb/> 7(2) contains only the <lb/> &lt;( finite gap &quot; potentials u. The <lb/>periodic KdV flows have been described by McKean and Trubowitz [25] in terms <lb/>of Riemann surfaces of (in general) infinite genus: the finite gap potentials are precisely <lb/>those for which the Riemann surface involved is of finite genus. The corresponding <lb/>solutions to the KdV hierarchy are then included in the class obtained by Krichever&apos;s <lb/>method. <lb/>We next explain how Krichever&apos;s construction is included in ours. Krichever <lb/>associates a function ofx, say u^^^ to an algebraic curve X with a distinguished point x^ <lb/> and a line bundle -S? (and also some additional data which we shall overlook in this <lb/>introduction). A solution of the KdV equation is obtained by letting -S^ move along a <lb/>straight line in the Jacobian of X. We shall see that a space W e Gr^ is naturally <lb/>associated to Krichever&apos;s data. Think of the circle S <lb/> 1 as a small circle around the <lb/>point x^ of X; then W consists of those functions on S <lb/> 1 which are boundary values of <lb/>holomorphic sections of J §f outside S <lb/> 1 —we suppose that JS^ has been trivialized near x^. <lb/> Krichever&apos;s solution u^ ^ is simply u^. When the curve X is non-singular, we shall <lb/>show in § 9 that the r-function r^y is essentially the 6-function of X. <lb/>The algebro-geometric solutions u are precisely those such that the operator 1^ <lb/>commutes with an operator of odd order. There is a very elegant theory, due essentially <lb/>to Burchnall and Ghaundy [4], relating commutative rings of differential operators <lb/>to algebraic curves. A modern treatment of the subject has been given by Mumford [16]; <lb/>but as it fits very naturally into our framework we have included a short self-contained <lb/>account in § 6. <lb/>We shall describe in particular detail the KdV flows on the two dense subspaces Gr^\ <lb/> and Gr^ of the Grassmannian corresponding respectively to polynomial and rational <lb/>loops in Ug. The first space corresponds exactly to the rational solutions of the KdV <lb/>equations which are zero at oo. It is a beautiful fact that the orbits of the group I\ <lb/>of KdV flows on Gr^ form a cell decomposition of Gr^, with one cell of each complex <lb/>dimension. (The Tz-th cell is the orbit of the function -- n{n + i)/A: <lb/> 2 .) <lb/>The points of Gr^ are those that arise by Krichever&apos;s construction from rational <lb/>curves with singularities. For any W e Gr^ the orbit ofW under I\ can be identified <lb/>with the Jacobian of the corresponding curve. <lb/>The KdV hierarchy has fairly obvious generalizations in which the operator <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body> D <lb/> 2 + u is replaced by an operator of order n: these hierarchies are related to the loop <lb/>space ofU^ in the same way that the KdV equations are related to QUg. For simplicity <lb/>of explanation we have restricted ourselves in the introduction to the case n = 2, but <lb/>in the body of the paper we shall always treat the general case, which presents no addi-<lb/>tional difficulty. In fact we shall treat a more general hierarchy still, that of the <lb/> &lt;( Kadomtsev-Petviashvili <lb/> 5? (KP) equations; the hierarchies already mentioned are <lb/>all specializations of this. Less obvious are the generalizations of the KdV hierarchy <lb/>due to DrinfePd and Sokolov [6], in which, roughly speaking, U^ is replaced by an <lb/>arbitrary compact Lie group; more precisely, DrinfePd and Sokolov asspciate several <lb/> &lt;( KdV &quot; hierarchies to each affine Kac-Moody algebra. Some of these hierarchies <lb/>are discussed in [5], though no general theory is developed there. The key step in [6] <lb/>which is missing from [5] is to view the KdV flows as quotients of certain simpler ones, <lb/>the &quot;modified KdV <lb/> 55 flows [12, 20]: the generalization of the latter is fairly evident. <lb/>We refer to [35] for a brief account of how the present theory generalizes to the equations <lb/>of DrinfePd and Sokolov: here we just mention that from this point of view our main <lb/>construction appears as a special case of a well known procedure (&quot; dressing&quot;) of <lb/>Zakharov and Shabat [23]. <lb/>We end with a technical remark. In this introduction we have been considering <lb/> u^ and TW as functions of the single variable x. In the body of the paper, however, <lb/>it will be more convenient to think of them as functions of an infinite sequence of variables <lb/> (x, f^y t^y ...), or alternatively as functions of the element <lb/> g=exp{xz+t^+t^+ ...) <lb/>of the group I\. To do this we define <lb/> U^{X, ^3, ...)== ^-iw(o), <lb/>T^(A:, t^ ^3, ...)== T^i^(o). <lb/> Then u = u^ will be a solution of the hierarchy (i. i) in the sense that <lb/> -<lb/> a -L — rp^ L 1 <lb/> a. -&quot;M —— V  s -U ? -&quot;MJ&quot; <lb/> ^k <lb/> Note added July 1984. — We draw the reader&apos;s attention to several related papers <lb/>and preprints [26-33] by Japanese authors, which we have seen since completing this <lb/>work. <lb/> Summary of contents <lb/>  § 2 describes the Grassmannian of Hilbert space and its relationship with loop <lb/>groups. <lb/> § 3 describes the determinant line bundle Det on the Grassmannian, and its <lb/>relationship with a central extension of the loop group. We introduce the r-function, <lb/>and calculate it explicitly for the subspaces which correspond to multisolitons. <lb/> io <lb/> GRAEME SEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/> § 4 is an outline of the basic formal theory of the generalized KdV equations. <lb/> § 5 describes the correspondence between points of the Grassmannian, Baker <lb/>functions, and differential operators, and works out the simplest examples. We also <lb/>give a characterization of the class of solutions ^ <lb/> (n) . <lb/> § 6 shows how Krichever&apos;s construction fits into the framework of § § 2-5. It <lb/>also contains a discussion of rings of commuting differential operators, and of the <lb/> &lt;( Pain-<lb/>lev^ property &quot; of the stationary solutions of the KdV equations. <lb/> § 7 is devoted to the subspaces Gr^ and Gr^ of the Grassmannian which were <lb/>mentioned above. <lb/> § 8 obtains the expansion of the general r-function as a sequence ofSchur functions. <lb/> § 9 proves that when W arises from an algebraic curve the r-function T^ can be <lb/>expressed explicitly in terms of the 6-function of the curve. <lb/> § io is an appendix explaining the connections between the theory developed in <lb/>the paper and the representation theory of loop groups. <lb/> 2. The Grassmannian and loop groups <lb/> In this section we shall describe the Grassmannian of Hilbert space and its relation <lb/>with loop groups. The material is all fairly well known, and we shall not prove all <lb/>our assertions. For a much more detailed discussion we refer the reader to [17]. <lb/> The Grassmannian <lb/> Let H be a separable complex Hilbert space with a given decomposition <lb/>H == H+ ® H_ as the direct sum of two infinite dimensional orthogonal closed subspaces. <lb/>We are interested in the Grassmannian of all subspaces of H which are comparable <lb/>with H^_ in the following sense. <lb/> Definition. — Gr(H) is the set of all closed subspaces W of H such that <lb/> (i) the orthogonal projection pr : W -&gt; H_^. is a Fredholm operator (i.e. has finite dimensional <lb/>kernel and cokernel), and <lb/> (ii) the orthogonal projection pr : W -&gt; H_ is a compact operator. <lb/> If W belongs to Gr(H), then so does the graph of any compact operator from <lb/>W to W-<lb/> 1 <lb/> &apos;. Thus W lies in a subset of Gr(H) which is in one to one correspondence <lb/>with the vector space jT(W; W <lb/> 1 <lb/> ) of compact operators W -»W <lb/> 1 <lb/> . This makes the <lb/>Grassmannian into a Banach manifold modelled on jf(H^;H_), which is given the <lb/>operator-norm topology. <lb/>If W e Gr(H), we shall call the index of the Fredholm operator pr : W -&gt; H^ <lb/>the virtual dimension of W (recall that the index of a Fredholm operator T is <lb/>dim(kerT)—dim(cokerT)). The Grassmannian is not connected: two subspaces <lb/>belong to the same component if and only if they have the same virtual dimension. <lb/>In the application to differential equations we shall be interested only in the component <lb/></body>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<body> n <lb/> consisting of subspaces of virtual dimension zero. These subspaces are precisely the <lb/>ones which are the images of embeddings H^. -&gt; H which differ from the standard <lb/>inclusion by a compact operator. <lb/>Because of the restrictions on the subspaces W belonging to Gr(H), not every <lb/>invertible operator on H induces a map of Gr(H). We define the restricted general linear <lb/>group GLrea(H) as follows. Let us write operators g e GL(H) in the block form <lb/> , <lb/>^ <lb/>l <lb/> a b\ <lb/>^ <lb/>^(c d) <lb/> with respect to the decomposition H==H+®H_.. Then GL,.gg(H) is the closed <lb/>subgroup ofGL(H) consisting of operators g whose off-diagonal blocks b and c are compact <lb/>operators. The blocks a and d are then automatically Fredholm. The group of con-<lb/>nected components of GL^g(H) is Z, the component being determined by the index <lb/>of the Fredholm operator a. <lb/>Lemma 9.2. — The group GL^g(H) acts on Gr(H). <lb/> Proof. — A subspace W belongs to Gr(H) precisely when it is the image of an <lb/>embedding w^. © w_ : H^. -&gt; H^ &lt;9 H_ with w^. Fredholm and w_ compact. Then <lb/>its transform by the element g in (2.1) above is the image of w^^w^^ where <lb/> w^ = aw^. + bw_ and w&apos;_ = cw^. + dw_. But w\ is Fredholm and w&apos;_ is compact. <lb/>We can read off from the formula for w\ that the virtual dimension of gW differs <lb/>from that of W by the index of a. <lb/>Remark. — The action of GL^s(H) on Gr(H) is easily seen to be transitive. <lb/>We now specialize to the case where H is the space of all square-integrable complex <lb/>valued functions on the unit circle S <lb/> 1 == {z e C : | z \ === i}. In this space we have <lb/>a natural orthonormal basis consisting of the functions {^}, k e Z. We define H^. <lb/>and H_ to be the closed subspaces spanned by the basis elements {z^} with k ^ o and <lb/> k &lt; o, respectively. Then H == H^. ® H_: we shall write simply Gr for the Grass-<lb/>mannian corresponding to this choice of (H,H+,H_). <lb/>Any continuous non-vanishing function f on S <lb/> 1 defines an invertible multiplication <lb/>operator, again written y, on H. This induces an action on Gr in view of the following <lb/>theorem. <lb/> Proposition 2.3. — Let F denote the group of continuous maps S <lb/> 1  -&gt;C <lb/> X <lb/> , regarded as <lb/>multiplication operators on H. Then rCGLreg(H). <lb/> If f: S <lb/> 1  -&gt;C^ is twice dijferentiable, then the off-diagonal blocks of the corresponding <lb/>operator are of trace class (i.e. nuclear). <lb/> Proof. — The first assertion follows from the second, as the usual topology on F <lb/>corresponds to the norm topology on the multiplication operators, and for this a limit <lb/>of operators of trace class is compact. <lb/></body>

			<page> 11 <lb/> 12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEME SEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> Now let f== 2/fc ^ be the Fourier expansion of/. The matrix of the correspon-<lb/>ding operator, with respect to the basis {^}^z <lb/> ofl1 , has (z&apos;J)-th entry /._^,. We must <lb/>show that the blocks [i&gt;_ o, j &lt; 0} and {i&lt; o,j^ 0} are of trace class. But a <lb/>matrix (o^.) is certainly of trace class if S | ay] &lt; oo. So what we need is that <lb/> S <lb/> l/i-,1 &lt; oo <lb/> and <lb/> S <lb/>|/,_, | &lt; oo, <lb/>»^o,j&lt;o <lb/> J <lb/> »&lt;o,j^o <lb/> J <lb/> that is, <lb/> SA|/J&lt;oo <lb/> and <lb/> SA|/_J&lt;oo. <lb/>fc&gt;o <lb/>&amp;&gt;o <lb/> These conditions are satisfied if/ is twice differentiable, because the Fourier series of <lb/>a G <lb/> 1  function is absolutely convergent. <lb/>In this paper we shall be interested mainly in the action of the subgroup F, of F <lb/>consisting of all real-analytic functions f:S <lb/> l -^C <lb/> X  which extend to holomorphic func-<lb/>tions f : Do -&gt;C <lb/> X  in the disc Do = {z e C :\z\&lt;_i} satisfying /(o) == i. (Here and <lb/>elsewhere, when we say that a function defined on a closed set in C is holomorphic, <lb/>we mean that it extends to a holomorphic function in a neighbourhood of the set.) We <lb/>shall also consider the subgroup F_ of F consisting of functions / which extend to non-<lb/>vanishing holomorphic functions in D^={zeCuoQ:\z\&gt;_i} satisfying /(oo) = i. <lb/>Concerning this subgroup we can assert <lb/> Proposition 2.4. — F_ acts freely on Gr. <lb/>We shall postpone the proof of this for a moment. <lb/> The stratification of Gr <lb/> We shall make much use of some special spaces Hg e Gr indexed by certain <lb/>subsets S of the integers: for any S C Z we define Hg to be the closed subspace of H <lb/>spanned by {^gg. The kernel and cokernel of the orthogonal projection Hg -&gt;H^ <lb/>are spanned by the functions {^} with i belonging to S \N and N\ S, respectively; <lb/>thus Hg e Gr precisely when both S \ N and N \ S are finite. We denote by y <lb/> the set of all subsets S C Z of this kind. If S e ^, we call the number <lb/>card(S\N) -card(N\S) <lb/>the virtual cardinal ofS: it is equal to the virtual dimension ofHg. A set of virtual car-<lb/>dinal d is simply an increasing sequence S = {sy, s^, jg, ... } of integers such that <lb/> Si == i — d for all sufficiently large i. Let us order the set y by defining <lb/>S &lt;. S&apos; o ^ ^ 4 for all k. <lb/> Lemma 2.5. — For every W e Gr, there exist sets S e y such that W is the graph of <lb/>a compact operator Hg -&gt;H^, or, equivalently^ such that the orthogonal projection W -&gt; Hg <lb/> is an isomorphism. Furthermore there is a unique minimal S with this property. <lb/></body>

			<page> 12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body> We shall omit the straightforward proof of this lemma: it can be found in [17]. <lb/>Let us only point out that the unique minimal S associated to W consists precisely of <lb/>those integers s such that W contains an element of order s, i.e. an element of the form <lb/>S a^ z <lb/> k  with a^ 4= o. <lb/> k^s <lb/> A very useful corollary of the lemma is <lb/> Proposition 2.6. — In any W e Gr, the elements of finite order form a dense sub space, <lb/>which we shall denote by W^. <lb/>This holds because a projection W -&gt; Hg which is an isomorphism induces an <lb/>isomorphism between W^ and H^; and the elements of finite order are obviously <lb/>dense in Hg. <lb/>Let us at this point return to give the proof of Proposition 2.4. Suppose that <lb/> W G Gr, and that g e r_ is such that gW = W. Now g is of the form i + S ^ ^ <lb/> fc . <lb/> fe&lt;0 <lb/> Let w eW be an element of minimal order SQ. Then gw — w is an element of W <lb/>of order less than SQ. So gw == w, and hence g == i. <lb/>The spaces W e Gr which are the graphs of operators Hg -&gt; H^ will be called <lb/> transverse to H^. They form an open set Ug ofGr; lemma 2.5 asserts that the Ug cover <lb/> Gr. The set of W such that S is the minimal indexing set with W e Ug form a closed <lb/>submanifold of Ug denoted by Sg. Notice that W belongs to 2g precisely when W^ <lb/>has a basis {wj^o (in the algebraic sense) with w^ of order ^. <lb/>The Sg constitute a stratification of Gr by manifolds of finite codimension. The <lb/>codimension of Sg is the length of S, defined as <lb/>^(S)=j^-^-^), <lb/>where d is the virtual cardinal of S. <lb/> Scaling <lb/> For each \ e S <lb/> 1 <lb/> , we can consider the operator R^ on H induced by rotating the <lb/>circle S <lb/> 1 <lb/> , that is, the operator defined by <lb/>RX/(O <lb/> = /^-<lb/> 1 ^ (/eH). <lb/>If ^ is a complex number with |X| 4= i, the operator R^ defined by this formula is <lb/>unbounded. Nevertheless, using (2.5), we can see that if |X| &lt;^ i, then the operator <lb/>R^ still induces a transformation of Gr. For then the domain of R^ includes the dense <lb/>subspace H^ of H consisting of functions of finite order, i.e. those whose Fourier series <lb/>involve only a finite number of positive powers of z. We can therefore define R^ W <lb/>to be the closure of the space R^W^. To see that R^W belongs to Gr, we use (2.5) : <lb/>ifW is transverse to H^-, then clearly R^ W is too, and is the graph of a compact operator. <lb/>We shall refer to the operators {R^ : \^\ &lt;_ i } as the semigroup of scaling transformations <lb/> of Gr. It should be noticed that R^ W depends continuously both on X and on W. <lb/></body>

			<page> 13 <lb/> 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEME SEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> The scaling operators R^ preserve the stratification ofGr by the 2g. In the sense <lb/>of Morse theory, 2g is the stable manifold of the point Hg for the scaling flow, i.e. the set <lb/>of all W such that R^ W -&gt; Hg as X -&gt; o. <lb/> Loop groups <lb/> We now come to the connection of the Grassmannian with loop groups. Although <lb/>this will not play a very prominent role in the paper, we regard it as fundamental. <lb/>Let H^ be the Hilbert space of all square integrable functions on S <lb/> 1 with values <lb/>in C^. We break up H^ as H^ © H^, using Fourier series just as in the case n = i. <lb/>The group LGL^(C) of all continuous maps y &apos; &apos; S <lb/> 1 -&gt;• GL^(C) acts on H^ in an obvious <lb/>way. Generalizing Proposition 2.3 we have <lb/> Proposition 2.7. — LGL^C) C GL^H^). <lb/>The proof is exactly the same as in the case n == i. <lb/>Thus LGL^(C) acts on Gr^). For each y e LGL^(C) we set W^y-H^-<lb/>Then ,8&apos; W.y C W^, where 2; denotes the operation of multiplication by the scalar-valued <lb/>function z on S <lb/> 1 <lb/> ; for multiplication by z commutes with the action of y on H^? and <lb/>2&apos;H^ C Hy. This leads us to introduce the <lb/> Definition. — Gr^ == {W e Gr^) : zW C W}. <lb/> Gr^ is a closed subspace of Gr, and LGL^(C) acts on it. One reason for its <lb/>importance is that it is essentially the loop space ^U^ of the unitary group U^, i.e. the <lb/>space of continuous maps Y <lb/> : S <lb/> 1 -&gt;U^ such that y( <lb/> 1 ) <lb/> == I -To be precise, y^Wy <lb/>maps Q-Vn injectively onto a dense subspace of Gr^; and indeed Gr^ can be identified, <lb/>if one wants, with a certain class of measurable loops in U^. <lb/>The construction by which one associates a loop to a subspace W in Gr^ is as <lb/>follows. One first observes that the quotient space W/^W is ^-dimensional. Let <lb/>Wi, . . ., w^ be elements of W which span W/^W. Think of them as functions on the <lb/>circle whose values are yz-component column vectors. Then (zx/i, Wg, . . ., w^) is a <lb/>function on the circle with values in GL^(C): call it y. It is obvious that y-H^ == W. <lb/>Unfortunately the matrix entries of y are a priori only L <lb/> 2 functions, and it may not be <lb/>possible to choose them continuous. If the elements w^, ..., w^ are chosen to be an <lb/>orthonormal basis for. the orthogonal complement of zW in W, then it is easy to see that <lb/>the loop Y takes its values in U^. Furthermore y is then unique up to multiplication on <lb/>the right by a constant unitary matrix. <lb/>We should notice that in the correspondence between loops and subspaces the <lb/>winding number of a loop y 1 <lb/> s minus the virtual dimension of Wy. (This can be seen <lb/>by deforming y continuously to a standard loop with the same winding number.) <lb/>We shall now identify the Hilbert space H^ with H = H^ by letting the stan-<lb/>dard basis {s, ^: i &lt;_ i &lt;^ n, k e Z} for H^ correspond lexicographically to the basis {^} <lb/></body>

			<page> 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body> for H. (Here { sj denotes the standard basis for C^.) Thus s, ^ corresponds to z^ <lb/> +i -<lb/> 1 . <lb/> More invariantly, given a vector valued function with components (/o, ...^..i), <lb/>we associate to it the scalar valued function/such that <lb/> 7(^) ==foW + rflW + . . . + ^-Vn-l^). <lb/> Conversely, given /eH, we have <lb/> /^)=^-V^) <lb/> where ^ runs through the n-th roots of z. The isomorphism H <lb/> (n) ^ H is an isometry. <lb/>It makes continuous functions correspond to continuous ones, and also preserves most <lb/>other reasonable classes of functions, for example: smooth, real analytic, rational, poly-<lb/>nomial. Multiplication by z on H^ corresponds to multiplication by ^ on H; and <lb/>H^ corresponds to H^.. From now on we shall always think of Gr^ as the subspace <lb/>of Gr given by <lb/> Gr^ = {W e Gr : ^W C W}. <lb/> Note that Gr^ is preserved by the action of the group F and also by the semigroup of <lb/>scaling transformations. <lb/> Proposition a. 8. — Let W e Gr^. Then for any complex number X with \\\&lt; i, <lb/> the space R^ W corresponds to a real analytic loop. <lb/> The proposition implies that for the purposes of this paper we could perfectly <lb/>well confine ourselves to the subspace of Gr^ consisting of those W that correspond <lb/>to analytic loops (see (5.10) below). However, most of our arguments apply naturally <lb/>to the larger space Gr^. <lb/> Proof of {2.8). — We have to see that there is a complementary subspace for ^(R^ W) <lb/>in R^ W consisting of analytic functions. Choose a complementary subspace A for ^ W <lb/>in W such that AC W^ (this is possible because, as we have seen, W^ is dense in W). <lb/>Then each feA has the form <lb/> M= S^ <lb/> 1 <lb/> — 00 <lb/> where the series converges for \z\&gt; i; hence the series for f(\~ <lb/> 1 z) converges for <lb/>| z | &gt; |^|, so that/(X~ <lb/> 1  z) is an analytic function on S <lb/> 1 <lb/> . Thus the space {f(\~ <lb/> 1 z) :f e A} <lb/>is a complement to ^(R^ W) in R^ W of the desired kind. <lb/> Rational and polynomial loops <lb/> In § 7 we shall consider two subspaces Gr^ and Gr^ ofGr^: they can be defined <lb/>as the subspaces corresponding to rational and Laurent polynomial loops, respectively. <lb/>They can also be characterized in another way, which will be more convenient for us. <lb/></body>

			<page> 15 <lb/> 16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEME SEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> Proposition 2.9. — The following conditions on a subspace W e Gr^ are equivalent. <lb/> (i) W = W^ for some rational loop y (that is, a loop such that each matrix entry in y is <lb/>a rational function of z with no poles on S <lb/> 1 }. <lb/> (ii) There exist polynomials p and q in z such that <lb/> ^H^CWCy-<lb/> l H+. <lb/>(iii) W is commensurable with H^_, i.e. W n H^. is of finite codimension in both W <lb/> and H^.. <lb/>We denote by Gr^ the subspace of Gr^ consisting of those W that satisfy the <lb/>conditions in (2.9). We define Gr^ to be the subspace ofGr consisting of those W e Gr <lb/>that satisfy condition (ii) in (2.9). Notice that we may assume that the roots of the <lb/>polynomials p and q all lie in the region {| z\ &lt; i}; for if \c\ &gt; i, then z — c is an <lb/>invertible operator on H_^. <lb/> Example 2.10. — For spaces W e Gr not belonging to any Gr^ the condition <lb/>of commensurability (2.9) (iii) does not imply condition (2.9) (ii). As an example, <lb/>consider the subspace W of codimension i in H_^. which is the kernel of the linear map <lb/>F : H+ -&gt; C defined by <lb/>F(/) = residue^(^V). <lb/>Obviously there is no polynomial p such that pH^. C W. <lb/> Proposition 2.11. — The following conditions on a subspace W e Gr^ are equivalent. <lb/> (i) z <lb/> q Vi^C&apos;WCz~ <lb/> q1 H.^ for some positive integer q. <lb/> (ii) W == W^ for some Laurent polynomial loop y (by this we mean that both y and y&quot;&quot; <lb/> 1 <lb/> have finite Laurent expansions). <lb/> We denote by Gro the subspace of Gr consisting of those W that satisfy the condi-<lb/>tion (2.11) (i), and we set <lb/> Gr^ = Gro n Gr^. <lb/> Then Gro is the union of all the Gr^. <lb/>We note that all the Grassmannians Gr^, Gr^, Gr^ and Gr^ are invariant under <lb/>the semigroup of scaling transformations, and also under the action of the group I\ <lb/>of holomorphic functions in the disc (defined after (2.3)). (Gro and Gr^ are preserved <lb/>by I\ because gH.^ = H^. for any g e I\.) <lb/> It is easy to see that Gro is dense in Gr. As Gro is the union of a sequence of com-<lb/>pact finite dimensional algebraic varieties (namely the Grassmannians of z~ <lb/> q <lb/> &apos;H.^|z <lb/> q <lb/> Vi^), <lb/> this implies that every holomorphic function on Gr is constant. <lb/>Although it will play only a minor role in this paper, we should mention that the <lb/>space Gro has a cell decomposition into even-dimensional cells indexed by the same <lb/></body>

			<page> 16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body> set y as the stratification. For S e y the cell Gg consists of all W e GTQ for which <lb/>W^ has a basis {Wg}^ g with w^ of the form <lb/> w^ == z <lb/> 8  + S a^, 2&apos;\ <lb/> t &gt; 8 <lb/> The cell Gg is homeomorphic to C^. It is a submanifold of Gr transversal to the <lb/>stratum Sg, which it meets in the single point Hg. On Gr^ the scaling operators R^ <lb/>make sense for all X e C <lb/> x <lb/> , and Cg is the &quot; unstable manifold &quot; of Hg for the scaling <lb/>flow, i.e. the set of W such that R^ W -&gt; Hg as X -&gt; oo. <lb/>Finally, let us observe that Hg belongs to Gr^ if and only if S + ^ C S. For such S <lb/>let us write C^ for Gg n Gr^. The G^ form a cell decomposition of Gr^, and the <lb/>dimension of C^ is S {i — s^ — d), where the sum is taken only over the n integers i <lb/> i <lb/> such that s^ ^ S + n, and d is the virtual cardinal of S. <lb/> 3. The determinant bundle and the T-function <lb/> In this section we are going to construct a holomorphic line bundle Det over Gr. <lb/>For simplicity, we shall confine ourselves to the connected component of the Grass-<lb/>mannian consisting of spaces of virtual dimension zero: the symbol Gr will now denote <lb/>this component. We think of Det as the <lb/> cc determinant bundle &quot;, that is, the bundle <lb/>whose fibre over W e Gr is the &quot; top exterior power &quot; ofW. Our first task is to explain <lb/>how to make sense of this. <lb/>On the Grassmannian Gr^C&quot;) of ^-dimensional subspaces of C&quot; the fibre of the <lb/>determinant line bundle at W e Gr^(C <lb/> 71 ) is det(W) =A <lb/> fc (W). A typical element of <lb/>A^W) can be written \w^ A Wg A . . . A ^, with \ e C, where {wj is a basis for W. <lb/>In analogy with this, an element of det(W), for W e Gr, will be an infinite expres-<lb/>sion \WQ/\ w^ A w^ A .... where {w^} is what we shall call an admissible basis for W. <lb/>The crucial property of the class of admissible bases is that if{wj and {w[} are two <lb/>admissible bases of W then the infinite matrix t relating them is of the kind that has <lb/>a determinant; for we want to be able to assert that <lb/> \WQ A W^ A W^ A ... = \ det{t) WQ A W[ A W^ A ... <lb/> when w^ == S^. w^. <lb/> Let us recall (see, for example, [19]) that an operator has a determinant if and <lb/>only if it differs from the identity by an operator of trace class. Now the subspaces W <lb/>we are considering have the property that the projection pr : W ~&gt; H^. is Fredholm <lb/>and of index zero. This means that W contains sequences {w^} such that <lb/>(i) the linear map w : H^ --&gt; H which takes z&apos; to w^ is continuous and injective and <lb/>has image W, and <lb/>(ii) the matrix relating {pr(z^)} to {^} differs from the identity by an operator of trace <lb/>class. <lb/></body>

			<page> 17 <lb/> 18 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEME SEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> Such a sequence {w^} will be called an admissible basis. (A possible choice <lb/>for {w^} is the inverse image of the sequence {-^ses ^der a projection W -&gt; Hg <lb/>which is an isomorphism (see (2.5).) <lb/>We shall think of Z£;:H^-&gt;H as a ZxN matrix <lb/> w <lb/> whose columns are the w^ and where w^. — i is of trace class; the block w_ is auto-<lb/>matically a compact operator. Then w is determined by W up to multiplication on <lb/>the right by an N X N matrix (or operator H_^. -&gt;• H^_) belonging to the group S&apos; <lb/> of all invertible matrices t such that t — i is of trace class. (The topology of ^ is <lb/>defined by the trace norm.) Because operators in ^ have determinants we can define <lb/>an element of Det (W) as a pair (w, X), where X e C and w is an admissible basis ofW, <lb/>and we identify (w, X) with (w\ X&apos;) when w&apos; == wt~ <lb/> 1  and X&apos; == X det(^) for some t e ^, <lb/>(We could also write {w, X) as \WQ A w^ A ...) <lb/>To be quite precise, the space 8ft of matrices w should be given the topology defined <lb/>by the operator norm on w_ and the trace norm on w^. — i. Then 2ft is a principal <lb/>^&quot;-bundle on Gr == ^/^, and the total space of Det is 3ft X ^-C where ^ acts on C <lb/>by det:r -^C^ <lb/>Now we come to the crucial difference between the finite and infinite dimensional <lb/>cases. The group GL^(C) acts on Gr^C^), and also on the total space of the line <lb/>bundle det on it: if g e GL^(C) and w^ A ... A w^ e det(W) then g. (w^ A ... A Wjc) <lb/> is defined as gw^ A ... A gw^ in det(^W). We have seen that the corresponding group <lb/>which acts on Gr is not the entire general linear group of H but the identity component <lb/>of the smaller group GLyeg(H) of invertible operators in H of the form <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/> la b\ <lb/>^ <lb/>^(c d) <lb/> (with respect to the decomposition H == H^.®H_)5 where b and c are compact. But <lb/>this action on Gr does not automatically induce an action on Det, for if{^} is an admis-<lb/>sible basis for W then {gw^} is usually not an admissible basis for ^W. To deal with <lb/>this problem we introduce the slightly smaller group GL^(H) consisting of invertible <lb/>operators g of the form (3.1), but where the blocks b and c are of trace class. The topo-<lb/>logy of GL^(H) is defined by the operator norm on a and d, and the trace norm on b <lb/> and c. We shall see that the action of the identity component GLi(H) <lb/> 0 on Gr does <lb/>lift projectively to Det. In other words there is a central extension GL^ of GLi(H)° <lb/>by C <lb/> &gt;&lt; which acts on Det, covering the action of GLi(H)° on Gr. <lb/>To obtain a transformation of Det we must give not only a transformation g of H <lb/>but also some information telling us how to replace a non-admissible basis {gw^} ofgW <lb/> by an admissible one. To do this we introduce the subgroup € of GLi(H)° X GL(H^.) <lb/>consisting of pairs (^, q) such that aq~ <lb/> 1  — i is of trace class, where a is as in (3. i). <lb/></body>

			<page> 18 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body> (We give € the topology induced by its embedding (g, q) h&gt; (^ ^ aq-<lb/> 1 — i) in <lb/>GLi(H) x GL(H+) x {operators of trace class}.) The definition of S is precisely <lb/>designed to make it act naturally on the space ^ of admissible bases by <lb/> {g,q).w==gwq-\ <lb/> and hence act on Det by {g, q). (w, X) = {gwq-\ X). <lb/>The group S has a homomorphism {g, q) }-&gt; g onto GLi(H)°. Its kernel can <lb/>clearly be identified with r. Thus we have an extension <lb/>r-&gt;^-^GLi(H)°. <lb/>But the subgroup ^ of r consisting of operators of determinant i acts trivially on Det, <lb/>so that in fact the quotient group GL^ == S\^ acts on Det. This last group is a central <lb/>extension of GLi(H)° by r/r^ ^ C^ <lb/>The extension <lb/>C <lb/> &gt;&lt;  -^GL^ -&gt;GLi(H)o <lb/> is a non-trivial fibre bundle: there is no continuous cross-section GLi(H)° -^ GL\ <lb/>and the extension cannot be described by a continuous cocycle. But on the dense <lb/>open set GLf^ ofGLi(H) <lb/> 0 where a is invertible, there is a cross-section s of g -&gt; GLi(H)° <lb/>given by s{g) = {g, a); the corresponding cocycle is <lb/>(^1^2) ^det(^^^-<lb/> 1 ), <lb/>where ^ = ^ <lb/> t <lb/> ^, and ^3 = ^^. We shall always make the elements of GL^ act <lb/>on Det by means of the section s. Of course, GL^ is not a group, and the map s is <lb/>not multiplicative. But let GL^- be the subgroup of GL^ consisting of elements whose <lb/>block decomposition has the form 1^ Y Then the restriction of s to GL^+ is an <lb/>inclusion of groups GLf -&gt; g and we can regard GLf as a group of automorphisms <lb/>of the bundle Det. Similar remarks apply to the subgroup GL^, consisting of elements <lb/>of GL^ whose block decomposition has the form I °L In particular the sub-<lb/> \c d) <lb/> groups I\ and F_ of the group of maps S <lb/> 1  -&gt; C <lb/> x act on Det, for 1^ C GLf. (Cf. remarks <lb/>following (2.3).) <lb/> The ^-function <lb/> We have now reached our main goal in this section, the definition of the r-function. <lb/>Alongside the determinant bundle Det just constructed there is its dual Det*, <lb/>whose fibres are the duals of the fibres of Det. A point of Det* over W e Gr can be <lb/>taken to be a pair {w, X), where w is an admissible basis for W, X e C, and (w, X) is iden-<lb/>tified with (^&apos;, X&apos;) if w&apos; == wt and X&apos; = Xdet(^) for some t e r. The action of GL^ <lb/></body>

			<page> 19 <lb/> 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEMESEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> on Det induces an action on Det*. The line bundle Det* has a canonical global holo-<lb/>morphic section o-, defined by <lb/>&lt;T(W)=(^,det^4), <lb/>where W e Gr, and w is an admissible basis for W. We can think of &lt;y(W) as the <lb/>determinant of the orthogonal projection W -&gt;• H_^; note that cr(W) == o if and only <lb/>if W is not transverse to H_. The section or is not equivariant with respect to the action <lb/>of I\ on Det*. For each W e Gr, the ^-function of W is the holomorphic function <lb/>TW : r+ -&gt; C defined by <lb/> ^QT&apos;W) <lb/> ^w{ §) == g~ <lb/> 1 <lb/> ^ <lb/> 9 <lb/> where Syv <lb/> ls some non-zero element of the fibre of Det* over W. In general there is no <lb/>canonical choice of 8^, so that T^ is defined only up to a constant factor. However, <lb/>if W is transverse to H_, it is natural to choose 8^ == ^(W), so that the r-function is <lb/>given by <lb/>(3.2) <lb/>Tw(&lt;?) .^~ <lb/> 1 &lt;r(W) == a(g~ <lb/> 1  W) (for W transverse to H_). <lb/> It is easy to give an explicit formula for T^ as an infinite determinant. <lb/> Proposition 3.3. — Let g~ <lb/> 1 e I\ have the block form <lb/> la b\ <lb/>\o d] <lb/> g-<lb/> 1 <lb/> with respect to the splitting H == H+ CH_. Then for W 6 Gr, we have <lb/> (3-4) <lb/> ^w{g) == det(w+ + a~ <lb/> 1 bwJ), <lb/>where w is an admissible basis o/W. In particular, ifVrf is transverse to H_ and T^ is normalized <lb/>as in (3.2), then we have <lb/> (3.5) <lb/> T^)=det(i +a-<lb/> l <lb/> bA), <lb/>where A: H^. -&gt; H_ is the map whose graph is W. <lb/> The proposition follows at once from the definitions. <lb/> Example <lb/> An interesting example of a space W belonging to Gr^ is the following one, which, <lb/>as we shall see, is related to the w-soliton solution of the KdV equation. <lb/>Let p^ .. .3^ be non-zero complex numbers such that |j&amp;J &lt; i and all p] are <lb/>distinct; and let ^ • • •? \n be also non-zero. Then W = Wp ^ denotes the closure <lb/>of the space of functions f which are holomorphic in the unit disc except for a pole of <lb/>order &lt;_ m at the origin, and which satisfy f(— pi) = \f{pi) tor i == i, ..., m. To <lb/></body>

			<page> 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body> calculate Ty we first determine the map A: H+ -^H_ whose graph is W, &quot; . This <lb/>assigns to /eH^. the polynomial <lb/> A  (/) <lb/> = »i(/) z-<lb/> 1 + ... + aj/) z-&quot; <lb/> such that /+ A(/) belongs to W,^. Clearly each a.(/) is a linear combination of <lb/> W), •••,? &quot; (/), where <lb/>P&lt;(/)=^(\ <lb/> i /(A)-\-<lb/> i /(-A)), <lb/> for A(/) is zero when the p.(/) vanish. In fact p&lt; == SMy a,, where <lb/> M,=^-(-z)\-i)^; <lb/> and Wp^ is transverse to H_ precisely when det(My) + o. <lb/>To apply (3.5) we must also calculate the map a~ <lb/> 1 b: H_ -&gt;H+ corresponding <lb/>to the element g~ <lb/> 1  of F+. We write g in the form exp S ^ 2*. <lb/> k&gt;9 <lb/> Suppose that a ^b takes z-&quot; to f^ eH+. Before determining /^ let us observe <lb/>that an infinite determinant of the form <lb/> det(i + S/.0a,) <lb/>reduces to the determinant of the m X m matrix whose (i,j)-th entry is <lb/> ^ + ^). <lb/>Thus Tw(t) = det(M,,)-<lb/> 1 det(M., + P.(^)). <lb/> If pr : H -&gt; H+ is the projection, we find <lb/> fk= g-pr(g-<lb/> 1 z-^ <lb/> = ,:-&quot;{r -^&lt;,^ + ^ ^ 4. ^ ^2 + , ^ ^ ^_^ ^-i^ <lb/> where 2c,z* is the expansion ofc-<lb/> 2 ^; and so <lb/> M., + (3i(^.) = -PJ^-^^^i + c,z + ... + ,,_, ^-i)}. <lb/> The determinant of this matrix, after the obvious column operations have been per-<lb/>formed on it, reduces to <lb/> /A-<lb/> 1 9i(9i + Si) A~ <lb/> 2 92(61+81) <lb/>... A-&apos;&quot;ym(9i+8i) \ <lb/> (-i)&quot; exp(S ^ ^) det ^-<lb/> 1 ?t(92 + ^) <lb/> V^&apos;y^+SJ <lb/>... <lb/>... ^&quot;•y^e^+SJ/ <lb/> where 9, == cosh for i odd and = sinh for i even, <lb/>6,= SA&apos;^, and <lb/> 7&lt;odd <lb/> 8i=^log\. <lb/>The constant factor (— i^de^My)-<lb/> 1 m TW can be ignored. <lb/></body>

			<page> 21 <lb/> 22 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEMESEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> /a\ <lb/> 2 <lb/> In § 5 we shall see that 2 — log T^ is a solution to the KdV equations. It is <lb/>W <lb/>usually called the &quot; ^-soliton <lb/> 9? solution. <lb/> The projective multiplier on r^_ and F_ <lb/> The results of this subsection will be used only in § 9. <lb/>The actions of the groups I\ and F_ on Gr obviously commute with each other. <lb/>However, their actions on Det* do not commute, and we shall need to know the relation-<lb/>ship between them. Note that since the discs DQ and D^ are simply connected, the <lb/>elements g e I\ and ^er_ can be written uniquely in the form g = e\ g&apos;== e^ <lb/> where /:Do-^C and /: D^ -&gt; C are holomorphic maps with /(o) =/(oo) = o. <lb/>Ify is an element of either I\ or F_, we shall write ^(y) for the corresponding automor-<lb/>phism of the bundle Det*. <lb/> Proposition 3.6. — If g e F^. and <lb/> / geT_, then <lb/>^)^{g)-c^g)Q[g)Q{g^ <lb/>where, if as above g&apos; = e <lb/> f and g = e\ we have <lb/>c{g,g)==e^f) <lb/>and <lb/> S(/,/) = — I f&apos;\z)f{z) dz. <lb/>2nl J gi <lb/> sw) = —• f ^W^) <lb/> dz -<lb/>2nl J gi <lb/> Proof. — It is immediate from the definition of the actions of F^ on Det* that we <lb/>have a formula of the kind stated, with <lb/> ^ §) =det{aaa-<lb/> 1 y-<lb/> 1 ) <lb/> where a and H are the H^. -^ H+ blocks of g and ^ (The commutator has a deter-<lb/>minant because, from the fact that g and ^commute, it is equal to i — b?a~ <lb/> 1 S&apos;~ <lb/> 1 , <lb/> where b and*? are the off-diagonal blocks of g and ^ which are of trace class by (2.3).) <lb/>The map c is a homomorphism from F_ x I\ to C; it follows easily that it is of the desired <lb/>form, with <lb/> S(yj-) = trace [a, ?], <lb/> /N/ <lb/>/^/ <lb/> where a and a&apos;are the H+ -&gt; H^. blocks of/and/. Now, if/= S^ z <lb/> i  and / == S^. ^~ <lb/> ^ , <lb/>the (^, k) matrix element of the commutator [a, o?] is <lb/> k <lb/> oo <lb/> S ^A~ S ^^. <lb/> m= 1 <lb/> m= 1 <lb/> The trace is therefore <lb/> S; ma^=—\ 7 <lb/> ; <lb/> (.)/(.)^. <lb/> w=l <lb/>27T? J gi <lb/>»n=l <lb/> m m <lb/> ZTT^Jgi <lb/> as stated. <lb/></body>

			<page> 22 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body> Lemma 3.7. — The section a ofDeC is equivariant with respect to the action of F_, that <lb/>is, we have <lb/> o(^W)=^(W) forger_. <lb/>Lemma 3.8. — For g&apos; e F_, we have <lb/> ^W^-^TwOO, <lb/> where as before g = e <lb/> f and &apos;g== e^ <lb/> Both lemmas follow at once from the definitions. <lb/> General remarks <lb/> In the theory of loop groups like the group L of smooth maps S <lb/> 1  -&gt; GL^(C) the <lb/>existence of a certain central extension <lb/> C <lb/> x  -^L -&gt;L <lb/> plays an important role. This extension (at least over the identity component of L) <lb/>is the restriction of the central extension GL^ constructed in this section, when L is <lb/>embedded in the usual way in GLi(H). <lb/> On the level of Lie algebras the extension can be described very simply for the <lb/>loop group LG of any reductive group G. The Lie algebra of LG is the vector space Lg <lb/>of loops in the Lie algebra g of G, and the extension is defined by the cocycle <lb/>(B : Lg x Lg  -&gt; C <lb/> given by <lb/> (B(/,,/,) = <lb/> I f^^e),/^)) dQ, <lb/> 2n Jo <lb/> where &lt; , &gt; is a suitably normalized invariant bilinear form on g. <lb/>The existence of the corresponding extension of groups is less obvious (cf. [18]), <lb/>partly because it is topologically non-trivial as a fibre bundle. The discussion in this <lb/>section provides a concrete realization of L as a group of holomorphic automorphisms <lb/>of the line bundle Det, in the case G == GL^(C). For the elements of L above y <lb/> e L <lb/>are precisely the holomorphic bundle maps y <lb/> : Det -&gt; Det which cover the action of y <lb/>on Gr. (For given y the possible choices of 9 differ only by multiplication by constants, <lb/>as any holomorphic function on Gr is constant. (Gf. remark following (2.11)).) <lb/>The corresponding central extension of the loop group of any complex reductive <lb/>group (characterized by its Lie algebra cocycle) can be constructed in a similar way <lb/>as a group of holomorphic automorphisms of a complex line bundle, and conversely <lb/>the holomorphic line bundle is determined by the group extension. This is explained <lb/>in [17]. But in the general case the line bundle does not have such a simple description. <lb/> 23 <lb/></body>

			<page> 24 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEMESEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> 4. Generalized KdV equations and the formal Baker function <lb/> The n-th generalized KdV hierarchy consists of all evolution equations for n — i <lb/>unknown functions UQ^X, t), ..., ^_a(^? ^) tihat can be written in the form 8Lfc)t = [P, L], <lb/>where L is the n-th order ordinary differential operator <lb/> L==D <lb/> n +^-2D <lb/> n-2 + ... +u,D+u, <lb/> and P is another differential operator. (As usual, D denotes ^/&amp;y.) The possible ope-<lb/>rators P are essentially determined by the requirement that [P, L] should have order <lb/>(at most) n — 2. A very simple description of them is available if we work in the <lb/>algebra of formal pseudo-differential operators, which we denote by Psd. <lb/>A formal pseudo-differential operator is, by definition, a formal series of the form <lb/> N <lb/> R == S r,[x) D <lb/> 1 <lb/> — 00 <lb/> for some N eZ. The coefficients r^{x) are supposed to lie in some algebra of smooth <lb/>functions of x. To multiply two such operators, we need to know how to move D~ <lb/> 1 <lb/> across a function r(x): the rule for this, <lb/> D-^r^ Sf-i^D-<lb/> 1 -^ <lb/>j=o <lb/> follows easily from the basic rule <lb/>(4.1) <lb/> Dr==rD+8rlSx <lb/> determining the composition of differential operators. It is easy to check that this makes <lb/>Psd into an associative algebra. <lb/> Proposition 4.2. — In the algebra Psd, the operator L has a unique n-th root of the form <lb/> L^^Q^D+S^D-<lb/> 1 . <lb/>i <lb/> The coefficients q^ are certain universal differential polynomials in the u^ if we assign to u^ the <lb/>weight n — i -{-j, then q^ is homogeneous of weight i + i. <lb/> Proof. — Equating coefficients of powers of D in the equality Q^ = L, we find <lb/>that <lb/>^_.-i ==»?,+ a,, <lb/>where a^ is some differential polynomial in q^ ..., y&lt;_i (here we have set Uj = o if <lb/> j &lt; o). We claim that if we give q^ weight i + J + <lb/> 1  then o^ is homogeneous of <lb/>weight i + i. Granting that, it is clear that the above equations can be solved uniquely <lb/>for the q^ and that these have the form stated. <lb/>The homogeneity of the a, is most easily seen as follows. Consider the algebra <lb/></body>

			<page> 24 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>125 <lb/></page>

			<body> of formal pseudo-differential operators whose coefficients are differential polynomials <lb/>in the g, (which we think of for the moment as abstract symbols, rather than as fixed <lb/>functions of x). Call such an operator homogeneous of weight r if the coefficient of D <lb/> 1 <lb/> is homogeneous of weight r -- i (thus D has weight i). From the homogeneity of the <lb/>basic rule (4.1) it follows at once that the product of two operators that are homo-<lb/>geneous of weights r and s is homogeneous of weight r + s. Since Q is homogeneous <lb/>of weight i, Q&quot; must be homogeneous of weight n. <lb/> If R == 2r^ D <lb/> 1  is a formal pseudo-differential operator, we shall write R, for the <lb/> (&lt; differential operator part &quot; R+ == S r,D <lb/> 1 , and R_ == S r,D\ Thus R = R, + R_. <lb/> i^.0 <lb/> i&lt;0 <lb/>&apos; <lb/> Proposition 4.3. — The equation <lb/> (4.4) <lb/>BL/^ = [Lf, L] <lb/> is equivalent to a system of evolution equations <lb/>^ <lb/>8t <lb/> J% <lb/> for the coefficients ^3 . . ., ^_g ofL. The f^ are differential polynomials in the u^ homogeneous <lb/>of weight n -\-r — i. <lb/> Proof. — Note first that L^ denotes (L^)^; L^ is defined as Q;. The only <lb/>part of the proposition that is not obvious from what precedes is that the commutator <lb/>in (4.4) is an operator of order at most n — 2. But that follows at once from the equality <lb/> [L^, L] = [-L^, L]. <lb/> (Of course I/^ and L commute, because they are both powers of Q^ = L <lb/> 17 <lb/> ^) <lb/>The equation (4.4) is called the r-th equation of the n-th KdV hierarchy. It is trivial <lb/>if r is a multiple of n, because then I/^ = I/^ is just an integral power of L. <lb/>It is usual to think of the equations (4.4) as defining flows on some space of func-<lb/>tions {uo{x), . . ., u^_^{x)}: it is then a basic fact that the flows corresponding to different <lb/>values of r commute. For this assertion to make sense, we need to identify some class <lb/>of functions on which the flows can be proved to exist, that is, we need to prove existence <lb/>and uniqueness theorems for solutions of the equations (4.4). However, the analytic <lb/>problems involved here are in a sense irrelevant: the basic <lb/> &lt;( infinitesimal &quot; fact under-<lb/>lying the commutativity can be formulated in a purely algebraic way. We refer to [22] <lb/>for a very simple proof of this algebraic version of the commutativity. In the present <lb/>paper none of these questions need concern us, because for the special class of solutions <lb/>that we are interested in, both the existence of the flows and their commutativity will <lb/>be clear from the construction. <lb/></body>

			<page> 25 <lb/> 26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEME SEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> The formal Baker function <lb/> The main idea in all studies of solutions of the equations (4.4) is this: as L changes <lb/>in time, we try to follow the evolution of the eigenfunctions ofL by comparing them with <lb/>the eigenfunctions of the constant operator D <lb/> 71 <lb/> . To do that, we find an operator K <lb/>such that K-<lb/> 1 LK == D^ then if ^ is an eigenfunction of D^ ^ = K^ will be an <lb/>eigenfunction of L. The algebra Psd enables us to give one realization of this idea. <lb/> Proposition 4.5.— There is an operator K e Psd of the form <lb/> (4-6) <lb/>K= i +S^)D-<lb/> 1 <lb/> such that K-<lb/> 1 LK == D\ Such a K is unique up to right multiplication by a constant coefficient <lb/>operator of the form i + ^ D~ <lb/> 1 + .... <lb/> Proof. — Only constant coefficient operators commute with D&quot;, so the statement <lb/>about uniqueness is trivial. To prove existence, we simply compare coefficients of powers <lb/>ofD in the equality LK == KD&quot;; this gives equations Sa^x ==..., where the right <lb/>hand side involves only ^. with j &lt; i; we can therefore solve these equations successively <lb/>to get suitable ^. <lb/>Proposition 4.5 can be reformulated as follows. <lb/> Proposition 4.7. — The equation L^ = ^ has a solution in the space of formal series <lb/>of the form <lb/> (4.8) <lb/> ^=e <lb/> x^ <lb/> {l+^a,{x)z-<lb/> i ). <lb/>The solution ^ is unique up to multiplication by a series with constant coefficients of the form <lb/> i +c^z~ <lb/> 1 + .... <lb/> The series ^ in (4.8) is called the formal Baker function ofL. The solutions of the <lb/>KdV equations that we are going to construct are characterized by the property that <lb/>this formal series actually converges (for \z\ sufficiently large). As we mentioned in <lb/>the introduction, among these solutions are the rank i algebro-geometric solutions of <lb/>Krichever: it was essentially in that context that the function ^ was originally introduced <lb/>by Baker [3]. <lb/>The intuitive reason for the equivalence of (4.5) and (4.7) was explained above: <lb/>since K-<lb/> 1 LK == D^ we expect the solutions of the equation L^ = ^ ^ to be of the <lb/>form ^ = K^o, where ^o is a solution of D <lb/> n ^ == ^ ^. If we take ^ == e^, then <lb/>formally it is clear that + = K^o should be given by (4.8). We can make this argument <lb/>i^gorous as follows. Let M be the space of all formal expressions / = e^J, where <lb/> f is a formal series <lb/>7= S fiW ^ (for some N). <lb/> — 00 <lb/></body>

			<page> 26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body> Differential operators act on M in an obvious way: the action of D on M is given by <lb/>D^7=^(D+^ <lb/>If we let D~ <lb/> 1 act on M by <lb/>D-^-^D+^r^ <lb/>where (D +-<lb/> 2 &apos;)&quot; <lb/> 1 ls  interpreted as the formal series z~ <lb/> 1 <lb/> —D-2~ <lb/> 2 4-•••5 it is <lb/>easy to check that this makes M into a module over the algebra Psd. If <lb/>R = .^r,{x) D <lb/> 1 e Psd, then <lb/>R^ = ^(S^) ^-<lb/> l ), <lb/>so that M is in fact a free Psd-module of rank i, with generator e^ e M. <lb/> The KP equations <lb/> It will often be convenient for us to regard the n-th KdV hierarchy (for any n) <lb/> as embedded in a certain &quot;universal KdV hierarchy &quot; of evolution equations in infinitely <lb/>many variables; for brevity we shall follow [5] and call these equations the KP (for <lb/>Kadomtsev-Petviashvili) hierarchy. The KP equations are defined as follows. Let Q^ be <lb/>a general first order formal pseudo-differential operator of the form <lb/> Q=D+SftWD-<lb/> 1 <lb/> (in general, such a Q/will not be the n-th root of a differential operator for any n). <lb/> Proposition 4.io« — The equation <lb/> (4.11) <lb/>^[Q^QJ <lb/> is equivalent to a system of evolution equations <lb/> ^ i _ r <lb/>ft-^ <lb/> for the (infinitely many) functions q^[x, t), i&gt;_ i. The f^ are certain universal differential poly-<lb/>nomials in the q^ homogeneous of weight r + i + i if we give q^ weight i +J+ <lb/> I <lb/> . <lb/> The proof is the same as that of (4.3). We call (4. n) the r-th equation of the KP <lb/>hierarchy. <lb/> Proposition 4.12. — The assignment L \-&gt; L <lb/> 17 <lb/> &quot; == Q^ sets up a i — i correspondence <lb/>between solutions of the n-th KdV hierarchy and solutions Q^ of the KP hierarchy such that Q^ is <lb/>a differential operator. <lb/> Proof. —It is trivial that if Q^ satisfies (4.11) then L === QJ <lb/> 1  satisfies (4.4). We <lb/> refer to [22] for the proof of the converse, which is only slightly harder. <lb/></body>

			<page> 27 <lb/>28 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEMESEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> The scaling transformation <lb/>Proposition 4.13. — Let Q^ == D + S^ D~ <lb/> 1 ^ fl7^ solution of the r-th equation (4.11). <lb/> For any non-zero complex number X, let R^Q^= D + S^D&quot; <lb/> 1 <lb/> , where the coefficients cf^ <lb/>are defined by <lb/> ^(^)==x*+ <lb/> 1 ^,^). <lb/> Then R^ Q^ i^ another solution of (4.11). <lb/> Proof. — This follows trivially from the assertion in (4.10) about the homogeneity <lb/>of the/,. <lb/>We call the operation R^ the scaling transformation of the solutions to the KP equa-<lb/>tions. Notice that each variable gets rescaled by the power of X corresponding to its <lb/>weight. The scaling transformations clearly act on the solutions to the n-th K-dV hie-<lb/>rarchy (for any n). <lb/>Note on the literature. — Our construction of the KdV equations follows closely <lb/>the exposition in [14]. The basic idea of using fractional powers of L first appeared <lb/>in the 1976 paper ofGePfand and Dikii [9], and has been used extensively in the literature <lb/>since then. In [5] this idea is attributed to Sato (1981). <lb/> 5. The Baker function <lb/> In this section Gr and Gr^ will denote the component of the Grassmannians <lb/>consisting of spaces of virtual dimension zero. We are going to associate to each W e Gr <lb/>a &quot; Baker function &quot; (j/w? ^d ^° <lb/> a sequence of differential operators defined in terms of 4/w <lb/>We recall from § 2 that the group I\ of holomorphic maps g :J)Q -&gt;C <lb/> X  with <lb/>^(o) == i acts on Gr. Given a space W e Gr, we set <lb/>r^ == {g e I\ : .g^W is transverse to H_}. <lb/>From now on we shall refer to spaces transverse to H_ simply as transverse. From § 3 <lb/>it follows that F^ is the complement of the zero set of the r-function r^y: F^. -&gt;C; <lb/> in particular it is a dense open subset of F^.. (We admit for the moment the fact that <lb/>r^ is not empty, that is, that the holomorphic function T^ is not identically zero: this <lb/>will be proved in § 8.) <lb/> Proposition 5.1. — For each W e Gr there is a unique function ^w(g, z), defined for <lb/>g e r^ and z e S <lb/> 1 <lb/> , such that <lb/> (i) ^ •) eW for each fixed g e 1^ <lb/>(ii) ^ has the form <lb/> (5.a) <lb/> ^w=^)(i+S^)^). <lb/> The coefficients a^ are analytic functions on F^; they extend to meromorphic functions on the whole <lb/> ofr.,. <lb/></body>

			<page> 28 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body> The proof of the last sentence depends on the properties of the r-function, and will <lb/>be given later in this section. The rest of the proposition is trivial: the infinite series <lb/>in (5.2) is simply the unique function of that form that lies in the transverse space g~ <lb/> 1  W, <lb/>that is, it is the inverse image of i under the orthogonal projection g~ <lb/> 1 ^ -&gt;H^.. <lb/>We call ^ the Baker function of W. <lb/>Now, each g e I\ can be written uniquely in the form <lb/>(5.3) <lb/> g{^) <lb/> = exp(^ +^z <lb/> 2 <lb/> +^z <lb/> 3 <lb/> + ...) <lb/>with x, t^ e C. When g is written in this way, we shall write ^w{x, t, z) instead of <lb/>^w(5? <lb/> z ) <lb/> 9 <lb/> Here t stands for (^, ^3, ...). In this notation, ^ is a &quot;function of infi-<lb/>nitely many variables &quot; of the form <lb/> 00 <lb/> (5-4) <lb/>+w(^ t, z) = exp{xz + ^ z <lb/> 2  + ...) (i + S^A:, t) z-^. <lb/> i <lb/> Proposition 5.5. — For each integer r&gt;_ 2, there is a unique differential operator Py of <lb/>the form <lb/> Pr-D^^D-^ ... +^_,D+A. <lb/> such that <lb/> l a\ <lb/> ^ <lb/> w <lb/> P f <lb/>(5-6) <lb/> ~W <lb/> r ^ <lb/> 9 <lb/> (Here as usual D == 3/fty.) The coefficients p^ are certain universal differential polynomials <lb/>in the functions a^ in (5.4). <lb/> Proof. — From (5.4), we have <lb/>^w <lb/> 8L <lb/> ^(W+^i^+O^-<lb/> 2 )). <lb/> On the other hand, D <lb/> r ^ also has this form, and in general we have <lb/> D^w-^K^+O^-<lb/> 1 )). <lb/> Comparing coefficients, we see at once that there is a unique operator Py of the form <lb/>stated such that <lb/> (5.7) <lb/>^-P^w-^XO^-<lb/> 1 )). <lb/> Now, since ^ lies in W for each fixed (A&quot;, t), the same is true of the derivatives 8^w/^r <lb/>and D^w-Hence the left hand side of (5.7) lies in W for each fixed value of (x, t) <lb/>for which it is defined, that is, for which the corresponding g belongs to F^. But the <lb/>right hand side of (5.7) belongs to ^H_. As g~ <lb/> 1  W is transverse, both sides must vanish. <lb/>Now let <lb/> K= i + S;^(^,t)D-<lb/> 1 <lb/> i <lb/></body>

			<page> 29 <lb/> 30 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEME SEGALANDGEORGEWILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> be the formal integral operator corresponding to ^ (see § 4). Equation (5.6) can be <lb/>written in the form <lb/>(5.3) <lb/>^+KD <lb/> r -P,K, <lb/> at, <lb/> so that in particular we have <lb/>^(KlyK-^Q:,., <lb/>where we have set Q= KDK~ <lb/> 1 . Thus Q^ is a formal pseudo-differential operator <lb/>of the form <lb/> Q=D+S;^,t)D-\ <lb/>i <lb/> Proposition 5.9. — The coefficients q^ of (^satisfy the equations of the KP hierarchy; that <lb/>is, we have <lb/> ^=[Q.,a]. <lb/> Each q^ is a meromorphic function of all the variables {x, t). <lb/> Proof. — Differentiating the relation defining Q and rewriting, we find <lb/>^[W^K-<lb/> 1 ,^]. <lb/> On the other hand, from (5.8) we have <lb/>^K-<lb/> 1 = P, -KD-K-<lb/> 1 = Q:^-Q:, <lb/> ^r <lb/> so the proposition follows at once. <lb/>Recall from § 2 that rescaling z induces an action W(-&gt;R^W of the semigroup <lb/>of complex numbers X with |X[ &lt; i on Gr. <lb/> Proposition 5.10. — The Baker function corresponding to the space R^ W is given by <lb/> +R^w(^ ^ h, ...; z) == ^{\x, •K <lb/> 2 1^ X <lb/> 2 ^3, . . .; X-<lb/> 1  z). <lb/>IfQ^is the solution oftheKP equations corresponding to W, then the solution corresponding to R^ W <lb/> is R^^ (4.13);. <lb/> The proof is trivial. <lb/>We now specialize to the case W e Gr^* <lb/> Proposition 5.11. — If W e Gr^, then <lb/> Pn+W-^W <lb/> Moreover, the functions a^ and hence also all the operators Py, are independent of ^, ^n? ^3n? • • •• <lb/></body>

			<page> 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<body> 01 <lb/> Proof. — From (5.4) and (5.6) we see that <lb/> P n ^ W -^ ^ W -^ S ^ ^ -<lb/> 1 . <lb/>1 ^n <lb/> For W e Gr^, the left hand side of this expression lies in W for each fixed {x, t); it <lb/>therefore vanishes by the same argument as in the proof of (5.5). That proves die <lb/>first statement in the proposition, and also that the a, are independent of ^. Since <lb/>obviously Gr^CGr^) for all r^ i, the a, are independent of ^ too. <lb/>Since the a, are independent of ^, the operator K is also, so (5.8) gives <lb/> P^^KD^K-<lb/> 1 ^ (y. <lb/> Thus if W e Gr^ then Q: is a differential operator. Write L for P^ == Q^; then L <lb/>has the form D-+ u^ D-<lb/> 2 + ... + u,. Combining (5.9) and (4.12), we get <lb/>the main result of this section. <lb/> Corollary 5.12. — If W e Gr^, the coefficients of the operator L satisfy the equations <lb/>of the n-th KdV hierarchy, that is, we have <lb/> ^-n^ TI <lb/>^&quot;-<lb/> LL+9LJ -<lb/> Let us reformulate this slightly. For each W e Gr^, let L^ denote the operator L <lb/>evaluated for ^ = ^3 = ... = o. The coefficients ^ •.., ^n-2 of L^ are functions <lb/>of one variable x: they are the &quot; initial values &apos; <lb/> 5 of the KdV flows. Let ^ <lb/> (n) be the space <lb/>ofallL^for W e Gr^. The map Gr^ -&gt;^ is not one to one: however, from (4.7) <lb/>we see that L^ = L^, precisely when W = yW&apos;, where y is a function of the form <lb/>i + ^ z&quot; <lb/> 1  + ... Since multiplication by y commutes with the action of I\, we can <lb/>restate (5.12) as follows. <lb/> Proposition 5.13. — The action of I\ 072 Gr^ ^W^y ^ action on the space ^ <lb/> {n) . The <lb/>flow W h&gt; exp(^ ^ <lb/> r <lb/> ) W on Gr^ zW^^ ^ r-th KdV flow on ^ <lb/> {n} . <lb/> Since I\ is commutative, it is obvious that the different KdV flows on ^ <lb/> (n) <lb/> commute. <lb/> Examples <lb/> To obtain the simplest interesting example of a space in Gr^ we choose p e C <lb/>so that o&lt; \p\ &lt; i, and \eC <lb/> X , and define Wp^ as the L <lb/> 2 closure of the space of <lb/>functions/which are holomorphic in | z\ &lt;_ i except for a possible simple pole at the <lb/>origin, and which satisfy f{—p) =\f{p). <lb/> The Baker function of Wp ^ must be of the form <lb/> +(t, 0 = 0^(1 + a{t)lz). <lb/> 31 <lb/></body>

			<page> 32 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEMESEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body>(We write here t == (^, ^, . ..), where ^ is identified with A:.) From the condition <lb/> ^^P) =U^P) we find <lb/> a{t) == —^tanh(6 + a), <lb/>where 6 = S p <lb/> 16 1^ <lb/> and <lb/>^ <lb/> a = ^.. <lb/> fcodd <lb/> The second-order differential operator L such that L^ = z <lb/> 2 ^ is D <lb/> 2 — 20&apos;, i.e. <lb/>D2+ a^sech^O + a). <lb/>This is the well known one-soliton solution of the KdV equation. <lb/>More generally, we have the subspace Wp^ introduced in § 3 which depends <lb/>on m points ^, . . .,An of the disc | z\ &lt; i and m parameters \, . .., ^ e C <lb/> x <lb/> . The <lb/>corresponding solution of the KdV equation is called the m-soliton solution. We shall <lb/>give an expression for it below in terms of the r-function which was calculated in § 3; <lb/>but let us at present notice the obvious fact that it depends on t only through &lt;? <lb/> e * <lb/> +a *, <lb/>where 6, = S ^ ^ and e <lb/> 2 ^ == \. This is because the orbit of W, , under F, is <lb/> k odd <lb/> p <lb/> &apos; <lb/> r <lb/> isomorphic to (C^: in fact if y : Do -&gt; C&quot; is an element of I\ then y-Wp ^ == W <lb/>where ^ = y(A) Y(~A)~ <lb/> 1 \-<lb/> The Baker function and the ^-function <lb/> We now turn to the proof of the last part of (5. i), concerning the properties of <lb/>the functions a,. It depends on the formula (5.14) below, relating the Baker function <lb/>to the T-function, which we mentioned in the Introduction as central to the theory. <lb/>We return to the case of an arbitrary space W e Gr (not necessarily in any Gr^). <lb/>Let us write <lb/> 00 <lb/> ?w(^ -2&apos;) == I +Sfl,(^) Z~ <lb/> 1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> for the infinite series in (5.2). Clearly ^w extends to an analytic function of z in the <lb/>region | z\ &gt; i (for each fixed g e F^). For ^ e C we write ^ for the map <lb/> q^z) == i -^. <lb/>Obviously <lb/> &lt;7^el\ for |?:|&gt; i. <lb/> Proposition 5.14. — For g e F^ and \ ^ \ &gt; i we have <lb/> ?w(^) ^^{g&apos;g^hw^&apos; <lb/> Proof. — It follows easily from (3.2) that the right hand side is equal to r-i^(y.). <lb/>The left hand side is characterized as the unique function of the form i + S^ ^ <lb/> -l <lb/> whose boundary value as [ S | -&gt; i lies in the transverse space g~ <lb/> 1  W. Hence the pro-<lb/>position follows at once if we apply the next lemma to g~ <lb/> 1  W. <lb/></body>

			<page> 32 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<body> Lemma 5.15. — Let W e Gr be transverse, and letfo be the unique element of H_ such <lb/>that i+/o^W. Then for |?:|&gt;i, we have <lb/> ^w(^) -i +W. <lb/> Proof. — We use the formula (3.5). When q, <lb/> 1  is written in the form ( <lb/> a b <lb/> \ the <lb/>\o d/ <lb/> 9 <lb/> map b : H_ -&gt; H+ takes z-<lb/> 1 &apos; to ^ ^ <lb/> 1 ; thus a-<lb/> 1 b is the map of rank one that takes <lb/>/ e H_ to the constant function/(^). The map a~ <lb/> 1 bA is thus also of rank one, and the <lb/>infinite determinant <lb/>^(^ -de^i +a~ <lb/> l bA) <lb/> is equal to <lb/> i + trace {a~ <lb/> 1 bA). <lb/> Since A maps i tof^z), the lemma follows. <lb/>If we write g in the form (5.3), and correspondingly write ^ in the form <lb/> 00 <lb/> q^z) = exp log(i -^) = exp(— S ^/^), <lb/>i <lb/>then (5.14) takes the form <lb/>(5.16) <lb/> ^(x, t, ?:) = Tw(^ -i/^, ^ ~ i/2^ <lb/> 2 , .. .)/Tw(^ t). <lb/>The fact that the functions a,{x, t) are meromorphic follows at once from this formula: <lb/>indeed, if we expand the numerator in a Taylor series, we see that each a, has the form <lb/> ^=P,T/T <lb/> where P, is a polynomial differential operator in 8/8x, B/^, ..., a/^,. For example, <lb/>we have <lb/> ^ = - ^x)l^ <lb/> ^= <lb/> I -(^T/a^-aT/%2)/T. <lb/> The proof of (5. i) is now complete. <lb/>We can be more precise about the orders of the poles of the functions a.. Let us <lb/>fix the values of the variables ^, ^3, .... say ^ = ^, and regard a, as a meromorphic <lb/>function of one variable x. <lb/>Proposition 5.17. — The poles of the function a,{x, t°) have order at most i. <lb/> In the case of a^, this follows at once from the formula above and the fact that <lb/>T is analytic. For i &gt; i, however, that is not so; for example, if we had T == ^ + ^, <lb/>then the corresponding function a^{x, o) would have a pole of order n at the origin. <lb/> Our proof of (5.17) uses the expansion of the r-function in terms of Schur functions: <lb/>it will be given in § 8. <lb/></body>

			<page> 33 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> 5 <lb/></note>

			<page> 34 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEME SEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> Corollary 5.18. — For W e Gr^, ^ differential operators L^ e ^ <lb/> (n)  have only regular <lb/>singular points (except for the point at infinity); that is, the coefficient u^ of D <lb/> ^  has poles of order <lb/>at most n — i. <lb/> Proof. — Recall that L^ = KD^-<lb/> 1 , where K == i + S^) D-\ Thus if <lb/>we give a^ weight k +j, then ^ is a homogeneous differential polynomial in the a^ <lb/> of weight n—i (cf. the proof of (4.2)). Thus the corollary follows at once from (5.17). <lb/>Finally, we note that the coefficients ^ of L can be expressed directly in terms of <lb/>the T-function. In the case n == 2, L has the form D <lb/> 2 + ^w? where <lb/> , <lb/>, <lb/>^i <lb/> ^ , <lb/> (5.19) <lb/>^———2-^=2^1og^. <lb/> However for n &gt; 2 the explicit formulae become very complicated. <lb/> The class ^ <lb/> (n) <lb/> We have shown how to associate an yz-th order differential operator <lb/> (5.20) <lb/> L^=D <lb/> n + u^{x) D^ <lb/> 2 + ... + ^oW, <lb/> with meromorphic coefficients and only regular singular points, to a space W e Gr^. <lb/>We shall now describe the inverse process of associating a space W to a differential ope-<lb/>rator L. This cannot be done for an arbitrary operator, even one which is meromorphic <lb/>with regular singular points. We do not know an altogether satisfying description of <lb/>the desired class ^?^; roughly speaking, it consists of the operators whose formal Baker <lb/>functions converge for large z. <lb/> Suppose that L is of the form (5.20), with coefficients defined and smooth in an <lb/>open interval I containing the origin. The formal Baker function <lb/> ^, z) = ^{ i + a,(x) z-<lb/> 1 + a^x) z-<lb/> 2 + ... } <lb/> ofL was introduced in § 4. It is a formal series whose coefficients a, are smooth functions <lb/>defined in the interval I, and it is uniquely determined by L if we normalize it so that <lb/>^(o, z) == i. If the n formal series <lb/> (5.21) <lb/>^(o,^),D^(o,^),...,D <lb/> n -<lb/> l ^(o,^) <lb/> (which belong to the field C((-2&apos;~ <lb/> 1 ))) converge for large z, then by a scaling transformation <lb/>we can make them converge for ] z \ &gt; i — e, so that they define n elements 4&apos;o? 4&apos;i3 • • • ? 4n-i <lb/>of our Hilbert space H. We should like to define the corresponding W e Gr^ as <lb/>the closed ^-invariant subspace of H generated by ^o, . . ., 4&apos;n-i? ^^ <lb/> as TH+, where <lb/>Y is the {n X ^-matrix-valued function (^o, ^, . . ., ^_i) on the circle. (In regarding <lb/>Y as a matrix-valued function we are using the identification H ^ H^ described in § 2.) <lb/>For this to be possible we need to know that y <lb/> ls a 1°°P °f winding number zero in <lb/>GL^(C) — otherwise W^ would turn out to be bigger than the space spanned alge-<lb/></body>

			<page> 24 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page> 35 <lb/></page>

			<body> braically by {z^ ^}&amp;^o,o^&lt;n-Making y explicit according to the formulae of § 2, <lb/>we find <lb/> /i ^ ... ^-\-<lb/> 1  /^i) ^i) ... ^-i(^)\ <lb/> I <lb/>^2 <lb/> W <lb/> ^2) <lb/>% <lb/> Y^)-<lb/>^-1(^2) <lb/> \1 <lb/> ^ . . . <lb/>^-<lb/> 1 / <lb/>Uo(^) <lb/>^n) <lb/> where ?^, ..., ^ are the n-th roots of z. But ^(-2&apos;) ^ ^ as 2&apos; <lb/> +n-l(^)/ <lb/> oo. So Y is holomor-<lb/>phic in |^| &gt; i — s, and y(-<lb/> 2 &apos;) ~^ <lb/> 1 as z  -<lb/> &gt; 00 <lb/> -By a further rescaling, if necessary, <lb/>we can therefore ensure that y(-2&apos;) is invertible for | z\ &gt; i — s, as we want. <lb/>Let us notice that the series D^ ^(o, -2:) depend only on the jets (i.e. Taylor series) <lb/>at the origin of the coefficients ^ ofL, and that conversely the series D^ ^(o, z) determine <lb/>the jets of the ^ at o. The space W which we have just constructed has its own Baker <lb/>function ^, which in turn defines a differential operator L^r with coefficients meromor-<lb/>phic in the entire complex plane. (For brevity, we shall write ^w{x, z) for the Baker <lb/>function evaluated at ^ === ^3 ==...== o.) Because both D^ ^(o, z) and D^ ^w(°5 <lb/> z ) <lb/> belong to W and are of the form ^ + (lower terms), it follows by induction on k that <lb/>they coincide. The jets of the coefficients ofL and L^y at o must therefore coincide too. <lb/>This gives us the first half of the following result. <lb/> Proposition 5.22. <lb/> (i) If the series (5.21) converge in a neighbourhood of z == oo, then there are meromorphic <lb/>functions %, ...,%_ 3 defined in the entire complex plane such that u, and ^ have the same Taylor <lb/>series at x == o. <lb/>(ii) If the series ^){x, z) converges for \z\ &gt; R for each x in I then the u^ coincide with <lb/>the ^ in I. <lb/> To prove the second statement, let ^{x, z&quot;) be the solution of L&lt;p = z&quot; 9 <lb/>characterized by the initial conditions D^ 9^(0, ^ <lb/> n ) = Sy. Each 9, is an entire <lb/>function of z <lb/> n  for x in I. If z is fixed and \z\ &gt; R, then ^{x, z) and <lb/> &quot;S 9z(^ ^ <lb/> n <lb/> ) D^(o, z) <lb/> t== 0 <lb/> are both solutions of 1.9 = z <lb/> n (^ with the same initial conditions. They must therefore <lb/>coincide, and it follows that ^i{x, •) belongs to W for all x e I. As ^{x, •) also belongs <lb/>to ^(i + H_), we can conclude that ^{x, z) == ^{x, z) for all x e I, and so L <lb/>and L^ coincide in I. <lb/> 6. Algebraic curves: the construction of Krichever <lb/> In Krichever&apos;s construction of solutions to the KdV equations the starting point <lb/>is a collection of data whose most important constituents are a compact Riemann sur-<lb/></body>

			<page> 35 <lb/> 36 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEMESEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> face X and a holomorphic line bundle oSf over it. Mumford [16] pointed out that the <lb/>construction still applies more or less unchanged if we allow X to be any complete <lb/>irreducible complex algebraic curve (possibly singular), and that in that case it is natural <lb/>to allow oS^ to be, more generally, a rank i torsion free coherent sheaf over X. (If X is <lb/>non-singular, any such sheaf is a line bundle.) One reason for including singular curves <lb/>is that the n-soliton solutions correspond to rational curves with n double points; and <lb/>even the solutions coming from torsion free sheaves that are not line bundles seem to <lb/>have nothing very exotic about them (we shall see examples in § 7). The inclusion of <lb/>torsion free sheaves will not cause us any extra difficulty, and will be essential for the <lb/>proof of theorem 6.10 below. <lb/>As well as X and o2 <lb/> 7 <lb/> , the construction requires three more pieces of data [Xy^, z, 9). <lb/>Here x^ is a non-singular point of X and z~ <lb/> 1  is a local parameter on X near x^. We <lb/>shall suppose that z is an isomorphism from some closed neighbourhood Xoo of x^ in X <lb/>to the disc D^ == {[ z | ^ i} in the Riemann sphere. That can always be achieved <lb/>by rescaling z (see remark 6.5 below). Finally, 9 is a trivialization of JSf over Xoo. <lb/>We shall use 9 to identify sections of S? over subsets of Xoo with complex-valued func-<lb/>tions. We shall also identify the unit circle S <lb/> 1 with its inverse image in X under z. <lb/> We denote by Xo the complement of the interior ofXoo: thus the closed sets Xoo and Xo <lb/>cover X, and their intersection is S <lb/> 1 <lb/> . <lb/>To all this data we associate the following subspace W of H = L^S <lb/> 1 <lb/> , C): W is <lb/>the closure of the space of analytic functions on S <lb/> 1  that extend to sections of oS^ over Xo. <lb/> Proposition 6.1. — The subspace W belongs to the Grassmannian Gr. The virtual dimen-<lb/>sion of W is equal to ^( <lb/> J <lb/> ^) — <lb/> I ? where as usual )c(°^) denotes the Euler characteristic <lb/> dim H°(X; J? <lb/> 7 <lb/> ) — dim H^X; JSf). <lb/> Proof. — We observe first that the projection W -&gt; H_ factorizes <lb/>W <lb/> B <lb/> ^ H -^ H_ -<lb/> B ^ H. <lb/>for suitable \ with o&lt; )\.&lt; i (here R^ is the scaling transformation discussed in § 2). <lb/>For X sufficiently close to i, the map R^-i: W -&gt;H is bounded: for each f e W is the <lb/>boundary value of a holomorphic section of J §f over X \ X^, and (by assumption) <lb/>the trivialization 9 extends over some open set containing X^. Thus R^-i simply <lb/>assigns to /eW the function z}-&gt;f{\z), i.e. / evaluated on a circle slightly inside the <lb/>boundary of Xo. Since R^ : H_ —^H_ is compact, the projection W -&gt;H_ is too. <lb/>It follows easily that the projection W -&gt; H+ has closed range. <lb/>It remains to show that the projection W -&gt; H+ is a Fredholm operator of the <lb/>index stated. We shall prove a more precise statement: the kernel and cokernel of the <lb/>orthogonal projection W -&gt; zH^. are H°(X, oS?) and H^X, JS?) respectively. Let Uo <lb/>and Uoo be open sets ofX containing Xo and X^, and let Uooo == Uo n U^,. Because <lb/>Uo,Uoo, and Uooo are Stein varieties, we can calculate the cohomology of X with <lb/></body>

			<page> 36 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<body> coefficients in any coherent sheaf from the covering {UQ, Uoo}; in particular, we have <lb/>an exact sequence <lb/>o -&gt; HO(X, ^ -&gt; »Sf(Uo) ® oSf(UJ -&gt; JS^(UoJ -&gt; H^X, ^) -&gt; o, <lb/> where oSf(U) denotes the sections of oSf over a subset U of X. Taking the direct limit <lb/>of this as UQ and U^ shrink to Xo and Xoo gives the exact sequence <lb/> o -&gt; H°(X, Ji?) -&gt; JS?(Xo) C Ji?(XJ -&gt; JS?(S <lb/> 1 ) -&gt; H^X, JSf) -&gt; o. <lb/> Since S is torsion free, its sections over X^ or X^ are determined by their restrictions <lb/>to S <lb/> 1 <lb/> ; thus we can identify oSf(Xo) and oS^(Xoo) with subspaces of the space J §?(S <lb/> 1 <lb/> ) of <lb/>real analytic functions on S <lb/> 1 <lb/> . The two middle terms in the above exact sequence then <lb/>become <lb/>W^e^H^-^H^, <lb/>the map being the inclusion on the first factor and minus the inclusion on the second <lb/>factor (we write V^ for the analytic functions in a subspace V ofH). The kernel and <lb/>cokernel of this map are the same as those of the projection W^ -&gt; ^H^, so we have <lb/>only to see that the kernel and cokernel of this do not change when we pass to the com-<lb/>pletions W -&gt; zH^. But a function in the kernel of this last projection is the common L <lb/> 2 <lb/> boundary value of holomorphic functions defined inside and outside S <lb/> 1 <lb/> , hence it must <lb/>be analytic: thus the two kernels coincide. That the cokernels coincide too follows <lb/>easily from the fact that W -&gt;H^_ has closed range. <lb/>The same argument shows that the kernel and cokernel of the orthogonal <lb/>projection W-&gt;H+ can be identified with H°(X, JS^) and H^X, o5^), where <lb/>o §^ = j §f® [— x^~\ is the sheaf whose sections are sections of JSf that vanish at x^. <lb/> In particular, W is transverse if and only if we have H°(X, - §^,) == H^X, JS^) = o. <lb/>For readers of[i6, 21], we note that it is the sheaf J §^, rather than o §^, that is considered <lb/>in those papers. <lb/>We are mainly interested in spaces of virtual dimension zero^ by (6.1), these <lb/>arise from sheaves with )c(°^) == <lb/> I -If &quot; §^ is a line bundle, the Riemann-Roch theorem <lb/>shows that its degree is then the arithmetic genus of X. <lb/>Combining the construction above with that of § 5, we obtain a solution to the <lb/>KP equations for each set of data (X, ^, z, oSf, &lt;p) with /(oS^) == i. This construction <lb/>is essentially the same as that of Krichever [10, n]. To be more precise, Krichever <lb/>considers the case where X is non-singular, and starts off from a positive divisor <lb/> Q = {Pi, ..., P^}, with P^ e X, of degree g equal to the genus of X. He assumes <lb/>that no P, is the point ^, and that Q is non-special. <lb/> c( Non-special &quot; means that the <lb/>line bundle oS? corresponding to Q has a unique (up to a constant multiple) holomorphic <lb/>section, which vanishes precisely at the points P^; this section therefore defines a trivia-<lb/>lization of oS? over the complement of{P^}, in particular over a neighbourhood of x^. <lb/></body>

			<page> 37 <lb/> 38 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEMESEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body>If all the points P, lie outside the disc X^, we can use this trivialization $ our construction <lb/>then reduces exactly to Krichever&apos;s. <lb/>The correspondence that we have described between algebro-geometric data and <lb/>subspaces ofH is obviously not one to one, for the following reason: suppose n : X&apos; -&gt;• X <lb/>is a map which is a birational equivalence (that is, intuitively, the curve X is obtained <lb/>from X&apos; by making it <lb/> (c more singular <lb/> 9? ). Then we obtain the same space W from a <lb/>sheaf ^&apos; on X&apos; and from its direct image JSf == -^(oSf) on X. We shall avoid this <lb/>ambiguity by agreeing to consider only maximal torsion free sheaves on X, that is ones <lb/>that do not arise as the direct image of a sheaf on a less singular curve. A perhaps more <lb/>illuminating description of them is as follows. Recall (see [7]) that the rank i torsion <lb/>free sheaves over X (of some fixed Euler characteristic) form a compact moduli space M <lb/>on which the generalized Jacobian of X (the line bundles of degree zero) acts by tensor <lb/>product. We claim that the maximal torsion free sheaves form precisely the part of M <lb/>on which the Jacobian acts freely. Indeed, if JSf is any rank i torsion free sheaf on X <lb/>and L is a line bundle of degree zero, then giving an isomorphism L ® oSf ^ jSf is equi-<lb/>valent to giving an isomorphism L ^ Hom{S, J §f) $ but Hom^, ,Sf) is just the structure <lb/>sheaf of the <lb/> (( least singular <lb/> 5? curve X&apos; such that JSf is the direct image of a sheaf on X&apos;, <lb/>hence it is 0^ exactly when oS^ is maximal. Obviously, any line bundle is a maximal <lb/>torsion free sheaf; and if all the singularities of X are planar, these are the only ones, <lb/>for in that case (and only in that case) M is an irreducible variety containing the line <lb/>bundles as a Zariski open subset (see [34]). However, in general there are many maximal <lb/>torsion free sheaves that are not line bundles: we shall meet simple examples in § 7. <lb/> Proposition 6.2. — The construction described above sets up a one to one correspondence <lb/>between isomorphism classes of data (X, JSf, ^, z, &lt;p), with ,Sf maximal, and certain spaces <lb/> WeGr. <lb/> Proof. — Let W be the space arising from data (X, jSf, x^, z, 9) with S maximal. <lb/>We have to show how to reconstruct all of this data (up to isomorphism) from W alone. <lb/>Let us recall from (2.6) the definition of the dense subspace W^ of W, consisting of <lb/>all elements of finite order. Clearly W^ can be identified with the space of algebraic <lb/>sections of oSf over X \ { x^}. If A is the coordinate ring of the affine curve X \ { x^ }, <lb/>then W^ is the rank one torsion free A-module corresponding to the sheaf oSf restricted <lb/>to X \{^}. On the other hand, let A^ be the ring of analytic functions/ on S <lb/> 1 such <lb/>that /. W^ C W^. Clearly A^ is an algebra containing A (if we identify functions <lb/>in A with their restrictions to S <lb/> 1 <lb/> ), and W^ is a faithful A^-module. As W is torsion-<lb/>free and of rank one as a module over A, it follows that A^ can be identified with an <lb/>integral subring of the quotient field of A. This means that Spec(A^) is a curve of the <lb/>form X&apos;\{^} (with X&apos; complete) projecting birationally on to X\{^}; and so <lb/>if oSf is maximal we must have A^ == A. Thus we have reconstructed from W the <lb/>curve X, the point x^, and the restriction of S to X\{^}. Finally, the inclusion <lb/></body>

			<page> 38 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<body> W^ C C[z] C H_ defines a trivialization of JS? over X^ \{x^} (and hence the exten-<lb/>sion of JS? to X); for if | ^ | &gt; i then evaluation at ^ defines a map W^ -&gt; C which <lb/>induces an isomorphism of the fibre of oS? at ^ with C. (That is clear, because the fibre <lb/>is canonically W^/mW^, where m C A^ is the ideal of functions that vanish at ^.) <lb/> Remark 6.3. — The definition of A^ makes sense for any W e Gr. In general, <lb/>however, it will be trivial, i.e. A^ == C. (This is clearly the case, for example, when W <lb/>is the subspace of codimension one in H_^. which was described in (2. io).) The spaces <lb/>W e Gr which arise from algebro-geometrical data are precisely those such that A^. <lb/>contains an element of each sufficiently large order, or, equivalently, such that the <lb/>A^y-module W^ has rank i. That follows at once from the preceding discussion, <lb/>in view of the fact that the coordinate rings A of irreducible curves of the form X \ {x^} <lb/> (where X is complete and x^ is a non-singular point) are characterized as integral <lb/>domains simply by the existence of a filtration <lb/> C = Ao C A! C Ag C ... C A <lb/> such that <lb/>(i) <lb/>A,.A^CA^., <lb/>(ii) <lb/>dim(AJA^_i) &lt;_ i for all ^, and <lb/>(iii) <lb/>dim(A^/A^i) = i for all large k. <lb/>Remark 6.4. — We should point out that for any W e Gr the construction of §5 <lb/>defines a realization of A^-as a commutative ring of differential operators. More pre-<lb/>cisely, the proof of (5.11) shows that for any / e A^ there is a unique differential ope-<lb/>rator L(/) such that <lb/> H/)^-/^)^. <lb/> If WeGr^, then ^eA^, and L^) == L^. In general, the order of the ope-<lb/>rator L(jf) is equal to the order ofy. <lb/> Remark 6.5. — As we saw in § 5, a change of local parameter z i-&gt; cz {c a non-zero <lb/>constant) corresponds to acting on the solution to the KP hierarchy by the scaling trans-<lb/>formation. Thus the condition that the validity of the parameter z should extend up <lb/>to [ z | == i is not a serious restriction in our theory. <lb/> Remark 6.6. — The solution to the KP hierarchy does not depend on the choice <lb/>of trivialization &lt;p: for a different choice of cp would just multiply W by a function of <lb/>the form CQ + q z~ <lb/> 1  + -• . (with CQ =t= o), which, as we know, does not change the <lb/>solution. Even the space W does not change if we replace 9 by c^ where c is a non-zero <lb/>constant; that does not contradict (6.2), because the quintuples of data (X, x^, z, J?, c^) <lb/> for different c 4= o are obviously isomorphic. <lb/></body>

			<page> 39 <lb/> 40 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEME SEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> Remark 6.7. — We get a solution to the n-th KdV hierarchy (i.e. W e Gr^) if <lb/>and only if z <lb/> n e A^; that is, if the local parameter z is such that ^ extends to a mero-<lb/>morphic function on X with no singularities except for the n&apos;th order pole at x^. For <lb/>fixed n, this of course imposes a restriction on which pairs (X, x^) can occur: for example <lb/>if n == 2 then X must be hyperelliptic and x^ must be a Weierstrass point. <lb/> Remark 6.8. — An important part of Krichever&apos;s theory is the observation that <lb/>the KdV (or KP) flows correspond to straight line motion on the Jacobian of X. That <lb/>is easily seen from our point of view as follows. For each g e F^, let L be the line <lb/>bundle obtained by taking trivial bundles over XQ and Xoo and glueing them by the <lb/>transition function g on (an open neighbourhood of) S <lb/> 1 <lb/> . Thus Ly comes equipped with <lb/>a trivialization &lt;p^ over Xoo. The natural action of F^. on Gr corresponds to the fol-<lb/>lowing action on the data (X, x^, z, oS^, 9): g e I\ acts trivially on the first three <lb/>components, and on (oSf, 9) by tensoring with (L^, (py). The action of I\ on solutions <lb/>to the KP hierarchy thus corresponds simply to S h&gt; oSf®L^. The assertion about <lb/>straight line motion is now clear in view of the following result. <lb/> Proposition 6.9. — The assignment g \-&gt; Lg defines a surjective homomorphism from I\ <lb/> to the generalized Jacobian of X (which consists of all holomorphic line bundles on X of degree <lb/>zero). <lb/> Proof. — If L is a line bundle on X then L | X^ and L | X^ are trivial, for all <lb/>bundles on affine curves are analytically trivial, and X^ and X^ are contained in affine <lb/>open sets of X. So L = L^ for some holomorphic function S <lb/> 1  -&gt; C <lb/> x whose winding <lb/>number is the degree ofL. We can change g by any element of F_ without affecting Lg&apos;y <lb/> and so if g has winding number zero we can choose it in I\. <lb/> Example <lb/> Let us return briefly to the subspace W == Wp ^ e Gr^ which was introduced <lb/>in § 3 and discussed further in § 5. In this case A^ consists of all polynomials / in z <lb/> such that f{— pi) •==f{pi) for each i. This is the coordinate ring of the affine curve <lb/>whose completion Xp is obtained from the Riemann sphere by identifying the point p^ <lb/> with — pi for each i: Xp is a rational curve with m double points. If we take ^ === z <lb/> 2 <lb/> and 7) == z{^ — p^) ... (^ — p <lb/> 2 ^) as generators of A^ then the equation of Xp is <lb/> ^^(S-^ <lb/> 2 ...^--^) <lb/> 2 . <lb/> We remarked in § 5 that the orbit of Wp ^ under I\ consists of all Wp ^, where <lb/> (JL runs through {C <lb/> X <lb/> ) <lb/> m . This conforms with (6.9), as (C^™ is the generalized Jacobian <lb/>ofXp. <lb/> Commuting differential operators <lb/> Our last goal in this section is to point out that our results lead directly to a proof <lb/>of the so-called &quot; Painlev^ property <lb/> 95 of the stationary KdV equations. Since these <lb/></body>

			<page> 40 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>41 <lb/></page>

			<body> have the form [P, L] = o, the result can be formulated as a statement about commuting <lb/>differential operators. <lb/> Theorem 6.10. — Let L = W + u,_^ D&quot;-<lb/> 2 + . . . + u, be an ordinary differential <lb/>operator whose coefficients u, are defined and smooth in a neighbourhood I of the origin in R. Sup-<lb/>pose that there exists a differential operator P of order m relatively prime to n that commutes with L. <lb/> Then the functions u, extend to meromorphic functions on the whole complex plane, with poles of <lb/>order at most n — i, so that all the finite singular points ofL are regular. <lb/> Note that the condition about relatively prime orders is obviously essential: if <lb/>we omitted it there would be trivial counterexamples to the theorem where L == P <lb/>or more generally L and P are both polynomials in some operator of lower order. <lb/> It is easy to see (for example by conjugating L into D&quot; by a formal integral operator <lb/>as in § 4) that any operator P that commutes with L is some linear combination <lb/> N <lb/> P=S^L^ <lb/> o <lb/>of the operators P,. occuring in the definition of the n-th KdV hierarchy. For each <lb/>fixed sequence of constants {c,}, the stationary KdV equation [P, L] == o is a system <lb/>of ordinary differential equations for the coefficients {^, . .., ^_a} of L. Let us call <lb/>such an equation (or the corresponding P) admissible if there is some index r relatively <lb/>prime to n with ^ =t= o. For example, if n is prime, then every non-trivial stationary <lb/>KdV equation is admissible. If P is admissible, then the algebra generated by L and <lb/>P contains operators of order relatively prime to 77. Thus (6.10) can be formulated as <lb/>follows: every solution {u,} of an admissible stationary KdV equation is of the kind stated in the <lb/>conclusion of (6.10). <lb/>Theorem 6.10 will follow from (5.18) if we show that every operator L satisfying <lb/>the hypotheses is of the form L^ for some W e Gr^ arising from an algebraic curve. <lb/>This is well known, and is proved in [16, 21]; however, for completeness we give a self-<lb/>contained proof, following the approach of Burchnall and Chaundy [4]. <lb/> Proposition 6.11. — If L and P are commuting differential operators as in (6.10), then: <lb/> (i) There is an irreducible polynomial F e C[^, T]] of the form <lb/> F = ^ + ... 4= ^ <lb/> such that F(L, P) = o. <lb/>(ii) For all but a finite number of points (X, pi) of the affine curve Xp whose equation is <lb/> F(^ ^) = o there is a unique common eigenf unction 9^ of L and P such that &lt;p^ (o) == i: <lb/> ^X, (z <lb/> = ^PX, v. ^ <lb/> ^X, (x == ^&lt;PX, ^ • <lb/> For any x e I, ^^{x) is a meromorphic function on the curve Xp. <lb/></body>

			<page> 41 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> 6 <lb/></note>

			<page> 42 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEME SEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> (iii) For x e I the formal Baker functions ^(^ <lb/> &lt;2: <lb/> ) <lb/> an ^ ^p(^ <lb/> z ) °f^ <lb/> a ^ P ^A converge <lb/>for large z^ and then <lb/> ^(^^) <lb/> === ^p^^ <lb/> /m ) <lb/> :== 9x,.W. <lb/> (Notice that X <lb/> 17 &quot; &lt;z/z^ pi <lb/> 1 <lb/> ^ ^r^ local parameters at the point at infinity of XpJ <lb/> We begin by proving assertion (i). For any X e C let V\ be the TZ-dimensional <lb/>vector space of solutions of L&lt;p == 7.9 on I. A basis for V\ is given by the func-<lb/>tions 9i(^, X) for o&lt;_i&lt;n such that 9^(0, X) =8^. Notice that for any &lt;peV^ <lb/>and any k we have <lb/> 9^(0) =YAiW ^(o) <lb/>i=o <lb/> where the ^(X) are polynomials independent of 9. <lb/>The operator P maps V^ into itself. In terms of the basis {9^} the action of P <lb/>on V\ is given by an n X n matrix P^ of polynomials in X. Let F(X, pi) be the charac-<lb/>teristic polynomial det(|ji — P^). It is not hard to see that F(X, pi) is a polynomial <lb/>of degree m in X: in fact one can show that (up to sign) it is the same as the polynomial <lb/>obtained by reversing the roles of P and L in the construction. Thus F has the form <lb/>stated in (i). Consider the differential operator F(L, P). There is at least one solu-<lb/>tion of F(L, P) 9 == o in each V^. As a differential operator can have only finitely <lb/>many linearly independent solutions, this implies that F(L, P) ^= o. But the same <lb/>argument shows that if G is any factor of F then G(L, P) === o; so F must be a power <lb/>of an irreducible polynomial. As F(X, [L) contains the monomials X&quot; <lb/> 1 and (JL^ the power <lb/>must divide both n and m. But these are relatively prime, so F must be irreducible. <lb/>We next prove assertion (ii). Because the polynomial F is irreducible there are, <lb/>for all but finitely many values of X, n distinct solutions \L of F(X, pi) = o. For each <lb/>of these values of ^ there is (up to a scalar multiple) a unique eigenvector &lt;p^ ^ of P^ <lb/>in V\ with eigenvalue (JL We can choose it so that its coordinates with respect to the <lb/>basis {9 i} ofV\ (i.e. its derivatives at o) are polynomials in X and [L: for example we can <lb/>take the coordinates to be the cofactors of any row of the matrix pi — P^. The value <lb/>of 9^ ^ at o cannot vanish identically, for the eigenvectors of P^ must span V\ for almost <lb/>allX. This permits us to normalize 9^^ so that 9^(0) == i, except at a finite number <lb/>of points (X, pi). The derivatives 9^(0) will then be rational functions of X and [L. <lb/> To see that 9^(A:) is meromorphic on Xp we observe that <lb/> 9x,,W-^9^(o)9,(^X). <lb/> (Note that 9^^, X) is an entire function of X.) <lb/>To prove (iii) we first observe that not only do we have L^^ = <lb/> zn  ^L by defi-<lb/>nition, but also P^L == ^) ^L5 where [L {z) is a formal power series belonging to the <lb/></body>

			<page> 42 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>43 <lb/></page>

			<body> N <lb/> field C((^-<lb/> 1 )) of formal series of the form S a, z\ To see this, choose K as in § 4 <lb/> i == — oo <lb/> so that K^EK == D^ Then K.^PK commutes with D^ and so must be a formal <lb/>pseudodifferential operator ^(D) with constant coefficients. Thus PK = Ku(D). <lb/>Applying both sides to ^ gives P^ == ^) ^, as Ke^ == ^-<lb/>Now we adopt the following point of view. The operators L and P can be thought <lb/>of as acting on the vector space of jets of functions (of A:) at the origin: in other words <lb/>we replace functions 9 by sequences {(p^o) }^o. Consider the vector space J of <lb/>formal jets whose components 9^(0) belong to the field C{{z~ <lb/> 1 )) of formal series. The <lb/>operator L — z&quot; acts on J, and has an ^-dimensional kernel J^ spanned by the jets <lb/>of the functions 9^, z&quot;) already mentioned. (Recall that 9^(0, z^ is a polynomial <lb/>in ^ <lb/> n .) Now formal series of the form e^ S^) z~^ define jets in J, and the jet of ^ <lb/>belongs toj^. Furthermore P preserves J^, and P^ == (^) k- On the other hand <lb/>we already know that the unique eigenvectors of P in J^, when normalized at o, are <lb/>the jets of 9^, where X = z^ and ^ runs through the n roots of F(X, ^) == o, which <lb/>are distinct for large X. This proves that ^\o, z) == 9^(0) for some point <lb/> {z^^z)) e Xp, and hence that the series ^(o, z) and pt(^) converge for large z. <lb/> In the preceding discussion the role of the origin could have been played by any <lb/>point XQ e I. Thus we can conclude that if a formal Baker function ^^ (^ ^) is cal-<lb/>culated at XQ then <lb/> ^o^O, ^ - 9^0) ^ ?.,^o)-<lb/> 1 <lb/> . <lb/> (The factor ^o <lb/> 3 P^ix^o)&quot; <lb/> 1 on the right occurs because ^,a; <lb/> is normalized by <lb/> ^L,x^o,z) ==^o <lb/> 2 .) The space W^ e Gr^ defined by ^o is &quot;therefore related to <lb/>the space W defined by 4&apos;L by <lb/> W <lb/>— /,a;o <lb/> 2 m <lb/>^y ^~&quot; <lb/> 1 W <lb/>&quot;aso ~ <lb/>r^tJi^^oJ <lb/> vv  * <lb/> But ^&quot;^^^^(^o) does not vanish for large z, and so (after scaling, if necessary) <lb/>it defines an element y of the group F_. Thus W^ and W define the same meromorphic <lb/>differential operator. The jets of its coefficients coincide with those of L at XQ and o <lb/>respectively. This proves (iii). <lb/> Remark 6.12. — Notice that we have proved that L arises by Krichever&apos;s construc-<lb/>tion from the curve Xp and the torsion-free sheaf JSf whose space of sections over Xp \ { oo } <lb/>is the space W^ generated by the 9^(0). In particular, this proves (6.10). It is <lb/>not hard to show that the fibre of S? at any point (X, \L) of Xp is canonically isomorphic <lb/>to the joint (X, (Ji)-eigenspace of L and P. <lb/> Remark 6.13. — We believe that theorem 6.10 is <lb/> &lt;c well known &quot; (except possibly <lb/>for the assertion about the orders of the poles), but our proof seems to be the first complete <lb/>one available. Krichever [10] noted that &quot;most <lb/> 55 of the solutions (that is, the ones <lb/>coming from non-singular curves X) of the stationary KdV equations are globally <lb/></body>

			<page> 43 <lb/> 44 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEME SEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> meromorphic; our proof is essentially the same as his except that he used the theta func-<lb/>tion of X where we use the more general r-function (see § 9 below). It might be inte-<lb/>resting to give a direct algebro-geometric proof of the theorem, presumably by introducing <lb/>suitable &quot;theta functions&quot; for singular curves. However, we note that one would <lb/>have to define a theta function, not merely for each singular curve, but for each orbit <lb/>of the Jacobian of such a curve acting on the space of maximal torsion free sheaves. <lb/> 7. Rational Curves <lb/> We recall from § 2 that Gr^ is the subspace ofGr consisting of spaces W such that <lb/> pH^CWCq-<lb/> 1 <lb/> ^ <lb/> for some polynomials p, q, and that p and q can be chosen so that all their roots lie in <lb/>the region | z \ &lt; i. <lb/> Proposition 7.1. — The construction described in the preceding section gives a one to one <lb/>correspondence between spaces W e Gr^ and isomorphism classes of data (X, JSf, x^, z, 9) <lb/> as in (6.2) such that <lb/> (i) X is a rational curve <lb/> (ii) z is a rational parameter on X <lb/>(iii) 9 extends to an algebraic f realization of3? over some Zariski open set containing the disc X^. <lb/>Before giving the proof, we clarify the term <lb/> (( rational parameter &quot;. The curve X <lb/>being rational means that there is an algebraic map / from the Riemann sphere to X <lb/>which is an isomorphism outside the inverse image of the singular set of X. We can <lb/>choose/so that /(oo) = x^. By a rational parameter z on X we mean the inverse of <lb/>such a map/in some neighbourhood of x^: note that its domain in fact extends to the <lb/>whole non-singular part of X. Note also that the rational parameter is uniquely deter-<lb/>mined up to a linear change z h&gt; az + b: for any two of them differ by a birational, <lb/>hence genuine, automorphism of the Riemann sphere preserving oo, which must be <lb/>linear. <lb/> Proof of (7.1). <lb/>(i) Let W e Gr^, and let p and q be polynomials as above. Let W^ and A^ <lb/>be as in the proof of (6.2). Clearly we have <lb/> (7.2) <lb/> ^C^CW^C^C^], <lb/> from which it follows easily that pqC[z] CA^C {pq)~ <lb/> 1  C[&gt;]. Since A^ is a ring, we <lb/>have in fact <lb/> pqC[z]CA^CC[z]. <lb/> Thus the inclusion ofA^ in C[z] induces an isomorphism of quotient fields; that shows <lb/>that the curve X\{^}=SpecA^ is rational, and that z is a rational parameter <lb/></body>

			<page> 44 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>45 <lb/></page>

			<body> on X. From (7.2) it is clear that the A^y-module W^, and hence also the corresponding <lb/>sheaf JSf on X, has rank i. It remains to prove (iii). Let ZQ e C; then evaluation at <lb/> ZQ gives a map e(Zo) : W^ -&gt; C which is defined provided that ZQ is not a root of y, <lb/>and non-zero provided that ZQ is not a root of p. Let Pg be the point of X corresponding <lb/>to ZQ, and let m C A^ be its maximal ideal. Then e{Zo) defines a map from the fibre <lb/>W^/mW^ of jy over Pp to C, which is an isomorphism provided that ZQ satisfies the <lb/>two conditions above and that Po lies in the open set of X over which JSf is a line bundle. <lb/>That completes the proof that W gives rise to algebro-geometric data of the kind stated <lb/>in the proposition. <lb/>(ii) Conversely, suppose we are given data (X, oSf, x^, z, 9) of the kind listed <lb/>in the proposition: we have to see that the corresponding W belongs to Gr^. Let B C X <lb/>be the finite set of points over which 9 is not defined. If necessary we enlarge B to <lb/>include all the singular points of X. Let {z^ .. .5 Zy}C C be the inverse image of B <lb/>under the map f: S <lb/> 2  -&gt;• X whose inverse is the parameter z. Then we can identify <lb/>the sections of JS^ over X \ B with the sections of a trivialized line bundle over <lb/>S <lb/> 2 ^-^, ..., Zy}. Thus W^, which is the space of sections of oSf over X\{.^}, is <lb/>identified with a subspace of the space F(^, ..., Zy; — v^, .. .3 — v^) of rational func-<lb/>tions of z that are holomorphic except for poles of prescribed orders v, at the points ^. <lb/>More precisely, W^ is the subspace of F(^, — v^) consisting of all functions whose <lb/>Laurent series at the points ^ satisfy some finite set of linear conditions. These conditions <lb/>are certainly satisfied by all polynomials that vanish to suitably high orders ^ at the <lb/>points z^. It follows that if we set p = Tl{z — z^y q = Tl{z — ^) <lb/> vt , then we have <lb/> pC^CW^Cq-<lb/> 1 <lb/> ^]. <lb/> Passing to the L <lb/> 2 closures, we find ptl+ C W C y&quot; <lb/> 1 <lb/> !!^., as required. <lb/>Next recall that Grg is the subspace of Gr^ consisting of spaces W for which the <lb/>polynomials p and q can be taken to be powers of z. If we follow through the above <lb/>proof in that case, we obtain the following. <lb/> Proposition 7.3. — The construction described in  § 6 gives a one to one correspondence between <lb/>spaces W e Gr^ and isomorphism classes of data (X, x^, z, oS^, 9) as in (6.2) such that <lb/> (i) X is a rational curve with just one irreducible (i.e. cusp-like) singularity <lb/> (ii) z is a rational parameter on X such that the singular point XQ corresponds to z == o <lb/>(iii) 9 extends to an algebraic trivialization of S over the whole non-singular part X \{^o} q/&apos;X. <lb/> The term <lb/> &lt;c irreducible <lb/> 3? in (i) means that when we resolve the singularity we <lb/>still get only one point, so that z is in fact a bijection between X and the Riemann sphere. <lb/>Note that z and 9 are now both uniquely determined up to multiplication by non-zero <lb/>constants. The fact that 9 is unique means that the correspondence between spaces <lb/>in GTQ and solutions to the KP hierarchy is one to one. Indeed it is easy to see directly <lb/></body>

			<page> 45 <lb/> 46 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEMESEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> that if W e Gio and y is a function of the form i + ^ z~ <lb/> 1  + . . ., then yW cannot <lb/>belong to Grg unless y <lb/> = I * <lb/>The subspaces W e Gr^ provide many simple examples of maximal torsion free <lb/>sheaves that are not line bundles. Indeed let W = Hg, where S C Z is a set of virtual <lb/>cardinal zero. Then W e Gro, and we claim that the corresponding maximal torsion <lb/>free sheaf is seldom a line bundle. Here W^ is the vector space spanned by {^^^g. <lb/>Let R be the semi-group of strictly positive integers r such that S + r ^ S. Then A^ <lb/>is the algebra spanned by i and {^reR? and the maximal ideal m of A^y corresponding <lb/>to the singular point z = o is spanned by {-s^gR. The dimension of the fibre <lb/>W^/mW^ of the sheaf J §^ over the singular point is thus the number of elements of <lb/>S \ S&apos;3 where we have set <lb/> S&apos;= U (S+r). <lb/> rGB <lb/> Unless this number is i, the maximal torsion free sheaf oS? is not a line bundle. The <lb/>simplest example is when S == {— i, o, 2, 3, . . . }; then R =={3,4, 5, . .. } and <lb/>S&apos; == { 2, 3, ...}. In this case the dimension of the singular fibre of oS^ is 2. Note that <lb/>since the algebra A^y = C[-2: <lb/> 3 <lb/> , -? <lb/> 4 <lb/> , z <lb/> 5 ] needs more than two generators, the singularity <lb/>here is not planar: this conforms with our observation in § 6 that in the planar case every <lb/>maximal torsion free sheaf is a line bundle. <lb/> The case n == 2 <lb/> In general, the isomorphism classes of data listed in (7.3) are hard to classify. <lb/>However, if we confine ourselves to the case ofGr^, then many simplifications take place: <lb/>perhaps the most important is that the orbits of the group I\ in Gr^ coincide with the <lb/>cells in the cell decomposition described in § 2. Here we give a brief description of the <lb/>situation, leaving most of the (easy) proofs to the reader. For simplicity, what follows <lb/>will refer only to the component of Gr^ consisting of spaces of virtual dimension zero. <lb/>We recall from § 2 that Gr^ has a cell decomposition with cells indexed by the <lb/>sets S e y such that S + 2 C S. It is easy to see that the only such S are the sets S^ <lb/>given by <lb/>Sfe=={--^ —k + 2, —k +4, ...,^,A + 1,^+2, ...}. <lb/>We denote by Cj^ the corresponding cell in Gr^; it has complex dimension k, and consists <lb/>of all W of virtual dimension zero such that z^ H^. CW C z~ <lb/> k  H^. and k is the smallest <lb/>number with this property. It is not hard to see directly that these W form a A-dimen-<lb/>sional cell: such a space W contains elements w of the form <lb/> ^ = Z-^ + 04 Z-^ <lb/> 1  + . . . + 02,_, ^-<lb/> 1 , <lb/> and {w, z <lb/> 2 w, ..., ^ <lb/> k <lb/> ~~&apos; <lb/> 2&gt; w} is then a basis for W/-^ H+. Thus w determines W uniquely. <lb/>The converse is not true; however, the coefficients a, can be normalized in various ways, <lb/>of which the most convenient for us is the following. <lb/></body>

			<page> 46 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>47 <lb/></page>

			<body> Lemma 7.4. — Each W e G^ contains a unique element w of the form <lb/>w = 2-^ exp(^i z + ^2 ^ + • • . + ^ ^ <lb/> -1 )-<lb/>The correspondence W&lt;-^ (^i, . . ., a^ gives us an explicit isomorphism of the <lb/>cell Cj, with C^; the centre of the cell (corresponding to the origin in (?) is the space Hg , <lb/>which we shall denote simply by H^. It is clear from (7.4) that the subgroup { exp (t^ ~ <lb/> 1 )} <lb/>of I\ acts on G^ by translating the r-th coordinate a^ In particular, we see that C^ <lb/>is precisely the orbit of H^; under I\. <lb/>It is interesting to see how this description of the orbits of I\ fits in with the algebro-<lb/>geometric one implicit in (7.3). The main points are as follows. First, if W = H^ <lb/>then Aw == C[&gt; <lb/> 2 <lb/> , ^ <lb/> +1 ] == A^, say. Let X^ == (Spec A^) u {^} be the corresponding <lb/>complete curve, and let J^ be the Jacobian of X^ (parametrizing line bundles of degree <lb/>zero). If we use the point x^ to identify the spaces of line bundles of different degrees, <lb/>then the torsion free sheaf over X^ corresponding to the space H^ is the neutral element <lb/>inj^; indeed, it is clear that H^ = ^A^. Hence the orbit of H^ under I\, that is, <lb/>the cell C^, can be identified with the Jacobian J^. The fact that the cells G^ <lb/>exhaust Gr^ implies that the curves X^ are the only ones that arise from a space <lb/>W eGr^, and also that every maximal torsion free sheaf over one of the curves X^ <lb/>is a line bundle. Both of these facts can be seen directly: it is easy to show that the A^ <lb/>are the only subalgebras of C[z\ containing z <lb/> 2  and also an odd power of z; and, as we <lb/>have observed before, the assertion about the sheaves is true for any curve with planar <lb/>singularities (a simple proof that covers our present case (X degenerate hyperelliptic) <lb/>can be found in [8]; in fact the assertion for singularities of the type y <lb/> n == y^ is implicitly <lb/>contained in [4 (c)]). To see directly that J^ is a ^-dimensional cell, we can use the <lb/>exponential sheaf theory exact sequence: since H^X^;, Z) = o, this gives an isomorphism <lb/>HP(X^, 0) ^ Jj,. The dimension k of the vector space H^X^, (P) can be calculated <lb/>as the number of <lb/> c( gaps &quot; in the ring A^, that is, the number of positive integers r such <lb/>that Aj^ does not contain a polynomial of order r. The algebras Aj, are invariant under <lb/> z}-&gt;cz, which implies that the pairs (X^, cz) for different c 4= o are isomorphic, so <lb/>that the scaling transformations can be viewed as flows on the Jacobians J^. Indeed, <lb/>from (7.4) we see that the scaling flow on the cell C^ is given by <lb/> RX^I,...,^) =^-<lb/> l ^...,X-<lb/> 2fc+l ^). <lb/> Finally, it is interesting to consider the closure Cj, of the cell C^: this the union of <lb/>all the cells C,. with r &lt;_ k. Alternatively, C^ consists of all W e Gr^ such that <lb/>A^ W C W. Hence each point of Cj, determines a torsion free sheaf (in general not <lb/>maximal) over X^; in fact we get a bijective map G^ -&gt; M^, where Mj, is the moduli <lb/>space of rank one torsion free sheaves of some fixed Euler characteristic over X^; (see [7]). <lb/>The closed cell C^ is an algebraic variety, for it is an algebraic subset (given by the condi-<lb/>tion ^WCW) of the Grassmannian of A-dimensional subspaces of z~ <lb/> k &apos;H.^|z <lb/> JC &apos;H.^, <lb/> and it is fairly clear that the above construction gives us an algebraic family of sheaves <lb/></body>

			<page> 47 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEMESEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> over X^: that implies that the bijection C^ -&gt; Mj, is an algebraic map. Unfortunately, <lb/>we cannot assert that it is an isomorphism of algebraic varieties: for example, C^ is a <lb/>one-dimensional projective space (non-singular), whereas M^ is isomorphic to the <lb/>curve Xi, which has a cusp. (We do not know a precise reference for this fact, but <lb/>P. Deligne and T. Ekedahl have kindly pointed out to us that it follows easily from (2.6.1) <lb/>in [24].) In general, we expect that C^ is the normalization of M^ The inclusion <lb/> \ <lb/> c A^_i induces a map X^ -&gt; X^, and hence (taking the direct image of sheaves) <lb/>a map M^_^ -^M^. This map corresponds to the inclusion C^C C^, and iden-<lb/>tifies M/,_i with the boundary of M/,, that is, with the space of torsion free sheaves <lb/>over X^; that are not line bundles. <lb/>The solutions to the KdV equations corresponding to the points of Gr^ have <lb/>been much studied (see [i, 2]): the cell C^ corresponds to the solutions to the KdV hie-<lb/>rarchy flowing out of the initial value <lb/> u{x, o, o, ...) == — k(k + i)/x <lb/> 2 . <lb/> (This is the initial value defined by the space H/,, as will become clear in § 8, when we <lb/>describe the r-functions of the spaces Hg.) It is known that these exhaust the rational <lb/>solutions to the KdV hierarchy that vanish at x = oo. <lb/> 8. The T-function and Schur functions <lb/> We have already given explicit formulae (3.4) and (3.5) for the T-function as <lb/>an infinite determinant. It is useful for some purposes to make the formula even more <lb/>explicit by expanding the determinants in a certain way: the result is that the T-function <lb/>can be written as an infinite linear combination of Schur functions. <lb/>We begin by reviewing the basic definitions concerning partitions and Schur <lb/>functions (for more details see, for example, [13]). By ^partition we mean an infinite <lb/>sequence v == (v^, v^, Vg, . . .) of non-negative integers such that v^ v^ ^&gt;_ ... <lb/>and all except a finite number of the v, are zero. The number | v [ = 2v, is called <lb/>the weight of v. To each partition v there is associated a Schur function F^. This is a <lb/>polynomial with integer coefficients in a sequence of indeterminates (^1,^,^3,...); <lb/>it is homogeneous of weight | v | when h, is given weight i. One way to define it is as <lb/>the r X r determinant <lb/>F,(h) = det(^._^.), (o:&lt;zj^r~i) <lb/>where r is any number sufficiently large so that v, = o for i ^ r. Here it is understood <lb/>that ho = i and h, = o for i&lt; o; it is clear that the value of the determinant does <lb/>not depend on the choice of r. One reason for the importance of Schur functions is <lb/>that they are characters of the general linear groups GL^C): to each partition v there <lb/>corresponds an irreducible representation of GL^C) (for any large N), and its character / &quot; <lb/>is given by ^(A) = F,(h), where <lb/> i +:SA^={det(i -Az)}-\ <lb/></body>

			<page> 48 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>49 <lb/></page>

			<body> that is, the h, are the <lb/> (&lt; complete homogeneous symmetric functions &apos; <lb/> 9 of the eigenvalues <lb/>of the matrix A. In our context, however, the Schur functions arise in a purely formal <lb/>manner, and the representations of GLj^C) do not seem to be relevant. <lb/>Let y^ denote the set of all subsets S C Z of virtual cardinal zero (see § 2); that <lb/>is, y^ consists of all strictly increasing sequences S = {^, ^, s^, . . . } of integers such <lb/>that ^ = i for all except a finite number of indices i. <lb/> Lemma 8.1. — There is a one to one correspondence between elements of y^ and partitions^ <lb/>given by S &lt;-&gt; v where \ == i — s^. <lb/> The proof is trivial. Notice that the weight | v | of a partition is equal to the <lb/>length /&apos;(S) of the corresponding S$ that is, it is the codimension of the stratum Sg of Gr. <lb/> In what follows we shall write Fg for the Schur function of the partition corresponding <lb/>to an element S e ^. <lb/> Recall from § 2 that if S e «?o, then Hg e Gr is the closed subspace of H spanned <lb/>by{^es. <lb/> Proposition 8.2. — Let W == Hg, where S e &lt;S^. Then the ^-function of W is given by <lb/> T^) = Fg(h) <lb/> where we have set <lb/> g-<lb/> 1 <lb/> ^ i +s^. <lb/> 1 <lb/> Proof. — We use the formula (3.4). As an admissible basis for Hg, we choose <lb/> w, = z <lb/> 81  where S = {j-o, ^, jg, . . . }. Also, the map {a, b) : H —H+ is just f\-&gt; {fg~ <lb/> 1 )^., <lb/> where the subscript + denotes orthogonal projection onto H+. Thus if,?&quot; <lb/> 1 is expanded <lb/>as in the statement of the proposition, it follows at once that the matrix of the map <lb/> aw^. + bw_ : H^. -&gt; H^. is <lb/>(^._^) = (A(,_^_^.), {ij eN). <lb/>Since s, == i for large i, this matrix is strictly (that is, with i&apos;s on the diagonal) upper <lb/>triangular apart from a finite block in the top left corner. The matrix of the map <lb/> a&apos;- H^. -&gt;• H^. is strictly upper triangular, so it follows easily that the r-function <lb/>det(w+ + a~ <lb/> 1 bw_) == det aT^^aw^ + bw_) <lb/> is equal to the determinant of this finite block. That proves the proposition. <lb/>Now let W e Gr be any space of virtual dimension zero. Fix an admissible <lb/>basis w = (WQ,W^, . ..) for W. As in § 3, we think of w as a Z x N matrix, using <lb/>the natural basis {^} for H. For each S e eS^, let w^ be the determinant of the <lb/>N X N matrix formed by extracting from w the rows indexed by the numbers s e S; <lb/>that is, if Wj == S^. z\ we set <lb/>^^detWzeSjeN-<lb/></body>

			<page> 49 <lb/> 50 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEMESEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> We call the numbers {w^} the Pliicker coordinates of W: they are homogeneous coordinates <lb/>(a different choice of admissible basis for W multiplies them all by the same non-zero <lb/>constant). As in the finite dimensional case, the Pliicker coordinates can be regarded <lb/>as giving a projective embedding of the Grassmannian (see the appendix § 10 below). <lb/>Notice that IV <lb/> s  is non-zero precisely when W is transverse to H{|-: indeed, w <lb/> 8 is just the <lb/>determinant of the orthogonal projection W—»-Hg with respect to the bases {Wy} <lb/> for W and {z <lb/> 8 : s e S} for Hg. In particular, by (2.5)5 there is a unique S of minimal <lb/>length such that w^ 4= o. If we choose w so that w^ has the form i + (finite rank), <lb/>then the w^ reduce to finite determinants. For example, if W is transverse, we can <lb/>choose w so that w^ == i, and then if we set S \ N = A and N \ S = B we have <lb/> IV <lb/> s  = det(^.)ieA,jeB-<lb/> Proposition 8.3. — The ^-function ofVf is given by <lb/> T^)==S^Fg(h), <lb/>s <lb/> where {w^} are the Pliicker coordinates of W, the sum is taken over all S e &lt;$ <lb/> 1 <lb/> ^, and the variables h^ <lb/>are related to g as in (8.2). <lb/> Proof. — We first observe that if v and w are m X n and n X m matrices respec-<lb/>tively, with n &gt;i m, then we have <lb/> det vw = S^g IV <lb/> s , <lb/> where the sum is taken over all subsets SC{i,2, ..., n} with m elements, ^g is the deter-<lb/>minant formed from the columns of v indexed by the elements of S, and w^ is the deter-<lb/>minant formed from the corresponding rows of w. (This identity simply expresses the <lb/>functoriality of the m-th exterior power.) It is not hard to see that the identity extends <lb/>to a product of infinite matrices, indexed by N X Z and Z X N, of the form <lb/> ^(::) <lb/> where 24 — i, w^. — i, v_ and w_ are all of trace class andS runs through the indexing <lb/>sets S C Z of virtual cardinal zero. <lb/>We apply this to the determinant (3.4) giving the r-function, with <lb/> 04,y_) == (i,fl-<lb/> 1 ^. <lb/> Then IV <lb/> s  is the Pliicker coordinate defined above and yg is the r-function of Hg, which <lb/>we calculated in (8.2). That completes the proof. <lb/>As we saw in § 5, for the application to differential equations we have to write <lb/>the elements of I\ in the form <lb/>^)=exp(S^ <lb/> 1 ) <lb/></body>

			<page> 50 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>51 <lb/></page>

			<body> (we write ^ where we wrote A: in § 5). We shall write r^(t) for the r-function expressed <lb/>in terms of these &quot; coordinates &quot; on I\: to calculate T^(t) from (8.2) or (8.3), we have <lb/>only to substitute the variables ^ for the h^ using the relation <lb/> oo <lb/> oo <lb/> (8.4) <lb/>exp(-S^ ,^) = i + S^ z\ <lb/> i <lb/>i <lb/> Each ^ is a polynomial in the h^ homogeneous of weight k if we give A, weight i. If <lb/>we regard the h, as symmetric functions of the eigenvalues {^.} of a matrix, as above, <lb/>then the ^ are given by <lb/> -kt^^ <lb/> (this differs by a sign from the convention adopted in [5]). <lb/> Example. — Let S == { — i, o, 2, 3, . . . }. The corresponding partition is <lb/>v == (i, i, o, . . .), so the Schur function is <lb/>F,(h)=det^ ;|;)=A^. <lb/>From (8.4), we have h^ == — t^ h^ = -t{ — t^ so by (8.2) the r-function of the <lb/>space W == Hg is <lb/> ^w(t) <lb/> == ^^+^• <lb/> We end this section with some examples of the use of (8.3). First, note that it <lb/>is clear that W has only finitely many non-zero Plucker coordinates if and only if it <lb/>belongs to Gr^; hence we can read off from (8.3) the following. <lb/> Proposition 8.5. — The function r^(t) is a polynomial in (a finite number of) the variables <lb/> (^, ^, . . .) if and only if W belongs to Grg. <lb/> As a more substantial application of (8.3), we shall prove the assertion (5.17) <lb/>about the orders of the poles of the functions a^x, t°). We shall continue to write ^ <lb/>instead of x. The crucial ingredient in the proof is the fact that the restriction of the <lb/>T-function to the one parameter subgroup exp(^ z) of F+ cannot be identically zero. <lb/>More precisely, we have the following. <lb/> Proposition 8.6. — For any W e Gr, we have <lb/> Tw(^i, o, o, . ..) = ct[ + (higher terms), <lb/>where c + o and t is the codimension of the stratum of Gr containing W (*). <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> (*) Added in proof. J. Fay has independently proved an equivalent result in the case when W arises from <lb/>a Riemann surface. (See his paper <lb/> &lt;( On the even-order vanishing of Jacobian theta functions &quot;, Duke Math. <lb/>J., 51 (1984), 109-132, thm 1.2.) <lb/></note>

			<page> 51 <lb/> 52 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEMESEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> In particular, the proposition shows that the r-function cannot vanish identically, <lb/>a fact that we used implicitly throughout § 5. <lb/> Proof of (8.6). — We first consider the behaviour of a Schur function Fg when <lb/>we set t^ = ^3 ==...= o. Since Fg is a homogeneous polynomial of weight /&apos;(S) <lb/>in the ^, it is clear that we have <lb/>Fg(^,o,o,...) ==d,t^ <lb/> where a?g is some rational number. We claim that this number is non-zero. Indeed, <lb/>rfg is equal to (— i)^ times the reciprocal of a certain positive integer, the &quot;product <lb/>of the hook lengths &quot; of the partition associated to S (see [13], p. 37, ex. 3). Explicitly, <lb/>we have <lb/> (-i)^ <lb/> 8 &apos;^ n ^-s,)/n {n-s,)\ <lb/> » &lt; ^ ^ n <lb/> I» ^ n <lb/> where n is any number large enough so that j^i = TZ + i, and as usual S = {so, ^, .. . } <lb/>(see [13], p. 9, formula (4)). We have already observed that for any W e Gr, there is <lb/>a unique S of minimal length /&apos;, say, such that the Pliicker coordinate w^ is non-zero; <lb/>this S is the index of the stratum containing W, and i is the codimension of the stratum. <lb/>That means that in the expansion (8.3) ofr^y, all the terms have weight at least i\ and <lb/>the terms of minimal weight I form a non-zero multiple of a single Schur function Fg. <lb/>Thus the proposition follows at once from (8.3) and the fact that &lt;/g 4= o. <lb/> Proof of (5.17). — Replacing W if necessary by gW for suitable g e I\, we see <lb/>that it is enough to consider the case where the pole is at the origin t == o. We already <lb/>observed in § 5 that the functions a^ are quotients of the form <lb/> ^=P,T/T <lb/> where P^ is a polynomial differential operator in {^/^}; indeed, P^ is the coefficient <lb/>of z~~^ in the formal expansion of the expression <lb/>exp[~S^-<lb/> r (a/^)]. <lb/> It follows at once from this that the operator P^ lowers weight by i (where, as always, <lb/>^ has weight k). Thus in the power series expansion of the numerator P^ T in the expres-<lb/>sion for a^ only terms of weight at least I — i can occur. (If I — i &lt; o, this statement <lb/>is vacuous.) Hence when we put ^ == ^3 = ... = o in the numerator, the lowest <lb/>power of^i that can occur is t[~ <lb/> 1  (any terms involving a lower power of^ must also involve <lb/>a higher ^, and hence vanish when we set ^ ==...= o). Proposition (5.17) follows <lb/>at once from this and (8.6). In fact the argument shows also that the order of the <lb/>pole of any ^ cannot be more than / (*). <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> (*) Added in proof. According to G. Laumon (private communication) the order cannot be more than —SQ. <lb/></note>

			<page> 62 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<body> 9. The T-funcdon and the theta function <lb/> Let X be a compact Riemann surface of genus g, and let J be the Jacobian of X: <lb/> it is the identity component of the group H^X, ^ <lb/> x ), where 0 is the sheaf of holomorphic <lb/>functions on X. We set U = IF(X, 0) and A = Hi(X, Z). The map f^ ef induces <lb/>a sheaf homomorphism Q -&gt; ^ with kernel 2mZ, from which we get the exact sequence <lb/> o -&gt;A -&gt;U -&gt;J -&gt;o <lb/> (the kernel is really H^X, 27riZ), but we identify this with H^X, Z) in the obvious <lb/>way). We recall that U is a ^-dimensional complex vector space, A is a lattice in U <lb/>and J == U/A is a complex torus. <lb/>We denote by B : U x U -&gt; C the unique Hermitian form whose imaginary <lb/>part is the R-bilinear extension of the intersection pairing A X A -&gt; Z. We fix a <lb/>quadratic form q : A -&gt; Z/2Z such that <lb/> q{\ + [L) — q{\) — q{^) == X. (A (mod 2)3 <lb/>where X. (A is the intersection pairing. Then the theta function ofX (see, for example, [15]) <lb/>is the holomorphic function 6 : U -&gt; C defined by <lb/> Q{u) = S (— i)^)^-i&quot;B(X,X+2M)^ <lb/>X£A <lb/> It is characterized (up to a constant factor) by the functional equation <lb/> (9.1) <lb/> Q{U +\) = (— l)^)^&quot;B(X,X+2u)Q^ <lb/> (for u e U, X eA). It follows at once that we have <lb/> Q{u + X) = CQ{u) 6(X) ^ <lb/> M <lb/> ) <lb/> (where G = 6(o)-<lb/> 1 ). We shall use the fact that this relation too characterizes the theta <lb/>function up to certain simple transformations. More precisely, we have the following. <lb/> Lemma 9.2. — Let 6 : U -&gt; C be a holomorphic function such that <lb/> e^+x) =G6^)e <lb/> / (x)^ <lb/> B ^ <lb/> M ) <lb/> for all u eU, X eA, and some (non&apos;zero) constant C. Then we can find a constant A, a <lb/>C-linear map a : U -&gt; C and a point (B e U such that <lb/>^(u) =A^6(M-p). <lb/> Proof. — Set <lb/> C(,A <lb/> GeM <lb/> w =  CQ(u)&apos; <lb/> Then G{u + \) == G{u) G(X), and the restriction of G to A is a homomorphism A -^C^ <lb/>Choose an R-linear map y : U -&gt; C such that G(X) == ^ for XeA. Splitting y <lb/> J3 <lb/></body>

			<page> 54 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEMESEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> into its C-linear and C-antilinear parts and using the non-degeneracy of the form B, <lb/>we see that there are a and (B as in the statement of the lemma such that <lb/> G(X) = ^w-7rB(x,p) <lb/> for X eA. If we set H{u) == e-^(u + (B)/6(^), then H{u + \) = H{u) for all <lb/> \ eA; hence the holomorphic function <lb/> Q^u) ==e-<lb/> ot{u}f Q{u+^ <lb/> satisfies the same functional equation (9.1) as the theta function, and must therefore <lb/>be a constant multiple of it. The lemma follows. <lb/> Remark 9.3. — Obviously, the constant A is uniquely determined by (L The a <lb/>and (B are not quite uniquely determined, because the map y occurring in the proof <lb/>of the lemma is determined only up to addition of a map yo with Yo(^) ^ 27riZ. How-<lb/>ever, it is easy to check that this would change the corresponding (3 only by a lattice <lb/>point, so the projection of (B onto the Jacobian U/A is uniquely determined. Also, <lb/>a is uniquely determined once we have chosen p. <lb/>The T-function is a function on the group I\; our next task is to explain how <lb/>we can regard the theta function too as defined on F^., so that it makes sense to compare <lb/>the two functions. We fix a point x^ e X and a local parameter z as in § 6. We <lb/>shall use z to identify Xoo C X with the disc Doo == { [ z \ ^ i } in the Riemann sphere. <lb/>We denote by V the vector space of all holomorphic maps f: Dg -&gt; C with f{o) == o. <lb/>As in § 5, we identify V with F+ via the map f\-&gt; e^ and we shall regard the r-function <lb/>as a function on V. Now, any f e V (indeed, any holomorphic function on S <lb/> 1 <lb/> ) can <lb/>be regarded as a cocycle for the Cech cohomology group H^X, ^), where ^ = { Ug, Uoo} <lb/>is an open covering ofX as in the proof of (6.1). Using again the fact that we can cal-<lb/>culate the cohomology of X from any such covering, we get a surjective homomorphism <lb/>V-^H^X,^) =U. <lb/>Thus if Ko denotes the kernel of this map, we can regard the theta function as a Ko-inva-<lb/>riant function on V. Now, K.o is the linear subspace of V consisting of all functions <lb/> k e V which can be written in the form k = k^ + k^, where k^ and k^ are holomorphic <lb/>functions on Xp and Xoo, respectively; the splitting is unique if we normalize k^ so that <lb/>A^(oo) = o. We denote by V the vector space of all such maps k^. Let K be the kernel <lb/>of the composite map V -&gt; U -^J$ it consists of all functions k e V such that there <lb/>is a factorization (necessarily unique) <lb/> (9.4) <lb/>^=9,^ <lb/> where k^ e V and &lt;p^ is a non-vanishing holomorphic function on Xo. Clearly <lb/>K/KQ ^ A, so that Ko is indeed the identity component of K, as the notation suggests. <lb/>In the proof of (9.10) below we shall give an explicit description of the integral coho-<lb/>mology class corresponding to an element k e K. <lb/></body>

			<page> 54 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>55 <lb/></page>

			<body> We now fix a line bundle oSf of degree g over X and a trivialization 9 as in § 6$ <lb/>let W e Gr be the corresponding space. For simplicity we assume that W is transverse <lb/>and that the function T === T^&quot; : V -&gt;• C is normalized as usual by r(o) == i. The <lb/>T-function is not usually Kg-invariant: however, we show next that a simple modification <lb/>of it is. We define a map a : K -&gt; V by a(k) == ^, where k^ is as in (9.4). Clearly <lb/> a is a homomorphism, and its restriction to Ko is a C-linear map. <lb/> Lemma 9.5. — Let f e V, k e K. Then we have <lb/>^f+k)=^f)^k)e^f\ <lb/>where S is the multiplier relating the actions ofF^. and F_ on the bundle Det* (see (3.6)^. <lb/> Proof. — By the definition of the r-function (see (3.2)), we have <lb/>(9-6) <lb/>TC/&apos;+^^-^W) =a{e-<lb/> f -<lb/> JS <lb/> ^). <lb/> From the definition of W, it is clear that &lt;p^W == W, so we have ^W = ^ <lb/> -a(fc) W <lb/>for A e K. Using this and the fact that G-is r_-equivariant (see (3.7)), we find <lb/> (9.7) <lb/> r(A) e-^ o(W) = e-^ (r(W). <lb/> The right hand side of (9.6) is equal to <lb/> e-^ a^W) = r(/) e-^ e-f (r(W) == r(/) ^ <lb/> (aw &apos;^ ^-^ ^-<lb/> a( ^ (r(W). <lb/> Inserting (9.7) into this and cancelling the non-zero vector e~ <lb/> f ~ <lb/> k  (r(\V), we get the <lb/>lemma. <lb/>If we apply (9.5) when bothy and k belong to K, we find that <lb/> S(a{k)^) -S(^),A) e2niZ <lb/> for all k, t e K. Extend a to an R-linear map V -&gt; V$ since K spans V over R, the <lb/>extension is unique, and we have <lb/> (9.8) <lb/> S{a{f),g)^-S{a{g)J)eiR <lb/> for ally, g e V. Write a = b + c, where b is C-linear and c is antilinear. Then (9.8) <lb/>implies that <lb/> w/},g) = STO,/), <lb/>s«n,5) = s(^v) <lb/> for all/, ^ eV. Since a | Kg is C-linear, we have (•(Kg) = o; thus c, and hence also <lb/>the Hermitian form {f,g) \-&gt;- S(c(/), g), are well defined on U = V/KQ. Set <lb/> Ti(/) = T(/) c-iW.fl. Then from (9.5) we have <lb/> ^(/+A)=Tl(/)T^)^ <lb/> e ( <lb/> i! &apos;•«. <lb/></body>

			<page> 55 <lb/> 5^ <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEMESEGALANDGEORGEWILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> In particular, the restriction of T^ to KQ is a homomorphism Ko -^C^ Choose a <lb/>C-linear map T] : V -&gt; C such that ^(k) = ^ <lb/> (fc) when k e KQ; set Tg(/) = T^/) ^&quot; <lb/> 7)(/) <lb/> . <lb/>Then T2(/+ k) == Tg(/) for A eKo. Thus Tg is well defined on U, and it satisfies <lb/>(9-9) <lb/>T^+X) == T^) Ta(X) e^^ <lb/> for X eA == K/Ko. But now we have the following crucial result. <lb/> Proposition 9.10. — For all k, I e K, we have <lb/> S{c{k)^) -SW),k) = 27^]. [&lt;|, <lb/> where \k}, \l} denote the classes ofk, t in the group K/Ko == A = H^X, Z). <lb/>The proposition shows that the Hermitian form occurring in the exponent in (9.9) <lb/>is n times the form B occurring in the definition of the theta function. We can therefore <lb/>apply (9.2) to obtain the main result of this section. <lb/> Theorem 9.11. — The ^-function r^y : V -&gt; C is related to the theta function by <lb/> ^(^^A^^iW)&apos;^^/-^), <lb/> where A is a constant, a^ : V -&gt; C is a linear map, (B^ is a point of U, and/denotes the projec-<lb/>tion off onto U == V/Ko. <lb/> Remarks <lb/> (i) Note that the quadratic term -S (6 (/),/) depends only on X and z. <lb/> (ii) By (9.3), the projection of(B^ onto thejacobian J is uniquely determined by W. <lb/>If W moves according to one of the KP flows, then (B^ moves along the corresponding <lb/>straight line in J. <lb/>(iii) There seems no point in trying to be more explicit about the map a, since <lb/>it depends on the choice of trivialization 9 (see (3.8)). <lb/>It remains to give the proof of (9.10). For this we fix a basis A =={a^, (B^}, <lb/>i &lt;_ i &lt; g, for H^(X, Z) of the standard kind, that is, such that a^.(B, == i and all other <lb/>intersections are zero. We can then regard the Riemann surface X in the classical <lb/>way as a quotient of a polygon Y with 4^ edges arranged in groups of four (a,, ^, a^~ <lb/> 1 <lb/> , (B^ <lb/> 1 ) <lb/>(we get X from Y by identifying the two edges corresponding to each element of A). <lb/>We suppose Y chosen so that the disc Xoo in X corresponds to a small disc Y^ in the <lb/>interior of Y; let Yp be the complement of the interior of Yoo. If k e K, then <lb/> k == HQ 4-^oo 5 where k^ and k^ are functions on Yg and Yoo, respectively. Now, <lb/> €kQ = ?A; <lb/> ls a function on X: that means that the values of ^o at corresponding points <lb/></body>

			<page> 56 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS ANT) EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>57 <lb/></page>

			<body> of the two edges ofY corresponding to a generator y <lb/> e A differ by an integer multiple <lb/>of 27n, say by 2nin[k, y). The cohomology class defined by k is then given by <lb/> [k]== s ^y)r <lb/> VGA <lb/> where {y*} is the basis of H^X, Z) = A dual to A. <lb/>Now, we have <lb/> S(^),/) -S(^)^) = S(a{k)^) -SW),k) <lb/> -^ f (^co-^co). <lb/> 27nJsi <lb/> After a short calculation we find that this is equal to <lb/> ^Jsi^ <lb/> -L.f <lb/> 27TZ J g] <lb/> Since ^o and /o are holomorphic functions on Yo, we can replace S <lb/> 1 by the boundary <lb/>ofY in this integral. The contribution to the integral of a typical set of four edges <lb/> a. <lb/>(B, <lb/>a^ <lb/>|3,-<lb/> 1 <lb/> o————^.—————o————&gt;.—————o————&gt;—————o————&gt;—————o <lb/> can be reduced to an integral over the middle pair ((B,, a^~ <lb/> 1 <lb/> ): we obtain <lb/> ^ ^ Jp/o + ^ a,) J^/o == 2^{ -TI(^, (B,) TZ^, a,) + n{k, a,) ^/, (B,)}. <lb/> Summing over t and using the fact that the intersection matrix of the basis {o^, (^} is <lb/>the same as that of{o^, (3j, we see that the integral is indeed equal to 2m\k\. [/&apos;]. <lb/> The Baker function and the theta function <lb/> If we combine (9.11) with (5.14), we obtain a formula expressing the Baker <lb/>function (of a space W arising from a Riemann surface) in terms of the theta function. <lb/>As we mentioned in the introduction, such a formula is well known in the Russian lite-<lb/>rature (see, for example, [10, n, 36]). However, it is perhaps not immediately obvious <lb/>that the Japanese formula (5.14) coincides with the Russian one: so at the suggestion <lb/>of the referee we end this section by offering a fairly detailed comparison of the two <lb/>formulas. <lb/>The Russian formula is expressed in terms of the classical Riemann theta function, <lb/>whose definition involves a choice of canonical homology basis {o^, (Bj as in the proof <lb/>of (9.10) above: we suppose such a basis fixed from now on. The classical theta func-<lb/>tion is a function on the dual space R* of the space R of global holomorphic differentials <lb/>on X; but R* is usually identified with O <lb/> 7 via the basis <lb/> I <lb/> » <lb/>\ <lb/> (o }-&gt; \ cx&gt; , (o e R. <lb/> Joe, <lb/>/ <lb/></body>

			<page> 57 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> 8 <lb/></note>

			<page> 58 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEMESEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> On the other hand we have the natural pairing <lb/> H^X, 0) ® H°(X, ^) -&gt; IP(X, 0.) ^ C, <lb/> where ti is the sheaf of holomorphic differentials on X, which canonically identifies R* <lb/>with the space U = H^X, (?) on which our theta function was defined. In what <lb/>follows we shall use without further comment these identifications U ^ R* ^ C <lb/> 7 <lb/> . The <lb/>choice of homology basis {o^, (B,} gives a natural choice for the form q:A -&gt;Z/2Z <lb/>occurring in our version of the theta function, namely, we can choose q to vanish on the <lb/>basis for A ^ H^X, Z) dual to {o^, (BJ. It is then easy to check that our theta function <lb/>differs from the classical one only by a factor exp Q^, u), where CMs a symmetric R-bili-<lb/>near form on U. Thus if we use the classical theta function, theorem 9.11 remains <lb/>true except that the quadratic form is different. From now on we write 6 for the clas-<lb/>sical theta function. <lb/>With these preliminaries, we can now explain the Russian formula relating the <lb/>Baker function and the theta function. We follow the account given in [36], to which <lb/>we refer the reader for more details. With Krichever, we fix a non-special positive <lb/>divisor Q == {P^, . . ., Pg} on X; without loss of generality (see (6.5)) we suppose <lb/>the points P, lie outside the disc Doo C X. We want to write down the Baker func-<lb/>tion ^, where W is the closure of the space of analytic functions on S <lb/> 1 which extend to <lb/>meromorphic functions on Xo that are regular except for (possible) simple poles at the <lb/>points P,. We fix a base point PQ =t= x^ in X, and let A : X -&gt; R* ^ C <lb/> 9  be the cor-<lb/>responding Abel map, given by <lb/>A(P)(&lt;o)=f&lt;o (PeX, coeR). <lb/>^PO <lb/> The map A is well defined only modulo the period lattice A (because of the choice of <lb/>path of integration). Let G e C <lb/> 9  be a constant vector such that the function (on X) <lb/>6(A(P) — G) vanishes precisely when P = P^, . . ., P^. For n = i, 2, ..., let co^ <lb/>be the differential of the second kind which has zero a-periods and is regular except for <lb/>a singularity at x^ with principal part d^). Let W^ e C <lb/> g  be the vector of (B-periods <lb/>of €«) &quot; . Consider the expression <lb/> , <lb/>, <lb/>(y.f <lb/> 11 <lb/> p(A(P) +2^W,-G) <lb/> (9.12) <lb/>exp S^J ^ <lb/>ft A^——C\——• <lb/> [ i Jpo I <lb/> 6(A(P) — G) <lb/> It is understood that the path of integration in the first term is the same as that used <lb/>in the Abel map; it is then easy to check (see [36], ch. 3, § i) that (9.12) is a well defined <lb/>function of PeX, although the individual terms in it are not. It is obvious that when <lb/>restricted to S <lb/> 1 C X the function (9.12) belongs to W for each fixed t, and has the form <lb/> exp 2^ z\a^t) + a^t) Z-<lb/> 1  +...). <lb/></body>

			<page> 58 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>59 <lb/></page>

			<body> Thus to get the Baker function ^y, we have only to divide by ^oW* That yields the <lb/>final formula <lb/> , , <lb/>, <lb/> 1^ r \ f v.A ,e(A(P)+^w,-G)e(A(^)--c) <lb/>(9.13) <lb/>^-<lb/> ex Pt <lb/> 2 ^p^ <lb/> ^ ) <lb/> exp{ &quot; <lb/> s ^ <lb/> ^o} e(A(P)-c)e(A(.J+^ <lb/> where the constants b^ are defined from the expansions <lb/>F^=z <lb/> n +^b^z-<lb/> r <lb/> JPo <lb/>0 <lb/> for z near x^. <lb/> The formula (9.13) is global (P can run over the whole Riemann surface X). <lb/>We now restrict it to P e D^ and accordingly write z instead of P. We claim that <lb/>(9.13) can then be identified with the formula obtained by substituting (9.11) into (5.14). <lb/>Note first that the quotient <lb/> 6(A(^) -C)/6(A(0 -C) <lb/> in (9.13) is nothing but a function of the form i + ^i -<lb/> 2-1 + • • • $ <lb/> lt  comes from the <lb/>uninteresting linear term a in (9.11). The exponential terms in (9.13) can be written <lb/>exp{S^}exp( f t^z-^\ <lb/> U,j==l <lb/> &apos; <lb/> the second factor here is the contribution to (9.13) coming from the quadratic term <lb/>in (9.11). To complete our check that (5.14) and (9.13) agree, we have still to see <lb/>two things: (i) that the vectors W^ e C <lb/> g  corresponding to the different ^ agree with <lb/>those in (9.11) (obtained by regarding the functions ^ as cocycles for H^X, (P)); (ii) that <lb/>the difference in the arguments of the two remaining theta function terms in (9.13) <lb/>agrees with the q^ in (5.14). For (i), we use the fact that the canonical pairing <lb/>U X R -&gt; C can be derived from the pairing V X R -&gt; C given by <lb/> (/,o)h&gt;-^-.f /co$ <lb/> 27TZJsi <lb/> the desired assertion then reduces to something well known (see, for example, [36], <lb/>(2.i.2i)). Concerning (ii), note that the difference in question is <lb/> A(.)-A(^)=A,(.), <lb/> where A^ is the Abel map defined using the base point x^. Hence the result we need <lb/>is the following. <lb/> Lemma 9.14. — Let I\ -&gt; U -&gt;J == U/A be the map used earlier in this section (defined <lb/> by regarding an element of I\ as a transition function for a line bundle on XJ. Then for \ ^ | &gt; i, <lb/> the image of q^ under this map is A^(^). <lb/></body>

			<page> 59 <lb/> 60 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEMESEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<body> Proof. — We write q^ in the form <lb/> q^z)^{z-<lb/> l -r^ <lb/> l <lb/> }z. <lb/> The two factors here are transition functions for the line bundles corresponding to the <lb/>divisors [^] and [— x^\, respectively. Thus the image of q^ in the Jacobian is [^] — [-^00] ? <lb/>which is indeed Aoo(^). <lb/>Finally, we point out that one can reverse some of the arguments we have just <lb/>given and prove (9.11) by comparing the formulas (5.14) and (9.13). This argument <lb/>is indicated in [5], and is indeed the only possible one there, because at this point in [5] <lb/>the T-function is defined in terms of the Baker function by the formula (5.14). In our <lb/>context, however, we have an independent definition of the r-function, so it seemed to <lb/>us very desirable to give a direct proof of (9.11), avoiding the use of the Baker function. <lb/> 10. Appendix: the representation theory of the loop group <lb/> In this paper we have not mentioned the representation theory of the loop <lb/>group LGL^(C), whereas the Japanese papers [5] put it in the foreground. The diffe-<lb/>rence, however, is more apparent than real, as we shall now explain. We shall begin <lb/>by describing the situation without any attempt at justification, and at the end we shall <lb/>return to give some indications about the proofs. <lb/>It will be convenient in this section to let Gr denote the &quot; Hilbert-Schmidt &quot; <lb/>Grassmannian of H, consisting of closed subspaces W of H such that the projection <lb/>W -&gt; H^. is Fredholm and the projection W -&gt; H__ is Hilbert-Schmidt. Alternatively, <lb/>Gr consists of the graphs of all Hilbert-Schmidt operators Hg -&gt;H^. It is clearly <lb/>a Hilbert manifold. We shall write LGL^(C) for the group of smooth loops. <lb/>We have seen* that a central extension ofLGL^(C) by C <lb/> x acts on the holomorphic <lb/>line bundle Det* on Gr. This means that LGL^(C) acts projectively on the space F(Det*) <lb/>of all holomorphic sections of Det*. With the topology of uniform convergence on <lb/>compact sets, F(Det*) is a complete topological vector space. It is the so-called &quot; basic &quot; <lb/>irreducible projective representation of LGL^(C). <lb/>For any indexing set S e y the &quot; Pliicker coordinate <lb/> )? W l-&gt; w^ (introduced <lb/>in § 8) is an element of r(Det*). We shall denote it by TTg. In fact the TCg span a dense <lb/>subspace; and there is a natural Hilbert space J^ inside F(Det*)—it can be thought of <lb/>as the &quot; square-integrable &quot; holomorphic sections—for which the TTg form an ortho-<lb/>normal basis. The subgroup LUy^ ofLGL^(CS) acts by a projective unitary representation <lb/>on e^. <lb/>The geometrical significance of J^ is that there is a natural antiholomorphic <lb/>embedding <lb/> 0.: Gr -&gt; P(e^) <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> * Strictly speaking, in § 3 we considered only one component of LGL^(C) and Gr; but it is not hard to extend <lb/>the discussion to include the other components (see [17]). <lb/></note>

			<page> 60 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>61 <lb/></page>

			<body> of the infinite dimensional complex manifold Gr in the projective space ofJf. It assigns <lb/>to W e Gr the ray in ^ containing the section Q^, of Det* defined by <lb/>4^&apos;) -det&lt;&gt;,w&apos;&gt;, <lb/>where w is an admissible basis ofW. (Here &lt; w, w&apos; &gt; denotes the matrix whose (z,j)-th ele-<lb/>ment is &lt;z^, ^j&apos;)^ and we are thinking of a section of Det* as a ^&quot;-equivariant map <lb/>^-&gt;C.) The embedding Q is equivariant with respect to LU^. <lb/>The vector in ^ corresponding to H^. with its standard basis, i.e. the canonical <lb/>section a of Det* (cf. § 3), is called the vacuum vector QQ* <lb/>If we think of the representation J^ as given, rather than the manifold Gr, then <lb/>the discussion of § § 3 and 5 can be very simply translated. The crucial formula is the <lb/>definition of the r-function, which becomes <lb/> ^C?) <lb/> == &lt;H)5A&gt;, <lb/> where g e I\, and w is an admissible basis for W. This is the definition in parts of [5], <lb/>except that these authors appear to have in mind only the group of polynomial loops, <lb/>corresponding to our Grassmannian Gr^. <lb/>Two other realizations of the Hilbert space ^ are of importance. To describe <lb/>the first, notice that the connected components of Gr are indexed by the integers, and <lb/>that correspondingly <lb/> ^ == © ^ <lb/> feez <lb/> fc? <lb/> where Jf^ consists of functions on the k&apos;th connected component. We saw in § 2 that <lb/>the group F_ of holomorphic functions in the disc | z \ ^ i acts freely on Gr. Let X <lb/>denote the orbit of H^. under F_. The restriction of Det* to X is canonically trivial; <lb/>so holomorphic sections of Det* restrict to give complex-valued holomorphic functions <lb/>on X. Writing a general element of F_ in the form <lb/> i +h^z-<lb/> 1 +h^z-<lb/> 2 + .... <lb/> we think of functions on X as functions of the infinite sequence of complex variables <lb/>^15 ^2? ^3? • • •• I <lb/> 11 ^ <lb/> act sections of Det* over the component of Gr containing H_^. are <lb/>determined by their restrictions to X, and we have. <lb/> Proposition 10.1. <lb/> (i) If S e y has virtual cardinal zero then the Plucker coordinate TTg e F(Det*) res-<lb/>tricts to the Schur function Fg(Ai, ^, . . .). (Cf.  § 6.) <lb/> (ii) J^o can be identified with the completion of the ring of symmetric polynomials Z[A^, Ag, . . . ] <lb/> with respect to its standard inner product [13]; equivalently, it is the space of\f holomorphic func-<lb/>tions on r_ with respect to the Gaussian measure <lb/> w-^&apos;^n^A, <lb/> where g == exp S^ z&apos; <lb/> 71 , <lb/></body>

			<page> 61 <lb/> 6a <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEMESEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/> </note>

			<body> The second concrete realization of Jf is as the exterior algebra on the Hilbert <lb/>space H_^.€)H_. As H^ and H_ have the orthonormal bases {^}&amp;&gt;o ^d { <lb/> zk }Jc&lt;o <lb/> respectively, the exterior algebra A(H_^ &lt;9 H_) has an orthonormal basis of the form <lb/> (l0.2) <lb/> Z^ A . . . A Z^ A ^ <lb/> 1  A . . . A Z\ <lb/> where a^ &lt; . .. &lt; a^ &lt; o &lt; b^ &lt; ... &lt; 6^. These basis elements correspond exactly <lb/>to the indexing sets S e y with which we are familiar: we write S \ N == {^i, . . ., a^} <lb/> and N\S ={&amp;i, ...,^}. Thus we can denote the element (10.2) by ^ <lb/> s ; the iso-<lb/>morphism A(H^. ® H_J ^ J^ makes z^ correspond to the Pliicker coordinate TCg. <lb/>A more interesting and also more relevant way of constructing the map <lb/>A(H^.©H_) -&gt;c^ is by defining &quot; fermionic field operators&quot; on J^. These amount <lb/>to an operator-valued distribution 6 l-» 9(6) on the circle, satisfying the anticommu-<lb/>tation relations <lb/> [&lt;p(9i),y(92)]+ -o. <lb/> [9(9l).y(92r]4-<lb/> = 8(9l~92). <lb/>Then the map A(H+CH_) -&gt;JT is <lb/> /I A . . . A/^ A ^ A ... A ^ ^ (p^ ... ^ ?;,... &lt;P^ ^o» <lb/> where <lb/> (p/ == -<lb/> s <lb/> - f &quot;/(O) 9(6) dQ. <lb/> 27r Jo <lb/> The highly singular &quot;vertex operator&quot; 9(6) is constructed from the action of <lb/>r == LC <lb/> X on j^ as the limit p -&gt; i + of the action of p^ q^ where ^ == p^°, and <lb/> q^== i —^~ <lb/> 1 z eF+, <lb/> ^=(i-^-i,-^er_. <lb/> The important formula (5.15) for the unique element of W n (i + H_) can be <lb/>written <lb/>^(o,^ <lb/> 6 ) =&lt;Qo,9(9)&quot;w&gt;. <lb/> This is equivalent to (5.15)5 because <lb/> &lt;QO, 9(6) Q^&gt; = lim &lt;0o^c ?^w&gt; <lb/>=lim&lt;^Qo.?^w&gt; <lb/>==lim&lt;Qo5^ <lb/> n w&gt; <lb/>=limTw(?^). <lb/> Remarks about the proofs <lb/> Let H^ &quot; === ^ <lb/> w H^./^ H+ when m &lt;_n. Then Gr contains the finite dimensional <lb/>Grassmannians Y^= Gr(H_^J, and the union of the Y^ is dense. The bundle Det* <lb/></body>

			<page> 62 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>63 <lb/></page>

			<body> on Gr restricts to the usual Det&apos; <lb/> 11 on Y^; so we know that r(Det* | YJ can be identified <lb/>with the exterior algebra A(H_^J. A section of Det* is determined by its restrictions <lb/>to the Y^. Thus we have an inclusion <lb/> (10.3) <lb/> r(Det*) ^-&gt;mnA(H_^). <lb/> n <lb/> Now A(H_^J has a basis indexed by the 2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> &quot; sets S e y such that <lb/> [72,00)CSC [—72,00). <lb/> These come from the corresponding Plucker coordinates TTg in r(Det*). This shows <lb/>that the map (10.3) has a dense image, and also that the TTg span a dense subspace <lb/>of r(Det*). <lb/>To construct the Hilbert space ^ we begin by observing that w [-&gt; Q^, defines <lb/>an antiholomorphic map <lb/> n : Det -&gt; r(Det*) <lb/>which is antilinear on each fibre of Det. (Notice that if w = {^gs <lb/> then 4n is the <lb/>Plucker coordinate TTg.) By transposing £1 we obtain a C-linear map <lb/>iy: F^I^Det&apos;), <lb/>where F is the antidual of I^Det*), i.e. the space of continuous antilinear maps <lb/>F(Det*) -&gt; C. This gives us a hermitian form F x F -&gt; C defined by <lb/> (a^^aOyp). <lb/> In fact O* is injective and has dense image, because the 0.^ span I^Det*), and the Hilbert <lb/>space completion e^ofFis sandwiched between F and r^Det&apos; <lb/> 11 ). It is clear that the TTg <lb/>form an orthonormal basis ofJ^. Because 0. is equivariant with respect to LU^ (or, <lb/>more accurately, with respect to a central extension of LU^ by the circle), it follows <lb/>that LUy, acts unitarily on Jf\ <lb/>The proof of (10. i) (i) is almost exactly the same as that of (8.2); the second part <lb/>is then routine. <lb/>For a discussion of vertex operators we refer to [17] or [18]. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> REFERENCES <lb/>[i] H. AIRAULT, H. P. McKEAN,J. MOSER, Rational and elliptic solutions of the Korteweg-de Vries equation and a <lb/>related many-body problem, Comm. Pure. Appl. Math. 30 (1977), 95-148. <lb/>[a] M. ADLER and J. MOSER, On a class of polynomials connected with the Korteweg-de Vries equation, Comm. <lb/>Math. Phys. 61 (1978), 1-30. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 63 <lb/> 64 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> GRAEMESEGAL AND GEORGE WILSON <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> [3] H. F. BAKER, Note on the foregoing paper &quot; Commutative ordinary differential operators &quot;, byj. L. BURCHNALL <lb/>and T. W. CHAUNDY, Proc. Royal Soc. London (A) 118 (1928), 584-593. <lb/>[4] J. L. BURCHNALL, T. W. CHAUNDY, a) Commutative ordinary differential operators, Proc. London Math. Soc. 21 <lb/> (1923), 420-440; b) Commutative ordinary differential operators, Proc. Royal Soc. London (A) 118 (1928), 557-583; <lb/> c) Commutative ordinary differential operators II. The identity P <lb/> 1 == Q^, Proc. Royal Soc. London (A) 134 <lb/> (1932), 47 <lb/> I -485• <lb/>[5] E. DATE, M. JIMBO, M. KASHIWARA, T. MIWA, Transformation groups for soliton equations: I. Proc. Japan <lb/>Acad. 57A (1981), 342-347; II- Ibid., 387-392; III. /. Phys. Soc. Japan 50 (1981), 3806-3812; IV. Physica 4D <lb/> (1982), 343-365; V. Publ. RIMS, Kyoto Univ. 18 (1982), 111 i-i 119; VI. J. Phys. Soc. Japan 50 (1981), 3813-3818; <lb/>VII. Publ. RIMS, Kyoto Univ. 18 (1982), 1077-1110. <lb/>[6] V. G. DRINFEL&apos;D, V. V. SOKOLOV, Equations of Korteweg-de Vries type and simple Lie algebras, Dokl. Akad. <lb/>Nauk SSSR 258 (i) (1981), 11-16; Soviet Math. Dokl. 23 (1981), 457-462. <lb/>[7] C. D&apos;SOUZA, Compactification of generalized Jacobians, Proc. Ind. Acad. Sci. 88A (1979), 421-457. <lb/>[8] F. EHLERS, H. KNORRER, An algebro-geometric interpretation of the Backlund transformation for the Korteweg-<lb/>de Vries equation. Comment. Math. Helvetic! 57 (1982), i-io. <lb/>[9] I. M. GEL&apos;FAND, L. A. DIKII, Fractional powers of operators and Hamiltonian systems, Funct. Anal. Appl. 10 (4) <lb/>(1976), 13-29 (Russian), 259-273 (English). <lb/>[10] I. M. KRICHEVER, Integration of non-linear equations by methods of algebraic geometry, Funct. Anal. Appl. 11 (i) <lb/>(1977), 15-31 (Russian), 12-26 (English). <lb/>[i i] I. M. KRICHEVER, Methods of algebraic geometry in the theory of non-linear equations, Uspekhi Mat. Nauk <lb/> 32 (6) (1977), 183-208; Russian Math. Surveys 32 (6) (1977), 185-213. <lb/>[12] B. A. KUPERSHMIDT, G. WILSON, Modifying Lax equations and the second Hamiltonian structure, Inventiones <lb/>Math. 62 (1981), 403-436. <lb/>[13] I. G. MACDONALD, Symmetric functions and Hall polynomials, Oxford University Press, 1979. <lb/>[14] I. Yu. MANIN, Algebraic aspects of non-linear differential equations, Itogi Nauki i Tekhniki, ser. Sovremennye <lb/>Problemi Matematiki 11 (1978), 5-152; J. Sov. Math. 11 (i) (1979), I-I22. <lb/>[15] D. MUMFORD, Abelian varieties, Oxford University Press, 1974. <lb/>[16] D. MUMFORD, An algebro-geometric construction of commuting operators and of solutions to the Toda lattice <lb/>equation, Korteweg-de Vries equation and related non-linear equations. Proceedings of Symposium on Algebraic <lb/>Geometry (M. NAGATA, ed.), Kinokuniya, Tokyo, 1978. <lb/>[17] A. PRESSLEY, G. SEGAL, Loop groups and their representations (Book in preparation; Oxford University Press). <lb/>[18] G. SEGAL, Unitary representations of some infinite dimensional groups, Commun. Math. Phys. 80 (1981), 301-342. <lb/>[19] B. SIMON, Notes on infinite determinants ofHilbert space operators. Adv. in Math. 24 (1977), 244-273. <lb/>[20] V. V. SOKOLOV, A. B. SHABAT, (L, A)-pairs and a substitution ofRiccati type, Funct. Anal. Appl. 14 (2) (1980), <lb/>79-80 (Russian), 148-150 (English). <lb/>[21] J.-L. VERDIER, Equations differentielles algebriques, Seminaire Bourbaki (1977-1978), Expose 512 = Lecture notes <lb/>in Math. 710, ioi-i22. <lb/>[22] G. WILSON, Commuting flows and conservation laws for Lax equations. Math. Proc. Camb. Phil. Soc. 86 (1979), <lb/>131-143. <lb/>[23] V. E. ZAKHAROV, A. B. SHABAT, Integration of the non-linear equations of mathematical physics by the inverse <lb/>scattering method II, Funct. Anal. Appl. 13 (3) (1979), 13-22 (Russian), 166-174 (English). <lb/>[24] P. DELIGNE, M. RAPOPORT, Les schemas de modules de courbes elliptiques, in Modular functions of one variable, II <lb/>(P. DELIGNE and W. KUYK, eds.). Lecture Notes in Math. 349, Springer, 1973. <lb/>[25] H. P. MCKEAN, E. TRUBOWITZ, Hill&apos;s operator and hyperelliptic function theory in the presence of infinitely <lb/>many branch points, Comm. Pure Appl. Math. 29 (1976), 143-226. <lb/>[26] M. MULASE, Geometry of soliton equations, M SRI preprint 035-82, Berkeley (1983). <lb/>[27] M. MULASE, Algebraic geometry of soliton equations I, M SRI preprint 040-83, Berkeley (1983). <lb/>[28] M. MULASE, Structure of the solution space of soliton equations, M SRI preprint 041-83, Berkeley (1983). <lb/>[29] M. MULASE, Complete integrability of the Kadomtsev-Petviashvili equation, M SRI preprint 053-83, Berkeley <lb/> (1983). <lb/> [30] M. MULASE, Algebraic geometry of soliton equations, Proc. Japan Acad. 59, Ser. A (1983), 285-288. <lb/>[31] M. MULASE, Cohomological structure of solutions of soliton equations, isospectral deformation of ordinary <lb/>differential operators and a characterization ofjacobian varieties, MSRI preprint 003-84-7, Berkeley (1984). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 64 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> LOOP GROUPS AND EQUATIONS OF KdV TYPE <lb/></note>

			<page>65 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [32] M. SATO, Y. SATO, Soliton equations as dynamical systems on infinite dimensional Grassmann manifold. Preprint, 13 pp. <lb/>(date unknown). <lb/>[33] T. SHIOTA, Characterization of Jacobian varieties in terms of soliton equations. Preprint, 63 pp., Harvard University <lb/>(1984). <lb/>[34] C.J. REGO, The compactified Jacobian, Ann. Scient. EC. Norm. Sup. 13 (1980), 211-223. <lb/>[35] G. WILSON, Habillage et fbnctions T, C. R. Acad. Sc. Paris, 299, Ser. I, n° 13 (1984), 587-590. <lb/>[36] B. A. DUBROVIN, Theta functions and non-linear equations, Uspekhi Mat. Nauk 36 (2) (1981), 11-80; Russian <lb/>Math. Surveys 36 (2) (1981), 11-92. <lb/></listBibl>

			<front> Mathematical Institute, <lb/>University of Oxford, <lb/>24-29 St. Giles, <lb/>Oxford OXi 3LB <lb/> Manuscrit refu Ie 25 mars 1983. <lb/></front>

			<page> 65 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> 9 </note>


	</text>
</tei>
