<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Chaotic Modeling and Simulation (CMSIM) 1: 123–145, 2012 <lb/> Complexity in Theory and Practice: Toward <lb/>the Unification of Non-equilibrium Physical <lb/>Processes <lb/> Georgios P. Pavlos <lb/> Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Engineering, <lb/>Democritus University of Thrace, <lb/>Kimmeria University Campus Xanthi, 67100, Greece <lb/>(E-mail: gpavlos@ee.duth.gr) <lb/> Abstract. During the last two decades our scientific group has developed new non-<lb/>linear methods of analysis applied to various physical systems. In this review study <lb/>we present our scientific contribution to nonlinear science, including also some novel <lb/>concepts as for the constructive role of complexity in modern physical theory. The <lb/>experimental verification of chaos existence in physical systems remains one of the <lb/>most significant problems of non linear science and complexity. The extended chaotic <lb/>algorithm presented in the following as well as the results concerning its application at <lb/>different experimental time series reveal the universal character of the complexity the-<lb/>ory for the far from equilibrium dynamics of spatially extended physical systems. The <lb/>developed methodology that was used compromises different types of computational <lb/>tools as well as theoretical concepts for the physical interpretation of the experimental <lb/>information. As we present here the strong dispute and criticism of chaos hypothesis <lb/>in physical systems during the last two decades was fruitful and challenged us to <lb/>develop a novel composition of experimental and theoretical knowledge of universal <lb/>character for the far from equilibrium dynamics. The solar and magnetospheric dy-<lb/>namics included in space plasma processes, the environmental and seismic dynamics, <lb/>the human brain or the on–chip workload are distinct systems which were studied <lb/>by our group revealing common chaotic characteristics and chaotic phase transition <lb/>processes. Moreover, the intellectual struggle for the comprehension of the theoretical <lb/>presuppositions of the experimentally observed universal chaotic character of spatially <lb/>distributed systems lead us to the fundamentals of complexity theory as manifested <lb/>at the macroscopic and microscopic level of physical reality. From this point of view, <lb/>some common characteristics of macroscopic and microscopic complexity included in <lb/>the scientific knowledge of the recent two or three decades can be used as a road <lb/>for the physical theory unification. That is complexity, scaling, chaos, quanticity and <lb/>fractality could be supported as different manifestations of a unified physical law from <lb/>the microscopic to the macroscopic and cosmological level. As we can argue, deter-<lb/>minism and probabilism can also be unified through chaoticity. Moreover, the rising <lb/>of new physical knowledge reveals that under the macroscopic or the microscopic <lb/>physical phenomena there exist a fundamental and multilevel acting unit physical <lb/>process that produces physical reality rather than a fundamental essence or simple <lb/>Received: 7 August 2011 / Accepted: 30 December 2011 <lb/>c <lb/> 2012 CMSIM <lb/>ISSN 2241-0503 <lb/></front>

			<page> 124 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> G. P. Pavlos <lb/></note>

			<front> substance from which cosmos can be build. <lb/> Keywords: Complexity theory, Intermittent turbulence, Nonlinear time series anal-<lb/>ysis, Nonextensive Tsallis statistics, Nonequilibrium phase transition, Chaos, SOC, <lb/>Macroscopic-microscopic complexity, Physical theory unification. <lb/></front>

			<body> Contents <lb/> 1. Introduction (p 124) <lb/>2. Theoretical Presuppositions and New Tools for the Time series Analysis (p <lb/>126) <lb/>3. Significant Applications of the Chaotic Algorithm (p 128) <lb/>3.1 Solar activity (p 128) <lb/>3.2 Chaos at the Earth and Jovian magnetospheres (p 129) <lb/>3.3 Low dimensional chaotic seismogenesis (p 130) <lb/>3.4 Brain activity during health and seizure state (p 131) <lb/>3.5 Self Organized Criticality and Chaos at the on-chip workload process <lb/>(p 131) <lb/>4. Theoretical Documentation of the Results Obtained by Chaotic Analysis <lb/>(p 132) <lb/>5. Is Complexity the Road for the Final Unification of the Physical Theory? <lb/>New Concepts for an Old Problem (p 134) <lb/>6. Complexity as a New Physical Theory (p 135) <lb/>7. Complexity as a Form of Macroscopic Quanticity (p 135) <lb/>8. Quantum Theory as a Form of Microscopic Chaoticity and Complexity (p <lb/>136) <lb/>9. Universality of Tsallis non-extensive statistical mechanics (p 137) <lb/>10. The road of Complexity for the Physical Theory Unification (p 138) <lb/> 1 Introduction <lb/> After the historical work by Prigogine, Nicolis, Glansdorff and others [43], [78]-<lb/>[83], [110], [111] the science of Complexity is rapidly growing providing the op-<lb/>portunity, combined with the computational power, for the development of new <lb/>methods of analysis, modeling and prediction of various processes with intense <lb/>stochastic or random–chaotic character. This is related to areas of great in-<lb/>terest, such as space plasmas, environment, material mechanics, bio–medicine, <lb/>economy, human society, psychology, urban development, e.t.c. On the other <lb/>hand, the nonlinear time series analysis as it was developed by Takens, Grass-<lb/>berger &amp; Proccacia, Theiler, Tsonis and others [44], [120], [121], [124], [125] <lb/>and was systematically used and extended by Pavlos and Athanasiou [6], [7], <lb/>[90]-[104] is the road for the experimental verification of complex dynamics. <lb/>The Complexity theory and the experimental time series analysis concerning <lb/>spatiotemporal and far from equilibrium nonlinear dynamics include signifi-<lb/>cant collective phenomena such as: fractal and multifractal structures, power <lb/>law distribution and critical scale invariance, nonequilibrium fluctuations caus-<lb/>ing spontaneous nucleation and evolution of turbulent motion from metastable <lb/>states, defect mediated turbulence and localized defects changing chaotically in <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Chaotic Modeling and Simulation (CMSIM) 1: 123–145, 2012 <lb/></note>

			<page>125 <lb/></page>

			<body> time and moving randomly in space, spatiotemporal intermittency, chaotic syn-<lb/>chronization, anomalous diffusion and directed percolation causing levy-flight <lb/>spreading processes, turbulent patches and percolation structures, threshold <lb/>dynamics and avalanches, chaotic itinerancy, or stochastic motion of vortex <lb/>like objects [10], [11], [29]-[31], [48], [67], [73], [118], [133]. <lb/>In particular, in the phase space of a complex system various finite dimen-<lb/>sional attractors can exist such as: fixed points, limit cycles -torus or more <lb/>complicated structures as strange attractors. Strange attractors can correspond <lb/>to chaotic dynamics as self-organized critical dynamics (SOC) or strong chaos. <lb/>Generally, spatiotemporal chaos includes early turbulence with low effective <lb/>dimensionality and few coherent spatial patterns or states of fully developed <lb/>turbulence. These states are out of equilibrium steady states related to bifurca-<lb/>tion points of the nonlinear distributed dynamics, as well as to first and second <lb/>order non-equilibrium phase transition processes. Also, other spatial and tem-<lb/>poral patterns as well as spatially localized structures are possible solutions <lb/>of the nonlinear spatially extended dynamics. With regard the exploration <lb/>of space plasma complexity by experimental time series analysis, the primary <lb/>studies by Vassiliadis, Pavlos and other scientists including nonlinear analysis <lb/>of magnetospheric data [12], [90]-[92], [129], [130], as well as the hypothesis of <lb/>magnetospheric chaos went through a strong and fruitful criticism [107]-[109]. <lb/>This criticism was a general dispute about the experimental verification of <lb/>chaos. In the following we present the main points of the criticism against low <lb/>dimensional chaos: a) The correlation dimension of experimental time series <lb/>cannot be distinguished from a stochastic signal with the same power spectrum <lb/>and amplitude distribution as the original data. b) There is no evidence for <lb/>the existence of low-dimensionality according to their estimate of correlation <lb/>dimension obtained using Takens method. c) When there is some evidence of <lb/>nonlinearity in the experimental time series it is not clear whether it is the <lb/>result of intrinsic dynamics or nonlinearities in the external pertubations of <lb/>the system. d) When the system is open and externally largely controlled this <lb/>alone should provide evidence against the existence of a strange attractor in the <lb/>observed signals as the system is a randomly driven non-autonomous system. <lb/>The refutation of the concept of low dimensional chaos in spatially extended <lb/>systems as the space plasmas it was further strengthened after the introduction <lb/>of the concept of self organized criticality (SOC) [10], [25], [64]. Under this cir-<lb/>cumstantial evidence, Pavlos et al. [95] introduced the term &quot; pseudo–chaos &quot; <lb/>to discriminate the real low-dimensional chaotic dynamics from the stochastic <lb/>and nonchaotic colored noise processes. Furthermore, the Thrace group cre-<lb/>ated an extended algorithm for the detection of low dimensional chaos by time <lb/>series analysis and the discrimination of chaos from stochastic processes which <lb/>can mimic low dimensional chaos. This algorithm was based on the Wold&apos;s de-<lb/>composition theorem, the theory of input–output dynamics and the embedding <lb/>theory of Takens, as well as the fruitful contribution of Theiler concerning the <lb/>method of surrogate data [2]-[7], [44], [95]-[98], [120], [121]. <lb/>During the last two decades the chaotic algorithm was used to analyse <lb/>experimental time series corresponding to various physical or technical systems <lb/>such as: The solar corona and the Earth–Jovian magnetospheres, the solid <lb/></body>

			<page> 126 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> G. P. Pavlos <lb/></note>

			<body> outer crust of the earth, the atmospheric system, the human brain and the <lb/>Network–on–chip Architecture of the mobile technology [53]-[55], [60]-[62], [98]-<lb/>[101], [126]. The far from equilibrium distributed input–output dynamics is the <lb/>common character in all these distinct cases of physical systems in which the <lb/>chaotic analysis of experimental time series revealed significant characteristics <lb/>such as: multiscale and critical dynamics phase transition processes as well as <lb/>the noticeable coexistence of intermittent turbulence, high dimensional SOC <lb/>and low dimensional chaotic processes. <lb/>After all, a necessity was raised for a theoretical interpretation of the uni-<lb/>versal and experimentally observed characteristics that lead us to the funda-<lb/>mentals of complexity theory, according to which phase transition processes or <lb/>intermittent turbulence phenomena and low dimensional self organized chaos <lb/>are at the edge of macroscopic and microscopic complexity. Moreover, the uni-<lb/>versality of Tsallis non-extensive statistics, verified at the macroscopic and the <lb/>microscopic level, indicates also the universality of complexity theory at both <lb/>macroscopic and microscopic level [122], [123]. After all the obtained until now <lb/>practical and theoretical experience makes us to believe that the complexity <lb/>theory could be the prime motivator towards a global theoretical unification <lb/>of our understanding of nature from the microscopic to the macroscopic level. <lb/>However, for such a dream to come true, new physical and mathematical con-<lb/>cepts must be used such as, cooperation of local, non–local and long–range <lb/>correlations in complex systems. A new complementarity is developed funda-<lb/>mental local physical interactions and global ordering physical process including <lb/>fractal space–time, or fuzzy space and non–communicative geometry or wild <lb/>topologies [15], [36], [38], [46], [50], [84], [87]. In this direction and in order to <lb/>remark the new state we can summarize by the following phrase of Castro: It <lb/> is reasonable to suggest that there must be a deeper organizing principle, from <lb/>small to large scales, operating in Nature which might be based in the theories <lb/>of complexity, non linear dynamics and information theory where dimensions, <lb/>energy and information are intricately connected [22]. <lb/>According to the previous description, this study includes two distinct parts. <lb/>In the first part (sections 2-4), we present the algorithm of chaotic analysis, as <lb/>well as significant results by using the chaotic algorithm at experimental signals <lb/>extracted by complex spatially extended systems. The physical presuppositions <lb/>of the algorithm and significant applications are presented also. In the second <lb/>part (sections 5-10), we introduce in a synthetic way significant theoretical <lb/>concepts aiming at the unifying role of complexity theory from the microscopic <lb/>to the macroscopic physical level. <lb/> 2 Theoretical Presuppositions and New Tools for the <lb/>Time Series Analysis <lb/> In general, the spatiotemporal dynamics of spatially extended physical sys-<lb/>tems is related to irreversible or non–equilibrium thermodynamics, as well as <lb/>to non–equilibrium statistical physics [25], [58], [123]. According to Nicolis and <lb/>Prigogine, [78]-[83], [110], [111] the existence of low dimensional order (peri-<lb/>odic or chaotic) in an extended system is the central character of physical self <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Chaotic Modeling and Simulation (CMSIM) 1: 123–145, 2012 <lb/></note>

			<page>127 <lb/></page>

			<body> organization and complexity theory. As we present here, different far from <lb/>equilibrium spatially extended physical systems reveal self organized complex-<lb/>ity and chaotic dynamics or other complex dynamics at the edge of chaos as <lb/>well as non–equilibrium statistical profile according to Tsallis non–extensive <lb/>statistical theory [123]. These significant characteristics of complexity theory <lb/>have been revealed by the application of an extended algorithm of nonlinear <lb/>time series analysis presented in the following. <lb/>The experimental study of spatiotemporal complexity includes the question: <lb/> &quot; if you have a time signal, what is the kind of information that you hope to get <lb/>out of it? &quot; . The physical systems, which we are interested in, are dissipative <lb/>and spatially extended. The attempt to understand the complex deterministic <lb/>motion of spatially extended nonlinear dissipative systems, so–called spatiotem-<lb/>poral chaos (STC), is at the forefront of research in nonlinear dynamics. In <lb/>contrast to simple chaotic systems in the time domain, in which few degrees of <lb/>freedom are nonlinearly coupled, spatially extended systems include an infinite <lb/>number of spatially distributed degrees of freedom. For this reason tools and <lb/>methods developed for low dimensional systems described by non-linear Ordi-<lb/>nary Differential Equations (ODE) must be adapted to spatially distributed <lb/>systems described by nonlinear Partial Differential Equations. The transition <lb/>to chaos in spatially extended systems is widely investigated in many natural <lb/>phenomena such as hydrodynamics or magnetohydrodynamics, chemical reac-<lb/>tions, pattern formation in biology or brain activity. Spatiotemporal chaos <lb/>involves intermediate situations between chaos and turbulence or to fully de-<lb/>veloped turbulence when the system is sufficiently confined. In these states it is <lb/>possible to characterize the dynamics from a local time series alone estimating <lb/>fractal dimensions, or Lyapunov exponents in the reconstructed phase space. <lb/>When the physical extension of the system increases then quantities, measuring <lb/>the amount of chaos, scale like the system size. When the system size is much <lb/>larger than the correlation length then the system can be viewed as a collection <lb/>of essentially independent sub–systems with a size of the order of correlation <lb/>length, so that the amount of chaos should be proportional to the number of <lb/>sub–systems. As long as x  i  &gt; L, where x  i  is the correlation length and L the <lb/>system size, we are dealing with a small system which may be chaotic in time <lb/>and coherent in space. In the opposite limit x  i  &lt;&lt; L the dynamical behavior <lb/>is incoherent in space. This regime occurs for L &gt;&gt; l  e  − l  D  , where l  D  is the <lb/>dissipative length and l  e  the excitation length, and it is the regime of spatial <lb/>chaos or weak turbulence. Weak turbulence is characterized by the chaotic <lb/>evolution of coherent structures roughly of the size of the correlation length ξ. <lb/> The dimension of a local attractor can scale linearly with the system volume <lb/> Ld, where d is the dimensionality of space while the attractor density D  H  /L  d <lb/> can be well defined. When the spatial structure plays an essential role then, <lb/>according to Chate, Manneville and Wang [29], [30], [133] the spatiotemporal <lb/>dynamics of the system can be very complex revealing chaotic synchronization, <lb/>spatiotemporal intermittency or directed percolation, sporadic chaos, localized <lb/>structures, and defect turbulence as well as phase transition processes. More-<lb/>over, defect turbulence and intermittent turbulence, self organized criticality <lb/>(SOC), avalanche threshold dynamics, spinodal and nucleation phenomena and <lb/></body>

			<page> 128 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> G. P. Pavlos <lb/></note>

			<body> far from equilibrium phase transition, Tsallis entropies and non–Gaussian fluc-<lb/>tuations as well as diffusion or Levy motion, are some of the different manifes-<lb/>tations of spatiotemporal complexity and multiscale–multifractal phenomena <lb/>that must be studied using nonlinear signal analysis [16], [63], [88], [122]. <lb/>The chaotic algorithm that can be used to uncover the hidden nonlinear spa-<lb/>tiotemporal dynamical characteristics underlying the experimental time series <lb/>includes different group of tools summarized as follows: <lb/>i. Computation Phenomenological Characteristics <lb/>(a) Autocorrelation Coefficient and Power Spectrum (Linear correlations, <lb/>periodicities, scaling laws <lb/>(b) (Mutual Information (Linear and Nonlinear Correlations) <lb/>(c) Probability Distributions (Power Laws) <lb/>(d) Hurst exponent (Persistence, anti-persistence, white noise) <lb/>(e) Flatness Coefficient F (Intermittent turbulence) <lb/>(f) Structure Functions (Turbulence, anomalous diffusion) <lb/>(g) (Phase portrait (Low Dimensionality) <lb/>(h) Entropy, energy, multifractal structures <lb/>(i) Estimation of q-Tsallis Statistics <lb/>(j) Wavelet analysis (Spatiotemporal structures) <lb/>ii. Computation of Geometrical characteristics in the reconstructed state space <lb/>(a) Correlation Dimension (Degrees of freedom) <lb/>(b) Generalized Dimension (Multifractals) <lb/>(c) False Neighbors (Degrees of Freedom) <lb/>(d) Singular values spectrum (SVD components, filtering) <lb/>iii. Computation of Dynamical Characteristics in the reconstructed state space <lb/>(a) Maximum Lyapunov Exponent (Sensitivity in initial conditions) <lb/>(b) Power Spectrum of Lyapunov Exponents (Sensitivity in initial condi-<lb/>tions in all dimensions in space state) <lb/>(c) Nonlinear modeling and nonlinear prediction algorithms <lb/>iv. Testing of Null Hypothesis in order to discriminate between low dimensional <lb/>chaotic dynamics and linear high dimensional stochastic dynamics <lb/>(a) Surrogate data <lb/>(b) Discriminating statistics <lb/>v. Singular Value Analysis in order to <lb/>(a) Estimate Degrees of Freedom <lb/>(b) Filter signals from White or Colored Noise <lb/>(c) Search for input-output dynamics <lb/>vi. Recently the above algorithm has been completed by significant new tools <lb/>such as <lb/>(a) Fuzzy analysis of time series <lb/>(b) Cellular automata, genetic algorithms and neural network modeling <lb/>(For spatiotemporal modeling and prediction of complexity) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Chaotic Modeling and Simulation (CMSIM) 1: 123–145, 2012 <lb/></note>

			<page>129 <lb/></page>

			<body> 3 Significant Applications of the Chaotic Algorithm <lb/> 3.1 Solar activity <lb/> Solar activity is produced by the emergence of magnetic flux through the pho-<lb/>tosphere. The magnetic flux forms active regions which include sunspots and <lb/>solar flares. The physical system underlying the solar activity and the solar <lb/>cycle is the convection zone of the sun. Convection zone is a strongly turbulent <lb/>region which occupies the one third of the solar interior. The generation of the <lb/>magnetic field and its evolution inside the convection zone is one of the most <lb/>challenging problems for the solar physics, related to the convection zone turbu-<lb/>lence, the coronal heating, the solar flares, particle acceleration and transport. <lb/>The random character of solar activity has been associated theoretically with <lb/>chaotic behavior and a solar low dimensional strange attractor [106], [113]. For <lb/>the first time [95] applied chaotic analysis at the sunspot index presenting some <lb/>evidence for low dimensions solar chaos. Price et al. [108] have criticized the <lb/>chaos hypothesis concerning the solar activity as they reported that applying <lb/>the chaotic analysis to the wolf sunspot number time series no evidence was <lb/>found for low dimensional deterministic nonlinear process. Oppositely, the self <lb/>organized criticality (SOC) theory was introduced for the explanation of solar <lb/>activity [132]. In a series of studies by Karakatsanis and Pavlos [60], Karakat-<lb/>sanis et al. [61] we have presented strong evidence for the coexistence of two <lb/>clearly discriminated physical processes in the solar activity. The first process <lb/>corresponds to the existence of self organized critical state according to the <lb/>general profile of SOC theory process. The second process corresponds to low <lb/>dimensional chaotic dynamics. These results were obtained after the nonlinear <lb/>analysis of the Sunspot Index, according to which, the original signal reveals <lb/>characteristics of a SOC process, that is, high dimensionality and zero value <lb/>of the largest Lyapunov exponent. The low dimensional chaotic process was <lb/>revealed after using high pass filtering of the original Sunspot Index and Solar <lb/>Flare Index with the methods of first difference or singular value decomposi-<lb/>tion analysis. The dual character of the solar activity which is hidden in the <lb/>observed Sunspot Index reveals a double input–output dynamics corresponding <lb/>to the photospheric and sub-photospheric zones activity of the Solar system. <lb/>Also, [60], [61] found strong evidence for intermittent solar turbulence as well <lb/>as for non-extensive statistical processes, according to Tsallis q–statistics. <lb/> 3.2 Chaos at the Earth and Jovian magnetospheres <lb/> The hypothesis of magnetospheric chaos was supported originally by Baker <lb/>[12], Pavlos [90]-[94] and Vassiliadis [130]. In this direction Tom Chang [24] <lb/>proposed for the far from equilibrium space plasmas dynamics the generaliza-<lb/>tion of Wilson Renormalization Group theory predicting SOC or chaos states. <lb/>Strong objection and criticism against the magnetospheric chaos was presented <lb/>by Price and Prichard [107]-[109]. Pavlos [90], Pavlos et al. [95] paralelly to <lb/>the nonlinear analysis of magnetospheric signals supported the hypothesis of <lb/>magnetospheric self organization as basic nonlinear and holistic theory space <lb/></body>

			<page> 130 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> G. P. Pavlos <lb/></note>

			<body> plasmas, according to [45], [79]. Moreover, the hypothesis of SOC process was <lb/>strongly supported as a physical explanation of the magnetospheric dynamics, <lb/>by Klimas et al. [64], Consolini [31], Uritsky [128], Chapman [28] and others. <lb/>After this in a series of papers we have shown the existence of two distinct mag-<lb/>netospheric dynamical components: one which is low dimensional and chaotic <lb/>and a second which is high dimensional of SOC type [95]-[97], [102]. <lb/>In particular we have shown: <lb/> • Change of the plasma sheet state from stochastic and high dimensional <lb/>(SOC state) to low dimensional and chaotic (chaos state) during the devel-<lb/>opment of a superstorm event. <lb/> • Strengthen of the intermittent character during the substorm period as well <lb/>as development of global self-organization and long-range correlation at the <lb/>plasma sheet. <lb/> • Low dimensional self-organization with long range, intermittent and cor-<lb/>related profile can be developed at regions near the magnetopause and the <lb/>bow shock. <lb/> • High dimensional and stochastic processes and intermittent turbulence dur-<lb/>ing quiet periods inside the plasma sheet <lb/> • q-Gaussian statistics and strong evidence for the application of non-extensive <lb/>statistics, according to Tsallis theory to space plasmas <lb/>These results confirm the model of phase transition-like behavior of the <lb/>magnetosphere during substorms introduced by Sitnov et al.[117]. According <lb/>to this model the magnetospheric dynamics includes multiscale self organized <lb/>criticality processes corresponding to second-order phase transition, as well <lb/>as low dimensional and chaotic processes corresponding to first-order phase <lb/>transition. The dual character of magnetospheric dynamics observed in situ by <lb/>the space-craft GEOTAIL by Pavlos et al. [101], [104] is in agreement with our <lb/>previous results [95], [97] and verify the concept of low dimensional chaos at <lb/>the magnetospheric dynamics, as well as the intermittent turbulence and SOC <lb/>in accordance with the general theory of Tom Chang [23], [27] concerning the <lb/>far from equilibrium self-organization of the magnetospheric system and the <lb/>far from equilibrium renormalization theory for critical dynamics. <lb/> 3.3 Low dimensional chaotic seismogenesis <lb/> The existence of power law distributions led many scientists to explain earth-<lb/>quakes as a Self Organized Critical (SOC) process, according to Bak theory [10] <lb/>as well as to consider seismicity as the turbulence of the solid earth crust [10], <lb/>[11], [18], [40], [59]. These concepts showed that earthquakes can be understood <lb/>via the general theory of statistical physics for dynamical processes of far from <lb/>equilibrium phase transitions applied to distributed fault&apos;s systems. The SOC <lb/>process has already been connected in the past to the unpredictability of earth-<lb/>quakes since the SOC dynamics is related to the edge of chaos phenomenon <lb/>characterized by strong randomness and high-dimensionality [119] since SOC <lb/>models have often been considered as alternatives to the low dimensional chaos <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Chaotic Modeling and Simulation (CMSIM) 1: 123–145, 2012 <lb/></note>

			<page>131 <lb/></page>

			<body> interpretation of the seismic process [98], [100]. On the other hand, chaos in-<lb/>cludes low dimensional determinism, in contrast with complete unpredictability <lb/>or randomness, which is lost over long enough time scales, but long-term, inter-<lb/>mediate and short term prediction could be related to a chaotic seismic-cycle <lb/>process [18], [40]. It was for the first time that Pavlos [96] constructed in-<lb/>terevent seismic time series according to the dripping faucet dynamical system <lb/>for testing the hypothesis of seismic chaos. The dripping faucet model is well <lb/>known for illustrating the appearance of chaotic behavior in nonlinear systems, <lb/>where time intervals between successive drop detachments are used to recon-<lb/>struct the dynamics of the system [115]. At low dripping rates the system is <lb/>periodic, while above a critical dripping rate the system exhibits chaotic behav-<lb/>ior characterized by qualitatively different types of strange attractors. Using <lb/>interevent time intervals between one drop to the next one, the reconstructed <lb/>dynamics reveals low dimensional deterministic behavior in the reconstructed <lb/>state space. According to Iliopoulos et al. [53] and Pavlos et al. [96] con-<lb/>cerning a seismic process, the loading rate m(t) of mass in the mechanistic <lb/>dripping faucet model of Shaw corresponds to the transfer of stress in the fault <lb/>system by the mantle and plate tectonic dynamics (the external driver of the <lb/>system), while mass unloading corresponds to earthquakes, as releases of the <lb/>elastic strain energy stored along a fault. The dripping faucet similarly to the <lb/>earthquake process can be understood as a local, driven, threshold process. In <lb/>a series of papers by Iliopoulos et al. [53]-[55] and Pavlos et al. [98] the seis-<lb/>mic low dimensional chaos was faithfully supported for the case of the Hellenic <lb/>seismogenesis. These studies showed clearly the existence of a global seismic <lb/>strange attractor in the Hellenic region with low dimensionality and strong <lb/>sensitivity to initial conditions concerning the spatiotemporal distribution of <lb/>earthquakes. Moreover, the chaotic analysis of seismic time series revealed <lb/>an independent high dimensional SOC dynamics concerning the energy release <lb/>process. Moreover, [55] applied nonlinear analysis to various seismic time series <lb/>indicating local low dimensional temporal chaotic character of the seismic pro-<lb/>cess in the North Aegean area and high dimensional SOC process concerning <lb/>the bursting seismic energy release. The non-extensive q-statistics of Tsallis <lb/>was observed also by [55]. <lb/> 3.4 Brain activity during health and seizure state <lb/> The human brain can be modelled as a driven nonlinear threshold system <lb/>including interacting spatial networks of statistically identical, nonlinear units <lb/>or cells. Each cell fires or falls when the electrical potential or current reaches <lb/>a threshold value. Numerical simulations of these systems reveal spatial and <lb/>temporal patterns of firing while the dynamics may also be modified by the <lb/>presence of noise. The spatiotemporal complexity of brain activity can reveal <lb/>various dynamical states during health or seizure periods [11], [41], [52], [66], <lb/>[69], [88], [98], [127], [134] applied chaotic analysis for EEG signals as the brain <lb/>activity changes from health to epilepsy seizure. In this study, we have shown <lb/>a phase transition process of brain activity from a high dimensional SOC state <lb/>during the health period to a gradually developed low dimensional chaotic <lb/></body>

			<page> 132 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> G. P. Pavlos <lb/></note>

			<body> state. Tsoutsouras et al. [126] produced a cellular Automata (CA) model <lb/>of healthy and epilepsy brain states. In this study, the chaotic clustering of <lb/>neurons was indicated as a basic mechanism of the phase transition of the <lb/>brain activity from high-dimensional stochastic dynamics to low-dimensional <lb/>chaotic dynamics. The CA modeling of brain activity by [126] was found to <lb/>simulate faithfully the brain dynamics underlying to real data. The brain phase <lb/>transition process from high-dimensional stochastic to low-dimensional chaotic <lb/>states supported by CA modeling and by real data chaotic analysis was found <lb/>to belong to a universal complex spatiotemporal process observed at various <lb/>physical systems such as the solar activity at the magnetospheric substorms, <lb/>as well as at the seismic process of the earth lithospheric fault system [54], [60], <lb/>[61], [101]. <lb/> 3.5 Self Organized Criticality and Chaos at the on-chip workload <lb/>process <lb/> In recent years, the mobile technology was developed so dramatically that has <lb/>opened new challenges in the embedded system design domain. Different, from <lb/>the traditional desktop systems, embedded devices demand not only high pro-<lb/>cessor performance but also low power consumption. Thus, the development <lb/>of proper methods in power consumption management, which will extend the <lb/>battery life, is without doubt, an imperative need. It was the first time that <lb/>a SOC–Chaos phase transition process was observed during periods of on-chip <lb/>workload by [136]. These are results of high significance concerning the design <lb/>of Network-on-chip Architecture. Dynamic frequency scaling (DFS) is used <lb/>to adjust the working frequency according to the system workload in order to <lb/>save the power consumption without degrading the system performance signif-<lb/>icantly beyond the application tolerance. The main problem of DFS solutions <lb/>is how to compute the system workload trend. Generally, the workload anal-<lb/>ysis is an open issue which has occupied the international literature by the <lb/>beginning of the computer science technology. Recently, [136] used chaotic <lb/>analysis of workload time series in order to develop novel power aware dynamic <lb/>frequency scaling technique based on the workload treud of an embedded ap-<lb/>plication. Particular chaotic analysis of workload signals showed the existence <lb/>of workload critical dynamics and phase transition between states with distinct <lb/>dynamical dimensionality. This gives the opportunity to handle dynamic data <lb/>streams with complex behavior. The benefit of this approach based at the real <lb/>time chaotic analysis of the workload signal is related to the management of <lb/>the power consumption. The simulation results showed that the methodology <lb/>based on chaotic analysis can achieve remarkable improvements at the final <lb/>power consumption. The main idea of our approach is to adjust the process-<lb/>ing frequency of our system by analysing the workload fluctuations without <lb/>degrading the final performance or violating any deadline. The key of our <lb/>methodology is that we use an abstract model of workload analysis that com-<lb/>bines advanced mathematical tools from the Chaos Theory domain. This gives <lb/>us the opportunity to handle dynamic data streams with complex behavior. <lb/>The benefit of our approach is that it is a system-level platform independent <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Chaotic Modeling and Simulation (CMSIM) 1: 123–145, 2012 <lb/></note>

			<page>133 <lb/></page>

			<body> technique, which permits us, through the analysis and the prediction of the <lb/>workload trend, to manage the power consumption of an embedded system <lb/>calibrating only the processing frequency. The simulation results showed that <lb/>our methodology can achieve remarkable improvements at the final power con-<lb/>sumption, which range between 17% and 38% depending on the restriction of <lb/>the application deadlines. These results are complementary to previous analy-<lb/>sis of system performance degray taking into account the interaction between <lb/>workload fluctuations and the nonlinearity of the system. Moreover, the phase <lb/>transition process described by Zompakis [136] can be used for proposing new <lb/>adaptive techniques related with dynamics power management. <lb/> 4 Theoretical Documentation of the Results Obtained <lb/>by Chaotic Analysis <lb/> Until now, Chaos or SOC states, intermittent turbulence including multifractal <lb/>and multiscale characteristics, Tsallis q-statistics, as well as out of equilibrium <lb/>phase transition processes, were found to be of universal character at distinct <lb/>physical or technological systems. Also, all the previous systems at which the <lb/>chaotic analysis was applied belong to the general type of distributed and far <lb/>from equilibrium input-output threshold nonlinear dynamics. For these sys-<lb/>tems the general theory of far from equilibrium non linear stochastic dynamics <lb/>described by generalized Langeving equations can be applied [47]. According <lb/>to Chang [23]-[25] the stochastic Lagrangian methodology for the solution of <lb/>the stochastic Langevin equations and the far from equilibrium renormalization <lb/>group theory can be used for the estimation of the fixed points of the dynam-<lb/>ics. From this point of view, various macroscopic states and process can be <lb/>related to different fixed points in the affine space of the stochastic Lagrangian <lb/>dynamics. In general, far from equilibrium nonlinear stochastic dynamics can <lb/>be described by a set of generalized Langevin equations [25]: <lb/> ∂φ  i <lb/> ∂t <lb/> = f  i  (φ, x, t) + n  i  (x, t) <lb/> (1) <lb/>where f  i  (i = 1, 2, . . .) are nonrandom forces corresponding to the functional <lb/>derivative of the free energy functional, x  µ  (µ = 1, . . . , d) are the spatial coordi-<lb/>nates, t is the time and φ(x, t) represents the stochastic variables which describe <lb/>the fault dynamics and n  i  (x, t) are random force fields or noises. According <lb/>to Chang [24] the behavior of a nonlinear stochastic system far from equilib-<lb/>rium can be described by the density functional P , defined by path integral <lb/>formulation: <lb/> P φ(x, t) = <lb/> D(x) exp <lb/> −i <lb/> L( ˙ <lb/> φ,φ,x)dxdt <lb/> (2) <lb/>where L( ˙ <lb/> φ, φ, x) being the stochastic Lagrangian of the system, which de-<lb/>scribes the full dynamics of the stochastic system. Moreover, the far from equi-<lb/>librium renormalization group theory applied to the stochastic Langrangian L <lb/> gives the singular points (fixed points) in the affine space of the stochastic <lb/></body>

			<page> 134 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> G. P. Pavlos <lb/></note>

			<body> distributed system. At the fixed points the system reveals the character of <lb/>criticality, as near criticality the correlations among the fluctuations of the <lb/>random dynamic field are extremely long-ranged and there exist many corre-<lb/>lation scales. Also, close to dynamic criticality certain linear combinations of <lb/>the parameters, characterizing the stochastic Lagrangian of the system, cor-<lb/>relate with each other in the form of power laws and the stochastic system <lb/>can be described by a small number of relevant parameters characterizing the <lb/>truncated system of equations with low or high dimensionality. According to <lb/>these theoretical results, the stochastic system can exhibit low dimensional <lb/>chaos or high dimensional SOC like behavior, including spatiotemporal fractal <lb/>structures with power law profiles. The power laws are connected to the near <lb/>criticality phase transition process which creates spatial and temporal corre-<lb/>lations as well as strong or weak reduction (self-organization) of the infinite <lb/>dimensionality corresponding to a spatially distributed system. According to <lb/>Lyra and Tsallis [71], the power laws are not caused by the SOC process, but by <lb/>the nonextensive statistics observed at far from equilibrium process with long <lb/>range correlations. From this point of view, a SOC or low dimensional chaos <lb/>interpretation depends upon the kind of the critical fixed (singular) point in the <lb/>functional solution space of the system. When the stochastic system is exter-<lb/>nally driven or perturbed, it can be moved from a particular state of criticality <lb/>to another characterized by a different fixed point and different dimensionality <lb/>or scaling laws. Thus, SOC theory could be a special type of critical dynam-<lb/>ics of an externally driven stochastic system [70]. Furthermore, according to <lb/>Chang [26], Chang et al. [27] as well as Vieira [131], SOC and low dimensional <lb/>chaos can coexist in the same dynamical system as a process manifested by <lb/>different kinds of fixed (critical) points in its solution space. As the dynamical <lb/>system evolves in time (autonomously or under external forcing), the state of <lb/>the system described by the values of the dynamical parameters in the stochas-<lb/>tic Lagrangian L, changes as well. The change of the critical state of the system <lb/>can reveal different dynamical scenarios, as it evolves from one critical state <lb/>to another, after external tuning. Also, it is possible to reveal local instabili-<lb/>ties by creating metastable states which evolve to states of lower energy. This <lb/>is a local symmetry breaking phenomenon and leads to a local phase transi-<lb/>tion process. Such local instabilities are connected to avalanche or nucleation <lb/>dynamics, which can be present in systems that are at mean-field or near-mean-<lb/>field state, with the possibility of spinodal decomposition process [63], [114]. <lb/>Moreover, the theory of far from equilibrium critical dynamics can be related <lb/>to the equilibrium phase transition theory, as both include local metastable <lb/>states characterized by spinodal lines and spinodal phase transitions. <lb/> 5 Is Complexity the Road for the Final Unification <lb/>of the Physical Theory? New Concepts for an Old <lb/>Problem. <lb/> The old problem in physics is the unification of mechanics and thermodynam-<lb/>ics. For Albert Einstein, physical theory must correspond objectively to the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Chaotic Modeling and Simulation (CMSIM) 1: 123–145, 2012 <lb/></note>

			<page>135 <lb/></page>

			<body> physical reality. Thus, the hard core of a final physical theory must be the <lb/>mathematical determinism. For Heisenberg, Bohr and Born, physical theory <lb/>has to be related to the phenomenology of reality. Because of this, probabil-<lb/>ism is the unavoidable hard core of every physical theory. On the other hand, <lb/>the hard core of complexity is nonlinearity. Nonlinear dynamics includes de-<lb/>terminism in the form of periodic attractors with integer dimension as well <lb/>as probabilism in the form of chaotic fractal attractors. From this point of <lb/>view we understand that there exists an internal connection between nonlinear <lb/>dynamics and thermodynamics since entropy is a propabilistic property of a dy-<lb/>namical system. Nonlinear deterministic dynamics including strong irregularity <lb/>of chaotic mixing or f  *  exact type, includes thermodynamical characteristics <lb/>[72]. Such a type of strongly nonlinear unstable determinism is equivalent also <lb/>to stochastic or probabilistic dynamics [74], [83], [111]. <lb/>Moreover determinism and probabilism can be interrelated also through <lb/>Rochlin theorem [112] according to which every f  *  exact transformation is the <lb/>factor of a k automorphism. In this way Boltzmann&apos;s (stochastic) dynamics can <lb/>be proved to be the trace of Liouville&apos;s (deterministic) dynamics or the Boltz-<lb/>mann&apos;s equation is the trace of Liouville equation [72]. In the same direction <lb/>quantum probabilism can be related to classical determinism and dissipation <lb/>according to [32], [49]. Another significant character of nonlinear deterministic <lb/>dynamics is the bifurcation profile of solutions and the critical point dynamics <lb/>(near or far from equilibrium) as the pattern formation or morphogenesis char-<lb/>acter [47]. According to Wilson [135] the critical physical theory related to the <lb/>dynamics must take into account the entire spectrum of length scales from 10 <lb/> −8 <lb/> cm to 10 <lb/> 11  cm. However, more than this it seems that complexity and nonlin-<lb/>ear dynamics includes the theoretical kernel for a global unification of physical <lb/>theory, as we argue in a previous study by Pavlos et al. [101]. Critical dynamics <lb/>showed the significance of renormalization group theory, the scale invariance <lb/>principle related to fractal geometry, as well as the relation of dynamics with <lb/>topological and dimensional characteristics of space. However, the deep ques-<lb/>tion of complexity theory is how forms are generated in nature and what is <lb/>the relationship between physical forces and the stable geometries of morpho-<lb/>genesis and pattern formation. According to Kovacs [67] somehow space-time <lb/>symmetries create the fundamental laws of nature. Moreover, it could be pos-<lb/>sible to imagine some extended kind of geometrical invariance principle and <lb/>novel topological characteristics to produce every kind of pattern, according to <lb/>the dream of Einstein, concerning the geometrical unification of physical theory <lb/>and physical dynamics. According to El Naschie [36], [39] and Ord [87] non-<lb/>commutative geometries and fractal space-time can be used for the extension <lb/>of complexity from the macroscopic to the microscopic level. Scale invariance <lb/>principles also can be used for the unification of microscopic and macroscopic <lb/>complexity. Some efficient evidence for such a dream we present indicatively <lb/>in the following. <lb/></body>

			<page> 136 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> G. P. Pavlos <lb/></note>

			<page> 6 Complexity as a New Physical Theory <lb/></page>

			<body> Is Complexity a major revolution in science such as Relativity and Quan-<lb/>tum Theory? For many scientists attempts to explain complexity and self-<lb/>organization by using the basic laws of physics have met with little success. <lb/>Novel forms of self-organization are generally unexpected for the classic re-<lb/>ductionistic point of view. However, while complexity is considered as a new <lb/>and independent physical theory which was developed after the Relativity The-<lb/>ory and Quantum mechanics, it must be consistent with these theories. It is <lb/>related to far from equilibrium dynamics and concerns the creation and destruc-<lb/>tion of spatiotemporal patterns, forms and structures. According to Balescu <lb/>[8], Nicolis and Prigogine [78], [79], Nicolis [80], [81], and Prigogine [110], [111], <lb/>complexity theory corresponds to the flow and development of space-time corre-<lb/>lations instead of the fundamental local interactions. According to the classical <lb/>point of view the physical phenomena (macroscopic or microscopic) must be <lb/>reducible to a few fundamental interactions. However, according to Nicolis [82], <lb/>since 1960 an increasing amount of experimental data challenging this idea has <lb/>become available. This impose a new attitude concerning the description of <lb/>Nature. Moreover, according to Sornette [118], systems with a large number <lb/>of mutually interacting parts and open to their environment can self-organize <lb/>their internal structure and their dynamics with novel and sometimes surpris-<lb/>ing macroscopic emergent properties. These general characteristics make the <lb/>complexity theory, a fundamentally probabilistic theory of the non-equilibrium <lb/>dynamics. <lb/> 7 Complexity as a Form of Macroscopic Quanticity <lb/> The central point of complexity theory is the possibility for a physical sys-<lb/>tem, which includes a great number of parts or elements, to develop internal <lb/>long-range correlations leading to macroscopic ordering and coherent patterns. <lb/>These long-range correlations can also appear at the quantum level. In partic-<lb/>ular, according to the general entanglement character of the Quantum theory, <lb/>the quantum mechanical states of a system with two or more parts cannot be <lb/>expressed as the conjunction of quantum states of the separate parts. This <lb/>situation generally reflects the existence of non-local interactions and quantum <lb/>correlations while the measurements bearing on either part correspond to ran-<lb/>dom variables which are not independent and can be correlated independently <lb/>with the spatial distance of the parts [116]. This means that the quantum den-<lb/>sity operator cannot be factored while the quantum state corresponds to the <lb/>global and undivided system. The macroscopic manifestation of the quantum <lb/>possibility for the development of long-range correlations is the spontaneous <lb/>appearance of ordered behavior in a macroscopic system, examples of which <lb/>are phenomena like superfluidity and superconductivity or lasers [68]. <lb/>These quantum phenomena display coherent behavior involving the col-<lb/>lective cooperation of a huge number of particles or simple elements and a <lb/>vast number of degrees of freedom. They correspond also to equilibrium or <lb/>nonequilibrium phase transition processes which constitute the meeting point <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Chaotic Modeling and Simulation (CMSIM) 1: 123–145, 2012 <lb/></note>

			<page>137 <lb/></page>

			<body> of quantum theory and complexity. Here the development of quantum long-<lb/>range correlations leads to a macroscopic phase transition process and macro-<lb/>scopic ordering. It is not out of logic or physical reality to extend the (unifying) <lb/>possibility of quantum process to developed long-range correlations, according <lb/>to the quantum entanglement character, into a macroscopic self-organizing fac-<lb/>tor causing also the far-from equilibrium symmetry breaking and macroscopic <lb/>pattern formation. From this point of view we can characterize complexity as <lb/>a form of a macroscopic quanticity [34], [135]. <lb/> 8 Quantum Theory as a Form of Microscopic Chaoticity <lb/>and Complexity <lb/> Bohm and Hiley [21] imagined that the Quantum theory must be the mani-<lb/>festation of subquantum complex dynamics. During the last years, we observe <lb/>the productive onset or the impetus invasion of chaos and complexity from <lb/>macroscopic to the microscopic quantum level. In the following we present <lb/>some novel concepts in this direction: <lb/> • Determinism at the Planck&apos;s scale [49]-[51]. <lb/> • Order and deterministic chaos at the quantum level [32] <lb/> • Analytical continuation and fractal space-time can convert an ordinary dif-<lb/>fusion equation into a Schrodinger&apos;s equation and a telegraph equation <lb/>into a Dirac&apos;s equation. From this point of view analytical continuation is <lb/>a short cut of quantization [76], [77]. <lb/> • Positive Lyapunov exponents of non-abelian gauge fields reveal the signifi-<lb/>cance of chaos for the quantum field theory [20]. <lb/> • Coupled map lattices with spatiotemporal chaotic profile can be used to <lb/>simulate quantum field theories in an appropriate scaling limit [17], [22]. <lb/> • Kaneko&apos;s coupled map lattices including chaotic strings provide the back-<lb/>ground for the Parisi-Wu stochastic quantization of ordinary string and <lb/>quantum field theories [14], [15]. Chaotic strings can be used also to pro-<lb/>vide a theoretical argument why certain standard model parameters are re-<lb/>alized in nature reproducing numerical values of the electroweak and strong <lb/>coupling constants masses of the known quarks and leptons neutrino, W <lb/>boson and Higg&apos;s mass. <lb/> • Renormalization group (RG) flows on the superstring world sheet becomes <lb/>chaotic and leads to non-Markovian Fokker-Planck equation with solutions <lb/>describing the transition from order to chaos and revealing the Feigenbaum <lb/>universal constant [65]. The appearance of this constant reveals the scaling <lb/>of space-time curvatures at the fixed points of the RG flow which becomes <lb/>chaotic near singularities where the curvature is very large [75], [105]. <lb/> • The Parisi-Wu [89] stochastic quantization theory relates the quantum field <lb/>theory in D-dimensions to a classical Langevin equation in D+1-dimensions <lb/> where the Parisi-Wu fictitious time plays the role of an extra dimension. <lb/>In this picture there exists a short of classical stochasticity and quantum <lb/>theory duality [33]. The stochastic quantization can be transformed to <lb/>chaotic quantization, similar to chaotic deterministic dynamical systems <lb/></body>

			<page> 138 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> G. P. Pavlos <lb/></note>

			<body> which can generate Langevin dynamics in an appropriate scaling limit. In <lb/>this approach, quantum field theories can be simulated by chaotic dynamics <lb/> • Non-extensive statistics [123], fractal string and branes, fractal statistics, <lb/>fractons and anyons particles as well as chaotic M(atrix) theory indicate the <lb/>establishment of chaos and complexity at the microscopic and the quantum <lb/>level [22]. In this direction, Gerardus &apos;t Hooft raised the conjecture that <lb/>quantum theory can be derived as the low-energy limit of a microscopically <lb/>deterministic but dissipative theory [50]. According to this concept clas-<lb/>sical Perron-Frobenius operators or deterministic automata can produce <lb/>quantum states in Hilbert spaces as well as the Schrodinger equation [1], <lb/>[9], [35], [42]. <lb/>After all, we can imagine that quantum states are produced by a sub-<lb/>quantum self-organized process. This sub-quantum self-organization must con-<lb/>cern information process rather than simple material or energy self-organization. <lb/> 9 Universality of Tsallis non-extensive statistical <lb/>mechanics <lb/> According to Tsallis, Boltzmann-Gibbs statistical mechanics and standard ther-<lb/>modynamics do not seem to be universal. Tsallis extended the Boltzmann-<lb/>Gibbs statistics and Boltzmann-Gibbs entropy to non-extensive statistical me-<lb/>chanics and non-extensive q-entropies. The classical Boltzmann-Gibbs exten-<lb/>sive thermostatistics constitutes a powerful tool when microscopic interactions <lb/>and memory are short ranged and space-time is a continuous and differentiable <lb/>Euclidean manifold. However, far from equilibrium these characteristics are <lb/>changed as multiscale coupling and non-locality characteristics can appears. In <lb/>turbulence for example, the presence of long-range correlations imply non-local <lb/>interactions between large and small scales as the relation between them is not <lb/>local in space and time but functional. This indicates that small-scale fluctua-<lb/>tions in each time space point depend on the large scale motions in the whole <lb/>time-space domain and vice versa. Generally, the non-extensive statistical me-<lb/>chanics introduced by Tsallis rather than being just a theoretical construction <lb/>it is relevant to many complex systems at the macroscopic or the microscopic <lb/>level with long-range correlations-interactions or multifractal behavior. A cru-<lb/>cial property of Tsallis entropy S  q  is the pseudo-additivity for given subsystems <lb/>A and B in the sense of factorizability of the microstate according to the rela-<lb/>tions S  q  (A + B) = S  q  (A) + S  q  (B) + (1 − q)S  q  (A)S  q  (B) where S  q  = k  B <lb/> (1− <lb/> p <lb/> q <lb/> i <lb/> q−1 <lb/> and k  B  is Boltzmann&apos;s constant. The non-local coupling and long-range cor-<lb/>relations of complex dynamics corresponds to the multiplicative tern of the <lb/>previous relation. Also, the non-extensive behavior of macroscopic or micro-<lb/>scopic complexity is related to the non-Euclidean and multi-fractal space time <lb/>[22], [46], [58], the quantum gravity and quantum entanglement [122]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Chaotic Modeling and Simulation (CMSIM) 1: 123–145, 2012 <lb/></note>

			<page>139 <lb/></page>

			<body> 10 The road of Complexity for the Physical Theory <lb/>Unification <lb/> According to previously presented concepts and descriptions, about the nonequi-<lb/>librium statistical mechanics, the Feynman rules and diagrams become common <lb/>tool from the estimation of probabilistic processes at the microscopic quantum <lb/>level or the macroscopic level of continuous media as they are being described by <lb/>the Ginzburg-Landau model [13], [19], [47]. In this direction, we could imagine <lb/>Feynman rules and renormalization group theory as the universal characteris-<lb/>tics of probabilistic processes at the microscopic and the macroscopic level. The <lb/>renormalization group equations have many common features with non-linear <lb/>dynamical systems, so that apart from existence of isolated fixed points, the <lb/>coupling in a renormalizable field theory may flow also towards more general <lb/>even fractal attractors. This could lead to Big Mess scenarios in application <lb/>to multiphase systems, from spin-glasses and neural networks to fundamental <lb/>string theory [75]. In this direction Cristopher Hill [46] introduced the fractal <lb/>theory space where the key idea is that the Feynman path integral is invariant <lb/>under a sequence of renormalization group transformations that map the kth <lb/> lattice into the k − 1 lattice. In the continuum limit these models produced <lb/>quantum field theories in fractal dimensions D. These theories are connected <lb/>to the scaling behavior of fractal strings (branes), while the couplings oscillate <lb/>on a limit cycle. Moreover the concept of fractal space-time can be used for <lb/>the foundation of an extended Einsteins Relativity Principle unifying the micro <lb/>and macro levels [84], [85]. <lb/>In this direction, [87] showed that fractal trajectories in space with Hans-<lb/>dorff dimension D = 2 exhibit both an uncertainty principle and a De Broglie <lb/>wave -particle duality relations. Furthermore, Nottale [84], [85] introduced <lb/>the principle of Scale Relativity according to which the laws of physics are <lb/>scale invariant. This theory is related also to the concept of fractal space-<lb/>time. According to Nottale, the consequence of scale invariance principle and <lb/>space-time fractality opens the door for a grand unification of cosmos, from <lb/>the microscopic quantum level to the macroscopic and cosmological level. The <lb/>starting point of the theory is the refusing of the unjustified assumption of <lb/>the differentiability of the space-time continuum. The non-differentiable space-<lb/>time continuum is necessarily fractal. The development of the theory starts by <lb/>making the various physical quantities explicitly dependent on the space-time <lb/>scale while the fundamental laws become also scale dependent. In this frame of <lb/>theory the non-differentiability of space-time implies the breaking of time re-<lb/>versibility, and the global unification of microscopical and macroscopical laws, <lb/>[37], [56], [57], [86], [103]. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1.Arefëva, I.Ya., Medvedev, P.B., Rytchkov, O.A. &amp; Volovich, I.V. [1999] &quot; Chaos in <lb/>M(atrix) Theory &quot; , Chaos, Solitons &amp; Fractals 10, p. 213. <lb/>2.Argyris J., I. Andreadis, G.P. Pavlos, M. Athanasiou [1998] &quot; The influence of noise <lb/>in the correlation dimension of chaotic attractors &quot; , Chaos, Solitons &amp; Fractals <lb/> 9(3), p. 343-361. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 140 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> G. P. Pavlos <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> 3.Argyris J., I. Andreadis, G.P. Pavlos, M. Athanasiou [1998] &quot; On the influence of <lb/>noise on the Largest Lyapunov exponent and on the geometric structure of at-<lb/>tractors &quot; , Chaos, Solitons &amp; Fractals 9(6), p. 947-958. <lb/>4.Argyris, J., L. Tenek, I. Andreadis, M. Athanasiu, and G.P. Pavlos [1998] &quot; On <lb/>chaotic oscillations of a laminated composite cylinder subject to periodic appli-<lb/>cation of temperature &quot;  Chaos, Solitons &amp; Fractals 9(9), p. 1529-1554. <lb/>5.Argyris J., I. Andreadis, G.P. Pavlos, M. Athanasiou [2000] &quot; On a classification of <lb/>dynamic systems subject to noise &quot;  Chaos, Solitons &amp; Fractals 11, p. 297-302. <lb/>6.Athanasiu,M.A. &amp; Pavlos, G.P. [2001] &quot; SVD Analysis of the magnetospheric AE in-<lb/>dex time series and comparison with low dimensional chaotic dynamics, &quot;  Nonlin. <lb/>Proc. Geophys. 8, p. 95-125. <lb/>7.Athanasiu M.A., G.P. Pavlos, D.V. Sarafopoulos, and E.T. Sarris [2003] &quot; SVD <lb/>Analysis of the magnetospheric AE index time series and comparison with low <lb/>dimensional chaotic dynamics, &quot;  Nonlin. Proc. Geophys. 8, p. 95-125. <lb/>8.Balescu, R. [1975] &quot; Equilibrium and nonequilibrium statistical mechanics &quot; , Copy-<lb/>right, Wiley, J., New York. <lb/>9.Banks, T., Fischler, W., Shenker, S.H. &amp; Susskind, L. [1997] &quot; M theory as a matrix <lb/>model: A conjecture &quot; , Phys. Rev. D, 55, p. 5112. <lb/>10.Bak, P., Tang, C. &amp; Wiesenfeld, K. [1988] &quot; Self Organized Criticality &quot;  Phys. Rev. <lb/>A 38(1), p. 364-374. <lb/>11.Bak, P. [1996] How Nature Works, (Springer-Verlag New York, Inc). <lb/>12.Baker, D.N., Klimas, A.J., McPherro, R.L. &amp; Buchner, J. [1990] &quot; The evolution <lb/>from weak to strong geomagnetic activity: An interpretation in terms of deter-<lb/>ministic chaos &quot;  Geophys. Res. Lett. 17, p. 41. <lb/>13.Bausch, R., Jansshen, H.K. &amp; Wagner, H. [1976] &quot; Renormalized Field Theory of <lb/>Critical Dynamics &quot; , Z.Physik, B24, p. 113. <lb/>14.Beck, C. [1991] &quot; Higher correlation functions of chaotic dynamical systems-a graph <lb/>theoretical approach &quot; , Nonlinearity, 4, p. 1131. <lb/>15.Beck, C. [1995] &quot; Chaotic quantization of field theories &quot; , Nonlinearity, 8, p. 423. <lb/>16.Beck, C. [2001] &quot; Dynamical Foundations of Nonextensive Statistical Mechanics &quot; , <lb/> Phys. Rev. Let., 87, p. 180601-1. <lb/>17.Beck, C. [2002] &quot; Nonextensive methods in turbulence and particle physics &quot; , Hysica <lb/>A, 305, p. 209. <lb/>18.Ben Zion, Y., Eneva, M. &amp; Liy, Y. [2003] &quot; Large earthquake cycles and intermit-<lb/>tent criticality on heterogeneous faults due to evolving stress and seismicity &quot; , J. <lb/>Geophys. Res., 108, p. 2307. <lb/>19.binne, J.J., Dowrick, N.J., Fisher, A.J. &amp; Newman, M.E.J. [1993] &quot; Theo theory of <lb/>critical phenomena &quot; , Oxford Universiy Press, New York. <lb/>20.Biro, T., Muller, B. &amp; Matinyan, S. [2004] &quot; Chaotic Quantization: Maybe the <lb/>Lord plays dice, after all? &quot; , Lecture Notes in Physics, 633, p. 164. <lb/>21.Bohm, D. &amp; Hilley, B. [1993] &quot; The undivided universe &quot; , Routledge, London. <lb/>22.Castro, C. [2005] &quot; ., On non-extensive statistics, chaos and fractal strings &quot; , Physica <lb/>A 347, p. 184. <lb/>23.Chang, T., Nicoll, J.F. &amp; Young, J.E. [1978] &quot; A closed-form differential renormal-<lb/>ization group generator for critical dynamics &quot; , Phys. Lett., 67A(4), p. 287-290. <lb/>24.Chang, T. [1992] &apos; &quot; Low-Dimensional Behavior and Symmetry Braking of Stochas-<lb/>tic Systems near Criticality Can these Effects be Observed in Space and in the <lb/>Laboratory &quot; , IEEE 20(6), p. 691-694. <lb/>25.Chang, T., Vvedensky, D.D. &amp; Nicoll, J.F [1992] &quot; Differential Renormalization <lb/>Group Generators for static and dynamic critical phenomena &quot; , Physics Reports, <lb/> 217(6), p. 279-360. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> Chaotic Modeling and Simulation (CMSIM) 1: 123–145, 2012 <lb/></note>

			<page>141 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>26.Chang, T. [1999] &quot; Self-organized criticality, multi-fractal spectra, sporadic local-<lb/>ized reconnections and intermittent turbulence in the magnetotail &quot; , Physics of <lb/>Plasmas, 6(11), p. 4137-4145. <lb/>27.Chang, T., Tam, S.W.Y., Wu, C-C, &amp; Consolini, G [2003] &quot; Complexity, Forced <lb/>and/or Self-Organized Criticality, and Topological Phase Transitions in Space <lb/>Plasmas &quot; , Space Sci. Rev., 107, p. 425-445. <lb/>28.Chapman, S.C., Watkins, N.W., Dendy, R.O., Helander, P. &amp; Rowlands, G. [1998] <lb/> &quot; A simple avalanche model as an analogue for magnetospheric activity &quot; , Geo-<lb/>physical Research Letters, 25(13), p. 2397-2400. <lb/>29.Chate, H. &amp; Manneville, P. [1989] &quot; Role of defects in the transition to turbulence <lb/>via spatiotemporal intermittency &quot; , Physica D, 37, p. 33-41. <lb/>30.Chate, H. [1995] &quot; On the analysis o spatiotemporally chaotic data &quot; , Physica D, <lb/> 86, p. 238-247. <lb/>31.Consolini, G., [1997] &quot; Sandpile cellular automata and magnetospheric dynamics &quot; , <lb/>8th GIFCO Conference: Cosmic physics in the year 2000, p. 123 -126. <lb/>32.Contopoulos, G., Efthymiopoulos, C. &amp; Harsoula, M. [2008] &quot; Order and chaos in <lb/>quantum mechanics &quot;  Non. Phenom. Complex Systems, 11, p. 107. <lb/>33.Damgaard, P. &amp; Huffel, H. [1987] &quot; Stochastic Quantization &quot; , Phys. Rev. Let., 152, <lb/> p. 227. <lb/>34.Davies, P. [1987] &quot; The Cosmic Blueprint &quot; , William Heinemann Ltd., Great Britain. <lb/>35.De Wit, B. [1988] &quot; On the quantum mechanics of supermembranes &quot; , Nuclear <lb/>Physics B, 305, p. 545. <lb/>36.El Naschie, M.S. [1998] &quot; Superstrings, Knots, and Noncommutative Geometry in <lb/>E(infinity) Space &quot; , Int. Journal of Theoretical Physics, 37, p. 2935. <lb/>37.El Naschie, M.S. [2004] &quot; A review of E infinity theory and the mass spectrum of <lb/>high energy particle physics &quot; , Chaos, Solitons &amp; Fractals, 19, p. 209-236. <lb/>38.El Naschie, M.S. [2005] &quot; Einstein&apos;s dream and fractal geometry &quot; , Chaos, Solitons <lb/>&amp; Fractals, 24, p. 1. <lb/>39.El Naschie, M.S. [2006] &quot; Elementary prerequisites for E-infinity (Recommended <lb/>background readings in nonlinear dynamics, geometry and topology) &quot; , Chaos, <lb/>Solitons &amp; Fractals, 30, p. 579. <lb/>40.Evison, F.F. [2001] &quot; Long-range synoptic earthquake forecasting: An aim for the <lb/>millennium, &quot;  Tectonophys., 338, p. 207-215. <lb/>41.Freeman, W.J. [1987] &quot; Simulation of chaotic EEG patterns with a dynamic model <lb/>of the olfactory system &quot; , Biol.Cybern., 56, p. 139-150. <lb/>42.Frohlich, J. &amp; Hoppe, J. [1998] &quot; On Zero-Mass Ground States in Super-Membrane <lb/>Matrix Models &quot; , Commun.Math.Phys., 191, p. 613. <lb/>43.Glansdorff, P. &amp; Prigogine, I. [1973] &quot; Thermodynamic Theory of Structure, Sta-<lb/>bility and Fluctuations &quot; , Am. J. Phys., 41(1), p. 147. <lb/>44.Grassberger, P. &amp; Procaccia, I. [1983] &quot; Measuring the strangeness of strange at-<lb/>tractors &quot; , Physica D: Nonlinear Pgenomena, 9, p. 189. <lb/>45.Haken, H. [1983] Synergetics: Introduction and Advanced Topics, Springer. <lb/>46.Hill, C. &quot; Fractal theory space: Spacetime of noninteger dimensionality &quot; , Phys. <lb/>Rev. D, 67, p. 085004. <lb/>47.Hohenberg, P. &amp; Halperin, B. &quot; Theory of dynamic critical phenomena &quot; , Rev. of <lb/>Mod. Phys., 49, p. 435. <lb/>48.Hohenberg, P.C. &amp; Shraiman, B.I. [1989] &quot; Chaotic behavior of an extended sys-<lb/>tem &quot; , Physica D, 37, p. 109-115. <lb/>49.Hooft, G.T. [1999] &quot; Quantum gravity as a dissipative deterministic system &quot; , Class. <lb/>Quantum Grav., 16, p. 3263-3279. <lb/>50.Hooft, G.T. [2001a] &quot; Determinism and Dissipation in Quantum Gravity &quot; , Basics <lb/>and highlights in fundamental physics: proceedings of the International School of <lb/>Subnuclear Physics, 37, p. 397. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 142 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> G. P. Pavlos <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> 51.Hooft, G.T. [2001b] &quot; How Does God Play Dice?(Pre) Determinism at the Planck <lb/>Scale &quot; , An Essay in Honor of John S. Bell, arXiv:hep-th/0104219. <lb/>52.Iasemidis L.D., &amp; Sackellares, J.C. [1996] &quot; Chaos Theory and Epilepsy &quot; , The Neu-<lb/>roscientist, 2, p. 118-126. <lb/>53.Iliopoulos, A., Pavlos, G. &amp; Athanasiu, M. [2008] &quot; Spatiotemporal Chaos into <lb/>the Hellenic Seismogenesis: Evidence for a Global Strange Attractor &quot; , Nonlin. <lb/>Phenom. Complex Sys. 11(2), p. 274. <lb/>54.Iliopoulos, A. &amp; Pavlos, G. [2010] &quot; Global Low Dimensional Seismic Chaos in the <lb/>Hellenic Region, &quot;  Intern. J. Bifurc. Chaos 20(7), p. 2071. <lb/>55.Iliopoulos, A.C., Pavlos, G.P., Papadimitriou, E., Sfiris, D. [2011] &quot; Chaos, Self Or-<lb/>ganized Criticality, Intermittent Turbulence and Nonextensisvity Revealed from <lb/>Seismogenesis in North Aegean Area &quot;  submitted. <lb/> 56.Iovane, G. [2006a] &quot; Cantorian spacetime and Hilbert space: Part I-Foundations &quot; , <lb/>Chaos, Solitons &amp; Fractals, 28, p. 857-878. <lb/>57.Iovane, G. [2006b] &quot; Cantorian space-time and Hilbert space: Part II-Relevant <lb/>consequences &quot; , Chaos, Solitons &amp; Fractals, 29, p. 1-22. <lb/>58.Jizba, P. &amp; Arimitsu, T. [2004] &quot; The world according to Renyi: thermodynamics <lb/>of multifractal systems &quot; , Annals of Physics, 312, p. 17. <lb/>59.Kagan, Y. Y. [1994] &quot; Observational evidence for earthquakes as a nonlinear dy-<lb/>namic process &quot;  Physica D, 77, p. 160-192. <lb/>60.Karakatsanis, L.P. &amp; Pavlos, G.P. [2008] &quot; Self Organized Criticality and Chaos <lb/>into the Solar Activity &quot; , Nonlinear Phenomena in Complex Systems, 11(2), p. <lb/>280-284. <lb/>61.Karakatsanis, L.P., Pavlos, G.P., Iliopoulos, A.C. &amp; Tsoutsouras, V.G. [2010] &quot; Ev-<lb/>idence for Coexistence of SOC and Chaos processes in the Solar Flare Dynamics &quot; , <lb/>Modern Challenges in Nonlinear Plasma Physics, Accepted for publication, Ac-<lb/>cepted for publication, eds. Vassiliadis, D., American Institute of Physics. <lb/>62.Karakatsanis, L.P., Pavlos, G.P., Iliopoulos, A.C., Tsoutsouras, V.G. &amp; Pavlos, <lb/>E.G., &quot; Evidence for Coexistence of SOC, Intermittent Turbulence and Low-<lb/>Dimensional Chaos Processes in Solar Flare Dynamics, AIP Conf. Proc., 1320, <lb/> pp. 55-64. <lb/>63.Klein, W., Gould, H., Gulbahce, N., Rundle, J.B. &amp; Tiampo, K. [2007], &quot; Structure <lb/>of fluctuations near mean-field critical points and spinodals and its implication <lb/>for physical processes &quot; , Phys. Rev. E, 75, p. 031114 <lb/>64.Klimas, A.J, Valdivia, J.A., Vassiliadis, D., Baker, D.N., Hesse, M. &amp; Takalo, J. <lb/>[2000] &quot; Self-organized criticality in the substorm phenomenon and its relation to <lb/>localized reconnection in the magnetospheric plasma sheet &quot; , J. Geophys. Res., <lb/> 105, p. 18765-18780. <lb/>65.Kogan, I. &amp; Polyakov, D. [2003] &quot; Chost-Matter Mixing and Feigenbaum Univer-<lb/>sality in String Theory &quot; , Physics of Atomic Nuclei, 66, p. 2062. <lb/>66.Korn, H., &amp; Faure, P. (2003), &quot; Is there chaos in the brain? II. Experimental <lb/>evidence and related models &quot; , C.R. Biologies, 326, p. 787-840. <lb/>67.Kovas, A.L. [1994] &quot; Nonlinear Dynamics of Spatio-Temporal Processes in Complex <lb/>Systems &quot; , Mathl. Comput. Modelling, 19, p. 47. <lb/>68.Leggett, A. [1989] &quot; Low temperature physics, superconductivity and superfluid-<lb/>ity &quot; , in Davies, Cambridge University Press <lb/>69.Linkenkaer-Hansen K., [2002] &quot; Self-Organized Criticality and Stochastic Reso-<lb/>nance in the Human Brain &quot; , Helsinki University of Technology, Laboratory of <lb/>Biomedical Engineering. <lb/>70.Lu, E.T. [1995] &quot; Avalanches in continuum driven dissipative systems &quot; , Phys. Rev. <lb/>Lett., 74, p. 13. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> Chaotic Modeling and Simulation (CMSIM) 1: 123–145, 2012 <lb/></note>

			<page>143 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>71.Lyra, M. L. &amp; Tsa lis C. [1998] &quot; Nonextensivity and Multifractality in Low-<lb/>Dimensional Dissipative Systems, &quot;  Phys. Rev. Lett. 80(1), p. 53-56. <lb/>72.Mackey, G.W. [1989] &quot; The dynamic origin of increasing entropy &quot; , Rev. Mod. Phys., <lb/> 61, p. 981. <lb/>73.Mayer-Kress, G. &amp; Kaneko, K. [1989] &quot; Spatiotemporal Chaos and Noise &quot; , Journal <lb/>of Statistical Physics, 54, p.1489. <lb/>74.Misra, B., Prigogine, I. &amp; Courbage, M. [1979] &quot; From deterministic dynamics to <lb/>probabilistic descriptions &quot; , Physica A, 98, p. 1. <lb/>75.Morozov, A. &amp; Niemi, J. [2006] &quot; Can Renormalization Group Flow End in a Big <lb/>Mess? &quot; , Nuclear Physics B, 666, p. 311. <lb/>76.Nelson, E. [1966] &quot; Derivation of the Schrodinger equation from Newtonian me-<lb/>chanics &quot; , Phys. Rev., 150, p. 1079. <lb/>77.Nelson, E. [1985] &quot; Quantum Fluctuations &quot; , Princeton University Press, New York. <lb/>78.Nicolis, G. &amp; Prigogine, I. [1971] &quot; Fluctuations in nonequilibrium systems &quot;  Proc. <lb/>Nat. Acad. Sci. 68x, p. 2102. <lb/>79.Nicolis, G. &amp; Prigogine, I. [1977] &quot; Self-organization in nonequilibrium systems: <lb/>From dissipative structures to order through fluctuations &quot; , Willey, New York. <lb/> 80.Nicolis, G. [1979] &quot; Irreversible thermodynamics &quot; , Rep. Prog. Phys., 42, p. 225. <lb/>81.Nicolis, G. [1986] &quot; Dissipative Systems &quot; , Rep. Prog. Phys., 49, p. 873. <lb/>82.Nicolis, G. [1989] &quot; Physics of Far-From-Equilibrium Systems and Self-<lb/>organisation &quot; , in Davies, Cambridge University Press. <lb/>83.Nicolis, G. &amp; Prigogine, I. [1989] &quot; Exploring Complexity: An Introduction &quot; , eds. <lb/>Freeman, W.H., San Francisco. <lb/>84.Nottale, L. [1993] &quot; Fractal Space-Time and Micro-physics &quot; , Towards a Theory of <lb/>Scale Relativity, eds. World Scientific. <lb/>85.Nottale, L. [1994] &quot; Scale Relativity, Fractal Space-time and Quantum Mechanics &quot; , <lb/> Chaos, Solitons &amp; Fractals, 4, p. 361. <lb/>86.Nottale, L. [1996] &quot; Scale Relativity and Fractal Space-Time: Applications to Quan-<lb/>tum Physics, Cosmology and Chaotic Systems &quot; , Chaos, Solitons &amp; Fractals, 7, <lb/> p. 877. <lb/>87.Ord, G.N. [1983] &quot; Fractal space-time: a geometric analogue of relativistic quantum <lb/>mechanics &quot; , J. Phys. A: Math. Gen., 16, p. 1869. <lb/>88.Paczuski M., Maslov S. &amp; Bak P., &quot; Avalanche dynamics in evolution, growth, and <lb/>depinning models &quot; , Phys. Rev. E, 53, p. 414. <lb/>89.Parisi, G. &amp; Wu, Y. [1981] &quot; Perturbation theory without gauge fixing &quot; , Scientia <lb/>Sinica, 25(4), p. 484. <lb/>90.Pavlos, G.P., [1988] &quot; Magnetospheric dynamics &quot; , in Proc. Symposium on Solar <lb/>and Space Physics, eds. Dialetis, D., National Observatory of Athens, p. 1-43. <lb/>91.Pavlos, G.P., Trochoutsos, P.C., Liatsis, P., Rigas, A.G &amp; Tsonis, T., [1991] &quot; Ev-<lb/>idence of low dimensional chaotic dynamics in solar wind plasma &quot; , XVI EGS, <lb/>General Assebly, Wiesbaden. <lb/>92.Pavlos, G.P., Rigas, A.G., Dialettis, D., Sarris, E.T., Karakatsanis, L.P. &amp; Tsonis, <lb/>A.A., [1992a] &quot; Evidence for Chaotic Dynamics in the outer Solar Plasma and <lb/>the Earth Magnetosphere &quot; , Chaotic Dynamics: Theory and Practice, NATO <lb/>ASI Series B:Physics, Plenum Press, New York, 298, p. 327-339. <lb/>93.Pavlos G.P., Dialettis, D., Kyriakou, G.A. &amp; Sarris, E.T. &quot; A Preliminary low-<lb/>dimensional Chaotic Analysis of the solar Cycle &quot; , Ann. Geophysicae, 10, p. 759-<lb/>762. <lb/>94.Pavlos G.P., Kyriakou, G.A., Rigas, A.G., Liatsis, P., Trochoutsos, P.C. &amp; Tsonis, <lb/>A.A. [1992c] &quot; Evidence for Strange Attractor Structures in Space Plasmas &quot; , Ann. <lb/>Geophysicae, 10,, p. 309-322. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 144 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> G. P. Pavlos <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> 95.Pavlos, G.P., Diamantidis, D., Adamopoulos, A., Rigas, A.G., Daglis, I.A. &amp; Sar-<lb/>ris, E.T. [1994a] &quot; Chaos and Magnetospheric Dynamics &quot; , Nonlinear Processes in <lb/>Geophysics, 1, p. 124-135. <lb/>96.Pavlos, G. P., Latousakis, I., Dialettis, D., Karakatsanis, L.P. &amp; Papaioannou, G. <lb/>[1994b] &quot; Chaotic analysis of a time series composed of seismic events recorded in <lb/>Japan &quot; , Int. J. Bifurcation and Chaos, 4, p. 87-98. <lb/>97.Pavlos, G.P., Athanasiou, M., Diamantidis, D., Rigas, A.G. &amp; Sarris, E.T. [1999] <lb/> &quot; Comments and new results about the magnetospheric chaos hypothesis &quot; , Non-<lb/>lin. Proc. Geophys., 6, p. 99-127. <lb/>98.Pavlos, G.P., Iliopoulos, A.C. &amp; Athanasiu, M. [2007] &quot; Self Organized Criticality <lb/>or / and Low Dimensional Chaos in Earthquake Processes. Theory and Practice <lb/>in Hellenic Region &quot; , Nonlinear Dynamics in Geosciences, eds. Tsonis A. &amp; Elsner <lb/>J. , (Springer), p. 235-259. <lb/>99.Pavlos, G.P., Tsoutsouras, V.G., Iliopoulos, L.P. &amp; Athanasiou, M. [2008a] &quot; Self <lb/>Organized Criticality (SOC) and Chaos Behavior in the Brain Activity &quot;  10th <lb/>volume of the series Order and Chaos, eds. Boundis A. &amp; Pnevmatikos S, (Uni-<lb/>versity of Patras Press), p. 145. <lb/>100.Pavlos, G.P., Iliopoulos, A.C., Karakatsanis, L.P. &amp; Athanasiou, M.A. [2008b] <lb/> &quot; The Broad Universality of the Stochastic Unification of SOC, Chaos and other <lb/>Nonlinear Processes &quot;  10th volume of the series Order and Chaos, eds. Boundis <lb/>A. &amp; Pnevmatikos S, (University of Patras Press), p. 157-167. <lb/>101.Pavlos, G.P., Iliopoulos, A.C., Tsoutsouras, V.G., Karakatsanis, L.P. &amp; Pavlos, <lb/>E.G. [2010a] &quot; Spatiotemporal Chaos in Distributed Systems: Theory and Prac-<lb/>tice &quot;  Chaotic Systems: Theory and applications, eds. Skiadas C. H. &amp; Dimotikalis <lb/>I., (World Scientific), p. 268-283. <lb/>102.Pavlos, G.P., Iliopoulos, A.C., Athanasiou, M.A., Karakatsalis, L.P. &amp; Tsout-<lb/>souras, V.G. [2010b] &quot; Complexity in Space Plasmas: Universality of Non-<lb/>equilibrium physical Processes &quot; , Modern Challenges in Nonlinear Plasma <lb/>Physics, Accepted for publication, eds. Vassiliadis, D., American Insittute of <lb/>Physics. <lb/>103.Pavlos, G.P., Iliopoulos, A.C., Karakatsanis, L.P., Tsoutsouras, V.G. &amp; Pavlos, <lb/>E.G. [2010c] &quot; Complexity Theory and Physical Unification: From Microscopic <lb/>to Macroscopic level &quot; , Submitted for Publication. <lb/> 104.Pavlos, G.P., Iliopoulos, A.C, Tsoutsouras, V.G., Sarafopoulos, D.V., Sphiris, <lb/>D.S., Karakatsanis, L.P. &amp; Pavlos, E.G. [2011] &quot; First and Second Order Non-<lb/>equilibrium Phase Transition and Evidence for Non-extensive Tsallis Statistics <lb/>in Earth&apos;s Magnetosphere &quot; , Submitted for Publication. <lb/> 105.Polyakov, D. [2001] &quot; Ads / CFT correspondence, critical strings and stochastic <lb/>quantization &quot; , Class. Quantum Grav., 18, p. 1979. <lb/>106.Polygiannakis J., Preka-Papadema, P., Moussas, X. [2003], &quot; On signalnoise de-<lb/>composition of timeseries using the continuous wavelet transform: application to <lb/>sunspot index &quot; , Mon. not. R. Astron. Soc., 343, p. 725-734. <lb/>107.Price, C.P. &amp; Prichard, D.J. [1993] &quot; The non-linear response of the magneto-<lb/>sphere: 30 October 1978 &quot; , Geophys. Res. Lett., 20, p. 771-774. <lb/>108.Price, C.P., Prichard, D.J. &amp; Bischoff, J.E. [1994] &quot; Nonlinear Input/Output Anal-<lb/>ysis of the Auroral Electrojet Index &quot; , J. Geophys. Res., 99, p. 13227-13238. <lb/>109.Prichard, D.J. [1995] &quot; Short comment for magnetospheric chaos &quot; , Nonlinear Proc. <lb/>Geophysics, 20, p. 771-774. <lb/>110.Prigogine, I. [1977] &quot; Time, structure and fluctuations &quot; , Nobel Lecture. <lb/>111.Prigogine, I. [1996] &quot; La Fin des Certitudes &quot; , Editions Odile Jacob. <lb/>112.Rochlin, V.A. [1964] &quot; Exact endomorphisms of Lebesque spaces &quot; , Am. Math. Soc. <lb/>Tansl., 39, p. 1. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> Chaotic Modeling and Simulation (CMSIM) 1: 123–145, 2012 <lb/></note>

			<page>145 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>113.Ruzmaikin, A.A. [1985] &quot; The solar Dynamo &quot; , Solar Physics, 100, p. 125-140. <lb/>114.Schweiger, A.O., Baros, K. &amp; Klein, W. [2007] &quot; Transient nucleation near the <lb/>mean-field spinodal &quot; , Phys. Rev. E, 75, p. 031102. <lb/>115.Shaw, R. [1984] &quot; The dripping faucet as a model chaotic system, &quot; The Science <lb/>Frontier Express Series (Aerial Press, Santa Cruz). <lb/>116.Shimony, A. [1989] &quot; Conceptual foundations of quantum mechanics &quot; , in Davies, <lb/>Cambridge University Press. <lb/>117.Sitnov, M.I., Sharma, A.S., Papadopoulos, K., &amp; Vassiliadis, D. [2001] &quot; Model-<lb/>ing substorm dynamics of the magnetosphere: From self-organization and self-<lb/>organized criticality to nonequilibrium phase transitions &quot; , Phys. Rev. E, 65, p. <lb/>016116. <lb/>118.Sornette, Didier [2006] &quot; Probability Distributions in Complex Systems, &quot;  En-<lb/>cyclopedia of Complexity and Systems Science, ed. Meyer, R.A., (Springer), p. <lb/>7009-7024. <lb/>119.Sykes, L.R. et al. [1999] &quot; Rethinking Earthquake Prediction &quot;  Pure Apll. Geophys. <lb/> 155, p. 207-232. <lb/>120.Takens, F. [1981] &quot; Detecting strange attractors in turbulence &quot; , Lecture Notes in <lb/>Mathematics, eds. D.A. Rand and L.S. Young, 898, p. 366. <lb/>121.Theiler, J., Galdikian, B., Longtin, A., Eubank, S., Farmer, J.D. [1992a] &quot; Us-<lb/>ing surrogate data to detect nonlinearity in time series &quot; , Nonlinear Modeling <lb/>and Forecasting, vol. XII of SFI studies in the Sciences of Complexity, eds. M. <lb/>Casdagli and S. Eubank, p.163. <lb/>122.Tsallis, C. [1988] &quot; Possible Generalization of Boltzmann-Gibbs Statistics &quot; , J. <lb/>Stat. Phys., 52, p. 479. <lb/>123.Tsallis, C. [2009] &quot; Introduction to Nonextensive Statistical Mechanics &quot; , Springer. <lb/>124.Tsonis A. [1992] &quot; Chaos: From Theory to Applications &quot; , Kluwer Academic Pub-<lb/>lications. <lb/>125.Tsonis A. [2008] &quot; Randomnicity: rules and randomness in the realm of the infi-<lb/>nite &quot; , Imperial College Press. <lb/>126.Tsoutsouras, V., Sirakoulis, G.,Pavlos, G., Iliopoulos, A. [2011] &quot; Simulation of <lb/>healthy and epileptiform brain activity using cellular automata &quot; , submitted. <lb/> 127.Tsuda I., [2001] &quot; Toward an interpretation of dynamic neural activity in terms <lb/>of chaotic dynamical systems &quot; , Behav. Brain. Sci., 24, p. 793-810. <lb/>128.Uritsky, V.M. &amp; Pudovnik, M.I. [1998] &quot; Low frequency 1/f-like fluctuations of <lb/>the AE-index as a possible manifestation of self-organized criticality in the mag-<lb/>netosphere &quot; , Ann. Geophysicae, 16, p. 1580. <lb/>129.Vassiliadi, D., Sharma, A.S. &amp; PApadopoulos, K. [1991] &quot; Lyapunov exponent of <lb/>magnetospheric activity from AL time series &quot; , Geophys. Res. Let., 18, p. 1643. <lb/>130.Vassiliadis, D., Sharma, A.S., Papadopoulos, K. [1992] &quot; Time series analysis of <lb/>magnetospheric activity using nonlinear dynamical methods &quot; , Chaotic Dyan-<lb/>mics: Theory and Practise &quot; , ed. Bountis, T., Plenum, (New York). <lb/>131.Vieira, M.S. [1999] &quot; Chaos and synchronized chaos in an earthquake model &quot; , <lb/> Phys. Rev. Lett., 82, p. 201-204. <lb/>132.Vlahos, L. ESA Publications, 505, p. 105. <lb/>133.Wang, J-X. [1995] &quot; Sporadic chaos in space-time dynamical processes &quot; , Physical <lb/>Review E 52, p. 1318. <lb/>134.West B.J., [1990] &quot; Fractal Physiology and Chaos in Medicine &quot; , World Scientific <lb/>Publishing Co. Pte. Ltd. <lb/>135.Wilson, K. [1983] &quot; The renormalization group and critical phenomena &quot; , Rev. <lb/>Mod. Phys., 55, p.583. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 146 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> G. P. Pavlos <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> 136.Zompakis, N., Bartzas, A., Tsoutsouras, V., Soudris, D. &amp; Pavlos, G. [2010] <lb/> &quot; Dynamic Frequency Scaling for MPSoCs based on Chaotic Workload Analysis &quot; , <lb/> ARCS &apos;10 -23th International Conference on Architecture of Computing Systens <lb/>2010 -23th International Conference on Architecture of Computing Systems, <lb/> Hannover, Germany </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
