<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> 32ND INTERNATIONAL COSMIC RAY CONFERENCE, BEIJING 2011 <lb/> The search for extremely high-energy neutrinos with IceCube <lb/> THE ICECUBE COLLABORATION <lb/> 1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> See special section in these proceedings <lb/> Abstract: The IceCube neutrino telescope was constructed to search for high energy neutrinos of cosmic origin. At <lb/>the highest energies, neutrinos associated with the interaction of the most energetic cosmic rays with cosmic microwave <lb/>background photons (GZK effect) are considered a guaranteed signal, with expected event rates of up to a few events <lb/>per year in a cubic kilometer detector. Searches for GZK neutrinos have been performed using data taken with the <lb/>intermediate construction stages of the now complete IceCube detector. We present the results of finished and on-going <lb/>analyses, with a focus on the search using data taken between spring 2009 and spring 2010, when the IceCube detector <lb/>was roughly 70% complete. <lb/> Corresponding authors: Henrike Wissing <lb/> 2  (hwissing@icecube.umd.edu), Aya Ishihara <lb/> 3  (aya@hepburn.s.chiba-u.ac.jp) <lb/> 2  University of Maryland. College Park, MD 20742, USA <lb/> 3  Chiba University, Chiba 263-8522, Japan <lb/> Keywords: IceCube, GZK neutrinos, EHE neurtinos <lb/></front>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> The detection of extremely-high energy (EHE) neutrinos <lb/>with energies in excess of 10 <lb/> 7 <lb/> GeV may shed light on the <lb/>yet unknown origin of the highest energy cosmic rays. <lb/>The direct observation of EHE charged cosmic ray parti-<lb/>cles is limited by their inevitable energy loss in the cos-<lb/>mic microwave background through photo-pion produc-<lb/>tion, known as the Greisen-Zatsepin-Kuzmin (GZK) ef-<lb/>fect [1]. The trajectories of the charged cosmic ray par-<lb/>ticles with diminished energies will have been random-<lb/>ized in cosmic magnetic fields upon arrival at the Earth. <lb/>Neutrinos from the decays of the secondary charged pions, <lb/> π <lb/> ±  → μ <lb/> ±  ν  μ  → e <lb/> ±  ν  e  ν  μ  ν  μ  , will travel in straight lines and <lb/>unattenuated over cosmological distances and carry infor-<lb/>mation about the sources of EHE cosmic rays. <lb/>The IceCube neutrino observatory consists of a cubic kilo-<lb/>meter sized Cherenkov detector embedded in the 2800 m <lb/>thick glacial ice cap at the South Pole and an overlying <lb/>square kilometer surface air-shower array. The in-ice de-<lb/>tector consists of 5160 light sensitive digital optical mod-<lb/>ules (DOMs) deployed at depths between 1450 and 2450 m <lb/>on 86 vertical cables ( &quot; strings &quot; ). Each DOM is equipped <lb/>with a 25 cm photo-multiplier tube (PMT) along with two <lb/>waveform digitizers and supporting data acquisition, cali-<lb/>bration, and control hardware [2, 3]. Interactions of high <lb/>energy neutrinos with the surrounding matter are detect-<lb/>ed via their Cherenkov emissions in the highly transparent <lb/>Polar ice [4]. With its large detection volume, the in-ice de-<lb/>tector is the first neutrino telescope with a realistic chance <lb/>to detect the small flux of EHE neutrinos associated with <lb/>the GZK effect. <lb/>During IceCube&apos;s construction phase, which started in <lb/>2005, data taken with the partially instrumented in-ice neu-<lb/>trino telescope have been searched for signatures of EHE <lb/>neutrinos [5, 6]. The analysis of data taken during the years <lb/>2008/2009, when 40 of the 86 strings of the in-ice detector <lb/>were deployed, has led to the currently most stringent lim-<lb/>its on fluxes of EHE neutrinos with energies between 1 PeV <lb/>and 10 EeV (Figure 1). In these proceedings, we report on <lb/>a search for EHE neutrinos in data taken with the 59-string <lb/>detector between spring 2009 and spring 2010. <lb/> 2 Method <lb/> The vast majority of the events recorded by IceCube are <lb/>due to down-going atmospheric muons that are created by <lb/>interactions of high energy cosmic rays in the atmosphere, <lb/>and which are sufficiently energetic to penetrate the ice <lb/>overburden and deposit Cherenkov light in the detector. A-<lb/>gainst this background, an EHE neutrino interaction inside <lb/>or in the vicinity of the detector would stand out with a <lb/>much higher Cherenkov light deposition. Figure 2 shows <lb/>the expected light deposition in terms of the number of <lb/>recorded photo-electrons (NP E) and its correlation with <lb/>the zenith angle (cos Θ) of the primary particle tracks for <lb/>simulated GZK neutrino induced events and simulated at-<lb/></body>

			<front> DOI: 10.7529/ICRC2011/V02/0949 <lb/></front>

			<page> Vol. 2, 157 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> ICECUBE EHE NEUTRINO SEARCH <lb/></note>

			<body> (Energy/GeV) <lb/> 10 <lb/> log <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>1 0 <lb/>] <lb/> -1 <lb/> sr <lb/> -1 <lb/> sec <lb/> -2 <lb/> (E) [GeV cm <lb/> φ <lb/> 2 <lb/> E <lb/> -10 <lb/>-8 <lb/>-6 <lb/>-4 <lb/> -10 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -9 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -8 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -7 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -6 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> WB bound <lb/> A  N IT A <lb/> PA O <lb/> YT ESS <lb/> IC -2 2 <lb/> IC-40 GZK <lb/> IC-40 UHE <lb/> Figure 1: Present flux limits on EHE neutrinos compared <lb/>to two all flavor GZK neutrino flux predictions, YT ((m, <lb/> Z  max  ) = (4,4) [7] and ESS (Ω  Λ  = 0.7) [8], and the <lb/>Waxman-Bahcall bound [9]. Limits from IceCube 40-<lb/>string GZK neutrino search (IC-40 GZK, differential limit <lb/>and E <lb/> −2 <lb/> spectrum integrated limit) [6] are shown as thick <lb/>black lines, the limit from an UHE neutrino search (IC-40 <lb/>UHE) [10] is shown as grey horizontal line. Less stringent <lb/>limits were set by Auger (PAO) [11], ANITA [12], and the <lb/>IceCube 22-string detector (IC-22) [5]. <lb/>mospheric background events. For both signal and back-<lb/>ground events, the light yield is strongly correlated with <lb/> cos Θ. For down-going atmospheric muon events, the ex-<lb/>pected NP E rapidly decreases with increasing inclination <lb/>of primary particle track, because with increasing slan-<lb/>t depth the muons will lose more energy before reaching <lb/>the detector. Below the horizon (cos Θ &lt; 0), low energy at-<lb/>mospheric neutrinos arriving from the opposite hemisphere <lb/>are the only expected background. The detection probabil-<lb/>ity of GZK neutrinos is highest for directions close to the <lb/>horizon, because of the relatively short neutrino interaction <lb/>length at EHE energies. <lb/>Exploiting the correlation between the event light yield and <lb/>the track direction, the data selection criteria to separate <lb/>signal from background events in IceCube&apos;s EHE neutrino <lb/>searches have routinely been designed as two-dimensional <lb/>boundaries in the NP E-cos Θ-plane [5, 6]. Simple geo-<lb/>metric fit methods, whose performance proved robust a-<lb/>gainst systematic uncertainties in the detector response, <lb/>were used to infer the track directions. In this analysis, <lb/>we follow the same strategy, but we use a different fitting <lb/>algorithm than previous analyses to determine the track di-<lb/>rection. <lb/>Following a blind analysis procedure, the selection criteria <lb/>are optimized on simulated signal and background events. <lb/>A subset of 10% of the experimental data, evenly distribut-<lb/>ed throughout the data taking period, is used to validate the <lb/>detector simulation. After the selection criteria are devel-<lb/>oped, the data selection is applied to the blinded 90% of the <lb/>data, which for the 2009/2010 data-taking period roughly <lb/>comprises 330 days of detector livetime. The 10% subset <lb/>is discarded, in order to avoid statistical bias. <lb/> 3 Monte Carlo simulations <lb/> The dominant background at the final data selection level-<lb/>s is high multiplicity muon bundles induced predominant-<lb/>ly by heavy cosmic ray primaries with PeV to EeV en-<lb/>ergies. This background was simulated with the CORSI-<lb/>KA air-shower simulation [13] using the SIBYLL 2.1 [14] <lb/>hadronic interaction model. Two primary types, proton <lb/>and iron, with energies between 10 <lb/> 4 <lb/> and 10 <lb/> 11 <lb/> GeV were <lb/>simulated. The primaries were sampled from a power-law <lb/>energy spectrum following dN/dE ∝ E <lb/> −2 <lb/> , in oder to <lb/>over-sample the high energy end of the cosmic ray spec-<lb/>trum, which is most important to this analysis. Proton and <lb/>iron components are then re-weighted to broken power-law <lb/>spectra, whose combination approximates the all particle <lb/>spectrum at PeV energies and above [15]. <lb/>Signal events induced by EHE neutrinos in the energy <lb/>range between 10 <lb/> 5 <lb/> and 10 <lb/> 11 <lb/> GeV were simulated with <lb/>the JULIeT package [16]. The charged secondary particles <lb/>were sampled from an energy spectrum ∝ E <lb/> −1 <lb/> . The events <lb/>can be re-weighted to various GZK neutrino flux predic-<lb/>tions. In these proceedings, we use the predictions from <lb/>references [7] and [8] (c. f. YT and ESS in Figure 1). The <lb/>quoted event rates correspond to the sum of all three neu-<lb/>trino flavors, ν  e  , ν  μ  , and ν  τ  . <lb/> 4 Event selection <lb/> The first data selection for the various IceCube analyses is <lb/>performed on-line at the South Pole, before data are sent to <lb/>the northern hemisphere. For this analysis, the on-line filter <lb/>required a minimum of 630 photo-electrons to be recorded <lb/>in an event. <lb/>Following the analysis strategy that was developed for the <lb/>40-string detector [6], further data reduction is achieved by <lb/>requiring at least 200 DOMs to have registered light within <lb/>a time window of [−4.4μs, 6.4μs] around the largest local <lb/>light deposition in the detector. The latter is defined as the <lb/>time at which 10% of the largest PMT pulse was captured. <lb/>Further, we require the total number of photo-electrons <lb/>recorded in this time window to be larger than 3200. With <lb/>these requirements, the atmospheric background is reduced <lb/>by two orders of magnitude, while 75% of the signal is re-<lb/>tained (Table 1). While the previous EHE search used the <lb/> linefit algorithm [17, 5] to reconstruct the track direction-<lb/>s, we use a different algorithm in this analysis, the dipolefit <lb/> [17]. The dipolefit assigns a dipole moment, <lb/>M , to the light <lb/>pattern recorded in each event: <lb/>M = <lb/>1 <lb/> NDOM <lb/> 2 <lb/> · <lb/> NDOM  <lb/> i= <lb/> N DOM <lb/> 2 <lb/> +1 <lb/> r  i  − r  i− <lb/> N DOM <lb/>2 <lb/> | r  i  − r  i− <lb/> N DOM <lb/>2 <lb/> | <lb/> , <lb/> (1) <lb/></body>

			<page> Vol. 2, 158 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> 32ND INTERNATIONAL COSMIC RAY CONFERENCE, BEIJING 2011 <lb/></note>

			<body> (NPE) <lb/> 10 <lb/> log <lb/> 2.5 <lb/>3 <lb/>3.5 <lb/>4 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>5 <lb/>5.5 <lb/>6 <lb/>6.5 <lb/>7 <lb/> events / 330 days <lb/> -4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 6 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 7 <lb/> 10 <lb/> background <lb/>experimental <lb/>GZK (YT) <lb/> 1 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> (NPE) <lb/> 10 <lb/> log <lb/> 3 <lb/>3.5 <lb/>4 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>5 <lb/>5.5 <lb/>6 <lb/>6.5 <lb/>7 <lb/> Θ <lb/> cos <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.8 <lb/>-0.6 <lb/>-0.4 <lb/>-0.2 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> background <lb/> -5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> (NPE) <lb/> 10 <lb/> log <lb/> 3 <lb/>3.5 <lb/>4 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>5 <lb/>5.5 <lb/>6 <lb/>6.5 <lb/>7 <lb/> Θ <lb/> cos <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.8 <lb/>-0.6 <lb/>-0.4 <lb/>-0.2 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> GZK (YT) <lb/> Figure 2: Expected light yield (logarithm of the number of detected photoelectrons, log  10  (NP E)), for simulated signal <lb/>and background events and a subset of the experimental data set (left) and the correlation with the cosine of the zenith <lb/>angle of the primary particle tracks for simulated atmospheric background events (middle) and GZK neutrinos (right). <lb/>The background prediction includes cosmic ray induced muons, assuming a cosmic ray spectrum according to [15], and <lb/>atmospheric neutrinos according to [18] with a contribution from prompt neutrinos according to [19]. The GZK neutrino <lb/>spectrum is simulated according to [7] (c. f. YT in Figure 1). <lb/>cut <lb/>Experimental <lb/>Background GZK YT [7] GZK ESS [8] <lb/> NP E &gt; 630 <lb/>6.20 × 10 <lb/> 7 <lb/> (6.86 ± 0.18) × 10 <lb/> 7 <lb/> 2.35 ± 0.01 <lb/>1.81 ± 0.01 <lb/> NP E &gt; 3200 and N  DOM  &gt; 200 <lb/>6.65 × 10 <lb/> 5 <lb/> (7.68 ± 0.12) × 10 <lb/> 5 <lb/> 1.80 ± 0.01 <lb/>1.38 ± 0.01 <lb/>log  10  (NP E) − 0.5 · D &gt; 4 <lb/>336 <lb/>365 ± 6 1.39 ± 0.01 <lb/>1.07 ± 0.01 <lb/> Table 1: Expected event rates at various selection levels for 330 days of detector livetime. The signal rates correspond to <lb/>the GZK neutrino models according to [7] (YT) and [8] (ESS). Errors are statistical only. <lb/>where r  i  is the vector of spatial coordinates of the DOM <lb/>that recorded the ith light signal in time, and N  DOM  is the <lb/>total number of DOMs fired in the event. The magnitude of <lb/>the dipole moment | <lb/>M | takes values between 0 and 1, and <lb/>provides a measure for the directionality of the light flow in <lb/>the event: large values of | <lb/>M | indicate a track-like signal, <lb/>while small values indicate a rather spherical light pattern. <lb/>EHE neutrino interactions typically yield small dipole mo-<lb/>ments. Cascades induced by ν  e  and ν  τ  interactions natu-<lb/>rally generate spherical light patterns, and the light pattern <lb/>from ν  μ  induced EHE muons has a broad radial distribu-<lb/>tion. Low energy atmospheric muon events on the other <lb/>hand, typically have dipole moments close to 1. <lb/>Figure 3 shows the correlation between the magnitude <lb/>and the direction (cos Θ  M  ) of the dipole moment for at-<lb/>mospheric background events and GZK neutrino signal. <lb/>Background events cluster in the region with large dipole <lb/>moments and down-going directions. A combination of <lb/>both magnitude and direction of the dipole moment, D = <lb/>cos Θ  M  + 2 · | <lb/>M |, is used as a measure of the similarity <lb/>of an event to a down-going track. Compared to a cut on <lb/>the reconstructed direction only, a larger fraction of the ex-<lb/>tremely bright EHE neutrino signal events is preserved. <lb/>Background events with low values of D are predomi-<lb/>nantly induced by low energy neutrinos and atmospher-<lb/>ic muons that pass outside the instrumented volume and <lb/>deposit only very little Cherenkov light. Figure 4 shows <lb/>the correlation of D with the light yield NP E. Signal <lb/>and background events are well separated in the D-NP E-<lb/> plane. A two-dimensional cut in this plane defined by <lb/> (log  10  (NP E) − 0.5 · D) &gt; 4 reduces the atmospheric <lb/>background by two more orders of magnitude, while the <lb/>expected GZK neutrino signal still exceeds one event in <lb/>330 days (Table 1). <lb/>Additional selection criteria to separate the GZK signal <lb/>events from the remaining background are being investigat-<lb/>ed. A realistic chance to detect a GZK neutrino signal re-<lb/>quires the further selection criteria to keep the signal expec-<lb/>tation above 1 event, while suppressing the background to a <lb/>level of O(0.1) expected events per year. The GZK neutri-<lb/>no search with the 40-string detector [6] achieved a signal <lb/>expectation of 0.5 events for GZK models presented here, <lb/>above an expected background of roughly 0.1 events at the <lb/>final selection level. With the larger 59-string detector, im-<lb/>proved event selection criteria, and better understanding of <lb/>the detector response, the required signal to background ra-<lb/>tio to either detect GZK neutrinos or to constrain the here <lb/>considered flux predictions seems within reach. <lb/> 5 Conclusions <lb/> The detection of GZK neutrinos with IceCube seems tan-<lb/>talizingly close. The analysis of data taken with an inter-<lb/>mediate construction stage of the detector, in which half <lb/>the in-ice detector was deployed, allowed to place the most <lb/>stringent limits on EHE neutrinos to-date. Data taken with <lb/>later construction stages are presently being analyzed. Al-<lb/>ready the next construction stage, which roughly 70% of <lb/> 

			<page>Vol. 2, 159 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> ICECUBE EHE NEUTRINO SEARCH <lb/></note>

			 1 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> ) <lb/> M <lb/> Θ <lb/> cos( <lb/> -1 -0.8 -0.6 -0.4 -0.2 0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 1 <lb/> | <lb/> M <lb/> | <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1  background <lb/> -5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> ) <lb/> M <lb/> Θ <lb/> cos( <lb/> -1 -0.8 -0.6 -0.4 -0.2 0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 1 <lb/> | <lb/> M <lb/> | <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1 <lb/> GZK (YT) <lb/> −1 <lb/>−0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3 <lb/> events / 330 days <lb/> −4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> background <lb/>experimental <lb/>GZK (YT) <lb/> D <lb/> Figure 3: Observables of the dipolefit. The magnitude of the dipole moment | <lb/> M | versus the reconstructed zenith angle <lb/>(cos Θ  M  ) for simulated background events (left) and simulated signal events (middle). The linear combination D = <lb/>cos Θ  M  + 2 · | <lb/>M | (right), is a measure the similarity of the event to a down-going track. <lb/> (NPE) <lb/> 10 <lb/> log <lb/> 3.5 <lb/>4 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>5 <lb/>5.5 <lb/>6 <lb/>6.5 <lb/>7 <lb/>7.5 <lb/> D <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3 <lb/> 1 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> background <lb/> (NPE) <lb/> 10 <lb/> log <lb/> 3.5 <lb/>4 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>5 <lb/>5.5 <lb/>6 <lb/>6.5 <lb/>7 <lb/>7.5 <lb/> D <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3 <lb/> -5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> GZK <lb/>(YT) <lb/> (NPE) − 0.5 D <lb/> 10 <lb/> log <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/> events / 330 days <lb/> −4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> background <lb/>experimental <lb/>GZK (YT) <lb/> Figure 4: Correlation of the combined dipole observable D = cos Θ  M  + 2 · | <lb/>M | with NP E for simulated background <lb/>events (left) and simulated signal events (middle). The linear combination of D and NP E that is used as a cut parameter <lb/>is shown in the right panel. The separating boundary defined by log  10  (NP E) − 0.5 · D &gt; 4 is shown as black lines in <lb/>the two dimensional plots. <lb/>the detector components deployed, may reach the sensitiv-<lb/>ity to probe current models of GZK neutrino fluxes. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] K. Greisen, Phys. Rev. Lett. 16, 748 (1966). G. T. Zat-<lb/>sepin and V. A. Kuzmin, Pisma Zh. Eksp. Teor. Fiz. 4, <lb/> 114 (1966) [JETP. Lett. 4, 78 (1966)]. <lb/>[2] R. Abbasi et al. (IceCube Collaboration), Nucl. In-<lb/>strum. Meth. A618, 139 (2010). <lb/>[3] R. Abbasi et al. (IceCube Collaboration), Nucl. In-<lb/>strum. Meth. A601, 294 (2009). <lb/>[4] M. Ackermann et al. (IceCube Collaboration), J. Geo-<lb/>phys. Res. 111, D13203 (2006). <lb/>[5] R. Abbasi et al. (IceCube Collaboration), <lb/>Phys. Rev. D82, 072003 (2010). <lb/>[6] R. Abbasi et al (IceCube Collaboration), Phys. Rev. <lb/> D83, 092003 (2011). <lb/>[7] S. Yoshida and M. Teshima, Prog. Theor. Phys. 89, 833 <lb/>(1993). <lb/>[8] R. Engel, D. Seckel, and T. Stanev, Phys. Rev. D64, <lb/> 093010 (2001). <lb/>[9] E. Waxman and J. Bahcall, Phys. Rev. D59, 023002 <lb/>(1999). S. Razzaque, P. Meszaros, and E. Waxman, <lb/>Phys. Rev. D68, 083001 (2003). <lb/>[10] H. Johansson, PhD Thesis, Stockholm University, <lb/>Sweden (2011). <lb/>[11] J. Abraham et al. (Pierre Auger Collaboration), <lb/>Phys. Rev. D79, 102001 (2009). <lb/>[12] P. W. Gorham et al. (ANITA Collaboration), <lb/>Phys. Rev. D82, 022004 (2010); arXiv:1011.5004 (er-<lb/>ratum). <lb/>[13] D. Heck et al., Report FZKA 6019 (Forschungszen-<lb/>trum Karlsruhe 1998). <lb/>[14] E. J. Ahn, R. Engel, T. K. Gaisser, P. Lipari, and T. S-<lb/>tanev, Phys. Rev. D80, 094003 (2009). <lb/>[15] R. Glasstetter et al., Proc. 26th ICRC, Salt Lake City, <lb/>USA (1999). <lb/>[16] S. Yoshida et al., Phys. Rev. D69, 103004 (2004). <lb/>[17] J. Ahrens et al. (IceCube Collaboration), Nucl. In-<lb/>strum. Meth. A524, 169 (2004). <lb/>[18] M. Honda et al., Phys. Rev. D75, 043006 (2007). <lb/>[19] E. Bugaev et al., Phys. Rev. D58, 054001 (1998). <lb/> </listBibl>

			<page> Vol. 2, 160 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
