<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> SF2A 2010 <lb/> S. Boissier, M. Heydari-Malayeri, R. Samadi and D. Valls-Gabaud (eds) <lb/> HAVE WE SEEN DARK MATTER ANNIHILATION IN THE COSMIC-RAY <lb/>ELECTRON AND POSITRON SPECTRA <lb/> J. Lavalle  1 <lb/> Abstract. Measurements of a rise in the cosmic positron fraction up to ∼ 100 GeV by the PAMELA <lb/>satellite have triggered putative interpretation attempts in terms of dark matter (DM) annihilation or decay, <lb/>even though generic DM particle models are not expected to contribute to this signal. Here, we review the <lb/>tricks that have been invoked to make DM-induced signals fit the data. We also recall how considering <lb/>conventional astrophysical sources — supernova remnants (SNRs) and pulsars — in a consistent cosmic-ray <lb/>(CR) propagation framework can easily explain these observations, despite large theoretical uncertainties. <lb/>Although this does not dismiss potential DM contributions, this unfortunately makes the related background <lb/>far too difficult to control for discovery purposes. Though the positron puzzle appears qualitatively solved <lb/>in terms of standard astrophysics, substantial improvements in the CR source and propagation modelings <lb/>are now clearly necessary to improve our understanding of the Galactic CR lepton budget and associated <lb/>multi-wavelength diffuse emissions. <lb/>Keywords: dark matter, cosmic-ray propagation, cosmic-ray sources, pulsars, supernova remnants <lb/></front>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> Indications of an increase in the CR positron fraction above a few GeV have been collected for quite a long <lb/>time (Fanselow et al. 1969; Golden et al. 1987; Barwick et al. 1997; Alcaraz et al. 2000), but the recent PAMELA <lb/>measurements have reached an unprecedented statistics allowing much more detailed analyses (Adriani et al. <lb/>2009). It turns out that this increase can hardly be explained in terms of secondary positrons <lb/>  *  (Moskalenko &amp; <lb/>Strong 1998; Delahaye et al. 2009), though peculiar spatial effects are still worth being investigated into more <lb/>details (Shaviv et al. 2009) — see also the original proposal by Roberts (2010) about a possible solar magnetic <lb/>lens effects. <lb/>Antimatter CR excess signals as potential probes of DM annihilation were first proposed by Silk &amp; Srednicki <lb/>(1984) after one became aware of the power of gamma-ray and CR observations to constrain the DM properties <lb/>(e.g. Gunn et al. 1978; Stecker 1978; Zeldovich et al. 1980). Later, as already mentioned by Tylka (1989), Baltz <lb/>&amp; Edsjö (1998) showed in detail that annihilation of supersymmetric neutralinos, one of the most popular DM <lb/>candidate so far, could hardly generate observable features in the local positron spectrum unless the annihilation <lb/>rate is substantially boosted, suggesting that DM substructures could play this amplifier role, following the idea <lb/>of Silk &amp; Stebbins (1993). It was recently shown that such subhalos can actually hardly be at the origin of the <lb/>large required enhancement (Lavalle et al. 2007, 2008b), and that even an isolated such dark source, as proposed <lb/>in Cumberbatch &amp; Silk (2007), would lead to tensions with current gamma-ray constraints (Bringmann et al. <lb/>2009). Despite this apparent failure of dark matter particle models to naturally yield CR positrons in sufficient <lb/>amount, an impressive number of papers has been released in the past few years to try to explain the PAMELA <lb/>data in terms of DM annihilation or decay. We will discuss a few aspects of the available proposals below, but <lb/>it is already worth noticing that all these works assumed the absence of astrophysical sources of positrons but <lb/>secondaries when fitting the data. <lb/></body>

			<front> 1  Universià di Torino &amp; INFN, Dipartimento di Fisica Teorica, Via Giuria 1, 10125 Torino — Italia <lb/>(from Oct. 2010: Instituto de Física Teórica (IFT), Madrid — Spain). e-mail: lavalle@in2p3.fr, lavalle@to.infn.it, <lb/>julien.lavalle@uam.es <lb/>  *  For the non-expert reader, a primary cosmic ray is produced — or/and accelerated — at sources, whereas a secondary cosmic <lb/>ray originates from nuclear interactions between primary CR nuclei and the interstellar gas (ISG). <lb/>c <lb/> Société Francaise d&apos;Astronomie et d&apos;Astrophysique (SF2A) 2010 <lb/></front>

			<page> 370 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">SF2A 2010 <lb/></note>

			<body> Although interpretations in terms of standard astrophysical sources were only a few in the past decades (e.g. <lb/>Arons 1981; Harding &amp; Ramaty 1987; Boulares 1989; Aharonian et al. 1995; Chi et al. 1996), they all relied <lb/>on quite sound physical arguments: pulsars were already predicted to produce a significant amount of electron-<lb/>positron pairs only few years after their discovery (e.g. Sturrock 1970), which is now indirectly proven from <lb/>the more recent observations of gamma-rays originating from pulsar magnetospheres. Another way to generate <lb/>primary-like positrons, also relying on standard astrophysics and recently widely surveyed, is to invoke the <lb/>diffusive acceleration of those secondary positrons created at SNR shocks (e.g. Berezhko et al. 2003; Blasi 2009). <lb/>Nevertheless, we will focus here on the pulsar solution when discussing standard astrophysical explanations of <lb/>the positron excess. <lb/>The outline of this proceeding is the following. We first recall the bases of electron-positron propagation in <lb/>the Galaxy. Then, we revisit the case for the DM interpretation of the cosmic positron excess, showing how <lb/>contrived this attempt can be. Afterwards, we discuss the requirements a model of astrophysical CR electrons <lb/>and positrons should obey. We emphasize that including pulsars as positron sources can naturally lead to a good <lb/>fit of the PAMELA data, with quite reasonable parameters. Finally, we conclude and discuss a few perspectives. <lb/> 2 Electron and positron propagation in the galaxy <lb/> Reviews and books on CR propagation are numerous, and we refer the reader to e.g. Strong et al. (2007) <lb/>for a recent review, and to Berezinskii et al. (1990) and Longair (1992, 1994) for valuable books. A detailed <lb/>description of CR electron <lb/>  †  propagation can be found in Delahaye et al. (2010). <lb/>Once produced, stable charged CRs (among which electrons) in the GeV-TeV energy range may experience <lb/>different processes. The dominant ones are diffusion in space (due to scattering with magnetic turbulences <lb/>and to convective winds) and diffusion in momentum (energy losses — negligible for CR nuclei — and diffusive <lb/>reacceleration — negligible above a few GeV). Electron propagation in this energy range is almost completely set <lb/>by spatial diffusion and energy losses, the latter being due to inverse Compton interactions with the interstellar <lb/>radiation field (ISRF, including the CMB) and the Galactic magnetic field (synchrotron). In steady state and <lb/>when convection is neglected, the master propagation equation associated with an electron density N ≡ dn/dE <lb/> reads − <lb/> ∇ <lb/> K(E, x) <lb/> ∇N (E, x) <lb/> − ∂  E  {b(E) N (E, x)} = Q(E, x) , where Q is the source term, K(E, x) is the <lb/>diffusion coefficient, and b(E) = −dE/dt is the energy loss rate; being set by Compton interactions,the latter <lb/>strongly increases with energy (b(E) ∝ E <lb/> 2  in the Thomson approximation). The typical energy loss timescale <lb/>is τ  l  ≈ 10 <lb/> 16  s at 1 GeV for Galactic electrons. Note that the diffusion coefficient can, in most of relevant <lb/>situations, be considered as homogeneous, and is usually modeled as a power law, K(E)  K  0  (E/E  0  ) <lb/> δ  . The <lb/>normalization and index can be determined from observed secondary-to-primary ratios of nuclei species which <lb/>mostly depend on K  0  /L, where L is the half-thickness of the diffusion zone (see e.g. Maurin et al. 2001; Putze <lb/>et al. 2010) — values are usually found close to K  0  (E  0  = 1 GeV) ≈ 3.4 × 10 <lb/> 27  cm <lb/> 2  /s, δ ≈ 0.7 and L ≈ 4 <lb/>kpc. The above equation (without spatial boundaries) admits a solution in the form of a Green function <lb/> G(E, x ← E  s  , x  s  ) = <lb/> exp <lb/> − <lb/> ( xs− x) 2 <lb/> λ 2 <lb/> b(E)(π λ  2  ) <lb/> 3 <lb/>2 <lb/> with λ <lb/> 2  ≡ 4 <lb/>  Es <lb/>E <lb/> dE <lb/>  K(E <lb/>  ) <lb/> b(E   )  , where λ is mean propagation scale, of the <lb/>order of <lb/> √ <lb/> K  0  τ  l  ≈ 2 kpc, i.e. usually less than L (spatial boundaries can therefore be neglected to a good <lb/>approximation): due to the very efficient energy losses, electrons with energies above a few tens of GeV are <lb/>mostly local. This Green function allows the computation of the electron density at the Earth given a source <lb/>term Q(E  s  , x  s  ) which features the spatial and energy distributions before propagation. <lb/>Primary and secondary CRs of astrophysical origin are injected in the Galactic plane, where the stan-<lb/>dard sources (SNRs and pulsars) and the ISG are located. For secondary positrons, which will constitute the <lb/> &quot; background &quot; in the next sections of this proceeding, one can approximate the source term as a power law <lb/>spectrum of index γ  s  , reminiscent from the CR nuclei index, and flatly distributed in the Galactic plane, so that <lb/> Q  s  ∝ E <lb/> −γs  δ(z). Thus (in the Thomson approximation for the energy losses), the secondary positron flux can <lb/>be derived analytically: φ  s  ∝ <lb/> τ  l  /K  0  E <lb/> −˜ s  , where <lb/>  s  = γ  s  + 0.5(α + δ − 1) — α ≡ ln(b(E)/b(E  0  )/ ln(E/E  0  ), <lb/> i.e. α = 2 in the Thomson approximation. Note that this reasoning also holds for primaries when neglect-<lb/>ing local discrete sources. By using the index inferred from considering CR nuclei interactions with the ISG, <lb/> i.e. γ  s  2.75, one readily gets <lb/>  s  3.45, quite close to the observed positron-only index (Delahaye et al. <lb/>2009, 2010). Nevertheless, predictions for the secondary positron flux fail to fit the positron fraction data — <lb/> f  e  +  ≡ φ  e  +  /(φ  e  −  + φ  e  +  ) — leading instead to a fraction decreasing with energy (Delahaye et al. 2009, 2010). <lb/>Nevertheless, taking into account the hardening in the proton spectrum above ∼ 2 TeV recently observed by <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> On the cosmic-ray e <lb/> +  /e <lb/> −  spectra <lb/></note>

			 <page>371 <lb/></page>

			<body> the CREAM experiment (Ahn et al. 2010) should result into a slightly harder secondary positron spectrum. <lb/>This effect remains to be checked in detail though we do not expect it to amplify the secondary flux by more <lb/>than 50%, while an enhancement factor  5 around 100 GeV is necessary to fit the data. <lb/> 3 Dark matter interpretation of the positron excess <lb/> DM particle scenarios rely on physics beyond the standard model. In most of them, e.g. in the so-called weakly <lb/>interacting massive particle (WIMP) paradigm, the total DM abundance is set by annihilation in the early <lb/>universe (for reviews, see e.g. Jungman et al. 1996; Bergström 2000; Murayama 2007). Originally in thermal and <lb/>chemical equilibrium with the primordial plasma after inflation, DM chemically decouples when the annihilation <lb/>rate becomes smaller than the expansion rate of the universe. This usually has to happen before big bang <lb/>nucleosynthesis (BBN), which must not be unsettled, when WIMPs are already non-relativistic — referred to <lb/>as cold DM (CDM). Therefore, cosmology imposes strong constraints to the annihilation cross section, provided <lb/>the expansion rate of the universe before BBN is taken standard <lb/>  ‡  . Typically, to get a relic abundance of <lb/>Ω  DM  ≈ 0.1/h <lb/> 2  , WIMPs need a thermally averaged annihilation cross section of σv ≈ 3 × 10 <lb/> −26  cm <lb/> 3  /s. <lb/> Annihilation is revived after DM has collapsed to form galaxies, its density being large enough in these <lb/>objects. WIMPs annihilation now occurs almost at rest and proceeds into pairs of standard model particles, <lb/>some of them further hadronizing or decaying, usually leading to the injection of CRs with continuous energy <lb/>spectra. Attempts to detect these annihilation products refer to as indirect detection (see e.g. Salati 2007). The <lb/>knowledge of the DM density distribution is crucial to compute the induced CR fluxes, since the annihilation <lb/>rate scales like the squared density; it is generally expressed in terms of the ratio of the mass density profile ρ to <lb/>the particle mass m  χ  , n  χ  = ρ/m  χ  , and constrained theoretically from N-body simulations and observationally <lb/>from kinematic data (e.g. Klypin et al. 2002). <lb/>In the case of high energy positrons, which are short range CRs, the most relevant input is the local <lb/>DM density set by ρ   ≈ 0.3 GeV/cm <lb/> 3  . At sufficiently high energy, positrons lose their energy before they <lb/>substantially diffuse, so that one can neglect spatial diffusion to a good approximation, provided the injection <lb/>rate does not fluctuate too much over short distances. In that case, the Green function defined earlier becomes <lb/> G(E, x ← E  s  , x  s  ) <lb/> λ→0 <lb/> ≈ δ <lb/> 3  ( x  s  − x)/b(E). The positron flux at the Earth generated by DM annihilation is thus <lb/>completely analytical: φ  e  +  (E) ≈ <lb/> β c <lb/> 4π <lb/> σv <lb/> 2 b(E) <lb/> ρ <lb/> m  χ <lb/>  2 <lb/>  m  χ <lb/>E <lb/> dE  s <lb/>dN  e + <lb/> dEs  leading to: <lb/> φ  e  +  (E) ≈ φ <lb/> 0 <lb/> χ <lb/> σv <lb/> 3 × 10  −26  cm <lb/> 3  /s <lb/> τ  l <lb/> 10  16  s <lb/> ρ   /(0.3 GeV/cm <lb/> 3  ) <lb/>(E/1 GeV)(m  χ  /100 GeV) <lb/>  2  m  χ <lb/>E <lb/> dE  s <lb/> dN  e  + <lb/> dE  s <lb/> , <lb/> (3.1) <lb/>where we find φ <lb/> 0 <lb/> χ  = 3.2 × 10 <lb/> −6  cm <lb/> −2  s <lb/> −1  GeV <lb/> −1  sr <lb/> −1  — if WIMPs are Dirac fermions, an additional factor <lb/>of 1/2 must be accounted for. Notice the dependence on energy and WIMP mass, which is explicit in this <lb/>equation. We can further simplify it by assuming annihilation into electron-positron pairs, so that the injected <lb/>spectrum dN  e  +  /dE  s  = δ(E  s  − m  χ  ). In this case, the positron flux associated with a WIMP mass of m  χ  = 100 <lb/>GeV at an energy of 100 GeV is φ  χ  (E = m  χ  = 100 GeV) ≈ 3.2 × 10 <lb/> −10  cm <lb/> −2  s <lb/> −1  GeV <lb/> −1  sr <lb/> −1  , amazingly close <lb/>to the value predicted for the secondary background at this energy. This means that such a model, provided <lb/>a small amplification (or boost) by a factor of a few, could very well explain the observed rise in the positron <lb/>fraction (Pieri et al. 2009). Nevertheless, such an exclusive annihilation into lepton pairs is quite a contrived <lb/>situation for WIMPs with masses greater than a few GeV, which can neither rely on sound particle physics <lb/>motivations nor be easily cooked up. For other annihilation final states, like heavy quarks or massive gauge <lb/>bosons, the required boost factor is much larger (see left panel of Fig. 2 in Lavalle 2010). Since the annihilation <lb/>cross section is fixed by the relic abundance, this low positron flux is a quite generic prediction, valid for most <lb/>of motivated DM particle scenarios like in supersymmetry or extra-dimensions (Lavalle et al. 2008a). <lb/>At this stage, the question is: are there ways to amplify the predicted signal which would be motivated by <lb/>some physical arguments? Actually, there are three different tracks one can explore: (i) enhancing annihilation <lb/>cross section; (ii) playing with CR propagation: theoretical uncertainties allow some freedom; (iii) considering <lb/>extra (local) sources of DM. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">  †  The term electrons will characterize both electrons and positrons when discussing general propagation features. <lb/>  ‡  This could change e.g. in the context of quintessence as a solution to dark energy (e.g. Salati 2003). <lb/></note>

			<page> 372 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> SF2A 2010 <lb/></note>

			<body> 3.1 Enhanced annihilation cross section <lb/> The physical motivation behind this possibility is that when WIMPs are much more massive than an exchanged <lb/>virtual boson field during the annihilation process, then a resonance can occur, which can strongly amplify the <lb/>cross section (referred to as Sommerfeld enhancement). This effect usually scales like the inverse squared velocity <lb/>of WIMPs, so it is stronger in galaxies today than at the decoupling time in the early universe. Nevertheless, <lb/>this effect concerns a very small part of the WIMP parameter space, and suffers severe constraints: all signals <lb/>associated with the amplified final state are enhanced the same, which generally leads the predicted antiproton <lb/>flux to overshoot the observational bounds, unless heavy DM particles annihilate only into leptons, which is <lb/>quite contrived (Cirelli et al. 2009). Such a possibility has therefore poor relevance. <lb/> 3.2 Impact of theoretical uncertainties in CR propagation <lb/> Since DM-induced CRs are produced everywhere in the Galaxy, enlarging the diffusion zone in the range <lb/>permitted by theoretical uncertainties may increase the flux predictions. Nevertheless, for positrons, this would <lb/>only affect the low energy part of the spectrum, since high energy positrons, bound to be short range by efficient <lb/>energy losses, must originate from very local regions. Therefore, tuning the propagation parameters also fails to <lb/>enhance the high energy positron flux (Lavalle et al. 2008b; Delahaye et al. 2008) — the energy loss parameters <lb/>being quite well constrained. <lb/> 3.3 Considering extra DM sources <lb/> The impact of DM substructures wandering in the Galactic halo was first emphasized by Silk &amp; Stebbins (1993). <lb/>Nevertheless, predicting the positron boost factor associated with these subhalos is not trivial, since it depends <lb/>on both their inner properties and their spatial distribution (Lavalle et al. 2007). Even when spanning the <lb/>full ranges for prescriptions coming from cosmological structure formation theory, it was actually shown that <lb/>these Galactic subhalos could not increase the signal by a large factor, with an upper limit  20 (Lavalle et al. <lb/>2008b). However, this upper bound is associated with a large statistical variance at high energy reflecting the <lb/>fact that though the probability of finding a massive enough subhalo close to the Earth is vanishingly small, <lb/>this would amplify the signal by a larger factor if this occurred. Nevertheless, even this tricky situation suffers <lb/>strong constraints coming e.g. from gamma-ray observations which strongly disfavors it as an explanation of a <lb/>rising positron fraction (Bringmann et al. 2009). <lb/>To conclude this section, we emphasize that the DM solution to the cosmic positron issue is by itself very <lb/>contrived and lacks strong physical motivations. Likewise, most of attempts are now excluded by complementary <lb/>constraints coming from other cosmic messengers. <lb/> 4 Towards a consistent model of CR leptons <lb/> We have already underlined that pulsars have long been proposed as sources of CR positrons, and were even <lb/>demonstrated, more than 15 years ago, to provide a good fit to the observed positron fraction above 5 GeV. Since <lb/>there are also other astrophysical proposals beside pulsars that could provide additional positrons, the question <lb/>is not really whether standard astrophysics can explain the data, but what a consistent CR model should look <lb/>like — note that the whole set of data such a model has to fit must also include the individual spectra of <lb/>electrons and positrons, and their sum as recently measured by Fermi and HESS up to TeV energies (Abdo <lb/>et al. 2009; Aharonian et al. 2008). In fact, it is probably because it was wrongly believed that a standard <lb/>model of CRs existed that PAMELA measurements triggered such a &quot; buzz &quot; . Indeed, the most advertized CR <lb/>model called GALPROP (Strong &amp; Moskalenko 1998; Moskalenko &amp; Strong 1998), which was too naively taken as <lb/>a reference in the debate on positrons, (i) was not including any source of primary positrons at that time and <lb/>(ii) was treating the injection of electrons with a smooth and continuous spatial distribution of SNRs associated <lb/>with an empirical energy spectrum, which also led to the claim of an excess in the Fermi data. Aside from the <lb/>lack of primary positrons in this model, it has been known for a long time that considering a smooth spatial <lb/>distribution of sources for high energy electrons failed for local predictions, just because the discreteness of <lb/>local sources has to manifest itself at high energy in the form of spectral fluctuations in the data (Shen 1970; <lb/>Kobayashi et al. 2004). Yet, this confusion cannot be attributed to the GALPROP model itself, since one of its <lb/>main goals was to investigate the diffuse Galactic multi-wavelength emissions originating from CR interactions <lb/>with the interstellar medium (ISM), either hadronic and electromagnetic, rather than the local electron budget. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> On the cosmic-ray e <lb/> +  /e <lb/> −  spectra <lb/></note>

			<page>373 <lb/></page>

			<body> Therefore, while we can fairly talk about a standard paradigm for CR propagation and sources, a standard <lb/>model is still far from achieved. A consistent prediction of the CR electron and positron fluxes at the Earth (or <lb/>at any point in the Galaxy) should at least include the contributions of (i) secondaries, (ii) a smooth distribution <lb/>of sources for the distant (and therefore low energy) primary component, with a radial cut-off set to a distance <lb/>from the Earth for which the source discreteness effects can safely be averaged out (∼ 2 kpc), and (iii) the <lb/>discrete sources located inside this cut-off radius. For the latter contribution, different catalogs are available for <lb/>pulsars and SNRs to constrain the relevant parameters, e.g. the position and age estimates (e.g. Manchester <lb/>et al. 2005; Green 2009). <lb/>We have mostly discussed the spatial distribution that a consistent CR electron model. Nevertheless, there is <lb/>still a major issue to mention: the injection from SNRs and pulsars. Indeed, though we can reasonably motivate <lb/>an average power law spectrum associated with an injection rate set by the explosion rate of supernovae and some <lb/>energetics considerations for the distant component (e.g. Malkov &amp; O&apos;C Drury 2001), an accurate modeling <lb/>of local sources is of paramount importance, since few of them might dominate the overall spectrum above <lb/> ∼ 100 GeV. Thus, the overall spectrum piles up all individual contributions and likely departs from a simple <lb/>power law. The individual amplitudes and spectral shapes strongly depend not only on the injected spectra, <lb/>but also on the source distances and ages (Delahaye et al. 2010). Moreover, the dynamics of CR (both nuclei <lb/>and electrons) injection into the ISM is still unclear (see discussion in e.g. O&apos;C. Drury 2010; Blasi &amp; Amato <lb/>2010). Nevertheless, the big advantage of local sources is that we have at hand a numerous multi-wavelength <lb/>observations to build a rather constrained model for each of them (see an example in Tatischeff 2009). Such <lb/>a thorough study involving sophisticated modelings for both local pulsars and SNRs remains to be achieved, <lb/>though some preliminary efforts have already been undergone in this direction. Delahaye et al. (2010) have <lb/>notably demonstrated that considering the observational properties of local sources is sufficient to explain the <lb/>whole set of data on CR electrons and positrons despite the large theoretical uncertainties, without overtuning <lb/>the parameters. This paves the road for further developments. <lb/> 5 Conclusion <lb/> We have discussed the DM interpretation of the so-called electron and positron excesses, showing that it was <lb/>likely too contrived to be supported from reasonable grounds, though one cannot formally exclude a DM <lb/>contribution to the electron and positron spectra. We have also emphasized that consistently considering well <lb/>known positron sources like pulsars can easily explain the current available data, despite the still large theoretical <lb/>errors associated with the predictions. This not only means that the explanation to these excesses is no longer <lb/>an issue, but also, unfortunately, that the positron channel is no longer an interesting discovery channel in <lb/>frame of indirect DM detection. Indeed, the uncertainties affecting the predictions make the background to DM <lb/>searches very hard to control. <lb/>Nevertheless, these new measurements of high energy CR electrons allow us to refine the current models <lb/>of CR propagation and sources. Beside studying more sophisticated propagation treatments (e.g. Shalchi <lb/>2009), improving and testing the physics of CR injection from sources is likely an important topic for the <lb/>next few years, which can now be implemented thanks to these unprecedented new data. Finally, clarifying <lb/>our understanding of local CR electrons will have a paramount impact on the predictions for associated multi-<lb/>wavelength electromagnetic diffuse emissions on the Galactic scale. Among interesting topics, this may provide <lb/>novel approaches to study the Galactic magnetic fields through the synchrotron emission, and also the diffuse <lb/>gamma-ray emission from the Galactic center. It is clear that the forthcoming lower frequency data expected <lb/>from instruments like Planck or Herschel (Tauber et al. 2010; Walmsley et al. 2010) will be precious in this <lb/>research field, as well as higher energy data on local electrons expected from AMS-02 <lb/>  §  . <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> I am grateful to the PCHE scientific committee for having selected this topic among so many other interesting ones for the plenary <lb/>PCHE talk. It is also a pleasure to thank some of my collaborators in this field for participation to the work itself and/or interesting <lb/>discussions, namely T. Delahaye, R. Lineros, A. Marcowith, D. Maurin and P. Salati. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> Abdo, A. A., Ackermann, M., Ajello, M., et al. 2009, Physical Review Letters, 102, 181101 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">  §  http://ams.cern.ch/ http://www.ams02.org/ <lb/></note>

			<page> 374 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> SF2A 2010 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> Adriani, O., Barbarino, G. C., Bazilevskaya, G. A., et al. 2009, Nature, 458, 607 <lb/>Aharonian, F., Akhperjanian, A. G., Barres de Almeida, U., et al. 2008, Physical Review Letters, 101, 261104 <lb/>Aharonian, F. A., Atoyan, A. M., &amp; Voelk, H. J. 1995, A&amp;A, 294, L41 <lb/>Ahn, H. S., Allison, P., Bagliesi, M. G., et al. 2010, ApJL, 714, L89 <lb/>Alcaraz, J., Alpat, B., Ambrosi, G., et al. 2000, Physics Letters B, 484, 10 <lb/>Arons, J. 1981, in IAU Symposium, Vol. 94, Origin of Cosmic Rays, ed. G. Setti, G. Spada, &amp; A. W. Wolfendale, 175–204 <lb/>Baltz, E. A. &amp; Edsjö, J. 1998, Phys. Rev. D, 59, 023511 <lb/>Barwick, S. W., Beatty, J. J., Bhattacharyya, A., et al. 1997, ApJL, 482, L191 <lb/>Berezhko, E. G., Ksenofontov, L. T., Ptuskin, V. S., Zirakashvili, V. N., &amp; Völk, H. J. 2003, A&amp;A, 410, 189 <lb/>Berezinskii, V. S., Bulanov, S. V., Dogiel, V. A., &amp; Ptuskin, V. S. 1990, Astrophysics of cosmic rays (Amsterdam: <lb/>North-Holland, 1990, edited by Ginzburg, V.L.) <lb/>Bergström, L. 2000, Reports on Progress in Physics, 63, 793 <lb/>Blasi, P. 2009, Physical Review Letters, 103, 051104 <lb/>Blasi, P. &amp; Amato, E. 2010, arXiv:1007.4745 <lb/>Boulares, A. 1989, ApJ, 342, 807 <lb/>Bringmann, T., Lavalle, J., &amp; Salati, P. 2009, Physical Review Letters, 103, 161301 <lb/>Chi, X., Cheng, K. S., &amp; Young, E. C. M. 1996, ApJL, 459, L83 <lb/>Cirelli, M., Kadastik, M., Raidal, M., &amp; Strumia, A. 2009, Nuclear Physics B, 813, 1 <lb/>Cumberbatch, D. &amp; Silk, J. 2007, MNRAS, 374, 455 <lb/>Delahaye, T., Donato, F., Fornengo, N., et al. 2009, A&amp;A, 501, 821 <lb/>Delahaye, T., Lavalle, J., Lineros, R., Donato, F., &amp; Fornengo, N. 2010, arXiv:1002.1910 <lb/>Delahaye, T., Lineros, R., Donato, F., Fornengo, N., &amp; Salati, P. 2008, Phys. Rev. D, 77, 063527 <lb/>Fanselow, J. L., Hartman, R. C., Hildebrad, R. H., &amp; Meyer, P. 1969, ApJ, 158, 771 <lb/>Golden, R. L., Mauger, B. G., Horan, S., et al. 1987, A&amp;A, 188, 145 <lb/>Green, D. A. 2009, Bull. Astron. Soc. Ind., 37, 45 <lb/>Gunn, J. E., Lee, B. W., Lerche, I., Schramm, D. N., &amp; Steigman, G. 1978, ApJ, 223, 1015 <lb/>Harding, A. K. &amp; Ramaty, R. 1987, in International Cosmic Ray Conference, Vol. 2, International Cosmic Ray Conference, <lb/>92 <lb/>Jungman, G., Kamionkowski, M., &amp; Griest, K. 1996, Phys. Rept., 267, 195 <lb/>Klypin, A., Zhao, H., &amp; Somerville, R. S. 2002, ApJ, 573, 597 <lb/>Kobayashi, T., Komori, Y., Yoshida, K., &amp; Nishimura, J. 2004, ApJ, 601, 340 <lb/>Lavalle, J. 2010, in American Institute of Physics Conference Series, Vol. 1241, American Institute of Physics Conference <lb/>Series, ed. J.-M. Alimi &amp; A. Fuözfa, 398–407 <lb/>Lavalle, J., Nezri, E., Athanassoula, E., Ling, F.-S., &amp; Teyssier, R. 2008a, Phys. Rev. D, 78, 103526 <lb/>Lavalle, J., Pochon, J., Salati, P., &amp; Taillet, R. 2007, A&amp;A, 462, 827 <lb/>Lavalle, J., Yuan, Q., Maurin, D., &amp; Bi, X.-J. 2008b, A&amp;A, 479, 427 <lb/>Longair, M. S. 1992, High energy astrophysics. Vol.1: Particles, photons and their detection (High Energy Astrophysics, <lb/>by Malcolm S. Longair, pp. 436. ISBN 0521387736. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press, March 1992.) <lb/>Longair, M. S. 1994, High energy astrophysics. Vol.2: Stars, the galaxy and the interstellar medium (Cambridge: Cam-<lb/>bridge University Press, —c1994, 2nd ed.) <lb/>Malkov, M. A. &amp; O&apos;C Drury, L. 2001, Reports on Progress in Physics, 64, 429 <lb/>Manchester, R. N., Hobbs, G. B., Teoh, A., &amp; Hobbs, M. 2005, AJ, 129, 1993 <lb/>Maurin, D., Donato, F., Taillet, R., &amp; Salati, P. 2001, ApJ, 555, 585 <lb/>Moskalenko, I. V. &amp; Strong, A. W. 1998, ApJ, 493, 694 <lb/>Murayama, H. 2007, arXiv:0704.2276 <lb/>O&apos;C. Drury, L. 2010, arXiv:1009.4799 <lb/>Pieri, L., Lavalle, J., Bertone, G., &amp; Branchini, E. 2009, arXiv:0908.0195 <lb/>Putze, A., Derome, L., &amp; Maurin, D. 2010, A&amp;A, 516, A66 <lb/>Roberts, J. P. 2010, arXiv:1005.4668 <lb/>Salati, P. 2003, Physics Letters B, 571, 121 <lb/>Salati, P. 2007, Proceedings of Science, Cargese 2007, 009 <lb/>Shalchi, A. 2009, Nonlinear Cosmic Ray Diffusion Theories (Springer) <lb/>Shaviv, N. J., Nakar, E., &amp; Piran, T. 2009, Physical Review Letters, 103, 111302 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> On the cosmic-ray e <lb/> +  /e <lb/> −  spectra <lb/></note>

			<page>375 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> Shen, C. S. 1970, ApJL, 162, L181 <lb/>Silk, J. &amp; Srednicki, M. 1984, Physical Review Letters, 53, 624 <lb/>Silk, J. &amp; Stebbins, A. 1993, ApJ, 411, 439 <lb/>Stecker, F. W. 1978, ApJ, 223, 1032 <lb/>Strong, A. W. &amp; Moskalenko, I. V. 1998, ApJ, 509, 212 <lb/>Strong, A. W., Moskalenko, I. V., &amp; Ptuskin, V. S. 2007, Annual Review of Nuclear and Particle Science, 57, 285 <lb/>Sturrock, P. A. 1970, Nature, 227, 465 <lb/>Tatischeff, V. 2009, A&amp;A, 499, 191 <lb/>Tauber, J. A., Mandolesi, N., Puget, J., et al. 2010, A&amp;A, 520, A1 <lb/>Tylka, A. J. 1989, Physical Review Letters, 63, 840 <lb/>Walmsley, C. M., Bertout, C., Combes, F., et al. 2010, A&amp;A, 521 <lb/>Zeldovich, Y. B., Klypin, A. A., Khlopov, M. Y., &amp; Chechetkin, V. M. 1980, Sov. J. Nucl. Phys., 31, 664 </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
