<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage> This content has been downloaded from IOPscience. Please scroll down to see the full text. <lb/>Download details: <lb/>IP Address: 188.184.3.52 <lb/>This content was downloaded on 22/02/2015 at 22:33 <lb/>Please note that terms and conditions apply. <lb/> Exotic ideas on mixed proton-neutron symmetry and their manifestation in heavy nuclei <lb/> View the table of contents for this issue, or go to the journal homepage for more <lb/>2013 J. Phys.: Conf. Ser. 445 012030 <lb/>(http://iopscience.iop.org/1742-6596/445/1/012030) <lb/>Home Search Collections Journals About Contact us My IOPscience <lb/></titlePage>

			<front> Exotic ideas on mixed proton-neutron symmetry and <lb/>their manifestation in heavy nuclei <lb/> N Pietralla  1  , C Bauer  1  , J Leske  1,3  , O Möller  1  , T Möller  1  , P <lb/>von Neumann-Cosel  1  , G Rainovski  2  , A Scheikh-Obeid  1  and C Walz  1 <lb/> 1  Institut für Kernphysik, Technische Universität Darmstadt, 64289 Darmstadt, Germany <lb/> 2  Faculty of Physics, St. Kliment Ohridski University of Sofia, 1164 Sofia, Bulgaria <lb/> Abstract. The one-quadrupole phonon excitation of mixed symmetry, the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1,ms  state, is a <lb/>fundamental building block of nuclear structure. This article gives a summary of our recent <lb/>experimental research on this excitation mode in the A = 90 and A = 130 mass regions. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> The contemporary quest for the structure of exotic nuclei addresses nuclear systems with <lb/>abnormal ratios of proton and neutron numbers. It, hence, focuses on the isospin dependence of <lb/>nuclear structure. The isospin degree of freedom of collective nuclear structures has been studied <lb/>[1] some 35 years ago in the framework of the proton-neutron version [2] of the interacting <lb/>boson model [3] by Takaharu Otsuka who worked at that time with Arima and Iachello. The <lb/>formulation of the IBM-2 in its F-spin limit [4, 5] has emphasized the fundamental role of <lb/>collective isovector valence-shell excitations, so-called mixed-symmetry states (MSSs), for the <lb/>first time [2]. After the discovery of the scissors mode [6] and the clarification of its quadrupole-<lb/>collective character [7, 8] it became obvious that the isovector quadrupole excitation of the <lb/>valence shell represents the building block of mixed-symmetric structures as it is particularly <lb/>apparent in the framework of the Q-phonon scheme [9] for mixed-symmetry states [10, 11]. The <lb/> Q-phonon scheme considers ground state correlations by only providing relative wave functions <lb/>and thereby benefits from a wide applicability to good approximation [12, 13, 14]. <lb/>Vibrational nuclei exhibit a one-quadrupole phonon excitation as the lowest-lying state of <lb/>mixed pn symmetry, i.e the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1,ms  state. Its close relation to the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1  state is evident in the <lb/> Q-phonon scheme where the wave functions of the one-quadrupole phonon excitations are in <lb/>general well approximated by the expressions <lb/> |2 <lb/> + <lb/>1  Q  s  |0 <lb/> + <lb/>1  = [Q  π  + Q  ν  ] |0 <lb/> + <lb/>1  <lb/> (1) <lb/> |2 <lb/> + <lb/>1,ms  Q  m  |0 <lb/> + <lb/>1  = N <lb/>  Q  π <lb/> N  π <lb/> − <lb/> Q  ν <lb/> N  ν <lb/> |0 <lb/> + <lb/>1  <lb/> (2) <lb/>where Q  π,ν  (N  π,ν  ) denote the proton and neutron quadrupole operators (boson numbers), <lb/> N = N  π  +N  ν  , and |0 <lb/> + <lb/>1  is the (in general highly correlated) ground state of a collective even-even <lb/>nucleus. Despite its fundamental role in nuclear structure, the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1,ms  state has only recently been <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 3  Present address: Helmut Fischer Gmbh, Sindelfingen, Germany <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> International Symposium on Exotic Nuclear Structure From Nucleons (ENSFN 2012) <lb/>IOP Publishing <lb/>Journal of Physics: Conference Series 445 (2013) 012030 <lb/>doi:10.1088/1742-6596/445/1/012030 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> Content from this work may be used under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 licence. Any further distribution <lb/>of this work must maintain attribution to the author(s) and the title of the work, journal citation and DOI. <lb/>Published under licence by IOP Publishing Ltd <lb/></note>

			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<body> studied systematically, e.g., [15, 16, 17, 18, 19]. The dominant fragments of the one-phonon 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1,ms <lb/> state are observed at about 2 MeV excitation energy. Due to their isovector character, MSSs <lb/>decay rapidly by dipole transitions and are very short lived, typically a few tens of femtoseconds. <lb/>Large M 1 matrix elements of ≈ 1 µ  N  are the unique signatures for MSSs and, thus, lifetime <lb/>information is needed for making safe assignments of mixed symmetry. A review article on the <lb/>status of experimental information on mixed symmetry states in vibrational nuclei has been <lb/>published [20]. We use the occasion of Taka Otsuka&apos;s 60th birthday to summarize our recent <lb/>experimental research on one-phonon MSSs. While we have recently been asked to talk on this <lb/>subject at various occasions the presentation of the present contribution is similar to what we <lb/>have recently contributed to other conference proceedings. <lb/> 2. Experimental Method <lb/> Projectile-Coulomb excitation has been established as a powerful method for the identification <lb/>and investigation of one-phonon MSSs [17, 19]. After this approach has first been applied to the <lb/>investigation of the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1,ms  state of  96  Ru at the Yale Tandem accelerator [17], we have begun a <lb/>research programme on the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1,ms  state at Argonne National Laboratory with the nucleus  138  Ce <lb/>as a first case study [19]. Crucial influence of sub-shell closures on mixed-symmetry structures <lb/>was first observed, a phenomenon which sensitively tests the effective proton-neutron interaction <lb/>in microscopic valence shell models [21, 22]. The one-phonon 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1,ms  state of  136  Ce has recently <lb/>been identified from similar Coulomb excitation experiments at Gammasphere [23]. <lb/>A sequence of experiments on Xenon, Barium, and Cerium isotopes has been performed. The <lb/>superconducting ATLAS accelerator provided the ion beams with energies corresponding to ∼ <lb/> 85 % of the Coulomb barrier for a reaction on  12  C nuclei. The beam intensity amounted typically <lb/>to ∼ 1pnA. The beam was impinging on a stationary carbon target of thickness 1 mg/cm  2  . Light <lb/>target ions were chosen in order to favor the one-step Coulomb excitation process over multi-<lb/>step processes for ease of data evaluation. The γ-rays emitted by Coulomb-excited states of <lb/>the beam nuclei were detected in the Gammasphere array which consisted of ∼ 100 high purity <lb/>Compton suppressed Germanium detectors arranged in 16 rings. An event was defined by a <lb/> γ-ray of multiplicity 1 or higher. Two corrections had to be done in order to get the total single <lb/>spectra, an example of which is displayed in Fig. 1, namely the Doppler correction (recoiling <lb/>velocity ∼ 6-8%) and the background subtraction (difference between the &quot; in-beam &quot; spectrum <lb/>and the &quot; off-beam &quot; spectrum scaled to eliminate the 1461 keV  40  K line). <lb/>The experimental γ-ray spectra are dominated by the decays of low-spin states, such as <lb/>2  +  or 3  −  states, that are predominantly populated by one-step Coulomb excitation from the <lb/>ground state. For each state observed we measured the excitation cross section relative to that <lb/> Figure 1. Background-subtracted <lb/>and Doppler-corrected singles γ-ray <lb/> spectrum summed over all Ge de-<lb/>tectors of the Gammasphere array <lb/>at ANL after Coulomb excitation of <lb/> 136  Ce on a carbon target [23]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> International Symposium on Exotic Nuclear Structure From Nucleons (ENSFN 2012) <lb/>IOP Publishing <lb/>Journal of Physics: Conference Series 445 (2013) 012030 <lb/>doi:10.1088/1742-6596/445/1/012030 <lb/></note>

			<page> 2 <lb/></page>

			<body> of the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1  state with an accuracy of 1 -0.1 %. By calculating the Coulomb excitation cross <lb/>sections for each excited state with the multiple-Coulomb excitation formalism and fitting them <lb/>to our experimental data (normalized to the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1  state), we deduced the electromagnetic matrix <lb/>elements corresponding to each transition of the excited states. The crucial multipole mixing <lb/>ratios of the 2  +  → 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1  transitions were obtained from γ-ray angular distributions if sufficient <lb/>statistics have been obtained. A possible large B(M 1) value, signature of the MSS, is then <lb/>easily derived from the data. For a further description of this method, the reader is referred to <lb/>Refs. [19, 20]. This experimental technique of projectile-Coulomb excitation on a light target <lb/>inside the Gammasphere array at ANL has been applied by us to 16 nuclei up to now:  136,138  Ce, <lb/> 124−134  Xe,  148,154  Sm,  194,196  Pt,  130,132  Ba,  96  Ru and  94  Mo. Figure 1 displays data from the <lb/>projectile-Coulomb excitation reactions of a  136  Ce-ion beam on a carbon target. <lb/> 3. Evolution of 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1,ms  states in the A = 130 region <lb/> The experiments performed so far allow for a nearly complete overview on the properties of the <lb/>MSS throughout the A = 130 region. A recent publication on the first identification of a MSS in <lb/>an unstable nucleus in  132  Te [24] expands the experimental data on the N = 80 isotonic chain. A <lb/>recent publication on the MSS in the nucleus  136  Ce [23] completes the experimental data on the <lb/>stable even-even N = 78 isotonic chain. A set of data currently under analysis on the nucleus <lb/> 132  Ba [25] will complete our information on the one-phonon mixed-symmetry state in the stable <lb/>even-even N = 76 isotones. An overview on the B(M 1; 2 <lb/> + <lb/> i  → 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1  ) strength distributions in the <lb/>even-even nuclei in the A = 130 region is shown in Figure 2. <lb/>In the stable N = 80 isotones the excitation energy of the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1,ms  state increases with increasing <lb/>proton number. This trend continues in the unstable nucleus  132  Te [24]. In the N = 78 isotonic <lb/>chain, the energy of the MSS again increases with increasing proton number. In the neighboring <lb/> N = 76 isotones, however, the excitation energy of the MSS decreases with increasing proton <lb/>number. It is also interesting to follow the evolution of the MSS&apos;s excitation energies in the <lb/>different isotopic chains. In the Ce and Ba isotopes, the excitation energy of the MSS increases <lb/>with increasing neutron number, whereas in the Xe isotopes an increase in N  ν  results in a <lb/>decrease of E(2 <lb/> + <lb/>1,ms  ). Apparently, the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1,ms  state evolves in different ways as a function of <lb/>valence particle numbers. Whether or not the observed differences are related to a critical point <lb/>of a nuclear shape phase transition near  134  Ba is unclear up to now. <lb/>From data on E(2 <lb/> + <lb/>1  ) and E(2 <lb/> + <lb/>1,ms  ), an estimate of the proton-neutron quadrupole-quadrupole <lb/>interaction V  QQ <lb/>pn  according to the two-state mixing scheme in [26] has been performed on the <lb/> Figure 2. Overview <lb/>of the B(M 1; 2 <lb/> + <lb/> i <lb/> → <lb/> 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1  ) strength distribu-<lb/>tions for the stable <lb/>even-even nuclei in the <lb/>A=130 region. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> International Symposium on Exotic Nuclear Structure From Nucleons (ENSFN 2012) <lb/>IOP Publishing <lb/>Journal of Physics: Conference Series 445 (2013) 012030 <lb/>doi:10.1088/1742-6596/445/1/012030 <lb/></note>

			<page> 3 <lb/></page>

			<body> Figure 3. Simultaneous fit of <lb/>the experimental energies of the <lb/>2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1  states (solid curve) and of the <lb/> B(M 1)-weighted average energies <lb/>of the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1,ms  states (dashed curve) <lb/>in the N = 78 isotones. Taken from <lb/>[23]. <lb/> N = 80 isotones [27], the Xe isotopes [28], and, just recently, on the N = 78 isotones [23]. <lb/>The results show, that the proton-neutron quadrupole-quadrupole interaction in the N = 78 <lb/>isotonic chain is about 14% smaller than that for the N = 80 isotopic chain [27] and about 6% <lb/>smaller than for the Xenon isotopic chain [28]. An example of the data, taken from Ref. [23], is <lb/>displayed in Fig. 3. <lb/> 4. Phase of proton-and neutron-components to MSSs: The case of  92  Zr <lb/> We studied the formation of quadrupole collectivity in the particularly simple case of a nucleus <lb/>with a low-energy structure that is dominated by one pair of valence particles each for protons <lb/>and neutrons. An example is the nucleus  92  Zr with 2 neutrons beyond the N = 50 shell closure <lb/>and 2 protons beyond the Z = 38 sub-shell closure. The lowest 2-quasiparticle (2qp) states <lb/>have π(1g  9/2  )  2  and ν(2d  5/2  )  2  configurations. In  92  Zr, the predominantly symmetric and mixed-<lb/>symmetric one-phonon 2  +  states are experimentally identified as the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1  and 2 <lb/> + <lb/>2  states [29, 20] <lb/>with some degree of configurational isospin polarization [30]. <lb/>To shed light on the microscopic origin of the effective pn-coupling strength in the valence <lb/>shell we consider the quasiparticle-phonon model (QPM) [31]. The QPM wave functions are <lb/>dominated by the lowest π and ν 2qp components, that show the expected in-phase and out-<lb/>of-phase behavior for the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>fs  and 2  + <lb/>ms  states. The electromagnetic properties and excitation <lb/>energies are in excellent agreement with the data [32]. The magnetic moments of these <lb/>states and the strong M 1 transition between them originate almost entirely from the valence-<lb/>shell configurations. However, the B(E2) strengths are generated to about 80% from many <lb/>components beyond the valence shell albeit their total contribution to the wave function norm <lb/>is small. This observation motivates a simple three-state mixing scenario between the proton-<lb/>valence shell configuration, the neutron-valence shell configuration, and the GQR for a deeper <lb/>insight in the formation of the one-quadrupole phonon states with symmetric and mixed-<lb/>symmetry character even on a semi-quantitative level [33]. For the nucleus  92  Zr with higher <lb/>energy for the proton valence-shell component than the neutron valence-shell component at <lb/>the Z = 40 sub-shell closure, this scheme inevitably requires that the neutron valence-shell <lb/>component flips its phase with respect to the GQR component when going from the proton-<lb/>neutron symmetric 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1  state to the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>2  state with predominant mixed symmetry. <lb/>Apparently, two probes with different sensitivity to protons and neutrons are needed to <lb/>study this quantum interference experimentally. Electron scattering at low momentum transfer <lb/>provides a measure of the charge transition radius. An (e, e   ) experiment was performed at <lb/>the Darmstadt superconducting electron linear accelerator (S-DALINAC). An enriched (94.6 <lb/>%) self-supporting  92  Zr target of 9.8 mg/cm  2  areal density was used. Data were taken covering <lb/>a momentum transfer range between q ∼ 0.3 − 0.6 fm <lb/> −1  indicating no difference between the <lb/>charge transition radii of the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>fs  and 2  + <lb/>ms  states within experimental uncertainties (Fig. 4, right). <lb/>Information about the neutron transition radii can be derived from the proton scattering data <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> International Symposium on Exotic Nuclear Structure From Nucleons (ENSFN 2012) <lb/>IOP Publishing <lb/>Journal of Physics: Conference Series 445 (2013) 012030 <lb/>doi:10.1088/1742-6596/445/1/012030 <lb/></note>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<body> Figure 4. Form factors for the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1,fs  (red, solid line) and 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1,ms  (blue, dashed line) from  92  Zr(p, p   ) <lb/>and  92  Zr(e, e   ) experiments (from [33]). <lb/>of Ref. [34]. At the incident energy of 800 MeV protons interact predominantly via the isoscalar <lb/>central piece of the effective projectile-nucleus interaction [35]. Clearly, the refraction pattern <lb/>of the (p, p   ) cross section for the 2  + <lb/>ms  state are shifted to higher q values as compared to those <lb/>for the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>fs  state (Fig. 4, left) corresponding to a smaller transition radius. <lb/>Figure 5 displays the proton and neutron transition densities of the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>fs  (top) and 2  + <lb/>ms  (bottom) <lb/>states calculated in the full QPM approach. The full transition densities (solid curves) are <lb/>decomposed in a collective part stemming from the GQR (dotted curves) and the predominant <lb/>2qp ν(2d  5/2  )  2  neutron contributions (dashed curves). <lb/>The key point is the different radial behaviour of both parts and their relative signs. An <lb/>out-of-phase coupling between the neutron valence shell contribution and the contribution <lb/>from the GQR in the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1,ms  state leads to a destructive quantum interference that reduces the <lb/>neutron transition density at large radii (due to the larger radius of the ν(2d  5/2  )  2  orbital) and <lb/>consequently shifts the maximum of the total neutron transition density to the interior with <lb/>respect to that one for the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>fs  state, as indicated by the arrows in Fig. 5. This effect reduces <lb/>the neutron transition radius of the 2  + <lb/>ms  with respect to the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>fs  state of  92  Zr. In contrast, the <lb/>proton transition radius remains essentially unchanged since the π(1g  9/2  )  2  part couples in-phase <lb/>to the GQR contribution in both states. The combination of both data sets unambiguously <lb/>demonstrates for the first time that the phase of the neutron valence-shell configurations in  92  Zr <lb/>changes its sign between the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>fs  and the 2  + <lb/>ms  state [33]. <lb/> Figure 5. Neutron transition den-<lb/>sities of the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>fs  (top) and 2  + <lb/>ms  (bot-<lb/>tom) states of  92  Zr from QPM cal-<lb/>culations. The full transition den-<lb/>sities (solid lines) are decomposed <lb/>in parts stemming from the GQR <lb/>(dotted lines) and from the main <lb/>2qp configurations (dashed lines). <lb/>The arrows indicate the maxima <lb/>of the corresponding full transition <lb/>densities. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> International Symposium on Exotic Nuclear Structure From Nucleons (ENSFN 2012) <lb/>IOP Publishing <lb/>Journal of Physics: Conference Series 445 (2013) 012030 <lb/>doi:10.1088/1742-6596/445/1/012030 <lb/></note>

			<page> 5 <lb/></page>

			<body> 5. Summary <lb/> The isovector one-quadrupole phonon excitation of the valence shell, the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1,ms  state with F -spin <lb/> F = F  max  − 1, has been systematically investigated in a large number of vibrational nuclei. <lb/>This state is generally identified from absolute M 1 transition strengths when the experimental <lb/>sensitivity is high enough and it occurs at energies around 2 MeV featuring an M 1 transition <lb/>matrix element to the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1  state between 0.5 and 1.5 µ  N  with some fragmentation. The details of <lb/>its evolution as a function of particle number is not entirely understood. It may depend on the <lb/>local shell structure around the Fermi level and on the evolution of quadrupole deformation. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments <lb/> We thank Taka Otsuka for inspiration to new experimental endeavors and for many discussions. <lb/>We thank all those who have contributed to our research on various aspects of mixed-symmetry <lb/>states. With respect to the data discussed in this contribution we particularly want to <lb/>acknowledge the scientists and staff members at the Argonne National Laboratory, USA, at <lb/>the iThemba Labs, South-Africa, and at the S-DALINAC, Germany. Support from the DFG <lb/>under grants Pi393/2-2 and SFB 634, by the German-Bulgarian exchange program under Grant <lb/>No. PPP 50751591 is gratefully acknowledged. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] Otsuka T 1978 Boson model of medium-heavy nuclei (University of Tokyo, PhD thesis) <lb/>[2] Arima A, Ohtsuka T, Iachello F and Talmi I 1977 Phys. Lett. B 66 205 <lb/>[3] Iachello F and Arima A 1987 The Interacting Boson Model (Cambridge University Press). <lb/>[4] Otsuka T, Arima A and Iachello F 1978 Nucl. Phys. A 309 1 <lb/>[5] Van Isacker P, Heyde K, Jolie J and Sevrin A 1986 Ann. Phys. (NY) 171 253 <lb/>[6] Bohle D, Richter A, Steffen W, Dieperink A, LoIudice N, Palumbo F , Scholten O 1984 Phys. Lett. B 137 27 <lb/>[7] Ziegler W, Rangacharyulu C, Richter A and Spieler C 1990 Phys. Rev. Lett. 65 2515 <lb/>[8] Pietralla N, Brentano P von, Herzberg R-D, Kneissl U, Lo Iudice N, Maser H, Pitz H H and Zilges A 1998 <lb/> Phys. Rev. C 58 184 <lb/>[9] Otsuka T and Kim K H 1994 Phys. Rev. C 50 R1768 <lb/>[10] Kim K-H, Otsuka T, Brentano P von, Gelberg A, Van Isacker P and Casten R F 1996 Proc. Int. Conf. on <lb/>Capture Gamma-Ray Spectroscopy and Related Topics vol 1, ed G. Molnár, (Budapest: Springer) p 195 <lb/>[11] Pietralla N et al. 1998 Phys. Rev. C 58 796 <lb/>[12] Pietralla N, Brentano P von, Casten R F, Otsuka T and Zamfir N V 1994 Phys. Rev. Lett. 73 2962 <lb/>[13] Pietralla N, Brentano P von, Otsuka T and Casten R F 1995 Phys. Lett. B 349 1 <lb/>[14] Pietralla N, Mizusaki T, Brentano P von, Jolos R V, Otsuka T and Werner V 1998 Phys. Rev. C 57 150 <lb/>[15] Pietralla N et al. 1999 Phys. Rev. Lett. 83 1303 <lb/>[16] Pietralla N et al. 2000 Phys. Rev. Lett. 84 3775 <lb/>[17] Pietralla N et al. 2001 Phys. Rev. C 64 031301 <lb/>[18] Pietralla N et al. 2003 Phys. Rev. C 68 031305(R) <lb/>[19] Rainovski G, Pietralla N, Ahn T et al. 2006 Phys. Rev. Lett. 96 122501 <lb/>[20] Pietralla N, Brentano P von and Lisetskiy A F 2008 Prog. Part. Nucl. Phys. 60 225 <lb/>[21] LoIudice N, Stoyanov C and Tarpanov D 2008 Phys. Rev. C 77 044310 <lb/>[22] Bianco D, Andreozzi F, LoIudice N, Porrino A and Knapp F 2012 Phys. Rev. C 85 034332 <lb/>[23] Ahn T, Rainovski G, Pietralla N et al. 2012 Phys. Rev. C 86 014303 <lb/>[24] Danchev M et al. 2011 Phys. Rev. C 84 061306 <lb/>[25] Möller T et al., in preparation. <lb/>[26] Heyde K and Sau J 1986 Phys. Rev. C 33 1050 <lb/>[27] Ahn T et al. 2009 Phys. Lett. B 679 19 <lb/>[28] Coquard L et al. 2010 Phys. Rev. C 82 024317 <lb/>[29] Werner V et al. 2002 Phys. Lett. B 550 140 <lb/>[30] Holt J D, Pietralla N, Holt J W, Kuo T T S and Rainovski G 2007 Phys. Rev. C 76 034325 <lb/>[31] Soloviev V 1992 Theory of Atomic Nuclei: Quasiparticles and Phonons (Bristol: Institute of Physics Pub.) <lb/>[32] LoIudice N and Stoyanov C 2006 Phys. Rev. C 73 037305 <lb/>[33] Walz C, Fujita H, Krugmann A, Neumann-Cosel P von, Pietralla N et al. 2011 Phys. Rev. Lett. 106 062501 <lb/>[34] Baker F et al. 1983 Nucl. Phys. A 393 283 <lb/>[35] Franey M A and Love W G 1985 Phys. Rev. C 31 488 <lb/> International Symposium on Exotic Nuclear Structure From Nucleons (ENSFN 2012) <lb/>IOP Publishing <lb/>Journal of Physics: Conference Series 445 (2013) 012030 <lb/>doi:10.1088/1742-6596/445/1/012030 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 6 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
