<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> The nonlinear Dirac equation in Bose-Einstein <lb/>condensates: Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak <lb/>harmonic trap <lb/> L. H. Haddad <lb/> 1  and Lincoln D. Carr <lb/> 1,2 <lb/> 1  Department of Physics, Colorado School of Mines, Golden, CO 80401,USA <lb/> 2  Physikalisches Institut, Universität Heidelberg, D-69120 Heidelberg, Germany <lb/> E-mail: laith.haddad@gmail.com, lcarr@mines.edu <lb/> Abstract. We analyze the vortex solution space of the (2 + 1)-dimensional nonlinear <lb/>Dirac equation for bosons in a honeycomb optical lattice at length scales much larger <lb/>than the lattice spacing. Dirac point relativistic covariance combined with s-wave <lb/>scattering for bosons leads to a large number of vortex solutions characterized by <lb/>different functional forms for the internal spin and overall phase of the order parameter. <lb/>We present a detailed derivation of these solutions which include skyrmions, half-<lb/>quantum vortices, Mermin-Ho and Anderson-Toulouse vortices for vortex winding <lb/> = 1. For  ≥ 2 we obtain topological as well as non-topological solutions defined <lb/>by the asymptotic radial dependence. For arbitrary values of  the non-topological <lb/>solutions are bright ring-vortices which explicitly demonstrate the confining effects <lb/>of the Dirac operator. We arrive at solutions through an asymptotic Bessel series, <lb/>algebraic closed-forms, and using standard numerical shooting methods. By including a <lb/>harmonic potential to simulate a finite trap we compute the discrete spectra associated <lb/>with radially quantized modes. We demonstrate the continuous spectral mapping <lb/>between the vortex and free particle limits for all of our solutions. <lb/>PACS numbers: 67.85.Hj, 67.85.Jk, 05.45.-a, 67.85.-d, 03.65.Pm, 02.30.Jr, 03.65.Pm <lb/> Submitted to: New J. Phys. <lb/> arXiv:1502.05621v1  [cond-mat.quant-gas] 19 Feb 2015 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 2 <lb/></page>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> Vortices appear in physical settings which span a wide range of energy scales and <lb/>disciplines ranging from hurricane phenomena [1] and turbulent flow in classical <lb/>fluids [2], to superfluidity in <lb/> 4  He [3] and general quantum fluids [4, 5], down to the <lb/>smallest length scales of Bogomol&apos;nyi-Prasad-Sommerfield states in supersymmetric <lb/>field theories [6]. Vortices are relevant from a technological standpoint in quantum <lb/>computing for example [7], as well as in more theoretical areas of research such as <lb/>galactic halos in Bose-Einstein condensate (BEC) theories of dark matter [8]. In BECs <lb/>vortices as stable rotating solutions of the nonlinear Schrödinger equation (NLSE) are <lb/>ubiquitous [9, 10]. Indeed, the presence of a persistent quantized rotation may be <lb/>considered a defining property of superfluidity. Although a variety of types of vortices <lb/>are possible in atomic condenstates [11], the Laplacian inherent to the Schrödinger <lb/>Hamiltonian constrains the number of observable vortex structures in the BEC. For <lb/>instance, a BEC made up of spin-F bosons gives rise to a (2F + 1)-component order <lb/>parameter which nevertheless solves a multi-component NLSE. An alternative method <lb/>of constructing a multicomponent BEC is to add the internal degrees of freedom by <lb/>placing a condensate in a two-dimensional honeycomb optical lattice [12, 13]. Atoms <lb/>are condensed into the lowest energy Bloch state then translated to a corner of the <lb/>Brillouin zone using laser assisted Bragg scattering [14]. At wavelengths large compared <lb/>to the lattice constant, the microscopic details of the lattice manifest as an additional <lb/>SL(2, C) spin group symmetry, i.e., a Dirac point structure emerges [12]. <lb/>In a previous paper we derived a BEC version of the nonlinear Dirac equation <lb/>(NLDE) for the case of weak interparticle interactions [12]. This has attracted attention <lb/>from diverse fields of research [15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, <lb/>30, 31, 32, 33, 34, 35, 36, 37, 38, 39, 40, 41]. Solutions of the NLDE are effectively long <lb/>wavelength limit lattice envelopes, and so can cover a large number of sites. The healing <lb/>length in our effectively quasi-2D system is typically about 10 times the lattice constant, <lb/>and we require the healing length to be small compared to the size of the cylindrical <lb/>container. In typical experiments, the number of lattice sites is on the order of 100 in <lb/>a linear direction, thus vortex solutions of the NLDE may be described accurately. In <lb/>this article we study relativistic quantum vortices in the superfluid phase of a Bose gas <lb/>at the Dirac point of a honeycomb optical lattice focusing on explicit vortex solutions of <lb/>the NLDE. Solution types differ by asymptotic conditions on the amplitude for radius <lb/> r much greater than the healing length, far from a vortex core, or r much less than <lb/>the healing length deep inside a vortex core. A general schematic for vortices in our <lb/>problem is shown in Fig. 1. Solutions may also differ by use of the internal degree of <lb/>freedom in the spinor structure and with respect to quantization of rotation. However, <lb/>we find that spinor components within a particular solution always differ by one unit of <lb/>rotation. <lb/>Quantized rotation in a (2 + 1)-dimensional spin-1/2 order parameter is best <lb/>characterized in terms of the topology of the circulation or phase winding around a <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 3 <lb/></page>

			<body> Lattice <lb/> background <lb/>Vortex <lb/>circulation <lb/>Vortex <lb/>axis <lb/> Figure 1. (color online) Relativistic vortex in the honeycomb lattice. The vortex <lb/>current is depicted by red arrows with the core towards the interior of the red circle. <lb/>The relativistic current is quantized around the core and incorporates the overall U (1) <lb/>phase into the internal SU (2) rotation. <lb/> singular core. Consider an overall macroscopic phase which wraps around the circular <lb/>boundary consisting of radial lengths much larger than the healing length. When the <lb/>internal spin degrees of freedom remain topologically unconstrained we simply referred <lb/>to this as a vortex. In contrast, when the wrapping around the circular boundary <lb/>includes the internal spin degrees of freedom in a nontrivial way the order parameter is <lb/>usually called a texture or skyrmion [42, 11]. Throughout our work we adhere to the <lb/>case where the Berry phase is spliced into the overall U (1) symmetry upon condensation <lb/>of the order parameter. Thus, we do not consider solutions with a macroscopic π-phase <lb/> disinclination. The presence of the Dirac operator in the NLDE adds new features over <lb/>conventional spinor BECs. In some cases the derivative terms act to defocus the solution <lb/>leading to conventional &quot; dark &quot; vortices with density minima in an otherwise uniform <lb/>background. In other cases the cross-mixing of spinor components in the Dirac term <lb/>has a confining effect resulting in a &quot; bright &quot; vortex made of spinning localized density <lb/>rings over a zero density background. These localized solutions are similar to ones found <lb/>in ordinary BECs with attractive interactions [43, 44], although we emphasize that in <lb/>the present work we consider only repulsive contact interactions. It is significant that <lb/>our solutions apply to certain spin-orbit coupled BECs [45]. In the low-energy limit of <lb/>these theories the linear (Dirac) kinetic term is dominant and one may safely neglect <lb/>the second order (Schrödinger) contribution. Tuning the interactions to eliminate cross <lb/>terms in the spinor components leads to our NLDE. The various types of NLDE vortices <lb/>are summarized in Fig 2. <lb/>To put relativistic vortices in a more general context, the large symmetry <lb/>groups encountered in high energy physics and cosmology admit vortex solutions as <lb/>fundamental ingredients. Examples include cosmic superstrings [46, 47, 48], mirror <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<body> Energy  from <lb/> Dirac point <lb/> Lattice and condensate <lb/>parameters <lb/>Singly-wound skyrmions <lb/>Hierarchy of <lb/>dark vortices <lb/>Series of <lb/>bright vortices <lb/>Dirac <lb/>point <lb/> 3 <lb/> 4 . . . <lb/> = 2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/> . . . <lb/> = 2 <lb/> Anderson-Toulouse <lb/>Mermin-Ho <lb/>Half-quantum <lb/>vortex <lb/> Figure 2. (color online) Schematic of relativistic nonlinear Dirac vortices. At the <lb/>Dirac point (horizontal direction) changing the interaction, lattice constant, particle <lb/>hopping, and density tunes the order parameter between bright vortices (red dots <lb/>over yellow) with different quantized rotation  ∈ Z <lb/> +  . The peaks and valleys <lb/>denote topological transitions between elements of the fundamental group π  1  (S <lb/> 1  ) <lb/>around the vortex core. Changing the chemical potential away from the Dirac point <lb/>(vertical direction) transitions the order parameter into skyrmion solutions with a <lb/>single quantum of rotation  = 1. Higher energy then leads to multiple phase winding <lb/>states  ≥ 2 (red dots over blue), the energy increasing with winding . <lb/> symmetry of Calabi-Yau manifolds [49, 50], and brane world scenarios [51]. Vortices <lb/>are generic to gauge theories where spontaneous symmetry breaking occurs. This <lb/>includes both the Abelian case [48, 52], as with Nielsen-Olesen vortices in the Abelian <lb/>Higgs model, in addition to the non-Abelian case [53], non-Abelian Yang-Mills <lb/>for example. Supersymmetric field theories which exhibit weak-strong duality rely <lb/>fundamentally on the presence of solitons and vortices, as these provide the necessary <lb/>degrees of freedom to make the dualities possible [54, 48]. <lb/>Our results are organized as follows. In Sec. 2 we express the full time-dependent <lb/>NLDE in (2+1)D in radial form appropriate for stationary vortices. This reduces <lb/>the problem to the solution of two coupled first order nonlinear ordinary differential <lb/>equations. In Sec. 3 we solve the NLDE analytically using asymptotic Bessel and <lb/>algebraic methods. Density and phase plots depicting each solution type are provided. <lb/>In Sec. 4 we present numerical methods and solutions for vortices. This approach allows <lb/>us to explore the full vortex landscape by tuning the various physical parameters using <lb/>the method of numerical shooting. Section 5 presents vortex solutions and spectra <lb/>in a weak harmonic trapping potential building on results from the previous sections. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 5 <lb/></page>

			<body> Finally, in Sec. 6 we conclude. <lb/> 2. Vortices in the nonlinear Dirac equation <lb/> In this section we express the NLDE in the appropriate coordinates for finding vortex <lb/>solutions and analyze the solution space at the energy functional level. We show that <lb/>in different regions of solution space the effective potentials switch between focusing <lb/>and defocusing forms, providing conditions for either bright (localized ring) or dark <lb/>(conventional) vortices. The NLDE describes the dynamics of a four-spinor in (2 + 1)-<lb/>dimensions, Ψ ≡ (Ψ  +  , Ψ  −  ) <lb/> T  , with the upper (+) and lower (−) two-spinors relating to <lb/>opposite K and K <lb/>  points of the honeycomb lattice and Ψ : R <lb/> 3  → C <lb/> 4  . The full NLDE <lb/>can be expressed as <lb/> iγ <lb/> µ  ∂  µ  − U <lb/> i=0,1 <lb/> Ψ <lb/>  †  M  i  ΨM  i <lb/> Ψ = 0 , <lb/> (1) <lb/>where the 4 × 4 interaction matrices M  i  are given by <lb/>M  i  ≡ <lb/> 1 <lb/>4 <lb/>(γ <lb/> 0  ) <lb/> 2  + <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>(−1) <lb/> i+1/2  γ <lb/> 1  γ <lb/> 2  , <lb/> (2) <lb/>constructed to give the correct cubic nonlinearites, local to each spinor component [12]. <lb/>The matrices γ <lb/> µ  (µ = 0, 1, 2) are the usual Dirac matrices in the chiral <lb/>representation [55]. Equation (1) describes a gapless theory which corresponds to <lb/>massless interacting Dirac spinors. Since the interactions do not couple different spinor <lb/>components, Eq. (1) can be split into two sets of equations (one for each of the K and <lb/> K <lb/>  points) of the form <lb/> i ∂  t  Ψ  +  = <lb/> −ic  l  σ · ∇ + U <lb/> i=0,1 <lb/> Ψ <lb/>  † <lb/> +  M <lb/> diag <lb/> i <lb/> Ψ  +  M <lb/> diag <lb/> i <lb/> Ψ  +  , <lb/> (3) <lb/>where we use the Pauli matrices σ ≡ (σ  x  , σ  y  , σ  z  ), and M <lb/> diag <lb/> i <lb/> is the nonzero 2 × 2 <lb/>submatrix along the diagonal of M  i  given explicitly by <lb/>M <lb/> diag <lb/> i <lb/> ≡ <lb/> 1 <lb/>4 <lb/>(σ  z  ) <lb/> 2  + <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>(−1) <lb/> i  σ  z  . <lb/> (4) <lb/>Note the presence of the effective speed of light c  l  and interaction strength U . For a <lb/>complete list of the relevant renormalized physical parameters see [14]. <lb/>We seek planar stationary solutions to Eq. (3), and thus we require the upper <lb/>two-spinor to be expressed in factorized form Ψ  +  (r, t) = exp(−iµt/) [ψ  A  (r), ψ  B  (r)] <lb/> T  , <lb/>where µ is the chemical potential of the system. The spinor components ψ  A(B)  (r) here <lb/>are complex functions on the plane, i.e., ψ  A(B)  : R <lb/> 2  → C. For stationary solutions in <lb/>rectangular coordinates, Eq. (3) further reduces to <lb/> − ic  l  (∂  x  − i∂  y  ) ψ  B  (x, y) + U |ψ  A  (x, y)| <lb/> 2  ψ  A  (x, y) = µψ  A  (x, y) , <lb/> (5) <lb/> −ic  l  (∂  x  + i∂  y  ) ψ  A  (x, y) + U |ψ  B  (x, y)| <lb/> 2  ψ  B  (x, y) = µψ  B  (x, y) , <lb/> (6) <lb/>with the full solution expressed as a linear combination of solutions from Dirac points <lb/> K and K <lb/>  . To obtain cylindrically symmetric solutions with arbitrary integer phase <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<body> winding, i.e. vortices, we transform to plane-polar coordinates. The time-independent <lb/>spinor wavefunctions are then written as <lb/> ψ  A  (r, θ) = ± i e <lb/> i(−1)θ  f  A  (r) , <lb/>ψ  B  (r, θ) = e <lb/> iiθ  f  B  (r) , <lb/> (7) <lb/>where  is the angular momentum quantum number (integral phase winding) and the <lb/>radial functions f  A(B)  are real functions of r. The asymmetric dependence on the winding <lb/>number  between spinor components in Eq. (7) is required. In polar coordinates, the <lb/>derivatives in Eq. (5)-(6) acquire factors of exp(−iθ) and exp(iθ), respectively. An offset <lb/>factor of exp(−iθ) in ψ  A  is then required in order to separate the rotational and radial <lb/>dependence. Applying the method of separation of variables forces the particular form <lb/>of angular dependence in Eq. (7). Equations. (5)-(6) then reduce to the two coupled <lb/>radial equations <lb/> − c  l <lb/> ∂  r  + <lb/>r <lb/> f  B  (r) + U |f  A  (r)| <lb/> 2  f  A  (r) = µf  A  (r) , <lb/> (8) <lb/> c  l <lb/> ∂  r  + <lb/>1− <lb/> r <lb/> f  A  (r) + U |f  B  (r)| <lb/> 2  f  B  (r) = µf  B  (r) . <lb/> (9) <lb/>Equations (8)-(9) comprise the key system of coupled nonlinear equations of this article. <lb/>In the sections that follow we will solve these using combinations of analytical and <lb/>numerical techniques for various asymptotic and core boundary conditions. Localized <lb/>solutions of Eqs. (8)-(9) may be categorized by their asymptotic forms, i.e., whether the <lb/>amplitudes f  A(B)  have zero or nonzero limits far from the core, a relevant distinction <lb/>in our problem. In particular, we note that in conventional BECs with repulsive <lb/>interactions the nonlinearity is always defocusing which leads to a vortex with the <lb/>familiar constant ambient profile that vanishes only at the core. This contrasts radically <lb/>to the physics in our problem, which we will see allows for (bipartite) vortices with <lb/>nonzero asymptotic profiles in addition to ones with asymptotically vanishing profiles. <lb/>The latter structures are the bright vortices or ring-vortices previously mentioned. <lb/> 3. Analytical vortex solutions <lb/> In this section we derive explicit vortex solutions of the NLDE using a combination of <lb/>analytical and numerical techniques. Different methods are applicable depending on <lb/>whether the chemical potential is zero or finite-valued and if the vortex has a single unit <lb/>of winding or arbitrarily large winding . For arbitrary winding and nonzero chemical <lb/>potential we use both an approximate asymptotic method and numerical shooting. In <lb/>the case where  = 0 or 1 exact analytical solutions are possible, and in particular <lb/>when µ = 0 concise algebraic forms occur. For all of the solutions in this section <lb/>we consider only the case of a spatially infinite condensate. In experiments, this is a <lb/>good approximation when the healing length, and thus the core of the vortex, is small <lb/>compared to the oscillator length associated with a trapping potential which sets the <lb/>size of the BEC. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 7 <lb/></page>

			<body> 3.1. Asymptotic Bessel solutions for large <lb/> Returning to the cylindrically symmetric form of the NLDE, Eqs. (8)-(9), we can see <lb/>that for winding values  ≥ 2 both f  A  and f  B  must vanish at r = 0 due to the presence <lb/>of the centrifugal terms. Thus, we will treat the special cases  = 0, 1 in a separate <lb/>section. To obtain vortex solutions we require spatial derivatives to vanish at infinity; <lb/>this means that for r → ∞, Eqs. (8)-(9) yield the asymptotic behavior <lb/>lim <lb/> r→∞ <lb/> f  A(B)  (r) <lb/> |f  A(B)  (r)| <lb/> 2  − µ/U <lb/> = 0 , <lb/> (10) <lb/>which implies <lb/>lim <lb/> r→∞ <lb/> f  A(B)  (r) <lb/> = 0, ± <lb/> µ/U . <lb/> (11) <lb/>The important point to note here is whether the f  A  (B) tends to zero or a non-zero <lb/>constant as r → ∞. To determine asymptotic forms for the radial functions we first look <lb/>for exponential decay to zero, or growth or decay to the constants ± <lb/> µ/U , in which case <lb/>we find no consistent asymptotic solution to Eqs. (8)-(9). Algebraic decay to zero may <lb/>be discerned by substituting f  A  (r) = r <lb/> −α  and f  B  (r) = r <lb/> −β  into Eqs. (8)-(9) for α, β &gt; 0, <lb/>decay or growth to ± <lb/> µ/U by f  A  (r) = r <lb/> −α  ± <lb/> µ/U and f  B  (r) = r <lb/> −β  ± <lb/> µ/U . For <lb/>the case of non-vanishing boundary conditions and  ≥ 2 the asymmetry in the angular <lb/>momentum terms complicates the task of finding solutions. We recall that the factors <lb/> ∂  r  + /r and ∂  r  + (1 − )/r act as index raising and lowering operators for the Bessel <lb/>functions J  n  . One can verify that Bessel functions are nearly exact solutions in the case <lb/>of a weak nonlinearity given by U |Ψ| <lb/> 2  /c  l  1. In this limit solutions of Eqs. (8)-(9) are <lb/>approximately Bessel functions of the first kind, J  l  and J  l−1  . A weak nonlinearity only <lb/>slightly modifies the Bessel form by perturbatively scattering J  l  and J  l−1  into higher <lb/> -valued states. <lb/>However, the case of strong nonlinearity is different. In this case we expect the <lb/>solution to deviate drastically from the Bessel form, especially for the non-vanishing <lb/>asymptotic profile of a vortex which interests us here. This heuristic discussion motivates <lb/>a modified Bessel-Fourier expansion as our ansatz, which must include Bessel functions <lb/>to all orders <lb/> f  A  (r) = A F (r) e <lb/> iQ(r) <lb/> a  0  + <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=1 <lb/> a  n  J  n  (r) <lb/> , <lb/> (12) <lb/> f  B  (r) = (B/A) f  A  (r) , <lb/> (13) <lb/>where A and B are normalization constants, J  n  (r) is the Bessel function of the first <lb/>kind of order n, a  0  and a  n  are the expansion coefficients, and Q(r) is the argument of <lb/>the integrating factor. Here we include the radial function F (r) in order to enlarge the <lb/>parameter space. The series that we have chosen to use runs over the Bessel index rather <lb/>than the usual form where the summation runs over the zeros of a single Bessel function <lb/>with a fixed index. This choice of expansion is valid but does not offer the convenience <lb/>of using the standard orthonormal relations for Bessel functions when computing the <lb/>coefficients a  n  . <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<body> Substituting the ansatz Eqs. (12)-(13) into Eq. (8)-(9), we then consolidate the <lb/>angular momentum and derivative terms in the resulting series expansion by using <lb/>the recurrence relations for Bessel functions: J  n  /r = (J  n−1  + J  n+1  )/2n and J <lb/> n  = <lb/>(J  n−1  − J  n+1  )/2. We obtain the recursion relations for the coefficients a  n  in addition to <lb/>two first-order differential equation for the integrating factor Q <lb/>iQ <lb/>  = − <lb/> F <lb/> F <lb/> − <lb/> a  0  <lb/>r <lb/> ± <lb/> U <lb/> c  l <lb/> i|AF | <lb/> 2 <lb/> a  0  + <lb/> n <lb/> a  n  J  n <lb/> 2 <lb/> ∓ i <lb/>µ <lb/> c  l <lb/> a  0  + <lb/> n  Ca  n  J  n <lb/> a  0  + <lb/> n  a  n  J  n <lb/> , <lb/> (14) <lb/> iQ <lb/>  = − <lb/> F <lb/> F <lb/> − <lb/> a  0  (1 − ) <lb/>r <lb/> ± <lb/> U <lb/> c  l <lb/> i|AF | <lb/> 2 <lb/> a  0  + <lb/> n <lb/> a  n  J  n <lb/> 2 <lb/> ∓ i <lb/>µ <lb/> c  l <lb/> a  0  + <lb/> n  Ca  n  J  n <lb/> a  0  + <lb/> n  a  n  J  n <lb/> , <lb/> (15) <lb/> − <lb/> µA <lb/> c  l  B <lb/> (1 − C)a  n  = <lb/> a  n+1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> + n + 1 <lb/> n + 1 <lb/> + <lb/> a  n−1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> − n + 1 <lb/> n − 1 <lb/> , <lb/> (16) <lb/> µB <lb/> c  l  A <lb/> (1 − C)a  n  = <lb/> a  n+1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 2 −  + n <lb/>n + 1 <lb/> + <lb/> a  n−1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 2 −  − n <lb/>n − 1 <lb/> . <lb/> (17) <lb/>In Eqs. (14)-(15) we have absorbed a fraction 1 − C &lt; 1 from the chemical potential <lb/>terms into the recursion relations. Solving the recursion relations leads to <lb/> A = ± iB , a  n  = <lb/> ± i <lb/>C µ <lb/>U (2 − 1) <lb/>  n−1  n ! <lb/> n  n−1  . <lb/> (18) <lb/>The vortex solution is obtained by setting a  0  = −1/(2) which cancels the factor of F (r) <lb/>in Eqs. (14)-(15), provided F = r <lb/> 1/2  . This effectively forces the solution to vanish at the <lb/>origin and also cancels the oscillating behavior of the Bessel functions at long distances. <lb/>Finally, the parameter C in Eq. (18) must be tuned to a critical value C vortex . If we <lb/>examine the asymptotic region r  ξ  Dirac  , far from the vortex core, the Bessel functions <lb/>decrease at a rate proportional to r <lb/> −1/2  . On the other hand, near the vortex core where <lb/> r  ξ  Dirac  , the Bessel functions have the form J  n  ∼ r <lb/> n  , for n ≥ 1. Using this information, <lb/>in the asymptotic regions r  ξ  Dirac  and r  ξ  Dirac  , we obtain the asymptotic solution <lb/>for Q <lb/>Q(r) ± <lb/> µ <lb/> c  l <lb/> r . <lb/> (19) <lb/>For <lb/> 2  1 the vortex profile is obtained for C vortex  (5/2) × (2 − 1) and µ/U = 1 <lb/>with closed form given by <lb/> f  A  (r) = A(U r/c  l  ) <lb/> 1/2  e <lb/> ±i(U r/c  l  ) <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=1 <lb/> 5 <lb/>2 <lb/> i <lb/>  n−1  n ! <lb/> n  n−1  J  n  (U r/c  l  ) , <lb/> (20) <lb/>where the overall constant A is determined by normalizing the wavefunction to the <lb/>particle number. We emphasize here that Eq. (20) is an approximate solution which <lb/>applies only very near to or far from the vortex core, and for large winding number. <lb/>Density and phase plots for the complex Bessel solution are shown in Fig. 3 on the left <lb/>with radial profile plots shown in Fig. 4(a). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 9 <lb/></page>

			<body> x/ξ  Dirac <lb/> x/ξ  Dirac <lb/> y/ξ <lb/> Dirac <lb/> y/ξ <lb/> Dirac <lb/> |Ψ| <lb/> 2 <lb/> arg(Ψ)/π <lb/> (a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>(c) <lb/>(d) <lb/> x/ξ  Dirac <lb/> x/ξ  Dirac <lb/> y/ξ <lb/> Dirac <lb/> y/ξ <lb/> Dirac <lb/> |Ψ| <lb/> 2 <lb/> arg(Ψ)/π <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>(c) <lb/>(d) <lb/> Figure 3. (color online) Phase and density plots for the  = 4 asymptotic Bessel <lb/>topological vortex (left) and numerical topological vortex (right). (a,b) A-sublattice <lb/>density and phase. (c,d) B-sublattice density and phase. <lb/> 3.2. Algebraic solutions <lb/> Here we treat solutions for µ = 0 and &gt; 1 since closed algebraic forms exist for <lb/> = 0, 1 with µ  = 0. By setting µ = 0 in Eqs. (8)-(9) we obtained exact non-topological <lb/>vortex solutions. From a technical standpoint eliminating the chemical potential terms <lb/>in the NLDE simplifies the problem considerably in that solutions to the homogeneous <lb/>non-interacting equations are algebraic forms. This means that vortex solutions do not <lb/>connect to Bessel function scattering states in the zero-interaction limit. To obtain <lb/>these solutions we start from an algebraic ansatz f  A  = Ar <lb/> α(β)  /(1 + γ r <lb/> δ  ) <lb/> 1/2  and likewise <lb/>for f  B  with A → B, where α, β, γ, δ ∈ R and A, B ∈ C. Substituting this form for f  A <lb/> and f  B  into Eqs. (8)-(9) and solving for A, B, α, β, γ and δ by matching coefficients of <lb/>like-power terms, we arrive at <lb/> f  A  (r) = <lb/> A (U r/c  l  ) <lb/> −1 <lb/> 1 + <lb/> |B|  2  B <lb/>A(4−2) <lb/> (U r/c  l  )  8(−1/2) <lb/>  1/2  , <lb/> (21) <lb/> f  B  (r) = <lb/> B (U r/c  l  ) <lb/> 3−2 <lb/> 1 + <lb/> |B|  2  B <lb/>A(4−2) <lb/> (U r/c  l  )  8(−1/2) <lb/>  1/2  , <lb/> (22) <lb/>where it can be proved by construction that no such solution exists when µ  = 0. <lb/>Additionally, the constants in Eqs. (21)-(22) satisfy the constraint and normalization <lb/>condition <lb/> |A| <lb/> 2  A <lb/>B <lb/> = <lb/> |B| <lb/> 2  B <lb/>CA <lb/> = 4 − 2 , <lb/> rdr <lb/> |A| <lb/> 2  (U r/c  l  ) <lb/> 2−2  + |B| <lb/> 2  (U r/c  l  ) <lb/> 6−4 <lb/> 1 + <lb/> |B|  2  B <lb/>A(4−2) <lb/> (U r/c  l  )  8(−1/2) <lb/> = 1 . (23) <lb/>When the winding number  = 0 or 1 an angular momentum term appears in only <lb/>one of Eqs. (8)-(9). In this case the NLDE is easier to solve and allows for algebraic forms <lb/>even when µ  = 0. For the homogeneous case µ = 0 though the results in Eqs. (21)-(22) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>

			<body> r/ξ  Dirac <lb/> r/ξ  Dirac <lb/> r/ξ  Dirac <lb/> r/ξ  Dirac <lb/> f  A <lb/> f  B <lb/> f  A <lb/> f  B <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>5 <lb/>5 <lb/>5 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.25 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/> |Ψ  A(B)  | <lb/> f  B  (r) <lb/> f  A  (r) <lb/> f  B  (r) <lb/> f  B  (r) <lb/> f  B  (r) <lb/> f  B  (r) <lb/> f  A  (r) <lb/> f  A  (r) <lb/> f  A  (r) <lb/> f  A  (r) <lb/> f  A  (r) <lb/> f  A  (r) <lb/> f  B  (r) <lb/> f  B  (r) <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>(c) <lb/>(d) <lb/>(e) <lb/>(f) <lb/>(g) <lb/>(h) <lb/> Figure 4. (color online) NLDE vortex radial solutions. (a) Bessel solution for  = 3; <lb/>(b) numerical solution for  = 4; (c) vortex/soliton; (d) Anderson-Toulouse vortex; <lb/>(e) ring-vortex solution for  = 4; (f) ring-vortex/soliton solution; (g) Mermin-Ho <lb/>vortex; (h) half-quantum vortex. The plot in (a) is the square modulus of the complex <lb/>asymptotic solution in Eq. (20). In each plot, the upper and lower spinor radial <lb/>solutions are indicated in red and blue, respectively. <lb/> can be used to obtain the correct solution. Substituting  = 1 into Eqs. (21)-(22) gives <lb/>the upper and lower spinor components <lb/> f  A  (r) = <lb/> A <lb/> 1 + <lb/> |B|  2  B <lb/> 2A <lb/> (U r/c  l  )  4 <lb/>  1/2  , <lb/> (24) <lb/> f  B  (r) = <lb/> B (U r/c  l  ) <lb/> 1 + <lb/> |B|  2  B <lb/> 2A <lb/> (U r/c  l  )  4 <lb/>  1/2  . <lb/> (25) <lb/>Equations (24)-(25) describe a vortex whose density peaks in the shape of a ring with <lb/>a bright soliton (no rotation) located at its center. This solution corresponds to the <lb/>ring-vortex/soliton from our previous work [13], but obtained here as a special case of <lb/>the more general result in Eqs. (21)-(22). Note that Setting  = 0 in Eqs. (21)-(22) <lb/>effectively interchanges the forms for f  A  and f  B  but leads to the same solution type. <lb/>The ring-vortex/soliton radial solution is plotted on the left in Fig. 4(d) with the density <lb/>and phase shown on the right of Fig. 5. <lb/>For the case µ  = 0 and  = 1 we obtain the solution <lb/> f  A  (r) = <lb/> µ/U (µ r/c  l  ) <lb/>[1 + (µ r/c  l  )  2  ] <lb/> 1/2 <lb/> , <lb/> (26) <lb/> f  B  (r) = <lb/> µ/U <lb/> [1 + (µ r/c  l  )  2  ] <lb/> 1/2 <lb/> . <lb/> (27) <lb/>This solution describes a coreless vortex, a vortex with unit rotation in f  A  and a bright <lb/>soliton in f  B  centered at the core of the vortex. This solution can also be obtained by <lb/>beginning with the ansatz f  A  = tanh[g(r)], f  B  = sech[g(r)] which, upon substitution <lb/>into the NLDE, may be directly integrated to give g(r) = arcsinh(µr/c  l  ); applying a <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 11 <lb/></page>

			<body> standard identity then yields Eqs. (26)-(27). The vortex/soliton radial solution, density <lb/>and phase are shown in Fig. 4(a) (right side) and Fig. 6 (left side), respectively. Radial <lb/>plots for the  = 4 ring-vortex are shown in Fig. 4(c) (left side) with density and phase <lb/>plots for the case  = 2 shown in Fig. 5 (left side). <lb/> x/ξ  Dirac <lb/> x/ξ  Dirac <lb/> y/ξ <lb/> Dirac <lb/> y/ξ <lb/> Dirac <lb/> |Ψ| <lb/> 2 <lb/> arg(Ψ)/π <lb/> (a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>(c) <lb/>(d) <lb/> x/ξ  Dirac <lb/> x/ξ  Dirac <lb/> y/ξ <lb/> Dirac <lb/> y/ξ <lb/> Dirac <lb/> |Ψ| <lb/> 2 <lb/> arg(Ψ)/π <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>(c) <lb/>(d) <lb/> Figure 5. (color online) Phase and density plots for the the  = 2 ring-vortex (left) <lb/>and the  = 1 ring-vortex/soliton (right). (a,b) A-sublattice density and phase. (c,d) <lb/>B-sublattice density and phase. <lb/> 3.3. Skyrmion solutions <lb/> To obtain Skyrmion solutions we choose an ansatz of the form f  A  = η cosϕ , f  B  = η sinϕ, <lb/>where the parameters η and ϕ are functions of the radial coordinate. For background <lb/>on skyrmions in 2-dimensions see [42, 56]. The NLDE then reduces to two first order <lb/>nonlinear ODEs <lb/> dϕ <lb/>dr <lb/> = <lb/>(1 + ) <lb/> 2r <lb/>sin2ϕ + <lb/> U <lb/> 2c  l <lb/> η <lb/> 2  (1 + cos <lb/> 2  2ϕ) − <lb/> µ <lb/> c  l <lb/> , <lb/> (28) <lb/> dη <lb/>dr <lb/> = η <lb/>r <lb/> cos2ϕ − η <lb/> 1 <lb/> r <lb/> cos <lb/> 2  ϕ + <lb/> U <lb/> c  l <lb/> η <lb/> 3  sin4ϕ . <lb/> (29) <lb/>The first point to note is that the centripetal terms place a restriction on the behavior <lb/>of ϕ for r → 0. Equation (28) forces the condition ϕ → nπ/2 (n ∈ Z), and the only <lb/>way to keep Eq. (29) finite at r = 0 is to require  = 1. This condition corresponds <lb/>to ϕ(0) = π, or  = 0 for ϕ(0) = π/2. Thus, skyrmion solutions exist only for one <lb/>unit of angular momentum in either the upper or the lower two-spinor component. As <lb/>we noted previously, choosing  = 0 or 1 simply transfers a unit of rotation from one <lb/>component to the other. We can reduce the problem further by adding the restriction <lb/>that η = C ≡ constant. We then obtain the value for C by examining the asymptotic <lb/>form of the equations for r → ∞. In this limit (assuming finite energy) we set the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 12 <lb/></page>

			<body> derivative terms equal to zero and thereby obtain the asymptotic values <lb/> ϕ(∞) = <lb/> mπ <lb/> 4 <lb/> , η = ± <lb/> 4 µ/U <lb/> 3 + (−1)  m  , <lb/> (30) <lb/>where m ∈ Z. Next, we combine Eqs. (28)-(29) into one equation for ϕ <lb/>dϕ <lb/>dr <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/> r <lb/> sin2ϕ − <lb/> µ <lb/> c  l <lb/> + <lb/>2µC  m <lb/> c  l <lb/> 1 + <lb/> cos <lb/> 2  ϕ − <lb/> 4µC  m <lb/> c  l <lb/> r sin4ϕ <lb/>  2 <lb/> , <lb/> (31) <lb/>for  = 1, and <lb/> dϕ <lb/>dr <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>2r <lb/>sin2ϕ − <lb/> µ <lb/> c  l <lb/> + <lb/>2µC  m <lb/> c  l <lb/> 1 + <lb/> sin <lb/> 2  ϕ − <lb/> 4µC  m <lb/> c  l <lb/> r sin4ϕ <lb/>  2 <lb/> , <lb/> (32) <lb/>for  = 0, where C  m  = 1/2 for odd m, and C  m  = 1/4 for even m. Equations. (28)-(29) <lb/>allow for two types of solutions labeled by the subscript m; one solution asymptotically <lb/>approaches π/4, whereas the other solution approaches 0. The Anderson-Toulouse <lb/>solution is obtained for ϕ(0) = π/2 and ϕ(∞) = 0 [57, 58], whereas the Mermin-<lb/>Ho skyrmion corresponds to the case ϕ(∞) = π/4 in Eq. (30) [57, 59]. Note that for the <lb/>Anderson-Toulouse and Mermin-Ho solutions we find that η = <lb/> 2µ/U for the envelope <lb/>factor. The radial profiles for both the Mermin-Ho and Anderson-Toulouse vortices are <lb/>obtained by solving Eqs. (31)-(32) using a straightforward shooting method [43]. We <lb/>have plotted the radial solutions for both types of skyrmions in Fig. 4(b)-(c) (right side), <lb/>with plots of the density and phase shown in Fig. 6 (right side) and Fig. 7 (left side). <lb/> x/ξ  Dirac <lb/> x/ξ  Dirac <lb/> y/ξ <lb/> Dirac <lb/> y/ξ <lb/> Dirac <lb/> |Ψ| <lb/> 2 <lb/> arg(Ψ)/π <lb/> (a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>(c) <lb/>(d) <lb/> x/ξ  Dirac <lb/> x/ξ  Dirac <lb/> y/ξ <lb/> Dirac <lb/> y/ξ <lb/> Dirac <lb/> |Ψ| <lb/> 2 <lb/> arg(Ψ)/π <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>(c) <lb/>(d) <lb/> Figure 6. (color online) Phase and density plots for the  = 1 vortex/soliton (left) <lb/>and  = 1 Anderson-Toulouse skyrmion (right). (a,b) A sublattice density and phase. <lb/>(c,d) B sublattice density and phase. <lb/> 3.4. Half-quantum vortices <lb/> The NLDE supports half-quantum vortices, i.e., vortices with half-integer winding <lb/> = 1/2. Such solutions are obtained by forming superpositions of the components f  A <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 13 <lb/></page>

			<body> x/ξ  Dirac <lb/> x/ξ  Dirac <lb/> y/ξ <lb/> Dirac <lb/> y/ξ <lb/> Dirac <lb/> |Ψ| <lb/> 2 <lb/> arg(Ψ)/π <lb/> (a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>(c) <lb/>(d) <lb/> x/ξ  Dirac <lb/> x/ξ  Dirac <lb/> y/ξ <lb/> Dirac <lb/> y/ξ <lb/> Dirac <lb/> |Ψ| <lb/> 2 <lb/> arg(Ψ)/π <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>(c) <lb/>(d) <lb/> Figure 7. (color online) Phase and density plots for the  = 1 Mermin-Ho skyrmion <lb/>(left) and half-quantum vortex solutions (right). (a,b) A sublattice density and phase. <lb/>(c,b) B sublattice density and phase. <lb/> and f  B  which solve the Mermin-Ho condition in part b. above [60, 61]. The necessary <lb/>requirement is that both spinor components approach the same nonzero value at spatial <lb/>infinity far from the vortex core (see Fig. 4(c)). The appropriate spinor combinations <lb/>are <lb/> f  A  = −ie <lb/> iθ/2  sinϕ − ie <lb/> −iθ/2  cosϕ , <lb/> (33) <lb/> f  B  = ie <lb/> iθ/2  sinϕ − ie <lb/> −iθ/2  cosϕ , <lb/> (34) <lb/>where ϕ(r) is the Mermin-Ho parameter. Note that Eqs. (34)-(34) constitute a solution <lb/>of the full time-dependent NLDE but do not solve the time-independent case. To see <lb/>that Eqs. (34)-(34) are associated with a fractional winding number we note that far <lb/>from the vortex core ϕ → π/4, where the wavefunction takes the form <lb/>Ψ = 2 <lb/> µ/U e <lb/> −iθ/2  [i cos(θ/2), sin(θ/2)] . <lb/> (35) <lb/>Using Eq. (35) we compute the geometric phase from circling the vortex core by the <lb/>Berry phase prescription <lb/> φ  B  ≡ exp <lb/> Ψ| <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂θ <lb/> |Ψ dθ <lb/> , <lb/> (36) <lb/>where φ  B  is the Berry phase and θ is the polar angle. The vortex wavefunction <lb/>transforms as a Dirac spinor under spatial rotations accumulating a phase factor <lb/>exp (−iσ  z  θ/2), where σ  z  is the third Pauli matrix. Working out the exponential in <lb/>Eq. (36) gives <lb/>  2π <lb/> 0 <lb/> dθ e <lb/> iθ/2 <lb/> − i e <lb/> iθ/2  cos(θ/2) , e <lb/> −iθ/2  sin(θ/2) <lb/> × <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂θ <lb/>e <lb/> −iθ/2 <lb/> i e <lb/> −iθ/2  cos(θ/2) <lb/> e <lb/> iθ/2  sin(θ/2) <lb/> = <lb/>  2π <lb/>0 <lb/> dθ <lb/> − <lb/> i <lb/> 2 <lb/> = −i π . <lb/> (37) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 14 <lb/></page>

			<body> Radial profiles for half-quantum vortex spinor components are plotted in Fig. 4(d) where <lb/>we have taken the polar angle equal to zero. Density and phase plots are shown in Fig. 7 <lb/>with general properties of vortices tabulated in Table 1. <lb/> Vortex type <lb/>Winding <lb/>Analytic form of Ψ(r) <lb/> Topology <lb/> Vortex/soliton <lb/> = 1 <lb/> i <lb/> 1 <lb/> √ <lb/> 1+ (r/r0)  2 <lb/> , e <lb/> iθ <lb/> (r/r0) <lb/> √ <lb/> 1+ (r/r0)  2 <lb/>  T <lb/> |ψ  A  (∞)| = 1 <lb/>Ring-vortex/soliton <lb/> = 1 <lb/> i <lb/> 1 <lb/> √ <lb/> 1+ (r/r0)  4 <lb/> , e <lb/> iθ <lb/> (r/r0) <lb/> √ <lb/> 1+ (r/r0)  4 <lb/>  T <lb/> non-<lb/>topological <lb/>Anderson-Toulouse skyrmion <lb/> = 1 <lb/> i cosϕ(r/r  0  ), e <lb/> iθ  sinϕ(r/r  0  ) <lb/>  T <lb/> ϕ(∞) = 0 <lb/>Mermin-Ho skyrmion <lb/> = 1 <lb/> i cosϕ(r/r  0  ), e <lb/> iθ  sinϕ(r/r  0  ) <lb/>  T <lb/> ϕ(∞) = π/4 <lb/> Half-quantum vortex <lb/> = 1 <lb/>[icos θ/2, sin θ/2] <lb/> T <lb/> |Ψ(∞)| = 1 <lb/>Ring-vortex <lb/> = 2, 3, 4, ... <lb/> ie <lb/> i(−1)θ <lb/> (r/r0)  −1 <lb/> √ <lb/> 1+ (r/r0)  8(−1/2) <lb/> , e <lb/> iiθ <lb/> (r/r0)  3−2 <lb/> √ <lb/> 1+ (r/r0)  8(−1/2) <lb/>  T <lb/> non-<lb/>topological <lb/>General topological vortex <lb/> = 2, 3, 4, ... <lb/> Numerical shooting method <lb/> |ψ  A  (∞)| = 1 <lb/> Table 1. Vortex solutions of the NLDE. Solutions are described by their phase <lb/>winding, closed-form expression, and topological properties. Solutions which retain <lb/>nonzero density far from the core have a conserved topological charge associated with <lb/>the radial direction, and we state their asymptotic form. This is in addition to the <lb/>azimuthal phase winding signifying elements of the fundamental group π  1  (S <lb/> 1  ) ∼ = Z. <lb/> Note that r  0  is the length scale associated with the chemical potential or the interaction <lb/>strength depending on the particular solution. <lb/> 4. Vortices by the method of numerical shooting <lb/> In general, vortex profiles for arbitrary phase winding  and chemical potential µ may be <lb/>obtained using a numerical shooting method as described in Refs. [43] and [62]. These <lb/>include topological vortices with non-vanishing tails as well as non-topological ring-<lb/>vortices whose tails vanish far from the core. To proceed we first convert the NLDE to <lb/>dimensionless form by introducing the rescaled radial coordinate and spinor components <lb/> χ ≡ µr/(c  l  ) , η  A  ≡ <lb/> U/µf  A  , η  B  ≡ <lb/> U/µf  B  , <lb/> (38) <lb/>so that Eqs. (8)-(9) become <lb/> ∂  χ  + <lb/>χ <lb/> η  B  (χ) − |η  A  (χ)| <lb/> 2  η  A  (χ) = −η  A  (χ) , <lb/> (39) <lb/> − <lb/> ∂  χ  + <lb/>1 − <lb/>χ <lb/> η  A  (χ) − |η  B  (χ)| <lb/> 2  η  B  (χ) = −η  B  (χ) . <lb/> (40) <lb/>Here the dependence of the solution on the choice of angular quantum number  is <lb/>implied. The asymptotic form of these equations shows that moduli for convergent <lb/>solutions |η  A(B)  | can approach either 0 or 1 for large χ. To study the analytic structure <lb/>as well as a practical starting point for application of numerical methods, we expand <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 15 <lb/></page>

			<body> (a) <lb/> (b) <lb/>(c) <lb/> f  A <lb/> f  B <lb/> 0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/> Ur/c  l <lb/> Ur/c  l <lb/> Ur/c  l <lb/> f  A  (r) <lb/> f  B  (r) <lb/> f  B  (r) <lb/> f  A  (r) <lb/> f  A  (r) <lb/> f  B  (r) <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/> −1 <lb/> Figure 8. (color online) Radial profiles for  &gt; 1 vortices by numerical shooting. (a) <lb/>Profile for  = 2. (b) Profile for  = 3. (c) Profile for  = 4. <lb/> the solution in a power series in χ <lb/> η  A  (χ) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> j=0 <lb/> a  j  χ <lb/> j  , <lb/>η  B  (χ) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> j=0 <lb/> b  j  χ <lb/> j  . <lb/> (41) <lb/>Substituting these forms into the NLDE gives relations for the expansion coefficients <lb/>(1 + )b  1  − a <lb/> 3 <lb/>0  = −a  0  , <lb/> (42) <lb/>(2 + )b  2  − 3a  1  a <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  = −a  1  , <lb/> (43) <lb/>(3 + )b  3  − 3a  2  a <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  − 3a  0  a <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  = −a  2  , <lb/> (44) <lb/>. . . <lb/>(2 − )a  1  + b <lb/> 3 <lb/>0  = b  0  , <lb/> (45) <lb/>(3 − )a  2  + 3b  1  b <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  = b  1  , <lb/> (46) <lb/>(4 − )a  3  + 3b  2  b <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  + 3b  0  b <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  = b  2  , <lb/> (47) <lb/>. . . <lb/> . <lb/> Choosing a particular value for  determines the values of both a  0  and b  0  and we find <lb/>that there is only one independent parameter. Thus, for a given value of  a vortex <lb/>is found by tuning a  −1  towards a critical value a vortex <lb/> −1 <lb/> . As examples, we have found <lb/>vortices for the three lowest  values for which both spinor components have nonzero <lb/>rotation <lb/> a vortex <lb/> 1 <lb/> = 0.571718... , <lb/> = 2 , <lb/> (48) <lb/> a vortex <lb/> 2 <lb/> = 0.145291... , <lb/> = 3 , <lb/> (49) <lb/> a vortex <lb/> 3 <lb/> = 0.0240267... , <lb/> = 4 . <lb/> (50) <lb/>The associated radial profiles for these solutions are plotted in Fig. 8. In Fig. 9 we <lb/>illustrate convergence for both spinor components for the  = 2 vortex. Convergence to <lb/>the vortex profile is seen by overlaying an excitation of the vortex (a) and the free-particle <lb/>Bessel-like solution (b). Note that there are two types of radially excited solutions <lb/>characterized by the property that |η  A,(B)  | oscillate around 1 or around 0. <lb/>We may elaborate further on the oscillating regimes on either side of the flat vortex <lb/>profile by examining the solution for  = 1. The  = 1 state corresponds to one unit of <lb/>rotation in ψ  B  and no rotation in ψ  A  , in which case a trivial constant solution exists, i.e., <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 16 <lb/></page>

			<body> (b) <lb/> r/ξ  Dirac <lb/> Ψ <lb/> (a) <lb/> r/ξ  Dirac <lb/> Ψ <lb/> (a) <lb/>( b) <lb/> 0 <lb/>10 <lb/>10 <lb/> r/ξ  Dirac <lb/> r/ξ  Dirac <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/> f  B <lb/> f  A <lb/> 0 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 2 <lb/>5 <lb/>5 <lb/> f  B  (x) <lb/> f  A  (x) <lb/> Figure 9. (color online) Convergence of numerical vortex for  = 2. (a) For <lb/> a  1  &gt; a vortex <lb/> 1 <lb/> , the solution overshoots to a radial excited state of the vortex. Note that <lb/>such oscillating solutions converge to unity far from the core. (b) For a  1  &lt; a vortex <lb/> 1 <lb/> , the <lb/>solution undershoots and converges to the linear solution Bessel functions. The solid <lb/>blue and dashed red plots are the A and B sublattice radial wavefunctions, respectively. <lb/>The solid black and dashed black plots are the exact solutions for the A and B sublattice <lb/>radial wavefunctions, respectively. <lb/> η  A  = 1 and η  B  = 0, for 0 ≥ χ &gt; ∞. We address this solution as it offers a clear look at <lb/>higher radial excitations. To see this we solve Eqs. (39)-(40) by numerical shooting for <lb/> = 1. The resulting spin component profiles are plotted in Fig. 10(a)-(c) where we have <lb/>also included plots of the associated total densities |Ψ| <lb/> 2  ≡ |ψ  A  | <lb/> 2  +|ψ  B  | <lb/> 2  in Figs. 10(d)-(f). <lb/>Radial excited states appear as we tune the initial value for η  A  , or equivalently a  0  in the <lb/>Taylor expansion, away from unity. The spatially constant solution obtained for a  0  = 1 <lb/>can be thought of as a boundary between two oscillating regimes: one characterized <lb/>by strong nonlinearity with oscillations around η  A  = 1, η  B  = 1 in Fig. 10(b); the <lb/>other associated with weak nonlinearity with oscillations around η  A  = η  B  = 0 shown in <lb/>Fig. 10(c). When tuning a  0  upward from unity, the total density in Fig. 10(e) shows <lb/>the onset of inward movement of bright vortex rings over a nonzero background. For <lb/>this plot we have chosen a  0  = 1 + 10 <lb/> −7  . Here we see that the solution overshoots to an <lb/>excited state of the vortex and enters a regime where the nonlinearity dominates the <lb/>kinetic energy. In contrast, for the choice a  0  = 1 − 10 <lb/> −7  Figs. 10(c) and (f) show the <lb/>onset of radial oscillations which result from a dominant kinetic energy in the equations <lb/>of motion. In this case the total density exhibits decaying oscillations towards a zero <lb/>background density. Here, undershooting the flat solution results in solutions which <lb/>approach the Bessel function form as seen in Fig. 10(c). This is what we expect to <lb/>see for weak nonlinearity. This illustration highlights the property of the Dirac kinetic <lb/>terms which act by confining the solution in the presence of strong nonlinearity. <lb/>So far in this section we have shown how tuning the initial condition above some <lb/>critical value forces the solution into the strongly nonlinear regime, whereas below this <lb/>value leads to solutions in the weakly nonlinear regime. In our analysis we held the <lb/>chemical potential and interaction fixed, µ = U = 1. We now study the effect of tuning <lb/>the chemical potential for µ &gt; 1 → µ = 0, while maintaining the initial value in the <lb/>shooting process and the interaction fixed. For arbitrary phase winding we will see a <lb/>progression from Bessel solutions through a topological vortex, then finally ending in a <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 17 <lb/></page>

			<body> Ur/c  l <lb/> Ur/c  l <lb/> Ur/c  l <lb/> 1 <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/> f  B <lb/> f  A <lb/> 0 <lb/>10 <lb/>25 <lb/>25 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>25 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/> (b) <lb/>(a) <lb/>(d) <lb/>(c) <lb/>(f) <lb/>(e) <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/> |Ψ| <lb/> 2 <lb/> f  A  (x) <lb/> f  B  (x) <lb/> 5 <lb/>15 20 <lb/>5 <lb/>5 <lb/>15 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>20 <lb/> Figure 10. (color online) Radial excitations for  = 1. (a) Globally flat solution. (b) <lb/>Strong nonlinearity. (c) Weak nonlinearity. <lb/> single bright ring-vortex with vanishing tail. This ending solution is non-topological in <lb/>the radial dimension in that the skyrmion condition |ψ  A  | <lb/> 2  + |ψ  B  | <lb/> 2  = 1 does not hold. <lb/>This solution resembles those found in attractive BECs and also in optics [refs here]. <lb/>Although we demonstrate such solutions by analytical methods in the next section, the <lb/>numerical approach allows us to demonstrate the transition from the free-particle limit, <lb/> µ  U (weak nonlinearity), to the vortex limit, µ  U (strong nonlinearity). To show <lb/>this transition we choose a particular rescaling of the NLDE such that the limit µ → 0 <lb/>makes sense, i.e., <lb/> χ ≡ U <lb/> 2  r/(c  l  µ) , η  A  ≡ <lb/> µ/U f  A  , η  B  ≡ <lb/> µ/U f  B  . <lb/> (51) <lb/>The resulting dimensionless NLDE is <lb/> − <lb/> ∂  χ  + <lb/>χ <lb/> η  B  (χ) + |η  A  (χ)| <lb/> 2  η  A  (χ) = ˜ <lb/> µ <lb/> 2  η  A  (χ) , <lb/> (52) <lb/> ∂  χ  + <lb/>1 − <lb/>χ <lb/> η  A  (χ) + |η  B  (χ)| <lb/> 2  η  B  (χ) = ˜ <lb/> µ <lb/> 2  η  B  (χ) . <lb/> (53) <lb/>Staring with the case  = 1, we fix a  0  = 1 and b  0  = 0 in the Taylor expansions, <lb/>Eq. (41), and tune <lb/>  ≡ µ/U toward zero starting from <lb/> &gt; 1. The progression <lb/>of this solution as <lb/>  → 0 is depicted in the sequence of plots in Fig. 11. As <lb/>  is <lb/>reduced towards 1, Fig. 11(a)-(c), Bessel-like oscillations about η  A(B)  = 0 are pushed <lb/>out towards large χ, completely flattening out the solution at <lb/>  = 1 in Fig. 11(d). As <lb/>we continue decreasing <lb/>  towards 0, oscillations about η  A(B)  = 1 move inward from <lb/>large χ and finally flatten out leaving only a coreless ring-vortex centered at χ = 0 <lb/>shown in Fig. 11(i). The precise values of the renormalized chemical potential are <lb/>  = 1.22, 1.09, 1.0005, 1, 0.9995, 0.775, 0.55, 0.316, 0.1, for the panels (a)-(i) in Fig. 11, <lb/>respectively. <lb/>Analogous progressions are seen for arbitrary  values culminating in a single ring-<lb/>vortex centered at χ = 0 wheñ <lb/> µ = 0. The qualitative difference between the solution <lb/>for  = 1 and those for &gt; 1 is that in the later case both components must vanish at the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 18 <lb/></page>

			<body> 2 <lb/> 5 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 2 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 2 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/> −1 <lb/> f  B <lb/> f  A <lb/> f  B <lb/> f  A <lb/> f  B <lb/> f  A <lb/> Ur/c  l <lb/> Ur/c  l <lb/> Ur/c  l <lb/> (a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>(c) <lb/>(d) <lb/>(e) <lb/>(f) <lb/>(g) <lb/>(h) <lb/>(i) <lb/> f  B  (x) <lb/> f  A  (x) <lb/> 2 <lb/> Figure 11. (color online) Progression of radial profiles for vortices with phase winding <lb/> = 1. (a)-(c) Solutions where the renormalized chemical potential satisfies the <lb/>conditioñ <lb/> µ &gt; 1. (d) Solution for <lb/>  = 1. (e)-(i) Solutions for <lb/> &lt; 1. The sequence <lb/>of plots depicts the transition from the weakly-interacting Bessel-like solution in (a) <lb/>for which µ &gt; U , to the strongly nonlinear case for which µ &lt; U in (i). Note that <lb/>  = 1 is the boundary between solutions which oscillate around 0 and solutions which <lb/>oscillate around 1 and corresponds to the topological vortex solution when the skyrmion <lb/>symmetry is present for  = 1, or generally for &gt; 1 . The results in these plots show <lb/>that general ring-vortex solutions may be obtained by starting from excited states such <lb/>as in (e), then reducing <lb/>  towards zero. <lb/> origin. In terms of numerics this requires taking b  0  = a  0  = 0, while specifying the first <lb/>derivative of η  A  at the origin. The progression is plotted for the case  = 2 in Fig. 12. <lb/>Note that for each value of  there are two distinct types of asymptotically flat vortices, <lb/>as displayed in panels (d) and (i) of Fig. 12. The specific values of the renormalized <lb/>chemical potential are <lb/>  = 1.3, 1.21, 1.2047, 1.204267325, 1.203, 0.85, 0.55, 0.32, 0.1, <lb/>for panels (a)-(i) of Fig. 12. <lb/>The NLDE allows for vortex solutions which satisfy an additional symmetry given <lb/>by the constraint |η  A  | <lb/> 2  + |η  B  | <lb/> 2  = 1. Solutions which satisfy this constraint are the <lb/>vortex/soltion or coreless vortex, Anderson-Toulouse and Mermin-Ho skyrmions. Such <lb/>solutions may be obtained numerically by shooting backwards from large χ towards <lb/> χ = 0. In particular, for the Mermin-Ho solution we integrate backwards starting with <lb/>the asymptotic boundary condition η  A  = cos(π/4) + 10 <lb/> −k  , η  B  = sin(π/4) − 10 <lb/> −k  . Here <lb/> k is a parameter tuned to give the desired values of functions at the origin, analogous <lb/>to a  0  for the forward shooting. The Anderson-Toulouse vortex is obtained similarly but <lb/>with the boundary condition η  A  = cos(π/2) + 10 <lb/> −k  , η  B  = sin(π/2) − 10 <lb/> −k  . The half-<lb/>quantum vortex is obtained by forming linear combinations of the numerical Mermin-Ho <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 19 <lb/></page> 

			<body> 2 <lb/> 5 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 2 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 2 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/> −1 <lb/> f  B <lb/> f  A <lb/> f  B <lb/> f  A <lb/> f  B <lb/> f  A <lb/> Ur/c  l <lb/> Ur/c  l <lb/> Ur/c  l <lb/> (a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>(c) <lb/>(d) <lb/>(e) <lb/>(f) <lb/>(g) <lb/>(h) <lb/>(i) <lb/> f  B  (x) <lb/> f  A  (x) <lb/> Figure 12. (color online) Progression of radial profiles for vortices with phase winding <lb/> = 2. (a) ˜ <lb/> µ = 1.3. (b) ˜ <lb/> µ = 1.21. (c) ˜ <lb/> µ = 1.2047. (d) ˜ <lb/> µ = 1.204267325. (e) ˜ <lb/> µ = 1.203. <lb/>(f) ˜ <lb/> µ = 0.85. (g) ˜ <lb/> µ = 0.55. (h) ˜ <lb/> µ = 0.32. (i) ˜ <lb/> µ = 0.1. The topological vortex solution <lb/>is shown in (d) and isolated ring-vortex in (i). <lb/> components, as previously discussed. <lb/> 5. Discrete Spectra in a Harmonic Trap <lb/> We now extend our numerical studies from Sec. 4 to the treatment of vortices bound <lb/>within a weak harmonic potential similar to the analysis in our previous work on solitons. <lb/>Physically this accounts for an additional external harmonic trapping potential present <lb/>in real experiments. We follow a similar procedure as before in preparing the NLDE <lb/>for numerical analysis by first converting to a dimensionless form. Here we examine <lb/>the same solutions as in Sec. 4 but with tight confinement assumed in one of three <lb/>spatial dimensions and with additional weak harmonic confinement in the remaining <lb/>two directions. The oscillator frequencies thus satisfy ω  z  ω ≡ ω  x  , ω  y  . Equations. (8)-<lb/>(9) are already defined for a quasi-2D system, as the z-dependence has been integrated <lb/>out and parameters are normalized accordingly. Thus, we require the harmonic potential <lb/>to be dependent only on the planar directions x and y. We then introduce the planar-<lb/>symmetric harmonic potential V (r) = (1/2)M ω <lb/> 2  (x <lb/> 2  + y <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> 2  = (1/2)M ω <lb/> 2  r <lb/> 2  . Next, we <lb/>choose a dimensional rescaling of the NLDE appropriate to the harmonic oscillator. <lb/>We divide through by the harmonic oscillator energy ω and define the dimensionless <lb/>variable and spinor components in terms of this energy scale <lb/> χ ≡ ωr/(c  l  ) , η  A(B)  ≡ <lb/> U/ω f  A(B)  . <lb/> (54) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 20 <lb/></page>

			<body> This transforms the NLDE to <lb/> − <lb/> ∂  χ  + <lb/>χ <lb/> η  B  (χ) + |η  A  (χ)| <lb/> 2  η  A  (χ) + Q χ <lb/> 2  η  A  (χ) = ˜ <lb/> µ η  A  (χ) , <lb/> (55) <lb/> ∂  χ  + <lb/>1 − <lb/>χ <lb/> η  A  (χ) + |η  B  (χ)| <lb/> 2  η  B  (χ) + Q χ <lb/> 2  η  B  (χ) = ˜ <lb/> µ η  B  (χ) , <lb/> (56) <lb/>where the two dimensionless parameters in our equations are <lb/> Q ≡ <lb/> M c <lb/> 2 <lb/> l <lb/> 2 ω <lb/> , <lb/> ˜ <lb/> µ ≡ <lb/> µ <lb/> ω <lb/> . <lb/> (57) <lb/>Solving Eqs. (55)-(56) subject to the radial boundary conditions consistent with the trap <lb/>potential leads to radially quantized solutions labelled by integer quantum numbers. <lb/>Fig. 13 shows the first six quantized solutions for the  = 2 topological vortex in panels <lb/>(a)-(f), respectively. <lb/> 2 <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> f  B  (x) <lb/> f  A  (x) <lb/> (a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>(c) <lb/>(d) <lb/>(e) <lb/>(f) <lb/> −0.5 <lb/> 0 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>10 <lb/> f  A <lb/> f  B <lb/> f  A <lb/> f  B <lb/> Ur/c  l <lb/> Ur/c  l <lb/> Ur/c  l <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/> Figure 13. (color online) Numerical shooting for quantized vortices in a quasi-<lb/>2D harmonic potential. (a)-(f) First six quantized states for  = 2. The extreme <lb/>vortex limit (a) is characterized by a dominant nonlinearity with the spinor functions <lb/>flattening out over a greater portion of the domain with a weaker contribution from <lb/>the derivate terms. In contrast, in the free-particle limit (f) spinor functions resemble <lb/>Bessel oscillations. <lb/> To connect our results to experiment we compute the discrete eigenvalue spectra <lb/>for our radially quantized solutions which relate the chemical potential for a particular <lb/>solution to the strength of the nonlinearity. The spectrum is computed by first defining <lb/>the normalization condition as an integral over the dimensionless spinor components <lb/> χdχ(|η  A  (χ)| <lb/> 2  + |η  B  (χ)| <lb/> 2  ) = N , <lb/> (58) <lb/>where N on the right hand side encapsulates key lattice, condensate, and trap <lb/>information through the relation <lb/> N = <lb/> √ <lb/> 3 ω N U <lb/> 3 t <lb/> 2 <lb/> h <lb/> . <lb/> (59) <lb/>The calculation proceeds by fixing the value of Q in Eqs. (55)-(56) and varying <lb/> , while <lb/>computing the norm N for each value of <lb/>  by integrating Eq. (58). This procedure gives <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 21 <lb/></page>

			<body> the paired values (N , ˜ <lb/> µ). Fixing the total particle number N gives a relation between <lb/>the chemical potential µ and the interaction U . The values for the free parameter in the <lb/>Taylor expansion, a  0  , normalization N , and corresponding chemical potential <lb/>  = µ/ω, <lb/> are tabulated in Table 2 for the lowest radial  = 2 mode shown in Fig. 13(a). Plots of <lb/>this data along with the spectra for other solutions are shown in Fig. 14. We have taken <lb/> Q = 0.001 for all of our calculations. The spectrum for a fixed quantized mode tracks <lb/>the flow of the chemical potential as one tunes the system between the free-particle and <lb/>strongly nonlinear limits. In the former limit radial profiles for the lowest excitations <lb/>resemble decaying Bessel functions as in harmonically trapped massless Dirac particles, <lb/>whereas in the latter limit the nonlinearity dominates and the lowest trapped solutions <lb/>flatten, consistent with the Thomas-Fermi regime. For higher quantized modes radial <lb/>derivatives force the solution to maintain the Bessel-like form even as one tunes the <lb/>parameters into the strongly nonlinear regime. Convergence of our solutions is provided <lb/>in Appendix A. <lb/> Free parameter a  0 <lb/> Normalization N Chemical potential <lb/> 0.00000003 <lb/>1.9679 × 10 <lb/> −5 <lb/> 1.8 <lb/>0.0000 0365 <lb/>0.29560 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.0000 1018 <lb/>1.85630 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.0000 1532 51 <lb/>3.63288 <lb/>4 <lb/>0.0000 2089 47 <lb/>5.87547 <lb/>5 <lb/>0.0000 2708 8395 <lb/>8.62326 <lb/>6 <lb/>0.0000 3387 0293 <lb/>11.72273 <lb/>7 <lb/>0.0000 4118 5861 75 <lb/>15.54209 <lb/>8 <lb/>0.0000 4899 1422 392 <lb/>20.12707 <lb/>9 <lb/>0.0000 5725 2724 4133 <lb/>24.87695 <lb/>10 <lb/>0.0000 6594 2040 6807 59 <lb/>30.25986 <lb/>11 <lb/>0.0000 75036 2691 0578 11 <lb/>35.51507 <lb/>12 <lb/>0.0000 8451 5722 6783 7827 3795 <lb/>37.30714 <lb/>13 <lb/> Table 2. Numbers for computing spectra of  = 2 topological vortex ground state <lb/> solution. For a fixed value of the chemical potential <lb/> , the free parameter a  0  is tuned <lb/>until the desired radially quantized state is reached, for which one then computes <lb/>the normalization N by Eq. (58). As <lb/>  increases into the Thomas-Fermi regime the <lb/>dependence of the solution on a  0  becomes more sensitive, requiring a greater degree of <lb/>tuned accuracy as shown in the column on the left. <lb/> 6. Conclusion <lb/> In this article we have solved the NLDE by a variety of different methods for both the <lb/>idealized case of zero trapping potential and in the harmonic case. The latter context <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 22 <lb/></page>

			<body> (c) <lb/> N <lb/> ˜ <lb/> µ <lb/> (b) <lb/> N <lb/> ˜ <lb/> µ <lb/> (a) <lb/> N <lb/> ˜ <lb/> µ <lb/> (a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>(c) <lb/> Figure 14. (color online) Spectra for relativistic vortices confined in a harmonic <lb/>potential.(a) Vortex/soliton (black curve), Anderson-Toulouse skyrmion (red), Mermin-<lb/>Ho skyrmion (blue), and half-quantum vortex (green). (b) Topological vortices for <lb/> = 2, 3, 4 (black, red, blue). (c) Radial ground state and first two excited states of the <lb/>vortex without skyrmion symmetry (black, red, blue). In each figure, the renormalized <lb/>chemical potential is plotted as a function of the normalization. <lb/> provides the opportunity to study spatial quantization of vortex solutions in the radial <lb/>dimension. A preliminary asymptotic solution using Bessel function expansions provides <lb/>insight into the structure of the NLDE itself. Algebraic solutions were then obtained by <lb/>considering the case of zero-chemical potential. For these solutions the derivative and <lb/>nonlinear terms are perfectly balanced leading to bright vortex rings over a zero-density <lb/>background, a direct consequence of the Dirac operator. More generally, for nonzero <lb/>chemical potential, we found that analytical solutions are only possible when one unit of <lb/>winding is considered. In this case we used a numerical approach to obtain vortices with <lb/>arbitrarily large winding number. A combination of numerical and analytical techniques <lb/>yields skyrmion and half-quantum vortices, i.e., textures. <lb/>Having obtained our solutions, we computed their discrete spectra in the presence of <lb/>a weak harmonic potential. This gives us the low-temperature µ versus U landscape for <lb/>relativistic vortices, where µ and U are the chemical potential and lattice renormalized <lb/>particle interaction, respectively. For example, for finite µ we found that a series of phase <lb/>transitions occur as U is tuned from zero upward: we encounter a Mermin-Ho skyrmion <lb/>transitioning into a half-quantum vortex, followed by the Anderson-Toulouse skyrmion, <lb/>then finally into a vortex/soliton, i.e., a bright soliton at the core of a singly-wound <lb/>vortex. <lb/>Some of our solutions are similar to those obtained in spinor BECs, skyrmions in <lb/>particular. However, presence of the Dirac operator contrasts heavily with the Laplacian <lb/>case. This difference is most obvious in our bright ring-vortex solutions. Components of <lb/>these solutions resemble the bright vortex which occurs in attractive BECs, but in our <lb/>case the confining (focusing) regime of the Dirac operator is responsible for the effect in <lb/>spite of repulsive atomic interactions. Furthermore, we should emphasize the significant <lb/>distinction between our results and similar confinement effects in spinor BECs and in <lb/>traditional models such as Thirring and Gross-Neveu. In each of these other theories <lb/>the presence of confinement relies on attractive interactions in addition to a mass term, <lb/>whereas we consider strictly the repulsive case with zero mass. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 23 <lb/></page>

			<body> The interdisciplinary nature of our work suggests several future research directions. <lb/>For instance, the form of our solutions implies possible mappings to finite energy <lb/>solutions to classical gauge field equations. In particular, there is a deep connection <lb/>between the NLDE and Chern-Simons terms relevant to quantum Hall fluids and more <lb/>generally to relativistic field theories [63, 64, 65]. To see this connection consider that <lb/>Eq. (3) resembles the low-energy effective theory for massless Dirac fermions interacting <lb/>through a gauge field, where the latter has been absorbed into the local fermion <lb/>contact terms. The Dirac term by itself is symmetric under global phase and chiral <lb/>rotations which are made local through the addition of a gauge field. Quantization <lb/>results in the well known axial anomaly which one finds to have exactly the Chern-<lb/>Simons structure [66, 67, 68]. Thus, quantized theories of interacting fermions generally <lb/>result in couplings to Chern-Simons terms. In our case we have focused only on the <lb/>fermion part of the argument which naturally retains imprints of the omitted Chern-<lb/>Simons terms. Another argument for the NLDE/Chern-Simons connection hinges <lb/>on the well established duality between the Thirring model in (2+1)-dimensions and <lb/>Maxwell-Chern-Simons theory. The mapping is arrived at through bosonization, i.e., <lb/>reformulation in terms of paired particle and antiparticle field operators effective at <lb/>strong coupling or low energy. These points merit further inquiry into potentially <lb/>fruitful questions. Finally, in light of the successful analogs to date connecting condensed <lb/>matter and nonlinear optics we expect that our results should be reproducible within <lb/>an optics setting. Another obvious direction is to go deeper into the mathematics of <lb/>nonlinear partial differential equations. The vast amount of work in this area provides <lb/>an array of solution and classification methods which may be used to fully understand <lb/>critical bounds for well-posedness as well as general solutions to the full NLDE with <lb/>time dependence. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments <lb/> This material is based in part upon work supported by the National Science Foundation <lb/>under grant numbers PHY-1067973, PHY-1011156, and the Air Force Office of Scientific <lb/>Research grant number FA9550-08-1-0069. L.D.C. thanks the Alexander von Humboldt <lb/>foundation and the Heidelberg Center for Quantum Dynamics for additional support. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex"> Appendix A. Convergence of numerical vortex solutions <lb/> We demonstrate convergence of solutions in the harmonic trap for three of the  = 2 <lb/>topological vortices associated with the black curve in Fig. 14(b). Radial profiles for <lb/>the chosen solutions are shown in Figs. A1(a)-(c). The corresponding values of the <lb/>chemical potential are µ = 4, µ = 7, and µ = 10. These values interpolate between <lb/>the free-particle and strongly nonlinear limits (small to large µ values). These solutions <lb/>were obtained by finite differencing using a shooting method to tune the precision of the <lb/>initial value of ψ  A  such that ψ  A  1 to pick out the ground state. For convergence at <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 24 <lb/></page>

			<body> a single radial point, we compute the value of the solution at the dimensionless radius <lb/> χ  i  ≡ r  i  /ξ  Dirac  = 10 for several values of the grid size N = 10 <lb/> 2  , 10 <lb/> 3  , 10 <lb/> 4  , 10 <lb/> 5  , 10 <lb/> 6  . We use <lb/>the error formula which depends on the dimensionless radius and number of grid points <lb/> ε  A(B)  (χ  i  , N) ≡ <lb/> ψ(χ  i  ) <lb/> N+1 <lb/> A(B)  − ψ(χ  i  ) <lb/> N <lb/> A(B)  ) <lb/> ψ(χ  i  ) <lb/> N+1 <lb/> A(B)  + ψ(χ  i  ) <lb/> N <lb/> A(B)  ) <lb/> , <lb/> (A.1) <lb/>where in the symbol ψ(χ  i  ) <lb/> N <lb/> A(B)  the subscript A(B) denotes the sublattice excitation, <lb/> χ  i  denotes the i <lb/> th  element in the discretized dimensionless radial coordinate, and the <lb/>superscript N denotes the number of grid points used in the calculation. In Figs. A1(d)-<lb/>(f), we have plotted log  10 <lb/> ε  A(B)  (10, N) <lb/> versus log  10  N, for the solutions shown in <lb/>Figs. A1(a)-(c). <lb/> (b) <lb/> (c) <lb/> 0 <lb/> −2 <lb/> −4 <lb/>−6 <lb/>−8 <lb/>−10 <lb/> log  10  |ε  B  (10, N)| <lb/>log  10  |ε  A  (10, N)| <lb/> 3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/> (a) <lb/>(d) <lb/>(e) <lb/>(f) <lb/> 2 <lb/>log <lb/> 10 <lb/> |ε(N)| <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>log  10  N <lb/>log  10  N <lb/>log  10  N <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/> r/ξ  Dirac <lb/> r/ξ  Dirac <lb/> r/ξ  Dirac <lb/> ψ  A <lb/> ψ  B <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>0 <lb/> −2 <lb/>−4 <lb/>−6 <lb/>−8 <lb/>−10 <lb/> V <lb/>µ = 4 <lb/> µ = 7 <lb/> µ = 10 <lb/> −0.5 <lb/> 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/> Figure A1. (color online) Convergence of  = 2 topological vortex radial profiles. <lb/> (a)-(c) The explicit radial profiles for U = 1, µ = 4, 7, 10 and grid size N = 10 <lb/> 6  . The <lb/>black dashed curve is the harmonic potential. The scale for the potential is shown <lb/>on the right hand vertical axis of panel (c) in units of 10 <lb/> −4  nK. (d)-(f) Log-log error <lb/>profiles computed using Eq. (A.1). Note that the curves are a guide to the eye with <lb/>data points representing actual data. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] K. A. Emanual. Toward a general theory of hurricanes. AmSci, 76:370–379, 1988. <lb/>[2] A. N. Kolmogorov. The local structure of turbulence in incompressible viscous fluid for very large <lb/>reynolds number. Dokl. Akad. Nauk. SSSR, 30:301–305, 1941. <lb/>[3] L. Landau. Theory of the Superfluidity of Helium II. Phys. Rev., 60:356–358, 1941. <lb/>[4] W.F. Vinen. An introduction to quantum turbulence. J. Low Temp. Phys., 145:7–24, 2006. <lb/>[5] B. Nowak, D. Sexty, and T. Gasenzer. Superfluid turbulence: Nonthermal fixed point in an <lb/>ultracold Bose gas. Phys. Rev. B, 84:020506, Jul 2011. <lb/>[6] S. Kawai and S. Sasaki. BPS vortices in nonrelativistic M2-brane Chern-Simons-matter theory. <lb/> Phys. Rev. D, 80:025007, 2009. <lb/>[7] T. Ohmi and M. Nakahara. Quantum computing with p-wave superfluid vortices. J. Phys. Soc. <lb/>Jpn., 79:104602, 2010. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 25 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [8] B. Kain and H. Y. Ling. Vortices in Bose-Einstein condensate dark matter. Phys. Rev. D, <lb/> 82:064042, September 2010. <lb/>[9] B. Anderson. Experiments with vortices in superfluid atomic gases. J. Low Temp. Phys., 161:574– <lb/>602, 2010. <lb/>[10] M. Tsubota and K. Kasamatsu. Quantized Vortices and Quantum Turbulence, volume 177 of <lb/> Springer Series in Solid-State Sciences. Springer Berlin Heidelberg, Springer DE Heidelberger <lb/>Platz 3 14197 Berlin Germany, 2013. <lb/>[11] Y. Kawaguchi and M. Ueda. Symmetry classification of spinor Bose-Einstein condensates. Phys. <lb/>Rev. A, 84:053616, November 2011. <lb/>[12] L. H. Haddad and L. D. Carr. The nonlinear Dirac equation in Bose-Einstein condensates: <lb/>Foundation and symmetries. Physica D: Nonlinear Phenomena, 238:1413, 2009. <lb/>[13] L. H. Haddad and L. D. Carr. Relativistic linear stability equations for the nonlinear Dirac <lb/>equation in Bose-Einstein condensates. EPL (Europhysics Letters), 94:56002, 2011. <lb/>[14] L. H. Haddad, K. M. O&apos;Hara, and Lincoln D. Carr. The nonlinear Dirac equation: Preparation <lb/>and stability of relativistic vortices in Bose-Einstein condensates. arXiv:1210.2114v2, 2012. <lb/>[15] S. G. Park, C.-H.and Louie. Making massless Dirac fermions from a patterned two-dimensional <lb/>electron gas. Nano Lett., 9:1793, 2009. <lb/>[16] J. Kusk Block and N. Nygaard. Honeycomb optical lattices with harmonic confinement. Phys. <lb/>Rev. A, 81:053421, 2010. <lb/>[17] A. Szameit, M. C. Rechtsman, O. Bahat-Treidel, and M. Segev. PT-symmetry in honeycomb <lb/>photonic lattices. Phys. Rev. A, 84:021806, 2011. <lb/>[18] F. Cooper, A. Khare, B. Mihaila, and A. Saxena. Solitary waves in the nonlinear Dirac equation <lb/>with arbitrary nonlinearity. Phys. Rev. E, 82:036604, 2010. <lb/>[19] O. Bahat-Treidel, O. Peleg, M. Segev, and H. Buljan. Breakdown of Dirac dynamics in honeycomb <lb/>lattices due to nonlinear interactions. Phys. Rev. A, 82:013830, 2010. <lb/>[20] P. J. Dellar, D. Lapitski, S. Palpacelli, and S. Succi. Isotropy of three-dimensional quantum lattice <lb/>Boltzmann schemes. Phys. Rev. E, 83:046706, 2011. <lb/>[21] M. J. Ablowitz and Y. Zhu. Evolution of Bloch-mode envelopes in two-dimensional generalized <lb/>honeycomb lattices. Phys. Rev. A, 82:013840, 2010. <lb/>[22] M. J. Ablowitz, C. W. Curtis, and Y. Zhu. On tight-binding approximations in optical lattices. <lb/> Studies in Applied Mathematics, 129:362–388, 2012. <lb/>[23] M. J. Ablowitz, C. W. Curtis, and Y. Zhu. Localized nonlinear edge states in honeycomb lattices. <lb/> Phys. Rev. A, 88:013850, 2013. <lb/>[24] M. Merkl, A. Jacob, F. E. Zimmer, P. Ahberg, and L. Santos. Chiral confinement in <lb/>quasirelativistic Bose-Einstein condensates. Phys. Rev. Lett., 104:073603, 2010. <lb/>[25] C. Becker, P. Soltan-Panahi, J. Kronjager, S. Dorscher, K. Bongs, and K. Sengstock. Ultracold <lb/>quantum gases in triangular optical lattices. New J. Phys., 12:065025, 2010. <lb/>[26] Z. Chen and B. Wu. Bose-Einstein condensate in a honeycomb optical lattice: Fingerprint of <lb/>superfluidity at the Dirac point. Phys. Rev. Lett., 107:065301, 2011. <lb/>[27] E. Kapit and E. Mueller. Optical-lattice Hamiltonians for relativistic quantum electrodynamics. <lb/> Phys. Rev. A, 83:033625, 2011. <lb/>[28] W. Zhang, P. Zhang, S. Duan, and X. G. Zhao. Quasi-energy spectra of a charged particle in <lb/>planar honeycomb lattices. New J. Phys., 11:063032, 2009. <lb/>[29] R. R. Parwani and W. K. Ng. Nonlinear Schrödinger-Pauli equations. In Proceedings of <lb/>the Conference in Honour of Murray Gell-Mann&apos;s 80th Birthday, pages 654–660, Singapore, <lb/>February 2010. World Scientific Publishing Co. Pte. Ltd. <lb/>[30] P. D. Gupta, S. Raj, and D. Chaudhuri. Some exact stationary state solutions of a nonlinear <lb/>Dirac equation in 2+1 dimensions. arXiv:1012.0976, 2010. <lb/>[31] W. K. Ng and R. R. Parwani. Information and particle physics. Mod. Phys. Lett. A, 26:681–689, <lb/>March 2011. <lb/>[32] L. Fu and C. L. Kane. Topological insulators with inversion symmetry. Phys. Rev. B, 76:045302, <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 26 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> 2007. <lb/> [33] M. Z. Hasan and C. L. Kane. Colloquium: Topological insulators. Rev. Mod. Phys., 82(4):3045, <lb/>2010. <lb/>[34] H. Buljan, G. Bartal, O. Cohen, T. Schwartz, O. Manela, T. Carmon, M. Segev, J. W. Fleischer, <lb/>and D. N. Christodoulides. Partially coherent waves in nonlinear periodic lattices. Stud. Appl. <lb/>Math., 115:173–208, 2005. <lb/>[35] N. K. Efremidis, J. Hudock, D. N. Christodoulides, J. W. Fleischer, O. Cohen, and M. Segev. <lb/>Two-dimensional optical lattice solitons. Phys. Rev. Lett., 91:213906, 2003. <lb/>[36] O. Peleg, G. Bartal, B. Freedman, O. Manela, M. Segev, and D. N. Christodoulides. Conical <lb/>diffraction and gap solitons in honeycomb photonic lattices. Phys. Rev. Lett., 98:103901, 2007. <lb/>[37] O. Bahat-Treidel, O. Peleg, and M. Segev. Symmetry breaking in honeycomb photonic lattices. <lb/> Opt. Lett., 33:2251, Oct 2008. <lb/>[38] O. Manela, M. Segev, D. N. Christodoulides, and D. Kip. Hofstadter butterflies in nonlinear <lb/>Harper lattices, and their optical realizations. New J. Phys., 12:053017, 2010. <lb/>[39] D. N. Christodoulides and R. I. Joseph. Vector solitons in birefringent nonlinear dispersive media. <lb/> Opt. Lett., 13:53, 1988. <lb/>[40] Z. H. Musslimani, M. Segev, and D. N. Christodoulides. Multicomponent two-dimensional solitons <lb/>carrying topological charges. Opt. Lett., 25:61, 2000. <lb/>[41] S. Bitner, B. Dietz, M. Miski-Oglu, P. Oria Iriarte, A. Richter, and F. Schaefer. Observation of a <lb/>dirac point in microwave experiments with a photonic crystal modeling graphene. Phys. Rev. <lb/>B, 82:014301, 2010. <lb/>[42] B. J. Schroer. The spectrum of Bogomol&apos;nyi solitons in gauged linear sigma models. Nucl. Phys. <lb/>B, 475:440, 1996. <lb/>[43] L. D. Carr and Charles W. Clark. Vortices in attractive Bose-Einstein condensates in two <lb/>dimensions. Phys. Rev. Lett., 97:010403, 2006. <lb/>[44] R.M. Caplan, R. C. Gonzlez, P.G. Kevrekidis, and B.A. Malomed. Existence, stability, and <lb/>scattering of bright vortices in the cubic and quintic nonlinear Schrödinger equation. Math. <lb/>Compu. Simulat., 82:1150 – 1171, 2012. <lb/>[45] T. D. Stanescu, B. Anderson, and V. Galitski. Spin-orbit coupled Bose-Einstein condensates. <lb/> Phys. Rev. A, 78:023616, 2008. <lb/>[46] J. Polchinski. Cosmic superstrings revisited. Int. J. Mod. Phys. A, 20:3413, 2005. <lb/>[47] K. Lee. The dual formulation of cosmic strings and vortices. Phys. Rev. D, 48:2493–2498, 1993. <lb/>[48] L. G. Aldrovandi and F. A. Schaposnik. Non-Abelian vortices in Chern-Simons theories and their <lb/>induced effective theory. Phys. Rev. D, 76:045010, 2007. <lb/>[49] D. Rickles. Mirror symmetry and other miracles in superstring theory. Found. Phys., 43:54–80, <lb/>2010. <lb/>[50] J. Maldacena C. Bachas, E. Gava, editor. Trieste lectures on mirror symmetry, Strada Costiera, <lb/>11, I -34151, Trieste Italy, 2002. ICTP spring school on superstrings and related matters, ICTP. <lb/>[51] Miao L. &apos;t Hooft vortices on d-branes. J. High Energ. Phys., 9807:3, 1998. <lb/>[52] H. B. Nielsen and P. Olesen. Vortex-line models for dual strings. Nucl. Phys. B, 61:45–61, 1973. <lb/>[53] R. Auzzi, S. Bolognesi, J. Evslin, K. Konishi, and A. Yung. Nonabelian superconductors: Vortices <lb/>and confinement in N=2 SQCD. Nucl. Phys. B, 673:187, 2003. <lb/>[54] N. Seiberg and E. Witten. Electric-magnetic duality, monopole condensation, and confinement in <lb/>N=2 supersymmetric Yang-Mills theory. Nucl. Phys. B, 426:19–52, 1994. <lb/>[55] J. D. Bjorken and S. D. Drell. Relativistic Quantum Mechanics. McGraw-Hill, New York, NY., <lb/>1964. <lb/>[56] K. Kasamatsu, M. Tsubota, and M. Ueda. Spin textures in rotating two-component Bose-Einstein <lb/>condensates. Phys. Rev. A, 71:043611, 2005. <lb/>[57] U. Leonhardt and G. Volovik. How to create an alice string (half-quantum vortex) in a vector <lb/>Bose-Einstein condensate. JETP Letters, 72:46–48, 2000. <lb/>[58] P. W. Anderson and G. Toulouse. Phase slippage without vortex cores: Vortex textures in <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> Vortex solutions and spectra in a weak harmonic trap <lb/></note>

			<page> 27 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> superfluid <lb/> 3  He. Phys. Rev. Lett., 38:508–511, Feb. 1977. <lb/>[59] N. D. Mermin and Tin-Lun Ho. Circulation and angular momentum in the a phase of superfluid <lb/>Helium-3. Phys. Rev. Lett., 36:594–597, 1976. <lb/>[60] M. M. Salomaa and G. E. Volovik. Half-quantum vortices in superfluid <lb/> 3  He-A. Phys. Rev. Lett., <lb/> 55:1184–1187, 1985. <lb/>[61] K. G. Lagoudakis, T. Ostatnick´ , A. V. Kavokin, Y. G. Rubo, R. André, and B. Deveaud-Plédran. <lb/>Observation of half-quantum vortices in an exciton-polariton condensate. Science, 326:974, 2009. <lb/>[62] L. H. Haddad, C. M. Weaver, and L. D. Carr. The nonlinear Dirac equation in Bose-Einstein <lb/>condensates: I. Relativistic solitons in armchair nanoribbon optical lattices. arXiv:1305.6532v3, <lb/> 2013. <lb/>[63] R. Jackiw and Erick J. Weinberg. Self-dual Chern-Simons vortices. Phys. Rev. Lett., 64:2234, <lb/>1990. <lb/>[64] G. V. Dunne, R. Jackiw, S.-Y. Pi, and C. A. Trugenberger. Self-dual Chern-Simons solitons and <lb/>two-dimensional nonlinear equations. Phys. Rev. D, 43:1332, 1991. <lb/>[65] P. A Horvathy and P. Zhang. Vortices in (abelian) Chern-Simons gauge theory. Physics Reports, <lb/> 481:88, 2008. <lb/>[66] S. L. Adler. Axial-vector vertex in spinor electrodynamics. Phys. Rev., 177:2426–2438, 1969. <lb/>[67] J.S. Bell and R. Jackiw. A PCAC puzzle: π <lb/> 0  → γγ in the σ-model. Il Nuovo Cimento A, 60:47–61, <lb/>1969. <lb/>[68] Mikio Nakahara. Geometry, Topology and Physics, Second Edition (Graduate Student Series in <lb/>Physics). Taylor &amp; Francis, Taylor &amp; Francis Group, 6000 Broken Sound Parkway NW, Suite <lb/>300, Boca Raton, FL 33487-2742, 2003. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
