<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> International Journal of Mass Spectrometry 349– 350 (2013) 172– 180 <lb/> Contents lists available at ScienceDirect <lb/> International Journal of Mass Spectrometry <lb/> j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : w w w . e l s e v i e r . c o m / l o c a t e / i j m s <lb/> Masses of unbound nuclear systems <lb/> H. Simon <lb/>  * <lb/> GSI Helmholtzzentrum für Schwerionenforschung GmbH, Planckstr. 1, 64291 Darmstadt, Germany <lb/> a r t i c l e i n f o <lb/> Article history: <lb/> Received 12 March 2013 <lb/>Received in revised form 12 May 2013 <lb/>Accepted 13 May 2013 <lb/> Available online 23 May 2013 <lb/> Keywords: <lb/> Unbound nuclear systems <lb/>Halo nuclei <lb/>nuclear reactions <lb/> a b s t r a c t <lb/> The availability of intense secondary beams in conjunction with modern efficient detection setups allows <lb/>for the production and detailed study of the most extreme nuclear systems, in terms of asymmetry of <lb/>proton and neutron number, in the continuum. The extraction of even fundamental quantities like masses <lb/>together with other spectroscopic information is challenging, as their determination requires disentan-<lb/>gling the production process from structures appearing in the extracted spectra due to the final state <lb/>interaction of the unbound system in the continuum that is to be described. Beta-unstable nuclei that <lb/>are produced close to the drip-lines, can be used as starting point for reaching out even more into the <lb/>unknown by producing unbound exotic nuclear systems e.g., in transfer and knockout reactions. Already <lb/>these represent open quantum systems where properties are hard to predict by nuclear structure the-<lb/>ory as they are strongly affected by their nearby lying continuum states. Experiments allow to measure <lb/>the momenta of the reaction products and the energy of the gamma radiation emerging from the reac-<lb/>tion zone. Information on momenta and correlations are gathered, which appear e.g., in the measured <lb/>momentum vectors, relative energy spectra, the spin alignment during the reaction process, and can be <lb/>further distinguished by observing dependent quantities like the profile function, denoting a momentum <lb/>width as function of relative energy. <lb/>In order to relate them to intrinsic properties of the unbound systems, properties of the seed nuclei <lb/>are to be studied and related to the observations in the continuum. In this paper examples for the above-<lb/>mentioned methods are presented. The quest for masses of their ground states is exemplified for light <lb/>systems like <lb/> 5,7 H, <lb/> 7−10 He, <lb/> 10−13 Li, and the most neutron-rich Oxygen systems. <lb/> © 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> One of the new opportunities arising with the availability of <lb/>intense secondary beams is the capability to produce nuclear sys-<lb/>tems at and even across the dripline at the outskirts of the nuclear <lb/>landscape shown in Fig. 1 for light nuclei. The so-called dripline is <lb/>a direct reflection of the binding energy and the mass of nuclear <lb/>systems. It is reached when the separation energy for additional <lb/>valence nucleons reduces to zero at extreme values for neutron-<lb/>to-proton asymmetry. <lb/>From theoretical point of view this avenue is interesting as <lb/>nuclear interactions are studied by extending the knowledge gath-<lb/>ered at the valley of beta-stability into namely the regions where <lb/>also mass predictions tend to fail. Deviations, compared to the <lb/>region of stable nuclei, have been studied in a variety of different <lb/>experiments, and can be seen by modifications of level energies <lb/>and masses for the ground states. This re-ordering of nuclear shell <lb/>structure has been predicted already early on and later explained <lb/></body>

			<front>  *  Tel.: +49 6159 71 2887. <lb/> E-mail address: h.simon@gsi.de <lb/></front>

			<body> [2,3] in dependence of proton-to-neutron ratio in these systems. It <lb/>is technically feasible to look at light nuclear systems, being bound <lb/>or unbound, in a microscopic picture. This can be shown e.g., by <lb/>recent calculations explaining the reason for the doubly magic 28 O <lb/>being unbound [4]. Here a state-of-the-art approach starting from <lb/>bare nucleon–nucleon forces has been used in order to describe this <lb/>nucleus. An example for a method to handle the appearing short-<lb/>and long-range correlations in the many-body system is described <lb/>in [5] where the Unitary Correlation Operator Method is applied <lb/>to predict the structure of helium and beryllium nuclei within the <lb/>Fermionic Molecular Dynamics model. <lb/>Nuclear reactions are routinely used to study properties of espe-<lb/>cially unbound nuclear systems. They allow to produce a variety of <lb/>final states, being bound or unbound, while taking advantage of the <lb/>already exotic systems in the entrance channel of the reaction. As <lb/>an example, the neutron-rich 8 He nucleus, which is beta unstable <lb/>with a half-life of 119.0(15) ms and bound can be used to produce <lb/>the very exotic 7 H as well as its binary 7 He system in the contin-<lb/>uum by removing one proton or neutron, respectively, in a nuclear <lb/>reaction. <lb/>The 7 H system can further be studied by observing the cor-<lb/>relations in its dominant decay channel into a triton and four <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 1387-3806/$ – see front matter © 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved. <lb/> http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ijms.2013.05.013 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> H. Simon / International Journal of Mass Spectrometry 349– 350 (2013) 172– 180 <lb/></note>

			<page> 173 <lb/></page>

			<body> Fig. 1. Excerpt of the chart of nuclei in the light isotope region (adapted from [1]). Unbound systems in reach via one-proton removal reactions are denoted at the neutron-rich <lb/>side. <lb/> neutrons. Reactions of this type have been proposed [6] already <lb/>in the late 1980s in order to study exotic structures across the <lb/>driplines. <lb/>If one aims at determining the mass of an unbound nuclear sys-<lb/>tem different nuclear reactions with their specific sensitivity to the <lb/>population of particular final states have to be used in order to <lb/>remove ambiguities introduced by the reaction mechanism in their <lb/>production. This is achieved by using different target–beam com-<lb/>binations at different energies while producing the same reaction <lb/>product. <lb/>Possible reaction types are exemplified for the population of the <lb/>unbound 7 He system and depicted in Fig. 2, taken from [7]. The <lb/>paper illustrates nicely that in order to understand the spin–orbit <lb/>interaction appearing in 7 He it is necessary to analyse the data <lb/>obtained in various reactions. This includes stable beam studies <lb/>using (multinucleon) transfer reactions and fragmentation reac-<lb/>tions, as well as experiments where unstable beams are used and <lb/>impinge on a reaction target, allowing for reactions in inverse kine-<lb/>matics. For transfer reactions, being used at lower beam energies <lb/>near the Coulomb barrier, the experimental techniques are outlined <lb/>in [8]. Transfer reactions and direct reactions at higher energies <lb/>yield similar information on nuclear structure [9] once particular <lb/>effects related to the reaction mechanisms are taken correctly [10] <lb/>into account. Simple reaction types like (p,d) and (d,p) in transfer, <lb/>and proton or neutron removal at large beam velocities, are con-<lb/>sidered favourable, as they facilitate linking the properties of the <lb/>better known bound nuclei to their unbound neighbours. Proton <lb/>removal at the neutron-dripline leads hereby to the most neutron-<lb/>rich final states like 7 H in proton removal of 8 He. However, these <lb/>protons are tightly bound so one may expect a complex reaction <lb/>mechanism for this reaction type. Breakup reactions with beams <lb/>of 460 MeV/u and 280 MeV/u from the GSI accelerator complex, <lb/>and 11 Be and 11 Li as secondary beams [11], have been used in a <lb/>reaction study. 10 Li in the final state is selected by requiring 9 Li in <lb/>coincidence with one neutron in the exit channel of the reaction. <lb/>Here the nuclear reaction mechanisms: diffraction dissociation, <lb/>halo-neutron removal and core removal can be distiguished by <lb/>the particular width of the observed associated transverse neutron <lb/>momentum distribution. In addition further studies [12] showed <lb/>for the 11 Be, 11 Li →  9 Li + n + X neutron and proton removal reac-<lb/>tions, that the intermediately formed 10 Li system entirely governs <lb/>the measured kinematical observables for the fragments through <lb/>the 9 Li − n final state interaction. The possible influence of the ini-<lb/>titial state and the reaction mechanism on the final state has been <lb/>addressed by using the observed momentum distributions [13] and <lb/>energy spectra [14] in a quantitative analysis while modelling these <lb/>processes. In turn, this means that the properties of 10 Li are studied <lb/>in these breakup reactions. <lb/>Despite all this progress the mass of the ground-state of 10 Li <lb/>is still not easily accessible. The interaction of 9 Li with the neu-<lb/>tron can be seen and characterized with the observed scattering <lb/>length [15]. The related peak in the observed spectrum appears at <lb/>the lowest energy close to threshold. At slightly higher energies, <lb/>as displayed in Fig. 3, a resonant p-state is found, where one may <lb/>attribute a certain life time through its resonance parameters. For <lb/>bound states the binding energy is determined as the difference <lb/>of the masses of the constituents being far enough apart in order <lb/>not to interact in comparison with the bound system. One finds, <lb/>however, correlated binary pairs [16] at both peaks in the spec-<lb/>trum if one applies event mixing techniques, as being used e.g., in <lb/>particle physics, in order to study these correlations and claim reso-<lb/>nant states. Thus, for particular cases, the extraction of mass values <lb/>directly from experimental data appears to be hampered by the <lb/>need to be able to correctly identify the underlying nuclear struc-<lb/>ture, based on theory interpretation, in order to be able to make <lb/>firm assignments. From experimental point of view, we comply to <lb/>the definitions made above. <lb/>An example, where mass determination in the binary unbound <lb/>subsystem works unambiguously, is the 7 He subsystem of 8 He. <lb/>Here the breakup reaction has been performed at high energies <lb/>on a carbon target at GSI. In an experiment using the same setup in <lb/>conjunction with a liquid hydrogen target the ground state energy <lb/>could be confirmed [17], and the spectroscopic factor for the pop-<lb/>ulation of the p  3/2 -state was found to be 0.61(3). Comparison to an <lb/>experiment using a 7 Li(d, 2 He) 7 He reaction at KVI [18], yielded a <lb/>spectroscopic factor of 0.64(9) [19] and found to be consistent with <lb/>Green&apos;s function Monte Carlo and fermionic molecular dynamics <lb/>calculations at the time. A very recent experiment, performed at <lb/>RIKEN, used a 82.3 MeV/u 8 He beam impinging on a CH 2 and a <lb/>carbon target with proton recoil detection [20], allowed to apply <lb/>cluster-and neutron-knockout tagging. Here kinematical correla-<lb/>tions [21] are used in order to distinguish ˛ from neutron removal <lb/>reactions, by analysing the recoil proton momenta in inverse kine-<lb/>matics. In this direct measurement a slightly lower spectroscopic <lb/>factor of 0.512(18) was determined for the 6 He ⊗ (0p 3/2 ) config-<lb/>uration. All experiments yield the same ground-state level energy <lb/>within the errors and show no dependence on the reaction mech-<lb/>anism having been chosen by using different beam energies and <lb/>reaction targets. <lb/>In order to be able to confirm also the angular momentum <lb/>assignment for different continuum states, a method has been <lb/>developed [22] that bases on the sudden approximation where the <lb/>reaction at relativistic energies does not change the initial momen-<lb/>tum contents of the breaking up system, and on the fact that the <lb/>width of the momentum distribution of the neutrons can be asso-<lb/>ciated with their angular momentum state. The momentum profile <lb/></body>

			<page> 174 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> H. Simon / International Journal of Mass Spectrometry 349– 350 (2013) 172– 180 <lb/></note>

			<body> Fig. 2. Selected reactions [7] leading to the population of the <lb/> 7 He unbound system at a variety of different beam–target combinations and performed from lowest to highest <lb/>beam energies. Stable beams or targets being used for the reactions are colored in grey. Secondary beams in the reaction are displayed in white color. <lb/>(Figure taken from [7]). <lb/> function shown in Fig. 4 shows the width of the momentum dis-<lb/>tribution in dependence on relative energy in the 7 He =  6 He + n <lb/> system. It first of all confirms the assignment, that the major part of <lb/>the 7 He spectrum seems to arise from =1 neutrons in 8 He. Inter-<lb/>estingly enough at low relative energies a deviation pointing to <lb/>the appearance of =0-strength is found with a weight of 4.3(5) <lb/>% in the 8 He ground-state wave-function, which is also expected <lb/>theoretically [23] with a weight of 7.8% for the (1s 1/2 ) 2 (0p 3/2 ) 2 con-<lb/>figuration. This has been seen before – while analysing the relative <lb/>energy spectrum of 5 He [24] – in 6 He. <lb/>If unbound systems are populated via an intermediate unbound <lb/>three-body – in general a many-body state – as it is the case <lb/>for 12 Li being produced [24,25] from, e.g., 14 B or 14 Be, the reac-<lb/>tion path through the intermediate – here 13 Li – system, has <lb/>to be treated with special care. The reaction path may directly <lb/>affect the population of the unbound systems, e.g., also whether <lb/>they are predominantly produced in excited states. Correlations <lb/>have to be used to unambiguously assign the respective decay <lb/>path. <lb/>As an example, the decay of the neutron-poor 6 Be = ˛ + p + p <lb/> has been studied and it could be shown [26] that the decay mainly <lb/>exhibits the features of a unbiased [27] so-called democratic, three-<lb/>body decay where a sequential decay through 5 Li is suppressed. <lb/>This has recently been confirmed in an experiment with much <lb/>better statistics and complete kinematics [28] at the NSCL, East <lb/>Lansing, where also the two-neutron decay of the neutron-rich 16 Be <lb/>has been investigated [29] with similar results. <lb/> 1.1. Three body systems <lb/> At the outskirts of the nuclear landscape nuclei with valence <lb/>neutron-pairs are more tightly bound, leading often to an indented <lb/>coastline for odd neutron numbers. The pioneering experiments by <lb/>I. Tanihata and co-workers [30] and their subsequent explanation <lb/>by Hansen and Jonson [31] showed early on that a halo nucleus like <lb/> 11 Li can be explained by a two-neutron halo being formed in the <lb/>classically forbidden region of the 9 Li core potential, induced by the <lb/>extremely low two-neutron separation-energy of only 300 keV. In <lb/>forthcoming studies it became clear that the initial idea to place <lb/>a di-neutron around the 9 Li core needs to replaced by a genuine <lb/>three-body cluster-picture. <lb/>When describing three-body systems or decays, it is most <lb/>convenient to use an adequate coordinate system where the centre-<lb/>of-mass motion is removed. In the following Jacobi coordinates in <lb/>momentum space are introduced and used to describe the reac-<lb/>tion dynamics. As illustrated in Fig. 5, the Jacobi coordinates for the <lb/> f+n+n system may be obtained for two different combinations of <lb/>pairs, which are referred to as Y- or T-systems. In the Y- and in the <lb/> T-system the relative momenta between the centre-of-mass of a <lb/> Fig. 3. Left panel: Momentum profile of the <lb/> 9 Li + n system. The model calculations are shown as a dotted line (s-wave), a dashed line (p-wave) and a dashed-dotted line <lb/>(d-wave). Right panel: relative-energy spectrum, with a virtual state close to threshold and a p-wave resonance above. The positions of both states are indicated with arrows <lb/>in the left panel. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> H. Simon / International Journal of Mass Spectrometry 349– 350 (2013) 172– 180 <lb/></note>

			<page> 175 <lb/></page>

			<body> Fig. 4. Upper panel: Momentum profile of the <lb/> 6 He + n system [22]. The model <lb/>calculations are shown as a dotted line (s-wave), a dashed line (p-wave) and a <lb/>dashed-dotted line (d-wave). Lower panel: relative-energy spectrum, the insert <lb/>shows an expanded view of the momentum profile at lower energies. <lb/> pair, and the third particle, and between the two particles forming <lb/>the pair may be formed as shown in Eqs. 1 and 2, respectively: <lb/> p  fn  =  31 <lb/>  p  3 <lb/> m  3 <lb/> − <lb/> p  1 <lb/> m  1 <lb/> , p  n−fn  =  2−31 <lb/>  p  2 <lb/> m  2 <lb/> − <lb/> p  3  + p  1 <lb/> m  3  + m  1 <lb/> , <lb/> 31  = <lb/> m  3  m  1 <lb/> m  3  + m  1 <lb/> , <lb/> 2−31  = <lb/> m  2 (m 3  + m  1 ) <lb/> m  1  + m  2  + m  3 <lb/> . <lb/> (1) <lb/> p  nn  =  12 <lb/>  p  1 <lb/> m  1 <lb/> − <lb/> p  2 <lb/> m  2 <lb/> , p  f −nn =  3−12 <lb/>  p  3 <lb/> m  3 <lb/> − <lb/> p  1  + p  2 <lb/> m  1  + m  2 <lb/> , <lb/> 12  = <lb/> m  1  m  2 <lb/> m  1  + m  2 <lb/> , <lb/> 3−12  = <lb/> m  3 (m 1  + m  2 ) <lb/> m  1  + m  2  + m  3 <lb/> . <lb/> (2) <lb/> Fig. 5. Two possible choices (Y and T) for Jacobi coordinates in momentum space for <lb/>a three body system comprising of a charged fragment f and two identical neutrons <lb/> n. The angle Â between the two relative-momentum vectors, and the ratio of the <lb/>relative two-body energy to the total energy in the three-body system (ε  fn  or εnn), <lb/> are used to describe the system. The angular momenta associated with the respective <lb/>momentum vectors are denoted lx(l <lb/> x  ) and ly(l <lb/> y  ). <lb/> dσ/dE <lb/> tnn (a.u.) <lb/> 120 <lb/>80 <lb/>40 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/> E tnn (MeV) <lb/> 1/2 + <lb/>3/2 + <lb/>5/2 + <lb/> 5 H H <lb/> Fig. 6. Relative energy spectrum of the unbound <lb/> 5 H-system reconstructed from its <lb/>triton + neutron + neutron fragments of an <lb/> 6 He beam stemming from the GSI acceler-<lb/>ator facility. The fit curves and decomposition of the otherwise featureless spectrum <lb/>into different components are explained in the text. <lb/> The relative angle between the two vectors in a particular sys-<lb/>tem is denoted with Â. From the relative momenta the relative <lb/>energies can be computed: <lb/> E fn  = <lb/> p  2 <lb/> fn <lb/> 2 31 <lb/> , E n−fn  = <lb/> p  2 <lb/> n−fn <lb/> 2 2−31 <lb/> , E = E fn  + E n−fn . <lb/> (3) <lb/> E nn  = <lb/> p  2 <lb/> nn <lb/> 2 12 <lb/> , E f −nn = <lb/> p  2 <lb/> f −nn <lb/> 2 3−12 <lb/> , E = E nn  + E f −nn  . <lb/> (4) <lb/>As shown here, two relative energies in either the Y- or T− sys-<lb/>tem add up to the total relative energy E in the three body system. <lb/>The decay of three-body system is characterised by the angle Â <lb/> between two momentum vectors, as illustrated in Fig. 5, and the <lb/>ratio of the relative energy in one of the two-body subsystems to <lb/>total relative energy in the three-body system E. In the following, <lb/>the fractional energy in the subsystem (1–2) ε  nn  = E nn  /E, and that <lb/>in the subsystem (1–3) ε  fn  = E fn  /E, will be used to unambiguously <lb/>characterize three-body decay kinematics. <lb/>The use of these variables (ε and Â) can be motivated by the <lb/>fact that any physical observable in a three-body system should <lb/>be described via three-body wave functions. These wave functions <lb/>may be expanded into hyperspherical harmonics (HH) compo-<lb/>nents. Hyperspherical harmonics are the equivalent of spherical <lb/>harmonics functions for the three body case, and are often <lb/>parametrized using Jacobi coordinates. The first attempt to expand <lb/>a three-body wave function into HH coefficients dates back to the <lb/>year 1935, when this technique was introduced by Zernike and <lb/>Brinkman [32]. The HH method was re-introduced 25 years later by <lb/>Delves [33], with the idea to derive expansion coefficients directly <lb/>from the Jacobi T system by a comparison to the experimental data. <lb/>Thus, the expansion into hyperspherical harmonics, bears the <lb/>opportunity to compare to either theoretical predictions, or other <lb/>experimental findings, in a straight-forward manner. <lb/> 2. A very heavy hydrogen isotope: 5 H <lb/> The most neutron-rich hydrogen isotopes turn out to be nuclear <lb/>systems with the largest A/Z ratios that can be reached in experi-<lb/>ments. 5 H has been first identified [34] in a stripping reaction from <lb/> 6 He at 36 MeV/u in an experiment performed at the RIKEN accel-<lb/>erator. A comparatively narrow resonance at 1.7(0.3) MeV with a <lb/>width of 1.9(0.4) MeV has been reported. Using the same projec-<lb/>tile, an experiments using relativistic beams at the GSI accelerator <lb/>complex [35,36], yielded a broad structure at 3 MeV with a width <lb/>of 6 MeV (FWHM) as shown in Fig. 6. This spectrum looks rather <lb/>featureless at the first glance. However, theory predicts a I   = 1/2 + <lb/> ground state for 5 H to be located at 2.5–3 MeV and to have a width <lb/></body>

			<page> 176 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> H. Simon / International Journal of Mass Spectrometry 349– 350 (2013) 172– 180 <lb/></note>

			<body> of  = 3 −4 MeV [37] based on a microscopic calculation, which <lb/>matches well with the observation. This would allow to draw a <lb/>conclusion on the mass of the system, based on direct compari-<lb/>son to theory! The discrepancy of the two data sets lead to further <lb/>enhanced measurements at JINR [38] and a consistent interpreta-<lb/>tion [39] of all data sets was attempted, where the very different <lb/>reaction mechanisms for these measurements at different energies <lb/>was taken into account. However the author claims the situation <lb/>still to be unsatisfactory and recommends: &quot; to improve things we <lb/>need highly detailed information: precise invariant-mass data in a <lb/>broad energy range. From the theoretical point of view it is very <lb/>important that correlation spectra of the particles from 5 H decay <lb/>become available; we have shown [. . .] that they make interpre-<lb/>tation of the data much more unambiguous &quot; . Following this, the <lb/>observed energy correlations, also known as Delves-plot, measured <lb/>in [35,36] were directly compared to more recent theoretical cal-<lb/>culations [40] and could be shown to be in good agreement while <lb/>confirming the dominant I   = 1/2 + assignment for the contents of <lb/>the measured spectrum, thus, reflecting the ground state proper-<lb/>ties of 5 H. In addition to that, 5 H and 5 H * have been seen in pion <lb/>absorption reactions [41] at LAMPF. Unfortunately, fragment cor-<lb/>relations have not been studied here to an extend allowing for the <lb/>above-mentioned decomposition. <lb/> 3. Ground state properties of the three body systems 10 He <lb/>and 13 He <lb/> Apart from 6 He, 11 Li can be seen as one of the most clean cases <lb/>for a two-neutron halo-nucleus. The cluster picture for 11 Li where <lb/>a nearly unpolarized charged 9 Li core inside a cloud of low density <lb/>neutron matter, formed by the two halo neutrons tunneling outside <lb/>the core&apos;s potential into the classically forbidden region, could be <lb/>confirmed by recent laser spectroscopy experiments where charge <lb/>radius [43,44], and quadrupole moment [45] have been measured <lb/>and compared to other lithium isotopes. In order to shed light on <lb/>the intrinsic correlations of the two halo neutrons, especially to <lb/>answer the question on the influence of pairing correlations on <lb/>the total binding of 11 Li, three body correlations in momentum <lb/>space have been investigated in the formation of the intermediate <lb/>unbound 10 Li subsystem [15] in breakup reactions. These momen-<lb/>tum correlations can be reconstructed by a missing momentum <lb/>analysis after removal of one halo neutron in 11 Li. The recoiling <lb/> 10 Li carries the information on the momentum of the removed neu-<lb/>tron versus its own centre-of-mass, whereas the relative motion of <lb/>the 9 Li fragment versus the remaining neutron allows reconstruc-<lb/>ting the second Jacobi momentum vector in the Y-system, in the <lb/>spirit that has been outlined towards the end of section 1. These <lb/>momentum vectors are used for an expansion into hyperspherical <lb/>harmonics for the three-body system. Spectroscopy of the recoil-<lb/>ing 10 Li system [16,22,46] provides additional information on the <lb/>subsystems interaction. An attempt to achieve a phenomenologi-<lb/>cal two-neutron halo wave-function [47] for 11 Li has been carried <lb/>out, that is constraint by and fit to the above-mentioned data, <lb/>and in agreement with the recent high-precision direct mass mea-<lb/>surements [48,49] for 11 Li. Thus, the ground state of 11 Li can be <lb/>considered to be known by experiment. <lb/>If now the unbound 10 He system is produced by a one-proton <lb/>removal reaction one may ask the question to which extend the <lb/>continuum structures, i.e., also the mass via the lowest state in <lb/>the relative energy spectrum, are determined by the ground state <lb/>properties of the seed nucleus 11 Li. In addition, one may consider <lb/>its structure [50] as being similar to the one of 11 Li, as it should <lb/>mainly reflect the interactions of the valence neutrons. During <lb/>the knockout reaction, momentum is transferred predominantly <lb/>to the removed proton, whereas the remaining 10 He system acts <lb/>as spectator, and subsequently decays into 8 He and two neutrons. <lb/>What is needed, is a method to observe the correlations [51] in <lb/>three-body decays. Ideally, they should eventually lead to a rep-<lb/>resentation of the data which can be described by a fit function <lb/>based on an expansion into hyperspherical harmonics. Fitting the <lb/>expansion coefficients yields the weight and relative phases of the <lb/>continuum states and facilitates a direct comparison to theoretical <lb/>calculations (for the presented case [52]) by using a well-suited <lb/>parametrisation. If the fits are carried out in both, the T- and <lb/>the Y-Jacobi coordinate system independently, the fixed trans-<lb/>formation properties [53] between both systems can be used to <lb/>eliminate effects of the experimental apparatus on the extracted <lb/>parameters. <lb/>The system 10 He has been discovered and studied already in the <lb/>1990s [54–56]. It has been shown in theory [57] that the strength <lb/>of interaction observed in 9 He= 8 He+n strongly affects the ground-<lb/>state properties of 10 He. It turns out, that the interpretation of the <lb/>observed broad structures in the measured energy spectra requires <lb/>additional information, e.g., provided by the measurement of corre-<lb/>lations. The weak interaction seen in the 9 He spectrum [58] triggers <lb/>the question, whether the three body system deviates at all from <lb/>a phase space decay of the initial 11 Li seed nucleus with just a <lb/>removed proton. An one-proton removal experiment with overde-<lb/>termined kinematics has been carried out at relativistic energies at <lb/>GSI. Fig. 8 shows the observed cross section [58] in dependence on <lb/> Â and ε in both, the T- and Y- coordinate systems. If one compares <lb/>the measured data in the 8 He + n + n decay to the intrinsic corre-<lb/>lations in the 11 Li seed nucleus, which become accessible through <lb/>the phenomenological wave function presented earlier, apparent <lb/>deviations can be clearly attributed to the formed 10 He final state. <lb/>The observed spectrum for 10 He is shown in Fig. 7. The 8 He+n+n <lb/>relative energy spectrum can be interpreted by a ground state 0 + <lb/> resonance at 1.42(10) or 1.54(11) MeV with a width () of 1.11(76) <lb/>or 1.91(41) MeV, respectively, by assuming that it either is super-<lb/>imposed to a non-correlated background of the reaction, or that <lb/>the spectrum comprises a 2 + excited state at 3.99(26) MeV with <lb/> =1.64(89) MeV. In either case the ground state mass of 10 He is <lb/>measured with about 100 keV accuracy. <lb/>Recently, the 10 He system has also been studied [59,60] in a two-<lb/>neutron transfer reaction to 8 He at the JINR in Dubna. The relative <lb/>energy spectrum is shown in Fig. 9. The spectrum shows a double <lb/>humped structure, with a different phase space behaviour com-<lb/>pared to the data obtained at large beam velocities. The structure <lb/>a lowest energies in both cases is identified as a 0 + groundstate, <lb/>supported by angular correlations. The total spectrum, however, is <lb/>decomposed here into three components including the previously <lb/>observed 2 + resonance together with an indication for an addi-<lb/>tional soft (1  −  ) dipole mode. The resonance parameters are only <lb/>in fair agreement to [42,58], discrepancies may arise from the dif-<lb/>ferent reaction mechanism and the additionally introduced state. <lb/>At NSCL a different 2p2n removal reaction [61] from a 14 Be beam at <lb/>59 MeV/u has been analysed. The extracted ground state resonance <lb/>parameters confirm the findings in [42,58] allowing, thus, to con-<lb/>clude that the 8 He + n + n final state interaction indeed dominates <lb/>the decay channel. <lb/>Similarly one may try to reach states in 13 Li via a one proton <lb/>removal reaction from 14 Be. For relativistic beam energies this has <lb/>been first shown [24] in an measurement carried out at GSI with a <lb/>304 MeV/u 14 Be beam. The results are shown in Fig. 7. The fact, that <lb/>the loosely bound 11 Li fragment survives the reaction in substan-<lb/>tial quantities supports the previously drawn conclusions on the <lb/>reaction mechanism. The 11 Li – neutron final state interaction can <lb/>be studied in the same experiment, when looking at the reaction <lb/>channels where both a proton and a neutron have been separated <lb/>in phase space far enough during the reaction, so that they don&apos;t fall <lb/>into the acceptance window of the experimental setup. From the <lb/>relative energy spectrum a scattering length of a s  = −13.7(1.6) fm <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> H. Simon / International Journal of Mass Spectrometry 349– 350 (2013) 172– 180 <lb/></note>

			<page> 177 <lb/></page>

			<body> dσ/dE  (mb/MeV) <lb/> 0.8 <lb/> 0.6 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.2 <lb/> 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>6 <lb/>4 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>6 <lb/>4 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>6 <lb/>4 <lb/> E (MeV) <lb/> f2n <lb/> E (MeV) <lb/> f2n <lb/> E (MeV) <lb/> f2n <lb/> a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/> Fig. 7. Missing mass spectrum [58] of <lb/> 10 He (a, b) and <lb/> 13 Li (c). The data was measured at GSI [42,24], respectively. The fit to the data is performed (a, c) with one resonance <lb/>being superimposed to the correlated background (dashed curve) stemming from the internal structure of the projectile. For the fit shown in panel (b) two overlapping <lb/>resonances are assumed. <lb/> can be deduced for the lowest state at threshold. A similar result, <lb/>shown in Fig. 10, has been achieved in an experiment carried out <lb/>at the NSCL [62], but with a different seed nucleus 14 B. Both seed <lb/>nuclei exhibit a different ground state structure: <lb/> 14 B : The ground state [63] consists of a valence neutron in the <lb/>(0d 5/2 ) 1 and (1s 1/2 ) 1 orbitals with about 30 % and 66 % probability, <lb/>respectively. <lb/> 14 Be: The ground state exhibits a 4n + 10 Be structure and com-<lb/>prises (1s 1/2 ) 2 , (0p 1/2 ) 2 , (0d 5/2 ) 2 neutron pairs being coupled to <lb/> 12 Be(0 + ), and (1s 1/2 , 0d 5/2 ) neutrons being coupled to an excited <lb/> 12 Be(2 + ) core. <lb/>Following this, two additional =2 resonances have been <lb/>assumed at higher relative energies in the NSCL experiment. It <lb/>can be seen in Fig. 10, that the steep rise at threshold, being <lb/> W(ε) <lb/> W(θ) <lb/> ε <lb/> cos θ <lb/> a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/> 1.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.20 0.40 0.60 0.80 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>-1.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/> W(ε) <lb/> W(θ) <lb/> Fig. 8. Momentum Correlations [58] observed in the <lb/> 10 He = <lb/> 8 He + n + n three body decay at GSI. The observed cross sections are shown in dependence on the fractional <lb/>energy ε (Panels a and c) and the correlation angle Â (Panels b and d) for the low energy part of the total energy spectrum (0–3 MeV) as shown in Fig. 7. The projections <lb/>are done in both possible choices for the Jacobi coordinates: T-system in Panels a, b and Y-system in Panels c, d. Experimental data are shown as dots with error bars. The <lb/>dashed lines show the result of calculations under the assumption that correlations between the breakup fragments are the same as in the three-body <lb/> 11 Li ground-state wave <lb/>function. The solid lines correspond to a fit made by using an expansion of the decay amplitude in a restricted series of hyperspherical harmonics assuming I <lb/>  = 0 <lb/> + and K≤2. <lb/>The dotted lines show the result when interference between the K = 0 and K = 2 components are excluded and show the sensitivity of the method as the observed admixture <lb/>contributes with only 0.2% to the spectrum. <lb/></body>

			<page> 178 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> H. Simon / International Journal of Mass Spectrometry 349– 350 (2013) 172– 180 <lb/></note>

			<body> Fig. 9. Missing mass spectrum of <lb/> 10 He obtained in a <lb/> 3 H( <lb/> 8 He, p) <lb/> 10 He transfer reaction <lb/>at 21.5 MeV/u beam energy at the JINR, Dubna [60]. Panel (a): Crosses indicate data <lb/>points with their associated errors. The grey shaded histogram shows the remaining <lb/>data having applied a condition in order to assure that the kinematical correlations, <lb/>where the associated fit parameters are shown in panel (b), are unambiguously mea-<lb/>surable. The dotted histogram indicates the detection efficiency of the setup. The <lb/>solid curve shows a fit to the data using the expansion into different partial waves <lb/>as presented in panel (c). Panel (b): Squared amplitudes for a fit to the angular cor-<lb/>relations, using a correlation function w depending on the Legendre polynomials <lb/> P(cos(ϑ8  He )): w = (AP0 + B <lb/> √ <lb/> 3P1 + C <lb/> √ <lb/> 5P0) <lb/> 2  + D <lb/> 2 , where ϑ8  He stands for the mea-<lb/>sured emission angle of the <lb/> 8 He fragment in the reaction. Panel (c): shape of different <lb/>spectra of <lb/> 10 He in dependence on J <lb/>  . The error bands represent uncertainties of the <lb/>model calculations. <lb/>(Figure taken from [60].) <lb/> Fig. 10. Decay or relative energy spectrum for <lb/> 12 Li = <lb/> 11 Li + n [62] produced in a <lb/>two-proton removal reaction using a 55 MeV/u <lb/> 14 B beam at the NSCL, East Lansing. <lb/>The solid line is the result of a simulation calculation assuming an =0 ground state <lb/>(dotted) and two =2 excited states with decay energies of 250 keV (dot-dashed) and <lb/>555 keV (dashed), motivated by the particular ground-state configuration of the <lb/> 14 B <lb/>seed nucleus. A more recent interpretation of this spectrum [25] leads to a worse <lb/>description for the lowest three data points (for details see text). <lb/>(Figure taken from [62]). <lb/> characteristic for =0 scattering states, is well reproduced with the <lb/>given parametrisation. <lb/>A more recent data set from the NSCL performed with a 14 Be <lb/>beam [25] suggests a much weaker final state interaction with <lb/> a s  &gt; −4 fm describing also the 14 B data set, even if some discrep-<lb/>ancies close to threshold can be seen. The fact that excited states <lb/>with 14 Be as seed nucleus have not been seen in the high energy <lb/>experiment [24] is confirmed. The interpretation of the lower part <lb/>of the 12 Li spectrum, however, is still controversial, and leaves the <lb/>parameters for the appearing structure close to threshold still unre-<lb/>solved. <lb/>The spectrum of 13 Li, shown in Fig. 7, exhibits a structure <lb/>exceeding the background caused by the 14 Be ground state corre-<lb/>lations. The non-resonant background is calculated using a formula <lb/>given in [64] and explicitely drawn into Fig. 7 for reference. <lb/>The extracted resonance parameters are E  0 = 1.47(35) MeV and <lb/>  0 = 2.1(1.1) MeV for the ground state in 13 Li. The assumption of a <lb/>resonance behaviour is further supported by the appearance of pro-<lb/>nounced three-body correlations [58], similar to the already shown <lb/>case of 10 He. It would be highly desirable to be able to compare <lb/>these correlations directly to the initial correlations in 14 Be. How-<lb/>ever, its structure is not settled enough yet and requires further <lb/>investigations. The detailed discussion of the determination of the <lb/> 14 Be properties is beyond the scope of this paper and is discussed <lb/>e.g., in reference [22]. <lb/> 4. Outlook <lb/> The results for ground state properties of unbound nuclear sys-<lb/>tems, in particular their resonance parameters, presented in this <lb/>paper have been focussed on hydrogen up to the lithium iso-<lb/>topes. It becomes obvious from the presented data, that most of <lb/>the experimental limitations come from limited beam intensities <lb/>at the present facilities. Nevertheless, attempts have been made <lb/>to access even the neutron-rich unbound oxygen systems which <lb/>allow to access nuclear properties at the next accessible potential <lb/>shell closure. In theory, 24 O can be computed in the meanwhile <lb/>from first principles see e.g., [65] where a state-of-the-art chi-<lb/>ral nucleon–nucleon interaction at next-to-next-to-next-to leading <lb/>order has been used together with a coupled cluster method in <lb/>order to study the ground state. The evolution towards 28 O is qual-<lb/>itatively understood with the repelling three-body component of <lb/>the nucleon-nucleon interaction [4] for neutrons being added to <lb/>the 24 O core. <lb/>These theoretical predictions still await to be challenged by <lb/>spectroscopic studies of these unbound oxygen isotopes. The <lb/>unbound 25 O has first been seen in an experiment performed at <lb/>the NSCL [66] using a proton removal reaction from a 26 F beam <lb/>at 85 MeV/u together with the MONA neutron detector array. The <lb/>ground-state has been identified to be unbound by 770 <lb/> +20 <lb/>−10  keV and <lb/>no excited states were seen in a spectrum containing a few hundred <lb/>counts. Recently, the analysis [67] of proton removal reactions of a <lb/> 27 F beam at 82 MeV/u in the same setup yielded the 26 O =  24 O+n+n <lb/>relative energy spectrum, and the ground state could be identi-<lb/>fied from a few tens entries at 150 <lb/> +50 <lb/>−150  keV, close to threshold. <lb/>These finding could be confirmed in an experiment carried out <lb/>at GSI [68,69] where 25,26 O could be populated as a by-product <lb/>in an experimental campaign at a beam intensity of 10 10  /s  40 Ar <lb/>ions, leading to a secondary beam intensity of only about 0.1 27 F/s. <lb/>According to this measurement, yielding a couple of counts in the <lb/>spectrum, 26 O is unbound by less than 120 keV with a lifetime less <lb/>equal to 5.7 ns (both at 95% confidence level), and potentially shows <lb/>an excited state at about 4 MeV. The experimental findings in their <lb/>current state are in accordance with theoretical [70,71] calcula-<lb/>tions. In any case, substantial improvements in the interpretation <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> H. Simon / International Journal of Mass Spectrometry 349– 350 (2013) 172– 180 <lb/></note>

			<page> 179 <lb/></page>

			<body> of the data can be expected, once there will be more events available <lb/>for analysis, allowing for more detailed studies. <lb/>In summary, experimental methods, and the accompanying <lb/>nuclear structure and reaction theory, have been developed in order <lb/>to identify ground states of unbound systems, and determine their <lb/>masses with good precision. The studies are still hampered by the <lb/>limited statistics in the measured spectra, even for the lightest <lb/>nuclei. Therefore, great progress is expected with the upcoming <lb/>secondary beam facilities, where an increase in intensity by several <lb/>orders of magnitude either has been shown (RIBF) or is expected <lb/>(RIA/FRIB, Spiral2, FAIR) in conjunction with currently planned <lb/>novel neutron detection arrays: MONA-LISA, Nebula, NeuLAND <lb/>which will feature an improved multi-neutron detection efficiency. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgements <lb/> This work is in parts the result of a collaborative effort of the <lb/>R 3 B collaboration [72]. The author wants to thank all collaborators <lb/>here. This work has been supported by the Helmholtz International <lb/>Center for FAIR within the framework of the LOEWE program, by <lb/>the Helmholtz Alliance Program contract number HA216/EMMI, <lb/>by the GSI-TU Darmstadt Cooperation agreement, and by the <lb/>BMBF, the German Ministry for Science and Education (06DA70471, <lb/>06DA9040I, 06MT238). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] http://www.nndc.bnl.gov/chart/visited 2012. <lb/>[2] I. Talmi, I. Unna, Physical Review Letters 4 (1960) 469; P.G. Hansen, Nucl. Phys. <lb/>A 682 (2001) 310c. <lb/>[3] J. Dobaczewski, W. Nazarewicz, T.R. Werner, J.F. Berger, C.R. Chinn, J. Dechargé, <lb/>Physical Review C 53 (1996) 2809. <lb/>[4] T. Otsuka, T. Suzuki, J.D. Holt, A. Schwenk, Y. Akaishi, Physical Review Letters <lb/>105 (2010) 032501. <lb/>[5] T. Neff, H. Feldmeier, R. Roth, Nuclear Physics A 752 (2005) 321c. <lb/>[6] P.G. Hansen, Nature 328 (1987) 476. <lb/>[7] D.H. Denby, P.A. DeYoung, T. Baumann, D. Bazin, E. Breitbach, J. Brown, N. Frank, <lb/>A. Gade, C.C. Hall, J. Hinnefeld, C.R. Hoffman, R. Howes, R.A. Jenson, B. Luther, <lb/>S.M. Mosby, C.W. Olson, W.A. Peters, A. Schiller, A. Spyrou, M. Thoennessen, <lb/>Physical Review C 78 (2008) 044303. <lb/>[8] J.S. Winfield, W.N. Catford, N.A. Orr, Nuclear Instruments and Methods A396 <lb/>(1997) 147. <lb/>[9] P.G. Hansen, J.A. Tostevin, Annual Review of Nuclear and Particle Science 53 <lb/>(2003) 219. <lb/>[10] J. Al-Khalili, F. Nunes, Journal of Physics G: Nuclear and Particle Physics 29 <lb/>(2003) R89. <lb/>[11] M. Zinser, F. Humbert, T. Nilsson, W. Schwab, Th. Blaich, M.J.G. Borge, L.V. <lb/>Chulkov, H. Eickhoff, Th.W. Elze, H. Emling, B. Franzke, H. Freiesleben, H. Geis-<lb/>sel, K. Grimm, D. Guillemaud-Mueller, P.G. Hansen, R. Holzmann, H. Irnich, B. <lb/>Jonson, J.G. Keller, O. Klepper, H. Klingler, J.V. Kratz, R. Kulessa, D. Lambrecht, Y. <lb/>Leifels, A. Magel, M. Mohar, A.C. Mueller, G. Münzenberg, F. Nickel, G. Nyman, A. <lb/>Richter, K. Riisager, C. Scheidenberger, G. Schrieder, B.M. Sherrill, H. Simon, K. <lb/>Stelzer, J. Stroth, O. Tengblad, W. Trautmann, E. Wajda, E. Zude, Physical Review <lb/>Letters 75 (1995) 1719. <lb/>[12] B. Jonson, K. Riisager, Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London <lb/>A356 (1998) 2063. <lb/>[13] P.G. Hansen, Physical Review Letters 77 (1996) 1016. <lb/>[14] G.F. Bertsch, K. Hencken, H. Esbensen, Physical Review C 57 (1998) 1366. <lb/>[15] H. Simon, D. Aleksandrov, T. Aumann, L. Axelsson, T. Baumann, M.J.G. Borge, <lb/>L.V. Chulkov, R. Collatz, J. Cub, W. Dostal, B. Eberlein, Th.W. Elze, H. Emling, <lb/>H. Geissel, A. Grünschloss, M. Hellström, J. Holeczek, R. Holzmann, B. Jonson, <lb/>J.V. Kratz, G. Kraus, R. Kulessa, Y. Leifels, A. Leistenschneider, T. Leth, I. Mukha, <lb/>G. Münzenberg, F. Nickel, T. Nilsson, G. Nyman, B. Petersen, M. Pfützner, A. <lb/>Richter, K. Riisager, C. Scheidenberger, G. Schrieder, W. Schwab, M.H. Smedberg, <lb/>J. Stroth, A. Surowiec, O. Tengblad, M.V. Zhukov, Physical Review Letters 83 <lb/>(1999) 496. <lb/>[16] H. Simon, M. Meister, T. Aumann, M.J.G. Borge, L.V. Chulkov, U. Datta Pramanik, <lb/>Th.W. Elze, H. Emling, C. Forssén, H. Geissel, M. Hellström, B. Jonson, J.V. Kratz, <lb/>R. Kulessa, Y. Leifels, K. Markenroth, G. Münzenberg, F. Nickel, T. Nilsson, G. <lb/>Nyman, A. Richter, K. Riisager, C. Scheidenberger, G. Schrieder, O. Tengblad, <lb/>M.V. Zhukov, Nuclear Physics A 791 (2007) 267. <lb/>[17] Yu. Aksyutina, H.T. Johansson, T. Aumann, K. Boretzky, M.J.G. Borge, A. Chatil-<lb/>lon, L.V. Chulkov, D. Cortina-Gila, U. Datta Pramanik, H. Emling, C. Forssén, <lb/>H.O.U. Fynbo, H. Geissel, G. Ickert, B. Jonson, R. Kulessa, C. Langer, M. Lantz, <lb/>T. LeBleis, A.O. Lindahl, K. Mahata, M. Meister, G. Münzenberg, T. Nilsson, <lb/>G. Nyman, R. Palit, S. Paschalis, W. Prokopowicz, R. Reifarth, A. Richter, <lb/>K. Riisager, G. Schrieder, H. Simon, K. Sümmerer, O. Tengblad, H. Weick, M.V. <lb/>Zhukov, Physics Letters B 679 (2009) 191. <lb/>[18] N. Ryezayeva, C. Bäumer, A.M. van den Berg, L.V. Chulkov, D. Frekers, D. <lb/>De Frenne, E.-W. Grewe, P. Haefner, E. Jacobs, H. Johanson, Y. Kalmykov, A. <lb/>Negret, P. von Neumann-Cosel, L. Popescu, S. Rakers, A. Richter, G. Schrieder, <lb/>A. Shevchenko, H. Simon, H.J. Wörtche, Physics Letters B 639 (2006) 623. <lb/>[19] F. Beck, D. Frekers, P. von Neumann-Cosel, A. Richter, N. Ryezayeva, I.J. Thomp-<lb/>son, Physics Letters B 645 (2007) 128. <lb/>[20] Z.X. Cao, Y.L. Ye, J. Xiao, L.H. Lv, D.X. Jiang, T. Zheng, H. Hua, Z.H. Li, X.Q. Li, Y.C. <lb/>Ge, J.L. Lou, R. Qiao, Q.T. Li, H.B. You, R.J. Chen, D.Y. Pang, H. Sakurai, H. Otsu, M. <lb/>Nishimura, S. Sakaguchi, H. Baba, Y. Togano, K. Yoneda, C. Li, S. Wang, H. Wang, <lb/>K.A. Li, T. Nakamura, Y. Nakayama, Y. Kondo, S. Deguchi, Y. Satou, K. Tshoo, <lb/>Physics Letters B 707 (2012) 46. <lb/>[21] L.V. Chulkov, F. Aksouh, A. Bleile, O.V. Bochkarev, D. Cortina-Gil, A.V. Dobrovol-<lb/>sky, P. Egelhof, H. Geissel, M. Hellström, N.B. Isaev, O.A. Kiseleve, B.G. Komkov, <lb/>M. Matoš, F.N. Moroz, G. Münzenberg, M. Mutterer, V.A. Mylnikov, S.R. Neu-<lb/>maier, V.N. Pribora, D.M. Seliverstov, L.O. Sergeev, A. Shrivastava, K. Sümmerer, <lb/>S.Yu. Torilov, H. Weick, M. Winkler, V.I. Yatsoura, Nuclear Physics A 759 (2005) <lb/>43. <lb/>[22] Yu. Aksyutina, T. Aumann, K. Boretzky, M.J.G. Borge, C. Caesar, A. Chatillon, L.V. <lb/>Chulkov, D. Cortina-Gil, U. Datta Pramanik, H. Emling, H.O.U. Fynbo, H. Geissel, <lb/>G. Ickert, H.T. Johansson, B. Jonson, R. Kulessa, C. Langer, T. LeBleis, K. Mahata, <lb/>G. Münzenberg, T. Nilsson, G. Nyman, R. Palit, S. Paschalis, W. Prokopowicz, R. <lb/>Reifarth, D. Rossi, A. Richter, K. Riisager, G. Schrieder, H. Simon, K. Sümmerer, <lb/>O. Tengblad, H. Weick, M.V. Zhukov, Physics Letters B 718 (2013) 1309. <lb/>[23] K. Hagino, N. Takahashi, H. Sagawa, Physical Review C 77 (2008) 054317. <lb/>[24] Yu. Aksyutina, H.T. Johansson, P. Adrich, F. Aksouh, T. Aumann, K. Boretzky, <lb/>M.J.G. Borge, A. Chatillon, L.V. Chulkov, D. Cortina-Gil, U. Datta Pramanik, H. <lb/>Emling, C. Forssén, H.O.U. Fynbo, H. Geissel, M. Hellström, G. Ickert, K.L. Jones, <lb/>B. Jonson, A. Kliemkiewicz, J.V. Kratz, R. Kulessa, M. Lantz, T. LeBleis, A.O. Lin-<lb/>dahl, K. Mahata, M. Matos, M. Meister, G. Münzenberg, T. Nilsson, G. Nyman, <lb/>R. Palit, M. Pantea, S. Paschalis, W. Prokopowicz, R. Reifarth, A. Richter, K. Riis-<lb/>ager, G. Schrieder, H. Simon, K. Sümmerer, O. Tengblad, W. Walus, H. Weick, <lb/>M.V. Zhukov, Physics Letters B 666 (2008) 430. <lb/>[25] Z. Kohley, E. Lunderberg, P.A. DeYoung, A. Volya, T. Baumann, D. Bazin, G. Chris-<lb/>tian, N.L. Cooper, N. Frank, A. Gade, C. Hall, J. Hinnefeld, B. Luther, S. Mosby, W.A. <lb/>Peters, J.K. Smith, J. Snyder, A. Spyrou, M. Thoennessen, Physical Review C 87 <lb/>(2013) 011304(R). <lb/>[26] O.V. Bochkarev, L.V. Chulkov, A.A. Korsheninnikov, E.A. Kuzmin, I.G. Mukha, <lb/>G.B. Yankov, Nuclear Physics A 505 (1989) 215. <lb/>[27] M. Pfützner, L.V. Grigorenko, M. Karny, K. Riisager, Reviews of Modern Physics <lb/>84 (2012) 567. <lb/>[28] I.A. Egorova, R.J. Charity, L.V. Grigorenko, Z. Chajecki, D. Coupland, J.M. Elson, <lb/>T.K. Ghosh, M.E. Howard, H. Iwasaki, M. Kilburn, Jenny Lee, W.G. Lynch, J. Man-<lb/>fredi, S.T. Marley, A. Sanetullaev, R. Shane, D.V. Shetty, L.G. Sobotka, M.B. Tsang, <lb/>J. Winkelbauer, A.H. Wuosmaa, M. Youngs, M.V. Zhukov, Physical Review Let-<lb/>ters 109 (2012) 202502. <lb/>[29] A. Spyrou, Z. Kohley, T. Baumann, D. Bazin, B.A. Brown, G. Christian, P.A. DeY-<lb/>oung, J.E. Finck, N. Frank, E. Lunderberg, S. Mosby, W.A. Peters, A. Schiller, J.K. <lb/>Smith, J. Snyder, M.J. Strongman, M. Thoennessen, A. Volya, Physical Review <lb/>Letters 108 (2012) 102501. <lb/>[30] I. Tanihata, H. Hamagaki, O. Hashimoto, Y. Shida, N. Yoshikawa, K. Sugimoto, <lb/>O. Yamakawa, T. Kobayashi, N. Takahashi, Physical Review Letters 55 (1985) <lb/>2676. <lb/>[31] P.G. Hansen, B. Jonson, Europhysics Letters 4 (1985) 409. <lb/>[32] F. Zernike, H.C. Brinkman, Proceedings of the Koninklijke Nederlandse <lb/>Akademie van Wetenschappen 38 (1935) 161. <lb/>[33] L.M. Delves, Nuclear Physics 9 (1959) 391; 20 (1960) 275. <lb/>[34] A.A. Korsheninnikov, M.S. Golovkov, I. Tanihata, A.M. Rodin, A.S. Fomichev, S.I. <lb/>Sidorchuk, S.V. Stepantsov, M.L. Chelnokov, V.A. Gorshkov, D.D. Bogdanov, R. <lb/>Wolski, G.M. Ter-Akopian, Yu.Ts. Oganessian, W. Mittig, P. Roussel-Chomaz, H. <lb/>Savajols, E.A. Kuzmin, E.Yu. Nikolskii, A.A. Ogloblin, Physical Review Letters 87 <lb/>(2001) 092501. <lb/>[35] M. Meister, L.V. Chulkov, H. Simon, T. Aumann, M.J.G. Borge, Th.W. Elze, H. <lb/>Emling, H. Geissel, M. Hellström, B. Jonson, J.V. Kratz, R. Kulessa, Y. Leifels, <lb/>K. Markenroth, G. Münzenberg, F. Nickel, T. Nilsson, G. Nyman, V. Pribora, A. <lb/>Richter, K. Riisager, C. Scheidenberger, G. Schrieder, O. Tengblad, M.V. Zhukov, <lb/>Physical Review Letters 91 (2003) 162504. <lb/>[36] M. Meister, L.V. Chulkov, H. Simon, T. Aumann, M.J.G. Borge, Th.W. Elze, H. <lb/>Emling, H. Geissel, M. Hellström, B. Jonson, J.V. Kratz, R. Kulessa, Y. Leifels, <lb/>K. Markenroth, G. Münzenberg, F. Nickel, T. Nilsson, G. Nyman, V. Pribora, <lb/>A. Richter, K. Riisager, C. Scheidenberger, G. Schrieder, O. Tengblad, Nuclear <lb/>Physics A 723 (2003) 13. <lb/>[37] N.B. Shulgina, B.V. Danilin, L.V. Grigorenko, M.V. Zhukov, J.M. Bang, Physical <lb/>Review C 62 (2000) 014312. <lb/>[38] M.S. Golovkov, L.V. Grigorenko, A.S. Fomichev, S.A. Krupko, Yu.Ts. Oganessian, <lb/>A.M. Rodin, S.I. Sidorchuk, R.S. Slepnev, S.V. Stepantsov, G.M. Ter-Akopian, R. <lb/>Wolski, M.G. Itkis, A.S. Denikin, A.A. Bogatchev, N.A. Kondratiev, E.M. Kozulin, <lb/>A.A. Korsheninnikov, E.Yu. Nikolskii, P. Roussel-Chomaz, W. Mittig, R. Palit, V. <lb/>Bouchat, V. Kinnard, T. Materna, F. Hanappe, O. Dorvaux, L. Stuttgé, C. Angulo, <lb/>V. Lapoux, R. Raabe, L. Nalpas, A.A. Yukhimchuk, V.V. Perevozchikov, Yu.I. <lb/>Vinogradov, S.K. Grishechkin, S.V. Zlatoustovskiy, Physical Review C 72 (2005) <lb/>064612. <lb/>[39] L.V. Grigorenko, Europhysics Journal A 20 (2004) 419. <lb/>[40] R. De Diego, E. Garrido, D.V. Fedorov, A.S. Jensen, Nuclear Physics A 786 (2007) <lb/>71. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 180 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> H. Simon / International Journal of Mass Spectrometry 349– 350 (2013) 172– 180 <lb/> [41] B. Gurov Yu, S.V. Lapushkin, B.A. Chernyshev, V.G. Sandukovsky, Physics of <lb/>Particle and Nuclei 40 (2009) 558. <lb/>[42] H.T. Johansson, Yu. Aksyutina, T. Aumann, K. Boretzky, M.J.G. Borge, A. Chatillon, <lb/>L.V. Chulkov, D. Cortina-Gil, U. Datta Pramanik, H. Emling, C. Forssén, H.O.U. <lb/>Fynbo, H. Geissel, G. Ickert, B. Jonson, R. Kulessa, C. Langer, M. Lantz, T. LeBleis, <lb/>K. Mahata, M. Meister, G. Münzenberg, T. Nilsson, G. Nyman, R. Palit, S. Paschalis, <lb/>W. Prokopowicz, R. Reifarth, A. Richter, K. Riisager, G. Schrieder, H. Simon, K. <lb/>Sümmerer, O. Tengblad, H. Weick, M.V. Zhukov, Nuclear Physics A842 (2010) <lb/>15. <lb/>[43] R. Sánchez, W. Nörtershäuser, G. Ewald, D. Albers, J. Behr, P. Bricault, B.A. <lb/>Bushaw, A. Dax, J. Dilling, M. Dombsky, G.W.F. Drake, S. Götte, R. Kirchner, <lb/>H.-J. Kluge, Th. Kühl, J. Lassen, C.D.P. Levy, M.R. Pearson, E.J. Prime, V. Ryjkov, <lb/>A. Wojtaszek, Z.-C. Yan, C. Zimmermann, Physical Review Letters 96 (2006) <lb/>033002. <lb/>[44] W. Nörtershäuser, T. Neff, R. Sanchez, I. Sick, Physical Review C 84 (2011) <lb/>024307. <lb/>[45] R. Neugart, D.L. Balabanski, K. Blaum, D. Borremans, P. Himpe, M. Kowalska, P. <lb/>Lievens, S. Mallion, G. Neyens, N. Vermeulen, D.T. Yordanov, Physical Review <lb/>Letters 101 (2008) 132502. <lb/>[46] H.B. Jeppesen, A.M. Moro, U.C. Bergmann, M.J.G. Borge, J. Cederkäll, L.M. Fraile, <lb/>H.O.U. Fynbo, J. Gómez-Camacho, H.T. Johansson, B. Jonson, M. Meister, T. Nils-<lb/>son, G. Nyman, M. Pantea, K. Riisager, A. b, G. Richter, T. Schrieder, O. Sieber, <lb/>E. Tengblad, M. Tengborn, F. Turrión, Wenander, Physics Letters B 642 (2006) <lb/>449. <lb/>[47] N.B. Shulgina, B. Jonson, M.V. Zhukov, Nuclear Physics A 825 (2009) <lb/>175. <lb/>[48] M. Smith, M. Brodeur, T. Brunner, S. Ettenauer, A. Lapierre, R. Ringle, V.L. Ryjkov, <lb/>F. Ames, P. Bricault, G.W.F. Drake, P. Delheij, D. Lunney, F. Sarazin, J. Dilling, <lb/>Physical Review Letters 101 (2008) 202501. <lb/>[49] C. Gaulard, C. Bachelet, G. Audi, C. Guénaut, D. Lunney, M. de Saint Simon, M. <lb/>Sewtz, C. Thibault, Nuclear Physics A 826 (2009) 1. <lb/>[50] S. Aoyama, Physical Review Letters 89 (2002) 052501. <lb/>[51] L.V. Chulkov, H. Simon, I.J. Thompson, T. Aumann, M.J.G. Borge, Th.W. Elze, H. <lb/>Emling, H. Geissel, L.V. Grigorenko, M. Hellström, B. Jonson, J.W.V. Kratz, R. <lb/>Kulessa, K. Markenroth, M. Meister, G. Münzenberg, F. Nickel, T. Nilsson, G. <lb/>Nyman, V. Pribora, A. Richter, K. Riisager, C. Scheidenberger, G. Schrieder, O. <lb/>Tengblad, M.V. Zhukov, Nuclear Physics A 759 (2005) 23. <lb/>[52] S.N. Ershov, B.V. Danilin, J.S. Vaagen, Physical Review C 74 (2006) 014603. <lb/>[53] J. Raynal, J. Revai, Nuovo Cimento LXVIII A (1970) 612. <lb/>[54] A.A. Korsheninnikov, K. Yoshida, D.V. Aleksandrov, N. Aoi, Y. Doki, N. Inabe, M. <lb/>Fujimaki, T. Kobayashi, H. Kumagai, C.-B. Moon, E.Yu. Nikolskii, M.M. Obuti, <lb/>A.A. Ogloblin, A. Ozawa, S. Shimoura, T. Suzuki, I. Tanihata, Y. Watanabe, M. <lb/>Yanokura, Physics Letters B 326 (1994) 31. <lb/>[55] A.N. Ostrowski, H.G. Bohlen, B. Gebauer, S.M. Grimes, R. Kalpakchieva, Th. Kirch-<lb/>ner, T.N. Massey, W. von Oertzen, Th. Stolla, M. Wilpert, Th. Wilpert, Physics <lb/>Letters B 338 (1994) 13. <lb/>[56] T. Kobayashi, K. Yoshida, A. Ozawa, I. Tanihata, A. Korsheninnikov, E. Nikolsky, <lb/>T. Nakamura, Nuclear Physics A 616 (1997) 223c. <lb/>[57] L. Grigorenko, M. Zhukov, Physical Review C 77 (2008) 034611. <lb/>[58] H.T. Johansson, Yu. Aksyutina, T. Aumann, K. Boretzky, M.J.G. Borge, A. Chatillon, <lb/>L.V. Chulkov, D. Cortina-Gil, U. Datta Pramanik, H. Emling, C. Forssén, H.O.U. <lb/>Fynbo, H. Geissel, G. Ickert, B. Jonson, R. Kulessa, C. Langer, M. Lantz, T. LeBleis, <lb/>K. Mahata, M. Meister, G. Münzenberg, T. Nilsson, G. Nyman, R. Palit, S. Paschalis, <lb/>W. Prokopowicz, R. Reifarth, A. Richter, K. Riisager, G. Schrieder, N.B. Shulgina, <lb/>H. Simon, K. Sümmerer, O. Tengblad, H. Weick, M.V. Zhukov, Nuclear Physics <lb/>A847 (2010) 66. <lb/>[59] M.S. Golovkov, et al., Physics Letters B 672 (2009) 22. <lb/>[60] S.I. Sidorchuk, A.A. Bezbakh, V. Chudoba, I.A. Egorova, A.S. Fomichev, M.S. <lb/>Golovkov, A.V. Gorshkov, V.A. Gorshkov, L.V. Grigorenko, P. Jal ůvková, G. <lb/>Kaminski, S.A. Krupko, E.A. Kuzmin, E.Yu. Nikolskii, Yu.Ts. Oganessian, Yu.L. <lb/>Parfenova, P.G. Sharov, R.S. Slepnev, S.V. Stepantsov, G.M. Ter-Akopian, R. Wol-<lb/>ski, A.A. Yukhimchuk, S.V. Filchagin, A.A. Kirdyashkin, I.P. Maksimkin, O.P. <lb/>Vikhlyantsev, Physical Review Letters 108 (2012) 202502. <lb/>[61] Z. Kohley, J. Snyder, T. Baumann, G. Christian, P.A. DeYoung, J.E. Finck, R.A. <lb/>Haring-Kaye, M. Jones, E. Lunderberg, B. Luther, S. Mosby, A. Simon, J.K. Smith, <lb/>A. Spyrou, S.L. Stephenson, M. Thoennessen, Physical Review Letters 109 (2012) <lb/>232501. <lb/>[62] C.C. Hall, E.M. Lunderberg, P.A. DeYoung, T. Baumann, D. Bazin, G. Blanchon, A. <lb/>Bonaccorso, B.A. Brown, J. Brown, G. Christian, D.H. Denby, J. Finck, N. Frank, A. <lb/>Gade, J. Hinnefeld, C.R. Hoffman, B. Luther, S. Mosby, W.A. Peters, A. Spyrou, M. <lb/>Thoennessen, Physical Review C 81 (2010) 021302(R). <lb/>[63] G. Blanchon, A. Bonaccorso, D.M. Brink, A. García-Camacho, N. Vinh Mau, <lb/>Nuclear Physics A 784 (2007) 49. <lb/>[64] C. Forssén, B. Jonson, M.V. Zhukov, Nuclear Physics A 673 (2000) 143. <lb/>[65] O. Jensen, G. Hagen, M. Hjorth-Jensen, J.S. Vaagen, Physical Review C 83 (2011) <lb/>021305. <lb/>[66] C.R. Hoffman, T. Baumann, D. Bazin, J. Brown, G. Christian, P.A. DeYoung, J.E. <lb/>Finck, N. Frank, J. Hinnefeld, R. Howes, P. Mears, E. Mosby, S. Mosby, J. Reith, B. <lb/>Rizzo, W.F. Rogers, G. Peaslee, W.A. Peters, A. Schiller, M.J. Scott, S.L. Tabor, M. <lb/>Thoennessen, P.J. Voss, T. Williams, Physical Review Letters 100 (2008) 152502. <lb/>[67] E. Lunderberg, P.A. DeYoung, Z. Kohley, H. Attanayake, T. Baumann, D. Bazin, G. <lb/>Christian, D. Divaratne, S.M. Grimes, A. Haagsma, J.E. Finck, N. Frank, B. Luther, <lb/>S. Mosby, T. Nagi, G.F. Peaslee, A. Schiller, J. Snyder, A. Spyrou, M.J. Strongman, <lb/>M. Thoennessen, Physical Review Letters 108 (2012) 142503. <lb/>[68] C. Caesar, PhD thesis D12, TU-Darmstadt, Germany, 2012. <lb/>[69] T. Aumann, V. Avdeichikov, M. Barr, S. Beceiro, D. Bemmerer, J. Benlliure, C.A. <lb/>Bertulani, K. Boretzky, M.J.G. Borge, G. Burgunder, M. Caamano, E. Casarejos, W. <lb/>Catford, J. Cederkäll, S. Chakraborty, M. Chartier, L. Chulkov, D. Cortina-Gil, U. <lb/>Datta Pramanik, P. Diaz Fernandez, I. Dillmann, Z. Elekes, J. Enders, O. Ershova, <lb/>A. Estrade, F. Farinon, L. M. Fraile, M. Freer, M. Freudenberger, H.O.U. Fynbo, D. <lb/>Galaviz, H. Geissel, R. Gernhäuser, P. Golubev, D. Gonzalez Diaz, J. Hagdahl, T. <lb/>Heftrich, M. Heil, M. Heine, A. Heinz, A. Henriques, M. Holl, J. D. Holt, G. Ickert, <lb/>A. Ignatov, B. Jakobsson, H.T. Johansson, B. Jonson, N. Kalantar, R. Kanungo, A. <lb/>Kelic-Heil, R. Knöbel, T. Kröll, R. Krücken, J. Kurcewicz, M. Labiche, C. Langer, T. <lb/>Le Bleis, R. Lemmon, O. Lepyoshkina, J. Machado, J. Marganiec, V. Maroussov, J. <lb/>Menendez, M. Mostazo, A. Movsesyan, A. Najafi, T. Nilsson, C. Nociforo, V. Panin, <lb/>A. Perea, S. Pietri, R. Plag, A. Prochazka, A. Rahaman, G. Rastrepina, R. Reifarth, G. <lb/>Ribeiro, M.V. Ricciardi, C. Rigollet, K. Riisager, M. Röder, D. Rossi, J. Sanchez del <lb/>Rio, D. Savran, H. Scheit, A. Schwenk, H. Simon, O. Sorlin, V. Stoica, B. Streicher, <lb/>J. Taylor, O. Tengblad, S. Terashima, R. Thies, Y. Togano, E. Uberseder, J. Van <lb/>de Walle, P. Velho, V. Volkov, A. Wagner, F. Wamers, H. Weick, M. Weigand, C. <lb/>Wheldon, G. Wilson, C. Wimmer, J. Winfield, P. Woods, D. Yakorev, M.V. Zhukov, <lb/>A. Zilges, M. Zoric, K. Zuber. arXiv:nucl-ex/1209.0156, 2012. <lb/>[70] A. Volya, V. Zelevinsky, Physical Review C 74 (2006) 064314. <lb/>[71] G. Hagen, M. Hjorth-Jensen, G.R. Jansen, R. Machleidt, T. Papenbrock, Physical <lb/>Review Letters 109 (2012) 032502. <lb/>[72] http://www.fair-center.eu/for-users/experiments/nustar/experiments/r3b. <lb/>html/ (visited 2012). </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
