<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Progress on the study of nuclear states with mixed proton-neutron <lb/>symmetry <lb/> N. Pietralla <lb/> 1,2,a , Th. Möller <lb/> 1 , T. Ahn <lb/> 1,3,4 , Ch. Bauer <lb/> 1 , L. Coquard <lb/> 1 , M. Danchev <lb/> 5 , K.A. Gladnishki <lb/> 5 , A. Krugmann <lb/> 1 , J. <lb/>Leske <lb/> 1 , O. Möller <lb/> 1 , P. von Neumann-Cosel <lb/> 1 , V.Yu. Ponomarev <lb/> 1 , G. Rainovski <lb/> 5 , A. Scheikh Obeid <lb/> 1 , M. Scheck <lb/> 1 , Ch. <lb/>Walz <lb/> 1 , and J. Wambach <lb/> 1,2 <lb/>1 Institut für Kernphysik, Technische Universität Darmstadt, 64289 Darmstadt, Germany <lb/> 2 GSI Helmholtzzentrum für Schwerionenforschung mbH, 64291 Darmstadt, Germany <lb/> 3 Wright Nuclear Structure Laboratory, Yale University, New Haven, CT, U.S.A. <lb/> 4 National Superconducting Cyclotron Lab, Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI 48824, USA <lb/> 5 Faculty of Physics, St. Kliment Ohridski University of Sofia, BG-1164 Sofia, Bulgaria <lb/> Abstract.  The one-quadrupole phonon excitation of mixed symmetry, the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1,ms state, is a fundamental building <lb/>block of nuclear structure. This article gives a summary of our recent experimental research on this excitation <lb/>mode in the A = 90 and A = 130 mass regions. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> The nuclear proton-neutron degree of freedom and its fun-<lb/>damental impact on nuclear structure represents one of the <lb/>central aspects of modern nuclear structure physics. The <lb/>structure of collective nuclear excitations is determined by <lb/>the nuclear shell structure that itself evolves as a function <lb/>of proton and neutron numbers. The evolution of nuclear <lb/>shell structure as a function of neutron-excess provides <lb/>us with a sensitive test for modern effective nuclear inter-<lb/>actions. It is studied at current radioactive ion beams by <lb/>tracing, for instance, the simplest properties of low-energy <lb/>quadrupole-collective states to the most neutron-rich nu-<lb/>clei accessible. The evolution of nuclear shells also dom-<lb/>inates the formation of nuclear deformation and collec-<lb/>tivity. It sets the conditions for the emergence of excited <lb/>nuclear quantum states with wave functions that include <lb/>many proton excitations and neutron excitations within the <lb/>valence shell that collectively couple in phase. This in-<lb/>phase coupling of proton and neutron valence-shell excita-<lb/>tions simultaneously leads to the occurrence of orthogonal <lb/>nuclear valence-shell excitations with partial out-of-phase <lb/>coupling of proton and neutron components. These states <lb/>represent a closely related aspect of the nuclear proton-<lb/>neutron degree of freedom. Indeed, nuclear excitations <lb/>may be classified according to the proton-neutron symme-<lb/>try of their wave functions, either in terms of isospin in the <lb/>framework of models that use nucleons as the fundamen-<lb/>tal degree of freedom or in terms of F-spin in approximate <lb/>bosonic nuclear models for collective valence-shell excita-<lb/>tions at low energies. <lb/>The formulation of the interacting boson model (IBM-<lb/>2) in its F-spin limit [1–3] has emphasized the fundamental <lb/></body>

			<front> a e-mail: pietralla@ikp.tu-darmstadt.de <lb/></front>

			<body> role of collective proton-neutron non-symmetric valence-<lb/>shell excitations, for the first time. Nuclear excitations <lb/>with F-spin quantum number F &lt; F  max  = (N  π  + N  ν  )/2, <lb/>where N  π(ν)  is half the number of valence protons (neu-<lb/>trons), contain parts in their wave functions where proton <lb/>bosons and neutron bosons are coupled antisymmetrically <lb/>with respect to the exchange of proton and neutron la-<lb/>bels. These states have been called mixed-symmetry states <lb/>(MSSs). Prominent examples of MSSs are the J <lb/> π  = 1 <lb/> + <lb/> scissors mode of deformed nuclei or the mixed-symmetry <lb/>2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1,ms one-phonon vibration in heavy spherical nuclei. In-<lb/>formation on the pro-ton-neutron symmetry of the low-<lb/>energy nuclear states, including the ground state, its col-<lb/>lective excitations, and MSSs, is needed for a correct inter-<lb/>pretation of the role of the nuclear proton-neutron degree <lb/>of freedom in the formation of nuclear structure. After the <lb/>discovery of the scissors mode [4] and the clarification of <lb/>its quadrupole-collective character [5,6] it became obvious <lb/>that the isovector quadrupole excitation of the valence shell <lb/>represents the building block of mixed-symmetric struc-<lb/>tures. <lb/>Vibrational nuclei exhibit a one-quadrupole phonon <lb/>excitation as the lowest-lying state of mixed-pn symmetry, <lb/> i.e the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1,ms state. Its close relation to the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1 state is evident <lb/>in the Q-phonon scheme [7], where the wave functions of <lb/>the one-quadrupole phonon excitations are well approxi-<lb/>mated by the expressions <lb/> |2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1  Q s  |0 <lb/> + <lb/> 1  = [Q  π  + Q  ν  ] |0 <lb/> + <lb/> 1  <lb/> (1) <lb/> |2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1,ms  Q m  |0 <lb/> + <lb/> 1  = N <lb/> Q  π <lb/> N  π <lb/> − <lb/> Q  ν <lb/> N  ν <lb/> |0 <lb/> + <lb/> 1  . <lb/> (2) <lb/>Here, Q  π,ν  (N  π,ν  ) denote the proton and neutron quadrupole <lb/>operators (boson numbers), N = N  π  + N  ν  , and |0 <lb/> + <lb/> 1  is the <lb/>(in general highly correlated) ground state of a collectively <lb/> EPJ Web of Conferences <lb/>DOI: 10.1051/ <lb/> C <lb/>  Owned by the authors, published by EDP Sciences, 2012 <lb/>, <lb/>epjconf 20123 <lb/> / <lb/> 38 <lb/> 810001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 2 0 , which <lb/>. <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distributi <lb/>and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/>on, <lb/> 10001 (2012) <lb/> Article available at http://www.epj-conferences.org or http://dx.doi.org/10.1051/epjconf/20123810001 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> EPJ Web of Conferences <lb/></note>

			<body> vibrating even-even nucleus. Despite its fundamental role <lb/>in nuclear structure, the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1,ms state has only recently been <lb/>studied systematically, [8–12]. The dominant fragments of <lb/>the one-phonon 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1,ms state are observed at about 2 MeV <lb/>excitation energy. Due to their isovector character, MSSs <lb/>decay rapidly by dipole transitions and are very short lived, <lb/>typically a few tens of femtoseconds. Large M1 matrix ele-<lb/>ments of ≈ 1 µ  N  are in fact the unique signatures for MSSs. <lb/>Consequently, lifetime information is needed for making <lb/>safe assignments of mixed symmetry to a nuclear energy <lb/>level. A review article on the status of experimental infor-<lb/>mation on mixed-symmetry states in vibrational nuclei has <lb/>been published [13]. We report on our recent progress on <lb/>this field. <lb/> 2 Experimental method <lb/> Projectile-Coulomb excitation has been established as a <lb/>powerful method for the identification and investigation <lb/>of one-phonon MSSs [10]. After this approach has first <lb/>been applied to the investigation of the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1,ms state of <lb/> 96 Ru <lb/>at the Yale Tandem accelerator [10], we have initiated a <lb/>research programme on the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1,ms state at ANL with the <lb/>nucleus <lb/> 138 Ce as a case study [12]. Crucial influence of <lb/>sub-shell closures on mixed-symmetry structures was ob-<lb/>served [12], a phenomenon which sensitively tests the ef-<lb/>fective proton-neutron interaction in microscopic valence <lb/>shell models [14]. The one-phonon 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1,ms state of <lb/> 136 Ce has <lb/>recently been identified from similar Coulomb-excitation <lb/>experiments at Gammasphere [15]. <lb/>A sequence of experiments has been performed at Ar-<lb/>gonne National Laboratory. The superconducting ATLAS <lb/>accelerator provided the ion beams of stable even-even <lb/>isotopes, e.g. of the Xenon, Barium and Cerium isotopic <lb/>chains, with energies corresponding to ∼ 85 % of the <lb/>Coulomb barrier for a reaction on <lb/> 12 C nuclei. The beam <lb/>intensities amounted typically to ∼ 1pnA. The beams were <lb/> Fig. 1. Background-subtracted and Doppler-corrected singles γ-<lb/> ray spectrum summed over all Ge detectors of the Gammasphere <lb/>array at ANL after Coulomb excitation of <lb/> 136 Ce on a carbon target <lb/>[15]. <lb/> impinging on a stationary carbon target of thickness 1 <lb/>mg/cm <lb/> 2 . Light target ions were chosen in order to favor <lb/>the one-step Coulomb excitation process over multi-step <lb/>processes for ease of data evaluation. The γ-rays emitted <lb/>by Coulomb-excited states of the beam nuclei were de-<lb/>tected in the Gammasphere array which consists of ∼ 100 <lb/>high purity Compton suppressed Germanium detectors ar-<lb/>ranged in 16 rings [16,17]. An event was defined by a γ-ray <lb/> of multiplicity 1 or higher. Doppler correction (recoiling <lb/>velocity ∼ 6-8%) and background subtraction (difference <lb/>between the &quot; in-beam &quot; spectrum and the &quot; off-beam &quot; spec-<lb/>trum scaled to eliminate the 1461 keV <lb/> 40 K line) had been <lb/>applied in order to obtain the total single spectra. Figure 1 <lb/>displays data from the projectile-Coulomb excitation reac-<lb/>tions of a <lb/> 136 Ce-ion beam on a carbon target. <lb/>The experimental γ-ray spectra are dominated by the <lb/>decays of low-spin states, such as 2 <lb/> +  or 3 <lb/> −  states, that <lb/>are predominantly populated by one-step Coulomb exci-<lb/>tation from the ground state. For each state observed we <lb/>measured the excitation cross section relative to that of <lb/>the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1 state with an accuracy of 1 -0.1 %. By calculat-<lb/>ing the Coulomb excitation cross sections for each excited <lb/>state with the multiple-Coulomb excitation code CLX and <lb/>fitting them to our experimental data (normalized to the <lb/>2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1 state), we deduced the electromagnetic matrix elements <lb/>corresponding to each transition of the excited states. The <lb/>crucial multipole-mixing ratios of the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> (i&gt;1)  → 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1 tran-<lb/>sitions were obtained from γ-ray angular distributions if <lb/>sufficient statistics have been obtained. A possible large <lb/> B(M1) value, signature of the MSS, is then easily derived <lb/>from the data. For a further description of this method, the <lb/>reader is referred to Refs. [12,13]. <lb/> 3 Evolution of  2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1,ms  states in the  A = 130 <lb/> region <lb/> The experiments performed so far [12,15,18,19] allow for <lb/>a nearly complete overview on the properties of the MSS <lb/>throughout the stable isotopes of the A = 130 region. A <lb/>recent publication on the first identification of a MSS in <lb/>the unstable nucleus <lb/> 132 Te [20] expands the experimen-<lb/>tal data on the N = 80 isotonic chain to the neutron-rich <lb/> Fig. 2. Overview on the B(M1; 2 <lb/> + <lb/> i  → 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1 ) strength distributions <lb/>for the stable even-even nuclei in the A=130 region. <lb/></body>

			<page> 10001-p.2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> NSRT12 <lb/></note>

			<body> radioactive isotopes. A set of data currently under anal-<lb/>ysis on the nucleus <lb/> 132 Ba [21] will complete our infor-<lb/>mation on the one-phonon mixed-symmetry state in the <lb/>stable even-even N = 76 isotones. An overview on the <lb/> B(M1; 2 <lb/> + <lb/> i  → 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1 ) strength distributions in the even-even <lb/>nuclei in the A = 130 region is shown in figure 2. <lb/>In the stable N = 80 isotones the excitation energy <lb/>of the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1,ms state increases with increasing proton num-<lb/>ber. This trend continues in the unstable nucleus <lb/> 132 Te [20]. <lb/>The evolution of one-quadrupole phonon MSSs along the <lb/> N = 80 isotonic chain has been studied microscopically <lb/>in the nuclear shell model either using large-scale diago-<lb/>nalization [22] or very recently using a new importance-<lb/>sampling iterative algorithm for matrix diagonalization <lb/>[23]. In the N = 78 isotonic chain, the energy of the <lb/>MSS again increases with increasing proton number. In <lb/>the neighboring N = 76 isotones, however, the opposite <lb/>trend can be observed. Here, the excitation energy of the <lb/>MSS decreases with increasing proton number. It is also <lb/>interesting to follow the evolution of the MSS excitation <lb/>energies in the different isotopic chains. Again, one finds <lb/>that in the Ce and Ba isotopes, the excitation energy of the <lb/>MSS increases with increasing neutron number, whereas <lb/>in the Xe isotopes an increase in N  ν  results in a decrease <lb/>of E(2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1,ms ). Apparently, the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1,ms state evolves in different <lb/>ways as a function of valence particle numbers. The evo-<lb/>lution of M1 transitions between mixed-symmetry states <lb/>and fully symmetric states in the γ-soft nuclei of the xenon <lb/>isotopic chain have recently been described in a schematic <lb/>microscopic approach [24] and in the nuclear shell model <lb/>using a new importance-sampling iterative algorithm for <lb/>matrix diagonalization [25]. Whether or not the observed <lb/>differences are related to a critical point of a nuclear shape <lb/>phase transition near <lb/> 134 Ba is unknown up to now. <lb/>From data on E(2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1 ) and E(2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1,ms ), an estimate of the <lb/>proton-neutron quadrupole-quadrupole interaction V <lb/> QQ <lb/>pn <lb/> according to the two-state mixing scheme in [26] has been <lb/>performed on the N = 80 isotones [18], the Xe isotopes <lb/>[19], and, just recently, on the N = 78 isotones [15]. The <lb/>results show, that the value derived for the proton-neutron <lb/>quadrupole-quadrupole interaction in the N = 78 isotonic <lb/>chain is about 14% smaller than that for the N = 80 iso-<lb/>topic chain [18] and about 6% smaller than the value for <lb/>the xenon isotopic chain [19]. An example of the data, <lb/>taken from Ref. [15], is displayed in figure 3. <lb/>In contrast to the lighter xenon isotopes, where the ex-<lb/>perimental sensitivity for identification of weakly collec-<lb/>tive 2 <lb/> +  states is limited up to 2.1-2.3 MeV, for the N = 78 <lb/>isotonic chain this sensitivity extends to up to 2.5 MeV <lb/>and, in the case of <lb/> 134 Ba [27], it extends to even higher <lb/>energies. Moreover, the summed B(M1) strength remains <lb/>constant as a function of proton number along the chain of <lb/> N = 78 isotones. <lb/> Fig. 3. Simultaneous fit of the experimental energies of the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1 <lb/> states (solid curve) and of the B(M1)-weighted average energies <lb/>of the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1,ms states (dashed curve) in the N = 78 isotones. Taken <lb/>from [15]. <lb/> 4 Phase of proton-and neutron-<lb/>components to MSSs: the case of <lb/> 92 <lb/> Zr <lb/> We studied the formation of quadrupole collectivity in the <lb/>particularly simple case of a nucleus with a low-energy <lb/>structure that is dominated by one pair of valence par-<lb/>ticles each for protons and neutrons. An example is the <lb/>nucleus <lb/> 92 Zr with 2 neutrons beyond the N = 50 shell <lb/>closure and 2 protons beyond the Z = 38 sub-shell clo-<lb/>sure. The lowest 2-quasiparticle (2qp) states will there-<lb/>fore have π(1g  9/2 ) <lb/> 2 and ν(2d  5/2 ) <lb/> 2 configurations. Due to the <lb/>residual proton-neutron interaction two different classes of <lb/>collective excitations appear at low energy in which the <lb/>amplitudes of the two most important 2qp configurations <lb/>are coupled in a symmetric or antisymmetric way, respec-<lb/>tively. In <lb/> 92 Zr, these are experimentally identified as the <lb/>2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1 and 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 2 states [13,28] with some degree of configura-<lb/>tional isospin polarization [29,30]. To shed light on the <lb/>microscopic origin of the effective coupling strength in the <lb/>valence shell we consider the quasiparticle-phonon model <lb/>(QPM) [31]. The QPM wave functions are dominated by <lb/>the lowest π and ν 2qp components, that show the ex-<lb/>pected in-phase and out-of-phase behavior for the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> fs fully <lb/>symmetric and 2 <lb/> + <lb/> ms mixed-symmetry states. The electro-<lb/>magnetic properties and excitation energies are in excel-<lb/>lent agreement with the data [32]. The magnetic moments <lb/>of these states and the strong M1 transition between them <lb/>originate almost entirely from the valence-shell configura-<lb/>tions. However, up to 80% of the B(E2) strengths are gen-<lb/>erated from many components beyond the valence shell al-<lb/>though their total contribution to the wave function norm <lb/>is small. This observation motivates a simple three-state <lb/>mixing scenario between the proton-valence shell config-<lb/>uration, the neutron-valence shell configuration, and the <lb/>Giant Quadrupole Resonance (GQR) for a deeper insight <lb/>in the formation of the one-quadrupole phonon states with <lb/>symmetric and mixed-symmetry character even on a semi-<lb/>quantitative level [33]. For the nucleus <lb/> 92 Zr which has <lb/></body>

			<page> 10001-p.3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> EPJ Web of Conferences <lb/></note>

			<body> Fig. 4. Form factors for the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1,fs (red, solid line) and 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1,ms (blue, <lb/>dashed line) from <lb/> 92  Zr(p, p <lb/>  ) and <lb/> 92  Zr(e, e <lb/>  ) experiments (from <lb/>[33]). <lb/> a higher energy for the proton valence-shell component <lb/>than the neutron valence-shell component at the Z = 40 <lb/>sub-shell closure, the three-state mixing scheme requires <lb/>that the neutron valence-shell component flips its phase <lb/>with respect to the GQR component when going from the <lb/>proton-neutron symmetric 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1 state to the predominantly <lb/>mixed-symmetric 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 2 state. <lb/>Two probes with different sensitivity to protons and <lb/>neutrons are necessary to study this quantum interfer-<lb/>ence experimentally. Electron scattering at low momen-<lb/>tum transfer provides a measure of the charge transition <lb/>radius. An (e, e <lb/>  ) experiment was performed at the high-<lb/>energy-resolution spectrometer [34] of the Darmstadt su-<lb/>perconducting electron linear accelerator (S-DALINAC). <lb/>A self-supporting zirconium metal target of 9.8 mg/cm <lb/> 2 <lb/> areal density and with enrichment to 94.6 % in the iso-<lb/>tope <lb/> 92 Zr was used. Data were taken covering a momen-<lb/>tum transfer range between q ∼ 0.3 − 0.6 fm <lb/> −1  indicat-<lb/>ing no difference between the charge transition radii of the <lb/>2 <lb/> + <lb/> fs and 2 <lb/> + <lb/> ms states within experimental uncertainties (figure <lb/>4, bottom). Information about the neutron transition radii <lb/>can be derived from the proton scattering data of Ref. [35]. <lb/>At the incident energy of 800 MeV protons interact pre-<lb/>dominantly via the isoscalar central piece of the effective <lb/>projectile-nucleus interaction [36]. Clearly, the refraction <lb/>pattern of the (p, p <lb/>  ) cross section for the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> ms state are <lb/>shifted to higher q values as compared to those for the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> fs <lb/> state (figure 4, top) corresponding to a smaller transition <lb/>radius. <lb/>Figure 5 displays the proton and neutron transition den-<lb/>sities of the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> fs (top) and 2 <lb/> + <lb/> ms (bottom) states calculated <lb/> Fig. 5. Neutron transition densities of the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> fs (top) and 2 <lb/> + <lb/> ms (bot-<lb/>tom) states of <lb/> 92 Zr from QPM calculations. The full transition <lb/>densities (solid lines) are decomposed in parts stemming from the <lb/>GQR (dotted lines) and from the main 2qp configurations (dashed <lb/>lines). The arrows indicate the maxima of the corresponding full <lb/>transition densities. <lb/> in the full QPM approach. The full transition densities <lb/>(solid curves) are decomposed into a collective part stem-<lb/>ming from the GQR (dotted curves) and the predominant <lb/> ν(2d  5/2 ) <lb/> 2 2qp neutron contributions (dashed curves). The <lb/>key point is the different radial behaviour of both parts <lb/>and their relative signs. An out-of-phase coupling between <lb/>the neutron valence shell contribution and the contribution <lb/>from the GQR in the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1,ms state leads to a destructive quan-<lb/>tum interference that reduces the neutron transition den-<lb/>sity at large radii (due to the larger radius of the ν(2d  5/2 ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> orbital) and consequently shifts the maximum of the total <lb/>neutron transition density to the interior with respect to that <lb/>one for the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> fs state, as indicated by the arrows in figure 5. <lb/>This effect reduces the neutron transition radius of the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> ms <lb/> with respect to the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> fs state of <lb/> 92 Zr. In contrast, the proton <lb/>transition radius remains essentially unchanged since the <lb/> π(1g  9/2 ) <lb/> 2 part couples in-phase to the GQR contribution <lb/>in both states. The combination of both data sets unam-<lb/>biguously demonstrates for the first time that the phase of <lb/>the neutron valence-shell configurations in <lb/> 92 Zr changes its <lb/>sign between the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> fs and the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> ms state [33]. <lb/> 5 Summary <lb/> The isovector one-quadrupole phonon excitation of the va-<lb/>lence shell has been systematically investigated in a large <lb/></body>

			<page> 10001-p.4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> NSRT12 <lb/></note>

			<body> number of vibrational nuclei in the mass regions A = 90 <lb/>and A = 130. It carries the signatures of the 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1,ms state with <lb/> F-spin quantum number F = F  max  − 1. This state is gener-<lb/>ally observed from absolute M1 transition strengths when <lb/>the experimental sensitivity is high enough. This state is <lb/>typically concentrated in a single 2 <lb/> +  state or distributed <lb/>over two or three fragments. It is found at energies around <lb/>2 MeV and features an M1 transition matrix element to the <lb/>2 <lb/> + <lb/> 1 state between 0.5 and 1.5 µ  N  . The details of its evolution <lb/>as a function of particle number is not entirely understood. <lb/>It may depend on the local shell structure around the Fermi <lb/>level and on the evolution of quadrupole deformation. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments <lb/> We thank all those who have contributed to our research on <lb/>various aspects of mixed-symmetry states. With respect to <lb/>the data discussed in this contribution we particularly want <lb/>to acknowledge the scientists and staff members at the Ar-<lb/>gonne National Laboratory, USA, at the iThemba Labs, <lb/>South-Africa, and at the S-DALINAC, Germany and thank <lb/>them for the productive scientific collaboration. Support <lb/>from the DFG under grants Pi 393/2-2 and SFB 634, by the <lb/>DAAD within the German-Bulgarian exchange program <lb/>under grant Nos. PPP 50751591 and DNTS/01/2/2011, by <lb/>the German Federal Ministry for Education and Research <lb/>under grant Nos. 06DA9041I and 06DA7046, and by the <lb/>Helmholtz International Center for FAIR funded through <lb/>the LOEWE programme by the state of Hesse is gratefully <lb/>acknowledged. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. A. Arima, T. Ohtsuka, F. Iachello, and I. Talmi, Phys. <lb/>Lett. B 66, 205 (1977) <lb/>2. F. Iachello, and A. Arima, The Interacting Boson <lb/>Model (Cambridge University Press, 1987) <lb/>3. P. Van Isacker, K. Heyde, J. Jolie, and A. Sevrin, Ann. <lb/>Phys. 171, 253 (1986) <lb/>4. D. Bohle, A. Richter, W. Steffen, A. Dieperink, N. L. <lb/>Iudice, F. Palumbo, and O. Scholten, Phys. Lett. B <lb/> 137, 27 (1984) <lb/>5. W. Ziegler, C. Rangacharyulu, A. Richter, and <lb/>C. Spieler, Phys. Rev. Lett. 65, 2515 (1990) <lb/>6. N. Pietralla, P. von Brentano, R.-D. Herzberg, <lb/>U. Kneissl, N. Lo Iudice, H. Maser, H. H. Pitz, and <lb/>A. Zilges, Phys. Rev. C 58, 184 (1998) <lb/>7. T. Otsuka and K.-H. Kim, Phys. Rev. C 50, R1768 <lb/>(1994) <lb/>8. N. Pietralla, C. Fransen, D. Belic, P. von Brentano, <lb/>C. Frießner, U. Kneissl, A. Linnemann, A. Nord, <lb/>H. H. Pitz, T. Otsuka, I. Schneider, V. Werner, and <lb/>I. Wiedenhöver, Phys. Rev. Lett. 83, 1303 (1999) <lb/>9. N. Pietralla, et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 84, 3775 (2000) <lb/>10. N. Pietralla, C. J. Barton, R. Krücken, C. W. Beausang, <lb/>M. A. Caprio, R. F. Casten, J. R. Cooper, A. A. Hecht, <lb/>H. Newman, J. R. Novak, and N. V. Zamfir, Phys. Rev. <lb/>C 64, 031301 (2001) <lb/>11. N. Pietralla, et al., Phys. Rev. C 68, 031305(R) (2003) <lb/>12. G. Rainovski, N. Pietralla, T. Ahn, C. J. Lister, R. V. F. <lb/>Janssens, M. P. Carpenter, S. Zhu, and C. J. Barton, <lb/>Phys. Rev. Lett. 96, 122501 (2006) <lb/>13. N. Pietralla, P. von Brentano, and A. F. Lisetskiy, <lb/>Prog.Part. Nucl. Phys. 60, 225 (2008) <lb/>14. N. Lo Iudice, C. Stoyanov, and D. Tarpanov, Phys. <lb/>Rev. C 77, 044310 (2008) <lb/>15. T. Ahn, G. Rainovski, N. Pietralla, L. Coquard, <lb/>T. Möller, A. Costin, R. V. F. Janssens, C. J. Lister, <lb/>M. P. Carpenter, and S. Zhu, Phys. Rev. C 86, 014303 <lb/>(2012) <lb/>16. I. Y. Lee, Nucl. Phys. A 520, 641c (1990) <lb/>17. P. Nolan, F. Beck, and D. Fossan, Annu. Rev. Nucl. <lb/>Part. Sci. 45, 561 (1994) <lb/>18. T. Ahn, L. Coquard, N. Pietralla, et al., Phys. Lett. B <lb/> 679, 19 (2009) <lb/>19. L. Coquard, et al., Phys. Rev. C 82, 024317 (2010) <lb/>20. M. Danchev, G. Rainovski, N. Pietralla, A. Gargano, <lb/>A. Covello, C. Baktash, J. R. Beene, C. R. Bingham, <lb/>A. Galindo-Uribarri, K. A. Gladnishki, C. J. Gross, <lb/>V. Yu. Ponomarev, D. C. Radford, L. L. Riedinger, <lb/>M. Scheck, A. E. Stuchbery, J. Wambach, C.-H. Yu, <lb/>and N. V. Zamfir, Phys. Rev. C 84, 061306 (2011) <lb/>21. T. Möller, et al., in preparation <lb/>22. K. Sieja, G. Martinez Pinedo, L. Coquard, and N. <lb/>Pietralla, Phys. Rev. C 80, 054311 (2009) <lb/>23. D. Bianco, F. Andreozzi, N. Lo Iudice, A. Porrino, and <lb/>F. Knapp, Phys. Rev. C 85, 034332 (2012) <lb/>24. R.V. Jolos, N. Pietralla, N.Yu. Shirikova, and V.V. <lb/>Voronov, Phys. Rev. C 84, 014315 (2011) <lb/>25. D. Bianco, F. Andreozzi, N. Lo Iudice, A. Porrino, and <lb/>F. Knapp, Phys. Rev. C 84, 024310 (2011) <lb/>26. K. Heyde and J. Sau, Phys. Rev. C 33, 1050 (1986) <lb/>27. B. Fazekas, T. Belgya, G. Molnar, and A. Veres, Nucl. <lb/>Phys. A 548, 249 (1992) <lb/>28. V. Werner, D. Belic, P. von Brentano, C. Fransen, <lb/>A. Gade, H. von Garrel, J. Jolie, U. Kneissl, <lb/>C. Kohstall, A. Linnemann, A. Lisetskiy, N. Pietralla, <lb/>H. Pitz, M. Scheck, K.-H. Speidel, F. Stedile, and <lb/>S. Yates, Phys. Lett. B 550, 140 (2002) <lb/>29. J. D. Holt, N. Pietralla, J. W. Holt, T. T. S. Kuo, and <lb/>G. Rainovski, Phys. Rev. C 76, 034325 (2007) <lb/>30. A.P. Severyukhin, N.N. Arsenyev, and N. Pietralla, <lb/>Phys. Rev. C 86, 024311 (2012) <lb/>31. V. Soloviev, Theory of Atomic Nuclei: Quasiparticles <lb/>and Phonons (IoP Publ., 1992) <lb/>32. N. Lo Iudice and C. Stoyanov, Phys. Rev. C 73, <lb/> 037305 (2006) <lb/>33. C. Walz, H. Fujita, A. Krugmann, P. von Neumann-<lb/>Cosel, N. Pietralla, V. Y. Ponomarev, A. Scheikh-<lb/>Obeid, and J. Wambach, Phys. Rev. Lett. 106, 062501 <lb/>(2011) <lb/>34. A. Lenhardt, U. Bonnes, O. Burda, P. von Neumann-<lb/>Cosel, M. Platz, A. Richter, and S. Watzlawik, Nucl. <lb/>Instr. Meth. Phys. A 562, 320 (2006) <lb/>35. F. Baker, A. Scott, M. Grimm, W. Love, V. Penu-<lb/>metcha, C. Glashausser, G. Adams, G. Igo, G. Hoff-<lb/>mann, J. Moss, W. Swenson, and B. Wood, Nucl. Phys. <lb/>A 393, 283 (1983) <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 10001-p.5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> EPJ Web of Conferences <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> 36. M. A. Franey and W. G. Love, Phys. Rev. C 31, 488 <lb/>(1985) <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 10001-p.6 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
