<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> PHYSICA <lb/> ELSEVIER <lb/> Physica A 218 (1995) 237-244 <lb/> Equivalence of classical spins and <lb/>Hartree-Fock-Bogoliubov approximation of the <lb/>fermionic anharmonic oscillator <lb/> M.T. Thomaz  a,l,  A.ER. de Toledo Piza b,2 <lb/> a Instituto de F(sica, Universidade Federal Fluminense, R. Gal. Milton Tavares dr Souza s/n., Campus da <lb/>Praia Vermelha, Niter6i, R.J., 24210-340, Brazil <lb/>b Instituto de F(sica, Universidade de Stio Paulo, Sdo Paulo, S.P, 01452-990, Brazil <lb/> Received 23 May 1994; revised 22 February 1995 <lb/> Abstract <lb/> We show that the Hartree-Fock-Bogoliubov (alias Gaussian) approximation of the initial <lb/>condition problem of the fermionic anharmonic oscillator is equivalent to a bosonic Hamiltonian <lb/>system of two classical spins. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. The equivalence of classical spins and the Hartree-Fock-Bogoliubov <lb/>approximation of the fermionic anharmonic oscillator <lb/> The degrees of freedom of quantum fermionic systems are described by anti-commu-<lb/>ting variables that have no counterpart in the description of classical systems. However, <lb/>classical analogies give physical insight to the understanding of quantum phenomena. <lb/>It has been shown that the Hartree-Fock (HF) approximation of a fermionic many-<lb/>body system can be mapped into an equivalent Hamiltonian classical system [ 1 ]. This <lb/>equivalence allows to derive physical properties of fermionic quantum systems by study-<lb/>ing the classical equation of the equivalent system. It is not an obvious statement  that <lb/> all fermionic quantum systems can be mapped onto a classical model. <lb/>The fermionic anharmonic oscillator (FAO) is the zero spatial realization of the <lb/>Hubbard model [2] describing the itinerant magnetism. It is known in the Theory <lb/></body>

			<front> 1 E-mail: GFIMTT@BRUFEBITNET <lb/>2 E-mail: PIZA@USPIE1EUSEBR <lb/>0378-437 l/95/$09.50 (~) 1995 Elsevier Science B.V. All rights reserved <lb/> SSDI 0378-437 1 (95)00100-X <lb/></front>

			<page> 238 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> M.T. Thomaz, A.ER. de Toledo Piza/Physica A 218 (1995) 237-244 <lb/></note>

			<body> of Magnetism as the limit of zero band width. Due to the anti-commutation relations <lb/>satisfied by the fermionic field operators, the FAO is a soluble model [3]. Even though <lb/>this model is exactly soluble the aim of this article is to show that its approximate <lb/>treatment allows one to associate to it a classical dynamic of a Hamiltonian system. In <lb/>the general initial condition problem we study the dynamical evolution under the FAO <lb/>dynamics of a given initial condition. Restricting ourselves to the extended mean field <lb/>approximation we have to consider the pairing correlation effect and the Bogoliubov <lb/>transformation is used to diagonalize the generalized matrix operator. In general the <lb/>Hartree-Fock-Bogoliubov (HFB) mean field does better than the usual HF mean field <lb/>in describing the many-body dynamics since it is able to take into account pairing <lb/>correlation effects. In the case of the present model we find in fact that it reproduces <lb/>the  exact  dynamics of the system. The same is not true for the plain HF mean field, <lb/>however. Also the HFB dynamics is not exact if applied to higher spatial dimensionality <lb/>versions of the model. These facts can be taken as a characterization of the dynamical <lb/>simplicity of the FAO. <lb/>All the one-particle information about a given many-body system is contained in the <lb/>one-particle density matrix and in the pairing tensor, whose expressions are respectively <lb/> [4] <lb/> Aij(t)  = Tr[a~aiU(t) ], <lb/>(la) <lb/>and <lb/> Ilij( t) = Tr[aiaj.~( t)  ], <lb/>(lb) <lb/>where a[ and  aj are respectively the fermionic creation and destruction operators asso-<lb/>ciated to the basis of one-particle state vectors. These operators satisfy usual fermionic <lb/>anti-commutation relations. <lb/>Let U(t) be the full density matrix of the system of identical fermionic particles. <lb/>When .7-(t) involves a coherent superposition of states that differ by two particles, the <lb/>pairing tensor does not vanish identically. The Bogoliubov transformation is then used <lb/>to define the quasi-particle operators [4] <lb/> A~ ( t)  = ~~[ o)ji( t)a ~ -k- Zji( t)aj]. <lb/> (2a) <lb/> J <lb/> They must also satisfy the usual fermionic anti-commutation relations and in the new <lb/>one-quasi-particle basis we have <lb/> Tr[ AJ ( t) Ai( t)~( t) ] = pia ( t)~ij, <lb/> (2b) <lb/>and <lb/> Tr[Aj(t)Ai(t)~(t)  ] = 0. <lb/>(2c) <lb/>The eigenvalues  pia(t)  give the average population in the quasi-particle state vector <lb/>a~(t) 10(t))a, where 10(t))a is the vacuum state of the quasi-particle operators. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> M.T. Thomaz, A.ER. de Toledo Piza/Physica A 218 (1995) 237-244 <lb/></note>

			<page> 239 <lb/></page>

			<body> Eqs. (2a) to (2c) can be related to the generalized density matrix [4] <lb/>(Art, <lb/>-Hn,, ) <lb/>(3) <lb/> 7-~tl, = H~l, Ill,  -- All, &apos; <lb/> which is a Hermitian and can be diagonalized by a similarity transformation <lb/>W+RW = N. <lb/>(4) <lb/>In the view of block structure of ~, the matrices W and N are of the form <lb/>(,~ <lb/>Z*) <lb/> W= <lb/> Z* <lb/>f~ <lb/>&apos; <lb/>(5a) <lb/> and <lb/> (po) <lb/> N= <lb/>0 1 -p <lb/>&apos; <lb/>p being a diagonal matrix. The elements of the matrix II are the coefficients  o~ij  of Eq. <lb/>(2a) and the elements of Z are the coefficients  zij  in the same equation. <lb/>The dynamical evolution of one-quasi-particle operators is obtained by taking the time <lb/>derivative of Eq. (4), i.e. <lb/>WtT~W = N + [N, Wtw]. <lb/>(6a) <lb/>Using the Bogoliubov transformation we get <lb/>W~7~ w  = (Tr(A~,(t)Al(t).~(t)) <lb/>Tr(Al,(t)Al(t).~(t)))  . <lb/>(6b) <lb/> Tr(A],(t)a~(t):P(t)) Tr(Al,(t)A~(t).~(t)) <lb/> The time derivative of the density matrix be(t) is given by the Liouville-von Neuman <lb/>equation <lb/> i~&apos;(t)  = [H, be(t)], <lb/>(7) <lb/>where H is the Hamiltonian of the identical fermionic system. In general it is not possible <lb/>to have the exact evolution of the density matrix operator be(t). We can however use <lb/>the projector operator method [5] to get an approximation to .T&apos;(t). Let us write be(t) <lb/> as <lb/> .T&apos;(t) = ~&apos;0(/) + .T&quot;(t), <lb/>(8) <lb/>where be0(t) contains the complete information of one-quasi-particle operators, <lb/>A/A/(t) = Tr [AJ(t)Ai(t).Y&apos;o(t)]  = p~(t)~ij, <lb/> (9a) <lb/> n}(t)  = Tr  [Aj(t)Ai(t)~&apos;o(t)]  = 0, <lb/>(9b) <lb/>the two-quasi-particle density is now approximated by <lb/></body>

			<page> 240 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> M.T. Thomaz, A.ER. de Toledo Piza/Physica A 218 (1995) 237-244 <lb/></note>

			<body> Tr  (A~ (t)AJ(t)At(t)Ak(t)~o(t)) =  Tr  (A~ (t)Ak(t)~o(t))  Tr  (h~(t)&amp;(t)~o(t)) <lb/> -Tr (,~  (t)&amp;(t)~o(t))Tr (AJ(t),~k(t)~o(t)), <lb/> (9c) <lb/>and finally we impose that Tr()r(t)) = Tr(Or0(t)) = 1. <lb/>The expression of .Yb(t) for a system of identical fermions that satisfies Eqs. (9a)-<lb/>(9c) is known [61 and it is equal to <lb/> a~o(t) = H [ pia(t)A~(t)Ai(&apos;) +  (1-p/~(t))Ai(t)A~(t)], <lb/>(10) <lb/> i <lb/> where  pia(t) are  the eigenvalues of Eq. (2b) and the product is over the different states <lb/>of one-quasi-particle (natural states). <lb/>~0(t) gives the HFB approximation. It is entirely determined by mean values of <lb/>one-particle observables and therefore corresponds to the Gaussian projection of the full <lb/>density ~(t). It is simple to show that in this mean field approximation, in which F(t) <lb/>is constrained, to have the form ~0(t) at all times, one has <lb/>l~(t) =0, <lb/>(,,) <lb/>so that this approximation gives constant population in each quasi-particle state. Using <lb/>the techniques of Refs. [5] and [7] one could moreover include many-body correlation <lb/>effects, but this further development will not be needed in the present context. <lb/>Now we specialize the HFB approximation to the fermionic anharmonic oscillator for <lb/>which the Hamiltonian is [3] <lb/>It <lb/>o=TA <lb/>and as and a~ are spin 1/2 fermionic operators satisfying the usual anti-commutation <lb/>relations. <lb/>As stated before, the FAO can be seen as a version of the Hubbard model [2] in zero <lb/>spatial dimension, or is better known in the literature as the limit of zero band width of <lb/>the Hubbard model. In analogy with this model one can think of U as representing a <lb/>&quot;repulsive interaction&quot; between the fermions and ,~B as describing the coupling of the <lb/>fermion magnetic moment to an external magnetic field. <lb/>We use for the initial state of the system a state vector of the most general form, <lb/>namely <lb/> [,I,) = ~(pl + <lb/>(13) <lb/> where the coefficients p, fl, otand T are complex numbers and the normalization con-<lb/>stant N is: N = Ipl 2 + [ill 2 + 1412 + I~&apos;l e. This general initial state involves a coherent <lb/>superposition of states with different number of particles. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> M.T. Thomaz, A.ER. de Toledo Piza/Physica A 218 (1995) 237-244 <lb/></note>

			<page> 241 <lb/></page>

			<body> The index j in the sum in Eq. (2a) assumes the values 3 1 and 2, and the matrix W <lb/>involves sixteen parameters. Due to the fact that W is a unitary matrix and taking its <lb/>block structure into account we find that we need in fact only four independent param-<lb/>eters to define the Bogoliubov transformation (2a). In terms of these four parameters, <lb/>the matrices ~ and Z become <lb/>and <lb/>cosy(t) cosG(t) <lb/> [~(t) = e i¢(t)  siny(t) cosG(t) <lb/> -e -i~°(t)  sin y(t) cosG(t) <lb/>cosy(t) cos so(t) <lb/>J <lb/> e iO(t)  sin y(t) sinG(t) <lb/>Z(t) =  -ei(°(&apos;)-~°(t))cosy(t)  sinG(t) <lb/>(14a) <lb/> e i(O(t)-~(t))  cosy(t) sin~:(t) &quot;~ <lb/> ei(°(t)-2~(t))siny(t)  sinG(t) ] &quot; <lb/>(14b) <lb/>We get the dynamical evolution of the parameters y(t), G(t),  O(t)  and ~p(t) through <lb/>Eqs. (6) and (7). In the Hartree-Fock-Bogoliubov approximation .T&apos;(t) in Eq. (6b) is <lb/>replaced by 5r0(t) whose expression is given by Eq. (10). <lb/>Due to the block structure of W and to the fact that N is a diagonal matrix, Eq. (6a) <lb/>in the Hartree-Fock-Bogoliubov approximation becomes <lb/>( <lb/>Tr([ A~A/, H]Y0(t)) <lb/> Tr([AtAi, lt]:Fo(t))) <lb/>(WtY~(t)W(t))it = -i <lb/> -(Tr([a~at,I-I]Uo(t)))* <lb/> -Tr([a~a.H]Uo(t)) <lb/> (p+[p,~tIl+ZfZ] <lb/>{p,~tZ* + Ztl)*}. ~tZ*. Z*[I* ) <lb/> = Zril+(~rZ_{p, Zril+(ZVZ} <lb/> -0-tp, ZrZ +l~rn ] <lb/>• <lb/> (]5) <lb/> To write the Hamiltonian H in terms of quasi-particle operators At and A~ we use <lb/>the fact that W is a unitary matrix. The calculation of Tr( [A~Ai, H]~0) shows that this <lb/>object is proportional to the difference (p~ -p/~) and therefore only the off-diagonal <lb/>terms are relevant in general. From the fact that the quasi-particle operators  At  and <lb/>A~ satisfy the usual fermionic anti-commutation relations, only Tr([AIA2,H]~0) is <lb/>different from zero. The time evolution of one-quasi-particle operators for the FAO in <lb/>the Hartree-Fock-Bogoliubov approximation appears therefore in terms of parameters <lb/> y(t), G(t), O(t)  and q,(t) as <lb/> Tr([a~(t)A,(t),H]Uo(t))=-AsB(p~-p~)sin(2a(t))e <lb/>-i÷(t), <lb/> (16a) <lb/>and <lb/>Tr  ([,~2(t)Al(t),H].Fo(t))  = ½(1 -p~ -p~) (2hw + U) <lb/> x sin(2fl(t))e -i(°(t)-~(t)). <lb/> (16b) <lb/>Since the matrix p is diagonal, for any matrix A, the commutator [p, A] has only <lb/>off-diagonal terms. Therefore, <lb/> 3 For the sake of simplicity we are redefining the indices of the ferrnionic operators: cr =T~ 1 and o-=l==-2. <lb/></body>

			<page> 242 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> M.T. Thomaz, A.ER. de Toledo Piza/Physica A 218 (1995) 237-244 <lb/></note>

			<body> lb(t) = 0, <lb/>(17) <lb/>and then the eigenvalues p/a, i = 1,2, are time independent. To get the values of the <lb/>p/a we recall that the columns of W(t) are the eigenvectors of matrix 7¢(t) with <lb/>eigenvalues p/a and (1 -p/a), i = 1,2. In particular for t = 0 we relate the average <lb/>population number p/a of each quasi-state i and the constants p, fl, a, 7-that characterize <lb/>the initial state vector, <lb/>p~ = 1  - ]p[2c°s2 ~o -b [I&quot;[2 sin 2 ~o + [pz[ sinZq~ <lb/>N <lb/>&apos; <lb/>(18a) <lb/>and <lb/>pa = I~&apos;[ 2 c°s2 ~o + [pl 2 sin 2 tp + cos(n~)Ip&apos;r[ sin 2~ <lb/>N <lb/>&apos; <lb/>(18b) <lb/>with tan(2~,) =  21~pl/(llpp 2- 17/21),  where n =0 for IPl &gt; I~&apos;1 and n = 1 for IPl &lt; I~&apos;l-<lb/>Eq. (15) now gives equations of motion for the parameters ~,(t), so(t), O(t) and ~o(t). <lb/>They read <lb/> -i~ • <lb/>~.d(cosycosl~) <lb/> -e <lb/>smycosg <lb/> + cosycos~ d(e-i~sinyc°s() <lb/>dt <lb/>dt <lb/>+e i(O-~) cos ~ sin fl d(e-i° sin y sin s ¢) <lb/> dt <lb/>-e i(°-2~) sin y sin ~&quot; d(e-i(°-~) cos y sin () <lb/> dt <lb/> = <lb/> -i,~nB sin(2y) e -i~, <lb/>(19a) <lb/>and <lb/> e--i(O--tp) COS y sin ~&quot; d(cos y cos s c ) <lb/> dt <lb/>-e i~ sin y cos ~ d(e-i° sin y sin s c) <lb/> dt <lb/> = ½i(2/ko + U) sin(2()e -i(°-~). <lb/> + e-i(°-2~) sin y sin s ¢ d (e-i~° sin y cos ~:) <lb/> dt <lb/> -cos y cos ~ d(e-i(°-¢) cos y sin g) <lb/> dt <lb/> (19b) <lb/>Equating separately the real and imaginary parts of Eqs. (19a)-(19b) we obtain <lb/>finally <lb/>and <lb/>~,(t) = O, <lb/>(20a) <lb/>~(t) = O, <lb/>(20b) <lb/> O(t) = 2ABB + 2hw + U, <lb/> (20c) <lb/> (o( t ) = 2haB. <lb/> (20d) <lb/>The above equations of motion are equivalent to the classical system of two spins. To <lb/>see this we define conjugate momenta of variables O(t) and ~o(t), <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> M.T. Thomaz, A.ER. de Toledo Piza/Physica A 218 (1995) 237-244 <lb/></note>

			<page> 243 <lb/></page>

			<body> jo(t)  =cosy(t), <lb/>(21a) <lb/>and <lb/> j~(t)  =cos~(t). <lb/>(21b) <lb/>The Hamiltonian <lb/> H = 2AsB(j¢ +jo) +  (2/-uo +  U)jo <lb/> (22) <lb/>gives the same equation of motion as (20a)-(20d). The Hamiltonian (22) describes <lb/>the paired mean-field dynamics of the FAO. It has the form of the action-angle classical <lb/>Hamiltonian for two precessing angular momenta of magnitude one. The action variables <lb/> jo  and j¢ represent in this picture the projections of the angular momenta on the axis <lb/>around which the precession takes place, while 0 and q~ are the precession angles. The <lb/>angles y and s c are of course just the colatitudes of the precessing angular momenta. <lb/>As can be easily checked from Eqs. (2a) and (14a)-(14b), the angles y and q~ are <lb/>associated with a spatial rotation of the original basis a] while ~: and 0 are related to <lb/>the Bogoliubov transformation which accounts for the pairing correlations. Furthermore, <lb/>it is straightforward to check that, in the case of the FAO, the time evolution of the <lb/>extended density which corresponds to the c-number dynamics given by Hamiltonian <lb/>Eq. (22) in fact  coincides  with that which corresponds to the full quantum evolution <lb/>of the inital state under the Hamiltonian of Eq. (12). The latter is trivially obtained <lb/>in this case since Eq. (13), as it stands, is written in the form of an expansion in <lb/>energy eigenstates. The time-dependent HFB mean field dynamics is therefore  exact  in <lb/>this case. This would not have been the case, should one have restricted oneself to the <lb/>HF approximation, since the pairing dynamics associated with s c and 0 would then be <lb/>absent. <lb/>We have therefore shown that the time-dependent Hartree-Fock-Bogoliubov approxi-<lb/>mation to the fennionic anharmonic oscillator produces exact results and can be studied <lb/>in terms of this simple classical Hamiltonian model. The anti-commutative nature of <lb/>underlying fermionic variables is of course involving two action (angle) variables fully <lb/>taken into account. <lb/>To study the dynamical evolution of the Hubbard model in one or more space di-<lb/>mensions under a general initial condition problem, we certainly need to go beyond <lb/>the Hartree-Fock-Bogoliubov approximation. The projection method [5] provides for <lb/>the necessary framework within which the mean field treatment described here can be <lb/>extended to include correlation effects beyond those incorporated through paring effects <lb/> [7]. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgements <lb/> M.T.T. thanks CNPq and FINEP for partial financial support. <lb/></div>

			<page> 244 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> M.T. Thomaz, A.ER. de Toledo Piza/Physica A 218 (1995) 237-244 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] A.K. Kerman and S.E. Koonin, Ann. of Phys. 100 (1976) 332. <lb/>[2] J. Hubbard, Proc. Roy. Soc. A 277 (1963) 237; 281 (1964) 401. <lb/>[3] W. Nolting, Quantentheorie des Magnetismus (Teubner, Stuttgart, 1986), pp. 228; <lb/>S.M. de Souza, S. Moss de Oliveira and M.T. Thomaz, Am. J. Phys. 60 (1992) 1122; <lb/>M.C.D. Barrozo, M.T. Thomaz and A.ER. de Toledo Piza, Dynamical Evolution of a Fermionic <lb/>Anharmonic Oscillator, accepted for publication in Am. J. Phys. <lb/>[41 E Ring and P, Schuck, The Nuclear Many-Body Problem (Springer, New York, 1980), pp. 245-248 and <lb/>251-252. <lb/>[51 C.R. Willis and R.H. Picard, Phys. Rev. A 9 (1974) 1343; 16 (1977) 1625; <lb/>M.C. Nemes and A.ER. de Toledo Piza, Phys. Rev. C 27 (1983) 862; Physica A 137 (1986) 367. <lb/>[6] J. Des Cloiseaux, Many-Body Physics, C. de Witt and R. Balian, eds. (Gordon and Breach, London, <lb/>1968), pp. 5. <lb/>[7] A.ER. de Toledo Piza and Chi-Yong Lin, Proceedings of the International Conference on Many-Body <lb/>Physics, C. Fiolhais, M. Fiolhais, C. Sousa and J.N. Urbano, eds. (World Scientific, Singapore, 1994), <lb/>pp. 277. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
