<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage> This content has been downloaded from IOPscience. Please scroll down to see the full text. <lb/>Download details: <lb/>IP Address: 188.184.3.52 <lb/>This content was downloaded on 22/02/2015 at 22:32 <lb/>Please note that terms and conditions apply. <lb/> Experimental evidences for low-lying octupole isovector states <lb/> View the table of contents for this issue, or go to the journal homepage for more <lb/>2012 J. Phys.: Conf. Ser. 366 012040 <lb/>(http://iopscience.iop.org/1742-6596/366/1/012040) <lb/>Home Search Collections Journals About Contact us My IOPscience <lb/></titlePage>

			<front> Experimental evidences for low-lying octupole <lb/>isovector states <lb/> M Scheck <lb/> Institut für Kernphysik, TU Darmstadt, D-64289 Darmstadt, Germany <lb/>E-mail: mscheck@ikp.tu-darmstadt.de <lb/> Abstract. An evaluation of data obtained with the (n, n <lb/> ′  γ) technique revealed in near <lb/>spherical nuclei strong M1 components in transitions connecting higher-lying 3 <lb/> − <lb/> i  states with the <lb/>3 <lb/> − <lb/> 1  state. The ⟨3 <lb/> − <lb/> 1  |M 1|3 <lb/> − <lb/> i  ⟩ matrix elements of these transitions are in the order of 1 µN . In the <lb/>quadrupole sector strong ⟨2 <lb/> + <lb/>1  |M 1|2 <lb/> + <lb/> ms  ⟩ matrix elements serve as fingerprints for the identification <lb/>of low-lying 2 <lb/> + <lb/> ms  isovector states, which are commonly referred to as mixed-symmetry states. <lb/>The ratio of the two matrix elements scales for most candidates to unity indicating similar <lb/>physics. Additional evidence for the assignment of the 3 <lb/> − <lb/> i  states as low-lying octupole isovector <lb/>states is provided by particle-scattering experiments, e.g. (e, e <lb/> ′  ) or (p, p <lb/> ′  ). The octupole states <lb/>under investigation exhibit enhanced scattering cross sections. This observation is in accordance <lb/>with the assignment of a one-phonon nature to these octupole excitations. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> Low-lying isovector states, such as the 1  +  Scissors mode in deformed nuclei [1, 2] or the 2  + <lb/> ms <lb/> state [3, 4] in near spherical nuclei, continue to have impact on the understanding of low-energy <lb/>nuclear structure physics. The importance of these kind of nuclear excitations is based on the <lb/>fact, that their observation yields direct experimental information about the strength of the <lb/>isovector (proton-neutron) part of the nuclear interaction. The existence of isovector states is a <lb/>feature of the nucleus as a two-component quantum system. From a more general perspective, <lb/>these class of excitations can be seen as the anti-symmetric coupling of proton and neutron <lb/>subsystems. Similar excitations have been observed in other two-component quantum systems, <lb/>as for example quantum dots [2]. <lb/>Low-lying quadrupole isovector, in the language of the IBA [5] so-called mixed-symmetry, <lb/>states are well established. Currently, their fine details are subject to experimental and <lb/>theoretical work. Therefore, nowadays, the theoretical description often uses microscopic models, <lb/>such as the shell model [6] (e.g. see ref. [7]) or the Quasiparticle-Phonon Model (QPM) [8] (see <lb/>ref. [9] and references therein). However, the sdf-IBA-2 predicts low-lying isovector excitations <lb/>for the octupole degree of freedom [10] as well. Within the U (1) ⊗ U (5) ⊗ U (7) limit of the <lb/>spf-IBA-2 the experimental signature of these octupole mixed-symmetry states is a strong M1 <lb/>transition to the first excited 3 <lb/> − <lb/> 1  state: <lb/> B(M 1, 3 <lb/> − <lb/> ms  → 3 <lb/> − <lb/> 1  ) = <lb/>9 <lb/> π <lb/> (g <lb/> ′ <lb/> π  − g <lb/> ′ <lb/> ν  ) <lb/> 2  N  π  N  ν <lb/> N <lb/>. <lb/> (1) <lb/>Thus, the strength of the M1 transition connecting the two 3  −  states only depends of the proton <lb/>(π) or neutron (ν) g-factors, g  ′ <lb/> ρ  (ρ = π or ν), the number of neutron and proton bosons, N  ρ  , and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> XIX International School on Nuclear Physics, Neutron Physics and Applications <lb/>IOP Publishing <lb/>Journal of Physics: Conference Series 366 (2012) 012040 <lb/>doi:10.1088/1742-6596/366/1/012040 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> Published under licence by IOP Publishing Ltd <lb/></note>

			<page> 1 <lb/></page>

			<body> 2 <lb/> + <lb/> 2 <lb/> 4 1 <lb/> + <lb/>2 1 <lb/> + <lb/>3 1 <lb/> − <lb/>3 <lb/>− <lb/> 2 <lb/> [MeV] <lb/> E <lb/> 0 1 <lb/> + <lb/>2 <lb/>+ <lb/> 3 <lb/> 0 − <lb/> 0.39 <lb/> 0.56 <lb/> 1 − <lb/>2 − <lb/> 60 <lb/>16 <lb/>26 <lb/>9.6 <lb/>2.2 <lb/> Figure 1. Partial level scheme of  94  Mo: E2 transitions are marked with blue arrows, E1 <lb/>transitions with green arrows and M1 transitions with dashed, red arrows. The thickness of the <lb/>arrows is for each multipolarity proportional to the strength of the transition. The numbers give <lb/>the B(πL, J  π  → (J  π  )  ′  ) strength in units of W.u. (E2) and µ  2 <lb/> N  (M1). Data are taken from [11]. <lb/>the total number of bosons, N = N  ν  + N  π  . However, the prediction of the excitation energy, <lb/>where the isovector-octupole states are expected is vaguely given as above 3.5 MeV. <lb/>As long as particle-hole excitations over a shell closure can be excluded, the microscopic <lb/>structure of octupole excitations is dominated by particle-hole excitations including the unique <lb/>parity intruder subshell. The latter is a necessary condition for a negative parity excitation. <lb/>Therefore, in the low-energy regime octupole excitations have, compared to quadrupole states, <lb/>the advantage that less microscopic configurations are available. This lower density of two-<lb/>quasiparticle excitations near the Fermi surface results in much simpler wavefunctions. Nuclei, <lb/>for which the Fermi levels of protons as well as neutrons are situated between the intruding <lb/>unique-parity subshell and the subshell three units lower in total (j) and orbital (l) angular <lb/>momentum, exhibit enhanced effects associated with the octupole degree of freedom [12]. The <lb/>main signatures for enhanced octupole collectivity are a low-lying first excited 3 <lb/> − <lb/> 1  state and a <lb/>high B(E3, 0  + <lb/> gs  → 3 <lb/> − <lb/> 1  ) value. Near spherical nuclei in such mass regions (Z or N ≈ 34, 56, 88, 134) <lb/>are favorable cases to search for octupole-isovector excitations. <lb/> 2. Evaluated data and discussion <lb/> An evaluation of data sets obtained in inelastic neutron scattering (INS) experiments [13] <lb/>revealed for several nuclei near the N=50, Z=50, and N=82 shell closures higher-lying 3  −  states, <lb/>which decay via strong M1 transitions to the first excited 3 <lb/> − <lb/> 1  state. <lb/>The INS technique represents one of the most powerful experimental tools for the investigation <lb/>of the low-energy level scheme of stable nuclei [14]. This spectroscopic complete tool allows <lb/>for the determination of transition energies, branching ratios, and γ-ray angular distributions. <lb/>Consequently, it is possible to deduce level energies, level spins and multipole-mixing ratios. <lb/>The use of mono-energetic neutrons, as it is successfully done for decades at the University of <lb/>Kentucky, additionally allows the application of the Doppler-shift attenuation method (DSAM) <lb/>[15] to determine level lifetimes and, therefore, in combination with the other observables also <lb/>absolute transition probabilities. <lb/>The limitations of INS are given by the maximum angular momentum transfer of six units <lb/>and by the excitation energy range, from which on the level density becomes too high. The <lb/>latter results in a lower excitation cross section for the individual states, what results in low <lb/> γ-ray yields and in crowded spectra with a large number of overlapping peaks. This drawback <lb/>led to considerable uncertainties in the data sets discussed in this contribution. <lb/>States that were identified by having a strong M1 component in their 3 <lb/> − <lb/> i  → 3 <lb/> − <lb/> 1  transition to <lb/>be a candidate for an isovector octupole excitation are listed in table I of ref. [13]. Uncertainties <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> XIX International School on Nuclear Physics, Neutron Physics and Applications <lb/>IOP Publishing <lb/>Journal of Physics: Conference Series 366 (2012) 012040 <lb/>doi:10.1088/1742-6596/366/1/012040 <lb/></note>

			<page> 2 <lb/></page>

			<body> 0  1 <lb/> + <lb/>3 1 <lb/> − <lb/>3 − <lb/> 3 <lb/> 2 3 <lb/> + <lb/>3 − <lb/> 2 <lb/> 2 1 <lb/> + <lb/>4 1 <lb/> + <lb/>2 + <lb/> 2 <lb/> 2 4 <lb/> + <lb/> Nd <lb/> 144 <lb/> E <lb/> [MeV] <lb/>0 − <lb/>1 − <lb/>2 − <lb/>3 − <lb/> 0.15 <lb/> 0.18 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>0.09 <lb/> Figure 2. Partial level scheme of  144  Nd: E2 transitions are marked with blue arrows, E1 <lb/>transitions with green arrows and M1 transitions with dashed, red arrows. The thickness of the <lb/>arrows is for each multipolarity proportional to the strength of the transition. The numbers give <lb/>the B(M 1, J  π  → (J  π  )  ′  ) strength in units of µ  2 <lb/> N  . Data are taken from [16]. <lb/>in the evaluated data sets, due to the above mentioned reasons, are discussed extensively in the <lb/>given reference. Two examples of partial level schemes are shown in figures 1 and 2. While for <lb/> 94  Mo an additional E2 component exhausting 50 % of the B(E2, 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1  → 0  + <lb/> gs  ) strength indicates a <lb/>mixing of the octupole isovector excitation with the quadrupole-octupole coupled 3  −  two-phonon <lb/>state, the octupole isovector candidate (3 <lb/> − <lb/> 3  level) in  144  Nd exhibits only a small mixing with <lb/>the quadrupole-octupole coupled 3 <lb/> − <lb/> 2  state at 2605 keV. However, as later will be discussed, the <lb/>candidate in  92  Zr given in ref. [13] is not the state at 3039.8 keV. <lb/>For the two Cd isotopes, where candidates for isovector octupole excitations were assigned, <lb/>it should be mentioned, that an assignment of octupole isovector states based on strong M1 <lb/>transitions is not as trivial as it seems. Recent measurements of the B(E2, 0  + <lb/> gs  → 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1  ) strength <lb/>in light Sn isotopes (e.g. see ref. [17]) provided evidence for proton contributions in the <lb/>wavefunctions of their 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1  states. This observed weakening of the Z=50 shell closure allows for the <lb/>contribution of two-quasiparticle components containing the g  7/2  subshell in the wavefunction <lb/>of excited 3  −  states. The decay of such a 3  −  state to the first excited 3 <lb/> − <lb/> 1  state with components <lb/>containing the g  9/2  subshell in the wavefunctions results in strong spin-flip M1 transitions. <lb/>The ratio of the M1 matrix element connecting the 3 <lb/> − <lb/> IV  octupole isovector candidate and <lb/>the first excited 3 <lb/> − <lb/> 1  state and the M1 matrix element connecting the 2  + <lb/> ms  quadrupole mixed <lb/>symmetry state and the first excited 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1  state scale for almost all candidates to unity. The <lb/>comparable strengths of the matrix elements indicate similar physics. <lb/>Besides the first evidence provided by the strong M1 components in the 3 <lb/> − <lb/> i  → 3 <lb/> − <lb/> 1  transitions, <lb/>an evaluation of data sets obtained in light-particle scattering experiments, such as (p, p  ′  ) and <lb/>(e, e  ′  ), provides additional evidence. These data sets exhibit enhanced cross sections for the <lb/>direct excitation of the candidates. As the isovector octupole excitations are one-phonon states a <lb/>relatively high excitation probability can be expected. Two exemplary spectra obtained with the <lb/>(p, p  ′  ) reaction measured using 200 MeV protons at iThemba Labs (RSA) are shown in figure 3. <lb/>Indeed, the excitation probability for the candidate in  94  Mo is, next to the 3 <lb/> − <lb/> 1  symmetric octupole <lb/>phonon, the only excited 3  −  state with a noteworthy cross section. The ratio of the maximum <lb/>scatting cross sections measured in this experiment for the excitation of the first 3 <lb/> − <lb/> 1  state and <lb/>the candidate for the isovector excitation are presented in table 1. Additionally, the ratio of <lb/>the 2  + <lb/> ms  quadrupole mixed-symmetry state and the first excited 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1  state is given. Furthermore, <lb/>the ratios of the excitation probabilities for  144  Nd, as obtained in (p, p  ′  ), (d, d  ′  ) [18] and (e, e  ′  ) <lb/>experiments [19], are presented. Indeed, the enhanced excitation strength from the ground state <lb/>indicates an one-phonon nature for the proposed candidates. For  92  Zr the results of the (p, p  ′  ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> XIX International School on Nuclear Physics, Neutron Physics and Applications <lb/>IOP Publishing <lb/>Journal of Physics: Conference Series 366 (2012) 012040 <lb/>doi:10.1088/1742-6596/366/1/012040 <lb/></note>

			<page> 3 <lb/></page>

			<body> 92 <lb/> 92 <lb/>94 <lb/>94 <lb/>C.M. <lb/> Θ <lb/> =9.7 o <lb/> C.M. <lb/> Θ <lb/> =9.7 o <lb/> C.M. <lb/> Θ <lb/> =25.9 <lb/>o <lb/> C.M. <lb/> Θ <lb/> =25.9 <lb/>o <lb/> 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> 3 <lb/> − <lb/>1 <lb/> 3 <lb/> − <lb/>1 <lb/> 3 <lb/> − <lb/>1 <lb/> 3 <lb/> − <lb/>1 <lb/> 3 <lb/> − <lb/>2 <lb/> 3 <lb/> − <lb/>2 <lb/> 3 <lb/> − <lb/>3 <lb/> 3 <lb/> − <lb/>3 <lb/> 2 <lb/> + <lb/>ms <lb/> 2 <lb/> + <lb/>ms <lb/> 2 <lb/> + <lb/>ms <lb/> 2 <lb/> + <lb/>ms <lb/> Zr(p,p&apos;)@200MeV <lb/>Zr(p,p&apos;)@200MeV <lb/>Mo(p,p&apos;)@200MeV <lb/>Mo(p,p&apos;)@200MeV <lb/> Energy [keV] <lb/>Counts <lb/> Figure 3. Spectra of  92  Zr and  94  Mo as measured in the (p, p  ′  ) reaction using 200 MeV protons <lb/>at iThemba labs (RSA). Figure is taken from [20]. <lb/>measurement qualify a state at 3450 keV as isovector octupole excitation, not as stated in [13] <lb/>the state at 3039.8 keV. In the (n, n  ′  γ) reaction [21] at 3452 keV a level with a transition to <lb/>the 3 <lb/> − <lb/> 1  state was observed. However, for two of the four transition depopulating this level to <lb/>states with a firmly assigned positive parity a multipole-mixing ratio with values deviating from <lb/>zero was measured. The latter indicates a positive parity of the state observed in the (n, n  ′  γ) <lb/> experiment. Nevertheless, a scenario with two degenerated levels, one with positive and one <lb/>with negative parity, is possible. Certainly, further experimental investigations are necessary to <lb/>clarify the situation. <lb/> Table 1. Ratios of selected quantities from light-particle scattering experiments. The same <lb/>ratios as presented for the first excited 3  −  state and the 3 <lb/> − <lb/> IV  octupole isovector candidate are <lb/>given for the first 2  +  state and the firmly identified 2  +  mixed-symmetry state(s). For  144  Nd the <lb/>summed B(E2) strength for the two fragments of the mixed-symmetry state were considered. <lb/>Nucleus <lb/>Method <lb/>Octupole <lb/>Quadrupole <lb/>Reference <lb/> 92  Zr <lb/>(p, p  ′  ) <lb/> σ(3 <lb/> − <lb/> 1  )max <lb/> σ(3 <lb/> − <lb/> IV  )max <lb/> = 8.7 <lb/> σ(2 <lb/> + <lb/>1  )max <lb/> σ(2 <lb/> + <lb/> IV  )max <lb/> = 4.0 <lb/>[20] <lb/> 94  Mo <lb/>(p, p  ′  ) <lb/> σ(3 <lb/> − <lb/> 1  )max <lb/> σ(3 <lb/> − <lb/> IV  )max <lb/> = 20.5 <lb/> σ(2 <lb/> + <lb/>1  )max <lb/> σ(2 <lb/> + <lb/> ms  )max <lb/> = 13.2 <lb/>[20] <lb/> 144  Nd <lb/>(p, p  ′  ), ((d, d  ′  ) <lb/> B(E3,0  +  →3 <lb/> − <lb/> 1  ) <lb/> B(E3,0  +  →3 <lb/> − <lb/> IV  ) <lb/> = 4.7(7) <lb/> B(E2,0  +  →2 <lb/> + <lb/>1  ) <lb/> B(E2,0  +  →2 <lb/> + <lb/> ms  ) <lb/> = 9.4(15) <lb/>[19] <lb/>(e, e  ′  ) <lb/> B(E3,0  +  →3 <lb/> − <lb/> 1  ) <lb/> B(E3,0  +  →3 <lb/> − <lb/> IV  ) <lb/> = 5.8(12) <lb/> B(E2,0  +  →2 <lb/> + <lb/>1  ) <lb/> B(E2,0  +  →2 <lb/> + <lb/> ms  ) <lb/> = 8.1(10) <lb/>[18] <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> XIX International School on Nuclear Physics, Neutron Physics and Applications <lb/>IOP Publishing <lb/>Journal of Physics: Conference Series 366 (2012) 012040 <lb/>doi:10.1088/1742-6596/366/1/012040 <lb/></note>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<body> 3. Summary <lb/> Data sets of near spherical nuclei, obtained with the (n, n  ′  γ) technique, reveal strong M1 <lb/>components in 3 <lb/> − <lb/> i  → 3 <lb/> − <lb/> 1  transitions. For several of the 3 <lb/> − <lb/> i  states light-particle scattering <lb/>experiments exhibit enhanced excitation cross sections from the ground state. The two <lb/>experimental features are with respect to the first excited 3  −  state in the order of magnitude as <lb/>observed for the combination of 2  + <lb/> ms  quadrupole mixed-symmetry state and the 2 <lb/> + <lb/>1  quadrupole <lb/>phonon. The possibility of assigning the 3 <lb/> − <lb/> i  states as candidates for isovector octupole excitations <lb/>was discussed. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> 4. Acknowledgments <lb/> Financial support from the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft under Grant SFB 634 is gratefully <lb/>acknowledged. Furthermore, the author appreciated stimulating discussions with P. A. Butler, <lb/>C. Fransen, K. Heyde, N. Pietralla, G. Rainovski, V. Werner, and S. W. Yates. The author is <lb/>indebted to the courtesy of C. Walz allowing the use of his data prior to publication. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] Bohle D et al. 1984 Phys. Lett. 137B 27 <lb/>[2] Heyde K, von Neumann Cosel P and Richter A 2010 Rev. Mod. Phys. 82 2365 <lb/>[3] Iachello F 1984 Phys. Rev. Lett. 53 1427 <lb/>[4] Pietralla N von Brentano P and Lisetzky A F 2008 Prog. Part. Nucl. Phys. 60 225 <lb/>[5] Iachello F and Arima A 2006 The interacting boson model (Cambridge University Press) <lb/>[6] Heyde K L G 1994 The nuclear shell model (Berlin Heidelberg Springer Verlag) <lb/>[7] Holt J D et al. 2007 Phys. Rev. C 76 034325 <lb/>[8] Soloviev V G 1992 Theory of Atomic Nuclei Quasiparticles and Phonons (London: IOP Publishing Ltd) <lb/>[9] Lo Iudice N, Stoyanov Ch and Pietralla N 2009 Phys. Rev. C 80 024311 <lb/>[10] Smirnova N A et al. 2000 Nucl. Phys. A 678 235 <lb/>[11] Fransen C et al. 2003 Phys. Rev. C 67 024307 <lb/>[12] Butler P A and Nazarewicz W 1996 Rev. Mod. Phys. 68 349 <lb/>[13] Scheck M et al. 2010 Phys. Rev. C 81 064305 <lb/>[14] Garrett P E, Warr N and Yates S W 2000 J. Res. Natl. Inst. Stand. Technol. 105 141 <lb/>[15] Belgya T, Molàr G and Yates S W 1996 Nucl. Phys. A 607 43 <lb/>[16] Hicks S et al. 1998 Phys. Rev. C 98 2264 <lb/>[17] Ekström A at al. 2008 Phys. Rev. Lett. 101 012502 <lb/>[18] Perrino R et al. 1993 Nucl. Phys. A 561 343 <lb/>[19] Pignanelli M et al. 1993 Nucl. Phys. A 559 1 <lb/>[20] Walz C 2010 Master Thesis, TU Darmstadt unpublished <lb/>[21] Fransen C et al. 2005 Phys. Rev. C 71 054304 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> XIX International School on Nuclear Physics, Neutron Physics and Applications <lb/>IOP Publishing <lb/>Journal of Physics: Conference Series 366 (2012) 012040 <lb/>doi:10.1088/1742-6596/366/1/012040 <lb/></note>

			<page> 5 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
