<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage> This content has been downloaded from IOPscience. Please scroll down to see the full text. <lb/>Download details: <lb/>IP Address: 137.138.124.224 <lb/>This content was downloaded on 13/04/2015 at 18:29 <lb/>Please note that terms and conditions apply. <lb/> Comment on &quot; Is radioactive decay really exponential? &quot; by Aston P. J. <lb/> View the table of contents for this issue, or go to the journal homepage for more <lb/>2013 EPL 101 42001 <lb/>(http://iopscience.iop.org/0295-5075/101/4/42001) <lb/>Home Search Collections Journals About Contact us My IOPscience <lb/></titlePage>

			<front> February 2013 <lb/> EPL, 101 (2013) 42001 <lb/> www.epljournal.org <lb/> doi: 10.1209/0295-5075/101/42001 <lb/> Comment <lb/> Comment on &quot; Is radioactive decay really exponential? &quot; <lb/>by Aston P. J. <lb/> Cleanthes A. Nicolaides <lb/> (a) <lb/> Theoretical and Physical Chemistry Institute, National Hellenic Research Foundation <lb/>48, Vasileos Constantinou Avenue, Athens, 11635 Greece, EU <lb/> received 23 October 2012; accepted in final form 8 February 2013 <lb/>published online 1 March 2013 <lb/> PACS  23.90.+w – Other topics in radioactive decay and in-beam spectroscopy <lb/> PACS  03.65.Sq – Quantum mechanics: Semiclassical theories and applications <lb/> PACS  02.30.Hq – Mathematical methods in physics: Ordinary differential equations <lb/> Copyright c <lb/> EPLA, 2013 <lb/></front>

			<body> An article published recently in this journal by Aston [1] <lb/>is titled &quot; Is radioactive decay really exponential? &quot; . This <lb/>intriguing title represents the essence of Aston&apos;s specu-<lb/>lative scenario as to the possible role of non-exponential <lb/>decay (NED) which has thus far been neglected in the <lb/>time-honored methodology of radioactive <lb/> 14  C dating. The <lb/>possible significance of resolving this issue is underlined <lb/>by Aston&apos;s statement: &quot; If the decay of <lb/> 14  C is indeed non-<lb/>exponential, then no other slowly decaying isotope can <lb/>be assumed to decay exponentially either, which would <lb/>remove a foundation stone of modern dating methods &quot; . <lb/>(See last section of [1].) <lb/>In this Comment, I provide theoretical results and <lb/>corresponding quantitative estimates which answer the <lb/>question in the affirmative. This conclusion implies <lb/>that the proposal presented in [1], concerning the <lb/>ostensible role of NED in radioactive carbon dating, is <lb/>untenable. <lb/> Criteria for NED. – Formalism in conjunction with <lb/>phenomenological models for nuclear and elementary <lb/>particle unstable states has revealed that there are three <lb/>principal regimes in the time-dependent curve of decay, <lb/> e.g., [2–4]: The dominant exponential decay (ED), the <lb/>short-time, pre-ED, NED and the long-time, post-ED, <lb/>NED. In the case of <lb/> 14  C, and of other long-lived nuclear <lb/>isotopes, (for <lb/> 14  C, the half-life is t  1/2  = 5730 years [5]) it <lb/>is easy to conclude that pre-ED and memory effects due <lb/>to its preparation are not at all significant. Therefore, the <lb/>focus regarding the possible measurable violation of ED <lb/>must be on long-time NED. <lb/>In order to establish the exact evolution of the decay <lb/>of <lb/> 14  C in terms of the probability of non-decay (survival), <lb/></body>

			<front> (a)  E-mail: caan@eie.gr <lb/></front>

			<body> P (t), one has to resort to theory, since its measurement <lb/>is not practical, even over one lifetime, τ . The standard <lb/>assumption about τ is that it is defined by e <lb/> −t/τ  , i.e., <lb/> by ED. P (t) is given by ||Ψ  0  |Ψ(t)| <lb/> 2  , where |Ψ(t) is the <lb/>exact solution of the time-dependent Schrödinger equation <lb/> (TDSE) from t = 0 to very long times, typically t  τ , <lb/>and Ψ  0  is the initial (t = 0) localized state, with energy <lb/> H = Ψ  0  |H|Ψ  0  ≡ E  0  . H is the system&apos;s Hamiltonian <lb/>operator. <lb/>The nucleus <lb/> 14 <lb/>6  C is a multi-particle system of 14 nucle-<lb/>ons, for which H can be written down only approximately. <lb/>Even so, if one&apos;s goal were to compute ||Ψ  0  |Ψ(t)| <lb/> 2  for all t <lb/> from first principles, he would have to obtain and employ <lb/>the accurate multi-particle solutions of the Schrödinger <lb/>equations for Ψ  0  and for Ψ(t) = e <lb/> −(i/)Ht <lb/> |Ψ  0  . This is a <lb/>formidable many-body problem of nuclear structure and <lb/>dynamics, which, thus far, escapes the possibility of treat-<lb/>ment. In this context, I cite the recent reports on advanced <lb/>and very extensive time-independent calculations pertain-<lb/>ing to the structure of <lb/> 14 <lb/>6  C, (i.e., of Ψ  0  ), and aiming at <lb/>the elucidation of the causes for its anomalously long life-<lb/>time [6–8]. <lb/>On the other hand, it is worth pointing out that the <lb/> ab initio computation of P (t) in terms of multi-electron <lb/>wave functions and matrix elements has indeed been <lb/>achieved in atomic many-body physics, with applications <lb/>to prototypical decaying states with Coulomb and spin-<lb/>dependent interactions, where the solutions for P (t) reveal <lb/>the state-specific nature of ED as well as of short-and <lb/>long-time NED [9–11]. <lb/>In view of the insurmountable difficulties of many-body <lb/>nuclear structure and dynamics in treating quantitatively <lb/>the problem of the numerical determination of the decay <lb/>curve of spontaneous fragmentation processes such as <lb/></body>

			<page> 42001-p1 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Comment <lb/></note>

			<body> 14 <lb/>6  C → <lb/> 14 <lb/>7  N+e <lb/> −  + ¯ <lb/> ν  e  , ( <lb/> 14 <lb/>7  N is a stable isotope, ¯ <lb/> ν  e  is the <lb/>electron antineutrino, and the energy released, E  r  , is <lb/>156476 eV [5]), the problem posed in the first paragraph <lb/>can be tackled reliably via an alternative approach, which <lb/>produces phenomenological analytic results in terms of <lb/>two physical quantities: E  r  and the width of a narrow and <lb/>isolated resonance, Γ. This is demonstrated in the next <lb/>section. In this section, I recall the following: <lb/>In the studies of NED in nuclei and particle physics <lb/>via models of the type [2–4], the choice of systems on <lb/>which the predictions of its magnitude and (in)significance <lb/>have been tested, has been done haphazardly, and not <lb/>by targeting characteristics of unstable states, which, <lb/>according to reliable theoretical criteria, ought to result <lb/>in enhanced NED that might be observable. <lb/>A different approach to the problem of establishing the <lb/>significance of NED of isolated unstable states was taken <lb/>in 1977 [12] —see also [13]. The syllogism and conclusions, <lb/>which are also applicable to the problem here, were as <lb/>follows: <lb/>If promising cases for significant NED are to be uncov-<lb/>ered, one ought to first establish generally applicable crite-<lb/>ria which indicate where to look for such a violation of <lb/>the &quot; law &quot; of ED. It was recognized and demonstrated <lb/>numerically that such criteria could be exhibited, clearly <lb/>and practically, by considering E  r  and Γ. Specifically, the <lb/>fundamental prerequisite for NED to be enhanced to the <lb/>point where it may become observable is for E  r  to be <lb/>very close to the fragmentation threshold and for the ratio <lb/> R ≡ <lb/> Er <lb/> Γ  to be of the order of 1–6. (The degree of validity <lb/>of the order of magnitude of this range depends on the <lb/>experimental arrangement for measurement and on the <lb/>time scale for decay.) <lb/> Application to the <lb/> 14 <lb/>6  C isotope. – The approach <lb/>of [12] solves the TDSE formally, via Fourier transforms <lb/>and the simple pole assumption [4]. This approximation <lb/>is completely reliable for the extremely narrow, non-<lb/>degenerate unstable state of <lb/> 14 <lb/>6  C, (J <lb/> π <lb/> , T ) = (0 <lb/> + <lb/> , 1), whose <lb/> E  r  is measured [5] and whose width is obtained simply <lb/>from Γ = <lb/> τ  . Specifically, it leads to an analytic expression <lb/>for the amplitude Ψ  0  |Ψ(t), subject to the constraints <lb/> t  0 and E  0. The consequence of these constraints <lb/>is the presence in the formalism of a complex energy <lb/>distribution, which expresses the time asymmetry of the <lb/>decay of the unstable state [12,13]. <lb/>The work in [12] led not only to a simple analytic <lb/>result for the NED survival probability, but also to <lb/>specially expressed numerical results for the full P (t), <lb/>plotted as fig. 2 of [12]. Specifically, P (t) was computed <lb/>from <lb/> P (t) = e <lb/> − <lb/> Γ <lb/>  t <lb/> 1 + <lb/> I  a  + I  b <lb/> 4π  2 <lb/> , <lb/> (1) <lb/>where I  a  and I  b  are finite integrals that are functions of <lb/>two critical to the problem quantities ([12], eqs. (17)–(19): <lb/> R ≡ <lb/> E  r <lb/> Γ <lb/> , <lb/>X≡ <lb/> Γt <lb/> = number of lifetimes. <lb/>(2) <lb/>When ln P (t) is plotted vs. X, the straight line with <lb/>negative slope represents ED. The deviations from ED are <lb/>easily read directly from the same plot, for different values <lb/>of R. The smaller R is, the earlier NED will acquire some <lb/>magnitude, and vice versa. A few characteristic orders of <lb/>magnitude are as follows: For R = 5, NED starts appearing <lb/>after about 10 lifetimes. For R = 100, it starts after about <lb/>17 lifetimes, and for R = 10 <lb/> 6  NED starts after about 37 <lb/>lifetimes. <lb/>Based on the above analysis and results, it is a straight-<lb/>forward matter to draw the final conclusion as to the possi-<lb/>ble significance of NED in the case of <lb/> 14 <lb/>6  C. Indeed, using <lb/>the experimental E  r  and Γ [5], E  r  ≈ 5.7 × 10 <lb/> 3  atomic units <lb/>(a.u.) and Γ10 <lb/> −28  a.u, it can be immediately recognized <lb/>from fig. 2 of [12] that, with such a huge R (≈ 6 × 10 <lb/> 31  ) <lb/>the deviation from ED would have to &quot; start &quot; (formally, <lb/>and not observationally) after hundreds of ED lifetimes, <lb/>by which time the sample has disappeared. <lb/> Conclusion. – The question of the title of [1] can <lb/>indeed be answered via a proper theoretical analysis <lb/>applicable to the decay of <lb/> 14 <lb/>6  C. Specifically, the herein <lb/>reported numerical estimates lead inescapably to the <lb/>conclusion that, for <lb/> 14 <lb/> 6  C and for all unstable, isolated <lb/>non-degenerate states of nuclei with large values of R <lb/> (eq. (2)) radioactive decay is really exponential! Therefore, <lb/>the scenario discussed by Aston [1] as to the possible role <lb/>of NED in radioactive carbon dating is baseless. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> REFERENCES <lb/>[1] Aston P. J., EPL, 97 (2012) 52001. <lb/>[2] Petzold J., Z. Phys., 155 (1959) 422. <lb/>[3] Winter R. G., Phys. Rev., 123 (1961) 1503; 126 (1962) <lb/>1152. <lb/>[4] Goldberger M. L. and Watson K. M., Collision <lb/>Theory (John Wiley and Sons, New York) 1964, Chapt. 8. <lb/>[5] WWW: Wikipedia, &quot; Carbon 14  &quot; . <lb/>[6] Holt J. W. et al., Phys. Rev. Lett., 100 (2008) 062501. <lb/>[7] Maris P. et al., Phys. Rev. Lett., 106 (2011) 202502. <lb/>[8] Robson D., Eur. Phys. J. A, 47 (2011) 95. <lb/>[9] Nicolaides C. A. and Mercouris Th., J. Phys. B, 29 <lb/> (1996) 1151. <lb/>[10] Mercouris Th. and Nicolaides C. A., J. Phys. B, 30 <lb/> (1997) 811. <lb/>[11] Mercouris Th. and Nicolaides C. A., Phys. Rev. A, <lb/> 65 (2002) 012112. <lb/>[12] Nicolaides C. A. and Beck D. R., Phys. Rev. Lett., 38 <lb/> (1977) 683. <lb/>[13] Nicolaides C. A., Phys. Rev. A, 66 (2002) 022118. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 42001-p2 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
