<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> International Journal of Mass Spectrometry 349– 350 (2013) 87– 93 <lb/> Contents lists available at ScienceDirect <lb/> International Journal of Mass Spectrometry <lb/> j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : w w w . e l s e v i e r . c o m / l o c a t e / i j m s <lb/> Penning trap mass spectrometry of rare isotopes produced via projectile <lb/>fragmentation at the LEBIT facility <lb/> Ryan Ringle <lb/> a, *  , Stefan Schwarz <lb/> a , Georg Bollen <lb/> a,b,c <lb/> a  National Superconducting Cyclotron Laboratory, East Lansing, MI, USA <lb/> b  Department of Physics and Astronomy, l Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI, USA <lb/> c  Facility for Rare Isotope Beams, East Lansing, MI, USA <lb/> a r t i c l e i n f o <lb/> Article history: <lb/> Received 12 February 2013 <lb/>Received in revised form 1 April 2013 <lb/>Accepted 1 April 2013 <lb/> Available online 12 April 2013 <lb/> Keywords: <lb/> Mass spectrometry <lb/>Penning trap <lb/>Rare isotopes <lb/>Projectile fragmentation <lb/> a b s t r a c t <lb/> The low-energy beam and ion trap facility, LEBIT, has been used to perform high-precision Penning trap <lb/>mass spectrometry using rare isotopes produced by fast-beam fragmentation. Gas stopping of the fast-<lb/>fragment beams and advanced ion manipulation techniques are used to produce brilliant, low-energy <lb/>beams for this type of measurement. The unique combination of fast, high-precision mass spectrom-<lb/>etry with the reach beyond the valley of beta stability afforded by projectile fragmentation has made <lb/>measurements possible that could not be performed at other facilities. <lb/> © 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> One of the most fundamental properties of an atomic nucleus <lb/>is its mass. The difference in the mass of the nucleus and the <lb/>sum total of the masses of the constituent nucleons is the nuclear <lb/>binding energy. The nuclear binding energy plays an important <lb/>role in several areas of physics, such as nuclear structure, nuclear <lb/>astrophysics, and fundamental interactions. In order to make mea-<lb/>surements relevant to these fields, rare isotopes, which do not exist <lb/>naturally on Earth, must be produced. <lb/>A powerful method for the production of rare isotopes is the <lb/>fragmentation of fast, heavy-ion beams after impinging on a light, <lb/>thin target, combined with their mass separation in flight [1]. This <lb/>is the method employed at the National Superconducting Cyclotron <lb/>Laboratory (NSCL). The benefits of this method are many fold. The <lb/>process produces fragments lighter than the projectile with no <lb/>dependence on chemistry. Also, as there are no delay times associ-<lb/>ated with diffusion out of a target, shorter-lived nuclei are available <lb/>from the fragmentation technique than from the Isotope Separation <lb/>Online (ISOL) technique [2]. Projectile fragmentation can be used <lb/>for the detection of rare isotopes with production rates on the order <lb/>of a few per day. The resulting fragments still possess a majority <lb/>of the energy of the original primary beam. High-energy, high-<lb/>emittance beams are poorly suited for low-energy experiments, <lb/></body>

			<front>  *  Corresponding author. Tel.: +1 517 908 7195. <lb/> E-mail addresses: ringle@nscl.msu.edu, ryan.ringle@me.com (R. Ringle). <lb/></front>

			<body> but present fewer difficulties for Coulomb excitation and reaction <lb/>studies. <lb/>The conversion of fast-projectile fragments into low-energy, <lb/>low-emittance beams of is important because it has the ability to <lb/>connect rare isotope beam production via projectile fragmentation <lb/>to high-precision experimental techniques like laser spectroscopy <lb/>and ion or atom trapping. With a number of refractory-element <lb/>beams not available at ISOL facilities, and advantages in the deliv-<lb/>ery of the most exotic nuclides, a wealth of new experiments with <lb/>stopped, and also re-accelerated, ion beams will become possi-<lb/>ble. This is reflected by the gas stopping scenario being an integral <lb/>part of the concept for all new radioactive beam facilities presently <lb/>under planning or construction, including the Facility for Rare Iso-<lb/>tope Beams (FRIB) [3] at MSU. <lb/>One of the most important recent developments in mass spec-<lb/>trometry is the use of Penning traps. Penning traps, used for many <lb/>years in mass spectrometry of stable charged particles, have proven <lb/>themselves invaluable for their accuracy, efficiency and sensitiv-<lb/>ity [4–6]. For the study of short-lived, rare isotopes several Penning <lb/>trap mass spectrometers have been installed at low-to-medium <lb/>energy radioactive-beam facilities around the world [7–12]. The <lb/>Low Energy Beam and Ion Trap facility (LEBIT) at the NSCL is the <lb/>first to implement Penning trap mass spectrometry at a high-<lb/>energy, rare-isotope facility using projectile fragmentation. LEBIT <lb/>was designed to be fast, efficient, and sensitive in order to make <lb/>optimal use of the most exotic beams available at the NSCL. <lb/>During its 4 years of operation, LEBIT successfully per-<lb/>formed high-precision mass measurements on rare isotope beams <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 1387-3806/$ – see front matter © 2013 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved. <lb/> http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ijms.2013.04.001 <lb/></note>

			<page> 88 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> R. Ringle et al. / International Journal of Mass Spectrometry 349– 350 (2013) 87– 93 <lb/></note>

			<body> produced from thermalized projectile fragments. Many of the <lb/>beams produced are not available at other facilities. The success <lb/>of the mass measurement program has inspired others to consider <lb/>the science opportunities using thermalized beams at the NSCL. <lb/>The NSCL&apos;s gas stopping facilities have recently been expanded <lb/>and upgraded, and will now serve the BECOLA experiment [13] <lb/>for collinear laser spectroscopy, ReA facility [14] for reaccelerated <lb/>beams, as well as LEBIT. <lb/> 2. Thermalized beams from projectile fragmentation for <lb/>Penning trap mass spectrometry <lb/> Penning trap mass spectrometry (PTMS) requires ion beams <lb/>with energies on the order of few eV with a small energy spread. <lb/>However, beams produced via projectile fragmentation at the <lb/>NSCL have energies on the order of 100 MeV/u with large energy <lb/>spreads and emittances. Thermalizing fast ion beams in gas stop-<lb/>pers bridges this disconnect, and has been developed by several <lb/>groups [15–18,17,19,20] at various facilities around the world. To <lb/>date, all gas stoppers used at radioactive beam facilities are of <lb/>the linear variety. The fast fragments are first slowed using solid <lb/>degraders before entering a chamber filled with helium buffer gas <lb/>where they are thermalized by collisions. Applied RF and DC fields <lb/>pull the ions through the gas to an orifice where gas flow sweeps <lb/>them into a differentially pumped, radiofrequency quadrupole <lb/>(RFQ) ion guide system where they are formed into a low-energy <lb/>beam. <lb/>A linear gas stopper has been used successfully at the NSCL, <lb/>and a new linear gas stopper has recently been commissioned. <lb/>One concern regarding the use of linear gas stoppers with high-<lb/>energy (≈ 100 MeV/u) beams is the large straggling range of lighter <lb/>ions, which either requires very large systems or high-pressure <lb/>operation, both resulting in extraction times for the rare isotopes <lb/>that can reach values on the order of 100 ms. For short-lived rare <lb/>isotopes significant decay losses become inevitable. Another con-<lb/>sideration is the purity of the extracted beam. Typically, stopping a <lb/>single ion generates about 10 6 He + –e  −  pairs. The helium ions will <lb/>charge exchange with any impurities in the buffer gas resulting in <lb/>stable, molecular ion beams being extracted simultaneously with <lb/>the rare isotopes, and can lead to systematic errors in the mass <lb/>determination if not removed from the Penning trap. <lb/>LEBIT&apos;s first 4 years of operation yielded many important sci-<lb/>ence results, thanks in no small part to the NSCL&apos;s first-generation <lb/>gas catcher [15]. In 2009 upgrades were begun on the NSCL&apos;s gas <lb/>stopping facility. A new linear gas catcher, designed and built at <lb/>Argonne National Lab (ANL), was installed in 2012 and has recently <lb/>been used to produce thermalized rare isotope beams for commis-<lb/>sioning. <lb/>The cyclotron gas stopper [21], currently being developed at the <lb/>NSCL, will complement linear gas stoppers and deliver high-purity, <lb/>short-lived rare isotope beams to LEBIT, and other experiments. <lb/>The cyclotron gas stopper promises increased efficiency for light <lb/>rare isotope beams, as compared to linear gas stoppers. A stopping <lb/>chamber, filled with 100 mbar of helium gas, is located in a weakly <lb/>focusing cyclotron-style magnet system. The stopping chamber is <lb/>cooled with liquid nitrogen in order to reduce the level of impu-<lb/>rities in the helium gas. Fast fragments enter through a window, <lb/>pass through a solid degrader, and spiral towards the axis as they <lb/>lose energy. Charge collection electrodes push the thermalized rare <lb/>isotopes to an RF carpet and are quickly transported to an extrac-<lb/>tion orifice using the ion surfing technique [22]. Gas flow carries <lb/>the rare isotopes out of the stopping chamber and into an RF ion <lb/>extraction system where they are formed into a beam for delivery <lb/>to experiments. The combination of cryogenic cooling, fragments <lb/>thermalizing close to the axis, and fast extraction promise purer, <lb/>shorter-lived rare isotope beams for Penning trap mass spectrom-<lb/>etry. <lb/>The cyclotron gas stopper is currently being constructed and <lb/>will begin initial offline testing later this year. The ANL gas catcher <lb/>and the cyclotron stopper will both be used as part of the gas stop-<lb/>ping facility. Having multiple gas catchers installed will allow for <lb/>direct comparisons of the devices and minimal interruption of ther-<lb/>malized beam delivery due to repairs or modifications. These two <lb/>new gas catchers will aid in extending LEBIT&apos;s reach to even more <lb/>exotic isotopes in the near future. Advances in the gas stopping <lb/>facility at the NSCL will be available to FRIB, the next-generation <lb/>rare-isotope facility currently being built at MSU, for production of <lb/>thermalized rare isotope beams on day one. With a primary beam <lb/>power 2–3 orders of magnitude greater than the current Coupled <lb/>Cyclotron Facility at the NSCL, FRIB will significantly extend the <lb/>reach of PTMS. <lb/> 3. The LEBIT facility <lb/> Fig. 1 shows a schematic layout of the gas stopping and LEBIT <lb/>facilities. The main components are a gas stopping station, an ion <lb/>beam cooler and buncher, and a Penning trap system for high-<lb/>precision mass measurements. Stable ion beams are provided by <lb/>plasma and laser ablation ion sources. The gas stoppers and LEBIT <lb/>are located on independent high-voltage (HV) platforms that share <lb/>a common 60 kV bias supply with the connecting beam line being <lb/>operated at ground potential. <lb/> 3.1. Stable beam ion sources <lb/> As shown in Fig. 1, there are two stable beam ion sources <lb/>installed upstream of the cooler and buncher. The plasma ion <lb/>source station consists of an ion source, an RFQ mass filter for <lb/>beam selection and acceleration optics. Beams from this station <lb/>are used extensively in system tuning and optimization, and also to <lb/>provide reference masses during radioactive mass measurements. <lb/>This source is used primarily to produce ion beams of alkali metals <lb/>and gases, but can also be used with an oven to produce beams of <lb/>other elements for mass measurements of stable isotopes [23,24]. <lb/>The laser ablation ion source is currently being commissioned and <lb/>will produce a variety of beams by ablating a target using a pulsed <lb/>Nd:Yag laser. The beams include carbon cluster for absolute mass <lb/>references, and other stable isotopes that cannot be obtained from <lb/>the plasma ion source. <lb/> 3.2. The LEBIT ion beam cooler and buncher <lb/> The LEBIT ion accumulator and buncher accepts a beam from <lb/>the gas stopping station, or a local stable ion source, and converts <lb/>it into a low-energy, low-emittance pulsed beam. This device is a <lb/>linear radiofrequency quadrupole ion trap filled with a buffer gas <lb/>at low pressure for ion cooling [25–27]. It features two separate <lb/>vacuum sections, one for beam pre-cooling and one for final cool-<lb/>ing, trapping and beam bunching. Before entering the system, the <lb/>ions are decelerated electrostatically to a few tens of eV. The first <lb/>section is typically operated with helium or neon at a pressure on <lb/>the order of 10  −2  mbar. Here the ions are transversely cooled and <lb/>decelerated before they pass through a miniature RFQ-ion guide <lb/>(an efficient differential pumping barrier) into the trap section. The <lb/>linear trap is operated with helium at a pressure 1–2 orders of <lb/>magnitude lower than that in the first section to minimize beam <lb/>heating during the pulsed-beam extraction. The ions are typically <lb/>stored for 20–30 ms for their final cooling before they are extracted <lb/>as a micro-second ion pulse for delivery to the Penning trap. Both <lb/>the pre-cooler and the trap section are cooled with liquid nitrogen <lb/>provided from a stationary cryogenic line. This cooling significantly <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> R. Ringle et al. / International Journal of Mass Spectrometry 349– 350 (2013) 87– 93 <lb/></note>

			<page> 89 <lb/></page>

			<body> Fig. 1. Schematic layout of the LEBIT and gas stopping facilities at the NSCL. <lb/> reduces the emittance of the resulting pulse which aids in achieving <lb/>high accuracy in the Penning trap mass measurements. <lb/> 3.3. The LEBIT 9.4 T Penning trap system <lb/> The magnetic field is provided by an actively-shielded persis-<lb/>tent superconducting 9.4 T magnet system. The magnet system <lb/>has been upgraded by the addition of external-field compensation <lb/>coils [28] to reduce the effect of external field changes that may <lb/>occur in an accelerator environment. The employment of a 9.4 T <lb/>field, as compared to ≈6 T which is typical of current systems, has <lb/>the advantage that a given precision can be achieved in about half <lb/>the measurement time, supporting the design goal of measuring <lb/>the shortest-lived isotopes. The pressure of the helium bath is sta-<lb/>bilized to minimize magnetic field changes, due to variations in the <lb/>helium boil-off rate. A precisely machined vacuum tube, mounted <lb/>inside of the room-temperature bore of the magnet, serves as an <lb/>ion-optical bench for the trap electrode system. Two ion-optical <lb/>packages, one containing the injection optics and Penning trap and <lb/>the other containing the ejection optics, are inserted into oppo-<lb/>site ends of this bore tube. The ion trap and optical elements in its <lb/>vicinity can be cooled with the help of a cryogenic shield. This aids <lb/>the creation of an ultra-high vacuum in the center of the bore tube <lb/>that is pumped by two turbomolecular pumps located on either <lb/>end of the magnet. The ring electrode has an eight-fold segmen-<lb/>tation. This allows not only for the creation of a quadrupolar RF <lb/>field, as required for the excitation of the ion motion at the ions <lb/>cyclotron frequency  c  [29], but also the application of an octupo-<lb/>lar RF field [30–32]. More information on the Penning trap system <lb/>can be found in [33]. <lb/> 3.4. Pushing the limits of Penning trap mass spectrometry – new <lb/>technical developments at LEBIT <lb/> In order to apply Penning trap mass spectrometry to increas-<lb/>ingly exotic rare isotopes, challenges that must be met are the <lb/>short half lives and low production rates of the isotopes that one <lb/>wants to measure. These challenges can be addressed by minimiz-<lb/>ing the preparation and measurement time of the rare isotopes, <lb/>maximizing the use of allocated beam time, and increasing sensi-<lb/>tivity. Technical developments currently underway towards these <lb/>ends include active magnetic field monitoring by employing a <lb/>miniature Penning trap as a magnetometer, the use of the stored <lb/>waveform inverse Fourier transform (SWIFT) method to most effec-<lb/>tively removed unwanted ions, and the construction of a single-ion <lb/>Penning trap that will utilize Fourier-Transform Ion Cyclotron <lb/>Resonance (FT-ICR) image-charge detection to enable mass deter-<lb/>minations using with a single ion. <lb/> 3.4.1. Miniature Penning trap magnetometer <lb/> Instead of alternating between reference measurements to track <lb/>the magnetic field, measurements of the ion of interest, a high-<lb/>precision magnetometer can be used to track the magnetic field. <lb/>For this purpose an additional miniature Penning trap has been <lb/>developed, shown in Fig. 2, which will be located inside the bore <lb/>of the 9.4 T superconducting magnet, close to precision trap. The <lb/>reduced cyclotron frequency,  + , of hydrogen ions produced by <lb/>electron-impact ionization will be measured via Fourier Transform <lb/>Ion Cyclotron Resonance (FT-ICR) [34] using narrow band detection <lb/>with a tuned resonant circuit. Measurements of relative changes in <lb/>the magnetic field on the order of B/B ≈ 10  −8  will be possible with <lb/>this device. The elimination of frequent reference measurements <lb/>will allow LEBIT to make better use of the rare isotope beam times. <lb/> 3.4.2. In-trap beam purification with SWIFT <lb/> Any unwanted, or contaminant, ions present in the LEBIT Pen-<lb/>ning trap during a measurement will reduce the resonance signal <lb/> Fig. 2. Photo of the miniature Penning trap magnetometer as it will be installed in <lb/>the 9.4 T magnet system. Two independent traps are used in case one fails. A U.S. <lb/>quarter is shown for scale. <lb/></body>

			<page> 90 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> R. Ringle et al. / International Journal of Mass Spectrometry 349– 350 (2013) 87– 93 <lb/></note>

			<body> Fig. 3. Schematic of the LEBIT facility with the future SIPT spectrometer included. <lb/> strength and, if stored simultaneously with the ion of interest, can <lb/>lead to systematic errors due to frequency shifts caused by ion–ion <lb/>interactions. For the study of short-lived isotopes, it is important <lb/>to have fast methods for purification in place. A multi-step purifi-<lb/>cation process is employed such that a single charge-to-mass ratio <lb/>is injected into the trap [35]. As there is usually isobaric contam-<lb/>ination still present in the beam, an additional purification step <lb/>with a high resolving power is required. Mass selective buffer gas <lb/>cooling is a method [36] that does not require knowledge of the <lb/>contaminant species, but the purification requires on the order of <lb/>100 ms. Another method involves the application of a dipolar RF <lb/>field at a contaminant ion&apos;s reduced cyclotron frequency to drive <lb/>it into the trap electrodes. The strength of the second method is <lb/>its speed, requiring only 10–20 ms for purification. Its weakness is <lb/>that each contaminant species must be identified, which takes time. <lb/>For very low incoming rates, identification may not be possible. In <lb/>pursuit of a fast cleaning technique that requires no knowledge of <lb/>the contaminant ion species, the Stored Waveform Inverse Fourier <lb/>Transform (SWIFT) method [37] has been adapted for use in clean-<lb/>ing isobaric contaminants from the Penning trap by delivering a <lb/>broad band excitation that removes any contaminant ions within <lb/>a defined frequency band [38]. SWIFT combines the strengths of <lb/>the previously discussed purification techniques without any of <lb/>their weaknesses. SWIFT has been tested in offline measurements <lb/>at LEBIT, and resolving powers greater than 10 4 have been demon-<lb/>strated. Greater detail will be provided in a future publication. <lb/> 3.4.3. Mass measurements using a single ion with SIPT <lb/> Mass measurements at LEBIT are currently performed using the <lb/>time-of-flight ion cyclotron resonance (TOF-ICR) technique [39,40]. <lb/>TOF-ICR is very flexible, requiring little effort to switch between <lb/>measurements of different isotopes. However, it is a destructive <lb/>technique that requires on the order of 100 detected ions to obtain <lb/>a resonance curve. Therefore TOF-ICR is not applicable to isotopes <lb/>that are delivered at very low rates (&lt;1 ion/h) due to the length of <lb/>time required to obtain a resonance curve. In order to apply PTMS <lb/>to these very exotic isotopes, and drastically extend its reach, the <lb/>LEBIT facility will be expanded with the addition of another Pen-<lb/>ning trap system capable of making a precise measurement with a <lb/>single ion. This Single-Ion Penning trap (SIPT) mass spectrometer, <lb/>presently under design and construction, will employ the narrow-<lb/>band FT-ICR technique. Fig. 3 shows a schematic of the LEBIT facility <lb/>with the SIPT trap included. Ion pulses from the cooler and buncher <lb/>will be sent either to the current 9.4 T system, or to SIPT using an <lb/>electrostatic kicker/bender system. The SIPT trap will be housed <lb/>in a separate 7 T solenoid magnet, together with the preampli-<lb/>fier circuitry, cooled to cryogenic temperatures. Superconducting <lb/>resonators are used to achieve a high Q-value, and thus greater <lb/>amplification. <lb/> 4. Science results from the LEBIT facility <lb/> In 4 years of online operation, LEBIT was used to perform mass <lb/>measurements on nearly 40 isotopes of 11 different elements. Most <lb/>of these elements are difficult or impossible to produce at ISOL facil-<lb/>ities, such as Fe, Co, Si, Br, and S. In this section, select measurements <lb/>and their impact will be discussed. <lb/> 4.1. Nuclear structure <lb/> Penning trap mass spectrometry can serve as a complementary <lb/>tool to traditional ␤ or ␥ spectroscopy, particularly when it is cou-<lb/>pled to a fragmentation facility, as the fragmentation process tends <lb/>to efficiently populate isomeric states. In addition, isomeric states <lb/>with half lives on the order of a few ␮s proliferate near these closed <lb/>shells [41] which time-of-flight spectrometers would be unable to <lb/>resolve and could serve as an unknown systematic error. As the <lb/>time scale involved with making a measurement with a Penning <lb/>trap is on the order of 10&apos;s of ms, these short-lived isomers would <lb/>not be present. <lb/>One example of mass measurements performed with LEBIT to <lb/>investigate nuclear structure are those of 63−66 Fe and 64−67 Co near <lb/> N = 40, Z = 28 [42,43]. The measurements revealed a previously <lb/>unknown isomeric state in 65 Fe and confirmed an isomeric state <lb/>in 67 Co recently discovered using ␤ spectroscopy [44]. The half life <lb/>of the recently discovered isomeric state in 65 Fe is estimated to be <lb/>greater than 150 ms, due to the time it spends in the Penning trap. A <lb/>tentative spin and parity of J   = 9/2 + has been assigned which would <lb/>be consistent with the structure of the nearby odd-A Fe isotopes <lb/>where an increasing monopole interaction could lead to increased <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> R. Ringle et al. / International Journal of Mass Spectrometry 349– 350 (2013) 87– 93 <lb/></note>

			<page> 91 <lb/></page>

			<body> 24 25 26 27 28 29 30 <lb/> Neutron number <lb/> 6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/>16 <lb/> S <lb/> 2n  [MeV] <lb/> S <lb/> Cl <lb/>Ar <lb/>P <lb/> Fig. 4. Updated two-neutron separation energy, S2n for Ar, Cl, S, and P near N = 28 <lb/>using the improved LEBIT mass values of <lb/> 40−44 S and those reported in [52]. <lb/> deformation and lower the energy of 9/2 + from 61 Fe to 67 Fe. Addi-<lb/>tionally, these measurements significantly smooth the previous <lb/>two-neutron separation energy, S 2n , curves of Fe and Co in this <lb/>region [42,43]. However, small observed discontinuities in the S 2n <lb/> curves of the neighboring elements Ni, Cu, and Ga could not be <lb/>confirmed in Fe and Co due to the large uncertainty in the mass <lb/>values of 67,68 Fe and 68,69 Co. It is expected that deformation in the <lb/>Fe isotopes will lead to a reduced neutron shell gap across N = 40. <lb/>Another example is the exploration of the N = 28 shell closure in <lb/>sulfur. The modification of magic numbers as one moves beyond the <lb/>valley of stability is a very active area of research in nuclear physics. <lb/>Harmonic oscillator shell closures with the addition of a spin–orbit <lb/>coupling successfully predict the shell closures at 28, 50, 82, and <lb/>126 in stable nuclei. In the heavy sulfur isotopes, changes in the <lb/>spin–orbit coupling [45,46] along with shape deformation [47–49] <lb/>are thought to reduce the N = 28 (1f 7/2 –2p 3/2 ) shell gap. Using <lb/>LEBIT the isotopes 40−44 S were measured [50]. These isotopes had <lb/>been measured previously [51–53] using the time-of-flight spec-<lb/>trometers TOFI and SPEG. There is agreement between all of the <lb/>measurements, but the LEBIT mass values are a factor of 20–50 <lb/>more precise. The new mass values can be used to calculate the <lb/>S 2n curves along the sulfur chain to look for the characteristic dis-<lb/>continuity which would indicate a shell closure crossing N = 28. As <lb/>shown in Fig. 4, for Ar and Cl, no sign of a shell closure is present. <lb/>Due to the large uncertainty in the mass of 45 S, the situation is still <lb/>unclear. One should note the anomalous uptick in the S 2n curve <lb/>of the P isotopes as N = 28 is crossed. Future mass measurements <lb/>of 45 S and 44 P would offer further information on the quenching of <lb/>the 1f 7/2 –2p 3/2 shell gap. <lb/> 4.2. Nuclear astrophysics <lb/> Type I X-ray bursts can occur in a binary star system consisting <lb/>of a neutron star and an expanded companion star. The neutron <lb/>star accretes matter from its companion until the temperature and <lb/>density have risen to the point where thermonuclear burning is <lb/>initiated, generating heavy elements and producing an X-ray light <lb/>curve which serves as the only observable from these events. In <lb/>order to accurately model these bursts, and obtain reliable pre-<lb/>dictions of the final nucleic composition of the ash, precise and <lb/>accurate masses of the involved nuclei must be known [54]. Once <lb/>the burning begins, heavier elements are synthesized in a series of <lb/>rapid proton captures and subsequent ␤ decays, commonly called <lb/>the rp process [55]. Nuclei capture protons until they reach the pro-<lb/>ton drip line, where adding another proton to a nucleus makes it <lb/>particle unbound. In order to proceed past this point the nucleus <lb/>must either undergo a ␤ decay or double proton capture. These <lb/>nuclei are known as waiting point nuclei. The effective lifetime of a <lb/>waiting point nucleus determines its effect on the light curve and <lb/>final composition of the ash. <lb/>The three waiting point nuclides in the area of the nuclear chart <lb/>around N≈Z≈34 are 64 Ge, 68 Se, and 72 Kr, and have been studied <lb/>extensively. LEBIT mass measurements in this area [58,59] have <lb/>provided valuable input data which was used to calculate [54] the <lb/>effective lifetime of 68 Se using the local network show in Fig. 5a. The <lb/>nuclides shown with the solid border were measured directly with <lb/>LEBIT, while those with the dashed border were calculated using <lb/>LEBIT measurements in conjunction with Coulomb displacement <lb/>energies [56]. Fig. 5b shows the results of effective lifetime calcu-<lb/>lations of 68 Se. The results show that for using the improved mass <lb/>values (shaded) compared to the mass values from the most recent <lb/>atomic mass evaluation [57] at the time, at typical stellar tempera-<lb/>tures, about 1.2–1.4 GK, 68 Se is a much stronger waiting point than <lb/>previously thought. This has significant effects on the light curve <lb/>and final elemental abundance of a type I X-ray burst, the details of <lb/>which can be found in [58]. <lb/> 4.3. Fundamental interactions <lb/> If the nucleon–nucleon interaction was completely charge-<lb/>independent, then isospin would be a good quantum number and <lb/>the 2T + 1 members of an isospin multiplet would have the same <lb/>mass. However, this degeneracy is broken by charge-dependent <lb/>interactions which, to first order, can be calculated [60,61] to lie on <lb/> Fig. 5. (a) Local network used in calculating the effective lifetime of <lb/> 68 Se using improved input mass values obtained with LEBIT. Solid borders indicate nuclides whose mass <lb/>values were directly measured, and dashed borders indicate mass values calculated using Coulomb displacement energies [56]. (b) Resulting effective lifetime calculation <lb/>of <lb/> 68 Se using the local network and the improved mass values (shaded) compared to the mass values included in the most recent atomic mass evaluation at the time, <lb/>AME&apos;03 [57]. <lb/></body>

			<page> 92 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> R. Ringle et al. / International Journal of Mass Spectrometry 349– 350 (2013) 87– 93 <lb/></note>

			<body> a parabola and is known as the Isobaric Multiplet Mass Equation <lb/>(IMME). The mass of any multiplet member with isospin projec-<lb/>tion can be written as T  z  = a + bT z  + cT <lb/> 2 <lb/> z  , where T z  = (N − Z)/2. The <lb/>parameters a, b, and c are unique to each multiplet and are deter-<lb/>mined experimentally. Therefore, at least a quartet is required to <lb/>determine these parameters absolutely and test the quadratic form <lb/>of IMME. Higher order terms, such dT <lb/> 3 <lb/> z  and eT <lb/> 4 <lb/> z  , can be introduced <lb/>by considering a charge-dependent nucleon–nucleon interaction, <lb/>second-order Coulomb effects, or many body forces. High-precision <lb/>mass measurements are key in testing the validity of the quadratic <lb/>form of IMME, and probing for higher-order corrections. After a <lb/>Penning trap measurement of 32 Ar [62] in 2003, the A = 32, T = 2 <lb/>quintet showed good agreement with the quadratic form of IMME. <lb/>However, in 2006 the first T = 2 state in 32 S was remeasured [63], <lb/>which disagreed with the previous measurement, and destroyed <lb/>the agreement with the quadratic form of IMME. Speculation of <lb/>possible isospin mixing in 32 S or an incorrect 32 Si mass value was <lb/>raised [63]. The mass of 32 Si was measured with LEBIT [64] to look <lb/>for a deviation in the mass value, and a 4 deviation with respect <lb/>to the AME03 value was found. However, the deviation was in <lb/>the opposite direction required to bring the data back into agree-<lb/>ment with the quadratic form of IMME. Adding a cubic term of <lb/> d = 1.00(9) keV restores agreement. Although this value is not out <lb/>of line with predictions of possible cubic terms due to isospin mix-<lb/>ing, no specific calculations for the A = 32, T = 2 quintet have been <lb/>performed. It is also possible that other experimental data could <lb/>be off and need to be remeasured. Without complete confidence in <lb/>the experimental data, no positive conclusions can be drawn. <lb/> 5. Summary <lb/> Rare isotope production by projectile fragmentation is a pow-<lb/>erful technique that is chemistry independent and capable of <lb/>producing isotopes far from the valley of stability. LEBIT is the first <lb/>and only facility to utilize isotopes produced by projectile frag-<lb/>mentation for high-precision Penning trap mass measurements <lb/>thanks to thermalized beams produced by the NSCL&apos;s first gen-<lb/>eration gas catcher. Upgrades to the NSCL&apos;s gas stopping facility <lb/>will deliver cleaner beams more efficiently, bringing more iso-<lb/>topes within reach of LEBIT. Other developments at LEBIT will <lb/>aid in using beam time more efficiently, and SIPT will greatly <lb/>extend LEBIT&apos;s reach to isotopes produced at very low rates. During <lb/>the first 4 years of operation, LEBIT has made important con-<lb/>tributions to several areas of nuclear science. The investments <lb/>being made in developments today will ensure that LEBIT can <lb/>make optimal use of beams available at the NSCL today, and FRIB <lb/>tomorrow. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgement <lb/> We wish to acknowledge the support of Michigan State <lb/>University, the National Science Foundation under Cooperative <lb/>Agreement no. PHY-11-02511. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] D.J. Morrissey, B.M. Sherrill, M. Steiner, A. Stolz, I. Wiedenhöver, Nuclear <lb/>Instruments and Methods in Physics Research Section B 204 (2003) 90–96, <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0168-583X(02)01895-5. <lb/>[2] U. Köster, European Physical Journal A 15 (1–2) (2002) 255–263, <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1140/epja/i2001-10264-2. <lb/>[3] G. Bollen, AIP Conference Proceedings 1224 (1) (2010) 432–441, <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.3431449. <lb/>[4] E.A. Cornell, R.M. Weisskoff, K.R. Boyce, R.W. Flanagan, G.P. Lafyatis, D.E. <lb/>Pritchard, Physical Review Letters 63 (16) (1989) 1674–1677. <lb/>[5] I. Bergström, C. Carlberg, T. Fritioff, G. Douysset, J. Schönfelder, R. Schuch, <lb/>Nuclear Instruments and Methods in Physics Research Section A 487 (3) (2002) <lb/>618–651. <lb/>[6] M. Redshaw, J. McDaniel, E.G. Myers, Physical Review Letters 100 (9) (2008), <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.100.093002. <lb/>[7] M. Mukherjee, D. Beck, K. Blaum, G. Bollen, J. Dilling, S. George, F. Herfurth, <lb/>A. Herlert, A. Kellerbauer, H.J.J. Kluge, S. Schwarz, L. Schweikhard, C. Yazid-<lb/>jian, European Physical Journal A 35 (1) (2008) 1–29, http://dx.doi.org/10.1140/ <lb/>epja/i2007-10528-9. <lb/>[8] G. Savard, R.C. Barber, D. Beeching, F. Buchinger, J.E. Crawford, S. Gulick, X. <lb/>Feng, E. Hagberg, J.C. Hardy, V.T. Koslowsky, J.K.P. Lee, R.B. Moore, K.S. Sharma, <lb/>M. Watson, Nuclear Physics A 626 (1–2) (1997) 353C–356C. <lb/>[9] S. Rahaman, M. Block, D. Ackermann, D. Beck, A. Chaudhuri, S. Eliseev, H. <lb/>Geissel, D. Habs, F. Herfurth, F.P. Heßberger, S. Hofmann, G. Marx, M. Mukher-<lb/>jee, J.B. Neumayr, M. Petrick, W.R. Plaß, W. Quint, C. Rauth, D. Rodríguez, <lb/>C. Scheidenberger, L. Schweikhard, P.G. Thirolf, C. Weber, International Jour-<lb/>nal of Mass Spectrometry 251 (2–3) (2006) 146–151, http://dx.doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.ijms.2006.01.049. <lb/>[10] T. Eronen, V. Kolhinen, V. Elomaa, D. Gorelov, U. Hager, J. Hakala, A. Joki-<lb/>nen, A. Kankainen, P. Karvonen, S. Kopecky, I. Moore, H. Penttilä, S. Rahaman, <lb/>S. Rinta-Antila, J. Rissanen, A. Saastamoinen, J. Szerypo, C. Weber, J. Äystö, <lb/>European Physical Journal A 48 (4) (2012) 1–21, http://dx.doi.org/10.1140/ <lb/>epja/i2012-12046-1. <lb/>[11] J. Dilling, R. Baartman, P. Bricault, M. Brodeur, L. Blomeley, F. Buchinger, <lb/>J.E. Crawford, J.R.C. López-Urrutia, P. Delheij, M. Froese, G.P. Gwinner, Z. <lb/>Ke, J.K.P. Lee, R.B. Moore, V.L. Ryjkov, G. Sikler, M. Smith, J. Ullrich, J. <lb/>Vaz, International Journal of Mass Spectrometry 251 (2–3) (2006) 198–203, <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ijms.2006.01.044. <lb/>[12] J. Ketelaer, J. Kraemer, D. Beck, K. Blaum, M. Block, K. Eberhardt, G. Eitel, R. Fer-<lb/>rer, C. Geppert, S. George, F. Herfurth, J. Ketter, S. Nagy, D. Neidherr, R. Neugart, <lb/>W. Nörtershäuser, J. Repp, C. Smorra, N. Trautmann, C. Weber, Nuclear Instru-<lb/>ments and Methods in Physics Research Section A 594 (2) (2008) 162–177, <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.nima.2008.06.023. <lb/>[13] K. Minamisono, P.F. Mantica, A. Klose, S. Vinnikova, A. Schneider, B. Johnson, <lb/>B. Barquest, Commissioning of the collinear laser spectroscopy system in the <lb/>becola facility at NSCL, Nuclear Instruments and Methods in Physics Research <lb/>Section A: Accelerators, Spectrometers, Detectors and Associated Equipment <lb/>(0) (2013)doi:10.1016/j.nima.2013.01.038 <lb/>[14] D. Leitner, C. Compton, A. Facco, M. Hodek, A. Lapierre, S. Nash, D. Morris, G. <lb/>Perdikakis, J. Popielarski, N. Usher, Proceedings of SRF2011, (2011) pp. 674–679. <lb/>[15] L. Weissman, D.J. Morrissey, G. Bollen, D.A. Davies, E. Kwan, P.A. Lofy, P. <lb/>Schury, S. Schwarz, C. Sumithrarachchi, T. Sun, R. Ringle, Nuclear Instru-<lb/>ments and Methods in Physics Research Section A 540 (2–3) (2005) 245–258, <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/J.Nima.2004.11.048. <lb/>[16] G. Sikler, D. Ackermann, F. Attallah, D. Beck, J. Dilling, S.A. Elisseev, H. Geis-<lb/>sel, D. Habs, S. Heinz, F. Herfurth, F. Heßberger, S. Hofmann, H.-J.J. Kluge, <lb/>C. Kozhuharov, G. Marx, M. Mukherjee, J. Neumayr, W.R. Plaß, W. Quint, S. <lb/>Rahaman, D. Rodríguez, C. Scheidenberger, M. Tarisien, P. Thirolf, V. Varentsov, <lb/>C. Weber, Z. Zhou, Nuclear Instruments and Methods in Physics Research <lb/>Section B 204 (2003) 482–486, http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0168-583X(02) <lb/>02116-X. <lb/>[17] G. Savard, J. Clark, C. Boudreau, F. Buchinger, J.E. Crawford, H. Geissel, J.P. <lb/>Greene, S. Gulick, A.S.A. Heinz, J.K.P. Lee, A. Levand, M. Maier, G. Münzenberg, <lb/>C. Scheidenberger, D. Seweryniak, K.S. Sharma, G. Sprouse, J. Vaz, J.C. Wang, <lb/>B.J. Zabransky, Z. Zhou, Nuclear Instruments and Methods in Physics Research <lb/>Section B 204 (0) (2003) 582–586, http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0168-583X(02) <lb/>02134-1. <lb/>[18] M. Wada, Y. Ishida, T. Nakamura, Y. Yamazaki, T. Kambara, H. Ohyama, Y. Kanai, <lb/>T.M. Kojima, Y. Nakai, N. Ohshima, A. Yoshida, T. Kubo, Y. Matsuo, Y. Fukuyama, <lb/>K. Okada, T. Sonoda, S. Ohtani, K. Noda, H. Kawakami, I. Katayama, Nuclear <lb/>Instruments and Methods in Physics Research Section B 204 (2003) 570–581, <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0168-583X(02)02151-1. <lb/>[19] G. Bollen, S. Chouhan, C. Guénaut, F. Marti, D.J. Morrissey, D. Lawton, J. Ottarson, <lb/>G. Pang, S. Schwarz, B.M. Sherrill, M. Wada, A.F. Zeller, European Physi-<lb/>cal Journal – Special Topics 150 (2007) 265–267, http://dx.doi.org/10.1140/ <lb/>epjst/e2007-00319-0. <lb/>[20] G. Savard, S. Baker, C. Davids, A.F. Levand, E.F. Moore, R.C. Pardo, R. Von-<lb/>drasek, B.J. Zabransky, G. Zinkann, Nuclear Instruments and Methods in Physics <lb/>Research Section B 266 (19–20) (2008) 4086–4091, http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>nimb.2008.05.091. <lb/>[21] G. Bollen, D.J. Morrissey, S. Schwarz, Nuclear Instruments and Methods in <lb/>Physics Research Section A 550 (1–2) (2005) 27–38, http://dx.doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.nima.2005.06.041. <lb/>[22] M. Brodeur, A.E. Gehring, G. Bollen, S. Schwarz, D.J. Morrissey, Inter-<lb/>national Journal of Mass Spectrometry (2013) doi:10.1016/j.ijms.2012.12. <lb/>011. <lb/>[23] M. Redshaw, G. Bollen, M. Brodeur, S. Bustabad, D.L. Lincoln, S.J. Novario, R. <lb/>Ringle, S. Schwarz, Physical Review C 86 (4) (2012) 041306, http://dx.doi.org/ <lb/>10.1103/PhysRevC.86.041306. <lb/>[24] D.L. Lincoln, J.D. Holt, G. Bollen, M. Brodeur, S. Bustabad, J. Engel, S.J. Novario, M. <lb/>Redshaw, R. Ringle, S. Schwarz, Physical Review Letters 110 (1) (2013) 012501, <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.110.012501. <lb/>[25] S. Schwarz, G. Bollen, D. Lawton, A. Neudert, R. Ringle, P. Schury, T. Sun, Nuclear <lb/>Instruments and Methods in Physics Research Section B 204 (2003) 474–477, <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0168-583x(02)02114-6. <lb/>[26] G. Bollen, S. Schwarz, D. Davies, P. Lofy, D. Morrissey, R. Ringle, P. Schury, T. <lb/>Sun, L. Weissman, Beam cooling at the low-energy-beam and ion-trap facility <lb/>at NSCL/MSU, Nuclear Instruments and Methods in Physics Research Section A <lb/>532 (1–2) (2004) 203–209, http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/J.Nima.2004.06.046. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> R. Ringle et al. / International Journal of Mass Spectrometry 349– 350 (2013) 87– 93 <lb/></note>

			<page> 93 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [27] T. Sun, S. Schwarz, G. Bollen, D. Lawton, R. Ringle, P. Schury, European Physical <lb/>Journal A 25 (2005) 61–62, http://dx.doi.org/10.1140/Epjad/I2005-06-126-9. <lb/>[28] G. Gabrielse, J. Tan, Self-shielding superconducting solenoid systems, Jour-<lb/>nal of Applied Physics 63 (10) (1988) 5143–5148, http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/ <lb/>1.340416. <lb/>[29] G. Bollen, R.B. Moore, G. Savard, H. Stolzenberg, Journal of Applied Physics 68 <lb/>(9) (1990) 4355–4374. <lb/>[30] R. Ringle, G. Bollen, P. Schury, S. Schwarz, T. Sun, International Jour-<lb/>nal of Mass Spectrometry 262 (1–2) (2007) 33–44, http://dx.doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/J.Ijms.2006.10.009. <lb/>[31] S. Eliseev, M. Block, A. Chaudhuri, F. Herfurth, H.J. Kluge, A. Martin, C. Rauth, G. <lb/>Vorobjev, International Journal of Mass Spectrometry 262 (1–2) (2007) 45–50, <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ijms.2006.10.003. <lb/>[32] S. Eliseev, C. Roux, K. Blaum, M. Block, C. Droese, F. Herfurth, M. Kretzsch-<lb/>mar, M.I. Krivoruchenko, E. Minaya Ramirez, Y.N. Novikov, L. Schweikhard, <lb/>V.M. Shabaev, F. ˇ <lb/>Simkovic, I.I. Tupitsyn, K. Zuber, N.A. Zubova, Phys-<lb/>ical Review Letters 107 (15) (2011) 152501, http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/ <lb/>PhysRevLett.107.152501. <lb/>[33] R. Ringle, G. Bollen, A. Prinke, J. Savory, P. Schury, S. Schwarz, T. Sun, Nuclear <lb/>Instruments and Methods in Physics Research Section A 604 (3) (2009) <lb/>536–547, http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/J.Nima.2009.03.207. <lb/>[34] A.G. Marshall, C.L. Hendrickson, G.S. Jackson, Mass Spectrometry Reviews 17 <lb/>(1) (1998) 1–35. <lb/>[35] P. Schury, G. Bollen, M. Block, D.J. Morrissey, R. Ringle, A. Prinke, J. Savory, <lb/>S. Schwarz, T. Sun, Hyperfine Interactions 173 (1–3) (2006) 165–170, <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/S10751-007-9553-0. <lb/>[36] G. Savard, S. Becker, G. Bollen, H.-J.J. Kluge, R.B. Moore, T. Otto, L. Schweikhard, <lb/>H. Stolzenberg, U. Wiess, Physics Letters A 158 (5) (1991) 247–252, <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0375-9601(91)91008-2. <lb/>[37] S. Guan, G. Marshall, International Journal of Mass Spectrometry (1996) 5–37, <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0168-1176(96)04461-8. <lb/>[38] A. K. Kwiatkowski, PhD thesis, Michigan State University, 2011. <lb/>[39] G. Gräff, H. Kalinowsky, J. Traut, Zeitschrift für Physik A – Hadrons and Nuclei <lb/>297 (1) (1980) 35–39. <lb/>[40] M. König, G. Bollen, H.J.J. Kluge, T. Otto, J. Szerypo, International Journal of Mass <lb/>Spectrometry 142 (1–2) (1995) 95–116. <lb/>[41] R. Grzywacz, R. Beraud, C. Borcea, A. Emsallem, M. Glogowski, H. <lb/>Grawe, D. Guillemaud-Mueller, M. Hjorth-Jensen, M. Houry, M. Lewitow-<lb/>icz, A.C. Mueller, A. Nowak, A. Plochocki, M. Pfutzner, K. Rykaczewski, <lb/>M.G. Saint-Laurent, J.E. Sauvestre, M. Schaefer, O. Sorlin, J. Szerypo, W. <lb/>Trinder, S. Viteritti, J. Winfield, Physical Review Letters 81 (4) (1998) <lb/>766–769. <lb/>[42] M. Block, C. Bachelet, G. Bollen, M. Facina, C.M. Folden, C. Guenaut, A.A. <lb/>Kwiatkowski, D.J. Morrissey, G.K. Pang, A. Prinke, R. Ringle, J. Savory, <lb/>P. Schury, S. Schwarz, Physical Review Letters 101 (5) (2008) 059901, <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/Physrevlett.101.059901. <lb/>[43] R. Ferrer, M. Block, C. Bachelet, B.R. Barquest, G. Bollen, C.M. Campbell, M. Facina, <lb/>C.M. Folden, C. Guénaut, A.A. Kwiatkowski, D.L. Lincoln, D.J. Morrissey, G.K. <lb/>Pang, A.M. Prinke, R. Ringle, J. Savory, P. Schury, S. Schwarz, Physical Review C <lb/>81 (4) (2010) 044318, http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevC.81.044318. <lb/>[44] D. Pauwels, O. Ivanov, N. Bree, J. Buscher, T.E. Cocolios, J. Gentens, M. Huyse, <lb/>A. Korgul, Y. Kudryavtsev, R. Raabe, M. Sawicka, I. Stefanescu, J. de Walle, P. <lb/>den Bergh, P. Duppen, W.B. Walters, Physical Review C 78 (2008) 041307(R), <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevC.78.041307. <lb/>[45] J. Dobaczewski, I. Hamamoto, W. Nazarewicz, J.A. Sheikh, Physical Review Let-<lb/>ters 72 (7) (1994) 981–984. <lb/>[46] L. Gaudefroy, O. Sorlin, D. Beaumel, Y. Blumenfeld, Z. Dombrádi, S. Fortier, <lb/>S. Franchoo, M. Gelin, J. Gibelin, S. Grévy, F. Hammache, F. Ibrahim, K.W. <lb/>Kemper, K.L. Kratz, S.M. Lukyanov, C. Monrozeau, L. Nalpas, F. Nowacki, A.N. <lb/>Ostrowski, T. Otsuka, Y.E. Penionzhkevich, J. Piekarewicz, E.C. Pollacco, P. <lb/>Roussel-Chomaz, E. Rich, J.A. Scarpaci, M.G.S. Laurent, D. Sohler, M. Stanoiu, T. <lb/>Suzuki, E. Tryggestad, D. Verney, Physical Review Letters 97 (9) (2006) 092501, <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.97.092501. <lb/>[47] H. Scheit, T. Glasmacher, B.A. Brown, J.A. Brown, P.D. Cottle, P.G. Hansen, R. <lb/>Harkewicz, M. Hellstrom, R.W. Ibbotson, J.K. Jewell, K.W. Kemper, D.J. Mor-<lb/>rissey, M. Steiner, P. Thirolf, M. Thoennessen, Physical Review Letters 77 (19) <lb/>(1996) 3967–3970. <lb/>[48] T. Glasmacher, B.A. Brown, M.J. Chromik, P.D. Cottle, M. Fauerbach, R.W. Ibbot-<lb/>son, K.W. Kemper, D.J. Morrissey, H. Scheit, D.W. Sklenicka, M. Steiner, Physics <lb/>Letters B 395 (3–4) (1997) 163–168. <lb/>[49] D. Sohler, Z. Dombrádi, J. Timar, O. Sorlin, F. Azaiez, F. Amorini, M. Belleguic, <lb/>C. Bourgeois, C. Donzaud, J. Duprat, D. Guillemaud-Mueller, F. Ibrahim, J.A. <lb/>Scarpaci, M. Stanoiu, M.J. Lopez, M.G. Saint-Laurent, F. Becker, F. Sarazin, C. <lb/>Stodel, G. Voltolini, S.M. Lukyanov, V. Maslov, Y.E. Penionzhkevich, M. Girod, <lb/>S. Peru, F. Nowacki, G. Sletten, R. Lucas, C. Theisen, D. Baiborodin, Z. Dlouhy, J. <lb/>Mrazek, C. Borcea, A. Bauchet, C.J. Moore, M.J. Taylor, Physical Review C 66 (5) <lb/>(2002) 054302, http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevC.66.054302. <lb/>[50] R. Ringle, C. Bachelet, M. Block, G. Bollen, M. Facina, C.M. Folden, C. Gue-<lb/>naut, A.A. Kwiatkowski, D.J. Morrissey, G.K. Pang, A.M. Prinke, J. Savory, P. <lb/>Schury, S. Schwarz, C.S. Sumithrarachchi, Physical Review C 80 (2009) 064321, <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevC.80.064321. <lb/>[51] X.G. Zhou, X.L. Tu, J.M. Wouters, D.J. Vieira, K.E.G. Lobner, H.L. Seifert, Z.Y. Zhou, <lb/>G.W. Butler, Physics Letters B 260 (3–4) (1991) 285–290. <lb/>[52] B. Jurado, H. Savajols, W. Mittig, N.A. Orr, P. Roussel-Chomaz, D. Baiborodin, <lb/>W.N. Catford, M. Chartier, C.E. Demonchy, Z. Dlouhy, A. Gillibert, L. Giot, <lb/>A. Khouaja, A. Lépine-Szily, S. Lukyanov, J. Mrazek, Y.E. Penionzhkevich, <lb/>S. Pita, M. Rousseau, A.C. Villari, Physics Letters B 649 (1) (2007) 43–48, <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.physletb.2007.04.006. <lb/>[53] F. Sarazin, H. Savajols, W. Mittig, F. Nowacki, N.A. Orr, Z. Ren, P. Roussel-<lb/>Chomaz, G. Auger, D. Baiborodin, A.V. Belozyorov, C. Borcea, E. Caurier, Z. <lb/>Dlouhy, A. Gillibert, A.S. Lalleman, M. Lewitowicz, S.M. Lukyanov, F. de Oliveira, <lb/>Y.E. Penionzhkevich, D. Ridikas, W. Sakurai, O. Tarasov, A. de Vismes, Physical <lb/>Review Letters 84 (22) (2000) 5062–5065. <lb/>[54] H. Schatz, International Journal of Mass Spectrometry 251 (2–3) (2006) <lb/>293–299, http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ijms.2006.02.014. <lb/>[55] R.K. Wallace, S.E. Woosley, Astrophysical Journal Supplement Series 45 (1981) <lb/>389–420. <lb/>[56] B.A. Brown, R.R.C. Clement, H. Schatz, A. Volya, W.A. Richter, Physical Review <lb/>C 65 (2002) 045802, http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevC.045802. <lb/>[57] G. Audi, A.H. Wapstra, C. Thibault, Nuclear Physics A 729 (1) (2003) 337–676, <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.nuclphysa.2003.11.003. <lb/>[58] J. Savory, P. Schury, C. Bachelet, M. Block, G. Bollen, M. Facina, C.M. Folden, <lb/>C. Guenaut, E. Kwan, A.A. Kwiatkowski, D.J. Morrissey, G.K. Pang, A. Prinke, R. <lb/>Ringle, H. Schatz, S. Schwarz, C.S. Sumithrarachchi, Physical Review Letters 102 <lb/>(13) (2009) 132501, http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/Physrevlett.102.132501. <lb/>[59] P. Schury, C. Bachelet, M. Block, G. Bollen, M. Facina, C.M. Folden, C. Guenaut, J. <lb/>Huikari, E. Kwan, A. Kwiatkowski, D.J. Morrissey, R. Ringle, G.K. Pang, A. Prinke, <lb/>J. Savory, H. Schatz, S. Schwarz, C.S. Sumithrarachchi, T. Sun, Physical Review C <lb/>75 (2007) 055801, http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/Physrevc.75.055801. <lb/>[60] S. Weinberg, S.B. Treiman, Physical Review 116 (2) (1959) 465–468. <lb/>[61] E.P. Wigner, Proceedings of the Robert A. Welch Foundation Conference on <lb/>Chemical Research 1, 1957. <lb/>[62] K. Blaum, G. Audi, D. Beck, G. Bollen, F. Herfurth, A. Kellerbauer, H.-J. <lb/>Kluge, E. Sauvan, S. Schwarz, Physical Review Letters 91 (26) (2003) 260801, <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.91.260801. <lb/>[63] S. Triambak, A. García, E.G. Adelberger, G.J.P. Hodges, D. Melconian, H.E. Swan-<lb/>son, S.A. Hoedl, S.K.L. Sjue, A.L. Sallaska, H. Iwamoto, Physical Review C 73 <lb/>(2006) 054313, http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevC.73.054313. <lb/>[64] A.A. Kwiatkowski, B.R. Barquest, G. Bollen, C.M. Campbell, D.L. Lincoln, D.J. <lb/>Morrissey, G.K. Pang, A.M. Prinke, J. Savory, S. Schwarz, C.M. Folden, D. <lb/>Melconian, S.K.L. Sjue, M. Block, Physical Review C 80 (2009) 051302(R), <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevC.80.051302. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
