<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="headnote"> arXiv:1501.03621v1  [math-ph] 15 Jan 2015 <lb/></note>

			<front> Classification of multipartite systems featuring only |W  and |GHZ genuine <lb/>entangled states <lb/> Frédéric Holweck <lb/> a)  , Péter Lévay <lb/> b)c) <lb/> In this paper we present several multipartite quantum systems featuring the same <lb/>type of genuine (tripartite) entanglement. Based on a geometric interpretation of the <lb/>so-called |W and |GHZ states we show that the classification of all multipartite <lb/>systems featuring those and only those two classes of genuine entanglement can be <lb/>deduced from earlier work of algebraic geometers. This classification corresponds in <lb/>fact to classification of fundamental subadjoint varieties and establish a connection <lb/>between those systems, well known in Quantum Information Theory and fundamental <lb/>simple Lie algebras. <lb/> a)  frederic.holweck@utbm.fr, Laboratoire IRTES-M3M, Université de Technologie de Belfort-Montbéliard, <lb/>90010 Belfort Cedex, France <lb/> b)  levay@phy.bme.hu, Department of Theoretical Physics, Institute of Physics, Budapest University of Tech-<lb/>nology and Economics , H-1521 Budapest, Hungary <lb/> c)  Hungarian Academy of Sciences <lb/></front>

			<page> 1 <lb/></page>

			<body> I. INTRODUCTION <lb/> Entanglement is a key resource of quantum information. It corresponds to a form of <lb/>correlation between subsystems of a given composite system which is stronger than any cor-<lb/>relation arising from classical communication <lb/> 1  . Since the advent of Quantum Information a <lb/>large amount of experimental and theoretical evidence demonstrates that quantum protocols <lb/>featuring this phenomenon exist that can overperform their classical counterparts. Beyond <lb/>this entanglement is of basic importance for obtaining new communication protocols such as <lb/>quantum teleportation, quantum superdense codding or quantum cryptography. It is also <lb/>acknowledged that quantum entanglement plays a central role in quantum algorithms and <lb/>quantum computation <lb/> 23,34  . <lb/>Quantum entanglement is a consequence of the superposition principle. Let us illustrate <lb/>this for a bipartite system. Given two copies of two-state systems (qubits) represented by <lb/>the vectors |ψ  A  ∈ H  A  and |ψ  B  ∈ H  B  with H  A  ≃ H  B  ≃ C <lb/> 2  , we define the composite system <lb/>of two qubits as the one represented by the tensor product H = H  A  ⊗ H  B  . Then a canonical <lb/>basis of H is {|00, |01, |10, |11} and the superposition principle tells us that one possible <lb/>state for the composite system is <lb/> |ψ  AB  = <lb/>1 <lb/> √ <lb/> 2 <lb/>(|00 + |11). <lb/> (1) <lb/>However, |ψ  AB  cannot be created from an initial state of type |ϕ  A  ⊗ |χ  B  by applying <lb/>only local operations (i.e. operations acting on |ϕ  A  and |χ  B  separately). Such states are <lb/>called entangled. Since entangled states cannot be generated locally they correspond to a <lb/>global resource shared by the actors of the protocol. On the other hand a state is said to be <lb/>separable if it can be generated locally from a state of the form |ϕ  A  ⊗ |χ  B  . <lb/>The multipartite generalization of our example provides the basic resource for Quantum <lb/>Information. However, as a resource entanglement needs to be classified. One possible <lb/>classification scheme is obtained by finding equivalence classes of entangled states under <lb/>Stochastic Local Operations and Classical Communications (SLOCC). SLOCC transforma-<lb/>tions are the mathematical representatives of certain physical manipulations allowed to be <lb/>performed on our composite system. These manipulations are consisting of local reversible <lb/>operations on each component of the multipartite system assisted by classical communi-<lb/>cation (i.e. the local operations may be coordinated). The word stochastic refers to the <lb/>possibility of converting a particular state of the system to another one and vice versa with <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body> some (generally different) probability of success. The mathematical representative of such <lb/>SLOCC transformations turns out to be a group acting on the Hilbert space of the composite <lb/>system. The precise form of this group will depend on the observables characterizing this <lb/>system. <lb/>The classification of entanglement classes of multipartite systems under SLOCC has been <lb/>investigated in the last 10 years by many authors <lb/> 2,3,6,11–13,18,19,30–33,36,39,40  . Interestingly under <lb/>SLOCC some <lb/> 3,6,11,13,30,36,39  of these entangled systems is featuring two genuine types of <lb/>entanglement. The aim of this paper for these systems is to provide a unified approach <lb/>based on recent results of algebraic geometry. <lb/>The paper is organized as follow. In Section II we introduce a geometric interpretation <lb/> 18,19 <lb/> of the entangled classes |W  and |GHZ which correspond to the two genuine entangled <lb/>classes in the Dür, Vidal and Cirac <lb/> 13  &apos;s classification of entanglement classes of three qubits. <lb/>Thanks to this geometric interpretation we can use, in Section III, classical results of in-<lb/>variant theory and algebraic geometry to classify all Hilbert spaces and quantum systems <lb/>which will feature those two and exactly those two types of genuine entangled classes. In <lb/>this process we recover different quantum systems investigated in the quantum information <lb/>literature and three new cases. The corresponding Hilbert spaces have a similar SLOCC <lb/>orbit structure (except for the case of three bosonic qubits see Remark III.2). We also <lb/>classify quantum systems with two and exactly two entanglement classes (not necessarly of <lb/>type |W and |GHZ). The connexion of those quantum systems with classification results <lb/>from algebraic geometry allows to give a uniform description of those quantum systems and <lb/>establish a link between those systems and the simple Lie algebras. In particular we collect <lb/>some geometrical information about such system in Appendix A. <lb/> Notations. In the text V (resp. H) will denote a vector (resp. Hilbert) space over <lb/>the field of complex numbers C, and P(V ) (resp. P(H)) will denote the corresponding <lb/>projective space. A vector v ∈ V will be projectivized to a point [v] ∈ P(V ). A projective <lb/>algebraic variety X ⊂ P(V ) will be defined as the zero locus of a collection of homogeneous <lb/>polynomials. A point [x] ∈ X will be said to be smooth if and only if the partial derivatives <lb/>of the defining equations do not simultaneously vanish at [x]. If [x] ∈ X is smooth, one can <lb/>define  <lb/>  x  X ⊂ P(V ) the embedded tangent space of X at [x]. <lb/> In this article we only consider pure quantum systems, i.e. a state |ψ of such systems <lb/>will always be considered as a (normalized) vector of H. <lb/></body>

			<page> 3 <lb/></page>

			<body> II. THE THREE QUBIT CLASSIFICATION REVISITED <lb/> Starting from the paper of Dür, Vidal and Cirac <lb/> 13  three-qubit entanglement has given rise <lb/>to a number of interesting applications <lb/> 4,7,10,22,29  . Let us denote by H  A  , H  B  and H  C  the three <lb/>Hilbert spaces isomorphic to C <lb/> 2  corresponding to qubits A, B and C, then the Hilbert space <lb/>of the composite system is H = H  A  ⊗ H  B  ⊗ H  C  . In this section for simplicity let us adopt <lb/>the notation |ψ  A  ≡ ψ  A  . If we forget about scalar normalization the relevant SLOCC group <lb/>turns out to be GL  2  (C) × GL  2  (C) × GL  2  (C) and the result established in Ref <lb/> 13  states that <lb/>under SLOCC action three qubits can be organized into six orbits i.e. SLOCC entanglement <lb/>classes (Table I). The three qubits classification features the interesting property of having <lb/> Name <lb/> Normal form <lb/>Separable <lb/> |000 <lb/> Biseparable <lb/> 1 <lb/> √ <lb/> 2 <lb/>(|000 + |011) <lb/> Biseparable <lb/> 1 <lb/> √ <lb/> 2 <lb/>(|000 + |101) <lb/> Biseparable <lb/> 1 <lb/> √ <lb/> 2 <lb/>(|000 + |110) <lb/>|W <lb/> 1 <lb/> √ <lb/> 3 <lb/>(|100 + |010 + |001) <lb/>|GHZ <lb/> 1 <lb/> √ <lb/> 2 <lb/>(|000 + |111) <lb/> Table I. Three qubit classification <lb/> exactly two classes of genuine entanglement, called the |W and |GHZ classes. It should be <lb/>also clear that, for instance, for the bipartite state |ψ = <lb/>1 <lb/> √ <lb/> 2 <lb/>(|000 + |101), particles A and <lb/> C are entangled while B is not. Note that from the projective point of view multiplication <lb/>by a nonzero scalar does not change the nature of the state and thus we can instead consider <lb/>the SL  2  (C) × SL  2  (C) × SL  2  (C) orbits of P(H). It turns out that this classification was <lb/>known, from mathematical perspective, since the work of Le Paige <lb/> 28  . Motivated by this <lb/>example we can adress the basic question of our paper as: which other types of quantum <lb/>systems do have two and only two types of genuine non-equivalent entangled states? <lb/>Following Ref <lb/> 18  let us rephrase the classification of three qubit entanglement classes by <lb/>means of algebraic geometry. In the projectivized Hilbert space P(H) we consider the image <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body> of the following map: <lb/> φ : P(H  A  ) × P(H  B  ) × P(H  C  ) → <lb/> P(H) <lb/> ([ψ  A  ], [ψ  B  ], [ψ  C  ]) <lb/> → [ψ  A  ⊗ ψ  B  ⊗ ψ  C  ] <lb/> (2) <lb/>The map φ is well-known as the Segre map <lb/> 17,20  . Let X = φ(P(H  A  ) × P(H  B  ) × P(H  C  )) ⊂ <lb/> P(H), in what follows we will denote this image simply by X = P <lb/> 1  × P <lb/> 1  × P <lb/> 1  because the <lb/>projectivization of the Hilbert space of each particle clearly corresponds to a projective line <lb/>(P(H) = P(C <lb/> 2  ) = P <lb/> 1  ). It can be easily shown that X is a smooth projective algebraic <lb/>variety <lb/> 17  . It is also clear that the variety X is the G = SL  2  (C) × SL  2  (C) × SL  2  (C) orbit of <lb/>any rank one tensor in P(H). Indeed given [ψ  A  ⊗ ψ  B  ⊗ ψ  C  ], then for any [ ˜ <lb/> ψ  A  ⊗ ˜ <lb/> ψ  B  ⊗ ˜ <lb/> ψ  C  ], <lb/> there exists g = (g  1  , g  2  , g  3  ) ∈ G such that [ ˜ <lb/> ψ  A  ⊗ ˜ <lb/> ψ  B  ⊗ ˜ <lb/> ψ  C  ] = [(g  1  ·ψ  A  )⊗(g  2  ·ψ  B  )⊗(g  3  ·ψ  C  )]. In <lb/>terms of quantum entanglement it follows from this description that the variety X represents <lb/>the set of separable states and can be described as the projectivized orbit of ψ = |000, i.e. <lb/> X = G · [|000] ⊂ P(H). <lb/> Similarly to what was done in Ref <lb/> 18,19  our goal is now to build from the algebraic variety <lb/>of separable states some auxiliary varieties which will encode different type of entanglement <lb/>classes. Consider Y <lb/> n  ⊂ P(V <lb/> n+a+1  ) a projective algebraic variety of dimension n embedded <lb/>in a projective space of dimension n + a, such that Y is smooth and not contained in a <lb/>hyperplane. Then one defines the secant variety <lb/> 41  of Y , denoted by σ(Y ), as the algebraic <lb/>closure, for the Zariski topology, of the union of secant lines of Y (Eq. (3)) <lb/> σ(Y ) = <lb/> x,y∈Y <lb/> P  1 <lb/> xy <lb/> (3) <lb/>Another interesting auxiliary variety is the tangential variety of Y , which is defined as the <lb/>union of embedded tangent spaces, ˜ <lb/> T  y  Y of Y (Eq. (4)) <lb/> τ (Y ) = <lb/> y∈Y <lb/>  y  Y <lb/> (4) <lb/>One point of importance is the following: If the variety Y is G-invariant for the action of a <lb/>group G (i.e. if y ∈ Y then g.y ∈ Y for all g ∈ G) then so are the varieties τ (Y ) and σ(Y ). <lb/> This property follows from the defintions of the two auxiliary varieties σ(Y ) and τ (Y ) which <lb/>are built from points of Y . <lb/>Clearly τ (Y ) ⊂ σ(Y ), as tangent lines can be seen as limits of secant lines, and the <lb/>expected dimensions of those varieties are min{2n, n + a} for τ (Y ) and min{2n + 1, n + a} <lb/></body>

			<page> 5 <lb/></page>

			<body> for σ(Y ). A consequence of the Fulton-Hansen connectedness Theorem <lb/> 14  is the following <lb/>corollary which will be central to what follows. <lb/> Proposition II.1. [Corollary 4 of Ref <lb/> 14  ] One of the following must hold <lb/>1. dim(τ (Y )) = 2n and dim(σ(Y )) = 2n + 1, or <lb/>2. τ (Y ) = σ(Y ). <lb/> If we go back to the case where X = P <lb/> 1  × P <lb/> 1  × P <lb/> 1  ⊂ P <lb/> 7  , a standard calculation <lb/> 1  shows <lb/>that dim(σ(X)) = 7, i.e. the secant variety is of expected dimension and fills the ambient <lb/>space. Therefore one automaticaly knows that τ (X) exists and is of codimension one in P <lb/> 7  . <lb/>Moreover given a general pair of points (x, y) ∈ X × X denoted by x = [ψ  A  ⊗ ψ  B  ⊗ ψ  C  ] and <lb/> y = [ ˜ <lb/> ψ  A  ⊗ ˜ <lb/> ψ  B  ⊗ ˜ <lb/> ψ  C  ] it is not difficult to see that there exists g = (g  1  , g  2  , g  3  ) ∈ SL  2  (C) × <lb/> SL  2  (C) × SL  2  (C) such that [g.(|000 + |111)] = [(g  1  .|0) ⊗ (g  2  .|0) ⊗ (g  3  .|0) + (g  1  .|1) ⊗ <lb/> (g  2  .|1) ⊗ (g  3  .|1) = [ψ  A  ⊗ ψ  B  ⊗ ψ  C  + ˜ <lb/> ψ  A  ⊗ ˜ <lb/> ψ  B  ⊗ ˜ <lb/> ψ  C  ]. In other words we have for G = <lb/> SL  2  (C) × SL  2  (C) × SL  2  (C) <lb/> σ(X) = σ(G.[|000]) = G.[|000 + |111] <lb/> (5) <lb/>Similarly one can provide an orbit description of τ (X): Let γ(t) = [(ψ  A  + t ˜ <lb/> ψ  A  ) ⊗ (ψ  B  + <lb/> t ˜ <lb/> ψ  B  ) ⊗ (ψ  C  + t ˜ <lb/> ψ  C  )] be a general curve of X passing through [ψ  A  ⊗ ψ  B  ⊗ ψ  C  ] such that ψ  i <lb/> and  <lb/>  i  are not colinear. Then a straightforward calculation shows that after differentiation <lb/>we get γ <lb/> ′  (0) = [ ˜ <lb/> ψ  A  ⊗ ψ  B  ⊗ ψ  C  + ψ  A  ⊗ ˜ <lb/> ψ  B  ⊗ ψ  C  + ψ  A  ⊗ ψ  B  ⊗ ˜ <lb/> ψ  C  ] ∈ ˜ <lb/> T  [ψ  A  ⊗ψ  B  ⊗ψ  C  ]  X. Again <lb/>under the group action G this calculation tells us that <lb/> τ (X) = τ (G.[|000]) = G.[|100 + |010 + |001] <lb/> (6) <lb/>Equations (5) and (6) say that the |GHZ and |W states form open subsets of the <lb/>secant and tangential varieties of the set of separable states respectively. Moreover, the fact <lb/>that the secant variety has the expected dimension implies that those two states are non <lb/>equivalent. Considering the biseparabe states the geometric picture can be completed as <lb/>follows: <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 1  The dimension of secant variety can be calculated via the Terracini&apos;s Lemma. The case we are interested <lb/>in, is for instance explicitly done in Ref <lb/> 24  example 5.3.1.5 page 123. Calculations involving Terracini&apos;s <lb/>Lemma in the context of QIT can also be found in Ref <lb/> 18,19 <lb/></note>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<body> σ(X) = P  7 <lb/> τ (P  1  × P  1  × P  1  ) <lb/> ❚ <lb/> ❚ <lb/>❚ <lb/>❚ <lb/>❚ <lb/>❚ <lb/>❚ <lb/>❚ <lb/>❚ <lb/>❚ <lb/>❚ <lb/>❚ <lb/>❚ <lb/>❚ <lb/>❚ <lb/> σ(P  1  × P  1  ) × P  1 <lb/> ❦ <lb/>❦ <lb/>❦ <lb/>❦ <lb/>❦ <lb/>❦ <lb/>❦ <lb/>❦ <lb/>❦ <lb/>❦ <lb/>❦ <lb/>❦ <lb/>❦ <lb/>❦ <lb/>❙ <lb/>❙ <lb/>❙ <lb/>❙ <lb/>❙ <lb/>❙ <lb/>❙ <lb/>❙ <lb/>❙ <lb/>❙ <lb/>❙ <lb/>❙ <lb/>❙ <lb/>❙ <lb/> P  1  × σ(P  1  × P  1  ) <lb/> σ(P  1  × P  1  × P  1  ) × P  1 <lb/> X = P  1  × P  1  × P  1 <lb/> • <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/> Figure 1. Stratification of the projectivized Hilbert space of three qubits by secant and tangential <lb/>varieties. <lb/> In Figure 1 the lines represent inclusions as algebraic varieties and σ(P <lb/> 1  × P <lb/> 1  × P <lb/> 1  ) × P <lb/> 1 <lb/> is a notation introduced in Ref <lb/> 18  to denote the variety of the closure of secant lines of X <lb/> between points of type [u ⊗ v ⊗ w] and [˜ u ⊗ v ⊗ ˜ <lb/> w]. <lb/> Based on the previous analysis we see, that an alternative way of saying: <lb/> « Three qubits have two non equivalent classes of genuine entanglement, one of type <lb/> |GHZ and the other of type |W » <lb/> would be, in geometrical terms, <lb/> «The secant variety of the set of separable states P <lb/> 1  × P <lb/> 1  × P <lb/> 1  has the expected dimension <lb/>and fills the ambient space». <lb/> In Section III we show what this last geometric formulation tells us about other types of <lb/>multipartite systems. <lb/> III. THE GEOMETRY OF TRIPARTITE ENTANGLEMENT <lb/> Let us now consider a semi-simple complex Lie group G and an irreducible G-module H, <lb/> i.e. a vector space such that G acts on H and does not contain any nontrivial submodule. <lb/>We call H an irreducible representation of G. Taking the projective space P(H) there exists <lb/>a unique smooth orbit X = G.[v] ⊂ P(H) called the highest weight orbit <lb/> 2  . In the case of <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 2  Highest weight vectors are defined after a choice of an ordering of the roots of the Lie algebra g = Lie(G) <lb/> which defines for each irreducible representation a unique highest weight <lb/> 15  . There is a bijection between <lb/>the highest weights (up to a choice of an ordering of the root system) and the irreducible representations <lb/>of G. <lb/></note>

			<page> 7 <lb/></page>

			<body> three qubits we have H = C <lb/> 2  ⊗ C <lb/> 2  ⊗ C <lb/> 2  , G = SL  2  (C) × SL  2  (C) × SL  2  (C) and v = |000, <lb/> i.e. X = G · [|000] = P({|ψ separable}. Let us look at an other standard example. <lb/> Example III.1. We consider G = SL  6  (C) and H = Λ <lb/> 3  C <lb/> 6  . The vector space H is an <lb/>irreducible representation of G (more generaly Λ <lb/> k  V are irreducible representations of SL(V ) <lb/> called the fundamental representations, see Ref <lb/> 15  page 221). Given (e  1  , e  2  , . . . , e  6  ) a basis <lb/>of C <lb/> 6  , a highest weight vector can be chosen to be v = e  1  ∧ e  2  ∧ e  3  . Then in this case <lb/> X = SL  6  (C) · [e  1  ∧ e  2  ∧ e  3  ] ⊂ P(Λ <lb/> 3  C <lb/> 6  ) = P <lb/> 19  . The variety X represents the set of 3-<lb/>dimensional planes in C <lb/> 6  also known as the Grassmannian G(3, 6). Given a three plane of <lb/> C <lb/> 6  spanned by u, v and w we can always find g ∈ SL  6  (C) such that [g · (e  1  ∧ e  2  ∧ e  3  )] = <lb/>[g · e  1  ∧ g · e  2  ∧ g · e  3  ] = [u ∧ v ∧ w]. In terms of skew-symmetric tensors, the variety X is <lb/>the set of rank one tensors in H. Now let us recall that, in quantum information theory, <lb/> H = Λ <lb/> 3  C <lb/> 6  is the Hilbert space describing systems made of three fermions with six single-<lb/>particles states. Then, from the above description, it follows that for three fermions with <lb/>six single-particle states, X = G(3, 6) is the set of separable states and G = SL  6  (C) is the <lb/>corresponding SLOCC group. <lb/> Remark III.1. Let P ⊂ G denotes the stabilizer of the highest weight v ∈ H, then <lb/> X = G/P and X = G/P ⊂ P(H) realizes the minimal embedding of the homogenous <lb/>variety G/P . The subgroup P ⊂ G is called a parabolic subgroup of G <lb/> 15  . <lb/> Based on our geometric interpretation of the classes |GHZ and |W in the three qubits <lb/>case, let us ask a more general question: what are the semi-simple Lie groups G and the <lb/>corresponding irreducible representations H such that <lb/> τ (X)  σ(X) = P(H) <lb/> (7) <lb/>where X is arising from the projectivization of the highest weight vector ? <lb/>First it should be noticed that σ(X) = σ(G/P ) = P(H) and τ (X) is a hypersurface <lb/>of P(H) imply the ring of G-invariant polynomials on H is generated by the G-invariant <lb/> irreducible polynomial vanishing on τ (X), i.e. C[H] <lb/> G  = C[F ] where F is the irrecudible <lb/>(up to scale) homogeneous polynomial defining τ (X). Indeed the fact that σ(G/P ) = P(H) <lb/> says there is a dense orbit (because the secant variety is always the closure of the orbit <lb/> G.[u + v] where (u, v) is a general pair of points of X, see Ref <lb/> 41  ). Therefore there are either <lb/>no invariants or the ring of invariants is generated by a single polynomial. The fact that <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body> τ (X) is a G-invariant hypersurface tells us we are in the second case. The representations <lb/>such that C[H] <lb/> G  = C[F ] have been classified by Kac, Popov and Vinberg <lb/> 21  . It can be <lb/>deduced from this classification which representations satisfy σ(G.[v]) = P(H) = P <lb/> 2n+1 <lb/> where the highest weight orbit G.[v] has dimension n. This is in fact done explicitly in the <lb/>book of F. Zak <lb/> 41  page 51 and 53 where the author studies in detail homogeneous varieties of <lb/>small codimension in order to understand a special class of them called the Severi varieties. <lb/>We summerize the result of Zak in Table II and we put in perspective the corresponding <lb/>systems in quantum information theory as well as the references where those cases have been <lb/>separately investigated. The notations of Table II are as follow: <lb/>• Sym <lb/> n  V and Λ <lb/> n  V denote respectively the symmetric and skew-symmetric parts of V <lb/> ⊗n  . <lb/>• v  k  : P(V ) → P(Sym <lb/> k  V ) is the Veronese map defined by v  k  ([v]) = [v • v • · · · • v] and <lb/> v  2  (P <lb/> 1  ) and v  3  (P <lb/> 1  ) are curves corresponding to the images of P <lb/> 1  by v  2  and v  3  also known <lb/>as the conic and the twisted cubic <lb/> 17  . <lb/>• Q <lb/> n−1  ⊂ P <lb/> n  denotes a smooth quadric in P <lb/> n  . <lb/>• The variety LG(k, n) ⊂ P(Λ <lb/> &lt;k&gt;  C <lb/> n  ) is the so-called Lagrangian Grassmannian. Given <lb/>a non degenerate symplectic form ω on C <lb/> n  , LG(k, n) is the variety of isotropic k-planes <lb/> in C <lb/> n  with respect to ω. <lb/> • As already mentioned in Example III.1, the variety G(k, n) ⊂ P(Λ <lb/> k  C <lb/> n  ) is the Grass-<lb/>mannian variety of k-planes in C <lb/> n  . <lb/>• The vector space ∆  12  is the standard representation of the group Spin  12  , i.e. the <lb/>double covering of SO(12), see Ref <lb/> 15  . The variety S  6  ⊂ P(∆  12  ) is the corresponding <lb/>highest weight orbit, called the Spinor variety. It is the variety of pure spinors <lb/> 8  . <lb/>• The vector space V  56  is the standard representation of the Lie group E  7  and E  7  /P  1 <lb/> denotes the corresponding highest weight orbit (in terms of parabolic groups P  1  cor-<lb/>responds to the parabolic group defined by the root α  1  ). <lb/>Table II provides a classification of quantum systems featuring two and only two classes of <lb/>genuine entanglement of types |W and |GHZ. Although most of these systems have been <lb/>studied independently by various authors of the quantum information theory community, it <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body> G <lb/> H <lb/> Highest weight orbit <lb/>QIT interpretation <lb/>References <lb/> SL  2  (C) <lb/> Sym  3  (C  2  ) <lb/> v  3  (P  1  ) ⊂ P  3 <lb/> Three bosonic <lb/>Brody, Gustavsson, Hughston. 6 <lb/>qubits <lb/>Vrana and Lévay 39 <lb/> SL  2  (C) × SO(m) <lb/>m = 3 <lb/> C  2  ⊗ Sym  2  (C  2  ) P  1  × v  2  (P  1  ) ⊂ P  5 <lb/> 1 distinguished qubit <lb/>Vrana and Lévay 39 <lb/>and 2 bosonic qubits <lb/> m = 4 <lb/> C  2  ⊗ C  2  ⊗ C  2  P  1  × P  1  × P  1  ⊂ P  7 <lb/> 3 qubits <lb/>Dür, Vidal, Cirac 13 <lb/> m = 5 <lb/> C  2  ⊗ Λ  &lt;2&gt;  C  4  P  1  × LG(2, 4) ⊂ P  9 <lb/> 1 distinguished qubit <lb/>New <lb/>and two fermions with <lb/>4 single-particle state <lb/>and a symplectic form condition <lb/> m = 6 <lb/> C  2  ⊗ Λ  2  C  4 <lb/> P  1  × G(2, 4) ⊂ P  11 <lb/> 1 qubit and two fermions <lb/>Vrana and Lévay  39 <lb/> with 4 single-particle states <lb/> m &gt; 6 <lb/> C  2  ⊗ C  m <lb/> P  1  × Q  m−2  ⊂ P  2m−1 1 qubit and 1 isotropic (m-1)-dits <lb/>New <lb/> Sp  6  (C) <lb/>Λ  &lt;3&gt;  C  6 <lb/> LG(3, 6) ⊂ P  13 <lb/> Three fermions <lb/>New <lb/>with six single-particle states <lb/>and a symplectic form condition <lb/> SL  6  (C) <lb/>Λ  3  C  6 <lb/> G(3, 6) ⊂ P  19 <lb/> Three fermions <lb/>Levay and Vrana 30 <lb/>with six single-particle states <lb/> Spin  12 <lb/> ∆  12 <lb/> S  6  ⊂ P  31 <lb/> Particles in <lb/>Sárosi and Lévay 36 <lb/>Fermionic Fock spaces <lb/> E  7 <lb/> V  56 <lb/> E  7  /P  1  ⊂ P  55 <lb/> Tripartite entanglement <lb/>Duff and Ferrara  11 <lb/> of seven qubits <lb/> Table II. Classification of smooth G-orbits satisfying τ (G.[v])  σ(G.[v)) = P(H) <lb/> is interesting to point out here that thanks to the work of F. Zak now a purely geometric <lb/>approach allows us to present them in a unique classification scheme. As we will discuss it <lb/>in the Appendix A this classification also corresponds to the classification of Freudenthal <lb/>varieties. The role of Freudenthal construction in the study of those quantum systems, in <lb/>particular the role of Freudenthal triple systems (FTS) has been already understood and <lb/>used by different authors <lb/> 3,5,39  . The Hilbert spaces and quantum systems of our Table II <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body> obtained by geometric arguments are the same Hilbert spaces and SLOCC groups of Table <lb/>II of Ref <lb/> 3  built from FTS. However the FTS construction does not show that this Table <lb/>provides a complete classification of quantum systems featuring this pecular entanglement <lb/>behavior. <lb/>Let us also point out that three new types of quantum systems with entanglement classes <lb/>similar to the three qubit systems appear in this classification. Their set of separables states <lb/>correspond to the following three algebraic varieties: <lb/>i) X = P <lb/> 1  × LG(2, 4) ⊂ P <lb/> 9  , <lb/>ii) X = LG(3, 6) ⊂ P <lb/> 13 <lb/> iii) X = P <lb/> 1  × Q <lb/> m−2  ⊂ P <lb/> 2m−1  , m &gt; 6. <lb/> As mentioned in Table II, the first system is made of a distinguished qubit and two <lb/>fermions with four single-particle states satisfying a symplectic condition and the second <lb/>system corresponds to three fermions with six single-particle states satisfying a symplectic <lb/>condition. The last new case corresponds to a system made of a qubit and a m − 1-dits <lb/> (m &gt; 6) which satisfies an isotropic condition given by a quadratic form. <lb/> Remark III.2. The orbit structure of the projectivized Hilbert spaces P(H) with the SLOCC <lb/>groups G of Table II is fully provided by Ref <lb/> 25  . In particular the authors show that, except <lb/>for G = SL  2  (C) and H = Sym <lb/> 3  (C <lb/> 2  ) (three bosonic qubits), there are exactly 4 orbits. The <lb/>Zariski closures of those orbits can be described as follow: <lb/> X <lb/> Separable <lb/> ⊂ σ  +  (X) <lb/> Biseparable <lb/> ⊂ τ (X) <lb/> |W <lb/> ⊂ σ(X) <lb/> |GHZ <lb/> = P(H) <lb/> (8) <lb/> The variety σ  +  (X) is the closure of points of type |ψ + |χ where |ψ and |χ are two <lb/>separable states which do not form a generic pair (see Ref <lb/> 25  for the description of the isotropic <lb/>condition satisfied by this pair (|ψ, |χ)). The smooth points of σ  +  (X) are therefore identified <lb/>with biseparable states. This variety is irreducible except in the case of three qubits where <lb/> σ  +  (P <lb/> 1  × P <lb/> 1  × P <lb/> 1  ) splits in three irreducible components (see Figure 1). <lb/>For three bosonic qubits, X = v  3  (P <lb/> 1  ), the orbit structure is sligthly different. It is only <lb/>made of three orbits as there is no variety such as σ  +  (X). <lb/></body>

			<page> 11 <lb/></page>

			<body> We conclude this Section with a variation of our initial problem. Instead of classifying <lb/>systems with two and only two classes of genuine entanglement of type |W  and |GHZ, <lb/> let us consider systems having two and only two types of genuine entanglement (but not <lb/>necessarly featuring |W and |GHZ). <lb/> Example III.2. Let H = C <lb/> 3  ⊗ C <lb/> 3  , G = SL  3  (C) × SL  3  (C), and X = G.[|00] = P <lb/> 2  × <lb/> P <lb/> 2  ⊂ P <lb/> 8  = P(H), i.e. X is the set of separable states of two qutrits. The variety X can <lb/>also be identified with the projectivization of the rank one 3 × 3 matrices and P(H) is the <lb/>projectivization of the space of 3 × 3 matrices. Under the action of SLOCC group G, it is <lb/>well known that we have only three orbits: <lb/> X = P{Matrices of rank 1} ⊂ P{Matrices of rank ≤ 2} ⊂ P{Matrices of rank ≤ 3} = P <lb/> 8 <lb/> (9) <lb/> Then the variety of rank less than two matrices is the secant variety of X and general points <lb/>of this variety correspond to the orbit of the state |ψ = |00 + |11. But in this example <lb/>there is no tangential variety because of dimension condition. Indeed dim(σ(X)) = 7 &lt; <lb/> 2 × 4 + 1 and by Proposition II.1 we have σ(X) = τ (X). Thus this is an example of a <lb/>multipartite system with two and only two types of non equivalent entangled states but there <lb/>is no entangled class of type |W . <lb/> It is clear form the previous example that quantum systems with only two types of genuine <lb/>entangled classes which are not considered in Table II should correspond to systems whose <lb/>set of separable states X ⊂ P(H) satisfies the following geometric conditions: <lb/> dim(σ(X)) &lt; 2dim(X)+1 and there is a SLOCC orbit corresponding to P(H)\σ(X) (10) <lb/>In turns out that the classification of homogeneous varieties X = G/P under the con-<lb/>ditions of Eq. (10) can also be deduced from Zak&apos;s work (See Ref <lb/> 41  page 54 and 59). We <lb/>summerize this result in Table III. The notations for Table III are as follows: <lb/>• V  27  is the standard representation of E  6  and E  6  /P  1  is the highest weight orbit. <lb/>The first four varieties of Table III are the so-called Severi varieties studied by F. Zak <lb/> 41  . <lb/>In terms of entanglement Tables II and III lead to the following result. <lb/> Theorem 1. The pure quantum systems having two and only two type of genuine entangle-<lb/>ment classes are classified by Tables II and III. <lb/></body>

			<page> 12 <lb/></page>

			<body> G <lb/> H <lb/> Highest weight orbit <lb/>QIT interpretation <lb/> SL  2  (C) <lb/> Sym  2  (C  3  ) v  2  (P  2  ) ⊂ P  5 <lb/> Two bosons <lb/>with 3 single-particle states <lb/> SL  3  (C) × SL  3  (C) C  3  ⊗ C  3 <lb/> P  2  × P  2  ⊂ P  8 <lb/> Two qutrits <lb/> SL  5  (C) <lb/>Λ  2  C  5 <lb/> G(2, 5) ⊂ P  14 <lb/> Two fermions <lb/>with five single-particle states <lb/> E  6 <lb/> V  27 <lb/> E  6  /P  1  ⊂ P  26 Bipartite entanglement of three qutrit  12 <lb/> SL  3  (C) × SL  4  (C) C  3  ⊗ C  4  P  2  × P  3  ⊂ P  11 <lb/> One qutrit and one 4-qudit <lb/> SL  7  (C) <lb/>Λ  2  C  7 <lb/> G(2, 7) ⊂ P  20 <lb/> Two fermions <lb/>with 7 single-particle states <lb/> Table III. Classification of smooth G-orbits with orbit structure G.[v] ⊂ σ(G.[v]) ⊂ P(H) <lb/> Remark III.3. It should be pointed it out that the composite quantum systems of Table II <lb/>are all tripartite systems (except in the case of H = C <lb/> 2  ⊗ C <lb/> m  with G = SL  2  (C) × SO(m) <lb/> for m &gt; 6), while the composite systems of Table III are all bipartite systems. This will be <lb/>emphasized in Appendix A 2 when we refer to a uniform geometric parametrization of the <lb/>varieties of separable states given by Ref <lb/> 25  . <lb/> IV. CONCLUSION <lb/> By means of algebraic geometry in this paper we intended to provide a uniform description <lb/>of pure quantum systems featuring a classification of entanglement types similar to the <lb/>famous case of three qubits. More precisely we explained how a geometric interpretation <lb/>of what the |W and |GHZ states are, allows us to use results of algebraic geometry and <lb/>invariant theory to give an explicit list (Table II) of all Hilbert spaces, with the corresponding <lb/>SLOCC group, such that the only types of genuine entangled states are the exact analogues <lb/>of the |W and |GHZ states. It turns our that this list of separable states for those <lb/>Hilbert spaces correponds to the list of subexceptional Freudenthal varieties. Those varieties <lb/>have a strong connexion with exceptional simple Lie algebras (as fundamental subadjoint <lb/>varieties). They also admit a uniform description as image of the same rational map (Plücker <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body> embedding) over different composition algebras. This map found by Ref <lb/> 25  is described in <lb/>Appendix A 2. The translation of the work of algebraic geometers <lb/> 25–27,41  we manage to <lb/>do to quantum information theory language could be summerize in the following sentence: <lb/>«Three fermions with 6 single-particle states over composition algebras can be entangled in <lb/>two different ways». This sentence includes all known cases of tripartite systems having a <lb/>similar orbit structure as the three qubit case. <lb/> Appendix A: The tripartite entanglement and the Freudenthal varieties <lb/> The algebraic varieties of Table II have been studied in the mathematics literature as the <lb/>fundamental subadjoint varieties or the Freudenthal varieties. In the early 2000, Landsberg <lb/>and Manivel investigated the geometry of those varieties in a series of papers <lb/> 25–27  . Their goal <lb/>was to establish new connections between representation theory and algebraic geometry. In <lb/>this Appendix we collect some results and descriptions of this sequence of varieties which <lb/>we believe to be relevant for quantum information theory. <lb/> 1. The subadjoint varieties <lb/> Let us consider g a complex simple Lie algebra of type B  n  , D  n  , G  2  , F  4  , E  6  , E  7  and E  8 <lb/> (i.e. all complex simple Lie algebras except those of type A  n  and C  n  ). They correspond <lb/>to the fundamental simple Lie algebras, i.e. Lie algebras whose adjoint representation is <lb/>fundamental <lb/> 25  . Then let X  G  ⊂ P(g) be the highest weight orbit for the adjoint representation <lb/>of the corresponding Lie group G. Consider  <lb/>  x  X  G  the embedded tangent space at any point <lb/> [x] of the homogeneous variety X  G  . Then Y = X  G  ∩ T  x  X  G  is a homogenous variety. Table <lb/>IV gives the correspondence between the Lie algebras g and the homogenenous varieties <lb/> Y . The sequence of algebraic varieties corresponding to quantum multipartite systems <lb/>featuring only the two types of genuine entanglement |W and |GHZ are connected to <lb/>fundamental adjoint representations of Lie algebras by this construction. Moreover in Ref <lb/> 26 <lb/> Landsberg and Manivel prove the existence of a rational map of degree 4 which allows from <lb/>the knowledge of Y to reconstruct the adjoint varieties X  G  ⊂ P(g) and thus to recover the <lb/>structure of the Lie algebra g. <lb/> To illustrate the construction of this rational map, let us detail one example. <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body> Y ⊂ P  n <lb/> g <lb/> v  3  (P  1  ) ⊂ P  3 <lb/> g  2 <lb/> P  1  × Q  m−4  ⊂ P  2m−5  so  m <lb/> LG(3, 6) ⊂ P  13 <lb/> f  4 <lb/> G(3, 6) ⊂ P  19 <lb/> e  6 <lb/> S  6  ⊂ P  31 <lb/> e  7 <lb/> E  7  /P  1  ⊂ P  55 <lb/> e  8 <lb/> Table IV. Fundamental subadjoint varieties <lb/> Example A.1. Let Y = G(3, 6) ⊂ P <lb/> 19  = P(V ) be the variety of separable states for a system <lb/>made of three fermions with six single-particule states. Let us denote by {x  1  , . . . , x  20  } a dual <lb/>basis of V . Then embedded linearly P(V ) = P <lb/> 19  ⊂  {x  0  =0}  P <lb/> 20  ⊂  {x  21  =0}  P <lb/> 21  and consider the <lb/>rational map φ : P <lb/> 21  → P <lb/> 77  defined by <lb/> φ([x  0  , . . . , x  21  ]) = [x <lb/> 4 <lb/>0  , x <lb/> 3 <lb/>0  x  21  , x <lb/> 3 <lb/>0  x  i  , x <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  I  2  (Y ), x  0  x  21  x  i  − x  0  I  3  (τ (Y )  sing  ), x <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  x <lb/> 2 <lb/>21  − I  4  (τ (Y ))] <lb/> where 1 ≤ i ≤ 20, I  k  (Z) denotes a set of generators of the ideal of degree k polynomials <lb/>defining Z and τ (Y )  sing  is the subvariety of singular points of τ (Y ). Then φ(G(3, 6)) = X  E  6  , <lb/>i.e. φ maps the set of separable three fermions with six single-particules states to the E  6 <lb/> adjoint variety. The E  6  adjoint variety contains the information defining the Lie algebra <lb/> e  6  as we have &lt; X  E  6  &gt;= P(e  6  ), i.e. the linear span fills the full space and the algebraic <lb/>structure can be recovered <lb/> 26  from the geometry of X  E  6  . <lb/> One sees from the previous example that the Lie algebra e  6  can be reconstructed from the <lb/>defining equation of τ (G(3, 6)), i.e. the unique (up to a multiplication by a scalar) SLOCC <lb/>invariant irreducible quartic on H = Λ <lb/> 3  (C <lb/> 6  ). Indeed the ideal of degree three polynomials <lb/>vanishing on the singular locus of τ (G(3, 6)) is generated by the derivatives of the quartic <lb/>invariant and the ideal of degree two polynomials defining G(3, 6) is spaned by the second <lb/>derivative of the quartic invariant. But this quartic invariant is known in the context of <lb/>entanglement as the analogue for three bosons of the 3-tangle <lb/> 39  . <lb/>Therefore in the context of entanglement Landsberg and Manivel&apos;s construction tells <lb/>us that Table IV can be read as follows: Consider a fundamental Lie algebra g and the <lb/>corresponding mutlipartite quantum system Y . Then g can be reconstructed from the <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body> knowlegde of the unique irreducible SLOCC invariant of degree 4 (i.e. the generalization of <lb/>the 3-tangle). This is another approach to construct Lie algebra from qubits <lb/> 9  . <lb/> 2. The Freudenthal subexceptional series <lb/> The subadjoint varieties also appeared in the work of Landsberg and Manivel in their <lb/>geometric investigation of the so-called Freudenthal magic square. Let us recall that the <lb/>Freudenthal magic square is a square of semi-simple Lie algebras due to Freudenthal <lb/> 16  and <lb/>Tits <lb/> 38  obtained from a pair of composition algebras (A, B) (where A and B are the complex-<lb/>ification of R, C, H, the quaternions or O, the octonions) by the following construction: <lb/> g = Der(A) ⊕ (A  0  ⊗ J  3  (B)  0  ) ⊕ Der(J  3  (B)) <lb/> (A1) <lb/>where A  0  denotes the space of imaginary elements, J  3  (B) denotes the Jordan algebra of <lb/> 3 × 3 Hermitian matrices over B and J  3  (B)  0  is the subspace of traceless matrices of J  3  (B). <lb/> For an algebra A, Der(A) is the derivation of A, i.e. the Lie algebra of the automorphism <lb/>group of A. <lb/> The Freudenthal magic square is thus given by: <lb/> R <lb/>C <lb/>H O <lb/>R so  3 <lb/> sl  3 <lb/> sp  6  f  4 <lb/> C sl  3  sl  3  × sl  3  sl  6  e  6 <lb/> H sp  6 <lb/> sl  6 <lb/> so  12  e  7 <lb/> O f  4 <lb/> e  6 <lb/> e  7  e  8 <lb/> Table V. The Freudenthal magic square <lb/> The relevence of Freudenthal construction to the study of entanglement has been pointed <lb/>out by various authors <lb/> 3,39  . However the geometric contribution has not been completely <lb/>explained so far in the context of quantum information theory. The geometric version of the <lb/>Freudenthal magic square given in Ref <lb/> 26,27  is the following square of homogeneous varieties: <lb/>The geometric magic square has the property that each homogeneous variety of the square <lb/>is homogenous for the corresponding Lie group in the Freudenthal magic square. Moreover <lb/>each variety of a given row can be recovered as a section (tangential or linear) of the next <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body> R <lb/> C <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>R v  2  (Q  1  ) P(T (P  2  )) LG(2, 6) E  6  /P  1  ∩ H <lb/> C v  2  (P  2  ) P  2  × P  2  G(2, 6) <lb/> E  6  /P  1 <lb/> H LG(3, 6) G(3, 6) <lb/> S  6 <lb/> E  7  /P  7 <lb/> O X  F  4 <lb/> X  E  6 <lb/> X  E  7 <lb/> X  E  8 <lb/> Table VI. The Geometric magic square <lb/> one. The connexion with composition algebras leads Landsberg and Manivel to formulate <lb/>a geometrical uniform description of the varieities of the third row (the one relevant for the <lb/>classification of Table II) as Grassmannians over the composition algebras. <lb/>It is well known that the variety G(3, 6) of Example A.1 can be parametrized by the so-<lb/>called Plücker map <lb/> 17  . Let v  1  , v  2  and v  3  be three complex vectors defining a three plane in C <lb/> 6  . <lb/>The coordinates can be chosen so that v  1  = [1 : 0 : 0 : 0 : 0 : 0], v  2  = [0 : 1 : 0 : 0 : 0 : 0 : 0] <lb/> and v  3  = [0 : 0 : 1 : 0 : 0 : 0]. Let [˜ v  1  ∧ ˜ <lb/> v  2  ∧ ˜ <lb/> v  3  ] be a three plane in the neighborhood of <lb/> [v  1  ∧ v  2  ∧ v  3  ]. One can choose  <lb/>  1  = [1 : 0 : 0 : a  11  : a  12  : a  13  ], ˜ <lb/> v  2  = [0 : 1 : 0 : a  21  : a  22  : a  23  ] <lb/> and  <lb/>  3  = [0 : 0 : 1 : a  31  : a  32  : a  33  ]. Locally the variety G(3, 6) is parametrized in the <lb/>neighborhood of [v  1  ∧ v  2  ∧ v  3  ] by <lb/> φ(1, P ) = (1, P, com(P ), det(P )) <lb/> (A2) <lb/>where P is the matrix P = (a  ij  ) and com(P ) is its comatrix. The map φ is the Plücker <lb/>map. <lb/>An alternative description of G(3, 6) can be given by considering P ∈ J  3  (A) where A = <lb/> C ⊕ C is the complexification of C, i.e. P = <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> α x  1  x  2 <lb/> x  1  β x  3 <lb/> x  2  x  3  γ <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> with α, β, γ ∈ C and x  1  , x  2  , x  3  ∈ <lb/> C ⊕ C. Then to recover the same parametrization one needs to require that the three <lb/>row vectors defining the matrix (I  3  |P ) are orthogonal with respect to the symplectic form <lb/> ω = <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> 0 I  3 <lb/> −I  3  0 <lb/>  <lb/> , i.e. the corresponding 3-plane is isotropic for ω. <lb/> Under the symplectic condition, one has G(3, 6) = LG  C⊕C  (3, 6). <lb/> Similarly the Plücker map of Eq. (A2) can be defined for P ∈ J  3  (A), with A one of the <lb/>three other complex composition algebras. Then if we denote by A = C, M  2  (C), O C  the <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body> complexifications of R, H, O, Landsberg and Manivel proved <lb/> 26  that the varieties of the third <lb/>row can all be interpreted as LG  A  (3, 6), i.e. <lb/> LG(3, 6) = LG  C  (3, 6) <lb/> G(3, 6) = LG  C⊕C  (3, 6) <lb/> S  6  = LG  M  2  (C)  (3, 6) <lb/> E  7  /P  7  = LG  O  C  (3, 6) <lb/>  <lb/>       <lb/>      <lb/> Three A-fermions with six single-particle <lb/>states satisfying a symplectic condition <lb/>(A3) <lb/>Moreover if we consider the case P ∈ J  3  (−1) = { <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> α 0 0 <lb/>0 α 0 <lb/>0 0 α <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> , α ∈ C} (notations of <lb/>Ref <lb/> 26  ) and the case P ∈ J  3  (0) = { <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> α 0 0 <lb/>0 β 0 <lb/>0 0 γ <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> , α, β, γ ∈ C}, one obtains a similar Plücker <lb/>parametrization of v  3  (P <lb/> 1  ) = LG  −1  (3, 6) and P <lb/> 1  × P <lb/> 1  × P <lb/> 1  = LG  0  (3, 6). <lb/> An important consequence for quantum information theory is that this geometric inter-<lb/>pretation of the varieties of the extended third row as Lagrangian Grassmannians over A say <lb/>that all quantum systems, which feature only the states |W and |GHZ as their genuine <lb/>entangled classes, are tripartite systems of indistingushable particles with six-single particle <lb/>states with coefficients in a complex composition algebra satisfying a symplectic condition. <lb/> Remark A.1. Similarly a description of the first four varieties of separable states of Table <lb/>III as Lagrangian Grassmannians LG(A <lb/> 2  , A <lb/> 6  ) is given in Ref <lb/> 26  . Those varieties correspond <lb/>to the second row of the geometric magic square. <lb/></body>

			<page> 18 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> REFERENCES <lb/> 1  Bell J. S. &quot; On the Einstein-Podolsky-Rosen paradox. &quot; Physics 1, no. 3 (1964): 195-200. <lb/> 2  Borsten L., Dahanayake D., Duff M. J., Marrani A. and Rubens W., &quot; Four-Qubit Entan-<lb/>glement Classification from String Theory &quot; , Phys. Rev. Lett. 105, 100507 (2010). <lb/> 3  Borsten L., Dahanayake D., Duff M. J., Ebrahim H. and Rubens W., &quot; Freudenthal triple <lb/>classification of three-qubit entanglement &quot; , Physical Review A 80, no 3 (2009):032326. <lb/> 4  Borsten L., Dahanayake D., Duff M. J., Ebrahim H., and Rubens W., &quot; Black holes, qubits <lb/>and octonions &quot; , Physics Reports 471, no. 3 (2009): 113-219. <lb/> 5  Borsten L., Duff M. J., Ferrara S., Marrani A. and Rubens, W., &quot; Explicit orbit clas-<lb/>sification of reducible Jordan algebras and Freudenthal triple systems &quot; . arXiv preprint <lb/>arXiv:1108.0908. (2011). <lb/> 6  Brody D.C., Gustavsson A.C.T. and Hughston L.P., &quot; Entanglement of three-qubit geom-<lb/>etry &quot; , J. Phys. Conf. Ser. 67, 012044 (2007). <lb/> 7  Borsten L., Duff M. J., and Levay P., &quot; The black-hole/qubit correspondence: an up-to-date <lb/>review. &quot; , arXiv preprint arXiv:1206.3166 (2012). <lb/> 8  Chevalley C., The Algebraic Theory of Spinors and Clifford Algebras: Collected Works. <lb/> Vol. 2. Springer, 1997. <lb/> 9  Cerchiai B. L. and van Geemen B. &quot; From qubits to E7 &quot; , Journal of mathematical physics, <lb/>51(12), 122203 (2010). <lb/> 10  Coffman V., Kundu J. and Wootters W. K., &quot; Distributed entanglement &quot; , Phys. Rev. A61, <lb/>052306 (2000). <lb/> 11  Duff M. J., and Ferrara S. &quot; E 7 and the tripartite entanglement of seven qubits &quot; , Physical <lb/>Review D 76.2 (2007): 025018. <lb/> 12  Duff M. J., and Ferrara, S. &quot; E 6 and the bipartite entanglement of three qutrits &quot; , Physical <lb/>Review D, 76 (12), (2007): 124023. <lb/> 13  Dür W., Vidal G. and Cirac J. I., &quot; Three qubits can be entangled in two inequivalent <lb/>ways &quot; , Phys. Rev. A 62, 062314 (2000). <lb/> 14  W. Fulton, J. Hansen, &quot; A connectedness theorem for projective varieties, with applications <lb/>to intersections and singularities of mapping &quot; , Ann. Math. 110 (1979), 159-166. <lb/> 15  W. Fulton, J. Harris, Representation Theory, Graduate Text in Mathematics, Springer <lb/>1991. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> 16  H. Freudenthal, &quot; Beziehungen der e  7  und ǫ  8  zur Oktavenebene, I, II &quot; , Indag. Math. 16 <lb/>(1954), 218-230, 363-368. III, IV, Indag. Math. 17 (1955), 151-157, 277-285. V -IX, Indag. <lb/>Math. 21 (1959), 165-201, 447-474. X, XI, Indag. Math. 25 (1963) 457-487. <lb/> 17  J. Harris, Algebraic Geometry: a first course, Graduate Texts in Mathematics 133 Springer <lb/>1992. <lb/> 18  Holweck F., Luque J.-G., Thibon J.-Y., &quot; Geometric descriptions of entangled states by <lb/>auxiliary varieties &quot; , Journal of Mathematical Physics 53, 102203 (2012). <lb/> 19  Holweck F., Luque J.-G., Thibon J.-Y., &quot; Entanglement of four qubit systems: a geometric <lb/>atlas with polynomial compass I (the finite world) &quot; , Journal of Mathematicla Physics 55 <lb/> (1), 012202 (2014). <lb/> 20  T. Ivey, J. M. Landsberg, Cartan for beginners: Differential Geometry via Moving Frames <lb/>and Exterior Differential Systems, Graduate Studies in Mathematics 61 2003. <lb/> 21  Kac V. G., Popov V. L. and Vinberg E. B., &quot; Sur les groupes algébriques dont l&apos;algèbre des <lb/>invariants est libre &quot; , C.R. Acad. Sci. Paris, ser A. 283 (1976), 875-878. <lb/> 22  Kallosh R. and Linde A., &quot; Strings Black Holes and Quantum Information &quot; , Phys. Rev. <lb/>D73 104033 (2006). <lb/> 23  Kitaev A. Y., Shen A. and Vyalyi M. N., Classical and quantum computation. No. 47. <lb/>American Mathematical Soc., 2002. <lb/> 24  Landsberg J. M., Tensors: Geometry and applications, Vol. 128. Amer Mathematical <lb/>Society, 2011. <lb/> 25  Landsberg J. M. and Manivel L., &quot; The projective geometry of Freudenthal&apos;s magic square &quot; , <lb/>Journal of Algebra 239.2 (2001): 477-512. <lb/> 26  Landsberg J. M. and Manivel L., &quot; Construction and classification of complex simple Lie <lb/>algebras via projective geometry &quot; , Selecta Mathematica 8.1 (2002): 137-159. <lb/> 27  Landsberg, J. M., and Manivel L. &quot; Representation Theory and Projective Geometry &quot; , in <lb/>Algebraic Transformation Groups and Algebraic Varieties, Encyclopedia of Mathemati-<lb/>cal Sciences. Subseries Invariant Theory and Algebraic Transformation Groups, Vol. III, <lb/>Springer-Verlag, 2004. <lb/> 28  Le Paige C., &quot; Sur la théorie des formes binaires à plusieurs séeries de variables &quot; , Bull. Acad. <lb/>Roy. Sci. Belgique 2 (3), 40-53 (1881). <lb/> 29  Lévay P. &quot; Three-qubit interpretation of BPS and non-BPS STU black holes. &quot; , Physical <lb/>Review D 76.10 (2007): 106011. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> 30  Lévay P., and Vrana P. &quot; Three fermions with six single-particle states can be entangled in <lb/>two inequivalent ways &quot; . Physical Review A, 78(2), 022329. (2008) <lb/> 31  Miyake A., &quot; Classification of multipartite entangled states by multidimensional determi-<lb/>nants &quot; , Phys. Rev. A 67, 012108 (2003). <lb/> 32  Miyake A., &quot; Multipartite Entanglement under Stochastic Local Operations and Classical <lb/>Communication &quot; , Int. J. Quant. Info. 2, 65-77 (2004). <lb/> 33  Miyake A. and Verstraete F., &quot; Multipartite entanglement in 2 × 2 × n quatum systems &quot; , <lb/>Phys. Rev. A 69, 012101 (2004). <lb/> 34  Nielsen M. A. and Chuang I. L., Quantum computation and quantum information. Cam-<lb/>bridge university press, 2010. <lb/> 35  Popov V., Vinberg E., &quot; Invariant theory &quot; , Algebraic geometry IV. Springer Berlin Heidel-<lb/>berg, 1994. 123-278. <lb/> 36  Sárosi G., and Lévay P., &quot; Entanglement in fermionic Fock space &quot; , Journal of Physics A: <lb/>Mathematical and Theoretical 47.11 (2014): 115304. <lb/> 37  Sárosi G., and Lévay P., &quot; Entanglement classification of three fermions with up to nine <lb/>single-particle states &quot; , Physical Review A 89, no. 4 (2014): 042310. <lb/> 38  Tits. J. &quot; Algèbres alternatives, algèbres de Jordan et algèbres de Lie exceptionnelles I : <lb/>Construction. &quot; Indag. Math. 28 223-237 (1966) <lb/> 39  Vrana P., and Lévay P., &quot; Special entangled quantum systems and the Freudenthal con-<lb/>struction &quot; , Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical 42.28 (2009): 285303. <lb/> 40  Verstraete F., Dehaene F., De Moor B. and Verschelde H., &quot; Four qubits can be entangled <lb/>in nine different ways &quot; , Phys. Rev.. A 65, 052112 (2002). <lb/> 41  F. Zak, Tangents and Secants of Algebraic Varieties, AMS Translations of mathematical <lb/>monographs 127 1993. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>21 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
