<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> October 8, 2010 0:12 <lb/>WSPC -Proceedings Trim Size: 9in x 6in Schussler˙Antares <lb/> 1 <lb/> Status and recent results of the ANTARES experiment <lb/> F. Schüssler  *  for the ANTARES Collaboration <lb/> Commissariat à l&apos;´ energie atomique et auxénergies alternatives <lb/>Institut de recherche sur les lois fondamentales de l&apos;Univers <lb/>91191 Gif-sur-Yvette Cedex, France <lb/>  *  E-mail: fabian.schussler@cea.fr <lb/> The ANTARES neutrino telescope located in the Mediterranean Sea has been <lb/>fully installed in 2008. As examples for the ongoing physics studies, we discuss <lb/>the search for a high energy excess over the atmospheric neutrino flux leading to <lb/>significant limits on the diffuse astrophysical neutrino flux in the multi TeV to <lb/>PeV range. Using data taken during the construction phase of the experiment, <lb/>an analysis searching for point-like excesses in the neutrino sky distribution <lb/>has been performed and the atmospheric muon flux has been determined. <lb/> Keywords: ANTARES; neutrino telescope; diffuse flux; point sources; atmo-<lb/>spheric muon flux <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> The key question to resolve the long standing mystery of the origin of <lb/>cosmic rays is to locate the sources and study the acceleration mechanisms <lb/>able to produce fundamental particles with energies orders of magnitude <lb/>above man-made accelerators. Over the last years it became more and more <lb/>obvious that multiple messengers will be needed to achieve this task. The <lb/>start of large neutrino telescopes at the South Pole (IceCube) and in the <lb/>Mediterranean Sea (ANTARES and KM3NeT) are important steps in this <lb/>direction. The ANTARES detector became fully equipped and operational <lb/>in 2008. The detector is composed of 12 detection lines placed at a depth <lb/>of 2475m off the French coast near Toulon. The detector lines are about <lb/>450m long and hold a total of 885 optical modules (OM), 17 &quot; glass spheres <lb/>housing each a 10 &quot; photomultiplier tube. A schematic layout of the detector <lb/>is shown in Fig. 1. <lb/>The neutrino detection relies on the emission of Cherenkov light by high <lb/>energy muons originating from charged current neutrino interactions near <lb/>the instrumented volume. The OMs look downward at 45 <lb/> •  in order to op-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> October 8, 2010 0:12 <lb/>WSPC -Proceedings Trim Size: 9in x 6in Schussler˙Antares <lb/></note>

			<page> 2 <lb/></page>

			<body> Fig. 1. Schematic view of the ANTARES detector. <lb/> timize the detection of upgoing, i.e. neutrino induced, tracks. All detected <lb/>signals are transmitted via an optical cable to a shore station, where a farm <lb/>of CPUs filters the data for coincident signals or hits, in several adjacent <lb/>OMs. The muon direction is then determined by minimizing a χ <lb/> 2  or a like-<lb/>lihood which compares the times of the hits with the expectation from a <lb/>Cherenkov signal of a muon track. Detailed descriptions of these reconstruc-<lb/>tion algorithms and their performances can be found in the references <lb/> 1,2  . <lb/>Two main backgrounds for the search for astrophysical neutrinos <lb/>can be identified: downgoing atmospheric muons which have been mis-<lb/>reconstructed as upgoing and atmospheric neutrinos originating in cosmic <lb/>ray induced air showers at the opposite side of the Earth (cf. Fig 2(a)). <lb/>Depending on the requirements of the analysis both backgrounds can be <lb/>discriminated using various parameters like the quality of the event recon-<lb/>struction, given by the likelihood or the χ <lb/> 2  , or an estimator for the deposited <lb/>energy. <lb/> 2. Diffuse flux of astrophysical neutrinos <lb/> The rejection of background is particularly important in the search for the <lb/>diffuse flux of astrophysical neutrinos. Without resolving individual sources, <lb/>this analysis relies on the assumption that astrophysical accelerators will <lb/>emit neutrinos with a hard spectrum usually supposed to follow E <lb/> −2  . At <lb/>high energies, typically above O(100 TeV), this flux will therefore dominate <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> October 8, 2010 0:12 <lb/>WSPC -Proceedings Trim Size: 9in x 6in Schussler˙Antares <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/> </page>

			<body> (a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>Fig. 2. Left plot: Zenith angle distribution of reconstructed ANTARES events. <lb/>Right plot: Distribution of the R parameter for the 134 neutrino candidates (points) <lb/>selected in the diffuse flux analysis compared to predictions of the Bartol flux (filled his-<lb/>togram), the contribution of prompt neutrinos (dotted line)and the astrophysical signal <lb/>at the level of the upper limit (full red line, cf. eq. 1). <lb/> over the atmospheric neutrino flux following a softer spectrum proportional <lb/>to E <lb/> −3.7  at high energies <lb/> 3  . <lb/>Stringent quality criteria have been applied to a sample with a total <lb/>lifetime of 334 days of data taken during the years 2008 and 2009 with a <lb/>detector in various configurations, i.e. 9, 10 and 12 lines. These selection cri-<lb/>teria involve for example a two dimensional cut on the number of recorded <lb/>hits and the likelihood value. Relying on a large set of Monte Carlo simu-<lb/>lations of both atmospheric muons and neutrinos, the event selection has <lb/>been optimized before the signal region was uncovered, unblinded, for the <lb/>dataset. The atmospheric neutrino background has been modeled following <lb/>the Bartol flux parameterization <lb/> 3  with an additional high energy &quot; prompt &quot; <lb/>component induced by the decay of charmed mesons. <lb/> 4  The signal neutrino <lb/>flux Φ is modeled with a E <lb/> −2  spectral shape and an arbitrary normaliza-<lb/>tion of E <lb/> 2  Φ = 1.0 × 10 <lb/> −7  GeV cm <lb/> −2  s <lb/> −1  sr <lb/> −1  . Passing all quality criteria <lb/>134 neutrino candidates were identified in the data set. The contamination <lb/>due to mis-reconstructed atmospheric muons could be reduced to about <lb/>0.1 ÷ 0.3 events. <lb/>The final discrimination between atmospheric and astrophysical neu-<lb/>trinos is relying on the fact that high energy muons (E &gt; 1 TeV) deposit <lb/>large fractions of their energy in electromagnetic showers along their tracks. <lb/>These cascades lead to a broadening of the arrival time distribution of pho-<lb/>tons at the OMs with respect to a pure Cherenkov signal. Averaging the <lb/>number of hit repetitions in each OM, a parameter R which is sensitive to <lb/>this time distribution and therefore to the muon energy can be constructed. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> October 8, 2010 0:12 <lb/>WSPC -Proceedings Trim Size: 9in x 6in Schussler˙Antares <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/> </page>

			<body> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 6 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 7 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 8 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -8 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -7 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -6 <lb/> ANTARES-2007-09 <lb/> (W&amp;B)/2 <lb/> Baikal NT-200 ( <lb/> e <lb/> + <lb/>)/3 <lb/>Amanda-II UHE <lb/>( <lb/> e <lb/> + <lb/>)/3 <lb/>Amanda-II <lb/>Frejus <lb/> E <lb/> 2 <lb/> dN/dE [GeV cm <lb/> -2 <lb/> s <lb/> -1 <lb/> sr <lb/> -1 <lb/> ] <lb/> E (GeV) <lb/> (MPR)/2 <lb/> MACRO <lb/> Fig. 3. ANTARES upper limit (90% c.l.) for a E  −2  diffuse high energy νµ + ¯ <lb/> νµ flux <lb/>compared to previous measurements and theoretical predictions. <lb/> Fig. 2(b) shows the distribution of the R parameter for atmospheric and <lb/>astrophysical neutrino expectations as well as for the selected data events. <lb/>The cut at R = 1.31 had been defined before unblinding the data. Above <lb/>this cut n  bg  = 10.72 background and n  data  = 9 observed events are found. <lb/>The main contribution to the systematic uncertainties are due to the atmo-<lb/>spheric neutrino flux (±1.1 events) and the detector acceptance including <lb/>environmental parameters like the photon scattering length in sea water <lb/>(±1.3 events). The derived upper limit on the astrophysical neutrino flux <lb/>is given as (cf. Fig. 3) <lb/> E <lb/> 2  Φ(E)  90%  = 5.3 × 10 <lb/> −8  GeV cm <lb/> −2  s <lb/> −1  sr <lb/> −1 <lb/> (1) <lb/> 3. Search for neutrino point sources <lb/> The location of the ANTARES detector in the Northern hemisphere makes <lb/>it particularly suited to observe the disk and especially the center of our <lb/>Galaxy, a region where many favored cosmic ray acceleration sites are lo-<lb/>cated. A first search for point sources in the data taken during the con-<lb/>struction phase of the experiment has been conducted. During this phase 5 <lb/>detection lines have been operated and the selected dataset corresponds to <lb/>an effective lifetime of 140 days. A reconstruction algorithm <lb/> 1  that is used <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> October 8, 2010 0:12 <lb/>WSPC -Proceedings Trim Size: 9in x 6in Schussler˙Antares <lb/></note>

			<page> 5 <lb/></page>

			<body> Fig. 4. ANTARES upper limits (90% c.l.) for a E  −2  νµ + ¯ <lb/> νµ flux compared to previous <lb/>measurements. The sensitivity of one year with the full 12 line ANTARES detector is <lb/>shown as solid red line. <lb/> in the online data reconstruction and proved to be very robust against bio-<lb/>luminescence activity has been used for this first and preliminary analysis. <lb/>A series of quality criteria has been optimized for the best source discovery <lb/>potential. In Fig. 2(a) the zenith angle distribution of the event passing <lb/>these criteria is shown in comparison to MC simulations. A dataset of 276 <lb/>events passes all quality criteria and a zenith angle cut below 90 <lb/> •  (upgo-<lb/>ing tracks). The angular resolution of the selected dataset is, due to the <lb/>asymmetric detector layout, depending on the declination of the incoming <lb/>neutrino. A median resolution between 3 and 5 deg has been derived from <lb/>MC simulations. Several algorithms searching for point sources and corre-<lb/>lations with a predefined list of 24 galactic and extra-galactic astrophysical <lb/>objects have been applied to the unblinded data set. No statistically signif-<lb/>icant excess has been found. The derived flux limits are shown in Fig. 4. <lb/>Using reconstruction algorithms yielding a higher angular resolution and <lb/>data taken with the full ANTARES detector, significant improvements on <lb/>these results will become available in the near future. <lb/> 4. Flux of atmospheric muons <lb/> The data recorded by the ANTARES detector in its 5-line configuration <lb/>has also been analyzed to derive the flux of atmospheric muons with high <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> October 8, 2010 0:12 <lb/>WSPC -Proceedings Trim Size: 9in x 6in Schussler˙Antares <lb/></note>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<body> Depth (m water equivalent) <lb/> 2000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>6000 <lb/>8000 <lb/>10000 <lb/> ) <lb/> -1 <lb/> sr <lb/> -1 <lb/> s <lb/> -2 <lb/> Vertical Intensity (cm <lb/> -10 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -9 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -8 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -7 <lb/> 10 <lb/> ANTARES 5 lines-this analysis <lb/>ANTARES 1 line <lb/>ANTARES 5 lines-low energy <lb/>DIR param. <lb/>AMANDA <lb/>AMANDA-II <lb/>BAIKAL <lb/>DUMAND <lb/>NESTOR <lb/>NEMO <lb/> Fig. 5. Vertical muon flux of atmospheric muons for the 5 line ANTARES data (black <lb/>points, from  5  ) as a function of the slant depth. <lb/> statistics. Correcting for the acceptance of the detector and resolution ef-<lb/>fects, the zenith angle distribution of reconstructed muon tracks could be <lb/>used to derive the muon flux as a function of slant depth <lb/> 5  . The result, <lb/>shown in Fig. 5, is in agreement with previous measurements and theoret-<lb/>ical predictions. <lb/> 5. Conclusion and outlook <lb/> The ANTARES neutrino telescope started routine data taking with a 5-<lb/>line configuration in 2007. These early data have been used to derive the <lb/>atmospheric muon flux as function of slant depth. A search for point-like <lb/>sources did not find a statistically significant excess. Data with a detector <lb/>of increasing size (9 to 12 lines) have been taken in 2008 and 2009. This <lb/>dataset has been analyzed in the search for an excess in the diffuse high <lb/>energy neutrino flux and sensitive upper limits could be derived. <lb/>Due to a much better angular resolution and acceptance, upcoming <lb/>analyses of data obtained with the full ANTARES configuration will be <lb/>significantly more sensitive to astrophysical sources of neutrinos. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. J. A. Aguilar et al., [ANTARES Collab.], submitted to Elsevier, October 2010. <lb/>2. A. Heijboer, PhD Thesis, Univ. Amsterdam, 2004 <lb/>3. G.D. Barr et al. Phys. Rev. D70 (2004) 023006. <lb/>4. E.V. Bugaev et al. Nuovo Cimento C, 12 (1989) 41. <lb/>5. J. A. Aguilar et al., [ANTARES Collab.], Astropart. Phys. 34 (2010) 179. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
