<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="headnote"> arXiv:1503.01371v1  [quant-ph] 4 Mar 2015 <lb/></note>

			<front> On the Lewis–Riesenfeld (Dodonov–Man&apos;ko) <lb/>invariant method <lb/> Julio Guerrero and Francisco F. López-Ruiz <lb/> E-mail: juguerre@um.es, paco.lopezruiz@uca.es <lb/> Abstract. <lb/> We revise the Lewis–Riesenfeld invariant method for solving the quantum time-<lb/>dependent harmonic oscillator in light of the Quantum Arnold Transformation <lb/>previously introduced and its recent generalization to the Quantum Arnold–Ermakov– <lb/>Pinney Transformation. We prove that both methods are equivalent and show the <lb/>advantages of the Quantum Arnold–Ermakov–Pinney transformation over the Lewis– <lb/>Riesenfeld invariant method. We show that, in the quantum time-dependent and <lb/>damped harmonic oscillator, the invariant proposed by Dodonov &amp; Man&apos;ko is more <lb/>suitable and provide some examples to illustrate it, focusing on the damped case. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> The Lewis–Riesenfeld invariant method [1, 2] is a technique that allows to obtain a <lb/>complete set of solutions of the Schrödinger equation for a time-dependent harmonic <lb/>oscillator in terms of the eigenstates of a quadratic invariant. This quadratic invariant, <lb/>the Lewis invariant, is built using an auxiliary variable that satisfies the Ermakov <lb/>equation [3, 4, 5, 6]. <lb/>The Quantum Arnold–Ermakov–Pinney Transformation (QAEPT) [7] is a unitary <lb/>transformation that maps solutions of a Generalized Caldirola–Kanai [8, 9, 10] <lb/>Schrödinger equation into solutions of another Generalized Caldirola–Kanai Schrödinger <lb/>equation. In particular, one of the systems can be the standard harmonic oscillator and <lb/>the other a time-dependent harmonic oscillator, and in this case we shall show that the <lb/>Lewis–Riesenfeld invariant method is recovered. <lb/>The idea of using invariants to solve equations is rather old, going back to S. Lie <lb/>(1883) [11] who showed that a second order differential equation has the maximal group <lb/>of symmetries if the differential equation is up to third order in the derivative, and the <lb/>coefficients satisfy certain relations [12, 13]. <lb/>V.P. Ermakov (1880) [3, 4] showed that the general solution of the non-linear <lb/>equation <lb/>¨ b + ω <lb/> 2  (t)b = <lb/> ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0 <lb/> b  3  , <lb/> (1) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> On the Lewis–Riesenfeld (Dodonov–Man&apos;ko) invariant method <lb/></note>

			<page> 2 <lb/></page>

			<body> where ω  0  is an arbitrary constant, can be obtained from two independent solutions y  1  , y  2 <lb/> of the corresponding linear equation: <lb/>¨ <lb/> y + ω <lb/> 2  (t)y = 0 <lb/>(2) <lb/>by: <lb/> b <lb/> 2  = c  1  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + c  2  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  + 2c  3  y  1  y  2  , <lb/> (3) <lb/>with c  1  c  2  − c <lb/> 2 <lb/>3  = ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  . Similar results were derived independently by W.E. Milne (1930) <lb/>[5] and E. Pinney (1950) [6]. <lb/>H.R. Lewis (1967) [1] obtained a classical and quantum quadratic invariant for a <lb/>time-dependent harmonic oscillator, of the form: <lb/> I  L  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2m <lb/>(bp − m ˙ <lb/> bx) <lb/> 2  + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> mω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0 <lb/> x <lb/> 2 <lb/> b  2  , <lb/> (4) <lb/>where, again, ω  0  is an arbitrary constant with dimension of frequency, in terms of an <lb/>auxiliary dimensionless function b(t) satisfying the Ermakov equation (1). Note that <lb/>classically x satisfies the equation of motion <lb/>¨ <lb/> x + ω <lb/> 2  (t)x = 0 . <lb/> (5) <lb/>The pair of equations (1) and (5) is denoted an Ermakov system. They are uncoupled <lb/>(given ω(t), they can be solved independently for x and b), although it has been <lb/>generalized to coupled equations and to higher dimensions [14, 15]. <lb/>The reader might wonder about the comparison of b (dimensionless), satisfying (1) <lb/>and providing the invariant (4), and a function ρ satisfying the usual Ermakov–Pinney <lb/>equation <lb/>  + ω(t) <lb/> 2  ρ = <lb/> 1 <lb/> ρ  3  , which has the dimensions of the square root of time (see e.g. <lb/>[1]). The relation between b and ρ is simply b = <lb/> √ ω  0  ρ. Also, the relation between I  L <lb/> and the invariant I in [1] is simply I  L  = ω  0  I, i.e. I  L  has dimension of energy meanwhile <lb/> I has dimension of action. The arbitrariness in the choice of b and I  L  was already noted <lb/>in [1, 2] and we make it explicit for later convenience (see also [16], where the authors <lb/>use the same convention). <lb/>Lewis &amp; Riesenfeld (1969) [2] used the eigenvectors of the quantum version of this <lb/>quadratic invariant <lb/>  L  written in terms of the auxiliary function b(t) satisfying the <lb/>Ermakov equation to obtain solutions of the Schrödinger equation for a time-dependent <lb/>harmonic oscillator. For this purpose, an extra time-dependent phase e <lb/> i <lb/>  ω 0 <lb/> b 2  dt  had to be <lb/>added to the eigenfunctions in order to satisfy the Schrödinger equation. They did not <lb/>considered damping (or time dependent mass) and they supposed that the quadratic <lb/>invariant has discrete spectrum. <lb/>V.I. Arnold (1978) [17], in the context of symmetries of second order ordinary <lb/>differential equations, introduced the term straightening for the linearization studied by <lb/>S. Lie and considered the case of Linear Second Order Differential Equations (LSODE): <lb/>¨ <lb/> x + ˙ <lb/> f ˙ <lb/> x + ω <lb/> 2  x = Λ , <lb/> (6) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> On the Lewis–Riesenfeld (Dodonov–Man&apos;ko) invariant method <lb/></note>

			<page> 3 <lb/></page>

			<body> where f , ω and Λ are time-dependent functions, giving explicitly the transformation for <lb/>this case: <lb/> A : R × T → R × T <lb/> (x, t) → (κ, τ ) <lb/>(7) <lb/>with <lb/> τ = <lb/> u  1  (t) <lb/> u  2  (t) <lb/> , <lb/>κ = <lb/> x − u  p  (t) <lb/> u  2  (t) <lb/> , <lb/> (8) <lb/>where T and T are, in general, open intervals; u  1  and u  2  are independent solutions of <lb/>the homogeneous LSODE, u  p  is a particular solution of the inhomogeneous LSODE, <lb/>and W (t) = ˙ <lb/> u  1  u  2  − u  1  ˙ <lb/> u  2  = e <lb/> −f  is the Wronskian of the two solutions ‡. <lb/>Under this transformation, the classical equation of motion (6) transforms as: <lb/>¨ <lb/> x + ˙ <lb/> f ˙ <lb/> x + ω <lb/> 2  x = Λ <lb/> A <lb/> −→ <lb/> W <lb/>u <lb/> 3 <lb/>2 <lb/> ¨ <lb/> κ = 0 . <lb/> (9) <lb/>Thus, the Arnold transformation maps patches of solutions of the LSODE system into <lb/>patches of free particle trajectories. <lb/>For convenience, we shall impose the canonicity conditions (see [10]): <lb/> u  1  (0) = ˙ <lb/> u  2  (0) = u  p  (0) = ˙ <lb/> u  p  (0) = 0 , ˙ <lb/> u  1  (0) = u  2  (0) = 1 . <lb/> (10) <lb/>These conditions play a crucial role in the physical interpretation of quantities mapped <lb/>from one system into the other through the Arnold transformation. More precisely, if <lb/> κ(τ ) and π(τ ) are the conserved position and momentum for the free particle (verifying <lb/>that κ(0) = κ and π(0) = π ≡ m ˙ <lb/> κ), then the transformed quantities through the Arnold <lb/>transformation are the conserved position x(t) and momentum p(t) in the LSODE <lb/>system (verifying x(0) = x and p(0) = p ≡ m ˙ <lb/> x). <lb/> Dodonov &amp; Man&apos;ko (1979) [18, 19] (and Malkin–Man&apos;ko–Trifonov [20] (1969) <lb/>without considering damping) computed the coherent states for the Generalized <lb/>Caldirola–Kanai model (the quantum version of a general LSODE system), whose <lb/>Hamiltonian is <lb/>ˆ <lb/> H  GCK  = <lb/>ˆ <lb/> p <lb/> 2 <lb/> 2m <lb/> e <lb/> −f  + ( <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> mω <lb/> 2  ˆ <lb/> x <lb/> 2  − mΛˆ )e <lb/> f  , <lb/> (11) <lb/>using first-order invariants as annihilation and creation operators. The number operator <lb/>associated with these annihilation and creation operators is a quadratic invariant that <lb/>will be denoted the Dodonov–Man&apos;ko invariant <lb/>  DM  . Later, other authors have used <lb/>first-order invariants to solve time-dependent problems [21]. <lb/>Hartley &amp; Ray (1981) [22] and Lewis &amp; Leach (1982) [23] generalized the <lb/>construction of the Lewis invariant to some non-linear systems. <lb/>Pedrosa (1987) [24] constructed the Lewis invariant for the Ermakov equation with <lb/>a damping term using canonical transformations. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">  ‡ If x represents position and t represents time, then u  1  has dimension of time, u  2  is dimensionless and <lb/> u  p  has dimension of length. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> On the Lewis–Riesenfeld (Dodonov–Man&apos;ko) invariant method <lb/></note>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<body> V. Aldaya et al. <lb/>(2011) [10] extended to the quantum case the Arnold <lb/>transformation and denoted it the Quantum Arnold Transformation (QAT): <lb/>ˆ <lb/> A : H  t  −→ H <lb/> G <lb/>τ <lb/> φ(x, t) −→ ϕ(κ, τ ) = ˆ <lb/> A (φ(x, t)) <lb/> = A <lb/>  * <lb/> u  2  (t) e <lb/> − <lb/> i <lb/> 2 <lb/> m <lb/> 1 <lb/> W (t) <lb/>˙ <lb/> u 2 (t) <lb/> u 2 (t) <lb/> x  2 <lb/> φ(x, t) <lb/> . <lb/> (12) <lb/>Here A <lb/>  *  is defined as A <lb/>  *  (f (x, t)) = f (A <lb/> −1  (κ, τ )), H  t  is the Hilbert space of solutions of <lb/>the Generalized Caldirola–Kanai Schrödinger equation at time t, and H <lb/> G <lb/>τ  is the Hilbert <lb/>space of solutions of the Schrödinger equation for the free Galilean particle at time <lb/> τ , where t and τ are related by the Arnold Transformation. Note that the QAT <lb/>transforms solutions of the time-dependent Schrödinger equation of the Generalized <lb/>Caldirola–Kanai system into free-particle wave functions, and that this is achieved by <lb/>applying the Arnold transformation together with multiplying the wave function by a <lb/>suitable phase and rescaling factor. These factors also renders the QAT unitary [10, 7]. <lb/>Some applications of the QAT were given in [25], where states from the harmonic <lb/>oscillator were mapped into the free particle giving rise to Hermite–Gauss and Laguerre– <lb/>Gauss wave packets; in [26, 27], where processes of Release and Recapture of a particle by <lb/>a harmonic trap were studied using the QAT; and in [28], where the QAT, which is a local <lb/>diffeomorphism in time, is extended beyond the &quot; focal &quot; points, correctly reproducing <lb/>the change in phase of the wave function (Maslov correction, see for instance [29]). <lb/>Castaños, Schuch &amp; Rosas-Ortiz (2013) [30] constructed coherent states for <lb/>different models (time-dependent and non-linear Hamiltonians) through complex Riccati <lb/>equations and found the corresponding Lewis invariants. <lb/>Since its introduction, the Lewis invariant and its associated Ermakov equation <lb/>entered an inflationary scenario with applications in many areas. One of the most <lb/>remarkable ones are the applications in Bose–Einstein Condensates (BEC) [31, 32], <lb/>where a transformation similar to that of Arnold (and known as scaling transformation in <lb/>this context) taking the time-dependent harmonic trap in the Gross–Pitaevskii equation <lb/>into a stationary one is applied. Although they did not use the Lewis invariant, the <lb/>scaling parameter satisfies the Ermakov equation (1). In this context, eq. (1) also <lb/>appears in [33]. <lb/>Recently, the Lewis–Riesenfeld invariant method has been used to inverse engineer <lb/>short-cuts to adiabaticity [16], to speed up cooling processes and transport in <lb/>electromagnetic traps and BECs, and to manipulate states in wave-guides [34], where <lb/>the relation with Generalized Caldirola–Kanai systems has been established [35]. The <lb/>main idea here is to design a Lewis invariant satisfying the property of commuting with <lb/>the Hamiltonian at initial and final times, and this can be achieved by building up a <lb/>function b satisfying certain boundary conditions and then determining, through the <lb/>Ermakov equation, the time-dependent frequency that should be applied in order to <lb/>take the system from the initial state to the desired final state without affecting to the <lb/>population of the levels. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> On the Lewis–Riesenfeld (Dodonov–Man&apos;ko) invariant method <lb/></note>

			<page> 5 <lb/></page>

			<body> Another recent application of the Lewis–Riesenfeld invariant method is in <lb/>mesoscopic RLC electric circuits [36], where the quantum evolution (even in the case of <lb/>time-dependent R(t), L(t) and C(t) and source term) is described. <lb/>The content of the paper is as follows. In Sec. 2 we revise the Lewis–Riesenfeld <lb/>method and explain it in terms of the QAT and the QAEPT, showing that the use of <lb/>the Dodonov–Man&apos;ko invariant is more appropriate for damped systems. In Sec. 3 the <lb/>examples of the Caldirola–Kanai and the Hermite oscillators are studied in detail. <lb/> 2. The Lewis–Riesenfeld method in light of the Quantum Arnold <lb/>Transformation <lb/> In their original paper Lewis &amp; Riesenfeld [2] provided a method to obtain a family <lb/>of exact wave functions for the time-dependent harmonic oscillator spanning the whole <lb/>Hilbert space. In a first step the method looks for an invariant, Hermitian operator <lb/>  L  , <lb/>a task which can follow the lines of [1]. Imposing the invariance condition § <lb/>d ˆ <lb/> I  L <lb/> dt <lb/> ≡ <lb/> ∂ ˆ <lb/> I  L <lb/> ∂t <lb/> + <lb/> i <lb/> [ ˆ <lb/> H(t), ˆ <lb/> I  L  ] = 0 , <lb/> (13) <lb/>wherê <lb/> H(t) is the Hamiltonian for the time-dependent harmonic oscillator and assuming <lb/>the most general quadratic invariant, they arrived at the quantum version of (4), where <lb/>the auxiliary function b(t) satisfies the Ermakov equation (1). In this equation ω  0  is just <lb/>an arbitrary constant. The possibility exists of giving a generic form for the invariant <lb/>(i.e. quadratic or linear, Hermitian or complex combinations of basic operators <lb/>  and <lb/> , etc.) and then solving for the coefficients to fulfill (13). <lb/>The second step in the method is realizing that finding eigenfunctions φ  s  (x, t) of <lb/>  L  , <lb/>ˆ <lb/> I  L  φ  s  (x, t) = λ  s  φ  s  (x, t), amounts to finding solutions of the Schrödinger equation except <lb/>for a time-dependent phase, which must be computed. That is, solutions ψ  s  (x, t) of the <lb/>Schrödinger equation <lb/> i <lb/>∂ψ  s <lb/> ∂t <lb/> = − <lb/> 2 <lb/> 2m <lb/> ∂ <lb/> 2  ψ  s <lb/> ∂x  2  + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> mω <lb/> 2  (t)x <lb/> 2  ψ  s  ≡ ˆ <lb/> H(t)ψ  s <lb/> (14) <lb/>may be of the form <lb/> ψ  s  (x, t) = e <lb/> iαs(t)  φ  s  (x, t) , <lb/> (15) <lb/>where α  s  (t) satisfies <lb/> dα  s  (t) <lb/>dt <lb/> φ  s  (x, t) = <lb/> i <lb/>∂ <lb/>∂t <lb/> − ˆ <lb/> H(t) <lb/> φ  s  (x, t) . <lb/> (16) <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> § Although we are working in the Schödinger picture of Quantum Mechanics, i.e. wavefunctions depend <lb/>explicitly on time and common operators like position <lb/>  and momentum <lb/>  do not depend on time, other <lb/>quantum operators may depend explicitly on time. This is precisely the case of the Hamiltonian for <lb/>non-conservative systems and in general for invariant operators. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> On the Lewis–Riesenfeld (Dodonov–Man&apos;ko) invariant method <lb/></note>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<body> That is just a nice consequence of the fact that <lb/>  L  applied on a solution of (14) is <lb/>again a solution: <lb/> i <lb/> ∂( ˆ <lb/> I  L  ψ  s  ) <lb/> ∂t <lb/> = ˆ <lb/> H(t)( ˆ <lb/> I  L  ψ  s  ) . <lb/> (17) <lb/>The phase can be solved in terms of b to give: <lb/> α  s  (t) = − <lb/> λ  s <lb/> dt <lb/>b(t)  2  . <lb/> (18) <lb/>Two observations can be made. First, the way in which the eigenfunctions φ  s  (x, t) <lb/> of the invariant are found are left to the ability of the user of the method. In this <lb/>respect, some authors have developed a unitary transformation from the Hamiltonian of <lb/>the simple harmonic oscillator into the invariant [37] (resembling very much the QAEPT, <lb/>see below). For this purpose, transforming the time-independent Schrödinger equation of <lb/>the simple harmonic oscillator, including the wave functions, would do the trick. Second, <lb/>although the Lewis-Riesenfeld method can provide all (quadratic) invariants for the time <lb/>dependent harmonic oscillator (by taking all possible solutions of the Ermakov equation) <lb/>it does not provide insight on their physical interpretation (like their spectra). In our <lb/>case, we provide a method that allows a neat physical interpretation of the invariants <lb/>since each one preserves the same character as in the harmonic oscillator. <lb/>In that sense the QAT and its generalization the QAEPT turn out to be very useful. <lb/> 2.1. The Quantum Arnold–Ermakov–Pinney transformation <lb/> The QAEPT is obtained when two different LSODE-systems are related by QATs with <lb/>the free-particle system as an intermediary, that is, when a QAT and an inverse QAT <lb/>are composed. That was shown in [7]. As the QAT, the QAEPT relies on the symmetry <lb/>structure of the systems of the Generalized Caldirola–Kanai type (see [10]). <lb/>In the QAEPT, it is the full set of invariant operators and the corresponding <lb/>eigenstates including the time dependence (with no need of searching for a phase as <lb/>it is given by the transformation) which is mapped from the simple harmonic oscillator <lb/>system into a Generalized Caldirola–Kanai system. The interpretation of the eigenstates <lb/>may be the same on both sides of the mapping. <lb/>Let A  1  and A  2  denote the Arnold transformations relating the LSODE-system 1 <lb/>and LSODE-system 2 to the free particle, respectively, then E = A <lb/> −1 <lb/> 1  A  2  relates LSODE-<lb/>system 2 to LSODE-system 1. E can be written as: <lb/> E : R × T  2  → R × T  1 <lb/> (x  2  , t  2  ) → (x  1  , t  1  ) = E(x  2  , t  2  ) . <lb/> (19) <lb/>The explicit form of the transformation can be easily computed by composing the <lb/>two Arnold transformations, resulting in: <lb/> x  1  = <lb/> x  2 <lb/> b(t  2  ) <lb/> W  1  (t  1  )dt  1  = <lb/> W  2  (t  2  ) <lb/> b(t  2  )  2  dt  2  , <lb/> (20) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> On the Lewis–Riesenfeld (Dodonov–Man&apos;ko) invariant method <lb/></note>

			<page> 7 <lb/></page>

			<body> where b(t  2  ) = <lb/> u <lb/> (2) <lb/> 2  (t  2  ) <lb/> u <lb/> (1) <lb/>2  (t  1  ) <lb/> satisfies the non-linear SODE: <lb/>¨ b + ˙ <lb/> f  2  ˙ <lb/> b + ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  b = <lb/> W <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 <lb/> W <lb/> 2 <lb/>1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> b  3 <lb/> ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + ˙ <lb/> f  1 <lb/> ˙ <lb/> u <lb/> (1) <lb/>2 <lb/> u <lb/> (1) <lb/>2 <lb/> (1 − b <lb/> 2  W  1 <lb/> W  2 <lb/> ) <lb/> , <lb/> (21) <lb/>and where u <lb/> (j) <lb/> i  refers to the i-th particular solution for system j; W  j  , ˙ <lb/> f  j  and ω  j  stand for <lb/>the Wronskian and the LSODE coefficients for system j; and the dot means derivation <lb/>with respect to the corresponding time variable. If all u <lb/> (j) <lb/> i <lb/> satisfy the canonicity <lb/>conditions (10) then b(t  2  ) satisfies the corresponding canonicity conditions <lb/> b(0) = 1 , <lb/> ˙ <lb/> b(0) = 0 . <lb/> (22) <lb/>Equation (21) constitutes a generalization of the Ermakov equation. That equation, <lb/>together with the LSODE of system 2, is a generalized Ermakov pair [14, 15]. Also, any <lb/>(quadratic) conserved quantity, which is shared by the two LSODE-systems, constitutes <lb/>a generalized Lewis invariant. Equation (21) actually defines a generalized Arnold <lb/>transformation, to be named (classical) Arnold–Ermakov–Pinney transformation, which <lb/>transforms solutions of the LSODE 1 into solutions of the LSODE 2. <lb/>The quantum version of the Arnold–Ermakov–Pinney transformation, ˆ <lb/> E, can be <lb/>obtained by computing the composition of a QAT and an inverse QAT to give: <lb/>ˆ <lb/> E : H <lb/> (2) <lb/> t  2 <lb/> −→ H <lb/> (1) <lb/> t  1 <lb/> φ(x  2  , t  2  ) −→ ϕ(x  1  , t  1  ) = ˆ <lb/> E (φ(x  2  , t  2  )) <lb/>= E <lb/>  * <lb/> b(t  2  ) e <lb/> − <lb/> i <lb/> 2 <lb/> m <lb/> 1 <lb/> W 2 (t 2 ) <lb/>˙ <lb/> b(t 2 ) <lb/> b(t 2 ) <lb/> x  2 <lb/>2 <lb/> φ(x  2  , t  2  ) <lb/> . <lb/> (23) <lb/>The Quantum Arnold–Ermakov–Pinney transformation (QAEPT) maps solutions <lb/>of a Generalized Caldirola–Kanai Schrödinger equation into solutions of a different, <lb/>auxiliary Generalized Caldirola–Kanai Schrödinger equation, and by construction it is <lb/>also a unitary transformation. The auxiliary system might be, in particular, the one <lb/>corresponding to a harmonic oscillator with frequency ω  1  (t) = ω  0  and ˙ <lb/> f  1  = 0. In this <lb/>case eqs. (20) and (21) reduce to: <lb/> x  1  = <lb/> x  2 <lb/> b(t  2  ) <lb/> , <lb/>t  1  = <lb/>  t  1 <lb/> 0 <lb/> W  2  (t) <lb/> b(t)  2  dt , <lb/> (24) <lb/>and <lb/>¨ b + ˙ <lb/> f  2  ˙ <lb/> b + ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  b = <lb/> W <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0 <lb/> b  3  . <lb/> (25) <lb/> 2.2. Ermakov System and interpretation of the Lewis Invariant <lb/> Consider the particular case where LSODE-system 1 is a harmonic oscillator (ω  1  (t  1  ) ≡ <lb/> ω  0  and ˙ <lb/> f  1  = 0), which can be described by the Hamiltonian <lb/> H  HO  = <lb/> p <lb/> 2 <lb/>1 <lb/> 2m <lb/>+ <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> mω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  x <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  , <lb/> (26) <lb/>and LSODE-system 2 is a time-dependent harmonic oscillator with frequency ω  2  (t  2  ) ≡ <lb/> ω(t) and ˙ <lb/> f  2  = 0, with Hamiltonian H(t) given by (14). Then, expressions (21) and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> On the Lewis–Riesenfeld (Dodonov–Man&apos;ko) invariant method <lb/></note>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<body> (25) simplify to (1). Obviously, for ω  0  = 0 the Arnold–Ermakov–Pinney transformation <lb/>reduces to the ordinary Arnold transformation, i.e. E = A. <lb/> Now, note that LSODE 1 Hamiltonian, H  HO  , is conserved, and that it is so on both <lb/>sides of the transformation E, given by (see (20)): <lb/> x  1  = <lb/> x <lb/>b <lb/>, t  1  = <lb/> 1 <lb/> b  2  dt = <lb/>1 <lb/> ω  0 <lb/> arctan ω  0  τ , <lb/> (27) <lb/>where τ denotes the (common) time in the free particle given by the Arnold <lb/>transformations A  1  and A  2  . Also, b(t) = u <lb/> (2) <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 + ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  τ  2  = <lb/> (u <lb/> (2) <lb/>2  )  2  + ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  (u <lb/> (2) <lb/>1  )  2  satisfies <lb/>the Ermakov equation (1) together with the canonicity conditions (22). <lb/>It should be stressed that b(t) never vanishes, otherwise the Wronskian W  2  (t) of <lb/>the two independent solutions would also vanish. And since in the quantum case the <lb/>time t  1  appears in the form e <lb/> −iω  0  t  1  = e <lb/> −i arctan(ω  0  τ )  , this expression is well-defined for <lb/>all times (even in the case where τ has singularities). This means that the QAEPT <lb/>transformation is well defined for all times (i.e. E : R × R → R × R). This is an <lb/>important advantage with respect to the QAT, that was defined only locally in time. <lb/>Computing the momentum p  1  = m ˙ <lb/> x  1  = m <lb/> dx  1 <lb/> dt  1 <lb/> = m <lb/> dt <lb/>dt  1 <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> ( <lb/> x <lb/>b <lb/> ) = m( ˙ <lb/> xb − ˙ <lb/> bx), we can <lb/>write H  HO  in variables corresponding to system 2: <lb/> H  HO  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2m <lb/>(pb − m ˙ <lb/> bx) <lb/> 2  + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> mω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  ( <lb/> x <lb/>b <lb/> ) <lb/> 2  ≡ I  L  . <lb/> (28) <lb/>That is easily recognized as the usual Lewis invariant I  L  . Thus, we have found a way to <lb/>characterize it through the Arnold–Ermakov–Pinney Transformation: I  L  corresponds <lb/>to the conserved quantity H  HO  imported from the simple harmonic oscillator, which is <lb/>used as an auxiliary system. Because the auxiliary system is arbitrary, I  L  is conserved <lb/>for any ω  0  , provided (1) is satisfied. Note that, in order to establish the identification <lb/> H  HO  ≡ I  L  it is essential to impose the canonicity conditions (22). <lb/>Using the explicit form of the inversê <lb/> E <lb/> −1  of (23) in this case, it is straightforward to <lb/>arrive at solutions φ(x, t) of the Schrödinger equation of the time-dependent harmonic <lb/>oscillator in terms of solutions of the Schrödinger equation for the simple harmonic <lb/>oscillator ϕ(x  1  , t  1  ): <lb/> φ(x, t) = <lb/>1 <lb/> √ <lb/> b <lb/>e <lb/> i <lb/> 2 <lb/> m <lb/> ˙ <lb/> b <lb/>b <lb/> x  2  ϕ <lb/> x <lb/>b <lb/>, <lb/> 1 <lb/> b  2  dt <lb/> , <lb/> (29) <lb/>where b is any solution of (1) satisfying the canonicity conditions (22). Note <lb/>that, if ϕ(x  1  , t  1  ) is chosen to be, for instance, an eigenfunction of the quantum <lb/>operator corresponding to (26), ˆ <lb/> H  HO  , then the transformed wave function φ(x, t) is <lb/>an eigenfunction of the quantum operator <lb/>  L  corresponding to the invariant (28) (the <lb/>explicit form of such operators is easily obtained from their classical counterpart by the <lb/>canonical quantization prescription). That shows that <lb/>  L  has discrete spectrum. <lb/>In the wave functions (29), two phases can be distinguished: the one corresponding <lb/>to the transformation itself, explicit in (29), and the phase mapped from e <lb/> −i(n+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> )ω  0  t  1 <lb/> (which is the only time dependence for stationary states in the harmonic oscillator) into <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> On the Lewis–Riesenfeld (Dodonov–Man&apos;ko) invariant method <lb/></note>

			<page> 9 <lb/></page>

			<body> e <lb/> −i(n+ <lb/> 1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> )ω  0 <lb/>  dt <lb/> b(t) 2  . The latter accounts for the phase of the Lewis–Riesenfeld method. The <lb/>former accounts for the phase (and the factor) which appears, for instance, in [37]. <lb/>Regarding the canonicity conditions (22), they play an important role in short-cuts <lb/>to adiabaticity processes for time-dependent harmonic oscillators, see [16], since they <lb/>imply that <lb/>  L  commute with the Hamiltonian at the initial time t = 0. If we further <lb/>imposë b = 0, then ω  0  = ω  2  (0) holds, and the Hamiltonian at t = 0 will coincide with <lb/>the invariant <lb/>  L  at t = 0. In the following, we shall assume that the Lewis invariant <lb/>  L <lb/> verifies these conditions. <lb/>The same process can be repeated for any other operator representing an invariant <lb/>in the simple harmonic oscillator (LSODE 1), showing the usefulness of the QAEPT to <lb/>perform quick computations. <lb/>In conclusion, it is the full set of invariant operators and the corresponding <lb/>eigenstates (with no need of searching a phase) what is mapped from the simple system <lb/>into the Generalized Caldirola–Kanai system through the QAEPT. Also, a word of <lb/>caution is in order: the Hamiltonian operator of one system is not mapped into the <lb/>Hamiltonian operator of the other system, which may not be invariant itself. <lb/> 2.3. The Lewis–Riesenfeld (Dodonov-Man&apos;ko) invariant method for the Generalized <lb/>Caldirola–Kanai oscillator through the QAEPT <lb/> In a Generalized Caldirola–Kanai system, the easiest way to find eigenstates of an <lb/>invariant operator and its eigenfunctions as solutions of the Generalized Caldirola–Kanai <lb/>Schrödinger equation, is to focus on an auxiliary system (the harmonic oscillator in the <lb/>previous subsection) with its Hamiltonian being the invariant operator and perform <lb/>the QATs or QAEPT necessary to map the Schrödinger equation of such auxiliary <lb/>system into the Generalized Caldirola–Kanai Schrödinger equation. In this process, <lb/>Hamiltonian is not mapped into Hamiltonian, but conserved operators into conserved <lb/>operators are. That procedure takes advantage of the fact that the eigenstates of the <lb/>harmonic oscillator Hamiltonian have a very simple time dependence, as has just been <lb/>noticed in the previous Subsection. <lb/>Let us now describe a different way of constructing an invariant. The idea is <lb/>to consider any linear combination of quadratic invariants in such a way that its <lb/>eigenfunctions solve the Generalized Caldirola–Kanai Schrödinger equation. The most <lb/>general invariant can be written in the form [10]: <lb/>ˆ <lb/> I = <lb/>1 <lb/>2m <lb/> 2  + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> m˜ <lb/> 2  ˆ <lb/> X <lb/> 2  + <lb/>˜ <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> X ˆ <lb/> P + ˆ <lb/> P ˆ <lb/> X <lb/> 2 <lb/> . <lb/> (30) <lb/>where <lb/>  and <lb/>  are arbitrary real numbers and <lb/> , ˆ <lb/> P are conserved position and <lb/>momentum operators satisfying that at t = 0 coincide with the usuaî <lb/> x, ˆ <lb/> p, namely <lb/>[10]: <lb/>ˆ <lb/> P = −iu  2 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂x <lb/> − mx <lb/> ˙ <lb/> u  2 <lb/> W <lb/>, <lb/> ˆ <lb/> X = <lb/>˙ <lb/> u  1 <lb/> W <lb/>x + <lb/> i <lb/>m <lb/>u  1 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂x <lb/>. <lb/> (31) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> On the Lewis–Riesenfeld (Dodonov–Man&apos;ko) invariant method <lb/></note>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>

			<body> The new invariant <lb/>  plays now the role of <lb/>  HO  in this more general setting. <lb/>The eigenfunctions of this operator, solutions of the Generalized Caldirola–Kanai <lb/>Schrödinger equation, are [10]: <lb/> φ  ν  (x, t) = <lb/>1 <lb/> √ <lb/> 2πΓ(ν + 1) ˜ b <lb/> ˜ <lb/> u  2  − i ˜ <lb/>Ωu  1 <lb/> ˜ b <lb/>  ν+ <lb/> 1 <lb/> 2  e <lb/> i <lb/> 2 <lb/> mx  2  ( <lb/> ˜ <lb/>Ω 2 u 1 <lb/>˜ <lb/> u 2 <lb/>˜ b 2  + <lb/> ˙ <lb/>˜ <lb/> u 2 <lb/>˜ <lb/> u 2 W <lb/> ) <lb/> C  1  D  ν <lb/> 2m <lb/> x <lb/> ˜ b <lb/> + C  2  D  −1−ν <lb/> i <lb/> 2m <lb/> x <lb/> ˜ b <lb/> , <lb/> (32) <lb/>where C  1  and C  2  are arbitrary constants, ˜ <lb/>Ω = <lb/> ˜ <lb/> ω  2  − <lb/> ˜ <lb/> γ  2 <lb/> 4 <lb/> and ν is in general a complex <lb/>number, D  ν  are the parabolic cylinder functions and Γ(z) is the Gamma function [39], <lb/> u  1  and u  2  are solutions of the LSODE equation corresponding to the given Generalized <lb/>Caldirola–Kanai oscillator, ˜ <lb/> u  2  = u  2  − ˜ <lb/> γu  1  /2 and the function <lb/>˜ b(t) = <lb/> ˜ <lb/> u <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  + ˜ <lb/>Ω  2  u <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  = <lb/> (u  2  − ˜ <lb/> γu  1  /2)  2  + ˜ <lb/>Ω  2  u <lb/> 2 <lb/>1 <lb/> (33) <lb/>plays the role of b(t), i.e. satisfies the Generalized Ermakov equation (25) with ω  0  = ˜ <lb/>Ω, <lb/>but with different initial conditions, namely  (0) = 1 and ˙ <lb/>˜ b(0) = − <lb/> ˜ <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/> . <lb/>As in the case without damping, neither b(t) nor  (t) vanish, otherwise the Wroskian <lb/> W (t) of the two solutions u  1  and u  2  would also vanish. <lb/>Thus, the invariant <lb/>  can be seen as <lb/>  HO  mapped from the harmonic oscillator with <lb/>frequency <lb/> through a QAEPT (24) characterized by  (t) satisfying (25) with ω  0  = ˜ <lb/>Ω. <lb/>The associated spectrum of <lb/>  is <lb/> λ  ν  =  ˜ <lb/>Ω (ν + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>) . <lb/> (34) <lb/>The integer, real or complex character of ν depends on the value of <lb/> (and this in <lb/>turns depends on the particular values of <lb/>  and <lb/> ). See [18] for a discussion in the case <lb/>of the damped harmonic oscillator. <lb/>The choice <lb/>  = ω  2  (0) and <lb/>  = 0 leads to a generalized Lewis invariant <lb/>  L  where <lb/>the arbitrary frequency has been chosen as ω  0  = ω  2  (0), providing an invariant that <lb/>commutes with the Generalized Caldirola–Kanai Hamiltonian (11), and in fact coincides <lb/>with it, at t = 0. This invariant could be useful in short-cuts to adiabaticity processes <lb/>for damped systems or with time-dependent mass (like in waveguides [35]), where an <lb/>invariant commuting with the Hamiltonian is needed. <lb/>For the damped harmonic oscillator with constant ω and γ (see Sec. 3.1), there <lb/>exists a different choice <lb/>  = ω and <lb/>  = γ leading to the only quadratic invariant <lb/> ≡ ˆ <lb/> I  DM  , the Dodonov–Man&apos;ko Invariant, whose unique, explicit time dependence is <lb/>through the Wronskian W (t) (like the Caldirola-Kanai Hamiltonian itself). Even more, <lb/>the coherent states associated with this invariant (through a factorization of the form <lb/>  DM  = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ( ˆ <lb/> A <lb/>  †  ˆ <lb/> A + ˆ <lb/> A ˆ <lb/> A <lb/>  †  ), ˆ <lb/> A <lb/>  †  , ˆ <lb/> A being conserved creation-annihilation operators) are the <lb/>only ones with minimal, time-independent uncertainty relations (see Dodonov &amp; Man&apos;ko <lb/>[18]). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> On the Lewis–Riesenfeld (Dodonov–Man&apos;ko) invariant method <lb/></note>

			<page> 11 <lb/></page>

			<body> In conclusion, when studying Generalized Caldirola-Kani systems with the Lewis– <lb/>Riesenfeld invariant method or with the more general method given by the QAEPT, a <lb/>different choice for the invariant operator than <lb/>  L  should be made, in particular <lb/>  (with <lb/>suitable coefficients <lb/>  and <lb/> ) may be more appropriate (like the case of <lb/>  DM  for the <lb/>damped harmonic oscillator). We shall denote this invariant a Generalized Dodonov– <lb/>Man&apos;ko invariant <lb/>  GDM  . <lb/> 2.4. Engineering a suitable QAEPT to build a Generalized Dodonov–Man&apos;ko invariant <lb/> Once the general setting has been established, let us apply the method in a suitable <lb/>way to obtain a proper invariant <lb/>  GDM  . The previous discussion on the choice of <lb/>an appropriate invariant, together with the corresponding analysis of the Caldirola– <lb/>Kanai oscillator (with constant damping and frequency, see below), suggest that it <lb/>would be helpful to construct a QAEPT from a Generalized Caldirola–Kanai system <lb/>2 to a yet undetermined Generalized Caldirola–Kanai system 1, but satisfying certain <lb/>requirements, implemented in the choice of b(t  2  ). In other words: we look for an auxiliary <lb/>system to help solving a Generalized Caldirola–Kanai oscillator in such a way that the <lb/>QAEPT is as simple as possible. <lb/>In particular, it is easy to check that choosing b = W <lb/> 1/2 <lb/>2  , the Generalized Caldirola– <lb/>Kanai system 1 is a time-dependent harmonic oscillator, i.e. it has no damping term. <lb/>In fact, with b = W <lb/> 1/2 <lb/>2 <lb/> the corresponding QAEPT is given by: <lb/> t  1  = <lb/> W  2 <lb/> b  2  dt  2  = t  2  ≡ t , <lb/>x  1  = <lb/> x  2 <lb/> b <lb/> = <lb/> x  2 <lb/> W <lb/> 1/2 <lb/>2 <lb/> , <lb/> (35) <lb/>and <lb/> φ(x  2  , t) = W <lb/> −1/4 <lb/> 2 <lb/> e <lb/> i <lb/> m <lb/> 4 <lb/> ˙ <lb/> W 2 <lb/> W 2 <lb/>2 <lb/> x  2 <lb/>2  ϕ( <lb/>x  2 <lb/> W <lb/> 1/2 <lb/>2 <lb/> , t) . <lb/> (36) <lb/>The wave function ϕ satisfies the Schrödinger equation for a time-dependent harmonic <lb/>oscillator with frequency <lb/> ω  1  (t) <lb/> 2  = ω  2  (t) <lb/> 2  + <lb/>2W  2  ¨ <lb/> W  2  − 3 ˙ <lb/> W <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 <lb/> 4W <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 <lb/> = ω  2  (t) <lb/> 2  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>4 <lb/>˙ <lb/> f <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>¨ <lb/> f  2  , <lb/> (37) <lb/>and the Wronskian for system 1 turns to be W  1  = 1, i.e. the auxiliary system 1 <lb/>is not damped. However, ω  1  (t) is not arbitrary but specifically designed to simplify <lb/>the mapping. Therefore, it is straightforward to map results (such as invariants) and <lb/>computations from the known, auxiliary system 1 to the Generalized Caldirola–Kanai <lb/>system 2. <lb/>In this case the canonicity conditions (22) are not satisfied in general, since b(0) = 1 <lb/>but ˙ <lb/> b(0) = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ˙ <lb/> W (0) (see the examples on Sec. 3). <lb/>Note that transformation (35), together with its corresponding extension to velocity, <lb/>is nothing other than a generalized version [24] of the time-dependent canonical <lb/>transformation that removes the damping in the damped harmonic oscillator [46] (see <lb/>also [47, 48]). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> On the Lewis–Riesenfeld (Dodonov–Man&apos;ko) invariant method <lb/></note>

			<page> 12 <lb/></page>

			<body> Constructing the Lewis invariant <lb/>  L  for this time-dependent harmonic oscillator, <lb/>and mapping it back to our Generalized Caldirola–Kanai system 2 through the previous <lb/>QAEPT, leads to a Generalized Dodonov–Man&apos;ko invariant <lb/>  GDM  for system 2. More <lb/>precisely, the invariant can be written as: <lb/>ˆ <lb/> I  GDM  = <lb/>ˆ <lb/> P <lb/> 2 <lb/> 2m <lb/>+ <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> m <lb/> ω  2  (0) <lb/> 2  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>¨ <lb/> f  2  (0) <lb/> ˆ <lb/> X <lb/> 2  + <lb/>˙ <lb/> f  2  (0) <lb/>2 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> X ˆ <lb/> P + ˆ <lb/> P ˆ <lb/> X <lb/> 2 <lb/> . <lb/> (38) <lb/>We shall provide examples of this construction in the next section. <lb/> 3. Examples <lb/> Let us discuss some examples of damped systems, where the previous ideas can be <lb/>applied to construct invariants and simplify analytical computations. <lb/> 3.1. Caldirola–Kanai oscillator <lb/> The simplest example that can be studied is the quantum damped harmonic oscillator, <lb/>also known as Caldirola–Kanai oscillator [8, 9]. From the point of view of invariant <lb/>operators, it was first studied by Dodonov &amp; Man&apos;ko [18], who constructed first-order <lb/>invariants in the form of conserved creation and annihilation operators and derived <lb/>a basis of number states and a family of coherent states satisfying minimal, time-<lb/>independent uncertainty relations. The classical equation of motion is given by (we <lb/>shall not consider the external force term): <lb/>¨ <lb/> x + γ ˙ <lb/> x + ω <lb/> 2  x = 0 , <lb/> (39) <lb/>where ω and γ are constants. Even though this is a linear equation with constant <lb/>coefficients, the system is not conservative since the Hamiltonian describing this equation <lb/>is time-dependent: <lb/> H  CK  = e <lb/> −γt  p <lb/> 2 <lb/> 2m <lb/>+ <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> mω <lb/> 2  e <lb/> γt  x <lb/> 2  . <lb/> (40) <lb/>There is an old controversy with the quantum version of the Caldirola–Kanai <lb/>oscillator concerning the dissipative character of this system [40]. The main drawback <lb/>is that the evolution is unitary for all times and there is no loss of coherence, something <lb/>that it is considered inherent to a quantum dissipative system. Some proposals have <lb/>been made to address that paradoxical situation [41] (see also [42]). <lb/>An alternative physical interpretation to the damping term in (39) is that of a <lb/>time-dependent mass, that is, the mass is actually of the form: <lb/> m(t) = me <lb/> γt <lb/> ⇒ <lb/> H  CK  = <lb/> p <lb/> 2 <lb/> 2m(t) <lb/>+ <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> m(t)ω <lb/> 2  x <lb/> 2  . <lb/> (41) <lb/>Thus the Caldirola–Kanai oscillator describes an oscillator whose mass is growing <lb/>exponentially. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> On the Lewis–Riesenfeld (Dodonov–Man&apos;ko) invariant method <lb/></note>

			<page> 13 <lb/></page>

			<body> The solutions of the classical equations (39), satisfying the canonical conditions <lb/> u  1  (0) = ˙ <lb/> u  2  (0) = 0, u  2  (0) = ˙ <lb/> u  1  (0) = 1 (see [10]) are: <lb/> u  1  (t) = e <lb/> − <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/> t  sin Ωt <lb/>Ω <lb/> , <lb/>u  2  (t) = e <lb/> − <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/> t <lb/> cos Ωt + <lb/> γ <lb/> 2Ω <lb/>sin Ωt <lb/> , <lb/> (42) <lb/>where Ω = <lb/> ω  2  − <lb/> γ  2 <lb/> 4 <lb/> and the Wronskian is given by W (t) ≡ ˙ <lb/> u  1  (t)u  2  (t) − u  1  (t) ˙ <lb/> u  2  (t) = <lb/> e <lb/> −γt  = m/m(t). The solutions are oscillatory if ω &gt; <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/> (underdamping) and have a <lb/>single zero for ω &lt; <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/> (overdamping) and ω = <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/> (critical damping). In this last case the <lb/>solutions are u  1  (t) = te <lb/> − <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/> t  and u  2  (t) = e <lb/> − <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/> t <lb/> 1 + <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/> t <lb/> . <lb/>Let us restrict to the underdamping case. From the previous solutions the Arnold <lb/>transformation (7) is given by: <lb/> τ = <lb/> u  1  (t) <lb/> u  2  (t) <lb/>= <lb/> sin Ωt <lb/>Ω <lb/> cos Ωt + <lb/> γ <lb/> 2Ω <lb/> sin Ωt <lb/> κ = <lb/> x <lb/>u  2  (t) <lb/>= <lb/> x <lb/>e <lb/> − <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/> t <lb/> cos Ωt + <lb/> γ <lb/> 2Ω <lb/> sin Ωt <lb/> . <lb/> (43) <lb/>The Arnold–Ermakov–Pinney transformation mapping the Caldirola–Kanai <lb/>oscillator into the standard harmonic oscillator (and its corresponding quantum version) <lb/>is also easily derived, resulting in: <lb/> t <lb/> ′  = <lb/> W (t) <lb/> b(t)  2  dt = <lb/>1 <lb/> ω  0 <lb/> arctan ω  0  τ <lb/>x <lb/> ′  = <lb/> x <lb/>b(t) <lb/>, <lb/> (44) <lb/>where ω  0  is the (arbitrary) frequency of the auxiliary harmonic oscillator, and <lb/> b(t) = u  2  (t) <lb/> 1 + ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  τ  2  = <lb/> u  2  (t)  2  + ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  u  1  (t)  2 <lb/> = e <lb/> − <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/> t <lb/> cos Ωt + <lb/> γ <lb/> 2Ω <lb/>sin Ωt <lb/>  2 <lb/> + ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0 <lb/> sin <lb/> 2  Ωt <lb/>Ω  2  . <lb/> (45) <lb/>Note that b(t) never vanishes since this would imply u  1  (t) = u  2  (t) = 0 at some time <lb/>instant, and thus the Wronskian would also be zero at that time instant, contradicting <lb/>the fact that u  1  and u  2  are independent solutions of (39). Note also that b(t) satisfies <lb/>the canonicity conditions (22). <lb/>Let us construct an invariant for the Caldirola–Kanai oscillator. The first possibility <lb/>is to construct a generalized Lewis invariant <lb/>  L  with <lb/>  = ω and <lb/>  = 0: <lb/>ˆ <lb/> I  L  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2m <lb/> 2  + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> mω <lb/> 2  ˆ <lb/> X <lb/> 2  , <lb/> (46) <lb/>leading to the invariant constructed by Pedrosa [24]. <lb/>According to the discussion in Sec. 2, for a damped system it is more appropriate <lb/>to use the Dodonov–Man&apos;ko invariant, which is built using the solution u  1  (t) and the <lb/>(noncanonical) solutioñ <lb/> u  2  (t), with <lb/>  = ω and <lb/>  = γ: <lb/>u  1  (t) = e <lb/> − <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/> t  sin Ωt <lb/>Ω <lb/> , <lb/> ˜ <lb/> u  2  (t) = u  2  (t) − <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/> u  1  (t) = e <lb/> − <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/> t  cos Ωt . <lb/> (47) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> On the Lewis–Riesenfeld (Dodonov–Man&apos;ko) invariant method <lb/></note>

			<page> 14 <lb/></page>

			<body> Therefore  (t) = <lb/> ˜ <lb/> u  2  (t)  2  + Ω  2  u  1  (t)  2  = e <lb/> − <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/> t  , which also never vanishes. The <lb/>Dodonov–Man&apos;ko invariant (30) for these solutions is given by: <lb/>ˆ <lb/> I  DM  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2m <lb/> 2  + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> mω <lb/> 2  ˆ <lb/> X <lb/> 2  + <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> X ˆ <lb/> P + ˆ <lb/> P ˆ <lb/> X <lb/> 2 <lb/>= ˆ <lb/> H  CK  + <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> xˆ  + ˆ <lb/> pˆ <lb/> 2 <lb/> . <lb/> (48) <lb/>It can be shown that, for the specific choice <lb/>  = ω and <lb/>  = γ made above, the <lb/>invariant <lb/>  DM  coincides with that provided by Nassar [44, 45]. It also coincides with <lb/>the invariant discussed by Cerveró &amp; Villarroel [38]. <lb/>The eigenstates of this invariant, solutions of the Caldirola–Kanai Schrödinger <lb/>equation (note that the time-dependent phase appearing in the Lewis–Riesenfeld <lb/>invariant method is included in the QAEPT), are derived from (32): <lb/> φ  n  (x, t) = <lb/>1 <lb/> √ <lb/> 2π2  n  n! <lb/>e <lb/> −i(nΩ+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> (Ω+i <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/> ))t  e <lb/> − <lb/> m <lb/> 2 <lb/> (Ω+i <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/> )e  γt  x  2  H  n <lb/> mΩ <lb/> e <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/> t  x <lb/> ,(49) <lb/> with eigenvalues Ω(n + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ), with n = 0, 1, . . . (assuming Ω &gt; 0). Thus, the result of [18] <lb/>is recovered. <lb/>Note that in deriving (49) it has been crucial to choose the solutions u  1  (t) and <lb/>  2  (t), <lb/>since in this case  (t) = e <lb/> − <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/> t  = W <lb/> 1/2  and thus the change of variables in time in (44) <lb/>is trivial, t <lb/> ′  = t (as explained in Sec. 2.4). Thus, for the case of the damped harmonic <lb/>oscillator the Generalized Dodonov-Man&apos;ko invariant <lb/>  GDM  coincide with <lb/>  DM  . This is <lb/>a special feature of the damped harmonic oscillator, sincë <lb/> f  2  (0) = 0 in this case. <lb/>For an arbitrary wave function ϕ  HO  of the harmonic oscillator, the corresponding <lb/>wave function φ  CK  in the Caldirola–Kanai system is given by: <lb/> φ  CK  (x, t) = <lb/>1 <lb/> ˜ b <lb/>e <lb/> i <lb/> m <lb/> 2 <lb/>˙ <lb/>˜ b <lb/>W ˜ b <lb/> x  2  ϕ  HO <lb/>  x <lb/> ˜ b <lb/>, t <lb/> = e <lb/> γ <lb/> 4 <lb/> t  e <lb/> −i <lb/> m <lb/> 4 <lb/> γe  γt  x  2  ϕ  HO <lb/> e <lb/> γ <lb/> 2 <lb/> t  x, t <lb/> . <lb/> (50) <lb/>This makes apparent the general strategy: make computations in a (simpler) system <lb/>(e.g. compute ϕ  HO  ) and map them to the system of interest (get φ  CK  ). <lb/>It should be stressed that in deriving (50) it has not been necessary to solve an <lb/>eigenvalue equation for an invariant in the Generalized Caldirola–Kanai variables, (50) <lb/>is the result of a unitary transformation between two Hilbert spaces. This is a great <lb/>improvement with respect to the Lewis–Riesenfeld or the Dodonov–Man&apos;ko invariant <lb/>method, where first an invariant is found and then its eigenvectors are computed in <lb/>order to provide a basis of the Hilbert space. With the QAEPT it is possible to map <lb/>any harmonic oscillator wave function ϕ  HO  into its corresponding function φ  CK  in the <lb/>Caldirola–Kanai Hilbert space. In particular number states, coherent states, squeezed <lb/>states, or even density matrices (see [25]). <lb/> 3.2. Hermite oscillator <lb/> Similar considerations can be made in more general systems following the same steps. <lb/>Let us consider a LSODE system that has a damping rate linear in time γ = αt, with <lb/> α &gt; 0: <lb/>¨ <lb/> x + αt ˙ <lb/> x + ω <lb/> 2  x = 0 . <lb/> (51) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> On the Lewis–Riesenfeld (Dodonov–Man&apos;ko) invariant method <lb/></note>

			<page> 15 <lb/></page>

			<body> This equation is similar to the Hermite differential equation, thus this system is known <lb/>as Hermite oscillator [49]. In analogy with the oscillator with time-dependent mass, the <lb/>Hermite oscillator would have a mass <lb/> m(t) = me <lb/> αt  2  /2  . <lb/> (52) <lb/>In order to seek for wavefunctions of the quantum Hermite oscillator we need the <lb/>solutions of the classical equation (51). Those satisfying the canonicity conditions (10) <lb/>are: <lb/> u  1  (t) = t  1  F  1 <lb/>  1 <lb/>2 <lb/>+ <lb/> ω <lb/> 2 <lb/> 2α <lb/>; <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>; −αt <lb/> 2  /2 <lb/> , u  2  (t) =  1  F  1 <lb/>  ω <lb/> 2 <lb/> 2α <lb/>; <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>; −αt <lb/> 2  /2 <lb/> (53) <lb/>and the Wronskian is W (t) = e <lb/> −αt  2  /2  . Here  1  F  1  (a; b; z) denotes the confluent <lb/>hypergeometric function [39]. <lb/>From these solutions the Arnold transformation (7) is given by: <lb/> τ = <lb/> u  1  (t) <lb/> u  2  (t) <lb/>= <lb/> t  1  F  1 <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> + <lb/> ω  2 <lb/> 2α <lb/> ; <lb/> 3 <lb/>2 <lb/> ; −αt <lb/> 2  /2 <lb/> 1  F  1 <lb/>  ω  2 <lb/> 2α <lb/> ; <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ; −αt  2  /2 <lb/> κ = <lb/> x <lb/>u  2  (t) <lb/>= <lb/> x <lb/> 1  F  1 <lb/>  ω  2 <lb/> 2α <lb/> ; <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ; −αt  2  /2 <lb/> , <lb/> (54) <lb/>and with this the QAT (12) is easily derived. <lb/>The solution u  2  (t) has zeros if α &lt; ω <lb/> 2  (underdamping) and has no zeros if <lb/> α &gt; ω <lb/> 2  (overdamping) or α = ω <lb/> 2  (critical damping). In this last case u  2  (t) = e <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> t  2  ω  2 <lb/> and u  1  (t) = <lb/> 1 <lb/> ω <lb/>  π <lb/> 2 <lb/> e <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> t  2  ω  2  Erfi <lb/> ωt <lb/> √ <lb/> 2 <lb/> . Thus, for overdamping and critical damping the <lb/>Arnolnd transformation is defined for all times, whereas for the underdamping case the <lb/>transformation is local in time, mapping a patch of the Hermite oscillator onto a patch <lb/>of a free particle trajectory. Note that in the underdamping case the system performs a <lb/>finite number of oscillations, since the zeros of the confluent hypergeometric functions <lb/>are finite: u  2  (t) is even and has 2⌈ <lb/> ω  2  −α <lb/> 2α <lb/> ⌉ zeros whereas u  1  (t) is odd and has 2⌈ <lb/> ω  2  −2α <lb/> 2α <lb/> ⌉ + 1 <lb/>zeros. <lb/>The Arnold–Ermakov–Pinney transformation (and its corresponding quantum <lb/>version QAEPT) is also easily derived, resulting in: <lb/> t <lb/> ′  = <lb/> W (t) <lb/> b(t)  2  dt = <lb/>1 <lb/> ω  0 <lb/> arctan ω  0  τ <lb/> (55) <lb/> x <lb/> ′  = <lb/> x <lb/>b(t) <lb/> (56) <lb/>where ω  0  is the (arbitrary) frequency of the auxiliary harmonic oscillator, and <lb/> b(t) = u  2  (t) <lb/> 1 + ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  τ  2  = <lb/> u  2  (t)  2  + ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  u  1  (t)  2 <lb/> (57) <lb/>Note that, as before, b(t) never vanishes. <lb/>With this the QAEPT is obtained and the generalized Lewis invariant <lb/>  L  (i.e. the <lb/>Hamiltonian for the harmonic oscillator mapped into the Hermite oscillator) can be <lb/>computed, recovering the results in [49]. Let us give, instead, the construction of a <lb/>generalized Dodonov–Man&apos;ko invariant as proposed in Sec. 2.3 and 2.4. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> On the Lewis–Riesenfeld (Dodonov–Man&apos;ko) invariant method <lb/></note>

			<page> 16 <lb/></page>

			<body> Choosing b(t) = W (t) = e <lb/> −αt  2  /2  and renaming x <lb/> ′  ≡ y, the equation (51) transforms <lb/>into <lb/>¨ <lb/> y + (ω <lb/> 2  − <lb/> α <lb/> 2 <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>4 <lb/> α <lb/> 2  t <lb/> 2  )y = 0 , <lb/> (58) <lb/>and the wave functions transform as given in (36): <lb/> φ(x, t) = e <lb/> 1 <lb/>8 <lb/> αt  2  e <lb/> −i <lb/> m <lb/> 4 <lb/> αte <lb/> αt 2 <lb/>2  x  2  ϕ(e <lb/> 1 <lb/>4 <lb/> αt  2  x, t) , <lb/> (59) <lb/>where ϕ(y, t) is a solution of the Schrödinger equation for the time-dependent harmonic <lb/>oscillator with frequency ω <lb/> 2  − <lb/> α <lb/> 2 <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>4 <lb/> α <lb/> 2  t <lb/> 2  . Applying the Lewis–Riesenfeld invariant <lb/>method to this time-dependent harmonic oscillator we obtain a Lewis invariant that, <lb/>when mapped to the original system provides a generalized Dodonov–Man&apos;ko invariant, <lb/>given by: <lb/>ˆ <lb/> I  GDM  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2m <lb/> 2  + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> m(ω <lb/> 2  − α) ˆ <lb/> X <lb/> 2 <lb/> (60) <lb/>Note that there is no term in <lb/>  + ˆ <lb/> P ˆ <lb/> X <lb/> 2 <lb/> , due to the fact that in this case ˙ <lb/> f (0) = 0. <lb/>This term would appear if we had chosen another initial time t  0  = 0. <lb/>A similar construction can be performed for the Lane–Endem oscillator: <lb/>¨ <lb/> x + <lb/> µ <lb/> 1 + νt <lb/> ˙ <lb/> x + ω <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  x = 0 , <lb/> (61) <lb/>for which the construction of the Lewis invariant was given in [50]. We shall only provide <lb/>here the expression of the Generalized Dodonov–Man&apos;ko invariant, which turns to be: <lb/>ˆ <lb/> I  GDM  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2m <lb/> 2  + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> m(ω <lb/> 2  + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> µν) ˆ <lb/> X <lb/> 2  + <lb/> µ <lb/> 2 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> X ˆ <lb/> P + ˆ <lb/> P ˆ <lb/> X <lb/> 2 <lb/> . <lb/> (62) <lb/> 4. Conclusion and outlook <lb/> In this paper the relation between the Lewis-Riesenfneld invariant method and the <lb/>Quantum Arnold-Ermakov-Pinney transformation has been established. The former <lb/>aims at finding an invariant for a time-dependent harmonic oscillator, in order to build <lb/>a basis of eigenstates of this invariant satisfying the Schrödinger equation (up to a time-<lb/>dependent phase). The latter is a unitary transformation that relates two Generalized <lb/>Caldirola-Kanai systems, and allows to map states and invariant operators from one <lb/>system to the other. In particular, if one of the system is a harmonic oscillator and the <lb/>other is a time-dependent harmonic oscillator, the Lewis-Riesenfeld invariant method <lb/>is recovered. The time-dependent phase is built into the transformation, in such a way <lb/>that it maps solutions of the Schrödinger equation for one system into solutions for the <lb/>Schrödinger equation of the other directly. <lb/>Any invariant of the harmonic oscillator is mapped, through the QAEPT, into an <lb/>invariant of the time-dependent harmonic oscillator. In particular, the Hamiltonian for <lb/>the harmonic oscillator is mapped to the Lewis invariant, explaining why it has discrete <lb/>eigenvalues. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> On the Lewis–Riesenfeld (Dodonov–Man&apos;ko) invariant method <lb/></note>

			<page> 17 <lb/></page>

			<body> In this paper we have also shown that the QAEPT is global, in contrast to the <lb/>QAT, which is local in time. This explains the robustness and wide applicability of the <lb/>Lewis-Riesenfeld invariant method. <lb/>The main advantage of the QAEPT is that it can also be applied to damped systems <lb/>(or with time-dependent mass) in a unified way. In the case of constant damping <lb/>and frequency we have shown that a more convenient choice is the Dodonov-Man&apos;ko <lb/>invariant, rather than the usual Lewis invariant. The reason is that it shares with the <lb/>Hamiltonian the loss-energy property [18] (which amounts to the only explicit time-<lb/>dependence being through the Wronskian W (t)), and therefore its eigenstates or the <lb/>associated coherent states have nicer properties. <lb/>We thus propose in the general case to use, as an alternative to the Lewis invariant, <lb/>the generalized version of the Dodonov-Man&apos;ko invariant when dealing with time-<lb/>dependent damped (Generalized Caldirola-Kanai) systems. This could be useful in <lb/>designing short-cuts to adiabaticity processes [16] when damping or time-dependent <lb/>masses are present [35, 34], as well as in constructing coherent and related states. <lb/>Another interesting application of the QAEPT would be in the case of mixed states <lb/>(see [25] where the QAT was discussed in this setting). Let us denote by <lb/>  HO  a density <lb/>matrix for the harmonic oscillator, satisfying the quantum Liouville equation <lb/> ∂ ˆ <lb/> ρ  HO <lb/> ∂t <lb/> = − <lb/> i <lb/> [ ˆ <lb/> H  HO  , ˆ <lb/> ρ  HO  ] . <lb/> (63) <lb/>Then, the density matrix <lb/>  GCK  = ˆ <lb/> E ˆ <lb/> ρ  HO  <lb/> −1  is a proper density matrix (sincê <lb/> E is <lb/>unitary Tr(ˆ ρ  GCK  ) = Tr(ˆ ρ  HO  ) = 1 ) satisfying the quantum Liouville equation for the <lb/>Generalized Caldirola-Kanai oscillator: <lb/> ∂ ˆ <lb/> ρ  GCK <lb/> ∂t <lb/> = − <lb/> i <lb/> [ ˆ <lb/> H  GCK  , ˆ <lb/> ρ  GCK  ] . <lb/> (64) <lb/>All properties of the density matrix <lb/>  HO  are transferred tô <lb/> ρ  GCK  , such as <lb/>characteristic functions, quasi-probability distributions, etc. Also, since Tr(ˆ ρ <lb/> 2 <lb/> GCK  ) = <lb/>Tr(ˆ ρ <lb/> 2 <lb/> HO  ), the purity or mixed-state character of <lb/>  HO  is shared by <lb/>  GCK  . In particular, <lb/>if <lb/>  HO  describes a Gaussian state, ˆ <lb/> ρ  GCK  also corresponds to a Gaussian state. <lb/>However, since the QAEPT does not transform Hamiltonians into each other (only <lb/>Schrödinger and quantum Liouville equations do), care should be taken in the physical <lb/>interpretation of the transformed density matrix. For instance, a thermal equilibrium <lb/>state for the harmonic oscillator is not mapped into a thermal equilibrium state of the <lb/>Generalized Caldirola-Kanai oscillator (in the case when it makes physical sense, for <lb/>instance when the time scale of the time-dependence of the Hamiltonian <lb/>  GCK  is much <lb/>larger than that of relaxation to thermal equilibrium). <lb/>A deeper study of the QAEPT applied to mixed states in order to analyze how <lb/>entanglement is transformed under <lb/>  (generalized to multipartite systems), and how <lb/>it can be used to describe dissipation and decoherence analyzing the transformation <lb/>  There is an interesting connection between the Dodonov-Man&apos;ko invariant and the Hamiltonian for <lb/>the damped harmonic oscillator in expanding coordinates H  exp  , see [47, 48, 51]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> On the Lewis–Riesenfeld (Dodonov–Man&apos;ko) invariant method <lb/></note>

			<page> 18 <lb/></page>

			<body> properties of master equations like the Lindblad one under <lb/>  is the subject of a work <lb/>in progress and will be presented elsewhere. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments <lb/> Work partially supported by the MCYT, Junta de Andalucía and Fundación Séneca <lb/>under projects FIS2008-06078-C03-01, P06-FQM-01951 and 08816/PI/08. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] Lewis H R Jr. (1967) Phys. Rev. Lett. 18 510 <lb/>[2] Lewis H R Jr. and Riesenfeld W B (1969) J. Math. Phys. 10 1458 <lb/>[3] Ermakov V P (1880) Univ. Izv. Kiev 20 1 <lb/>[4] Ermakov V P (2008) Appl. Anal. Discrete Math. 2, 123 <lb/>[5] Milne W E (1930) Phys. Rev. 35 86367 <lb/>[6] Pinney E (1950) Proc. A.M.S. 1 681 <lb/>[7] Guerrero J and López-Ruiz FF (2013), Phys. Scr. 87, 038105 <lb/>[8] Caldirola P (1941) Nuovo Cimento 18 393 <lb/>[9] Kanai E (1948) Prog. Theor. Phys. 3 440 <lb/>[10] Aldaya V, Cossío F, Guerrero J and López-Ruiz FF (2011) J. Phys. A 44 065302 <lb/>[11] Lie S (1883) Arch. Math. VIII,IX 187 <lb/>[12] Mahomed F M, Qadir A (2009) J. Nonlinear Math. Phys. 16 283 <lb/>[13] Aminova A V and N. Aminov N A-M (2010) Sb. Math. 201 631 <lb/>[14] Maamache M (1995) Phys. Rev. A52, 936 <lb/>[15] Rogers C and Hoenselaers C (1993) On higher dimensional Ermakov systems: canonical reductions <lb/> Loughborough University of Technology, Department of Mathematical Sciences <lb/>[16] Chen X, Ruschhaupt A, Schmidt S, del Campo A, Guéry-Odelin D and Muga JG (2010) Phys. <lb/>Rev. Lett. 104 063002 <lb/>[17] Arnold V I, Supplementary Chapters to the Theory of Ordinary Differential Equations (Nauka, <lb/>Moscow, 1978); English transl., Geometrical Methods in the Theory of Ordinary Differential <lb/>Equations, (Springer–Verlag, New York–Berlin, 1983) <lb/>[18] Dodonov V.V. and Man&apos;ko V.I.(1979) Phys. Rev. A 20 550 <lb/>[19] Dodonov V V, Man&apos;ko V I (1989) Invariants and the Evolution of Nonstationary Quantum Systems, <lb/> Nova Science Pub Inc, 1989 <lb/>[20] Malkin I A, Man&apos;ko V I, Trifonov D A (1969) Phys. Lett. A 30 414 <lb/>[21] Pedrosa I A and Rosas A (2009) Phys. Rev. Lett. 103 010402 <lb/>[22] Hartley J G and Ray J R (1982), Phys. Rev. D 25, 382 <lb/>[23] Lewis H R and Leach P G L (1982) J. Math. Phys. 23 165 <lb/>[24] Pedrosa I A (1987) J. Math. Phys. 28 2662 <lb/>[25] Guerrero J, López-Ruiz FF, Aldaya V and Cossío F (2011) J. Phys. A 44 445307 <lb/>[26] López-Ruiz FF, Guerrero J and Aldaya V (2011) J. Russ. Laser Res. 32 372 <lb/>[27] Guerrero J and López-Ruiz FF (2013) Il Nuovo Cimento C 36 127 <lb/>[28] Guerrero J, Aldaya V, López-Ruiz FF and Cossío F (2012) Int. J. Geom. Meth. Mod. Phys. 9 <lb/> 1260011 <lb/>[29] Horvathy P A (1979) Int. J. Theor. Phys 18 245–250 <lb/>[30] Castaños O, Schuch D and Rosas-Ortiz O (2013), J. Phys. A 46, 075304 <lb/>[31] Kagan Y, Surkov E L and Shlyapnikov G V (1996) Phys. Rev. A 54 R1753 <lb/>[32] Castin Y and Dum R (1996) Phys. Rev. Lett. 77 5315 <lb/>[33] García-Ripoll JJ, Pérez-García Vm and Torres P, (1999) Phys. Rev. Lett. 83 1715 <lb/>[34] Stefanatos D (2014) Phys. Rev. A90 023811 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> On the Lewis–Riesenfeld (Dodonov–Man&apos;ko) invariant method <lb/></note>

			<page> 19 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [35] Rodríguez-Lara B M, Aleahmad P, Moya-Cessa H M and Christodoulides D N (2014) Opt. Lett. <lb/> 39 2083 <lb/>[36] Pedrosa I A, Melo J L and Nogueira E Jr. (2014) Modern Physics Letters B28 1450212 <lb/>[37] Moya-Cessa H, Fernández Guasti M (2003) Phys. Lett. A311 1 <lb/>[38] Cerveró J M and Villarroel J (1984) J. Phys. A17 2963 <lb/>[39] Gradshteyn I.S. and Ryzhik I.M., Table of integrals, series and products (Academic, 2007) <lb/>[40] Gzyl H (1983) Phys. Rev A27 2297 <lb/>[41] Schuch D (1997) Phys. Rev. A55 935 <lb/>[42] Dekker H (1981) Phys. Rep. 80 1 <lb/>[43] Dodonov V V, Malkin I A and Man&apos;ko V I (1974), Physica 74 597 <lb/>[44] Nassar AB (1986) J. Math. Phys. 27 755 <lb/>[45] Nassar AB (1986) J. Math. Phys. 27 2949 <lb/>[46] Gzyl H (1983) Phys. Rev. A 27 2297 <lb/>[47] Schuch D 1990 Int. J. Quant. Chem., Quant. Chem. Symp. 24 767 <lb/>[48] Schuch D 1999 Int. J. Quant. Chem. 72 537 <lb/>[49] Um C-I, Choi J-R and Yeon K-H (2001) J. Korean Phys. Soc. 38 447 <lb/>[50] Vubangsi M, Tchoffo M and Fai L C (2013) Afr. Rev. Phys. 8 341 <lb/>[51] Schuch D, Guerrero J, López-Ruiz FF and Aldaya V (2013) Interrelations between different <lb/>canonical descriptions of dissipative systems, arXiv:1306.4533v2 </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
