<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> February 16, 2015 14:54 WSPC/CRC <lb/>9.75 x 6.5 <lb/>1560022 <lb/> QCD Evolution Workshop 2014 <lb/>International Journal of Modern Physics: Conference Series <lb/>Vol. 37 (2015) 1560022 (8 pages) <lb/>c <lb/> The Authors <lb/>DOI: 10.1142/S2010194515600228 <lb/> Color Entanglement in Hadronic Processes for Transverse <lb/>Momentum Dependent Parton Distribution Functions <lb/> M. G. A. Buffing  *  and P. J. Mulders  † <lb/> Theory Group, Nikhef &amp; Department of Physics, <lb/>Faculty of Science, VU University <lb/>De Boelelaan 1081, NL-1081 HV Amsterdam, the Netherlands <lb/>  *  m.g.a.buffing@vu.nl <lb/>  †  p.j.g.mulders@vu.nl <lb/> Published 25 February 2015 <lb/>In the description of protons, we go beyond the ordinary collinear parton distribution <lb/>functions (PDFs), by including transverse momentum dependent PDFs (TMDs). As <lb/>such, we become sensitive to polarization modes of the partons and protons that one <lb/>cannot probe without accounting for transverse momenta of partons, in particular when <lb/>looking at azimuthal asymmetries. <lb/>Hadronic processes require the inclusion of gluon contributions forming the gauge <lb/>links, which are path-ordered exponentials tracing the color flow. In processes with two <lb/>hadrons in the initial state, such as Drell-Yan (DY), the gauge links from different parts of <lb/>the process get entangled. We show that in color disentangling this gauge link structure, <lb/>one becomes sensitive to this color flow. After disentanglement, particular combinations <lb/>of TMDs will require a different numerical color factor than one naively might have <lb/>expected. Such color factors will even play a role for azimuthal asymmetries in the <lb/>simplest hadronic processes such as DY. <lb/> Keywords: Drell-Yan; parton distribution functions; gauge links. <lb/>PACS Numbers: 12.38.−t, 13.85.Qk, 13.90.+i <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> Transverse momentum dependent parton distribution functions (TMDs) are used to <lb/>describe the proton in momentum space when going beyond the collinear approach <lb/>by including transverse directions. <lb/> 1–3  Whereas in the transverse momentum inte-<lb/>grated case only three distribution functions are present, namely for unpolarized <lb/>quarks in an unpolarized proton, f  1  (x), for longitudinally polarized (actually chiral) <lb/>quarks in a longitudinally polarized proton, the helicity distribution g  1  (x), and for <lb/>transversely polarized quarks in a transversely polarized proton, the transversity <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> This is an Open Access article published by World Scientific Publishing Company. It is distributed <lb/>under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 (CC-BY) License. Further distribution <lb/>of this work is permitted, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/></note>

			<page> 1560022-1 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. Conf. Ser. 2015.37. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> February 16, 2015 14:54 WSPC/CRC <lb/>9.75 x 6.5 <lb/>1560022 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> M. G. A. Buffing &amp; P. J. Mulders <lb/></note>

			<body> h  1  (x), more functions become available once transverse momenta are included, such <lb/>as the Sivers function for unpolarized quarks in a transversely polarized proton. <lb/>It has a &apos;single-spin&apos; nature and is time-reversal odd (T-odd). A special effect for <lb/>T-odd TMDs such as the Sivers function [4]–[8] is a sign flip between the Sivers <lb/>TMD as measured in the Drell-Yan process compared to the Sivers TMD as mea-<lb/>sured in SIDIS. This sign flip is in particular a consequence of the presence of gauge <lb/>links (Wilson lines), which are path-ordered exponentials connecting the (anti)quark <lb/>fields in the quark correlator and which assure color gauge invariance. In Section 2, <lb/>based on Ref. [9], we give an overview of these kind of universality issues for the <lb/>other quark TMDs as well. We show that also for the Pretzelocity function, a ten-<lb/>sor correlation for transversely polarized quarks in a transversely polarized proton, <lb/>process dependence is implied. Rather than having a potential infinite number of <lb/>these functions, one for each process, we show that three independent Pretzelocity <lb/>TMDs are sufficient, of which in principle different combinations appear in a given <lb/>process. For this study we use transverse moments. <lb/>In Section 3, based on the Refs. [10] and [11] we go one step further, by consid-<lb/>ering processes with multiple hadronic correlators, the simplest example of which <lb/>is the Drell-Yan process. <lb/> 12  By again using transverse moments, we find an entan-<lb/>glement between the gauge link contributions, which manifests itself in specific <lb/>overall factors for those azimuthal asymmetries that involve combinations of TMDs <lb/>describing the quark distributions in two hadrons. <lb/> 2. TMD formalism <lb/> The quark correlator Φ <lb/> [U]  (x, p  T  is given by a matrix element containing a bilocal <lb/>combination of fields and a gauge link in the form <lb/>Φ <lb/> [U] <lb/> ij  (x, p  T  ; n) = <lb/> d ξ·P d <lb/> 2  ξ  T <lb/> (2π)  3  e <lb/> ip·ξ <lb/> P |ψ  j  (0) U  [0,ξ]  ψ  i  (ξ)|P <lb/> ξ·n=0 <lb/> . <lb/> (1) <lb/>The gauge link, required for making the object color gauge invariant, is a path-<lb/>ordered exponential. The two simplest paths, the staple links U <lb/> [±]  illustrated in <lb/>Fig. 1, are given by U <lb/> [±] <lb/>[0,ξ]  = U <lb/> [n] <lb/>[0,±∞]  U <lb/> T <lb/> [0T ,ξT ]  U <lb/> [n] <lb/>[±∞,ξ]  and connect the two fields at <lb/>the (spatial) locations 0 and ξ through a staple like path that runs through either <lb/>plus or minus infinity. More complicated paths are allowed as well, depending on <lb/>the process under consideration, see e.g. Ref. [13] for a list of gauge link structures. <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/> Fig. 1. The two simplest gauge links for the quark correlator, where the path of the staple runs <lb/>through (a) through plus light cone infinity and (b) through minus light cone infinity. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1560022-2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. Conf. Ser. 2015.37. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> February 16, 2015 14:54 WSPC/CRC <lb/>9.75 x 6.5 <lb/>1560022 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Color Entanglement in Hadronic Processes for TMDs <lb/></note>

			<body> The correlator in Eq. 1 can be parametrized in terms of TMDs as <lb/> 14 <lb/> Φ <lb/> [U]  (x, p  T  ; n) = <lb/> f <lb/> [U] <lb/>1  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) − f <lb/> ⊥[U] <lb/> 1T  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) <lb/> ρσ <lb/> T <lb/> p  T  ρ  S  T  σ <lb/> M <lb/> + S  L  g <lb/> [U] <lb/>1L  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> )γ  5 <lb/> − <lb/> p  T  · S  T <lb/> M <lb/>g <lb/> [U] <lb/>1T  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> )γ  5  + h <lb/> [U] <lb/>1T  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) γ  5  / <lb/>S  T  + S  L  h <lb/> ⊥[U] <lb/> 1L  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) <lb/> γ  5  / p <lb/> T <lb/> M <lb/> − <lb/> p  T  · S  T <lb/> M <lb/>h <lb/> ⊥[U] <lb/> 1T  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) <lb/> γ  5  / p <lb/> T <lb/> M <lb/> + ih <lb/> ⊥[U] <lb/> 1 <lb/> (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) <lb/> / p <lb/> T <lb/> M <lb/> / <lb/>P <lb/> 2 <lb/> , <lb/> (2) <lb/>with the spin vector parametrization S <lb/> µ  = S  L  P <lb/> µ  + S <lb/> µ <lb/> T <lb/> + M <lb/> 2  S  L  n <lb/> µ  . <lb/>In order to make an identification between the separate descriptions, we use <lb/>weightings with transverse momenta. For a single transverse weighting, this gives <lb/>the result <lb/> 15 <lb/> Φ <lb/> α[U] <lb/>∂ <lb/> (x) ≡ <lb/> d <lb/> 2  p  T  p <lb/> α <lb/> T <lb/> Φ <lb/> [U]  (x, p  T  ) = <lb/> Φ <lb/> α <lb/>D  (x) − Φ <lb/> α <lb/>A  (x) <lb/> + C <lb/> [U] <lb/> G  Φ <lb/> α <lb/>G  (x) <lb/>= <lb/> Φ <lb/> α <lb/>∂  (x) + C <lb/> [U] <lb/> G  Φ <lb/> α <lb/>G  (x), <lb/>(3) <lb/>where the matrix elements in the above equation are defined through <lb/>Φ <lb/> α <lb/>D  (x) = <lb/> dx  1  Φ <lb/> α <lb/>D  (x − x  1  , x  1  |x), <lb/> (4) <lb/>Φ <lb/> α <lb/>A  (x) ≡ <lb/> dx  1  PV <lb/> i <lb/>x  1 <lb/> Φ <lb/> nα <lb/>F  (x − x  1  , x  1  |x), <lb/> (5) <lb/>Φ <lb/> α <lb/>G  (x) = π Φ <lb/> nα <lb/>F  (x, 0|x) <lb/>( 6 ) <lb/>and where we have used the collinear multi-parton correlators <lb/>Φ <lb/> α <lb/>D ij  (x − x  1  , x  1  |x) = <lb/> dξ·P dη·P <lb/> (2π)  2  e <lb/> ip1·η+i(p−p1)·ξ <lb/> ××P |ψ  j  (0)U  [0,η]  iD <lb/> α <lb/> T <lb/> (η) U  [η,ξ]  ψ  i  (ξ)|P <lb/> LC <lb/> , <lb/> (7) <lb/>Φ <lb/> α <lb/>F ij  (x − x  1  , x  1  |x) = <lb/> dξ·P dη·P <lb/> (2π)  2  e <lb/> ip1·η+i(p−p1)·ξ <lb/> ××P |ψ  j  (0)U  [0,η]  F <lb/> nα <lb/> T <lb/> (η) U  [η,ξ]  ψ  i  (ξ)|P <lb/> LC <lb/> . <lb/> (8) <lb/>In the above equations, the Φ  G  (x) is the gluonic pole or Efremov-Teryaev-Qiu-<lb/>Sterman matrix element [16]–[21]. This is a T-odd multi-parton twist three corre-<lb/>lator at zero gluon momentum. The time reversal even (T-even) correlators <lb/> Φ <lb/> α <lb/>∂  (x) <lb/>will be referred to as the partial derivative matrix element in the rest of these pro-<lb/>ceedings. Since gluonic poles vanish for fragmentation correlators [22]–[26], we will <lb/>focus on distribution correlators only. <lb/>Going beyond the single transverse weighting, we write down the expansion of <lb/>the quark correlator as the summation over all possible matrix elements that are <lb/>allowed. In doing so we use matrix elements containing zero, one, or more gluonic <lb/>poles or partial derivative matrix elements. Apart from terms containing gluonic <lb/></body>

			<page> 1560022-3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. Conf. Ser. 2015.37. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> February 16, 2015 14:54 WSPC/CRC <lb/>9.75 x 6.5 <lb/>1560022 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> M. G. A. Buffing &amp; P. J. Mulders <lb/></note>

			<body> poles or partial derivative contributions only, also mixed contributions appear, giv-<lb/>ing terms that have both types of contributions in them, such as <lb/> Φ <lb/> ij <lb/> {∂G}  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ). <lb/>Note that the parentheses in {∂G} indicate that the contributions are symmetrized. <lb/>Writing down the expansion, we get <lb/> 9 <lb/> Φ <lb/> [U]  (x, p  T  ) <lb/>= Φ(x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) + <lb/> p  T  i <lb/> M <lb/> Φ <lb/> i <lb/>∂  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) + <lb/> p  T  ij <lb/> M  2 <lb/> Φ <lb/> ij <lb/>∂∂  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) + <lb/> p  T  ijk <lb/> M  3 <lb/> Φ <lb/> ijk <lb/>∂∂∂  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) + . . . <lb/> + C <lb/> [U] <lb/> G <lb/> p  T  i <lb/> M <lb/> Φ <lb/> i <lb/>G  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) + <lb/> p  T  ij <lb/> M  2 <lb/> Φ <lb/> ij <lb/> {∂G}  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) + <lb/> p  T  ijk <lb/> M  3 <lb/> Φ <lb/> ijk <lb/> {∂∂G}  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) + . . . <lb/> + <lb/> c <lb/> C <lb/> [U] <lb/> GG,c <lb/> p  T  ij <lb/> M  2  Φ <lb/> ij <lb/>GG,c  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) + <lb/> p  T  ijk <lb/> M  3 <lb/> Φ <lb/> ijk <lb/> {∂GG},c  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) + . . . <lb/> + <lb/> c <lb/> C <lb/> [U] <lb/> GGG,c <lb/> p  T  ijk <lb/> M  3  Φ <lb/> ijk <lb/>GGG,c  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) + . . . <lb/> + . . . . <lb/> (9) <lb/>Here we have omitted trace contributions. All the terms on the r.h.s. of the above <lb/>equation are multiplied by a tensor of definite rank, i.e. 1, p  T  i  , p  T  ij  or p  T  ijk  . This <lb/>rank corresponds to the number of transverse operators that the corresponding <lb/>matrix element contains and encodes specific azimuthal behavior. E.g. a single glu-<lb/>onic pole matrix element is of rank 1, having azimuthal dependence exp(±iϕ), <lb/>whereas a triple gluonic pole matrix element is of rank 3. <lb/>For our study of the (non)universality properties of TMDs, we use transverse <lb/>weightings, which for TMDs are denoted <lb/> f <lb/> (n)[U] <lb/> ... <lb/> (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) = <lb/> −p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> 2M  2 <lb/> n <lb/> f <lb/> [U] <lb/> ...  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ). <lb/>(10) <lb/>Note that the transverse moments integrated over p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> are in general the ones that <lb/>can be related to collinear correlators. The p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> -dependent moments are the ones <lb/>that show up after integration over the azimuthal angles only. This is sufficient <lb/>to select specific TMDs. E.g., a single transverse weighting selects the worm gear <lb/>functions g <lb/> [U] <lb/>1T  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) and h <lb/> ⊥[U] <lb/> 1L  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ), the Sivers function f <lb/> ⊥[U] <lb/> 1T  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) and the Boer-<lb/>Mulders function h <lb/> ⊥[U] <lb/> 1 <lb/> (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ). These functions survive, since in the parametrization <lb/>in Eq. (2) they come with one factor of p  T  . Similarly, a weighting with two factors of <lb/> p  T  selects out the Pretzelocity function h <lb/> ⊥[U] <lb/> 1T  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ), since it comes with two factors <lb/>of p  T  in the expansion in Eq. (2). These weightings can be performed on Eq. (9) as <lb/>well. There we have the same mechanism that a single transverse weighting projects <lb/>out the matrix elements with one factor of p  T  in front of them, and similarly for <lb/>higher weightings. <lb/>In order to make the identification between matrix elements containing gluonic <lb/>poles and/or partial derivative operators and the moments of TMDs, we use the <lb/>behavior under time reversal symmetry of these objects as well. They are either time <lb/>reversal even (T-even) or time reversal odd (T-odd). In Eq. (9), all elements contain-<lb/>ing an odd number of gluonic poles are T-odd, whereas all other contributions are <lb/></body>

			<page> 1560022-4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. Conf. Ser. 2015.37. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> February 16, 2015 14:54 WSPC/CRC <lb/>9.75 x 6.5 <lb/>1560022 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Color Entanglement in Hadronic Processes for TMDs <lb/></note>

			<body> T-even. Hence, the worm gear functions g <lb/> [U] <lb/> 1T  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) and h <lb/> ⊥[U] <lb/> 1L  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) correspond to <lb/> Φ <lb/> i <lb/> ∂  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) and are therefore universal, whereas the Sivers function f <lb/> ⊥[U] <lb/> 1T  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) and <lb/>the Boer-Mulders function h <lb/> ⊥[U] <lb/> 1 <lb/> (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) correspond to C <lb/> [U] <lb/> G  Φ <lb/> i <lb/>G  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) and therefore <lb/>are process dependent. <lb/>For the rank 2 Pretzelocity function we could attempt a similar procedure. At the <lb/>level of the matrix elements, there are two types of objects that will appear. Firstly <lb/>there is the <lb/> Φ <lb/> ij <lb/>∂∂  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ), which is independent of the gauge link structure. Secondly, <lb/>there is C <lb/> [U] <lb/> GG,c  Φ <lb/> ij <lb/>GG,c  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ), a double gluonic pole contribution, which depending <lb/>on the process can appear in two color configurations, hence the summation over <lb/>the color index c. Both these contributions are T-even. Hence, the Pretzelocity <lb/>contribution is of the form <lb/> 9, 27 <lb/> h <lb/> ⊥[U] <lb/> 1T  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) = h <lb/> ⊥(A) <lb/> 1T  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) + C <lb/> [U] <lb/> GG,1  h <lb/> ⊥(B1) <lb/> 1T <lb/> (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) + C <lb/> [U] <lb/> GG,2  h <lb/> ⊥(B2) <lb/> 1T <lb/> (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ). (11) <lb/>Therefore, we have found that the Pretzelocity function is process dependent. We <lb/>go one step further at this point, by reminding the relation <lb/> h <lb/> [U] <lb/>1  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) = h <lb/> [U] <lb/>1T  (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ) + h <lb/> ⊥[U](1) <lb/> 1T <lb/> (x, p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> ). <lb/>(12) <lb/>From the Eqs. (11) and (12), we also find that the p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> behavior of the rank 0 <lb/>functions, e.g. the transversity distribution is affected by the Pretzelocity functions <lb/>through trace terms <lb/> Φ  G·G,c  , which will be explained in more detail in a future <lb/>study. <lb/> 28 <lb/> 3. Color entanglement <lb/> In this section, which is based on the Refs. [10] and [11], we go one step further, by <lb/>looking at processes containing multiple correlators rather than just the individual <lb/>correlators by using transverse weighting with transverse moments the way we see <lb/>it. <lb/>In Ref. [29] is was shown for a specific quark-quark scattering diagram that color <lb/>entanglement occurs. For the diagram in this reference, this was a result of contri-<lb/>butions where two additional gluons coming from the parts that are associated with <lb/>the quark correlators couple on the hard scattering contribution. Since these gluons <lb/>carry color, the color flow is in such a way that the diagram cannot be disentangled <lb/>into a product of two quark correlators and a hard scattering contribution. <lb/>In our case, we focus on Drell-Yan as an example. In the Drell-Yan process, a <lb/>quark and an antiquark produce a virtual photon, which in turn produces something <lb/>else (e.g. a quark-antiquark pair). In the simplest description, where we ignore the <lb/>gauge link contributions, the cross section is given by <lb/> dσ  DY  ∼ Tr  c <lb/> Φ(x  1  , p  1T  )Γ <lb/>  *  Φ(x  2  , p  2T  )Γ <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/> N  c <lb/> Φ(x  1  , p  1T  )Γ <lb/>  *  Φ(x  2  , p  2T  )Γ. <lb/>(13) <lb/></body>

			<page> 1560022-5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. Conf. Ser. 2015.37. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> February 16, 2015 14:54 WSPC/CRC <lb/>9.75 x 6.5 <lb/>1560022 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> M. G. A. Buffing &amp; P. J. Mulders</note>

			<body> <lb/> (a) <lb/>(b) <lb/> Fig. 2. The Drell-Yan process illustrated. In (a) the process can be seen, whereas in (b) the gauge <lb/>knots are indicated as well. The numbers next to these gauge knots indicate their path. <lb/> In principle, the gauge link contributions have to be included as well, which is <lb/>indicated in Fig. 2. Note that the Figs. 2(a) and 2(b) are taken from Ref. [11]. The <lb/> U &apos;s in this figure will we referred to as gauge knots rather than gauge links, since <lb/>these path-ordered exponentials are not yet evaluated between the quark fields in <lb/>the correlators. This implies for the cross section that <lb/> dσ  DY  = Tr  c <lb/> U <lb/>  † <lb/> −  [p  2  ]Φ(x  1  , p  1T  )U  −  [p  2  ]Γ <lb/>  *  U <lb/>  † <lb/>−  [p  1  ]Φ(x  2  , p  2T  )U  −  [p  1  ]Γ <lb/> (14) <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/> N  c <lb/> Φ <lb/> [−]  (x  1  , p  1T  )Γ <lb/>  *  Φ <lb/> [− <lb/>  †  ]  (x  2  , p  2T  )Γ. <lb/>Since the gauge knots are nontrivial objects in color space, an entanglement becomes <lb/>apparent at this point. In the analysis of this entanglement we use transverse weight-<lb/>ings, introduced before in Section 2. <lb/>An immediate integration of Eq. (14) over transverse momenta yields an object <lb/>that no longer is color entangled, as the transverse gauge link contributions dis-<lb/>appear. In fact, after weighting, the color entanglement only remains apparent for <lb/>the contributions containing gluonic poles from both correlators. As for all gluons, <lb/>a color matrix will appear at the position of the gauge knot on the external leg of <lb/>the hard process. Even after transverse integration, this color matrices remain at <lb/>the locations where the gluonic poles couple. If just a single gluonic pole were to be <lb/>present, this would not be a problem. However, in the situation that there is a glu-<lb/>onic pole for both the correlators (i.e. both the hadronic initial state particles), these <lb/>color matrices cause a color entanglement, involving an ordering Tr  c  [T <lb/> a  T <lb/> b  T <lb/> a  T <lb/> b  ]. In <lb/>order to write this cross section contribution as the product of two hadronic corre-<lb/>lators and a hard scattering contribution, we would like to have the color structure <lb/>Tr  c  [T <lb/> a  T <lb/> a  ] Tr  c  [T <lb/> b  T <lb/> b  ]. The difference between these two configurations is <lb/>Tr  c  [T <lb/> a  T <lb/> b  T <lb/> a  T <lb/> b  ] <lb/>Tr  c  [T  a  T  a  ] Tr  c  [T  b  T  b  ] <lb/>= − <lb/> 1 <lb/> N  2 <lb/> c  − 1 <lb/>1 <lb/> N  c <lb/> . <lb/> 1560022-6 <lb/> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. Conf. Ser. 2015.37. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> February 16, 2015 14:54 WSPC/CRC <lb/>9.75 x 6.5 <lb/>1560022 <lb/> Color Entanglement in Hadronic Processes for TMDs <lb/> It is for this reason that transverse weighting of the correlator in both the partonic <lb/>momenta gives the result <lb/> p <lb/> α <lb/> 1T  p <lb/> β <lb/> 2T  σ  DY  = <lb/>1 <lb/> N  c <lb/> Φ <lb/> α <lb/>∂  (x  1  )Γ <lb/>  *  <lb/> Φ <lb/> β <lb/>∂  (x  2  )Γ <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/> N  c <lb/> Φ <lb/> α <lb/>G  (x  1  ) Γ <lb/>  *  <lb/> Φ <lb/> β <lb/>∂  (x  2  )Γ + <lb/> Φ <lb/> α <lb/>∂  (x  1  )Γ <lb/>  *  Φ <lb/> β <lb/>G  (x  2  )Γ <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/> N  2 <lb/> c  − 1 <lb/>1 <lb/> N  c <lb/> Φ <lb/> α <lb/>G  (x  1  ) Γ <lb/>  *  Φ <lb/> β <lb/>G  (x  2  ) Γ. <lb/>(15) <lb/>The color factor of the last contribution is different from the 1/N  c  that one would <lb/>expect if color entanglement effects were to be absent. Not only is the numerical <lb/>value different, there is a sign flip associated with it as well. Going back to Section 2, <lb/>it is known that (single) gluonic pole matrix elements correspond, among others, <lb/>with the Boer-Mulders function. Based on this identification, we could argue that it <lb/>is the double Boer-Mulders contribution where these entanglement effects will start <lb/>to play a role, provided that the transverse weighting procedure as we see it is the <lb/>correct one. <lb/>In principle weightings with an arbitrary number of transverse momenta can be <lb/>performed. To accommodate this additional step, we propose the introduction of <lb/>an additional color factor f <lb/> [U1,U2] <lb/> RG1RG2  , such that the contribution to the cross section <lb/>is given by <lb/> σ(x  1  , x  2  , q  T  ) ∼ <lb/> 1 <lb/> N  c <lb/> f <lb/> [U1,U2] <lb/> RG1RG2  Φ <lb/> [U1]  (x  1  , p  1T  ) ⊗ Φ <lb/> [U2]  (x  2  , p  2T  ) ˆ <lb/> σ(x  1  , x  2  ). <lb/>(16) <lb/>This additional numerically calculable color factor depends on the number of gluonic <lb/>poles for both the correlators (R  G1  and R  G2  ) and the gauge link structures U  1  and <lb/> U  2  contributing to both the correlators. <lb/> 4. Conclusions <lb/> By using an analysis in terms of transverse moments, we can make an identification <lb/>between matrix elements and TMDs. As a result, some of the TMDs turn out to be <lb/>process dependent. However, despite this process dependence for some of the TMDs, <lb/>only a finite number of basic functions exists, with a calculable linear combination <lb/>of them appearing in any given process. This leads e.g. to the presence of three <lb/>Pretzelocity functions and (calculable) process-dependence of the p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> behavior of for <lb/>instance the transversity functions, of which details will be given in a forthcoming <lb/>publication. <lb/> 28 <lb/> In hard scattering processes with two hadronic particles in the initial state, color <lb/>entanglement could occur for specific contributions to the cross section. This entan-<lb/>glement is a result of gauge knots that are &apos;stuck&apos; on the specific external parton legs <lb/>in the diagram for the hard scattering process. After transverse integration, these <lb/>gauge knots usually are of no concern in the sense that they do not cause entan-<lb/>glement, but are absorbed in their respective hadronic matrix elements. However, <lb/></body>

			<page> 1560022-7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. Conf. Ser. 2015.37. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> February 16, 2015 14:54 WSPC/CRC <lb/>9.75 x 6.5 <lb/>1560022 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> M. G. A. Buffing &amp; P. J. Mulders <lb/></note>

			<body> in the situation where there are gluonic poles for initial state hadronic correlators, <lb/>the entanglement remains, even for processes like Drell-Yan. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments <lb/> This research is part of the research program of the &quot; Stichting voor Fundamenteel <lb/>Onderzoek der Materie (FOM) &quot; , which is financially supported by the &quot; Nederlandse <lb/>Organisatie voor Wetenschappelijk Onderzoek (NWO) &quot; . We also acknowledge the <lb/>FP7 EU-programmes HadronPhysics3 (contract No. 283286) and QWORK (con-<lb/>tract 320389). We acknowledge discussions with Asmita Mukherjee, coauthor of <lb/>Ref. [9], on which Section 2 is based, Daniël Boer, and various participants of the <lb/>QCD evolution workshop. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. J. P. Ralston and D. E. Soper, Nucl. Phys. B 152, 109 (1979). <lb/>2. R. D. Tangerman and P. J. Mulders, Phys. Rev. D 51, 3357–3372 (1995). <lb/>3. D. Boer, Phys. Rev. D 60, 014012 (1999). <lb/>4. D. W. Sivers, Phys. Rev. D 41, 83 (1990). <lb/>5. D. W. Sivers, Phys. Rev. D 43, 261–263 (1991). <lb/>6. J. C. Collins, Nucl. Phys. B 396, 161–182 (1993). <lb/>7. J. C. Collins, Phys. Lett. B 536, 43–48 (2002). <lb/>8. S. J. Brodsky, D. S. Hwang and I. Schmidt, Nucl. Phys. B 642, 344–356 (2002). <lb/>9. M. G. A. Buffing, A. Mukherjee and P. J. Mulders, Phys. Rev. D 86, 074030 (2012). <lb/>10. M. G. A. Buffing and P. J. Mulders, JHEP 1107, 065 (2011). <lb/>11. M. G. A. Buffing and P. J. Mulders, Phys. Rev. Lett. 112 092002 (2014). <lb/>12. S. D. Drell and T.-M. Yan, Phys. Rev. Lett. 25, 316 (1970); Erratum-ibid. 25, 902(E), <lb/>(1970). <lb/>13. C. J. Bomhof, P. J. Mulders and F. Pijlman, Eur. Phys. J. C 47, 147 (2006). <lb/>14. A. Bacchetta, M. Diehl, K. Goeke, A. Metz, P. J. Mulders and M. Schlegel, JHEP <lb/> 0702, 093 (2007). <lb/>15. D. Boer, P. J. Mulders and F. Pijlman, Nucl. Phys. B 667 201–241 (2003). <lb/>16. A. V. Efremov and O. V. Teryaev, Sov. J. Nucl. Phys. 36, 140 (1982). <lb/>17. A. V. Efremov and O. V. Teryaev, Phys. Lett. B 150, 383 (1985). <lb/>18. J-W. Qiu and G. F. Sterman, Phys. Rev. Lett. 67, 2264 (1991). <lb/>19. J-W. Qiu and G. F. Sterman, Nucl. Phys. B 378, 52 (1992). <lb/>20. J-W. Qiu and G. F. Sterman, Phys. Rev. D 59, 014004 (1998). <lb/>21. Y. Kanazawa and Y. Koike, Phys. Lett. B 478, 121 (2000). <lb/>22. A. Metz, Phys. Lett. B 549, 139–145 (2002). <lb/>23. J. C. Collins and A. Metz, Phys. Rev. Lett. 93, 252001 (2004). <lb/>24. L. P. Gamberg, A. Mukherjee and P. J. Mulders, Phys. Rev. D 77, 114026 (2008). <lb/>25. S. Meissner and A. Metz, Phys. Rev. Lett. 102, 172003 (2009). <lb/>26. L. P. Gamberg, A. Mukherjee and P. J Mulders, Phys. Rev. D 83, 071503 (2011). <lb/>27. M. G. A. Buffing and P. J. Mulders, Int. J. Mod. Phys. Conf. Ser. 20, 66 (2012). <lb/>28. D. Boer, M. G. A. Buffing and P. J. Mulders, in preparation. <lb/>29. T. C. Rogers and P. J. Mulders, Phys. Rev. D 81, 094006 (2010). <lb/> </listBibl>

			<page> 1560022-8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. Conf. Ser. 2015.37. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only.</note>


	</text>
</tei>
