<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage> Fock–Tani representation for composite particles in a soluble model <lb/> M. D. Girardeau <lb/> Citation: Journal of Mathematical Physics 21, 2365 (1980); doi: 10.1063/1.524693 <lb/>View online: http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.524693 <lb/>View Table of Contents: http://scitation.aip.org/content/aip/journal/jmp/21/9?ver=pdfcov <lb/>Published by the AIP Publishing <lb/> Articles you may be interested in <lb/> Ground state of the massless Nelson model in a non-Fock representation <lb/>J. Math. Phys. 46, 102107 (2005); 10.1063/1.2050507 <lb/>Second‐quantization representation for a nonrelativistic system of composite particles. II. Kinematical properties <lb/>of the multispecies Tani transformation <lb/>J. Math. Phys. 19, 2605 (1978); 10.1063/1.523615 <lb/>Second‐quantized representation for a model system with composite particles <lb/>J. Math. Phys. 18, 791 (1977); 10.1063/1.523309 <lb/>Second‐quantization representation for a nonrelativistic system of composite particles. I. Generalized Tani <lb/>transformation and its iterative evaluation <lb/>J. Math. Phys. 16, 1901 (1975); 10.1063/1.522742 <lb/>Total Number of Particles and Fock Representation <lb/>J. Math. Phys. 8, 663 (1967); 10.1063/1.1705261 <lb/> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:47:30 <lb/></titlePage>

			<front> Fock-Tani representation for composite particles in a soluble model <lb/> M. D. Girardeau a) <lb/> Physique Thiorique, Universite de Nice,  b)  Nice, France <lb/> (Received  29  January  1980;  accepted for publication 6 June  1980) <lb/> The transformation from the usual Fock representation to the Fock-Tani representation for <lb/>composite particles is carried out for a simplified model of the composite which allows closed-<lb/>form expressions for the transformed quantities. A &quot;statistical renormalization&quot;, in which single <lb/>particle energies and interactions become dependent on the composite particle occupation <lb/>number, plays an essential role in the solution, allowing absorption of unlinked terms into the <lb/>definition of the renormalized energies. <lb/></front>

			<body> I. INTRODUCTION <lb/> The Fock-Tani representation for composite particles <lb/>has been shown to be a convenient representation for the <lb/>states and observables of systems of composite particles such <lb/>as atoms, molecules. ions, and nuclei, allowing explicit in-<lb/>corporation of the effects of internal structure and excita-<lb/>tion. rearrangement collisions, etc ... into the algebra of states <lb/>and observables.  \-4  There are. however. some formidable <lb/>mathematical problems involved in the transformation from <lb/>the standard Fock representation to the new Fock-Tani re-<lb/>presentation. and as a result only partial results are available <lb/>for the explicit terms in the Hamiltonian in the new repre-<lb/>sentation.  It  is therefore useful to examine a model in which <lb/>the structure of the system is so simplified that all steps of the <lb/>change of representation can be carried out explicitly, in <lb/>hopes that the insight thus gained into the structure of the <lb/>representation can be extended to real physical systems. <lb/>The simplest imaginable quantum-mechanical model <lb/>of a composite particle is one composed of two types of fer-<lb/>mions. distinguished by two values  1.2  of a fermion species <lb/>subscript. such that each type of fermion can be present in <lb/>only a single state. Denote the annihilation and creation op-<lb/>erators for the fermion of type 1 by  tf!\  and  tf!T,  and those for <lb/>the second fermion by  tf!2  and  tf!1.  As usual. the dagger de-<lb/>notes the Hermitian conjugate. These are assumed to satisfy <lb/>anticommutation relations of the usual form <lb/> 5 <lb/> Vli  =  J/li  = o.  [tf!\.tf!T ] +  =  [tf!2.tf!/1  +  = 1. <lb/> [tf!\,tf!2]  + =  [tf!\.tf!lL  =0. <lb/> (1) <lb/> The Hamiltonian is taken to be <lb/> H  =  E\tf!T tf!\  +  E2tf!1 tf!2  +  vtf!T tf!1 tf!2tf!\. <lb/> (2) <lb/> It  has only four eigenstates, consisting of the vacuum state <lb/> 10)  with eigenvalue zero, the one-fermion states <lb/> 11)  =  tf!T  10). 12)  =  tf!110) <lb/> (3) <lb/> with eigenvalues  E  J and  E2  respectively, and a two-fermion <lb/>state <lb/> la)  = tf!T tf!I 10)==.4  tIO). <lb/>(4) <lb/> with eigenvalue <lb/></body>

			<front> a)On leave from Dept. of Physics, University of Oregon, Eugene, Oregon <lb/>97043. (present address). <lb/>b)Laboratoire de Physique Theorique, Universite de Nice, Pare Valrose <lb/>06034 Nice Cedex, France. Equipe de Recherche Associee au C.N.R.S. <lb/>N&quot;.128. <lb/></front>

			<body> Ea  =  E.  +  E2  +  v. <lb/>(5) <lb/> If  v  &lt; - (E.  +  E 2 ).  then this state can be thought of as a sim-<lb/>plified model of a bound atom (composite particle), and for <lb/>this reason the notation  I  a)  will be employed. The &quot;physical <lb/>atom&quot; creation operation At  = tf!T  tf!1  and its corresponding <lb/>annihilation operator  A  =  tf!2tf!.  are not Bose operators even <lb/>though built from fermions pairs, but instead satisfy the non-<lb/>trivial commutation relations <lb/> A  2  =  0,  [A.A  tJ _  =  1 - N\ - N 2 , <lb/> [A,tf!d _  =  [A,tf!2] _  =  Atf!.  =  Atf!2  =  0, <lb/>(6) <lb/> [A.tf!T ] _  =  tf!2, [A,tf!l] - = - tf!J&apos; <lb/> whereN.  = tf!T  tf!.  andN 2  =  tf!1 tf!2  are the fermion occupation <lb/>numbers. The model may be described as a &quot;zero-dimen-<lb/>sional&quot; model since the composite particle has neither trans-<lb/>lational nor internal degrees of freedom. <lb/>The Fock space spanned by the eigenstates of  H  is only <lb/>four-dimensional and the quantum mechanics is utterly triv-<lb/>ial. Nevertheless, and in fact for this very reason, the model <lb/>is very useful for investigation and comparison of various <lb/>procedures for carrying out the transformation to the Fock-<lb/>Tani representation. In the following sections we shall inves-<lb/>tigate two methods, the &quot;d-matrix&quot; method <lb/> 3 based on nor-<lb/>mally ordered operator basis expansions, and a new method <lb/>involving a &quot;statistical renormalization&quot; of the d-matrix and <lb/>of the matrix elements of the Hamiltonian, leading to com-<lb/>pletely explicit expressions in closed form. This latter meth-<lb/>od may have important implications for both the mathemat-<lb/>ical structure and the physical implications of this <lb/>representation in realistic models; the investigation of such <lb/>generalizations is best deferred until the simplest model is <lb/>thoroughly understood. <lb/> 2. IDEAL  STATE SPACE <lb/> Introduce ideal Bose operators  a, a  t  satisfying the ele-<lb/>mentary Bose communication relation <lb/> [a,a  t ] _ = 1, <lb/>(7) <lb/> and acting on an &quot;ideal atom&quot; Fock space  d  spanned by the <lb/>states  (n!)  -1/2 (atrlO), where  10)  is the vacuum state of  d. <lb/> This space is initially completely independent of the physical <lb/>Fock space  Y  spanned by the four eigenstates  10), 11), 12). <lb/> la&gt;  of  H.  The ideal state space  Y  is defined to be the direct <lb/>product![ =  Y  ®  d of the physical and ideal atom spaces. <lb/></body>

			<page> 2365 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">J.  Math. Phys. 21 (9), September 1980 <lb/> 0022-2488/80/092365-11 $1.00 <lb/> ® 1980 American Institute of Physics <lb/></note>

			<page> 2365 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:47:30 <lb/></note>

			<body> The operators 1/11&apos;  1/11.1/12,1/11  on  Y  and those  a, a  t on dare <lb/>extended to  ~  in the usual way, <lb/> I/1j(~)  =  l/1iY  )  ®  l(d),  I/1J(~  =  I/1J(.7)  ® l(d) <lb/> a(~  =  1(.7)  ®a(d),  at(~  =  1(.7)  ®at(d) <lb/> (8) <lb/> and the vacuum 10) now is interpreted as the direct product <lb/>of that of  Y  and that of  d  satisfying <lb/> (9) <lb/> On this extended state space  ~,  the annihilation and cre-<lb/>ation operators satisfy the anticommunication and commu-<lb/>tation relations <lb/> t/li  =iflz  =0, [l/1pl/11L = [1/12,I/11L = 1, <lb/> [1/11,1/12]+ =[1/1\&gt;1/1/]+ =0, <lb/>[a,at] _  =  1, <lb/> [a,1/111 _ =  [a,1/121 _ =  [a,1/11] _ =  [a,1/11] _ = O. <lb/> (10) <lb/>Note the simplicity of the relations involving  a  compound <lb/>with those involving  A  [Eq. (6)]. This is the main advantage <lb/>of ideal state space representations in more realistic cases <lb/>where bound composite states cause difficulties with quan-<lb/>tum field theory methods in the usual Fock representation. <lb/>There is an isometry between the physical state space <lb/> Y  and the  subspace~&apos;  of  ~  spanned by the four states 10), <lb/>11), 12), and  la),  where <lb/> 11)  =  1/111 0), 12) = 1/1110),  la)  = atIO). <lb/>(11) <lb/> The mapping 10)_10), 10-11), 12)_12) is trivial, merely <lb/>involving replacement of the vacuum 10) of  Y  by that 10) of <lb/> Y.  On the other hand, the mapping  la)-Ia)  from the phys-<lb/>ical to ideal atom state is nontrivial, involving replacement <lb/>of the fermion pair operator  A  t  by the ideal boson operator <lb/> at  satisfying simpler commutation relations. Nevertheless, <lb/>the mapping is an isometry in that norms and inner products <lb/>between the four basis states 10), 11), 12),  la)  of Yare the <lb/>same as those involving the corresponding ideal states 10), <lb/>11), 12), la) which span  ~&apos;.  One can also define an ideal <lb/>Hamiltonian <lb/> l£=E l ll)(11 +E212)(21  +Eala)(al +li(l  -l~), <lb/> (12) <lb/> where 11)(11, 12)(21, and la)(al are the projectors onto the <lb/>corresponding ideal states,  ~  is the projector onto  ~&apos;, <lb/> ~  =  10)(01 + 11)(11 + 12)(21 +  la)(al, <lb/> (13) <lb/>and  B  is an arbitrary operator on  Y.  The ideal Hamiltonian <lb/> H  has the same eigenvalues on  Y&apos;  as  H  does on  Y,  with <lb/>eTgenstates which are the images of those of  H  according to <lb/>the previously defined mapping; however,  H  also has phys-<lb/>ically spurious eigenstates lying in ~e~&apos;~The projected <lb/>Hamiltonian <lb/> ~  =  ~1£~  =  Ell 1)(11 + E212)(21 +  Ea la)(al, <lb/> (14) <lb/> has the same eigenstates and eigenvalues as does  1£  on the <lb/>subspace  Y&apos;  isometric with  Y,  whereas it annihilates the <lb/>spurious states (they all have eigenvalue zero). These proper-<lb/>ties are all special cases of a general ideal state space formula-<lb/>tion of the quantum mechanics of systems of composite par-<lb/>ticles, but the definition of  1£,  ~,  and!!, in terms of <lb/></body>

			<page> 2366 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> J. Math. Phys., Vol. 21, No.9, September 1980 <lb/></note>

			<body> TABLE  I.  Notation for the operator basis. <lb/> B, <lb/> n,  1 <lb/> (a&apos;)&quot;a&quot; <lb/> n,  2 <lb/> (at)&quot;¢ri  ¢r,a&quot; <lb/> n,  3 <lb/> (a &apos;)&quot;¢r; ¢r2a&quot; <lb/> n,4 <lb/> (at)&quot;¢ri¢r;a&quot;  +&apos; <lb/> n,5 <lb/> (at)&quot;  +&apos;  ¢r2¢r,a&quot; <lb/> n,  6 <lb/> (a  t)&quot;¢ri  ¢r; ¢r2¢r,a&quot; <lb/> projectors is rather abstract. A number of methods are <lb/>known for constructing explicit expressions for Hand  JY  in <lb/>terms of annihilation and creation operators. <lb/> 6  The particular <lb/>method which will be employed in the remainder of this pa-<lb/>per is that of the generalized Tani transformation. 1-4 <lb/> 3. GENERALIZED TANI TRANSFORMATION <lb/> Consider the unitary operator U  on~,  defined by <lb/> U  = exp (;  F), F=A ta - atA  =  1/1/1/11a - a t 1/121/11&apos; <lb/> (15) <lb/> If follows from the properties <lb/> FlO)  = 0,  FI/11  10) =  FI/11  10) = 0, <lb/> FI/111/11  10) = -at 10),  FatlO)  = 1/111/1110), <lb/> (16) <lb/> and the power series expansion of the exponential that <lb/> U-110)=10), U-1 1l)=ll), U-1 12)=12), <lb/> U - Ila) = la), <lb/> (17) <lb/>where 11) = 1/1110), 12) = 1/1110), and la)  =  1/111/1110). Thus <lb/>this transformation effects the desired mapping from  Y  to <lb/> Y&apos;.  The ideal Hamiltonian  H,  which has the same eigenval-<lb/>ties and matrix elements on  Y&apos;  as  H  does on  Y,  is taken to <lb/>be <lb/> H= U-1HU. <lb/> The projector  ~  on  ~&apos;  is <lb/> ~  =  U  -I~OU, <lb/> (18) <lb/>(19) <lb/>where  Po  is the projector onto the subspace of  Y  spanned by <lb/>eigenstates of  Na  with eigenvalue zero; here  N:  is the ideal <lb/>boson number operator  Na  =  ata. Po  has a number ofrepre-<lb/>sentations of which two convenient ones are <lb/> 2 <lb/> (20) <lb/> and <lb/> (21) <lb/> where the colons denote the normal-ordering operation. The <lb/>evaluation of  H, R,  and  JY  is a nontrivial mathematical <lb/>problem. Use ofthe multiPle commutator expansion for the <lb/>unitary transformation (18) is not productive since  11&apos;/2  is <lb/>not a small expansion parameter and the infinite operator <lb/>series are difficult to sum into closed-form expressions. <lb/>Equation of motion techniques are much more powerful and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> M. D. Girardeau <lb/></note>

			<page> 2366 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:47:30 <lb/></note>

			<body> n=O <lb/> n=1 ••• <lb/> n=O <lb/> n  = 1 <lb/> FIG.  I.  Tridiagonal block structure of the d-matrix. <lb/> can, in fact, be made to yield exact closed-form expressions <lb/>in this simple case. Define <lb/> B  (t)  =  e - tFBe <lb/> tF <lb/>, <lb/> (22) <lb/> where  B  is any operator on!!. Then <lb/> B(O)=B, B(;)= U-1BU. <lb/> B  (t)  satisfies the &quot;equation of motion&quot; <lb/> B(t)  =  [B(t),F] _, <lb/> (23) <lb/>(24) <lb/>where the dot denotes the derivative with respect to  t.  The <lb/>equation of motion techniques are based on systematic <lb/>methods of solving these equations of motion subject to the <lb/>initial conditions  B  (0) =  B.  Evaluation of the solutions at <lb/>&quot;time&quot;  t  = 11&quot;!2 then yields the desired transforms. <lb/> 4. d-MATRIX METHOD AND NORMAL EXPANSIONS <lb/> This method <lb/> 3 is based on operator basis expansions of <lb/>the equations of motion. Define an  operator basis [Bi  J to be a <lb/>set oflinearly independent operators on the state space, i.e., a <lb/>set of operators such that no linear combination of these <lb/>operators with c-number coefficients is the zero operator on <lb/>the given state space.  It  is furthermore assumed that this <lb/>basis is sufficiently complete to allow expansion (with  c-<lb/> number coefficients) of every operator of physical interest. <lb/> In  practice this implies that the set  [Bi  J  must be closed un-<lb/>der commutation with  F.  The operators  Bi (t ) involved in the <lb/>equations of motion (24) are expanded as <lb/> (25) <lb/> j <lb/> with c-number coefficients  cij  to be determined. The d-ma-<lb/>trix  (d i )  with respect to the basis  B,  is defined by <lb/> (26) <lb/> The d-matrix elements are &quot;structure constants&quot; of the com-<lb/>posite particle which exhibit the kinematical relations be-<lb/>tween the composite and its constituents. Substitution into <lb/>the equations of motion (24) and use of the linear indepen-<lb/></body>

			<page> 2367 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> J.  Math. Phys., Vol. 21, No.9, September 1980 <lb/></note>

			<body> dence of the different B  j  leads to the following coupled equa-<lb/>tions of motion for the  c(t ): <lb/> (\(t)  =  &apos;2..cik(t)dkj , <lb/> (27) <lb/> k <lb/> or in matrix notation  6(t)  =  c(t  )d, with the formal solution <lb/> c(t)  =  C(O)etd. <lb/> (28) <lb/>However, exponentiation of the d-matrix is difficult, and  it  is <lb/>easier to proceed by direct solution of the coupled differen-<lb/>tial equations. <lb/>A convenient choice of basis elements  B  i ,  sufficiently <lb/>complete to expand all operators involved in the Hamilton-<lb/>ian, the transformation  U,  and the projector, is given by the <lb/>normally ordered products  (atYa n , (attl/lr  I/Ila&quot;, <lb/> (atYl/lil/l2a&quot;, (atYl/lrl/lia n + I , (a t t+II/I21/1la n ,  and <lb/> (af)nl/lT I/Ii  1/121/1lan.  Let  i  stand for the pair  (n,v)  whree <lb/> n  = 1,2, ... is the boson index and  v  = 1, ... ,6 the fermion in-<lb/>dex. The notation is then defined by Table  I.  The method of <lb/>evaluation of the d-matrix elements is illustrated by the fol-<lb/>lowing example: <lb/> [(atyan,F] _  =  Iinl;n·&quot;B n · v <lb/>n&apos;v <lb/> which implies <lb/> dnl ;&quot;  -1,4  =  dnl;n  -1,5  = - n, <lb/> (30) <lb/> dnl;n&apos;&quot;  = 0,  (n&apos;v)¥(n  -1,4) or  (n -1,5). <lb/> In  evaluating the commutators it is convenient to write <lb/> [(a f)nan,F ] _  =  (a tYanl/l!  I/Ii  a - I/Ir  1/11  a(a ttan <lb/>-(a t ta n a t l/l 2 1/11  +  a t l/l21/1I(a t )&quot;a n ,  (31) <lb/> and to make use of the identities <lb/>(32) <lb/>leading immediately to (30). Evaluating the other elements <lb/>similarly, one finds the d-matrix shown in Figs. 1 and 2. The <lb/>blocks shown in Fig. 1 are the 6 X 6 submatrices of  dnv;n&apos;v&apos; <lb/> with fixed values of nand  n&apos;  but with  v  and  v&apos;  running from 1 <lb/>to 6. Note the tridiagonal block structure; only the blocks <lb/> dnv;n&apos;v&quot; dnv;n  +  I,v&quot;  and  dnv;n  _I  .v&apos;  are nonzero. The elements <lb/>of the nonzero blocks are exhibited in Fig. 2. <lb/> n - I <lb/> n <lb/> n • I <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 0  -n -n  0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 0 <lb/>0 0 <lb/>0 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/> 0 0 <lb/> 0 <lb/> • • <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 0 0 <lb/>0 <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/> • <lb/> 1 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0 0 0 <lb/>0 0 <lb/> n <lb/> 0 0 <lb/>0 0 <lb/>0 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 0 0  O-(n.l) <lb/> 1  -I -I <lb/> 0 0 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 0 <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 0 <lb/> 0 <lb/> O-{nt!) <lb/> 1  -I -I <lb/> 0 0 <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 0 <lb/>0 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 0 <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 0 <lb/> FIG. 2. The  (nv)  rows ofthed-matrix for  v  =  1, ... ,6 and a single valueofn. <lb/>All nonzero elements lie in the columns with  n&apos;  =  n  -I,  n  or  n  +  I. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> M. D. Girardeau <lb/></note>

			<page> 2367 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:47:30 <lb/></note>

			<body> In  terms ofthe  (nv)  notation the equations of motion <lb/>(27) are <lb/>(33) <lb/>The initial condition is obtained from (22), which implies <lb/> Bnv(O)  =  Bnv  and hence, by (25), <lb/>(34) <lb/>where  0  is the Kronecker delta function.  It  follows from Fig. <lb/>2 that <lb/> Cnv;OI (t)  =  CnV;&lt;?2 (t)  =  C n v;03 (t)  = 0, <lb/> ° <lb/>° <lb/> -1  ° <lb/> 1 <lb/> ° <lb/> The general solution of this inhomogeneous equation is the <lb/>sum of the general solution of the homogeneous equation <lb/>and a particular solution of the inhomogeneous equation. <lb/>One choice of the particular solution is <lb/> C n V;04 P (t)  =  cnv;osP(t)  =  C n v;06 P (t)  = 0, <lb/>(38) <lb/>The four linearly independent solutions of the homogeneous <lb/>equation can be taken to be the eigenvectors of the secular <lb/>equation <lb/> -iw <lb/> ° <lb/> -1 <lb/> ° <lb/> -jw <lb/> -1 <lb/>-1 <lb/> -;w <lb/> ° <lb/> =0 <lb/> (39) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> ° <lb/> -iw <lb/> with roots  w  = °  (with multiplicity two) and  w  = ±  2. The <lb/>solutions are linear combinations of the functions  e <lb/> iOJI  with <lb/>these &quot;frequencies&quot;.  It  is convenient to choose  cos(2t ) and <lb/>sin(2t) as basis functions rather than  e  ±  i21.  Then one has <lb/> C n v;04 (t)  =  A04 +  B04cos(2t)  +  C 04 sin(2t), <lb/>C nv;OS (t ) =  Aos  +  Boscos(2t )  +  Cossin(2t ), <lb/> C n v;06  (I)  =  A06  +  B06cos(2t)  +  C 06 sin(2t), <lb/>C n v;1I  (t)  =  A  11  +  BlIcos(2t)  +  C lI sin(2t). <lb/> (40) <lb/> The particular solution (38) may be considered to be includ-<lb/>ed in  A  II&apos; The initial conditions on the  C  nv;n&apos;v&apos;  and their de-<lb/>rivatives imply <lb/>A04  +  B04 =  OnO O v4&apos; <lb/> Aos  +  Bos =  on0 8 vs&apos; <lb/>A06  + B06 =  on0 0 v6&apos; <lb/> Att  +BII =8n1 8 v  l&gt; <lb/> 2C04  =  0nO(Ov2  +  8v3  +  0v6) - Onl Ovl&apos; <lb/> 2Cos  =  onO (Ov2  +  Ov3  +  0v6) - Onl Ovl , <lb/> 2C 06 = - ono(8 v4  +  ovs), <lb/> 2C tt  =  0nO(0v4  +  ovs), <lb/> (41) <lb/> whereas the differential equations imply <lb/>A06 -AlI  +  0nO(Ov2  +  0v3)  =  0,  2B04  +  C 06 -C lI  =  0, <lb/>-2C 04  +  B06 -BII  =  0, 2Bos  +  C 06 -C II  =  0, <lb/></body>

			<page> 2368 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> J. Math. Phys., Vol. 21, No.9, September 1980 <lb/></note>

			<body> Cnv;OI (t)  =  onOOvl&apos;  Cn V;02  (t)  =  onOOv2&apos; <lb/> (35) <lb/> cnv;OJ (t)  =  onO Ov3&apos; <lb/> Similarly, Fig. 2 and Eqs. (35) imply <lb/> C nv;04 (t)  =  C nv;OS (t ) <lb/> = Cnv;02  (t)  +  Cnv;03 (t)  +  C nv ;06 (t) - Cnv;1  1  (t) <lb/>=OnO O v2 +ono Ov3 +Cnv;06(t)-C n v;ll(t), <lb/>Cnv;06 (t )  = - C n v;04 (t) - cnv;os (t) <lb/>C nv;  II  (t ) = C  nv;04 (t)  +  C  nv;OS  (t). <lb/> (36) <lb/> These four equations can be written in matrix form as <lb/>follows: <lb/>-2Cos  +  B06 - BII  =  0, A04  +Aos  =  0, <lb/> 2B06 - C 04 -Cos  =  0, 2C 06  +  B04  +  Bos  = 0, <lb/> 2B  II  +  C 04  +  Cos  =  0, 2C  II - B04 - Bos  =  0, <lb/> Equations (41) and (42) are all satisfied by <lb/> A04  = - Aos  =  ~Ono(Ov4  - ovs), <lb/> A06  =  !Ono(0v6 - 8v2 - 0v3)  +  !Onl Ovl&apos; <lb/>A  11 =  !ono(ov2  +  Ov3  +  0v6)  +  !O&quot;I Ovl&apos; <lb/> B04  =  Bos  =  !ono(8v4  +  Ovs)&apos; <lb/> B06  = - Bll =  !Ono(Ov2  +  Ov3  +  0v6) - !OnIOvl&apos; <lb/> C04 = Co$.  =  !O&quot;o(Ov2  +  Ov3  +  0v6) - !Onl  OYI&apos; <lb/> CII  = - C 06  =  !O&quot;o(Ov4  +  ovs). <lb/>The solutions (40) are then <lb/> C n y,04(t)  =  Ono0v4cos2t - onoovssinSt <lb/> (37) <lb/>(42) <lb/>(43) <lb/> + H  0,,0  (Ov2  +  Ov3  +  0v6) - Onl  Ovl  ]sin(2t), <lb/> Cnv;os(t)  =  onOovscos2t - onoov4sin2t <lb/> +  HOno(Ov2  +  Ov3  +  0v6) - OnlOYI  ]sin <lb/> 2  (2/), <lb/> C n  v;06  (t)  =  OnOOv6  cos 2 t  +  [Onl Ovi - onO (ov2  +  0v3)  ]sin <lb/>2 <lb/> t <lb/> -!Ono(Ov4 +0vS)sin(2t), <lb/> CnV;11  (t)  =  Onl Ovl cos <lb/> 2 t  +  OnO(Ov2  +  Ov3  +  ov6)sin <lb/> 2 t <lb/>+  ~OnO(Ov4  +  ovs)sin(2t). <lb/> (44) <lb/> This method of solution can be extended to determine, <lb/>successively, the  cnv;n&apos;v&apos;  for  n&apos;  = 1,2, ... The differential equa-<lb/>tions for  n&apos;&gt;  1  are found to be <lb/> env;n&apos;l (t)  =  Cnv;n&apos;  -1.4  (t)  +  Cnv;n&apos; _ 1,5  (t), <lb/>C nv;n&apos;2 (t)  =  C n v;n&apos;3 (t)  = - enV;n&apos;  -1,4  (t) - Cnv;n&apos; _ t.s  (t), <lb/> Cnv;n&apos;4 (t)  = Cnv;n&apos;S  (t) <lb/>= C n v;n&apos;2 (t)  +  C n v;n&apos;3 (t)  +  e n v;n&apos;6(t) - (n&apos;  + 1) <lb/> Cnv;n&apos;  +  1.1  (t), <lb/>C n v;n&apos;6(t)  = - (n&apos;  +  l)e n v;n&apos;4(t) - (n&apos;  +  l)c  n v;n&apos;S(t).  (45) <lb/> The second and third of these equations are solved by qua-<lb/>drature using the previously determined solutions for <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> M. D. Girardeau <lb/></note>

			<page> 2368 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:47:30 <lb/></note>

			<body> Cnv-,n&apos; _  1.4 and cnv;n&apos;  -1.5&apos;  The fourth. fifth, sixth. and first <lb/>(with  n&apos;  replaced by  n&apos;  +  1 in the first) can be solved simulta-<lb/>neously by the matrix method as were Eqs. (36). taking  c  n~;n&apos;2 <lb/> and  c n v;n&apos;3 as known inhomogeneous terms. The secular <lb/>equation for the homogeneous system is <lb/> -iw <lb/> 0 <lb/>- (n&apos;  +  1) <lb/> o <lb/>- iw <lb/> - (n&apos;  +  1) <lb/> =0. <lb/> -(n&apos;  +  1) - (n&apos;  +  1) - iw <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/>0 <lb/> -iw <lb/> (46) <lb/> with roots  w  = 0, ±  2(n&apos;  +  1 )1/1. In addition. the inhomoge-<lb/>neous terms contribute all the &quot;frequencies&quot; generated pre-<lb/>viously for smaller values of  n&apos;,  i.e.  w  =  O. 2, 2·2  [/2,  2.3 1/2 , ... , <lb/> 2{n&apos;)1/1. Hence the solutions for c n v;n&apos;4&apos; cnv;n&apos;S&apos;  C  n v;n&apos;6&apos; and <lb/> h <lb/> &quot;f <lb/>...  0 2 2 2112 2 3 112 <lb/> cnv;&apos;&quot;  +  1.1 ave requencles , , &apos; <lb/>. &apos; <lb/>, .... <lb/> 2(n&apos;  +1)1/2. <lb/> We shall exhibit the solutions obtained in this way for <lb/>the case  n&apos;  = 1. without the details ofthe derivation. One <lb/>finds <lb/> C nv ,12(t)  =  {jn1 8v2 - ~8no({jv4  +8 vs )sin(2t) <lb/>-[8,,0({jv2  +  t&gt;v3  +  8,,.;) - 8 nl {jvl ]sin2t, <lb/> C  n  v;\3  (t) <lb/> = D  n1 t&gt;Y3 - ~{jno({jv4  +  {jys)sin(2t) <lb/> - [{j,,0({jv2  +  {jv3  +  {j&quot;o) -c5 lt1 {jvl ]sin <lb/> 2 t. <lb/> C  nv ;14  «() <lb/> =  !c5&quot;, (c5v4 - c5vs  ) +  !(o&quot;o  +  Onl )(c5v4  +  8vS ) <lb/> X  COS(2 <lb/> 31 1t)  + (2  -3!2{jno(Ov2  +  Ov3  +  c5 &quot;o ) +  2 - 3/2c5&quot;  I  (c5 v2 <lb/> +  c5 v ] + {j&quot;o - c5  vl ) - 2 -1/2c5,,20YI ]sin(2 <lb/> 3/2  t) <lb/> -!O&quot;O(Ov4  +  b&apos;vs)cos(2t) <lb/> -H  c5,,0 ({jv2  +  c5 v3  +  {jv6) - {jnl c5 vl ]sin(2t), <lb/>Cnv;IS (t)  =  C n v;14 (t)  +  c5&quot;l ({jyS - 0v4), <lb/> C&quot;v;l(i (I) <lb/> ~{jnO(c5v2  +  {)v3  +  {j&quot;o)  +  !{j&quot;1 (0,,0 - {jvl - {)v2 - {)v3) <lb/> +  onzovJ  +  B{j&quot;O(OV2  +  {jv3  +  0,,0) <lb/> +  ~Onl  ({jv2  +  c5  Y3 +  c5&quot;o - {jvl) - On2c5vl ]COS(23/2() <lb/>-2 -112(8 no  +  {)nl  )({jv4  +  {jyS )sin(23/2() <lb/> -[c5 no (c5 v2  +  c5 v3  +  c5 &quot;o ) -c5,,1 ovl ]cos(2t) <lb/> +  8no (8v4  +  °vS)sin(2t) <lb/> Cnv.21  (t)  =  -1{jno(c5 v2  +  {jv3  +  8,11) <lb/> +  lc5nl  ({jvl  +  {jv2  +  8v3  +  {)&quot;o)  +  ~8&quot;28vl <lb/> + [ - !{j&quot;0({jv2  +  {jv3  +  8,,0) - !{)&quot;l <lb/> X  ({jv2  +  {jv3  +  {j&quot;o -{jvl)  + 18&quot;2  {)vl ]COS(2 <lb/> 3/2 t) <lb/> +  2 -312(15,,0  +  {j&quot;I)({jv4  +  {jvs)sin(23J2t ) <lb/> +  H{),,0(c5 v2  +  b&apos;v3  +  0,,0) - b&apos;,,1  c5 vl Jcos(2t) <lb/>-!{)nO({)v4  +  {jys)sin(2t). <lb/> (47) <lb/> One notes that there are no secular terms in the solu-<lb/>tions for the c&quot;v;n&apos;v&apos; for  n&apos;  = 0 and  n&apos;  = 1, i.e .• t appears only <lb/>inside trigonometric functions and not algebraically. This <lb/>result is in fact quite general, i.e., it holds for all of the cnv;n&apos;v&quot; <lb/> not merely for those with  n&apos;  = 0 and 1. Although a proof <lb/>could probably be constructed by thd d-matrix method of <lb/>this section, the proof is simpler in terms of the more power-<lb/></body>

			<page> 2369 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> J, Math. Phys.,  Vol.  21, No.9, September 1980 <lb/></note>

			<body> ful method of Secs. 6 and 7 and will therefore be deferred <lb/>until then. The absence of secular terms in  t  implies that <lb/> when we evaluate the transformed Hamiltonian by putting <lb/> t  =  1&apos;12,  factors of  l&apos;  will occur only inside trigonometric <lb/>functions and not algebraically. This is an important result. <lb/>since other iterative methods of solution can lead to secular <lb/>terms <lb/> 2  which would require complication rearrangements <lb/>and resummations to remove. <lb/> 5.  HAMILTONIAN, PROJECTOR, AND PROJECTED <lb/>HAMILTONIAN <lb/> It  follows from Eqs. (2), (23), and (25) and Table I that <lb/>the Fock-Tani Hamiltonian H of Eg. (18) is given, in terms <lb/>of the solutions  C nvon·At ) evaluated at &quot;time&quot;  1&apos;12.  by <lb/> II  =  ~[EIC02;n&apos;v  ( ; )  +  E2C03;n&apos;v&apos;  (;) <lb/> + vC06;n&apos;Y&apos;  ( ; )  ]Bn,v&quot; <lb/>(48) <lb/> The solutions (35), (44), and (47) allow explicit evaluation of <lb/>all of the terms with  n&apos;  =  0 and 1, and also those with  n&apos;  = 2, <lb/> v&apos;  = 1, yielding <lb/>!!. =!!.o  +  ~ <lb/> !!.o =  Eaata  +  E1l/lr 1/11  +  E21/1i 1/12, <lb/> ~  =  (v - Ea)I/I! 1/111/121/11 - taatl/l! &quot;&apos;la - Ea a t l/l1 1/12 a <lb/> +  2 - 312 sin(21/21&apos;)Ea  [atl/lt 1/11a 2  +  (a t fl/l2&apos;&quot;  I  a ] <lb/> +  H3  +  COS(21/21&apos;)]Eaat&quot;,r  &quot;&apos; 1  &quot;&apos;21/1la <lb/> -H3  +  COS(21;21&apos;)]Ea(at)2a 2  + &quot;&apos;, <lb/> (49) <lb/>where the terms &quot; ... &quot; not exhibited involve the operators <lb/> B  n&apos;v&apos;  (Table I) with  n&apos;&gt;  2,  v&apos;  =  2 -6. as well as the  B  n&apos;  1 [i.e., <lb/> (a1)n&apos;a&quot;&apos;]  with  n&apos;&gt;3.  Note the decomposition into a free-<lb/>composite and free-constituent Hamiltonain!!.o plus an in-<lb/>teraction term  V,  as in the previous work l -4 on the Fock-<lb/>Tani representation. Recall that  Ea  is the composite particle <lb/>energy, Eq. (5). Note also that the states 11), 12), and  la)  of <lb/>Eq. (11) are exact eigenstates of  H  [including the omitted <lb/>terms ..... &quot; in (49)] witheigenvaluesE  I ,  E2&apos;  andE a , respective-<lb/>ly. The composite particle is stable (an energy eigenstate) <lb/>and hence there are no spontaneous breakup and recombina-<lb/>tion terms &quot;&apos; 1  I/Ii a  and a t &quot;&apos; 2&quot;&apos; 1 in  ~  a property expressed alge-<lb/>braically by <lb/> ~Ia)  =  0 <lb/>(50) <lb/> Again, this is as in the previous work <lb/> 4 ;  however, we now <lb/>have exact, explicit expressions (in this simplified model) for <lb/>some terms which were previously only evaluated <lb/>approximately. <lb/>The projector  R  onto the physical subspace  Y&apos;  of the <lb/>Fock-Tani state  sp~e ~  is given, according to (f9), (21), <lb/> (23). (25), and Table I, by <lb/> ~  = f (- ;Y rCnl;,,&apos;&quot;  (.!.\»&quot;&apos;&quot;. <lb/> &quot; =  0 <lb/> n. <lb/> n&apos;v&apos; <lb/> 2  r <lb/> (5]) <lb/>Again evaluating all the terms with  n&apos;  = 0, 1 and those with <lb/> n&apos;  =  2,  v&apos;  =  1, one finds <lb/> R  =  1 - vA  &quot;&apos;i &quot;&apos;21/11 - atl/l! I/Ila - atl/li 1/12fl <lb/> +  2a t l/l!  I/Ii  1/12&quot;&apos;la - !(a1) 2 a 2  + ... , <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> M. D. Girardeau <lb/> (52) <lb/></note>

			<page> 2369 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:47:30 <lb/></note>

			<body> where the terms &quot; ... &quot; not exhibited involve the same opera-<lb/>tors as in (49). Note that the terms proportional to sin  (2 <lb/> 112 1T) <lb/> and cos  (2 <lb/> 1/2 <lb/>1T)  have cancelled. The projected Hamiltonian <lb/>(14) is <lb/> ~  =  IY!.  =  l!.~! <lb/> (53) <lb/> since the operator  Po  ofEq. (19) commutes with  H,  therefore <lb/> ~  commutes with  l!.,  and  ~  is a projector and hence idempo-<lb/>tent,  ~  2  =  ~.  Multiplication of the expressions (52) and (49) <lb/>for Rand H, using Wick&apos;s theorem or the commutation and <lb/>antiC&quot;ommti&quot;tation relations, leads to the following expression <lb/>for the leading terms in the normal expansion of  ~: <lb/> ~=l!.o  +  ~ <lb/> &apos;Y =  (11. - Ea  )&quot;&apos; 1 &quot;&apos; 1 &quot;&apos;2&quot;&apos;1 - (Ea  +  E  l)a  t  &quot;&apos; 1  &quot;&apos;I  a <lb/>-(Ea  +  E2)a <lb/> t <lb/> &quot;&apos;i &quot;,za  + ( 2E a - v)at&quot;&apos; T &quot;&apos; 1 &quot;&apos; Z&quot;&apos; la <lb/> -Ea(a t )2a 2  + ... , <lb/> (54) <lb/>in which  l!.o  is the same unperturbed Hamiltonian as in (49), <lb/>whereas  &apos;Y  has terms ofthe same structure as Vbut with <lb/>different matrix elements.  It  is interesting to note that  R V <lb/> vanishes by cancellations between various contributions; all <lb/>the contributions to both  l!.o  and  ~  in (54) come from  ~l!.o. <lb/> It  is easy to demonstrate explicitly that the expression <lb/>(54) has the desired projection properties <lb/> ~ll,2)  =  ~Il,a)  =  ~(2,a)  =  ~ll,2,a)  =  ~Ia,a)  =  0, <lb/> (55) <lb/> for the states <lb/> 1  1  ,2)  =  &quot;&apos; 1 &quot;&apos; 1 10),ll,a)  =  &quot;&apos; 1 a <lb/> t  I0),12,a)  =  &quot;&apos;iatIO), <lb/>11,2,a)  =  &quot;&apos; 1 &quot;&apos;iatIO),  la,a)  =  2 -112(af) z IO), <lb/> (56) <lb/> lying in the unphysical subspace  YaY&apos;  of the Fock-Tani <lb/>state space Y. This unphysical  subspa~  is of infinite dimen-<lb/>sionality, there being an infinity of other unphysical states <lb/>also annihilated by K in addition to the ones (55); however, <lb/>an explicit demonstration would require the terms in  JY&apos;  be-<lb/>yond those exhibited in (54). K has the same  eigenval~es  as <lb/> H  on the physical subspace  .7&apos;  spanned by the four Fock-<lb/>Tani states 10), 11), 17), ad la) [Eq. (11)]. In fact, one finds <lb/> ~IO)  = l!.10)  =  l!.010)  =  0,  ~Il)  =  l!.ll) <lb/> = l!.011)  = Ed 1), <lb/> K12)  =  H  12)  =  Ho12)  =  E212),  Kia)  =  H  la) <lb/> ;;;;, l!.ola) ;;;;, Ea la). -<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/> (57) <lb/> The physical states are all annihilated by both J.:: and  ~: <lb/> J.:: 10) =  ~IO)  =  0, J.:: 11)  =  ~11)  = 0, <lb/> (58) <lb/> J.::12)  =  ~12)  =  0, J.::la)  =  ~Ia)  =  0, <lb/> since  Ho  incorporates the internal interaction energy of the <lb/>composite as well as the free-constituent energies. <lb/>6.  STATISTICAL RENORMALIZATION <lb/> The form of the solutions for  l!.,  ~  and  ~,  involving <lb/>increasing powers  (a  f)n to the left and  an  to the right bf the six <lb/>operators  Bov,  suggests a different choice of operator basis <lb/>than the fully normally-ordered one of Table I. The products <lb/> (atta <lb/> n  are related to the boson number operator  Na  =  at  a <lb/></body>

			<page> 2370 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> J.  Math. Phys., Vol. 21, No.9, September 1980 <lb/></note>

			<body> by the identity <lb/> (atta n  =  Na!/(N a - n)! <lb/> = Na(N a -1) .. ·(N a - n  +  1). <lb/>(59) <lb/> Furthermore, one has the identities <lb/> aG(N a )  =  G(Na  +  l)a, atG(Na)  =  G(Na -1)a t ,  (60) <lb/> for any function G of the operator  N  a •  It  follows that  H, R, <lb/> and  ~  can each be represented as a linear  combinatio~  of <lb/>the operators  Bov  of Table I, but with coefficients which are <lb/>functions of  Na  rather than c-numbers. We can define a  re-<lb/>duced operator basis {Bv  1  to be a set of operators which are <lb/>linearly independent in the generalized sense that an equa-<lb/>tion of the form <lb/> (61) <lb/> implies that each  Gv(N a )  vanishes separately. The basis is <lb/>also required to be sufficiently complete that all operators of <lb/>interest can be written as linear combination,  with coeffi-<lb/>cients which may depend upon N a ,  oftheB v • This process of <lb/>allowing the coefficients to depend upon the occupation <lb/>number operator  Na  is what is meant by the terminology <lb/>statistical renormalization; the physical significance will be-<lb/>come clearer after we have evaluated the closed-form expres-<lb/>sions for  l!.  and~.  The above statement that the basis  {B v  1 <lb/> must be &quot;sufficiently complete ... &quot; means, in our application <lb/>to the evaluation of Tani transforms (22), that the set  {Bv  1 <lb/> must be closed under commutation with  F,  but again in the <lb/>generalized sense that the coefficients in the linear combina-<lb/>tions are allowed to depend upon N  a •  Such bases are easy to <lb/>construct. Starting with a set of operators  Bv  whose Tani <lb/>transforms are desired and which are linearly independent in <lb/>the renormalized sense (61), one evaluates their commuta-<lb/>tors with  F,  adjoining each new linearly independent opera-<lb/>tor which arises to the set  (B  v  1, and continuing until the set <lb/>closes. <lb/>The transforms  &quot;&apos;I(t)  and  &quot;&apos;2(t)  of the constituent field <lb/>operators are of interest in themselves since they determine <lb/>the transformation of states from the original Fock space  Y <lb/> to the Fock-Tani space  ~.  Furthermore, it is clear from (2) <lb/>that the transformed Hamiltonian is expressible in terms of <lb/>these fields and their hermitian conjugates  1/11 (t ) and  1/11 (t ). <lb/> Let us therefore first consider the bases appropriate to evalu-<lb/>ation of  1/I1(t)  and  1/Iz(t).  For the case of  &quot;&apos; I&apos;  evaluation of <lb/>commutators with  F  shows that the four-dimensional basis <lb/>of Table II is both linearly independent in the sense (61) and <lb/>complete with respect to  &quot;&apos;I(t)  in the sense that  &quot;&apos;I(t)  is ex-<lb/>pressible as a linear combination of the given  Bv  with coeffi-<lb/>cients depending uponNa&apos; The transforms (22) of these basis <lb/>elements can be expanded as <lb/> B,,(t)  =  &apos;2.Gvv,(N a  ,t)B&quot;&quot; <lb/> (62) <lb/> v&apos; <lb/> with coefficients Gvv&apos; to be determined. Note thatthe G vv &apos; do <lb/>not commute with  B2  and  B 4 ,  so it is necessary to pay atten-<lb/>tion to the order. Using the identities <lb/> B 2 G(N a )  =  G(Na  +  I)B2&apos; B4G(Na)  =  G(Na  +  I)B4• (63) <lb/> which follow from (60), one can always write operator ex-<lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> M. D. Girardeau <lb/></note>

			<page> 2370 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:47:30 <lb/></note>

			<body> TABLE II. Reduced operator basis for  &quot;&apos;I(t). <lb/> v <lb/> B&quot; <lb/> 1 <lb/> &quot;&apos; , <lb/> 2 <lb/> &quot;&apos;ia <lb/> 3 <lb/> &quot;&apos; 1 &quot;&apos; 2&quot;&quot; <lb/> 4 <lb/> &quot;,r  &quot;&apos; 1  &quot;&quot;a <lb/> pressions so that the basis elements  B&quot;  are to the right and <lb/>their  No  -dependent coefficients to the left, and we shall take <lb/>this as the standard order, as in (62). <lb/>The  B v (t ) satisfy the equations of motion <lb/> B,,(t)  =  I/;vv,(No,t)B&quot;, <lb/> v&apos; <lb/> = I  [GvANa,t)B&quot;,,F] _. <lb/> (64) <lb/> v&apos; <lb/> This commutator has to be rewritten as a linear combination <lb/>ofthe  B&quot;.  with the  B&quot;.  on the right and their  Na  -dependent <lb/>coefficients on the left.  It  follows from (15) and (60) that <lb/> [Gw(Na,t)Bv&quot;F] -<lb/> =  G w (Na,t )B&quot;,(1/Ir  1/11  a - a t 1/l21/11) <lb/>-Gw(N a +I,t)1/Ii1/lIaB&quot;, <lb/>+ Gw(N a -1,t)a t 1/l21/1t B v&quot; <lb/> (65) <lb/>and the factors to the right of the  G w  can be written as linear <lb/>combinations of the  B v&apos;  by use of Wick&apos;s theorem or the <lb/>commutation and anticommutation relations. Define three <lb/>D-matrices  (D w  0)&apos;  (D vv&apos;  +), and  (D w -) by <lb/> B,,(1/I!  1/11  a - a t 1/l21/11)  =  IDvv&apos; O(Na)B v &quot; <lb/> v&apos; <lb/> (66) <lb/> -1/Ir1/lIaB&quot;  =  IDvv&apos;  +  (Na)B v &quot; <lb/> v&apos; <lb/> a t 1/l21/1IBv  =  ID vv &apos; -(Na)B v &quot; <lb/> v&apos; <lb/> Then (64) can be written as <lb/> IGvANa,t)Bv&apos;  = I  [Gw(Na,t)D&quot;,v&apos; O(N a ) <lb/> v&apos; <lb/> v&apos;v&apos;&quot; <lb/> + Gv&quot;.{N a  +  l,t)Dy&apos;y&quot; +(N a ) <lb/>+ G w (Na -I,t )Dv&apos;v&apos; - (Na&gt;JBv&quot;  (67) <lb/> Interchanging the summation indices  v&apos;  and  v <lb/> H  on the right <lb/>and equating like basis elements  B v&apos;,  one finds the equations <lb/>of motion <lb/> Gvv,{Na,t)  =  I[Gvv·(No,t)D,,·v,O(N a ) <lb/> v&apos; <lb/> + Gvv·(N a  +  I,t)D v  &apos;v&apos;  +  (N a ) <lb/>+ Gvv·{N a -l,t)D v &apos; v &apos; -(N a )] <lb/>(68) <lb/> or in matrix notation <lb/> G(Na&apos;!)  =  G(Na,t)DO(Na)  +  G(Na  +  l,t)D+(N a ) <lb/>+ G{Na -I,t)D-{N a ). <lb/>(69) <lb/></body>

			<page> 2371 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> J.  Math. Phys., Vol. 21, No.9, September 1980 <lb/></note>

			<body> These equations of motion are to be solved subject to the <lb/>initial conditions <lb/>(70) <lb/>which follow from (62) and (22). <lb/>The explicit expressions for the D-matrices relative to <lb/>the basis of Table II are easily worked out and are exhibited <lb/>in Eqs. (71)-(73): <lb/> [  ~ ~  001 0 <lb/> (Dvv&apos;  0)  = <lb/>- (No  +  1) <lb/> o <lb/>o <lb/> il <lb/> (71) <lb/> [ <lb/> ~ ~ ~ ~1] <lb/> (D._,  +) = <lb/> vv <lb/> 0 0 0 0 &apos; <lb/> o  0 0 <lb/>0 <lb/> (72) <lb/> (Dw  -)~ [~~. ~ j~&quot; ~]  o . <lb/>o <lb/> (73) <lb/>The explicit forms of the equations of motion (68) are then <lb/> G V1 (Na ,t)  = - No G v2 (Na -l,t)  +  Na G v4 (Na - l,t), <lb/>G v2 (Na ,t)  =  G&quot;I  (Na,t)  +  G,,3 (Na,t), <lb/>G,,3(N a ,t)= -(Na +1)G v2 (N a  ,t)  +  N a G v2 (N a -l,t) <lb/>-No G v4 (Na - 1,t), <lb/>G v4 {N a  ,t)  =  G VI (Na,t)  +  G v3 (N a ,t) - G VI (Na  +  l,t).  (74) <lb/> Differentiating the first equation and substituting from the <lb/>other, one finds <lb/>of which the solution satisfying the initial conditions <lb/> G VI (Na  ,0)  =  DVI , <lb/> (75) <lb/> G VI (Na,O)  = - N a G v2 (No  -1,0)  +  N a G v4 {N a  -1,0), <lb/> (76) <lb/>is <lb/> G VI (Na,t)  =  DVI  cos(N  !lZt )  +  (Dv4 - D v2 )N  ! <lb/> 12 <lb/> sin(N  ! <lb/> 12 t). <lb/> (77) <lb/> Similarly differentiating the equation for  G,,2&apos;  one finds <lb/>(78) <lb/>of which the solution satisfying the initial conditions is <lb/> G  v2 (N a ,t)  =  DV 2 COS[(N a  +  1)  1/2 t ] <lb/> (79) <lb/> + (Dvl  +  DV3){N a  +  1)  -1I2  sin[(N a  +  1)1/2t ]. <lb/> The equations for  G  vi and  G  v2  can then be solved directly for <lb/> G  V3  and G  v4 ,  giving <lb/> G v3 {N a ,t)= -D v2 {N a +I)1/2 sin[{N a +I)1/2t ] <lb/>+ (D v1  +  Dv3)COs[(Na  +  IY/2t ] <lb/> -Dvl  cos{N  ! /2 t)  +  (D v2 - D v4 )N  ! <lb/> 12 sin{N  !/2t ), <lb/>G v4 {N a ,t)  =  DV3{N a  +  1) -<lb/> 112 sin[{Na  +  1) <lb/> I/Z  t ] <lb/>+ Dv4  cos  [{Na  +  l)lt2t ]. <lb/> (80) <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> M. D. Girardeau <lb/></note>

			<page> 2371 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:47:30 <lb/></note>

			<body> T ABLE III. Reduced operator basis for :/I2(t). <lb/> v <lb/> Bv <lb/> 1 <lb/> &quot;&apos; 2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> :/Ii  a <lb/> 3 <lb/> ¢i:/l,.p, <lb/> 4 <lb/> Ifri  f/I;  t/t2 G <lb/> = <lb/> The desired Tani transform  I/I1(t)  is, in the notation of Table <lb/> II, equal to  DI(t).  and one then has by Eq. (61) <lb/> 1/;,(t)  = cos(N  ::2t)I/I1  +  (No  +  1) -1/2sin[(Na  +  1)1/2t  J <lb/> X1/;!a  +  {cos(N a  +  1)v2t  ] - cOS(N~/2t)}¢1¢2¢1&apos; <lb/> (81) <lb/> The derivation of the explicit expressi()n for  &quot;&apos;2(t)  proceeds in <lb/>the same way, The appropriate choice of basis is that of Table <lb/> Ill.  The derivation differs from that of(81) only in notation <lb/>and a few sign changes, and we shall only give the result: <lb/> t/Jit)= cOS(N!/2t)¢2-(N a +1)- &apos;12 sin[(Na  +1)1/2t  ]&quot;&apos;ta <lb/> -I cos  [(Na  +  l) <lb/> I/Z  t  J - cos(N  !/2t )  1  &quot;,r  &quot;&apos;2&quot;&apos;1&apos; (82) <lb/>The power of the method of statistical renormalization <lb/>should now be evident. We have found closed-form expres-<lb/>SI&lt;lns for  ¢l(t)  and  1/12(t)  by  ~a1culations  which are almost <lb/>trivIal (once the appropriate mathematical framework has <lb/>been erected), whereas the method of Sec. 4, based on com-<lb/>pletely normally ordered expansions, would lead to an infi-<lb/>nite series of terms whose complexity increases rapidly with <lb/>order, such that the general term could probably not be <lb/>found at all. Indeed, if one attempts to derive the normal <lb/>expansions by reordering of the functions of  Na  appearing in <lb/>Eqs. (81) and (82), one rapidly finds that it is a formidable <lb/>algebraic problem. <lb/>The transformed Hamiltonian 1! of Eq. (18) is given <lb/>according to (2) by <lb/> 1!.  = EI1/!.11/!.1  +  £21/!.11/!.2  +  vV!.i  t{j  1/!.2V!.I&apos; <lb/>(83) <lb/>with <lb/> (84) <lb/> According to (22) and (23) these transforms are obtained by <lb/>evaluating ¢I(t) and  ¢it)  at &quot;time&quot;  -rr/2,  yielding <lb/>1/!.1 = cos  (N~/2  ;)1/11  +  (Na  +  1) -1/2 <lb/>Xsin  [(N  Q  +  1)1/2 ;  l1j1~a  +  {COS[(Na  +  1)1/2 ; 1 <lb/> -cos  (N !/2 ;)  }¢~ ~Z&quot;&apos;I&apos; <lb/> ¥!..2=  COS(N~12 ;)I/I2-(N~  +1)-1/2 <lb/> Xsin  [(N  a  +  1)1/2 ;  1&quot;&apos; 1a - {cos  [(N  a  +  1)1/2 ; ] <lb/> -cos  (N  !/2 ;) }&quot;&apos; T  TfiztP,· <lb/> (85) <lb/></body>

			<page> 2372 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> J.  Math. Phys., Vol. 21, No. S, September 1980 <lb/></note>

			<body> It  is amusing to note that the operators V!.l&apos;  V!.2&apos;  V!.! , and t[:i are <lb/>indeed Fermi operators, i.e., they satisfy the elementary fer-<lb/>mion anticommutation relatiDns (1) even though they in-<lb/>volve boson operators  a,  at via No  =  ata;  the proof involves <lb/>use of (60) and trigonometric identities. The expression for <lb/> l!..  is found by substitution of(85) into (83) and use of (60) <lb/> and the commutation and anticommunication relations; we <lb/>shaH only exhibit the result: <lb/> H  =  E sin 2  (N  lIZ!!....)  +  [E -E sin 2  (N  1/2!!...) ].,.t  .1. <lb/> -<lb/>a <lb/> 0 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> a <lb/>a <lb/> 2 <lb/> &apos;f&apos;1 &apos;f&apos;1 <lb/> +  [Ez -EaSin <lb/>2 (N!/2  ~)  11/1it/J2 <lb/> +  ~Ea  [N  a-l/2sin(N  !/211&apos;  )a  t t/J21j11 <lb/> +  tP1  I/I~  aN ;- l/2 sin(N  ! 12 7r) ] <lb/> +  {v  +  Ea  cos <lb/> 2  [(N&quot;  +  1) 1/2 ; ] <lb/> -ca  COS <lb/>Z  (N!/2 ;)  }I/Ir&quot;,il/lztPl&apos; <lb/> (86) <lb/> This is the exact expression of which (49) is the first few <lb/>terms of the normal expansion. It is clear (at least in this <lb/>model) that it is great advantage to leave the functions of the <lb/>occupation number in their given forms and not to reorder <lb/>them into normal expansions. <lb/>To evaluate the projected Hamiltonian  ~  we need the <lb/>projector  R  of Eqs. (19) and (20). In principle, exp(iNJ} ) <lb/>could be evaluated by the D-matrix method (using a different <lb/>choice of operator basis) but it is more efficient to make use <lb/>of the previously obtained results in the evaluation, It is easy <lb/>to show either algebraically or from the physical interpreta-<lb/>tion that the operators  No  +  t/J!  1f1 and  Na  +  1f11fz  commute <lb/>with  F;  hence <lb/> Jl{a  =  No ( ;) =  Na  +  Ifi &quot;&apos;I - V!.I V!.l <lb/> = No  +  Ifi  t/Jz - 1!.i I{:z-<lb/> (87) <lb/> Using the expression (85) for V!.  I  or v!.z. one finds after algebra-<lb/> ic reductions <lb/> Jl{a <lb/> Na - sin <lb/> 2  (N!/2 ;) + sin <lb/> 2  (N!/2 ; )(&quot;&apos;; 1/11  +  1/11 &quot;&apos;2) <lb/> - ~N  a- &apos;/2sin(N  ;/211&apos; ) at  1/J2  1/1  I <lb/> -HNa  +  1) - \/2  sin  [(Na  +  1  )1/211&apos; ]t/Jl  Tfi~  a <lb/> +  H cos(N  ~1211&apos;)  - cos  [(N a  +  1  y/211&apos; ] 1 &quot;&apos; 1 Tfil  ¢21/1  I&apos;  (88) <lb/>We must next exponentiate this expression to find <lb/> exp(iNa  tJ).  This can again be done by an equation of motion <lb/>method. By forming products and powers of the various <lb/> TABLE IV. Reduced operator basis for  exp(j~.  {}). <lb/> v <lb/> 2 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 5 <lb/> I/If.p,  +  1/1:1/12 <lb/> a&apos;r/12¢&apos; <lb/> t!&gt;;  ¢i a <lb/> ,pi,pi  tP2¢&apos; <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> M. D. Girardeau <lb/></note>

			<page> 2372 <lb/> </page>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:47:30 <lb/></note>

			<body> tenns in (88), it is easy to show that  exp(i~a  {} ) is expressible <lb/>in the fonn <lb/> s <lb/> exp(i~a{})  =  &apos;L  G&quot;(Na,{})B,,, <lb/> (89) <lb/> v=l <lb/> where the basis elements  B&quot;  are given in Table IV. Differen-<lb/>tiating (89) with respect to {}, one finds <lb/> &apos;LG&quot;(Na{})B,,  =  i~aexp(i~a{}) <lb/> v <lb/> =  &apos;Li~aG&quot;(Na,{})B,,, <lb/> (90) <lb/> &quot; <lb/> where the dot now represents differentiation with respect to <lb/>{}. Upon substituting (88), perfonning the algebraic reduc-<lb/>tions necessary to represent the right side as a linear combi-<lb/>nation (with Na-dependent coefficients) of the basis ele-<lb/>ments  B&quot;,  and equating coefficients oflike basis elements, <lb/>one obtains the following differential equations for the  G,,: <lb/>G1(N a ,{})  =  i[Na _sin 2 (N!12 ;) ]G1(Na,{}) <lb/>-!iN ! /2 sin(N !l2rr)GiN a - l,{}), <lb/> G 2 (N a ,{})  =  iN a G 2 (N a ,{})  + isin 2  (N!/2 ;)G1(N a ,{}) <lb/>+ !iN ! 12 sin(N !l2rr)G 4 (N a  -l,{}), <lb/> G 3 (Na ,{}) =  i [Na - sin <lb/>2  (N !/2 ;) ]GiNa,{}) <lb/> -FN  a-1/2sin(N!/2rr)[GI(Na  -l,{}) +  Gs(N a  -l,{})] <lb/> -iN a-1I2sin(N !l2rr)GiNa - l,{}), <lb/> GiN a ,{}) <lb/> = i{Na  +sin <lb/>2  [(Na  +1)1!2;]  }GiNa,{}) <lb/>-F(N a  + 1) - 1I2 sin[(Na  +  1)1/2rr]G 1 (N a  + l,{}), <lb/> Gs(N a ,{})  =  i {Na  + sin 2  [(N a  + 1)1/2 ; ]  }Gs(N a ,{}) <lb/> + 2isin <lb/> 2 <lb/> [(N  a  + 1)1/2 ;  ]G  2  (N  a ,{}) <lb/> + !i{cos(N!l2rr) - cos  [(Na  +  1)V2rr ]}G I (N a ,{}) <lb/>-!iN!/2sin(N!/2rr)GiNa  -l,{}) <lb/> - ~i(Na  +  l)l!2 sin[(N a  + 1)1/2rr ]  GiNa  + l,{}). (91) <lb/>These are to be solved subject to the initial conditions <lb/>(92) <lb/>following from (89) and Table IV. Addition of the first two <lb/>equations gives <lb/> d <lb/> -<lb/>[G1(N a ,{})  +  G 2 (N a ,{})] <lb/> d{} <lb/> = iNa [G1(N a ,{})  +  G 2 (N a ,{})], <lb/> whose solution subject to the initial conditions is <lb/> (93) <lb/> (94) <lb/>which can be used to eliminate  G 2  from the third and fifth <lb/>equations. The first and fourth equations can be combined <lb/>into a single matrix equation <lb/></body>

			<page> 2373 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> J.  Math. Phys., Vol. 21, No.9, September 1980 <lb/></note>

			<body> d [  G1(Na,{})]. <lb/>[G1(Na,{})] <lb/> -<lb/>=  IM(Na  ) <lb/> -(1) , <lb/> d{}  GiNa - l,{}) <lb/> GiNa - l,v <lb/> where the elements of the matrix Mare <lb/> MI1 =  Na - sin <lb/>2 (  N!12 ;), <lb/> M12  = -!N  ! /2 sin(N !121T), <lb/> M21  = -!N  a-112sin(N  !l2rr), <lb/> M22  =  Na - 1 + sin 2 (  N !/2 ;) . <lb/> (95) <lb/>(96) <lb/> The solution vector is a linear combination of the two eigen-<lb/>vectors of M. The eigenvalues are the solutions of the secular <lb/>equation <lb/> [MI1(N a ) - A  ][M 22 (N a ) - A] - MdNa)M21(Na)  = 0, <lb/> (97) <lb/> of which the roots are <lb/> A  +  (N a )  =  N a , A _ (N a )  =  Na  -1. <lb/> (98) <lb/>The determination of the solution satisfying the initial condi-<lb/>tions (92) is then straightforward; we give only the result: <lb/> G (N {}) = cos 2  (N  112  !!....)iNa,&quot;) <lb/> 1 <lb/> a&apos; <lb/>a <lb/> 2 <lb/> + .  2  (N  112 rr)  i(N&quot; - I),&quot;} <lb/> SIn <lb/> a -e <lb/>, <lb/> 2 <lb/> GiN a ,{})  =  ~(Na  +1)-1I2sin[(N a +1)1/2rr ] <lb/> X  [e iN .,&quot;) _ ei(N.  +  I),&quot;} ]. <lb/> Then by (94) <lb/> G (N  -(1) _ .  2  (N 1/2  !!....) [  iN.,&quot;} _  i(N.-I),&quot;}] <lb/> 2 <lb/> a&apos;v - SIn <lb/> a <lb/> e <lb/>e <lb/>. <lb/> 2 <lb/>(99) <lb/>(100) <lb/> The third and fifth equations (91) can also be solved by the <lb/>matrix method, taking  G  1  and  G  2  as known inhomogeneous <lb/>tenns; we again give only the result: <lb/> GiNa ,{}) =  !N  a-1/2sin(N  !l2rr)  [i(N.  -I),&quot;} _  e iN .,&quot;} ], <lb/> Gs(N a ,{}) <lb/> =  sin 2 [  (Na  + 1)1/2 ;  ]ei(N&quot;  + I),&quot;) <lb/> -{sin2(N!12  ;)+sin <lb/>2  [(N a  +1)1/2 ;]} <lb/> xe iN .,&quot;}  + sin 2  (N!12 ; )ei(N. - I),&quot;). <lb/> (101) <lb/>The final expression for  exp(i~a  {} ) given by Eq. (89) and <lb/>Table IV is then <lb/> exp(i~a  {})  =  cos <lb/> 2  (N !/2 ; )e iN .,&quot;)  + sin <lb/> 2  (N!12 ; )ei(N.  -I),&quot;) <lb/> + sin <lb/> 2  (N !/2 ;) [e <lb/> iN <lb/>.,&quot;} - ei(N.  -I),&quot;}  ](tP1  tPI + tP1  tP2) <lb/>+!N a-1/2sin(N!/2rr)[ei(N.-I),&quot;} - iN.,&quot;} ]at tP2tPl <lb/> + !(N a  + 1) - 112 sin[(Na  +  I)V2rr] [e <lb/> iN <lb/>.,&quot;} - ei(N.  +  I),&quot;}  ]tPl tP1a <lb/> + {sin2(N!12  ;)i(Na-I ), &quot;}  +sin 2  [(N a  +1)1/2;  ]ei(Na+I),&quot;) <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> M. D. Girardeau <lb/></note>

			<page> 2373 <lb/></page> 

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:47:30 <lb/></note>

			<body> - sin <lb/> 2  (N  ~/2  ;  )e <lb/> l <lb/> &quot;N«.1 -<lb/> sin 2  [(N a  +  1)1/2 ; ]/N«.1  }tPi  tP1  tP2tP1&apos; <lb/> (102) <lb/>The projectors  ~  can now be evaluated by performing the <lb/>integrals over {}, using the representation <lb/> f21T <lb/> ~  =  (21T) - I  Jo  d{)  exp(ilfa {}) <lb/>(103) <lb/>following from (19) and (20). Equation (20) generalizes to <lb/>(104) <lb/>where  P  n  is the projector onto the subspace of  Y  spanned by <lb/>eigenstates of  Na  with eigenvalue  n.  One has the obvious <lb/>identity <lb/>(105) <lb/>Furthermore, there exist on eigenstates of  Na  with negative <lb/>eigenvalues, so the terms in (102) involving  /(N«  +  1),1  inte-<lb/>grate to zero. One then finds a very simple expression <lb/> ~  =  ~o  +  ~I  - ~1(tPTtPI  +  tP1tP2) <lb/>+  (~I  - ~o)tPi  tPItP2tPl&apos; <lb/>(106) <lb/>Upon multiplying this by (85), applying the identities (105), <lb/>one finds the following expression for the projected <lb/>Hamiltonian <lb/> ~  =  Ea~lata  +  (El~O  - Ea~l)tPr  tPI +  (E2~O  - Ea~1)tPItP2 <lb/> +  [(v - Ea)~o  +  Ea~)  ]tP!  tP! tP2tPI&apos; <lb/>(107) <lb/> In  view ofEq. (105) the factor ata =  Na  in the first term <lb/>could have been omitted; however, it is included in order to <lb/>facilitate the physical interpretation which will be discussed <lb/>in the next section. The very simple expression (107) for  ~ <lb/> could have been obtained without all the elaborate machin-<lb/>ery of the Tani transformation, D-matrix, etc ... in this simple <lb/>model. However, for realistic systems trivial representations <lb/>such as (14) are not available, and the Fock-Tani representa-<lb/>tion has definite physical and mathematical advantages <lb/>which have already been discussed.  1-4  The methods that <lb/>have been illustrated here ought to be applicable to realistic <lb/>systems as well, although one can hardly expect closed-form <lb/>solutions in the general case. <lb/> 7 .  STATISTICALLY RENORMALIZED HAMILTONIAN <lb/> The physical interpretation and generalization to realis-<lb/>tic systems require a more explicit expression than (107), in <lb/>which the projectors  Po  and  p)  are expressed as functions of <lb/> N  a •  The most convenient representation for our purposes is <lb/>obtained by changing the limits of integration in (104) to <lb/> [ - 1T,1T],  taking advantage of the fact that  Na  has only inte-<lb/>gral eigenvalues. The integration is then trivial and yields the <lb/>representation <lb/> wherejo  is the spherical Bessel function of order zero, <lb/> jo(x)  =  sinx/x. Since <lb/>(108) <lb/> jo(O)  = 1;  jo(n1T)  = 0,  n  =  ±  1,  ±  2, .. &quot; <lb/>(109) <lb/>the desired projection properties of the representation (108) <lb/></body>

			<page> 2374 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> J.  Math. Phys .. Vol. 21, NO.9, September 1980 <lb/></note>

			<body> are evident. One then finds the following expression for the <lb/>projected Hamiltonian (107) <lb/> ~  =  Ea(Na)ata  +  E,(Na)tP!  tPI +  EiNa)tPI  tP2 <lb/> +  veNa  )tPi tP1 tP2tPI&apos; <lb/>(110) <lb/>where  Ea(N a ), EI(N a ),  and  E 2 (N a )  are statistically renorma-<lb/>lized single-particle energies and similarly  v(N a )  is a statisti-<lb/>cally renormalized interaction, defined by <lb/> Ea(N a )  =  Edo«N a -1)11&apos;), <lb/>E)(N a )  =  Eljo(N a 1T) - €do«Na -1)11&apos;), <lb/>€iN a )  =  E2jo(N a 11&apos;) - €do«Na - 1)11&apos;), <lb/>v(N a )  =  (v-Ea)io(N a 1T)  +  €do«N a -1)11&apos;). <lb/>(111) <lb/> It  was noted in Secs. 4 and 5 that secular terms (powers <lb/> 1T,r,··)  do not appear in the normal expansions for either  H <lb/> or  ~  to the orders exhibited in Eqs. (44) and (54). This -<lb/>result is in fact valid in arbitrary order, as can be seen by <lb/>noting how the normal expansions can be generated starting <lb/>from the statistically renormalized expressions (86) and <lb/>(110). The proof is simpler for  ~.  It  follows from (110) and <lb/>(111) that the normal expansion for JY&apos; can be obtained im-<lb/>mediately once those  ofjo(N a 1T) andj~«Na  -1)11&apos;)  are <lb/>known. That  ofjo(N a 1T)  is already known from Eq. (21) <lb/> 00 <lb/> (_1)&quot; <lb/> jo(N a 1T)  =  Po  =  I -- (at)&quot;a&quot;. <lb/>(112) <lb/> -<lb/>n  =  0 <lb/> n! <lb/> The normal expansion of  PI  can be derived by the same <lb/>method <lb/> 2 as was (112). One has <lb/> jo«N a -1)1T)  =  ~l  =  !  cn(at)&quot;a&quot;, <lb/> (113) <lb/> n=O <lb/> with coefficients C&quot; to be determined. Letting  In)  be the ei-<lb/>genstate const. (at)&quot;iO) of  Na  with eigenvalue  n,  one has suc-<lb/>cessively, with (59), <lb/> ~IIO)  = Co = 0, <lb/> ~lll)  = c  l ll)  = 11), c 1 = 1, <lb/> ~112)=(2+2c2)12)=0,  C 2  = -1, <lb/> ~113)  = (3 -6 +6c 3 )13) = 0, c 3 =!, <lb/> C&quot;  =  l(n - I)!, <lb/> and hence <lb/> jo«N a -1)11&apos;)  =  p)  = ! (-1)&quot;  (a~&quot;a&quot;. <lb/> -<lb/>n  =  1  (n  -I)! <lb/> (114) <lb/>(115) <lb/>Substitution of (112) and (115) into (110) and (111), noting <lb/>thatjo«N a  -1)1T)a <lb/> t  a  =  jo«N a -1)1T),  yields the complete <lb/>normal expansion of  ~,  of which only the first few terms <lb/>were exhibited in Eq. (54) <lb/> JY&apos;  =  JY&apos;0  +  r, <lb/> ~  =  ! (-=- l~n  + 1  [(n  +  I)Ea _ v ] (a  t)&quot;tPi tP1  tP2tP)a n <lb/> &quot;=0 <lb/> n. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> M. D. Girardeau <lb/></note>

			<page> 2374 <lb/></page> 

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:47:30 <lb/></note>

			<body> (116) <lb/> Here  Ho  is the unperturbed Fock-Tani Hamiltonian <lb/>(49). No secular terms (powers of  11&apos;)  appear in the expression <lb/>(116). Note how easy it is to obtain the general term in the <lb/>normal expansion once the (nontrivial) task of determina-<lb/>tion of the statistically renormalized expression for u!&apos; has <lb/>been accomplished. Note also that the statistically renorma-<lb/>lized expression is much simpler, both in mathematical form <lb/>and in physical interpretation, than the completely normally <lb/>ordered expression (116). <lb/>The determination of the normal expansion for the un-<lb/>projected Hamiltonian  H  can be done in the same way, al-<lb/>though the algebra is more complicated. According to (86) <lb/>one needs the normal expansions of sin <lb/> 2 (N  !1211&apos; /2), <lb/>cos 2 (N !1211&apos;  12).  N  a~  \ <lb/> /2 sin(N !1211&apos;),  and <lb/> cos 2 [(N a  +  I)V211&apos;/2].  These can be determined as in (114), <lb/>(115); one finds <lb/>sin 2  (N !/2 ;) =  ata  +! - i  -lcos(2 112 11&apos;)] (a t fa 2 <lb/> + [ ! +  *OS(2 1/2 11&apos;) - fzcos(31/211&apos;)]  (a~3a3  + .... <lb/> cos 2  (N  1/ <lb/> 2 <lb/> !!....) = 1 -sin 2  (N  \/2!!....) <lb/> a <lb/> 2 <lb/> a <lb/> 2 &apos; <lb/> N  a~  \  12 sin(N  !/211&apos;)  = 2  ~  312 sin(211211&apos;)(a  t  2 a <lb/> 2 ) <lb/> + [ - 2  ~3/2sin(21/211&apos;)  +  p  ~312sin(3J;2i)] <lb/> X  (a  t )3a3  + .... <lb/> cos 2  [(N a +1)1/2;]  =  [~+!COS(21/211&apos;)]ata <lb/> + [ - i - !COS(2 112 11&apos;)  +  icos(31;211&apos;)](a~2a2 <lb/> + ! n +  !COS(2V <lb/> 2 11&apos;) - !COS(3 1/2 11&apos;) <lb/>+ fzc0s(4V 2 11&apos;)] (a t ?a <lb/> 3 <lb/> + .... <lb/> (117) <lb/>Substitution into (86) gives terms in the normal expansion of <lb/>Hbeyond those exhibited in (49).  It  is clear without attempt-<lb/> i~g  to evaluate the general term that no secular terms appear <lb/>in any order. The statistically renormalized expression (86) <lb/>is much simpler and preferable to the completely normally <lb/>ordered expression. <lb/> 8.  LINKED VERSUS UNLINKED EXPRESSIONS <lb/> Consider the action of the various terms in the normal <lb/>expansion (116) of  ~  upon a state  (at)mIO)  with a specified <lb/>number  m  ofbosons. In view of the identity (59), it is clear <lb/></body>

			<page> 2375 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> J.  Math. Phys., Vol. 21, No.9, September 1980 <lb/></note>

			<body> that for  m-+oo.  the terms in (116) with index  n  give energy <lb/>contributions of order  mn.  assuming  n  fixed as  m-+  00. The <lb/>contributions for  n  &gt;  2 are &quot;hyperextensive&quot;. i.e., increase <lb/>more rapidly than linearly with  mas m-+oo.  This type of <lb/>unphysical behavior is typical of the unlinked clusters in <lb/>Rayleigh-Schrodinger perturbation theory of a many-parti-<lb/>cle system. In fact, if one introduces a diagram notation for <lb/>the various terms in  ~.  then each term with a factor  (a  ty on <lb/>the left and  an  on the right is represented by a diagram con-<lb/>taining  n  free boson lines disconnected from the rest of the <lb/>diagram. Actually, the unlinked terms all cancel when com-<lb/>bined properly so as to pass to the statistically renormalized <lb/>expression for K. This is clear from (110), in which there are <lb/>no unlinked teOns. Some of the unlinked terms of (116) are <lb/>absorbed into the definition of the renormalized single-parti-<lb/>cle energies  Ea(N a ). E\(N a ),  and  Ez(N a ).  while the rest are <lb/>included in the definition of the renormalized interaction <lb/>vertex  u(N a ).  The statistically renormalized expression (110) <lb/>is therefore analogous to the expressions obtained in linked <lb/>cluster forms of many-particle perturbation theory. This is <lb/>still another reason for the superiority of the statistically <lb/>renormalized representation as compared with the usual <lb/>normal series. Indeed, it shows that the procedure of statisti-<lb/>cal renormalization is essential for obtaining physically cor-<lb/>rect results in the Fock-Tani representation for a system of <lb/>many composite particles as soon as one goes beyond the <lb/>lowest-order terms in the normal expansion. The simplified <lb/>model investigated here does not really allow many-boson <lb/>states, but these observations should be relevant to more re-<lb/>alistic models. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/> This work was begun while I was a visitor in the Labor-<lb/>atoire de Physique Quantique, Universite Paul Sabatier, <lb/>Toulouse, France and concluded at the Laboratoire de Phy-<lb/>sique Theorique, Universite de Nice. France. I am grateful to <lb/>these institutions for Visisting Professorships which made <lb/>this work possible. and particularly to Y. Soulet of the for-<lb/>mer institution and F. Rocca of the latter. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> &apos;M. D. Girardeau, Phys. Rev. Lett. 27,1416 (1971). <lb/> 2M. D. Girardeau,  J.  Math. Phys. 16, i901 (1975). <lb/> &apos;J. D. Gilbert, J. Math. Phys. 18,791 (1977). <lb/>4M. D. Girardeau and J. D. Gilbert, Physica A 97, 42 (1979). <lb/>&apos;R. F. Streater and A. S. Wightman, peT, Spin and Statistics, and All That <lb/> (Benjamin, New York, 1964), pp. 146ft&apos;. <lb/> 6y&apos; Soulet, R. Fleckinger, and M. D. Girardeau, Adv. Chern. Phys. (to be <lb/>published). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote"> M. D. Girardeau <lb/></note>

			<page> 2375 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:47:30 </note>


	</text>
</tei>
