<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> ELSEVIER <lb/> Physica A 241 (1997) 535-548 <lb/> Dynamics of one-site fermionic model in the <lb/>presence of precessing magnetic field <lb/> A.C.  Aguiar Pinto, R. Bruno, M.T. Thomaz* <lb/> Instituto de Fisica, Unioersidade Federal Fluminense, R. Gal. Milton Tavares de Souza s/n°., <lb/>Campus da Praia Vermelha, Niter6i, R.J., 24210-340, Brazil <lb/> Received 19 August 1996; received in revised form 3 December 1996 <lb/> Abstract <lb/> The one site self-interacting fermionic model is considered in the presence of an external <lb/>magnetic field precessing with constant angular velocity around a fixed axis. We get the exact <lb/>density operator for the identical particle system as well as its one-particle properties, for general <lb/>initial conditions. Due to the non-trivial topology of the external magnetic field, the one-particle <lb/>states get Berry&apos;s phases. We show that the geometric phases contribute to the frequency of the <lb/>one-particle population state in the adiabatic regime. <lb/> PACS:  03.65.-w; 05.30.-d <lb/> Keywords:  Matrix operator; Fermionic system; Berry&apos;s phases <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> It is a great challenge to understand the full dynamics of quantum systems. Much has <lb/>been done, but in general, the derived results involve approximations, whenever part or <lb/>the whole system is bosonic [1]. However, due to the Pauli&apos;s principle, for fermionic <lb/>systems with few degrees of freedom it is possible to obtain the exact dynamics of <lb/>these quantum systems under general initial conditions. <lb/>Kiibler and Zeh [2] considered the exact dynamics of two fermions interacting via <lb/>a two level model and in the presence of a constant external magnetic field. Once <lb/>the dimension of the basis for this problem is finite, it was possible to obtain the <lb/>expression for one-particle population, that was numerically studied. Recently, we used <lb/>the approach of Ref. [2] to study the model of self-interacting one site fermionic model, <lb/>that has four energy levels in the presence of an external magnetic field [3,4]. In Ref. [4] <lb/></body>

			<front>* Corresponding author. E-mail: mtt@if.uff.br. <lb/>0378-4371/97/$17.00 Copyright (~) 1997 Published by Elsevier Science B.V. All rights reserved <lb/> PH  S0378-4371 (97)00172-6 <lb/></front>

			<page> 536 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A.C Aguiar Pinto et al./Physica A 241 (1997) 535-548 <lb/></note>

			<body> we considered the external magnetic field varying in time along a fixed direction. <lb/>The topology of this type of external magnetic field is trivial and the states do not get <lb/>Berry&apos;s phases [5]. In this case, the population of one-particle state is time-independent. <lb/>However, one interesting question is what happens with the population of one-particle <lb/>subsystem when the external magnetic field has a non-trivial topology. The simplest <lb/>situation corresponds to the external magnetic field, with constant norm, precessing at <lb/>a constant angular velocity around a fixed direction. <lb/>A dimer formed by two radical molecules has been considered as the smallest struc-<lb/>ture responsible for the optical properties of organic charge-transfer salts [6]. The <lb/>electronic state of this system has been described by a hamiltonian with two self-<lb/>interacting fermionic sites endowed only with spin degrees. The time for an electron <lb/>to stay at one site is inversely proportional to the hopping constant. When the constant <lb/>that characterizes the hopping of the electron to the nearby site is very small, for time <lb/>interval much smaller than the characteristic hopping time, this system can be first <lb/>approximated by two independent one site self-interacting fermionic model. <lb/>In the present paper, we study the one site self-interacting fermionic model in the <lb/>presence of an external magnetic field precessing around the z-axis, with constant <lb/>angular velocity. The system is studied for any regime, that is, for any ratio between <lb/>the time scales of the quantum system and the period of the external magnetic field. <lb/>But, we will also consider explicitly the adiabatic limit to see the effect of the geometric <lb/>phases in the dynamics of one-particle density matrix. <lb/>In Section 2 we present the fermionic model and the time evolution of a general <lb/>initial vector state of the one site fermionic model. In Section 3 we get the exact <lb/>one-particle density matrix and the pairing tensor, for any initial pure state. We study <lb/>the adiabatic approximation and consider one particular case to explicit the physics <lb/>in the one-particle density matrix. In Section 4, we derive the one-particle density <lb/>matrix for an initial mixed state that represents the fermionic system initially at thermal <lb/>equilibrium with a reservoir. Finally, in Section 5 we present our conclusions. <lb/> 2. Fermionic model and its dynamics <lb/> The one-site self-interacting fermionic system [7] in the presence of a time-dependent <lb/>external magnetic field  B(t)  is described by the Hamiltonian: <lb/>H(t) = ~ ~ogata~ + UnTn ~ +  2[Bx(t)(a~a T +  a~a~) <lb/>~=T,I <lb/> +iBy(t)(aIa T - a~a+) + Bz(t)(n T -n+)], <lb/>(1) <lb/>where a~ and a~ are spin ½ fermionic destruction and creation operators, respectively, <lb/>satisfying the anticommutation relations, <lb/>{a~,a~,}--0 and {a~,a~,}=fi~,n, <lb/>(2) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> A.C. Ayuiar Pinto et al./Physica A 241 (1997) 535-548 <lb/></note>

			<page> 537 <lb/></page>

			<body> and n~ = a~a~, a = T, ~, gives the operator number of fermions with spin-component a. <lb/>The Hamiltonian (1) has only internal fermionic degrees of freedom and one can <lb/>think of U as representing a &quot;repulsive interaction&quot; between the fermions at the same <lb/>space site. In Hamiltonian (1) we used the Zeeman coupling to take into account the <lb/>interaction between the fermionic system and the external magnetic field. The constant <lb/>2----g#~/2, where 9 is the Land6 factor and #~ is the Bohr magneton, and  Bx(t), <lb/>By(t)  and  Bz(t)  are the three components of the time varying external magnetic field <lb/> B(t).  We should note that in general [H(q),H(t2)] 50 for tL ~ te. <lb/>Hamiltonian (1) has four eigenvalues. The eigenvalues and their respective eigen-<lb/>vectors are: <lb/> (i)  Eo=O, <lb/>H(t)10 ) =0, <lb/>(3) <lb/>where 10) is the vacuum state of the system (a~10)=0, a= T, ~). <lb/>(ii)  Ell)(t)=he)- ]2B(t)l , <lb/>H(t)lu~l); <lb/>(l) <lb/>(1) <lb/> ti=E 1  (t)iu 1 ;t), <lb/>(4) <lb/>where lull); t) is the eigenvector of H(t) at time t. In terms of states with definite <lb/>number of fermions with spin a, the normalized state lull); t) is <lb/>+  Bz(t) <lb/>Bx(t) + iBy(t)at ] <lb/> [u&apos;~&apos;); t) = <lb/>[a~ + <lb/>IO) <lb/>(5) <lb/> V ~]B-(&apos;~ <lb/>]B(t)l + Bz(t) ~] &quot; <lb/> (iii)  E~l)(t)=ho9 +  I,~e(t)l, <lb/> H(t)[u~l);t)  ~.(1) .... (1) <lb/>=L 2  U)Iu2  ;t), <lb/>(6) <lb/>and as in the previous case, lull); t) is the eigenstate of Hamiltonian H(t) at instant t. <lb/>(1). <lb/>The normalized state u 2  ,  t) can be written as <lb/> /[B(t)l-Bz(t) Wa~_Bx(t)+iBy(t) ¢] <lb/> lu~l);t)=  V ~B-~ <lb/>~ <lb/>IB(t)l-Bz(t)al] IO)&quot; <lb/> (7) <lb/>(iv) E2----2hco + U, <lb/> H(t)a~a~10) =(2hco + U)a~a~10). <lb/>(8) <lb/> The eigenvectors of Hamiltonian (1) are also, at each instant t, eigenvectors of <lb/>operator fi(t).a, where  fi(t)  is an unitary vector such that  fi(t)=B(t)/JB(t)l ,  and a are <lb/>the Pauli matrices. <lb/>Any state vector of the identical particle fermionic system can be written in the basis <lb/>of eigenstates of Hamiltonian (1) at time t, as [5,8], <lb/>I V(t)) = c0(t)]0) +  c2(t)e-~(ea~°+U)ta~a~  10) <lb/> +c]l)(t)e-i/h f/ at&apos; (noJ-[2B(t&apos;)l)lu%l); t) <lb/>_l_c~l )(t)e-i/h f&apos; dr&apos; (~to+12B(t&apos;)1)]u~l);  t). <lb/>(9) <lb/></body>

			<page> 538 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A.C. Ayuiar Pinto et al./Physica A 241 (1997) 535-548 <lb/></note>

			<body> (1 <lb/> The values of the coefficients  co(t), c2(t), c 1 )(t)  and  c~2)(t),  at t=0, are determined <lb/>by the initial vector state of the system. <lb/>Hamiltonian ( 1 ) commutes with the operator of total number of fermions N(N --- ny + <lb/> nt ). As a consequence of this fact, the dynamics of the system does not mix up states of <lb/>different Fock sub-spaces. Therefore, we calculate independently the time dependence <lb/>of the coefficients in Eq. (9) of states belonging to different Fock sub-spaces. <lb/>The Schr6dinger equation satisfied by IV(t)), <lb/>H(t)l ~P(t)) = ih al ~(t)) , <lb/>where H(t) is given by Eq. (1), determines the time equations satisfied by the coef-<lb/>ficients in Eq. (9). For the different Fock sub-spaces N, and N here means the total <lb/>number of particles, we have the equations: <lb/>(i) N=0 <lb/> ih~ <lb/> =0 <lb/> (ii) N=2 <lb/> co(t)=co(O). <lb/> (10) <lb/> clc~( t ~ <lb/>ih~=O <lb/> =~  c2(t)=c2(0). <lb/> (11) <lb/>The results (10) and (11) only reflect the fact that the sub-spaces N=0 and N=2 <lb/>are unidimensional. <lb/>(iii) N= 1, reduces to the two-state problem that has been treated previously [9]. <lb/>In expression (9), the basis chosen by us to expand the vectors in N = 1 sub-sector is <lb/>different from the one used in Ref. [9]. In our case, the differential equations satisfied <lb/>by the coefficients c}l)(t), i= 1,2, are <lb/> dt <lb/>_e-(2il;,I/~) £  IB(t&apos;)lat&apos;,/ul ;(l) t ~?t~?t, u(&apos;);2  t))c~&apos;)(t) , <lb/> (12) <lb/> dc~&apos; )(t)dt = -e(2il;d/h) g IB(t&apos;)ldt&apos;(u~l); t[-~ (lu]l); t) )ClI)(/) <lb/> --(U~I);  t] ~t (lu~l);  t))c~l)(t). <lb/> (13) <lb/>It is interesting to point out here that  8[@);t)/St, i=  1,2, is a measure of how the <lb/>eigenstates of Hamiltonian (1) change at each time [8]. <lb/>From now on, we restrict ourselves to the case of an external magnetic field with <lb/>constant norm, precessing around the z axis at constant angular velocity, <lb/> d[B(t)]=O  and  dBz(t)=o <lb/> (14) <lb/> dt <lb/>dt <lb/>&apos; <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> A.C. Aouiar Pinto et al. IPhysica A 241 (1997) 535-548 <lb/></note>

			<page> 539 <lb/></page>

			<body> and <lb/> Bx( t )  + iBy( t )= ~ --ff~ e i°~°t , <lb/> (15) <lb/> where B = IB(t)l, and o90 is the constant angular velocity of  B(t)  precessing around <lb/>the z axis.The sense of axis z is arbitrary. We choose it such that Bz/&gt; 0. This implies <lb/>that 0, the angle between the magnetic field  B(t)  and z axis is fixed and belongs to the <lb/>interval [0, rt/2]. For positive (negative) to0 we have a left (right) circularly polarized <lb/>magnetic field. <lb/>To write the next expressions in a shorter way, we define: <lb/>= B~Bz <lb/>~//1-cos0 <lb/>(16) <lb/>A_ V 2B -<lb/>2 <lb/>&apos; <lb/>and <lb/> D=-? +Bz2B  ~/1 +cos02 <lb/>(17) <lb/>Let us also define <lb/> ~--I&apos;zIB <lb/> (18) <lb/> h <lb/>From Eqs. (4) and (6), we have that 2~//=(/z 2 <lb/>Using those definitions and the expressions of lull); t), i= 1,2 (Eqs. (5) and (7)), the <lb/>coupling equations ( 1 2) and ( 1 3), become <lb/> dc]l)(t)  --imoA2c] &apos;)(t)  +  icooADe-2i~&apos;t c~ &apos;)(t) , <lb/> dt <lb/> dc~ 1)(t) _  itooADe2 i** , c{l)(t) -itooD2c~ l)(t) . <lb/>dt <lb/> The solutions of these coupled equations are: <lb/>(19) <lb/> (20) <lb/> c(ll)(t)=e-i/2(ogo+2q¢)t{c(tl)(O)cos(~--~t) <lb/> and <lb/>2~&quot; <lb/>c~,)(O)] sin (_~t) } <lb/>+Fi I( c°sO+ O~o) c{&apos;)(O)+sinO <lb/> (21) <lb/> i I <lb/>2. <lb/> sin Oc]l)(O) -<lb/>~Oo <lb/>+ <lb/>where <lb/>+ 2cos0 <lb/>) c~1)(0)] sin (-~t) }, <lb/>(22) <lb/> (23) <lb/></body>

			<page> 540 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A.C Aouiar Pinto et al./Physica A 241 (1997) 535 548 <lb/></note>

			<body> cl&apos;)(0) and c~1)(0) are the coefficients of the eigenstates lull);0), i=1,2, of <lb/>Hamiltonian (1) in the initial state vector. We should note that  2~//Ico01  is the ra-<lb/>tio between the frequency associated to the splitting of one-particle energy level, due <lb/>to the presence of the external field, and the frequency of precession of  B(t)  around <lb/>z axis. For 090&lt;0, in Eqs. (21) and (22), the terms proportional to  sin((Fcoo/2)t)  get <lb/>a global sign. Even though the periodic part of the whole system is the external field, <lb/>the frequency of  c~l)(t)  and c~l)(t) depends on coo as well as on 2~/C/co0, the geometric <lb/>parameter cos 0 and the sign of COo. <lb/>The results (21) and (22) are also valid for the two state fermionic model, when <lb/>we have U--0. <lb/> 3. One-particle density matrix: Initial pure states <lb/> For the cases in which the system is initially described by a vector state IT J(0)), <lb/>the time evolution of this state vector is obtained from expressions (9), (21) and (22) <lb/>by a suitable choice of the coefficients: c0(0), c2(0), c~l)(0) and c~1)(0). The operator <lb/>density of the identical particle fermionic system is <lb/>~-(t) = I ~(t)) ( ~(t)]. <lb/>(24) <lb/>Once we know ~(t) exactly, at any instant t, we have all the quantum information <lb/>available about the system. In particular, the mean values of one-particle observables <lb/>of the system are derived by the knowledge of one-particle density matrix  A(t), <lb/>Aij(t) = Tr[a~ai~(t)] <lb/>~-(~P(t)la~ail~P(t)), <lb/> i,j----1,2, <lb/>(25) <lb/>and the pairing tensor//(t), <lb/> Hij(t) = Tr[aiaj~(t)] <lb/>= (~P(t)laiaj]TJ(t)), <lb/>i,j=  1,2. <lb/>(26) <lb/>We are using the convention: ~r= T = i=1 and a= .L -i=2. <lb/>Only states that differ by two particles contribute to  El(t).  From the previous results, <lb/>we have that, <lb/> H(t)  has no oscilattory behaviour because the states with N=0 and N=2 particles do <lb/>not couple to the external magnetic field. Besides this, the density operators (reduced <lb/>or not) are insensible to global phases. <lb/>From the definition of  A(t),  we have that it is an hermitian matrix (see Eq. (25)) <lb/>and its trace gives the average number of fermions in the system. The average number <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> A.C. Aguiar Pinto et al. IPhysica A 241 (1997) 535-548 <lb/></note>

			<page> 541 <lb/></page>

			<body> of fermions in the system is constant, hence to get A(t), it is enough to calculate <lb/>All(t) and Alz(t). <lb/>From the expression (9) of I~(t)), we get that <lb/>All(t) ---- [C2(0)] 2 +  D2lc]l)(t)l 2 +  A2[c~l)(t)l 2 <lb/>+2AD~(c]l&apos;*(t)c~l)(t)e-2r~&apos;t). <lb/> (28) <lb/>Substituting the expressions of  c]l)(t)  (Eq. (21)) and  c~l)(t)  (Eq. (22)) in Eq. (28), <lb/>we have <lb/> D21c]l)(t)l 2 ~-A2lc~l)(t)]2  = ½(Ic]l)(0)l 2 ~-Ic~l)(0)[ 2) <lb/> +cosO( Ic~l )(°)l z-l c~l )(°)l = <lb/>)~  -F~-2 sin(20) sin2 (-~ t ) <lb/> ,c l&gt; o &lt;, ( oso+ 70) <lb/> sin(20) ~(c]1)* (0)c~1)(0)) sin(Fo)ot) <lb/>2F <lb/>(29) <lb/>and <lb/> ~(t) = c] 1 )* (t)c~&apos;)(t)e -2i~t  = c] 1 )* (0)c~ 1)(0) cos(r~o0t) <lb/>2&quot;W <lb/>sin 0 <lb/>+---fT-sin2(~-~t) [(cos0+ o)o)(]c]l)(0)[2--]c~l)(0)l z) <lb/>2sinO N(c~L)*(O)c~l)(o)) + sin(F~oot) <lb/>+ <lb/> (30) <lb/> By the definitions of A and D, 2AD= sin 0. Remember that in principle, c~l)(0) and <lb/>c~l)(0) are complex numbers determined by the initial condition problem. F is given <lb/>by Eq. (23) and 0 is the angle between the magnetic field and the z axis. All(t) gives <lb/>the average number of particles with spin a = T-The Fock sub-space sectors N = 1 <lb/>and N=2 give independent contributions to  All(t).  The frequency of oscillation of <lb/>the population in the state a~ 10) is F~o0, and it is independent of the initial condition <lb/>problem. <lb/>The non-diagonal elements of  A(t)  are: Azl(t)= A~&apos;z(t), and <lb/></body>

			<page> 542 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A.C.  Aguiar Pinto et al. IPhysica A 241 (1997) 535-548 <lb/></note>

			<body> where the function ~e(t) is given by Eq. (30). Directly from the expressions of  cO)(t) <lb/> and  c~l)(t),  we get, <lb/>[ <lb/>2sin2 0 <lb/>(ff_~2) <lb/> Ic{1)(t)l 2 --]c~l)(t)] 2 =(Ic{1)(0)l 2- ]C~l)(0)J 2) 1 <lb/> F2 sin 2 <lb/> t <lb/> 4sin0 ( <lb/>+~-T-<lb/>cos0+ <lb/>× sin2 (-~t) <lb/>--<lb/>2~W) ~(c{ll ) * <lb/>O) <lb/> (O)c 2 (o)) <lb/> 600 <lb/> 2 sin  0 .,~(c{l)*(0)c~l)(0)) sin(Fogot). <lb/>F <lb/>(32) <lb/>The contribution to A12(t) only comes, in this model, from N = 1 sector once N = 2 <lb/>sector is one-dimensional. <lb/>From Eqs. (29) and (30), we see that the period of oscillation of one-particle states <lb/>with spin a is <lb/>2~z <lb/>T = Fifo0[ . <lb/>(33) <lb/>For B ~ 0, the factor F can be smaller, equal or bigger than 1. For 2# p &lt; [COo], COo &lt;0 <lb/>and 0 E [0 °, arccos(~W/l~o0[)), F is smaller than 1. For o9&gt;0, F is always bigger than 1. <lb/>In the latter, the oscillatory variation of one-particle subsystem is always faster than the <lb/>external field. For fermions in the adiabatic regime, 2Y¢~/Ico d ~ 1, we have that F,~I <lb/>and T ,~ 2~z/~o0 = To, where To is the period of  B(t).  For the case in which 2&quot;///&quot; = COo, <lb/>we have that T = To/[2 cos(° )], and cos(°) E [1, cos v/2/2]. <lb/>For 0 = 0 °, we recover the results of Ref. [4]. <lb/> 3.1. One-particle state density matrix: Adiabatic approximation <lb/> In this section, we consider explicitly the case in which the interaction between <lb/>the quantum system and the environment (external field) is adiabatic. This regime is <lb/>characterized by the conditions: co0/2~/¢&quot; ~ 1 and COo --+ 0. Imposing those conditions on <lb/>the solutions (21) and (22), we get [5,8] <lb/>and <lb/> c(ll)(t) = C{1)(0)  e-iO~oIa(O)t/4rr <lb/> c~l)(t) = c~l)(o)  e-i°9oOOt-O)t/4~ &apos; <lb/> (34) <lb/>and t2(~)/2r~ = 1 -cos ~, and it represents the solid angle subtended by a line that ro-<lb/>tates around the z-axis making an angle ~ with this direction. The phases in <lb/>Eqs. (34) and (35) are the Berry&apos;s phases for the two one-particle states. <lb/>The pairing tensor is still given by expression (27) since it depends only on the <lb/>states of sub-spaces N = 0 and N = 2, which do not couple to the external magnetic <lb/>field. <lb/> (35) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> A.C. Aguiar Pinto et al. I Physica A 241 (1997) 535-548 <lb/></note>

			<page> 543 <lb/></page>

			<body> The expressions (28) and (31) were derived for the case in which the quantum sys-<lb/>tem is initially in a pure state. Hence Eqs. (28) and (31) are still valid in the adiabatic <lb/>approximation. Substituting  c]l)(t) and c~l)(t)  by Eqs. (34) and (35) respectively, we <lb/>obtain in the adiabatic approximation: <lb/> All(t)  =  le2(0){ 2 ~-(le~1)(0)12 +2 [c~1)(0)12) + cos 0 (le]l)(0)[2 --2 1e~1)(0)12) <lb/>+]c~O(0)c~l)(0)l sin 0 cos((2~ + (Do cos  O)t +  0~O(0) --0~O(0)), (36) <lb/>and <lb/> e-io~ot <lb/> A12(t)  = ~{sin0 <lb/> ()e~l)(0)l 2 -le~l&gt;(0)l 2) <lb/> -2 [c] I)(0)c~&apos;)(0)1 [cos 0 cos((2~V&quot; + (Do cos  O)t + 0~&apos;  )(0) -0~ 1 )(0)) <lb/>+i sin((Z~W + 09o cos  O)t +  011)(0) -0~t)(0))]}. <lb/>(37) <lb/>The frequency of oscillation of population of one-particle state is <lb/>~o ~ 2~W + (Do cos 0, <lb/>(38) <lb/>and the term o90 cos0, on the r.h.s, of Eq. (38), is a direct consequence to the fact <lb/>that the two one-particle states get different geometric phases. The contribution of <lb/>the Berry&apos;s phases to the r.h.s, of Eq. (38) depends only on the geometry of the <lb/>configuration of the external field, but it is sensible to the sign of (Do. In the adiabatic <lb/>approximation, the period of one-particle fermionic subsystem is <lb/>2re ( <lb/>(Do <lb/>) <lb/>T ~ (2&quot;W------) 1 -~ cos 0 . <lb/>(39) <lb/>T is smaller (bigger) than the period 2rc/2~W for (Do &gt; 0 ((Do &lt;0). The period 27z/2~// <lb/>is the time scale associated to the splitting of the one-particle energies by the presence <lb/>of the external magnetic field. In  Alfft),  there is a sin0 multiplying the oscillary part <lb/>of Eq. (36). For 0 ---0 °, the external field has a trivial topology and the population of <lb/>one-particle states becomes time-independent as we obtained in Ref. [4]. <lb/> 3.2. One-particle density matrix: Particular case <lb/> The elements (28) and (31) of one-particle density matrix  A(t) are  awkward. To <lb/>explicit some physical results from them that come from the dynamics of coupling be-<lb/>tween the quantum system and the external field, we consider a simple initial condition <lb/>for the vector that describes the fermionic system at t = 0. <lb/>For Ic~°(0)l =  le l&gt;(0)l, the elements of  A(t)  reduce to: <lb/>sin(20) ( <lb/>2~/r ) <lb/> All(t)=[c2(O)12+]c~l)(o)l 2+  /--&apos;5---COS0+ <lb/>~(c~l)*(0) c~l)(0)) <lb/> (DO <lb/> × sin 2 <lb/>t <lb/>2/&quot; ~(el (0)e 2 (0)) sm(/&apos;(Dot) + sin 0 ~.~e(t) <lb/>(40) <lb/></body>

			<page> 544 <lb/></page>

			<body> and <lb/> with <lb/> A.  C  Aguiar Pinto et al./Physica A 241 (1997) 535-548 <lb/> Al2(t)=e -i~°°t  f 2sin20 (cos0+ ~) <lb/> N(cll)*(O)c~l)(O))sin2(-~t) <lb/> t--rv-<lb/> sin 2 0 <lb/>(1)* <lb/>(l <lb/>] <lb/>F ~(cl (0)c 2 )(0)) sin(Fo)0t) -cos 0 ~(t) +  i.~(t) f, <lb/> (41) <lb/> ~k~&apos;(t)~--c(ll)*(O)c2  ~(O)cos(ro)0t)+  r---T-<lb/>(O)c:  (0))sin <lb/>t <lb/>~. cos0 + <lb/> c(ll)*(O)c~&apos;)(O)sin(Fo)ot). <lb/> (42) <lb/> (D o <lb/>(1 <lb/> Taking  c I )(0)=c~l)(0)E ~, we finally have <lb/>All(t) = ]cz(0)[ 2 + (¢11)(0)) 2 [l -t-sinOcos(Fo)ot) <lb/>1 &apos;~ <lb/>2sin0 ((2_~0)) <lb/>(_~2)] <lb/>+ _---=z--1 +cos0 <lb/>sin 2 <lb/>t <lb/>and <lb/>(43) <lb/> { <lb/> 2sin20 <lb/> A12(t)=(c(ll)(o))2e -i°J°t -cosOcos(ro)ot)+ ~ <lb/>-~o  sin2 <lb/>t <lb/>~ cos 0 + <lb/>sin(Fo0t) . <lb/>(44) <lb/> o)0 <lb/> Recently, Kim et al. [10] have proposed a simple measure of the degree of deco-<lb/>herence of subsystem given by the &apos;&quot;idempotency defect&quot; 6(t) of the reduced matrix, <lb/> 6(0 = Tr(A(t) - A2(t)). <lb/>(45) <lb/>For this present case we get that  6(0  = -2(1c2(0)14 +21c=(0)12(c(11)(0))2 +2(c11)(0)) 4-<lb/>[c2(0)12-(c(11)(0))2). Therefore, the subsystem is only a pure state when c11)(0)=0 <lb/>or c2(0)= 0, that means that the initial state of the identical particle system has to be <lb/>restricted to one Fock sub-space. <lb/>The average z component of the magnetization of the one-site fermionic model is, <lb/> (mz)(t)  = 212Al~(t) -(N)], <lb/>(46) <lb/>where (N)=(~P(0)]NI~(0)), the average number of fermions in the system. From <lb/>expansion (9) for the vector state of the system, we get <lb/>(N) = 2lee(0)] 2 + 2(ell)(0)) z . <lb/>(47) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> A.C. Aouiar Pinto et al. IPhysica A 241 (1997) 535-548 <lb/></note>

			<page> 545 <lb/></page>

			<body> Therefore, substituting Eq. (43) in Eq. (46), we obtain <lb/> (mz)(t)  = 22(c~1)(0)) 2 <lb/>[ <lb/>2sin0 ((2_~0) <lb/>) <lb/>(_Q~)] <lb/>x sin 0 cos(Fco0t) + ~ <lb/>1 + cos 0 <lb/>sin 2 <lb/>t , <lb/>(48) <lb/>As expected,  (mz)(t)  is a periodic function of the time with frequency Fco0, that is the <lb/>frequency of oscillation of the quantum system. <lb/>The operator m 2  - m 2 is a constant of motion since [H(t), m 2] = 0, for any instant t. <lb/>But the components of m vary with time, as we got in Eq. (48). We want to see now <lb/>the time evolution of the average of one component of m that is perpendicular to the <lb/>direction around which the external field is precessing. We choose to calculate  (mx)(t), <lb/>(mx)(t)  : Tr[2(a~a2 + at2al)~(t)] = 22 ~Alz(t). <lb/>(49) <lb/>From Eq. (44), we have that <lb/> (mx)(t) =  22(c(11)(0)) 2 <lb/>{ <lb/>2sinZ 0 ( 2&quot;W ) <lb/>(~-~) <lb/>× <lb/>-cos 0 cos(Fcoot) + ~ <lb/>-~o sin2 <lb/>t <lb/>cos COot <lb/>1 cos 0 + <lb/>sin(Fco0t) sin coot • <lb/>(50) <lb/>F <lb/>coo <lb/>The surprising result is that unless F =  p/q,  where p and q E 7/+, the function (50) is <lb/>not periodic, even though the quantum system is coupled to an external periodic field. <lb/>If for a given 0-angle where F =  p/q,  we change the angle 0, {mx)(t) is not any more <lb/>a periodic function. This surprising behavior comes from the global phase  e -i°)°t  in <lb/> Aj2(t)  (see Eq. (31)). <lb/>The norm of the magnetization is constant, but from Eqs. (48) and (49), we get <lb/>that, in general, the magnetization vector does not have a periodic motion. <lb/> 4. One-particle density matrix: Mixed states <lb/> Once the non-trivial geometric phases belong to states of the Fock sub-space N = 1, <lb/>in this section, we restrict ourselves to study the system in this particular sub-space. <lb/>We assume that at t =-0, the fermionic system is at thermal equilibrium with a heat <lb/>reservoir at temperature  fl(fl = 1/kT, k  is the Boltzmann constant and T is the absolute <lb/>temperature) in the presence of the external magnetic field. The quantum system, at <lb/>t---0 is described by the density operator <lb/>-n~&quot;~ <lb/>e-~&quot; <lb/>1); <lb/>~(0)-e --, lu%1);O)(u%l);O[ + <lb/>[u~ O)(u(21);O[, <lb/>(51) <lb/>Z <lb/>Z <lb/></body>

			<page> 546 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> .4.C. Aguiar Pinto et al./Physica A 241 (1997) 535-548 <lb/></note>

			<body> where <lb/> Z=e-~e&apos;, &apos;&apos; + e-~L&apos;._ &apos;&apos;. <lb/> At any other instant t, the density operator becomes <lb/> e-t~E&quot;&quot; <lb/>e -t~E&apos;2&apos;) l <lb/> ~(t)=  ---~--]ul&apos;)(t);O)(u]l)(t);O] + ~lu~ <lb/>)(t);O)(u~&apos;)(t);O] , <lb/> (52) <lb/>and [ull)(t); 0), i= 1,2, is the time evolution of lull); 0). The evolution of these vector <lb/>states are obtained directly from Eq. (9) by imposing the initial conditions: cl~)(0)= 1 <lb/>and c~.1)(0)=0 forj ¢ i. <lb/>Taking into account the results (28) and (31), a minor algebra gives us <lb/>f <lb/>(2~¢//) sin20 <lb/>(~)] <lb/> A,,(t)= ~ +  tanh(/~]),lB ) c2-~0 + -~0 -~-T-sin2 <lb/>t <lb/>(53) <lb/>and <lb/> AI2(t)=tanh([3[2lB)e-i&apos;°tsinO  [~ -~ (1 + cos0 (2o@0)) <lb/>(_~) <lb/>i <lb/>] <lb/>× sin 2 <lb/>t + ~-~ sin(F~o0t) . <lb/>(54) <lb/>The population of one-particle state also has an oscillatory behavior with frequency <lb/>og=F]~o0]. The population of the one-particle state completes one period before the <lb/>external field returns to its original value. Once  Al2(t)  has the global phase  e -i~°°t,  also <lb/>here, in general  (mx)(t)  is not a periodic function of time. <lb/>The temperature dependence on All(t) and Al2(t) determines the amplitude of <lb/>the oscillations, but plays no game in determining the frequency of the quantum <lb/>system. <lb/> 5. Conclusions <lb/> We obtained the full dynamics of one site self-interacting fermionic model in the <lb/>presence of an external magnetic field precessing around a fixed direction. Even though <lb/>this is a simple model, it is nice that it shows that the quantum system in the presence <lb/>of a periodic external coupling, has also a periodic behavior whose frequency can <lb/>be smaller, equal or bigger than the frequency of the external field. The inequality <lb/>depends on the sense of circular polarization of the external field and its geometry. <lb/>The one-particle properties of the identical particle system are gotten exactly, and we <lb/>explicitly consider them in the adiabatic regime. In the latter, the Berry&apos;s phase is <lb/>responsible for the frequency that characterizes the fermionic system be different from <lb/>the natural frequency of the system, that is given by the splitting of the energy level in <lb/>the presence of the external magnetic field. From Eq. (39) we see that the period of the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> A.C A#uiar Pinto et al. IPhysica A 241 (1997) 535-548 <lb/></note>

			<page> 547 <lb/></page>

			<body> system depends on the sign of co0. This happens because, while the geometric phase is <lb/>sensible to sign of c00, the dynamical phase (see Eq. (9)) is not. A consequence of this <lb/>observation is that this model in the presence of linearly polarized external magnetic <lb/>field do not get a Berry&apos;s phase [4,5]. <lb/>Not all physical quantities get a periodic behavior due to the coupling to the external <lb/>field. The components of magnetization perpendicular to the direction around which the <lb/>magnetic field is precessing, are periodic only in very particular situations. <lb/>The N-=-1 sub-sector discussed here is identical to the two-state problem. The cou-<lb/>pling constant U, of the interaction term of Hamiltonian (1), plays no role in the <lb/>matrix density oparator, once it is insensible to global phases and the sub-space N---2 <lb/>is unidimensional. <lb/>Certainly, these results have to be extended to the case with two fermionic space <lb/>sites, that is the model used to describe the optical properties of organic charge-transfer <lb/>salts [6]. The most interesting half-filling situation, certainly can be numerically de-<lb/>scribed, however we expect to derive the analytical dynamical evolution, for general <lb/>initial conditions, in the case of small hopping constant. For doing that, we will use <lb/>the present results and treat the hopping term as a perturbation to the two independent <lb/>one-site fermionic model. This approximation complemented with the weak-coupling <lb/>approximation, using the Fermi liquid theory [11], will give us a broader vision of <lb/>the dynamics of this physical model in the half-filling case. For this type of salts, <lb/>we are sure that the electronic states in the sub-spaces N = 1 and N --3 resemble the <lb/>equivalent states in the one-site fermionic model. The exact results to be derived in the <lb/>adiabatic regime, will allow us the possibility to look for quantities where the presence <lb/>of Berry&apos;s phase can be measured. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgements <lb/> A.C.A.P. and M.T.T. thank CNPq for total and partial financial support respectively. <lb/>R.B. and M.T.T. thank FINEP for partial financial support. M.T.T. thanks A.F.R. de <lb/>Toledo Piza for enlighten discussions. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] C.R. Willis, R.H. Picard, Phys. Rev. A 9 (1974) 1343; A 16 1625; M.C. Nemes, A.F.R. de Toledo Piza, <lb/>Physica A 137 (1986) 367. <lb/>[2] O. Kiibler, H.D. Zeh, Ann. Phys. 76 (1973) 405. <lb/>[3] M.C.D. Barrozo, M.T. Thomaz, A.F.R. de Toledo Piza, Am. J. Phys. 63 (1995) 463; M.T. Thomaz, <lb/>A.F.R. de Toledo Piza, Physica A 218 (1995) 237. <lb/>[4] M.T. Thomaz, Mod. Phys. Lett. B 10 (1996) 643. <lb/>[5] M.V. Berry, Proc. R. Soc. A 392 (1984) 45. <lb/>[6] M.E. Koslov, V.A. Ivanov, K. Yakushi, J. Phys: Condens. Matter 8 (1996) 1011 and references therein. <lb/>[7] M.D. Girardeau, J. Math. Phys. 21 (1980) 2365; W. Nolting, Quantentheorie des Magnetismus, Teubner <lb/>(1986), pp. 228. <lb/>[8l W. Dittrich, M. Reuter, Classical and Quantum Dynamics-from Classical Paths to Path Integrals, 2nd <lb/>Corrected and Enlarged ed., Springer, Berlin, 1994, ch. 28. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 548 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A.C. Aouiar Pinto et al./Physica A 241 (1997) 535-548 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> [9] J.J. Sakurai, Modem Quantum Mechanics, Addison-Wesley, Reading, MA, 1985, ch. 5. <lb/>[10] J.1. Kim, M.C. Nemes, A.F.R. de Toledo Piza, H.E. Borges, Phys. Rev. Lett. 77 (1996) 207. <lb/>[11] D. Pines, P. Nozibres, The Theory of Quantum Liquids, vol. I, W.A. Benjamin, New York, 1966. <lb/>E. Fradkin, Field Theories of Condensed Matter Systems, Addison-Wesley, Reading, MA, 1991. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
