<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Ideal Black Hole Gas <lb/>Larry L. Smalley <lb/>Department of Physics <lb/>University of Alabama in Huntsville <lb/>Huntsville,  AL  35899 <lb/>and <lb/>Space Science Laboratory <lb/>Marshall Space Flight Center,  AL  35812 <lb/> 7 August 1987 <lb/> (NASA-TB-107788) <lb/> I D E A L  BLACK HOLE G A S <lb/> (NASA. <lb/> Marshall S p a c e P l i q h t C e n t e r ) <lb/> 1 2 F <lb/> CSCL  0 3 8 <lb/> -4 <lb/> 1 <lb/> w <lb/> U n c l a s <lb/> G3/9Ct <lb/> 0213096 <lb/></front>

			<page> 2 <lb/></page>

			<body> The concept of primordial black hole creation in the early universe <lb/>has been a common theme in early cosmological scenarios.&apos; <lb/>letter we put forward the concept of a primordial black hole fluid with <lb/>intrinsic spin density and its consequence for supercluster-sized, i.e. <lb/>large-scale voids, and the missing mass question. <lb/>In this <lb/> 2 <lb/> 3 <lb/> It has been hypothesized that the mass of primordial black holes <lb/> -5 <lb/> range as far down as the Planckian mass limit of about 10 gm. On <lb/>the other extreme, primordial black holes with a mass of about  lo1&apos;  gm <lb/>should now be in the final stages of Hawking e~aporation.~ <lb/>time, it was thought that these latter black holes were candidates for <lb/>g-a-ray <lb/>and x-ray bursts. However it appears more likely that <lb/>these events are associated with the dynamics of solar remnants. <lb/>Thus it would be likely, within the original scenario, that either these <lb/>relic black holes were not created with sufficient mass to survive until <lb/>the present epoch or that they were just simply not created at all. <lb/>There is, however, the supposition that the lifetime of the inflationary <lb/>era is associated with the evaporation time  f o r  the primordial mini black <lb/>holes. <lb/>been created with masses consistent with the evaporation time scale. <lb/>What follows does not in principle conflict with this hypothesis although <lb/>it probably modifies the time scale somewhat and makes our scenario <lb/>more difficult.  On  the other hand, quantum mechanical arguments have <lb/>been put forth that suggest that the ultimate remnants of an evaporat-<lb/>At one <lb/> 5 <lb/> This would mean that the primordial black holes would have <lb/> 6 <lb/> ing black hole <lb/>a degenerate gas of Planck mass black holes called <lb/>planckons.which are stable against further decay due to the onset of <lb/>quantum stability of the &quot;lowest&quot; state of a black hole.&apos; <lb/>If this is the <lb/></body>

			<page> 3 <lb/></page>

			<body> case, our scenario would be easier to construct. However, the consis-<lb/>tency between the temperature of the evaporating mini black holes and <lb/>that of the planckons seems to contradict the principle of Hawking <lb/>evaporation and the existence of the planckons themselves. That is, <lb/>the planckons must be relatively cool, or they would interfere with the <lb/>big bang relic  3  K black body radiation. We do not know how this can <lb/>be overcome, but the thermodynamic description must somehow be <lb/>replaced with a quantum mechanical decay process especially in the <lb/>latter stages of evaporation. <lb/>from the planckian limit and thus well within the classical realm. <lb/>In either case, what we present is far <lb/>Recent observations supports the existence of significant large <lb/>scale structures8 with extent greater than 80 Mpc. It is in fact likely <lb/>that some of these objects may not even be visible, such as the recent-<lb/>ly discovered object in the constellation Leo which, it is conjectured, <lb/>supposedly lenses a quasar over 1.6 Gpc distant.&apos; The existence of <lb/>large scale voids with diameters of the order of 100 Mpc seem to be a <lb/>consistent with this structure. &quot; The general features of the universe <lb/>shows a vast network of clusters, filaments, and voids as is evident in <lb/> the analysis of the Shane-Wirtanen survey. l1 <lb/> general features is the question of the missing mass which is usually <lb/>attributed to massive neutrinos, axions, strings, l4 Higgs boson <lb/>decay, &quot; or other generally unspecified cool or even hot dark mass. <lb/>The existence of large quantities of dark matter seems to be indicted <lb/>for instance by infall in the Virgo cluster; &quot; however this dark matter <lb/>is probably not composed of baryons.  l8 <lb/> this missing mass be attributed to an ideal black hole gas with <lb/>Combined with these <lb/>12 <lb/>13 <lb/>16 <lb/>In this note we propose that <lb/></body>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<body> sufficient intrinsic spin density to avoid collapse and collocated with the <lb/>large scale voids. <lb/>In order to avoid confrontation with the  3  K black body back-<lb/>ground radiation field, which appears from experimental measurements <lb/>to be highly isotropic with quadrapole or higher multipole moments <lb/>consistent with zero,&quot; we assume that the temperature of objects within <lb/>the &quot;voids&quot; have an average temperature close to the background <lb/>blackbody temperature. <lb/>fluid which must be met: <lb/>librium with the back ground radiation field, and the surface tempera-<lb/>ture of the mini black holes must also be near  3  K. <lb/> This imposes two constraints on a black hole <lb/>the fluid temperature itself must be in equi-<lb/> 20 <lb/> We assume that during the early stages of the big bang, mini <lb/>black holes, with possibly some intrinsic spin will be formed. <lb/>ter the black holes can grow by accretion of other black holes. <lb/>the accretion process, the spin of the black holes will tend to increase <lb/>both through the union of individual spins and the absorption of the <lb/>relative orbital angular momentum of colliding black holes (and perhaps <lb/> ordinary matter). <lb/> &quot;his  tendency  for  the intrinsic spin of the daughter <lb/>black holes in black hole coalescence to increase is due to the random-<lb/>ness of both the initial spin distributions and the collisions between <lb/>pairs of blackholes. <lb/>intrinsic spin of the newly formed black holes after each union will <lb/>favor an increase in spin angular momentum of succeding daughters. <lb/>Thereaf-<lb/>During <lb/>This means that the random walk absorption of the <lb/>Consider a large scale, supercluster-sized void with diameter 100 <lb/>Mpc. <lb/>same as elsewhere in the universe with a density close to the critical <lb/>density  p <lb/> If we assume that the initial matter density in the void is the <lb/> 3 <lb/> =  loe2&apos;  gm/cm  ,  then the mass in the void would be <lb/> C <lb/></body>

			<page> 5 <lb/> </page>

			<body>50 <lb/> approximately 8.2 X 10  gm.  This assumption follows closely the <lb/>results of a recent measurement by Loh and Spillar of the mass density <lb/>of the universe based upon the redshift and fluxes of 1000 field galax-<lb/>ies. They find that the density of matter is 0.9  (+0.7,-0.5)  the critical <lb/>mass density at the 95% confidence level. <lb/>sensitive to any matter, dark or luminous.21 <lb/>Their method is suposedly <lb/>It is interesting to note <lb/>for later comparison that if all this matter had coalesced into a single <lb/>gigantic Schwarzschild black hole, it would have a radius 1.2 X <lb/> cm <lb/> (or about 40 kpc) with an &quot;internal density&quot; of about 1.1 X 10 <lb/> gm/cm  . <lb/> -19 <lb/> 3 <lb/>The surface temperature of a black hole is given by <lb/>4,22 <lb/> T  =  (8nMl-l  =  1.225 X lo1&apos; gm-K/M <lb/> (1) <lb/> where M is given in grams. <lb/>only approximate since the mass should be corrected for rotation. <lb/>(In what follows, this should be taken as <lb/> 18 <lb/> The temperature and mass could be iterated in what follows, but this <lb/>would not change our qualitative conclusion.) For a surface tempera-<lb/>ture of 3 K, the mass would be M3K  =  4.1 X 10l8 gm with radius R <lb/> 6.1 X 10-l&apos; cm with internal density  4 . 2  X 10 <lb/> = <lb/> 3K <lb/>gm/cm  .  Note that <lb/> 51 <lb/> 3 <lb/>this radius is larger than the radius of  a  nucleus. Thus  i f  all the mass <lb/>of the cluster were concentrated in such black holes, there would be <lb/> 2.0  X <lb/> of them in the black hole fluid! <lb/>The spin of matter should give rise to a repulsion (or bounce) <lb/>23 <lb/>during the &quot;final&quot; collapse of the universe towards a singularity. <lb/>The same would be true for any fluid with sufficient spin density. <lb/>Thus if the 3 K black holes have sufficient spin, they would be stable <lb/>against further coalescence. <lb/>growth problem even for stiff matter.24 <lb/>This repulsion then avoids the further <lb/>Suppose that the relaxation <lb/></body>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<body> process has continued until the black hole fluid has attained a density <lb/>comparable with nuclear density,  p  =  7 X 10 gm/cm  .  The 3  K  black <lb/>n <lb/>holes would have a relative separation of the order of 5.2 X 10 <lb/>a root mean square fluid velocity of 1.7 X 10 <lb/> 9 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 cm and <lb/>-17 cm/s. Such numbers <lb/>give a new meaning to the concept of &quot;stiff&quot; matter used below. <lb/>close-packed &quot;radius&quot; of the fluid would be about 30 X 1013 cm, and <lb/>The <lb/>thus the fluid could be contained in a region within the orbit of Jupi-<lb/>ter. This should be compared with the gigantic supercluster-sized <lb/>black hole mentioned above. Although such a large black hole is possi-<lb/>ble, the surface temperature is far below the background 3  K  black <lb/>body radiation and thus should give rise to some dectectable multipole <lb/>components to the uniform blackbody radiation. Experimental data, <lb/>however, seems to exclude this possibility19 although there is now <lb/>reasonable evidence that large black holes with mass of the order of <lb/> 1 0 6 &apos; 8 solar masses are contained in the nuclei of gala~ies.~&apos; Such <lb/>masses are consistent with previously observed mass distributions in <lb/>spiral galaxies providing the mass of the black hole is less than 10% of <lb/> the mass of the galaxy.  26  Within the context of our arguments  here, <lb/>the spin was not able to prevent coalescence. <lb/>We now investigate how spin can prevent the fluid from collapsing. <lb/>It can be shown that for a fluid with randomly oriented spin density, <lb/>the renormalized pressure and energy density is given by <lb/>2 2 <lb/> p&apos;  =  p  - 2 r G  s  /C <lb/>and <lb/>2 4 <lb/> p &apos;  =  p  - 2nG  s  /C <lb/></body>

			<page> 7 <lb/></page>

			<body> where G is the gravitationa constant, c is the speeu of light, and  s  is <lb/>the spin density. Let the renormalized density be of the order of <lb/>nuclear density and let the fluid be ideal. Then <lb/>p  - (2rG/cL)sL  =  pn kT/mgK <lb/> 2 <lb/> For a stiff fluid, p  =  pnc  ,  then <lb/>2 2 <lb/>pnc2  - (2nG/c  )s  =  pn  kT/m3K <lb/>and <lb/> 4 <lb/> 2 <lb/> s2  =  (pnc /2nG)[1  - kT/rn3Kc  ] <lb/> For  T  =  3K and  M3K  =  4.1 X 10l8 gm, we note that <lb/>kT/m3Kc2  =  1.1 X 10 -55 <lb/> (4) <lb/> ( 5 ) <lb/> (7) <lb/> and the spin density <lb/> s  =  1 . 2  x <lb/> gm/cm-s. <lb/> ( 8 ) <lb/> This is the spin density that gives an energy density comparible with <lb/>the nuclear energy density and thus prevents collapse of the fluid into <lb/> a larger black hole. <lb/>We note the &quot;fine tuning&quot; of the energy associated with the fluid <lb/>temperature to that of the rest mass energy of the fluid &quot;particles&quot; to <lb/> one part in  los5.  Such fine tuning between present epoch astronomical <lb/>data compared with intial conditions in the big bang has been noticed <lb/> consistently before. <lb/>Experimental evidence indicates that large compact objects are <lb/>contained in the cores of some galaxies. Thus galaxies (and necessarily <lb/>clusters) may have passed beyond fluid state  so  that they contain a <lb/>large black hole core or even a small black hole fluid core. This is <lb/>precisely what one would expect on the average for a system  so  finely <lb/>tuned. Thus  f o r  galaxies the initial state was also a black hole fluid; <lb/>however the &quot;particle&quot; mass of the fluid did not grow sufficiently to <lb/></body>

			<page> a <lb/></page>

			<body> avoid the Hawking evaporation up to the present epoch. <lb/>masses of the order of  10 <lb/> and source for the emission of energy by a quasar. <lb/>hole fluid is much more concentratdthen a single black hole of compara-<lb/>For particle <lb/> gm, we now have a possible mechanism <lb/>Since the black <lb/> 14-15 <lb/> ble mass, the size of the emission regions would no longer be a source <lb/>problem for quasar emission. If this hypothesis is correct, then some <lb/>quasars could be relatively close providing the particle masses were <lb/>large enough. For example, quasars with  z  &lt;  0.2 are known but are <lb/>rare compared with those with z  &gt;  1.  It is interesting to speculate that <lb/>the most spectacular event that we might observe would be the &quot;turning <lb/>on&quot; of a quasar, or even a galactic nucleus, e.g. the brightening by a <lb/>factor of two of  3C147  over a period of six years although this is <lb/>normally attributed to relativistic motion within the core.  27  We also <lb/>speculate that the spin axes of the black hole fluid would tend to align <lb/>over the accretion period period of the fluid since anti-alignment would <lb/>favor particle coalescence. <lb/>orbital angular momentum) of the black hole fJuid would then be S  = <lb/> The total spin (not including any overall <lb/> 70 <lb/>2 <lb/> V  s  =  1.4  X 10 <lb/> gm cm  /s.  Muradian has shown that astronomical <lb/> 3K <lb/> objects  seem  to group into two angular momentum, J, classes:28 J  =  fi <lb/> (M/m  ) 4 &apos; 3 <lb/> for planets and stars, and J  =  d  (M/mp)3/2 for galaxies and <lb/>clusters where m is the mass of a proton. For the  4/3  exponent, J  = <lb/> 1.1 x 10  gm  cm  / s ,  whereas for the 3/2 exponent, J is twelve orders <lb/>P <lb/>P <lb/> 72 <lb/>2 <lb/> of magnitude larger. Thus the total spin of the black hole fluid com-<lb/>pares well with the observed angular momentum relationship for planets <lb/>and stars. We speculate that this implies that local black hole evapora-<lb/>tion provides the seed perturbation for stars instead of galaxies where-<lb/>as the overall orbital motion is imparted to the galaxy (or cluster) as a <lb/></body>

			<page> 9 <lb/></page>

			<body> whole. <lb/> polarized medium (object) which could explain the directionality and <lb/>perhaps the strength of jets (radio lobes) from quasars. <lb/> Also  the fluid would represent in its mature stages a compact <lb/>Finally the overall consequence is that the dark matter in the <lb/>universe which is concentrated in the &apos;&apos;voids&quot; should be of the same <lb/>order of magnitude as visible matter in the universe. <lb/>this scenario, the universe would probably be closed. <lb/> On  the basis of <lb/></body>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. <lb/> R. D. Blandford  &amp;  K.  S .  Thorne, in General Relativity: an Ein-<lb/>stein Centenary Survey, (Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, <lb/> 1979), p. 494. <lb/>2. <lb/> J.  P. Ostriker  &amp;  P. J. E. Peebles, Astrophys. J.  186, 467 (1973); <lb/> J. R. Ipser  &amp;  R. H. Price, Astrophys. J.  216, 578 (1977); J.  R. <lb/> Thorstensen  &amp;  R. B. Partridge, Astrophys. J.  200, 527 (1975); B. <lb/> J.  Carr, Mon. Not. R. Astron. SOC. 181, 293 (1977). <lb/>3. <lb/> Ya.  B.  Zel&apos;Dovich, in General Relativity: an Einstein Centenary <lb/>Survey, (Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, 19791, p. 529. <lb/>S. W. Hawking, Nature 248,  30  (1974); Comm. Math. Phys. 43, <lb/> 189 (1975). <lb/> 4. <lb/> 5. D. D. Clayton, &quot;Principles of Stellar Evolution and Nucleosyn-<lb/>thesis,&quot; (McGraw-Hill, New York, 1968),  B. L. Webster  &amp;  P. <lb/> Murdin, Nature 235, 37 (1972); C.  T.  Bolton, Nat. Phys. Sci. <lb/> 240, 124 (1972). <lb/> 6. <lb/> J. G&amp;henian, E. Gunzig,  &amp;  I. Stengers, Found. Phys. 17, 585 <lb/> (1987). <lb/> 7. Y. Aharonov, A. Casher  &amp;  S.  Nussinov, Phys. Lett. B 191, 51 <lb/> (1987). <lb/> 8 . <lb/> V. de Lapporen, J. F. Geller  &amp;  J.  P. Huchar, J. Phys. 302, L1 <lb/> (1986). <lb/> 9. E. L. Turner, D. P. Schneider, B. F. Burke, J. N. Hewitt, G. <lb/> I. Langston, J. E. Gunn, C. R. Lawrence  &amp;  M. Schmidt, Nature, <lb/> 321, 142 (1986). <lb/>10. R. P. Kirshner, A. Oemler, P. L. Schechter  &amp; S.  A. Schectman, <lb/>Astrophys. J. Lett. 248,  L57  (1981). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 11 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> 11. M. Seldner, B. Sieber, E. J. Groth  &amp;  P. J. E. Peebles, Astron. <lb/> - J.  82,  249 (1977). <lb/> D. N. Schramm, Fermilab preprint, 86/70 ,1986 (unpublished). <lb/>12. <lb/>13. J. Preskill  &amp;  M. B. Wise, Phys. Lett. B  120,  127 (1983); L. F. <lb/> Abbott  &amp;  P. Sikivie, Phys. Lett. B  120,  133 (1983); and M. Dine <lb/> &amp;  W. Fischler Phys. Lett. B  120  137 (1983). <lb/>14. D. V. Nanopoulos  &amp;  K.  A.  Olive, Nature  302,  487 (1987). <lb/> 15. N. A. Batakis, &quot;On a possible resolution of the missing mass <lb/>problem,&quot; Cern preprint,  TH.3627-CERN,  June, 1983. <lb/> 16. K. A. Olive  &amp;  D. N. Schramm, Corn. Nucl. Phys.  15,  69 (1985); <lb/> H. R. Pagels, Comm. Nucl. Phys.  14,  289 (1985); and R. A. <lb/> Flores, &quot;Galaxy formation with Baryonic infall: Inplications for <lb/> galaxy dynamics, decaying dark matter and dark matter detection,&quot; <lb/>presented Theoretical Workshop on Cosmology and Particle Physics, <lb/>Lawrence Berkeley Laboratory, August 1986, preprint, CERN-<lb/>TH.4604/86, Nov. 1986 (unpublished). <lb/>17 J. R. Primack, preprint,  SLAC-PUB-3387,  1984 (unpublished). <lb/> 18. D. J.  Heygi  &amp;  K.  A .  Olive, Phys. Lett. B126,  28  (1983). <lb/> 19. V. N. Lukosh  &amp;  I. D. Novikov, &quot;Crucial cosmological observa-<lb/>tions,&quot; presented at the Symposium of the International Astronomi-<lb/>cal Union 124, 25-30 August 1986, Beijing (unpublished). A. A. <lb/> Klypin, M. V. Sazhin, D. P. Skullachev  &amp;  I. A. Strukov, Astron. <lb/>Zh. Lett. (to be published). <lb/> 20. S. W. Hawking  &amp;  N. Israel, in General Relativity: an Einstein <lb/>Centenary Sumey, (Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, <lb/>1979), p. 18; P. D. Nasel&apos;skii  &amp;  A. G. Polnerev, Sov. Astron.  29, <lb/> 487 (1985). <lb/> , <lb/> n <lb/>o <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 12 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>21. E.  D.  Loh  &amp;  E. J. Spillar, Astrophys. J, Lett. 307,  L1  (1986). <lb/>22. G. W. Gibbons, in General Relativity: an Einstein Centenary <lb/>Survey, (Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, 1979)  ,  p. 669. <lb/>23. F.  W. Hehl, P. von der Heyde  &amp;  G. D. Kerlick, Phys. Rev. D 10, <lb/> 1066 (1974); W. Kopczyhski, Phys. Lett. 39A, 219 (1972);  A. <lb/> Trautman, Nat. Phys. Sci.  242,  7  (1973); J.  Stewart  &amp;  P. HQjicek, <lb/>Nat.  Phys.  Sci.  244,  96 (1973); and  J.  Tafel, Phys. Lett. 45A, <lb/>241 (1973). <lb/>24. Ya.  B. <lb/> JETP 16, 1163 (1962). <lb/>25.  A. Dressler &quot;Stellar dynamics in nuclei of M31  &amp;  M32: Evidence <lb/> A <lb/> for massiv;? black holes,&quot; to be published in Astrophysical Journal, <lb/> 1988. <lb/>26.  L.  K.  Erickson,  S .  D. Gottesman,  &amp;  J. H. Hunter, Jr., Nature <lb/> 325,  779 (1987). <lb/>27.  R.  S.  Simon, A. C.  S .  Readhead, A. T. Moffet, P. N. Wilkinson, <lb/> B. Allen,  &amp;  B. F. Burke, Nature  302,  487 (1983). <lb/>28.  R.  M.  Muradian, Astrofizika 11,  237 (1975); Astrophys. Sp. Sci. <lb/> 69,  339 (1980). </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
