<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> DISTA-2007 <lb/> Balanced Superprojective Varieties <lb/> R. Catenacci  ®,H  , M. Debernardi  ®  , <lb/>P.A. Grassi  ®,H,K  , and D. Matessi  ® <lb/> ® DISTA, Universià del Piemonte Orientale, <lb/>Via Bellini 25/G, Alessandria, I-15100, Italy, <lb/> H INFN -Sezione di Torino-Gruppo collegato di Alessandria <lb/> K Centro Studi e Ricerche E. Fermi, Compendio Viminale, I-00184, Roma, Italy. <lb/> Abstract <lb/> We first review the definition of superprojective spaces from the functor-of-points <lb/>perspective. We derive the relation between superprojective spaces and supercosets <lb/>in the framework of the theory of sheaves. As an application of the geometry of <lb/>superprojective spaces, we extend Donaldson&apos;s definition of balanced manifolds to su-<lb/>permanifolds and we derive the new conditions of a balanced supermanifold. We apply <lb/>the construction to superpoints viewed as submanifolds of superprojective spaces. We <lb/>conclude with a list of open issues and interesting problems that can be addressed in <lb/>the present context. <lb/>catenacc@mfn.unipmn.it, marcod@mfn.unipmn.i, pgrassi@cern.ch, and matessi@mfn.unipmn.it <lb/> arXiv:0707.4246v1  [math-ph] 28 Jul 2007 <lb/></front>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> Supermanifolds are rather well-known in supersymmetric theories and in string theory. They <lb/>provide a very natural ground to understand the supersymmetry and supergravity from a <lb/>geometric point of view. Indeed, a supermanifold contains the anticommuting coordinates <lb/>which are needed to construct the superfields whose natural environment is the graded <lb/>algebras [2, 3]. However, the best way to understand the supermanifold is using the theory <lb/>of sheaves [3, 7]. In the present notes we review this approach and its usefulness in theoretical <lb/>physics and in particular in the last developments (twistor string theory [10] and pure spinor <lb/>string theory [11]). <lb/>In the case of twistor string theory, the target space is indeed the supermanifold CP <lb/> (3|4) <lb/> which can be described in two ways: as a supercoset of the supergroup P SU (4|4)/SU (3|4) <lb/>or as a quotient of the quadratic hypersurface in the superspace C <lb/> (4|4)  given by <lb/> α ˙ <lb/> α <lb/> |Z <lb/> α ˙ <lb/> α  | <lb/> 2  + <lb/> A <lb/> ¯ <lb/> ψ  A  ψ <lb/> A  = 1 <lb/>(1.1) <lb/>where (Z <lb/> α ˙ <lb/> α  , ψ <lb/> A  ) are the supertwistor coordinates. Obviously, this equation needs a clarifi-<lb/>cation: the commuting coordinates Z <lb/> α ˙ <lb/> α  cannot be numbers for the above equation to have <lb/>a non-trivial meaning. One way to interpret the above equation is using the sheaf point of <lb/>view where Z <lb/> α ˙ <lb/> α  , ψ <lb/> A  are the generators of a sheaf of supercommuting algebra over open sets <lb/>on CP <lb/> 3  . In this way, the supermanifold can be viewed as <lb/>(CP <lb/> 3  , O  CP <lb/> 3  (Z <lb/> α ˙ <lb/> α  , ψ <lb/> A  )) <lb/>(1.2) <lb/>and the equation (1.1) makes sense (see also [8]). The second way is using the functor of <lb/>point. This is a functor between the category of sets and the category of supermanifolds and, <lb/>as is well explained in [5] and the forthcoming sections, it assigns a point in a supermanifold <lb/>in terms of a set of coordinates. The easiest way to realize the functor of point is to map <lb/>a superspace into a supermanifold and describe the latter in terms of points identified by <lb/>morphisms. Concretely, this amount to choose a graded algebra with N generators and <lb/>represent the generators of the sheaf O  CP <lb/> 3  (Z <lb/> α ˙ <lb/> α  , ψ <lb/> A  ) in terms of them. Then inserting this <lb/>decomposition in (1.1), one gets a set of numerical equations for the coefficients of the <lb/>decomposition and they can be solved or studied by the conventional means of algebraic <lb/>geometry. <lb/>Of course the hypersurface (1.1) is one example of manifold that can be realized in terms <lb/>of the generators of O  CP <lb/> 3  (Z <lb/> α ˙ <lb/> α  , ψ <lb/> A  ) and that can be studied by means of the functor of <lb/>points. Notice that also from the supercoset point of view, the technique of the functor <lb/>of point gives us a representation of the supercoset in terms of the generators of a sheaf. <lb/>Indeed, by multiplying supermatrices (whose entries are the generators of the sheaf) one <lb/>finds that the entries cannot be numbers and they have to be promoted to the generator <lb/>of a sheaf. Therefore the multiplication between matrices and the group multiplication of a <lb/>supergroup has to be understood as a morphism of a ringed space. This point of view has <lb/>been emphasized by Manin [3] and recently by [5, 6]. We provide here a more elementary <lb/>explanation of the role of functor-of-point in the case of supergroup and supercosets. The <lb/>purpose of this is to use the functor-of-point to define the superprojective spaces (as CP <lb/> (3|4) <lb/></body>

			<page> 1 <lb/></page>

			<body> above) and to prove the isomorphism with the supercoset point-of-view as in the purely <lb/>bosonic case. <lb/>In the second part of the paper, we develop two applications for superprojective spaces. <lb/>Following the recent analysis of Donaldson [13] on balanced manifold, we extend his definition <lb/>to supermanifolds. One ingredient is the definition of balanced submanifold of a projective <lb/>space (for example a point or a line). For that we extend the integral equation given in [13] <lb/>to an integration on the supermanifold. The definition of the integral of a superform in a <lb/>supermanifold is not an obvious extension since a regularization is needed. This can be done <lb/>using the projection forms as illustrated in [17] and discussed in more detail in [18]. We <lb/>briefly discuss this point in the text, but we refer to a forthcoming publication for a more <lb/>detailed account [21]. <lb/>After discussing the general theory, we provided a simple example of the embedding of <lb/> P <lb/> 1|2  into the superprojective space P <lb/> 2m−1|2m  of sections H <lb/> 0  (P <lb/> 1|2  , L <lb/> ⊗m  ) where L <lb/> ⊗m  is the m-<lb/>power of a line bundle L over P <lb/> 1|2  . In this case both the base manifold and the sections <lb/> P <lb/> 2m−1|2m  are super-Calabi-Yau spaces (in the sense that they are super-Kähler spaces with <lb/>vanishing Ricci tensor and an holomorphic top form Ω  CY  ) and for those there is a natural <lb/>measure for integrating superforms provided by Ω  CY  ∧ ¯ <lb/>Ω  CY  . It is shown that there are <lb/>two types of conditions emerging from the extension of the Donaldson equations to the <lb/>supermanifold case and therefore this restricts the number of supermanifolds that can be <lb/>balanced subvarieties of superprojective spaces. In generalizing the analysis of Donaldson <lb/>we have taken into account the extension of the Kodaira embedding theorem discussed in <lb/>[19]. <lb/>The second application is to consider a set of points C <lb/> 0|N  immersed in the superprojective <lb/>space P <lb/> 1|N  as a subvariety. In this case we computed explicitly the general expression for <lb/>the case C <lb/> 0|2  embedded into P <lb/> 1|2  and we found the condition for the balancing of a point. <lb/>We found also how the supermanifold case generalizes the classical embedding condition and <lb/>we argued how one can recover the classical balancing in addition to the requirements on <lb/>the parameter of the superembeddings. We showed that this is tied to the choice of the <lb/>integration measure for superforms. <lb/>A concluding remark: we have not explored all possible implications of our extension <lb/>neither we have discussed the relation with the stability of points in the sense of Geometric <lb/>Invariant Theory (GIT) [12] Nevertheless we have found rather interesting that some appli-<lb/>cations admit a non trivial generalization of the usual geometric setting. These results open <lb/>new questions about the geometry of sheaves and their functor-of-point interpretation. <lb/>The paper is organized as follows: in sec. 2 we define the supermanifolds form a sheaf <lb/>theory point of view. We discuss the basic architecture and the set of morphisms. In sec. 3 <lb/>we define superprojective spaces and in sec. 4 we provide a functor-of-point interpretation <lb/>Part of this material is summary of notes [5]. This allows us to use the local coordinates <lb/>and to define the concept of a point in a supermanifold. In sec. 5, we study supergroups <lb/>and superdeterminant (Berezinians) from the functor-of -point perspective needed to see the <lb/>definition of superprojective space as supercosets of supergroups discussed in sec. 5.1. In <lb/>sec. 6, we extend the construction of Donaldson to supermanifold and we define balanced <lb/>supermanifolds. Finally, in sec. 6.2 we discuss the balancing of points in superprojective <lb/>spaces. <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body> 2 Supermanifolds <lb/> 2.1 Definitions <lb/> A super-commutative ring is a Z  2  -graded ring A = A  0  ⊕ A  1  such that if i, j ∈ Z  2  , then <lb/> a  i  a  j  ∈ A  i+j  and a  i  a  j  = (−1) <lb/> i+j  a  j  a  i  , where a  k  ∈ A  k  . Elements in A  0  (resp. A  1  ) are called <lb/> even (resp. odd). <lb/> A super-space is a super-ringed space such that the stalks are local super-commutative <lb/>rings (Manin-Varadarajan). Since the odd elements are nilpotent, this reduces to require <lb/>that the even component reduces to a local commutative ring. <lb/>A super-domain U <lb/> p|q  is the super-ringed space <lb/> U <lb/> p  , C <lb/> ∞p|q <lb/> , where U <lb/> p  ⊆ R <lb/> p  is open and <lb/> C <lb/> ∞p|q  is the sheaf of super-commutative rings given by: <lb/> V → C <lb/> ∞  (V ) <lb/> θ <lb/> 1  , θ <lb/> 2  , ..., θ <lb/> q <lb/> , <lb/> (2.1) <lb/>where V ⊆ U <lb/> p  is and θ <lb/> 1  , θ <lb/> 2  , ..., θ <lb/> q  are generators of a Grassmann algebra. The grading is <lb/>the natural grading in even and odd elements. The notation is taken from [4] and from the <lb/>notes [5]. <lb/>Every element of C <lb/> ∞p|q  (V ) may be written as <lb/> I  f  I  θ <lb/> I  , where I is a multi-index. A super-<lb/>manifold of dimension p|q is a super-ringed space locally isomorphic, as a ringed space, to <lb/> R <lb/> p|q  . The coordinates x  i  of R <lb/> p  are called the even coordinates (or bosonic), while the coor-<lb/>dinates θ <lb/> j  are called the odd coordinates (or fermionic). We will denote by (M, O  M  ) the su-<lb/>permanifold whose underlying topological space is M and whose sheaf of super-commutative <lb/>rings is O  M  . <lb/>To a section s of O  M  on an open set containing x one may associate the value of s in x <lb/> as the unique real number s <lb/> ∼  (x) such that s − s <lb/> ∼  (x) is not invertible on every neighborhood <lb/>of x. The sheaf of algebras O <lb/> ∼  , whose sections are the functions s <lb/> ∼  , defines the structure of <lb/>a differentiable manifold on M , called the reduced manifold and denoted M <lb/> ∼  . <lb/> 2.2 Morphisms. <lb/> In order to understand the structure of supermanifolds it is useful to study their morphisms. <lb/>Here we describe how a morphism of supermanifolds looks like locally. A morphism ψ from <lb/>(X, O  X  ) to (Y, O  Y  ) is given by a smooth map map ψ <lb/> ∼  from X <lb/> ∼  to Y <lb/> ∼  together with a sheaf <lb/>map: <lb/> ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> V  : O  Y  (V ) −→ O  X  (ψ <lb/> −1  (V )), <lb/>(2.2) <lb/>where V is open in Y . The homomorphisms ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> V  must commute with the restrictions and <lb/>they must be compatible with the super-ring structure. Moreover they satisfy <lb/> ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> V  (s) <lb/> ∼  = s <lb/> ∼  • ψ <lb/> ∼  . <lb/> We illustrate this with an example taken from [5]. Given M = R <lb/> 1|2  , we describe a <lb/>morphism ψ of M into itself such that ψ <lb/> ∼  is the identity. Let ψ <lb/>  *  be the pull-back map <lb/>defined previously. We denote {t, θ <lb/> 1  , θ <lb/> 2  } the coordinates on M , where t can be interpreted <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body> both as the coordinate on M <lb/> ∼  = R or as an even section of the sheaf. Since the sheaf map <lb/>must be compatible with the Z  2  −grading, ψ <lb/>  *  t is an even section and (ψ <lb/>  *  t) <lb/> ∼  = t. Then, <lb/> ψ <lb/>  *  (t) = t + f (t)θ <lb/> 1  θ <lb/> 2  . <lb/> Similarly, <lb/> ψ <lb/>  *  (θ <lb/> j  ) = g  j  (t)θ <lb/> 1  + h  j  (t)θ <lb/> 2  . <lb/> It is important to observe that this defines uniquely ψ <lb/>  *  for sections of the form <lb/> a + b  1  θ <lb/> 1  + b  2  θ <lb/> 2  . <lb/> where a, b  1  and b  2  are polynomials in t. It is therefore reasonable to expect that ψ <lb/>  *  is <lb/>uniquely defined. Let us take, for simplicity, the case where <lb/> ψ <lb/>  *  (t) = t + θ <lb/> 1  θ <lb/> 2  , <lb/> and <lb/> ψ <lb/>  *  (θ <lb/> j  ) = θ <lb/> j  . <lb/> (2.3) <lb/>If g is a smooth function of t on an open set U ⊆ R, we want to define ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> U  (g). <lb/>Let us expand g(t + θ <lb/> 1  θ <lb/> 2  ) as a formal Taylor series: <lb/> g(t + θ <lb/> 1  θ <lb/> 2  ) = g(t) + g <lb/>  (t)θ <lb/> 1  θ <lb/> 2  . <lb/> The series does not continue because (θ <lb/> 1  θ <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> 2  = 0. Then, we define <lb/> ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> U  (g) = g(t) + g <lb/>  (t)θ <lb/> 1  θ <lb/> 2  . <lb/> If <lb/> g = g  0  + g  1  θ <lb/> 1  + g  2  θ <lb/> 2  + g  12  θ <lb/> 1  θ <lb/> 2  , <lb/> then we must define <lb/> ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> U  (g) = ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> U  (g  0  ) + ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> U  (g  1  )θ <lb/> 1  + ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> U  (g  2  )θ <lb/> 2  + ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> U  (g  12  )θ <lb/> 1  θ <lb/> 2  . <lb/> where we have used (2.3). The family (ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> U  ) then defines a morphism between R <lb/> 1|2  and itself. <lb/>This method can be extended to the general case. <lb/>Let us recall some fundamental local properties of morphisms. A morphism ψ between <lb/>two super-domains U <lb/> p|q  and V <lb/> r|s  is given by a smooth map ψ <lb/> ∼  : U → V and a homomorphism <lb/>of super-algebras <lb/> ψ <lb/>  *  : C <lb/> ∞ r|s  (V ) → C <lb/> ∞ p|q  (U ). <lb/>It must satisfy the following properties: <lb/> • If t = (t  1  , . . . , t  r  ) are coordinates on V <lb/> r  , each component t  j  can also be interpreted as a <lb/>section of C <lb/> ∞ r|s  (V ). If f  i  = ψ <lb/>  *  (t  i  ), then f  i  is an even element of the algebra C <lb/> ∞ p|q  (U ). <lb/> • The smooth map ψ <lb/> ∼  : U → V must be ψ <lb/> ∼  = (f <lb/> ∼ <lb/> 1  , . . . , f <lb/> ∼ <lb/> r  ), where the f <lb/> ∼ <lb/> i  are the values <lb/>of the even elements above. <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body> • If θ  j  is a generator of C <lb/> ∞ r|s  (V ), then g  j  = ψ <lb/>  *  (θ  j  ) is an odd element of the algebra <lb/> C <lb/> ∞ p|q  (U ). <lb/>The following fundamental theorem (see for example [5]) gives a local characterization of <lb/>morphisms: <lb/> Theorem 1 [Structure of morphisms] Suppose φ : U → V is a smooth map and f  i  , g  j  , <lb/>with i = 1, . . . , r, j = 1, . . . , s, are given elements of C <lb/> ∞ p|q  (U ), with f  i  even, g  j  odd and <lb/>satisfying φ = (f <lb/> ∼ <lb/> 1  , . . . , f <lb/> ∼ <lb/> r  ). Then there exists a unique morphism ψ : U <lb/> p|q  → V <lb/> r|s  with <lb/> ψ <lb/> ∼  = φ and ψ <lb/>  *  (t  i  ) = f  i  and ψ <lb/>  *  (θ  j  ) = g  j  . <lb/> Remark. If V is a vector bundle over a smooth manifold M , then we can form its exterior <lb/>bundle E = Λ <lb/> max  V . Let O(E) be the sheaf of sections of E. Then, locally on M , the <lb/>sheaf is isomorphic to U <lb/> p|q  where p = dim(M ) and q = rank(V ). This is clearly true <lb/>whenever V is restricted to some open subset of M over which it is trivial. Consequently, <lb/>(M, O(E)) is a super-manifold, denoted by E <lb/>  . Every super-manifold is locally isomorphic <lb/>to a super-manifold of the form E <lb/>  . However we should note the important fact that E <lb/>  , as a <lb/>supermanifold, has many more morphisms than the corresponding exterior bundle E, because <lb/>of the possibility that the even and odd coordinates can be mixed under transformations. <lb/>This is well illustrated by the previous simple example. Another way to say the same thing <lb/>is that there are less morphisms which preserve the bundle structure than morphisms which <lb/>preserve the super-manifold structure. <lb/> 2.3 Local charts on supermanifolds <lb/> We describe how supermanifolds can be constructed by patching local charts. Let X = <lb/> i  X  i <lb/> be a topological space, with {X  i  } open, and let O  i  be a sheaf of rings on X  i  , for each i. <lb/> We write (see [4]) X  ij  = X  i  ∩ X  j  , X  ijk  = X  i  ∩ X  j  ∩ X  k  , and so on. We now introduce <lb/>isomorphisms of sheaves which represent the &quot; coordinate changes &quot; on our super-manifold. <lb/>They allow us to glue the single pieces to get the final supermanifold. Let <lb/> f  ij  : <lb/> X  ji  , O  j  |  X  ji <lb/> −→ <lb/> X  ij  , O  i  |  X  ij <lb/> be an isomorphisms of sheaves with <lb/> f <lb/> ∼ <lb/> ij  = Id. <lb/> This means that these maps represent differentiable coordinate changes on the underlying <lb/>manifold. <lb/>To say that we glue the ringed spaces (X  i  , O  i  ) through the f  ij  means that we are con-<lb/>structing a sheaf of rings O on X and for each i a sheaf isomorphism <lb/> f  i  : (X  i  , O|  X  i  ) −→ (X  i  , O  i  ), <lb/> f <lb/> ∼ <lb/> i  = Id  X  i <lb/> such that <lb/> f  ij  = f  i  f <lb/> −1 <lb/> j  , <lb/></body>

			<page> 5 <lb/></page>

			<body> for all i and j. <lb/> The following usual cocycle conditions are necessary and sufficient for the existence of <lb/>the sheaf O: <lb/> i. f  ii  = Id on O  i  ; <lb/> ii. f  ij  f  ji  = Id on O  i  |  X  i  ; <lb/> iii. f  ij  f  jk  f  ki  = Id on O  i  |  X  ijk  . <lb/> 3 Projective superspaces <lb/> Due to their importance in physical applications we now give a detailed description of projec-<lb/>tive superspaces. One can work either on R or on C, but we choose to stay on C. Let X be the <lb/>complex projective space of dimension n. The super-projective space will be called Y . The <lb/>homogeneous coordinates are {z  i  }. Let us consider the underlying topological space as X, <lb/> and let us construct the sheaf of super-commutative rings on it. For any open subset V ⊆ X <lb/> we denote by V <lb/>  its preimage in C <lb/> n+1  \{0}. Then, let us define A (V <lb/>  ) = H (V <lb/>  ) [θ <lb/> 1  , θ <lb/> 2  , ..., θ <lb/> q  ], <lb/>where H (V <lb/>  ) is the algebra of holomorphic functions on V <lb/>  and {θ <lb/> 1  , θ <lb/> 2  , ..., θ <lb/> q  } are the odd <lb/>generators of a Grassmann algebra. C <lb/>  *  acts on this super-algebra by: <lb/> t : <lb/> I <lb/> f  I  (z) θ <lb/> I  −→ <lb/> I <lb/> t <lb/> −|I|  f  I <lb/> t <lb/> −1  z <lb/> θ <lb/> I  . <lb/> (3.1) <lb/>The super-projective space has a ring over V given by: <lb/> O  Y  (V ) = A (V <lb/>  ) <lb/> C  * <lb/> which is the subalgebra of elements invariant by this action. This is the formal definition of <lb/>a projective superspace (see for example [5]), however we would like to construct the same <lb/>space more explicitly from gluing different superdomains as in sec. 2.3. <lb/>Let X  i  be the open set where the coordinate z  i  does not vanish. Then the super-<lb/>commutative ring O  Y  (X  i  ) is generated by elements of the type <lb/> f  0 <lb/> z  0 <lb/> z  i <lb/> , . . . , <lb/>z  i−1 <lb/> z  i <lb/> , <lb/>z  i+1 <lb/> z  i <lb/> , . . . , <lb/>z  n <lb/> z  i <lb/> , f  r <lb/> z  0 <lb/> z  i <lb/> , ..., <lb/>z  i−1 <lb/> z  i <lb/> , <lb/>z  i+1 <lb/> z  i <lb/> , ..., <lb/>z  n <lb/> z  i <lb/> θ <lb/> r <lb/> z  i <lb/> , r = 1, . . . , q . <lb/> In fact, to be invariant with respect to the action of C <lb/>  *  , the functions f  I  in equation (3.1) <lb/>must be homogeneous of degree −|I|. Then, it is obvious that the only coordinate we can <lb/>divide by, on X  i  , is z  i  : all functions f  I  are of degree −|I| and holomorphic on X  i  . If we put, <lb/>on X  i  , for l  = i, Ξ <lb/> (i) <lb/> l  = <lb/> z  l <lb/> z  i <lb/> and Θ <lb/> (i) <lb/> r  = <lb/> θ  r <lb/> z  i <lb/> , then O  Y  (X  i  ) is generated, as a super-commutative <lb/>ring, by the objects of the form <lb/> F <lb/> (i) <lb/>0 <lb/> Ξ <lb/> (i) <lb/>0  , Ξ <lb/> (i) <lb/>1  , ..., Ξ <lb/> (i) <lb/> i−1  , Ξ <lb/> (i) <lb/> i+1  , ..., Ξ <lb/> (i) <lb/> n <lb/> , F <lb/> (i) <lb/> a <lb/> Ξ <lb/> (i) <lb/>0  , Ξ <lb/> (i) <lb/>1  , ..., Ξ <lb/> (i) <lb/> i−1  , Ξ <lb/> (i) <lb/> i+1  , ..., Ξ <lb/> (i) <lb/> n <lb/> Θ <lb/> (i) <lb/> a  , <lb/> where F <lb/> (i) <lb/>0  and the F <lb/> (i) <lb/> a  &apos;s are analytic functions on C <lb/> n  . In order to avoid confusion we have <lb/>put the index i in parenthesis: it just denotes the fact that we are defining objects over the <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body> local chart X  i  . In the following, for convenience in the notation, we also adopt the convention <lb/>that Ξ <lb/> (i) <lb/> i  = 1 for all i. <lb/> To explain the &quot; coordinate change &quot; morphisms let us recall what happens in the ordinary <lb/>complex projective spaces. <lb/>If we consider P <lb/> n  (C) with the ordinary complex analytic structure, then, over the affine <lb/>open set X  i  where z  i  = 0, we can define the affine coordinates w <lb/> (i) <lb/> a  = <lb/> za <lb/>z  i <lb/> , a  = i. The sheaf of <lb/>rings over X  i  is H(X  i  ), the ring of analytic functions over X  i  . Every element f of H(X  i  ) can <lb/>also be expressed as a function in homogeneous coordinates F (z  0  , z  1  , ..., z  n  ). Two functions, <lb/> F <lb/> (i)  on X  i  and F <lb/> (j)  on X  j  , represent &quot; the same function &quot; on the intersection X  i  ∩X  j  if, when <lb/>expressed in homogeneous coordinates, they give the same function F . The isomorphism <lb/>between (X  i  ∩ X  j  , H(X  i  )|  X  j  ) and (X  j  ∩ X  i  , H(X  j  )|  X  i  ) sends F <lb/> (i)  to F <lb/> (j)  , i.e. expresses F <lb/> (i) <lb/> with respect to the affine coordinates w <lb/> (j) <lb/> a  = <lb/> za <lb/>z  j <lb/> . The total manifold is obtained by gluing <lb/>these domains X  i  as in the previous section. <lb/>We now return to considering the super-projective spaces. We have the two sheaves <lb/> O  Y  (X  i  )|  X  j  and O  Y  (X  j  )|  X  i  . In the same way as before, we have the morphisms given by <lb/>the &quot; coordinate changes &quot; . So, on X  i  ∩ X  j  , the isomorphism simply affirms the equivalence <lb/>between the objects of the super-commutative ring expressed either by the first system of <lb/>affine coordinates, or by the second one. So for instance we have that Ξ <lb/> (j) <lb/> l  = <lb/> z  l <lb/> z  j <lb/> and Θ <lb/> (j) <lb/> r  = <lb/> θ  r <lb/> z  j <lb/> can be also expressed as <lb/>Ξ <lb/> (j) <lb/> l  = <lb/>Ξ <lb/> (i) <lb/> l <lb/> Ξ <lb/> (i) <lb/> j <lb/> , Θ <lb/> (j) <lb/> r  = <lb/>Θ <lb/> (i) <lb/> r <lb/> Ξ <lb/> (i) <lb/> j <lb/> . <lb/> Which, in the language used in the previous section, means that the morphism ψ  ji  gluing <lb/>(X  i  ∩ X  j  , O  Y  (X  i  )|  X  j  ) and (X  j  ∩ X  i  , O  Y  (X  j  )|  X  i  ) is such that ψ <lb/> ∼ <lb/> ji  is the usual change of <lb/>coordinates map on projective space and <lb/> ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> ji  (Ξ <lb/> (j) <lb/> l  ) = <lb/>Ξ <lb/> (i) <lb/> l <lb/> Ξ <lb/> (i) <lb/> j <lb/> , ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> ji  (Θ <lb/> (j) <lb/> r  ) = <lb/>Θ <lb/> (i) <lb/> r <lb/> Ξ <lb/> (i) <lb/> j <lb/> The super-manifold is obtained by observing that the coordinate changes satisfy the <lb/>cocycle conditions of the previous section. <lb/> 4 The functor of points <lb/> We now wish to explain how the physicists&apos; interpretation of the z  i  &apos;s as &quot; even coordinates &quot; <lb/>and the θ  j  &apos;s as &quot; odd coordinates &quot; can be obtained from the &quot; super-ringed space &quot; interpreta-<lb/>tion of supermanifolds through the concept of &quot; functor of points &quot; . The key to understanding <lb/>this is Theorem 1. <lb/>Given two supermanifolds X and S, the S-points of X (or the points of X parametrized <lb/>by S) are given by the set <lb/> X(S) = Hom(S, X) = {set of morphisms S → X} . <lb/>X is the supermanifold we want to describe and S is the model on which we base the <lb/>description of X. Changing S modifies the description of X. The functor which associates S <lb/></body>

			<page> 7 <lb/></page>

			<body> to X(S) is a functor between the category of supermanifolds and the category of sets (which <lb/>are the &quot; points &quot; of the supermanifolds). See also [6] for more details. <lb/>Let us interpret this in the case when X = V <lb/> r|s  and S = U <lb/> p|q  . According to Theorem 1, <lb/>a morphism ψ ∈ Hom(U <lb/> p|q  , V <lb/> r|s  ) is uniquely determined by a choice of r even sections and s <lb/> odd sections of C <lb/> ∞ p|q  (U ), i.e. morphisms are in one to one correspondence with (r+s)-tuples <lb/>(f  1  , . . . , f  r  , g  1  , . . . , g  s  ), where f  j  &apos;s are even and g  j  &apos;s are odd in the algebra C <lb/> ∞ p|q  (U ). If we <lb/>denote by Γ <lb/> 0 <lb/> q  (U ) and Γ <lb/> 1 <lb/> q  (U ) respectively the set of even and odd sections of C <lb/> ∞ p|q  (U ), then <lb/>the above fact is expressed as <lb/>Hom(U <lb/> p|q  , V <lb/> r|s  ) = (Γ <lb/> 0 <lb/> q  (U )) <lb/> r  × (Γ <lb/> 1 <lb/> q  (U )) <lb/> s  . <lb/> (4.1) <lb/>The sub-index q denotes the &quot; number of odd generators &quot; of the algebra we are considering. <lb/>In particular, if S = R <lb/> 0|q  , then <lb/>Hom(R <lb/> 0|q  , V <lb/> r|s  ) = (Γ <lb/> 0 <lb/> q  ) <lb/> r  × (Γ <lb/> 1 <lb/> q  ) <lb/> s <lb/> (4.2) <lb/>where (Γ <lb/> 0 <lb/> q  ) and (Γ <lb/> 1 <lb/> q  ) represent the even and the odd component of a Grassmann algebra with <lb/> q generators, respectively. <lb/>One could say that the &quot; super-ringed space &quot; structure of X encodes the information of <lb/>how the even and odd coordinates (z, θ) glue together, but independently of the number of <lb/>generators of the underlying super-algebra. The number of generators (q in the above case) <lb/>can be fixed by taking a supermanifold S and constructing Hom(S, X). We will see some <lb/>examples shortly. <lb/> 4.1 Coordinates of Superprojective Spaces. <lb/> We are going to consider the superprojective space <lb/> P <lb/> p|q  = (P <lb/> p  , O  P  p  ) <lb/>(4.3) <lb/>which is defined as in section 3 as a ringed space and dim(O  P  p  ) = q. We want to describe the <lb/>set of C <lb/> 0|N  − points of this space. The space C <lb/> 0|N  can be viewed as the super-commutative <lb/>ring O  C  0  over the single point (denoted by P ) of the corresponding topological space C <lb/> 0  and <lb/>can be identified precisely with the Grassmann algebra with N generators that we denote <lb/>by Γ  N  . <lb/>Let&apos;s consider the open subsets {X  i  }, i = 0, 1, 2, ..., p, of P <lb/> p  where z  i  = 0, with the <lb/>corresponding super-commutative ring O  X  i  . A morphism between C <lb/> 0|N  and (X  i  , O  X  i  ) is <lb/>completely defined by the pull-back for each generator of the ring O  X  i <lb/> τ  (i)  ∈ Hom(C <lb/> 0|N  , (X  i  , O  X  i  )) , <lb/>τ <lb/>  * <lb/> (i)  : O  X  i  → O  C  0 <lb/> (4.4) <lb/>where O  C  0  = C[θ  1  , ..., θ  N  ] = Γ  N  . To clarify this point, we take the generators of O  X  i  : <lb/>Θ <lb/> (i) <lb/> j  , j = 1, . . . , q and the affine coordinates Ξ <lb/> (i) <lb/> j  on X  i  and we map into C[θ  1  , ..., θ  N  ] as <lb/>follows <lb/> τ <lb/>  * <lb/> (i)  (Ξ <lb/> (i) <lb/> j  ) = f <lb/> (i) <lb/> j <lb/> j = 1, . . . , p <lb/> (4.5) <lb/> τ <lb/>  * <lb/> (i)  (Θ <lb/> (i) <lb/> r  ) = η <lb/> (i) <lb/> r <lb/> r = 1, . . . , q <lb/></body>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<body> where the f <lb/> (i) <lb/> j  (resp. η <lb/> (i) <lb/> r  ) are even (resp. odd) elements of the Grassmann algebra Γ  N  . It is <lb/>clear that τ <lb/> ∼ <lb/> (i)  (P ) = ((f <lb/> (i) <lb/>1  ) <lb/> ∼  , . . . , (f <lb/> (i) <lb/> p  ) <lb/> ∼  ). We therefore see that for every i, Hom(C <lb/> 0|N  , (X  i  , O  X  i  )) <lb/>can be identified with a copy of (Γ <lb/> 0 <lb/> N  ) <lb/> p  × (Γ <lb/> 1 <lb/> N  ) <lb/> q  . <lb/>To obtain all the possible morphisms from C <lb/> 0|N  to P <lb/> p|q  , we must take into account that the <lb/>latter is built by &quot; gluing &quot; super-domains by means of the &quot; coordinate change isomorphisms &quot; , <lb/>this corresponds to gluing together all copies of (Γ <lb/> 0 <lb/> N  ) <lb/> p  × (Γ <lb/> 1 <lb/> N  ) <lb/> q  for all possible i&apos;s. Since a <lb/>morphism in Hom(C <lb/> 0|N  , P <lb/> p|q  ) must be compatible with the restriction maps, it must commute <lb/>with the &quot; coordinate changes &quot; . This means that, if τ <lb/>  * <lb/> (j)  is the pull-back of a morphism to <lb/> X  j  , and ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> ij  : O  X  j  |  X  i  ∩X  j  −→ O  X  i  |  X  i  ∩X  j  is the isomorphism which represents &quot; coordinate <lb/>changes &quot; , then <lb/> τ <lb/>  * <lb/> (j)  = τ <lb/>  * <lb/> (i)  • ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> ij  . <lb/> This then induces a map between subsets of the i-th and j-th copy of (Γ <lb/> 0 <lb/> N  ) <lb/> p  × (Γ <lb/> 1 <lb/> N  ) <lb/> q  as <lb/>follows <lb/>(f <lb/> (i) <lb/>1  , . . . , f <lb/> (i) <lb/> p  ) → (f <lb/> (i) <lb/> j  ) <lb/> −1  (f <lb/> (i) <lb/>1  , . . . , 1, . . . , f <lb/> (i) <lb/> p  ), <lb/>(η <lb/> (i) <lb/>1  , . . . , η <lb/> (i) <lb/> q  ) → (f <lb/> (i) <lb/> j  ) <lb/> −1  (η <lb/> (i) <lb/>1  , . . . , η <lb/> (i) <lb/> q  ). <lb/>By means of this map we glue the two copies together. Performing all these gluings gives a <lb/>model for Hom(C <lb/> 0|N  , P <lb/> p|q  ), consisting of the C <lb/> 0|N  -points of P <lb/> p|q  . <lb/>Another way to interpret this model is as follows. We consider a set of &quot; homogeneous &quot; <lb/>(even and odd) generators z  0  , ..., z  p  , θ  1  , ..., θ  q  , where the z  j  &apos;s are in Γ <lb/> 0 <lb/> N  and at least one them <lb/>is invertible and the θ  j  &apos;s are in Γ <lb/> 1 <lb/> N  . One obtains the local generators on each X  i  simply <lb/> &quot; dividing &quot; by z  i  (exactly like in the standard projective case, when one looks for the &quot; affine <lb/>coordinates &quot; ). This way we see that we can identify <lb/>Hom(C <lb/> 0|N  , P <lb/> p|q  ) = <lb/> (Γ <lb/> 0 <lb/> N  ) <lb/> p+1  \ B <lb/> p+1 <lb/> × (Γ <lb/> 1 <lb/> N  ) <lb/> q <lb/> (Γ <lb/> 0 <lb/> N  ) <lb/>  * <lb/> , <lb/> where (Γ <lb/> 0 <lb/> N  ) <lb/>  *  is the set of the even invertible elements and B = (Γ <lb/> 0 <lb/> N  ) \ (Γ <lb/> 0 <lb/> N  ) <lb/>  *  . This model is <lb/>exactly the generalization of the projective space as a supermanifold in the sense of Rogers, <lb/>Bruzzo and others (see book [7] for a complete discussion). <lb/> 5 Supergroups and Superdeterminants <lb/> As another illustration of the meaning of the functor of points we consider the case of <lb/>supergroups. For simplicity we will just look at the cases of GL(1|1), SL(1|1) and fi-<lb/>nally we will give another construction of the superprojective space as the quotient space <lb/> SU (n|m)/U (n − 1|m). <lb/>Let us now consider the simplest case of supergroup GL(1|1). As a supermanifold, <lb/> GL(1|1) is isomorphic to the super-domain U <lb/> 2|2  = (U <lb/> 2  , C <lb/> ∞2|2  ), where U <lb/> 2  = (C <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> 2  . If (z  1  , z  2  ) <lb/>are the coordinates on U <lb/> 2  and θ  1  , θ  2  are the generators of the Grassmann algebra, it is <lb/>convenient to use the notation in matrix form <lb/> z  1  θ  1 <lb/> θ  2  z  2 <lb/> . <lb/> (5.1) <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body> We can define the &quot; product &quot; on GL(1|1) as a morphism <lb/> ψ ∈ Hom(GL(1|1) × GL(1|1), GL(1|1)) <lb/> such that <lb/> ψ <lb/> ∼  : GL(1|1)  0  × GL(1|1)  0  −→ GL(1|1)  0 <lb/> (z  1  , z  2  ) × (z  3  , z  4  ) <lb/> −→ (z  1  z  3  , z  2  z  4  ), <lb/> ψ <lb/>  *  : C <lb/> ∞  (U <lb/> 2  ) [ϑ  1  , ϑ  2  ] −→ <lb/>C <lb/> ∞  (U <lb/> 2  × U <lb/> 2  ) [θ  1  , θ  2  , θ  3  , θ  4  ] <lb/> w  1  ϑ  1 <lb/> ϑ  2  w  2 <lb/> −→ <lb/> z  1  z  3  + θ  1  θ  4  θ  1  z  4  + z  1  θ  3 <lb/> θ  2  z  3  + z  2  θ  4  z  2  z  4  + θ  2  θ  3 <lb/> , <lb/> where the action of the pull-back morphism ψ <lb/>  *  has been specified only for the generators of <lb/>the algebra (see Theorem 1). <lb/>We now apply the functor of points to recover the usual interpretation of GL(1|1) as the <lb/>set of &quot; invertible supermatrices &quot; . Take as model space S = C <lb/> 0|q  , then Hom(S, GL(1|1)) can <lb/>be identified with the set of matrices <lb/> g = <lb/> ψ <lb/>  *  z  1  ψ <lb/>  *  θ  1 <lb/> ψ <lb/>  *  θ  2  ψ <lb/>  *  z  2 <lb/> , <lb/> (5.2) <lb/>where ψ <lb/>  *  z  i  are even elements of the Grassmann algebra Γ  q  , whose value is different from <lb/>zero, and ψ <lb/>  *  θ  i  are odd elements. To simplify notation we denote ψ <lb/>  *  z  i  (resp. ψ <lb/>  *  θ  i  ) by z  i <lb/> (resp. θ  i  ). <lb/>The above &quot; product &quot; becomes the usual multiplication of super-matrices as follows. A <lb/>morphism form S to GL(1|1) × GL(1|1) is given by a pair of matrices, g  1  and g  2  , as above. <lb/>Composition with the product morphism gives a morphism from S to GL(1|1), represented <lb/>by a matrix g  3  , which can be seen to be given by the usual multiplication of matrices: <lb/> g  1  = <lb/> z  1  θ  1 <lb/> θ  2  z  2 <lb/> , <lb/>g  2  = <lb/> z  3  θ  3 <lb/> θ  4  z  4 <lb/> (5.3) <lb/> g  3  = g  1  g  2  = <lb/> z  1  z  3  + θ  1  θ  4  θ  1  z  4  + z  1  θ  3 <lb/> θ  2  z  3  + z  2  θ  4  z  2  z  4  + θ  2  θ  3 <lb/> . <lb/> Recall the classical formula for the superderminant (or Berezinian) of a super-matrix in <lb/>GL(1|1): <lb/> sdet(g) = Ber(g) = <lb/> z  1 <lb/> z  2 <lb/> 1 + <lb/> θ  1  θ  2 <lb/> z  1  z  2 <lb/> (5.4) <lb/>which is well defined if z  2  = 0. The Berezinian can also be understood from the sheaf point <lb/>of view, as a morphism Ber from GL(1|1) to C <lb/> 1|0  : <lb/> Ber <lb/> ∼  : GL(1|1)  0  −→ <lb/> C <lb/> (z  1  , z  2  ) <lb/> −→ z  1  /z  2 <lb/> , <lb/>Ber <lb/>  *  : C <lb/> ∞1|0  −→ <lb/>C <lb/> ∞2|2 <lb/> w <lb/> −→ <lb/> z  1 <lb/> z  2 <lb/> 1 + <lb/> θ  1  θ  2 <lb/> z  1  z  2 <lb/> . <lb/></body>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>

			<body> Next, we consider a subset of supermatrices GL(1|1) with the property that &quot; the su-<lb/>perdeterminant is 1 &quot; . They are denoted by SL(1|1). We want to describe this space using <lb/>the sheaf theoretic interpretation of supermanifolds, by restricting the base manifold and <lb/>considering an appropriate quotient sheaf. We need to give a meaningful interpretation of <lb/>the relation <lb/> z  1 <lb/> z  2 <lb/> 1 + <lb/> θ  1  θ  2 <lb/> z  1  z  2 <lb/> = 1 . <lb/> (5.5) <lb/>We do it as follows. Let J be the ideal in C <lb/> ∞ 2|2  generated by <lb/> z  1 <lb/> z  2 <lb/> 1 + <lb/> θ  1  θ  2 <lb/> z  1  z  2 <lb/> − 1 . <lb/> (5.6) <lb/>The base manifold of SL(1|1) is the support of this ideal, i.e. the subset X ⊂ C <lb/>  *  × C <lb/>  *  of <lb/>points around which no element of J is invertible. Clearly X is the diagonal in C <lb/>  *  × C <lb/>  *  , i.e. <lb/>the set where z  1  = z  2  . The sheaf O  X  is the restriction to X of the quotient sheaf <lb/> C <lb/> ∞ 2|2  /J . <lb/> (5.7) <lb/>It remains to show that this ringed manifold SL(1|1) is really a supermanifold, i.e. it is <lb/>obtained by pasting super-domains. In fact observe that the relation (5.6) tells us that over <lb/>an open set V ⊂ X, z  1  = z  2  − <lb/> θ  1  θ  2 <lb/> z  2 <lb/> . Therefore the ring over V is C <lb/> ∞  (z  2  − <lb/> θ  1  θ  2 <lb/> z  2 <lb/> , z  2  )[θ  1  , θ  2  ] <lb/>which can be seen to be isomorphic to a super-ring of the type C <lb/> ∞  (z)[Ψ  1  , Ψ  2  ], so locally <lb/> SL(1|1) is isomorphic to a superdomain. What we have done here is to show explicitly that <lb/> SL(1|1) is a sub-supermanifold of dimension 1|2 of GL(1|1) in the sense of [5]. <lb/>To conclude the description of X = SL(1|1), we present its interpretation by means of <lb/>the functor of points, using the model space S = C <lb/> 0|N  . Then, the morphisms in Hom(S, X) <lb/> can be viewed as the morphisms in Hom(S, GL(1|1)) such that: <lb/>i.) the map between the underlying topological spaces has image contained in the diagonal <lb/>of C <lb/>  *  × C <lb/>  *  ; <lb/>ii.) the pull-back map descends to the quotient, i.e. ψ <lb/>  *  (j) = 0 for any j ∈ J . <lb/>Then, the set Hom(S, X) can be viewed as the matrices of the form <lb/> g = <lb/> ψ <lb/>  *  z  1  ψ <lb/>  *  θ  1 <lb/> ψ <lb/>  *  θ  2  ψ <lb/>  *  z  2 <lb/> , <lb/> (5.8) <lb/>with the conditions that: 1) the value of ψ <lb/>  *  z  1  is equal to the value of ψ <lb/>  *  z  2  (by (i)), and 2) <lb/>the super-determinant of the matrix in (5.8) is 1 (by (ii)). <lb/>We start describing GL(1|1, C) in a different way, by passing to real super-groups. We <lb/>use the following idea: think about C <lb/> n  , with a complex basis {v  1  ; v  2  ; ...; v  n  }. Then, C <lb/> n  can <lb/>be viewed as a real 2n-dimensional space, with a real basis <lb/> {v  1  ; iv  1  ; v  2  ; iv  2  ; ...; v  n  ; iv  n  } . <lb/></body>

			<page> 11 <lb/></page>

			<body> So, let&apos;s take V <lb/> 2  = {(a; b) ∈ R <lb/> 2  : a <lb/> 2  + b <lb/> 2  = 0}. We take, as a base manifold, (V <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> 2  , and <lb/>the ring over this total space is C <lb/> ∞ <lb/> R  (z  1  ; z <lb/> 1  ; z  2  ; z <lb/> 2  ) [θ; θ <lb/>  ; ψ; ψ <lb/>  ]. Note that z <lb/> 1  and z <lb/> 2  (as even <lb/>generators), and θ <lb/>  and ψ <lb/>  (as odd generators) play the role of the vectors (written above) iv  j  . <lb/>So, the primed generators are independent from the real point of view; sums like xz  1  + yz <lb/> 1 <lb/> (or θ + θ <lb/>  ) represent complex even (respectively, odd) elements, since they put together the <lb/>real and the imaginary part. <lb/>We can view the generators in the following matrix form, which helps us in writing the <lb/>product morphism. <lb/> z  1  + z <lb/> 1 <lb/> θ + θ <lb/> ψ + ψ <lb/>  z  2  + z <lb/> 2 <lb/> . <lb/> (5.9) <lb/>The product morphism is defined by: m : (V <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> 2  × (V <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> 2  −→ (V <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> 2  , and one can describe <lb/>exactly the pull-back morphism by performing explicitly the matrix multiplication: <lb/> z <lb/> 1 <lb/>1  + z <lb/> 1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> θ <lb/> 1  + θ <lb/> 1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> 1  + ψ <lb/> 1  z <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  + z <lb/> 1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> · <lb/> z <lb/> 2 <lb/>1  + z <lb/> 2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> θ <lb/> 2  + θ <lb/> 2 <lb/> ψ <lb/> 2  + ψ <lb/> 2  z <lb/> 2 <lb/>2  + z <lb/> 2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> Then, we try to define a &quot; complex conjugation &quot; . It is a morphism, such that its pull-back <lb/>map takes the form: <lb/> ρ <lb/>  *  : C <lb/> ∞ <lb/> R  (z  1  ; z <lb/> 1  ; z  2  ; z <lb/> 2  ) [θ; θ <lb/>  ; ψ; ψ <lb/>  ] −→ C <lb/> ∞ <lb/> R  (z  1  ; z <lb/> 1  ; z  2  ; z <lb/> 2  ) [θ; θ <lb/>  ; ψ; ψ <lb/>  ] , <lb/> and it is completely determined once one knows the behavior of the generators. In fact, it <lb/>sends z  1  ; z  2  ; θ; ψ to themselves, while the primed elements z <lb/> 1  ; z <lb/> 2  ; θ <lb/>  ; ψ <lb/>  undergo a change of <lb/>sign, going respectively to −z <lb/> 1  ; −z <lb/> 2  ; −θ <lb/>  ; −ψ <lb/>  . <lb/>Next, we define the &quot; Hermitian transpose &quot; , which will be denoted by the symbol H. <lb/> Its pull-back map sends z  1  ; z  2  to themselves, z <lb/> 1  ; z <lb/> 2  to −z <lb/> 1  ; −z <lb/> 2  , respectively; θ; θ <lb/>  to ψ <lb/>  ; ψ, <lb/> respectively, and ψ <lb/>  ; −ψ to θ <lb/>  ; −θ, respectively. Note that the exchange of the θ with the <lb/> ψ is due to the transposition operation, while the exchange of a non-primed generator with <lb/>a primed one is due to a multiplication by −i. We will see this better when we pass to <lb/>Grassmann algebras by the functor of points. We have again to require that H is a morphism. <lb/>Note that it is not true that (H <lb/>  *  ) <lb/> 2  = Id . <lb/> Now, we can describe the functor of points with respect to a particular model space. We <lb/>choose, as a model space, C <lb/> 0|q  . So, C <lb/> 0|q  = ({pt.} ; C [ξ  1  ; ξ  2  ; ...; ξ  q  ]). The conjugation is a map, <lb/>defined, in a standard way (since C <lb/> 0|q  is simply a Grassmann algebra) σ : C <lb/> 0|q  −→ C <lb/> 0|q  , with <lb/>pull-back defined by: σ <lb/>  *  ((x + iy) ξ  i  ) = (x − iy) ξ  i  . <lb/>When we construct the morphisms Hom <lb/> C <lb/> 0|q  ; GL (1|1) <lb/> , we only take the ones which <lb/>are R-linear and compatible with conjugations, which means that σ <lb/>  *  • ϕ <lb/>  *  = ϕ <lb/>  *  • ρ <lb/>  *  . This <lb/>means for example, that, if we choose an odd element of C <lb/> 0|q  as the pull-back of θ, the <lb/>pull-back of θ <lb/>  is consequently i times the pull-back of θ. (In general this is not true, but we <lb/>have assumed here that there is a complex structure J on the anticommuting coordinates <lb/>and we consider only those morphisms which commute with J.) <lb/> In this way, we can describe the C <lb/> 0|q  -points of GL (1|1) as the set of matrices of the form <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body> a α <lb/>β b <lb/> , <lb/> where a; b are even elements of a complex Grassmann algebra with q generators, α;β are odd <lb/>elements of the same algebra, and the Berezinian is invertible. <lb/>Now, we can pass to construct the super-group U (1|1). Note that it is a real super-<lb/>manifold. We have to perform the quotient of C <lb/> ∞ <lb/> R  (z  1  ; z <lb/> 1  ; z  2  ; z <lb/> 2  ) [θ; θ <lb/>  ; ψ; ψ <lb/>  ], by the four <lb/>relations obtained from: <lb/> A · H <lb/>  *  (A) = I, <lb/> (5.10) <lb/>where A is a sheaf element written in the matrix form (5.9). By explicitly writing the <lb/>elements on the left, we get four generators of an ideal I. Taking the quotient <lb/> C <lb/> ∞ <lb/> R  (z  1  ; z <lb/> 1  ; z  2  ; z <lb/> 2  ) [θ; θ <lb/>  ; ψ; ψ <lb/>  ]/I , <lb/> we finally get the sheaf corresponding to U (1|1). The base manifold is the support of this <lb/>sheaf. Applying the functor of points interpretation and using C <lb/> 0|q  as a model, it is easy to <lb/>see that the elements of U (1|1) correspond, as a set, to the matrices of the form <lb/> B = <lb/> a α <lb/>β b <lb/> . <lb/> (5.11) <lb/>They preserve the &quot; scalar &quot; product (z, θ), (z, θ) = z ¯ <lb/> z + iθ ¯ <lb/> θ. Note that the bar is the <lb/>conjugation in C <lb/> 0|q  , i.e. a = σ <lb/>  *  (a). It follows that B <lb/>  †  · B = I, where <lb/>  †  represents the <lb/>usual &quot; adjoint &quot; of super-matrices. It represents the correspondence between a matrix and <lb/>its Hermitian transpose from the C <lb/> 0|q  point of view, since we can see that for every element <lb/> ϕ ∈ Hom <lb/> C <lb/> 0|q  ; GL (1|1) <lb/> , ϕ <lb/>  *  • H <lb/>  *  is related to ϕ <lb/>  *  by exactly performing the <lb/>  †  operation. <lb/>More precisely, <lb/> B <lb/>  †  = <lb/> a −iβ <lb/>−iα b <lb/> . <lb/> (5.12) <lb/>For the sake of completeness, we write explicitly the C <lb/> 0|q  -points of U (1|1). They are in <lb/>bijective correspondence with the matrices of the form <lb/> U = <lb/> 1 − <lb/> i <lb/> 2 <lb/> γγ <lb/> −ie <lb/> iψ  γ <lb/>γ <lb/>e <lb/> iψ <lb/> 1 + <lb/> i <lb/> 2 <lb/> γγ <lb/> , <lb/> (5.13) <lb/>where ψ is a real phase and γ is a generic odd element of the Grassmann algebra. <lb/>A similar construction applies to U (n|m) supergroups. To get the supergroups SU (n|m) <lb/>we have to quotient with respect to the Berezinian equal to one. The body part of SU (n|m) <lb/>is U (1) × SU (n) × SU (m). The odd part belongs to the fundamental representation of <lb/> SU (n) × U (m). <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body> 5.1 Superprojective spaces as Supercosets <lb/> Here we show that, using the functor-of-points framework, the superprojective spaces can <lb/>be described in three different and equivalent ways. We first remind the reader the three <lb/>methods to define the classical projective space and then we extend it to superprojective <lb/>ones. <lb/>In the classical case, let z  i  , i = 1, . . . , n + 1 be the coordinates on C <lb/> n+1  − {0} and define <lb/>the projective space P <lb/> n  by the quotient <lb/>(z  1  , . . . , z  n+1  ) ∼ λ(z  1  , . . . , z  n+1  ) , λ ∈ C <lb/>  *  . <lb/> (5.14) <lb/>This is the standard definition of P <lb/> n  . Alternatively, one can fix the modulus of λ by setting <lb/> n+1 <lb/> i=1 <lb/> |z  i  | <lb/> 2  = r &gt; 0 , <lb/>z  i  ∼ e <lb/> iφ  z  i  , ∀i , φ ∈ R . <lb/> (5.15) <lb/>up to the phase φ. The first equation fixes the modulus |λ| <lb/> 2  = 1 and the second equation <lb/>removes its phase. Let us choose r = 1, this implies that the vector z  i  has modulus equal to <lb/>one. <lb/>The SU (n + 1) symmetry of (5.15) is used to bring the vector z  i  in the form (1, 0, . . . , 0) <lb/>which has modulus equal to one. This vector has a stability group which is U (n). A stability <lb/>group is the subgroup of transformations which leaves (1, 0, . . . , 0) invariant. Therefore, we <lb/>can define the projective space as the coset <lb/> SU (n + 1)/U (n) . <lb/> (5.16) <lb/>The three ways to define a P <lb/> n  are easily seen to be equivalent. <lb/>Let us consider now the superprojective spaces P <lb/> n|m  . The definition (5.14) can be re-<lb/>peated as follows <lb/>(z  1  , . . . , z  n+1  , θ  1  , . . . , θ  m  ) ∼ λ(z  1  , . . . , z  n+1  , θ  1  , . . . , θ  m  ) , <lb/> (5.17) <lb/>with λ not belonging to C <lb/>  *  , but to the space of even quantities which are invertible (see sec. <lb/>4.1). Again, we can use the alternative definition of P <lb/> n|m  ([8, 9, 10, 5]) <lb/> n+1 <lb/> i=1 <lb/> |z  i  | <lb/> 2  + i <lb/> m <lb/> A=1 <lb/> ¯ <lb/> θ  A  θ  A  = r &gt; 0 , <lb/>z  i  ∼ e <lb/> iφ  z  i  , θ  A  ∼ e <lb/> iφ  θ  A  , <lb/> ∀i, A , φ ∈ C . (5.18) <lb/>The equation (5.18) is the correct extension of (5.15), but its interpretation needs some <lb/>comment. As we have seen there are two ways to describe supermanifolds: i) using the <lb/>sheaf description and ii) using the functor-of-points. According to the first framework, <lb/>eq. (5.18) can be seen as an algebraic equation among the generators of the sheaves of <lb/>the supermanifolds. Eq. (5.18) is consistent with the projection (5.17) and it defines an <lb/>hypersurface in P <lb/> n|m  . According to the second description, one has to decompose the <lb/>coordinates z  i  and θ  A  on the basis of the generators of the superdomain and the coefficients <lb/>need to satisfy a set of algebraic equations. <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body> Note that SU (n + 1|m) acts on P <lb/> n|m  as follows: <lb/> ψ : SU (n + 1|m) × P <lb/> n|m  −→ P <lb/> n|m <lb/> (5.19) <lb/>with the pull-back defined by <lb/> ψ <lb/>  *  (z  i  ) = <lb/> n+1 <lb/> j=1 <lb/> A  ij  z  j  + <lb/> m <lb/> A=1 <lb/> α  iA  θ  A  , <lb/>ψ <lb/>  *  (θ  A  ) = <lb/> n+1 <lb/> j=1 <lb/> β  Aj  z  j  + <lb/> m <lb/> B=1 <lb/> B  BA  θ  I  , <lb/> (5.20) <lb/>where A  ij  , B  AB  are the even generators of SU (n + 1|m) and α  iA  , β  Aj  are the odd ones. It <lb/>is easy to see that the action is transitive like in the classical case. So, as in the classical <lb/>case one can define the supercoset SU (n + 1|m)/SU (n|m) which can be identified with the <lb/>superprojective space P <lb/> n|m  . An analysis of the supercosets can be found in in the book [3] <lb/>and recently it has been discussed in [6]. <lb/>Therefore applying the construction above and starting from a vector ((1, . . . , 0), (0, . . . , 0)) <lb/>(where the first set of components are the even coordinates and the second set the odd ones) <lb/>we end up with eq. (5.18). The odd part of (5.18) is obtained by acting with the odd part <lb/>of the supergroup on the unit vector. Notice that this is not the only possibility, indeed we <lb/>can start from an odd vector ((0, . . . , 0), (1, . . . , 0)) which has the following norm <lb/> ||((0, . . . , 0), (1, . . . , 0))|| <lb/> 2  = i θ  1  ¯ <lb/> θ  1  . <lb/> In this case, acting with the supergroup on it (and preserving the subgroup U (n|m)), we <lb/>end up with the new equation <lb/> n+1 <lb/> i=1 <lb/> |z  i  | <lb/> 2  + i <lb/> m <lb/> A=1 <lb/> ¯ <lb/> θ  A  θ  A  = r , <lb/> (5.21) <lb/>where r is an even element of the algebra. For example, starting from the vector <lb/>((1, . . . , 0), (1, . . . , 0)) <lb/>we have r = r  0  + i θ  1  ¯ <lb/> θ  1  whose body r  0  is positive. <lb/> 6 Balanced Supermanifolds <lb/> In this section, we propose a possible extension of notion of balanced manifold (see [13]) to <lb/>the supermanifolds. We found appropriate to report the present results since they call for a <lb/>functor-of-point interpretation and for the definition of stable supermanifolds. <lb/> 6.1 Donaldson&apos;s balanced superprojective spaces <lb/> Let us consider the superprojective space P <lb/> p|q  with standard coordinates [z  0  , . . . , z  p  , θ  1  , . . . , θ  q  ] <lb/>and the matrix valued function on P <lb/> p|q  given by <lb/> B  ik  = <lb/> z  i  ¯ <lb/> z  k <lb/>  p <lb/>l=0  |z  i  |  2  + i <lb/>  q <lb/>l=1  θ  I  ¯ <lb/> θ  I <lb/> , <lb/></body>

			<page> 15 <lb/></page>

			<body> B  iK  = <lb/> z  i  ¯ <lb/> θ  K <lb/>  p <lb/>l=0  |z  i  |  2  + i <lb/>  q <lb/>l=1  θ  I  ¯ <lb/> θ  I <lb/> , B  Ik  = <lb/> θ  I  ¯ <lb/> z  k <lb/>  p <lb/>l=0  |z  i  |  2  + i <lb/>  q <lb/>l=1  θ  I  ¯ <lb/> θ  I <lb/> , <lb/> (6.1) <lb/> B  IK  = <lb/> iθ  I  ¯ <lb/> θ  K <lb/>  p <lb/>l=0  |z  i  |  2  + i <lb/>  q <lb/>l=1  θ  I  ¯ <lb/> θ  I <lb/> , <lb/> If we denote by V a projective subsupervariety of P <lb/> p|q  , we define the (p + q + 1) × (p + q + 1)-<lb/>matrix by the block matrix <lb/> M (V )  AB  = <lb/> V <lb/> B  ik  dµ  V <lb/> V <lb/> B  iK  dµ  V <lb/> V <lb/> B  Ik  dµ  V <lb/> V <lb/> B  IK  dµ  V <lb/> (6.2) <lb/>where the indices A, B run over p + 1 + q values. Notice that M (V )  ij  = M  ji  , M (V )  iK  = <lb/> M (V )  Ik  and M (V )  IK  = −M  KI  . The measure dµ  V  is defined as follows. For the superpro-<lb/>jective space P <lb/> p|q  , the Fubini-Study form is given by <lb/>Ω  F S  = <lb/> i <lb/> 2π <lb/> ∂ ¯ <lb/> ∂ log <lb/>  p <lb/> l=0 <lb/> |z  i  | <lb/> 2  + i <lb/> q <lb/> l=1 <lb/> θ  I  ¯ <lb/> θ  I <lb/> , <lb/> (6.3) <lb/>where ∂ = dz <lb/> i  ∂  i  + dθ  I  ∂  I  and ¯ <lb/> ∂ is its conjugate. The supertangent space and the cotangent <lb/>space are defined in [5]. The expressions for ∂ and ¯ <lb/> ∂ are the natural extensions of usual <lb/>geometry and acting on a superfunction they produce a superform of type (1, 1). The <lb/>Fubini-Study form is real Ω  F S  = Ω  F S  . Then, one can form <lb/> dµ  V  = <lb/>Ω <lb/> p+q <lb/>F B <lb/> (p + q)! <lb/> V <lb/> = f  V  (z, ¯ <lb/> z, θ, ¯ <lb/> θ) d <lb/> p  z ∧ d <lb/> p  ¯ <lb/> z ∧ d <lb/> q  θ ∧ d <lb/> q  ¯ <lb/> θ , <lb/> (6.4) <lb/>where p + q is the sum of the bosonic and fermionic dimension of V <lb/> p|q  and f  µ  (z, ¯ <lb/> z, θ, ¯ <lb/> θ) is a <lb/>real superfield. <lb/>Notice that the wedge product in dµ  V  is a skew product for one-forms dx <lb/> i  , while is a <lb/>symmetric product for the dθ  I  &apos;s. This super-p + q-form does no correspond to a integration <lb/>measure for the supermanifold P <lb/> p|q  since it is not clear how to integrate on the cotangent <lb/>bundle generated by the commuting superforms dθ and d ¯ <lb/> θ. While the integration of functions <lb/>on the supermanifold is clear since it is obtained by the Berezin integral [4], the integration <lb/>on the superforms is obtained by using the method of the projection forms <lb/> d <lb/> µ  V  = <lb/>1 <lb/> p! <lb/> Ω <lb/> p <lb/>F B  ∧ U  q <lb/> (6.5) <lb/>where U  m  is the Thom class obtained by viewing the supermanifold P <lb/> p|q  as modeled on P <lb/> p  . <lb/>For a nice review see [20]. The construction of U  m  for P <lb/> p|q  will be given in [21]. <lb/>Applying this rules, one immediately gets <lb/> M (V )  iK  = M (V )  Ik  = 0 <lb/>(6.6) <lb/>and there are only non-trivial blocks M  ik  and M  IK  . Since the computation of U  q  requires <lb/>new ingredients, we consider in the following only super-Calabi-Yau spaces. For them we <lb/>can use a different measure provided by the holomorphic form. <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body> Following Donaldson [13], we define a balanced supermanifold if M (V ) is a multiple of <lb/>the identity matrix. Notice that the identity matrix in the supermanifold has the block <lb/>structure I = (δ  i ¯ j  , δ  I ¯ <lb/> K  ). Hence, a supermanifold is balanced iff there exist two real numbers <lb/> λ and η such that <lb/> V <lb/> B  i ¯ j  dµ  V  = λ δ  i ¯ j  , <lb/> V <lb/> B  i ¯ <lb/> J  dµ  V  = 0 , <lb/> V <lb/> B  I ¯ <lb/> J  dµ  V  = η δ  I ¯ <lb/> J  . <lb/> (6.7) <lb/>If p = q, then we must have λ = −η. This is due to the presence of a additional U (1) subgroup <lb/>of the stability group SU (p|q) (which is the group of isometries of the supermetric I) and <lb/>this reduces the supergroup to P SU (p|p). Notice that the integration over the fermionic <lb/>coordinates produces two terms: one is coming from the expansion of the denominator in <lb/> B  i ¯ j  or B  I ¯ <lb/> K  and the second is coming from the expansion of the measure d µ  V  . The second <lb/>source of interest in (6.7) is the presence of the additional constraints (the second and the <lb/>third relations) on the bosonic manifold. <lb/>In the case of super-Calabi-Yau space we use the integration measure obtained by the <lb/>nowhere-vanishing holomorphic form Ω  CY  . This simplifies the construction and we give here <lb/>the prescription how to integrate a given function F (notice that in [14], in the case of CY&apos;s, <lb/>the holomorphic form is used to define the measure in order to accelerate the convergence <lb/>of integrals). We focus on the super-Calabi-Yau P <lb/> 1|2  whose holomorphic form is (see [10]) <lb/>Ω  CY  = zdz  ij <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂θ  i <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂θ  j  . <lb/> (6.8) <lb/>Therefore, we have <lb/> P  1|2 <lb/> Ω  CY  ∧ ¯ <lb/>Ω  CY  F (z, ¯ <lb/> z, θ <lb/> i  , ¯ <lb/> θ <lb/> i  ) = <lb/> P  1 <lb/> |z| <lb/> 2  dz ∧ d¯ z  ij <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂θ  i <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂θ  j   ij <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂ ¯ <lb/> θ  i <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂ ¯ <lb/> θ  j  F (z, ¯ <lb/> z, θ <lb/> i  , ¯ <lb/> θ <lb/> i  )|  θ= ¯ <lb/> θ=0  . (6.9) <lb/>In the second line we have taken the four derivatives with respect to the fermionic coordinates <lb/> θ  i  and ¯ <lb/> θ  i  and then set them to zero. It remains to perform the usual integration on the P <lb/> 1  . <lb/>Let us now consider a generic polarized supermanifold (M, L) with L an holomorphic <lb/>super line bundle where the transition functions are elements of GL(1|1). In addition, we <lb/>require that the super line bundle has its first Chern class c  1  (L) represented by a Kähler <lb/>form of the supermanifold ω. For a positive m, we construct the tensor power series L <lb/> ⊗m <lb/> of the super line bundle and we denote by H <lb/> 0  (M, L <lb/> ⊗m  ) the space of holomorphic sections <lb/>(as clarified above) of L <lb/> ⊗m  . The holomorphic section could be odd or even. We use the <lb/>extension of the Kodaira embedding theorem [19] asserting that for a sufficiently large m <lb/> the holomorphic sections define a projective embedding <lb/> i  m  : M → P <lb/> H <lb/> 0  (M, L <lb/> ⊗m  ) <lb/> (6.10) <lb/>A choice of holomorphic sections (s  0|0  , . . . , s  pm|qm  ) in H <lb/> 0  (M, L <lb/> ⊗m  ) identifies P <lb/> H <lb/> 0  (M, L <lb/> ⊗m  ) <lb/> with a superprojective P <lb/> pm|qm  where the superdimensions p  m  and q  m  are due to the choice <lb/>of even and odd sections. <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body> Let us consider an example. We consider P <lb/> 1|2  (which is a super-Calabi-Yau). Chosen m, <lb/> H <lb/> 0  (P <lb/> 1|2  , L <lb/> ⊗m  ) is spanned by <lb/> H <lb/> 0  (P <lb/> 1|2  , L <lb/> ⊗m  ) = <lb/> z <lb/> a <lb/> 0  z <lb/> m−a <lb/> 1 <lb/> , z <lb/> a <lb/> 0  z <lb/> m−a−1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> θ  I  , z <lb/> a <lb/> 0  z <lb/> m−a−2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> θ  1  θ  2 <lb/> (6.11) <lb/> p  m  = 2m−1 and q  m  = 2m. We can see that each space H <lb/> 0  (P <lb/> 1|2  , L <lb/> ⊗m  ) is again a super-Calabi-<lb/>Yau space. This can be verified easily using the formulas given in [16] and it amounts to <lb/>see that the number of anticommuting coordinates must exceed of one w.r.t. the commuting <lb/>ones. In analogy with the bosonic case, we define the supermanifold (M, L <lb/> ⊗m  ) superbalanced <lb/>if one can choose a basis in P <lb/> H <lb/> 0  (M, L <lb/> ⊗  ) <lb/> such that the V = ι  m  (M ) is a superbalanced <lb/>variety. <lb/>On the space P <lb/> H <lb/> 0  (M, L <lb/> ⊗m  ) <lb/> we can define the Khäler form induced by the Fubini-<lb/>Study form on P <lb/> pm|qm  , namely <lb/> ω  m  = <lb/> i <lb/> 2π <lb/> ∂ ¯ <lb/> ∂ log <lb/> pm+qm <lb/> l=0 <lb/> s  l  (x) <lb/> σ(x) <lb/> 2 <lb/> (6.12) <lb/>where σ(x) is an invertible even section of H <lb/> 0  (P <lb/> 1|2  , L <lb/> ⊗m  ). For H <lb/> 0  (P <lb/> 1|2  , L <lb/> ⊗m  ) we have <lb/> ω  m  = <lb/> i <lb/> 2π <lb/> ∂ ¯ <lb/> ∂ log <lb/>  m <lb/> l=0 <lb/> |z <lb/> l <lb/> 0  z <lb/> m−l <lb/> 1 <lb/> | <lb/> 2  +i <lb/> m−1 <lb/> l=0 <lb/> |z <lb/> l <lb/> 0  z <lb/> m−1−l <lb/> 1 <lb/> | <lb/> 2  (θ  0  +θ  1  )( ¯ <lb/> θ  0  + ¯ <lb/> θ  1  )− <lb/> m−2 <lb/> l=0 <lb/> |z <lb/> l <lb/> 0  z <lb/> m−2−l <lb/> 1 <lb/> | <lb/> 2  θ  1  ¯ <lb/> θ  1  θ  2  ¯ <lb/> θ  2 <lb/> . <lb/> (6.13) <lb/>The θ − ¯ <lb/> θ-sections are absent in the usual geometry and it appeared in physics in the <lb/>context of supertwistor geometry. The differentials ∂ and ¯ <lb/> ∂ are natural extensions of the <lb/>one dimensional case. <lb/> 1 <lb/> The next step is to consider a super Hermitian metric L <lb/> ⊗m  × L <lb/> ⊗m  → C <lb/> 1|0  defined by the <lb/>formula <lb/> h  m  (q, q <lb/>  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/> λ <lb/> q <lb/>σ(x) <lb/>q  <lb/> σ(x) <lb/>  pm+qm <lb/>l=0 <lb/> |s  l  (x)|  2  . <lb/> (6.15) <lb/>In the denominator, we have both commuting and anticommuting sections and they have to <lb/>be taken into account to define an L <lb/> 2  -product and an orthonormal basis for P <lb/> H <lb/> 0  (M, L <lb/> ⊗m  ) <lb/> as follows <lb/> s  i  , s  j   h  = <lb/> M <lb/> h  m  (s  i  (x), s  j  (x))Ω  CY  ∧ ¯ <lb/>Ω  CY  = (δ  ij  ,  ij  ) <lb/>(6.16) <lb/>where δ  ij  is the diagonal metric for even sections and  ij  is the off-diagonal metric for odd sec-<lb/>tions. The metric · · · , · · ··  h  reduced the symmetry group from GL(p  m  |q  m  ) to the supergroup <lb/> SU (p  m  |q  m  ). <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 1  In the case of H <lb/> 0  (P <lb/> 1|2  , L <lb/> ⊗m  ), we can define an holomorphic form by separating the commuting sections <lb/> s  i  with i = 1, . . . , 2m − 1 from the anticommuting ones <lb/> s  I  with I = 1, . . . , 2m <lb/>Ω  m  =  i1...i2m−1  s  i1  d s  i2  ∧ d s  i2m−1   I1...I2m <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂ s  I1 <lb/> . . . <lb/>∂ <lb/>∂ s  I2m <lb/> . <lb/> (6.14) <lb/></note>

			<page> 18 <lb/></page>

			<body> To finish this paragraph, we analyze in detail the balancing of P <lb/> 1|2  into H <lb/> 0  (P <lb/> 1|2  , L <lb/> ⊗2  ), <lb/>namely into the space of homogeneous sections of degree-2. They are given by the set <lb/> z <lb/> a <lb/> 0  z <lb/> 2−a <lb/>1 <lb/> , z <lb/> a <lb/> 0  z <lb/> 1−a  <lb/> 1 <lb/> θ  I  , θ  1  θ  2 <lb/> (6.17) <lb/>where a = 0, 1, 2 and a <lb/>  = 0, 1. So, we can form the following integrals (where z is the affine <lb/>coordinate on P <lb/> 1  ) <lb/> B  a,b  = <lb/> P  1|2 <lb/> Ω  CY  ∧ ¯ <lb/>Ω  CY <lb/> z <lb/> 2−a  ¯ <lb/> z <lb/> 2−b <lb/> 1 + <lb/> a=0,1  |z|  4−2a  + i <lb/> a   =0,1  |z|  2−2a   θ  I  ¯ <lb/> θ  I  + θ  1  ¯ <lb/> θ  1  θ  2  ¯ <lb/> θ  2 <lb/> B  a   I,b   J  = <lb/> P  1|2 <lb/> Ω  CY  ∧ ¯ <lb/>Ω  CY <lb/> z <lb/> 1−a   ¯ <lb/> z <lb/> 1−b   θ  I  ¯ <lb/> θ  J <lb/> 1 + <lb/> a=0,1  |z|  4−2a  + i <lb/> a   =0,1  |z|  2−2a   θ  I  ¯ <lb/> θ  I  + θ  1  ¯ <lb/> θ  1  θ  2  ¯ <lb/> θ  2 <lb/> B  12,12  = <lb/> P  1|2 <lb/> Ω  CY  ∧ ¯ <lb/>Ω  CY <lb/> θ  1  θ  2  ¯ <lb/> θ  1  ¯ <lb/> θ  2 <lb/> 1 + <lb/> a=0,1  |z|  4−2a  + i <lb/> a   =0,1  |z|  2−2a   θ  I  ¯ <lb/> θ  I  + θ  1  ¯ <lb/> θ  1  θ  2  ¯ <lb/> θ  2 <lb/> (6.18) <lb/>where the integrals are easily performed by the previous instructions. In the last integral, the <lb/>Berezin integration removes those θ&apos;s and it leaves a bosonic integral on P <lb/> 1  which is similar <lb/>to the classical integrals in the bosonic balanced manifolds. However, here we see that we <lb/>have new conditions coming from the other integrals. For example, from the first one we <lb/>need to expand the denominator to soak up enough θ&apos;s. And this leads to new conditions <lb/>on the embeddings. Notice that in general the form of the embedding given by (6.17) is not <lb/>balanced, but one needs to adjust some numerical coefficients in front of each given section. <lb/> 6.2 Balancing of points <lb/> As a second application, we consider the problem of the stability of point of the type C <lb/> 0|n <lb/> into the superprojective space P <lb/> 1|n  . Since the superspace C <lb/> 0|n  is not a Calabi-Yau, we need to <lb/>use the measure defined in (6.5). Before doing that, we specify the embedding as follows: we <lb/>denote by η  i  , ¯ <lb/> η  i  the anticommuting generators of C <lb/> 0|n  , we construct the morphism between <lb/>the two superspace by the map <lb/> P : C <lb/> 0|n  −→ P <lb/> 1|n <lb/> X  I  = P <lb/>  *  (x  I  ) = α  I  + α  I,[jk]  η  j  η  k  + . . . <lb/> (6.19) <lb/>Θ  i  = P <lb/>  *  (θ  i  ) = β  i,j  η  j  + β  i,jkl  η  j  η  k  η  l  + . . . <lb/> (6.20) <lb/>where x  I  , θ  i  are the homogeneous coordinates on P <lb/> 1|n  , with I = 0, 1 and i = 1, . . . , n. The <lb/>capital letters denote the pull-backs of the sheaf generators. <lb/>First we construct the matrices for the bosonic embeddings. For each single point [x  0  : x  1  ] <lb/>the map discussed in (6.1-6.2) gives <lb/> B[x  0  : x  1  ] = <lb/>1 <lb/> |x  0  |  2  + |x  1  |  2 <lb/> |x  0  | <lb/> 2  x  0  ¯ <lb/> x  1 <lb/> x  1  ¯ <lb/> x  0  |x  1  | <lb/> 2 <lb/> (6.21) <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body> and to extend it to supermanifold, we substitute the pull-backs X  I  in place of the coordinates <lb/> x  I  . In this way, the momentum map becomes a superfield of the anticommuting coordinates <lb/> η  i  and therefore we need to integrate over them to get a numerical value. For that reason <lb/>we define the following new quantity <lb/> M (P ) = <lb/>  n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> dη  i  d¯ η  i <lb/> 1 <lb/> |X  0  |  2  + |X  1  |  2  + i <lb/> j  Θ  j  ¯ <lb/>Θ  j <lb/> |X  0  | <lb/> 2 <lb/> X  0  ¯ <lb/> X  1 <lb/> X  1  ¯ <lb/> X  0  |X  1  | <lb/> 2 <lb/> (6.22) <lb/>where P is the point in the superprojective space P <lb/> 1|N  . We also define σ  ij  = <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂η  i <lb/> Θ  j  (η  i  ) as <lb/>the embedding matrix <lb/> σ  ij  = β  i,j  + β  i,jkl  η  k  η  l  + . . . <lb/> (6.23) <lb/>The function M (P ) is the generalization of the usual moment map B[x  0  : x  1  ], where we <lb/>embed the point [x  0  : x  1  ] into a su(2) matrix. On the other hand, for supermanifolds M (P ) <lb/>is the embedding of the point P into the upper-left corner of the supermatrix su(2|N ) which <lb/>is the Lie algebra of the isometry group of P <lb/> 1|N  which is represented by an su(2) matrix. For <lb/>that reason the normalization term |X  0  | <lb/> 2  + |X  1  | <lb/> 2  + i <lb/> j  Θ  j  ¯ <lb/>Θ  j  acquires the supplementary <lb/>summand i <lb/> j  Θ  j  ¯ <lb/>Θ  j  . Notice that we have also to take into account the embedding of the <lb/>point into the su(N ) part of the supermatrix needed to implement the third type of condition <lb/>in eqs. (6.7) and this will be done later. <lb/>So, the final condition for the stability of a set of points C <lb/> 0|n  immersed into P <lb/> 1|n  is <lb/> P <lb/>n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂η  i <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂ ¯ <lb/> η  i <lb/> M  P  |  η  i  =¯ η  i  =0  = λ1 , <lb/> M  P  = <lb/>1 <lb/> |X  P,0  |  2  + |X  P,1  |  2  + i <lb/> j  Θ  P,j  ¯ <lb/>Θ  P,j <lb/> |X  P,0  | <lb/> 2 <lb/> X  P,0  ¯ <lb/> X  P,1 <lb/> X  P,1  ¯ <lb/> X  P,0  |X  P,1  | <lb/> 2 <lb/> (6.24) <lb/>where X  P,I  , Θ  P,i  are respectively the embeddings for the point P and the sum is extended <lb/>over all points. <lb/>Before discussing the third type of condition in eqs. (6.7), let us analyze the condition <lb/>(6.24) for a specific example, when C <lb/> 0|2  is embedded into P <lb/> 1|2  . For that we consider the <lb/>embedding <lb/> P : C <lb/> 0|2  −→ P <lb/> 1|2 <lb/> X  i  = P <lb/>  *  (x  i  ) = α  i  + <lb/> α  i  η  1  η  2 <lb/> (6.25) <lb/>Θ  i  = P <lb/>  *  (θ  i  ) = σ  i,j  η  j <lb/> and we compute explicitly the expression in (6.24). After few manipulations, we get <lb/> P <lb/> Υ <lb/> 3 <lb/> P <lb/> 2| <lb/> i <lb/> ¯ <lb/> α  P,i  <lb/> α  P,i  | <lb/> 2  − <lb/> i <lb/> |α  P,i  | <lb/> 2 <lb/> i <lb/> | α  P,i  | <lb/> 2  − 2 (det|σ| <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> |α  P,0  | <lb/> 2 <lb/> α  P,0  ¯ <lb/> α  P,1 <lb/> α  P,1  ¯ <lb/> α  P,0  |α  P,1  | <lb/> 2 <lb/> +Υ <lb/> 2 <lb/> P <lb/> i <lb/> α  P,i  ¯ <lb/> α  P,i <lb/> α  P,0  ¯ <lb/> α  P,0  α  P,1  ¯ <lb/> α  P,0 <lb/> α  P,0  ¯ <lb/> α  P,1  α  P,1  ¯ <lb/> α  P,1 <lb/> + h.c. <lb/> − Υ  P <lb/> | α  P,0  | <lb/> 2 <lb/> α  P,0  ¯ <lb/> α  P,1 <lb/> α  P,1  ¯ <lb/> α  P,0  | α  P,1  | <lb/> 2 <lb/> = λ1 . <lb/> (6.26) <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body> where Υ  P  = 1/ <lb/> i  |α  P,i  | <lb/> 2  . For example, in the case of only a single point P = [1 : 0], we get <lb/>the simplified equation <lb/> −| α  1  | <lb/> 2  + <lb/> α <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  +  ¯ <lb/> α <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  − 2det|σ| <lb/> 2 <lb/> α  0  <lb/> α  1  − <lb/> α  0  ¯ <lb/> α  1 <lb/>  ¯ <lb/> α  0  ¯ <lb/> α  1  −  ¯ <lb/> α  0  <lb/> α  1 <lb/> −| α  1  | <lb/> 2 <lb/> = λ1 . <lb/> (6.27) <lb/>From the up-right corner we get <lb/> α  1  is real and this fixes the constant λ. Then, we get the <lb/>condition, <lb/> α <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  +  ¯ <lb/> α <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  − 2 det|σ| <lb/> 2  = 0 which can be solved in terms of <lb/> α  0  . Therefore, there is <lb/>a single point whose embedding into P <lb/> 1|2  is balanced. The logic can be repeated for several <lb/>points and other solutions can be also found. Notice that the non-numerical part of X  i  , <lb/>namely the part which is parametrized by <lb/> α  i  plays a fundamental role and serves for the <lb/>balancing. We can also recover the classical solution by setting all <lb/> α  i  to zero. This implies <lb/>the classical balancing condition and therefore we found that there are also the classical <lb/>solutions with anticommuting coordinates. <lb/>It remains to compute the contribution for the embedding in the second su(2) of the <lb/>supermatrix su(2|2) and for that we have <lb/> M (P )  kl  = <lb/>  n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> dη  i  d¯ η  i <lb/> iΘ  k  ¯ <lb/>Θ  l <lb/> |X  0  |  2  + |X  1  |  2  + i <lb/> j  Θ  j  ¯ <lb/>Θ  j <lb/> (6.28) <lb/>as follows from (6.7). It is easy to evaluate the Berezin integrals to get <lb/> M (P )  kl  = λδ  kl <lb/> (6.29) <lb/>where λ = det|σ| <lb/> 2  /( <lb/> i  |α  i  | <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> 2  and in the case of the point P = [1 : 0] we have λ = det|σ| <lb/> 2  . <lb/>In the way, we notice that this part of the embedding is automatically balanced and it does <lb/>not yield a new condition on the parameters of the embedding. <lb/>To our knowledge, the present discussion is a way to formulate the balancing of points <lb/>into a superprojective space. Of course, one can add further condition, for example inserting <lb/>in the integral the factor exp(i <lb/> j  Θ  j  ¯ <lb/>Θ  j  ). This term reproduces the previous results, but <lb/>in addition it leads to a further condition that coincides with the classical requirement of <lb/>balanced points into a projective space. So, instead of imposing by hands the additional <lb/>condition of classical stability, the modification of the integration measure yields all possible <lb/>set of conditions. Moreover, for the case with more than 2 anticommuting coordinates the <lb/>exponential factor exp(i <lb/> j  Θ  j  ¯ <lb/>Θ  j  ) will lead to new conditions on the embedding. This makes <lb/>sense since adding new anticommuting coordinates requires new embedding parameters to <lb/>be fixed. <lb/>There are several questions that can be addressed in the same framework, for example: <lb/>can all points be made balanced after an SL(2|2) transformation? Is there a relation be-<lb/>tween our definition of balanced supermanifolds and a suitable notion of stability, such as in <lb/>GIT, in the supermanifold context (see [12])? We will leave these questions to forthcoming <lb/>publications. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments <lb/> We thank P. Aschieri, U. Bruzzo, L. Castellani, P. Fré, and E. Scheidegger for useful discus-<lb/>sions and remarks. <lb/></div>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] C. Arezzo and A. Loi, &quot; Moment maps, scalar curvature and quantization of Kähler <lb/>manifolds &quot; . Comm. Math. Phys. 246 (2004), no. 3, 543–559; <lb/>[2] J. Wess and J. Bagger, &quot; Supersymmetry and Supergravity &quot; , <lb/>[3] Yu. Manin, Complex Manifolds and Gauge fields, Springer; 1997. <lb/>[4] V. S. Varadarajan, &quot; Supersymmetry for mathematicians: An introduction, &quot; Courant Lec-<lb/>tures Notes, American Mathematical Society, 2004 <lb/>[5] V. S. Varadarajan, &quot; Courant Lectures on Supersymmetry, &quot; <lb/>http://www.math.ucla.edu/∼vsv/susy.html <lb/>[6] R. Fioresi, M. A. Lledo and V. S. Varadarajan, &quot; The super Minkowski and superconfor-<lb/>mal space times, &quot; arXiv:math.ra/0609813. <lb/>[7] C. Bartocci, U. Bruzzo, and D. Hernandez-Rupierez, The Geometry of Supermanifolds <lb/> Ed. Kluvers Academic Publishers. <lb/>[8] A. S. Schwarz, &quot; Sigma models having supermanifolds as target spaces, &quot; Lett. Math. <lb/>Phys. 38 (1996) 91 [arXiv:hep-th/9506070]. <lb/>[9] A. Konechny and A. S. Schwarz, &quot; On (k+l—q)-dimensional supermanifolds, &quot; arXiv:hep-<lb/>th/9706003. <lb/>[10] E. Witten, &quot; Perturbative gauge theory as a string theory in twistor space, &quot; Commun. <lb/>Math. Phys. 252 (2004) 189 [arXiv:hep-th/0312171]. <lb/>[11] N. Berkovits, &quot; Super-Poincare covariant quantization of the superstring, &quot; JHEP 0004, <lb/> 018 (2000) [arXiv:hep-th/0001035]. <lb/>[12] R. P. Thomas &quot; Notes on GIT and symplectic reduction for bundles and varieties &quot; , <lb/>Surveys in Differential Geometry, 10 (2006). <lb/>[13] S. K. Donaldson, &quot; Scalar curvature and projective embeddings I &quot; . J. Differential Geom. <lb/>59 (2001), no. 3, 479–522 <lb/>[14] S. K. Donaldson, &quot; Some numerical results in complex differential geometry &quot; , <lb/>arXiv:math/0512625. <lb/>[15] G. Tian, &quot; On a set of polarized Kähler metrics on algebraic manifolds &quot; . J. Differential <lb/>Geom. 32 (1990), no. 1, 99–130. <lb/>[16] P. A. Grassi and M. Marescotti, &quot; Flux vacua and supermanifolds, &quot; JHEP 0701, 068 <lb/>(2007) [arXiv:hep-th/0607243]. <lb/>[17] P. A. Grassi and G. Policastro, &quot; Super-Chern-Simons theory as superstring theory, &quot; <lb/>arXiv:hep-th/0412272. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [18] N. Berkovits and N. Nekrasov, &quot; Multiloop superstring amplitudes from non-minimal <lb/>pure spinor formalism, &quot; JHEP 0612 (2006) 029 [arXiv:hep-th/0609012]. <lb/>[19] C. LeBrun, Y-S. Poon and R.O. Wells, Jr &quot; Projective Embeddings of Complex Super-<lb/>manifolds &quot; , Comm. Math. Phys. 126 (1990) 433. <lb/>[20] S. Cordes, G. W. Moore and S. Ramgoolam, &quot; Lectures On 2-D Yang-Mills Theory, <lb/>Equivariant Cohomology And Topological Field Theories, &quot; Nucl. Phys. Proc. Suppl. 41, <lb/> 184 (1995) [arXiv:hep-th/9411210]. <lb/>[21] P.A. Grassi and M. Marescotti, in preparation. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>23 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
