<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="footnote"> arXiv:0805.2980v3  [quant-ph] 5 Jan 2009 <lb/></note>

			<front> Spin lattices with two-body Hamiltonians for which the ground state encodes a <lb/>cluster state <lb/> Tom Griffin and Stephen D. Bartlett <lb/> School of Physics, The University of Sydney, Sydney, New South Wales 2006, Australia <lb/> (Dated: 4 December 2008) <lb/>We present a general procedure for constructing lattices of qubits with a Hamiltonian composed <lb/>of nearest-neighbour two-body interactions such that the ground state encodes a cluster state. We <lb/>give specific details for lattices in one-, two-, and three-dimensions, investigating both periodic and <lb/>fixed boundary conditions, as well as present a proof for the applicability of this procedure to any <lb/>graph. We determine the energy gap of these systems, which is shown to be independent of the <lb/>size of the lattice but dependent on the type of lattice (in particular, the coordination number), <lb/>and investigate the scaling of this gap in terms of the coupling constants of the Hamiltonian. We <lb/>provide a comparative analysis of the different lattice types with respect to their usefulness for <lb/>measurement-based quantum computation. <lb/> PACS numbers: 03.67.Lx <lb/></front>

			<body> I. INTRODUCTION <lb/> There is currently considerable interest in preparing <lb/>exotic quantum states of many-body systems which can <lb/>be used as resource states for measurement-based quan-<lb/>tum computation (MBQC) – that is, quantum computa-<lb/>tion that proceeds solely through local adaptive measure-<lb/>ments on single quantum systems [1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6]. The <lb/>canonical example of such a resource state is the clus-<lb/>ter state [1, 2], which is a universal resource for MBQC <lb/>on suitable lattices or graphs [7]. It may be possible to <lb/>prepare such a cluster state dynamically in atomic sys-<lb/>tems such as an optical lattice [8] or using single pho-<lb/>tons [9, 10]. However, one exciting possibility is that <lb/>such resource states might be the non-degenerate ground <lb/>state of a &quot; natural &quot; Hamiltonian lattice system. If the <lb/>system is gapped, then one simply needs to cool it suf-<lb/>ficiently in order to obtain the desired state (although, <lb/>even for gapped systems, this cooling process may be dif-<lb/>ficult [11]). <lb/>Consider the cluster state on a lattice L, defined as the <lb/>unique +1 eigenstate of a set of stabilizer operators S  µ  = <lb/> X  µ  ⊗  ν∼µ  Z  ν  , where X  µ  (Z  µ  ) is the Pauli X (Z) operator <lb/>at site µ and where ν ∼ µ denotes that ν is connected to <lb/> µ by a bond in the lattice L. The Hamiltonian <lb/> H = −∆ <lb/> µ∈L <lb/> S  µ  , <lb/> (1) <lb/>with ∆ an energy constant, has the cluster state as <lb/>its unique ground state [2]. In addition, this system <lb/>is gapped (the gap is 2∆), and such a system can be <lb/>cooled efficiently [12]. However, for any non-trivial lat-<lb/>tice or graph, this Hamiltonian involves many-body in-<lb/>teractions, as opposed to the two-body interactions that <lb/>occur frequently in nature. <lb/>An obvious question, then, is whether it is possible to <lb/>realize any given highly-entangled quantum state as the <lb/>ground state of a Hamiltonian with only two-body in-<lb/>teractions. Haselgrove et al. [13] proved that this is not <lb/>possible in general, and Nielsen [14] used this result to <lb/>prove that a cluster state on a computationally universal <lb/>(i.e., two-dimensional or higher) lattice cannot arise as <lb/>the ground state of a Hamiltonian with only two-body <lb/>interactions. However, investigations into quantum com-<lb/>plexity theory [15, 16] have demonstrated that cluster <lb/>states (and other such states that are universal) can be <lb/> approximated by the ground state of a local two-body <lb/>Hamiltonian. The key idea is to make use of &quot; mediating &quot; <lb/>ancilla qubits to create an effective many-body coupling <lb/>out of two-body interactions. The problem with such <lb/>methods is that the detailed parameters in the perturb-<lb/>ing Hamiltonian must be controlled with a precision that <lb/>increases with the size of the system [17], making such <lb/>approaches impractical for the task of creating cluster <lb/>states on large lattices. <lb/>Using an alternate method based on the idea behind <lb/>projected entangled pair states (PEPS) [18], Bartlett and <lb/>Rudolph [19] proved that it was possible to obtain a state <lb/>that closely approximates an encoded cluster state on a <lb/>square lattice using a Hamiltonian with only two-body <lb/>nearest-neighbour interactions. In addition, they proved <lb/>that MBQC can proceed using such an encoded resource <lb/>state, still requiring only adaptive single-qubit measure-<lb/>ments. <lb/>In this paper, we present a general method for con-<lb/>structing two-body nearest-neighbour Hamiltonian sys-<lb/>tems for which the ground state encodes a cluster state, <lb/>based on the techniques of [19]. Our rigorous application <lb/>of perturbation theory reveals errors in the calculation of <lb/>the energy gap for the square lattice investigated in [19] <lb/>(although these errors do not affect their key result) and <lb/>we provide a correct treatment of this case. We also <lb/>investigate the cluster state on a one-dimensional line <lb/>(useful for illustration, as well as for its application as a <lb/>quantum wire [4]), a hexagonal lattice in two-dimensions <lb/>– a universal MBQC resource with the best scaling of the <lb/>energy gap in perturbation, and the cubic lattice in three-<lb/>dimensions – a resource state for which fault-tolerance <lb/>thresholds have been found [20, 21]. We explicitly char-<lb/></body>

			<page> 2 <lb/></page>

			<body> acterise the effects of fixed boundary conditions on the <lb/>lattice, proving that such boundary conditions do not af-<lb/>fect the main result. Finally, we provide an outline of a <lb/>proof that this method yields an encoded cluster state as <lb/>the ground state on any graph. <lb/> II. A PEPS HAMILTONIAN <lb/> Our general method relies on the fact that the cluster <lb/>state is simply represented as a projected entangled pair <lb/>state (PEPS), also known as a valence-bond solid state. <lb/> A. The PEPS representation of a cluster state <lb/> The PEPS representation [18] is a powerful and often <lb/>compact method of describing the state of a many-body <lb/>system. Consider a regular lattice L of qubits, with co-<lb/>ordination number c (i.e., c bonds connect each qubit to <lb/>other sites on the lattice). A PEP state on L can be <lb/>constructed by assigning a pair of virtual quantum sys-<lb/>tems of dimension D to each bond on the lattice, each <lb/>pair prepared in a maximally-entangled state, and then <lb/>applying a projection P to the c virtual systems associ-<lb/>ated with each site. The cluster state (and a wide variety <lb/>of other states of interest) require only D = 2 for their <lb/>representation; in what follows, we restrict our attention <lb/>to this case where the virtual systems are qubits. In ad-<lb/>dition, we choose the maximally-entangled state of these <lb/>virtual qubits to be the two-qubit cluster state <lb/> |C  2  = <lb/> 1 <lb/> √ <lb/> 2 <lb/> |0|+ + |1|− <lb/> , <lb/> (2) <lb/>where |± = <lb/> 1 <lb/> √ <lb/> 2 <lb/> (|0 ± |1). With this convention, the <lb/>cluster state has a simple PEPS representation [18] cor-<lb/>responding to the projection operator <lb/> P  L  = |0  L  00 . . . 0| + |1  L  11 . . . 1| , <lb/> (3) <lb/>at each site, with c zeros (ones) in 00 . . . 0| (11 . . . 1|), <lb/>and the states |0  L  and |1  L  forming a basis for the re-<lb/>sulting qubit at each site. <lb/>As an example, consider the PEPS representation <lb/>of the cluster state on a two-dimensional square lat-<lb/>tice. There are four bonds emanating from every site <lb/>in a square lattice, and so each site possesses four vir-<lb/>tual qubits. Virtual qubits connected by a bond are <lb/>placed in the state |C  2  , and then a projection P  L  = <lb/> ⊗  sites  (|0  L  0000| + |1  L  1111|) is applied. The resultant <lb/>state, |φ = P  L  ⊗  bonds  |C  2  is a cluster state on the square <lb/>lattice. <lb/> B. A two-body PEPS Hamiltonian <lb/> The essential idea of the method presented in this pa-<lb/>per is to mimic the PEPS construction procedure using <lb/>a physical two-body Hamiltonian, wherein the &quot; virtual &quot; <lb/>qubits are real physical systems and the resulting PEPS <lb/>state is encoded into logical qubits. Consider a regular <lb/>lattice. Let L denote the set of sites, each with coordina-<lb/>tion number c. We assign c qubits to each site, and label <lb/>with a double index (µ, i), with µ ∈ L and i = 1, 2, . . . , c. <lb/> (The choice of the second label i is completely arbitrary.) <lb/>Let σ <lb/> x <lb/> (µ,i)  and σ <lb/> z <lb/> (µ,i)  denote the Pauli X and Z operators <lb/>for the ith qubit at site µ ∈ L. Following the PEPS <lb/>construction, if a site µ is connected to a site ν by a <lb/>bond (denoted µ ∼ ν), then we associate qubit (µ, i) and <lb/>(ν, i) for some i to this bond. (We note that this notation <lb/>can become problematic with certain periodic conditions, <lb/>but it should be clear from the context how to adjust it <lb/>appropriately.) <lb/>Our PEPS Hamiltonian is defined as follows. At each <lb/>site, we require a two-body Hamiltonian with a two-<lb/>dimensional ground state space spanned by |00 . . . 0 and <lb/> |11 . . . 1. For this, we choose a site Hamiltonian H  0 <lb/> which is of Ising form <lb/> H  0  = − <lb/> µ∈L <lb/> i↔j <lb/> σ <lb/> z <lb/> (µ,i)  ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> (µ,j)  , <lb/> (4) <lb/>where i ↔ j denotes that qubits i and j are connected <lb/>according to some graph structure. Aside from being con-<lb/>nected, the specific form of this graph is relatively unim-<lb/>portant; however its structure will affect the energy lev-<lb/>els of the Hamiltonian. For example, for two-dimensional <lb/>lattices, it is natural to choose a ring structure. <lb/>Between sites, we define a different two-body interac-<lb/>tion of the form <lb/> V = − <lb/> µ∈L <lb/>c <lb/> i=1 <lb/> σ <lb/> x <lb/> (µ,i)  ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> (ν(i),i)  , <lb/> (5) <lb/>where ν(i) is the site connected to µ via bond i. With <lb/>this Hamiltonian, on every bond in the lattice µ ∼ ν <lb/> there are two terms: σ <lb/> x <lb/> (µ,i)  ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> (ν,i)  and σ <lb/> z <lb/> (µ,i)  ⊗ σ <lb/> x <lb/> (ν,i)  . <lb/>Note that the terms in V stabilise |C  2  , and therefore <lb/> ⊗  bonds  |C  2  is the ground state of V . This product of <lb/>maximally-entangled states is the starting point of the <lb/>PEPS construction. The site Hamiltonian H  0  is meant <lb/>to &quot; implement &quot; the PEPS projection by ensuring that <lb/>the qubits at a site act as a single logical qubit; to do so, <lb/>the site Hamiltonian H  0  must be much stronger than the <lb/>bond Hamiltonian V . One is then lead to consider the <lb/>ground state of the Hamiltonian <lb/> H = gH  0  + λV , <lb/> (6) <lb/>where g ≫ λ &gt; 0, which is suitable for perturbative <lb/>analysis in λ/g. <lb/> In [19], this procedure was applied to a square lattice. <lb/>The terms in the perturbation combine at higher orders <lb/>to yield the stabilisers of the logical cluster state, and <lb/>the resulting low-energy theory of the lattice is governed <lb/>by an effective Hamiltonian of the form of Eq. (1). Fur-<lb/>thermore, the gap to the next excited state is finite and <lb/></body>

			<page> 3 <lb/></page>

			<body> independent of the size of the lattice. Of course, because <lb/>this is a perturbative approach there will now be correc-<lb/>tions to the unperturbed logical eigenstates which will <lb/>not be in the logical space. So the exact cluster state <lb/>will not be obtained. However, these errors will be small <lb/>(occurring with probability (λ/g) <lb/> 2  , as we will show) and <lb/>so a state arbitrarily close to the cluster state can be ob-<lb/>tained. In what follows, this procedure is generalised to <lb/>other lattice structures important in quantum computa-<lb/>tion. <lb/> C. General properties of the PEPS Hamiltonian <lb/> 1. Duality transformation to uncoupled sites <lb/> We now present a simple duality transformation that <lb/>maps the Hamiltonian (6) to one describing uncoupled <lb/>sites. Consider decomposing (6) as a sum of commuting <lb/>terms H  µ  , as <lb/> H = <lb/> µ∈L <lb/> H  µ  , <lb/> (7) <lb/>where <lb/> H  µ  = −g <lb/> i↔j <lb/> σ <lb/> z <lb/> (µ,i)  ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> (µ,j)  − λ <lb/> c <lb/> i=1 <lb/> σ <lb/> x <lb/> (µ,i)  ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> (ν(i),i)  . (8) <lb/>Note that [H  µ  , H  ν  ] = 0 for µ  = ν. Define the unitary <lb/>transformation CS  L  to be the application of a CSIGN <lb/>gate <lb/>CSIGN : <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> σ <lb/> x  ⊗ I → σ <lb/> x  ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> σ <lb/> z  ⊗ I → σ <lb/> z  ⊗ I <lb/>I ⊗ σ <lb/> x <lb/> → σ <lb/> z  ⊗ σ <lb/> x <lb/> I ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> → I ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> (9) <lb/>to every bond on the lattice. The action of this transfor-<lb/>mation on the bond terms in the above Hamiltonian is <lb/>(CS  L  )σ <lb/> x <lb/> (µ,i)  ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> (ν(i),i)  (CS  L  ) = σ <lb/> x <lb/> (µ,i)  . Transforming each <lb/>term H  µ  thus yields <lb/> H <lb/> ′ <lb/> µ  = (CS  L  )H  µ  (CS  L  ) <lb/>= −g <lb/> i↔j <lb/> σ <lb/> z <lb/> (µ,i)  ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> (µ,j)  − λ <lb/> c <lb/> i=1 <lb/> σ <lb/> x <lb/> (µ,i)  , <lb/> (10) <lb/>which is localized entirely to the site µ. Thus, the duality <lb/>transformation CS  L  yields a Hamiltonian of uncoupled <lb/>sites, where each site Hamiltonian takes the form of a <lb/>transverse-field Ising model on some connected graph. <lb/>With this mapping, the spectrum of the Hamilto-<lb/>nian (6) can be calculated explicitly, with the Hamilto-<lb/>nian term H <lb/> ′ <lb/> µ  at each site, for example by using a Jordan-<lb/>Wigner transformation. We note at this point that each <lb/>Hamiltonian H <lb/> ′ <lb/> µ  has a nondegenerate ground state for <lb/>all λ &gt; 0; thus, our PEPS Hamiltonian on the full lattice <lb/>will also possess a nondegenerate ground state for λ &gt; 0. <lb/> 2. Encoded stabilizers: Constants of motion <lb/> For each site µ, define the operator <lb/> K  µ  := <lb/> c <lb/> i=1 <lb/> σ <lb/> x <lb/> (µ,i)  ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> (ν(i),i)  . <lb/> (11) <lb/>That is, K  µ  is the tensor product of σ <lb/> x  for every qubit at <lb/>site µ together with σ <lb/> z  on every neighbouring site. It is <lb/>straightforward to show that all such operators commute <lb/>with the Hamiltonian of Eq. (6), <lb/>[K  µ  , H] = 0 , ∀ µ ∈ L , <lb/> (12) <lb/>and with each other, <lb/>[K  µ  , K  ν  ] = 0 , ∀ µ, ν ∈ L . <lb/> (13) <lb/>Thus, if H has a nondegenerate ground state (as is the <lb/>case for the PEPS Hamiltonian with λ &gt; 0), it must also <lb/>be a simultaneous eigenstate of all operators K  µ  . <lb/>Using the duality transformation CS  L  defined above, <lb/>we find that <lb/>(CS  L  )K  µ  (CS  L  ) = <lb/> c <lb/> i=1 <lb/> σ <lb/> x <lb/> (µ,i)  . <lb/> (14) <lb/>Using the well-known solution to the transverse-field <lb/>Ising model with Hamiltonian (10), we find that the <lb/>ground state for λ &gt; 0 is the +1 eigenstate of this oper-<lb/>ator. (This can be inferred by the fact that the ground <lb/>state is clearly the +1 eigenstate of ⊗ <lb/> c <lb/>i=1  σ <lb/> x <lb/> (µ,i)  in the limit <lb/> λ/g → ∞.) Thus, we have that the ground state of the <lb/>PEPS Hamiltonian for λ &gt; 0 is the simultaneous +1 <lb/>eigenstate of all operators K  µ  , µ ∈ L. <lb/> The operators K  µ  , then, can be viewed as encoded clus-<lb/>ter stabilizers, and the ground state for λ &gt; 0 as an en-<lb/>coded cluster state. Unfortunately, for λ &gt; 0, this encod-<lb/>ing is no longer in the ground state space of H  0  spanned <lb/>locally at sites by the states |00 . . . 0 and |11 . . . 1. Our <lb/>perspective is to consider the encoding to be fixed in this <lb/>space and view the ground state of the PEPS Hamil-<lb/>tonian as the desired locally-encoded cluster state plus <lb/>perturbative corrections in λ/g. These concepts are best <lb/>illustrated through a simple example. <lb/> III. EXAMPLE: A 1-D LINE <lb/> First we illustrate this approach on the simplest lattice: <lb/>a one-dimensional line of qubits with periodic boundary <lb/>conditions. We demonstrate explicitly that the pertur-<lb/>bative procedure yields a low-energy effective Hamilto-<lb/>nian on the logical qubits of the form of Eq. (1), and <lb/>that an approximate cluster state is obtained as the non-<lb/>degenerate ground state. The basic steps outlined in this <lb/>example for the one-dimensional line, suitably general-<lb/>ized, will be applicable to more complex lattice struc-<lb/>tures. <lb/></body>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<body> lattice site (a logical qubit) <lb/> Insert 2 physical qubits <lb/>at every lattice site: <lb/>physical qubits <lb/> FIG. 1: The logical lattice and the physical lattice structure <lb/>for the 1D line. <lb/> Consider a one-dimensional line consisting of N  S  qubit <lb/>sites with periodic boundary conditions (i.e., a ring). The <lb/>coordination number of this lattice is c = 2, and thus <lb/>our construction requires two qubits to be placed at each <lb/>site. This lattice structure is illustrated in Fig. 1. The <lb/>Hamiltonian is that of Eq. (6). <lb/> A. The unperturbed spectrum <lb/> We first investigate the energy eigenvalue spectrum of <lb/>the unperturbed Hamiltonian gH  0  . Because gH  0  is a sum <lb/>of terms, each of the form σ <lb/> z  ⊗ σ <lb/> z  acting on a single site, <lb/>the energy spectrum can be determined by analysing each <lb/>site individually. At a single site, there are two energy <lb/>levels. The ground-state is degenerate, two-dimensional, <lb/>and spanned by the states <lb/> |00 =: |0  L  , |11 =: |1  L  . <lb/> (15) <lb/>The ground state space of the unperturbed Hamiltonian <lb/>at each site, then, can be viewed as a logical qubit. Note <lb/>also that this ground state space is, by construction, the <lb/>logical subspace for the cluster state PEPS projection. <lb/>The energy of this ground state space is −g. The first <lb/>excited state at each site is also two-dimensional, has an <lb/>energy of g, and is spanned by the states |01 and |10. <lb/> With the spectrum of gH  0  at each site, we now describe <lb/>the spectrum of the unperturbed Hamiltonian gH  0  on the <lb/>entire lattice. The lattice ground-state space is spanned <lb/>by product states of all of the individual sites in the <lb/>ground state (i.e. in the logical space). This ground-state <lb/>space has energy E <lb/> (0) <lb/>0  = −gN  S  , is 2 <lb/> NS  -dimensional, and <lb/>is spanned by all logical states of N  S  qubits. We denote <lb/>this space H  L  . The first-excited space is (2N  S  · 2 <lb/> NS−1  )-<lb/>dimensional, and has energy E <lb/> (0) <lb/>1 <lb/> = −g(N  S  − 2). Thus, <lb/>for the unperturbed Hamiltonian gH  0  , the gap from the <lb/>ground to first-excited space is 2g. The second-excited <lb/>space has energy E <lb/> (0) <lb/>2 <lb/> = −g(N  S  − 4), and so on. These <lb/>energies will serve as the zeroth-order energies in pertur-<lb/>bation theory for the total Hamiltonian. <lb/> B. Perturbation theory <lb/> We now turn to perturbation theory and determine the <lb/>effect of the term λV in the Hamiltonian (6). We will <lb/> |00&gt; <lb/>|11&gt; <lb/>{ |01&gt; , |10&gt; } <lb/>Energy <lb/>+g <lb/>-g <lb/>σ x <lb/> σ x <lb/> FIG. 2: The effect of the σ <lb/> x  terms in V on a single site. <lb/> show that this term lifts degeneracy of the ground state, <lb/>and that the logical cluster state arises as the unique <lb/>ground state (although we also show that there are per-<lb/>turbative corrections to this state). For details of our use <lb/>of perturbation theory and notation, see the Appendix. <lb/>Let the nth-order energy correction to the jth state in <lb/> H  L  be denoted by λ <lb/> n  E <lb/> (n) <lb/>0j  . Let P  L  be the projection onto <lb/>the degenerate ground state space of the unperturbed <lb/>Hamiltonian gH  0  , i.e., onto the &quot; logical &quot; space H  L  . De-<lb/>fine ¯ <lb/> P  L  := I − P  L  to be the projection onto the &quot; illogical <lb/>space &quot; (denoted H¯  L  ) and let the projection onto the jth <lb/> unperturbed excited level be denoted P  j  . <lb/>To obtain a conceptual view of the perturbation it is <lb/>useful to see the effect of V on a single site. The Hamilto-<lb/>nian V is a sum of terms of the form −σ <lb/> z  ⊗ σ <lb/> x  ; however, <lb/>each of the Pauli operators in such a term act on differ-<lb/>ent sites, and so we must consider the action of σ <lb/> x  and <lb/> σ <lb/> z  separately. Because the logical space H  L  is spanned <lb/>by |00 and |11, the action of σ <lb/> x  will move a site out of <lb/>the logical space; the action of σ <lb/> z  will not, and simply <lb/>induce a phase. The possible actions by the σ <lb/> x  part of <lb/> V at a single site are shown in Fig. 2. <lb/>The first-order corrections to the energy are governed <lb/>by the operator (see Eq. (A15) in the Appendix) <lb/> θ <lb/> (1)  = P  L  V P  L  . <lb/> (16) <lb/>Specifically, the first order energy corrections E <lb/> (1) <lb/>0j  to the <lb/>ground state are the eigenvalues of this operator. Because <lb/>all of the terms in V contain a single σ <lb/> x  , they all move <lb/>a state in the logical space to the first excited state (i.e., <lb/> V P  L  = P  1  V P  L  ). Thus, P  L  V P  L  = 0, and there is no <lb/>first-order correction to the energies. <lb/>The second-order corrections are governed by the op-<lb/>erator <lb/> θ <lb/> (2)  = P  L  V ¯ <lb/> P  L  (E <lb/> (0) <lb/>0  − gH  0  ) <lb/> −1  ¯ <lb/> P  L  V P  L <lb/> = <lb/> P  L  V P  1  V P  L <lb/> (E <lb/> (0) <lb/>0  − E <lb/> (0) <lb/>1  ) <lb/> . <lb/> (17) <lb/>where the expression has been simplified using V P  L  = <lb/> P  1  V P  L  . The operator P  L  V P  1  V P  L  maps states from the <lb/></body>

			<page> 5 <lb/></page>

			<body> ground state space to the first excited space and then <lb/>back to ground state space. By investigating the differ-<lb/>ent ways of returning to the logical space after just two <lb/> σ <lb/> x  operations, it is clear that there are two possible con-<lb/>tributions to this term: <lb/>1. If σ <lb/> z  ⊗ σ <lb/> x  in V is applied twice to the same bond, <lb/>it yields the identity. The first σ <lb/> x  can be applied to <lb/>any of the qubits and then must be applied again <lb/>to the same qubit, so there are 2N  S  of these terms. <lb/>2. If σ <lb/> x  is applied to each of the two qubits at a site <lb/>(and corresponding σ <lb/> z  operations to qubits in the <lb/>neighboring sites), then the lattice remains in the <lb/>ground state. We can apply the first σ <lb/> x  to either of <lb/>the two qubits at the site and so there will be two <lb/>of these terms that occur at each site. Explicitly, <lb/>this case will be a term applied to the logical space <lb/>of the form <lb/> K  µ  := <lb/> i=1,2 <lb/> σ <lb/> x <lb/> (µ,i)  ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> (ν(i),i)  , <lb/> (18) <lb/>where µ ∼ ν. <lb/> The operator S  µ  := P  L  K  µ  P  L  , which acts only on <lb/>the logical space, can be determined explicitly as <lb/>follows. Note that the product of two σ <lb/> x  opera-<lb/>tors on a single site µ (one on each physical qubit), <lb/>restricted to the logical space, is equivalent to a <lb/> logical X operator <lb/> X  µ  := P  L  σ <lb/> x <lb/> (µ,1)  σ <lb/> x <lb/> (µ,2)  P  L  . <lb/> (19) <lb/>Also, a single σ <lb/> z  operator acting on either of the <lb/>two physical qubits at a site ν, restricted to the <lb/>logical space, is equivalent to a logical Z operator <lb/> Z  ν  := P  L  σ <lb/> z <lb/> (ν,i)  P  L  . <lb/> (20) <lb/>Thus, S  µ  = X  µ  ⊗  ν∼µ  Z  ν  . This operator is a (logical) <lb/>stabilizer of the cluster state on this lattice. <lb/>Therefore, we have <lb/> P  L  V P  1  V P  L  = 2N  S  P  L  + 2 <lb/> µ∈L <lb/> S  µ  . <lb/> (21) <lb/>Substituting this result into Eq. (17) and using E <lb/> (0) <lb/>0  − <lb/> E <lb/> (0) <lb/>1  = −2g gives <lb/> θ <lb/> (2)  = <lb/>2N  S  P  L  + 2 <lb/> µ∈L  S  µ <lb/> −2g <lb/> . <lb/> (22) <lb/>The energies E <lb/> (2) <lb/>0j  are the eigenvalues of θ <lb/> (2)  and the cor-<lb/>responding eigenstates of θ <lb/> (2)  will be the zeroth-order <lb/>energy eigenstates after the degeneracy is lifted. <lb/>Next, we identify the basis which diagonalises θ <lb/> (2)  ; <lb/>this is straightforward given the expression (22). As <lb/>the cluster state is the simultaneous +1 eigenstate of all <lb/>stabilizer operators S  µ  , the logical cluster state on this <lb/>lattice, denoted by |C, is an eigenstate of θ <lb/> (2)  . Simi-<lb/>larly, the other eigenstates of θ <lb/> (2)  are also just the si-<lb/>multaneous eigenstates of the stabilizers S  µ  (as all such <lb/>stabilizers commute). Explicitly, let |C{α, β, . . .} de-<lb/>note the logical cluster state with a logical Z-operator <lb/> (called a Z-error ) applied to the sites α, β, . . . ∈ L. Us-<lb/>ing the anti-commutation relations of the Pauli matri-<lb/>ces, |C{α, β, . . .} is the −1 eigenstate of S  α  , S  β  , ... and <lb/>the +1 eigenstate of S  µ  for µ  = α, β, . . .. Therefore, <lb/>the 2 <lb/> NS  states of the form |C{α, β, . . .} will be eigen-<lb/>states of θ <lb/> (2)  . Furthermore, these states are orthogonal, <lb/>as each pair of states will have a differing eigenvalue for <lb/>least one of the S  µ  operators. In summary, the set of <lb/>states {|C, |C{α}, |C{α, β}, . . .}, running over logical <lb/> Z-errors at all possible sites, forms an orthogonal basis <lb/>of H  L  and diagonalises θ <lb/> (2)  . <lb/>The eigenvalue spectrum of θ <lb/> (2)  is then straightforward <lb/>to calculate using the properties of stabilisers. From the <lb/>form of θ <lb/> (2)  in Eq. (22), the lowest energy eigenstate will <lb/>be the cluster state |C, because it is an eigenstate of <lb/>all stabilisers in the sum <lb/> µ∈L  S  µ  with eigenvalue +1. <lb/>Thus the second-order correction for the energy associ-<lb/>ated with the cluster state is <lb/> λ <lb/> 2  E <lb/> (2) <lb/> |C  = <lb/>2N  S  + 2N  S <lb/> −2g <lb/> λ <lb/> 2  = −2N  S <lb/> λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> g <lb/>. <lb/> (23) <lb/>Next, consider a state |C{α} = Z  α  |C, a cluster state <lb/>with a single Z-error at the site α. This state is also <lb/>an eigenstate of all stabilizers in the sum <lb/> µ∈L  S  µ  with <lb/>eigenvalue +1 except the stabilizer S  α  for which it has <lb/>eigenvalue −1. Therefore, <lb/> λ <lb/> 2  E <lb/> (2) <lb/> |C{α}  = <lb/>2N  S  + 2(N  S  − 2) <lb/> −2g <lb/> λ <lb/> 2  = −2(N  S  − 1) <lb/> λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> g <lb/>. <lb/> (24) <lb/>Because there are N  S  states of the form |C{α}, this <lb/>1 <lb/> st  excited space is N  S  -dimensional. Similarly, the nth <lb/> excited space up to n = N  S  is <lb/>  NS <lb/>n <lb/> -dimensional and (to <lb/>zeroth order) is spanned by states obtained from |C by <lb/> n logical Z-errors. <lb/> Higher order corrections can be calculated by following <lb/>a similar procedure. As noted in Sec. II C 1, this Hamil-<lb/>tonian can be easily solved exactly, with a ground state <lb/>energy given by <lb/> E  |C  = −gN  S <lb/> 1 + 4 <lb/> λ  2 <lb/> g  2  . <lb/> (25) <lb/>There is an energy gap <lb/>∆ := g <lb/> 1 + 4 <lb/> λ  2 <lb/> g  2  − 1 <lb/> ≃ 2λ <lb/> 2  /g + O(λ <lb/> 3  /g <lb/> 2  ) , <lb/> (26) <lb/>to the first excited space; all higher levels have energy <lb/> E  n  = E  |C  + n∆. Note that ∆ is independent of N  S  , the <lb/></body>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<body> size of the lattice. Intuitively, then, one may associate <lb/>logical Z errors on any site with a fixed energy ∆ each. <lb/>In summary, we have shown that the non-degenerate <lb/>ground state of the Hamiltonian H = gH  0  + λV is the <lb/>cluster state, to zeroth order in λ/g, with an energy gap <lb/>to the second excited state scaling as ∼ λ <lb/> 2  /g. <lb/> C. Perturbative corrections to the ground state <lb/> We have shown that, to zeroth order in λ/g, the ground <lb/>state of the system is the logical cluster state |C. How-<lb/>ever, the perturbation will also modify the energy eigen-<lb/>states from their unperturbed states. To first order in V , <lb/>the perturbed ground state |E  0  is given (up to normal-<lb/>ization) as <lb/> |E  0  ∝ |C + λ <lb/> |j∈H  ¯ <lb/> L <lb/> j|V |C <lb/> E <lb/> (0) <lb/>0  − E <lb/> (0) <lb/> j <lb/> |j <lb/> + <lb/> |l∈HL,|l =|C <lb/> l|θ <lb/> (3)  |C <lb/> E <lb/> (2) <lb/> |C  − E <lb/> (2) <lb/> l <lb/> |l <lb/> , (27) <lb/>where <lb/> θ <lb/> (3)  = P  L  V [(E <lb/> (0) <lb/>0  − H  0  ) <lb/> −1  ¯ <lb/> P  L  V ] <lb/> 2  P  L  . <lb/> (28) <lb/>For this perturbation, θ <lb/> (3)  = 0; however, there exist <lb/>states |j ∈ H¯  L  such that j|V |C <lb/> = 0. <lb/>Note that V is a sum of 2N  S  terms of the form σ <lb/> x  ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> acting across a bond. Each of these terms applied to |C <lb/> gives an excited state of the form <lb/> |k  (µ,i)  := σ <lb/> x <lb/> (µ,i)  ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> (ν(i),i)  |C . <lb/> (29) <lb/>Using the anti-commutation relations of the Pauli matri-<lb/>ces, the terms in H  0  act on |k  (µ,i)  as <lb/>(σ <lb/> z <lb/> (µ,i)  ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> (µ,i+1)  )|k  (µ,i)  = −|k  (µ,i)  , <lb/> (30) <lb/>(σ <lb/> z <lb/> (ρ,i)  ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> (ρ,i+1)  )|k  (µ,i)  = |k  (µ,i)  , ρ  = µ . <lb/> (31) <lb/>Hence gH  0  |k  (µ,i)  = −g(N  S  − 2)|k  (µ,i)  = E <lb/> (0) <lb/>1  |k  (µ,i)  , <lb/> and therefore the states |k  (µ,i)  are in the first excited <lb/>space of gH  0  . Eq. (31) also shows that |k  (µ1,i1)  and <lb/> |k  (µ2,i2)  for µ  1  = µ  2  are eigenvectors with different <lb/>eigenvalues for the operator σ <lb/> z <lb/> (µ1,1)  ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> (µ1,2)  and thus <lb/>they are orthogonal. However, recalling from earlier <lb/>that K  µ  := ⊗ <lb/> 2 <lb/> i=1  σ <lb/> x <lb/> (µ,i)  ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> (ν(i),i)  stabilises |C, we have <lb/>that k  (µ,1)  |k  (µ,2)  = C|K  µ  |C = 1 and thus |k  (µ,1)  = <lb/> |k  (µ,2)  . Hence k  (µ,1)  |V |C = 2, and <lb/> |E  0  ∝ |C + λ <lb/> µ∈L <lb/> k  (µ,1)  |V |C <lb/> E <lb/> (0) <lb/>0  − E <lb/> (0) <lb/>1 <lb/> |k  (µ,1)  <lb/>∝ |C − <lb/> λ <lb/>g <lb/> µ∈L <lb/> |k  (µ,1)  . <lb/> (32) <lb/>There are N  S  states in the above sum, which determines <lb/>the normalization. Thus, we can calculate the fidelity <lb/> F = |C|E  0  | <lb/> 2  of the ground state with the exact cluster <lb/>state, which in this case is found to be <lb/> F = <lb/>1 <lb/>1 + N  S  λ  2  /g  2  . <lb/> (33) <lb/>This fidelity decays rapidly for increasing N  S  , which is <lb/>unsurprising given that it is comparing quantum states <lb/>on a large lattice and is an extensive quantity. For any <lb/>lattice system with N  S  large, this fidelity is known to <lb/>scale as F = d <lb/> NS  , where d is an intensive quantity that <lb/>can be interpreted as the average fidelity per site [23]. <lb/>Precisely, <lb/>log d := lim <lb/> NS→∞ <lb/> N <lb/> −1 <lb/> S  log F , <lb/> (34) <lb/>which is found to satisfy <lb/>log d = −N <lb/> −1 <lb/> S  log(1 + N  S  λ <lb/> 2  /g <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> &gt; −N <lb/> −1 <lb/> S  log(1 + λ <lb/> 2  /g <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> NS <lb/> = − log(1 + λ <lb/> 2  /g <lb/> 2  ) . <lb/> (35) <lb/>Thus d &gt; (1 + λ <lb/> 2  /g <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> −1  , which is independent of N  S  . <lb/>This result demonstrates that the ground state is &quot; close &quot; <lb/>to the ideal cluster state, as quantified by a large average <lb/>fidelity per site, for λ ≪ g. <lb/> IV. UNIVERSAL RESOURCES FOR MBQC <lb/> Although it serves as an illustrative example of the <lb/>techniques presented in this paper, the cluster state on <lb/>a line is not a universal resource for MBQC; a higher-<lb/>dimensional lattice is required. In this section, we apply <lb/>the perturbative procedure to lattice structures that are <lb/>interesting from a MBQC perspective, and comment on <lb/>their utility. <lb/> A. Hexagonal lattice <lb/> For a hexagonal lattice in two dimensions with N  S  sites <lb/>and periodic boundary conditions, the coordination num-<lb/>ber is 3, and we require three physical qubits at each site <lb/>(see Fig. 3). The Hamiltonian for the lattice is again <lb/>given by Eq. (6). <lb/>We investigate the spectrum of the unperturbed <lb/>Hamiltonian gH  0  by considering its action at a single <lb/>site, where the three site qubits interact via the Ising <lb/>coupling on a ring. The ground-state is degenerate, two-<lb/>dimensional, and spanned by the states <lb/> |000 =: |0  L  , |111 =: |1  L  , <lb/> (36) <lb/>which encode our logical qubit. The energy of this <lb/>ground state space is −3g. The first excited state is <lb/></body>

			<page> 7 <lb/></page>

			<body> |000&gt; <lb/> |111&gt; <lb/> { |100&gt; , |010&gt; <lb/>, |001&gt;} <lb/> Energy <lb/>+g <lb/>-3g <lb/>σ x <lb/> σ x <lb/> { |011&gt; , |101&gt; <lb/>, |110&gt;} <lb/> σ x <lb/> FIG. 3: The hexagonal lattice structure, and the effect of the σ <lb/> x  terms in V on a single site. <lb/> six-dimensional, and has an energy of g. Thus, for <lb/>the entire lattice of N  S  sites, the ground-state space <lb/>has energy E <lb/> (0) <lb/> 0 <lb/> = −3gN  S  , is 2 <lb/> NS  -dimensional, and is <lb/>spanned by all logical states of N  S  qubits. The first-<lb/>excited space is (6N  S  · 2 <lb/> NS−1  )-dimensional, and has en-<lb/>ergy E <lb/> (0) <lb/>1  = −g(3N  S  − 4). <lb/>We now turn to perturbation theory. It is again useful <lb/>to obtain a conceptual view of the effect of V on a single <lb/>site, as illustrated in Fig. 3. As the ground state space is <lb/>spanned by |000 and |111 at each site, only the action of <lb/> σ <lb/> x  (and not σ <lb/> z  ) will map states out of the logical ground <lb/>state space. The possible actions by the σ <lb/> x  part of V at <lb/>a single site are shown in Fig. 3. Once again, P  L  V P  L  = 0 <lb/>and there is no first-order correction to the energies. <lb/>The second order corrections E <lb/> (2) <lb/>0j  are the eigenvalues <lb/>of the operator θ <lb/> (2)  defined in Eq. (A17). To evaluate the <lb/>operator P  L  V P  1  V P  L  , we examine Fig. 3 and the ways of <lb/>returning to the logical space after just two applications <lb/>of V . It is clear that there is only one possible contribu-<lb/>tion: if a σ <lb/> z  ⊗ σ <lb/> x  in V is applied twice to the same bond, <lb/>this will yield the identity. The first σ <lb/> x  can be applied <lb/>to any of the qubits and then must be applied again to <lb/>the same qubit, so there are 3N  S  such terms. Hence <lb/> P  L  V P  1  V P  L  = 3N  S  P  L  . <lb/> (37) <lb/>Using this result in Eq. (22) as well as E <lb/> (0) <lb/>0  − E <lb/> (0) <lb/>1  = −4g <lb/> gives <lb/> θ <lb/> (2)  = <lb/>3N  S  P  L <lb/> (−4g) <lb/> . <lb/> (38) <lb/>This operator simply acts as the identity on the logical <lb/>space and so there is a constant second-order correction <lb/>to the ground-state energy – an energy shift – given by <lb/> λ <lb/> 2  E <lb/> (2) <lb/>0  = − <lb/> 3N  S  λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> 4g <lb/> . <lb/> (39) <lb/>The energy degeneracy of the ground state has still not <lb/>been broken at second order and we must proceed to <lb/>third order. <lb/>The third order corrections E <lb/> (3) <lb/>0j  are the eigenvalues of <lb/>the operator θ <lb/> (3)  given by <lb/> θ <lb/> (3)  = P  L  V <lb/> (E <lb/> (0) <lb/>0  − H  0  ) <lb/> −1  ¯ <lb/> P  L  V <lb/>  2  P  L <lb/> = <lb/> P  L  V P  1  V P  1  V P  L <lb/> (E <lb/> (0) <lb/>0  − E <lb/> (0) <lb/>1  )  2 <lb/> , <lb/> (40) <lb/>where the expression has been simplified using V P  L  = <lb/> P  1  V P  L  . With three applications of the perturbation <lb/> V , the operator P  L  V P  1  V P  1  V P  L  maps states out of the <lb/>ground state space and then back again via the first ex-<lb/>cited space. Again investigating Fig. 3, it is only possible <lb/>for the lattice to remain in the ground state after three <lb/>perturbation terms if σ <lb/> x  operators are applied to each <lb/>of the three qubits at a site (and, through V , the corre-<lb/>sponding σ <lb/> z  operators to the qubits on each of the neigh-<lb/>boring sites). That is, this case will be a term applied to <lb/>the logical space of the form <lb/> K  µ  := <lb/> i=1,2,3 <lb/> σ <lb/> x <lb/> (µ,i)  ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> (ν(i),i)  , <lb/> (41) <lb/>where ν(i) is the site connected to (µ, i) by a bond. Just <lb/>as in the case of the line, the operator K  µ  acts on the <lb/>logical space as S  µ  := P  L  K  µ  P  L  = X  µ <lb/> ν∼µ  Z  ν  , a logical <lb/>cluster-state stabilizer operator. The three qubits at the <lb/>site can be ordered in 3! possible ways, and so there will <lb/></body>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<body> be 3! of these terms that occur at each site. Therefore, <lb/> P  L  V P  1  V P  1  V P  L  = −3! <lb/> µ∈L <lb/> S  µ  , <lb/> (42) <lb/>and <lb/> θ <lb/> (3)  = <lb/> −3! <lb/> µ∈L  S  µ <lb/> (−4g)  2 <lb/> = − <lb/> 3 <lb/>8g  2 <lb/> µ∈L <lb/> S  µ  . <lb/> (43) <lb/>Once again, as in the line, the set of 2 <lb/> NS  states <lb/> {|C, |C{α}, |C{α, β}, . . .}, running over logical Z-<lb/> errors on the cluster state |C at all possible sites, forms <lb/>an orthogonal basis of H  L  and diagonalises θ <lb/> (3)  . The <lb/>cluster state |C is the unique lowest eigenstate of θ <lb/> (3)  . <lb/>The third-order correction for the energy associated with <lb/>this state is <lb/> λ <lb/> 3  E <lb/> (3) <lb/> |C  = − <lb/> 3 <lb/>8 <lb/> N  S <lb/> λ <lb/> 3 <lb/> g  2  . <lb/> (44) <lb/>Again, this case is simple enough to analyze analytically; <lb/>the ground state of the Hamiltonian H = gH  0  + λV has <lb/>energy <lb/> E  |C  = −gN  S <lb/> 1 + <lb/> λ <lb/>g <lb/> + 2 <lb/> λ  2 <lb/> g  2  + <lb/> λ <lb/>g <lb/> + 1 <lb/> ≃ −3gN  S <lb/> 1 + <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/> λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> g  2  + <lb/>1 <lb/>8 <lb/> λ <lb/> 3 <lb/> g  3 <lb/> . <lb/> (45) <lb/>The nth excited space up to n = N  S  is <lb/>  NS <lb/>n <lb/> -dimensional <lb/>and is spanned (to zeroth order) by states obtained from <lb/> |C with n logical Z errors. These states have energy <lb/> E  n  = E  |C  + n∆ where <lb/>∆ := 2 <lb/> λ <lb/>g <lb/> − <lb/> λ  2 <lb/> g  2  + <lb/> λ <lb/>g <lb/> + 1 + <lb/> λ  2 <lb/> g  2  − <lb/> λ <lb/>g <lb/> + 1 <lb/> ≃ <lb/> 3 <lb/>4 <lb/> λ <lb/> 3 <lb/> g  2  + O(λ <lb/> 4  /g <lb/> 3  ) . <lb/> (46) <lb/>We can also calculate the first-order corrections to <lb/>the ground state |C, by finding states |j ∈ H¯  L  such <lb/>that j|V |C <lb/> = 0. As before, define |k  (µ,i)  := σ <lb/> x <lb/> (µ,i)  ⊗ <lb/> σ <lb/> z <lb/> (ν(i),i)  |C. By determining the effect of each of the terms <lb/>in gH  0  on |k  (µ,i)  it is clear that they are in the first ex-<lb/>cited space of gH  0  and are orthogonal to each other. To <lb/>first order in λ/g, <lb/> |E  0  ∝ |C − <lb/> λ <lb/> 4g <lb/> µ∈L <lb/> 3 <lb/> i=1 <lb/> |k  (µ,i)  . <lb/> (47) <lb/>Comparing this ground state with the ideal cluster state, <lb/>we find that the average fidelity per site d is bounded by <lb/> d &gt; (1 + 3λ <lb/> 2  /(4g) <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> −1  . <lb/> B. Square lattice <lb/> We now repeat the above procedure for a 2D square <lb/>lattice with N  S  sites and periodic boundary conditions. <lb/>This case was originally examined in [19]; however, our <lb/>detailed derivation reveals some errors in their calcula-<lb/>tion of the perturbed energies and the gap. <lb/>The coordination number of this lattice is 4, and so <lb/>four physical qubits are necessary at each site (see Fig. 4). <lb/>The Hamiltonian for the lattice is again given by Eq. (6), <lb/>again with a ring of four qubits coupled via an Ising in-<lb/>teraction. There are now three energy levels of gH  0  at <lb/>a single site. The ground-state space of gH  0  at a single <lb/>site is spanned by the states <lb/> |0000 =: |0  L  , |1111 =: |1  L  , <lb/> (48) <lb/>and the energy of this ground state space is −4g. The <lb/>first excited state is twelve-dimensional, and has an en-<lb/>ergy of 0. The second excited state is two-dimensional <lb/>and has a energy of 4g. So, for the entire lattice of N  S <lb/> sites, the ground-state space has energy E <lb/> (0) <lb/>0 <lb/> = −4gN  S  , <lb/>is 2 <lb/> NS  -dimensional, and is spanned by all logical states <lb/>of N  S  qubits. The first-excited space has energy E <lb/> (0) <lb/>1  = <lb/> −4g(N  S  − 1) and the second-excited space has energy <lb/> E <lb/> (0) <lb/>2  = −4g(N  S  − 2). <lb/>The possible actions by the σ <lb/> x  part of V at a single <lb/>site are shown in Fig. 4. We now follow the identical <lb/>procedure as done previously, and find <lb/> θ <lb/> (1)  = 0 , <lb/> (49) <lb/> θ <lb/> (2)  = <lb/>4N  S  P  L <lb/> (−4g) <lb/> , <lb/> (50) <lb/> θ <lb/> (3)  = 0 , <lb/> (51) <lb/> θ <lb/> (4)  = − <lb/> 5 <lb/>16g  3 <lb/> µ∈L <lb/> S  µ  − <lb/> N  S <lb/> 16g  3  P  L  . <lb/> (52) <lb/>That is, there are no first-or third-order corrections <lb/>to the energy; at second-order there is a constant en-<lb/>ergy shift λ <lb/> 2  E <lb/> (2) <lb/>0 <lb/> = −N  S  λ <lb/> 2  /g to the ground state; at <lb/>fourth-order the degeneracy is broken. In the expres-<lb/>sion for θ <lb/> (4)  , the first term is recognized as propor-<lb/>tional to the cluster Hamiltonian: the sum of stabilis-<lb/>ers of the cluster state S  µ  . Therefore the set of 2 <lb/> NS <lb/> states {|C, |C{α}, |C{α, β}, . . .}, running over logical <lb/> Z-errors at all possible sites on the cluster state |C, is <lb/>an orthogonal basis of H  L  which diagonalises θ <lb/> (4)  . <lb/>The cluster state |C is the unique lowest eigenstate <lb/>of θ <lb/> (4)  , because it is an eigenstate of all stabilisers in <lb/>the sum <lb/> µ∈L  S  µ  with eigenvalue +1. The fourth-order <lb/>correction for the energy associated with this state is <lb/> λ <lb/> 4  E <lb/> (4) <lb/> |C  = − <lb/> 3 <lb/>8 <lb/> N  S <lb/> λ <lb/> 4 <lb/> g  3  . <lb/> (53) <lb/>We note that this result differs, by numerical factors, <lb/>from the result of [19]. (The error in [19] arises from <lb/></body>

			<page> 9 <lb/></page>

			<body> |0000&gt; <lb/> |1111&gt; <lb/> { |1000&gt; , |0100&gt;, <lb/>|0010&gt;, |0001&gt;} <lb/> Energy <lb/>0 <lb/>-4g <lb/>σ x <lb/> σ x <lb/> { |0111&gt; , |1101&gt;, <lb/>|1101&gt;, |1110&gt;} <lb/> σ x <lb/> { |1010&gt; , |0101&gt;} <lb/> σ x <lb/> σ x <lb/> { |1100&gt; , |0011&gt;, <lb/>|0110&gt;, |1001&gt;} <lb/> σ x <lb/> 4g <lb/> FIG. 4: The square lattice structure, and the effect of the σ <lb/> x  terms in V on a single site. <lb/> missing contributions to the perturbation operator θ <lb/> (4) <lb/> in Eq. (52).) Higher-order corrections follow in a similar <lb/>fashion, and a complete analytic solution for the ground <lb/>state energy is found to be <lb/> E  |C  = −2gN  S <lb/> 2 + 2 <lb/> λ  2 <lb/> g  2  + 2 <lb/> λ  4 <lb/> g  4  + 1 <lb/> ≃ −4gN  S <lb/> 1 + <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/> λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> g  2  + <lb/>3 <lb/>32 <lb/> λ <lb/> 4 <lb/> g  4 <lb/> . <lb/> (54) <lb/>The nth excited space up to n = N  S  is <lb/>  NS <lb/>n <lb/> -<lb/>dimensional and is spanned (to zeroth order) by states <lb/>obtained from |C by n logical Z errors. These states <lb/>have energy E  n  = E  |C  + n∆, where <lb/>∆ := −2g <lb/> 1 + <lb/> λ  2 <lb/> g  2  + 1 + <lb/> 2 + 2 <lb/> λ  2 <lb/> g  2  + 2 <lb/> λ  4 <lb/> g  4  + 1 <lb/> ≃ <lb/> 5 <lb/>8 <lb/> λ <lb/> 4 <lb/> g  3  . <lb/> (55) <lb/>Once again we can also calculate the first-order correc-<lb/>tions to the ground state |C is calculated to be <lb/> |E  0  ∝ |C − <lb/> λ <lb/> 4g <lb/> µ∈L <lb/> 4 <lb/> i=1 <lb/> |k  (µ,i)  , <lb/> (56) <lb/>where |k  (µ,i)  := σ <lb/> x <lb/> (µ,i)  ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> (ν(i),i)  |C. Comparing this <lb/>ground state with the ideal cluster state, we again find <lb/>that the average fidelity per site d is bounded by d &gt; <lb/> (1 + 4λ <lb/> 2  /(4g) <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> −1  . <lb/> C. Cubic lattice <lb/> We apply the now familiar procedure to a cubic lattice <lb/>in three dimensions with N  S  sites and periodic boundary <lb/>conditions. The coordination number is 6, and so six <lb/>physical qubits are necessary at each site (see Fig. 5). <lb/>The Hamiltonian for the lattice is given in Eq. (6), where <lb/>we arrange the 6 qubits on the vertices of a octahedron, <lb/>and place σ <lb/> z  ⊗ σ <lb/> z  couplings between all qubits connected <lb/>by an edge of the octahedron, as in Fig. 5. There are four <lb/>energy levels of gH  0  at a single site; the ground-state is <lb/>degenerate, two-dimensional, and spanned by the states <lb/> |000000 =: |0  L  , |111111 =: |1  L  . <lb/> (57) <lb/>The energy of this ground state space is −12g; the first <lb/>excited state space has energy −4g; the second excited <lb/>state space has energy 0; the third excited state space <lb/>has energy 4g. <lb/>The possible actions of σ <lb/> x  at a single site are shown in <lb/>Fig. 5. Again following our general perturbative proce-<lb/>dure we find θ <lb/> (1)  = θ <lb/> (3)  = θ <lb/> (5)  = 0 and <lb/> θ <lb/> (2)  = − <lb/> 6N  S <lb/> 8g <lb/> P  L  , <lb/> (58) <lb/> θ <lb/> (4)  = − <lb/> N  S <lb/> 256g  3  P  L  , <lb/> (59) <lb/> θ <lb/> (6)  = − <lb/> 13N  S <lb/> 49152g  5  P  L  − <lb/> 83 <lb/>16384g  5 <lb/> µ∈L <lb/> S  µ  . <lb/> (60) <lb/>Thus, there are two constant energy shifts at second and <lb/>fourth order of <lb/> λ <lb/> 2  E <lb/> (2) <lb/>0  = − <lb/> 3N  S  λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> 4g <lb/> , <lb/>λ <lb/> 4  E <lb/> (4) <lb/>0  = − <lb/> N  S  λ <lb/> 4 <lb/> 256g  3  . <lb/> (61) <lb/>In the expression for θ <lb/> (6)  , the degeneracy is broken by the <lb/>terms S  µ  = X  µ  ⊗  ν∼µ  Z  ν  which are the cluster stabiliz-<lb/>ers. The set of 2 <lb/> NS  states {|C, |C{α}, |C{α, β}, . . .}, <lb/> running over logical Z-errors at all possible sites of the <lb/>cluster state |C, forms an orthogonal basis of H  L  which <lb/>diagonalises θ <lb/> (6)  . <lb/></body>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>

			<body> |000000&gt; <lb/> |111111&gt; <lb/> { |110000&gt;, <lb/>|101000&gt;, ...} <lb/> Energy <lb/>0 <lb/>-12g <lb/> { |001111&gt;, <lb/>|010111&gt;,...} <lb/>{ |100001&gt;, ...} <lb/>{ |111000&gt;, ...&gt;} <lb/> 4g <lb/> { |100000&gt;, ...} <lb/>{ |011111&gt;,...} <lb/>{ |110001&gt;, ...} <lb/>{ |011110&gt;, ...} <lb/>σ x <lb/> -4g <lb/> σ x <lb/> σ x <lb/> σ x <lb/> σ x <lb/> σ x <lb/> σ <lb/> x <lb/> σ <lb/> x <lb/> σ x <lb/> σ x <lb/> σ x <lb/> σ <lb/> x <lb/> FIG. 5: The cubic lattice structure, and the effect of the σ <lb/> x  terms in V on a single site. <lb/> The cluster state |C is the unique lowest eigenstate of <lb/> θ <lb/> (6)  . The sixth-order correction for the energy associated <lb/>with this state is <lb/> λ <lb/> 6  E <lb/> (6) <lb/> |C  = − <lb/> 131 <lb/>24576 <lb/> N  S <lb/> λ <lb/> 6 <lb/> g  5  . <lb/> (62) <lb/>Therefore, to sixth order, the energy of the ground state <lb/>is <lb/> E  |C  = −12gN  S <lb/> 1 + <lb/>1 <lb/>16 <lb/> λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> g  2  + <lb/>1 <lb/>3 · 2  10 <lb/> λ <lb/> 4 <lb/> g  4  + <lb/>131 <lb/>3  2  · 2  15 <lb/> λ <lb/> 6 <lb/> g  6 <lb/> . <lb/> (63) <lb/>The nth excited space up to n = N  S  is <lb/>  NS <lb/>n <lb/> -dimensional <lb/>and is spanned (to zeroth order) by states obtained from <lb/> |C by n logical Z errors. These states have energy E  n  = <lb/> E  |C  + n∆, where <lb/>∆ := <lb/>83 <lb/>8192 <lb/> λ <lb/> 6 <lb/> g  5  . <lb/> (64) <lb/>Once again we can also calculate the first-order correc-<lb/>tions to the ground state |C is calculated to be <lb/> |E  0  = |C − <lb/> λ <lb/> 8g <lb/> µ∈L <lb/> 6 <lb/> i=1 <lb/> |k  (µ,i)  , <lb/> (65) <lb/>where |k  (µ,i)  := σ <lb/> x <lb/> (µ,i)  ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> (ν(i),i)  |C. Comparing this <lb/>ground state with the ideal cluster state, we find that <lb/>the average fidelity per site d is bounded by d &gt; (1 + <lb/>6λ <lb/> 2  /(8g) <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> −1  . <lb/> D. Implications for MBQC <lb/> The cluster states on the three lattice types examined <lb/>in this section (the square, hexagonal and cubic lattices) <lb/>are all universal resources for quantum computation. In <lb/>each case, it has been shown above that the perturba-<lb/>tive procedure produces a non-degenerate ground state <lb/>which approximates an encoded cluster state on the lat-<lb/>tice. We chose to investigate each of these lattice struc-<lb/>tures because each has a unique relevance to the study of <lb/>MBQC. The 2D square lattice is the canonical example <lb/>for use in cluster-state quantum computing and was the <lb/>original lattice structure presented in [1]. This lattice is <lb/>also the most easily accessible to experimental investi-<lb/>gation in cold atomic systems [8]. A hexagonal lattice <lb/>was also examined above because (as argued in [19]) the <lb/>perturbative procedure produces a cluster state with the <lb/>largest energy gap for a given ratio λ/g. We discuss the <lb/>implications of this observation below. Finally, recent <lb/>work [20, 21] has shown that fault-tolerant thresholds can <lb/>be found for MBQC if the lattice used is 3-dimensional. <lb/>Following on from the discussion in [19], we now com-<lb/>pare the results for each lattice and relate it to its useful-<lb/>ness for quantum computation. There are two sources of <lb/>error when using the ground state obtained in the pertur-<lb/>bative procedure for cluster-state quantum computation. <lb/>First, note that errors will arise because the ground <lb/>state of the system is not exactly the cluster state, <lb/>but contains perturbative corrections (cf. Eq. (47), (56), <lb/>(65)). In each case the ground state is given by a su-<lb/>perposition of the cluster state with other first-excited <lb/>states corresponding to &quot; errors &quot;  σ <lb/> x  ⊗ σ <lb/> z  applied to all <lb/>bonds on the cluster state independently. This error rate <lb/>is quantified by the average fidelity per lattice site d, de-<lb/>fined by Eq. (34), which was explicitly bounded in all of <lb/>the above examples. This bound takes the general form <lb/> d &gt; <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 + kλ  2  /g  2  , <lb/> (66) <lb/></body>

			<page> 11 <lb/></page>

			<body> where k is a constant of order one which depends on the <lb/>lattice. This bound tells us that, for λ ≪ g, the ground <lb/>state is very close to the cluster state, and that the er-<lb/>ror rate for the independent σ <lb/> x  ⊗ σ <lb/> z  is less than kλ <lb/> 2  /g <lb/> 2  . <lb/>Because we require λ ≪ g, this error probability will <lb/>be small. The effect, and possible error correction, for <lb/>such two-qubit correlated errors has not yet been inves-<lb/>tigated, but the independence and locality of the errors <lb/>makes them amenable to existing error correction tech-<lb/>niques. In particular, we note that such an error can be <lb/>identified by checking sites, each of which should be in <lb/>the code space spanned by |00 . . . 0 and |11 . . . 1. Errors <lb/>of the form σ <lb/> x  ⊗ σ <lb/> z  will cause a correctable error to this <lb/>code space (which must also include a phase correction <lb/>to the appropriate neighbouring site) provided that the <lb/>lattice has coordination number c &gt; 1, i.e., for lattices <lb/>of higher dimension than the 1-D line. This correction <lb/>scheme would require measurements of multiple qubits, <lb/>and it would be worthwhile to investigate whether such <lb/>error correction could be performed using single-qubit <lb/>measurements. <lb/>The main difference arising in the calculations for each <lb/>lattice structure, however, is the order in the perturba-<lb/>tion theory at which the ground-state degeneracy is bro-<lb/>ken. This occurs at third order for the hexagonal lattice, <lb/>fourth order for the square lattice and sixth order for the <lb/>cubic lattice. In general, the order at which perturba-<lb/>tion theory breaks the ground-state degeneracy is given <lb/>by the coordination number of the lattice. This result <lb/>leads directly to a dependence of the energy gap ∆ on <lb/>the coordination number c of the lattice, as <lb/>∆ ∼ (λ/g) <lb/> c  . <lb/> (67) <lb/>In all cases the energy gap ∆ is independent of the size <lb/>of the lattice, i.e. the system is gapped. Given that the <lb/>rate at which the thermal state of this system will ex-<lb/>hibit Z-errors depends explicitly on the size of this gap, <lb/>the system will be less sensitive to these errors if the en-<lb/>ergy gap ∆ is made larger. The hexagonal lattice will <lb/>have the largest energy gap, as is consequently less sensi-<lb/>tive to thermal errors. It should be noted, however, that <lb/>methods to identify and correct for such thermal errors <lb/>(and Pauli errors in general) within the MBQC paradigm <lb/>currently exist only for 3-dimensional lattices [20, 21]. <lb/>(See also [25].) The 2-D lattices (hexagonal and square) <lb/>may not allow for error correction of such thermal errors <lb/>using only single-qubit measurements; this remains a key <lb/>open question. <lb/>We note that there exists a trade-off between these <lb/>two types of errors when using the state for MBQC. In-<lb/>creasing the value of λ/g will reduce the probability of <lb/>thermal errors at a given temperature but also perturb <lb/>the ground state away from the cluster state. <lb/> V. FIXED BOUNDARY CONDITIONS <lb/> The perturbative approach has so far been successful <lb/>in producing the cluster state on each lattice type with <lb/>periodic boundary conditions. We now analyse the effect <lb/>of placing fixed boundaries on the lattice. <lb/> A. A line with fixed boundaries <lb/> We first examine a line with fixed endpoints. The in-<lb/>terior sites still have coordination number 2, and so we <lb/>require two physical qubits at these sites. However, the <lb/>boundary sites will consist of just a single physical qubit. <lb/>Denote the number of interior sites by N  S  , so that there <lb/>are (N  S  + 2) sites in the entire line. In addition, denote <lb/>the two boundary sites by the labels µ = B  1  and µ = B  2  . <lb/>The Hamiltonian for this lattice will remain that of <lb/>Eq. (6), where we do not place any site Hamiltonian <lb/>term on the boundary sites. The unperturbed energy <lb/>spectrum at each of the interior sites is unchanged from <lb/>the periodic boundary case (as in Fig. 2). The two <lb/>boundary qubits, however, have zero unperturbed en-<lb/>ergy. The spectrum of the unperturbed Hamiltonian for <lb/>the entire line is therefore a 2 <lb/> NS+2  -dimensional ground-<lb/>state space with energy E <lb/> (0) <lb/>0 <lb/> = −gN  S  , and is spanned <lb/>by all logical states of (N  S  + 2) qubits. The first-<lb/>excited space is (2N  S  · 2 <lb/> NS+1  )-dimensional, and has en-<lb/>ergy E <lb/> (0) <lb/>1  = −g(N  S  − 2). <lb/>We now turn to perturbation theory. Note that, for <lb/>the two boundary qubits, a single application of σ <lb/> x  maps <lb/>the logical space onto itself. Thus, due to the contribu-<lb/>tions from the boundary qubits, there is now a first order <lb/>correction to the energy <lb/> θ <lb/> (1)  = P  L  V P  L <lb/> = −P  L  (K  B1  + K  B2  )P  L <lb/> = −(S  B1  + S  B2  ) , <lb/> (68) <lb/>where <lb/> K  B1  = σ <lb/> x <lb/>B1  ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> (ν=1,1)  , <lb/> (69) <lb/> K  B2  = σ <lb/> x <lb/>B2  ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> (ν=NS ,2)  , <lb/> (70) <lb/>and as usual S  µ  = X  µ  ⊗  ν∼µ  Z  ν  . In particular, the cluster <lb/>stabilizers for the end sites are given by the product of an <lb/> X operator on the boundary site with a single Z operator <lb/>on its sole neighbour. <lb/>The first-order corrections to the ground-state en-<lb/>ergy, E <lb/> (1) <lb/>0j  , are the eigenvalues of θ <lb/> (1)  . This operator <lb/>is diagonal in our familiar basis for H  L  of the 2 <lb/> NS+2 <lb/> states {|C, |C{α}, |C{α, β}, . . .}, running over logical <lb/> Z-errors at all possible sites. The states in this basis <lb/>which are the +1-eigenstates of both S  B1  and S  B2  will <lb/>be the lowest eigenvalues of θ <lb/> (1)  . By the property of sta-<lb/>bilisers, the subspace T ∈ H  L  which is stabilised by S  B1 <lb/> and S  B2  is 2 <lb/> NS  -fold degenerate, and so the degeneracy <lb/></body>

			<page> 12 <lb/></page>

			<body> is reduced by a factor of 4 at first order. The cluster <lb/>state |C is contained in this subspace, as are all states <lb/>with logical Z-errors anywhere except on the boundary. <lb/>Thus the lowest energy space T has a first-order correc-<lb/>tion given by: <lb/> λE <lb/> (1) <lb/> T  = −2λ . <lb/> (71) <lb/>The next highest energy level includes states which have <lb/>a Z-error at either of the boundary sites B  1  or B  2  but not <lb/>both. These 2 <lb/> NS+1  states have λE <lb/> (1)  = 0, which is a gap <lb/>of 2λ above the space T . The second highest energy level <lb/>will include states which have Z-errors at both boundary <lb/>sites, and in this case λE <lb/> (1)  = 2λ. <lb/>The second order correction is calculated in an iden-<lb/>tical manner to the case with periodic boundary condi-<lb/>tions. We have <lb/> θ <lb/> (2)  = <lb/> P  L  V P  1  V P  L <lb/> (E <lb/> (0) <lb/>0  − E <lb/> (0) <lb/>1  ) <lb/>= <lb/>2N  S  P  L  + 2 <lb/> µ =B1,B2  S  µ <lb/> −2g <lb/> . (72) <lb/>The above operator is already diagonal in our chosen ba-<lb/>sis (the states of the form |C{α, β, . . .}). Of the states in <lb/> T , the cluster state |C is the unique +1 eigenstate of all <lb/>the stabilisers in the above sum, and so will be the lowest <lb/>eigenvalue of θ <lb/> (2)  . Thus the second-order correction for <lb/>the energy associated with this state is <lb/> λ <lb/> 2  E <lb/> (2) <lb/> |C  = <lb/>2N  S  + 2N  S <lb/> −2g <lb/> λ <lb/> 2  = −2N  S <lb/> λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> g <lb/>. <lb/> (73) <lb/>So in the case of fixed boundary conditions, the cluster <lb/>state is still the ground state produced (to zeroth order), <lb/>with energy to 2nd order of <lb/> E  |C  = −gN  S  − 2λ − 2N  S <lb/> λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> g <lb/>. <lb/> (74) <lb/>A state |C{α, β, . . .} with n  B  Z-errors at boundary sites <lb/>and n  I  Z-errors at interior sites will have energy: <lb/> E  (nB ,nI )  = E  |C  + n  B  ∆  B  + n  I  ∆  I <lb/> (75) <lb/>where ∆  I  := 2λ <lb/> 2  /g and ∆  B  := 2λ. Provided λ/g &lt; 1, <lb/>the energy gap will be ∆  I  = 2λ <lb/> 2  /g, the same energy gap <lb/>which was obtained with the periodic boundary condi-<lb/>tions. <lb/>The first order corrections to this ground state will be <lb/>given by <lb/> |E  0  = |C − <lb/> λ <lb/>g <lb/> µ =B1,B2 <lb/> |k  (µ,1)  , <lb/> (76) <lb/>and the bound on d, the average fidelity per site, remains <lb/>the same as for periodic boundary conditions. <lb/> B. Square lattice with fixed boundaries <lb/> Consider a square lattice of dimension l × l. We define <lb/>the number of interior (non-boundary) sites to be N  S  , <lb/>and so l = <lb/> √ <lb/> N  S  + 2 and the total number of sites is <lb/> N  S  + 4 <lb/> √ <lb/> N  S  + 4. Interior sites have coordination number <lb/>4, edge sites coordination number 3, and corner sites co-<lb/>ordination number 2, determining the number of qubits <lb/>at each site. Denote the set of corner boundary sites <lb/>by L  1  , the set of edge boundary sites by L  2  , and the <lb/>set of interior sites by L  3  . Each of the three type of <lb/>sites will have a different unperturbed spectrum at each, <lb/>corresponding to Figs. 2, 3 and 4 respectively. The ze-<lb/>roth order energies of the lattice are now much more <lb/>complicated due to the presence of these three differ-<lb/>ent types of sites. The ground state of gH  0  for the <lb/>entire lattice, spanned by all possible logical states, is <lb/>2 <lb/> (NS+4 <lb/> √ <lb/> NS +4)  -dimensional ground-state space with en-<lb/>ergy E <lb/> (0) <lb/>0 <lb/> = −4gN  S  − 12g <lb/> √ <lb/> N  S  − 8g. The next four ex-<lb/>cited states separated by a energy gaps of 2g. <lb/>At first-order in the perturbation, θ <lb/> (1)  = P  L  V P  L  = <lb/>0, and thus there is still no first-order correction to the <lb/>energies. At second, third, and fourth order, we have <lb/> θ <lb/> (2)  = − <lb/> (N  S  + 3 <lb/> √ <lb/> N  S  + 4)P  L  + <lb/> µ∈L1  S  µ <lb/> g <lb/>, <lb/>θ <lb/> (3)  = − <lb/> 3! <lb/> µ∈L2  S  µ <lb/> (−4g)  2  , <lb/>θ <lb/> (4)  = − <lb/> 5 <lb/>16g  3 <lb/> µ∈L3 <lb/> S  µ  − <lb/> N  S  + 3 <lb/> √ <lb/> N  S  − 4 + 4n  1 <lb/> 4g  3 <lb/> µ∈L1 <lb/> S  µ <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2g  3 <lb/> µ,ν∈L1,µ =ν <lb/> S  µ  S  ν <lb/> + <lb/> 15/16NS +45/16 <lb/> √ <lb/> NS+10−(NS/2+3 <lb/> √ <lb/> NS/2+4)n1 <lb/>g  3 <lb/> P  L  . <lb/> (77) <lb/>(In this expression, n  1  is the number of Z-errors at sites <lb/>in L  1  relative to the cluster state. It appears is this <lb/>expression because θ <lb/> (4)  depends on the second-order en-<lb/>ergies.) This operator is diagonal in the familiar basis <lb/> {|C, |C{α}, |C{α, β}, . . .}. The corresponding correc-<lb/>tions to the lowest energy ground-state energy are <lb/> λ <lb/> 2  E <lb/> (2) <lb/> |C  = − <lb/> (N  S  + 3 <lb/> √ <lb/> N  S  + 8) <lb/> g <lb/>λ <lb/> 2  , <lb/>λ <lb/> 3  E <lb/> (3) <lb/> |C  = − <lb/> 3 <lb/> √ <lb/> N  S <lb/> 2g  2  λ <lb/> 3  , <lb/>λ <lb/> 4  E <lb/> (4) <lb/> |C  = <lb/> −6N  S  − 3 <lb/> √ <lb/> N  S  + 128 <lb/>16 <lb/> λ <lb/> 4 <lb/> g  3  . <lb/> (78) <lb/>Thus, the non-degenerate ground state of the system is <lb/>the cluster state |C, to zeroth order, with an energy to <lb/>fourth-order given by <lb/> E  0  = − 4gN  S  − 12g <lb/> N  S  − 8g − <lb/> (N  S  + 3 <lb/> √ <lb/> N  S  + 8) <lb/> g <lb/>λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> − <lb/> 3 <lb/> √ <lb/> N  S <lb/> 2g  2  λ <lb/> 3  − <lb/> 6N  S  + 3 <lb/> √ <lb/> N  S  − 128 <lb/>16g  3 <lb/> λ <lb/> 4  . <lb/> (79) <lb/>A state |C{α, β, . . .} obtained from the cluster state by <lb/> n  1  Z-errors at sites in L  1  , n  2  Z-errors at sites in L  2  and <lb/></body>

			<page> 13 <lb/></page>

			<body> n  3  Z-errors at sites in L  3  will have energy <lb/> E  (n1,n2,n3)  = E  |C  + ∆(n  1  ) + n  2  ∆  2  + n  3  ∆  3  , <lb/> (80) <lb/>where <lb/>∆  3  := <lb/>5λ <lb/> 4 <lb/> 8g  3 <lb/> ∆  2  := <lb/>3λ <lb/> 3 <lb/> 4g  2 <lb/> ∆(n  1  ) := ( <lb/>2λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> g <lb/> − <lb/> 6λ <lb/> 4 <lb/> g  3  )n  1  + <lb/>2λ <lb/> 4 <lb/> g  3  n  1 <lb/>2  + k  n1 <lb/> (81) <lb/> k  0  := k  4  := 0 , k  1  := k  3  := <lb/>6λ <lb/> 4 <lb/> g  3  , k  2  := <lb/>8λ <lb/> 4 <lb/> g  3  . <lb/> For the range λ/g &lt; 1, the energy gap will be ∆  3  = <lb/>(5/8)λ <lb/> 4  /g <lb/> 3  , the same energy gap obtained using periodic <lb/>boundary conditions. <lb/>In summary, the perturbative procedure is still suc-<lb/>cessful on the line and square lattice with fixed bound-<lb/>ary conditions, producing an approximate cluster state <lb/>as the non-degenerate ground state. Furthermore, the <lb/>energy gap to the first-excited space is unchanged from <lb/>the case with periodic boundary conditions. Extending <lb/>these results to other lattices is straightforward. <lb/> VI. THE CLUSTER STATE ON A GENERAL <lb/>GRAPH <lb/> We have shown that the perturbative procedure pre-<lb/>sented here is successful in producing a non-degenerate <lb/>ground state that approximates the cluster state on all <lb/>of the lattice types examined so far. In fact, the cluster <lb/>state on any lattice type with any boundary conditions, <lb/>or more generally on any graph, can be approximated <lb/>using this method. We now outline a proof of this result. <lb/>For any graph, we place at each site a number of <lb/>physical qubits equal to the coordination number (the <lb/>number of bonds connecting that site to others) and <lb/>take the Hamiltonian as in Eq. (6). We note that <lb/>the form of the site Hamiltonian H  0  needs only yield <lb/>a two-dimensional degenerate ground state spanned by <lb/> |00 . . . 0 and |11 . . . 1 of all qubits at each site; aside <lb/>from this requirement, its precise form is quite flexible. <lb/>We first show that the operators produced at each or-<lb/>der in perturbation theory will always possess the cluster <lb/>state as an eigenstate, and more generally are diagonal-<lb/>ized by the set of cluster states with Z errors. Note that <lb/>the operators that arise at each order of the perturbation <lb/>theory are linear combinations of terms of the form <lb/> P  L  V <lb/>  l <lb/>k=1  (Ω <lb/> α  k  ¯ <lb/> P  L  V ) <lb/> P  L  , <lb/> (82) <lb/>for some integers l and α  k  , where Ω := (E <lb/> (0) <lb/>0  − gH  0  ) <lb/> −1  . <lb/>Now, V is a sum of operators σ <lb/> z <lb/> (µ,i)  ⊗ σ <lb/> x <lb/> (ν,j)  where µ  = ν, <lb/> and therefore P  L  V ( <lb/>  l <lb/>k=1  (Ω <lb/> α  k  ¯ <lb/> P  L  V ))P  L  will be a sum of <lb/>operators which map states in the logical space through <lb/>the illogical spaces (by applications of σ <lb/> z  ⊗ σ <lb/> x  over <lb/>various bonds) and then return it to the logical space. <lb/>From the Pauli operator commutation relations, we note <lb/>that every term σ <lb/> z  ⊗ σ <lb/> x  that is applied to the logical <lb/>space either commutes or anticommutes with the terms <lb/>in H  0  and so it will always yield an eigenstate of H  0  . <lb/>Thus, successive applications maps the logical space to <lb/>eigenspaces of definite unperturbed energy, and the term <lb/>Ω = (E <lb/> (0) <lb/>0  −gH  0  ) <lb/> −1  will just be a multiplicative constant. <lb/>Furthermore, the fact that each application of σ <lb/> z  ⊗ σ <lb/> x <lb/> keeps the system in some eigenstate of H  0  means that all <lb/>the terms in the sum are of the form P  L  KP  L  , where K is <lb/>some product of the σ <lb/> z  ⊗ σ <lb/> x  . Now, suppose K does not <lb/>commute with all the terms in H  0  (i.e. it anticommutes <lb/>with at least one of them), then the effect of this term <lb/>will be that K maps logical states to illogical ones (the <lb/>resultant state will have a −1 eigenvalue for at least one <lb/>term in H  0  , whereas the logical space is the +1 eigenstate <lb/>of all the terms in H  0  ). Thus in this case P  L  KP  L  = 0. <lb/>The only non-zero operators in the perturbation theory <lb/>will be of the form P  L  KP  L  where K commutes with all <lb/>the terms in H  0  (i.e. all the σ <lb/> z <lb/> (µ,i)  ⊗ σ <lb/> z <lb/> (µ,i+1)  ). But then, <lb/>if K commutes with each term in H  0  it commutes with <lb/> P  L  , the projection onto the logical subspace. Thus, we <lb/>have the eigenvalue relation <lb/> P  L  KP  L  |C = P  L  KP  L <lb/> P  L  |C  2  |C  2  · · · |C  2  <lb/> = P  L  K|C  2  |C  2  · · · |C  2  <lb/> = P  L  |C  2  |C  2  · · · |C  2  = |C <lb/> (83) <lb/>where the last line follows because σ <lb/> z  ⊗ σ <lb/> x  |C  2  = σ <lb/> x  ⊗ <lb/> σ <lb/> z  |C  2  = |C  2  , and K is a product of σ <lb/> z  ⊗ σ <lb/> x  terms. <lb/>Hence, we have shown that all the terms that arise at <lb/>each order in the perturbation theory stabilise the cluster <lb/>state. This certainly shows that, to zeroth order, the <lb/>cluster state is one of the eigenstates selected out of the <lb/>degeneracy by the perturbation. We now show that it is <lb/>the non-degenerate ground state. <lb/>Each term of the form P  L  KP  L  stabilises the cluster <lb/>state, and the eigenvalues of P  L  KP  L  are restricted to <lb/> ±1. Therefore, all that must be checked is that the sign <lb/>in front of P  L  KP  L  in the perturbation theory is negative <lb/>to ensure that the cluster state is selected as the ground <lb/> state. Suppose K is a product of m σ <lb/> z  ⊗ σ <lb/> x  terms. Then <lb/>the operator P  L  KP  L  will first appear at the mth order <lb/>as a term in P  L  V [Ω ¯ <lb/> P  L  V ] <lb/> m−1  P  L  . The Ω operators will <lb/>always contribute a sign (−1) <lb/> m−1  to the energy correc-<lb/>tion. Furthermore, each σ <lb/> z  ⊗σ <lb/> x  carries with it a negative <lb/>sign in the definition of V , contributing a further (−1) <lb/> m <lb/> to the the energy correction. Therefore, each P  L  KP  L <lb/> will always appear in the energy correction with a neg-<lb/>ative sign, thus selecting the cluster state as the ground <lb/>state. Moreover, because it is clear that the cluster state <lb/>stabilisers S  µ  = X  µ  ⊗  ν∼µ  Z  ν  , will always arise as one of <lb/>the P  L  KP  L  terms in the perturbation theory, the ground <lb/>state must be non-degenerate (as the state stabilised by <lb/>these operators is unique). Hence we have shown what <lb/>we set out to prove: that the cluster state on any lattice <lb/>type can be approximated using this method. In fact, this <lb/>perturbative approach can also be further generalised to <lb/></body>

			<page> 14 <lb/></page>

			<body> approximate other states with a PEPS description. <lb/> VII. CONCLUSION <lb/> The existence of gapped quantum many-body systems, <lb/>with Hamiltonians consisting of only two-body nearest-<lb/>neighbour interactions, for which the ground state en-<lb/>codes a cluster state allowing universal MBQC is an ex-<lb/>citing result for the potential realisation of a quantum <lb/>computer. The obvious avenue for future investigation is <lb/>whether existing natural or artificial materials exist with <lb/>interactions similar to those described here. <lb/>As we have shown, as the perturbation parameter λ/g <lb/> becomes larger, the ground state begins to deviate from <lb/>the cluster state due to perturbative corrections. In this <lb/>work, we have analysed these corrections as a source of <lb/>error. It may also be fruitful, however, to analyse the <lb/>usefulness of the finite λ/g ground state for MBQC in <lb/>terms of the performance of a universal set of quantum <lb/>gates, as in [24]. Although we do not believe the model <lb/>investigated here exhibits a phase transition at any λ/g <lb/> (this is however an open question), it may nevertheless <lb/>be possible that the usefulness of the ground state for <lb/>MBQC undergoes some form of sharp transition [25]. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/> This work was supported by the Australian Research <lb/>Council. We thank Sergey Bravyi for identifying that the <lb/>PEPS Hamiltonian ground state was a simultaneous +1 <lb/>eigenstate of the encoded stabilizer operators K  µ  , and <lb/>for identifying their role in obtaining exact solutions to <lb/>this model. We thank Andrew Doherty, Terry Rudolph <lb/>and Stein Olav Skrøvseth for helpful discussions. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex"> APPENDIX A: PERTURBATION THEORY <lb/> We briefly outline the formalism of degenerate pertur-<lb/>bation theory and the notation that we use, closely fol-<lb/>lowing Ref. [22]. <lb/>Suppose that the Hamiltonian has the form H  0  + V , <lb/>and that the eigenvalue problem has been solved exactly <lb/>for H  0  . The corrections brought about by the introduc-<lb/>tion of the perturbation V can then be approximated by <lb/>a power series expansion in V . For perturbation theory <lb/>to converge, the magnitude of the largest eigenvalue of V <lb/> must be smaller than that of H  0  . <lb/>Suppose the unperturbed spectrum has a degenerate <lb/>subspace H  L  with energy E <lb/> (0) <lb/> L  and we are interested in <lb/>finding out how this energy degeneracy is broken. After <lb/>the perturbation has been applied, denote the perturbed <lb/>eigenstates of this subspace by |ψ  i  and the perturbed <lb/>energies by E  i  , for i = 1, . . . , dim H  L  , i.e., <lb/>(H  0  + V )|ψ  i  = E  i  |ψ  i  . <lb/> (A1) <lb/>Denote the projection onto the degenerate subspace H  L <lb/> as P  L  and define P  L  = I − P  L  . Then we can decompose <lb/> |ψ  i  as |ψ  i  = |ψ  i   L  + |ψ  i  ¯  L  , where |ψ  i   L  := P  L  |ψ  i  and <lb/> |ψ  i  ¯  L  := P  L  |ψ  i  . <lb/> Applying this decomposition to Eq. (A1), we have: <lb/>(H  0  + V )|ψ  i   L  + (H  0  + V )|ψ  i  ¯  L  = E  i  |ψ  i   L  + E  i  |ψ  i  ¯  L  . <lb/> (A2) <lb/>Note that P  L  H  0  = H  0  P  L  = E <lb/> (0) <lb/> L  P  L  and therefore that <lb/> P  L  H  0  = H  0  P  L  . Multiplying Eq. (A2) by P  L  and P  L <lb/> respectively, we obtain <lb/>(E  i  − E <lb/> (0) <lb/> L  − P  L  V P  L  )|ψ  i   L  − (P  L  V P  L  )|ψ  i  ¯  L  = 0 (A3) <lb/>(E  i  − H  0  − P  L  V P  L  )|ψ  i  ¯  L  − (P  L  V P  L  )|ψ  i   L  = 0 . <lb/> (A4) <lb/>Eq. (A4) has the formal solution <lb/> |ψ  i  ¯  L  = (E  i  − H  0  − P  L  V P  L  ) <lb/> −1  (P  L  V P  L  )|ψ  i   L  , (A5) <lb/>which can be substituted back into Eq. (A3) to obtain <lb/> θ|ψ  i   L  = (E  i  − E <lb/> (0) <lb/> L  )|ψ  i   L  , <lb/> (A6) <lb/>where <lb/> θ := P  L  V P  L <lb/> + (P  L  V P  L  )(E  i  − H  0  − P  L  V P  L  ) <lb/> −1  (P  L  V P  L  ) . (A7) <lb/>This equation allows us to determine perturbed energy at <lb/>any order of the perturbation theory. So far no approxi-<lb/>mations have been made. To implement the perturbation <lb/>theory, it is necessary to expand θ as a power series in <lb/> V . We use <lb/>(E  i  −H  0  − P  L  V P  L  ) <lb/> −1 <lb/> = <lb/> I − (E  i  − H  0  ) <lb/> −1  P  L  V P  L <lb/>  −1  (E  i  − H  0  ) <lb/> −1 <lb/> = <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> m=0 <lb/> (E  i  − H  0  ) <lb/> −1  P  L  V P  L <lb/>  m <lb/> (E  i  − H  0  ) <lb/> −1  . <lb/> (A8) <lb/>The energies E  i  in these expressions must also be ex-<lb/>panded as power series, E  i  = E <lb/> (0) <lb/> L  + <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> k=1  E <lb/> (k) <lb/> i  . Then <lb/>we have <lb/>(E  i  −H  0  ) <lb/> −1  = (E <lb/> (0) <lb/> L  + <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=1 <lb/> E <lb/> (k) <lb/> i <lb/> − H  0  ) <lb/> −1 <lb/> = <lb/> I + (E <lb/> (0) <lb/> L  − H  0  ) <lb/> −1 <lb/>∞ <lb/> k=1 <lb/> E <lb/> (k) <lb/> i <lb/>  −1 <lb/> (E <lb/> (0) <lb/> L  − H  0  ) <lb/> −1 <lb/> = ΛΩ <lb/>(A9) <lb/>where we have defined the operators <lb/>Ω := (E <lb/> (0) <lb/> L  − H  0  ) <lb/> −1  , <lb/> (A10) <lb/>Λ := <lb/> I + Ω <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=1 <lb/> E <lb/> (k) <lb/> i <lb/>  −1  . <lb/> (A11) <lb/></div>

			<page> 15 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex"> The operator θ can then be expressed as <lb/> θ = P  L  V P  L  + P  L  V <lb/> ∞ <lb/> m=0 <lb/> [ΛΩP  L  V ] <lb/> m  ΛΩP  L  V P  L  , (A12) <lb/>where we have used the fact that P  L  commutes with Ω <lb/>and Λ. Additionally, Λ must be further expanded out as <lb/>a power series <lb/>Λ = (I + Ω <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=1 <lb/> E <lb/> (k) <lb/> i  ) <lb/> −1  = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> j=0 <lb/> (−Ω <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=1 <lb/> E <lb/> (k) <lb/> i  ) <lb/> j  . (A13) <lb/>We can now identify the terms in Eq. (A12) of each <lb/>order. Specifically, denote the terms in θ of kth order by <lb/> θ <lb/> (k)  , so that θ = <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> k=1  θ <lb/> (k)  . Then, when approximated <lb/>to nth order in V , Eq. (A6) becomes <lb/> n <lb/> k=1 <lb/> θ <lb/> (k)  |ψ  i   L  = <lb/> n <lb/> k=1 <lb/> E <lb/> (k) <lb/> i  |ψ  i   L  , <lb/> (A14) <lb/>which is an eigenvalue equation over the subspace L. (We <lb/>note that |ψ  i   L  = 0 because |ψ  i  ∈ H  L  at zeroth order <lb/>and the perturbation is assumed small). The energy cor-<lb/>rections to nth order <lb/>  n <lb/>k=1  E <lb/> (k) <lb/> i <lb/> are the eigenvalues of the <lb/>operator <lb/>  n <lb/>k=1  θ <lb/> (k)  . Furthermore, the eigenstates that <lb/>are selected by the perturbation to break the degeneracy <lb/>(to zeroth order) are just the eigenvectors of <lb/>  n <lb/>k=1  θ <lb/> (k) <lb/> corresponding to each eigenvalue. Note that θ <lb/> (k)  depends <lb/>on lower order energy corrections and so each lower or-<lb/>der correction must be calculated before proceeding to <lb/>the higher order corrections. At each stage we must in-<lb/>sist that the nth order energies differ from the (n−1)th <lb/>order energies only by an amount nth order in V , which <lb/>removes any non-physical solutions. <lb/>To determine the explicit form of the θ <lb/> (k)  , we sim-<lb/>ply substitute Eq. (A13) into Eq. (A12) and identify the <lb/>terms of the required order. Clearly θ <lb/> (1)  = P  L  V P  L  , and <lb/>so to first order in V , Eq. (A14) becomes <lb/> θ <lb/> (1)  |ψ  i   L  = P  L  V P  L  |ψ  i   L  = E <lb/> (1) <lb/> i  |ψ  i   L  . <lb/> (A15) <lb/>Thus, the first order energy corrections to states in H  L <lb/> are just the eigenvalues of the matrix P  L  V P  L  . In the <lb/>non-degenerate case we see that Eq. (A15) reduces to the <lb/>well-known expression E <lb/> (1) <lb/> i <lb/> = L|V |L. If this eigenvalue <lb/>spectrum is still degenerate, then the degeneracy is not <lb/>completely broken at first order. It is then necessary to <lb/>go to second order <lb/>(E <lb/> (1) <lb/> i <lb/> + E <lb/> (2) <lb/> i  )|ψ  i   L  = (θ <lb/> (1)  + θ <lb/> (2)  )|ψ  i   L <lb/> = (P  L  V P  L  + P  L  V ΩP  L  V P  L  )|ψ  i   L  . <lb/> (A16) <lb/>Again we can examine whether the degeneracy has <lb/>been broken at this stage by examining the eigenval-<lb/>ues and eigenvectors of the above operator P  L  V P  L  + <lb/> P  L  V ΩP  L  V P  L  . If not, we must continue to proceed to <lb/>higher orders. The formulae for higher orders become in-<lb/>creasingly complex, but they simplify if we assume that <lb/> E <lb/> (1) <lb/> i <lb/> = 0, which will be true for all the cases of interest <lb/>that we investigate in this paper. For example we find <lb/>(with E <lb/> (1) <lb/> i <lb/> = 0) <lb/> θ <lb/> (1)  = P  L  V P  L <lb/> θ <lb/> (2)  = P  L  V ΩP  L  V P  L <lb/> θ <lb/> (3)  = P  L  V [ΩP  L  V ] <lb/> 2  P  L <lb/> θ <lb/> (4)  = P  L  V [ΩP  L  V ] <lb/> 3  P  L  − E <lb/> (2) <lb/> i  P  L  V Ω <lb/> 2  P  L  V P  L  , (A17) <lb/>and so forth. <lb/>There are two additional points that must be noted. <lb/>First, from Eq. (A12), it can be concluded that <lb/>  N <lb/>k=1  E <lb/> (k) <lb/> i <lb/> are the eigenvalues of the operator <lb/>  N <lb/>k=1  θ <lb/> (k) <lb/> for each order N . However, the energies E <lb/> (k) <lb/> i <lb/> are not <lb/>generally the eigenvalues of the operators θ <lb/> (k)  ; this will <lb/>only be true in general when all operators θ <lb/> (k)  can be si-<lb/>multaneously diagonalised. Fortunately, for the systems <lb/>investigated in this paper, it can be shown that the θ <lb/> (k) <lb/> commute with each other and therefore the energies E <lb/> (k) <lb/> i <lb/> are indeed the eigenvalues of the operators θ <lb/> (k)  . Second, <lb/>there are some general properties we can note about the <lb/>form of the θ <lb/> (k)  operators. From the form of Eq. (A12) <lb/>and the series expansion in Eq. (A13), it is clear that all <lb/>terms in the expansion of θ are proportional to operators <lb/>of the form P  L  V ( <lb/>  l <lb/>k=1  (Ω <lb/> α  k  P  L  V ))P  L  for some l, α  k  ∈ N. <lb/> This result is used in Sec. VI. <lb/>The above analysis allows the zeroth order energy <lb/>eigenstates to be determined. We now direct our atten-<lb/>tion to the first order corrections to these states. Suppose <lb/>we have determined that |ψ  i  = |ψ  i   L  = |i to zeroth or-<lb/>der for some |i ∈ H  L  using the above method. From <lb/>Eq. (A5) and using Eqs. (A8) and (A9) we have, to first <lb/>order in V , <lb/> |ψ  i  ¯  L  = Ω(P  L  V P  L  )|ψ  i   L  = <lb/> |j∈H  ¯ <lb/> L <lb/> j|V |i <lb/> E <lb/> (0) <lb/> L  − E <lb/> (0) <lb/> j <lb/> |j , <lb/> (A18) <lb/>where |j ∈ H¯  L  are the eigenstates of H  0  with energy <lb/> E <lb/> (0) <lb/> j  . Determining |ψ  i   L  to first order is somewhat more <lb/>complicated: even though |ψ  i   L  = |i to zeroth order, it <lb/>is possible for first order corrections to come from other <lb/>states |l ∈ H  L  . However, if the energy degeneracy be-<lb/>tween |i and |l is only broken at order m  l  , then one <lb/>must go to the order (m  l  + 1) equations just to deter-<lb/>mine the first order eigenstate corrections to |ψ  i   L  . In <lb/>this case, <lb/>  m  l  −1 <lb/> k=1  E <lb/> (k) <lb/> i <lb/> = <lb/>  m  l  −1 <lb/> k=1  E <lb/> (k) <lb/> l <lb/> but E <lb/> (m  l  ) <lb/> i <lb/>  = E <lb/> (m  l  ) <lb/> l <lb/> . <lb/>Then, at order (m  l  + 1), Eq. (A14) reads <lb/>( <lb/> m  l <lb/> k=1 <lb/> θ <lb/> (k)  + θ <lb/> (m  l  +1)  )|ψ  i   L  = <lb/> m  l  +1 <lb/> k=1 <lb/> E <lb/> (k) <lb/> i  |ψ  i   L  . <lb/> (A19) <lb/></div>

			<page> 16 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex"> Taking the inner product with |l and rearranging gives <lb/> l|ψ  i   L  = <lb/> l|θ <lb/> (m  l  +1)  |ψ  i   L  − E <lb/> (m  l  +1) <lb/> i <lb/> l|ψ  i   L <lb/> E <lb/> (m  l  ) <lb/> i <lb/> − E <lb/> (m  l  ) <lb/> l <lb/> = <lb/> l|θ <lb/> (m  l  +1)  |i <lb/> E <lb/> (m  l  ) <lb/> i <lb/> − E <lb/> (m  l  ) <lb/> l <lb/> , <lb/> (A20) <lb/>to first order in V . Therefore, to first order in V , we have <lb/> |ψ  i  = |i + <lb/> |j∈H  ¯ <lb/> L <lb/> j|V |i <lb/> E <lb/> (0) <lb/> L  − E <lb/> (0) <lb/> j <lb/> |j <lb/> + <lb/> |l∈HL,l =i <lb/> l|θ <lb/> (m  l  +1)  |i <lb/> E <lb/> (m  l  ) <lb/> i <lb/> − E <lb/> (m  l  ) <lb/> l <lb/> |l . (A21) <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> [1] R. Raussendorf and H. J. Briegel, Phys. Rev. Lett. 86, <lb/> 5188 (2001). <lb/>[2] R. Raussendorf, D. E. Browne and H. J. Briegel, Phys. <lb/>Rev. A 68, 022312 (2003). <lb/>[3] D. Gross and J. Eisert, Phys. Rev. Lett. 98, 220503 <lb/>(2007). <lb/>[4] D. Gross, J. Eisert, N. Schuch, and D. Perez-Garcia, <lb/>Phys. Rev. A 76, 052315 (2007). <lb/>[5] M. Van den Nest, W. Dür, A. Miyake, and H. J. Briegel, <lb/>New J. Phys. 9, 204 (2007). <lb/>[6] G. K. Brennen and A. Miyake, Phys. Rev. Lett. 101, <lb/> 010502 (2008). <lb/>[7] M. Van den Nest, A. Miyake, W. Dür, and H.-J. Briegel, <lb/>Phys. Rev. Lett. 97, 150504 (2006). <lb/>[8] P. Treutlein et al., Fortschr. Phys. 54, 702 (2006). <lb/>[9] D. E. Browne and T. Rudolph, Phys. Rev. Lett. 95, <lb/> 010501 (2005). <lb/>[10] P. Walther et al., Nature (London) 434, 169 (2005). <lb/>[11] N. Schuch, I. Cirac, and F. Verstraete, Phys. Rev. Lett. <lb/> 100, 250501 (2008). <lb/>[12] F. Verstraete, M. M. Wolf, and J. I. Cirac, <lb/>arXiv:0803.1447. <lb/>[13] H. L. Haselgrove, M. A. Nielsen, and T. J. Osborne, Phys. <lb/>Rev. Lett. 91, 210401 (2003). <lb/>[14] M. A. Nielsen, arXiv:quant-ph/0504097 (2005). <lb/>[15] J. Kempe, A. Kitaev, and O. Regev, SIAM Journal of <lb/>Computing, 35, 1070 (2006). <lb/>[16] R. Oliveira and B. M. Terhal, Quant. Inf. Comp. 8, 900 <lb/>(2008). <lb/>[17] M. Van den Nest, K. Luttmer, W. Dür, and H. J. Briegel, <lb/>Phys. Rev. A 77, 012301 (2008). <lb/>[18] F. Verstraete and J. I. Cirac, Phys. Rev. A 70, 060302(R) <lb/>(2004). <lb/>[19] S. D. Bartlett and T. Rudolph, Phys. Rev. A 74, <lb/> 040302(R) (2006). <lb/>[20] R. Raussendorf, J. Harrington, and K. Goyal, Ann. Phys. <lb/> 321, 2242 (2006). <lb/>[21] R. Raussendorf, J. Harrington, and K. Goyal, New J. <lb/>Phys. 9, 199 (2007). <lb/>[22] D. Yao and J. Shi, Am. J. Phys. 68, 278 (2000). <lb/>[23] H.-Q. <lb/>Zhou <lb/>and <lb/>J. <lb/>P. <lb/>Barjaktarevi´ , <lb/>arXiv:cond-mat/0701608. <lb/>[24] A. C. Doherty and S. D. Bartlett, arXiv:0802.4314. <lb/>[25] S. D. Barrett, S. D. Bartlett, A. C. Doherty, D. Jennings, <lb/>and T. Rudolph, arXiv:0807.4797. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
