<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="footnote"> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 1 <lb/></note>

			<front> International Journal of Modern Physics A <lb/>Vol. 30, No. 3 (2015) 1530016 (50 pages) <lb/>c <lb/> World Scientific Publishing Company <lb/>DOI: 10.1142/S0217751X15300161 <lb/> The string theory landscape <lb/>  * <lb/> A. N. Schellekens  † <lb/> Nikhef, Science Park 105, 1098 XG Amsterdam, The Netherlands <lb/> Published 30 January 2015 <lb/>Perhaps the most important way string theory has affected the perspective of particle <lb/>physics phenomenology is through the &quot; string theory landscape &quot; . We discuss the ev-<lb/>idence supporting its existence, describe the regions of the landscape that have been <lb/>explored, and examine what the string theory landscape might imply for most Standard <lb/>Model problems. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Changing Perspectives <lb/> This chapter consists of three parts. In the present section, we will give a brief his-<lb/>torical overview of the birth of the string theory landscape and we will explain its <lb/>main features. We also present the main arguments in favor of its existence, both <lb/>from a top-down (string theory) and a bottom up (the Standard Model) point of <lb/>view. Furthermore we underline the important changes this concept has on the per-<lb/>spectives for string phenomenology. In Sec. 2 we present an overview of the various <lb/>methods of constructing string theories in four dimensions, by direct construction <lb/>and by compactification. In Sec. 3 we discuss how far one can get towards under-<lb/>standing the Standard Model from the landscape perspective, in comparison to the <lb/>traditional, symmetry-based approach. <lb/>Part of this paper is based on the review article. <lb/> 1 <lb/> 1.1. The age of symmetries <lb/> At the time when string theory started being considered as a theory of all interac-<lb/>tions including gravity, the theoretical work on the Standard Model had reached its <lb/>final form. Several decades of experimental work were still needed to establish it, but <lb/>theorists started moving ahead using the concepts that had led to so much success <lb/>in understanding the three non-gravitational interactions. The most important of <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> *  Also published in &quot; Perspectives on String Phenomenology &quot; , edited by B. Acharya, G. L. Kane <lb/>and P. Kumar (World Scientific, 2015), pp. 155–217. <lb/>  †  Nikhef, Amsterdam; IMAPP, Radboud Universiteit Nijmegen; IFF-CSIC, Madrid. <lb/></note>

			<page> 1530016-1 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 2 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A. N. Schellekens <lb/></note>

			<body> these concepts was symmetry. It revolutionized the understanding of fundamental <lb/>physics. From the seemingly hopeless chaos of nuclear and hadronic physics a very <lb/>simple description of those interactions had emerged in just about two decades: a <lb/>spontaneously broken gauge theory which was called the &quot; Standard Model &quot; . <lb/>The name does not suggest much confidence in this idea, and indeed nobody <lb/>saw the Standard Model as more than an intermediate stage, at best an approx-<lb/>imate description of nature, eventually to be supplanted by something even sim-<lb/>pler and mathematically more elegant. Indeed, by using the same group-theoretical <lb/>methods that turned out to be so successful in the description of the Standard <lb/>Model, new theories were found that looked more attractive. The highest achiev-<lb/>able goal appeared to be supersymmetric Grand Unified Theories (susy-GUTs), <lb/>which got even more credibility in the early nineties, when the precision results <lb/>of LEP suggested that the three gauge couplings evolved to a common value at <lb/>the very interesting energy scale of about 10 <lb/> 16  GeV, a few orders of magnitude <lb/>below the Planck scale. Even today, despite the fact that the experimental evi-<lb/>dence has not (yet) shown up, it is hard to believe that this could all be just a <lb/>coincidence. <lb/>A few years earlier string phenomenology had entered the scene. When it did, it <lb/>seemed to point at even grander symmetries. In 1984, the first results obtained by <lb/>compactifying the just-discovered E  8  × E  8  heterotic string suggested the ultimate <lb/>unification. The Standard Model appeared to emerge (almost) uniquely from the <lb/>jewel of Lie algebra theory, the Lie algebra E  8  . <lb/> 1.2. The birth of the landscape <lb/> But in the remainder of the eighties there was the beginning of a slow shift away <lb/>from the notions of symmetry and uniqueness that were considered almost self-<lb/>understood until then. History will decide if this was the beginning of a paradigm <lb/>shift or just prematurely giving up on uniqueness. But the evidence that the former <lb/>is true is mounting. <lb/>Perhaps we will conclude one day that these beautiful ideas have always carried <lb/>the seeds of their own destruction. A Standard Model family fits beautifully in <lb/>the (5) + (10) of SU (5) and even more beautifully in the (16) of SO(10), but the <lb/>Standard Model Higgs field does not. Furthermore, even if SU (5) or SO(10) exist <lb/>as symmetries at short distances, there is no unique path to the Standard Model at <lb/>the weak scale: in SU (5) models there are two minima of the GUT Higgs potential, <lb/>one leading to the Standard Model, and one to a SU (4) × U (1) gauge theory. In <lb/> SO(10) models the number of options increases. <lb/>The idea of low energy supersymmetry was also plagued by serious problems <lb/>from the very beginning. It introduces light bosons into the spectrum that lead <lb/>to rapid proton decay. By contrast, a sufficiently long life-time of the proton is <lb/>automatic in the Standard Model. On general grounds, one would expect low energy <lb/>supersymmetry to give rise to flavor violations that should have been observed a <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 3 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The string theory landscape <lb/></note>

			<body> long time ago already. These, as well as other problems can be evaded by additional <lb/>assumptions, but it is disturbing that the pieces of the puzzle do not fall into place <lb/>more easily. Furthermore, although susy and GUTs are well-motivated answers <lb/>to important questions, they have never led to a substantial simplification of the <lb/>Standard Model. <lb/>1.2.1. String vacua <lb/> The uniqueness of string theory was also in doubt right from the start. The E  8  × E  8 <lb/> heterotic string was not unique, but part of a small set of 10-and 11-dimensional <lb/>supersymmetric theories which were initially taken less seriously. <lb/>But more importantly, there was an explosion of compactifications and four-<lb/>dimensional string constructions in the two years following 1984. <lb/> 2–7  Already as early <lb/>as 1986 it became customary to think of the different string theories or compacti-<lb/>fications as &quot; vacua &quot; or &quot; ground states &quot; of a fundamental theory (see for example <lb/>the last line of Ref. 8 or discussion at the end of Ref. 9; here one also finds the <lb/>remark that perhaps our universe is merely a sufficiently long-lived metastable <lb/>state). The proliferation of &quot; string vacua &quot; has not stopped since then. Here and <lb/>in the following we use the word &quot; vacuum &quot; for the metastable state that correctly <lb/>describes our Universe, and all its analogues with different gauge theories. The <lb/>proper definition is itself a difficult issue, especially in de Sitter space, but if no well-<lb/>defined description exists that matches our Universe, string theory would be wrong <lb/>anyway. <lb/>1.2.2. Moduli <lb/> Soon it became clear that these &quot; string compactifications &quot; or &quot; four-dimensional <lb/>strings &quot; had continuous deformations that can be described by vacuum expecta-<lb/>tion values of massless scalar singlets, called &quot; moduli &quot; . Typically, there are tens or <lb/>hundreds of them. All quantum field theory parameters depend on the moduli, and <lb/>hence the existence of moduli is a first step towards a plethora of possibilities. <lb/>These singlets generate unobserved fifth forces and their presence is cosmo-<lb/>logically unacceptable, <lb/> 10,11  but so is the fact that supersymmetry is unbroken. <lb/>For more than a decade, this left room for the possibility that the abundance of <lb/>string vacua would be reduced to just a few, maybe just one, once these problems <lb/>were solved. But in the beginning of this century considerable progress was made <lb/>towards solving the problem of moduli stabilization and — to a lesser extent — <lb/>that of supersymmetry breaking. <lb/>The large number of available ingredients (fluxes, D-branes, orientifold planes <lb/>and various perturbative and non-perturbative effects) led to the nearly inevitable <lb/>conclusion that if there was one solution, there were going to be many more. Almost <lb/>two decades after 1984 the denial phase reached its end, marked by an influential <lb/>and somewhat provocative paper by L. Susskind, <lb/> 12  who also gave the subject its <lb/>current name, the &quot; string landscape &quot; . <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 4 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A. N. Schellekens <lb/></note>

			<body> 1.2.3. The cosmological constant <lb/> Remarkably, these developments were driven to a considerable extent by observa-<lb/>tion: the discovery of an accelerated expansion of the universe in 1998. <lb/> 13,14  The most <lb/>straightforward interpretation is that we live in a universe with positive vacuum <lb/>energy density, which acts like a cosmological constant, and implies that we live in <lb/>de Sitter (dS) rather than flat Minkowski space. Contrary to some statements in the <lb/>literature, there was never any difficulty in getting positive vacuum energy in string <lb/>theory. Some of the aforementioned papers from 1986 built non-supersymmetric <lb/>strings, and some of those string theories have positive vacuum energy. At that <lb/>time this feature was merely observed, but not yet considered to be of any interest. <lb/>However, we have little computational control over non-supersymmetric strings, <lb/>and at the moment the only viable path to string theory in dS space is to &quot; up-lift &quot; <lb/>supersymmetric AdS vacua with negative vacuum energy. <lb/>The explanation of the observed accelerated expansion requires not only positive <lb/>vacuum energy, but an extremely small amount of it. It is about 120 to 60 orders <lb/>of magnitude less than its natural scale, depending on whether one compares to <lb/>the Planck scale or the weak scale. In non-supersymmetric string theory vacuum <lb/>energy comes out as a sum of positive and negative contributions of Planckian size. <lb/>Everything we know suggests that this will give rise to numbers of order one in <lb/>units of the natural value. If the contributions in the sum are random, the chance <lb/>of finding a result near the observed value is about 1 in 10 <lb/> 120  . This would imply <lb/>that one needs an ensemble of at least 10 <lb/> 120  vacua to have a chance of finding one <lb/>like ours. With any smaller ensemble, the existence of the small observed value <lb/>would be a bizarre coincidence. <lb/>1.2.4. The Bousso–Polchinski mechanism <lb/> It was realized decades ago <lb/> 15  that anti-symmetric tensor fields A  µνρ  might play <lb/>an important rôle in solving the cosmological constant problem. Such four-index <lb/>field strengths can get constant values without breaking Lorentz invariance, namely <lb/> F  µνρσ  = cc  µνρσ  . If we couple the theory to gravity, it gives a contribution to the <lb/>cosmological constant Λ: <lb/>Λ = Λ  0  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>48 <lb/> F  µνρσ  F <lb/> µνρσ  = Λ  0  + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> c <lb/> 2  , <lb/> (1) <lb/>where Λ  0  is the cosmological constant in the absence of anti-symmetric field strength <lb/>contributions. In string theory c is not an arbitrary real number: it is quantized. <lb/> 16 <lb/> These quantized fields are called &quot; fluxes &quot; . It turns out that string theory typically <lb/>contains hundreds of fields F  µνρσ  , which we label by i = 1, . . . , N . The resulting <lb/>formula for Λ is <lb/>Λ = Λ  0  + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> N <lb/> i=1 <lb/> n <lb/> 2 <lb/> i  f <lb/> 2 <lb/> i  . <lb/> (2) <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 5 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The string theory landscape <lb/></note>

			<body> where the f  i  are numbers derived from the string theory under consideration. One <lb/>would expect the values for the real numbers f  i  to be different. If the values of <lb/> f  i  are distinct and incommensurate, then Eq. (2) defines a dense discrete set of <lb/>values. Bousso and Polchinski called it a &quot; discretuum &quot; . This realizes a dynamical <lb/>neutralization of Λ first proposed by Refs. 17, 18. See also Ref. 19 for a related <lb/>realization of this idea in string theory. <lb/>The discretuum is populated by some physical process that is able to connect <lb/>the different string vacua. The mechanism proposed for this is tunneling by bubble <lb/>nucleation in eternal inflation, a near inevitability in most models of inflation. See <lb/>Refs. 20, 21 for reviews and references. This area is — so far — less deeply connected <lb/>to string theory, and therefore we will not discuss it in detail, except to mention that <lb/>it leads to the very thorny issue of the multiverse measure problem. See Refs. 22–25 <lb/>for various ideas about this. <lb/>1.2.5. Existence and distribution of de Sitter vacua <lb/> To make use of the Bousso–Polchinski neutralization of Λ a sufficiently dense dis-<lb/>cretuum of such vacua is needed. This mechanism relies on the fact that whatever <lb/>the contribution of particle physics, cosmology and fundamental theory might be, <lb/>it can always be canceled to 120 significant digits by flux contributions, without <lb/>making actual computations with that precision. If in reality these distributions are <lb/>severely depleted in part of the range, or have a highly complicated non-flat struc-<lb/>ture, this argument would fail. There might still exist a huge landscape, but it <lb/>would be useless. <lb/>We will consider here only type-IIB (and related F-theory) compactifications <lb/>where the most explicit results have been obtained. For references to work in other <lb/>areas and more details see Refs. 1, 26–30. <lb/>In type-IIB theories one starts with a Calabi–Yau compactification with h  21 <lb/> complex structure ( &quot; shape &quot; ) moduli and h  11  Kähler ( &quot; size &quot; ) moduli, where h  21  and <lb/> h  11  are the Hodge numbers of the CY manifold (see Subsec. 2.3 for more details <lb/>on Calabi–Yau compactifications). One can add to this background configuration a <lb/>choice of gadgets from the string theory toolbox, such as 3-form RR and NS fluxes, <lb/>5-form fluxes, denoted F 3, H3 and F 5 respectively, and D3 and D7 branes. <lb/>The 3-form fluxes can stabilize all complex structure moduli. This is due to a <lb/>tree-level term in the superpotential that takes the form <lb/> 31 <lb/> W  flux  = <lb/> (F  3  − τ H  3  ) ∧ Ω , <lb/> (3) <lb/>where τ = a + ie <lb/> −φ  , and a is the axion and φ the dilaton. The dependence on the <lb/>complex structure moduli is through Ω, the holomorphic three-form of the Calabi– <lb/>Yau manifold. This term also fixes the dilaton and axion. However, W  flux  does not <lb/>depend on the Kähler moduli and hence cannot fix them. Since every CY manifold <lb/>has at least one Kähler modulus, this leaves therefore at least one modulus unfixed. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 6 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A. N. Schellekens <lb/></note>

			<body> One may fix the size moduli with non-perturbative terms in the superpoten-<lb/>tial. These take the form W ∝ exp(iλs), where s is the size modulus and λ a <lb/>parameter. Such terms can be generated by instantons associated with Euclidean <lb/>D3-branes <lb/> 32  or from gaugino condensation in gauge groups on wrapped D7 branes. <lb/>If at least one of these effects is present, string vacua with all moduli stabilized can <lb/>be obtained. <lb/> 33  This work, usually referred to as &quot; KKLT &quot; , builds on several earlier <lb/>results, such as Refs. 34–36 and references cited therein. The solution obtained in <lb/>this way has a negative vacuum energy, and is a fully stabilized supersymmetric <lb/>AdS vacuum. However, the required instanton contributions may not exist in all <lb/>cases. They are not generic <lb/> 37  and may even be so rare that one only gets a &quot; barren <lb/>landscape &quot; . <lb/> 38 <lb/> The next step is more problematic and more controversial. One must break <lb/>supersymmetry and obtain a dS vacuum (this is called &quot; up-lifting &quot; ). In KKLT this <lb/>is done by adding an anti-D3 brane in a suitable location on the Calabi–Yau mani-<lb/>fold, such that the validity of the approximations is not affected. Anti-D3 branes <lb/>explicitly violate supersymmetry, and hence after introducing them one loses the <lb/>control offered by supergravity. Attempts to realize the KKLT uplifting in super-<lb/>gravity or string theory have failed so far, <lb/> 39,40  but opinions differ on the implications <lb/>of that result. There exist several alternatives to D3-brane uplifting. <lb/> 41–45 <lb/> The result of a fully realized KKLT construction is a string vacuum that is free <lb/>of tachyons, but one still has to worry about non-perturbative instability. The uplift <lb/>contribution vanishes in the limit of large moduli, so there is always a supersym-<lb/>metric vacuum in that limit, separated from the dS vacuum by the uplifted barrier <lb/>that stabilized the AdS vacuum. One can work out the tunneling amplitude, and <lb/>KKLT showed that it is generically much larger than the observed lifetime of our <lb/>universe. <lb/>An alternative scenario (called the LARGE volume scenario or LVS) was pre-<lb/>sented in Ref. 46. The starting point is type-IIB fluxes stabilizing the complex <lb/>structure moduli and the dilaton and axion. By means of suitable (α <lb/>  ) <lb/> 3  correc-<lb/>tions these authors were able to find minima where all moduli are stabilized at <lb/>exponentially large volumes in non-supersymmetric AdS vacua. Additional mecha-<lb/>nisms are then needed to lift the vacuum to dS. An explicit example was presented <lb/>recently. <lb/> 47 <lb/> The existence of the required dense distribution of vacua is still disputed, and <lb/>some even question the existence of any such vacuum. Recent work seems to indi-<lb/>cate that in the vast majority of cases the AdS vacua become tachyonic after up-<lb/>lifting. <lb/> 48,49  Another potential problem is a dramatic increase in tunneling rates <lb/>as a function of the number of moduli. <lb/> 50  These effects may dramatically reduce <lb/>the number of dS vacua, rendering the Bousso–Polchinski argument inadequate. In <lb/>Ref. 51 several criticism of the landscape are presented, including the use of effec-<lb/>tive potentials and of Coleman–de Luccia <lb/> 52  tunneling between dS vacua in theories <lb/>of gravity. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 7 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The string theory landscape <lb/></note>

			<body> 1.2.6. Vacuum counting <lb/> The KKLT construction has been the starting point for estimates of the total <lb/>number of flux vacua, <lb/> 53–55 <lb/> N  vac  ≈ <lb/> (2πL) <lb/> K/2 <lb/> (K/2)! <lb/> , <lb/> (4) <lb/>where L is a number of order 1 to 100 (the &quot; tadpole charge &quot; ) and K the number <lb/>of distinct fluxes. For typical manifolds this gives numbers of order 10 <lb/> N  , where N <lb/> is of order a few hundred. A often quoted estimate is 10 <lb/> 500  . <lb/>It is noteworthy that this formula turns a nuisance (a large number of moduli) <lb/>into a virtue: the large number of moduli gives rise to the exponent of Eq. (4), <lb/>and it is this large exponent that makes neutralization of the cosmological constant <lb/>possible. All the ingredients used in the foregoing discussion are already present <lb/>in string theory. Since all Standard Model parameters depend on the moduli, this <lb/>results in a large distribution of options covering the environment of the Standard <lb/>Model in QFT. <lb/> 1.3. A paradigm shift? <lb/> If we were to accept that our laws of physics are picked out of a huge ensemble, and <lb/>that the parameters have such special values just by coincidence, this would imply <lb/>the end of science. Then the entire Standard Model could just be a random item <lb/>from a huge ensemble. It is indeed remarkable that in the current state of particle <lb/>physics, many of the remaining problems could be just environmental: the Standard <lb/>Model provides an adequate description, but often with strange parameter values. <lb/>Some genuine problems remain (such as dark matter and the mechanisms behind <lb/>inflation and baryogenesis), but most other problems that are often discussed should <lb/>really be called &quot; worries &quot; . This means that we cannot be completely sure that there <lb/>exists a solution. Perhaps these problems only exist in our minds. This includes the <lb/>choice of the Standard Model gauge group, the choice of matter representations, <lb/>charge quantization, the number of families, quark and lepton mass hierarchies, the <lb/>smallness of neutrino masses, the gauge hierarchy problem and dark energy. <lb/>1.3.1. Anthropic arguments <lb/> All these worries only exist because there are minds to worry about them. It is quite <lb/>plausible that this would not be the case if we allow the parameters and discrete <lb/>choices of the Standard Model to vary. In an ensemble like the string landscape <lb/>many such variations can occur, and it is inevitable that worrying minds will only <lb/>worry about the small subset in which they can exist. This statement is one of <lb/>several possible formulations of the &quot; anthropic principle &quot; . It is a misnomer for <lb/>several reasons, and in this formulation it is certainly not a principle of physics, <lb/>like the equivalence principle. It is output, not input. One could even choose to <lb/>ignore it, but then one would miss several potential explanations of some of the <lb/>environmental problems. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 8 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A. N. Schellekens <lb/></note>

			<body> Without its embedding in the string theory landscape, anthropic reasoning <lb/>might also be called the end of physics, but in combination the two concepts merely <lb/>are a complete change of course for traditional physics. The notion of symmetries <lb/>as a fundamental concept is replaced by a combination of anthropic arguments and <lb/>information about distributions of parameters in a mathematically well-defined <lb/>ensemble. The lack of evidence for &quot; new physics &quot; may imply that we have reached <lb/>the historical moment where this change is occurring. But particle physics is an <lb/>experimental science, and the huge number of experimental results coming up in <lb/>the next few years may revive the notion of symmetries, and postpone the emer-<lb/>gence of a first glimpse of a landscape indefinitely. <lb/>1.3.2. Derivability vs. uniqueness <lb/> One often finds criticisms of string theory like: &quot; String theory was supposed to <lb/>explain why elementary particles could only have the precise masses and forces <lb/>that they do &quot; . In reality there has never been even a shred of evidence that string <lb/>theory was going to lead to that. It is also nearly impossible to find quotes of this <lb/>kind even in the earliest string papers. People making such statements are simply <lb/>projecting their own expectations for a fundamental theory on string theory. <lb/>These expectations reflect the traditional uniqueness paradigm of particle <lb/>physics: the hope that one day we will be able to derive all laws of physics, in <lb/>particular the Standard Model and all its parameters. The fine structure constant <lb/> α was expected to be given by some simple formula. This hope can be illustrated <lb/>by famous quotes by Einstein, Feynman and others. But two concepts are often <lb/>confused in this discussion, uniqueness and derivability. According to our current <lb/>understanding of string theory, it is not really the uniqueness of the underlying <lb/>theory that is at stake, but the uniqueness of the vacuum. If the vacuum is not <lb/>unique, the Standard Model and its parameters cannot be derived by purely math-<lb/>ematical manipulations. Additional information about the choice of vacuum, either <lb/>phenomenological or anthropic, must be provided. <lb/>The fact that the Standard Model and it couplings fit nicely in an SU (5) susy-<lb/>GUT is often proclaimed as a strong hint in favor of uniqueness. But once again a <lb/>distinction between uniqueness and derivability must be made. While GUTs may <lb/>indeed point in the direction of a unique theory, SU(5) GUTs also gave the first <lb/>hint against derivability, since they have two physically distinct vacua. The non-<lb/>uniqueness of the return path towards lower energies first encountered in GUTs <lb/>becomes much worse if one starts from the loftier vantage point of E  8  ×E  8  heterotic <lb/>strings. It is like climbing a mountain: eventually one may reach a unique point, <lb/>the top, but there may exist many other paths downwards, leading to other valleys. <lb/>Since string theory emerged during the height of the symmetry era, it is not <lb/>surprising that it was first seen as the realization of the dream of uniqueness, <lb/>interpreted as derivability. But in reality, string theory has been sending us exactly <lb/>the opposite message almost from the beginning. One day, this may be recognized <lb/>as its most important contribution to science. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 9 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The string theory landscape <lb/></note>

			<body> 1.3.3. Evidence outside string theory <lb/> From now on we will use the term &quot; uniqueness &quot; rather than &quot; derivability &quot; , because <lb/>that is what is commonly used. There has never been any evidence in favor of the <lb/>uniqueness paradigm, the idea that the Standard Model has to be derivable. But <lb/>there are several pieces of circumstantial evidence of the contrary, even without <lb/>string theory. <lb/>Theories of inflation typically lead to multiple instances of new universes, a <lb/> &quot; multiverse &quot; . Even without inflation, what argument do we have to suggest that <lb/>our own universe is unique, in any sense of the word? And if it is not unique, what <lb/>argument do we have to tell us that the other universes must have exactly the same <lb/>laws of physics as ours? The only fact that makes our universe and laws of physics <lb/>unique is that they are the only ones we can observe. <lb/>The possible existence of a plethora of scalars provides another reason to ques-<lb/>tion the uniqueness of the Standard Model. We have seen particles of various spins <lb/>and Standard Model couplings, but only recently we may have observed the first <lb/>Lorentz scalar, the Higgs boson. We have only been able to see it because it is un-<lb/>usually light and because it comes from a field that is not a Standard Model singlet. <lb/>But experimentally we know nothing about Lorentz scalar fields that are gauge sin-<lb/>glets. If they exist, they would appear in the Lagrangian as polynomials, modifying <lb/>all dimensionless parameters. Then all parameter values are vacuum expectation <lb/>values of scalar fields. One may still hope that this vacuum expectation value is <lb/>somehow uniquely determined, but in almost all examples we know (including the <lb/>Higgs potential of SU (5) GUTs) scalar potentials tend to have more than one local <lb/>minimum. One cannot say more without a more concretely defined theory, but in <lb/>the only theory where such potentials can be discussed, string theory, the number <lb/>of local minima appears to be astronomical. <lb/>Finally, the fact that the Standard Model is anthropically tuned provides evi-<lb/>dence against the idea of its derivability. This is because the Standard Model stands <lb/>out as a very special region in parameter space where nuclear physics and chemis-<lb/>try lead to complex structures we call &quot; life &quot; . It would require an uncanny miracle <lb/>for the two unrelated computations to give compatible results. Especially the last <lb/>argument suggests that the ultimate fundamental theory — assuming such a notion <lb/>makes sense and that we have enough intelligence and information to determine it — <lb/>must have a large ensemble of physically connected vacua. This allows a process <lb/>like eternal inflation to sample all these vacua, occasionally producing a universe <lb/>within the anthropic domain. <lb/>1.3.4. Uniqueness in the string landscape? <lb/> One may still hope that the resulting scalar potential somehow has a mathemat-<lb/>ically unique local minimum, but that would be pure wishful thinking. One may <lb/>even hope for a unique global minimum. However, it is not clear what to minimize, <lb/>because vacuum energy is not bounded from below. However, if vacuum energy <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 10 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A. N. Schellekens <lb/></note>

			<body> takes discrete values, there is a — presumably unique — vacuum with the low-<lb/>est positive vacuum energy. Could that describe our universe? Could it be that in <lb/>the sampling process of universes this particular one is somehow preferred? Another <lb/>notion is the &quot; dominant master vacuum &quot; , the state that dominates eternal inflation <lb/>because it is most frequently sampled, often by a huge factor. <lb/> 56  This is determined <lb/>by its stability against tunneling to other states, as well as the likelihood of others <lb/>tunneling into it. Both of these — the vacuum with lowest positive vacuum energy <lb/>or the dominant master vacuum — have a sense of uniqueness, but the anthropic <lb/>tuning argument makes it very unlikely that they happen to have the properties <lb/>that allow life to exist. There is no need for that, once there is a landscape. Then <lb/>the anthropic genie is already out of the bottle. All that is required is that there <lb/>exist metastable vacua in the anthropic zone of parameter space, and that their <lb/>sampling frequency is non-zero. There is no reason why they should dominate the <lb/>multiverse statistics. The dominant master vacuum does have an important positive <lb/>feature, because one may argue that most vacua have it in its history. Then it can <lb/>serve as a kind of eraser of initial conditions. Most observers would find themselves <lb/>in the anthropic universe most frequently reached by tunneling from the dominant <lb/>master vacuum. See Ref. 57 for some speculations regarding this idea. <lb/> 1.4. Changing perspectives on string phenomenology <lb/> The existence (or non-existence) of the string theory landscape has an important <lb/>impact on string phenomenology. One may distinguish at least three different atti-<lb/>tudes. The first is that we should simply find the exact point in the landscape that <lb/>corresponds to the Standard Model, use current data to fix it completely, and then <lb/>make an indefinite number of predictions for future experiments and observations. <lb/>This includes all work on explicit &quot; string model building &quot; in many corners of the <lb/>landscape, reviewed in the next section. The second is trying to extract generic <lb/>predictions from classes of models rather than individual ones. An example of work <lb/>in this category is the study of a class of M-theory models, reviewed in Ref. 58 <lb/>(see also Subsec. 2.11). The third is to try and understand the Standard Model by <lb/>considering landscape distributions in combination with anthropic constraints. This <lb/>is the point of view we take in Sec. 3. These three points of view are not mutually <lb/>exclusive. Their relative importance depends on how optimistic one is about the <lb/>chances of finding the exact Standard Model as a point in the landscape. <lb/> 2. The Compactification Landscape <lb/> We will present here just a brief sketch of the string compactification landscape. <lb/>For further details we recommend the very complete book <lb/> 59  and references therein. <lb/> 2.1. World-sheet versus space-time <lb/> In their simplest form, fermionic string theories live in ten flat dimensions. In addi-<lb/>tion there is an 11-dimensional theory that is not described by interacting strings, <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 11 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The string theory landscape <lb/></note>

			<body> but closely related to string theory, known as M-theory. But in any case, to make <lb/>contact with the real world we have to find theories in four dimensions. <lb/>There are essentially two ways of doing that: to choose another background <lb/>space-time geometry, or to change the world-sheet theory. The geometry can <lb/>be chosen as a flat four-dimensional space-time combined with a compact six-<lb/>dimensional space. This is called &quot; compactification &quot; . The world-sheet theory can <lb/>be modified by choosing an appropriate two-dimensional conformal field theory. In <lb/>D-dimensional flat space a string theory is described by D free two-dimensional <lb/>bosons X <lb/> µ  , and, if it is a fermionic string, also by D free fermions ψ <lb/> µ  . Instead, one <lb/>can choose another two-dimensional field theory that satisfies the same conditions <lb/>of conformal invariance, called a conformal field theory (CFT). In particular one <lb/>may use interacting two-dimensional theories, as long as X <lb/> µ  and ψ <lb/> µ  µ = 0, . . . , 3 <lb/>remain free fields. <lb/>The simplest compactification manifold is a six-dimensional torus. This can <lb/>easily be described both from the space-time and the world-sheet point of view. <lb/>The resulting theories only have non-chiral fermions in their space-time spectrum. <lb/>The same is true for the more general asymmetric torus compactifications of the <lb/>heterotic string with 6 left-moving and 22 right-moving &quot; chiral &quot; bosons found by <lb/>Narain. <lb/> 2 <lb/> The chirality problem is easily solved by a simple generalization that yields a <lb/>valid compactification manifold, namely a torus with discrete identifications. These <lb/>are called orbifold compactifications. <lb/> 60  These methods opened many new directions, <lb/>such as orbifolds with gauge background fields ( &quot; Wilson lines &quot; ), <lb/> 61  and were soon <lb/>generalized to asymmetric orbifolds, <lb/> 7  where &quot; asymmetric &quot; refers to the way left-<lb/>and right-moving modes were treated. Just as torus compactifications, orbifolds <lb/>can be viewed from both a space-time and a world-sheet perspective. Some orbifold <lb/>compactifications can be understood as singular limits of geometric Calabi–Yau <lb/>compactifications, which historically were discovered a little earlier (see Subsec. 2.3). <lb/>With more complicated compactifications, the connection between the world-sheet <lb/>and space-time perspectives becomes more and more difficult to make. <lb/> 2.2. General features <lb/> 2.2.1. Massive and massless modes <lb/> Before introducing some of the earliest string constructions and compactifications <lb/>in a little more detail, we will give a summary of the kind of spectra they generically <lb/>produce. Here we will assume a supersymmetric spectrum. This already implies the <lb/>prediction of a large number of particles that have not (yet) been observed. All <lb/>types of particles listed below typically occur in non-supersymmetric string spectra <lb/>as well, but in that case it is even less clear what their ultimate fate is, since the <lb/>stability of these string theories is not understood. <lb/>Any string theory contains infinitely many additional particles: massive string <lb/>excitations, Kaluza–Klein modes as in field theory compactifications, and winding <lb/>modes due to strings wrapping the compact spaces. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 12 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A. N. Schellekens <lb/></note>

			<body> Their masses are respectively proportional to the string scale, the inverse of <lb/>the compactification radius or the compactification radius itself. In world-sheet <lb/>constructions the different kinds of modes are on equal footing, and have Planckian <lb/>masses. In geometric constructions one can consider large volume limits, where <lb/>other mass distributions are possible. But in any case, of all the modes of the string <lb/>only the massless ones are relevant for providing the Standard Model particles, <lb/>which will acquire their masses from the Higgs mechanism and QCD, as usual. <lb/>Among the massless modes of string theories one may find some that match <lb/>known particles, but usually there are many that do not match anything we know. <lb/>This may just be an artifact of the necessarily primitive methods at our disposal. <lb/>Our intuition from many years of four-dimensional string model building may well <lb/>be heavily distorted by being too close to the supersymmetric limit, and by alge-<lb/>braically too simple constructions. Some of the additional particles may actually <lb/>be a blessing, if they solve some of the remaining problems of particle physics and <lb/>cosmology. The art of string phenomenology is to turn all seemingly superfluous <lb/>particles into a blessing, or understand why their presence is not generic. <lb/>In addition to moduli (already introduced in Subsec. 1.2.2) and axions (to be <lb/>discussed in Subsec. 3.6) string spectra generically include: <lb/>2.2.2. Chiral fermions and mirrors <lb/> All charged Standard Model fermions are chiral, and hence they can only acquire <lb/>a mass after weak symmetry breaking. Therefore one can say that the weak inter-<lb/>actions protect them from being very massive. It is very well possible that for this <lb/>reason all we have seen so far at low energy is chiral fermionic matter. <lb/>In attempts at getting the Standard Model from string theory, it is therefore <lb/>reasonable to require that the chiral spectra match. In general one finds additional <lb/>vector-like matter, whose mass is not protected by the weak interactions. Typically, <lb/>if one requires three chiral families, one gets N + 3 families and N mirror families. <lb/>If the N families &quot; pair off &quot; with the N mirror families to acquire a sufficiently large <lb/>mass, the low energy spectrum agrees with the data. <lb/>2.2.3. Additional vector bosons <lb/> Most string spectra have considerably more vector bosons than the twelve we have <lb/>seen so far in nature. Even if the presence of SU (3), SU (2) and U (1) as factors <lb/>in the gauge group is imposed as a condition, one rarely finds just the Standard <lb/>Model gauge group. In heterotic strings one is usually left with one of the E  8  factors. <lb/>Furthermore in nearly all string constructions additional U (1) factors are found. A <lb/>very common one is a gauged B − L symmetry. <lb/>Additional gauge groups are often needed as &quot; hidden sectors &quot; in model building, <lb/>especially for supersymmetry breaking. Extra U (1)&apos;s may be observable trough <lb/>kinetic mixing <lb/> 62  with the Standard Model U (1), via contributions to the action <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 13 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The string theory landscape <lb/></note>

			<body> proportional to F  µν  V <lb/> µν  , where F is the Y field strength, and V the one of the <lb/>extra U (1)&apos;s <lb/>2.2.4. Exotics <lb/> One often finds particles that do not match any of the observed matter representa-<lb/>tions, nor their mirrors. Notorious examples are color singlets with fractional electric <lb/>charge or higher rank tensors. These are generically called &quot; exotics &quot; . If there are <lb/>exotics that are chiral with respect to SU (3) × SU (2) × U (1), these spectra should <lb/>be rejected, because any attempt to make sense of such theories is too far-fetched <lb/>to be credible. These particles may be acceptable if they are vector-like, because <lb/>one may hope that they become massive under generic perturbations. <lb/> 2.3. Calabi Yau compactifications <lb/> The first examples of compactifications with chiral spectra and N = 1 supersym-<lb/>metry were found for the E  8  × E  8  heterotic string in Ref. 63, even before the afore-<lb/>mentioned mathematically simpler orbifold compactifications. The compactification <lb/>manifolds are six-dimensional, Ricci-flat Kähler manifolds with SU (3) holonomy, <lb/>called Calabi–Yau manifolds. The B  µν  field strength H  µνρ  was assumed to vanish, <lb/>which leads to the consistency condition <lb/> dH = Tr R ∧ R − <lb/> 1 <lb/>30 <lb/>Tr F ∧ F = 0 . <lb/> (5) <lb/>This implies in particular a relation between the gravitational and gauge field back-<lb/>grounds. This condition can be solved by using a background gauge field that is <lb/>equal to the spin connection of the manifold, embedded in an SU (3) subgroup of <lb/>one of the E  8  factors. In compactifications of this kind one obtains a spectrum with <lb/>a gauge group E  6  × E  8  . The group E  6  contains the Standard Model gauge group <lb/> SU (3) × SU (2) × U (1) plus two additional U (1)&apos;s. The group E  8  is superfluous <lb/>but hidden (Standard Model particles do not couple to it), and may play a rôle in <lb/>supersymmetry breaking. <lb/>If some dimensions of space are compactified, ten-dimensional fermion fields are <lb/>split as <lb/>Ψ  +  (x, y) = Ψ  L  (x)Ψ  +  (y) + Ψ  R  (x)Ψ  −  (y) <lb/>(6) <lb/>where x denotes four-dimensional and y six-dimensional coordinates, +/− denotes <lb/>chirality in ten and six dimensions, and L, R denote chirality in four dimensions. <lb/>The number of massless fermions of each chirality observed in four dimensions <lb/>is determined by the number of zero-mode solutions of the six-dimensional Dirac <lb/>equation in the background of interest. These numbers are equal to two topological <lb/>invariants of the Calabi–Yau manifold, the Hodge numbers, h  11  and h  12  . As a result <lb/>one obtains h  11  chiral fermions in the representation (27) and h  12  in the (27) of E  6  . <lb/>The group E  6  is a known extension of the Standard Model, an example of a Grand <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 14 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A. N. Schellekens <lb/></note>

			<body> Unified Theory, in which all three factors of the Standard Model are embedded in <lb/>one simple Lie algebra. It is not the most preferred extension; a Standard Model <lb/>family contains 15 or 16 (if we assume the existence of a right-handed neutrino) <lb/>chiral fermions, not 27. However, since the 11 superfluous fermions are not chiral <lb/>with respect to SU (3) × SU (2) × U (1), they can acquire a mass without the help <lb/>of the Higgs mechanism, in the unbroken Standard Model. Therefore these masses <lb/>may be well above current experimental limits. <lb/>The number of Calabi–Yau manifolds is huge. A subset associated with four-<lb/>dimensional reflexive polyhedra has been completely enumerated. <lb/> 64  This list con-<lb/>tains more than 470 million topological classes with 31,108 distinct Hodge number <lb/>pairs. <lb/>In 1986 Strominger <lb/> 3  considered more general geometric background geometries <lb/>with torsion. This gave rise to so many possibilities that the author concluded &quot; all <lb/> predictive power seems to have been lost  &quot; . <lb/> 2.4. Free field theory constructions <lb/> Several other methods were developed around the same time as Calabi–Yau com-<lb/>pactifications and orbifolds. Narain&apos;s generalized torus compactifications lead to a <lb/>continuous infinity of possibilities, but all without chiral fermions. Although this <lb/>infinity of possibilities is not really a surprising feature for a torus compactifi-<lb/>cation, Narain&apos;s paper was an eye-opener because, unlike standard six-dimensional <lb/>torus compactifications, this approach allowed a complete modification of the gauge <lb/>group. <lb/>More general world-sheet methods started being explored in 1986. Free field <lb/>theory constructions allowed a more systematic exploration of certain classes of <lb/>string theories. It became clear very quickly that also in this case there was a <lb/>plethora of possibilities. But unlike Narain&apos;s constructions, these theories can have <lb/>chiral fermions, and furthermore they did not seem to provide a continuum of <lb/>options, but only discrete choices. With the benefit of hindsight, one can now say <lb/>that all these theories do have continuous deformations, which can be realized by <lb/>giving vacuum expectation values to certain massless scalars in the spectrum. Since <lb/>these deformed theories do not have a free field theory descriptions, these defor-<lb/>mations are not manifest in the construction. They are the world sheet construc-<lb/>tion counterparts of the geometric moduli. This does however not imply that the <lb/>plethora of solutions can simply be viewed as different points in one continuous <lb/>moduli space. Since many spectra are chirally distinct, it is more appropriate to <lb/>view this as the discovery of a huge number of distinct moduli spaces, all leading <lb/>to different physics. <lb/>An important tool in these free-field theory constructions is boson-fermion <lb/>equivalence in two dimensions. In this way the artificial distinction between the <lb/>two can be removed, and one can describe the heterotic string entirely in terms of <lb/>free fermions <lb/> 4,6  or free bosons. <lb/> 5  These constructions are closely related, and there <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 15 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The string theory landscape <lb/></note>

			<body> is a huge area of overlap: constructions based on complex free fermions pairs can <lb/>be written in terms of free bosons. However, one may also consider real fermions or <lb/>free bosons on lattices that do not allow a straightforward realization in terms of <lb/>free fermions. <lb/>2.4.1. Free fermions <lb/> Both methods have to face the problem of finding solutions to the conditions of <lb/>modular invariance, a one-loop consistency condition. In the fermionic construc-<lb/>tions this is done by allowing periodic or anti-periodic boundaries on closed cycles <lb/>on the manifold for all fermions independently. Modular transformations change <lb/>those boundary conditions, and hence they are constrained by the requirements of <lb/>modular invariance. These constraints can be solved systematically (although in <lb/>practice usually not exhaustively). Very roughly (ignoring some of the constraints), <lb/>the number of modular invariant combinations is of order 2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> 2  n(n−1)  for n fermions. <lb/>There are 44 right-moving and 18 left-moving fermions, so that there are potentially <lb/>huge numbers of string theories. In reality there are however many degeneracies. <lb/>In-depth explorations <lb/> 65  have been done of a subclass of fermionic constructions <lb/>using a special set of free fermion boundary conditions that allows spectra with <lb/>three families to come out. This work focuses on Pati–Salam model. Other work <lb/> 66,67 <lb/> explores the variations of the &quot; NAHE &quot; set of free fermion boundary conditions. This <lb/>is a set of fermion boundary vectors proposed in Ref. 68 that are a useful starting <lb/>point for finding &quot; realistic &quot; spectra. <lb/>2.4.2. Free bosons: Covariant lattices <lb/> In bosonic constructions the modular invariance constraints are solved by requiring <lb/>that the momenta of the bosons lie on a Lorentzian even self-dual lattice. This <lb/>means that the lattice of quantized momenta is identical to the lattice defining the <lb/>compactified space, and that all vectors have even norm. Both conditions are defined <lb/>in terms of a metric, which is +1 for left-moving bosons and −1 for right-moving <lb/>ones. These bosons include the ones of Narain&apos;s torus, plus eight right-moving ones <lb/>representing the fermionic degrees of freedom, ψ <lb/> µ  and the ghosts of superconformal <lb/>invariance. These eight bosons originate from the bosonic string map (originally <lb/>developed for ten-dimensional strings <lb/> 69  ) used to map the entire fermionic sector <lb/>of the heterotic string to a bosonic string sector. <lb/> 5  Then the Lorentzian metric <lb/>has signature ((+) <lb/> 22  , (−) <lb/> 14  )), and the even self-dual lattice is denoted Γ  22,14  . This <lb/>is called a covariant lattice because it incorporates space-time Lorentz invariance <lb/>for the fermionic string. Since the conditions for modular invariance are invariant <lb/>under SO(22, 14) Lorentz transformations, and since the spectrum of L  0  and ¯ <lb/> L  0  is <lb/>changed under such transformations, their would appear to be a continuous infinity <lb/>of solutions. But the right-moving modes of the lattice are strongly constrained <lb/>by the requirement of two-dimensional supersymmetry, which is imposed using a <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 16 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A. N. Schellekens <lb/></note>

			<body> non-linear realization <lb/> 70  (other realizations exist, see for example Refs. 71, 72). This <lb/>leads to the so called &quot; triplet constraint &quot; . <lb/> 4  This makes the right-moving part of <lb/>the lattice rigid. The canonical linear realization of supersymmetry, relating X <lb/> µ  to <lb/> ψ <lb/> µ  , on the other hand leads to lattices Γ  22,6  × E  8  with complete Lorentz rotation <lb/>freedom in the first factor, which is just a Narain lattice. <lb/> 2.5. An early attempt at vacuum counting <lb/> Several of the 1986 papers make attempts at getting a rough idea about the number <lb/>of solutions. This is fairly straightforward for free fermions with periodic and anti-<lb/>periodic boundary conditions, as explained above. However, the main problem is <lb/>that not all solutions are different. Indeed, in general there are huge degeneracies <lb/>among solutions that reduce the estimate by large factors. We will explain here <lb/>a counting estimate used for covariant lattice constructions, because it give an <lb/>interesting insight in the growth of the number of possibilities. However, this should <lb/>not be confused with counting moduli stabilized points in potentials. Indeed, all <lb/>these string theories have unstabilized moduli. <lb/>An interesting estimate exists for even self dual lattices, which has the advantage <lb/>that it only counts distinct solutions. Unfortunately, heterotic strings are based on <lb/>lorentzian lattices, for which there are no such theorems. In fact, these lattices are <lb/>unique up to Lorentz transformations, but the Lorentz transformations modify the <lb/>heterotic spectrum. However, covariant lattices that lead to chiral spectra have a <lb/>rigid right-moving sector that forbids continuous Lorentz transformations. <lb/>The rigidity of the right-moving part of the lattice discretizes the number of <lb/>solutions, which is in fact finite for a given world-sheet supersymmetry realization. <lb/>A very crude attempt to estimate the number of solutions was made in Ref. 5, and <lb/>works as follows. One can map the right-moving bosons to a definite set of 66 left-<lb/>moving bosons, while preserving modular invariance. This brings us into the realm <lb/>of even self-dual Euclidean lattices, for which powerful classification theorems exist. <lb/>Such lattices exist only in dimensions that are a multiple of eight, and have <lb/>been enumerated for dimensions 8, 16 and 24, with respectively 1, 2 and 24 solutions <lb/>(in 8 dimensions the solution is the root lattice of E  8  , in 16 dimensions they are <lb/> E  8  ⊕E  8  and the root lattice of D  16  plus a spinor weight lattice, and in 24 dimensions <lb/>the solutions were enumerated in Ref. 73). There exists a remarkable formula (the <lb/> &quot; Siegel mass formula &quot; ) which gives information about the total number of distinct <lb/>lattices Λ of dimension 8k in terms of: <lb/> Λ <lb/> g(Λ) <lb/> −1  = <lb/>1 <lb/>8k <lb/> B  4k <lb/>4k−1 <lb/> j=1 <lb/> B  2j <lb/> 4j <lb/> . <lb/> (7) <lb/>Here g(Λ) is the order of the automorphism group of the lattice Λ and B  2j  are <lb/>the Bernoulli numbers. Since the automorphisms include the reflection symmetry, <lb/> g(Λ) ≥ 2. If we assume that the lattice of maximal symmetry is D  8k  (the root <lb/>lattice plus a spinor, which is a canonical way to get an even self-dual lattice) we <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 17 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The string theory landscape <lb/></note>

			<body> have a plausible guess for the upper limit of g(Λ) as well, namely the size of the <lb/>Weyl group of D  8k  , 2 <lb/> 8k−1  (8k)!. This assumption is incorrect for k = 1, where the <lb/>only lattice is E  8  , and k = 2, where the lattice E  8  × E  8  wins against D  16  , but for <lb/> k = 3 and larger the Weyl group of D  8k  is larger than the automorphism group of <lb/>the lattice (E  8  ) <lb/> k  . For k = 3 the assumption has been checked in Ref. 74 for all 24 <lb/>Niemeier lattices. Making this assumption we get <lb/>1 <lb/>4k <lb/> B  4k <lb/>4k−1 <lb/> j=1 <lb/> B  2j <lb/> 4j <lb/> &lt; N  8k  &lt; 2 <lb/> 8k−1  (8k − 1)!B  4k <lb/>4k−1 <lb/> j=1 <lb/> B  2j <lb/> 4j <lb/>(8) <lb/>which for k = 11 gives 10 <lb/> 930  &lt; N  88  &lt; 10 <lb/> 1090  (in Ref. 75 this number was esti-<lb/>mated rather inaccurately as 10 <lb/> 1500  ; all numbers quoted here are based on an exact <lb/>computation). <lb/>From a list of all N  88  lattices one could read off all the free bosonic CFTs <lb/>with the world-sheet supersymmetry realization discussed above. In particular, this <lb/>shows that the total number is finite. However, there is a very restrictive subsidiary <lb/>constraint due to the fact that 66 of the 88 bosons were obtained from the right <lb/>moving sector. Those bosons must have their momenta on a D  3  × (D  7  ) <lb/> 9  lattice <lb/>and satisfy an additional constraint inherited from world sheet supersymmetry, <lb/>the triplet constraint. Perhaps a more reasonable estimate is to view this as a <lb/>lattice with 32 orthogonal building blocks, D  3  × (D  7  ) <lb/> 9  × (D  1  ) <lb/> 22  , which should be <lb/>combinatorically similar to (D  1  ) <lb/> 32  then the relevant number would be N  32  , which <lb/>lies between 8 × 10 <lb/> 7  and 2.4 × 10 <lb/> 51  . But unlike N  88  , N  32  is not a strict limit, and <lb/>furthermore is still subject to the triplet constraint. <lb/>All of this can be done explicitly for 10 dimensional strings. Then one needs <lb/>the lattices of dimension 24, and eight of the 24 lattices satisfy the subsidiary <lb/>constraints for ten-dimensional strings, <lb/> 75  namely the presence of a D  8  factor. <lb/> 2.6. Unexplored landscapes: Meromorphic CFTs <lb/> The concept of chiral conformal field theories and even self-dual lattices can <lb/>be generalized to interacting theories, the so-called meromorphic conformal field <lb/>theories. <lb/> 76  These can only exist if the central charge c (the generalization of the <lb/>lattice dimension to CFT) is a multiple of 8. For c = 8 and c = 16 these meromor-<lb/>phic CFTs are just chiral bosons on even self-dual lattices, but for c = 24 there <lb/>71 CFT&apos;s are conjectured <lb/> 77  to exist including the 24 Niemeier lattices (most of <lb/>them have indeed been constructed). Gauge symmetries in the vast majority of the <lb/>heterotic strings in the literature (for exceptions see for example Ref. 78) are math-<lb/>ematically described in terms of affine Lie algebras, a kind of string generalization <lb/>of simple Lie-algebras, whose representations are characterized by a Lie-algebra <lb/>highest weight and an additional integer parameter k called the level. In the free <lb/>boson theories the only representations one encounters have k = 1, and the total <lb/>rank equals the number of compactified bosons in the left-moving sector, 22 for <lb/>four-dimensional strings, and 24 for Niemeier lattices. All even self-dual lattices are <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-17 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 18 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A. N. Schellekens <lb/></note>

			<body> direct sums of level 1 affine algebras plus a number of abelian factors (U(1)&apos;s), which <lb/>we will call the gauge group of the theory. In meromorphic CFT&apos;s the restriction <lb/>to level one is removed. The list of 71 meromorphic CFTs contains 70 cases with a <lb/>gauge group whose total central charge is 24, plus one that has no gauge group at <lb/>all, the &quot; monster module &quot; . Just one of these yields an additional ten-dimensional <lb/>string theory with tachyons and an E  8  realized as an affine Lie algebra at level 2. <lb/>This solution was already known, <lb/> 79  and was obtained using free fermions. <lb/>The importance of the meromorphic CFT approach is that it gives a complete <lb/>classification of all solutions without assuming a particular construction method. <lb/>In four dimensions the same method can be used. For example, from a list of <lb/>meromorphic CFTs with c = 88 all four-dimensional string theories with a given <lb/>realization of world-sheet supersymmetry (namely the same one used above) can be <lb/>obtained, independent of the construction method. Unfortunately next to nothing <lb/>is known about meromorphic CFTs for c ≥ 32. It is not known if, like lattices, <lb/>they are finite in number. Their gauge groups can have central charges that are not <lb/>necessarily 0 or the total central charge of the meromorphic CFT. It is not known <lb/>if the gauge groups are typically large or small. There is an entire landscape here <lb/>that is totally unexplored, but hard to access. <lb/>So far this method of mapping a heterotic theory to a meromorphic CFT has <lb/>only been applied to a world-sheet supersymmetry realization using the triplet <lb/>constraint. But this can be generalized to other realizations of world-sheet super-<lb/>symmetry, including perhaps the ones discussed in the next section. <lb/>The point we are trying to make here is that despite many decades of work, we <lb/>are probably still only able to see the tip of a huge iceberg. <lb/> 2.7. Gepner models <lb/> In 1987 world-sheet constructions were extended further by the use of interacting <lb/>rather than free two-dimensional conformal field theories. <lb/> 80  The &quot; building blocks &quot; <lb/>of this construction are two-dimensional conformal field theories with N = 2 world-<lb/>sheet supersymmetry. These building blocks are combined ( &quot; tensored &quot; ) in such a <lb/>way that they contribute in the same way to the energy momentum tensor as six <lb/>free bosons and fermions. This is measured in terms of the central charge of the <lb/>Virasoro algebra, which must have a value c = 9. In principle the number of such <lb/>building blocks is huge, but in practice only a very limited set is available, namely <lb/>the &quot; minimal models &quot; with central charge c = 3k/(k + 2), for k = 1 . . . ∞. There <lb/>are 168 distinct ways of adding these numbers to 9, so that only a few members of <lb/>the infinite set are actually used. <lb/>With the constraints of superconformal invariance solved, one now has to deal <lb/>with modular invariance. In exact CFT constructions the partition function takes <lb/>the form <lb/> P (τ, ¯ <lb/> τ ) = <lb/> ij <lb/> χ  i  (τ )M  ij  ¯ <lb/> χ  j  (¯ τ ) , <lb/> (9) <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-18 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 19 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The string theory landscape <lb/></note>

			<body> where χ  i  are characters of the Virasoro algebra, traces over the entire Hilbert space <lb/>built on the ground state labeled i by the action of the Virasoro generators L  n  : <lb/> χ  i  (τ ) = Tr e <lb/> 2πiτ (L0−c/24)  . <lb/> (10) <lb/>The multiplicity matrix M indicates how often the ground states |i|j occurs in <lb/>the spectrum. Its entries are non-negative integers, and it is severely constrained <lb/>by modular invariance. Note that in (9) we allowed for the possibility that the <lb/>left-and right-moving modes have a different symmetry (a different extension of <lb/>superconformal symmetry) with different sets of characters χ and ¯ <lb/> χ. But then <lb/>the conditions for modular invariance are very hard to solve. They can be trivially <lb/>solved if the left and right algebras are the same. Then modular invariance demands <lb/>that M must commute with the matrices S and T that represent the action of the <lb/>modular transformations τ → −1/τ and τ → τ + 1 on the characters. This has <lb/>always at least one solution, M  ij  = δ  ij  . <lb/>However, assuming identical left and right algebras is contrary to the basic idea <lb/>of the heterotic string. Instead Gepner model building focuses on a subset, namely <lb/>those spectra that can be obtained from a symmetric type-II spectrum by mapping <lb/>one of the fermionic sectors to a bosonic sector. For this purpose we can use the <lb/>same bosonic string map discussed above. This results in a very special and very <lb/>limited subset of the possible bosonic sectors. <lb/>Using the discrete symmetries of the building blocks, for each of the 168 tensor <lb/>combinations, a number of distinct modular invariant partition functions can be <lb/>constructed, for a grand total of about five thousand. <lb/> 81  Each of them gives a string <lb/>spectrum with a gauge group E  6  × E  8  (or occasionally an extension of E  6  to E  7  or <lb/> E  8  ) with massless chiral matter in the representations (27) and (27) of E  6  , exactly <lb/>like the Calabi–Yau compactifications discussed above. <lb/>Indeed, it was understood not long thereafter that there is a close relationship <lb/>between these &quot; Gepner models &quot; and geometric compactifications on Calabi–Yau <lb/>manifolds. Exact correspondences between their spectra were found, including the <lb/>number of singlets. This led to the conjecture that Gepner Models are Calabi– <lb/>Yau compactifications in a special point of moduli space. Evidence was provided <lb/>by a conjectured relation between N = 2 minimal models and critical points of <lb/>Landau–Ginzburg models. <lb/> 82,83 <lb/> Getting the right number of families in this class of models has been challenging, <lb/>since this number turns out to be quantized in units of six or four in nearly all cases <lb/>that were studied initially. The only exception is a class studied in Ref. 84. <lb/> 2.8. Dualities, M-theory and F-theory <lb/> In general, four-dimensional string theories are related to others by maps like <lb/>S-duality <lb/> 85  (strong-weak dualities due to inversion of coupling constants), T-<lb/>duality (transformations involving inversion of compactification radii) and combi-<lb/>nations thereof. This suggests a connected &quot; landscape &quot; of four-dimensional strings. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-19 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 20 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A. N. Schellekens <lb/></note>

			<body> However, this is still largely based on anecdotal evidence. A complete picture of the <lb/>four-dimensional string landscape is still very far away. <lb/>In ten (and eleven) dimensions, the picture is better understood. Under S-<lb/>duality, Type-IIA string theory is mapped to an 11-dimensional theory compactified <lb/>on a circle. <lb/> 86,87  The 11-dimensional theory is not a string theory. It is called &quot; M-<lb/>theory &quot; . Its field theory limit is D = 11 supergravity. <lb/>A similar relation holds for the E  8  × E  8  heterotic string. Its strong coupling <lb/>limit can be formulated in terms of 11-dimensional M-theory compactified on a line-<lb/>segment, <lb/> 88  the circle with two halves identified. This is sometimes called &quot; heterotic <lb/>M-theory &quot; . <lb/>Strong coupling duality maps type-IIB strings to themselves. <lb/> 89  Furthermore the <lb/>self-duality can be extended from an action just on the string coupling, and hence <lb/>the dilaton, to an action on the entire dilaton-axion multiplet. This action is math-<lb/>ematically identical to the action of modular transformations on the two moduli <lb/>of the torus, and corresponds to the group SL(2, Z). This isomorphism suggests <lb/>a geometric understanding of the self-duality in terms of a compactification torus <lb/> T  2  , whose degrees of freedom correspond to the dilaton and axion field. An obvious <lb/>guess would be that the type-IIB string may be viewed as a torus compactification <lb/>of some twelve-dimensional theory. <lb/> 90  But there is no such theory. The first attempts <lb/>to develop this idea led instead to a new piece of the landscape called &quot; F-theory &quot; , <lb/>consisting only of compactifications and related to E  8  × E  8  heterotic strings and <lb/>M-theory by chains of dualities. <lb/> 2.9. New directions in heterotic strings <lb/> 2.9.1. New embeddings <lb/> The discovery of heterotic M-theory opened many new directions. Instead of the <lb/>canonical embedding of the SU (3) valued spin-connection of a Calabi–Yau manifold, <lb/>some of these manifolds admit other bundles that can be embedded in the gauge <lb/>group. In general, condition (5) is then not automatically satisfied, but in heterotic <lb/>M-theory one may get extra contributions from heterotic five branes. <lb/> 91,92 <lb/> In this way one can avoid getting the Standard Model via the complicated route <lb/>of E  6  Grand Unification. Some examples that have been studied are SU (4) bun-<lb/>dles, <lb/> 93  U (1) <lb/> 4  bundles <lb/> 94  and SU (N ) × U (1) bundles, <lb/> 95  which break E  8  to the more <lb/>appealing SO(10) GUTs, to SU (5) GUTs, or even directly to the Standard Model. <lb/>Extensive and systematic searches are underway that have resulted in hundreds <lb/>of distinct examples <lb/> 96  with the exact supersymmetric Standard Model spectrum, <lb/>without even any vector-like matter (but with extra gauge groups and the usual <lb/>large numbers of singlets). However, the gauge group contains extra U (1)&apos;s and an <lb/> E  8  factor, and large numbers of gauge singlets, including unstabilized moduli. There <lb/>can be several Higgs multiplets. To break the GUT groups down to the Standard <lb/>Model, background gauge fields on suitable Wilson lines are used. For this purpose <lb/>one needs a manifold with a freely acting (i.e. no point on the manifold is fixed by <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 21 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The string theory landscape <lb/></note>

			<body> the action) discrete symmetry. One then identifies points on the manifold related by <lb/>this symmetry and adds a background gauge field on a closed cycle on the quotient <lb/>manifold (a Wilson line). <lb/>2.9.2. The heterotic mini-landscape <lb/> The Heterotic Mini-landscape is a class of orbifold compactifications on a torus <lb/> T <lb/> 6  /Z  6  cleverly constructed so that the heterotic gauge group E  8  ×E  8  is broken down <lb/>to different subgroups in different fixed points, such as SO(10), SU (4) <lb/> 2  and SU (6)× <lb/> SU (2). This leads to the notion of local unification. <lb/> 97–99  The Standard Model gauge <lb/>group is the intersection of the various &quot; local &quot; gauge realized at the fixed points. <lb/>Fields that are localized near the fixed points must respect its symmetry, and hence <lb/>be in complete multiplets of that group. Unlike field theory GUTs, these models <lb/>have no limit where SO(10) is an exact global symmetry. In this way one can <lb/>make sure that matter families are in complete spinor representations of SO(10), <lb/> while Higgs bosons need not be in complete representations of SO(10), avoiding <lb/>the notorious doublet splitting problem of GUTs. The number of 3-family models <lb/>in this part of the landscape is of order a few hundred, and there is an extensive <lb/>body of work on their phenomenological successes and problems, see for example <lb/>Refs. 100, 101 and references therein. <lb/>2.9.3. Heterotic Gepner models <lb/> As explained above, the original Gepner models are limited in scope by the require-<lb/>ment that the left and right algebras should be the same. There is no such limita-<lb/>tion in free CFT constructions, but they are limited in being non-interacting in two <lb/>dimensions. What we would like to have is asymmetric, interacting CFT construc-<lb/>tions. Examples in this class have been obtained using a method called &quot; heterotic <lb/>weight lifting &quot; . <lb/> 102  In the left-moving sector one of the superconformal building <lb/>blocks (combined with one of the E  8  factors) is replaced by another CFT that has <lb/>no superconformal symmetry, but is isomorphic to the original building block as <lb/>a modular group representation. This opens up an entirely new area of the het-<lb/>erotic string landscape. It turns out that the difficulty in getting three families now <lb/>disappears. <lb/> 2.10. Orientifolds and intersecting branes <lb/> The Standard Model comes out remarkably easily from the simplest heterotic <lb/>strings. But that is by no means the only way. One may also get gauge groups <lb/>in string theory from stacks of membranes. If open strings end on a D-brane that <lb/>does not fill all of space-time, a distinction must be made between their fluctuations <lb/>away from the branes, and the fluctuations of their endpoints on the branes. The <lb/>former are standard string vibrations leading to gravity (as well as a dilaton, and <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-21 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 22 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A. N. Schellekens <lb/></note>

			<body> other vibrational modes of closed strings), whereas fluctuations of the endpoints <lb/>are only observable on the brane, and give rise to fermions and gauge interactions. <lb/>2.10.1. Chan–Paton groups <lb/> The possibility of getting gauge theories and matter from branes sparked another <lb/>direction of research with the goal of getting the Standard Model from open string <lb/>theories. To get towards the Standard Model, one starts with type-II string theory, <lb/>and compactifies six dimensions on a manifold. This compactified manifold may <lb/>have a large radius, as in the brane world scenario, but this is optional. In these <lb/>theories one finds suitable D-branes coinciding with four-dimensional Minkowski <lb/>space, and intersecting each other in the compactified directions. These can be <lb/>D5, D7 or D9 branes in type-IIB and D6 branes in type-IIA. Each such brane <lb/>can give rise to a gauge group, called a Chan–Paton gauge group, which can be <lb/> U (N ), Sp(N ) or O(N ). <lb/> 103  By having several different branes one can obtain a <lb/>gauge group consisting of several factors, like the one of the Standard Model. The <lb/>brane intersections can give rise to massless string excitations of open strings with <lb/>their ends on the two intersecting branes. These excitations can be fermions, and <lb/>they can be chiral. Each open string end endows the fermion with a fundamental <lb/>representation of one of the two Chan–Paton groups, so that the matter is in a <lb/>bi-fundamental representation of those gauge groups. <lb/>Remarkably, a Standard Model family has precisely the right structure to be <lb/>realized in this manner. The first example is the so-called &quot; Madrid model &quot; . <lb/> 104  It <lb/>consists of four stacks of branes, a U (3) stack giving the strong interactions, a U (2) <lb/>or Sp(2) stack for the weak interactions, plus two U (1) stacks. The Standard Model <lb/> Y charge is a linear combination of the unitary phase factors of the first, third and <lb/>fourth stack (the stacks are labeled a . . . d) <lb/> Y = <lb/>1 <lb/>6 <lb/> Q  a  + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> Q  c  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> Q  d  . <lb/> This configuration is depicted in Fig. 1(a). <lb/>2.10.2. The three main classes <lb/> There are other ways of getting the Standard Model. They fall into three broad <lb/>classes, labeled by a real number x. The Standard Model generator is in general <lb/>some linear combination of all four brane charges (assuming stack b is U (2) and <lb/>not Sp(2)), and takes the form <lb/> 105 <lb/> Y = <lb/> x − <lb/> 1 <lb/>3 <lb/> Q  a  + <lb/> x − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> Q  b  + xQ  c  + (x − 1)Q  d  . <lb/> (11) <lb/>Two values of x are special. The case x = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  leads to a large class containing among <lb/>others the Madrid model, Pati–Salam models <lb/> 106  and flipped SU (5) <lb/> 107  models. The <lb/>value x = 0 gives rise to classic SU (5) GUTs. <lb/> 108  To get Standard Model families <lb/></body>

			<page>1530016-22 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 23 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The string theory landscape <lb/></note>

			<body> e <lb/> + <lb/> , v  R <lb/> (e <lb/> − <lb/> , ν) <lb/> (u, d) <lb/> u <lb/>  * <lb/> , d <lb/>  * <lb/> (10) <lb/> (5*) <lb/> (a) <lb/> (b) <lb/>(c) <lb/> Fig. 1. Brane configurations: (a) the Madrid model, (b) SU(5) GUTs and (c) Trinification. <lb/> in this case one needs chiral anti-symmetric rank-2 tensors, which originate from <lb/>open strings with both their endpoints on the same brane. The simplest example <lb/>is shown in Fig. 1(b). It has one U (5) stack giving rise to the GUT gauge group, <lb/>but needs at least one other brane in order to get matter in the (5) representation <lb/>of SU (5). <lb/>Other values of x can only occur for oriented strings, which means that there is <lb/>a definite orientation distinguishing one end of the string from the other end. An <lb/>interesting possibility in this class is the trinification model, depicted in Fig. 1(c). <lb/>Note that it was assumed here that there are at most four branes participating <lb/>in the Standard Model. If one relaxes that condition, the number of possibilities is <lb/>unlimited. <lb/>2.10.3. Orientifolds <lb/> An important issue in open string model building is the cancellation of tadpoles of <lb/>the disk diagram. These lead to divergences and can lead to chiral anomalies. These <lb/>tadpoles can sometimes be canceled by adding another object to the theory, called <lb/>an orientifold plane. In fact, the usual procedure is to start with an oriented type-II <lb/>string, and consider an involution of the world-sheet that reverses its orientation. <lb/>Then one allows strings to close up to that involution. In terms of world-sheet <lb/>topology, this amounts to adding surfaces with the topology of a Klein bottle. The <lb/>combination of torus and Klein-bottle diagram acts like a projection on the closed <lb/>string theory, removing some of its states. In most cases, removing states from <lb/>string theory comes at a price: other states must be added to compensate what <lb/>was removed. In this case, this rôle is played by open strings. These ideas were <lb/>pioneered in Refs. 109, 110. <lb/>Orientifold model building has been very actively pursued during the first decade <lb/>of this century (see Ref. 111 for a review). <lb/>2.10.4. Anomalies, axions and massive abelian vector bosons <lb/> Canceling all tadpoles between the disk and crosscap diagram removes most <lb/>anomalies, but some factorized anomalies remain which can then be canceled by <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-23 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 24 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A. N. Schellekens <lb/></note>

			<body> the Green–Schwarz mechanism <lb/> 112  involving tree-level diagrams with exchange of <lb/>axions. In contrast to perturbative heterotic strings the anomaly factorizes in terms <lb/>of several factors. These anomalies are then canceled by a Green–Schwarz mecha-<lb/>nism involving multiple axions, which are available in the Ramond–Ramond sector <lb/>of the closed theory. <lb/>In four dimensions, a factorized anomaly always involves a U (1). The corre-<lb/>sponding U (1) vector bosons acquire a mass by &quot; eating &quot; the axion, which provides <lb/>the missing longitudinal mode. String theory will always remove anomalous sym-<lb/>metries in this manner, but it turns out that this can happen for non-anomalous <lb/> U (1) <lb/>  s as well. This can be traced back to anomalies in six dimensions. <lb/> 113 <lb/> 2.10.5. Boundary RCFT constructions <lb/> Just as in the heterotic string, one can construct orientifold spectra using purely <lb/>geometric methods, orbifold methods or world-sheet constructions. Most work in <lb/>the literature uses the second approach. <lb/>World-sheet approaches use boundary CFT: conformal field theory on surfaces <lb/>with boundaries and crosscaps. This requires an extension of the closed string <lb/>Hilbert space with &quot; states &quot; (in fact not normalizable, and hence not in the closed <lb/>string Hilbert space) that describe closed strings near a boundary, or in the pre-<lb/>sence of orientation reversal. An extensive formalism for computing boundary and <lb/>crosscap states in (rational) CFT was developed in the last decade of last century, <lb/>starting with Ref. 114, developed further by several groups, <lb/> 115–119  culminating in <lb/>a simple and general formula. <lb/> 120  For an extensive review of this field see Ref. 121. <lb/>This was applied to orientifolds of Gepner models, <lb/> 122  and led to a huge (of order <lb/>200.000) number of distinct string spectra that match the chiral Standard Model. <lb/>This set provides an extensive scan over the orientifold landscape. <lb/>These spectra are exact in perturbative string theory and not only the massless <lb/>but also all massive states are known explicitly. There are no chiral exotics, but <lb/>in general there are large numbers of the ubiquitous vector-like states that plague <lb/>almost all exact string spectra. All tadpoles are canceled, but in most cases this <lb/>requires hidden sectors. However, there are a few cases where all tadpoles cancel <lb/>entirely among the Standard Model branes (hence no hidden sector is present) and <lb/>furthermore the superfluous B−L vector bosons acquires a mass from axion mixing. <lb/>These spectra have a gauge group which is exactly SU (3) × SU (2) × U (1) (there <lb/>are a few additional vector bosons from the closed sector, but the perturbative <lb/>spectrum contains no matter that is charged under these bosons; this is the same <lb/>as in the type IIA string, which contains a vector boson that only couples to non-<lb/>perturbative states, D0-branes). <lb/> 2.11. Decoupling limits <lb/> Brane model building led to an interesting change in strategy. Whereas string theory <lb/>constructions were originally &quot; top-down &quot; (one constructs a string theory and then <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-24 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 25 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The string theory landscape <lb/></note>

			<body> compares with the Standard Model), using branes one can to some extent work in <lb/>the opposite direction, &quot; bottom-up &quot; . The idea is to start with the Standard Model <lb/>and construct a brane configuration to match it, using branes localized at (orbifold) <lb/>singularities. Then this brane configuration may be embedded in string theory at a <lb/>later stage. This point of view was pioneered in Ref. 123, who found examples with <lb/> Z  3  singularities. See e.g. Refs. 124, 125 for other kinds of singularities. <lb/>One extreme possibility is to decouple gravity by sending the compactification <lb/>radius to infinity. In heterotic string models both gravity and gauge interactions <lb/>originate from closed string exchange, and such a decoupling limit would not make <lb/>sense. <lb/>The other extreme is to take the details of the Standard Model for granted <lb/>and focus on issues like moduli, supersymmetry breaking and hierarchies. In this <lb/>case one has to assume that once the latter are solved, the Standard Model can be <lb/>added. <lb/>Both points of view are to some extent a return to the &quot; old days &quot; of quantum <lb/>field theory. On the one hand, the techniques of branes and higher dimensions are <lb/>used to enrich old ideas in GUT model building; on the other hand, string theory is <lb/>treated as a &quot; framework &quot; , analogous to quantum field theory, where gauge groups, <lb/>representations and couplings are input rather than output. <lb/>Decoupling of gravity is an important element in recent work on F-theory <lb/>GUTs <lb/> 126–128  obtained by compactifying F-theory on elliptically fibered Calabi–Yau <lb/>fourfolds. This allows the construction of models that may be thought of as non-<lb/>perturbative realizations of the orientifold SU (5) GUT models depicted in Fig. 1(b), <lb/>solving some of their problems, especially the absence of the top-Yukawa coupling, <lb/>which is perturbatively forbidden. This has led to a revival of Grand Unified Theo-<lb/>ries, invigorated with features of higher dimensional theories. See the reviews <lb/> 129–132 <lb/> for further details. <lb/>An example in the second category is recent work in the area of M-theory <lb/>compactifications. <lb/> 58  Getting chiral N = 1 supersymmetric spectra in M-theory <lb/>requires compactification on a seven dimensional manifold with G  2  holonomy, <lb/> 133 <lb/> also known as a Joyce manifold. Much less is known about M-theory than about <lb/>string theory, and much less is known about Joyce manifolds than about Calabi– <lb/>Yau manifolds, since the powerful tool of complex geometry is not available. For <lb/>this reason the Standard Model is treated as input rather than output, in the spirit <lb/>of QFT. <lb/>Another kind of compactification that allows splitting the problem into decou-<lb/>pled parts is the LARGE Volume Scenario, <lb/> 46  originally invented for the purpose <lb/>of moduli stabilization (see Subsec. 1.2.5). Here both kinds of decoupling limits <lb/>have been discussed, and there have also been steps towards putting both parts <lb/>together. <lb/> 134  This illustrates that focusing on decoupling limits does not mean that <lb/>the original goal of a complete theory is forgotten. Indeed, there also exist global <lb/> F-theory constructions. <lb/> 135,136 <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-25 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 26 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A. N. Schellekens <lb/></note>

			<body> 2.12. Non-supersymmetric strings <lb/> Although the vast majority of the literature on string constructions concerns space-<lb/>time supersymmetric spectra, in world-sheet based methods — free bosons and <lb/>fermions, Gepner models, and certain orbifolds — it is as easy to construct non-<lb/>supersymmetric ones. In fact, it is easier, because space-time supersymmetry is <lb/>an additional constraint. These spectra are generally plagued by tachyons, but <lb/>by systematic searches one can find examples where no tachyons occur. This was <lb/>first done in ten dimensions in Refs. 137, 138. These authors found a heterotic <lb/>string theory with a SO(16) × SO(16) gauge group, the only tachyon-free non-<lb/>supersymmetric theory in ten dimensions, out of a total of seven. Four-dimensional <lb/>non-supersymmetric strings were already constructed shortly thereafter. <lb/> 5,79  Non-<lb/>supersymmetric strings can also be constructed using orientifold methods, see for <lb/>example Refs. 139–143. <lb/>Non-supersymmetric strings can have a vacuum energy Λ of either sign. See for <lb/>example Ref. 144 for a distribution of values of the vacuum energy for a class of <lb/>heterotic strings. There also exist examples where Λ vanishes exactly to all orders in <lb/>perturbation theory <lb/> 145  but probably this feature does not hold beyond perturbation <lb/>theory. <lb/> 146 <lb/> One might think that in the absence of any evidence for low energy supersym-<lb/>metry, and because of the evidence in favor of an accelerated expansion of the <lb/>universe, non-supersymmetric strings with a positive cosmological constant are a <lb/>better candidate for describing our universe than the much more frequently studied <lb/>supersymmetric ones. But the absence of supersymmetry is a serious threat for <lb/>the stability of these theories, even in the absence of tachyons in the perturbative <lb/>spectrum. <lb/> 3. The Standard Model in the Landscape <lb/> In this chapter we will discuss how the main features of the Standard Model fit <lb/>in the String Theory Landscape, taking into account anthropic restrictions and <lb/>analytical and numerical work on landscape distributions. We focus on questions <lb/>related to susy-GUTs, where the stress between symmetry and landscape anarchy <lb/>has been building up in the last few years. <lb/> 3.1. The gauge group <lb/> It is by now abundantly clear that string theory can reproduce the discrete struc-<lb/>ture of the Standard Model: the gauge group SU (3) × SU (2) × U (1) with chiral <lb/>fermion representations. Indeed, the gauge group is easy to get in many con-<lb/>struction methods: Heterotic Calabi–Yau and orbifold compactifications with GUT <lb/>symmetries broken by Wilson lines, orientifold models with various kinds of inter-<lb/>section branes, strings at singularities, free fermion and free boson constructions, <lb/>heterotic Gepner models and Gepner orientifolds, higher level heterotic strings with <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 27 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The string theory landscape <lb/></note>

			<body> symmetry breaking by the standard adjoint Higgs, F-theory with Y-flux, and others. <lb/>See Sec. 2 for references to all this work. <lb/>But this work also demonstrates very clearly that there is nothing special about <lb/>the Standard Model from the top down perspective, except that it is rather simple. <lb/>Many other gauge theories and representations are possible as well, although both <lb/>are limited in size. Unlike quantum field theory, string theory only allows small <lb/>representations. Furthermore, the size of the gauge group tends to be limited by <lb/>the conformal anomaly in closed strings, or dilaton tadpole cancellation in open <lb/>strings. This is not a theorem: there are remarkable exceptions with very large <lb/>gauge groups, but it seems plausible that these are far out in the tail of landscape <lb/>distributions, and hence statistically very rare. The Standard Model gauge group <lb/>does have one remarkable feature, namely that it fits beautifully in a Grand Unified <lb/>gauge theory. We will discuss that below in Subsec. 3.2.3. <lb/>From the landscape perspective, one might hope that the gauge group can be un-<lb/>derstood using string theory plus anthropic constraints. The anthropic constraints <lb/>are hard to determine, but all three factors of the gauge group are needed for our <lb/> kind of life. Electromagnetism is so essential that it is impossible to imagine life <lb/>without it. One can imagine life without SU (3)  color  and only electromagnetism, <lb/>but it is by no means obvious that such universes will really come to life. Rigorous <lb/>evidence of such statements is unlikely to emerge soon, as it requires to work out <lb/>the full nuclear and atomic spectrum as well as astrophysics, nucleosynthesis and <lb/>baryogenesis for alternatives of the Standard Model. But given what we know, the <lb/>presence of electromagnetic and strong interactions are well-motivated anthropic <lb/>assumptions. <lb/>The weak interactions also play a crucial rôle in our universe, but perhaps not in <lb/>every habitable one. See Ref. 147 for a detailed discussion of a &quot; weakless &quot; universe <lb/>that may yield acceptable nuclear and atomic physics even though the weak scale <lb/>is pushed towards the Planck scale. Perhaps the main rôle of the weak interactions <lb/>is to provide chirality to fermions, protecting them from getting a large mass. For <lb/>this to be true, one has to be able to argue that in the string theory landscape it <lb/>is easier to have a single light scalar than several light fermions. See Ref. 148 for a <lb/>discussion along these lines. <lb/> 3.2. Family structure and charge quantization <lb/> 3.2.1. Quantum field theory <lb/> A Standard Model family is described by the following reducible SU (3) × SU (2) × <lb/> U (1) representation: <lb/> 3, 2, <lb/>1 <lb/>6 <lb/> + <lb/> 3 <lb/>  *  , 1, <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/> + <lb/> 3 <lb/>  *  , 1, − <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/> + <lb/> 1, 2, − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> + (1, 1, 1) , <lb/> (12) <lb/>where we ignore singlets. This occurs three times, and in addition to this there <lb/>is a Higgs field in the representation (1, 2, − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  ). At first, this looks arbitrary <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-27 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 28 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A. N. Schellekens <lb/></note>

			<body> and unintuitive, but on closer examination some structure becomes apparent. For <lb/>example, the three entries of each irreducible term multiply to an integer. This <lb/>fact implies that all color singlet bound states of the broken SU (3) × U (1) spec-<lb/>trum have charges that are integer multiples of the electron charge. This fact is <lb/>not explained in the Standard Model. An arbitrary representation has the form <lb/>(R  3  , R  2  , q) where R  n  is an SU (n) representation and q a real number. But the <lb/>observed representations satisfy the rule <lb/> t  3 <lb/> 3 <lb/>+ <lb/> t  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/>+ <lb/>1 <lb/>6 <lb/>= 0 mod 1 , <lb/> (13) <lb/>where t  3  is the triality of the SU (3) representation and t  2  the duality of SU (2), <lb/>twice the spin modulo integers. Group-theoretically this means that all observed <lb/>representations are in fact representations of the group S(U (3) × U (2)), which has <lb/>the same Lie algebra as SU (3) × SU (2) × U (1). <lb/>It seems clear that the family structure is more than just an environmental <lb/>fact. Some of it is explained by the consistency conditions imposed by anomaly <lb/>cancellation. This implies that four cubic traces and a linear one must vanish. <lb/>There is also a global SU (2) anomaly <lb/> 149  and perhaps one should impose a string-<lb/>inspired non-abelian SU (2) anomaly. <lb/> 150  These anomaly cancellation conditions are <lb/>sufficient to explain charge quantization if one assumes that there is just a single <lb/>family with the observed SU (3) × SU (2) content. But quantum field theory offers <lb/>no reason for these assumptions, and the fact that there are three families ruins the <lb/>argument anyway. <lb/>3.2.2. String theory <lb/> String theory makes important contributions towards understanding the family <lb/>structure. First of all, it limits the choice of representations to only a handful <lb/>of options. Secondly, as far as anyone knows, string theory always implies absolute <lb/>charge quantization. By this we mean that the charges are rational numbers, though <lb/>not necessarily the right ones. And thirdly, string theory provides a rationale for <lb/>anomaly cancellation that is somewhat more deeply rooted than the ad hoc rules <lb/>of quantum field theory. <lb/>3.2.3. Grand unification <lb/> Usually Grand Unification is invoked to explain Eq. (12). In the context of quantum <lb/>field theory, this would offer a plausible explanation for the fact that particles fit in <lb/> S(U (3) × U (2)) representations. There is no good motivation in QFT to consider <lb/>just S(U (3) × U (2)). From the traditional symmetry-based perspective, assuming <lb/>that what we see is a broken SU (5) (or larger) gauge theory looks like a natural <lb/>idea. But it is by no means perfect. It does not explain the family structure, but <lb/>it just limits the allowed combinations of SU (3) × SU (2) × U (1) representations. <lb/>It does not explain why a breaking to SU (3) × SU (2) × U (1) is preferred, and it <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-28 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 29 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The string theory landscape <lb/></note>

			<body> has difficulties accommodating the Higgs field. In SU (5) the Standard Model Higgs <lb/>has an SU (3) triplet partner which must remain heavy and cannot have a vacuum <lb/>expectation value: the doublet triplet splitting problem. The GUT hypothesis would <lb/>get a lot more credibility if a second non-trivial coincidence is established: the <lb/>renormalization group convergence of the coupling constants to a single value at the <lb/>GUT scale. This does not hold if one extrapolates the current low-energy couplings, <lb/>but it would work if more or less standard supersymmetric partners of all Standard <lb/>Model particles are discovered at a future run of LHC. <lb/>Since many Standard Model realizations in string theory look superficially like <lb/>GUT theories, one might have expected that all facts mentioned in the foregoing <lb/>paragraphs are naturally combined to get a satisfactory explanation of family struc-<lb/>ture and charge quantization. But this has never worked as easily as it should. <lb/>3.2.4. Grand unification in heterotic strings <lb/> The oldest examples studied are compactifications of the heterotic string. There <lb/>are two equivalent ways of understanding why Grand Unification emerges so easily <lb/>in E  8  × E  8  heterotic strings. In Calabi–Yau compactification this comes from the <lb/>embedding of the SU (3) holonomy group of the manifold in one of the E  8  factors, <lb/>breaking it to E  6  , which contains SO(10) (and hence SU (5) as a subgroup). In <lb/>world-sheet constructions this is a consequence of the &quot; bosonic string map &quot; <lb/> 5  used <lb/>to map the fermionic (right-moving) sector of the theory into a bosonic one, in order <lb/>to be able to combine it in a modular invariant way with the left-moving sector. <lb/>The bosonic string map takes the fermionic sector of a heterotic or type-II string, <lb/>and maps it to a bosonic sector. The world-sheet fermions ψ <lb/> µ  transform under the <lb/> D-dimensional Lorentz group SO(D −1, 1). The bosonic string map replaces this <lb/>by an SO(D + 6) × E  8  affine Lie algebra, which manifests itself as a gauge group <lb/>in space-time. In Ref. 5 this trick was used to map the problem of finding modular <lb/>invariants to the already solved problem of characterizing even self-dual lattices. <lb/>This automatically gives rise to a four-dimensional theory with an SO(10) × E  8 <lb/> gauge group and chiral fermions in the spinor representation of the first factor. <lb/>With only slight exaggeration one can state that this ideal GUT group, SO(10), <lb/> emerges uniquely from the heterotic string. All we had to do is specify the space-<lb/>time dimension, D = 4, and apply the bosonic string map, and we get SO(10) for <lb/>free. <lb/>3.2.5. Fractional charges in heterotic spectra <lb/> A mechanism to break SO(10) to SU (3) × SU (2) × U (1) can also be found, but it <lb/>does not come out automatically. Furthermore, it does not work as nicely as in field <lb/>theory GUTs, because the heterotic string spectrum does not contain the Higgs <lb/>representation used in field theory. The breaking can instead be achieved by adding <lb/>background fields (Wilson lines). <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-29 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 30 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A. N. Schellekens <lb/></note>

			<body> But in that case the full spectrum of these heterotic strings will never satisfy <lb/>(13), and it is precisely the deep underlying structure of string theory that is the <lb/>culprit. In a string spectrum every state is relevant, as is fairly obvious from the <lb/>modular invariance condition. Removing one state destroys modular invariance. In <lb/>this case, what one would like to remove are the extra gauge bosons in SU (5) in <lb/>comparison to SU (3) × SU (2) × U (1). To do this one has to add something else <lb/>to the spectrum, and it turns out that the only possibility is to add something <lb/>that violates (13) and hence is fractionally charged. <lb/> 151  The possible presence of <lb/>unconfined fractional charges in string spectra was first pointed out in Ref. 152 and <lb/>the implications were discussed further in Ref. 153. <lb/>The occurrence of fractional charges in heterotic string spectra has been studied <lb/>systematically for free fermion constructions and for heterotic Gepner models. All <lb/>these models realize the gauge group in the canonical heterotic way, as a sub-<lb/>group of SO(10) (which may be further extended to E  6  ). There is a total of <lb/>four distinct subgroups that one may encounter within SO(10). These subgroups <lb/>are further subdivided into several classes, distinguished by the minimal electric <lb/>charge quantum that occurs in their spectra. These charge quanta are not deter-<lb/>mined by group theory in quantum field theory, but by affine Lie algebras in string <lb/>theory. This gives a total of eight possibilities, with charge quanta given in curly <lb/>brackets: <lb/> SU (3) × SU (2) × U (1) × U (1) <lb/>  1 <lb/>6  , <lb/> 1 <lb/>3  , <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> SU (3) × SU (2)  L  × SU (2)  R  × U (1) <lb/>  1 <lb/>6  , <lb/> 1 <lb/>3 <lb/> SU (4) × SU (2)  L  × SU (2)  R <lb/>  1 <lb/>2 <lb/> plus SU (5) × U (1) and SO(10), which automatically yield integer charges. This <lb/>classification applies to all constructions in the literature where the Standard Model <lb/>is realized with level 1 affine Lie algebras, with a standard Y charge normalization, <lb/>embedded via an SO(10) group. The minimal electric charge must be realized in <lb/>the spectrum, but it is in principle possible that fractionally charged particles are <lb/>vector-like (so that they might become massive under deformations of the theory), <lb/>have Planck-scale masses or are coupled to an additional interaction that confines <lb/>them into integer charges, just as QCD does with quarks. <lb/>Fractional charges can be avoided by looking for spectra where all these particles <lb/>have Planckian masses. In Ref. 65 a large class of free fermionic theories with Pati– <lb/>Salam spectra was investigated. These authors did find examples with three families <lb/>where all fractionally charged particles are at the Planck mass, but only in about <lb/>10 <lb/> −5  of the chiral spectra. In Refs. 102, 154–156 a similar small fraction was seen, <lb/>but examples were only found for even numbers of families. These authors also <lb/>compared the total number of spectra with chiral and vector-like fractional charges, <lb/>and found that about in 5% to 20% of the chiral, non-GUT spectra the fractional <lb/>charges are massless, but vector-like. They also found some examples of confined <lb/>fractional charges. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-30 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 31 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The string theory landscape <lb/></note>

			<body> In a substantial fraction of explicitly constructed string vacua the fractionally <lb/>charged particles are vector-like. If one assumes that in genuine string vacua vector-<lb/>like particles will always be very massive, this provides a way out. There is a <lb/>more attractive possibility. In orbifold models SO(10) is broken using background <lb/>gauge fields on Wilson lines. In this process fractional charges must appear, and <lb/>therefore they must be in the twisted sector of the orbifold model. If the Wilson <lb/>lines correspond to freely acting discrete symmetries of the manifold (see Ref. 157), <lb/>the twisted sector fields are massive, and hence all fractionally charge particles <lb/>are heavy. This method is commonly used in Calabi–Yau based constructions, e.g. <lb/>Ref. 158, but is chosen for phenomenological reasons, and hence this does not answer <lb/>the question why nature would have chosen this option. Also in the heterotic mini-<lb/>landscape an example was found. <lb/> 159  These authors suggested another rationale for <lb/>using freely acting symmetries, namely that otherwise the Standard Model Y charge <lb/>breaks if the orbifold singularities are &quot; blown up &quot; . <lb/>But even though there are ways out, it is disappointing that charge quantization <lb/>comes out less easily than it does in field theoretic SU (5) GUTs, without string <lb/>theory. <lb/>3.2.6. GUT unification in brane models <lb/> There is another important region in the landscape where SU (5) GUTs can be <lb/>obtained, namely intersecting brane models. The simplest possibility is to intersect <lb/>a stack of U (3) branes with a stack of U (2) branes. The entire Standard Model <lb/>group can be embedded in these two groups, but to get the matter representations <lb/>one needs not only bi-fundamentals (from strings stretching between the two stacks) <lb/>and rank-2 anti-symmetric tensors, but also U (3) and U (2) vectors. They would <lb/>come from endpoints of an open string, but then additional neutral branes are <lb/>needed for the other endpoint to end on. The resulting configuration is exactly as <lb/>shown in Fig. 1(b), but with the U (5) stack split in U (3) and U (2). <lb/>It has been known for a long time already that SU (5) GUTs can be obtained <lb/>from configurations like Fig. 1(b). <lb/> 160  These authors noticed however that solutions <lb/>to the tadpole conditions do not generically lead to the expected anomaly free <lb/>representation (5)+(10), but to more complicated solutions involving the symmetric <lb/>tensor (15). One can also start with a split stack, but then more input would <lb/>seem to be required. This includes not only the brane configuration, but also the <lb/>exact embedding of the U (1) group in U (3) × U (2) and the particle assignment. In <lb/>other words, a set of allowed massless open string states is hand-picked to match <lb/>the Standard Model spectrum. With all these assumptions, one can indeed find <lb/>numerous solutions. <lb/> 105 <lb/> Interestingly, these U (3) × U (2) intersecting brane models do provide a con-<lb/>vincing rationale for the gauge group U (3) × U (2), which is not easily found in <lb/>field theory models. But how do we get the restriction to S(U (3) × U (2)) to give <lb/>the correct charge conjugation, and how do we justify the choice of representations <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-31 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 32 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A. N. Schellekens <lb/></note>

			<body> in a Standard Model family? For example, if even in the U (5) limit symmetric <lb/>tensors are hard to avoid, with split stacks there are even more possibilities. Note <lb/>that by &quot; split stacks &quot; we do not necessarily mean a U (5) stack with branes move <lb/>apart. There are more general possibilities, where the U (3) and U (2) stacks occupy <lb/>unrelated cycles on a compactification manifold. <lb/>It turns out that there is an extremely simple answer to this question if one <lb/>allows a mild anthropic condition. <lb/> 148  It turns out that for all anomaly free matter <lb/>configurations, and for all possible U (1) embeddings the electromagnetic U (1) is <lb/>chiral after Higgs symmetry breaking, or there remain massless charged leptons in <lb/>the spectrum, with one exception: the Standard Model, with a number of families <lb/>of the form (12). The motivation for these conditions is that a chiral U (1) will <lb/>be broken by the color group, and massless charged leptons can be pair-produced <lb/>without limit, so that the entire universe becomes an opaque plasma of lepton-<lb/>antilepton pairs. <lb/> 161  Although we cannot prove that life is impossible without a <lb/>massless photon or in an opaque plasma, the circumstances for our kind of life — <lb/>indeed, any kind of life based on atomic physics — are so adverse that one can <lb/>certainly defend this as a well-motivated anthropic assumption. <lb/>One can say that the assumption of symmetry at high energies has been traded <lb/>for these anthropic assumptions, and remarkably, the latter are more powerful. <lb/>Even the Higgs choice does not have to be put in, but is determined. Indeed, unless <lb/>we see evidence for gauge coupling unification because of new matter bending the <lb/>coupling constant curves, full SU (5) unification has nothing useful to offer. <lb/>The argument can be extended to more general U (M ) × U (N ) stacks with a <lb/>few additional assumptions. The group SU (M ) is assumed not to be broken by <lb/>the Higgs, and to be a strong interaction group that is asymptotically free, and <lb/>dominates over the other gauge interactions. The Higgs is assumed to give mass <lb/>to all charge fermions, not just the leptons (above we just required the quarks to <lb/>become non-chiral, not necessarily massive). These simple conditions have a few <lb/>solutions: the Standard Model, a series of models without leptons, a few cases <lb/>with SU (2) &quot; color &quot; and no conserved baryon number, and a few models with just <lb/>electromagnetism and no strong interactions. Finally, there is an SU (4) × U (1) <lb/>model, broken by a Higgs boson to SU (3)  color  × U (1)  em  . This uses the alternative <lb/>breaking pattern of SU (5) to SU (4)×U (1) instead of the Standard Model. However, <lb/>it has baryon-number violating weak interactions that are probably fatal. All other <lb/>alternatives appear to have fatal problems for life as well, and the Standard Model <lb/>really stands out as the optimal, and probably unique anthropic solution within <lb/>this class of brane models. <lb/>In this class, SU (5) symmetry is not needed to explain charge quantization, nor <lb/>the structure of a family. In the heterotic case, it does not work as an explanation of <lb/>charge quantization. Similar remarks may apply to F-theory GUTs, where the GUT <lb/>group is present by choice, and not because it is required. There are some corners <lb/>in the landscape where SU (5) really works as in field theory. The only example we <lb/>know are heterotic string theories with GUT group with affine level larger than 1. <lb/> 162 <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-32 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 33 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The string theory landscape <lb/></note>

			<body> 3.3. The number of families <lb/> The string theory landscape does not offer, according to our current understand-<lb/>ing, an answer to the question why we observe three families. Although early con-<lb/>structions, for example the first Gepner models, had some difficulties getting three <lb/>families (the number was predominantly a multiple of four or six <lb/> 81,163  ), further <lb/>work showed that the number of families in heterotic strings has a slow exponential <lb/>fall-off, with the number three appearing not much less frequently than 2 (see e.g. <lb/>Refs. 154, 164). In orientifold models the fall off seems to be much faster. <lb/> 122 <lb/> There is no convincing anthropic argument for three families. We are built out <lb/>of just one family. The most often mentioned feature is that three families are <lb/>needed for CP violation in the CKM matrix, which in its turn might be required <lb/>for baryogenesis, which is obviously anthropically relevant. But CP violation in <lb/>the CKM matrix is not believed to be sufficient. The top quark plays an inter-<lb/>esting rôle in the running of couplings, and the stability of our vacuum under <lb/>tunneling depends in a remarkable way on both the top and the Higgs mass. Per-<lb/>haps this points to an important rôle for the third family, but then why does the <lb/>second family exist? The s-quark is not completely irrelevant in QCD, and the muon <lb/>affects biological mutations, but neither of these arguments provides a convincing <lb/>reason. <lb/> 3.4. Quark and lepton mass hierarchies <lb/> An area where there is an interesting rivalry between symmetry-based ideas and <lb/>landscape anarchy is the understanding of quark and lepton mass hierarchies. <lb/>Already long ago Grand Unified theories predicted interesting mass relations for the <lb/>second and third family fermions. Certain string approaches, such as the heterotic <lb/>mini landscape point to top Yukawa-gauge unification. Using F-theory compacti-<lb/>fications, part of the structure of the observed masses and mixing angles can be <lb/>nicely explained. <lb/>But on the other hand, one can also get a long way towards the correct distri-<lb/>bution of quark and lepton masses by assuming statistical distributions of Yukawa <lb/>couplings. Clearly, flat distributions will not work, because the quark and lepton <lb/>masses have an unmistakable hierarchical structure, and the mixing angles are small, <lb/>and seem to get smaller as the hierarchies get larger. However, scale invariant dis-<lb/>tributions (with a cut-off fit to the data) <lb/> 165,166  or Gaussian overlaps <lb/> 167,168  work <lb/>rather well. They even lead generically to small mixing angles, but it is not auto-<lb/>matic in all cases that the mass eigenvalues of the up and down quarks are ordered <lb/>correctly. Then in an alternative universe the three charge <lb/> 2 <lb/>3  quarks would predomi-<lb/>nantly couple to a different permutation of the three charge − <lb/> 1 <lb/>3  quarks, and only in <lb/>one-sixth of all universes with SU (3) × SU (2) × U (1) the Standard Model ordering <lb/>would be observed. One may view this either as a minor statistical problem, or an <lb/>indication that something essential is missing. For a more detailed discussion and <lb/>references see Ref. 1. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-33 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 34 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A. N. Schellekens <lb/></note>

			<body> This issue is far from settled. Without prior knowledge of the answer, none of <lb/>the aforementioned ideas would have given an accurate description of the quark and <lb/>lepton spectrum, even if the existence of three families is provided as information, <lb/>and even if the anthropic constraints on the light fermions are used. Furthermore it <lb/>is plausible that the top quark mass, in combination with weak symmetry breaking <lb/>and the Higgs mass, plays an important rôle that remains to be elucidated. <lb/>The smallness of neutrino masses has a well-known natural explanation, the <lb/>see-saw mechanism. This is so natural and requires so few changes to the Standard <lb/>Model that it is generally seen as the most plausible kind of beyond the Standard <lb/>Model physics. Indeed, all that is required are additional singlets (right-handed <lb/>neutrinos) having their natural mass. This mass is not proportional to the Higgs <lb/>vev, and hence one would expect it to be large. How large, and how it is distributed <lb/>depends on several assumptions, and there are also several anthropic issues related <lb/>to neutrino masses. See Ref. 1 for more details. <lb/> 3.5. The scales of the Standard Model <lb/> The Standard Model has two scales, the strong and the weak scale. To first approx-<lb/>imation the strong scale, Λ  QCD  , determines the proton mass, and the weak scale <lb/> M  weak  determines the masses of the quarks and leptons. The proton mass owes less <lb/>than 1% of its mass to the up and down quarks. However, the smallness of both <lb/>scales with respect to the Planck scale has an important environmental impact. <lb/>In quantum field theory, the strong scale is said to be determined by &quot; dimen-<lb/>sional transmutation &quot; , which turns a dimensionless coupling constant into a scale. <lb/>The appearance of a scale from a dimensionless theory is due to quantum loop <lb/>effects. The relation is: <lb/>Λ  QCD  = Q e <lb/> −1/(2β0αs(Q <lb/> 2  ))  , <lb/> (14) <lb/>where α  s  is the strong coupling constant, Q the scale where it is defined and β  0 <lb/> the leading coefficient of the β-function. This relation does not determine the scale, <lb/>since α  s  (Q <lb/> 2  ) is input, but from a landscape perspective it affects the distribution <lb/>of scales in such a way that a large hierarchy is easy to obtain. How easy depends <lb/>on the distribution of α  s  in a fundamental theory, but what we know about the <lb/>landscape suggests that this argument is valid. <lb/>This then leaves the weak scale M  weak  to worry about. In contrast to Λ  QCD  , the <lb/> µ <lb/> 2  parameter in the Standard Model Higgs potential receives quadratic quantum <lb/>corrections from higher scales. This worry has been the focus of decades of work on <lb/>natural solutions to the hierarchy problem. All of these solutions lead to predictions <lb/>of new particles near the weak scale, although some can be pushed a few orders <lb/>of magnitude higher. So far no such particles have been found. One can take the <lb/>point of view that we simply have to be more patient. After all, the top quark and <lb/>the Higgs boson also required a lot of patience. But the current situation clearly <lb/>demands a reassessment of the arguments. During the year 2013, after the existence <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-34 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 35 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The string theory landscape <lb/></note>

			<body> of the Higgs boson was convincingly established, there has been a lot of discussion <lb/>about this. The different lines of argument are roughly as follows. <lb/> • There is no hierarchy. Some people argue that the hierarchy should be viewed as <lb/>a misconception in quantum field theory. They point to the fact that unlike loga-<lb/>rithmic corrections, quadratic corrections are not present in every regularization <lb/>scheme, and argue that they may not really be physical; see e.g. Refs. 169–172. <lb/>However, these papers deal with just the Standard Model in quantum field theory, <lb/>and ignore potential BSM physics (such as GUTs) and certain BSM physics <lb/>(gravity). There is general agreement that the existence of new massive parti-<lb/>cles beyond the weak scale implies a quadratic hierarchy for µ <lb/> 2  . <lb/> 173  One can try <lb/>to get around this by following a minimalistic approach in which new physics <lb/>beyond the weak scale is completely avoided, as in Ref. 174. But then one still <lb/>has to deal with gravity. It is possible that the naive notion that since there is a <lb/>Planck scale, there must be new physics at that scale is wrong. Perhaps nature <lb/>is fundamentally scale invariant (as suggested for example in Refs. 175–177; see <lb/>however Ref. 178 for criticism). However, this escape route is closed off in string <lb/>theory, which clearly predicts not just new physics but concrete new particles at <lb/>the Planck scale. This still leaves the next option: <lb/> • The Planck scale is at the weak scale. This possibility exists if there are large <lb/>extra dimensions at a length scale far larger than typical length scale of particle <lb/>physics, even as large as 0.1 mm. Such a scenario was proposed in Ref. 179, but it <lb/>predicts observable gravitational physics, perhaps even black holes, at the weak <lb/>scale. This idea is put under severe stress by the latest LHC results. <lb/> • The weak/GUT or weak/Planck scale hierarchy is real and is generated by new <lb/>dynamics (technicolor, compositeness) at the weak scale. In this approach the <lb/>weak scale is generated analogously to the strong scale by dimensional transmu-<lb/>tation. Also in this case absence of new physics at the LHC is a serious problem. <lb/>Furthermore it is hard to build credible examples where the entire Standard <lb/>Model (including quark and lepton masses) is reproduced. <lb/> • The weak/GUT or weak/Planck scale hierarchy is real and is &quot; protected &quot; by low <lb/>energy supersymmetry. Since low energy supersymmetry does not determine the <lb/>weak scale, this still requires an additional mechanism to generate it, and often <lb/>this is related to dimensional transmutation (e.g. gaugino condensation). This <lb/>idea is facing similar observational problems as the previous two. <lb/> • The hierarchy is mainly anthropic (see below). <lb/>From the string theory perspective, the second option is very attractive since it <lb/>would give direct access to gravitational physics; from the landscape perspective the <lb/>question is how often large extra dimensions occur in conjunction with a Standard <lb/>Model with a weak scale as we observe. The third option is unattractive from <lb/>the landscape point of view since it would imply that our vision of fundamental <lb/>physics would be blurred by an additional &quot; onion shell &quot; which we have to peel <lb/>off first (since technicolor gained some renewed interest due to an interpretation <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-35 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 36 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A. N. Schellekens <lb/></note>

			<body> as a dual of a Randal–Sundrum model, <lb/> 180  some people view this as an appealing <lb/>prospect). <lb/>At this moment, low energy supersymmetry is usually considered to be the most <lb/>attractive of options 2, 3 and 4. It is a well-motivated idea because it not only con-<lb/>trols the hierarchy, but also provides additional particles needed for the convergence <lb/>of the running coupling constants as well as dark matter candidates. Furthermore <lb/>string theory may come with supersymmetry built in. The latter statement holds <lb/>for all string theories with a controlled perturbative expansion. Without super-<lb/>symmetry, quantum corrections diverge beyond one loop. Supersymmetry may be <lb/>required for a fundamental understanding of quantum gravity, or it may just be a <lb/>calculational tool we need because our current understanding is too primitive. <lb/>Since, despite good arguments in its favor, no sign of low energy supersymme-<lb/>try has been seen so far, we have to ask which mistakes may have been made in <lb/>arriving at the overly optimistic expectations. We will mention three here, labeled <lb/>as &quot; anthropic &quot; , &quot; landscape &quot; and &quot; string theory &quot; . <lb/> Anthropic. The idea that the hierarchy might be anthropic was not even men-<lb/>tioned during three of the four decades of discussion of naturalness, and during the <lb/>past decade was mentioned only to ridicule it. And yet it is true. It is true in the <lb/>sense that in an ensemble of theories with a range of gauge hierarchies, (intelligent) <lb/>life can exist only for theories with a large hierarchy. The simplest argument is <lb/>based on the weakness of gravity. The largest structures that can exist without <lb/>being crushed into a black hole have N building blocks, where N = (M  Planck  /m) <lb/> 3 <lb/> and m is the mass of the building block (the proton mass in our universe). This <lb/>already requires a hierarchy of nine orders of magnitude for something with the <lb/>complexity of a human brain to exist. More detailed arguments with stronger (and <lb/>more debatable) assumptions pin the weak scale down with a precision of less than <lb/>ten per cent (see Ref. 1 for more details and references). But even if the entire hier-<lb/>archy of 18 orders of magnitude is fully understood anthropically, this still does not <lb/>imply that the hierarchy is explained by anthropic arguments alone, as suggested <lb/>in Refs. 181 and 182. <lb/> Landscape. One may still ask the question if the underlying physics helps in getting <lb/>the anthropically required hierarchy. In a landscape of variants of the Standard <lb/>Model with a fixed Planck scale and a full range of values of µ <lb/> 2  , flatly distributed, <lb/>the chance of getting an anthropically acceptable theory is about 10 <lb/> −34  . That is <lb/>the fraction of theories with a µ <lb/> 2  parameter that is small enough, if the parameter <lb/> µ <lb/> 2  can be though of as a sum of uncorrelated terms of order (M  Planck  ) <lb/> 2  . So with a <lb/>large enough landscape, one could consider the problem solved. But this is not true <lb/>if the landscape contains other vacua where the statistical penalty of 10 <lb/> −34  does <lb/>not have to be paid. Technically natural theories escape this penalty. However, then <lb/>the question arises what the cost is in getting technical naturalness. <lb/>These questions can only be addressed in a context where the relative abun-<lb/>dance of theories can be compared. In particular, it makes no sense in quantum <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-36 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 37 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The string theory landscape <lb/></note>

			<body> field theory. Indeed, the very concept of technical naturalness is at best a poorly <lb/>defined intuitive notion without the context of an ensemble of theories, a landscape. <lb/>The string theory landscape certainly contains supersymmetric theories; indeed, <lb/>these are the only ones under computational control. To predict if they dominate, <lb/>one would have to estimate the ratio of the number of supersymmetric and non-<lb/>supersymmetric theories, given the hierarchy. Supersymmetric theories start with <lb/>a huge advantage of a factor 10 <lb/> 34  , but they may still lose by being far less abun-<lb/>dant, or because they have to satisfy additional anthropic constraints to avoid fast, <lb/>catastrophic proton decay. Unfortunately, answering this question is not feasible at <lb/>present. What has been tried is comparing supersymmetric theories with different <lb/>supersymmetry breaking scales. Very roughly (for many more details see Ref. 27) <lb/>one would like to compute <lb/> P <lb/> M  weak <lb/> M  susy <lb/> P <lb/> M  susy <lb/> M  Planck <lb/> , <lb/> (15) <lb/>the probability for getting a weak scale given a supersymmetry breaking scale times <lb/>the probability for getting a certain supersymmetry breaking scale given the Planck <lb/>scale. The first factor is (M  weak  /M  susy  ) <lb/> 2  by the usual naturalness argument. It varies <lb/>between 1 and 10 <lb/> −34  if we move M  susy  from the weak scale to the Planck scale, <lb/>and this is the basis for the prediction M  susy  ≈ M  weak  . But all QFT-based, bottom <lb/>up naturalness arguments completely ignore the second factor, which is not even <lb/>defined in QFT. The first attempts to compute it in the string landscape produced <lb/>the result that it was proportional to M  susy  /M  Planck  to a power larger than 2, so that <lb/>large susy scales dominate over small ones by a large factor. <lb/> 183,184  Meanwhile that <lb/>conclusion has been shown to be too simplistic, <lb/> 27,185  and furthermore an important <lb/>contributing factor was underestimated in earlier work, namely that vacua with <lb/>broken susy are less likely to be stable. This can lead to a huge suppression. <lb/> 48,49 <lb/> But one conclusion remains: even if the second factor in Eq. (15) is difficult to <lb/>compute in a well-defined setting, this does not imply that it can be ignored in <lb/>approaches where it cannot even be defined. <lb/> String Theory. An obvious weakness of the &quot; MSSM &quot; hypothesis is the first M, <lb/>which stands for &quot; minimal &quot; . There is no good fundamental reason to expect mini-<lb/>mality, but dropping this restriction implies a substantial loss of predictive power. If <lb/>the supersymmetric Standard Model is realized in string theory, the result is rarely <lb/>minimal, see Subsec. 2.2. But while most of the additional particles can at least be <lb/>avoided in special constructions, one kind is essentially inevitable: moduli. <lb/>It has been known for a long time that moduli can lead to cosmological prob-<lb/>lems. <lb/> 10,11,186  If they decay during or after BBN they will produce additional <lb/>baryonic matter and destroy the successful BBN predictions. Bosonic moduli have <lb/>potentials, and will in general be displaced from their minima. Their time evolution <lb/>is governed by the equation <lb/>¨ <lb/> φ + 3H ˙ <lb/> φ + <lb/> ∂V <lb/>∂φ <lb/> = 0 , <lb/> (16) <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-37 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 38 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A. N. Schellekens <lb/></note>

			<body> where H is the Hubble constant. If V = <lb/> 1 <lb/> 2  m <lb/> 2  φ <lb/> 2  + higher order terms, and H  m, <lb/> then the second term dominates over the third, and φ gets frozen at some constant <lb/>value ( &quot; Hubble friction &quot; ). This lasts until H drops below m. Then the field starts <lb/>oscillating in its potential, and releases its energy. The requirement that this does <lb/>not alter BBN predictions leads to a lower bound on the scalar moduli mass of a <lb/>few tens of TeV (30 TeV, for definiteness). For higher masses moduli decay can <lb/>reheat the universe sufficiently to restart BBN from electroweak equilibrium. <lb/>Furthermore one can argue <lb/> 187  that the mass of the lightest modulus is of the <lb/>same order of magnitude as the gravitino mass, m  3/2  . The latter mass is generically <lb/>of the same order as the soft susy breaking scalar masses: the squarks and sleptons <lb/>searched for at the LHC. Gaugino masses can be one or two orders of magnitude <lb/>less. This chain of arguments leads to the prediction that the sparticle masses will <lb/>be a few tens of TeV, out of reach for the LHC, probably even after its upgrade, <lb/>but there would still be a good chance to observe gauginos. Circumstantial evidence <lb/>in favor of this scenario is that it prefers a Higgs mass near the observed value, <lb/> 188 <lb/> whereas bottom-up supersymmetric models, ignoring moduli, suggested an upper <lb/>limit of at most 120 GeV. <lb/>But there is one worrisome point. The 30 TeV bound on moduli masses is not <lb/>an anthropic bound. Observers in universes with moduli masses below that bound <lb/>would be deeply puzzled that their attempts at computing BBN abundances gave <lb/>incorrect answers. They might see a helium abundance of only 19% while their <lb/>computations predicted 24%, but nothing we know suggests that this has adverse <lb/>effects on life. Now if supersymmetry prefers a lower scale because of naturalness, <lb/>this would imply that universes with deeply puzzled observers should dominate <lb/>universes with observers enjoying successful BBN predictions, such as ourselves. <lb/>None of these three mistakes is obviously fatal, but taking into account the <lb/> &quot; anthropic landscape of string theory &quot; and all its implications definitely lowers the <lb/>confidence level of predictions of low energy supersymmetry. <lb/> 3.6. Axions and the strong CP problem <lb/> The Standard Model Lagrangian contains a term <lb/> θ <lb/>g <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/> 32π  2 <lb/>8 <lb/> a=1 <lb/> F <lb/> a <lb/>µν  F <lb/> a <lb/>ρσ  <lb/> µνρσ <lb/> (17) <lb/>where the sum is over the eight generators of SU (3). The parameter θ, an angle <lb/>with values between 0 and 2π, is not an observable by itself. By making suitable <lb/>phase rotations of the fermions its value can be changed, but then these phase <lb/>rotations end up in the mass-matrices of the quarks. In the end, this leads to one <lb/>new physical parameter, ¯ <lb/> θ = θ − arg det (M  u  M  d  ), where M  u  and M  d  are the quark <lb/>mass matrices. A non-zero value for this parameter would produce a non-zero dipole <lb/>moment for the neutron and certain nuclei, which so far has not been observed. This <lb/>puts an upper limit on ¯ <lb/> θ of about 10 <lb/> −10  . Since there is no anthropic argument in <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-38 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 39 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The string theory landscape <lb/></note>

			<body> favor of such a small value — the smallest one can argue for anthropically <lb/> 189  is <lb/>10 <lb/> −3  — this is the one of the most serious naturalness problems in the Standard <lb/>Model. No one would argue that we observe such a small value just by chance. <lb/>This problem has a rather simple solution, the Peccei–Quinn <lb/> 190  mechanism. It <lb/>works by postulating an additional pseudoscalar boson with a dimension 5 interac-<lb/>tion with the QCD vector bosons <lb/>∆L = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ∂  µ  a∂ <lb/> µ  a + <lb/> a <lb/> 32π  2  f  a <lb/> a <lb/> F <lb/> a <lb/>µν  F <lb/> a <lb/>ρσ  <lb/> µνρσ  , <lb/> (18) <lb/>where f  a  is the &quot; axion decay constant &quot; . Since F ˜ <lb/> F (where <lb/>  µν  = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2   µνρσ  F <lb/> ρσ  ) is a <lb/>total derivative, after integration by parts the second term is proportional to ∂  µ  a. <lb/> Hence there is a shift symmetry a → a + . This allows us to shift a by a constant <lb/> − ¯ <lb/> θf  a  so that the F ˜ <lb/> F term (17) is removed from the action. However, the shift <lb/>symmetry is anomalous with respect to QCD because the F ˜ <lb/> F term is a derivative <lb/>of a gauge non-invariant operator. Through non-perturbative effects the anomaly <lb/>generates a potential with a minimum at a = 0 of the form <lb/> V (a) ∝ Λ <lb/> 4 <lb/>QCD  (1 − cos(a/f  a  )) . <lb/> (19) <lb/>Note that ¯ <lb/> θ is periodic with period 2π, so that the shift symmetry is globally a <lb/> U (1) symmetry. It was pointed out in Refs. 191, 192 that this breaking of the <lb/> U (1) symmetry leads to a pseudo-scalar pseudo-Goldstone boson, which was called <lb/> &quot; axion &quot; . <lb/>The mass of this particle is roughly Λ <lb/> 2 <lb/>QCD  /f  a  , but if we take into account the <lb/>proportionality factors in (19) the correct answer is <lb/> m  a  = <lb/> m  π  f  π <lb/> f  a <lb/> F (m  q  ), <lb/>(20) <lb/>where f  π  is the pion decay constant and F (m  q  ) a function of the (light) quark <lb/>masses that is proportional to their product. The scale f  a  was originally assumed <lb/>to be that of the weak interactions, leading to a mass prediction of order 100 KeV, <lb/>that is now ruled out. But soon it was realized that f  a  could be chosen freely, and <lb/>in particular much higher, making the axion &quot; harmless &quot; or &quot; invisible &quot; (see Ref. 193 <lb/>and references therein). This works if the coupling f  a  is within a narrow window. <lb/>For small f  a  the constraint is due to the fact that supernovae or white dwarfs would <lb/>cool too fast by axion emission. This gives a lower limit f  a  &gt; 10 <lb/> 9  GeV. There is an <lb/>upper limit of f  a  &lt; 10 <lb/> 12  GeV because if f  a  were larger the contribution of axions <lb/>to dark matter would be too large. This results in a small allowed window for the <lb/>axion mass: 6 µeV &lt; m  a  &lt; 6 meV. <lb/>The upper limit of f  a  is interesting since on the one hand it is large, but on <lb/>the other hand it does not quite reach the string scale. The non-renormalizable <lb/>interaction in the axion Lagrangian points to new physics at that scale, and from <lb/>a string theory perspective the natural candidate for such new physics would be <lb/>string theory itself. But then the scale seems uncomfortably low in comparison to <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-39 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 40 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A. N. Schellekens <lb/></note>

			<body> typical string scales. Indeed, in Ref. 194 the difficulties are examined and possible <lb/>ways out are discussed. <lb/>One way out is suggested by the fact that the amount of axion dark matter <lb/>is proportional to sin <lb/> 2  θ  0  , where θ  0  is the initial misalignment angle of the axion <lb/>potential. In deriving the upper bound, one assumes that our universe emerges <lb/>from a configuration with random alignments, resulting in an average of sin <lb/> 2  θ  0  . <lb/>This would give a value of <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  for sin <lb/> 2  θ  0  . <lb/> The fact that the parameter is an angle and that axions are not strongly coupled <lb/>to the rest of the landscape makes it an ideal arena for anthropic reasoning. <lb/> 195  It <lb/>is possible that our universe comes from a single inflated region with a small value <lb/>of θ  0  . For a larger value of θ  0  (given an axion decay constant at the string scale) <lb/>too much dark matter would be produced. One has to argue that, even though the <lb/>likelihood of living in a region with small θ  0  is small, this is compensated by the <lb/>fact that more observers will find themselves in such regions, because larger dark <lb/>matter densities are detrimental for the existence of life. The most likely reason <lb/>for that is galaxy formation and the density of matter in galaxies, both of which <lb/>depend on the dark matter fraction. See Refs. 196–199 for further discussion. It <lb/>has even been argued that finding a high scale axion would provide evidence for <lb/>the multiverse and the string theory landscape. <lb/> 200  The upper bound on the axion <lb/>decay constant can also be raised if there is a non-thermal cosmological history, for <lb/>example caused by decay of heavy moduli. <lb/> 58 <lb/> Candidate axions occur abundantly in string theory, but their survival as light <lb/>particles is affected by the moduli stabilization mechanism. They may be thought <lb/>of as phase factors of complex fields. The real parts of those fields must be sta-<lb/>bilized. They would otherwise give rise to fifth forces or affect BBN predictions. <lb/>But thanks to their derivative couplings, axions are far less constrained. However, <lb/>not every mechanism to stabilize moduli is capable of giving mass to the real part <lb/>and leave the imaginary part unaffected. For example, stabilization by fluxes or by <lb/>instanton induced terms in the superpotential gives mass to both the moduli and <lb/>the corresponding axions. <lb/>Axions that survive moduli stabilization may in principle play the role of PQ <lb/>axions that solve the strong CP problem, provided they do not acquire masses <lb/>by other mechanisms. The usual folklore that gravity does not allow exact global <lb/>symmetries suggests that all axions will eventually get a mass. Otherwise their <lb/>presence as massless particles would imply the existence of an exact, but sponta-<lb/>neously broken global symmetry, with axions as Goldstone bosons. Just as the QCD <lb/>instanton get a mass from non-perturbative QCD effects, all other axions should <lb/>get a mass as well. The Peccei–Quinn mechanism works as long as there is an axion <lb/>coupling to QCD with a mass contribution from any other sources that is at least <lb/>ten orders of magnitude smaller than the QCD contribution. <lb/>It is clear from the previous paragraph that if string theory produces a PQ <lb/>axion, it is likely that it produces many other axions in addition to this. Since <lb/>their masses are generated by non-perturbative effects, it is natural to expect them <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-40 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 41 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The string theory landscape <lb/></note>

			<body> to be distributed in a scale invariant way, spanning many orders of magnitude. <lb/>This plenitude of axions has been called the &quot; axiverse &quot; . <lb/> 200  Since the masses of the <lb/>additional axions (not involved in the PQ mechanism) are not limited to the QCD <lb/>window, this provides ample opportunities for observations in many mass regions. <lb/>Realizations of an axiverse have been discussed in fluxless M-theory compactifi-<lb/>cations <lb/> 201  and in type-IIB models in the LARGE Volume Scenario. <lb/> 202  Both papers <lb/>consider compactifications with many Kähler moduli that are stabilized by a single <lb/>non-perturbative contribution rather than a separate contribution for each modu-<lb/>lus. Then all Kähler moduli can be stabilized, but just one &quot; common phase &quot; axion <lb/>acquires a large mass. For supersymmetric moduli stabilization (such as the KKLT <lb/>scenario, but unlike LVS) a no-go theorem was proved in Ref. 203. Axions in the <lb/>heterotic mini-landscape were discussed in Ref. 204. They consider discrete symme-<lb/>tries that restrict the superpotential, so that the lowest order terms have accidental <lb/> U (1) symmetries that may include a PQ symmetry. <lb/>There are numerous possibilities for experiments and observations that may <lb/>shed light on the rôle of axions in our universe, and thereby provide information on <lb/>the string theory landscape. The observation of tensor modes in the CMB might <lb/>falsify the axiverse. <lb/> 201,205  See Refs. 200, 206, 207 for a variety of possible signatures, <lb/>ongoing experiments and references. <lb/> 4. Conclusions <lb/> The past four decades have been a magnificent golden age for particle physics, <lb/>but also for the leading approach to understanding it in terms of a fundamental <lb/>theory of quantum gravity, string theory. Now we appear to be approaching an <lb/>interesting and perhaps decisive moment in history. The Standard Model seems <lb/>complete, and string theory has led to a mathematical challenge of monstrous pro-<lb/>portions: the string theory landscape. Whether one likes it or not, successful string <lb/>phenomenology requires taming this monster. This will almost certainly involve a <lb/>reconsideration of the questions we wish to answer. In the future, the current time <lb/>may be remembered as the transition from the era of symmetries to a new era with <lb/>different ways of thinking about fundamental problems. <lb/>In experimental physics, we are faced with a situation where positive results <lb/>may emerge but are not guaranteed, and where negative results tell us fairly little. <lb/>Apart from the traditional &quot; new physics &quot; , examples of positive results that would <lb/>have an impact on the landscape are variations of constants of nature, the obser-<lb/>vation of axions, dark matter of any kind, neutrino Majorana masses, sterile neu-<lb/>trinos, massive vector bosons, and many serendipitous discoveries ranging from <lb/>desirable (e.g. proton decay or magnetic monopoles) to totally unexpected (e.g. <lb/>something like faster-than-light neutrinos). With the large number of experiments <lb/>and astrophysical observations still underway, it seems unthinkable that the Higgs <lb/>particle will turn out to be the last discovery in particle physics. But if it is, this <lb/>has to be viewed as circumstantial evidence in favor of a landscape. Any of the <lb/></body>

			<page> 1530016-41 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 42 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A. N. Schellekens <lb/></note>

			<body> aforementioned positive results can be good or bad for the landscape idea, but <lb/>there is no gold-plated experiment that verifies or falsifies it. <lb/>Further supportive or damaging evidence must come from pure theory. The <lb/>(non)-existence of a broadly spread distribution of de Sitter vacua in string theory <lb/>is a decidable issue, but it has turned out to be very difficult to reach a conclusion. <lb/>The fundamental principle behind string theory still eludes us. The quantization <lb/>of vibrating strings is not an acceptable fundamental starting point, and does not <lb/>describe everything we call string theory anyway. The best hope for acceptance <lb/>of the landscape idea is that it is derived from a fundamental theory of gravity <lb/>which in its turn is derived from a plausible principle of nature. Meanwhile, we <lb/>can try to bridge the gap between the Standard Model and the string landscape. <lb/>We must convince ourselves that our Universe is indeed contained in the string <lb/>theory landscape. We can explore our environment in the landscape, to see if we can <lb/>understand why we observe the Standard Model and all of its features, especially the <lb/>puzzling ones. This requires determining landscape distributions in various regions, <lb/>and using anthropic arguments where possible. <lb/>This may all be postponed until the indefinite future if new physics still emerges <lb/>during the next few years. If that new physics is due to large extra dimensions and a <lb/>low higher-dimensional Planck scale, we can explore quantum gravity directly. This <lb/>has always seemed too good to be true, and probably it is. If the new physics is low <lb/>energy supersymmetry, which is still a well-motivated option, perhaps the winding <lb/>road to the string landscape becomes a broad avenue all the way to the Planck <lb/>scale. Most other options may provide more decades of exciting particle physics, <lb/>but the historic moment we might be witnessing now would have passed and may <lb/>never return. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments <lb/> It is a pleasure to thank Beatriz Gato-Rivera for reading the manuscript and many <lb/>useful comments. This work has been partially supported by funding of the Spanish <lb/>Ministerio de Economía y Competitividad, Research Project FIS2012-38816, and by <lb/>the Project CONSOLIDER-INGENIO 2010, Programme CPAN (CSD2007-00042). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. A. Schellekens, Rev. Mod. Phys. 85, 1491 (2013), doi: 10.1103/RevModPhys.85.1491. <lb/>2. K. Narain, Phys. Lett. B 169, 41 (1986), doi: 10.1016/0370-2693(86)90682-9. <lb/>3. A. Strominger, Nucl. Phys. B 274, 253 (1986), doi: 10.1016/0550-3213(86)90286-5. <lb/>4. H. Kawai, D. C. Lewellen and S. H. Tye, Phys. Rev. Lett. 57, 1832 (1986), doi: <lb/>10.1103/PhysRevLett.57.1832. <lb/>5. W. Lerche, D. Lust and A. N. Schellekens, Nucl. Phys. B 287, 477 (1987), doi: <lb/>10.1016/0550-3213(87)90115-5. <lb/>6. I. Antoniadis, C. Bachas and C. Kounnas, Nucl. Phys. B 289, 87 (1987), doi: <lb/>10.1016/0550-3213(87)90372-5. <lb/>7. K. Narain, M. Sarmadi and C. Vafa, Nucl. Phys. B 288, 551 (1987), doi: <lb/>10.1016/0550-3213(87)90228-8. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 1530016-42 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 43 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> The string theory landscape <lb/> 8. L. J. Dixon, J. A. Harvey, C. Vafa and E. Witten, Nucl. Phys. B 274, 285–314 <lb/>(1986), doi: 10.1016/0550-3213(86)90287-7. <lb/>9. H. Kawai, D. C. Lewellen and S. H. Tye, Nucl. Phys. B 288, 1 (1987), doi: <lb/>10.1016/0550-3213(87)90208-2. <lb/>10. B. de Carlos, J. Casas, F. Quevedo and E. Roulet, Phys. Lett. B 318, 447–456 (1993), <lb/>doi: 10.1016/0370-2693(93)91538-X. <lb/>11. T. Banks, D. B. Kaplan and A. E. Nelson, Phys. Rev. D 49, 779–787 (1994), doi: <lb/>10.1103/PhysRevD.49.779. <lb/>12. L. Susskind, The anthropic landscape of string theory, in Universe or Multiverse?, <lb/> ed. B. J. Carr (Cambridge University Press, 2003), pp. 247–266. <lb/>13. A. G. Riess et al., Astron. J. 116, 1009–1038 (1998), doi: 10.1086/300499. <lb/>14. S. Perlmutter et al., Astrophys. J. 517, 565–586 (1999), doi: 10.1086/307221. <lb/>15. A. D. Linde, Rept. Prog. Phys. 47, 925–986 (1984), doi: 10.1088/0034-<lb/>4885/47/8/002. <lb/>16. R. Bousso and J. Polchinski, J. High Energy Phys. 0006, 006 (2000). <lb/>17. J. D. Brown and C. Teitelboim, Phys. Lett. B 195, 177–182 (1987), doi: <lb/>10.1016/0370-2693(87)91190-7. <lb/>18. J. D. Brown and C. Teitelboim, Nucl. Phys. B 297, 787–836 (1988), doi: <lb/>10.1016/0550-3213(88)90559-7. <lb/>19. J. L. Feng, J. March-Russell, S. Sethi and F. Wilczek, Nucl. Phys. B 602, 307–328 <lb/>(2001), doi: 10.1016/S0550-3213(01)00097-9. <lb/>20. A. H. Guth, Phys. Rept. 333, 555–574 (2000), doi: 10.1016/S0370-1573(00)00037-5. <lb/>21. A. D. Linde, Inflation, quantum cosmology and the anthropic principle, in Science <lb/>and Ultimate Reality, ed. J. Barrow (2002), pp. 426–458. <lb/>22. A. Vilenkin, Probabilities in the landscape (2006). <lb/>23. A. H. Guth, J. Phys. A 40, 6811–6826 (2007), doi: 10.1088/1751-8113/40/25/S25. <lb/>24. B. Freivogel, Class. Quantum Grav. 28, 204007 (2011), doi: 10.1088/0264-<lb/>9381/28/20/204007. <lb/>25. Y. Nomura, Astron. Rev. 7, 36 (2012). <lb/>26. M. Graña, Phys. Rept. 423, 91–158 (2006), doi: 10.1016/j.physrep.2005.10.008. <lb/>27. M. R. Douglas and S. Kachru, Rev. Mod. Phys. 79, 733–796 (2007), doi: <lb/>10.1103/RevModPhys.79.733. <lb/>28. R. Blumenhagen, B. Kors, D. Lust and S. Stieberger, Phys. Rept. 445, 1–193 (2007), <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.physrep.2007.04.003. <lb/>29. F. Denef, Les Houches lectures on constructing string vacua, in String Theory and <lb/>the Real World : From Particle Physics to Astrophysics, Proceedings, Summer School <lb/>in Theoretical Physics, Les Houches, France, July 2–27, 2007 (North Holland, 2008), <lb/>pp. 483–610. <lb/>30. F. Denef, M. R. Douglas and S. Kachru, Annu. Rev. Nucl. Part. Sci. 57, 119–144 <lb/>(2007), doi: 10.1146/annurev.nucl.57.090506.123042. <lb/>31. S. Gukov, C. Vafa and E. Witten, Nucl. Phys. B 584, 69–108 (2000), doi: <lb/>10.1016/S0550-3213(00)00373-4. <lb/>32. E. Witten, Nucl. Phys. B 474, 343–360 (1996), doi: 10.1016/0550-3213(96)00283-0. <lb/>33. S. Kachru, R. Kallosh, A. D. Linde and S. P. Trivedi, Phys. Rev. D 68, 046005 <lb/>(2003), doi: 10.1103/PhysRevD.68.046005. <lb/>34. K. Dasgupta, G. Rajesh and S. Sethi, J. High Energy Phys. 9908, 023 (1999). <lb/>35. I. R. Klebanov and M. J. Strassler, J. High Energy Phys. 0008, 052 (2000). <lb/>36. S. B. Giddings, S. Kachru and J. Polchinski, Phys. Rev. D 66, 106006 (2002), doi: <lb/>10.1103/PhysRevD.66.106006. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 1530016-43 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 44 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> A. N. Schellekens <lb/> 37. F. Denef, M. R. Douglas and B. Florea, J. High Energy Phys. 0406, 034 (2004), doi: <lb/>10.1088/1126-6708/2004/06/034. <lb/>38. D. Robbins and S. Sethi, Phys. Rev. D 71, 046008 (2005), doi: 10.1103/Phys-<lb/>RevD.71.046008. <lb/>39. I. Bena, M. Grana, S. Kuperstein and S. Massai, Phys. Rev. D 87, 106010 (2013), <lb/>doi: 10.1103/PhysRevD.87.106010. <lb/>40. I. Bena, M. Graña, S. Kuperstein and S. Massai, Polchinski-Strassler does not uplift <lb/>Klebanov-Strassler (2012). <lb/>41. C. Burgess, R. Kallosh and F. Quevedo, J. High Energy Phys. 0310, 056 (2003). <lb/>42. A. Saltman and E. Silverstein, J. High Energy Phys. 0411, 066 (2004), doi: <lb/>10.1088/1126-6708/2004/11/066. <lb/>43. O. Lebedev, H. P. Nilles and M. Ratz, Phys. Lett. B 636, 126–131 (2006), doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.physletb.2006.03.046. <lb/>44. A. Westphal, J. High Energy Phys. 0801, 012 (2008), doi: 10.1088/1126-<lb/>6708/2008/01/012. <lb/>45. L. Covi et al., J. High Energy Phys. 0806, 057 (2008), doi: 10.1088/1126-<lb/>6708/2008/06/057. <lb/>46. V. Balasubramanian, P. Berglund, J. P. Conlon and F. Quevedo, J. High Energy <lb/>Phys. 0503, 007 (2005), doi: 10.1088/1126-6708/2005/03/007. <lb/>47. J. Louis, M. Rummel, R. Valandro and A. Westphal, J. High Energy Phys. 1210, <lb/> 163 (2012), doi: 10.1007/JHEP10(2012)163. <lb/>48. X. Chen, G. Shiu, Y. Sumitomo and S. H. Tye, J. High Energy Phys. 1204, 026 <lb/>(2012), doi: 10.1007/JHEP04(2012)026. <lb/>49. D. Marsh, L. McAllister and T. Wrase, J. High Energy Phys. 1203, 102 (2012), doi: <lb/>10.1007/JHEP03(2012)102. <lb/>50. B. Greene, D. Kagan, A. Masoumi, E. Weinberg and X. Xiao, Tumbling through a <lb/>landscape: Evidence of instabilities in high-dimensional moduli spaces (2013). <lb/>51. T. Banks, The top 10 <lb/> 500  reasons not to believe in the landscape (2012). <lb/>52. S. R. Coleman and F. De Luccia, Phys. Rev. D 21, 3305 (1980), doi: 10.1103/Phys-<lb/>RevD.21.3305. <lb/>53. M. R. Douglas, Comptes Rendus Physique 5, 965–977 (2004), doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.crhy.2004.09.008. <lb/>54. S. Ashok and M. R. Douglas, J. High Energy Phys. 0401, 060 (2004), doi: <lb/>10.1088/1126-6708/2004/01/060. <lb/>55. F. Denef and M. R. Douglas, J. High Energy Phys. 0405, 072 (2004), doi: <lb/>10.1088/1126-6708/2004/05/072. <lb/>56. J. Garriga, D. Schwartz-Perlov, A. Vilenkin and S. Winitzki, J. Cosmol. Astropart. <lb/>Phys. 0601, 017 (2006), doi: 10.1088/1475-7516/2006/01/017. <lb/>57. M. R. Douglas, The string landscape and low energy supersymmetry, in Strings, <lb/>Gauge Fields and the Geometry Behind. The Legacy of Max Kreuzer (World Scien-<lb/>tific, 2012), pp. 261–288. <lb/>58. B. S. Acharya, G. Kane and P. Kumar, Int. J. Mod. Phys. A 27, 1230012 (2012). <lb/>59. L. E. Ibañez and A. M. Uranga, String Theory and Particle Physics: An Introduction <lb/>to String Phenomenology (Cambridge University Press, 2012). <lb/>60. L. J. Dixon, J. A. Harvey, C. Vafa and E. Witten, Nucl. Phys. B 261, 678–686 <lb/>(1985), doi: 10.1016/0550-3213(85)90593-0. <lb/>61. L. E. Ibañez, H. P. Nilles and F. Quevedo, Phys. Lett. B 187, 25–32 (1987), doi: <lb/>10.1016/0370-2693(87)90066-9. <lb/>62. M. Goodsell and A. Ringwald, Fortschr. Phys. 58, 716–720 (2010), doi: <lb/>10.1002/prop.201000026. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 1530016-44 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 45 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> The string theory landscape <lb/> 63. P. Candelas, G. T. Horowitz, A. Strominger and E. Witten, Nucl. Phys. B 258, <lb/> 46–74 (1985), doi: 10.1016/0550-3213(85)90602-9. <lb/>64. M. Kreuzer and H. Skarke, Adv. Theor. Math. Phys. 4, 1209–1230 (2002). <lb/>65. B. Assel, K. Christodoulides, A. E. Faraggi, C. Kounnas and J. Rizos, Nucl. Phys. <lb/>B 844, 365–396 (2011), doi: 10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2010.11.011. <lb/>66. T. Renner, J. Greenwald, D. Moore and G. Cleaver, Eur. Phys. J. C 72, 2167 (2012), <lb/>doi: 10.1140/epjc/s10052-012-2167-y. <lb/>67. T. Renner, J. Greenwald, D. Moore and G. Cleaver, Initial systematic investigations <lb/>of the landscape of low layer NAHE variation extensions (2011). <lb/>68. I. Antoniadis, J. R. Ellis, J. Hagelin and D. V. Nanopoulos, Phys. Lett. B 231, 65 <lb/>(1989), doi: 10.1016/0370-2693(89)90115-9. <lb/>69. F. Englert, H. Nicolai and A. Schellekens, Nucl. Phys. B 274, 315–348 (1986), doi: <lb/>10.1016/0550-3213(86)90288-9. <lb/>70. I. Antoniadis, C. Bachas, C. Kounnas and P. Windey, Phys. Lett. B 171, 51 (1986), <lb/>doi: 10.1016/0370-2693(86)90996-2. <lb/>71. G. Waterson, Phys. Lett. B 171, 77 (1986), doi: 10.1016/0370-2693(86)91002-6. <lb/>72. A. N. Schellekens and N. Warner, Nucl. Phys. B 308, 397 (1988), doi: 10.1016/0550-<lb/>3213(88)90570-6. <lb/>73. H. Niemeier, J. Number Theory 5, 142 (1973). <lb/>74. J. Conway and N. Sloane, J. Number Theory 14, 83–94 (1982). <lb/>75. W. Lerche, D. Lust and A. N. Schellekens, Phys. Lett. B 181, 71 (1986), doi: <lb/>10.1016/0370-2693(86)91257-8. <lb/>76. P. Goddard, Meromorphic conformal field theory (1989). <lb/>77. A. Schellekens, Commun. Math. Phys. 153, 159–186 (1993), doi: <lb/>10.1007/BF02099044. <lb/>78. P. Candelas, E. Perevalov and G. Rajesh, Nucl. Phys. B 507, 445–474 (1997), doi: <lb/>10.1016/S0550-3213(97)00563-4. <lb/>79. H. Kawai, D. Lewellen and S. Tye, Phys. Rev. D 34, 3794 (1986), doi: 10.1103/Phys-<lb/>RevD.34.3794. <lb/>80. D. Gepner, Nucl. Phys. B 296, 757 (1988), doi: 10.1016/0550-3213(88)90397-5. <lb/>81. A. N. Schellekens and S. Yankielowicz, Nucl. Phys. B 330, 103 (1990), doi: <lb/>10.1016/0550-3213(90)90303-U. <lb/>82. C. Vafa and N. P. Warner, Phys. Lett. B 218, 51 (1989), doi: 10.1016/0370-<lb/>2693(89)90473-5. <lb/>83. W. Lerche, C. Vafa and N. P. Warner, Nucl. Phys. B 324, 427 (1989), doi: <lb/>10.1016/0550-3213(89)90474-4. <lb/>84. D. Gepner, String theory on Calabi–Yau manifolds: The three generations case <lb/>(1987). <lb/>85. A. Font, L. E. Ibañez, D. Lust and F. Quevedo, Phys. Lett. B 249, 35–43 (1990), <lb/>doi: 10.1016/0370-2693(90)90523-9. <lb/>86. E. Witten, Nucl. Phys. B 443, 85–126 (1995), doi: 10.1016/0550-3213(95)00158-O. <lb/>87. P. Townsend, Phys. Lett. B 350, 184–187 (1995), doi: 10.1016/0370-2693(95)00397-4. <lb/>88. P. Horava and E. Witten, Nucl. Phys. B 460, 506–524 (1996), doi: 10.1016/0550-<lb/>3213(95)00621-4. <lb/>89. C. Hull and P. Townsend, Nucl. Phys. B 438, 109–137 (1995), doi: 10.1016/0550-<lb/>3213(94)00559-W. <lb/>90. C. Vafa, Nucl. Phys. B 469, 403–418 (1996), doi: 10.1016/0550-3213(96)00172-1. <lb/>91. A. Lukas, B. A. Ovrut and D. Waldram, Phys. Rev. D 59, 106005 (1999), doi: <lb/>10.1103/PhysRevD.59.106005. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 1530016-45 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 46 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> A. N. Schellekens <lb/> 92. Z. Lalak, S. Pokorski and S. Thomas, Nucl. Phys. B 549, 63–97 (1999), doi: <lb/>10.1016/S0550-3213(99)00136-4. <lb/>93. V. Braun, Y.-H. He, B. A. Ovrut and T. Pantev, J. High Energy Phys. 0605, 043 <lb/>(2006), doi: 10.1088/1126-6708/2006/05/043. <lb/>94. L. B. Anderson, J. Gray, A. Lukas and E. Palti, J. High Energy Phys. 1206, 113 <lb/>(2012), doi: 10.1007/JHEP06(2012)113. <lb/>95. R. Blumenhagen, S. Moster and T. Weigand, Nucl. Phys. B 751, 186–221 (2006), <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2006.06.005. <lb/>96. L. B. Anderson, J. Gray, A. Lukas and E. Palti, Phys. Rev. D 84, 106005 (2011), <lb/>doi: 10.1103/PhysRevD.84.106005. <lb/>97. S. Forste, H. P. Nilles, P. K. Vaudrevange and A. Wingerter, Phys. Rev. D 70, 106008 <lb/>(2004), doi: 10.1103/PhysRevD.70.106008. <lb/>98. W. Buchmuller, K. Hamaguchi, O. Lebedev and M. Ratz, Nucl. Phys. B 712, 139– <lb/>156 (2005), doi: 10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2005.01.038. <lb/>99. W. Buchmuller, K. Hamaguchi, O. Lebedev and M. Ratz, Phys. Rev. Lett. 96, 121602 <lb/>(2006), doi: 10.1103/PhysRevLett.96.121602. <lb/>100. O. <lb/>Lebedev <lb/> et <lb/>al., <lb/>Phys. <lb/>Lett. <lb/>B <lb/> 645, <lb/> 88–94 <lb/>(2007), <lb/>doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.physletb.2006.12.012. <lb/>101. H. P. Nilles, S. Ramos-Sanchez, M. Ratz and P. K. Vaudrevange, Eur. Phys. J. C <lb/> 59, 249–267 (2009), doi: 10.1140/epjc/s10052-008-0740-1. <lb/>102. B. Gato-Rivera and A. N. Schellekens, Nucl. Phys. B 846, 429–468 (2011), doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2011.01.011. <lb/>103. N. Marcus and A. Sagnotti, Phys. Lett. B 188, 58 (1987), doi: 10.1016/0370-<lb/>2693(87)90705-2. <lb/>104. L. E. Ibañez, F. Marchesano and R. Rabadan, J. High Energy Phys. 11, 002 (2001). <lb/>105. P. Anastasopoulos, T. Dijkstra, E. Kiritsis and A. N. Schellekens, Nucl. Phys. B <lb/> 759, 83–146 (2006), doi: 10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2006.10.013. <lb/>106. J. C. Pati and A. Salam, Phys. Rev. D 10, 275–289 (1974), doi: 10.1103/Phys-<lb/>RevD.10.275, 10.1103/PhysRevD.11.703.2. <lb/>107. S. M. Barr, Phys. Lett. B 112, 219 (1982), doi: 10.1016/0370-2693(82)90966-2. <lb/>108. H. Georgi and S. Glashow, Phys. Rev. Lett. 32, 438–441 (1974), doi: 10.1103/Phys-<lb/>RevLett.32.438. <lb/>109. A. Sagnotti, Phys. Rept. 184, 167–175 (1989), doi: 10.1016/0370-1573(89)90036-7. <lb/>110. P. Horava, Nucl. Phys. B 327, 461 (1989), doi: 10.1016/0550-3213(89)90279-4. <lb/>111. R. Blumenhagen, M. Cvetic, P. Langacker and G. Shiu, Annu. Rev. Nucl. Part. Sci. <lb/> 55, 71–139 (2005), doi: 10.1146/annurev.nucl.55.090704.151541. <lb/>112. M. B. Green and J. H. Schwarz, Phys. Lett. B 149, 117–122 (1984), doi: <lb/>10.1016/0370-2693(84)91565-X. <lb/>113. E. Kiritsis, Phys. Rept. 421, 105–190 (2005), doi: 10.1016/j.physrep.2005.09.001, <lb/>10.1002/prop.200310120. <lb/>114. J. L. Cardy, Nucl. Phys. B 324, 581 (1989), doi: 10.1016/0550-3213(89)90521-X. <lb/>115. M. Bianchi and A. Sagnotti, Phys. Lett. B 247, 517–524 (1990), doi: 10.1016/0370-<lb/>2693(90)91894-H. <lb/>116. G. Pradisi, A. Sagnotti and Y. Stanev, Phys. Lett. B 381, 97–104 (1996), doi: <lb/>10.1016/0370-2693(96)00578-3. <lb/>117. J. Fuchs and C. Schweigert, Nucl. Phys. B 530, 99–136 (1998), doi: 10.1016/S0550-<lb/>3213(98)00352-6. <lb/>118. R. E. Behrend, P. A. Pearce, V. B. Petkova and J.-B. Zuber, Nucl. Phys. B 570, <lb/> 525–589 (2000), doi: 10.1016/S0550-3213(99)00592-1. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 1530016-46 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 47 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The string theory landscape <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> 119. L. Huiszoon, A. Schellekens and N. Sousa, Phys. Lett. B 470, 95–102 (1999), doi: <lb/>10.1016/S0370-2693(99)01241-1. <lb/>120. J. Fuchs, L. Huiszoon, A. Schellekens, C. Schweigert and J. Walcher, Phys. Lett. B <lb/> 495, 427–434 (2000), doi: 10.1016/S0370-2693(00)01271-5. <lb/>121. C. Angelantonj and A. Sagnotti, Phys. Rept. 371, 1–150 (2002), doi: 10.1016/S0370-<lb/>1573(02)00273-9. <lb/>122. T. Dijkstra, L. Huiszoon and A. N. Schellekens, Nucl. Phys. B 710, 3–57 (2005), <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2004.12.032. <lb/>123. G. Aldazabal, L. E. Ibañez, F. Quevedo and A. Uranga, J. High Energy Phys. 0008, <lb/> 002 (2000). <lb/>124. D. Berenstein, V. Jejjala and R. G. Leigh, Phys. Rev. Lett. 88, 071602 (2002), doi: <lb/>10.1103/PhysRevLett.88.071602. <lb/>125. H. Verlinde and M. Wijnholt, J. High Energy Phys. 0701, 106 (2007), doi: <lb/>10.1088/1126-6708/2007/01/106. <lb/>126. C. Beasley, J. J. Heckman and C. Vafa, J. High Energy Phys. 0901, 058 (2009), doi: <lb/>10.1088/1126-6708/2009/01/058. <lb/>127. C. Beasley, J. J. Heckman and C. Vafa, J. High Energy Phys. 0901, 059 (2009), doi: <lb/>10.1088/1126-6708/2009/01/059. <lb/>128. R. Donagi and M. Wijnholt, Adv. Theor. Math. Phys. 15, 1237–1318 (2011). <lb/>129. T. Weigand, Class. Quantum Grav. 27, 214004 (2010), doi: 10.1088/0264-<lb/>9381/27/21/214004. <lb/>130. J. J. Heckman, Annu. Rev. Nucl. Part. Sci. 60, 237–265 (2010), doi: 10.1146/an-<lb/>nurev.nucl.012809.104532. <lb/>131. G. K. Leontaris, PoS CORFU2011, 095 (2011). <lb/>132. A. Maharana and E. Palti, Int. J. Mod. Phys. A 28, 1330005 (2013), doi: <lb/>10.1142/S0217751X13300056. <lb/>133. B. S. Acharya and E. Witten, Chiral fermions from manifolds of G(2) holonomy <lb/>(2001). <lb/>134. J. P. Conlon, A. Maharana and F. Quevedo, J. High Energy Phys. 0905, 109 (2009), <lb/>doi: 10.1088/1126-6708/2009/05/109. <lb/>135. R. Blumenhagen, T. W. Grimm, B. Jurke and T. Weigand, Nucl. Phys. B 829, <lb/> 325–369 (2010), doi: 10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2009.12.013. <lb/>136. J. Marsano, H. Clemens, T. Pantev, S. Raby and H.-H. Tseng, J. High Energy Phys. <lb/> 1301, 150 (2013), doi: 10.1007/JHEP01(2013)150. <lb/>137. L. J. Dixon and J. A. Harvey, Nucl. Phys. B 274, 93–105 (1986), doi: 10.1016/0550-<lb/>3213(86)90619-X. <lb/>138. L. Alvarez-Gaumé, P. H. Ginsparg, G. W. Moore and C. Vafa, Phys. Lett. B 171, <lb/> 155 (1986), doi: 10.1016/0370-2693(86)91524-8. <lb/>139. A. Sagnotti, Some properties of open string theories, in Supersymmetry and Unifi-<lb/>cation of Fundamental Interactions, Palaiseau, Susy 95, eds. I. Antoniadis and H. <lb/>Videau (Ed. Frontieres, 1995), pp. 473–484. <lb/>140. C. Angelantonj, Phys. Lett. B 444, 309–317 (1998), doi: 10.1016/S0370-<lb/>2693(98)01430-0. <lb/>141. S. Sugimoto, Prog. Theor. Phys. 102, 685–699 (1999), doi: 10.1143/PTP.102.685. <lb/>142. B. Gato-Rivera and A. Schellekens, Phys. Lett. B 671, 105–110 (2009), doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.physletb.2008.11.039. <lb/>143. I. Antoniadis, E. Dudas and A. Sagnotti, Phys. Lett. B 464, 38–45 (1999), doi: <lb/>10.1016/S0370-2693(99)01023-0. <lb/>144. K. R. Dienes, Phys. Rev. D 73, 106010 (2006), doi: 10.1103/PhysRevD.73.106010. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 1530016-47 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 48 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> A. N. Schellekens <lb/> 145. S. Kachru, J. Kumar and E. Silverstein, Phys. Rev. D 59, 106004 (1999), doi: <lb/>10.1103/PhysRevD.59.106004. <lb/>146. J. A. Harvey, Phys. Rev. D 59, 026002 (1999), doi: 10.1103/PhysRevD.59.026002. <lb/>147. R. Harnik, G. D. Kribs and G. Perez, Phys. Rev. D 74, 035006 (2006), doi: <lb/>10.1103/PhysRevD.74.035006. <lb/>148. B. Gato-Rivera and A. N. Schellekens, GUTs without guts (2014). <lb/>149. E. Witten, Phys. Lett. B 117, 324–328 (1982), doi: 10.1016/0370-2693(82)90728-6. <lb/>150. J. Halverson, Phys. Rev. Lett. 111, 261601 (2013). <lb/>151. A. N. Schellekens, Phys. Lett. B 237, 363 (1990), doi: 10.1016/0370-2693(90)91190-<lb/>M. <lb/>152. X.-G. Wen and E. Witten, Nucl. Phys. B 261, 651 (1985), doi: 10.1016/0550-<lb/>3213(85)90592-9. <lb/>153. G. G. Athanasiu, J. J. Atick, M. Dine and W. Fischler, Phys. Lett. B 214, 55 (1988), <lb/>doi: 10.1016/0370-2693(88)90451-0. <lb/>154. B. Gato-Rivera and A. N. Schellekens, Nucl. Phys. B 841, 100–129 (2010), doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2010.07.020. <lb/>155. B. Gato-Rivera and A. Schellekens, Nucl. Phys. B 847, 532–548 (2011), doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2011.02.004. <lb/>156. M. Maio and A. Schellekens, Nucl. Phys. B 848, 594–628 (2011), doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2011.03.012. <lb/>157. E. Witten, Nucl. Phys. B 258, 75 (1985), doi: 10.1016/0550-3213(85)90603-0. <lb/>158. L. B. Anderson, J. Gray, Y.-H. He and A. Lukas, J. High Energy Phys. 1002, 054 <lb/>(2010), doi: 10.1007/JHEP02(2010)054. <lb/>159. M. Blaszczyk et al., Phys. Lett. B 683, 340–348 (2010), doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.physletb.2009.12.036. <lb/>160. M. Cvetic, I. Papadimitriou and G. Shiu, Nucl. Phys. B 659, 193–223 (2003), doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2004.06.041. <lb/>161. C. Quigg and R. Shrock, Phys. Rev. D 79, 096002 (2009), doi: 10.1103/Phys-<lb/>RevD.79.096002. <lb/>162. Z. Kakushadze and S. H. Tye, Phys. Lett. B 392, 335–342 (1997), doi: 10.1016/S0370-<lb/>2693(96)01543-2. <lb/>163. J. Fuchs, A. Klemm, C. Scheich and M. G. Schmidt, Ann. Phys. 204, 1–51 (1990), <lb/>doi: 10.1016/0003-4916(90)90119-9. <lb/>164. A. E. Faraggi, C. Kounnas and J. Rizos, Phys. Lett. B 648, 84–89 (2007), doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.physletb.2006.09.071. <lb/>165. J. F. Donoghue, Phys. Rev. D 57, 5499–5508 (1998), doi: 10.1103/PhysRevD.57.5499. <lb/>166. J. F. Donoghue, K. Dutta and A. Ross, Phys. Rev. D 73, 113002 (2006), doi: <lb/>10.1103/PhysRevD.73.113002. <lb/>167. L. J. Hall, M. P. Salem and T. Watari, Phys. Rev. Lett. 100, 141801 (2008), doi: <lb/>10.1103/PhysRevLett.100.141801. <lb/>168. L. J. Hall, M. P. Salem and T. Watari, Phys. Rev. D 76, 093001 (2007), doi: <lb/>10.1103/PhysRevD.76.093001. <lb/>169. W. A. Bardeen, On naturalness in the standard model (1995). <lb/>170. H. Aoki and S. Iso, Phys. Rev. D 86, 013001 (2012), doi: 10.1103/Phys-<lb/>RevD.86.013001. <lb/>171. B. W. Lynn, Spontaneously broken Standard Model (SM) symmetries and the Gold-<lb/>stone theorem protect the Higgs mass and ensure that it has no Higgs Fine Tuning <lb/>Problem (HFTP) (2011). <lb/>172. F. Jegerlehner, The hierarchy problem of the electroweak Standard Model revisited <lb/>(2013). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 1530016-48 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 49 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> The string theory landscape <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> 173. S. P. Martin, A supersymmetry primer (1997). <lb/>174. T. Asaka and M. Shaposhnikov, Phys. Lett. B 620, 17–26 (2005), doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.physletb.2005.06.020. <lb/>175. K. A. Meissner and H. Nicolai, Phys. Lett. B 648, 312–317 (2007), doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.physletb.2007.03.023. <lb/>176. M. Shaposhnikov and D. Zenhausern, Phys. Lett. B 671, 162–166 (2009), doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.physletb.2008.11.041. <lb/>177. M. Heikinheimo, A. Racioppi, M. Raidal, C. Spethmann and K. Tuominen, Physical <lb/>naturalness and dynamical breaking of classical scale invariance (2013). <lb/>178. G. Marques Tavares, M. Schmaltz and W. Skiba, Phys. Rev. D 89, 015009 (2014), <lb/>doi: 10.1103/PhysRevD.89.015009. <lb/>179. N. Arkani-Hamed, S. Dimopoulos and G. Dvali, Phys. Lett. B 429, 263–272 (1998), <lb/>doi: 10.1016/S0370-2693(98)00466-3. <lb/>180. L. Randall and R. Sundrum, Phys. Rev. Lett. 83, 3370–3373 (1999), doi: <lb/>10.1103/PhysRevLett.83.3370. <lb/>181. V. Agrawal, S. M. Barr, J. F. Donoghue and D. Seckel, Phys. Rev. D 57, 5480–5492 <lb/>(1998), doi: 10.1103/PhysRevD.57.5480. <lb/>182. S. Weinberg, Living in the multiverse, in Universe or Multiverse? ed. B. Carr (Cam-<lb/>bridge University Press, 2005), pp. 29–42. <lb/>183. M. R. Douglas, Statistical analysis of the supersymmetry breaking scale (2004). <lb/>184. L. Susskind, Supersymmetry breaking in the anthropic landscape, in From Fields to <lb/>Strings, Vol. 3, ed. M. Shifman (World Scientific, 2004), pp. 1745–1749. <lb/>185. F. Denef and M. R. Douglas, J. High Energy Phys. 0503, 061 (2005), doi: <lb/>10.1088/1126-6708/2005/03/061. <lb/>186. G. Coughlan, W. Fischler, E. W. Kolb, S. Raby and G. G. Ross, Phys. Lett. B 131, <lb/> 59 (1983), doi: 10.1016/0370-2693(83)91091-2. <lb/>187. B. S. Acharya, G. Kane and E. Kuflik, String theories with moduli stabilization <lb/>imply non-thermal cosmological history and particular dark matter (2010). <lb/>188. G. Kane, P. Kumar, R. Lu and B. Zheng, Phys. Rev. D 85, 075026 (2012), doi: <lb/>10.1103/PhysRevD.85.075026. <lb/>189. L. Ubaldi, Phys. Rev. D 81, 025011 (2010), doi: 10.1103/PhysRevD.81.025011. <lb/>190. R. Peccei and H. R. Quinn, Phys. Rev. Lett. 38, 1440–1443 (1977), doi: 10.1103/Phys-<lb/>RevLett.38.1440. <lb/>191. S. Weinberg, Phys. Rev. Lett. 40, 223–226 (1978), doi: 10.1103/PhysRevLett.40.223. <lb/>192. F. Wilczek, Phys. Rev. Lett. 40, 279–282 (1978), doi: 10.1103/PhysRevLett.40.279. <lb/>193. J. E. Kim, Phys. Rept. 150, 1–177 (1987), doi: 10.1016/0370-1573(87)90017-2. <lb/>194. P. Svrcek and E. Witten, J. High Energy Phys. 0606, 051 (2006), doi: 10.1088/1126-<lb/>6708/2006/06/051. <lb/>195. F. Wilczek, A model of anthropic reasoning, addressing the dark to ordinary matter <lb/>coincidence, in Universe or Multiverse?, ed. B. Carr (Cambridge University Press, <lb/>2004), pp. 151–162. <lb/>196. A. D. Linde, Phys. Lett. B 259, 38–47 (1991), doi: 10.1016/0370-2693(91)90130-I. <lb/>197. S. Hellerman and J. Walcher, Phys. Rev. D 72, 123520 (2005), doi: 10.1103/Phys-<lb/>RevD.72.123520. <lb/>198. M. Tegmark, A. Aguirre, M. Rees and F. Wilczek, Phys. Rev. D 73, 023505 (2006), <lb/>doi: 10.1103/PhysRevD.73.023505. <lb/>199. B. Freivogel, J. Cosmol. Astropart. Phys. 1003, 021 (2010), doi: 10.1088/1475-<lb/>7516/2010/03/021. <lb/>200. A. Arvanitaki, S. Dimopoulos, S. Dubovsky, N. Kaloper and J. March-Russell, Phys. <lb/>Rev. D 81, 123530 (2010), doi: 10.1103/PhysRevD.81.123530. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 1530016-49 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> January 30, 2015 10:36 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15300161 page 50 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> A. N. Schellekens <lb/> 201. B. S. Acharya, K. Bobkov and P. Kumar, J. High Energy Phys. 1011, 105 (2010), <lb/>doi: 10.1007/JHEP11(2010)105. <lb/>202. M. Cicoli, M. Goodsell, A. Ringwald, M. Goodsell and A. Ringwald, J. High Energy <lb/>Phys. 1210, 146 (2012), doi: 10.1007/JHEP10(2012)146. <lb/>203. J. P. Conlon, J. High Energy Phys. 0605, 078 (2006), doi: 10.1088/1126-<lb/>6708/2006/05/078. <lb/>204. K.-S. Choi, H. P. Nilles, S. Ramos-Sanchez and P. K. Vaudrevange, Phys. Lett. B <lb/> 675, 381–386 (2009), doi: 10.1016/j.physletb.2009.04.028. <lb/>205. P. Fox, A. Pierce and S. D. Thomas, Probing a QCD string axion with precision <lb/>cosmological measurements (2004). <lb/>206. D. J. Marsh, E. Macaulay, M. Trebitsch and P. G. Ferreira, Phys. Rev. D 85, 103514 <lb/>(2012). <lb/>207. A. Ringwald, Phys. Dark Univ. 1, 116–135 (2012), doi: 10.1016/j.dark.2012.10.008. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 1530016-50 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. </note>


	</text>
</tei>
