<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> arXiv:math/0612510v3  [math.AG] 21 Jan 2009 <lb/> Tautological relations and the r-spin Witten <lb/>conjecture <lb/> Carel Faber <lb/>  * <lb/> , Sergey Shadrin <lb/>  † <lb/> , Dimitri Zvonkine <lb/>  ‡ <lb/> Abstract <lb/> In [23, 24], Y.-P. Lee introduced a notion of universal relation for <lb/>formal Gromov–Witten potentials. Universal relations are connected <lb/>to tautological relations in the cohomology ring of the moduli space <lb/> M  g,n  of stable curves. Y.-P. Lee conjectured that the two sets of <lb/>relations coincide and proved the inclusion (tautological relations) ⊂ <lb/> (universal relations) modulo certain results announced by C. Teleman. <lb/>He also proposed an algorithm that, conjecturally, computes all uni-<lb/>versal/tautological relations. <lb/>Here we give a geometric interpretation of Y.-P. Lee&apos;s algorithm. <lb/>This leads to a much simpler proof of the fact that every tautological <lb/>relation gives rise to a universal relation. We also show that Y.-P. Lee&apos;s <lb/>algorithm computes the tautological relations correctly if and only if <lb/>the Gorenstein conjecture on the tautological cohomology ring of M  g,n <lb/> is true. These results are first steps in the task of establishing an <lb/>equivalence between formal and geometric Gromov–Witten theories. <lb/>In particular, it implies that in any semi-simple Gromov–Witten <lb/>theory where arbitrary correlators can be expressed in genus 0 corre-<lb/>lators using only tautological relations, the formal and the geometric <lb/>Gromov–Witten potentials coincide. <lb/>  *  Institutionen för Matematik, Kungliga Tekniska Högskolan, S-10044 Stockholm, Swe-<lb/>den. E-mail: faber@kth.se. <lb/>  †  Korteweg -de Vries Instituut voor Wiskunde, Universiteit van Amsterdam, Plantage <lb/>Muidergracht 24, 1018 TV Amsterdam, Netherlands. Department of Mathematics, Insti-<lb/>tute of System Research, Nakhimovskii prospekt 36-1, Moscow 117218, Russia. E-mail: <lb/>s.shadrin@uva.nl, shadrin@mccme.ru . <lb/>  ‡  Institut mathématique de Jussieu, Université Paris VI, 175, rue du Chevaleret, 75013 <lb/>Paris, France. E-mail: zvonkine@math.jussieu.fr. <lb/> 2000 Mathematics Subject Classification: 14H10, 14N35, 53D45, 53D50. <lb/> Key words: Quantization of Frobenius manifolds, Gromov–Witten potential, moduli of <lb/>curves, r-spin structures, Witten&apos;s conjecture. <lb/></front>

			<page> 1 <lb/></page>

			<front> As the most important application we show that our results suf-<lb/>fice to deduce the statement of a 1991 Witten conjecture on r-spin <lb/> structures from the results obtained by Givental for the correspond-<lb/>ing formal Gromov–Witten potential. <lb/>The conjecture in question states that certain intersection numbers <lb/>on the moduli space of r-spin structures can be arranged into a power <lb/>series that satisfies the r-KdV (or rth higher Gelfand-Dikii) hierarchy <lb/>of partial differential equations. <lb/></front>

			<body> Contents <lb/> 1 Introduction <lb/>3 <lb/> 1.1 Tautological relations and universal relations . . . . . . . . . . 3 <lb/>1.2 Witten&apos;s conjecture . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 4 <lb/> 2 Formal Gromov–Witten potentials and tautological classes <lb/>6 <lb/> 2.1 Formal Gromov–Witten descendant potentials . . . . . . . . . 6 <lb/>2.2 Tautological classes and dual graphs . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 10 <lb/>2.2.1 The κ-classes . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 10 <lb/>2.2.2 The dual graphs . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 12 <lb/>2.3 Universal relations . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 13 <lb/>2.4 Y.-P. Lee&apos;s algorithm . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 18 <lb/>2.4.1 The operators τ  k  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 18 <lb/>2.4.2 The algorithm . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 20 <lb/> 3 Geometrical interpretation <lb/>20 <lb/> 3.1 Operators τ  i  and boundary classes . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 20 <lb/>3.2 The algorithm and the Gorenstein conjecture . . . . . . . . . . 24 <lb/> 4 A proof of Witten&apos;s conjecture <lb/>25 <lb/> 4.1 Witten&apos;s conjecture and Gromov–Witten theories . . . . . . . 26 <lb/>4.2 Admissible covers and double ramification cycles . . . . . . . . 28 <lb/> 5 More on Givental&apos;s quantization and Y.-P. Lee&apos;s theorem <lb/>31 <lb/> 5.1 The upper triangular group . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 33 <lb/>5.2 The lower triangular group . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 37 <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> 1.1 Tautological relations and universal relations <lb/> Tautological cohomology classes of M  g,n  are, roughly, intersections of bound-<lb/>ary components with ψ-classes and κ-classes. They are described by so-called <lb/> dual graphs (Definition 2.11). Sometimes it happens that a nontrivial linear <lb/>combination L of dual graphs determines a zero cohomology class [L] = 0. <lb/>Such linear combinations are called tautological relations. Until now there is <lb/>no known way to generate all of them by an algorithm. <lb/>Every tautological relation gives rise to a large family of relations in every <lb/>geometric Gromov–Witten theory. Indeed, let X  g,n+n  ′  ,D  = M  g,n+n  ′  (X, D) be <lb/>the space of stable maps from genus g curves with n + n <lb/> ′  marked points <lb/>to a target compact Kähler manifold X, of degree D ∈ H  2  (X, Z). Denote <lb/>by [X  g,n+n  ′  ,D  ] its virtual fundamental class. (Virtual fundamental classes <lb/>are defined in [2, 26, 35], but we will actually use only certain factorization <lb/>properties of these classes.) Let p : X  g,n+n  ′  ,D  → M  g,n  be the forgetful map. <lb/>Further, let L be a tautological relation on M  g,n  , and β ∈ H <lb/>  *  (X  g,n+n  ′  ,D  ) <lb/>a cohomology class of the form <lb/>  n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1  ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  ), where µ  i  are cohomology <lb/>classes of X and ev  i  the evaluation maps. Then the integral <lb/> [X  g,n+n ′ ,D  ] <lb/> p <lb/>  *  [L] β <lb/> (1) <lb/>can be expressed as a polynomial in Gromov–Witten invariants of X in a <lb/>standard way. On the other hand, we know in advance that this integral <lb/>vanishes because [L] = 0. <lb/>In [8], A. Givental introduced a notion of formal Gromov–Witten de-<lb/>scendant potentials. It is conjectured that formal Gromov–Witten poten-<lb/>tials contain all possible geometric Gromov–Witten potentials and more. <lb/>The relation between formal Gromov–Witten theory and geometry is not <lb/>established, although C. Teleman announced some important results on this <lb/>subject <lb/> 1  . Nonetheless, since there exists a universal expression in Gromov– <lb/>Witten correlators that represents integral (1) for geometric Gromov–Witten <lb/>potentials, it is natural to conjecture that this expression vanishes not only <lb/>in the geometric case, but for all formal Gromov–Witten potentials as well. <lb/>This led Y.-P. Lee to introduce the notion of a universal relation <lb/> in [23, 24]. Roughly speaking, it is a linear combination of dual graphs <lb/>such that the induced relations for Gromov–Witten correlators hold for all <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 1  Teleman&apos;s preprint [36] with a classification of semi-simple cohomological field theories <lb/>appeared a year after the first version of this paper was completed. <lb/></note>

			<page> 3 <lb/></page>

			<body> formal Gromov–Witten potentials, see Definition 2.15. Y.-P. Lee conjectured <lb/>that the tautological relations and the universal relations were exactly the <lb/>same and suggested an algorithm to compute them. To put things clearly, <lb/>let Taut denote the set of tautological relations, Univ the set of universal <lb/>relations, and Alg the set of relations computed by Y.-P. Lee&apos;s algorithm. <lb/>The inclusion Alg ⊂ Univ is a reformulation of Theorem 4. It was proved <lb/>by Y.-P. Lee in [24] and we re-explain the proof here in Section 5 with some <lb/>additional details. <lb/>Y.-P. Lee also stated as a theorem the inclusion Taut ⊂ Univ, although <lb/>his proof is quite complicated and involves a reference to C. Teleman&apos;s results. <lb/>In Section 3.2 we prove the following theorem. <lb/> Theorem 1 A linear combination of dual graphs L belongs to Alg if and <lb/>only if the intersection numbers of the class [L] with all tautological classes <lb/>of complementary dimension vanish. <lb/> It follows immediately that Taut ⊂ Alg ⊂ Univ. Moreover, we have <lb/>Taut = Alg if and only if the so-called Gorenstein conjecture, stating that <lb/>the Poincaré pairing is nondegenerate on the tautological cohomology ring <lb/>of M  g,n  , is true. <lb/>We have no new information about the conjectured equalities Alg <lb/> ? <lb/> = Univ <lb/>and Taut <lb/> ? <lb/> = Univ. <lb/>Summarizing, we see that if a linear combination L of dual graphs rep-<lb/>resents a zero cohomology class, then all formal Gromov–Witten potentials <lb/> &quot; know about it &quot; in the sense that the expressions in correlators that represent <lb/>intersection numbers with the pull-back of [L] vanish. <lb/>This result constitutes a rather powerful tool for establishing equivalences <lb/>between formal and geometric Gromov–Witten potentials: <lb/> In any semi-simple Gromov–Witten theory where any correlator can be <lb/>expressed in terms of genus 0 correlators using only tautological relations, <lb/>the formal Gromov–Witten potential coincides with the geometric Gromov– <lb/>Witten potential. <lb/> A more precise formulation is given in Theorem 3. <lb/>As the main application, we show that this result suffices to deduce Wit-<lb/>ten&apos;s conjecture on the space of r-spin structures from the results already <lb/>established by Givental for formal Gromov–Witten potentials. <lb/> 1.2 Witten&apos;s conjecture <lb/> In 1991 E. Witten formulated a conjecture on the intersection theory of the <lb/>spaces of r-spin structures of Riemann surfaces [37]. An r-spin structure on <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body> a smooth curve C with n ≥ 1 marked points x  1  , . . . , x  n  is a line bundle T <lb/> together with an identification <lb/> T <lb/> ⊗r  → ∼ K(− <lb/> a  i  x  i  ), <lb/>where K is the cotangent line bundle and the integers a  i  ∈ {0, . . . , r − 1} <lb/>are chosen in such a way that 2g − 2 − <lb/> a  i  is divisible by r. The space of <lb/> r-spin structures has a natural compactification M <lb/> 1/r <lb/> g;a  1  ,...,an  with a forgetful <lb/>map p : M <lb/> 1/r <lb/> g;a  1  ,...,an  → M  g,n  (see [15, 1, 4]). Using the line bundle T and <lb/>the map p one can define on M  g,n  a cohomology class c  W  (a  1  , . . . , a  n  ) of pure <lb/>dimension, now called Witten&apos;s class. Assuming that H <lb/> 0  (C, T ) = 0 for every <lb/>stable curve C, we find that V = H <lb/> 1  (C, T ) is a vector bundle over M <lb/> 1/r <lb/> g;a  1  ,...,an  . <lb/>Then Witten&apos;s class is defined by <lb/> c  W  (a  1  , . . . , a  n  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/> r  g  p  *  (c  top  (V <lb/> ∨  )). <lb/>In other words: take the dual vector bundle of V , take its Euler (or top <lb/>Chern) class, take its push forward to M  g,n  , and divide by r <lb/> g  . In the general <lb/>case, when H <lb/> 0  (C, T ) does not vanish identically, Witten&apos;s class has a much <lb/>more intricate definition that we do not recall here. <lb/>Witten&apos;s conjecture states that the intersection numbers of Witten&apos;s class <lb/>with powers of ψ-classes can be arranged into a generating series satisfying <lb/>the r-KdV (or rth higher Gelfand-Dikii) hierarchy. <lb/> Theorem 2 Witten&apos;s r-spin conjecture is true. <lb/> Below we give a summary of our proof of this conjecture. The ideas we <lb/>use are close to those used by Y.-P. Lee to prove the conjecture in low genus <lb/>in [21, 22]. <lb/>1. In his initial paper E. Witten [37] proved that the conjecture was true <lb/>in genus 0 provided the class c  W  satisfied certain postulated properties. <lb/>The space of r-spin structures and the class c  W  were later constructed <lb/>precisely and shown to possess the expected properties by a joint effort <lb/>of several people [15, 16, 27, 31, 30]. <lb/>2. A. Givental [8] constructed a transitive group action on all semi-simple <lb/>formal Gromov–Witten theories. He found a specific group element <lb/>that takes the Gromov–Witten potential of a point to the string solution <lb/>of the r-KdV hierarchy. (In particular, the genus zero part of this <lb/>solution coincides with the genus zero part of the generating function <lb/>for Witten&apos;s correlators.) <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body> 3. Y.-P. Lee [23, 24] found an algorithm that allows one to compute uni-<lb/>versal relations on Gromov–Witten potentials in Givental&apos;s theory, i.e., <lb/> relations satisfied by all formal Gromov–Witten descendant potentials. <lb/>4. In this paper we give a geometric interpretation of Y.-P. Lee&apos;s algorithm <lb/>and deduce a simple proof of Y.-P. Lee&apos;s claim that any tautological <lb/>relation in H <lb/>  *  (M  g,n  ) gives rise to a universal relation in Givental&apos;s <lb/>theory. <lb/>5. The first author together with R. Pandharipande [7] studied the so-<lb/>called double ramification classes in H <lb/>  *  (M  g,n  ) and proved that they <lb/>were tautological. Therefore integrals of Witten&apos;s class and powers of <lb/> ψ-classes on these cycles correspond to some polynomials in correlators <lb/>of the Gromov–Witten potential in Givental&apos;s setting. <lb/>6. Finally, the last two authors [34] showed that tautological relations on <lb/>double ramification classes were sufficient to express Witten&apos;s correlator <lb/>in terms of genus zero correlators. <lb/>The logic of our proof is the following. Item 6 gives an algorithm that <lb/>expresses any given correlator in terms of genus 0 correlators. The steps <lb/>of this algorithm can be performed in Givental&apos;s theory by Item 4. Thus <lb/>the generating series for the correlators coincides with the Gromov–Witten <lb/>potential given by Givental. But the latter is known to give a solution of the <lb/> r-KdV hierarchy by Item 2. <lb/>Useful references on Witten&apos;s r-spin conjecture also include [20, 1, 3, 17, <lb/>18, 19, 4, 5, 33]. <lb/> 2 Formal Gromov–Witten potentials and <lb/>tautological classes <lb/> In this section we give a short overview of the aspects of Givental&apos;s theory <lb/>of formal Gromov–Witten potentials that we will need. <lb/> 2.1 Formal Gromov–Witten descendant potentials <lb/> Definition 2.1 The genus g Gromov–Witten descendant potential of a point <lb/> is the formal power series <lb/> F <lb/> pt <lb/> g  (t  0  , t  1  , . . . ) = <lb/> n≥0 <lb/> d  1  ,...,dn <lb/> τ  d  1  . . . τ  dn  <lb/> t  d  1  . . . t  dn <lb/> n! <lb/>, <lb/></body>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<body> where <lb/> τ  d  1  . . . τ  dn  = <lb/> Mg,n <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  1 <lb/> 1  . . . ψ <lb/> dn <lb/>n  , <lb/>g being determined by the condition dim M  g,n  = 3g − 3 + n = <lb/> d  i  . The <lb/> total Gromov–Witten descendant potential of a point is F <lb/> pt  = <lb/> F <lb/> pt <lb/> g  <lb/> g−1  and <lb/>its exponential Z <lb/> pt  = exp F <lb/> pt  is called the Gromov–Witten partition function <lb/> of a point. <lb/>A formal Gromov–Witten potential is defined to model certain proper-<lb/>ties of F <lb/> pt  and those of Gromov–Witten potentials of more general target <lb/>Kähler manifolds X. We restrict our considerations to the even part of the <lb/>cohomology of X. In our description we explain in brackets the geometric <lb/>aspects that motivate the axiomatic definitions. <lb/>Let V be a complex vector space [the space H <lb/> even  (X, C)] in which we <lb/>choose a basis A. The space V possesses a distinguished element 1 [coho-<lb/>mology class 1], which we usually assume to be the first vector of the basis. <lb/> V also carries a nondegenerate symmetric bilinear form η [Poincaré pairing]. <lb/>The coefficients of η in the basis will be denoted by η  µν  and the coefficients <lb/>of the inverse matrix by η <lb/> µν  . <lb/> Definition 2.2 Let M be a neighborhood of the origin in V . Let F  0  be a <lb/>power series in variables t <lb/> µ <lb/>d  , d = 1, 2, 3, . . . , µ ∈ A, whose coefficients are <lb/>analytic functions on M in variables t <lb/> µ <lb/> 0  . The coefficients of F  0  are denoted <lb/>by <lb/> F  0  = <lb/> n≥0 <lb/> d  1  ,...,dn≥0 <lb/>µ  1  ,...,µn∈A <lb/> τ  d  1  ,µ  1  . . . τ  dn,µn  <lb/> t <lb/> µ  1 <lb/> d  1 <lb/> . . . t <lb/> µn <lb/>dn <lb/> n! <lb/>. <lb/>F  0  is called a formal genus 0 Gromov–Witten potential if it satisfies the string <lb/>equation, the dilaton equation, and the topological recursion relation (see, for <lb/>instance, [8], [10] or [11]). The open set M is called a Frobenius manifold <lb/> 2  . <lb/> Remark 2.3 If X is a Kähler manifold and E ⊂ H  2  (X, Z) its semi-group <lb/>of effective 2-cycles, one usually considers Gromov–Witten potentials with <lb/>coefficients not in C, but in the Novikov ring of power series of the form <lb/> D∈E <lb/> c  D  Q <lb/> D  , <lb/>c  D  ∈ C. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 2  Sometimes the definition of a Frobenius manifold also includes an Euler field and F  0 <lb/> is required to satisfy certain homogeneity conditions with respect to this field. In other <lb/>sources Frobenius manifolds with an Euler field are called conformal. <lb/></note>

			<page> 7 <lb/></page>

			<body> We will mostly work with Gromov–Witten potentials over C, since we do not <lb/>need Novikov rings for our main application, namely the Witten conjecture. <lb/>However, we indicate in remarks the modifications that must be made in the <lb/>general case. A detailed introduction to formal Gromov–Witten potentials, <lb/>including a discussion of Novikov rings, can be found in [25]. <lb/>Given a formal genus 0 Gromov–Witten potential F  0  (t <lb/> µ <lb/> d  ), let f  0  (t <lb/> µ <lb/> 0  ) be <lb/>the series obtained from F  0  by setting t <lb/> µ <lb/>d  = 0 for d ≥ 1. On every tangent <lb/>space to M one defines an algebra via the structural constants <lb/> C <lb/> µ  3 <lb/> µ  1  ,µ  2  (t <lb/> µ <lb/> 0  ) = <lb/> ν <lb/> ∂ <lb/> 3  f  0 <lb/> ∂t <lb/> µ  1 <lb/> 0  ∂t <lb/> µ  2 <lb/> 0  ∂t <lb/> ν <lb/> 0 <lb/> η <lb/> ν,µ  3 <lb/> depending on t <lb/> µ <lb/> 0  ∈ M. Together with the bilinear form η, one gets the <lb/>structure of a Frobenius algebra in every tangent space to M. <lb/> Definition 2.4 F  0  is called semi-simple if the algebra structure is semi-<lb/>simple for generic t <lb/> µ <lb/> 0  ∈ M. The rank of F  0  is the dimension of V . <lb/> Remark 2.5 A (genus 0) Gromov–Witten potential defined over a Novikov <lb/>ring R is called semi-simple if the algebra structure at a generic point is <lb/>semi-simple over the algebraic closure of the field of fractions of R. <lb/> Example 2.6 Let F be the string solution of the 3-KdV hierarchy (the <lb/>Gromov–Witten potential that appears in Witten&apos;s conjecture for r = 3, see <lb/>Section 4.1). Denote x = t <lb/> 0 <lb/>0  , y = t <lb/> 1 <lb/>0  . Then <lb/> f  0  (x, y) = <lb/> x <lb/> 2  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>+ <lb/> y <lb/> 4 <lb/> 72 <lb/> . <lb/> Let F be the Gromov–Witten potential of CP <lb/> 1  . Denote x = t <lb/> 1 <lb/>0  , y = t <lb/> ω <lb/> 0  , <lb/>where 1 ∈ H <lb/> 0  (CP <lb/> 1  ) and ω ∈ H <lb/> 2  (CP <lb/> 1  ) form the natural basis of H <lb/>  *  (CP <lb/> 1  ). <lb/>Then <lb/> f  0  (x, y) = <lb/> x <lb/> 2  y <lb/> 2 <lb/>+ Qe <lb/> y  . <lb/> In [10], Givental constructs an action of the so-called twisted loop group <lb/> on Gromov–Witten potentials of rank k. More precisely, the group itself is <lb/>ill-defined, but there is a well-defined action of its upper triangular and lower <lb/>triangular parts. <lb/>This action is almost transitive on semi-simple potentials of rank k. De-<lb/>note by <lb/> F <lb/> pt,α  = <lb/> g−1  α <lb/> 2−2g− <lb/> P d  i  τ  d  1  . . . τ  dn  <lb/> t  d  1  . . . t  dn <lb/> n! <lb/> (2) <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body> a rescaled Gromov–Witten potential of the point. <lb/>Then, whenever F  0  is semi-simple and of rank k, there exists an element S <lb/> of the lower-triangular group and an element R of the upper-triangular group <lb/>such that SR takes F <lb/> pt,α  1 <lb/> 0 <lb/> ⊕ · · · ⊕ F <lb/> pt,α  k <lb/> 0 <lb/> to F  0  , where α  1  , . . . , α  k  are appro-<lb/>priately chosen constants. <lb/>A quantized version of the same group (described in [8]), that we will call <lb/> Givental&apos;s group, acts on Gromov–Witten descendant partition functions. <lb/>The quantization <lb/> S() <lb/> R() of SR acts on power series in  and t <lb/> µ <lb/>d  . It takes <lb/> Z <lb/> pt,α  1  × · · · × Z <lb/> pt,α  k  to some power series Z = exp <lb/> g−1  F  g  . More precisely, <lb/> Z is in general a power series in variables t <lb/> µ <lb/>d  for d ≥ 1, whose coefficients are <lb/>functions on M in variables t <lb/> µ <lb/> 0  . These functions are analytic on M outside <lb/>of the discriminant, i.e., the subvariety where the tangent Frobenius algebra <lb/>is not semi-simple. <lb/>In practice it often happens that for mysterious reasons the coefficient <lb/>functions of Z turn out to be regular on the discriminant of M. In particular, <lb/>this is the case for the A  r  singularity, which is the main example of interest <lb/>for us, and for Gromov–Witten potentials of Kähler manifolds. In the sequel <lb/>we will only consider the cases where Z is regular at the origin and thus can <lb/>be decomposed into a power series. However, the examples of [6], Section 6, <lb/>show that singularities on the discriminant do appear in many cases. <lb/>Taking the lowest degree term in  (that is, the coefficient of <lb/> −1  ) in the <lb/>logarithm of Z, we recover the action of SR. <lb/> In Section 5 we will give a precise description of the upper and lower <lb/>triangular groups and their actions. <lb/> Definition 2.7 The series F = ln Z is called a genus expansion of the genus <lb/>zero potential F  0  or a formal Gromov–Witten descendant potential. <lb/> In terminology coming from physics, the Taylor coefficients <lb/> τ  d  1  ,µ  1  . . . τ  dn,µn   g,D  of the Gromov–Witten potential F are called cor-<lb/>relators, while the elements of the basis A are called primary fields. <lb/> The genus expansion of a formal genus 0 potential is not unique, because <lb/>the action of the twisted loop group is not free. Indeed, the upper-triangular <lb/>subgroup of the rank 1 twisted loop group acts trivially on F <lb/> pt <lb/>0  . The direct <lb/>product of k copies of the rank 1 upper-triangular subgroup forms a subgroup <lb/>of the rank k upper triangular subgroup. This subgroup acts trivially on <lb/> F <lb/> pt,α  1 <lb/> 0 <lb/> ⊕ · · · ⊕ F <lb/> pt,α  k <lb/> 0 <lb/> . But the quantizations of the elements of this subgroup <lb/>do not act trivially on Z <lb/> pt,α  1  ×· · ·×Z <lb/> pt,α  k  , and thus we obtain several different <lb/>genus expansions. <lb/>However, the ambiguity of the genus expansion can be fixed using an <lb/>additional property of homogeneity. <lb/></body>

			<page> 9 <lb/></page>

			<body> To illustrate this property, let us first assume that Z = exp <lb/> g−1  F  g  is <lb/>the descendant Gromov–Witten partition function of a target Kähler man-<lb/>ifold X. Choose a homogeneous basis A of H <lb/>  *  (X). To each variable t <lb/> µ <lb/>d  we <lb/>assign its weight w(t <lb/> µ <lb/>d  ) = d + deg(µ) − 1, where deg(µ) is the algebraic de-<lb/>gree of µ ∈ A. Further, introduce a weight function on the Novikov ring: <lb/> w(Q <lb/> D  ) = − D, c  1  (T X) for an effective divisor D. Finally, denote by dim X <lb/> the dimension of X. <lb/> The expected dimension of X  g,n,D  is n+(1−g)(dim X −3)+D, c  1  (T X). <lb/> Therefore the correlator τ  d  1  ,µ  1  . . . τ  dn,µn   g,D  vanishes unless <lb/> d  i  + <lb/> deg(µ  i  ) = n + (1 − g)(dim X − 3) + D, c  1  (T X) <lb/> ⇐⇒ <lb/> w(t <lb/> µ  i <lb/> d  i <lb/> ) + w(Q <lb/> D  ) = (1 − g)(dim X − 3). <lb/>In other words, F  g  is quasihomogeneous of total weight (1 − g)(dim X − 3). <lb/>This property is formalized in the following definition. <lb/> Definition 2.8 Introduce a weight map w : A → Q such that w(1) = −1, <lb/> let w(t <lb/> µ <lb/>d  ) = d + w(µ). Also introduce a weight function on the Novikov ring. <lb/>Let dim ∈ Q be a constant. <lb/>A formal Gromov–Witten potential F = <lb/> g−1  F  g  is called homogeneous <lb/> with respect to w and dim if every F  g  is quasihomogeneous of total weight (1− <lb/> g)(dim −3). <lb/> A homogeneous formal genus 0 Gromov–Witten potential has a unique <lb/> homogeneous genus expansion ([8] Proposition 6.7 c and Remark 6.9 a). <lb/>Givental conjectured that if F  0  is the geometric genus 0 potential of a <lb/>target space X, then the total geometric Gromov–Witten potential of X <lb/> coincides with the homogeneous genus expansion of its genus 0 part. <lb/> 2.2 Tautological classes and dual graphs <lb/> 2.2.1 The κ-classes <lb/> Definition 2.9 The cohomology class κ  k  1  ,...,km  on M  g,n  is defined by <lb/> κ  k  1  ,...,km  = π  *  (ψ <lb/> k  1  +1 <lb/> n+1  . . . ψ <lb/> km+1 <lb/>n+m  ), <lb/>where <lb/> π : M  g,n+m  → M  g,n <lb/> is the forgetful map. <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body> This definition is compatible with the usual definition of κ-classes κ  k  (for <lb/> m = 1). The classes κ  k  1  ,...,km  and the monomials κ  k  1  . . . κ  km  form two bases of <lb/>the same vector space and the matrix of basis change is triangular. Indeed, <lb/>we have <lb/> κ  k  1  ,...,km  = <lb/> σ∈Sm <lb/> c=cycle of σ <lb/> κ  k(c)  , where k(c) = <lb/> i∈c <lb/> k  i  . <lb/> For instance, <lb/> κ  k  1  ,k  2  = κ  k  1  κ  k  2  + κ  k  1  +k  2  , <lb/>κ  k  1  ,k  2  ,k  3  = κ  k  1  κ  k  2  κ  k  3  + κ  k  1  +k  2  κ  k  3  + κ  k  1  +k  3  κ  k  2  + κ  k  2  +k  3  κ  k  1  + 2κ  k  1  +k  2  +k  3  . <lb/> We prefer to work with the classes κ  k  1  ,...,km  because they are easier to express <lb/>in terms of Gromov–Witten correlators. <lb/>Let p : M  g,n+1  → M  g,n  be the forgetful map. Let r : M  g−1,n+2  → M  g,n <lb/> and q : M  g  1  ,n  1  +1  × M  g  2  ,n  2  +1  → M  g,n  be the usual &quot; gluing &quot; mappings to the <lb/>boundary components of M  g,n  . <lb/> Lemma 2.10 We have <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (κ  k  1  ,...,km  ) = κ  k  1  ,...,km  − <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> k  i <lb/> n+1  κ  k  1  ,..., b <lb/> k  i  ,...,km  , <lb/>q <lb/>  *  (κ  k  1  ,...,km  ) = <lb/> I⊔J={1,...,m} <lb/> κ  k  I  × κ  k  J  , <lb/>r <lb/>  *  (κ  k  1  ,...,km  ) = κ  k  1  ,...,km  , <lb/> where k  I  = {k  i  }  i∈I  , k  J  = {k  i  }  i∈J  , and <lb/> k  i  means that the index is omitted. <lb/> Proof. Only the first equality is nontrivial. Consider the forgetful map <lb/> p : M  g,n+1+m  → M  g,n+m  . <lb/> To avoid confusion in indices, suppose the n+m marked points are numbered <lb/>from 1 to n+m, while the forgotten point is labeled with α. In H <lb/> 2  (M  g,n+m+1  ) <lb/>we have <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (ψ  n+i  ) = ψ  n+i  − D  n+i,α  , where D  n+i,α  is the divisor of curves on <lb/>which the points n + i and α lie on a separate sphere with no other marked <lb/>points. From the relations <lb/> ψ  n+i  D  n+i,α  = 0 for 1 ≤ i ≤ m, <lb/>D  n+i,α  D  n+j,α  = 0 for i  = j, <lb/> we obtain that <lb/> p <lb/>  * <lb/>  m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> k  i  +1 <lb/> n+i <lb/> = <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> k  i  +1 <lb/> n+i  + <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> k  1  +1 <lb/> n+1  . . . (−D  n+i,α  ) <lb/> k  i  +1  . . . ψ <lb/> km+1 <lb/>n+m  . <lb/></body>

			<page> 11 <lb/></page>

			<body> Taking the push-forward of this class to M  g,n+1  we obtain the right-hand <lb/>side of the first equality of the lemma. <lb/>The second equality comes from the fact that each of the m points for-<lb/>gotten by the map π : M  g,n+m  → M  g,n  can find itself on either of the two <lb/>components of the boundary curves. The third equality follows directly from <lb/>the definition. <lb/> ♦ <lb/> 2.2.2 The dual graphs <lb/> Consider a stable curve C of genus g with n marked points in a one-to-one <lb/>correspondence with a set of markings S. The topological type of C can be <lb/>described by a graph G obtained by replacing every irreducible component <lb/>of the curve by a vertex and every node of the curve by an edge. Every <lb/>marked point is replaced by a tail (an edge that does not lead to any vertex) <lb/>retaining the same marking as the marked point. Each vertex v is labeled <lb/>by an integer g  v  : the geometric genus of the corresponding component. The <lb/> g  v  &apos;s and the first Betti number of G add up to g. <lb/> In order to avoid problems with automorphisms, we will label all the <lb/>half-edges of G. To G we assign the space <lb/> M  G  = <lb/> v <lb/> M  gv,nv  , <lb/> where the product goes over the set of vertices of G, g  v  is the genus of the <lb/>vertex v, and n  v  its valency (the number of half-edges and tails adjacent <lb/>to it). The space M  G  comes with a natural map p : M  G  → M  g,n  whose <lb/>image is the closure of the set of stable curves homeomorphic to C. Note <lb/>that p  *  [M  G  ] = |Aut(G)| · [p(M  G  )]. <lb/>We can define a cohomology class on M  G  (and hence on M  g,n  taking the <lb/>push-forward by p) by assigning a class κ  k  1  ,...,km  to each vertex of G and a <lb/>power ψ <lb/> d  of the ψ-class to each half-edge and each tail of G. <lb/> Definition 2.11 A graph G with labeled half-edges and tails, describing <lb/>the topological type of a stable curve, with an additional label κ  k  1  ,...,km  (v) <lb/>assigned to each vertex v and a nonnegative integer d  e  assigned to each <lb/>half-edge and each tail e is called a stable dual graph. The corresponding <lb/>cohomology class of M  g,n  is called the tautological class assigned to G and <lb/>denoted by [G]. The genus of a dual graph is the genus of the corresponding <lb/>stable curves, its degree is the algebraic degree of the corresponding coho-<lb/>mology class, and its dimension is dim M  g,n  − degree = 3g − 3 + n − degree. <lb/>This definition allows several modifications. <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body> First of all, we can consider not necessarily connected dual graphs. They <lb/>represent tautological classes on direct products of several moduli spaces. <lb/>Second, we can consider dual graphs that describe the topology of a semi-<lb/>stable curve that is not necessarily stable. In this case we will also label each <lb/>tail of the graph with a primary field µ ∈ A. If we work over a Novikov <lb/>ring, we also assign an effective 2-cycle D ∈ E to the whole graph. Such a <lb/>graph will be called a semi-stable dual graph with primary fields. It describes <lb/>a tautological cohomology class in the space of stable maps M  g,n+n  ′  (X, D). <lb/> A &quot; dual graph &quot; with no other specifications will mean &quot; stable connected <lb/>dual graph &quot; . <lb/> 2.3 Universal relations <lb/> Let F = <lb/> g−1  F  g  be the geometric Gromov–Witten potential of some target <lb/>Kähler manifold X, A a basis of H <lb/>  *  (X) and η the Poincaré pairing. Let <lb/> L = <lb/> c  i  G  i  be a linear combination of dual graphs representing a class <lb/>[L] ∈ H <lb/>  *  (M  g,n  ). As in the introduction, let X  g,n+n  ′  ,D  = M  g,n+n  ′  (X, D), <lb/> where D ∈ E is an effective 2-cycle, let [X  g,n+n  ′  ,D  ] be its virtual fundamental <lb/>class, and let p : X  g,n+n  ′  ,D  → M  g,n  be the forgetful map. We are going to <lb/>describe a way to express the integrals of the form <lb/> D∈E <lb/> Q <lb/> D <lb/> [X  g,n+n ′ ,D  ] <lb/> p <lb/>  *  ([L]) <lb/> n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  ) <lb/>via η <lb/> µν  and the coefficients of the series F  0  , . . . , F  g  . <lb/>We start with assigning a polynomial in correlators and coefficients η <lb/> µν <lb/> to any stable dual graph or any semi-stable dual graph with primary fields <lb/>that does not contain κ-classes. <lb/> Definition 2.12 Let G be a stable dual graph or a semi-stable dual graph <lb/>with primary fields such that no κ-classes are assigned to its vertices. We <lb/>define the polynomial P  G  by the following procedure. (i) Assign a primary <lb/>field µ ∈ A to every half-edge of G. In the case of a stable dual graph, <lb/>assign, moreover, the distinguished primary field 1 ∈ A to the tails. (ii) To <lb/>every vertex v assign the correlator <lb/> τ  d  1  ,µ  1  . . . τ  dn  v  ,µn  v <lb/> gv <lb/> , where g  v  is the genus <lb/>of v, n  v  its valency, and d  i  , µ  i  the labels on the half-edges and tails adjacent <lb/>to v. (iii) To every edge assign the coefficient η <lb/> µν  , where µ and ν are the <lb/>primary fields corresponding to its half-edges. (iv) Take the product of all <lb/>the correlators and the coefficients η <lb/> µν  thus obtained. (v) Sum over all the <lb/>ways to attribute primary fields to the half-edges. If we work over a Novikov <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body> ring, we must also sum over all the ways to assign effective 2-cycles D  v  to <lb/>the vertices in such a way that <lb/> D  v  = D. <lb/> Note that every edge of G introduces a contraction of indices via the <lb/>bilinear form η. This comes from the fact that the class of the diagonal in <lb/> X × X equals <lb/> µ,ν  η <lb/> µν  µ × ν. <lb/> Note also that the definition works perfectly well for not necessarily con-<lb/>nected dual graphs. <lb/>Now we go back to our problem of constructing a pull-back in X  g,n+n  ′  ,D <lb/> of the tautological class [L]. Let G be a stable dual graph participating in <lb/>the linear combination L. <lb/> Step 1: eliminating the κ-classes. If a vertex v of G is labeled with <lb/> κ  k  1  ,...,km  , erase this label and replace it by m new tails issuing from v with <lb/>labels ψ <lb/> k  1  +1  , . . . , ψ <lb/> km+1  on them. Thus we obtain a new dual graph G  1  . The <lb/>newly added tails will be called κ-tails. <lb/> This rule is justified by the following remark: if π : M  g,n+m  → M  g,n  is <lb/>the forgetful map, we have <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  1 <lb/> 1  . . . ψ <lb/> dn <lb/>n  κ  k  1  ,...,km  = π  *  (ψ <lb/> d  1 <lb/> 1  . . . ψ <lb/> dn <lb/>n  ψ <lb/> k  1  +1 <lb/> n+1  . . . ψ <lb/> km+1 <lb/>n+m  ) <lb/>in H <lb/>  *  (M  g,n  ). <lb/> Example 2.13 Let <lb/> G = <lb/> g = 2 <lb/> g = 1 <lb/> κ  1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> 0 <lb/> ψ <lb/> 0 <lb/> ψ <lb/> 1 <lb/> (here g = 3, n = 1). Then we have <lb/> P  G  1  = <lb/> µ,ν∈A <lb/> τ  0,1  τ  2,1  τ  0,ν   2  η <lb/> νµ  τ  1,µ   1  . <lb/> Step 2: recomputing the ψ-classes. There is a difference between the <lb/> ψ-classes on M  g,n  and on X  g,n+n  ′  ,D  , because of the presence of additional <lb/>marked points and because of the appearance of semi-stable source curves. <lb/>To take this into account, we modify G  1  according to the following rule: <lb/>replace every half-edge and every tail with label ψ <lb/> d <lb/> ψ <lb/> d <lb/> by the linear combination <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body> d <lb/> p=0 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> p <lb/> d  0  +···+dp=d−p <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/> ψ <lb/> 0 <lb/> ψ <lb/> 0 <lb/> ψ <lb/> 0 <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  0 <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  p−1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> dp <lb/> Thus we obtain a linear combination of dual graphs G  2  . When we perform <lb/>Steps 1 and 2 with all graphs of the linear combination L, we obtain a new <lb/>linear combination L  2  of semi-stable dual graphs (without primary fields). It <lb/>represents the class p <lb/>  *  ([L]) and will therefore be denoted by L  2  = p <lb/>  *  (L). <lb/>In terms of polynomials P  G  assigned to the dual graphs, replacing G  1 <lb/> by the linear combination of dual graphs G  2  is equivalent to making the <lb/>following substitutions in P  G  1  : <lb/> τ  1,µ  → τ  1,µ  − <lb/> µ  1  ,ν  1 <lb/> τ  0,µ  τ  0,ν  1   0  η <lb/> ν  1  µ  1  τ  0,µ  1  , <lb/>τ  2,µ  → τ  2,µ  − <lb/> µ  1  ,ν  1 <lb/> τ  1,µ  τ  0,ν  1   0  η <lb/> ν  1  µ  1  τ  0,µ  1  − <lb/> µ  1  ,ν  1 <lb/> τ  0,µ  τ  0,ν  1   0  η <lb/> ν  1  µ  1  τ  1,µ  1 <lb/> + <lb/> µ  1  ,ν  1  ,µ  2  ,ν  2 <lb/> τ  0,µ  τ  0,ν  1   0  η <lb/> ν  1  µ  1  τ  0,µ  1  τ  0,ν  2   0  η <lb/> ν  2  µ  2  τ  0,µ  2  , <lb/> and so on. In general, every insertion of τ  d,µ  must be replaced by <lb/> τ  d,µ  + <lb/> d <lb/> p=1 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> p <lb/> d  0  +···+dp=d−p <lb/> µ  1  ,ν  1  ,...,µp,νp <lb/> τ  d  0  ,µ  τ  0,ν  1   0  η <lb/> ν  1  µ  1  τ  d  1  ,µ  1  τ  0,ν  2   0  η <lb/> ν  2  µ  2  . . . η <lb/> νpµp  τ  dp,µp  . (3) <lb/>This formula is used in the following way: the symbol τ  d,µ  was part of some <lb/>correlator x; now we put τ  dp,µp  in its place, while the other factors of the <lb/>formula become factors in front of x. <lb/> It is important to note that the procedure of Step 2 for expressing ancestor <lb/> ψ-classes in terms of descendant ψ-classes is universal. This means that the <lb/>expression remains valid for any number of additional marked points n <lb/> ′  and <lb/>for any target manifold X. <lb/> Step 3: multiplying by <lb/>  n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1  ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  ). Let G  2  be one of the dual <lb/>graphs involved in the linear combination L  2  . It has two kinds of tails: the <lb/> κ-tails and the ordinary tails numbered from 1 to n. Add n <lb/> ′  more tails <lb/>numbered from n + 1 to n + n <lb/> ′  by attaching them to the vertices of G  2  in all <lb/>possible ways. <lb/>Now, the κ-tails already bear labels ψ <lb/> k  . We also label them with the <lb/>distinguished primary field 1. <lb/>The tails from 1 to n also bear labels ψ <lb/> d  ′ <lb/> i  , 1 ≤ i ≤ n. We replace ψ <lb/> d  ′ <lb/> i  on <lb/>the ith tail by ψ <lb/> d  ′ <lb/> i  +d  i  and also label the ith tail with the primary field µ  i  . <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body> The tails from n + 1 to n + n <lb/> ′  have no labels. We label them with ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> and µ  i  , n + 1 ≤ i ≤ n + n <lb/> ′  . <lb/>Thus we obtain a linear combination L  3  of semi-stable dual graphs <lb/>with primary fields. This linear combination will be denoted by L  3  = <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (L) <lb/>  n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1  ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  ). <lb/>In terms of polynomials P  G  , replacing P  L  2  by P  L  3  is equivalent to (i) re-<lb/>placing the symbols τ  d  ′ <lb/> i  ,1  corresponding to the tails from 1 to n by symbols <lb/> τ  d  ′ <lb/> i  +d  i  ,µ  i  and (ii) inserting new symbols τ  d  i  ,µ  i  for n + 1 ≤ i ≤ n + n <lb/> ′  in the <lb/>existing correlators in all possible ways. <lb/>The corresponding polynomial in correlators will be denoted by <lb/> P  L  3  = <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (L) <lb/> n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  ) <lb/> g <lb/> . <lb/> If F is the geometric Gromov–Witten potential of some target space X, we <lb/>have <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (L) <lb/> n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  ) <lb/> g <lb/> = <lb/> D∈H  2  (X) <lb/> [X  g,n+n ′ ,D  ] <lb/> p <lb/>  *  ([L]) <lb/> n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  ). <lb/>However it will be important for us that the expression <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (L) <lb/>  n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1  ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  ) <lb/> g <lb/> makes sense for any power series F = <lb/> g−1  F  g <lb/> in variables t <lb/> µ <lb/>d  , in particular for formal Gromov–Witten potentials. Note <lb/>that if two different linear combinations L and L <lb/> ′  of dual graphs represent <lb/>the same cohomology class, it is, for the time being, not at all obvious <lb/>that <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (L) <lb/>  n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1  ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  ) <lb/> g <lb/> and <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (L <lb/> ′  ) <lb/>  n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1  ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  ) <lb/> g <lb/> coincide <lb/>for every formal Gromov–Witten potential. <lb/> Definition 2.14 Let L be a linear combination of dual graphs. Let F = <lb/> g−1  F  g  be a power series in variables t <lb/> µ <lb/>d  . The infinite vector of the values <lb/>of <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (L) <lb/>  n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1  ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  ) <lb/> g <lb/> for all n <lb/> ′  ≥ 0 and for all d  i  , µ  i  , is called the <lb/> induced vector of L and is denoted by F  L  . <lb/> Definition 2.15 A linear combination L of dual graphs is called a universal <lb/>relation if the vector F  L  is equal to 0 for any semi-simple formal Gromov– <lb/>Witten descendant potential F , as defined by Givental. <lb/> Proposition 2.16 The vanishing of F  L  can be expressed as an infinite family <lb/>of partial differential equations on F  0  , F  1  , . . . . <lb/></body>

			<page> 16 <lb/></page>

			<body> This is a standard fact so we do not prove it here but instead illustrate <lb/>it with an example. <lb/> Example 2.17 The tautological relation <lb/> g = 1 <lb/> ψ <lb/>g = 0 <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>12 <lb/>= 0 <lb/>gives rise to the following family of partial differential equations indexed by <lb/> d ≥ 0 and ρ ∈ A: <lb/>∂F  1 <lb/> ∂t <lb/> ρ <lb/> d+1 <lb/> − <lb/> µ,ν <lb/> ∂F  1 <lb/> ∂t <lb/> µ <lb/> 0 <lb/> η <lb/> µν  ∂ <lb/> 2  F  0 <lb/> ∂t <lb/> ν <lb/> 0  dt <lb/> ρ <lb/>d <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>24 <lb/> µ,ν <lb/> ∂ <lb/> 3  F  0 <lb/> ∂t <lb/> µ <lb/> 0  ∂t <lb/> ν <lb/> 0  dt <lb/> ρ <lb/>d <lb/> η <lb/> µν  = 0. <lb/>The notion of universal relation is naturally generalized to not necessarily <lb/>connected stable dual graphs, but this should be done carefully. The simplest <lb/>way to define a universal relation in this case is the following. <lb/>Consider any graph as a product of its connected components. Then a <lb/>linear combination L of not necessarily connected stable dual graphs is called <lb/>a universal relation if it can be represented as a sum of several products such <lb/>that every term of the sum contains a universal relation for connected graphs <lb/>as a factor. <lb/>In other words, if we consider the product M  g  1  ,n  1  × · · · × M  g  k  ,n  k  , a uni-<lb/>versal relation in one of the factors times any class in the product of the <lb/>remaining factors is a universal relation, and a linear combination of univer-<lb/>sal relations is still a universal relation. <lb/> Remark 2.18 The method we used to define the induced vector F  L  works <lb/>for a linear combination L of not necessarily connected stable dual graphs. <lb/>However, in this case a more natural notion is that of an extended induced <lb/>vector <lb/> F  L  . Its definition is similar to that of F  L  , with the difference that <lb/>when we add new marked points to the curve, we are allowed to prescribe <lb/>the connected component to which every point should go. L is a universal <lb/>relation if and only if <lb/> F  L  vanishes. We do not know whether the conditions <lb/> F  L  = 0 and F  L  = 0 are equivalent. <lb/>Now we can give a precise formulation of the theorem announced in the <lb/>introduction. <lb/>Let F = <lb/> g−1  F  g  be a power series in  and t <lb/> µ <lb/>d  , where F  0  is a formal <lb/>genus 0 Gromov–Witten potential. We introduce five properties of F . <lb/>1. Homogeneity. F is homogeneous (in the sense of Definition 2.8) for <lb/>some w and dim. <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body> 2. Geometricity. F  L  vanishes for every tautological relation L. <lb/> 3. Semi-simplicity. F  0  is semi-simple at some point t. <lb/> 4. Reducibility to genus 0. Every correlator of F can be expressed in <lb/>terms of genus 0 correlators using only properties 1 and 2. <lb/>5. Analyticity. The homogeneous genus expansion of F  0  is regular at <lb/>the origin. <lb/>All geometric Gromov–Witten potentials of target Kähler manifolds sat-<lb/>isfy conditions 1 and 2. Conditions 3, 4, and 5, on the other hand, must be <lb/>checked in every particular case. <lb/>In Section 4 we will see an example of a potential that satisfies all five <lb/>conditions without being the geometric potential of a target manifold. <lb/> Theorem 3 A power series F satisfying conditions (1-5) coincides with the <lb/>homogeneous genus expansion of F  0  . <lb/> Proof. Let <lb/> F be the homogeneous genus expansion of F  0  . The expressions <lb/> F  L  and <lb/> F  L  vanish for all tautological relations L (the vanishing of <lb/> F  L  follows <lb/>from Theorems 1 and 4). Similarly, the nonhomogeneous correlators vanish <lb/>both for F and for <lb/> F . According to condition 4, these vanishing conditions <lb/>are enough to express every correlator in terms of genus 0 correlators. But <lb/>the genus 0 correlators coincide, since both are given by F  0  . Thus F = <lb/> F . ♦ <lb/> In [24], Y.-P. Lee studied the action of Givental&apos;s group on the induced <lb/>vectors F  L  and constructed an algoritm that computes certain, conjecturally <lb/>all, universal relations. We are now going to state his results. <lb/> 2.4 Y.-P. Lee&apos;s algorithm <lb/> 2.4.1 The operators τ  k <lb/> We are going to define linear operators τ  k  acting on the space of linear com-<lb/>binations of dual graphs. Here k is an arbitrary positive integer. <lb/>If G is a connected dual graph whose tails are labeled by a set S, then <lb/> τ  k  (G) is a linear combination of not necessarily connected dual graphs with <lb/>labeling set S ∪ {α, β}. The graphs of this linear combination are obtained <lb/>from G by the following operations. <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body> 1. Cut an edge of G into two tails. Change their labels to α and β in both <lb/>possible ways. If the labels on the half-edges were ψ <lb/> a  (on α) and ψ <lb/> b <lb/> (on β) before the cutting, we now label them first with ψ <lb/> a+k  and ψ <lb/> b  and <lb/>then with ψ <lb/> a  and ψ <lb/> b+k  . The first stable graph thus obtained is taken <lb/>with coefficient 1 while the second is taken with coefficient (−1) <lb/> k−1  . <lb/> ψ <lb/> a  ψ <lb/> b <lb/> α β <lb/>α β <lb/>ψ <lb/> a+k  ψ <lb/> b <lb/> ψ <lb/> a  ψ <lb/> b+k <lb/> + (−1) <lb/> k−1 <lb/> + two more terms. <lb/>2. Split a vertex v of G in two, and add a new tail on each of them, one <lb/>marked by α and the other one by β. If the genus of v was g, assign to <lb/>the new vertices genera g  1  and g  2  such that g  1  + g  2  = g in all possible <lb/>ways. Distribute the edges that were going out of v between the two <lb/>vertices in all possible ways. If v carried the label κ  k  1  ,...,km  , split the <lb/>set {k  1  , . . . , k  n  } in two disjoint subsets I and J in all possible ways and <lb/>assign to the new vertices the labels κ  I  and κ  J  . Label tail α with ψ <lb/> i <lb/> and tail β with ψ <lb/> j  , in all possible ways with the condition i + j = k − 1. <lb/>The dual graph thus obtained is taken with coefficient (−1) <lb/> j+1  . Keep <lb/>only stable graphs and sum over all the possibilities described above. <lb/> g <lb/>κ  k  1  ,...,km <lb/> (−1) <lb/> j+1 <lb/> g  1 <lb/> g  2 <lb/> κ  I <lb/> κ  J <lb/> α β <lb/>ψ <lb/> i  ψ <lb/> j <lb/> + <lb/> (−1) <lb/> j+1 <lb/> g  1 <lb/> g  2 <lb/> κ  I <lb/> κ  J <lb/> α β <lb/>ψ <lb/> i  ψ <lb/> j <lb/> + . . . <lb/> 3. Choose a vertex of G, decrease its genus by 1 and add two new tails on <lb/>it, one marked by α and the other one by β. Label tail α with ψ <lb/> i  and <lb/>tail β with ψ <lb/> j  , in all possible ways with the condition i + j = k − 1. <lb/>The dual graph thus obtained is taken with coefficient (−1) <lb/> j+1  . Sum <lb/>over all possible i and j. <lb/>g <lb/> (−1) <lb/> j+1 <lb/> g − 1 <lb/> α <lb/>β <lb/>ψ <lb/> i <lb/> ψ <lb/> j <lb/></body>

			<page> 19 <lb/></page>

			<body> The operations τ  k  are extended to linear combinations of dual graphs by <lb/>linearity. <lb/> 2.4.2 The algorithm <lb/>Theorem 4 (Y.-P. Lee) A linear combination L of dual graphs is a uni-<lb/>versal relation whenever (i) F <lb/> pt <lb/> L  = 0 and (ii) τ  k  (L) is a universal relation for <lb/>all k ≥ 1. <lb/>This theorem is actually an algorithm for computing universal relations <lb/>for Gromov–Witten potentials. Indeed, the vector F <lb/> pt <lb/> L  has an infinite number <lb/>of entries, but they can be expressed via a finite number of entries using the <lb/>string and dilaton equations. Therefore it is enough to check Condition (i) <lb/>for a finite number of entries. Now, the dimension (see Definition 2.11) of <lb/> τ  k  (L) is smaller than that of L, therefore we can proceed by induction on the <lb/>dimension of the relations. <lb/>Y.-P. Lee conjectures that this algorithm finds all universal relations on <lb/>formal Gromov–Witten potentials and that these universal relations arise <lb/>from tautological relations in the tautological ring of M  g,n  . However, neither <lb/>of these claims is proved. <lb/>Y.-P. Lee has also observed that in many cases Condition (i) is unneces-<lb/>sary and conjectured that checking Condition (ii) is enough for dim L ≥ 1. <lb/>However, it follows from our geometric interpretation that this conjecture is <lb/>wrong. The first example where it fails is in M  2,1  in dimension 1. <lb/>Y.-P. Lee&apos;s proof of Theorem 4 is summarized in Section 5. <lb/> 3 Geometrical interpretation <lb/> In this section we give a geometric interpretation of the operators τ  k  as in-<lb/>tersections with the boundary. (This interpretation was discovered indepen-<lb/>dently by Y.-P. Lee and R. Pandharipande -private communication.) Using <lb/>it, we prove that a linear combination L of dual graphs is obtained as a re-<lb/>lation in Y.-P. Lee&apos;s algorithm if and only if the intersection of [L] with all <lb/>tautological classes of complementary dimension vanishes. <lb/> 3.1 Operators τ  i  and boundary classes <lb/> In the universal curve C  g,n  , consider the codimension 2 subvariety ∆ of nodes <lb/>in the singular fibers of C  g,n  . Each point of ∆ is a node of a stable curve and <lb/>we will label by α and β the two marked points of its normalization identified <lb/>at this node. This can be done in two ways, hence we obtain a double covering <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body> of ∆ that we will call D. The space D = D  g,n  has one connected component <lb/>isomorphic to M  g−1,n+2  (unless g = 0) and (g+1)2 <lb/> n  −2(n+1) other connected <lb/>components, each of which is isomorphic to M  g  1  ,n  1  +1  ×M  g  2  ,n  2  +1  for suitable g  i <lb/> and n  i  with g  1  + g  2  = g and n  1  + n  2  = n. It comes with a natural map <lb/> p : D → M  g,n  , whose image is the boundary ∂M  g,n  = M  g,n  \ M  g,n  . Note <lb/>that all tautological classes supported on ∂M  g,n  are defined as push-forwards <lb/>of classes on D under p. <lb/> On D we define the following cohomology classes: <lb/> ρ  1  = 1 <lb/> ρ  2  = ψ  α  − ψ  β <lb/> ρ  3  = ψ <lb/> 2 <lb/> α  − ψ  α  ψ  β  + ψ <lb/> 2 <lb/> β <lb/> ρ  4  = ψ <lb/> 3 <lb/> α  − ψ <lb/> 2 <lb/> α  ψ  β  + ψ  α  ψ <lb/> 2 <lb/> β  − ψ <lb/> 3 <lb/> β <lb/> and so on. <lb/> Proposition 3.1 Let G be a dual graph of genus g with n tails. Then we <lb/>have <lb/> [τ  k  (G)] = −ρ  k  p <lb/>  *  [G] <lb/> in the cohomology ring of D. <lb/> Corollary 3.2 Let L be a linear combination of dual graphs and suppose <lb/>that the class [τ  1  (L)] vanishes (respectively, has zero intersection with all <lb/>tautological classes of complementary dimension). Then the class [τ  k  (L)] <lb/> vanishes (respectively, has zero intersection with all tautological classes of <lb/>complementary dimension) for all k. <lb/> Proof. The class [τ  k  (L)] is obtained from [τ  1  (L)] by a multiplication <lb/>by ρ  k  . <lb/> ♦ <lb/> This corollary confirms Y.-P. Lee&apos;s experimental observation that requir-<lb/>ing τ  k  (L) to be a universal relation for all k ≥ 1 is equivalent to requiring <lb/>just τ  1  (L) to be a universal relation ([23], Section 2.2, Remark (iii)). <lb/> Proof of Proposition 3.1. The main idea of the proof is very simple. <lb/>On every boundary component of M  g,n  we can define the classes ψ  α  and ψ  β <lb/> corresponding to the marked points α and β identified at the node. It is well-<lb/>known that the first Chern class of the normal line bundle to the boundary <lb/>component in M  g,n  equals −(ψ  α  + ψ  β  ). <lb/>Now, when we intersect a tautological class with a boundary component <lb/>of M  g,n  two cases can occur: either the class is entirely contained in the <lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body> component, or it intersects it transversally. In the first case we must multiply <lb/>our class by the first Chern class of the normal line bundle −(ψ  α  + ψ  β  ) and <lb/>then by −ρ  k  . Their product is equal to ψ <lb/> k <lb/>α  + (−1) <lb/> k−1  ψ <lb/> k <lb/>β  . In the second <lb/>case, we must add a new node, that either separates a component of the <lb/>curve in two or is a nonseparating node. In both cases we multiply the class <lb/>thus obtained by −ρ  k  = <lb/> i+j=k−1  (−1) <lb/> j+1  ψ <lb/> i <lb/>α  ψ <lb/> j <lb/>β  . These three possibilities <lb/>correspond to the three operations in the definition of τ  k  . <lb/>Now we present the proof with all necessary details. <lb/>To begin with, consider the case where G is a dual graph of genus g with n <lb/> tails with trivial labels assigned to all vertices, tails, and half-edges. Thus [G] <lb/>is the cohomology class p  G *  [M  G  ] on M  g,n  . <lb/>The computation of p <lb/>  *  [G] fits in the framework of [12], A.4. The con-<lb/>tributing graphs are of two kinds: either they have one more edge than G or <lb/>they have the same number of edges as G. <lb/> Consider a contributing graph with one extra edge. Contracting the extra <lb/>edge, we obtain the graph G and the contracted edge determines a unique <lb/>vertex v of G; let g  v  be the geometric genus of the corresponding component <lb/>and let n  v  be the valence of G at v including both half-edges and tails. Un-<lb/>less g  v  = 0, there is exactly one contributing graph corresponding to v whose <lb/>extra edge is a self-edge at a vertex with geometric genus g  v  − 1. Moreover, <lb/>there are exactly (g  v  +1)2 <lb/> nv  −2(n  v  +1) other contributing graphs correspond-<lb/>ing to v whose extra edge connects two distinct vertices. In other words, the <lb/>contributing graphs whose extra edge contracts to v are in one-to-one cor-<lb/>respondence with the connected components of the double covering D  gv,nv  . <lb/>Let Γ be a contributing graph with extra edge e. Let h  α  and h  β  be the <lb/>labeled half-edges constituting e and let α and β be the corresponding tails <lb/>arising upon cutting e. If cutting e disconnects the graph, put <lb/> M  e  := M  gα,nα  × M  g  β  ,n  β <lb/> where g  α  resp. g  β  and n  α  resp. n  β  are the genus and the number of tails of <lb/>the connected component containing α resp. β. If e is non-disconnecting, put <lb/> M  e  := M  g−1,n+2  . <lb/> Further, let <lb/> p  Γ,e  : M  Γ  → M  e  ⊂ D  g,n <lb/> be the map obtained via cutting e and contracting all other edges. Then <lb/>by [12], A.4 the contribution of (Γ, e) to p <lb/>  *  [G] equals <lb/> p  Γ,e *  [M  Γ  ]. <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body> Next, consider a contributing graph with the same number of edges as G. <lb/> The graph may then be identified with G and exactly one edge e of G has <lb/>been selected: it is identified by the excess line bundle. Define M  e  as above <lb/>and let <lb/> p  G,e  : M  G  → M  e  ⊂ D  g,n <lb/> be the map obtained via cutting e and contracting all other edges. Then <lb/>by [12], A.4 the contribution of (G, e) to p <lb/>  *  [G] equals <lb/> p  G,e *  (−ψ  α  − ψ  β  ) = (−ψ  α  − ψ  β  )p  G,e *  [M  G  ] <lb/>(with a slight abuse of notation). <lb/>We find the following formula for p <lb/>  *  [G]: <lb/> p <lb/>  *  [G] = <lb/> (Γ,e): Γ/e=G <lb/> p  Γ,e *  [Γ] + <lb/> e=(hα,h  β  )∈E(G) <lb/> (−ψ  α  − ψ  β  )p  G,e *  [G]. <lb/>If v  0  (G) denotes the number of vertices of G of geometric genus 0, the number <lb/>of summands in the first sum equals <lb/> v∈V (G) <lb/> (g  v  + 1)2 <lb/> nv  − 2n  v  − 2 <lb/> + |V (G)| − v  0  (G), <lb/>while the second sum runs over the half-edges of G. <lb/> Having dealt with the case of a dual graph with trivial labels, we consider <lb/>the case where G is a decorated dual graph: each vertex v of G has been <lb/>assigned a class κ  Kv  , where K  v  is a collection of m  v  nonnegative integers, <lb/>and each half-edge or tail h has been assigned a power ψ <lb/> d  h <lb/> h  of its ψ-class ψ  h  . <lb/>Each half-edge or tail on G determines a unique such on Γ. Taking this <lb/>into account, the formula above for p <lb/>  *  [G] continues to hold in the case of <lb/>decorated half-edges or tails. <lb/>Let v be a vertex of G. In case the extra edge e on Γ doesn&apos;t contract <lb/>to v, a unique vertex w of Γ corresponds to v and it is decorated with the <lb/>corresponding class κ  Kv  . We proceed analogously in case e is a self-edge at a <lb/>vertex w (with genus g  w  = g  v  −1) contracting to v. Finally, if e contracts to v <lb/> and connects two distinct vertices, the decoration κ  Kv  has to be divided up <lb/>in all 2 <lb/> mv  possible ways over the two vertices (cf. Lemma 2.10). The formula <lb/>above for p <lb/>  *  [G] continues to hold for an arbitrary decorated dual graph; note <lb/>that the number of summands in the first sum equals <lb/> v∈V (G) <lb/> 2 <lb/> mv <lb/> (g  v  + 1)2 <lb/> nv  − 2n  v  − 2 <lb/> + |V (G)| − v  0  (G). <lb/></body>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body> These considerations prove the statement for τ  1  . The statement for τ  k <lb/> follows from the trivial remark that <lb/> ρ  k  (ψ  α  + ψ  β  ) = ψ <lb/> k <lb/>α  + (−1) <lb/> k−1  ψ <lb/> k <lb/>β  . <lb/> ♦ <lb/> 3.2 The algorithm and the Gorenstein conjecture <lb/> The Gorenstein conjecture [29] states that the tautological ring of M  g,n  has <lb/>the form of the cohomology ring of a smooth manifold, that is, it has a unique <lb/>top degree class and a nondegenerate Poincaré duality. The conjecture is <lb/>made for the Q-subalgebra R <lb/>  *  (M  g,n  ) of the rational Chow ring generated <lb/>by the tautological classes. In this case the first claim holds (see [13, 7]), <lb/>but little is known about the second claim. In this paper we consider the <lb/>Gorenstein conjecture for the tautological cohomology ring RH <lb/>  *  (M  g,n  ), the <lb/>image in cohomology of R <lb/>  *  (M  g,n  ). The first claim is then obvious: the top <lb/>degree class is the class of a point and it can be represented by any dual <lb/>graph of maximal degeneration without ψ- and κ-classes. The second claim <lb/>is again not known. <lb/> Definition 3.3 We say that a tautological cohomology class on M  g,n  is <lb/> Gorenstein vanishing if its intersection numbers with all tautological classes <lb/>of complementary dimension vanish. <lb/>Here we are going to prove Theorem 1 stating that a linear combination L <lb/> of dual graphs appears as a relation in Y.-P. Lee&apos;s algorithm if and only if <lb/>the class [L] is Gorenstein vanishing. <lb/> Proof of Theorem 1. Denote by p : M  g,n+n  ′  → M  g,n  the forgetful map <lb/>and by q : D → M  g,n  the natural projection. <lb/>Taking into account the form of Y.-P. Lee&apos;s algorithm (Section 2.4.2), <lb/>and the geometric interpretation of the operators τ  k  , the theorem can be <lb/>reformulated as follows: <lb/> A tautological class α ∈ H <lb/>  *  (M  g,n  ) is Gorenstein vanishing if and only if <lb/>(i) all the intersection numbers <lb/> M  g,n+n ′ <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (α) <lb/> n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  , <lb/> vanish; and <lb/></body>

			<page> 24 <lb/></page>

			<body> (ii) the classes ρ  k  q <lb/>  *  (α) are Gorenstein vanishing for all k. <lb/> Since ρ  1  = 1, the second condition can, of course, be replaced by the <lb/>condition q <lb/>  *  (α) is Gorenstein vanishing. <lb/> The only if part. Suppose α is Gorenstein vanishing. Then <lb/> M  g,n+n ′ <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (α) <lb/> n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  = <lb/> Mg,n <lb/> α p  * <lb/>  n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i <lb/> = 0, <lb/>because the class p  * <lb/>  n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1  ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i <lb/> is tautological. <lb/>Similarly, if β is a tautological class on D, then <lb/> D <lb/> q <lb/>  *  (α) β = <lb/> Mg,n <lb/> α q  *  (β) = 0, <lb/>because q  *  (β) is tautological. <lb/> The if part. Suppose α satisfies Conditions (i) and (ii), and let G be a <lb/>dual graph of genus g with n tails, of complementary dimension to α. We <lb/>wish to prove that α ∩ [G] = 0. <lb/>First consider the case when G has no edges. This means that [G] is <lb/>a polynomial in ψ- and κ-classes. A class like that can be represented as <lb/>a linear combination of several classes p  * <lb/>  n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1  ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i <lb/> . But, by the same <lb/>equality that we used in the &quot; if &quot; part, we have <lb/> Mg,n <lb/> α p  * <lb/>  n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i <lb/> = <lb/> M  g,n+n ′ <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (α) <lb/> n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  = 0 <lb/>by Condition (i). <lb/>Now suppose G has at least one edge. Then the class [G] is the push-<lb/>forward of some tautological class β on D, in other words, [G] = q  *  (β). Thus <lb/> α ∩ [G] = <lb/> Mg,n <lb/> α q  *  (β) = <lb/> D <lb/> q <lb/>  *  (α) β = 0, <lb/>because q <lb/>  *  (α) is Gorenstein vanishing by Condition (ii). <lb/> ♦ <lb/> 4 A proof of Witten&apos;s conjecture <lb/> In this section we explain in more detail the plan of the proof of Witten&apos;s <lb/>conjecture outlined in the introduction. <lb/></body>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body> 4.1 Witten&apos;s conjecture and Gromov–Witten theories <lb/> The generating series studied in Witten&apos;s conjecture is <lb/> F <lb/> [r]  = <lb/> g≥0 <lb/> n≥1 <lb/> d  1  ,...,dn <lb/>a  1  ,...,an <lb/> Mg,n <lb/> c  W  (a  1  , . . . , a  n  ) ψ <lb/> d  1 <lb/> 1  . . . ψ <lb/> dn <lb/>n  · <lb/> t <lb/> a  1 <lb/> d  1 <lb/> . . . t <lb/> an <lb/>dn <lb/> n! <lb/>, <lb/> where c  W  (a  1  , . . . , a  n  ), also depending on r and g, is the Witten class briefly <lb/>introduced in the introduction. <lb/>Although this series is not the Gromov–Witten potential of any target <lb/>space, it is part of the framework of Gromov–Witten theories, because its <lb/>genus 0 part satisfies the string, the dilaton, and the TRR equations (see [16]). <lb/>The set of primary fields A, its distinguished element, and the bilinear <lb/>form η (that participates in the TRR equation) are determined by the fol-<lb/>lowing properties of Witten&apos;s class, proved in [30]. <lb/> 1. If a  i  = r − 1 for some i, then c  W  (a  1  , . . . , a  n  ) = 0. Thus the set A <lb/> equals {0, . . . , r − 2}. <lb/> 2. Let p : M  g,n+1  → M  g,n  be the forgetful map. Then <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (c  W  (a  1  , . . . , a  n  )) = c  W  (a  1  , . . . , a  n  , 0). <lb/>It follows that the distinguished primary field is 0. (There is an unfortunate <lb/>clash of notation with the Givental theory, where the distinguished primary <lb/>field is usually denoted by 1, a convention that we followed in our paper <lb/>except in the applications to Witten&apos;s conjecture.) <lb/> 3. Let r : M  g−1,n+2  → M  g,n  and q : M  g  1  ,n  1  +1  × M  g  2  ,n  2  +1  → M  g,n  be <lb/>the gluing mappings to the boundary components of M  g,n  . In the second <lb/>case we assume, for simplicity, that the n  1  marked points on the compo-<lb/>nent of genus g  1  have numbers 1, . . . , n  1  , while the n  2  marked points on the <lb/>component of genus g  2  have numbers n  1  + 1, . . . , n. Then we have <lb/> q <lb/>  *  (c  W  (a  1  , . . . , a  n  )) = <lb/> a  ′  +a  ′′  =r−2 <lb/> c  W  (a  1  , . . . , a  n  1  , a <lb/> ′  ) × c  W  (a <lb/> ′′  , a  n  1  +1  , . . . , a  n  ), <lb/>(where at most one term of the sum is actually nonzero, because of the <lb/>condition 2g  1  − 2 − <lb/>  n  1 <lb/> i=1  a  i  − a <lb/> ′  ≡ 2g  2  − 2 − <lb/>  n <lb/>i=n  1  +1  a  i  − a <lb/> ′′  ≡ 0 mod r), <lb/> and <lb/> r <lb/>  *  (c  W  (a  1  , . . . , a  n  )) = <lb/> a  ′  +a  ′′  =r−2 <lb/> c  W  (a  1  , . . . , a  n  , a <lb/> ′  , a <lb/> ′′  ). <lb/>It follows that the bilinear form is given by <lb/> η <lb/> ab  = δ <lb/> a+b,r−2  . <lb/></body>

			<page> 26 <lb/></page>

			<body> The string, the dilaton, and the TRR equations allow us to express all <lb/>genus zero correlators of the series F <lb/> [r]  using only the correlators for g = 0, <lb/> n = 3, 4, which were computed in Witten&apos;s original paper. <lb/>In [9], Givental found a specific element of Givental&apos;s group that sends <lb/>the series <lb/> Z <lb/> pt  × · · · × Z <lb/> pt <lb/> (r − 1 factors) <lb/>to the series Z <lb/> (r)  = exp <lb/> F <lb/> (r) <lb/> g  <lb/> g−1  such that Z <lb/> (r)  |  =1  is the τ -function of <lb/>the string solution of the r-KdV hierarchy, while F <lb/> (r)  = <lb/> F <lb/> (r) <lb/> g <lb/> is the string <lb/>solution itself. The genus 0 part of F <lb/> (r)  coincides with the genus 0 part <lb/>of F <lb/> [r]  . Indeed, both satisfy the string, the dilaton, and the TRR equations <lb/>and it is easy to check that they have the same coefficients for n = 3, 4. <lb/>Thus what remains to be proved is that the geometric series F <lb/> [r]  and the <lb/>formal Gromov–Witten potential F <lb/> (r)  coincide also in higher genus. To do <lb/>that, we will use Theorem 3, so let us check the conditions (1-5) involved in <lb/>its formulation. <lb/> Homogeneity. The correlator <lb/> τ  d  1  ,a  1  . . . τ  dn,an   g <lb/> vanishes unless <lb/> d  i  + <lb/> a  i <lb/> r <lb/> = n + <lb/> r − 2 <lb/> r <lb/> − 3 <lb/> (1 − g). <lb/> Indeed, from the definitions of Section 1.2, we get c  1  (T ) = (2g − 2 − <lb/> a  i  )/r, <lb/>hence the rank of V and the degree of c  W  equal <lb/>deg c  W  = <lb/>(r − 2)(g − 1) + <lb/> a  i <lb/> r <lb/>. <lb/> Thus the series F <lb/> [r]  satisfies the homogeneity property for the weight <lb/>function w(i) = <lb/> i <lb/>r <lb/> − 1, and the &quot; dimension &quot; dim = <lb/> r−2 <lb/>r <lb/> . (There is no need <lb/>for a weight function on a Novikov ring, because we are working over C) <lb/> Geometricity. It is obvious that the Gromov–Witten potential F <lb/> [r] <lb/> respects all tautological relations because of its geometric origin. <lb/> Semi-simplicity. There exists a bi-polynomial isomorphism <lb/> C <lb/> r−2  → C <lb/> r−2  : (t  0,1  , . . . , t  0,r−2  ) → (s  1  , . . . , s  r−2  ) <lb/>such that the algebra described in Definition 2.4 is naturally identified with <lb/>the algebra <lb/> C[X]/(X <lb/> r−1  + s  1  X <lb/> r−3  + · · · + s  r−2  ). <lb/></body>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body> Thus it is semi-simple whenever the polynomial has r − 1 distinct roots. <lb/>For instance, for r = 5, the algebra of Definition 2.4 is isomorphic to <lb/> C[X]/P <lb/> ′  , where <lb/> P (X) = X <lb/> 5  − t  0,3  X <lb/> 3  − t  0,2  X <lb/> 2  + (t <lb/> 2 <lb/>0,3  /5 − t  0,1  )X <lb/>and P <lb/> ′  is its derivative. <lb/>For more details, see [9]. <lb/> Reducibility to genus 0. This property will be established in Theo-<lb/>rem 5. <lb/> Analyticity. In [9] the genus expansion of F <lb/> (r) <lb/>0 <lb/> is given in the form of a <lb/>power series at the origin. <lb/> 4.2 Admissible covers and double ramification cycles <lb/> The spaces of admissible covers and the double ramification cycles were first <lb/>introduced by Ionel [14] and proved very useful in the study of moduli spaces. <lb/>Let us briefly recall their definitions. <lb/>Consider a map ϕ from a smooth curve C with n marked points to the <lb/>sphere S = CP <lb/> 1  . On S we mark all branch points of ϕ and the images of <lb/>the n marked points of C. On C we then mark all the preimages of the <lb/>points that are marked on S. Now choose several disjoint simple loops on <lb/> S, that do not pass through the marked points. Suppose that if we contract <lb/>these loops we obtain a stable genus 0 curve S <lb/> ′  . Now contract also all the <lb/>preimages of the loops in C to obtain a nodal curve C <lb/> ′  that turns out to be <lb/>automatically stable. We have obtained a map ϕ <lb/> ′  from a stable curve C <lb/> ′  of <lb/>genus g to a stable curve S <lb/> ′  of genus 0. It has the same degree over every <lb/>component of S <lb/> ′  . Moreover, at each node of C <lb/> ′  , the projection ϕ <lb/> ′  has the <lb/>same local multiplicity on both components meeting at the node. <lb/> Definition 4.1 A map from a stable curve of genus g to a stable curve <lb/>of genus 0 topologically equivalent to a map described above is called an <lb/> admissible covering. <lb/> We will be particularly interested in the space of admissible coverings <lb/>with multiple ramifications over only 2 points labeled with 0 and ∞, the <lb/>other ramification points being simple. <lb/> Definition 4.2 Consider the space of admissible coverings of some given <lb/>genus g with prescribed ramification types over two points labeled 0 and ∞, <lb/> and with simple ramifications elsewhere. The normalization of this space is <lb/>called a double ramification space or a DR-space. <lb/></body>

			<page> 28 <lb/></page>

			<body> Definition 4.3 Let k  1  , . . . , k  n+p  be a list of integers such that <lb/> k  i  = 0 <lb/>and k  i  = 0 for n + 1 ≤ i ≤ n + p. Consider the set of smooth <lb/>curves (C, x  1  , . . . , x  n  ) ∈ M  g,n  such that there exist p more marked points <lb/> x  n+1  , . . . , x  n+p  and a meromorphic function on C with no zeroes or poles <lb/>outside of x  1  , . . . , x  n+p  , the orders of zeroes or poles being prescribed by the <lb/>list k  1  , . . . , k  n+p  (k  i  &gt; 0 for the zeroes, k  i  &lt; 0 for the poles, and k  i  = 0 for <lb/>the marked points that are neither zeroes nor poles). The closure of this set <lb/>in M  g,n  is called the double ramification cycle or a DR-cycle. <lb/> Here are some basic facts about the double ramification cycles that make <lb/>them so useful. <lb/>1. The codimension of a DR-cycle is equal to g − p whenever there is at <lb/>least one positive and one negative number among k  1  , . . . , k  n  (see [28, <lb/>14]). Assuming that this condition is satisfied we see that for p = g the <lb/>DR-cycle coincides with the moduli space M  g,n  . <lb/>2. The cohomology class Poincaré dual to any DR-cycle belongs to the <lb/>tautological ring of M  g,n  (proved in [7]). <lb/>This makes the results of this paper applicable to DR-cycles. <lb/>3. Each DR-cycle is the image of the corresponding DR-space under the <lb/>forgetful map π that forgets the covering and all the marked points <lb/>except x  1  , . . . , x  n  , but retains and stabilizes the source curve with the n <lb/> remaining marked points. The map π sends the fundamental homology <lb/>class of the DR-space to a multiple of the fundamental homology class <lb/>of the DR-cycle. <lb/>4. Every class π <lb/>  *  (ψ  i  ) on a DR-space can be expressed as a linear combi-<lb/>nation of boundary divisors [14, 32]. <lb/>This is a very important property that can be used to compute integrals <lb/>involving ψ-classes. Indeed, it allows us to get rid of the ψ-classes one <lb/>by one by reducing the integral to simpler integrals over smaller spaces. <lb/>Using this procedure, the following result was established in [34], The-<lb/>orem 1. <lb/> Theorem 5 [34] Every correlator in the r-spin Witten conjecture can be <lb/>expressed in genus zero correlators using only tautological relations. <lb/> The last result shows that Theorem 3 is applicable to the r-spin Witten <lb/>conjecture and suffices to prove it. <lb/></body>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body> The proof of Theorem 5 in [34] goes as follows. As explained in Item 1, the <lb/>fundamental class of M  g,n  can be represented as a DR-cycle with p = g. If <lb/>this is done in an intelligent way, then the elimination of ψ-classes according <lb/>to Item 4, leads us to boundary divisors that can themselves be expressed as <lb/>DR-cycles on the boundary. We end up with the integral of Witten&apos;s class <lb/> c  W  (without ψ-classes) over a DR-cycle. A dimension count shows that an <lb/>integral like that may be nonzero only if g = 0 or 1 and the codimension <lb/>of the DR-cycle is equal to the genus (0 for g = 0 and 1 for g = 1). In <lb/>the latter case we must do some more work: putting one ψ-class back into <lb/>the integral and expressing it as a linear combination of boundary divisors <lb/>in different ways we obtain certain relations between genus 1 and genus 0 <lb/>integrals of c  W  . It turns out that these relations suffice to reduce all genus 1 <lb/>integrals to genus 0 integrals. <lb/>However, now we can give a simpler, although less constructive, proof. <lb/> Proof of Theorem 5. In [14], Ionel proved the following assertion: <lb/> Let M be a monomial in ψ- and κ-classes on M  g,n  , of degree <lb/> 3  at least g <lb/> for g ≥ 1 or at least 1 for g = 0. Then the class M can be represented as a <lb/>linear combination of classes of the form <lb/> q  *  [(DR-cycle)  1  × · · · × (DR-cycle)  k  ] . <lb/> Here k ≥ 1 is an integer that can be different for different terms of the sum, <lb/> q : M  g  1  ,n  1  ×· · ·×M  g  k  ,n  k  → M  g,n  is the gluing map from a product of smaller <lb/>moduli spaces to a boundary stratum of M  g,n  and the cycles (DR-cycle)  j  are <lb/>DR-cycles on the smaller moduli spaces. <lb/>It was established in [7] that every DR-cycle is tautological and that <lb/>Ionel&apos;s theorem can therefore be improved in the following way: <lb/> Let M be a monomial in ψ- and κ-classes on M  g,n  , of degree at least g <lb/> for g ≥ 1 or at least 1 for g = 0. Then the class M can be represented by a <lb/>linear combination of dual graphs each of which has at least one edge. <lb/> We will call this property the g-reduction. <lb/> Now, a simple dimension count shows that the integral <lb/> Mg,n <lb/> β · c  W  (a  1  , . . . , a  n  ) <lb/>vanishes unless the class β has complex degree at least g. Indeed, the degree <lb/>of Witten&apos;s class equals <lb/>deg c  W  = <lb/>(r − 2)(g − 1) + <lb/> a  i <lb/> r <lb/> ≤ <lb/> (r − 2)(n + g − 1) <lb/> r <lb/>, <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 3  The degree of a ψ-class equals 1, while the degree of κ  k  equals k. <lb/></note>

			<page> 30 <lb/></page>

			<body> while the dimension of M  g,n  is 3g − 3 + n (use the exact expression for g = 1 <lb/>and the upper bound for g ≥ 2). <lb/>Recall that the pull-back of Witten&apos;s class to the boundary components <lb/>is given by the factorization property (3) of Section 4.1. This makes it easy <lb/>to apply the g-reduction to integrals involving Witten&apos;s class. <lb/>The rest of the proof is simple. Suppose we wish to compute the integral <lb/> Mg,n <lb/> c  W  (a  1  , . . . , a  n  ) ψ <lb/> d  1 <lb/> 1  . . . ψ <lb/> dn <lb/>n  . <lb/> Apply the g-reduction in iteration as many times as possible, starting with <lb/>the class ψ <lb/> d  1 <lb/> 1  . . . ψ <lb/> dn <lb/>n  . In the end we will obtain an expression of <lb/>  n <lb/>i=1  ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i <lb/> as a linear combination of dual graphs G satisfying the following condition. <lb/>Suppose a vertex v of G is labeled with genus g  v  &gt; 0 and with a class κ  k  1  ,...,km  , <lb/>and suppose the half-edges and tails issuing from v are labeled with ψ <lb/> d  1  , . . . , <lb/> ψ <lb/> dn  v  . Then <lb/> k  i  + <lb/> d  i  &lt; g  v  . (Indeed, if <lb/> k  i  + <lb/> d  i  ≥ g  v  for at least <lb/>one vertex, we can apply the g-reduction to this vertex.) But, as we have <lb/>already explained, the integral of Witten&apos;s class over the class [G] represented <lb/>by a dual graph like that vanishes whenever there is at least one vertex of <lb/>nonzero genus. Thus the only contribution comes from graphs with only <lb/>genus zero vertices with no ψ- or κ-classes. So we have reduced any given <lb/>correlator involved in Witten&apos;s conjecture to a linear combination of products <lb/>of genus 0 correlators. More precisely, the only remaining correlators are <lb/>integrals of Witten&apos;s class with no ψ-classes over genus zero moduli spaces. <lb/> ♦ <lb/> As we have already explained, this implies that the formal Gromov– <lb/>Witten potential F <lb/> (r)  coincides with the geometric Gromov–Witten potential <lb/> F <lb/> [r]  and proves the Witten conjecture. <lb/> 5 More on Givental&apos;s quantization and Y.-P. <lb/>Lee&apos;s theorem <lb/> A proof of Theorem 4 is contained in [24]. However there are some missing <lb/>details that we would like to fill in here. First, we would like to explain <lb/>precisely why the operators τ  k  act on the κ-classes in the way described in <lb/>Section 2.4.1 (this is done in Proposition 5.5). Second, we explain more <lb/>precisely how Givental&apos;s quantization is applied to prove the theorem. <lb/> &quot; Givental&apos;s group &quot; is really not a group, but a collection of two groups: <lb/>the so-called &quot; lower triangular &quot; and &quot; upper triangular &quot; groups. This is anal-<lb/>ogous to the Birkhoff decomposition in the finite-dimensional case. However, <lb/></body>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body> because both groups are infinite-dimensional, it is in general not possible to <lb/>multiply their elements, like it is impossible to multiply a power series in z <lb/> and a power series in z <lb/> −1  . On the other hand, it turns out that, under some <lb/>conditions, one can apply first an element of the upper triangular group and <lb/>then an element of the lower triangular group to a Gromov–Witten potential. <lb/>Both the lower triangular and the upper triangular group possess Lie <lb/>algebras. An element of the lower triangular Lie algebra is a series s(z <lb/> −1  ) = <lb/> l≥1  s  l  z <lb/> −l  of linear operators on the vector space V . The operators s  l  are <lb/>self-adjoint for l odd and skew-self-adjoint for l even with respect to the <lb/>quadratic form η. <lb/> Similarly, an element of the upper triangular Lie algebra is a series r(z) = <lb/> l≥1  r  l  z <lb/> l  of linear operators on V . The operators r  l  are self-adjoint for l odd <lb/>and skew-self-adjoint for l even with respect to the quadratic form η. <lb/> The coefficients of s  l  and r  l  in the basis A will be denoted by (s  l  ) <lb/> ν <lb/>µ  and <lb/>(r  l  ) <lb/> ν <lb/>µ  . We will also need the bivectors and the bilinear forms given by <lb/>(s  l  )  µν  = <lb/> ρ <lb/> η  µρ  (s  l  ) <lb/> ρ <lb/>ν  , <lb/> (s  l  ) <lb/> µν  = <lb/> ρ <lb/> η <lb/> µρ  (s  l  ) <lb/> ν <lb/>ρ  , <lb/> (r  l  )  µν  = <lb/> ρ <lb/> η  µρ  (r  l  ) <lb/> ρ <lb/>ν  , <lb/> (r  l  ) <lb/> µν  = <lb/> ρ <lb/> η <lb/> µρ  (r  l  ) <lb/> ν <lb/>ρ  . <lb/> The matrices (s  l  )  µν  , (r  l  )  µν  , (s  l  ) <lb/> µν  , and (r  l  ) <lb/> µν  are symmetric for odd l and <lb/>skew-symmetric for even l. <lb/> Y.-P. Lee [24] writes down explicit formulas for the action of s and r <lb/> on any given correlator of a Gromov–Witten potential F (see below). Once <lb/>this is done, the main problem is to understand what happens when we <lb/>apply these formulas to the induced vector of a tautological class: indeed, <lb/>both Y.-P. Lee&apos;s formulas for the derivatives of an individual correlator and <lb/>the expression of the induced vector in terms of correlators (described in <lb/>Section 2.3) are fairly complicated. <lb/>Below we sum up the argument of [24] and give more detailed statements <lb/>of certain results. <lb/>If s(z <lb/> −1  ) = <lb/> l≥1  s  l  z <lb/> −l  is an element of the lower triangular Lie algebra <lb/>and r(z) = <lb/> l≥1  r  l  z <lb/> l  an element of the upper triangular Lie algebra, denote, <lb/>for shortness <lb/> s  l  (τ  d,µ  ) = <lb/> ν <lb/> (s  l  ) <lb/> ν <lb/>µ  τ  d−l,ν  , <lb/>r  l  (τ  d,µ  ) = <lb/> ν <lb/> (r  l  ) <lb/> ν <lb/>µ  τ  d+l,ν  . <lb/> Now we are going to follow the path from the Gromov–Witten potential <lb/>of a point to the general formal semi-simple Gromov–Witten potential. <lb/></body>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<body> 5.1 The upper triangular group <lb/> Let t <lb/> µ <lb/> 0  be flat coordinates on a semi-simple Frobenius manifold M of dimen-<lb/>sion k. Let f (t <lb/> µ <lb/> 0  ) be the corresponding genus 0 potential. We assume that f <lb/> is an analytic function. At a semi-simple point, the tangent Frobenius alge-<lb/>bra T  *  M to the Frobenius manifold M possesses a basis of primitive idem-<lb/>potents. Denote by α  1  , . . . , α  k  their scalar squares in the metric η. Givental <lb/>constructs an element R of the upper triangular group whose action trans-<lb/>forms the constant Frobenius structure on T  *  M into the Frobenius structure <lb/>of M at the neighborhood of the semi-simple point. <lb/>In other words, the first step of Givental&apos;s quantization is to apply the <lb/>quantized action of R to the partition function Z <lb/> pt,α  1  × · · · × Z <lb/> pt,α  k  , see <lb/>Eq. (2). <lb/>The potential F <lb/> pt,α  1  ⊕ · · · ⊕ F <lb/> pt,α  k  obviously possesses the two following <lb/>crucial properties. <lb/> Definition 5.1 A Gromov–Witten potential is tame if <lb/> τ <lb/> µ  1 <lb/> d  1 <lb/> · · · τ <lb/> µn <lb/>dn <lb/> g <lb/> van-<lb/>ishes whenever <lb/> d  i  &gt; 3g − 3 + n. <lb/> Definition 5.2 A Gromov–Witten potential is an ancestor potential if its <lb/>correlators with 2 − 2g − n ≥ 0 vanish. <lb/>Let r = ln R be an element of the upper triangular Lie algebra. In <lb/>general, the action of R on a power series is not well defined. However, <lb/>it is easy to check (cf. Proposition 5.3) that the action of r  l  increases the <lb/>grading <lb/> d  i  − n − 3g + 3 by l. Therefore the action of R on a tame series <lb/>is well-defined and is equal to the exponential of the action of r. <lb/> According to Givental&apos;s formulas, r = <lb/> l≥1  r  l  z <lb/> l  acts on the partition <lb/>function Z via the second order differential operator <lb/> r = <lb/> − <lb/> l≥1 <lb/>µ <lb/> (r  l  ) <lb/> µ <lb/> 1 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t <lb/> µ <lb/>l+1 <lb/> + <lb/> d≥0,l≥1 <lb/>µ,ν <lb/> (r  l  ) <lb/> µ <lb/>ν  t <lb/> ν <lb/>d <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t <lb/> µ <lb/>d+l <lb/> + <lb/> 2 <lb/> d  1  ,d  2  ≥0 <lb/> µ  1  ,µ  2 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> d  1  +1  (r  d  1  +d  2  +1  ) <lb/> µ  1  µ  2 <lb/> ∂ <lb/> 2 <lb/> ∂t <lb/> µ  1 <lb/> d  1 <lb/> ∂t <lb/> µ  2 <lb/> d  2 <lb/> . <lb/> The next proposition gives the action of r on individual correlators. <lb/></body>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body> Proposition 5.3 ([24], Equation (23)) <lb/> r. τ  d  1  ,µ  1  . . . τ  dn,µn   g  = <lb/>(4) <lb/> − <lb/> ∞ <lb/> l=1 <lb/> r  l  (τ  1,1  ) τ  d  1  ,µ  1  . . . τ  dn,µn   g <lb/> + <lb/> ∞ <lb/> l=1 <lb/>n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> τ  d  1  ,µ  1  . . . r  l  (τ  d  i  ,µ  i  ) . . . τ  dn,µn   g <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ∞ <lb/> l=1 <lb/> m+m  ′  =l−1 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> m+1 <lb/> µ,ν <lb/> (r  l  ) <lb/> µν  τ  m,µ  τ  m  ′  ,ν  τ  d  1  ,µ  1  . . . τ  dn,µn   g−1 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ∞ <lb/> l=1 <lb/> m+m  ′  =l−1 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> m+1 <lb/> g  1  +g  2  =g <lb/> I⊔J={1,...,n} <lb/> µ,ν <lb/> (r  l  ) <lb/> µν <lb/> τ  m,µ <lb/> i∈I <lb/> τ  d  i  ,µ  i <lb/> g  1 <lb/> τ  m  ′  ,ν <lb/> i∈J <lb/> τ  d  i  ,µ  i <lb/> g  2 <lb/> . <lb/> Remark 5.4 One can easily deduce from these formulas that the action of <lb/>the upper triangular group preserves the tameness property and the property <lb/>of being an ancestor potential. <lb/> Proposition 5.5 (based on [24], Section 6) Let L be a linear combination <lb/>of dual graphs and r an element of the upper triangular Lie subalgebra of <lb/>Givental&apos;s Lie algebra. Let F be a formal tame ancestor potential. Then <lb/> r. <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (L) <lb/> n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  ) <lb/> g <lb/> is a linear combination of polynomials in correlators of the form <lb/> (i) <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (L) <lb/> n+n  ′  +1 <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  ) <lb/> g <lb/> , <lb/> where d  n+n  ′  +1  ≥ 2 and µ  n+n  ′  +1  is a primary field; <lb/> (ii) <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (L) <lb/> n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  ′ <lb/> i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ <lb/> ′ <lb/> i  ) <lb/> g <lb/> , <lb/> where d <lb/> ′ <lb/> i  = d  i  , µ <lb/> ′ <lb/> i  = µ  i  for all i except one, and d <lb/> ′ <lb/> i  &gt; d  i  for one i; <lb/> (iii) <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (τ  l  (L)) <lb/> n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  ) · ev <lb/>  * <lb/> α  (µ  α  )ev <lb/>  * <lb/> β  (µ  β  ) <lb/> g <lb/> , <lb/></body>

			<page> 34 <lb/></page>

			<body> where l ≥ 1 and µ  α  , µ  β  are primary fields; <lb/> (iv) <lb/> τ  dα,µα <lb/> i∈I <lb/> τ  d  i  ,µ  i <lb/> 0 <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (L) ψ <lb/> d  β <lb/> β  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> β  (µ  β  ) <lb/> i∈J <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  ) <lb/> g <lb/> , <lb/> where I ⊂ {n + 1, . . . , n + n <lb/> ′  }, I ⊔ J = {1, . . . , n + n <lb/> ′  }, d  α  and d  β  are <lb/>nonnegative integers, and µ  α  , µ  β  are primary fields; <lb/> (v) <lb/> τ  dα,µα  τ  d  j  ,µ  j <lb/> i∈I <lb/> τ  d  i  ,µ  i <lb/> 0 <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (L) ψ <lb/> d  β <lb/> β  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> β  (µ  β  ) <lb/> i∈J <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  ) <lb/> g <lb/> , <lb/> where I ⊂ {n + 1, . . . , n + n <lb/> ′  }, j ∈ {1, . . . , n}, I ⊔ J ⊔ {j} = {1, . . . , n + n <lb/> ′  }, <lb/> d  α  and d  β  are nonnegative integers, and µ  α  , µ  β  are primary fields. <lb/> Remark 5.6 If we work over a Novikov ring, we must introduce a summa-<lb/>tion over D  1  + D  2  = D in the last term of the equality in Proposition 5.3 as <lb/>well as in terms (iv) and (v) of Proposition 5.5. <lb/> Corollary 5.7 Let L be a linear combination of genus g dual graphs with <lb/> n tails such that τ  k  (L) is a universal relation for all k. Assume that F <lb/> pt <lb/> L <lb/> vanishes. Then F  L  also vanishes for every F that can be obtained from <lb/> F <lb/> pt,α  1 <lb/> 0 <lb/> ⊕ · · · ⊕ F <lb/> pt,α  k <lb/> 0 <lb/> by the upper triangular group action. <lb/> Proof. The polynomials (i) to (v) are either entries of F  L  of F  τ  l  (L)  . In the <lb/>latter case they vanish by assumption. Therefore the vector F  L  on the orbit <lb/> e <lb/> tr  F is the solution of a linear differential equation with vanishing initial <lb/>conditions. Thus F  L  = 0 on the whole orbit. <lb/> ♦ <lb/> Proof of Proposition 5.5. <lb/>1. We first prove the proposition in the particular case n <lb/> ′  = 0, d  1  = · · · = <lb/> d  n  = 0. In Section 2.3 we gave a three steps algorithm to determine the <lb/>linear combination of graphs p <lb/>  *  (L) <lb/>  n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1  ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  ). In our particular case, <lb/>the steps are greatly simplified: Step 1 (replacing κ-classes by additional <lb/>tails) remains unchanged; Step 2 (expressing ancestor ψ-classes in terms of <lb/>descendant ψ-classes) can be skipped, since all genus zero 2-point correlators <lb/>vanish for an ancestor potential and since there are no additional marked <lb/>points; Step 3 (adding tails from n+1 to n+n <lb/> ′  and multiplying by ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  )) <lb/>reduces to assigning the markings µ  1  , . . . , µ  n  to tails 1 to n. <lb/> As for the claim of our proposition, if n <lb/> ′  = 0, then terms (iv) and (v) <lb/>disappear, because I ⊂ {n + 1, . . . , n + n <lb/> ′  } is then empty, and an ancestor <lb/>potential does not have genus 0 correlators with fewer than 3 entries. Thus we <lb/></body>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body> must prove that r. p <lb/>  *  (L) <lb/>  n <lb/> i=1  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  )  g  is a linear combination of terms (i), <lb/>(ii), and (iii). <lb/>Let G be a graph in L. <lb/> 1a. First suppose that G has only one vertex (of genus g and valency n) <lb/> with a class κ  k  1  ,...,km  assigned to the vertex and classes ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  assigned to the <lb/>tails. Applying Steps 1 and 3 we obtain <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (G) <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  ) <lb/> = <lb/>  m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> τ  k  i  +1,1 <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> τ  d  i  ,µ  i <lb/> . <lb/> To determine the action of r on the correlator in the right-hand side we apply <lb/>Equation (4) to it. <lb/>Applying the third and fourth terms in Equation (4) gives us term (iii) <lb/>involving τ  l  (G). Note that when we apply the fourth term of Equation (4), <lb/>the indices k  1  , . . . , k  m  are distributed among the two correlators in all possible <lb/>ways, according to the description of τ  l  . <lb/>Now apply the first two terms of Equation (4) to our correlator. We <lb/>regroup them in the following way: <lb/> ∞ <lb/> l=1 <lb/> µ <lb/> (r  l  ) <lb/> 1 <lb/> µ <lb/>  m <lb/> j=1 <lb/> τ  k  j  +l+1,µ <lb/> i =j <lb/> τ  k  i  +1,1 <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> τ  d  i  ,µ  i <lb/> − <lb/> τ  l+1,µ <lb/>m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> τ  k  i  +1,1 <lb/> n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> τ  d  i  ,µ  i <lb/> + <lb/> n <lb/> j=1 <lb/> r  l  (τ  d  j  ,µ  j  ) <lb/> m <lb/> i=1 <lb/> τ  k  i  +1,1 <lb/> i =j <lb/> τ  d  i  ,µ  i <lb/> . <lb/> (5) <lb/>Consider the forgetful map π : M  g,n+1  → M  g,n  . The pull-back <lb/> π <lb/>  *  (κ  k  1  ,...,km  ) given by Lemma 2.10 imitates the expression in square brackets <lb/>of (5). In addition, we have π <lb/>  *  (ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  )ψ <lb/> l+1 <lb/>n+1  = ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ψ <lb/> l+1 <lb/>n+1  . It follows that the terms <lb/>in square brackets add up to give term (i). <lb/>The last term of Equation (5) replaces one of the symbols τ  d  j  ,µ  j  by τ  d  ′ <lb/> j  ,µ  ′ <lb/> j <lb/> with d <lb/> ′ <lb/> j  &gt; d  j  , which gives us term (ii). <lb/> 1b. Now let G be an arbitrary dual graph. Then the terms in square <lb/>brackets of Equation (5) will appear for each vertex of the graph and their <lb/>sum will still represent the class π <lb/>  *  (G) · ψ <lb/> l+1 <lb/>n+1  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> n+1  (µ). <lb/>The last term of Equation (5) replaces as before, one of the symbols τ  d  j  ,µ  j <lb/> by τ  d  ′ <lb/> j  ,µ  ′ <lb/> j <lb/> . But now this symbol can either correspond to a tail or to a half-<lb/>edge of G. If the symbol we replace corresponds to a tail, it gives rise to <lb/>term (ii) in the proposition. If it corresponds to a half-edge of G, the corre-<lb/>sponding term <lb/> r  l  (τ  d  j  ,µ  j  ) <lb/>  m <lb/>i=1  τ  k  i  +1,1 <lb/> i =j  τ  d  i  ,µ  i <lb/> contributes to term (iii) of <lb/></body>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<body> the proposition. Finally, the third and fourth terms in Equation (4) complete <lb/>the expression for term (iii). <lb/> 2. Now we return to the general case, when n <lb/> ′  and d  1  , . . . , d  n+n  ′  are <lb/>arbitrary. Consider the forgetful maps <lb/> M  g,n+n  ′  +1 <lb/> π  1 <lb/> → M  g,n+n  ′ <lb/> π  2 <lb/> → M  g,n <lb/> and the composition π = π  2  • π  1  . <lb/>If L is our initial linear combination of dual graphs, then L <lb/> ′  = <lb/> π <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (L) <lb/>  n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1  ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  is a well-defined linear combination of dual graphs obtained <lb/>by the usual three steps algorithm, but without attaching the markings µ  i <lb/> to the tails. <lb/>Now we can apply the particular case that we have just proved to the <lb/>linear combination L <lb/> ′  . All we have to do is reinterpret the answer in terms <lb/>of L. We claim the following. <lb/>Term (i) for L <lb/> ′  gives term (i) for L. Indeed, the classes on the moduli <lb/>spaces of curves involved in this term are <lb/> π <lb/>  * <lb/> 1  (L <lb/> ′  ) ψ <lb/> d  n+n ′ +1 <lb/> n+n  ′  +1  = π <lb/>  *  (L) π <lb/>  * <lb/> 1 <lb/>  n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  n+n ′ +1 <lb/> n+n  ′  +1  . <lb/> But since d  n+n  ′  +1  ≥ 2, we have π <lb/>  * <lb/> 1  (ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  )ψ <lb/> d  n+n ′ +1 <lb/> n+n  ′  +1  = ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ψ <lb/> d  n+n ′ +1 <lb/> n+n  ′  +1  on M  g,n+n  ′  +1  . <lb/>Term (ii) for L <lb/> ′  gives term (ii) for L. This is obvious. <lb/>Term (iii) for L <lb/> ′  gives terms (iii), (iv), and (v) for L. Indeed, the space <lb/> D  g,n+n  ′  has two kinds of irreducible components: those that project to a <lb/>component of D  g,n  under π  2  and those that project onto M  g,n  under π  2  . In <lb/>the first case we obtain term (iii) of the proposition. As to the second case, it <lb/>occurs when the generic curve of the component of D  g,n+n  ′  has one component <lb/>of genus g and one component of genus 0 that is contracted by π  2  . The class <lb/> π <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (L) is supported on the genus g component. The contracted component of <lb/>genus 0 contains either 0 or 1 point with markings 1, . . . , n (those that are <lb/>not forgotten by π  2  ). According to these two cases we obtain either term (iv) <lb/>or term (v) from the proposition. <lb/> ♦ <lb/> 5.2 The lower triangular group <lb/> By the action of the upper triangular group we have obtained a Gromov– <lb/>Witten potential that describes the semi-simple Frobenius manifold M that <lb/>we started with. Recall that this Gromov–Witten potential is a power series <lb/>in variables t <lb/> µ <lb/> 1  , t <lb/> µ <lb/> 2  , . . . whose coefficients are functions in variables t <lb/> µ <lb/> 0  analytic <lb/>outside the discriminant of M. <lb/></body>

			<page> 37 <lb/></page>

			<body> Now the action of the lower triangular group re-expands the Gromov– <lb/>Witten potential at a different (possibly non semi-simple) point of M and <lb/>simultaneously incorporates 1-and 2-point genus 0 correlators. <lb/>The element s = <lb/> l≥1  s  l  z <lb/> −l  acts on the partition function Z via the first <lb/>order differential operator <lb/> s = − <lb/> µ <lb/> (s  1  ) <lb/> µ <lb/> 1 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t <lb/> µ <lb/> 0 <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> d,µ <lb/> (s  d+2  )  1,µ  t <lb/> µ <lb/>d  + <lb/> d,l <lb/>µ,ν <lb/> (s  l  ) <lb/> µ <lb/>ν  t <lb/> ν <lb/>d+l <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t <lb/> µ <lb/>d <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> d  1  ,d  2 <lb/> µ  2  ,µ  2 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> d  1  (s  d  1  +d  2  +1  )  µ  1  ,µ  2  t <lb/> µ  1 <lb/> d  1 <lb/> t <lb/> µ  2 <lb/> d  2 <lb/> . <lb/> In this expression we have omitted the term − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> (s  3  )  1,1  . Indeed, it com-<lb/>mutes with all other terms and the action of its exponential only adds the <lb/>constant (s  3  )  1,1  to F  0  . Similarly, in the sequel we will consider F  0  to be de-<lb/>fined up to an additive constant and omit those terms in differential operators <lb/>that do nothing more than changing this constant. <lb/>The following proposition makes the action of s on individual correlators <lb/>explicit. <lb/> Proposition 5.8 ([24], Equations (19),(20)) For 2 − 2g − n &lt; 0, we have <lb/> s. τ  d  1  ,µ  1  . . . τ  dn,µn   g  = <lb/>(6) <lb/> − s  1  (τ  1,1  ) τ  d  1  ,µ  1  . . . τ  dn,µn   g  + <lb/> ∞ <lb/> l=1 <lb/>n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> τ  d  1  ,µ  1  . . . s  l  (τ  d  i  ,µ  i  ) . . . τ  dn,µn   g  . <lb/> If g = 0 and n = 2, we have <lb/> s. τ  d  1  ,µ  1  τ  d  2  ,µ  2   0  = <lb/>(7) <lb/> − s  1  (τ  1,1  ) τ  d  1  ,µ  1  τ  d  2  ,µ  2   0  + <lb/> ∞ <lb/> l=1 <lb/> s  l  (τ  d  1  ,µ  1  )τ  d  2  ,µ  2   0  + τ  d  1  ,µ  1  s  l  (τ  d  2  ,µ  2  )  0 <lb/> + (−1) <lb/> d  1  (s  d  1  +d  2  +1  )  µ  1  µ  2  . <lb/> If g = 0 and n = 1, we have <lb/> s. τ  d,µ   0  = − s  1  (τ  1,1  ) τ  d,µ   0  + <lb/> ∞ <lb/> l=1 <lb/> s  l  (τ  d,µ  )  0  + (s  d+2  )  1µ  . <lb/> (8) <lb/>Looking at Equations (6), (7), (8) we see that s  l  decreases the grading <lb/> d  i  by l, except for the first term involving s  1  (τ  1,1  ). This annoying term <lb/></body>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<body> leads to a problem that we have to discuss in more detail. The corresponding <lb/>term <lb/> u = <lb/> µ <lb/> (s  1  ) <lb/> µ <lb/> 1 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t <lb/> µ <lb/> 0 <lb/> in the differential operator <lb/> s is simply a partial derivative in the direction <lb/> s  1  (1). The exponential exp( u) is then a shift of the coordinates t <lb/> µ <lb/> 0  in this <lb/>direction. A shift of coordinates is not a well-defined operation for formal <lb/>power series. In our case, we consider power series in variables t <lb/> µ <lb/> 1  , t <lb/> µ <lb/> 2  , . . . , <lb/>whose coefficients are analytic in t <lb/> µ <lb/> 0  on the Frobenius manifold except perhaps <lb/>its discriminant. Thus the shift is a well-defined operation, but it can, in <lb/>some cases, lead us out of the realm of power series. In this case the genus <lb/>expansion of the genus 0 Gromov–Witten potential will be a power series in <lb/> t <lb/> µ <lb/> 1  , t <lb/> µ <lb/> 2  , . . . , whose coefficients are analytic functions in t <lb/> µ <lb/> 0  with a singularity at <lb/>the origin. (See, for instance, [6], Section 6, where F and G are the Gromov– <lb/>Witten potentials without descendants for genus 0 and 1 respectively.) <lb/>We also need to give a proper definition of the action of S = exp(s). We <lb/>have, up to omitted constant terms, <lb/>[ s, <lb/> u] = <lb/>1 <lb/> d,µ <lb/> (s  1  s  d+1  )  1,µ  t <lb/> µ <lb/>d  , <lb/> [ s, [ s, <lb/> u]] = <lb/>1 <lb/> l,d,µ <lb/> (s  l  s  1  s  d+1  )  1,µ  t <lb/> µ <lb/>d+l  , <lb/> [ s, [ s, [ s, <lb/> u]]] = <lb/>1 <lb/> l  1  ,l  2  ,d,µ <lb/> (s  l  1  s  l  2  s  1  s  d+1  )  1,µ  t <lb/> µ <lb/>d+l  1  +l  2 <lb/> , <lb/> etc. On the other hand, [ u, [ u,  s]] = 0 (again, up to constant term). Thus, <lb/>according to the Baker–Campbell–Hausdorff formula, we have e <lb/> b <lb/> s  = e <lb/> −b u  e <lb/> b <lb/> v  , <lb/>where <lb/> v = <lb/> u + <lb/> s − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>[ s, <lb/> u] + <lb/>1 <lb/>12 <lb/>[ s, [ s, <lb/> u]] − <lb/> 1 <lb/>720 <lb/>[ s, [ s, [ s, <lb/> u]]] + . . . <lb/> (9) <lb/>= <lb/> d,l <lb/>µ,ν <lb/> (s  l  ) <lb/> µ <lb/>ν  t <lb/> ν <lb/>d+l <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t <lb/> µ <lb/>d <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> d  1  ,d  2 <lb/> µ  2  ,µ  2 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> d  1  (s  d  1  +d  2  +1  )  µ  1  ,µ  2  t <lb/> µ  1 <lb/> d  1 <lb/> t <lb/> µ  2 <lb/> d  2 <lb/> + <lb/> C  d,µ  t <lb/> µ <lb/>d  , <lb/> where every C  d,µ  is a finite polynomial in the matrix elements (s  l  )  µν  . <lb/> Proposition 5.9 For 2 − 2g − n &lt; 0, we have <lb/> v. τ  d  1  ,µ  1  . . . τ  dn,µn   g  = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> l=1 <lb/>n <lb/> i=1 <lb/> τ  d  1  ,µ  1  . . . s  l  (τ  d  i  ,µ  i  ) . . . τ  dn,µn   g  . <lb/> (10) <lb/></body>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<body> If g = 0 and n = 2, we have <lb/> v. τ  d  1  ,µ  1  τ  d  2  ,µ  2   0  = <lb/>(11) <lb/> ∞ <lb/> l=1 <lb/> s  l  (τ  d  1  ,µ  1  )τ  d  2  ,µ  2   0  + τ  d  1  ,µ  1  s  l  (τ  d  2  ,µ  2  )  0 <lb/> + (−1) <lb/> d  1  (s  d  1  +d  2  +1  )  µ  1  µ  2  . <lb/> Remark 5.10 The action of <lb/> v on genus 0 one point correlators involves the <lb/>coefficients C <lb/> µ <lb/>d  and is much more complicated. However it is easy to see that <lb/>such correlators never appear in the induced vectors of tautological relations. <lb/>Therefore the action of  v on them is immaterial to us. <lb/> Lemma 5.11 The action of e <lb/> b <lb/> v  is well-defined on power series; in other <lb/>words, every coefficient in the series e <lb/> b <lb/> v  Z is a finite polynomial in coefficients <lb/>of Z. <lb/> Proof. The action of <lb/> v on a correlator is a polynomial involving correlators <lb/>with strictly smaller <lb/> d  i  and matrix elements of the matrices s  l  . <lb/> ♦ <lb/> Definition 5.12 The action of e <lb/> b <lb/> s  on Z is defined as the action of e <lb/> b <lb/> v  followed <lb/>by a translation of coordinates t <lb/> µ <lb/> 0  by the vector −(s  0  ) <lb/> µ <lb/> 1  . <lb/>To sum up: the same element s of the lower triangular Lie subalgebra <lb/>of Givental&apos;s Lie algebra determines three differential operators: <lb/> s, <lb/> u, and <lb/> v. <lb/> They have the following properties: the action of e <lb/> b <lb/> v  is well-defined on power <lb/>series; the action of e <lb/> b <lb/> u  is a translation of coordinates; we have e <lb/> b <lb/> s  = e <lb/> −b u  e <lb/> b <lb/> v  . <lb/>Now let L be a linear combination of dual graphs of genus g with n tails <lb/>and <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (L) <lb/>  n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1  ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  ) <lb/> g <lb/> an entry of its induced vector. Let s be an <lb/>element of the lower triangular Lie subalgebra of Givental&apos;s Lie algebra and <lb/> v the operator defined by Equation (9). <lb/> Proposition 5.13 The result of the action <lb/> v. <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (L) <lb/> n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  ) <lb/> g <lb/> is a linear combination of polynomials in correlators of the form <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (L) <lb/> n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  ′ <lb/> i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ <lb/> ′ <lb/> i  ) <lb/> g <lb/> (12) <lb/> with d <lb/> ′ <lb/> i  = d  i  , µ <lb/> ′ <lb/> i  = µ  i  for all i except one, while d <lb/> ′ <lb/> i  &lt; d  i  for one i. <lb/></body>

			<page> 40 <lb/></page>

			<body> Corollary 5.14 If the induced vector F  L  vanishes for one formal Gromov– <lb/>Witten potential F then it also vanishes for all potentials that can be obtained <lb/>from F by the action of the lower triangular subgroup of Givental&apos;s group. <lb/> Proof. The polynomials (12) are themselves entries of F  L  . Therefore the <lb/>vector F  L  on the orbit e <lb/> tb v  F is the solution of a linear differential equation <lb/>with vanishing initial conditions. Thus F  L  = 0 on the whole orbit. <lb/>We know that the vanishing of F  L  can be expressed as a family of partial <lb/>differential equations with constant coefficients. These equations are pre-<lb/>served by translations of t <lb/> µ <lb/> 0  . It follows that the condition F  L  = 0 is preserved <lb/>by the action of the lower triangular group. <lb/> ♦ <lb/> Proof of Proposition 5.13. We must compute <lb/> v. <lb/> p <lb/>  *  (L) <lb/> n+n  ′ <lb/> i=1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  i <lb/> i  ev <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (µ  i  ) <lb/> g <lb/> . <lb/> The main element of the proof is the following observation: every contribu-<lb/>tion of the second term in Equation (11) cancels with some contribution of <lb/>the first term in Equations (10) and (11). <lb/>Indeed, recall that in the definition of the induced vector F  L  every half-<lb/>edge and every tail of each graph in L was replaced by a &quot; stick &quot; of several <lb/>edges (Step 2), and then new tails were added in all possible ways to the <lb/>new graphs (Step 3). Consider the linear combination L  3  of graphs obtained <lb/>after Step 3 of the procedure. In L  3  take two graphs Γ  1  and Γ  2  differing only <lb/>in one fragment: <lb/> ψ <lb/> da+d  b  +1 <lb/> ψ <lb/> da <lb/> ψ <lb/> d  b <lb/> Γ  1  = <lb/>Γ  2  = <lb/> I <lb/>I <lb/> Here I ⊂ {n + 1, . . . , n + n <lb/> ′  } is a set of labels of the tails added in Step 3. <lb/>The polynomial P  Γ  1  contains the factor <lb/> Q  Γ  1  = <lb/> τ  da+d  b  +1,µ  b  τ  0,ν  b <lb/> i∈I <lb/> τ  d  i  ,µ  i <lb/> 0 <lb/> . <lb/></body>

			<page> 41 <lb/></page>

			<body> The polynomial P  Γ  2  contains the factor <lb/> Q  Γ  2  = <lb/> µa,νa <lb/> τ  da,µa  τ  0,νa   0  η <lb/> νaµ  b <lb/> τ  d  b  ,µ  b  τ  0,ν  b <lb/> i∈I <lb/> τ  d  i  ,µ  i <lb/> 0 <lb/> . <lb/> Apply the operator  v to the correlator τ  da,µa  τ  0,νa   0  in the expression Q  Γ  2  , <lb/>and take the contribution of the second term in Equation (11). We obtain <lb/>(−1) <lb/> da <lb/> µa,νa <lb/> (s  da+1  )  µaνa  η <lb/> νaµ  b <lb/> τ  d  b  ,µ  b  τ  0,ν  b <lb/> i∈I <lb/> τ  d  i  ,µ  i <lb/> 0 <lb/> = <lb/> s  da+1  (τ  da+d  b  +1,µ  b  ) τ  0,ν  b <lb/> i∈I <lb/> τ  d  i  ,µ  i <lb/> 0 <lb/> . <lb/> But this term is part of the action of <lb/> v on P  Γ  1  . Indeed, it is part of the sum <lb/>in the first term of Equations (10) and (11) applied to <lb/> τ  da+d  b  +1,µ  b  τ  0,ν  b <lb/> i∈I <lb/> τ  d  i  ,µ  i <lb/> 0 <lb/> . <lb/> Since Γ  2  has one edge more than Γ  1  , these terms appear with opposite signs <lb/>in Substitution (1) and hence cancel. <lb/>Let us look at the contributions of the first term of Equations (10) <lb/>and (11) that survived the cancellation. They are exactly those where s  l <lb/> is applied to the symbols τ  d,µ  corresponding to the n + n <lb/> ′  marked points <lb/>and such that l is smaller than or equal to the corresponding d  i  . These <lb/>contributions combine into the expression given in the proposition. <lb/> ♦ <lb/> Proof of Theorem 4. The result follows from Corollaries 5.7 and 5.14. ♦ <lb/> Remark 5.15 Unfortunately, for the time being we cannot prove the impli-<lb/>cation (L is a universal relation) ⇒ (τ  1  (L) is a universal relation). There are <lb/>two reasons for that. First, as explained in Remark 2.18, for not necessarily <lb/>connected graphs checking that Z  τ  1  (L)  = 0 does not imply that τ  1  (L) is a <lb/>universal relation. Second, term (iii) of Proposition 5.5 does not allow us to <lb/>multiply τ  1  (L) by arbitrary powers of ψ  α  and ψ  β  , but only by some of their <lb/>combinations, namely, the classes ρ  k  of Section 3.1. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgements <lb/> The authors are deeply grateful to M. Kazarian for his explanations on Frobe-<lb/>nius manifolds and Givental&apos;s quantization. We thank B. Dubrovin for point-<lb/>ing out the necessity of analyticity conditions on Gromov–Witten potentials. <lb/></div>

			<page>42 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">The third author benefited greatly from a discussion with Tom Coates. We <lb/>also wish to thank the participants of the Moduli Spaces program at the <lb/>Mittag-Leffler Institute (Djursholm, Sweden) for the stimulating atmosphere <lb/>and lots of interesting discussions. We thank the Institute for hospitality and <lb/>support. <lb/>C.F. is supported by the grants 622-2003-1123 from the Swedish Research <lb/>Council and DMS-0600803 from the National Science Foundation and by the <lb/>Göran Gustafsson Foundation for Research in Natural Sciences and Medicine. <lb/>D.Z. is partly supported by the ANR project &quot; Geometry and Integrability in <lb/>Mathematical Physics &quot; ANR-05-BLAN-0029-01. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>  References <lb/> [1] D. Abramovich, T. J. Jarvis. Moduli of twisted spin curves. – Comm. <lb/>in Alg. 31 (2003), 3547–3618, math.AG/0104154. <lb/> [2] K. Behrend, B. Fantechi. The intrinsic normal cone. – Invent. Math. <lb/> 128 (1997), no. 1, 45–88, alg-geom/9601010. <lb/> [3] L. Caporaso, C. Casagrande, M. Cornalba. Moduli of roots of line <lb/>bundles of curves. – Trans. Amer. Math. Soc. 359 (2007), no. 8, 3733– <lb/>3768 (electronic), math.AG/0404078. <lb/> [4] A. Chiodo. Stable twisted curves and their r-spin structures. – <lb/> math.AG/0603687. <lb/> [5] A. Chiodo. The Witten top Chern class via K-theory. – J. Algebraic <lb/>Geom. 15 (2006), no. 4, 681–707, math.AG/0210398. <lb/> [6] B. Dubrovin, Y. Zhang. Bihamiltonian hierarchies in 2D topologi-<lb/>cal field theory at one-loop approximation. – Comm. Math. Phys. 198 <lb/> (1998), arXiv:hep-th/9712232. <lb/> [7] C. Faber, R. Pandharipande. Relative maps and tautological classes. <lb/> – J. Eur. Math. Soc. 7 (2005), 13–49, math.AG/0304485. <lb/> [8] A. Givental. Gromov–Witten invariants and quantization of quadratic <lb/>hamiltonians. – In &quot; Frobenius manifolds &quot; , 91–112, Aspects Math., E36, <lb/>Vieweg, Wiesbaden, 2004, math.AG/0108100. <lb/> [9] A. Givental. A  n−1  singularities and nKdV hierarchies. – Mosc. Math. <lb/>J. 3 (2003), no. 2, 475–505 and 743, math.AG/0209205. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 43 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [10] A. Givental. Symplectic geometry of Frobenius structures. – Mosc. <lb/>Math. J. 1 (2001), no. 4, 551–568 and 645, math.AG/0305409. <lb/> [11] A. Givental. Semisimple Frobenius structures at higher genus. – Inter-<lb/>nat. Math. Res. Notices 2001, no. 23, 1265–1286, math.AG/0008067. <lb/> [12] T. Graber, R. Pandharipande. Constructions of nontautological <lb/>classes on moduli spaces of curves. – Michigan Math. J. 51 (2003), no. 1, <lb/>93–109, math.AG/0104057. <lb/> [13] T. Graber, R. Vakil. On the tautological ring of M  g,n  . – Turkish J. <lb/>Math. 25 (2001), no. 1, 237–243, math.AG/0011100. <lb/> [14] E.-N. Ionel. Topological Recursive Relations in H <lb/> 2g  (M  g,n  ). – Invent. <lb/>Math., 148 (2002), no. 3, 627–658, math.AG/9908060. <lb/> [15] T. J. Jarvis. Geometry of the moduli of higher spin curves. – Internat. <lb/>J. Math. 11 (2000), 637–663, math.AG/9809138. <lb/> [16] T. J. Jarvis, T. Kimura, A. Vaintrob. Moduli Spaces of Higher <lb/>Spin Curves and Integrable Hierarchies. – Compositio Math. 126 (2001), <lb/>no. 2, 157–212, math.AG/9905034. <lb/> [17] T. J. Jarvis, T. Kimura, A. Vaintrob. Tensor products of Frobenius <lb/>manifolds and moduli spaces of higher spin curves. – Conférence Moshé <lb/>Flato 1999, Vol. II (Dijon), 145–166, Math. Phys. Stud., 22, Kluwer <lb/>Acad. Publ., Dordrecht, 2000, math.AG/9911029. <lb/> [18] T. J. Jarvis, T. Kimura, A. Vaintrob. Gravitational Descendants <lb/>and the Moduli Space of Higher Spin Curves. – Advances in algebraic <lb/>geometry motivated by physics (Lowell, MA, 2000), 167–177, Contemp. <lb/>Math., 276, Amer. Math. Soc., Providence, RI, 2001, math.AG/0009066. <lb/> [19] T. J. Jarvis, T. Kimura, A. Vaintrob. Spin Gromov–Witten <lb/>invariants. – Comm. Math. Phys. 259 (2005), no. 3, 511–543, <lb/> math.AG/0012210. <lb/> [20] M. Kontsevich. Intersection theory on the moduli space of curves and <lb/>the matrix Airy function. – Comm. Math. Phys. 147 (1992), 1–23. <lb/>[21] Y.-P. Lee. Witten&apos;s conjecture, Virasoro conjecture, and invariance of <lb/>tautological equations. – math.AG/0311100. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 44 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [22] Y.-P. Lee. Witten&apos;s conjecture and Virasoro conjecture for genus up <lb/>to two. – Gromov–Witten theory of spin curves and orbifolds, 31– <lb/>42, Contemp. Math., 403, Amer. Math. Soc., Providence, RI, 2006, <lb/> math.AG/0310442. <lb/> [23] Y.-P. Lee. Invariance of tautological equations I: conjectures and ap-<lb/>plications. – J. Eur. Math. Soc. (JEMS) 10 (2008), no. 2, 399–413. <lb/> math.AG/0604318. <lb/> [24] Y.-P. Lee. Invariance of tautological equations II: Gromov–Witten the-<lb/>ory. – math.AG/0605708, 26 pp. <lb/>[25] Y.-P. Lee, R. Pandharipande. Frobenius manifolds, Gromov– <lb/>Witten theory, and Virasoro constraints. – www.math.princeton.edu/ <lb/>~rahulp/Part1.ps and .../Part2.ps. <lb/> [26] J. Li, G. Tian. Virtual moduli cycles and Gromov–Witten invariants <lb/>of algebraic varieties. – J. Amer. Math. Soc. 11 (1998), no. 1, 119–174, <lb/> alg-geom/9602007. <lb/> [27] T. Mochizuki. The virtual class of the moduli stack of stable r-spin <lb/> curves. – Comm. Math. Phys. 264 (2006), no. 1, 1–40. <lb/>[28] D. Mumford. Towards an enumerative geometry of the moduli space of <lb/>curves. – In &quot; Arithmetic and Geometry &quot; , vol. II, 271–328, Progr. Math., <lb/> 36, M. Artin, J. Tate eds, Birkhäuser Boston, MA, 1983. <lb/>[29] R. Pandharipande. Three questions in Gromov–Witten theory. – Pro-<lb/>ceedings of the International Congress of Mathematicians, Vol. II (Bei-<lb/>jing, 2002), 503–512, Higher Ed. Press, Beijing, 2002, math.AG/0302077. <lb/> [30] A. Polishchuk. Witten&apos;s top Chern class on the moduli space of higher <lb/>spin curves. Frobenius manifolds, 253–264, Aspects Math., E36, Vieweg, <lb/>Wiesbaden, 2004, math.AG/0208112. <lb/> [31] A. Polishchuk, A. Vaintrob. Algebraic construction of Witten&apos;s top <lb/>Chern class. – &quot; Advances in algebraic geometry motivated by physics &quot; , <lb/>(Lowell, MA, 2000), 229–250, Contemp. Math. 276, Ed. E. Previato, <lb/>AMS, Providence, RI, (2001), math.AG/0011032. <lb/> [32] S. Shadrin. Geometry of meromorphic functions and intersections on <lb/>moduli spaces of curves. – Int. Math. Res. Not. 2003, no. 38, 2051–2094, <lb/> math.AG/0209282. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 45 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [33] S. Shadrin. Intersections in genus 3 and the Boussinesq hierarchy. Lett. <lb/>Math. Phys. 65 (2003), no. 2, 125–131, math.AG/0307326. <lb/> [34] S. Shadrin, D. Zvonkine. Intersection numbers with Witten&apos;s <lb/>top Chern class. Geom. Topol. 12 (2008), no. 2, 713–745, – <lb/> math.AG/0601075. <lb/> [35] B. Siebert. Virtual fundamental classes, global normal cones and Ful-<lb/>ton&apos;s canonical classes. – in &quot; Frobenius manifolds &quot; , 341–358, Aspects <lb/>Math., E36, Vieweg, Wiesbaden, 2004, math.AG/0509076. <lb/> [36] C. Teleman. The structure of 2D semi-simple field theories. – <lb/> arXiv:0712.0160, 28 pp. <lb/>[37] E. Witten. Algebraic geometry associated with matrix models of two-<lb/>dimensional gravity. – &quot; Topological methods in modern mathematics &quot; <lb/>(Stony Brook, NY, 1991), 235–269, Publish or Perish, Houston, TX <lb/>(1993). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>46 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
