<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> BLED WORKSHOPS <lb/> IN  PHYSICS <lb/>VOL. 3, NO. 3 <lb/> Proceedins of the Mini-Workshop <lb/> Quarks and hadrons (p. 7) <lb/> Bled, Slovenia, July 7-14, 2002 <lb/> Effective U  A  (1) symmetry breaking interactions <lb/> V. Dmitrašinovi´ <lb/> Vinˇča Institute of Nuclear Sciences, P.O.Box 522, 11001 Beograd, Yugoslavia <lb/> Abstract. We review the phenomenological consequences of various effective U  A  (1) sym-<lb/>metry breaking interactions. In particular we look at the baryon spectra. We comment on <lb/>the recent conjecture that the chiral symmetry might be restored in the higher regions of <lb/>hadron spectra in the light of our results for scalar mesons and the spectral sum rules. <lb/> The so-called &quot; U  A  (1) problem &quot; consists of (i) the fact that the sum of the <lb/>eighth and ninth pseudoscalar meson η(550), η <lb/>  (960) masses lies (far) above the <lb/>flavour SU(3) mass relations prediction of two kaon masses (2 m  K  ) and (ii) that <lb/>their mixing angle is far from being the &quot; ideal &quot; one. These two facts imply a large <lb/> explicit U  A  (1) symmetry breaking, that is believed to be induced by instantons <lb/>in QCD. These instanton effects can be described by &apos;t Hooft&apos;s U  A  (1)-symmetry <lb/> breaking quark flavour determinant effective interaction [1] <lb/> L <lb/> (6) <lb/> tH  = −K  tH <lb/>  det <lb/> ¯ <lb/> ψ(1 + γ  5  )ψ <lb/> + det <lb/> ¯ <lb/> ψ(1 − γ  5  )ψ <lb/> = −2K  tH  e <lb/> det ¯ <lb/> ψ(1 + γ  5  )ψ <lb/> . <lb/> (1) <lb/>Phenomenological consequences of the determinant effective interaction in spin-<lb/>less meson channels of either parity have been studied in Ref. [2], where new <lb/>effects for the scalar mesons were reported. In the same place the strength K of <lb/>the &apos;t Hooft interaction was also fixed in terms of the pseudoscalar (PS) meson <lb/>properties as <lb/> −12K  tH  ¯ <lb/> qq <lb/> 3  = f <lb/> 2 <lb/>η <lb/> m <lb/> 2 <lb/>η   + m <lb/> 2 <lb/>η  − 2m <lb/> 2 <lb/>K <lb/> . <lb/> (2) <lb/>Equivalent results for scalar mesons have been reported in Ref. [3] using directly <lb/>the instanton-induced (II) interaction with a finite spatial range. <lb/>There is another U  A  (1) symmetry breaking effective interaction that is pro-<lb/>portional to the squared imaginary part of the determinant <lb/> L <lb/> (12) <lb/> VW  = K  VW <lb/>  det <lb/> ¯ <lb/> ψ(1 + γ  5  )ψ <lb/> − det <lb/> ¯ <lb/> ψ(1 − γ  5  )ψ <lb/>  2 <lb/> = −4K  VW <lb/> mdet ¯ <lb/> ψ(1 + γ  5  )ψ <lb/>  2  . <lb/> (3) <lb/>as well as the analogues of the above two with antisymmetric Pauli tensors in-<lb/>serted between the Dirac spinors [4]. <lb/></front>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> V. Dmitrašinovi´ <lb/></note>

			<body> 1 Mesons <lb/> The role of U  A  (1) symmetry breaking in meson spectra has been extensively stud-<lb/>ied over the past 10 years [2–7]; a brief review of the field can be found in Ref. <lb/>[8]. There scalar meson spectra and the V -A spectral sum rules were discussed. <lb/>Considering the fact that the recent parity-doubling/chiral symmetry restoration <lb/>(χSR) conjecture [9] uses several methods and/or results obtained or used in the <lb/>aforementioned studies, this seems like a good place to make several comments <lb/>of direct relevance to this conjecture, rather than to review again some established <lb/>facts. This is by no means to be understood as a polemic, but rather as a part of <lb/>an academic dialogue: It is an observation on matters not discussed by Glozman <lb/>that could potentially have serious implications for the viability of this idea. <lb/>1. An explicit counterexample to the claim that asymptotic restoration of chi-<lb/>ral SU  L  (N  f  ) × SU  R  (N  f  ) symmetry implies parity doubling in meson spectra <lb/>is the original form of the second Weinberg sum rule: Even with as strong <lb/>an assumption as the vanishing of the zeroth moment of the spectral den-<lb/>sity difference (that later proved to be false in QCD), Weinberg still had to <lb/>assume another ( &quot; KSFR &quot; ) relation (connecting the widths of the vector and <lb/>axial-vector states) before he could turn his assumption into a prediction of <lb/>the vector/axial-vector meson mass ratio (that turned out to be 1/ <lb/> √ <lb/> 2 rather <lb/>than unity, as conjectured by Glozman!). Now, one may object that these are <lb/>only the ground state mesons, that are not subject of the χSR conjecture. But, <lb/>as one increases the number of states in the spectra, the number of new &quot; ra-<lb/>dially excited state KSFR &quot; relations, that are necessary to calculate the V/A <lb/>mass ratios, also grows. Clearly, more is necessary for parity doubling of vec-<lb/>tor (V) and axial-vector (A) mesons than mere asymptotic equality of spec-<lb/>tral functions. If that were not enough, it has been shown [4] that the second <lb/>spectral sum rule is not only sensitive to SU  L  (N  f  ) × SU  R  (N  f  ) chiral symme-<lb/>try breaking (χSB), but rather to nonconservation of the &quot; larger &quot; (enveloping) <lb/> U  L  (2N  f  ) × U  R  (2N  f  ) current algebra. Thus, one may have χSR and still have a <lb/>nonvanishing second spectral sum. In other words, spectral functions do not <lb/> depend only on chiral symmetry, as assumed by Glozman, but also on higher <lb/>current algebras. <lb/>2. Technical objections to the way U  A  (1) symmetry breaking was treated. (i) <lb/> U  A  (1) symmetry breaking depends (sensitively) on the number of (light) fla-<lb/>vours, c.f. Ref. [2]. Glozman uses two-flavour mass formulas for &quot; realistic &quot; <lb/>purposes (to compare with experimental spectra), instead of the three flavour <lb/>ones. This is inadmissible and only hides other shortcomings of this scheme: <lb/>(a) Too few flavour singlets are predicted: some observed states must be as-<lb/>signed to glueballs, so it is not clear which states are radial excitations; (b) not <lb/>all of the suggested mass differences may serve as measure of U  A  (1) symme-<lb/>try breaking: In this regard we have shown in Ref. [6] that the scalar meson <lb/>mass difference may vanish even with &apos;t Hooft force turned on, depending <lb/>on the strength of the vector/axial-vector interaction, i.e. on the admixing of <lb/>pseudo-vector component to the pseudoscalar mesons. (ii) An oversimplified <lb/>assignment of mesons to chiral symmetry irreducible representations (irreps) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Effective U  A  (1) symmetry breaking interactions <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body> has been made in Ref. [9]: mixings of pseudoscalar (PS) and axial vector (A), <lb/>scalar (S) and vector (V), V and tensor (T), A and pseudotensor (PT) have been <lb/>ignored. As we have shown in Ref. [6], mixing of PS and A mesons substan-<lb/>tially changes the scalar meson mass difference that was used as a measure <lb/>of U  A  (1) symmetry restoration by Glozman. Indeed the said mass difference <lb/>can be made arbitrarily close to zero, even in the presence of U  A  (1) symmetry <lb/>breaking interaction, by means of changing the amount of the PS-A mixing. <lb/>Other mixings, mentioned above, may well have similarly dramatic effects. <lb/>3. Objections to the identification procedure for chiral multiplets. Even if the <lb/>experimental interpretation in Ref. [9] were correct, the conclusion that chiral <lb/>symmetry restoration-induced parity doublets have already been observed <lb/>would still be invalid. Rather, the &quot; observed &quot; parity doubling would be purely <lb/>accidental. This is so because members of different chiral multiplets have been <lb/>compared (see below) in Glozman&apos;s putative scheme [9]. That is, of course, in-<lb/>admissible: chiral restoration implies parity doubling within the same chiral <lb/>multiplet, not among members of two different multiplets (which doubling <lb/>may indeed occur, but only due to random coincidence) [10]. In a logically <lb/>consistent check of chiral restoration one must first positively identify the <lb/>purported members of chiral multiplets going from the bottom up, i.e. start-<lb/>ing with the ground state and then matching corresponding excited states. <lb/>One must not start at some high-lying set of (accidental) parity doublets and <lb/>then move down until one arbitrarily declares victory and all states lying be-<lb/>low that arbitrary line as being beyond the reach of the conjecture, as was <lb/>done in Ref. [9]. As one moves down in mass from the alleged parity doubled <lb/>chiral partners in Glozman&apos;s proposed scheme, one finds that some chiral <lb/>multiplets are incomplete: for example, the (well established) π(1300) state <lb/>does not have a scalar partner in the observed spectrum, according to Gloz-<lb/>man&apos;s scheme. This proves that a misidentification of chiral multiplets has <lb/>taken place, which fact negates all claims relating to chiral symmetry restora-<lb/>tion in meson spectra at high masses. <lb/> 2 Baryons <lb/> More recently, significant effects due to the instanton-induced interaction have <lb/>been reported in baryon spectroscopy [11]. In this note we wish to give a simple <lb/>explanation of the &apos;t Hooft quark flavour-determinant effective interaction&apos;s ef-<lb/>fects in baryon spectroscopy. We confirm the results of earlier studies [11], with <lb/>one distinction: we have no free parameters to adjust in our calculation because <lb/>we take the value of the &apos;t Hooft coupling constant K as constrained above by the <lb/>meson spectra. <lb/>The effective two-body &apos;t Hooft interaction leads to the following two-quark <lb/>potential <lb/> V  12  = 4K ¯ <lb/> qq  0  P <lb/> ¯ <lb/> 3 <lb/>12 <lb/> 1 + γ <lb/> 5 <lb/> 1  γ <lb/> 5 <lb/> 2 <lb/> δ(r  1  − r  2  ) <lb/> P <lb/> ¯ <lb/> 3 <lb/>12  = <lb/> 1 <lb/>3 <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>4 <lb/> λ  1  · λ  2 <lb/> . <lb/> (4) <lb/></body>

			<page> 10 <lb/> </page> 

			<note place="headnote"> V. Dmitrašinovi´ <lb/></note>
			
			<body> The flavour dependence of this potential is proportional to the ¯ <lb/> 3 projection oper-<lb/>ator P <lb/> ¯ <lb/> 3 <lb/> 12  , i.e., it only operates in the flavour antisymmetric state. Note, however, <lb/>that in the q ¯ <lb/> q channels the same flavour factor is not exactly a flavour singlet pro-<lb/>jector any more. <lb/>The &apos;t Hooft interaction also leads to the following three-quark potential <lb/> V  123  = 12KP <lb/> 1 <lb/>123 <lb/>  <lb/>  1 + <lb/> 3 <lb/> i&lt;j <lb/> γ <lb/> 5 <lb/> i  γ <lb/> 5 <lb/> j <lb/>  <lb/> δ(r  1  − r  2  )δ(r  3  − r  2  ) <lb/> 12P <lb/> 1 <lb/>123  = <lb/>  <lb/> 4 <lb/>9 <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>3 <lb/> 3 <lb/> i&lt;j <lb/> λ  i  · λ  j  + d <lb/> abc  λ <lb/> a <lb/>1  λ <lb/> b <lb/>2  λ <lb/> c <lb/>3 <lb/>  <lb/> . <lb/> (5) <lb/>As can be seen from Eq. (5) the flavour dependence of the &apos;t Hooft three-quark <lb/>potential is just the flavour SU(3) singlet projection operator P <lb/> 1 <lb/>123  [8] for three <lb/>quarks. Thus the &apos;t Hooft three-quark potential contributes only in the flavour <lb/>singlet q <lb/> 3 <lb/> channel, as already noticed in Ref. [11]. As the lowest lying flavour <lb/>singlet is necessarily a P-wave state (due to the Pauli principle) and the spatial <lb/>part of the three-body potential Eq. (5) contains two Dirac delta functions, its <lb/>matrix element is zero. <lb/>We use the constituent quark model [12] with the harmonic oscillator Hamil-<lb/>tonian to calculate the basic effects of the &apos;t Hooft interaction. This model is clearly <lb/>rather simple, but should be adequate for the purpose of identifying the qual-<lb/>itative features and making first estimates of the &apos;t Hooft interaction effects in <lb/>baryons. In the following we shall keep only the leading-order (O(1)) terms in <lb/>the nonrelativistic [NR] expansion, i.e. we do not keep the spin dependent parts. <lb/>In this spirit we have also neglected the strong-hyperfine ( &quot; Breit &quot; ) interaction in <lb/>the constituent quark Hamiltonian [12], that is believed to be an important part of <lb/>the (extended) constituent quark model, but that also suffers from several short-<lb/>comings, an excessively large coupling constant being one. We shall show that <lb/>some of the best known effects associated with the strong Breit force are repro-<lb/>duced by the &apos;t Hooft interaction. <lb/>With these assumptions we can calculate the three-quark system spectra in <lb/>different flavour channels. But as the &apos;t Hooft potential is a contact term, one can-<lb/>not separate the resulting Schr ödinger equation exactly. So, we must use some <lb/>approximate method, e.g. perturbation theory. We find the following &apos;t Hooft po-<lb/>tential flavour space matrix elements <lb/> V  1  = 12K ¯ <lb/> qq  0  δ(r  1  − r  2  )  1 <lb/> (6) <lb/> V  8  = 6K ¯ <lb/> qq  0  δ(r  1  − r  2  )  8 <lb/> (7) <lb/> V  10  = 0 <lb/> (8) <lb/>The reason for the last line is that the flavour singlet 1 three-quark system can-<lb/>not have a completely symmetric spin-spatial wave function, the way the ground <lb/>state octet and decimet do, due to the Pauli principle and the complete antisym-<lb/>metry of the singlet&apos;s flavour-and colour wave functions. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Effective U  A  (1) symmetry breaking interactions <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body> Fig. 1. Baryon mass spectrum as calculated in the nonrelativistic quark model with har-<lb/>monic oscillator confinement without (K = 0) and with (K  = 0) &apos;tHooft interaction for the <lb/>two lowest lying shells (N = 0,1); the prediction for the Roper resonance (N = 2) is not <lb/>shown. Also shown are the observed baryon states (expt). <lb/> In the first approximation with all spin-spin interactions neglected, <lb/> Ψ  S  (N = 0)|δ(r  1  − r  2  )|Ψ  S  (N = 0) = δ(r  1  − r  2  )  8⊂56  = δ(r  1  − r  2  )  10⊂56 <lb/> ≡ I = <lb/> m  q  ω <lb/> √ <lb/> 2π <lb/>  3/2 <lb/> (9) <lb/> Ψ  P  (N = 1)|δ(r  1  − r  2  )|Ψ  P  (N = 1) = δ(r  1  − r  2  )  1⊂70  = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> M <lb/> ψ <lb/> λ <lb/>1M  |δ(r  1  − r  2  )|ψ <lb/> λ <lb/>1M  <lb/> = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>I = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> m  q  ω <lb/> √ <lb/> 2π <lb/>  3/2 <lb/> (10) <lb/> Ψ <lb/> S  (N = 2)|δ(r  1  − r  2  )|Ψ <lb/> S  (N = 2) = δ(r  1  − r  2  )  8⊂56 <lb/> = <lb/> 5 <lb/>4 <lb/>I = <lb/> 5 <lb/>4 <lb/> m  q  ω <lb/> √ <lb/> 2π <lb/>  3/2 <lb/> , <lb/> (11) <lb/>where ω= 500 MeV is the oscillator frequency in the model, and the constituent <lb/>quark mass, m  q  = 313MeV, is approximately one third of the nucleon&apos;s. Thus we <lb/>find the following energy shifts <lb/> δE  1⊂70  (N = 1) = δE  8⊂56  (N = 0) = 6K ¯ <lb/> qq  0  I <lb/> (12) <lb/></body>

			<page> 12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> V. Dmitrašinovi´ <lb/></note>

			<body> δE  8⊂70  (N = 1) = 3K ¯ <lb/> qq  0  I <lb/> (13) <lb/> δE  8⊂56  (N = 2) = <lb/> 15 <lb/>2 <lb/>K ¯ <lb/> qq  0  I <lb/> (14) <lb/> δE  10  = 0. <lb/> (15) <lb/>Inserting into Eq. (2) the experimental value for the ps meson masses and decay <lb/>constants, as well as the quark condensate  ¯ <lb/> qq = −(225MeV) <lb/> 3 <lb/> , the &apos;t Hooft cou-<lb/>pling constant becomes K = 390GeV <lb/> −5  , we find the baryon spectrum shown in <lb/>Fig. 1. The second radially excited state (the Roper resonance) mass moves down <lb/>by about 130MeV, but is still too large to be visible in Fig. 1. There one can see that <lb/>about one third of the observed positive parity ground state 8 − 10 mass splitting <lb/>and about one half of the observed negative parity 1 − 10 mass splitting are repro-<lb/>duced by &apos;t Hooft interaction. Admittedly, one cannot describe the fine structure <lb/>(LS splitting) of the spectra (as yet), but that ought to be possible with the inclu-<lb/>sion of spin-dependent forces. In particular these results show that &apos;t Hooft&apos;s in-<lb/>teraction causes a significant part (at least a half) of the Λ  0  (1405) and Λ  0  (1520)&apos;s <lb/>mass shifts to anomalously low masses compared with other P-wave baryons. <lb/>[Remember that N <lb/>  *  (1535) and N <lb/>  *  (1520) ought to be about 130 MeV lighter than <lb/>the corresponding Λ  0  &apos;s, due to one strange quark in the latter, in the absence of <lb/>&apos;t Hooft&apos;s interaction.] This mass shift was first pointed out in Ref. [11]. Finally, <lb/>the mystery of the Roper resonance&apos;s abnormally low mass now seems within the <lb/>reach of rational explanation starting from QCD. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. G. &apos;t Hooft, Phys. Rev. D 14, 3432 (1976), (E) ibid. 18, 2199 (1978); <lb/>2. V. Dmitrašinovi´ , Phys. Rev. C 53, 1383 (1996). <lb/>3. E. Klempt, B. C. Metsch, C. R. M ¨ <lb/>unz, and H. R. Petry, Phys. Lett. B 361, 160 (1995). <lb/>4. V. Dmitrašinovi´ , Phys. Rev. D 56, 247 (1997). <lb/>5. V. Dmitrašinovi´ , Phys. Rev. D 57, 7019 (1998). <lb/>6. V. Dmitrašinovi´ , Nucl. Phys. A 686, 377 (2001). <lb/>7. V. Dmitrašinovi´ , Phys. Rev. D 62, 096010(8) (2000). <lb/>8. V. Dmitrašinovi´ , p. 46 -53 in &quot; Hadrons and Nuclei: First International Symposium &quot; , <lb/>AIP Conf. Proc. 594; ed. I-T. Cheon, T. Choi, S.-W. Hong and S.H. Lee, American Insti-<lb/>tute of Physics, Melville, N.Y., (2001). <lb/>9. L. Ya. Glozman, hep-ph/0205072 and these proceedings. <lb/>10. D. Jido, Y. Nemoto, M.Oka and A. Hosaka, Nucl. Phys. A 671, 471 (2000). <lb/>11. U. L ¨ <lb/>oring, B.Ch. Metsch, and H.R. Petry,Eur. Phys. J. A 10, 395 (2001); ibid.A 10, 447 <lb/>(2001). <lb/>12. A. Le Yaouanc, L L. Oliver, O. P` ene and J.-C. Raynal, Hadron Transitions in the Quark <lb/>Model, (Gordon and Breach, New York, 1988). </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
