<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> BLED WORKSHOPS <lb/> IN  PHYSICS <lb/>VOL. 4, NO. 1 <lb/> Proceedings of the Mini-Workshop <lb/> Effective q-q Interaction (p. 19) <lb/> Bled, Slovenia, July 7-14, 2003 <lb/> Scalar mesons in the Gaussian approximation <lb/>to the linear  odel <lb/> V. Dmitrašinovi´ <lb/> Vinˇča Institute (Lab 010), P.O.Box 522, 11001 Belgrade <lb/> Abstract. I report on recent progress in our understanding of the bosonic sector of the <lb/>linear sigma model in the nonperturbative Gaussian wave functional approximation, ac-<lb/>complished in collaboration with I. Nakamura. We have proven a number of chiral Ward-<lb/>Takahashi identities, such as the Nambu-Goldstone theorem and axial current conserva-<lb/>tion in the Gaussian approximation to these models. The particle content of the models is <lb/>elucidated with particular emphasis on the question of multiple states in the scalar chan-<lb/>nel. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> One of the most persistent problems in hadron spectroscopy is that of the low-<lb/>lying scalar mesons: there are too many of them and they do not fit into the <lb/>flavour singlet + octet pattern. It is clear from the P-wave meson LS splitting that <lb/>the lightest scalars (f  0  (980) and a  0  (980)) are too light to be q ¯ <lb/> q states. The only <lb/>plausible alternative is that they are (q ¯ <lb/> q) <lb/> 2 <lb/> states, either as (a) resonances/bound <lb/>states of two ordinary q ¯ <lb/> q (pseudoscalar) mesons, or (b) related to &quot; hidden-colour &quot; <lb/> (q ¯ <lb/> q) <lb/> 2 <lb/> states embedded in the ordinary two-meson continuum. <lb/>In this talk we concentrate on class (a) models. Even within this class a large <lb/>number of different strategies and models have been used, some of them non-<lb/>relativistic and nonchiral. As the masses of scalar mesons are at least twice those <lb/>of their &quot; constituent &quot; pseudoscalars, we believe that relativity and chiral sym-<lb/>metry are indispensable in this problem. Moreover, unitarity, causality and non-<lb/>perturbative nature of the approximation all seem to be a must in this problem <lb/>(similarity to the &quot; bootstrap &quot; program is not accidental). <lb/>Within the class of relativistic chiral models there are (at least) two options: <lb/>(i) linear, and (ii) nonlinear realization models. [There is also the older calcula-<lb/>tion of T ¨ <lb/>ornqvist [1] that does not specify a Lagrangian.] In either approach it is <lb/>important to have a clear criterion for the differentiation between the underly-<lb/>ing ( &quot; bare &quot; ) q ¯ <lb/> q states and the ( &quot; composite &quot; ) (q ¯ <lb/> q) <lb/> 2 <lb/> states with identical quantum <lb/>numbers, even if it is defined in some perhaps unusual limit. Models of type (ii) <lb/>have recently been constructed, most notably by the Syracuse, N.Y. and two Span-<lb/>ish groups [2–4]. These calculations display many interesting features, but suffer <lb/>from all the usual difficulties of nonlinear models, and a few that are specific to <lb/>the nonperturbative nature of their approximation. <lb/></body>

			<page> 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> V. Dmitrašinovi´ <lb/></note>

			<body> We shall take the route (i). As the scalar fields are the chiral partners of the <lb/>pseudoscalar mesons in a linearly realized chiral symmetry, it has long been sus-<lb/>pected that the scalar meson problem is related to linear realization of chiral sym-<lb/>metry. The open question is: how does one implement a consistent Lorentz invari-<lb/>ant, unitary, causal and chirally symmetric approximation to such models that <lb/>can also describe bound states? The very existence of such an approximation, let <lb/>alone its technical details, was not known until recently. A solution to this prob-<lb/>lem that has all the required properties was found in a little known variational <lb/>approach to QFT, called the Gaussian wave functional approximation, which also <lb/>happens to be an answer to the old meson &quot; bootstrap &quot; problem, albeit within <lb/>field theory. This solution &quot; dresses &quot; the underlying ( &quot; fundamental &quot; ) mesons with <lb/> &quot; meson cloud &quot; , which in turn changes their properties to such an extent that they <lb/>cannot be recognized as the original Nambu-Goldstone [NG] particles any more. <lb/>The NG particles become two-body bound states of the dressed mesons. <lb/>In the following we give a short introduction to this method and discuss <lb/>its implementation in the two-flavour linear sigma model of Gell-Mann—Levy <lb/>[5]. This model has been derived ( &quot; bosonized &quot; ) [6] from the NJL chiral quark <lb/>model which includes the QCD instanton-induced &apos;t Hooft quark (self)interaction <lb/>[7], with all the free parameters/coupling constants determined. Thus the boson <lb/>fields correspond to (bare) q ¯ <lb/> q bound states. <lb/> 2 Basics of the Gaussian variational method <lb/> This variational method is based on the minimization of the ground state&apos;s [g.s.] <lb/>energy density  0  =  0  (m  i  ; ffi  i  ) (for infinite homogeneous systems) with respect <lb/>to the variational parameters m  i  ; ffi  i  . The g.s. energy is evaluated with a Gaussian <lb/>Ansatz [8,9] for the g.s. wave functional j¯  0  , which, in a theory with N scalar <lb/>fields like the sigma model, is a function of 2N variational parameters (the fields&apos; <lb/>masses and v.e.v.s) (m  i  ; ffi  i  ); i (1; :::; N), i.e., j¯  0  = j¯  0  (m  i  ; ffi  i  ) , <lb/> E  0  (m  i  ; ffi  i  ) = ¯  0  j H j ¯  0  ¯  0  j¯  0 <lb/> -1  ; <lb/> in the Schroedinger representation of QFT. Similarly one can construct one-, two-, <lb/>..., n-body states and minimize their energies. Of course, only few-body states are <lb/>amenable to practical applications. The 2N vacuum energy minimization/statio-<lb/>narity equations <lb/> @  0  (m  i  ; ffi  i  ) <lb/> @ ffi  i <lb/>min <lb/> = 0 = <lb/> @  0  (m  i  ; ffi  i  ) <lb/> @m  i <lb/>min <lb/> ; i = 0; : : : 3 ; <lb/> turn out to have a Feynman diagrammatic interpretation as (truncated) Schwinger-<lb/>Dyson [SD] equations for the one-and two-point Green functions [10], i.e. for the <lb/>equations determining the vacuum and single particle properties. (The truncation <lb/>in question is a consequence of the approximate nature of the Gaussian Ansatz, <lb/>and it implies elimination of the two-loop O(h <lb/> 2  ) diagrams from their respective <lb/>SD equations.) This should not have been a surprise as the minimized &quot; vacuum &quot; <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Scalar mesons in the Gaussian approximation to the linear  odel <lb/></note>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body> energy density  0  (m  i  ; ffi  i  )  min  is (up to an additive constant) also the Gaussian <lb/>approximation effective potential <lb/> V  eff  (ffi  i  ) =  0  (m  i  ; ffi  i  )  min  - 0  (m  i  ; ffi  i  = 0) <lb/> with all its usual properties, in particular its being the generating function of <lb/>the one-particle irreducible Green functions at vanishing external momenta. This <lb/>means that derivatives of the effective potential yield higher order Green func-<lb/>tions [11], the &quot; only &quot; problem being a positive identification of SD eqs., i.e., of <lb/>Feynman diagrams from the corresponding analytic expressions. In other words, <lb/>there should be no ambiguity as to which Feynman diagrams enter the GA equa-<lb/>tions of motion. The practical significance of this fact will become clear only when <lb/>the GA is applied to linear sigma models. <lb/> 3 Application to the linear  odel <lb/> The linear sigma model of Gell-Mann and Levy is the simplest one so we shall <lb/>consider it first. It is an O(4) symmetric ffi <lb/> 4 <lb/> (pseudo)scalar field theory with the <lb/>Lagrangian <lb/> = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> (@  —  ffi) <lb/> 2  - V(ffi <lb/> 2  ) ; <lb/> (1) <lb/>where <lb/> ffi = (ffi  0  ; ffi  1  ; ffi  2  ; ffi  3  ) = (ff; ı); <lb/> is meson quartet consisting of an isoscalar scalar ff and a pseudoscalar isotriplet <lb/>of pions ı and V is the characteristic &quot; Mexican hat &quot; potential <lb/> V(ffi <lb/> 2  ) = -<lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>— <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  ffi <lb/> 2  + <lb/> –  0 <lb/> 4 <lb/> ffi <lb/> 2 2  : <lb/> We assume here that –  0  and — <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  are not only positive, but such that spontaneous <lb/>symmetry breakdown (SSB) occurs in the mean-field approximation [MFA] to be <lb/>introduced later. That leads to spontaneous breaking of the internal O(4) (chiral) <lb/>symmetry, and in the last parentheses we have written the explicit symmetry <lb/>breaking term. As the chiral symmetry breaking (fflSB) term in the Lagrangian we <lb/>take <lb/> fflSB  = - fflSB  = &quot;ff: <lb/> (2) <lb/>In the first perturbative ( &quot; Born &quot; ) approximation we have m  ı  = 0 in the chiral <lb/>limit &quot; = 0, i.e., the Nambu-Goldstone (NG) theorem holds. The Born approxi-<lb/>mation ff meson mass is not constrained by chiral symmetry, but rather its square <lb/>is proportional to the coupling constant –  0  . It remains to be seen what happens to <lb/>this mass in higher approximations. We shall see that the nonperturbative Gaus-<lb/>sian approximation particle content of this model can differ from the one in per-<lb/>turbation theory, viz. from the simple O(4) multiplet, depending on the strength <lb/>of the coupling –  0  . The GA equations in the linear sigma model of Gell-Mann— <lb/>Levy are shown in Figs. 1 and 2. <lb/></body>

			<page> 22 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> V. Dmitrašinovi´ <lb/></note>

			<body> Fig. 1. Zero-particle, or &quot; vacuum &quot; (one-point) Green function Schwinger-Dyson equation. <lb/> Fig. 2. One-particle, or &quot; gap &quot; (two-point) Green function Schwinger-Dyson equation. <lb/> Note their (self-)consistency: the solution to one SD equation enters the def-<lb/>inition of the other, and vice versa. This is also an expected property of so-called <lb/> &quot; bootstrap &quot; solutions to field theory. Figures 1 and 2 lead to two coupled nonlin-<lb/>ear equations in two unknowns: <lb/> M <lb/> 2  = <lb/> &quot; <lb/>v <lb/> + 2–  0  v <lb/> 2 <lb/> (3) <lb/> — <lb/> 2  = <lb/> &quot; <lb/>v <lb/> + 2–  0  ~ [I  0  (—) - I  0  (M)] ; <lb/> (4) <lb/>where <lb/> I  0  (m  i  ) = i <lb/> Z d <lb/> 4  k <lb/> (2ı)  4 <lb/> 1 <lb/>k  2  - m  2 <lb/>i  + i&quot; <lb/> (5) <lb/>depending implicitly on the cutoff  which is necessary for the regularization of <lb/>infinities in the integrals I  0  (m  i  ), and the bare coupling constant –  0  . Due to the <lb/>relation between M <lb/> 2 <lb/> and –  0  f <lb/> 2 <lb/>ı  , Eq. 3, M is proportional to –  0  , meaning that a <lb/>change in M corresponds to a change in –  0  at fixed v = f  ı  = 93MeV. <lb/>The solutions M; — do not have the (naively) expected properties viz. the <lb/>(NG) pion field is not massless (—=0), even in the chiral limit, as first noted by <lb/>Kamefuchi and Umezawa in 1964 [12]. (We show the nonchiral solutions with <lb/>fixed pion decay constant in Fig. 3. Note that the boson loops tend to restore the <lb/>broken symmetry, unlike the fermion ones.) <lb/>This fact presented a serious problem for the GA for the following 30 years. <lb/>The solution to this problem, first proposed in 1994 [13], consists in construct-<lb/>ing two-body states which mix with the corresponding &quot; elementary &quot; one-body <lb/>(or Castillejo-Dalitz-Dyson, or CDD) states, and observing their properties, thus <lb/>finding a massless state among them with all the right NG boson properties, va-<lb/>lidity of the chiral Ward identities being just one of them. In other words, there <lb/>are massless bound states of two massive mesons in the GA, a provocative idea <lb/>at the time. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Scalar mesons in the Gaussian approximation to the linear  odel <lb/></note>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body> Fig. 3. Solutions to the gap equation in the GML model: M, and —. <lb/> 3.1 Chiral symmetry and the Gaussian approximation <lb/> Originally the Nambu-Goldstone boson problem was solved by direct construc-<lb/>tion of the Gaussian approximation two-body (SD) equation, a.k.a. the Bethe-<lb/>Salpeter (BS) equation (The same result, only at vanishing external momenta, can <lb/>be obtained by differentiating the effective potential.). In Ref. [13] we have shown <lb/>that the Nambu-Goldstone particles appear as poles in the two-particle propagator <lb/> i.e. they are bound states of the two distinct massive elementary excitations in <lb/>the theory. We specify the two-body dynamics in the theory in terms of the four-<lb/>point SD equation or, equivalently, of the Bethe-Salpeter equation, see Figs. 4 and <lb/>5. The appearance of massless NG bound states of two massive single-particle <lb/> Fig. 4. Four-point Green function Schwinger-Dyson, or Bethe-Salpeter equation. The <lb/>square &quot; box &quot; represents the potential, whereas the round &quot; blob &quot; is the BS amplitude it-<lb/>self. All lines are meant as dressed fields, i.e. as double lines in Figs. 1 and 2. <lb/> states produced a certain amount of surprise and confusion, as it seems to imply <lb/>a doubling of states with identical ( &quot; flavour &quot; ) quantum numbers: in each flavour <lb/>channel, beside the massive one-body CDD state there is also a lighter two-body <lb/>state. At first sight this &quot; bootstrap &quot; mechanism would appear to explain the &quot; su-<lb/>pernumerary &quot; scalar states (f  0  (980), a  0  (980)), but on second inspection one can <lb/>see that it produces new problems in that it also implies particle doubling in <lb/>channels other than the scalar ones where supernumerary states have not been <lb/>found. <lb/></body>

			<page> 24 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> V. Dmitrašinovi´ <lb/></note>

			<body> Fig. 5. The potential (square &quot; box &quot; ) entering the Bethe-Salpeter equation, as defined in the <lb/>RPA. <lb/> 3.2 Real and fake particle doubling <lb/> The problem of (naive) supernumerary states (CDD poles) was resolved in Ref. <lb/>[11,14] by way of spectral analysis: the Kallen-Lehmann functions were calcu-<lb/>lated from the solutions to the BS equation in the GA and it was found that the <lb/>single-particle (CDD) poles disappear altogether from the spectra: <lb/> Fig. 6. Pion channel Kallen-Lehmann spectral function for various values of M. <lb/> The remaining delta function in the ı spectrum, Fig. 6, corresponds to the <lb/>dynamical state (solution to the BS equation) with the (pion) mass squared fixed <lb/>by the Dashen relation at &quot;/v, which is always below the single-particle (CDD) <lb/>mass —. Similarly the peak in the ff channel spectral function, Fig. 7, corresponds <lb/>to the dynamical state mass, which lies below the corresponding single particle <lb/>mass M, Ref. [10]. <lb/>So, one may say that the influence of the two-particle continuum has pushed <lb/>the masses of the dynamical states below their single-particle values and below <lb/>the two-particle threshold, see Fig. 8, where the exact solutions to the BS equation <lb/>are shown together with the two-body thresholds. Note however, that there are <lb/>other solutions to the BS equation, see Fig. 9, at higher masses, which do not show <lb/>up in the spectral functions due to their even larger imaginary parts. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Scalar mesons in the Gaussian approximation to the linear  odel <lb/></note>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body> 0.0 <lb/> 0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>s <lb/> 1/2 (GeV) <lb/>0.0 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>200.0 <lb/>300.0 <lb/>400.0 <lb/> ρ <lb/> σ <lb/> Λ  4 = 0.5 GeV, µ = 146 MeV, M = 300 MeV <lb/> Λ  4 = 0.5 GeV, µ = 156 MeV, M = 400 MeV <lb/> Λ  4 = 0.5 GeV, µ = 165 MeV, M = 470 MeV <lb/> Fig. 7. Sigma channel Kallen-Lehmann spectral function for various values of M, —. <lb/> 120.0 <lb/> 320.0 <lb/>520.0 <lb/>720.0 <lb/>920.0 <lb/>M (MeV) <lb/>140.0 <lb/>340.0 <lb/>540.0 <lb/>740.0 <lb/>m <lb/> σ  (MeV) <lb/> Λ  4  = 1 GeV <lb/> Λ  4  = 0.5 GeV <lb/> Λ  4  = 1 GeV (M = 2µ) <lb/> Λ  4  = 0.5 GeV (M = 2µ) <lb/> M = m  σ <lb/> Fig. 8. Sigma mass as a function of M, and the position of the lowest threshold (M = 2 —). <lb/> These solutions owe their existence to the large nonlinearities in the BS equa-<lb/>tion at very large masses/couplings. Yet, we must keep the possibility of such <lb/>solutions in mind, in case they move to lower masses for a different model La-<lb/>grangian. <lb/>Moreover, we have proven in Ref. [11] the identity of the Gaussian BS and <lb/>the N/D equations in the S-matrix theory, which fact immediately implies uni-<lb/>tarity and causality of their solutions. This translates into analytic properties of <lb/>the scattering amplitude which tell us what branch of the equations to solve and <lb/></body>

			<page> 26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> V. Dmitrašinovi´ <lb/></note>

			<body> the solution&apos;s physical interpretation. The solutions to the N/D equations are not <lb/>unique in general, however, the arbitrariness showing up in the form of so-called <lb/>Castillejo-Dalitz-Dyson (CDD) poles. The position of a CDD pole, and the coeffi-<lb/>cient multiplying it are arbitrary in the usual S-matrix, or N/D approach, but in <lb/>our approach they are completely determined by the Gaussian approximation to <lb/>the underlying ff model. <lb/> 0.0 <lb/> 2000.0 <lb/>4000.0 <lb/>6000.0 <lb/>m  σ  (MeV) <lb/>140.0 <lb/>340.0 <lb/>540.0 <lb/>740.0 <lb/>M (MeV) <lb/> Λ  4  = 0.2 GeV <lb/> Fig. 9. Sigma mass as a function of M. <lb/> 4 Conclusions <lb/> We have shown that the Gaussian Approximation is: (a) Lorentz and chirally in-<lb/>variant, (b) causal and unitary, and (c) selfconsistent and nonperturbative, i.e., <lb/>it may describe mesons as bound states of other mesons. These are precisely the <lb/>properties demanded of a relativistic quantum theory in the so-called &quot; bootstrap &quot; <lb/>approach to hadronic particle physics of the 1960 s, but with several profound <lb/>differences, viz. (1) a Lagrangian starting point based on a chiral quark model, <lb/>therefore with a definite number of CDD poles with well defined properties (the <lb/>bare Lagrangian free parameters are fixed by the quark model); (2) no arbitrari-<lb/>ness at all: the &quot; subtraction constants &quot; , in S-matrix language, i.e., &quot; infinite parts &quot; <lb/>of Feynman diagrams are known due to the renormalizability of the GA. <lb/>These results open new questions: for certain Lagrangians, such as the &apos;t <lb/>Hooft and the SU(3) linear sigma models, the number of flavour channels (greatly) <lb/>exceeds the number of fields, i.e., there is no one-to-one correspondence between <lb/>the Lagrangian fields and the available flavour channels, thus opening the pos-<lb/>sibility of light bound states in channels without CDD poles (almost inevitably <lb/>these are exotic channels). We shall return to these issues in the future. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Scalar mesons in the Gaussian approximation to the linear  odel <lb/></note>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. N.A. T ¨ <lb/>ornqvist, Z. Phys. C 68, 647 (1995). <lb/>2. D. Black, A. H. Fariborz, F. Sannino, J. Schechter, Phys.Rev. D 59: 074026 (1999). <lb/>3. J.A. Oller, E. Oset, J.R. Pelaez, Phys.Rev. D 59: 074001, (1999). <lb/>4. J. Nieves, E. Ruiz Arriola, Nucl. Phys. A 679, 57, (2000). <lb/>5. G. &apos;t Hooft, Phys. Rep. 142, 357 (1986). <lb/>6. V. Dmitrašinovi´ , Phys. Rev. C 53, 1383 (1996). <lb/>7. G. &apos;t Hooft, Phys. Rev. D 14, 3432 (1976), (E) ibid. D 18, 2199 (1978). <lb/>8. T. Barnes and G.I. Ghandour, Phys.Rev. D22, 924 (1980); see also eds. L. Polley and <lb/>D.E.L. Pottinger, Variational Calculations in Quantum Field Theory, World Scientific, Sin-<lb/>gapore (1987). <lb/>9. R.J. Rivers, Path Integral Methods in Quantum Field Theory, Cambridge University Press, <lb/>Cambridge (1987); and B. Hatfield, Quantum Field Theory of Point Particles and Strings, <lb/> Addison-Wesley, Reading (1992). <lb/>10. Issei Nakamura and V. Dmitrašinovi´ , Prog. Theor. Phys. 106, 1195 (2001). <lb/>11. Issei Nakamura and V. Dmitrašinovi´ , Nucl. Phys. A 713, 133 (2003). <lb/>12. S. Kamefuchi, and H. Umezawa, Nuov. Cim. 31, 429 (1964). <lb/>13. V. Dmitrašinovi´ , J. A. McNeil and J. Shepard, Z. Phys. C 69, 359 (1996). <lb/>14. V. Dmitrašinovi´ , Phys. Lett. B 433, 362 (1998). <lb/>15. V. Dmitrašinovi´ and Issei Nakamura, J. Math. Phys. 44, 2839 (2003). </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
