<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="footnote"> arXiv:0706.3897v1  [quant-ph] 26 Jun 2007 <lb/></note>

			<front> Romanovski Polynomials in Selected Physics Problems <lb/> A. P. Raposo <lb/> 1  , H. J. Weber <lb/> 2  , D. Alvarez-Castillo <lb/> 3  , M. Kirchbach <lb/> 3  , <lb/> 1  Facultad de Ciencias, Av. Salvador Nava s/n, San Luis Potosí, <lb/>S.L.P. 78290, Universidad Autónoma de San Luis Potosí, México, <lb/> 2  Department of Physics, University of Virginia, <lb/>Charlottesville, VA 22904, USA and <lb/> 3  Instituto de Física, Av. Manuel Nava 6, San Luis Potosí, <lb/>S.L.P. 78290, Universidad Autónoma de San Luis Potosí, México <lb/> (Dated: February 1, 2008) <lb/> Abstract <lb/> We briefly review the five possible real polynomial solutions of hypergeometric differential equa-<lb/>tions. Three of them are the well known classical orthogonal polynomials, but the other two are <lb/>different with respect to their orthogonality properties. We then focus on the family of polynomials <lb/>which exhibits a finite orthogonality. This family, to be referred to as the Romanovski polynomi-<lb/>als, is required in exact solutions of several physics problems ranging from quantum mechanics and <lb/>quark physics to random matrix theory. It appears timely to draw attention to it by the present <lb/>study. Our survey also includes several new observations on the orthogonality properties of the <lb/>Romanovski polynomials and new developments from their Rodrigues formula. <lb/></front>

			<page> 1 <lb/></page>

			<body> I. INTRODUCTION <lb/> Several physics problems ranging from ordinary–and supersymmetric quantum mechan-<lb/>ics to applications of random matrix theory in nuclear and condensed matter physics are <lb/>ordinarily resolved in terms of Jacobi polynomials of purely imaginary arguments and param-<lb/>eters that are complex conjugate to each other. Depending on whether the degree n of these <lb/>polynomials is even or odd, they appear either genuinely real or purely imaginary. The fact <lb/>is that all the above problems are naturally resolved in terms of manifestly real orthogonal <lb/>polynomials. These real polynomials happen to be related to the above Jacobi polynomials <lb/>by the purely imaginary phase factor, i <lb/> n  , much like the phase relationship between the hy-<lb/>perbolic and the trigonometric functions, i.e. sin ix = i sinh x. These polynomials have first <lb/>been reported by Sir Edward John Routh [1] in 1884, and then were rediscovered within the <lb/>context of probability distributions by Vsevolod Romanovski [2] in 1929. They are known <lb/>in the mathematics literature under the name of &quot; Romanovski &quot; polynomials. <lb/>Romanovski polynomials may be derived as the polynomial solutions of the ODE <lb/>(1 + x <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> d <lb/> 2  R(x) <lb/>dx  2  + t(x) <lb/>dR(x) <lb/>dx <lb/> + λR(x) = 0, <lb/>(1) <lb/>with t(x) a polynomial, at most a linear, which is a particular subclass of the hypergeometric <lb/>differential equations [3], [4]. Other subclasses give rise to the well known classical orthogonal <lb/>polynomials of Hermite, Laguerre and Jacobi [4], [5]. Romanovski polynomials are not so <lb/>widespread as the others in applications. But in recent years several problems have been <lb/>solved in terms of this family of polynomials (Schrödinger equation with the hyperbolic <lb/>Scarf and the trigonometric Rosen-Morse potentials [6, 7], Klein-Gordon equation with equal <lb/>vector and scalar potentials [8], certain classes of non-central potential problems as well [9]) <lb/>and so they deserve a closer look and be placed on equal footing with the classical orthogonal <lb/>polynomials. <lb/>In this context, our goal is threefold. First of all, it is to establish the orthogonality <lb/>properties of these polynomials. This is achieved by the same methods as for any other <lb/>hypergeometric differential equation. Our second goal is to explain their use as orthogonal <lb/>eigenfunctions of some Hamiltonian operators. Third, Eq. (1) has been described in [10] as <lb/>a complexification of the Jacobi ODE, a general expression that can be written as <lb/>(1 − x <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> d <lb/> 2  P (x) <lb/> dx  2  + t(x) <lb/>dP (x) <lb/> dx <lb/> + λP (x) = 0, <lb/>(2) <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body> where t(x) is again an arbitrary polynomial of at most first degree, but not necessarily the <lb/>same as in Eq. (1). If that were the case, solutions to Eq. (1) would be the complexification <lb/>of the solutions to Eq. (2), that is, the complexification of the Jacobi polynomials. Hence, <lb/>our final goal is to clarify this relationship. <lb/>We deal with all these issues in the following way: In Section II we give a classification <lb/>of hypergeometric equations placing Eq. (1) among them. Next, in Section III we show <lb/>some expected properties of the R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) functions as solutions of a hypergeometric ODE <lb/>such as: being indeed polynomials, recurrence relations; and the absence of another, namely <lb/>general orthogonality. In Section IV we compare the polynomials R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) with the com-<lb/>plexified Jacobi polynomials. In Section V we show some examples of physical problems <lb/>whose solutions lead to Romanovski polynomials. Section VI sheds light on some peculiar-<lb/>ities of orthogonal polynomials as part of quantum mechanics wave functions. In the final <lb/>Section VII we summarize our conclusions. <lb/> II. CLASSIFICATION OF HYPERGEOMETRIC DIFFERENTIAL EQUATIONS <lb/> A hypergeometric equation [3] is an ODE of the form <lb/> s(x)F <lb/> ′′  (x) + t(x)F <lb/> ′  (x) + λF (x) = 0, <lb/>(3) <lb/>where the unknown is a real function of real variable F : U → R, where U ⊂ R is some <lb/>open subset of the real line, and λ ∈ R a corresponding eigenvalue, and where the functions <lb/> s and t are real polynomials of at most second order and first order, respectively. Here the <lb/>prime stands for differentiation with respect to the variable x. This class of ODEs is very <lb/>well known both from the mathematical and the physical points of view. From the mathe-<lb/>matical one, many properties that its solutions exhibit make them interesting in their own <lb/>right. For instance, the classical orthogonal polynomials [3], [11], [12] (Hermite, Laguerre <lb/>and Jacobi polynomials, the latter including as particular cases Legendre, Chebyshev and <lb/>Gegenbauer polynomials) are solutions of particular subfamilies of hypergeometric ODEs. <lb/>From the physical point of view, many of the exact solutions to the eigenvalue equation of <lb/>a quantum mechanical Hamilton operator lead to an equation of the hypergeometric kind: <lb/>harmonic oscillator, Coulomb potential, the trigonometric Rosen-Morse and Scarf potentials, <lb/>hyperbolic Rosen-Morse and hyperbolic Scarf potentials. <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body> As to our goal, the mathematical properties we are interested in are the following (refer <lb/>to [3] for a detailed study and proofs of these statements). The leading property, which gives <lb/>the differential equation its name &quot; hypergeometric, &quot; is that if F (x) is a solution to Eq. (3), <lb/>then the derivative F <lb/> ′  (x) is a solution to another hypergeometric equation that is closely <lb/>related to the former: <lb/> s(x)(F <lb/> ′  (x)) <lb/> ′′  + t <lb/> (1)  (x)(F <lb/> ′  (x)) <lb/> ′  + λ <lb/> (1)  F <lb/> ′  (x) = 0, <lb/>(4) <lb/>where t <lb/> (1)  (x) ≡ t(x) + s <lb/> ′  (x) and λ <lb/> (1)  ≡ λ + t <lb/> ′  (x). Iteratively, it is easy to show that the mth <lb/> derivative, F <lb/> (m)  (x) is a solution of <lb/> s(x)(F <lb/> (m)  (x)) <lb/> ′′  + t <lb/> (m)  (x)(F <lb/> (m)  (x)) <lb/> ′  + λ <lb/> (m)  F <lb/> (m)  (x) = 0, <lb/>(5) <lb/>where now t <lb/> (m)  (x) ≡ t(x) + ms <lb/> ′  (x) and λ <lb/> (m)  ≡ λ + mt <lb/> ′  (x) + <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> m(m − 1)s <lb/> ′′  (x). The next result <lb/>is that, for any n ∈ {0, 1, 2, . . . }, there exists a polynomial F  n  (x) of degree n, together with <lb/>a constant λ  n  which satisfy Eq. (3). The constant is given by <lb/> λ  n  = −n <lb/> t <lb/> ′  (x) + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(n − 1)s <lb/> ′′  (x) <lb/> . <lb/> (6) <lb/>The last result, together with the former, tells us that F  n  (x) and its derivatives, F <lb/> (m) <lb/> n  (x), are <lb/>solutions to similar equations. By means of a weight function, it is possible to write down a <lb/>formula which gives all these polynomials at once. A weight function w(x) associated with <lb/>Eq. (3) is a solution of Pearson&apos;s differential equation <lb/>[s(x)w(x)] <lb/> ′  = t(x)w(x), <lb/> (7) <lb/>that assures the self-adjointness of the differential operator of the hypergeometric ODE. <lb/>Then, the generalized Rodrigues formula gives the mth derivative of the polynomial F  n  (x) <lb/>as <lb/> F <lb/> (m) <lb/> n  (x) = N  nm <lb/> 1 <lb/> w(x)s(x)  m <lb/> d <lb/> n−m <lb/> dx  n−m  [w(x)s(x) <lb/> n  ] , <lb/> 0 ≤ m ≤ n, <lb/> (8) <lb/>where N  nm  is a normalization constant. This constant is related to the coefficient a  n  of the <lb/>term of degree n in the polynomial F  n  (x) by the expression <lb/> N  nm  = <lb/>(−1) <lb/> n−m  n! a  n <lb/>  n−1 <lb/>k=m  λ <lb/> (k) <lb/> n <lb/> , <lb/> (9) <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body> which is valid for 0 ≤ m ≤ n − 1 and n ≥ 1. Equation (8), with m = 0, gives the classical <lb/>Rodrigues formula <lb/> F  n  (x) = N  n <lb/> 1 <lb/> w(x) <lb/>d <lb/> n <lb/> dx  n  [w(x)s(x) <lb/> n  ] , <lb/> (10) <lb/>where we have identified F <lb/> (0) <lb/> n  (x) = F  n  (x) and N  n0  = N  n  . <lb/>If the functions s(x) and w(x) satisfy yet another condition, namely both being positive <lb/>within an interval (a, b) and <lb/>lim <lb/> x→a <lb/> s(x)w(x)x <lb/> l  − lim <lb/> x→b <lb/> s(x)w(x)x <lb/> l  = 0 , <lb/> (11) <lb/>for any nonnegative integer l, then the family of polynomials is orthogonal with respect to <lb/>the weight function w, i.e. <lb/>  b <lb/>a <lb/> w(x)F  m  (x)F  n  (x) dx = (f  n  ) <lb/> 2  δ  mn  , <lb/> ∀m, n ∈ {0, 1, 2, . . . }, <lb/> (12) <lb/>where f  n  is the norm of the polynomials. Hence, all hypergeometric ODEs admit a family <lb/>of polynomial solutions. But this family is not orthogonal for all hypergeometric ODEs. <lb/>The fact that a solution F (x) and its derivatives F <lb/> (m)  (x) obey hypergeometric ODEs <lb/>with the same coefficient s(x), Eqs. (3) and (5), suggests a classification in terms of the <lb/>polynomial s(x). Moreover, a classification according to the roots of s(x) has proved useful <lb/>and provides a characterization of the solutions [3],[4],[5]. There are five classes in this <lb/>scheme, as s(x) may be a constant, a first degree polynomial or a second order one with <lb/>two distinct real roots, one real root or, finally, two complex conjugate, not real, roots. In <lb/>addition, it is useful to note that an affine change of variable (i.e., x → a x + b, a  = 0) <lb/>does preserve the hypergeometric character of Eq. (3) and the kind of roots of polynomial <lb/> s(x). Then, in each class, we may consider only a canonical form of the equation, to which <lb/>any other can be reduced by an affine change of the independent variable. <lb/>1. Polynomial s(x) is a constant: <lb/> We take as canonical form <lb/> H <lb/> ′′  (x) − 2αxH <lb/> ′  (x) + λH(x) = 0, <lb/>(13) <lb/>where α ∈ R is an arbitrary constant, i.e., we have here a one-parameter family of ODEs. <lb/>We call it generalized Hermite equation (the equation with α = 1 is called Hermite equa-<lb/>tion). The polynomials are a generalization of Hermite polynomials, denoted {H <lb/> (α) <lb/> n  }, <lb/></body>

			<page> 5 <lb/></page>

			<body> n ∈ {0, 1, 2, . . . }. The weight function is <lb/> w(x) = e <lb/> −αx  2  . <lb/> (14) <lb/>For α &gt; 0 the additional conditions for orthogonality, Eq. (11), are fulfilled in the interval <lb/>(−∞, ∞), hence we get an orthogonality relation: <lb/>  ∞ <lb/>−∞ <lb/> e <lb/> −αx  2  H <lb/> (α) <lb/> m  (x)H <lb/> (α) <lb/> n  (x) dx = (h  n  ) <lb/> 2  δ  mn  , <lb/> ∀m, n ∈ {0, 1, 2, . . . }, α &gt; 0. <lb/>(15) <lb/>2. Polynomial s(x) is of the first degree: <lb/> The canonical form of the ODE is <lb/> xL <lb/> ′′  (x) + t(x)L <lb/> ′  (x) + λL(x) = 0, <lb/>(16) <lb/>which we call generalized Laguerre equation. The first-order polynomial t is still arbitrary, <lb/>so this is a two-parameter family of ODEs. If t(x) is written as t(x) = −αx + β + 1, with <lb/> α, β ∈ R, the parameters (actually, Eq. (16) is called associated Laguerre equation in the <lb/>case α = 1, and Laguerre equation if α = 1 and β = 0), then the weight function is <lb/> w(x) = x <lb/> β  e <lb/> −αx  , <lb/> (17) <lb/>and the polynomials are written {L <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> }, n ∈ {0, 1, 2, . . . }. If α, β &gt; 0, the condition of <lb/>Eq. (11) is fulfilled and one gets orthogonality in the interval [0, ∞) as <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> 0 <lb/> x <lb/> β  e <lb/> −αx  L <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> m <lb/> (x)L <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) dx = (l  n  ) <lb/> 2  δ  mn  , <lb/> ∀m, n ∈ {0, 1, 2, . . . }, α, β &gt; 0. <lb/>(18) <lb/>3. Polynomial s(x) is of the second degree, with two different real roots: <lb/> The canonical form of the ODE is <lb/>(1 − x <lb/> 2  )P <lb/> ′′  (x) + t(x)P <lb/> ′  (x) + λP (x) = 0, <lb/>(19) <lb/>which is known as Jacobi equation. It is customary to write the arbitrary polynomial t(x) <lb/> in the form t(x) = β − α − (α + β + 2)x, where α, β ∈ R are the parameters. Then, for each <lb/>pair (α, β), the Rodrigues formula defines a family of polynomials, the Jacobi polynomials, <lb/>denoted {P <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> }, n ∈ {0, 1, 2, . . . } with the weight function given by <lb/> w(x) = (1 − x) <lb/> α  (1 + x) <lb/> β  . <lb/> (20) <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body> If parameters α and β satisfy α, β &gt; −1, the additional condition of Eq. (11) is fulfilled in <lb/> the interval (−1, 1), so there is an orthonormalization relation: <lb/>  1 <lb/> −1 <lb/> (1 − x) <lb/> α  (1 + x) <lb/> β  P <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> m <lb/> (x)P <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) dx = (p  n  ) <lb/> 2  δ  mn  , <lb/> ∀m, n ∈ {0, 1, 2, . . . }, α, β &gt; −1. <lb/> (21) <lb/>Some particular cases received special names: Gegenbauer polynomials if α = β, Chebyshev <lb/>I and II if α = β = ±1/2, Legendre polynomials if α = β = 0. <lb/>4. Polynomial s(x) is of the second degree, with one double real root: <lb/> We choose as canonical form of the ODE <lb/> x <lb/> 2  B <lb/> ′′  (x) + t(x)B <lb/> ′  (x) + λB(x) = 0, <lb/>(22) <lb/>If the arbitrary first order polynomial is written as t(x) = (α + 2)x + β, with α, β ∈ R the <lb/>parameters, then the weight function is <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (x) = x <lb/> α  e <lb/> − <lb/> β <lb/> x  . <lb/> (23) <lb/>We write the polynomials as {B <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> }, n ∈ {0, 1, 2, . . . }, which are called Bessel polynomials <lb/>[13] (they were also given under type V in Ref. [2] and classified in Ref. [4]). There is <lb/>no combination of any particular values of the parameters and any interval which satisfies <lb/>Eq. (11), so neither of these families is orthogonal with respect to the weight function (23). <lb/>5. Polynomial s(x) is of the second degree, with two complex roots: <lb/> The canonical form of the ODE for this case is chosen as <lb/>(1 + x <lb/> 2  )R <lb/> ′′  (x) + t(x)R <lb/> ′  (x) + λR(x) = 0, <lb/>(24) <lb/>which is the one studied in [4]–[6], and [14]–[15]. A note of caution: the solutions introduced <lb/>in [6] and [7] seem to be different, but this is due just to a different form given to the <lb/>arbitrary polynomial t(x). A careful review shows that both papers are dealing with the <lb/>same ODE, namely Eq. (24), so the solutions must be the same up to a constant factor. <lb/>Writing the polynomial t(x) as t(x) = 2βx + α, with α, β ∈ R, we have again a two-<lb/>parameter family of ODEs with their respective families of polynomials which we denote <lb/> {R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> }, n ∈ {0, 1, 2, . . . }. With this notation (which differs slightly from [6],[7],[16]) the <lb/>weight function is <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (x) = (1 + x <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> β−1  e <lb/> −α cot  −1  x  . <lb/> (25) <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body> Upon comparison with Romanovski&apos;s original work [2], we conclude {R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> } are the Ro-<lb/>manovski polynomials. In Section III we study the properties of these polynomials. <lb/>In Ref. [4] polynomial solutions of linear homogeneous 2nd-order ODEs <lb/> s(x)y <lb/> ′′ <lb/> n  (x) + t(x)y <lb/> ′ <lb/> n  (x) = n[(n − 1)e + 2ε]y  n  (x), <lb/> s(x) = ex <lb/> 2  + 2f x + g, t(x) = 2ε + γ, <lb/>n ∈ {0, 1, . . .}, e, f, g, ε, γ ∈ R , <lb/> (26) <lb/>are classified upon substituting the finite power series <lb/> y  n  (x) = <lb/> n <lb/> k=0 <lb/> a  n,k <lb/> k! <lb/> (x + c) <lb/> k  , <lb/>a  n,n  = 0, c ∈ C , <lb/> (27) <lb/>and analyzing the resulting recursions among the coefficients. No other solutions other than <lb/>the polynomials given above are found. Their orthogonality properties are derived by means <lb/>of the spectral theorem (of Favard [12]). <lb/>To sum up, all hypergeometric equations fall into one of these five classes. Three of them <lb/>give rise to the very well studied classical orthogonal polynomials (Jacobi, Laguerre and <lb/>Hermite) or a slight generalization of them. A fourth one has not attracted much attention <lb/>due to, we guess, the lack of general orthogonality. Finally, a fifth class is the family of <lb/>ODEs we are dealing with here. <lb/> III. DEFINITION AND PROPERTIES OF ROMANOVSKI POLYNOMIALS <lb/> We focus now on the Romanovski polynomials R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> and study some well known, and <lb/>some new properties they have. We start by writing down the explicit Rodrigues formula, <lb/>Eq. (10), for this case, that we take as their definition. For each α, β ∈ R and each <lb/> n ∈ N = {0, 1, 2, . . . } we define the function R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> , by the Rodrigues formula <lb/> R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) ≡ <lb/> 1 <lb/> w  (α,β)  (x) <lb/>d <lb/> n <lb/> dx  n <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (x)s(x) <lb/> n <lb/> , <lb/> (28) <lb/>where <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (x) ≡ (1 + x <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> β−1  e <lb/> −α cot  −1  x  , <lb/> (29) <lb/>is the weight function, same as in equation (25), and <lb/> s(x) ≡ 1 + x <lb/> 2  , <lb/> (30) <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body> is the coefficient of the second derivative of the hypergeometric differential equation (24). <lb/>Notice that we have chosen the normalization constants N  n  = 1, which is equivalent to <lb/>make a choice of the coefficient of highest degree in the polynomial, as given by equation <lb/>(9), which takes the form <lb/> a  n  = <lb/>1 <lb/> n! <lb/> n−1  <lb/> k=0 <lb/> [2β(n − k) + n(n − 1) − k(k − 1)] , <lb/>n ≥ 1. <lb/>(31) <lb/>Notice that the coefficient a  n  does not depend on the parameter α, but only on β and, <lb/>for particular values of β, a  n  is zero (i.e., for all the values β = <lb/> k(k−1)−n(n−1) <lb/> 2(n−k) <lb/> where k = <lb/>0, . . . , n − 1). This observation poses a problem that we will address somewhere else. For <lb/>later reference, we write explicitly the polynomials of degree 0, 1 and 2 <lb/> R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/>0 <lb/> (x) = 1, <lb/>(32) <lb/> R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/>1 <lb/> (x) = <lb/>1 <lb/> w  (α,β)  (x) <lb/> w <lb/> ′  (α,β)  (x)s(x) + s <lb/> ′  (x)w <lb/> (α,β)  (x) <lb/> = t <lb/> (α,β)  (x) = 2βx + α, (33) <lb/> R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/>2 <lb/> (x) = <lb/>1 <lb/> w  (α,β)  (x) <lb/> d <lb/>dx <lb/> [s <lb/> 2  (x)w <lb/> ′  (α,β)  (x) + 2s(x)s <lb/> ′  (x)w <lb/> (α,β)  (x)] <lb/>= <lb/>1 <lb/> w  (α,β)  (x) <lb/> d <lb/>dx <lb/> s(x)w <lb/> (α,β)  (x)(t <lb/> (α,β)  (x) + s <lb/> ′  (x)) <lb/> = (2x + t <lb/> (α,β)  (x))t <lb/> (α,β)  (x) + (2 + t <lb/> ′  (α,β)  (x))s(x) <lb/>= (2β + 1)(2β + 2)x <lb/> 2  + 2(2β + 1)αx + (2β + α <lb/> 2  + 2) <lb/>(34) <lb/>that derive from the Rodrigues formula (28) in conjunction with Pearson&apos;s ODE (7). <lb/>The whole set of Romanovski polynomials is spanned by the three parameters α, β and <lb/> n <lb/> {R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> : α, β ∈ R, n ∈ N}. <lb/> (35) <lb/>In order to study their properties we have found it useful to classify them in families. The <lb/>properties are stated for each family. We have found two different classifications in families <lb/>of different kinds which share different properties, so we distinguish them in the following <lb/>two subsections. <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body> A. The R  (α,β)  families <lb/> The family R <lb/> (α,β)  contains the polynomials with fixed parameters α and β. <lb/> R <lb/> (α,β)  ≡ {R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> : n ∈ N}. <lb/> (36) <lb/>This family has one polynomial, and only one, of each degree; two different families do <lb/>not share any polynomial in common and the union of all of them gives the whole set of <lb/>Romanovski polynomials (i.e., they form a partition of this set). <lb/>The first property of one of these families is that which led to their construction: the <lb/>family R <lb/> (α,β)  (x) comprises all the polynomial solutions of the hypergeometric differential <lb/>equation <lb/>(1 + x <lb/> 2  )R <lb/> ′′  (x) + (2βx + α)R <lb/> ′  (x) + λR(x) = 0, <lb/>(37) <lb/>where λ is a constant which, for the solution R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x), is given by λ  n  = −n(2β + n − 1). <lb/>Other characteristic properties of classical polynomials are present in the R <lb/> (α,β)  family <lb/>too, such as a differential recursion relation and an expression for a generating function in <lb/>closed form. <lb/>The differential recursion relation is obtained from the Rodrigues formula, Eq. (28), for <lb/>the polynomial R  n+1  (x) (superscripts (α, β) omitted for clarity). <lb/> R  n+1  (x) = <lb/>1 <lb/> w(x) <lb/> d <lb/> n+1 <lb/> dx  n+1 <lb/> w(x)s(x) <lb/> n+1 <lb/> . <lb/> (38) <lb/>Then, because of the very definition of the weight function, Eq. (7), it is easy to see that <lb/> w(x)s(x) <lb/> n+1 <lb/>  ′  = w(x)s(x) <lb/> n  [2(β + n)x + α]. <lb/> (39) <lb/>Upon substitution in Eq. (38) and a straightforward derivation one gets <lb/> R  n+1  (x) = <lb/>1 <lb/> w(x) <lb/> [2(β + n)x + α] <lb/> d <lb/> n <lb/> dx  n  [w(x)s(x) <lb/> n  ] + 2n(β + n) <lb/> d <lb/> n−1 <lb/> dx  n−1  [w(x)s(x) <lb/> n  ] <lb/> . (40) <lb/>In the first term, the formula for R  n  (x) is recognized, while in the second term its derivative, <lb/> R <lb/> ′ <lb/> n  (x), appears (by means of Eq. (8) applied to the present case). The result, which makes <lb/>use of Eqs. (9) and (31), is the following differential recursion relation <lb/>2(β + n)(1 + x <lb/> 2  ) <lb/>dR <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) <lb/>dx <lb/>= (2β + n − 1) <lb/> R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n+1  (x) − [2(β + n)x + α]R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) <lb/> . (41) <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body> An integral representation of the Romanovski polynomials is obtained by means of the <lb/>Cauchy&apos;s integral formula. As the weight function can be extended to the complex plane, <lb/>where it is analytic except at points ±i, we can use Cauchy&apos;s integral formula to get <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (x)s(x) <lb/> n  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πi <lb/> γ <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (z)s(z) <lb/> n <lb/> z − x <lb/> dz, <lb/>(42) <lb/>where x is real but z is a complex variable, and γ is a closed curve in the complex plane, <lb/>enclosing point x, but not ±i. Substituting this equation into the definition of Romanovski <lb/>polynomials, Eq. (28), we get <lb/> R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πiw  (α,β)  (x) <lb/>d <lb/> n <lb/> dx  n <lb/> γ <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (z)s(z) <lb/> n <lb/> z − x <lb/> dz. <lb/>(43) <lb/>The n derivatives with respect to x can be easily performed under the integral sign, giving <lb/>rise to the following integral representation: <lb/> R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) = <lb/> n! <lb/> 2πiw  (α,β)  (x) <lb/> γ <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (z)s(z) <lb/> n <lb/> (z − x)  n+1  dz. <lb/>(44) <lb/>This representation is useful in calculating the generating function, as explained in [3]. A <lb/>generating function, R <lb/> (α,β)  (x, y), of the family R <lb/> (α,β)  is a function that is analytic in the <lb/>variable y and whose Taylor expansion in the variable y has the form <lb/> R <lb/> (α,β)  (x, y) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=0 <lb/> y <lb/> k <lb/> k! <lb/>R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> k <lb/> (x). <lb/>(45) <lb/>Upon substitution of Eq. (44) in previous equation, and interchanging the order of integral <lb/>and sum signs (which is allowed since the function is analytic), we get <lb/> R <lb/> (α,β)  (x, y) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πiw  (α,β)  (x) <lb/> γ <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (z) <lb/> z − x <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=0 <lb/> y <lb/> k  s(z) <lb/> k <lb/> (z − x)  k  dz. <lb/>(46) <lb/>The sum is a geometric series, which can be summed as <lb/> ∞ <lb/> k=0 <lb/>  ys(z) <lb/>z − x <lb/>  k <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/>1 − <lb/> ys(z) <lb/>z−x <lb/> = <lb/> z − x <lb/>z − x − ys(z) <lb/>, <lb/> (47) <lb/>provided | <lb/> ys(z) <lb/>z−x <lb/> | &lt; 1. In this case, the expression for the generating function results in an <lb/>integral which can be easily evaluated by the method of residues. <lb/> R <lb/> (α,β)  (x, y) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πiw  (α,β)  (x) <lb/> γ <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (z) <lb/> z − x − ys(z) <lb/> dz = <lb/>1 <lb/> w  (α,β)  (x) <lb/>Res <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (z) <lb/> z − x − ys(z) <lb/>, z  1 <lb/> , (48) <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body> where z  1  is one of the roots (the one closer to x so it is the only one enclosed by γ) of the <lb/>second order polynomial in z in the denominator: z − x − ys(z) = −yz <lb/> 2  + z − (x + y). The <lb/>residue is <lb/>Res <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (z) <lb/> z − x − ys(z) <lb/>, z  1 <lb/> = <lb/> −yw <lb/> (α,β)  (z  1  ) <lb/> 1 − 4y(x + y) <lb/>, <lb/> (49) <lb/>where z  1  = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2y <lb/> (1 − <lb/> 1 − 4y(x + y)). Direct substitution gives the final form for the gener-<lb/>ating function: <lb/> R <lb/> (α,β)  (x, y) = <lb/> y(1 + A <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> β−1  e <lb/> −α cot  −1  A <lb/> (2yA − 1) (1 + x  2  )  β−1  e  −α cot  −1  x  , <lb/> (50) <lb/>where <lb/> A = <lb/>1 − <lb/> 1 − 4y(x + y) <lb/> 2y <lb/> . <lb/> (51) <lb/>The next issue to study is the orthogonality properties inside one family. In contrast with <lb/>the classical orthogonal polynomials, these families are not orthogonal with respect to the <lb/>weight function w <lb/> (α,β)  (x) in the natural interval (−∞, ∞) as the following counterexample <lb/>shows. <lb/>Let us consider the family of polynomials with α = 0 and β = 0 and, within it, the <lb/>polynomials of degree 0 and 2 which, upon substitution in Eqs. (32) and (34), result <lb/> R <lb/> (0,0) <lb/>0 <lb/> (x) = 1, <lb/>(52) <lb/> R <lb/> (0,0) <lb/>2 <lb/> (x) = 2(x <lb/> 2  + 1). <lb/>(53) <lb/>Then, an integral of the form of that in Eq. (12), in the interval (−∞, ∞), takes the form <lb/>  ∞ <lb/>−∞ <lb/> w <lb/> (0,0)  (x)R <lb/> (0,0) <lb/>0 <lb/> (x)R <lb/> (0,0) <lb/>2 <lb/> (x) dx = 2 <lb/>  ∞ <lb/>−∞ <lb/> dx, <lb/>(54) <lb/>which does not converge. Notice that this poses also a problem with the normalization: <lb/>polynomial R <lb/> (0,0) <lb/>2 <lb/> (x), for instance, is not normalizable. The most that can be said is the <lb/>following theorem [2],[4] that we state and prove, which establishes (the so-called finite) <lb/>orthogonality among a few of the polynomials in the family. <lb/>If R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> m <lb/> (x) and R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x), m  = n, are Romanovski polynomials of degree m and <lb/> n respectively, then <lb/>  ∞ <lb/>−∞ <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (x)R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> m <lb/> (x)R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) dx = 0 <lb/>(55) <lb/>if, and only if, m + n &lt; 1 − 2β. <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body> The proof follows the steps of the usual proof of orthogonality of the polynomial solutions of <lb/>hypergeometric equations. Express Eq. (37) in the adjoint form with the aid of the weight <lb/>function (it is possible thanks to the Pearson&apos;s relation in Eq. (7)) for R  m  (x) (in the proof <lb/>we drop the superscripts (α, β) as they are fixed): <lb/>[w(x)s(x)R <lb/> ′ <lb/> m  (x)] <lb/> ′  + λ  m  w(x)R  m  (x) = 0. <lb/>(56) <lb/>Multiply by R  n  (x), and do the same as above but interchange m and n. Then subtract and <lb/>integrate, which leads to <lb/>  ∞ <lb/>−∞ <lb/> {R  n  (x)[w(x)s(x)R <lb/> ′ <lb/> m  (x)] <lb/> ′  − R  m  (x)[w(x)s(x)R <lb/> ′ <lb/> n  (x)] <lb/> ′  } dx <lb/>+ (λ  m  − λ  n  ) <lb/>  ∞ <lb/>−∞ <lb/> w(x)R  m  (x)R  n  (x) dx = 0. (57) <lb/>The second integral is the orthogonality integral of Eq. (12). The first integral, upon in-<lb/>tegration by parts, vanishes except for the boundary terms, so we are left with (because <lb/> λ  m  = λ  n  ) <lb/>  ∞ <lb/>−∞ <lb/> w(x)R  m  (x)R  n  (x) dx = <lb/>1 <lb/> λ  m  − λ  n <lb/> {w(x)s(x)[R  m  (x)R <lb/> ′ <lb/> n  (x) − R <lb/> ′ <lb/> m  (x)R  n  (x)]} <lb/> ∞ <lb/>−∞  . (58) <lb/>The boundary term must be evaluated as <lb/>lim <lb/> x→∞ <lb/> M(x) − lim <lb/> x→−∞ <lb/> M(x), <lb/> (59) <lb/>where <lb/> M(x) = <lb/> (1 + x <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> β  e <lb/> −α cot  −1  x  [R  m  (x)R <lb/> ′ <lb/> n  (x) − R <lb/> ′ <lb/> m  (x)R  n  (x)] <lb/> . <lb/> (60) <lb/>Both limits must exist separately. Notice that the limit of the exponential factor is a positive <lb/>constant (1 or e <lb/> −απ  ). The other factors behave as a power of x with exponent (2β+m+n−1). <lb/>Then, both limits exist if, and only if, this exponent is negative, in which case both are zero, <lb/>as claimed. <lb/>With a similar argument the following is proved, but we omit the explicit proof: <lb/>For the family of polynomials R <lb/> (α,β)  only the polynomials R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) with n &lt; −β <lb/> are normalizable, i.e., the integral <lb/>  ∞ <lb/>−∞ <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (x) <lb/> R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) <lb/>  2  dx, <lb/>(61) <lb/>converges. <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body> So, for the family R <lb/> (α,β)  only the polynomials in a finite subset are normalizable, and only <lb/>a finite number of couples are orthogonal. This type of orthogonality is sometimes called <lb/>finite orthogonality. <lb/> B. The Q  (α,β)  families <lb/> In order to calculate explicitly a polynomial R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) one has to evaluate the nth deriva-<lb/>tive <lb/> d  n <lb/> dx  n <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (x)s(x) <lb/> n <lb/> , step by step: first <lb/> d <lb/>dx <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (x)s(x) <lb/> n <lb/> , then <lb/> d  2 <lb/> dx  2 <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (x)s(x) <lb/> n <lb/> , <lb/>and so on. It is useful to notice the following relation holds <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (x)s(x) <lb/> n  = w <lb/> (α,β+n)  (x), <lb/>(62) <lb/>as can be seen directly in the definitions of w <lb/> (α,β)  (x) and s(x), Eq. (25). Thus, it is enough <lb/>to have an expression for the νth derivative of w <lb/> (α,β)  (x). In looking for it one soon discovers <lb/>the structure of these derivatives: the νth derivative can be factorized as w(x)s(x) <lb/> −ν  and <lb/>a polynomial of degree ν. For instance, it is easy to calculate directly the first derivative <lb/>(compare with Pearson&apos;s ODE (7)) <lb/>d <lb/>dx <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (x) <lb/> = w <lb/> (α,β)  (x)s(x) <lb/> −1  [2(β − 1)x + α]. <lb/> (63) <lb/>By induction, it is easy to prove the statement in general: for fixed α and β, the νth <lb/> derivative, ν ∈ N, of w <lb/> (α,β)  (x) has the form <lb/>d <lb/> ν <lb/> dx  ν <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (x) <lb/> = Q  ν  (x)w <lb/> (α,β)  (x)s(x) <lb/> −ν  , <lb/> (64) <lb/>where Q  ν  (x) is a polynomial of degree ν. The case ν = 0 is trivial, and the case ν = 1 is <lb/>shown in Eq. (63). The step from case ν to ν + 1 is a straightforward derivation. So, for <lb/>given α, β and ν we define the polynomial Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν <lb/> as <lb/> Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν <lb/> (x) ≡ <lb/> s(x) <lb/> ν <lb/> w  (α,β)  (x) <lb/>d <lb/> ν <lb/> dx  ν <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (x) <lb/> . <lb/> (65) <lb/>Using Pearson&apos;s ODE (7) as above the first three polynomials for fixed α and β are <lb/> Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/>0 <lb/> (x) = 1, <lb/>(66) <lb/> Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/>1 <lb/> (x) = 2(β − 1)x + α, <lb/> (67) <lb/> Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/>2 <lb/> (x) = 2(β − 1)(2β − 3)x <lb/> 2  + 2α(2β − 3)x + 2(β − 1) + α <lb/> 2  . <lb/> (68) <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body> By looking at these expressions, and upon comparison with the first three R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) polyno-<lb/>mials, one readily suspects some relation between the polynomials Q  ν  (x) and R  ν  (x). This <lb/>relation indeed exists and is the following. <lb/>The polynomial Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν <lb/> (x) is a Romanovski polynomial, specifically <lb/> Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν <lb/> = R <lb/> (α,β−ν) <lb/> ν <lb/> . <lb/> (69) <lb/>The proof is a straightforward manipulation of Eq. (28), applied to R <lb/> (α,β−ν) <lb/> ν <lb/> with the aid of <lb/>Eq. (62): <lb/> R <lb/> (α,β−ν) <lb/> ν <lb/> (x) = <lb/>1 <lb/> w  (α,β−ν)  (x) <lb/>d <lb/> ν <lb/> dx  ν <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β−ν)  (x)s(x) <lb/> ν <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/> w  (α,β)  (x)s(x)  −ν <lb/> d <lb/> ν <lb/> dx  ν <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (x) <lb/> . <lb/> (70) <lb/>But the last term is precisely the definition of Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν <lb/> (x), Eq. (65). <lb/>We now define the family Q <lb/> (α,β)  as <lb/> Q <lb/> (α,β)  (x) ≡ {Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν <lb/> : ν ∈ N} = {R <lb/> (α,β−ν) <lb/> ν <lb/> : ν ∈ N}. <lb/> (71) <lb/>This family contains Romanovski polynomials with one fixed superscript and the other <lb/>running with the degree. As in the case of the R families, the Q <lb/> (α,β)  family contains one, <lb/>and only one, polynomial of each degree; two different families do not share any polynomial <lb/>in common and the union of all the families gives the whole set of Romanovski polynomials <lb/>(i.e. they constitute another partition of this set). <lb/>We now study the properties of the polynomials in the family Q <lb/> (α,β)  . <lb/>In the first place we give some Rodrigues-looking expressions for the Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν <lb/> polynomials. <lb/>The polynomials in the family Q <lb/> (α,β)  obey the following formulas: <lb/> Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν <lb/> (x) = <lb/>1 <lb/> w  (α,β−ν)  (x) <lb/>d <lb/> ν <lb/> dx  ν <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β−ν)  (x)s(x) <lb/> ν <lb/> , <lb/> (72) <lb/> Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν <lb/> (x) = <lb/>1 <lb/> w  (α,β)  (x)s(x)  −ν <lb/> d <lb/> ν−µ <lb/> dx  ν−µ <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (x)s(x) <lb/> −µ  Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> µ <lb/> (x) <lb/> . <lb/> (73) <lb/>The first one arises right from the definition in Eq. (65) and Eq. (62). For the second <lb/>formula, take µ derivatives of w <lb/> (α,β)  (x) in Eq. (65) and apply the definition of the Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> µ <lb/> (x) <lb/>polynomial. <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body> A second property is the one which makes worthy the definition of the families Q <lb/> (α,β)  , <lb/>for it captures the exact relation between a Romanovski polynomial and its derivative, <lb/>and expresses it in a simple fashion. We already know that if R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) is a Romanovski <lb/>polynomial, so is its derivative, because it is a solution of the same hypergeometric equation <lb/>for the parameters (α, β + 1). So <lb/> dR <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) <lb/>dx <lb/> and R <lb/> (α,β+1) <lb/> n−1 <lb/> (x) must be proportional. Working <lb/>through Eqs. (8), (9) and (31), the exact relation results: <lb/>dR <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) <lb/>dx <lb/>= n(2β + n − 1) R <lb/> (α,β+1) <lb/> n−1 <lb/> (x). <lb/>(74) <lb/>This equation, when expressed in terms of the Q  ν  (x) polynomials, takes the form <lb/>dQ <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν <lb/> (x) <lb/>dx <lb/>= ν(2β + ν − 1) Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν−1  (x), <lb/>(75) <lb/>which tells us that in the family Q <lb/> (α,β)  , each polynomial is the derivative (up to a constant <lb/>factor) of the following polynomial in the same family. <lb/>For a third property, let us note first that the family Q <lb/> (α,β)  obeys the following differential <lb/>recurrence relation: <lb/> Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν+1  (x) = s(x) <lb/> dQ <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν <lb/> (x) <lb/>dx <lb/>+ [2(β + ν − 1)x + α]Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν <lb/> (x). <lb/>(76) <lb/>For a proof, derive the definition of Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν <lb/> (x), Eq. (65), and get <lb/>dQ <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν <lb/> (x) <lb/>dx <lb/>= − <lb/> 1 <lb/>(w  (α,β−ν)  (x))  2 <lb/> dw <lb/> (α,β−ν)  (x) <lb/>dx <lb/>d <lb/> ν  w <lb/> (α,β)  (x) <lb/>dx  ν <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> w  (α,β−ν)  (x) <lb/>d <lb/> ν+1  w <lb/> (α,β)  (x) <lb/>dx  ν+1 <lb/> . <lb/> The second term on the right is s <lb/> −1  (x)Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν+1  (x). The first term in the right, after the <lb/>derivation of w <lb/> (α,β−ν)  (x), gives s <lb/> −1  (x)[2(β − ν − 1)x + α]Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν <lb/> (x). The result arises after <lb/>reordering. Then, the substitution of the derivative formula, Eq. (75), gives a three term <lb/>recurrence relation. <lb/> Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν+1  (x) − [2(β + ν − 1)x + α]Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν <lb/> (x) − ν(2β + ν − 1)(1 + x <lb/> 2  )Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν−1  (x) = 0, <lb/>(77) <lb/>from which the polynomials can be efficiently generated, in contrast to the Rodrigues formu-<lb/>las. A fourth property states that Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν <lb/> (x) is the polynomial solution to the hypergeometric <lb/>differential equation <lb/>(1 + x <lb/> 2  )Q <lb/> ′′  (x) + [2(β − ν)x + α]Q <lb/> ′  (x) + λ  ν  Q(x) = 0, <lb/>(78) <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body> where λ  ν  = −ν(2β − ν − 1). This equation is just the hypergeometric differential equation <lb/>(37) for the polynomial R <lb/> (α,β−ν) <lb/> ν <lb/> (x), which is Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν <lb/> (x), so it is proved. <lb/>The fifth property is that there exists a generating function Q <lb/> (α,β)  (x, y) in closed form <lb/>for the family Q <lb/> (α,β)  , which is an analytic function whose Taylor expansion in the variable <lb/> y is given by <lb/> Q <lb/> (α,β)  (x, y) = <lb/> ∞ <lb/> ν=0 <lb/> y <lb/> ν <lb/> ν! <lb/>Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν <lb/> (x). <lb/>(79) <lb/>By substituting the definition of Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν <lb/> (x), Eq. (65), in previous equation and grouping <lb/>factors and setting z = x + ys(x) we get <lb/> Q <lb/> (α,β)  (x, y) = <lb/>1 <lb/> w  (α,β)  (x) <lb/> ∞ <lb/> ν=0 <lb/> [ys(x)] <lb/> ν <lb/> ν! <lb/> d <lb/> ν <lb/> dx  ν <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (x) <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/> w  (α,β)  (x) <lb/> ∞ <lb/> ν=0 <lb/> (z − x) <lb/> ν <lb/> ν! <lb/> d <lb/> ν <lb/> dz  ν <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (z) <lb/> |  z=x  , <lb/> (80) <lb/>which is a Taylor expansion of the function inside the derivative at the point (x + ys(x)) <lb/> with base point x. Thus, the summation of the series is given by w <lb/> (α,β)  at the point B = <lb/> x + ys(x) = x + y(1 + x <lb/> 2  ). The result is <lb/> Q <lb/> (α,β)  (x, y) = <lb/>(1 + B <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> β−1  e <lb/> −α cot  −1  B <lb/> (1 + x  2  )  β−1  e  −α cot  −1  x  , <lb/> (81) <lb/>from which numerous recursion relations, such as Eq. (77), may be derived as usual [17], <lb/>[18], [19]. <lb/>We now address an orthogonality property of the Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> ν <lb/> (x) polynomials. Polynomials in <lb/>the family Q <lb/> (α,β)  , with β &lt; ε − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> , satisfy the following relation: <lb/>  ∞ <lb/>−∞ <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (x) <lb/> s(x) <lb/> ε <lb/> 2 <lb/> Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> m <lb/> (x) <lb/> s(x) <lb/> m <lb/> 2 <lb/> Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) <lb/> s(x) <lb/> n <lb/> 2 <lb/> dx = 0, <lb/>(82) <lb/>where m  = n and ε = 1 if m + n is odd, and ε = 2 if m + n is even. This is an orthogonality <lb/>integral between the functions Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> m <lb/> /s(x) <lb/> m/2  and Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> /s(x) <lb/> n/2  built on top of the poly-<lb/>nomials in Q <lb/> (α,β)  . In contrast to the orthogonality relations in the R <lb/> (α,β)  families, which <lb/>are valid only for a finite subfamily of polynomials, Eq. (82) applies to the whole family <lb/> Q <lb/> (α,β)  . In terms of the Romanovski polynomials in Eq. (69) the integral in Eq. (82) takes <lb/>the following form <lb/>  ∞ <lb/>−∞ <lb/> w  (α,β−m)  (x) R <lb/> (α,β−m) <lb/> m <lb/> (x) <lb/> w  (α,β−n)  (x) R <lb/> (α,β−n) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) <lb/>1 <lb/> s(x) <lb/> ε <lb/> 2 <lb/> dx = 0, <lb/>(83) <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body> which can be read as orthogonality within the infinite sequence of polynomials R <lb/> (α,β−k) <lb/> k <lb/> with <lb/>a running parameter attached to the polynomial degree. <lb/>In fact, Eq. (82) stands for two different results which require separate proofs. In any <lb/>case, since m  = n, we can take m &gt; n. Let us consider first the case of even m + n. Then, <lb/>the integral of Eq. (82) is <lb/> O  m,n  = <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> −∞ <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (x) <lb/> s(x) <lb/>Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> m <lb/> (x) <lb/> s(x) <lb/> m <lb/> 2 <lb/> Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) <lb/> s(x) <lb/> n <lb/> 2 <lb/> dx. <lb/>(84) <lb/>Upon substitution of Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> m <lb/> (x) by its definition, Eq. (65), we get <lb/> O  m,n  = <lb/>  ∞ <lb/>−∞ <lb/> s(x) <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> (m−n)−1  Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) <lb/>d <lb/> m <lb/> dx  m  w <lb/> (α,β)  (x) dx. <lb/>(85) <lb/>Because m + n is even and m &gt; n, then m − n − 2 is an even, nonnegative, integer. Thus, <lb/> s(x) <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> (m−n)−1  is a polynomial of degree m−n−2 and s(x) <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> (m−n)−1  Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) is a polynomial of <lb/>degree m − 2, which we call P  m−2  . Then, after m − 1 integrations by parts, m − 1 derivatives <lb/>are applied to P  m−2  so it vanishes and we are left only with the boundary terms. <lb/> O  m,n  = <lb/> m−1  <lb/> k=1 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> k−1 <lb/>  d <lb/> k−1  P  m−2  (x) <lb/>dx  k−1 <lb/> d <lb/> m−k  w <lb/> (α,β)  (x) <lb/>dx  m−k <lb/>  ∞ <lb/>−∞ <lb/> . <lb/> (86) <lb/>For each k, the derivative of P  m−2  is a polynomial of degree m − k − 1 whereas the m − k <lb/> derivative of w <lb/> (α,β)  is given in terms of the polynomial Q <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> m−k  , again by its definition in <lb/>Eq. (65). Then, the k boundary term results <lb/>d <lb/> k−1  P  m−2  (x) <lb/>dx  k−1 <lb/> d <lb/> m−k  w <lb/> (α,β)  (x) <lb/>dx  m−k <lb/> = e <lb/> −α cot  −1  x  (1 + x <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> β−m+k−1  <lb/>  2m−2k−1  (x), <lb/>(87) <lb/>where <lb/>  2m−2k−1  is a polynomial of degree 2m − 2k − 1. The asymptotic behavior of this <lb/>term at ±∞ is the same as x <lb/> 2β−3  and, thus, it goes to zero if, and only if, β &lt; <lb/> 3 <lb/>2 <lb/> . <lb/>The proof of the case with (m + n) odd is similar. <lb/> IV. RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN ROMANOVSKI POLYNOMIALS AND JA-<lb/>COBI POLYNOMIALS <lb/> Romanovski and Jacobi polynomials are closely related. In fact, it is common that <lb/>Romanovski polynomials are referred to as complexified Jacobi polynomials [1], [10]. In <lb/>this section we are showing which is the precise relationship between them and which is not: <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body> Romanovski polynomials can indeed be obtained from a generalization of Jacobi polynomials <lb/>to the complex plane, but not through the complexification of Jacobi polynomials, which is <lb/>a different issue. Let us distinguish both concepts. <lb/>For ease of reference, we recall here equations (1) and (2), which are the equations <lb/>Romanovski polynomials and Jacobi polynomials solve, respectively. <lb/>(1 + x <lb/> 2  )R <lb/> ′′  + t(x)R <lb/> ′  + λR = 0, <lb/>(88a) <lb/>(1 − x <lb/> 2  )P <lb/> ′′  + t(x)P <lb/> ′  + λP = 0, <lb/>(88b) <lb/>where t(x) is a polynomial of, at most, first degree. <lb/>The argument of the complexification is based on the fact that the change from x to ix <lb/> transforms the coefficient (1 − x <lb/> 2  ) in Eq. (88b) into (1 + x <lb/> 2  ), the coefficient in Eq. (88a). But <lb/>caution is needed with this idea. Complexification is a transformation which takes real valued <lb/>functions of a real variable into complex functions of a real variable. If g : U ⊂ R → R is <lb/>such a real valued function, defined in an open subset of the real line, we define the function <lb/> g : U <lb/> ′  ⊂ U → C by the recipe (wherever it makes sense) <lb/> g(x) ≡ g(ix). <lb/> (89) <lb/>The new function  g may, or may not, be well defined in all the points of U and may, or may <lb/>not, inherit the continuity and differentiability properties of g in all points of U (think, for <lb/>an instance, of the function g(x) = (1 + x <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> −1  ). In the case g happens to be a polynomial <lb/>it is easy to see that both continuity and differentiability are indeed respected. Then, the <lb/>derivatives of g and  g with respect to x satisfy the following identity: <lb/> g <lb/> (n)  = i <lb/> n  <lb/> g  (n)  , <lb/>n ∈ {0, 1, . . . }. <lb/> (90) <lb/>Complexification respects the sum and product operations, i.e., <lb/> f + g = <lb/> f +  g and <lb/> f g = <lb/> f  g <lb/> (it is a ring homomorphism from a ring of real valued functions of a real variable to the <lb/>ring of complex valued functions of a real variable). Thus, if the function g is a solution <lb/>to a linear differential equation, then  g is a solution of the complexification of that linear <lb/>differential equation. The application of this argument to the Jacobi polynomials gives the <lb/>result that <lb/> P <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) ≡ P <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (ix) verifies the complexification of Eq. (88b), namely <lb/>(1 + x <lb/> 2  )( <lb/> P ) <lb/> ′′  + i t(ix)( <lb/> P ) <lb/> ′  − λ <lb/> P = 0, <lb/>(91) <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body> where the prime still stands for derivative with respect to the real variable x. But equation <lb/>(91) is not the same as equation (88a) unless i t(ix) is real. If we write t(x) = β − α − (α + <lb/> β + 2)x, as is customary in the Jacobi equation (see Eq. (19)), we need (α + β + 2) to be <lb/>real and (β − α) to be imaginary, which is achieved only if α and β are complex and β = α <lb/>  *  . <lb/>Hence we have to consider the functions P <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (ix) with complex parameters α and β which <lb/>are no longer the complexification of the classical Jacobi polynomials as described above. So, <lb/>the complexification of Jacobi polynomials does not result in the Romanovski polynomials. <lb/>But, even in case it did, not all the properties of Jacobi polynomials would be translated to <lb/>properties of Romanovski polynomials: only those which made use of theorems like equation <lb/>(90), which relates the derivatives. For instance, there is no theorem relating integrals of <lb/>a complexified function and the original function; thus, all the properties depending on <lb/>integrations, such as the orthogonality, would have no translation to the complexified version. <lb/>An alternative scenario is to extend the definition of Jacobi polynomials to the complex <lb/>plane: complex variable z, complex parameters α and β and, obviously, complex values. In <lb/>[20] this definition has been successfully given as <lb/> P <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (z) ≡ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  n <lb/>n <lb/> k=0 <lb/>  n + α <lb/>n − k <lb/> n + β <lb/>k <lb/> (1 − z) <lb/> k  (1 + z) <lb/> n−k <lb/> (92) <lb/>or, equivalently, by the Rodrigues formula <lb/> P <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (z) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2  n  n! <lb/> (1 − z) <lb/> −α  (1 + z) <lb/> −β  d <lb/> n <lb/> dz  n <lb/> (1 − z) <lb/> n+α  (1 + z) <lb/> n+β <lb/> , <lb/> (93) <lb/>which are formally the same as the classical ones except now z, α, β ∈ C while n ∈ <lb/>{0, 1, 2, . . . }. These polynomials solve the complex Jacobi ODE <lb/>(1 − z <lb/> 2  )P <lb/> ′′  (z) + [β − α − (α + β + 2)z]P <lb/> ′  (z) + (α + β + 1 + n)nP (z) = 0, <lb/>(94) <lb/>where the prime stands now for the derivative with respect to the complex variable z. <lb/> The specialization of the variable to the imaginary axis, z = ix, and the parameters to <lb/> β = α <lb/>  *  leaves us with Eq. (88a) (notice the change from d/dz to d/dx gives an extra i), so <lb/>these complex Jacobi polynomials solve the differential equation that define the Romanovski <lb/>polynomials. One has to prove now that functions P <lb/> (α,α  *  ) <lb/> n <lb/> (z) restricted to z = ix are real <lb/>valued or, at least, proportional to a real valued one. This is easily achieved by computing <lb/>the complex conjugate of the function P <lb/> (α,α  *  ) <lb/> n <lb/> (ix) in terms of the definition in Eq. (92) <lb/> P <lb/> (α,α  *  ) <lb/> n <lb/> (ix) <lb/>  *  = <lb/>(−1) <lb/> n <lb/> 2  n <lb/>n <lb/> k=0 <lb/>  n + α <lb/>  * <lb/> n − k <lb/> n + α <lb/>k <lb/> (1 + ix) <lb/> k  (1 − ix) <lb/> n−k  . <lb/> (95) <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body> With a change in the summation index from k to l = n − k, we get <lb/> P <lb/> (α,α  *  ) <lb/> n <lb/> (ix) <lb/>  *  = (−1) <lb/> n  P <lb/> (α,α  *  ) <lb/> n <lb/> (ix), <lb/>(96) <lb/>i.e., for even n, P <lb/> (α,α  *  ) <lb/> n <lb/> (ix) is real, while for odd n, it is imaginary. Hence, the combination <lb/> i <lb/> n  P <lb/> (α,α  *  ) <lb/> n <lb/> (ix) is a real function for all n. Finally, because the polynomial solutions of a <lb/>hypergeometric differential equation are unique for each degree, up to a constant factor, <lb/>we conclude that i <lb/> n  P <lb/> (α,α  *  ) <lb/> n <lb/> (ix) is the Romanovski polynomial of degree n with parameters <lb/> −2ℑ(α) and −(ℜ(α) + 1). In other words, complex Jacobi polynomials do provide another <lb/>characterization of the Romanovski polynomials via <lb/> R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) = i <lb/> n  P <lb/> (1−β− <lb/> i <lb/> 2 <lb/> α,1−β+ <lb/> i <lb/> 2 <lb/> α) <lb/>n <lb/> (ix), <lb/>(97) <lb/>(with suitably chosen normalization constants for the Jacobi polynomials). However, this <lb/>alternative characterization is of no help when it comes to study the orthogonality properties, <lb/>because the orthogonality properties of the complex Jacobi polynomials are not well known. <lb/>In [20] the authors state some new results on the orthogonality along some particular paths <lb/>in the complex plane. For instance, in their Eq. (4.3) an orthogonality relation is given <lb/>along the imaginary axis, which is our case, but only for a special case demanding real, not <lb/>integer, parameters, which is not our case. To our knowledge, at the present time there are <lb/>no results concerning the orthogonality of these complex polynomials which would provide <lb/>an alternative approach to the results on orthogonality stated in Subsection III A. <lb/>The argument presented here states that Romanovski polynomials are just a subset of <lb/>complex Jacobi polynomials. Therefore it may seem that Romanovski polynomials are, <lb/>somehow, subordinated to the Jacobi polynomials. But the whole argument could be re-<lb/>versed if we had a definition of complex Romanovski polynomials as the one given in Ref. [20] <lb/>(here reproduced in Eq. (92)). If that would be the case, it would not be surprising to get <lb/>a relation of the form <lb/> P <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) = −(i <lb/> n  )R <lb/> (i(α−β), <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> (α+β)+1) <lb/> n <lb/> (ix), <lb/>where, now, P <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) is a real Jacobi polynomial and R <lb/> (i(α−β), <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> (α+β)+1) <lb/> n <lb/> (ix) would be a <lb/>complex Romanovski polynomial. But, as we do not have such a definition, this last formula <lb/>is nothing but a conjecture. <lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body> V. ROMANOVSKI POLYNOMIALS IN SELECTED QUANTUM MECHANICS <lb/>PROBLEMS <lb/> The Romanovski polynomials are part of the exact solutions of several problems in ordi-<lb/>nary and supersymmetric quantum mechanics. In this section we review a few prominent <lb/>cases. The selection of the examples certainly reflects personal preferences and does not <lb/>pretend to be complete. <lb/>In general, the exactly soluble Schrödinger equations enjoy a special status because most <lb/>of them describe phenomena that play a key role in physics. Suffice it to mention in that <lb/>regard such textbook examples as the description of the spectrum of the hydrogen atom in <lb/>terms of the Coulomb potential [21], or the description of vibrational modes in molecules and <lb/>nuclei in terms of the Hulthen and Morse potentials [22], [23]. More recently, exactly soluble <lb/>potentials acquired importance within the context of supersymmetric quantum mechanics <lb/>(SUSYQM) which considers the special class of Schrödinger equations (H(z) − E)Ψ(z) = 0, <lb/>with H(z) standing for the Hamiltonian (of the one-dimensional, real variable z), and E <lb/> for the energy, which allow [24] a factorization of H(z) according to H(z) = A <lb/> +  (z)A <lb/> −  (z) + <lb/> E  gst  , and A <lb/> −  (z)Ψ  gst  (z) = 0. SUSYQM provides a powerful technique for finding the exact <lb/>solutions of Schrödinger equations. To be specific, any excited state can be obtained by <lb/>the successive action on the ground state, Ψ  gst  (z), of an appropriate number of creation <lb/>operators, A <lb/> +  (z), defined in terms of the so-called superpotential, U(z), as <lb/> A <lb/> ±  (z) ≡ <lb/> ± <lb/> ¯ <lb/> h <lb/> √ 2µ <lb/>d <lb/>dz <lb/>+ U(z) <lb/> . <lb/> Supersymmetric quantum mechanics governs a family of exactly soluble potentials (see <lb/>Refs. [25]– [28] for details) two of which are the so-called hyperbolic Scarf and trigono-<lb/>metric Rosen-Morse potentials, that have been solved recently in [6], [7], [16] in terms of the <lb/>Romanovski polynomials as discussed in the next two subsections. The third subsection is <lb/>devoted to applications of the Romanovski polynomials in random matrix theory. <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body> A. Romanovski polynomials in problems with non-central electric potentials <lb/> The (one-dimensional) Schrödinger equation with the hyperbolic Scarf potential is <lb/> − <lb/> ¯ <lb/> h <lb/> 2 <lb/> 2µ <lb/>d <lb/> 2 <lb/> dz  2  + V  h  (z) − E <lb/> Ψ(z) = 0 , <lb/>V  h  (z) ≡ [B <lb/> 2  − A(A + 1)] <lb/>1 <lb/>cosh <lb/> 2  z <lb/> − B(2A + 1) tanh z <lb/> 1 <lb/>cosh z <lb/>. <lb/> (98) <lb/>This equation appears, among others, in the problem of a particle within a non-central scalar <lb/>potential, a result due to Ref. [9]. In denoting such a potential by V (r, θ), one can make for <lb/>it the specific choice of <lb/> V (r, θ) = V  1  (r) + <lb/> V  2  (θ) <lb/> r  2  , <lb/>V  2  (θ) = −b cot θ. <lb/> (99) <lb/>An interesting phenomenon is the electrostatic non-central potential in which case V  1  (r) is <lb/>the Coulomb potential. The corresponding Schrödinger equation <lb/> − <lb/> ¯ <lb/> h <lb/> 2 <lb/> 2µ <lb/> 1 <lb/> r  2 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂r <lb/>r <lb/> 2  ∂ <lb/>∂r <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> r  2  sin θ <lb/>∂ <lb/>∂θ <lb/> sin θ <lb/>∂ <lb/>∂θ <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> r  2  sin <lb/> 2  θ <lb/>∂ <lb/> 2 <lb/> ∂φ  2 <lb/> + V (r, θ) <lb/> Ψ(r, θ, ϕ) <lb/> = EΨ(r, θ, ϕ) , (100) <lb/>is solved in the standard way by separating variables. As long as the potential does not <lb/>depend on the azimuthal angle, one assumes <lb/>Ψ(r, θ, φ) = R(r)Θ(θ)e <lb/> imφ  . <lb/> (101) <lb/>The radial and angular differential equations for R(r) and Θ(θ) are then found as <lb/> d <lb/> 2  R(r) <lb/> dr  2  + <lb/>2 <lb/> r <lb/>dR(r) <lb/>dr <lb/> + <lb/> 2µ <lb/>¯ <lb/> h <lb/> 2  [V  1  (r) + E] − <lb/> l(l + 1) <lb/> r  2  ) <lb/> R(r) = 0, <lb/>(102) <lb/>and <lb/> d <lb/> 2  Θ(θ) <lb/> dθ  2  + cot(θ) <lb/> dΘ(θ) <lb/>dθ <lb/> + <lb/> l(l + 1) − <lb/> 2µV  2  (θ) <lb/>¯ <lb/> h <lb/> 2 <lb/> − <lb/> m <lb/> 2 <lb/> sin <lb/> 2  θ <lb/> Θ(θ) = 0 , <lb/> (103) <lb/>with l(l + 1) being the separation constant. From now on we will focus on the second <lb/>equation. Notice that for V  2  (θ) = 0, and upon changing variables from θ to cos θ, the last <lb/>equation transforms into the associated Legendre equation and correspondingly <lb/>Θ(θ) <lb/> V  2  (θ)→0 <lb/> − −−−− → P <lb/> m <lb/>l  (cos θ) , <lb/> (104) <lb/></body>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body> an observation that will become important below. <lb/>Following Ref. [9] one begins with substituting the polar angle variable by a new variable, <lb/> z, introduced via θ = f (z), with f to be determined. This leads to the new equation <lb/> d <lb/> 2 <lb/> dz  2  + <lb/> − <lb/> f <lb/> ′′  (z) <lb/> f  ′  (z) <lb/>+ f <lb/> ′  (z) cot f (z) <lb/> d <lb/>dz <lb/> + <lb/> − <lb/> 2µ <lb/>¯ <lb/> h <lb/> 2  V  2  (f (z)) + l(l + 1) − <lb/> m <lb/> 2 <lb/> sin <lb/> 2  f (z) <lb/> f <lb/> ′ 2  (z) <lb/> ψ(z) = 0 (105) <lb/>with f <lb/> ′  (z) ≡ <lb/> df (z) <lb/> dz <lb/> , and ψ(z) defined as ψ(z) ≡ Θ(f (z)). Next one can require that f <lb/> ′  (z) <lb/>approaches zero at z = 0 like sin z, meaning, lim  z→0  f <lb/> ′  (z)/ sin z = 1, and define f (z) via <lb/> f <lb/> ′′  (z) <lb/> f  ′  (z) <lb/>= f <lb/> ′  (z) cot f (z) . <lb/> (106) <lb/>The latter equation is solved by f (z) = 2 tan <lb/> −1  e <lb/> z  . With this relation one finds that <lb/>sin θ = <lb/>1 <lb/>cosh z <lb/>, cos θ = − tanh z , <lb/> (107) <lb/>and consequently, f <lb/> ′  (z) = sin f (z) = sech z. Upon substituting the last relations into <lb/>Eqs. (99), and (105), one arrives at <lb/> d <lb/> 2  ψ(z) <lb/>dz  2  + <lb/> l(l + 1) <lb/>1 <lb/>cosh <lb/> 2  z <lb/> − <lb/> 2µ <lb/>¯ <lb/> h <lb/> 2  b tanh z <lb/> 1 <lb/>cosh z <lb/> − m <lb/> 2 <lb/> ψ(z) = 0 . <lb/> (108) <lb/>In taking in consideration Eqs. (98), (107) one realizes that the letter equation is precisely <lb/>the one-dimensional Schrödinger equation with the hyperbolic Scarf potential and with <lb/> • l(l + 1) playing the role of −(B <lb/> 2  − A(A + 1))/ <lb/> ¯ <lb/> h <lb/> 2  /(2µ) <lb/> , <lb/> • m <lb/> 2  playing the role of −E  n  / <lb/> ¯ <lb/> h <lb/> 2  /(2µ) <lb/> , <lb/> • b playing the role of −B(2A + 1). <lb/>This equation has been solved in terms of the Romanovski polynomials in Ref. [6] upon sub-<lb/>stituting sinh z = x. Notice that there the weight function was defined as (1 + x <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> −p  e <lb/> q tan  −1  x  , <lb/>and the polynomials have been labeled correspondingly as R <lb/> (p,q) <lb/> n <lb/> (x), following [29]. A com-<lb/>parison with Eq. (25) allows identifying p −→ −β + 1, q −→ α. In terms of the notations <lb/>of the present work, the result of Ref. [6] can be cast into the following form: <lb/> ψ  n  (z) = C  n  [1 + (sinh z) <lb/> 2  ] <lb/> β <lb/> 2 <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>4  e <lb/> α <lb/> 2 <lb/> tan  −1  sinh z  R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (sinh z), <lb/>α = −2B, β = −A + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> , E  n  = −(A − n) <lb/> 2  , <lb/> (109) <lb/></body>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body> with C  n  being a normalization constant. Back to the θ variable and in making use of the <lb/>equality x <lb/> def <lb/> := sinh z = − cot θ, we find <lb/>Θ(θ) = ψ  n  (sinh <lb/> 1  (− cot θ)) = C  n  [1 + (cot θ) <lb/> 2  ] <lb/> β <lb/> 2 <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>4  e <lb/> α <lb/> 2 <lb/> tan  −1  (− cot θ)  R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (− cot θ), <lb/> (110) <lb/>showing that the angular part of the exact solution to the non-central potential under con-<lb/>sideration is defined by the Romanovski polynomials. In turning off the non-central piece <lb/>of the potential, the angular part of the solutions will become the standard spherical har-<lb/>monics, Y <lb/> m <lb/>l  (θ, φ) = P <lb/> m <lb/>l  (θ) e <lb/> imφ  , which will produce a relationship between the Romanovski <lb/>polynomials and the associated Legendre functions, an issue to be considered in more detail <lb/>at the end of this section. <lb/>Now, in accord with the theorem on the finite orthogonality of the Romanovski polyno-<lb/>mials in Eq. (55), also only a finite number of eigen-wave functions to the hyperbolic Scarf <lb/>potential appears orthogonal, <lb/>  +∞ <lb/> −∞ <lb/> ψ  n  (z)ψ  m  (z)dz = C  m  C  n <lb/>  +∞ <lb/> ∞ <lb/> w <lb/> (α,β)  (x)R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> m <lb/> (x)R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) = δ  mn  , <lb/>m + n ≤ 2A . <lb/> (111) <lb/>This finite orthogonality reflects the finite number of bound states within the potential under <lb/>consideration. <lb/>Next, it is quite instructive to consider the case of a vanishing V  2  (θ), i.e. b = 0, and <lb/>compare Eq. (108) to Eq. (98) for B = 0. From now on we will give all quantities in units <lb/>of ¯ <lb/> h = 1 = 2µ. In this case <lb/> • Eq. (108) reduces to the equation for the associated Legendre polynomials, P <lb/> m <lb/>l  (cos θ), <lb/> • l becomes A, <lb/> • m <lb/> 2  becomes (l − n) <lb/> 2  , <lb/> • Eq. (98) produces R <lb/> (α=0,β=−l+ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) as part of its solutions, <lb/>which allows one to relate n to l and m as m = l − n. In taking into account Eq. (104) <lb/>together with cot θ = − sinh z provides the following relationship between the associated <lb/>Legendre functions and the Romanovski polynomials <lb/> P <lb/> m <lb/>l  (cos θ) =  const[1  + (cot θ) <lb/> 2  ] <lb/> − <lb/> l <lb/> 2  R <lb/> (0, <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> −l) <lb/> m+l <lb/> (− cot θ) , <lb/>m + l = n ∈ {0, 1, . . . , l}. <lb/> (112) <lb/></body>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body> In substituting the latter equation into the orthogonality integral between the associated <lb/>Legendre functions, <lb/>  1 <lb/> −1 <lb/> P <lb/> m <lb/> l  (cos θ)P <lb/> m <lb/>l  ′  (cos θ) d cos θ = 0, <lb/> l  = l <lb/> ′  , <lb/> (113) <lb/>we find <lb/>  1 <lb/> −1 <lb/> (1 + (cot θ) <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> − <lb/> l+l ′ <lb/> 2  R <lb/> (0, <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> −l) <lb/> l+m <lb/> (− cot θ)R <lb/> (0, <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> −l  ′  ) <lb/> l  ′  +m <lb/> (− cot θ)d cos θ = 0, <lb/> l  = l <lb/> ′  . <lb/> (114) <lb/>The latter relationship amounts to the following orthogonality integral <lb/>  ∞ <lb/>−∞ <lb/> (1 + (sinh z) <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> − <lb/> l+l ′ <lb/> 2  R <lb/> (0, <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> −l) <lb/> n <lb/> (sinh z)R <lb/> (0, <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> −l  ′  ) <lb/> n  ′ <lb/> (sinh z)(sech z) <lb/> 2  dz = <lb/>  ∞ <lb/>−∞ <lb/> w <lb/> (0, <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> −l)  (x)R <lb/> (0, <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> −l) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) <lb/> w <lb/> (0, <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> −l  ′  )  (x)R <lb/> (0, <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> −l  ′  ) <lb/> n  ′ <lb/> (x) <lb/>1 <lb/> s(x) <lb/> dx = 0, <lb/> x = sinh z, l − n = l <lb/> ′  − n <lb/> ′  = m ≥ 0, l  = l <lb/> ′  . (115) <lb/>Careful inspection shows that this equation is nothing but a particular case of the orthogo-<lb/>nality relation in the family of polynomials Q <lb/> (α,β)  , established in Eq. (82) and translated to <lb/>the R <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> n <lb/> notation in Eq. (83). <lb/>A further example is given by the Klein-Gordon equation with equal scalar and vector <lb/>potentials. It has been shown in Ref. [8] that the former can be reduced to the corresponding <lb/>Schrödinger equation. Therefore, in case one uses the hyperbolic Scarf potential in the above <lb/>Klein-Gordon equation, one will face again the Romanovski polynomials as part of its exact <lb/>solutions. <lb/> B. Romanovski polynomials in quark physics. <lb/> The interaction of quarks, the fundamental constituents of the baryons, are governed by <lb/>Quantum Chromodynamics (QCD) which is a non-Abelian gauge theory with gauge bosons <lb/>being the so called gluons. QCD predicts that the quark interactions run from one-to many <lb/>gluon exchanges over gluon self-interactions, the latter being responsible for the so-called <lb/>quark confinement, where highly energetic quarks remain trapped but behave as (asymptot-<lb/>ically) free particles at high energies and momenta. The QCD equations are nonlinear and <lb/></body>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body> FIG. 1: The non-central potential V (r, θ), here displayed in its intersection with the x = 0 plane, <lb/>i.e. for r = <lb/> y  2  + z  2  , and θ = tan  −1 y <lb/> z  . The polar angle part of its exact solutions is expressed in <lb/>terms of the Romanovski polynomials. <lb/> complicated due to the gluonic self-interaction processes and their solution requires employ-<lb/>ment of highly sophisticated techniques such as discretization of space time, so-called lattice <lb/>QCD. Lattice QCD calculations of the properties of hadrons, which are all strongly interact-<lb/>ing composite particles, predict a linear confinement potential with increasing energy. The <lb/>one-gluon exchange potential, which is Coulomb-like, ∼ 1/r, adds to the linear confinement <lb/>potential, ∼ r, a combination that is believed to provide the basic properties of two-body <lb/>(mainly quark-antiquark) systems as concluded from quark model calculations. In contrast <lb/>to this, three quark systems (baryons) have been believed for a long time to involve more <lb/>complicated interactions depending on the internal quark degrees of freedom such as their <lb/>spins, isospins, flavors, and combinations of them, while the potential in coordinate space <lb/>has been considered of lesser relevance and modeled preferably by means of the harmonic <lb/>oscillator. However, in so doing, one encounters the problem of a serious excess of predicted <lb/>baryon excitations in comparison with data [30] (so called &quot; missing resonances &quot; ). <lb/>More recently, the structure of the baryon spectra has been re-analyzed in Refs. [31] with <lb/>the emphasis on the light quark resonances. The result was the observation of a striking <lb/>grouping of resonances with different spins and parities in narrow mass bands separated <lb/></body>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body> by significant spacings. More specifically, it was found that to a very good accuracy, the <lb/>nucleon excitation levels carry the same degeneracies as the levels of the electron with spin <lb/>in the hydrogen atom, though the splittings of the former are quite different from those of <lb/>the latter. Namely, compared to the hydrogen atom, the baryon level splittings contain, in <lb/>addition to the Balmer term, also its inverse but of opposite sign. The same was found to <lb/>be valid for the excitation spectrum of the so called ∆(1232) particle, the most important <lb/>baryon excitation after the nucleon. The appeal of these results lies in the fact that no <lb/>state drops out of the systematics, on the one side, and that the number of &quot; missing &quot; <lb/>states predicted by it is significantly less than within all preceding schemes. The observed <lb/>degeneracies in the spectra of the light quark baryons have been attributed in Ref. [32] to <lb/>the dominance of a quark–antiquark configuration in baryon structure. Within the light of <lb/>these findings, the form of the potential in configuration space acquires importance anew. <lb/>In Refs. [7],[16] the case was made that the trigonometric Rosen-Morse potential provides <lb/>precisely degeneracies and level splittings as required by the light quark baryon spectra. The <lb/>trigonometric Rosen-Morse potential in the parametrization of Ref. [16] reads: <lb/> v  tRM  (z) = −2b cot z + l(l + 1) <lb/>1 <lb/>sin <lb/> 2  z <lb/>, <lb/> (116) <lb/>with l standing for the relative angular momentum between the quark and the di-quark in <lb/>units, as usual, of ¯ <lb/> h = 1 = 2µ, and z = <lb/> r <lb/>d <lb/> is a dimensionless variable built with a suited <lb/>length scale d. <lb/> The reason for the success of this potential in quark physics is that it captures the essential <lb/>traits of the QCD quark-gluon dynamics in interpolating between the Coulomb potential <lb/>(associated with the one-gluon exchange) and the infinite wall potential (associated with the <lb/>trapped but asymptotically free quarks) while passing through a linear confinement region <lb/>(as predicted by lattice QCD) (see Fig. 2). It is quite instructive to perform the Taylor <lb/>expansion of the potential of interest, <lb/> v(z)  tRM  ≈ − <lb/> 2b <lb/> z <lb/> + <lb/>2b <lb/>3 <lb/> z + <lb/> l(l + 1) <lb/> z  2 <lb/> + <lb/> l(l + 1) <lb/>15 <lb/> z <lb/> 2  + ... <lb/> (117) <lb/>This expansion clearly reveals the proximity of the cot term to the Coulomb-plus-linear <lb/>confinement potential, and the proximity of the csc <lb/> 2  term to the standard centrifugal bar-<lb/>rier. The great advantage of the trigonometric Rosen-Morse potential over the linear-plus-<lb/>Coulomb potential is that while the latter is neither especially symmetric, nor exactly soluble, <lb/></body>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body> FIG. 2: The trigonometric Rosen-Morse potential (solid line) and its proximity to the Coulomb-<lb/>plus-linear potential as predicted by lattice QCD (dashed line) for the toy values l = 1, b = 50 of <lb/>the parameters. <lb/> the former is both, it has the dynamical O(4) symmetry (as the hydrogen atom) and is ex-<lb/>actly soluble. The exact solutions of the, now three dimensional, Schrödinger equation with <lb/> v  tRM  (z) from Eq. (116) have been constructed in [16] on the basis of the one-dimensional <lb/>solutions found in [7] and read: <lb/> ψ  n  (cot <lb/> −1  x) = (1 + x <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> − <lb/> n+l <lb/> 2  e <lb/> − <lb/> b <lb/>n+l+1 <lb/> cot  −1  x  C <lb/> (−(n+l)+1, <lb/> 2b <lb/> n+l+1  ) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) , <lb/> (118) <lb/>with x = cot z. The C polynomials from [7] are Romanovski polynomials but with parame-<lb/>ters that depend on the degree of the polynomial. The following identification is valid: <lb/> C <lb/> (−(n+l)+1, <lb/> 2b <lb/> n+l+1 <lb/> ) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) ≡ R <lb/> (αn,βn) <lb/> n <lb/> (x), <lb/> α  n  = <lb/>2b <lb/> n + l + 1 <lb/> , β  n  = −(n + l) + 1, n ∈ {0, 1, 2, . . . } <lb/> (119) <lb/>The Schrödinger wave functions are orthogonal, as they are eigenfunctions of a Hamilton <lb/>operator. Their orthogonality integral (here in z space) reads <lb/>  π <lb/> 0 <lb/> dz ψ  n  (z)ψ  n  ′  (z) = δ  nn  ′  . <lb/> (120) <lb/>The orthogonality of the wave functions ψ  n  (z) implies in x space orthogonality of the <lb/> R <lb/> (αn,βn) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) polynomials with respect to w <lb/> (αn,βn)  (x) <lb/> dz <lb/>dx <lb/> due to the variable change. As long as <lb/></body>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body> d cot  −1  x <lb/>dx <lb/> = −1/(1 + x <lb/> 2  ) = −1/s(x) then the orthogonality integral takes the form <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> −∞ <lb/> dx <lb/>s(x) <lb/> w  (αn,βn)  (x)R <lb/> (αn,βn) <lb/> n <lb/> (x) <lb/> w  (α  n ′  ,β  n ′  )  (x)R <lb/> (α  n ′  ,β  n ′  ) <lb/> n  ′ <lb/> (x) = δ  nn  ′  . <lb/> (121) <lb/>To recapitulate, the Romanovski polynomials have been shown to be important ingredients <lb/>of the wave functions of quarks in accord with QCD quark-gluon dynamics. <lb/> C. Romanovski polynomials in random matrix theory <lb/> Random matrix theory was pioneered by Wigner [33] for the sake of modeling spectra <lb/>of heavy nuclei which are characterized by complicated interactions between large numbers <lb/>of protons and neutrons. Wigner&apos;s idea was to limit the infinite dimensional Hamiltonian <lb/>matrix in configuration space to a finite, real quadratic (N × N), and symmetric, matrix <lb/>with elements being chosen at random from a suitable probability density distribution, say, <lb/>the Gaussian one. Along this line one can then model the densities of the nuclear states <lb/>as averages over the weighted sets of matrices. The advantage of this method is that as <lb/> N −→ ∞, the (normalized) eigenvalues of any randomly chosen matrix approach the limits <lb/>of the corresponding system averages, much like the general limit theorem. The probability <lb/>density distribution (p.d.f.) of the eigenvalues of the Gaussian ensemble of random matrices <lb/>is given by (the presentation in this section closely follows Ref. [34]): <lb/>1 <lb/> C  N <lb/> e <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/> 2 <lb/> P  N <lb/>j=1  λ  2 <lb/> j <lb/> 1≤j&lt;k≤N <lb/> |λ  k  − λ  j  |, <lb/> (122) <lb/>where C  N  is the normalization constant and λ  i  are the eigenvalues. Besides the Gaussian <lb/>random ensemble there are other random matrix ensembles under consideration in quantum <lb/>physics such as the circular Jacobi ensemble and the Cauchy ensemble, and precisely these <lb/>are of interest in the present section. However, their definitions require us to go beyond <lb/>the ensembles of random real matrices and consider matrices with complex entries. To be <lb/>more specific, one considers random ensembles composed by symmetric, unitary matrices, in <lb/>which case the theory is not developed from an explicit distribution density function for their <lb/>elements but rather from the requirement of the existence of a certain appropriate uniform <lb/>measure. The random unitary matrix ensemble is special not only because it forms a group <lb/>but mainly because this group is compact and allows for the definition of the so called Haar <lb/> volume, which then provides the uniform measure on the space as required above. <lb/></body>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<body> Definition: The circular unitary ensemble is the group of unitary matrices U <lb/> endowed with the volume form (d  H  U) = <lb/> 1 <lb/> C <lb/> U <lb/>  †  U <lb/> = idM  2  with M  2  hermitian. <lb/>The eigenvalues of the circular ensembles are confined to the unit circle, i.e. to λ  j  = e <lb/> iθ  j <lb/> with −π &lt; θ  j  &lt; π. The associated probability density distribution of the eigenvalues is then <lb/>given by <lb/>1 <lb/> C <lb/> 1≤j&lt;k≤N <lb/> |e <lb/> iθ  k  − e <lb/> iθ  j  | , <lb/> −π &lt; θ  l  &lt; π . <lb/> (123) <lb/>More generally, an ensemble of unitary and symmetric matrices has an eigenvalues p.d.f of <lb/>the form (in the notations of Ref. [34]) <lb/> N <lb/> l=1 <lb/> w  2  (z  l  ) <lb/> 1≤j≤k≤N <lb/> |z  k  − z  j  |, <lb/> z = e <lb/> iθ  = e <lb/> 2πix <lb/> L  , θ ∈ [0, 2π), x ∈ [0, L) , <lb/> (124) <lb/>where w  2  (z  l  ) is a specific weight function. The circular Jacobi ensemble is specified by <lb/> w  2  (z) = |1 − z| <lb/> 2a  . <lb/> (125) <lb/>A relevant research goal in quantum physics is finding the spacings in the spectra of the <lb/>circular Jacobi ensemble. Compared to the state densities, the calculation of gap proba-<lb/>bilities in the spectra deserves special efforts. In this section we review briefly the concept <lb/>for the calculation of gap probabilities in the circular Jacobi ensemble by means of the so <lb/>called Cauchy random matrix ensemble, a venue that will conduct us one more time to the <lb/>Romanovski polynomials . <lb/>To begin with, one considers the mapping <lb/> e <lb/> iθ  = <lb/>1 + iλ <lb/> 1 − iλ <lb/>, <lb/> (126) <lb/>which maps each point λ on the real line to a point θ on the unit circle (measured anticlock-<lb/>wise from the origin) via a stereographic projection. Changing correspondingly variables in <lb/>Eqs. (124)–(125) amounts to the following eigenvalue p.d.f.: <lb/> N <lb/> l=1 <lb/> (1 + λ <lb/> 2 <lb/> j  ) <lb/> −N −a <lb/> 1≤j≤k≤N <lb/> |λ  k  − λ  j  | , <lb/>λ  j  ∈ (−∞, +∞) . <lb/> (127) <lb/></body>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body> As long as one recognizes in the weight function the Cauchy weight, the random unitary <lb/>matrix ensemble generated this way is termed the Cauchy ensemble. On the other hand, <lb/>a comparison with the weight function of the Romanovski polynomials reveals the Cauchy <lb/>weight as w <lb/> (0,−N −a+1)  (x), an observation that will acquire a profound importance in the <lb/>following. <lb/>Back to the main goal, the gap probability, or better, the probability for no eigenvalues <lb/>in a region I, denoted by E(0, I), and for the case of any ensemble is now calculated as [34] <lb/> E(0, I) = 1 + <lb/> ∞ <lb/> n=1 <lb/> (−1) <lb/> n <lb/> n! <lb/> I <lb/> dx  1  ... <lb/> I <lb/> dx  n  det <lb/> N −1 <lb/> l=0 <lb/> w  2  (x  i  )p  l  (x  i  ) <lb/> w  2  (x  j  )p  l  (x  j  ) , <lb/> (128) <lb/>where p  l  (x) with l = 0, 1, 2, ... stand for the orthogonal polynomials associated with the <lb/>weight function w  2  (x). In other words, knowing the orthogonal polynomials is crucial for <lb/>the calculation of gap probabilities in any random matrix ensemble. In the specific case under <lb/>consideration, one seems to have two options in the choice for those polynomials, Romanovski <lb/>versus Jacobi polynomials in accord with their relationship established in Eq. (97). The <lb/>choice is clearly in favor of the Romanovski polynomials because the formalism developed <lb/>for calculating E(0, I) (see Ref. [35] for details) is based on real coupled differential equations. <lb/> In choosing the Romanovski polynomials one, to speak with the authors of Ref. [34], avoids <lb/>the clumsy and unnecessary work of recasting the formalism on the circle, i.e. in terms of <lb/>the complexified Jacobi polynomials. In summary, the Romanovski polynomials (termed <lb/>Cauchy weight polynomials in Ref. [34]) provide a natural and comfortable tool for finding <lb/>all the results for the circular Jacobi ensemble from those of the Cauchy ensemble. <lb/> VI. ON THE ORTHOGONALITY RELATIONS <lb/> We have shown in the previous sections not one but several different orthogonality rela-<lb/>tions among the Romanovski polynomials. In this section we comment on this issue. <lb/>First we have shown, in Eq. (55), a finite orthogonality in the family R <lb/> (α,β)  (that of <lb/>polynomials with fixed parameters α and β). It is the equivalent relation to the well known <lb/>orthogonality of the Hermite, Laguerre and Jacobi polynomials, except that in these cases, <lb/>there is complete orthogonality. The finite orthogonality, however, is required as such in <lb/>the solution of the wave eigenfunctions of the hyperbolic Scarf potential, see Eq. (111) in <lb/>subsection V A or Ref. [6]: in this case only a finite number of states are bounded; precisely <lb/></body>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<body> those which are normalizable. The orthogonality relation in the Q <lb/> (α,β)  family, Eq. (82), <lb/>is a complete, not finite, orthogonality: it is valid for all the polynomials in the family. <lb/>The difference with the previous is that the Q <lb/> (α,β)  family is made up with Romanovski <lb/>polynomials with one fixed parameter but the other running attached to the degree. This <lb/>different orthogonality also find its application in, for instance, Eq. (115) in subsection V A. <lb/>Finally another physics problem, the eigenfunctions of the trigonometric Rosen-Morse <lb/>potential studied in [7] and [10] and revised in Subsection V B, has given rise to yet another <lb/>orthogonality relation: the one in Eq. (121), which is very similar to the orthogonality <lb/>in the Q <lb/> (α,β)  family, but not equivalent. The polynomials involved in Eq. (121) have both <lb/>parameters, α and β running with the degree, as shown in Eq. (119). This last orthogonality <lb/>is proved not directly as the others, but by means of the Schrödinger equation where it comes <lb/>from: as the functions involved are the eigenfunctions of a self-adjoint operator, they are <lb/>orthogonal. Here, thus, it seems as if the Schrödinger equation carefully chooses, from <lb/>the set of all Romanovski polynomials, another family with a special combination between <lb/>parameters and degrees such that another orthogonality relation surfaces. This kind of fine <lb/>tuned combination of parameters is not completely new. Here is a well known instance: the <lb/>radial part of the well-known solution of the hydrogen atom, which is given by <lb/> R  nl  (x  n  ) = N  nl <lb/> x <lb/> β l <lb/> 2 <lb/> n <lb/> √ x  n <lb/> e <lb/> − <lb/> xn <lb/> 2  L <lb/> (1,β  l  ) <lb/> n−l−1  (x  n  ), β  l  = 2l + 1, x  n  = a  n  r, <lb/> (129) <lb/>where x  n  is the dimensionless but n dependent variable (see also Problem 13.2.11 in Ref. [19]), <lb/>while r is the radial one. Here L <lb/> (α,β) <lb/> m <lb/> (x) is the generalized Laguerre polynomial of degree <lb/> m as introduced after Eq. (17). Notice that Laguerre polynomials of different degrees in <lb/>Eq. (129) emerge within different potential strengths, Ze <lb/> 2  /a  n  , and, henceforth, the orthog-<lb/>onality relation given by the Schrödinger equation <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> 0 <lb/> x <lb/> β l <lb/> 2 <lb/> n <lb/> √ x  n <lb/> e <lb/> − <lb/> xn <lb/> 2  L <lb/> (1,β  l  ) <lb/> m  (n,l) <lb/> (x  n  ) <lb/> x <lb/> β l <lb/> 2 <lb/> n  ′ <lb/> √ x  n  ′ <lb/> e <lb/> − <lb/> x n ′ <lb/> 2  L <lb/> (1,β  l  ) <lb/> m  (n ′ ,l) <lb/> (x  n  ′  ) x <lb/> 2 <lb/> n  dx  n  = 0, <lb/> β  k  = 2k + 1, m  (n,k)  = n − k − 1, n  = n <lb/> ′  , x  n  ′  = <lb/> a  n  ′ <lb/> a  n <lb/> x  n  , <lb/> (130) <lb/>is not equivalent to the orthogonality given by the weight function, Eq. (18), here restated <lb/>for α = 1 <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> 0 <lb/> x <lb/> β <lb/> 2  e <lb/> − <lb/> x <lb/> 2  L <lb/> (1,β) <lb/> m  (x)x <lb/> β <lb/> 2  e <lb/> − <lb/> x <lb/> 2  L <lb/> (1,β) <lb/> m  ′  (x)dx = 0, <lb/> m  = m <lb/> ′  , β &gt; 0. <lb/>(131) <lb/></body>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body> In particular, notice that Eq. (131), when β ∈ N, is recovered from Eq. (130) in the case <lb/> l <lb/> ′  = l, but for β / <lb/> ∈ N both formulas are completely different. <lb/>In the Introduction we said that, perhaps, the lack of general orthogonality of Romanovski <lb/>polynomials has been seen as a weakness and because of it they have not attracted as much <lb/>attention as the classical orthogonal polynomials. Now we have shown that, far from being <lb/>a weakness, the various orthogonality relations of Romanovski polynomials give them new <lb/>appealing properties which widens their possible applications. <lb/> VII. CONCLUSIONS <lb/> We have presented a fairly complete description of the Romanovski polynomials as so-<lb/>lutions of the hypergeometric differential equation (1), properties derived from it and some <lb/>applications, with the following prominent items: <lb/>1. We have described a complete classification of the hypergeometric differential equations <lb/>in order to place Eq. (1) in its proper context. <lb/>2. We have described completely, in Eq. (28) the polynomial solutions to Eq. (1), which <lb/>are the Romanovski polynomials. We have also stated some known and some new <lb/>properties of these polynomials. We have proposed different partitions of the set of <lb/>all Romanovski polynomials into families which allows one to express the plethora of <lb/>properties in a simpler and more ordered form. This approach can be applied as well to <lb/>the other four classes of polynomial solutions of hypergeometric equations: Hermite, <lb/>Laguerre, Jacobi and Bessel. <lb/>3. In particular we have stated exact results about several orthogonality relations among <lb/>the Romanovski polynomials. We have shown that a family of Romanovski polynomi-<lb/>als, solutions to the same hypergeometric equation, is not completely orthogonal, but <lb/>exhibits a finite orthogonality, Eq. (55). However, we have found two other orthog-<lb/>onality relations, in families with running parameters (attached to the degree of the <lb/>polynomial) which provide infinite orthogonality, Eqs. (82) and (121). <lb/>4. The relationship between Romanovski polynomials and Jacobi polynomials has been <lb/>precisely stated: Romanovski polynomials cannot be obtained as just a complexifi-<lb/>cation of Jacobi polynomials (i.e., change x by ix), but they can be realized as a <lb/></body>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<body> particularization of complex Jacobi polynomials (an extension to the complex plane <lb/>with complex parameters). Yet, despite this relation, these complex Jacobi polyno-<lb/>mials are not completely understood so, for instance, the orthogonality properties of <lb/>Romanovski polynomials cannot be derived, at the present time, from properties of <lb/>the Jacobi polynomials. <lb/>5. We have presented three instances of the use of Romanovski polynomials in actual <lb/>physics problems. In particular the polynomials introduced in [7] and [6] are recognized <lb/>as Romanovski polynomials. The orthonormality relations shown in these references <lb/>are explained in this context. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments <lb/> We thank Cliffor Compean for various constructive discussions on the orthogonality issue, <lb/>José-Luis López Bonilla for communicating to us some relevant references, and Yuri Neretin <lb/>for a valuable correspondence on Romanovski&apos;s biographical data. Work partly supported <lb/>by Consejo Nacional de Ciencia y Tecnología (CONACyT, Mexico) under grant number <lb/>C01-39820. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> [1] E. J. Routh: &quot; On some properties of certain solutions of a differential equation of second <lb/>order &quot; , Proc. London Math. Soc., Vol. 16, (1884), pp. 245-261. <lb/>[2] V. Romanovski: &quot; Sur quelques classes nouvelles de polynomes orthogonaux &quot; , C. R. Acad. Sci. <lb/>Paris, Vol. 188, (1929), pp. 1023-1025. <lb/>[3] A. F. Nikiforov and V. B. Uvarov: Special Functions of Mathematical Physics, Birkhäuser <lb/>Verlag, Basel, 1988. <lb/>[4] P. A. Lesky: &quot; Endliche und unendliche Systeme von kontinuierlichen klassischen Orthogo-<lb/>nalpolynomen &quot; , Z. Angew. Math. Mech., Vol. 76, (1996), pp. 181-184. <lb/>[5] H. J. Weber: &quot; Connections between real polynomial solutions of hypergeometric-type differen-<lb/>tial equations with Rodrigues formula &quot; , C.E.J.Math. (2007), DOI-10.2478/s115333-007-0004-<lb/>6. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 35 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [6] D.E. Alvarez-Castillo and M. Kirchbach: &quot; Exact spectrum and wave functions of the hy-<lb/>perbolic Scarf potential in terms of finite Romanovski polynomials &quot; , E-Print Archive: <lb/>quant-ph/0603122. <lb/> [7] C. B. Compean and M. Kirchbach: &quot; The trigonometric Rosen-Morse potential in supersym-<lb/>metric quantum mechanics and its exact solutions &quot; , J. Phys. A:Math.Gen., Vol. 39, (2006), <lb/>pp. 547-557, and refs. therein. <lb/>[8] Wen-Chao Qiang: &quot; Bound states of Klein-Gordon equation for ring-shaped harmonic oscil-<lb/>lator scalar and vector potentials &quot; , Chinese Physics, Vol. 12, (2003), pp. 136-139; Wen-Chao <lb/>Qiang and Shi-Hai Dong, &quot; SUSYQM and SWKB approaches to the relativistic equations with <lb/>hyperbolic potential V  0  tanh <lb/> 2  (r/d) &quot; , Physica Scripta, Vol. 72, (2005), pp. 127-131. <lb/>[9] R. Dutt, A. Gangopadhyaya and U. P. Sukhatme: &quot; Non-Central potentials and spherical <lb/>harmonics using supersymmetry and shape invariance &quot; , Am. J. Phys., Vol. 65, (1997), pp. <lb/>400-403; E-Print Archive: hep-th / 9611087. <lb/> [10] N. Cotfas: &quot; Systems of orthogonal polynomials defined by hypergeometric type equations <lb/>with application to quantum mechanics &quot; , C. E. J. P., Vol. 2, (2004), pp. 456-466. N. Cotfas: <lb/> &quot; Shape invariant hypergeometric type operators with application to quantum mechanics &quot; , <lb/>E-Print Archive: math-ph/0603032. <lb/> [11] G. Szegö: Orthogonal Polynomials, American Math. Soc. Vol. XXIII, Prov., RI, 1939. <lb/>[12] M. E. H. Ismail: Classical and Quantum Orthogonal Polynomials in One Variable, Cambridge <lb/>Univ. Press, 2005. <lb/>[13] H. L. Krall and O. Fink: &quot; A new class of orthogonal polynomials: The Bessel polynomials &quot; , <lb/>Trans. Amer. Math. Soc., Vol. 65, (1948), pp. 100-115. <lb/>[14] A. Zarzo-Altarejos: &quot; Differential equations of the hypergeometric type &quot; , (in Spanish), Ph. D. <lb/>thesis, Faculty of Science, University of Granada, 1995. <lb/>[15] R. Askey: &quot; Beta integrals and the associated orthogonal polynomials &quot; , in Number Theory, <lb/> Madras, Vol. 1395 of Lecture Notes in Math., Springer, Berlin, 1987, pp. 84-121. <lb/>[16] C.B. Compean and M. Kirchbach: &quot; Angular momentum dependent quark potential of QCD <lb/>traits and dynamical O(4) symmetry &quot; , Bled Workshops in Physics, Vol. 7, (2006), pp. 7-19; <lb/>E-Print Archive: quant-ph/0610001; <lb/> C. Compean, M. Kirchbach, &quot; The trigonometric Rosen-Morse potential as a prime candidate <lb/>for an effective QCD potential &quot; , AIP Conf. Proc., Vol. 857, (2006) pp. 275-278. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 36 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [17] P. Dennery and A. Krzywicki: Mathematics for Physicists, Dover, New York, 1996. <lb/>[18] M. Abramowitz and I.A. Stegun: Handbook of Mathematical Functions with Formulas, Graphs <lb/>and Mathematical Tables, Dover, 2nd edition, New York, 1972. <lb/>[19] G. B. Arfken and H. J. Weber: Mathematical Methods for Physicists, 6th ed., Elsevier-<lb/>Academic Press, Amsterdam, 2005. <lb/>[20] A. B. J. Kuijlaars, A. Martínez-Finkelshtein and R. Orive: &quot; Orthogonality of Jacobi poly-<lb/>nomials with general parameters &quot; , Electronic Transactions on Numerical Analysis, Vol. 19, <lb/>(2003), pp. 1-17. <lb/>[21] W. Greiner and B. Müller: Quantum Mechanics: Symmetries, Springer, 2nd rev. ed., Berlin-<lb/>Heidelberg, 2004; <lb/>G. F. Torres del Castillo and J. L. Calvario Acócal: &quot; On the dynamical symmetry of the <lb/>quantum Kepler problem &quot; , Rev. Mex. Fis., Vol. 44, No. 4, (1998), pp. 344-352. <lb/>[22] V. C. Aguilera-Navarro, E. Ley-Koo and S. Mateos-Cortés: &quot; Vibrational-rotational analysis of <lb/>the Hulthen potential using hydrogenic eigenfunction bases &quot; , Rev. Mex. Fis., Vol. 44, (1998), <lb/>pp. 413-419. <lb/>[23] F. Iachello and R. D. Levine: Algebraic Theory of Molecules, Oxford Univ. Press, New York, <lb/>1992. <lb/>[24] P. M. Morse and H. Feshbach: Methods of Theoretical Physics, Part I, McGraw-Hill Book <lb/>Company, Inc., New York, 1953. <lb/>[25] C. V. Sukumar: &quot; Supersymmetric quantum mechanics of one-dimensional systems &quot; , J. Phys. <lb/>A:Math. Gen., Vol. 18, (1985), pp. 2917-2936 ; <lb/>C. V. Sukumar: &quot; Supersymmetric quantum mechanics and its applications &quot; , in AIP Proc., <lb/>Vol. 744, eds. R. Bijker et al. Supersymmetries in Physics and Applications, New York, 2005, <lb/>pp. 166 -235. <lb/>[26] F. Cooper, A. Khare and U. P. Sukhatme: Supersymmetry in Quantum Mechanics, World <lb/>Scientific, Singapore, 2001. <lb/>[27] G. Lévai: &quot; A search for shape invariant solvable potentials &quot; , J. Phys. A:Math.Gen., Vol. 22, <lb/>(1989), pp. 689-702. <lb/>[28] B. Bagchi and R. Roychoudhury: &quot; A new PT-symmetric complex Hamiltonian with a real <lb/>spectrum &quot; , J. Phys. A:Math.Gen., Vol. 33, (2000), L1-L3. <lb/>[29] W. Koepf and M. Masjed-Jamei: &quot; A generic polynomial solution for the differential equation <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 37 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> of hypergeometric type and six sequences of orthogonal polynomials &quot; , Integral Transforms <lb/>and Special Functions, Vol. 17, (2006), pp.559-576.; <lb/>M. Masjed-Jamei: &quot; Classical orthogonal polynomials with weight function ((ax + b)  2  + (cx + <lb/> d)  2  )  −p  exp(q arctan <lb/> ax+b <lb/> cx+d  ), x ∈ (−∞, +∞) and generalization of T and F distributions &quot; , Inte-<lb/>gral Transforms and Special Functions, Vol. 15, (2002), pp. 137-153. <lb/> [30] Particle Data Group, S. Eidelman et al., &quot; Review of particle physics &quot; , Phys. Lett. B, Vol. 592, <lb/>(2004), pp. 1. <lb/>[31] M. Kirchbach: &quot; On the parity degeneracy of baryons &quot; , Mod. Phys. Lett. A, Vol. 12, (1997), <lb/>pp. 2373-2386. <lb/>[32] M. Kirchbach, M. Moshinsky and Yu. F. Smirnov: &quot; Baryons in O(4) and vibron model &quot; , Phys. <lb/>Rev. D, Vol. 64, (2001), pp. 114005-1-114005-11. <lb/>[33] E. P. Wigner: &quot; Characteristic vectors of bordered matrices with infinite dimensions &quot; , Ann. <lb/>Math., Vol. 62, (1955), pp. 548-564. <lb/>[34] N. S. Witte and P. J. Forrester: &quot; Gap probabilities in the finite and scaled Caushy random <lb/>matrix ensembles &quot; , Nonlinearity, Vol. 13, (2000), pp. 1965-1986. <lb/>P. J. Forrester: Random Matrices in Log Gases, http://www.ms.unimelb.edu.au/˜ math-<lb/>pjf/mathpjf.html (book in preparation). <lb/>[35] C. A. Tracy and H. Widom: &quot; Fredholm determinants, differential equations, and matrix <lb/>models &quot; , Commun. Math. Phys., Vol. 163, (1994), pp. 33-72. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 38 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
