<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="footnote"> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 1 <lb/></note>

			<front> International Journal of Modern Physics A <lb/>Vol. 30, No. 9 (2015) 1550043 (29 pages) <lb/>c <lb/> World Scientific Publishing Company <lb/>DOI: 10.1142/S0217751X15500438 <lb/> Complex potential and bottomonium suppression at LHC energy <lb/> Uttam Kakade,  *  Binoy Krishna Patra  †  and Lata Thakur  ‡ <lb/> Department of Physics, Indian Institute of Technology Roorkee, 247 667, India <lb/>  *  usk11dph@iitr.ac.in <lb/>  †  binoyfph@iitr.ac.in <lb/>  ‡  lata1dph@iitr.ac.in <lb/> Received 29 October 2014 <lb/>Revised 16 January 2015 <lb/>Accepted 22 January 2015 <lb/>Published 18 March 2015 <lb/>We have studied the thermal suppression of the bottomonium states in relativistic heavy-<lb/>ion collision at LHC energies as function of centrality, rapidity, transverse momentum. <lb/>First, we address the effects of the nonperturbative confining force and the momentum <lb/>anisotropy together on heavy quark potential at finite temperature, which are resolved <lb/>by correcting both the perturbative and nonperturbative terms of the potential at T = 0 <lb/>in a weakly-anisotropic medium, not its perturbative term alone as usually done in the <lb/>literature. Second, we model the expansion of medium by the Bjorken hydrodynamics in <lb/>the presence of both shear and bulk viscosity, followed by an additional pre-equilibrium <lb/>anisotropic evolution. Finally, we couple them together to quantify the yields of bottomo-<lb/>nium production in nucleus–nucleus collisions at LHC energies and found a better agree-<lb/>ment with the CMS data. Our estimate of the inclusive Υ(1S) production indirectly <lb/>constrains both the uncertainties in isotropization time and the shear-to-entropy den-<lb/>sity ratio and favors the values as 0.3 fm/c and 0.3 (perturbative result), respectively. <lb/> Keywords: Bottomonium states; nonperturbative effects; thermal suppression; aniso-<lb/>tropy; pre-equilibrium; isotropization; viscous forces. <lb/>PACS numbers: 12.39.−x, 11.10.St, 12.38.Mh, 12.39.Pn, 12.39.Hg, 12.38.Gc <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> The experimental heavy ion programs at SPS, RHIC and LHC open up an window <lb/>into the phase diagram of QCD in the region of small baryon density. Lattice calcula-<lb/>tions <lb/> 1  predict a crossover transition for temperatures ranging from 150 to 200 MeV. <lb/>From experimental point of view, the properties of the medium can be characterized <lb/>by either through its bulk properties or the hard probes. Heavy quarkonium has <lb/>been one of the most actively investigated hard probes in this connection. Matsui <lb/>and Satz <lb/> 2  first proposed the idea of Debye screening of the potential between a <lb/>heavy quark and a heavy antiquark, which causes the suppression of the yields of <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-1 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 2 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> U. Kakade, B. K. Patra &amp; L. Thakur <lb/></note>

			<body> heavy quarkonium states in relativistic heavy-ion collisions. This is indeed observed <lb/>at SPS, RHIC and LHC in the dilepton spectrum. <lb/> 3–5  Nowadays, the dissociation <lb/>mechanism identified is known as Landau-damping, <lb/> 6  when a light parton of the <lb/>medium (either gluon or quark) scatters off the bound state by exchanging gluons <lb/>and dissociates it into an unbound color octet. The current consensus is that the <lb/>experimental results cannot be explained by the cold nuclear matter effects alone, <lb/>therefore the effects of hot nuclear matter are still under investigation. Moreover <lb/>the LHC results have opened up the possibility of the cleaner bottomonium probe <lb/>with the availability of quality data on the Υ resonances, <lb/> 4  which is the central <lb/>theme of our work. <lb/>A large number of studies on the in-medium dynamics of the Q ¯ <lb/> Q bound states <lb/>has been carried out with phenomenological potential models, <lb/> 7  where all medium <lb/>effects are encoded in a temperature dependent potential with nonperturbative <lb/>inputs taken from lattice simulations. The derivation of such models from QCD was <lb/>however not established. However, lattice calculations of free energies and other <lb/>quantities <lb/> 8,9  obtained from the correlation functions of Polyakov loop are often <lb/>taken as input for the potential. Although these quantities have been thought to <lb/>be related to the color-singlet and color-octet heavy quark potentials at finite tem-<lb/>perature <lb/> 9,10  a precise answer is still missing. <lb/> 11  Recently, quarkonium at finite tem-<lb/>perature has been studied by taking advantage of the nonrelativistic and thermal <lb/>energy scales that characterize the system. There are different scales in the heavy <lb/>quark bound state problem related to the heavy quark mass m  Q  , the exchange <lb/>of momentum ∼ m  Q  v  Q  and the binding energy ∼ m  Q  v <lb/> 2 <lb/> Q  . Since the heavy quark <lb/>velocity, v  Q  in the bound state is considered to be a small parameter, so these scales <lb/>are hierarchically ordered: m  Q  ≫ m  Q  v  Q  ≫ m  Q  v <lb/> 2 <lb/> Q  . Similarly the thermal scales are <lb/>also hierarchically related: T ≫ gT ≫ g <lb/> 2  T in weak coupling regime. Integrating <lb/>out the successive energy scales lead to a sequence of low-energy effective field theo-<lb/>ries (EFTs) <lb/> 12,13  viz. nonrelativistic QCD (NRQCD), potential nonrelativistic QCD <lb/>(pNRQCD). The pNRQCD describes the quarkonium dynamics through poten-<lb/>tials and low-energy interactions. <lb/> 14,15  Thermal corrections to the real part of the <lb/>color-singlet potential lead to the color-screening phenomenon <lb/> 14  whereas thermal <lb/>corrections to the imaginary part of the color-singlet potential induce a thermal <lb/>width. Several mechanisms may contribute to the imaginary part of the potential. <lb/>One of these is precisely the Landau-damping mechanism, <lb/> 6  which is the princi-<lb/>pal source of quarkonium dissociation at weak coupling, responsible for keeping <lb/>the quarkonium to be dissociated even at temperatures where color screening has <lb/>faded away. Moreover, lattice studies have shown that the potential may have a siz-<lb/>able imaginary part also at strong coupling. <lb/> 16–18  These imaginary contributions to <lb/>the potential are related to quarkonium decay processes in the plasma. The conse-<lb/>quences of such imaginary parts on heavy quarkonium spectral functions, <lb/> 19,20  per-<lb/>turbative thermal widths, <lb/> 6,21  quarkonium suppression in a T-matrix approach, <lb/> 22–24 <lb/> and in stochastic real-time dynamics <lb/> 25  have recently been studied; however, these <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 3 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Complex potential and bottomonium suppression at LHC energy <lb/></note>

			<body> studies were restricted to an isotropic thermal plasma, which is only the case if <lb/>one assumes ideal hydrodynamical evolution. However, the separation of thermal <lb/>scales in EFT is not evident and one needs lattice techniques to test the approach, <lb/>where the dissociation of the quarkonium states can be studied even without the <lb/>potential models rather the physics of a given quarkonium state is encoded in its <lb/>spectral function in terms of the Euclidean meson correlation functions. <lb/> 26–33  How-<lb/>ever, the reconstruction of the spectral function from the lattice meson correlators <lb/>turns out to be very difficult. At finite temperature the situation becomes worse <lb/>because the temporal extent is decreasing and particularly, for the bottomonium <lb/>states, it becomes worst, thus inadvertently supports the use of potential models <lb/>at finite temperature to complement the lattice studies. <lb/>The above-mentioned discussion of quarkonium at finite temperature becomes <lb/>complicated in nucleus–nucleus collisions. The heavy quark (Q ¯ <lb/> Q) pairs are pro-<lb/>duced in heavy ion collisions on a very short time-scale (∼ 1/2m  Q  ). The initial <lb/>state effects on the parton densities (shadowing), <lb/> 34  the initial state energy loss, <lb/> 35 <lb/> the final state absorption on nucleons <lb/> 34,36  etc. could affect the production mech-<lb/>anism intimately. The shadowing and absorption are important at mid rapidity <lb/>whereas the (initial-state) energy loss and intrinsic heavy flavor are important at <lb/>forward rapidity. As the time elapsed, the resonances are formed over a formation <lb/>time, τ  F  and traverses the plasma and then the hadronic matter before leaving <lb/>the interacting system to be decayed into a dilepton. By the time the resonance is <lb/>formed, either the screening of the color force <lb/> 2  or an energetic gluon, <lb/> 37–40  even a <lb/>comoving hadron <lb/> 41  could dissociate the resonance(s). Thus, a study of quarkonium <lb/>production in nuclear collisions is poised to provide a wealth of information about <lb/>the evolution of the plasma and the in-medium properties of quarkonia states. At <lb/>SPS and RHIC, most of the interests were focused on the suppression of c¯ c bound <lb/>states <lb/> 2,7,42–47  but several observations are yet to be understood namely the suppres-<lb/>sion of ψ(1S) does not increase from SPS to RHIC, even though the center-of-mass <lb/>energy is increased by 15 times. The heavy-ion program at the LHC may resolve <lb/>those puzzles because the beam energy and luminosity are increased by 10 times <lb/>of that of the RHIC. That is why the interest may be shifted to the bottomonium <lb/>states at the LHC energy due to the following reasons: (i) The initial state effects <lb/>are much smaller than the charmonium production. (ii) The competition due to the <lb/>recombination is unlikely. (iii) The bottomonium states can be dealt efficiently by <lb/>the potential approach. (iv) Although the Υ states have diverse binding energies <lb/>their similar decay kinematics and production mechanisms enable to measure their <lb/>relative suppression unambiguously. <lb/>The works described above were limited to an isotropic medium but the system <lb/>produced in relativistic heavy-ion collision may not be homogeneous and isotropic <lb/>because at the early stages of the collision, the asymptotic weak-coupling enhances <lb/>the longitudinal expansion substantially than the radial expansion. There have been <lb/>significant advances in the dynamical models used to simulate plasma evolution with <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 4 <lb/> U. Kakade, B. K. Patra &amp; L. Thakur <lb/></note>

			<body> the momentum-space anisotropies. <lb/> 48–53  In recent years, the effects of anisotropy <lb/>on the quarkonia states have been extensively investigated <lb/> 54–57  by the leading-<lb/>anisotropic correction to the perturbative term of the potential alone. Although <lb/>the direct lattice QCD based determinations of the potential have progressed a lot, <lb/>still a model potential for the phenomenological descriptions of heavy quarkonium <lb/>suppression would indeed be quite useful. <lb/>The aforesaid works <lb/> 54–57  assumed only a screened Coulomb potential above <lb/>the critical temperature (T  c  ) because the linear/string term was assumed to be <lb/>zero. However, the string tension does not vanish abruptly at the deconfinement <lb/>temperature, <lb/> 58–61  so one should study its effect on heavy quark potential even <lb/>above T  c  . This issue usually overlooked in the literature was certainly worth of <lb/>investigation. Therefore, we had recently derived the medium modifications to both <lb/>perturbative and nonperturbative terms of the Q ¯ <lb/> Q potential <lb/> 62–64  in the presence <lb/>of a not necessarily isotropic QCD medium. We found that the inclusion of the <lb/>confining string term makes both the real and imaginary parts of the potential <lb/>more stronger, compared to the medium correction of the perturbative term of the <lb/>potential alone. <lb/> 63,64  Moreover, the presence of the anisotropy makes the real-part <lb/>of the potential stronger but the imaginary-part becomes leaner and overall the <lb/>anisotropy makes the quarkonia to dissociate at higher temperatures, compared to <lb/>the isotropic medium. <lb/>Recently the quarkonium suppression in nucleus–nucleus collisions has been <lb/>studied <lb/> 65  by employing the potentials <lb/> 54,55,57  with the medium modifications of <lb/>the perturbative term (Coulomb) of the potential alone in an anisotropic medium. <lb/>In the present work, we have employed the potential in Ref. 63 in anisotropic <lb/>medium, where medium modifications to both perturbative and nonperturbative <lb/>(string) terms are taken into account. Thereafter we have numerically obtained the <lb/>dissociation temperatures of the ground and the excited states of the Υ family. We <lb/>have found that the quarkonium states are now dissociated at higher temperatures <lb/>compared to the medium-consideration of the Coulomb term alone, which may <lb/>have an impact on bottomonium suppression. With these understandings about the <lb/>quarkonia states, we aim to study the dynamical suppression of the bottomonium <lb/>states at the LHC and observed that the local equilibrium hydrodynamic regime <lb/>alone may not be sufficient to suppress the bottomonium states adequately and <lb/>some additional pre-equilibrium time zone of plasma evolution may be needed. The <lb/>unique features of the bottomonium ground (1S) state, namely the tiny formation <lb/>time (≤ isotropization time) and the large binding energy, facilitate to probe both <lb/>the (pre-equilibrium) era prior to the isotropization time and the shear viscosity-<lb/>to-the entropy density ratio. <lb/>Our work is organized as follows. In Sec. 2, we revisited the anisotropic cor-<lb/>rections to the retarded, advanced and symmetric gluon self-energies and the cor-<lb/>responding propagators and then obtained the real and imaginary parts of the <lb/>potential. We then employ the complex potential to obtain the real and imaginary <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 5 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Complex potential and bottomonium suppression at LHC energy <lb/></note>

			<body> parts of the binding energies and calculate the dissociation temperatures of the <lb/>ground and excited b ¯ b states. In Sec. 3, we switch over our calculation to a medium, <lb/>which evolves through the successive pre-equilibrium and equilibrium evolution, to <lb/>study the survival of the bottomonium states. We found that our result explains <lb/>the CMS data <lb/> 4  reasonably well. Finally, we conclude in Sec. 4. <lb/> 2. Bottomonium in Anisotropic Medium <lb/> An interesting property at the initial phase of the QGP is the presence of the <lb/>momentum anisotropy. <lb/> 66–68  It is therefore worthwhile to consider the properties of <lb/>quarkonia such as the binding energy, decay width in such a system. The calculation <lb/>of the real part of the potential at finite anisotropy was first obtained in Refs. 6, <lb/>54, 55, 67 and was later extended for the imaginary part, <lb/> 13,55,69  by the leading <lb/>anisotropic corrections to the perturbative term of the potential alone and coupled <lb/>with the dynamical evolution of the anisotropic plasma. We now continue with <lb/>the above works to derive the potential at finite temperature keeping both the <lb/>perturbative and nonperturbative terms via the Keyldesh presentation in real-time <lb/>formalism. <lb/> 2.1. Real part of the potential <lb/> Since the mass of the heavy quark is very large, so both the requirements: m  Q  ≫ <lb/> Λ  QCD  and T ≪ m  Q  are met for the description of the interactions between a <lb/>pair of heavy quark and antiquark at finite temperature, in terms of a quantum <lb/>mechanical potential. We thus obtain the potential by correcting both the short-<lb/>and long-distance part of the Q ¯ <lb/> Q potential, with a dielectric function, ǫ(p) (Ref. 62) <lb/>embodying the effect of the medium <lb/> V (r, T ) = <lb/> d <lb/> 3  p <lb/> (2π) <lb/> 3/2 <lb/> e <lb/> ip·r  − 1 <lb/> V (p) <lb/> ǫ(p) <lb/>. <lb/> (1) <lb/>We regulate both terms by multiplying with an exponential damping factor and is <lb/>switched off after the Fourier transform V (p), which is given by <lb/> V (p) = − <lb/> 2 <lb/> π <lb/> α <lb/>p  2  − <lb/> 4σ <lb/> √ <lb/> 2πp  4 <lb/> . <lb/> (2) <lb/>We will now obtain the dielectric permittivity through the leading anisotropic cor-<lb/>rections to the self-energies and then to the static propagators in weak coupling <lb/>HTL approximation. In Keldysh representation, the retarded (R), advanced (A) <lb/>and symmetric (F ) propagators can be written as the linear combination of the <lb/>components of the (2 × 2) matrix propagator in real-time formalism: <lb/> D <lb/> 0 <lb/> R  = D <lb/> 0 <lb/>11  − D <lb/> 0 <lb/>12  , D <lb/> 0 <lb/> A  = D <lb/> 0 <lb/>11  − D <lb/> 0 <lb/>21  , D <lb/> 0 <lb/> F  = D <lb/> 0 <lb/>11  + D <lb/> 0 <lb/>22  , <lb/> (3) <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 6 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> U. Kakade, B. K. Patra &amp; L. Thakur <lb/></note>

			<body> where only the symmetric component involves the distribution functions and is of <lb/>particular advantage for the HTL diagrams where the terms containing distribution <lb/>functions dominate. Similar relations hold good for the retarded (Π  R  ), advanced <lb/>(Π  A  ) and symmetric (Π  F  ) self-energies. Now the resummation of the propagators <lb/>is done via the Dyson–Schwinger equation <lb/> D  R,A  = D <lb/> 0 <lb/> R,A  + D <lb/> 0 <lb/> R,A  Π  R,A  D  R,A  , <lb/> (4) <lb/> D  F  = D <lb/> 0 <lb/> F  + D <lb/> 0 <lb/> R  Π  R  D  F  + D <lb/> 0 <lb/> F  Π  A  D  A  + D <lb/> 0 <lb/> R  Π  F  D  A  . <lb/> (5) <lb/>For the static potential, we need only the temporal component ( &quot; 00 &quot;  ≡ L) of <lb/>the propagator, whose evaluation is easier in the Coulomb gauge. Thus the above <lb/>resummation (4) can be recast through its temporal component as <lb/> D <lb/> L <lb/>R,A(iso)  = D <lb/> L(0) <lb/>R,A  + D <lb/> L(0) <lb/>R,A  Π <lb/> L <lb/>R,A(iso)  D <lb/> L <lb/>R,A(iso)  . <lb/> (6) <lb/>The above relations are not satisfied for the anisotropic system due to the preferen-<lb/>tial direction of anisotropy. However, for anisotropic medium which exhibits a weak <lb/>anisotropy (ξ ≪ 1), we circumvent the problem, by expanding the propagators and <lb/>self-energies in ξ: <lb/>D = D  iso  + ξD  aniso  , Π = Π  iso  + ξΠ  aniso  , <lb/> (7) <lb/>where the parameter ξ is a measure of the anisotropy <lb/> ξ = <lb/> p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> 2 <lb/> p  2 <lb/> L <lb/>  − 1 , <lb/> (8) <lb/>where p  L  = p · n and p  T  = p − n(p · n) are the components of momentum parallel <lb/>and perpendicular to the direction of anisotropy, n, respectively. Thus in the pre-<lb/>sence of small anisotropy, the (resummed) temporal component of the retarded <lb/>(advanced) propagator becomes <lb/> D <lb/> L <lb/>R,A(aniso)  = D <lb/> L(0) <lb/>R,A  Π <lb/> L <lb/>R,A(aniso)  D <lb/> L <lb/>R,A(iso)  + D <lb/> L(0) <lb/>R,A  Π <lb/> L <lb/>R,A(iso)  D <lb/> L <lb/>R,A(aniso)  . <lb/> (9) <lb/>We will now calculate the temporal component of the retarded/advanced gluon <lb/>self-energy in the HTL-approximation, where the leading isotropic contribution is <lb/>Π <lb/> L <lb/>R,A(iso)  (P ) = m <lb/> 2 <lb/> D <lb/>  p  0 <lb/> 2p <lb/>ln <lb/> p  0  + p ± iǫ <lb/>p  0  − p ± iǫ <lb/> − 1 <lb/> , <lb/> (10) <lb/>with the prescriptions +iǫ (−iǫ), for the retarded and advanced self-energies, respec-<lb/>tively and m <lb/> 2 <lb/> D <lb/> = <lb/> g <lb/> 2  T <lb/> 2 <lb/> 6  (N  f  + 2N  c  ) <lb/> is the square of Debye mass. The full anisotropic <lb/>contribution is then <lb/>Π <lb/> L <lb/>R,A(aniso)  (P ) = <lb/> m <lb/> 2 <lb/> D <lb/> 6 <lb/> 1 + 3 cos 2θ  p <lb/> + Π <lb/> L <lb/>R(iso)  (P ) <lb/> cos(2θ  p  ) − <lb/> p  0 <lb/>2 <lb/> 2p  2  (1 + 3 cos 2θ  p  ) <lb/> . <lb/> (11) <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 7 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Complex potential and bottomonium suppression at LHC energy <lb/></note>

			<body> Similarly the isotropic and anisotropic terms for the temporal component of the <lb/>symmetric self-energy are given by <lb/>Π <lb/> L <lb/> F (iso)  (P ) = −2πim <lb/> 2 <lb/> D <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> Θ(p <lb/> 2  − p  0 <lb/>2  ) , <lb/> Π <lb/> L <lb/>F (aniso)  (P ) = <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/> πim <lb/> 2 <lb/> D <lb/> T <lb/>p <lb/> sin <lb/> 2  θ  p  + <lb/> p <lb/> 2 <lb/>0 <lb/> p  2  (3 cos <lb/> 2  θ  p  − 1) <lb/> Θ <lb/> p <lb/> 2  − p  0 <lb/>2  <lb/> . <lb/> (12) <lb/>Thus the gluon self-energy is found to have both real and imaginary parts which are <lb/>responsible for the Debye screening and the Landau damping, respectively where <lb/>the former is usually obtained from the retarded and advanced self-energy and the <lb/>later is obtained from the symmetric self-energy alone. <lb/>Therefore the real part of the temporal component of retarded (or advanced) <lb/>propagator in the static limit gives <lb/> ℜD <lb/> 00 <lb/> R,A  (0, p) = − <lb/> 1 <lb/> p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D <lb/>  + ξ <lb/>m <lb/> 2 <lb/> D <lb/> 6 <lb/> p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D <lb/>  2  (3 cos 2θ  p  − 1) <lb/>(13) <lb/>and the static limit of the imaginary part of the temporal component of symmetric <lb/>propagator is <lb/> ℑD <lb/> 00 <lb/> F  (0, p) = <lb/> −2πT m <lb/> 2 <lb/> D <lb/> p(p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D  )  2  + ξ <lb/> 3πT m <lb/> 2 <lb/> D <lb/> 2p <lb/> p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D <lb/>  2  sin <lb/> 2  θ  p <lb/> − <lb/> 4πT m <lb/> 4 <lb/> D <lb/> p <lb/> p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D <lb/>  3 <lb/> sin <lb/> 2  θ  p  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>3 <lb/> . <lb/> (14) <lb/>The dielectric permittivity is defined by the static limit of the &quot; 00 &quot; -component <lb/>of gluon propagator <lb/> ǫ <lb/> −1  (p) = − lim <lb/> ω→0 <lb/> p <lb/> 2  D <lb/> 00 <lb/>11  (ω, p) , <lb/> (15) <lb/>where the real and imaginary parts of D <lb/> 00 <lb/>11  can be written as <lb/> ℜD <lb/> 00 <lb/>11  (ω, p) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> D <lb/> 00 <lb/> R  + D <lb/> 00 <lb/> A <lb/> and ℑD <lb/> 00 <lb/>11  (ω, p) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> D <lb/> 00 <lb/> F  . <lb/> (16) <lb/>After substituting D <lb/> 00 <lb/> R  , D <lb/> 00 <lb/> A  and D <lb/> 00 <lb/> F  into Eq. (15), the real and imaginary parts of <lb/>dielectric permittivity become <lb/> ℜǫ <lb/> −1  (p) = p <lb/> 2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D <lb/>  − <lb/> ξm <lb/> 2 <lb/> D <lb/> 6 <lb/> p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D <lb/>  2  (3 cos(2θ  p  ) − 1) <lb/> , <lb/> (17) <lb/> ℑǫ <lb/> −1  (p) = p <lb/> 2 <lb/> −πT m <lb/> 2 <lb/> D <lb/> p <lb/> p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D <lb/>  2  + ξ <lb/> 3πT m <lb/> 2 <lb/> D <lb/> 4p <lb/> p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D <lb/>  2  sin <lb/> 2  θ  p <lb/> − <lb/> 2πT m <lb/> 4 <lb/> D <lb/> p <lb/> p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D <lb/>  3 <lb/> sin <lb/> 2  θ  p  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>3 <lb/> . <lb/> (18) <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 8 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> U. Kakade, B. K. Patra &amp; L. Thakur <lb/></note>

			<body> The above results are perturbative in nature but the presence of nonperturbative <lb/>effects, such as the string tension, the dependence of the dielectric function on the <lb/>Debye mass may get modified. For the sake of simplicity, we use a multiplication <lb/>factor 1.4 to the leading-order Debye mass, to take into account the next-to-leading <lb/>corrections <lb/> 70  (the factor is also obtained by fitting with the lattice results for the <lb/>color-singlet free energy <lb/> 71  ). <lb/>After plug in the real part of dielectric permittivity in definition of potential <lb/>(1), the real-part of the potential becomes <lb/> ℜV  (aniso)  (r, ξ, T ) = <lb/> d <lb/> 3  p <lb/> (2π) <lb/> 3/2 <lb/> e <lb/> ip·r  − 1 <lb/> − <lb/> 2 <lb/> π <lb/> α <lb/>p  2  − <lb/> 4σ <lb/> √ <lb/> 2π p  4 <lb/> × p <lb/> 2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D <lb/>  − <lb/> ξm <lb/> 2 <lb/> D <lb/> 6 <lb/> p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D <lb/>  2  (3 cos(2θ  p  ) − 1) <lb/> ≡ ℜV  1(aniso)  (r, ξ, T ) + ℜV  2(aniso)  (r, ξ, T ) , <lb/> (19) <lb/>where θ  p  is the angle between r and n (direction of anisotropy). Here the same <lb/>screening mass scale (m  D  ) for both the perturbative Coulomb term and the non-<lb/>perturbative long-distance contribution due to string are assumed. However, dif-<lb/>ferent scales for the Coulomb and linear pieces of the T = 0 potential, rather <lb/>than a single one, was employed <lb/> 72  through a dimension-two gluon condensates to <lb/>calculate the heavy quark free energy. To illustrate the effect of different scales for <lb/>perturbative and nonperturbative terms of the potential, we <lb/> 63  had compared our <lb/>results with Ref. 72 for the isotropic case. <lb/> a <lb/> The medium modifications corresponding to the Coulomb and string term, re-<lb/>spectively, are given by (ˆ r = rm  D  ) <lb/> ℜV  1(aniso)  (r, θ  r  , T ) = −αm  D <lb/>  e <lb/> −ˆ  <lb/> + 1 <lb/> + ξ <lb/> e <lb/> −ˆ   − 1 <lb/>6 <lb/> + <lb/> e <lb/> −ˆ  <lb/> 6 <lb/>+ <lb/> e <lb/> −ˆ  <lb/> 2ˆ  <lb/> + <lb/> e <lb/> −ˆ  <lb/>  2  + <lb/> e <lb/> −ˆ   − 1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r  3 <lb/> (1 − 3 cos <lb/> 2  θ  r  ) <lb/> (20) <lb/>and <lb/> ℜV  2(aniso)  (r, θ  r  , T ) = <lb/>2σ <lb/> m  D <lb/>  e <lb/> −ˆ   − 1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> + 1 <lb/> + 2ξ <lb/> e <lb/> −ˆ   − 1 <lb/>6ˆ  <lb/> + <lb/> e <lb/> −ˆ   + 2 <lb/>12 <lb/> + <lb/> e <lb/> −ˆ  <lb/>  2  + <lb/>5e <lb/> −ˆ   + ˆ <lb/> re <lb/> −ˆ   + 1 <lb/>12ˆ  <lb/> + <lb/> e <lb/> −ˆ   − 1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r  3 <lb/> (1 − 3 cos <lb/> 2  θ  r  ) <lb/> . <lb/> (21) <lb/> a  There is a similar calculation in the framework of Debye–Hückel theory to obtain the free <lb/>energy,  73  where different screening functions fc and fs are employed for the Coulomb and string <lb/>terms, respectively. In Ref. 64, we had compared the asymptotic limit (r → ∞) of Eq. (22) with <lb/>their limit. <lb/> 1550043-8 <lb/> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 9 <lb/> Complex potential and bottomonium suppression at LHC energy <lb/> Thus the real-part of the potential in anisotropic medium becomes <lb/> ℜV  aniso  (r, θ  r  , T ) = <lb/>2σ <lb/> m  D <lb/>  e <lb/> −ˆ   − 1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> + 1 <lb/> − αm  D <lb/>  e <lb/> −ˆ  <lb/> + 1 <lb/> + ξ <lb/>e <lb/> −ˆ  <lb/> × <lb/> 2σ <lb/> m  D <lb/>  e <lb/> ˆ <lb/> r  − 1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r  2  + <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> 2  e <lb/> ˆ <lb/> r  − 3 <lb/>3ˆ  <lb/> − <lb/> 5e <lb/>ê <lb/> r  − ˆ <lb/> r + 1 <lb/>12 <lb/> − <lb/> αm  D <lb/> 2 <lb/> e <lb/> ˆ <lb/> r  − 1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r  2  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> − <lb/> 2ˆ e <lb/>ê <lb/> r  − ˆ <lb/> r + 3 <lb/>6 <lb/> + <lb/> 2σ <lb/> m  D <lb/> 3 <lb/> e <lb/> ˆ <lb/> r  − 1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r  2  − <lb/> 3 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> − <lb/> e <lb/> ˆ <lb/> r  + ˆ <lb/> r + 5 <lb/>4 <lb/> − <lb/> αm  D <lb/> 2 <lb/> 3 <lb/> e <lb/> ˆ <lb/> r  − 1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r  2  − <lb/> 3 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> − <lb/> ˆ <lb/> r + 3 <lb/>2 <lb/> cos 2θ  r <lb/> = ℜV  iso  (r, T ) + V  tensor  (r, θ  r  , T ) . <lb/> (22) <lb/>It should be mentioned here that the above potential contains both the perturbative <lb/>(Coulomb) and nonperturbative (string) terms, compared to the results, <lb/> 55–57  where <lb/>the medium contribution to the perturbative (Coulomb) term alone is present. The <lb/>effect of the linear term, in addition to the Coulomb term was discussed with (σ = 0) <lb/>and without string term (σ  = 0) (details are given in Ref. 64) where it was found <lb/>that the inclusion of linear term makes the potential more attractive, compared <lb/>to potential with the Coulomb term only. In addition the momentum anisotropy <lb/>causes the (real part) potential more stronger (attractive) than the isotropic case, <lb/>which can be understood due to reduction of the Debye mass in the anisotropic <lb/>medium. <lb/> 63,64 <lb/> Recently the above potential was evaluated <lb/> 64  for the increasing temperatures <lb/>and it was found that the potential <lb/> b  decreases with the temperature at large dis-<lb/>tances and becomes short-range, which agrees qualitatively with the results of lat-<lb/>tice free energy. Thus the deconfinement is reflected clearly in the large-distance <lb/>behavior of heavy quark potential at finite temperature, where the screening is <lb/>operative. <lb/> 2.2. Imaginary part of the potential <lb/> The imaginary part of the potential is obtained by the medium corrections to both <lb/>the nonperturbative part (string term) and perturbative part of the potential at <lb/> b  The real part of the potential, at the leading-order calculation is the singlet free energy  71  because <lb/>it contains entropy contribution. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 10 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> U. Kakade, B. K. Patra &amp; L. Thakur <lb/></note>

			<body> T = 0, by the imaginary part of the dielectric function (14): <lb/> ℑV  (aniso)  (r, ξ, T ) = − <lb/> d <lb/> 3  p <lb/> (2π)  3/2 <lb/> e <lb/> ip·r  − 1 <lb/> − <lb/> 2 <lb/> π <lb/>α <lb/>p  2  − <lb/> 4σ <lb/> √ <lb/> 2πp  4 <lb/> × p <lb/> 2 <lb/> −πT m <lb/> 2 <lb/> D <lb/> p <lb/> p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D <lb/>  2  + ξ <lb/> 3πT m <lb/> 2 <lb/> D <lb/> 4p <lb/> p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D <lb/>  2  sin <lb/> 2  θ  p <lb/> − <lb/> 2πT m <lb/> 4 <lb/> D <lb/> p(p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D  )  3 <lb/> sin <lb/> 2  θ  p  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>3 <lb/> ≡ ℑV  1(aniso)  (r, ξ, T ) + ℑV  2(aniso)  (r, ξ, T ) , <lb/> (23) <lb/>where ℑV  1(aniso)  (r, ξ, T ) and ℑV  2(aniso)  (r, ξ, T ) are the imaginary contributions cor-<lb/>responding to the Coulombic and linear terms in anisotropic medium, respectively. <lb/>The contribution due to the perturbative term in the leading-order is given by <lb/> 55,56,74 <lb/> ℑV  1(aniso)  (r, ξ, T ) = −αT (φ  0  (ˆ r) + ξ[φ  1  (ˆ r, θ  r  ) + φ  2  (ˆ r, θ  r  )]) , <lb/> (24) <lb/>where the functions φ  0  (ˆ r), φ  1  (ˆ r, θ  r  ) and φ  2  (ˆ r, θ  r  ) are given by <lb/> φ  0  (ˆ r) = −αT <lb/> − <lb/> ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> 2 <lb/> 9 <lb/>(−4 + 3γ  E  + 3 log <lb/> ) <lb/> , <lb/>φ  1  (ˆ r, θ  r  ) = <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> 2 <lb/> 600 <lb/>[123 − 90γ  E  − 90 log <lb/>  + cos 2θ  r  (−31 + 30γ  E  + 30 log <lb/> )] , <lb/>φ  2  (ˆ r, θ  r  ) = <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> 2 <lb/> 90 <lb/>(−4 + 3 cos 2θ  r  ) . <lb/> (25) <lb/>Similarly the imaginary part due to the nonperturbative (linear) term has also the <lb/>isotropic and anisotropic term: <lb/> ℑV  2(aniso)  (r, ξ, T ) = <lb/>2σT <lb/> m  2 <lb/> D <lb/> ψ  0  (ˆ r) − ξ[ψ  1  (ˆ r, θ  r  ) + ψ  2  (ˆ r, θ  r  )] <lb/> , <lb/> (26) <lb/>where the functions ψ  0  (ˆ r), ψ  1  (ˆ r, θ  r  ) and ψ  2  (ˆ r, θ  r  ) are given by <lb/> ψ  0  (ˆ r) = <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> 2 <lb/> 6 <lb/>+ <lb/> −107 + 60γ  E  + 60 log(ˆ r) <lb/> 3600 <lb/> 4  + O(ˆ r <lb/> 5  ) , <lb/> (27) <lb/> ψ  1  (ˆ r, θ  r  ) = <lb/> dz <lb/>z(z  2  + 1)  2 <lb/> 1 − <lb/> 3 <lb/>2 <lb/> sin <lb/> 2  θ  r <lb/> sin zˆ <lb/>zˆ <lb/> + (1 − 3 cos <lb/> 2  θ  r  )G(ˆ r, z) <lb/> , <lb/> (28) <lb/> ψ  2  (ˆ r, θ  r  ) = − <lb/> 4 <lb/>3 <lb/> dz <lb/>z(z  2  + 1)  3 <lb/> × <lb/> 1 − 3 <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/> − cos <lb/> 2  θ  r <lb/>  sin zˆ <lb/>zˆ <lb/> + (1 − 3 cos <lb/> 2  θ  r  )G(ˆ r, z) <lb/> , <lb/> (29) <lb/>where <lb/> G(ˆ r, z) = <lb/> zˆ  cos(zˆ ) − sin(zˆ ) <lb/> (zˆ )  3 <lb/> . <lb/> (30) <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 11 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Complex potential and bottomonium suppression at LHC energy <lb/></note>

			<body> Thus, the imaginary part of the potential in anisotropic medium in the leading <lb/>logarithmic order becomes <lb/> ℑV  (aniso)  (r, θ  r  , T ) = −T <lb/> αˆ <lb/> 2 <lb/> 3 <lb/>+ <lb/> σˆ <lb/> 4 <lb/> 30m  2 <lb/> D <lb/> log <lb/> 1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> + ξT <lb/> αˆ <lb/> 2 <lb/> 5 <lb/>+ <lb/>3σˆ  <lb/> 4 <lb/> 140m  2 <lb/> D <lb/> − cos <lb/> 2  θ  r <lb/>  αˆ <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/>+ <lb/> σˆ <lb/> 4 <lb/> 70m  2 <lb/> D <lb/> log <lb/> 1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> , <lb/> (31) <lb/>which shows that imaginary part vanishes for small distances and its magnitude is <lb/>larger than the case where only the Coulombic term is considered. <lb/> 54,55,57  Moreover <lb/>the presence of anisotropy makes the (magnitude) imaginary potential smaller, <lb/>compared to the isotropic medium. <lb/>In weak anisotropic limit, the imaginary part is a perturbation and thus provides <lb/>an estimate for the (thermal) width for a particular resonance state: <lb/>Γ  (aniso) <lb/> 2 <lb/>= <lb/> d <lb/> 3  r|Ψ(r)| <lb/> 2 <lb/> αT  <lb/> 2  log <lb/> 1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> 1 <lb/>3 <lb/> − ξ <lb/> 3 − cos 2θ  r <lb/> 20 <lb/> + <lb/>2σT <lb/> m  2 <lb/> D <lb/> ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> 4  log <lb/> 1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> 1 <lb/>20 <lb/> 1 <lb/>3 <lb/> − ξ <lb/> 2 − cos 2θ  r <lb/> 14 <lb/> = T <lb/> 4 <lb/> αm  2 <lb/> Q <lb/> + <lb/>12σ <lb/> α  2  m  4 <lb/> Q <lb/> 1 − <lb/> ξ <lb/> 2 <lb/> m <lb/> 2 <lb/> D  log <lb/> αm  Q <lb/> 2m  D <lb/> , <lb/> (32) <lb/>which shows that the in-medium thermal width in anisotropic medium becomes <lb/>smaller than in isotropic medium and gets narrower with the increase of anisotropy. <lb/>For simplicity, we have taken Ψ(r) as the Coulombic wave function, similar to the <lb/>ground state wave function in hydrogen atom. <lb/>It is worth to mention that the inclusion of nonvanishing nonperturbative string <lb/>term, in addition to the Coulomb term, makes the width larger than the result with <lb/>the perturbative Coulomb term <lb/> 54,55  only and thus the damping of the exchanged <lb/>gluon in the heat bath provides larger contribution to the dissociation rate and <lb/>consequently reduces the yield of dileptons in the peak. <lb/> 2.3. Dissociation in a complex potential <lb/> The dissociation physics of Q ¯ <lb/> Q bound state at finite temperature has gone through <lb/>many refinements over the years. Experimentally the properties of thermally pro-<lb/>duced heavy quarkonium can be observed through the dilepton spectrum, <lb/> 75,76  where <lb/>the dissociation of resonances correspond to the disappearance of the peaks in the <lb/>dilepton production rate. A resonance is dissolved into a medium due to its inter-<lb/>action with the partons in the medium, resulting the broadening of the peak. In <lb/>early days a quarkonium was thought to be dissociated when the Debye screen-<lb/>ing becomes so strong that it inhibits the formation of bound states. Nowadays a <lb/>quarkonium is believed to be dissociated at a lower temperature <lb/> 6,19  even though its <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 12 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> U. Kakade, B. K. Patra &amp; L. Thakur <lb/></note>

			<body> binding energy is nonvanishing, rather is overtaken by the Landau-damping induced <lb/>thermal width, <lb/> 16  obtained from the imaginary part of the potential. <lb/>Thus the dissociation of the resonances are obtained when the binding energy <lb/>decreases with the increase of the temperature and becomes equal to ∼ Γ. <lb/> 19,77 <lb/> Equivalently it can also be obtained from the intersection of the binding energies <lb/>obtained from the real and imaginary parts of the potential, <lb/> 74,78–80  respectively. <lb/>In short-distance or low temperature (r ≪ 1/m  D  ) limit, the potential reduces <lb/>to its vacuum form for isotropic medium. On the other hand, for r ≫ 1/m  D  limit, <lb/>we can neglect the Yukawa term and for large values of temperature the product <lb/> αm  D  will be much greater than 2σ/m  D  . So, finally the potential (22) reduces to a <lb/>Coulomb plus a subleading anisotropic contribution: <lb/> ℜV  (aniso)  (r, θ  r  , T ) <lb/> ˆ <lb/> r≫1 <lb/> ≃ − <lb/> 2σ <lb/> m  2 <lb/> D  r <lb/> − αm  D  − <lb/> 5ξ <lb/>12 <lb/>2σ <lb/> m  2 <lb/> D  r <lb/> 1 + <lb/>3 <lb/>5 <lb/>cos 2θ  r <lb/> (33) <lb/> ≡ ℜV  iso  (ˆ r ≫ 1, T ) + V  tensor  (ˆ r ≫ 1, θ  r  , T ) . <lb/> (34) <lb/>Thus the resulting potential looks like a Coulombic one, by identifying the factor, <lb/>2σ/m <lb/> 2 <lb/> D  with the fine-structure constant, e <lb/> 2  . It has then to satisfy the condition: <lb/> a  0  m  D  ≫ 1, where a  0  is the Bohr radius and m  D  (= gT ) is the Debye mass, for <lb/>the validity of taking this limit. Comparing the expression for the Bohr radius <lb/>(= 1/me <lb/> 2  ) for hydrogen atom, the above condition for rT ≫ 1 limit implies that <lb/> m <lb/> 3 <lb/> D  /(m  Q  σ) should be greater than 1. The validity of the above condition is dis-<lb/>cussed in Ref. 63, where the condition is found to be satisfied for the temperatures <lb/>above the critical temperature. To check the validity of the large-distance limit, <lb/>we have evaluated both the full potential and its large-distance limit at different <lb/>temperatures viz. at 1.2T  c  , 2T  c  and 2.5T  c  (shown in Fig. 1), where we observe that <lb/>both of them initially rise with increasing r, but slower than the linear way and at <lb/>some large enough r it simply flattens out (due to the breaking of QCD string, i.e. <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>r fm <lb/>-2 <lb/>-1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>V <lb/> iso <lb/> (r,T) GeV <lb/> T=1.2T C <lb/> T=2T C <lb/> T=2.5T C <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>r fm <lb/>-5 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-3 <lb/>-2 <lb/>-1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>V <lb/> iso <lb/> (r,T) GeV <lb/> T=1.2T C ( r <lb/>^ &gt;&gt;1) <lb/>T=2T C ( r <lb/>^ &gt;&gt;1) <lb/>T=2.5T C ( r <lb/>^ &gt;&gt;1) <lb/> Fig. 1. The full potential (left) and its rm  D  ≫ 1 limit (right) are plotted as a function of r for <lb/>increasing temperatures. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 13 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Complex potential and bottomonium suppression at LHC energy <lb/></note>

			<body> a heavy meson splits into two heavy-light mesons). This observation agrees with <lb/>the lattice calculations <lb/> 81,82  qualitatively. Therefore, in the large-distance limit of <lb/>the potential (22), the real part of binding energy may be obtained from the radial <lb/>part of the Schrödinger equation (of the isotropic component) plus the first-order <lb/>perturbation due to the anisotropic component as: <lb/> E <lb/> aniso <lb/>bin <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r≫1 <lb/> ≃ <lb/> m  Q  σ <lb/> 2 <lb/> m  4 <lb/> D  n  2  + αm  D <lb/> + <lb/>2ξ <lb/>3 <lb/> m  Q  σ <lb/> 2 <lb/> m  4 <lb/> D  n  2  . <lb/> (35) <lb/>However, in the intermediate-distance scale, the (real part) potential (22) does <lb/>not look simple, so we will solve the full potential (22) numerically. Usually the <lb/>time-dependent or independent Schrödinger equation is solved by the finite dif-<lb/>ference time domain method (FDTD) or matrix method, respectively. In the matrix <lb/>method, the Schrödinger equation can be solved in a matrix form through a discrete <lb/>basis, instead of the continuous real-space position basis spanned by the states | <lb/> → <lb/> x. <lb/> Here the confining potential V is subdivided into N discrete wells with potentials <lb/> V  1  , V  2  , . . . , V  N +2  such that for ith boundary potential, V = V  i  for x  i−1  &lt; x &lt; x  i  ; <lb/> i = 2, 3, . . . , (N + 1). Therefore for the existence of a bound state, there must be <lb/>exponentially decaying wave function in the region x &gt; x  N +1  as x → ∞ and has <lb/>the form: <lb/>Ψ  N +2  (x) = P  E  exp[−γ  N +2  (x − x  N +1  )] + Q  E  exp[γ  N +2  (x − x  N +1  )] , <lb/> (36) <lb/>where <lb/> P  E  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(A  N +2  −B  N +2  ) , Q  E  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(A  N +2  +B  N +2  ) and γ  N +2  = <lb/> 2µ(V  N +2  − E) . <lb/> The eigenvalues can be obtained by identifying the zeros of Q  E  . <lb/>We have then obtained the real and imaginary parts of the binding energies of <lb/>the bottomonium states (shown in Fig. 2) numerically by above-mentioned matrix <lb/>method with the (full) real (22) and imaginary parts (31) of the potential, respec-<lb/>tively and their intersections give the dissociation temperatures. The dissociation <lb/> 1 <lb/> 1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3 <lb/>T/T c <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.25 <lb/> ϒ(1S)  B.E. (GeV) <lb/> Re B.E.(ξ=0) <lb/>Re B.E.(ξ=0.3) <lb/>Im B.E.(ξ=0) <lb/>Im B.E. (ξ=0.3) <lb/> 1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3 <lb/>T/T c <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/> ϒ(2S)  B.E. (GeV) <lb/> Re B.E.(ξ=0) <lb/>Re B.E.(ξ=0.3) <lb/>Im B.E.(ξ=0) <lb/>Im B.E.(ξ=0.3) <lb/> Fig. 2. The real and imaginary parts of the binding energies for the 1S and 2S states. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 14 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> U. Kakade, B. K. Patra &amp; L. Thakur <lb/></note>

			<body> Table 1. Dissociation temperatures (T  D  ) for bottomonium states, their forma-<lb/>tion times (τ  F  )  78  and screening energy densities (ǫs) and the speed of sound (c  2 <lb/> s  ) <lb/>(in isotropic medium). <lb/> T  D <lb/> State <lb/> ξ = 0 <lb/> ξ = 0.3 <lb/> ξ = 0.6 <lb/> τ  F  (fm) <lb/> ǫs (ξ = 0) <lb/> c  2 <lb/> s <lb/> Υ(1S) <lb/>1.97 <lb/>2.01 <lb/>2.11 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>42.49 <lb/>0.307 <lb/>Υ(2S) <lb/>1.44 <lb/>1.50 <lb/>1.54 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>12.74 <lb/>0.284 <lb/>Υ(3S) <lb/>1.12 <lb/>1.15 <lb/>1.21 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>5.21 <lb/>0.249 <lb/> χ  b1 <lb/> 1.57 <lb/>1.59 <lb/>1.64 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>17.66 <lb/>0.292 <lb/> temperatures (T  D  &apos;s) for the Υ(1S) and Υ(2S) states are found to be 1.97T  c  and <lb/>1.44T  c  , respectively (Table 1) in isotropic medium and increases with the increase <lb/>of anisotropy (ξ &gt; 0), i.e. the bottomonium states survives up to 2.1T  c  for ξ = 0.6 <lb/>and can be empirically written as T <lb/> D <lb/> aniso  (ξ) ≃ T <lb/> D <lb/> iso <lb/> 1 + <lb/> ξ <lb/> 7 <lb/> , compared to the relation <lb/> T <lb/> D <lb/> aniso  (ξ) = T <lb/> D <lb/> iso <lb/> 1 + <lb/> ξ <lb/> 6 <lb/> by Laine et al. <lb/> 57  Our results are found relatively higher <lb/>compared to similar calculation, <lb/> 74,78  which may be due to the absence of three-<lb/>dimensional medium modification of the linear term in their calculation. <lb/> 3. Quarkonium in Expanding Medium <lb/> Let us now consider a nucleus–nucleus collision, where the partons are formed at <lb/>time τ  i  ∼ Q <lb/> −1 <lb/> s  (Q  s  is the saturation scale) and the system started evolving. There <lb/>may be three plausible scenarios in space–time evolution viz. (i) the partons are <lb/>initially isotropized (τ  i  = τ  iso  ), i.e. the system evolves hydrodynamically, (ii) the <lb/>system never isotropizes (τ  iso  → ∞), i.e. it undergoes free streaming motion and <lb/>(iii) finally the system takes finite time to isotropize (τ  i  &lt; τ &lt; τ  iso  ), i.e. undergoes <lb/>through successive anisotropic (pre-equilibrium) and isotropic (equilibrium) phases. <lb/>The pre-equilibrium era may be conceived by the fact that the asymptotic weak-<lb/>coupling at the early stage of the collision enhances the expansion in the beam direc-<lb/>tion (longitudinal) substantially than the radial expansion and results an anisotropy. <lb/>This anisotropy makes the partonic system unstable with respect to the chromo-<lb/>magnetic plasma modes, <lb/> 79  which facilitate the system to isotropize quickly. <lb/> 66,83,84 <lb/> Recently there have been significant advances in the dynamical models for the <lb/>plasma evolution to incorporate the momentum anisotropy. <lb/> 85–87 <lb/> Let us consider a region of energy density in the transverse plane, which is <lb/>greater than or equal to the screening energy density, ǫ  s  (which is defined as the <lb/>energy density of the deconfined medium, corresponding to the dissociation tem-<lb/>perature and is obtained from Eq. (39). During the expansion, if the system has <lb/>been cooled to an energy density less than or equal to ǫ  s  , the Q ¯ <lb/> Q pair would escape <lb/>and form the (quarkonium) resonance. On the other hand if the energy density <lb/>is still higher than ǫ  s  , the resonance will not form and suppress the quarkonium <lb/>production. Thus the pattern of suppression of the quarkonium states depends on <lb/>how rapidly the system cools and how large is the screening energy density of the <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 15 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Complex potential and bottomonium suppression at LHC energy <lb/></note>

			<body> particular resonance state. Thus the discussion on the suppression of resonances in <lb/>expanding medium is three fold respects: First, we discuss on the equation of state <lb/>(EoS) which gives the speed of sound (which controls the expansion of the medium) <lb/>as a function of temperature, in contrast to the constant value usually adopted in <lb/>the literature and use the EoS to evaluate the screening energy density correspond-<lb/>ing to the temperature T  D  . Second, we discuss the evolution of the system first <lb/>through the pre-equilibrium era and subsequently the (local) equilibrium era in <lb/>the Bjorken boost-invariant expansion in the presence of dissipative forces. Finally <lb/>the above ingredients are coupled to quantify the suppression of the bottomonium <lb/>states at the LHC. <lb/> 3.1. Lattice equation of state <lb/> To study the QCD equation of state at zero baryon chemical potential, the pressure <lb/>(p(T, µ = 0)), and the trace anomaly (I(T, µ = 0)) are two important observables. <lb/>In the limit of vanishing baryon chemical potential, the trace anomaly has been <lb/>parametrized in the following form <lb/> 88,89  (with t = T /200): <lb/>I(T, µ = 0) <lb/> T  4 <lb/> = e <lb/> −h1/t−h2/t <lb/> 2 <lb/> h  0  + <lb/> f  0  [tanh(f  1  t + f  2  ) + 1] <lb/>1 + g  1  t + g  2  t  2 <lb/> . <lb/> (37) <lb/>There exists an inverse relation between the pressure and the trace anomaly at <lb/> µ = 0 as: <lb/> p(T, 0) <lb/> T  4  = <lb/>  T <lb/> 0 <lb/> dT <lb/> ′  I(T <lb/> ′  , 0) <lb/> T  ′ 5  . <lb/> (38) <lb/>The energy density ǫ is then obtained from the trace anomaly and the pressure <lb/> ǫ = I + 3p , <lb/> (39) <lb/>hence the speed of sound c  s  can be obtained from the relation: <lb/> c <lb/> 2 <lb/> s  = <lb/> ∂p <lb/>∂ǫ <lb/> s/n <lb/> . <lb/> (40) <lb/>We have shown that how the speed of sound varies with temperature rapidly in <lb/>the vicinity of the critical point and approaches toward the asymptotically ideal <lb/>value (1/3) (in Fig. 3) for very high temperature. In particular we have marked <lb/>the values of c <lb/> 2 <lb/> s  &apos;s at the dissociation temperatures (T  D  &apos;s) of the Υ(nS) states and <lb/>indicates that how the expansion of the system deviates from the ideal one at T  D  &apos;s <lb/>and hence has a large bearing on the suppression. <lb/>Thus the EoS can be used to calculate the energy density (ǫ  s  ) at the dissociation <lb/>temperature (T  D  ) and also be used as an input to the hydrodynamic equation of <lb/>motion. Another dynamical quantity in the quarkonium suppression is the screening <lb/>time, which can be obtained from ǫ  s  and c <lb/> 2 <lb/> s  . <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 16 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> U. Kakade, B. K. Patra &amp; L. Thakur <lb/></note>

			<body> 1 <lb/> 1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3 <lb/>3.5 <lb/>4 <lb/>T/T c <lb/> 0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.35 <lb/> C <lb/> s <lb/> 2 <lb/> C s <lb/>2 Ideal <lb/>C s <lb/>2 Lattice <lb/> ϒ(1S) <lb/> ϒ(2S) <lb/>ϒ(3S) <lb/> Fig. 3. Variation of the speed of sound. <lb/> 3.2. Evolution in pre-equilibrium era <lb/> The evolution of the pre-equilibrium (anisotropic) hydrodynamics may be dealt in <lb/>two ways: the first one is a phenomenological and refers directly to tensor structure <lb/>of an anisotropic fluid <lb/> 51–53  and the second one employs the transport equation <lb/>for the gluon distribution function in the anisotropic background. <lb/> 48–50  Phenomeno-<lb/>logically the generalized anisotropy parameter can be written in (1+1) dimension <lb/> 87 <lb/> ξ(τ, δ) = <lb/> τ <lb/>τ  i <lb/>  δ <lb/> − 1 , <lb/> (41) <lb/>where the interpolating coefficient, δ characterizes the various isotropization pro-<lb/>cess, viz. the asymptotic limits δ → 0 and 2 represent the (local equilibrium) <lb/>hydrodynamics and the free-streaming, respectively whereas the intermediate values <lb/>1/6 ≤ δ ≤ 1/2 and 2/3 denote the plasma instability and the collisional broadening, <lb/>respectively. For the general value of δ, the proper time dependence of the energy <lb/>density, the hard momentum scale and the number density for large times, τ ≫ τ  i  , <lb/>can be written as, <lb/> ε(τ ) = ε  0 <lb/>  τ  i <lb/> τ <lb/>  4(1−δ/8)/3 <lb/> , <lb/> (42) <lb/> p  hard  (τ ) = T  0 <lb/>  τ  i <lb/> τ <lb/>  (1−δ/2)/3 <lb/> , <lb/> (43) <lb/> n(τ ) = n  0 <lb/>  τ  i <lb/> τ <lb/> , <lb/> (44) <lb/>respectively. The smoothness of the transition from a nonzero value (of δ) to 0 at <lb/> τ ∼ τ  iso  , is governed by a smeared step function λ(τ ), <lb/> 48,49,87 <lb/> λ(τ ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> tanh <lb/> γ(τ − τ  iso  ) <lb/> τ  i <lb/> + 1 <lb/> , <lb/> (45) <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 17 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Complex potential and bottomonium suppression at LHC energy <lb/></note>

			<body> where the parameter, γ sets the sharpness of the transition from pre-equilibrium to <lb/>(local equilibrium) hydrodynamic behavior. Thus the above dependence, in terms <lb/>of λ(τ ), become <lb/> ξ(τ, δ) = <lb/> τ <lb/>τ  i <lb/>  δ(1−λ(τ )) <lb/> − 1 , <lb/> (46) <lb/> E(τ ) = E  0  R(ξ) ¯ <lb/> U <lb/> 4/3  , <lb/> (47) <lb/> p  hard  (τ ) = T  0  ¯ <lb/> U <lb/> 1/3  , <lb/> (48) <lb/>where the functions R(ξ) and ¯ <lb/> U are given by <lb/> R(ξ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> ξ + 1 <lb/>+ <lb/>tan <lb/> −1 <lb/> √ <lb/> ξ <lb/> √ <lb/> ξ <lb/> , <lb/> (49) <lb/>¯ <lb/> U = <lb/> U(τ ) <lb/> U(τ  i  ) <lb/> , <lb/> (50) <lb/>with <lb/> U(τ ) ≡ <lb/> R <lb/> τ  iso <lb/> τ  i <lb/>  δ <lb/> − 1 <lb/>  3λ(τ )/4  τ  iso <lb/> τ <lb/>  1−δ(1−λ(τ ))/2 <lb/> . <lb/> (51) <lb/> 3.3. Evolution in equilibrium era: Bjorken expansion <lb/> When the rate of interaction overcomes the expansion rate the system attains local <lb/>thermodynamic equilibrium for times τ ≥ τ  iso  . The energy–momentum tensor of <lb/>the plasma in the absence of dissipative forces is written as: <lb/> T <lb/> µν  = (ǫ + p)u <lb/> µ  u <lb/> ν  + g <lb/> µν  p , <lb/> (52) <lb/>where ǫ and p are the energy density and the pressure, respectively. Then, the <lb/>Bjorken&apos;s boost-invariant longitudinal expansion gives the equation of motion: <lb/> dǫ <lb/>dτ <lb/> = − <lb/> ǫ + p <lb/>τ <lb/>, <lb/> (53) <lb/>where the EoS (p = c <lb/> 2 <lb/> s  ǫ) has been coupled to give rise <lb/> ǫ(τ )τ <lb/> 1+c <lb/> 2 <lb/> s  = ǫ(τ  i  )τ <lb/> 1+c <lb/> 2 <lb/> s <lb/> i <lb/> . <lb/> (54) <lb/>Now we study the corrections to the Bjorken expansion due to the dissipative forces <lb/>in the energy–momentum tensor: <lb/> T <lb/> µν  = (ǫ + p)u <lb/> µ  u <lb/> ν  + g <lb/> µν  p + Π <lb/> µν  , <lb/> (55) <lb/>where the dissipative part (viscous stress tensor), Π <lb/> µν  is given by <lb/>Π <lb/> µν  = η <lb/> ∇ <lb/> µ  u <lb/> ν  + ∇ <lb/> ν  u <lb/> µ  − <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/> ∇ <lb/> µν  ∇ <lb/> ρ  u  ρ <lb/> + ζ∇ <lb/> µν  ∇ <lb/> ρ  u  ρ  , <lb/> (56) <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-17 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 18 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> U. Kakade, B. K. Patra &amp; L. Thakur <lb/></note>

			<body> where η and ζ are the shear and bulk viscosities, respectively and ∇ <lb/> µ  = ∇ <lb/> µν  ∂  ν <lb/> with ∇ <lb/> µν  = g <lb/> µν  − u <lb/> µ  u <lb/> ν  . In first-order viscous hydrodynamics, the bulk and shear <lb/>stresses can be written in a gradient expansion: <lb/>Π = −ζ∂ <lb/> µ  u  µ  , π <lb/> µν  = η∇ <lb/> µ  u <lb/> ν  , <lb/> (57) <lb/>where ∇ <lb/> µ  u <lb/> ν  is the symmetrized velocity gradient. The Israel–Stewart theory of <lb/>second-order dissipative hydrodynamics <lb/> 90  modifies the equation of motion for the <lb/>ideal fluid (53) into <lb/> 91–94 <lb/> dǫ <lb/>dτ <lb/> = − <lb/> 1 <lb/> τ <lb/> (ǫ + p − Φ + Π) , <lb/> (58) <lb/>where the bulk (Π) and the shear stress (Φ) will asymptotically (after the relaxation <lb/>times τ  Π  and τ  π  , respectively) reduce to their first-order values. In the Navier–Stokes <lb/>limit, the one-dimensional boost-invariant expansion gives, <lb/> 95 <lb/> Φ = <lb/>4η <lb/>3τ <lb/> , Π = − <lb/> ζ <lb/>τ <lb/>. <lb/> (59) <lb/>Substituting the values of Φ and Π in (58), the Bjorken longitudinal expansion can <lb/>be read as: <lb/> dǫ <lb/>dτ <lb/> + <lb/> ǫ + p <lb/>τ <lb/> = <lb/> 4η <lb/>3  + ζ <lb/>τ  2  , <lb/> (60) <lb/>whose solution can be obtained with the EoS p = c <lb/> 2 <lb/> s  ǫ, <lb/>ǫ(τ )τ <lb/> 1+c <lb/> 2 <lb/> s  + c <lb/> 4η <lb/>3s <lb/>+ <lb/> ζ <lb/>s <lb/> τ <lb/> 1+c <lb/> 2 <lb/> s <lb/> ˜ <lb/> τ  2  = ǫ(τ  i  )τ <lb/> 1+c <lb/> 2 <lb/> s <lb/> i <lb/> + c <lb/> 4η <lb/>3s <lb/>+ <lb/> ζ <lb/>s <lb/> τ <lb/> 1+c <lb/> 2 <lb/> s <lb/> i <lb/> ˜ <lb/> τ  i <lb/> 2  , <lb/> (61) <lb/>where the constant, c is (1 + c <lb/> 2 <lb/> s  )a  f  T <lb/> 3 <lb/> i  τ  i  with a  f  = (16 + 21n  f  /2)π <lb/> 2  /90, and <lb/> 2 <lb/> (or <lb/> 2 <lb/> i  ) are denoted by (1 − c <lb/> 2 <lb/> s  )τ <lb/> 2  ((1 − c <lb/> 2 <lb/> s  )τ <lb/> 2 <lb/> i  ), respectively. The first term in both <lb/>left-hand side and right-hand side accounts for the contributions coming from the <lb/>zeroth-order expansion while the second term is due to the viscous corrections. <lb/>In the present work we use the shear viscosity to-entropy ratio, η/s from the <lb/>perturbative QCD <lb/> 96  and AdS/CFT calculations, <lb/> 97  whereas for the bulk-viscosity, <lb/> ζ/s we consider the parametrization in Refs. 98–100, which suggest a sharp peak <lb/>in the vicinity of T  c  and is tiny below T  c  : <lb/> 101 <lb/> ζ <lb/>s <lb/> = <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> a  1  exp <lb/> T − T  c <lb/> ∆T <lb/> + b  1 <lb/>  T  c <lb/> T <lb/>  2 <lb/> if T &gt; T  c  , <lb/>a  1  exp <lb/> 10(T  c  − T ) <lb/>∆T <lb/> + <lb/> b  1 <lb/> 10 <lb/> T <lb/>T  c <lb/>  2 <lb/> if T  c  ≥ T , <lb/> (62) <lb/>where the parameter a  1  (= 0.901) and the ∆T (= T  c  /14.5) controls the height and <lb/>the width of the curve, both of which are not well understood and may be varied <lb/>considerably. The parameter b  1  (= 0.061) is obtained by fitting Meyer&apos;s central value <lb/>of ζ/s at higher temperatures. <lb/> 98 <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-18 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 19 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Complex potential and bottomonium suppression at LHC energy <lb/></note>

			<body> 3.4. Survival of b ¯ b states <lb/> Let us take a simple parametrization for the initial energy density profile on the <lb/>transverse plane: <lb/> ǫ(τ  i  , r) = ǫ  i  A  T  (r) , <lb/> (63) <lb/>with the profile function <lb/> A  T  (r) = <lb/> 1 − <lb/> r <lb/> 2 <lb/> R  2 <lb/> T <lb/>  β <lb/> θ(R  T  − r) , <lb/> (64) <lb/>where r is the transverse coordinate, R  T  is the transverse radius of the nucleus and <lb/> β represents the proportionality of the deposited energy to the nuclear thickness. <lb/>Thus the average initial energy density, ǫ  i  can be obtained as <lb/> ǫ  i  = (1 + β)ǫ  i  . <lb/> (65) <lb/>With this initial energy density profile (63), we now obtain the screening time <lb/>(τ  s  (r)), when the energy density drops to the screening energy density ǫ  s  , and <lb/>construct the screening energy density contour. Since the system evolves through <lb/>the successive pre-equilibrium and equilibrium era, so the entire contour is obtained <lb/>by amalgamating the contours in pre-equilibrium and the equilibrium era. The <lb/>contour in the pre-equilibrium era is obtained from the energy density (47) whereas <lb/>the equilibrium era gives the contour: <lb/> τ  s  (r) = τ  i <lb/>  ˜ <lb/> τ  s <lb/> ˜ <lb/> τ  i <lb/>  2/1+c <lb/> 2 <lb/> s <lb/> ǫ  i  (r)˜ τ <lb/> 2 <lb/> i  + c <lb/>  4η <lb/>3s  + <lb/> ζ <lb/>s <lb/> ǫ  s  ˜ <lb/> τ  2 <lb/> s  + c <lb/>  4η <lb/>3s  + <lb/> ζ <lb/>s <lb/> 1/1+c <lb/> 2 <lb/> s <lb/> . <lb/> (66) <lb/>The significance of the contour can be understood as follows: if a Q ¯ <lb/> Q pair is pro-<lb/>duced inside the contour, the pair cannot escape and hence the resonance cannot <lb/>be formed. If it is produced outside the contour, it survives. Since the Q ¯ <lb/> Q pair <lb/>takes finite time (τ  F  ) to form the physical resonances (J/ψ, Υ, etc.), the boundary <lb/>of the region (r  s  ), where the quarkonium formation is suppressed, has been quan-<lb/>tified by equating the duration of screening time τ  s  (r) to the formation time t  F <lb/> in the plasma frame (= γτ  F  , where γ is the dilation factor). For the equilibrium <lb/>era undergoing through the Bjorken boost-invariant expansion, the screening radius <lb/>can calculated as: <lb/> r  s  = R  T  (1 − A) <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  Θ(1 − A) , <lb/> (67) <lb/> A = <lb/> ǫ  s <lb/> ǫ  i <lb/>  t  F <lb/> τ  i <lb/>  1+c <lb/> 2 <lb/> s <lb/> + <lb/> c <lb/>  4η <lb/>3s  + <lb/> ζ <lb/>s <lb/> ǫ  i <lb/> tF <lb/>τi <lb/>  1+cs <lb/> 2 <lb/> ˜ <lb/> τ  2 <lb/> s <lb/> − <lb/> 1 <lb/>˜ <lb/> τ  2 <lb/> i <lb/>  1/β <lb/> , <lb/> (68) <lb/>which depends on the initial conditions, the dynamics of the evolution, and also <lb/>the dynamical properties of the resonance states. Since the initial conditions are <lb/>related to the centrality of the collisions, thus the screening boundary gives rise a <lb/>centrality dependent suppression pattern. Suppose a Q ¯ <lb/> Q pair is created initially <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-19 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 20 <lb/> U. Kakade, B. K. Patra &amp; L. Thakur <lb/></note>

			<body> at r  0  with the transverse momentum p  T  on the transverse plane. By the time the <lb/>resonance is formed, the pair moves then to a new position r = r  0  + t  F  p  T  /M <lb/> and if |r| is greater than or equal to the screening radius r  s  , the pair will escape <lb/>the deadly contour, otherwise the resonance will never be formed. This gives rise a <lb/>characteristic dependence of p  T  in the suppression pattern as well as the inequalities <lb/>of the cosine of the angle between r and p  T  vectors: <lb/>cos φ ≥ <lb/> r <lb/> 2 <lb/> s  − r <lb/> 2  <lb/> M − τ <lb/> 2 <lb/> F  p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T  /M <lb/> [2rτ  F  p  T  ] <lb/> , <lb/> (69) <lb/>which leads to a range of values of φ when the quarkonium would escape. <lb/>Now we can write for the survival probability of the quarkonium: <lb/> S(p  T  ) = <lb/> RT <lb/> 0 <lb/> r dr <lb/>  +φmax <lb/> −φmax <lb/> dφ P (r, p  T  ) <lb/> 2π <lb/>  RT <lb/> 0 <lb/> r dr P (r, p  T  ) <lb/> , <lb/> (70) <lb/>where φ  max  is the maximum positive angle (0 ≤ φ ≤ π) allowed by Eq. (69): <lb/> φ  max  = <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> π <lb/> if y ≤ −1 , <lb/> cos <lb/> −1  |y| if −1 &lt; y &lt; 1 , <lb/> 0 <lb/>if y ≥ 1 , <lb/> (71) <lb/>with <lb/> y = <lb/> r <lb/> 2 <lb/> s  − r <lb/> 2  <lb/> M − τ <lb/> 2 <lb/> F  p <lb/> 2 <lb/> T  /M <lb/> [2rτ  F  p  T  ] <lb/> , <lb/> (72) <lb/> M is the mass of the resonance and P is the probability for the quark-pair produc-<lb/>tion at (r, p  T  ), in a hard collision which may be factored out as <lb/> P (r, p  T  ) = f (r)g(p  T  ) , <lb/> (73) <lb/>where we take the profile function f (r) (with α = 1/2) as <lb/> f (r) ∝ <lb/> 1 − <lb/> r <lb/> 2 <lb/> R  2 <lb/> T <lb/>  α <lb/> θ(R  T  − r) . <lb/> (74) <lb/>Often experimental measurement of survival probability at a given number of <lb/>participants (N  part  ) or rapidity (y) is reported in terms of the p  T  integrated yield <lb/>ratio: <lb/> 102 <lb/> S = <lb/>  p <lb/> max <lb/> T <lb/> p  min <lb/> T <lb/> dp  T  S(p  T  ) <lb/>  p  max <lb/> T <lb/> p  min <lb/> T <lb/> dp  T <lb/> . <lb/> (75) <lb/>The production of b ¯ b mesons occur in-part through the production of higher excited <lb/> b ¯ b states and their decay into the ground state. Since the ground and excited <lb/>states have different sizes (binding energies), the excited states will dissolve earlier <lb/>compared to the tightly bound ground states, so a sequential suppression results. <lb/>However, the situation may not be that simple because the states have different <lb/>formation times too, opposite to their binding energies. So while calculating the <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 21 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Complex potential and bottomonium suppression at LHC energy <lb/></note>

			<body> p  T  -integrated inclusive survival probability for individual states, the feed-down cor-<lb/>rections may be taken into account as: <lb/> S <lb/> incl  (3S) = S(3S) , <lb/> (76) <lb/> S <lb/> incl  (2S) = f  1  S(2S) + f  2  S(3S) , <lb/> (77) <lb/> S <lb/> incl  (1S) = g  1  S(1S) + g  2  Sχ  b1  + g  3  S(2S) + g  4  S(3S) , <lb/> (78) <lb/>where the branching factors f  i  &apos;s and g  i  &apos;s are obtained from the CDF measure-<lb/>ment, <lb/> 103  where g  i  &apos;s are 0.509, 0.271, 0.107 and 0.113, respectively, assuming the <lb/>survival probabilities of Υ(3S) and χ  b  (2P ) are same with g  4  as combined frac-<lb/>tion while factors f  1  and f  2  are taken as 0.5. To study the centrality dependence <lb/>of the suppression factor, we use the CMS measurements of the pseudorapidity <lb/>and centrality dependent transverse energy density in Pb–Pb collisions at the LHC <lb/>energy, <lb/> 104  to obtain the initial condition: <lb/> ǫ  i  = <lb/> ς <lb/>A  T  cτ  i <lb/> J(y, η) <lb/>dE  T <lb/> dη <lb/>, <lb/> (79) <lb/>where the Jacobian J(y, η)(= 1.09) is taken from HYDJET 1.8 for the pseudo-<lb/>rapidity range |η| &lt; 0.35 in central collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> S  N N  = 2.76 TeV. <lb/> 104,105 <lb/> For the top 5% central (Pb–Pb) collisions at the LHC, the Bjorken formula (79) <lb/>(without the factor, ς) estimates the (initial) energy density, ǫ  i  = 14 GeV/fm <lb/> 3 <lb/> for initial time τ  i  = 1 fm. Although this estimate is 2.6 times larger than that at <lb/>RHIC energy, <lb/> 105  but it underestimates the initial energy density to the extent such <lb/>that even the excited states of Υ family have not been dissolved by the deconfined <lb/>medium. So a scale factor (ς ∼ 5) has been introduced in the Bjorken formula to <lb/>get rid of the unusually smaller values. <lb/> 106,107 <lb/> 3.5. Results and discussions <lb/> Quarkonium suppression in nucleus–nucleus collisions compared to p–p collisions <lb/>involves various time-scales associated with the initial condition, the dynamics of <lb/>the expansion, and the in-medium properties of the quarkonium states etc. The first <lb/>one is related to the time scale of thermalization, the second one is the formation <lb/>time of resonances (τ  F  ), which obeys the relation: τ  F  (1S) &lt; τ  F  (2S) &lt; τ  F  (3S). <lb/>The third one is related to the expansion of the medium which depends on c <lb/> 2 <lb/> S <lb/> through the EoS (p = c <lb/> 2 <lb/> s  ǫ). The fourth one is the screening time which depends on <lb/>both the screening energy, ǫ  s  and the speed of sound, c  s  . The screening time (τ  s  ) <lb/>also depends on the centrality of the collision, i.e. if the collision is more central <lb/>then the system starts initially from the higher energy density and take longer <lb/>time to reach ǫ  s  . Since the excited states are dissociated at lower temperatures <lb/>compared to the ground state, i.e. ǫ  s  (1S) ≫ ǫ  s  (2S) ≫ ǫ  s  (3S), so τ  s  &apos;s are related <lb/>by: τ  s  (1S) &lt; τ  s  (2S) &lt; τ  s  (3S). Thus, the hierarchies in screening and formations <lb/>times make the suppression pattern interesting for example, suppression of Υ(2S) <lb/>state may not always be more than Υ(1S) suppression, etc. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-21 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 22 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> U. Kakade, B. K. Patra &amp; L. Thakur <lb/></note>

			<body> 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>r (fm) <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.25 <lb/> τ <lb/> s <lb/> (fm/c) <lb/> η=ζ=0 <lb/>η=0,ζ≠0 <lb/>η≠0,ζ≠0 <lb/> ϒ(1S) <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>r (fm) <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/> τ <lb/> s <lb/> (fm/c) <lb/> η=0,ζ=0 <lb/>η=0,ζ≠0 <lb/>η≠0,ζ≠0 <lb/>ϒ(2S) <lb/> Fig. 4. Constant energy density contour for the Υ(1S) (left panel) and the Υ(2S) (right panel) <lb/>for different values of shear (η) and bulk (ζ) viscosities. <lb/> We will now discuss how the competition of the various time-scales transpires <lb/>into the suppression pattern. Suppose if ǫ  s  ǫ  i  , there will be no suppression and if <lb/> ǫ  i  ǫ  s  , there will be suppression but the extent of suppression depends on (i) how <lb/>large is the difference, ∆(= ǫ  i  − ǫ  s  ) between ǫ  i  and ǫ  s  , and (ii) how fast does the <lb/>system reach to ǫ  s  . As a consequence, (for a fixed centrality) Υ(1S) is suppressed <lb/>less than the excited states whereas for fixed ∆, τ  s  becomes larger due to the <lb/>presence of dissipative forces, compared to ideal fluid. Because the shear viscosity <lb/>slows down the expansion at the early stages of the expansion and thus affect the <lb/>screening of the Υ(1S) most whereas the bulk viscosity slows down the late stages <lb/>of the expansion and hence the excited states are affected much. <lb/>With this understanding, we now analyze the results on the screening energy <lb/>density contours for the Υ(1S) and Υ(2S) states in Fig. 4 at LHC energy. The <lb/>main observations are: (i) the contour of the excited states are bigger than the <lb/>ground state because the system takes longer to reach ǫ  s  for the excited states <lb/>than the ground state (τ  s  (2S) &gt; τ  s  (1S)) and (ii) the contour of the ground state is <lb/>affected mainly by the shear term only, whereas the excited states are affected by <lb/>both. The above observations are reflected in the boundary of the screening region <lb/>(shown in Fig. 5). It is found that the size of the screening boundary (r  s  ) increases <lb/>rapidly with the centrality and explains why there is more suppression in most <lb/>central collision and less suppression in peripheral collision. To be more specific, <lb/>for 1S state, the screening boundary initially increases rapidly and gets saturated <lb/>beyond N  part  ≃ 300, while for the excited states it increases monotonically. This <lb/>explains why there are a saturation trend in the CMS data for 1S suppression for <lb/> N  part  &gt; 300 (left panel of Fig. 6) and gradual suppression for the excited (2S and <lb/>3S) states (in Fig. 7). <lb/>In Fig. 5, we also notice that for a given centrality, the screening boundary for <lb/>the Υ(1S) state gets squeezed rapidly for Q ¯ <lb/> Q pairs having larger p  T  , while the <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-22 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 23 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Complex potential and bottomonium suppression at LHC energy <lb/></note>

			<body> 0 <lb/> 100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>N Part <lb/> 5.6 <lb/>5.8 <lb/>6 <lb/>6.2 <lb/>6.4 <lb/>6.6 <lb/>6.8 <lb/>7 <lb/> r <lb/> s <lb/> (fm) <lb/> P t =1 GeV <lb/>P T =2 GeV <lb/>P T =6 GeV <lb/>P T =10 GeV <lb/> ϒ(1S) <lb/> 0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>N Part <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/> r <lb/> s <lb/> (fm) <lb/> P T =1 GeV <lb/>P T =2 GeV <lb/>P T =6 GeV <lb/>P T =10 GeV <lb/> ϒ(2S) <lb/> Fig. 5. Centrality dependence of screening radius at fixed P  T  for Υ(1S) (left panel) and Υ(2S) <lb/>(right panel). <lb/> 100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>N PART <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1 <lb/> &lt; S &gt; <lb/> incl <lb/> ϒ(1S) <lb/> R AA  ϒ(1S) CMS Data <lb/> η/s=0.08, ζ/s≠0 <lb/>η/s=0.3, ζ/s≠0 <lb/> 2.5 <lb/>5 <lb/>7.5 <lb/>10 <lb/>12.5 <lb/>P T (GeV) <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/> S(P <lb/> T <lb/> ) <lb/> ϒ(1S) <lb/> R AA CMS Y(1S) PbPb <lb/> √S  NN =2.76 TeV <lb/>cent. 0-100% <lb/>Our result (η=0.3, ζ≠0) <lb/> Fig. 6. Centrality dependence of suppression factor for Υ(1S) (left panel) and variation of sup-<lb/>pression factor against P  T  for Υ(1S) (right panel). <lb/> 100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>N part <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> &lt; S &gt; <lb/> incl <lb/> ϒ(2S) <lb/> R AA  ϒ(2S) CMS data <lb/> η/s = 0.3 , ζ/s ≠ 0 <lb/> 100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>N part <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> &lt; S &gt; <lb/> incl <lb/> ϒ(3S) <lb/> ϒ(3S) (η/s=0.3 , ζ/s≠0) <lb/> ↓ <lb/> 0-100 % <lb/> ↓ ϒ(3S) 95 % upper limit (CMS ) <lb/> Fig. 7. The centrality dependence of the inclusive survival probability of the 2S (left panel) and <lb/>3S (right panel) states, respectively. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-23 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 24 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> U. Kakade, B. K. Patra &amp; L. Thakur <lb/></note>

			<body> boundary gets swelled for pairs with smaller p  T  . Thus for smaller participants, the <lb/> p  T  (above which a pair can escape) is larger than the larger participants. Since <lb/>the production of partons with smaller p  T  &apos;s are more abundant in collisions of <lb/>smaller centrality than the higher centrality, so the above observation explains why <lb/>there is more suppression even in the smaller centrality (which will be seen in left <lb/>panel of Fig. 6). Finally the sensitivity of the transverse momenta is less prominent <lb/>for the excited states, that is why there is no strong centrality dependence in the <lb/>suppression pattern for Υ(2S) and (3S) states (which will be seen later in Fig. 7), <lb/>in contrast to the Υ(1S) state (left panel of Fig. 6). <lb/>With these ingredients, we explain our results on the inclusive survival proba-<lb/>bility for the Υ(1S) state computed from the feed down of the excited states (left <lb/>panel of Fig. 6). We found that the suppression increases with the centrality up to <lb/> N  part  = 300 and nearly saturates beyond N  part  &gt; 350. This finding is compatible <lb/>with our earlier observation (left panel of Fig. 5), where the screening radius (r  s  ) <lb/>is almost independent of the centrality beyond a certain value. We also notice that <lb/>the inclusive (survival) probability (averaged over the centrality) for Υ(1S) state <lb/>increases linearly with p  T  (right panel of Fig. 6). This is again compatible with our <lb/>earlier observation, where for a given centrality, r  s  increases almost linearly with <lb/> p  T  . In Fig. 7, we have found that the survival probability for Υ(2S) and (3S) states <lb/>decrease slowly with the centrality. This finding matches with our earlier observa-<lb/>tion, where for a given p  T  , the screening radius (r  s  ) for 2S state increases linearly <lb/>(smaller slope) with the centrality and for a given centrality, r  S  almost remains <lb/>constant with p  T  . <lb/>The initial state effects affect the Υ(nS) states in a similar manner, so <lb/>the possible acceptance and/or efficiency differences cancel out in the ratio, <lb/>Υ(nS)/Υ(1S)  Pb Pb  (with respect to the p–p collisions). Moreover the final state <lb/>nuclear absorption effects are expected to minimum at LHC energies, <lb/> 108  so we have <lb/>calculated the double ratio (in Fig. 8), which shows poor suppression of 2S state <lb/>with respect to 1S state for peripheral collision and no characteristic dependence on <lb/>the collision centrality for N  part  &gt; 100 (left panel of Fig. 8). But the CMS results <lb/> 4 <lb/> show more suppression of Υ(2S) for peripheral collisions, which may be due to some <lb/>additional suppression mechanisms which are still missing in the theoretical calcu-<lb/>lations or CMS measurements are not sufficient to disentangle the nuclear effects <lb/>from medium effects and it could be better resolved on availability of more data <lb/>from heavy-ion and proton–nucleus collision runs at LHC in future. The results of <lb/>double ratio show more suppression for the excited states than the ground state <lb/>(right panel of Fig. 8). However, at present experimental results are not available <lb/>to compare our predictions. <lb/>To explore the effects of the viscous forces on the suppression, we take the shear <lb/>viscosity to entropy ratio, η/s as 0.08 and 0.3 along with the parametrization of <lb/> ζ/s, taken from (62). We notice that the suppression increases with η/s because <lb/>more the η/s is more the screening time. Furthermore our estimate matches with <lb/>the CMS data for the perturbative result of η/s (0.3) and it seems justified because <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-24 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 25 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> Complex potential and bottomonium suppression at LHC energy <lb/></note>

			<body> 0 <lb/> 100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/> N part <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> [ϒ(2S)/ϒ(1S)] <lb/> PbPb <lb/> /[ϒ(2S)/ϒ(1S)] <lb/> pp <lb/> CMS data <lb/>Our result <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/> N part <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> [ϒ(3S)/ϒ(1S)] <lb/> PbPb <lb/> /[ϒ(3S)/ϒ(1S)] <lb/> pp <lb/> Our result <lb/> Fig. 8. Centrality dependence of the double ratio <lb/> Υ(2S)/Υ(1S)|Pb Pb <lb/>Υ(2S)/Υ(1S)|pp <lb/> (left panel) and <lb/> Υ(3S)/Υ(1S)|Pb Pb <lb/>Υ(3S)/Υ(1S)|pp <lb/> (right panel), respectively. <lb/> the screening energy density for Υ(1S) state is much higher where the perturbative <lb/>calculation becomes meaningful. Thus the suppression of Υ(1S) states can be used <lb/>to constrain the η/s ratio. <lb/>Our calculation assumes that the system produced in relativistic heavy-ion colli-<lb/>sion expands successively though pre-equilibrium and equilibrium evolutions, which <lb/>follow slower and faster cooling rate, respectively. Since the physics of isotropiza-<lb/>tion/equilibration is yet to understand theoretically, so the duration of the pre-<lb/>equilibrium era is uncertain. Hence we vary the isotropization time scale (τ  iso  ) and <lb/>constrain it by the bottomonium suppression observed at LHC, as follows: The <lb/>dynamical suppression for any state starts only after its formation, i.e. τ ≥ τ  F  and <lb/>continues as long as the energy density of the system is greater than the screening <lb/>energy density, i.e. ǫ ≥ ǫ  s  . Since the duration of screening times depends especially <lb/>on the cooling rate (discussed in the first paragraph of this section), so the expan-<lb/>sion rates and the durations of the pre-equilibrium and equilibrium evolutions offer <lb/>a rich structure to the suppression pattern. For a given state if τ  F  ≥ τ  iso  then state <lb/>is suppressed dynamically through the equilibrium hydrodynamics only whereas if <lb/> τ  F  &lt; τ  iso  then state is suppressed through the pre-equilibrium evolution till τ  iso <lb/> and then through the equilibrium hydrodynamics. Therefore for τ  iso  = 0.2 fm/c, <lb/>all the bottomonium states (with τ  F  , given in Table 1) are suppressed through <lb/>the equilibrium regime, and hence shows less inclusive suppression, compared to <lb/>higher τ  iso  . For example, for τ  iso  = 0.3 fm/c, only the Υ(1S) state passes through <lb/>both pre-equilibrium and equilibrium evolutions whereas the excited states (Υ(2S), <lb/>Υ(3S) etc.) pass through the equilibrium regime only. So the excited states are not <lb/>affected by the pre-equilibrium evolution. Moreover since the time spent by Υ(1S) <lb/>in the pre-equilibrium regime is very small and the difference in the cooling rates <lb/>of two regimes are not large in the initial stage of evolution, so the effect of varying <lb/> τ  iso  (from 0.2–1 fm/c) on the Υ(1S) suppression is not drastic. This is also seen in <lb/>Fig. 9(a). <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-25 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 26 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> U. Kakade, B. K. Patra &amp; L. Thakur <lb/></note>

			<body> 100 <lb/> 200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>N PART <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/> &lt; S &gt; <lb/> incl <lb/> ϒ(1S) <lb/> R AA  ϒ(1S) CMS Data <lb/> τ  iso = 0.2 fm/c <lb/> τ  iso = 0.3 fm/c <lb/> τ  iso = 0.5 fm/c <lb/> τ  iso = 1.0 fm/c <lb/> (a) <lb/> 100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>N part <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> &lt; S &gt; <lb/> incl <lb/> ϒ(2S) <lb/> R AA  ϒ(2S) CMS data <lb/> τ  iso = 0.2 fm/c <lb/> τ  iso = 0.3 fm/c <lb/> (b) <lb/> 100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>N part <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> &lt; S &gt; <lb/> incl <lb/> ϒ(3S) <lb/> τ  iso = 0.2 fm/c <lb/> τ  iso = 0.3 fm/c <lb/> ↓ <lb/> 0-100 % <lb/> ↓ ϒ(3S) 95 % upper limit (CMS ) <lb/> (c) <lb/> (a) <lb/> (b) <lb/>(c) <lb/>Fig. 9. Centrality dependence of the sequential suppression of Υ(1S) for different isotropization <lb/>times (a) and same for Υ(2S) and Υ(3S) in (b) and (c), respectively. <lb/> At a first glance the excited states (Υ(2S), Υ(3S), etc.) cannot probe the pre-<lb/>equilibrium regime directly because they formed later, compared to isotropization <lb/> τ  iso  of the system. But for a given initial time (τ  i  ), as τ  iso  is increased, the system <lb/>will find less time to reach the formation time (for excited states, τ  F  is usually larger <lb/>than τ  iso  ). As a result the quarkonium state will encounter relatively hotter system <lb/>at τ  F  and hence will be suppressed more. This is exactly seen in Figs. 9(b) and 9(c). <lb/>However, since the excited states contribute a smaller fraction of total bottomonium <lb/>yields, having bad statistics, compared to 1S, so the excited states may not be <lb/>suitable handle to decipher the time scales associated with the equilibration. <lb/> 4. Conclusions <lb/> In conclusion, we have studied the sequential suppression for Υ(1S) and Υ(2S) <lb/>states at the LHC energy in a longitudinally expanding partonic system, which <lb/>undergone the successive pre-equilibrium and equilibrium phases in the presence <lb/>of dissipative forces. Quarkonium suppression in nucleus–nucleus collisions com-<lb/>pared to p–p collisions couples the in-medium properties of the quarkonium states <lb/>with the dynamics of the expanding medium. In this work, we obtained the dis-<lb/>sociation temperatures of the quarkonium states by correcting both the perturba-<lb/>tive and nonperturbative terms in Q ¯ <lb/> Q potential in (an)isotropic medium through <lb/>the HTL resummed perturbation. We then modeled the pre-equilibrium evolution <lb/>as anisotropic fluid via the time-dependent anisotropic parameter, ξ(τ ) and hard <lb/>momentum scale, P  hard  (τ ) while the equilibrium era is governed by the second-order <lb/>dissipative hydrodynamics in (1 + 1) Bjorken boost-invariant model and coupled <lb/>them together to estimate the sequential suppression. The expansion in equilib-<lb/>rium hydrodynamics is controlled by the speed of sound c <lb/> 2 <lb/> s  , which could be further <lb/>handled by the lattice QCD equation of state, the shear (η) and bulk (ζ) viscous <lb/>forces, etc. <lb/>The bulk viscosity in conjunction with the shear viscosity enhances the cool-<lb/>ing rate and thus causes more suppression to the ground state, however, the bulk <lb/></body>

			<page> 1550043-26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 27 <lb/></note>

			<body> Complex potential and bottomonium suppression at LHC energy <lb/> viscosity ζ/s is significant for exited states. The sequential suppression is a very <lb/>complex phenomenon, which depends on several parameters such as the scale of the <lb/>dissociation of quarkonium states, the decay of the excited states, the centrality of <lb/>collision, the transverse momentum, the screening time, the formation time, the <lb/>dissipative forces, the isotropization time, etc. The tiny formation time (compared <lb/>to the isotropization time) and tightly bound character of the Υ(1S) state helps <lb/>the suppression of bottomonium to constrain both the isotropization time (0.3 fm) <lb/>as well as the shear viscosity-to-the entropy ratio (0.3). <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments <lb/> Binoy Krishna Patra is thankful for some financial assistance from CSIR project <lb/>(CSR-656-PHY), Government of India and is also thankful to Asis Kumar Chaud-<lb/>huri for a fruitful discussion during this work. Uttam Kakade is also thankful to <lb/>Government of Maharashtra for the financial assistance. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. P. Petreczky, J. Phys. G 39, 093002 (2012), arXiv:1203.5320 [hep-lat]. <lb/>2. T. Matsui and H. Satz, Phys. Lett. B 178, 416 (1986). <lb/>3. N. Brambilla et al., Eur. Phys. J. C 71, 1534 (2011), arXiv:1010.5827 [hep-ph]. <lb/>4. CMS Collab. (S. Chatrchyan et al.), Phys. Rev. Lett. 109, 222301 (2012), <lb/>arXiv:1208.2826 [nucl-ex]. <lb/>5. ALICE Collab. (B. Abelev et al.), Phys. Rev. Lett. 109, 072301 (2012), arXiv: <lb/>1202.1383 [hep-ex]. <lb/>6. M. Laine, O. Philipsen, P. Romatschke and M. Tassler, J. High Energy Phys. 0703, <lb/> 054 (2007). <lb/>7. F. Karsch, M. T. Mehr and H. Satz, Z. Phys. C 37, 617 (1988). <lb/>8. L. D. McLerran and B. Svetitsky, Phys. Rev. D 24, 450 (1981). <lb/>9. S. Nadkarni, Phys. Rev. D 34, 3904 (1986). <lb/>10. S. Nadkarni, Phys. Rev. D 33, 3738 (1986). <lb/>11. O. Philipsen, Nucl. Phys. A 820, 33C (2009), arXiv:0810.4685 [hep-ph]. <lb/>12. M. A. Escobedo and J. Soto, Phys. Rev. A 78, 032520 (2008), arXiv:0804.0691 <lb/>[hep-ph]. <lb/>13. N. Brambilla, J. Alighieri, A. Vairo and P. Petreczky, Phys. Rev. D 78, 014017 <lb/>(2008). <lb/>14. A. Pineda and J. Soto, Nucl. Phys. B (Proc. Suppl.) 64, 428 (1998), arXiv:hep-<lb/>ph/9707481. <lb/>15. N. Brambilla, A. Pineda, J. Soto and A. Vairo, Nucl. Phys. B 566, 275 (2000), <lb/>arXiv:hep-ph/9907240. <lb/>16. M. Laine, O. Philipsen and M. Tassler, J. High Energy Phys. 09, 066 (2007). <lb/>17. A. Rothkopf, T. Hatsuda and S. Sasaki, Phys. Rev. Lett. 108, 162001 (2012), <lb/>arXiv:1108.1579 [hep-lat]. <lb/>18. Y. Burnier and A. Rothkopf, Phys. Rev. D 86, 051503 (2012), arXiv:1208.1899 <lb/>[hep-ph]. <lb/>19. Y. Burnier, M. Laine and M. Vepsalainen, J. High Energy Phys. 01, 043 (2008). <lb/>20. C. Miao, A. Mocsy and P. Petreczky, Nucl. Phys. A 855, 125 (2011). <lb/>21. N. Brambilla, M. A. Escobedo, J. Ghiglieri, J. Soto and A. Vairo, J. High Energy <lb/>Phys. 09, 038 (2010). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 1550043-27 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 28 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> U. Kakade, B. K. Patra &amp; L. Thakur <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> 22. L. Grandchamp, S. Lumpkins, D. Sun, H. van Hees and R. Rapp, Phys. Rev. C 73, <lb/> 064906 (2006). <lb/>23. R. Rapp, D. Blaschke and P. Crochet, Part. Nucl. Phys. 65, 209 (2010), <lb/>arXiv:0807.2470. <lb/>24. F. Riek and R. Rapp, New J. Phys. 13, 045007 (2011). <lb/>25. Y. Akamatsu and A. Rothkopf, Phys. Rev. D 85, 105011 (2012), arXiv:1110.1203 <lb/>[hep-ph]. <lb/>26. F. Karsch, M. G. Mustafa and M. H. Thoma, Phys. Lett. B 497, 249 (2001). <lb/>27. A. Mocsy and P. Petreczky, Eur. Phys. J. C 43, 77 (2005). <lb/>28. A. Mocsy and P. Petreczky, Phys. Rev. D 73, 074007 (2006). <lb/>29. A. Mocsy and P. Petreczky, Phys. Rev. D 77, 014501 (2008). <lb/>30. C. Y. Wong, Phys. Rev. C 72, 034906 (2005). <lb/>31. D. Cabrera and R. Rapp, Phys. Rev. D 76, 114506 (2007). <lb/>32. W. M. Alberico, A. Beraudo, A. De Pace and A. Molinari, Phys. Rev. D 77, 017502 <lb/>(2008). <lb/>33. Ph. de Forcrand et al., Phys. Rev. D 63, 054501 (2001). <lb/>34. R. Vogt, Phys. Rev. C 81, 044903 (2010). <lb/>35. R. Vogt, Phys. Rev. C 61, 035203 (2000), arXiv:hep-ph/9907317. <lb/>36. S. Gavin and J. Milana, Phys. Rev. Lett. 68, 1834 (1992). <lb/>37. X. M. Xu, D. Kharzeev, H. Satz and X. N. Wang, Phys. Rev. C 53, 3051 (1997). <lb/>38. B. K. Patra and V. J. Menon, Eur. Phys. J. C 37, 115 (2004). <lb/>39. B. K. Patra and V. J. Menon, Eur. Phys. J. C 44, 567 (2005). <lb/>40. B. K. Patra and V. J. Menon, Eur. Phys. J. C 48, 207 (2006). <lb/>41. R. Vogt, Phys. Rep. 310, 197 (1999). <lb/>42. F. Karsch, M. T. Mehr and H. Satz, Z. Phys. C 37, 617 (1988). <lb/>43. F. Karsch and H. Satz, Z. Phys. C 51, 209 (1991). <lb/>44. J. P. Blaizot and J. Y. Ollitrault, Phys. Rev. Lett. 77, 1703 (1992). <lb/>45. NA50 Collab. (B. Alessandro et al.), Eur. Phys. J. C 39, 335 (2005). <lb/>46. NA60 Collab. (R. Arnaldi et al.), Phys. Rev. Lett. 99, 132302 (2007). <lb/>47. S. Digal, P. Petreczky and H. Satz, Phys. Rev. D 64, 094015 (2001). <lb/>48. M. Martinez and M. Strickland, Nucl. Phys. A 856, 68 (2011). <lb/>49. M. Martinez and M. Strickland, Nucl. Phys. A 848, 183 (2010). <lb/>50. M. Martinez, R. Ryblewski and M. Strickland, Phys. Rev. C 85, 064913 (2012). <lb/>51. R. Ryblewski and W. Florkowski, J. Phys. G 38, 015104 (2011). <lb/>52. R. Ryblewski and W. Florkowski, Phys. Rev. C 85, 064901 (2012). <lb/>53. W. Florkowski and R. Ryblewski, Phys. Rev. C 83, 034907 (2011), arXiv:1007.0130. <lb/>54. A. Dumitru, Y. Guo and M. Strickland, Phys. Lett. B 662, 37 (2008). <lb/>55. A. Dumitru, Y. Guo and M. Strickland, Phys. Rev. D 79, 114003 (2009). <lb/>56. A. Dumitru, Y. Guo, A. Mocsy and M. Strickland, Phys. Rev. D 79, 54019 (2009). <lb/>57. Y. Burnier, M. Laine and M. Vepsalainen, Phys. Lett. B 678, 86 (2009), <lb/>arXiv:0903.3467. <lb/>58. A. Dumitru, Y. Hatta, J. Lenaghan, K. Orginos and R. D. Pisarski, Phys. Rev. D <lb/> 70, 034511 (2004). <lb/>59. M. Cheng et al., Phys. Rev. D 78, 034506 (2008). <lb/>60. Y. Maezawa, N. Ukita, S. Aoki, S. Ejiri, T. Hatsuda, N. Ishii and K. Kanaya, Phys. <lb/>Rev. D 75, 074501 (2007). <lb/>61. O. Andreev and V. I. Zakharov, Phys. Lett. B 645, 437 (2007). <lb/>62. V. Agotiya, V. Chandra and B. K. Patra, Phys. Rev. C 80, 025210 (2009). <lb/>63. L. Thakur, N. Haque, U. Kakade and B. K. Patra, Phys. Rev. D 88, 054022 (2013). <lb/>64. L. Thakur, U. Kakade and B. K. Patra, Phys. Rev. D 89, 094020 (2014). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 1550043-28 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. <lb/> March 24, 2015 15:52 <lb/>IJMPA <lb/>S0217751X15500438 page 29 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> Complex potential and bottomonium suppression at LHC energy <lb/> 65. M. Strickland, Phys. Rev. Lett. 107, 132301 (2011), arXiv:1106.2571. <lb/>66. P. Arnold, J. Lenaghan, G. Moore and L. Yaffe, Phys. Rev. Lett. 94, 072302 (2005). <lb/>67. U. Romatschke, Phys. Rev. Lett. 99, 172301 (2007). <lb/>68. A. Rebhan, P. Romatschke and M. Stickland, Phys. Rev. Lett. 94, 102303 (2005). <lb/>69. M. Laine, Nucl. Phys. A 820, 25C (2009), arXiv:0810.1112. <lb/>70. K. Kajantie, M. Laine, J. Peisa, A. Rajantie, K. Rummukainen and M. E. Shaposh-<lb/>nikov, Phys. Rev. Lett. 79, 3130 (1997). <lb/>71. P. Petreczky, Eur. Phys. J. C 43, 51 (2005). <lb/>72. E. Megias, E. Ruiz Arriola and L. L. Salcedo, Phys. Rev. D 75, 105019 (2007). <lb/>73. S. Digal, O. Kaczmarek, F. Karsch and H. Satz, Eur. Phys. J. C 43, 71 (2005). <lb/>74. M. Margotta, K. McCarty, C. McGahan, M. Strickland and D. Yager-Elorriaga, <lb/> Phys. Rev. D 83, 105019 (2011). <lb/>75. B. Schenke and M. Strickland, Phys. Rev. D 76, 025023 (2007). <lb/>76. M. Martinez and M. Strickland, Phys. Rev. Lett. 100, 102301 (2008). <lb/>77. A. Mocsy and P. Petreczky, Phys. Rev. Lett. 99, 211602 (2007). <lb/>78. M. Strickland and D. Bazow, Nucl. Phys. A 879, 25 (2012). <lb/>79. P. Romatschke and M. Strikland, Phys. Rev. D 68, 036004 (2003). <lb/>80. M. Martinez and M. Strickland, Phys. Rev. C 79, 044903 (2009). <lb/>81. O. Kaczmarek, S. Ejiri, F. Karsch, E. Laermann and F. Zantow, Prog. Theor. Phys. <lb/>Suppl. 153, 287 (2004). <lb/>82. Y. Burnier, O. Kaczmarek and A. Rothkopf, arXiv:1410.2546 [hep-lat]. <lb/>83. S. Mrowezynski, Phys. Lett. B 314, 118 (1999). <lb/>84. P. Arnold, G. D. Moore and L. G. Yaffe, J. High Energy Phys. 05, 051 (2003). <lb/>85. S. Mrowczynski and M. H. Thoma, Phys. Rev. D 62, 036011 (2000). <lb/>86. M. Strickland, J. Phys. G: Nucl. Part. Phys. 34, S429 (2007). <lb/>87. M. Martinez and M. Strickland, Phys. Rev. C 78, 034917 (2008). <lb/>88. S. Borsanyi, G. Endrodi, Z. Fodor, S. D. Katz, S. Krieg, C. Ratti and K. Szabo, <lb/> J. High Energy Phys. 08, 053 (2012). <lb/>89. S. Borsanyi, G. Endrodi, Z. Fodor, S. D. Katz, S. Krieg, C. Ratti and K. Szabo, <lb/> J. High Energy Phys. 11, 077 (2011), arXiv:1204.6710v2. <lb/>90. W. Israel and J. M. Stewart, Ann. Phys. 118, 341 (1979). <lb/>91. U. W. Heinz, arXiv:nucl-th/0512049. <lb/>92. A. Muronga, Phys. Rev. C 69, 034903 (2004). <lb/>93. R. Baier, P. Romatschke and U. A. Wiedemann, Phys. Rev. C 73, 064903 (2006). <lb/>94. R. Baier, P. Romatschke, D. Son, A. Starinets and M. Stephanov, J. High Energy <lb/>Phys. 04, 100 (2008). <lb/>95. R. Fries, B. Muller and A. Schafer, Phys. Rev. C 78, 034913 (2003). <lb/>96. P. Arnold, G. D. Moore and L. G. Yaffe, J. High Energy Phys. 11, 001 (2000). <lb/>97. P. Kovtun, D. Son and A. Starinets, Phys. Rev. Lett. 94, 111601 (2005). <lb/>98. A. Jaiswal, R. Bhalerao and S. Pal, Phys. Rev. C 87, 021901 (2013). <lb/>99. K. Rajagopal and N. Tripuraneni, J. High Energy Phys. 1003, 018 (2010). <lb/>100. H. B. Mayer, Phys. Rev. Lett. 100, 162001 (2008). <lb/>101. M. Prakash, M. Prakash, R. Venugopalan and G. Welke, Phys. Rep. 227, 321 (1993). <lb/>102. B. K. Patra, V. Agotia and V. Chandra, Eur. Phys. J. C 67, 465 (2010). <lb/>103. T. Affolder et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 84, 2094 (2000). <lb/>104. CMS Collab., Phys. Rev. Lett. 109, 152303 (2012). <lb/>105. Phenix Collab., Phys. Rev. C 71, 034908 (2005) [Erratum: ibid. 71, 049901 (2005)]. <lb/>106. T. Hirano and K. Tsuda, Phys. Rev. C 66, 054905 (2002). <lb/>107. T. Hirano, Phys. Rev. C 65, 011901(R) (2001). <lb/>108. Z. W. Lin and C. M. Ko, Phys. Lett. B 503, 104 (2001). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 1550043-29 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> Int.  J. Mod. Phys. A 2015.30. Downloaded from www.worldscientific.com <lb/> by  EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) on 04/13/15. For personal use only. </note>


	</text>
</tei>
