<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="footnote"> arXiv:1503.08530v1  [math.DG] 30 Mar 2015 <lb/></note>

			<front> ON THE K ¨ <lb/>AHLER STRUCTURES OVER QUOT SCHEMES, II <lb/> INDRANIL BISWAS AND HARISH SESHADRI <lb/> Abstract. Let X be a compact connected Riemann surface of genus g, with g ≥ 2, <lb/>and let O  X  denote the sheaf of holomorphic functions on X. Fix positive integers r and <lb/> d and let Q(r, d) be the Quot scheme parametrizing all torsion coherent quotients of O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X <lb/> of degree d. We prove that Q(r, d) does not admit a Kähler metric whose holomorphic <lb/>bisectional curvatures are all nonnegative. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> Let X be a compact connected Riemann surface of genus g, with g ≥ 2. For any positive <lb/>integer d, let S <lb/> d  (X) denote the d-fold symmetric product of X. The main theorem of <lb/>[BoR] says the following (see [BoR, Theorem 1.1]): If d ≤ 2(g − 1), then S <lb/> d  (X) does <lb/>not admit any Kähler metric for which all the holomorphic bisectional curvatures are <lb/>nonnegative. <lb/>A natural generalization of the symmetric product S <lb/> d  (X) is the Quot scheme Q(r, d) <lb/> that parametrizes all torsion coherent quotients of O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  of degree d. So, Q(1, d) = S <lb/> d  (X). <lb/>These Quot schemes arise naturally in the study of vector bundles on curves (see [BGL]). <lb/>They also appear in mathematical physics as moduli spaces of vortices (cf. [Ba], [BiR], <lb/>[BoR]). <lb/>Our aim here is to prove the following (see Theorem 3.1): <lb/> The complex manifold Q(r, d) does not admit any Kähler metric such that all the holo-<lb/>morphic bisectional curvatures are nonnegative. <lb/> In [BS], this was proved under the assumption that d ≤ 2(g − 1). <lb/>2. The Albanese map for Q <lb/> Let X be a compact connected Riemann surface of genus g, with g ≥ 2. The sheaf of <lb/>germs of holomorphic functions on X will be denoted by O  X  . Fix positive integers r and <lb/> d. Let <lb/> Q := Q(r, d) <lb/> be the Quot scheme that parametrizes all torsion coherent quotients of O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  of degree d. <lb/> In other words, Q parametrizes all coherent subsheaves of O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  of rank r and degree −d. <lb/></body>

			<front> 2000 Mathematics Subject Classification. 14H60, 32Q10, 14H81. <lb/> Key words and phrases. Quot scheme, holomorphic bisectional curvature, automorphism, Albanese <lb/>map. <lb/></front>

			<page> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> I. BISWAS AND H. SESHADRI <lb/></note>

			<body> The group of permutations of {1 , · · · , d} will be denoted by P  d  . Let S <lb/> d  (X) := X <lb/> d  /P  d <lb/> be the symmetric product of X. The Quot scheme Q(1, d) is identified with S <lb/> d  (X) by <lb/>sending any quotient Q <lb/> ′  ∈ Q(1, d) of O  X  to the scheme-theoretic support of Q <lb/> ′  . Take <lb/>any quotient Q ∈ Q = Q(r, d). Consider the corresponding short exact sequence <lb/>0 −→ K  Q  −→ O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  −→ Q −→ 0 <lb/>on X. Let <lb/>0 −→ <lb/>  r <lb/> K  Q  −→ <lb/>  r <lb/> O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  = O  X  −→ ( <lb/>  r <lb/> O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  )/( <lb/>  r <lb/> K  Q  ) := Q <lb/> ′  −→ 0 <lb/>be the short exact sequence obtained from it by taking r-th exterior product. Sending <lb/>any Q ∈ Q to Q <lb/> ′  ∈ Q(1, d) constructed as above from Q we get a morphism <lb/>(2.1) <lb/> f : Q −→ S <lb/> d  (X) = Q(1, d) . <lb/> Lemma 2.1. Take any point z ∈ S <lb/> d  (X). There is a sequence of holomorphic maps <lb/>ending at the point z, <lb/>Y <lb/> z <lb/>d <lb/>p  d <lb/> −→ Y <lb/> z <lb/>d−1 <lb/>p  d−1 <lb/> −→ · · · <lb/> p  2 <lb/> −→ Y <lb/> z <lb/> 1 <lb/> p  1 <lb/> −→ Y <lb/> z <lb/> 0  = {z} , <lb/> such that <lb/> • all the fibers of each p  i  are isomorphic to CP <lb/> r−1  , and <lb/> • there is a surjective holomorphic map from Y <lb/> z <lb/>d  to the fiber f <lb/> −1  (z). <lb/> Proof. Fix a point <lb/>(x  1  , · · · , x  d  ) ∈ X <lb/> d <lb/> that projects to z under the quotient map X <lb/> d  −→ X <lb/> d  /P  d  = S <lb/> d  (X). For any integer <lb/> i ∈ [1 , d], let Y <lb/> z <lb/>i  be the space of all filtrations of coherent analytic subsheaves <lb/>(2.2) <lb/> W  i  ⊂ W  i−1  ⊂ · · · ⊂ W  1  ⊂ W  0  = O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  , <lb/> where W  j  /W  j+1  , 0 ≤ j ≤ i − 1, is a torsion sheaf supported at x  j+1  such that the <lb/>dimension of the stalk of W  j  /W  j+1  at x  j+1  is one. Therefore, W  j+1  is a holomorphic <lb/>vector bundle of rank r and degree −j − 1. In particular, W  i  is a holomorphic vector <lb/>bundle of rank r and degree −i. We have the natural forgetful map <lb/> p  i  : Y <lb/> z <lb/>i  −→ Y <lb/> z <lb/>i−1 <lb/> that forgets the smallest subsheaf in the filtration (it forgets W  i  in (2.2)). The inverse <lb/>image, under the projection p  i  , of a point <lb/> W  i−1  ⊂ · · · ⊂ W  1  ⊂ W  0  = O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X <lb/> of Y <lb/> z <lb/>i−1  is the projective space P(W  i−1  )  x  i  that parametrizes all hyperplanes in the fiber of <lb/>the vector bundle W  i−1  over the point x  i  . In particular, the map p  i  makes Y <lb/> z <lb/>i  a projective <lb/>bundle over Y <lb/> z <lb/>i−1  of relative dimension r − 1. <lb/>Sending any point <lb/> W  d  ⊂ W  d−1  ⊂ · · · ⊂ W  1  ⊂ W  0  = O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  , <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> ON THE K ¨ <lb/>AHLER STRUCTURES OVER QUOT SCHEMES, II <lb/></note>

			<page> 3 <lb/></page>

			<body> of Y <lb/> z <lb/> d  to the subsheaf W  d  ⊂ O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  we get a holomorphic map <lb/> Y <lb/> z <lb/>d  −→ f <lb/> −1  (z) . <lb/> This map is clearly surjective. <lb/> Let <lb/>(2.3) <lb/> ϕ : S <lb/> d  (X) −→ Pic <lb/> d  (X) <lb/>be the morphism that sends a divisor to the corresponding holomorphic line bundle on <lb/> X. <lb/> Corollary 2.2. The composition ϕ • f : Q −→ Pic <lb/> d  (X) is the Albanese morphism for <lb/>the variety Q. <lb/> Proof. Since there is no nonconstant morphism from a rational curve to an abelian variety, <lb/>from Lemma 2.1 it follows immediately that the Albanese morphism for Q factors through <lb/> f : Take any holomorphic line bundle L ∈ Pic <lb/> d  (X). Note that the fiber ϕ <lb/> −1  (L) is the <lb/>projective space PH <lb/> 0  (X, L) <lb/>  *  . Therefore, the Albanese morphism for Q factors through <lb/> ϕ • f . <lb/> 3. Holomorphic bisectional curvatures <lb/> We continue with the notation of Section 2. <lb/> Theorem 3.1. The complex manifold Q does not admit any Kähler metric such that all <lb/>the holomorphic bisectional curvatures are nonnegative. <lb/>Proof. Assume that Q admits a Kähler metric g  Q  with nonnegative holomorphic bisec-<lb/>tional curvatures. Let ω denote the Kähler form of g  Q  . <lb/>Let <lb/>(3.1) <lb/> ρ : <lb/> Q −→ Q <lb/> be the universal cover. Then, by Mok&apos;s uniformization theorem for compact Kähler <lb/>manifolds with nonnegative bisectional curvature [Mo, p. 179, Main Theorem], the Kähler <lb/>manifold ( <lb/> Q , ρ <lb/>  *  g  Q  ) decomposes as a Cartesian product <lb/>( <lb/> Q , ρ <lb/>  *  g) = (C <lb/> N  , g  0  ) × ( <lb/> k <lb/> i=1 <lb/> (CP <lb/> r  i  , g  i  )) × ( <lb/> ℓ <lb/> j=1 <lb/> ((H  j  , h  j  )) <lb/>of Kähler manifolds for some nonnegative integers r  1  , · · · , r  k  , , ℓ; here (C <lb/> N  , g  0  ) is the <lb/>Euclidean space with its standard complex structure and metric, g  i  are Kähler metrics <lb/>of nonnegative bisectional curvature on CP <lb/> r  i  , and h  j  are the standard symmetric Kähler <lb/>metrics on certain Hermitian symmetric spaces H  j  of compact type. In what follows we <lb/>do not need the specific information on the non-Euclidean factors in the decomposition. <lb/>We write <lb/>( <lb/> Q , ρ <lb/>  *  g  Q  ) = (C <lb/> N  , g  0  ) × (H , g <lb/> ′  ) , <lb/></body>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> I. BISWAS AND H. SESHADRI <lb/></note>

			<body> where (H, g <lb/> ′  ) = ( <lb/>  k <lb/> i=1  (CP <lb/> r  i  , g  i  )) × ( <lb/>  ℓ <lb/>j=1  ((H  j  , h  j  )). <lb/>Let <lb/> q  1  : C <lb/> N  × H −→ C <lb/> N <lb/> be the projection to the first factor. Let <lb/> γ ∈ Gal(ρ) <lb/>be a deck transformation for the covering ρ in (3.1). Since there is no nonconstant <lb/>holomorphic map from H to C <lb/> N  , there is a holomorphic isometry γ <lb/> ′  ∈ Aut(C <lb/> N  ) such <lb/>that <lb/> q  1  • γ = γ <lb/> ′  • q  1  . <lb/> Therefore, q  1  descends to a holomorphic submersion of the form <lb/>(3.2) <lb/> β : Q −→ Y <lb/> such that Y is (regularly) covered by C <lb/> N  ; so C <lb/> N  is a universal cover of Y . More precisely, <lb/>there is a Kähler form preserving covering map <lb/> ρ <lb/> ′  : C <lb/> N  −→ Y <lb/> such that ρ <lb/> ′  • q  1  = β • ρ. We note that β makes Q a holomorphic fiber bundle over Y <lb/> with fibers isomorphic to H. <lb/> Consider the C <lb/> ∞  distribution <lb/> S ⊂ T Q <lb/> on Q obtained by taking the orthogonal complement, with respect to ω, of the relative <lb/>tangent bundle for the projection β in (3.2). The pulled back distribution <lb/> ρ <lb/> ⋆  S = (dρ) <lb/> −1  (S) ⊂ T <lb/> Q <lb/> coincides with the relative tangent bundle for the projection q  2  : C <lb/> N  × H −→ H to <lb/>the second factor; here dρ : T <lb/> Q −→ T Q is the differential of ρ. In particular, ρ <lb/> ⋆  S is <lb/>an integrable holomorphic distribution. In other words, ρ <lb/> ⋆  S defines a flat holomorphic <lb/>connection on the fiber bundle <lb/> q  1  : C <lb/> N  × H −→ C <lb/> N  . <lb/> This implies that S is a flat holomorphic connection on the fiber bundle β : Q −→ Y . <lb/>Let <lb/>(3.3) <lb/> ∇ <lb/> denote this flat holomorphic connection on β : Q −→ Y . <lb/>We now need the following proposition. <lb/> Proposition 3.2. The fibers of the map β coincides with the fibers of the map ϕ • f . In <lb/>particular, there is a biholomorphism <lb/> α : Y −→ image(ϕ • f ) <lb/> such that α • β = ϕ • f . <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> ON THE K ¨ <lb/>AHLER STRUCTURES OVER QUOT SCHEMES, II <lb/></note>

			<page> 5 <lb/></page>

			<body> Proof of Proposition 3.2. Take a point y ∈ Y . Consider the restriction of the map ϕ • f <lb/> to β <lb/> −1  (y). Since β <lb/> −1  (y) = H is simply connected, this map <lb/>(ϕ • f )|  β  −1  (y)  : β <lb/> −1  (y) −→ Pic <lb/> d  (X) <lb/>lifts to a map <lb/> β <lb/> −1  (y) −→ <lb/> Pic <lb/> d  (X) , <lb/> where <lb/> Pic <lb/> d  (X) is the universal cover of Pic <lb/> d  (X). But <lb/> Pic <lb/> d  (X) is isomorphic to C <lb/> g  , and <lb/>hence any holomorphic map to it from β <lb/> −1  (y) is a constant map. <lb/>Conversely, take any point L ∈ ϕ • f (Q). We will show that the restriction of the <lb/>map β to the fiber (ϕ • f ) <lb/> −1  (L) is a constant map. For this we first show that there is <lb/>no nonconstant holomorphic map from CP <lb/> 1  to Y . To prove this note that CP <lb/> 1  is simply <lb/>connected and the universal over of Y is C <lb/> N  . Therefore, any holomorphic map from CP <lb/> 1 <lb/> to Y lifts to a holomorphic map from CP <lb/> 1  to C <lb/> N  , but there are no such nonconstant <lb/>holomorphic maps. <lb/>Since there is no nonconstant holomorphic map from CP <lb/> 1  to Y , from Lemma 2.1 it <lb/>follows that the map <lb/> β|  (ϕ•f )  −1  (L)  : (ϕ • f ) <lb/> −1  (L) −→ Y <lb/> factors through (ϕ • f ) <lb/> −1  (L) <lb/> f <lb/> −→ ϕ <lb/> −1  (L). As noted in the proof of Corollary 2.2, the <lb/>fiber ϕ <lb/> −1  (L) is a projective space. Hence the restriction of β to the fiber (ϕ • f ) <lb/> −1  (L) is <lb/>a constant map. This completes the proof of the proposition. <lb/> Continuing with the proof of the theorem, since g ≥ 2, we know that Q(r, d) does not <lb/>admit any Kähler metric with nonnegative holomorphic bisectional curvature if d &lt; g [BS, <lb/>Corollary 4.1]. Therefore, we assume that d ≥ g. Consequently, the map ϕ is surjective. <lb/>Since f is surjective, this implies that ϕ • f is surjective. Now from Proposition 3.2 we <lb/>know that Y is an abelian variety. <lb/>Choose a point of Y to make it a group. The universal covering map C <lb/> N  −→ Y is <lb/>chosen to be a homomorphism of groups. For any point v in the universal cover C <lb/> N  of Y , <lb/>let <lb/> τ  v  : Y −→ Y <lb/> be the automorphism given by the automorphism w −→ w + v of C <lb/> N  . We have a one-<lb/>parameter family of automorphisms Y given by τ  tv  , t ∈ [0 , 1], that connects τ  v  with the <lb/>identity map of Y . <lb/>Consider the flat holomorphic connection ∇ in (3.3). Given a point y ∈ Y , we may take <lb/>parallel translation of the fiber of β over y along the path τ  tv  (y), t ∈ [0 , 1]. Taking parallel <lb/>translations for ∇ along such paths τ  tv  , t ∈ [0 , 1], we get holomorphic automorphisms of <lb/> Q. If v is sufficiently close to zero, then the automorphism τ  v  of Y clearly does not have <lb/>any fixed-point. Hence for v sufficiently close to zero, we get holomorphic automorphisms <lb/>of Q that do not have any fixed point. <lb/></body>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> I. BISWAS AND H. SESHADRI <lb/></note>

			<body> Let Aut(Q) denote the group of holomorphic automorphisms of Q. Let Aut <lb/> 0  (Q) ⊂ <lb/> Aut(Q) be the connected component of it containing the identity element. <lb/>The standard action of GL(r, C) on C <lb/> r  produces an action of GL(r, C) on the trivial <lb/>vector bundle O <lb/> ⊕r <lb/> X  = X ×C <lb/> r  . The corresponding action of GL(r, C) on Q factors through <lb/>the quotient group PGL(r, C) = GL(r, C)/C <lb/>  *  . Since this action of PGL(r, C) on Q is <lb/>effective, we have <lb/>PGL(r, C) ⊂ Aut <lb/> 0  (Q) . <lb/> It is known that PGL(r, C) = Aut <lb/> 0  (Q) [BDH, Theorem 1.1]. Since the standard action <lb/>on CP <lb/> r−1  of any element A ∈ PGL(r, C) has a fixed point, the action of A on Q has a <lb/>fixed point. <lb/>This contradicts our earlier construction of automorphisms of Q without fixed points. <lb/>In view of this contradiction, we conclude that Q does not admit any Kähler structure <lb/>such that all the holomorphic bisectional curvatures are nonnegative. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [Ba] <lb/> J. M. Baptista, On the L <lb/> 2  –metric of vortex moduli spaces, Nuclear Phys. B 844 (2011), 308–333. <lb/>[BGL] E. Bifet, F. Ghione, and M. Letizia, On the Abel-Jacobi map for divisors of higher rank on a <lb/>curve, Math. Ann. 299 (1994), 641–672. <lb/>[BDH] I. Biswas, A. Dhillon and J. Hurtubise, Automorphisms of the Quot schemes associated to com-<lb/>pact Riemann surfaces, Int. Math. Res. Not., doi: 10.1093/imrn/rnt259. <lb/>[BiR] I. Biswas and N. M. Romão, Moduli of vortices and Grassmann manifolds, Comm. Math. Phys. <lb/> 320 (2013), 1–20. <lb/>[BS] <lb/>I. Biswas and H. Seshadri, On the Kähler structures over Quot schemes, Ill. Jour. Math. 57 <lb/> (2013), 1019–1024. <lb/>[BoR] M. Bökstedt and N. M. Romão, On the curvature of vortex moduli spaces, Math. Zeit. 277 <lb/> (2014), 549–573. <lb/>[Mo] <lb/>N. Mok, The uniformization theorem for compact Kähler manifolds of nonnegative holomorphic <lb/>bisectional curvature, Jour. Diff. Geom. 27 (1988), 179–214. <lb/></listBibl>

			<front> School of Mathematics, Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Homi Bhabha Road, <lb/>Bombay 400005, India <lb/> E-mail address: indranil@math.tifr.res.in <lb/> Indian Institute of Science, Department of Mathematics, Bangalore 560003, India <lb/> E-mail address: harish@math.iisc.ernet.in </front>


	</text>
</tei>
