<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> 33RD INTERNATIONAL COSMIC RAY CONFERENCE, RIO DE JANEIRO 2013 <lb/> THE ASTROPARTICLE PHYSICS CONFERENCE <lb/> The Multiple Muon Charge Ratio in MINOS <lb/> C. M. CASTROMONTE 1 , R. A. GOMES 1 , FOR THE MINOS COLLABORATION. <lb/> 1  Instituto de Física, Universidade Federal de Goiás, CP 131, 74001-970, Goiânia, GO, Brazil <lb/> cesarc@if.ufg.br <lb/> Abstract: The MINOS Far Detector is a magnetized planar steel-scintillator detector situated underground at <lb/>depth of 2070 mwe. A small fraction of the cosmic ray muons observed in the MINOS FD contain multiple muons. <lb/>These events on average are expected to have originated from either higher mass primaries, or higher energy <lb/>protons than their single muon counterparts. Using the complete MINOS atmospheric data set we will present the <lb/>first measurement of the multiple muon events charge ratio R  µ  = N  µ  +  /N  µ  −  . Systematic uncertainties on the charge <lb/>ratio were minimized by utilizing data collected with both forward and reversed magnetic field running. <lb/> Keywords: MINOS, cosmic rays, multiple muons. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> Atmospheric muons are produced when primary cosmic ray <lb/>nuclei interact near the top of the atmosphere to produce <lb/>hadronic showers which contain pions and kaons. These <lb/>secondary mesons can either interact in further collisions <lb/>in the atmosphere or decay to produce atmospheric muons. <lb/>Since the majority of primary cosmic rays are protons, there <lb/>is an excess of positively charged mesons in the showers, <lb/>and consequently, the atmospheric muon charge ratio R  µ  = <lb/>N  µ  +  /N  µ  −  , defined as the number of positive over negative <lb/>muons, is larger than unity. It&apos;s expected that heavier ele-<lb/>ments become a more important component of cosmic ray <lb/>primaries as the energy increases. This increasingly heavy <lb/>composition would decrease the ratio of primary protons to <lb/>neutrons, which in turn, would decrease the muon charge <lb/>ratio. With careful measurements of the muon charge ratio <lb/>in the cosmic rays, models of the interactions of cosmic <lb/>rays in the atmosphere can be improved. <lb/>A multiple muon event is one in which two or more <lb/>nearly parallel, time-coincident muon tracks are observed in <lb/>the detector. At high energies, massive primaries generate <lb/>more high-energy muons per event than proton primaries <lb/>of the same total energy. This is because the initial parent <lb/>meson (predominantly pion) particle multiplicities are larger <lb/>from the more massive primary, and the atmosphere is <lb/>more favorable to pion decay versus interaction early in <lb/>the cascade development. In addition, the point of first <lb/>interaction of the heavy primary is likely to be higher in the <lb/>atmosphere than for the proton primary due to the larger <lb/>cross section of the heavy nucleus-air interactions. <lb/>Previous single muon charge ratio measurements per-<lb/>formed by MINOS (Near Detector) [1], L3 + C [2], Bess-<lb/>TEV [3], CosmoALEPH [4] and CMS [5] at energies at <lb/>the surface level E  µ  ranging from a few hundred Mev to <lb/>500 GeV are consistent with the 2001 world average of <lb/>1.268 ± [0.008 ± 0.0002 <lb/> E  µ <lb/> GeV  ] [6]. MINOS (Far Detector) <lb/>[7] and OPERA [8] also reported, at TeV surface energies, <lb/>a higher value for the muon charge ratio (≈ 1.37). For the <lb/>multiple muon charge ratio, OPERA reported the values of <lb/>1.23 ± 0.06 [8] (2010) and 1.18 ± 0.03 [9] (2013). <lb/>In this paper we present a measurement of the atmosphe-<lb/>ric muon charge ratio using a sample of multiple muons <lb/>recorded by the MINOS Far Detector. <lb/> 2 The MINOS Far Detector <lb/> The MINOS Far Detector is a magnetized planar steel-<lb/>scintillator detector located at a depth of 2070 mwe in <lb/>the Soudan Underground Laboratory in an iron mine in <lb/>northern Minnesota (latitude 47.820 27  •  N and longitude <lb/>92.241 41  •  W). The detector contains 486 octagonal steel <lb/>planes, each 2.54 cm thick, interleaved with 484 planes <lb/>of 1 cm thick extruded polystyrene scintillator strips at <lb/>a 5.94 cm pitch. Each scintillator plane has 192 strips <lb/>of width 4.1 cm. The length of each strip depends on its <lb/>position in the plane and varies between 3.4 and 8.0 m. <lb/>The scintillator strips in alternating detector planes are <lb/>oriented at ±45 •  to the vertical. The modular detector <lb/>consists of two supermodules (SM) separated by a gap of <lb/>1.1 m. Scintillation light is collected by wavelength shifting <lb/>(WLS) plastic fibers embedded within the scintillator strips. <lb/>The WLS fibers are coupled to clear optical fibers at both <lb/>ends of a strip and are read out using 16-pixel multianode <lb/>phototmultiplier tubes (PMTs). The signals from eight <lb/>strips, each one of which is separated by approximately 1 m <lb/>within the same plane, are optically summed and read out <lb/>by a single PMT pixel. The fibers summed on each pixel <lb/>are different for the two sides of the detector, which enables <lb/>the resulting eightfold ambiguity to be resolved for single <lb/>particle events. For all other types of events, ambiguities <lb/>are effectively resolved using additional information from <lb/>timing and event topology. <lb/>In order to measure the momentum of muons traversing <lb/>the detector, the steel has been magnetized into a toroidal <lb/>field configuration. The field varies in strength from 1.8 <lb/>T near the magnetic coil to almost 1 T near the edges. A <lb/>muon is &quot; focused &quot; when the magnetic field steers it toward <lb/>the center of the detector and &quot; defocused &quot; when directed <lb/>away from the center. The MINOS magnetic field was <lb/>designed to focus negatively charged particles coming from <lb/>the south (i.e., µ  −  resulting from ν µ  interactions in the <lb/>detector from neutrinos originating in the Fermilab NuMI <lb/>beam) toward the center of the detector. This magnetic <lb/>field orientation will be referred as data forward ( &quot; DF &quot; ) <lb/>configuration. MINOS has a second field orientation, data <lb/>reverse ( &quot; DR &quot; ) configuration, in which the coil current <lb/>is reversed and µ  +  from the south are focused into the <lb/>detector. <lb/>Information regarding the data acquisition and trigger <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> MINOS Multiple Muon Charge Ratio <lb/>33RD INTERNATIONAL COSMIC RAY CONFERENCE, RIO DE JANEIRO 2013 <lb/></note>

			<body> systems can be found in [10]. The detector calibration has <lb/>been described in [11]. More detailed detector information <lb/>can be found in [12]. <lb/> 3 Data Analysis <lb/> The multiple muon sample reported in this paper was <lb/>recorded between August 2003 and April 2012. During the <lb/>data taking period, the detector run with both the DF and <lb/>DR magnetic field configurations. <lb/> 3.1 Event selection <lb/> A selection criteria (or cuts) have been chosen to ensure the <lb/>highest quality of data. The first stage of the event selection <lb/>is to identify and remove periods of data associated with <lb/>detector hardware problems. The criteria which define bad <lb/>runs are described in [13]. Most of the cuts used to select <lb/>the sample for this analysis are similar to those used in <lb/>previous Far Detector muon analysis [7, 14]. For a multiple <lb/>muon event it was required that tracks in the event to be <lb/>downward-going and to satisfy a &quot; parallel &quot; cut, i.e., for <lb/>each muon track there is an angular separation of less than <lb/>5  •  from at least one other muon in the group. If at least a <lb/>pair of tracks in the event satisfies this cut, all the muons <lb/>in that event are considered in the calculation of the charge <lb/>ratio. This cut is meant to ensure that at least two tracks <lb/>are correlated. A summary of the cuts applied and their <lb/>selection efficiencies are shown in Table 1. <lb/> 3.1.1 Charge-sign quality cuts <lb/> Two selection variables are used to further increase the <lb/>degree of confidence in the assigned curvature and charge <lb/>sign of the tracks. The Kalman filter [15] technique used <lb/>in the track curvature fitting involves a series of recursive <lb/>matrix manipulations to specify the trajectory of the parti-<lb/>cle as well as the ratio of its charge to its momentum (q/p). <lb/>It also provides an uncertainty σ (q/p) on the measured <lb/>value of q/p. The first charge sign quality cut is based on <lb/>the charge-sign significance, (q/p)/σ (q/p), determined by <lb/>the track fitter. The second cut variable BdL is defined as <lb/> BdL ≡ <lb/>  end <lb/>beg <lb/> B  perp  (r)dL <lb/> (1) <lb/>where B  perp  (r) = |  B(r) × n| is the component of the mag-<lb/>netic field perpendicular to the track direction  n at a given <lb/>point along the track path, r is the distance from the de-<lb/>tector center axis, dL is the differential pathlength element <lb/>along the track, beg is the point at which the muon enters <lb/>the detector, and end is the point at which it either exits the <lb/>detector or stops in the detector. The BdL cut ensures that <lb/>the magnitude of the bending due to curvature is larger than <lb/>apparent bending due to multiple scattering. <lb/>Figures 1 and 2 show the multiple muon charge ratio as a <lb/>function of (q/p)/σ (q/p) and of BdL respectively, for data <lb/>collected in both magnetic field orientations. The charge <lb/>ratio for data collected in a single magnetic field orientation <lb/>is defined as the ratio of positive to negative muons collec-<lb/>ted only in that orientation. The figures also show syste-<lb/>matic differences in the charge ratio measurements between <lb/>forward and and reverse magnetic field running. These diffe-<lb/>rences come from acceptance effects due to the magnetic <lb/>field, detector asymmetry, and detector alignment errors. To <lb/>remove these biases, data taken in the two field orientations <lb/>were combined by calculating a geometric mean (GM) <lb/>between both data sets. This procedure will be discussed in <lb/>the next section. <lb/>For the charge-sign significance, it was required <lb/> (q/p)/σ (q/p) &gt; 3. Above this value the charge ratio tends <lb/>to be asymptotically flat, suggesting that the charge sign <lb/>and momentum are well-fit. As (q/p)/σ (q/p) tends to <lb/>zero, the charge sign determined by the fitter becomes less <lb/>reliable. Low values of the (q/p)/σ (q/p) indicates that the <lb/>fitter picks the two charge signs with equal probability and <lb/>the measured charge-sign ratio tends to unity. Events with <lb/>low values of the charge-sign significance are typically high <lb/>momentum tracks (&gt; 100 GeV/c) that traverse the detector <lb/>in such a way as to bend only slightly in the magnetic field. <lb/>It was also required BdL &gt; 5 T m. For low values of <lb/> BdL, the measured charge ratio approaches to one, as <lb/>expected in the case of random charge determination. As the <lb/>integrated magnetic field increases, the charge ratio increa-<lb/>ses to a plateau value where the charge misidentification <lb/>is suppressed. The BdL cut was chosen as the value where <lb/>the plateau is reached. Above this value the charge ratio as <lb/>function of BdL is consistent with being constant. <lb/>Superposed onto both, the (q/p)/σ (q/p) and BdL data <lb/>plots, there is a fit of the combined distributions to a constant <lb/>charge ratio. In both cases it was obtained a muon charge <lb/>ratio of 1.08 ± 0.01. <lb/> (q/p) <lb/> σ <lb/> (q/p)/ <lb/> 0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/> -<lb/> µ <lb/> / N <lb/> + <lb/> µ <lb/> N <lb/> 0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>(q/p) &gt; 3 <lb/> σ <lb/> (q/p)/ <lb/> MINOS PRELIMINARY <lb/> (Statistical errors only) <lb/> Forward Field <lb/>Reverse Field <lb/>Geometric Mean <lb/>0.004 <lb/> ± <lb/> r = 1.082 <lb/> Fig. 1: Charge ratio for reconstructed multiple muon tracks <lb/>as a function of (q/p)/σ (q/p) after all selection cuts <lb/>and requiring that BdL &gt; 5 T m. The vertical line is the <lb/>threshold value used in the charge-sign quality selection. <lb/>Data points show only statistical errors. Superposed is the fit <lb/>of the combined distribution (geometric mean) to a constant <lb/>charge ratio N  µ  +  /N  µ  −  . <lb/>Events which have passed all the cuts summarized in <lb/>Table 1 are used in the calculation of the multiple muon <lb/>charge ratio described in the next section. <lb/> 3.1.2 Measurement of the Multiple Muon charge <lb/>ratio underground <lb/> In this section we determine the muon charge ratio, R  µ  = <lb/>N  µ  +  /N  µ  −  , as a function of the muon multiplicity. <lb/>As shown in the previous section, magnetic field effects <lb/>in the Far Detector introduce a bias in the charge ratio when <lb/>it is calculated using only data from a single magnetic field <lb/>orientation. A method to cancel geometrical acceptance <lb/>effects and alignment errors is discussed in [7, 16]. Two <lb/>independent equations for the charge ratio, r a  and r b  , can <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> MINOS Multiple Muon Charge Ratio <lb/>33RD INTERNATIONAL COSMIC RAY CONFERENCE, RIO DE JANEIRO 2013 <lb/></note>

			<body> m] <lb/> ⋅ <lb/> BdL [T <lb/> 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/> -<lb/> µ <lb/> / N <lb/> + <lb/> µ <lb/> N <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>BdL &gt; 5 <lb/> MINOS PRELIMINARY <lb/> (Statistical errors only) <lb/> Forward Field <lb/>Reverse Field <lb/>Geometric Mean <lb/>0.004 <lb/> ± <lb/> r = 1.081 <lb/> Fig. 2: Charge ratio for reconstructed multiple muon tracks <lb/>as a function of BdL after all selection cuts and requiring <lb/>that (q/p)/σ (q/p) &gt; 3. The vertical line is the threshold <lb/>value used in the charge-sign quality selection. Data points <lb/>show only statistical errors. Superposed is the fit of the com-<lb/>bined distribution (geometric mean) to a constant charge <lb/>ratio N  µ  +  /N  µ  −  . <lb/>be constructed in which the magnetic field effects cancel. <lb/>These live time corrected ratios are <lb/> r a  = (N <lb/> µ  + <lb/> DF  /τ  DF  )/(N <lb/> µ  − <lb/> DR  /τ  DR  ) <lb/> (2) <lb/>and <lb/> r b  = (N <lb/> µ  + <lb/> DR  /τ  DR  )/(N <lb/> µ  − <lb/> DF  /τ  DF  ) <lb/> (3) <lb/>The geometric mean (GM) of r a  and r b  provides a mea-<lb/>surement of the charge ratio, R  µ  , in which magnetic field <lb/>effects, alignment errors and live time biases cancel <lb/>R  µ  = [r  a  × r b  ] <lb/> 1/2  = <lb/> N <lb/> µ  + <lb/> DF <lb/> N <lb/> µ  − <lb/> DF <lb/> × <lb/> N <lb/> µ  + <lb/> DR <lb/> N <lb/> µ  − <lb/> DR <lb/>  1/2 <lb/> (4) <lb/>Figures 1 and 2 illustrate very well that the apparent signifi-<lb/>cant bias in the charge ratio in a single field orientation data <lb/>set is strongly suppressed in the geometric mean. <lb/>After all the cuts shown in Table 1 have been applied we <lb/>obtain a final sample of 393144 muons. Figure 3 and Table <lb/>2 show the calculated muon charge ratio as a function of <lb/>the muon multiplicity. The errors shown in both are only <lb/>statistical. <lb/>By fitting the combined data set (GM) in Figure 3 to <lb/>a constant charge ratio we obtain a value of N  µ  +  /N  µ  − <lb/> = 1.080 ± 0.004(stat), for muon multiplicities between 2 <lb/>and 7. <lb/> 4 Summary <lb/> A preliminary measured of the atmospheric muon charge <lb/>ratio R  µ  = N  µ  +  /N  µ  −  as a function of the muon multiplicity <lb/>was performed using the full MINOS Far Detector atmos-<lb/>pheric data set. <lb/>For muon multiplicities between 2 and 7, we obtain a <lb/>charge ratio value <lb/>N  µ  +  /N  µ  −  = 1.080 ± 0.004(stat) <lb/>Cuts <lb/>Data selection efficiency <lb/># muons before cuts <lb/>8.35 × 10 6 (100%) <lb/>Preselection <lb/>magnet coil status <lb/>8.06 × 10 6 (96.5%) <lb/>one well reconst. track <lb/>7.66 × 10 6 (91.7%) <lb/>Physics cuts <lb/>parallel tracks (&lt; 5  •  ) <lb/>7.31 × 10 6 (87.5%) <lb/>at least 20 planes <lb/>5.88 × 10 6 (70.5%) <lb/> &gt; 2 m track length <lb/>5.87 × 10 6 (70.3%) <lb/>downward-going track <lb/>5.86 × 10 6 (70.2%) <lb/>XY track vtx. pos. &gt; 0.5 m <lb/>5.85 × 10 6 (70.0%) <lb/>Charge-sign quality <lb/> (q/p)/σ (q/p) &gt; 3 <lb/>1.10 × 10 6 (16.7%) <lb/> BdL &gt; 5 <lb/>3.93 × 10 5 (4.7%) <lb/> Table 1: Summary of the cuts applied. Each row shows the <lb/>total number of muons remaining after all the applied cuts; <lb/>in parenthesis, the percentage of muons remaining. <lb/>Mult. <lb/>DF <lb/>DR <lb/>GM <lb/>2 <lb/>1.182 ± 0.005 1.021 ± 0.009 1.098 ± 0.005 <lb/> 3 <lb/>1.120 ± 0.010 0.963 ± 0.017 1.039 ± 0.010 <lb/> 4 <lb/>1.119 ± 0.016 0.978 ± 0.028 1.046 ± 0.017 <lb/> 5 <lb/>1.146 ± 0.026 0.876 ± 0.041 1.002 ± 0.026 <lb/> 6 <lb/>1.115 ± 0.040 0.962 ± 0.071 1.036 ± 0.042 <lb/> 7 <lb/>1.127 ± 0.067 0.898 ± 0.101 1.006 ± 0.064 <lb/>Table 2: Summary of the measured muon charge ratio as <lb/>a function of muon multiplicity for DF, DR and combined <lb/>(GM) data sets. The errors shown in the charge ratios are <lb/>only statistical. <lb/>No efficiency corrections or systematic errors have been <lb/>included in the results as this analysis is currently underway. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgment: This work was supported by the U.S. DOE, <lb/>the United Kingdom STFC, the U.S. NSF, the State and University <lb/>of Minnesota, the University of Athens, Greece, and Brazils <lb/>CAPES and REUNI-UFG. We gratefully acknowledge the Mi-<lb/>nnesota Department of Natural Resources and the crew of Soudan <lb/>Underground Laboratory. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] P. Adamson et al. (MINOS Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D 83, <lb/>032011 (2011). <lb/>[2] P. Achard et al. (L3 Collaboration), Phys. Lett. B 598, 15 <lb/>(2004). <lb/>[3] S. Haino et al., Phys. Lett. B 594, 35 (2004). <lb/>[4] D. Zimmermann et al., Nucl. Instrum. Meth. A 525, 141 <lb/>(2004). <lb/>[5] V. Khachatryan et al. (CMS Collaboration), Phys. Lett. B 692, <lb/>83 (2010). <lb/>[6] T. Hebbeker and C. Timmermans, Astropart. Phys. 18, 107 <lb/>(2002). <lb/>[7] P. Adamson et al. (MINOS Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D 76, <lb/>052003 (2007). <lb/>[8] N. Agafonova et al. (OPERA Collaboration), Eur. Phys. J. C <lb/>67, 25 (2010). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> MINOS Multiple Muon Charge Ratio <lb/>33RD INTERNATIONAL COSMIC RAY CONFERENCE, RIO DE JANEIRO 2013 <lb/></note>

			<body> Muon Multiplicity <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/> -<lb/> µ <lb/> / N <lb/> + <lb/> µ <lb/> N <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/> MINOS PRELIMINARY <lb/> (Statistical errors only) <lb/> Forward Field <lb/>Reverse Field <lb/>Geometric Mean <lb/>0.004 <lb/> ± <lb/> r = 1.080 <lb/> Fig. 3: The measured muon charge ratio as a function of <lb/>the muon multiplicity for the DF data set, DR data set <lb/>and combined data set (GM). The GM distribution shows <lb/>the charge ratio in which magnetic field effects, alignment <lb/>errors and live time biases cancel. Data points show only <lb/>statistical errors. Superposed is the fit of the GM distribution <lb/>to a constant charge ratio N  µ  +  /N  µ  −  , for muon multiplicities <lb/>between 2 and 7. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> [9] N. Mauri et al. (OPERA Collaboration), LHC-CR Workshop: <lb/>Results and prospects of forward physics at the LHC, (2013). <lb/>[10] P. Adamson et al. (MINOS Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D 73, <lb/>072002 (2006). <lb/>[11] P. Adamson et al. (MINOS Collaboration), MINOS <lb/>Technical Design Report, Fermilab Note MINOS-337, 1998. <lb/>[12] D.G. Michael et al. (MINOS Collaboration), Nucl. Instrum. <lb/>Meth. A 596, 190-228 (2008). <lb/>[13] A. Blake, Ph.D. thesis, Cambridge University, 2005. <lb/>[14] P. Adamson et al. (MINOS Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D 81, <lb/>012001 (2010). <lb/>[15] R. Fruhwirth, Nucl. Instrum. Meth. A 262, 444 (1987). <lb/>[16] S. Matsuno et al., Phys. Rev. D 29, 1 (1984). </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
