<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> BLED WORKSHOPS <lb/> IN PHYSICS <lb/>VOL. 8, NO. 1 <lb/> p. 17 <lb/>Proceedings of the Mini-Workshop <lb/> Hadron Structure and Lattice QCD <lb/> Bled, Slovenia, July 9-16, 2007 <lb/> Does nucleon parity doubling imply U  A  (1) symmetry <lb/>restoration? <lb/> ⋆ <lb/> V. Dmitrašinovi´ <lb/> a  , K. Nagata <lb/> b  , A. Hosaka <lb/> c <lb/> a  Vinča Institute of Nuclear Sciences, lab 010, P.O.Box 522, 11001 Beograd, Serbia <lb/> b  Department of Physics, Chung-Yuan Christian University, Chung-Li 320, Taiwan <lb/> c  Research Center for Nuclear Physics, Osaka University, Mihogaoka 10-1, <lb/>Osaka 567-0047, Japan <lb/> Abstract. We examine the role of U  A  (1) symmetry and its breaking/restoration in two <lb/>complete chiral multiplets consisting of the nucleon and the Roper and their two &quot; chiral <lb/>mirror &quot; odd-parity resonances. We base our work on the recent classification of the chiral <lb/> SU  L  (2) × SU  R  (2) transformation properties of the two (Ioffe) independent local tri-quark <lb/>nucleon interpolating fields in QCD [1]. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> Over the past five years there has been considerable activity on the question if <lb/>the chiral U  A  (1) symmetry restoration is in any way related to the (purported) <lb/>parity doubling in the nucleon spectrum [2,3]. In the previous additions to the <lb/>literature [2], following an old and to a large extent formal example by Ben Lee <lb/>[4], it was assumed that the nucleons admitted only certain specific linear non-<lb/>Abelian chiral transformation properties -no assumptions were made about the <lb/>Abelian ones, however. <lb/>Rather than guess at the chiral properties of the nucleon, we use the results of <lb/>our study [1] of the SU  L  (2)×SU  R  (2) and U  A  (1) (the non-Abelian and the Abelian <lb/>chiral symmetries, respectively) transformations of the over-complete set of (five) <lb/>three-quark non-derivative (local) nucleon interpolating fields. We showed that <lb/>the two independent nucleon fields form two different irreducible U  A  (1) repre-<lb/>sentations: one with the axial baryon number minus one (the Abelian &quot; mirror &quot; <lb/>field), and another with three (the Abelian triply &quot; naive &quot; nucleon in the parlance <lb/>of Ref. [5]). <lb/>For odd-parity nucleons, on the other hand, the inclusion of at least one <lb/>space-time derivative is natural. Once we allow for a derivative to exist in the <lb/>interpolating field, we find two nucleon fields with chiral properties opposite to <lb/>the non-derivative ones, e.g. the non-Abelian chiral properties of the derivative <lb/>fields are &quot; mirror &quot; compared to the &quot; naive &quot; non-derivative ones. Thus, altogether <lb/>we have four independent nucleon fields constructed from three quarks with or <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> ⋆  Talk delivered by V. Dmitrašinovi´ <lb/></note>

			<page> 18 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> V. Dmitrašinovi´ <lb/></note>

			<body> without one derivative. They can be classified as being non-Abelian &quot; naive &quot; or <lb/> &quot; mirror &quot; and similarly for the Abelian chiral transformation properties. <lb/>As an illustrative example, we identify these four specific nucleon fields with <lb/>the four lowest-lying nucleon resonances: the nucleon-Roper even-parity pair <lb/>and the N <lb/>  *  (1535), N <lb/>  *  (1650) pair of odd-parity resonances, and construct an ef-<lb/>fective Lagrangian with the U  A  (1) and SU  L  (2) × SU  R  (2) symmetries. We show <lb/>that, after spontaneous symmetry breakdown to SU(2)  V  , the mass splitting in-<lb/>duced by this effective interaction can reproduce all four nucleon&apos;s masses even <lb/> without explicit U  A  (1) symmetry breaking. This is an explicit counter-example to <lb/>the statement in the literature that the parity doubling in the nucleon spectrum is <lb/>related to the restoration of the U  A  (1) symmetry. <lb/>Our method applies equally well to any, and not just the low-lying, U  A  (1) <lb/> chiral quartet, i.e., pair of nucleon parity doublets. Of course, this result is subject <lb/>to the assumption of three-quark nature of the corresponding nucleon states. <lb/> 2 Three-quark nucleon interpolating fields <lb/> We start by summarizing the transformation properties of various quark trilin-<lb/>ear forms with quantum numbers of the nucleon as shown in Ref. [1]. It turns <lb/>out that every nucleon, i.e., spin-and isospin 1/2 field, besides having same non-<lb/>Abelian transformation properties, comes in two varieties: one with &quot; mirror &quot; and <lb/>another with &quot; triple-naive &quot; Abelian chiral properties. This allows us to address <lb/>the old (Ioffe) problem of duplication/ambiguity of nucleon fields: For J <lb/> P  = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> + <lb/> nucleons there is only one non-Abelian representation allowed, the ( <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  , 0) ⊕ (0, <lb/> 1 <lb/>2  ), <lb/> but with the two afore-mentioned Abelian chiral properties, thus lending phys-<lb/>ical distinction to Ioffe&apos;s two nucleon fields: the nucleon ground state, the two <lb/>odd-parity resonances and the Roper are the four mutually orthogonal admix-<lb/>tures of the Abelian &quot; mirror &quot; -(so called Ioffe current), the Abelian &quot; triple naive &quot; -<lb/>and their non-Abelian mirror fields. <lb/> Table 1. The Abelian axial charges (+ sign indicates &quot; naive &quot; , -sign &quot; mirror &quot; transformation <lb/>properties) and the non-Abelian chiral multiplets of J <lb/> P  = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> +  nucleon interpolating fields <lb/>in the Lorentz group representation D( <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> , 0) without derivatives. In the last column we <lb/>show the Fierz identical fields, see [1]. <lb/> U  A  (1) SU  A  (2) SU  V  (2) × SU  A  (2) Fierz identical <lb/> N  1  − N  2  −1 <lb/> +1 <lb/>( <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> , 0) ⊕ (0, <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ) <lb/> N  3  , N  4 <lb/> N  1  + N  2  +3 <lb/>+1 <lb/>( <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> , 0) ⊕ (0, <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ) <lb/> N  5 <lb/> We can construct nucleon fields with &quot; opposite &quot; chiral transformations to <lb/>those shown above by replacing γ  µ  with i∂  µ  : for example we may use the follow-<lb/>ing two nucleon interpolating fields involving three quarks and one derivative <lb/> N <lb/> ′  − <lb/> 1  = ϵ  abc  i∂  µ  ( ˜ <lb/> q  a  q  b  )γ <lb/> µ  γ <lb/> 5  q  c  , <lb/> (1) <lb/> N <lb/> ′  − <lb/> 2  = ϵ  abc  i∂  µ  ( ˜ <lb/> q  a  γ <lb/> 5  q  b  )γ <lb/> µ  q  c  . <lb/> (2) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Does nucleon parity doubling imply U  A  (1) symmetry restoration? <lb/></note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body> They are odd-parity, spin 1/2 and isospin 1/2 fields, i.e. they describe (some) <lb/>nucleon resonances. A prime in the superscript implies that the fields contain a <lb/>derivative, and we show below that therefore they have opposite, i.e., &quot; mirror &quot; <lb/>non-Abelian chiral transformation properties to those of the corresponding non-<lb/>derivative fields. <lb/>Taking the symmetric and antisymmetric linear combinations of two nucleon <lb/>fields N <lb/> ′  − <lb/> 1,2  as the new canonical fields <lb/> N <lb/> ′  − <lb/> m  = <lb/> 1 <lb/> √ <lb/> 2 <lb/> (N <lb/> ′  − <lb/> 1  + N <lb/> ′  − <lb/> 2  ) <lb/> (3) <lb/> N <lb/> ′  − <lb/> n  = <lb/> 1 <lb/> √ <lb/> 2 <lb/> (N <lb/> ′  − <lb/> 1  − N <lb/> ′  − <lb/> 2  ), <lb/> (4) <lb/>their Abelian chiral transformation properties read <lb/> δ  5  N <lb/> ′  − <lb/> m  = −3iaγ  5  N <lb/> ′  − <lb/> m <lb/> (5) <lb/> δ  5  N <lb/> ′  − <lb/> n  = iaγ  5  N <lb/> ′  − <lb/> n  , <lb/> (6) <lb/>whereas the non-Abelian ones remain &quot; mirror &quot; <lb/> δ  5  N <lb/> ′  − <lb/> m,n  = −iγ  5  τ · aN <lb/> ′  − <lb/> m,n  . <lb/> (7) <lb/>In summary, we have explicitly constructed four independent nucleon fields: two <lb/>fields with &quot; naive &quot; and two fields with &quot; mirror &quot; Abelian and non-Abelian chiral <lb/>transformation properties. In the present paper, we identify these fields with the <lb/>nucleon ground state N(940) and its resonances N(1440), N(1535) and N(1650). <lb/> We summarize the properties of the four fields in Table.2. With these fields we <lb/>can construct the &quot; naive-mirror &quot; interactions. <lb/> Table 2. The axial charges of the nucleon fields. <lb/>Interpolating fields U  A  (1) SU  A  (2) Assigned states <lb/> Nm <lb/> −1 <lb/> +1 <lb/> N (940) <lb/> Nn <lb/> +3 <lb/>+1 <lb/> N (1440) <lb/> N <lb/> ′ <lb/> n <lb/> +1 <lb/> −1 <lb/> N (1650) <lb/> N <lb/> ′ <lb/> m <lb/> −3 <lb/>−1 <lb/> N (1535) <lb/> 3 The U  A  (1) symmetry in baryons <lb/> The U  A  (1) symmetry&apos;s explicit breaking due to the triangle anomaly and topo-<lb/>logically non-trivial configurations in QCD has only a few firmly established <lb/>observable consequences, all of which are in the flavor-singlet spin-less meson <lb/>sector, see Ref. [11] and references therein, with lots of recent speculation about <lb/>its role in the baryon sector ( &quot; parity doubling &quot; ), especially with regard to its al-<lb/>leged/purported &quot; restoration high up in the hadron spectrum &quot; Ref. [2]. This sce-<lb/>nario has effectively been disproven in the meson case in Refs. [2]. <lb/></body>

			<page> 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> V. Dmitrašinovi´ <lb/></note>

			<body> The baryon case is much more difficult to handle, due to, inter alia, a funda-<lb/>mental lack of knowledge of the baryon chiral transformation properties. In the <lb/>baryon sector, the empirically observed parity doubling has been quantitatively <lb/>analyzed by Jaffe et. al. [3], who proposed that the physics behind that might be <lb/>the (explicitly broken) U  A  (1) symmetry. In the absence of direct lattice measure-<lb/>ments the best one can do is resort to chiral models. <lb/>Lee, DeTar, Kunihiro, Jido, Oka and others [4,5] have developed a Lagran-<lb/>gian formalism based on one pair of &quot; naive &quot; and &quot; mirror &quot; opposite-parity nu-<lb/>cleon fields. They did not consider the U  A  (1) symmetry, however. Christos [8] has <lb/>shown that there are two independent cubic interactions for each parity doublet <lb/>that preserve both U  A  (1) and SU(2)  L  × SU(2)  R  symmetry. However Christos did <lb/>not include Abelian chiral mirror fields, so he obtained vanishing off-diagonal <lb/> πNN <lb/>  *  couplings. Our strategy was first to construct the SU  L  (2) × SU  R  (2) chi-<lb/>ral invariant interaction(s) for two pairs of nucleon (N <lb/> + <lb/> m,n  and N <lb/> ′  − <lb/> m,n  ) fields; and <lb/>then to include the U  A  (1) symmetry [12]. We have classified these terms accord-<lb/>ing to the power of the meson fields. We found that besides the linear (in meson <lb/>fields) interactions there are also quadratic and cubic ones. The form of these in-<lb/>teractions is uniquely dictated by the U  A  (1) symmetry; higher-order terms may <lb/>appear only as products of these three lower-order ones. That allows altogether <lb/>six interactions: four diagonal ones in the two doublets and two &quot; inter-doublet &quot; <lb/>ones. Furthermore, we included all quadratic terms allowed by the non-Abelian <lb/> &quot; mirror &quot; properties of the baryons. Then we found that one does not need any <lb/> U  A  (1) symmetry breaking to describe the nucleon mass spectrum, provided one <lb/>uses a complete set of interactions. <lb/> 4 Results <lb/> In the following discussion, it is convenient to group the four nucleon fields as fol-<lb/>lows; Ψ = (N <lb/> + <lb/> m  , N <lb/> ′  − <lb/> n  ) for the pair of the single Abelian charge (the single-Abelian <lb/>doublet), and Φ = (N <lb/> + <lb/> n  , N <lb/> ′  − <lb/> m  ) for that of the triple Abelian charge (the triple-<lb/>Abelian doublet). We emphasize that the two nucleons in each of these pairs are in <lb/> &quot; mirror &quot; relations to each other, with regard to both the Abelian and non-Abelian <lb/>chiral symmetries. Manifestly, the identification of fields, or their admixtures, <lb/>with actual resonances viz. N(940), R(1440), N <lb/>  *  (1535) and N <lb/>  *  (1650) is not unique. <lb/>In this brief review we consider only one choice; another scenario is considered <lb/>in Ref. [12]. A substantial body of QCD sum rule evidence is pointing towards <lb/> N(940) being the &quot; Ioffe current &quot;  N <lb/> + <lb/> 1m  . Together with the lowest negative parity <lb/>nucleon N(1535) in the partner of the parity doublet, we have Ψ = (N <lb/> + <lb/> m  , N <lb/> ′− <lb/> n  ) = <lb/>(N(940), N(1535)) and consequently Φ = (N <lb/> + <lb/> n  , N <lb/> ′− <lb/> m  ) = (N(1440), N(1650)). <lb/> The nucleon mass matrix is already in a simple block-diagonal form when <lb/>the nucleon fields form the following 1×4 row/column &quot; vector &quot; : <lb/> (Ψ, Φ) = (N <lb/> + <lb/> m  , N <lb/> ′  − <lb/> n  , N <lb/> + <lb/> n  , N <lb/> ′  − <lb/> m  ) → (N <lb/> + <lb/> m  , γ  5  N <lb/> ′  − <lb/> n  , N <lb/> + <lb/> n  , γ  5  N <lb/> ′  − <lb/> m  ) , <lb/> Does nucleon parity doubling imply U  A  (1) symmetry restoration? <lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body> lim <lb/> U A  (1)symm. <lb/> M = <lb/> ⎛ <lb/> ⎜ <lb/>⎜ <lb/>⎝ <lb/> g  1  f  π  m  12  γ  5 <lb/> 0 <lb/>g  5  f  π  γ  5 <lb/> m  12  γ  5  g  2  f  π  g  6  f  π  γ  5 <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>g  6  f  π  γ  5  g  3  f  π  m  34  γ  5 <lb/> g  5  f  π  γ  5 <lb/> 0 <lb/>m  34  γ  5  g  4  f  π <lb/> ⎞ <lb/>⎟ <lb/>⎟ <lb/>⎠ . <lb/> (8) <lb/>Note that only the parity-changing interaction g  5,6  mixes these two new equal <lb/>parity doublets. Without inter-doublet interactions (g  5,6  = 0) one can immedi-<lb/>ately read off the eigenvalues following Ref. [5]. We determine the coupling and <lb/>mass parameters and show them in Table 3 and Fig. 1. <lb/> Table 3. Coupling constants obtained from the nucleon masses with doublets <lb/>(N(940), N <lb/>  *  (1535)), (R(1440), N <lb/>  *  (1650)) and the decay widths N <lb/>  *  (1535) → πN(940) and <lb/> N <lb/>  *  (1650) → πR(1440). <lb/> constant g  1  g  2 <lb/> m  12 <lb/> g  3  g  4 <lb/> m  34 <lb/> value 10.4 16.8 270 MeV 14.6 16.8 503 MeV <lb/> 0 <lb/> 50 <lb/>100 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>N(1535) <lb/>N(940) <lb/>N(1440) <lb/>N(1650) <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/> B  [MeV] <lb/> π <lb/> 0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>Mass [GeV] <lb/> Mass [GeV] <lb/> B  [MeV] <lb/> π <lb/> Fig. 1. The nucleon masses as functions of ⟨σ⟩  0  . <lb/> Manifestly, the good U  A  (1) symmetry limit is sufficient to reproduce the nu-<lb/>cleon spectrum. Thence our main conclusion: the mass degeneracy of opposite-parity <lb/>nucleon resonances is not a consequence of the explicit U  A  (1) symmetry (non) breaking. <lb/> This conclusion was also reached by Christos [8], albeit for one parity doublet and <lb/>without mirror fields, which means that his N <lb/>  *  (1535) can not decay into N(940) <lb/> by π emission. <lb/> 5 Summary and Discussion <lb/> We have analyzed the U  A  (1) symmetry in the nucleon-Roper-two-odd-parity-<lb/>nucleon-resonances system, under the assumption that the above four nucleon <lb/></body>

			<page> 22 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> V. Dmitrašinovi´ <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex"> states are described by a particular set of independent interpolating fields. The <lb/>four nucleon fields naturally split into two &quot; parity doublets &quot; due to their U  A  (1) <lb/> symmetry transformation properties. <lb/>Our analysis has been based on the Born approximation: Higher-order (one-, <lb/>two-, etc. meson loop) corrections belong to the O(1/N  c  ) corrections, that have <lb/>been studied only intermittently in chiral quark models of the nucleon and then <lb/>only in certain simple models with one kind of nucleon. In principle, instanton <lb/>effects are expected to vanish in the large-N  c  limit, which justifies our assumption <lb/>of good U  A  (1) symmetry, ex post facto. The extracted value of the &quot; bare mirror &quot; <lb/>nucleon mass (m  12  =270 MeV, see also Ref. [6]) is something that can be checked <lb/>on the lattice, now that the interpolating fields have been specified for the mirror <lb/>nucleons. <lb/>The insight that the nucleon and the Roper fields may form two different <lb/>representations of the U  A  (1) symmetry, and that their mass difference can be <lb/>viewed as a consequence of U  A  (1) symmetry conservation and not of the sym-<lb/>metry breaking, are the main results of this work. A corollary of this result is that <lb/>the parity-doublet mass splittings are not entirely determined by the U  A  (1) sym-<lb/>metry breaking, as was conjectured in the literature [3]. Moreover, the nucleon-<lb/>Roper mass difference in some calculations, such as the one of Ref. [10] in the NJL <lb/>model, are not a consequence of the broken U  A  (1) symmetry in that model. <lb/> U  A  (1) symmetry in nucleon spectra has been discussed before, most notably <lb/>by Christos [8], who used only one parity doublet (N(940) and N <lb/>  *  (1535)), how-<lb/>ever. He argued that the parity doublet mass difference is proportional to a par-<lb/>ticular ηNN <lb/>  *  coupling constant, which is in close agreement with our results. He <lb/>did not try to relate other mass differences, such as the Roper-nucleon one, to this <lb/>mechanism, as he did not know of an alternative ( &quot; mirror &quot; ) set of fields, which <lb/>is a novel feature/contribution of our paper. Consequently his N <lb/>  *  (1535) can not <lb/>decay into N(940) by π emission, in blatant conflict with experiment. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. K. Nagata, A. Hosaka and V. Dmitrašinovi´ , arXiv:0705.1896 [hep-ph]. <lb/>2. T. D. Cohen and L. Ya. Glozman, Phys.Rev.D 65, 016006 (2002); Int.J.Mod.Phys. A 17, <lb/> 1327 (2002). <lb/>3. R. L. Jaffe, D. Pirjol and A. Scardicchio, Phys. Rev. Lett. 96 (2006) 121601, and R. L. Jaffe, <lb/>D. Pirjol and A. Scardicchio, Phys. Rept. 435 (2006) 157. <lb/>4. B. W. Lee, Chiral Dynamics, (Gordon and Breach, New York, 1972). <lb/>5. D. Jido, M. Oka and A. Hosaka, Prog. Theor. Phys. 106, 873 (2001). <lb/>6. C. DeTar and T. Kunihiro, Phys. Rev. D 39, 2805 (1989). <lb/>7. B.L. Ioffe, Nucl. Phys. B 188, 317 (1981); ibid. B 191, 591 (1981) (E); Z. Phys. C 18, 67 <lb/>(1983). <lb/>8. G.A. Christos, Z. Phys. C 21, 83 (1983); Phys. Rev. D 35, 330 (1987). <lb/>9. D. Jido, M. Oka and A. Hosaka, Phys. Rev. Lett. 80, 448 (1998). <lb/>10. K. Nagata and A. Hosaka, J. Phys. G 32 (2006) 777 ; K. Nagata, A. Hosaka, Laith J. <lb/>Abu-Raddad, Phys.Rev. C72:035208 (2005), (E)-ibid. C 73:049903 (2006). <lb/>11. V. Dmitrašinovi´ , Phys. Rev. C 53, 1383 (1996), Nucl. Phys. A 686, 377 (2001); E. Klempt, <lb/>B. C. Metsch, C. R. M ¨ <lb/>unz, and H. R. Petry, Phys. Lett. B 361, 160 (1995); M. Hirata and <lb/> Does nucleon parity doubling imply U  A  (1) symmetry restoration? <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> N. Tsutsui, Phys. Rev. D 56, 5696 (1997); M. Takizawa, and T. Umekawa, Prog. Theor. <lb/>Phys. 109, 969 (2003) and T. Umekawa, K. Naito, M. Oka, and M. Takizawa, Phys.Rev. <lb/> C 70:055205 (2004). <lb/>12. K. Nagata, A. Hosaka and V. Dmitrašinovi´ , in preparation (2007). </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
