<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Proc Indian Natn Sci Acad 81 No. 1 February 2015 Special Issue, pp. 75-85 <lb/>c <lb/> Printed in India. <lb/> Imaginary Part of the Medium Modified Heavy Quark Potential <lb/> LATA THAKUR  *  , UTTAM KAKADE and BINOY KRISHNA PATRA <lb/> Department of Physics, Indian Institute of Technology Roorkee 247 667, India <lb/> (Received on 31 May 2014; Accepted on 25 June 2014) <lb/> We have calculated the dissociation of quarkonia through an imaginary potential which is obtained by <lb/>correcting both the perturbative and non-perturbative terms of the potential at T=0 through the dielectric <lb/>function in real-time formalism. The real-part of the potential becomes stronger and thus makes the <lb/>quarkonia more bound whereas the (magnitude) imaginary-part too becomes larger and thus contribute <lb/>more to the thermal width, compared to the medium-contribution of the Coulomb term alone. We have <lb/>also extended our calculation to anisotropic medium, by calculating the leading anisotropic corrections <lb/>to the propagators in Keldysh representation. The presence of anisotropy makes the real-part of the <lb/>potential stronger but the imaginary-part is weakened slightly and the competition between them results <lb/>in higher dissociation temperatures compared to isotropic medium. <lb/> Key Words : Quantum Chromodynamics; Debye Mass; Momentum Anisotropy; String Tension; <lb/>Dielectric Permittivity; Heavy Quark Potential; Decay Width <lb/></front>

			<body> Introduction <lb/> Heavy quarkonium systems have turned out to provide extremely useful probes for the deconfined state of <lb/>matter because the force between a heavy quark and its anti-quark, is weakened due to the presence of light <lb/>quarks and gluons which leads to the dissociation of quarkonium bound states (Matsui and Satz, 1986). <lb/>The medium effects can be envisaged through a temperature-dependent heavy quark potentials and have <lb/>been studied over the decades either phenomenologically or through lattice based free-energy calculations <lb/>(Mocsy and Petreczky, 2008). Among the recent theoretical developments in the quarkonium studies, the <lb/>first-principle calculations of imaginary contributions to the heavy quark potential either due to gluonic <lb/>Landau damping (Laine et al., 2007) or due to the singlet to octet transitions etc. (Brambilla et al., 2008), <lb/>which describe the decaying of the Q ¯ <lb/> Q correlation with its initial state due to scatterings in the plasma <lb/></body>

			<front> *  Author for Correspondence : E-mail: thakurphyom@gmail.com <lb/> DOI: 10.16943/ptinsa/2015/v81i1/48054 <lb/></front>

			<page> 76 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Lata Thakur et al., <lb/></note>

			<body> (Beraudo et al., 2008), are well known. Earlier it was thought that a quarkonium state is dissociated when <lb/>the screening becomes so strong that it inhibits the formation of bound states but nowadays a quarkonium <lb/>is dissociated at a lower temperature (Laine et al., 2007; Burnier et al., 2008) even though its binding <lb/>energy is nonvanishing, rather is overtaken by the Landau-damping induced thermal width (Laine et al., <lb/> 2007; Hatsuda, 2013). Although the lattice studies predicts a sizable imaginary component in the potential <lb/>(Rothkopf et al., 2009, 2012), it may not be reliable because the necessary quality of the data has not yet <lb/>been achieved. One thus needs inadvertent support from the potential models at finite temperature as an <lb/>important tool to complement the lattice studies. Since the string-tension does not vanish abruptly at the <lb/>deconfinement point (Cheng et al., 2008), one should study its effects on heavy quark potential even above <lb/> T  c  . So we aim here to calculate the imaginary part, in addition to the real part of the potential both in <lb/>isotropic and anisotropic medium by correcting the full Cornell potential and not its Coulomb part alone. <lb/>The structure of this paper is as follows: We have reviewed the potential introduced in (Agotiya et al., <lb/> 2009) and extended it to the imaginary part of the potential for both the isotropic as well as anisotropic <lb/>medium. We have started with propagators and self energies in Keldysh representation and their evaluation <lb/>in HTL resummed theory. Then we have studied the dissociation of charmonium and bottomonium states <lb/>by calculating their (thermal) widths and binding energies. Finally we conclude our main results. <lb/> Potential in a Hot QCD Medium <lb/> The medium-modification to the vacuum potential can be obtained by correcting its both short and long-<lb/>distance part with a dielectric function (p) encoding the effect of deconfinement (Agotiya et al., 2009). <lb/>Fourier transform of potential at vanishing frequency gives the desired non-relativistic potential at finite <lb/>temperature. <lb/> V (r, T ) = <lb/> d  3  p <lb/> (2π) <lb/> 3/2 <lb/> (e <lb/> ip·r  − 1) <lb/> V (p) <lb/> (p) <lb/>, <lb/> (1) <lb/>where the r-independent term needed to renormalize the heavy quark free energy is the perturbative free <lb/>energy of quarkonium at infinite separation (Dumitru et al., 2009). V (p) is the Fourier transform of the <lb/>potential given by: <lb/> V (p) = − <lb/> (2/π) <lb/> α <lb/>p  2  − <lb/> 4σ <lb/> √ <lb/> 2πp  4 <lb/> . <lb/> (2) <lb/> (p) is the dielectric permittivity given by (Schneider, 2002): <lb/> (p) = <lb/> 1 + <lb/>Π  L  (0, p, T ) <lb/> p  2 <lb/> ≡ <lb/> 1 + <lb/> m  2 <lb/> D <lb/> p  2 <lb/> , <lb/> (3) <lb/>where m  D  is the screening mass. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Imaginary Part of the Medium Modified Heavy Quark Potential <lb/></note>

			<page> 77 <lb/></page>

			<body> However in the presence of non-perturbative effects, the dependence of the dielectric function on the <lb/>Debye mass may get modified. In this work the same (perturbative) screening scale are employed for <lb/>both the linear and Coulombic terms which may not look plausible. It would be interesting to see the <lb/>effects of different scales for the Coulomb and linear pieces of the T=0 potential in Ref. (Megias et al., <lb/> 2007, 2011) rather than a single one, where the non-perturbative effects have been incorporated beyond the <lb/>deconfinement temperature through dimension-two gluon condensates. The difference with their calculation <lb/>lies in the large distance limit of the potential and is found more attractive than our potential. <lb/>The dielectric permittivity can be calculated once the self energies and propagators are obtained in <lb/>HTL resummation theory in the real-time formalism (Carrington et al., 1999). The gluon self-energy can <lb/>be obtained by folding the approximated phase-space distribution in anisotropic medium (Romatschke and <lb/>Strickland, 2003) (ξ  1) as: <lb/> f  aniso  (k) = f  iso <lb/> k  2  + ξ(k.n)  2 <lb/> and hence the resummed propagator. The contribution from the quark loop (Dumitru et al., 2009) to the <lb/>gluon self energy with external and internal momenta as P (p  0  , p) and K(k  0  , k), respectively (with Q = <lb/> K − P ): <lb/> Π <lb/> µν  (P ) = − <lb/> i <lb/> 2 <lb/> N  f  g <lb/> 2 <lb/>  d  4  K <lb/> (2π)  4  tr[γ <lb/> µ  S(Q)γ <lb/> ν  S(K)]. <lb/> (4) <lb/>In HTL-limit, the quark and gluon loops together give the isotropic part of retarded (advanced) self-<lb/>energy (Dumitru, 2009) <lb/> Π <lb/> L <lb/>R,A(iso)  (P ) = m <lb/> 2 <lb/> D <lb/>  p  0 <lb/> 2p <lb/>ln <lb/> p  0  + p ± ii <lb/>p  0  − p ± ii <lb/> − 1 <lb/> , <lb/> (5) <lb/>with the prescriptions +ii (−ii), for the retarded (advanced) self-energies, respectively whereas the anisotropic <lb/>part for the retarded (advanced) self energies are <lb/> Π <lb/> L <lb/>R,A(aniso)  (P ) = <lb/> m  2 <lb/> D <lb/> 6 <lb/> 1 + <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>cos 2θ  p <lb/> + Π <lb/> L <lb/>R(iso)  (P ) <lb/> × <lb/> cos(2θ  p  ) − <lb/> p  0 <lb/>2 <lb/> 2p  2  (1 + 3 cos 2θ  p  ) <lb/> . <lb/> (6) <lb/>Similarly the isotropic and anisotropic terms for the temporal component of the symmetric part are given <lb/>by <lb/> Π <lb/> L <lb/>F (iso)  (P ) = −2πim <lb/> 2 <lb/> D <lb/> T <lb/>p <lb/> Θ(p <lb/> 2  − p  0 <lb/>2  ) , <lb/> Π <lb/> L <lb/>F (aniso)  (P ) = <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/> πim <lb/> 2 <lb/> D <lb/> T <lb/>p <lb/> sin <lb/> 2  θ  p  + <lb/> p  2 <lb/>0 <lb/> p  2  (3 cos <lb/> 2  θ  p  − 1) <lb/> Θ(p <lb/> 2  − p  0 <lb/>2  ). <lb/> (7) <lb/></body>

			<page> 78 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Lata Thakur et al., <lb/></note>

			<body> Thus the gluon self-energy is found to have both real and imaginary part which are responsible for the <lb/>Debye screening and the Landau damping, respectively. The real part of the static potential can be obtained <lb/>from the temporal component of retarded (or advanced) propagator (in static limit) <lb/> ReD <lb/> 00 <lb/> R,A  (0, p) = − <lb/> 1 <lb/>(p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D  ) <lb/>+ ξ <lb/>m  2 <lb/> D <lb/> 6(p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D  )  2  (3 cos 2θ  p  − 1) , <lb/> (8) <lb/>while for the imaginary part of the potential, the imaginary part of the temporal component of symmetric <lb/>propagator is given by <lb/> ImD <lb/> 00 <lb/> F  (0, p) = <lb/> −2πT m  2 <lb/> D <lb/> p(p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D  )  2  + ξ <lb/> 3πT m  2 <lb/> D <lb/> 2p(p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D  )  2  sin <lb/> 2  θ  p <lb/> − <lb/> 4πT m  4 <lb/> D <lb/> p(p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D  )  3 <lb/> sin <lb/> 2  θ  p  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>3 <lb/> . <lb/> (9) <lb/> Real Part of the Potential <lb/> The real part of the static potential can thus be obtained from eq. (1) by substituting the dielectric permittivity <lb/> (p) in terms of the physical &quot; 11 &quot; -component of the gluon propagator. The relation between the dielectric <lb/>permittivity and the static limit of the &quot; 00 &quot; -component of gluon propagator in Coulomb gauge is obtained <lb/>from the linear response theory (Kapusta and Gale, 1996): <lb/> −1  (p) = − lim  ω→0  p  2  D  00 <lb/>11  (ω, p) , where the real <lb/>and imaginary parts of D  00 <lb/>11  can be written as <lb/> ReD <lb/> 00 <lb/>11  (ω, p) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> D <lb/> 00 <lb/> R  + D <lb/> 00 <lb/> A <lb/>  and ImD <lb/> 00 <lb/>11  (ω, p) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> D <lb/> 00 <lb/> F  . <lb/> (10) <lb/>The real-part of the potential is then obtained as <lb/> ReV  (aniso)  (r, ξ, T ) = <lb/> d  3  p <lb/> (2π) <lb/> 3/2 <lb/> (e <lb/> ip·r  − 1) <lb/> − <lb/> (2/π) <lb/> α <lb/>p  2  − <lb/> 4σ <lb/> √ <lb/> 2πp  4 <lb/> × <lb/> p <lb/> 2 <lb/> 1 <lb/>(p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D  ) <lb/> − <lb/> ξm  2 <lb/> D <lb/> 6(p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D  )  2  (3 cos(2θ  p  ) − 1) <lb/> (11) <lb/>where θ  p  is the angle between r and n (direction of anisotropy). After performing the integration, the <lb/> , <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Imaginary Part of the Medium Modified Heavy Quark Potential <lb/></note>

			<page> 79 <lb/></page>

			<body> real-part of the potential in anisotropic medium becomes (Thakur et al., 2013) <lb/> V  aniso  (r, θ  r  , T ) = <lb/>2σ <lb/> m  D <lb/>  e <lb/> −ˆ   − 1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> + 1 <lb/> − αm  D <lb/>  e <lb/> −ˆ  <lb/> + 1 <lb/> + ξ <lb/>e <lb/> −ˆ  <lb/> × <lb/> 2σ <lb/> m  D <lb/>  e <lb/> ˆ <lb/> r  − 1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r  2  + <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> 2  e <lb/> ˆ <lb/> r  − 3 <lb/>3ˆ  <lb/> − <lb/> 5e <lb/>ê <lb/> r  − ˆ <lb/> r + 1 <lb/>12 <lb/> − <lb/> αm  D <lb/> 2 <lb/> e <lb/> ˆ <lb/> r  − 1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r  2  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> − <lb/> 2ˆ e <lb/>ê <lb/> r  − ˆ <lb/> r + 3 <lb/>6 <lb/> + <lb/> 2σ <lb/> m  D <lb/> 3 <lb/> e <lb/> ˆ <lb/> r  − 1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r  2  − <lb/> 3 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> − <lb/> e <lb/> ˆ <lb/> r  + ˆ <lb/> r + 5 <lb/>4 <lb/> − <lb/> αm  D <lb/> 2 <lb/> 3 <lb/> e <lb/> ˆ <lb/> r  − 1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r  2  − <lb/> 3 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> − <lb/> ˆ <lb/> r + 3 <lb/>2 <lb/> cos 2θ  r <lb/> = V  iso  (r, T ) + V  tensor  (r, θ  r  , T ). <lb/> (12) <lb/> Thus the anisotropy in the momentum space introduces an angular (θ  r  ) dependence, in addition to the <lb/>inter-particle separation (r), to the real part of the potential. The real potential becomes stronger with the <lb/>increase of anisotropy because the (anisotropic) Debye mass m  D  (ξ, T ) (or equivalently angular-dependent <lb/>Debye mass m  D  (θ  r  , T )) in an anisotropic medium is always smaller than in an isotropic medium. <lb/> Imaginary Part of the Potential: Thermal Width, Γ <lb/> The imaginary part of the potential plays an important role in weakening the bound state peak or transform-<lb/>ing it to mere threshold enhancement. It leads to a finite width (Γ) for the resonance peak in the spectral <lb/>function, which, in turn, determines the dissociation temperature. In recent years the imaginary part with a <lb/>momentum-space anisotropy and its effects on the thermal widths of the resonance states have been studied <lb/>(Dumitru et al., 2009; Margotta et al., 2011; Dumitru, 2011), with the medium-modification to the perturba-<lb/>tive (Coulomb) term only. We follow their work by including the medium corrections to both perturbative <lb/>(Coulombic) and non-perturbative (string) terms in a weakly anisotropic medium by the imaginary part of <lb/>the dielectric function: <lb/> ImV  (aniso)  (r, ξ, T ) = − <lb/> d  3  p <lb/> (2π)  3/2  (e <lb/> ip·r  − 1) <lb/> − <lb/> 2 <lb/> π <lb/>α <lb/>p  2  − <lb/> 4σ <lb/> √ <lb/> 2πp  4 <lb/> p <lb/> 2 <lb/> × <lb/> −πT m  2 <lb/> D <lb/> p(p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D  )  2  + ξ[ <lb/> 3πT m  2 <lb/> D <lb/> 4p(p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D  )  2  sin <lb/> 2  θ  p <lb/> − <lb/> 2πT m  4 <lb/> D <lb/> p(p  2  + m  2 <lb/> D  )  3  (sin <lb/> 2  θ  p  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>3 <lb/>) <lb/> ≡ ImV  1(aniso)  (r, ξ, T ) + ImV  2(aniso)  (r, ξ, T ) , <lb/> (13) <lb/>where ImV  1(aniso)  (r, ξ, T ) and ImV  2(aniso)  (r, ξ, T ) are the imaginary contributions corresponding to the <lb/>Coulombic and linear terms in anisotropic medium, respectively. The contribution due to the perturbative <lb/></body>

			<page> 80 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Lata Thakur et al., <lb/></note>

			<body> term in the leading-order is given by (Dumitru et al., 2009) <lb/> ImV  1(aniso)  (r, ξ, T ) = −αT (φ  0  (ˆ r) + ξ [φ  1  (ˆ r, θ  r  ) + φ  2  (ˆ r, θ  r  )]) , <lb/> (14) <lb/>where the functions φ  0  (ˆ r), φ  1  (ˆ r, θ  r  ) and φ  2  (ˆ r, θ  r  ) are given by <lb/> φ  0  (ˆ r) = −αT <lb/> − <lb/> ˆ <lb/> r  2 <lb/> 9 <lb/>(−4 + 3γ  E  + 3 log <lb/> ) <lb/> φ  1  (ˆ r, θ  r  ) = <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r  2 <lb/> 600 <lb/>[123 − 90γ  E  − 90 log <lb/>  + cos 2θ  r  (−31 + 30γ  E  + 30 log <lb/> )] <lb/>φ  2  (ˆ r, θ  r  ) = <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r  2 <lb/> 90 <lb/>(−4 + 3 cos 2θ  r  ) <lb/> (15) <lb/> Fig. 1: Imaginary part of the potential for parallel (A) and perpendicular (B) alignment in an anisotropic medium <lb/> Similarly the imaginary part due to the non-perturbative (linear) term has also the isotropic and anisotropic <lb/>term: <lb/> ImV  2(aniso)  (r, ξ, T ) = <lb/>2σT <lb/> m  2 <lb/> D <lb/> ψ  0  (ˆ r) − ξ [ψ  1  (ˆ r, θ  r  ) + ψ  2  (ˆ r, θ  r  )] <lb/> , <lb/> (16) <lb/> A <lb/> B <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Imaginary Part of the Medium Modified Heavy Quark Potential <lb/></note>

			<page> 81 <lb/></page>

			<body> where the functions ψ  0  (ˆ r), ψ  1  (ˆ r, θ  r  ) and ψ  2  (ˆ r, θ  r  ) are given by <lb/> ψ  0  (ˆ r) = <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r  2 <lb/> 6 <lb/>+ <lb/> −107 + 60γ  E  + 60 log(ˆ r) <lb/> 3600 <lb/> 4  + O(ˆ r <lb/> 5  ) , <lb/> (17) <lb/> ψ  1  (ˆ r, θ  r  ) = <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r  2 <lb/> 10 <lb/>+ <lb/>(−739 + 420γ  E  + 420 log(ˆ r))ˆ r  4 <lb/> 39200 <lb/>+ <lb/> − <lb/> ˆ <lb/> r  2 <lb/> 20 <lb/>+ <lb/>(176 − 105γ  E  − 105 log(ˆ r))ˆ r  4 <lb/> 14700 <lb/> cos <lb/> 2  θ  r  , <lb/> (18) <lb/> ψ  2  (ˆ r, θ  r  ) = − <lb/> 4 <lb/>3 <lb/> 7ˆ   2 <lb/> 120 <lb/> − <lb/> 11ˆ   4 <lb/> 3360 <lb/>+ O(ˆ r <lb/> 5  ) <lb/> − 4 <lb/> − <lb/> ˆ <lb/> r  2 <lb/> 60 <lb/>+ <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r  4 <lb/> 840 <lb/>+ O(ˆ r <lb/> 5  ) <lb/> cos <lb/> 2  θ  r  , <lb/> (19) <lb/>respectively and γ  E  is the Euler-Gamma constant. Finally the short and long-distance contributions, in the <lb/>leading logarithmic order, gives the imaginary part of the potential in the anisotropic medium <lb/> Fig. 2: The thermal width for the J/ψ and Υ states in the anisotropic medium <lb/> ImV  (aniso)  (r, θ  r  , T ) = −T <lb/> αˆ  2 <lb/> 3 <lb/>+ <lb/> σˆ  4 <lb/> 30m  2 <lb/> D <lb/> log( <lb/>1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> ) <lb/>+ξT <lb/> αˆ  2 <lb/> 5 <lb/>+ <lb/>3σˆ   4 <lb/> 140m  2 <lb/> D <lb/> − cos <lb/> 2  θ  r <lb/>  αˆ  2 <lb/> 10 <lb/>+ <lb/> σˆ  4 <lb/> 70m  2 <lb/> D <lb/> log( <lb/>1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> ) , <lb/> (20) <lb/></body>

			<page> 82 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Lata Thakur et al., <lb/></note>

			<body> which is found to be smaller than the isotropic medium and decreases with the increase of anisotropy (shown <lb/>in Fig. 1). The imaginary part of the potential, in small-distance limit, is a perturbation to the vacuum <lb/>potential and thus provides an estimate for the width (Γ) of a resonance state and can be calculated, in a <lb/>first-order perturbation, by folding with the unperturbed (1S) Coulomb wave function <lb/> Γ  (aniso)  = <lb/> d <lb/> 3  r|Ψ(r)| <lb/> 2 <lb/> αT  <lb/> 2  log( <lb/>1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> ) <lb/> 1 <lb/>3 <lb/> − ξ <lb/> 3 − cos 2θ  r <lb/> 20 <lb/> + <lb/>2σT <lb/> m  2 <lb/> D <lb/> ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> 4  log( <lb/>1 <lb/>ˆ <lb/> r <lb/> ) <lb/>1 <lb/>20 <lb/> 1 <lb/>3 <lb/> − ξ <lb/> 2 − cos 2θ  r <lb/> 14 <lb/> = T <lb/> 4 <lb/> αm  2 <lb/> Q <lb/> + <lb/>12σ <lb/> α  2  m  4 <lb/> Q <lb/> 1 − <lb/> ξ <lb/> 2 <lb/> m <lb/> 2 <lb/> D  log <lb/> αm  Q <lb/> 2m  D <lb/> . <lb/> (21) <lb/>From the (Fig. 2) it is clear that the width always increases with the temperature. The non-perturbative string <lb/>term, in addition to the Coulomb term, makes the width larger than the earlier result with the perturbative <lb/>Coulomb term (Dumitru, 2011) only and thus the damping of the exchanged gluon in the heat bath provides <lb/>larger contribution to the dissociation rate. Width becomes smaller in anisotropic medium than in isotropic <lb/>medium and gets narrower with the increase of anisotropy because Γ is approximately proportional to the <lb/>(square) Debye mass and the Debye mass decreases in the anisotropic medium. <lb/> Real and Imaginary Binding Energies: Dissociation Temperatures <lb/> In order to understand the in-medium properties of the quarkonium states, one need to solve the Schrödinger <lb/>equation with both the real and imaginary part of the finite temperature potential. The real part of binding <lb/>energy may be obtained from the radial part of the Schrödinger equation (of the isotropic component) plus <lb/>the first-order perturbation due to the anisotropic component as <lb/> Re E <lb/> aniso <lb/>bin  = <lb/> m  Q  σ  2 <lb/> m  4 <lb/> D <lb/> n  2  + αm  D <lb/> + <lb/>2ξ <lb/>3 <lb/> m  Q  σ  2 <lb/> m  4 <lb/> D <lb/> n  2  , <lb/> (22) <lb/>where the first term is the solution of (radial-part) of the Schrödinger equation with the isotropic part <lb/>(ReV  iso  (ˆ r  1, T )) and the second term is due to the anisotropic perturbation of the tensorial compo-<lb/>nent (V  tensor  (ˆ r  1, θ  r  , T )) calculated from the first-order perturbation theory. The complex potential in <lb/>general needs to be dealt with numerically to obtain the real and imaginary binding energies. Here we use <lb/>the matrix method to solve the corresponding schrödinger equation (Thakur et al., 2013). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Imaginary Part of the Medium Modified Heavy Quark Potential <lb/></note>

			<page> 83 <lb/></page>

			<body> Table 1:  Dissociation temperatures of J/ψ and Υ states for different anisotropies with the Debye mass in leading-order <lb/> Method <lb/>State ξ = 0.0 ξ = 0.3 ξ = 0.6 <lb/> Re B.E.=Im B.E. J/ψ <lb/> 2.45 <lb/>2.46 <lb/>2.47 <lb/> Υ <lb/> 3.40 <lb/>3.45 <lb/>3.46 <lb/> Γ=2B.E. <lb/> J/ψ <lb/> 1.40 <lb/>1.46 <lb/>1.54 <lb/> Υ <lb/> 3.10 <lb/>3.17 <lb/>3.26 <lb/> Fig. 3: Variation of the real and imaginary part of the binding energies for J/ψ and Υ states for different anisotropies <lb/> We will now study the dissociation in thermal medium to calculate the dissociation temperature (T  d  ) either <lb/>from the intersection of the (real and imaginary) binding energies (Strickland and Bazow, 2012; Margotta <lb/> et al., 2011) or from the conservative criterion on the width of the resonance as: Γ ≥ 2Re B.E. (Mocsy <lb/>and Petreczky, 2008). Although both definitions are physically equivalent but they are numerically different <lb/>(Table 1). <lb/>The real and imaginary part of the binding energies for the J/ψ and Υ states are computed numerically <lb/>in Fig. 3 for different values of anisotropies. We have computed the dissociation temperatures at different <lb/>anisotropies in Table 1 from these numerical observations. <lb/> Conclusion <lb/> We have studied the properties of charmonium and bottomonium states with the in-medium modifica-<lb/>tions to both perturbative and non-perturbative part of the Cornell potential. The inclusion of the string <lb/>term, in an(isotropic) medium, makes the quarkonium states more tight compared to the medium modi-<lb/>fication to the Coulomb term alone and increases the magnitude of the imaginary part. The presence of <lb/></body>

			<page> 84 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Lata Thakur et al., <lb/></note>

			<body> string terms broadens the (thermal) width of the states which plays an important role in the dissociation <lb/>mechanism. We found that the quarkonium states are dissociated at higher temperature compared to the <lb/>medium-consideration of the Coulomb term only. As the (effective) Debye mass in anisotropic medium is <lb/>always smaller than that in isotropic medium, both the real and imaginary part of the potential becomes <lb/>deeper with the increase of anisotropy and the binding of Q ¯ <lb/> Q pairs becomes more stronger with respect <lb/>to their isotropic counterpart. The overall observation is that the dissociation temperature increases with <lb/>anisotropy and string term. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgement <lb/> We are thankful for financial assistance from MHRD, India. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. Agotiya V, Chandra V and Patra BK (2009) Dissociation of quarkonium in hot QCD medium: Modification of <lb/>the inter-quark potential Phys Rev C80 025210 <lb/>2. Brambilla N, Ghiglieri J, Vairo A and Petreczky P (2008) Static quark-antiquark pairs at finite temperature Phys <lb/>Rev D78 014017 <lb/>3. Beraudo A, Blaizot JP and Ratti C (2008) Real and imaginary-time Q anti-Q correlators in a thermal medium <lb/> Nucl Phys A806 312-338 <lb/>4. Burnier Y, Laine M and Vepsalainen M (2008) Heavy quarkonium in any channel in resummed hot QCD JHEP <lb/> 01 043 <lb/>5. Carrington ME, Defu H and Thoma MH (1999) Equilibrium and nonequilibrium hard thermal loop resumma-<lb/>tion in the real time formalism Eur Phys J C7 347-354 <lb/>6. Cheng M, Datta S, Heide van der J, Huebner K et al. (2008) The Spatial String Tension and Dimensional <lb/>Reduction in QCD Phys Rev D78 034506 <lb/>7. Dumitru A, Guo Y and Strickland M (2009) The Imaginary part of the static gluon propagator in an anisotropic <lb/>(viscous) QCD plasma Phys Rev D79 114003 <lb/>8. Dumitru A (2011) Quarkonium in a non-ideal hot QCD Plasma Prog Theor Phys Suppl 187 87 <lb/>9. Hatsuda T (2013) Heavy quarkonium in hot medium Nucl Phys A904-905 210c-216c <lb/>10. Kapusta JI and Gale C (1996) Finite Temperature Field Theory Principle and Applications (Cambridge Univer-<lb/>sity Press, Cambridge) 2nd ed <lb/>11. Laine M, Philipsen O, Romatschke P and Tassler M (2007) Real-time static potential in hot QCD JHEP 03 054 <lb/>12. Laine M, Philipsen O, and Tassler M (2007) Thermal imaginary part of a real-time static potential from classical <lb/>lattice gauge theory simulations JHEP 09 066 <lb/>13. Matsui T and Satz H (1986) J/ψ suppression by quark-gluon plasma formation Phys Lett B178 416 <lb/>14. Mocsy A and Petreczky P (2007) Color screening melts quarkonium Phys Rev Lett 99 211602 <lb/> Imaginary Part of the Medium Modified Heavy Quark Potential <lb/> 85 <lb/> 15. Mocsy A and Petreczky P (2008) Can quarkonia survive deconfinement? Phys Rev D77 014501 <lb/>16. Mocsy A (2009) Potential Models for Quarkonia Eur Phys J C61 705-710 <lb/>17. Megias E, Arriola ER and Salceedo LL(2007) The Quark-antiquark potential at finite temperature and the <lb/>dimension two gluon condensate Phys Rev D75 105019 <lb/>18. Megias E, Arriola ER and Salceedo LL (2011) Trace Anomaly and dimension two gluon condensate above the <lb/>phase transition Indian J Phys 85 1191-1196 <lb/>19. Margotta M, McCarty K, McGahan C, Strickland M and Elorriaga DY (2011) Quarkonium states in a complex-<lb/>valued potential Phys Rev D83 105019 <lb/>20. Romatschke P and Strickland M (2003) Collective modes of an anisotropic quark gluon plasma Phys Rev D68 <lb/> 036004 <lb/>21. Rothkopf A, Hatsuda T and Sasaki S (2009) Proper heavy-quark potential from a spectral decomposition of the <lb/>thermal Wilson loop PoS LAT 162 <lb/>22. Rothkopf A, Hatsuda T and Sasaki S (2012) Complex Heavy-Quark Potential at Finite Temperature from Lattice <lb/>QCD Phys Rev Lett 108 162001 <lb/>23. Schneider RA (2002) Debye screening at finite temperature, revisited Phys Rev D66 036003 <lb/>24. Strickland M and Bazow D (2012) Thermal Bottomonium Suppression at RHIC and LHC Nucl Phys A879 25 <lb/>25. Thakur L, Haque N, Kakade U and Patra BK (2013) Dissociation of quarkonium in an anisotropic hot QCD <lb/>medium Phys Rev D88 054022. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
