<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage> Behavior of Asymptotically Flat Empty Spaces <lb/> Ezra T. Newman and Theodore W. J. Unti <lb/>Citation: Journal of Mathematical Physics 3, 891 (1962); doi: 10.1063/1.1724303 <lb/>View online: http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.1724303 <lb/>View Table of Contents: http://scitation.aip.org/content/aip/journal/jmp/3/5?ver=pdfcov <lb/>Published by the AIP Publishing <lb/> Articles you may be interested in <lb/> The Eikonal equation in asymptotically flat space–times <lb/>J. Math. Phys. 40, 1041 (1999); 10.1063/1.532705 <lb/>Asymptotically flat H spaces <lb/>J. Math. Phys. 22, 818 (1981); 10.1063/1.524988 <lb/>A property of asymptotically flat, static, vacuum space‐times <lb/>J. Math. Phys. 15, 413 (1974); 10.1063/1.1666660 <lb/>Equations of motion for the sources of asymptotically flat spaces <lb/>J. Math. Phys. 13, 1884 (1972); 10.1063/1.1665927 <lb/>A Note on Asymptotically Flat Spaces <lb/>J. Math. Phys. 12, 2462 (1971); 10.1063/1.1665558 <lb/> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:48:35 <lb/></titlePage>

			<front> JOURNAL OF MATHEMATICAL PHYSICS <lb/>VOLUME 3, NUMBER 5 <lb/>SEPTE:\I BER-OCTOBER 1962 <lb/> Behavior of Asymptotically Flat Empty Spaces* <lb/> EZRA T. NEWMAN AND THEODORE W. J. UNTI <lb/> University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania <lb/> (Received April 27, 1962) <lb/>The asymptotic behavior of the Weyl tensor and metric tensor is investigated for probably all <lb/> as~~ptotically  flat solutions of the empty space Einstein field equations. The systematic investigation <lb/>utilizes a set of first order differential equations which are equivalent to the empty space Einstein <lb/>equations. These are solved asymptotically, subject to a condition imposed on a tetrad component <lb/>of the Riemann tensor  \[fo  which ensures the approach to flatness at spatial infinity of the space-time. <lb/> If \[fo.  is assumed to be an analytic function of a suitably defined radial coordinate, uniqueness of the <lb/>s?lutlOns can be proved. However, this paper makes considerable progress toward establishing a <lb/>ngorous proof of uniqueness in the nonanalytic case. A brief discussion of the remaining coordinate <lb/>freedom, with certain topological aspects, is also included. <lb/></front>

			<body> I.  INTRODUCTION <lb/> T <lb/> HE problem of the behavior of the metric <lb/>tensor and Riemann tensor at spatial infinity <lb/>in an asymptotically flat space-time has recently <lb/>received considerable attention for a variety of <lb/>reasons. For example, Trautman and others <lb/> l  have <lb/>used the  as~mptotic  behavior to study conservation <lb/>of energy and momentum as well as gravitational <lb/>radiation. Bergmann <lb/> 2 has been interested in the <lb/>group properties of the transformation at spatial <lb/>infinity in order to shed light on quantization <lb/>problems. <lb/>Until recently, most of these approaches were <lb/>based on reasonable guesses for the behavior of <lb/> gIl&apos;  at infinity. Bondi <lb/> 3 and Bondi and Sachs <lb/> 4 have <lb/>improved this situation with some beautiful theorems <lb/>on the asymptotic behavior of the metric. Their <lb/>work, however, contained several restrictive as-<lb/>sumptions; the analytic behavior of all expressions <lb/>as functions of r-<lb/> l  (r  is a suitably defined radial <lb/>coordinate), and certain simplifying topological re-<lb/>strictions. <lb/>In the present paper, these assumptions are <lb/>dropped, and the techniques developed by Newman <lb/>and Penrose <lb/> 5 (this reference will be denoted by <lb/>NP) are applied to the general problem of the asymp-<lb/>totic behavior of the Weyl tensor and metric tensor <lb/>for probably all asymptotically flat solutions to the <lb/>empty space Einstein field equations. <lb/>In a hyperbolic Riemannian manifold a family of <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> *  This work has been supported by the Office of Aerospace <lb/>Research, U.S. Air Force. <lb/> 1 A. Trautman, &quot;Conservation Laws in General Relativity&quot; <lb/>(to be published); This is also an excellent source of references <lb/>to recent works on conservation laws. <lb/> 2 P. Bergmann, Phys. Rev. 124,274 (1961). <lb/> 8 H. Bondi, Proc. Roy. Soc. (London) (to be published). <lb/> 4 H. Bondi and R. Sachs (private communication). <lb/> 6  E.  Newman and R. Penrose, J. Math. Phys. 3, 566 (1962). <lb/></note>

			<body> null hypersurfaces may always be introduced. This <lb/>being done, in Sec. II a coordinate system and <lb/>tetrad are associated with the given surfaces, <lb/>bringing the metric into a certain canonical form. <lb/>Then a set of equations equivalent to the empty <lb/>space Einstein field equations is shown, and the <lb/>variables occurring in these equations are defined. <lb/>From these equations the asymptotic behavior of <lb/>the field can be investigated, systematically and in <lb/>detail, subject to a condition of approach to flatness <lb/>at infinity on the space-time. This condition of <lb/>asymptotic flatness is not imposed on the metric, <lb/>as is usually done, but is instead imposed on the <lb/>empty-space Riemann tensor. More explicitly, <lb/>using the orthonormal tetrad defined in Sec. II, <lb/>there are only five independent (complex) tetrad <lb/>components of the Weyl tensor, which we denote by <lb/> \{I  A&apos;  One of these components  &apos;ltD,  is specified asymp-<lb/>totically as  O(r- 5 ),6  which guarantees the asymptotic <lb/>flatness of the space. <lb/>In Sec. III the field equations are solved asymp-<lb/>totically, with the above condition on \lIo. In order <lb/>to do this, the field equations are divided into three <lb/>groups. The first group is integrated to find the <lb/>radial dependence of all the variables, up to an <lb/>appropriate order of magnitude. Each integration <lb/>produces an arbitrary function of the remaining <lb/>three (nonradial) coordinates. The second group of <lb/>equations sets up relations among these&quot; constants&quot; <lb/>of integration, which allow most of the functions <lb/>to be expressed in terms of two basic functions. <lb/>The third group of equations, part of the Bianchi <lb/>identities, determines the propagation of com-<lb/>ponents of the Weyl tensor off the hypersurface. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 6  fer,  u, Xk).  =  O~g(r))  means  If(r,  u, xk)1  &lt;  g(r)F(u, x k ) <lb/> for some functIOn  F  mdependent of  r  and for all  r,  sufficiently <lb/>large. <lb/></note>

			<page> 891 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:48:35 <lb/></note>

			<page> 892 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> E. T. NEWMAN AND T. W. J. UNTI <lb/></note>

			<body> In Sec. IV the general class of coordinate trans-<lb/>formations which preserves the form of the metric <lb/>is found. Some of the coordinate transformations <lb/>change the system of hypersurfaces, others do not. <lb/>Most of this coordinate freedom is eliminated in <lb/>achieving a simplification of one of the basic <lb/>variables. <lb/>In Sec. V we summarize the results already ob-<lb/>tained and discuss the independent data that can be <lb/>specified to determine a solution of the field equa-<lb/>tions. These data consist of a complex function <lb/>defined from the shear of a null congruence (Bondi <lb/> 3 <lb/> calls it the &quot;news function&quot;), a two-dimensional <lb/>metric tensor for the surface r  = const (Bondi <lb/>chooses this surface to be a sphere), and certain <lb/>Weyl tensor parts, including  \fro.  In order to obtain <lb/>explicit information from the third group of equa-<lb/>tions (the equations which propagate the Weyl <lb/>tensor off the hypersurface), one must specify in <lb/>more detail the dependence of \fro on r-<lb/> l <lb/> ,  other than <lb/> \fro =  O(r-<lb/> 5 <lb/>).  For example, if one writes <lb/>then the propagation of  \fr~  off the surface can be <lb/>explicitly worked out. <lb/> If  one assumes that &apos;l&apos;o is an analytic function <lb/>of  r-&apos;\  it can be shown that the solution of the field <lb/>equations is uniquely determined by the data that <lb/>have been set and the field equations themselves. <lb/> 4 <lb/> However, it now seems to be generally agreed that <lb/>the assumption of analyticity is probably not <lb/>essential in showing that the solution is unique.  It <lb/> would be very desirable to have a rigorous proof of <lb/>uniqueness in the nonanalytic case. Our work carries <lb/>this proof almost to completeness; the final step <lb/>would be to show that the propagation of the non-<lb/>analytic \fro off the surface is unique. Finally, the <lb/>remaining coordinate freedom is discussed. <lb/>In a recent paper, Sachs <lb/> 7 discusses the geometric <lb/>interpretation of several of the terms and first order <lb/>differential equations listed in Sec. II of this paper. <lb/>The range and summation conventions used here <lb/>are: lower case Greek indices 1, 2, 3, 4; lower case <lb/>Latin indices 3, 4. <lb/> II. THE FIELD EQUATIONS <lb/> In this section a special coordinate system, with <lb/>an associated tetrad, is constructed as in Robinson-<lb/>Trautman <lb/> 8 and NP. The pertinent results of NP are <lb/>presented, including a set of equations which are <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 7 R. Sachs, Proc. Roy. Soc. (London) 264, 309 (1961). <lb/> 8  1.  Robinson and A. Trautman, Proc. Roy. Soc. (London) <lb/>265, 463 (1962). <lb/></note>

			<body> equivalent to the Einstein empty space field equa-<lb/>tions. <lb/>We begin by introducing a family of null hyper-<lb/>surfaces, which is always possible in a normal hyper-<lb/>bolic Riemannian space. (In flat space-time a <lb/>particular family might be the null cones emanating <lb/>from a timelike world line.) They may be desig-<lb/>nated by a parameter  u  = const, so that <lb/> g&quot;&apos;u,&quot;U&quot;  = o. <lb/> (1) <lb/> The first tetrad vector will be chosen to be orthogonal <lb/>to the hypersurfaces, <lb/> (2) <lb/> Since the hypersurfaces are null, the vectors Z&quot; <lb/>will also be tangent to a family of curves that lie <lb/>within the surfaces. These curves are null geodesics; <lb/>their tangent vectors Za satisfy <lb/> Z&quot;;,l&apos;  = O. <lb/> Using this geometric approach, it is convenient <lb/>to take  u  as coordinate Xl. Then Eq, (2) becomes <lb/> la  =  o~. <lb/> An affine parameter, defined up to a linear trans-<lb/>formation, can be associated with the null geodesics <lb/>lying in the hypersurfaces. This affine parameter r <lb/> will be the coordinate x <lb/> 2 <lb/>•  The two remaining co-<lb/>ordinates  Xk  will label the geodesics on each hyper-<lb/>surface  u  = const. <lb/>The tangents to the geodesics are given by <lb/> l&quot;  =  dx&quot; jdr  =  g&quot;&apos;u&quot;  = g&quot;l. <lb/> (3) <lb/> With our choice of coordinates, r being the affine <lb/>parameter  x <lb/> 2 <lb/>,  Eq. (3) becomes <lb/> Z&quot; =  o~  = g&quot;l. <lb/> Hence, the metric assumes the form <lb/>0: 1 :0 <lb/>0 <lb/> __ 1 ___ 1 ____ <lb/> 1 <lb/> 1  g&quot;2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> 2k <lb/>g&quot;&apos; <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 <lb/> g <lb/> (4) <lb/> __ 1 ---1 ----<lb/> 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1  g2k  1  gm&quot; <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 <lb/> 0 <lb/> I <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/> In addition to the vector  Z&quot;,  we define another <lb/>null vector  n&quot;  normalized by  Z&quot;n&quot;  = 1, and two <lb/>unit spacelike vectors S-&quot; and  p&quot;  orthogonal to  Z&quot;, <lb/> n&quot;,  and each other. Instead of the real spacelike <lb/>vectors  p&quot;  and S-&quot; it is convenient to use the following <lb/>complex vectors <lb/> m&quot;  =  W - ip&quot;)/V&apos;2 <lb/> iii&quot;  =  W +  ip&quot;)jV2. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:48:35 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> BEHAVIOR OF ASYMPTOTICALLY FLAT EMPTY SPACES <lb/></note>

			<page> 893 <lb/></page>

			<body>The four tetrad vectors  l&quot;, n&quot;, m&quot;,  and  iii&quot;  are null <lb/>and satisfy the following orthonormality relations <lb/> l&quot;n&quot;  =  -m&quot;iii&quot;  = 1, <lb/> l&quot;l&quot;  =  n&quot;n&quot;  =  m&quot;m&quot;  =  m&quot;iii&quot;  =  l&quot;m&quot;  =  l&quot;m&quot; <lb/>(5) <lb/> In order to satisfy Eqs. (5), the vectors  m&quot;  and  n&quot; <lb/> must have the form <lb/> m&quot;  =  wo~  +  ~kO~ <lb/> n&quot;  = 0&apos;; +  Uo~  +  XkO~, <lb/> where w,  ~\  [7, and X&quot; are arbitrary functions of <lb/>the coordinates. The completeness relation <lb/> g&quot;&apos;  =  l&quot;n&apos;  +  n&quot;l&apos; - m&quot;iii&apos; - iii&quot;m&apos; <lb/> is a consequence of the orthonormality relations <lb/>Eqs. (5).  It  permits us to express the metric in <lb/>terms of the tetrad components; <lb/> 9&quot;2 =  2(U - ww) <lb/> g&quot;k  = X k _  (~kW  +  ~kW) <lb/> gmn  =  _(c~n  +  ~T). <lb/> (6) <lb/> There remains the following freedom in the choice <lb/>of the tetrad; the spatial rotation <lb/> r&apos; =  l&quot;, <lb/> which depends on one parameter, and a 2-param-<lb/>eter group, the so-called null rotations <lb/> r&apos;  =  l&quot;  ,  n&quot;&apos;  =  n&quot;  +  Em&quot;  +  Bm&quot;  +  BEl&quot; <lb/> m&apos;&quot;  =  m&quot;  +  Br, <lb/> (B  complex). <lb/> (8) <lb/> These tetrad transformations leave the direction <lb/>of  l&quot;  fixed. Later (Sec. IV) we will be interested in <lb/>coordinate transformations which necessitate the <lb/>choice of an entirely new family of hypersurfaces <lb/>and tetrad system. But at this point the restricted <lb/>3-parameter group Eqs.  (7)  and  (8)  can be used to <lb/>simplify some of the calculations. We will demand <lb/>parallel propagation of the tetrad along the geodesics, <lb/>restricting the functions C and  B  to be independent <lb/>of  r. <lb/> With the above preparations, we are in a position <lb/>to derive the asymptotic behavior of the metric <lb/>and Riemann tensors for empty space. In NP a set <lb/>of equations was developed which are equivalent to <lb/>the Einstein empty space field equationii. Although <lb/>many more in number, these equations are of first <lb/>order, most of them being linear. They are es-<lb/>sentially linear combinations of the equations for <lb/>the Riemann tensor expressed in terms of either <lb/>Ricci rotation coefficients, or in terms of the spinor <lb/>affine connection, many of the equations having <lb/>straightforward geometric interpretations. <lb/> 7 <lb/> The field equations [using our coordinate con-<lb/>ditions, Eq. (4)] may be divided into three groups. <lb/>The first group iii distinguished by a simple  D  ==  a / ar <lb/> derivative. Integration of these equations yields the <lb/> r  dependence of the variables, with (in general) a <lb/>&quot;constant&quot; of integration, a function of  u, x <lb/> 3 <lb/>, x\ <lb/> for each variable. <lb/> I. Radial equations: <lb/> D\fI1  -<lb/> D\f!2-<lb/> D\fI3-<lb/>D\fI.-<lb/> D~i  =  p~&apos;  +  at, <lb/> Dw  =  pw  +  aw - (IX +  (3), <lb/> DX&apos;  =  (IX  +  (3)~&apos;  +  (a  +  i3)r, <lb/> (9a) <lb/>(9 b) <lb/>(9c) <lb/> 1)U  =  (IX +  (3)w  +  (a  +  i3)w - (oy  +  &apos;9), (9d) <lb/> Dp  = / +  aiJ, <lb/> (ge) <lb/> Da  =  2pa  +  \flo, <lb/> (9f) <lb/> DT  =  Tp  +  Ta  +  \fIl&apos; <lb/> (9g) <lb/> Da  =  ap  +  {3iJ, <lb/> (9h) <lb/> D{3  =  (3p  +  aa  +  \fIl, <lb/> (9i) <lb/> D&apos;Y  =  m +  T,B  +  \fI2, <lb/> (9j) <lb/> DA = Ap  +  J.l.iJ, <lb/> (9k) <lb/> DJ.I.  =  J.l.p  +  Aa  +  \fI2&apos; <lb/> (91) <lb/> Dv  = TA  +  TJ.I.  +  \fI3, <lb/> (9m) <lb/> Wro =  4p\fl  1 - 4a\fl o , <lb/> (9n) <lb/> Wrl  =  3p\fl  2 - 2a\fl  1 - A\fI o , <lb/> (90) <lb/> Wr2  =  2p\fl 3 - 2A\fIl, <lb/> (9p) <lb/> Wr3  =  p\fl.  +  2a\fl&quot; - 3A\fI2, <lb/> (9q) <lb/>The second group have more complicated deriva-<lb/>tives, <lb/> ~  =  U(a/ar)  +  (a/au)  +  Xk(a/axk) <lb/> o =  w(a/ar)  +  ~k(a/axk). <lb/> From this group we obtain relations between the <lb/>integration &quot;constants&quot; found above. <lb/> II. N onradial equations: <lb/> oX&apos; - ~~;  (J.I.  +  &apos;9 - &apos;Y)(  +  xt, <lb/> (lOa) <lb/> o~&apos;  - b~&apos;  =  (i3 - a)~i  +  (IX - mt, <lb/> (lOb) <lb/> ow - bw  = Ci3 - a)w  + (IX - (3)w  +  (J.I. - jl),  (lOc) <lb/> oU - ~w  = (J.I.  +  &apos;9 - &apos;Y)w  +  };.w - v, <lb/> (lOd) <lb/> </body>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:48:35 <lb/></note>

			<page> 894 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> E. T. NEWMAN AND T. W. J. UNTI <lb/></note>

			<body> .1X - Bv  =  2001  +  (1 -31&apos; - f.J. - il)X - &apos;1&apos;4, (lOe) <lb/> op - Bu  = ({3  +  ii)  P  +  (~  - 3a)u - &apos;lrI&apos; (lOf) <lb/> oa - B{3  =  f.J.p - Xu - 2a{3  +  aii  +  {3~  - &apos;lr2&apos;  (lOg) <lb/>oX - Bf.J.  =  (a  +  ~)f.J.  + (ii - 3{3)X -&apos;lra, (10 h) <lb/> OV - .1f.J.  =  I&apos;f.J. - 2,,{3  +  1f.J.  +  f.J.2  +  AX, <lb/> (lOi) <lb/>01&apos; -.1{3 =  Tf.J. - UV  +  (f.J. - I&apos;  + 1){3 +  Xa,  (lOj) <lb/> OT - .1u  =  2T{3  +  (1  +  f . J. - 31&apos;)u  +  Xp,  (1 Ok) <lb/> .1p - BT  = (y + 1 - il)P - 2aT - AU - &apos;lr2 (101) <lb/> .1a - BI&apos;  =  pv - TA -AfJ  + (1 - I&apos; - il)a - &apos;lra, <lb/> (10m) <lb/> The third group, derived from the Bianchi <lb/>identities, determines the propagation of the tetrad <lb/>components of the Weyl tensor in the u-direction, <lb/>from null surface to null surface. <lb/> III. The u-derillative equations: <lb/> .1&apos;lr  o - o&apos;lr  l  = [41&apos; - f.J.]&apos;lro  - [4T  +  2,8]&apos;1&apos;1  +  3u&apos;lr2 <lb/> (11 a) <lb/> .1&apos;lrl - 0&apos;lr2  =  V\[rn  +  [21&apos; -2f.J.N&apos;1 - 3T&apos;I&apos;2  +  2u&apos;lra <lb/> (11 b) <lb/> .1&apos;lr2 - o&apos;lra = 2,,&apos;lr1 - 3f.J.&apos;lr2  + [  -2T  +  2,6]&apos;lra  +  u&apos;lr4 <lb/> (l1c) <lb/> .1&apos;lr a - 0&apos;lr4  =  3,,&apos;lr2  - [21&apos; + 4f.J.]&apos;lra + [ - T  + 4,6J&apos;lr4 <lb/> (lId) <lb/> The complex functions  p,  u, a, .. , are defined <lb/>either in terms of the Ricci rotation coefficients, or <lb/>the spinor affine connection. In NP they are named <lb/>&quot;spin-coefficients.&quot; Their definitions in terms of the <lb/>tetrad are: <lb/> p  =  Z&quot;;pm&quot;iii:, <lb/>u  =  Z&quot;:,m&quot;m&apos;, <lb/> T  =  Z&quot;:,m&quot;n&apos;, <lb/> a  =  t(l&quot;&quot;n&quot;iii: - m&quot;:,iii&quot;iii&apos;) , <lb/> {3 =  t(l&quot;&quot;n·m <lb/>P - m.:piii&quot;m·) , <lb/> I&apos;  =  tCZ.:pn&quot;n&apos; - m.:,iii&quot;nP) , <lb/> A  =  -n.&quot; iii&quot; iii: , <lb/> f . J.  =  n.:piii·m&apos;, <lb/>v  =  -n&quot;&quot;iii·n&quot;. <lb/> (12a) <lb/>(l2b) <lb/>(12c) <lb/>(l2d) <lb/>(12 e) <lb/>(12f) <lb/>(12g) <lb/>(12 h) <lb/>(12i) <lb/>In NP it is shown that, in this coordinate system, <lb/> T  = ii  +  ,6. <lb/>As mentioned above, many of the spin-coefficients <lb/>have simple geometric meanings, such as the shear <lb/>and divergence of the null geodesic congruence, etc. <lb/>(See reference 7 and NP, Sec. IV). <lb/>The &apos;lr  A  are the tetrad components of the Weyl <lb/>tensor (or empty space Riemann tensor); <lb/> &apos;lr  o  =  -Ca{3&apos;Yozam{3Fmo, <lb/> (12j) <lb/>&apos;lr  l  =  -Ca{3&apos;Yazan{3Fmo, <lb/> (12k) <lb/> &apos;lr2=  -tc a {3&apos;Yo(za n {3Pn°  +  za n {3m&apos;YiiiO), <lb/> (121) <lb/>&apos;lra =  C a{3&apos;Ya zan {3n  &apos;Y  iii  ° , <lb/> (12m) <lb/>&apos;lr4 =  -C a{3&apos; Y an aiii{3n  &apos;Y  iii!. <lb/> (12n) <lb/>We wish to solve the field equations with the <lb/>condition that all the &apos;lr  A  approach zero as  r  ap-<lb/>proaches infinity.  It  was shown in NP that an <lb/>extremely weak (if not the weakest) assumption to <lb/>ensure this boundary condition is &apos;lro  =  0(r-<lb/> 6 <lb/>). <lb/> Here we will adopt the slightly stronger condition <lb/> 9 <lb/> &apos;lro =  &apos;lr~r-5  +  0(r-<lb/> 6 <lb/>). <lb/> (13) <lb/> (In the remainder of the paper, a zero superscript <lb/>indicates the variable is independent of  r).  It  will <lb/>also be necessary to make assumptions on the <lb/>derivatives of  &apos;lr  o ; <lb/> lJiJt  0 =  a&apos;lr  0/  ar  = - 5&apos;lr~r  -6 +  OCr  -7) , (14) <lb/>and &quot;uniform smoothness,&quot; <lb/> di&apos;lr O  =  (di&apos;lr~)r-5  + o  (r-<lb/> 6 <lb/>) , . , . , <lb/> did;dmdn&apos;lr  o  =  (d;d;dmdn&apos;lr~)r-5  + 0  (r-6) , <lb/> d;D&apos;lr  o  =  -5(di&apos;lr~)r-6  +  0(r-<lb/> 7 <lb/>), ••• , <lb/> did;dkD&apos;lr  o  = - 5(d;d;dk&apos;l&apos;~)r-6  +  OCr  -7), <lb/> where  (i, j,  k, m, n  =  3,4) <lb/> d;  ~  a/ax <lb/> i <lb/>• <lb/> (15) <lb/> Needed in the next section is the asymptotic <lb/>behavior of each of the spin-coefficients, tetrad <lb/>components, and remaining Weyl tensor com-<lb/>ponents. This information was derived in NP, using <lb/>some powerful theorems of· Levinson and Cotting-<lb/>ton. <lb/> JO <lb/> p  =  -r-<lb/> I <lb/> +  0(r-<lb/> 2 <lb/>) <lb/> u  =  0(r-<lb/> 2 <lb/>) <lb/> a,  ,6, X,  f.J., T  =  OCr-I) <lb/> II, I&apos; =  0(1) <lb/> ~k  =  OCr-I) <lb/> X·, w  =  O(l) <lb/> U  =  OCr) <lb/> &apos;lrI =  0(r-<lb/> 4 <lb/>) <lb/> &apos;1&apos;2 = OVa) <lb/>&apos;lra =  0(r-<lb/> 2 <lb/>) <lb/> &apos;lr4  =  O(r-I) <lb/> (16) <lb/> (17) <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 9 We wish to study the propagation of  &apos;fro  in the  u  &quot;direc-<lb/>tion.&quot; Such a study would be more difficult under the general <lb/>assumption &apos;fro  =  O(r- 6 ). <lb/> 10 E. Coddington and N. Levinson,  Theory of Ordinary <lb/>Differential Equations  (McGraw-Hill Book Company, Inc., <lb/>New York, 1955), p. 103. <lb/> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:48:35 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> BEHAVIOR OF ASYMPTOTICALLY FLAT EMPTY SPACES <lb/></note>

			<page> 895 <lb/></page>

			<body> m.  SOLUTIONS <lb/> This section outlines the method of solving the <lb/>empty space field equations listed in Sec. II. The <lb/>first-order radial differential equations [all of which <lb/>are linear except Eqs. (ge, f), and these can be <lb/>made linear by increasing the order of differentia-<lb/>tion] fall naturally into certain subgroups, which <lb/>are solved simultaneously. All the theorems on <lb/>linear differential equations, existence, uniqueness, <lb/>etc., thus apply. By integrating these equations, <lb/>the  r  dependence of all the variables is easily ob-<lb/>tained. In general there is a &quot;constant&quot; of integra-<lb/>tion, a function of the remaining coordinates,  u, <lb/> x <lb/> 3 <lb/>, x\  in the solution of each of these differential <lb/>equations. Relations between these integration <lb/>&quot;constants&quot; are obtained from the equations having <lb/>compound derivatives  0  =  w(alar)  +  ~k(alaxk), <lb/> ~  =  U(alar)  +  (alau)  +  Xk(alaxk) ,  by setting <lb/>the coefficients of powers of  r-<lb/> I  independently equal <lb/>to zero. <lb/>The pair of equations (ge, f) <lb/> Dp  = / +  ujj, <lb/>Du  =  2prJ  +  &apos;1&apos;0 <lb/> with the asymptotic behavior, Eqs. (16),  p  =  _r-<lb/> 1 <lb/> + <lb/> 0(r-<lb/> 2 <lb/>), u  =  0(r-<lb/> 2 <lb/>),  can be integrated for the com-<lb/>plete  r  dependence of  p  and  u,  up to  0(r-<lb/> 5 <lb/>).  The <lb/>method of solution uses formal integration of the <lb/>order of magnitude symbols (which is permissable), <lb/>but not differentiation of them.ll <lb/>In the following,  g(r)  and  her)  will be used generi-<lb/>cally. We have <lb/> p  = _r-<lb/> 1 <lb/> +  g(r), <lb/> u  =  her),  where  g, h  =  0(r-<lb/> 2 <lb/>). <lb/> By Eqs. (ge, f), <lb/> Dg  +  2r-<lb/> 1 g  =  l  +  hii  =  0(r-<lb/>4 <lb/>) <lb/>Dh  +  2r-<lb/> 1 h  =  2hg  +  &apos;1&apos;0 =  0(r-4 ). <lb/> The solution will be determined in steps. The first <lb/>step is to find  p  and  u  up to  O(r-a).  Hence, the <lb/>equations to be solved at this stage are <lb/> Dg  +  2r-&apos;g  =  0(r-4 ) <lb/>Dh  +  2r-&apos;h  =  0(r-<lb/> 4 <lb/>) <lb/> with the immediate solution,12 <lb/> 11 A. Erdelyi,  Asymptotic Expansions  (Dover Publications, <lb/>Inc., New York, 1956), p. 7. The theorem is <lb/> 1~  O(f(r&apos;» ar&apos;  =  0(1~  If(r&apos;)  I  ar&apos;) , as  r  ~  co. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> &apos;2 H. Margenau and G. Murphy,  The Mathematics of <lb/>Physics and Chemistry  (D. Van Nostrand Oompany, Inc., <lb/>Princeton, New Jersey, 1943), p. 42, Eq. (2-6).</note>

			<body> <lb/> g  =  e-J2drlr{J eJ2drlrO(r-4) ar  +  po} , <lb/> = r-<lb/> 2 {J 0(r-<lb/> 2 <lb/>) dr  +  po}  =  pOr-<lb/> 2 <lb/> +  0(r-<lb/> 3 <lb/>), <lb/> and with a similar solution for  her).  Therefore <lb/> p  =  -r-&apos;  +  p&quot;r-<lb/> 2 <lb/> +  0(r-<lb/> 3 <lb/>) , <lb/> p&quot;  =  pO(u, Xk) <lb/> By a coordinate transformation  r&apos;  =  r - pO(u, Xk), <lb/> the  po 1,,2  term is eliminated. Dropping primes, we <lb/>have <lb/>Again letting <lb/>where this time <lb/> p  =  _r-<lb/> 1 <lb/> + OVa) <lb/> rJ =  uOr-<lb/> 2 <lb/> +  OV 3 ). <lb/> p  =  -r-<lb/> I <lb/> +  g(r) <lb/>u  =  uOr-<lb/> 2 <lb/> +  h(r) , <lb/> g(r) , her)  = 0  (r-3) , <lb/> (18) <lb/>and grouping all terms of  0(r-<lb/> 5 <lb/>)  under the order <lb/>symbol, we have, <lb/> Dg  +  2r-<lb/> 1 g  =  uOjjOr-<lb/> 4 <lb/> +  0(r-<lb/> 5 <lb/>) <lb/> Dh  +  2r-<lb/> 1 h  =  0(r-<lb/> 5 <lb/>) <lb/> with solutions <lb/> g  =  r-<lb/> 2 {J r2[uOjjOr-4  +  0(r-<lb/> 5  )J  dr  +  CI} <lb/> h  =  r-<lb/>2 <lb/>{J r <lb/>2 <lb/>0(r-<lb/> 5 <lb/>) dr  +  C2} , <lb/>g  =  (&apos;\r-<lb/> 2 _ <lb/> uOjjOr- a  +  0(r-4 ) <lb/> h  =  C  2  r-<lb/> 2 <lb/> +  0(r-<lb/> 4 <lb/>). <lb/> The conditions (18),  g,  h  =  0(r-<lb/> 3 <lb/>),  imply that <lb/> C,  =  C  2  = o. Hence <lb/> p  =  -r-&apos; - uOjjOr-~  +  0(r-4 ) <lb/> (19) <lb/> u  =  uOr-2  +  0(r-<lb/> 4 <lb/>). <lb/> Repeating the process, it is found that <lb/> p  =  _r- 1 _  uOijor-<lb/> 3 <lb/> +  0(r-<lb/> 5 ) <lb/> (20) <lb/> u  =  uOr-2  +  (jjOuo&apos; - !&apos;1&apos;~)r-4  +  0(r-<lb/> 5 <lb/>), <lb/> which are the desired asymptotic expressions for <lb/> p,  rJ. At this point it should be observed that, had <lb/>the more general assumption &apos;1&apos;0 =  0(r-<lb/> 5 <lb/>) <lb/> been <lb/>made, we would have obtained explicitly the forms <lb/> (19) but not the extra term in Eq. (20).  It  is evident <lb/> </body>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:48:35 <lb/></note>

			<page> 896 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> E. T.  NEWMA~  AND T. W. J. UKTI <lb/></note>

			<body> that this extra term results from the specialization <lb/> &apos;lro =  &apos;lr~r-5  +  0(1&apos;-6).  On the other hand, the <lb/>general term&quot;  0(1&apos;-6)&quot;  of &apos;lro prevents us from ob-<lb/>taining forms more explicit than Eqs. (20), as <lb/>follows: In accordance with Eqs. (20) let <lb/> p  = _1&apos;-1 _  (]&apos;0ijor-3  +  g(r) <lb/> (]&apos; =  (]&apos;°r-2  +  Qr-4  +  h(r) , <lb/> where <lb/> g(r) , her)  =  0(1&apos;-5), <lb/> and <lb/>By Eq. (9f) <lb/> Dh  +  ~  h  =  2(]&apos;:g _  2(]&apos;o~oQ  _  2(]&apos;o~oh  +  2g. Q <lb/> l&apos; <lb/> l&apos; <lb/>l&apos; <lb/> l&apos; <lb/> l&apos; <lb/> where the final term  0(1&apos;--6)  comes from  &apos;lr o .  How-<lb/>ever, the five preceding terms are seen to be ab-<lb/>sorbed into  0(1&apos;-6),  so that <lb/> Dh  +  (2/r)h  =  0(1&apos;-6). <lb/> Integration gives (the integration constant is zero), <lb/>and no new information is obtained. Similarly Eq. <lb/>(ge) fails to produce further explicit terms. <lb/>Equation (9a) is solved in the same manner as <lb/>Eqs. (ge, f). The condition (16),  ~k  =  0(1&apos;-1)  is <lb/>translated into <lb/> ~k  =  g(r) , <lb/> Putting this into Eq. (9a) yields <lb/> Dg  +  r-Ig  =  0(1&apos;-3) <lb/> ~k  =  g  = r-I{r k  +  J 1&apos;0(1&apos;-3) dr}  =  rkr-I  +  0(1&apos;-2). <lb/> The higher order terms of  ~k  are obtained similarly. <lb/>The next group of related equations involve  a,  (3,  w, <lb/> and  &apos;lr  l •  They are Eqs. (9h, i), Eq. (9b), and Eq. <lb/>(9n). &apos;lr  I  is known to be  0(1&apos;-4)  by Eqs. (17), which <lb/>allows the solutions of  a  and (3 from Eqs. (9h, i) up <lb/>to  0(1&apos;-3).  Upon performing these integrations using <lb/>the techniques shown above, it is found that <lb/> a  =  aOr-1  +  ijor:/r-2  +  0(1&apos;-3) <lb/> (3  =  {3°r-1  +  (]&apos;°iJor-2  +  o  (r-3 ) • <lb/> By use of the null rotation Eq. (8), we may set <lb/> TO  =  aO  +  (30  = O. <lb/> (21) <lb/> Therefore,  T  = a  +  (3 =  0(1&apos;-3),  which is used in the <lb/>integration of <lb/> Dw  =  pw  + (]&apos; w - T. <lb/> Here the  l&apos;  dependence is found by considering the <lb/>coupled equations, <lb/> Dw  =  pw  + (]&apos; w - T <lb/> Dw  =  pw  +  ijw - T. <lb/> Inserting orders of magnitude we get <lb/> Dw  +  r-Iw  =  (]&apos;°r-2 w  +  0(1&apos;-3), <lb/>Dw  + r-Iw =  ijor-2 w  +  0(1&apos;-3). <lb/> Formal integrations give <lb/> w =  r-I{J (]&apos;°r-Iw dr  +  0(1&apos;-1)  +  KI} <lb/> w =  r-I{J ijor-Iw dr  +  0(1&apos;-1)  +  KI}&apos; <lb/> (22) <lb/>Using the information w =  0(1),  w  =  0(1),  it is <lb/>seen that <lb/> w  =  Klr-I  +  0(1&apos;-2)  +  (]&apos;°r-I J  0(1&apos;-1)  dr <lb/> = K,r-&apos;  +  0(1&apos;-2)  +  O(ln  1&apos;11&apos;)  =  O(1n  1&apos;11&apos;) <lb/> and <lb/> w = O(1n  1&apos;11&apos;). <lb/> When these orders are again inserted in Eq. (22), <lb/>the results are <lb/> w  =  K,r-I  +  0(1&apos;-2)  +  O(ln  1&apos;11&apos;2)  =  0(1&apos;-1) <lb/> w  =  O(r-I). <lb/> Finally, when this information is fed into Eq. (22) <lb/>for the third time, we arrive at the desired result, <lb/> w  =  wOr-&apos;  +  0(r-2 ). <lb/> This is sufficient to derive the r dependence of &apos;lr  l <lb/> from Eq. (9n). We have <lb/> Wro =  w&apos;lr O . 2  +  ~k&apos;lrO.k  =  ~okqr~.kr-6  +  0(r-<lb/> 7 <lb/>) <lb/> by the initial assumptions on  &apos;lro,  Eqs. (14) and <lb/>(15). Equation (9n) becomes <lb/> D&apos;lr  l +  4&apos;lr,r-1  =  ~ok&apos;lr~.kr-6  - 4a°&apos;lr~r-6  +  0(r-<lb/> 7 <lb/>) <lb/> where &apos;lr  l  =  0(1&apos;-4)  has been used. Integration <lb/>immediately gives <lb/> </body>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:48:35 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> BEHAVIOR OF ASYMPTOTICALLY FLAT EMPTY SPACES <lb/></note>

			<page> 897 <lb/></page>

			<body> q,l =  r- 4 {J r 4 [(  -4aNf~  +  ~Ok&apos;lr~,k)r-6 <lb/> + 0(r-<lb/>7 <lb/>)] dr  +  &apos;lr~} <lb/> q,l =  &apos;r:~  +  4a°&apos;lr~ ~ ~Ok&apos;lr~.k  +  0(r- 6 ). <lb/> r <lb/> r <lb/> This information is sufficient to complete the inte-<lb/>grations of Eqs. (9h, i) and Eq. (9b). <lb/>The asymptotic  r  dependence of all the variables <lb/>may be calculated by this method. The results are <lb/>as follows: <lb/> &apos;lr 0 =  &apos;lr~r-5  +  o  (r-<lb/> 6 <lb/>) , <lb/> (23a) <lb/> &apos;lrl =  &apos;lr~r-4  +  (4a°&apos;lr~  - ~ok&apos;lr~,k)r-5  +  0(r-<lb/> 6 <lb/>), <lb/> (23 b) <lb/> &apos;lr2  =  &apos;lr~r-a  +  (2ao1i~  - ~ok&apos;lr~,k)r-4  +  0(r-<lb/> 5 <lb/>), <lb/> (23c) <lb/> &apos;lra  =  1i;r-2 - ~Ok1i;,kr-a  +  0(r-4 ), <lb/> (23 d) <lb/> &apos;lr4 =  &apos;lr:r-1 - (2a°&apos;lr;  +  ~Ok&apos;lr;.k)r-2  +  O(r-a).  (23e) <lb/> p  =  _r-1 - u&quot;a-°r-3  +  0(r-5 ), <lb/> (24a) <lb/> u  =  uOr-2  +  (a-°uo&apos; - !&apos;lr~)r-4  +  0(r-<lb/> 5 <lb/>), <lb/> (24 b) <lb/> a  =  aOr-1  +  a-°cr.&quot;r-2  +  u°a-°aor-<lb/> a <lb/> +  0(r-4 ),  (24 c) <lb/> (3= <lb/> _0  -1 <lb/> 0 <lb/>0  -2 <lb/> -a r - u ar <lb/>-(u°a-°ao  +  !&apos;lr~)r-3  +  O(r-·),  (24 d) <lb/> T  =  -(1/2ra)&apos;lr~  +  (l/6r4)(2~Ok&apos;lr~,k <lb/> - 8a°&apos;lr~  +  UO~~)  +  o  (r-<lb/> 5 <lb/>) , <lb/> (24 e) <lb/> A =  AOr-1 - a-°fJ.°r-2  +  (1/r <lb/> 3 )(uOuOAO  +  !a-0&apos;lr;) <lb/> +  OCr  -4) , (24f) <lb/> fJ.  =  fJ.°r-1 - (UOAO  +  &apos;lr;)r-2  +  (u°a-°fJ.° <lb/>-a°&apos;lr;  +  Wk&apos;lr~,k)r-a  +  0(r-4 ),  (24g) <lb/> &apos; Y = &apos;Y. - (l/2r2)&apos;lr;  +  (l/ra)(t~ok&apos;lr~  ,k <lb/> - iao~~  - !ao1i~)  +  0(r-4 ), <lb/> (24h) <lb/> p  =  pO _ (l/r)&apos;lr;  +  (l/2r2)~ok&apos;lr;,k  +  0(r-3 ).  (24i) <lb/> U  =  -(&apos;YO  +  yO)r  +  UO - (l/2r)(&apos;lr~  +  ~;) <lb/> +  (l/6r2)[(~ok&apos;lr~,k  +  rk~~.k) <lb/> - 2(aO~~  +  ao~m  +  0(r-3) , <lb/> X k  =  (1/6r3)(&apos;lr~~ok  +  ~~rk)  +  0(r-4) , <lb/> (25a) <lb/>(25 b) <lb/> ~k  =  rkr  -1 _  uO~Okr  -2  +  UO a-°rkr  -3 +  OCr  -4) , (25c) <lb/> w  =  wOr-1 - (l/r2)(uOwO  +  !&apos;lr~)  +  0(r-3 ),  (25 d) <lb/> Further terms of most of these functions can be <lb/>easily calculated. <lb/>In the above we have tacitly used a coordinate <lb/>transformation (which will be discussed) to elimi-<lb/>nate the&quot; constant&quot;  XOk. <lb/> Another coordinate transformation can be made <lb/>at this point to simplify the remaining calculations. <lb/>The metric is in the form Eq. (4), with <lb/> g&quot;&apos;&quot;  = _  (~m~n  +  ~mt) <lb/> = _  (rm~on  +  ~oTn)r  -2  + &apos;&quot; <lb/> Under the remaining coordinate transformations, <lb/>the leading term of  gm&quot;  transforms as a 2 X 2 <lb/>metric, hence it may be reduced to a conformally <lb/>flat metric. <lb/> 13 (Robinson and Trautman <lb/> 8 make  gm&quot; <lb/> conformally flat. We can only do this for the leading <lb/>term of  gmn).  Up to  0(r-3 ), g33  =  l4,  and  g34  = <lb/> g43  = O. However, since <lb/> g33 <lb/> _  2~03~03r  -2 +  OCr  -3) , <lb/> g34 <lb/> (~03~04  +  ~03~04)r-2  +  0er-3 ) , <lb/> g44  =  _2r4~J4r-2  +  0(r-3) , <lb/> we have  r <lb/> 3 =  -ir <lb/> 4 =  P(u, Xk). <lb/> At this point the remaining coordinate freedom <lb/>for the variables  x <lb/> 3  and  X4  is, 14 <lb/> (26) <lb/> The next step is to solve the nonradial equations, <lb/>which allow us to express most of the&quot; constants&quot; <lb/>of integration  aD, WO,  AO, &apos;&quot; as functions of  u&apos;  and  P. <lb/> Equation (10 1) will be done as an example of the <lb/>procedure. Explicitly it takes the form, <lb/> P,I +  Up,2  +  Xkp,k - WT,2 - ~kT,k  +  (jZ - &apos;Y  -y)p <lb/> +  2ar  + AU +  &apos;lr2 = O. <lb/> When the differentiations with respect to rare <lb/>performed and the coefficients of the various powers <lb/>of  l/r  set equal to zero/ <lb/> 5 we find <lb/>(1) the coefficient of  l/r  is identically zero, <lb/>(2) the coefficient of  1/r <lb/> 2  is  (UO - jZO),  implying <lb/> U&apos;  =  jZo, <lb/> (3) the coefficient of  1/r 3  is <lb/> (U°a-°),1  +  2u&apos;a-°(&apos;Y&apos;  +  yO) - (U·A&apos;  +  a-0~O)  = O. <lb/> This defines either &apos;Y&apos; or  A&apos;  if the other is known. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 13 L. Eisenhart,  Riemannian Geometry  (Princeton Uni-<lb/>versity Press, Princeton, New Jersey, 1960), p. 90. <lb/> I.  L. Eisenhart,  A Treatise on the Differential Geometry <lb/>of Curves and Surfaces  (Ginn and Company, Boston, Massa-<lb/>chusetts 1949), Chap, 2, Sec. 40. <lb/> 15 For example, if given the asymptotic expression <lb/> Ar- I  +  Br-&apos;l  +  Cr- 3  +  O(r-4)  = 0  (A, B, C  independent of  r), <lb/> multiplying through by  r  and taking the limit as  r  -+  co <lb/> implies  A  =  0; similarly multiplying by  r 2  implies  B =  0, etc. <lb/> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:48:35 <lb/></note>

			<page> 898 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> E. T. NEWMAN AND T. W. J. UNTI <lb/></note>

			<body> I t turns out that both  &apos;Yo  and  A  °  can be obtained more <lb/>easily from the other nonradial equations. <lb/>(4) the coefficient of  l/r <lb/> 4  is identically zero by <lb/>virtue of information from the other nonradial <lb/>equations. <lb/>In general it was found the lowest nontrivial <lb/>powers of  l/r  yielded all necessary information. <lb/>Coefficients of the higher powers duplicated this <lb/>information, but in a rather complicated form; <lb/>for example a coefficient of  l/r4  would generally <lb/>involve the sums and products of several  l/r  and <lb/> l/r2  coefficients. A few of the higher powers of  l/r <lb/> gave the same information as group III, the  1t-<lb/> derivative equations. Due to the tediousness of the <lb/>calculations, we did not carry the computation of <lb/>the coefficients of some higher powers in  l/r  to <lb/>completion. Partial cheeks were made however, <lb/>where undefined variables appeared. When the <lb/>coefficients of these undefined variables (namely, <lb/> &apos;Ir~, &apos;Ir~,  and &apos;Ir;  +  \fr;)  were collected, they were <lb/>found to vanish identically. For this reason it <lb/>appeared that no new information was forthcoming. <lb/>The nonradial equations yield the following <lb/>relations <lb/> l6 <lb/>; let &apos;V ==  alax <lb/> 3 <lb/> +  i  (l/ax <lb/> 4 <lb/>,  then <lb/> &apos;Yo  = -HlnP),I, <lb/> aO  = t.P&apos;V(ln  P), <lb/> VO  = -t.PV(ln  P.P),I, <lb/> WO  = .P[&apos;Vr/ - 20&apos;°V(lnP)], <lb/> AO =  o-°[ln  (ti°PI/2IF3/2)L, <lb/>fJ.0  =  Vo  =  -tP.P  &apos;VV In  (PF). <lb/> &apos;Ir; - \fr;  =  (.P&apos;Vwo  +  2aowo  +  o-°XO) <lb/>-(PVw&quot;  +  2a&quot;wo  +  O&apos;°AO), <lb/> &apos;Ir; =  .PVfJ.° - P&apos;VAo  +  4aoAo, <lb/> (27) <lb/> (28) <lb/> The only functions left undefined are  0&apos;0  and  P, <lb/> chosen to be the basic functions, and  &apos;Ir~,  &apos;Ir;,  and <lb/> (&apos;Ir;  +  \fr;).  (The significance of these quuntities is <lb/>explained in Sec. V). However, the propagation of <lb/> &apos;Ir~,  &apos;Ir;,  and &apos;Ir; in the  1t  direction is determined by <lb/>group III, the u-derivative equations. Equation <lb/>(lIa) is worked out as as an example. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 16 Actually the intelljrations of group I give a more com-<lb/>plicated set of expresslOns than Eqs. (23), (24), and (25), <lb/>involving the integration &quot;constant&quot;  Xok  in several places. <lb/>However, one of the nonradial equations, Eq. (lOa), indicates <lb/>that  Xoa  +  iX04  is an analytic function of X S  +  ix&apos;,  and <lb/>may be transformed away by Eq, (26). <lb/></note>

			<body> Here again the explicit powers of  l/r  are limited by <lb/>assumption (13). Hence <lb/> &apos;ltg. 1 - PV&apos;Ir~  +  (&apos;Yo  +  51&quot;)&apos;Ir~ <lb/> -2a°&apos;lr; - 30&apos;°&apos;lr;  = O. <lb/>(29) <lb/> Similarly the next two equations of group III, <lb/>Eqs. (lIb, c), yield <lb/> &apos;It;,1 - PV&apos;lt;  + 2(&apos;Y&quot; +  2,t)&apos;Ir~  - 20&apos;°&apos;lt;  =  0 (30) <lb/> &apos;It;,1  +  3(-1&apos;°  +  &quot;y&quot;)\[!; <lb/> -PV&apos;lt;  +  2a°&apos;lr; - O&apos;0&apos;lt:  = O. <lb/> The final equation of group III, Eq. (lId), yielded <lb/>identities, as far as we had carried it. <lb/> IV. COORDINATE TRANSFORMATIONS <lb/> At this point the explicit  r  dependence of the <lb/>metric, Eqs. (4) and (6), is <lb/> 2k <lb/> g <lb/> b~r-2  +  b;r- a  + ... , <lb/> -2P-P  omy2  +  d;&quot;r- 3 <lb/> where <lb/> a-I  == (In  PPL, <lb/> al  == - (&apos;Ir;  +  \fr;), <lb/> b~  == - (~OkWO  +  ~Okwo),  .•. , <lb/> d;n  ==  2(iTT m  r n  +  O&apos;0~om~&quot;&quot;),  ... <lb/>(32) <lb/> It  is of interest to find the most general coordinate <lb/>transformation which preserves every relation de-<lb/>termined up to this point. We can introduce a new <lb/>system of hypersurfaces  u &apos;  and a new tetrad exactly <lb/>as before, and arrive at all the previous results. <lb/>Moreover, this coordinate freedom can be used to <lb/>specify the  u  dependence of,  P,  and in particular <lb/>can be used to set  p. I  =  O. <lb/>These coordinate transformations may be arrived <lb/>at more simply by first considering the analogous <lb/>infinitesimal transformations,  x <lb/> P <lb/>&apos; <lb/> =  x <lb/> P <lb/> +  rp(x&apos;), <lb/> and using <lb/> &apos;8g P &apos;  ==  gP&quot; (x&quot;) - g·&apos;(x&quot;) <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:48:35 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> BEHAVIOR OF ASYMPTOTICALLY FLAT EMPTY SPACES <lb/></note>

			<page> 899 <lb/></page>

			<body> In order to preserve the form of the metric Eq. <lb/> (31), it is necessary that <lb/> ~gll  =  &apos;8g 12  =  ~glk  = 0, <lb/> ~lk  =  (b~&apos;  - b~)r-2  +  (b~&apos;  - b~)r-3  + ... , <lb/> &apos;8g 33  =  -2(P&apos;P&apos; _ PP)r-2  +  (d~3&apos;  _  d~3y3 <lb/> -6(c/i/P&apos;P&apos; - O&apos; O ijOPP)r-4  + <lb/> ~g34  =  (d~4&apos;  _  d~4)r-3  + ... , <lb/> ~g44  =  -2(P&apos;P&apos; _ PP)r-2 _  (d~3&apos;  _  d~3)r-3 <lb/> _ 6(O&apos; o &apos;ijo&apos;P&apos;P&apos; _ O&apos; O ijOPP)r-<lb/> 4 <lb/> + <lb/> Under the above restrictions, the infinitesimal <lb/>transformations reduce to <lb/> 51 =  5°\U,  Xk), <lb/>t 2  = - t~:r  +  t02(U, Xk) <lb/>- t~ab~r-l  +  !b~r-2  + ... ], <lb/> t  k  =  rk(x&quot;)  +  t:~[-2PP  o&quot;&apos;kr-l <lb/> + !  d;k r -2 _ 2O&apos; o ij o PP O&quot;,k r -3  + ... ], <lb/> where <lb/> t~~  =  S-~:, <lb/> S-~!  = - S-~:, <lb/> t02  =  pp(r~3  +  t:!.). <lb/> The restrictions on  r <lb/> k  result from the conformal <lb/>form of the leading term of  g&quot;,n&apos;,  whereas the last <lb/>equation reflects the fact that when the hyper-<lb/>surfaces  u&apos;  are chosen, there is no freedom in the <lb/>choice of  r&apos;.  As yet no restrictions exist on  rl(u,  Xk). <lb/> If this is chosen to satisfy a certain differential <lb/>equation, the coefficient of  r&apos;  in  g22&apos;,  namely, <lb/>(In  P&apos;  P&apos;).1&gt;  vanishes. <lb/>The finite transformations built up from the <lb/>infinitesimal ones take the form, <lb/> u&apos;  =  Vo  +  V_ l r-l  +  V_ 2 r-<lb/> 2 <lb/> + <lb/> r&apos;  =  R1r  +  Ro  +  R_ 1 r-l  + ... , <lb/> x&apos;&quot;  =  Y~  +  Y:\r-<lb/> 1 <lb/> + ... , <lb/> (33a) <lb/> (33 b) <lb/> (33c) <lb/> where the upper case letters are funct.ions of  u,  Xk. <lb/> The condition  gl1&apos;  = 0  leaves  Vo  unspecified but <lb/>determines the remaining  V&apos;s; <lb/> (34) <lb/> and  V  -2 etc. as functions of the  V  o ,  &apos;P,  and  0&apos;0. <lb/> The condition  l2&apos;  = 0 leaves  Ro  unspecified but <lb/>yields the remaining  R&apos;s; <lb/> the  R-l&apos; R-2  etc. being functions of  Vo, R o , P,  and  (To. <lb/> Setting  glk&apos;  =  0 determines  Y~1  as <lb/> Y:l  =  -2PP(V  O •  l )-I[V  O •  3  Y~.3  +  V  O •  4  Y~.4],  (36) <lb/> the  Y: 2 , Y: 3 ,  etc. also being determined. <lb/>Prescribing the form  g2k&apos;  and  grnn&apos;  as in Eqs. (31) <lb/> determines  Ro  as a function of the remaining free <lb/>variables, and imposes relations on  Y~, <lb/> Finally, choosing <lb/> Y~  =  Y~(xm) <lb/> Y~.3  = ±  Y~.4 <lb/> Y~.4  = =t=  Y~.3&apos; <lb/> (37) <lb/> Vo  =  J(x <lb/> 3 <lb/>,  X <lb/> 4 <lb/>)  J  (Pp)1I2 du  +  K(x <lb/> 3 <lb/>,  ;r4), <lb/> (38) <lb/> where  J  and  K  are arbitrary functions of  x <lb/> 3  and  X4, <lb/> eliminates the coefficient of  r&apos;  in  g22&apos; <lb/> (In  P&apos;P&apos;).l  = O. <lb/> The tetrad transformation Eq. (7) can be used to <lb/>make  P  ==  IPieilf&gt;  real as follows, <lb/>Since m <lb/> k  =  fkr-lo~  +  O(r-2 ),  f3 <lb/> by choosing  C  = -cp,  we have <lb/> P&apos;  = IPi. <lb/> This, together with (In  pi  P I ).1  = 0, yields <lb/> P&apos;  =  P&apos;(x&quot;&apos;&apos;). <lb/> P, <lb/> (39) <lb/> This has the effect of immensely simplifying most <lb/>of the previous relations. Equations  (27)  and  (28) <lb/> become (dropping primes) <lb/> &quot;,0 = 0, <lb/> c!  =  !VP, <lb/> pO  =  0, <lb/> }.L0  = -p <lb/> 2  VV  In  P, <lb/> (&apos;It; - 1f~)  =  p <lb/> 2 [V(WO/P) - V(wo/P)l <lb/> &apos;It;  =  -PV(p <lb/> 2  VV  in  P) <lb/> _  p3(ij~dP2), <lb/> (40a) <lb/> (40 b) <lb/> (40 c) <lb/> (40  d) <lb/> (40 e) <lb/> (40£) <lb/> (40g) <lb/> (40 h) <lb/> (40i) <lb/> (35) The u-derivative equations (29) and (30) become <lb/> </body>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:48:35 <lb/></note>

			<page> 900 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> E. T. NEWMAN AND T. W. J. UNTI <lb/></note>

			<body> &apos;l&apos;;.1 - P&apos;V&apos;l&apos;; - 20&apos;°&apos;l&apos;;  =  0 <lb/> &apos;l&apos;;.1 - p <lb/>2 <lb/>&apos;V(&apos;l&apos;;/P)  +  0&apos;°a-~11  = O. <lb/> V. RESULTS AND DISCUSSION <lb/> The metric has the form <lb/>0: 1 : 0 <lb/>0 <lb/> __ 1 ___ 1 ____ _ <lb/> 1 <lb/> 1 <lb/>22 1 <lb/> 2k <lb/> 1 <lb/> g i g <lb/> --1 ---1 -----<lb/> 0: : <lb/> 1 <lb/> 2k  1 <lb/> mn <lb/> 1  g i g <lb/> 0: : <lb/> with the coordinate dependence, <lb/> 22 <lb/> g <lb/> +  ipf  &apos;V(~~)  +  &apos;V(~~) <lb/> _  6P4&apos;V(~;)&apos;V(ffi;)}  -2 +  o  (r-<lb/> 3 <lb/>) , <lb/> l3 _r-<lb/> 2  Re {f}  +  r-<lb/> 3  Re Ih}  +  O(r-<lb/> 4 <lb/>), <lb/> l4  =  r-2  1m 111 +  r-<lb/> 3  1m  Ih}  +  O(r- 4 ), <lb/> where <lb/> p  =  P(x <lb/> 3 <lb/>, X4), <lb/> f  ==  2p 4 &apos;V(a-o /p2), <lb/> h  ==  4P[i&apos;l&apos;~  +  p <lb/> 3 0&apos;0&apos;V(a-o /p 2  )J, <lb/> l3 _2p2 r -2  +  2P2(O&apos;o  +  a-°)r-<lb/> 3 <lb/> (40j) <lb/>(40k) <lb/>(401) <lb/>(41a) <lb/>(41 b) <lb/>(41c) <lb/>(41  d) <lb/> (41 e) <lb/> -60&apos;°a-°p2r-4  +  O(r-<lb/> S <lb/>), <lb/> (4lf) <lb/>(41g) <lb/> l4 _2p2 r -2 _ 2P2(O&apos;o  +  a-°)r-<lb/> 3 <lb/> -60&apos;&quot;a-°p2r-4  +  O(r-<lb/> S <lb/>). <lb/> (41  h) <lb/> More terms could easily have been calculated;  l2 <lb/> to  O(r- 4 )  and  g&quot;k  to O(r-<lb/> S <lb/>). <lb/> The u-derivative equations  (40j,k,l),  derived from <lb/>the Bianchi identities, give the propagation of the <lb/>tetrad components of the Weyl tensor as follows, <lb/> &apos;l&apos;~.1  - &apos;V(P\f/~)  - 30&apos;&quot;&apos;l&apos;;  = 0 <lb/> (42a) <lb/> &apos;l&apos;~.1  -P&apos;V&apos;l&apos;; - 20&apos;&apos;&apos;&apos;Ir;  = 0 <lb/>(42 b) <lb/> &apos;l&apos;;.1  +  0&apos;°a-~11  - p 2 &apos;V(&apos;l&apos;;/P)  = 0 (42c) <lb/>where <lb/>With these results (also considering the higher order <lb/>terms not explicitly written out) the solution of the <lb/>initial value problem can be stated simply. <lb/>The first piece of data that is chosen is &apos;l&apos; 0 on an <lb/>initial null-surface denoted by  Uo  subject to the <lb/>condition that  limT~&quot;&quot;  (r <lb/>5 <lb/>&apos;l&apos;0)  &lt;  00. For convenience, <lb/>we use a slightly stronger condition in the form <lb/> % =  &apos;l&apos;~r-5  +  O(r-<lb/> 6 <lb/>).  It  should be noted that in <lb/>this paper we do not specify &apos;l&apos;o in complete detail, <lb/>and hence, the data are correspondingly not com-<lb/>pletely specified. The second piece of data is given <lb/>on the timelike world-tube taken at spatial infinity. <lb/>On this tube we choose  0&apos;0  ==  limr~&quot;&quot;  (r 2 0&apos;) , as an <lb/>arbitrary function of  u, x <lb/> 3 <lb/>,  and  X4.  The last data <lb/>are given on the two-dimensional surface at infinity <lb/>which is defined by the intersection of the null surface <lb/> Uo and the world-tube. On this two-surface we give <lb/> &apos;l&apos;~  == lim r4&apos;l&apos;t, <lb/>&apos;l&apos;;  +  11; == lim  r <lb/> 3 (&apos;l&apos;2  +  112) <lb/> r-~co <lb/> and <lb/>as functions of  x <lb/> 3  and  X4. <lb/> This information, used with the three differential <lb/>equations (42), completes the solution for the metric <lb/>tensor and Riemann tensor up to the completeness of <lb/>the data on  uo.  (If, for example, we had taken <lb/>on  Uo,  there would have been an additional equation <lb/>for the  u  derivative of each  &apos;l&apos;~.)  However, aside <lb/>from the incompleteness of the Uo data and the <lb/>consequent incompleteness of the solution (we could <lb/>give additional data and carry the solution as far as <lb/>desired) the problem of finding the metric tensor <lb/>for empty space, flat at infinity, appears to be <lb/>solved.  It  should be pointed out that if &apos;l&apos;o is not <lb/>an analytic function of  (l/r),  it has not been proven <lb/>that the solution of Eq. (lla), which yields the <lb/>propagation of &apos;l&apos;o off the hypersurface, is unique, <lb/>(although it is generally believed that the solution <lb/>is unique). <lb/>An interesting special case which we will consider <lb/>is  0&apos;0  initially zero, then varying in an arbitrary <lb/>manner, and eventually becoming zero again. By <lb/>multiplying Eq. (42c) by  p-2  and integrating over <lb/> X3  and  X4,  we obtain after a few operations <lb/> [J  ;2  (&apos;l&apos;;  +  0&apos;0  a-~t)  dx 3 dx <lb/> 4 <lb/>]  , I <lb/> J <lb/> 1  ° - °  d  3  d  4 +  J  &quot;,(&apos;l&apos;;)  d  3  d  4 <lb/> =  p20&apos;.IO&apos;,1 XX <lb/> V <lb/> P  X X. <lb/> (43) <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:48:35 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> BEHAVIOR OF ASYMPTOTICALLY FLAT EMPTY SPACES <lb/></note>

			<page> 901 <lb/></page>

			<body> Remembering that the integral is over the closed <lb/>two-surface with metric <lb/> fli;  =  lim  (r <lb/> 2 g <lb/> ii )  =  p2 a <lb/> ii <lb/> (the element of area is p-2 dx 3 dx 4 ), it is easy to see <lb/>that the last term on the right is zero. We <lb/>now integrate over u, and using the fact that <lb/> I  p-21T : 1U : 1  dx <lb/> 3  dx <lb/> 4  is positive and that  ITo  vanishes <lb/>at the two end points, we have <lb/> J  p-~;  dx <lb/> 3 dX41::  &gt;  0; <lb/>(44) <lb/>in other words the quantity  M  == - I p-<lb/> 2 &apos;Ir; dx <lb/> 3 dx <lb/> 4 <lb/> decreases. We can re&quot;Tite this as <lb/> M  = - J  Re &apos;1&apos;;  dS, <lb/> (45) <lb/> because from Eqs. (40g) and (40d) , 1m  &apos;Ir;  = 0 <lb/>when  ITo  = O. In the case of the Schwartzchild solu-<lb/>tion  M  is proportional to the mass, from which <lb/>we generalize and say  M  is always proportional to <lb/>the mass. <lb/> s <lb/> The remaining coordinate freedom is given by <lb/>transformations of the form Eqs. (33). As  r  -7 co, <lb/> the leading terms of these transformations are <lb/> u&apos;  =  J(x <lb/> 3 , x <lb/> 4 <lb/> )u  +  K(x <lb/> 3 <lb/>, X4), <lb/> r&apos;  =  [l/J(x <lb/> 3 <lb/>, x <lb/> 4  )Jr, <lb/>(46) <lb/> x k ,  =  yk(X <lb/> 3 , X4), <lb/> where  J  and  K  are arbitrary functions of  x <lb/> 3 <lb/>,  X4. <lb/> The  yk  must satisfy <lb/> Y~3  = ±  y~4 <lb/> Y~4  =  =F  Y~3 <lb/> (47) <lb/> and the yk are otherwise arbitrary functions of <lb/> x <lb/> 3 <lb/>, X4.17  The transformation law of the basic variable <lb/> P(x <lb/> k <lb/>)  is easily obtained by considering the trans-<lb/>formation of the  1/r2  term in  l3  or  l4; <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 17 In a recent preprint of R. Sachs, there is a detailed <lb/>discussion of the transformations, Eq. (46). <lb/></note>

			<body> p,2  =  p 2 r 2 det  IY&apos;::.I. <lb/> (48) <lb/>The transformation <lb/> p,2  =  p2 det  I  Y~nl <lb/> represents a two-dimensional conformal coordinate <lb/>transformation of a two-surface, with metric tensor <lb/> gO;;  =  p <lb/> 2 <lb/> a <lb/> ii ,  onto itself. 14 Neglecting this and <lb/>considering only  p&apos;  =  pr\  we see that Eq. (48) <lb/>represents the transformation of one surface into <lb/>another. Equation (46) indicates that  J(xa, x <lb/> 4 <lb/>) <lb/> may have neither zeros nor infinities, hence from <lb/>Eq. (48) we can conclude that  p&apos;  must have the <lb/>same number of zeros and infinities as  P.  (We are <lb/>assuming that  P,  which is part of the initial data, <lb/>is given not in patches but over the entire surface.) <lb/> It  thus appears that many topological properties of <lb/>the surface are retained under the transformation <lb/>Eq. (48). This leads to several interesting topological <lb/>questions. For example: What is the simplest surface <lb/>that may be obtained by Eq. (48) from a given <lb/>surface? <lb/>Such difficulties can be avoided by taking as part <lb/>of the initial data a relatively simple surface such <lb/>as a sphere,17 or possibly a torus, and restricting Eq. <lb/>(48) to the identity  P&apos;  =  P;  in other words, by <lb/>requiring J2  =  det  [y.,::[. <lb/> As a closing remark, it may be pointed out that <lb/>Newman and Tamburino <lb/> 18 have found exact solu-<lb/>tions corresponding to a special case  (&apos;Iro  = 0) of the <lb/>asymptotic solutions found here. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/> The authors wish to thank Dr. A. Janis, Dr. R. <lb/> Penrose, Dr.  I.  Robinson, Dr. J. Stachel, L. Tam-<lb/>burino, and Dr. A. Trautman for valuable sugges-<lb/>tions and discussions. We are particularly indebted <lb/>to Dr. R. Sachs for a detailed criticism of the <lb/>manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote"> 18 E. T. Newman and L. A. Tamburino, J. Math. Phys. 3, <lb/>902 (1962), following paper. <lb/> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. Downloaded to IP: <lb/>137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:48:35 </note>


	</text>
</tei>
