<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/>www.elsevier.com/locate/npe <lb/> Analysis of the 11 B( 7 Li, 7 Be) 11 Be reaction at <lb/>57 MeV in a microscopic approach <lb/> F. Cappuzzello <lb/> a, *  , H. Lenske <lb/> b , A. Cunsolo <lb/> a,c , D. Beaumel <lb/> d , <lb/>S. Fortier <lb/> d , A. Foti <lb/> c,e , A. Lazzaro <lb/> a,c , C. Nociforo <lb/> a , <lb/>S.E.A. Orrigo <lb/> a,c , J.S. Winfield <lb/> a <lb/> a  INFN–Laboratori Nazionali del Sud., Via S. Sofia 44, 95123 Catania, Italy <lb/> b  Institut für Theoretische Physik, Universität Giessen, Heinrich–Buff-Ring 16, D-35392 Giessen, Germany <lb/> c  Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia, Università di Catania, Via S. Sofia 64, 95123 Catania, Italy <lb/> d  Institut de Physique Nucléaire, IN2P3-CNRS, 91406 Orsay cedex, France <lb/> e  INFN–Sezione di Catania, Via S. Sofia 64, 95123 Catania, Italy <lb/> Received 25 June 2003; received in revised form 26 March 2004; accepted 30 March 2004 <lb/>Available online 23 April 2004 <lb/> Abstract <lb/> The 11 B( 7 Li, 7 Be) 11 Be charge exchange reaction has been studied at an incident energy of 57 <lb/>MeV. Spectra were measured at forward angles, θ  cm  35  •  . The good energy resolution (∼50 keV) <lb/>allowed the identification of transitions both to the 7 Be (3/2  −  , gs) and 7 Be(1/2  −  , 429 keV) <lb/>exit channels and hence the direct measurement of the ratio of the respective cross sections and <lb/>angular distributions. Besides the bound ground and first excited state of 11 Be several low lying <lb/>excitations just above the neutron threshold are observed. A structure seen at E  *  = 9.4 MeV with <lb/>FWHM ∼7 MeV is compatible with the spin dipole resonance (SDR). The data are analysed in <lb/>a many-body approach. For the projectile transitions shell model results are used. In order to <lb/>account properly for the special features of the weakly bound 11 Be system the target transitions <lb/>are described microscopically by Hartree–Fock–Bogoliubov (HFB) and quasi-particle random phase <lb/>approximation (QRPA) theory. The HFB ground state densities and the QRPA transition densities, <lb/>respectively, are used in folding calculations for the optical potentials and transition form factors. <lb/>Spectra and β-decay transitions strengths are reasonably well described. The measured cross section <lb/>are well reproduced by one-step direct charge exchange distorted wave born approximation (DWBA) <lb/>calculations. A dominance of unnatural parity transitions is found. This is explained in terms of the <lb/>spin transfer behaviour of the nucleon–nucleon isovector interaction at low bombarding energy. <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote"> * Corresponding author. <lb/> E-mail address: cappuzzello@lns.infn.it (F. Cappuzzello). <lb/>0375-9474/$ – see front matter  2004 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.nuclphysa.2004.03.221 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<page> 31 <lb/></page>

			<front>   2004 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved. <lb/> PACS: 21.10.-k; 21.10.Pc; 21.30.Fe; 21.60.Jz; 23.20.En; 23.40.Hc; 24.10.Eq; 24.50.+g; 25.70.kk; 27.20.+n <lb/> Keywords: NUCLEAR REACTIONS  +11  B( +7 Li,  +7  Be), E = 57 MeV; measured particle spectra, σ (E, θ).  +11  Be <lb/>deduced levels, configurations. Quasiparticle RPA analysis. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> Over the last decades the (n, p) and (p, n) charge exchange reactions (CEX) on <lb/>nuclear targets have been the major source of information on charge changing nuclear <lb/>isovector excitations. Because of their selectivity they also have provided much significant <lb/>information on nucleon–nucleon isovector interactions [1,2]. Heavy ion charge exchange <lb/>reactions are useful for obtaining complementary information on states which are not easily <lb/>excited with the elementary probes. This includes the excitation of high spin states in <lb/>the highly peripheral heavy ion collisions and the selection of Fermi and Gamow–Teller <lb/>transitions by an appropriate choice of projectile-target combinations or selecting suitable <lb/>projectile transitions, respectively. <lb/>One aim of such reaction studies is to derive information on β-decay strength <lb/>distributions which otherwise are not accessible. However, non-elastic nuclear reactions <lb/>typically proceed at a finite, albeit small, momentum transfer q while β-decay is a process <lb/>at vanishing q, at least in the Fermi-approximation with q  M W  → ∞, where M W  is the <lb/>mass of the W boson. Investigations for nucleon induced CEX at intermediate energies <lb/>(E lab  &gt; 100 MeV) are supporting, on an empirical level, a close relationship between <lb/> β-decay probabilities and nuclear charge exchange cross sections at low momentum <lb/>transfer [3,4]. Such relationship has been observed, although more approximately, also <lb/>for heavy ion charge exchange reactions in certain cases [1]. <lb/>An unwanted but unavoidable complications for heavy ion induced charge exchange <lb/>reactions are admixtures from more complicated reaction mechanisms, typically given by <lb/>sequential transfer or inelastic processes of second or higher order [5–9]. The competition <lb/>of one-step direct and two-step sequential transfer charge exchange processes are discussed <lb/>in detail, e.g., in Ref. [9]. <lb/>A typical heavy-ion CEX reaction investigated in recent years is ( 7 Li, 7 Be). In general <lb/> 7 Li beams are available in many laboratories at a broad range of energies. Also it is usually <lb/>a simple task to identify the 7 Be ejectiles using standard detection equipment. On the other <lb/>hand the non-zero values of the transferred angular momentum between the 7 Li 3/2  − <lb/> ground state and the 7 Be 3/2  −  ground or 1/2  −  first excited state makes the spectroscopy <lb/>somewhat complicated. <lb/>The competition between direct one-and two-step sequential mechanisms for the <lb/>( 7 Li, 7 Be) reaction has been discussed for long time [10–15]. Different arguments have <lb/>been used in order to determine the conditions under which direct process dominates. It <lb/>appears that these conditions depend on the particular nucleus studied, and sometimes on <lb/>the particular excited state. However, at least the intermediate transfer channel involving <lb/> 8 Be is particle unstable, thus having a reduced overlap with the bound initial and final <lb/>projectile states. In general, calculations based on the assumption of direct CEX give <lb/></body>

			<page> 32 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<body> angular distributions with a steeper decrease at backward angles than the experimental <lb/>data indicating the increased importance of higher-order processes at large momentum <lb/>transfer [9,11,12]. For ( 7 Li, 7 Be) reactions it was shown by Clarke and Cook [11] that the <lb/>unresolved theoretical ambiguities inhibit clear statements on the significance of two-step <lb/>contributions. Typically, one finds that the agreement with data is hardly improved. <lb/>Quantitative studies of the two-step reaction channels in ( 7 Li, 7 Be) reactions are <lb/>missing, mainly because reliable methods for treating three-body continuum transfer <lb/>channels are lacking. However, the total two-step transfer contribution in the ( 7 Li, 7 Be) <lb/>reactions can be expected to be small at low energies (below 10 MeV/u) and forward <lb/>angles, as indicated by the good results of data analyses based on one-step DWBA <lb/>calculations, see, e.g., Refs. [11,12]. This is the view also taken in the present analysis. <lb/>A distinct feature of the ( 7 Li, 7 Be) reaction is the significant population of the first <lb/>excited 1/2  −  (and only) bound state of 7 Be at 0.43 MeV. If properly separated in the <lb/>experiments, the relative yields measured in the 7 Be (gs −0.43 MeV) doublets can be <lb/>directly connected to the ratio of spin–flip to non-spin–flip interaction [16–19]. Thereby <lb/>important information on the spin structure of the isovector nucleon–nucleon interaction <lb/>is obtained. This connection to the spin-transfer probability is most clearly evident if a <lb/>direct mechanism transferring a small amount of linear momentum driven by a central <lb/>force is the dominant contribution to the cross section [2]. Such conditions are most easily <lb/>accomplished at forward angles and small reaction Q-values. Although the best realization <lb/>is obtained at incident energies well above the Coulomb barrier, comprehensive studies can <lb/>be done already at energies not far from the Coulomb barrier. <lb/>The separation of the 7 Be doublet has been achieved in experiments at energies <lb/>above 20 MeV/u through the coincident detection of 0.43 MeV γ -rays [18,19]. This <lb/>technique is particularly useful when the energy resolution or the natural width of the <lb/>peaks does not allow the separation of the 7 Be doublet in the inclusive spectra. However, <lb/>the coincidence requirement reduces the yield and introduces supplemental uncertainties <lb/>in the measurement of the cross sections. At low incident energy, with the 7 Be ejectiles <lb/>detected by silicon telescopes or magnetic spectrometers [12,20], the separation of the <lb/>doublet is obtained in the inclusive spectra. In particular, the use of a magnetic spectrometer <lb/>allows the exploration of the important region at very forward angles, including 0  •  . This <lb/>technique is therefore very interesting for the spectroscopy of light exotic nuclei, where <lb/>narrow resonances are often present well beyond the particle emission threshold and a <lb/>high resolution measurement of the energy of the excited states can provide a fundamental <lb/>test of modern theories of nuclear structure. <lb/>In Ref. [20] the above technique has been used to explore the spectrum of 11 Be up to <lb/>15 MeV excitation energy. The resolution obtained (∼ 50 keV) allowed the identification <lb/>of the single particle excitations below 2 MeV and a group of narrow resonances in the <lb/>continuum, some of which were observed for the first time. A QRPA approach, based on <lb/>two quasi-particle excitations, gives an appropriate description of the resonances observed <lb/>below 2 MeV, while it fails in describing the fragmentation of the strength distribution <lb/>observed at higher excitation energy. This fragmentation cannot be associated to single <lb/>particle excitations and needs more sophisticated interpretation, such as the ones within <lb/>the dynamical core polarisation model of Refs. [21,22]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<page> 33 <lb/></page>

			<body> In this paper a deeper insight into both the spectroscopy of 11 Be and of the ( 7 Li, 7 Be) <lb/>reaction mechanism beyond that discussed in [20] will be given. The paper is organised as <lb/>follows. In Section 2 some of the experimental data on the 11 B( 7 Li, 7 Be) 11 Be reaction <lb/>at 57 MeV, not previously presented in Ref. [20], are shown. In Section 3 a new <lb/>microscopic approach, based on the QRPA theory, to the charge exchange transitions <lb/>in exotic nuclei is described. Thereafter the calculated response functions are compared <lb/>with the experimental spectra. In Sections 4 and 5 the CEX cross sections are calculated <lb/>within the framework of the optical model and the DWBA theory and compared with the <lb/>measured angular distributions. Finally the main results obtained in this work and the future <lb/>developments of the theory and the experiments are discussed in Section 6. <lb/> 2. Experimental results <lb/> The experiment was performed at the IPN-Orsay Tandem laboratory. A 7 Li  +++  beam <lb/>at 57 MeV was focused on a 95% enriched 11 B self supporting target about 130 µg/cm 2 <lb/> thick. Additional measurements were done with a 12 C target of about 100 µg/cm 2 . The <lb/> 7 Be ejectiles were detected by the split-pole magnetic spectrometer. The focal plane <lb/>detector consisted of a position and angle sensitive multi-wire drift counter, a proportional <lb/>counter and stopping plastic scintillator. Further details of the experiment may be found in <lb/>Refs. [20,23]. <lb/>In Ref. [20] the shapes of the excitation energy spectra were discussed and compared <lb/>to the results of QRPA calculations of transition level densities. In the spectra the three-<lb/>body phase space, taken from Ref. [24], was normalized to the high excitation energy of <lb/>each spectrum. This procedure, although useful to analyze centroids and widths of narrow <lb/>resonances, is less adequate for a precise estimation of the cross sections and for the <lb/>analysis of broad resonances at high excitation energy. Instead in this work, the typical <lb/>three-body phase space of Ref. [24] for the 7 Be +  10 Be + n exit channel is transformed <lb/>into 11 Be excitation energy and normalized in order to fit the high excitation energy region <lb/>of the spectrum at 18  •  (the most backward angle measured). The result of this procedure <lb/>for the spectrum at 9  •  is shown on the left panel of Fig. 1. In order to reduce statistical <lb/>fluctuations, this spectrum is compressed by a factor 20 compared to the high resolution <lb/>one, at the same angle, shown in Ref. [20]. <lb/>All the measured spectra are consistent with the existence of a broad bump with an <lb/>average centroid and width of 9.4 ± 0.5 MeV and 7.0 ± 0.5 MeV, respectively. The error <lb/>bars on the measured parameters depend on the uncertainty in the fit procedure due to <lb/>the excitation of the doublet in 7 Be and the estimated three-body phase space. These <lb/>values agree with those (centroid energy between 9 and 10 MeV and width around 7 MeV) <lb/>previously measured in the 11 B(d, 2 He) 11 Be reaction at 70 and 270 MeV [25,26] for the <lb/>spin dipole resonance (SDR). A broad structure centred at 9 MeV has also been observed <lb/>in the 11 B(t, 3 He) 11 Be reaction at 127 MeV/u [27]. <lb/>After peak integration and kinematic transformation the absolute cross sections in the <lb/>center of mass reference frame are extracted. It is interesting to compare these quantities <lb/>for the 11 B( 7 Li, 7 Be) 11 Be and the 12 C( 7 Li, 7 Be) 12 B reactions at 0  •  , similarly to what Sakai <lb/>et al. did in Ref. [25] (see Table 1). In the ( 7 Li, 7 Be) reaction the distribution of the counts <lb/></body>

			<page> 34 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<body> Fig. 1. Excitation energy spectra of 11 B( 7 Li, 7 Be ) 11 Be reaction at 57 MeV. (a) Spectrum at 9  •  . The histogram <lb/>is obtained by compressing of a factor 20 that presented in Ref. [20]. The solid line is the result of a peak fitting <lb/>analysis. The dashed and the dotted lines represent the 3-body phase space and the Gaussian model of the broad <lb/>resonance at 9.4 MeV, respectively. The structure around 15 MeV is due to a fault in one of the wires of the <lb/>focal plane detector and has no physical meaning. (b) Detail of the fitted structure around 4 MeV in the spectrum <lb/>at 2.5  •  . The peaks marked with an asterisk refer to the excitation of 7 Be at 0.429 MeV. The shaded histogram <lb/>represents the normalized background of 12 C( 7 Li, 7 Be) 12 B reaction, the continuous line is the sum of 3-body <lb/>phase space and the broad resonance as in panel (a). <lb/> over the 7 Be doublet must be considered. Consequently, the total transition strength for <lb/>each of the 11 Be and 12 B states is derived by integrating over both the peaks. <lb/>In Ref. [25] the GT strength for 11 Be is extracted from the integrated counts of the 0.32, <lb/>2.67 and 3.89 MeV states, while for the 12 B only the ground state is considered. The energy <lb/>resolution of the present work allows, for the first time in a CEX experiment, to separate <lb/>in the 11 Be spectra the doublet at 3.89 and 3.96 MeV, as shown, for example, on the right <lb/>panel of Fig. 1. In Ref. [28] the state at 3.89 MeV is assigned to be as 3/2  +  , while that <lb/>one at 3.96 MeV as 3/2  −  . As a consequence we consider this latter state as relevant for <lb/>GT excitation, rather than integrating the doublet, as previously done [25–27]. The non-<lb/>zero value of the linear momentum transfer is considered to have very similar effect on <lb/> 11 Be and 12 B cases, since the bombarding energy, the scattering angle and the reaction <lb/> Q-value are very similar. The β-decay strengths B(GT) and B(SD), listed in Table 1 for <lb/>Gamow–Teller (GT) and spin dipole (SD), are calculated in the framework of the QRPA <lb/>theory discussed in Section 3. A useful quantity that can be evaluated is the reduced cross <lb/>section  <lb/>  , defined as the ratio between the CEX reaction cross section measured at 0  •  and <lb/>the β-decay strengths for the same transition [3]. <lb/>A linear relation between measured cross sections and the associated β-decay strengths <lb/>holds for the GT transitions. This is shown in Table 1, where the reduced cross sections <lb/>for GT transitions to the 11 Be and 12 B differ less than the experimental uncertainty. The <lb/>calculated B(GT) strength distribution for the 12 C gs  →  11 B transition is almost entirely <lb/>concentrated in one sharp peak, corresponding to the transition to the 12 B ground state. <lb/>For 11 B →  11 Be case, even if the different GT transitions are separated in the experiment, <lb/>it was not possible to disentangle them in the calculations and the obtained B(GT) was <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<page> 35 <lb/></page>

			<body> integrated over 4 MeV. This introduces only a minor source of uncertainties in the reduced <lb/>cross section if the integrated B(GT) is compared with the sum of the cross sections at <lb/>0.32, 2.67 and 3.96 MeV, as discussed before. The values of the reduced cross sections are <lb/>about a factor 40 smaller than those obtained via the (n, p) reaction at 96 MeV [29] and <lb/>the (t, 3 He) at 127 MeV/u on 11 B target [27]. This may be explained by the larger linear <lb/>momentum transferred in the ( 7 Li, 7 Be) reaction at 8 MeV/u (q = 0.55 fm  −1  at 2 MeV <lb/>excitation energy and 0  •  ) compared to the previously mentioned cases, e.g., q = 0.14 fm  −1 <lb/> at 2 MeV excitation energy and 0  •  for (n, p). For an approximate estimation of this effect <lb/>on the cross sections one could consider the relation σ (q) ∝ exp(− <lb/> 1 <lb/>3  q  2  r  2  ), which is <lb/>valid at intermediate energy and low momentum transfer [2]. The ( 7 Li, 7 Be) cross section <lb/>is reduced by about one order of magnitude compared to the (n, p) one, assuming typical <lb/>values of r  2  = 16.7 fm 2 for (n, p) and 20 fm 2 for ( 7 Li, 7 Be) [2]. The comparison of <lb/>distorted and plane wave Born approximation calculations in the approach of Section 4 <lb/>has shown a further reduction of about two for the ( 7 Li, 7 Be) cross section due to the <lb/>stronger distortions [2] produced by the optical potential for the heavy ions compared to <lb/>the (n, p) case. Of course, these analyses, being valid in the intermediate energy domain, <lb/>are here only intended as guideline to explain the order of magnitude of the measured cross <lb/>sections. The fact that this is possible within a factor two or less represents an interesting <lb/>empirical observation which certainly will help to estimate experimental yields in future <lb/>experiments. <lb/>Proportionality relations, similar to those discussed above for GT transitions, hold also <lb/>for the SD ones. They involve the excitation of the 11 Be ground state and 1.77 MeV state, <lb/>and partly the broad resonance, while the states at 1.67, 2.62, 4.5 MeV and the higher <lb/>excitation energy up to 15 MeV are relevant for the 12 B case. These comparisons may be <lb/>affected by noticeable uncertainties, mainly connected to the subtraction of the three body <lb/>phase space and to the contribution from the strengths different than SD ones. Nonetheless, <lb/>as argued in Ref. [25] an accuracy within 20% may be obtained, providing that the data <lb/>for the 12 B and 11 Be cases are analyzed in a consistent manner, as is done here. For the <lb/>broader resonances a supplemental source of uncertainty comes from the estimation of <lb/>three-body phase space to be subtracted. In the calculations for the SD excitations in 11 Be, <lb/>two sharp peaks appear at 0 and 2 MeV together with a broad continuous distribution up to <lb/>15 MeV, so it was possible to make a comparison with the single resonances observed in <lb/>the experiment. For the case of 12 B, on the other hand, only a global comparison is done. <lb/>As shown in Table 1 the reduced cross sections for different SD transitions built on <lb/>the 12 C and 11 B ground states agree within the uncertainty, supporting the idea that <lb/>a proportionality law holds also for the SD transitions. The broad bump in the 11 Be <lb/>spectrum deviates from this behavior well beyond the uncertainty of this analysis. This <lb/>may be because of an increased strength for transitions with higher multipolarities at higher <lb/>excitation energy. Such an effect may be more pronounced for 11 Be, being excited from <lb/> 11 B with a 3/2  −  ground state, as compared to the production of 12 B from 12 C(0  +  , gs). In <lb/>the latter case, in fact, the strength of a fixed transition operator is limited, especially for <lb/>high multipolarity, by the reduced density of levels with the unique allowed values of spin <lb/>and parity, as compared to the broader phase space accessed by the same operator in the <lb/>case of the non-zero spin of 11 B ground state. <lb/></body>

			<page> 36 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<body> Table 1 <lb/>Cross sections for ( 7 Li, 7 Be) reaction on 11 B and 12 C targets at 57 MeV and 0  •  and β-decay strengths for GT <lb/>and SD transitions. The uncertainty of the cross sections for narrow resonances is estimated to be around 20%. <lb/>The last two columns refer to the (d, 2 He) data taken from Ref. [25] <lb/>GT <lb/>( 7 Li, 7 Be gs ) + ( 7 Li, 7 Be 0.43 ) <lb/>( d , 2 He) <lb/>Target J i <lb/> J f <lb/> E x  (MeV) <lb/>dσ/dω <lb/>(µb/sr) <lb/>B(GT) <lb/>(QRPA) <lb/> ˆ <lb/> σ  GT <lb/> (µb/sr) <lb/>B(GT) <lb/>(shell model) <lb/> ˆ <lb/> σ  GT <lb/> (µb/sr) <lb/> 12 C <lb/>0  + <lb/> 1  + <lb/> 0.0 <lb/>235 <lb/>1.01 <lb/>233 <lb/>0.98 a <lb/> 17.9 <lb/> 11 B <lb/>3/2  −  1/2  −  , 3/2  −  , <lb/>5/2  − <lb/> 0.32, 2.67, <lb/>3.96 <lb/>149 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>199 b <lb/> 0.73 c <lb/> 20.9 <lb/>SD <lb/>( 7 Li, 7 Be gs ) + ( 7 Li, 7 Be 0.43 ) <lb/>( d , 2 He) <lb/>Target J i <lb/> J f <lb/> E x  (MeV) <lb/>dσ/dω <lb/>(µb/sr) <lb/>B(SD) (fm 2 ) <lb/>(QRPA) <lb/> ˆ <lb/> σ  SD <lb/> (µb/sr) c <lb/> B(SD) (fm 2 ) <lb/>(shell model) <lb/> ˆ <lb/> σ  SD <lb/> (µb/sr) c <lb/>12 C <lb/>0  + <lb/> 0  −  , 1  −  , 2  − <lb/> 1.67, 2.62, <lb/>4.5–15 <lb/>570 <lb/>44.3 <lb/>7 4 .9 <lb/> 3 1 .0 <lb/> 9 .0  d <lb/> 1/2  + <lb/> 0.0 <lb/>36 <lb/>3.22 <lb/>68.6 <lb/> 11 B <lb/>3/2  −  3/2  +  , 5/2  + <lb/> 1.77 <lb/>75 <lb/>7.55 <lb/>60.9 <lb/>2 4 .4 <lb/> 8 .24  e <lb/> 9.4 <lb/>1067 <lb/>40.2 <lb/>162.9 <lb/> a See Ref. [30]. <lb/> b Adding the state at 3.89 MeV one obtains a value of 268 for the reduced cross section. <lb/> c The reduced cross sections are scaled with the quantities r  gs   2 , where r  gs is the QRPA ground state <lb/>transition density radius. This is equal to 2.41 fm for the 12 C case and 2.47 fm for the 11 B one. <lb/> d In Ref. [25] the B(SD) is taken from Ref. [31] and refers to the interval between 2 and 30 MeV. <lb/> e In Ref. [25] the B(SD) is taken from Ref. [32] and refers to the interval between 2 and 23 MeV. <lb/> As mentioned in the introduction, the separation of the 7 Be doublet of states allows <lb/>a direct estimation of the spin transfer component of the isovector nucleon–nucleon <lb/>interaction. In reference [18,19] it was shown that the ratio G = σ (  7 Be ex )/(σ (  7 Be ex  ) + <lb/> σ (  7 Be gs  )), where σ (  7 Be gs  ) and σ (  7 Be ex  ) are the cross sections for the transition to the <lb/> 7 Be ground and first excited state respectively, should be 0.46 for pure GT transitions and <lb/>zero for Fermi ones. This is valid in the case of a small transfer of linear momentum, of <lb/>negligible contribution of the tensor force and for a direct exchange reaction mechanism. <lb/>All of these conditions are best satisfied at very forward angles. In the case of the <lb/> 11 B gs  →  11 Be transitions, the 3/2  −  spin-parity nature of 11 B ground state does not impose <lb/>strong selection rules on spin transfer for every transition. In contrast for the 12 C gs  →  12 B <lb/>unnatural transitions, the 0  +  nature of 12 C ground state selects more efficiently spin transfer <lb/>dynamics. <lb/>As shown in Table 2, the extracted values of G around 0  •  for the transitions to all <lb/> 11 Be states are definitely different from 0, and close to the 0.46 limit of GT transitions <lb/>in the projectile. DWBA calculations for the reaction cross sections show (Section 4) a <lb/>dominant direct mechanism at forward angles, however, with a non-negligible role of the <lb/>tensor force. This in principle makes the situation discussed here somewhat different from <lb/>that of Refs. [18,19]. Nevertheless it will be shown in Section 4, that the tensor force has a <lb/>minor effect on the G factor at 0  •  . Therefore our results do indicate the dominance of spin <lb/>transfer even though the projectile transitions are not pure GT. <lb/>In the same table the G factors for the transitions from the 12 C ground state to the <lb/>excited states of 12 B are also reported. It is interesting to note that some of these deviate <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<page> 37 <lb/></page>

			<body> Table 2 <lb/>Values of G measured at around 0  •  for ( 7 Li, 7 Be) reaction on 11 B and 12 C targets. σ G  represent the total <lb/>uncertainty in the G parameter <lb/> 11 Be <lb/> 12 B <lb/> J π a <lb/> 1/2  +  1/2  −  3/2  + <lb/> 5/2  + <lb/> 3/2  −  3/2  +  3/2  −  – <lb/>1  + <lb/> 2  + <lb/> 2  − <lb/> 1  − <lb/> 1  −  , 2  −  , 4  − <lb/> E x  [MeV] 0 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>1.77 <lb/>2.67 <lb/>3.89 <lb/>3.96 <lb/>6.05 0 <lb/>0.95 1.67 2.62 4.5 <lb/> G (θ ∼ = 0  •  ) 0.38 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>0.46 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>0.47 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.56 0.15 0.17 0.40 0.33 0.34 <lb/> σ G <lb/> 0.04 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.03 0.03 0.03 0.06 0.07 0.03 <lb/> a From Refs. [28,30]. <lb/> from the behaviour observed at higher bombarding energies [13,28,29]. In particular, the <lb/>results at higher energy indicate a prevalent GT nature of the transition to the 1  +  state and <lb/>a minor contribution of spin transfer for the transition to the 2  +  . On the contrary, at the <lb/>energy of the present data, the G parameters for the two transitions to 12 B do not show a <lb/>distinguishable difference and exhibit an intermediate value between 0 and 0.46. A possible <lb/>interpretation of this fact is the increased role of the two-step mechanisms for the transition <lb/>to the well bound 12 B (see, e.g., Ref. [9]) that hide, in this case, the simple relation between <lb/>the G factor and the spin–flip probability. <lb/>In Figs. 2–5 the experimental angular distributions for the 11 B( 7 Li, 7 Be) 11 Be and <lb/> 12 C( 7 Li, 7 Be) 12 B are shown for both the population of the ground and first excited state <lb/>of 7 Be. These distributions are in general weakly oscillatory and peaked towards forward <lb/>angles. However, in detail they differ considerably from each other in regard to shape, <lb/>especially at very forward angles. This behaviour is not unusual for CEX reactions <lb/>involving light nuclei and is generally related to a direct process which dominates at very <lb/>forward angles, superimposed on a flat two-step cross section which contributes especially <lb/>at larger angles. In addition the many possible values of angular momentum transferred, <lb/>especially in the 11 B( 7 Li, 7 Be) 11 Be reaction, combine to smear out oscillations in the <lb/>observed angular distributions. <lb/> 3. Nuclear structure aspects of charge exchange transitions in exotic nuclei <lb/> Microscopic methods have been an important tool in understanding the reaction <lb/>dynamics and the nuclear structure aspects of the (n, p) and (p, n) reactions, as well as <lb/>of the complementary heavy ion counterparts. The detailed description of the nuclear <lb/>transition matrix elements in terms of interactions and consistently derived wave functions <lb/>together with the explicit reference to nucleon–nucleon interactions, well tested either <lb/>in free space or in the nuclear medium via structure calculations, have proven in <lb/>the past to remove most of the uncertainties [5,9,13]. Here we follow these former <lb/>experiences by applying microscopic many-body methods in analysing the structure <lb/>and reaction aspects of the present data. Similar to previous applications shell model <lb/>results are used for the A = 7 systems. For the only slightly heavier A = 11 target-like <lb/>nuclei HFB and QRPA many-body methods are already applicable. Here, HFB theory <lb/>is used to obtain an appropriate single particle basis for the 11 B ground state and the <lb/></body>

			<page> 38 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<body> Fig. 2. Angular distributions for the transitions to the 11 Be ground and the excited states at E  *  = 0.32, 1.77, 2.67, <lb/>3.41, 3.89, 3.96, 6.05 and 9.4 MeV, connected to the 7 Be ground state. <lb/> particle and hole spectra entering into the QRPA description of the charge exchange <lb/>excitations. QRPA theory represents the appropriate class of next-order diagrams by <lb/>complete resummation of particle–hole type loop diagrams for two quasi-particle (QP) <lb/>configurations. <lb/>For stable nuclei both the structure and the reaction approaches have been applied <lb/>before, e.g., for the low energy ( 7 Li, 7 Be) reaction [33] and the ( 12 C, 12 B) [12], <lb/>( 13 C, 13 N) [34] and ( 42 Ca, 42 Sc) reactions [35] in the range of E/A between 10 and <lb/>100 MeV/u. In these references and in [5] the theory of nuclear excitations of β  ±  -type <lb/>in stable nuclei applications to heavy ion CEX reactions, including also sequential two-<lb/>step transfer processes, have been discussed. Here, the main emphasis is on the special <lb/>properties of neutron-rich exotic nuclei such as 11 Be, where in this case the existence of a <lb/>single neutron halo and the level inversion are the most outstanding features. In this section <lb/>the theoretical description of the nuclear structure aspects and the reaction dynamics of <lb/>CEX processes will be discussed subsequently. <lb/> 3.1. Description of CEX transitions in unstable nuclei <lb/> It is generally agreed that the multi-configuration shell model is an appropriate approach <lb/>to the structure of light mass nuclei, A  16. In fact, also here we will use shell model <lb/>transition amplitudes for the ( 7 Li, 7 Be) transitions, taken from Ref. [12]. However, the <lb/>shell model typically relies on empirical matrix elements assumed to behave regularly <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<page> 39 <lb/></page>

			<body> Fig. 3. Angular distributions for the transitions to the 11 Be ground and the excited states at E  *  = 0.32, 1.77, 2.67, <lb/>3.41, 3.89, 3.96, 6.05 and 9.4 MeV, connected to the 7 Be first excited state. <lb/> and smoothly as functions of mass and charge. That assumption must no longer hold far <lb/>from stability. Irregular behavior must be expected from the weak binding of the valence <lb/>particles and because of admixtures of continuum states. Both effects will cause rapid <lb/>variations of matrix elements hardly being accounted for by extrapolations from the stable <lb/>region. For the weakly bound nuclei we therefore choose a mean-field approach which <lb/>properly takes care of modification of matrix elements and related spectral observables due <lb/>to the irregular behavior of wave functions close to the drip-line. Also, such an approach <lb/>is rather independent of pre-selections on the active shells. However, in order to keep <lb/>the calculations on a feasible level we have to restrict the complexity of configurations <lb/>to the lowest level, namely to 1 particle–1 hole (1p–1h) states, or, in a more general <lb/>notation, to 2 quasi-particle (2QP) states. Since we are going to describe charge exchange <lb/>transitions converting protons into neutrons and vice versa the 2QP states are given by <lb/>angular momentum coupled proton–neutron configurations <lb/> Q <lb/>  † <lb/> J M (j  p  j  n  ) = <lb/> α <lb/>  † <lb/> j  p <lb/> ⊗ α <lb/>  † <lb/> j  n <lb/> J M <lb/> , <lb/> (1) <lb/>where α <lb/>  † <lb/> j  = u j a <lb/>  † <lb/> j  + v j  ˜ <lb/> a j  are the one quasi-particle (1QP) state operators obtained by a <lb/>Bogoliubov transformation with coefficients obeying u  2 <lb/> j  + v  2 <lb/> j  = 1 from the normal state <lb/>operators a <lb/>  † <lb/> j  . In practice, the 1QP states are obtained self-consistently by means of HFB <lb/></body>

			<page> 40 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<body> Fig. 4. Angular distributions for the transitions to the 12 B ground and excited states, connected to the 7 Be ground <lb/>state. The angular distributions for the transitions to the 12 B state at 3.76 and 3.39 MeV with 7 Be excited are <lb/>summed (see text). <lb/> calculations. We have to take into account the possibility of a coherent superposition of <lb/>such states which leads us to use a QRPA description <lb/> Ω <lb/>  † <lb/> J M (c) = <lb/> j  p  j  n <lb/> x <lb/> c <lb/>J (j  p  j  n  )Q <lb/>  † <lb/> J M (j  p  j  n  ) − y <lb/> c  * <lb/> J (j  p  j  n  ) ˜ <lb/> Q J M (j  p  j  n  ) <lb/> (2) <lb/>including the contributions from ground state correlations by the terms proportional to y  *  . <lb/>The ansatz of Eq. (2) is general in the sense that the state operators Ω  † describe both <lb/> β  +  and β  −  transitions. The QRPA approach—and refinements thereof—is widely used in <lb/>current β-decay studies, e.g., [36]. Recent applications of an extended version of QRPA, <lb/>including the coupling of up to 3 phonon configurations (i.e., 6QP sates), to the newly <lb/>discovered 2  −  twist mode in 58 Ni and the dipole pygmy resonances in 208 Pb are found <lb/>in [37,38], respectively. <lb/>A special feature of weakly bound systems is their closeness to the single particle <lb/>continuum which, for our purposes, implies that Eq. (2) in fact includes an integral over <lb/>the unbound proton and neutron states continuously distributed in energy. A theoretically <lb/>appropriate approach which is able to account for continuum effects in observables is the <lb/>Green function formulation of QRPA. This has been previously applied, e.g., in Ref. [39], <lb/>to the description of the response of, medium and heavy nuclei in inelastic scattering at <lb/>intermediate energies and, in Ref. [40], to exotic nuclei as light as 8 B. The propagation <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<page> 41 <lb/></page>

			<body> Fig. 5. Angular distributions for the transitions to the 12 B ground and excited states connected to the 7 Be first <lb/>excited state. <lb/> of the states Ω  † is described by the QRPA Green function G(ω) [39,41]. From the Dyson <lb/>equation for G(ω) one finds the response functions for an external one-body field F [39,41] <lb/> R(ω, F ) = <lb/> 1 <lb/> π <lb/> Im0|F <lb/> †  G(ω)F |0 <lb/> (3) <lb/>given as expectation values over the QRPA ground state |0. A convenient way to <lb/>determine R(ω, F ) is to solve the coupled-Dyson equations for G(ω) by matrix inversion <lb/>in coordinate space as in Ref. [39] where the original approach of Ref. [42] was extended in <lb/>various aspects. Similar to Ref. [39] we use a 2QP interaction obtained from a G-matrix but <lb/>including additional density dependent pieces in order to reproduce properly the saturation <lb/>properties of infinite symmetric and asymmetric nuclear matter [43–45]. The continuum <lb/>part of the QRPA Green functions are constructed by representations in terms of a set of <lb/>discretized continuum single particle HFB wave functions. <lb/>Of practical interest are solutions of Eq. (3) for multipole operators of Fermi-type, F ∼ <lb/> F <lb/> ± <lb/> LM  = τ  ±  r L Y LM  , and the Gamow–Teller type operators F ∼ F <lb/> ± <lb/> J M  = τ  ±  r L  [Y  L  ⊗ σ ]  J M  , <lb/>where J = L, L ± 1 and τ  ±  are the isospin ladder operators. The (reduced) matrix <lb/>elements of these operators determine the β-decay properties of nuclear states being related <lb/>to the longstanding question to what extend hadronic charge exchange reaction provide <lb/>complementary information to β-decay measurements [1,2]. From Eq. (3) we also obtain <lb/>immediately the sum rules <lb/> S n <lb/> F <lb/> ± <lb/>  = <lb/> R <lb/> ω, F <lb/> ± <lb/> ω <lb/> n dω, <lb/> (4) <lb/></body>

			<page> 42 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<body> Table 3 <lb/>State dependent pairing for single proton and neutron orbitals, occupation probabilities and mean field energies <lb/>are listed <lb/>Protons <lb/>Neutrons <lb/>Single particle (N L J ) 1s 1/2 <lb/> 1p 3/2 <lb/> 1p 1/2 <lb/> 2s 1/2 <lb/> 1d 5/2 <lb/> 1s 1/2 <lb/> 1p 3/2 <lb/> 2s 1/2 <lb/> 1p 1/2 <lb/> N  j  [%] <lb/>0.99748 0.74746 0.00665 0.00012 0.00027 0.99999 0.99991 0.00005 0.00014 <lb/> E mf  [MeV] <lb/> −35.673 −19.636 −11.755 −1.894 −0.169 −31.017 −6.812 −0.458 −0.163 <lb/> where n = 0, 1 denote the non-energy (NEWSR) and energy weighted (EWSR) sum rules, <lb/>respectively, which, in practice, are of special importance. In particular, the difference of <lb/>the NEWSR for β  ±  transitions lead to the well known Ikeda sum rules [46]. They relate <lb/>the dynamical response of a nucleus to ground state properties, namely differences of <lb/>radial moments of the proton and neutron ground state densities. In fact, in Ref. [47] these <lb/>relations were used for the dipole case to obtain information on the neutron skin thickness <lb/>in Sn isotopes. <lb/> 3.2. QRPA response functions <lb/> Single neutron and proton orbitals with the 10 Be core are calculated up to 100 MeV <lb/>excitation energy and L = 6 by enclosing the 10 Be system in a box with a radius of <lb/>60 fm. This large radius was chosen such that the proton and neutron single particle <lb/>continua are represented with sufficiently high densities of states, also resolving accurately <lb/>single particle potential resonances, e.g., in the d  5/2 neutron channel. Proton and neutron <lb/>states are obtained from HFB calculations for 10 Be with an interaction obtained in local <lb/>density approximation from a G-matrix as in Ref. [43], complemented by additional three-<lb/>body terms such that nuclear and neutron matter properties are correctly described. The <lb/>pairing problem was solved with a density dependent zero-range interaction obtained from <lb/>the Bonn-B [48] singlet-even NN potential. For 10 Be the HFB calculation gives a total <lb/>binding energy per particle of B/A = 6.36 MeV which agrees reasonably well with the <lb/>experimental value B/A = 6.50 MeV [49]. In fact, the HFB results show that pairing does <lb/>not play a significant role in the A = 10 nuclides. The 10 Be HFB potentials are then used <lb/>as reference for the mean-fields of the valence proton and neutron states in 11 B and 11 Be <lb/>by adjusting the depths of the potentials such that the experimental separation energies <lb/>were reproduced. In this way we account for energy shifts in single particle states from <lb/>core polarization which is known to play an important role in 1p-shell nuclei, e.g., causing <lb/>the parity inversion in 11 Be(1/2  +  , gs) [50]. The spectrum of bound single particle states <lb/>entering into the QRPA calculations is given in Table 3. <lb/>The dissipation of the QRPA states into higher order configurations was taken into <lb/>account by dispersive self-energies. The imaginary parts are obtained phenomenologically <lb/>from optical potentials [36,39]. The real parts were calculated by dispersion theory, thus <lb/>assuring analyticity. A subtracted dispersion relation was used leaving the ground state <lb/>unaffected by the polarization self-energies by choosing the Fermi level as the subtraction <lb/>point. The results of the QRPA calculations are plotted in Fig. 6, for multipolarities <lb/> J π  = 0  ±  , . . . , 4  ±  , both for natural and unnatural parities. Displayed are the QRPA level <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<page> 43 <lb/></page>

			<body> density distributions (per energy), obtained by normalizing the QRPA multipole response <lb/>functions to the NEWSR of the same operator: <lb/>d(ω, F ) = R(ω, F )/S  0  (F ), <lb/> dω d(ω, F ) = 1. <lb/>(5) <lb/>The folding with the experimental energy resolution of about 50 keV at FWHM is <lb/>included. In both cases narrow states are found at energies below or slightly above the <lb/>neutron separation energy in 11 Be. At higher energies the response functions are rather <lb/>featureless. The broad structures are mainly due to the continuum decay widths of the 11 Be <lb/>states with minor contributions from the imaginary part of the dispersive self-energies. <lb/>The response functions to the Fermi and Gamow–Teller like operators were calculated <lb/>according to the Eq. (3), both for the 11 B →  11 Be and the 12 C →  12 B transitions. These <lb/>allow a comparison with known experimental B(GT) [26,27,29,51] and calculated B(GT) <lb/>and B(SD) within shell model [30–32]. A B(GT) = 1.01 is obtained in our calculations <lb/>for the 12 C →  12 B transition, in agreement with the experimental value (B(GT) = 0.99 <lb/> ±0.01) from Log f t values of Ref. [51]. For the 11 B →  11 Be case we obtain B(GT) = 0.75 <lb/>to be compared with contradictory experimental results of 0.47 ± 0.08 from Ref. [27], <lb/>0.58 ± 0.06 from Ref. [29] and 0.85 ± 0.05 from Ref. [26]. Our calculated B(GT) and <lb/>B(SD) are typically slightly higher than the equivalent from shell model [30–32]. That is <lb/>probably a consequence of the broad excitation energy range (80 MeV) spanned by our <lb/>QRPA approach allowing the excitation of two quasi-particle configurations from both the <lb/>valence shells and the core, while in the shell model calculations only nucleons close to <lb/>the valence shells are involved. <lb/>The microscopic transition form factors are described in a folding model. The 11 B → <lb/> 11 Be target transitions were described by the QRPA theory discussed above. The majority <lb/>of the 11 B →  11 Be transitions lead to states above the 11 Be neutron emission threshold. <lb/>Hence, we are confronted with a new situation where the final states no longer form a <lb/>discrete spectrum but are given by spectral distributions, as in Fig. 6. The special features <lb/>introduced by continuum effects and spectral functions in general are well accounted for <lb/>by the QRPA Green function formulation discussed above. Eq. (3), in fact, could be used <lb/>to calculate the direct charge exchange cross sections provided we would construct the <lb/>appropriate hadronic transition operator from the in-and outgoing waves and the NN <lb/>interaction. <lb/>As discussed in Ref. [39] for inelastic excitations a more practical approach for <lb/>continuum transitions is to use one-body transition densities (OBTD) <lb/> ρ(ω, r) = <lb/> 1 <lb/> π <lb/> Im0|F <lb/> †  G(ω) ˆ <lb/> ρ|0/ <lb/> R(ω, F ) <lb/> (6) <lb/>defined in terms of the one-body density operator  <lb/>  and weighted by the matrix elements <lb/>of beta-decay multipole operators F . Obviously, the presently available schemes for shell <lb/>model calculations are not able to provide reliable descriptions of such excitations into <lb/>the continuum. Fermi and Gamow–Teller results were checked by the non-spin–flip and <lb/>spin–flip Ikeda sum rules [46] which were fulfilled by better than 95% when integrating <lb/>the strength up to 30 MeV excitation energy. <lb/></body>

			<page> 44 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<body> Fig. 6. QRPA level densities for charge exchange transitions from 11 B(3/2  −  , gs) to the excited states of 11 Be. <lb/> 4. Optical model and DWBA approach to heavy-ion CEX reactions <lb/> 4.1. Choice of interaction <lb/> In view of the fact that we are considering a reaction involving nuclei of rarely known <lb/>structure and unknown interaction potentials we have to take special care also with <lb/>respect to the choice of interactions in the initial and final channels and for the charge <lb/>exchange reaction process. In order to keep uncertainties on a controllable level we use <lb/>NN interactions whose momentum structure and other properties are compatible with the <lb/>interactions used in the structure calculations. Taking advantage of the low incident energy <lb/>we can extrapolate the density dependent G-matrix interaction into the region above the <lb/>particle threshold, as, e.g., by Khoa and von Oertzen in Ref. [44]. Since the G-matrix, in <lb/>fact, is a K-matrix we can retrieve the full complex NN T -matrix t  NN in momentum space <lb/>by means of the relation [48] <lb/> t  NN  (k, q) = K(k, q) − iπ <lb/> d <lb/> 3  q <lb/>  K(k, q <lb/>  )δ <lb/> E(q) − E(q <lb/>  ) <lb/> t  NN  (q <lb/>  , q)/(2π) <lb/> 3 <lb/> (8) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<page> 45 <lb/></page>

			<body> Table 4 <lb/>Total reaction cross sections, volume integrals J  U,W  (in MeV fm 3 ) per nucleon and root-mean-square radii <lb/> R  U,W  (in fm) for the 7 Li +  11 B (in) and 7 Be +  11 Be (out) optical potentials used in the calculations. The <lb/>symbol U and W refer to the real and imaginary part of the potential, respectively <lb/> σ R <lb/> (in) <lb/> σ R <lb/> (out) <lb/> J U <lb/> (in) <lb/> J W <lb/> (in) <lb/> J U <lb/> (out) <lb/> J W <lb/> (out) <lb/> R  U   i <lb/> R  w   i <lb/> R  U   O <lb/> R  w   O <lb/> 1285.3 <lb/>1379.7 <lb/> −278 <lb/>−166 <lb/>−260 <lb/>−170 <lb/> 3.91 <lb/>3.67 <lb/>3.82 <lb/>3.80 <lb/>Table 5 <lb/>Volume integrals for the nucleus–nucleus interaction at vanishing density <lb/>Central (S, T ) interactions in (A, B) rest frame: <lb/>TNN at p = 0 [MeV fm 3 ] <lb/>(00) <lb/>(01) <lb/>(10) <lb/>(11) <lb/>DIRECT <lb/>130.1 <lb/>239.3 <lb/>154.1 <lb/>175.8 <lb/>EXCHANGE <lb/> −834.4 <lb/> 6 0 .9 <lb/> −15.1 <lb/>−6.2 <lb/> Tensor (S, T ) interactions in (A, B) rest frame: <lb/>TNN at p = 0 [MeV fm 5 ] <lb/>(10) <lb/>(11) <lb/>DIRECT <lb/> −17.8 <lb/>−150.1 <lb/> EXCHANGE <lb/>89.8 <lb/> −30.7 <lb/> given here for the &quot; half off-shell &quot;  T -matrix where E(q) is the NN on-shell energy as <lb/>defined by the incident energy. Obviously, the density dependence of the G- or K-matrix, <lb/> respectively, implies a density dependent T -matrix. Numerical calculations are simplified <lb/>by expressing the density dependence in a separable local density approximation (LDA), <lb/>as, e.g., in Refs. [43,44]. <lb/>The charge exchange interaction was taken from the isovector parts of the D3Y G-<lb/> matrix [43] including spin-dependent and spin-independent direct and exchange central <lb/>interactions together with second rank tensor. The NN spin–orbit interactions were <lb/>neglected. Hence, we are using the same interaction as in the HFB ground state calculations <lb/>and the QRPA description of excitations thus retaining the consistency of structure and <lb/>reaction calculations. The global properties of the interaction in the various spin–isospin <lb/>channels (S, T ) are summarized in Table 5. <lb/>Inspecting of the interactions in momentum space one notices that the tensor force <lb/>cannot be neglected in the region around a momentum transfer of about 1 fm  −1  , where <lb/>the reaction mostly takes place. The exchange components are treated here in the local <lb/>momentum approximation (LMA), e.g., in Ref. [43,44]. They are especially important for <lb/>the isoscalar central force, indicating a pronounced momentum dependence and therefore <lb/>non-locality in that channel, but play only a minor role for the isovector interactions. <lb/> 4.2. Optical model description of elastic scattering for incident and exit channel <lb/> Low-energy optical potentials are known for the stable 7 Li nuclide for elastic scattering <lb/>on stable target nuclei, e.g., Refs. [52,53]. But such information can obviously not be <lb/>obtained empirically for the scattering of unstable nuclei as in the 7 Be +  11 Be exit <lb/></body>

			<page> 46 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<body> channel. Because reliable empirical optical potentials for 7,11 Be are not known we use <lb/>a double folding approach. For consistency this was done also for the 7 Li and 11 B <lb/>incident channel. Since density dependent effects were found to be small for elastic <lb/>scattering at forward angles, we used the free nucleon–nucleon T -matrix, derived by <lb/>Franey and Love [54] for energies at and above E  lab  = 50 MeV, for calculating the real <lb/>and the imaginary part of the optical potentials in the incident and the exit channels <lb/>in the double folding approach in lowest order impulse approximation. The nucleon– <lb/>nucleon T -matrix t  NN  (p, E) at the current incident energy was obtained by a spline <lb/>extrapolation in momentum space. Including isoscalar (τ = 0) and isovector (τ = 1) <lb/>central interactions t τ <lb/> NN  (p, E), respectively, and accounting for exchange contributions <lb/>by the already mentioned LMA we find by double folding over the Fourier transforms <lb/>of the isoscalar and isovector projectile and target ground state densities ρ τ <lb/>a,A (p), <lb/> respectively, <lb/> U  opt  (r, E) = <lb/> τ =0,1 <lb/> d <lb/> 3 p ρ <lb/> τ <lb/>a (p)ρ <lb/> τ <lb/>A (p)t <lb/> τ <lb/> NN  (p, E)e <lb/> ipr /(2π) <lb/> 3  . <lb/> (9) <lb/>In addition, the semi-classical model of Bonaccorso and Carstoiu [55] was used to <lb/>estimate the long range contributions to the optical potential due to the coupling of halo <lb/>wave functions to the breakup channels. According to this model the imaginary part of this <lb/>potential is simply related to the properties of the halo wave function through the break-up <lb/>probability. The real part, accounting for the extra polarization induced by the halo at long <lb/>range, is obtained through a dispersion relation. The resulting breakup potentials, including <lb/>those for 7 Be +  11 Be at E = 57 MeV, are discussed in Ref. [55]. <lb/>In Table 4 the global properties of these potentials are displayed. The larger value for <lb/>the reaction cross section in the outgoing channel σ R  (out) compared with the ingoing one <lb/> σ R  (in) reflects the halo structure of the 11 Be gs density distribution, extending much further <lb/>into space than the 11 B one. In addition, the long range potential accounting for break-up in <lb/>the outgoing channel slightly increases σ R  (out). Indeed, both the imaginary and real part <lb/>of this break-up potential were found to give a contribution to the calculated CEX cross <lb/>sections, improving the agreement with the data. <lb/> 4.3. Reaction mechanism of the ( 7 Li, 7 Be) CEX reactions <lb/> The reaction dynamics of heavy-ion CEX processes at low and intermediate energies <lb/>have been investigated extensively before in Refs. [9,33,52,56]. While the competition <lb/>of one-step direct and two-step transfer CEX routes was found to be important for <lb/>reactions with an incident 12 C projectile [9] this seems not be the case in ( 7 Li, 7 Be) <lb/>reactions [11–13]. Although a study of comparable detail as in Ref. [9] for the 12 C <lb/>projectile is missing—and is not the purpose of this paper—the suppression of two-step <lb/>processes in ( 7 Li, 7 Be) reactions, also found in previous work [13,56], is very likely related <lb/>to the fact that unbound intermediate states are involved. Since the overlap of their wave <lb/>functions with bound, localized configurations is reduced the two-step amplitudes as a <lb/>whole seem to be of very small magnitude. <lb/>In order to give stronger support to these qualitative arguments—and neglecting the <lb/>completely unsolved normalization problem due to the largely unknown spectroscopy <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<page> 47 <lb/></page>

			<body> Fig. 7. Estimate for the two-step transfer contributions to the 11 Be gs  +  7 Be gs exit channel via intermediate 6 Li <lb/>and 12 B channels. The angular distribution is normalized arbitrarily to the data point at the largest scattering <lb/>angle. <lb/>Fig. 8. Estimate for the two-step transfer contributions to the 11 Be(0.32) +  7 Be gs exit channel via intermediate <lb/> 6 Li and 12 B channels. The angular distribution is normalized arbitrarily to the data point at the largest scattering <lb/>angle. <lb/></body>

			<page> 48 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<body> of the intermediate channels—we have performed two-step transfer charge exchange <lb/>calculations for some selective cases. In Fig. 7 we show results for the sequential &quot; neutron-<lb/>pickup–proton-stripping &quot; two-step route via intermediate states in 6 Li and 12 B and leading <lb/>to the ground states of 11 Be and 7 Be, respectively. Two-step results for the same route but <lb/>ending instead in the first excited state in 11 Be at 0.32 MeV are displayed in Fig. 8. <lb/>In both cases the angular distribution was normalized arbitrarily to the data point at the <lb/>largest scattering angle, which should be considered as the upper limit for the expected two-<lb/>step strength. It is seen that the shape of the angular distributions is obviously flatter than <lb/>the measured ones. Hence, we might conclude that at least at forward angles (θ cm  &lt; 15  •  ) <lb/>the direct one-step processes will exhaust the measured cross sections to a reasonable <lb/>degree. <lb/>Under these assumptions the reaction mechanism is considered here as being predom-<lb/>inantly given by a one-step direct process, for which DWBA theory as discussed in Sec-<lb/>tion 4.2 is providing the appropriate descriptions. In Ref. [20] we argued how the QRPA <lb/>theory successfully describes the 11 Be single particle strength including the ground and the <lb/>excited states at 0.32 and 1.77 MeV. Results, obtained with microscopic form factors and <lb/>response functions and using the HIDEX code [57], are presented below. <lb/> 4.4. The CEX reaction form factors and cross sections <lb/> The transition form factors are obtained by folding the nucleon–nucleon (NN) <lb/>interaction in momentum space with the Fourier transforms of the β  ±  charge exchange <lb/>transition densities, either the shell model OBTD for the projectile (ρ  τ <lb/>λa  ) [12] or the QRPA <lb/>OBTD of Eq. (6) for the target nucleus (ρ  τ <lb/>λA ), respectively <lb/> F (r, E) = <lb/> d <lb/> 3 p ρ <lb/> τ <lb/>λa (p)ρ <lb/> τ <lb/>λA (p)t <lb/> τ <lb/> NN  (p, E)e <lb/> ipr /(2π) <lb/> 3  . <lb/> (10) <lb/>As in the optical potentials exchange effects due to anti-symmetrization are included <lb/>in the local momentum approximation (LMA), see, e.g., Refs. [32,43,44]. Here, we also <lb/>included transitions into the 7 Be(1/2  −  ) excited state at E x  = 429 keV as they are clearly <lb/>visible in the data. <lb/>These form factors are then used in DWBA calculations to obtain the double differential <lb/>direct charge exchange cross section <lb/>d 2  σ <lb/> dΩ dE <lb/> = <lb/> λ(aA) <lb/> S λA (E) <lb/> dσ  λ(aA) <lb/> dΩ <lb/>(11) <lb/>summed over all multipolarities λ(aA), the discrete projectile states a and weighted by the <lb/>target response functions per energy S A (E). The reduced DWBA cross sections calculated <lb/>with the form factors, Eq. (10), are denoted by dσ  λ(aA) /dΩ. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<page> 49 <lb/></page>

			<body> 5. Discussion of results <lb/> 5.1. Angular distributions to bound and unbound states in 11 Be <lb/> In Figs. 9–11 the angular distributions for the transitions to the analysed 11 Be states <lb/>are shown for 7 Be gs and 7 Be 0.43 states, respectively. The results are in agreement with <lb/>the measured cross sections for the 11 Be ground state (Fig. 9) and the excited state at <lb/>1.77 MeV (Fig. 11), while for the state at 0.32 MeV (Fig. 10) the calculated cross section <lb/>underestimates the data by about a factor between two and three. The likely reason for this <lb/>irregular behaviour lies in the optical model potential as will be discussed in Section 5.3. <lb/>A sudden change of the reaction mechanism for the different states of 11 Be would be <lb/>puzzling. At backward angles (θ cm  &gt; 20  •  ) a systematic underestimation of strength may <lb/>indicate a non-negligible contribution from the two-step processes in this angular region <lb/>(see Figs. 7 and 8). It is interesting to note that in the past the calculated cross sections for <lb/>the ( 7 Li, 7 Be) reaction typically have required large scaling factors to agree with the data, <lb/>see, for example, Refs. [10,11,13,19]. <lb/>Instead the present calculations describe on average the data surprisingly well without <lb/>the need for introducing large scaling factors. This rather satisfying overall agreement is <lb/>mainly due to two reasons; namely, the realistic description of the single particle continuum <lb/>effects and the large 2QP configurations space in solving the QRPA Dyson equations <lb/>and the use of a density dependent in-medium NN interaction [43]. In particular the <lb/>D3Y G-matrix interaction of Ref. [43] seems to account in a better way for the situation <lb/>encountered at low energy in a halo systems, as considered in this article, than the often <lb/>used Love and Franey interaction [54]. <lb/> Fig. 9. Angular distributions for the 11 B( 7 Li, 7 Be gs ) 11 Be gs and 11 B( 7 Li, 7 Be * ) 11 Be gs transitions. The calculated <lb/>cross sections are not scaled. <lb/></body>

			<page> 50 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<body> Fig. 10. Angular distributions for the 11 B( 7 Li, 7 Be gs ) 11 Be 1/2  −  and 11 B( 7 Li, 7 Be * ) 11 Be 1/2  −  transitions. The <lb/>calculated cross sections are not scaled. <lb/>Fig. 11. Angular distributions for the 11 B( 7 Li, 7 Be gs ) 11 Be 5/2  +  and 11 B( 7 Li, 7 Be * ) 11 Be 5/2  +  transitions. The <lb/>calculated cross sections are not scaled. <lb/> 5.2. Central and tensor interactions <lb/> The cross sections are not simply determined by only the central direct interac-<lb/>tion but the tensor becomes crucial, as illustrated, for example, in Fig. 12 for the <lb/> 11 B( 7 Li, 7 Be gs ) 11 Be gs and the 11 B( 7 Li, 7 Be 0.43 ) 11 Be gs transitions. <lb/>The results of Fig. 12 confirm the importance of the tensor interaction in heavy ion <lb/>charge exchange reactions, in line with the findings in Ref. [11]. Note how the contribution <lb/>of the tensor force to each of the two angular distributions in Fig. 12 is almost the same <lb/>at zero degree, thus having a minor influence on the G ratio as mentioned in Section 2. <lb/>It is worthwhile to investigate in more detail the contribution to the cross sections of <lb/>the different combinations of angular momentum. These are shown in Figs. 9–11 for the <lb/> 11 B gs  →  11 Be couplings. It is evident that the unnatural parity transitions account for the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<page> 51 <lb/></page>

			<body> Fig. 12. Contribution of the central and tensor forces on the angular distribution for the 11 B( 7 Li, 7 Be gs ) 11 Be gs <lb/> transition on the left, and the 11 B( 7 Li, 7 Be 0.43 ) 11 Be gs one on the right. The calculated cross sections are not <lb/>scaled. <lb/> major part of the observed cross sections. In particular the 2  −  coupling dominates for <lb/>the 11 Be ground state, the 1  +  for the 0.32 MeV and the 2  −  and 4  −  for the 1.77 MeV, <lb/>indicating more favourable conditions for the mechanism of nucleonic spin transfer. This <lb/>is confirmed by the comparison of the different angular momentum couplings in the <lb/> 7 Li →  7 Be transitions. These findings reveal a predominance of 1  +  and 3  +  couplings, <lb/>as shown in Fig. 13 for the unnatural parity couplings between 11 B gs and 11 Be states. <lb/> 5.3. Angular distributions for the G-ratios <lb/> In Fig. 14 the angular distributions for the G-ratio factor are presented. As opposed <lb/>to the cross sections, these quantities are almost insensitive to the optical model, which <lb/>is approximately cancelled out in the ratio. In this manner a supplemental test of the <lb/>microscopic theory of the form factors presented in this article is made. <lb/>The results show a good agreement with the experimental data for the 11 Be single <lb/>particle states, giving strong support to the assumptions on the structure of the states and <lb/>the reaction mechanism. They also confirm the phenomenological argument of Section 2, <lb/>based on the measured G factors at 0  •  , about the large contribution of the nucleonic spin <lb/>transfer dynamics, for the isovector interaction at low bombarding energy. <lb/>The agreement of the theoretical and the measured G-ratios for 11 Be single particle <lb/>states deserves some further discussion. On first sight it is unexpected because of the <lb/>pronounced differences in the cross sections. In our microscopic approach the cross <lb/>sections are calculated in DWBA approximation where initial and final state interaction <lb/>among the incoming and outgoing ions are described by an optical potential. For the <lb/>charge exchange transitions form factors obtained in double folding approach are used. The <lb/>structure parts include shell model OBTD for the 7 Li →  7 Be transitions, QRPA OBTD for <lb/>the 11 B →  11 Be ones, and a D3Y G-matrix interaction. Potentially each of these ingredient <lb/>influences the final result of the calculations for the cross sections. The shell model OBTD <lb/></body>

			<page> 52 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<body> Fig. 13. Decomposition of the calculated cross sections in terms of the angular momentum J B transferred in the <lb/>projectile 7 Li →  7 Be transitions. The shown examples refer to the unnatural parity transitions to the 11 Be ground <lb/>(panel (a)), the first (b) and the second excited state ((c) and (d)). Nth is an overall scaling factor for the calculated <lb/>cross sections. <lb/> for projectile transitions are well known and very accurate for p-shell mirror nuclei as <lb/> 7 Li and 7 Be. In addition, together with the D3Y G-matrix interaction they are the same <lb/>for all the calculations. So it would be very surprising if they would only fail for the <lb/>angular distribution of the 1/2  −  state in 11 Be. Also the structure calculations regarding <lb/>QRPA succeed to explain both the 11 Be low lying spectrum and the β-decay strengths, <lb/>and also verify the sum rules. Hence, the only ingredient that can be reasonably changing <lb/>for different transitions is the optical potential where rapid variations indicate a strong <lb/>influence of coupled channels effects. The problem in fact is due to the proximity of the <lb/>0.32 MeV state to the continuum (only 180 keV) which makes the coupling to break-up <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<page> 53 <lb/></page>

			<body> Fig. 14. Angular distributions for the G factors relative to the 11 Be ground, first and second excited states. In the <lb/>plots the analysis in terms of angular momentum transfer J B in the projectile transitions are also shown. <lb/> channels very important in this case. A full quantum mechanical treatment of this problem <lb/>is beyond the scope of this article. The observation that the G ratios behave more regularly <lb/>leads us to conclude that these quantities are only weakly affected by initial and final state <lb/>interactions which would explain the nice agreement with the data. <lb/> 6. Conclusions <lb/> The 11 B( 7 Li, 7 Be) 11 Be reaction has been studied at 57 MeV bombarding energy. From <lb/>an experimental point of view the use of a Tandem beam and of a high resolution magnetic <lb/>spectrometer allows a clear identification of several states and the direct measurement of <lb/>the spin flip probabilities. An empirical relation of proportionality between the measured <lb/>cross sections at zero degrees and the β-decay strengths is found to be valid within 20– <lb/>30%, both for GT and SD transitions. In addition the measured values of the reduced cross <lb/>sections for GT transitions are found to be deducible from the well known systematics of <lb/>the same transitions driven by (n, p) reactions. Of course, these analyses, being valid in <lb/>the intermediate energy domain, are here only intended as guideline to explain the order of <lb/>magnitude of the measured cross sections. The fact that this is possible within a factor of <lb/>two or less indicates that the microscopic processes that govern the reaction mechanism are <lb/>following essentially a pure one-step CEX while higher order transfer processes are only of <lb/>minor importance. Nevertheless, dealing with 7 Be doublets one cannot exclude, from our <lb/>results, that two-step mechanisms could still contribute to redistribute the strength between <lb/>these two states, having less influence in the sum. <lb/>The analyses of the doublet shapes trough the G factors at zero degrees, enforce the <lb/>evidence of direct one-step mechanism for the case of 11 B →  11 Be transitions while <lb/>hampering it for the 12 C →  12 B ones. Most likely, the dominance of the one step direct <lb/>charge reaction mechanism for 11 Be, as compared to the 12 B case, at low incident energy <lb/>is a consequence of the much narrower distribution of 11 Be wave functions peaked at <lb/>low values in the momentum space. This gives a larger overlap with the one-step CEX <lb/></body>

			<page> 54 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<body> operators, especially at low momentum transfer, i.e., at forward scattering angles. These <lb/>characteristics will reduce the overlap with the more broadly distributed two-step operators <lb/>thus reducing the overall transfer charge exchange contribution to the cross sections. <lb/>A many-body approach, appropriate for the weakly bound residual nucleus, has been <lb/>formulated in order to analyze the data. The use of the QRPA theory for the calculation <lb/>of the microscopic transition densities for the 11 B gs  →  11 Be coupling and of the D3Y <lb/> G-matrix interaction of Ref. [43] allows an upgraded and fully consistent description of <lb/>the data compared to traditional analyses of CEX reactions at low incident energy. The <lb/>cross sections for the single particle states are then calculated assuming a one-step direct <lb/>mechanism for the CEX, in the framework of the DWBA theory with a double folding <lb/>optical model and a specific term accounting for the break-up of the loosely bound halo <lb/>states. The analysis of the other states would involve a more complicated structure model <lb/>approach including a detailed treatment of the 2p–2h (4QP) excitations. This is beyond <lb/>the scope of the present article, although calculations of this kind have been done for <lb/>excitations in stable nuclei [37,38]. <lb/>The results show the success of our method, which reasonably well reproduces both <lb/>the angular distributions for the cross sections at forward angle and also the spin–flip <lb/>probabilities. In general, the calculations for the cross sections underestimate the data <lb/>at backward angles, where the contribution of two-step mechanisms are expected to be <lb/>non-negligible. On the other hand, at forward angles, they show a general trend of spin <lb/>transfer dynamics. This agrees with the known prevalence, at low excitation energy, of <lb/>GT and SD transitions, observed in CEX reactions at higher bombarding energy. At low <lb/>incident energy and for weakly bound systems the role of the tensor interaction, mainly <lb/>driven by long range pion exchange, becomes crucial and the traditional phenomenological <lb/>potentials need to be substituted by the more accurate treatment of the modern microscopic <lb/>interactions. <lb/>Finally, the calculations for the 0.32 MeV state point to a problem of general interest <lb/>for analyses of reactions with exotic nuclei. The close vicinity to the continuum (less <lb/>than 0.2 MeV) makes this channel very peculiar with respect to reaction dynamics and <lb/>structure. Both the diagonal density distribution, entering into the calculation of the double <lb/>folding potential, and the breakup contribution to the optical potential are not known. The <lb/>magnitude of the charge exchange cross section is in particular affected by the absorptive <lb/>part of the optical potentials in the incident and the exit channels to which the breakup <lb/>polarization self-energies mostly contribute. While we seem to have these quantities well <lb/>under control for the transitions involving the 11 Be ground state this must not be true on the <lb/>same level of confidence for the 0.32 MeV state. In fact, fully microscopic calculations of <lb/>the break-up contributions to the exit channel optical potential are not feasible at present. A <lb/>conclusive results, however, is that the microscopic calculations for this transition correctly <lb/>reproduce the G-ratio angular distribution while the cross sections are underestimated by <lb/>a factor of two. Most likely, this indicates that reaction dynamical effects are canceled out <lb/>from the G-ratio but fully contribute to the cross sections. <lb/>The challenge for the future exploration of the ( 7 Li, 7 Be) reaction is twofold. <lb/>Experimentally one has to provide high resolution spectra also at intermediate energy, for <lb/>example, by dispersing matching technique. Theoretically the goal is to build a microscopic <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<page> 55 <lb/></page>

			<body> approach, where the model wave functions for the structure of exotic nuclei and the detailed <lb/>description of the reaction mechanism are consistently derived from many-body theory. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgements <lb/> The authors wish to thank Dr. M. Khaled, Dr. H. Laurent, Dr. J.M. Maison, Dr. L. Rosier, <lb/>Dr. C. Stephan and Dr. L. Tassan-Got for their help during data taking. Part of the work <lb/>was supported by DFG under contract Le439/5. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] W.P. Alford, B.M. Spicer, in: J.W. Negele, E. Vogt (Eds.), Adv. in Nucl. Phys., vol. 24, Plenum, New York, <lb/>1998, p. 1. <lb/>[2] F. Osterfeld, Rev. Mod. Phys. 64 (1992) 491. <lb/>[3] T.N. Taddeucci, et al., Nucl. Phys. A 469 (1987) 125. <lb/>[4] V.F. Dmitriev, V. Zelevinsky, S.M. Austin, Phys. Rev. C 65 (2001) 015803. <lb/>[5] H. Lenske, Nucl. Phys. A 482 (1988) 343. <lb/>[6] M. Toyama, Phys. Lett. B 38 (1972) 147. <lb/>[7] W.R. Wharton, P.T. Debecev, Phys. Rev. C 11 (1975) 1963. <lb/>[8] J.S. Winfield, et al., Phys. Rev. C 33 (1986) 1333; <lb/>J.S. Winfield, et al., Phys. Rev. C 35 (1987) 1166, Erratum. <lb/>[9] H. Lenske, H.H. Wolter, H.G. Bohlen, Phys. Rev. Lett. 62 (1989) 1457. <lb/>[10] J. Bang, et al., Nucl. Phys. A 429 (1984) 330. <lb/>[11] J. Cook, et al., Phys. Rev. C 30 (1984) 1538; <lb/>N.M. Clarke, J. Cook, Nucl. Phys. A 458 (1986) 137. <lb/>[12] A. Etchegoyen, et al., Phys. Rev. C 38 (1988) 2124. <lb/>[13] S. Nakayama, et al., Phys. Lett. B 246 (1990) 342. <lb/>[14] S.B. Sakuta, et al., Europhys. Lett. 22 (1993) 511. <lb/>[15] L.K. Fifield, et al., Nucl. Phys. A 552 (1993) 125. <lb/>[16] J.D. Anderson, C. Wong, V.A. Madsen, Phys. Rev. Lett. 24 (1970) 1074. <lb/>[17] S.M. Austin, et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 44 (1980) 972. <lb/>[18] S. Nakayama, et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 67 (1991) 1082. <lb/>[19] J. Jänecke, Phys. Rev. C 54 (1996) 1070. <lb/>[20] F. Cappuzzello, et al., Phys. Lett. B 516 (2001) 21. <lb/>[21] F.J. Eckle, H. Lenske, et al., Phys. Rev. C 39 (1989) 1662; <lb/>F.J. Eckle, H. Lenske, et al., Nucl. Phys. A 506 (1990) 199. <lb/>[22] H. Lenske, J. Phys. G: Nucl. Part. Phys. 24 (1998) 1429. <lb/>[23] F. Cappuzzello, Ph.D. Thesis, Università di Catania, Catania, Italy, 1999. <lb/>[24] G.G. Ohlsen, Nucl. Instrum. Methods 37 (1965) 240. <lb/>[25] H. Sakai, et al., Phys. Lett. B 302 (1993) 7. <lb/>[26] T. Ohnishi, et al., Nucl. Phys. A 687 (2001) 38c. <lb/>[27] I. Daito, et al., Phys. Lett. B 418 (1998) 27. <lb/>[28] G.B. Liu, H.T. Fortune, Phys. Rev. C 42 (1990) 167. <lb/>[29] A. Ringbom, et al., Nucl. Phys. A 679 (2001) 231. <lb/>[30] S. Cohen, D. Kurath, Nucl. Phys. 73 (1965) 1. <lb/>[31] D.J. Millener, D. Kurath, Nucl. Phys. A 255 (1975) 315. <lb/>[32] T. Hoshino, H. Sagawa, A. Arima, Nucl. Phys. A 523 (1991) 228. <lb/>[33] S. Nakayama, et al., Nucl. Phys. A 507 (1990) 515. <lb/>[34] C. Berat, et al., Phys. Lett. B 218 (1989) 299. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 56 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> F. Cappuzzello et al. / Nuclear Physics A 739 (2004) 30–56 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> [35] C. Brendel, et al., Nucl. Phys. A 477 (1988) 162. <lb/>[36] C. Mahaux, H. Ngo, Nucl. Phys. A 378 (1982) 205. <lb/>[37] B. Reitz, et al., Phys. Lett. B 532 (2002) 179. <lb/>[38] N. Ryezayeva, et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 89 (2002) 272502. <lb/>[39] F.T. Baker, et al., Phys. Rep. 289 (1997) 235. <lb/>[40] D. Cortina-Gil, et al., Eur. Phys. J. A 10 (2001) 49. <lb/>[41] A.L. Fetter, D.J. Walecka, Quantum Theory of Many-Particle Systems, McGraw–Hill, New York, 1971. <lb/>[42] G.F. Bertsch, S.F. Tsai, Phys. Rep. 18 (1975) 125. <lb/>[43] F. Hofmann, H. Lenske, Phys. Rev. C 57 (1998) 2281. <lb/>[44] D.T. Khoa, W. von Oertzen, Phys. Lett. B 304 (1993) 8. <lb/>[45] F. Hofmann, C. Keil, H. Lenske, Phys. Rev. C 64 (2001) 034314, nucl-th/0007050. <lb/>[46] K. Ikeda, Prog. Theor. Phys. 31 (1964) 434. <lb/>[47] A. Krasznahorkay, et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 82 (1999) 3216. <lb/>[48] R. Machleidt, K. Holinde, C. Elster, Phys. Rep. 149 (1987) 1. <lb/>[49] G. Audi, A.H. Wapstra, Nucl. Phys. A 595 (1995) 409. <lb/>[50] H. Lenske, F. Hofmann, C.M. Keil, Rep. Prog. Nucl. Part. Phys. 46 (2001) 187, nucl-th/0012082. <lb/>[51] F. Ajzenberg-Selove, Nucl. Phys. A 506 (1990) 1. <lb/>[52] J.S. Winfield, et al., Phys. Rev. C 54 (1996) 125. <lb/>[53] L. Trache, et al., Phys. Rev. C 61 (2000) 024612. <lb/>[54] W.G. Love, M.A. Franey, Phys. Rev. C 24 (1981) 1073; <lb/>M.A. Franey, W.G. Love, Phys. Rev. C 31 (1985) 488. <lb/>[55] A. Bonaccorso, F. Carstoiu, Nucl. Phys. A 706 (2002) 322. <lb/>[56] S. Nakayama, et al., Phys. Rev. C 60 (1999) 047303. <lb/>[57] H. Lenske, HIDEX code. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
