<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Proc Indian Natn Sci Acad 81 No. 1 February 2015 Special Issue, pp. 174-178 <lb/>c <lb/> Printed in India. <lb/> Modified Surface Tension of a QGP-Droplet Under One Loop Correction in <lb/>Peshier Potential <lb/> S SOMORENDRO SINGH  1  , AGAM K JHA  * 2  and K K GUPTA  3 <lb/> 1  Department of Physics and Astrophysics, University of Delhi, Delhi 110 007, India <lb/> 2  Department of Physics, Bose Institute, Kolkata 700 009, India <lb/> 3  Department of Physics, Kirori Mal College, University of Delhi, Delhi 110 007, India <lb/> (Received on 1 May 2014; Accepted on 23 June 2014) <lb/> Under one loop correction in Peshier potential surface tension of a Quark-Gluon Plasma (QGP) droplet <lb/>has been recomputed. The correction reduces the stable size of a QGP droplet. The value of surface <lb/>tension obtained here is in better agreement with the current lattice result. <lb/> Key Words : Quark-Gluon Plasma; Quark-Hadron Phase Transition <lb/></front>

			<body> Introduction <lb/> It is well known that under extreme conditions of hadronic density and/or temperature the hadronic system <lb/>would split into its fundamental constituents, quarks and gluons, such that the bulk properties of the hadronic <lb/>system would be governed by these degrees of freedom (Shuryak, 1973). Such a (locally) thermally equi-<lb/>librated state of matter in which quarks and gluons are deconfined from hadrons, so that color degrees of <lb/>freedom become manifest over inter nuclear distances rather than just intra nucleonic distances, is called <lb/>Quark-Gluon Plasma (QGP) (Satz, 1978). The phase transition (Csernai et al., 2003; Mustafa et al., 1998; <lb/>Ramanathan et al., 2007; Shukla and Mohanty, 2001) might be anticipated during Ultra Relativistic Heavy <lb/>Ions Collisions (URHIC). So ongoing experiments related to URHIC at RHIC and LHC are much more <lb/>concerned for the new state. <lb/>Under a phase transition, the critical free energy difference between the two phases with the help of <lb/>liquid drop model is given (Kapusta et al., 1995) as: <lb/> ∆F = − <lb/> 4π <lb/>3 <lb/> R <lb/> 3  [P  had  (T ) − P  q,g  (T )] <lb/>+4πR <lb/> 2  σ + τ  crit  T ln [1 + ( <lb/>4π <lb/>3 <lb/>)R <lb/> 3  s  q,g  ]. <lb/> (1) <lb/></body>

			<front> *  Author for Correspondence : E-mail: agamjha 2001@yahoo.co.in <lb/> DOI: 10.16943/ptinsa/2015/v81i1/48066 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote"> Modified Surface Tension of a QGP-Droplet <lb/></note>

			<page> 175 <lb/></page>

			<body> The surface tension is calculated by minimizing the expression (1) with respect to the droplet size. It is <lb/>obtained as (Linde, 1983): <lb/> R  c  = <lb/>2σ <lb/>∆p <lb/> or σ = <lb/>3π∆F <lb/>4πR  2 <lb/> c <lb/> . <lb/> (2) <lb/>In this paper, we briefly revisit free energy incorporating one loop correction factor in the mean-field <lb/>potential and compute, once again, the surface tension of stable droplets. The perturbative part modifies the <lb/>density of state of the constituent particles of QGP. <lb/> Potential with one Loop Correction and DOS <lb/> The density of states (DOS) of QGP droplet is determined adapting a phenomenological confining potential <lb/> V  conf  (k). The potential is evaluated by considering the interactions between the constituent particles. The <lb/>calculation is considered with first order correction factor in the potential called mean field potential in phase <lb/>space. The correction is done in such a way that the expansion of strong coupling constant is perturbed with a <lb/>loop correction between quark-antiquark and quark-gluons (Ramanathan et al., 2007; Shukla and Mohanty, <lb/>2001; Brambilla et al., 2001). It is calculated through the Hamiltonian of system. So the interacting mean <lb/>field potential is expressed as: <lb/> V conf (k) = (2π/k)β α  s  (k)T <lb/> 2  [1 + <lb/> α  s  (k) <lb/>4π <lb/> a  1  ] − <lb/> m  2 <lb/>0 <lb/> 2k <lb/> , <lb/> (3) <lb/>where <lb/> β = <lb/> √ <lb/> 2 × <lb/> (1/β  g  )  2  + (1/β  q  )  2 <lb/> (4) <lb/>called the effective rms value of parametrization factor of β  q  = 1/8 and β  g  = (8−10) β  q  . These factors de-<lb/>termine the dynamics of QGP flow and subsequent transformation to the confining colorless hadrons. α  s  (k) <lb/> is the coupling value of quark and gluon with degree of freedom n  f  , <lb/>α  s  (k) = <lb/>4π <lb/>(33 − 2n  f  ) ln(1 + k  2  /Λ  2  ) <lb/> (5) <lb/>in which QCD parameter is defined as Λ = 0.15 GeV . The coefficient a  1  is one loop correction in the <lb/>interactions (Fischler, 1977; Billoire, 1980) and it is given as: <lb/> a  1  = 2.5833 − 0.2778 n  l  , <lb/> (6) <lb/>where n  l  is considered with the number of light quark elements (Smirnov et al., 2008). <lb/>So the density of states in phase space with one loop correction factor in the potential is obtained through <lb/>Ramanathan et al., (Ramanathan et al., 2007; Shukla and Mohanty, 2001; Ramanathan et al., 2004) as: <lb/> ρ  q,g  (k)dk = <lb/> ν <lb/>π  2  [−V  conf  (k)] <lb/> 2  dV  conf <lb/> dk <lb/> (7) <lb/></body>

			<page> 176 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> S. Somorendro Singh et al. <lb/></note>

			<body> or, <lb/> ρ  q,g  (k) = <lb/> ν <lb/>π  2  [ <lb/> β  3 <lb/> q,g  T  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/>] <lb/> 3  g <lb/> 6  (k)A <lb/> (8) <lb/>where, <lb/> A = {1 + <lb/> α  s  a  1 <lb/> π <lb/> } <lb/> 2  [ <lb/>(1 + α  s  a  1  /π) <lb/>k  4 <lb/> + <lb/>2(1 + 2α  s  a  1  /π) <lb/>k  2  (k  2  + Λ  2  ) ln(1 + <lb/> k  2 <lb/> Λ  2  ) <lb/>], <lb/> (9) <lb/> ν is the volume occupied by the QGP and k is the relativistic four-momentum in natural units and g  2  (k) = <lb/>4πα  s  (k). <lb/> The Free Energy Evolution and Surface Tension <lb/> With the help of free energies (Peshier et al., 1994; Smirnov et al., 2008; Ramanathan et al., 2004; Nee-<lb/>gaard and Madsen, 1999; Christiansen and Madsen, 1997; Balian and Block, 1970; Marder and <lb/>Sretitsky, 1991; Singh and Ramanathan, 2013; Iwasaki et al., 1994) under the loop correction, the surface <lb/>tension is computed as <lb/> Table 1: Surface tension of QGP droplet at β  g  = 8β  q  ,β  q  = 1/8; <lb/> T  c <lb/> ∆F  c <lb/> R  c <lb/> σ <lb/> σ <lb/>T  3 <lb/> c <lb/> (M eV ) (M eV ) (f m) (M eV /f m  2  ) <lb/> 150 <lb/>242.28 <lb/>2.57 <lb/>8.785 0.10 <lb/>170 <lb/>263.24 <lb/>2.60 <lb/>9.282 0.10 <lb/>190 <lb/>510.02 <lb/>2.61 <lb/>17.861 0.10 <lb/>210 <lb/>678.23 <lb/>2.59 <lb/>24.082 0.10 <lb/>230 <lb/>861.58 <lb/>2.55 <lb/>31.683 0.10 <lb/>250 1053.00 <lb/>2.49 <lb/>40.709 0.10 <lb/>270 1244.00 <lb/>2.41 <lb/>51.002 0.10 <lb/>290 1430.00 <lb/>2.32 <lb/>63.265 0.10 <lb/> Result and Conclusion <lb/> The surface tension at a suitable flow parameter such as β  q  = 1/8, β  g  = 8β  q  is evaluated through the <lb/>expression (2). Now surface tension σ(M eV /f m  2  ) is found to be increasing function with respect to the <lb/>corresponding temperature of different droplet size in the both parameters. The increment is also observed <lb/>with high gluon flow parameter at which the stability of QGP droplet is obtained near the hadronic phase. <lb/>Moreover if we consider the ratio of surface tension to the cube of critical temperature, the result is found to <lb/>be independent of the critical temperature and constancy is also observed in both cases of flow parameter. <lb/>Thus surface tension σ is found to be 0.10T  3  with the correction value in the potential. It increases from <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Modified Surface Tension of a QGP-Droplet <lb/></note>

			<page> 177 <lb/></page>

			<body> the earlier value 0.078 T  3  to 0.10 T  3  . There is an improvement in the result and it becomes closer to lattice <lb/>value 0.24 T  3  . This means that result with the correction factor in the mean field potential increases the <lb/>value of surface tension to a very close result of lattice QCD (Iwasaki et al., 1994). It implies that the loop <lb/>correction in the potential provides the stability of QGP dynamics with the appropriate flow parameters as <lb/>well as the surface tension of the droplets with a good result. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments <lb/> The authors thank R. Ramanathan for his critical readings, discussions and suggestions in preparing the <lb/>manuscript. We thank University Research Grant for financial support. One of the authors, Agam K Jha, <lb/>also expresses gratitude to University of Delhi for financial support under Innovation Project. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. Balian R and Block C (1970) Distribution of eigenfrequencies for the wave equation in a finite domain: I. <lb/>Three-dimensional problem with smooth boundary surface Ann Phys (NY) 64 401 <lb/>2. Billoire A (1980) How Heavy Must Be Quarks in Order to Build Coulombic q anti-q Bound States Phys Lett <lb/> B92 343 <lb/>3. Brambilla N, Pineda A, Soto J and Vairo A (2001) The QCD potential at O(1/m) Phys Rev D63 014023 <lb/>4. Christiansen MB and Madsen J (1997) Inhomogeneity scale from the cosmological quark-hadron transition J <lb/>Phys G23 2039 <lb/>5. Csernai LP, Kapusta JI and Osnes E (2003) Domain wall dynamics of phase interfaces Phys Rev D67 045003 <lb/>6. Fischler W (1977) Quark -anti-Quark Potential in QCD Nucl Phys B129 157 <lb/>7. Iwasaki Y, Kanaya K, Rummukainen K and Yoshie T (1994) Interface tension in quenched QCD Phys Rev D49 <lb/> 3540 <lb/>8. Kapusta JI, Vischler AP and Venugopalan R (1995) Nucleation of quark -gluon plasma from hadronic matter <lb/> Phys Rev C51 901 <lb/>9. Linde AD (1983) Decay of the False Vacuum at Finite Temperature Nucl Phys B216 421 <lb/>10. Mardor I and Svetitsky B (1991) Bubble free energy at the quark -hadron phase transition Phys Rev D44 878 <lb/>11. Mustafa MG, Srivastava DK and Sinha B (1998) Effect of color singletness of quark gluon plasma in quark <lb/>hadron phase transition Euro Phys J C5 711 <lb/>12. Neergaard G and Madsen J (1999) Free energy of bubbles in the quark hadron phase transition Phys Rev D60 <lb/> 054011 <lb/>13. Peshier A, Kämpfer B, Pavlenko OP and Soff G (1994) An Effective model of the quark -gluon plasma with <lb/>thermal parton masses Phys Lett B337 235 <lb/>14. Ramanathan R, Gupta KK, Jha AK and Singh SS (2007) The interfacial surface tension of a quark-gluon plasma <lb/>fireball in a hadronic medium Pram J Phys 68 757 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 178 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> S. Somorendro Singh et al. <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> 15. Ramanathan R, Mathur Y, Gupta KK and Jha AK (2004) A Simple statistical model for analysis of QGP-droplet <lb/>(fireball) formation Phys Rev C70 027903 <lb/>16. Satz H (1978) From Hadron To Quark Matter CERN-TH-2590 18pp <lb/>17. Shukla P and Mohanty AK (2001) Nucleation versus spinodal decomposition in a first order quark hadron phase <lb/>transition Phys Rev C64 (2001) 054910 <lb/>18. Shuryak EV (1973) Quantum Chromodynamics and the Theory of Superdense Matter Phys Rep 61 71 <lb/>19. Singh SS and Ramanathan R (2013) arXiv: 1308.3757v1 <lb/> 20. Smirnov AV, Smirnov VA and Steinhauser M (2008) Fermionic contributions to the three-loop static potential <lb/> Phys Lett B668 293. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
