<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage> This content has been downloaded from IOPscience. Please scroll down to see the full text. <lb/>Download details: <lb/>IP Address: 137.138.124.224 <lb/>This content was downloaded on 13/04/2015 at 18:47 <lb/>Please note that terms and conditions apply. <lb/> Residual Fluctuations in the Matter and Radiation Distribution After the Decoupling Epoch <lb/> View the table of contents for this issue, or go to the journal homepage for more <lb/>1980 Phys. Scr. 21 708 <lb/>(http://iopscience.iop.org/1402-4896/21/5/022) <lb/>Home Search Collections Journals About Contact us My IOPscience <lb/> Physica Scripta. Vol. 21, 708-713, 1980 <lb/></titlePage>

			<front> Residual Fluctuations in the Matter and Radiation Distribution <lb/>After the Oecoupling Epoch <lb/> Joseph Silk <lb/> Astronomy Dept., University of California, Berkeley, Calif. 94720, U.S.A. <lb/> and <lb/>Michael L. Wilson <lb/> Physics Dept., University of California, Berkeley, Calif. 94720, U.S.A. <lb/> Received August  31,  1979 <lb/> Abstract <lb/> Residual fluctuations in the matter and radiation distribution after the <lb/>decoupling epoch.  Joseph Silk (Astronomy Department, University of <lb/>California, Berkeley, Calif. 94720, U.S.A.); and Michael L. Wilson <lb/>(Physics Department, University of California, Berkeley, Calif. 94720, <lb/>U.S.A.). <lb/> Physica Scripta (Sweden) 21,  708-713, 1980. <lb/>The residual spectra of matter and radiation fluctuations in the early uni-<lb/>verse are investigated. We study the evolution of primordial adiabatic and <lb/>isothermal fluctuations through the decoupling epoch. Amplification of <lb/> adiabatic density fluctuations during decoupling, or velocity &quot; overshoot &quot; , <lb/>is largely suppressed by Compton drag. Consequently, the amplitude of <lb/>density fluctuations entering the horizon prior to decoupling is larger <lb/>than hitherto assumed in the adiabatic theory. Damping of primordial <lb/>adiabatic density fluctuations by an order of magnitude occurs on mass-<lb/>scales of  3  x  1oi3&amp;fD  ( a  = 1)  or  1 0 1 4 ~ 0 <lb/> ( a  =  0.2). <lb/>Comparison of the residual radiation fluctuations with observational <lb/>limits indicates that the adiabatic theory is only acceptable if re-ionization <lb/>of the intergalactic medium results in additional scattering of the radiation <lb/>after decoupling. Primordial isothermal fluctuations are found to yield <lb/>radiation fluctuations which are insensitive to the assumed spectrum and <lb/>lie a factor  - 5  below current limits. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/>According to the standard Big Bang theory, galaxies originated <lb/>from infinitesimal inhomogeneities in the early universe.  As <lb/> demonstrated first by Lifshitz  [  11, but foreseen in earlier work <lb/> [  21, density fluctuations amplify under the influence of their <lb/>own self-gravity, eventually collapsing to form bound systems. <lb/>To determine the nature of these primordial fluctuations is an <lb/>important goal of cosmology. <lb/>Two key questions may be posed.  Da  physical processes in <lb/>the early universe impose any natural scales on an initially scale-<lb/>free spectrum of fluctuations? And can we hope to directly <lb/>observe the primordial fluctuations by detecting fine-scale <lb/>anisotropy in the cosmic microwave background radiation? It is <lb/>also possible that the spectrum and amplitude of these fluctu-<lb/>ations may give some information on the cosmological density <lb/>parameter  CL. <lb/> Most of the previous work on the residual fluctuation spec-<lb/>trum of the matter and radiation from the early universe has <lb/>been analytic  [  3-71, While this approach is satisfactory prior to <lb/>decoupling, a correct treatment of damping during the decoup-<lb/>ling epoch necessitates a numerical approach. The first direct <lb/>attack on this problem was carried out for primordial adiabatic <lb/>perturbations by Peebles and Yu  [ 8 ] .  A  recent discussion by <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> Physica Scripta  21 <lb/></note>

			<body> Doroshkevich, Zel&apos;dovich, and Sunyaev  [  91 extends these <lb/>results to isothermal perturbations. <lb/>There are several reasons for returning to this problem. One <lb/>would like to consider primordial isothermal fluctuations in <lb/>more detail, because of their popularity among proponents of <lb/> hierarchical clustering models of galaxy formation [lo]. The <lb/>effects of space curvature should be explored, these effects <lb/>being important on angular scales in excess of 10&apos; in low density <lb/>cosmological models. The role of velocity overshoot during <lb/>decoupling is controversial: Zel&apos;dovich and Sunyaev argue that <lb/>this effect, due to the drastic decrease of the Jeans length at <lb/>decoupling, can lead to strong amplification by up to a factor of <lb/>100 on galactic mass-scales for adiabatic density fluctuations. <lb/>However, this conclusion has been disputed  [ 6, 111. Without <lb/>the benefit of this amplification effect, non-linear steepening of <lb/>adiabatic fluctuations and shock formation are more likely to <lb/>occur prior to decoupling, since the amplitude must be corre-<lb/>spondingly greater. Finally, it is useful to consider a wide range <lb/>of initial fluctuation spectra, and to reexamine the criteria for <lb/>normalization of these spectra. Use of, for example, the galaxy <lb/>correlation function may be preferable to making assumptions <lb/>about the epoch of galaxy formation (cf. [12]). <lb/> For these reasons, we have chosen to reexamine the effects <lb/>of decoupling on primordial inhomogeneities, and to recalculate <lb/>the residual matter and radiation fluctuation spectra. In the <lb/>following section, we describe a simple theoretical model for <lb/>following the evolution of inhomogeneities through decoupling. <lb/>We then apply this procedure to evaluate the residual matter <lb/>(Section 3) and radiation (Section 4) spectra. A final section <lb/>summarizes our results. <lb/> 2. Theory <lb/> Our procedure for computing the residual matter and radiation <lb/>fluctuations follows that of Peebles and Yu [8]. Briefly, we <lb/>define a radiation distribution function  f,  with the radiation <lb/>evolution described by the Boltzmann equation, <lb/>where the sole interaction between matter and radiation is <lb/> taken t o be Thomson scattering (cross-section uT), and  f  is the <lb/>direction-averaged radiation distribution. Thus, in the matter <lb/>rest-frame <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Residual fluctuations in the Matter and Radiation Distribution After the Decoupling Epoch <lb/></note>

			<page> 709 <lb/></page>

			<body> We consider axially symmetric, irrotational plane-wave fluctu-<lb/> 3.1 <lb/> ations of the form <lb/>1671 <lb/> ? ( x i , E , j . , t )  =  __  [ l +(f+?&apos;)2]  f(x&apos;,E,+&apos;,t)da&apos; <lb/> 6,(x)  =  d3k eik&apos; &quot; 6,(k) <lb/>where the proper wavelength is  2nlkT  and  k&apos;  =  k2  =  0,  k3  =  k. <lb/> We also have  U&apos;  =  v2  =  0,  v3  =  v ,  h l j  =  0  ( i #  j ) ,  h l l  =  hz2,  and <lb/> hii  =  h. The co-moving mass is defined by  M ( k )  =  1/6np0 <lb/> (2n/kT)3  =  1 / 6 n b ( 2 ~ / k ) ~ . <lb/>be the cosine of the angle between photon <lb/>direction and wave-vector. We have 6  =  6(k,  t , p ) ,  and we <lb/>expand  6  in Legendre polynomials t o take account of the <lb/>angular dependence: <lb/> s <lb/> where  i.  is a unit vector indicating photon direction. The energy-<lb/>momentum conservation equations are given by <lb/> (T$,&apos;+  T/&apos;);v  =  0 <lb/> where subscript m denotes matter and r radiation. and <lb/> T E  =  p m u P u V <lb/> the fluid velocity is  U&apos;,  and the matter density is  p,.  Also <lb/> 7&apos;:&apos;  =  1  ppp &quot; f  *  y.  d  3P <lb/> 2.1.  Linearization <lb/> equations: <lb/>Let  p = T <lb/> m <lb/> 6 ( k ,  t,  U&gt; =  C 6n(k- t&gt;Pn(p) <lb/> We linearize about the Friedmann solution t o Einstein&apos;s field <lb/> n=  0 <lb/> It follows that  $ =  60.  f  = f Z  =  0,  f 3  =  61/3,  fij  =  0  (i  f  i), <lb/> f l l  =  f Z 2  = 6o - a2/5,  and  f 3 3  = 6o +  262  f 5 .  We fmally obtain <lb/>the following set of equations for  6 , ,  v,  k. and 6 : <lb/> R p v  =  8nG(T,v  - t g , u m <lb/> and define <lb/> 6,  =  -ikTv  +  ih; <lb/> (8) <lb/> (9) <lb/> pm =  Po(t)(l  +  6 <lb/>, <lb/>) <lb/>; <lb/> f  =  fo(E,  t)(l  +  S,),  u i  =  v&apos;R-&apos; <lb/> T <lb/> aT <lb/> T <lb/> b <lb/> = - v  +  3fleOT  - (61  - 4v); <lb/>with gauge conditions <lb/> T . <lb/> g,, =  -1 . <lb/> g .  =  O g . .  =g!y&apos;-RZh.. <lb/> 41 <lb/> &apos;  11 <lb/> 11 <lb/> h  =  2  - h  +  8nG(bT36,  +  2aT460); <lb/> Here  R(t)  is the cosmological scale factor. which we normalize <lb/> T <lb/>16nGi <lb/> d  +  ( n e u ~ <lb/> +  ikTp)F  =  2 p z h  +  (1  - 3 p 2 )  __  kT <lb/> to  R  =  1  / T ,  and the unperturbed Friedmann model satisfies <lb/> X  (bT3v  +  3aT461)  +  n e U T ( 6 0 -&amp; ( 1  -3p2)62  f  4pV). <lb/> (2) <lb/> 8nG <lb/> 1 2 <lb/> T  = - T3 <lb/> (0  +  bT-&apos;  -<lb/> where  K  =  (8nG/3)(aTi  +  bTo)[(CLo  - l)/flO],  p,(t&gt;  =  aT4,  and <lb/>p d t )  =  bT3.  Up through the time of decoupling, it is a good <lb/>approximation to take  K  =  0, which we do in the following. We <lb/> now define the frequency-averaged radiation perturbation <lb/> 6  = --<lb/> Also, we write the perturbed radiation density  8  =  (1/4n) J 6 d n , <lb/> fij  =  (3/4n)  J &quot;  Gq&apos;+&apos;dCL, and the radiation flux  f&apos;  =  (l/4n)  J &quot; <lb/> 6;/&apos;dR. Note that  fo  =  2h-3(eEiT- l)-&apos; and  J &quot;  f o E 3 d E  = <lb/> .f  6,  *  f o  * E 3 d E <lb/> -. <lb/> J f o E 3 d E  , <lb/> 2.2.  So  lu  t  io  n <lb/> Initial conditions are chosen as follows. At early times, well <lb/>before decoupling, there are four modes: 6,  a t m ,  with <lb/> m  = - 1, 0,  4, +  1. The  m  =  0 mode is isothermal; the other <lb/>modes are adiabatic. We restrict our attention to the  m  =  0 <lb/> isothermal mode and t o the most rapidly growing  m  =  1 <lb/> adiabatic mode. We compute the solutions numerically until <lb/>well after decoupling, starting with initial conditions: <lb/> m  =  0 :  6 ,  =  constant, 6o  =  0 , h  = O,Z&apos; =  0; <lb/> (1  2 ) <lb/> aT4/4n. The relevant perturbation equations are. from the <lb/>Boltzmann equation <lb/> m  =  1:  6 , a t :  6o  =  I S , , <lb/> h  =  26,It.v  =  -$ikTtG,. <lb/> . .  a6 <lb/> ax <lb/> (13) <lb/> d  f  Ty&apos;  7- 2hij+&apos;+j  =  neoT(tS  +  ifij+i+j  - 6  +  4vij.&apos;) <lb/>At late epochs, when the universe is matter-dominated and <lb/>at z  &gt;  Cl-&apos;,  the solution is continued analytically. using <lb/> (3) <lb/> from the energy-momentum conservation equations <lb/>arid <lb/>and from the gravitational field equations, <lb/> Kii  - 2 <lb/> T . <lb/> hii  =  8nG(bT36,  +  2aT4s) <lb/> 1 <lb/> and <lb/> 6 ,  =  ~ ~ ( t / t ~ ) ~ &apos; ~ <lb/> +  C 2 ( t / t R ) -l , <lb/> v  =  i ~ ~ ( t / t ~ ) - &quot; ~ , <lb/> (4) <lb/> .  4 c, <lb/> c 2 <lb/> 3 tR <lb/> t R <lb/> h  =  ---( t / t ~ ) -&apos; &apos; ~ - 2  - (t/tR)-&apos;-2 k T ~ C 3 ( t / t ~ ) -~ &apos; ~ . <lb/>(16) <lb/> ( 5 ) <lb/> The residual radiation fluctuation after decoupling reduces t o <lb/> x  exp  [- 3 i p ~ ( a <lb/> - l)]  + 8C1  ( &apos; i z <lb/> -- - a )  +  4ic3pa-2 <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> Pfrysica Scripta 21 <lb/></note>

			<page> 7 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Joseph  Silk and Michael L. Wilson <lb/></note>

			<body> where <lb/> K  =  kTRtR  and  (Y =  ( t / t ~ ) &apos; &apos; ~ . <lb/> In practice, we ignore the slowly varying (in angle) terms in eq. <lb/>(17), and define  arms  to be the root mean square value of the <lb/>expression in square brackets. It is an adequate approximation <lb/>to write <lb/> ,-ihkp <lb/> 6 ( ~ , <lb/> t )  e  6rms <lb/> where <lb/> =  3TRtR((Y- 1). <lb/> 3.  Residual matter  fluctuations <lb/> The effects of radiative damping on the adiabatic fluctuation <lb/>spectrum that emerges from decoupling are shown in Fig. 1, <lb/>where the residual mass fluctuation spectrum  P(k)&apos;/&apos; <lb/> k3/2/6,(k)I  is shown as a function of comoving mass-scale <lb/>for an initially flat  (SL(k)  0: ko)  spectrum. Since the variance <lb/>of the density  CS&amp;)  =  8n3/V*  477  J d(ln  k ) k 3 16,(k)I2, P ( k ) <lb/> is the contribution to the variance of the mass density per <lb/>logarithmic increment of wavenumber  k .  P(K)  is actually an <lb/>oscillatory function, and Fig. 1 only shows the amplitude, <lb/>which varies smoothly. <lb/>Use of a Hubble constant  Ho  =  50  km  s-l Mpc-&apos; yields some-<lb/>what larger values for the damping mass (all results scale as <lb/> !XI;)  than found by Peebles and Yu in the spatially flat model <lb/>(our results agree for  H,,  =  lOOkms-&apos;Mpc-&apos;). For  s2  =  1 and <lb/> f2  =  0.2, the mass spectrum decays by a factor 10 at mass-scales <lb/> 3  x  1013M, and 1  x  10&apos;4M, respectively. <lb/> A  comparison is also shown with fitting an analytic expression <lb/>advocated by Doroshkevich et al. [9], of the form (kr)&quot;&apos;sin <lb/> (kr)  exp  (- i k r ) .  In the exponential damping regime, this <lb/>formula underestimates the damping for  i2  =  1 and overesti-<lb/>mates the damping for  52  =  0.2. The flattening of the  52  =  1 <lb/> curve at large mass-scales is due in part to the preferential <lb/>enhancement of mass-scales greater than the Jeans mass while <lb/>the universe is matter-dominated prior to decoupling (see Fig.  3 <lb/> below). However, some damping occurs even on large scales. <lb/>We may elucidate this latter point by noting that there is no <lb/>significant velocity overshoot effect which boosts the amplitude <lb/>of the adiabatic matter fluctuations at decoupling. Velocity <lb/>overshoot is evidently counter-balanced by damping. This is <lb/> IO&quot; 10&quot; IO&quot; 10&apos;~ <lb/>IO&quot; IO&quot; <lb/> M a s s ( M O ) <lb/> Fig. I .  Transfer function for adiabatic fluctuations <lb/>open  ( a  =  0.2)  cosmological models. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> Physica Scripta  21 <lb/></note>

			<body> I <lb/> 6000 <lb/> 5000 <lb/> 4000 <lb/> 3000 <lb/> ?WO <lb/> T ( K ) <lb/> Fig. 2.  Amplitude  o f  adiabatic density and associated velocity fluctu-<lb/>ations for comoving mass-scales of  1.4  X  1015M0  and  2.5  X  10l4Mn, <lb/> with  52  =  1. <lb/> Mass  (MO) <lb/> ? 7 <lb/> =  e 6 <lb/> -4 <lb/> r 3 <lb/> a 2 <lb/> I <lb/> 0 <lb/> g 5 <lb/> 2 -<lb/> v <lb/> 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 1 0 <lb/> k d 0 &quot; (sec-&apos;K-&apos;) <lb/> Fig. 3.  Residual matter and radiation adiabatic fluctuation spectra, evalu-<lb/>ated well after decoupling for  0  =  1 cosmological model. Also shown for <lb/>comparison is the analytic fit of the residual matter spectrum proposed <lb/>by Doroshkevich et al.  [  91, denoted by DZS. The initial conditions corre-<lb/>spond to choice of the fastest growing adiabatic mode; the normalization <lb/>is arbitrary, but the relative normalization is chosen for  T = 2000K. <lb/> 6,  a  T -&apos; ,  whereas  6 , <lb/>, <lb/> is constant in time. <lb/>in flat  (52  =  1) and <lb/> Fzg, <lb/> k x IO&quot; (sec-&apos;K? <lb/> 4.  As Fig.  3,  but for n  =  0.2. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Residual Fluctuations in the Matter arid Radiation Distribution After the Decoupling Epoch <lb/></note>

			<page> 7  1  1 <lb/></page>

			<body> I O <lb/> -<lb/> 2 <lb/> 3 6 -<lb/> s  7 -<lb/> 0 <lb/> clearly demonstrated in Fig. 2, where we show the time-evolution <lb/>of  6 ,  and  ZI  through the decoupling epoch for mass scales of <lb/> 2.5  x  1014 and 1.4  x  10&quot;M,. It is evident that a smooth tran-<lb/>sition is made t o the density perturbation at  T  - 3000 K, while <lb/>the velocity perturbation decays. <lb/>To examine the long wavelength spectrum in more detail, <lb/>Figs. 3 and 4 display the adiabatic mass fluctuation spectrum <lb/> k3&quot;  16, l <lb/> for the fastest growing mode, for  5;2 =  1 and 0.2 <lb/> respectively. The spectra are valid well after decoupling. The <lb/>dominance of the largest wavelength mode (- lO&quot;M,) in the <lb/> I1  =  1 model occurs because this scale suffers uninterrupted <lb/>growth prior t o decoupling. While this is also true of the largest <lb/>mass-scales in the  R  =  0.2 model, in this case it is partially com-<lb/>pensated by the velocity overshoot. The velocity overshoot and <lb/>the damping effects approximately balance each other in the <lb/> S l  =  1 model, but there is much less velocity overshoot to com-<lb/>pensate for the damping, since the matter-domination reduces <lb/>the sound speed. In the  R  =  0.2 model, the universe is radiation-<lb/>dominated almost until decoupling, and the sound speed remains <lb/>close to c/3l&quot;. Consequently, there is little preferential amplifi-<lb/>cation of the largest mass-scales. Comparison with the results of <lb/>Doroshkevich et al. is again shown for  s2  =  1. We return t o <lb/>examine the initial fluctuation spectra required for galaxy forma-<lb/>tion after examining the constraints imposed by the search for <lb/>fine-scale radiation anisotropy. <lb/> -<lb/> / <lb/> - - 8,  k&apos;g <lb/> 4 <lb/> -l OS,,kh <lb/> U -<lb/> 4.  Residual radiation fluctuations <lb/> 4.1.  Evaluation  o f  6, , , <lb/> In Figs. 3 and 4 we show the residual radiation fluctuation spec-<lb/>trum  k3&apos;*  &amp; , <lb/>, <lb/> for cosmological models with  R  =  1 and 0.2, <lb/> respectively, for adiabatic fluctuations. Smearing by scattering <lb/>due to the residual ionization immediately after the decoupling <lb/>epoch is responsible for removing most of the small-scale struc-<lb/>ture. Thus the residual radiation spectra appear similar in shape <lb/>(,note that the normalization is arbitrary) for both  s2  =  1 and <lb/> R  =  0.2 cosmological models. Only the secondary peak at <lb/> - 5  x <lb/> is somewhat more pronounced in the low density <lb/>model. The magnitude of the largest wavelength peak at <lb/> 3  x  10i7M, is  6, , ,  - j &amp;, I <lb/>, <lb/> and has been enhanced by the <lb/>self-gravity of the fluctuation. Evidently, the naive approxi-<lb/>mation  S, , <lb/>, <lb/> =  1/3 16,l is very poor: at smaller scales <lb/> (:&lt;  5  x  10&quot;  Ms),  scattering provides an important diminution of <lb/> Mass (M,) <lb/> 10mlO&quot;  i0&apos;65~10&apos;5 lo&apos;&quot;  540&apos; <lb/> K~ 1 0 &apos; ~ <lb/> ( sec&quot; <lb/> Fig.  5.  Residual matter and radiation fluctuation spectra. associated with <lb/>the isothermal mode. evaluated well after decoupling for the  R  =  1 <lb/>cosmological model.  As  before, the relative normalization is chosen for <lb/> 7- =  2000  K. <lb/> the radiation fluctuations. The graphs are for an initial white <lb/>noise  (n  = 0)  spectrum. <lb/>Similar results are shown in Figs.  5  and 6 for the residual <lb/>radiation fluctuation spectrum induced by primordial isothermal <lb/>fluctuations for  R  =  1 and  R  =  0.2, respectively. These radiation <lb/>fluctuations are induced by scattering of radiation from the den-<lb/>sity fluctuations w h c h are generating potential motions as the <lb/>sound velocity drops during the decoupling epoch. Large scales <lb/>preferentially survive because of scattering by different fluctu-<lb/>ations and the intervening medium, the dominant scale being <lb/>about 5  x  1014Ma. Even though significant motions are gener-<lb/>ated on scales down to  - 1014Mor as is apparent from the <lb/>residual 16,  I  (which initially was flat), no radiation fluctuations <lb/>survive to a significant level except on much larger scales. The <lb/>dominant Fourier component, where  6, , , <lb/> peaks, satisfies <lb/> A <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/> 5  0.6 l6,l (R  =  1) or  5  0.3  l 6 , l  (R  =  0.2); however, the <lb/>integrated contribution is much less than for the radiation fluc-<lb/>tuations associated with adiabatic fluctuations. To express this <lb/>difference in terms of an observable parameter, we must define <lb/>radiation temperature fluctuations that a radio telescope can <lb/>measure. <lb/> 4.2. Comparison with observational limits <lb/> A low upper limit on possible fluctuations in the microwave <lb/>background radiation has been given by Partridge  [  131, who <lb/>used a beam half-width a  =  1.8&apos; and a switching angle  0  =  9&apos;. <lb/> To express our results in a form that can be compared with the <lb/>experimental limit, we must convolve the radiation fluctuations <lb/> 6 , , ,  with the antenna response function, for which we adopt a <lb/>Gaussian form: <lb/> f(+&apos;  -<lb/> 1 <lb/> 2 n d <lb/> ? ; a &gt;  = -- exp [-(+&apos;- +&gt;&apos;/&apos;-a&apos;]. <lb/> The brightness fluctuations averaged over the antenna beam are <lb/> 6&apos;(k,  +;  a)  = [  6(k, ?&apos;)f(T&apos;  - T,  a) d n &apos; . <lb/>The mean-square temperature fluctuation for a beam switched <lb/>between directions y, and  y2  separated by an angle  0 is <lb/> (6T/Tj2  = ;(  ifs&apos;(+l)  - f 6 &apos; ( + 2 )  I ? ) = ( I  fs&apos;(+)  i2) <lb/> - A  (6&apos;(Yl)  6 ;(YJ  ). <lb/> The numerical factor is chosen so that in the limit of large  0, <lb/> where  (  6&apos;(yl)  ti&apos;(?,))  =  0 since fluctuations are randomly corre-<lb/>lated. we obtain <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> PIiTsica Scripta 21 <lb/></note>

			<page> 7  12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Joseph Silk and Michael L.  Wilson <lb/></note>

			<body> 18 <lb/> I9 <lb/> 16 <lb/> 15 <lb/> I4 <lb/> 13 <lb/> 12 <lb/> I I <lb/> IO <lb/> x 8 <lb/> + 7 <lb/> b 6 <lb/> - 5 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 2 <lb/> I <lb/> 0 <lb/> &quot; 0 9 <lb/> -<lb/> m <lb/> 0 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 2 0 <lb/>3 0 <lb/> 40 <lb/> 50 <lb/>60 <lb/> 8  (arc-minutes ) <lb/> Fig.  7. Residual temperature fluctuations associated with primordial <lb/>adiabatic density fluctuations as a function of beam switching angle  0, <lb/> evaluated for a 1:8 beam. Results are shown for initial spectra  n  =  t  1, 0, <lb/> - 1 and for  i2  =  1 and 0.2. <lb/> (6r/r)&apos;=.(l~6&apos;(i.)IZ~. <lb/> The expression for  (ST/T)&apos;  reduces to <lb/>d(1n  k ) k36,2,,(k) <lb/> 16  V <lb/> where  j o ( x )  =  sin  x/x  and the Fourier components are taken to <lb/>be periodic in some large volume  V  (large compared with the <lb/>horizon scale). <lb/>Normalization is performed by f i i n g the residual matter <lb/>fluctuation spectrum. We proceed by finding where the matter <lb/>fluctuation spectrum  k 3 IF,(k)  1&apos;  peaks, and then we assume <lb/>that density fluctuations reach unit amplitude at some redshift <lb/> z*  by writing <lb/>We illustrate our results in Fig. 7 for  z* =  1 and  U  =  1:8, for dif-<lb/>ferent values of  n,  defined by  I 6, I &apos; <lb/> a  k&quot;  initially. The upper <lb/>limit of  2  x <lb/> at 8  =  9&apos; poses a severe constraint on adiabatic <lb/>density fluctuations. <lb/>Inspection of Fig. 7 leads to the following remarks. Low  R <lb/> models are inconsistent with the adiabatic theory of density <lb/>fluctuations provided that the intergalactic medium does not <lb/>subsequently become reionized at an early epoch. Moreover <lb/>the predicted  F  TIT  values are moderately insensitive to choice <lb/>of  n ,  slightly larger fluctuations tending to be produced on small <lb/>scales if  n  &gt;  0 than if  n  &lt;  0 (the converse is true however on <lb/>large angular scales). Initial spectra with  n  &lt;  1 result in flat <lb/> (n  =  1) residual matter fluctuation spectra or in spectra which <lb/>increase towardslarger scales  (n  &lt;  1): thisis because an adiabatic <lb/>fluctuation power spectrum 16,  I&apos;  a  k&quot;  near the singularity <lb/>corresponds to  IF,  )*  a  kn-&quot;  for mass-scales that have entered <lb/>the horizon. The corresponding density fluctuation spectrum <lb/>is  6 p / p  a  M(1-n)&apos;6. According to Doroshkevich and Shandarin&apos; <lb/> [  141, a value of  n  &gt;  2  is required to give accord with the corre-<lb/>lation function studies of the large-scale structure of the uni-<lb/>verse: in the linear regime at scales  Z  10 Mpc, we are presumably <lb/>directly sampling  6 <lb/>, <lb/>. <lb/> The predicted values of 6  TIT  for isothermal fluctuations are <lb/>shown in Fig. 8. Normalization has been performed by requiring <lb/>the matter fluctuations to be of amplitude <lb/> a-&apos;  on a scale <lb/>at decoupling that corresponds to the scale  ro,  where the two-<lb/>point correlation function for the galaxy distribution <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> Physica Scripta 21 <lb/></note>

			<body> 18-<lb/> 1 7 -<lb/> 1 6 - --= I <lb/> 1 5 - - n.02 <lb/> 1 4 -<lb/> -<lb/> n=O <lb/> n = + l <lb/> 0 <lb/> IO <lb/> 20 <lb/> 30 <lb/> 40 <lb/>5 0 <lb/> 60 <lb/> 8  (arc-minutes) <lb/> Fig.  8.  As  Fig. 7, but for isothermal fluctuations. <lb/> [ ( r )  =  (r/ro)-&apos;.&quot; <lb/> enters the linear regime. According to Peebles [15],  ro= <lb/> 8.4(50 km s-&apos; Mpc-&apos;/Ho), Results are shown for initial spectra <lb/> n  = +  1,0, and  - 1, and  Sl  =  1 and 0.2. In order of magnitude, <lb/>we can understand the low value of 6  TIT  for isothermal fluctu-<lb/>ations as follows: if  Cl  =  1, <lb/>where from Fig. 5, we infer that <lb/> 5.  Conclusions <lb/> Upper limits on the small scale anisotropy of the cosmic micro-<lb/>wave background radiation are below the values predicted by <lb/>the adiabatic fluctuation theory of galaxy formation. This result <lb/>is in agreement with the conclusions reached by Doroshkevich <lb/>et al.  [  91, who however overestimated the fluctuations predicted <lb/>in the isothermal fluctuation theory. The adiabatic fluctuation <lb/>theory can be reconciled with current observational limits if the <lb/>intervening medium is reionized sufficiently early so that rescat-<lb/>tering of the microwave radiation occurs. However, a pure adia-<lb/>batic primordial fluctuation spectrum allows no possibility for <lb/>early reionization in the standard model, since galaxy formation <lb/>occurs at a late epoch. If the last scattering surface is shifted to <lb/> z  &lt;  1000 by reionization, this process will itself result in the <lb/>generation of smaller, but nevertheless significant, small scale <lb/>anisotropy in the radiation that is last scattered  [  16, 171. <lb/>We have found that the initial amplitudes required in the <lb/>adiabatic fluctuation theory are significantly larger than pre-<lb/>viously proposed [18]. The velocity overshoot effect fails to <lb/>provide any significant amplification in view of the strong <lb/>Compton drag during decoupling. This means, for example, that <lb/>with the scale invariant choice  n  = +  1 for the fluctuation spec-<lb/>trum near the singularity, the amplitude of density fluctuations <lb/>on scales entering the horizon before decoupling is  Z <lb/> for <lb/>5 2 5 1 . <lb/>The residual matter spectrum associated with primordial <lb/>adiabatic fluctuations is damped by an order of magnitude at <lb/>mass-scales of 3  x  1013M,  (Sl  =  1) or 1014M,  (R  =  0.2). These <lb/>large damping scales are not necessarily an obstacle to galaxy <lb/>formation theory: for example, if  R  =  1, and galaxy formation <lb/>occurs with an efficiency of a few percent, one could account <lb/>for the mass in luminous galaxies (contributing  Qgal  - 0.01-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> Residual fluctuations in the Matter and Radiation Distribution After the Decoupling Epoch <lb/></note>

			<page> I1  3 <lb/></page>

			<body> O.l), with most of what remains assumed t o be non-luminous <lb/>matter. Formation of smaller galaxies cannot be attributed t o <lb/>primordial adiabatic fluctuations: radiative damping and non-<lb/>linear dissipation are effective at destroying them, Fragment-<lb/>ation after decoupling remains a possibility, however. Residual <lb/>radiation fluctuations associated with primordial isothermal <lb/>density fluctuations are about a factor 5 below current obser-<lb/>vational limits. Confirmation of radiation fluctuations requires <lb/>measurement of  6 T / T -<lb/> and attainment of this level of <lb/> sensitivity is an extremely worthwhile goal. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgements <lb/> This research has been supported in part by NASA under grant <lb/>NGR 05-003-578. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. Lifshitz, E.  M.,  J. Phys. (USSR) 10, 116 (1946). <lb/> 2. Gamow, G. and Teller, E.. Phys. Rev.  55,  654 (1939) <lb/>3. Silk, J., Astrophys. J. 151, 659 (1968). <lb/>4. Weinberg, S., Astrophys. J. 168, 175 (1971). <lb/> 5. Chibisov, G. V., Sov. Astron. 16, 56 (1973). <lb/> 6. Silk, J., Confrontation of Cosmological Theories with Observational <lb/>Data, I.A.U. Symp. 63, ed. M. Longair (Dordrecht: D. Reidel). p. <lb/>175, (1974). <lb/>7. Sunyaev, R. A. and Zel&apos;dovich, Ya. B., Astrophys. Sp. Sci. 7. 1 <lb/> (1970). <lb/> 8. Peebles, P. J. E. and Yu, J. T.: Astrophys. J. 162, 815 (1970). <lb/>9. Doroshkevich, A. G., Zel&apos;dovich, .Tu. B. and Sunyaev, R. A., Sov. <lb/>Astron. 22, 523 (1978). <lb/>10. Fall,  S.  M.,  Proc. 9th Texas Symp. on Rel. Astrophys. (in press) <lb/> (  19 79). <lb/>11. Press, W. T. and Vishniac, E. T. (preprint, 1979). <lb/>12. Davis,  M.  and Boynton, P. (preprint, 1979). <lb/>13. Partridge, R.  B.  (preprint, 1979). <lb/>14. Doroshkevich,A.G. and Shandarin. S. F., 1978, M.N.R.A.S.. 183. <lb/> 21. <lb/> 15. Peebles, P. J. E.. Physica Scripta (in press) (1979). <lb/>16. Silk, J., Astrophys. J.  194,  215 (1974). <lb/>17. Sunyaev, R. A. (preprint, 1978). <lb/>18. Doroshkevich, A. G., Sunyaev, R. A. and Zel&apos;dovich, Ya. B., Con-<lb/>frontation of Cosmological Theories with Observational Data. I.A.U. <lb/>Symp. 63, ed.  M.  Longair (Dordrecht: D. Reidel). p. 213, 1974. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote"> Physica Scripta 21 </note>


	</text>
</tei>
