<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="footnote"> arXiv:cond-mat/9711200v1  20 Nov 1997 <lb/></note>

			<front> The Cooperon and the Random Matrix Model for Type-II Superconductors <lb/> Safi R. Bahcall <lb/> Department of Physics, University of California, Berkeley CA 94720 <lb/> We derive the connection between the Cooperon problem in weak localization theory and the random <lb/>matrix description of type-II superconductors. As magnetic field and disorder increase, an extreme <lb/>type-II superconductor crosses over from a state in which the low energy quasiparticles are primarily <lb/>localized and the density of states is determined by the electronic structure of individual vortices, <lb/>to a &apos;chaotic&apos; state, in which quasiparticles are primarily extended and the density of states is <lb/>determined by the random matrix description. <lb/>PACS numbers: 74.60.-w, 74.25.Jb, 74.50.+r, 05.40.+j <lb/></front>

			<body> I. INTRODUCTION <lb/> In this paper we explore the hypothesis that electrons <lb/>in a superconductor with explicit time-reversal breaking <lb/>pair via random matrix elements. This hypothesis com-<lb/>bines ideas and techniques from three fields of study usu-<lb/>ally considered unrelated: random matrices, type-II su-<lb/>perconductors, and the Cooperon problem of weak local-<lb/>ization. We will show that incorporating these ideas into <lb/>a random matrix model allows us to calculate the density <lb/>of states of a type-II superconductor non-perturbatively <lb/>and leads to new possibilities for investigating chaotic <lb/>behavior in complex quantum systems. <lb/>This section contains brief introductions, with refer-<lb/>ences to extensive reviews, of the main ingredients of <lb/>the theory. In section II we describe the random ma-<lb/>trix model, a generalization of the Anderson description <lb/>of disordered superconductors to superconductors in a <lb/>magnetic field. In section III we derive the connection <lb/>between this description of type-II superconductors and <lb/>the Cooperon. In section IV we show that this connec-<lb/>tion yields the correct answer for the semiclassical upper <lb/>critical field, H  c2  . In section V we discuss the weak field <lb/>limit and the relation between the random matrix model <lb/>and the Abrikosov-Gor&apos;kov theory. Finally, in section <lb/>VI we summarize the principal results and describe open <lb/>questions and further possible areas of research. <lb/> A. Random Matrices <lb/> Random matrices were introduced into theoretical <lb/>physics by Wigner in the 1950&apos;s as a tool for under-<lb/>standing the distribution of energy level spacings and <lb/>widths observed in nuclei [1]. The distribution of level <lb/>spacings in nuclei was compared with the distribution of <lb/>level spacings of a large matrix filled with random (un-<lb/>correlated) matrix elements; quantitatively good agree-<lb/>ment was eventually found [2]. The idea of comparing the <lb/>level spacings of complex quantum systems with the level <lb/>spacings of random matrices was eventually extended <lb/>to atoms [3], small metallic particles [4], and classically <lb/>chaotic systems [5]. In all of these applications, in con-<lb/>densed matter, atomic, and nuclear physics, the focus has <lb/>been on understanding the distribution of the spacings of <lb/>energy levels, that is, the probability P (E, x)dx that the <lb/>neighbor of a level at energy E has an energy in the range <lb/> E + x to E + x + dx. In contrast, we will use random <lb/>matrices to understand the density of energy levels, that <lb/>is, the number of energy levels ρ(E)dE in the range E to <lb/> E + dE. <lb/> Random matrices have also been studied in the con-<lb/>text of field theory, spurred by &apos;t Hooft and Brezin et <lb/>al.&apos;s discovery of the connection with the large-N limit <lb/>of certain SU(N)-invariant field theories [6]. A connec-<lb/>tion between the Feynmann diagram expansion for ran-<lb/>dom matrix theories and the sum over random surfaces <lb/>in two-dimensional quantum gravity was also established <lb/>[7]. More recently, random matrices have resurfaced as <lb/>a possible unification of various string theories [8], and <lb/>as a concrete example of a more general theory of &quot; non-<lb/>commuting random variables &quot; [9]. <lb/>Extensive recent reviews can be found in Refs. [10] and <lb/>[11]. <lb/> B. Type-II Superconductors <lb/> The BCS theory [12] describes the electronic properties <lb/>of ideal, uniform superconductors; it applies to the interi-<lb/>ors of type-I superconductors, which expel magnetic field, <lb/>or to type-II superconductors below the field of first pen-<lb/>etration, H  c1  . The presence of a magnetic field, which <lb/>occurs for type-II superconductors in the mixed state, <lb/> H  c1  &lt; H &lt; H  c2  , makes the calculation of electronic <lb/>properties significantly more complicated. The magnetic <lb/>field destroys both the spatial uniformity and the time-<lb/>reversal symmetry implicit in the BCS description. <lb/>Magnetic field penetrates a superconductor in the form <lb/>of tubes of magnetic flux (vortices) enclosing circulat-<lb/>ing quasiparticle currents. These currents lead to elec-<lb/>tronic states which are bound to individual vortices. Such <lb/>states are not only spatially inhomogeneous, but may <lb/></body>

			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<body> overlap strongly with neighboring vortices and form en-<lb/>ergy bands, the details of which will be sensitive to the <lb/>presence of disorder or the deviations from an ideal vor-<lb/>tex lattice that are found in most materials. <lb/>It is possible to attack the problem of the electronic <lb/>properties of type-II superconductors numerically. For a <lb/>fixed type of vortex lattice, a large unit cell can be con-<lb/>sidered which contains one or more vortices. Either the <lb/>full Bogoliubov-de Gennes equations [13] or the approx-<lb/>imate Eilenberger equations [14] (derived by assuming <lb/>slow variations on the scale of the Fermi wavelength) may <lb/>be solved to obtain the quasiparticle eigenstates [15,16]. <lb/>The numerical approach to the electronic properties of <lb/>type-II superconductors has several drawbacks: (1) It is <lb/>difficult to get useful results numerically, both because of <lb/>the large number of electrons per unit cell for realistic ma-<lb/>terials and because of the widely different energy scales in <lb/>the problem. (The cyclotron frequency is much less than <lb/>the BCS gap, which is in turn much less than the Debye <lb/>energy.) (2) In a magnetic field, unlike conventional su-<lb/>perconductors at zero field, the electronic properties are <lb/>sensitive to disorder. The highly idealized impurity-free <lb/>perfect vortex lattice is unrealistic for most materials. <lb/>(3) The numerical approach calculates every quasipar-<lb/>ticle wavefunction in the superconductor. This is often <lb/>an overkill: for many applications we need much less in-<lb/>formation, for example, just the single-particle density <lb/>of states. An approach which is simpler and more gen-<lb/>eral than numerically solving the Bogoliubov-de Gennes <lb/>equations is desirable. <lb/>Analytically manageable extensions of the BCS theory <lb/>to disordered superconductors were given both by An-<lb/>derson [17] and by Abrikosov and Gor&apos;kov [18]. Ander-<lb/>son generalized the BCS description to show that non-<lb/>magnetic impurities have little effect on conventional su-<lb/>perconductors. Abrikosov and Gor&apos;kov introduced a di-<lb/>agrammatic technique to include the effects of a random <lb/>ensemble of impurities, and showed that magnetic impu-<lb/>rities can suppress superconductivity. <lb/>Neither the Anderson nor the Abrikosov-Gor&apos;kov de-<lb/>scription, however, applies directly to the mixed state <lb/>of type-II superconductors. The Abrikosov-Gor&apos;kov de-<lb/>scription requires spatial homogeneity, which is violated <lb/>in the mixed state, and, in order to apply to a type-II <lb/>superconductor, must assume that random magnetic im-<lb/>purities are equivalent to an applied magnetic field [19]. <lb/>The Anderson description is more general, in the sense <lb/>that it is not tied to the assumption of averaging over a <lb/>random ensemble of impurities, however it requires both <lb/>time-reversal symmetry and spatial homogeneity. The <lb/>method described below can be considered a generaliza-<lb/>tion of the Anderson description which has neither of <lb/>these constraints. <lb/> C. The Cooperon <lb/> The problem of the localization of a quantum particle <lb/>by a random potential was originally posed by Ander-<lb/>son in 1958 [20], in the context of understanding metal-<lb/>insulator transitions, and has led to a large body of work <lb/>on the subject of the quantum effects of disorder in met-<lb/>als. The field has been summarized in a number of recent <lb/>reviews [21–24]. <lb/>One of the theoretical approaches to understanding the <lb/>quantum effects of disorder is impurity-averaged pertur-<lb/>bation theory [18,25]. For non-interacting electrons scat-<lb/>tered by rigid impurities, Green&apos;s functions may be ex-<lb/>panded perturbatively in the impurity potential. Averag-<lb/>ing over a random ensemble of impurity potentials yields <lb/>classes of diagrams which can be organized by the powers <lb/>of k  F  ℓ they contain, where k  F  is the Fermi momentum <lb/>and ℓ is the mean free path. Diagrams within a given <lb/>class may be summed, resulting in a series expansion in <lb/> k  F  ℓ for the desired Green&apos;s function. <lb/>Impurity-averaged perturbation theory can be used to <lb/>calculate the conductivity of an electron gas in the pres-<lb/>ence of random disorder. The conductivity is related <lb/>to the current-current response function by the Kubo-<lb/>Greenwood formula, and the impurity diagrams for the <lb/>current-current response function can be summed. It was <lb/>recognized early on that a certain class of diagrams, the <lb/>maximally crossed ones, yield a significant quantum cor-<lb/>rection to the classical conductivity [26]. This estimate <lb/>for the quantum correction was used as support for the <lb/>scaling theory of localization [27,28]. <lb/>The maximally crossed diagrams for the current-cur-<lb/>rent response function (a particle-hole response function) <lb/>can be related by time-reversal to ladder diagrams for a <lb/>response function in the particle-particle channel. The <lb/>impurity-averaged particle-particle response function was <lb/>called the &apos;Cooperon&apos; by Altshuler et al. [29,30]. It is this <lb/>response function, the Cooperon, originally used to study <lb/>the conductivity of a disordered electron gas, which ap-<lb/>pears in the random matrix description of type-II super-<lb/>conductors described below. <lb/> II. RANDOM MATRIX MODEL <lb/> The starting point for an electronic description of type-<lb/>II superconductors is the Hamiltonian [31] <lb/> H = <lb/> dr c <lb/>  † <lb/> r σ  H  0  (r)c  r σ  − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> V  0  Ω <lb/> dr c <lb/>  † <lb/> rσ  c <lb/>  † <lb/> rσ  ′  c  rσ  ′  c  rσ  . (1) <lb/>Here Ω is the system volume, V  0  &gt; 0 represents an at-<lb/>tractive short-ranged interaction, the creation operators <lb/>satisfy <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body> {c  rσ  , c <lb/>  † <lb/> r  ′  σ  ′  } = δ  σσ  ′  δ <lb/> 3  (r − r <lb/> ′  ) <lb/> {c  rσ  , c  r  ′  σ  ′  } = {c <lb/>  † <lb/> rσ  , c <lb/>  † <lb/> r  ′  σ  ′  } = 0 , <lb/> and the bare Hamiltonian H  0  is <lb/> H  0  (r) ≡ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2m <lb/> i∇ − <lb/> e <lb/>c <lb/> A(r) <lb/>  2 <lb/> + U (r) − E  F  , <lb/> (2) <lb/>with U (r) the potential due to a static distribution of im-<lb/>purities. The creation operators in the interaction term <lb/>in Eq. (1) are understood to be superpositions of opera-<lb/>tors which create states only near the Fermi surface, that <lb/>is, c  r  = <lb/> dp exp(ip · r) c  p  θ  p  , where the theta-function <lb/>limits the energy to be within a Debye frequency of the <lb/>Fermi energy: θ  p  ≡ θ(ω  D  − |ε  p  − E  F  |). In the weak-<lb/>coupling limit, where the range of the attractive poten-<lb/>tial is much smaller than the extent of a Cooper pair <lb/>(v  F  /ω  D  ≪ v  F  /∆  0  ), the interaction term may be consid-<lb/>ered local [32]. <lb/>The variational approach to the Hamiltonian in Eq. <lb/>(1) is defined by <lb/> H <lb/> ′  = <lb/> dr Ψ <lb/>  † <lb/> r <lb/> H  0  (r) Φ(r) <lb/>Φ <lb/>  *  (r) −H <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (r) <lb/> Ψ  r  , <lb/> (3) <lb/>where <lb/>Ψ <lb/>  † <lb/> r  ≡ <lb/> c <lb/>  † <lb/> r↑  c  r↓ <lb/> . <lb/> The order parameter Φ(r) is determined self-consistently <lb/>from the equation <lb/>Φ(r) = −V  0  Ω c  r↑  c  r↓  . <lb/> (4) <lb/>For a pure system (U = 0) with no magnetic field, plane <lb/>waves diagonalize the bare Hamiltonian H  0  . If the or-<lb/>der parameter is assumed to be a constant, Φ(r) = ∆  0  , <lb/>then Eq. (3) separates into 2 × 2 matrices. This yields <lb/>the standard BCS results: the spectrum is given by <lb/> E  k  = <lb/> ε  2 <lb/> k  + ∆  2 <lb/>0  , where ε  k  = k <lb/> 2  /2m − E  F  , and Eq. <lb/>(4) becomes the BCS gap equation ρ  0  V  0 <lb/> dε  k  /2E  k  = 1, <lb/>with ρ  0  the density of states at the Fermi level. <lb/>In the case of a system with impurities (U  = 0), but <lb/>with no magnetic field, a similar result holds, as shown <lb/>by Anderson [17]. If we write the eigenstates of the bare <lb/>Hamiltonian as <lb/> H  0  (H = 0) ψ <lb/> 0 <lb/> α  = ε  α  ψ <lb/> 0 <lb/> α <lb/> (5) <lb/>and rotate to a basis defined by these eigenstates, <lb/> c <lb/>  † <lb/> ασ  ≡ <lb/> dr ψ <lb/> 0 <lb/> α  (r) c <lb/>  † <lb/> rσ  , <lb/> (6) <lb/>then the off-diagonal, pairing term in H <lb/> ′  becomes <lb/> dr Φ(r) c  r↑  c  r↓  = ˜ <lb/>∆ <lb/> αβ <lb/> c  α↑  c  β↓  A <lb/> 0 <lb/> αβ  , <lb/> (7) <lb/>where <lb/> A <lb/> 0 <lb/> αβ  ≡ <lb/> dr ψ <lb/> 0 <lb/> α  (r)ψ <lb/> 0 <lb/> β  (r) . <lb/> (8) <lb/>Note that we explicitly assume that the order parameter <lb/>is spatially homogeneous: Φ(r) = ˜ <lb/>∆. The time-reversal <lb/>symmetry of the system (no magnetic field, no magnetic <lb/>impurities) implies that H  0  = H <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  and therefore a basis <lb/>may be chosen in which ψ <lb/> 0 <lb/> α  = ψ <lb/> 0 * <lb/> α  . The overlap integral <lb/>in Eq. (8) then yields <lb/> A <lb/> 0 <lb/> αβ  = δ  αβ <lb/> (9) <lb/>The Hamiltonian H <lb/> ′  again factorizes into 2 × 2 matrices, <lb/>the spectrum is again given by E  α  = <lb/> ε  2 <lb/> α  + ˜ <lb/>∆  2  and solv-<lb/>ing the self-consistency equation yields the same result as <lb/>in the impurity free case (assuming the density of states <lb/>at the Fermi level is unchanged): ˜ <lb/>∆ = ∆  0  . <lb/>The random matrix description we will use for type-II <lb/>superconductors [33] is a generalization of the Ander-<lb/>son description in the sense that we start by using ex-<lb/>act eigenstates of the bare Hamiltonian H  0  as a basis. <lb/>This includes whatever vortex or impurity distribution is <lb/>present. The eigenstates are <lb/> H  0  ψ  α  = ε  α  ψ  α  , <lb/> (10) <lb/>and we rotate to the basis <lb/> c  ασ  ≡ <lb/> dr ψ  α  (r) c  rσ  . <lb/> (11) <lb/>There are two important differences from the zero mag-<lb/>netic field case. First, the order parameter will no <lb/>longer be spatially homogeneous; the phase winds rapidly <lb/>throughout the superconductor (by 2π near the center of <lb/>each vortex) and the magnitude vanishes at the center of <lb/>each vortex. In order to extract a typical measure of the <lb/>magnitude of the superconductivity, we define <lb/>Φ(r) ≡ φ χ(r) , <lb/> (12) <lb/>where χ(r) is normalized so that <lb/> |χ(r)| <lb/> 2  dr = Ω. Hence <lb/> φ <lb/> 2  is the spatial average of the magnitude of the order <lb/>parameter. Second, we no longer have time-reversal sym-<lb/>metry, because of the applied magnetic field. We still <lb/>define the pairing matrix as <lb/> A  αβ  ≡ <lb/> dr χ(r) ψ  α  (r) ψ  β  (r) , <lb/> (13) <lb/>but we no longer have A  αβ  = δ  αβ  . Specifically, writing <lb/> A  αβ  = g  αβ  h <lb/> 1/2  (ε  α  − ε  β  ) , <lb/> (14) <lb/>then in zero magnetic field we have h(ε  α  − ε  β  ) = δ  αβ  . <lb/>In the next section we will show that for a randomly <lb/>disordered electron gas in a magnetic field, the δ-function <lb/></body>

			<page> 3 <lb/></page>

			<body> distribution for h(ε) broadens by an amount proportional <lb/>to the magnetic field. <lb/>The motivation behind the random matrix model is <lb/>that g  αβ  is a material-specific, rapidly varying complex <lb/>function, the details of which should not affect the den-<lb/>sity of states averaged over a random ensemble of dis-<lb/>ordered superconductors. The average density of states <lb/>is sensitive to the overall structure of the pairing matrix <lb/>elements – the broadening of the zero-field δ-function dis-<lb/>tribution of h(ε) – but not to the rapidly varying O(1) <lb/> complex numbers which multiply it. <lb/>The basic assumption of the random matrix model is <lb/>therefore that average properties of an ensemble of super-<lb/>conductors can be modeled by choosing complex numbers <lb/> g  αβ  from a random, uncorrelated distribution: <lb/> g  αβ  g <lb/>  * <lb/> α  ′  β  ′ <lb/> av <lb/> = δ  αα  ′  δ  ββ  ′  , <lb/> (15) <lb/>where the brackets denote an average over the distribu-<lb/>tion: [X]  av  ≡ (1/N  µ  ) <lb/>  Nµ <lb/>µ=1  X <lb/> (µ)  . The particular choice <lb/>of symmetry for g  αβ  , whether real symmetric (GOE), <lb/>Hermitian (GUE), or complex symmetric, will affect the <lb/>eigenvalue spacing distribution but will not affect the <lb/>density of states in the large matrix size limit. <lb/>Using the above definitions for Φ(r) and A, and rotat-<lb/>ing to the basis of bare eigenstates defined by Eq. (11), <lb/>the Hamiltonian in Eq. (3) becomes <lb/> H <lb/> ′  = <lb/> Ψ <lb/>  † <lb/> E  0  φ A <lb/> φ A <lb/>  †  −E  0 <lb/> Ψ , <lb/> (16) <lb/>where E  0  = diag(. . . ε  α  . . .) is the diagonal matrix of the <lb/>eigenvalues of H  0  , and <lb/> Ψ <lb/>  †  = [. . . c <lb/>  † <lb/> α↑  . . . . . . c  β↓  . . .]. The <lb/>assumption of uncorrelated random numbers for g  αβ  al-<lb/>lows us to determine exactly, in the large matrix limit, <lb/>the Green&apos;s functions of H <lb/> ′  [33]. <lb/> III. THE PAIRING MATRIX AND THE <lb/>COOPERON <lb/> The random matrix assumption for g  αβ  lets us write <lb/>down integral equations for the Green&apos;s functions of the <lb/>Hamiltonian H <lb/> ′  for any value of φ, the overall strength <lb/>of the pairing, and h(ω), the average pairing amplitude <lb/>defined in Eq. (14). This will only be useful in comparing <lb/>with experiment if we have some prediction for, or theo-<lb/>retical understanding of, the pairing amplitude h(ω). For <lb/>a diffusive system, and a disordered vortex lattice, there <lb/>is a simple prediction. <lb/>We can rewrite Eq. (14) to express h(ω) in terms of the <lb/>average squared matrix element as a function of energy <lb/>difference: <lb/> h(ω) = <lb/>1 <lb/> N ρ  0 <lb/> αβ <lb/> |A  αβ  | <lb/> 2  δ(ω − ε  α  + ε  β  ) <lb/> av <lb/> , (17) <lb/>where the brackets denote averaging over the random <lb/>ensemble. The density of levels of the normal metal, <lb/> ρ  0  ≡ ρ(E  F  ), is assumed to be independent of energy <lb/>in the narrow range about the Fermi energy relevant to <lb/>superconductivity. The total number of levels that are <lb/>being paired in H <lb/> ′  , which determines the size N of the <lb/>matrix, is the level density times the maximum pairing <lb/>energy. This cutoff is usually taken to be the Debye en-<lb/>ergy, so N = ρ  0  ω  D  . The normalization factor 1/N ρ  0  in <lb/>Eq. (17) follows from Eq. (14) and the continuous limit <lb/>for the energy levels: <lb/> α  → <lb/> dε  α  ρ(ε  α  ). <lb/>Note also that we will always be interested in the limit <lb/>where N → ∞, because ω  D  is much larger than the level <lb/>spacing (as well as the pairing strength φ and the bare <lb/>BCS gap ∆  0  ). In order for the Hamiltonian H <lb/> ′  in Eq. <lb/>(16) to be interesting in that limit, the matrix elements <lb/> A  αβ  must be O(1/ <lb/> √ <lb/> N ). (This is easy to see with per-<lb/>turbation theory: the shift in energy of some level ε  α  is <lb/> δε  α  = φ <lb/> 2 <lb/> β  |A  αβ  | <lb/> 2  /(ε  α  + ε  β  ). The N terms in the sum <lb/>must be canceled by a 1/N factor from |A  αβ  | <lb/> 2  .) <lb/>Inserting Eq. (13) for A  αβ  into Eq. (17) yields <lb/> h(ω) = <lb/>1 <lb/> N ρ  0 <lb/> αβ <lb/> dr dr <lb/> ′  ψ  α  (r)ψ  β  (r)ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> α  (r <lb/> ′  )ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> β  (r <lb/> ′  ) <lb/> × χ(r)χ <lb/>  *  (r <lb/> ′  ) δ(ω − ε  α  + ε  β  ) <lb/> av <lb/> . (18) <lb/>We can insert a factor of 1 = <lb/> dE δ(E − ε  α  ) and write <lb/>this as <lb/> h(ω) = <lb/>(2π) <lb/> −2 <lb/> N ρ  0 <lb/> dr dr <lb/> ′  dE <lb/> δG  0  (r, r <lb/> ′  , E) <lb/> × δG  0  (r, r <lb/> ′  , E + ω) χ(r)χ <lb/>  *  (r <lb/> ′  ) <lb/> av <lb/> , (19) <lb/>where the bare single particle Green&apos;s functions are <lb/> δG  0  ≡ G <lb/> + <lb/>0  − G <lb/> − <lb/> 0 <lb/> G <lb/> ± <lb/> 0  (r, r <lb/> ′  , E) ≡ <lb/> α <lb/> ψ  α  (r)ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> α  (r <lb/> ′  ) <lb/> E − ε  α  ± i0  +  . <lb/> To make further progress, we will need to make a key <lb/>assumption: that there is, on average, no correlation be-<lb/>tween the bare single particle Green&apos;s functions G <lb/> ± <lb/> 0  and <lb/>the order parameter product χ(r)χ <lb/>  *  (r <lb/> ′  ) appearing above: <lb/> G <lb/> ± <lb/> 0  G <lb/> ± <lb/> 0  χχ <lb/>  * <lb/> av <lb/> = <lb/> G <lb/> ± <lb/> 0  G <lb/> ± <lb/> 0 <lb/> av <lb/> χχ <lb/>  * <lb/> av <lb/> . <lb/> (20) <lb/>The wavefunctions which enter G  0  are the eigenstates of <lb/>the bare Hamiltonian H  0  , not the eigenstates of the full <lb/>superconducting Hamiltonian. Hence the assumption is <lb/>that the product of the bare Green&apos;s functions is uncorre-<lb/>lated, on average, with the order parameter, that is, the <lb/>positions of the vortices. Below, we will only be inter-<lb/>ested in the case in which the magnetic field is nearly uni-<lb/>form within the superconductor, H ≫ H  c1  . In this limit, <lb/>since the magnetic field in H  0  is uniform, the positions <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body> of the vortices affect G  0  only through a gauge-dependent <lb/>phase. The quantity we are interested in, h(ω), is gauge-<lb/>invariant. Therefore, with the gauge-invariance of the <lb/>product of the two terms properly maintained, and for <lb/> H ≫ H  c1  , there are no additional correlations between <lb/>the bare Green&apos;s functions and the order parameter. <lb/>With the average over the order parameter product <lb/>written as <lb/> χ(r)χ <lb/>  *  (r <lb/> ′  ) <lb/> av <lb/> ≡ g(r, r <lb/> ′  ) , <lb/> (21) <lb/>the expression for h(ω) then becomes <lb/> h(ω) = <lb/>(2π) <lb/> −2 <lb/> N ρ  0 <lb/> Re <lb/> dr dr <lb/> ′ <lb/> dE G <lb/> + <lb/>0  (r, r <lb/> ′  , E) <lb/> × G <lb/> − <lb/> 0  (r, r <lb/> ′  , E + ω) <lb/> av <lb/> g(r, r <lb/> ′  ) , (22) <lb/>where we have used the identity <lb/> G <lb/> + <lb/>0  (r, r <lb/> ′  , E) G <lb/> − <lb/> 0  (r, r <lb/> ′  , E + ω) <lb/>  * <lb/> = <lb/> G <lb/> − <lb/> 0  (r <lb/> ′  , r, E) G <lb/> + <lb/>0  (r <lb/> ′  , r, E + ω) <lb/> (23) <lb/>and we omit the terms involving G <lb/> −  G <lb/> −  and G <lb/> +  G <lb/> +  be-<lb/>cause they do not contribute. <lb/>As mentioned in the introduction, in weak localiza-<lb/>tion theory quantum corrections to classical transport <lb/>are calculated by studying averaged values of response <lb/>functions of non-interacting electrons in a random disor-<lb/>der potential. The quantity in brackets in Eq. (22) is one <lb/>such disorder-averaged response function: the Cooperon <lb/>[29,30]. <lb/>The order of r and r <lb/> ′  in Eq. (22) is important. If <lb/>the single particle Green&apos;s functions appeared in the <lb/>form G  0  (r, r <lb/> ′  , E) G  0  (r <lb/> ′  , r, E + ω), the quantity in brack-<lb/>ets would be just the real-space Fourier transform of the <lb/>usual density-density response function. It is because <lb/> A  αβ  is a matrix element for electrons in a Cooper pair <lb/>(the overlap between ψ  α  and ψ  β  rather than ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> α  and ψ  β  ), <lb/>that the order of r and r <lb/> ′  is reversed, and the bracketed <lb/>quantity in Eq. (22) is the Cooperon rather than the <lb/>diffuson. <lb/>The Cooperon response function C(r, r <lb/> ′  , ω) is defined <lb/>as <lb/> C(r, r <lb/> ′  , ω) = <lb/> dE G <lb/> + <lb/>0  (r, r <lb/> ′  , E) G <lb/> − <lb/> 0  (r, r <lb/> ′  , E + ω) <lb/> av <lb/> . <lb/> (24) <lb/>This response function, in the limit in which the mean <lb/>free path is much smaller than the magnetic length but <lb/>much larger than the Fermi wavelength (λ  F  ≪ ℓ ≪ ℓ  H  ≡ <lb/> ¯ hc/eH), obeys a diffusive equation of motion [29] <lb/> − iω + D <lb/> i∇ + <lb/>2e <lb/>¯ hc <lb/> A <lb/>  2  <lb/> C(r, r <lb/> ′  , ω) = δ(r − r <lb/> ′  ) . (25) <lb/>The diffusion constant D = v  F  ℓ/d, where d is the space <lb/>dimensionality. This equation defines the Green&apos;s func-<lb/>tion for the Schroedinger equation of a single particle of <lb/>charge 2e in a magnetic field. The solution is therefore <lb/> C(r, r <lb/> ′  , ω) = <lb/> nk <lb/>  dk  z <lb/> 2π <lb/> ϕ  nk  (x, y)ϕ <lb/>  * <lb/> nk  (x <lb/> ′  , y <lb/> ′  ) e <lb/> ikz(z−z <lb/> ′  ) <lb/> −iω + (4D/ℓ  2 <lb/> H  )(n + 1/2) + Dk  2 <lb/> z <lb/> , (26) <lb/>where ϕ  nk  (x, y) are normalized 2D Landau level wave-<lb/>functions and we assume a uniform magnetic field H <lb/> (valid for H ≫ H  c1  ). <lb/>This solution is not sufficient to evaluate h(ω); we also <lb/>need to know the order parameter correlation, g(r, r <lb/> ′  ), <lb/>defined by Eqs. (12) and (21). The phase of the order <lb/>parameter winds by 2π around each vortex. In a su-<lb/>perconductor with a perfectly periodic vortex lattice we <lb/>expect Φ(r)Φ <lb/>  *  (r <lb/> ′  ) to reflect the long-range ordered struc-<lb/>ture of the vortex lattice. Averaged over an ensemble <lb/>of disordered materials, however, the phase will disorder <lb/>on the length scale set by the inter-vortex spacing ℓ  H  . <lb/>Therefore we will assume that the averaged correlation <lb/>function has the form <lb/> g(r, r <lb/> ′  ) = e <lb/> −|r−r <lb/> ′  | <lb/> 2  /ℓ <lb/> 2 <lb/> H  e <lb/> iθgauge(r,r <lb/> ′  )  . <lb/> (27) <lb/>The gauge-dependent phase factor is required to keep the <lb/>product C(r, r <lb/> ′  , ω)g(r, r <lb/> ′  ) gauge-invariant. In the Landau <lb/>gauge A = Hxˆ , we have θ  gauge  (r, r <lb/> ′  ) = (x + x <lb/> ′  )(y − <lb/> y <lb/> ′  )/2ℓ <lb/> 2 <lb/> H  . <lb/>The form of |g(r, r <lb/> ′  )| is an additional assumption that <lb/>is necessary for evaluating h(ω). It is not essential that <lb/>this form be Gaussian. However, the Gaussian form is <lb/>natural for a random system, and also has the property <lb/>that the result for h(ω) is particularly simple. <lb/>We now substitute the expressions for C(r, r <lb/> ′  , ω) and <lb/> g(r, r <lb/> ′  ), Eqs. (26) and (27), into Eq. (22). The integral <lb/>over z − z <lb/> ′  sets k  z  = 0 in the denominator. The Gaus-<lb/>sian form for g(r, r <lb/> ′  ) can be written as |g| = <lb/> √ π h  0  ((x − <lb/> x <lb/> ′  )/ℓ  H  )h  0  ((y − y <lb/> ′  )/ℓ  H  ), where h  n  (u) are the normalized <lb/>harmonic oscillator eigenstates (Hermite functions). The <lb/>2D Landau level wavefunctions in Landau gauge have <lb/>the form ϕ  nk  (x, y) = A exp(ikx) h  n  (kℓ  H  / <lb/> √ <lb/> 2 + <lb/> √ <lb/> 2y/ℓ  H  ). <lb/>Rewriting the product in Eq. (26) using the identity <lb/> h  n  (a)h  n  (b) = <lb/> j  C <lb/> j <lb/>nn  h  2n−j  ((a + b)/ <lb/> √ <lb/> 2)h  j  ((a − b)/ <lb/> √ <lb/> 2) <lb/>[34], we see that the spatial integrals in Eq. (22) and the <lb/>orthogonality of the Hermite functions set n = 0. The <lb/>final result is therefore that only the vanishing n and k  z <lb/> terms survive in the sums in Eq. (26). This yields for <lb/> h(ω): <lb/>h(ω) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2πρ  0 <lb/> W <lb/>ω  2  + W  2  , <lb/> (28) <lb/>where the width W is <lb/> W = 2¯ hD/ℓ <lb/> 2 <lb/> H  = 2eDH/c , <lb/> (29) <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body> and we have normalized to ρ  0 <lb/> dω h(ω) = 1. <lb/>The Lorentzian form for h(ω), Eq. (28), is what might <lb/>be expected on general grounds in a diffusive system <lb/>where the time-evolution of pair correlations obeys an <lb/>exponential decay law. This point was discussed by de <lb/>Gennes in the context of the &quot; ergodic evolution of the <lb/>time-reversal operator &quot; [35]. de Gennes considered the <lb/>problem of evaluating the transition temperature T  c  (H) <lb/>for a general superconducting system in a magnetic field <lb/>described by the variational Hamiltonian in Eq. (3). He <lb/>used a perturbative expansion in the order parameter <lb/>Φ(r), which is valid near the phase transition, and found <lb/>that the average over single-particle wavefunctions which <lb/>appears in Eq. (18) is the kernel operator acting on Φ(r) <lb/>in the gap equation. de Gennes related that average over <lb/>single-particle wavefunctions to the time evolution of the <lb/>time-reversal operator, K(t), for one electron moving in <lb/>the potential described by the Hamiltonian H  0  (Eq. (2)). <lb/>An &quot; ergodic &quot; system was defined as one in which the <lb/>motion of the electron is diffusive, in the sense that the <lb/>time-reversal operator decays exponentially with time: <lb/>lim <lb/> t→∞ <lb/> K <lb/>  †  (0)K(t) = e <lb/> −t/τ  . <lb/> (30) <lb/>For a system defined as ergodic in this sense, h(ω), which <lb/>is the power spectrum of the operator K(t), has the <lb/>Lorentzian form given in Eq. (28), with W = τ <lb/> −1  . <lb/>The interesting result here is that the average over <lb/>the single-particle wavefunctions in Eq. (18) appears not <lb/>only in the equation for T  c  (H), but also in the random <lb/>matrix description of the pairing Hamiltonian. The func-<lb/>tional form of h(ω) and the random matrix technique al-<lb/>low us to go beyond perturbation theory and therefore <lb/>beyond calculating T  c  (H). At any field for which the <lb/>random matrix element hypothesis is valid, we can ob-<lb/>tain the full Green&apos;s functions non-perturbatively. <lb/>We note also that the connection with &quot; ergodic super-<lb/>conductors &quot; suggests that the random matrix description <lb/>may apply, in addition to the bulk disordered systems <lb/>considered here, to other systems discussed by de Gennes <lb/> et al. as being ergodic, for example, thin films and su-<lb/>perconducting nanoparticles [35,36]. <lb/> IV. UPPER CRITICAL FIELD <lb/> Using Eqs. (28) and (29) we may derive a relation be-<lb/>tween the upper critical field H  c2  and the diffusion con-<lb/>stant D. This will allow us to test whether the formalism <lb/>described in the previous section yields a result consistent <lb/>with the prediction of the semiclassical theory of type-II <lb/>superconductors. That theory is based on the pertur-<lb/>bative solution of the Gor&apos;kov equations near H  c2  using <lb/>semiclassical Green&apos;s functions to include the effects of <lb/>the magnetic field. <lb/>The difference in energy between the normal metal <lb/>ground state of the Hamiltonian in Eq. (3), given by <lb/> φ = 0, and the superconducting ground state, is, to sec-<lb/>ond order in φ: <lb/> ∆E = φ <lb/> 2 <lb/>  <lb/> 1 <lb/> V  0 <lb/> − <lb/> αβ <lb/> |A  αβ  | <lb/> 2 <lb/> |ε  α  + ε  β  | <lb/> θ(ε  α  ε  β  ) <lb/>  <lb/> + O(φ <lb/> 4  ) . (31) <lb/>The |A  αβ  | <lb/> 2  term is second order perturbation theory for <lb/>the Hamiltonian Eq. (3), where θ(x) is the step func-<lb/>tion (for non-zero temperatures, θ(ε  α  ε  β  ) is replaced by <lb/>[tanh(ε  α  /2T )+tanh(ε  β  /2T )]/2) and the upper cutoffs for <lb/>the energies are |ε  α  | &lt; ω  D  , |ε  β  | &lt; ω  D  . The 1/V  0  term is <lb/>the usual Hartree-Fock self-consistency contribution and <lb/>follows from <lb/> dr Φ(r)c  r↑  c  r↓  and Φ(r) = −ΩV  0  c  r↑  c  r↓  . <lb/> We must ignore small non-perturbative effects [37] (the <lb/>breakdown of second-order perturbation theory), in order <lb/>to reproduce the semiclassical limit. <lb/>The upper critical field is the field H  c2  at which the <lb/>quantity in brackets in Eq. (31) vanishes. At lower fields, <lb/>the coefficient of φ <lb/> 2  is negative and φ &gt; 0 minimizes the <lb/>energy; at higher fields, the coefficient of φ <lb/> 2  is positive <lb/>and φ = 0 minimizes the energy. <lb/>Averaging over the ensemble amounts to replacing <lb/> |A  αβ  | <lb/> 2  in Eq. (31) by its average value h(ε  α  −ε  β  ). Taking <lb/>the continuum limit for the energies, inserting Eq. (28) <lb/>for h(ν), and using the definition of the BCS coupling <lb/>constant, 1/g ≡ 1/ρ  0  V  0  , yields that the O(φ <lb/> 2  ) term in <lb/>Eq. (31) vanishes when <lb/>1 <lb/> g <lb/> = <lb/>2 <lb/> π <lb/>  ωD <lb/> 0 <lb/>  ωD <lb/> 0 <lb/> dε  α  dε  β <lb/> ε  α  + ε  β <lb/> W <lb/> (ε  α  − ε  β  )  2  + W  2  . (32) <lb/>Performing the integrals yields <lb/>1 <lb/> g <lb/> = log <lb/> 2ω  D <lb/> W <lb/> 1 + O <lb/> W <lb/>ω  D <lb/> . <lb/> (33) <lb/>In the weak coupling limit W/ω  D  → 0. Subtracting the <lb/>zero-field BCS result, <lb/>1 <lb/> g <lb/> = log <lb/> 2ω  D <lb/> ∆  0 <lb/> , <lb/> (34) <lb/>where ∆  0  is the zero-field BCS gap, we obtain the equa-<lb/>tion which determines the upper critical field: <lb/> W (H  c2  ) = ∆  0  . <lb/> (35) <lb/>Inserting Eq. (29) for W (H) yields <lb/> H  c2  = <lb/>3 <lb/>2π  2 <lb/> Φ  0 <lb/> ℓ ξ  0 <lb/> , <lb/> (36) <lb/>where ξ  0  = ¯ <lb/> hv  F  /π∆  0  is the zero-field BCS coherence <lb/>length and D = v  F  ℓ/3 in three dimensions. <lb/>This result may be compared with the result derived <lb/>with the semiclassical theory of dirty type-II supercon-<lb/>ductors. The semiclassical approach starts with plane <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body> wave electronic eigenstates, assumes a weak magnetic <lb/>field, and includes the effects of impurities through the <lb/>Abrikosov-Gor&apos;kov impurity averaged perturbation the-<lb/>ory technique. The resulting Gor&apos;kov equations can be <lb/>expanded perturbatively in the order parameter (near <lb/> H  c2  ) and yield the equation which determines H  c2  [38–40] <lb/>ln <lb/> T  c0 <lb/> T <lb/> = −ψ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> + ψ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>+ <lb/> H <lb/> d <lb/>c2  D <lb/> 2 Φ  0  T <lb/> , <lb/> (37) <lb/>where ψ(x) is the digamma function, T  c0  is the zero-field <lb/>critical temperature, and H <lb/> d <lb/>c2  denotes the dirty limit, <lb/> ℓ ≪ ξ  0  . As T → 0 this gives H <lb/> d <lb/>c2  = (3/2π <lb/> 2  )(Φ  0  /ℓξ  0  ), <lb/>in agreement with Eq. (36). <lb/>The agreement with the semiclassical theory shows <lb/>that the random matrix description combined with the <lb/>results from the Cooperon problem reproduces the per-<lb/>turbative result of the more conventional approach to <lb/>understanding dirty type-II superconductors. <lb/> V. CONNECTION WITH ABRIKOSOV-GOR&apos;KOV <lb/>THEORY, AND THE H → 0 LIMIT <lb/> As pointed out in Ref. [33], in the weak field limit, for <lb/>which the T-breaking scale W ≪ ∆  0  , the random matrix <lb/>model described in the previous sections does not yield <lb/>the density of states the zero-field BCS theory. What <lb/>happens in this limit is that the central assumption of the <lb/>model, that the Hamiltonian of the superconductor can <lb/>be well described by a large matrix with random pairing <lb/>elements, breaks down. For small W/∆  0  there exists a <lb/>special basis, discussed below, in which the Hamiltonian <lb/>has a simpler form. The existence of a special basis means <lb/>that correlations have developed which are not obvious <lb/>in the original basis. (As a simple analogy, consider an <lb/>electron in a cylindrically symmetric potential. Random <lb/>matrix elements in a plane wave basis would be a poor <lb/>assumption.) <lb/>To understand what happens to the random matrix <lb/>model of the previous sections in the weak field limit, we <lb/>first write down two additional possible random matrix <lb/>models for superconductors with T-breaking. The first <lb/>of these turns out to be a random matrix formulation of <lb/>the Abrikosov-Gor&apos;kov theory. The second of these we <lb/>will argue describes the weak field limit, H ≪ H  c2  , of a <lb/>superconductor in a magnetic field. <lb/>The theory described in the previous sections we de-<lb/>note by H  I  : <lb/> H  I  = <lb/> E  0  φ A <lb/> φ A <lb/>  †  −E  0 <lb/> , <lb/> (38) <lb/>with A satisfying <lb/> A  ij  A <lb/>  * <lb/> kl <lb/> av <lb/> = δ  ik  δ  jl  h(ε  i  − ε  j  ) . <lb/> As before, E  0  = diag(. . . ε  α  . . .) is a diagonal matrix of <lb/>uniformly distributed eigenvalues. <lb/>A different possible random matrix model occurs if we <lb/>start with BCS and add a random matrix to the diago-<lb/>nal components, in a way which breaks the time-reversal <lb/>symmetry: <lb/> H  II  = <lb/> E  0  ∆ <lb/>∆ −E  0 <lb/> + α <lb/> M 0 <lb/>0 M <lb/> , <lb/> (39) <lb/>with M satisfying <lb/> M  ij  M <lb/>  * <lb/> kl <lb/> av <lb/> = δ  ik  δ  jl  . <lb/>E  0  is a diagonal matrix as in the previous case, ∆ is <lb/>proportional to the identity matrix: ∆ = ∆  0  δ  ij  , α is <lb/>a parameter which measures the amount of T-breaking, <lb/>and M is a random Hermitian matrix with no weighting <lb/>factor h(ε  i  −ε  j  ) in it. The T-breaking in this model is rep-<lb/>resented by the same sign for M in the upper and lower <lb/>diagonal quadrants. Since these quadrants correspond to <lb/>the energies for up-spin electrons and down-spin holes, <lb/>this indicates a potential which has opposite sign for up <lb/>and down spins. In other words, this model appears to <lb/>correspond to random magnetic impurities. In fact, the <lb/>equations for the Green&apos;s functions of this random matrix <lb/>model are the same as the Abrikosov-Gor&apos;kov equations <lb/>for a superconductor in the presence of random magnetic <lb/>impurities. This random matrix model is a reformulation <lb/>of the AG theory [41]. <lb/>The final random matrix model we consider is <lb/> H  III  = <lb/> E  0  ∆ <lb/>∆ −E  0 <lb/> + α  1 <lb/> M <lb/> (1) <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 M <lb/> (1) <lb/> + α  2 <lb/> 0 M <lb/> (2) <lb/> M <lb/> (2) <lb/> 0 <lb/> , <lb/> (40) <lb/>with the matrices M <lb/> (a)  satisfying <lb/> M <lb/> (a) <lb/> ij  M <lb/> (b) * <lb/> kl <lb/> av <lb/> = δ  ab  δ  ik  δ  jl  . <lb/> This differs from H  II  in that a random matrix appears <lb/>in both the diagonal and off-diagonal quadrants. <lb/>How do we best describe a superconductor in the weak <lb/>field limit, H ≪ H  c2  ? The order parameter in a super-<lb/>conductor may be written as <lb/>Φ(r) = f (r) e <lb/> iθ(r)  , <lb/> (41) <lb/>where f (r) is real and θ(r) is a position dependent phase <lb/>that winds by 2π around the center of each vortex. For <lb/>a given material, with some order parameter phase re-<lb/>alization θ(r), we may transform the standard creation <lb/>operators to a new basis defined by <lb/> c  r  → ˜ <lb/> c  r  ≡ c  r  e <lb/> iθ(r)/2  . <lb/> (42) <lb/>In this basis the pairing interaction takes the form <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body> Φ(r) c <lb/>  † <lb/> r↑  c <lb/>  † <lb/> r↓  → f (r) ˜ <lb/> c <lb/>  † <lb/> r↑  <lb/>  † <lb/> r↓  . <lb/> (43) <lb/>The effective order parameter in the new basis is purely <lb/>real. Note that although this has sometimes been called <lb/>a gauge transformation, it is not: the magnetic field <lb/>changes. The vector potential is <lb/> (r) = A(r)+ ∇θ/2e so <lb/>õ <lb/> A(r) · dl  = <lb/> A(r) · dl around a loop enclosing a vortex. <lb/>Physically, we are transforming to a basis in which the <lb/>magnetic field is the previous field distribution plus one <lb/>flux quantum threaded through the center of each vor-<lb/>tex in a direction opposite to that of the applied field. <lb/>This means that far away from an isolated vortex, the <lb/>net effective flux seen by an electron is zero rather one <lb/>flux quantum. In the original basis, the vector potential <lb/> A falls off as 1/r for distances greater than a penetra-<lb/>tion depth away from a single vortex. The transformed <lb/>vector potential, ˜ <lb/> A, follows the superfluid velocity v  s  (r), <lb/>and vanishes exponentially for distances greater than a <lb/>penetration depth. <lb/>The matrix model of the previous sections, H  I  , uses <lb/>as a basis the eigenstates of the full Hamiltonian H  0  , <lb/>which includes the magnetic field. The models described <lb/>by H  II  and H  III  first apply the above transformation, <lb/>then use the the basis defined by the eigenstates of just <lb/>the T-invariant part of the Hamiltonian. This has two <lb/>important effects when the magnetic field is weak. <lb/>First, weak T-breaking implies that the phase gradi-<lb/>ent of the order parameter varies slowly on the scale of <lb/>a coherence length: ξ  0  ∇θ ≪ 2π. Therefore the term in <lb/>the bare Hamiltonian due to the superfluid velocity is <lb/>small compared to the energy gap: (1/m)p · e ˜ <lb/> A(r) ∼ <lb/> v  F  ∇θ ≪ ∆  0  . Second, weak T-breaking in a conven-<lb/>tional superconductor means that the deviation in the <lb/>magnitude of the order parameter from the bare BCS <lb/>value is small: δf /∆  0  ≡ <lb/> (dr/Ω)|f (r) − ∆  0  |/∆  0  ≪ 1. <lb/>In the Ginzburg-Landau description of an isolated vor-<lb/>tex, the order parameter relaxes to the bare value ex-<lb/>ponentially, on the scale of the coherence length. Hence <lb/> δf /∆  0  ∼ ξ <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  /ℓ <lb/> 2 <lb/> H  = H/H  c2  . In a more realistic descrip-<lb/>tion, f (r) may have power-law behavior |f (r) − ∆  0  | ∼ <lb/> (ξ  0  /r) <lb/> n  which yields δf /∆  0  ∼ (H/H  c2  ) <lb/> 1/2  (n = 1), or <lb/> δf /∆  0  ∼ (H/H  c2  ) ln(H  c2  /H) (n = 2). In either case, <lb/>rotating to a basis of the eigenstates of the T-invariant <lb/>part of H  0  for which the order parameter is real yields <lb/>a Hamiltonain which is a small correction to the BCS <lb/>theory. <lb/>The models H  II  and H  III  are defined by the assump-<lb/>tion that the matrix elements of the T-breaking correc-<lb/>tions to the BCS theory are uncorrelated. That is, in <lb/>Eqs. (39) and (40), the matrices M and M <lb/> (1)  (the super-<lb/>fluid velocity correction), and M <lb/> (2)  (the order parameter <lb/>correction), are assumed to be random. The difference <lb/>between the two models is that in H  II  the effect of the <lb/>deviation of the order parameter from the constant mag-<lb/>nitude is ignored, whereas in H  III  it is included. Hence in <lb/> H  II  the pairing is diagonal, ∆  0  δ  ij  , because i|T |j = δ  ij <lb/> (T is the time reversal operator T : ψ  i  (r) → ψ <lb/>  * <lb/> i  (r)), <lb/>while in H  III  , the deviation of the order parameter yields <lb/>an additional correction: i|T f (r)|j = ∆  0  δ  ij  + α  2  M <lb/> (2) <lb/> ij  , <lb/>where α  2  ∼ δf . <lb/>These models describe small corrections to BCS and <lb/>hence properly reproduce the BCS result as H/H  c2  → 0. <lb/>The matrix model of the previous sections, H  I  , can not <lb/>be described as a small correction to BCS. In the weak <lb/>field limit, W/∆  0  ∼ H/H  c2  → 0, so h(ω) → δ(ω). How-<lb/>ever, because the bare level spacing is always assumed to <lb/>be much less than the T-breaking scale (δ  0  ≪ W ), the <lb/>resulting matrix model still pairs many levels with equal, <lb/>random amplitude. This leads to large deviations from <lb/>BCS. For W/∆  0  → 0, the density of states has a node <lb/>near zero energy, ρ(E) ∼ E, rather than a gap as in the <lb/>BCS spectrum [33]. <lb/>At weak fields, or more generally for weak T-breaking, <lb/>when the correction to BCS behavior can be consid-<lb/>ered small, the most appropriate random matrix descrip-<lb/>tion is that of the third model listed above: H  III  . As <lb/>the T-breaking energy scale increases, this description <lb/>must break down. Although the order parameter can <lb/>always be written as the BCS value plus a correction, <lb/> f (r) = ∆  0  + δf (r), the assumption that the matrix ele-<lb/>ment i|T δf (r)|j is random is no longer justifiable when <lb/> δf /∆  0  ∼ 1; f (r) and δf (r) are comparable functions. At <lb/>sufficiently high fields, the only consistent assumption of <lb/>randomness applies to the entire pairing matrix, as as-<lb/>sumed in H  I  . This may called &apos;chaotic&apos; pairing. <lb/>Figure 1 illustrates schematically the different regimes. <lb/>Physically, at low fields, vortices are well separated, <lb/>bound states are confined primarily to individual vor-<lb/>tices, and the effect of the superfluid velocity on extended <lb/>states is small, yielding only a small correction to the or-<lb/>dered BCS state. At higher fields, core states overlap <lb/>significantly and form energy bands, which interact in <lb/>a complicated way with extended states, the superfluid <lb/>velocity, and whatever disorder is present. In the Ander-<lb/>son metal-insulator transition, delocalization is accom-<lb/>panied by a change from ordered (Poisson) statistics to <lb/>chaotic (random matrix) statistics. In a type-II super-<lb/>conductor, we are suggesting that the delocalization due <lb/>to increasing vortex density (increasing magnetic field) <lb/>is accompanied by a transition from a small correction <lb/>to the BCS theory to chaotic pairing. This raises inter-<lb/>esting possibilities and questions, discussed in the next <lb/>section, regarding the nature of such a transition in a <lb/>superconductor. <lb/> VI. SUMMARY AND CONCLUSIONS <lb/> When the disorder and magnetic field are sufficiently <lb/>large in a type-II superconductor, so that electronic <lb/>structure calculations and small deviations from the BCS <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body> theory are no longer applicable, the chaotic pairing pic-<lb/>ture of the random matrix model may apply. The moti-<lb/>vation for the model is that the density of states is not <lb/>sensitive to details of the rapidly varying O(1) factors in <lb/>the matrix elements between electrons in a Cooper pair, <lb/>but rather to the average structure of the pairing matrix. <lb/>In section III we showed that the average amplitude to <lb/>pair electrons is related to the Cooperon response func-<lb/>tion previously discussed in the context of weak localiza-<lb/>tion theory. For a dirty metal this response function may <lb/>be calculated and yields a simple form for the average <lb/>pairing amplitude, characteristic of a diffusive system. <lb/>The connection between the average pairing amplitude <lb/>and diffusion is related to what was called by de Gennes <lb/> &quot; ergodic pairing &quot; . That connection was established by <lb/>de Gennes in the context of evaluating the critical field <lb/>of dirty superconductors, H  c2  , using perturbation theory. <lb/>Here we have shown that this connection exists indepen-<lb/>dent of perturbation theory. This allows us to evaluate <lb/>the density of states for fields far away from the regime <lb/>in which perturbation theory is valid. <lb/>Finally, we considered the weak field limit of the ran-<lb/>dom matrix model, H ≪ H  c2  . At sufficiently weak fields <lb/>the random matrix picture must break down because the <lb/>system must approach the ordered BCS state. This sug-<lb/>gests a crossover between a low-field ordered state, in <lb/>which the corrections to BCS theory are small and can <lb/>be understood as being due to states localized near in-<lb/>dividual vortices, to a high-field chaotic state, in which <lb/>most of the states are extended. A useful analogy is the <lb/>Anderson metal-insulator transition. Instead of varying <lb/>the electron density (chemical potential) from a regime <lb/>of localized states to a regime of delocalized states, in <lb/>the superconductor we vary the vortex density (magnetic <lb/>field) between a regime of bound states to a regime of ex-<lb/>tended states. In the metal-insulator transition we have <lb/>a change in statistics from Poisson to random matrices; <lb/>in the superconductor we have a change in the pairing, <lb/>from BCS-like to chaotic. <lb/>The connection between the field-dependence of the <lb/>pairing in a superconductor and the nature of the low-<lb/>energy quasiparticles raises several interesting questions. <lb/>Is there a true localization phase transition for quasi-<lb/>particles? Is there a sharp change between an ordered <lb/>regime and a chaotic regime or merely a crossover? Are <lb/>there simple models for which, using techniques similar <lb/>to those in the theory of disordered metals, the chaotic <lb/>pairing picture may be derived? What is the interplay be-<lb/>tween localization, disorder, and magnetic field for high-<lb/>T  c  superconductors, where the prediction in zero field <lb/>for a two-dimensional d-wave superconductor is &quot; univer-<lb/>sal conductivity &quot; [42]? A further important issue is to <lb/>test the validity of the random matrix prediction for the <lb/>density of states, for each of the possible regimes, by di-<lb/>rect comparison with tunneling experiments. <lb/>This work was supported by a Miller Post-Doctoral <lb/>Fellowship from the Miller Institute for Basic Research <lb/>in Science. I would like to thank D.-H. Lee for additional <lb/>support and useful discussions. <lb/> chaotic <lb/> H I <lb/> weak <lb/>T-breaking <lb/>H III <lb/> electronic structure <lb/>H/H c2 <lb/> disorder <lb/> FIG. 1. In the absence of impurities and for an ordered <lb/>lattice of vortices, the quasiparticle spectrum of a type-II su-<lb/>perconductor may be calculated by numerically solving the <lb/>Bogoliubov-de Gennes equations. In the presence of random <lb/>disorder, and for weak magnetic fields, the quasiparticle spec-<lb/>trum may be calculated as a small correction to the BCS <lb/>theory, Eq. (40), similar to the Abrikosov-Gor&apos;kov theory. <lb/>For stronger disorder or magnetic fields, the system enters <lb/>a chaotic regime in which the pairing is completely random, <lb/>Eq. (38). <lb/></body>

			<page> 9 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [1] E. P. Wigner, Proc. Cambr. Philos. Soc. 47, 790 (1951); <lb/>Ann. Math. 53, 36 (1951); 62, 548 (1955); 67, 325 (1958). <lb/>[2] Reviewed in T. A. Brody et al., Rev. Mod. Phys. 53, 385 <lb/>(1981); R. U. Haq, A. Pandey, and O. Bohigas, Phys. <lb/>Rev. Lett. 48, 1086 (1982). <lb/>[3] Statistical Theories of Spectra: Fluctuations, edited by <lb/>C. E. Porter, (Academic Press, New York, 1965). <lb/>[4] L. P. Gor&apos;kov and G. M. Eliashberg, Zh. Eksp. Teor. Fiz. <lb/> 48, 1407 (1965) [Sov. Phys. JETP 21, 940 (1965)]. Re-<lb/>viewed in J. Perenboom, P. Wyder, and F. Meier, Phys. <lb/>Rep. 78, 173 (1981). <lb/>[5] M. V. Berry and M. Tabor, Proc. R. Soc. Lond. A 356, <lb/> 375 (1977); G. M. Zaslavskii, Sov. Phys. JETP 46, 1094 <lb/>(1977); O. Bohigas, M.-J. Giannoni, and C. Schmit, <lb/>Phys. Rev. Lett. 52, 1 (1984); M. V. Berry, Proc. R. Soc. <lb/>Lond. A 400, 229 (1985). Reviewed in M. C. Gutzwiller, <lb/> Chaos in Classical and Quantum Mechanics (Springer-<lb/>Verlag, New York, 1990). <lb/>[6] G. &apos;t Hooft, Nucl. Phys. B72, 461 (1974); E. Brezin, <lb/>C. Itzykson, G. Parisi, and J.-B. Zuber, Comm. Math. <lb/>Phys. 59, 35 (1978). <lb/>[7] Reviewed in P. Di Francesco, P. Ginsparg, J. Zinn-Justin, <lb/>Phys. Rep. 254, 1 (1995). <lb/>[8] T. Banks, W. Fischler, S. H. Shenker, L. Susskind, Phys. <lb/>Rev. D 55, 5112 (1997). <lb/>[9] D. V. Voiculescu, K. J. Dykema, A. Nica, Free Random <lb/>Variables (American Mathematical Society, Providence, <lb/>1992). <lb/>[10] M. L. Mehta, Random Matrices, 2nd ed. (Academic <lb/>Press, New York, 1991). <lb/>[11] T. Guhr, A. Muller-Groeling, and H. A. Wiedenmuller, <lb/>cond-mat/9707301. <lb/>[12] J. Bardeen, L. N. Cooper, and J. R. Schrieffer, Phys. <lb/>Rev. 108, 1175 (1957). <lb/>[13] P. G. de Gennes, Superconductivity of Metals and Alloys <lb/> (Benjamin, New York, 1966). <lb/>[14] G. Eilenberger, Z. Phys. 214, 195 (1968). <lb/>[15] M. R. Norman, A. H. MacDonald, and H. Akera, Phys. <lb/>Rev. B 51, 5927 (1995) and references therein. <lb/>[16] M. Ichioka, N. Hayashi, K. Machida, Phys. Rev. B 55, <lb/> 6565 (1997). <lb/>[17] P. W. Anderson, J. Phys. Chem. Solids 11, 26 (1959). <lb/>[18] A. A. Abrikosov and L. P. Gor&apos;kov, Zh. Eksp. Teor. Fiz. <lb/> 39, 1781 (1960) [Sov. Phys. JETP 12, 1243 (1961)]. <lb/>[19] K. Maki in Superconductivity, edited by R. D. Parks <lb/>(Marcel Dekker, New York, 1969). <lb/>[20] P. W. Anderson, Phys. Rev. 109, 1492 (1958). <lb/>[21] P. A. Lee and T. V. Ramakrishnan, Rev. Mod. Phys. 57, <lb/> 287 (1995). <lb/>[22] S. Chakravarty and A. Schmid, Phys. Rep. 140, 193 <lb/>(1986). <lb/>[23] B. Kramer and A. MacKinnon, Rep. Prog. Phys. 56, 1469 <lb/>(1993). <lb/>[24] B. L. Altshuler and B. D. Simons in Mesoscopic Quantum <lb/>Physics edited by E. Akkermans et al. (Elsevier, New <lb/>York, 1995). <lb/>[25] S. F. Edwards, Philos. Mag. 3, 1020 (1958). <lb/>[26] J. S. Langer and T. Neal, Phys. Rev. Lett. 16, 984 (1966). <lb/>[27] E. Abrahams, P. W. Anderson, D. C. Licciardello, and <lb/>T. V. Ramakrishnan, Phys. Rev. Lett. 42, 673 (1979). <lb/>[28] L. P. Gor&apos;kov, A. I. Larkin, and D. E. Khmel&apos;nitskii, <lb/>JETP Lett. 30, 248 (1979);E. Abrahams and T. V. Ra-<lb/>makrishnan, J. Non-Cryst. Solids 35, 15 (1980). <lb/>[29] B. L. Altshuler, D. E. Khmelnitsky, A. I. Larkin, and P. <lb/>A. Lee, Phys. Rev. B 22, 5142 (1980). <lb/>[30] B. L. Altshuler, A. G. Aronov, A. I. Larkin, and D. E. <lb/>Khmelnitsky, Zh. Eksp. Teor. Fiz. 81, 768 (1981) [Sov. <lb/>Phys. JETP 54, 411 (1981)]. <lb/>[31] L. P. Gor&apos;kov, Zh. Eksperim. i Teor. Fiz. 37, 833 (1959) <lb/>[Sov. Phys. JETP 10, 593 (1960)]. <lb/>[32] A. A. Abrikosov, L. P. Gor&apos;kov, and I. E. Dzhyaloshinskii, <lb/> Methods of Quantum Field Theory in Statistical Physics <lb/> (Prentice-Hall, New Jersey, 1963). <lb/>[33] S. R. Bahcall, Phys. Rev. Lett. 77, 5276 (1996). <lb/>[34] S. R. Bahcall, Phys. Rev. Lett. 75, 1376 (1995). <lb/>[35] P. G. de Gennes, Superconductivity of Metals and Alloys <lb/> (Benjamin, New York, 1966). <lb/>[36] P. G. de Gennes and M. Tinkham, Phys. 1, 107 (1964). <lb/>[37] S. R. Bahcall, Sol. State Comm. 100, 297 (1996). <lb/>[38] K. Maki, Physics 1, 21 (1964). <lb/>[39] P. G. de Gennes, Phys. Kond. Mat. 3, 79 (1964). <lb/>[40] E. Helfand and N. R. Werthamer, Phys. Rev. 147, 288 <lb/>(1966). <lb/>[41] S. R. Bahcall, Yu. P. Krotov, and D.-H. Lee, to appear. <lb/>[42] P. A. Lee, Phys. Rev. Lett. 71, 1887 (1993). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 10 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
