<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage> First results and planned experiments with the INFN‐LNS ray‐tracing <lb/>magnetic spectrometer MAGNEX <lb/> A. Cunsolo, F. Cappuzzello, M. Cavallaro, A. Foti, S. E. A. Orrigo, M. R. D. Rodrigues, T. <lb/>Borello‐Lewin, H. Petrascu, and D. Carbone <lb/>Citation: AIP Conference Proceedings 1245, 3 (2010); doi: 10.1063/1.3448014 <lb/>View online: http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.3448014 <lb/>View Table of Contents: <lb/>http://scitation.aip.org/content/aip/proceeding/aipcp/1245?ver=pdfcov <lb/>Published by the AIP Publishing <lb/> Articles you may be interested in <lb/> Preliminary Study of Two‐Neutron States via the ( 18 O , 16 O ) Reaction at 84 MeV <lb/>AIP Conf. Proc. 1377, 234 (2011); 10.1063/1.3628385 <lb/>SHARAQ Spectrometer—Current status and future experimental plans— <lb/>AIP Conf. Proc. 1224, 573 (2010); 10.1063/1.3431474 <lb/>Results from the HARP Experiment <lb/>AIP Conf. Proc. 981, 151 (2008); 10.1063/1.2898915 <lb/>Status Of The EXCYT Facility at INFN‐LNS <lb/>AIP Conf. Proc. 701, 354 (2004); 10.1063/1.1691729 <lb/>MAGNEX: A large acceptance magnetic spectrometer for EXCYT <lb/>AIP Conf. Proc. 513, 270 (2000); 10.1063/1.1303379 <lb/> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. <lb/>Downloaded to IP: 137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:38:12 <lb/></titlePage>

			<front> First results and planned experiments with the <lb/>INFN-LNS ray-tracing magnetic spectrometer <lb/>MAGNEX <lb/> A.Cunsolo <lb/> a,b , F.Cappuzzello <lb/> a,b , M.Cavallaro <lb/> a,b , A.Foti <lb/> c <lb/> , S.E.A.Orrigo <lb/> a,b , <lb/>M.R.D.Rodrigues <lb/> b T.Borello-Lewin <lb/> d , H.Petrascu <lb/> e , D.Carbone <lb/> a <lb/> a <lb/> Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia, Università di Catania, Catania, Italy <lb/> b <lb/> INFN-Laboratori Nazionali del Sud, Catania, Italy <lb/> c INFN-Sezione di Catania, Catania, Italy <lb/> d IFUSP,S.Paolo,Brazil <lb/> e NIPNE, Bucarest, Romania <lb/> Abstract. The MAGNEX large-acceptance ray-tracing magnetic spectrometer has recently been <lb/>used with beams from the INFN-LNS Tandem accelerator. After an accurate commissioning, the <lb/>instrument has started an ambitious experimental program. In the first experiment the <lb/> 19 F <lb/> (7 Li, <lb/> 7 Be) <lb/> 19 <lb/> O charge-exchange reaction was studied at 52 MeV incident energy. The <lb/> 19 <lb/> O <lb/>excitation energy spectrum was reconstructed and the angular distributions measured. The <lb/>second experiment was aimed at the study of the <lb/> 15 C via the <lb/> 13 <lb/> C( <lb/> 18 <lb/> O, <lb/> 16 O) <lb/> 15 C reaction at 84 MeV <lb/>incident energy. The ejectiles where detected at forward angles and mass identified by means of <lb/>an innovative technique. The <lb/> 15 <lb/> C excitation energy spectra up to about 20 MeV were obtained <lb/>with a 250 keV FWHM energy resolution. In addition to several known states, the spectra show <lb/>two unknown resonant-like structures at 11.4 and 14.0 MeV. The strong population of these <lb/>structures, together with the measured widths, could indicate the collective nature of these states <lb/>associated to a correlated neutron pair transfer. Besides the first results of physical interest from <lb/>these two experiments, future experiments with MAGNEX are briefly outlined. <lb/> Keywords: Magnetic spectrometers. Spectroscopy of light nuclei. <lb/> PACS: 07.81.+a, 07.77.Ka, 29.30.Ep, 29.40.-n, 21.10.Pc, 21.10.Re, 25.70.Hi <lb/></front>

			<body> INTRODUCTION <lb/> The MAGNEX large-acceptance magnetic spectrometer [1-2] has been <lb/>commissioned and recently used in experiments performed with beams by the INFN-<lb/>LNS Tandem. MAGNEX has been designed particularly for applications where the <lb/>counting rate is expected to be rather low and the experimental information is required <lb/>to be very clean. Experiments with stable beams from both the Tandem and the <lb/>Superconducting Cyclotron (CS) have been foreseen, as well as one based on the use <lb/>with RNBs from the EXCYT facility at the LNS. The spectrometer relies partly on <lb/>hardware (especially the shape of the entrance and exit dipole pole tips) and partly on <lb/>software (ray reconstruction) to overcome the strong aberrations inherent in the 50-<lb/> 3 <lb/> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded to IP: 137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:38:12 <lb/> CREDIT LINE (BELOW) TO BE INSERTED ON THE FIRST PAGE OF EACH PAPER <lb/> CP1245, The XXXII Brazilian Workshop on Nuclear Physics <lb/> A. Deppman, C. Krug, G. S. Zahn, J. Lubian, N. Added, V. S. Timóteo <lb/> © 2010 American Institute of Physics 978-0-7354-0792-3/10/$30.00 <lb/></note>

			<body> msr acceptance. The magnetic elements – Quadrupole, Dipole, α- and β-surface coils <lb/>– and the optics in general, were tested with elastically scattered <lb/> 16 O beams with slit <lb/>and pepperpot apertures mounted after the target. The software reconstruction is <lb/>based on inverse-matrices calculated from the complicated 3D-interpolation of the <lb/>measured fields [3-4]. A demonstration of the particle identification capabilities of the <lb/>PSD start detector [5] and the focal plane detector (FPD) [6-7] was given by a <lb/>measurement of the <lb/> 19 F( <lb/> 7 <lb/> Li, <lb/> 7 Be) <lb/> 19 O charge exchange reaction at 25 ± 5º, using the full <lb/>acceptance of the spectrometer. The charge state distribution of <lb/> 48 Ti ions scattered at <lb/>120 MeV was also measured and found to be in good agreement with the predictions <lb/>of INTENSITY [8]. The overall angular and energy resolution measured after the <lb/>application of ray reconstruction algorithms agree with the prediction of the <lb/>simulations. Fig.1 shows the general view of the Spectrometer. <lb/> FIGURE 1. General view of the MAGNEX spectrometer. From the left to the right the scattering <lb/>chamber, the quadrupole, the dipole and the Focal Plane Detector are visible. <lb/> THE MOTIVATION OF THE FIRST EXPERIMENT <lb/> In the last years, the study of nuclear structure and reaction dynamics far off the <lb/>stability valley has attracted much interest from both the theoretical and experimental <lb/>sides. The present study of the <lb/> 19 O neutron-rich nucleus via the ( <lb/> 7 Li, <lb/> 7 Be) charge-<lb/>exchange reaction is well inserted into this context. <lb/>The investigation of this nucleus belongs to a research line that aims at a systematic <lb/>exploration of structural properties of light neutron-rich nuclei, for which an inner core <lb/>of an integer number of α particles is coupled to three external neutrons (Nα + 3 <lb/>neutrons). The ( <lb/> 7 Li, <lb/> 7 Be) reaction at about 8 MeV/A incident energy has shown to be a <lb/>suitable tool to explore such systems, as demonstrated by previous studies on other <lb/></body>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. <lb/>Downloaded to IP: 137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:38:12 <lb/></note>

			<body> nuclei belonging to this category: <lb/> 11 Be and <lb/> 15 C [9-10]. In fact, this process in such <lb/>energy range proceeds with a predominance of the direct one-step mechanism, <lb/>resulting in an useful probe for spectroscopic studies. In addition, it turned out to be <lb/>suitable to populate configurations more complex than the single-particle ones, <lb/>providing, thanks also to the good resolution that can be achieved, complementary <lb/>information on nuclear structure. Therefore the first experiment performed with <lb/>MAGNEX was the <lb/> 19 F <lb/> (7 Li, <lb/> 7 Be) <lb/> 19 O charge-exchange reaction at 52 MeV, in order to <lb/>investigate the <lb/> 19 O nucleus , i.e. the N = 4 member. <lb/> EXPERIMENTAL DETAILS <lb/> The 52.2 MeV <lb/> 7 Li <lb/> +++ beam was accelerated by the Tandem facility of the INFN-<lb/>LNS. The <lb/> 19 <lb/> F target was a 80 μg/cm <lb/> 2 thick AlF  3 foil evaporated on a gold backing of <lb/> 250 μg/cm <lb/> 2 . A <lb/> 27 <lb/> Al target (116 μg/cm <lb/> 2 ) was also used in order to estimate and subtract <lb/>the aluminium contribution in the final spectra. Supplementary runs were done also on <lb/>a WO 3 target (150 μg/cm <lb/> 2 <lb/> on 20 μg/cm <lb/> 2 carbon backing) and on a carbon target (76 <lb/> μg/cm <lb/> 2 ) with the same purpose. The reaction ejectiles were momentum analyzed by <lb/> MAGNEX. The quadrupole and dipole fields and the α-surface coil, together with the <lb/>position of the FPD, were set in order to focus the <lb/> 7 Be ejectiles associated to the <lb/> 19 O g.s. <lb/> in the focal plane position corresponding to a momentum deviation δ = 0.08 with <lb/>respect to the central one. The FPD is an hybrid detector consisting of a gas section <lb/>followed by a Si detector hodoscope. The gas section consists of two couples of two <lb/>Drift chambers spaced by a proportional chamber. It was filled with 99.95% pure <lb/>isobutane gas at 10 mbar pressure. The cathode was supplied –950 V, while the Frish-<lb/>grid was grounded. The high voltage in the proportional wires was +750 V, and the <lb/>lateral shaping wires between the Frish-grid and the proportional wires were <lb/>maintained at increasing voltage by a separate power supply at +400 V. The 45 silicon <lb/>detectors, each 500 µm thick, cover the back of the FPD and were powered with +60 <lb/>V voltage in a full depletion mode. To identify the ions the PSD start detector was not <lb/>needed. The data analyzed up to now were taken when the spectrometer was located at <lb/>a central angle of <lb/> ° <lb/>= 25 <lb/>. <lb/>12 <lb/> lab <lb/> θ <lb/> with respect to the beam incident direction. Due to the <lb/>large angular acceptance of MAGNEX (horizontally –0.090 rad, +0.110 rad, <lb/> vertically ±0.125 rad in the spectrometer reference frame), this angular setting <lb/>corresponds to a covered angular range 7.1° &lt; θ  lab  &lt; 19.8°. Measurements at <lb/> ° <lb/>= 0 <lb/> lab <lb/> θ <lb/> and <lb/> ° <lb/>= 25 <lb/>. <lb/>6 <lb/> lab <lb/> θ <lb/> were also performed and the relative data analysis is in progress. <lb/> 19 O EXCITATION ENERGY SPECTRA <lb/> The identification of the <lb/> 7 Be ejectiles was done by the MAGNEX Focal Plane <lb/>Detector through a ΔE-E technique combined with the measurement of the magnetic <lb/>rigidity vs. the kinetic energy of each detected particle [11]. An algebraic technique of <lb/>ray-reconstruction of the detected ions [3-4] has been used to relate the final <lb/>parameters measured at the focal plane to the initial phase space parameters. Such ray-<lb/></body>

			<page> 5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. <lb/>Downloaded to IP: 137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:38:12 <lb/></note>

			<body> reconstruction technique is based on the formalism of Differential Algebra [12]. This <lb/>technique is used to solve the differential equations describing the motion of ions <lb/>through the spectrometer and to obtain the Taylor coefficients of the flow linking the <lb/>initial phase space with the final one. In this mathematic environment, the integration <lb/>of the differential equations results in a simpler algebraic task, therefore very high <lb/>order of the perturbation series can be treated. With this technique, if the appropriate <lb/>position and direction of the detected ion is accurately measured at the focal plane, one <lb/>can reconstruct (i.e. trace) the ion trajectory back to the reaction target and <lb/>consequently obtain the scattering angles (polar and azimuthal) and the initial <lb/>momentum of the ion, by the application of the inverse map of the measured phase <lb/>space parameters. <lb/> FIGURE 2. <lb/> 19  O excitation energy spectrum with the AlF  3 target and, superimposed, the <lb/>normalized spectrum obtained with the Al target. The known states of <lb/> 19  O are indicated with <lb/>their energy. The presence of <lb/> 27  Mg and <lb/> 16 <lb/> N states is also shown. Peaks marked with an asterisk <lb/>refer to the transitions in which <lb/> 7 <lb/> Be ejectiles are in the first excited state at 0.43 MeV. <lb/> In Fig.2 a reconstructed spectrum of the <lb/> 19 O excitation energy is shown. In <lb/>detail the spectrum obtained from the data with the AlF 3 target is shown <lb/>superimposed the one relative to the aluminium target. Several <lb/> 19 O excited states <lb/>are observed and identified in the low excitation energy region. The well <lb/>isolated peaks are labelled with their excitation energy in MeV. Peaks marked <lb/>with an asterisk refer to the transitions in which <lb/> 7 Be ejectiles are in the 0.43 <lb/>MeV first excited state. Most of the <lb/> 19 O states have been observed in the past by <lb/>one and two neutron transfer reactions (see [13] and reference therein), thus <lb/>confirming the capability of the ( <lb/> 7 Li, <lb/> 7 Be) reactions to populate such states. For <lb/></body>

			<page> 6 <lb/> </page>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. <lb/>Downloaded to IP: 137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:38:12 <lb/></note>

			<body> most of them the shell structure configuration is well known as for example for <lb/>the 1.47 MeV excited state (1/2 <lb/> + ) which is mainly a single-particle state, i.e. a <lb/>2s 1/2 neutron coupled to a <lb/> 18 O(0 <lb/> + ) core. The energy resolution is about 80 KeV <lb/>(FWHM). <lb/> THE ( <lb/> 7 LI, <lb/> 7 BE) ANGULAR DISTRIBUTIONS <lb/> One of the advantages when working with a large acceptance spectrometer is that, <lb/>in a single setting of the instrument, several scattering angles are covered. Therefore, a <lb/>consistent part of the angular distributions relative to the transitions associated to the <lb/>detected ejectiles can be measured at once, i.e. in the same experimental conditions, <lb/>resulting in a reduction of the normalisation uncertainty. In the present case, a single <lb/>set of measurements at central angle <lb/> ° <lb/> = 25 <lb/>. <lb/>12 <lb/> lab <lb/> θ <lb/> allows to obtain angular <lb/>distributions for scattering angles in the range 10° &lt;  θ  CM  &lt; 21° in the centre of mass <lb/>reference frame. In Fig. 3 the measured angular distributions for the transition to the <lb/>not resolved doublet of <lb/> 19 O ground and first excited state at 0.096 MeV is shown. In <lb/>Fig. 4 the angular distribution for the transition to the <lb/> 19 O(1.47MeV, ½ <lb/> + ) excited state <lb/>is shown. <lb/>A theoretical analysis of the <lb/> 19 F( <lb/> 7 Li, <lb/> 7 Be) <lb/> 19 O reaction in the framework of the <lb/>Charge-Exchange Quasi-particle Random Phase Approximation (CEX-QRPA) [14] is <lb/>on the way [15]. This approach is very powerful since it can be used to describe the <lb/> 19 O nuclear structure and also to calculate the transition densities connecting the <lb/> 19 F <lb/>ground to the 1p-1h states of <lb/> 19 O, thus allowing a direct connection to reaction cross <lb/>section calculations by a suitable Distorted Wave Born Approximation (DWBA). The <lb/>use of a realistic semi-microscopic interaction, that includes the tensor contribution, in <lb/>both structure and reaction calculations, has allowed in the past to describe very well <lb/>reactions similar to the present one as the <lb/> 11 B( <lb/> 7 Li, <lb/> 7 Be) <lb/> 11 Be and <lb/> 15 N( <lb/> 7 Li, <lb/> 7 Be) <lb/> 15 C in the <lb/>same energy region [9-10]. <lb/> 7 <lb/> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. <lb/>Downloaded to IP: 137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:38:12 <lb/> FIGURE 3. Measured angular distribution for the <lb/> 7 Li + <lb/> 19 F → <lb/> 7 <lb/> Be + <lb/> 19 O <lb/> * <lb/> (g.s. + 0.096MeV) transition. <lb/> FIGURE 4. Measured angular distribution for the <lb/> 7 Li + <lb/> 19 <lb/> F → <lb/> 7 Be + <lb/> 19 O <lb/> * <lb/> (1.47MeV) transition. <lb/> THE MOTIVATION OF THE SECOND EXPERIMENT <lb/> The <lb/> 15 <lb/> C nucleus is a neutron rich system which has stimulated an increasing <lb/>spectroscopic interest in the years (see [16-17] and references therein). A simple <lb/>representation of the low lying states with positive parity can be established within the <lb/>1p-2h space, i.e. a sd-shell neutron coupled to the <lb/> 14 <lb/> C ground state. Differently for the <lb/>negative parity states, where the 2p-3h space with the inclusion of the supplemental <lb/> 7  Li + <lb/> 19  F → <lb/> 7  Be + <lb/> 19 <lb/> O  1.47 <lb/> θ  CM  (deg) <lb/>dσ/dΩ (μb/sr) <lb/> dσ/dΩ (μb/sr) <lb/> θ  CM  (deg) <lb/> 7  Li + <lb/> 19 <lb/> F → <lb/> 7  Be + <lb/> 19 <lb/> O g.s.+0.096 <lb/></body>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. <lb/>Downloaded to IP: 137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:38:12 <lb/></note>

			<body> hole in the p-shell, is necessary. A detailed study of both kind of excitation has been <lb/>done in the past by transfer reactions [16]. In addition a clear evidence of the effect of <lb/>the core polarisation has been found in charge exchange reactions by the appearance <lb/>of Fano resonances at about 8.4 MeV excitation energy [10]. The present experiment <lb/>represent a new attempt to study the <lb/> 15 C spectra by the use of the ( <lb/> 18 O, <lb/> 16 <lb/> O) transfer <lb/>reaction at 84 MeV. It is known that, at incident energies about 7.5 times the Coulomb <lb/>barrier the angular distributions of multi nucleon transfer reactions are sensitive to the <lb/>details of the final populated states [18-19]. Under these conditions, according to the <lb/>Brink&apos;s energy and angular momentum matching conditions [20], one expects to <lb/>excite significantly states with L = 0, 2 and 4. <lb/> EXPERIMENTAL DETAILS <lb/> The experiment has been performed in two steps, first in January 2008 and after in <lb/>March 2009, at the INFN-LNS Laboratory of Catania. In the first run a restricted <lb/>angular range between 18° and 40° in the CM reference frame was covered. In the <lb/>second, the range was enlarged from 9° to 50° and a supplemental target of <lb/> 12 C was <lb/>used. In this paper we report on the first run, being the analysis of the second still <lb/>under way. The <lb/> 18 O beam bombarded a 140 µg/cm <lb/> 2 self supporting <lb/> 13 C target at 84 <lb/>MeV incident energy. The Oxygen ions produced in the collisions were detected by <lb/>the MAGNEX spectrometer with the purpose to study the structure of <lb/> 14 C, <lb/> 15 <lb/> C and <lb/> 16 <lb/> C <lb/>nuclei via the ( <lb/> 18 O, <lb/> 17,16,15 <lb/> O) multi-neutron transfer reactions. The magnetic fields were <lb/>set in order to accept the Oxygen ions with charge between 6 <lb/> + to 8 <lb/> + at the maximum <lb/>kinetic energy. These were identified by the simultaneous measurement of their <lb/>position along the focal plane and their residual energy on the silicon detector <lb/>hodoscope. <lb/> FIGURE 5. In the left panel the measured energy loss is shown versus the kinetic energy. Different <lb/>ions are identified by comparison with loci expected from kinematics and energy loss calculations. The <lb/>selection condition for the Oxygen ions is also drawn. In the right panel the focal plane position is <lb/>correlated with the kinetic energy for the gated Oxygen ions. Different isotopes and charge states are <lb/>identified. The selection condition for the <lb/> 16 O <lb/> 8+ ions is also drawn. <lb/></body>

			<page> 9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. <lb/>Downloaded to IP: 137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:38:12 <lb/></note>

			<body> In Fig.5 an example of the identification capabilities of the instrument is shown. <lb/>This result indicates that, for many cases the particle identification can be successfully <lb/>obtained without the standard measurement of the time of flight as discussed in ref. <lb/>[8]. After gating on the <lb/> 16 O <lb/> 8+ ejectiles, the horizontal and vertical positions and angles <lb/>at the focal plane are analyzed, thus providing the constraints for the application of the <lb/>high order algorithms of trajectory reconstruction, implemented in the spectrometer. <lb/>As said before, this procedure does allow for the reconstruction of interesting physical <lb/>quantities as the scattering angle and the excitation energy of the target residual. An <lb/>example of obtained bi-dimensional histogram correlating these quantities is shown in <lb/>Fig.6. In the plot several vertical lines are evident, especially at low excitation energy. <lb/>These indicate the population of discrete states and narrow resonances of the <lb/> 15 C. One <lb/>should also note the achieved independence of the reconstructed excitation energy <lb/>from the scattering angle. By projecting the same data on the abscissa, as done in <lb/>Fig.7, one gets the energy of these states. Several peaks are recognized as due to <lb/>transitions to known states of <lb/> 15 C, namely the ground and states at excitation energy of <lb/>0.74, 3.1, 4.22, 4.66, 6.84 and 7.35 MeV. Deviations between the measured energies <lb/>and the known ones are within 50 keV. Two broad structures are observed with <lb/>energies centered at about 11.4 and 14.0 MeV and FWHM of 2 and 2.5 MeV, <lb/>respectively. A systematic error of about 1 MeV originated by the underlying <lb/>background is estimated for these latter. These are unknown from literature and <lb/>represent an interesting finding of the experiment. <lb/> FIGURE 6. Bi-dimensional spectrum of the reconstructed laboratory angle versus the reconstructed <lb/> 15 C <lb/>excitation energy for the selected <lb/> 16 O <lb/> 8+ ions , in the angular range 0.174 &lt; θ  lab  &lt; 0.189 rad. <lb/></body>

			<page> 10 <lb/> </page>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. <lb/>Downloaded to IP: 137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:38:12 <lb/></note>

			<body> FIGURE 7. One-dimensional spectrum of the reconstructed <lb/> 15 C excitation energy for the selected <lb/> 16 O <lb/> 8+ <lb/> ions , in the angular range 7.16° &lt; θ  lab  &lt; 13.4°. The solid line is only intended to guide the eye. <lb/> In Fig.8a the angular distribution of the resonance at 11.4 MeV is compared with <lb/>that of the 1/2 <lb/> -<lb/> resonance at 3.103 MeV, which is almost a pure L = 0 transition from <lb/>the 1/2 <lb/> -13 <lb/> C ground state [16-17]. Similarly in Fig.8b the same comparison is done <lb/>with the angular distribution for the L = 3 transition to the 5/2 <lb/> + bound state at 0.74 <lb/>MeV. A similar behavior is observed between the transition to the 11.4 MeV <lb/>resonance and the L = 0 one, while deviations are observed with the L = 3 one, at least <lb/>as regards the slope of the curves. Similar deviations are observed in the comparison <lb/>with the L = 4 transitions to the 7/2 <lb/> -<lb/> ,9/2 <lb/> - states at 6.84 and 7.35 MeV. As regards the <lb/>resonance at 14.0 MeV it behaves exactly as the one at 11.4 MeV, indicating that very <lb/>likely the physical origin of both is the same. Taking all of this into account one can <lb/>infer that the L = 0 transfer seems to be the angular momentum transferred for the <lb/>population of the resonances at 11.4 and 14.0 MeV. <lb/> 15  C Excitation Energy (MeV) <lb/></body>

			<page> 11 <lb/> </page>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. <lb/>Downloaded to IP: 137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:38:12 <lb/></note>

			<body> FIGURE 8. a) Comparison of the measured angular distributions for the transition to the resonance at <lb/> E  x  = 11.45 MeV and at E x  = 3.103 MeV (L = 0). b) Comparison of the measured angular distributions <lb/>for the transition to the resonance at E x  = 11.45 MeV and to the bound state at E x  = 0.74 MeV (L = 3). <lb/> It is also interesting to note in Fig.8a that the cross section for the resonances at <lb/>11.4 and 14.0 MeV are about one order of magnitude larger than that at 3.1 MeV, <lb/>clearly showing that a large amount of the L = 0 strength is exhausted in the former. <lb/>Since the state at 3.1 MeV is an almost pure 2p-1h state, one can conclude about the <lb/>collective nature of these resonances. To summarize, the dominance of the two <lb/>neutron transfer mechanism compared to the single neutron transfer has been <lb/>observed. This indicates the dominance of the pair transfer compared to the second <lb/>order process of sequential transfer of two uncorrelated neutrons in such experimental <lb/>conditions. In addition it seems that a collective L = 0 degree of freedom has been <lb/></body>

			<page> 12 <lb/> </page>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. <lb/>Downloaded to IP: 137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:38:12 <lb/></note>

			<body> excited by the pair transfer mechanism. The preliminary analysis of the data of the <lb/>second experiment seems to agree with the main features discussed above . <lb/> FUTURE PLANNED EXPERIMENTS <lb/> The future experiments involving MAGNEX and approved by the INFN-LNS <lb/>PAC are the following ones: THM, Multineutron, Nuclear Rainbow, CEX, α-<lb/> MAGNEX and <lb/> 8 He states. <lb/>The first one concerns the measurement of the <lb/> 12 <lb/> C + <lb/> 12 C fusion cross section at <lb/>energies of astrophysical interest via the Trojan Horse Method [21]. In this case the <lb/>system studied will be <lb/> 16 O+ <lb/> 12 C at 26 MeV incident energy, being the Trojan Horse the <lb/> 16 O nucleus. If, in the target nucleus field, it breaks in an α particle, which is emitted <lb/>at forward angles (the spectator) and detected by means of MAGNEX, the correlated <lb/> 12 <lb/> C nucleus will interact and mainly fuse with the <lb/> 12 C target. The α particle or protons <lb/>evaporated by the <lb/> 24 Mg Compound Nucleus, will be detected in coincidence with the <lb/>spectator by means of a couple of position sensitive silicon telescopes. The <lb/>coincidence cross sections will allow to extract the <lb/> 12 C + <lb/> 12 C (participants) one. The <lb/>THM experiment is planned in November of the current year. <lb/>The ( <lb/> 18 O, <lb/> 16 O) Multineutron experiment will be aimed to complete the angular <lb/>distribution measurements already done, including zero degrees, as well as to extend, <lb/>at the same incident energy, the measurements on <lb/> 9 Be, <lb/> 14 C and <lb/> 15 N targets. It is <lb/>planned on March 2010. <lb/>Also the ( <lb/> 7 Li, <lb/> 7 Be) angular distributions, already measured, will be completed <lb/>including the zero degrees measurements and extended to <lb/> 24 Mg and <lb/> 28 Si targets in the <lb/>CEX experiment planned in April 2010. In fact, the proportionality between the <lb/>measured cross section at zero degrees and the β-decay strengths for Gamow-Teller <lb/>(GT) transitions, or with the equivalent ones measured via corresponding (n,p) or <lb/>(p,n) reactions at energies above 100 MeV, is considered a proof of almost pure direct <lb/>one-step reaction mechanism. <lb/>The Nuclear Rainbow experiment will concern the measurement of the elastic <lb/>scattering of the reaction <lb/> 27 Al( <lb/> 16 O, <lb/> 16 O) <lb/> 27 Al at 100 MeV incident energy, in order to <lb/>verify the presence of characteristic &quot; Rainbow &quot; pattern [22]. This experiment has <lb/>been recently suggested by IFUSP and IFF colleagues, on the basis of calculations <lb/>done in the framework of the Sao Paulo Potential procedure and will be performed in <lb/>February 2010. It is a quite challenging experiment, because the elastically scattered <lb/> 16 O nuclei should be measured up to very large angles, where very low yield is <lb/>expected. <lb/>The α-MAGNEX experiment is aimed to investigate the α-cluster states in medium <lb/>– heavy nuclei populated via the ( <lb/> 6 Li,d) reaction at E 6Li = 40 MeV and verify the <lb/>theoretical prediction based on a convolution potential. As it implies the detection of <lb/>high energy deuterons, some up-grading of the FPD is needed . Therefore it is planned <lb/>in the 2011. <lb/>The <lb/> 8 He states experiment foresees the <lb/> 8 Li radioactive beam from the EXCYT-LNS <lb/>facility impinging on a <lb/> 7 Li target. The spectrometer will detect the <lb/> 7 Be ions, emitted in <lb/>the CEX <lb/> 7 Li( <lb/> 8 Li, <lb/> 7 Be) <lb/> 8 He reaction at MeV incident energy. This will allow to measure <lb/></body>

			<page> 13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. <lb/>Downloaded to IP: 137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:38:12 <lb/></note>

			<body> the excitation energy of the <lb/> 8 He states with very good precision. This information is <lb/>relevant in order to shed light on the behavior of the L-S coupling as function of the <lb/>isospin. Also this experiment is planned in the 2011, to wait for a <lb/> 8 Li beam intensity of <lb/>about 2.5 x10 <lb/> 5 particles/sec. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> REFERENCES <lb/> 1. A. Cunsolo et al., Nucl. Instr. and Meth. A 481, 48 (2002). <lb/>2. A. Cunsolo et al., Nucl. Instr. and Meth. A, 484, 56 (2002). <lb/>3. A. Lazzaro et al., &quot; Computational aspects of the trajectory reconstruction in the MAGNEX large <lb/>acceptance spectrometer &quot; in &quot; 7 <lb/> th International Computational Accelerator Physics Conference &quot; , <lb/> edited by M.Berz and K.Makino, IOP Conference Proceedings 175, Institute of Physics, Bristol and <lb/>Philadelphia, 2002, pp.171-180. <lb/>4. A. Lazzaro et al.Nucl. Instr. and Meth. A 570, 192 (2007) and references therein. <lb/>5. S.E.A. Orrigo et al., LNS Activity Report 2006, 109. <lb/>6. A. Cunsolo et al. Nucl. Instr. and Meth. A 495, 216 (2002). <lb/>7. C. Boiano et al. IEEE Trans. on Nucl. Sc. 55, 3563 (2008). <lb/>8. A.Cunsolo et al. Eur.Phys.J. Special Topics 150, 343-346 (2007). <lb/>9. F. Cappuzzello et al. Nucl. Phys. A 739, 30 (2004). <lb/>10. S.E.A. Orrigo et al., Phys. Lett. B 633, 469 (2006). <lb/>11. F. Cappuzzello et al., Nucl. Instr. Meth. A (submitted). <lb/>12. M. Berz, Nucl. Instr. Meth. A 298 426 (1990). <lb/>13. J.L.Wiza et al., Phys. Rev. 143, 676 (1966). <lb/>14. H. Lenske, Nucl.Phys. A 482, 343 (1988) and H. Hoffmann et al., Phys. Rev.C 57, 2281 (1998). <lb/>15. M. Cavallaro, &quot; First Application of the MAGNEX Spectrometer: Investigation of the <lb/> 19 F( <lb/> 7 Li, <lb/> 7 Be) <lb/> 19 O reaction at 52 MeV &quot; , Ph.D. Thesis, University of Catania, 2009. <lb/>16. R. Jahn et al., Phys. Rev. C 18, 9-21 (1978). <lb/>17. S. Truong and H.T. Fortune, Phys. Rev. C 28, 977-979 (1983). <lb/>18. N. Anyas-Weiss et al., Phys. Rep. 12, 201-272 (1974). <lb/>19. S. Kahana and A.J. Baltz, Adv. in Nucl. Phys. 9, 1-122 (1977). <lb/>20. D.M. Brink, Phys. Lett. B 40 37-40 (1972). <lb/>21. S. Cherubini et al., Astrophys. Jour. 457, 855 (1996). <lb/>22. D.Pereira et al., Phys. Lett. B, 670, 330 (2009). <lb/>23. M.R.D.Rodrigues et al. contribution to this XXXII Workshop on Nuclear Physics in Brazil. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> This article is copyrighted as indicated in the article. Reuse of AIP content is subject to the terms at: http://scitation.aip.org/termsconditions. <lb/>Downloaded to IP: 137.138.124.224 On: Mon, 13 Apr 2015 18:38:12 </note>


	</text>
</tei>
