<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<page> 181 <lb/></page>

			<front> Preliminary study of the <lb/> 19 <lb/> F( <lb/> 7 <lb/> Li, <lb/> 7 <lb/> Be) <lb/> 19 <lb/> O reaction at 52 MeV with MAGNEX <lb/> M. Cavallaro <lb/> a,b , A. Cunsolo <lb/> a,b , F. Cappuzzello <lb/> a,b , D. Carbone <lb/> a,b , A. Foti <lb/> c , S.E.A.Orrigo <lb/> a,b , M.R.D. <lb/>Rodrigues <lb/> b , M. Schillaci <lb/> a,b , T.Borello-Lewin <lb/> e , H.Petrascu <lb/> f <lb/>a  Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia, Università di Catania, Italy <lb/> b  INFN-Laboratori Nazionali del Sud, Catania, Italy <lb/> c  INFN-Sezione di Catania, Italy <lb/> e  NIPNE, Bucarest, Romania <lb/> Abstract <lb/> The <lb/> 19  F( <lb/> 7  Li, <lb/> 7 <lb/> Be) <lb/> 19  O charge-exchange reaction at 52 MeV incident energy has been <lb/>performed at INFN-LNS in Catania using the MAGNEX spectrometer. The use of <lb/>an algebraic ray-reconstruction technique has allowed to extract the <lb/> 19  O excitation <lb/>energy spectrum and the experimental angular distributions obtained with a single <lb/>angular setting of the spectrometer. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1 <lb/> Introduction <lb/> Over the last years, a general interest has concerned the study of nuclear structure and reaction <lb/>dynamics far off the stability valley, arising from the possibility to explore new and exciting phenomena <lb/>characteristic of those systems. The present study of the <lb/> 19  O neutron-rich nucleus via the ( <lb/> 7 <lb/> Li, <lb/> 7  Be) charge-<lb/>exchange reaction is well inserted into this general context. <lb/>The investigation of this nucleus belongs to a research line that aims to a systematic exploration of <lb/>both structural properties of a particular category of light neutron-rich nuclei, for which an inner core of an <lb/>integer number of α particles is coupled to three external neutrons (Nα + 3 neutrons). The ( <lb/> 7  Li, <lb/> 7  Be) reaction <lb/>at about 8 MeV/A incident energy has shown to be a suitable tool to explore such systems, as demonstrated <lb/>by previous studies on other nuclei belonging to this category: <lb/> 11  Be and <lb/> 15  C [1], [2]. In fact, this process in <lb/>such energy range proceeds with a considerable predominance of the direct one-step mechanism, thus being <lb/>an useful probe for spectroscopic studies. In addition it has turned out to be suitable to populate <lb/>configurations more complex than the single-particle ones, providing, thanks also to the good resolution <lb/>achievable, complementary information on nuclear structure. <lb/> 2 <lb/> Experimental Setup <lb/> The <lb/> 7 Li <lb/> +++ beam at 52.2 MeV was accelerated by the Tandem facility of INFN-LNS. The <lb/> 19  F target was a 80 <lb/> μg/cm <lb/> 2 thick AlF  3 foil evaporated on a gold backing of 250 μg/cm <lb/> 2 produced at the chemical laboratory of <lb/>LNS. A <lb/> 27 Al target (116 μg/cm <lb/> 2 ) was also used in order to estimate the aluminium presence in the target <lb/>compound and subtract it in the final spectra. Supplementary runs were done also on a WO  3 target (150 <lb/>μg/cm <lb/> 2 on 20 μg/cm <lb/> 2 carbon backing) and on a carbon target (76 μg/cm <lb/> 2 ) for the subtraction of the <lb/>contribution in the final spectra due to the oxygen and carbon impurities in the AlF  3 target. <lb/>The reaction ejectiles were momentum analyzed by the MAGNEX large acceptance magnetic spectrometer <lb/>A picture of MAGNEX is shown in Fig.1. The MAGNEX quadrupole and dipole fields and the α-surface <lb/>coil, together with the position of the Focal Plane Detector (FPD), were set in order to focus the <lb/> 7  Be ejectiles <lb/>relative to the <lb/> 19  O g.s.  in the focal plane position corresponding to a momentum deviation δ = 0.08 with respect <lb/>to the central one. <lb/>The FPD [3],[4] was filled with 99.95% pure isobutane gas at 7 mbar pressure. The cathode was supplied at <lb/>–950 V while the Frish-grid was grounded. The high voltage in the proportional wires was +750 V, and the <lb/>lateral shaping wires between the Frish-grid and the proportional wires were maintained at increasing voltage <lb/>by a separate power supply at +400 V. The silicon detectors were powered with +60 V voltage in a full <lb/>depletion mode. <lb/></body>

			<page> 182 <lb/></page>

			<body> In the data analyzed up to now the spectrometer was located at a central angle of <lb/> 25 <lb/> . <lb/>12 <lb/> lab <lb/> with respect <lb/>to the beam incidence direction. Due to the large angular acceptance of MAGNEX (horizontally –0.090 rad, <lb/> +0.110 rad, vertically ±0.125 rad in the spectrometer reference frame), this angular setting corresponds to a <lb/>covered angular range 7.1° &lt; θ  lab  &lt; 19.8° in the laboratory reference frame. Measurements at <lb/> 0 <lb/> lab <lb/> and <lb/> 25 <lb/> . <lb/>6 <lb/> lab <lb/> were also performed and the data analysis is in progress. <lb/> Fig.1: General view of the MAGNEX spectrometer. From the left to the right the scattering chamber, the <lb/>quadrupole, the dipole and the Focal Plane Detector are visible. <lb/> 3 <lb/> 19 <lb/> O excitation energy spectra <lb/> The identification of the <lb/> 7  Be ejectiles was done by the MAGNEX Focal Plane Detector through a ΔE-E <lb/> technique combined with the measurement of the magnetic rigidity vs. the kinetic energy of each detected <lb/>particle [5]. <lb/>An algebraic technique of ray-reconstruction of the detected ions [6] has been used to relate the final <lb/>parameters measured at the focal plane to the initial phase space parameters. Such ray-reconstruction <lb/>technique is based on the formalism of Differential Algebra [7]. It is a perturbative technique to solve the <lb/>differential equations describing the motion of ions through the spectrometer and to obtain the Taylor <lb/>coefficients of the flow linking the initial phase space with the final one. In this mathematic environment, the <lb/>integration of the differential equations results a simpler algebraic task and very high order of the <lb/>perturbation series can be treated. <lb/>With this technique, if the appropriate positions and directions of the detected ions are determined by <lb/>measurement at the focal plane, one can reconstruct the full trajectories back to the reaction target and <lb/>consequently obtain the scattering angles and the initial momenta of the reaction products, by the application <lb/>of the inverse map of the measured phase space parameters. <lb/>In Fig.2 a reconstructed spectrum of the <lb/> 19  O excitation energy is shown. The spectrum obtained from the data <lb/>with the AlF  3 target is shown with superimposed that related to the aluminium target. The contribution of the <lb/> Al-derived reaction is the only one up to about 6 MeV <lb/> 19  O excitation energy. <lb/>Several excited states are observed and identified in the low excitation energy region. The well isolated <lb/>peaks are labelled with the relative excitation energy in MeV. Peaks marked with an asterisk refer to the <lb/>transitions in which <lb/> 7  Be ejectiles are in the first excited state at 0.43 MeV. Most of the <lb/> 19  O states have been <lb/>observed in the past by one and two neutron transfer reactions [8], thus confirming the capability of the <lb/>( <lb/> 7 Li, <lb/> 7 Be) reactions to populate such states. For most of them the shell structure configuration is quite well <lb/></body>

			<page> 183 <lb/></page>

			<body> known as for example for the 1.47 MeV excited state (1/2 <lb/> + ) which is mainly a single-particle state with the <lb/>configuration of one neutron in the 2s 1/2 orbital on a <lb/> 18 <lb/> O(0 <lb/> + ) core. <lb/>The estimated energy resolution is about 80 KeV (FWHM). In a previous test run, realized with the same <lb/>experimental setting in order to check the feasibility and study the working conditions, a better resolution <lb/>was achieved (about 50 KeV) [9]. There are two main reasons causing the lack of resolution in the present <lb/>experiment. First, the gold backing of the AlF  3 target was thicker (250 μg/cm <lb/> 2 ) in the present experiment <lb/>compared to 120 μg/cm <lb/> 2 in the test run, thus producing less straggling in the target. In addition, in the test <lb/>run the magnetic fields were set to focus the <lb/> 7  Be relative to the <lb/> 19  O g.s.  in a different focal plane position, <lb/>closer to the spectrometer optical axis (X  foc  = 0), where a minor contribution of aberrations is expected. <lb/> Fig.2 <lb/> 19  O excitation energy spectrum obtained using the AlF  3 target and, superimposed, the normalized <lb/>spectrum obtained from the aluminium target. The known states of <lb/> 19  O are indicated with their energy. <lb/>The presence of <lb/> 27 <lb/> Mg and <lb/> 16 <lb/> N impurity states are also shown. Peaks marked with an asterisk refer to the <lb/>transitions in which <lb/> 7 <lb/> Be ejectiles are in the first excited state at 0.43 MeV. <lb/> 4 <lb/>Angular Distributions <lb/> One of the advantage of working with a large acceptance spectrometer is that, in a single setting of the <lb/>instrument, several scattering angles are covered. As a consequence, a consistent part of a cross section <lb/>angular distribution can be measured in a single run in the same experimental conditions, resulting in a <lb/>reduction of the uncertainty due to the normalization of runs at different angles. <lb/>In the present case, a single set of measurements at central angle <lb/> 25 <lb/> . <lb/>12 <lb/> lab <lb/> allows to obtain an angular <lb/>distribution for scattering angles about 10° &lt;  CM  &lt; 21° in the centre of mass reference frame. <lb/>In Fig. 3 the measured angular distributions for the transition to the not resolved doublet of <lb/> 19  O ground and <lb/>first excited state at 0.096 MeV is shown. In Fig. 4 the angular distribution for the transition to the <lb/> 19  O(1.47MeV, ½ <lb/> + ) excited state is shown. <lb/>A theoretical analysis of the <lb/> 19  F( <lb/> 7  Li, <lb/> 7 <lb/> Be) <lb/> 19  O reaction in the framework of the Charge-Exchange <lb/>Quasiparticle Random Phase Approximation (CEX-QRPA) [10] is on the way. This approach is very <lb/>powerful since can be used to describe the <lb/> 19  O nuclear structure and also to calculate the transition densities <lb/>connecting the <lb/> 19  F ground to the 1p-1h states of <lb/> 19  O, thus allowing a direct connection to reaction cross <lb/>section calculations by a suitable Distorted Wave Born Approximation (DWBA). The use of a realistic semi-<lb/></body>

			<page> 184 <lb/></page>

			<body> microscopic interaction [11], that includes the tensor contribution, in both structure and reaction calculations, <lb/>has allowed in the past to describe very well reactions similar to the present one as the <lb/> 11  B( <lb/> 7 <lb/> Li, <lb/> 7  Be) <lb/> 11  Be and <lb/> 15  N( <lb/> 7  Li, <lb/> 7  Be) <lb/> 15 <lb/> C in the same energy region [1], [2]. <lb/> Fig.3 <lb/> Measured angular distribution for the <lb/> 7  Li + <lb/> 19  F → <lb/> 7  Be + <lb/> 19 <lb/> O(g.s. + 0.096MeV) transition. <lb/> Fig.4 <lb/> Measured angular distribution for the <lb/> 7 <lb/> Li + <lb/> 19  F → <lb/> 7 <lb/> Be + <lb/> 19  O(1.47MeV) transition. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] F. Cappuzzello et al., Nucl. Phys. A 739 (2004) 30. <lb/>[2] S.E.A. Orrigo et al., Phys. Lett. B 633 (2006) 469. <lb/>[3] M. Cavallaro,  &quot; First Application of the MAGNEX Spectrometer: Investigation of the <lb/> 19  F( <lb/> 7  Li, <lb/> 7  Be) <lb/> 19  O <lb/>reaction at 52 MeV &quot; , Ph.D. Thesis, University of Catania, 2009. <lb/>[4] C. Boiano at al., IEEE Transactions On Nuclear Science, 55 (2008) 3563. <lb/>[5] F. Cappuzzello et al., Nucl. Instr. Meth. A (submitted). <lb/>[6] A.Lazzaro et al., Proceedings of the &quot; 7 <lb/> th International Computational Accelerator Physics <lb/>Conference &quot; , East Lansing, Michigan, 2002. IOP series 175 (2002) 171. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body> dσ/dΩ (μb/sr) <lb/> θ CM  (deg) <lb/> 7  Li + <lb/> 19  F → <lb/> 7  Be + <lb/> 19 <lb/> O g.s.+0.096 <lb/> 7  Li + <lb/> 19 <lb/> F → <lb/> 7  Be + <lb/> 19  O  1.47 <lb/> θ CM  (deg) <lb/>dσ/dΩ (μb/sr) <lb/></body>

			<page> 185 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [7] M. Berz, Nucl. Instr. Meth. A 298 (1990) 426. <lb/>[8] J.L.Wiza et al., Phys. Rev. 143 (1966) 676. <lb/>[9] M. Cavallaro et al., Proceedings of the Conference: &quot; Nuclear Physics and Astrophysics: From Stable <lb/>Beams to Exotic Nuclei, 2008, Cappadocia, Turkey. AIP Conf. Proc. 1072 (2008) 249. <lb/>[10] H. Lenske, Nucl.Phys. A482 (1988) 343. <lb/>[11] H. Hoffmann et al., Phys. Rev.C 57 (1998) 2281. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
