<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="headnote"> arXiv:1406.0546v1  [physics.acc-ph] 2 Jun 2014 <lb/></note>

			<front> LHC Optics Measurement with Proton Tracks <lb/>Detected by the Roman Pots of the TOTEM <lb/>Experiment <lb/> The TOTEM Collaboration: G. Antchev <lb/> a  , P. Aspell <lb/> 8  , <lb/>I. Atanassov <lb/> 8,a  , V. Avati <lb/> 8  , J. Baechler <lb/> 8  , V. Berardi <lb/> 5a,5b  , <lb/>M. Berretti <lb/> 7b  , E. Bossini <lb/> 7b  , U. Bottigli <lb/> 7b  , M. Bozzo <lb/> 6a,6b  , <lb/>E. Brücken <lb/> 3a,3b  , A. Buzzo <lb/> 6a  , F. S. Cafagna <lb/> 5a  , M. G. Catanesi <lb/> 5a  , <lb/>C. Covault <lb/> 9  , M. Csanád <lb/> 4,b  , T. Csörg˝ o <lb/> 4  , M. Deile <lb/> 8  , <lb/>M. Doubek <lb/> 1b  , K. Eggert <lb/> 9  , V. Eremin <lb/> c  , F. Ferro <lb/> 6a  , A. <lb/>Fiergolski <lb/> 5a,d  , F. Garcia <lb/> 3a  , V. Georgiev <lb/> 11  , S. Giani <lb/> 8  , <lb/>L. Grzanka <lb/> 10,e  , J. Hammerbauer <lb/> 11  , J. Heino <lb/> 3a  , T. Hilden <lb/> 3a,3b  , <lb/>A. Karev <lb/> 8  , J. Kašpar <lb/> 1a,8  , J. Kopal <lb/> 1a,8  , V. Kundrát <lb/> 1a  , S. Lami <lb/> 7a  , <lb/>G. Latino <lb/> 7b  , R. Lauhakangas <lb/> 3a  , T. Leszko <lb/> d  , E. Lippmaa <lb/> 2  , <lb/>J. Lippmaa <lb/> 2  , M. V. Lokajíček <lb/> 1a  , L. Losurdo <lb/> 7b  , <lb/>M. Lo Vetere <lb/> 6a,6b  , F. Lucas Rodríguez <lb/> 8  , M. Macrí <lb/> 6a  , T. Mäki <lb/> 3a  , <lb/>A. Mercadante <lb/> 5a  , N. Minafra <lb/> 5b ,8  , S. Minutoli <lb/> 6a  , F. Nemes <lb/> 4,b  , <lb/>H. Niewiadomski <lb/> 8  , E. Oliveri <lb/> 7b  , F. Oljemark <lb/> 3a,3b  , R. Orava <lb/> 3a,3b  , <lb/>M. Oriunno <lb/> f  , K. ¨ <lb/>Osterberg <lb/> 3a,3b  , P. Palazzi <lb/> 7b  , Z. Peroutka <lb/> 11  , <lb/>J. Procházka <lb/> 1a  , M. Quinto <lb/> 5a,5b  , E. Radermacher <lb/> 8  , <lb/>E. Radicioni <lb/> 5a  , F. Ravotti <lb/> 8  , E. Robutti <lb/> 6a  , L. Ropelewski <lb/> 8  , <lb/>G. Ruggiero <lb/> 8  , H. Saarikko <lb/> 3a ,3b  , A. Scribano <lb/> 7b  , J. Smajek <lb/> 8  , <lb/>W. Snoeys <lb/> 8  , J. Sziklai <lb/> 4  , C. Taylor <lb/> 9  , N. Turini <lb/> 7b  , V. Vacek <lb/> 1b  , <lb/>J. Welti <lb/> 3a,3b  , J. Whitmore <lb/> g  , P. Wyszkowski <lb/> 10  , K. Zielinski <lb/> 10 <lb/> 1a  Institute of Physics, ASCR, Praha, Czech Republic, <lb/> 1b  Czech Technical University, Praha, Czech Republic, <lb/> 2  National Institute of Chemical Physics and Biophysics NICPB, Tallinn, Estonia, <lb/> 3a  Helsinki Institute of Physics, Helsinki, Finland, <lb/> 3b  Department of Physics, University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland, <lb/> 4  MTA Wigner Research Center, RMKI Budapest, Hungary, <lb/> 5a  INFN Sezione di Bari, Bari, Italy, <lb/> 5b  Dipartimento Interateneo di Fisica di Bari, Italy, <lb/> 6a  INFN Sezione di Genova, Genova, Italy, <lb/> 6b  Universià degli Studi di Genova, Genova, Italy, <lb/> 7a  INFN Sezione di Pisa, Pisa, Italy, <lb/> 7b  Universià degli Studi di Siena and Gruppo Collegato INFN di Siena, Siena, Italy, <lb/> 8  CERN, Geneva, Switzerland, <lb/> 9  Case Western Reserve University, Dept. of Physics, Cleveland, OH, USA, <lb/> 10  AGH University of Science and Technology, Krakow, Poland, <lb/> 11  University of West Bohemia, Pilsen, Czech Republic. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote"> LHC Optics Measurement with Proton Tracks by TOTEM <lb/></note>

			<page> 2 <lb/></page>

			<front> E-mail: frigyes.janos.nemes@cern.ch <lb/> Abstract. Precise knowledge of the beam optics at the LHC is crucial to fulfill <lb/>the physics goals of the TOTEM experiment, where the kinematics of the scattered <lb/>protons is reconstructed with the near-beam telescopes – so-called Roman Pots (RP). <lb/>Before being detected, the protons&apos; trajectories are influenced by the magnetic fields <lb/>of the accelerator lattice. Thus precise understanding of the proton transport is of <lb/>key importance for the experiment. A novel method of optics evaluation is proposed <lb/>which exploits kinematical distributions of elastically scattered protons observed in the <lb/>RPs. Theoretical predictions, as well as Monte Carlo studies, show that the residual <lb/>uncertainty of this optics estimation method is smaller than 2.5 . <lb/> PACS numbers: 29.27.Eg, 25.60.Bx, 25.40.Cm, 02.50.Ng <lb/> Submitted to: New J. Phys. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote"> LHC Optics Measurement with Proton Tracks by TOTEM <lb/></note>

			<page> 3 <lb/></page>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> The TOTEM experiment [1] at the LHC is equipped with near beam movable insertions <lb/>– called Roman Pots (RP) – which host silicon detectors to detect protons scattered at <lb/>the LHC Interaction Point 5 (IP5) [2]. This paper reports the results based on data <lb/>acquired with a total of 12 RPs installed symmetrically with respect to IP5. Two units <lb/>of 3 RPs are inserted downstream of each outgoing LHC beam: the &quot; near &quot; and the <lb/> &quot; far &quot; unit located at s = ±214.63 m and s = ±220.00 m, respectively, where s denotes <lb/>the distance from IP5. The arrangement of the RP devices along the two beams is <lb/>schematically illustrated in figure 1. <lb/>Each unit consists of 2 vertical, so-called &quot; top &quot; and &quot; bottom &quot; , and 1 horizontal RP. <lb/>The two diagonals top left of IP–bottom right of IP and bottom left of IP–top right of <lb/>IP, tagging elastic candidates, are used as almost independent experiments. The details <lb/>of the set-up are discussed in [3]. <lb/> Figure 1. (color online) Schematic layout of the LHC magnet lattice at IP5 up to the <lb/> &quot; near &quot; and &quot; far &quot; Roman Pot units, where the near and far pots are indicated by full <lb/>(red) dots on beams 1 and 2, at the positions indicated by arrows. <lb/> Each RP is equipped with a telescope of 10 silicon microstrip sensors of 66 µm pitch <lb/>which provides spatial track reconstruction resolution σ(x, y) of 11 µm [4]. Given the <lb/>longitudinal distance between the units of ∆s = 5.372 m the proton angles are measured <lb/>by the RPs with an uncertainty of 2.9 µrad. <lb/> During the measurement the detectors in the vertical and horizontal RPs overlap, <lb/>which enables a precise relative alignment of all the three RPs by correlating their <lb/>positions via common particle tracks. The alignment uncertainty better than 10 µm is <lb/>attained, the details are discussed in [4, 5]. <lb/>The proton trajectories, thus their positions observed by RPs, are affected by <lb/>magnetic fields of the accelerator lattice. The accelerator settings define the machine <lb/>optics which can be characterized with the value of β <lb/>  *  at IP5. It determines the physics <lb/>reach of the experiment [3]: runs with high β <lb/>  *  = 90 – 2500 m are characterized by low <lb/>beam divergence allowing for precise scattering angle measurements while runs of low <lb/> β <lb/>  *  = 0.5 – 11 m, due to small interaction vertex size, provide higher luminosity and thus <lb/>are more suitable to study rare processes. In the following sections we will analyze two <lb/>representatives of these LHC runs, corresponding to machine optics with β <lb/>  *  = 3.5 m <lb/>and 90 m, respectively [2, 6]. <lb/>In order to reconstruct the kinematics of proton-proton scattering precisely, an <lb/>accurate model of proton transport is indispensable. TOTEM has developed a novel <lb/>method to evaluate the optics of the machine by using angle-position distributions of <lb/>elastically scattered protons observed in the RP detectors. The method, discussed in <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> LHC Optics Measurement with Proton Tracks by TOTEM <lb/></note>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<body> detail in the following sections, has been successfully applied to data samples recorded <lb/>in 2010 and 2012 [8–12]. <lb/>Section 2 introduces the so-called transport matrix, which describes the proton <lb/>transport through the LHC lattice, while machine imperfections are discussed <lb/>in section 3. The proposed novel method for optics evaluation is based on the correlations <lb/>between the transport matrix elements. These correlations allow the estimation of <lb/>those optical functions which are strongly correlated to measurable combinations and <lb/>estimators of certain elements of this transport matrix. Therefore, it is fundamental to <lb/>study these correlations in detail, which is the subject of section 4. The corresponding <lb/>eigenvector decomposition of the transport matrix is used to gain insight into the <lb/>magnitude of the reduction of uncertainties in the determination of LHC optics that <lb/>can be obtained from using TOTEM data and provides the theoretical baseline of the <lb/>method. <lb/>Section 5 brings the theory to practice, by specifying the estimators, obtained from <lb/>elastic track distributions measured in RPs. Finally, the algorithm that we applied to <lb/>estimate the LHC optics from TOTEM data is described and discussed in section 6. <lb/>The uncertainty of this novel method of LHC optics determination was estimated with <lb/>Monte Carlo simulations, that are described in detail in section 7. <lb/> 2. Proton transport model <lb/> Scattered protons are detected by the Roman Pots after having traversed a segment of <lb/>the LHC lattice containing 29 main and corrector magnets per beam, shown in figure 1. <lb/>The trajectory of protons produced with transverse positions ‡ (x <lb/>  *  , y <lb/>  *  ) and angles <lb/>(Θ <lb/>  * <lb/> x  , Θ <lb/>  * <lb/> y  ) at IP5 is described approximately by a linear formula <lb/>d(s) = T (s) · <lb/>d <lb/>  *  , <lb/> (1) <lb/>where <lb/>d = (x, Θ  x  , y, Θ  y  , ∆p/p) <lb/> T  , p and ∆p denote the nominal beam momentum and <lb/>the proton longitudinal momentum loss, respectively. The single pass transport matrix <lb/> T = <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> v  x  L  x  m  13  m  14  D  x <lb/> dvx <lb/>ds <lb/>dLx <lb/>ds <lb/> m  23  m  24 <lb/>dDx <lb/>ds <lb/> m  31  m  32  v  y <lb/> L  y  D  y <lb/> m  41  m  42 <lb/>dvy <lb/>ds <lb/>dLy <lb/>ds <lb/>dDy <lb/>ds <lb/> 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> (2) <lb/>is defined by the optical functions [13]. The horizontal and vertical magnifications <lb/> v  x,y  = <lb/> β  x,y  /β  *  cos ∆µ  x,y <lb/> (3) <lb/>and the effective lengths <lb/> L  x,y  = <lb/> β  x,y  β  *  sin ∆µ  x,y <lb/> (4) <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">  ‡ The &apos; <lb/>  *  &apos; superscript indicates that the value is taken at the LHC Interaction Point 5. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> LHC Optics Measurement with Proton Tracks by TOTEM <lb/></note>

			<page> 5 <lb/></page>

			<body> are functions of the betatron amplitudes β  x,y  and the relative phase advance <lb/>∆µ  x,y  = <lb/>  RP <lb/> IP <lb/> ds <lb/> β  x,y <lb/> , <lb/> (5) <lb/>and are of particular importance for proton kinematics reconstruction. The D  x  and D  y <lb/> elements are the horizontal and vertical dispersion, respectively. <lb/>Elastically scattered protons are relatively easy to distinguish due to their scattering <lb/>angle correlations. In addition, these correlations are sensitive to the machine <lb/>optics. Therefore, elastic proton-proton scattering measurements are ideally suited to <lb/>investigate the optics the LHC accelerator. <lb/>In case of the LHC nominal optics the coupling coefficients are, by design, equal to <lb/>zero <lb/> m  13  , ..., m  42  = 0 . <lb/> (6) <lb/>Moreover, for elastically scattered protons the contribution of the vertex position (x <lb/>  *  , y <lb/>  *  ) <lb/>in (1) is canceled due to the anti-symmetry of the elastic scattering angles of the two <lb/>diagonals. Also, those terms of (1) which are proportional to the horizontal or vertical <lb/>dispersions D  x,y  vanish, since ∆p = 0 for elastic scattering. Furthermore, the horizontal <lb/>phase advance ∆µ  x  = π at 219.59 m, shown in figure 2, and consequently the horizontal <lb/>effective length L  x  vanishes close to the far RP unit, as it is shown in figure 3. Therefore, <lb/>dL  x  /ds is used for the reconstruction of the kinematics of proton-proton scattering. <lb/>In summary, the kinematics of elastically scattered protons at IP5 can be <lb/>reconstructed on the basis of RP proton tracks using (1): <lb/>Θ <lb/>  * <lb/> y  ≈ <lb/> y <lb/>L  y <lb/> , <lb/> Θ <lb/>  * <lb/> x  ≈ <lb/> 1 <lb/> dLx <lb/>ds <lb/> Θ  x  − <lb/> dv  x <lb/> ds <lb/> x <lb/>  * <lb/> , <lb/>x <lb/>  *  = <lb/> x <lb/>v  x <lb/> . <lb/> (7) <lb/>The vertical effective length L  y  and the horizontal magnification v  x  are applied <lb/>in (7) due to their sizeable values, as shown in figures 4 and 5. As the values of the <lb/>reconstructed angles are inversely proportional to the optical functions, the errors of the <lb/>optical functions dominate the systematic errors of the final, physics results of TOTEM <lb/>RP measurements. <lb/>The proton transport matrix T (s; M), calculated with MAD-X [14], is defined by <lb/>the machine settings M, which are obtained on the basis of several data sources: the <lb/>magnet currents are first retrieved from TIMBER [15] and then converted to magnet <lb/>strengths with LSA [16], implementing the conversion curves measured by FIDEL [17]. <lb/>The WISE database [18] contains the measured imperfections (field harmonics, magnet <lb/>displacements and rotations) included in M. <lb/> 3. Machine imperfections <lb/> The real LHC machine [2] is subject to additional imperfections ∆M, not measured <lb/>well enough so far, which alter the transport matrix by ∆T : <lb/> T (s; M) → T (s; M + ∆M) = T (s; M) + ∆T. <lb/>(8) <lb/>The most important transport matrix imperfections are due to: <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> LHC Optics Measurement with Proton Tracks by TOTEM <lb/></note>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<body> Figure 2. (color online) The horizontal β  x  and vertical betatron amplitude β  y  for the <lb/>LHC β <lb/>  *  = 3.5 m optics. The horizontal ∆µ  x  and vertical phase advance ∆µ  y  are also <lb/>shown, these functions are normalized to 2π. The plot shows that the horizontal phase <lb/>advance ∆µ  x  = π close to the far RP unit. <lb/> – the magnet current–strength conversion error: σ(k)/k ≈ 10 <lb/> −3  , <lb/>– the beam momentum offset: σ(p)/p ≈ 10 <lb/> −3  . <lb/>Their impact on the important optical functions L  y  and dL  x  /ds is presented in table 1. <lb/>It is clearly visible that the imperfections of the inner triplet (the so called MQXA and <lb/>MQXB magnets) are of high influence on the transport matrix while the optics is less <lb/>sensitive to the strength of the quadrupoles MQY and MQML. <lb/>Other imperfections that are of lower, but not negligible, significance: <lb/>– magnet rotations: δφ ≈ 1 mrad, <lb/>– beam harmonics: δB/B ≈ 10 <lb/> −4  , <lb/>– power converter errors: δI/I ≈ 10 <lb/> −4  , <lb/>– magnet positions: δx, δy ≈ 100 µm. <lb/> Generally, as indicated in table 1, for high-β <lb/>  *  optics the magnitude of ∆T is sufficiently <lb/>small from the viewpoint of data analysis. <lb/>However, the sensitivity of the low-β <lb/>  *  optics to the machine imperfections is <lb/>significant and cannot be neglected. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> LHC Optics Measurement with Proton Tracks by TOTEM <lb/></note>

			<page> 7 <lb/></page>

			<body> Figure 3. (color online) The horizontal effective length L  x  and its derivative dL  x  /ds <lb/> with respect to s as a function of the distance s in case of the LHC β <lb/>  *  = 3.5 m optics. <lb/>The evolution of the optical functions is shown starting from IP5 up to the Roman <lb/>Pot stations. The plot indicates that L  x  = 0 close to the far RP unit, thus in the <lb/>reconstruction of proton kinematics, dL  x  /ds is used instead of L  x  . <lb/> The proton reconstruction is based on (7). Thus it is necessary to know the effective <lb/>lengths L  x,y  and their derivatives with an uncertainty better than 1–2 % in order to <lb/>measure the total cross-section σ  tot  with the aimed uncertainty of [19]. The currently <lb/>available ∆β/β beating measurement with an error of 5−10 % does not allow to estimate <lb/>∆T with the uncertainty, required by the TOTEM physics program [20]. However, as it <lb/>is shown in the following sections, ∆T can be determined well enough from the proton <lb/>tracks in the Roman Pots, by exploiting the properties of the optics and those of the <lb/>elastic pp scattering, so that the aimed 1% relative uncertainty in the determination of <lb/>the total pp cross-section becomes within the reach of TOTEM. <lb/> 4. Correlations in the transport matrix <lb/> The transport matrix T defining the proton transport from IP5 to the RPs is a product <lb/>of matrices that describe the magnetic field of the lattice elements along the proton <lb/>trajectory. The imperfections of the individual magnets alter the cumulative transport <lb/>function. It turns out that independently of the origin of the imperfection (strength of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> LHC Optics Measurement with Proton Tracks by TOTEM <lb/></note>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<body> Figure 4. (color online) The evolution of the vertical effective length L  y  and its <lb/>derivative dL  y  /ds between IP5 and the location of the Roman Pot stations, for the <lb/> β <lb/>  *  = 3.5 m optics of the LHC. <lb/> δL  y,b  1  ,f ar  /L  y,b  1  ,f ar  [%] <lb/> δ <lb/> dL  x,b 1 <lb/> ds <lb/> / <lb/> dL  x,b 1 <lb/> ds <lb/> [%] <lb/>Perturbed element β <lb/>  *  = 3.5 m β <lb/>  *  = 90 m β <lb/>  *  = 3.5 m β <lb/>  *  = 90 m <lb/> MQXA.1R5 <lb/>0.98 <lb/>0.14 <lb/> −0.46 <lb/> −0.42 <lb/> MQXB.A2R5 <lb/> −2.24 <lb/>−0.23 <lb/> 0.33 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>MQXB.B2R5 <lb/> −2.42 <lb/>−0.25 <lb/> 0.45 <lb/>0.42 <lb/>MQXA.3R5 <lb/>1.45 <lb/>0.20 <lb/> −1.14 <lb/>−1.08 <lb/> MQY.4R5.B1 <lb/> −0.10 <lb/>−0.01 <lb/>−0.02 <lb/> 0.00 <lb/>MQML.5R5.B1 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>∆p  b  1  /p  b  1 <lb/> −2.19 <lb/> 0.01 <lb/> −0.79 <lb/> 0.71 <lb/>Total sensitivity <lb/>4.33 <lb/>0.42 <lb/>1.57 <lb/>1.46 <lb/> Table 1. Sensitivity of the vertical effective length L  y,b1  and dL  x,b1  /ds to 1 <lb/> deviations of magnet strengths or beam momentum for low-and high-β <lb/>  *  optics of <lb/>the LHC beam 1. The subscript b  1  indicates Beam 1. Only the most important <lb/>contributions are presented. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> LHC Optics Measurement with Proton Tracks by TOTEM <lb/></note>

			<page> 9 <lb/></page>

			<body> Figure 5. (color online) The evolution of the horizontal ν  x  and vertical ν  y <lb/> magnifications, for the β <lb/>  *  = 3.5 m optics of the LHC. <lb/> any of the magnets, beam momentum offset) the transport matrix is altered in a similar <lb/>way, as can be described quantitatively with eigenvector decomposition, discussed <lb/>in section 4.1. <lb/> 4.1. Correlation matrix of imperfections <lb/> Assuming that the imperfections discussed in section 2 are independent, the covariance <lb/>matrix describing the relations among the errors of the optical functions can be <lb/>calculated: <lb/> V = Cov(∆T  r  ) = E <lb/> ∆T  r  ∆T <lb/> T <lb/>r <lb/> , <lb/> (9) <lb/>where T  r  is the relevant 8-dimensional subset of the transport matrix <lb/> T  T <lb/> r  = (v  x  , L  x  , <lb/> dv  x <lb/> ds <lb/> , <lb/> dL  x <lb/> ds <lb/> , v  y  , L  y  , <lb/> dv  y <lb/> ds <lb/> , <lb/> dL  y <lb/> ds <lb/>) , <lb/> (10) <lb/>which is presented as a vector for simplicity. <lb/>The optical functions contained in T  r  differ by orders of magnitude and, are <lb/>expressed in different physical units. Therefore, a normalization of V is necessary and <lb/>the use of the correlation matrix C, defined as <lb/> C  i,j  = <lb/> V  i,j <lb/> V  i,i  · V  j,j <lb/> , <lb/> (11) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> LHC Optics Measurement with Proton Tracks by TOTEM <lb/></note>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>

			<body> is preferred. An identical behaviour of uncertainties for both beams was observed and <lb/>therefore it is enough to study the Beam 1. In case of the β <lb/>  *  = 3.5 m optics the following <lb/>error correlation matrix is obtained: <lb/> C = <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> 1.00 <lb/>0.74 −0.42 −0.80 −0.51 −0.46 −0.61 −0.44 <lb/> 0.74 <lb/>1.00 −0.63 −1.00 −0.25 −0.30 −0.32 −0.29 <lb/>−0.42 −0.63 <lb/> 1.00 <lb/>0.62 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.08 <lb/> −0.80 −1.00 <lb/> 0.62 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>0.33 <lb/>0.37 <lb/>0.32 <lb/> −0.51 −0.25 <lb/> 0.03 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.99 <lb/>0.98 <lb/>0.98 <lb/> −0.46 −0.30 <lb/> 0.07 <lb/>0.33 <lb/>0.99 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.96 <lb/>1.00 <lb/> −0.61 −0.32 <lb/> 0.01 <lb/>0.37 <lb/>0.98 <lb/>0.96 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.95 <lb/> −0.44 −0.29 <lb/> 0.08 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>0.98 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.95 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> . (12) <lb/> The non-diagonal elements of C, which are close to ±1, indicate strong correlations <lb/>between the elements of ∆T  r  . Consequently, the machine imperfections alter correlated <lb/> groups of optical functions. <lb/>This observation can be further quantified by the eigenvector decomposition of C, <lb/> which yields the following vector of eigenvalues λ(C) for the β <lb/>  *  = 3.5 m optics: <lb/> λ(C) = (4.9, 2.3, 0.53, 0.27, 0.01, 0.01, 0.00, 0.00) . <lb/> (13) <lb/>Since the two largest eigenvalues λ  1  = 4.9 and λ  2  = 2.3 dominate the others, the <lb/>correlation system is practically two dimensional with the following two eigenvectors <lb/> v  1  = ( 0.35, 0.30, −0.16, −0.31, −0.40, −0.41, −0.41, −0.40) , <lb/> (14) <lb/> v  2  = (−0.26, −0.46, 0.47, 0.45, −0.29, −0.27, −0.25, −0.28) . <lb/> (15) <lb/>Therefore, contributions of the individual lattice imperfections cannot be evaluated. <lb/>On the other hand, as the imperfections alter approximately only a two-dimensional <lb/>subspace, a measurement of a small set of weakly correlated optical functions would <lb/>theoretically yield an approximate knowledge of ∆T  r  . <lb/> 4.2. Error estimation of the method <lb/> Let us assume for the moment that we can precisely reconstruct the contributions to ∆T  r <lb/> of the two most significant eigenvectors while neglecting that of the others. The error <lb/>of such reconstructed transport matrix can be estimated by evaluating the contribution <lb/>of the remaining eigenvectors: <lb/> δ∆T  r,i  = <lb/> E  i,i  · V  i,i  , <lb/> (16) <lb/>where <lb/> E = N · <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> 0 0 0 0 0 <lb/>0 0 0 0 0 <lb/>0 0 λ  3  0 0 <lb/>. . . <lb/>. . . <lb/>. . . <lb/>0 0 0 0 λ  8 <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> · N <lb/> T <lb/> (17) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> LHC Optics Measurement with Proton Tracks by TOTEM <lb/></note>

			<page> 11 <lb/></page>

			<body> and N = (ν  1  , ..., ν  8  ) is the basis change matrix composed of eigenvectors ν  i  corresponding <lb/>to the eigenvalues λ  i  . <lb/>The relative optics uncertainty before and after the estimation of the most <lb/>significant eigenvectors is summarized in table 2. According to the table, even if we <lb/> v  x,f ar <lb/> L  x,f ar <lb/> dvx <lb/>ds <lb/>dLx <lb/>ds <lb/> T  r,i <lb/> −3.1 <lb/> −1.32 · 10 <lb/> −1  m <lb/>3.1 · 10 <lb/> −2  m <lb/> −1 <lb/> −3.21 · 10 <lb/> −1 <lb/> √ <lb/> V  i,i <lb/> |T  r,i  |  [%] 2.0 · 10 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 3.4 · 10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 4.2 · 10 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 1.6 <lb/> δ∆T  r,i <lb/> |T  r,i  |  [%] 9.5 · 10 <lb/> −2 <lb/> 9.1 · 10 <lb/> 1 <lb/> 2.6 · 10 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 3.4 · 10 <lb/> −1 <lb/> v  y,f ar <lb/> L  y,f ar <lb/> dvy <lb/>ds <lb/>dLy <lb/>ds <lb/> T  r,i <lb/> −4.3 <lb/> 2.24 · 10 <lb/> 1  m −6.1 · 10 <lb/> −2  m <lb/> −1 <lb/> 8.60 · 10 <lb/> −2 <lb/> √ <lb/> V  i,i <lb/> |T  r,i  | <lb/> [%] 6.8 · 10 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 4.3 <lb/>5.9 · 10 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 1.5 · 10 <lb/> 1 <lb/> δ∆T  r,i <lb/> |T  r,i  |  [%] 6.1 · 10 <lb/> −2 <lb/> 6.4 · 10 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 8.3 · 10 <lb/> −2 <lb/> 2.75 <lb/> Table 2. Nominal values of the optical functions T  r,i  and their relative uncertainty <lb/>before ( <lb/> V  i,i  / |T  r,i  |) and after (δ∆T  r,i  / |T  r,i  |) the determination of the two most <lb/>significant eigenvectors (β <lb/>  *  = 3.5 m, Beam 1). <lb/> limit ourselves only to the first two most significant eigenvalues, the uncertainty of <lb/>optical functions due to machine imperfections drops significantly. In particular, in case <lb/>of dL  x  /ds and L  y  a significant error reduction down to a per mil level is observed. <lb/>Unfortunately, due to ∆µ  x  = π (figure 2), the uncertainty of L  x  , although importantly <lb/>improved, remains very large and the use of dL  x  /ds for proton kinematics reconstruction <lb/>should be preferred. <lb/>In the following sections a practical numerical method of inferring the optics from <lb/>the RP proton tracks is presented and its validation with Monte Carlo calculations is <lb/>reported. <lb/> 5. Optics estimators from proton tracks measured by Roman Pots (β <lb/>  *  =3.5 <lb/>m optics) <lb/> The TOTEM experiment can select the elastically scattered protons with high purity <lb/>and efficiency [8,9]. The RP detector system, due to its high resolution (σ(x, y) ≈ 11 µm, <lb/>σ(Θ  x,y  ) ≈ 2.9 µrad), can measure very precisely the proton angles, positions and the <lb/>angle-position relations on an event-by-event basis. These quantities can be used to <lb/>define a set of estimators characterizing the correlations between the elements of the <lb/>transport matrix T or between the transport matrices of the two LHC beams. Such a <lb/>set of estimators <lb/>  1  , ..., ˆ <lb/> R  10  (defined in the next sections) is exploited to reconstruct, for <lb/>both LHC beams, the imperfect transport matrix T (M) + ∆T defined in (8). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> LHC Optics Measurement with Proton Tracks by TOTEM <lb/></note>

			<page> 12 <lb/></page>

			<body> 5.1. Correlations between the beams <lb/> Since the momentum of the two LHC beams is identical, the elastically scattered protons <lb/>will be deflected symmetrically from their nominal trajectories of Beam 1 and Beam 2: <lb/>Θ <lb/>  * <lb/> x,b  1 <lb/> = −Θ <lb/>  * <lb/> x,b  2 <lb/> , Θ <lb/>  * <lb/> y,b  1 <lb/> = −Θ <lb/>  * <lb/> y,b  2 <lb/> , <lb/> (18) <lb/>which allows to compute ratios R  1,2  relating the effective lengths at the RP locations of <lb/>the two beams. From (1) and (18) we obtain: <lb/> R  1  ≡ <lb/> Θ  x,b  1 <lb/> Θ  x,b  2 <lb/> ≈ <lb/> dL  x,b 1 <lb/> ds <lb/> · Θ <lb/>  * <lb/> x,b  1 <lb/> dL  x,b 2 <lb/> ds <lb/> · Θ <lb/>  * <lb/> x,b  2 <lb/> = − <lb/> dL  x,b 1 <lb/> ds <lb/>dL  x,b 2 <lb/> ds <lb/> , <lb/> (19) <lb/> R  2  ≡ <lb/> y  b  1  ,f ar <lb/> y  b  2  ,f ar <lb/> ≈ − <lb/> L  y,b  1  ,f ar <lb/> L  y,b  2  ,f ar <lb/> , <lb/> (20) <lb/>where the subscripts b  1  and b  2  indicate Beam 1 and 2, respectively. Approximations <lb/>present in (19) and (20) represent the impact of statistical effects such as detector <lb/>resolution, beam divergence and primary vertex position distribution. The estimators <lb/>  1  and <lb/>  2  are finally obtained from the (Θ  x,b  1  , Θ  x,b  2  ) and (y  b  1  ,f ar  , y  b  2  ,f ar  ) distributions <lb/>and are defined with the help of the distributions&apos; principal eigenvector, as illustrated <lb/>in figures 6 and 7. <lb/>The width of the distributions is determined by the beam divergence and the vertex <lb/>contribution, which leads to 0.5% uncertainty on the eigenvector&apos;s slope parameter. <lb/> [rad] <lb/> x,b <lb/> Q <lb/> -0.15 -0.1 -0.05 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 0.15 <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> rad] <lb/> x,b <lb/> Q <lb/> -0.15 <lb/>-0.1 <lb/>-0.05 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> Figure 6. (color online) Beam 1 and 2 elastic scattering angle correlation in the <lb/>horizontal plane (Θ  x,b1  , Θ  x,b2  ) of protons detected by the Roman Pots. <lb/> 5.2. Single beam correlations <lb/> The distributions of proton angles and positions measured by the Roman Pots define <lb/>the ratios of certain elements of the transport matrix T , defined by (1) and (2). First <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> LHC Optics Measurement with Proton Tracks by TOTEM <lb/></note>

			<page> 13 <lb/></page>

			<body> [mm] <lb/> b ,220 <lb/> y <lb/>-10 <lb/>-5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>[mm] <lb/> b , 220 <lb/> y <lb/> -10 <lb/>-5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 2 <lb/>1 <lb/> Figure 7. (color online) Correlation between positions (vertical projections) of <lb/>elastically scattered protons detected in Beam 1 and 2. The sharp edges are due <lb/>to the vertical acceptance limits of the detectors. <lb/> of all, dL  y  /ds and L  y  are related by <lb/> R  3  ≡ <lb/> Θ  y,b  1 <lb/> y  b  1 <lb/> ≈ <lb/> dL  y,b 1 <lb/> ds <lb/> L  y,b  1 <lb/> , <lb/>R  4  ≡ <lb/> Θ  y,b  2 <lb/> y  b  2 <lb/> ≈ <lb/> dL  y,b 2 <lb/> ds <lb/> L  y,b  2 <lb/> . <lb/> (21) <lb/>The corresponding estimators <lb/>  3  and <lb/>  4  can be calculated with an uncertainty of 0.5% <lb/>from the distributions as presented in figure 8. <lb/> Figure 8. (color online) Correlation between vertical position and angle of elastically <lb/>scattered protons at the RP of Beam 1. <lb/> Similarly, we exploit the horizontal dependencies to quantify the relations between <lb/>dL  x  /ds and L  x  . As L  x  is close to 0, see figure 3, instead of defining the ratio we rather <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> LHC Optics Measurement with Proton Tracks by TOTEM <lb/></note>

			<page> 14 <lb/></page>

			<body> estimate the position s  0  along the beam line (with the uncertainty of about 1 m), for <lb/>which L  x  = 0. This is accomplished by resolving <lb/> L  x  (s  0  ) <lb/>dL  x  (s  1  )/ds <lb/>= <lb/> L  x  (s  1  ) <lb/>dL  x  (s  1  )/ds <lb/>+ (s  0  − s  1  ) = 0 , <lb/> (22) <lb/>for s  0  , where s  1  denotes the coordinate of the Roman Pot station along the beam with <lb/>respect to IP5. Obviously, dL  x  (s)/ds is constant along the RP station as no magnetic <lb/>fields are present at the RP location. The ratios L  x  (s  1  )/ <lb/> dLx(s  1  ) <lb/>ds <lb/> for Beam 1 and 2, <lb/>similarly to the vertical constraints R  3  and R  4  , are defined by the proton tracks: <lb/> L  x <lb/> dLx <lb/>ds <lb/> ≈ <lb/> x <lb/> Θ  x <lb/> , <lb/> (23) <lb/>which is illustrated in figure 9. In this way two further constraints and the corresponding <lb/>estimators (for Beam 1 and 2) are obtained: <lb/> R  5  ≡ s  b  1  and R  6  ≡ s  b  2  . <lb/> (24) <lb/> Figure 9. (color online) Correlation between the horizontal angle and position of <lb/>elastically scattered protons at the RP of Beam 1. <lb/> 5.3. Coupling / rotation <lb/> In reality the coupling coefficients m  13  , ..., m  42  cannot be always neglected, as it is <lb/>assumed by (6). RP proton tracks can help to determine the coupling components <lb/>of the transport matrix T as well, where it is especially important that L  x  is close to <lb/>zero at the RP locations. Always based on (1) and (2), four additional constraints (for <lb/>each of the two LHC beams and for each unit of the RP station) can be defined: <lb/> R  7,...,10  ≡ <lb/> x  near(f ar) <lb/> y  near(f ar) <lb/> ≈ <lb/> m  14,near(f ar) <lb/> L  y,near(f ar) <lb/> . <lb/> (25) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> LHC Optics Measurement with Proton Tracks by TOTEM <lb/></note>

			<page> 15 <lb/></page>

			<body> The subscripts &quot; near &quot; and &quot; far &quot; indicate the position of the RP along the beam with <lb/>respect to the IP. Geometrically R  7,...,10  describe the rotation of the RP scoring plane <lb/>about the beam axis. Analogously to the previous sections, the estimators <lb/>  7,...,10  are <lb/>obtained from track distributions as presented in figure 10 and an uncertainty of 3% is <lb/>achieved. <lb/> Figure 10. (color online) Vertical vs. horizontal track position at the RP  near  of the <lb/>LHC Beam 1. <lb/> 6. Optical functions estimation <lb/> The machine imperfections ∆M, leading to the transport matrix change ∆T , are in <lb/>practice determined with the χ <lb/> 2  minimization procedure: <lb/> ∆M = arg min(χ <lb/> 2  ) , <lb/> (26) <lb/>defined on the basis of the estimators <lb/>  1  ... ˆ <lb/> R  10  , where the arg min function gives the <lb/>phase space position where the χ <lb/> 2  is minimized. As it was discussed in section 4.1, <lb/>although the overall alteration of the transport matrix ∆T can be determined precisely <lb/>based on a few optical functions&apos; measurements, the contributions of individual <lb/>imperfections cannot be established. In terms of optimization, such a problem has <lb/>no unique solution and additional constraints, defined by the machine tolerance, have <lb/>to be added. <lb/>Therefore, the χ <lb/> 2  function is composed of the part defined by the Roman Pot tracks&apos; <lb/>distributions and the one reflecting the LHC tolerances: <lb/> χ <lb/> 2  = χ <lb/> 2 <lb/> Design  + χ <lb/> 2 <lb/> M easured  . <lb/> (27) <lb/>The design part <lb/> χ <lb/> 2 <lb/> Design  = <lb/> 12 <lb/> i=1 <lb/>  k  i  − k  i,MAD-X <lb/> σ(k  i  ) <lb/>  2 <lb/> + <lb/> 12 <lb/> i=1 <lb/>  φ  i  − φ  i,MAD-X <lb/> σ(φ  i  ) <lb/>  2 <lb/> + <lb/> 2 <lb/> i=1 <lb/>  p  i  − p  i,MAD-X <lb/> σ(p  i  ) <lb/>  2 <lb/> (28) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> LHC Optics Measurement with Proton Tracks by TOTEM <lb/></note>

			<page> 16 <lb/></page>

			<body> where k  i  and φ  i  are the nominal strength and rotation of the ith magnet, respectively. <lb/>Thus (28) defines the nominal machine (k  i  , φ  i  , p  i  ) as an attractor in the phase space. <lb/>Both LHC beams are treated simultaneously. Only the relevant subset of machine <lb/>imperfections ∆M was selected. The obtained 26-dimensional optimization phase <lb/>space includes the magnet strengths (12 variables), rotations (12 variables) and beam <lb/>momentum offsets (2 variables). Magnet rotations are included into the phase space, <lb/>otherwise only the coupling coefficients m  13  , ..., m  42  could induce rotations in the (x, y) <lb/> plane (25), which could bias the result. <lb/>The measured part <lb/> χ <lb/> 2 <lb/> M easured  = <lb/> 10 <lb/> i=1 <lb/>  i  − R  i,MAD-X <lb/> σ( ˆ <lb/> R  i  ) <lb/>  2 <lb/> (29) <lb/>contains the track-based estimators <lb/>  1  ... ˆ <lb/> R  10  (discussed in detail in section 5) together <lb/>with their uncertainty. The subscript &quot; MAD-X &quot; defines the corresponding values <lb/>evaluated with the MAD-X software during the χ <lb/> 2  minimization. <lb/>Table 3 presents the results of the optimization procedure for the β <lb/>  *  = 3.5 m optics <lb/>used by LHC in October 2010 at beam energy E = 3.5 TeV. <lb/>The obtained value of the effective length L  y  of Beam 1 is close to the nominal <lb/>one, while Beam 2 shows a significant change. The same pattern applies to the values <lb/>of dL  x  /ds. The error estimation of the procedure is discussed in section 7. <lb/> L  y,b  1  ,f ar  [m] dL  x,b  1  /ds L  y,b  2  ,f ar  [m] dL  x,b  2  /ds <lb/> Nominal <lb/>22.4 <lb/> −3.21 · 10 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 18.4 <lb/> −3.29 · 10 <lb/> −1 <lb/> Estimated <lb/>22.6 <lb/> −3.12 · 10 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 20.7 <lb/> −3.15 · 10 <lb/> −1 <lb/> Table 3. Selected optical functions of both LHC beams for the β <lb/>  *  = 3.5 m optics, <lb/>obtained with the estimation procedure, compared to their nominal values. <lb/> 7. Monte Carlo validation <lb/> In order to demonstrate that the proposed <lb/>  i  optics estimators are effective the method <lb/>was validated with Monte Carlo simulations. <lb/>In each Monte Carlo simulation the nominal machine settings M were altered <lb/>with simulated machine imperfections ∆M within their tolerances using Gaussian <lb/>distributions. The simulated elastic proton tracks were used afterwards to calculate <lb/>the estimators <lb/>  1  ... ˆ <lb/> R  10  . The study included the impact of <lb/>– magnet strengths, <lb/>– beam momenta, <lb/>– magnet displacements, rotations and harmonics, <lb/>– settings of kickers, <lb/>– measured proton angular distribution. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> LHC Optics Measurement with Proton Tracks by TOTEM <lb/></note>

			<page> 17 <lb/></page>

			<body> The error distributions of the optical functions ∆T obtained for β <lb/>  *  = 3.5 m and <lb/> E = 3.5 TeV are presented in figure 11 and table 4, while the β <lb/>  *  = 90 m results at <lb/> E = 4 TeV are shown in figure 12 and table 5. <lb/>Simulated <lb/>Reconstructed <lb/>optics distribution <lb/>optics error <lb/>Relative optics Mean <lb/>RMS <lb/>Mean <lb/>RMS <lb/>distribution <lb/>[%] <lb/>[%] <lb/>[%] <lb/>[%] <lb/> δL  y,b 1 ,f ar <lb/> L  y,b 1 ,f ar <lb/> 0.39 <lb/>4.2 <lb/>8.3 · 10 <lb/> −2  0.16 <lb/> δdL  x,b 1  /ds <lb/> dL  x,b 1  /ds <lb/> −0.97 <lb/> 1.6 <lb/> −0.13 <lb/> 0.17 <lb/> δL  y,b 2 ,f ar <lb/> L  y,b 2 ,f ar <lb/> −0.14 <lb/> 4.9 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>0.16 <lb/> δdL  x,b 2  /ds <lb/> dL  x,b 2  /ds <lb/> 0.10 <lb/>1.7 <lb/> −9.7 · 10 <lb/> −2  0.17 <lb/> Table 4. The Monte-Carlo study of the impact of the LHC imperfections ∆M on <lb/>selected transport matrix elements dL  x  /ds and L  y  for β <lb/>  *  = 3.5 m at E = 3.5 TeV. The <lb/>LHC parameters were altered within their tolerances. The relative errors of dL  x  /ds <lb/> and L  y  (mean value and RMS) characterize the optics uncertainty before and after <lb/>optics estimation. <lb/> [%] <lb/> y,b1,far <lb/> L <lb/> y,b1,far <lb/> L <lb/> δ <lb/> -8 <lb/>-6 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>Machine instances <lb/> 0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>140 <lb/>160 <lb/>180 <lb/>200 <lb/>220 <lb/> Perturbed optics-<lb/>nominal <lb/>Mean 0.39 % <lb/>RMS 4.2 % <lb/>Perturbed optics-<lb/>reconstructed <lb/>Mean 0.083 % <lb/>RMS 0.16 % <lb/> [%] <lb/>/ds <lb/> x,b1 <lb/> dL <lb/>/ds <lb/> x,b1 <lb/> dL <lb/> δ <lb/> -8 <lb/>-6 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>Machine instances <lb/> 0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>140 <lb/>160 <lb/>180 <lb/>200 <lb/>220 <lb/> Perturbed optics-<lb/>nominal <lb/>Mean -0.97 % <lb/>RMS 1.6 % <lb/>Perturbed optics-<lb/>reconstructed <lb/>Mean -0.13 % <lb/>RMS 0.17 % <lb/> Figure 11. (color online) The MC error distribution of β <lb/>  *  = 3.5 m optical functions <lb/> L  y  and dL  x  /ds for Beam 1 at E = 3.5 TeV, before and after optics estimation. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> LHC Optics Measurement with Proton Tracks by TOTEM <lb/></note>

			<page> 18 <lb/></page>

			<body> Simulated <lb/>Reconstructed <lb/>optics distribution <lb/>optics error <lb/>Relative optics Mean <lb/>RMS <lb/>Mean <lb/>RMS <lb/>distribution <lb/>[%] <lb/>[%] <lb/>[%] <lb/>[%] <lb/> δL  y,b 1 ,f ar <lb/> L  y,b 1 ,f ar <lb/> 2.2 · 10 <lb/> −2 <lb/> 0.46 <lb/>5.8 · 10 <lb/> −2  0.23 <lb/> δdL  x,b 1  /ds <lb/> dL  x,b 1  /ds <lb/> 6.7 · 10 <lb/> −3 <lb/> 1.5 <lb/> −6.4 · 10 <lb/> −2  0.20 <lb/> δL  y,b 2 ,f ar <lb/> L  y,b 2 ,f ar <lb/> −5 · 10 <lb/> −3 <lb/> 0.47 <lb/>5.8 · 10 <lb/> −2 <lb/> 0.23 <lb/> δdL  x,b 2  /ds <lb/> dL  x,b 2  /ds <lb/> 1.8 · 10 <lb/> −2 <lb/> 1.5 <lb/> −7 · 10 <lb/> −2 <lb/> 0.21 <lb/> Table 5. The Monte-Carlo study of the impact of the LHC imperfections ∆M on <lb/>selected transport matrix elements dL  x  /ds and L  y  for β <lb/>  *  = 90 m at E = 4 TeV. The <lb/>LHC parameters were altered within their tolerances. The relative errors of dL  x  /ds <lb/> and L  y  (mean value and RMS) characterize the optics uncertainty before and after <lb/>optics estimation. <lb/> [%] <lb/> y,b1,far <lb/> L <lb/> y,b1,far <lb/> L <lb/> δ <lb/> -8 <lb/>-6 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>Machine instances <lb/> 0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>140 <lb/>160 <lb/>180 <lb/>200 <lb/>220 <lb/> Perturbed optics-<lb/>nominal <lb/>Mean 1 % <lb/>RMS 2 % <lb/>Perturbed optics-<lb/>nominal <lb/>Mean 0.022 % <lb/>RMS 0.46 % <lb/>Perturbed optics-<lb/>reconstructed <lb/>Mean 0.058 % <lb/>RMS 0.23 % <lb/> [%] <lb/>/ds <lb/> x,b1 <lb/> dL <lb/>/ds <lb/> x,b1 <lb/> dL <lb/> δ <lb/> -8 <lb/>-6 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>Machine instances <lb/> 0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>140 <lb/>160 <lb/>180 <lb/>200 <lb/>220 <lb/>240 <lb/> Perturbed optics-<lb/>nominal <lb/>% <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> × <lb/> Mean 6.7 <lb/>RMS 1.5 % <lb/>Perturbed optics-<lb/>reconstructed <lb/>Mean -0.064 % <lb/>RMS 0.2 % <lb/> Figure 12. (color online) The MC error distribution of β <lb/>  *  = 90 m optical functions <lb/> L  y  and dL  x  /ds for Beam 1 at E = 4 TeV, before and after optics estimation. <lb/> First of all, the impact of the machine imperfections ∆M on the transport matrix <lb/>∆T , as shown by the MC study, is identical to the theoretical prediction presented <lb/>in table 2. The bias of the simulated optics distributions is due to magnetic field <lb/>harmonics as reported by the LHC imperfections database [18]. The final value of mean <lb/>after optics estimation procedure contributes to the total uncertainty of the method. <lb/>The errors of the reconstructed optical functions are significantly smaller than <lb/>evaluated theoretically in section 4.2. This results from the larger number of design and <lb/>measured constraints (27), employed in the numerical estimation procedure of section 6. <lb/>In particular, the collinearity of elastically scattered protons was exploited in addition. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> LHC Optics Measurement with Proton Tracks by TOTEM <lb/></note>

			<page> 19 <lb/></page>

			<body> Finally, the achieved uncertainties of dL  x  /ds and L  y  are both lower than 2.5  for both <lb/>beams. <lb/> 8. Conclusions <lb/> TOTEM has proposed a novel approach to estimate the optics at LHC. The method, <lb/>based on the correlations of the transport matrix, consists of the determination of <lb/>the optical functions, which are strongly correlated to measurable combinations of the <lb/>transport matrix elements. <lb/>At low-β <lb/>  *  LHC optics, where machine imperfections are more significant, the <lb/>method allowed us to determine the real optics with a per mil level uncertainty, and <lb/>also permitted to assess the errors of the transport matrix errors from the tolerances <lb/>of various machine parameters. In case of high-β <lb/>  *  LHC optics, where the machine <lb/>imperfections have smaller effect on the optical functions, the method remains effective <lb/>and reduces the uncertainties to the desired per mil level. The method has been validated <lb/>with the Monte Carlo studies both for high-and low-β <lb/>  *  optics and was successfully used <lb/>in the TOTEM experiment to calibrate the optics of the LHC accelerator directly from <lb/>data in physics runs for precision TOTEM measurements of the total pp cross-section. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments <lb/> This work was supported by the institutions listed on the front page and partially <lb/>also by NSF (US), the Magnus Ehrnrooth foundation (Finland), the Waldemar von <lb/>Frenckell foundation (Finland), the Academy of Finland, the Finnish Academy of <lb/>Science and Letters (The Vilho, Yrjö and Kalle Väisälä Fund), the OTKA grant NK <lb/>101438 (Hungary) and the Ch. Simonyi Fund (Hungary). <lb/></div>

			<front> Individual members of the TOTEM Collaboration are also from: <lb/> a  INRNE-BAS, Institute for Nuclear Research and Nuclear Energy, Bulgarian <lb/>Academy of Sciences, Sofia, Bulgaria, <lb/> b  Department of Atomic Physics, Eötvös University, Budapest, Hungary, <lb/> c  Ioffe Physical -Technical Institute of Russian Academy of Sciences, St.Petersburg, <lb/>Russia, <lb/> d  Warsaw University of Technology, Warsaw, Poland, <lb/> e  Institute of Nuclear Physics, Polish Academy of Science, Cracow, Poland, <lb/> f  SLAC National Accelerator Laboratory, Stanford CA, USA, <lb/> g  Penn State University, Dept. of Physics, University Park, PA USA. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote"> LHC Optics Measurement with Proton Tracks by TOTEM <lb/></note>

			<page> 20 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] Antchev G et al. 2008 JINST 3 S08007 <lb/>[2] Evans L and Bryant P 2008 JINST 3 S08001 <lb/>[3] Anelli G et al. 2008 JINST 3 S08007 <lb/>[4] Antchev G et al. 2013 Int. J. Mod. Phys. A 28 1330046 <lb/>[5] Kašpar J 2011 PhD Thesis CERN-THESIS-2011-214 <lb/>[6] Burkhardt H and White S 2010  &quot; High-β <lb/>  *  Optics for the LHC &quot;  LHC Project Note 431 <lb/>[7] Niewiadomski H 2008 PhD Thesis CERN-THESIS-2008-080 <lb/>[8] Antchev G et al. 2011 Europhys. Lett. 95 41001 <lb/>[9] Antchev G et al. 2011 Europhys. Lett. 96 21002 <lb/>[10] Antchev G et al. 2013 Europhys. Lett. 101 21002 <lb/>[11] Antchev G et al. 2013 Europhys. Lett. 101 21004 <lb/>[12] Antchev G et al. 2013 Phys. Rev. Lett. 111 012001 <lb/>[13] Wiedemann H 2007 Particle Accelerator Physics, 3rd ed., ISBN: 978-3540490432, Springer <lb/>[14] MAD-X : An Upgrade from MAD8, CERN-AB-2003-024-ABP. <lb/>[15] The LHC Logging Service, CERN-AB-Note-2006-046. <lb/>[16] The LSA Database to Drive the Accelerator Settings, CERN-ATS-2009-100. <lb/>[17] FIDEL – The Field Description for the LHC, LHC-C-ES-0012 ver.2.0. <lb/>[18] WISE: A Simulation of the LHC Optics Including Magnet Geometrical Data, Proc. of EPAC08, <lb/>Genova, Italy. <lb/>[19] Berardi V et al. 2004 TOTEM Technical Design Report. 1st ed. CERN, Geneva, ISBN 9290832193. <lb/>[20] Tomás R et al. 2010 LHC Optics Model Measurements and Corrections, Proc. of IPAC10, Kyoto, <lb/>Japan </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
