<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Physics Letters B 740 (2015) 1-7 <lb/>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect <lb/>Physics Letters B <lb/>www.elsevier.com/locate/physletb <lb/>First determination of the CP content of D → π + π − π 0 <lb/>and D → K + K − π 0 <lb/>M. Nayak a , J. Libby a, * , S. Malde b , C. Thomas b , G. Wilkinson b,c , R.A. Briere d , P. Naik e , <lb/>T. Gershon f , G. Bonvicini g <lb/>a Indian Institute of Technology Madras, Chennai 600036, India <lb/>b University of Oxford, Denys Wilkinson Building, Keble Road, OX1 3RH, United Kingdom <lb/>c European Organisation for Nuclear Research (CERN), CH-1211, Geneva 23, Switzerland <lb/>d Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA 15213, USA <lb/>e University of Bristol, Bristol, BS8 1TL, United Kingdom <lb/>f University of Warwick, Coventry, CV4 7AL, United Kingdom <lb/>g Wayne State University, Detroit, MI 48202, USA <lb/>a r t i c l e i n f o <lb/>a b s t r a c t <lb/>Article history: <lb/>Received 15 October 2014 <lb/>Received in revised form 12 November 2014 <lb/>Accepted 13 November 2014 <lb/>Available online 18 November 2014 <lb/>Editor: L. Rolandi <lb/>Keywords: <lb/>Charm decay <lb/>Quantum correlations <lb/>CP violation <lb/>Quantum-correlated ψ(3770) → D D decays collected by the CLEO-c experiment are used to perform first <lb/>measurements of F + , the fractional CP-even content of the self-conjugate decays D → π + π − π 0 and <lb/>D → K + K − π 0 . Values of 0.968 ± 0.017 ± 0.006 and 0.731 ± 0.058 ± 0.021 are obtained for π + π − π 0 <lb/>and K + K − π 0 , respectively. It is demonstrated how modes of this sort can be cleanly included in <lb/>measurements of the unitarity triangle angle γ using B ∓ → D K ∓ decays. The high CP-even content <lb/>of D → π + π − π 0 , in particular, makes this a promising mode for improving the precision on γ . <lb/>© 2014 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V. This is an open access article under the CC BY license <lb/>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/). Funded by SCOAP 3 . <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>Improved knowledge of the unitarity triangle angle γ (also <lb/>denoted φ 3 ) = arg(−V ud V * <lb/>ub /V cd V * <lb/>cb ) is necessary for testing the <lb/>Standard Model description of CP violation. Sensitivity to γ can be <lb/>obtained by studying CP-violating observables in B ∓ → D K ∓ de-<lb/>cays, where D indicates a neutral charm meson reconstructed in a <lb/>final state common to both D 0 and D0 mesons. Examples include <lb/>CP-eigenstates [1], quasi-flavour specific states such as K ± π ∓ [2], <lb/>self-conjugate modes such as K 0 <lb/>S π + π − [3,4] and singly Cabibbo-<lb/>suppressed decays such as K 0 <lb/>S K ± π ∓ [5]. The current world average <lb/>precision on γ is significantly worse than that of the other an-<lb/>gles of the unitarity triangle [6]. Therefore, including additional <lb/>D-meson final states is desirable to reduce the statistical uncer-<lb/>tainty on γ at current and future facilities. <lb/>In the case that the D does not decay to a pure CP eigenstate, <lb/>information is required on the strong decay dynamics in order <lb/>to relate the CP-violating observables to γ . This information can <lb/>be obtained from studies of quantum-correlated D D mesons pro-<lb/>* Corresponding author. <lb/>E-mail address: libby@iitm.ac.in (J. Libby). <lb/>duced in e + e − collisions at an energy corresponding to the mass <lb/>of the ψ(3770) [3,7-9], and relevant measurements have been <lb/>performed for several decay channels exploiting data collected by <lb/>CLEO-c [10-15] and BESIII [16]. <lb/>The decay D → π + π − π 0 is a promising candidate to be added <lb/>to the suite of modes used in the γ measurement. Its Dalitz <lb/>plot has been studied by the CLEO and BaBar Collaborations us-<lb/>ing flavour-tagged D 0 decays and exhibits a strikingly symmetric <lb/>distribution that suggests the decay may be dominated by a single <lb/>CP eigenstate [17,18]. 1 An isospin analysis [19] of the amplitude <lb/>model for D 0 → π + π − π 0 presented in Ref. [18] concludes that <lb/>the final state is almost exclusively I = 0. Therefore, given that <lb/>the parity and G-parity of the three-pion final state is odd and <lb/>G = (−1) I C , the final state is expected to be C = −1 and CP = +1. <lb/>As its branching ratio of 1.43 ± 0.06% [6] is significantly larger <lb/>than those of the pure two-body CP-even modes, it has the po-<lb/>tential to contribute strongly in any analysis making use of such <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">1 Furthermore, the model-dependent analysis in Ref. [18] uses an amplitude <lb/>model derived from the D 0 sample to search for CP violation in B ± → D K ± de-<lb/>cays. This is a different analysis strategy to that made possible through the results <lb/>presented in this Letter. <lb/></note>

			<front>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.physletb.2014.11.022 <lb/>0370-2693/© 2014 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V. This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/). Funded by <lb/>SCOAP 3 . <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">M. Nayak et al. / Physics Letters B 740 (2015) 1-7 <lb/></note>

			<body>decays. The channel D → K + K − π 0 is a similar, but less abundant, <lb/>self-conjugate mode that has also attracted interest [20,21]. This <lb/>Letter presents the first analysis of these decays using quantum-<lb/>correlated D D decays, and measurements of their CP content, mak-<lb/>ing use of the CLEO-c ψ(3770) data set. These measurements allow <lb/>the inclusive decays to be included in future B ∓ → D K ∓ analyses <lb/>in a straightforward and model-independent manner, thus allow-<lb/>ing for an improved determination of the angle γ . Throughout the <lb/>effects of CP violation in charm mesons are neglected, which is a <lb/>good assumption given theoretical expectations and current exper-<lb/>imental limits [6,22]. <lb/>The remainder of the Letter is structured as follows. Section 2 <lb/>describes how quantum-correlated D decays are used to determine <lb/>the CP content. In addition, predictions for the CP content of the <lb/>state from existing amplitude models are presented. The data set <lb/>and event selection are described in Section 3. The results and the <lb/>determination of the systematic uncertainties are presented in Sec-<lb/>tion 4. In Section 5 the implications for the measurement of the <lb/>unitarity triangle angle γ are discussed. Section 6 gives the con-<lb/>clusions. <lb/>2. Measuring the CP content <lb/>Consider a ψ(3770) → D D analysis in which the signal de-<lb/>cay mode is D → h + h − π 0 . Let M + designate the number of <lb/>&quot;double-tagged&quot; candidates, after background subtraction, where <lb/>one D meson is reconstructed in the signal mode of interest, and <lb/>the other is reconstructed in a CP-odd eigenstate. The quantum-<lb/>numbers of the ψ(3770) resonance then require that the signal <lb/>mode is in a CP-even state, hence the + superscript. The observ-<lb/>able M − is defined in an analogous manner. Let S + (S − ) designate <lb/>the number of &quot;single-tagged&quot; CP-odd (CP-even) candidates in the <lb/>data sample, where a D meson is reconstructed decaying to a CP <lb/>eigenstate, with no requirement on the final state of the other D <lb/>meson in the event. The small effects of D 0 D0 mixing are elimi-<lb/>nated from the measurement by correcting the measured single-<lb/>tagged yields S ± <lb/>meas such that S ± = S ± <lb/>meas /(1 − η ± y D ), where η ± <lb/>is the CP eigenvalue of the mode, and y D ∼ 10 −2 is one of the <lb/>well-known D 0 D0 mixing parameters [23]. For a time-integrated <lb/>measurement at the ψ(3770) there are no effects on the double-<lb/>tagged yields at leading order in the mixing parameters. <lb/>On the assumption that for double-tagged candidates the re-<lb/>construction efficiencies of each D meson are independent, then <lb/>the quantity N + ≡ M + /S + has no dependence on the branching <lb/>fractions or reconstruction efficiencies of the CP-eigenstate modes, <lb/>and can be directly compared with the analogous quantity N − to <lb/>gain insight into the CP content of the signal mode. The CP fraction <lb/>is defined <lb/>F + ≡ <lb/>N + <lb/>N + + N − <lb/>(1) <lb/>and is 1 (0) for a signal mode that is fully CP-even (CP-odd). The <lb/>notation F + (π + π − π 0 ) and F + (K + K − π 0 ) is used in the discus-<lb/>sion when it is necessary to distinguish between the two final <lb/>states. <lb/>It is also instructive to interpret the observable F + making use <lb/>of the formalism developed in Ref. [8] for binned analyses of self-<lb/>conjugate three-body final states. Consider the situation where the <lb/>D 0 → h + h − π 0 Dalitz plot is divided into two bins by the line <lb/>m 2 (h + π 0 ) = m 2 (h − π 0 ). The bin for which m 2 (h + π 0 ) &gt; m 2 (h − π 0 ) <lb/>is labelled −1 and the opposite bin is labelled +1. The CP-tagged <lb/>populations of these bins, N ± <lb/>i , normalised by the corresponding <lb/>single CP-tag yields, is given by <lb/>N ± <lb/>1 = h D K 1 ± 2c 1 K 1 K −1 + K −1 , <lb/>N ± <lb/>−1 = h D K −1 ± 2c −1 K −1 K 1 + K 1 . <lb/>(2) <lb/>Here h D is a normalisation factor independent of bin number and <lb/>CP tag. The parameter K i is the flavour-tagged fraction, being the <lb/>proportion of decays to fall in bin i in the case that the mother <lb/>particle is known to be a D 0 meson, for example through tagging <lb/>the other D meson in the event with a semileptonic decay. The <lb/>parameter c i is the cosine of the strong-phase difference between <lb/>D 0 and D0 decays averaged in bin i and weighted by the absolute <lb/>decay rate (a precise definition may be found in Ref. [8]). By mak-<lb/>ing use of the relations N ± = i N ± <lb/>i , <lb/>i K i = 1 and c 1 = c −1 it <lb/>follows that <lb/>F + = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(1 + 2c 1 K 1 K −1 ). <lb/>(3) <lb/>Therefore the inclusive decay tends to a pure CP eigenstate in the <lb/>limit that the flavour-tagged Dalitz plot is symmetric, with K 1 = <lb/>K −1 = 1/2, and c 1 is −1 or 1. <lb/>Amplitude models of D 0 → π + π − π 0 and D 0 → K + K − π 0 <lb/>are available from studies of flavour-tagged D 0 decays performed <lb/>by the BaBar Collaboration [18,21]. These models, together with <lb/>Eq. (3), can be used to calculate predictions for the CP content for <lb/>each decay. Values of F + (π + π − π 0 ) = 0.92 and F + (K + K − π 0 ) = <lb/>0.64 are obtained. 2 The amplitude models are fitted to time-<lb/>integrated data and include the effects of D 0 D0 mixing. The bi-<lb/>ases in the predicted values of F + arising from mixing effects are <lb/>&lt;0.01. Other possible biases, associated with the uncertainties in <lb/>the fitted model components, are expected to be larger, but have <lb/>not been evaluated. <lb/>The CP content of the state D → h + h − π 0 also has conse-<lb/>quences for the number of self tags M self , which are events con-<lb/>taining two D → π + π − π 0 or two D → K + K − π 0 candidates. Us-<lb/>ing the formalism of Ref. [8] for self-tagged events, and once more <lb/>considering a Dalitz plot divided into two, the number of self-tag <lb/>candidates in bins i and j is given by <lb/>M self <lb/>ij = 0.5R K i K − j + K −i K j <lb/>− 2 K i K − j K −i K j (c i c j + s i s j ) . <lb/>(4) <lb/>Here R = N D D (B R h + h − π 0 ) 2 , where N D D is the number of D <lb/>D <lb/>pairs in the sample, B R h + h − π 0 is the branching fraction of D 0 → <lb/>h + h − π 0 and is the detection efficiency. The parameter s i is the <lb/>sine of the strong-phase difference between D 0 and D0 decays <lb/>averaged in bin i and weighted by the absolute decay rate. Em-<lb/>ploying the same relations as previously, together with s 1 = −s −1 <lb/>and M self = i, j M self <lb/>ij , it follows that <lb/>M self = R 1 − 4c 2 <lb/>1 K 1 K −1 <lb/>= 4R F + (1 − F + ), <lb/>(5) <lb/>where Eq. (3) has been used to express M self in terms of F + . Hence <lb/>the number of self tags vanishes in the case that the signal mode <lb/>is a CP eigenstate. <lb/>3. Data set and event selection <lb/>The data set analysed consists of e + e − collisions produced by <lb/>the Cornell Electron Storage Ring (CESR) at <lb/>√ <lb/>s = 3.77 GeV and <lb/>collected with the CLEO-c detector. The integrated luminosity of <lb/>the data set is 818 pb −1 . The CLEO-c detector is described in de-<lb/>tail elsewhere [24]. Simulated Monte Carlo (MC) samples of signal <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">2 The value of x 0 = 0.850 reported in Ref. [18] corresponds to a value of F + that <lb/>is very close to the model-derived result given in this Letter. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">M. Nayak et al. / Physics Letters B 740 (2015) 1-7 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1 <lb/>D final states reconstructed in this analysis. <lb/>Type <lb/>Final states <lb/>Signal <lb/>π + π − π 0 , K + K − π 0 <lb/>CP-even <lb/>K + K − , π + π − , K 0 <lb/>S π 0 π 0 , K 0 <lb/>L π 0 , K 0 <lb/>L ω <lb/>CP-odd <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S π 0 , K 0 <lb/>S ω, K 0 <lb/>S η, K 0 <lb/>S η <lb/>decays are used to estimate selection efficiencies. Possible back-<lb/>ground contributions are determined from a generic MC sample <lb/>corresponding to approximately ten times the integrated luminos-<lb/>ity of the data set. The EVTGEN generator [25] is used to simulate <lb/>the decays. The detector response is modelled using the GEANT <lb/>software package [26]. <lb/>Table 1 lists the reconstructed D 0 and D0 final states. The un-<lb/>stable final state particles are reconstructed in the following de-<lb/>cay modes: π 0 → γ γ , K 0 <lb/>S → π + π − , ω → π + π − π 0 , η → γ γ , <lb/>η → π + π − π 0 and η → η(γ γ )π + π − . The π 0 , K 0 <lb/>S , ω, η and η <lb/>reconstruction procedure is identical to that used in Ref. [14]. <lb/>Final states that do not contain a K 0 <lb/>L are fully reconstructed <lb/>via two kinematic variables: the beam-constrained candidate mass, <lb/>M bc ≡ s/4c 4 − p 2 <lb/>D /c 2 , where p D is the D-candidate momentum, <lb/>and E ≡ E D − <lb/>√ <lb/>s/2, where E D is the D-candidate energy. The <lb/>M bc and E distributions of correctly reconstructed D-meson can-<lb/>didates will peak at the nominal D 0 mass and zero, respectively. <lb/>Neither E nor M bc distributions exhibit any peaking structure for <lb/>combinatoric background. The double-tagged yield is determined <lb/>from counting events in signal and sideband regions of M bc after <lb/>placing requirements on <lb/>E. The yield determination procedure <lb/>is identical to that presented in Refs. [10,14] for all modes apart <lb/>from h + h − π 0 vs. h + h − π 0 , which is described separately later in <lb/>this section. <lb/>The selection procedures are almost identical to those pre-<lb/>sented in Refs. [10,14] apart from that for h + h − π 0 vs. h + h − . An <lb/>additional requirement is placed on the D 0 → h + h − candidates <lb/>such that events with the h ± compatible with the electron or <lb/>muon particle identification hypothesis are removed; this criterion <lb/>removes background from the single-tag sample arising from cos-<lb/>mic ray muons and radiative Bhabha events. These backgrounds <lb/>distort the combinatoric background shape of the single-tag M bc <lb/>distribution, such that it cannot be fit readily by an analytic func-<lb/>tion. (The single-tag yield determination is described later in this <lb/>section.) <lb/>The only final state not considered in Refs. [10,14] is h + h − π 0 , <lb/>for which the criterion −58.3 &lt; E &lt; 35.0 MeV is applied. This <lb/>E criterion corresponds to a range of approximately three times <lb/>the experimental resolution around zero. In addition, to suppress <lb/>background from D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S π 0 in the D 0 → π + π − π 0 selection, re-<lb/>quirements are placed on the vertex of the π + π − pair to be con-<lb/>sistent with originating from the e + e − collision point. Fig. 1 shows <lb/>the M bc distributions for CP-tagged signal candidates, summed <lb/>over all CP-even and CP-odd tags, respectively, where the CP-tag <lb/>final state does not contain a K 0 <lb/>L meson. <lb/>Many K 0 <lb/>L mesons produced do not deposit any reconstructible <lb/>signal in the detector. However, double-tag candidates can be fully <lb/>reconstructed using a missing-mass squared (M 2 <lb/>miss ) technique <lb/>[27] for tags containing a single K 0 <lb/>L meson. Yields are extracted <lb/>from the signal and sideband regions of the M 2 <lb/>miss distribution. <lb/>Fig. 2 shows the M 2 <lb/>miss distributions for candidates tagged with <lb/>either a K 0 <lb/>L π 0 or K 0 <lb/>L ω tag. <lb/>In the selection of π + π − π 0 vs. π + π − π 0 candidates an ad-<lb/>ditional K 0 <lb/>S veto is applied to remove D → K 0 <lb/>S (π + π − )π 0 decays <lb/>that are otherwise found to dominate the sample. Candidates are <lb/>rejected if they have a π + π − invariant mass within 30 MeV/c 2 <lb/>of the nominal K 0 <lb/>S mass. The selected sample of π + π − π 0 vs. <lb/>π + π − π 0 candidates contains a significant combinatoric back-<lb/>ground from continuum e + e − → u ū, d d events that hadronise <lb/>to six pions. Furthermore, this combinatoric background does not <lb/>follow a uniform distribution in M bc as in the other double-tag <lb/>modes. Therefore, an alternative strategy is used to determine the <lb/>signal yield. A maximum-likelihood fit to the distribution of the <lb/>average M bc of the two D → π + π − π 0 candidates is used to deter-<lb/>mine the signal yield. The probability density functions (PDFs) are <lb/>parametrised by a Crystal Ball function [28] and a threshold ARGUS <lb/>function [29] for the signal and combinatoric background compo-<lb/>nents, respectively. Apart from the signal yield all other parame-<lb/>ters of the signal PDF are fixed to those obtained from the signal <lb/>MC sample. All parameters for the background PDF are obtained <lb/>from the fit to data. The average M bc distribution for π + π − π 0 <lb/>vs. π + π − π 0 candidates is shown in Fig. 3(a), along with the re-<lb/>sult of the fit. No significant signal is observed. Even though the <lb/>combinatoric background in the sample of K + K − π 0 vs. K + K − π 0 <lb/>candidates is smaller, the same method is applied to determine <lb/>the signal yield as for π + π − π 0 vs. π + π − π 0 . The average M bc <lb/>distribution and fit result for K + K − π 0 vs. K + K − π 0 candidates is <lb/>shown in Fig. 3(b); again no significant signal is observed. <lb/>The peaking background estimates are determined from the <lb/>generic MC sample of D D events. For final states without a K 0 <lb/>L <lb/>the peaking backgrounds are found to be extremely small or negli-<lb/>gible. The peaking backgrounds are significant in the states tagged <lb/>by K 0 <lb/>L π 0 and K 0 <lb/>L ω as shown in Fig. 2. The dominant source of <lb/>peaking background is D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S X , K 0 <lb/>S → π 0 π 0 ( X = π 0 , ω) events <lb/>where the π 0 mesons from the K 0 <lb/>S decay are not reconstructed. <lb/>The measured event yields after background subtraction are <lb/>given in Table 2. No significant signal is seen in any of the modes <lb/>tagged by a CP-even eigenstate, whereas significant signals are <lb/>seen in most modes tagged by CP-odd eigenstates. <lb/>It is also necessary to know the single-tag yield for the <lb/>CP-eigenstates to normalise the double-tagged yields appropriately <lb/>to obtain a value of F + . The selection of single tags is only pos-<lb/>sible for modes without a K 0 <lb/>L in the final state. The selection <lb/>criteria are identical to those for the double-tag selection. The <lb/>signal yield is estimated using a maximum likelihood fit to the <lb/>M bc distribution where the signal is modelled by the sum of a <lb/>Gaussian and an asymmetric Gaussian and the combinatoric back-<lb/>ground is modelled by an ARGUS function. Apart from the signal <lb/>yield all other parameters of the signal PDF are fixed to those <lb/>obtained from the signal MC sample. All parameters for the back-<lb/>ground PDF are obtained from the fit to data. The signal yield <lb/>is estimated by integrating the best-fit PDF within the interval <lb/>1.86 &lt; M bc &lt; 1.87 GeV/c 2 . Peaking backgrounds are estimated <lb/>from the generic D D simulation. Significant contributions are only <lb/>found for D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S ω and D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S η (π + π − π 0 ) candidates, corre-<lb/>sponding to 1.9% and 3.8% of the signal, respectively; in both cases <lb/>the dominant sources of peaking background are states with in-<lb/>termediate K * , K 1 and K 2 resonances which lead to K 0 <lb/>S π + π − π 0 <lb/>in the final state. The background-subtracted single-tag yields are <lb/>given in Table 2. <lb/>4. Results, systematic uncertainties and consistency checks <lb/>The yields of double-tagged and single CP-tag candidates are <lb/>used to determine the quantities N + and N − , and from these the <lb/>CP fraction F + . The values for N + and N − are calculated from <lb/>the ensemble of CP-odd and CP-even tags, respectively, accounting <lb/>for statistical and systematic uncertainties, and allowing for the <lb/>correlations that exist between certain systematic components. <lb/>There is an uncertainty in the single-tag yields S ± <lb/>meas associ-<lb/>ated with the fit function used to model the M bc distribution <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">M. Nayak et al. / Physics Letters B 740 (2015) 1-7 <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 1. M bc distributions for D → π + π − π 0 candidates tagged by CP-even (a) and CP-odd (b) eigenstates; corresponding plots for D → K + K − π 0 for CP-even (c) and <lb/>CP-odd (d). Tags involving a K 0 <lb/>L are not included. The vertical dotted lines indicate the applied signal window. <lb/>Fig. 2. M 2 <lb/>miss distributions for D → π + π − π 0 (a) and D → K + K − π 0 candidates tagged by CP eigenstates that contain a K 0 <lb/>L . The shaded histogram indicates the peaking <lb/>background. The vertical dotted lines indicate the applied signal window. <lb/>of the signal. This shape of the distribution varies depending on <lb/>whether there are no electromagnetic neutral final-state particles <lb/>present (K + K − and π + π − ), whether the neutrals are relatively <lb/>hard (K 0 <lb/>S π 0 (γ γ ) and K 0 <lb/>S η(γ γ )) or soft (all other modes). Uncer-<lb/>tainties are assigned of 2.0%, 2.5% and 5.0%, respectively. These <lb/>assignments also adequately cover those uncertainties related to <lb/>the assumption of the double-tag efficiency factorising into the <lb/>product of the two single-tag efficiencies. S ± <lb/>meas is corrected for <lb/>the effects of D 0 D0 mixing using y D = 0.62 ± 0.08 [23]. <lb/>Tags involving a K 0 <lb/>L require special treatment as it is not pos-<lb/>sible to measure a single-tag yield for these modes. The expected <lb/>value for the tag K 0 <lb/>L π 0 without mixing effects, S − (K 0 <lb/>L π 0 ), is given <lb/>by 2N D D K 0 <lb/>L π 0 B h + h − π 0 . Here K 0 <lb/>L π 0 is an effective single tag effi-<lb/>ciency, taken to be equal to the ratio of the double-tagged effi-<lb/>ciency to the single-tagged signal efficiency, as determined from <lb/>simulation and B h + h − π 0 is the D → h + h − π 0 branching fraction <lb/>[6]. The number of D D pairs in the sample, N D D , can be measured <lb/>from the double-tagged yield of decays into Cabibbo-favoured fi-<lb/>nal states. It is found that S − (K 0 <lb/>L π 0 ) = 24 433 ± 3934, where the <lb/>assigned error reflects the uncertainties in the input factors and as-<lb/>sumptions of this calculation. A similar procedure for K 0 <lb/>L ω yields <lb/>S − (K 0 <lb/>L ω) = 8923 ± 4015. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">M. Nayak et al. / Physics Letters B 740 (2015) 1-7 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 3. Average M bc distributions (points with error bars) for (a) π + π − π 0 vs. π + π − π 0 and (b) K + K − π 0 vs. K + K − π 0 . Superimposed are the total (solid line), signal <lb/>(dashed line) and background (dotted line) fit results. The shaded histogram indicates the peaking background. <lb/>Table 2 <lb/>Background subtracted signal yields and statistical uncertainties for double tags and <lb/>the CP single-tag yields. <lb/>Tag <lb/>π + π − π 0 <lb/>K + K − π 0 <lb/>Single <lb/>π + π − π 0 <lb/>34.3 ± 20.0 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>K + K − π 0 <lb/>-<lb/>2 .7 ± 3.6 <lb/>-<lb/>K + K − <lb/>3.9 ± 5.5 <lb/>1 1 .3 ± 4.1 <lb/>11 970 ± 116 <lb/>π + π − <lb/>13.3 ± 6.6 <lb/>1 .7 ± 3.8 <lb/>5595 ± 109 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S π 0 π 0 <lb/>1.9 ± 3.4 <lb/>2 .8 ± 2.0 <lb/>7306 ± 125 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>L π 0 <lb/>14.6 ± 7.9 <lb/>1 0 .6 ± 4.0 <lb/>-<lb/>K 0 <lb/>L ω <lb/>−4.3 ± 4.0 <lb/>3 .5 ± 4.4 <lb/>-<lb/>K 0 <lb/>S π 0 <lb/>214.0 ± 15.0 <lb/>2 6 .0 ± 5.2 <lb/>2 0 0 6 9 ± 146 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S ω <lb/>95.5 ± 9.9 <lb/>1 1 .6 ± 3.4 <lb/>7960 ± 99 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S η(γ γ ) <lb/>33.0 ± 5.8 <lb/>3 .5 ± 2.4 <lb/>2903 ± 71 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S η(π + π − π 0 ) <lb/>8.8 ± 3.1 <lb/>1 .0 ± 1.0 <lb/>1161 ± 48 <lb/>K 0 <lb/>S η <lb/>17.6 ± 4.2 <lb/>3 .0 ± 1.7 <lb/>1405 ± 38 <lb/>Finally, there is a possible source of bias arising from non-<lb/>uniformities in the Dalitz acceptance. The efficiency of reconstruc-<lb/>tion at CLEO-c is rather flat across phase space, but residual varia-<lb/>tions are parameterised and used to weight the amplitude models <lb/>for the two signal modes, and the resulting effective values of F + <lb/>are then calculated. The potential bias is assessed to be 0.001 for <lb/>π + π − π 0 , and 0.010 for K + K − π 0 . The significant difference be-<lb/>tween the two values is attributed to the larger fraction of events <lb/>in the CP-odd Dalitz plot for D → K + K − π 0 , which will be dis-<lb/>tributed differently than those in the CP-even Dalitz plot. There-<lb/>fore, the measured value of F + is affected more significantly by <lb/>efficiency variations than for D → π + π − π 0 . <lb/>The measured values for N + and N − for the two signal modes <lb/>are displayed in Fig. 4. It can be seen that there is consistency <lb/>between the individual tags for each measurement. From these re-<lb/>sults it is determined that F + (π + π − π 0 ) = 0.968 ± 0.017 ± 0.006 <lb/>and F + (K + K − π 0 ) = 0.731 ± 0.058 ± 0.021, where the first uncer-<lb/>tainty is statistical and the second is systematic. These values are <lb/>slightly higher than, but compatible with, the model predictions <lb/>reported in Section 2. <lb/>The results for the number of self tags are not used in the de-<lb/>termination of the CP-even content because they provide much <lb/>weaker constraints than the CP-tags, and because the K 0 <lb/>S veto im-<lb/>posed on the invariant mass of π + π − pairs for the π + π − π 0 vs. <lb/>π + π − π 0 selection distorts the Dalitz space for this mode. Instead, <lb/>the self-tagged yields are employed as a cross-check. Making use <lb/>of Eq. (5) and taking the above values for the F + (π + π − π 0 ) and <lb/>F + (π + π − π 0 ) leads to an expectation of 2.6 ± 1.6 and 0.4 ± 0.1 <lb/>candidates for the number of D → π + π − π 0 and D → K + K − π 0 <lb/>self tags, respectively. These predictions are compatible with the <lb/>measured values reported in Table 2. <lb/>5. Implications for the measurement of γ <lb/>Sensitivity to the unitarity triangle angle γ is obtained by mea-<lb/>suring the relative rates of B ∓ → D(h + h − π 0 )K ∓ decays and re-<lb/>lated observables. Once more considering the Dalitz plot to be <lb/>divided into a pair of symmetric bins, as introduced in Section 2, <lb/>and making use of the relations of Ref. [8] and Eq. (3), it follows <lb/>that <lb/>Γ B ∓ → D h + h − π 0 K ∓ = h B 1 + r 2 <lb/>B 1 − 2c 1 y D K 1 K −1 <lb/>+ 2x ∓ 2c 1 K 1 K −1 − y D <lb/>= h B 1 + r 2 <lb/>B 1 − (2F + − 1) y D <lb/>+ 2x ∓ (2F + − 1) − y D . <lb/>(6) <lb/>Here h B is a normalisation factor, r B is the ratio of the mag-<lb/>nitudes of the B + → D 0 K + and B + → D0 K + amplitudes, δ B is <lb/>the strong-phase difference between these amplitudes and x ± = <lb/>r B cos(δ B ± γ ). This expression includes the effects of D 0 D0 oscil-<lb/>lations at leading order in the mixing parameters [30]. <lb/>These partial widths and those involving flavour-specific D me-<lb/>son decays can be used to construct the partial-widths ratio R F + <lb/>and CP-asymmetry A F + : <lb/>R F + ≡ <lb/>Γ (B − → D F + K − ) + Γ (B + → D F + K + ) <lb/>Γ (B − → D 0 K − ) + Γ (B + → D0 K + ) <lb/>, <lb/>(7) <lb/>A F + ≡ <lb/>Γ (B − → D F + K − ) − Γ (B + → D F + K + ) <lb/>Γ (B − → D F + K − ) + Γ (B + → D F + K + ) <lb/>, <lb/>(8) <lb/>where D F + indicates a D meson of CP-even content F + , estab-<lb/>lished through its decay into the final state h + h − π 0 . These ob-<lb/>servables are directly analogous to the usual so-called GLW [1] <lb/>observables R CP± and A CP± , where the D meson is reconstructed <lb/>in a pure CP eigenstate.</body>

			<note place="footnote">3 <lb/>In order to make explicit the relationship to the pure CP-eigen-<lb/>state case, the effects of mixing are now neglected. Then R F + and <lb/>3 Experimentally, and following the usual procedure established in GLW analyses <lb/>for measuring R CP± [31-34], it is more convenient to determine R F+ from the dou-<lb/>ble ratio R F+ <lb/>Γ (B − →D F+ K − )+Γ (B + →D F+ K + ) <lb/>Γ (B − →D F+ π − )+Γ (B + →D F+ π + ) / <lb/>Γ (B − →D K − π + K − )+Γ (B + →D K + π − K + ) <lb/>Γ (B − →D K − π + π − )+Γ (B + →D K + π − π + ) , <lb/>where in the second ratio the D mesons are reconstructed in the Cabibbo-favoured <lb/>decay. <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">M. Nayak et al. / Physics Letters B 740 (2015) 1-7 <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 4. D → π + π − π 0 results for N + (a) and N − (b). D → K + K − π 0 results for N + (c) and N − (d). In each plot the vertical (yellow in the web version) band indicates the <lb/>value obtained from the combination of all tags. <lb/>A F + are found to have the following dependence on the underlying <lb/>physics parameters: <lb/>R F + = 1 + r 2 <lb/>B + (2F + − 1) • 2r B cos δ B cos γ , <lb/>(9) <lb/>A F + = (2F + − 1) • 2r B sin δ B sin γ /R F + , <lb/>(10) <lb/>which reduces to the equivalent expressions for R CP± and A CP± <lb/>in the case F + is 1 or 0. Therefore inclusive final states such as <lb/>h + h − π 0 may be cleanly interpreted in terms of γ and the other <lb/>parameters of interest, provided that F + is known. At leading order <lb/>the only difference that the CP asymmetry A F + has with respect <lb/>to the pure CP-eigenstate case is a dilution factor of (2F + − 1), <lb/>which is 0.936 ± 0.036 for D → π + π − π 0 and 0.462 ± 0.124 for <lb/>D → K + K − π 0 . The measurement of F + presented here assumes <lb/>a uniform acceptance across the Dalitz plot; any non-uniformity is <lb/>considered as a potential source of systematic uncertainty. There-<lb/>fore, any non-uniformity of the acceptance over the Dalitz plot for <lb/>an experiment determining R F + and A F + must be corrected for, if <lb/>necessary, and a suitable systematic uncertainty assigned. <lb/>6. Conclusion <lb/>Data corresponding to an integrated luminosity of 818 pb −1 <lb/>collected by the CLEO-c experiment in e + e − collisions at the <lb/>ψ(3770) resonance have been analysed for the decays D → <lb/>π + π − π 0 and D → K + K − π 0 . Measurements of F + , the frac-<lb/>tional CP-even content of each decay have been performed. Values <lb/>of F + (π + π − π 0 ) = 0.968 ± 0.017 ± 0.006 and F + (K + K − π 0 ) = <lb/>0.731 ± 0.058 ± 0.021 are obtained, where the first uncertainty <lb/>is statistical, and the second is systematic. It has been demon-<lb/>strated that such self-conjugate inclusive channels can be cleanly <lb/>included in measurements of the unitarity-triangle angle γ , us-<lb/>ing B ∓ → D K ∓ decays. The high value of F + obtained for D → <lb/>π + π − π 0 makes this channel, in particular, a valuable addition to <lb/>the suite of D-decay modes used in the measurement of γ at LHCb <lb/>and Belle-II. Furthermore, given the large branching fraction, the <lb/>D → π + π − π 0 state can provide an additional source of CP-even <lb/>tags for quantum-correlated measurements at the ψ(3770). The <lb/>sample of D → π + π − π 0 tags would be approximately twice as <lb/>large as the D → h + h − sample. However, the formalism needs <lb/>to be adjusted to incorporate F + to account for the small CP-odd <lb/>component in the final state. Improved precision on the F + param-<lb/>eters can be obtained using the larger ψ(3770) data set available <lb/>at BESIII, and similar measurements can also be performed for <lb/>other self-conjugate final states. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>This analysis was performed using CLEO-c data, and as mem-<lb/>bers of the former CLEO Collaboration we thank it for this priv-<lb/>ilege. We thank Brian Meadows and Kalanand Mishra for useful <lb/>advice, and for helping us implement the BaBar amplitude models. <lb/>We have benefited from valuable discussions with Mateo Rama, <lb/>Anton Poluektov, Bhubanjyoti Bhattacharya and Jonathan Rosner. <lb/>We are grateful for support from the UK Science and Technology <lb/>Facilities Council and the UK-India Education and Research Initia-<lb/>tive. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">M. Nayak et al. / Physics Letters B 740 (2015) 1-7 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] M. Gronau, D. London, How to determine all the angles of the unitarity triangle <lb/>from B 0 <lb/>d → D K S and B 0 <lb/>s → Dφ, Phys. Lett. B 253 (1991) 483; <lb/>M. Gronau, D. Wyler, On determining a weak phase from CP asymmetries in <lb/>charged B decays, Phys. Lett. B 265 (1991) 172. <lb/>[2] D. Atwood, I. Dunietz, A. Soni, Enhanced CP violation with B → K D 0 ( D0 ) <lb/>modes and extraction of the Cabibbo-Kobayashi-Maskawa angle γ , Phys. Rev. <lb/>Lett. 78 (1997) 3257, arXiv:hep-ph/9612433; <lb/>D. Atwood, I. Dunietz, A. Soni, Improved methods for observing CP violation in <lb/>B + → K D and measuring the CKM phase γ , Phys. Rev. D 63 (2001) 036005, <lb/>arXiv:hep-ph/0008090. <lb/>[3] A. Giri, Y. Grossman, A. Soffer, J. Zupan, Determining γ using B ± → D K ± with <lb/>multibody D decays, Phys. Rev. D 68 (2003) 054018, arXiv:hep-ph/0303187. <lb/>[4] A. Bondar, in: Proceedings of BINP Special Analysis Meeting on Dalitz Analysis, <lb/>24-26 Sep. 2002, unpublished. <lb/>[5] Y. Grossman, Z. Ligeti, A. Soffer, Measuring γ in B ± → K ± (K K * ) D decays, <lb/>Phys. Rev. D 67 (2003) 071301, arXiv:hep-ph/0210433. <lb/>[6] K.A. Olive, et al., Particle Data Group, Review of particle physics, Chin. Phys. C <lb/>38 (2014) 090001. <lb/>[7] M. Gronau, Y. Grossman, J.L. Rosner, Measuring D 0 D0 mixing and relative <lb/>strong phases at a charm factory, Phys. Lett. B 508 (2001) 37, arXiv:hep-ph/ <lb/>0103110. <lb/>[8] A. Bondar, A. Poluektov, The use of quantum correlated D 0 decays for φ 3 mea-<lb/>surements, Eur. Phys. J. C 55 (2008) 51, arXiv:0801.0840 [hep-ex]; <lb/>A. Bondar, A. Poluektov, Feasibility study of model-independent approach to <lb/>φ 3 measurement using Dalitz plot analysis, Eur. Phys. J. C 47 (2006) 347, arXiv: <lb/>hep-ph/0510246. <lb/>[9] D. Atwood, A. Soni, Role of charm factory in extracting CKM phase information <lb/>via B → D K , Phys. Rev. D 68 (2003) 033003, arXiv:hep-ph/0304085. <lb/>[10] D.M. Asner, et al., CLEO Collaboration, Determination of the D 0 → K + π − rel-<lb/>ative strong phase using quantum-correlated measurements in e + e − → D 0 D0 <lb/>at CLEO, Phys. Rev. D 78 (2008) 012001, arXiv:0802.2268 [hep-ex]. <lb/>[11] D.M. Asner, et al., CLEO Collaboration, Updated measurement of the strong <lb/>phase in D 0 → K + π − decay using quantum correlations in e + e − → D 0 D0 at <lb/>CLEO, Phys. Rev. D 86 (2012) 112001, arXiv:1210.0939 [hep-ex]. <lb/>[12] J. Libby, et al., CLEO Collaboration, Model-independent determination of the <lb/>strong-phase difference between the decays D 0 and D0 → K 0 <lb/>S,L h + h − (h = <lb/>π , K ) and its impact on the measurement of the CKM angle γ , Phys. Rev. D <lb/>82 (2010) 112006, arXiv:1010.2817 [hep-ex]; <lb/>R.A. Briere, et al., CLEO Collaboration, First model-independent determination <lb/>of the relative strong-phase between D 0 and D0 → K 0 <lb/>S π + π − and its im-<lb/>pact on the CKM angle γ /φ 3 measurement, Phys. Rev. D 80 (2009) 032002, <lb/>arXiv:0903.1681 [hep-ex]. <lb/>[13] J. Libby, et al., New determination of the D 0 → K − π + π 0 and D 0 → <lb/>K − π + π + π − coherence factors and average strong-phase differences, Phys. <lb/>Lett. B 731 (2014) 197, arXiv:1401.1904 [hep-ex]. <lb/>[14] N. Lowrey, et al., CLEO Collaboration, Determination of the D 0 → K − π + π 0 and <lb/>D 0 → K − π + π + π − coherence factors and average strong-phase differences <lb/>using quantum-correlated measurements, Phys. Rev. D 80 (2009) 031105(R), <lb/>arXiv:0903.4853 [hep-ex]. <lb/>[15] J. Insler, et al., CLEO Collaboration, Studies of the decays of the D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K − π + <lb/>and D 0 → K 0 <lb/>S K + π − , Phys. Rev. D 85 (2012) 092016, arXiv:1203.3804 [hep-ex]. <lb/>[16] M. Ablikim, et al., BESIII Collaboration, Measurement of the D → K − π + <lb/>strong phase difference in ψ(3770) → D 0 D0 , Phys. Lett. B 734 (2014) 227, <lb/>arXiv:1404.4691 [hep-ex]. <lb/>[17] D. Cronin-Hennessey, et al., CLEO Collaboration, Searches for CP violation and <lb/>ππ S wave in the Dalitz-plot analysis of D 0 → π + π − π + , Phys. Rev. D 72 <lb/>(2005) 031102(R), arXiv:hep-ex/0503052 (Erratum); <lb/>D. Cronin-Hennessey, et al., CLEO Collaboration, Phys. Rev. D 75 (2007) 119904. <lb/>[18] B. Aubert, et al., BaBar Collaboration, Measurement of CP violation parameters <lb/>with a Dalitz plot analysis of B ± → D π + π − π 0 K ± , Phys. Rev. Lett. 99 (2007) <lb/>251801, arXiv:hep-ex/0703037. <lb/>[19] M. Gaspero, B. Meadows, K. Mishra, A. Soffer, Isospin anaysis of D 0 decay to <lb/>three pions, Phys. Rev. D 78 (2008) 014015, arXiv:0805.4050 [hep-ex]. <lb/>[20] C. Cawlfield, et al., CLEO Collaboration, Measurement of interfering K * + K − <lb/>and K * − K + amplitudes in the decay D 0 → K + K − π 0 , Phys. Rev. D 74 (2006) <lb/>031108(R), arXiv:hep-ex/0606045. <lb/>[21] B. Aubert, et al., BaBar Collaboration, Amplitude analysis of the decay D 0 → <lb/>K − K + π 0 , Phys. Rev. D 76 (2007) 011102, arXiv:0704.3593 [hep-ex]. <lb/>[22] R. Aaij, et al., LHCb Collaboration, A model-independent unbinned search for <lb/>CP violation in D 0 → π + π − π 0 decays, LHCb-PAPER-2014-054, Phys. Lett. B <lb/>(2014), in press. <lb/>[23] Y. Amhis, et al., HFAG, Averages of b-hadron, c-hadron, and τ -lepton prop-<lb/>erties as of early 2012, arXiv:1207.1158, online updates at http://www.slac. <lb/>stanford.edu/xorg/hfag, numbers taken from June 2014 charm physics update. <lb/>[24] Y. Kubota, et al., CLEO Collaboration, The CLEO II detector, Nucl. Instrum. Meth-<lb/>ods Phys. Res., Sect. A, Accel. Spectrom. Detect. Assoc. Equip. 320 (1992) 66; <lb/>D. Peterson, et al., The CLEO III drift chamber, Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. <lb/>Res., Sect. A, Accel. Spectrom. Detect. Assoc. Equip. 478 (2002) 142; <lb/>M. Artuso, et al., Construction, pattern recognition and performance of the <lb/>CLEO III LiF-TEA RICH detector, Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res., Sect. A, Ac-<lb/>cel. Spectrom. Detect. Assoc. Equip. 502 (2003) 91; <lb/>R.A. Briere, et al., CLEO-c/CESR-c Taskforces, CLEO-c Collaboration, CLEO-c and <lb/>CESR-c: a new frontier of weak and strong interactions, Cornell LEPP Report <lb/>CLNS Report No. 01/1742, 2001. <lb/>[25] D.J. Lange, The EvtGen particle decay simulation package, Nucl. Instrum. Meth-<lb/>ods Phys. Res., Sect. A, Accel. Spectrom. Detect. Assoc. Equip. 462 (2001) 152. <lb/>[26] R. Brun, et al., GEANT 3.21, CERN Program Library Long Writeup W5013, un-<lb/>published. <lb/>[27] Q. He, et al., CLEO Collaboration, Comparison of D → K 0 <lb/>S π and D → K 0 <lb/>L π de-<lb/>cay rates, Phys. Rev. Lett. 100 (2008) 091801, arXiv:0711.1463 [hep-ex]. <lb/>[28] T. Skwarnicki, A Study of the radiative cascade transitions between the Υ and <lb/>Υ resonances, Ph.D. Thesis, DESY F31-86-02, 1986, Appendix E. <lb/>[29] H. Albrecht, et al., ARGUS Collaboration, Search for hadronic b → u decays, <lb/>Phys. Lett. B 241 (1990) 278. <lb/>[30] M. Rama, Effect of D-D mixing in the extraction of γ with B − → D 0 K − and <lb/>B − → D 0 π − decays, Phys. Rev. D 89 (2014) 014021, arXiv:1307.4384 [hep-ex]. <lb/>[31] P. del Amo Sanchez, et al., BaBar Collaboration, Measurement of CP observables <lb/>in B ± → D CP K ± decays and constraints on the angle γ , Phys. Rev. D 82 (2010) <lb/>072004, arXiv:1007.0504 [hep-ex]. <lb/>[32] K. Abe, et al., Belle Collaboration, Study of B ± → D CP K ± and D * <lb/>CP K ± decays, <lb/>Phys. Rev. D 73 (2006) 051106, arXiv:hep-ex/0601032. <lb/>[33] T. Aaltonen, et al., CDF Collaboration, Measurements of branching fraction ra-<lb/>tios and CP asymmetries in B ± → D CP K ± decays in hadron collisions, Phys. <lb/>Rev. D 81 (2010) 031105, arXiv:0911.0425 [hep-ex]. <lb/>[34] R. Aaij, et al., LHCb Collaboration, Observation of CP violation in B + → D K + <lb/>decays, Phys. Lett. B 712 (2012) 203, arXiv:1203.3662 [hep-ex]; <lb/>R. Aaij, et al., LHCb Collaboration, Phys. Lett. B 713 (2012) 351 (Erratum). </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
