<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage>This is the accepted manuscript made available via CHORUS. The article has been <lb/>published as: <lb/>Study of CP Asymmetry in B^{0}-B[over ¯]^{0} Mixing <lb/>with Inclusive Dilepton Events <lb/>J. P. Lees et al. (BABAR Collaboration) <lb/>Phys. Rev. Lett. 114, 081801 -Published 25 February 2015 <lb/>DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevLett.114.081801 <lb/></titlePage>

			<front>BABAR-PUB-14/006 <lb/>SLAC-PUB-15983 <lb/>Study of CP asymmetry in B 0 -B 0 mixing with inclusive dilepton events <lb/>J. P. Lees, 1 V. Poireau, 1 V. Tisserand, 1 E. Grauges, 2 A. Palano ab , 3 G. Eigen, 4 B. Stugu, 4 D. N. Brown, 5 <lb/>L. T. Kerth, 5 Yu. G. Kolomensky, 5 M. J. Lee, 5 G. Lynch, 5 H. Koch, 6 T. Schroeder, 6 C. Hearty, 7 T. S. Mattison, 7 <lb/>J. A. McKenna, 7 R. Y. So, 7 A. Khan, 8 V. E. Blinov abc , 9 A. R. Buzykaev a , 9 V. P. Druzhinin ab , 9 V. B. Golubev ab , 9 <lb/>E. A. Kravchenko ab , 9 A. P. Onuchin abc , 9 S. I. Serednyakov ab , 9 Yu. I. Skovpen ab , 9 E. P. Solodov ab , 9 <lb/>K. Yu. Todyshev ab , 9 A. J. Lankford, 10 M. Mandelkern, 10 B. Dey, 11 J. W. Gary, 11 O. Long, 11 C. Campagnari, 12 <lb/>M. Franco Sevilla, 12 T. M. Hong, 12 D. Kovalskyi, 12 J. D. Richman, 12 C. A. West, 12 A. M. Eisner, 13 <lb/>W. S. Lockman, 13 W. Panduro Vazquez, 13 B. A. Schumm, 13 A. Seiden, 13 D. S. Chao, 14 C. H. Cheng, 14 <lb/>B. Echenard, 14 K. T. Flood, 14 D. G. Hitlin, 14 T. S. Miyashita, 14 P. Ongmongkolkul, 14 F. C. Porter, 14 <lb/>M. Röhrken, 14 R. Andreassen, 15 Z. Huard, 15 B. T. Meadows, 15 B. G. Pushpawela, 15 M. D. Sokoloff, 15 L. Sun, 15 <lb/>P. C. Bloom, 16 W. T. Ford, 16 A. Gaz, 16 J. G. Smith, 16 S. R. Wagner, 16 R. Ayad, 17, a W. H. Toki, 17 B. Spaan, 18 <lb/>D. Bernard, 19 M. Verderi, 19 S. Playfer, 20 D. Bettoni a , 21 C. Bozzi a , 21 R. Calabrese ab , 21 G. Cibinetto ab , 21 <lb/>E. Fioravanti ab , 21 I. Garzia ab , 21 E. Luppi ab , 21 L. Piemontese a , 21 V. Santoro a , 21 A. Calcaterra, 22 R. de Sangro, 22 <lb/>G. Finocchiaro, 22 S. Martellotti, 22 P. Patteri, 22 I. M. Peruzzi, 22, b M. Piccolo, 22 M. Rama, 22 A. Zallo, 22 <lb/>R. Contri ab , 23 M. Lo Vetere ab , 23 M. R. Monge ab , 23 S. Passaggio a , 23 C. Patrignani ab , 23 E. Robutti a , 23 B. Bhuyan, 24 <lb/>V. Prasad, 24 A. Adametz, 25 U. Uwer, 25 H. M. Lacker, 26 P. D. Dauncey, 27 U. Mallik, 28 C. Chen, 29 J. Cochran, 29 <lb/>S. Prell, 29 H. Ahmed, 30 A. V. Gritsan, 31 N. Arnaud, 32 M. Davier, 32 D. Derkach, 32 G. Grosdidier, 32 <lb/>F. Le Diberder, 32 A. M. Lutz, 32 B. Malaescu, 32, c P. Roudeau, 32 A. Stocchi, 32 G. Wormser, 32 D. J. Lange, 33 <lb/>D. M. Wright, 33 J. P. Coleman, 34 J. R. Fry, 34 E. Gabathuler, 34 D. E. Hutchcroft, 34 D. J. Payne, 34 <lb/>C. Touramanis, 34 A. J. Bevan, 35 F. Di Lodovico, 35 R. Sacco, 35 G. Cowan, 36 J. Bougher, 37 D. N. Brown, 37 <lb/>C. L. Davis, 37 A. G. Denig, 38 M. Fritsch, 38 W. Gradl, 38 K. Griessinger, 38 A. Hafner, 38 K. R. Schubert, 38 <lb/>R. J. Barlow, 39, d G. D. Lafferty, 39 R. Cenci, 40 B. Hamilton, 40 A. Jawahery, 40 D. A. Roberts, 40 R. Cowan, 41 <lb/>G. Sciolla, 41 R. Cheaib, 42 P. M. Patel, 42, e S. H. Robertson, 42 N. Neri a , 43 F. Palombo ab , 43 L. Cremaldi, 44 <lb/>R. Godang, 44, f P. Sonnek, 44 D. J. Summers, 44 M. Simard, 45 P. Taras, 45 G. De Nardo ab , 46 G. Onorato ab , 46 <lb/>C. Sciacca ab , 46 M. Martinelli, 47 G. Raven, 47 C. P. Jessop, 48 J. M. LoSecco, 48 K. Honscheid, 49 R. Kass, 49 <lb/>E. Feltresi ab , 50 M. Margoni ab , 50 M. Morandin a , 50 M. Posocco a , 50 M. Rotondo a , 50 G. Simi ab , 50 F. Simonetto ab , 50 <lb/>R. Stroili ab , 50 S. Akar, 51 E. Ben-Haim, 51 M. Bomben, 51 G. R. Bonneaud, 51 H. Briand, 51 G. Calderini, 51 <lb/>J. Chauveau, 51 Ph. Leruste, 51 G. Marchiori, 51 J. Ocariz, 51 M. Biasini ab , 52 E. Manoni a , 52 S. Pacetti ab , 52 <lb/>A. Rossi a , 52 C. Angelini ab , 53 G. Batignani ab , 53 S. Bettarini ab , 53 M. Carpinelli ab , 53, g G. Casarosa ab , 53 <lb/>A. Cervelli ab , 53 M. Chrzaszcz a , 53 F. Forti ab , 53 M. A. Giorgi ab , 53 A. Lusiani ac , 53 B. Oberhof ab , 53 E. Paoloni ab , 53 <lb/>A. Perez a , 53 G. Rizzo ab , 53 J. J. Walsh a , 53 D. Lopes Pegna, 54 J. Olsen, 54 A. J. S. Smith, 54 R. Faccini ab , 55 <lb/>F. Ferrarotto a , 55 F. Ferroni ab , 55 M. Gaspero ab , 55 L. Li Gioi a , 55 A. Pilloni ab , 55 G. Piredda a , 55 C. Bünger, 56 <lb/>S. Dittrich, 56 O. Grünberg, 56 M. Hess, 56 T. Leddig, 56 C. Voß, 56 R. Waldi, 56 T. Adye, 57 E. O. Olaiya, 57 <lb/>F. F. Wilson, 57 S. Emery, 58 G. Vasseur, 58 F. Anulli, 59, h D. Aston, 59 D. J. Bard, 59 C. Cartaro, 59 M. R. Convery, 59 <lb/>J. Dorfan, 59 G. P. Dubois-Felsmann, 59 W. Dunwoodie, 59 M. Ebert, 59 R. C. Field, 59 B. G. Fulsom, 59 <lb/>M. T. Graham, 59 C. Hast, 59 W. R. Innes, 59 P. Kim, 59 D. W. G. S. Leith, 59 P. Lewis, 59 D. Lindemann, 59 <lb/>S. Luitz, 59 V. Luth, 59 H. L. Lynch, 59 D. B. MacFarlane, 59 D. R. Muller, 59 H. Neal, 59 M. Perl, 59, e T. Pulliam, 59 <lb/>B. N. Ratcliff, 59 A. Roodman, 59 A. A. Salnikov, 59 R. H. Schindler, 59 A. Snyder, 59 D. Su, 59 M. K. Sullivan, 59 <lb/>J. Va&apos;vra, 59 W. J. Wisniewski, 59 H. W. Wulsin, 59 M. V. Purohit, 60 R. M. White, 60, i J. R. Wilson, 60 <lb/>A. Randle-Conde, 61 S. J. Sekula, 61 M. Bellis, 62 P. R. Burchat, 62 E. M. T. Puccio, 62 M. S. Alam, 63 J. A. Ernst, 63 <lb/>R. Gorodeisky, 64 N. Guttman, 64 D. R. Peimer, 64 A. Soffer, 64 S. M. Spanier, 65 J. L. Ritchie, 66 A. M. Ruland, 66 <lb/>R. F. Schwitters, 66 B. C. Wray, 66 J. M. Izen, 67 X. C. Lou, 67 F. Bianchi ab , 68 F. De Mori ab , 68 A. Filippi a , 68 <lb/>D. Gamba ab , 68 L. Lanceri ab , 69 L. Vitale ab , 69 F. Martinez-Vidal, 70 A. Oyanguren, 70 P. Villanueva-Perez, 70 <lb/>J. Albert, 71 Sw. Banerjee, 71 A. Beaulieu, 71 F. U. Bernlochner, 71 H. H. F. Choi, 71 G. J. King, 71 R. Kowalewski, 71 <lb/>M. J. Lewczuk, 71 T. Lueck, 71 I. M. Nugent, 71 J. M. Roney, 71 R. J. Sobie, 71 N. Tasneem, 71 T. J. Gershon, 72 <lb/>P. F. Harrison, 72 T. E. Latham, 72 H. R. Band, 73 S. Dasu, 73 Y. Pan, 73 R. Prepost, 73 and S. L. Wu 73 <lb/>(The BABAR Collaboration) <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">1 Laboratoire d&apos;Annecy-le-Vieux de Physique des Particules (LAPP), <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>Université de Savoie, CNRS/IN2P3, F-74941 Annecy-Le-Vieux, France <lb/>2 Universitat de Barcelona, Facultat de Fisica, Departament ECM, E-08028 Barcelona, Spain <lb/>3 INFN Sezione di Bari a ; Dipartimento di Fisica, Università di Bari b , I-70126 Bari, Italy <lb/>4 University of Bergen, Institute of Physics, N-5007 Bergen, Norway <lb/>5 Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory and University of California, Berkeley, California 94720, USA <lb/>6 Ruhr Universität Bochum, Institut für Experimentalphysik 1, D-44780 Bochum, Germany <lb/>7 University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada V6T 1Z1 <lb/>8 Brunel University, Uxbridge, Middlesex UB8 3PH, United Kingdom <lb/>9 Budker Institute of Nuclear Physics SB RAS, Novosibirsk 630090 a , <lb/>Novosibirsk State University, Novosibirsk 630090 b , <lb/>Novosibirsk State Technical University, Novosibirsk 630092 c , Russia <lb/>10 University of California at Irvine, Irvine, California 92697, USA <lb/>11 University of California at Riverside, Riverside, California 92521, USA <lb/>12 University of California at Santa Barbara, Santa Barbara, California 93106, USA <lb/>13 University of California at Santa Cruz, Institute for Particle Physics, Santa Cruz, California 95064, USA <lb/>14 California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, California 91125, USA <lb/>15 University of Cincinnati, Cincinnati, Ohio 45221, USA <lb/>16 University of Colorado, Boulder, Colorado 80309, USA <lb/>17 Colorado State University, Fort Collins, Colorado 80523, USA <lb/>18 Technische Universität Dortmund, Fakultät Physik, D-44221 Dortmund, Germany <lb/>19 Laboratoire Leprince-Ringuet, Ecole Polytechnique, CNRS/IN2P3, F-91128 Palaiseau, France <lb/>20 University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh EH9 3JZ, United Kingdom <lb/>21 INFN Sezione di Ferrara a ; Dipartimento di Fisica e Scienze della Terra, Università di Ferrara b , I-44122 Ferrara, Italy <lb/>22 INFN Laboratori Nazionali di Frascati, I-00044 Frascati, Italy <lb/>23 INFN Sezione di Genova a ; Dipartimento di Fisica, Università di Genova b , I-16146 Genova, Italy <lb/>24 Indian Institute of Technology Guwahati, Guwahati, Assam, 781 039, India <lb/>25 Universität Heidelberg, Physikalisches Institut, D-69120 Heidelberg, Germany <lb/>26 Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin, Institut für Physik, D-12489 Berlin, Germany <lb/>27 Imperial College London, London, SW7 2AZ, United Kingdom <lb/>28 University of Iowa, Iowa City, Iowa 52242, USA <lb/>29 Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa 50011-3160, USA <lb/>30 Physics Department, Jazan University, Jazan 22822, Kingdom of Saudia Arabia <lb/>31 Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Maryland 21218, USA <lb/>32 Laboratoire de l&apos;Accélérateur Linéaire, IN2P3/CNRS et Université Paris-Sud 11, <lb/>Centre Scientifique d&apos;Orsay, F-91898 Orsay Cedex, France <lb/>33 Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, Livermore, California 94550, USA <lb/>34 University of Liverpool, Liverpool L69 7ZE, United Kingdom <lb/>35 Queen Mary, University of London, London, E1 4NS, United Kingdom <lb/>36 University of London, Royal Holloway and Bedford New College, Egham, Surrey TW20 0EX, United Kingdom <lb/>37 University of Louisville, Louisville, Kentucky 40292, USA <lb/>38 Johannes Gutenberg-Universität Mainz, Institut für Kernphysik, D-55099 Mainz, Germany <lb/>39 University of Manchester, Manchester M13 9PL, United Kingdom <lb/>40 University of Maryland, College Park, Maryland 20742, USA <lb/>41 Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Laboratory for Nuclear Science, Cambridge, Massachusetts 02139, USA <lb/>42 McGill University, Montréal, Québec, Canada H3A 2T8 <lb/>43 INFN Sezione di Milano a ; Dipartimento di Fisica, Università di Milano b , I-20133 Milano, Italy <lb/>44 University of Mississippi, University, Mississippi 38677, USA <lb/>45 Université de Montréal, Physique des Particules, Montréal, Québec, Canada H3C 3J7 <lb/>46 INFN Sezione di Napoli a ; Dipartimento di Scienze Fisiche, <lb/>Università di Napoli Federico II b , I-80126 Napoli, Italy <lb/>47 NIKHEF, National Institute for Nuclear Physics and High Energy Physics, NL-1009 DB Amsterdam, The Netherlands <lb/>48 University of Notre Dame, Notre Dame, Indiana 46556, USA <lb/>49 Ohio State University, Columbus, Ohio 43210, USA <lb/>50 INFN Sezione di Padova a ; Dipartimento di Fisica, Università di Padova b , I-35131 Padova, Italy <lb/>51 Laboratoire de Physique Nucléaire et de Hautes Energies, <lb/>IN2P3/CNRS, Université Pierre et Marie Curie-Paris6, <lb/>Université Denis Diderot-Paris7, F-75252 Paris, France <lb/>52 INFN Sezione di Perugia a ; Dipartimento di Fisica, Università di Perugia b , I-06123 Perugia, Italy <lb/>53 INFN Sezione di Pisa a ; Dipartimento di Fisica, <lb/>Università di Pisa b ; Scuola Normale Superiore di Pisa c , I-56127 Pisa, Italy <lb/>54 Princeton University, Princeton, New Jersey 08544, USA <lb/>55 INFN Sezione di Roma a ; Dipartimento di Fisica, <lb/>Università di Roma La Sapienza b , I-00185 Roma, Italy <lb/>56 Universität Rostock, D-18051 Rostock, Germany <lb/></front>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<front>57 Rutherford Appleton Laboratory, Chilton, Didcot, Oxon, OX11 0QX, United Kingdom <lb/>58 CEA, Irfu, SPP, Centre de Saclay, F-91191 Gif-sur-Yvette, France <lb/>59 SLAC National Accelerator Laboratory, Stanford, California 94309 USA <lb/>60 University of South Carolina, Columbia, South Carolina 29208, USA <lb/>61 Southern Methodist University, Dallas, Texas 75275, USA <lb/>62 Stanford University, Stanford, California 94305-4060, USA <lb/>63 State University of New York, Albany, New York 12222, USA <lb/>64 Tel Aviv University, School of Physics and Astronomy, Tel Aviv, 69978, Israel <lb/>65 University of Tennessee, Knoxville, Tennessee 37996, USA <lb/>66 University of Texas at Austin, Austin, Texas 78712, USA <lb/>67 University of Texas at Dallas, Richardson, Texas 75083, USA <lb/>68 INFN Sezione di Torino a ; Dipartimento di Fisica, Università di Torino b , I-10125 Torino, Italy <lb/>69 INFN Sezione di Trieste a ; Dipartimento di Fisica, Università di Trieste b , I-34127 Trieste, Italy <lb/>70 IFIC, Universitat de Valencia-CSIC, E-46071 Valencia, Spain <lb/>71 University of Victoria, Victoria, British Columbia, Canada V8W 3P6 <lb/>72 Department of Physics, University of Warwick, Coventry CV4 7AL, United Kingdom <lb/>73 University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wisconsin 53706, USA <lb/>We present a measurement of the asymmetry ACP between same-sign inclusive dilepton samples <lb/>+ + and − − ( = e, µ) from semileptonic B decays in Υ (4S) → BB events, using the complete <lb/>data set recorded by the BABAR experiment near the Υ (4S) resonance, corresponding to 471 million <lb/>BB pairs. The asymmetry ACP allows comparison between the mixing probabilities P(B 0 → B 0 ) <lb/>and P(B 0 → B 0 ), and therefore probes CP and T violation. The result, ACP = (−3.9 ± 3.5(stat.) ± <lb/>1.9(syst.)) × 10 −3 , is consistent with the Standard Model expectation. <lb/>PACS numbers: 13.20.He, 11.30.Er <lb/></front>

			<body>A neutral B meson can transform to its antiparticle <lb/>through the weak interaction. A difference between the <lb/>probabilities P(B 0 → B 0 ) and P(B 0 → B 0 ) is allowed <lb/>by the Standard Model (SM), and is a signature of vi-<lb/>olations of both CP and T symmetries. This type of <lb/>CP violation, called CP violation in mixing, was first ob-<lb/>served in the neutral kaon system [1], but has not been <lb/>observed in the neutral B system, where the SM predicts <lb/>an asymmetry of the order of 10 −4 [2]. The current ex-<lb/>perimental average of CP asymmetry in mixing measured <lb/>in the B 0 system alone is A CP = (+2.3 ± 2.6) × 10 −3 [3], <lb/>dominated by the BABAR [4, 5], DØ [6], and Belle [7] <lb/>experiments. The most recent LHCb result A CP = <lb/>(−0.2 ± 1.9 ± 3.0) × 10 −3 [8] had not been included in <lb/>the aforementioned average. A recent measurement in a <lb/>mixture of B 0 and B 0 <lb/>s mesons by the DØ collaboration <lb/>deviates from the SM expectation by more than three <lb/>standard deviations [9]. Improving the experimental pre-<lb/>cision is crucial for understanding the source of this ap-<lb/>parent discrepancy. <lb/>The neutral B meson system can be described by an ef-<lb/>fective Hamiltonian H = M−iΓ/2 for the two states |B 0 <lb/>and |B 0 . Assuming CPT symmetry, the mass eigenstates <lb/>can be written as |B L/H = p|B 0 ± q|B 0 . If |q/p| = 1, <lb/>both CP and T symmetries are violated. Details of the <lb/>formalism can be found in Refs. [10, 11]. <lb/>The B 0 B 0 pair created in the Υ (4S) decay evolves <lb/>coherently until one B meson decays. In this analysis, <lb/>we use the charge of the lepton (electron or muon) in <lb/>semileptonic B decays to identify the flavor of the B me-<lb/>son at the time of its decay. If the second B meson has <lb/>oscillated to its antiparticle, it will produce a lepton that <lb/>has the same charge as the lepton from the first B de-<lb/>cay. The CP asymmetry A CP between P(B 0 → B 0 ) and <lb/>P(B 0 → B 0 ) can be measured by the charge asymmetry <lb/>of the same-sign dilepton event rate P ±± : <lb/>A CP = <lb/>P ++ − P −− <lb/>P ++ + P −− = <lb/>1 − |q/p| 4 <lb/>1 + |q/p| 4 . <lb/>(1) <lb/>This asymmetry is independent of the B decay time. <lb/>We present herein an updated measurement of A CP <lb/>using inclusive dilepton events collected by the BABAR <lb/>detector at the PEP-II asymmetric-energy e + e − storage <lb/>rings at SLAC National Accelerator Laboratory. The <lb/>data set consists of 471 × 10 6 BB pairs produced at the <lb/>Υ (4S) resonance peak (on-peak) and 44 fb −1 of data col-<lb/>lected at a center-of-mass (CM) energy 40 MeV below the <lb/>peak (off-peak) [12]. Monte Carlo (MC) simulated BB <lb/>events equivalent to 10 times the data set based on Evt-<lb/>Gen [13] and GEANT4 [14] with full detector response <lb/>and event reconstruction are used to test the analysis <lb/>procedure. The main changes with respect to the previ-<lb/>ous BABAR analysis [4] include doubling the data set, a <lb/>higher signal selection efficiency, improved particle iden-<lb/>tification algorithms, and a time-independent approach <lb/>instead of a time-dependent analysis. <lb/>The BABAR detector is described in detail else-<lb/>where [15]. Events are selected if the two highest-<lb/>momentum particles in the event are consistent with the <lb/>electron or muon hypotheses. All quantities are evaluated <lb/>in the CM frame unless stated otherwise. The higher-<lb/>momentum and lower-momentum lepton candidates are <lb/>labeled as 1 and 2, respectively. Four lepton combina-<lb/>tions are allowed: 1 2 = {ee, eµ, µe, µµ}, as are four <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>charge combinations, for a total of 16 subsamples. We <lb/>assume e-µ universality, i.e., equal A CP for all 1 2 combi-<lb/>nations. The time-integrated signal yields can be written <lb/>as [16] <lb/>N ±± <lb/>1 2 = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>N 0 <lb/>1 2 (1 ± a 1 ± a 2 ± A CP )χ 1 2 <lb/>d <lb/>, <lb/>(2) <lb/>N ±∓ <lb/>1 2 = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>N 0 <lb/>1 2 (1 ± a 1 ∓ a 2 )(1 − χ 1 2 <lb/>d <lb/>+ r B ), (3) <lb/>in the limit of A CP <lb/>1 and a j <lb/>1, where a j = <lb/>( + <lb/>j − − <lb/>j )/( + <lb/>j + − <lb/>j ) is the average charge asymmetry <lb/>of the detection efficiency for lepton j, r B is the B + /B 0 <lb/>event ratio, χ 1 2 <lb/>d <lb/>is the effective mixing probability of <lb/>neutral B mesons including efficiency corrections, and <lb/>N 0 <lb/>1 2 is the neutral B signal yield for the 1 2 flavor <lb/>combination. <lb/>A small fraction of the background comes from <lb/>e + e − → f f (γ) continuum events (f ∈ {u, d, s, c, e, µ, τ }). <lb/>This contribution is subtracted using the off-peak data <lb/>and the integrated luminosity ratio [12] between the on-<lb/>peak and off-peak data sets. The remaining background <lb/>comes from BB events, where at least one lepton candi-<lb/>date originates from B → X → Y cascade decays, or <lb/>from a hadron misidentified as a lepton. <lb/>Including the background, we expand Eqs.(2,3) to pa-<lb/>rameterize the total observed numbers of events as <lb/>M ±± <lb/>1 2 = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>N 0 <lb/>1 2 (1 + R ±± <lb/>1 2 ) 1 ± a 1 ± a 2 ± <lb/>1 + δ 1 2 R ±± <lb/>1 2 <lb/>1 + R ±± <lb/>1 2 <lb/>A CP χ 1 2 <lb/>d <lb/>, <lb/>(4) <lb/>M ±∓ <lb/>1 2 = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>N 0 <lb/>1 2 (1 + R ±∓ <lb/>1 2 )(1 ± a 1 ∓ a 2 )(1 − χ 1 2 <lb/>d <lb/>+ r B ), <lb/>(5) <lb/>where R ±± <lb/>1 2 and R ±∓ <lb/>1 2 are background-to-signal ratios un-<lb/>der the condition A CP = 0, and δ 1 2 is the probability <lb/>of a same-sign background event being consistent with <lb/>the flavors of the neutral B pairs at the time of their <lb/>decay after B 0 -B 0 mixing, i.e., + + ( − − ) for B 0 B 0 <lb/>(B 0 B 0 ), minus the probability of the opposite case, i.e., <lb/>+ + ( − − ) for B 0 B 0 (B 0 B 0 ). The detailed derivation <lb/>can be found in the supplemental material [16]. For <lb/>the opposite-sign events, signal is CP symmetric. The <lb/>background originating from B 0 B 0 (B 0 B 0 ) preferably <lb/>contributes to + − ( − + ) because a primary lepton <lb/>tends to have a higher momentum than a cascade lep-<lb/>ton. Therefore, the background yield is also a function <lb/>of A CP . However, the coefficient of A CP is less than 0.01 <lb/>for the final data sample, so it is ignored in the fits. <lb/>Events with ≥ 1 lepton (single-lepton sample) are used <lb/>to constrain the charge asymmetry of the detector effi-<lb/>ciency a ≡ (a 1 + a 2 )/2. The inclusive single-lepton <lb/>asymmetry a on in on-peak data can be expressed as [16] <lb/>a on = α + βχ d A CP + γa , <lb/>(6) <lb/>where parameters α, β, and γ are functions of the fol-<lb/>lowing quantities: the fractions and asymmetries of the <lb/>continuum background, misidentified leptons, and cas-<lb/>cade leptons; the B 0 /B + ratio; and w casc <lb/>B 0 the probability <lb/>of the cascade-lepton&apos;s charge incorrectly identifying the <lb/>B flavor at the time of the B decay. <lb/>We build a χ 2 fit using the 8+8+1 equations repre-<lb/>sented by Eqs. (4)-(6) to extract A CP . For the single-<lb/>lepton sample, we use only electrons since the purity is <lb/>much higher than that of muons. <lb/>The event selection requires ≥ 4 charged particle <lb/>tracks and the normalized second-order Fox-Wolfram mo-<lb/>ment [17] R 2 &lt; 0.6. The leptons should satisfy 0.6 GeV &lt; <lb/>p 2 ≤ p 1 &lt; 2.2 GeV. The polar angle θ of the electron <lb/>(muon) candidate in the laboratory frame is required to <lb/>satisfy −0.788 &lt; cos θ &lt; 0.961 (−0.755 &lt; cos θ &lt; 0.956). <lb/>The lepton is rejected if, when combined with another <lb/>lepton of opposite charge, the invariant mass is consis-<lb/>tent with that of a J/ψ or a ψ(2S) meson, or the kine-<lb/>matics is consistent with a photon conversion. The lepton <lb/>tracks must pass a set of quality requirements. For dilep-<lb/>ton events, the invariant mass of the lepton pair must be <lb/>greater than 150 MeV. The proper decay time difference <lb/>∆t of the two B mesons can be determined from the dis-<lb/>tance along the collision axis between the points of clos-<lb/>est approach of the lepton tracks to the beam spot, and <lb/>the boost factor ( 0.56) of the CM frame. We require <lb/>|∆t| &lt; 15 ps and its uncertainty σ ∆t &lt; 3 ps. <lb/>Electrons and muons are identified by two sepa-<lb/>rate multivariate algorithms that predominately use the <lb/>shower shape and energy deposition in the electromag-<lb/>netic calorimeter for electrons, and the track path length <lb/>and cluster shape in the instrumented flux return for <lb/>muons. The electron (muon) identification efficiency <lb/>is approximately 93% (40%-80% depending on momen-<lb/>tum). The probability of a hadron being identified as an <lb/>electron (muon) is &lt; 0.1% (∼ 1%). <lb/>To further suppress background, we use random for-<lb/>est multivariate classifiers [18]. Off-peak data are used <lb/>to represent continuum events, and simulated events are <lb/>used for signal and BB background. In the dilepton sam-<lb/>ple, we use six variables: p 1 , p 2 , thrust and spheric-<lb/>ity [19] of the rest of the event, the opening angle θ 12 of <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>the two tracks in the CM frame, and ∆t. Separate classi-<lb/>fiers are trained on the same-sign and opposite-sign sam-<lb/>ples. The ee, eµ, µe, and µµ samples are also trained sep-<lb/>arately. The dilepton signal probability distributions of <lb/>the classifiers are shown in Fig. 1. We select events with a <lb/>probability &gt; 0.7 to minimize the statistical uncertainty <lb/>based on fits to the BB MC sample. The final on-peak <lb/>data sample includes 2.5% continuum background for all <lb/>dilepton samples, and 35% (8%) BB background in the <lb/>same-sign (opposite-sign) sample. <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>(a) <lb/>0.5 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1.0 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>Ratio <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>Multivariate output <lb/>0 <lb/>40 <lb/>80 <lb/>120 <lb/>(b) <lb/>0.5 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1.0 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>Ratio <lb/>Entries / 0.005 ( <lb/>×10 3 <lb/>) <lb/>FIG. 1. (Color online) Signal probability distributions from <lb/>the dilepton multivariate algorithm for (a) the same-sign sam-<lb/>ple and (b) the opposite-sign sample; all lepton flavors are <lb/>combined. Points are continuum-subtracted data; shaded re-<lb/>gions from bottom to top are for signal, BB background with <lb/>≥ 1 misidentified lepton, and BB background with both real <lb/>leptons. Hatched region is rejected. Data/MC ratios are <lb/>shown in inset plots. Regions below 0.45 are not shown. <lb/>Approximately 0.1% (3%) of selected electrons <lb/>(muons) in dilepton samples are misidentified. According <lb/>to the simulation, nearly 98% of the misidentified elec-<lb/>trons come from pions and 87% (12%) of the misidenti-<lb/>fied muons come from pions (kaons). To correct for the <lb/>difference in the muon misidentification rates between <lb/>data and MC samples, we study the muon identification <lb/>efficiency in clean kaon and pion control samples from <lb/>the process D * + → D 0 (→ K − π + )π + (and the charge-<lb/>conjugate process). The ratios of the efficiencies between <lb/>data and MC samples are used to scale the misidentified <lb/>muon component in the MC sample. The corrections <lb/>to µ + (µ − ) is 0.792 ± 0.012 (0.797 ± 0.013). Since the <lb/>misidentification rate is very low for electrons, we use a <lb/>much larger pion control sample from K 0 <lb/>S → π + π − de-<lb/>cays. This control sample has a lower momentum spec-<lb/>trum and does not cover the region of p &gt; 2.5 GeV in the <lb/>laboratory frame, which accounts for less than 8% of the <lb/>misidentified leptons. The corrections to misidentified e + <lb/>(e − ) is 1.00±0.10 (0.56±0.10). The quoted uncertainties <lb/>are conservative estimates that result from mismatched <lb/>momentum spectra and from a small fraction of kaons <lb/>and protons among misidentified electrons. <lb/>For the single-lepton sample, the random forest algo-<lb/>rithm uses the number of tracks, the event thrust, R 2 , the <lb/>difference between the observed energy in the event and <lb/>the sum of the e + e − beam energies, the cosines of the an-<lb/>gles between the lepton and the axes of the thrust and the <lb/>sphericity of the rest of the event, and the zeroth-order <lb/>and second-order polynomial moments L 0 and L 2 , where <lb/>L n = <lb/>p i (cos θ i ) n , p i is the momentum of a particles <lb/>in the rest of the event and θ i is the angle between that <lb/>particle and the single-lepton candidate. We optimize <lb/>the selection requirement by minimizing the uncertainty <lb/>of the charge asymmetry after the continuum component <lb/>is subtracted from the on-peak data. A total of 8.5 × 10 7 <lb/>single electrons are selected in the on-peak data, of which <lb/>approximately 63% are from direct semileptonic B de-<lb/>cays. Finally, the single electrons are randomly sampled <lb/>so that the signal momentum spectrum matches that of <lb/>the dilepton events. <lb/>Raw asymmetries of the single electrons in the on-and <lb/>off-peak data are found to be a on = (4.16 ± 0.14) × 10 −3 <lb/>and a off = (11.1 ± 1.4) × 10 −3 . The larger asymme-<lb/>try in the off-peak data is primarily due to the radiative <lb/>Bhabha background and the larger detector acceptance <lb/>in the backward (positron-beam) direction. The contin-<lb/>uum fraction f cont = (10.32±0.02)% is obtained from the <lb/>ratio of the selected single electrons and the integrated <lb/>luminosities in off-and on-peak data [12]. The neutral <lb/>B fraction in the BB component f B 0 = (48.5 ± 0.6)% <lb/>is the Υ (4S) → B 0 B 0 branching fraction [20] corrected <lb/>for the selection efficiency. The cascade event frac-<lb/>tions f casc <lb/>B 0 <lb/>= 19.8% and f casc <lb/>B ± = 15.3% are obtained <lb/>from simulation, with negligible statistical uncertain-<lb/>ties. The fraction of the misidentified electron is 0.19%, <lb/>and the asymmetry is approximately 35%. The differ-<lb/>ence between direct and cascade electron asymmetries <lb/>is (−1.16 ± 0.25) × 10 −3 in MC. The probability w casc <lb/>B 0 <lb/>in MC is found to be (73.8 ± 0.1)%. Using these nu-<lb/>merical values, we determine the coefficients in Eq. (6): <lb/>a on − α = (2.60 ± 0.20) × 10 −3 , βχ d = 0.057 ± 0.001, and <lb/>γ = 0.8951 ± 0.0002. <lb/>The fitting procedure is tested on the BB MC sam-<lb/>ple; the result A MC <lb/>CP = (−1.00 ± 1.04) × 10 −3 is consistent <lb/>with the CP -symmetric simulation model. We artificially <lb/>create a non-zero A CP by reweighing mixed events in the <lb/>MC sample, and confirm that the fitting procedure tracks <lb/>the change in the A CP without bias. The continuum-<lb/>subtracted event yields are shown in Table I and are used <lb/>in Eqs. (4-5) for the fit. The result of the fit to data, after <lb/>correcting for the small bias (−1.0 × 10 −3 ) in the simula-<lb/>tion, is A CP = (−3.9±3.5)×10 −3 , a e1 = (3.4±0.6)×10 −3 , <lb/>a e2 = (3.0 ± 0.6) × 10 −3 , a µ1 = (−5.6 ± 1.1) × 10 −3 , and <lb/>a µ2 = (−6.5 ± 1.1) × 10 −3 . The remaining free parame-<lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE I. Continuum-subtracted number of events. <lb/>+ + <lb/>+ − <lb/>− + <lb/>− − <lb/>ee 82 303 ± 320 426 296 ± 783 425 309 ± 782 81 586 ± 323 <lb/>eµ 55 277 ± 263 384 552 ± 684 378 261 ± 660 55 878 ± 264 <lb/>µe 67 399 ± 290 467 591 ± 737 475 363 ± 744 67 152 ± 290 <lb/>µµ 47 384 ± 243 277 936 ± 619 278 691 ± 618 48 145 ± 247 <lb/>ters are N 0 <lb/>1 2 and χ 1 2 <lb/>d <lb/>. The χ 2 value is 6.2 for 4 degrees <lb/>of freedom. The correlations between A CP and a e1 , a e2 , <lb/>a µ1 , and a µ2 are −0.41, −0.47, −0.54, and −0.51, respec-<lb/>tively. Correlations among other parameters are negligi-<lb/>ble. Figure 2 shows the fit results for the six data-taking <lb/>periods and the four flavor subsamples. <lb/>1 2 3 4 5 6 <lb/>1-4 5-6 <lb/>ee eµ µe µµ <lb/>Subsample <lb/>40 <lb/>30 <lb/>20 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>A <lb/>CP (10 −3 <lb/>) <lb/>FIG. 2. (Color online) ACP of the six data-taking periods <lb/>(dots), the first four and the last two periods (squares), and <lb/>the four flavor subsamples (rhombuses). The horizontal band <lb/>is the ±1σ region of the final fit result. All error bars are <lb/>statistical only. <lb/>The systematic uncertainties are summarized in Ta-<lb/>ble II. The branching fractions in the B decay chain par-<lb/>tially determine the background-to-signal ratio. We cor-<lb/>rect the MC samples so that important branching frac-<lb/>tions are consistent with the world average [20]. These <lb/>branching fractions correspond to inclusive B semilep-<lb/>tonic decays, B → τ ν τ X, charm production (D 0 , D 0 , <lb/>D ± , D ± <lb/>s , Λ + <lb/>c , and Λ − <lb/>c ) from B decays, and inclusive <lb/>charm semileptonic decays. The corrections vary for <lb/>most decays between 0.57 and 1.32, depending on the <lb/>channel. We estimate the systematic uncertainty by <lb/>varying the corrections over their uncertainties, which <lb/>are dominated by the errors of the world averages. <lb/>The systematic uncertainties due to misidentified lep-<lb/>tons are estimated by varying the uncertainties of the <lb/>corrections to e + , e − , µ + , and µ − individually, and sep-<lb/>arately for the dilepton and single-electron samples. <lb/>In the single-electron MC sample, the charge asymme-<lb/>try of the electron in B 0 B 0 is slightly different from that <lb/>in B + B − by (0.46 ± 0.18) × 10 −3 . Since we cannot sep-<lb/>arate B + B − electrons from B 0 B 0 electrons in data, the <lb/>single-electron asymmetry measurement is the average <lb/>of the two asymmetries, which is half the difference away <lb/>from the B 0 B 0 electron charge asymmetry. The system-<lb/>atic uncertainty is determined by the change in A CP af-<lb/>ter shifting the asymmetry in the signal component of <lb/>the single-electron sample by half the charge asymmetry <lb/>difference . <lb/>The difference in charge asymmetry between the direct <lb/>and the cascade electrons is found to be a casc <lb/>e <lb/>− a dir <lb/>e <lb/>= <lb/>(−1.16 ± 0.25) × 10 −3 in the single-electron MC sam-<lb/>ple. The difference between the lower-momentum and <lb/>the higher-momentum electron asymmetries is negative. <lb/>This trend is consistent with the result of the fit to <lb/>the dilepton data: a e2 − a e1 = (−0.4 ± 0.7) × 10 −3 . <lb/>For muons, the corresponding values are a casc <lb/>µ <lb/>− a dir <lb/>µ = <lb/>(−0.47±0.28)×10 −3 and a µ2 −a µ1 = (−0.9±1.2)×10 −3 . <lb/>In each case, we set the cascade lepton charge asymmetry <lb/>to that of the direct lepton, and use the change in A CP <lb/>as a systematic uncertainty. <lb/>The background-to-signal ratios R ±± <lb/>1 2 and R ±∓ <lb/>1 2 (un-<lb/>der the condition A CP =0) in the dilepton sample are <lb/>determined from the MC sample. The correction for <lb/>the misidentified lepton background has been dealt with <lb/>above. The real lepton portion of the ratio is in prin-<lb/>ciple the same between + + and − − samples because <lb/>the particle identification efficiencies cancel between the <lb/>background and the signal. In the MC sample, they are <lb/>consistent within 1 σ. Varying R ++ <lb/>1 2 and R −− <lb/>1 2 or R +− <lb/>1 2 <lb/>and R −+ <lb/>1 2 simultaneously in the same direction results <lb/>in negligible changes in A CP . If they are varied indepen-<lb/>dently, the quadratic sum of the changes in A CP is larger. <lb/>We use the latter as a systematic uncertainty. <lb/>The random forest output distribution in the data <lb/>could be different from that in the MC sample. The <lb/>selection efficiency in the MC BB dilepton events is ap-<lb/>proximately 2% larger than that in the data. We move <lb/>the dilepton random forest selection for the MC sample, <lb/>while keeping data the same, so that the selected MC <lb/>events are reduced by up to 6%. We take the average <lb/>change in A CP as a systematic uncertainty. <lb/>Several other sources of systematic uncertainties are <lb/>studied and found to be negligible. These include the <lb/>overall dilepton signal fraction estimate, the kinematic <lb/>difference between on-peak and off-peak data due to dif-<lb/>ferent CM energies, the continuum component fraction, <lb/>the probability w casc <lb/>B 0 , the neutral-to-charged B ratio, the <lb/>same-sign background dilution factors δ 1 2 , and the over-<lb/>all cascade event fraction. <lb/>In conclusion, we measure the CP asymmetry A CP = <lb/>(−3.9 ± 3.5 ± 1.9) × 10 −3 in B 0 -B 0 mixing using inclu-<lb/>sive dilepton decays. This result is consistent with the <lb/>SM prediction and the world average [3]. This measure-<lb/>ment represents a significant improvement with respect <lb/>to our previous result [4] (superseded by this result), and <lb/>is among the most precise measurements [8, 20]. A com-<lb/>parison of experimental results and averages is shown in <lb/>Fig. 3. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">We are grateful for the excellent luminosity and ma-<lb/>chine conditions provided by our PEP-II colleagues, and <lb/>for the substantial dedicated effort from the computing <lb/>organizations that support BABAR. The collaborating <lb/></div>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE II. Summary of systematic uncertainties on ACP . <lb/>Source <lb/>(10 −3 ) <lb/>Generic MC bias correction <lb/>1.04 <lb/>MC branching fractions <lb/>0.43 <lb/>Misidentified lepton corrections in dilepton events 0.77 <lb/>Misidentified e correction in single electron events 0.65 <lb/>Neutral/charged B difference <lb/>0.74 <lb/>Direct-/cascade e asymmetry difference <lb/>0.44 <lb/>Direct-/cascade µ asymmetry difference <lb/>0.34 <lb/>Background-to-signal ratios <lb/>0.68 <lb/>Random forest cut efficiency <lb/>0.08 <lb/>Total <lb/>1.90 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>A CP (B 0 ) <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>A <lb/>CP (B 0 <lb/>s ) <lb/>B 0 <lb/>B 0 <lb/>s <lb/>DØ D <lb/>s µX <lb/>LHCb D <lb/>s µX <lb/>Belle <lb/>BABAR (old) <lb/>BABAR D * ν <lb/>DØ D ( * ) µX <lb/>D <lb/>Ø <lb/>µ <lb/>µ <lb/>HFAG Spring&apos;14 <lb/>SM <lb/>BABAR (2014) <lb/>LHCb D ( * ) µX (2014) <lb/>∆χ 2 =1 contours <lb/>FIG. 3. (Color online) Measurements of CP asymmetry in <lb/>neutral B mixing, including this measurement (red square), <lb/>recent LHCb result [8] (teal rhombus), Refs. [4-7] (B 0 ; green <lb/>triangles), Refs. [21, 22] (B 0 <lb/>s ; blue dots), and Ref. [9] (B 0 , B 0 <lb/>s <lb/>mixture; magenta contour). The vertical band is the aver-<lb/>age of Refs. [4-7] and several other older measurements (not <lb/>shown). The horizontal band is the average of Refs. [21, 22]. <lb/>The average &quot;HFAG Spring &apos;14&quot; [3] (excluding LHCb [8] and <lb/>this result) is also shown (orange contour). <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">institutions wish to thank SLAC for its support and <lb/>kind hospitality. This work is supported by DOE and <lb/>NSF (USA), NSERC (Canada), CEA and CNRS-IN2P3 <lb/>(France), BMBF and DFG (Germany), INFN (Italy), <lb/>FOM (The Netherlands), NFR (Norway), MES (Russia), <lb/>MINECO (Spain), STFC (United Kingdom), BSF (USA-<lb/>Israel). Individuals have received support from the Marie <lb/>Curie EIF (European Union) and the A. P. Sloan Foun-<lb/>dation (USA). <lb/></div>

			<front>a at: University of Tabuk, Tabuk 71491, Saudi Arabia <lb/>b Also at: Università di Perugia, Dipartimento di Fisica, <lb/>I-06123 Perugia, Italy <lb/>c Now at: Laboratoire de Physique Nucléaire et de Hautes <lb/>Energies, IN2P3/CNRS, F-75252 Paris, France <lb/>d Now at: University of Huddersfield, Huddersfield HD1 <lb/>3DH, UK <lb/>e Deceased <lb/>f Now at: University of South Alabama, Mobile, Alabama <lb/>36688, USA <lb/>g Also at: Università di Sassari, I-07100 Sassari, Italy <lb/>h Also at: INFN Sezione di Roma, I-00185 Roma, Italy <lb/>i Now at: Universidad Técnica Federico Santa Maria, <lb/>2390123 Valparaiso, Chile <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>[1] J. Christenson, J. Cronin, V. Fitch, and R. Turlay, Phys. <lb/>Rev. Lett. 13, 138 (1964); D. E. Dorfan et al., ibid. 19, <lb/>987 (1967); S. Bennett et al., ibid. 19, 993 (1967). <lb/>[2] A. Lenz et al., Phys. Rev. D 83, 036004 (2011), <lb/>arXiv:1008.1593 [hep-ph]; A. Lenz and U. Nierste, <lb/>(2011), arXiv:1102.4274 [hep-ph]. <lb/>[3] Y. Amhis et al. (Heavy Flavor Averaging Group), <lb/>(2012), arXiv:1207.1158 [hep-ex] and online update <lb/>http://www.slac.stanford.edu/xorg/hfag/osc/spring 2014/. <lb/>[4] B. Aubert et al. (BABAR Collaboration), Phys. Rev. Lett. <lb/>96, 251802 (2006), arXiv:hep-ex/0603053 [hep-ex]. <lb/>[5] J. Lees et al. (BABAR Collaboration), Phys. Rev. Lett. <lb/>111, 101802 (2013), arXiv:1305.1575 [hep-ex]. <lb/>[6] V. M. Abazov et al. (DØ Collaboration), Phys.Rev. D <lb/>86, 072009 (2012), arXiv:1208.5813 [hep-ex]. <lb/>[7] E. Nakano et al. (Belle Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D 73, <lb/>112002 (2006), arXiv:hep-ex/0505017 [hep-ex]. <lb/>[8] R. Aaij et al. (LHCb collaboration), <lb/>(2014), <lb/>arXiv:1409.8586 [hep-ex]. <lb/>[9] V. M. Abazov et al. (DØ Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D <lb/>89, 012002 (2014), arXiv:1310.0447 [hep-ex]. <lb/>[10] V. A. Kostelecky, Phys. Rev. D 64, 076001 (2001), <lb/>arXiv:hep-ph/0104120 [hep-ph]. <lb/>[11] B. Aubert et al. (BABAR Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D <lb/>70, 012007 (2004), arXiv:hep-ex/0403002 [hep-ex]. <lb/>[12] J. Lees et al. (BABAR Collaboration), Nucl. Instrum. <lb/>Meth. A 726, 203 (2013), arXiv:1301.2703 [hep-ex]. <lb/>[13] D. Lange, Nucl. Instrum. Meth. A 462, 152 (2001). <lb/>[14] S. Agostinelli et al. (GEANT4), Nucl. Instrum. Meth. A <lb/>506, 250 (2003). <lb/>[15] B. Aubert et al. (BABAR Collaboration), Nucl. Instrum. <lb/>Meth. A 479, 1 (2002), arXiv:hep-ex/0105044 [hep-ex]; <lb/>729, 615 (2013), arXiv:1305.3560 [physics.ins-det]. <lb/>[16] See Supplemental Material at [URL will be inserted by <lb/>publisher] for the detailed derivation. <lb/>[17] G. C. Fox and S. Wolfram, Phys. Rev. Lett. 41, 1581 <lb/>(1978). <lb/>[18] L. Breiman, Machine Learning 45, 5 (2001). <lb/>[19] See Ch.4 of D. Boutigny et al. (BABAR Collaboration), <lb/>The BABAR Physics Book, edited by P. F. Harrison and <lb/>H. R. Quinn, SLAC-R-504 (1998). <lb/>[20] J. Beringer et al. (Particle Data Group), Phys. Rev. D <lb/>86, 010001 (2012). <lb/>[21] V. Abazov et al. (DØ Collaboration), Phys. Rev. Lett. <lb/>110, 011801 (2013), arXiv:1207.1769 [hep-ex]. <lb/>[22] R. Aaij et al. (LHCb collaboration), Phys. Lett. B 728, <lb/>607 (2014), arXiv:1308.1048 [hep-ex]. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
