<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>BioMed Central <lb/>Page 1 of 9 <lb/>(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/>Current Controlled Trials in <lb/>Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/>Open Access <lb/>Current Controlled Trials in Cardiovascular Medicine <lb/>2002, <lb/>3 <lb/>x <lb/>Research article <lb/>Validation of Heart Failure Events in the Antihypertensive and Lipid <lb/>Lowering Treatment to Prevent Heart Attack Trial (ALLHAT) <lb/>Participants Assigned to Doxazosin and Chlorthalidone <lb/>Linda B Piller* 1 , Barry R Davis 1 , Jeffrey A Cutler 2 , William C Cushman 3 , <lb/>Jackson T Wright Jr 4 , Jeff D Williamson 5 , Frans HH Leenen 6 , <lb/>Paula T Einhorn 2 , Otelio S Randall 7 , John S Golden 8 and L Julian Haywood 9 <lb/>for the ALLHAT Collaborative Research Group 10 <lb/>Address: 1 The University of Texas School of Public Health, Houston, TX, USA, 2 National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, Bethesda, MD, USA, <lb/>3 Memphis Veterans Affairs Medical Center, Memphis, TN, USA, 4 Case Western Reserve University School of Medicine, Cleveland, OH, USA, 5 Wake <lb/>Forest University, Winston-Salem, NC, USA, 6 University of Ottawa Heart Institute, Ottawa, ON, Canada, 7 Howard University Medical School, <lb/>Washington, DC, USA, 8 Kaiser Permanente, Mid-Atlantic States, Washington, DC, USA, 9 Keck School of Medicine, University of Southern <lb/>California, Los Angeles, CA, USA and 10 For a complete list of members of the ALLHAT Collaborative Research Group see JAMA 2000; 283:1973-<lb/>1975 <lb/>E-mail: Linda B Piller* -lpiller@sph.uth.tmc.edu; Barry R Davis -bdavis@sph.uth.tmc.edu; Jeffrey A Cutler -CUTLERJ@NHLBI.NIH.GOV; <lb/>William C Cushman -WILLIAM.CUSHMAN@MED.VA.GOV; Jackson T Wright -JXW20@PO.CWRU.EDU; <lb/>Jeff D Williamson -JWILLIAM@WFUBMC.EDU; Frans HH Leenen -fleenen@ottawaheart.ca; Paula T Einhorn -einhornp@nhlbi.nih.gov; <lb/>Otelio S Randall -osrandall@howard.edu; John S Golden -John.Golden@kp.org; L Julian Haywood -JHAYWOOD@HSC.USC.EDU; <lb/>the ALLHAT Collaborative Research Group -bdavis@sph.uth.tmc.edu <lb/>*Corresponding author <lb/>Keywords: heart failure, alpha-blocker, diuretic, clinical trial <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Background: The Antihypertensive and Lipid Lowering Treatment to Prevent Heart Attack Trial <lb/>(ALLHAT) is a randomized, double-blind, active-controlled trial designed to compare the rate of <lb/>coronary heart disease events in high-risk hypertensive participants initially randomized to a <lb/>diuretic (chlorthalidone) versus each of three alternative antihypertensive drugs: alpha-adrenergic <lb/>blocker (doxazosin), ACE-inhibitor (lisinopril), and calcium-channel blocker (amlodipine). <lb/>Combined cardiovascular disease risk was significantly increased in the doxazosin arm compared <lb/>to the chlorthalidone arm (RR 1.25; 95% CI, 1.17-1.33; P &lt; .001), with a doubling of heart failure <lb/>(fatal, hospitalized, or non-hospitalized but treated) (RR 2.04; 95% CI, 1.79-2.32; P &lt; .001). <lb/>Questions about heart failure diagnostic criteria led to steps to validate these events further. <lb/>Methods and Results: Baseline characteristics (age, race, sex, blood pressure) did not differ <lb/>significantly between treatment groups (P &lt; .05) for participants with heart failure events. Post-<lb/>event pharmacologic management was similar in both groups and generally conformed to accepted <lb/>heart failure therapy. Central review of a small sample of cases showed high adherence to ALLHAT <lb/>heart failure criteria. Of 105 participants with quantitative ejection fraction measurements <lb/>provided, (67% by echocardiogram, 31% by catheterization), 29/46 (63%) from the chlorthalidone <lb/>group and 41/59 (70%) from the doxazosin group were at or below 40%. Two-year heart failure <lb/>case-fatalities (22% and 19% in the doxazosin and chlorthalidone groups, respectively) were as <lb/>expected and did not differ significantly (RR 0.96; 95% CI, 0.67-1.38; P = 0.83). <lb/>Published: 14 November 2002 <lb/>Current Controlled Trials in Cardiovascular Medicine 2002, 3:10 <lb/>Received: 23 October 2002 <lb/>Accepted: 14 November 2002 <lb/>This article is available from: http://cvm.controlled-trials.com/content/3/1/10 <lb/>© 2002 Piller et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This article is published in Open Access: verbatim copying and redistribution of this article are permitted <lb/>in all media for any purpose, provided this notice is preserved along with the article&apos;s original URL. <lb/>Current Controlled Trials in Cardiovascular Medicine 2002, 3 <lb/>http://cvm.controlled-trials.com/content/3/1/10 <lb/></front>

			<page>Page 2 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>

			<front>Conclusion: Results of the validation process supported findings of increased heart failure in the <lb/>ALLHAT doxazosin treatment arm compared to the chlorthalidone treatment arm. <lb/></front>

			<body>The Antihypertensive and Lipid Lowering Treatment to <lb/>Prevent Heart Attack Trial (ALLHAT) is a randomized, <lb/>two-component clinical trial sponsored by the National <lb/>Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI). A double-<lb/>blind, active-controlled hypertension component is de-<lb/>signed to compare the rate of fatal coronary heart disease <lb/>(CHD) or nonfatal myocardial infarction (MI) (the pri-<lb/>mary endpoint) in high-risk hypertensive participants, <lb/>aged 55 years or older, between those randomized to <lb/>treatment initiated with a diuretic (chlorthalidone) and <lb/>treatment initiated with each of three alternative antihy-<lb/>pertensive drugs: a calcium-channel blocker (am-<lb/>lodipine), an angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE)-<lb/>inhibitor (lisinopril), or an alpha-adrenergic blocker <lb/>(doxazosin). An open-label lipid-lowering component is <lb/>designed to determine if lowering LDL cholesterol with <lb/>pravastatin compared to &quot;usual care&quot; reduces all-cause <lb/>mortality in a subset of moderately hypercholesterolemic <lb/>patients. Randomization to the hypertension component <lb/>began in February, 1994, and continued through January, <lb/>1998, with 42,418 participants recruited at 623 clinical <lb/>centers in the United States, Canada, Puerto Rico and the <lb/>US Virgin Islands. Randomization of 10,355 participants <lb/>into the lipid trial ended May 31, 1998. Follow-up on all <lb/>participants continued through March, 2002 [1]. <lb/>Following independent reviews by the Data and Safety <lb/>Monitoring Board (DSMB) on January 6, 2000, and by an <lb/>Ad Hoc Committee on January 21, 2000, the Director of <lb/>the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute accepted a <lb/>recommendation to discontinue the doxazosin treatment <lb/>arm of the antihypertensive trial. This recommendation <lb/>was based on the low probability of doxazosin showing <lb/>benefit over chlorthalidone for the primary endpoint, as <lb/>well as the significantly increased occurrence of the sec-<lb/>ondary endpoint, combined cardiovascular disease <lb/>(CVD) (encompassing CHD deaths, nonfatal MI, stroke, <lb/>coronary revascularization procedures [coronary artery <lb/>bypass graft or CABG, percutaneous transluminal coro-<lb/>nary angioplasty or PTCA/stent], angina [hospitalized or <lb/>treated as an outpatient], heart failure [HF/treated in the <lb/>hospital or as an outpatient], and peripheral arterial dis-<lb/>ease [in-hospital or outpatient revascularization]) in the <lb/>doxazosin arm (RR 1.25; 95% CI, 1.17-1.33; P &lt; .001), <lb/>with a doubling of risk of HF (fatal, hospitalized and treat-<lb/>ed but nonhospitalized) (RR 2.04; 95% CI, 1.79-2.32; P <lb/>&lt; .001). When only fatal and hospitalized HF were ana-<lb/>lyzed, the large difference remained (RR 1.83; 95% CI, <lb/>1.58-2.13;P &lt; .001). The findings and operational aspects <lb/>of stopping the doxazosin arm of the study have been pre-<lb/>viously described [2-4]. <lb/>The observed increase in HF in the doxazosin group as <lb/>compared to the chlorthalidone group led to several addi-<lb/>tional analyses aimed toward validation of the diagnoses, <lb/>with a focus on hospitalized and fatal HF. The purposes of <lb/>these analyses were: 1) to evaluate the reality of HF cases, <lb/>i.e. whether diagnosis, management, and clinical course <lb/>were what might be expected, and 2) to compare these <lb/>features between the two treatment groups. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Study Design <lb/>The rationale and design of ALLHAT are described in de-<lb/>tail elsewhere [1]. Briefly, those eligible for randomiza-<lb/>tion had systolic blood pressure (SBP) of at least 140 mm <lb/>Hg and/or diastolic blood pressure of at least 90 mm Hg, <lb/>or took medication for hypertension, and had at least one <lb/>other risk factor for CHD events. Risk factors included pre-<lb/>vious MI or stroke, left ventricular hypertrophy by electro-<lb/>cardiogram or echocardiogram, history of type 2 diabetes, <lb/>current cigarette smoking, and low high-density lipopro-<lb/>tein (HDL) level. <lb/>The primary endpoint of the blood pressure (BP) trial is <lb/>the composite of nonfatal MI and fatal CHD. The four <lb/>protocol-defined secondary clinical outcomes are all-<lb/>cause mortality, combined CHD (including CHD death, <lb/>nonfatal MI, coronary revascularization procedures and <lb/>hospitalized angina), stroke, and combined CVD (includ-<lb/>ing CHD death, nonfatal MI, stroke, coronary revasculari-<lb/>zation procedures, angina treated in the hospital or as an <lb/>outpatient, lower extremity peripheral arterial disease <lb/>treated in the hospital or with outpatient revasculariza-<lb/>tion, and HF, fatal or treated in the hospital or as an out-<lb/>patient). <lb/>The validation of HF diagnosis entailed answering several <lb/>questions: <lb/>1. Did HF cases meet ALLHAT diagnostic criteria? <lb/>2. Were baseline characteristics and medical management <lb/>for HF cases as expected and similar across the drug <lb/>groups? <lb/>3. Were prevalence and severity of systolic dysfunction as <lb/>expected and similar across drug groups? <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Current Controlled Trials in Cardiovascular Medicine 2002, 3 <lb/>http://cvm.controlled-trials.com/content/3/1/10 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 3 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>

			<body>4. Were case-fatality rates as expected and similar across <lb/>drug groups? <lb/>Unless otherwise specified, all data for these analyses were <lb/>collected as of December, 1999. <lb/>Heart Failure Diagnosis <lb/>At each follow-up clinic visit the occurrence of study clin-<lb/>ical events was assessed, and, if identified by the clinical <lb/>investigator, reported on an endpoint form. For each <lb/>event involving hospitalization, a hospital discharge sum-<lb/>mary or expiration summary was to be submitted, and for <lb/>each death a death certificate was required. Endpoint <lb/>forms and supporting documentation were reviewed at <lb/>the ALLHAT Clinical Trials Center (CTC) for accuracy and <lb/>appropriateness. When a discrepancy or ambiguity was <lb/>found, the CTC sent a written query to the Principal Inves-<lb/>tigator, who retained the final word concerning the diag-<lb/>nosis or cause of death. A random 10% sample of strokes, <lb/>nonfatal MIs and CHD deaths was selected for blinded <lb/>quality control evaluation by the ALLHAT Endpoints Sub-<lb/>committee; for these cases additional documentation was <lb/>requested. <lb/>No such routine Endpoints Subcommittee quality control <lb/>was initially planned for reported HF. However, the Sub-<lb/>committee was subsequently called upon to evaluate a <lb/>random sample of reported fatal and hospitalized nonfa-<lb/>tal HF events. As this occurred prior to the termination of <lb/>the doxazosin arm, neither the chair nor the members of <lb/>the Subcommittee was informed of the major reason for <lb/>this review, namely, the trend toward a higher HF event <lb/>rate in the doxazosin group compared to the chlortha-<lb/>lidone group. The Subcommittee was told that the review <lb/>was undertaken at the request of the DSMB to address the <lb/>reliability and validity of reported HF events. This evalua-<lb/>tion consisted of fifty events, evenly distributed across the <lb/>four treatment groups, reported as fatal or hospitalized <lb/>nonfatal HF and with protocol-required documentation <lb/>(discharge summary for hospitalized events, death certifi-<lb/>cates for deaths). Additional material was not requested, <lb/>since this would have posed an undue burden on the clin-<lb/>ical site staff and would have risked raising questions <lb/>about emerging differences among treatment groups. <lb/>The ALLHAT definition of HF, used previously in the <lb/>Systolic Hypertension in the Elderly Program (SHEP) [5], <lb/>includes &quot;patients with clear-cut signs or symptoms of left <lb/>or right ventricular dysfunction that cannot be attributed <lb/>to other causes...&quot; The diagnosis of HF must include at <lb/>least one of four stated symptoms [paroxysmal nocturnal <lb/>dyspnea, dyspnea at rest, New York Heart Classification <lb/>functional class III (for definition see Additional Informa-<lb/>tion, Item 1), or orthopnea], and one of seven stated signs <lb/>(rales, 2+ or greater ankle edema, tachycardia of 120 <lb/>beats/minute or more after five minutes at rest, cardiome-<lb/>galy by chest x-ray, chest x-ray characteristic of HF, S 3 gal-<lb/>lop, or jugular venous distention). Since lower extremity <lb/>edema or exertional dyspnea may be due to non-cardiac <lb/>causes, the presence of either of these alone, without other <lb/>indications of heart failure, is not sufficient for a diagnosis <lb/>of HF. Study guidelines caution against a hasty HF diagno-<lb/>sis in patients with severe pulmonary disease, including <lb/>chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), pneu-<lb/>monia, or other severe, documented lung disease. <lb/>Baseline Characteristics and Medical Management <lb/>Baseline characteristics of chlorthalidone and doxazosin <lb/>participants were compared. These analyses were stratified <lb/>by HF outcome: 1) fatal and hospitalized HF; 2) treated, <lb/>non-hospitalized HF; and, 3) no HF. <lb/>Post-HF event medical management may provide addi-<lb/>tional evidence of the physicians&apos; confidence in the HF di-<lb/>agnosis. The post-event use of open-label diuretics, ACE-<lb/>inhibitors, and beta-blockers, i.e., accepted treatments for <lb/>HF [6-9], was compared between doxazosin and chlo-<lb/>rthalidone groups, as was the proportion in each group of <lb/>those who remained on assigned blinded medication after <lb/>the event. (For study guidelines regarding the use and re-<lb/>porting of open-label medicines of the same class as the <lb/>blinded drugs, see Additional Information, Items 2 and <lb/>3.) <lb/>Ejection Fraction Review <lb/>A CTC physician plus non-medical staff reviewed in a <lb/>blinded fashion 361 hospitalized HF events (representing <lb/>278 participants) for ejection fraction data: looking for <lb/>whether an ejection fraction was measured, the method <lb/>utilized, and the measurement. Results, tabulated by ran-<lb/>domization groups, reflected data that had been collected <lb/>up to July, 1999, the time of the review. <lb/>Case-Fatality Rates and Causes of Death <lb/>As a measure of the diagnostic validity and severity of HF <lb/>and comparability between drug groups, time-from-<lb/>event-to-death analyses of participants with hospitalized <lb/>or treated HF were compared between the two groups. <lb/>Causes of death of such participants were also compared <lb/>in the doxazosin and chlorthalidone groups. <lb/>Statistical Analyses <lb/>Data were analyzed according to participants&apos; randomiza-<lb/>tion assignments and HF outcome status, regardless of <lb/>subsequent medication adherence. The Kaplan-Meier <lb/>method was utilized in calculating cumulative event rates. <lb/>Descriptive statistics by treatment groups were presented <lb/>for baseline characteristics, HF ascertainment, ejection <lb/>fractions and use of HF medications. Comparability of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Current Controlled Trials in Cardiovascular Medicine 2002, 3 <lb/>http://cvm.controlled-trials.com/content/3/1/10 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 4 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>

			<body>baseline characteristics of the treatment and HF outcome <lb/>groups was ascertained by the χ 2 test for categorical varia-<lb/>bles and standard normal (z) test for continuous varia-<lb/>bles. <lb/>Results <lb/>Heart Failure Diagnostic Criteria <lb/>The blinded review by the Endpoints Subcommittee of 50 <lb/>fatal or hospitalized HF events from the 4 drug groups de-<lb/>termined 11 (22%) to have incomplete data for a defini-<lb/>tive review. Of the remaining 39, 33 (85%) were <lb/>confirmed to have HF by one or both reviewers. For both <lb/>the chlorthalidone and doxazosin groups, the diagnosis of <lb/>HF was confirmed in 90% (18/20). <lb/>Baseline Characteristics <lb/>Baseline characteristics for the doxazosin and chlortha-<lb/>lidone treatment groups, stratified for HF status, are de-<lb/>scribed in Table 1. <lb/>Baseline characteristics of doxazosin and chlorthalidone <lb/>participants with subsequent hospitalized or fatal HF were <lb/>compared. Doxazosin participants with hospitalized or <lb/>fatal HF had a higher baseline SBP than the chlortha-<lb/>lidone participants (150.1 vs. 147.8 mm Hg at the rand-<lb/>omization visit). More doxazosin participants had LVH by <lb/>ECG (22.3% vs. 20.5% of chlorthalidone participants); <lb/>slightly more chlorthalidone than doxazosin participants <lb/>had LVH by echocardiogram. Several eligibility risk fac-<lb/>tors, including previous MIs or strokes, coronary revascu-<lb/>larization procedures, other atherosclerotic cardiovascular <lb/>Table 1: Baseline Characteristics of Participants With and Without Heart Failure <lb/>Hospitalized and Fatal HF <lb/>Treated, Nonhospitalized HF <lb/>Without HF* <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>No. of subjects <lb/>327 <lb/>346 <lb/>93 <lb/>145 <lb/>14493 <lb/>8347 <lb/>Age, years, mean (SD) <lb/>70.7 (8.3) <lb/>71.0 (8.6) <lb/>70.3 (8.2) <lb/>69.9 (7.2) <lb/>66.8 (7.6) <lb/>66.6 (7.6) <lb/>Race <lb/>White, non-Hispanic, % <lb/>61.2 <lb/>55.8 <lb/>63.4 <lb/>64.8 <lb/>47.3 <lb/>46.3 <lb/>Black, non-Hispanic, % <lb/>30.6 <lb/>35.3 <lb/>32.3 <lb/>30.3 <lb/>32.0 <lb/>32.9 <lb/>Hispanic, % <lb/>4.6 <lb/>5.5 <lb/>2.2 <lb/>2.8 <lb/>15.6 <lb/>16.1 <lb/>Other, % <lb/>3.7 <lb/>3.1 <lb/>2.2 <lb/>2.1 <lb/>5.1 <lb/>4.8 <lb/>W o m e n , % <lb/>4 2 . 8 <lb/>3 9 . 6 <lb/>3 3 . 3 <lb/>4 4 . 1 <lb/>4 7 . 0 <lb/>4 6 . 5 <lb/>Education, years, mean (SD) <lb/>10.5 (3.9) <lb/>10.7 (3.4) <lb/>11.3 (3.6) <lb/>12.1 (3.2) <lb/>11.0 (4.0) <lb/>11.0 (4.0) <lb/>Cigarette smoking, current, % <lb/>19.0 <lb/>19.4 <lb/>11.8 <lb/>17.9 <lb/>22.1 <lb/>21.9 <lb/>Antihypertensive treatment <lb/>T r e a t e d &gt; 2 m o n t h s , % <lb/>8 6 . 9 <lb/>8 6 . 8 <lb/>9 5 . 7 <lb/>9 5 . 2 <lb/>8 6 . 9 <lb/>8 6 . 7 <lb/>Treated &lt; 2 months, % <lb/>3.3 <lb/>3.3 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>3.3 <lb/>3.3 <lb/>Untreated, % <lb/>9.8 <lb/>10.0 <lb/>3.2 <lb/>4.8 <lb/>9.9 <lb/>10.0 <lb/>Blood pressure, mm Hg, mean (SD) <lb/>147.8/81.1 <lb/>(17.6/10.9) <lb/>150.1/81.8 <lb/>(16.5/11.0) <lb/>147.1/82.2 <lb/>(16.0/10.5) <lb/>145.9/82.0 <lb/>(15.8/10.6) <lb/>146.2/84.1 <lb/>(15.6/10.0) <lb/>146.1/84.1 <lb/>(15.7/10) <lb/>Pulse pressure, mm Hg, mean (SD) <lb/>66.7 (16.5) <lb/>68.3 (15.3) <lb/>64.9 (13.0) <lb/>63.9 (15.3) <lb/>62.1 (14.1) <lb/>62.1 (14.2) <lb/>Eligibility risk factors † <lb/>LVH <lb/>B y e l e c t r o c a r d i o g r a m , % <lb/>2 0 . 5 <lb/>2 2 . 3 <lb/>1 8 . 3 <lb/>2 1 . 4 <lb/>1 6 . 1 <lb/>1 6 . 1 <lb/>By echocardiogram, % <lb/>6.3 <lb/>4.7 <lb/>4.4 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>4.6 <lb/>4.6 <lb/>O l d M I o r s t r o k e , % <lb/>3 6 . 1 <lb/>3 4 . 7 <lb/>4 1 . 9 <lb/>3 3 . 1 <lb/>2 3 . 1 <lb/>2 2 . 3 <lb/>C A B G / A n g i o p l a s t y , % <lb/>2 2 . 6 <lb/>1 8 . 5 <lb/>2 5 . 8 <lb/>2 6 . 2 <lb/>1 2 . 9 <lb/>1 2 . 6 <lb/>A S C V D , % <lb/>3 3 . 3 <lb/>2 9 . 2 <lb/>3 1 . 2 <lb/>3 1 . 0 <lb/>2 3 . 4 <lb/>2 4 . 6 ‡ <lb/>T y p e 2 d i a b e t e s , % <lb/>4 6 . 8 <lb/>4 8 . 3 <lb/>4 3 . 0 <lb/>4 0 . 7 <lb/>3 5 . 9 <lb/>3 4 . 7 <lb/>H D L &lt; 3 5 m g / d l , % <lb/>1 2 . 8 <lb/>1 3 . 6 <lb/>1 4 . 0 <lb/>1 3 . 8 <lb/>1 1 . 9 <lb/>1 1 . 7 <lb/>S T -T w a v e c h a n g e s , % <lb/>1 2 . 8 <lb/>1 0 . 6 <lb/>1 0 . 9 <lb/>1 2 . 9 <lb/>1 0 . 4 <lb/>1 0 . 2 <lb/>HF= Heart Failure C = Chlorthalidone treatment group D = Doxazosin treatment group mm Hg = millimeters mercury LVH = Left ventricular <lb/>hypertrophy MI = Myocardial infarction CABG = Coronary artery bypass graft ASCVD = Atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease HDL = High-den-<lb/>sity lipoprotein *Only participants with at least one follow-up visit are included. 355 chlorthalidone and 229 doxazosin participants are excluded <lb/>due to lack of at least one follow-up visit. † For trial eligibility, participants had to have at least 1 other risk factor in addition to hypertension. The <lb/>indicated risk factors are not mutually exclusive or exhaustive and do not represent prevalence. ‡ P = .0484 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Current Controlled Trials in Cardiovascular Medicine 2002, 3 <lb/>http://cvm.controlled-trials.com/content/3/1/10 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 5 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>

			<body>disease (ASCVD), and ST-T wave changes, were reported <lb/>more often in chlorthalidone than in doxazosin partici-<lb/>pants, though the differences were not significant. Chlo-<lb/>rthalidone and doxazosin participants with hospitalized <lb/>or fatal HF had similar pre-trial antihypertensive treat-<lb/>ment durations. None of these differences was significant <lb/>at P &lt; .05. <lb/>Participants with HF events displayed higher rates of most <lb/>cardiovascular risk factors compared to those without HF <lb/>events. Approximately 35-36% of chlorthalidone and <lb/>doxazosin participants with fatal or hospitalized HF had <lb/>reported prior MI or stroke as baseline eligibility risk fac-<lb/>tors, compared to 22-23% of those without HF (P &lt; <lb/>.001). Participants with hospitalized/fatal HF had signifi-<lb/>cantly higher rates of pre-randomization coronary artery <lb/>bypass grafts (CABGs) and coronary angioplasties (19-<lb/>23% of those with HF vs. 13% of those without; P &lt; .001) <lb/>and other atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease (ASCVD) <lb/>(29-33% of those with HF vs. 23-25% of those without; <lb/>P &lt; .001). Diabetes as a baseline risk factor occurred more <lb/>frequently in those with HF: 47-48% in those with HF, <lb/>35-36% in those without (P &lt; .001). Left ventricular <lb/>hypertrophy (LVH) by ECG was a risk factor in 21-22% of <lb/>those who later developed HF, compared with 16% of <lb/>those in each group who did not develop HF (P &lt; .001). <lb/>Baseline pulse pressure (PP) showed some variation be-<lb/>tween participants who did and did not develop HF. For <lb/>participants with subsequent hospitalization or death <lb/>from HF, PP was 67 and 68 mm Hg for the chlorthalidone <lb/>and doxazosin groups, respectively. Treated, non-hospi-<lb/>talized participants showed a lower mean baseline PP of <lb/>65 (chlorthalidone group) and 64 mm Hg (doxazosin <lb/>group), and an even lower mean PP in those without HF <lb/>(62 mm Hg in each group). <lb/>Medical Management <lb/>Table 2 presents post-event pharmacologic treatment of <lb/>participants with HF and antihypertensive treatment of <lb/>participants without HF. Following hospitalization for <lb/>HF, 36% (83/232) of chlorthalidone participants and <lb/>45% (126/281) of doxazosin participants remained on <lb/>their blinded medications. Percentages of participants on <lb/>open-label diuretics and ACE-inhibitors were similar fol-<lb/>lowing the event: 58% (135/232) of chlorthalidone par-<lb/>ticipants and 64% (180/281) of doxazosin participants <lb/>were prescribed open-label diuretics; 39% (90/232) of <lb/>chlorthalidone participants and 41% (114/281) of doxa-<lb/>zosin participants were prescribed open-label ACE-inhib-<lb/>itors. Beta-blockers were prescribed for 14% of each group <lb/>following the event, which was actually somewhat less <lb/>than for participants who did not develop HF. Three-quar-<lb/>ters of hospitalized HF participants in each group (169/ <lb/>232 in chlorthalidone group, 210/281 in doxazosin <lb/>group) received at least one of the three medications (di-<lb/>uretic, ACE-inhibitor, or beta-blocker) post-hospitaliza-<lb/>tion. <lb/>Among participants treated but not hospitalized for HF, <lb/>58% (54/93) of the chlorthalidone group and 64% (93/ <lb/>145) of the doxazosin group remained on their blinded <lb/>medication. Over 60% of participants in each group were <lb/>prescribed open-label diuretics and over 30% received <lb/>ACE-inhibitors. Open-label beta-blocker use post-event <lb/>occurred in 19% (18/93) of the chlorthalidone group and <lb/>Table 2: Post-Event Pharmacologic Treatment of Participants With and Without Heart Failure <lb/>Hospitalized Heart Failure* <lb/>Treated, Nonhospitalized <lb/>Heart Failure* <lb/>Without Heart Failure † <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>No. of participants <lb/>232 <lb/>281 <lb/>93 <lb/>145 <lb/>14493 <lb/>8347 <lb/>Post-event medication <lb/>Blinded medication, (%) <lb/>83 (35.8) <lb/>126 (44.8) <lb/>54 (58.1) <lb/>93 (64.1) <lb/>11247 (77.6) <lb/>6096 (73.0) <lb/>Open-label diuretic (%) <lb/>135 (58.2) <lb/>180 (64.0) <lb/>57 (61.3) <lb/>98 (67.6) <lb/>1279 (8.8) <lb/>1153 (13.8) <lb/>Open-label ACE-inhibitor (%) <lb/>90 (38.8) <lb/>114 (40.5) <lb/>31 (33.3) <lb/>44 (30.3) <lb/>1154 (8.0) <lb/>826 (9.9) <lb/>Open-label beta-blocker (%) <lb/>33 (14.2) <lb/>38 (13.5) <lb/>18 (19.4) <lb/>32 (22.1) <lb/>3149 (21.7) <lb/>2016 (24.0) <lb/>Open-label diuretic, ACE-inhibitor <lb/>or beta-blocker (%) <lb/>169 (72.8) <lb/>210 (74.8) <lb/>72 (77.4) <lb/>119 (82.1) <lb/>4829 (33.3) <lb/>3347 (40.1) <lb/>C = Chlorthalidone treatment group D = Doxazosin treatment group ACE = Angiotensin converting enzyme *Represents data as of first clinic visit <lb/>after event. † Represents data as of most recent clinic visit. All participants represented have at least one follow-up visit. 355 chlorthalidone and 229 <lb/>doxazosin participants are excluded due to lack of at least one follow-up visit. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Current Controlled Trials in Cardiovascular Medicine 2002, 3 <lb/>http://cvm.controlled-trials.com/content/3/1/10 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 6 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>

			<body>22% (32/145) of the doxazosin group, approximately the <lb/>same frequency as in participants without HF. In both <lb/>treatment groups, a diuretic, ACE-inhibitor or beta-block-<lb/>er was prescribed for over 75% of these participants (72/ <lb/>93 in chlorthalidone group, 119/145 in doxazosin <lb/>group). <lb/>Ejection Fraction Review <lb/>Table 3 displays the ejection fraction data. About half <lb/>(178/361) of reviewed discharge summaries mentioned <lb/>ejection fractions measured during hospitalization, two-<lb/>thirds (116/169) of which had quantitative measure-<lb/>ments reported in the discharge summaries (data not giv-<lb/>en). Considering only the earliest ejection fraction <lb/>information ascertained for each HF participant, 63% <lb/>(29/46) of the chlorthalidone and 70% (41/59) of the <lb/>doxazosin participants had ejection fractions at or below <lb/>40%. Just under half (27/59) of the ejection fractions re-<lb/>ported in the doxazosin group were at or below 30%, <lb/>compared with one third (15/46) in the chlorthalidone <lb/>group. Two-thirds of ejection fractions were obtained by <lb/>echocardiograms, though catheterizations accounted for a <lb/>larger percentage of results in the doxazosin group than in <lb/>the chlorthalidone group (36% vs. 24%). <lb/>Causes of Death and 2-Year Case-Fatality <lb/>Causes of death of participants with previous HF hospital-<lb/>ization were distributed similarly in the two groups, with <lb/>slight variations. HF accounted for 21.2% (11/52) of the <lb/>deaths among chlorthalidone participants and 17.1% <lb/>(12/70) of the deaths among doxazosin participants. Over <lb/>half of the deaths in each group (29/52 in the chlortha-<lb/>lidone group; 43/70 in the doxazosin group) were due to <lb/>cardiovascular events. Fifteen percent (8/52) of deaths in <lb/>the chlorthalidone group were attributed to cancer, com-<lb/>pared to 9% (6/70) in the doxazosin group (Table 4). <lb/>Case-fatality for participants with hospitalized HF events <lb/>showed no significant differences (RR 0.96, 95% CI, <lb/>0.67-1.38, P = 0.83) between the two treatment groups <lb/>(Figure 1). Among participants in the doxazosin treat-<lb/>ment group who had been previously hospitalized for HF, <lb/>22.1% (70/317) subsequently died, compared to 18.6% <lb/>(52/280) of those in the chlorthalidone group (Table 4). <lb/>As previously reported, all-cause mortality did not signifi-<lb/>cantly differ in the two treatment groups (RR 1.03, 95% CI <lb/>0.90-1.15, P = 0.56) [2]. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>The finding of significantly increased HF events in the <lb/>doxazosin group compared with the chlorthalidone <lb/>group created a dilemma for ALLHAT. Since the trial was <lb/>not designed to focus on HF, a component of a secondary <lb/>endpoint, the validity of reported HF events became an is-<lb/>sue. In this paper, we have described several analyses to <lb/>address this concern. <lb/>As previously reported, lost-to-follow-up and event docu-<lb/>mentation were similar in the two treatment groups [2]. <lb/>Steps employed to validate the HF outcome in these treat-<lb/>ment groups confirmed the consistency of HF event re-<lb/>porting. Participants in the two drug groups had similar <lb/>Table 3: Ejection Fraction Data for Participants Hospitalized with Heart Failure* <lb/>Chlorthalidone Treatment <lb/>Group <lb/>Doxazosin Treatment <lb/>Group <lb/>Total <lb/>Participants with hospitalized heart failure <lb/>245 <lb/>296 <lb/>541 <lb/>Hospitalized heart failure participants reviewed <lb/>134 <lb/>144 <lb/>278 <lb/>Total reviewed heart failure participants with quantitative <lb/>ejection fractions † <lb/>46 <lb/>59 <lb/>105 <lb/>By cardiac catheterization (%) <lb/>11 (23.9) <lb/>21 (35.6) <lb/>32 (30.5) <lb/>By echocardiogram (%) <lb/>33 (71.7) <lb/>37 (62.7) <lb/>70 (66.7) <lb/>Method not given (%) <lb/>2 (4.3) <lb/>1 (1.7) <lb/>3 (2.9) <lb/>Ejection fraction (%) ‡ <lb/>1-30% <lb/>15 (32.6) <lb/>27 (45.8) <lb/>42 (40.0) <lb/>31-40% <lb/>14 (30.4) <lb/>14 (23.7) <lb/>28 (26.7) <lb/>41-50% <lb/>9 (19.6) <lb/>7 (11.9) <lb/>16 (15.2) <lb/>51-60% <lb/>3 (6.5) <lb/>10 (16.9) <lb/>13 (12.4) <lb/>&gt;60% <lb/>5 (10.9) <lb/>1 (1.7) <lb/>6 (5.7) <lb/>*Evaluation of documentation for ejection fractions was completed in July, 1999, 6 months prior to the decision to discontinue the doxazosin arm <lb/>of ALLHAT. Total numbers of events and participants with heart failure in Table 3 are based on data at the time of review. † Event documentation <lb/>which referred to ejection fraction measurements but which did not provide numeric values was excluded from this tally. ‡ Ejection fraction for a <lb/>participant is based upon the earliest post-randomization heart failure hospitalization with quantitative ejection fraction information provided. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Current Controlled Trials in Cardiovascular Medicine 2002, 3 <lb/>http://cvm.controlled-trials.com/content/3/1/10 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 7 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>

			<body>baseline characteristics when stratified by HF status. The <lb/>differences in eligibility risk factors between those partici-<lb/>pants with HF and those without is not surprising: larger <lb/>percentages of those with HF had a history of MI, stroke, <lb/>CABG, angioplasty, other atherosclerotic cardiovascular <lb/>disease (ASCVD), diabetes, low HDL levels and ECG ab-<lb/>normalities. Nonetheless, these eligibility factors were not <lb/>substantially different between chlorthalidone and doxa-<lb/>zosin participants with HF. <lb/>Post-diagnosis pharmacologic management of patients is <lb/>one measure of the strength of physicians&apos; confidence in <lb/>the HF diagnoses. Open-label diuretics, ACE-inhibitors <lb/>and beta-blockers, all recognized treatments for HF, were <lb/>prescribed similarly for the chlorthalidone and doxazosin <lb/>groups, suggesting similar assessment of these events in <lb/>the two treatment groups. <lb/>ALLHAT criteria for HF were equivalently met in the two <lb/>groups. While the sample (n = 50) of hospitalized or fatal <lb/>HF reports reviewed by the ALLHAT Endpoints Subcom-<lb/>mittee was limited in number and in adequacy of corrob-<lb/>orating documentation, the review nonetheless showed <lb/>adherence to study criteria for the majority (85%) of the <lb/>event reports. The sometimes-discrepant results between <lb/>reviewers pertained more often to incomplete data than to <lb/>rejection of a HF diagnosis. <lb/>Clinical use of more objective measures, including nonin-<lb/>vasive and/or invasive tools for the measurement of left <lb/>ventricular function, offers a means of establishing and <lb/>quantifying systolic failure in cases clinically suggestive of <lb/>HF [7,10]. Among the ejection fractions reported in the <lb/>ALLHAT events that were reviewed, the majority fell at or <lb/>below 40%, indicating some degree of systolic dysfunc-<lb/>tion. However, HF is a clinical diagnosis that does not nec-<lb/>essarily exclude those with intact left ventricular systolic <lb/>function [11]. Hypertension is a major risk factor for di-<lb/>astolic HF; as many as 25% of asymptomatic hyperten-<lb/>sives with left ventricular hypertrophy have diastolic <lb/>dysfunction. Additionally, 90% of patients with coronary <lb/>artery disease may have some degree of diastolic dysfunc-<lb/>tion [12]. <lb/>The two-fold increased relative risk of HF in the doxazosin <lb/>group compared to the chlorthalidone group changed lit-<lb/>tle when confined to hospitalized and fatal events. Fur-<lb/>ther, HF patients in both the doxazosin and <lb/>chlorthalidone treatment groups showed a rather high <lb/>20% case-fatality rate over two years, as expected in HF pa-<lb/>tients [11,13,14], further supporting the validity of the di-<lb/>agnoses in the two groups. Among participants <lb/>hospitalized for HF who subsequently died, over half of <lb/>the deaths in each drug group were attributed to cardio-<lb/>vascular causes. <lb/>Treatment group differences in mortality attributed to HF <lb/>may take time to be recognized. Patients with HF are at <lb/>risk for other competing causes of death. Accordingly, it <lb/>may be too early to determine if a higher rate of HF in the <lb/>doxazosin group translates into a higher overall mortality <lb/>rate. A 20% 2-year case-fatality rate with a 4% difference <lb/>in HF incidence rate translates into a 0.8% potential dif-<lb/>ference in total mortality without any competing causes of <lb/>Table 4: Causes of Death of Participants with Prior Heart Failure Hospitalization <lb/>Chlorthalidone Treatment Group <lb/>Doxazosin Treatment Group <lb/>No. of participants with hospitalization for heart <lb/>failure prior to death* <lb/>280 <lb/>317 <lb/>No. of deaths (%) <lb/>52 (18.6) <lb/>70 (22.1) <lb/>Cause of death (%) <lb/>Myocardial infarction <lb/>7 (13.5) <lb/>5 (7.1) <lb/>Definite CHD <lb/>5 (9.6) <lb/>9 (12.9) <lb/>Possible CHD <lb/>1 (1.9) <lb/>7 (10.0) <lb/>Stroke <lb/>1 (1.9) <lb/>3 (4.3) <lb/>Heart failure <lb/>11 (21.2) <lb/>12 (17.1) <lb/>Other CVD <lb/>4 (7.7) <lb/>7 (10.0) <lb/>Total cardiovascular deaths (%) <lb/>29 (55.8) <lb/>43 (61.4) <lb/>Cancer <lb/>8 (15.4) <lb/>6 (8.6) <lb/>Kidney disease <lb/>1 (1.9) <lb/>1 (1.4) <lb/>Accident/suicide/homicide <lb/>0 (0) <lb/>1 (1.4) <lb/>Other non-CVD <lb/>8 (15.4) <lb/>11 (15.7) <lb/>Unknown <lb/>6 (11.5) <lb/>8 (11.4) <lb/>CHD = Coronary heart disease CVD = Cardiovascular disease *Excludes participants for whom death is the first reported heart failure event <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Current Controlled Trials in Cardiovascular Medicine 2002, 3 <lb/>http://cvm.controlled-trials.com/content/3/1/10 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 8 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>

			<body>death. With competing causes, the difference would be <lb/>smaller and difficult to detect even in a trial of ALLHAT&apos;s <lb/>size. <lb/>The diagnosis of HF is generally made on the basis of signs <lb/>and symptoms that may overlap with those of other cardi-<lb/>ovascular and pulmonary pathologies. Moreover, the clin-<lb/>ical picture may be further complicated for patients taking <lb/>doxazosin, side effects of which (edema, dyspnea, and <lb/>tachycardia) [15] may be misinterpreted as manifesta-<lb/>tions of HF. <lb/>The capture of events in a &quot;large and simple trial&quot; such as <lb/>ALLHAT has potential limitations. Built into a structure <lb/>composed largely of community-based physicians is the <lb/>assumption that their characterization of clinical events <lb/>reflects diagnostic standards of the medical community, <lb/>and, as such, meets study criteria. However, with its large <lb/>number of endpoints, resources available to ALLHAT pre-<lb/>cluded more than modest confirmatory event documenta-<lb/>tion. Resources were allocated for additional <lb/>documentation for quality control validation only for a <lb/>sample of the primary endpoint (MIs and fatal CHD) and <lb/>for strokes. While all reported events are reviewed at the <lb/>CTC, the sometimes incomplete supporting details in <lb/>documentation may not allow for validation of all events <lb/>according to ALLHAT criteria. Some discharge summaries <lb/>and death certificates may lack sufficient descriptive infor-<lb/>mation needed to confirm the clinical diagnoses. Clinic <lb/>staff are unable to provide corroborating documentation <lb/>for 2% of ALLHAT event reports. <lb/>Efforts to authenticate the HF events in the doxazosin and <lb/>chlorthalidone treatment groups represented a desirable <lb/>step in the examination of the increased rate of HR in the <lb/>doxazosin group. All methods employed provided con-<lb/>firmatory evidence that both the HF diagnosis and the dif-<lb/>ference in HF rates noted between the doxazosin and <lb/>Figure 1 <lb/>Kaplan-Meier estimates for cumulative mortality for hospitalized heart failure cases in the chlorthalidone and doxazosin groups <lb/>(RR 0.96, 95% CI, 0.67-1.38; P = 0.84) <lb/>Cumulative Mortality Rate <lb/>Years Hospitalized Heart Failure to Death <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>0 <lb/>.1 <lb/>.2 <lb/>.3 <lb/>.4 <lb/>.5 <lb/>Chlorthalidone <lb/>Doxazosiṅ˙˙˙˙˙˙_ <lb/>____ <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Current Controlled Trials in Cardiovascular Medicine 2002, 3 <lb/>http://cvm.controlled-trials.com/content/3/1/10 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 9 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>

			<body>chlorthalidone groups were valid. Results of this explora-<lb/>tory investigation support the event ascertainment meth-<lb/>ods developed for ALLHAT, specifically for HF events. This <lb/>validation exercise further illustrates the ability of large, <lb/>simple trials to answer important public health questions <lb/>requiring large sample sizes and to grapple with unexpect-<lb/>ed results in a responsible and meaningful manner. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Competing Interests <lb/>The authors of this paper disclose their affiliations with <lb/>Aventis (A), Abbott (AB), AstraZeneca (AZ), Bayer (B), Bi-<lb/>ovail (BV), Bristol-Myers Squibb (BMS), Forest (F), Glaxo-<lb/>SmithKline/SmithKline Beecham (GSK/SKB), King Phar-<lb/>maceuticals/Monarch (KM), Merck (M), Novartis (N), <lb/>Nu-Pharm (NP), Pharmacia/Upjohn (PHU), Pfizer, Inc. <lb/>(P), Sankyo (SY), Searle (SE), Solvay (SV), Takeda (T). <lb/>These relate to personal or institutional-affiliated receipt <lb/>of income in the areas of research grants, consultant fees, <lb/>or other compensation: BRD (AB,BMS,F,M,P,PHU,GSK/ <lb/>SKB), WCC (AZ,BMS,F,M,P,PHU,SY,SE,SV,T), JTW <lb/>(A,B,BMS,F,KM, <lb/>M,N,P), <lb/>FHHL <lb/>(AZ,B,BMS,M,NP,P,PHU), LJH (PHU); the other authors <lb/>report no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Additional Information <lb/>1) New York Heart Classification functional class III: &quot;Pa-<lb/>tients with cardiac disease resulting in marked limitation <lb/>of physical activity. They are comfortable at rest. Less than <lb/>ordinary physical activity causes fatigue, palpitation, dys-<lb/>pnea, or anginal pain.&quot; 1994 Revisions to Classification of <lb/>Functional Capacity and Objective Assessment of Patients <lb/>with Diseases of the Heart: AHA Medical/Scientific State-<lb/>ment. <lb/>2) The ALLHAT Manual of Operations provides for pre-<lb/>scription of open-label medicines of the same class as the <lb/>blinded medications, when a compelling indication ex-<lb/>ists, such that the total dose of the added open-label drug <lb/>should not exceed 1/2 of the maximum dose as recom-<lb/>mended in the Sixth Report of the Joint National Com-<lb/>mittee on Detection, Evaluation and Treatment of High <lb/>Blood Pressure (JNC VI). If a compelling reason requires a <lb/>higher dose, it is permitted. <lb/>3) The ALLHAT follow-up form allows for reporting of <lb/>open-label ACE-inhibitors and diuretics; among beta-<lb/>blockers, only atenolol is reported. The use of other beta-<lb/>blockers cannot be ascertained from the data. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>This study is supported by a contract with the National Heart, Blood, and <lb/>Lung Institute (NHLBI). The ALLHAT investigators acknowledge contribu-<lb/>tions of study medications supplied by Pfizer, Inc. (amlodipine and doxa-<lb/>zosin), AstraZeneca (atenolol and lisinopril), and Bristol-Myers Squibb <lb/>(pravastatin), and financial support provided by Pfizer to the NHLBI. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. <lb/>Davis BR, Cutler JA, Gordon D, for the ALLHAT Research Group, et <lb/>al: Rationale and design of the Antihypertensive and Lipid <lb/>Lowering Treatment to Prevent Heart Attack Trial (ALL-<lb/>HAT). Am J Hypertens 1996, 9:342-360 <lb/>2. <lb/>The ALLHAT Officers and Coordinators for the ALLHAT Collabora-<lb/>tive Research Group: Major cardiovascular events in hyperten-<lb/>sive patients randomized to doxazosin vs. chlorthalidone: <lb/>The Antihypertensive and Lipid-Lowering Treatment to <lb/>Prevent Heart Attack Trial (ALLHAT). JAMA 2000, 283:1967-<lb/>1975 <lb/>3. <lb/>Furberg CD, Cutler JA, Davis BR: Status of alpha-blocker thera-<lb/>py in the treatment of hypertension: Findings of ALLHAT. <lb/>Harrison&apos;s Online. The Mc-Graw-Hill Companies 2001update article <lb/>to Chapter 246 <lb/>4. <lb/>Pressel SL, Davis BR, Wright JT, et al: Operational aspects of ter-<lb/>minating the doxazosin arm of the Antihypertensive and Li-<lb/>pid Lowering Treatment to Prevent Heart Attack Trial <lb/>(ALLHAT). Control Clin Trials 2001, 22:29-41 <lb/>5. <lb/>Kostis JB, Davis BR, Cutler J: Prevention of heart failure by anti-<lb/>hypertensive drug treatment in older persons with isolated <lb/>systolic hypertension. JAMA 1997, 278:212-216 <lb/>6. <lb/>Braunwald E , Editor: Heart Disease: A Textbook of Cardiovascular Med-<lb/>icine W.B. Saunders Co 1997, 471-491 <lb/>7. <lb/>Williams JF, Bristow MR, Fowler MB, et al: Guidelines for the eval-<lb/>uation and management of heart failure: Report of the <lb/>American College of Cardiology/American Heart Associa-<lb/>tion Task Force on Practice Guidelines (Committee on Eval-<lb/>uation and Management of Heart Failure). Circulation 1995, <lb/>92:2764-2784 <lb/>8. <lb/>Changes in mortality from heart failure -United States, <lb/>1980-1995 CDC MMWR Weekly 1998, 47:633-637 <lb/>9. <lb/>Kronstam MA: Progress in heart failure management? Lessons <lb/>from the real world (editorial). Circulation 2000, 102:1076-1078 <lb/>10. Shamsham F, Mitchell J: Essentials of the diagnosis of heart fail-<lb/>ure. Am Family Physician 2000, 61:1319-1328 <lb/>11. Vasan RS, Larson MG, Benjamin EJ, et al: Congestive heart failure <lb/>in subjects with normal versus reduced left ventricular ejec-<lb/>tion fraction: Prevalence and mortality in a population-based <lb/>cohort. J Am Coll Cardiol 1999, 33:1948-1955 <lb/>12. Mandinov L, Eferli FR, Seiler C, et al: Diastolic heart failure (re-<lb/>view). Cardiovasc Res 2000, 45:813-825 <lb/>13. MacIntire K, Capewell S., Stewart JWT, et al: Evidence of improv-<lb/>ing prognosis in heart failure: Trends in case fatality in 66547 <lb/>patients hospitalized between 1986 and 1995. Circulation 2000, <lb/>102:1126-1131 <lb/>14. Ho KKL, Anderson KM, Kannel WB, et al: Survival after the onset <lb/>of congestive heart failure in Framingham Heart Study sub-<lb/>jects. Circulation 1993, 88:107-115 <lb/>15. Physician&apos;s Desk Reference. 2001, 2475-2476 <lb/></listBibl>

			Publish with BioMed Central and every <lb/>scientist can read your work free of charge <lb/>&quot;BioMedcentral will be the most significant development for <lb/>disseminating the results of biomedical research in our lifetime.&quot; <lb/>Paul Nurse, Director-General, Imperial Cancer Research Fund <lb/>Publish with BMC and your research papers will be: <lb/>available free of charge to the entire biomedical community <lb/>peer reviewed and published immediately upon acceptance <lb/>cited in PubMed and archived on PubMed Central <lb/>yours -you keep the copyright <lb/>editorial@biomedcentral.com <lb/>Submit your manuscript here: <lb/>http://www.biomedcentral.com/manuscript/ <lb/>BioMedcentral.com 


	</text>
</tei>
