<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_1471-2148-9-32"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="headnote">BioMed Central <lb/></note> 
			
			<page>Page 1 of 13 <lb/></page> 
			
			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note> 
			
			<front>BMC Evolutionary Biology <lb/> Open Access <lb/> Research article <lb/> Genetic analysis of hybridization and introgression between wild <lb/>mongoose and brown lemurs <lb/> Jennifer Pastorini* 1,2 , Alphonse Zaramody 3 , Deborah J Curtis 4 , <lb/>Caroline M Nievergelt 5 and Nicholas I Mundy 6 <lb/> Address: 1 Anthropologisches Institut, Universität Zürich, Winterthurerstrasse 190, 8057 Zürich, Switzerland, 2 Centre for Conservation and <lb/>Research, 35 Gunasekara Gardens, Nawala Road, Rajagiriya, Sri Lanka, 3 Département des Sciences de la Terre, Université de Mahajanga, Faculté <lb/>des Sciences, Dépt. de Biologie Animale, B.P. 652, Mahajanga 401, Madagascar, 4 Department of Anthropology &amp; Geography, School of Social <lb/>Sciences &amp; Law, Oxford Brookes University, Gipsy Lane, Headington, Oxford, OX3 0BP, UK, 5 Department of Psychiatry, University of California <lb/>at San Diego, 9500 Gilman Drive, La Jolla, CA 92093-0603, USA and 6 Department of Zoology, University of Cambridge, Downing Street, <lb/>Cambridge, CB2 3EJ, UK <lb/>Email: Jennifer Pastorini* -jenny@aim.uzh.ch; Alphonse Zaramody -zaramody@univ-mahajanga.mg; <lb/>Deborah J Curtis -curtis@scimedtrans.co.uk; Caroline M Nievergelt -cnieverg@ucsd.edu; Nicholas I Mundy -nim21@cam.ac.uk <lb/>* Corresponding author <lb/> Abstract <lb/> Background: Hybrid zones generally represent areas of secondary contact after speciation. The <lb/>nature of the interaction between genes of individuals in a hybrid zone is of interest in the study of <lb/>evolutionary processes. In this study, data from nuclear microsatellites and mitochondrial DNA <lb/>sequences were used to genetically characterize hybridization between wild mongoose lemurs <lb/>(Eulemur mongoz) and brown lemurs (E. fulvus) at Anjamena in west Madagascar. <lb/> Results: Two segments of mtDNA have been sequenced and 12 microsatellite loci screened in <lb/>162 brown lemurs and mongoose lemurs. Among the mongoose lemur population at Anjamena, <lb/>we identified two F1 hybrids (one also having the mtDNA haplotype of E. fulvus) and six other <lb/>individuals with putative introgressed alleles in their genotype. Principal component analysis groups <lb/>both hybrids as intermediate between E. mongoz and E. fulvus and admixture analyses revealed an <lb/>admixed genotype for both animals. Paternity testing proved one F1 hybrid to be fertile. Of the <lb/>eight brown lemurs genotyped, all have either putative introgressed microsatellite alleles and/or <lb/>the mtDNA haplotype of E. mongoz. <lb/> Conclusion: Introgression is bidirectional for the two species, with an indication that it is more <lb/>frequent in brown lemurs than in mongoose lemurs. We conclude that this hybridization occurs <lb/>because mongoose lemurs have expanded their range relatively recently. Introgressive <lb/>hybridization may play an important role in the unique lemur radiation, as has already been shown <lb/>in other rapidly evolving animals. <lb/></front> 
			
			<body> Background <lb/> Hybridization among animals has traditionally been <lb/>viewed as an unusual event. However, recent genetic stud-<lb/>ies have shown that it occurs more commonly than origi-<lb/>nally believed [1,2]. Hybridization may occur due to <lb/>human impact, such as between domestic or captive spe-<lb/>cies, wild and domestic species [3,4] or between intro-<lb/>duced and native species [5,6]. Natural hybridization has <lb/></body> 
			
			<front>Published: 5 February 2009 <lb/> BMC Evolutionary Biology 2009, 9:32 doi:10.1186/1471-2148-9-32 <lb/> Received: 5 April 2008 <lb/> Accepted: 5 February 2009 <lb/> This article is available from: http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2148/9/32 <lb/> © 2009 Pastorini et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. <lb/>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), <lb/>which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/>

			BMC Evolutionary Biology 2009, 9:32 <lb/>

			http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2148/9/32 <lb/></front>
			
			<page>Page 2 of 13 <lb/></page> 
			
			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note> 
			
			<body>been found across the animal kingdom, including insects <lb/>[7], fish [8], amphibians [9], birds [10,11], carnivores <lb/>[12], and monkeys [13-15]. Among the Malagasy lemurs, <lb/>a few cases of hybridization between subspecies have been <lb/>reported in the wild [16-19]. <lb/>Harrison [20] defined hybridization as &quot;the interbreeding <lb/>of individuals from two populations, or groups of popu-<lb/>lations, which are distinguishable on the basis of one or <lb/>more heritable characters.&quot; Hybridization occurs when <lb/>there are incomplete reproductive barriers between two <lb/>taxa. There are many possible evolutionary outcomes of <lb/>hybridization: 1) The two hybridizing taxa may merge, 2) <lb/>reproductive barriers may be reinforced between the <lb/>parental taxa, 3) transfer of genetic material into one or <lb/>both parental taxa may occur, which might facilitate adap-<lb/>tive evolution 4) a new species of hybrid origin may be <lb/>formed, or 5) the hybrid zone may become established <lb/>without any major impact on the parental taxa [21,22]. <lb/>Therefore, studies of natural hybrids and their genetic <lb/>composition can shed new light on issues concerning <lb/>reproductive barriers, survivorship and fitness of hybrids <lb/>and give important insights into evolutionary processes <lb/>and the adaptation of species. <lb/>The Malagasy lemurs are a spectacular example of adap-<lb/>tive radiation and provide an ideal model for studies of <lb/>evolutionary diversification [23]. Currently, 71 lemur spe-<lb/>cies and subspecies are recognized, which are distributed <lb/>across 15 genera in 5 families [24]. Madagascar&apos;s isola-<lb/>tion, diverse climate, geology and vegetation provide con-<lb/>ditions equating to a natural experiment in taxonomic <lb/>diversification. Hybridization has been found to play a <lb/>major role in rapid radiations such as Darwin&apos;s finches <lb/>[11], East African cichlid fishes [8], Hawaiian crickets [25] <lb/>and passion-vine butterflies [7]. However, little is known <lb/>about interspecific gene flow or its role in the radiation of <lb/>lemurs. <lb/>During a field study on mongoose lemurs (Eulemur mon-<lb/> goz) at Anjamena in western Madagascar an animal was <lb/>observed which exhibited a pelage coloration intermedi-<lb/>ate between that of red-fronted brown lemurs (E. fulvus <lb/>rufus) and mongoose lemurs [26]. This phenotypic varia-<lb/>tion was the first sign that interspecific hybridization <lb/>might be occurring at this site. When sequencing some E. <lb/>f. rufus individuals from the same locality for a phyloge-<lb/>netic study of brown lemurs [27], one individual was <lb/>found to have the mtDNA haplotype of E. mongoz [28]. <lb/>This hardened the suspicion of Anjamena being a hybrid <lb/>zone between two taxonomically well accepted Eulemur <lb/> species. <lb/>Mongoose lemurs and brown lemurs are two of five spe-<lb/>cies in the genus Eulemur, in the family Lemuridae. E. mon-<lb/>goz occurs in the west of Madagascar. Brown lemurs are <lb/>divided into 6 subspecies, which together range over a <lb/>large area of Madagascar, excluding the South of the <lb/>island. Notably, E. fulvus and E. mongoz are the only two <lb/>species of lemurs found outside Madagascar, and are <lb/>thought to have been introduced to the Comoros by <lb/>humans. In Madagascar, East of the Betsiboka river (Fig-<lb/>ure 1), mongoose lemur distribution overlaps with that of <lb/> E. f. fulvus. To the west of the Betsiboka river E. mongoz is <lb/>sympatric with E. f. rufus. The ranges of both brown lemur <lb/>subspecies are much larger than the relatively small area <lb/>mongoose lemurs occupy. E. mongoz is identified as &apos;vul-<lb/>nerable&apos; in the IUCN red list of threatened species, while <lb/> E. fulvus is classified as at &apos;lower risk&apos; of extinction [29]. <lb/>Habitat destruction and forest fragmentation are the main <lb/>threats to both taxa. <lb/>Mongoose lemurs at Anjamena live in small family groups <lb/>of 2–6 individuals, consisting of an adult pair and associ-<lb/>ated offspring. Group composition remains relatively <lb/>constant, with changes being limited to births and emigra-<lb/>tion of subadult individuals [26]. Mongoose lemurs are <lb/>cathemeral throughout the year with shifts towards more <lb/>diurnal activity in the wet season and more nocturnal <lb/>activity in the dry season [30]. E. mongoz is predominantly <lb/>frugivorous, its diet being supplemented by leaves, flow-<lb/>ers, and nectar [31]. <lb/>The most important potential competitor for mongoose <lb/>lemurs at Anjamena is E. f. rufus, as it not only shares food <lb/>resources (fruit and leaves) with E. mongoz but also exhib-<lb/>its a similar activity pattern [26]. Brown lemurs at Anja-<lb/>mena live in large groups of up to nine individuals with a <lb/>variable sex and age composition [32]. In 1995, popula-<lb/>tion density of E. f. rufus (121 individuals per km 2 ) in the <lb/>vicinity of Anjamena was much higher than that of E. <lb/>mongoz (45 individuals per km 2 ) [32]. Both E. mongoz and <lb/> E. fulvus exhibit sexual dichromatism. The pelage colora-<lb/>tion of brown lemur males and females is very different <lb/>from that of mongoose lemur males and females (for <lb/>illustrations see [24]). At Anjamena, the body weight of <lb/>adult brown lemurs (ca. 1700 g) is higher than that of <lb/>adult mongoose lemurs (ca. 1200 g, pers. observation). <lb/>Association between the two species has not been <lb/>observed at Anjamena [26]. <lb/>We conducted a comprehensive genetic analysis, includ-<lb/>ing both nuclear microsatellites and mitochondrial DNA <lb/>(mtDNA) sequences of E. mongoz and E. fulvus, to gain <lb/>insights into the genetic composition of the two species, <lb/>and to assess hybridization between them in Anjamena. <lb/>Microsatellites show a high degree of length polymor-<lb/>phism, which makes it possible to obtain pedigree-level <lb/>characterization of populations as well as to detect intro-<lb/>gression of alleles between species. Analysis of mtDNA <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">BMC Evolutionary Biology 2009, 9:32 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2148/9/32 <lb/></note>
			
			<page>Page 3 of 13 <lb/></page> 
			
			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note> 
			
			sequences allows direct determination of matrilineal <lb/>relatedness, which provides information on past hybrid <lb/>events. <lb/> Methods <lb/> Study population <lb/> A total of 163 samples from mongoose lemurs (108) and <lb/>brown lemurs (55) were collected from the wild and cap-<lb/>tivity (Table 1). The main study site Anjamena is situated <lb/>in the riverine forests of the Mahavavy in western Mada-<lb/>gascar (45°55&apos;E, 16°03&apos;S, Figure 1) from where a total of <lb/>38 samples of E. mongoz were collected. Five hair samples <lb/>were collected in 1994 and 1995 during a behavioural <lb/>study [30]. From August to September 1997, samples of <lb/>33 mongoose lemurs from 12 neighbouring groups and 8 <lb/>brown lemurs from 7 groups were collected at Anjamena. <lb/>In the same time period, 4 E. mongoz and 2 E. fulvus sam-<lb/>ples were collected from animals living near Anadabo-<lb/>mandry across the Mahavavy river from Anjamena. <lb/>Additionally, 2 mongoose lemur and 3 brown lemur sam-<lb/>ples from Ampijoroa (110 km east of Anjamena, sepa-<lb/>rated by the river Betsiboka, Figure 1) were analysed. From <lb/>the animals sampled in 1997, body weight was measured <lb/>and fur coloration was recorded by taking photographs. <lb/>A total of 63 blood, hair or tissue samples were collected <lb/>from mongoose lemurs in captivity. The origin of the cap-<lb/>tive mongoose lemur population is not entirely known, <lb/>but some founder animals originated from the Comoro <lb/>islands. One E. mongoz sample was of unknown origin. An <lb/>additional 42 E. fulvus samples were acquired from vari-<lb/>ous zoos, covering all brown lemur subspecies (Table 1). <lb/>In addition, samples of 3 E. coronatus, 3 E. rubriventer, 3 E. <lb/>macaco macaco, 3 E. m. flavifrons and 2 Lemur catta (all zoo <lb/>animals) were sequenced for mtDNA [for more details see <lb/>Additional file 1]. <lb/> Molecular methods <lb/> DNA was extracted from hair, blood or tissue samples <lb/>using a standard phenol-chloroform extraction [33]. <lb/>Approximately 10–100 ng template DNA was amplified <lb/>in 20 μl (microsatellites) or 50 μl (mtDNA) reactions <lb/>using 0.06 M Tris, 0.015 M (NH 4 ) 2 SO 4 , 1.5 mM MgCl 2 , <lb/>0.78 M DMSO, 0.025 mM for each dNTP, 1 mM for each <lb/>primer, and 0.5 U Thermophilus aquaticus (Taq) polymer-<lb/>ase. Samples were amplified for 25–35 cycles, with dena-<lb/>turing at 95°C for 30 s, primer annealing at 50–65°C for <lb/>60 s, and extension at 72°C for 60 s, followed by a final <lb/>extension for 5 min at 72°C. The number of cycles and/or <lb/>the annealing temperature was changed as necessary, to <lb/>optimize the PCR conditions for each locus. <lb/>A total of 12 microsatellite loci were used for this study. <lb/>Locus Efr09J was originally isolated from E. f. rufus [34]. <lb/>We performed the PCR of that locus with 60°C annealing <lb/>and 25 cycles. To amplify locus Lc8, which was developed <lb/>for L. catta [35], 55°C annealing temperature and 35 <lb/>cycles were used. The other 10 loci were amplified using <lb/>the PCR conditions described in [36]. PCR products were <lb/>run on an ABI PRISM 377XL or 3730 automated DNA <lb/>sequencer. Allele sizes were determined with GeneScan <lb/>software (Applied Biosystems). For all loci, samples of 30 <lb/>offspring and their known pairs of parents as well as 15 <lb/>offspring with one available parent from the captive mon-<lb/>goose lemur colony were genotyped, allowing testing for <lb/>Mendelian inheritance. <lb/> Location of Anjamena (red cross) where E. mongoz and E. ful-<lb/>vus hybridize <lb/> Figure 1 <lb/>Location of Anjamena (red cross) where E. mongoz <lb/> and E. fulvus hybridize. Two additional sample locations <lb/>(Anadabomandry and Ampijoroa) and one fossil site (Anjo-<lb/>hibe) are labelled in red. Green areas are forests. The inset <lb/>shows the distribution of E. mongoz (blue border), E. f. rufus <lb/> (yellow) and other E. fulvus subspecies (red). <lb/> Canale de Moçambique <lb/> 20 km <lb/>0 <lb/> Lac Kinkony <lb/> Katsepy <lb/>Namakia <lb/> Mahajanga <lb/> Mitsinjo <lb/> ANJAMENA <lb/> Marovoay <lb/> Ampijoroa <lb/> A n k a r a f a n t s i k a <lb/> Bekipa <lb/> B e ts ib o k a <lb/> M a h a v a v y <lb/> M ah aj am ba <lb/> A <lb/> n <lb/> o <lb/> m <lb/> a <lb/> v <lb/> o <lb/> Anjohibe <lb/> Anadabomandry <lb/> Table 1: Samples available from mongoose and brown lemurs <lb/> Taxon <lb/>Location <lb/># Samples <lb/> Eulemur mongoz Anjamena <lb/>38 <lb/>Anadabomandry <lb/>4 <lb/>Ampijoroa <lb/>2 <lb/>Madagascar (unknown) <lb/>1 <lb/>Captivity <lb/>63 <lb/> E. fulvus rufus <lb/> Anjamena <lb/>8 <lb/>Anadabomandry <lb/>2 <lb/>Other <lb/>12 <lb/> E. f. fulvus <lb/> Various zoos/locations <lb/>14 <lb/> E. f. albifrons <lb/> Various zoos/locations <lb/>10 <lb/> E. f. sanfordi <lb/> Tsimbazaza Zoo <lb/>3 <lb/> E. f. collaris <lb/> Banham Zoo, pet in Fort Dauphin <lb/>2 <lb/> E. f. albocollaris <lb/> Strasbourg, Tsimbazaza Zoo <lb/> 4 <lb/>
			
			 <note place="headnote">BMC Evolutionary Biology 2009, 9:32 <lb/></note>  
			 
			 <note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2148/9/32 <lb/></note> 
			 
			 <page>Page 4 of 13 <lb/></page> 
			 
			 <note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>  
			 
			 The 3&apos; end of the tRNA Thr gene, the complete tRNA Pro gene <lb/>and the 5&apos; end of the control region (D-loop), as well as <lb/>part of the NADH-dehydrogenase subunit 4 (ND4) gene <lb/>were amplified and sequenced, using the primers listed in <lb/>Table 2. The PCR products were electrophoresed in 2% <lb/>agarose gels to estimate template concentration. The <lb/>sequencing reactions were carried out with the BigDye <lb/>Terminator Cycle Sequencing Ready Reaction Kit <lb/>(Applied Biosystems), using 1 μl of terminator mix and 2 <lb/> μl of 5× buffer for a 9 μl reaction. The completed sequenc-<lb/>ing reactions were cleaned of excess dyes with ethanol pre-<lb/>cipitation before being run on an automated DNA <lb/>sequencer. All templates were sequenced in their entirety <lb/>for both strands. The sequencing data was aligned with <lb/>Sequencher™ 4.2.2 (Gene Codes Corporation). <lb/> Statistical analyses <lb/> For microsatellite data, CERVUS 3.0.3 [37] was used to <lb/>calculate observed (H O ) and expected (H E ) heterozygosi-<lb/>ties, frequency estimates for null alleles and to test for <lb/>deviations from the Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium. Addi-<lb/>tionally, non-exclusion probabilities for first and second <lb/>parents on the 12 autosomal microsatellite loci and the <lb/>probability for two random individuals having the same <lb/>genotype were determined with CERVUS. GENEPOP <lb/>4.0.6 [38] was used to test for genotypic linkage disequi-<lb/>librium in the wild mongoose lemurs at Anjamena. Bon-<lb/>ferroni correction was applied to alpha to adjust for <lb/>multiple testing of 12 loci. The population genetic struc-<lb/>ture was inferred by calculating F is , F st and R st estimates in <lb/>GENEPOP and by performing an analysis of molecular <lb/>variance (AMOVA) in Arlequin 3.11 [39]. Principal com-<lb/>ponent analysis of the multilocus genotypes was carried <lb/>out with GENETIX 4.05 [40]. STRUCTURE 2.2.2 [41] was <lb/>used to infer the genetic structure of the populations <lb/>based on microsatellite loci. The number K of populations <lb/>was estimated using a burn-in period of 10,000 and <lb/>100,000 MCMC replicates, applying the admixture model <lb/>and independent or correlated allele frequencies. The esti-<lb/>mated membership coefficients Q for each individual in <lb/>each cluster was calculated by STRUCTURE, in order to <lb/>assign the individual to one or, if admixed, to several clus-<lb/>ters. <lb/>The aligned mtDNA sequences were analysed with PAUP <lb/>4.0b10 [42] using maximum parsimony (2500 random <lb/>addition heuristic search) and neighbor-joining (Kimura <lb/>2-parameter distances) methods. Gaps were considered as <lb/>a fifth character state in parsimony analyses, whereas in <lb/>neighbor-joining analyses they were treated as missing <lb/>data. Bootstrap analyses of 1000 replicates (10 random <lb/>addition heuristic searches each) for maximum parsi-<lb/>mony and 2500 replicates for neighbor-joining were per-<lb/>formed to examine the relative support of each <lb/>relationship in the resultant topologies. Two Lemur catta <lb/> sequences were used as the outgroup. <lb/> Results <lb/> Microsatellite variation <lb/> Overall, the multilocus panel employed was found to be <lb/>very informative. The probability that two individuals <lb/>cannot be differentiated is 3.08E-9 for E. mongoz and <lb/>3.64E-14 for E. fulvus. With one exception, all individuals <lb/>have unique multilocus genotypes. One adult mongoose <lb/>lemur male from Anjamena sampled in 1995 has exactly <lb/>the same genotype as a male from 1997. Because none of <lb/>the wild animals sampled were marked permanently, it is <lb/>likely that the same male was captured twice. Therefore, <lb/>one of the two samples was removed from the data set. <lb/>Variation among mongoose and brown lemurs for the 12 <lb/>microsatellite loci is summarized in Table 3. There is no <lb/>evidence for linkage disequilibrium between loci in the <lb/>mongoose lemur population at Anjamena. When assess-<lb/>ing the parent-offspring relationships in the captive mon-<lb/>goose lemur population with known pedigrees, all alleles <lb/>are found to segregate with Mendelian expectations. <lb/>Allelic diversity ranges from 3 to 9 alleles per locus (mean <lb/>= 5.9 ± 1.8 SE) in mongoose lemurs and from 3 to 17 (9.0 <lb/>± 3.9) in brown lemurs. Mongoose lemurs at Anjamena <lb/>have observed heterozygosities of 0.16 to 0.89 (0.50 ± <lb/>0.20) per locus, which are slightly higher than expected <lb/>heterozygosities (Table 3). In the mongoose lemur popu-<lb/>lation at Anjamena, no locus differs significantly from <lb/>Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium. The other samples were not <lb/>tested for the Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium because they <lb/>are either from captivity (no random mating) or from dif-<lb/> Table 2: Forward (F) and reverse (R) primers used to amplify (A) and sequence (S) the two mtDNA fragments <lb/> Primer <lb/>Sequence 5&apos;-3&apos; <lb/>Map position* <lb/>F/R <lb/>A <lb/>S <lb/> 283 <lb/> tacactggtcttgtaaacc <lb/>15908–15926 <lb/>F <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>LemurDLF1 <lb/>aagcctagtccatacgcatataagc <lb/>16181–16205 <lb/>F <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>LemurDLR2 <lb/>ggtagattaagctacgatc <lb/>16303–16321 <lb/>R <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>LemurDLR4 <lb/>atctcYtatgtccttcaagcat <lb/>219–240 <lb/>R <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>282 <lb/>aaggctaggaccaaacct <lb/>651–668 <lb/>R <lb/>x <lb/>ND4F <lb/>taggaggataYggRataatacg <lb/>11472–11493 <lb/>F <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>ND4R <lb/>atagatattagggtattttctcg <lb/>12053–12075 <lb/>R <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>* Relative to human mtDNA [GenBank: V00662] <lb/> 
			 
			 <note place="headnote">BMC Evolutionary Biology 2009, 9:32 <lb/></note> 
			 
			 <note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2148/9/32 <lb/></note>
			 
			 <page>Page 5 of 13 <lb/></page> 
			 
			 <note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note> 
			 
			 ferent subspecies (different populations). All loci have <lb/>low inbreeding coefficients (-0.17&lt;F is &lt; 0.40, Table 3). <lb/>With one exception, estimates of null allele frequencies <lb/>range from -0.11 to 0.05 for each locus, indicating <lb/>absence of null alleles. Locus Em5 has an estimated null <lb/>allele frequency of 0.24. However, since the locus is in <lb/>Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium and the alleles are inherited <lb/>in Mendelian fashion when testing the 45 offspring with <lb/>known parents, the presence of a null allele is unlikely to <lb/>be the reason for this result. We therefore retained this <lb/>locus for further data analyses. <lb/> Species differentiation and hybrids <lb/> Analysis of molecular variance applied to the two Eulemur <lb/> species showed 23.21% between-species variability <lb/>(AMOVA, P &lt; 0.0001), indicating that 76.79% of the <lb/>genetic variation was found within each species. Genetic <lb/>differentiation between the two species is relatively high <lb/>(F st = 0.232, R st = 0.636) and significant at each locus <lb/>(exact G test, P = 0). <lb/>Principal component analysis (PCA) clearly separates <lb/>brown lemurs from mongoose lemurs (left and right on <lb/>Figure 2). Within E. mongoz, the wild and captive popula-<lb/>tions are grouped apart (top and bottom in Figure 2) with <lb/>little overlap. There are no obvious subgroups among <lb/>brown lemurs. Two mongoose lemurs (JP167 and JP184) <lb/>are intermediate between E. mongoz and E. fulvus (Figure <lb/>2). <lb/>We used STRUCTURE on the microsatellite data to iden-<lb/>tify distinct genetic populations, assign individuals to <lb/>populations, and identify admixed individuals. When <lb/>assuming two populations (K = 2), all 162 samples are <lb/>correctly assigned to their species (Figure 3). Most mon-<lb/>goose lemurs clearly fall into cluster 1 with the proportion <lb/>of membership Q1 ranging from 0.833 to 0.998 (0.994 ± <lb/>0.018). Only two mongoose lemurs from Anjamena <lb/>(JP167 and JP184) split between cluster 1 (Q1 = 0.632 <lb/>and 0.539) and cluster 2 (Q2 = 0.368 and 0.461). All 55 <lb/>brown lemurs are grouped into cluster 2, with Q2 ranging <lb/>from 0.814 to 0.998 (0.983 ± 0.035). <lb/>When K is increased from 2 up to 16, the samples are <lb/>divided into more clusters, with K = 12 showing the high-<lb/>est probability. The different clusters mainly represent <lb/>subspecies in E. fulvus or populations/groups in mon-<lb/>goose lemurs (data not shown). However, while individ-<lb/>uals might be admixed between populations or <lb/>subspecies of the same species, there is no admixture of <lb/>the two species (apart from JP167 and JP184). These tests <lb/>confirm the clear separation of the two species and the <lb/>intermediate positioning of JP167 and JP184. <lb/>We also ran analyses using only the 42 mongoose and <lb/>brown lemurs from Anjamena. When assuming K = 2 <lb/>populations, most lemurs are clearly assigned to the cor-<lb/>rect species (Q1 = 0.996 ± 0.006 in most E. mongoz and Q2 <lb/>= 0.995 ± 0.004 in all E. fulvus). There are 3 mongoose <lb/>lemurs that are split between the two clusters. As in the <lb/>previous analyses, the two individuals JP167 and JP184 <lb/>have the highest probabilities to be admixed (Q1/Q2 = <lb/>0.527/0.473 and 0.714//0.286). In addition, a third mon-<lb/>goose lemur (JP152) has a slightly increased proportion <lb/>of membership for cluster 2 (Q2 = 0.192). When increas-<lb/>ing K, no further subdivision at Anjamena is possible. <lb/> Introgression of microsatellite alleles in mongoose lemurs <lb/> A total of 71 alleles are found at the 12 loci in the 107 <lb/>mongoose lemurs studied. The 37 E. mongoz at Anjamena <lb/> Table 3: Characteristics* of the 12 microsatellite loci used in E. mongoz and E. fulvus <lb/> Locus <lb/> E. mongoz at Anjamena <lb/> E. mongoz <lb/>E. fulvus <lb/> N I <lb/> N A <lb/> H O <lb/> H E <lb/> F is <lb/> SR <lb/>N I <lb/> N A <lb/> SR <lb/>N I <lb/> N A <lb/> Em1 <lb/> 37 <lb/>5 <lb/>0.892 <lb/>0.767 <lb/>-0.165 <lb/>161–175 <lb/>107 <lb/>8 <lb/>161–199 <lb/>53 <lb/>17 <lb/>Em2 <lb/>37 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.162 <lb/>0.153 <lb/>-0.061 <lb/>156–164 <lb/>107 <lb/>4 <lb/>150–176 <lb/>54 <lb/>11 <lb/>Em4 <lb/>37 <lb/>4 <lb/>0.568 <lb/>0.504 <lb/>-0.129 <lb/>146–158 <lb/>107 <lb/>5 <lb/>142–160 <lb/>55 <lb/>8 <lb/>Em5 <lb/>37 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.270 <lb/>0.444 <lb/>0.395 <lb/>172–176 <lb/>107 <lb/>3 <lb/>170–180 <lb/>55 <lb/>6 <lb/>Em7 <lb/>37 <lb/>6 <lb/>0.649 <lb/>0.729 <lb/>0.112 <lb/>129–147 <lb/>107 <lb/>7 <lb/>129–151 <lb/>55 <lb/>9 <lb/>Em8 <lb/>37 <lb/>6 <lb/>0.703 <lb/>0.719 <lb/>0.023 <lb/>159–177 <lb/>107 <lb/>9 <lb/>143–175 <lb/>55 <lb/>12 <lb/>Em9 <lb/>37 <lb/>4 <lb/>0.432 <lb/>0.437 <lb/>0.011 <lb/>171–183 <lb/>106 <lb/>7 <lb/>169–197 <lb/>53 <lb/>13 <lb/>Em11 <lb/>37 <lb/>4 <lb/>0.541 <lb/>0.534 <lb/>-0.013 <lb/>250–259 <lb/>107 <lb/>6 <lb/>247–257 <lb/>55 <lb/>6 <lb/>Em15 <lb/>37 <lb/>4 <lb/>0.595 <lb/>0.652 <lb/>0.089 <lb/>206–224 <lb/>107 <lb/>6 <lb/>204–212 <lb/>55 <lb/>3 <lb/>Lc1 <lb/>37 <lb/>5 <lb/>0.757 <lb/>0.672 <lb/>-0.129 <lb/>86–98 <lb/>107 <lb/>5 <lb/>90–100 <lb/>55 <lb/>6 <lb/>Lc8 <lb/>35 <lb/>5 <lb/>0.429 <lb/>0.393 <lb/>-0.091 <lb/>221–231 <lb/>104 <lb/>7 <lb/>217–237 <lb/>50 <lb/>11 <lb/>Efr09 <lb/>37 <lb/>4 <lb/>0.622 <lb/>0.542 <lb/>-0.150 <lb/>99–105 <lb/>107 <lb/>4 <lb/>95–107 <lb/>51 <lb/>6 <lb/>Mean <lb/>36.8 <lb/>4.3 <lb/>0.552 <lb/>0.545 <lb/>-0.009 <lb/>106.7 <lb/>5.9 <lb/>53.8 <lb/>9.0 <lb/>* N I = number of individuals genotyped; N A = number of alleles found; H O = observed heterozygosity; H E = expected heterozygosity; F is = <lb/>inbreeding coefficient; SR = size range of alleles in base positions <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">BMC Evolutionary Biology 2009, 9:32 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2148/9/32 <lb/></note>
			
			<page>Page 6 of 13 <lb/></page> 
			
			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note> 
			
			have 53 different alleles, of which 10 alleles are not found <lb/>in any other mongoose lemur outside Anjamena. Assum-<lb/>ing that hybridization is restricted to Anjamena, these 10 <lb/>private alleles for Anjamena are potential candidates for <lb/>introgression into the mongoose lemur gene pool by <lb/>hybridization with brown lemurs. However, one allele is <lb/>not observed in any brown lemur, which excludes it from <lb/>being of E. fulvus origin. Details of the remaining 9 alleles <lb/>are given in Table 4. <lb/>Five of the possibly introgressed alleles are very common <lb/>(&gt;20%) in E. f. rufus at Anjamena, which supports their <lb/>origin in brown lemurs. Three alleles are found only once <lb/>or twice among the 8 Anjamena brown lemurs (6–13%), <lb/>however, since they are very rare in mongoose lemurs <lb/>(each allele only found once), they might still be of brown <lb/>lemur origin. One mongoose lemur at Anjamena has an <lb/>allele (Lc8–223), not found in any other mongoose lemur <lb/>and also not in the brown lemurs at Anjamena. Only one <lb/> E. f. fulvus has that same allele. <lb/>The two hybrid mongoose lemurs (JP167 and JP184) <lb/>identified from PCA/STRUCTURE analyses have 4 puta-<lb/>tive introgressed alleles each. These two animals have 7 <lb/>putative introgressed alleles found only once or twice in <lb/>the mongoose lemurs at Anjamena (Table 4). Another 6 <lb/>mongoose lemurs at Anjamena have one or both of the <lb/>remaining 2 possibly introgressed alleles. One allele (Lc1– <lb/>98) occurs in 3 mongoose lemurs and with a frequency of <lb/>31% is well represented among the brown lemurs in Anja-<lb/>mena. The other allele (Lc8–221) is found 5 times in <lb/>mongoose lemurs and has an allele frequency of 21% in <lb/> E. f. rufus. <lb/> Parentage of hybrids <lb/> At the time of our field study, JP167 was still a juvenile <lb/>female without offspring. The other hybrid JP184 was an <lb/>adult female. We were able to collect samples from the <lb/>adult male and the juvenile of her social group. In parent-<lb/>age testing using microsatellites, neither the adult male <lb/>nor the hybrid female JP184 are excluded as parents of the <lb/>juvenile JP152. With a high probability (99.0% if accept-<lb/>ing the adult male as the father, 91.0% if only considering <lb/>the female), this makes JP184 the mother of the juvenile. <lb/> Introgressed microsatellite alleles in brown lemurs <lb/> The 13 brown lemurs in the E. f. rufus subspecies clade, <lb/>which includes the animals from Anjamena (see Figure 4, <lb/>the other 9 E. f. rufus samples mentioned in Table 1 form <lb/>another subspecies clade), have 60 different alleles. Seven <lb/>alleles are unique to the 8 brown lemurs at Anjamena and <lb/>also present in the mongoose lemur gene pool at Anja-<lb/>mena. Two of these alleles are only found in mongoose <lb/>and brown lemurs at Anjamena and hence could originate <lb/>from either species (Em4–146 and Lc8–221, Table 4). <lb/>Based on their low frequency in mongoose lemurs and <lb/>high frequency in brown lemurs they are more likely to be <lb/>of brown lemur origin. This leaves 5 alleles, which might <lb/>have been introduced into the brown lemur gene pool by <lb/>hybridization (Table 4). With one exception, each brown <lb/>lemur has 1 to 5 of these possibly introgressed alleles in <lb/>its haplotype (2.57 ± 1.51). Due to the very low sample <lb/>size for E. f. rufus (N = 13), this identification of putatively <lb/>introgressed alleles is only preliminary. <lb/> mtDNA results <lb/> We sequenced two fragments of the mtDNA genome for <lb/>107 mongoose lemurs and 55 brown lemurs, as well as 12 <lb/>individuals from the other three Eulemur species and 2 <lb/> Lemur catta. The aligned nucleotide sequences span a total <lb/>of 1463 base positions (bp). The analysed data set consists <lb/>of 31 bp of tRNA Thr , 66 bp of tRNA Pro , 804 bp of D-loop <lb/>and 559 bp of ND4. Details on the number of haplotypes <lb/>found with D-loop data, ND4 data and the combined <lb/>data set in animals at Anjamena or across the species <lb/>range are given in Table 5. A total of 36 variable positions <lb/>are present among mongoose lemurs, while brown <lb/>lemurs exhibit 178 variable sites (Table 5). Nucleotide <lb/>divergence between the two species ranges from 0.054 to <lb/>0.077 (0.063 ± 0.004 Tamura-Nei distance). Some of the <lb/>ND4 sequences have been published previously [27,43]. <lb/>New sequences were deposited on GenBank [D-loop: <lb/>EU333172–EU333247, ND4: EU333248–EU333274, see <lb/>also Additional file 1]. <lb/>There are 5 mtDNA haplotypes (MA-ME) in the mon-<lb/>goose lemur population at Anjamena. In addition, one <lb/>mongoose lemur exhibits the mtDNA haplotype of a <lb/>brown lemur. The brown lemurs at Anjamena have 3 hap-<lb/>lotypes (FA, FB, FC). One of these (FA), is the haplotype <lb/>also observed in the mongoose lemur. There are 4 E. fulvus <lb/> at Anjamena with the E. mongoz haplotype MF, which is <lb/>not found in any mongoose lemur at Anjamena. While <lb/>the haplotypes MA-ME differ from each other by 1 or 2 bp, <lb/>haplotype MF is 4–5 bp different from the other haplo-<lb/>types found among mongoose lemurs in Anjamena. The 3 <lb/> E. fulvus haplotypes at Anjamena differ from each other by <lb/>1 or 2 bp. <lb/>Among all 107 mongoose lemurs, 10 haplotypes (MA-<lb/>MK) are found. The most common (57%) haplotype, MI, <lb/>is present in 61 E. mongoz kept in various zoos. Two ani-<lb/>mals in captivity each have a unique haplotype (MJ and <lb/>MK). The 3 haplotypes found in captivity differ from each <lb/>other by only 1 or 2 bp. The two animals at Ampijoroa <lb/>have haplotype MH and the 4 mongoose lemurs from <lb/>Anadabomandry have haplotype MG. <lb/>In the phylogenetic analyses, four distinct clades of mon-<lb/>goose lemurs can be recognized (Figure 4). One clade con-<lb/>

			<note place="headnote">BMC Evolutionary Biology 2009, 9:32 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2148/9/32 <lb/></note>
			
			<page>Page 7 of 13 <lb/></page> 
			
			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>
			
			tains the animals from Anjamena, including the <lb/>haplotype found in the 4 brown lemurs at Anjamena. The <lb/>3 haplotypes from the captive mongoose lemurs form a <lb/>second clade while the haplotypes from Ampijoroa and <lb/>Anadabomandry each form a separate clade. Haplotypes <lb/>between those 4 clades differ from each other at 12 to 21 <lb/>bp (17.6 ± 3.2). <lb/>Among brown lemurs, a total of 34 haplotypes are found. <lb/>Phylogenetic analyses group them into 6 clades (Figure <lb/>4). Each of these subspecies clades gets 93 – 100% boot-<lb/>strap support in neighbor-joining and maximum parsi-<lb/>mony analyses (Figure 4). The clade containing the brown <lb/>lemurs from Anjamena includes 5 additional animals, <lb/>which add 4 more haplotypes to this clade: Two haplo-<lb/>types FD and FE are present at Anadabomandry, which <lb/>differ from each other by 5 bp. One zoo animal of <lb/>unknown origin also exhibits haplotype FD. The remain-<lb/>ing 2 haplotypes are found in a zoo animal of unknown <lb/>origin (FF) and in a red-fronted brown lemur from <lb/>Maintirano, which lies further south from Anjamena on <lb/>the western coast of Madagascar (FG). <lb/> Discussion <lb/> F1 hybrids in the mongoose lemur population <lb/> Principal component analysis positions two animals <lb/>between E. mongoz and E. fulvus (Figure 2) and admixture <lb/>analyses reveal an admixed genotype for the same two <lb/>individuals (Figure 3). These two animals are most likely <lb/>F1 hybrids. Whereas one allele per locus and, hence, 12 <lb/>introgressed alleles would be expected in an F1 hybrid, we <lb/>observed only 4. The 8 brown lemurs from Anjamena <lb/>have a total of 37 different alleles in their genotypes, of <lb/>which 16 alleles are shared with the mongoose lemurs at <lb/>Anjamena. Therefore, only 21 alleles are unique to E. ful-<lb/>vus and are identifiable as introgressed in a hybrid. Taking <lb/>the allele frequencies into account, a hybrid would inherit <lb/>from its brown lemur parent on average 5.03 alleles which <lb/>are exclusive to brown lemurs and 6.97 alleles which are <lb/>shared between E. mongoz and E. fulvus, which is consist-<lb/>ent with the pattern found. <lb/>JP167 is a juvenile female, which is part of a group con-<lb/>sisting of 3 animals. Fur coloration of JP167 is clearly <lb/>intermediate between brown lemur and mongoose lemur <lb/>females. This led us to suspect in the field, that she might <lb/>be a hybrid. The two other group members are an adult <lb/>male and an adult female. We were only able to capture <lb/>the adult female, that exhibited normal mongoose lemur <lb/>fur coloration. She has the mtDNA haplotype of a regular <lb/>mongoose lemur and has no putative introgressed alleles. <lb/>Apart from the mtDNA, this adult female is also excluded <lb/>at 2 microsatellite loci from being the mother of JP167. <lb/>The second mongoose lemur of hybrid origin is an adult <lb/>female (JP184). She is a member of a small social group, <lb/>including herself, an adult male, subadult female and <lb/>juvenile male. The adult male has the normal fur colora-<lb/>tion of a mongoose lemur male. The juvenile (JP152), like <lb/>JP184 exhibits a mixture of fur colours from E. mongoz and <lb/> E. fulvus. Parentage testing indicates that the adult hybrid <lb/>female JP184 is most likely (&gt;90%) the mother of the <lb/>juvenile. The genotype of the juvenile contains none of <lb/>the 4 putative introgressed alleles from the mother. How-<lb/>ever, admixture analyses of the lemurs at Anjamena reveal <lb/>a proportion of brown lemur ancestry (Q2 = 0.192) in its <lb/>genotype that is consistent with an F2. <lb/> Descendants of hybrids in the mongoose lemur population <lb/> The 6 mongoose lemurs with one or two putative intro-<lb/>gressed alleles might be descendants of a hybrid crossing. <lb/>Neither PCA nor admixture analyses were able to differen-<lb/>tiate them from other mongoose lemurs. Consistent with <lb/> Principal component analysis of individual E. mongoz and E. <lb/>fulvus genotypes <lb/> Figure 2 <lb/>Principal component analysis of individual E. mongoz <lb/> and E. fulvus genotypes. First and second axes represent <lb/>the first two factorial components. The two hybrids (JP167 <lb/>and JP184) are specially marked. <lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">BMC Evolutionary Biology 2009, 9:32 <lb/></note> 
			
			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2148/9/32 <lb/></note> 
			
			<page>Page 8 of 13 <lb/></page> 
			
			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>  
			
			this, their coat coloration was normal for mongoose <lb/>lemurs and so they could not be F1s, and are unlikely to <lb/>be F2s, since the confirmed offspring of an F1 hybrid and <lb/>a mongoose lemur (JP152) has intermediate coat colour. <lb/>If hybridization had occurred, a single event could have <lb/>accounted for the allele distribution. Further data would <lb/>be required to assess whether these alleles truly represent <lb/>a signature of past introgression events, and to estimate <lb/>the rate of introgression. <lb/> Conclusions on hybrid crossings in the mongoose lemur <lb/>population <lb/> We found genetic evidence for a minimum of 2 hybridiza-<lb/>tion events in mongoose lemurs of Anjamena. Two hybrid <lb/>crossings were very recent (F1). In addition, one of the F1 <lb/>hybrids had an offspring where paternity could be geneti-<lb/>cally confirmed. Therefore, hybridization between mon-<lb/>goose and brown lemurs occurs in the wild and yields <lb/>fertile offspring, which can successfully backcross with <lb/>mongoose lemurs. A third potential hybrid crossing might <lb/>have happened a few generations ago, which would again <lb/>show the fertility of the hybrids. <lb/>One of the F1 hybrids has the mtDNA haplotype of a <lb/>brown lemur and the other of a mongoose lemur. Hybrid <lb/>crossings can therefore occur between E. mongoz females <lb/>and E. fulvus males as well as between E. mongoz males and <lb/> E. fulvus females. <lb/> Introgression into the brown lemur population <lb/> Due to the small sample size (N = 8) and also not know-<lb/>ing the familial relationships among the members of each <lb/>social group (containing several males and females), no <lb/>detailed information on hybrid crossings can be obtained <lb/>for the brown lemurs at Anjamena. However, half of the <lb/>brown lemurs sampled have an E. mongoz mtDNA haplo-<lb/>type. As all 4 animals have the same haplotype MF, the <lb/>presence of that haplotype could be the consequence of a <lb/>single hybrid crossing. Interestingly, haplotype MF is not <lb/>found in any of the 35 mongoose lemurs sampled at Anja-<lb/>mena and is the most divergent of the 5 E. mongoz haplo-<lb/>types found there (Figure 4). These two factors make it <lb/>likely that the hybrid crossing from which haplotype MF <lb/>is derived occurred in the past, with the mongoose lemurs <lb/>at Anjamena subsequently losing haplotype MF due to <lb/>genetic drift. Alternatively, it could have occurred between <lb/>a brown lemur male and a mongoose lemur female <lb/>located some distance from Anjamena. <lb/>Seven of the eight brown lemur genotypes from Anjamena <lb/>contain putative introgressed microsatellite alleles. The <lb/>only brown lemur without any introgressed alleles has the <lb/>mtDNA genotype of E. mongoz. The samples were col-<lb/>lected from animals living in 7 different social groups at <lb/>Anjamena. Principal component analysis failed to group <lb/>the 8 animals closely together (Figure 2). Therefore, close <lb/>familial relationships are no explanation for the high <lb/>presence of introgressed alleles among these brown <lb/>lemurs. Fur coloration of all 8 animals appeared to be nor-<lb/>mal for red-fronted brown lemurs, excluding them from <lb/>being F1 or F2 hybrids. However, a larger sample from <lb/>brown lemurs at Anjamena and across the subspecies <lb/>range is needed to confirm this result. Some of the current <lb/>putative introgressed alleles might be found in other E. f. <lb/>rufus outside Anjamena, making an origin in E. mongoz <lb/> unlikely, while a more detailed study on the brown <lb/>lemurs at Anjamena might reveal new introgressed alleles. <lb/> Evolutionary consequences <lb/> Some time after the five species of Eulemur radiated across <lb/>Madagascar, a brown lemur radiation started, most likely <lb/>in the South, where E. f. albocollaris and E. f. collaris occur. <lb/>This is the only area where brown lemurs do not overlap <lb/>with another Eulemur species. Brown lemurs then radiated <lb/>back across the island to the North [43], becoming sym-<lb/>patric with the other 4 Eulemur species. However, no <lb/>hybrids are reported between the brown lemurs and sym-<lb/>patric E. rubriventer in the East, E. coronatus in the North, <lb/>or E. macaco in the Northwest. E mongoz is sympatric with <lb/> E. f. fulvus and E. f. rufus in the West, but there also seems <lb/>to be no hybridization between E. mongoz and E. f. fulvus. <lb/> Only E. f. rufus and E. mongoz at Anjamena are known to <lb/>hybridize. <lb/>A possible explanation for this hybridization is that one <lb/>species only recently expanded its range and there were no <lb/>reproductive barriers in place between the two newly <lb/>overlapping taxa. During the radiation of brown lemurs <lb/>the Betsiboka river formed a barrier dividing E. fulvus pop-<lb/> Admixture analysis of 162 mongoose and brown lemurs <lb/> Figure 3 <lb/>Admixture analysis of 162 mongoose and brown <lb/>lemurs. Each individual is represented by a single vertical <lb/>line broken into K = 2 segments, with lengths proportional <lb/>to the estimated membership in each cluster (Q1 for E. mon-<lb/>goz and Q2 for E. fulvus). The two hybrids (JP167 and JP184) <lb/>are marked with *. <lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">BMC Evolutionary Biology 2009, 9:32 <lb/></note>  
			
			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2148/9/32 <lb/></note> 
			
			<page>Page 9 of 13 <lb/></page> 
			
			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>  
			
			ulations, resulting in it being the northern limit of E. f. <lb/>rufus, with E. f. fulvus subspecies being formed across the <lb/>river (see also Figure 1). In contrast, E. mongoz is one of the <lb/>few lemur taxa for which the Betsiboka river is not a taxo-<lb/>nomic boundary [44]. The current mongoose lemur range <lb/>extends a little southwest of Anjamena, across the Maha-<lb/>vavy river. Our mtDNA sequence data shows (Figure 4) <lb/>that the mongoose lemurs at Anjamena are substantially <lb/>different from those at Ampijoroa (14–15 bp out of 1463 <lb/>bp), but do not differ to the extent seen in the two brown <lb/>lemur subspecies (44–46 bp). This implies that the Betsi-<lb/>boka river serves as a geographic boundary in both taxa, <lb/>but was crossed by E. mongoz later. The other option <lb/>would be that E. f. rufus, coming from the southwest, only <lb/>recently crossed the Mahavavy river. However, genetic dis-<lb/>tances between animals on the west (Anadabomandry) <lb/>and east (Anjamena) side of this river are higher for E. f. <lb/>rufus (21–24 bp) than for E. mongoz (12–15 bp). This <lb/>again indicates that E. mongoz expanded its range more <lb/>recently than E. f. rufus. <lb/> A cladistic biogeographic analysis on the extant lemur dis-<lb/>tribution in western Madagascar suggests that E. mongoz <lb/> either had a wide distribution in the past and then disap-<lb/>peared from large parts of its former range, or dispersed <lb/>across otherwise efficient geographical barriers [45]. In <lb/>1939, Lamberton found a subfossil femur of E. mongoz at <lb/>Ampasambazimba [46], which lies in the central western <lb/>highlands of Madagascar, where the Betsiboka and Maha-<lb/>vavy rivers originate. More subfossil mongoose lemur <lb/>remains were found near the coast at Anjohibe [46], to the <lb/>east of the Betsiboka river (Figure 1). There are two possi-<lb/>ble scenarios, which would explain the unusual current <lb/>mongoose lemur distribution [45], the fossil evidence <lb/>thus far available [46] and the low genetic differentiation <lb/>across the Betsiboka and Mahavavy rivers in E. mongoz <lb/> (this study). One is, that mongoose lemurs had a large dis-<lb/>tribution in the past with regular gene flow across the <lb/>range. Only once they lost their range in central Madagas-<lb/>car relatively recently, was gene flow no longer possible <lb/>across the range because the Betsiboka and Mahavay rivers <lb/>became geographical barriers. The other option is, that in <lb/>the past mongoose lemurs occurred only to the east of the <lb/>Betsiboka river all the way up to central highlands and <lb/>only later expanded their range towards the coast on the <lb/>west side of the Betsiboka and Mahavavy rivers, while dis-<lb/>appearing from central Madagascar. In the first scenario <lb/>they were sympatric with E. f. fulvus and E. f. rufus for a <lb/>long time, while in the second scenario they only became <lb/>sympatric with E. f. rufus relatively recently. <lb/>The influx of a new species into a novel ecosystem can <lb/>result in hybridization between the new species (in this <lb/>case E. mongoz) and the related native species (E. fulvus). <lb/> Where few reproductive barriers to gene flow exist, this <lb/>frequently leads to the rapid introgression of genetic and <lb/>phenotypic characters from one species into another [47]. <lb/>In captivity, crosses between various E. fulvus subspecies <lb/>resulted in fertile offspring [48]. Among captive Eulemur <lb/> species, crossbreeding between E. macaco and E. fulvus <lb/> Table 4: Details on 15 microsatellite alleles, which might originate from the other species <lb/> E. mongoz <lb/>E. fulvus <lb/> Origin <lb/>Locus <lb/>Allele <lb/>N a <lb/> F b <lb/> Other c <lb/> N a <lb/> F b <lb/> Other c <lb/> Fulvus <lb/> Em11 <lb/> 251 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>+ <lb/>Em11 <lb/>253 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>13 <lb/>0.81 <lb/>+ <lb/>Em2 <lb/>164 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>+ <lb/>Em7 <lb/>129 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>+ <lb/>Lc8 <lb/>223 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>Em15 <lb/>206 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>14 <lb/>0.88 <lb/>+ <lb/>Lc1 <lb/>98 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>5 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>+ <lb/> Fulvus  d <lb/> Em4 <lb/>146 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>7 <lb/>0.44 <lb/>+ <lb/>Lc8 <lb/>221 <lb/>5 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>+ <lb/> Mongoz <lb/> Em1 <lb/>163 <lb/>12 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>+ <lb/>9 <lb/>0.64 <lb/>Em1 <lb/>167 <lb/>23 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>+ <lb/>2 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>+ <lb/>Em8 <lb/>159 <lb/>19 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>+ <lb/>2 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>+ <lb/>Em9 <lb/>179 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>+ <lb/>3 <lb/>0.19 <lb/>+ <lb/>L c 1 <lb/>9 4 <lb/>1 9 <lb/>0 . 2 4 <lb/>+ <lb/>2 <lb/>0 . 1 3 <lb/>+ <lb/> a Number of alleles found at Anjamena <lb/> b Allele frequency at Anjamena <lb/> c + indicates that the allele is also found in individuals outside Anjamena <lb/> d Those two alleles are hybrid candidates for both taxa. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">BMC Evolutionary Biology 2009, 9:32 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2148/9/32 <lb/></note>
			
			<page>Page 10 of 13 <lb/></page> 
			
			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note> 
			
			Neighbor-joining phylogram of 176 lemurs sequenced for a D-loop and ND4 fragment of the mtDNA genome <lb/> Figure 4 <lb/>Neighbor-joining phylogram of 176 lemurs sequenced for a D-loop and ND4 fragment of the mtDNA genome. <lb/> Clades containing animals with identical haplotypes were lumped together into one branch, providing the number of united <lb/>individuals behind the taxon name. The two haplotypes of E. mongoz and E. fulvus, which were also found in the other species, <lb/>are marked with an asterisk (*). Bootstrap values obtained with neighbor-joining (above nodes) and maximum parsimony <lb/>(below nodes) analyses are provided at relevant branches. &quot;ns&quot; means that the maximum parsimony tree topology did not <lb/>show that node. <lb/> E.f. albocollaris <lb/>E.f. albocollaris (3) <lb/> E.f. collaris <lb/> MI (61) <lb/>MK <lb/>MJ <lb/>MA (25) <lb/>MD <lb/>ME (2) <lb/>MB (7) <lb/>MC (2) <lb/>MF (4) <lb/>MG (4) <lb/>MH (2) <lb/> E.f. rufus -FA (2) <lb/> E.f. rufus -FC <lb/> E.f. rufus -FB (2) <lb/> E.f. rufus -FF <lb/> E.f. rufus -FG <lb/> E.f. rufus -FD (2) <lb/> E.f. rufus -FE <lb/> E.f. albifrons (4) <lb/> E.f. fulvus <lb/>E.f. mayottensis <lb/>E.f. fulvus (3) <lb/> E.f. mayottensis <lb/>E.f. fulvus <lb/>E.f. mayottensis (2) <lb/> E.f. fulvus <lb/>E.f. albifrons <lb/>E.f. albifrons (2) <lb/> E.f. albifrons <lb/>E.f. sanfordi <lb/>E.f. fulvus <lb/>E.f. fulvus <lb/>E.f. sanfordi (2) <lb/> E.f. albifrons <lb/>E.f. albifrons <lb/>E.f. albifrons <lb/>E.f. fulvus <lb/>E.f. rufus (2) <lb/> E.f. rufus (3) <lb/> E.f. rufus <lb/>E.f. rufus (3) <lb/> E.f. collaris <lb/>E. rubriventer <lb/>E. rubriventer <lb/>E. rubriventer <lb/>E. coronatus <lb/>E. coronatus <lb/>E. coronatus <lb/>E.m. macaco (2) <lb/> E.m. macaco <lb/>E.m. flavifrons <lb/>E.m. flavifrons (2) <lb/> Lemur catta <lb/>Lemur catta <lb/> 0.005 substitutions/site <lb/> 100 <lb/>97 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>98 <lb/>100 <lb/>76 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>97 <lb/>52 <lb/>98 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>35 <lb/>99 <lb/>64 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/> Anjamena <lb/> Anadabomandry <lb/>Ampijoroa <lb/>Captivity <lb/> Anjamena <lb/> Anadabomandry <lb/> 92 <lb/> Ampijoroa <lb/> E.  mongoz <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/> E. fulvus <lb/> * <lb/>* <lb/> 100 <lb/>92 <lb/>100 <lb/>97 <lb/>93 <lb/>100 <lb/>56 <lb/>97 <lb/>100 <lb/>57 <lb/>71 <lb/>95 <lb/>94 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>54 <lb/>48 <lb/>ns <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>99 <lb/>100 <lb/> 94 <lb/>

				
				<note place="headnote">BMC Evolutionary Biology 2009, 9:32 <lb/></note> 
				
				<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2148/9/32 <lb/></note>
				
				<page>Page 11 of 13 <lb/></page> 
				
				<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note> 
				
				gave rise to fertile hybrids [48]. In the wild, hybridization <lb/>has been reported between E. macaco macaco and E. m. fla-<lb/>vifrons [16], E. f. fulvus and E. f. rufus [17], and E. f. rufus <lb/>and E. f. albocollaris [18] subspecies. All these hybridiza-<lb/>tion events among Eulemur species and subspecies indi-<lb/>cate that reproductive barriers among Eulemur taxa are not <lb/>very well developed. <lb/>Hybridization between newly overlapping species pro-<lb/>vides a unique opportunity to observe the initial stages of <lb/>hybridization and its evolutionary consequences. Hybrid-<lb/>ization which results in fertile offspring, is expected to <lb/>introduce sets of alleles that gradually disperse through <lb/>the gene pool of the parent organisms through successive <lb/>backcrosses. Such extensive introgression might have <lb/>occurred among brown lemurs at Anjamena with 7 (88%) <lb/>brown lemurs possibly having introgressed alleles and 4 <lb/>(50%) brown lemurs having the mtDNA haplotype of E. <lb/>mongoz. However, larger sample sizes are needed to con-<lb/>firm the extent of introgression. In mongoose lemurs, <lb/>only 8 (22%) of the 37 animals studied show signs of <lb/>introgression. <lb/>There are several possible evolutionary consequences of <lb/>hybridization (see also introduction). In extreme cases, <lb/>parental taxa may be lost in the process and/or new taxa <lb/>formed [21,22]. A third possibility is that a stable hybrid <lb/>zone will form, with limited introgression across the zone. <lb/>Having already radiated across Madagascar twice, the <lb/>genus Eulemur has proved to be very successful in adapt-<lb/>ing to a variety of ecological niches. Introgressive hybridi-<lb/>zation among taxa is known to quickly increase levels of <lb/>variation, allowing more rapid responses to environmen-<lb/>tal changes [21,22]. Considering all the reported hybridi-<lb/>zation events known so far between Eulemur taxa in the <lb/>wild [[16-18], this study], hybridization might also have <lb/>played an important role in the success of the radiation of <lb/> Eulemur across Madagascar. <lb/> Conclusion <lb/> The genetic data presented here confirms the occurrence <lb/>of hybridization between E. mongoz and E. fulvus in west-<lb/>ern Madagascar. Most other hybrid zones reported so far <lb/>in lemurs are also between Eulemur taxa [16-18]. Only one <lb/>hybridization event has been found among other lemur <lb/>taxa, that of Varecia variegata subspecies [19]. It is known <lb/>that some groups of organisms seem to hybridize more <lb/>readily than others [1,47] and Eulemur may be more capa-<lb/>ble of hybridizing than other lemur taxa. However, <lb/>hybrids are not easy to detect. They are much easier to <lb/>identify and are generally recorded more often if the <lb/>hybridizing taxa are brightly and distinctively coloured <lb/>(e.g., birds, butterflies [1]). That is very much the case for <lb/> Eulemur species and subspecies, as well as for Varecia vari-<lb/>egata subspecies. The detection of hybridization in lemurs <lb/>may follow a similar time sequence as the discovery of <lb/>parent taxa, with nocturnal species lagging behind. For <lb/>nocturnal lemurs, the pelage coloration of which is nei-<lb/>ther bright nor varies much between taxa, only detailed <lb/>genetic studies are likely to detect hybridization events. <lb/>Our study records an instance of on-going hybridization <lb/>in the wild. Introgressive hybridization may hasten speci-<lb/>ation and allow rapid ecological adaptation of taxa, hence <lb/>be one of the driving forces for the adaptive radiation of <lb/>lemurs in Madagascar. <lb/> Authors&apos; contributions <lb/> JP participated in the design of the study and the field <lb/>expedition, carried out the lab work, conducted data anal-<lb/>yses and wrote the first draft of the manuscript. AZ organ-<lb/>ized and lead the field expedition to Anjamena to collect <lb/>the samples. DC participated in the design of the study, <lb/>helped with the logistics of the field expedition and <lb/>revised a draft version of the manuscript. CN advised and <lb/>participated in the data analyses. NM critically revised the <lb/>draft version of the manuscript. All authors approved the <lb/>final version of the manuscript. <lb/> Table 5: mtDNA haplotypes found in mongoose lemurs and brown lemurs <lb/> E. mongoz <lb/>E. fulvus <lb/> Anjamena <lb/>All <lb/>Anjamena <lb/> E. f. rufus  a <lb/> All <lb/> # individuals <lb/>37 <lb/>107 <lb/>8 <lb/>13 <lb/>55 <lb/># haplotypes D-loop <lb/>2+1* <lb/>5+1* <lb/>1+1* <lb/>5+1* <lb/>31+1* <lb/># haplotypes ND4 <lb/>4+1* <lb/>9+1* <lb/>3+1* <lb/>6+1* <lb/>30+1* <lb/># haplotypes D-loop &amp; ND4 <lb/>5+1* <lb/>10+1* <lb/>3+1* <lb/>7+1* <lb/>34+1* <lb/># variable base positions D-loop b <lb/> 1 <lb/>25 <lb/>0 <lb/>29 <lb/>114 <lb/># variable base positions ND4 b <lb/> 3 <lb/>1 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>8 <lb/>6 4 <lb/> a only brown lemurs from the same subspecies clade (clade #4 in Figure 4) <lb/> b excluding the haplotype from the other species <lb/>* one haplotype was found from the other Eulemur species <lb/>

		</body>

		<back>
			
			<note place="headnote">BMC Evolutionary Biology 2009, 9:32 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2148/9/32 <lb/></note>
			
			<page>Page 12 of 13 <lb/></page> 
			
			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note> 
			
			<div type="annex">Additional material <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements<lb/> We would like to thank M. Clark (London Zoo), P. Ferebee (Natural Sci-<lb/>ence Center of Greensboro) T. Geissmann (Universität Zürich), D. Haring <lb/>(Duke University Primate Center), A. Kitchener (National Museums of <lb/>Scotland), P. Moisson (Mulhouse Zoo), K. Parr (Cleveland Metroparks <lb/>Zoo), G. Peters (Musem Koenig, Bonn), C. Rabarivola (Université de <lb/>Antananarivo), G. Rakotoarisoa (Parc Zoologique et Botanique de Tsim-<lb/>bazaza), M. Rasmussen (Duke University), Y. Rumpler (Université Louis <lb/>Pasteur, Strasbourg), N. Vasey (Pennsylvania State University) and Y. <lb/>Wyner (American Museum of Natural History) for providing the samples. <lb/>We are most grateful to G. Anzenberger, T. Bettinger, E. Davis, K. <lb/>Detwiler, R. Humphrey and R.D. Martin for help with the sample collection. <lb/>We are grateful for support during the field research from M. Clark, J. Ger-<lb/>son, A. Müller, C. Rabarivola, E.O. Raheliarisoa, W. Scheffrahn, U. Thal-<lb/>mann and M. Waters. We thank W. Amos (University of Cambridge), M. <lb/>Krützen (Universität Zürich) and D. Melnick (Columbia University) for let-<lb/>ting us use their lab facilities and for valuable assistance during the lab work. <lb/>We are grateful for M. Roth&apos;s help with Figure 1. We appreciate P. Fern-<lb/>ando&apos;s helpful comments on the manuscript. Acquisition of samples in <lb/>Madagascar was conducted under an &apos;Accord de Coopération&apos; between the <lb/>Universities of Zürich (Switzerland) and Mahajanga (Madagascar), and the <lb/>governmental institutions of Madagascar (Commission Tripartite) gave <lb/>research permission. Financial support from the Swiss National Science <lb/>Foundation, Vontobel Foundation, Julius Klaus Foundation, A.H. Schultz <lb/>Foundation and Cleveland Zoological Society is gratefully acknowledged. <lb/></div> 
			
			<listBibl>References <lb/> 1. <lb/>Mallet J: Hybridization as an invasion of the genome. Trends <lb/> Ecol Evol 2005, 20:229-237. <lb/> 2. <lb/>Arnold ML, Meyer A: Natural hybridization in primates: One <lb/>evolutionary mechanism. Zoology 2006, 109:261-276. <lb/> 3. <lb/>Nijman IJ, Otsen M, Verkaar ELC, de Ruijter C, Hanekamp E, Ochieng <lb/>JW, Shamshad S, Rege JEO, Hanotte O, Barwegen MW, Sulawati T, <lb/>Lenstra JA: Hybridization of banteng (Bos javanicus) and zebu <lb/>(Bos indicus) revealed by mitochondrial DNA, satellite DNA, <lb/>AFLP and microsatellites. Heredity 2003, 90:10-16. <lb/> 4. <lb/>Lecis R, Pierpaoli M, Biro ZS, Szemethy L, Ragni B, Vercillo F, Randi E: <lb/> Bayesian analyses of admixture in wild and domestic cats <lb/>(Felis silvestris) using linked microsatellite loci. Mol Ecol 2006, <lb/> 15:119-131. <lb/> 5. <lb/>Goodman SJ, Barton NH, Swanson G, Abernethy K, Pemberton JM: <lb/> Introgression through rare hybridization: A genetic study of <lb/>a hybrid zone between red and sika deer (genus Cervus) in <lb/>Argyll, Scotland. Genetics 1999, 152:355-371. <lb/> 6. <lb/>Riley SPD, Shaffer HB, Voss SR, Fitzpatrick BM: Hybridization <lb/>between a rare, native tiger salamander (Ambystoma cali-<lb/>forniense) and its introduced congener. Ecol Applic 2003, <lb/> 13:1263-1275. <lb/> 7. <lb/>Beltrán M, Jiggins CD, Bull V, Linares M, Mallet J, McMillan WO, Ber-<lb/>mingham E: Phylogenetic discordance at the species boundary: <lb/>Comparative gene genealogies among rapidly radiating Heli-<lb/>conius butterflies. Mol Biol Evol 2002, 19:2176-2190. <lb/> 8. <lb/>Salzburger W, Baric S, Sturmbauer C: Speciation via introgressive <lb/>hybridization in East African cichlids? <lb/> Mol Ecol 2002, <lb/> 11:619-625. <lb/> 9. <lb/>Szymura JM, Barton NH: The genetic structure of the hybrid <lb/>zone between the fire-bellied toads Bombina bombina and B. <lb/>variegata: Comparison between transects and between loci. <lb/> Evolution 1991, 45:237-261. <lb/> 10. Saetre G-P, Borge T, Lindell J, Moum T, Primmer CR, Sheldon BC, <lb/>Haavie J, Johnsen A, Ellegren H: Speciation, introgressive hybrid-<lb/>ization and nonlinear rate of molecular evolution in flycatch-<lb/>ers. Mol Ecol 2001, 10:737-749. <lb/> 11. Grant PR, Grant BR, Markert JA, Keller LF, Petren K: Convergent <lb/>evolution of Darwin&apos;s finches caused by introgressive hybrid-<lb/>ization and selection. Evolution 2004, 58:1588-1599. <lb/> 12. Lehman N, Eisenhawer A, Hansen K, Mech DL, Peterson RO, Gogan <lb/>PJP, Wayne RK: Introgression of coyote mitochondrial DNA <lb/>into sympatric north American gray wolf populations. Evolu-<lb/>tion 1991, 45:104-119. <lb/> 13. Alberts SC, Altmann J: Immigration and hybridization patterns <lb/>of yellow and anubis baboons in and around Amboseli, <lb/>Kenya. Am J Primatol 2001, 53:139-154. <lb/> 14. Evans BJ, Supriatna J, Melnick DJ: Hybridization and population <lb/>genetics of two macaque species in Sulawesi, Indonesia. Evo-<lb/>lution 2001, 55:1686-1702. <lb/> 15. Cortés-Ortiz L, Duda TF Jr, Canales-Espinosa D, Garcia-Orduna F, <lb/>Rodriguez-Luna E, Bermingham E: Hybridization in large-bodied <lb/>New World primates. Genetics 2007, 176:2421-2425. <lb/> 16. Rabarivola C, Meyers D, Rumpler Y: Distribution and morpholog-<lb/>ical character of inermediate forms between the black lemur <lb/>(Eulemur macaco macaco) and the sclater&apos;s lemur (E. m. flav-<lb/>ifrons). Primates 1991, 32:269-273. <lb/> 17. Lehman SM, Wright PC: Preliminary study of the conservation <lb/>status of lemur communities in the Betsakafandrika region <lb/>of eastern Madagascar. Lemur News 2000, 5:23-25 [http:// <lb/>www.dpz.gwdg.de/index.php?id=53&amp;L=0]. <lb/>18. Wyner YM, Johnson SE, Stumpf RM, DeSalle R: Genetic assess-<lb/>ment of a white-collared x red-fronted lemur hybrid zone at <lb/>Andringitra, Madagascar. Am J Primatol 2002, 67:51-66. <lb/> 19. Vasey N, Tattersall I: Do ruffed lemurs form a hybrid zone? Dis-<lb/>tribution and discovery of Varecia, with systematic and con-<lb/>servation implications. Am Mus Novitates 2002, 3376:1-26. <lb/> 20. Harrison RG: Hybrids and hybrid zones: historical perspective. <lb/> In Hybrid Zones and the Evolutionary Process Edited by: Harrison RG. <lb/>Oxford, UK: Oxford University Press; 1993:3-12. <lb/>21. Arnold ML: Natural hybridization as an evolutionary process. <lb/> Annu Rev Ecol Syst 1992, 23:237-261. <lb/> 22. Seehausen O: Hybridization and adaptive radiation. Trends Ecol <lb/>Evol 2004, 19:198-207. <lb/> 23. Martin RD: Adaptive radiation and behaviour of the Malagasy <lb/>lemurs. Phil Trans R Soc Lond B 1972, 264:295-352. <lb/> 24. Mittermeier RA, Konstant WR, Hawkins F, Louis EE, Langrand O, <lb/>Ratsimbazafy J, Rasoloarison R, Ganzhorn JU, Rajaoblina S, Tattersall <lb/>I, Meyers DM: Lemurs of Madagascar Second edition. Washington, <lb/>DC: Conservation International; 2006. <lb/>25. Shaw KL: Conflict between nuclear and mitochondrial DNA <lb/>phylogenies of a recent species radiation: What mtDNA <lb/>reveals and conceals about modes of speciation in Hawaiian <lb/>crickets. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 2002, 99:16122-16127. <lb/> 26. Curtis DJ, Zaramody A: Group size, home range use, and sea-<lb/>sonal variation in the ecology of Eulemur mongoz. Int J Primatol <lb/> 1998, 19:811-835. <lb/> 27. Pastorini J, Forstner MRJ, Martin RD: Relationships among brown <lb/>lemurs (Eulemur fulvus) based on mitochondrial DNA <lb/>sequences. Mol Phylogenet Evol 2000, 16:418-429. <lb/> 28. Zaramody A, Pastorini J: Indications for hybridisation between <lb/>red-fronted lemurs (Eulemur fulvus rufus) and mongoose <lb/>lemurs (E. mongoz) in northwest Madagascar. Lemur News <lb/> 2001, 6:28-31 [http://www.dpz.gwdg.de/index.php?id=53&amp;L=0]. <lb/>29. IUCN: IUCN Red List of Threatened Species. 2007 [http:// <lb/>www.iucnredlist.org]. <lb/>30. Curtis DJ, Zaramody A, Martin RD: Cathemerality in the mon-<lb/>goose lemur, Eulemur mongoz. Am J Primatol 1999, 47:279-298. <lb/> 31. Curtis DJ: Diet and nutrition in wild mongoose lemurs (Eule-<lb/> mur mongoz) and their implications for the evolution of <lb/>female dominance and small group size in lemurs. Am J Phys <lb/>Anthropol 2004, 124:234-247. <lb/> 32. Müller P, Velo A, Raheliarisoa E-O, Zaramody A, Curtis DJ: Surveys <lb/>of sympatric lemurs at Anjamena, northwest Madagascar. <lb/> Afr J Ecol 2000, 38:248-257. <lb/></listBibl>  
			
			<div type="annex">Additional File 1 <lb/> Locality, sample type and GenBank numbers for all E. mongoz hap-<lb/>lotypes and E. fulvus samples. none. <lb/> Click here for file <lb/>[http://www.biomedcentral.com/content/supplementary/1471-<lb/>2148-9-32-S1.doc] <lb/></div>
			
			<note place="footnote">Publish with Bio Med Central and every <lb/>scientist can read your work free of charge <lb/> &quot;BioMed Central will be the most significant development for <lb/>disseminating the results of biomedical researc h in our lifetime.&quot; <lb/> Sir Paul Nurse, Cancer Research UK <lb/> Your research papers will be: <lb/> available free of charge to the entire biomedical community <lb/>peer reviewed and published immediately upon acceptance <lb/>cited in PubMed and archived on PubMed Central <lb/>yours — you keep the copyright <lb/> Submit your manuscript here: <lb/> http://www.biomedcentral.com/info/publishing_adv.asp <lb/> BioMedcentral <lb/></note> 
			
			<note place="headnote">BMC Evolutionary Biology 2009, 9:32 <lb/></note> 
			
			<note place="headnote">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2148/9/32 <lb/></note>
			
			<page>Page 13 of 13 <lb/></page> 
			
			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note> 
			
			<listBibl>33. Sambrook J, Fritsch E, Maniatis T: Molecular Cloning – A Laboratory <lb/>Manual Cold Spring Harbour: Cold Spring Harbour Laboratory Press; <lb/>1989. <lb/>34. Jekielek J, Strobeck C: Characterization of polymorphic brown <lb/>lemur (Eulemur fulvus) microsatellite loci and their amplifica-<lb/>tion in the family Lemuridae. Mol Ecol 1999, 8:901-903. <lb/> 35. Pastorini J, Fernando P, Forstner MRJ, Melnick DJ: Characteriza-<lb/>tion of new microsatellite loci for the ring-tailed lemur <lb/>(Lemur catta). Mol Ecol Notes 2005, 5:149-151. <lb/> 36. Pastorini J, Fernando P, Melnick DJ, Forstner MRJ: Isolation of 10 <lb/>microsatellite markers for mongoose lemurs (Eulemur mon-<lb/>goz). Mol Ecol Notes 2004, 4:67-69. <lb/> 37. Kalinowski ST, Taper ML, Marshall TC: Revising how the compu-<lb/>ter program CERVUS accommodates genotyping error <lb/>increases success in paternity assignment. Mol Ecol 2007, <lb/> 16:1099-1106. <lb/> 38. Raymond M, Rousset F: GENEPOP (Version 1.2): Population <lb/>genetics software for exact tests and ecumenicism. J Hered <lb/> 1995, 86:248-249. <lb/> 39. Excoffier L, Laval G, Schneider S: Arlequin (ver. 3.0): An inte-<lb/>grated software package for population genetics data analy-<lb/>sis. Evol Bioinformatics Online 2005, 1:47-50. <lb/> 40. Belkhir K, Borsa P, Chikhi L, Raufaste N, Bonhomme F: GENETIX 4.05, <lb/>logiciel sous Windows TM pour la génétique des populations 2004 [http:// <lb/>www.genetix.univ-montp2.fr/genetix/genetix.htm]. <lb/>Laboratoire <lb/>Génome, Populations, Université de Montpellier II, Montpellier, <lb/>France <lb/>41. Pritchard JK, Stephens M, Donnelly P: Inference of population <lb/>structure using multilocus genotype data. Genetics 2000, <lb/> 155:945-959. <lb/> 42. Swofford DL: PAUP* Phylogenetic Analysis Using Parsimony (*and Other <lb/>Methods). Version 4 Sunderland: Sinauer Associates; 1999. <lb/>43. Pastorini J, Forstner MRJ, Martin RD: Phylogenetic relationships <lb/>among Lemuridae (Primates): evidence from mtDNA. J Hum <lb/>Evol 2002, 43:463-478. <lb/> 44. Pastorini J, Thalmann U, Martin RD: A molecular approach to <lb/>comparative phylogeography of extant Malagasy lemurs. <lb/> Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 2003, 100:5879-5884. <lb/> 45. Thalmann U: Lemur diversity and distribution in western <lb/>Madagascar – Inferences and predictions using a cladistic <lb/>approach. In Diversité et Endémisme à Madagascar Edited by: <lb/>Lourenço WR, Goodman SM. Paris: Mémoires de la Société de <lb/>Biogéographie, ORSTOM; 2000:191-202. <lb/>46. Godfrey LR, Jungers WL, Simons EL, Chatrath PS, Rakotosamimanana <lb/>B: Past and present distributions of lemurs in Madagascar. In <lb/> New Directions in Lemur Studies Edited by: Rakotosamimanana B, Ras-<lb/>amimanana H, Ganzhorn JU, Goodman SM. New York and Boston: <lb/>Kluwer Academic/Plenum Publishers; 1999:19-53. <lb/>47. Abbott RJ, James JK, Milne RI, Gillies ACM: Plant introductions, <lb/>hybridization and gene flow. Phil Trans R Soc Lond B 2003, <lb/> 358:1123-1132. <lb/> 48. Djelati R, Brun B, Rumpler Y: Meiotic study of hybrids in the <lb/>genus Eulemur and taxonomic considerations. Am J Primatol <lb/> 1997, 42:235-245. </listBibl>
			
		</back>
	</text>
</tei>
