<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_1471-2229-8-14"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="headnote"> BioMed Central <lb/></note>

			<page> Page 1 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> (page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>

			<front> BMC Plant Biology <lb/> Open Access <lb/> Research article <lb/> BAC libraries construction from the ancestral diploid genomes of <lb/>the allotetraploid cultivated peanut <lb/> Patricia M Guimarães*  †1 , Olivier Garsmeur  †2 , Karina Proite  †1,3 , <lb/>Soraya CM Leal-Bertioli 1 , Guilhermo Seijo 4 , Christian Chaine 2 , <lb/>David J Bertioli 5 and Angelique D&apos;Hont 2 <lb/> Address: 1 Biotechnology Unit, Embrapa Genetic Resources and Biotechnology, Brasília, DF, Brazil, 2 Centre de Coopération International en <lb/>Recherche Agronomique pour le Developpement (CIRAD), Montpellier, France, 3 Cell Biology Department, IB-University of Brasília (UnB), <lb/>Brasília, DF, Brazil, 4 Plant Cytogenetics and Evolution Laboratory, Instituto de Botánica del Nordeste, Corrientes, Argentina and 5 Biotechnology <lb/>and Genomic Sciences Department, Campus II Catholic University of Brasília, Brasília, DF, Brazil <lb/>Email: Patricia M Guimarães* -messenbe@cenargen.embrapa.br; Olivier Garsmeur -olivier.garsmeur@cirad.fr; <lb/>Karina Proite -proite@gmail.com; Soraya CM Leal-Bertioli -soraya@cenargen.embrapa.br; Guilhermo Seijo -jgseijo@yahoo.com; <lb/>Christian Chaine -christian.chaine@cirad.fr; David J Bertioli -david@pos.ucb.br; Angelique D&apos;Hont -angelique.dhont@cirad.fr <lb/>* Corresponding author †Equal contributors <lb/> Abstract <lb/> Background: Cultivated peanut, Arachis hypogaea is an allotetraploid of recent origin, with an <lb/>AABB genome. In common with many other polyploids, it seems that a severe genetic bottle-neck <lb/>was imposed at the species origin, via hybridisation of two wild species and spontaneous <lb/>chromosome duplication. Therefore, the study of the genome of peanut is hampered both by the <lb/>crop&apos;s low genetic diversity and its polyploidy. In contrast to cultivated peanut, most wild Arachis <lb/> species are diploid with high genetic diversity. The study of diploid Arachis genomes is therefore <lb/>attractive, both to simplify the construction of genetic and physical maps, and for the isolation and <lb/>characterization of wild alleles. The most probable wild ancestors of cultivated peanut are A. <lb/>duranensis and A. ipaënsis with genome types AA and BB respectively. <lb/> Results: We constructed and characterized two large-insert libraries in Bacterial Artificial <lb/>Chromosome (BAC) vector, one for each of the diploid ancestral species. The libraries (AA and <lb/>BB) are respectively c. 7.4 and c. 5.3 genome equivalents with low organelle contamination and <lb/>average insert sizes of 110 and 100 kb. Both libraries were used for the isolation of clones <lb/>containing genetically mapped legume anchor markers (single copy genes), and resistance gene <lb/>analogues. <lb/> Conclusion: These diploid BAC libraries are important tools for the isolation of wild alleles <lb/>conferring resistances to biotic stresses, comparisons of orthologous regions of the AA and BB <lb/>genomes with each other and with other legume species, and will facilitate the construction of a <lb/>physical map. <lb/> 
			
			Published: 29 January 2008 <lb/> 
			
			BMC Plant Biology 2008, 8:14 doi:10.1186/1471-2229-8-14 <lb/>
			
			Received: 30 August 2007 <lb/>
			
			Accepted: 29 January 2008 <lb/>
			
			This article is available from: http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2229/8/14 <lb/>

			>© 2008 Guimarães et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. <lb/>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), <lb/>which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/>

			BMC Plant Biology 2008, 8:14 <lb/> http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2229/8/14 <lb/></front>

			<page>Page 2 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> (page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>

			<body> Background <lb/> Cultivated peanut (Arachis hypogaea L) is the second-most <lb/>important grain legume crop worldwide after soybean, <lb/>with a production of 33 million tons in 2003/04 [1]. Pea-<lb/>nut is produced throughout the tropics and warmer <lb/>regions of the subtropics, but is particularly important in <lb/>Africa, Asia and in the United States [1]. It is an allotetra-<lb/>ploid (AABB) of recent origin that arose from hybridiza-<lb/>tion of two wild species and spontaneous chromosome <lb/>duplication [2,3]. This polyploidization event gave rise to <lb/>a severe genetic bottle-neck [2,3] which has led to lack of <lb/>variability in some important traits, limited availability of <lb/>allelic combinations and consequently restrictions in pro-<lb/>ductivity. In addition, the very low level of polymorphism <lb/>in cultivated peanut has hampered genetic and genomic <lb/>characterization. In contrast, diploid wild relatives of pea-<lb/>nut have high genetic diversity and have been selected <lb/>during evolution in a range of environments and biotic <lb/>stresses, constituting a rich source of allele diversity [3]. <lb/>Wild alleles can be introduced into the gene-pool of culti-<lb/>vated peanut using a &quot;resynthesis&quot; pathway, essentially <lb/>artificially recreating events similar to those that gave rise <lb/>to the origin of the crop species [4]. Recent advances in the <lb/>knowledge of the relationships of wild and cultivated <lb/>genomes through traditional taxonomy, cytogenetics and <lb/>molecular studies are enabling new choices of wild species <lb/>for resynthesis [5-8]. In parallel new genetic and genomic <lb/>tools (see below) for monitoring the introgression of wild <lb/>genes into a cultivated background are opening the per-<lb/>spectives for the efficient introgression of wild genes into <lb/>the peanut crop using molecular breeding. <lb/>The very low level of polymorphism in cultivated peanut <lb/>has hampered genetic mapping and QTL (Quantitative <lb/>trait loci) studies. Consequently only a few linkage maps <lb/>have been published. All of them have used wild species <lb/>to enable the generation of sufficient polymorphic mark-<lb/>ers. Restriction fragment length polymorphism (RFLP) <lb/>maps were developed by Halward based on a cross of two <lb/>AA genome species, A. stenosperma Krapov. &amp; WC Gregory <lb/>and A. cardenasii Krapov. &amp; WC Gregory, and a tetraploid <lb/>map based on a cross of TxAG-6 (a synthetic amphiploid) <lb/>and A. hypogaea was published by Burow et al. [9]. <lb/>Recently, we developed an SSR-based map for the AA <lb/>genome of Arachis based on a cross of A. stenosperma and <lb/> A. duranensis Krapov. &amp; WC Gregory [10] and a map of the <lb/>BB genome, based on a cross of A. ipaënsis Krapov., WC <lb/>Gregory &amp; CE Simpson and A. magna Krapov., WC Gre-<lb/>gory &amp; CE Simpson [11]. Currently there are 54,168 ESTs <lb/>for A. hypogaea in Genbank [12-14], and 6,264 for the <lb/>wild AA genome A. stenosperma [15,16]. <lb/>Bacterial Artificial Chromosome (BAC) libraries are fun-<lb/>damental tools for genomic studies, being important for <lb/>physical mapping, map-based gene cloning and analysis <lb/>of gene structure and function. The easy handling and <lb/>propagation of the clones, their relatively stability and <lb/>low degree of chimerism compared with yeast artificial <lb/>chromosome (YAC) vectors have made BAC vectors the <lb/>cloning system of choice [17,18]. A number of strategies <lb/>have been proposed for physical mapping with large-<lb/>insert clones: hybridisation-based methods such as inter-<lb/>active hybridisation using individual cDNA or genomic <lb/>clones as probes [19], restriction-based fingerprinting <lb/>methods [20] integrated BAC end sequencing and finger-<lb/>print analysis [21] or more recently, the use of oligonucle-<lb/>otide-based &quot;overgos&quot; [22]. <lb/>Within the Leguminosae, BAC libraries are available for <lb/> Phaseolus vulgaris [23], Vigna radiata [24], Glycine max [25], <lb/> Trifolium pretense [26] and the model legumes Lotus japon-<lb/>icus [27] and Medicago truncatula [28]. Within the genus <lb/> Arachis, one BAC library for the allopolyploid cultivated <lb/>peanut has been developed [29]. As a complement to this <lb/>resource, here we describe the production of BAC libraries <lb/>for the two diploid wild species A. duranensis (AA <lb/>genome) and A. ipaënsis (BB genome) that have been <lb/>identified as the most probable ancestors of cultivated <lb/>peanut [8,30]. Using whole genome in-situ hybridization <lb/>(GISH) we also further investigated the affinities and cov-<lb/>erage of the selected diploid genomes compared to those <lb/>present in A. hypogaea. <lb/> Results <lb/> In-situ hybridizations <lb/> Total genomic DNA of A. duranensis (AA genome) and A. <lb/>ipaënsis (BB genome) when used as probes on the chro-<lb/>mosomes of A. hypogaea displayed intense and uniform <lb/>hybridization patterns onto AA and BB chromosomes of <lb/> A. hypogaea respectively (Fig. 1). This clear genome dis-<lb/>crimination of the chromosome subsets from the corre-<lb/>sponding parental genomes in the tetraploids was <lb/>possible without the need of any unlabelled blocking <lb/>DNA, which is normally used to avoid cross-hybridization <lb/>between a specific probe from one genome and homolo-<lb/>gous DNA sequences from another genome. Counter-<lb/>stained A and B chromosomes show very similar total <lb/>sizes for the two genomic components (Fig. 1). <lb/> High Molecular Weight (HMW) DNA isolation <lb/> The use of standard HMW DNA isolation protocols <lb/>[31,32] did not produce sufficient amounts of good qual-<lb/>ity nuclei for Arachis. High levels of carbohydrate and <lb/>polyphenols are present in both A. duranensis and A. <lb/>ipaënsis leaves. This results in high viscosity leaf extracts, <lb/>which are difficult to filtrate, increasing considerably the <lb/>time of the nuclei exposure to the action of oxidizing sub-<lb/>stances. To overcome this problem, some modifications <lb/>were necessary: inclusion of PVP-40 in the extraction <lb/>buffer, filtration of leaf extracts in four layers of cheese-<lb/>

			<note place="headnote"> BMC Plant Biology 2008, 8:14 <lb/> http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2229/8/14 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 3 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> (page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>

			cloth followed by two layers of Miracloth, centrifugation <lb/>at low speed (60 × g for 2 min) and a Percoll gradient <lb/>(37.5%). The analysis of the extracts by DAPI-staining <lb/>microscopy enabled the correct evaluation of the amount <lb/>and quality of the nuclei preparations. <lb/>The inclusion of an extra purification step, consisting of <lb/>PFGE of agarose plugs for 40 min before digestion, ena-<lb/>bled the purging of smaller fragments and eliminated <lb/>impurities, increasing cloning efficiency. To obtain the <lb/>highest amount of restricted DNA after electro-elution, <lb/>only 50 μL was recovered at the very bottom of the collec-<lb/>tion tube instead of 300 μL as described in the standard <lb/>protocol [21]. After the double size selection, various <lb/>ratios of ligation were tested with the 1/4 V/I ratio result-<lb/>ing in the greatest number of transformants. Overall, five <lb/>different ligations were necessary to obtain each BAC <lb/>library (Table 1). <lb/> BAC libraries characterisation <lb/> The BAC library for the AA genome (A. duranensis) con-<lb/>tained 84,096 clones whilst the BB genome library (A. <lb/> ipaënsis) consisted of 75,648 (Table 1). A random sample <lb/>of each library was analyzed by NotI digestion, and the <lb/>average insert size was 110 and 100 kb for A. duranensis <lb/> and A. ipaënsis respectively (Fig. 2a and 2b; Fig. 3). <lb/>The organelle contamination in both BAC libraries was <lb/>evaluated by screening the high-density filters with mito-<lb/>chondrial and chloroplast specific probes. For A. duranen-<lb/>sis, the contamination of BAC clones with chloroplast <lb/>sequences was of 0.016% and mitochondrial sequences of <lb/>0.21%. For A. ipaënsis 0.363% was contaminated with <lb/>chloroplast sequences and 0.081% of the clones with <lb/>mitochondrial DNA. These values, together with the <lb/>microscopic DAPI-staining observations, reflect the high <lb/>level of purification of the Arachis nuclei obtained with <lb/>the modified protocol. <lb/>Based on the library average insert size and A. duranensis <lb/> haploid genome, equivalent to 1260 Mb [33], the esti-<lb/>mated coverage of the AA genome BAC library is of 7.4 <lb/>haploid genome equivalents. However, for A. ipaënsis, the <lb/>DNA-content determination is controversial. It is possible <lb/>that the haploid genome equivalent of 2,830 Mb reported <lb/>by Singh et al [34] is a 2.0 fold overestimate because of <lb/>measurement inconsistencies, as already described for <lb/>other Arachis species [33,35] Therefore the BB genome <lb/>BAC library for A. ipaënsis could represent from 2.7 to 5.3 <lb/>the haploid genome equivalents of the species. Consider-<lb/>ing that A and B chromosomes show very similar sizes for <lb/>the two genomic components of the tetraploid (as men-<lb/>tioned above, Fig. 1) we consider that latter to be a better <lb/>estimate. To further test the coverage, high-density filters <lb/>were screened with probes corresponding to single copy <lb/>gene used as anchor markers in legume and that have <lb/>been placed on the Arachis AA genetic map (unpublished <lb/>data). An average of 5.1 clones per probe was identified in <lb/>the AA genome and 4.5 in the BB (Table 2). <lb/>The hybridization of both BAC libraries with an Arachis <lb/> resistance gene analogue RGA S1_A_36 identified two <lb/>clones in the AA genome but none in the BB genome <lb/>(Table 2). <lb/> Discussion <lb/> Cultivated peanut is an allotetraploid with two nuclear <lb/>genomic components, AA and BB. Although it is generally <lb/>agreed that these component genomes are derived from <lb/> GISH of Arachis hypogaea metaphase chromosomes <lb/> Figure 1 <lb/>GISH of Arachis hypogaea metaphase chromosomes. <lb/> Somatic metaphases of Arachis hypogaea (subsp. hypogaea var. <lb/> hypogaea, race Guaycurú) after a) 4&apos;6-diamidino-2-phenylin-<lb/>dole (DAPI) counterstaining (blue, shown in black and white), <lb/>b) Genomic in situ hybridization using genomic DNA from <lb/> A.duranensis (in green) and A. ipaënsis (red). <lb/> Table 1: Characteristics of the A. duranensis and A. ipaënsis BAC libraries <lb/> Species <lb/>Ligations(no.) Genome size (Mb) Clones (no.) Average insert size <lb/> (kb) <lb/> mtDNA(%) cpDNA(%) Estimated genome <lb/>coverage <lb/> A. duranensis <lb/> 5 <lb/>1 2 6 0 a <lb/> 84,096 <lb/>110 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>0.016 <lb/>7.4× <lb/> A. ipaënsis <lb/> 5 <lb/>1415–2830 b <lb/> 75,648 <lb/>100 <lb/>0.081 <lb/>0.363 <lb/>5.3–2.7 b x <lb/>mt: mitochondrial, cp: chloroplastic <lb/> a Temsch &amp; Greilhuber, 2001 <lb/> b Singh et al, 1996 <lb/>

			<note place="headnote"> BMC Plant Biology 2008, 8:14 <lb/> http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2229/8/14 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 4 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> (page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>

			diploid wild ancestors, the exact species involved has been <lb/>a matter of some research and discussion. Although the <lb/>evidence is not completely clear cut, analysis of data from <lb/>molecular markers, cytogenetics, morphology and geo-<lb/>graphical distributions support that A. duranensis and A. <lb/>ipaënsis are the direct ancestors of cultivated peanut <lb/>[8,30]. <lb/>Genomic in situ hybridization (GISH) of A. hypogaea met-<lb/>aphase chromosomes with total genomic DNA from the <lb/>AA genome of A. duranensis and the BB genome of A. <lb/>ipaënsis allowed a clear differentiation of the A and B chro-<lb/>mosomes. Firstly, this observation reinforces the evidence <lb/>of the close relationship between the genomes of A. duran-<lb/>ensis, A. ipaënsis and cultivated peanut. Secondly, since <lb/>GISH relies largely on the hybridization of repetitive <lb/>sequences, it also indicates that A. duranensis and A. ipaën-<lb/>sis genomes have diverged substantially regarding their <lb/>repeated sequences/transposable elements contents. <lb/>In contrast, the evidence available indicates that the gene <lb/>order in the AA and BB genomes is substantially conserved <lb/>[9]. This situation of largely syntenic gene frameworks <lb/>embedded within quickly evolving repetitive DNA seems <lb/>to be a recurrent theme in plant evolution [36-39]. <lb/>The availability of BAC libraries from the allopolyploid <lb/>and the two wild ancestors will allow the comparison of <lb/>these genomes regarding microsynteny and repetitive <lb/>DNA contents, in particular transposable elements and <lb/>will provide insights into the fascinating area of polyploid <lb/>genome evolution. <lb/> Table 2: BAC library filter-hybridization results using legume single-copy probes and one RGA <lb/> Probe <lb/>Number of BAC clones detected <lb/> A. duranensis <lb/>A. ipaënsis <lb/> RGA S1_A_36 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>Leg083 <lb/>2 <lb/>5 <lb/>Leg128 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>Leg092, Leg149, Leg178 (mixed) <lb/>19 <lb/>Leg 92 <lb/>10 <lb/>* <lb/>Leg237 <lb/>5 <lb/>* <lb/>Leg242 <lb/>6 <lb/>* <lb/>Leg 88 <lb/>0 <lb/>* <lb/>Average Leg clones <lb/>5,11 <lb/>4,5 <lb/>* Not tested <lb/> A. duranensis (a) and A. ipaënsis (b) libraries sizing <lb/> Figure 2 <lb/> A. duranensis (a) and A. ipaënsis (b) libraries sizing. <lb/> Random BAC clones from the A. duranensis (a) and A. ipaënsis <lb/> (b) libraries digested with NotI and separated by PGEF. The <lb/>size of a few reference bands from Lambda Ladder PFG <lb/>Marker (New England Biolabs) are indicated in kilobases. <lb/>BAC libraries insert sizes <lb/> Figure 3 <lb/>BAC libraries insert sizes. Distribution of insert sizes <lb/>from randomly selected BAC clones from the A. duranensis <lb/> and A. ipaënsis libraries. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote"> BMC Plant Biology 2008, 8:14 <lb/> http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2229/8/14 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 5 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> (page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>

			In addition, the legume single copy anchor markers, used <lb/>to characterize the libraries, will allow orthologous <lb/>regions to be identified and compared between the AA <lb/>and BB Arachis genomes, and with other legume genomes, <lb/>in particular the sequenced genomes of Lotus and Medi-<lb/>cago, providing insight into legume genome evolution. <lb/>Construction of BAC libraries in some plants can require <lb/>substantial effort due to particular chemical constitution <lb/>as already experienced by us before [32]. For Arachis, <lb/> obtaining good quality HMW DNA was difficult due to <lb/>contamination from polyphenols and carbohydrates, <lb/>which are abundant in Arachis leaves. A number of steps <lb/>had to be added to the standard protocols of nuclei extrac-<lb/>tion and several ligations had to be made to obtain a rea-<lb/>sonable number of BAC clones. These difficulties were <lb/>also reported by Yuksel and Paterson [29] for the con-<lb/>struction of the A hypogaea BAC library. <lb/>The genome coverage of the BAC libraries was estimated <lb/>between 7.4 and 5.1 haploid genome equivalents for the <lb/>A genome and 5.3 to 4.5 for the B genome. These dispari-<lb/>ties are due to variations of the density of restriction sites <lb/>in certain genome regions or difficulties in cloning too <lb/>large or too small fragments [40]. Considering that 99% <lb/>coverage is equivalent to 4.7× haploid genomes [40]A. <lb/> duranensis and A ipaënsis genomes are well represented <lb/>and the libraries will be suitable for many applications. <lb/>The availability of BAC libraries from diploid Arachis will <lb/>greatly facilitate the development of a reference physical <lb/>map for Arachis. The construction of this physical map <lb/>will be initiated soon with the A. duranensis BAC library. <lb/>This species was used as a parent of the mapping popula-<lb/>tion used for the construction of the Arachis SSR-based <lb/>map [10]. A. ipaënsis is also the parent of a mapping pop-<lb/>ulation [11]. This will facilitate the integration of genetic <lb/>and physical maps. <lb/>The exploitation of peanut&apos;s diploid wild relatives for <lb/>breeding is very attractive since they possess various resist-<lb/>ances to biotic and abiotic stresses. The two species used <lb/>to make the BAC libraries harbour resistances to nema-<lb/>tode and fungal diseases[41,42]. These new BAC resources <lb/>will help the tagging and/or the isolation of the corre-<lb/>sponding resistance genes. For example, a QTL for resist-<lb/>ance to late leaf spot, caused by Cercosporidium personatum <lb/> has been mapped in a cross of A. duranensis with A. steno-<lb/>sperma [43]. S1_A_36, a RGA that co-segregates with this <lb/>QTL has been used to identify two BAC clones in the A. <lb/>duranensis library, whilst no clones in the A. ipaënsis <lb/> library were found. Sequencing of the BAC clones should <lb/>enable the identification of microsatellites in the target <lb/>region, thus providing more convenient markers for track-<lb/>ing the QTL in segregating populations. <lb/> Conclusion <lb/> In summary, here we describe the production of BAC <lb/>libraries for the AA and BB genomes of Arachis. The librar-<lb/>ies will be a useful resource for the isolation of genes, the <lb/>construction and correlation of physical and genetic <lb/>maps, the isolation of probes for cytogenetic analysis, the <lb/>study of the evolution of the two genome types, and, by <lb/>comparison with the allotetraploid genome of cultivated <lb/>peanut, for the study of the evolution of polyploid <lb/>genomes. <lb/> Methods <lb/> Plant Material <lb/> Seeds were obtained from the Arachis germplasm collec-<lb/>tion, maintained at Embrapa Genetic Resources and Bio-<lb/>technology – CENARGEN (Brasília-DF, Brazil). The <lb/>germination was improved by placing the seeds on a blot-<lb/>ting paper humidified with a 1% Ethephon. For HMW <lb/>DNA isolation, A. duranensis V14167 (genome AA) and A. <lb/>ipaënsis KG30076 (genome BB) were grown under green-<lb/>house conditions. Young leaves were collected in liquid <lb/>nitrogen then stored at -80°C. <lb/> Probe labelling and fluorescent in situ hybridization <lb/> Whole genomic DNA from A. duranensis and A. ipaënsis <lb/> were used as probes in genomic in situ hybridization <lb/>(GISH). Probes were labelled with digoxigenin-11-dUTP <lb/>(Roche, Mannheim, Germany) or biotin-11-dUTP <lb/>(Sigma) by nick translation. <lb/>Pre-treatment of preparations, chromosome and probe <lb/>denaturation, conditions for the in situ hybridization <lb/>(hybridization mixes contained DNA probes at a concen-<lb/>tration of 2.5–3.5 ng/μL), post-hybridization washings, <lb/>blocking, and indirect detection by fluorochrome conju-<lb/>gated antibodies were performed according to Moscone et <lb/>al[44]. Antibodies consisted of mouse anti-biotin (Dako-<lb/>patts, Dako, Carpinteria, California, USA) and sheep anti-<lb/>digoxigenin conjugated to fluorescein isothiocyanate <lb/>(FITC) (Roche) in PBS (0.13 mol/L NaCl, 0.007 mol/L <lb/>Na 2 HPO 4 , 0.003 mol/L NaH 2 PO 4 ), 3% (w/v) bovine <lb/>serum albumin (BSA) or, rabbit anti-mouse conjugated to <lb/>tetramethyl-rodamine isothiocyanate (TRITC) (Dako-<lb/>patts) and FITC-conjugated rabbit anti-sheep (Dakopatts) <lb/>in PBS, 3% (w/v) BSA. Preparations were counterstained <lb/>and mounted with Vectashield medium (Vector Laborato-<lb/>ries, Burlingame, California, USA) containing 2 μg/mL of <lb/>4&apos;,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI, Sigma). <lb/>The DAPI counterstaining subsequent to GISH resulted in <lb/>a C banding-like pattern with major heterochromatin <lb/>bands fluorescing more intensely, thus aiding chromo-<lb/>some identification [8,44]. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote"> BMC Plant Biology 2008, 8:14 <lb/> http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2229/8/14 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 6 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> (page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>

			Fluorescence microscopy and image acquisition <lb/> Chromosomes were viewed and photographed with a <lb/>Leica DMLB fluorescence microscope (Leica, Heerbrugg, <lb/>Switzerland) equipped with a computer-assisted Leica DC <lb/>250 digital camera system. Red, green, and blue images <lb/>were captured in black and white using appropriate filters <lb/>for TRITC, FITC, and DAPI excitation, respectively. Digital <lb/>images were pseudo-coloured and combined using IM <lb/>1000 Leica software, then imported into Adobe Pho-<lb/>toshop, version 7.0 (Adobe, San Jose, California, USA) for <lb/>final processing. <lb/> HMW DNA isolation <lb/> Nuclei were isolated from leaves according to Meyers et al. <lb/>[31] with some modifications. Fifty grams of young leaves <lb/>were ground in liquid nitrogen and nuclei were liberated <lb/>by incubating the cell extract at 4°C for 20 min in HB 1× <lb/>extraction buffer, plus 0.2% of polyvinylpyrrolidone (PVP <lb/>40). PVP was added to the buffer to reduce the production <lb/>of oxidizing polyphenolic substances. To eliminate cell <lb/>debris, the leaf homogenate was filtered successively <lb/>through four layers of cheesecloth then two layers of Mir-<lb/>acloth (250 μm), (Calbiochem, UK) and a low speed cen-<lb/>trifugation (60 × g for 2 min) was performed. <lb/>Centrifugation at 850 × g for 8 min at 4°C was followed <lb/>by a Percoll gradient (37.5%) to separate nuclei from the <lb/>pectin matrix [45]. The nuclei was washed in 20 mL of HB <lb/>1× extraction buffer without β-mercaptoethanol and Tri-<lb/>ton-100×, and then centrifuged at 850 × g for 8 min at <lb/>4°C. Finally the nuclei pellet was resuspended in 1 mL of <lb/>filtered HB 1× and embedded in 1.2% low-melting-point <lb/>agarose plugs (InCert Agarose, Cambrex-Bioscience, Rock-<lb/>land, Inc.). An aliquot of the nuclei extraction was evalu-<lb/>ated under a microscope using DAPI staining to observe <lb/>the integrity of the nuclei and the purity of the preparation <lb/>in terms of organelle contamination. Agarose plugs con-<lb/>taining HMW DNA were incubated for 24 h at 50°C in <lb/>lysis buffer (5% Sodium Lauryl Sarcosyl, 0.625 M EDTA <lb/>pH 9.0, 50 mg Proteinase K), washed for 1 h at 4°C in <lb/>inactivation solution (0.5 M EDTA, pH 8.0, 1 mM PMSF), <lb/>then washed four times for 30 min in TE 10/10 (10 mM <lb/>Tris-HCl, 10 mM EDTA, pH 8.0). An extra HMW DNA <lb/>purification step was conducted with a pulsed-field gel <lb/>electrophoresis (PFGE) using a CHEF Mapper™ XA appa-<lb/>ratus (Bio-Rad, U.K.) at 6 V/cm, with 3 s of switch time, <lb/>and an angle of 120° for 40 min aiming to eliminate the <lb/>degraded DNA. Agarose plugs were finally washed four <lb/>times for 30 min in TE 10/1 (10 mM Tris-HCl, 1 mM <lb/>EDTA, pH 8.0). at 4°C before being used for restriction <lb/>enzyme digestions. <lb/> BAC library construction <lb/> Agarose plugs containing HMW DNA were chopped into <lb/>small pieces and incubated on ice, with agitation, three <lb/>times in 1 mL of HindIII restriction buffer (Gibco BRL, <lb/>USA), with buffer exchange every 30 min. Seven units of <lb/> HindIII was added to each chopped plug and allowed to <lb/>diffuse for 4 hours on ice. For partial digestions, the reac-<lb/>tions were incubated for 15 min at 37°C and then <lb/>stopped by adding one-tenth of the total volume of 0.5 M <lb/>EDTA, pH 8.0. Partially digested HMW DNA was size-<lb/>selected by two successive PFGE in 1% GTG SEAKEM aga-<lb/>rose gels in 0.5× TBE at 14°C. The first-sizing was per-<lb/>formed at 6 V/cm, with 1 s to 50 s of switch-time, and an <lb/>angle of 120° for 20 h. Two regions from 80 to150 kb and <lb/>150 to 250 kb were excised from the gel and loaded onto <lb/>a new gel. The second-sizing selection was then performed <lb/>at 6 V/cm, with 3 s of switch time, and an angle of 120° <lb/>for 20 h. The regions from 100 to 250 kb were cut out <lb/>from the latter gel and the DNA was recovered through an <lb/>electro-elution (BIO-RAD/electro-eluter, UK). DNA con-<lb/>centration was estimated in 1% agarose gel in 1× TAE. Sev-<lb/>eral ligation reactions were tested containing different <lb/>ratios of vector to insert. A constant 30 ng of the commer-<lb/>cial vector &quot;pIndigo BAC-5 HindIII-Cloning Ready&quot; (Epi-<lb/>centre, USA) was used, and varying amounts of DNA <lb/>ranging from 50 to 600 ng of HMW DNA were used. One <lb/>microlitre of ligation was mixed to 20 microlitres of com-<lb/>petent E. coli cells (ElectroMAX DH10B, Invitrogen) and <lb/>electro-transformed using a BRL Cell-Porator system <lb/>according to the manufacturer&apos;s recommendations but <lb/>with a charge rate of 355 volts. Transformants were <lb/>selected on 2YT plates (tryptone 16 g/L, yeast extract 10 g/ <lb/>L, sodium chloride 5 g/L, agar 16 g/L) containing 12.5 μg/ <lb/> mL of chloramphenicol, 50 μg/mL of 5-bromo-4-chloro-<lb/>3-indole-β-D-galactopyranoside (X-Gal) and 25 μg/mL of <lb/>isopropyl-thiogalactoside (IPTG). White colonies were <lb/>picked using a Q-Pix 2 colony picker robot (Genetix) and <lb/>transferred to 384-well plates containing 80 μL of 2YT, 7% <lb/>glycerol. Microplates were incubated for 18–20 h at 37°C <lb/>and stored at -80°C. <lb/> BAC library screening and DNA isolation <lb/> For estimation of BAC clone insert sizes, random individ-<lb/>ual clones were grown in 100 μL pre-innoculum and then <lb/>in 3 mL 2YT liquid medium containing chloramphenicol <lb/>(12.5 μg/mL). BAC DNA was isolated using a QIAGEN <lb/>BIO-ROBOT 9600 (Qiagen GmbH, Germany). BAC DNA <lb/>was digested with NotI to release the inserts. The digested <lb/>clones were separated by PFGE at 6 V, a switch time from <lb/>5 to 15 s, an angle of 120° and run for 15 h. High-density <lb/>filters were made using a Q-Pix 2 robot (Genetix). Each <lb/>high-density filter contained 18,432 double-spotted <lb/>clones. Hybridisations were performed as described in the <lb/>Clemson BAC protocols [45]. Filters were exposed for 24 <lb/>h to Ferrania LifeRay XCG-films. <lb/> Genomic probes <lb/> Estimation of organelle contamination in both libraries <lb/>was evaluated by hybridization of high-density filters <lb/>

			<note place="headnote"> BMC Plant Biology 2008, 8:14 <lb/> http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2229/8/14 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 7 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote"> (page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>

			using probes from a spinach chloroplast gene, the large <lb/>Rubisco subunit (1.5 kb) and a wheat mitochondrial gene <lb/>of cytochrome oxidase cox I (1.3 kb) [32]. BAC libraries <lb/>were also hybridized to probes from single-copy genes <lb/>that have been defined as legume anchor markers [46] <lb/>and the Arachis resistance gene analogue S1_A_36 [47] <lb/>(Genbank accession AY157808). This RGA was isolated <lb/>from the AA genome species A. stenosperma and has been <lb/>found to co-localize with a QTL for resistance to the late-<lb/>leaf spot Cercosporidium personatum [43]. <lb/> 
		
		</body>

		<back>
			
			<div type="annex">Authors&apos; contributions <lb/> PMG conceived the study, constructed the libraries and <lb/>drafted the manuscript. KP constructed the libraries and <lb/>participated in planning the experiments. OG adapted the <lb/>BAC library construction protocol to Arachis, constructed <lb/>the libraries, and contributed to the writing of the manu-<lb/>script. SCLB conceived the study, contributed resources <lb/>and participated in drafting the manuscript. GS conducted <lb/>the cytogenetic experiments. CC was responsible for the <lb/>maintenance of the plants in greenhouse. DJB conceived <lb/>and coordinated the study and drafted the manuscript. <lb/>ADH contributed materials and resources, coordinated <lb/>libraries construction and contributed to the writing of <lb/>the manuscript. All authors read and approved the manu-<lb/>script. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgements <lb/> This work was funded by the Generation Challenge Program (Project #31) <lb/>and host institutions. Karina Proite had a doctoral fellowship granted by the <lb/>Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior (CAPES). <lb/>The authors would like to thank Dr. José.F.M.Valls for his valuable advice <lb/>and for providing seeds from EMBRAPA&apos;s Germplasm Bank, also thanks are <lb/>due to Xavier Sabau for robotic technical assistance. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. <lb/>FAO: FAOSTAT Agriculture. 2003. <lb/>2. <lb/>Young ND, Weeden NF, Kochert G: Genome mapping in leg-<lb/>umes (Family Fabaceae) . In Genome mapping in plants Edited by: <lb/>Paterson AH LRG. Austin ; 1996. <lb/>3. <lb/>Halward TM, Stalker HT, Kochert G: Development of an RFLP <lb/>linkage map in diploid peanut species. Theoretical and Applied <lb/>Genetics 1993, 87:379-384. <lb/> 4. <lb/>Simpson CE, Starr JL, Church GT, Burrow MD, Paterson AH: Regis-<lb/>tration of NemaTAM peanut. Crop Science 2003, 43:1561. <lb/> 5. <lb/>Singh AK, Smartt J: The genome donors of the groundnut/pea-<lb/>nut (Arachis hypogaea L.) revisited. Genetic Resources and Crop <lb/>Evolution 1998, 45:113-118. <lb/> 6. <lb/>Moretzsohn MC, Hopkins MS, Mitchell SE, Kresovich S, Valls JF, Fer-<lb/>reira ME: Genetic diversity of peanut (Arachis hypogaea L.) <lb/>and its wild relatives based on the analysis of hypervariable <lb/>regions of the genome. BMC Plant Biology 2004, 4:11. <lb/> 7. <lb/>Valls JFM, Simpson CE: New species of Arachis L. (Legumi-<lb/>nosae) from Brazil, Paraguay and Bolivia. Bonplandia 2005, <lb/> 14:35-64. <lb/> 8. <lb/>Seijo JG, Lavia GI, Fernández A, Krapovickas A, Ducasse D, Moscone <lb/>EA: Physical mapping of the 5S and 18S-25S rRNA genes by <lb/>FISH as evidence that Arachis duranensis and A. ipaënsis are <lb/>the wild diploid progenitors of A. hypogaea (leguminosae). <lb/> American Journal of Botany 2004, 91:1294-1303. <lb/> 9. <lb/>Burow MD, Simpson CE, Starr JL, Paterson AH: Transmission <lb/>genetics of chromatin from a synthetic amphidiploid to cul-<lb/>tivated peanut (Arachis hypogaea L.). broadening the gene <lb/>pool of a monophyletic polyploid species. Genetics 2001, <lb/> 159(2):823-837. <lb/> 10. Moretzsohn MC, Leoi L, Proite K, Guimaraes PM, Leal-Bertioli SC, <lb/>Gimenes MA, Martins WS, Valls JF, Grattapaglia D, Bertioli DJ: A <lb/>microsatellite-based, gene-rich linkage map for the AA <lb/>genome of Arachis (Fabaceae). Theoretical and Applied Genetics <lb/> 2005, 111(6):1060-1071. <lb/> 11. Gobbi A, Teixeira C, Moretszohn M, Guimarães PM, Leal-Bertioli S, <lb/>Bertioli D, Lopes CR, Gimenes MA: Development of a linkage <lb/>map to species of B genome related to the peanut (Arachis <lb/>hypogaea–AABB) : San Diego, Califórnia. ; 2006:679. <lb/>12. Luo M, Liang XQ, Dang P, Holbrook CC, Bausher MG, Lee RD, Guo <lb/>BZ: Microarray-based screening of differentially expressed <lb/>genes in peanut in response to Aspergillus parasiticus infec-<lb/>tion and drought stress. Plant Science 2005, 169:695-703. <lb/> 13. Luo M, Dang P, Bausher MG, Holbrook CC, Lee RD, Lynch RE, Guo <lb/>BZ: Identification of transcripts involved in resistance <lb/>responses to leaf spot disease caused by Cercosporidium <lb/>personatum in peanut (Arachis hypogaea). Phytopathology <lb/> 2005, 95:381-387. <lb/> 14. Luo M, Dang P, Guo BZ, He G, Holbrook C, Bausher MG, Lee RD: <lb/> Generation of Expressed Sequenced tags (ESTs) for gene <lb/>discovery and marker development in cultivated peanut. <lb/> Crop Science 2005, 45:346-353. <lb/> 15. Proite K, Leal-Bertioli SC, Bertioli DJ, Moretzsohn MC, da Silva FR, <lb/>Martins NF, Guimaraes PM: ESTs from a wild Arachis species for <lb/>gene discovery and marker development. BMC Plant Biology <lb/> 2007, 7:7. <lb/> 16. Martins W, de Sousa D, Proite K, Guimaraes P, Moretzsohn M, Ber-<lb/>tioli D: New softwares for automated microsatellite marker <lb/>development. Nucleic Acids Research 2006, 34(4):e31. <lb/> 17. Dvorak J, Yang ZL, You FM, Luo MC: Deletion polymorphism in <lb/>wheat chromosome regions with contrasting recombination <lb/>rates. Genetics 2004, 168(3):1665-1675. <lb/> 18. Chalhoub B, Belcram H, Caboche M: Efficient cloning of plant <lb/>genomes into bacterial artificial chromosome (BAC) librar-<lb/>ies with larger and more uniform insert size. Plant Biotechnology <lb/>Journal 2004, 2(3):181-188. <lb/> 19. Mozo T, Dewar K, Dunn P, Ecker JR, Fischer S, Kloska S, Lehrach H, <lb/>Marra M, Martienssen R, Meier-Ewert S, Altmann T: A complete <lb/>BAC-based physical map of the Arabidopsis thaliana <lb/>genome. Nature Genetics 1999, 22(3):271-275. <lb/> 20. Hong G: A rapid and accurate strategy for rice contig map <lb/>construction by combination of fingerprinting and hybridiza-<lb/>tion. Plant Molecular Biology 1997, 35(1-2):129-133. <lb/> 21. Mayer K, Schuller C, Wambutt R, Murphy G, Volckaert G, Pohl T, <lb/>Dusterhoft A, Stiekema W, Entian KD, Terryn N, Harris B, Ansorge <lb/>W, Brandt P, Grivell L, Rieger M, Weichselgartner M, de Simone V, <lb/>Obermaier B, Mache R, Muller M, Kreis M, Delseny M, Puigdomenech <lb/>P, Watson M, Schmidtheini T, Reichert B, Portatelle D, Perez-Alonso <lb/>M, Boutry M, Bancroft I, Vos P, Hoheisel J, Zimmermann W, Wedler <lb/>H, Ridley P, Langham SA, McCullagh B, Bilham L, Robben J, Van der <lb/>Schueren J, Grymonprez B, Chuang YJ, Vandenbussche F, Braeken M, <lb/>Weltjens I, Voet M, Bastiaens I, Aert R, Defoor E, Weitzenegger T, <lb/>Bothe G, Ramsperger U, Hilbert H, Braun M, Holzer E, Brandt A, <lb/>Peters S, van Staveren M, Dirske W, Mooijman P, Klein Lankhorst R, <lb/>Rose M, Hauf J, Kotter P, Berneiser S, Hempel S, Feldpausch M, Lam-<lb/>berth S, Van den Daele H, De Keyser A, Buysshaert C, Gielen J, Vil-<lb/>larroel R, De Clercq R, Van Montagu M, Rogers J, Cronin A, Quail M, <lb/>Bray-Allen S, Clark L, Doggett J, Hall S, Kay M, Lennard N, McLay K, <lb/>Mayes R, Pettett A, Rajandream MA, Lyne M, Benes V, Rechmann S, <lb/>Borkova D, Blocker H, Scharfe M, Grimm M, Lohnert TH, Dose S, de <lb/>Haan M, Maarse A, Schafer M, Muller-Auer S, Gabel C, Fuchs M, Fart-<lb/>mann B, Granderath K, Dauner D, Herzl A, Neumann S, Argiriou A, <lb/>Vitale D, Liguori R, Piravandi E, Massenet O, Quigley F, Clabauld G, <lb/>Mundlein A, Felber R, Schnabl S, Hiller R, Schmidt W, Lecharny A, <lb/>Aubourg S, Chefdor F, Cooke R, Berger C, Montfort A, Casacuberta <lb/>E, Gibbons T, Weber N, Vandenbol M, Bargues M, Terol J, Torres A, <lb/>Perez-Perez A, Purnelle B, Bent E, Johnson S, Tacon D, Jesse T, Hei-<lb/>jnen L, Schwarz S, Scholler P, Heber S, Francs P, Bielke C, Frishman <lb/>D, Haase D, Lemcke K, Mewes HW, Stocker S, Zaccaria P, Bevan M, <lb/>Wilson RK, de la Bastide M, Habermann K, Parnell L, Dedhia N, Gnoj <lb/>L, Schutz K, Huang E, Spiegel L, Sehkon M, Murray J, Sheet P, Cordes <lb/>M, Abu-Threideh J, Stoneking T, Kalicki J, Graves T, Harmon G, <lb/>Edwards J, Latreille P, Courtney L, Cloud J, Abbott A, Scott K, John-<lb/>son D, Minx P, Bentley D, Fulton B, Miller N, Greco T, Kemp K, <lb/></listBibl> 
			
			<note place="footnote">Publish with Bio Med Central and every <lb/>scientist can read your work free of charge <lb/> &quot;BioMed Central will be the most significant development for <lb/>disseminating the results of biomedical researc h in our lifetime.&quot; <lb/> Sir Paul Nurse, Cancer Research UK <lb/> Your research papers will be: <lb/> available free of charge to the entire biomedical community <lb/>peer reviewed and published immediately upon acceptance <lb/>cited in PubMed and archived on PubMed Central <lb/>yours — you keep the copyright <lb/> Submit your manuscript here: <lb/> http://www.biomedcentral.com/info/publishing_adv.asp <lb/> BioMedcentral <lb/></note> 
			
			<note place="headnote">BMC Plant Biology 2008, 8:14 <lb/> http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2229/8/14 <lb/></note>
			
			<page>Page 8 of 8 <lb/></page> 
			
			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note> 
			
			<listBibl>Kramer J, Fulton L, Mardis E, Dante M, Pepin K, Hillier L, Nelson J, <lb/>Spieth J, Ryan E, Andrews S, Geisel C, Layman D, Du H, Ali J, Berghoff <lb/>A, Jones K, Drone K, Cotton M, Joshu C, Antonoiu B, Zidanic M, <lb/>Strong C, Sun H, Lamar B, Yordan C, Ma P, Zhong J, Preston R, Vil D, <lb/>Shekher M, Matero A, Shah R, Swaby IK, O&apos;Shaughnessy A, Rodriguez <lb/>M, Hoffmann J, Till S, Granat S, Shohdy N, Hasegawa A, Hameed A, <lb/>Lodhi M, Johnson A, Chen E, Marra M, Martienssen R, McCombie <lb/>WR: Sequence and analysis of chromosome 4 of the plant <lb/>Arabidopsis thaliana. Nature 1999, 402(6763):769-777. <lb/> 22. Gardiner J, Schroeder S, Polacco ML, Sanchez-Villeda H, Fang Z, Mor-<lb/>gante M, Landewe T, Fengler K, Useche F, Hanafey M, Tingey S, Chou <lb/>H, Wing R, Soderlund C, Coe EH Jr.: Anchoring 9,371 maize <lb/>expressed sequence tagged unigenes to the bacterial artifi-<lb/>cial chromosome contig map by two-dimensional overgo <lb/>hybridization. Plant Physiology 2004, 134(4):1317-1326. <lb/> 23. Vanhouten W, MacKenzie S: Construction and characterization <lb/>of a common bean bacterial artificial chromosome library. <lb/> Plant Molecular Biology 1999, 40(6):977-983. <lb/> 24. Miyagi M, Humphry M, Ma ZY, Lambrides CJ, Bateson M, Liu CJ: Con-<lb/>struction of bacterial artificial chromosome libraries and <lb/>their application in developing PCR-based markers closely <lb/>linked to a major locus conditioning bruchid resistance in <lb/>mungbean (Vigna radiata L. Wilczek). Theoretical and Applied <lb/>Genetics 2004, 110(1):151-156. <lb/> 25. Danesh D, Peñuela S, Mudge J, Denny RL, Nordstrom H, Martinez JP, <lb/>Young ND: A bacterial artificial chromosome library for soy-<lb/>bean and identification of clones near a major cyst nematode <lb/>resistance gene. Theoretical and Applied Genetics 1998, 96:196-202. <lb/> 26. Sato S, Isobe S, Asamizu E, Ohmido N, Kataoka R, Nakamura Y, <lb/>Kaneko T, Sakurai N, Okumura K, Klimenko I, Sasamoto S, Wada T, <lb/>Watanabe A, Kohara M, Fujishiro T, Tabata S: Comprehensive <lb/>Structural Analysis of the Genome of Red Clover (Trifolium <lb/>pratense L.). DNA Research 2005, 12(5):301-364. <lb/> 27. Kawasaki S, Murakami Y: Genome Analysis of Lotus japonicus. <lb/> Journal of Plant Research 2000:0918-9440. <lb/>28. Nam YW, Penmetsa RV, Endre G, Uribe P, Kim D, Cook DR: Con-<lb/>struction of a bacterial artificial chromosome library of Med-<lb/>icago truncatula and identification of clones containing <lb/>ethylene-response genes. Theoretical and Applied Genetics 1999, <lb/> 98:3-4. <lb/> 29. Yuksel B, Paterson AH: Construction and characterization of a <lb/>peanut HindIII BAC library. Theoretical and Applied Genetics 2005, <lb/> 111(4):630-639. <lb/> 30. Kochert G, Stalker HT, Gimenes M, Galgaro L, Lopes CR, Moore K: <lb/> RFLP and cytogenetic evidence on the origin and evolution <lb/>of allotetraploid domesticated peanut Arachis hypogaea <lb/>(Leguminosae). American Journal of Botany 1996, 83:1282-11291. <lb/> 31. Zhang HB, Zhao X, Ding X, Paterson AH, Wing RA: Preparation of <lb/>megabase-size DNA from plant nuclei. Plant Journal 1995, <lb/> 7:175-184. <lb/> 32. Vilarinhos AD, Piffanelli P, Lagoda P, Thibivilliers S, Sabau X, Carreel <lb/>F, D&apos;Hont A: Construction and characterization of a bacterial <lb/>artificial chromosome library of banana (Musa acuminata <lb/>Colla). Theor Appl Genet 2003, 106(6):1102-1106. <lb/> 33. Temsch EM, Greilhuber J: Genome size in Arachis duranensis: a <lb/>critical study. Genome 2001, 44(5):826-830. <lb/> 34. Singh KP, Raina SN, Singh AK: Variation in chromosomal DNA <lb/>associated with the evolution of Arachis species. Genome <lb/> 1996, 39:890-897. <lb/> 35. Temsch EM, Greilhuber J: Genome size variation in Arachis <lb/>hypogaea and A. monticola re-evaluated. Genome 2000, <lb/> 43(3):449-451. <lb/> 36. Gale MD, Devos KM: Plant Comparative Genetics after 10 <lb/>Years. Science 1998, 282:656-658. <lb/> 37. McCouch SR: Genomics and Synteny. Plant Physiology 2001, <lb/> 125:152-155. <lb/> 38. Lonnig WE, Saedler H: Chromosome rearrangements and <lb/>transposable elements. <lb/> Annual Review of Genetics 2002, <lb/> 36:389-410. <lb/> 39. Kazazian HH Jr.: Mobile elements: drivers of genome evolu-<lb/>tion. Science 2004, 303(5664):1626-1632. <lb/> 40. Zhang HB, Wu C: BAC as tools for genome sequencing. Plant <lb/>Physiology and Biochemistry 2001, 39:195-209. <lb/> 41. Subrahmanyam P, McDonald D, Gibbons RW, Subba RPV: Compo-<lb/>nents of resistance to Puccinia arachidis in peanuts. Phytopa-<lb/>thology 1983:253-256. <lb/>42. Nelson SC, Simpson CE, Starr JL: Resistance to Meloidogyne are-<lb/>naria in Arachis spp. germplasm. Journal of Nematology 1989, <lb/> 21():654-660. <lb/> 43. Moretzsohn MC: Desenvolvimento e mapeamento de marca-<lb/>dores microssatélites e identificação de QTLs ligados à prod-<lb/>utividade e à resistência à mancha preta em Arachis spp. In <lb/> Molecular Biology Volume Doctoral Thesis. Brasília , Universidade de <lb/>Brasília; 2006:142. <lb/>44. Moscone EA, Klein F, Lambrou M, Fuchs J, Schweizer D: Quantita-<lb/>tive karyotyping and dual-color FISH mapping of 5S and 18S-<lb/>25S rDNA probes in the cultivated Phaseolus species (Legu-<lb/>minosae). Genome 1999, 42(6):1224-1233. <lb/> 45. Peterson DG, Tomkins JP, Frisch DA, Wing RA, Paterson AH: Con-<lb/>struction of plant bacterial artificial chromosome (BAC) <lb/>libraries: an illustrated guide. Journal of Agricultural Genomics <lb/> 2000, 5:. <lb/> 46. Fredslund J, Madsen LH, Hougaard BK, Nielsen AM, Bertioli D, Sandal <lb/>N, Stougaard J, Schauser L: A general pipeline for the develop-<lb/>ment of anchor markers for comparative genomics in plants. <lb/> BMC Genomics 2006, 7:207. <lb/> 47. Bertioli DJ, Leal-Bertioli SC, Lion MB, Santos VL, Pappas G Jr., Cannon <lb/>SB, Guimaraes PM: A large scale analysis of resistance gene <lb/>homologues in Arachis. Molecular Genetics and Genomics 2003, <lb/> 270(1):34-45. </listBibl>

		</back>
	</text>
</tei>
