<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>BioMed Central <lb/>Annals of General Hospital <lb/>Psychiatry <lb/>Open Access <lb/>Primary research <lb/>Brain choline concentrations may not be altered in euthymic <lb/>bipolar disorder patients chronically treated with either lithium or <lb/>sodium valproate <lb/>Ren H Wu 1 , Tina O&apos;Donnell 2 , Michele Ulrich 2 , Sheila J Asghar 2 , <lb/>Christopher C Hanstock 1 and Peter H Silverstone* 2 <lb/>Address: 1 Department of Biomedical Engineering, University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada and 2 Department of Psychiatry, University <lb/>of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada <lb/>Email: Ren H Wu -wurh20000@sina.com; Tina O&apos;Donnell -tina@gpu.srv.ualberta.ca; Michele Ulrich -mulrich@ualberta.ca; <lb/>Sheila J Asghar -sheila_canada@yahoo.com; Christopher C Hanstock -chris.hanstock@ualberta.ca; <lb/>Peter H Silverstone* -peter.silverstone@ualberta.ca <lb/>* Corresponding author <lb/>Published: 30 July 2004 <lb/>Annals of General Hospital Psychiatry 2004, 3:13 doi:10.1186/1475-2832-3-13 <lb/>Received: 30 September 2003 <lb/>Accepted: 30 July 2004 <lb/>This article is available from: http://www.general-hospital-psychiatry.com/content/3/1/13 <lb/>© 2004 Wu et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License <lb/>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is <lb/>properly cited. <lb/>Bipolar disorderlithiumsodium valproatemagnetic resonance spectroscopycholine <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Background: It has been suggested that lithium increases choline concentrations, although <lb/>previous human studies examining this possibility using 1 H magnetic resonance spectroscopy ( 1 H <lb/>MRS) have had mixed results: some found increases while most found no differences. <lb/> Methods: The present study utilized 1 H MRS, in a 3 T scanner to examine the effects of both <lb/>lithium and sodium valproate upon choline concentrations in treated euthymic bipolar patients <lb/>utilizing two different methodologies. In the first part of the study healthy controls (n = 18) were <lb/>compared with euthymic Bipolar Disorder patients (Type I and Type II) who were taking either <lb/>lithium (n = 14) or sodium valproate (n = 11), and temporal lobe choline/creatine (Cho/Cr) ratios <lb/>were determined. In the second part we examined a separate group of euthymic Bipolar Disorder <lb/>Type I patients taking sodium valproate (n = 9) and compared these to controls (n = 11). Here we <lb/>measured the absolute concentrations of choline in both temporal and frontal lobes. <lb/>Results: The results from the first part of the study showed that bipolar patients chronically <lb/>treated with both lithium and sodium valproate had significantly reduced temporal lobe Cho/Cr <lb/>ratios. In contrast, in the second part of the study, there were no effects of sodium valproate on <lb/>either absolute choline concentrations or on Cho/Cr ratios in either temporal or frontal lobes. <lb/>Conclusions: These findings suggest that measuring Cho/Cr ratios may not accurately reflect <lb/>brain choline concentrations. In addition, the results do not support previous suggestions that <lb/>either lithium or valproate increases choline concentrations in bipolar patients. <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">Page 1 of 7 <lb/>(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Annals of General Hospital Psychiatry 2004, 3:13 <lb/>http://www.general-hospital-psychiatry.com/content/3/1/13 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 2 of 7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>

			<body>Background <lb/>Bipolar disorder is a chronic severe mental illness affect-<lb/>ing approximately 1% of the adult population. The most <lb/>widely used mood stabilizer for this condition is lithium <lb/>[1], although the exact mechanism by which it is clinically <lb/>effective remains undetermined. One suggestion is that it <lb/>acts via effects on choline metabolism. This is based upon <lb/>findings that lithium can inhibit the membrane transport <lb/>of choline in both animals [2], and human post-mortem <lb/>brain tissue [3]. It also increases the accumulation of <lb/>erythrocyte choline in lithium-treated patients [4-7]. Also <lb/>of note is that choline concentrations increase signifi-<lb/>cantly in rats following electroconvulsive shock [8]. Based <lb/>upon this data choline has been used to treat mania in a <lb/>some small pilot studies [9], with one open label study <lb/>reporting that choline augmentation of lithium treatment <lb/>helped rapid-cyclers [10]. Patients treated with choline <lb/>also had increased basal ganglia concentrations of <lb/>choline, suggesting that externally administered choline <lb/>could alter brain concentrations [11,12]. <lb/>The most appropriate method to measure brain choline <lb/>concentrations in vivo utilizes proton magnetic resonance <lb/>spectroscopy ( 1 H-MRS). Previous studies of bipolar <lb/>patients utilizing this methodology have had mixed find-<lb/>ings. Overall, while some studies have suggested there <lb/>may be increased choline concentrations in specific situa-<lb/>tions [13-18], more have found no changes [19-27], and <lb/>one found a trend towards a decrease in concentrations <lb/>[28]. In both patients and volunteers lithium also doesn&apos;t <lb/>appear to alter choline/creatine peak ratios concentrations <lb/>[29,30]. Nonetheless, two reviews concluded that the evi-<lb/>dence to date suggests that lithium increases brain choline <lb/>concentrations [31,32], although as noted in these <lb/>reviews previous studies have varied considerably in terms <lb/>of patient populations, brain region studied, medications <lb/>administered, and MRS methodology. Many studies have <lb/>also examined differing patients (Type I and Type II) in <lb/>differing mood states (mixed, depressed, manic, and <lb/>euthymic). This may partially explain the varied results. <lb/>Sodium valproate is also widely used as a mood stabilizer, <lb/>both alone and in combination with lithium [33]. To date <lb/>there have been few studies which have examined the <lb/>effects of sodium valproate on choline concentrations or <lb/>activity. An in-vitro study suggested that valproate may <lb/>inhibit choline acetyltransferase activity [34]. In one study <lb/>9 patients taking either lithium or valproate were exam-<lb/>ined [35], and increased Cho/Cr ratios were seen in the <lb/>bipolar patients compared to controls. There were no dif-<lb/>ferences between the lithium and valproate treatment <lb/>groups, although the sample sizes were small. However, <lb/>another study in epilepsy patients treated with valproate <lb/>found no changes in choline concentrations [36]. None-<lb/>theless, given the lack of studies to date, the possibility <lb/>that valproate and lithium may both increase choline con-<lb/>centrations warrants further investigation. <lb/>Most of the previous studies have examined Cho/Cr <lb/>ratios. However, it should be noted that the &quot;choline&quot; res-<lb/>onance peak seen in 1 H-MRS spectra is composed prima-<lb/>rily of phosphocholine and glycerophosphocholine, <lb/>along with free choline, acetylcholine, and cytidine <lb/>diphosphate choline. Also, we have shown in animal <lb/>studies that both lithium and valproate can both decrease <lb/>creatine concentrations [37]. Therefore, when using Cho/ <lb/>Cr ratios it is not possible to be certain that any changes in <lb/>this peak represent changes in brain choline concentra-<lb/>tions. We were therefore interested to determine if there <lb/>were any differences in results when using different meth-<lb/>odologies, and more specifically to determine if studies <lb/>using a ratio methodology may have different results from <lb/>studies utilizing metabolite concentrations. <lb/>Methods <lb/>In the first part of the study patients taking either lithium <lb/>or valproate were examined using the Cho/Cr ratio <lb/>method, and both Bipolar Type I and Bipolar Type II <lb/>patients were included who could also be taking other <lb/>medications. In the second part of this study only Bipolar <lb/>Type I patients on valproate monotherapy were included, <lb/>and quantification of choline concentrations was made. <lb/>Some of the data from the first part of this study has been <lb/>reported previously [38]. <lb/>Subjects and Study Design <lb/>All subjects gave full informed consent, and both studies <lb/>were approved by the ethics committee at the University <lb/>of Alberta. Healthy controls were examined using a <lb/>detailed, but non-standardized, psychiatric interview. <lb/>They were excluded if there was any personal history, or <lb/>immediate family history, of psychiatric disorder. For <lb/>patients, diagnoses were made using DSM-IV criteria for <lb/>Bipolar Disorder Type I or Type II following detailed psy-<lb/>chiatric interview, with additional information being <lb/>available in almost all cases from long-term psychiatric <lb/>clinic records. They also had to be taking a dose of either <lb/>lithium or valproate which maintained their blood levels <lb/>within the ranges of 0.4–1.2 mmol/l for lithium and 200– <lb/>700 µmol/l for sodium valproate. Serum lithium and val-<lb/>proate levels were also measured on the day of MRS scan-<lb/>ning. Other medications taken by the patient were noted. <lb/>In the second part of the study the same criteria were used, <lb/>except that only patients meeting diagnostic criteria for <lb/>Bipolar Disorder Type I were included, and they had to be <lb/>on sodium valproate monotherapy. This was done to <lb/>examine Bipolar Type I patients in more detail, and to <lb/>remove a possible confounding variable. All patients had <lb/>to be euthymic for the previous 3 months, as determined <lb/>by interviews with the patient, and additional interviews <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Annals of General Hospital Psychiatry 2004, 3:13 <lb/>http://www.general-hospital-psychiatry.com/content/3/1/13 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 3 of 7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>

			<body>with their relatives and bipolar clinic records when avail-<lb/>able. MRS scans were carried out within 24 hours of this <lb/>interview. <lb/>Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy Methodology <lb/>For both studies magnetic resonance experiments were <lb/>performed using a Magnex 3 T scanner with 80 cm bore <lb/>equipped with actively shielded gradient, and spectrome-<lb/>ter control was provided by an Surrey Medical Imaging <lb/>System (SMIS) console. The subjects head was immobi-<lb/>lized with a restraint system. Signal transmission and <lb/>reception were achieved using a quadrature birdcage reso-<lb/>nator for 1 H measurements. <lb/>Part 1 -Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy <lb/>Initially, MRI data were acquired using gradient echo <lb/>imaging sequences to produce multiple slice images along <lb/>both coronal and transverse planes. This allowed registra-<lb/>tion of a 2 × 2 × 3 cm volume-of-interest (VOI) to be <lb/>selected in the temporal lobe. 1 H MR spectra were <lb/>acquired using the PRESS localization method [39,40], <lb/>with TE = 32 ms, TR = 3 s, and with 128 averages. Baseline <lb/>correction and deconvolution of the spectra was accom-<lb/>plished using the Peak Research (PERCH) spectrum anal-<lb/>ysis software package. The metabolite peaks of interest <lb/>[choline (Cho) and creatine (Cr)] in each spectrum were <lb/>fitted to a Gaussian line-shape for peak area estimation. <lb/>To determine changes in choline concentrations we exam-<lb/>ined the Cho/Cr ratio. Figure 1 shows an individual 1 H <lb/>MRS spectra in which all the major metabolite peaks can <lb/>be seen. <lb/>Study 2 -Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy <lb/>To accurately quantify the brain concentration of creatine <lb/>we used a 125 ml glass sphere containing a solution of 4 <lb/>mmol creatine as an external standard. The PRESS <lb/>sequence was used to acquire proton MRS data with TE1 <lb/>= 25 msec, TE2 = 25 msec, TR = 3000 msec, and 128 scan <lb/>averages. The MRS data were acquired from three 2 × 2 × <lb/>2 cm 3 voxels placed in the cortex of the left frontal lobe, <lb/>the cortex of the left temporal lobe, and in the external <lb/>standard solution. The average coordinates [41,42] of the <lb/>centers of the two brain voxels were determined: x = 0.5 <lb/>mm (SD = 1.6), y = 63.5 mm (SD = 12.1), z = -25.5 mm <lb/>(SD = 4.2) in the frontal lobe, and x= 32.2 mm (SD = 6.3), <lb/>y = 20.5 mm (SD = 3.9), z = 10.7 mm (SD = 2.6) in the <lb/>temporal lobe. In order to measure T 1 and T 2 values of the <lb/>metabolites in the brain and external standard solution, <lb/>MRS data were collected with different TE values at a con-<lb/>stant TR and different TR values at a constant TE both for <lb/>the healthy volunteers and the patients and also from <lb/>external standard solution [42]. However, due to these <lb/>constraints, the fact that the two studies used different <lb/>populations at different times, and the size of the external <lb/>125 ml container (which limited voxel size to 2 × 2 × 2 <lb/>cm 3 ), it was not possible to exactly match the voxel size or <lb/>location between the two studies. <lb/>MRS Data Analysis <lb/>For quantitative measurement of brain metabolite con-<lb/>centrations we used previously described methodology <lb/>[42,43]. In this, [Met] b , in millimoles per kg of wet brain, <lb/>the CSF volume fraction, f csf , in the spectroscopic voxels <lb/>must be corrected. Thus, brain metabolite concentrations <lb/>were calculated as described in the following equation: <lb/>where V voxel is the volume of a 8 cm 3 spectroscopic voxel <lb/>[43], and N b represents the number of metabolite mole-<lb/>cules per unit voxel in brain. <lb/>Statistical Analysis for both MRS studies <lb/>Means ± SEM were used in the statistical analysis. Sex dif-<lb/>ferences were analyzed using chi-squared, and age differ-<lb/>ences with ANOVA with post-hoc Tukey tests. The MRS <lb/>data was analyzed using Student&apos;s unpaired t-test using a <lb/>A typical 1 H-MRS spectrum of the human brain at 3.0 T. A <lb/>number of metabolites can be seen <lb/>Figure 1 <lb/>A typical 1 H-MRS spectrum of the human brain at 3.0 T. A <lb/>number of metabolites can be seen. 1: creatine (methylene) + <lb/>phosphocreatine, 2: glutamate + glutamine, 3: myo-inositol + <lb/>glycine, 4: taurine, 5: total choline compounds, 6: creatine <lb/>(methyl) + phosphocreatine, 7: N-acetylaspartate. <lb/>Met <lb/>N <lb/>1 f <lb/>V <lb/>b <lb/>b <lb/>csf <lb/>voxel <lb/>[ ] = − <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Annals of General Hospital Psychiatry 2004, 3:13 <lb/>http://www.general-hospital-psychiatry.com/content/3/1/13 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 4 of 7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>

			<body>significance level of p &lt; 0.05 comparing diagnostic groups <lb/>(patients vs controls) in each brain region (frontal and <lb/>temporal). <lb/>Results <lb/>Study 1 <lb/>Subjects <lb/>A total of 18 healthy controls, 14 bipolar patients taking <lb/>lithium, and 11 bipolar patients taking valproate com-<lb/>pleted this study. Of the 14 bipolar patients taking lith-<lb/>ium, 7 were Type I and 7 were Type II. In the valproate <lb/>group, 7 were Type I and 4 were Type II. These groups were <lb/>studied both separately and together, but as there were no <lb/>statistically significant differences between the Type I and <lb/>Type II patients, the results for both types are presented <lb/>together. Of the 14 bipolar patients taking lithium 12 <lb/>patients were taking other psychotropic medications: <lb/>these were benzodiazepines (7 patients), antidepressants <lb/>(5 patients), and antipsychotics (2 patients). Of the 11 <lb/>patients taking sodium valproate 10 patients were taking <lb/>other psychotropic medications: these were benzodi-<lb/>azepines (5 patients), antidepressants (5 patients), and <lb/>antipsychotics (4 patients). <lb/>The mean age for the lithium group was 40.43 ± 2.96 <lb/>years, for the valproate group 35.47 ± 2.27 years, and for <lb/>the control group was 31.35 ± 2.89 years. These differ-<lb/>ences were statistically significant (F = 3.68, df = 2, p = <lb/>&lt;0.05), which was attributable to the lithium group being <lb/>significantly older than the control group (Tukey post hoc, <lb/>p &lt; 0.05). <lb/>There were no gender differences within the groups: 10 <lb/>females and 8 males in the control group (χ 2 = 0.167, df <lb/>1, p &gt; 0.05), 5 females and 9 males in the lithium group <lb/>(χ 2 = 1.143, df 1, p &gt; 0.05), and 6 females and 5 males in <lb/>the valproate group (χ 2 = 0.474, df 1, p &gt; 0.05). <lb/>Mean serum lithium levels were 0.79 ± 0.06 mmol/l, and <lb/>the range was 0.46–1.08 mmol/l. The mean serum val-<lb/>proate levels were 508 ± 42 µmol/l, and the range was <lb/>210–912 µmol/l. <lb/>MRS Data <lb/>1 H MRS <lb/>We utilized the ratio of the choline peak to creatine peak <lb/>(Cho/Cr) as a primary correlate of Choline concentra-<lb/>tions. This result has been reported briefly in a previous <lb/>publication [38]. The mean Cho/Cr ratio with this meas-<lb/>ure was 1.46 ± 0.04 for controls, 1.18 ± 0.07 for lithium-<lb/>treated patients, and 1.12 ± 0.08 for valproate-treated <lb/>patients. These were statistically significant, with a reduc-<lb/>tion in ratios occurring in both the control vs. lithium <lb/>comparison (t = 3.628, df = 30, p = 0.001) and the control <lb/>vs. valproate comparison (t = 4.248, df = 27, p = 0.002). <lb/>Study 2 <lb/>Subjects <lb/>A total of 11 healthy controls and 9 Bipolar Type I patients <lb/>taking valproate as monotherapy were entered into this <lb/>study. The mean age for the control group was 37.3 ± 2.2 <lb/>years, and for the valproate patients 42.4 ± 3.0 years. <lb/>These differences were not statistically significant (F = <lb/>1.49, df = 1, p = 0.27). <lb/>There were no gender differences within the groups: 7 <lb/>females and 2 males in the valproate group and 5 females <lb/>and 6 males in the control group (χ 2 = 0.474, df 1, p &gt; <lb/>0.05). The mean serum valproate levels were 472 ± 36 <lb/>µmol/l, and the range was 284–728 µmol/l. <lb/>In the frontal lobe the mean choline concentration for the <lb/>healthy controls was 2.21 ± 0.17 mmol/kg wet brain and <lb/>for the patients was 2.38 ± 0.12 mmol/kg wet brain. In the <lb/>temporal lobe the mean choline concentration for the <lb/>healthy controls was 2.35 ± 0.14 mmol/kg wet brain and <lb/>for the patients was 2.40 ± 0.19 mmol/kg wet brain. There <lb/>were no statistically significant differences between the <lb/>controls and patients in either the frontal (t = 0.78, df = <lb/>18, p = 0.44) or temporal (t = 0.203 df = 18, p = 0.84) <lb/>lobes (Table 1). <lb/>The Cho/Cr ratios in the frontal lobes were 0.27 ± 0.028 <lb/>in controls and 0.28 ± 0.015 in patients. In the temporal <lb/>lobes the Cho/Cr ratios were 0.26 ± 0.021 in controls and <lb/>0.28 ± 0.016 in patients. There were no statistically signif-<lb/>icant differences between the controls and patients in <lb/>either the frontal (t = 0.367, df = 18, p = 0.72) or temporal <lb/>(t = 0.539, df = 18, p = 0.59) lobes (Table 1). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>The results from the present study vary considerably <lb/>between the two sections utilizing differing methodolo-<lb/>gies. This is despite the fact that both studies were carried <lb/>out by the same group on the same scanner with bipolar <lb/>patients coming from the same patient pool. This strongly <lb/>suggests that the methodology used to determine choline <lb/>concentrations can considerably alter the results. In the <lb/>first part of the study we found that both the lithium-<lb/>treated and valproate-treated patients had significantly <lb/>reduced Cho/Cr peak ratios compared to controls. This is <lb/>similar to the findings from one previous study which also <lb/>suggested that there may be a trend towards decreased <lb/>choline in grey matter [28]. This study was a frontal lobe <lb/>study that measured metabolite concentrations in a 1.5 T <lb/>scanner in bipolar type I patients hospitalized for manic <lb/>(n = 9) or mixed (n = 8) states. In this study most patients <lb/>were being treated with valproate and an atypical <lb/>antipsychotic. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Annals of General Hospital Psychiatry 2004, 3:13 <lb/>http://www.general-hospital-psychiatry.com/content/3/1/13 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 5 of 7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>

			<body>These findings, however, differ from those in the second <lb/>part of the present study in which we found no differences <lb/>in choline concentrations between valproate-treated <lb/>patients and controls in either frontal or temporal lobes. <lb/>This second part of the study was much better controlled <lb/>in terms of the patients receiving valproate monotherapy, <lb/>only including bipolar Type I patients, and in using an <lb/>external choline solution to accurately quantify choline <lb/>concentrations. This finding of a lack of change is also in <lb/>keeping with most previous studies. Several studies which <lb/>have also previously measured metabolite concentrations <lb/>with 1.5 T scanners also found no changes. These include <lb/>a study of the hippocampus in 15 euthymic bipolar type <lb/>1 patients, of whom 10 were taking either lithium or val-<lb/>proate [19], a study of basal ganglia in 8 rapid cycling <lb/>patients on lithium [22], a study of the anterior cingulate <lb/>in 10 bipolar children [23], and a study in frontal lobes of <lb/>23 euthymic bipolar patients of whom 13 were on lithium <lb/>[25]. Several other studies have examined metabolite <lb/>ratios, mostly in patients on lithium, and those also found <lb/>no changes in choline concentrations [20,21,26,27]. In a <lb/>study using metabolite ratios in bipolar children who <lb/>were off medication for at least one week there was also <lb/>no change in choline concentrations [24]. In a double-<lb/>blind placebo-controlled human volunteer study before <lb/>and after one week of lithium administration we also <lb/>found no changes in cholinein 10 volunteers [30], which <lb/>is similar to a patient study which compared 7 patients on <lb/>lithium to 6 non-lithium treated controls and in which no <lb/>differences were seen [29]. <lb/>In contrast, animal studies have suggested that lithium <lb/>may increase brain choline concentrations, and in lith-<lb/>ium-treated patients it also increases the accumulation of <lb/>choline within erythrocytes [4-7]. Nonetheless, 1 H-MRS <lb/>studies in patients examining this possibility is mixed. To <lb/>date 6 studies have suggested some support for this [13-<lb/>18], but in none of these studies were metabolite <lb/>concentrations measured, and most of the studies meas-<lb/>ured choline/creatine ratios [14-18], the other one meas-<lb/>uring metabolite intensity/tissue volume [13]. The first <lb/>study to examine brain choline in basal ganglia studied <lb/>only 4 patients, all of whom were on lithium [18]. <lb/>Another study examined 19 euthymic inpatients and <lb/>found increased choline/creatine ratios in basal ganglia, <lb/>but only 10 of these patients were receiving lithium [17]. <lb/>Table 1: Concentrations (mmol/kg wet brain) and ratios (Cho/Cre) in frontal and temporal lobes in healthy volunteers and in patients <lb/>chronically treated with valproate (Study #2) <lb/>Choline (Cho) <lb/>Creatine (Cre) <lb/>Cho/Cre <lb/>Frontal <lb/>Temporal <lb/>Frontal <lb/>Temporal <lb/>Frontal <lb/>Temporal <lb/>Healthy Controls <lb/>Age <lb/>Sex <lb/>1 <lb/>50 <lb/>M <lb/>3.51 <lb/>2.95 <lb/>6.67 <lb/>8.53 <lb/>0.53 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>2 <lb/>45 <lb/>M <lb/>2.19 <lb/>3.03 <lb/>10.1 <lb/>9.11 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>0.33 <lb/>3 <lb/>43 <lb/>F <lb/>3.01 <lb/>2.31 <lb/>9.97 <lb/>9.52 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>4 <lb/>39 <lb/>M <lb/>2.11 <lb/>2.72 <lb/>7.94 <lb/>7.60 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>5 <lb/>37 <lb/>F <lb/>2.47 <lb/>2.34 <lb/>9.98 <lb/>9.89 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>6 <lb/>36 <lb/>F <lb/>1.91 <lb/>1.76 <lb/>8.28 <lb/>8.19 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>7 <lb/>35 <lb/>M <lb/>1.76 <lb/>2.36 <lb/>7.93 <lb/>8.36 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>8 <lb/>32 <lb/>F <lb/>1.88 <lb/>1.51 <lb/>9.56 <lb/>9.56 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>9 <lb/>32 <lb/>M <lb/>1.94 <lb/>2.14 <lb/>7.04 <lb/>7.79 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>10 <lb/>30 <lb/>F <lb/>1.82 <lb/>2.52 <lb/>7.8 <lb/>8.63 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>1 1 <lb/>2 8 <lb/>M <lb/>1 . 7 2 <lb/>2 . 2 3 <lb/>7 . 1 6 <lb/>8 . 5 1 <lb/>0 . 2 4 <lb/>0 . 2 6 <lb/>Mean <lb/>37.00 <lb/>2.21 <lb/>2.35 <lb/>8.40 <lb/>8.70 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>Valproate Treated Patients <lb/>1 <lb/>58 <lb/>F <lb/>2.72 <lb/>2.1 <lb/>9.16 <lb/>10.13 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>2 <lb/>50 <lb/>M <lb/>2.61 <lb/>3.42 <lb/>8.17 <lb/>10.53 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>0.33 <lb/>3 <lb/>49 <lb/>F <lb/>2.03 <lb/>1.79 <lb/>8.56 <lb/>7.48 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>4 <lb/>48 <lb/>F <lb/>2.44 <lb/>1.88 <lb/>9.93 <lb/>8.19 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>5 <lb/>36 <lb/>M <lb/>2.60 <lb/>2.53 <lb/>7.84 <lb/>7.51 <lb/>0.33 <lb/>0.34 <lb/>6 <lb/>35 <lb/>F <lb/>2.07 <lb/>2.77 <lb/>9.26 <lb/>10.39 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>7 <lb/>35 <lb/>F <lb/>2.78 <lb/>1.89 <lb/>8.35 <lb/>9.79 <lb/>0.33 <lb/>0.19 <lb/>8 <lb/>34 <lb/>F <lb/>1.76 <lb/>2.93 <lb/>7.26 <lb/>8.01 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>0.37 <lb/>9 <lb/>34 <lb/>F <lb/>2.43 <lb/>2.27 <lb/>7.75 <lb/>7.23 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>Mean <lb/>42.11 <lb/>2.38 <lb/>2.40 <lb/>8.48 <lb/>8.81 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>0.28 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Annals of General Hospital Psychiatry 2004, 3:13 <lb/>http://www.general-hospital-psychiatry.com/content/3/1/13 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 6 of 7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>

			<body>The third study to report an increase in this ratio (in this <lb/>case in the left subcortical region) was in a mixed group of <lb/>patients receiving a wide range of medications [16]. Two <lb/>other studies have reported increased choline concentra-<lb/>tions, but only in limited circumstances. In one study in <lb/>11 bipolar children patients were examined before and <lb/>after lithium administration [14]. There were no signifi-<lb/>cant findings before or after lithium administration, <lb/>although there was a trend towards increased choline/cre-<lb/>atine ratios in the patients before lithium treatment. This <lb/>latter finding does not suggest that in patients lithium sig-<lb/>nificantly alters the choline/creatine ratio. The final study <lb/>examined 15 euthymic males who were on either lithium <lb/>or valproate [13]. This study found that thalamic choline <lb/>concentrations, determined by measuring metabolite <lb/>intensity/tissue volume ratios, were significantly <lb/>increased only if the right and left hemisphere were com-<lb/>pared separately, but not if they were compared together. <lb/>It is also conceivable that both lithium and valproate may <lb/>increase Choline concentrations, but that the differences <lb/>were not large enough for us to detect, or that without lith-<lb/>ium or valproate treatment patients would have lower <lb/>Choline concentrations. The cross-sectional nature of this <lb/>study does not allow this to be examined. It is also impor-<lb/>tant to recognize other limitations of the present study. <lb/>Firstly, these MRS studies are not pre-and post-treat-<lb/>ments, so may not accurately reflect changes that occur in <lb/>individual patients. Secondly, part of the study used a <lb/>ratio-method to assess choline concentrations, the limita-<lb/>tions of which are increasingly clear (particularly since <lb/>creatine concentrations may be altered by medication <lb/> [37]). Thirdly, the sizes of all groups are small and it there-<lb/>fore possible that a larger study may have been fully pow-<lb/>ered to identify differences between groups. Fourthly, <lb/>several patients in the first study (but not the second <lb/>study) were on other drugs which may have affected the <lb/>results of this study. Fifthly, we have not determined if age <lb/>affects the results, and in the first part the groups were not <lb/>all matched for age. In addition, the voxel locations were <lb/>not the same in both studies due to the reasons discussed <lb/>in the methodology section. Nonetheless, despite these <lb/>limitations we believe the results add significantly to the <lb/>literature in this under-researched area. <lb/>We conclude that, taking all current evidence together <lb/>including the findings from the present study, it is <lb/>unlikely that either lithium or valproate significantly alter <lb/>brain choline concentrations. However, given the large <lb/>differences in patients populations, medications received, <lb/>and MRS methodologies it is difficult to directly compare <lb/>all these studies. In addition, the methodology used to <lb/>measure choline concentrations can significantly alter the <lb/>results. Future MRS studies in bipolar patients should, <lb/>therefore, examine metabolite concentrations rather than <lb/>a ratio of choline compared to other metabolites. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests <lb/>None declared. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>This work was supported in part by peer-reviewed grants from the Cana-<lb/>dian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR) and the Alberta Heritage Foun-<lb/>dation for Medical Research (AHFMR). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. <lb/>Vestergaard P, Licht RW: 50 Years with lithium treatment in <lb/>affective disorders: present problems and priorities. World J <lb/>Biol Psychiatry 2001, 2:18-26. <lb/>2. <lb/>Lingsch C, Martin K: An irreversible effect of lithium adminis-<lb/>tration to patients. Br J Pharmacol 1976, 57:323-7. <lb/>3. <lb/>Uney JB, Marchbanks RM, Reynolds GP, Perry RH: Lithium proph-<lb/>ylaxis inhibits choline transport in post-mortem brain. Lancet <lb/>1986, 2(Aug 23):458. <lb/>4. <lb/>Jope RS, Jenden DJ, Ehrlich BE, Diamond JM: Choline accumulates <lb/>in erythrocytes during lithium therapy. N Engl J Med 1978, <lb/>299:833-834. <lb/>5. <lb/>Brinkman SD, Pomara N, Barnett N, Block R, Domino EF, Gershon S: <lb/>Lithium-induced increases in red blood cell choline and <lb/>memory performance in Alzheimer-type dementia. Biol <lb/>Psychiatry 1984, 19:157-64. <lb/>6. <lb/>Domino EF, Sharp RR, Lipper S, Ballast CL, Delidow B, Bronzo MR: <lb/>NMR chemistry analysis of red blood cell constituents in nor-<lb/>mal subjects and lithium-treated psychiatric patients. Biol <lb/>Psychiatry 1985, 20:1277-1283. <lb/>7. <lb/>Stoll AL, Cohen BM, Hanin I: Erythrocyte choline concentra-<lb/>tions in psychiatric disorders. Biol Psychiatry 1991, 29:309-321. <lb/>8. <lb/>Sartorius A, Neumann-Haefelin C, Bollmayr B, Hoehn M, Henn FA: <lb/>Choline rise in the rat hippocampus induced by electrocon-<lb/>vulsive shock treatment. Biol Psychiat 2003, 53:620-623. <lb/>9. <lb/>Leiva DB: The neurochemistry of mania: a hypothesis of etiol-<lb/>ogy and rationale for treatment. Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol <lb/>Psychiatry 1990, 14:423-9. <lb/>10. Stoll AL, Sachs GS, Cohen BM, Lafer B, Christensen JD, Renshaw PF: <lb/>Choline in the treatment of rapid-cycling bipolar disorder: <lb/>clinical and neurochemical findings in lithium-treated <lb/>patients. Biol Psychiat 1996, 40:382-8. <lb/>11. Stoll AL, Renshaw PF, De Micheli E, Wurtman R, Pillay SS, Cohen BM: <lb/>Choline ingestion increases the resonance of choline-con-<lb/>taining compounds in human brain: an in vivo proton mag-<lb/>netic resonance study. Biol Psychiat 1995, 37:170-4. <lb/>12. Cohen BM, Renshaw PF, Stoll AL, Wurtman RJ, Yurgelun-Todd D, <lb/>Babb SM: Decreased brain choline uptake in older adults. An <lb/>in vivo proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy study. JAMA <lb/>1995, 274:902-7. <lb/>13. Deicken RF, Eliaz Y, Feiwell R, Schuff N: Increased thalamic N -<lb/>acetylaspartate in male patients with familial bipolar I <lb/>disorder. Psychiatry Res 2001, 106:35-45. <lb/>14. Davanzo P, Thomas MA, Yue K, Oshiro T, Belin T, Strober M, <lb/>McCracken J: Decreased anterior cingulated myo-inositol/cre-<lb/>atine spectroscopy resonance with lithium treatment in chil-<lb/>dren with bipolar disorder. Neuropsychopharmacology 2001, <lb/>24:359-369. <lb/>15. Moore CM, Breeze JL, Gruber SA, Babb SM, deB Frederick B, Villafu-<lb/>erte RA, Stoll AL, Hennen J, Yurgelun-Todd DA, Cohen BM, Renshaw <lb/>PF: Choline, myo-inositol and mood in bipolar disorder: a <lb/>proton magnetic resonance spectroscopic imaging study of <lb/>the anterior cingulate cortex. Bipolar Disord 2000, 2:207-216. <lb/>16. Hamakawa H, Kato T, Murashita J, Kato N: Quantitative proton <lb/>magnetic resonance spectroscopy of the basal ganglia in <lb/>patients with affective disorders. Eur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci <lb/>1998, 248:53-58. <lb/>17. Kato T, Hamakawa H, Shioiri T, Murashita J, Takahashi Y, Takahashi <lb/>S, Inubushi T: Choline-containing compounds detected by pro-<lb/>ton magnetic resonance spectroscopy in the basal ganglia in <lb/>bipolar disorder. J Psychiatry Neurosci 1996, 21:248-254. <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">Publish with Bio Med Central and every <lb/>scientist can read your work free of charge <lb/>&quot;BioMed Central will be the most significant development for <lb/>disseminating the results of biomedical researc h in our lifetime.&quot; <lb/>Sir Paul Nurse, Cancer Research UK <lb/>Your research papers will be: <lb/>available free of charge to the entire biomedical community <lb/>peer reviewed and published immediately upon acceptance <lb/>cited in PubMed and archived on PubMed Central <lb/>yours — you keep the copyright <lb/>Submit your manuscript here: <lb/>http://www.biomedcentral.com/info/publishing_adv.asp <lb/>BioMedcentral <lb/>Annals of General Hospital Psychiatry 2004, 3:13 <lb/>http://www.general-hospital-psychiatry.com/content/3/1/13 <lb/></div>

			<page>Page 7 of 7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purposes) <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>18. Sharma R, Venkatasubramanian PN, Barany M, Davis JM: Proton <lb/>magnetic resonance spectroscopy of the brain in schizo-<lb/>phrenic and affective patients. Schizophr Res 1992, 8:43-49. <lb/>19. Deicken RF, Pegues MP, Anzalone S, Feiwell R, Soher B: Lower con-<lb/>centration of hippocampal N-acetylaspartate in familial <lb/>bipolar I disorder. Am J Psychiat 2003, 160:873-882. <lb/>20. Bertolino A, Frye M, Callicott JH, Mattay VS, Rakow R, Shelton-<lb/>Repella J, Post R, Weinberger DR: Neuronal pathology in the hip-<lb/>pocampal area of patients with bipolar disorder: a study with <lb/>proton magnetic resonance spectroscopic imaging. Biol <lb/>Psychiat 2003, 53:906-913. <lb/>21. Chang K, Adleman N, Dienes K, Barnea-Goraly N, Reiss A, Ketter T: <lb/>Decreased N-acetylaspartate in children with familial bipo-<lb/>lar disorder. Biol Psychiat 2003, 53:1059-1065. <lb/>22. Lyoo IK, Demopulos CM, Hirashima F, Ahn KW, Renshaw PF: Oral <lb/>choline decreases brain purine levels in lithium-treated sub-<lb/>jects with rapid-cycling bipolar disorder: a double-blind trial <lb/>using proton and lithium magnetic resonance spectroscopy. <lb/>Bipolar Disord 2003, 5:300-306. <lb/>23. Davanzo P, Yue K, Thomas MA, Belin T, Mintz J, Venkatraman TN, <lb/>Santoro E, Barnett S, McCracken J: Proton magnetic spectros-<lb/>copy of bipolar disorder versus intermittent explosive disor-<lb/>der in children and adolescents. Am J Psychiatry 2003, 160:. <lb/>24. Castillo M, Kwock L, Courvoisie H, Hooper SR: Proton MR spec-<lb/>troscopy in children with bipolar affective disorder: prelimi-<lb/>nary observations. Am J Neuroradiol 2000, 21:832-838. <lb/>25. Hamakawa H, Kato T, Shioiri T, Inubushi T, Kato N: Quantitative <lb/>proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy of the bilateral <lb/>frontal lobes in patients with bipolar disorder. Psychological Med <lb/>1999, 29:639-644. <lb/>26. Ohara K, Isoda H, Suzuki Y, Takehara Y, Ochiai M, Takeda H, Igarashi <lb/>Y, Ohara K: Proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy of the <lb/>lenticular nuclei in bipolar I affective disorder. Psych Res Neu-<lb/>roimag Sect 1998, 84:55-60. <lb/>27. Bruhn H, Stoppe G, Staedt J, Merboldt KD, Hänicke W, Frahm J: <lb/>Quantitative proton MRS in vivo shows cerebral myo -inosi-<lb/>tol and cholines to be unchanged in manic-depressive <lb/>patients treated with lithium [abstract]. Proc Soc Mag Res Med <lb/>1993:1543. <lb/>28. Cecil KM, DelBello MP, Morey R, Strakowski SM: Frontal lobe dif-<lb/>ferences in bipolar disorder as determined by proton MR <lb/>spectroscopy. Bipolar Dis 2002, 4:357-365. <lb/>29. Stoll AL, Renshaw PF, Sachs GS, Guimaraes AR, Miller C, Cohen BM, <lb/>Lafer B, Gonzalez RG: The human brain resonance of choline-<lb/>containing compounds is similar in patients receiving lithium <lb/>treatment and controls: an in vivo proton magnetic reso-<lb/>nance spectroscopy study. Biol Psychiatry 1992, 32:944-949. <lb/>30. Silverstone PH, Hanstock CC, Rotzinger S: Lithium does not alter <lb/>the choline/creatine ratio in the temporal lobe of human vol-<lb/>unteers as measured by proton magnetic resonance <lb/>spectroscopy. J Psychiatry Neurosci 1999, 24:222-226. <lb/>31. Stoll AL, Renshaw PF, Yurgelun-Todd DA, Cohen BM: Neuroimag-<lb/>ing in bipolar disorder: what have we learned? Biol Psychiatry <lb/>2000, 48:505-517. <lb/>32. Strakowski SM, DelBello MP, Adler C, Cecil KM, Saz KW: Neuroim-<lb/>aging in bipolar disorder. Bipolar Disord 2000, 2:148-164. <lb/>33. Pies R: Combining lithium and anticonvulsants in bipolar dis-<lb/>order: a review. Ann Clin Psychiatry 2002, 14:223-232. <lb/>34. Sher PK, Neale EA, Graubard BI, Habig WH, Fitzgerald SC, Nelson <lb/>PG: Differential neurochemical effects of chronic exposure of <lb/>cerebral cortical cell culture to valproic acid, diazepam, or <lb/>ethosuximide. Pediatr Neurol 1985, 1:232-7. <lb/>35. Moore CM, Breeze JL, Gruber SA, Babb SM, deB Frederick B, Villafu-<lb/>erte RA, Stoll AL, Hennen J, Yurgelun-Todd DA, Cohen BM, Renshaw <lb/>PF: Choline, myo-inositol and mood in bipolar disorder: a <lb/>proton magnetic resonance spectroscopic imaging study of <lb/>the anterior cingulate cortex. Bipolar Disord 2000, 2:207-216. <lb/>36. Simister RJ, McLean MA, Barker GJ, Duncan JS: Proton MRS <lb/>reveals frontal lobe metabolite abnormalities in idiopathic <lb/>generalized epilepsy. Neurology 2003, 61:897-902. <lb/>37. O&apos;Donnell T, Rotzinger S, Nakashima TT, Hanstock CC, Ulrich M, Sil-<lb/>verstone PH: Chronic lithium and sodium valproate both <lb/>decrease the concentration of myo-inositol and increase the <lb/>concentration of inositol monophosphates in rat brain. Brain <lb/>Research 2000, 880:84-91. <lb/>38. Silverstone PH, Asghar SJ, O&apos;Donnell T, Ulrich M, Hanstock CC: <lb/>Lithium protects against dextro-amphetamine induced <lb/>brain choline concentration changes in bipolar disorder <lb/>patients. World J Biol Psychiat 2004, 5:35-41. <lb/>39. Gordon RE, Ordidge RJ: Volume selection for high resolution <lb/>NMR studies [abstract]. Proc Soc Magn Reson Med 1984:272. <lb/>40. Bottomley PA: Spatial localization in NMR spectroscopy in <lb/>vivo. Ann NY Acad Sci 1987, 508:333-348. <lb/>41. Talairach J, Tournoux P: Co-planar stereotaxic atlas of the <lb/>human brain. New York: Thieme Medical 1988:51-110. <lb/>42. Huang W, Alexander GE, Daly EM, Shetty HU, Krasuski JS, Rapoport <lb/>SI, Schapiro MB: High brain myo -inositol levels in the prede-<lb/>mentia phase of Alzheimer&apos;s disease in adults with Down&apos;s <lb/>syndrome: a 1 H MRS study. Am J Psychiatry 1999, 156:1879-1886. <lb/>43. Vermathen P, Capizzano AA, Maudsley AA: Administration and <lb/>(1)H MRS detection of histidine in human brain: application <lb/>to in vivo pH measurement. Magn Reson Med 2000, 43:665-675. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
