<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Evidence for Non-Exponential Elastic Proton-Proton Differential <lb/>Cross-Section at Low |t| and <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 8 TeV by TOTEM <lb/> The TOTEM Collaboration <lb/>G. Antchev <lb/> 1 <lb/> , P. Aspell <lb/> q <lb/> , I. Atanassov <lb/> 1 <lb/> , V. Avati <lb/> q <lb/> , J. Baechler <lb/> q <lb/> , V. Berardi <lb/> j,i <lb/> , M. Berretti <lb/> q,o <lb/> , <lb/>E. Bossini <lb/> o <lb/> , U. Bottigli <lb/> o <lb/> , M. Bozzo <lb/> l <lb/> , A. Buzzo <lb/> l <lb/> , F. S. Cafagna <lb/> i <lb/> , C. E. Campanella <lb/> k,i <lb/> , <lb/>M. G. Catanesi <lb/> i <lb/> , M. Csanád <lb/> g,2 <lb/> , T. Csörg˝ o <lb/> g,h <lb/> , M. Deile <lb/> q <lb/> , F. De Leonardis <lb/> k,i <lb/> , A. D&apos;Orazio <lb/> k,i <lb/> , <lb/>M. Doubek <lb/> c <lb/> , K. Eggert <lb/> r <lb/> , V. Eremin <lb/> 5 <lb/> , F. Ferro <lb/> l <lb/> , A. Fiergolski <lb/> i,4 <lb/> , F. Garcia <lb/> e <lb/> , V. Georgiev <lb/> a <lb/> , <lb/>S. Giani <lb/> q <lb/> , L. Grzanka <lb/> p,3 <lb/> , C. Guaragnella <lb/> k,i <lb/> , J. Hammerbauer <lb/> a <lb/> , J. Heino <lb/> e <lb/> , A. Karev <lb/> q <lb/> , J. Kašpar <lb/> b,q <lb/> , <lb/>J. Kopal <lb/> b <lb/> , V. Kundrát <lb/> b <lb/> , S. Lami <lb/> n <lb/> , G. Latino <lb/> o <lb/> , R. Lauhakangas <lb/> e <lb/> , E. Lippmaa <lb/> d <lb/> , J. Lippmaa <lb/> d <lb/> , <lb/>M. V. Lokajíček <lb/> b <lb/> , L. Losurdo <lb/> o <lb/> , M. Lo Vetere <lb/> m,l <lb/> , F. Lucas Rodríguez <lb/> q <lb/> , M. Macrí <lb/> l <lb/> , A. Mercadante <lb/> i <lb/> , <lb/>N. Minafra <lb/> q,j <lb/> , S. Minutoli <lb/> l <lb/> , T. Naaranoja <lb/> e,f <lb/> , F. Nemes <lb/> g,2 <lb/> , H. Niewiadomski <lb/> r <lb/> , E. Oliveri <lb/> q <lb/> , <lb/>F. Oljemark <lb/> e,f <lb/> , R. Orava <lb/> e,f <lb/> , M. Oriunno <lb/> 6 <lb/> , K. ¨ <lb/>Osterberg <lb/> e,f <lb/> , P. Palazzi <lb/> q <lb/> , V. Passaro <lb/> k,i <lb/> , Z. Peroutka <lb/> a <lb/> , <lb/>V. Petruzzelli <lb/> k,i <lb/> , T. Politi <lb/> k,i <lb/> , J. Procházka <lb/> b <lb/> , F. Prudenzano <lb/> k,i <lb/> , M. Quinto <lb/> i,j <lb/> , E. Radermacher <lb/> q <lb/> , <lb/>E. Radicioni <lb/> i <lb/> , F. Ravotti <lb/> q <lb/> , E. Robutti <lb/> l <lb/> , L. Ropelewski <lb/> q <lb/> , G. Ruggiero <lb/> q <lb/> , H. Saarikko <lb/> e,f <lb/> , <lb/>A. Scribano <lb/> n <lb/> , J. Smajek <lb/> q <lb/> , W. Snoeys <lb/> q <lb/> , T. Sodzawiczny <lb/> q <lb/> , J. Sziklai <lb/> g <lb/> , C. Taylor <lb/> r <lb/> , N. Turini <lb/> o <lb/> , <lb/>V. Vacek <lb/> c <lb/> , J. Welti <lb/> e,f <lb/> , P. Wyszkowski <lb/> p <lb/> , K. Zielinski <lb/> p <lb/> a <lb/> University of West Bohemia, Pilsen, Czech Republic. <lb/> b <lb/> Institute of Physics of the Academy of Sciences of the Czech Republic, Praha, Czech Republic. <lb/> c <lb/> Czech Technical University, Praha, Czech Republic. <lb/> d <lb/> National Institute of Chemical Physics and Biophysics NICPB, Tallinn, Estonia. <lb/> e <lb/> Helsinki Institute of Physics, Helsinki, Finland. <lb/> f <lb/> Department of Physics, University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland. <lb/> g <lb/> Wigner Research Centre for Physics, RMKI, Budapest, Hungary. <lb/> h <lb/> KRF University College, Gyöngyös, Hungary. <lb/> i <lb/> INFN Sezione di Bari, Bari, Italy. <lb/> j <lb/> Dipartimento Interateneo di Fisica di Bari, Bari, Italy. <lb/> k <lb/> Dipartimento di Ingegneria Elettrica e dell&apos;Informazione -Politecnico di Bari, Bari, Italy. <lb/> l <lb/> INFN Sezione di Genova, Genova, Italy. <lb/> m <lb/> Universià degli Studi di Genova, Italy. <lb/> n <lb/> INFN Sezione di Pisa, Pisa, Italy. <lb/> o <lb/> Universià degli Studi di Siena and Gruppo Collegato INFN di Siena, Siena, Italy. <lb/> p <lb/> AGH University of Science and Technology, Krakow, Poland. <lb/> q <lb/> CERN, Geneva, Switzerland. <lb/> r <lb/> Case Western Reserve University, Dept. of Physics, Cleveland, OH, USA. <lb/> 1 <lb/> INRNE-BAS, Institute for Nuclear Research and Nuclear Energy, Bulgarian Academy of Sciences, Sofia, Bul-<lb/>garia. <lb/> 2 <lb/> Department of Atomic Physics, ELTE University, Budapest, Hungary. <lb/> 3 <lb/> Institute of Nuclear Physics, Polish Academy of Science, Krakow, Poland. <lb/> 4 <lb/> Warsaw University of Technology, Warsaw, Poland. <lb/> 5 <lb/> Ioffe Physical -Technical Institute of Russian Academy of Sciences, St. Petersburg, Russian Federation. <lb/> 6 <lb/> SLAC National Accelerator Laboratory, Stanford CA, USA. <lb/> Preprint submitted to Nuclear Physics B <lb/>April 13, 2015 <lb/> arXiv:1503.08111v2  [hep-ex] 9 Apr 2015 <lb/> Abstract <lb/> The TOTEM experiment has made a precise measurement of the elastic proton-proton differential <lb/>cross-section at the centre-of-mass energy <lb/> √ s = 8 TeV based on a high-statistics data sample <lb/>obtained with the β <lb/>  * <lb/> = 90 m optics. Both the statistical and systematic uncertainties remain below <lb/>1 %, except for the t-independent contribution from the overall normalisation. This unprecedented <lb/>precision allows to exclude a purely exponential differential cross-section in the range of four-<lb/>momentum transfer squared 0.027 &lt; |t| &lt; 0.2 GeV <lb/> 2 <lb/> with a significance greater than 7 σ. Two <lb/>extended parametrisations, with quadratic and cubic polynomials in the exponent, are shown to be <lb/>well compatible with the data. Using them for the differential cross-section extrapolation to t = 0, <lb/>and further applying the optical theorem, yields total cross-section estimates of (100.8 ± 2.1) mb <lb/>and (101.2 ± 2.1) mb, respectively, in agreement with previous TOTEM measurements. <lb/> Keywords: proton-proton interactions, elastic scattering, total cross-section, LHC, TOTEM <lb/> PACS: 13.60.Hb <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> The differential cross-section dσ/dt of hadronic proton-(anti)proton scattering at low |t| has <lb/>traditionally been parametrised with a simple exponential function, e <lb/> −B|t| <lb/> , giving a satisfactory <lb/>description of all past experimental data. Nonetheless, a few experiments have already reported <lb/>about hints of slight deviations from this behaviour. At the ISR, for <lb/> √ s between 21.5 GeV and <lb/>52.8 GeV, elastic pp and partly ¯ <lb/>pp data have shown a change of slope [1, 2] or have been better <lb/>parametrised with quadratic exponential functions, e <lb/> −B|t|−Ct  2 [3, 4]. At the S¯ ppS, for <lb/> √ s = 546 GeV, <lb/>a change of slope at |t| ≈ 0.14 GeV <lb/> 2 <lb/> has been observed, while the inclusion of a quadratic term in <lb/>the exponent did not improve the fit significantly [5]. At the Tevatron [6, 7, 8, 9] no deviations from <lb/>pure exponential functions were observed, except at larger |t| where the influence of the shoulder <lb/>(∼ 0.8 GeV <lb/> 2 <lb/> at <lb/> √ s = 0.546 TeV and ∼ 0.6 GeV <lb/> 2 <lb/> at 1.8 and 1.96 TeV) becomes visible. At the <lb/>LHC, at 7 TeV as well as at 8 TeV, all data published so far [10, 11, 12, 13] have been compatible <lb/>with a pure exponential shape. <lb/>This report presents a new data sample of elastic scattering at the energy of <lb/> √ s = 8 TeV. <lb/>Thanks to its high statistics, an unprecedented precision has been reached in the region 0.027 <lb/> |t|  0.2 GeV <lb/> 2 <lb/> . Both the statistical and systematic components of the differential cross-section <lb/>uncertainty are controlled at a level below 1 %, except for the overall normalisation (Section 5.2.6). <lb/>Consequently, the functional form of the cross-section can be strongly constrained, thus having <lb/>more impact on theoretical model building and, in particular, on the extrapolation to t = 0 used for <lb/>total cross-section determination. Neglecting the influence of Coulomb scattering in the observed <lb/>range, the often used purely exponential extrapolation has been found inadequate, and extended <lb/>parametrisations are provided, still yielding total cross-section values compatible with the previous <lb/>TOTEM results [12] at the same energy. <lb/>This article is organised as follows. Section 2 outlines the detector apparatus used for this <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body> measurement. Section 3 summarises the data-taking conditions; details on the LHC beam optics <lb/>are given in Section 4. Section 5 describes the data analysis and reconstruction of the differential <lb/>cross-section. In Section 6 three parametrisations of the differential cross-section are tested, and <lb/>from those compatible with data the total cross-section is derived. The results are summarised in <lb/>Section 7. <lb/> 2. Experimental Apparatus <lb/> The TOTEM experiment is located at the LHC interaction point (IP) 5 together with the CMS <lb/>experiment. In this article only the Roman Pot (RP) system, the sub-detector relevant for elastic <lb/>scattering measurement, is outlined, whereas TOTEM&apos;s full experimental apparatus is described <lb/>elsewhere [14]. RPs are movable beam-pipe insertions that approach the LHC beam very closely <lb/>in order to detect particles scattered to very small angles. They are organised in two stations placed <lb/>symmetrically around the IP: one on the left side (in LHC sector 45), one on the right (sector 56). <lb/>Each station is formed by two units: near (214 m from the IP) and far (220 m). Each unit includes <lb/>three RPs: one approaching the beam from the top, one from the bottom and one horizontally. <lb/>Each RP hosts a stack of 10 silicon strip sensors (pitch 66 µm) with strongly reduced insensitive <lb/>region at the edge facing the beam (few tens of micrometres). The sensors are equipped with <lb/>trigger-capable electronics. Since elastic scattering events consist of two anti-parallel protons, the <lb/>detected events can have two topologies, called diagonals: 45 bottom – 56 top and 45 top – 56 <lb/>bottom. <lb/>This report will use a reference frame where x denotes the horizontal axis (pointing out of <lb/>the LHC ring), y the vertical axis (pointing against gravity) and z the beam axis (in the clockwise <lb/>direction). <lb/> 3. Data Taking <lb/> The measurement presented here is based on data taken in July 2012, during the LHC fill num-<lb/>ber 2836 providing protons colliding at the centre-of-mass energy <lb/> √ s = 8 TeV. The vertical RPs <lb/>were inserted at a distance of 9.5 times the transverse beam size, σ  beam . Initially two, later three <lb/>colliding bunch-pairs were used, each with a typical population of 8 · 10 <lb/> 10 <lb/> protons, yielding an in-<lb/>stantaneous luminosity of about 10 <lb/> 28 <lb/> cm <lb/> −2 <lb/> s <lb/> −1 <lb/> per bunch. The main trigger required a coincidence <lb/>between the RPs in both arms, combining the near and far units of a station in OR to ensure maxi-<lb/>mal efficiency. During the about 11 h long data-taking, a luminosity of 735 µb <lb/> −1 <lb/> was accumulated, <lb/>giving 7.2 · 10 <lb/> 6 <lb/> tagged elastic events. <lb/> 4. Beam Optics <lb/> The beam optics relates the proton state at the IP to its state at the RP location. At the IP, the <lb/>direction of a proton can be described by the scattering angle θ <lb/>  * <lb/> (with respect to the z axis) and <lb/>azimuthal angle φ <lb/>  * <lb/> (about the z axis). Alternatively, the horizontal (x) and vertical (y) projections <lb/>of the scattering angle can be used: <lb/> θ <lb/>  * <lb/> x  = θ <lb/>  * <lb/> cos φ <lb/>  * <lb/> , <lb/>θ <lb/>  * <lb/> y  = θ <lb/>  * <lb/> sin φ <lb/>  * <lb/> . <lb/> (1) <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body> Table 1: Optical functions for elastic proton transport. The values refer to the right arm, for the left one they are very <lb/>similar. <lb/> unit <lb/> L  x <lb/> v x <lb/> L y <lb/> v y <lb/> near <lb/>2.45 m −2.17 239 m 0.040 <lb/>far −0.37 m −1.87 264 m 0.021 <lb/>A proton with such scattering angles, emerging from the vertex (x <lb/>  * <lb/> , y <lb/>  * <lb/> ) with relative momentum <lb/>loss ξ ≡ ∆p/p arrives at the RPs with transverse position <lb/> x = L x  θ <lb/>  * <lb/> x  + v x x <lb/>  * <lb/> + D x  ξ , <lb/> y = L y  θ <lb/>  * <lb/> y  + v y y <lb/>  * <lb/> + D y  ξ , <lb/> (2) <lb/>given by the optical functions: effective length L, magnification v and dispersion D. Since protons <lb/>lose no momentum in elastic collisions (i.e. ξ = 0), the dispersion terms can be ignored for this <lb/>process. <lb/>For the reported measurement, a special β <lb/>  * <lb/> = 90 m optics was used, with essentially the same <lb/>characteristics as at <lb/> √ s = 7 TeV [10], see Table 1 for details. In the vertical plane, it features <lb/>parallel-to-point focussing (v  y  ≈ 0) and large effective length L y  . In the horizontal plane, the <lb/>almost vanishing effective length L x  simplifies the separation of elastic and diffractive events: any <lb/>sizeable horizontal displacement must be due to a momentum loss ξ. <lb/> 5. Analysis <lb/> The analysis method is similar to the ones used in the previous publications [11, 12]. However, <lb/>a different normalisation approach is used (Section 5.2.6) that makes all t-independent scaling <lb/>factors irrelevant. <lb/>The analysis is presented in two main blocks. Section 5.1 covers all aspects related to the <lb/>reconstruction of a single event. Section 5.2 describes the steps of transforming a raw t-distribution <lb/> into the differential cross-section. The t-distributions for the two diagonals are analysed separately. <lb/>After comparison (Section 5.3) they are finally merged (Section 5.4). <lb/> 5.1. Event Analysis <lb/> Event kinematics are determined from the coordinates of track hits in the RPs after proper <lb/>alignment (see Section 5.1.2), using the LHC optics (see Section 5.1.3). <lb/> 5.1.1. Kinematics Reconstruction <lb/> The scattering angles and vertex position are first determined for each proton (i.e. from each <lb/>arm) separately by inverting the proton transport, Eq. (2), assuming ξ = 0. The following formulae <lb/>optimise the robustness against optics imperfections: <lb/> θ <lb/>  * L,R <lb/> x <lb/> = <lb/> v <lb/> N <lb/> x x <lb/> F <lb/> − v <lb/> F <lb/> x x <lb/> N <lb/> v  N <lb/> x L  F <lb/> x  − v  F <lb/> x L  N <lb/> x <lb/> , <lb/>θ <lb/>  * L,R <lb/> y <lb/> = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> y <lb/> N <lb/> L  N <lb/> y <lb/> + <lb/> y <lb/> F <lb/> L  F <lb/> y <lb/> , <lb/> x <lb/>  * L,R <lb/> = <lb/> L <lb/> F <lb/> x x <lb/> N <lb/> − L <lb/> N <lb/> x x <lb/> F <lb/> v  N <lb/> x L  F <lb/> x  − v  F <lb/> x L  N <lb/> x <lb/> , <lb/> (3) <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body> where the N and F superscripts refer to the near and far units, L and R to the left and right arm, <lb/>respectively. This one-arm reconstruction is used for tagging elastic events, where the left and <lb/>right arm protons are compared. <lb/>Once an event is selected, the information from both arms is merged yielding better angular <lb/>resolution: <lb/> θ <lb/>  * <lb/> x  = <lb/> θ <lb/>  * L <lb/> x  + θ <lb/>  * R <lb/> x <lb/> 2 <lb/> , <lb/>θ <lb/>  * <lb/> y  = <lb/> θ <lb/>  * L <lb/> y  + θ <lb/>  * R <lb/> y <lb/> 2 <lb/> . <lb/> (4) <lb/>Eventually, the full scattering angle and four-momentum transfer squared are calculated as <lb/> θ <lb/>  * <lb/> = <lb/> θ  * <lb/> x <lb/> 2 <lb/> + θ  * <lb/> y <lb/> 2 <lb/> , <lb/> t = −p <lb/> 2 <lb/> θ <lb/>  * <lb/> x <lb/> 2 <lb/> + θ <lb/>  * <lb/> y <lb/> 2 <lb/>  , <lb/> (5) <lb/>where p denotes the beam momentum. <lb/> 5.1.2. Alignment <lb/> The standard three-step procedure [15] has been applied: beam-based alignment prior to the <lb/>run (as for LHC collimators) followed by two off-line methods. First, track-based alignment for <lb/>relative positions among RPs, and second, alignment with elastic events for absolute position with <lb/>respect to the beam. The final uncertainties per unit (common for top and bottom RPs) are: 2 µm <lb/> (horizontal shift), 100 µm (vertical shift) and 0.2 mrad (rotation about the beam axis). Propagated <lb/>through Eqs. (3) and (4) to the scattering angles reconstructed from both arms, the shifts lead <lb/>to uncertainties of 0.8 µrad (horizontal) and 0.2 µrad (vertical). The relatively large impact of <lb/>horizontal misalignment is due to the almost vanishing effective length L x  (cf. Eq. (3)). RP <lb/>rotations induce a bias in the reconstructed horizontal scattering angle: <lb/> θ <lb/>  * <lb/> x  → θ <lb/>  * <lb/> x  + cθ <lb/>  * <lb/> y  , <lb/> (6) <lb/>where the proportionality constant c has a mean of 0 and a standard deviation of 0.02. <lb/> 5.1.3. Optics <lb/> In order to reduce the impact of imperfect optics knowledge, the LHC optics calibration [16] <lb/>has been applied. This method uses various RP observables to determine fine corrections to the <lb/>optical functions presented in Eq. (2). <lb/>The residual errors induce a bias in the reconstructed scattering angles: <lb/> θ <lb/>  * <lb/> x  → (1 + d x  ) θ <lb/>  * <lb/> x  , <lb/>θ <lb/>  * <lb/> y  → (1 + d y  ) θ <lb/>  * <lb/> y  . <lb/> (7) <lb/>For the two-arm reconstruction, Eq. (4), the biases d x  and d y  have uncertainties of 0.21 % and <lb/>0.25 %, respectively, and a correlation factor of −0.70. These estimates include the effects of mag-<lb/>net field harmonics. For evaluating the impact on the t-distribution, it is convenient to decompose <lb/>the correlated biases d x  and d y  into eigenvectors of the covariance matrix: <lb/> d x <lb/> d y <lb/> = η  1 <lb/>  −0.182 % <lb/> +0.235 % <lb/> mode 1 <lb/> + η  2 <lb/>  −0.096 % <lb/> −0.074 % <lb/> mode 2 <lb/> (8) <lb/>normalised such that the factors η  1,2 have unit variance. <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body> 10  −1 <lb/> 10 0 <lb/> 10 1 <lb/> 10 2 <lb/> 10 3 <lb/> events per bin <lb/> −15 −12 −9 <lb/>−6 <lb/>−3 <lb/> 0 <lb/>3 <lb/>6 <lb/>9 <lb/>12 <lb/>15 <lb/> θ  * R <lb/> y  −  θ  * L <lb/> y <lb/> [µrad] <lb/> Figure 1: Difference between vertical scattering angles reconstructed in the right and left arm, for the diagonal 45 <lb/>bottom -56 top. Red: data from run start (0.5 to 1.5 h from the beginning of the run). Blue: data from run end (10.5 <lb/>to 11.5 h), scaled by 0.1. The solid lines represent Gaussian fits. <lb/> 5.1.4. Resolution <lb/> Statistical fluctuations in the reconstructed scattering angles are caused by the beam divergence <lb/>and, in the horizontal projection (due to the small L x  ), also by the sensor resolution. They are <lb/>studied by comparing the scattering angles reconstructed from the two arms, in particular through <lb/>differences θ <lb/>  * R <lb/> x,y  − θ <lb/>  * L <lb/> x,y  as illustrated in Figure 1. The distributions exhibit small deviations from a <lb/>Gaussian shape which decrease with time. <lb/>Since in good approximation the fluctuations are independent in each arm, the angular reso-<lb/>lution for the two-arm reconstruction, Eq. (4), is given by half of the standard deviation of the <lb/> θ <lb/>  * R <lb/> x,y  − θ <lb/>  * L <lb/> x,y  distributions. As shown in Figure 2, the resolution deteriorates slightly with time, which <lb/>can be expected mainly due to the emittance growth. The small difference in θ <lb/>  * <lb/> x  resolution between <lb/>the diagonals can be attributed to different RPs, each with slightly different spatial resolution, be-<lb/>ing involved in the two diagonals. <lb/>Measurements of beam emittances [17] show that the vertical beam divergences of the two <lb/>beams are equal within a tolerance of about 15 %. Exploiting this equality, one can deconvolute <lb/>the distribution of θ <lb/>  * R <lb/> y  − θ <lb/>  * L <lb/> y  in order to obtain the beam-divergence distribution, used e.g. for <lb/>acceptance corrections discussed in Section 5.2.3 (only required in the vertical plane). <lb/> 5.2. Differential Cross-Section <lb/> For a given t bin, the differential cross-section is evaluated by selecting and counting elastic <lb/>events: <lb/>dσ <lb/>dt <lb/>(bin) = N U(bin) B <lb/> t∈bin <lb/> A(θ <lb/> * <lb/> , θ <lb/>  * <lb/> y  ) E(θ <lb/> * <lb/> y  ) <lb/> ∆t <lb/> , <lb/> (9) <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body> 4 <lb/> 4.2 <lb/>4.4 <lb/>4.6 <lb/>4.8 <lb/>5 <lb/> θ <lb/>  * <lb/> x  resolution [µrad] <lb/> 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>time [h] <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.7 <lb/>1.8 <lb/> θ <lb/>  * <lb/> y  resolution [µrad] <lb/> 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>time [h] <lb/>45 bottom – 56 top <lb/>45 top – 56 bottom <lb/> Figure 2: Angular resolution for the two-arm reconstruction, Eq. (4), as a function of time (from the beginning of the <lb/>run). The step in θ <lb/>  * <lb/> y  resolution around 7 h is due to inclusion of another colliding bunch-pair with a larger vertical <lb/>emittance. <lb/>Table 2: The elastic selection cuts. The superscripts R and L refer to the right and left arm, N and F correspond to the <lb/>near and far units, respectively. The constant α = L <lb/> F <lb/> y  /L <lb/> N <lb/> y  − 1 ≈ 0.11. The right-most column gives a typical RMS of <lb/>the cut distribution. <lb/> discriminator <lb/>cut quantity <lb/>RMS (≡ 1σ) <lb/>1 <lb/> θ <lb/>  * R <lb/> x  − θ <lb/>  * L <lb/> x <lb/> 9.5 µrad <lb/> 2 <lb/> θ <lb/>  * R <lb/> y  − θ <lb/>  * L <lb/> y <lb/> 3.3 µrad <lb/> 3 <lb/> α y <lb/> R,N <lb/> − (y <lb/> R,F <lb/> − y <lb/> R,N <lb/> ) <lb/>18 µm <lb/> 4 <lb/> α y <lb/> L,N <lb/> − (y <lb/> L,F <lb/> − y <lb/> L,N <lb/> ) <lb/>18 µm <lb/> 5 <lb/> x <lb/>  * R <lb/> − x <lb/>  * L <lb/> 8.5 µm <lb/> where ∆t is the width of the bin, N is a normalisation factor, and the other symbols stand for <lb/>various correction factors: U for unfolding of resolution effects, B for background subtraction, A <lb/> for acceptance correction and E for detection and reconstruction efficiency. <lb/> 5.2.1. Event Tagging <lb/> The cuts used to select elastic events are summarised in Table 2. Cuts 1 and 2 require the <lb/>reconstructed-track collinearity between the left and right arm. Cuts 3 and 4 control the elasticity <lb/>– if a proton loses momentum, the vertical position-angle correlation at the RPs is lost. Cut 5 <lb/>ensures that the two protons come from the same vertex (horizontally). The correlation plots <lb/>corresponding to these cuts are shown in Figure 3. <lb/>Monte-Carlo simulation suggests that applying all the five cuts at 3 σ level would lead to a loss <lb/>of about 2 % of elastic events. Setting the thresholds to 4 σ yields a tolerable loss of about 0.07 % <lb/>and therefore the cuts are applied at the 4 σ level. <lb/>The tagging efficiency is studied experimentally by applying the cuts also at the 5 σ level. This <lb/>selection yields about 0.5 % more events in every t bin – thus the inefficiency is irrelevant for this <lb/>analysis since the overall normalisation is determined from another dataset, see Section 5.2.6. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body> cut 1 <lb/> −250 <lb/> 0 <lb/>250 <lb/> θ  * R <lb/> x <lb/> [µrad] <lb/> −400 <lb/>−300 <lb/>−200 <lb/>−100 <lb/> 0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/> θ <lb/>  * L <lb/> x <lb/> [µrad] <lb/> 10 0 <lb/> 10 1 <lb/> 10 2 <lb/> 10 3 <lb/> 10 4 <lb/> cut 2 <lb/> −120 <lb/>−90 <lb/>−60 <lb/>−30 <lb/> θ  * R <lb/> y <lb/> [µrad] <lb/> −120 <lb/>−100 <lb/>−80 <lb/>−60 <lb/>−40 <lb/>−20 <lb/> θ <lb/>  * L <lb/> y <lb/> [µrad] <lb/> 10 0 <lb/> 10 1 <lb/> 10 2 <lb/> 10 3 <lb/> 10 4 <lb/> cut 3 <lb/> −30 <lb/>−20 <lb/>−10 <lb/> y  R,N [mm] <lb/> −3 <lb/>−2 <lb/>−1 <lb/> y  R,F <lb/> −  y  R,N <lb/> [mm] <lb/> 10 0 <lb/> 10 1 <lb/> 10 2 <lb/> 10 3 <lb/> 10 4 <lb/> cut 4 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/> y  L,N [mm] <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/> y  L,F <lb/> −  y  L,N <lb/> [mm] <lb/> 10 0 <lb/> 10 1 <lb/> 10 2 <lb/> 10 3 <lb/> 10 4 <lb/> cut 5 <lb/> −500 <lb/> 0 <lb/>500 <lb/> x  * R  [µm] <lb/> −800 <lb/>−600 <lb/>−400 <lb/>−200 <lb/> 0 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/> x <lb/>  * L  [µm] <lb/> 10 0 <lb/> 10 1 <lb/> 10 2 <lb/> 10 3 <lb/> 10 4 <lb/> 10 5 <lb/> Figure 3: Correlation plots for the event selection cuts summarised in Table 2, using all events with diagonal topology <lb/>45 top – 56 bottom. The black solid lines delimit the signal (±4 σ) region. <lb/></body>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<body> 10  0 <lb/> 10 1 <lb/> 10 2 <lb/> 10 3 <lb/> 10 4 <lb/> 10 5 <lb/> 10 6 <lb/> events per bin <lb/> −200 <lb/> −100 <lb/> 0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/> θ  * R <lb/> x  − θ  * L <lb/> x <lb/> [µrad] <lb/>45 top – 56 bottom: <lb/>no cuts <lb/>cuts 2 <lb/>cuts 2, 3 <lb/>cuts 2, 3, 4 <lb/>cuts 2, 3, 4, 5 <lb/>cuts 2, 3, 4, 5: <lb/>45 bot – 56 bot <lb/>45 top – 56 top <lb/> Figure 4: Distributions of discriminator 1, i.e. the difference between the horizontal scattering angle reconstructed <lb/>from the right and the left arm. Solid curves: data from diagonal 45 top – 56 bottom, the different colours correspond <lb/>to various combinations of the selection cuts (see numbering in Table 2). Dotted curves: data from non-diagonal <lb/>RP configurations, obtained by inverting track coordinates in the left arm. The vertical dashed lines represent the <lb/>boundaries of the signal region (±4 σ). <lb/> 5.2.2. Background <lb/> Expectable background (i.e. non-elastic events passing the tagging cuts) may come from cen-<lb/>tral diffraction as well as pile-up of single diffraction and/or beam-halo protons. The background <lb/>rate is studied by plotting the discriminators from Table 2 under various cut combinations, see <lb/>an example in Figure 4. While the central part (signal) remains essentially constant, the tails <lb/>(background) are strongly suppressed with increasing number of cuts applied. This interpretation <lb/>is further supported by the discriminator distributions from non-diagonal RP configurations, see <lb/>the dotted curves in the figure. While these top – top or bottom – bottom configurations cannot <lb/>contain any elastic signal, they are likely to have a similar share of events causing background to <lb/>the presented analysis. And indeed, the figure shows a good agreement at the distribution tails. <lb/>Integrating the non-diagonal curve over the signal region (see the dashed lines in the figure) yields <lb/>a background estimate of 1 − B &lt; 10 <lb/> −4 <lb/> . <lb/> 5.2.3. Acceptance Correction <lb/> Two proton detection limitations have been identified: detector coverage (mostly at the edge <lb/>facing the beam, i.e. relevant for small |θ <lb/> * <lb/> y  |) and LHC apertures (|θ <lb/>  * <lb/> y  | ≈ 100 µrad). The correction <lb/>accounting for these limitations includes two contributions – a geometrical correction A  geom re-<lb/>flecting the fraction of the phase space within the acceptance and a component A  fluct correcting <lb/>for fluctuations around the acceptance limits (cuts in θ <lb/>  * <lb/> y  ): <lb/> A(θ <lb/> * <lb/> , θ <lb/>  * <lb/> y  ) = A  geom (θ <lb/>  * <lb/> ) A  fluct (θ <lb/>  * <lb/> y  ) . <lb/> (10) <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body> → <lb/> θ  * <lb/> [µrad] <lb/> 50 <lb/> 100 <lb/> 150 <lb/> −150 −100 −50 <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 100 150 <lb/> θ  * <lb/> x  [µrad] <lb/> −150 <lb/>−100 <lb/>−50 <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/> θ <lb/>  * <lb/> y  [µrad] <lb/> 10 0 <lb/> 10 1 <lb/> 10 2 <lb/> 10 3 <lb/> Figure 5: Distribution of scattering angle projections θ <lb/>  * <lb/> y  vs. θ <lb/>  * <lb/> x  . The upper (lower) part comes from the diagonal 45 <lb/>bottom – 56 top (45 top – 56 bottom). The colour scale gives number of events (after the A  fluct correction) per bin. <lb/>The red horizontal lines represent cuts due to the LHC apertures, the magenta horizontal lines cuts due to the sensor <lb/>edges. The dotted circles show contours of constant scattering angle θ <lb/>  * <lb/> as indicated in the middle of the plot. The <lb/>parts of the contours within acceptance are emphasized in thick black. <lb/> The calculation of the geometrical correction A  geom is based on the azimuthal symmetry of <lb/>elastic scattering, experimentally verified for the data within acceptance. As shown in Figure 5, <lb/>for a given value of θ <lb/>  * <lb/> the correction is given by: <lb/> A  geom (θ <lb/>  * <lb/> ) = <lb/> full arc length <lb/>arc length within acceptance <lb/> . <lb/> (11) <lb/>The correction A  fluct is calculated analytically from the probability that any of the two elas-<lb/>tic protons leaves the region of acceptance due to the beam divergence. The beam divergence <lb/>distribution is modelled as a Gaussian with the spread determined by the method described in Sec-<lb/>tion 5.1.4. This correction contribution is sizeable only close to the acceptance limits but is kept <lb/>below 1.5 by discarding data with larger corrections. The uncertainties are related to the resolution <lb/>parameters (vertical beam divergence, left-right asymmetry and non-Gaussian shape), and all stay <lb/>below 0.1 %. <lb/>Figure 6 shows an example for the t-dependence of the acceptance correction for one diagonal. <lb/>Since a single diagonal cannot cover more than half of the phase space, the minimum value of <lb/>the correction is 2. As indicated in the figure, data points with too large correction (A  5) are <lb/>discarded. <lb/> 5.2.4. Inefficiency Corrections <lb/> Since the overall normalisation is determined from another dataset (see Section 5.2.6), any <lb/>inefficiency correction that does not alter the t-distribution shape does not need to be considered <lb/>in this analysis (trigger, data acquisition and pile-up inefficiency discussed in [11, 12]). The inef-<lb/>ficiencies left are related to inability of a RP to resolve the elastic proton track. <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body> 2 <lb/> 3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>acceptance correction <lb/> A <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/> |t| [GeV 2 ] <lb/> Figure 6: Full acceptance correction, A, for diagonal 45 bottom – 56 top. The points give the mean value per bin, the <lb/>error bars indicate the standard deviation. The sharp shape change at |t| ≈ 0.16 GeV <lb/> 2 <lb/> is caused by the LHC aperture <lb/>cuts. The data left of the dashed vertical line are discarded due to excessively large acceptance correction. <lb/> One such case is when a single RP cannot detect and/or reconstruct a proton track, with no <lb/>correlation to other RPs. This type of inefficiency, I  3/4 , is evaluated by removing the RP from <lb/>the tagging cuts (Table 2), repeating the event selection and calculating the fraction of recovered <lb/>events. A typical example is given in Figure 7, showing that the efficiency decreases gently with <lb/>the vertical scattering angle. This dependence stems from the fact that protons with larger |θ <lb/> * <lb/> y  | hit <lb/>the RPs further from their edge and therefore the potentially created secondary particles have more <lb/>chance to induce additional signal in the sensors and thus prevent from resolving the elastic proton <lb/>track. <lb/>Another source of inefficiency are proton interactions in a near RP affecting simultaneously <lb/>the far RP downstream. The contribution from these near-far correlated inefficiencies, I  2/4 , is <lb/>determined by evaluating the rate of events with high track multiplicity ( 5) in both near and far <lb/>RPs. Events with high track multiplicity simultaneously in a near top and near bottom RP are not <lb/>counted as such a shower is likely to have started upstream from the RP station and thus unrelated <lb/>to the elastic proton interacting with detectors. The outcome, I  2/4  ≈ 1.5 %, is compatible between <lb/>left/right arms and top/bottom RP pairs, in addition it compares well to Monte-Carlo simulations <lb/>(e.g. section 7.5 in [18]). <lb/>The full correction is calculated as <lb/> E(θ <lb/> * <lb/> y  ) = <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 − <lb/> i∈RPs <lb/> I <lb/> i <lb/> 3/4 (θ  * <lb/> y  ) + 2I 2/4 <lb/>  . <lb/> (12) <lb/>The first term in the parentheses sums the contributions from the four RPs of a diagonal and grows <lb/>from about 7 to 10 % from the lowest to the highest |θ <lb/> * <lb/> y  |. The second term amounts to about 3 %. <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body> 96 <lb/> 96.5 <lb/>97 <lb/>97.5 <lb/>98 <lb/>efficiency, 1 <lb/> −  I  3/4 [%] <lb/> 20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>100 <lb/>110 <lb/> θ  * <lb/> y  [µrad] <lb/>slope = (−83.5±10.4) rad  −1 <lb/> Figure 7: Single-RP uncorrelated inefficiency for the far top RP in the left arm. The rapid drop at θ <lb/>  * <lb/> y  ≈ 35 µrad is due <lb/>to acceptance effects at the sensor edge. The red lines represent a linear fit of the efficiency dependence on the vertical <lb/>scattering angle (solid) and its extrapolation to the region affected by acceptance effects (dashed). <lb/> 5.2.5. Unfolding of Resolution Effects <lb/> The correction for resolution effects has been determined by the following iterative procedure. <lb/>The differential cross-section data are fitted by a smooth curve which serves as an input to a Monte-<lb/>Carlo simulation using the resolution parameters determined in Section 5.1.4. Making a ratio <lb/>between simulated histograms with and without smearing effects gives a set of per-bin correction <lb/>factors. Applying them to the yet uncorrected differential cross-section yields a better estimate of <lb/>the true t-distribution which can be used as input to the next iteration. The iterations stop when <lb/>the difference between the input and output t-distributions becomes negligible, which is typically <lb/>achieved after the second iteration. Thanks to the good angular resolution (see Section 5.1.4), the <lb/>final correction is not large, as shown in Figure 8. <lb/>For the uncertainty estimate, the uncertainties of θ <lb/>  * <lb/> x  and θ <lb/>  * <lb/> y  resolutions (accommodating the full <lb/>time variation) as well as fit-model dependence have been considered, the first contribution being <lb/>dominant. <lb/> 5.2.6. Normalisation <lb/> The normalisation N is determined by requiring the same cross-section integral between |t| = <lb/> 0.027 and 0.083 GeV <lb/> 2 <lb/> as for dataset 1 from [12], where the luminosity-independent calibration <lb/>was applied. The leading uncertainty of the scaling factor 4.2 % comes from the luminosity-<lb/>independent method. <lb/> 5.2.7. Binning <lb/> Two binnings have been considered. The &quot; optimised &quot; option sets the bin size to 1 σ of the <lb/>resolution in t. The &quot; per-mille &quot; binning is built such that each bin collects about one per-mille of <lb/>the events. <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body> 0.97 <lb/> 0.975 <lb/>0.98 <lb/>0.985 <lb/>0.99 <lb/>0.995 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.005 <lb/>1.01 <lb/>unfolding correction <lb/> U <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/> |t| [GeV 2 ] <lb/>45 bottom – 56 top <lb/>45 top – 56 bottom <lb/> Figure 8: Unfolding correction as a function of |t|. The different shape for |t|  0.16 GeV <lb/> 2 <lb/> is due to a slightly different <lb/>position of the LHC aperture cut in the two diagonals. <lb/> 5.2.8. Systematic Uncertainties <lb/> Besides the systematic uncertainties mentioned at the above analysis steps, the uncertainty of <lb/>the beam momentum, 0.1 %, needs to be considered when the scattering angles are translated into <lb/> t, see Eq. (5). <lb/>The systematic effects are propagated to the t-distribution with help of a Monte-Carlo simu-<lb/>lation. A fit of the final differential cross-section data is used to generate the true t-distribution. <lb/> Simultaneously, another t-distribution is built, having introduced one of the above mentioned sys-<lb/>tematic effects at 1 σ level. The difference between the t-distributions gives the systematic effect <lb/>on the differential cross-section. Formally, this procedure is equivalent to evaluating <lb/> δs  q  (t) ≡ <lb/> ∂(dσ/dt) <lb/>∂q <lb/>δq , <lb/> (13) <lb/>where δq corresponds to 1 σ bias in the quantity q responsible for a given systematic effect. <lb/>The Monte-Carlo simulations show that the combined effect of several systematic errors is well <lb/>approximated by linear combination of the individual contributions from Eq. (13). <lb/> 5.3. Systematic Cross-Checks <lb/> Compatible results have been obtained from data originating from different bunches, different <lb/>diagonals and different time periods. <lb/>In addition, the complete analysis chain has been applied in two independent analysis imple-<lb/>mentations, yielding compatible results. <lb/> 5.4. Final Data Merging <lb/> Finally, the differential cross-section histograms from both diagonals are merged. This is ac-<lb/>complished by a per-bin weighted average, with the weight given by inverse squared statistical <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body> −1 <lb/> −0.5 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>relative cross-section variation [%] <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/> |t| [GeV 2 ] <lb/> −0.2 <lb/>−0.1 <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>relative cross-section variation [%] <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/> |t| [GeV 2 ] <lb/> alignment: <lb/> horizontal <lb/>vertical <lb/> alignment + optics: <lb/> tilt in x-y plane <lb/> optics: <lb/> mode 1 <lb/>mode 2 <lb/> acceptance correction: <lb/> beam divergence RMS uncertainty <lb/>beam divergence left-right asymmetry <lb/>beam divergence non-gaussianity <lb/> uncorrelated 1-RP efficiencies: <lb/> slope uncertainty <lb/> beam momentum: <lb/> offset from nominal <lb/> unfolding: <lb/> θ  * <lb/> x  resolution uncertainty <lb/> envelope of uncertainties: <lb/> ±1  σ <lb/> Figure 9: Impact of t-dependent systematic effects on the differential cross-section. Each curve corresponds to a <lb/>systematic error at 1 σ, cf. Eq. (13). The two contributions due to optics correspond to the two vectors in Eq. (8). The <lb/>envelope is determined by summing all shown contributions in quadrature for each |t| value. The right plot provides a <lb/>zoom of the left one. <lb/></body>

			<page> 14 <lb/></page>

			<body> uncertainty. The statistical and systematic uncertainties are propagated accordingly. For the sys-<lb/>tematic ones, the correlation between the diagonals is taken into account. For example, the vertical <lb/>(mis-)alignment of the RPs within one unit is almost fully correlated, thus the effect on the dif-<lb/>ferential cross-section is opposite in the two diagonals, and consequently its impact is strongly <lb/>reduced once the diagonals are merged. <lb/>The final systematic uncertainties, except the 4.2 % coming from the normalisation, are sum-<lb/>marised in Figure 9 where their impact on the differential cross-section is shown. The leading un-<lb/>certainties include normalisation, optics imperfections and beam momentum offset. Their effects <lb/>are quantified in Table 3, which can be used to approximate the covariance matrix of systematic <lb/>uncertainties: <lb/> V  i j  = <lb/> q <lb/> δs  q  (i) δs  q  ( j) , <lb/> (14) <lb/>where i and j are bin indices (row numbers in Table 3) and the sum goes over the leading error <lb/>contributions q (four right-most columns in the table). <lb/> 5.5. Statistical Uncertainty Adjustment <lb/> The statistical fluctuations in the differential cross-section using the &quot; optimised &quot; binning have <lb/>been slightly overestimated, whereas the &quot; per-mille &quot; binning does not suffer from this problem. <lb/>One way to demonstrate this is to split the data into groups of consecutive points small enough <lb/>for a linear function to approximate well the differential cross-section within each group. Then, <lb/>performing straight-line fits through each group yields on average χ <lb/> 2 <lb/> values slightly too low. Al-<lb/>ternatively, the issue can be demonstrated as follows. The data sample is divided into several <lb/>sub-samples corresponding to the same luminosity, and the analysis method described in the ear-<lb/>lier sections is repeated for each of these sub-samples. Then, fluctuations of each bin content <lb/>are determined from the several sub-samples, giving values slightly lower than the uncertainty <lb/>estimates. <lb/>As a remedy, the statistical uncertainties in the &quot; optimised &quot; binning have been divided by a <lb/>factor of 1.176. This value has been determined by requiring both binnings to give the same value <lb/>of χ <lb/> 2 <lb/> /ndf for fits of dσ/dt to the fit function in Eq. (15) with N b  = 3 which has enough flexibility <lb/>to describe the data. <lb/> 6. Results <lb/> The final differential cross-section in the &quot; optimised &quot; binning is presented in Table 3 and Figure <lb/>10. In order to visualise small deviations from the leading pure-exponential behaviour, Figure 11 <lb/>shows the relative difference of the cross-section from a reference exponential. This plot immedi-<lb/>ately suggests a non-exponentiality of the data: pure exponentials would look like (almost) linear <lb/>functions in this kind of representation. <lb/>To study the detailed behaviour of the differential cross-section, a series of fits has been made <lb/>using the parametrisation: <lb/>dσ <lb/>dt <lb/>(t) = <lb/> dσ <lb/>dt <lb/> t=0 <lb/> exp <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> N b <lb/> i=1 <lb/> b i t <lb/> i <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> , <lb/> (15) <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body> Table 3: The elastic differential cross-section as determined in this analysis using the &quot; optimised &quot; binning. The three <lb/>left-most columns describe the bins in t. The representative point gives the t value suitable for fitting [19]. The other <lb/>columns are related to the differential cross-section. The four right-most columns give the leading systematic biases <lb/>in dσ/dt for 1σ-shifts in the respective quantities, δs  q  , see Eqs. (13) and (14). The two contributions due to optics <lb/>correspond to the two vectors in Eq. (8). <lb/> |t| bin [GeV <lb/> 2 <lb/> ] <lb/>dσ/dt [mb/GeV <lb/> 2 <lb/> ] <lb/>left <lb/>right represent. <lb/>value <lb/>statistical systematic normalisation optics <lb/>optics <lb/>beam <lb/>edge <lb/>edge <lb/>point <lb/>uncertainty uncertainty <lb/> N <lb/> mode 1 mode 2 momentum <lb/>0.02697 0.03005 0.02850 300.94 <lb/>0.520 <lb/>12.68 <lb/> +12.66 <lb/> −0.473 −0.259 <lb/> +0.254 <lb/> 0.03005 0.03325 0.03164 284.04 <lb/>0.471 <lb/>11.91 <lb/> +11.90 <lb/> −0.495 −0.214 <lb/> +0.204 <lb/> 0.03325 0.03658 0.03491 265.59 <lb/>0.430 <lb/>11.17 <lb/> +11.15 <lb/> −0.484 −0.172 <lb/> +0.157 <lb/> 0.03658 0.04005 0.03831 247.90 <lb/>0.395 <lb/>10.44 <lb/> +10.43 <lb/> −0.472 −0.133 <lb/> +0.114 <lb/> 0.04005 0.04365 0.04184 231.95 <lb/>0.366 <lb/>9.740 <lb/> + 9.727 <lb/> −0.459 −0.0968 +0.0740 <lb/> 0.04365 0.04740 0.04551 215.35 <lb/>0.338 <lb/>9.061 <lb/> + 9.048 <lb/> −0.445 −0.0638 +0.0378 <lb/> 0.04740 0.05129 0.04933 199.89 <lb/>0.314 <lb/>8.405 <lb/> + 8.393 <lb/> −0.431 −0.0338 +0.0051 <lb/> 0.05129 0.05534 0.05330 184.55 <lb/>0.291 <lb/>7.775 <lb/> + 7.763 <lb/> −0.415 −0.0069 −0.0240 <lb/> 0.05534 0.05956 0.05743 170.71 <lb/>0.271 <lb/>7.171 <lb/> + 7.159 <lb/> −0.399 +0.0170 −0.0498 <lb/> 0.05956 0.06394 0.06173 156.62 <lb/>0.251 <lb/>6.594 <lb/> + 6.581 <lb/> −0.382 +0.0380 −0.0721 <lb/> 0.06394 0.06850 0.06620 142.96 <lb/>0.233 <lb/>6.044 <lb/> + 6.031 <lb/> −0.365 +0.0561 −0.0913 <lb/> 0.06850 0.07324 0.07085 131.31 <lb/>0.216 <lb/>5.521 <lb/> + 5.508 <lb/> −0.348 +0.0715 −0.107 <lb/> 0.07324 0.07817 0.07568 119.59 <lb/>0.201 <lb/>5.027 <lb/> + 5.013 <lb/> −0.330 +0.0842 −0.120 <lb/> 0.07817 0.08329 0.08071 108.28 <lb/>0.186 <lb/>4.560 <lb/> + 4.546 <lb/> −0.312 +0.0944 −0.130 <lb/> 0.08329 0.08862 0.08593 <lb/>97.732 0.172 <lb/>4.122 <lb/> + 4.107 <lb/> −0.293 +0.102 <lb/> −0.138 <lb/> 0.08862 0.09417 0.09137 <lb/>87.916 0.158 <lb/>3.711 <lb/> + 3.696 <lb/> −0.275 +0.108 <lb/> −0.143 <lb/> 0.09417 0.09994 0.09702 <lb/>78.866 0.146 <lb/>3.329 <lb/> + 3.313 <lb/> −0.257 +0.112 <lb/> −0.145 <lb/> 0.09994 0.10593 0.10290 <lb/>70.641 0.135 <lb/>2.973 <lb/> + 2.957 <lb/> −0.239 +0.113 <lb/> −0.146 <lb/> 0.10593 0.11217 0.10902 <lb/>62.480 0.124 <lb/>2.644 <lb/> + 2.628 <lb/> −0.221 +0.113 <lb/> −0.145 <lb/> 0.11217 0.11866 0.11538 <lb/>55.454 0.113 <lb/>2.341 <lb/> + 2.325 <lb/> −0.204 +0.112 <lb/> −0.142 <lb/> 0.11866 0.12540 0.12199 <lb/>48.733 0.104 <lb/>2.063 <lb/> + 2.047 <lb/> −0.187 +0.109 <lb/> −0.138 <lb/> 0.12540 0.13242 0.12887 <lb/>42.712 <lb/>0.0948 <lb/>1.810 <lb/> + 1.793 <lb/> −0.170 +0.106 <lb/> −0.132 <lb/> 0.13242 0.13972 0.13602 <lb/>37.277 <lb/>0.0864 <lb/>1.580 <lb/> + 1.563 <lb/> −0.155 +0.101 <lb/> −0.126 <lb/> 0.13972 0.14730 0.14346 <lb/>32.207 <lb/>0.0784 <lb/>1.372 <lb/> + 1.356 <lb/> −0.140 +0.0961 −0.118 <lb/> 0.14730 0.15520 0.15120 <lb/>27.731 <lb/>0.0710 <lb/>1.185 <lb/> + 1.169 <lb/> −0.125 +0.0911 −0.110 <lb/> 0.15520 0.16340 0.15925 <lb/>23.827 <lb/>0.0650 <lb/>1.016 <lb/> + 1.002 <lb/> −0.0942 +0.0855 −0.102 <lb/> 0.16340 0.17194 0.16761 <lb/>20.364 <lb/>0.0608 <lb/>0.865 <lb/> + 0.854 <lb/> −0.0582 +0.0793 −0.0938 <lb/> 0.17194 0.18082 0.17632 <lb/>17.249 <lb/>0.0566 <lb/>0.733 <lb/> + 0.723 <lb/> −0.0298 +0.0729 −0.0853 <lb/> 0.18082 0.19005 0.18537 <lb/>14.480 <lb/>0.0536 <lb/>0.618 <lb/> + 0.609 <lb/> −0.0080 +0.0664 −0.0769 <lb/> 0.19005 0.19965 0.19478 <lb/>12.124 <lb/>0.0498 <lb/>0.517 <lb/> + 0.508 <lb/> +0.0052 +0.0598 −0.0687 <lb/></body>

			<page> 16 <lb/></page>

			<body> 10  1 <lb/> 10 2 <lb/> dσ  /dt <lb/> [mb/GeV 2 <lb/> ] <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/> |t| [GeV 2 ] <lb/>data, statistical uncertainty <lb/>full systematic uncertainty band <lb/>syst. unc. band without normalisation <lb/> Figure 10: Differential cross-section using &quot; optimised &quot; binning, as given in Table 3. <lb/> which includes the pure exponential (N  b  = 1) and its straight-forward extensions (N  b  = 2, 3). <lb/>The fits have been performed by the standard least-squares method, in particular minimising: <lb/> χ <lb/> 2 <lb/> = ∆ <lb/> T  V <lb/> −1 <lb/> ∆ , <lb/> ∆ = (data − fit) , <lb/> V  =  V  stat  +  V  syst  , <lb/> (16) <lb/>where ∆ is a vector of differences between the differential cross-section data and a fit function <lb/>evaluated at the bin representative points (see Table 3). The covariance matrix  V  is given by the <lb/>sum of the statistical component  V  stat (statistical uncertainty squared from Table 3 on the diagonal) <lb/>and the systematic component  V  syst (see Eq. (14)). <lb/>The quality of fits is judged on the basis of several measures. The first is the value of χ <lb/> 2 <lb/> after <lb/>minimisation divided by the number of degrees of freedom (ndf). Secondly, the p-value stands <lb/>for the probability that a χ <lb/> 2 <lb/> value greater than the observed one would be drawn from the χ <lb/> 2 <lb/> distribution with the given number of degrees of freedom. Finally, significance means the half-<lb/>width of a central region that needs to be excluded from a normal distribution to get the same <lb/>integrated probability as the p-value. The significance is expressed in multiples of sigma, the <lb/>standard deviation of the normal distribution. <lb/>Figure 11 shows several fits of the differential cross-section with the parametrisation in Eq. (15) <lb/>and different numbers of parameters in the exponent, N b  . The corresponding fit quality is given <lb/>in Table 4, indicating that the purely exponential fit (N  b  = 1) is excluded at 7.2 σ significance. <lb/>The other two fits (N  b  = 2, 3) are of reasonable quality and can, therefore, be used for a total <lb/>cross-section estimation with the optical theorem in the form <lb/> σ <lb/> 2 <lb/>tot  = <lb/> 16π (c) <lb/> 2 <lb/> 1 + ρ  2 <lb/> dσ el <lb/> dt <lb/> t=0 <lb/> , <lb/> (17) <lb/>which neglects the effects due to the Coulomb interaction. Using the COMPETE [20] preferred-<lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body> Table 4: Fit quality measures for fits in Figure 11. <lb/> N  b <lb/> χ  2  /ndf <lb/> p-value <lb/>significance <lb/>1 117.5/28 = 4.20 6.1 · 10  −13 <lb/> 7.2 σ <lb/> 2 <lb/>29.3/27 = 1.09 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>0.94 σ <lb/> 3 <lb/>25.5/26 = 0.98 <lb/>0.49 <lb/>0.69 σ <lb/> −0.05 <lb/> −0.04 <lb/>−0.03 <lb/>−0.02 <lb/>−0.01 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>dσ  /dt <lb/> −  ref <lb/> ref <lb/> , <lb/> ref = 519.5 e <lb/> −19.38 |t| <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.18 <lb/>0.2 <lb/> |t| [GeV 2 ] <lb/>data, statistical uncertainties <lb/>full systematic uncertainty band <lb/>syst. unc. band without normalisation <lb/> N  b  = 1 <lb/> N b  = 2 <lb/> N b  = 3 <lb/> Figure 11: Differential cross-section using the &quot; optimised &quot; binning and plotted as relative difference from a reference <lb/>exponential (see vertical axis). The black dots represent data points with statistical uncertainty bars. The coloured <lb/>lines correspond to fits with parametrisation Eq. (15) and different numbers of parameters in the exponent. The red line <lb/>lies seemingly too high with respect to the data points, which is a consequence of the systematic degrees of freedom <lb/>included in the fit: some of the effects in Figure 9 may flatten the distribution which at the same time changes the <lb/>overall normalisation. The yellow band corresponds to the full systematic uncertainty, the brown-hatched one includes <lb/>all systematic contributions except the normalisation. Both bands are centred around the fit curve with N b  = 3. <lb/> model extrapolation of ρ = 0.140 ± 0.007 yields <lb/> N b  = 2 : σ  tot  = (100.8 ± 2.1) mb , <lb/> N b  = 3 : σ  tot  = (101.2 ± 2.1) mb , <lb/> (18) <lb/>which are well compatible with the previous measurement using the luminosity-independent <lb/>method [12]. <lb/>The incompatibility between a pure-exponential behaviour and the data with the &quot; per-mille &quot; <lb/>binning can be shown equally well. However, since the number of points is drastically increased, <lb/>the straight-forward χ <lb/> 2 <lb/> test does not have sufficient sensitivity, and a different test is used. Assum-<lb/>ing that the data can be described by a pure exponential, the fit parameters should have compatible <lb/>values for fits over different ranges. Figure 12 shows a fit (minimisation of χ <lb/> 2 <lb/> from Eq. (16)) with <lb/>the parametrisation <lb/>dσ <lb/>dt <lb/>(t) = <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> a  1 e <lb/> b  1  |t| <lb/> |t| &lt; 0.07 GeV <lb/> 2 <lb/> a  2 e <lb/> b  2  |t| <lb/> |t| &gt; 0.07 GeV <lb/> 2 <lb/> (19) <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body> −0.05 <lb/> −0.04 <lb/>−0.03 <lb/>−0.02 <lb/>−0.01 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>dσ  /dt <lb/> −  ref <lb/> ref <lb/> , <lb/> ref = 519.5 e <lb/> −19.38 |t| <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.18 <lb/>0.2 <lb/> |t| [GeV 2 ] <lb/>data, statistical uncertainties <lb/>full systematic uncertainty band <lb/>syst. unc. band without normalisation <lb/> Figure 12: Differential cross-section using the &quot; per-mille &quot; binning and plotted as relative difference from the reference <lb/>exponential (see vertical axis). The black dots represent data points with statistical uncertainty bars. The red line <lb/>shows pure exponential fits in regions below and above |t| = 0.07 GeV <lb/> 2 <lb/> , see Eq. (19). The yellow band corresponds to <lb/>the full systematic uncertainty, the brown-hatched one includes all systematic contributions except the normalisation. <lb/>Both bands are centred around the fit curve. <lb/> giving a reasonable fit quality (p-value of 0.57). The compatibility of the parameters in the two |t| <lb/> regions can be verified by evaluating <lb/> χ <lb/> 2 <lb/> p  = ∆ <lb/> T <lb/> p  V <lb/> −1 <lb/> p  ∆  p  , ∆  p  = <lb/> a  1  − a  2 <lb/> b  1  − b  2 <lb/> , <lb/> (20) <lb/>where  V  p  is the covariance matrix for the difference vector ∆  p  . It yields χ <lb/> 2 <lb/> p  = 65.4 which with 2 <lb/>degrees of freedom corresponds to a p-value of 6.2 · 10 <lb/> −15 <lb/> and a significance of 7.8 σ. This, in <lb/>turn, rules out the hypothesis of a purely exponential behaviour of the data over the entire observed <lb/>range. <lb/>Since parameters estimated with the least squares method are unbiased, the test in Eq. (20) is <lb/>asymptotically binning independent. Indeed, applying it to the data in the &quot; optimised &quot; binning <lb/>(prior to the statistical uncertainty rescaling, Section 5.5) yields χ <lb/> 2 <lb/> p  = 65.7 which corresponds to a <lb/>significance of 7.8 σ. After the uncertainty rescaling, the exclusion significance increases to 9.0 σ. <lb/> 7. Conclusions and Outlook <lb/> Thanks to a very-high statistics data set TOTEM has excluded a purely exponential differential <lb/>cross-section for elastic proton-proton scattering with significance greater than 7 σ in the |t| range <lb/>from 0.027 to 0.2 GeV <lb/> 2 <lb/> at <lb/> √ s = 8 TeV. The data are described satisfactorily with an exponent <lb/>quadratic or cubic in t. Using this refined parametrisation for the extrapolation to the optical point, <lb/> t = 0, yields total cross-section values compatible with the previous measurement, in all cases <lb/>neglecting the effects due to the Coulomb interaction. <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body> In an upcoming analysis, this proof of non-exponentiality in a t-domain strongly dominated by <lb/>hadronic interactions will be combined with a measurement of elastic scattering in the Coulomb-<lb/>nuclear interference region, aiming at constraints on the phenomenological description of the <lb/>hadronic phase and of the interference mechanism. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgements <lb/> This work was supported by the institutions listed on the front page and also by the Magnus <lb/>Ehrnrooth foundation (Finland), the Waldemar von Frenckell foundation (Finland), the Academy <lb/>of Finland, the Finnish Academy of Science and Letters (The Vilho, Yrjö and Kalle Väisälä Fund), <lb/>the OTKA grant NK 101438 (Hungary). Individuals have received support from Nylands nation <lb/>vid Helsingfors universitet (Finland) and from the M ˇ <lb/>SMT ČR (Czech Republic). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] G. Barbiellini et al., Phys. Lett. B39 (1972) 663 <lb/>[2] M. Ambrosio et al., Phys. Lett. B115 (1982) 495 <lb/>[3] L. Baksay et al., Nucl. Phys. B141 (1978) 1 <lb/>[4] A. Breakstone et al., Nucl. Phys. B248 (1984) 253 <lb/>[5] M. Bozzo et al., Phys. Lett. B147 (1984) 385 <lb/>[6] N.A. Amos et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 61 (1988) 525 <lb/>[7] N.A. Amos et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 68 (1992) 2433 <lb/>[8] F. Abe et al., Phys. Rev. D50 (1994) 5518 <lb/>[9] V.M. Abazov et al., Phys. Rev. D86 (2012) 012009 <lb/>[10] G. Antchev et al. (TOTEM Collaboration), Europhys. Lett. 96 (2011) 21002 <lb/>[11] G. Antchev et al. (TOTEM Collaboration), Europhys. Lett. 101 (2013) 21002 <lb/>[12] G. Antchev et al. (TOTEM Collaboration), Phys. Rev. Lett. 111 (2013) 012001 <lb/>[13] G. Aad et al. (ATLAS Collaboration), Nucl. Phys. B889 (2014) 486-548 <lb/>[14] G. Anelli et al. (TOTEM Collaboration), JINST 3 (2008) S08007 <lb/>[15] G. Antchev et al. (TOTEM Collaboration), Int. J. Mod. Phys. A 28 (2013) 1330046 <lb/>[16] G. Antchev et al. (TOTEM Collaboration), New J. Phys. 16 (2014) 103041 <lb/>[17] CERN BE-OP eLogbook: https://www.cern.ch/ab-dep-op-elogbook/elogbook/secure/eLogbook. <lb/> php?shiftId=1045825 <lb/> [18] H. Niewiadomski, &quot; Reconstruction of Protons in the TOTEM Roman Pot Detectors at the LHC &quot; , PhD thesis, <lb/>University of Manchester, 2008; CERN-THESIS-2008-080, http://cds.cern.ch/record/1131825 <lb/> [19] G. D. Lafferty and T.R. Wyatt, Nucl. Instrum. Meth. A 355 (1995) 541 <lb/>[20] J. R. Cudell et al. (COMPETE Collaboration), Phys. Rev. Lett. 89 (2002) 201801 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 20 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
