<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH <lb/> CERN-PH-EP-2015-068 <lb/>13 March 2015 <lb/>© 2015 CERN for the benefit of the ALICE Collaboration. <lb/>Reproduction of this article or parts of it is allowed as specified in the CC-BY-4.0 license. <lb/> Measurement of pion, kaon and proton production <lb/>in proton-proton collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/> ALICE Collaboration  * <lb/> Abstract <lb/> The measurement of primary π  ±  , K  ±  , p and p production at mid-rapidity (|y| &lt; 0.5) in proton-<lb/>proton collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV performed with ALICE (A Large Ion Collider Experiment) at the <lb/>Large Hadron Collider (LHC) is reported. Particle identification is performed using the specific <lb/>ionization energy loss and time-of-flight information, the ring-imaging Cherenkov technique and the <lb/>kink-topology identification of weak decays of charged kaons. Transverse momentum spectra are <lb/>measured from 0.1 GeV/c up to 3 GeV/c for pions, from 0.2 up to 6 GeV/c for kaons and from 0.3 up <lb/>to 6 GeV/c for protons. The measured spectra and particle ratios are compared with QCD-inspired <lb/>models, tuned to reproduce also the earlier measurements performed at the LHC. Furthermore, the <lb/>integrated particle yields and ratios as well as the average transverse momenta are compared with <lb/>results at lower collision energies. <lb/>  *  See Appendix A for the list of collaboration members <lb/> arXiv:1504.00024v1  [nucl-ex] 31 Mar 2015 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> The majority of the particles produced at mid-rapidity in proton-proton collisions are low-momentum <lb/>hadrons not originating from the fragmentation of partons produced in scattering processes with large <lb/>momentum transfer. Their production, therefore, cannot be computed from first principles via pertur-<lb/>bative Quantum Chromodynamics (pQCD). Currently available models describing hadron-hadron col-<lb/>lisions at high energy, such as the event generators PYTHIA6 [1], PYTHIA8 [2, 3], EPOS [4, 5] and <lb/>PHOJET [6], combine pQCD calculations for the description of hard processes with phenomenological <lb/>models for the description of the soft component. The measurement of low-momentum particle produc-<lb/>tion and species composition is therefore important as it provides crucial input for the modeling of the <lb/>soft component and of the hadronization processes. Furthermore, it serves as a reference for the same <lb/>measurement in Pb-Pb collisions to study the properties of the hot and dense strongly-interacting medium <lb/>with partonic degrees of freedom, the Quark-Gluon Plasma (QGP), which is created in these collisions. <lb/>In this paper, the measurement of primary π  ±  , K  ±  , p and p production at mid-rapidity in proton-proton <lb/>collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV using the ALICE detector [7–10] is presented. Primary particles are defined <lb/>as prompt particles produced in the collision including decay products, except those from weak decays <lb/>of light flavour hadrons and muons. Pions, kaons and protons are identified over a wide momentum <lb/>range by combining the information extracted from the specific ionization energy-loss (dE/dx) mea-<lb/>sured in the Inner Tracking System (ITS) [11] and in the Time Projection Chamber (TPC) [12], the time <lb/>of flight measured in the Time-Of-Flight (TOF) detector [13], the Cherenkov radiation measured in the <lb/>High-Momentum Particle Identification Detector (HMPID) [14] and the kink-topology identification of <lb/>the weak decays of charged kaons. Similar measurements in proton-proton collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 900 GeV <lb/>and 2.76 TeV are reported in [15–17] and are included, together with lower energy data [18–24], in the <lb/>discussion of the evolution of particle production with collision energy. <lb/>The paper is organized as follows. In Section 2 the ALICE experimental setup is described, focusing <lb/>on the detectors and the corresponding Particle IDentification (PID) techniques relevant for the present <lb/>measurement. Details on the event and track selection criteria and the corrections applied to the measured <lb/>raw yields are also presented. In Section 3 the results on the production of primary π  ±  , K  ±  p and p are <lb/>shown. These include the transverse momentum (p T ) distributions and the p  T -integrated production <lb/>yields of each particle species and the K/π and p/π ratios. The evolution with collision energy of the p  T -<lb/>integrated particle yields, of their ratios and of their average transverse momenta p  T  is also presented. <lb/>In Section 4 particle spectra and their ratios (K/π and p/π) are compared with models, in particular with <lb/>different PYTHIA tunes [1–3, 25, 26], EPOS [4, 5] and PHOJET [6]. Section 5 concludes the paper <lb/>summarizing the results. <lb/> 2 Experimental setup and data analysis <lb/> 2.1 The ALICE detector <lb/> The ALICE detector was specifically optimized to reconstruct and identify particles over a wide momen-<lb/>tum range thanks to the low material budget, the moderate magnetic field and the presence of detectors <lb/>exploiting all the known PID techniques. A comprehensive description of the ALICE experimental setup <lb/>and performance can be found in [7–10]. In the following, the PID detectors relevant for the analysis <lb/>presented in this paper are briefly described, namely ITS, TPC, TOF and HMPID. They are located in the <lb/>ALICE central barrel in a B = 0.5 T solenoidal magnetic field directed along the beam axis. The ITS, TPC <lb/>and TOF detectors cover the full azimuth (ϕ) and have a pseudorapidity coverage of |η| &lt; 0.9, while the <lb/>HMPID covers the pseudorapidity interval |η| &lt; 0.55 and the azimuthal angle range 1.2  •  &lt; ϕ &lt; 58.5  •  . <lb/>The ITS [11] is the innermost central barrel detector. It is composed of six cylindrical layers of silicon de-<lb/>tectors, located at radial distances between 3.9 and 43 cm from the beam axis. The two innermost layers <lb/>are equipped with Silicon Pixel Detectors (SPD), the two intermediate ones are Silicon Drift Detectors <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body>(SDD), while the two outermost ones are Silicon Strip Detectors (SSD). The ITS provides high resolu-<lb/>tion tracking points close to the beam line, which allows us to reconstruct primary and secondary vertices <lb/>with high precision, to measure with excellent resolution the Distance of Closest Approach (DCA) of a <lb/>track to the primary vertex, and to improve the track p  T resolution. It is also used as a stand-alone tracker <lb/>to reconstruct particles that do not reach the TPC or do not cross its sensitive areas. The SDD and SSD <lb/>are equipped with analogue readout enabling PID via dE/dx measurements with a relative resolution of <lb/>about 10%. <lb/>The TPC [12] is the main tracking detector of the ALICE central barrel. It is a large volume cylindri-<lb/>cal chamber with high-granularity readout that surrounds the ITS covering the region 85 &lt; r &lt; 247 cm <lb/>and -250 &lt; z &lt; +250 cm in the radial r and longitudinal z directions, respectively. It provides three-<lb/>dimensional space points and specific ionization energy loss dE/dx with up to 159 samples per track. <lb/>The relative dE/dx resolution is measured to be about 5.5% for tracks that cross from the centre of the <lb/>outer edge of the detector. <lb/>The TOF detector [13] is a large-area array of Multigap Resistive Plate Chambers (MRPC) with an in-<lb/>trinsic time resolution of 50 ps, including the electronic readout contribution. It is a cylindrical detector <lb/>located at a radial distance 370 &lt; r &lt; 399 cm from the beam axis. Particles are identified using simulta-<lb/>neously the time-of-flight information with the momentum and track length measured with the ITS and <lb/>the TPC. <lb/>The HMPID [14] is a single-arm proximity-focusing Ring Imaging CHerenkov (RICH) detector located <lb/>at 475 cm from the beam axis. The Cherenkov radiator is a 15-mm-thick layer of liquid C 6 F 14 (perfluo-<lb/>rohexane) with a refractive index of n = 1.2989 at a photon wave length λ = 175 nm, corresponding to <lb/>a minimum particle velocity β  min  = 0.77. <lb/>In addition to the detectors described above that provide PID information, the VZERO system [27] is <lb/>used for trigger and event selection. It is composed of two scintillator arrays, which cover the pseudora-<lb/>pidity ranges 2.8 &lt; η &lt; 5.1 and −3.7 &lt; η &lt; −1.7. <lb/> 2.2 Data sample, event and track selection <lb/> The results presented in this paper are obtained combining five independent analyses, namely ITS stand-<lb/>alone, TPC-TOF, TOF, HMPID, kink, using different PID methods. The analyzed data are proton-proton <lb/>collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV collected in 2010. During that period, the instantaneous luminosity at the <lb/>ALICE interaction point was kept within the range 0.6-1.2×10 29 cm  −2  s  −1  to limit the collision pile-up <lb/>probability. Only runs with a collision pile-up probability smaller than 4% are used in this analysis, <lb/>leading to an average pile-up rate of 2.5%. The number of events used in the five independent analyses <lb/>is reported in Table 1. The data were collected using a minimum-bias trigger, which required a hit in the <lb/>SPD or in at least one of the VZERO scintillator arrays in coincidence with the arrival of proton bunches <lb/>from both directions. This trigger selection essentially corresponds to the requirement of having at least <lb/>one charged particle in 8 units of pseudorapidity. The contamination due to beam-induced background is <lb/>removed off-line by using the timing information from the VZERO detector, which measures the event <lb/>time with a resolution of about 1 ns, and the correlation between the number of clusters and track seg-<lb/>ments (tracklets) in the SPD [15]. <lb/>Selected events are further required to have a reconstructed primary vertex. For 87% of the triggered <lb/>events, the interaction vertex position is determined from the tracks reconstructed in TPC and ITS. For <lb/>events that do not have a vertex reconstructed from tracks, which are essentially collisions with low mul-<lb/>tiplicity of charged particles, the primary vertex is reconstructed from the SPD tracklets, which are track <lb/>segments built from pairs of hits in the two innermost layers of the ITS. Overall, the fraction of events <lb/>with reconstructed primary vertex, either from tracks or from SPD tracklets, is of 91%. Accepted events <lb/>are required to have the reconstructed vertex position along the beam direction, z, within ± 10 cm from <lb/>the centre of the ALICE central barrel. This ensures good rapidity coverage, uniformity of the particle <lb/>reconstruction efficiency in ITS and TPC and reduction of the remaining beam-gas contamination. In the <lb/>following analyses two different sets of tracks are used: the global tracks, reconstructed using informa-<lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body> Analysis # of events <lb/> π <lb/> K <lb/>p <lb/>ITS-sa <lb/>5.4 · 10 7 <lb/> 0.1-0.6 0.2-0.5 0.3-0.6 <lb/>TPC–TOF <lb/>5.4 · 10 7 <lb/> 0.25-1.2 0.3-1.2 0.45-2.0 <lb/>TOF <lb/>5.4 · 10 7 <lb/> 0.5-2.5 0.5-2.4 0.8-4.0 <lb/>HMPID <lb/>8.1 · 10 7 <lb/> 1.5-3.0 1.5-3.0 1.5-6.0 <lb/>Kink <lb/>16.9 · 10 7 <lb/> -<lb/>0.2-6.0 <lb/>-<lb/> Table 1: Number of analyzed events and p  T range (GeV/c) covered by each analysis. <lb/> tion from both ITS and TPC, and the ITS-sa tracks, reconstructed by using only the hits in the ITS. To <lb/>limit the contamination due to secondary particles and tracks with wrongly associated hits and to ensure <lb/>high tracking efficiency, tracks are selected according to the following criteria. The global tracks are <lb/>required to cross over at least 70 TPC readout rows with a value of χ  2  /N  clusters of the momentum fit in <lb/>the TPC lower than 4, to have at least two clusters reconstructed in the ITS out of which at least one is <lb/>in the SPD layers and to have a DCA to the interaction vertex in the longitudinal plane, DCA  z  &lt; 2 cm. <lb/>Furthermore, the daughter tracks of reconstructed kinks are rejected. This last cut is not applied in the <lb/>kink analysis where a further p  T -dependent selection on the DCA of the selected tracks to the primary <lb/>vertex in the transverse plane (DCA  xy  ) is requested. The global tracks that satisfy these selection criteria <lb/>have a p  T resolution of 1% at p  T = 1 GeV/c and 2% at p  T = 10 GeV/c. The ITS-sa tracks are required to <lb/>have at least four ITS clusters out of which at least one in the SPD layers and three in the SSD and SDD, <lb/> χ  2  /N  clusters  &lt; 2.5 and a DCA  xy  satisfying a p  T -dependent upper cut corresponding to 7 times the DCA <lb/>resolution. The selected ITS-sa tracks have a maximum p  T resolution of 6% for pions, 8% for kaons <lb/>and 10% for protons in the p  T range used in the analysis. Both global and ITS-sa tracks have similar <lb/>resolution in the DCA  xy  parameter that is 75 µm at p  T = 1 GeV/c and 20 µm at p  T = 15 GeV/c [28], <lb/>which is well reproduced in the simulation of the detector performance. The final spectra are calculated <lb/>for |y| &lt; 0.5. <lb/> 2.3 Particle identification strategy <lb/> To measure the production of π  ±  , K  ±  , p and p over a wide p  T range, results from five independent <lb/>analyses, namely ITS-sa, TPC-TOF, TOF, HMPID and kink, are combined. Each analysis uses different <lb/>PID signals in order to identify particles in the complementary p  T ranges reported in Table 1. In the <lb/>following, the PID strategies used by ITS-sa, TPC-TOF and TOF analyses are briefly summarized since <lb/>they are already discussed in detail in [15, 29], while the HMPID analysis, presented here for the first <lb/>time, and the kink analysis, modified with respect to that described in [15], are presented in more detail. <lb/> 2.3.1 ITS stand-alone analysis <lb/> In this analysis ITS-sa tracks are used and particles are identified by comparing the dE/dx measurement <lb/>provided by the ITS detector with the expected values at a given momentum p under the corresponding <lb/>mass hypotheses. In Fig. 1, the measured dE/dx values are shown as a function of track momentum <lb/>together with the curves of the energy loss for the different particle species, which are calculated using <lb/>the PHOBOS parametrization [30] of the Bethe-Bloch curves at large β γ and with a polynomial to correct <lb/>for instrumental effects. A single identity is assigned to each track according to the mass hypothesis for <lb/>which the expected specific energy-loss value is the closest to the measured dE/dx for a track with <lb/>momentum p. No explicit selection on the difference between the measured and expected values is <lb/>applied except for a lower limit on pions set to two times the dE/dx resolution (σ ) and an upper limit on <lb/>protons given by the mid-point between the proton and the deuteron expected dE/dx. The ITS dE/dx is <lb/>calculated as a truncated mean of three or four dE/dx values provided by the SDD and SSD layers. The <lb/>truncated mean is the average of the lowest two dE/dx values in case signals in all the four layers are <lb/>available, or as a weighted average of the lowest (weight 1) and the second lowest (weight 1/2) values in <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body> ) <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> p <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/> m) <lb/> µ <lb/> in ITS (keV/300 <lb/> x <lb/> /d <lb/> E <lb/> d <lb/> 0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>700 <lb/> ITS standalone tracks <lb/> π <lb/> K <lb/>p <lb/>e <lb/>= 7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> pp, <lb/>ALICE <lb/> Fig. 1: Distribution of dE/dx as a function of momentum (p) measured in the ITS using ITS-sa tracks in |η| &lt; 0.9. <lb/>The continuous curves represent the parametrization of dE/dx for e, π, K and p while the dashed curves are the <lb/>bands used in the PID procedure. <lb/> the case where only three dE/dx samples are measured. Even with this truncated mean approach, used to <lb/>reduce the effect of the tail of the Landau distribution at large dE/dx, the small number of samples results <lb/>in residual non-Gaussian tails in the dE/dx distribution, which are partially reproduced in simulation. <lb/>These non-Gaussian tails increase the misidentification rate, e.g. pions falling in the kaon identification <lb/>bands. The misidentification probability is estimated using a Monte-Carlo simulations where the particle <lb/>abundances were adjusted to those observed in data. This correction is at most 10% in the p  T range <lb/>of this analysis. In order to check possible systematic effects due to these non-Gaussian tails and their <lb/>imperfect description in Monte-Carlo simulations, the analysis was repeated with different strategies for <lb/>the particle identification, namely using a 3σ compatibility band around the expected dE/dx curves and <lb/>extracting the yields of pions, kaons and protons using the unfolding method described in [15], which is <lb/>based on fits to the dE/dx distributions in each p  T interval. The difference among the results from these <lb/>different analysis strategies is assigned as a systematic uncertainty due to the PID. <lb/> 2.3.2 TPC–TOF analysis <lb/> In this analysis global tracks are used and particle identification is performed by comparing the measured <lb/>PID signals in the TPC and TOF detectors (dE/dx, time of flight) with the expected values for different <lb/>mass hypotheses. An identity is assigned to a track if the measured signal differs from the expected <lb/>value by less than three times its resolution σ . For pions and protons with p  T  &lt; 0.6 GeV/c and kaons <lb/>with p  T  &lt; 0.5 GeV/c, a compatibility within 3σ is required on the dE/dx measurement provided by <lb/>the TPC computed as a truncated mean of the lowest 60% of the available dE/dx samples. The dE/dx <lb/>resulting from this truncated mean approach is Gaussian and it is shown in Fig. 2 as a function of the <lb/>track momentum together with the expected energy-loss curves (see [31] for a discussion about the <lb/>dE/dx parametrization). Above these p  T thresholds, i.e. p  T  ≥ 0.6 GeV/c for pions and protons and <lb/> p  T  ≥ 0.5 GeV/c for kaons, a three σ requirement is applied to both the dE/dx measurement provided <lb/>by the TPC and the time of flight t  tof provided by the TOF detector. The time of flight t  tof , as will be <lb/>described in more detail in the next section, is the difference between the arrival time τ  TOF measured with <lb/>the TOF detector and the event start time t  0 , namely t  tof  = τ  TOF  −t  0 . The additional condition on the TOF <lb/>signal helps in extending the particle identification on a track-by-track basis to higher p  T where the TPC <lb/>separation power decreases. The particles for which the time-of-flight signal is available are a sub-sample <lb/>of the global tracks reconstructed using ITS and TPC information. The time-of-flight information is not <lb/>available for tracks that cross inactive regions of the TOF detector, for particles that decay or interact <lb/>with the material before the TOF and for tracks whose trajectory, after prolongation from the TPC outer <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body> ) <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> p <lb/> 1 <lb/>10 <lb/> in TPC (arb.units) <lb/> x <lb/> /d <lb/> E <lb/> d <lb/> 40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>140 <lb/>160 <lb/>180 <lb/>200 <lb/>= 7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> pp, <lb/>ALICE <lb/>p <lb/>K <lb/> π <lb/> e <lb/>d <lb/> Fig. 2: Distribution of dE/dx as a function of momentum (p) measured in the TPC using global tracks for |η| &lt; 0.9. <lb/>The continuous curves represent the Bethe-Bloch parametrization. <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> /z (GeV/ <lb/> p <lb/> -5 -4 -3 -2 -1 0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/> β <lb/> 0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1 <lb/> = 7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> pp, <lb/>ALICE <lb/> + <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> p <lb/>d <lb/> -<lb/> π <lb/> -<lb/> K <lb/> p <lb/>d <lb/> Fig. 3: Particle velocity β measured by the TOF detector as a function of the rigidity p/z, where z is the particle <lb/>charge, for |η| &lt; 0.9. <lb/> radius, is not matched with a hit in the TOF detector. The fraction of global tracks with associated <lb/>time-of-flight information (TOF matching efficiency) depends on the particle species and p  T as well as <lb/>on the fraction of the TOF active readout channels. For the data analysis presented in this paper the <lb/>matching efficiency increases with increasing p  T until it saturates, e.g. at about 65% for pions with p  T <lb/> &gt; 1 GeV/c. In Fig. 3 the velocity β of the tracks, computed from the trajectory length measured with <lb/>the ITS and TPC and the time of flight measured with the TOF, is reported as a function of the rigidity <lb/> p/z, where z is the charge assigned based on the measured direction of the track curvature. More than <lb/>one identity can be assigned to a track if it fulfils PID and rapidity selection criteria for different particle <lb/>species. The frequency of such cases is at most 0.5% in the momentum range used in this analysis. The <lb/>misidentification of primary particles is computed and corrected for using Monte-Carlo simulations. It <lb/>is at most 2% for pions and protons and 8% for kaons in the considered p  T ranges. The correction of the <lb/>raw spectra for the misidentified particles provides also a way to remove the overestimation of the total <lb/>number of particles introduced by the possibility, described above, to assign more than one identity to a <lb/>track. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body> (ps) <lb/> π <lb/> t <lb/> ∆ <lb/> -1000 -500 <lb/>0 <lb/>500 1000 1500 2000 <lb/> Counts <lb/> 0 <lb/>2000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>6000 <lb/>8000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>12000 <lb/>14000 <lb/>16000 <lb/> c <lb/> &lt; 2.0 GeV/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 1.9 &lt; <lb/>Data <lb/> + <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/>p <lb/>Total <lb/> = 7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> pp, <lb/> ALICE <lb/> Fig. 4: Distribution of ∆t  i  assuming the pion mass hypothesis in the transverse momentum interval <lb/>1.9 &lt; p  T  &lt; 2.0 GeV/c. The data (black points) are fitted with a function (light blue line) that is the sum of <lb/>the signal due to pions (green dotted line) and the two populations corresponding to kaons (red dotted line) and <lb/>protons (purple dashed line). <lb/> 2.3.3 TOF analysis <lb/> This analysis uses the sub-sample of global tracks for which a time-of-flight measurement is available. <lb/>The PID procedure utilizes a statistical unfolding approach that provides a p  T reach higher than the three <lb/> σ approach described in the previous section. The procedure is based on the comparison between the <lb/>measured time of flight from the primary vertex to the TOF detector, t  tof , and the time expected under <lb/>a given mass hypothesis, t <lb/> exp <lb/> i <lb/> (i = π, K, p), namely on the variable ∆t  i  = t  tof  − t <lb/> exp <lb/> i  . As mentioned in <lb/>the previous section, the time of flight t  tof is defined as the difference between the time measured with <lb/>the TOF detector τ  TOF and the event start time t  0 . The t  0 value is computed from the analyzed tracks <lb/>themselves on an event-by-event basis, using a combinatorial algorithm which compares the measured <lb/> τ  TOF with the expected ones for different mass hypotheses. The track under study is excluded to avoid <lb/>any bias in the PID procedure [13, 15]. In case the TOF t  0 algorithm fails, the average beam-beam <lb/>interaction time is used. The former approach provides a better t  0 resolution, but requires at least three <lb/>reconstructed tracks with an associated TOF timing measurement. The yield of particles of species i in <lb/>a given p  T interval is obtained by fitting the distribution of the variable ∆t  i  obtained from all the tracks <lb/>regardless of the method used to compute the t  0 . This distribution is composed of the signal from particles <lb/>of species i, which is centered at ∆t  i  = 0, and two distinct populations corresponding to the other two <lb/>hadron species, j, k  = i. The ∆t  i  distribution is therefore fitted with the sum of three functions f (∆t  i  ), one <lb/>for the signal and two for the other hadron species, as shown in Fig. 4. The f (∆t  i  ) functional forms are <lb/>defined using the data in the region of clear species separation. The TOF signal is not purely Gaussian <lb/>and it is described by a function f (∆t  i  ) that is composed of a Gaussian term and an exponential tail at <lb/>high ∆t  i  mainly due to tracks inducing signals in more than one elementary detector readout element [13]. <lb/>The raw yield of the species i is given by the integral of the signal fit function. The reach in p  T of this PID <lb/>method depends on the resolution of ∆t  i  that is the combination of the TOF detector intrinsic resolution, <lb/>the uncertainty on the start time and the tracking and momentum resolution. Its value, for the data used <lb/>in this analysis, is about 120 ps leading to 2σ pion-kaon and kaon-proton separation at p  T = 2.5 GeV/c <lb/>and p  T = 4.0 GeV/c, respectively. This PID procedure has the advantage of not requiring a Monte-Carlo <lb/>based correction for misidentification because the contamination under the signal of particles of species <lb/> i due to other particle species is accounted for by the background fit functions. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body> Pad Y <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>Pad X <lb/> 50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>= 7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> pp, <lb/>ALICE <lb/> MIP cluster <lb/> LOW <lb/>HIGH <lb/> (a.u.) <lb/> Photon clusters <lb/> Fig. 5: Display of a Cherenkov ring detected in a module of HMPID for an inclined track crossing the detector. <lb/>The colors are proportional to the pad charge signal. <lb/> 2.3.4 HMPID analysis <lb/> The HMPID is a Ring Imaging Cherenkov (RICH) detector in a proximity focusing layout in which <lb/>the primary ionizing charged particle generates Cherenkov light inside a liquid C 6 F 14 radiator [14]. <lb/>The UV photons are converted into photoelectrons in a thin CsI film of the PhotoCathodes (PCs) and <lb/>the photoelectrons are amplified in an avalanche process inside a Multi-Wire Proportional Chamber <lb/>(MWPC) operated with CH 4 . To obtain position sensitivity for the reconstruction of the Cherenkov <lb/>rings, the PCs are segmented into pads. The final image of a Cherenkov ring is then formed by a cluster <lb/>of pads (called &quot; MIP &quot; cluster) associated to the primary ionization of the particle and the photoelectron <lb/>clusters associated to Cherenkov photons. In Fig. 5 a typical Cherenkov ring is shown. <lb/>In this analysis, the sub-sample of global tracks that reach the HMPID detector and produce the Cherenkov <lb/>rings is used. Starting from the photoelectron cluster coordinates on the photocathode, a back-tracking <lb/>algorithm calculates the corresponding single photon Cherenkov angle by using the impact angle of a <lb/>track extrapolated from the central tracking detectors up to the radiator volume. A selection on the dis-<lb/>tance (d MIP−trk ) computed on the cathode plane between the centroid of the MIP cluster and the track <lb/>extrapolation, set to d  MIP−trk  &lt; 5 cm, rejects fake associations in the detector. Background discrimina-<lb/>tion is performed using the Hough Transform Method (HTM) [32]. <lb/>The mean Cherenkov angle θ  ckov  is obtained if at least three photoelectron clusters are detected. For <lb/>a given track, θ  ckov  is computed as the weighted average of the single photon angles (if any) selected <lb/>by HTM. Pions, kaons and protons become indistinguishable at high momentum when the resolution on <lb/> θ  ckov  reaches 3.5 mead. The angle θ  ckov  as a function of the track momentum is shown in Fig. 6, <lb/>where the solid lines represent the θ  ckov dependence on the particle momentum <lb/> θ  ckov  = cos <lb/> −1 <lb/> p  2  + m  2 <lb/> np <lb/> , <lb/> (1) <lb/>where n is the refractive index of the liquid radiator, m the mass of the particle and p its momentum. <lb/>This analysis is performed for p &gt;1.5 GeV/c, where pions, kaons and protons produce a ring with enough <lb/>photoelectron clusters to be reconstructed. If the track momentum is below the threshold to produce <lb/>Cherenkov photons, background clusters could be wrongly associated to the track. As an example the few <lb/>entries visible in Fig. 6 between the pion and kaon bands at low θ  ckov  correspond to wrong associations <lb/>of clusters with a kaon or a proton below the threshold to produce Cherenkov photons. <lb/>The particle yields are extracted from a fit to the Cherenkov angle distribution in narrow transverse <lb/>momentum intervals. In Fig. 7, examples of the reconstructed Cherenkov angle distributions in two <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body> ) <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> p <lb/> 0 0.5 1 1.5 2 2.5 3 3.5 4 4.5 5 <lb/> (rad) <lb/> 〉 <lb/> ckov <lb/> θ <lb/> 〈 <lb/> HMPID <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>= 7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> pp, <lb/>ALICE <lb/>p <lb/>K <lb/> π <lb/> Fig. 6: Mean Cherenkov angle θ  ckov  measured with HMPID in its full geometrical acceptance as a function of <lb/>the particle momentum p for positively and negatively charged tracks. The solid lines represent the theoretical <lb/>curves for each particle species. <lb/> narrow p  T intervals (3.4 &lt; p  T  &lt; 3.6 GeV/c and 5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 5.5 GeV/c) for negatively-charged tracks are <lb/>shown. <lb/>The background, mainly due to noisy pads and photoelectron clusters from other rings overlapping to <lb/>the reconstructed one, is negligible in the momentum range considered in this analysis. The fit function <lb/>(shown as a solid line in Fig. 7) is a sum of three Gaussian functions, one for each particle species (dashed <lb/>lines), whose mean and sigma are fixed to the Monte-Carlo values. The extracted separation power of <lb/>hadron identification in the HMPID as a function of p  T is shown in Fig. 8. The separation between <lb/>pions and kaons (kaons and protons) is expressed as the difference between the means of the θ  ckov  <lb/> angle Gaussian distributions for the two given particle species (∆  π,K  or ∆  K,p ) divided by the average of <lb/>the Gaussian widths of the two distributions, i.e. (σ  π  +σ K )/2 or (σ K +σ p )/2. A separation at 3σ level in <lb/> θ  ckov  is achieved up to p  T = 3 GeV/c for K-π and up to p  T = 5 GeV/c for K-p. The separation at <lb/>6 GeV/c for K-p can be extrapolated from the curve and it is about 2.5σ . The HMPID geometrical <lb/>acceptance is about 5% for tracks with high momentum. Therefore the analysis of HMPID required to <lb/>analyze a larger data sample with respect to the other PID methods, as reported in Table 1. The total <lb/>efficiency is the convolution of the tracking, matching and PID efficiencies. The PID efficiency of this <lb/>method is determined by the Cherenkov angle reconstruction efficiency. It has been computed by means <lb/>of Monte-Carlo simulations and it reaches 90% for particles with velocity β ∼ 1. As a cross check, the <lb/>PID efficiency has been determined using clean samples of protons and pions from Λ and K 0 <lb/>s decays. <lb/>The measured efficiency agrees within the statistical uncertainties with the Monte-Carlo estimates, in the <lb/>momentum range 1.5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 6 GeV/c. Moreover, the correction due to the d  MIP−trk cut is computed <lb/>from the same sample of identified protons and pions from Λ and K 0 <lb/>s decays. <lb/> 2.3.5 Kink analysis <lb/> Charged kaons can also be identified in the TPC by reconstructing their weak-decay vertices, which <lb/>exhibit a characteristic kink topology defined by a decay vertex with two tracks (mother and daughter) <lb/>having the same charge. This procedure extends the measurement of charged kaons on a track-by-track <lb/>basis to p  T = 6 GeV/c. The algorithm for the kink reconstruction is applied inside a fiducial volume of <lb/>the TPC, namely 130 &lt; R &lt; 200 cm, needed to reconstruct both the mother and the daughter tracks. The <lb/>mother track is selected with similar criteria as the global tracks (Section 2.2), but with a looser selection <lb/>on the minimum number of TPC clusters, which is set to 20, and a wider rapidity range set to |y| &lt; 0.7 to <lb/>increase the statistics of kink candidates. No selections are applied on the charged daughter track. The <lb/>reconstructed invariant mass M  µν  is calculated assuming the charged daughter track to be a muon and the <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body> (rad) <lb/> 〉 <lb/> ckov <lb/> θ <lb/> 〈 <lb/> Cherenkov angle <lb/> 0.6 0.62 0.64 0.66 0.68 0.7 <lb/> 0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>140 <lb/>160 <lb/>Data <lb/> -<lb/> π <lb/> -<lb/> K <lb/>p <lb/>Total <lb/> c <lb/> &lt; 5.5 GeV/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 5 &lt; <lb/> 0.6 <lb/>0.62 <lb/>0.64 <lb/>0.66 <lb/>0.68 <lb/>0.7 <lb/> Counts <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>300 <lb/>350 <lb/> = 7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> pp, <lb/>ALICE <lb/> c <lb/> &lt; 3.6 GeV/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 3.4 &lt; <lb/> Fig. 7: Distributions of θ  ckov  measured with the HMPID in the two narrow p  T intervals 3.4 &lt; p  T  &lt; 3.6 GeV/c <lb/>(top) and 5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 5.5 GeV/c (bottom) for tracks from negatively-charged particles. Solid lines represent the total <lb/>fit (sum of three Gaussian functions). Dotted lines correspond to pion, kaon and proton signals. The background <lb/>is negligible. <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>) <lb/> σ <lb/> HMPID separation (n <lb/> 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/> = 7 TeV <lb/>s <lb/>pp, <lb/>ALICE <lb/> K-p <lb/> π <lb/> K-<lb/> Fig. 8: Separation power (n  σ  ) of hadron identification in the HMPID as a function of p  T . The separation n  σ  of <lb/>pions and kaons (kaons and protons) is defined as the difference between the average of the Gaussian distributions <lb/>of θ  ckov  for the two hadron species divided by the average of the Gaussian widths of the two distributions. <lb/></body>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body> ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> ν <lb/> µ <lb/> M <lb/> 0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0 <lb/>50000 <lb/>100000 <lb/>150000 <lb/> ν <lb/>µ <lb/>→ <lb/> K <lb/> 0 <lb/> π <lb/>π <lb/>→ <lb/> K <lb/> After topological selection <lb/> = 7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> pp, <lb/>ALICE <lb/> c <lb/> &lt; 6 GeV/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 0.2 &lt; <lb/> ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> ν <lb/>µ <lb/> M <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/> Counts <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 6 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 7 <lb/> 10 <lb/> ν <lb/>µ <lb/>→ <lb/>π <lb/> c <lb/> &lt; 6 GeV/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 0.2 &lt; <lb/>Before topological selection <lb/> ν <lb/>µ <lb/>→ <lb/> K <lb/> 0 <lb/> π <lb/>π <lb/>→ <lb/> K <lb/> Data <lb/>MC PYTHIA <lb/> Fig. 9: Kink invariant mass M  µν  in data (red circles) and Monte-Carlo (black line) for summed particles and <lb/>antiparticles, integrated over the mother transverse momentum range 0.2 &lt; p  T  &lt; 6.0 GeV/c and |y| &lt; 0.7 before <lb/>(top panel) and after (bottom panel) the topological selections, based mainly on the q  T and the maximum decay <lb/>opening angle. <lb/> undetected neutral daughter track to be a neutrino. The neutrino momentum is the difference between the <lb/>measured momenta of the mother particle and of the charged daughter. The M  µν  distribution, for summed <lb/>positive and negative charges, integrated over the mother transverse momentum range 0.2 &lt; p  T  &lt; 6.0 <lb/>GeV/c is reported in the top panel of Fig. 9 for both data and PYTHIA simulations normalized to the <lb/>same number of entries. Three peaks are present: one centered on the kaon mass due to the kaon decays <lb/>K→ µ + ν µ  (branching ratio BR = 63.55%), one centered at M  µν  = 0.43 GeV/c 2 due to the K→ π + π  0 <lb/> decay (BR = 20.66%), whose kinematics is calculated with wrong mass assumptions, and the peak due <lb/>to pion decays π → µ + ν µ  (BR = 99.99%). The width of the peaks reflects the momentum resolution <lb/>of the detector, which is well reproduced in Monte-Carlo simulations. The two-body kinematics of the <lb/>kink topology allows one to separate kaon decays from the main source of background due to charged <lb/>pion decays [15]. In the µ + ν µ  channel, the upper limit of the q  T variable, where q  T is defined as <lb/>the transverse momentum of the daughter track with respect to the mother&apos;s direction, is 236 MeV/c for <lb/>muons from kaon decays and 30 MeV/c for muons from pion decays. To remove most of the pion decays, <lb/>a q  T  &gt; 120 MeV/c selection is applied. The background is further reduced by rejecting kink decays for <lb/>which the decay angle, namely the angle between the momenta of the mother and the charged daughter <lb/>tracks is larger than the maximum angle allowed in the hypothesis K→ µ + ν µ  . The bottom panel of <lb/>Fig. 9 shows the invariant mass distribution of the kaon candidates with mother transverse momentum <lb/>0.2 &lt; p  T  &lt; 6.0 GeV/c after the topological selection criteria for kaon identification (mainly the q  T and <lb/>decay angle cuts) are applied. It is evident that only the two peaks coming from kaon decays are present <lb/>while the pion background peak is removed. The broad structure on the left originates from the three-<lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/></note>

			<body> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/>body decays of kaons. The agreement between data and simulations in this figure (Fig. 9) is better than <lb/>8%. Most of the selected mother tracks have a dE/dx in the TPC which is compatible with the values <lb/>expected for kaons. Tracks outside 3.5σ from the expected kaon dE/dx have been removed to attain a <lb/>purity &gt; 97 % in the p  T range studied in this analysis. These rejected tracks are less than 4%, have p  T  &lt; <lb/> 0.8 GeV/c and are, according to Monte-Carlo studies, pions. The raw kaon spectra are obtained from the <lb/>integral of the invariant mass distribution computed in narrow p  T intervals after the topological selection <lb/>criteria on the q T  , the decay opening angle, and the compatibility with the expected dE/dx for kaons are <lb/>applied. The kaon misidentification is computed and corrected for by using Monte-Carlo simulations. <lb/>It depends on the mother&apos;s transverse momentum with a maximum value of 3.6% at 0.8 GeV/c and a <lb/>minimum of 2% at 1 GeV/c, remaining almost flat up to p  T  = 6 GeV/c. Its average value in the p  T range <lb/>considered in this analysis is 2.1%. <lb/> 2.4 Correction of raw spectra <lb/> To obtain the p  T distributions of primary π, K and p, the contribution of secondaries is subtracted from <lb/>the raw spectra. Then, the spectra are corrected for the PID efficiency, the misidentification probability, <lb/>the acceptance, the reconstruction and the selection efficiencies according to <lb/>d 2  N <lb/> dp T dy <lb/> = N  raw  (p  T  ) <lb/> 1 <lb/> ∆p  T  ∆y <lb/> 1 − s(p  T  ) <lb/> ε(p  T  ) <lb/> · f (p  T  ), <lb/> (2) <lb/>where N  raw  (p  T  ) <lb/> 1 <lb/> ∆p  T  ∆y  is the raw yield in a given p  T interval, s(p  T  ) is the total contamination including <lb/>effects of secondary and misidentified particles, ε(p  T  ) is the acceptance×efficiency including PID effi-<lb/>ciency, detector acceptance, reconstruction and selection efficiencies and f (p  T  ) is an additional factor to <lb/>correct for imperfections of the cross sections for antiparticle interactions with the material used in the <lb/>GEANT3 code. <lb/>The contamination due to weak decays of light flavour hadrons (mainly K 0 <lb/> s  affecting π spectra and Λ and <lb/> Σ  +  affecting p spectra) and interactions with the material has to be computed and subtracted from the <lb/>raw spectra. Since strangeness production is underestimated in the event generators and the interactions <lb/>of low p  T particles with the material are not properly modelled in the transport codes, the secondary-<lb/>particle contribution is evaluated with a data-driven approach. This approach exploits the high resolution <lb/>determination of the track impact parameter in the transverse plane, DCA  xy  , and the fact that secondary <lb/>particles from strange hadron decays and interactions with the detector material, originate from sec-<lb/>ondary vertices significantly displaced from the interaction point and, therefore, their tracks have, on <lb/>average, larger absolute values of DCA  xy  with respect to primary particles. Hence, for each of the PID <lb/>techniques described in the previous sections, the contribution of secondary particles to the measured raw <lb/>yield of a given hadron species in a given p  T interval is extracted by fitting the measured distributions of <lb/>DCA  xy  of the tracks identified as particles of the considered hadron species. The DCA  xy  distributions are <lb/>modelled with three contributions, called templates. Their shapes are extracted for each p  T interval and <lb/>particle species from simulations, as described in [29], and represent the DCA  xy  distributions of primary <lb/>particles, secondary particles from weak decays of strange hadrons and secondary particles produced in <lb/>interactions with the detector material, respectively. An example for protons in the interval 0.55 &lt; p  T  &lt; <lb/> 0.60 GeV/c is shown in Fig. 10. The correction for secondary particle contamination is relevant for π  ± <lb/> (from 10% at low p  T to less than 2% at high p  T ), p and p (from 35% at low p  T to 2% at high p  T ). Due <lb/>to the different track and PID selections the contribution of secondaries is different for each analysis. <lb/>In the case of kaons, the contamination from secondary particles is negligible, except for the TPC-<lb/>TOF analysis where a contamination originating from secondary e  ±  produced by photon conversions <lb/>in the detector material is present. This contamination is significant only in the momentum range <lb/>0.4 &lt; p &lt; 0.6 GeV/c, where the dE/dx of kaons and electrons in the TPC gas are similar, not al-<lb/>lowing for their separation, as shown in Fig. 2. Therefore, in the case of kaons, the fit to the DCA  xy <lb/></body>

			<page> 12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body> (cm) <lb/> xy <lb/> DCA <lb/> -3 <lb/>-2 <lb/>-1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/> Norm. counts <lb/> -4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/> Data (proton) <lb/>Combined fit <lb/>Primaries <lb/>Weak decays <lb/>Material <lb/> = 7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> pp, <lb/>ALICE <lb/> c <lb/> &lt; 0.6 GeV/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 0.55 &lt; <lb/> Fig. 10: Proton DCA  xy  distribution in the range 0.55 &lt; p  T  &lt; 0.60 GeV/c together with the Monte-Carlo templates <lb/>for primary protons (green dotted line), secondary protons from weak decays (red dotted line) and secondary <lb/>protons produced in interactions with the detector material (blue dashed line) which are fitted to the data. The light <lb/>blue line represents the combined fit, while the black dots are the data. <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/> p p p p <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ITS-sa <lb/>TPC-TOF <lb/>TOF <lb/>HMPID x 10 <lb/>KINK x 10 <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/> = 7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> ALICE pp <lb/> + <lb/> π <lb/> = 7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> ALICE pp <lb/> + <lb/> π <lb/> = 7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> ALICE pp <lb/> + <lb/> π <lb/> = 7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> ALICE pp <lb/> + <lb/> π <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/> p p p p <lb/> -<lb/> K <lb/> -<lb/> K <lb/> -<lb/> K <lb/> -<lb/> K <lb/> -<lb/> K <lb/> -<lb/> π <lb/> -<lb/> π <lb/> -<lb/> π <lb/> -<lb/> π <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> ε <lb/> Fig. 11: Correction factors (ε(p T ) in Eq. 2) for π  +  , K  +  and p (left panel) and their antiparticles (right panel) <lb/>accounting for PID efficiency, detector acceptance, reconstruction and selection efficiencies for ITS-sa (red circles), <lb/>TPC-TOF (light blue squares), TOF (green diamonds), HMPID (black stars) and kink (purple crosses) analyses. <lb/></body>

			<page> 13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body>distributions is used only in the TPC-TOF analysis for p  T  &lt; 0.5 GeV/c to subtract the contamination due <lb/>to secondary e  ±  . This contamination is about 16% for p  T = 0.5 GeV/c. <lb/>The resulting spectra are corrected for the detector acceptance and for the reconstruction and selection <lb/>efficiencies. This correction is specific to each analysis and accounts for the acceptance of the detector <lb/>used in the PID procedure, the trigger selection and the vertex and track reconstruction efficiencies. <lb/>They are evaluated by performing the same analyses on simulated events generated with PYTHIA 6.4 <lb/>(Perugia0 tune) [25]. The particles are propagated through the detector using the GEANT3 transport <lb/>code [33], where the detector geometry and response as well as the data taking conditions are reproduced <lb/>in detail. <lb/>In Fig. 11 the efficiency ε(p  T ), specific to each analysis, accounting for PID efficiency, acceptance, <lb/>reconstruction and selection efficiencies are shown. The lower value of ε for HMPID and kink analyses <lb/>is due to the limited geometrical acceptance of the HMPID detector and to the limited TPC fiducial <lb/>volume used for the kink vertex reconstruction. The drop in the correction for the TPC-TOF analysis at <lb/> p  T = 0.6 GeV/c for pions and protons and p  T = 0.5 GeV/c for kaons is due to the efficiency of track <lb/>propagation to the TOF. The ITS-sa analysis has a larger kaon efficiency than TPC-TOF analysis at low <lb/> p  T because the ITS-sa tracking allows the reconstruction of kaons that decay before reaching the TPC. <lb/>The corrections for particles (left panel of Fig. 11) and antiparticles (right panel) are compatible within <lb/>the uncertanties. <lb/>Since GEANT3 does not describe well the interaction of low-momentum p and K  −  with the material, <lb/>corrections to the efficiencies, estimated with a dedicated FLUKA simulation [29, 34], are applied. The <lb/>correction factor f (p T ) is 0.71 &lt; f (p T ) &lt; 1 for p and 0.95 &lt; f (p T ) &lt; 1 for K  −  . <lb/>The corrected spectra are, finally, normalized to the number of inelastic proton-proton collisions that is <lb/>obtained from the number of analyzed minimum-bias events via the scaling factor 0.852 as described <lb/>in [35]. <lb/> 2.5 Systematic uncertainties <lb/> The main sources of systematic uncertainties, for each analysis, are summarized in Table 2. They are <lb/>related to the PID procedure, the subtraction of the contribution from secondary particles, imperfect <lb/>description of the material budget in the Monte-Carlo simulation, particle interactions in the detector <lb/>material, tracking efficiency and variables used for the track selection. <lb/>The systematic uncertainties introduced by the PID procedure are estimated differently depending on <lb/>the specific analysis. In the ITS-sa analysis different techniques are used for the identification: a 3σ <lb/>compatibility cut and an unfolding method as described in section 2.3.1. In the TPC-TOF analysis the 3σ <lb/>selection is varied to 2σ and 4σ . Furthermore, the systematic uncertainty on the estimated contamination <lb/>from misidentified hadrons, which is due to the different relative abundances of pions, kaons and protons <lb/>in data and simulation, has been estimated to be below 1% for pions and protons and below 4% for kaons. <lb/>In TOF and HMPID analyses the parameters of the fit function used to extract the raw yields are varied <lb/>(one at a time) by ±10%. <lb/> The systematic uncertainty due to the subtraction of secondary particles is estimated by changing the fit <lb/>range of the DCA  xy  distribution. The shape of the DCA  xy  template for p and p from weak decays is also <lb/>varied by modifying the relative contribution of the different mother particles. The main sources of p <lb/>and p from weak decays are Λ and Σ  +  (and their antiparticles), which have significantly different mean <lb/>proper decay lengths (cτ = 7.89 cm and 2.404 cm respectively [36]). Therefore, the DCA template of <lb/>protons from weak decays depends on the Λ to Σ  +  ratio in the event generator used in the simulation. <lb/>To evaluate the systematic effect due to the uncertainty in the material budget (about ±7% [37]), the <lb/>efficiency corrections are computed by using Monte-Carlo simulations with the material budget modified <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body> Source of uncertainty common to all the analyses <lb/> π  ± <lb/> K  ± <lb/> p and p <lb/>Correction for secondaries <lb/> &lt; 1% <lb/>5% − 1.5% (p) <lb/>1.5% (p) <lb/>Material budget <lb/>5% − Negl. 3% − Negl. <lb/>3% − Negl. <lb/>Cross sections for interactions in the material <lb/>2% − 1% <lb/>4% − 1% <lb/>4% − Negl. (p) <lb/>6% − 1% (p) <lb/>ITS-TPC matching (excluded in ITS-sa analysis) <lb/>3%-<lb/>3% <lb/>3% <lb/> Source of uncertainty specific to an analysis <lb/> π  ± <lb/> K  ± <lb/> p and p <lb/>ITS-sa PID <lb/>2% <lb/>4% <lb/>4.5% <lb/>Tracking efficiency (ITS-sa tracks) <lb/>3% <lb/>3% <lb/>3% <lb/> E×B effect <lb/>3% <lb/>3% <lb/>3% <lb/>TPC-TOF PID <lb/> &lt; 1% <lb/>1% − 5% <lb/> &lt; 1% <lb/>Tracking efficiency (global tracks) <lb/>2% <lb/>2% <lb/>2% <lb/>Matching efficiency <lb/>3% <lb/>6% <lb/>4% <lb/>(p T  &gt; 0.5 GeV/c for K and 0.6 GeV/c for π, p) <lb/>TOF PID <lb/>0.5% − 3% 1% − 11% <lb/>1% − 14% <lb/>Tracking efficiency (global tracks) <lb/>2% <lb/>2% <lb/>2% <lb/>Matching efficiency <lb/>3% <lb/>6% <lb/>4% <lb/>HMPID PID <lb/>4% <lb/>5% <lb/>5% − 9% <lb/>Tracking efficiency (global tracks) <lb/>5% <lb/>5% <lb/>7% <lb/>d MIP−trk cut <lb/>2% − 6% <lb/>2% − 6% <lb/>2% − 6% <lb/>Kink PID <lb/>3% <lb/>Tracking efficiency (global tracks) <lb/>2% <lb/>Kink reconstruction efficiency <lb/>3% <lb/>Kink contamination <lb/>3.6% − 2% <lb/> Table 2: Sources of systematic uncertainties on the corrected spectra <lb/> d 2  N <lb/> dp T dy . In case of p  T -dependent systematic <lb/>uncertainty, the values in the lowest and highest p  T intervals are reported. <lb/> by this percentage. The systematic uncertainties in modelling the particle interactions with the detector <lb/>material are evaluated using different transport codes, as described in [29]. <lb/>For all the analyses, the systematic uncertainties related to tracking procedure are estimated by varying <lb/>the track selection criteria (e.g. number of crossed readout rows in TPC, number of clusters in ITS, <lb/>DCA  z  , DCA  xy  ) reported in Section 2.2. For global tracks an additional uncertainty, related to the ITS-<lb/>TPC matching, is also included. It is estimated by comparing the matching efficiency in data and Monte-<lb/>Carlo simulations. <lb/>Further systematic uncertainty sources, specific to each analysis, are also evaluated. In the case of the <lb/>ITS-sa analysis, the Lorentz force causes shifts of the cluster position in the ITS, pushing the charge in <lb/>opposite directions depending on the polarity of the magnetic field of the experiment (E×B effect). This <lb/>effect is not fully reproduced in the simulation. It is estimated by analysing data samples collected with <lb/>different magnetic field polarities, which resulted in an uncertainty of 3%. In the case of TPC-TOF and <lb/>TOF analyses, the influence of the material budget on the matching of global tracks with hits in the TOF <lb/>detector is computed by comparing the matching efficiency for tracks traversing a different amount of <lb/>material, in particular sectors with and without Transition Radiation Detector (TRD) modules installed. <lb/>In the HMPID analysis, the d  MIP−trk cut selection is varied to check its systematic effect on the matching <lb/>of global tracks with HMPID signals. <lb/>In the kink analysis, the total systematic uncertainty is calculated as the quadratic sum of the contribu-<lb/>tions listed in Table 2. The kaon misidentification correction (1 -purity) described in Section 2.3.5, which <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body>is on average 2.1%, depends on the relative particle abundances in the Monte-Carlo and a p  T -dependent <lb/>uncertainty of about 2% on the purity is estimated. The kink identification uncertainty (3%, almost flat <lb/>in the considered p  T region) is also estimated with Monte-Carlo simulations by comparing the results by <lb/>varying slightly some parameters of the analysis: the fiducial volume of the TPC is increased from the <lb/>nominal 130 &lt; R &lt; 200 cm to 120 &lt; R &lt; 210 cm, the q  T threshold is reduced from the nominal 120 <lb/>MeV/c to 40 MeV/c, and the requirement on the number of TPC clusters of the mother track is increased <lb/>from the nominal 20 to 50 clusters. <lb/>The systematic uncertainty on the efficiency for findable kink vertices was estimated to be 3% indepen-<lb/>dently of p  T by comparing, in real data and Monte Carlo simulations, the number of raw reconstructed <lb/>kinks per kink radius unit in two different fiducial volumes inside the TPC, namely 130-200 cm and <lb/>140-190 cm. <lb/>Finally, a systematic uncertainty common to each analysis is related to the normalization to inelastic <lb/>collisions. The normalization factor was evaluated in [35] and it is 0.852 <lb/> +0.062 <lb/> −0.030  . <lb/>All described uncertainties are strongly correlated among the p  T bins. Most of the uncertainties (e.g. <lb/>tracking efficiency, ITS-TPC matching, TOF matching, material budget or PID) are also correlated be-<lb/>tween the different particle species. <lb/> 3 Results <lb/> The mid-rapidity (|y| &lt; 0.5) transverse momentum spectra of π  +  +π  −  , K  +  +K  −  and p+p obtained with <lb/>the five analysis techniques discussed in Section 2, normalized to the number of inelastic collisions <lb/> N  INEL , are reported in the top panel of Fig. 12. For a given hadron species, the spectra of particles and <lb/>antiparticles are found to be compatible within uncertainties. Therefore, all the spectra shown in this <lb/>section are reported for summed charges. Since in their overlap p  T regions the spectra from the different <lb/>PID techniques are consistent within uncertainties, they are averaged in a sequential procedure. The first <lb/>step consists in averaging the two analyses whose results are the most closely correlated (namely TPC-<lb/>TOF and TOF). Successively, the other analyses are added one-by-one to the running average according <lb/>to their degree of correlation with the previous ones. At each step of this sequential procedure, a weighted <lb/>average of two spectra is computed by using as weights the inverse of the squares of the uncorrelated <lb/>systematic uncertainties. The uncorrelated and correlated uncertainties are propagated separately through <lb/>the weighted average formula. In Fig. 13 the π, K and p spectra, resulting from the combination of the <lb/>five analyses, are reported. The bottom panels of Fig. 12 show the ratios between the spectra from <lb/>each analysis and the combined one: the former are considered with their total systematic uncertainties <lb/>while the latter without uncertainty. The uncertainty due to the normalization to inelastic collisions <lb/>( <lb/> +7 <lb/> −4  %), common to the five PID analyses, is not included. The agreement between each analysis and the <lb/>combined one is satisfactory, being within the total systematic uncertainties. <lb/>To extrapolate to zero and infinite momentum, the combined spectra reported in Fig. 13 are fitted with <lb/>the Lévy-Tsallis function [38, 39] <lb/>d 2  N <lb/> dp T dy <lb/> = p  T <lb/> dN <lb/>dy <lb/> K <lb/> 1 + <lb/> m  T  − m  0 <lb/> nC <lb/>  −n <lb/> , <lb/> (3) <lb/>where <lb/> K = <lb/>(n − 1)(n − 2) <lb/> nC(nC + m  0  (n − 2)) <lb/> , <lb/> (4) <lb/> m  T  = <lb/> p  2 <lb/>T  + m  2 <lb/>0 , m  0 is the particle rest mass and C, n and the yield dN/dy are the free parameters. The <lb/>Lévy-Tsallis function describes rather well the spectra. The χ  2 per number of degrees of freedom (ndf) <lb/>of the fit are lower than unity (see Table 3) due to residual correlations in the point-to-point systematic <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body> 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/> ] <lb/> -1 <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> ) [(GeV/ <lb/> y <lb/> d <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> /(d <lb/> N <lb/> 2 <lb/> d <lb/> INEL <lb/> N <lb/> 1/ <lb/> -4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>= 7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> pp, <lb/>ALICE <lb/> -<lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> + <lb/> π <lb/> -<lb/> +K <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/>p <lb/>p+ <lb/>| &lt; 0.5 <lb/> y <lb/> | <lb/> ITS-sa <lb/>TPC-TOF <lb/>TOF <lb/>HMPID <lb/>Kink <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/> Combined <lb/> 0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/> -<lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> + <lb/> π <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/> Analysis / <lb/> 0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/> -<lb/> +K <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/> 0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/> p <lb/>p+ <lb/> Fig. 12: Top panel: p  T spectra of π, K and p, sum of particles and antiparticles, measured with ALICE at mid-<lb/>rapidity (|y| &lt; 0.5) in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV by using different PID techniques. The spectra are normalized <lb/>to the number of inelastic collisions. Statistical (vertical error bars) and systematic (open boxes) uncertainties are <lb/>reported. The horizontal width of the boxes represents the p  T -bin width. The markers are placed at the bin centre. <lb/>Bottom panels: ratio between the spectra obtained from each analysis and the combined one. The error bands <lb/>represent the total systematic uncertainties for each analysis. The uncertainty due to the normalization to inelastic <lb/>collisions ( <lb/> +7 <lb/> −4  %), common to the five PID analyses, is not included. <lb/> uncertainties. In Table 3 the values of the p  T -integrated yield dN/dy and of the mean transverse mo-<lb/>mentum p  T  are reported for each particle species. They are obtained using the measured data in the p  T <lb/> range where they are available and the Lévy-Tsallis function fitted to the data elsewhere, to extrapolate <lb/>to zero and infinite momentum. The lowest p  T experimentally accessible and the fraction of yield con-<lb/>tained in the extrapolated region are also reported in the table. The extrapolation to infinite momentum <lb/>gives a negligible contribution to the values of both dN/dy and p  T  . The dN/dy and p  T  uncertain-<lb/>ties reported in Table 3 are the combination of the statistical and the systematic ones. The statistical <lb/>uncertainties are negligible, while the systematic uncertainties are the sum of two independent contribu-<lb/>tions. The first contribution is due to the systematic uncertainties on the measured p  T -differential yields <lb/>and it was estimated as the maximum deviation of the dN/dy and p  T  obtained by repeating the Lévy-<lb/>Tsallis fits moving the measured points within their systematic uncertainties. The second contribution is <lb/>due to the extrapolation to zero momentum and it is estimated using different fitting functions (namely <lb/>modified Hagedorn [40] and UA1 parametrization [41]). Results for positively and negatively charged <lb/>particles, separately, are also reported. It should be noticed that the yields of particles and antiparticles <lb/>are compatible within uncertainties. <lb/>In Fig. 14 the p  T spectra of identified charged hadrons, sum of particles and antiparticles, measured <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body> ) <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/> ] <lb/> -1 <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> ) [(GeV/ <lb/> y <lb/> d <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> /(d <lb/> N <lb/> 2 <lb/> d <lb/> INEL <lb/> N <lb/> 1/ <lb/> -4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>= 7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> pp, <lb/>ALICE <lb/>| &lt; 0.5 <lb/> y <lb/> | <lb/> -<lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> + <lb/> π <lb/> -<lb/> + K <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/>p <lb/>p + <lb/>vy-Tsallis fits <lb/>e <lb/>L <lb/> Fig. 13: Combined p  T spectra of π, K and p, sum of particles and antiparticles, measured with ALICE at mid-<lb/>rapidity (|y| &lt; 0.5) in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV normalized to the number of inelastic collisions. Statistical <lb/>(vertical error bars) and systematic (open boxes) uncertainties are reported. The uncertainty due to the normaliza-<lb/>tion to inelastic collisions ( <lb/> +7 <lb/> −4  %) is not shown. The spectra are fitted with Lévy-Tsallis functions. <lb/> Particle <lb/>dN//dy <lb/> p  T  <lb/> (GeV/c) <lb/> χ  2  /ndf L. p  T <lb/> (GeV/c) <lb/>Extr. <lb/>% <lb/> π  + + π  − <lb/> 4.49 ± 0.20 <lb/>0.466 ± 0.010 19.1/38 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>9 <lb/>K  +  + K  −  0.572 ± 0.032 0.773 ± 0.016 5.0/45 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>10 <lb/>p + p <lb/>0.247 ± 0.018 0.900 ± 0.029 10.8/43 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>12 <lb/> π  + <lb/> 2.26 ± 0.10 <lb/>0.464 ± 0.010 24.0/38 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>9 <lb/> π  − <lb/> 2.23 ± 0.10 <lb/>0.469 ± 0.010 15.0/38 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>9 <lb/>K  + <lb/> 0.286 ± 0.016 0.777 ± 0.016 7.4/45 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>9 <lb/>K  − <lb/> 0.286 ± 0.016 0.770 ± 0.016 10.0/45 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>10 <lb/>p <lb/>0.124 ± 0.009 0.900 ± 0.027 9.5/43 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>12 <lb/>p <lb/>0.123 ± 0.010 0.900 ± 0.032 12.3/43 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>12 <lb/> Table 3: dN/dy and p  T  extracted from Lévy-Tsallis fits to the measured π, K, p spectra in inelastic pp collisions <lb/>at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV for |y| &lt; 0.5 with combined statistical and systematic uncertainties (statistical uncertainties are <lb/>negligible) together with the p  T of the lowest experimentally accessible point (L. p  T  ) and the extrapolated fraction. <lb/>The systematic uncertainty on dN/dy due to normalization to inelastic collisions ( <lb/> +7 <lb/> −4  %) is not included. <lb/> with ALICE at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV are compared to the results obtained by the CMS Collaboration at the same <lb/>centre-of-mass energy [17]. Even though the measurements are performed in different rapidity intervals <lb/>(|y| &lt; 0.5 for ALICE, |y| &lt; 1 for CMS), they can be compared since the p  T spectra are essentially <lb/>independent of rapidity for |y| &lt; 1. A similar comparison at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 0.9 TeV is reported in [17]. At both <lb/>energies, the ALICE spectra are normalized to the number of inelastic collisions, while the CMS results <lb/>are normalized to the double-sided selection (at least one particle with E &gt; 3 GeV in both −5 &lt; η &lt; −3 <lb/> and 3 &lt; η &lt; 5). An empirical scaling factor of 0.78, computed by the CMS Collaboration in [17] for <lb/>the spectra measured in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 0.9 TeV, is therefore applied to the CMS data points at <lb/> √ <lb/> s <lb/> = 7 TeV, to take into account the different event selections (details are given in [17]). With this scaling, <lb/>the pion and kaon spectra measured with ALICE and CMS are found to agree within uncertainties. <lb/>The proton spectra have different slopes: for p  T  &lt; 1 GeV/c the ALICE and CMS results agree within <lb/>uncertainties, while at higher p  T a discrepancy of up to 20% is observed. <lb/>In Fig. 15 the π, K and p integrated yields, dN/dy, are compared with similar measurements in the central <lb/>rapidity region at various collision energies. In particular, results from ALICE at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 900 GeV [15] <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body> ) <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/> ] <lb/> -1 <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> ) [(GeV/ <lb/> y <lb/> d <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> /(d <lb/> N <lb/> 2 <lb/> d <lb/> ev <lb/> N <lb/> 1/ <lb/> -6 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> (4x) <lb/> π <lb/> -<lb/> INEL <lb/> ALICE <lb/>-K (2x) <lb/> INEL <lb/> ALICE <lb/>-p <lb/> INEL <lb/> ALICE <lb/>x 0.78 (4x) <lb/> π <lb/> -<lb/> DS <lb/> CMS <lb/>-K x 0.78 (2x) <lb/> DS <lb/> CMS <lb/>-p x 0.78 <lb/> DS <lb/> CMS <lb/>norm. uncert. <lb/> = 7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> pp, <lb/> (GeV/c) <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/> ALICE/CMS <lb/> 0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/> Fig. 14: Comparison of p  T spectra of π, K and p (sum of particles and antiparticles) measured by the ALICE <lb/>(|y| &lt; 0.5) and CMS Collaborations (|y| &lt; 1) in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV. The CMS data points are scaled by <lb/>the empirical factor 0.78, as described in [17]. Inset plot: Ratios between ALICE and CMS data in the common p  T <lb/> range. The combined ALICE and CMS statistical (vertical error bars) and systematic (open boxes) uncertainties <lb/>are reported. The combined ALICE ( <lb/> +7 <lb/> −4  %) and CMS (±3%) normalization uncertainty is shown as a grey box <lb/>around 1 and not included in the point-to-point uncertainties. <lb/> (GeV) <lb/> s <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> y <lb/> /d <lb/> N <lb/> d <lb/> -2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/> )/2 <lb/>p <lb/>)/2, (p + <lb/> -<lb/> + K <lb/> + <lb/> )/2, (K <lb/> -<lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> + <lb/> π <lb/> ALICE, ( <lb/>)/2 <lb/>p <lb/>)/2, (p + <lb/> -<lb/> + K <lb/> + <lb/> )/2, (K <lb/> -<lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> + <lb/> π <lb/> CMS, ( <lb/>, p <lb/> + <lb/> , K <lb/> + <lb/> π <lb/> PHENIX, <lb/>p <lb/>, <lb/> -<lb/> , K <lb/> -<lb/> π <lb/> PHENIX, <lb/> π <lb/> K <lb/>p <lb/> Fig. 15: p  T -integrated yields dN/dy of π, K and p as a function of the centre-of-mass energy in pp collisions. <lb/>PHENIX results are for separate charges while CMS and ALICE results are the average of the dN/dy of particles <lb/>and antiparticles. ALICE and CMS points are slightly shifted along the x-axis for a better visualization. Errors <lb/>(open boxes) are the combination of statistical (negligible), systematic and normalization uncertainties. <lb/> and <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 2.76 TeV [16], PHENIX at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 62.4 GeV and <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 200 GeV [18] and CMS, scaled by the <lb/>empirical factor 0.78, at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 900 GeV, <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 2.76 TeV and <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV [17] are shown. The dN/dy values <lb/>from PHENIX are reported for particles and antiparticles separately, while the results at LHC energies are <lb/>the average between positively and negatively charged particles, since particle and antiparticle spectra are <lb/>compatible at these energies. We notice that the CMS Collaboration does not include, in the systematic <lb/>uncertainties associated to dN/dy and p  T  , the contribution due to the extrapolation to p  T = 0. For this <lb/>reason, in Fig. 16 and Fig. 17, the ALICE uncertainties are larger than the CMS ones. Similar results <lb/>from the STAR Collaboration [42] are not included, here and in the following plots, since they are <lb/>provided for non-single diffractive events and include contributions of feed-down from weak decays. <lb/>The (K  +  +K  −  )/(π  +  +π  −  ) and (p+p)/(π  +  +π  −  ) ratios, as a function of the centre-of-mass energy, are shown <lb/>in the top and bottom panels of Fig. 16, respectively. Results at mid-rapidity from ALICE at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 0.9, <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body> (GeV) <lb/> s <lb/> 10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> ) <lb/> -<lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> + <lb/> π <lb/> )/( <lb/> p <lb/> (p + <lb/> 0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.09 <lb/> ALICE, pp <lb/>CMS, pp <lb/>PHENIX, pp <lb/>NA49, pp <lb/>) <lb/> + <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> -<lb/> π <lb/> /( <lb/>p <lb/>p, 2 <lb/>p <lb/>E735, <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/>UA5, <lb/> (GeV) <lb/> s <lb/> 10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> ) <lb/> -<lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> + <lb/> π <lb/> )/( <lb/> -<lb/> + K <lb/> + <lb/> (K <lb/> 0.08 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.18 <lb/> Fig. 16: (K  +  +K  −  )/(π  +  +π  −  ) (top) and (p+p)/(π  +  +π  −  ) (bottom) ratios in pp and pp collisions as a function of the <lb/>collision energy <lb/> √ <lb/> s. Errors (open boxes) are the combination of statistical (negligible) and systematic uncertain-<lb/>ties. <lb/> 2.76 [15, 16] and 7 TeV, CMS at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 0.9, 2.76 and 7 TeV [17], PHENIX at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 62.4 and 200 GeV [18] <lb/>and NA49 at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 17.3 GeV [19–21] are displayed. The ratio (p+p)/(π  +  +π  −  ) from NA49, calculated <lb/>from the measured particle yields, is not reported because the uncertainty can not be computed from the <lb/>results published in [19–21]. Results in proton-antiproton collisions from E735 at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 0.3, 0.54, 1 and <lb/>1.8 TeV [22, 23] and UA5 at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 0.2, 0.546 and 0.9 TeV [24] are reported, but a direct comparison with <lb/>them is not straightforward due to different baryon number in the initial state. The E735 Collaboration <lb/>provides measurements only for p and not for p yields. Hence the proton-to-pion ratio is computed as <lb/>2p/(π  +  +π  −  ). In addition, the E735 results for the proton-to-pion ratio are shown in Fig. 16 only for <lb/> √ <lb/> s = <lb/>1.8 TeV because at the other energies the p spectra include contributions of feed-down from weak decays <lb/>and are not directly comparable with the measurements provided by the other experiments. For <lb/> √ <lb/> s &gt; 0.9 <lb/>TeV, no dependence on the centre-of-mass energy of the (K  +  +K  −  )/(π  +  +π  −  ) and (p+p)/(π  +  +π  −  ) ratios <lb/>is observed within uncertainties. <lb/>In Fig. 17 the average transverse momenta p  T  of pions, kaons, and protons, extracted from the sum of <lb/>particle and antiparticle spectra, as a function of the centre-of-mass energy are reported. Results at mid-<lb/>rapidity in proton-proton collisions from ALICE at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 0.9, 2.76 [15, 16] and 7 TeV, CMS at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 0.9, <lb/>2.76 and 7 TeV [17] and PHENIX at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 62.4 and 200 GeV [18] are shown. In addition measurements <lb/>obtained with E735 at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 0.3, 0.54, 1 and 1.8 TeV [22] and UA5 at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 0.2, 0.546, 0.9 TeV [24] in <lb/>proton-antiproton collisions are also reported. The values of p  T  of p from E735 are not shown since the <lb/>spectra include contributions of feed-down from weak decays and hence are not directly comparable with <lb/>the values provided by the other experiments. A slight increase of p  T  with increasing centre-of-mass <lb/>energy is observed. This rising trend is in particular apparent for <lb/> √ <lb/> s &gt; 0.9 TeV and it could be related <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body>to the increasing importance of hard processes at these energies. At <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV, the ALICE and CMS <lb/>results are consistent within uncertainties except for the proton p  T  . This discrepancy is mostly due to <lb/>the difference in the shape of the proton spectra seen in Fig. 14, rather than to the extrapolation to the <lb/>unmeasured p  T range: a 13% difference is observed on the p  T  values calculated from the ALICE and <lb/>CMS data points in the common p  T range. <lb/> (GeV) <lb/> s <lb/> 1 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> 〉 <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 〈 <lb/> 0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/> ALICE, pp <lb/>CMS, pp <lb/>PHENIX, pp <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/>UA5, <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/>E735, <lb/> π <lb/> K <lb/>p <lb/> Fig. 17: (Colour online) p  T  as a function of the centre-of-mass energy. Errors (open boxes) are the combination <lb/>of statistical (negligible) and systematic uncertainties. Normalization uncertainties are not included. <lb/> 4 Comparison to models <lb/> The comparison between the measured p  T spectra of π, K and p and the calculations of QCD-inspired <lb/>Monte-Carlo event generators gives useful information on hadron production mechanisms. Figure 18 <lb/>shows the comparison of the measured pion, kaon and proton p  T spectra, sum of particles and antipar-<lb/>ticles, with two tunes of the PYTHIA6 generator (PYTHIA6-CentralPerugia2011 [25] and PYTHIA6-<lb/>Z2 [26]) 1 , PYTHIA8 tune 4Cx [2, 3], EPOS LHC [4, 5] and PHOJET [6]. <lb/>These event generators are often used and tested to describe hadron collisions at high energies. PYTHIA <lb/>is a general-purpose pQCD-based event generator, which uses a factorized perturbative expansion for <lb/>the hardest parton-parton interaction, combined with parton showers and detailed models of hadroniza-<lb/>tion and multiparton interactions. All presented PYTHIA tunes use a color reconnection mechanism [1] <lb/>which can mimic effects similar to that induced by collective flow in Pb-Pb collisions [44]. In both <lb/>PHOJET and EPOS, which are microscopic models that utilize the color-exchange mechanism of string <lb/>excitation, the hadronic interactions are treated in terms of Reggeon and Pomeron exchanges. <lb/>PYTHIA6-Z2 tune is based on the first measurement of multiplicity distributions in minimum-bias pp <lb/>collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 900 GeV at the LHC. In the CentralPerugia2011 tuning both LEP fragmentation func-<lb/>tions and minimun-bias charged particle multiplicity and underlying event data from the LHC are used. <lb/>Both PYTHIA8 and EPOS LHC are tuned to reproduce the existing data available from the LHC (e.g. <lb/>multiplicity and, for EPOS, also identified hadron production up to 1 GeV/c for pions and kaons and up <lb/>to 1.5 GeV/c for protons). The PHOJET parameters are not retuned using the LHC data. <lb/>The measured pion p  T spectrum is reproduced by EPOS within 15% over the whole p  T range. PYTHIA6-<lb/>Z2, PYTHIA6-CentralPerugia2011 and PYTHIA8 show similar trends. They correctly predict the shapes <lb/>of the pion spectra for p  T  &gt; 500 MeV/c, overestimating the data by about 10%, 20% and 25%, respec-<lb/>tively, while the shapes differ from data for p  T  &lt; 200 MeV/c (the ratios are not flat) and the yields are <lb/>underestimated by up to 30%. The PHOJET generator does not provide a satisfactory description of the <lb/>measured spectrum shape for any of the particle species. The deviations from the data show a maximum <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 1 The PYTHIA6 tunes are simulated using Rivet [43], a toolkit for validation of Monte-Carlo event generators. <lb/></note>

			<page> 21 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body> 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/> ] <lb/> -1 <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> ) [(GeV/ <lb/> y <lb/> d <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> /(d <lb/> N <lb/> 2 <lb/> d <lb/> INEL <lb/> N <lb/> 1/ <lb/> -4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/>= 7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> pp, <lb/>ALICE <lb/>| &lt; 0.5 <lb/> y <lb/> | <lb/> PYTHIA 6.4.26 Z2, Tune 343 <lb/>PYTHIA 6.4.26 Tune 350 <lb/>(Central Perugia 2011) <lb/>PHOJET <lb/>EPOS LHC <lb/>PYTHIA 8.170, Tune 4Cx <lb/> (6x) <lb/> -<lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> + <lb/> π <lb/> (3x) <lb/> -<lb/> +K <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/>p <lb/>p+ <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/> 0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/> -<lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> + <lb/> π <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/> Data/MC <lb/> 0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/> -<lb/> +K <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/> 0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/> p <lb/>p+ <lb/> Fig. 18: Top panel: Measured p  T spectra of pions, kaons and protons, sum of particles and antiparticles, compared <lb/>to PYTHIA6-Z2, PYTHIA6-CentralPerugia2011, PYTHIA8, EPOS LHC and PHOJET Monte-Carlo calculations. <lb/>Statistical (vertical error bars) and systematic (open boxes) uncertainties are reported for the measured spectra. <lb/>Bottom panels: ratios between data and Monte-Carlo calculations. <lb/> for p  T  ∼ 1.2 GeV/c and are more pronounced for kaons and protons than for pions. All the tested Monte-<lb/>Carlo generators underestimate the kaon yield by about 20-30% for p  T  &gt; 600 MeV/c while for p  T  &lt; <lb/> 400 MeV/c they overestimate the data by up to 30%. A similar deviation is observed by the ALICE col-<lb/>laboration also for other strange particle species with a hierarchy depending on the strangeness content <lb/>[45]. The proton yield is well described by EPOS only at low transverse momenta (p T  &lt; 1 GeV/c), while <lb/>the generator tends to overestimate the data by up to 30% at higher p  T . None of the three PYTHIA tunes <lb/>describes the shape of the proton spectrum in the full p  T range. All of them give a reasonable description <lb/>of the yield in the range 1 &lt; p  T  &lt; 2 GeV/c, but they overestimate the data at lower and higher p  T by up <lb/>to 40%. <lb/>The comparison of the p  T -dependent particle ratios with models allows the hadronization and soft parton <lb/>interaction mechanisms implemented in the event generators to be tested. In the left and right panels of <lb/>Fig. 19, the measured (K  +  +K  −  )/(π  +  +π  −  ) and (p+p)/(π  +  +π  −  ) ratios as a function of p  T are compared <lb/>with the same event generators shown in Fig. 18. The measured (K  +  +K  −  )/(π  +  +π  −  ) ratio increases from <lb/>0.05 at p  T = 0.2 GeV/c up to 0.45 at p  T  ∼ 3 GeV/c with a slope that decreases with increasing p  T . All <lb/>the models underestimate the data at high momenta, with EPOS exhibiting the smallest deviation. The <lb/>measured (p+p)/(π  +  +π  −  ) shows an increase from 0.03 at p  T = 0.3 GeV/c up to 0.25 at p  T  ∼ 1.5 GeV/c <lb/>while above this p  T it tends to flatten. The data are well described by PYTHIA6-Z2 while PYTHIA6-<lb/>CentralPerugia2011, PHOJET and EPOS show a large deviation at high momenta. PYTHIA8 shows a <lb/>smaller deviation over the whole momentum range even if, as seen in Fig. 18, it overestimates both pion <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body> 0 0.5 1 1.5 2 2.5 3 <lb/> Ratio <lb/> 0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/> -<lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> + <lb/> π <lb/> -<lb/> + K <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/>= 7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> pp, <lb/>ALICE <lb/>| &lt; 0.5 <lb/> y <lb/> | <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 0 0.5 1 1.5 2 2.5 3 <lb/> 0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/> ALICE <lb/>PYTHIA 6.4.26 Z2, Tune 343 <lb/>PYTHIA 6.4.26 Tune 350 <lb/>(Central Perugia 2011) <lb/>PHOJET <lb/>EPOS LHC <lb/>PYTHIA 8.170, Tune 4Cx <lb/> -<lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> + <lb/> π <lb/> p <lb/>p + <lb/> Fig. 19: Measured (K  +  +K  −  )/(π  +  +π  −  ) (left) and (p+p)/(π  +  +π  −  ) (right) ratios as a function of p  T compared <lb/>to PYTHIA6-Z2, PYTHIA6-CentralPerugia2011, PYTHIA8, EPOS LHC and PHOJET calculations. Statistical <lb/>(vertical error bars) and systematic (open boxes) uncertainties are reported for the measured spectra. <lb/> and proton spectra. <lb/>The comparison between data and Monte-Carlo calculations shows that the tunes of the generators based <lb/>only on few global observables, such as the integrated charged hadron multiplicity, allow only for a <lb/>partial description of the data. The high-precision measurements of identified charged hadron p  T spectra <lb/>reported here, which cover a wide momentum range in the central rapidity region, give useful information <lb/>for a fine tuning of the Monte-Carlo generators and a better understanding of soft particle production <lb/>mechanisms at LHC energies. <lb/> 5 Summary <lb/> A detailed analysis of primary π  ±  , K  ±  , p and p production in proton-proton collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV with <lb/>the ALICE detector has been performed. Particle identification is performed using several techniques <lb/>namely the specific ionization energy loss measured in the ITS and TPC, the time of flight measured <lb/>with the TOF detector, the Cherenkov radiation measured in the HMPID and the kink topology identifi-<lb/>cation of the weak decays of charged kaons. The combination of these techniques allows for precision <lb/>measurements of the p  T spectra over a wide momentum range: from 0.1 up to 3 GeV/c for pions, from 0.2 <lb/>up to 6 GeV/c for kaons and from 0.3 up to 6 GeV/c for protons. A comparison of the ALICE results with <lb/>similar measurements performed by the PHENIX Collaboration at RHIC shows that the p  T -integrated <lb/>yields increase with collision energy for all the measured particle species. A slight increase of the p  T  <lb/> with <lb/> √ <lb/> s is also observed. This rising trend that becomes apparent at <lb/> √ <lb/> s &gt; 0.9 TeV is established by the <lb/>higher <lb/> √ <lb/> s LHC data. It could be related to the increasing importance of hard processes at these energies. <lb/>The p  T -integrated K/π and p/π ratios extend the measurements available at lower collision energies from <lb/>SPS, SppS and RHIC experiments showing a saturation above <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 0.9 TeV. Finally, the p  T spectra and <lb/>particle ratios have been compared with the calculations of QCD-inspired Monte-Carlo models namely <lb/>PYTHIA6-Z2, PYTHIA6-CentralPerugia2011, PYTHIA8, EPOS LHC and PHOJET. Even though the <lb/>shapes of the spectra are fairly well reproduced by all models (except PHOJET that fails to describe the <lb/>spectrum shape of all the three hadron species), none of them can describe simultaneously the measured <lb/>yields of pions, kaons and protons. These results can be used for a better understanding of the hadron <lb/></body>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body>production mechanisms in pp interactions at LHC energies and could further constrain the parameters of <lb/>the models. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgements <lb/> The ALICE Collaboration would like to thank all its engineers and technicians for their invaluable con-<lb/>tributions to the construction of the experiment and the CERN accelerator teams for the outstanding <lb/>performance of the LHC complex. The ALICE Collaboration gratefully acknowledges the resources and <lb/>support provided by all Grid centres and the Worldwide LHC Computing Grid (WLCG) collaboration. <lb/>The ALICE Collaboration acknowledges the following funding agencies for their support in building <lb/>and running the ALICE detector: State Committee of Science, World Federation of Scientists (WFS) <lb/>and Swiss Fonds Kidagan, Armenia, Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico <lb/>(CNPq), Financiadora de Estudos e Projetos (FINEP), Fundaç ão de Amparò <lb/>a Pesquisa do Estado de São <lb/>Paulo (FAPESP); National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC), the Chinese Ministry of Edu-<lb/>cation (CMOE) and the Ministry of Science and Technology of China (MSTC); Ministry of Education <lb/>and Youth of the Czech Republic; Danish Natural Science Research Council, the Carlsberg Foundation <lb/>and the Danish National Research Foundation; The European Research Council under the European <lb/>Community&apos;s Seventh Framework Programme; Helsinki Institute of Physics and the Academy of Fin-<lb/>land; French CNRS-IN2P3, the &apos;Region Pays de Loire&apos;, &apos;Region Alsace&apos;, &apos;Region Auvergne&apos; and CEA, <lb/>France; German Bundesministerium fur Bildung, Wissenschaft, Forschung und Technologie (BMBF) <lb/>and the Helmholtz Association; General Secretariat for Research and Technology, Ministry of Develop-<lb/>ment, Greece; Hungarian Orszagos Tudomanyos Kutatasi Alappgrammok (OTKA) and National Office <lb/>for Research and Technology (NKTH); Department of Atomic Energy and Department of Science and <lb/>Technology of the Government of India; Istituto Nazionale di Fisica Nucleare (INFN) and Centro Fermi <lb/>-Museo Storico della Fisica e Centro Studi e Ricerche &quot; Enrico Fermi &quot; , Italy; MEXT Grant-in-Aid for <lb/>Specially Promoted Research, Japan; Joint Institute for Nuclear Research, Dubna; National Research <lb/>Foundation of Korea (NRF); Consejo Nacional de Cienca y Tecnologia (CONACYT), Direccion Gen-<lb/>eral de Asuntos del Personal Academico(DGAPA), México, :Amerique Latine Formation academique <lb/>European Commission(ALFA-EC) and the EPLANET Program (European Particle Physics Latin Amer-<lb/>ican Network) Stichting voor Fundamenteel Onderzoek der Materie (FOM) and the Nederlandse Or-<lb/>ganisatie voor Wetenschappelijk Onderzoek (NWO), Netherlands; Research Council of Norway (NFR); <lb/>National Science Centre, Poland; Ministry of National Education/Institute for Atomic Physics and Con-<lb/>siliul Naional al Cercetrii tiinifice -Executive Agency for Higher Education Research Development and <lb/>Innovation Funding (CNCS-UEFISCDI) -Romania; Ministry of Education and Science of Russian Fed-<lb/>eration, Russian Academy of Sciences, Russian Federal Agency of Atomic Energy, Russian Federal <lb/>Agency for Science and Innovations and The Russian Foundation for Basic Research; Ministry of Ed-<lb/>ucation of Slovakia; Department of Science and Technology, South Africa; Centro de Investigaciones <lb/>Energeticas, Medioambientales y Tecnologicas (CIEMAT), E-Infrastructure shared between Europe and <lb/>Latin America (EELA), Ministerio de Economía y Competitividad (MINECO) of Spain, Xunta de Gali-<lb/>cia (Consellería de Educación), Centro de Aplicaciones Tecnolgicas y Desarrollo Nuclear (CEADEN), <lb/>Cubaenergía, Cuba, and IAEA (International Atomic Energy Agency); Swedish Research Council (VR) <lb/>and Knut &amp; Alice Wallenberg Foundation (KAW); Ukraine Ministry of Education and Science; United <lb/>Kingdom Science and Technology Facilities Council (STFC); The United States Department of Energy, <lb/>the United States National Science Foundation, the State of Texas, and the State of Ohio; Ministry of Sci-<lb/>ence, Education and Sports of Croatia and Unity through Knowledge Fund, Croatia. Council of Scientific <lb/>and Industrial Research (CSIR), New Delhi, India <lb/></div>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body></body>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] T. Sjöstrand, S. Mrenna, and P. Z. Skands, &quot; PYTHIA 6.4 Physics and Manual, &quot;  JHEP 0605 (2006) <lb/>026, arXiv:hep-ph/0603175 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [2] T. Sjöstrand, S. Mrenna, and P. Z. Skands, &quot; A Brief Introduction to PYTHIA 8.1, &quot; <lb/> Comput.Phys.Commun. 178 (2008) 852–867, arXiv:0710.3820 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [3] R. Corke and T. Sjöstrand, &quot; Multiparton Interactions with an x-dependent Proton Size, &quot;  JHEP <lb/> 1105 (2011) 009, arXiv:1101.5953 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [4] T. Pierog, I. Karpenko, J. Katzy, E. Yatsenko, and K. Werner, &quot; EPOS LHC : test of collective <lb/>hadronization with LHC data, &quot;  arXiv:1306.0121 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [5] K. Werner, I. Karpenko, T. Pierog, M. Bleicher, and K. Mikhailov, &quot; Event-by-Event Simulation of <lb/>the Three-Dimensional Hydrodynamic Evolution from Flux Tube Initial Conditions in <lb/>Ultrarelativistic Heavy Ion Collisions, &quot;  Phys.Rev. C82 (2010) 044904, arXiv:1004.0805 <lb/>[nucl-th]. <lb/> [6] R. Engel, J. Ranft, and S. Roesler, &quot; Hard diffraction in hadron hadron interactions and in <lb/>photoproduction, &quot;  Phys.Rev. D52 (1995) 1459–1468, arXiv:hep-ph/9502319 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [7] ALICE Collaboration, F. Carminati et al.,  &quot; ALICE: Physics performance report, volume I, &quot; <lb/> J.Phys. G30 (2004) 1517–1763. <lb/>[8] ALICE Collaboration, B. Alessandro et al.,  &quot; ALICE: Physics performance report, volume II, &quot; <lb/> J.Phys. G32 (2006) 1295–2040. <lb/>[9] ALICE Collaboration, B. B. Abelev et al.,  &quot; Performance of the ALICE Experiment at the CERN <lb/>LHC, &quot;  Int.J.Mod.Phys. A29 (2014) 1430044, arXiv:1402.4476 [nucl-ex]. <lb/> [10] ALICE Collaboration, K. Aamodt et al.,  &quot; The ALICE experiment at the CERN LHC, &quot;  JINST 3 <lb/> (2008) S08002. <lb/>[11] ALICE Collaboration, K. Aamodt et al.,  &quot; Alignment of the ALICE Inner Tracking System with <lb/>cosmic-ray tracks, &quot;  JINST 5 (2010) P03003, arXiv:1001.0502 [physics.ins-det]. <lb/> [12] J. Alme, Y. Andres, H. Appelshauser, S. Bablok, N. Bialas, et al.,  &quot; The ALICE TPC, a large <lb/>3-dimensional tracking device with fast readout for ultra-high multiplicity events, &quot; <lb/> Nucl.Instrum.Meth. A622 (2010) 316–367, arXiv:1001.1950 [physics.ins-det]. <lb/> [13] A. Akindinov, A. Alici, A. Agostinelli, P. Antonioli, S. Arcelli, et al.,  &quot; Performance of the ALICE <lb/>Time-Of-Flight detector at the LHC, &quot;  Eur.Phys.J.Plus 128 (2013) 44. <lb/>[14] ALICE Collaboration, P. Martinengo, &quot; The ALICE high momentum particle identification <lb/>system: An overview after the first Large Hadron Collider run, &quot;  Nucl.Instrum.Meth. A639 (2011) <lb/> 7–10. <lb/>[15] ALICE Collaboration, K. Aamodt et al.,  &quot; Production of pions, kaons and protons in pp collisions <lb/>at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 900 GeV with ALICE at the LHC, &quot;  Eur.Phys.J. C71 (2011) 1655, arXiv:1101.4110 <lb/>[hep-ex]. <lb/> [16] ALICE Collaboration, B. B. Abelev et al.,  &quot; Production of charged pions, kaons and protons at <lb/>large transverse momenta in pp and PbPb collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  NN =2.76 TeV, &quot;  Phys.Lett. B736 (2014) <lb/>196–207, arXiv:1401.1250 [nucl-ex]. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 25 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[17] CMS Collaboration, S. Chatrchyan et al.,  &quot; Study of the inclusive production of charged pions, <lb/>kaons, and protons in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 0.9, 2.76, and 7 TeV, &quot;  Eur.Phys.J. C72 (2012) 2164, <lb/> arXiv:1207.4724 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [18] PHENIX Collaboration, A. Adare et al.,  &quot; Identified charged hadron production in p + p collisions <lb/>at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 200 and 62.4 GeV, &quot;  Phys.Rev. C83 (2011) 064903, arXiv:1102.0753 [nucl-ex]. <lb/> [19] NA49 Collaboration, C. Alt et al.,  &quot; Inclusive production of charged pions in p+p collisions at <lb/>158-GeV/c beam momentum, &quot;  Eur.Phys.J. C45 (2006) 343–381, arXiv:hep-ex/0510009 <lb/>[hep-ex]. <lb/> [20] NA49 Collaboration, T. Anticic et al.,  &quot; Inclusive production of charged kaons in p+p collisions at <lb/>158 GeV/c beam momentum and a new evaluation of the energy dependence of kaon production <lb/>up to collider energies, &quot;  Eur.Phys.J. C68 (2010) 1–73, arXiv:1004.1889 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [21] NA49 Collaboration, T. Anticic et al.,  &quot; Inclusive production of protons, anti-protons and neutrons <lb/>in p+p collisions at 158-GeV/c beam momentum, &quot;  Eur.Phys.J. C65 (2010) 9–63, <lb/> arXiv:0904.2708 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [22] E735 Collaboration, T. Alexopoulos et al.,  &quot; Mass identified particle production in p ¯ <lb/> p collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 300-GeV, 540-GeV, 1000-GeV, and 1800-GeV, &quot;  Phys.Rev. D48 (1993) 984–997. <lb/>[23] T. Alexopoulos, C. Allen, E. Anderson, V. Balamurali, S. Banerjee, et al.,  &quot; Hyperon production <lb/>from p ¯ <lb/> p collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 1.8-TeV. FNAL-735 experiment, &quot;  Phys.Rev. D46 (1992) 2773–2786. <lb/>[24] UA5 Collaboration, R. Ansorge et al.,  &quot; Kaon Production at 200-GeV and 900-GeV <lb/>Center-of-mass Energy, &quot;  Phys.Lett. B199 (1987) 311–316. <lb/>[25] P. Z. Skands, &quot; Tuning Monte Carlo Generators: The Perugia Tunes, &quot;  Phys.Rev. D82 (2010) <lb/>074018, arXiv:1005.3457 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [26] R. Field, &quot; Early LHC Underlying Event Data -Findings and Surprises, &quot;  arXiv:1010.3558 <lb/>[hep-ph]. <lb/> [27] ALICE Collaboration, E. Abbas et al.,  &quot; Performance of the ALICE VZERO system, &quot;  JINST 8 <lb/> (2013) P10016, arXiv:1306.3130 [nucl-ex]. <lb/> [28] ALICE Collaboration, B. Abelev et al.,  &quot; Measurement of charm production at central rapidity in <lb/>proton-proton collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV, &quot;  JHEP 1201 (2012) 128, arXiv:1111.1553 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [29] ALICE Collaboration, B. Abelev et al.,  &quot; Centrality dependence of π, K, p production in Pb-Pb <lb/>collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s NN  = 2.76 TeV, &quot;  Phys.Rev. C88 no. 4, (2013) 044910, arXiv:1303.0737 <lb/>[hep-ex]. <lb/> [30] PHOBOS Collaboration, B. Back et al.,  &quot; Identified hadron transverse momentum spectra in <lb/>Au+Au collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s NN  = 62.4-GeV, &quot;  Phys.Rev. C75 (2007) 024910, <lb/> arXiv:nucl-ex/0610001 [nucl-ex]. <lb/> [31] L. Rolandi, W. Riegler, and W. Blum, Particle Detection with Drift Chambers. 2008. <lb/>[32] ALICE Collaboration, D. Di Bari, &quot; The pattern recognition method for the CsI-RICH detector in <lb/>ALICE, &quot;  Nucl.Instrum.Meth. A502 (2003) 300–304. <lb/>[33] R. Brun, F. Carminati, and S. Giani, GEANT Detector Description and Simulation Tool. 1994. <lb/>[34] G. Battistoni, S. Muraro, P. R. Sala, F. Cerutti, A. Ferrari, et al.,  &quot; The FLUKA code: Description <lb/>and benchmarking, &quot;  AIP Conf.Proc. 896 (2007) 31–49. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body>[35] ALICE Collaboration, B. Abelev et al.,  &quot; Measurement of inelastic, single-and double-diffraction <lb/>cross sections in proton–proton collisions at the LHC with ALICE, &quot;  Eur.Phys.J. C73 no. 6, (2013) <lb/>2456, arXiv:1208.4968 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [36] Particle Data Group Collaboration, J. Beringer et al.,  &quot; Review of Particle Physics (RPP), &quot; <lb/> Phys.Rev. D86 (2012) 010001. <lb/>[37] ALICE Collaboration, B. Abelev et al.,  &quot; Neutral pion and η meson production in proton-proton <lb/>collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 0.9 TeV and <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV, &quot;  Phys.Lett. B717 (2012) 162–172, <lb/> arXiv:1205.5724 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [38] C. Tsallis, &quot; Possible Generalization of Boltzmann-Gibbs Statistics, &quot;  J.Statist.Phys. 52 (1988) <lb/>479–487. <lb/>[39] STAR Collaboration, B. Abelev et al.,  &quot; Strange particle production in p+p collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = <lb/>200-GeV, &quot;  Phys.Rev. C75 (2007) 064901, arXiv:nucl-ex/0607033 [nucl-ex]. <lb/> [40] PHENIX Collaboration, A. Adare et al.,  &quot; Detailed measurement of the e  +  e  −  pair continuum in <lb/> p + p and Au+Au collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s NN  = 200 GeV and implications for direct photon production, &quot; <lb/> Phys.Rev. C81 (2010) 034911, arXiv:0912.0244 [nucl-ex]. <lb/> [41] UA1 Collaboration, C. Albajar et al.,  &quot; A Study of the General Characteristics of p ¯ <lb/> p Collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 0.2-TeV to 0.9-TeV, &quot;  Nucl.Phys. B335 (1990) 261. <lb/>[42] STAR Collaboration, B. Abelev et al.,  &quot; Systematic Measurements of Identified Particle Spectra in <lb/> pp, d  +  Au and Au+Au Collisions from STAR, &quot;  Phys.Rev. C79 (2009) 034909, <lb/> arXiv:0808.2041 [nucl-ex]. <lb/> [43] A. Buckley, J. Butterworth, L. Lonnblad, D. Grellscheid, H. Hoeth, et al.,  &quot; Rivet user manual, &quot; <lb/> Comput.Phys.Commun. 184 (2013) 2803–2819, arXiv:1003.0694 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [44] A. Ortiz Velasquez, P. Christiansen, E. Cuautle Flores, I. Maldonado Cervantes, and G. Pai, &quot; Color <lb/>Reconnection and Flowlike Patterns in pp Collisions, &quot;  Phys.Rev.Lett. 111 no. 4, (2013) 042001, <lb/> arXiv:1303.6326 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [45] ALICE Collaboration, B. Abelev et al.,  &quot; Multi-strange baryon production in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = <lb/>7 TeV with ALICE, &quot;  Phys.Lett. B712 (2012) 309–318, arXiv:1204.0282 [nucl-ex]. <lb/></body>

			<page> 27 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<front> A The ALICE Collaboration <lb/> J. Adam 40 , D. Adamová 83 , M.M. Aggarwal 87 , G. Aglieri Rinella 36 , M. Agnello 111 , N. Agrawal 48 , <lb/>Z. Ahammed 131 , I. Ahmed 16 , S.U. Ahn 68 , I. Aimo 94 ,111 , S. Aiola 136 , M. Ajaz 16 , A. Akindinov 58 , <lb/>S.N. Alam 131 , D. Aleksandrov 100 , B. Alessandro 111 , D. Alexandre 102 , R. Alfaro Molina 64 , A. Alici 105 ,12 , <lb/>A. Alkin 3 , J. Alme 38 , T. Alt 43 , S. Altinpinar 18 , I. Altsybeev 130 , C. Alves Garcia Prado 119 , C. Andrei 78 , <lb/>A. Andronic 97 , V. Anguelov 93 , J. Anielski 54 , T. Antiči´  98 , F. Antinori 108 , P. Antonioli 105 , L. Aphecetche 113 , <lb/>H. Appelshäuser 53 , S. Arcelli 28 , N. Armesto 17 , R. Arnaldi 111 , T. Aronsson 136 , I.C. Arsene 22 , M. Arslandok 53 , <lb/>A. Augustinus 36 , R. Averbeck 97 , M.D. Azmi 19 , M. Bach 43 , A. Badì a 107 , Y.W. Baek 44 , S. Bagnasco 111 , <lb/>R. Bailhache 53 , R. Bala 90 , A. Baldisseri 15 , M. Ball 92 , F. Baltasar Dos Santos Pedrosa 36 , R.C. Baral 61 , <lb/>A.M. Barbano 111 , R. Barbera 29 , F. Barile 33 , G.G. Barnaföldi 135 , L.S. Barnby 102 , V. Barret 70 , P. Bartalini 7 , <lb/>J. Bartke 116 , E. Bartsch 53 , M. Basile 28 , N. Bastid 70 , S. Basu 131 , B. Bathen 54 , G. Batigne 113 , A. Batista <lb/>Camejo 70 , B. Batyunya 66 , P.C. Batzing 22 , I.G. Bearden 80 , H. Beck 53 , C. Bedda 111 , N.K. Behera 49 ,48 , <lb/>I. Belikov 55 , F. Bellini 28 , H. Bello Martinez 2 , R. Bellwied 121 , R. Belmont 134 , E. Belmont-Moreno 64 , <lb/>V. Belyaev 76 , G. Bencedi 135 , S. Beole 27 , I. Berceanu 78 , A. Bercuci 78 , Y. Berdnikov 85 , D. Berenyi 135 , <lb/>R.A. Bertens 57 , D. Berzano 36 ,27 , L. Betev 36 , A. Bhasin 90 , I.R. Bhat 90 , A.K. Bhati 87 , B. Bhattacharjee 45 , <lb/>J. Bhom 127 , L. Bianchi 27 ,121 , N. Bianchi 72 , C. Bianchin 134 ,57 , J. Bielčík 40 , J. Bielčíková 83 , A. Bilandzic 80 , <lb/>S. Biswas 79 , S. Bjelogrlic 57 , F. Blanco 10 , D. Blau 100 , C. Blume 53 , F. Bock 74 ,93 , A. Bogdanov 76 , <lb/>H. Bøggild 80 , L. Boldizsár 135 , M. Bombara 41 , J. Book 53 , H. Borel 15 , A. Borissov 96 , M. Borri 82 , F. Bossú 65 , <lb/>M. Botje 81 , E. Botta 27 , S. Böttger 52 , P. Braun-Munzinger 97 , M. Bregant 119 , T. Breitner 52 , T.A. Broker 53 , <lb/>T.A. Browning 95 , M. Broz 40 , E.J. Brucken 46 , E. Bruna 111 , G.E. Bruno 33 , D. Budnikov 99 , H. Buesching 53 , <lb/>S. Bufalino 36 ,111 , P. Buncic 36 , O. Busch 93 , Z. Buthelezi 65 , J.T. Buxton 20 , D. Caffarri 36 ,30 , X. Cai 7 , <lb/>H. Caines 136 , L. Calero Diaz 72 , A. Caliva 57 , E. Calvo Villar 103 , P. Camerini 26 , F. Carena 36 , W. Carena 36 , <lb/>J. Castillo Castellanos 15 , A.J. Castro 124 , E.A.R. Casula 25 , C. Cavicchioli 36 , C. Ceballos Sanchez 9 , J. Cepila 40 , <lb/>P. Cerello 111 , B. Chang 122 , S. Chapeland 36 , M. Chartier 123 , J.L. Charvet 15 , S. Chattopadhyay 131 , <lb/>S. Chattopadhyay 101 , V. Chelnokov 3 , M. Cherney 86 , C. Cheshkov 129 , B. Cheynis 129 , V. Chibante Barroso 36 , <lb/>D.D. Chinellato 120 , P. Chochula 36 , K. Choi 96 , M. Chojnacki 80 , S. Choudhury 131 , P. Christakoglou 81 , <lb/>C.H. Christensen 80 , P. Christiansen 34 , T. Chujo 127 , S.U. Chung 96 , C. Cicalo 106 , L. Cifarelli 12 ,28 , <lb/>F. Cindolo 105 , J. Cleymans 89 , F. Colamaria 33 , D. Colella 33 , A. Collu 25 , M. Colocci 28 , G. Conesa Balbastre 71 , <lb/>Z. Conesa del Valle 51 , M.E. Connors 136 , J.G. Contreras 11 ,40 , T.M. Cormier 84 , Y. Corrales Morales 27 , I. Cortés <lb/>Maldonado 2 , P. Cortese 32 , M.R. Cosentino 119 , F. Costa 36 , P. Crochet 70 , R. Cruz Albino 11 , E. Cuautle 63 , <lb/>L. Cunqueiro 36 , T. Dahms 92 ,37 , A. Dainese 108 , A. Danu 62 , D. Das 101 , I. Das 51 ,101 , S. Das 4 , A. Dash 120 , <lb/>S. Dash 48 , S. De 119 , A. De Caro 31 ,12 , G. de Cataldo 104 , J. de Cuveland 43 , A. De Falco 25 , D. De Gruttola 12 ,31 , <lb/>N. De Marco 111 , S. De Pasquale 31 , A. Deisting 97 ,93 , A. Deloff 77 , E. Dénes 135 , G. D&apos;Erasmo 33 , D. Di Bari 33 , <lb/>A. Di Mauro 36 , P. Di Nezza 72 , M.A. Diaz Corchero 10 , T. Dietel 89 , P. Dillenseger 53 , R. Diì a 36 , <lb/>Ø. Djuvsland 18 , A. Dobrin 57 ,81 , T. Dobrowolski 77 ,i , D. Domenicis Gimenez 119 , B. Dönigus 53 , O. Dordic 22 , <lb/>A.K. Dubey 131 , A. Dubla 57 , L. Ducroux 129 , P. Dupieux 70 , R.J. Ehlers 136 , D. Elia 104 , H. Engel 52 , <lb/>B. Erazmus 113 ,36 , F. Erhardt 128 , D. Eschweiler 43 , B. Espagnon 51 , M. Estienne 113 , S. Esumi 127 , J. Eum 96 , <lb/>D. Evans 102 , S. Evdokimov 112 , G. Eyyubova 40 , L. Fabbietti 37 ,92 , D. Fabris 108 , J. Faivre 71 , A. Fantoni 72 , <lb/>M. Fasel 74 , L. Feldkamp 54 , D. Felea 62 , A. Feliciello 111 , G. Feofilov 130 , J. Ferencei 83 , A. Fernández Téllez 2 , <lb/>E.G. Ferreiro 17 , A. Ferretti 27 , A. Festanti 30 , J. Figiel 116 , M.A.S. Figueredo 123 , S. Filchagin 99 , D. Finogeev 56 , <lb/>F.M. Fionda 104 , E.M. Fiore 33 , M.G. Fleck 93 , M. Floris 36 , S. Foertsch 65 , P. Foka 97 , S. Fokin 100 , <lb/>E. Fragiacomo 110 , A. Francescon 36 ,30 , U. Frankenfeld 97 , U. Fuchs 36 , C. Furget 71 , A. Furs 56 , M. Fusco <lb/>Girard 31 , J.J. Gaardhøje 80 , M. Gagliardi 27 , A.M. Gago 103 , M. Gallio 27 , D.R. Gangadharan 74 , P. Ganoti 88 , <lb/>C. Gao 7 , C. Garabatos 97 , E. Garcia-Solis 13 , C. Gargiulo 36 , P. Gasik 37 ,92 , M. Germain 113 , A. Gheata 36 , <lb/>M. Gheata 62 ,36 , P. Ghosh 131 , S.K. Ghosh 4 , P. Gianotti 72 , P. Giubellino 36 , P. Giubilato 30 , <lb/>E. Gladysz-Dziadus 116 , P. Glässel 93 , A. Gomez Ramirez 52 , P. González-Zamora 10 , S. Gorbunov 43 , <lb/>L. Görlich 116 , S. Gotovac 115 , V. Grabski 64 , L.K. Graczykowski 133 , A. Grelli 57 , A. Grigoras 36 , C. Grigoras 36 , <lb/>V. Grigoriev 76 , A. Grigoryan 1 , S. Grigoryan 66 , B. Grinyov 3 , N. Grion 110 , J.F. Grosse-Oetringhaus 36 , <lb/>J.-Y. Grossiord 129 , R. Grosso 36 , F. Guber 56 , R. Guernane 71 , B. Guerzoni 28 , K. Gulbrandsen 80 , H. Gulkanyan 1 , <lb/>T. Gunji 126 , A. Gupta 90 , R. Gupta 90 , R. Haake 54 , Ø. Haaland 18 , C. Hadjidakis 51 , M. Haiduc 62 , <lb/>H. Hamagaki 126 , G. Hamar 135 , L.D. Hanratty 102 , A. Hansen 80 , J.W. Harris 136 , H. Hartmann 43 , A. Harton 13 , <lb/>D. Hatzifotiadou 105 , S. Hayashi 126 , S.T. Heckel 53 , M. Heide 54 , H. Helstrup 38 , A. Herghelegiu 78 , G. Herrera <lb/>Corral 11 , B.A. Hess 35 , K.F. Hetland 38 , T.E. Hilden 46 , H. Hillemanns 36 , B. Hippolyte 55 , P. Hristov 36 , <lb/>M. Huang 18 , T.J. Humanic 20 , N. Hussain 45 , T. Hussain 19 , D. Hutter 43 , D.S. Hwang 21 , R. Ilkaev 99 , I. Ilkiv 77 , <lb/>M. Inaba 127 , C. Ionita 36 , M. Ippolitov 76 ,100 , M. Irfan 19 , M. Ivanov 97 , V. Ivanov 85 , V. Izucheev 112 , <lb/>P.M. Jacobs 74 , C. Jahnke 119 , H.J. Jang 68 , M.A. Janik 133 , P.H.S.Y. Jayarathna 121 , C. Jena 30 , S. Jena 121 , <lb/></front>

			<page> 28 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<front> R.T. Jimenez Bustamante 63 , P.G. Jones 102 , H. Jung 44 , A. Jusko 102 , P. Kalinak 59 , A. Kalweit 36 , J. Kamin 53 , <lb/>J.H. Kang 137 , V. Kaplin 76 , S. Kar 131 , A. Karasu Uysal 69 , O. Karavichev 56 , T. Karavicheva 56 , E. Karpechev 56 , <lb/>U. Kebschull 52 , R. Keidel 138 , D.L.D. Keijdener 57 , M. Keil 36 , K.H. Khan 16 , M.M. Khan 19 , P. Khan 101 , <lb/>S.A. Khan 131 , A. Khanzadeev 85 , Y. Kharlov 112 , B. Kileng 38 , B. Kim 137 , D.W. Kim 44 ,68 , D.J. Kim 122 , <lb/>H. Kim 137 , J.S. Kim 44 , M. Kim 44 , M. Kim 137 , S. Kim 21 , T. Kim 137 , S. Kirsch 43 , I. Kisel 43 , S. Kiselev 58 , <lb/>A. Kisiel 133 , G. Kiss 135 , J.L. Klay 6 , C. Klein 53 , J. Klein 93 , C. Klein-Bösing 54 , A. Kluge 36 , M.L. Knichel 93 , <lb/>A.G. Knospe 117 , T. Kobayashi 127 , C. Kobdaj 114 , M. Kofarago 36 , M.K. Köhler 97 , T. Kollegger 97 ,43 , <lb/>A. Kolojvari 130 , V. Kondratiev 130 , N. Kondratyeva 76 , E. Kondratyuk 112 , A. Konevskikh 56 , <lb/>C. Kouzinopoulos 36 , O. Kovalenko 77 , V. Kovalenko 130 , M. Kowalski 116 ,36 , S. Kox 71 , G. Koyithatta <lb/>Meethaleveedu 48 , J. Kral 122 , I. Králik 59 , A. Kravčáková 41 , M. Krelina 40 , M. Kretz 43 , M. Krivda 102 ,59 , <lb/>F. Krizek 83 , E. Kryshen 36 , M. Krzewicki 97 ,43 , A.M. Kubera 20 , V. Kučera 83 , Y. Kucheriaev 100 ,i , <lb/>T. Kugathasan 36 , C. Kuhn 55 , P.G. Kuijer 81 , I. Kulakov 43 , J. Kumar 48 , L. Kumar 79 ,87 , P. Kurashvili 77 , <lb/>A. Kurepin 56 , A.B. Kurepin 56 , A. Kuryakin 99 , S. Kushpil 83 , M.J. Kweon 50 , Y. Kwon 137 , S.L. La Pointe 111 , <lb/>P. La Rocca 29 , C. Lagana Fernandes 119 , I. Lakomov 51 ,36 , R. Langoy 42 , C. Lara 52 , A. Lardeux 15 , A. Lattuca 27 , <lb/>E. Laudi 36 , R. Lea 26 , L. Leardini 93 , G.R. Lee 102 , S. Lee 137 , I. Legrand 36 , J. Lehnert 53 , R.C. Lemmon 82 , <lb/>V. Lenti 104 , E. Leogrande 57 , I. León Monzón 118 , M. Leoncino 27 , P. Lévai 135 , S. Li 7 ,70 , X. Li 14 , J. Lien 42 , <lb/>R. Lietava 102 , S. Lindal 22 , V. Lindenstruth 43 , C. Lippmann 97 , M.A. Lisa 20 , H.M. Ljunggren 34 , D.F. Lodato 57 , <lb/>P.I. Loenne 18 , V.R. Loggins 134 , V. Loginov 76 , C. Loizides 74 , X. Lopez 70 , E. López Torres 9 , A. Lowe 135 , <lb/>X.-G. Lu 93 , P. Luettig 53 , M. Lunardon 30 , G. Luparello 57 ,26 , A. Maevskaya 56 , M. Mager 36 , S. Mahajan 90 , <lb/>S.M. Mahmood 22 , A. Maire 55 , R.D. Majka 136 , M. Malaev 85 , I. Maldonado Cervantes 63 , L. Malinina 66 , <lb/>D. Mal&apos;Kevich 58 , P. Malzacher 97 , A. Mamonov 99 , L. Manceau 111 , V. Manko 100 , F. Manso 70 , <lb/>V. Manzari 104 ,36 , M. Marchisone 27 , J. Mareš 60 , G.V. Margagliotti 26 , A. Margotti 105 , J. Margutti 57 , <lb/>A. Marín 97 , C. Markert 117 , M. Marquard 53 , N.A. Martin 97 , J. Martin Blanco 113 , P. Martinengo 36 , <lb/>M.I. Martínez 2 , G. Martínez García 113 , M. Martinez Pedreira 36 , Y. Martynov 3 , A. Mas 119 , S. Masciocchi 97 , <lb/>M. Masera 27 , A. Masoni 106 , L. Massacrier 113 , A. Mastroserio 33 , H. Masui 127 , A. Matyja 116 , C. Mayer 116 , <lb/>J. Mazer 124 , M.A. Mazzoni 109 , D. Mcdonald 121 , F. Meddi 24 , A. Menchaca-Rocha 64 , E. Meninno 31 , J. Mercado <lb/>Pérez 93 , M. Meres 39 , Y. Miake 127 , M.M. Mieskolainen 46 , K. Mikhaylov 58 ,66 , L. Milano 36 , J. Milosevic 22 ,132 , <lb/>L.M. Minervini 104 ,23 , A. Mischke 57 , A.N. Mishra 49 , D. Mi´ kowiec 97 , J. Mitra 131 , C.M. Mitu 62 , <lb/>N. Mohammadi 57 , B. Mohanty 79 ,131 , L. Molnar 55 , L. Montaño Zetina 11 , E. Montes 10 , M. Morando 30 , <lb/>D.A. Moreira De Godoy 113 , S. Moretto 30 , A. Morreale 113 , A. Morsch 36 , V. Muccifora 72 , E. Mudnic 115 , <lb/>D. Mühlheim 54 , S. Muhuri 131 , M. Mukherjee 131 , H. Müller 36 , J.D. Mulligan 136 , M.G. Munhoz 119 , <lb/>S. Murray 65 , L. Musa 36 , J. Musinsky 59 , B.K. Nandi 48 , R. Nania 105 , E. Nappi 104 , M.U. Naru 16 , C. Nattrass 124 , <lb/>K. Nayak 79 , T.K. Nayak 131 , S. Nazarenko 99 , A. Nedosekin 58 , L. Nellen 63 , F. Ng 121 , M. Nicassio 97 , <lb/>M. Niculescu 62 ,36 , J. Niedziela 36 , B.S. Nielsen 80 , S. Nikolaev 100 , S. Nikulin 100 , V. Nikulin 85 , <lb/>F. Noferini 105 ,12 , P. Nomokonov 66 , G. Nooren 57 , J. Norman 123 , A. Nyanin 100 , J. Nystrand 18 , H. Oeschler 93 , <lb/>S. Oh 136 , S.K. Oh 67 , A. Ohlson 36 , A. Okatan 69 , T. Okubo 47 , L. Olah 135 , J. Oleniacz 133 , A.C. Oliveira Da <lb/>Silva 119 , M.H. Oliver 136 , J. Onderwaater 97 , C. Oppedisano 111 , A. Ortiz Velasquez 63 , A. Oskarsson 34 , <lb/>J. Otwinowski 97 ,116 , K. Oyama 93 , M. Ozdemir 53 , Y. Pachmayer 93 , P. Pagano 31 , G. Pai´  63 , C. Pajares 17 , <lb/>S.K. Pal 131 , J. Pan 134 , A.K. Pandey 48 , D. Pant 48 , V. Papikyan 1 , G.S. Pappalardo 107 , P. Pareek 49 , W.J. Park 97 , <lb/>S. Parmar 87 , A. Passfeld 54 , V. Paticchio 104 , B. Paul 101 , T. Pawlak 133 , T. Peitzmann 57 , H. Pereira Da Costa 15 , <lb/>E. Pereira De Oliveira Filho 119 , D. Peresunko 76 ,100 , C.E. Pérez Lara 81 , V. Peskov 53 , Y. Pestov 5 , V. Petráček 40 , <lb/>V. Petrov 112 , M. Petrovici 78 , C. Petta 29 , S. Piano 110 , M. Pikna 39 , P. Pillot 113 , O. Pinazza 105 ,36 , L. Pinsky 121 , <lb/>D.B. Piyarathna 121 , M. Płosko´  74 , M. Planinic 128 , J. Pluta 133 , S. Pochybova 135 , P.L.M. Podesta-Lerma 118 , <lb/>M.G. Poghosyan 86 , B. Polichtchouk 112 , N. Poljak 128 , W. Poonsawat 114 , A. Pop 78 , S. Porteboeuf-Houssais 70 , <lb/>J. Porter 74 , J. Pospisil 83 , S.K. Prasad 4 , R. Preghenella 105 ,36 , F. Prino 111 , C.A. Pruneau 134 , I. Pshenichnov 56 , <lb/>M. Puccio 111 , G. Puddu 25 , P. Pujahari 134 , V. Punin 99 , J. Putschke 134 , H. Qvigstad 22 , A. Rachevski 110 , <lb/>S. Raha 4 , S. Rajput 90 , J. Rak 122 , A. Rakotozafindrabe 15 , L. Ramello 32 , R. Raniwala 91 , S. Raniwala 91 , <lb/>S.S. Räsänen 46 , B.T. Rascanu 53 , D. Rathee 87 , V. Razazi 25 , K.F. Read 124 , J.S. Real 71 , K. Redlich 77 , <lb/>R.J. Reed 134 , A. Rehman 18 , P. Reichelt 53 , M. Reicher 57 , F. Reidt 93 ,36 , X. Ren 7 , R. Renfordt 53 , <lb/>A.R. Reolon 72 , A. Reshetin 56 , F. Rettig 43 , J.-P. Revol 12 , K. Reygers 93 , V. Riabov 85 , R.A. Ricci 73 , T. Richert 34 , <lb/>M. Richter 22 , P. Riedler 36 , W. Riegler 36 , F. Riggi 29 , C. Ristea 62 , A. Rivetti 111 , E. Rocco 57 , M. Rodríguez <lb/>Cahuantzi 11 ,2 , A. Rodriguez Manso 81 , K. Røed 22 , E. Rogochaya 66 , D. Rohr 43 , D. Röhrich 18 , R. Romita 123 , <lb/>F. Ronchetti 72 , L. Ronflette 113 , P. Rosnet 70 , A. Rossi 36 , F. Roukoutakis 88 , A. Roy 49 , C. Roy 55 , P. Roy 101 , <lb/>A.J. Rubio Montero 10 , R. Rui 26 , R. Russo 27 , E. Ryabinkin 100 , Y. Ryabov 85 , A. Rybicki 116 , S. Sadovsky 112 , <lb/>K. ˇ <lb/>Safařík 36 , B. Sahlmuller 53 , P. Sahoo 49 , R. Sahoo 49 , S. Sahoo 61 , P.K. Sahu 61 , J. Saini 131 , S. Sakai 72 , <lb/>M.A. Saleh 134 , C.A. Salgado 17 , J. Salzwedel 20 , S. Sambyal 90 , V. Samsonov 85 , X. Sanchez Castro 55 , <lb/></front>

			<page> 29 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<front> L. ˇ <lb/>Sándor 59 , A. Sandoval 64 , M. Sano 127 , G. Santagati 29 , D. Sarkar 131 , E. Scapparone 105 , F. Scarlassara 30 , <lb/>R.P. Scharenberg 95 , C. Schiaua 78 , R. Schicker 93 , C. Schmidt 97 , H.R. Schmidt 35 , S. Schuchmann 53 , <lb/>J. Schukraft 36 , M. Schulc 40 , T. Schuster 136 , Y. Schutz 113 ,36 , K. Schwarz 97 , K. Schweda 97 , G. Scioli 28 , <lb/>E. Scomparin 111 , R. Scott 124 , K.S. Seeder 119 , J.E. Seger 86 , Y. Sekiguchi 126 , I. Selyuzhenkov 97 , K. Senosi 65 , <lb/>J. Seo 67 ,96 , E. Serradilla 10 ,64 , A. Sevcenco 62 , A. Shabanov 56 , A. Shabetai 113 , O. Shadura 3 , R. Shahoyan 36 , <lb/>A. Shangaraev 112 , A. Sharma 90 , N. Sharma 61 ,124 , K. Shigaki 47 , K. Shtejer 9 ,27 , Y. Sibiriak 100 , <lb/>S. Siddhanta 106 , K.M. Sielewicz 36 , T. Siemiarczuk 77 , D. Silvermyr 84 ,34 , C. Silvestre 71 , G. Simatovic 128 , <lb/>G. Simonetti 36 , R. Singaraju 131 , R. Singh 79 , S. Singha 79 ,131 , V. Singhal 131 , B.C. Sinha 131 , T. Sinha 101 , <lb/>B. Sitar 39 , M. Sitta 32 , T.B. Skaali 22 , M. Slupecki 122 , N. Smirnov 136 , R.J.M. Snellings 57 , T.W. Snellman 122 , <lb/>C. Søgaard 34 , R. Soltz 75 , J. Song 96 , M. Song 137 , Z. Song 7 , F. Soramel 30 , S. Sorensen 124 , M. Spacek 40 , <lb/>E. Spiriti 72 , I. Sputowska 116 , M. Spyropoulou-Stassinaki 88 , B.K. Srivastava 95 , J. Stachel 93 , I. Stan 62 , <lb/>G. Stefanek 77 , M. Steinpreis 20 , E. Stenlund 34 , G. Steyn 65 , J.H. Stiller 93 , D. Stocco 113 , P. Strmen 39 , <lb/>A.A.P. Suaide 119 , T. Sugitate 47 , C. Suire 51 , M. Suleymanov 16 , R. Sultanov 58 , M. ˇ <lb/>Sumbera 83 , <lb/>T.J.M. Symons 74 , A. Szabo 39 , A. Szanto de Toledo 119 ,i , I. Szarka 39 , A. Szczepankiewicz 36 , M. Szymanski 133 , <lb/>J. Takahashi 120 , N. Tanaka 127 , M.A. Tangaro 33 , J.D. Tapia Takaki ,ii,51 , A. Tarantola Peloni 53 , M. Tariq 19 , <lb/>M.G. Tarzila 78 , A. Tauro 36 , G. Tejeda Muñoz 2 , A. Telesca 36 , K. Terasaki 126 , C. Terrevoli 30 ,25 , B. Teyssier 129 , <lb/>J. Thäder 97 ,74 , D. Thomas 117 , R. Tieulent 129 , A.R. Timmins 121 , A. Toia 53 , S. Trogolo 111 , V. Trubnikov 3 , <lb/>W.H. Trzaska 122 , T. Tsuji 126 , A. Tumkin 99 , R. Turrisi 108 , T.S. Tveter 22 , K. Ullaland 18 , A. Uras 129 , <lb/>G.L. Usai 25 , A. Utrobicic 128 , M. Vajzer 83 , M. Vala 59 , L. Valencia Palomo 70 , S. Vallero 27 , J. Van Der Maarel 57 , <lb/>J.W. Van Hoorne 36 , M. van Leeuwen 57 , T. Vanat 83 , P. Vande Vyvre 36 , D. Varga 135 , A. Vargas 2 , M. Vargyas 122 , <lb/>R. Varma 48 , M. Vasileiou 88 , A. Vasiliev 100 , A. Vauthier 71 , V. Vechernin 130 , A.M. Veen 57 , M. Veldhoen 57 , <lb/>A. Velure 18 , M. Venaruzzo 73 , E. Vercellin 27 , S. Vergara Limón 2 , R. Vernet 8 , M. Verweij 134 , L. Vickovic 115 , <lb/>G. Viesti 30 ,i , J. Viinikainen 122 , Z. Vilakazi 125 , O. Villalobos Baillie 102 , A. Vinogradov 100 , L. Vinogradov 130 , <lb/>Y. Vinogradov 99 , T. Virgili 31 , V. Vislavicius 34 , Y.P. Viyogi 131 , A. Vodopyanov 66 , M.A. Völkl 93 , K. Voloshin 58 , <lb/>S.A. Voloshin 134 , G. Volpe 135 ,36 , B. von Haller 36 , I. Vorobyev 92 ,37 , D. Vranic 97 ,36 , J. Vrláková 41 , <lb/>B. Vulpescu 70 , A. Vyushin 99 , B. Wagner 18 , J. Wagner 97 , H. Wang 57 , M. Wang 7 ,113 , Y. Wang 93 , <lb/>D. Watanabe 127 , M. Weber 36 ,121 , S.G. Weber 97 , J.P. Wessels 54 , U. Westerhoff 54 , J. Wiechula 35 , J. Wikne 22 , <lb/>M. Wilde 54 , G. Wilk 77 , J. Wilkinson 93 , M.C.S. Williams 105 , B. Windelband 93 , M. Winn 93 , C.G. Yaldo 134 , <lb/>Y. Yamaguchi 126 , H. Yang 57 , P. Yang 7 , S. Yano 47 , S. Yasnopolskiy 100 , Z. Yin 7 , H. Yokoyama 127 , I.-K. Yoo 96 , <lb/>V. Yurchenko 3 , I. Yushmanov 100 , A. Zaborowska 133 , V. Zaccolo 80 , A. Zaman 16 , C. Zampolli 105 , <lb/>H.J.C. Zanoli 119 , S. Zaporozhets 66 , A. Zarochentsev 130 , P. Závada 60 , N. Zaviyalov 99 , H. Zbroszczyk 133 , <lb/>I.S. Zgura 62 , M. Zhalov 85 , H. Zhang 18 ,7 , X. Zhang 74 , Y. Zhang 7 , C. Zhao 22 , N. Zhigareva 58 , D. Zhou 7 , <lb/>Y. Zhou 80 ,57 , Z. Zhou 18 , H. Zhu 18 ,7 , J. Zhu 113 ,7 , X. Zhu 7 , A. Zichichi 12 ,28 , A. Zimmermann 93 , <lb/>M.B. Zimmermann 54 ,36 , G. Zinovjev 3 , M. Zyzak 43 <lb/> Affiliation notes <lb/> i Deceased <lb/> ii Also at: University of Kansas, Lawrence, Kansas, United States <lb/> Collaboration Institutes <lb/> 1 A.I. Alikhanyan National Science Laboratory (Yerevan Physics Institute) Foundation, Yerevan, Armenia <lb/> 2 Benemérita Universidad Autónoma de Puebla, Puebla, Mexico <lb/> 3 Bogolyubov Institute for Theoretical Physics, Kiev, Ukraine <lb/> 4 Bose Institute, Department of Physics and Centre for Astroparticle Physics and Space Science (CAPSS), <lb/>Kolkata, India <lb/> 5 Budker Institute for Nuclear Physics, Novosibirsk, Russia <lb/> 6 California Polytechnic State University, San Luis Obispo, California, United States <lb/> 7 Central China Normal University, Wuhan, China <lb/> 8 Centre de Calcul de l&apos;IN2P3, Villeurbanne, France <lb/> 9 Centro de Aplicaciones Tecnológicas y Desarrollo Nuclear (CEADEN), Havana, Cuba <lb/> 10 Centro de Investigaciones Energéticas Medioambientales y Tecnológicas (CIEMAT), Madrid, Spain <lb/> 11 Centro de Investigación y de Estudios Avanzados (CINVESTAV), Mexico City and Mérida, Mexico <lb/> 12 Centro Fermi -Museo Storico della Fisica e Centro Studi e Ricerche &quot; Enrico Fermi &quot; , Rome, Italy <lb/> 13 Chicago State University, Chicago, Illinois, USA <lb/> 14 China Institute of Atomic Energy, Beijing, China <lb/></front>

			<page> 30 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<front> 15 Commissariat à l&apos;Energie Atomique, IRFU, Saclay, France <lb/> 16 COMSATS Institute of Information Technology (CIIT), Islamabad, Pakistan <lb/> 17 Departamento de Física de Partículas and IGFAE, Universidad de Santiago de Compostela, Santiago de <lb/>Compostela, Spain <lb/> 18 Department of Physics and Technology, University of Bergen, Bergen, Norway <lb/> 19 Department of Physics, Aligarh Muslim University, Aligarh, India <lb/> 20 Department of Physics, Ohio State University, Columbus, Ohio, United States <lb/> 21 Department of Physics, Sejong University, Seoul, South Korea <lb/> 22 Department of Physics, University of Oslo, Oslo, Norway <lb/> 23 Dipartimento di Elettrotecnica ed Elettronica del Politecnico, Bari, Italy <lb/> 24 Dipartimento di Fisica dell&apos;Universià &apos;La Sapienza&apos; and Sezione INFN Rome, Italy <lb/> 25 Dipartimento di Fisica dell&apos;Universià and Sezione INFN, Cagliari, Italy <lb/> 26 Dipartimento di Fisica dell&apos;Universià and Sezione INFN, Trieste, Italy <lb/> 27 Dipartimento di Fisica dell&apos;Universià and Sezione INFN, Turin, Italy <lb/> 28 Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia dell&apos;Universià and Sezione INFN, Bologna, Italy <lb/> 29 Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia dell&apos;Universià and Sezione INFN, Catania, Italy <lb/> 30 Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia dell&apos;Universià and Sezione INFN, Padova, Italy <lb/> 31 Dipartimento di Fisica &apos;E.R. Caianiello&apos; dell&apos;Universià and Gruppo Collegato INFN, Salerno, Italy <lb/> 32 Dipartimento di Scienze e Innovazione Tecnologica dell&apos;Universià del Piemonte Orientale and Gruppo <lb/>Collegato INFN, Alessandria, Italy <lb/> 33 Dipartimento Interateneo di Fisica &apos;M. Merlin&apos; and Sezione INFN, Bari, Italy <lb/> 34 Division of Experimental High Energy Physics, University of Lund, Lund, Sweden <lb/> 35 Eberhard Karls Universität Tübingen, Tübingen, Germany <lb/> 36 European Organization for Nuclear Research (CERN), Geneva, Switzerland <lb/> 37 Excellence Cluster Universe, Technische Universität München, Munich, Germany <lb/> 38 Faculty of Engineering, Bergen University College, Bergen, Norway <lb/> 39 Faculty of Mathematics, Physics and Informatics, Comenius University, Bratislava, Slovakia <lb/> 40 Faculty of Nuclear Sciences and Physical Engineering, Czech Technical University in Prague, Prague, <lb/>Czech Republic <lb/> 41 Faculty of Science, P.J. ˇ <lb/>Safárik University, Košice, Slovakia <lb/> 42 Faculty of Technology, Buskerud and Vestfold University College, Vestfold, Norway <lb/> 43 Frankfurt Institute for Advanced Studies, Johann Wolfgang Goethe-Universität Frankfurt, Frankfurt, <lb/>Germany <lb/> 44 Gangneung-Wonju National University, Gangneung, South Korea <lb/> 45 Gauhati University, Department of Physics, Guwahati, India <lb/> 46 Helsinki Institute of Physics (HIP), Helsinki, Finland <lb/> 47 Hiroshima University, Hiroshima, Japan <lb/> 48 Indian Institute of Technology Bombay (IIT), Mumbai, India <lb/> 49 Indian Institute of Technology Indore, Indore (IITI), India <lb/> 50 Inha University, Incheon, South Korea <lb/> 51 Institut de Physique Nucléaire d&apos;Orsay (IPNO), Université Paris-Sud, CNRS-IN2P3, Orsay, France <lb/> 52 Institut für Informatik, Johann Wolfgang Goethe-Universität Frankfurt, Frankfurt, Germany <lb/> 53 Institut für Kernphysik, Johann Wolfgang Goethe-Universität Frankfurt, Frankfurt, Germany <lb/> 54 Institut für Kernphysik, Westfälische Wilhelms-Universität Münster, Münster, Germany <lb/> 55 Institut Pluridisciplinaire Hubert Curien (IPHC), Université de Strasbourg, CNRS-IN2P3, Strasbourg, <lb/>France <lb/> 56 Institute for Nuclear Research, Academy of Sciences, Moscow, Russia <lb/> 57 Institute for Subatomic Physics of Utrecht University, Utrecht, Netherlands <lb/> 58 Institute for Theoretical and Experimental Physics, Moscow, Russia <lb/> 59 Institute of Experimental Physics, Slovak Academy of Sciences, Košice, Slovakia <lb/> 60 Institute of Physics, Academy of Sciences of the Czech Republic, Prague, Czech Republic <lb/> 61 Institute of Physics, Bhubaneswar, India <lb/> 62 Institute of Space Science (ISS), Bucharest, Romania <lb/> 63 Instituto de Ciencias Nucleares, Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México, Mexico City, Mexico <lb/> 64 Instituto de Física, Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México, Mexico City, Mexico <lb/> 65 iThemba LABS, National Research Foundation, Somerset West, South Africa <lb/></front>

			<page> 31 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<front> 66 Joint Institute for Nuclear Research (JINR), Dubna, Russia <lb/> 67 Konkuk University, Seoul, South Korea <lb/> 68 Korea Institute of Science and Technology Information, Daejeon, South Korea <lb/> 69 KTO Karatay University, Konya, Turkey <lb/> 70 Laboratoire de Physique Corpusculaire (LPC), Clermont Université, Université Blaise Pascal, <lb/>CNRS–IN2P3, Clermont-Ferrand, France <lb/> 71 Laboratoire de Physique Subatomique et de Cosmologie, Université Grenoble-Alpes, CNRS-IN2P3, <lb/>Grenoble, France <lb/> 72 Laboratori Nazionali di Frascati, INFN, Frascati, Italy <lb/> 73 Laboratori Nazionali di Legnaro, INFN, Legnaro, Italy <lb/> 74 Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, Berkeley, California, United States <lb/> 75 Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, Livermore, California, United States <lb/> 76 Moscow Engineering Physics Institute, Moscow, Russia <lb/> 77 National Centre for Nuclear Studies, Warsaw, Poland <lb/> 78 National Institute for Physics and Nuclear Engineering, Bucharest, Romania <lb/> 79 National Institute of Science Education and Research, Bhubaneswar, India <lb/> 80 Niels Bohr Institute, University of Copenhagen, Copenhagen, Denmark <lb/> 81 Nikhef, National Institute for Subatomic Physics, Amsterdam, Netherlands <lb/> 82 Nuclear Physics Group, STFC Daresbury Laboratory, Daresbury, United Kingdom <lb/> 83 Nuclear Physics Institute, Academy of Sciences of the Czech Republic, ˇ <lb/>Rež u Prahy, Czech Republic <lb/> 84 Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Oak Ridge, Tennessee, United States <lb/> 85 Petersburg Nuclear Physics Institute, Gatchina, Russia <lb/> 86 Physics Department, Creighton University, Omaha, Nebraska, United States <lb/> 87 Physics Department, Panjab University, Chandigarh, India <lb/> 88 Physics Department, University of Athens, Athens, Greece <lb/> 89 Physics Department, University of Cape Town, Cape Town, South Africa <lb/> 90 Physics Department, University of Jammu, Jammu, India <lb/> 91 Physics Department, University of Rajasthan, Jaipur, India <lb/> 92 Physik Department, Technische Universität München, Munich, Germany <lb/> 93 Physikalisches Institut, Ruprecht-Karls-Universität Heidelberg, Heidelberg, Germany <lb/> 94 Politecnico di Torino, Turin, Italy <lb/> 95 Purdue University, West Lafayette, Indiana, United States <lb/> 96 Pusan National University, Pusan, South Korea <lb/> 97 Research Division and ExtreMe Matter Institute EMMI, GSI Helmholtzzentrum für <lb/>Schwerionenforschung, Darmstadt, Germany <lb/> 98 Rudjer Boškovi´ Institute, Zagreb, Croatia <lb/> 99 Russian Federal Nuclear Center (VNIIEF), Sarov, Russia <lb/> 100 Russian Research Centre Kurchatov Institute, Moscow, Russia <lb/> 101 Saha Institute of Nuclear Physics, Kolkata, India <lb/> 102 School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Birmingham, Birmingham, United Kingdom <lb/> 103 Sección Física, Departamento de Ciencias, Pontificia Universidad Católica del Perú, Lima, Peru <lb/> 104 Sezione INFN, Bari, Italy <lb/> 105 Sezione INFN, Bologna, Italy <lb/> 106 Sezione INFN, Cagliari, Italy <lb/> 107 Sezione INFN, Catania, Italy <lb/> 108 Sezione INFN, Padova, Italy <lb/> 109 Sezione INFN, Rome, Italy <lb/> 110 Sezione INFN, Trieste, Italy <lb/> 111 Sezione INFN, Turin, Italy <lb/> 112 SSC IHEP of NRC Kurchatov institute, Protvino, Russia <lb/> 113 SUBATECH, Ecole des Mines de Nantes, Université de Nantes, CNRS-IN2P3, Nantes, France <lb/> 114 Suranaree University of Technology, Nakhon Ratchasima, Thailand <lb/> 115 Technical University of Split FESB, Split, Croatia <lb/> 116 The Henryk Niewodniczanski Institute of Nuclear Physics, Polish Academy of Sciences, Cracow, Poland <lb/> 117 The University of Texas at Austin, Physics Department, Austin, Texas, USA <lb/> 118 Universidad Autónoma de Sinaloa, Culiacán, Mexico <lb/></front>

			<page> 32 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Pion, kaon and proton productionin pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<front> 119 Universidade de São Paulo (USP), São Paulo, Brazil <lb/> 120 Universidade Estadual de Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil <lb/> 121 University of Houston, Houston, Texas, United States <lb/> 122 University of Jyväskylä, Jyväskylä, Finland <lb/> 123 University of Liverpool, Liverpool, United Kingdom <lb/> 124 University of Tennessee, Knoxville, Tennessee, United States <lb/> 125 University of the Witwatersrand, Johannesburg, South Africa <lb/> 126 University of Tokyo, Tokyo, Japan <lb/> 127 University of Tsukuba, Tsukuba, Japan <lb/> 128 University of Zagreb, Zagreb, Croatia <lb/> 129 Université de Lyon, Université Lyon 1, CNRS/IN2P3, IPN-Lyon, Villeurbanne, France <lb/> 130 V. Fock Institute for Physics, St. Petersburg State University, St. Petersburg, Russia <lb/> 131 Variable Energy Cyclotron Centre, Kolkata, India <lb/> 132 Vinča Institute of Nuclear Sciences, Belgrade, Serbia <lb/> 133 Warsaw University of Technology, Warsaw, Poland <lb/> 134 Wayne State University, Detroit, Michigan, United States <lb/> 135 Wigner Research Centre for Physics, Hungarian Academy of Sciences, Budapest, Hungary <lb/> 136 Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut, United States <lb/> 137 Yonsei University, Seoul, South Korea <lb/> 138 Zentrum für Technologietransfer und Telekommunikation (ZTT), Fachhochschule Worms, Worms, <lb/>Germany <lb/></front>

			<page> 33 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
