<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> arXiv:1504.07151v1  [nucl-ex] 27 Apr 2015 <lb/> EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH <lb/> CERN-PH-EP-2015-092 <lb/>1 April 2015 <lb/>c <lb/> 2015 CERN for the benefit of the ALICE Collaboration. <lb/>Reproduction of this article or parts of it is allowed as specified in the CC-BY-3.0 license. <lb/> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production at mid-rapidity in <lb/>Pb-Pb collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  NN = 2.76 TeV <lb/> ALICE Collaboration  * <lb/> Abstract <lb/> The transverse momentum (p T ) dependence of the nuclear modification factor R  AA and the centrality <lb/>dependence of the average transverse momentum p  T  for inclusive J/ψ have been measured with <lb/>ALICE for Pb-Pb collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  NN = 2.76 TeV in the e  +  e  −  decay channel at mid-rapidity (|y| &lt; 0.8). <lb/>The p  T  is significantly smaller than the one observed for pp collisions at the same centre-of-mass <lb/>energy. Consistently, an increase of R  AA is observed towards low p  T . These observations might be <lb/>indicative of a sizable contribution of charm quark coalescence to the J/ψ production. Additionally, <lb/>the fraction of non-prompt J/ψ from beauty hadron decays, f  B , has been determined in the region <lb/>1.5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 10 GeV/c in three centrality intervals. No significant centrality dependence of f  B is <lb/>observed. Finally, the R  AA of non-prompt J/ψ is discussed and compared with model predictions. <lb/>The nuclear modification in the region 4.5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 10 GeV/c is found to be stronger than predicted <lb/>by most models. <lb/>  *  See Appendix A for the list of collaboration members <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> Heavy-ion collisions at high energies allow the study of strongly interacting matter under extreme condi-<lb/>tions. Calculations based on Quantum-Chromo-Dynamics (QCD) on the lattice indicate that the hot and <lb/>dense medium created in these collisions behaves like a strongly coupled Quark-Gluon Plasma (QGP) <lb/>[1–4]. Heavy quarks are an important probe for the properties of this state of matter, since they are <lb/>produced via hard partonic collisions at a very early stage and thus experience the complete evolution of <lb/>the system. Quarkonium states, i.e. bound states of a heavy quark and anti-quark such as the J/ψ meson <lb/>(c¯ c state) are of particular interest. It was predicted that the J/ψ formation is suppressed in a QGP due to <lb/>the screening of the c¯ c potential in the presence of free colour charges [5]. Experimentally, a suppression <lb/>of the inclusive J/ψ yield in heavy-ion collisions relative to the corresponding yield in pp, scaled by <lb/>the number of binary nucleon-nucleon collisions, has been observed at the Super Proton Synchrotron <lb/>(SPS) [6–8] and the Relativistic Heavy Ion Collider (RHIC) [9, 10]. The level of suppression was found <lb/>to be similar at SPS and RHIC, despite the significantly different collision energy. More recently, the <lb/>nuclear modification of J/ψ was also measured for Pb-Pb collisions at the LHC [11–13]. While at high <lb/>transverse momentum (p T  &gt; 4 GeV/c) the suppression factor is at the same level as the one observed <lb/>at RHIC in the low p  T region, a significant reduction of the suppression is measured towards lower p  T . <lb/>This has been interpreted as the effect of an additional contribution to J/ψ production at low p  T , due <lb/>to the combination of correlated or uncorrelated c and ¯ <lb/>c quarks [14, 15]. This contribution becomes <lb/>sizable at LHC energies, since the number of c¯ c pairs is much higher than at lower energies. Assuming <lb/>that a deconfined phase is produced and that all the J/ψ are dissociated, this process happens at the <lb/>chemical freeze-out stage of the fireball evolution. This is the approach followed within the statistical <lb/>hadronization models described in Refs. [16, 17]. Alternatively, J/ψ could be generated via coalescence <lb/>throughout the full evolution of the QGP phase, if their survival probability in this environment is large <lb/>enough. This scenario has been implemented in several partonic transport models [18, 19]. It was found <lb/>that both approaches can provide a description of the measured nuclear modification factors [12] and of <lb/>the elliptic flow of inclusive J/ψ [20]. <lb/>The production of open beauty hadrons is expected to be sensitive to the density of the medium created <lb/>in heavy-ion collisions due to the energy loss experienced by the parent parton (a beauty quark) which <lb/>hadronizes into the beauty hadron. This energy loss is expected to occur via medium-induced gluon ra-<lb/>diation [21, 22] and elastic collisional energy loss processes [23–25] and it depends on the QCD Casimir <lb/>coupling factor of the parton (larger for gluons than for quarks) and on the parton mass [26–29]. Other <lb/>mechanisms, such as in-medium hadron formation and dissociation, can be envisaged as particularly <lb/>relevant for heavy-flavour hadrons due to their small formation times [30–32]. <lb/>Inclusive J/ψ production is the sum of several contributions. In addition to the directly produced J/ψ, <lb/>the decays of heavier charmonium states, such as the  χ  c  and  ψ(2S),  also contribute to the inclusive <lb/>J/ψ yield. These two sources (direct and charmonium decays) are defined as prompt J/ψ, where the <lb/>contribution from charmonium decays is about 35% as measured in pp collisions [33]. Since heavier <lb/>charmonia are less strongly bound than the J/ψ they should be more easily dissolved in a deconfined <lb/>medium [34]. The J/ψ suppression measured at the SPS is indeed compatible with the assumption that <lb/>only the excited states are dissolved and not the directly produced J/ψ [6, 7]. On top of the prompt J/ψ <lb/>production, there is an additional non-prompt contribution to the inclusive J/ψ at high centre-of-mass <lb/>energies, coming from the decay of beauty hadrons. Since these decays proceed via weak interactions, <lb/>the resulting J/ψ will originate from a decay vertex that is displaced from the main interaction vertex. <lb/>Their measurement provides a direct determination of the nuclear modification of beauty hadrons. By <lb/>subtracting the non-prompt contribution from the inclusive J/ψ yield one can also provide an unbiased <lb/>information on medium modification of prompt charmonia. The non-prompt J/ψ contribution at mid-<lb/>rapidity has already been measured in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV by ATLAS [35], CMS [36] and <lb/>ALICE [37]. For Pb-Pb collisions at <lb/> √ s  NN = 2.76 TeV CMS has also published prompt and non-prompt <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body> J/ψ production results at mid-rapidity for p  T  &gt; 6.5 GeV/c [13]. <lb/>In this paper we present a differential measurement of the inclusive J/ψ production at mid-rapidity in <lb/>Pb-Pb collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  NN = 2.76 TeV. The p  T dependence of the nuclear modification factor and the <lb/>centrality dependence of the average transverse momentum of J/ψ have been obtained, extending the set <lb/>of results presented in [12]. A measurement of the prompt and non-prompt contributions to the inclusive <lb/>J/ψ production is also presented. The nuclear modification factor of non-prompt J/ψ is determined <lb/>down to p  T = 1.5 GeV/c and compared to model predictions. <lb/> 2 Data Analysis <lb/> A detailed description of the ALICE detector can be found in [38]. For the analysis presented here the <lb/>detectors of the central barrel have been used, in particular the Inner Tracking System (ITS) and the <lb/>Time Projection Chamber (TPC). These detectors are located inside a large solenoidal magnet with a <lb/>field strength of 0.5 T. They allow the measurement of J/ψ mesons via the dielectron decay channel <lb/>in the central rapidity region down to zero p  T . The ITS [39] consists of six layers of silicon detectors <lb/>surrounding the beam pipe at radial positions between 3.9 cm and 43.0 cm. Its two innermost layers <lb/>are composed of Silicon Pixel Detectors (SPD), which provide the spatial resolution to separate on a <lb/>statistical basis the non-prompt J/ψ. The active volume of the TPC [40] covers the range along the beam <lb/>direction −250 &lt; z &lt; 250 cm relative to the Interaction Point (IP) and extends in radial direction from <lb/>85 cm to 247 cm. It is the main tracking device in the central barrel and is in addition used for particle <lb/>identification via the measurement of the specific ionization (dE/dx) in the detector gas. <lb/>Triggering and event characterization is performed via forward detectors, the V0 [41] and two Zero <lb/>Degree Calorimeters (ZDC) [42]. The V0 detectors consist of two scintillator arrays positioned at z = <lb/> −90 cm and z = +340 cm and cover the pseudo-rapidity ranges −3.7 ≤  η  ≤ −1.7 and 2.8 ≤  η  ≤ 5.1. <lb/>The ZDCs, each one consisting of two quartz fiber sampling calorimeters, are placed at a distance of <lb/>114 m relative to the IP in both directions along the beam axis and are used to detect spectator nucleons. <lb/>The results presented in this article are based on data samples collected during the Pb-Pb data taking <lb/>periods of the LHC in the years 2010 and 2011. In the case of the 2011 data sample the Minimum Bias <lb/>(MB) Level-0 (L0) trigger condition was defined by the coincidence of signals in both V0 detectors along <lb/>with a valid bunch crossing trigger. For the 2010 data sample, in addition, the detection of at least two <lb/>hits in the ITS was required. Both MB trigger definitions lead to trigger efficiencies larger than 95% for <lb/>inelastic Pb-Pb collisions. Electromagnetic interactions were rejected by the Level-1 (L1) trigger, which <lb/>required a minimum energy deposition in the ZDC by spectator neutrons. The beam-induced background <lb/>was further reduced during the offline analysis by selecting events according to the relative timing of <lb/>signals in V0 and ZDC. The offline centrality selection is done using the sum of the two V0 signal <lb/>amplitudes. By fitting the corresponding distribution with the results of Glauber model simulations, the <lb/>average number of participants N  part  and the average nuclear overlap function T  AA  = N  coll  /σ  inel <lb/> NN for <lb/>a given centrality class can be determined as described in [43]. Here, N  coll  is the average number of <lb/>binary nucleon-nucleon collisions and  σ  inel <lb/> NN the inelastic nucleon-nucleon cross section. The numerical <lb/>values for N  part  , N  coll  , and T  AA  are tabulated in [12]. <lb/>The 2010 data sample consists of 1.5 × 10 7 events, taken with the corresponding MB trigger. The 2011 <lb/>event sample was enriched with central and semi-central Pb-Pb collisions by using thresholds on the <lb/>V0 multiplicity at the L0 trigger. From the latter data set we analyzed 1.9 × 10 7 central (0–10% of the <lb/>centrality distribution) and 1.7 × 10 7 semi-central (10–50%) events. The summed 2010 and 2011 data <lb/>samples correspond to an integrated luminosity of L  int  = 26.4 ± 0.3(stat.) <lb/> +2.1 <lb/> −1.7  (syst.)  µb  −1  [12]. <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body>  ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> ee <lb/> M <lb/> 2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3 <lb/>3.5 <lb/>4 <lb/> 2 <lb/> c <lb/> Counts per 40 MeV/ <lb/> 20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> × <lb/> ALICE <lb/>= 2.76 TeV <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> 0-40% Pb-Pb, <lb/> c <lb/> &lt; 2.5 GeV/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 0&lt; <lb/>Opposite sign <lb/>Mixed event <lb/> ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> ee <lb/> m <lb/> 2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3 <lb/>3.5 <lb/>4 <lb/> 2 <lb/> c <lb/> Counts per 40 MeV/ <lb/> 500 <lb/> − <lb/> 0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1500 <lb/>2000 <lb/>2500 <lb/>3000 <lb/> 596 <lb/> ± <lb/> = 5011 <lb/> ψ <lb/> J/ <lb/> N <lb/>1.0 <lb/> ± <lb/> : 8.5 <lb/>S+B <lb/>S/ <lb/>0.2% <lb/> ± <lb/> S/B: 1.5 <lb/>Data <lb/>MC <lb/> ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> ee <lb/> M <lb/> 2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3 <lb/>3.5 <lb/>4 <lb/> 2 <lb/> c <lb/> Counts per 40 MeV/ <lb/> 10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> × <lb/> ALICE <lb/>= 2.76 TeV <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> 0-40% Pb-Pb, <lb/> c <lb/> &lt; 6 GeV/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 2.5&lt; <lb/> ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> ee <lb/> m <lb/> 2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3 <lb/>3.5 <lb/>4 <lb/> 2 <lb/> c <lb/> Counts per 40 MeV/ <lb/> 400 <lb/> − <lb/> 200 <lb/> − <lb/> 0 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/>1000 <lb/> 274 <lb/> ± <lb/> = 2911 <lb/> ψ <lb/> J/ <lb/> N <lb/>1.0 <lb/> ± <lb/> : 10.7 <lb/>S+B <lb/>S/ <lb/>0.4% <lb/> ± <lb/> S/B: 4.1 <lb/> Fig. 1: The invariant mass distributions of inclusive J/ψ at mid-rapidity (|y| &lt; 0.8) for Pb-Pb collisions (0–40% <lb/>most central) at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  NN = 2.76 TeV. The left panels show the interval 0 &lt; p  T  &lt; 2.5 GeV/c and the right ones <lb/>2.5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 6 GeV/c. The upper panels display the opposite sign distributions together with the result of the <lb/>mixed event procedure. In the lower panels the background subtracted distributions are shown and compared to <lb/>the simulated line shape. Also, the signal-to-background ratio S/B and the significance of the signal are given. <lb/> 2.1 Inclusive J/ψ <lb/> J/ψ candidates are reconstructed by combining opposite-sign (OS) pairs of electron/positron candidates <lb/>and calculating their invariant mass m  ee . These candidates are selected from tracks reconstructed in the <lb/>ITS and the TPC by employing the set of quality criteria described in [12, 44]. In order to reject the <lb/>background from photon conversions in the detector material, tracks are required to have a hit in one <lb/>of the SPD layers. In addition, at least 70 out of a maximum of 159 space points reconstructed in the <lb/>TPC must be assigned to a given track, which also needs to fulfill a quality criterion of the track fit <lb/>(χ 2  /nd f &lt; 4). The tracks are required to be in the range |η| &lt; 0.8, where the tracking and particle <lb/>identification performance of the TPC is optimal, and to have p  T  &gt; 0.85 GeV/c to improve the signal-<lb/>to-background ratio in the J/ψ mass region. <lb/>Electron candidates are selected by requiring that the dE/dx measurement in the TPC lies within a band <lb/> [−1σ , +3σ ] around the momentum-dependent parameterization of the expected signal, where  σ  is the <lb/>phase space dependent dE/dx resolution (details can be found in [45]). The selection is asymmetric in <lb/>order to minimize the contribution from pions. To further suppress the hadron contamination, tracks that <lb/>are compatible within ±4σ with the proton expectation are rejected. A side effect of this cut is that tracks <lb/>below p  T  = 1 GeV/c are effectively removed. <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body>  Measurement of the inclusive J/ψ yield <lb/> The J/ψ signal counts N  J/ψ are obtained from the number of entries in the background subtracted invari-<lb/>ant mass distributions in the range 2.92 &lt; m  ee  &lt; 3.16 GeV/c 2 . The uncorrelated background is evaluated <lb/>with a mixed event (ME) technique. In order to achieve a good description of the background only elec-<lb/>trons and positrons from events with similar properties in terms of centrality, primary vertex position, <lb/>and event plane angle are combined. The ME distributions are scaled to the same event (SE) distribu-<lb/>tions in the mass ranges 1.5 &lt; m  ee  &lt; 2.5 GeV/c 2 and 3.2 &lt; m  ee  &lt; 4.2 GeV/c 2 , so that the J/ψ signal <lb/>region is excluded. The normalization area contains the  ψ(2S)  signal, but its contribution is negligible <lb/>and can therefore be safely ignored. Also, contributions from the tail of the J/ψ signal shape to this mass <lb/>interval are below the percent level and will thus not significantly affect the normalization. Figure 1 <lb/>shows a comparison of the SE and ME invariant mass distributions for the 0–40% most central Pb-Pb <lb/>collisions for electron-positron pairs at mid-rapidity (|y| &lt; 0.8) in two p  T intervals: 0 – 2.5 GeV/c and <lb/>2.5 – 6 GeV/c. The agreement between the SE and ME distributions outside the signal region is very <lb/>good and allows signal extraction with significances larger than eight. <lb/>The J/ψ yield per MB event in a given p  T interval, Y  J/ψ , is obtained as <lb/> Y  J/ψ  (p  T  ) = <lb/> N  J/ψ  (p  T  ) <lb/> BR ee  N  evts  A ×  ε(p  T  ) <lb/> . <lb/> (1) <lb/>Here BR ee is the branching ratio for the decay J/ψ → e  +  e  −  , N  evts the number of events, and A ×  ε  the <lb/>phase space dependent product of acceptance A and reconstruction efficiency  ε.  The latter is calculated <lb/>from Monte Carlo (MC) simulations as the ratio between the number of reconstructed and generated MC <lb/>J/ψ, which are assumed to be unpolarized. In pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV the J/ψ polarization has <lb/>been measured and was found to be compatible with zero at mid-rapidity (p T  &gt; 10 GeV/c) and forward <lb/>rapidity (p T  &gt; 2 GeV/c) [46–48]. In heavy-ion collisions no measurement exists, but J/ψ mesons <lb/>produced from the recombination of charm quarks in the medium are expected to be unpolarized 1 . The <lb/>MC events used for the calculation of A ×  ε  are constructed by adding to background events, generated <lb/>with the HIJING model [49], J/ψ mesons decaying into e  +  e  −  pairs, whose phase space distribution <lb/>is obtained from extrapolations of other measurements [50], taking into account shadowing effects as <lb/>parameterized in EKS98 [51]. The dielectron decay is simulated with the EvtGen [52] package, using <lb/>the PHOTOS model [53] to describe the influence of final state radiation. This choice, together with the <lb/>simulation of bremsstrahlung in the detector material, is mandatory for a proper description of the low <lb/>mass tail in the measured J/ψ mass distribution and ensures that the fraction of the signal outside of <lb/>the m  ee integration window is properly accounted for in the correction A ×  ε.  The propagation of the <lb/>simulated particles is done by GEANT3 [54] and a full simulation of the detector response is performed. <lb/>The same reconstruction procedure and cuts are applied to MC events and to real data. The quality of the <lb/>simulation is illustrated by the good agreement of the background-subtracted invariant mass distributions <lb/>with the MC simulation of the J/ψ signal shape, after normalizing it to the same integral as the measured <lb/>signal (see Fig. 1). <lb/> Determination of the pp reference for R AA <lb/> From the corrected J/ψ yield Y  J/ψ  (p  T  ) the nuclear modification factor R  AA  (p  T  ) is calculated as <lb/> R  AA  (p  T  ) = <lb/> Y  J/ψ  (p  T  ) <lb/> T  AA   σ <lb/> pp <lb/>J/ψ  (p  T  ) <lb/> . <lb/> (2) <lb/>Since no differential J/ψ measurement at mid-rapidity at low p  T is available for pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = <lb/>2.76 TeV [55], the reference needed for the construction of R  AA is based on an interpolation of the mid-<lb/>rapidity measurements by PHENIX at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 0.2 TeV [56], CDF at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 1.96 TeV [57], and ALICE at <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 1 The impact of the polarization on the acceptance was studied for extreme polarization scenarios in [44]. <lb/></note>

			<page> 5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body>  ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> ee <lb/> m <lb/> 2.6 2.8 <lb/>3 <lb/>3.2 3.4 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>2 <lb/>2.2 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>2.6 <lb/> ALICE <lb/>40-90% Pb-Pb <lb/>= 2.76 TeV <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> ee <lb/> m <lb/> 2.6 2.8 <lb/>3 <lb/>3.2 3.4 <lb/>1.45 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1.55 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.65 <lb/>1.7 <lb/> ALICE <lb/>10-40% Pb-Pb <lb/>= 2.76 TeV <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/>c <lb/> &lt; 10 GeV/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> ee <lb/> m <lb/> 2.6 2.8 <lb/>3 <lb/>3.2 3.4 <lb/>) <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> 〉 <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 〈 <lb/> 1.45 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1.55 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.65 <lb/>1.7 <lb/> ALICE <lb/>0-10% Pb-Pb <lb/>= 2.76 TeV <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> Combined fit <lb/>Mixed event <lb/>Opposite sign <lb/> Fig. 2: The average transverse momentum p  T  of e  +  e  −  pairs, measured for the p  T range 0 – 10 GeV/c, as a func-<lb/>tion of the invariant mass m  ee in centrality selected Pb-Pb collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  NN = 2.76 TeV. The shown uncertainties <lb/>are statistical only. The background p  T  distributions and the total fit results are also shown superimposed to the <lb/>data points. <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV [55]. The interpolated p  T distribution is obtained by fitting the following parameterization <lb/>to the available data sets [50] <lb/>1 <lb/>dσ /dy <lb/> d <lb/> 2 <lb/> σ <lb/> dz T dy <lb/> = c <lb/>z  T <lb/> (1 + a  2  z  2 <lb/>T  )  n  . <lb/> (3) <lb/>Here, z  T is defined as p  T  /p  T  , a = Γ(3/2) Γ(n − 3/2)/Γ(n − 1), and c = 2(n − 1) a, where n is <lb/>the only free fit parameter. The value for p  T  (calculated in the p  T range 0 – 10 GeV/c) at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = <lb/>2.76 TeV, which is needed to translate this parameterization into dσ /dp  T , is determined by interpo-<lb/>lating between the existing p  T  measurements for pp and p¯ p collisions [55–57]. This interpolation is <lb/>done using various functional forms for the <lb/> √ <lb/> s dependence to determine the systematic uncertainty. <lb/>For the absolute normalization of the parametrized spectrum, the same interpolated value dσ /dy = <lb/> 4.25 ± 0.28(stat.) ± 0.43(syst.)  µb  as in [12] is used. <lb/>The main sources of systematic uncertainties for the p  T dependent R  AA of inclusive J/ψ are the signal <lb/>reconstruction procedure, the MC input kinematics, the uncertainties on the interpolated pp reference <lb/>and on the nuclear overlap function. The corresponding values are summarized in Tab. 1. While the first <lb/>two components are uncorrelated between the p  T intervals (type II), the uncertainty due to the nuclear <lb/>overlap function is fully correlated (type I). The pp reference on the other hand introduces both uncorre-<lb/>lated and correlated contributions. To determine the uncertainty related to the signal reconstruction, the <lb/>normalization range of the ME background and the size and positions of the m  ee bins have been varied. <lb/>All track and electron selection criteria, such as the electron inclusion cut and the SPD hit requirement, <lb/>have been relaxed and/or tightened in order to test the stability of the result, as was performed in [12]. <lb/>The value of the systematic uncertainty is determined as the standard deviation of the distribution of all <lb/>results obtained with the listed variations. The evaluation of the uncertainties associated with the MC <lb/>input kinematics is also described in [12], while the uncertainty of the pp reference is estimated from the <lb/>differences between the cross-section values obtained with the fitting procedure based on Eq. (3) and the <lb/>measured values used for the fit at the various energies. <lb/> Determination of p  T  and p  2 <lb/> T  <lb/> Since the collected Pb-Pb statistics would allow the extraction of the J/ψ yield in a few p  T intervals only, <lb/>the average transverse momentum p  T  is determined by a fit to the distribution of the p  T  of e  +  e  −  pairs <lb/>as a function of m  ee . When building such a distribution, the individual e  +  e  −  pairs are weighted by the <lb/>inverse of their acceptance times efficiency (A ×  ε)  −1  , assuming that they come from the decay of a J/ψ. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body>  p  T range (GeV/c) <lb/>0–40% <lb/>0–50% <lb/>Source <lb/>0 – 2.5 2.5 – 6 0 – 1.5 1.5 – 4.5 4.5 – 10 Type <lb/>Signal reconstruction <lb/>10.9 <lb/>11.0 <lb/>22.6 <lb/>8.5 <lb/>10.0 <lb/>II <lb/>MC input kinematics <lb/>3.2 <lb/>5.9 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>4.7 <lb/>5.3 <lb/>II <lb/>Nuclear overlap function T  AA  <lb/> 3.2 <lb/>3.2 <lb/>3.8 <lb/>3.8 <lb/>3.8 <lb/>I <lb/>pp reference <lb/>12.1 <lb/>12.1 <lb/>12.1 <lb/>12.1 <lb/>12.1 <lb/>I <lb/>4.5 <lb/>4.9 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>4.3 <lb/>10.1 <lb/>II <lb/>Total <lb/>12.6 <lb/>12.6 <lb/>12.7 <lb/>12.7 <lb/>12.7 <lb/>I <lb/>12.3 <lb/>13.5 <lb/>23.2 <lb/>10.6 <lb/>15.2 <lb/>II <lb/> Table 1: The correlated (type I) and uncorrelated (type II) systematic uncertainties (in percent) on the measure-<lb/>ment of the nuclear modification factor R  AA of inclusive J/ψ for several p  T intervals in Pb-Pb collisions (0–40% <lb/>and 0–50% most central) at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  NN = 2.76 TeV. <lb/> The resulting p  T  distributions are fitted by the expression <lb/> p  T   meas  = <lb/> 1 <lb/> S(m  ee  ) + B(m  ee  ) <lb/> S(m  ee  ) p  T   J/ψ  + B(m  ee  ) p  T   Bkg <lb/> . <lb/> (4) <lb/>Both factors S and B depend on m  ee and correspond to the distribution of the J/ψ signal and of the back-<lb/>ground. For S the same background subtracted signal distribution S(m  ee  ) is used as for the extraction <lb/>of the yield (see lower panels of Fig. 1), while the background B is generated from the ME sample, as <lb/> B(m  ee  ) = c  B  B  ME  (m  ee  ). The normalization factor is determined by fitting c  B  B  ME  (m  ee  ) to the corresponding <lb/> m  ee distribution of e  +  e  −  pairs excluding the signal region. For the sum S(m  ee  ) + B(m  ee  ) in the denom-<lb/>inator of Eq. (4), the measured OS pair m  ee distribution is used. The p  T   Bkg , defined as the p  T  of the <lb/>combinatorial background pairs, is also calculated from the ME sample. This analysis is performed in <lb/>three different centrality intervals: 0–10%, 10–40%, and 40–90%. Figure 2 shows the measured p  T  of <lb/>the e  +  e  −  pairs in the p  T range 0 – 10 GeV/c together with the results of the fit procedure. In addition, <lb/>with an equivalent method, the mean square transverse momentum p  2 <lb/>T  is also calculated for the same <lb/>centrality intervals. <lb/>The systematic uncertainties of the p  T  measurement for inclusive J/ψ are mainly determined by the <lb/>signal extraction, the stability of track and electron selection criteria and the fit procedure (see Tab. 2). <lb/>While the first two components are not correlated between the different centrality intervals (type II), the <lb/>systematic uncertainty intrinsic to the fit procedure can affect the data points in a correlated way (type I). <lb/>The uncertainties related to the signal extraction have been evaluated by varying the normalization range <lb/>of the ME background, the size and positions of the m  ee bins, the fit region and by using in addition <lb/>to the ME background a linear function for the background description. In addition, the stability of the <lb/>fit procedure was tested by modifying the approach, e.g. by using in the fit the direct sum of S and B, <lb/> instead of the OS pair m  ee distribution, or by using a fit function for B, instead of ME. It was also verified <lb/>by applying the above described method to MC events, which were constructed by combining signal <lb/>with background events with a realistic S/B ratio. It turned out that the procedure allows to recover the <lb/> p  T  of the simulated J/ψ mesons within a 2% difference. This value is assumed as correlated (type I) <lb/>uncertainty. Finally, the uncertainty in the signal-to-background ratio is propagated into the statistical <lb/>uncertainty of the p  T   J/ψ . <lb/> 2.2 Non-prompt J/ψ <lb/> The candidate selection for the non-prompt J/ψ analysis includes, in addition to the previously described <lb/>criteria, the condition that at least one of the two decay tracks has a hit in the first SPD layer, in order to <lb/>enhance the resolution of secondary vertices. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body> Centrality <lb/>Source <lb/>0–10% 10–40% 40–90% type <lb/>Signal extraction <lb/>2.0 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>II <lb/>Track selection <lb/>3.1 <lb/>3.9 <lb/>13.7 <lb/>II <lb/>Stability of the fit procedure (from MC) <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>I <lb/>Total <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>I <lb/>3.7 <lb/>4.2 <lb/>14.4 <lb/>II <lb/> Table 2: The correlated (type I) and uncorrelated (type II) systematic uncertainties (in percent) on the measure-<lb/>ment of the average transverse momentum p  T  of inclusive J/ψ in three centrality intervals in Pb-Pb collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  NN = 2.76 TeV. <lb/> The non-prompt J/ψ fraction has been determined using an unbinned two-dimensional log-likelihood fit <lb/>described in detail in [37], which is performed by maximizing the quantity <lb/>ln L = <lb/> N <lb/> ∑  ln [ f  Sig  · F  Sig  (x) · M  Sig  (m  ee  ) + (1 − f  Sig  ) · F  Bkg  (x) · M  Bkg  (m  ee  )] , <lb/> (5) <lb/>where N is the total number of OS candidates in the range 2.2 &lt; m  ee  &lt; 4 GeV/c 2 and x is the pseudo-<lb/>proper decay length of the candidate <lb/> x = <lb/> c (  L · <lb/> p  T  /p  T  ) m  J/ψ <lb/> p  T <lb/> . <lb/> (6) <lb/>Here  L is the vector pointing from the primary vertex to the J/ψ decay vertex. F  Sig  (x) and F  Bkg  (x) <lb/> (M Sig  (m  ee  ) and M  Bkg  (m  ee  )) are Probability Density Functions (p.d.f.) describing the pseudo-proper de-<lb/>cay length (invariant mass) distribution for signal and background candidates, respectively. F  Sig  (x) is <lb/>defined as <lb/> F  Sig  (x) = f <lb/> ′ <lb/> B  · F  B  (x) + (1 − f <lb/> ′ <lb/> B  ) · F  prompt  (x) , <lb/> (7) <lb/>where F  prompt  (x) and F  B  (x) are the p.d.f. for prompt and non-prompt J/ψ, respectively, and f  ′ <lb/> B is the <lb/>fraction of reconstructed J/ψ coming from beauty hadron decays <lb/> f <lb/> ′ <lb/> B  = <lb/> N  J/ψ←h  B <lb/> N  J/ψ←h  B  + N  prompt <lb/> . <lb/> (8) <lb/>A correction due to different average A ×  ε  values, in a given p  T interval, for prompt and non-prompt <lb/>J/ψ, is necessary to obtain from f  ′ <lb/> B the fraction of produced non-prompt J/ψ, f  B <lb/> f  B  = <lb/> 1 + <lb/> 1 − f  ′ <lb/> B <lb/> f  ′ <lb/> B <lb/> A ×  ε  B <lb/> A ×  ε  prompt <lb/>  −1 <lb/> . <lb/> (9) <lb/>The various ingredients for the determination of f  B are described in the following: <lb/> Monte Carlo p T distributions and polarization assumptions <lb/> Assuming both prompt and non-prompt J/ψ to be unpolarized, at a given p  T their acceptance times <lb/>efficiency values A ×  ε  are the same. However, the p  T distributions of prompt and non-prompt J/ψ <lb/>can be different, resulting in different average A ×  ε  computed over a p  T range of finite size. Different <lb/>hypotheses for the kinematical (p T ) distributions of both prompt and non-prompt J/ψ are considered, i.e. <lb/>including or excluding shadowing or suppression effects as, e.g., those predicted in references [58–60] <lb/>for non-prompt J/ψ. Due to the weak p  T dependence of A ×  ε,  the resulting uncertainty on f  B is small, <lb/>being ∼ 5% at low p  T and ∼ 3% in the highest p  T bin, and is independent of centrality. <lb/>At a given p  T , prompt and non-prompt J/ψ can have different polarization and therefore a different <lb/>acceptance. However, the polarization of J/ψ from b-hadron decays is expected to be small due to the <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body>  ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> ee <lb/> m <lb/> 2.2 2.4 2.6 2.8 3 3.2 3.4 3.6 3.8 4 <lb/> 2 <lb/> c <lb/> Counts per 40 MeV/ <lb/> 0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1500 <lb/>2000 <lb/>2500 <lb/>3000 <lb/> = 61/44 <lb/> dof <lb/> / <lb/> 2 <lb/> χ <lb/> = 2.76 TeV <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> ALICE 0-50% Pb-Pb, <lb/> c <lb/> &lt; 10.0 GeV/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 1.5 &lt; <lb/> Opposite sign <lb/>Fit, all <lb/>3) <lb/> × <lb/> Fit, signal ( <lb/>Fit, background <lb/> m) <lb/> µ <lb/> Pseudo-proper decay length ( <lb/>6000 <lb/> − <lb/> 4000 <lb/> − <lb/> 2000 <lb/> − <lb/> 0 <lb/>2000 4000 6000 <lb/>m <lb/> µ <lb/> Counts per 40 <lb/> 1 <lb/> − <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> = 115/176 <lb/> dof <lb/> / <lb/> 2 <lb/> χ <lb/> 2 <lb/> c <lb/> &lt; 3.16 GeV/ <lb/> ee <lb/> m <lb/> 2.92 &lt; <lb/> c <lb/> &lt; 10.0 GeV/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 1.5 &lt; <lb/> Opposite sign <lb/>Fit, all <lb/> ψ <lb/> Fit, prompt J/ <lb/>from b-hadrons <lb/> ψ <lb/> Fit, J/ <lb/> = 2.76 TeV <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> ALICE 0-50% Pb-Pb, <lb/> Fig. 3: The invariant mass (upper panel) and pseudo-proper decay length (lower panel) distributions for e <lb/> +  e <lb/> −  pairs <lb/>with p  T  &gt; 1.5 GeV/c in Pb-Pb collisions in the centrality interval 10–50% at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  NN = 2.76 TeV. The projections of <lb/>the maximum likelihood fit used to extract f  B are superimposed to the data. <lb/> averaging effect caused by the admixture of various exclusive B → J/ψ + X decay channels. Indeed, in <lb/>more elementary colliding systems, the sizable polarization, which is observed when the polarization axis <lb/>refers to the B-meson direction [61], is strongly smeared when calculated with respect to the direction <lb/>of the daughter J/ψ [62], as observed by CDF [63]. The central values of the fraction of non-prompt <lb/>J/ψ are evaluated with Eq. (9) assuming unpolarized prompt J/ψ and a polarization of non-prompt J/ψ <lb/>as predicted by EVTGEN [52]. The assumption of a null polarization for non-prompt J/ψ results in a <lb/>relative decrease of f  B by only 1% at high p  T (4.5 – 10 GeV/c) and 3% at low p  T (1.5 – 4.5 GeV/c). The <lb/>relative variations of f  B expected in extreme scenarios for the polarization of prompt J/ψ was studied <lb/>in [44]. The uncertainties related to the polarization of prompt and non-prompt J/ψ are are not further <lb/>propagated to the results. <lb/> P.d.f. for prompt J/ψ: F prompt  (x) <lb/> The x distribution F  prompt  (x) for prompt J/ψ, which decay at the primary vertex, coincides with the <lb/>resolution function R(x), which describes the accuracy by which x can be reconstructed. It also enters <lb/>in the p.d.f. describing the x distributions of non-prompt J/ψ, F  B  (x), and of the background candidates, <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body>  F  Bkg  (x). The determination of R(x) is based on the same MC data sample as used for the inclusive <lb/>J/ψ analysis (see Sect. 2.1). The systematic uncertainty on R(x) was estimated with a MC approach <lb/>by propagating the maximum observed discrepancies of the track parameters (space and momentum <lb/>variables) between data and MC to the x variable [45, 64, 65] and was found to be at most 10%. To <lb/>propagate this systematic uncertainty to the final results the fits are repeated after modifying in the log-<lb/>likelihood function the resolution to (1/(1 +  δ  )) × R (x/(1 +  δ  )). In this expression  δ  parameterizes the <lb/>relative variation of the RMS of the resolution function and is varied between −10% and +10%. The <lb/>systematic uncertainty due to the resolution function is smaller in the highest p  T bin, because of the <lb/>better resolution in the x variable and the higher values of the signal-to-background ratio. <lb/> P.d.f. for non-prompt J/ψ: F B  (x) <lb/> The shape of the x distribution of non-prompt J/ψ is estimated by using PYTHIA 6.4.21 [66] in the <lb/>Perugia-0 tune [67] to generate beauty hadrons at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 2.76 TeV, and the EvtGen package [52] to <lb/>describe their decays. The systematic uncertainty related to this shape is estimated by assuming a softer <lb/> p  T distribution for the non-prompt J/ψ which is obtained by adding the suppression effects as predicted <lb/>in [60] and a harder one taken from the same PYTHIA event generator at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV instead of 2.76 TeV. <lb/>The resulting systematic uncertainty is within 3 – 4%. <lb/> P.d.f. for the background: F Bkg  (x) <lb/> The main difference of the analysis presented in this section, with respect to previous work on pp col-<lb/>lisions [37], concerns the description of F  Bkg  (x). In this analysis such a function includes an extra sym-<lb/>metric exponential tail (∝ e  −|x|/λ  sym ) [57] and depends on the invariant mass and the p  T of the dielectron <lb/>pair. It is determined, for each centrality class, by a fit to the data in three p  T regions (1.5 – 3, 3 – 4.5, <lb/>4.5 – 10 GeV/c) and in four invariant mass regions on the side-bands of the J/ψ mass peak (2.2 – 2.6, <lb/>2.6 – 2.8, 3.16 – 3.5, 3.5 – 4 GeV/c 2 , labelled with the indices 1, 2, 3 and 4, respectively), for a total <lb/>of 3 × 4 combinations. The background function in the invariant mass region 2.8 – 3.16 GeV/c 2 and in <lb/>each of the three p  T ranges are obtained by an interpolation procedure as the weighted combination of the <lb/>p.d.f. determined in the other four invariant mass regions. The weights are chosen inversely proportional <lb/>to the absolute difference (or its square) between the mean of the invariant mass distribution in the given <lb/>mass interval and that in the interpolated region <lb/> F  Bkg interp  (x) = <lb/> 4 <lb/> ∑ <lb/> i=1 <lb/> w i F  Bkg i  (x); w i  ∝ |m  ee   i  − m  ee   interp  | <lb/> −n <lb/> (n = 1 or 2). <lb/>(10) <lb/>Optionally, only the two adjacent mass regions can be considered in the interpolation procedure, cor-<lb/>responding to the condition w  1  = w  4  = 0. The central value of f  B has been determined as the average <lb/>of the values obtained with the different assumptions (n = 1 or n = 2, with or without the condition <lb/> w  1  = w  4  = 0). The RMS of the distributions of the relative variations obtained for f  B is used to define <lb/>the systematic uncertainty. It becomes larger for central events and in the lowest p  T interval, where the <lb/>signal-to-background ratio S/B is lower. This approach allows to cope with the much lower S/B ratio in <lb/>Pb-Pb than in pp collisions. <lb/> P.d.f. for the invariant mass distribution of the signal: M Sig  (m  ee  ) <lb/> The shape of the invariant mass distribution for the signal is determined by the same MC simulations de-<lb/>scribed in Sect. 2.1. The influence of detector material budget is studied with dedicated MC simulations, <lb/>where the material budget is varied within its uncertainty (±6%) [68]. The resulting contribution to the <lb/>systematic uncertainty on f  B slightly increases for central events, and ranges from 2 to 4%. <lb/> P.d.f. for the invariant mass distribution of the background: M Bkg  (m  ee  ) <lb/> The shape of the invariant mass distribution for the background candidates is determined from ME pairs. <lb/>The related systematic uncertainty on f  B is evaluated using the like-sign distribution, instead of the ME <lb/>one. The uncertainty increases at higher centrality and in the lowest p  T interval due to the decrease of <lb/>the S/B ratio. <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body>  1.5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 10 GeV/c <lb/>Centr. 0–10% <lb/>Type <lb/>Source <lb/>Centr. <lb/>Centr. <lb/>Centr. <lb/> p  T <lb/> p  T <lb/> 0–10% 10–40% 40–90% 1.5 – 4.5 GeV/c 4.5 – 10 GeV/c <lb/>Resolution function <lb/>23 <lb/>15 <lb/>10 <lb/>28 <lb/>12 <lb/>I <lb/>P.d.f. for non-prompt J/ψ <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>I <lb/>P.d.f. for the background <lb/>22 <lb/>15 <lb/>5 <lb/>23 <lb/>19 <lb/>II <lb/>MC p  T distribution <lb/>5 <lb/>5 <lb/>5 <lb/>5 <lb/>3 <lb/>I <lb/>P.d.f. for the invariant mass of signal <lb/>5 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>5 <lb/>3 <lb/>I <lb/>P.d.f. for the invariant mass of background <lb/>7 <lb/>5 <lb/>3 <lb/>7 <lb/>5 <lb/>II <lb/>Total <lb/>34 <lb/>23 <lb/>13 <lb/>38 <lb/>24 <lb/> Table 3: Systematic uncertainties (in percent) on the measurement of the fraction f  B of J/ψ from the decay of <lb/>beauty hadrons, for different centrality intervals in the transverse momentum range 1.5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 10 GeV/c, and <lb/>in the two p  T intervals for the most central collisions. The contributions which are fully correlated between the <lb/>different centrality classes are denoted as type I, the uncorrelated ones as type II. <lb/> As an example in Fig. 3 the projections of the best fit function for n = 1 and w  1  = w  4  = 0 are shown <lb/>superimposed to the invariant mass (upper panel) and x (lower panel) distributions of the candidates in <lb/>the centrality range 10–50% for 1.5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 10 GeV/c. <lb/>A summary of the systematic uncertainties on the determination of the non-prompt J/ψ fraction is pro-<lb/>vided in Tab. 3 for the three centrality intervals in the integrated p  T range and, in the two p  T ranges where <lb/>the results will be given, for the most central collisions (0–10%). <lb/>The value of f  B is determined in two p  T bins (1.5 – 4.5 and 4.5 – 10 GeV/c) for the 0–50% centrality <lb/>range and in three centrality classes (0–10%, 10–40% and 40–90%) for 1.5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 10 GeV/c. The <lb/> f  B measurements are then combined with the nuclear modification factors of inclusive J/ψ to get the <lb/>non-prompt and prompt J/ψ R  AA <lb/> R <lb/> non−prompt J/ψ <lb/> AA <lb/> = <lb/> f  Pb−Pb <lb/> B <lb/> f <lb/> pp <lb/> B <lb/> R <lb/> incl. J/ψ <lb/> AA <lb/> , <lb/> R <lb/> prompt J/ψ <lb/> AA <lb/> = <lb/> 1 − f  Pb−Pb <lb/> B <lb/> 1 − f <lb/> pp <lb/> B <lb/> R <lb/> incl. J/ψ <lb/> AA <lb/> . <lb/> (11) <lb/> pp interpolation <lb/> The value of f  B in pp collision at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 2.76 TeV, f <lb/> pp <lb/> B , is needed to compute the R  AA for prompt and <lb/>non-prompt J/ψ mesons, see Eq. (11). It is determined by an interpolation procedure. Therefore, a fit is <lb/>performed to the existing measurements of f  B as a function of p  T in mid-rapidity pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = <lb/>7 TeV (ALICE [37], ATLAS [35] and CMS [69]). The function used to fit the data is chosen as <lb/> f <lb/> model <lb/> B <lb/> (p  T  ) = <lb/> dσ <lb/> FONLL <lb/> J/ψ←h B <lb/> dyd p  T <lb/> dσ <lb/> phenom. <lb/>J/ψ <lb/> dyd p  T <lb/> , <lb/> (12) <lb/>which is the ratio of the differential cross section for non-prompt J/ψ obtained by an implementation <lb/>of pQCD calculations at fixed order with next-to leading-log resummation (FONLL) [70] to that for <lb/>inclusive J/ψ, parameterized by the phenomenological function defined in Eq. (3). A similar fit is then <lb/>performed to the CDF results [57] in p¯ p collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 1.96 TeV. Finally, the f <lb/> pp <lb/> B (p T ) value at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = <lb/>2.76 TeV is determined by an energy interpolation, which gives f <lb/> pp <lb/> B  = 0.122 ± 0.010 in the integrated p  T <lb/> range 1.5 – 10 GeV/c. The quoted uncertainty includes: (i) a component from the fit procedure, which <lb/>depends on the uncertainties of both data and FONLL predictions; (ii) the systematic uncertainty due <lb/>to the energy interpolation, which has been estimated by considering different functional forms of the <lb/> √ <lb/> s dependency (linear, exponential and power law); (iii) an additional systematic uncertainty, which has <lb/>been obtained by repeating the whole fitting procedure after excluding, one at a time, the data samples <lb/>used for the f  B fit in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV. <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body>  〉 <lb/> part <lb/> N <lb/> 〈 <lb/> 0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>) <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> 〉 <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 〈 <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/> Transport model (Zhou et al., PRC89 (2014) 054911) <lb/>Transport model (Zhao et al., PRC82 (2010) 064905) <lb/>&lt;0.8 <lb/> y <lb/> =2.76 TeV, pp, Pb-Pb, <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> ALICE, <lb/>2% <lb/> ± <lb/> correlated syst. = <lb/> 〉 <lb/> part <lb/> N <lb/> 〈 <lb/> 0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>) <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> 〉 <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 〈 <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/> &lt;0.8 <lb/> y <lb/> =2.76 TeV, pp, Pb-Pb, <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> ALICE, <lb/>&lt;0.35 <lb/> y <lb/> =0.2 TeV, pp, Cu-Cu, Au-Au, <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> PHENIX, <lb/>&lt;1 <lb/> y <lb/> =17.3 GeV, Pb-Pb, <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> NA50, <lb/> Fig. 4: The average transverse momentum p  T  of inclusive J/ψ measured at mid-rapidity (|y| &lt; 0.8) in centrality <lb/>selected Pb-Pb collisions (filled circles) and pp collisions (open circles) at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  NN = 2.76 TeV as a function of the <lb/>number of participants N  part  . The uncorrelated systematic uncertainties (type II) are depicted by the open boxes. <lb/>Left panel: A comparison to results obtained by the PHENIX collaboration for Au-Au and Cu-Cu collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  NN = 0.2 TeV [9, 71] (open and filled diamonds) and by the NA50 collaboration for Pb-Pb collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  NN = <lb/>17.3 GeV [72] (crosses). The p  T  values are calculated for NA50 and PHENIX in the p  T interval 0 – 5 GeV/c, <lb/>while for ALICE the p  T interval is 0 – 10 GeV/c. Right panel: p  T  is compared to theory predictions by Zhou et <lb/>al. [73] and Zhao et al. [74, 75] for the p  T interval 0 – 10 GeV/c. <lb/> Centrality <lb/> p  T  (GeV/c) <lb/> p  2 <lb/>T  (GeV 2  /c  2 ) <lb/>0–10% 2.23 ± 0.10 ± 0.08 5.50 ± 0.58 ± 0.25 <lb/>10–40% 2.01 ± 0.12 ± 0.08 4.97 ± 0.65 ± 0.34 <lb/>40–90% 2.02 ± 0.19 ± 0.29 5.15 ± 1.05 ± 1.23 <lb/>pp 2.54 ± 0.02 ± 0.01 9.07 ± 0.15 ± 0.07 <lb/> Table 4: The numerical values of p  T  and p  2 <lb/> T  calculated in the range 0 &lt; p  T  &lt; 10 GeV/c for the three analyzed <lb/>centrality intervals in Pb-Pb collisions (the first uncertainty is the statistical and the second is the uncorrelated <lb/>systematic (type II), the correlated uncertainty has a value of 2%, see Tab. 2). The values for pp collisions obtained <lb/>by the interpolation procedure are given as a reference. <lb/> 3 Results <lb/> Figure 4 shows the p  T  of inclusive J/ψ for the three analyzed centrality intervals. The numerical <lb/>values for p  T  are summarized in Tab. 4. As a reference, the p  T  in pp collisions at the same centre-<lb/>of-mass energy, as determined by the interpolation method described in Sect. 2.1, is also presented. The <lb/> p  T  for Pb-Pb collisions is significantly smaller than that for pp collisions. Such a behaviour is not <lb/>observed at smaller centre-of-mass energies (see left panel of Fig. 4), for which no significant system <lb/>size dependence of p  T  is seen. This might indicate the onset of processes which either deplete the high <lb/> p  T region or enhance the J/ψ production at low p  T in heavy-ion collisions at the LHC. The latter effect <lb/>would be expected as a consequence of a significant contribution from c¯ c coalescence. <lb/>It has been suggested [76] that the observable r  AA  = p  2 <lb/>T   AA  /p  2 <lb/>T   pp should be particularly sensitive to <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body>  〉 <lb/> part <lb/> N <lb/> 〈 <lb/> 0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/> pp <lb/> 〉 <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 〈 <lb/> / <lb/> AA <lb/> 〉 <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 〈 <lb/> = <lb/> AA <lb/> r <lb/> 0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/> Transport model (Zhou et al., PRC89 (2014) 054911) <lb/>Transport model (Zhao et al., PRC82 (2010) 064905) <lb/>&lt;0.8 <lb/> y <lb/> =2.76 TeV, Pb-Pb, <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> ALICE, <lb/> 〉 <lb/> part <lb/> N <lb/> 〈 <lb/> 0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/> pp <lb/> 〉 <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 〈 <lb/> / <lb/> AA <lb/> 〉 <lb/> 2 <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 〈 <lb/> = <lb/> AA <lb/> r <lb/> 0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/> &lt;0.8 <lb/> y <lb/> =2.76 TeV, Pb-Pb, <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> ALICE, <lb/>&lt;0.35 <lb/> y <lb/> =0.2 TeV, Cu-Cu, Au-Au, <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> PHENIX, <lb/>&lt;1 <lb/> y <lb/> =17.3 GeV, Pb-Pb, <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> NA50, <lb/> Fig. 5: The ratio r  AA  = p  2 <lb/> T   AA  /p  2 <lb/> T   pp in the p  T interval 0 – 10 GeV/c for inclusive J/ψ measured at mid-rapidity <lb/>(|y| &lt; 0.8) in centrality selected Pb-Pb collisions (filled circles) at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  NN = 2.76 TeV as a function of the number <lb/>of participants N  part  . The uncorrelated systematic uncertainties (type II) are depicted by the open boxes, while <lb/>correlated uncertainty (type I) is shown as the filled box at unity. Left panel: A comparison to results obtained by <lb/>the PHENIX collaboration for Au-Au and Cu-Cu collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  NN = 0.2 TeV [9, 71] (filled diamonds) and by the <lb/>NA50 collaboration for Pb-Pb collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  NN = 17.3 GeV [72] (crosses). The PHENIX and NA50 r  AA values <lb/>are calculated in the p  T interval 0 – 5 GeV/c. Right panel: r  AA is compared to theory predictions by Zhou et al. <lb/>[73] and Zhao et al. [74, 75] for the p  T interval 0 – 10 GeV/c. <lb/> medium modifications affecting the J/ψ transverse momentum distributions. The measured p  2 <lb/>T  values <lb/>for Pb-Pb collisions at <lb/> √ s  NN = 2.76 TeV are summarized in Tab. 4. The corresponding r  AA values as a <lb/>function of N  part  are shown in Fig. 5 and are found to be significantly below unity. This is in contrast <lb/>to results from lower centre-of-mass energies, where either values consistent with unity (PHENIX at <lb/> √ s  NN = 0.2 TeV [9, 71]) or around 1.5 (NA50 at <lb/> √ s  NN = 17.3 GeV [72]) were obtained (see left panel <lb/>of Fig. 5). The measured N  part  dependences of p  T  and r  AA are compared with a transport model <lb/>for inclusive J/ψ by Zhao et al. [74, 75] in the right panels of Figs. 4 and 5. This model includes <lb/>regeneration and dissociation processes, based on in-medium J/ψ spectral functions, throughout the <lb/>evolution of a thermally expanding fireball. It also incorporates nuclear shadowing by reducing the input <lb/>charm cross section by a factor of up to 1/3, with a centrality dependence as estimated in [77]. There is a <lb/>fair agreement between our p  T  results and the model calculation, while the r  AA is poorly reproduced by <lb/>the model. Our p  T  and r  AA results are also compared with the calculations by Zhou et al. [73]. These <lb/>calculations are also based on a transport approach and incorporate dissociation and regeneration of J/ψ <lb/>and heavier charmonia, as well as nuclear shadowing according to EKS98 [51]. The agreement with the <lb/> r  AA measurement is rather poor. It must be noted that our results from Pb-Pb collisions at forward rapidity <lb/>[78] exhibit a continuous decrease of p  T  and r  AA from peripheral towards central events and are thus <lb/>closer to the theory predictions, while the behaviour of mid-rapidity Pb-Pb results is more compatible <lb/>with a flat N  part  dependence. <lb/>The R  AA of inclusive J/ψ in three p  T intervals is shown in Fig. 6 along with the results by the CMS col-<lb/>laboration for the interval 6.5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 30 GeV/c [13], both in 0–40% most central Pb-Pb collisions. The <lb/>corresponding numerical values are 0.82 ± 0.11(stat.) ± 0.10(syst.) for the interval 0 &lt; p  T  &lt; 2.5 GeV/c <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body>  ) <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/> AA <lb/> R <lb/> 0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/> Transport model (Zhou et al., PRC89 (2014) 054911) <lb/>Transport model (Zhao et al., NPA859 (2011) 114) <lb/>&lt;0.8 <lb/> y <lb/> =2.76 TeV, <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> ALICE, Pb-Pb, <lb/>&lt;2.4 <lb/> y <lb/> =2.76 TeV, <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> CMS, Pb-Pb, <lb/>&lt;0.35 <lb/> y <lb/> =0.2 TeV, <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> PHENIX, Au-Au, <lb/> Centrality 0-40% <lb/> Fig. 6: The nuclear modification factor R  AA of inclusive J/ψ, measured at mid-rapidity (|y| &lt; 0.8) in Pb-Pb <lb/>collisions (0–40% most central) at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  NN = 2.76 TeV, as a function of transverse momentum p  T . The filled symbols <lb/>are placed at the measured p  T for the given interval. Since for the data point in 4.5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 10 GeV/c (open <lb/>symbol, 0–50% most central) p  T  is not available due to the limited statistics, it is plotted at the centre of the <lb/> p  T interval. The uncorrelated systematic uncertainties (type II) are depicted by the open boxes, while the correlated <lb/>uncertainties (type I) are shown as the filled boxes at unity. The data are compared to corresponding results by <lb/>PHENIX for Au-Au collisions (0–40% most central) at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  NN = 0.2 TeV [9], by CMS for Pb-Pb collisions (0–40% <lb/>most central) at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  NN = 2.76 TeV [13], and to predictions by the model of Zhou et al. [73] and Zhao et al [74, 75]. <lb/> and 0.58 ± 0.06(stat.) ± 0.08(syst.) for 2.5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 6 GeV/c, where the systematic uncertainties quoted <lb/>here are the uncorrelated (type II) ones, as listed in Tab. 1. The data point for 4.5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 10 GeV/c <lb/>corresponds to the R  AA value given in Tab. 5 (centrality range 0–50%). Note that the binning and cen-<lb/>trality selection chosen for the R  AA values in Tab. 5 is optimized for the extraction of non-prompt J/ψ <lb/>and therefore differs from the one used for the inclusive J/ψ analysis. The results obtained with the two <lb/>binnings are in very good agreement. Table 5 also contains the R  AA values for prompt J/ψ, which are <lb/>numerically identical to the ones for inclusive J/ψ. The inclusive R  AA values below p  T  = 6 GeV/c are <lb/>significantly higher than those measured at higher p  T , corresponding to a decrease of R  AA with increasing <lb/> p  T , while the high p  T data point is close to the CMS measurement. This p  T dependence is similar to the <lb/>one observed at forward rapidity [12], and is in clear contrast to the p  T dependence measured at lower <lb/>centre-of-mass energies by the PHENIX collaboration for <lb/> √ s  NN = 0.2 TeV [9]. Figure 6 also shows <lb/>the model predictions by Zhou et al. [73]. The value of the predicted R  AA is systematically below the <lb/>measurement and exhibits a p  T dependence similar to the one in the data. The prediction by Zhao et al. <lb/>[74, 75] is close to our result. In both models, the rise of R  AA towards p  T  = 0 is due to the dominant <lb/>contribution from J/ψ regeneration via coalescence. <lb/>The fraction of non-prompt J/ψ in the p  T range 1.5 – 10 GeV/c is shown as a function of the number <lb/>of participants for the centrality intervals 40–90% (N part  = 38), 10–40% (N part  = 192), and 0–10% <lb/>(N part  = 356) in the left panel of Fig. 7. Within uncertainties, no centrality dependence is observed. <lb/>The p  T dependence of f  B (centrality: 0–50%) is shown in the right panel of Fig. 7 and compared with <lb/>the measurements by CMS in the centrality interval 0–100% and p  T  &gt; 6.5 GeV/c (for the numerical <lb/>values see Tab. 5). Our results at low transverse momenta extend the CMS measurements in Pb-Pb <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body>  〉 <lb/> part <lb/> N <lb/> 〈 <lb/> 0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/> B <lb/> f <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> | &lt; 0.8 <lb/> y <lb/> , | <lb/> c <lb/> &lt; 10 GeV/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 1.5 &lt; <lb/>= 2.76 TeV <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> ALICE Pb-Pb, <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 1 <lb/>10 <lb/> B <lb/> f <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> =2.76 TeV <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> CMS 0-100% Pb-Pb, <lb/>=2.76 TeV <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> ALICE 0-50% Pb-Pb, <lb/>=7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> ALICE pp, <lb/>=7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> ATLAS pp, <lb/>=7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> CMS pp, <lb/>=1.96 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> , <lb/>p <lb/>CDF p <lb/>=2.76 TeV <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> CMS 0-100% Pb-Pb, <lb/>=2.76 TeV <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> ALICE 0-50% Pb-Pb, <lb/>=7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> ALICE pp, <lb/>=7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> ATLAS pp, <lb/>=7 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> CMS pp, <lb/>=1.96 TeV <lb/> s <lb/> , <lb/>p <lb/>CDF p <lb/> Fig. 7: The fraction of J/ψ from beauty hadron decays f  B at mid-rapidity measured in the p  T interval 1.5 &lt; p  T  &lt; <lb/> 10 GeV/c for centrality selected Pb-Pb collisions at <lb/> √ s  NN = 2.76 TeV (left). The p  T dependence of f  B at mid-<lb/>rapidity for Pb-Pb ( <lb/> √ <lb/> s  NN = 2.76 TeV, |y  J/ψ  | &lt; 0.8) and pp ( <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV, |y  J/ψ  | &lt; 0.9) [37] collisions is compared <lb/>with measurements by CDF (|y J/ψ  | &lt; 0.6) [57], ATLAS (|y J/ψ  | &lt; 0.75) [35], and CMS (|y J/ψ  | &lt; 0.9) [13, 69] <lb/>(right). <lb/> p  T (GeV/c) <lb/> f  B (%) <lb/> R  AA (inclusive J/ψ) R  AA (prompt J/ψ) R  AA (non-prompt J/ψ) <lb/>0.0 – 1.5 <lb/>– <lb/>0.89±0.20±0.21 <lb/>– <lb/>– <lb/>1.5 – 4.5 <lb/>10.7±4.8±2.5 <lb/>0.76±0.09±0.08 <lb/>0.76±0.10±0.08 <lb/>0.73±0.34±0.20 <lb/>4.5 – 10.0 17.0±6.1±2.2 <lb/>0.38±0.07±0.06 <lb/>0.38±0.07±0.06 <lb/>0.37±0.15±0.09 <lb/> Table 5: The numerical values on the fraction of J/ψ from beauty hadron decays f  B at mid-rapidity and the nuclear <lb/>modification factors R  AA of inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ for Pb-Pb collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 2.76 TeV. These <lb/>results correspond to the centrality interval 0–50%. The first uncertainty is statistical and the second uncorrelated <lb/>systematic (type II). <lb/> collisions towards lower p  T . Also shown are results at mid-rapidity in pp at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV (ALICE [37], <lb/>ATLAS [35] and CMS [69]) and in p¯ p collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 1.96 TeV (CDF [57]). Considering the ALICE <lb/>and CMS results in Pb-Pb collisions together, a similar p  T dependence as in pp is observed. However, <lb/>this similarity could be coincidental, being due to a compensation of the medium effects on the prompt <lb/>component (J/ψ dissociation and recombination) and on the non-prompt part (b-quark energy loss). <lb/>In Fig. 8 the nuclear modification factor for non-prompt J/ψ for 1.5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 4.5 GeV/c and 4.5 &lt; <lb/> p  T  &lt; 10 GeV/c is shown together with the result by CMS for 6.5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 30 GeV/c [13] and with <lb/>theoretical model predictions [30, 31, 58–60, 79–82]. One should note that the centrality ranges are <lb/>not the same for ALICE (0–50%) and CMS (0–20% and 20–100%). However, the results obtained by <lb/>CMS for these two centrality bins are compatible with each other, and also compatible with our mea-<lb/>surement in the high p  T interval (4.5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 10 GeV/c). The model by Uphoff et al. [60] follows a <lb/>partonic transport approach based on the Boltzmann equation, which allows interactions among all par-<lb/>tons. It does not include radiative processes for heavy quarks. The calculation has been performed for a <lb/>fixed impact parameter b = 5 fm. In the model of Alberico et al. [58, 59] the propagation of the heavy <lb/>quarks in the medium is described by the relativistic Langevin equation. The predicted p  T dependence <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body>  ) <lb/> c <lb/> (GeV/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/> ψ <lb/> non-prompt J/ <lb/> AA <lb/> R <lb/> 0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/> |&lt;0.8) <lb/> y <lb/> 0-50% ALICE (| <lb/> 0-20% <lb/>20-100% <lb/> |&lt;2.4) <lb/> y <lb/> CMS (| <lb/> w/o Coll. Diss. <lb/>with Coll. Diss. <lb/> et al. <lb/> Vitev I. <lb/> HTL <lb/>LatQCD <lb/> et al. <lb/> He M. <lb/> et al. <lb/> Uphoff J. <lb/> et al. <lb/> Djordjevic M. <lb/>WHDG <lb/>AdS/CFT <lb/> et al. <lb/> Alberico W. M. <lb/> = 2.76 TeV <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/> Pb-Pb, <lb/> ψ <lb/> non-prompt J/ <lb/>AA <lb/> R <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/> et al. <lb/> Alberico <lb/> HTL <lb/> Lat. QCD <lb/>w/o Coll. Diss. <lb/>with Coll. Diss. <lb/> c <lb/> ) &lt; 10 GeV/ <lb/> ψ <lb/> (J/ <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 4.5 &lt; <lb/> ALICE <lb/> et al. <lb/> He M. <lb/> et al. <lb/> Uphoff J. <lb/> et al. <lb/> Vitev I. M. <lb/> Fig. 8: The nuclear modification factor R  AA at mid-rapidity (|y| &lt; 0.8) for non-prompt J/ψ in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  NN = 2.76 TeV as a function of transverse momentum p  T . The ALICE measurement corresponds to the 0– <lb/>50% centrality range and to the p  T intervals 1.5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 4.5 GeV/c and 4.5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 10 GeV/c. The uncorrelated <lb/>systematic uncertainties (type II) are depicted by the open boxes, while the correlated uncertainties (type I) are <lb/>shown as filled boxes at unity. Results by CMS for higher p  T in the centrality range 0–20% and 20–100% [13] are <lb/>also shown (the two points have been slightly displaced horizontally for better visibility). The data are compared to <lb/>theoretical predictions at mid-rapidity (see text for details). In the right panel, the ALICE result in the p  T interval <lb/>4.5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 10 GeV/c is compared to theoretical predictions integrated over the same p  T range. <lb/> of R  AA is strongly influenced by the choice of transport coefficients. Two values are considered, either <lb/>as provided by a perturbative calculation (hard thermal loop approach) or extracted from lattice-QCD <lb/>simulations. The calculations have been provided for the centrality range 0–50%. A transport approach, <lb/>which is based on a strong-coupling scheme, is employed in the model of He et al. [79]. The trans-<lb/>port is implemented using non-perturbative interactions for heavy quarks and mesons through the QGP, <lb/>hadronization and hadronic phases of a nuclear collision. In particular, the elastic heavy-quark scattering <lb/>in the QGP is evaluated within a thermodynamic T-matrix approach, by generating resonances close to <lb/>the critical temperature that can in turn recombine into B mesons, followed by hadronic diffusion using <lb/>effective hadronic scattering amplitudes. The hydrodynamic evolution of the system is quantitatively <lb/>constrained by the measured transverse momentum distributions and elliptic flow of light hadrons. Ra-<lb/>diative processes, which should improve the description at high p  T , are not included in this approach. <lb/>The calculations have been performed in the centrality range 0–50%. The model of Vitev et al. [30, 31] <lb/>assumes the existence of open heavy flavour bound-state solutions in the QGP in the vicinity of the crit-<lb/>ical temperature. A description of beauty quark quenching is combined with B meson inelastic breakup <lb/>processes. Furthermore, modified beauty parton distribution functions and beauty fragmentation func-<lb/>tions in a co-moving plasma are implemented in this calculation. The prediction is shown for a fixed <lb/>centrality, corresponding to N  part  = 200, a value very close to the average number of participants in <lb/>the centrality range 0–50%. In the model, a sizable fraction of the suppression is ascribed to the inelas-<lb/>tic break-up processes (collisional dissociation), as can be deduced from Fig. 8 by comparing the full <lb/>model prediction with and without the contribution of this specific process. The model of Djordjevic <lb/>[80], shown in Fig. 8 for the centrality range 0–50%, uses a formalism that takes into account finite size <lb/>dynamical QCD medium with finite magnetic mass effects and running coupling. In the WHDG model <lb/>[81] (centrality range 0–50%) the energy loss is computed using perturbative QCD and considering both <lb/>elastic and inelastic partonic collisions and path length fluctuations. Finally, in the model of Horowitz <lb/>and Gyulassy [82], also applied to the centrality interval 0–50%, the string inspired AdS/CFT gravity-<lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<body> gauge theory correspondence [83, 84] is applied to the case of heavy quark energy loss. In the right hand <lb/>inset of Fig. 8, the ALICE R  AA value, integrated over the range 4.5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 10 GeV/c, is compared to <lb/>theoretical predictions computed in the same p  T range. Most of the models predict a larger value of R  AA <lb/> than observed in the measurement. However, more precise data are needed to discriminate among the <lb/>different models. The next LHC run will provide increased statistics for this measurement. <lb/> 4 Conclusions <lb/> A study of J/ψ production at mid-rapidity in Pb-Pb collisions at <lb/> √ s  NN = 2.76 TeV has been presented. <lb/>A reduction of the inclusive J/ψ p  T  between pp and Pb-Pb collisions is observed. The ratio r  AA  = <lb/> p  2 <lb/>T   AA  /p  2 <lb/>T   pp is found to be significantly below unity, corresponding to a medium-induced change in <lb/>the shape of the p  T spectra. The nuclear modification factor R  AA depends on p  T . It is around 0.8 for <lb/> p  T  &lt; 2.5 GeV/c and reaches, at higher p  T , almost the same level of suppression as observed at RHIC <lb/>energies at low p  T . These observations might be indicative of a sizable contribution of charm quark <lb/>coalescence to the J/ψ production at low p  T . Transport models including this additional component are <lb/>able to qualitatively describe the features seen in the data. <lb/>The fraction of J/ψ from beauty hadron decays is determined as a function of centrality and p  T . No <lb/>significant centrality dependence is observed. By combining this measurement with the inclusive J/ψ <lb/>results the R  AA of non-prompt J/ψ is obtained in the region 1.5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 10 GeV/c, thus extending the <lb/>coverage of CMS to the low p  T region. The nuclear modification in the region 4.5 &lt; p  T  &lt; 10 GeV/c is <lb/>found to be stronger than predicted by most of the models. <lb/></body> 

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgements <lb/> The ALICE Collaboration would like to thank all its engineers and technicians for their invaluable con-<lb/>tributions to the construction of the experiment and the CERN accelerator teams for the outstanding <lb/>performance of the LHC complex. The ALICE Collaboration gratefully acknowledges the resources and <lb/>support provided by all Grid centres and the Worldwide LHC Computing Grid (WLCG) collaboration. <lb/>The ALICE Collaboration acknowledges the following funding agencies for their support in building <lb/>and running the ALICE detector: State Committee of Science, World Federation of Scientists (WFS) <lb/>and Swiss Fonds Kidagan, Armenia, Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico <lb/>(CNPq), Financiadora de Estudos e Projetos (FINEP), Fundaç ão de Amparò <lb/>a Pesquisa do Estado de São <lb/>Paulo (FAPESP); National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC), the Chinese Ministry of Edu-<lb/>cation (CMOE) and the Ministry of Science and Technology of China (MSTC); Ministry of Education <lb/>and Youth of the Czech Republic; Danish Natural Science Research Council, the Carlsberg Foundation <lb/>and the Danish National Research Foundation; The European Research Council under the European <lb/>Community&apos;s Seventh Framework Programme; Helsinki Institute of Physics and the Academy of Fin-<lb/>land; French CNRS-IN2P3, the &apos;Region Pays de Loire&apos;, &apos;Region Alsace&apos;, &apos;Region Auvergne&apos; and CEA, <lb/>France; German Bundesministerium fur Bildung, Wissenschaft, Forschung und Technologie (BMBF) <lb/>and the Helmholtz Association; General Secretariat for Research and Technology, Ministry of Develop-<lb/>ment, Greece; Hungarian Orszagos Tudomanyos Kutatasi Alappgrammok (OTKA) and National Office <lb/>for Research and Technology (NKTH); Department of Atomic Energy and Department of Science and <lb/>Technology of the Government of India; Istituto Nazionale di Fisica Nucleare (INFN) and Centro Fermi <lb/>-Museo Storico della Fisica e Centro Studi e Ricerche &quot; Enrico Fermi &quot; , Italy; MEXT Grant-in-Aid for <lb/>Specially Promoted Research, Japan; Joint Institute for Nuclear Research, Dubna; National Research <lb/>Foundation of Korea (NRF); Consejo Nacional de Cienca y Tecnologia (CONACYT), Direccion Gen-<lb/>eral de Asuntos del Personal Academico(DGAPA), México, :Amerique Latine Formation academique <lb/>European Commission(ALFA-EC) and the EPLANET Program (European Particle Physics Latin Amer-<lb/>ican Network) Stichting voor Fundamenteel Onderzoek der Materie (FOM) and the Nederlandse Or-<lb/></div>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> ganisatie voor Wetenschappelijk Onderzoek (NWO), Netherlands; Research Council of Norway (NFR); <lb/>National Science Centre, Poland; Ministry of National Education/Institute for Atomic Physics and Con-<lb/>siliul Naional al Cercetrii tiinifice -Executive Agency for Higher Education Research Development and <lb/>Innovation Funding (CNCS-UEFISCDI) -Romania; Ministry of Education and Science of Russian Fed-<lb/>eration, Russian Academy of Sciences, Russian Federal Agency of Atomic Energy, Russian Federal <lb/>Agency for Science and Innovations and The Russian Foundation for Basic Research; Ministry of Ed-<lb/>ucation of Slovakia; Department of Science and Technology, South Africa; Centro de Investigaciones <lb/>Energeticas, Medioambientales y Tecnologicas (CIEMAT), E-Infrastructure shared between Europe and <lb/>Latin America (EELA), Ministerio de Economía y Competitividad (MINECO) of Spain, Xunta de Gali-<lb/>cia (Consellería de Educación), Centro de Aplicaciones Tecnolgicas y Desarrollo Nuclear (CEADEN), <lb/>Cubaenergía, Cuba, and IAEA (International Atomic Energy Agency); Swedish Research Council (VR) <lb/>and Knut &amp; Alice Wallenberg Foundation (KAW); Ukraine Ministry of Education and Science; United <lb/>Kingdom Science and Technology Facilities Council (STFC); The United States Department of Energy, <lb/>the United States National Science Foundation, the State of Texas, and the State of Ohio; Ministry of Sci-<lb/>ence, Education and Sports of Croatia and Unity through Knowledge Fund, Croatia. Council of Scientific <lb/>and Industrial Research (CSIR), New Delhi, India <lb/></div>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] F. Karsch, &quot; Lattice simulations of the thermodynamics of strongly interacting elementary particles <lb/>and the exploration of new phases of matter in relativistic heavy ion collisions, &quot; <lb/> J. Phys. Conf. Ser. 46 (2006) 122–131, arXiv:hep-lat/0608003 [hep-lat]. <lb/> [2] Wuppertal-Budapest Collaboration, S. Borsanyi et al.,  &quot; Is there still any T c  mystery in lattice <lb/>QCD? Results with physical masses in the continuum limit III, &quot;  JHEP 1009 (2010) 073, <lb/> arXiv:1005.3508 [hep-lat]. <lb/> [3] S. Borsanyi, G. Endrodi, Z. Fodor, A. Jakovac, S. D. Katz, et al.,  &quot; The QCD equation of state with <lb/>dynamical quarks, &quot;  JHEP 1011 (2010) 077, arXiv:1007.2580 [hep-lat]. <lb/> [4] A. Bazavov, T. Bhattacharya, M. Cheng, C. DeTar, H. Ding, et al.,  &quot; The chiral and deconfinement <lb/>aspects of the QCD transition, &quot;  Phys. Rev. D85 (2012) 054503, arXiv:1111.1710 [hep-lat]. <lb/> [5] T. Matsui and H. Satz, &quot; J/ψ Suppression by Quark-Gluon Plasma Formation, &quot; <lb/> Phys. Lett. B178 (1986) 416. <lb/>[6] NA50 Collaboration, B. Alessandro et al.,  &quot; A New measurement of J/ψ suppression in Pb-Pb <lb/>collisions at 158-GeV per nucleon, &quot;  Eur. Phys. J. C39 (2005) 335–345, <lb/> arXiv:hep-ex/0412036 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [7] NA60 Collaboration, R. Arnaldi, &quot; J/ψ production in p-A and A-A collisions at fixed target <lb/>experiments, &quot;  Nucl. Phys. A830 (2009) 345C–352C, arXiv:0907.5004 [nucl-ex]. <lb/> [8] N. Brambilla, S. Eidelman, B. Heltsley, R. Vogt, G. Bodwin, et al.,  &quot; Heavy quarkonium: progress, <lb/>puzzles, and opportunities, &quot;  Eur. Phys. J. C71 (2011) 1534, arXiv:1010.5827 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [9] PHENIX Collaboration, A. Adare et al.,  &quot; J/ψ Production vs Centrality, Transverse Momentum, <lb/>and Rapidity in Au+Au Collisions at <lb/> √ s NN  = 200 GeV, &quot;  Phys. Rev. Lett. 98 (2007) 232301, <lb/> arXiv:nucl-ex/0611020 [nucl-ex]. <lb/> [10] PHENIX Collaboration, A. Adare et al.,  &quot; J/ψ suppression at forward rapidity in Au+Au <lb/>collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s NN  = 200 GeV, &quot;  Phys. Rev. C84 (2011) 054912, arXiv:1103.6269 [nucl-ex]. <lb/> [11] ALICE Collaboration, B. Abelev et al.,  &quot; J/ψ suppression at forward rapidity in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>at <lb/> √ s NN  = 2.76 TeV, &quot;  Phys. Rev. Lett. 109 (2012) 072301, arXiv:1202.1383 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [12] ALICE Collaboration, B. B. Abelev et al.,  &quot; Centrality, rapidity and transverse momentum <lb/>dependence of J/ψ suppression in Pb-Pb collisions at <lb/> √ s  NN =2.76 TeV, &quot; <lb/> Phys. Lett. B734 (2014) 314–327, arXiv:1311.0214 [nucl-ex]. <lb/> [13] CMS Collaboration, S. Chatrchyan et al.,  &quot; Suppression of non-prompt J/ψ, prompt J/ψ, and <lb/>Y(1S) in PbPb collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s NN  = 2.76 TeV, &quot;  JHEP 1205 (2012) 063, <lb/> arXiv:1201.5069 [nucl-ex]. <lb/> [14] P. Braun-Munzinger and J. Stachel, &quot; (Non)thermal aspects of charmonium production and a new <lb/>look at J/ψ suppression, &quot;  Phys. Lett. B490 (2000) 196–202, <lb/> arXiv:nucl-th/0007059 [nucl-th]. <lb/> [15] R. L. Thews, M. Schroedter, and J. Rafelski, &quot; Enhanced J/ψ production in deconfined quark <lb/>matter, &quot;  Phys. Rev. C63 (2001) 054905, arXiv:hep-ph/0007323 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [16] M. I. Gorenstein, A. Kostyuk, H. Stoecker, and W. Greiner, &quot; Statistical coalescence model with <lb/>exact charm conservation, &quot;  Phys. Lett. B509 (2001) 277–282, <lb/> arXiv:hep-ph/0010148 [hep-ph]. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 19 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> [17] A. Andronic, P. Braun-Munzinger, K. Redlich, and J. Stachel, &quot; Statistical hadronization of charm <lb/>in heavy ion collisions at SPS, RHIC and LHC, &quot;  Phys. Lett. B571 (2003) 36–44, <lb/> arXiv:nucl-th/0303036 [nucl-th]. <lb/> [18] X. Zhao and R. Rapp, &quot; Transverse Momentum Spectra of J/ψ in Heavy-Ion Collisions, &quot; <lb/> Phys. Lett. B664 (2008) 253–257, arXiv:0712.2407 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [19] Y.-p. Liu, Z. Qu, N. Xu, and P.-f. Zhuang, &quot; J/ψ Transverse Momentum Distribution in High <lb/>Energy Nuclear Collisions at RHIC, &quot;  Phys. Lett. B678 (2009) 72–76, <lb/> arXiv:0901.2757 [nucl-th]. <lb/> [20] ALICE Collaboration, E. Abbas et al.,  &quot; J/ψ Elliptic Flow in Pb-Pb Collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  NN = 2.76 <lb/>TeV, &quot;  Phys. Rev. Lett. 111 (2013) 162301, arXiv:1303.5880 [nucl-ex]. <lb/> [21] M. Gyulassy and M. Plumer, &quot; Jet Quenching in Dense Matter, &quot;  Phys. Lett. B243 (1990) 432–438. <lb/>[22] R. Baier, Y. L. Dokshitzer, A. H. Mueller, S. Peigne, and D. Schiff, &quot; Radiative energy loss and p  ⊥ <lb/> broadening of high-energy partons in nuclei, &quot;  Nucl. Phys. B484 (1997) 265–282, <lb/> arXiv:hep-ph/9608322 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [23] M. H. Thoma and M. Gyulassy, &quot; Quark Damping and Energy Loss in the High Temperature <lb/>QCD, &quot;  Nucl. Phys. B351 (1991) 491–506. <lb/>[24] E. Braaten and M. H. Thoma, &quot; Energy loss of a heavy fermion in a hot plasma, &quot; <lb/> Phys. Rev. D44 (1991) 1298–1310. <lb/>[25] E. Braaten and M. H. Thoma, &quot; Energy loss of a heavy quark in the quark -gluon plasma, &quot; <lb/> Phys. Rev. D44 (1991) 2625–2630. <lb/>[26] Y. L. Dokshitzer and D. Kharzeev, &quot; Heavy quark colorimetry of QCD matter, &quot; <lb/> Phys. Lett. B519 (2001) 199–206, arXiv:hep-ph/0106202 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [27] N. Armesto, C. A. Salgado, and U. A. Wiedemann, &quot; Medium induced gluon radiation off massive <lb/>quarks fills the dead cone, &quot;  Phys. Rev. D69 (2004) 114003, arXiv:hep-ph/0312106 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [28] S. Wicks, W. Horowitz, M. Djordjevic, and M. Gyulassy, &quot; Heavy quark jet quenching with <lb/>collisional plus radiative energy loss and path length fluctuations, &quot; <lb/> Nucl. Phys. A783 (2007) 493–496, arXiv:nucl-th/0701063 [nucl-th]. <lb/> [29] B.-W. Zhang, E. Wang, and X.-N. Wang, &quot; Heavy quark energy loss in nuclear medium, &quot; <lb/> Phys. Rev. Lett. 93 (2004) 072301, arXiv:nucl-th/0309040 [nucl-th]. <lb/> [30] R. Sharma, I. Vitev, and B.-W. Zhang, &quot; Light-cone wave function approach to open heavy flavor <lb/>dynamics in QCD matter, &quot;  Phys. Rev. C80 (2009) 054902, arXiv:0904.0032 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [31] R. Sharma and I. Vitev, &quot; High transverse momentum quarkonium production and dissociation in <lb/>heavy ion collisions, &quot;  Phys. Rev. C87 no. 4, (2013) 044905, arXiv:1203.0329 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [32] A. Adil and I. Vitev, &quot; Collisional dissociation of heavy mesons in dense QCD matter, &quot; <lb/> Phys. Lett. B649 (2007) 139–146, arXiv:hep-ph/0611109 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [33] P. Faccioli, C. Lourenco, J. Seixas, and H. Woehri, &quot; Study of  ψ  ′  and  χ  c  decays as feed-down <lb/>sources of J/ψ hadro-production, &quot;  JHEP 0810 (2008) 004, arXiv:0809.2153 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [34] A. Mocsy and P. Petreczky, &quot; Color screening melts quarkonium, &quot; <lb/> Phys. Rev. Lett. 99 (2007) 211602, arXiv:0706.2183 [hep-ph]. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> [35] ATLAS Collaboration, G. Aad et al.,  &quot; Measurement of the differential cross-sections of inclusive, <lb/>prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in proton-proton collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV, &quot; <lb/> Nucl. Phys. B850 (2011) 387–444, arXiv:1104.3038 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [36] CMS Collaboration, S. Chatrchyan et al.,  &quot; J/ψ and  ψ(2S)  production in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 <lb/>TeV, &quot;  JHEP 1202 (2012) 011, arXiv:1111.1557 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [37] ALICE Collaboration, B. Abelev et al.,  &quot; Measurement of prompt J/ψ and beauty hadron <lb/>production cross sections at mid-rapidity in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV, &quot;  JHEP 1211 (2012) 065, <lb/> arXiv:1205.5880 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [38] ALICE Collaboration, K. Aamodt et al.,  &quot; The ALICE experiment at the CERN LHC, &quot; <lb/> JINST 3 (2008) S08002. <lb/>[39] ALICE Collaboration, K. Aamodt et al.,  &quot; Alignment of the ALICE Inner Tracking System with <lb/>cosmic-ray tracks, &quot;  JINST 5 (2010) P03003, arXiv:1001.0502 [physics.ins-det]. <lb/> [40] J. Alme, Y. Andres, H. Appelshauser, S. Bablok, N. Bialas, et al.,  &quot; The ALICE TPC, a large <lb/>3-dimensional tracking device with fast readout for ultra-high multiplicity events, &quot; <lb/> Nucl. Instrum. Meth. A622 (2010) 316–367, arXiv:1001.1950 [physics.ins-det]. <lb/> [41] ALICE Collaboration, E. Abbas et al.,  &quot; Performance of the ALICE VZERO system, &quot; <lb/> JINST 8 (2013) P10016, arXiv:1306.3130 [nucl-ex]. <lb/> [42] ALICE Collaboration, B. Abelev et al.,  &quot; Measurement of the Cross Section for Electromagnetic <lb/>Dissociation with Neutron Emission in Pb-Pb Collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s NN  = 2.76 TeV, &quot; <lb/> Phys. Rev. Lett. 109 (2012) 252302, arXiv:1203.2436 [nucl-ex]. <lb/> [43] ALICE Collaboration, B. Abelev et al.,  &quot; Centrality determination of Pb-Pb collisions at <lb/> √ s NN  = <lb/>2.76 TeV with ALICE, &quot;  Phys. Rev. C88 no. 4, (2013) 044909, arXiv:1301.4361 [nucl-ex]. <lb/> [44] ALICE Collaboration, K. Aamodt et al.,  &quot; Rapidity and transverse momentum dependence of <lb/>inclusive J/ψ production in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV, &quot;  Phys. Lett. B704 (2011) 442–455, <lb/> arXiv:1105.0380 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [45] ALICE Collaboration, B. B. Abelev et al.,  &quot; Performance of the ALICE Experiment at the CERN <lb/>LHC, &quot;  Int. J. Mod. Phys. A29 (2014) 1430044, arXiv:1402.4476 [nucl-ex]. <lb/> [46] ALICE Collaboration, B. Abelev et al.,  &quot; J/ψ polarization in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV, &quot; <lb/> Phys. Rev. Lett. 108 (2012) 082001, arXiv:1111.1630 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [47] CMS Collaboration, S. Chatrchyan et al.,  &quot; Measurement of the prompt J/ψ and  ψ(2S) <lb/> polarizations in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV, &quot;  Phys. Lett. B727 (2013) 381–402, <lb/> arXiv:1307.6070 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [48] LHCb Collaboration, R. Aaij et al.,  &quot; Measurement of J/ψ polarization in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 <lb/>TeV, &quot;  Eur. Phys. J. C73 no. 11, (2013) 2631, arXiv:1307.6379 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [49] X.-N. Wang and M. Gyulassy, &quot; HIJING: A Monte Carlo model for multiple jet production in p p, <lb/>p A and A A collisions, &quot;  Phys. Rev. D44 (1991) 3501–3516. <lb/>[50] F. Bossu, Z. C. del Valle, A. de Falco, M. Gagliardi, S. Grigoryan, et al.,  &quot; Phenomenological <lb/>interpolation of the inclusive J/ψ cross section to proton-proton collisions at 2.76 TeV and 5.5 <lb/>TeV, &quot;  arXiv:1103.2394 [nucl-ex]. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 21 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> [51] K. Eskola, V. Kolhinen, and C. Salgado, &quot; The Scale dependent nuclear effects in parton <lb/>distributions for practical applications, &quot;  Eur. Phys. J. C9 (1999) 61–68, <lb/> arXiv:hep-ph/9807297 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [52] D. Lange, &quot; The EvtGen particle decay simulation package, &quot; <lb/> Nucl. Instrum. Meth. A462 (2001) 152–155. <lb/>[53] E. Barberio and Z. Was, &quot; PHOTOS: A Universal Monte Carlo for QED radiative corrections. <lb/>Version 2.0, &quot;  Comput. Phys. Commun. 79 (1994) 291–308. <lb/>[54] R. Brun, F. Carminati, and S. Giani, &quot; GEANT Detector Description and Simulation Tool, &quot; . <lb/>[55] ALICE Collaboration, B. Abelev et al.,  &quot; Inclusive J/ψ production in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 2.76 <lb/>TeV, &quot;  Phys. Lett. B718 (2012) 295–306, arXiv:1203.3641 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [56] PHENIX Collaboration, A. Adare et al.,  &quot; J/ψ production versus transverse momentum and <lb/>rapidity in p  +  p collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 200-GeV, &quot;  Phys. Rev. Lett. 98 (2007) 232002, <lb/> arXiv:hep-ex/0611020 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [57] CDF Collaboration, D. Acosta et al.,  &quot; Measurement of the J/ψ meson and b−hadron production <lb/>cross sections in p ¯ <lb/> p collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 1960 GeV, &quot;  Phys. Rev. D71 (2005) 032001, <lb/> arXiv:hep-ex/0412071 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [58] W. Alberico, A. Beraudo, A. De Pace, A. Molinari, M. Monteno, et al.,  &quot; Heavy-flavour spectra in <lb/>high energy nucleus-nucleus collisions, &quot;  Eur. Phys. J. C71 (2011) 1666, <lb/> arXiv:1101.6008 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [59] W. Alberico, A. Beraudo, A. De Pace, A. Molinari, M. Monteno, et al.,  &quot; Heavy flavors in AA <lb/> collisions: production, transport and final spectra, &quot;  Eur. Phys. J. C73 (2013) 2481, <lb/> arXiv:1305.7421 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [60] J. Uphoff, O. Fochler, Z. Xu, and C. Greiner, &quot; Open Heavy Flavor in Pb+Pb Collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 2.76 TeV within a Transport Model, &quot;  Phys. Lett. B717 (2012) 430–435, <lb/> arXiv:1205.4945 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [61] BaBar Collaboration, B. Aubert et al.,  &quot; Study of inclusive production of charmonium mesons in B <lb/> decay, &quot;  Phys. Rev. D67 (2003) 032002, arXiv:hep-ex/0207097 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [62] LHCb Collaboration, R. Aaij et al.,  &quot; Measurement of J/ψ production in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV, &quot;  Eur. Phys. J. C71 (2011) 1645, arXiv:1103.0423 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [63] CDF Collaboration, A. Abulencia et al.,  &quot; Polarization of J/ψ and  ψ(2S)  mesons produced in p ¯ <lb/> p <lb/> collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 1.96-TeV, &quot;  Phys. Rev. Lett. 99 (2007) 132001, arXiv:0704.0638 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [64] ALICE Collaboration, B. Abelev et al.,  &quot; Suppression of high transverse momentum D mesons in <lb/>central Pb-Pb collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s NN  = 2.76 TeV, &quot;  JHEP 1209 (2012) 112, <lb/> arXiv:1203.2160 [nucl-ex]. <lb/> [65] ALICE Collaboration, B. Abelev et al.,  &quot; Technical Design Report for the Upgrade of the ALICE <lb/>Inner Tracking System, &quot;  J. Phys. G41 (2014) 087002. <lb/>[66] T. Sjostrand, S. Mrenna, and P. Z. Skands, &quot; PYTHIA 6.4 Physics and Manual, &quot; <lb/> JHEP 0605 (2006) 026, arXiv:hep-ph/0603175 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [67] P. Z. Skands, &quot; Tuning Monte Carlo Generators: The Perugia Tunes, &quot; <lb/> Phys. Rev. D82 (2010) 074018, arXiv:1005.3457 [hep-ph]. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 22 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> [68] ALICE Collaboration, K. Koch, &quot; π 0 and  η  measurement with photon conversions in ALICE in <lb/>proton-proton collisions at sqrt(s) = 7 TeV, &quot;  Nucl. Phys. A855 (2011) 281–284, <lb/> arXiv:1103.2217 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [69] CMS Collaboration, V. Khachatryan et al.,  &quot; Prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in pp <lb/> collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV, &quot;  Eur. Phys. J. C71 (2011) 1575, arXiv:1011.4193 [hep-ex]. <lb/> [70] M. Cacciari, S. Frixione, N. Houdeau, M. L. Mangano, P. Nason, et al.,  &quot; Theoretical predictions <lb/>for charm and bottom production at the LHC, &quot;  JHEP 1210 (2012) 137, <lb/> arXiv:1205.6344 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [71] PHENIX Collaboration, A. Adare et al.,  &quot; J/ψ Production in <lb/> √ <lb/> s N N = 200 GeV Cu+Cu <lb/>Collisions, &quot;  Phys. Rev. Lett. 101 (2008) 122301, arXiv:0801.0220 [nucl-ex]. <lb/> [72] NA50 Collaboration, M. Abreu et al.,  &quot; Transverse momentum distributions of J/ψ,  ψ  ′  , Drell-Yan <lb/>and continuum dimuons produced in Pb Pb interactions at the SPS, &quot; <lb/> Phys. Lett. B499 (2001) 85–96. <lb/>[73] K. Zhou, N. Xu, Z. Xu, and P. Zhuang, &quot; Medium effects on charmonium production at <lb/>ultrarelativistic energies available at the CERN Large Hadron Collider, &quot; <lb/> Phys. Rev. C89 no. 5, (2014) 054911, arXiv:1401.5845 [nucl-th]. <lb/> [74] X. Zhao and R. Rapp, &quot; Charmonium in Medium: From Correlators to Experiment, &quot; <lb/> Phys. Rev. C82 (2010) 064905, arXiv:1008.5328 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [75] X. Zhao and R. Rapp, &quot; Medium Modifications and Production of Charmonia at LHC, &quot; <lb/> Nucl. Phys. A859 (2011) 114–125, arXiv:1102.2194 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [76] K. Zhou, N. Xu, and P. Zhuang, &quot; Quarkonium Production and Medium Effects in High Energy <lb/>Nuclear Collisions, &quot;  arXiv:1309.7520 [nucl-th]. <lb/> [77] K. Tuchin, &quot; Forward hadron production in high energy pA collisions: From RHIC to LHC, &quot; <lb/> Nucl. Phys. A798 (2008) 61–73, arXiv:0705.2193 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [78] ALICE Collaboration, J. Adams et al.,  &quot; Differential studies of J/ψ and  ψ(2S)  production in <lb/>Pb-Pb collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s NN  = 2.76 TeV. &quot; . <lb/>[79] M. He, R. J. Fries, and R. Rapp, &quot; Heavy Flavor at the Large Hadron Collider in a Strong Coupling <lb/>Approach, &quot;  Phys. Lett. B735 (2014) 445–450, arXiv:1401.3817 [nucl-th]. <lb/> [80] M. Djordjevic and M. Djordjevic, &quot; LHC jet suppression of light and heavy flavor observables, &quot; <lb/> Phys. Lett. B734 (2014) 286–289, arXiv:1307.4098 [hep-ph]. <lb/> [81] S. Wicks, W. Horowitz, M. Djordjevic, and M. Gyulassy, &quot; Elastic, inelastic, and path length <lb/>fluctuations in jet tomography, &quot;  Nucl. Phys. A784 (2007) 426–442, <lb/> arXiv:nucl-th/0512076 [nucl-th]. <lb/> [82] W. Horowitz and M. Gyulassy, &quot; Heavy quark jet tomography of Pb + Pb at LHC: AdS/CFT drag <lb/>or pQCD energy loss?, &quot;  Phys. Lett. B666 (2008) 320–323, arXiv:0706.2336 [nucl-th]. <lb/> [83] J. M. Maldacena, &quot; The Large N limit of superconformal field theories and supergravity, &quot; <lb/> Int. J. Theor. Phys. 38 (1999) 1113–1133, arXiv:hep-th/9711200 [hep-th]. <lb/> [84] S. Gubser, I. R. Klebanov, and A. M. Polyakov, &quot; Gauge theory correlators from noncritical string <lb/>theory, &quot;  Phys. Lett. B428 (1998) 105–114, arXiv:hep-th/9802109 [hep-th]. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 23 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<front> A The ALICE Collaboration <lb/> J. Adam 40 , D. Adamová 83 , M.M. Aggarwal 87 , G. Aglieri Rinella 36 , M. Agnello 111 , N. Agrawal 48 , <lb/>Z. Ahammed 132 , S.U. Ahn 68 , I. Aimo 94 ,111 , S. Aiola 137 , M. Ajaz 16 , A. Akindinov 58 , S.N. Alam 132 , <lb/>D. Aleksandrov 100 , B. Alessandro 111 , D. Alexandre 102 , R. Alfaro Molina 64 , A. Alici 105 ,12 , A. Alkin 3 , <lb/>J. Alme <lb/> 38 , T. Alt <lb/> 43 , S. Altinpinar <lb/> 18 , I. Altsybeev <lb/> 131 , C. Alves Garcia Prado <lb/> 120 , C. Andrei <lb/> 78 , A. Andronic <lb/> 97 , <lb/>V. Anguelov 93 , J. Anielski 54 , T. Antiči´  98 , F. Antinori 108 , P. Antonioli 105 , L. Aphecetche 113 , <lb/>H. Appelshäuser 53 , S. Arcelli 28 , N. Armesto 17 , R. Arnaldi 111 , I.C. Arsene 22 , M. Arslandok 53 , B. Audurier 113 , <lb/>A. Augustinus 36 , R. Averbeck 97 , M.D. Azmi 19 , M. Bach 43 , A. Badì a 107 , Y.W. Baek 44 , S. Bagnasco 111 , <lb/>R. Bailhache 53 , R. Bala 90 , A. Baldisseri 15 , F. Baltasar Dos Santos Pedrosa 36 , R.C. Baral 61 , A.M. Barbano 111 , <lb/>R. Barbera 29 , F. Barile 33 , G.G. Barnaföldi 136 , L.S. Barnby 102 , V. Barret 70 , P. Bartalini 7 , K. Barth 36 , <lb/>J. Bartke 117 , E. Bartsch 53 , M. Basile 28 , N. Bastid 70 , S. Basu 132 , B. Bathen 54 , G. Batigne 113 , A. Batista <lb/>Camejo 70 , B. Batyunya 66 , P.C. Batzing 22 , I.G. Bearden 80 , H. Beck 53 , C. Bedda 111 , N.K. Behera 49 ,48 , <lb/>I. Belikov <lb/> 55 , F. Bellini <lb/> 28 , H. Bello Martinez <lb/> 2 , R. Bellwied <lb/> 122 , R. Belmont <lb/> 135 , E. Belmont-Moreno <lb/> 64 , <lb/>V. Belyaev 76 , G. Bencedi 136 , S. Beole 27 , I. Berceanu 78 , A. Bercuci 78 , Y. Berdnikov 85 , D. Berenyi 136 , <lb/>R.A. Bertens 57 , D. Berzano 36 ,27 , L. Betev 36 , A. Bhasin 90 , I.R. Bhat 90 , A.K. Bhati 87 , B. Bhattacharjee 45 , <lb/>J. Bhom 128 , L. Bianchi 122 , N. Bianchi 72 , C. Bianchin 135 ,57 , J. Bielčík 40 , J. Bielčíková 83 , A. Bilandzic 80 , <lb/>R. Biswas 4 , S. Biswas 79 , S. Bjelogrlic 57 , F. Blanco 10 , D. Blau 100 , C. Blume 53 , F. Bock 74 ,93 , A. Bogdanov 76 , <lb/>H. Bøggild 80 , L. Boldizsár 136 , M. Bombara 41 , J. Book 53 , H. Borel 15 , A. Borissov 96 , M. Borri 82 , F. Bossú 65 , <lb/>M. Botje 81 , E. Botta 27 , S. Böttger 52 , P. Braun-Munzinger 97 , M. Bregant 120 , T. Breitner 52 , T.A. Broker 53 , <lb/>T.A. Browning 95 , M. Broz 40 , E.J. Brucken 46 , E. Bruna 111 , G.E. Bruno 33 , D. Budnikov 99 , H. Buesching 53 , <lb/>S. Bufalino <lb/> 111 ,36 , P. Buncic <lb/> 36 , O. Busch <lb/> 93 ,128 , Z. Buthelezi <lb/> 65 , J.T. Buxton <lb/> 20 , D. Caffarri <lb/> 36 , X. Cai <lb/> 7 , <lb/>H. Caines 137 , L. Calero Diaz 72 , A. Caliva 57 , E. Calvo Villar 103 , P. Camerini 26 , F. Carena 36 , W. Carena 36 , <lb/>J. Castillo Castellanos 15 , A.J. Castro 125 , E.A.R. Casula 25 , C. Cavicchioli 36 , C. Ceballos Sanchez 9 , J. Cepila 40 , <lb/>P. Cerello 111 , J. Cerkala 115 , B. Chang 123 , S. Chapeland 36 , M. Chartier 124 , J.L. Charvet 15 , S. Chattopadhyay 132 , <lb/>S. Chattopadhyay 101 , V. Chelnokov 3 , M. Cherney 86 , C. Cheshkov 130 , B. Cheynis 130 , V. Chibante Barroso 36 , <lb/>D.D. Chinellato 121 , P. Chochula 36 , K. Choi 96 , M. Chojnacki 80 , S. Choudhury 132 , P. Christakoglou 81 , <lb/>C.H. Christensen 80 , P. Christiansen 34 , T. Chujo 128 , S.U. Chung 96 , Z. Chunhui 57 , C. Cicalo 106 , L. Cifarelli 12 ,28 , <lb/>F. Cindolo 105 , J. Cleymans 89 , F. Colamaria 33 , D. Colella 33 , A. Collu 25 , M. Colocci 28 , G. Conesa Balbastre 71 , <lb/>Z. Conesa del Valle <lb/> 51 , M.E. Connors <lb/> 137 , J.G. Contreras <lb/> 11 ,40 , T.M. Cormier <lb/> 84 , Y. Corrales Morales <lb/> 27 , I. Cortés <lb/>Maldonado 2 , P. Cortese 32 , M.R. Cosentino 120 , F. Costa 36 , P. Crochet 70 , R. Cruz Albino 11 , E. Cuautle 63 , <lb/>L. Cunqueiro 36 , T. Dahms 92 ,37 , A. Dainese 108 , A. Danu 62 , D. Das 101 , I. Das 51 ,101 , S. Das 4 , A. Dash 121 , <lb/>S. Dash 48 , S. De 120 , A. De Caro 31 ,12 , G. de Cataldo 104 , J. de Cuveland 43 , A. De Falco 25 , D. De Gruttola 12 ,31 , <lb/>N. De Marco 111 , S. De Pasquale 31 , A. Deisting 97 ,93 , A. Deloff 77 , E. Dénes 136 , G. D&apos;Erasmo 33 , D. Di Bari 33 , <lb/>A. Di Mauro 36 , P. Di Nezza 72 , M.A. Diaz Corchero 10 , T. Dietel 89 , P. Dillenseger 53 , R. Diì a 36 , <lb/>Ø. Djuvsland 18 , A. Dobrin 57 ,81 , T. Dobrowolski 77 ,i , D. Domenicis Gimenez 120 , B. Dönigus 53 , O. Dordic 22 , <lb/>A.K. Dubey 132 , A. Dubla 57 , L. Ducroux 130 , P. Dupieux 70 , R.J. Ehlers 137 , D. Elia 104 , H. Engel 52 , <lb/>B. Erazmus <lb/> 36 ,113 , I. Erdemir <lb/> 53 , F. Erhardt <lb/> 129 , D. Eschweiler <lb/> 43 , B. Espagnon <lb/> 51 , M. Estienne <lb/> 113 , S. Esumi <lb/> 128 , <lb/>J. Eum 96 , D. Evans 102 , S. Evdokimov 112 , G. Eyyubova 40 , L. Fabbietti 37 ,92 , D. Fabris 108 , J. Faivre 71 , <lb/>A. Fantoni 72 , M. Fasel 74 , L. Feldkamp 54 , D. Felea 62 , A. Feliciello 111 , G. Feofilov 131 , J. Ferencei 83 , <lb/>A. Fernández Téllez 2 , E.G. Ferreiro 17 , A. Ferretti 27 , A. Festanti 30 , V.J.G. Feuillard 15 , J. Figiel 117 , <lb/>M.A.S. Figueredo 124 , S. Filchagin 99 , D. Finogeev 56 , F.M. Fionda 104 , E.M. Fiore 33 , M.G. Fleck 93 , M. Floris 36 , <lb/>S. Foertsch 65 , P. Foka 97 , S. Fokin 100 , E. Fragiacomo 110 , A. Francescon 36 ,30 , U. Frankenfeld 97 , U. Fuchs 36 , <lb/>C. Furget 71 , A. Furs 56 , M. Fusco Girard 31 , J.J. Gaardhøje 80 , M. Gagliardi 27 , A.M. Gago 103 , M. Gallio 27 , <lb/>D.R. Gangadharan 74 , P. Ganoti 88 , C. Gao 7 , C. Garabatos 97 , E. Garcia-Solis 13 , C. Gargiulo 36 , P. Gasik 92 ,37 , <lb/>M. Germain <lb/> 113 , A. Gheata <lb/> 36 , M. Gheata <lb/> 62 ,36 , P. Ghosh <lb/> 132 , S.K. Ghosh <lb/> 4 , P. Gianotti <lb/> 72 , P. Giubellino <lb/> 36 , <lb/>P. Giubilato 30 , E. Gladysz-Dziadus 117 , P. Glässel 93 , A. Gomez Ramirez 52 , P. González-Zamora 10 , <lb/>S. Gorbunov 43 , L. Görlich 117 , S. Gotovac 116 , V. Grabski 64 , L.K. Graczykowski 134 , K.L. Graham 102 , <lb/>A. Grelli 57 , A. Grigoras 36 , C. Grigoras 36 , V. Grigoriev 76 , A. Grigoryan 1 , S. Grigoryan 66 , B. Grinyov 3 , <lb/>N. Grion 110 , J.F. Grosse-Oetringhaus 36 , J.-Y. Grossiord 130 , R. Grosso 36 , F. Guber 56 , R. Guernane 71 , <lb/>B. Guerzoni 28 , K. Gulbrandsen 80 , H. Gulkanyan 1 , T. Gunji 127 , A. Gupta 90 , R. Gupta 90 , R. Haake 54 , <lb/>Ø. Haaland 18 , C. Hadjidakis 51 , M. Haiduc 62 , H. Hamagaki 127 , G. Hamar 136 , A. Hansen 80 , J.W. Harris 137 , <lb/>H. Hartmann 43 , A. Harton 13 , D. Hatzifotiadou 105 , S. Hayashi 127 , S.T. Heckel 53 , M. Heide 54 , H. Helstrup 38 , <lb/>A. Herghelegiu <lb/> 78 , G. Herrera Corral <lb/> 11 , B.A. Hess <lb/> 35 , K.F. Hetland <lb/> 38 , T.E. Hilden <lb/> 46 , H. Hillemanns <lb/> 36 , <lb/>B. Hippolyte 55 , P. Hristov 36 , M. Huang 18 , T.J. Humanic 20 , N. Hussain 45 , T. Hussain 19 , D. Hutter 43 , <lb/>D.S. Hwang 21 , R. Ilkaev 99 , I. Ilkiv 77 , M. Inaba 128 , C. Ionita 36 , M. Ippolitov 76 ,100 , M. Irfan 19 , M. Ivanov 97 , <lb/>V. Ivanov <lb/> 85 , V. Izucheev <lb/> 112 , P.M. Jacobs <lb/> 74 , S. Jadlovska <lb/> 115 , C. Jahnke <lb/> 120 , H.J. Jang <lb/> 68 , M.A. Janik <lb/> 134 , <lb/></front>

			<page> 24 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<front> P.H.S.Y. Jayarathna 122 , C. Jena 30 , S. Jena 122 , R.T. Jimenez Bustamante 97 , P.G. Jones 102 , H. Jung 44 , <lb/>A. Jusko 102 , P. Kalinak 59 , A. Kalweit 36 , J. Kamin 53 , J.H. Kang 138 , V. Kaplin 76 , S. Kar 132 , A. Karasu Uysal 69 , <lb/>O. Karavichev <lb/> 56 , T. Karavicheva <lb/> 56 , E. Karpechev <lb/> 56 , U. Kebschull <lb/> 52 , R. Keidel <lb/> 139 , D.L.D. Keijdener <lb/> 57 , <lb/>M. Keil 36 , K.H. Khan 16 , M.M. Khan 19 , P. Khan 101 , S.A. Khan 132 , A. Khanzadeev 85 , Y. Kharlov 112 , <lb/>B. Kileng 38 , B. Kim 138 , D.W. Kim 68 ,44 , D.J. Kim 123 , H. Kim 138 , J.S. Kim 44 , M. Kim 44 , M. Kim 138 , <lb/>S. Kim 21 , T. Kim 138 , S. Kirsch 43 , I. Kisel 43 , S. Kiselev 58 , A. Kisiel 134 , G. Kiss 136 , J.L. Klay 6 , C. Klein 53 , <lb/>J. Klein 93 , C. Klein-Bösing 54 , A. Kluge 36 , M.L. Knichel 93 , A.G. Knospe 118 , T. Kobayashi 128 , C. Kobdaj 114 , <lb/>M. Kofarago 36 , T. Kollegger 97 ,43 , A. Kolojvari 131 , V. Kondratiev 131 , N. Kondratyeva 76 , E. Kondratyuk 112 , <lb/>A. Konevskikh 56 , M. Kopcik 115 , C. Kouzinopoulos 36 , O. Kovalenko 77 , V. Kovalenko 131 , M. Kowalski 117 , <lb/>S. Kox 71 , G. Koyithatta Meethaleveedu 48 , J. Kral 123 , I. Králik 59 , A. Kravčáková 41 , M. Krelina 40 , M. Kretz 43 , <lb/>M. Krivda <lb/> 102 ,59 , F. Krizek <lb/> 83 , E. Kryshen <lb/> 36 , M. Krzewicki <lb/> 43 , A.M. Kubera <lb/> 20 , V. Kučera <lb/> 83 , T. Kugathasan <lb/> 36 , <lb/>C. Kuhn 55 , P.G. Kuijer 81 , I. Kulakov 43 , J. Kumar 48 , L. Kumar 79 ,87 , P. Kurashvili 77 , A. Kurepin 56 , <lb/>A.B. Kurepin 56 , A. Kuryakin 99 , S. Kushpil 83 , M.J. Kweon 50 , Y. Kwon 138 , S.L. La Pointe 111 , P. La Rocca 29 , <lb/>C. Lagana Fernandes 120 , I. Lakomov 36 , R. Langoy 42 , C. Lara 52 , A. Lardeux 15 , A. Lattuca 27 , E. Laudi 36 , <lb/>R. Lea 26 , L. Leardini 93 , G.R. Lee 102 , S. Lee 138 , I. Legrand 36 , R.C. Lemmon 82 , V. Lenti 104 , E. Leogrande 57 , <lb/>I. León Monzón 119 , M. Leoncino 27 , P. Lévai 136 , S. Li 7 ,70 , X. Li 14 , J. Lien 42 , R. Lietava 102 , S. Lindal 22 , <lb/>V. Lindenstruth 43 , C. Lippmann 97 , M.A. Lisa 20 , H.M. Ljunggren 34 , D.F. Lodato 57 , P.I. Loenne 18 , <lb/>V.R. Loggins 135 , V. Loginov 76 , C. Loizides 74 , X. Lopez 70 , E. López Torres 9 , A. Lowe 136 , P. Luettig 53 , <lb/>M. Lunardon <lb/> 30 , G. Luparello <lb/> 26 , P.H.F.N.D. Luz <lb/> 120 , A. Maevskaya <lb/> 56 , M. Mager <lb/> 36 , S. Mahajan <lb/> 90 , <lb/>S.M. Mahmood 22 , A. Maire 55 , R.D. Majka 137 , M. Malaev 85 , I. Maldonado Cervantes 63 , L. Malinina 66 , <lb/>D. Mal&apos;Kevich 58 , P. Malzacher 97 , A. Mamonov 99 , L. Manceau 111 , V. Manko 100 , F. Manso 70 , <lb/>V. Manzari 104 ,36 , M. Marchisone 27 , J. Mareš 60 , G.V. Margagliotti 26 , A. Margotti 105 , J. Margutti 57 , <lb/>A. Marín 97 , C. Markert 118 , M. Marquard 53 , N.A. Martin 97 , J. Martin Blanco 113 , P. Martinengo 36 , <lb/>M.I. Martínez 2 , G. Martínez García 113 , M. Martinez Pedreira 36 , Y. Martynov 3 , A. Mas 120 , S. Masciocchi 97 , <lb/>M. Masera 27 , A. Masoni 106 , L. Massacrier 113 , A. Mastroserio 33 , H. Masui 128 , A. Matyja 117 , C. Mayer 117 , <lb/>J. Mazer 125 , M.A. Mazzoni 109 , D. Mcdonald 122 , F. Meddi 24 , A. Menchaca-Rocha 64 , E. Meninno 31 , J. Mercado <lb/>Pérez <lb/> 93 , M. Meres <lb/> 39 , Y. Miake <lb/> 128 , M.M. Mieskolainen <lb/> 46 , K. Mikhaylov <lb/> 58 ,66 , L. Milano <lb/> 36 , J. Milosevic <lb/> 22 ,133 , <lb/>L.M. Minervini 23 ,104 , A. Mischke 57 , A.N. Mishra 49 , D. Mi´ kowiec 97 , J. Mitra 132 , C.M. Mitu 62 , <lb/>N. Mohammadi 57 , B. Mohanty 79 ,132 , L. Molnar 55 , L. Montaño Zetina 11 , E. Montes 10 , M. Morando 30 , <lb/>D.A. Moreira De Godoy 54 ,113 , S. Moretto 30 , A. Morreale 113 , A. Morsch 36 , V. Muccifora 72 , E. Mudnic 116 , <lb/>D. Mühlheim 54 , S. Muhuri 132 , M. Mukherjee 132 , J.D. Mulligan 137 , M.G. Munhoz 120 , S. Murray 65 , L. Musa 36 , <lb/>J. Musinsky 59 , B.K. Nandi 48 , R. Nania 105 , E. Nappi 104 , M.U. Naru 16 , C. Nattrass 125 , K. Nayak 79 , <lb/>T.K. Nayak 132 , S. Nazarenko 99 , A. Nedosekin 58 , L. Nellen 63 , F. Ng 122 , M. Nicassio 97 , M. Niculescu 62 ,36 , <lb/>J. Niedziela 36 , B.S. Nielsen 80 , S. Nikolaev 100 , S. Nikulin 100 , V. Nikulin 85 , F. Noferini 12 ,105 , P. Nomokonov 66 , <lb/>G. Nooren <lb/> 57 , J. Norman <lb/> 124 , A. Nyanin <lb/> 100 , J. Nystrand <lb/> 18 , H. Oeschler <lb/> 93 , S. Oh <lb/> 137 , S.K. Oh <lb/> 67 , A. Ohlson <lb/> 36 , <lb/>A. Okatan 69 , T. Okubo 47 , L. Olah 136 , J. Oleniacz 134 , A.C. Oliveira Da Silva 120 , M.H. Oliver 137 , <lb/>J. Onderwaater 97 , C. Oppedisano 111 , A. Ortiz Velasquez 63 , A. Oskarsson 34 , J. Otwinowski 117 , K. Oyama 93 , <lb/>M. Ozdemir <lb/> 53 , Y. Pachmayer <lb/> 93 , P. Pagano <lb/> 31 , G. Pai´ <lb/> 63 , C. Pajares <lb/> 17 , S.K. Pal <lb/> 132 , J. Pan <lb/> 135 , A.K. Pandey <lb/> 48 , <lb/>D. Pant 48 , P. Papcun 115 , V. Papikyan 1 , G.S. Pappalardo 107 , P. Pareek 49 , W.J. Park 97 , S. Parmar 87 , <lb/>A. Passfeld 54 , V. Paticchio 104 , R.N. Patra 132 , B. Paul 101 , T. Peitzmann 57 , H. Pereira Da Costa 15 , E. Pereira De <lb/>Oliveira Filho 120 , D. Peresunko 76 ,100 , C.E. Pérez Lara 81 , V. Peskov 53 , Y. Pestov 5 , V. Petráček 40 , V. Petrov 112 , <lb/>M. Petrovici 78 , C. Petta 29 , S. Piano 110 , M. Pikna 39 , P. Pillot 113 , O. Pinazza 105 ,36 , L. Pinsky 122 , <lb/>D.B. Piyarathna 122 , M. Płosko´  74 , M. Planinic 129 , J. Pluta 134 , S. Pochybova 136 , P.L.M. Podesta-Lerma 119 , <lb/>M.G. Poghosyan 86 , B. Polichtchouk 112 , N. Poljak 129 , W. Poonsawat 114 , A. Pop 78 , S. Porteboeuf-Houssais 70 , <lb/>J. Porter 74 , J. Pospisil 83 , S.K. Prasad 4 , R. Preghenella 105 ,36 , F. Prino 111 , C.A. Pruneau 135 , I. Pshenichnov 56 , <lb/>M. Puccio <lb/> 111 , G. Puddu <lb/> 25 , P. Pujahari <lb/> 135 , V. Punin <lb/> 99 , J. Putschke <lb/> 135 , H. Qvigstad <lb/> 22 , A. Rachevski <lb/> 110 , <lb/>S. Raha 4 , S. Rajput 90 , J. Rak 123 , A. Rakotozafindrabe 15 , L. Ramello 32 , R. Raniwala 91 , S. Raniwala 91 , <lb/>S.S. Räsänen 46 , B.T. Rascanu 53 , D. Rathee 87 , K.F. Read 125 , J.S. Real 71 , K. Redlich 77 , R.J. Reed 135 , <lb/>A. Rehman 18 , P. Reichelt 53 , F. Reidt 93 ,36 , X. Ren 7 , R. Renfordt 53 , A.R. Reolon 72 , A. Reshetin 56 , F. Rettig 43 , <lb/>J.-P. Revol 12 , K. Reygers 93 , V. Riabov 85 , R.A. Ricci 73 , T. Richert 34 , M. Richter 22 , P. Riedler 36 , W. Riegler 36 , <lb/>F. Riggi 29 , C. Ristea 62 , A. Rivetti 111 , E. Rocco 57 , M. Rodríguez Cahuantzi 2 , A. Rodriguez Manso 81 , <lb/>K. Røed 22 , E. Rogochaya 66 , D. Rohr 43 , D. Röhrich 18 , R. Romita 124 , F. Ronchetti 72 , L. Ronflette 113 , <lb/>P. Rosnet 70 , A. Rossi 36 ,30 , F. Roukoutakis 88 , A. Roy 49 , C. Roy 55 , P. Roy 101 , A.J. Rubio Montero 10 , R. Rui 26 , <lb/>R. Russo <lb/> 27 , E. Ryabinkin <lb/> 100 , Y. Ryabov <lb/> 85 , A. Rybicki <lb/> 117 , S. Sadovsky <lb/> 112 , K. ˇ <lb/>Safařík <lb/> 36 , B. Sahlmuller <lb/> 53 , <lb/>P. Sahoo 49 , R. Sahoo 49 , S. Sahoo 61 , P.K. Sahu 61 , J. Saini 132 , S. Sakai 72 , M.A. Saleh 135 , C.A. Salgado 17 , <lb/>J. Salzwedel 20 , S. Sambyal 90 , V. Samsonov 85 , X. Sanchez Castro 55 , L. ˇ <lb/>Sándor 59 , A. Sandoval 64 , M. Sano 128 , <lb/></front>

			<page> 25 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<front> G. Santagati 29 , D. Sarkar 132 , E. Scapparone 105 , F. Scarlassara 30 , R.P. Scharenberg 95 , C. Schiaua 78 , <lb/>R. Schicker 93 , C. Schmidt 97 , H.R. Schmidt 35 , S. Schuchmann 53 , J. Schukraft 36 , M. Schulc 40 , T. Schuster 137 , <lb/>Y. Schutz <lb/> 113 ,36 , K. Schwarz <lb/> 97 , K. Schweda <lb/> 97 , G. Scioli <lb/> 28 , E. Scomparin <lb/> 111 , R. Scott <lb/> 125 , K.S. Seeder <lb/> 120 , <lb/>J.E. Seger 86 , Y. Sekiguchi 127 , D. Sekihata 47 , I. Selyuzhenkov 97 , K. Senosi 65 , J. Seo 96 ,67 , E. Serradilla 64 ,10 , <lb/>A. Sevcenco 62 , A. Shabanov 56 , A. Shabetai 113 , O. Shadura 3 , R. Shahoyan 36 , A. Shangaraev 112 , A. Sharma 90 , <lb/>N. Sharma 61 ,125 , K. Shigaki 47 , K. Shtejer 9 ,27 , Y. Sibiriak 100 , S. Siddhanta 106 , K.M. Sielewicz 36 , <lb/>T. Siemiarczuk 77 , D. Silvermyr 84 ,34 , C. Silvestre 71 , G. Simatovic 129 , G. Simonetti 36 , R. Singaraju 132 , <lb/>R. Singh 79 , S. Singha 79 ,132 , V. Singhal 132 , B.C. Sinha 132 , T. Sinha 101 , B. Sitar 39 , M. Sitta 32 , T.B. Skaali 22 , <lb/>M. Slupecki 123 , N. Smirnov 137 , R.J.M. Snellings 57 , T.W. Snellman 123 , C. Søgaard 34 , R. Soltz 75 , J. Song 96 , <lb/>M. Song 138 , Z. Song 7 , F. Soramel 30 , S. Sorensen 125 , M. Spacek 40 , E. Spiriti 72 , I. Sputowska 117 , <lb/>M. Spyropoulou-Stassinaki <lb/> 88 , B.K. Srivastava <lb/> 95 , J. Stachel <lb/> 93 , I. Stan <lb/> 62 , G. Stefanek <lb/> 77 , M. Steinpreis <lb/> 20 , <lb/>E. Stenlund 34 , G. Steyn 65 , J.H. Stiller 93 , D. Stocco 113 , P. Strmen 39 , A.A.P. Suaide 120 , T. Sugitate 47 , <lb/>C. Suire 51 , M. Suleymanov 16 , R. Sultanov 58 , M. ˇ <lb/>Sumbera 83 , T.J.M. Symons 74 , A. Szabo 39 , A. Szanto de <lb/>Toledo 120 ,i , I. Szarka 39 , A. Szczepankiewicz 36 , M. Szymanski 134 , J. Takahashi 121 , N. Tanaka 128 , <lb/>M.A. Tangaro 33 , J.D. Tapia Takaki ,ii,51 , A. Tarantola Peloni 53 , M. Tarhini 51 , M. Tariq 19 , M.G. Tarzila 78 , <lb/>A. Tauro 36 , G. Tejeda Muñoz 2 , A. Telesca 36 , K. Terasaki 127 , C. Terrevoli 30 ,25 , B. Teyssier 130 , J. Thäder 74 ,97 , <lb/>D. Thomas 118 , R. Tieulent 130 , A.R. Timmins 122 , A. Toia 53 , S. Trogolo 111 , V. Trubnikov 3 , W.H. Trzaska 123 , <lb/>T. Tsuji 127 , A. Tumkin 99 , R. Turrisi 108 , T.S. Tveter 22 , K. Ullaland 18 , A. Uras 130 , G.L. Usai 25 , A. Utrobicic 129 , <lb/>M. Vajzer <lb/> 83 , M. Vala <lb/> 59 , L. Valencia Palomo <lb/> 70 , S. Vallero <lb/> 27 , J. Van Der Maarel <lb/> 57 , J.W. Van Hoorne <lb/> 36 , M. van <lb/>Leeuwen 57 , T. Vanat 83 , P. Vande Vyvre 36 , D. Varga 136 , A. Vargas 2 , M. Vargyas 123 , R. Varma 48 , <lb/>M. Vasileiou 88 , A. Vasiliev 100 , A. Vauthier 71 , V. Vechernin 131 , A.M. Veen 57 , M. Veldhoen 57 , A. Velure 18 , <lb/>M. Venaruzzo 73 , E. Vercellin 27 , S. Vergara Limón 2 , R. Vernet 8 , M. Verweij 135 , L. Vickovic 116 , G. Viesti 30 ,i , <lb/>J. Viinikainen 123 , Z. Vilakazi 126 , O. Villalobos Baillie 102 , A. Vinogradov 100 , L. Vinogradov 131 , <lb/>Y. Vinogradov 99 , T. Virgili 31 , V. Vislavicius 34 , Y.P. Viyogi 132 , A. Vodopyanov 66 , M.A. Völkl 93 , K. Voloshin 58 , <lb/>S.A. Voloshin 135 , G. Volpe 136 ,36 , B. von Haller 36 , I. Vorobyev 92 ,37 , D. Vranic 97 ,36 , J. Vrláková 41 , <lb/>B. Vulpescu 70 , A. Vyushin 99 , B. Wagner 18 , J. Wagner 97 , H. Wang 57 , M. Wang 7 ,113 , Y. Wang 93 , <lb/>D. Watanabe <lb/> 128 , Y. Watanabe <lb/> 127 , M. Weber <lb/> 36 , S.G. Weber <lb/> 97 , J.P. Wessels <lb/> 54 , U. Westerhoff <lb/> 54 , J. Wiechula <lb/> 35 , <lb/>J. Wikne 22 , M. Wilde 54 , G. Wilk 77 , J. Wilkinson 93 , M.C.S. Williams 105 , B. Windelband 93 , M. Winn 93 , <lb/>C.G. Yaldo 135 , H. Yang 57 , P. Yang 7 , S. Yano 47 , Z. Yin 7 , H. Yokoyama 128 , I.-K. Yoo 96 , V. Yurchenko 3 , <lb/>I. Yushmanov 100 , A. Zaborowska 134 , V. Zaccolo 80 , A. Zaman 16 , C. Zampolli 105 , H.J.C. Zanoli 120 , <lb/>S. Zaporozhets 66 , N. Zardoshti 102 , A. Zarochentsev 131 , P. Závada 60 , N. Zaviyalov 99 , H. Zbroszczyk 134 , <lb/>I.S. Zgura 62 , M. Zhalov 85 , H. Zhang 18 ,7 , X. Zhang 74 , Y. Zhang 7 , C. Zhao 22 , N. Zhigareva 58 , D. Zhou 7 , <lb/>Y. Zhou 80 ,57 , Z. Zhou 18 , H. Zhu 18 ,7 , J. Zhu 113 ,7 , X. Zhu 7 , A. Zichichi 12 ,28 , A. Zimmermann 93 , <lb/>M.B. Zimmermann 54 ,36 , G. Zinovjev 3 , M. Zyzak 43 <lb/> Affiliation notes <lb/> i Deceased <lb/> ii Also at: University of Kansas, Lawrence, Kansas, United States <lb/> Collaboration Institutes <lb/> 1 A.I. Alikhanyan National Science Laboratory (Yerevan Physics Institute) Foundation, Yerevan, Armenia <lb/> 2 Benemérita Universidad Autónoma de Puebla, Puebla, Mexico <lb/> 3 Bogolyubov Institute for Theoretical Physics, Kiev, Ukraine <lb/> 4 Bose Institute, Department of Physics and Centre for Astroparticle Physics and Space Science (CAPSS), <lb/>Kolkata, India <lb/> 5 Budker Institute for Nuclear Physics, Novosibirsk, Russia <lb/> 6 California Polytechnic State University, San Luis Obispo, California, United States <lb/> 7 Central China Normal University, Wuhan, China <lb/> 8 Centre de Calcul de l&apos;IN2P3, Villeurbanne, France <lb/> 9 Centro de Aplicaciones Tecnológicas y Desarrollo Nuclear (CEADEN), Havana, Cuba <lb/> 10 Centro de Investigaciones Energéticas Medioambientales y Tecnológicas (CIEMAT), Madrid, Spain <lb/> 11 Centro de Investigación y de Estudios Avanzados (CINVESTAV), Mexico City and Mérida, Mexico <lb/> 12 Centro Fermi -Museo Storico della Fisica e Centro Studi e Ricerche &quot; Enrico Fermi &quot; , Rome, Italy <lb/> 13 Chicago State University, Chicago, Illinois, USA <lb/> 14 China Institute of Atomic Energy, Beijing, China <lb/></front>

			<page> 26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<front> 15 Commissariat à l&apos;Energie Atomique, IRFU, Saclay, France <lb/> 16 COMSATS Institute of Information Technology (CIIT), Islamabad, Pakistan <lb/> 17 Departamento de Física de Partículas and IGFAE, Universidad de Santiago de Compostela, Santiago de <lb/>Compostela, Spain <lb/> 18 Department of Physics and Technology, University of Bergen, Bergen, Norway <lb/> 19 Department of Physics, Aligarh Muslim University, Aligarh, India <lb/> 20 Department of Physics, Ohio State University, Columbus, Ohio, United States <lb/> 21 Department of Physics, Sejong University, Seoul, South Korea <lb/> 22 Department of Physics, University of Oslo, Oslo, Norway <lb/> 23 Dipartimento di Elettrotecnica ed Elettronica del Politecnico, Bari, Italy <lb/> 24 Dipartimento di Fisica dell&apos;Universià &apos;La Sapienza&apos; and Sezione INFN Rome, Italy <lb/> 25 Dipartimento di Fisica dell&apos;Universià and Sezione INFN, Cagliari, Italy <lb/> 26 Dipartimento di Fisica dell&apos;Universià and Sezione INFN, Trieste, Italy <lb/> 27 Dipartimento di Fisica dell&apos;Universià and Sezione INFN, Turin, Italy <lb/> 28 Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia dell&apos;Universià and Sezione INFN, Bologna, Italy <lb/> 29 Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia dell&apos;Universià and Sezione INFN, Catania, Italy <lb/> 30 Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia dell&apos;Universià and Sezione INFN, Padova, Italy <lb/> 31 Dipartimento di Fisica &apos;E.R. Caianiello&apos; dell&apos;Universià and Gruppo Collegato INFN, Salerno, Italy <lb/> 32 Dipartimento di Scienze e Innovazione Tecnologica dell&apos;Universià del Piemonte Orientale and Gruppo <lb/>Collegato INFN, Alessandria, Italy <lb/> 33 Dipartimento Interateneo di Fisica &apos;M. Merlin&apos; and Sezione INFN, Bari, Italy <lb/> 34 Division of Experimental High Energy Physics, University of Lund, Lund, Sweden <lb/> 35 Eberhard Karls Universität Tübingen, Tübingen, Germany <lb/> 36 European Organization for Nuclear Research (CERN), Geneva, Switzerland <lb/> 37 Excellence Cluster Universe, Technische Universität München, Munich, Germany <lb/> 38 Faculty of Engineering, Bergen University College, Bergen, Norway <lb/> 39 Faculty of Mathematics, Physics and Informatics, Comenius University, Bratislava, Slovakia <lb/> 40 Faculty of Nuclear Sciences and Physical Engineering, Czech Technical University in Prague, Prague, <lb/>Czech Republic <lb/> 41 Faculty of Science, P.J. ˇ <lb/>Safárik University, Košice, Slovakia <lb/> 42 Faculty of Technology, Buskerud and Vestfold University College, Vestfold, Norway <lb/> 43 Frankfurt Institute for Advanced Studies, Johann Wolfgang Goethe-Universität Frankfurt, Frankfurt, <lb/>Germany <lb/> 44 Gangneung-Wonju National University, Gangneung, South Korea <lb/> 45 Gauhati University, Department of Physics, Guwahati, India <lb/> 46 Helsinki Institute of Physics (HIP), Helsinki, Finland <lb/> 47 Hiroshima University, Hiroshima, Japan <lb/> 48 Indian Institute of Technology Bombay (IIT), Mumbai, India <lb/> 49 Indian Institute of Technology Indore, Indore (IITI), India <lb/> 50 Inha University, Incheon, South Korea <lb/> 51 Institut de Physique Nucléaire d&apos;Orsay (IPNO), Université Paris-Sud, CNRS-IN2P3, Orsay, France <lb/> 52 Institut für Informatik, Johann Wolfgang Goethe-Universität Frankfurt, Frankfurt, Germany <lb/> 53 Institut für Kernphysik, Johann Wolfgang Goethe-Universität Frankfurt, Frankfurt, Germany <lb/> 54 Institut für Kernphysik, Westfälische Wilhelms-Universität Münster, Münster, Germany <lb/> 55 Institut Pluridisciplinaire Hubert Curien (IPHC), Université de Strasbourg, CNRS-IN2P3, Strasbourg, <lb/>France <lb/> 56 Institute for Nuclear Research, Academy of Sciences, Moscow, Russia <lb/> 57 Institute for Subatomic Physics of Utrecht University, Utrecht, Netherlands <lb/> 58 Institute for Theoretical and Experimental Physics, Moscow, Russia <lb/> 59 Institute of Experimental Physics, Slovak Academy of Sciences, Košice, Slovakia <lb/> 60 Institute of Physics, Academy of Sciences of the Czech Republic, Prague, Czech Republic <lb/> 61 Institute of Physics, Bhubaneswar, India <lb/> 62 Institute of Space Science (ISS), Bucharest, Romania <lb/> 63 Instituto de Ciencias Nucleares, Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México, Mexico City, Mexico <lb/> 64 Instituto de Física, Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México, Mexico City, Mexico <lb/> 65 iThemba LABS, National Research Foundation, Somerset West, South Africa <lb/></front>

			<page> 27 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<front> 66 Joint Institute for Nuclear Research (JINR), Dubna, Russia <lb/> 67 Konkuk University, Seoul, South Korea <lb/> 68 Korea Institute of Science and Technology Information, Daejeon, South Korea <lb/> 69 KTO Karatay University, Konya, Turkey <lb/> 70 Laboratoire de Physique Corpusculaire (LPC), Clermont Université, Université Blaise Pascal, <lb/>CNRS–IN2P3, Clermont-Ferrand, France <lb/> 71 Laboratoire de Physique Subatomique et de Cosmologie, Université Grenoble-Alpes, CNRS-IN2P3, <lb/>Grenoble, France <lb/> 72 Laboratori Nazionali di Frascati, INFN, Frascati, Italy <lb/> 73 Laboratori Nazionali di Legnaro, INFN, Legnaro, Italy <lb/> 74 Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, Berkeley, California, United States <lb/> 75 Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, Livermore, California, United States <lb/> 76 Moscow Engineering Physics Institute, Moscow, Russia <lb/> 77 National Centre for Nuclear Studies, Warsaw, Poland <lb/> 78 National Institute for Physics and Nuclear Engineering, Bucharest, Romania <lb/> 79 National Institute of Science Education and Research, Bhubaneswar, India <lb/> 80 Niels Bohr Institute, University of Copenhagen, Copenhagen, Denmark <lb/> 81 Nikhef, National Institute for Subatomic Physics, Amsterdam, Netherlands <lb/> 82 Nuclear Physics Group, STFC Daresbury Laboratory, Daresbury, United Kingdom <lb/> 83 Nuclear Physics Institute, Academy of Sciences of the Czech Republic, ˇ <lb/>Rež u Prahy, Czech Republic <lb/> 84 Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Oak Ridge, Tennessee, United States <lb/> 85 Petersburg Nuclear Physics Institute, Gatchina, Russia <lb/> 86 Physics Department, Creighton University, Omaha, Nebraska, United States <lb/> 87 Physics Department, Panjab University, Chandigarh, India <lb/> 88 Physics Department, University of Athens, Athens, Greece <lb/> 89 Physics Department, University of Cape Town, Cape Town, South Africa <lb/> 90 Physics Department, University of Jammu, Jammu, India <lb/> 91 Physics Department, University of Rajasthan, Jaipur, India <lb/> 92 Physik Department, Technische Universität München, Munich, Germany <lb/> 93 Physikalisches Institut, Ruprecht-Karls-Universität Heidelberg, Heidelberg, Germany <lb/> 94 Politecnico di Torino, Turin, Italy <lb/> 95 Purdue University, West Lafayette, Indiana, United States <lb/> 96 Pusan National University, Pusan, South Korea <lb/> 97 Research Division and ExtreMe Matter Institute EMMI, GSI Helmholtzzentrum für <lb/>Schwerionenforschung, Darmstadt, Germany <lb/> 98 Rudjer Boškovi´ Institute, Zagreb, Croatia <lb/> 99 Russian Federal Nuclear Center (VNIIEF), Sarov, Russia <lb/> 100 Russian Research Centre Kurchatov Institute, Moscow, Russia <lb/> 101 Saha Institute of Nuclear Physics, Kolkata, India <lb/> 102 School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Birmingham, Birmingham, United Kingdom <lb/> 103 Sección Física, Departamento de Ciencias, Pontificia Universidad Católica del Perú, Lima, Peru <lb/> 104 Sezione INFN, Bari, Italy <lb/> 105 Sezione INFN, Bologna, Italy <lb/> 106 Sezione INFN, Cagliari, Italy <lb/> 107 Sezione INFN, Catania, Italy <lb/> 108 Sezione INFN, Padova, Italy <lb/> 109 Sezione INFN, Rome, Italy <lb/> 110 Sezione INFN, Trieste, Italy <lb/> 111 Sezione INFN, Turin, Italy <lb/> 112 SSC IHEP of NRC Kurchatov institute, Protvino, Russia <lb/> 113 SUBATECH, Ecole des Mines de Nantes, Université de Nantes, CNRS-IN2P3, Nantes, France <lb/> 114 Suranaree University of Technology, Nakhon Ratchasima, Thailand <lb/> 115 Technical University of Košice, Košice, Slovakia <lb/> 116 Technical University of Split FESB, Split, Croatia <lb/> 117 The Henryk Niewodniczanski Institute of Nuclear Physics, Polish Academy of Sciences, Cracow, Poland <lb/> 118 The University of Texas at Austin, Physics Department, Austin, Texas, USA <lb/></front>

			<page> 28 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Inclusive, prompt and non-prompt J/ψ production in Pb-Pb collisions <lb/>ALICE Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<front> 119 Universidad Autónoma de Sinaloa, Culiacán, Mexico <lb/> 120 Universidade de São Paulo (USP), São Paulo, Brazil <lb/> 121 Universidade Estadual de Campinas (UNICAMP), Campinas, Brazil <lb/> 122 University of Houston, Houston, Texas, United States <lb/> 123 University of Jyväskylä, Jyväskylä, Finland <lb/> 124 University of Liverpool, Liverpool, United Kingdom <lb/> 125 University of Tennessee, Knoxville, Tennessee, United States <lb/> 126 University of the Witwatersrand, Johannesburg, South Africa <lb/> 127 University of Tokyo, Tokyo, Japan <lb/> 128 University of Tsukuba, Tsukuba, Japan <lb/> 129 University of Zagreb, Zagreb, Croatia <lb/> 130 Université de Lyon, Université Lyon 1, CNRS/IN2P3, IPN-Lyon, Villeurbanne, France <lb/> 131 V. Fock Institute for Physics, St. Petersburg State University, St. Petersburg, Russia <lb/> 132 Variable Energy Cyclotron Centre, Kolkata, India <lb/> 133 Vinča Institute of Nuclear Sciences, Belgrade, Serbia <lb/> 134 Warsaw University of Technology, Warsaw, Poland <lb/> 135 Wayne State University, Detroit, Michigan, United States <lb/> 136 Wigner Research Centre for Physics, Hungarian Academy of Sciences, Budapest, Hungary <lb/> 137 Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut, United States <lb/> 138 Yonsei University, Seoul, South Korea <lb/> 139 Zentrum für Technologietransfer und Telekommunikation (ZTT), Fachhochschule Worms, Worms, <lb/>Germany <lb/></front>

			<page> 29 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
