<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front place="headnote"> EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) <lb/> CERN-PH-EP/2015-088 <lb/>2015/04/15 <lb/> CMS-SMP-13-010 <lb/> Angular coefficients of Z bosons produced in pp collisions <lb/>at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  =  8 TeV and decaying to µ <lb/> +  µ <lb/> − <lb/> as a function of <lb/>transverse momentum and rapidity <lb/> The CMS Collaboration <lb/>  * <lb/> Abstract <lb/> Measurements of the five most significant angular coefficients, A  0 through A  4 , for Z <lb/>bosons produced in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  =  8 TeV and decaying to µ  +  µ  −  are presented <lb/>as a function of the transverse momentum and rapidity of Z boson. The integrated <lb/>luminosity of the dataset collected with the CMS detector at the LHC corresponds <lb/>to 19.7 fb <lb/> −1  . These measurements provide comprehensive information about Z boson <lb/>production mechanisms, and are compared to QCD predictions at leading order, next-<lb/>to-leading order, and next-to-next-to-leading order in perturbation theory. <lb/> Submitted to Physics Letters B <lb/> c <lb/> 2015 CERN for the benefit of the CMS Collaboration. CC-BY-3.0 license <lb/>  *  See Appendix A for the list of collaboration members <lb/> arXiv:1504.03512v1  [hep-ex] 14 Apr 2015 <lb/></front>

			<page> 1 <lb/></page>

			<body> We report the first measurement of the angular coefficients of Z bosons produced in pp col-<lb/>lisions and decaying to muon pairs. These coefficients govern the decay of the Z boson and <lb/>thereby the kinematics of the lepton. Their values follow from the vector and axial vector (V-A) <lb/>structure of boson-fermion couplings. The general structure of the lepton angular distribution <lb/>in the boson rest frame is given by <lb/>d 2  σ <lb/> d cos θ  *  dφ  *  ∝ <lb/> (1 +  cos <lb/> 2  θ <lb/>  *  ) +  A  0 <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> (1 −  3 cos <lb/> 2  θ <lb/>  *  ) +  A  1 sin(2θ <lb/>  *  )  cos φ <lb/>  *  +  A  2 <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>sin <lb/> 2  θ <lb/>  *  cos(2φ <lb/>  *  ) <lb/>+A  3 sin θ <lb/>  *  cos φ <lb/>  *  +  A  4 cos θ <lb/>  *  +  A  5 sin <lb/> 2  θ <lb/>  *  sin(2φ <lb/>  *  ) +  A  6 sin(2θ <lb/>  *  )  sin φ <lb/>  *  +  A  7 sin θ <lb/>  *  sin φ <lb/>  * <lb/> . <lb/>(1) <lb/>Here, θ  *  and φ  *  are the polar and azimuthal angles of the negatively charged lepton in the rest <lb/>frame of the lepton pair. In this analysis we choose the Collins–Soper (CS) frame [1] to measure <lb/>the angular coefficients A i  , considering the momentum of the beam proton closest in rapidity <lb/>to the Z boson as &quot; target momentum &quot; [1]. The parameters A  0 , A  1 , and A  2 are related to the <lb/>polarization of the Z boson, whilst A  3 and A  4 are also sensitive to the V-A structure of the <lb/>couplings of the muons. The angular coefficients vanish as the transverse momentum of the <lb/>Z boson q  T approaches zero, except for A  0 , which measures the longitudinal polarization with <lb/>respect to the z axis, and A  4 , the electroweak parity violation term, which reflects the difference <lb/>of the polarization along the z axis and the strength of V-A couplings. <lb/>The only previous measurement of four of the angular coefficients was performed by the CDF <lb/>Collaboration in pp interactions for q  T up to 55 GeV [2]. The angular coefficients in pp collisions <lb/>are expected to differ from those in pp collisions for several reasons. For pp collisions, Z boson <lb/>production occurs predominantly via the qq annihilation process, whilst for pp collisions there <lb/>is a significant contribution from the qg Compton process. For the qq process in the CS frame, <lb/> A  0  =  A  2  =  q  2 <lb/>T /(M 2 <lb/>Z  +  q  2 <lb/>T  )  [3–6], where M  Z is the Z boson mass. For the qg Compton process <lb/> A  0  =  A  2  ≈  5q 2 <lb/>T /(M 2 <lb/>Z  +  5q 2 <lb/>T  )  [7]. The relation A  0  =  A  2 is known as the Lam–Tung relation [8], <lb/>reflecting the full transverse polarization of vector bosons coupling to quarks, as well as rota-<lb/>tional invariance [9]. Processes containing non-planar configurations (e.g., from higher order <lb/>multi-gluon emission) smear the transverse polarization, leading to A  2  &lt;  A  0 [10]. In contrast <lb/>to what happens at the Tevatron, the average handedness of Z bosons is nonzero at the LHC, <lb/>as for the W boson [11–13]. <lb/>The angular coefficients of Z bosons produced in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  =  8 TeV and decaying to <lb/> µ  +  µ  −  are measured as a function of q  T and rapidity y. The data sample, taken with the CMS <lb/>detector at the LHC, corresponds to an integrated luminosity of 19.7 fb <lb/> −1  . The large Z boson <lb/>event sample collected by the CMS experiment allows precision measurements of the angular <lb/>distribution for q  T  &lt;  200 GeV and  |y| &lt;  2.1. The coefficients, measured as a function of q  T <lb/> and  |y|,  are compared with three perturbative QCD predictions by FEWZ at next-to-next-to-<lb/>leading order (NNLO) [14], POWHEG at next-to-leading order (NLO) [15–18], and MADGRAPH <lb/>at leading order (LO) [19]. <lb/>The central feature of the CMS apparatus is a superconducting solenoid of 6 m internal diame-<lb/>ter, providing a magnetic field of 3.8 T. Within the solenoid volume are a silicon pixel and strip <lb/>tracker, a lead tungstate crystal electromagnetic calorimeter, and a brass and plastic scintillator <lb/>hadron calorimeter, each composed of a barrel and two endcap sections. Muons are measured <lb/>in gas-ionization detectors embedded in the steel flux-return yoke outside the solenoid. Exten-<lb/>sive forward calorimetry complements the coverage provided by the barrel and endcap detec-<lb/>tors. Muons are measured in the pseudorapidity range  |η| &lt;  2.4, with detection planes made <lb/>using three technologies: drift tubes, cathode strip chambers, and resistive plate chambers. <lb/></body>

			<page> 2 <lb/></page>

			<body> Matching muons to tracks measured in the silicon tracker results in a relative p  T resolution for <lb/>muons with 20  &lt;  p  T  &lt;  100 GeV of 1.3–2.0% in the barrel and better than 6% in the endcaps. <lb/>A more detailed description of the CMS detector, together with a definition of the coordinate <lb/>system and the relevant kinematic variables, can be found in Ref. [20]. A particle-flow (PF) <lb/>event reconstruction algorithm [21, 22] is used in this analysis. It consists of reconstructing and <lb/>identifying each single particle with an optimized combination of all subdetector information. <lb/>A trigger for single isolated muon is used, requiring p  T  &gt;  24 GeV and  |η| &lt;  2.1. The leading <lb/>reconstructed muon in p  T is matched to the muon selected by the trigger. <lb/>The signal process is simulated using the MADGRAPH 1.3.30 generator [19] with zero to four <lb/>additional jets, interfaced with PYTHIA v6.4.24 [23] with the Z2* tune [24]. The matching be-<lb/>tween the matrix element calculation and the parton shower is performed with the k  T -MLM al-<lb/>gorithm [25]. The CTEQ6L1 [26] parton distribution functions (PDF) are used for the event gen-<lb/>eration. Multiple-parton interactions are simulated by PYTHIA. The POWHEG generator [15–18] <lb/>interfaced with PYTHIA and the CT10 PDF set [27] are used as an alternate to test any model <lb/>dependence in the shapes of the angular distributions. <lb/>Background simulations are performed with MADGRAPH (W+jets, tt, ττ),  POWHEG (single <lb/>top quark [28, 29]), and PYTHIA (WW, WZ, ZZ). The normalizations of the inclusive Drell– <lb/>Yan, W boson [14], and tt [30] distributions are set using NNLO cross sections. For single top <lb/>quark production a higher order (approximate NNLO [31]) inclusive cross section is used. The <lb/>generated events are passed through a detector simulation based on GEANT4 [32]. <lb/>Each muon candidate is required to be reconstructed in the muon detectors and in the inner <lb/>tracker, and the global track fit is required to have a reduced χ  2  &lt;  10. The vertex with the <lb/>highest sum of p  2 <lb/>T for associated tracks is defined as the primary vertex. The distance of the <lb/>muon candidate trajectories with respect to the primary vertex must be smaller than 2 mm in <lb/>the transverse plane and 5 mm along the z axis. The leading (subleading) muon is required to <lb/>have p  T  &gt;  25  (10)  GeV and  |η| &lt;  2.1  (2.4).  In order to suppress background events, the muons <lb/>are required to be isolated from nearby particles. The relative isolation is calculated as the ratio <lb/>of the scalar sum of p  T of all PF candidates from the same primary vertex, within a cone of <lb/> ∆R  = <lb/> √ <lb/> (∆η)  2  + (∆φ)  2  &lt;  0.4, and the p  T of the muon. For the leading (subleading) muon in <lb/> p  T , the relative isolation must be less than 0.12 (0.5). Oppositely charged muon pairs with an <lb/>invariant mass in the range 81–101 GeV are selected. In the rare case that more than two muons <lb/>are selected, the muon pair with invariant mass closest to the Z boson mass is chosen. The <lb/>muon pair must satisfy  |y| &lt;  2.1; for higher  |y|  the acceptance varies rapidly. <lb/>A &quot; tag-and-probe &quot; method [33] is used to measure the efficiencies for track reconstruction, <lb/>trigger, muon isolation, and muon identification in data and simulation. Efficiency corrections <lb/>are applied as multiplicative scale factors to the simulation values. The efficiency for track <lb/>reconstruction is measured in bins of η since the p  T dependence is weak. The trigger efficiency <lb/>is determined in bins of p  T and η, separately for µ  +  and µ  −  . The identification efficiency is <lb/>measured in bins of p  T and η. Since the subleading muon can point in the direction of the <lb/>hadronic activity, a looser isolation requirement is used and its efficiency is measured as a <lb/>function of q  T , cos θ  *  , and φ  *  . The efficiency of the isolation requirement for the leading muon <lb/>is measured as a function of p  T and η of the muon, as detector effects relate to these variables <lb/>more directly than to the Z boson q  T and y. <lb/> After event selection, the background contribution ranges from  ∼0.1%  at low q  T to  ∼1.5%  at <lb/>high q  T . The yields of the backgrounds from tt, ττ, WW, tW, and W+jets production are esti-<lb/>mated from data using lepton flavor universality. Most of these backgrounds typically have <lb/>two prompt leptons, which may have the same flavor. The W+jets background is flavor asym-<lb/></body>

			<page> 3 <lb/></page>

			<body> metric, but its contribution is small. We assume that the ratio of the number of oppositely <lb/>charged background µµ and eµ events is the same in data and simulation. We use the ratio of <lb/>the eµ yields in data and simulation to normalize the simulation to data. <lb/>The acceptance and the efficiency at the event level vary in cos θ  *  and φ  *  , and strongly with q  T <lb/> and y. In order to avoid a bias in the acceptance due to the modeling of the Z boson kinematics, <lb/>the simulation is reweighted in fine bins of q  T and y to match the background-subtracted data <lb/>distribution. The weights are determined at the reconstruction level and applied at the genera-<lb/>tor level. The weighting is iterated four times, with negligible change between the second and <lb/>fourth iteration. <lb/>The angular coefficients are measured in eight bins of q  T and two bins of  |y|,  by fitting the <lb/>two-dimensional (cos θ  *  , φ  *  ) distribution in data with a linear combination of templates. These <lb/>templates are built for each coefficient A i  by reweighting the simulation at generator level to <lb/>the corresponding angular distribution, as given in Eq. (1). The templates are based on recon-<lb/>structed muons, and thereby incorporate the effects of resolution, efficiency and acceptance. <lb/>A template is also built for the term  (1 +  cos 2  θ  *  )  of Eq. (1). An additional template, with <lb/>shape and normalization fixed, is developed for fitting the backgrounds. A binned maximum-<lb/>likelihood method with Poisson uncertainties is employed for the fit. The angular coefficients <lb/> A  5 , A  6 , and A  7 are predicted to be very small; they are set to zero and excluded from the fit. <lb/>Since A  0 through A  4 are sign invariant in φ  *  , the absolute value  |φ  *  |  is used. The fit is made in <lb/>12×12 equidistant bins in cos θ  *  and  |φ  *  |.  The statistical uncertainties from the fit are confirmed <lb/>by comparison with pseudo-experiments. <lb/>The angular coefficients A  0 , A  2 , A  3 , and A  4 are also measured by an independent analysis simi-<lb/>lar to that reported in Ref. [2], where one-dimensional (1D) templates produced using POWHEG <lb/> with NLO CT10 PDFs are fitted to the distributions in cos θ  *  and  |φ  *  |.  The 1D fit analysis <lb/>is performed iteratively, so as to be unbiased with respect to the assumed templates and to <lb/>possible correlations between cos θ  *  and  |φ  *  |.  The analysis differs in the triggers, estimation <lb/>of backgrounds, simulation, and selection criteria. The 1D fit analysis uses a sample that re-<lb/>quires a dimuon trigger with asymmetric muon p  T thresholds of 17 and 8 GeV. Both results are <lb/>consistent within their total systematic uncertainties, excluding uncertainties common to both <lb/>analyses. <lb/>Some examples of the measured cos θ  *  and  |φ  *  |  distributions from the 1D analysis are given in <lb/>Fig. 1. The measured and simulated distributions are shown together using the best fit values <lb/>of the angular coefficients. The shape of the cos θ  *  distribution changes with q  T and  |y|  because <lb/>the acceptance and efficiency in cos θ  *  depend strongly on these two variables. For  |φ  *  |,  the <lb/>shape of the distribution changes moderately with q  T , and is almost insensitive to  |y|.  The <lb/>comparison of data and simulation shown in Fig. 1 gives confidence that the acceptance and <lb/>efficiency dependences are correctly modeled in the simulation. <lb/>Several sources of systematic uncertainties are taken into account. The most significant source <lb/>is the muon efficiency that includes the trigger, track reconstruction, isolation, and identifica-<lb/>tion. The statistical uncertainties of the measured efficiency scale factors are taken into account <lb/>by simulating many pseudo-experiments in which the templates are reformed, each time vary-<lb/>ing the scale factors randomly within the given uncertainty. The systematic uncertainties in <lb/>the extraction of the efficiency (e.g., background estimates) are also included. Another sig-<lb/>nificant uncertainty stems from the statistical precision of the templates, which is estimated <lb/>using pseudo-experiments. The pileup uncertainty is estimated by varying the cross section <lb/>of the minimum bias events by  ±5%.  The muon momentum bias is measured in data and <lb/>simulation, and corresponding corrections are applied [34]. The statistical uncertainties in the <lb/></body>

			<page> 4 <lb/></page>

			<body> * <lb/> θ <lb/> cos <lb/> -1 -0.8 -0.6 -0.4 -0.2 0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 1 <lb/> Data/MC <lb/> 0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/> Events  per 0.04 <lb/> 0 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>15000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>25000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>35000 <lb/> | &lt; 1 <lb/> y <lb/> Data, | <lb/>| &lt; 1 <lb/> y <lb/> MC, | <lb/>| &lt; 2.1 <lb/> y <lb/> Data, 1 &lt; | <lb/>| &lt; 2.1 <lb/> y <lb/> MC, 1 &lt; | <lb/> CMS <lb/>(8 TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/>&lt; 20 GeV <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 10 &lt; <lb/> | [rad] <lb/> * <lb/> φ <lb/> | <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3 <lb/> Data/MC <lb/> 0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/> [rad] <lb/> π <lb/> Events per 0.04 <lb/> 0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/> CMS <lb/>(8 TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/>&lt; 20 GeV <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 10 &lt; <lb/> * <lb/> θ <lb/> cos <lb/> -1 -0.8 -0.6 -0.4 -0.2 0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 1 <lb/> Data/MC <lb/> 0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/> Events  per 0.04 <lb/> 0 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/>1000 <lb/> CMS <lb/>(8 TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/>&lt; 200 GeV <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 120 &lt; <lb/> | [rad] <lb/> * <lb/> φ <lb/> | <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3 <lb/> Data/MC <lb/> 0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/> [rad] <lb/> π <lb/> Events per 0.04 <lb/> 0 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1200 <lb/>1400 <lb/>1600 <lb/>1800 <lb/>2000 <lb/> CMS <lb/>(8 TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/>&lt; 200 GeV <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 120 &lt; <lb/> Figure 1: A few examples of the observed 1D angular distributions in cos θ  *  (left) and  |φ  *  | <lb/> (right) compared to the MC simulation using the best fit values of the angular coefficients. The <lb/>top (bottom) plots show the distributions for 10  &lt;  q  T  &lt;  20 GeV (120  &lt;  q  T  &lt;  200 GeV), a region <lb/>where A  0 and A  2 are small (large). The background-subtracted data points are shown with <lb/>filled (open) circles for  |y| &lt;  1 (1  &lt; |y| &lt;  2.1), whilst the corresponding MC results are shown <lb/>with the solid (dashed) lines. Vertical bars represent the statistical uncertainties. The lower <lb/>panels show the data-to-MC ratios. <lb/>muon momentum correction factors are propagated to a systematic uncertainty using pseudo-<lb/>experiments. In addition, a systematic uncertainty is assessed to take into account possible <lb/>global offsets from the peak position of the Z boson mass. The systematic uncertainties for <lb/>the background are estimated by varying the normalization scale factor of the eµ sample by <lb/>10% and the yields of WZ and ZZ events by 50%. The statistical precision of the iterative <lb/>reweighting is determined using pseudo-experiments. The difference between the last two it-<lb/>erations is assigned as additional systematic uncertainty. The effect of final-state radiation is <lb/>taken into account by adding the energy of photons within a cone of radius 0.1 around the <lb/>muon direction [35]. Weights are applied to the simulation to reflect the difference between a <lb/>soft-collinear approach and the exact O(α QED ) result and the reconstructed template is rebuilt <lb/>using the weighted simulation. The difference between templates is used to estimate the sys-<lb/>tematic uncertainty from final-state radiation. Finally, the acceptance uncertainty, related to the <lb/>values of A i  assumed in the simulation, is estimated by reweighting with the fitted values of <lb/> A i  , and the difference in results is included as a systematic uncertainty. Generally, the statis-<lb/>tical uncertainties dominate in the highest bins in q  T , whilst the systematic uncertainty in the <lb/>efficiency tends to be the most important elsewhere. The various systematic uncertainties of <lb/>the five angular coefficients A  0 to A  4 are presented in Fig. 2. <lb/></body>

			<page> 5 <lb/></page>

			<body> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>Absolute uncertainty <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> | &lt; 1 <lb/> y <lb/> : | <lb/> 0 <lb/> A <lb/> Statistical <lb/>Total systematic <lb/>Efficiencies <lb/>Templates <lb/>Pileup <lb/>) scale+resolution <lb/> µ <lb/> ( <lb/> p <lb/> shape <lb/> y <lb/> , <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> Background <lb/>FSR <lb/>MC pol. <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>Absolute uncertainty <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> | &lt; 2.1 <lb/> y <lb/> : 1 &lt; | <lb/> 0 <lb/> A <lb/> Statistical <lb/>Total systematic <lb/>Efficiencies <lb/>Templates <lb/>Pileup <lb/>) scale+resolution <lb/> µ <lb/> ( <lb/> p <lb/> shape <lb/> y <lb/> , <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> Background <lb/>FSR <lb/>MC pol. <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>Absolute uncertainty <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> | &lt; 1 <lb/> y <lb/> : | <lb/> 1 <lb/> A <lb/> Statistical <lb/>Total systematic <lb/>Efficiencies <lb/>Templates <lb/>Pileup <lb/>) scale+resolution <lb/> µ <lb/> ( <lb/> p <lb/> shape <lb/> y <lb/> , <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> Background <lb/>FSR <lb/>MC pol. <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>Absolute uncertainty <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> | &lt; 2.1 <lb/> y <lb/> : 1 &lt; | <lb/> 1 <lb/> A <lb/> Statistical <lb/>Total systematic <lb/>Efficiencies <lb/>Templates <lb/>Pileup <lb/>) scale+resolution <lb/> µ <lb/> ( <lb/> p <lb/> shape <lb/> y <lb/> , <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> Background <lb/>FSR <lb/>MC pol. <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>Absolute uncertainty <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.1 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> | &lt; 1 <lb/> y <lb/> : | <lb/> 2 <lb/> A <lb/> Statistical <lb/>Total systematic <lb/>Efficiencies <lb/>Templates <lb/>Pileup <lb/>) scale+resolution <lb/> µ <lb/> ( <lb/> p <lb/> shape <lb/> y <lb/> , <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> Background <lb/>FSR <lb/>MC pol. <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>Absolute uncertainty <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.1 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> | &lt; 2.1 <lb/> y <lb/> : 1 &lt; | <lb/> 2 <lb/> A <lb/> Statistical <lb/>Total systematic <lb/>Efficiencies <lb/>Templates <lb/>Pileup <lb/>) scale+resolution <lb/> µ <lb/> ( <lb/> p <lb/> shape <lb/> y <lb/> , <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> Background <lb/>FSR <lb/>MC pol. <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>Absolute uncertainty <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.06 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> | &lt; 1 <lb/> y <lb/> : | <lb/> 3 <lb/> A <lb/> Statistical <lb/>Total systematic <lb/>Efficiencies <lb/>Templates <lb/>Pileup <lb/>) scale+resolution <lb/> µ <lb/> ( <lb/> p <lb/> shape <lb/> y <lb/> , <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> Background <lb/>FSR <lb/>MC pol. <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>Absolute uncertainty <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.06 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> | &lt; 2.1 <lb/> y <lb/> : 1 &lt; | <lb/> 3 <lb/> A <lb/> Statistical <lb/>Total systematic <lb/>Efficiencies <lb/>Templates <lb/>Pileup <lb/>) scale+resolution <lb/> µ <lb/> ( <lb/> p <lb/> shape <lb/> y <lb/> , <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> Background <lb/>FSR <lb/>MC pol. <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>Absolute uncertainty <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> | &lt; 1 <lb/> y <lb/> : | <lb/> 4 <lb/> A <lb/> Statistical <lb/>Total systematic <lb/>Efficiencies <lb/>Templates <lb/>Pileup <lb/>) scale+resolution <lb/> µ <lb/> ( <lb/> p <lb/> shape <lb/> y <lb/> , <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> Background <lb/>FSR <lb/>MC pol. <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>Absolute uncertainty <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> | &lt; 2.1 <lb/> y <lb/> : 1 &lt; | <lb/> 4 <lb/> A <lb/> Statistical <lb/>Total systematic <lb/>Efficiencies <lb/>Templates <lb/>Pileup <lb/>) scale+resolution <lb/> µ <lb/> ( <lb/> p <lb/> shape <lb/> y <lb/> , <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> Background <lb/>FSR <lb/>MC pol. <lb/> Figure 2: Absolute uncertainties in the five angular coefficients A  0 to A  4 . Each figure shows the <lb/> q  T dependence in the indicated ranges of  |y|. <lb/></body>

			<page> 6 <lb/></page>

			<body> The results of the q  T and  |y|  dependent measurement of the angular coefficients A  0 to A  4 as <lb/>well as the difference A  0  −  A  2 are presented along with MADGRAPH, POWHEG, and FEWZ <lb/> (at NNLO) calculations in Figs. 3 and 4. The values and uncertainties of the coefficients are <lb/>provided in Tables 1 and 2. The PDF sets used in the calculations are CTEQ6L for MADGRAPH <lb/>and CT10 for POWHEG (at NLO) and FEWZ (at NNLO). The MADGRAPH predictions for A  4 <lb/> are systematically higher than those of POWHEG and FEWZ because MADGRAPH uses a weak <lb/>mixing angle calculated without considering radiative corrections. The measured A  0 and A  2 <lb/> coefficients agree better with the prediction of MADGRAPH than with those of POWHEG and <lb/> FEWZ, especially at high q  T . At q  T  =  0, the POWHEG prediction for A  0 is negative, which <lb/>is unphysical and has been traced to approximations in the shower matching algorithm. We <lb/>find that A  0 (q T ) and A  2 (q T ) are larger in pp collisions than those measured in pp collisions at <lb/>the Tevatron. The significant contribution from the qg process in pp collisions at the LHC is <lb/>responsible for this difference. We observe the violation of the Lam–Tung relation (A 0  =  A  2 ) <lb/>anticipated by QCD calculations beyond leading order [36]. We find that A  0  &gt;  A  2 , especially <lb/>for high q  T . In addition, we measure nonzero values of A  1 and A  3 . The comparison of the <lb/>results for  |y| &lt;  1 and 1  &lt; |y| &lt;  2.1 is shown in Fig. 5. <lb/>In summary, we presented the five major angular coefficients, A  0 through A  4 , for the produc-<lb/>tion of the Z boson decaying to muon pairs as a function of q  T and  |y|  in pp collisions. These <lb/>results play an important role in future high-precision measurements, such as the measurement <lb/>of the mass of the W boson and of the electroweak mixing angle. Some theoretical predictions <lb/>deviate from the measurements in q  T . Further refinements of the theory are needed to achieve <lb/>a better agreement with the experimental results. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments <lb/> We congratulate our colleagues in the CERN accelerator departments for the excellent perfor-<lb/>mance of the LHC and thank the technical and administrative staffs at CERN and at other CMS <lb/>institutes for their contributions to the success of the CMS effort. In addition, we gratefully <lb/>acknowledge the computing centers and personnel of the Worldwide LHC Computing Grid <lb/>for delivering so effectively the computing infrastructure essential to our analyses. Finally, we <lb/>acknowledge the enduring support for the construction and operation of the LHC and the CMS <lb/>detector provided by the following funding agencies: BMWFW and FWF (Austria); FNRS and <lb/>FWO (Belgium); CNPq, CAPES, FAPERJ, and FAPESP (Brazil); MES (Bulgaria); CERN; CAS, <lb/>MoST, and NSFC (China); COLCIENCIAS (Colombia); MSES and CSF (Croatia); RPF (Cyprus); <lb/>MoER, ERC IUT and ERDF (Estonia); Academy of Finland, MEC, and HIP (Finland); CEA and <lb/>CNRS/IN2P3 (France); BMBF, DFG, and HGF (Germany); GSRT (Greece); OTKA and NIH <lb/>(Hungary); DAE and DST (India); IPM (Iran); SFI (Ireland); INFN (Italy); MSIP and NRF (Re-<lb/>public of Korea); LAS (Lithuania); MOE and UM (Malaysia); CINVESTAV, CONACYT, SEP, <lb/>and UASLP-FAI (Mexico); MBIE (New Zealand); PAEC (Pakistan); MSHE and NSC (Poland); <lb/>FCT (Portugal); JINR (Dubna); MON, RosAtom, RAS and RFBR (Russia); MESTD (Serbia); <lb/>SEIDI and CPAN (Spain); Swiss Funding Agencies (Switzerland); MST (Taipei); ThEPCenter, <lb/>IPST, STAR and NSTDA (Thailand); TUBITAK and TAEK (Turkey); NASU and SFFR (Ukraine); <lb/>STFC (United Kingdom); DOE and NSF (USA). <lb/>Individuals have received support from the Marie-Curie program and the European Research <lb/>Council and EPLANET (European Union); the Leventis Foundation; the A. P. Sloan Founda-<lb/>tion; the Alexander von Humboldt Foundation; the Belgian Federal Science Policy Office; the <lb/>Fonds pour la Formation à la Recherche dans l&apos;Industrie et dans l&apos;Agriculture (FRIA-Belgium); <lb/>the Agentschap voor Innovatie door Wetenschap en Technologie (IWT-Belgium); the Ministry <lb/></div>

			<page> 7 <lb/></page>

			<body> Table 1: The five angular coefficients A  0 to A  4 and A  0  −  A  2 in bins of q  T for  |y| &lt;  1. <lb/> q  T [GeV] <lb/> A  0  ±δ  stat  ±δ  syst <lb/> A  1  ±δ  stat  ±δ  syst <lb/> A  2  ±δ  stat  ±δ  syst <lb/> 0–10 <lb/>0.018  ±0.003 ±0.009 −0.008 ±0.002 ±0.005 <lb/> 0.007  ±0.004 ±0.003 <lb/> 10–20 0.068  ±0.004 ±0.010 −0.006 ±0.003 ±0.005 <lb/> 0.037  ±0.004 ±0.005 <lb/> 20–35 0.179  ±0.004 ±0.013  0.014  ±0.003 ±0.008 <lb/> 0.136  ±0.006 ±0.014 <lb/> 35–55 0.357  ±0.006 ±0.013  0.033  ±0.005 ±0.014 <lb/> 0.278  ±0.008 ±0.022 <lb/> 55–80 0.563  ±0.007 ±0.010  0.031  ±0.007 ±0.017 <lb/> 0.447  ±0.012 ±0.022 <lb/> 80–120 0.716  ±0.010 ±0.009  0.029  ±0.010 ±0.017 <lb/> 0.583  ±0.017 ±0.037 <lb/> 120–200 0.834  ±0.015 ±0.014  0.002  ±0.015 ±0.013 <lb/> 0.741  ±0.029 ±0.043 <lb/> &gt;200  0.928  ±0.035 ±0.015 −0.020 ±0.032 ±0.012 <lb/> 0.689  ±0.068 ±0.035 <lb/> q  T [GeV] <lb/> A  3  ±δ  stat  ±δ  syst <lb/> A  4  ±δ  stat  ±δ  syst  A  0  −  A  2  ±δ  stat  ±δ  syst <lb/> 0–10 <lb/>0.007  ±0.002 ±0.004  0.020  ±0.002 ±0.002 <lb/> 0.011  ±0.005 ±0.009 <lb/> 10–20 0.003  ±0.002 ±0.003  0.013  ±0.003 ±0.002 <lb/> 0.032  ±0.006 ±0.011 <lb/> 20–35 0.006  ±0.003 ±0.003  0.015  ±0.003 ±0.003 <lb/> 0.043  ±0.007 ±0.016 <lb/> 35–55 0.005  ±0.004 ±0.005  0.021  ±0.004 ±0.004 <lb/> 0.079  ±0.010 ±0.018 <lb/> 55–80 0.009  ±0.006 ±0.006  0.002  ±0.006 ±0.004 <lb/> 0.116  ±0.014 ±0.022 <lb/> 80–120 0.033  ±0.008 ±0.010  0.019  ±0.008 ±0.005 <lb/> 0.133  ±0.019 ±0.032 <lb/> 120–200 0.008  ±0.014 ±0.010  0.010  ±0.012 ±0.007 <lb/> 0.093  ±0.031 ±0.031 <lb/> &gt;200  0.101  ±0.031 ±0.016  0.029  ±0.026 ±0.010 <lb/> 0.239  ±0.072 ±0.028 <lb/> Table 2: The five angular coefficients A  0 to A  4 and A  0  −  A  2 in bins of q  T for 1  &lt; |y| &lt;  2.1. <lb/> q  T [GeV] <lb/> A  0  ±δ  stat  ±δ  syst <lb/> A  1  ±δ  stat  ±δ  syst <lb/> A  2  ±δ  stat  ±δ  syst <lb/> 0–10 <lb/>0.032  ±0.005 ±0.010  0.002  ±0.003 ±0.007 <lb/> 0.019  ±0.005 ±0.006 <lb/> 10–20 0.077  ±0.006 ±0.009  0.018  ±0.004 ±0.006 <lb/> 0.038  ±0.005 ±0.007 <lb/> 20–35 0.179  ±0.008 ±0.013  0.038  ±0.005 ±0.008 <lb/> 0.129  ±0.006 ±0.016 <lb/> 35–55 0.385  ±0.011 ±0.017  0.063  ±0.007 ±0.011 <lb/> 0.260  ±0.009 ±0.024 <lb/> 55–80 0.554  ±0.013 ±0.015  0.066  ±0.011 ±0.016 <lb/> 0.448  ±0.014 ±0.021 <lb/> 80–120 0.737  ±0.015 ±0.014  0.059  ±0.015 ±0.019 <lb/> 0.587  ±0.021 ±0.031 <lb/> 120–200 0.860  ±0.020 ±0.012  0.064  ±0.021 ±0.018 <lb/> 0.758  ±0.035 ±0.035 <lb/> &gt;200  0.876  ±0.045 ±0.020  0.040  ±0.044 ±0.020 <lb/> 0.864  ±0.087 ±0.041 <lb/> q  T [GeV] <lb/> A  3  ±δ  stat  ±δ  syst <lb/> A  4  ±δ  stat  ±δ  syst  A  0  −  A  2  ±δ  stat  ±δ  syst <lb/> 0–10 <lb/>0.009  ±0.002 ±0.005  0.076  ±0.003 ±0.004 <lb/> 0.013  ±0.007 ±0.011 <lb/> 10–20 0.003  ±0.002 ±0.004  0.072  ±0.004 ±0.005 <lb/> 0.039  ±0.008 ±0.011 <lb/> 20–35 0.012  ±0.003 ±0.006  0.044  ±0.005 ±0.007 <lb/> 0.051  ±0.010 ±0.017 <lb/> 35–55 0.012  ±0.005 ±0.008  0.052  ±0.007 ±0.009 <lb/> 0.124  ±0.014 ±0.021 <lb/> 55–80 0.036  ±0.007 ±0.018  0.052  ±0.009 ±0.008 <lb/> 0.106  ±0.019 ±0.019 <lb/> 80–120 0.074  ±0.010 ±0.028  0.074  ±0.011 ±0.014 <lb/> 0.150  ±0.025 ±0.028 <lb/> 120–200 0.121  ±0.017 ±0.029  0.056  ±0.016 ±0.017 <lb/> 0.102  ±0.039 ±0.031 <lb/> &gt;200  0.181  ±0.041 ±0.027  0.005  ±0.034 ±0.017 <lb/> 0.012  ±0.090 ±0.039 <lb/></body>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<body> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 100 150 200 250 300 <lb/> 0 <lb/> A <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> Data <lb/>MadGraph <lb/>Powheg <lb/>FEWZ,NNLO <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 100 150 200 250 300 <lb/> 1 <lb/> A <lb/> -0.04 <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> Data <lb/>MadGraph <lb/>Powheg <lb/>FEWZ,NNLO <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 100 150 200 250 300 <lb/> 2 <lb/> A <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> Data <lb/>MadGraph <lb/>Powheg <lb/>FEWZ,NNLO <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 100 150 200 250 300 <lb/> 3 <lb/> A <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.14 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> Data <lb/>MadGraph <lb/>Powheg <lb/>FEWZ,NNLO <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 100 150 200 250 300 <lb/> 4 <lb/> A <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.06 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> Data <lb/>MadGraph <lb/>Powheg <lb/>FEWZ,NNLO <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 100 150 200 250 300 <lb/> ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> A <lb/> -<lb/> 0 <lb/> A <lb/> ( <lb/> -0.05 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.3 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> Data <lb/>MadGraph <lb/>Powheg <lb/>FEWZ,NNLO <lb/> Figure 3: Comparison of the five angular coefficients A  i  and A  0  −  A  2 measured in the Collins– <lb/>Soper frame in bins of q  T for  |y| &lt;  1. The circles show the measured results. The vertical bars <lb/>represent the statistical uncertainties and the boxes the systematic uncertainties of the measure-<lb/>ment. The triangles show the predictions from MADGRAPH, the diamonds from POWHEG, and <lb/>the crosses from FEWZ at NNLO. The boxes at the FEWZ values indicate the PDF uncertainties. <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 100 150 200 250 300 <lb/> 0 <lb/> A <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> Data <lb/>MadGraph <lb/>Powheg <lb/>FEWZ,NNLO <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 100 150 200 250 300 <lb/> 1 <lb/> A <lb/> -0.02 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.14 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> Data <lb/>MadGraph <lb/>Powheg <lb/>FEWZ,NNLO <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 100 150 200 250 300 <lb/> 2 <lb/> A <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> Data <lb/>MadGraph <lb/>Powheg <lb/>FEWZ,NNLO <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 100 150 200 250 300 <lb/> 3 <lb/> A <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> Data <lb/>MadGraph <lb/>Powheg <lb/>FEWZ,NNLO <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 100 150 200 250 300 <lb/> 4 <lb/> A <lb/> -0.02 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.12 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> Data <lb/>MadGraph <lb/>Powheg <lb/>FEWZ,NNLO <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 100 150 200 250 300 <lb/> ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> A <lb/> -<lb/> 0 <lb/> A <lb/> ( <lb/> -0.05 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.35 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> Data <lb/>MadGraph <lb/>Powheg <lb/>FEWZ,NNLO <lb/> Figure 4: Comparison of the five angular coefficients and A  0  −  A  2 under the same conditions <lb/>as Fig. 3, for the rapidity bin 1  &lt; |y| &lt;  2.1. <lb/>of Education, Youth and Sports (MEYS) of the Czech Republic; the Council of Science and In-<lb/>dustrial Research, India; the HOMING PLUS program of the Foundation for Polish Science, <lb/>cofinanced from European Union, Regional Development Fund; the Compagnia di San Paolo <lb/>(Torino); the Consorzio per la Fisica (Trieste); MIUR project 20108T4XTM (Italy); the Thalis <lb/>and Aristeia programs cofinanced by EU-ESF and the Greek NSRF; and the National Priorities <lb/>Research Program by Qatar National Research Fund. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote"> References <lb/></note>

			<page> 9 <lb/></page>

			<body> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 100 150 200 250 300 <lb/> 0 <lb/> A <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> |&lt;1 <lb/> y <lb/> | <lb/>|&lt;2.1 <lb/> y <lb/> 1&lt;| <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 100 150 200 250 300 <lb/> 1 <lb/> A <lb/> -0.04 <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> |&lt;1 <lb/> y <lb/> | <lb/>|&lt;2.1 <lb/> y <lb/> 1&lt;| <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 100 150 200 250 300 <lb/> 2 <lb/> A <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> |&lt;1 <lb/> y <lb/> | <lb/>|&lt;2.1 <lb/> y <lb/> 1&lt;| <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 100 150 200 250 300 <lb/> 3 <lb/> A <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> |&lt;1 <lb/> y <lb/> | <lb/>|&lt;2.1 <lb/> y <lb/> 1&lt;| <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 100 150 200 250 300 <lb/> 4 <lb/> A <lb/> -0.02 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.12 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> |&lt;1 <lb/> y <lb/> | <lb/>|&lt;2.1 <lb/> y <lb/> 1&lt;| <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> q <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 100 150 200 250 300 <lb/> ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> A <lb/> -<lb/> 0 <lb/> A <lb/> ( <lb/> -0.05 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.3 <lb/> (8TeV) <lb/> -1 <lb/> 19.7 fb <lb/> CMS <lb/> |&lt;1 <lb/> y <lb/> | <lb/>|&lt;2.1 <lb/> y <lb/> 1&lt;| <lb/> Figure 5: Comparison of the five angular coefficients A  i  and A  0  −  A  2 measured in the Collins– <lb/>Soper frame in bins of q  T between  |y| &lt;  1 (circles) and 1  &lt; |y| &lt;  2.1 (triangles). The vertical <lb/>bars represent the statistical uncertainties and the boxes the systematic uncertainties of the <lb/>measurement. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] J. C. Collins and D. E. Soper, &quot; Angular distribution of dileptons in high-energy hadron <lb/>collisions &quot; , Phys. Rev. D 16 (1977) 2219, doi:10.1103/PhysRevD.16.2219. <lb/> [2] CDF Collaboration, &quot; First Measurement of the Angular Coefficients of Drell-Yan e  +  e  − <lb/> pairs in the Z Mass Region from p ¯ <lb/>p Collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 1.96 TeV &quot; , Phys. Rev. Lett. 106 <lb/> (2011) 241801, doi:10.1103/PhysRevLett.106.241801, arXiv:1103.5699. <lb/> [3] J. C. Collins, &quot; Simple Prediction of Quantum Chromodynamics for Angular Distribution <lb/>of Dileptons in Hadron Collisions &quot; , Phys. Rev. Lett. 42 (1979) 291, <lb/> doi:10.1103/PhysRevLett.42.291. <lb/> [4] D. Boer and W. Vogelsang, &quot; Drell-Yan lepton angular distribution at small transverse <lb/>momentum &quot; , Phys. Rev. D 74 (2006) 014004, doi:10.1103/PhysRevD.74.014004, <lb/>arXiv:hep-ph/0604177. <lb/> [5] E. L. Berger, J.-W. Qiu, and R. A. Rodriguez-Pedraza, &quot; Angular distribution of leptons <lb/>from the decay of massive vector bosons &quot; , Phys. Lett. B 656 (2007) 74, <lb/> doi:10.1016/j.physletb.2007.09.008, arXiv:0707.3150. <lb/> [6] A. Bodek, &quot; A simple event weighting technique for optimizing the measurement of the <lb/>forward-backward asymmetry of Drell-Yan dilepton pairs at hadron colliders &quot; , Eur. Phys. <lb/>J. C 67 (2010) 321, doi:10.1140/epjc/s10052-010-1287-5, arXiv:0911.2850. <lb/> [7] J. Lindfors, &quot; Angular Distribution of Large q  T Muon Pairs in Different Reference <lb/>Frames &quot; , Physica Scripta 20 (1979) 19, doi:10.1088/0031-8949/20/1/003. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> References <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> [8] C. S. Lam and W.-K. Tung, &quot; Structure function relations at large transverse momenta in <lb/>Lepton-pair production processes &quot; , Phys. Lett. B 80 (1979) 228, <lb/> doi:10.1016/0370-2693(79)90204-1. <lb/> [9] P. Faccioli, C. Lourenco, and J. Seixas, &quot; Rotation-Invariant Relations in Vector Meson <lb/>Decays into Fermion Pairs &quot; , Phys. Rev. Lett. 105 (2010) 061601, <lb/> doi:10.1103/PhysRevLett.105.061601, arXiv:1005.2601. <lb/> [10] P. Faccioli, C. Lourenco, J. Seixas, and H. K. Woehri, &quot; Model-independent constraints on <lb/>the shape parameters of dilepton angular distributions &quot; , Phys. Rev. D 83 (2011) 056008, <lb/> doi:10.1103/PhysRevD.83.056008, arXiv:1102.3946. <lb/> [11] CMS Collaboration, &quot; Measurement of the Polarization of W Bosons with Large <lb/>Transverse Momenta in W+Jets Events at the LHC &quot; , Phys. Rev. Lett. 107 (2011) 021802, <lb/> doi:10.1103/PhysRevLett.107.021802, arXiv:1104.3829. <lb/> [12] ATLAS Collaboration, &quot; Measurement of the polarisation of W bosons produced with <lb/>large transverse momentum in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  =  7 TeV with the ATLAS experiment &quot; , <lb/> Eur. Phys. J. C 72 (2012) 2001, doi:10.1140/epjc/s10052-012-2001-6, <lb/>arXiv:1203.2165. <lb/> [13] Z. Bern et al., &quot; Left-handed W bosons at the LHC &quot; , Phys. Rev. D 84 (2011) 034008, <lb/> doi:10.1103/PhysRevD.84.034008, arXiv:1103.5445. <lb/> [14] R. Gavin, Y. Li, F. Petriello, and S. Quackenbush, &quot; FEWZ 2.0: A code for hadronic Z <lb/>production at next-to-next-to-leading order &quot; , Comput. Phys. Commun. 182 (2011) 2388, <lb/> doi:10.1016/j.cpc.2011.06.008, arXiv:1011.3540. <lb/> [15] P. Nason, &quot; A new method for combining NLO QCD with shower Monte Carlo <lb/>algorithms &quot; , JHEP 11 (2004) 040, doi:10.1088/1126-6708/2004/11/040, <lb/>arXiv:hep-ph/0409146. <lb/> [16] S. Frixione, P. Nason, and C. Oleari, &quot; Matching NLO QCD computations with parton <lb/>shower simulations: the POWHEG method &quot; , JHEP 11 (2007) 070, <lb/> doi:10.1088/1126-6708/2007/11/070, arXiv:0709.2092. <lb/> [17] S. Alioli, P. Nason, C. Oleari, and E. Re, &quot; A general framework for implementing NLO <lb/>calculations in shower Monte Carlo programs: the POWHEG BOX &quot; , JHEP 06 (2010) 043, <lb/> doi:10.1007/JHEP06(2010)043, arXiv:1002.2581. <lb/> [18] S. Alioli, P. Nason, C. Oleari, and E. Re, &quot; NLO vector-boson production matched with <lb/>shower in POWHEG &quot; , JHEP 07 (2008) 060, <lb/> doi:10.1088/1126-6708/2008/07/060, arXiv:0805.4802. <lb/> [19] J. Alwall et al., &quot; The automated computation of tree-level and next-to-leading order <lb/>differential cross sections, and their matching to parton shower simulations &quot; , JHEP 07 <lb/> (2014) 079, doi:10.1007/JHEP07(2014)079, arXiv:1405.0301. <lb/> [20] CMS Collaboration, &quot; The CMS experiment at the CERN LHC &quot; , JINST 3 (2008) S08004, <lb/> doi:10.1088/1748-0221/3/08/S08004. <lb/> [21] CMS Collaboration, &quot; Particle–Flow Event Reconstruction in CMS and Performance for <lb/>Jets, Taus, and E  miss <lb/>T <lb/> &quot; , CMS Physics Analysis Summary CMS-PAS-PFT-09-001, 2009. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote"> References <lb/></note>

			<page> 11 <lb/></page>

			<body> [22] CMS Collaboration, &quot; Commissioning of the Particle-flow Event Reconstruction with the <lb/>first LHC collisions recorded in the CMS detector &quot; , CMS Physics Analysis Summary <lb/>CMS-PAS-PFT-10-001, 2010. <lb/>[23] T. Sj östrand, S. Mrenna, and P. Z. Skands, &quot; PYTHIA 6.4 physics and manual &quot; , JHEP 05 <lb/> (2006) 026, doi:10.1088/1126-6708/2006/05/026, arXiv:hep-ph/0603175. <lb/> [24] CMS Collaboration, &quot; Study of the underlying event at forward rapidity in pp collisions <lb/>at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  =  0.9, 2.76, and 7 TeV &quot; , JHEP 04 (2013) 072, doi:10.1007/JHEP04(2013)072, <lb/>arXiv:1302.2394. <lb/> [25] J. Alwall et al., &quot; Comparative study of various algorithms for the merging of parton <lb/>showers and matrix elements in hadronic collisions &quot; , Eur. Phys. J. C 53 (2008) 473, <lb/> doi:10.1140/epjc/s10052-007-0490-5, arXiv:0706.2569. <lb/> [26] J. Pumplin et al., &quot; New generation of parton distributions with uncertainties from global <lb/>QCD analysis &quot; , JHEP 07 (2002) 012, doi:10.1088/1126-6708/2002/07/012, <lb/>arXiv:hep-ph/0201195. <lb/> [27] H.-L. Lai et al., &quot; New parton distributions for collider physics &quot; , Phys. Rev. D 82 (2010) <lb/>074024, doi:10.1103/PhysRevD.82.074024, arXiv:1007.2241. <lb/> [28] S. Alioli, P. Nason, C. Oleari, and E. Re, &quot; NLO single-top production matched with <lb/>shower in POWHEG: s-and t-channel contributions &quot; , JHEP 09 (2009) 111, <lb/> doi:10.1007/JHEP02(2010)011, arXiv:0907.4076. <lb/> [29] E. Re, &quot; Single-top Wt-channel production matched with parton showers using the <lb/>POWHEG method &quot; , Eur. Phys. J. C 71 (2011) 1547, <lb/> doi:10.1140/epjc/s10052-011-1547-z, arXiv:1009.2450. <lb/> [30] M. Czakon, P. Fiedler, and A. Mitov, &quot; Total Top-Quark Pair-Production Cross Section at <lb/>Hadron Colliders Through O(α  4 <lb/> S  ) &quot; ,  Phys. Rev. Lett. 110 (2013) 252004, <lb/> doi:10.1103/PhysRevLett.110.252004, arXiv:1303.6254. <lb/> [31] N. Kidonakis, &quot; Differential and total cross sections for top pair and single top <lb/>production &quot; , in XX Int. Workshop on Deep-Inelastic Scattering and Related Subjects, p. 831. <lb/>Bonn, Germany, 2012. arXiv:1205.3453. <lb/>doi:10.3204/DESY-PROC-2012-02/251. <lb/> [32] GEANT4 Collaboration, &quot; GEANT4: A simulation toolkit &quot; , Nucl. Instrum. Meth. A 506 <lb/> (2003) 250, doi:10.1016/S0168-9002(03)01368-8. <lb/> [33] CMS Collaboration, &quot; Performance of CMS muon reconstruction in pp collision events at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  =  7 TeV &quot; , JINST 7 (2012) P10002, doi:10.1088/1748-0221/7/10/P10002, <lb/>arXiv:1206.4071. <lb/> [34] A. Bodek et al., &quot; Extracting muon momentum scale corrections for hadron collider <lb/>experiments &quot; , Eur. Phys. J. C 72 (2012) 2194, <lb/> doi:10.1140/epjc/s10052-012-2194-8, arXiv:1208.3710. <lb/> [35] CMS Collaboration, &quot; Measurements of inclusive W and Z cross sections in pp collisions <lb/>at <lb/> √ <lb/> s  =  7 TeV &quot; , JHEP 01 (2011) 080, doi:10.1007/JHEP01(2011)080, <lb/>arXiv:1012.2466. <lb/></body>

			<page> 12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> References <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> [36] E. Mirkes and J. Ohnemus, &quot; Angular distributions of Drell-Yan lepton pairs at the <lb/>Fermilab Tevatron: Order α  2 <lb/> S  corrections and Monte Carlo studies &quot; , Phys. Rev. D 51 <lb/> (1995) 4891, doi:10.1103/PhysRevD.51.4891, arXiv:hep-ph/9412289. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 13 <lb/></page>

			<front> A The CMS Collaboration <lb/> Yerevan Physics Institute, Yerevan, Armenia <lb/> V. Khachatryan, A.M. Sirunyan, A. Tumasyan <lb/> Institut f ¨ <lb/>ur Hochenergiephysik der OeAW, Wien, Austria <lb/> W. Adam, T. Bergauer, M. Dragicevic, J. Er ö, M. Friedl, R. Fr ühwirth 1 , V.M. Ghete, C. Hartl, <lb/>N. H ¨ <lb/>ormann, J. Hrubec, M. Jeitler 1 , W. Kiesenhofer, V. Kn ünz, M. Krammer 1 , I. Krätschmer, <lb/>D. Liko, I. Mikulec, D. Rabady 2 , B. Rahbaran, H. Rohringer, J. Schieck, R. Sch öfbeck, J. Strauss, <lb/>W. Treberer-Treberspurg, W. Waltenberger, C.-E. Wulz 1 <lb/> National Centre for Particle and High Energy Physics, Minsk, Belarus <lb/> V. Mossolov, N. Shumeiko, J. Suarez Gonzalez <lb/> Universiteit Antwerpen, Antwerpen, Belgium <lb/> S. Alderweireldt, S. Bansal, T. Cornelis, E.A. De Wolf, X. Janssen, A. Knutsson, J. Lauwers, <lb/>S. Luyckx, S. Ochesanu, R. Rougny, M. Van De Klundert, H. Van Haevermaet, P. Van Mechelen, <lb/>N. Van Remortel, A. Van Spilbeeck <lb/> Vrije Universiteit Brussel, Brussel, Belgium <lb/> F. Blekman, S. Blyweert, J. D&apos;Hondt, N. Daci, N. Heracleous, J. Keaveney, S. Lowette, M. Maes, <lb/>A. Olbrechts, Q. Python, D. Strom, S. Tavernier, W. Van Doninck, P. Van Mulders, G.P. Van <lb/>Onsem, I. Villella <lb/> Université Libre de Bruxelles, Bruxelles, Belgium <lb/> C. Caillol, B. Clerbaux, G. De Lentdecker, D. Dobur, G. Fasanella, L. Favart, A.P.R. Gay, <lb/>A. Grebenyuk, A. Léonard, A. Mohammadi, L. Perì e 2 , A. Randle-conde, T. Reis, T. Seva, <lb/>L. Thomas, C. Vander Velde, P. Vanlaer, J. Wang, F. Zenoni <lb/> Ghent University, Ghent, Belgium <lb/> V. Adler, K. Beernaert, L. Benucci, A. Cimmino, S. Costantini, S. Crucy, A. Fagot, G. Garcia, <lb/>J. Mccartin, A.A. Ocampo Rios, D. Poyraz, D. Ryckbosch, S. Salva Diblen, M. Sigamani, <lb/>N. Strobbe, F. Thyssen, M. Tytgat, E. Yazgan, N. Zaganidis <lb/> Université Catholique de Louvain, Louvain-la-Neuve, Belgium <lb/> S. Basegmez, C. Beluffi 3 , G. Bruno, R. Castello, A. Caudron, L. Ceard, G.G. Da Silveira, <lb/>C. Delaere, T. du Pree, D. Favart, L. Forthomme, A. Giammanco 4 , J. Hollar, A. Jafari, P. Jez, <lb/>M. Komm, V. Lemaitre, C. Nuttens, D. Pagano, L. Perrini, A. Pin, K. Piotrzkowski, A. Popov 5 , <lb/>L. Quertenmont, M. Selvaggi, M. Vidal Marono <lb/> Université de Mons, Mons, Belgium <lb/> N. Beliy, T. Caebergs, E. Daubie, G.H. Hammad <lb/> Centro Brasileiro de Pesquisas Fisicas, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil <lb/> W.L. Aldá J ´ <lb/>unior, G.A. Alves, L. Brito, M. Correa Martins Junior, T. Dos Reis Martins, J. Molina, <lb/>C. Mora Herrera, M.E. Pol, P. Rebello Teles <lb/> Universidade do Estado do Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil <lb/> E. Belchior Batista Das Chagas, W. Carvalho, J. Chinellato 6 , A. Cust ódio, E.M. Da Costa, <lb/>D. De Jesus Damiao, C. De Oliveira Martins, S. Fonseca De Souza, L.M. Huertas Guativa, <lb/>H. Malbouisson, D. Matos Figueiredo, L. Mundim, H. Nogima, W.L. Prado Da Silva, <lb/>J. Santaolalla, A. Santoro, A. Sznajder, E.J. Tonelli Manganote 6 , A. Vilela Pereira <lb/></front>

			<page> 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A The CMS Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<front> Universidade Estadual Paulista  a  , Universidade Federal do ABC  b  , São Paulo, Brazil <lb/> C.A. Bernardes  b  , S. Dogra  a  , T.R. Fernandez Perez Tomei  a  , E.M. Gregores  b  , P.G. Mercadante  b  , <lb/>S.F. Novaes  a  , Sandra S. Padula  a <lb/> Institute for Nuclear Research and Nuclear Energy, Sofia, Bulgaria <lb/> A. Aleksandrov, V. Genchev 2 , R. Hadjiiska, P. Iaydjiev, A. Marinov, S. Piperov, M. Rodozov, <lb/>S. Stoykova, G. Sultanov, M. Vutova <lb/> University of Sofia, Sofia, Bulgaria <lb/> A. Dimitrov, I. Glushkov, L. Litov, B. Pavlov, P. Petkov <lb/> Institute of High Energy Physics, Beijing, China <lb/> J.G. Bian, G.M. Chen, H.S. Chen, M. Chen, T. Cheng, R. Du, C.H. Jiang, R. Plestina 7 , F. Romeo, <lb/>J. Tao, Z. Wang <lb/> State Key Laboratory of Nuclear Physics and Technology, Peking University, Beijing, China <lb/> C. Asawatangtrakuldee, Y. Ban, S. Liu, Y. Mao, S.J. Qian, D. Wang, Z. Xu, F. Zhang 8 , L. Zhang, <lb/>W. Zou <lb/> Universidad de Los Andes, Bogota, Colombia <lb/> C. Avila, A. Cabrera, L.F. Chaparro Sierra, C. Florez, J.P. Gomez, B. Gomez Moreno, <lb/>J.C. Sanabria <lb/> University of Split, Faculty of Electrical Engineering, Mechanical Engineering and Naval <lb/>Architecture, Split, Croatia <lb/> N. Godinovic, D. Lelas, D. Polic, I. Puljak <lb/> University of Split, Faculty of Science, Split, Croatia <lb/> Z. Antunovic, M. Kovac <lb/> Institute Rudjer Boskovic, Zagreb, Croatia <lb/> V. Brigljevic, K. Kadija, J. Luetic, D. Mekterovic, L. Sudic <lb/> University of Cyprus, Nicosia, Cyprus <lb/> A. Attikis, G. Mavromanolakis, J. Mousa, C. Nicolaou, F. Ptochos, P.A. Razis, H. Rykaczewski <lb/> Charles University, Prague, Czech Republic <lb/> M. Bodlak, M. Finger, M. Finger Jr. 9 <lb/> Academy of Scientific Research and Technology of the Arab Republic of Egypt, Egyptian <lb/>Network of High Energy Physics, Cairo, Egypt <lb/> Y. Assran 10 , A. Ellithi Kamel 11 , M.A. Mahmoud 12 , A. Radi 13,14 <lb/> National Institute of Chemical Physics and Biophysics, Tallinn, Estonia <lb/> M. Kadastik, M. Murumaa, M. Raidal, A. Tiko <lb/> Department of Physics, University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland <lb/> P. Eerola, M. Voutilainen <lb/> Helsinki Institute of Physics, Helsinki, Finland <lb/> J. Härk önen, V. Karimäki, R. Kinnunen, T. Lampén, K. Lassila-Perini, S. Lehti, T. Lindén, <lb/>P. Luukka, T. Mäenpää, T. Peltola, E. Tuominen, J. Tuominiemi, E. Tuovinen, L. Wendland <lb/> Lappeenranta University of Technology, Lappeenranta, Finland <lb/> J. Talvitie, T. Tuuva <lb/></front>

			<page> 15 <lb/></page>

			<front> DSM/IRFU, CEA/Saclay, Gif-sur-Yvette, France <lb/> M. Besancon, F. Couderc, M. Dejardin, D. Denegri, B. Fabbro, J.L. Faure, C. Favaro, F. Ferri, <lb/>S. Ganjour, A. Givernaud, P. Gras, G. Hamel de Monchenault, P. Jarry, E. Locci, J. Malcles, <lb/>J. Rander, A. Rosowsky, M. Titov, A. Zghiche <lb/> Laboratoire Leprince-Ringuet, Ecole Polytechnique, IN2P3-CNRS, Palaiseau, France <lb/> S. Baffioni, F. Beaudette, P. Busson, E. Chapon, C. Charlot, T. Dahms, O. Davignon, <lb/>L. Dobrzynski, N. Filipovic, A. Florent, R. Granier de Cassagnac, L. Mastrolorenzo, P. Miné, <lb/>I.N. Naranjo, M. Nguyen, C. Ochando, G. Ortona, P. Paganini, S. Regnard, R. Salerno, <lb/>J.B. Sauvan, Y. Sirois, C. Veelken, Y. Yilmaz, A. Zabi <lb/> Institut Pluridisciplinaire Hubert Curien, Université de Strasbourg, Université de Haute <lb/>Alsace Mulhouse, CNRS/IN2P3, Strasbourg, France <lb/> J.-L. Agram 15 , J. Andrea, A. Aubin, D. Bloch, J.-M. Brom, E.C. Chabert, N. Chanon, C. Collard, <lb/>E. Conte 15 , J.-C. Fontaine 15 , D. Gelé, U. Goerlach, C. Goetzmann, A.-C. Le Bihan, K. Skovpen, <lb/>P. Van Hove <lb/> Centre de Calcul de l&apos;Institut National de Physique Nucleaire et de Physique des Particules, <lb/>CNRS/IN2P3, Villeurbanne, France <lb/> S. Gadrat <lb/> Université de Lyon, Université Claude Bernard Lyon 1, CNRS-IN2P3, Institut de Physique <lb/>Nucléaire de Lyon, Villeurbanne, France <lb/> S. Beauceron, N. Beaupere, C. Bernet 7 , G. Boudoul 2 , E. Bouvier, S. Brochet, C.A. Carrillo <lb/>Montoya, J. Chasserat, R. Chierici, D. Contardo 2 , B. Courbon, P. Depasse, H. El Mamouni, <lb/>J. Fan, J. Fay, S. Gascon, M. Gouzevitch, B. Ille, T. Kurca, M. Lethuillier, L. Mirabito, <lb/>A.L. Pequegnot, S. Perries, J.D. Ruiz Alvarez, D. Sabes, L. Sgandurra, V. Sordini, M. Vander <lb/>Donckt, P. Verdier, S. Viret, H. Xiao <lb/> Institute of High Energy Physics and Informatization, Tbilisi State University, Tbilisi, <lb/>Georgia <lb/> Z. Tsamalaidze 9 <lb/> RWTH Aachen University, I. Physikalisches Institut, Aachen, Germany <lb/> C. Autermann, S. Beranek, M. Bontenackels, M. Edelhoff, L. Feld, A. Heister, K. Klein, <lb/>M. Lipinski, A. Ostapchuk, M. Preuten, F. Raupach, J. Sammet, S. Schael, J.F. Schulte, H. Weber, <lb/>B. Wittmer, V. Zhukov 5 <lb/> RWTH Aachen University, III. Physikalisches Institut A, Aachen, Germany <lb/> M. Ata, M. Brodski, E. Dietz-Laursonn, D. Duchardt, M. Erdmann, R. Fischer, A. G ¨ <lb/>uth, <lb/>T. Hebbeker, C. Heidemann, K. Hoepfner, D. Klingebiel, S. Knutzen, P. Kreuzer, <lb/>M. Merschmeyer, A. Meyer, P. Millet, M. Olschewski, K. Padeken, P. Papacz, H. Reithler, <lb/>S.A. Schmitz, L. Sonnenschein, D. Teyssier, S. Th üer <lb/> RWTH Aachen University, III. Physikalisches Institut B, Aachen, Germany <lb/> V. Cherepanov, Y. Erdogan, G. Fï <lb/>ugge, H. Geenen, M. Geisler, W. Haj Ahmad, F. Hoehle, <lb/>B. Kargoll, T. Kress, Y. Kuessel, A. K ¨ <lb/>unsken, J. Lingemann 2 , A. Nowack, I.M. Nugent, <lb/>C. Pistone, O. Pooth, A. Stahl <lb/> Deutsches Elektronen-Synchrotron, Hamburg, Germany <lb/> M. Aldaya Martin, I. Asin, N. Bartosik, J. Behr, U. Behrens, A.J. Bell, A. Bethani, K. Borras, <lb/>A. Burgmeier, A. Cakir, L. Calligaris, A. Campbell, S. Choudhury, F. Costanza, C. Diez Pardos, <lb/>G. Dolinska, S. Dooling, T. Dorland, G. Eckerlin, D. Eckstein, T. Eichhorn, G. Flucke, J. Garay <lb/>Garcia, A. Geiser, A. Gizhko, P. Gunnellini, J. Hauk, M. Hempel 16 , H. Jung, A. Kalogeropoulos, <lb/></front>

			<page> 16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A The CMS Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<front> O. Karacheban 16 , M. Kasemann, P. Katsas, J. Kieseler, C. Kleinwort, I. Korol, W. Lange, <lb/>J. Leonard, K. Lipka, A. Lobanov, W. Lohmann 16 , R. Mankel, I. Marfin 16 , I.-A. Melzer-<lb/>Pellmann, A.B. Meyer, G. Mittag, J. Mnich, A. Mussgiller, S. Naumann-Emme, A. Nayak, <lb/>E. Ntomari, H. Perrey, D. Pitzl, R. Placakyte, A. Raspereza, P.M. Ribeiro Cipriano, B. Roland, <lb/>E. Ron, M. ¨ <lb/>O. Sahin, J. Salfeld-Nebgen, P. Saxena, T. Schoerner-Sadenius, M. Schr öder, C. Seitz, <lb/>S. Spannagel, A.D.R. Vargas Trevino, R. Walsh, C. Wissing <lb/> University of Hamburg, Hamburg, Germany <lb/> V. Blobel, M. Centis Vignali, A.R. Draeger, J. Erfle, E. Garutti, K. Goebel, M. G ¨ <lb/>orner, J. Haller, <lb/>M. Hoffmann, R.S. H ¨ <lb/>oing, A. Junkes, H. Kirschenmann, R. Klanner, R. Kogler, T. Lapsien, <lb/>T. Lenz, I. Marchesini, D. Marconi, D. Nowatschin, J. Ott, T. Peiffer, A. Perieanu, N. Pietsch, <lb/>J. Poehlsen, T. Poehlsen, D. Rathjens, C. Sander, H. Schettler, P. Schleper, E. Schlieckau, <lb/>A. Schmidt, M. Seidel, V. Sola, H. Stadie, G. Steinbr ück, H. Tholen, D. Troendle, E. Usai, <lb/>L. Vanelderen, A. Vanhoefer <lb/> Institut f ¨ <lb/>ur Experimentelle Kernphysik, Karlsruhe, Germany <lb/> M. Akbiyik, C. Barth, C. Baus, J. Berger, C. B ¨ <lb/>oser, E. Butz, T. Chwalek, W. De Boer, <lb/>A. Descroix, A. Dierlamm, M. Feindt, F. Frensch, M. Giffels, A. Gilbert, F. Hartmann 2 , T. Hauth, <lb/>U. Husemann, I. Katkov 5 , A. Kornmayer 2 , P. Lobelle Pardo, M.U. Mozer, T. M ¨ <lb/>uller, Th. M ¨ <lb/>uller, <lb/>A. N ¨ <lb/>urnberg, G. Quast, K. Rabbertz, S. R ¨ <lb/>ocker, H.J. Simonis, F.M. Stober, R. Ulrich, J. Wagner-<lb/>Kuhr, S. Wayand, T. Weiler, C. W ¨ <lb/>ohrmann, R. Wolf <lb/> Institute of Nuclear and Particle Physics (INPP), NCSR Demokritos, Aghia Paraskevi, <lb/>Greece <lb/> G. Anagnostou, G. Daskalakis, T. Geralis, V.A. Giakoumopoulou, A. Kyriakis, D. Loukas, <lb/>A. Markou, C. Markou, A. Psallidas, I. Topsis-Giotis <lb/> University of Athens, Athens, Greece <lb/> A. Agapitos, S. Kesisoglou, A. Panagiotou, N. Saoulidou, E. Stiliaris, E. Tziaferi <lb/> University of Ioánnina, Ioánnina, Greece <lb/> X. Aslanoglou, I. Evangelou, G. Flouris, C. Foudas, P. Kokkas, N. Manthos, I. Papadopoulos, <lb/>E. Paradas, J. Strologas <lb/> Wigner Research Centre for Physics, Budapest, Hungary <lb/> G. Bencze, C. Hajdu, P. Hidas, D. Horvath 17 , F. Sikler, V. Veszpremi, G. Vesztergombi 18 , <lb/>A.J. Zsigmond <lb/> Institute of Nuclear Research ATOMKI, Debrecen, Hungary <lb/> N. Beni, S. Czellar, J. Karancsi 19 , J. Molnar, J. Palinkas, Z. Szillasi <lb/> University of Debrecen, Debrecen, Hungary <lb/> A. Makovec, P. Raics, Z.L. Trocsanyi, B. Ujvari <lb/> National Institute of Science Education and Research, Bhubaneswar, India <lb/> S.K. Swain <lb/> Panjab University, Chandigarh, India <lb/> S.B. Beri, V. Bhatnagar, R. Gupta, U.Bhawandeep, A.K. Kalsi, M. Kaur, R. Kumar, M. Mittal, <lb/>N. Nishu, J.B. Singh <lb/> University of Delhi, Delhi, India <lb/> Ashok Kumar, Arun Kumar, S. Ahuja, A. Bhardwaj, B.C. Choudhary, A. Kumar, S. Malhotra, <lb/>M. Naimuddin, K. Ranjan, V. Sharma <lb/></front>

			<page> 17 <lb/></page>

			<front> Saha Institute of Nuclear Physics, Kolkata, India <lb/> S. Banerjee, S. Bhattacharya, K. Chatterjee, S. Dutta, B. Gomber, Sa. Jain, Sh. Jain, R. Khurana, <lb/>A. Modak, S. Mukherjee, D. Roy, S. Roy Chowdhury, S. Sarkar, M. Sharan <lb/> Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Mumbai, India <lb/> A. Abdulsalam, D. Dutta, V. Kumar, A.K. Mohanty 2 , L.M. Pant, P. Shukla, A. Topkar <lb/> Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Mumbai, India <lb/> T. Aziz, S. Banerjee, S. Bhowmik 20 , R.M. Chatterjee, R.K. Dewanjee, S. Dugad, S. Ganguly, <lb/>S. Ghosh, M. Guchait, A. Gurtu 21 , G. Kole, S. Kumar, M. Maity 20 , G. Majumder, K. Mazumdar, <lb/>G.B. Mohanty, B. Parida, K. Sudhakar, N. Wickramage 22 <lb/> Indian Institute of Science Education and Research (IISER), Pune, India <lb/> S. Sharma <lb/> Institute for Research in Fundamental Sciences (IPM), Tehran, Iran <lb/> H. Bakhshiansohi, H. Behnamian, S.M. Etesami 23 , A. Fahim 24 , R. Goldouzian, M. Khakzad, <lb/>M. Mohammadi Najafabadi, M. Naseri, S. Paktinat Mehdiabadi, F. Rezaei Hosseinabadi, <lb/>B. Safarzadeh 25 , M. Zeinali <lb/> University College Dublin, Dublin, Ireland <lb/> M. Felcini, M. Grunewald <lb/> INFN Sezione di Bari  a  , Universià di Bari  b  , Politecnico di Bari  c  , Bari, Italy <lb/> M. Abbrescia  a,b  , C. Calabria  a,b  , S.S. Chhibra  a,b  , A. Colaleo  a  , D. Creanza  a,c  , L. Cristella  a,b  , N. De <lb/>Filippis  a,c  , M. De Palma  a,b  , L. Fiore  a  , G. Iaselli  a,c  , G. Maggi  a,c  , M. Maggi  a  , S. My  a,c  , S. Nuzzo  a,b  , <lb/>A. Pompili  a,b  , G. Pugliese  a,c  , R. Radogna  a,b,2  , G. Selvaggi  a,b  , A. Sharma  a  , L. Silvestris  a,2  , <lb/>R. Venditti  a,b  , P. Verwilligen  a <lb/> INFN Sezione di Bologna  a  , Universià di Bologna  b  , Bologna, Italy <lb/> G. Abbiendi  a  , C. Battilana, A.C. Benvenuti  a  , D. Bonacorsi  a,b  , S. Braibant-Giacomelli  a,b  , <lb/>L. Brigliadori  a,b  , R. Campanini  a,b  , P. Capiluppi  a,b  , A. Castro  a,b  , F.R. Cavallo  a  , G. Codispoti  a,b  , <lb/>M. Cuffiani  a,b  , G.M. Dallavalle  a  , F. Fabbri  a  , A. Fanfani  a,b  , D. Fasanella  a,b  , P. Giacomelli  a  , <lb/>C. Grandi  a  , L. Guiducci  a,b  , S. Marcellini  a  , G. Masetti  a  , A. Montanari  a  , F.L. Navarria  a,b  , <lb/>A. Perrotta  a  , A.M. Rossi  a,b  , T. Rovelli  a,b  , G.P. Siroli  a,b  , N. Tosi  a,b  , R. Travaglini  a,b <lb/> INFN Sezione di Catania  a  , Universià di Catania  b  , CSFNSM  c  , Catania, Italy <lb/> S. Albergo  a,b  , G. Cappello  a  , M. Chiorboli  a,b  , S. Costa  a,b  , F. Giordano  a,2  , R. Potenza  a,b  , <lb/>A. Tricomi  a,b  , C. Tuve  a,b <lb/> INFN Sezione di Firenze  a  , Universià di Firenze  b  , Firenze, Italy <lb/> G. Barbagli  a  , V. Ciulli  a,b  , C. Civinini  a  , R. D&apos;Alessandro  a,b  , E. Focardi  a,b  , E. Gallo  a  , S. Gonzi  a,b  , <lb/>V. Gori  a,b  , P. Lenzi  a,b  , M. Meschini  a  , S. Paoletti  a  , G. Sguazzoni  a  , A. Tropiano  a,b <lb/> INFN Laboratori Nazionali di Frascati, Frascati, Italy <lb/> L. Benussi, S. Bianco, F. Fabbri, D. Piccolo <lb/> INFN Sezione di Genova  a  , Universià di Genova  b  , Genova, Italy <lb/> F. Ferro  a  , M. Lo Vetere  a,b  , E. Robutti  a  , S. Tosi  a,b <lb/> INFN Sezione di Milano-Bicocca  a  , Universià di Milano-Bicocca  b  , Milano, Italy <lb/> M.E. Dinardo  a,b  , S. Fiorendi  a,b  , S. Gennai  a,2  , R. Gerosa  a,b,2  , A. Ghezzi  a,b  , P. Govoni  a,b  , <lb/>M.T. Lucchini  a,b,2  , S. Malvezzi  a  , R.A. Manzoni  a,b  , A. Martelli  a,b  , B. Marzocchi  a,b,2  , D. Menasce  a  , <lb/>L. Moroni  a  , M. Paganoni  a,b  , D. front  a  , S. Ragazzi  a,b  , N. Redaelli  a  , T. Tabarelli de Fatis  a,b <lb/></front>

			<page> 18 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A The CMS Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<front> INFN Sezione di Napoli  a  , Universià di Napoli &apos;Federico II&apos;  b  , Napoli, Italy, Universià della <lb/>Basilicata  c  , Potenza, Italy, Universià G. Marconi  d  , Roma, Italy <lb/> S. Buontempo  a  , N. Cavallo  a,c  , S. Di Guida  a,d,2  , F. Fabozzi  a,c  , A.O.M. Iorio  a,b  , L. Lista  a  , <lb/>S. Meola  a,d,2  , M. Merola  a  , P. Paolucci  a,2 <lb/> INFN Sezione di Padova  a  , Universià di Padova  b  , Padova, Italy, Universià di Trento  c  , <lb/>Trento, Italy <lb/> P. Azzi  a  , N. Bacchetta  a  , D. Bisello  a,b  , R. Carlin  a,b  , P. Checchia  a  , M. Dall&apos;Osso  a,b  , T. Dorigo  a  , <lb/>U. Dosselli  a  , F. Gasparini  a,b  , U. Gasparini  a,b  , A. Gozzelino  a  , S. Lacaprara  a  , M. Margoni  a,b  , <lb/>A.T. Meneguzzo  a,b  , F. Montecassiano  a  , M. Passaseo  a  , J. Pazzini  a,b  , N. Pozzobon  a,b  , <lb/>P. Ronchese  a,b  , F. Simonetto  a,b  , E. Torassa  a  , M. Tosi  a,b  , P. Zotto  a,b  , A. Zucchetta  a,b  , G. Zumerle  a,b <lb/> INFN Sezione di Pavia  a  , Universià di Pavia  b  , Pavia, Italy <lb/> M. Gabusi  a,b  , A. Magnani  a  , S.P. Ratti  a,b  , V. Re  a  , C. Riccardi  a,b  , P. Salvini  a  , I. Vai  a  , P. Vitulo  a,b <lb/> INFN Sezione di Perugia  a  , Universià di Perugia  b  , Perugia, Italy <lb/> M. Biasini  a,b  , G.M. Bilei  a  , D. Ciangottini  a,b,2  , L. Fan ò  a,b  , P. Lariccia  a,b  , G. Mantovani  a,b  , <lb/>M. Menichelli  a  , A. Saha  a  , A. Santocchia  a,b  , A. Spiezia  a,b,2 <lb/> INFN Sezione di Pisa  a  , Universià di Pisa  b  , Scuola Normale Superiore di Pisa  c  , Pisa, Italy <lb/> K. Androsov  a,26  , P. Azzurri  a  , G. Bagliesi  a  , J. Bernardini  a  , T. Boccali  a  , G. Broccolo  a,c  , R. Castaldi  a  , <lb/>M.A. Ciocci  a,26  , R. Dell&apos;Orso  a  , S. Donato  a,c,2  , G. Fedi, F. Fiori  a,c  , L. ò a  a,c  , A. Giassi  a  , <lb/>M.T. Grippo  a,26  , F. Ligabue  a,c  , T. Lomtadze  a  , L. Martini  a,b  , A. Messineo  a,b  , C.S. Moon  a,27  , <lb/>F. Palla  a  , A. Rizzi  a,b  , A. Savoy-Navarro  a,28  , A.T. Serban  a  , P. Spagnolo  a  , P. Squillacioti  a,26  , <lb/>R. Tenchini  a  , G. Tonelli  a,b  , A. Venturi  a  , P.G. Verdini  a <lb/> INFN Sezione di Roma  a  , Universià di Roma  b  , Roma, Italy <lb/> L. Barone  a,b  , F. Cavallari  a  , G. D&apos;imperio  a,b  , D. Del Re  a,b  , M. Diemoz  a  , C. Jorda  a  , E. Longo  a,b  , <lb/>F. Margaroli  a,b  , P. Meridiani  a  , F. Micheli  a,b,2  , G. Organtini  a,b  , R. Paramatti  a  , S. Rahatlou  a,b  , <lb/>C. Rovelli  a  , F. Santanastasio  a,b  , L. Soffi  a,b  , P. Traczyk  a,b,2 <lb/> INFN Sezione di Torino  a  , Universià di Torino  b  , Torino, Italy, Universià del Piemonte <lb/>Orientale  c  , Novara, Italy <lb/> N. Amapane  a,b  , R. Arcidiacono  a,c  , S. Argiro  a,b  , M. Arneodo  a,c  , R. Bellan  a,b  , C. Biino  a  , <lb/>N. Cartiglia  a  , S. Casasso  a,b,2  , M. Costa  a,b  , R. Covarelli, A. Degano  a,b  , N. Demaria  a  , L. Finco  a,b,2  , <lb/>C. Mariotti  a  , S. Maselli  a  , G. Mazza  a  , E. Migliore  a,b  , V. Monaco  a,b  , M. Musich  a  , M.M. Obertino  a,c  , <lb/>L. Pacher  a,b  , N. Pastrone  a  , M. Pelliccioni  a  , G.L. Pinna Angioni  a,b  , A. Romero  a,b  , M. Ruspa  a,c  , <lb/>R. Sacchi  a,b  , A. Solano  a,b  , A. Staiano  a  , U. Tamponi  a <lb/> INFN Sezione di Trieste  a  , Universià di Trieste  b  , Trieste, Italy <lb/> S. Belforte  a  , V. Candelise  a,b,2  , M. Casarsa  a  , F. Cossutti  a  , G. Della Ricca  a,b  , B. Gobbo  a  , C. La <lb/>Licata  a,b  , M. Marone  a,b  , A. Schizzi  a,b  , T. Umer  a,b  , A. Zanetti  a <lb/> Kangwon National University, Chunchon, Korea <lb/> S. Chang, A. Kropivnitskaya, S.K. Nam <lb/> Kyungpook National University, Daegu, Korea <lb/> D.H. Kim, G.N. Kim, M.S. Kim, D.J. Kong, S. Lee, Y.D. Oh, H. Park, A. Sakharov, D.C. Son <lb/> Chonbuk National University, Jeonju, Korea <lb/> T.J. Kim, M.S. Ryu <lb/> Chonnam National University, Institute for Universe and Elementary Particles, Kwangju, <lb/>Korea <lb/> J.Y. Kim, D.H. Moon, S. Song <lb/></front>

			<page> 19 <lb/></page>

			<front> Korea University, Seoul, Korea <lb/> S. Choi, D. Gyun, B. Hong, M. Jo, H. Kim, Y. Kim, B. Lee, K.S. Lee, S.K. Park, Y. Roh <lb/> Seoul National University, Seoul, Korea <lb/> H.D. Yoo <lb/> University of Seoul, Seoul, Korea <lb/> M. Choi, J.H. Kim, I.C. Park, G. Ryu <lb/> Sungkyunkwan University, Suwon, Korea <lb/> Y. Choi, Y.K. Choi, J. Goh, D. Kim, E. Kwon, J. Lee, I. Yu <lb/> Vilnius University, Vilnius, Lithuania <lb/> A. Juodagalvis <lb/> National Centre for Particle Physics, Universiti Malaya, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia <lb/> J.R. Komaragiri, M.A.B. Md Ali 29 , W.A.T. Wan Abdullah <lb/> Centro de Investigacion y de Estudios Avanzados del IPN, Mexico City, Mexico <lb/> E. Casimiro Linares, H. Castilla-Valdez, E. De La Cruz-Burelo, I. Heredia-de La Cruz, <lb/>A. Hernandez-Almada, R. Lopez-Fernandez, A. Sanchez-Hernandez <lb/> Universidad Iberoamericana, Mexico City, Mexico <lb/> S. Carrillo Moreno, F. Vazquez Valencia <lb/> Benemerita Universidad Autonoma de Puebla, Puebla, Mexico <lb/> I. Pedraza, H.A. Salazar Ibarguen <lb/> Universidad Aut ónoma de San Luis Potosí, San Luis Potosí, Mexico <lb/> A. Morelos Pineda <lb/> University of Auckland, Auckland, New Zealand <lb/> D. Krofcheck <lb/> University of Canterbury, Christchurch, New Zealand <lb/> P.H. Butler, S. Reucroft <lb/> National Centre for Physics, Quaid-I-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan <lb/> A. Ahmad, M. Ahmad, Q. Hassan, H.R. Hoorani, W.A. Khan, T. Khurshid, M. Shoaib <lb/> National Centre for Nuclear Research, Swierk, Poland <lb/> H. Bialkowska, M. Bluj, B. Boimska, T. Frueboes, M. G ´ <lb/>orski, M. Kazana, K. Nawrocki, <lb/>K. Romanowska-Rybinska, M. Szleper, P. Zalewski <lb/> Institute of Experimental Physics, Faculty of Physics, University of Warsaw, Warsaw, Poland <lb/> G. Brona, K. Bunkowski, M. Cwiok, W. Dominik, K. Doroba, A. Kalinowski, M. Konecki, <lb/>J. Krolikowski, M. Misiura, M. Olszewski <lb/> Laborat ório de Instrumentação e Física Experimental de Partículas, Lisboa, Portugal <lb/> P. Bargassa, C. Beirão Da Cruz E Silva, A. Di Francesco, P. Faccioli, P.G. Ferreira Parracho, <lb/>M. Gallinaro, L. Lloret Iglesias, F. Nguyen, J. Rodrigues Antunes, J. Seixas, O. Toldaiev, <lb/>D. Vadruccio, J. Varela, P. Vischia <lb/> Joint Institute for Nuclear Research, Dubna, Russia <lb/> P. Bunin, M. Gavrilenko, I. Golutvin, A. Kamenev, V. Karjavin, V. Konoplyanikov, V. Korenkov, <lb/>A. Lanev, A. Malakhov, V. Matveev 30 , V.V. Mitsyn, P. Moisenz, V. Palichik, V. Perelygin, <lb/>S. Shmatov, V. Smirnov, E. Tikhonenko, A. Zarubin <lb/></front>

			<page> 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A The CMS Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<front> Petersburg Nuclear Physics Institute, Gatchina (St. Petersburg), Russia <lb/> V. Golovtsov, Y. Ivanov, V. Kim 31 , E. Kuznetsova, P. Levchenko, V. Murzin, V. Oreshkin, <lb/>I. Smirnov, V. Sulimov, L. Uvarov, S. Vavilov, A. Vorobyev, An. Vorobyev <lb/> Institute for Nuclear Research, Moscow, Russia <lb/> Yu. Andreev, A. Dermenev, S. Gninenko, N. Golubev, M. Kirsanov, N. Krasnikov, A. Pashenkov, <lb/>D. Tlisov, A. Toropin <lb/> Institute for Theoretical and Experimental Physics, Moscow, Russia <lb/> V. Epshteyn, V. Gavrilov, N. Lychkovskaya, V. Popov, I. Pozdnyakov, G. Safronov, S. Semenov, <lb/>A. Spiridonov, E. Vlasov, A. Zhokin <lb/> P.N. Lebedev Physical Institute, Moscow, Russia <lb/> V. Andreev, M. Azarkin 32 , I. Dremin 32 , M. Kirakosyan, A. Leonidov 32 , G. Mesyats, S.V. Rusakov, <lb/>A. Vinogradov <lb/> Skobeltsyn Institute of Nuclear Physics, Lomonosov Moscow State University, Moscow, <lb/>Russia <lb/> A. Belyaev, E. Boos, M. Dubinin 33 , L. Dudko, A. Ershov, A. Gribushin, V. Klyukhin, <lb/>O. Kodolova, I. Lokhtin, S. Obraztsov, S. Petrushanko, V. Savrin, A. Snigirev <lb/> State Research Center of Russian Federation, Institute for High Energy Physics, Protvino, <lb/>Russia <lb/> I. Azhgirey, I. Bayshev, S. Bitioukov, V. Kachanov, A. Kalinin, D. Konstantinov, V. Krychkine, <lb/>V. Petrov, R. Ryutin, A. Sobol, L. Tourtchanovitch, S. Troshin, N. Tyurin, A. Uzunian, A. Volkov <lb/> University of Belgrade, Faculty of Physics and Vinca Institute of Nuclear Sciences, Belgrade, <lb/>Serbia <lb/> P. Adzic 34 , M. Ekmedzic, J. Milosevic, V. Rekovic <lb/> Centro de Investigaciones Energéticas Medioambientales y Tecnoí <lb/>ogicas (CIEMAT), <lb/>Madrid, Spain <lb/> J. Alcaraz Maestre, E. Calvo, M. Cerrada, M. Chamizo Llatas, N. Colino, B. De La Cruz, <lb/>A. Delgado Peris, D. Domínguez Vázquez, A. Escalante Del Valle, C. Fernandez Bedoya, <lb/>J.P. Fernández Ramos, J. Flix, M.C. Fouz, P. Garcia-Abia, O. Gonzalez Lopez, S. Goy Lopez, <lb/>J.M. Hernandez, M.I. Josa, E. Navarro De Martino, A. Pérez-Calero Yzquierdo, J. Puerta Pelayo, <lb/>A. Quintario Olmeda, I. Redondo, L. Romero, M.S. Soares <lb/> Universidad Aut ónoma de Madrid, Madrid, Spain <lb/> C. Albajar, J.F. de Troc óniz, M. Missiroli, D. Moran <lb/> Universidad de Oviedo, Oviedo, Spain <lb/> H. Brun, J. Cuevas, J. Fernandez Menendez, S. Folgueras, I. Gonzalez Caballero, E. Palencia <lb/>Cortezon, J.M. Vizan Garcia <lb/> Instituto de Física de Cantabria (IFCA), CSIC-Universidad de Cantabria, Santander, Spain <lb/> J.A. Brochero Cifuentes, I.J. Cabrillo, A. Calderon, J. Duarte Campderros, M. Fernandez, <lb/>G. Gomez, A. Graziano, A. Lopez Virto, J. Marco, R. Marco, C. Martinez Rivero, F. Matorras, <lb/>F.J. Munoz Sanchez, J. Piedra Gomez, T. Rodrigo, A.Y. Rodríguez-Marrero, A. Ruiz-Jimeno, <lb/>L. Scodellaro, I. Vila, R. Vilar Cortabitarte <lb/> CERN, European Organization for Nuclear Research, Geneva, Switzerland <lb/> D. Abbaneo, E. Auffray, G. Auzinger, M. Bachtis, P. Baillon, A.H. Ball, D. Barney, A. Benaglia, <lb/>J. Bendavid, L. Benhabib, J.F. Benitez, P. Bloch, A. Bocci, A. Bonato, O. Bondu, C. Botta, <lb/>H. Breuker, T. Camporesi, G. Cerminara, S. Colafranceschi 35 , M. D&apos;Alfonso, D. d&apos;Enterria, <lb/></front>

			<page> 21 <lb/></page>

			<front> A. Dabrowski, V. Daponte, A. David, F. De Guio, A. De Roeck, S. De Visscher, E. Di Marco, <lb/>M. Dobson, M. Dordevic, B. Dorney, N. Dupont-Sagorin, A. Elliott-Peisert, G. Franzoni, <lb/>W. Funk, D. Gigi, K. Gill, D. Giordano, M. Girone, F. Glege, R. Guida, S. Gundacker, M. Guthoff, <lb/>J. Hammer, M. Hansen, P. Harris, J. Hegeman, V. Innocente, P. Janot, M.J. Kortelainen, <lb/>K. Kousouris, K. Krajczar, P. Lecoq, C. Lourenço, N. Magini, L. Malgeri, M. Mannelli, <lb/>J. Marrouche, L. Masetti, F. Meijers, S. Mersi, E. Meschi, F. Moortgat, S. Morovic, M. Mulders, <lb/>S. Orfanelli, L. Orsini, L. Pape, E. Perez, A. Petrilli, G. Petrucciani, A. Pfeiffer, M. Pimiä, <lb/>D. Piparo, M. Plagge, A. Racz, G. Rolandi 36 , M. Rovere, H. Sakulin, C. Schäfer, C. Schwick, <lb/>A. Sharma, P. Siegrist, P. Silva, M. Simon, P. Sphicas 37 , D. Spiga, J. Steggemann, B. Stieger, <lb/>M. Stoye, Y. Takahashi, D. Treille, A. Tsirou, G.I. Veres 18 , N. Wardle, H.K. W ¨ <lb/>ohri, H. Wollny, <lb/>W.D. Zeuner <lb/> Paul Scherrer Institut, Villigen, Switzerland <lb/> W. Bertl, K. Deiters, W. Erdmann, R. Horisberger, Q. Ingram, H.C. Kaestli, D. Kotlinski, <lb/>U. Langenegger, D. Renker, T. Rohe <lb/> Institute for Particle Physics, ETH Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland <lb/> F. Bachmair, L. Bäni, L. Bianchini, M.A. Buchmann, B. Casal, G. Dissertori, M. Dittmar, <lb/>M. Doneà, M. D ¨ <lb/>unser, P. Eller, C. Grab, D. Hits, J. Hoss, G. Kasieczka, W. Lustermann, <lb/>B. Mangano, A.C. Marini, M. Marionneau, P. Martinez Ruiz del Arbol, M. Masciovecchio, <lb/>D. Meister, N. Mohr, P. Musella, F. Nessi-Tedaldi, F. Pandolfi, F. Pauss, L. Perrozzi, M. Peruzzi, <lb/>M. Quittnat, L. Rebane, M. Rossini, A. Starodumov 38 , M. Takahashi, K. Theofilatos, R. Wallny, <lb/>H.A. Weber <lb/> Universität Z ¨ <lb/>urich, Zurich, Switzerland <lb/> C. Amsler 39 , M.F. Canelli, V. Chiochia, A. De Cosa, A. Hinzmann, T. Hreus, B. Kilminster, <lb/>C. Lange, J. Ngadiuba, D. Pinna, P. Robmann, F.J. Ronga, S. Taroni, Y. Yang <lb/> National Central University, Chung-Li, Taiwan <lb/> M. Cardaci, K.H. Chen, C. Ferro, C.M. Kuo, W. Lin, Y.J. Lu, R. Volpe, S.S. Yu <lb/> National Taiwan University (NTU), Taipei, Taiwan <lb/> P. Chang, Y.H. Chang, Y. Chao, K.F. Chen, P.H. Chen, C. Dietz, U. Grundler, W.-S. Hou, Y.F. Liu, <lb/>R.-S. Lu, M. Mi ñano Moya, E. Petrakou, J.f. Tsai, Y.M. Tzeng, R. Wilken <lb/> Chulalongkorn University, Faculty of Science, Department of Physics, Bangkok, Thailand <lb/> B. Asavapibhop, G. Singh, N. Srimanobhas, N. Suwonjandee <lb/> Cukurova University, Adana, Turkey <lb/> A. Adiguzel, M.N. Bakirci 40 , S. Cerci 41 , C. Dozen, I. Dumanoglu, E. Eskut, S. Girgis, <lb/>G. Gokbulut, Y. Guler, E. Gurpinar, I. Hos, E.E. Kangal 42 , A. Kayis Topaksu, G. Onengut 43 , <lb/>K. Ozdemir 44 , S. Ozturk 40 , A. Polatoz, D. Sunar Cerci 41 , B. Tali 41 , H. Topakli 40 , M. Vergili, <lb/>C. Zorbilmez <lb/> Middle East Technical University, Physics Department, Ankara, Turkey <lb/> I.V. Akin, B. Bilin, S. Bilmis, H. Gamsizkan 45 , B. Isildak 46 , G. Karapinar 47 , K. Ocalan 48 , <lb/>S. Sekmen, U.E. Surat, M. Yalvac, M. Zeyrek <lb/> Bogazici University, Istanbul, Turkey <lb/> E.A. Albayrak 49 , E. G ¨ <lb/>ulmez, M. Kaya 50 , O. Kaya 51 , T. Yetkin 52 <lb/> Istanbul Technical University, Istanbul, Turkey <lb/> K. Cankocak, F.I. Vardarlı <lb/></front>

			<page> 22 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A The CMS Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<front> National Scientific Center, Kharkov Institute of Physics and Technology, Kharkov, Ukraine <lb/> L. Levchuk, P. Sorokin <lb/> University of Bristol, Bristol, United Kingdom <lb/> J.J. Brooke, E. Clement, D. Cussans, H. Flacher, J. Goldstein, M. Grimes, G.P. Heath, H.F. Heath, <lb/>J. Jacob, L. Kreczko, C. Lucas, Z. Meng, D.M. Newbold 53 , S. Paramesvaran, A. Poll, T. Sakuma, <lb/>S. Seif El Nasr-storey, S. Senkin, V.J. Smith <lb/> Rutherford Appleton Laboratory, Didcot, United Kingdom <lb/> K.W. Bell, A. Belyaev 54 , C. Brew, R.M. Brown, D.J.A. Cockerill, J.A. Coughlan, K. Harder, <lb/>S. Harper, E. Olaiya, D. Petyt, C.H. Shepherd-Themistocleous, A. Thea, I.R. Tomalin, <lb/>T. Williams, W.J. Womersley, S.D. Worm <lb/> Imperial College, London, United Kingdom <lb/> M. Baber, R. Bainbridge, O. Buchmuller, D. Burton, D. Colling, N. Cripps, P. Dauncey, <lb/>G. Davies, A. De Wit, M. Della Negra, P. Dunne, A. Elwood, W. Ferguson, J. Fulcher, D. Futyan, <lb/>G. Hall, G. Iles, M. Jarvis, G. Karapostoli, M. Kenzie, R. Lane, R. Lucas 53 , L. Lyons, A.-<lb/>M. Magnan, S. Malik, B. Mathias, J. Nash, A. Nikitenko 38 , J. Pela, M. Pesaresi, K. Petridis, <lb/>D.M. Raymond, S. Rogerson, A. Rose, C. Seez, P. Sharp  †  , A. Tapper, M. Vazquez Acosta, <lb/>T. Virdee, S.C. Zenz <lb/> Brunel University, Uxbridge, United Kingdom <lb/> J.E. Cole, P.R. Hobson, A. Khan, P. Kyberd, D. Leggat, D. Leslie, I.D. Reid, P. Symonds, <lb/>L. Teodorescu, M. Turner <lb/> Baylor University, Waco, USA <lb/> J. Dittmann, K. Hatakeyama, A. Kasmi, H. Liu, N. Pastika, T. Scarborough, Z. Wu <lb/> The University of Alabama, Tuscaloosa, USA <lb/> O. Charaf, S.I. Cooper, C. Henderson, P. Rumerio <lb/> Boston University, Boston, USA <lb/> A. Avetisyan, T. Bose, C. Fantasia, P. Lawson, D. Rankin, C. Richardson, J. Rohlf, J. St. John, <lb/>L. Sulak, D. Zou <lb/> Brown University, Providence, USA <lb/> J. Alimena, E. Berry, S. Bhattacharya, G. Christopher, D. Cutts, Z. Demiragli, N. Dhingra, <lb/>A. Ferapontov, A. Garabedian, U. Heintz, E. Laird, G. Landsberg, Z. Mao, M. Narain, S. Sagir, <lb/>T. Sinthuprasith, T. Speer, J. Swanson <lb/> University of California, Davis, Davis, USA <lb/> R. Breedon, G. Breto, M. Calderon De La Barca Sanchez, S. Chauhan, M. Chertok, J. Conway, <lb/>R. Conway, P.T. Cox, R. Erbacher, M. Gardner, W. Ko, R. Lander, M. Mulhearn, D. Pellett, J. Pilot, <lb/>F. Ricci-Tam, S. Shalhout, J. Smith, M. Squires, D. Stolp, M. Tripathi, S. Wilbur, R. Yohay <lb/> University of California, Los Angeles, USA <lb/> R. Cousins, P. Everaerts, C. Farrell, J. Hauser, M. Ignatenko, G. Rakness, E. Takasugi, V. Valuev, <lb/>M. Weber <lb/> University of California, Riverside, Riverside, USA <lb/> K. Burt, R. Clare, J. Ellison, J.W. Gary, G. Hanson, J. Heilman, M. Ivova Rikova, P. Jandir, <lb/>E. Kennedy, F. Lacroix, O.R. Long, A. Luthra, M. Malberti, M. Olmedo Negrete, A. Shrinivas, <lb/>S. Sumowidagdo, S. Wimpenny <lb/></front>

			<page> 23 <lb/></page>

			<front> University of California, San Diego, La Jolla, USA <lb/> J.G. Branson, G.B. Cerati, S. Cittolin, R.T. D&apos;Agnolo, A. Holzner, R. Kelley, D. Klein, J. Letts, <lb/>I. Macneill, D. Olivito, S. Padhi, C. Palmer, M. Pieri, M. Sani, V. Sharma, S. Simon, M. Tadel, <lb/>Y. Tu, A. Vartak, C. Welke, F. W ¨ <lb/>urthwein, A. Yagil, G. Zevi Della Porta <lb/> University of California, Santa Barbara, Santa Barbara, USA <lb/> D. Barge, J. Bradmiller-Feld, C. Campagnari, T. Danielson, A. Dishaw, V. Dutta, K. Flowers, <lb/>M. Franco Sevilla, P. Geffert, C. George, F. Golf, L. Gouskos, J. Incandela, C. Justus, N. Mccoll, <lb/>S.D. Mullin, J. Richman, D. Stuart, W. To, C. West, J. Yoo <lb/> California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, USA <lb/> A. Apresyan, A. Bornheim, J. Bunn, Y. Chen, J. Duarte, A. Mott, H.B. Newman, C. Pena, <lb/>M. Pierini, M. Spiropulu, J.R. Vlimant, R. Wilkinson, S. Xie, R.Y. Zhu <lb/> Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, USA <lb/> V. Azzolini, A. Calamba, B. Carlson, T. Ferguson, Y. Iiyama, M. Paulini, J. Russ, H. Vogel, <lb/>I. Vorobiev <lb/> University of Colorado at Boulder, Boulder, USA <lb/> J.P. Cumalat, W.T. Ford, A. Gaz, M. Krohn, E. Luiggi Lopez, U. Nauenberg, J.G. Smith, <lb/>K. Stenson, S.R. Wagner <lb/> Cornell University, Ithaca, USA <lb/> J. Alexander, A. Chatterjee, J. Chaves, J. Chu, S. Dittmer, N. Eggert, N. Mirman, G. Nicolas <lb/>Kaufman, J.R. Patterson, A. Ryd, E. Salvati, L. Skinnari, W. Sun, W.D. Teo, J. Thom, <lb/>J. Thompson, J. Tucker, Y. Weng, L. Winstrom, P. Wittich <lb/> Fairfield University, Fairfield, USA <lb/> D. Winn <lb/> Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory, Batavia, USA <lb/> S. Abdullin, M. Albrow, J. Anderson, G. Apollinari, L.A.T. Bauerdick, A. Beretvas, J. Berryhill, <lb/>P.C. Bhat, G. Bolla, K. Burkett, J.N. Butler, H.W.K. Cheung, F. Chlebana, S. Cihangir, V.D. Elvira, <lb/>I. Fisk, J. Freeman, E. Gottschalk, L. Gray, D. Green, S. Gr ünendahl, O. Gutsche, J. Hanlon, <lb/>D. Hare, R.M. Harris, J. Hirschauer, B. Hooberman, S. Jindariani, M. Johnson, U. Joshi, B. Klima, <lb/>B. Kreis, S. Kwan  †  , J. Linacre, D. Lincoln, R. Lipton, T. Liu, R. Lopes De Sá, J. Lykken, <lb/>K. Maeshima, J.M. Marraffino, V.I. Martinez Outschoorn, S. Maruyama, D. Mason, P. McBride, <lb/>P. Merkel, K. Mishra, S. Mrenna, S. Nahn, C. Newman-Holmes, V. O&apos;Dell, O. Prokofyev, <lb/>E. Sexton-Kennedy, A. Soha, W.J. Spalding, L. Spiegel, L. Taylor, S. Tkaczyk, N.V. Tran, <lb/>L. Uplegger, E.W. Vaandering, C. Vernieri, R. Vidal, A. Whitbeck, J. Whitmore, F. Yang <lb/> University of Florida, Gainesville, USA <lb/> D. Acosta, P. Avery, P. Bortignon, D. Bourilkov, M. Carver, D. Curry, S. Das, M. De Gruttola, <lb/>G.P. Di Giovanni, R.D. Field, M. Fisher, I.K. Furic, J. Hugon, J. Konigsberg, A. Korytov, <lb/>T. Kypreos, J.F. Low, K. Matchev, H. Mei, P. Milenovic 55 , G. Mitselmakher, L. Muniz, <lb/>A. Rinkevicius, L. Shchutska, M. Snowball, D. Sperka, J. Yelton <lb/> Florida International University, Miami, USA <lb/> S. Hewamanage, S. Linn, P. Markowitz, G. Martinez, J.L. Rodriguez <lb/> Florida State University, Tallahassee, USA <lb/> A. Ackert, J.R. Adams, T. Adams, A. Askew, J. Bochenek, B. Diamond, J. Haas, S. Hagopian, <lb/>V. Hagopian, K.F. Johnson, H. Prosper, V. Veeraraghavan, M. Weinberg <lb/></front>

			<page> 24 <lb/></page>

			<front> A The CMS Collaboration <lb/> Florida Institute of Technology, Melbourne, USA <lb/> M.M. Baarmand, M. Hohlmann, H. Kalakhety, F. Yumiceva <lb/> University of Illinois at Chicago (UIC), Chicago, USA <lb/> M.R. Adams, L. Apanasevich, D. Berry, R.R. Betts, I. Bucinskaite, R. Cavanaugh, O. Evdokimov, <lb/>L. Gauthier, C.E. Gerber, D.J. Hofman, P. Kurt, C. O&apos;Brien, I.D. Sandoval Gonzalez, <lb/>C. Silkworth, P. Turner, N. Varelas, M. Zakaria <lb/> The University of Iowa, Iowa City, USA <lb/> B. Bilki 56 , W. Clarida, K. Dilsiz, M. Haytmyradov, V. Khristenko, J.-P. Merlo, H. Mermerkaya 57 , <lb/>A. Mestvirishvili, A. Moeller, J. Nachtman, H. Ogul, Y. Onel, F. Ozok 49 , A. Penzo, R. Rahmat, <lb/>S. Sen, P. Tan, E. Tiras, J. Wetzel, K. Yi <lb/> Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, USA <lb/> I. Anderson, B.A. Barnett, B. Blumenfeld, S. Bolognesi, D. Fehling, A.V. Gritsan, P. Maksimovic, <lb/>C. Martin, M. Swartz, M. Xiao <lb/> The University of Kansas, Lawrence, USA <lb/> P. Baringer, A. Bean, G. Benelli, C. Bruner, J. Gray, R.P. Kenny III, D. Majumder, M. Malek, <lb/>M. Murray, D. Noonan, S. Sanders, J. Sekaric, R. Stringer, Q. Wang, J.S. Wood <lb/> Kansas State University, Manhattan, USA <lb/> I. Chakaberia, A. Ivanov, K. Kaadze, S. Khalil, M. Makouski, Y. Maravin, L.K. Saini, <lb/>N. Skhirtladze, I. Svintradze <lb/> Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, Livermore, USA <lb/> J. Gronberg, D. Lange, F. Rebassoo, D. Wright <lb/> University of Maryland, College Park, USA <lb/> C. Anelli, A. Baden, A. Belloni, B. Calvert, S.C. Eno, J.A. Gomez, N.J. Hadley, S. Jabeen, <lb/>R.G. Kellogg, T. Kolberg, Y. Lu, A.C. Mignerey, K. Pedro, Y.H. Shin, A. Skuja, M.B. Tonjes, <lb/>S.C. Tonwar <lb/> Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, USA <lb/> A. Apyan, R. Barbieri, A. Baty, K. Bierwagen, S. Brandt, W. Busza, I.A. Cali, L. Di Matteo, <lb/>G. Gomez Ceballos, M. Goncharov, D. Gulhan, M. Klute, Y.S. Lai, Y.-J. Lee, A. Levin, <lb/>P.D. Luckey, X. Niu, C. Paus, D. Ralph, C. Roland, G. Roland, G.S.F. Stephans, K. Sumorok, <lb/>D. Velicanu, J. Veverka, T.W. Wang, B. Wyslouch, M. Yang, M. Zanetti, V. Zhukova <lb/> University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, USA <lb/> B. Dahmes, A. Gude, S.C. Kao, K. Klapoetke, Y. Kubota, J. Mans, S. Nourbakhsh, R. Rusack, <lb/>A. Singovsky, N. Tambe, J. Turkewitz <lb/> University of Mississippi, Oxford, USA <lb/> J.G. Acosta, S. Oliveros <lb/> University of Nebraska-Lincoln, Lincoln, USA <lb/> E. Avdeeva, K. Bloom, S. Bose, D.R. Claes, A. Dominguez, R. Gonzalez Suarez, J. Keller, <lb/>D. Knowlton, I. Kravchenko, J. Lazo-Flores, F. Meier, F. Ratnikov, G.R. Snow, M. Zvada <lb/> State University of New York at Buffalo, Buffalo, USA <lb/> J. Dolen, A. Godshalk, I. Iashvili, A. Kharchilava, A. Kumar, S. Rappoccio <lb/> Northeastern University, Boston, USA <lb/> G. Alverson, E. Barberis, D. Baumgartel, M. Chasco, A. Massironi, D.M. Morse, D. Nash, <lb/>T. Orimoto, R. Teixeira De Lima, D. Trocino, R.-J. Wang, D. Wood, J. Zhang <lb/></front>

			<page> 25 <lb/></page>

			<front> Northwestern University, Evanston, USA <lb/> K.A. Hahn, A. Kubik, N. Mucia, N. Odell, B. Pollack, A. Pozdnyakov, M. Schmitt, S. Stoynev, <lb/>K. Sung, M. Trovato, M. Velasco, S. Won <lb/> University of Notre Dame, Notre Dame, USA <lb/> A. Brinkerhoff, K.M. Chan, A. Drozdetskiy, M. Hildreth, C. Jessop, D.J. Karmgard, N. Kellams, <lb/>K. Lannon, S. Lynch, N. Marinelli, F. Meng, C. Mueller, Y. Musienko 30 , T. Pearson, M. Planer, <lb/>R. Ruchti, G. Smith, N. Valls, M. Wayne, M. Wolf, A. Woodard <lb/> The Ohio State University, Columbus, USA <lb/> L. Antonelli, J. Brinson, B. Bylsma, L.S. Durkin, S. Flowers, A. Hart, C. Hill, R. Hughes, <lb/>K. Kotov, T.Y. Ling, B. Liu, W. Luo, D. Puigh, M. Rodenburg, B.L. Winer, H. Wolfe, H.W. Wulsin <lb/> Princeton University, Princeton, USA <lb/> O. Driga, P. Elmer, J. Hardenbrook, P. Hebda, S.A. Koay, P. Lujan, D. Marlow, T. Medvedeva, <lb/>M. Mooney, J. Olsen, P. Piroué, X. Quan, H. Saka, D. Stickland 2 , C. Tully, J.S. Werner, <lb/>A. Zuranski <lb/> University of Puerto Rico, Mayaguez, USA <lb/> E. Brownson, S. Malik, H. Mendez, J.E. Ramirez Vargas <lb/> Purdue University, West Lafayette, USA <lb/> V.E. Barnes, D. Benedetti, D. Bortoletto, L. Gutay, Z. Hu, M.K. Jha, M. Jones, K. Jung, M. Kress, <lb/>N. Leonardo, D.H. Miller, N. Neumeister, F. Primavera, B.C. Radburn-Smith, X. Shi, I. Shipsey, <lb/>D. Silvers, A. Svyatkovskiy, F. Wang, W. Xie, L. Xu, J. Zablocki <lb/> Purdue University Calumet, Hammond, USA <lb/> N. Parashar, J. Stupak <lb/> Rice University, Houston, USA <lb/> A. Adair, B. Akgun, K.M. Ecklund, F.J.M. Geurts, W. Li, B. Michlin, B.P. Padley, R. Redjimi, <lb/>J. Roberts, J. Zabel <lb/> University of Rochester, Rochester, USA <lb/> B. Betchart, A. Bodek, P. de Barbaro, R. Demina, Y. Eshaq, T. Ferbel, M. Galanti, A. Garcia-<lb/>Bellido, P. Goldenzweig, J. Han, A. Harel, O. Hindrichs, A. Khukhunaishvili, S. Korjenevski, <lb/>G. Petrillo, M. Verzetti, D. Vishnevskiy <lb/> The Rockefeller University, New York, USA <lb/> R. Ciesielski, L. Demortier, K. Goulianos, C. Mesropian <lb/> Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey, Piscataway, USA <lb/> S. Arora, A. Barker, J.P. Chou, C. Contreras-Campana, E. Contreras-Campana, D. Duggan, <lb/>D. Ferencek, Y. Gershtein, R. Gray, E. Halkiadakis, D. Hidas, E. Hughes, S. Kaplan, <lb/>R. Kunnawalkam Elayavalli, A. Lath, S. Panwalkar, M. Park, S. Salur, S. Schnetzer, D. Sheffield, <lb/>S. Somalwar, R. Stone, S. Thomas, P. Thomassen, M. Walker <lb/> University of Tennessee, Knoxville, USA <lb/> K. Rose, S. Spanier, A. York <lb/> Texas A&amp;M University, College Station, USA <lb/> O. Bouhali 58 , A. Castaneda Hernandez, M. Dalchenko, M. De Mattia, S. Dildick, R. Eusebi, <lb/>W. Flanagan, J. Gilmore, T. Kamon 59 , V. Khotilovich, V. Krutelyov, R. Montalvo, I. Osipenkov, <lb/>Y. Pakhotin, R. Patel, A. Perloff, J. Roe, A. Rose, A. Safonov, I. Suarez, A. Tatarinov, K.A. Ulmer <lb/></front>

			<page> 26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> A The CMS Collaboration <lb/></note>

			<front> Texas Tech University, Lubbock, USA <lb/> N. Akchurin, C. Cowden, J. Damgov, C. Dragoiu, P.R. Dudero, J. Faulkner, K. Kovitanggoon, <lb/>S. Kunori, S.W. Lee, T. Libeiro, I. Volobouev <lb/> Vanderbilt University, Nashville, USA <lb/> E. Appelt, A.G. Delannoy, S. Greene, A. Gurrola, W. Johns, C. Maguire, Y. Mao, A. Melo, <lb/>M. Sharma, P. Sheldon, B. Snook, S. Tuo, J. Velkovska <lb/> University of Virginia, Charlottesville, USA <lb/> M.W. Arenton, S. Boutle, B. Cox, B. Francis, J. Goodell, R. Hirosky, A. Ledovskoy, H. Li, C. Lin, <lb/>C. Neu, E. Wolfe, J. Wood <lb/> Wayne State University, Detroit, USA <lb/> C. Clarke, R. Harr, P.E. Karchin, C. Kottachchi Kankanamge Don, P. Lamichhane, J. Sturdy <lb/> University of Wisconsin, Madison, USA <lb/> D.A. Belknap, D. Carlsmith, M. Cepeda, S. Dasu, L. Dodd, S. Duric, E. Friis, R. Hall-<lb/>Wilton, M. Herndon, A. Hervé, P. Klabbers, A. Lanaro, C. Lazaridis, A. Levine, R. Loveless, <lb/>A. Mohapatra, I. Ojalvo, T. Perry, G.A. Pierro, G. Polese, I. Ross, T. Sarangi, A. Savin, <lb/>W.H. Smith, D. Taylor, C. Vuosalo, N. Woods <lb/> †: Deceased <lb/>1: Also at Vienna University of Technology, Vienna, Austria <lb/>2: Also at CERN, European Organization for Nuclear Research, Geneva, Switzerland <lb/>3: Also at Institut Pluridisciplinaire Hubert Curien, Université de Strasbourg, Université de <lb/>Haute Alsace Mulhouse, CNRS/IN2P3, Strasbourg, France <lb/>4: Also at National Institute of Chemical Physics and Biophysics, Tallinn, Estonia <lb/>5: Also at Skobeltsyn Institute of Nuclear Physics, Lomonosov Moscow State University, <lb/>Moscow, Russia <lb/>6: Also at Universidade Estadual de Campinas, Campinas, Brazil <lb/>7: Also at Laboratoire Leprince-Ringuet, Ecole Polytechnique, IN2P3-CNRS, Palaiseau, France <lb/>8: Also at Université Libre de Bruxelles, Bruxelles, Belgium <lb/>9: Also at Joint Institute for Nuclear Research, Dubna, Russia <lb/>10: Also at Suez University, Suez, Egypt <lb/>11: Also at Cairo University, Cairo, Egypt <lb/>12: Also at Fayoum University, El-Fayoum, Egypt <lb/>13: Also at British University in Egypt, Cairo, Egypt <lb/>14: Now at Ain Shams University, Cairo, Egypt <lb/>15: Also at Université de Haute Alsace, Mulhouse, France <lb/>16: Also at Brandenburg University of Technology, Cottbus, Germany <lb/>17: Also at Institute of Nuclear Research ATOMKI, Debrecen, Hungary <lb/>18: Also at E ¨ <lb/>otv ös Loránd University, Budapest, Hungary <lb/>19: Also at University of Debrecen, Debrecen, Hungary <lb/>20: Also at University of Visva-Bharati, Santiniketan, India <lb/>21: Now at King Abdulaziz University, Jeddah, Saudi Arabia <lb/>22: Also at University of Ruhuna, Matara, Sri Lanka <lb/>23: Also at Isfahan University of Technology, Isfahan, Iran <lb/>24: Also at University of Tehran, Department of Engineering Science, Tehran, Iran <lb/>25: Also at Plasma Physics Research Center, Science and Research Branch, Islamic Azad <lb/>University, Tehran, Iran <lb/>26: Also at Universià degli Studi di Siena, Siena, Italy <lb/>27: Also at Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique (CNRS) -IN2P3, Paris, France <lb/></front>

			<page> 27 <lb/></page>

			<front> 28: Also at Purdue University, West Lafayette, USA <lb/>29: Also at International Islamic University of Malaysia, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia <lb/>30: Also at Institute for Nuclear Research, Moscow, Russia <lb/>31: Also at St. Petersburg State Polytechnical University, St. Petersburg, Russia <lb/>32: Also at National Research Nuclear University &apos;Moscow Engineering Physics <lb/>Institute&apos; (MEPhI), Moscow, Russia <lb/>33: Also at California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, USA <lb/>34: Also at Faculty of Physics, University of Belgrade, Belgrade, Serbia <lb/>35: Also at Facolà Ingegneria, Universià di Roma, Roma, Italy <lb/>36: Also at Scuola Normale e Sezione dell&apos;INFN, Pisa, Italy <lb/>37: Also at University of Athens, Athens, Greece <lb/>38: Also at Institute for Theoretical and Experimental Physics, Moscow, Russia <lb/>39: Also at Albert Einstein Center for Fundamental Physics, Bern, Switzerland <lb/>40: Also at Gaziosmanpasa University, Tokat, Turkey <lb/>41: Also at Adiyaman University, Adiyaman, Turkey <lb/>42: Also at Mersin University, Mersin, Turkey <lb/>43: Also at Cag University, Mersin, Turkey <lb/>44: Also at Piri Reis University, Istanbul, Turkey <lb/>45: Also at Anadolu University, Eskisehir, Turkey <lb/>46: Also at Ozyegin University, Istanbul, Turkey <lb/>47: Also at Izmir Institute of Technology, Izmir, Turkey <lb/>48: Also at Necmettin Erbakan University, Konya, Turkey <lb/>49: Also at Mimar Sinan University, Istanbul, Istanbul, Turkey <lb/>50: Also at Marmara University, Istanbul, Turkey <lb/>51: Also at Kafkas University, Kars, Turkey <lb/>52: Also at Yildiz Technical University, Istanbul, Turkey <lb/>53: Also at Rutherford Appleton Laboratory, Didcot, United Kingdom <lb/>54: Also at School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Southampton, Southampton, <lb/>United Kingdom <lb/>55: Also at University of Belgrade, Faculty of Physics and Vinca Institute of Nuclear Sciences, <lb/>Belgrade, Serbia <lb/>56: Also at Argonne National Laboratory, Argonne, USA <lb/>57: Also at Erzincan University, Erzincan, Turkey <lb/>58: Also at Texas A&amp;M University at Qatar, Doha, Qatar <lb/>59: Also at Kyungpook National University, Daegu, Korea </front>


	</text>
</tei>
