<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Overview of ALICE results on azimuthal correlations <lb/>using neutral-and heavy-flavor triggers <lb/> Sona Pochybova for the ALICE Collaboration <lb/> MTA Wigner RCP, 29 − 33 Konkoly-Thége Miklós street, 1121 Budapest, Hungary <lb/>E-mail: sona.pochybova@cern.ch <lb/> Abstract. The ALICE detector is dedicated to studying the properties of hot and dense <lb/>matter created in heavy-ion collisions. Among the probes used to investigate these properties <lb/>are high-momentum particles, which originate in hard-scatterings occurring before the fireball <lb/>creation. The fragments of hard scatterings interact with the hot and dense matter and via <lb/>this interaction their spectra and azimuthal distributions are modified. This is probed by <lb/>the measurement of the nuclear modification factor, where the pT spectra obtained in Pb–Pb <lb/>collisions are compared to a pp baseline. A strong suppression of charged hadrons as well <lb/>as neutral-and heavy-flavor mesons was observed at pT &gt; 4 GeV/c. Azimuthal correlations, <lb/>using high-momentum (pT &gt; 4 GeV/c) hadrons as triggers, can provide further insight into <lb/>how the presence of the medium modifies the final kinematic distributions of the particles. <lb/>Comparison with theoretical models can be used to test their predictions about the properties <lb/>of the medium. We give an overview of ALICE azimuthal-correlation measurements of neutral-<lb/>and heavy-flavor mesons with charged hadrons in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV and Pb–Pb <lb/>collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> sNN = 2.76 TeV. We also present a measurement of the π <lb/> 0  correlation with jets <lb/>in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV. <lb/></front>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/> In the high-energy heavy-ion collisions the creation of a new state of matter is expected. This <lb/>matter is the hot and dense &quot; primordial soup &quot; called the Quark-Gluon Plasma (QGP) [1]. The <lb/>ALICE (A Large Ion Collider Experiment) collaboration at the LHC is dedicated to the study of <lb/>the properties of this new state of matter [2]. To do this, a set of probes are exploited. Among <lb/>these are the high-momentum particles that were created from the fragments of high-momentum <lb/>partons produced in the early stages of the collision. These partons may travel through the <lb/>fireball probing its evolution. Partons lose energy via medium-induced gluon radiation [3, 4] or <lb/>via elastic collisions with the medium constituents [5, 6]. Once the fireball freezes out, these <lb/>partons hadronize into high-momentum particles that carry the information about the parton-<lb/>medium interaction. We can look at how the properties of these high-momentum particles <lb/>change with respect to simpler systems as pp and p–Pb collisions and obtain information about <lb/>the properties of the matter they emerged from and test our expectations. <lb/>In this work, we focus on the measurements using high-momentum π  0  and D mesons as <lb/>trigger particles. High-momentum neutral pions are experimentally identified via the 2-photon <lb/>decay channel in a wide range of momentum and can be used to scan different regions. The D <lb/> mesons consist of charm quarks, that are created in the initial stages of the collision. Due to <lb/>their large masses, they are predominantly produced in hard scatterings. The energy loss these <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> arXiv:1504.01918v1  [hep-ex] 8 Apr 2015 <lb/></note>

			<body> heavy quarks suffer, is expected to differ from light quarks and gluons. The gluon radiation at <lb/>small angles with respect to the quark direction is suppressed in heavy-quark fragmentation, <lb/>which produces a  &quot; dead-cone &quot;  around the original parton. This implies a smaller energy loss <lb/>for heavier quarks. The dead-cone effect is also present in vacuum [7]. <lb/>One of the observables sensitive to the parton-medium interaction is the Nuclear modification <lb/>factor : <lb/> R  AA  (p  T  ) = <lb/>1 <lb/> T  AA  <lb/> dN  AA  /dp  T <lb/> dσ  pp  /dp  T <lb/> , <lb/> (1) <lb/>where T  AA  is the nuclear overlap function evaluated in the Glauber model [8], proportional <lb/>to the number of binary nucleon-nucleon collisions N  coll  . By comparing the yields extracted <lb/>in heavy-ion and pp collisions, this variable tests whether the heavy-ion collision is a mere <lb/>superposition of independent nucleon-nucleon collisions. If this would be the case, the <lb/> R  AA  (p  T  ) should be 1. Previous measurements showed a yield-suppression at high momenta <lb/>for unidentified hadrons [9] as well as D mesons [10] and π  0  [11]. This suppression is generally <lb/>understood as a manifestation of the energy loss the initial partons suffer when they traverse <lb/>the QGP. <lb/>Another observable, that complements the modification of the momentum spectrum is the <lb/>per-trigger yield obtained from angular correlations: <lb/> C(∆η∆ϕ) = <lb/>1 <lb/> N  trig <lb/> dN  assoc <lb/> d∆ηd∆ϕ <lb/> . <lb/> (2) <lb/>This analysis considers hadrons with p  T  &gt; 8 GeV/c as high-momentum triggers. We take <lb/>the trigger-hadron and investigate the angular distribution of the associated hadrons in different <lb/>momentum bins. In this way, we can observe how the associated particle distributions are <lb/>modified by the presence of the medium. When a high-virtuality process occurs it produces, at <lb/>leading order, two back-to-back partons. If this process occurs close to the surface of the fireball, <lb/>one of the partons will have to travel a shorter distance through the hot and dense matter than <lb/>the other. Therefore the correlation analysis suffers a &quot; surface-bias &quot; that allows us to study <lb/>path-length dependence of the parton energy-loss. The high-momentum particles associated <lb/>with the parton close to the surface are identified as triggers and particles associated with this <lb/>parton&apos;s energy-loss appear on the near-side (∆ϕ ≈ 0). The other parton has to travel through <lb/>the fireball experiencing large energy-loss and producing associated particles on the away-side <lb/>(∆ϕ ≈ π). To quantify the modification of the particle-yields in a certain momentum interval <lb/>associated with the trigger, we construct the per-trigger yield modification factor (I  AA  ): <lb/> I  AA  (∆ϕ, p  T  ) = <lb/> Y ield(Pb–Pb) <lb/>Y ield(pp) <lb/>. <lb/> (3) <lb/>Apart from the yield-modification, one can also look at the changes in the shape of the <lb/>angular distribution of the associated particles produced along the path of the trigger. Such <lb/>measurement targets the broadening and softening of the initial parton fragmentation and is <lb/>done by measuring the widths of the near-and away-side peaks. <lb/>In the following, we present the results of the analysis on π  0  angular correlation with charged <lb/>particles (h  ±  ) in pp and Pb–Pb collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 2.76 TeV per-nucleon and π  0  -jet angular <lb/>correlations in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV. The correlations of D mesons and charged particles <lb/>in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV are compared with results from p–Pb collisions at <lb/> √ s  N N  = 5.02 <lb/>TeV and PYTHIA Monte Carlo simulations [12, 13, 14]. <lb/> 2. Analysis setup <lb/> The ALICE detector is a powerful system of sub-detectors, that was designed to investigate the <lb/>properties of QGP in a broad range of variables and kinematics. A detailed description can <lb/>be found in Ref. [15]. In the presented analysis, the following sub-detectors were used: for the <lb/>tracking and identification of the charged particles the ITS [16], TPC [17] and TOF [18] were <lb/>used covering the central pseudo-rapidity region |η| &lt; 0.9 and full azimuth ϕ = 2π. The π  0  s were <lb/>reconstructed using the EMCal [19] electromagnetic calorimeter with the acceptance |η| &lt; 0.7 <lb/>and ∆ϕ = 100  •  . In the π  0  -jet analysis, jets were reconstructed using the anti−k  T  jet-finding <lb/>algorithm [20]. For the reconstruction only charged tracks have been used in |η| &lt; 0.9 and jets <lb/>with R = 0.4 and |η| &lt; 0.5 were accepted. <lb/> 2.1. Identification of π  0 <lb/> The neutral pions were identified using the shower-shape topological analysis in the EMCal. For <lb/>energies larger than 5 − 6 GeV, the electromagnetic showers produced in the calorimeter by the <lb/>two photons from π  0  decay merge into a single large cluster of calorimeter cells (a cell is the <lb/>smallest unit of the calorimeter, with 6 × 6 cm  2  area at 4.28 m from the interaction point). By <lb/>studying the energy profile of the cluster, we can determine whether it was produced by a single <lb/>photon or if it is a superposition of two. This procedure allows us to measure π  0  s in the EMCal <lb/>up to 50 GeV. <lb/> 2.2. Identification of D mesons <lb/> For the D-meson triggered correlation analysis the D  +  , D  0  and D  * +  have been reconstructed in <lb/>three decay modes: D  0  → K  −  π  +  , D  +  → K  −  π  +  π  +  and D  *  (2010)  +  → D  0  π  0  [21]. A detailed <lb/>description of the procedure can be found in Ref. [22] and the references therein. The selection <lb/>procedure exploits the displacement of the decay vertex with respect to the primary vertex. <lb/>Kaons and pions were identified using TPC and TOF detectors and from these the D-meson <lb/> invariant mass was reconstructed. <lb/> 2.3. Setup of the correlation studies <lb/> In the correlation analysis, the triggers were associated with the unidentified hadrons and <lb/>charged jets. For each trigger-associated pair, we calculate ∆ϕ = ϕ  trig  − ϕ  assoc  and ∆η = <lb/> η  trig  − η  assoc  in the signal event. To correct for the detector ∆ϕ and ∆η acceptance, we divide <lb/>the raw (∆ϕ∆η) correlation with the mixed-event correlation. This is a correlation, that is not <lb/>physical and is constructed by taking a trigger from the signal event and correlating it with an <lb/>associated particle from another, but topologically similar event. Dividing the signal correlation <lb/>by the mixed, we obtain the pair-acceptance corrected distribution. This distribution consists of <lb/>two peaks, which sit on top of a pedestal, that is not correlated with the trigger and has different <lb/>physics origins. In these analyses, we want to only study the per-trigger yield in the peaks so <lb/>we have to subtract this pedestal. In pp collisions, the background is assumed to be flat and is <lb/>determined using Zero Yield At Minimum (ZYAM) assumption [23]. In Pb–Pb collisions, the <lb/>situation becomes more complicated, since the background is expected to be modulated by the <lb/>initial azimuthal anisotropy called elliptic flow [24]. Therefore, the background is subtracted in <lb/>the analysis of Pb–Pb data using both a flat and a flow assumption. <lb/> 3. Results and discussion <lb/> In this section, we present our results on the angular correlation analyses using π  0  and D mesons <lb/>as triggers. First, the results of π  0  -hadron and π  0  -jet correlation are shown, then, we proceed <lb/>with D-meson analyses. The plots include both systematic and statistical errors, which are not <lb/>combined but are plotted separately. <lb/> (a) <lb/> (b) <lb/> Figure 1. The π  0  -charged particle correlation: angular distribution of the per-trigger <lb/>yield for different colliding systems and different momentum of π  0  − h  ±  pairs without <lb/>background subtraction. The distributions are corrected for the pair-acceptance. Panel (a) <lb/>shows results from pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 2.76 TeV with 8.0 &lt; p <lb/> trig <lb/>T <lb/> &lt; 12.0 GeV/c and <lb/> p  assoc <lb/>T <lb/> ∈ {(0.5; 1.0), (1.0; 2.0), (2.0; 4.0), (4.0; 6.0)} GeV/c. Panel (b) shows the per-trigger yield <lb/>in Pb–Pb collisions at <lb/> √ s  NN  = 2.76 TeV. The momentum ranges of the associated pairs are <lb/> p  assoc <lb/>T <lb/> ∈ {(1.0; 2.0), (2.0; 4.0)} GeV/c and the ranges of trigger-momentum are 8.0 &lt; p <lb/> trig <lb/>T  &lt; 12.0 <lb/>GeV/c and 12.0 &lt; p <lb/> trig <lb/>T  &lt; 16.0 GeV/c at top and bottom of the figure, respectively. <lb/> 3.1. The π  0  triggered correlations <lb/> The π  0  -charged particle correlation analysis was performed in pp collisions and 10% most <lb/>central Pb–Pb collisions at a per-nucleon collision energy of 2.76 TeV. <lb/>Figure 1 shows the evolution of the angular distribution of the per-trigger yield as it changes <lb/>with the momentum of the trigger-associate pair and with colliding system from pp to Pb–Pb <lb/>collisions. The distributions are corrected for the pair-acceptance but are not corrected for the <lb/>background below the jet-peaks. We observe that with increasing momentum of the associated <lb/>particles, this background becomes suppressed and the jet peaks start to become the dominant <lb/>features in the distribution. This behavior is common to both pp and Pb–Pb systems, but is <lb/>more pronounced in the former. <lb/>Once background is subtracted and only the jet-peaks remain, the per-trigger yield is <lb/>extracted in the p  assoc <lb/>T <lb/> bins for the near-and away-side. The size of the integration range in ∆ϕ <lb/>is 0.7 and is the same on both sides. In the case of pp collisions, only the flat background <lb/>assumption was considered, whereas in the case of Pb–Pb collisions, a flow background <lb/>assumption was added. The results are shown in Figure 2. The yield decreases with momentum <lb/>of the associated tracks and is smaller on the away-side. In the Pb–Pb case, the extracted yields <lb/>are consistent for both background assumptions within errors. <lb/>To quantify the difference between the behavior of the π  0  − h  ±  correlation in pp and Pb–Pb <lb/>collisions, the I  AA  (defined by eq. 3) is calculated from the extracted yields. The p  assoc <lb/>T <lb/> dependence of this variable is shown in Figure 3. On the near-side, we observe a ≈ 20% <lb/>enhancement while on the away-side a ≈ 50% suppression. The I  AA  is independent of momentum <lb/>and background assumption within errors. The results are compared to the results of h  ±  − h  ± <lb/> (GeV/c) <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/>) <lb/> c <lb/> -1 <lb/> (GeV <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> /d <lb/> assoc <lb/> dN <lb/> trig <lb/> 1/N <lb/> -2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/> =2.76 TeV <lb/>s <lb/>pp <lb/> c <lb/> &lt; 16.0 GeV/ <lb/> trig <lb/>T <lb/> p <lb/> 8.0 &lt; <lb/>| &lt; 0.7 <lb/> ϕ <lb/> ∆ <lb/> Near side (NS) | <lb/>| &lt; 0.7 <lb/> π <lb/> -<lb/> ϕ <lb/>∆ <lb/> Away side (AS) | <lb/>NS: Flat Background <lb/>AS: Flat Background <lb/> ALICE Preliminary <lb/> ALI−PREL−79238 <lb/> (GeV/c) <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> -1 <lb/> (GeV <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> /d <lb/> assoc <lb/> dN <lb/> trig <lb/> 1/N <lb/> -2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/> =2.76 TeV <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/>Pb-Pb <lb/>0-10% <lb/> c <lb/> &lt; 16.0 GeV/ <lb/> trig <lb/>T <lb/> p <lb/> 8.0 &lt; <lb/>| &lt; 0.7 <lb/> ϕ <lb/> ∆ <lb/> Near side (NS) | <lb/>| &lt; 0.7 <lb/> π <lb/> -<lb/> ϕ <lb/>∆ <lb/> Away side (AS) | <lb/>NS: Flat Background <lb/>AS: Flat Background <lb/>NS: Flow Background <lb/>AS: Flow Background <lb/> ALICE Preliminary <lb/> ALI−PREL−79322 <lb/> Figure 2. The π  0  − h  ±  correlation: per-trigger yield on the near-and away-side as a function <lb/>of associated track momentum in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 2.76 TeV (left) and in 10% most central <lb/>Pb–Pb collisions at <lb/> √ s  NN  = 2.76 TeV (right). The background subtracted in pp collisions is <lb/>flat. In Pb–Pb collisions, the yields are compared for flat and flow background assumption. <lb/> (GeV/c) <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/> AA <lb/> I <lb/> 0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>2 <lb/>2.2 <lb/>2.4 <lb/> =2.76 TeV <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/>Pb-Pb <lb/>0-10% <lb/> c <lb/> &lt; 16.0 GeV/ <lb/> trig <lb/>T <lb/> p <lb/> 8.0 &lt; <lb/>| &lt; 0.7 <lb/> ϕ <lb/> ∆ <lb/> Near side | <lb/>Flat Background <lb/> ± <lb/> -h <lb/> 0 <lb/> π <lb/> Flat Background <lb/> ± <lb/> -h <lb/> ± <lb/> h <lb/>Flow Background <lb/> ± <lb/> -h <lb/> 0 <lb/> π <lb/> Flow Background <lb/> ± <lb/> -h <lb/> ± <lb/> h <lb/>Black points: PRL 108, 092301 (2012) <lb/> ALICE Preliminary <lb/> ALI−PREL−79136 <lb/> (GeV/c) <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/> AA <lb/> I <lb/> 0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>2 <lb/>2.2 <lb/>2.4 <lb/> =2.76 TeV <lb/> NN <lb/> s <lb/>Pb-Pb <lb/>0-10% <lb/> c <lb/> &lt; 16.0 GeV/ <lb/> trig <lb/>T <lb/> p <lb/> 8.0 &lt; <lb/>| &lt; 0.7 <lb/> π <lb/> -<lb/> ϕ <lb/>∆ <lb/> Away side | <lb/>Flat Background <lb/> ± <lb/> -h <lb/> 0 <lb/> π <lb/> Flat Background <lb/> ± <lb/> -h <lb/> ± <lb/> h <lb/>Flow Background <lb/> ± <lb/> -h <lb/> 0 <lb/> π <lb/> Flow Background <lb/> ± <lb/> -h <lb/> ± <lb/> h <lb/>Black points: PRL 108, 092301 (2012) <lb/> ALICE Preliminary <lb/> ALI−PREL−79167 <lb/> Figure 3. Per-trigger yield modification factor (I  AA  ) as a function of the p  T  of the associated <lb/>particle on the near-side (left) and away-side (right) for 10% most central Pb–Pb collisions at <lb/> √ s  NN  = 2.76 TeV. The results of the π  0  − h  ±  analysis are compared to the results of h  ±  − h  ± <lb/> analysis for a flat and a flow background assumption. <lb/>analysis [25] and are found to be consistent within errors. <lb/>The suppression on the away-side can be understood in terms of medium-induced parton <lb/>energy-loss mentioned in the introduction. It is interesting to point out, that this suppression <lb/>is smaller than the one measured by the STAR collaboration at RHIC [26] (≈ 75%). The <lb/>difference in the suppression might indicate a difference in the biases of the correlation analysis <lb/>between the two experiments. A discussion on how various biases of the experimental correlation <lb/> measurements influence the results and their interpretation can be found in [27]. Based on this, <lb/>the main contributors to the differences may be the interplay between the following effects: (i) <lb/> different &quot; surface bias &quot; of the measurement (ii) larger momentum transfer in hard-scattering <lb/>processes at LHC and (iii) change of the fraction of quarks and gluons produced in the final <lb/>state. <lb/>Due to larger collision energies, the partons created in the hard-scatterings have a higher <lb/>initial energy and it is likely for them to survive the fireball with shifted momentum even if <lb/>they have to travel through the whole length of the medium. Apart from this, even if the hard-<lb/>scattering occurs further away from the surface, the partons might be energetic enough to have <lb/>the particles produced in their fragmentation triggered in the experimental setup. Additionally, <lb/>the fraction of quarks and gluons created in the final state of hard-scatterings changed when <lb/>going from RHIC to LHC energies. While the quarks dominated in the RHIC regime, it is more <lb/>likely to produce gluons at the LHC. Gluons have a softer fragmentation, thus one can expect <lb/>them to be more prone to interact with the surrounding medium and as a result produce a large <lb/>number of particles. The higher initial parton energy combined with a softer fragmentation and <lb/>a higher probability to interact with medium may result in an apparently smaller suppression <lb/>in a given momentum range. <lb/>Looking at the near-side, the STAR collaboration measured an I  AA  consistent with unity. <lb/>The consistency with unity suggests, that very little interaction between the trigger and the <lb/>surrounding matter occurred. The presented ALICE measurement showed a clear enhancement, <lb/>indicating that the trigger has been affected by its travel through the medium. Following a <lb/>similar line of thought to the previous paragraph, one can understand this via the difference <lb/>between the kinematics of the hard-scattering processes between the RHIC and the LHC. Apart <lb/>from identifying triggers at the surface, one identifies also the ones originating inside the fireball. <lb/>These suffer the medium-induced energy-loss and are identified as triggers in a lower momentum <lb/>bin together with an abundance of particles around them, that were produced as the result of <lb/>the parton-medium interaction. The fact supporting that the difference in the I  AA  between <lb/>STAR and ALICE has the same source on the near-and away-side is that ALICE adds ≈ 20% <lb/>to both sides of the STAR result. <lb/>Other possible interpretation of this enhancement is the medium-induced softening of the <lb/>fragmentation function, discussed briefly in Ref. [25]. Hadrons in a given momentum range, <lb/>which were produced in such modified fragmentation, originate from higher-momentum partons <lb/>in Pb–Pb collisions as compared to pp. This difference between the two systems is then translated <lb/>into I  AA  &gt; 1. <lb/>To further test these ideas, one would need to conduct an analysis targeting directly the <lb/>jet-fragmentation via the measurements of hadron-jet correlations. Such measurements have <lb/>already started. The π  0  -jet correlation analysis was performed in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV. <lb/>Three trigger-momentum bins and three jet-momentum thresholds were studied. The angular <lb/>distributions of the per-trigger jet-yield are shown in Figure 4. We observe clear peaks on both <lb/>the near-and away-side. The jet-yield increases with the momentum of π  0  and decrease with <lb/>the jet-momentum threshold. <lb/>Figure 5 shows the widths of the peaks and their dependence on p <lb/> trig <lb/>T  and p  assoc <lb/>T,ch.jet  . Within <lb/>errors, the widths are independent of associated jet momentum-threshold and they exhibit a <lb/>decreasing trend with the trigger-particle momentum. <lb/>These results show that the meson is produced closer to the jet-axis as its momentum <lb/>increases. On the other hand, the width of the angular distribution seems to be independent <lb/>of jet&apos;s threshold momentum. This indicates a small jet-momentum dependence of jet-<lb/>fragmentation into π  0  s. However, it is important to mention that this measurement was done <lb/>using only charged jets, and so it is difficult to establish a direct relationship between the <lb/>charged-jet and neutral-pion momentum. A more robust claim on the jet&apos;s fragmentation into <lb/> Figure 4. Angular distribution of per-trigger jet-yield from the π  0  -jet correlation analysis in <lb/>pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV. The distributions are compared for three trigger-momentum bins: <lb/> p <lb/> trig <lb/>T,ch.jet  ∈ {(8; 12), (16; 20), (24; 36)} GeV/c. For the associated jet three momentum thresholds <lb/>are defined: p  assoc <lb/>T,ch.jet  &gt; 10 GeV/c (left), p  assoc <lb/>T,ch.jet  &gt; 20 GeV/c (middle) and p  assoc <lb/>T,ch.jet  &gt; 30 GeV/c <lb/>(right). <lb/> Figure 5. Widths of the angular distribution of per-trigger jet-yield from the π  0  -jet analysis <lb/>in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV. The widths are plotted as a function of π  0  momentum for three <lb/>associated jet-momentum thresholds: p  assoc <lb/>T,ch.jet  &gt; 10, 20, 30 GeV/c. The widths are extracted on <lb/>the near-(left) and away-side (right). <lb/> π  0  s requires a full-jet reconstruction with both the charged and the neutral part. <lb/> 3.2. D meson -charged particle azimuthal correlations <lb/> Azimuthal correlations of D mesons and charged particles were studied in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 <lb/>TeV and p–Pb collisions at <lb/> √ s  N N  = 5.02 TeV. The D mesons were identified in the range <lb/>8 &lt; p  D <lb/> T  &lt; 16 GeV/c and were correlated to unidentified charged particles with p  assoc <lb/>T <lb/> &gt; 1 <lb/>GeV/c. The per-trigger yield as a function of ∆ϕ is shown in Figure 6. The distributions are <lb/>compared to PYTHIA Monte Carlo simulations of pp collisions at corresponding center-of-mass <lb/>energies: PYTHIA 8 [13] and PYTHIA 6 with Perugia 2010 and Perugia 2011 tunes [14]. Both <lb/>pp and p–Pb results are within errors reproduced by the Monte Carlo models. <lb/>Figure 7 shows a direct comparison of angular distribution of per-trigger yield (left) and <lb/> Figure 6. The D meson -charged particle azimuthal correlations:: angular distribution of <lb/>per-trigger yield in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV (left) and p–Pb collisions at <lb/> √ s  NN  = 5.02 <lb/>TeV (right). The trigger used is a D meson with transverse momentum 8.0 &lt; p  D <lb/>T  &lt; 16 GeV/c. <lb/>The associated tracks are unidentified particles with p  assoc <lb/>T <lb/> &gt; 1.0 GeV/c. The distributions are <lb/>compared to Monte Carlo simulations of pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV in the case of pp collisions, <lb/>and <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 5.02 TeV in the case of p–Pb collisions. The PYTHIA 8 and PYTHIA 6 generators <lb/>are used, the latter implementing two tunes: Perugia 2010 and Perugia2011. <lb/> Figure 7. Comparison of D meson -charged particle correlations in pp collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 <lb/>TeV and p–Pb collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 5.02 TeV. Left: Comparison of the angular distribution <lb/>of per-trigger yield. Right: Comparison of near-side per-trigger yield as a function D-meson <lb/> momentum. <lb/>near-side yield as a function of p  D <lb/> T  (right) in pp and p–Pb collisions. The results obtained in <lb/>the two collision systems agree within errors. However, due to large uncertainties it is difficult <lb/>to draw strong conclusions about the comparison. <lb/> 4. Conclusions and final remarks <lb/> We have presented an overview of the results on the correlation-measurements with π  0  and D <lb/> mesons as high-p  T  triggers. We can conclude, that the results from π  0  -triggered correlations in <lb/>Pb–Pb collisions are consistent with the presence of hot and dense matter that causes partons <lb/>to lose energy as they travel through it. This interaction is affected by the kinematics of the <lb/>partons created in the initial stages of the collision as can be seen from the comparison of RHIC <lb/>and LHC results. A ore detailed investigation of the jet-fragmentation modification has already <lb/>begun. <lb/>In the D-meson correlation measurements, first results are available in pp and p–Pb collisions, <lb/>setting an important baseline for upcoming heavy-ion analyses. In p–Pb collisions, no indication <lb/>of hot nuclear effects were observed. In the upcoming Run II, the statistical uncertainties <lb/>are expected to significantly improve. The ITS upgrade planned for Run III should provide <lb/>an improved spatial resolution for the secondary vertex recognition, which is crucial for the <lb/>performance in heavy-flavor measurements. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> 4.1. Acknowledgments <lb/> I would like to thank the ALICE Collaboration for giving me the opportunity to present the <lb/>results. Further, I would like to thank the Wigner RCP and the OTKA grant NK 116109 for <lb/>providing necessary funding for my attendance of the 10  th  International Workshop on High-pT <lb/>Physics in the RHIC/LHC era in Nantes, France (9  th  − 12  th  September 2014). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] Bazavov A et al. Phys.Rev., D 85:054503, 2012. <lb/>[2] Alessandro B et al. J.Phys., G 32:1295–2040, 2006. <lb/>[3] Gyulassy M and Plumer M. Phys.Lett., B 243:432–438, 1990. <lb/>[4] Baier R et al. Nucl.Phys., B 484:265–282, 1997. <lb/>[5] Thoma H M and Gyulassy M. Nucl.Phys., B 351:491–506, 1991. <lb/>[6] Braaten E and Thoma M H. Phys.Rev., D 44:1298–1310, 1991. <lb/>[7] Dokshitzer Y L and Kharzeev D E. Phys.Lett., B 519:199–206, 2001. <lb/>[8] Miller M L et al. Ann.Rev.Nucl.Part.Sci., 57:205–243, 2007. <lb/>[9] Aamodt K et al. Phys.Lett., B 696:30–39, 2011. <lb/>[10] Abelev B et al. JHEP, 1209:112, 2012. <lb/>[11] Abelev B et al. Eur.Phys.J., C 74(10):3108, 2014. <lb/>[12] Mrenna S Sjostrand T and Skands P Z. JHEP, 0605:026, 2006. <lb/>[13] Sjstrand T et al. 2014. <lb/>[14] Skands P Z. Phys.Rev., D 82:074018, 2010. <lb/>[15] Aamodt K et al. JINST, 3:S08002, 2008. <lb/>[16] Aamodt K et al. JINST, 5:P03003, 2010. <lb/>[17] Alme J et al. Nucl.Instrum.Meth., A 622:316–367, 2010. <lb/>[18] Akindinov A et al. Nucl.Instrum.Meth., A 615:37–41, 2010. <lb/>[19] Bourrion O et al. JINST, 8:C01013, 2013. <lb/>[20] and Salam G P Cacciari M and Soyez G. Eur.Phys.J., C 72:1896, 2012. <lb/>[21] Nakamura K et al. J.Phys., G 37:075021, 2010. <lb/>[22] Abelev B et al. JHEP, 1201:128, 2012. <lb/>[23] Ajitanand N N et al. Phys.Rev., C 72:011902, 2005. <lb/>[24] Adler C et al. Phys.Rev.Lett., 90:032301, 2003. <lb/>[25] Aamodt K et al. Phys.Rev.Lett., 108:092301, 2012. <lb/>[26] Adams J et al. Phys.Rev.Lett., 97:162301, 2006. <lb/>[27] Renk T. Phys.Rev., C 88(5):054902, 2013. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
