<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) <lb/> CERN-PH-EP-2015-101 <lb/>LHCb-PAPER-2015-016 <lb/>April 28, 2015 <lb/> Identification of beauty and charm <lb/>quark jets at LHCb <lb/> The LHCb collaboration <lb/>  † <lb/> Abstract <lb/> Identification of jets originating from beauty and charm quarks is important for <lb/>measuring Standard Model processes and for searching for new physics. The per-<lb/>formance of algorithms developed to select b- and c-quark jets is measured using <lb/>data recorded by LHCb from proton-proton collisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV in 2011 and at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 8 TeV in 2012. The efficiency for identifying a b(c) jet is about 65%(25%) with <lb/>a probability for misidentifying a light-parton jet of 0.3% for jets with transverse <lb/>momentum p  T  &gt; 20 GeV and pseudorapidity 2.2 &lt; η &lt; 4.2. The dependence of the <lb/>performance on the p  T  and η of the jet is also measured. <lb/> Submitted to JINST <lb/> c <lb/> CERN on behalf of the LHCb collaboration, license CC-BY-4.0. <lb/>  †  Authors are listed at the end of this paper. <lb/> arXiv:1504.07670v1  [hep-ex] 28 Apr 2015 <lb/></front>

			<page> ii <lb/></page>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> Identification of jets that originate from the hadronization of beauty (b) and charm (c) <lb/>quarks is important for studying Standard Model (SM) processes and for searching for new <lb/>physics. For example, the ability to efficiently identify b jets with minimal misidentification <lb/>of c and light-parton jets is crucial for the measurement of top-quark production. The <lb/>study of t ¯ <lb/> t production in the forward region probes the structure of the proton [1] and can <lb/>be used to search for physics beyond the SM [2]. Measuring charge asymmetries in di-b-jet <lb/>production also probes beyond the SM physics [3, 4]. Furthermore, identification of c jets <lb/>is important for probing the structure of the proton, e.g. in W +c production. <lb/>The signature of a b or c jet is the presence of a long-lived b or c hadron that carries a <lb/>sizable fraction of the jet energy. The LHCb detector was designed to identify b and c <lb/> hadrons, and so is expected to perform well at identifying, or tagging, b and c jets. This <lb/>paper describes two algorithms for identifying b and c jets, one designed to identify both b <lb/> and c jets offline, and another initially designed to identify b-hadron decays in the trigger. <lb/>The performance of each algorithm is measured using several subsamples of the 3 fb <lb/> −1  of <lb/>proton-proton collision data collected at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV in 2011 and at 8 TeV in 2012 by the <lb/>LHCb detector. The distributions of observable quantities used to discriminate between b, <lb/>c and light-parton jets are compared between data and simulation. <lb/> 2 The LHCb detector <lb/> The LHCb detector [5, 6] is a single-arm forward spectrometer covering the pseudorapidity <lb/>range 2 &lt; η &lt; 5, designed for the study of particles containing b or c quarks. The <lb/>detector includes a high-precision tracking system consisting of a silicon-strip vertex <lb/>detector surrounding the pp interaction region [7], a large-area silicon-strip detector <lb/>located upstream of a dipole magnet with a bending power of about 4 Tm, and three <lb/>stations of silicon-strip detectors and straw drift tubes [8] placed downstream of the <lb/>magnet. The tracking system provides a measurement of momentum, p, of charged <lb/>particles with a relative uncertainty that varies from 0.5% at low momentum to 1.0% at <lb/>200 GeV (c = 1 throughout this paper). The minimum distance of a track to a primary <lb/>vertex, the impact parameter, is measured with a resolution of (15 + 29/p  T  ) µm, where p  T <lb/> is the component of the momentum transverse to the beam, in GeV. Different types of <lb/>charged hadrons are distinguished using information from two ring-imaging Cherenkov <lb/>detectors. Photons, electrons and hadrons are identified by a calorimeter system consisting <lb/>of scintillating-pad and preshower detectors, an electromagnetic calorimeter and a hadronic <lb/>calorimeter. The electromagnetic and hadronic calorimeters have an energy resolution of <lb/> σ(E)/E = 10%/ <lb/> √ <lb/> E ⊕ 1% and σ(E)/E = 69%/ <lb/> √ <lb/> E ⊕ 9% (with E in GeV), respectively. <lb/>Muons are identified by a system composed of alternating layers of iron and multiwire <lb/>proportional chambers [9]. <lb/>The trigger [10] consists of a hardware stage, based on information from the calorimeter <lb/>and muon systems, followed by a software stage, which applies a full event reconstruction. <lb/></body>

			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<body> This analysis requires that either a high-p  T  muon or a (b, c)-hadron <lb/> 1  candidate satisfies <lb/>the trigger requirements. Events recorded due to the presence of a high-p  T  muon are <lb/>required to have a muon candidate with p  T  &gt; 10 GeV. Events recorded due to the presence <lb/>of a (b, c)-hadron decay require that at least one track should have p  T  &gt; 1.7 GeV and <lb/> χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  with respect to any primary interaction greater than 16, where χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  is defined as the <lb/>difference in χ <lb/> 2  of a given primary pp interaction vertex (PV) reconstructed with and <lb/>without the considered track. Decays of b hadrons are inclusively identified by requiring a <lb/>two-, three-or four-track secondary vertex (SV) with a large sum of p  T  of the tracks and <lb/>a significant displacement from the PV. A specialized boosted decision tree (BDT) [11] <lb/>algorithm is used for the identification of SVs consistent with the decay of a b hadron [12]. <lb/>This inclusive trigger algorithm is called the topological trigger (TOPO) and is studied as <lb/>a b-jet tagger in this paper. Decays of long-lived c hadrons are identified either exclusively <lb/>using decay modes with large branching fractions, or in D <lb/>  *  (2010) <lb/> ±  → D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> ±  decays where <lb/>the D <lb/> 0  is selected inclusively by the presence of a two-track SV. <lb/>In the simulation, pp collisions are generated using Pythia [13] with a specific LHCb <lb/>configuration [14]. Decays of hadronic particles are described by EvtGen [15], in which <lb/>final-state radiation is generated using Photos [16]. The interaction of the generated <lb/>particles with the detector, and its response, are implemented using the Geant4 toolkit [17] <lb/>as described in Ref. [18]. <lb/> 3 Jet identification algorithms <lb/> Jets are clustered using the anti-k  T  algorithm [19] with a distance parameter 0.5, as <lb/>implemented in Fastjet [20]. Information from all the detector sub-systems is used <lb/>to create charged and neutral particle inputs to the jet algorithm using a particle flow <lb/>approach [21]. During 2011 and 2012, LHCb collected data with a mean number of pp <lb/> collisions per crossing of about 1.7. To reduce contamination from multiple pp interactions, <lb/>charged particles reconstructed within the vertex detector may only be clustered into a jet <lb/>if they are associated to the same PV. The identification of (b, c) jets is performed using <lb/>SVs from the decays of (b, c) hadrons. The choice of using SVs and not single-track or <lb/>other non-SV-based jet properties, e.g. the number of particles in the jet, is driven by the <lb/>need for a small misidentification probability of light-parton jets in the analyses performed <lb/>at LHCb. Furthermore, the properties of SVs from (b, c)-hadron decays are known to be <lb/>well modeled in LHCb simulation. <lb/> 3.1 The SV tagger <lb/> The tracks used as inputs to the SV-tagger algorithm are required to have p  T  &gt; 0.5 GeV <lb/>and χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  &gt; 16. The χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  requirement is rarely satisfied by tracks reconstructed from particles <lb/>originating directly from the PV. All tracks are assigned a pion mass, and hadronic particle <lb/>identification is not used. In contrast to many other jet-tagging algorithms, tracks are <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 1  The notation (b, c) is used to mean b or c throughout this paper. <lb/></note>

			<page> 2 <lb/></page>

			<body> not required to have ∆R ≡ <lb/> ∆η  2  + ∆φ  2  &lt; 0.5, where ∆η(∆φ) is the difference in <lb/>pseudorapidity (azimuthal angle) between the track momentum and jet axis, since for low <lb/> p  T  jets usage of tracks outside of the jet cone helps to discriminate between c and b jets. <lb/>All possible two-track SVs are built using pairs of the input tracks such that the <lb/>distance of closest approach between the tracks is less than 0.2 mm, the vertex fit χ <lb/> 2  &lt; 10 <lb/>and the two-body mass is in the range 0.4 GeV &lt; M &lt; M (B), where M (B) is the nominal <lb/> B <lb/> 0  mass [22]. Since all particles are assigned a pion mass, the upper mass requirement <lb/>rarely removes SVs from any long-lived b hadrons. The lower mass requirement removes <lb/>SVs from most strange-particle decays, including the Λ baryon whose computed mass is <lb/>always below 0.4 GeV when the proton is assigned a pion mass. At this stage tracks are <lb/>allowed to belong to multiple SVs. Next, all two-track SVs with ∆R &lt; 0.5 relative to the <lb/>jet axis, where the direction of flight is taken as the PV to SV vector, are collected as <lb/>candidates for a so-called linking procedure. This procedure involves merging SVs that <lb/>share tracks until none of the remaining SVs with ∆R &lt; 0.5 share tracks. The SV position <lb/>is taken to be the weighted average of the 2-body SV positions using the inverse of the <lb/>2-body vertex χ <lb/> 2  values as the weights. <lb/>The linking procedure can produce SVs that contain any number of tracks. The linked <lb/> n-track SVs are required to have p  T  &gt; 2 GeV, significant spatial separation from the PV, <lb/>and to contain at most one track with ∆R &gt; 0.5 relative to the jet axis. If the SV has only <lb/>two tracks and a mass consistent with that of the K <lb/> 0 <lb/> S  [22], the SV is rejected. Interactions <lb/>with material, and strange-particle decays, are suppressed by requiring that the flight <lb/>distance divided by the momentum of the SV is less than 1.5 mm/GeV; this quantity <lb/>serves as a proxy for the hadron lifetime. The SV position is also required to be within a <lb/>restricted region consistent with that of (b, c)-hadron decays. <lb/>An important quantity for discriminating between hadron types is the so-called corrected <lb/>mass defined as <lb/> M  cor  = <lb/> M  2  + p  2  sin <lb/> 2  θ + p sin θ, <lb/> (1) <lb/>where M and p are the invariant mass and momentum of the particles that form the SV <lb/>and θ is the angle between the momentum and the direction of flight of the SV. The <lb/>corrected mass is the minimum mass that the long-lived hadron can have that is consistent <lb/>with the direction of flight. The linked n-track SVs are required to have M  cor  &gt; 0.6 GeV <lb/>to remove any remaining kaon or hyperon decays. A few percent of jets contain multiple <lb/>SVs that pass all requirements; in such cases the SV with the highest p  T  is chosen. The <lb/>fraction of multi-SV-tagged jets is consistent in data and simulation. <lb/>Two BDTs are used to identify b and c jets: BDT(bc|udsg) trained to separate (b, c) <lb/> jets from light-parton jets and BDT(b|c) trained to separate b jets from c jets. Both BDTs <lb/>are trained on simulated samples of b, c and light-parton jets. The inputs to both BDTs <lb/>are as follows: <lb/> • the SV mass M ; <lb/> • the SV corrected mass M  cor  ; <lb/> • the transverse flight distance of the two-track SV closest to the PV; <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body> • the fraction of the jet p  T  carried by the SV, p  T  (SV)/p  T  (jet); <lb/> • ∆R between the SV flight direction and the jet; <lb/> • the number of tracks in the SV; <lb/> • the number of SV tracks with ∆R &lt; 0.5 relative to the jet axis; <lb/> • the net charge of the tracks that form the SV; <lb/> • the flight distance χ <lb/> 2  ; <lb/> • the sum of all SV track χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  . <lb/>For jets that contain an SV passing all of the requirements, the two BDT responses are <lb/>used to identify the jet as either b, c or light-parton. <lb/> 3.2 The topological trigger <lb/> The topological trigger algorithm uses SVs that satisfy similar criteria to those used in <lb/>the SV-tagger algorithm to build two-, three-and four-track SVs. The TOPO SVs are <lb/>required to have p  T  and flight-distance significance consistent with the decay of a b hadron. <lb/>The TOPO provides an efficient trigger option for generic b-jet events, as the SV used by <lb/>the TOPO to trigger recording of the event can also be used to tag a b jet. The BDT used <lb/>in the TOPO algorithm uses the following inputs: <lb/> • the SV mass; <lb/> • the SV corrected mass; <lb/> • the sum of the p  T  of the SV tracks; <lb/> • the maximum distance of closest approach between the SV tracks; <lb/> • the χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  of the SV formed using the momentum of the tracks that form the SV and <lb/>SV position; <lb/> • the flight distance χ <lb/> 2  of the SV from the PV; <lb/> • the minimum p  T  of the SV tracks. <lb/>To ensure stability during data-taking the TOPO BDT uses discretized inputs as described <lb/>in detail in Ref. [12]. Further details about the TOPO algorithm and its performance on <lb/> b-hadron decays as measured in LHCb data can be found in Ref. [10]. <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body> ) <lb/> udsg <lb/> | <lb/> bc <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> | <lb/> b <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> LHCb simulation <lb/>-jets <lb/> b <lb/> ) <lb/> udsg <lb/> | <lb/> bc <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> | <lb/> b <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> LHCb simulation <lb/>-jets <lb/> c <lb/> ) <lb/> udsg <lb/> | <lb/> bc <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> | <lb/> b <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> LHCb simulation <lb/>-jets <lb/> udsg <lb/> Figure 1: SV-tagger algorithm BDT(b|c) versus BDT(bc|udsg) distributions obtained from <lb/>simulation for (left) b, (middle) c and (right) light-parton jets. <lb/> 3.3 Performance in simulation <lb/> Figure 1 shows the SV-tagger BDT distributions obtained from simulated W+jet events <lb/>for each jet type. The distributions in the two-dimensional BDT plane of SV-tagged <lb/> b, c, and light-parton jets are clearly distinguishable. Figure 2 shows the performance <lb/>of the SV-tagger algorithm obtained from simulated events for a BDT(bc|udsg) &gt; 0.2 <lb/>requirement that is about 90% efficient on SV-tagged (b, c) jets and highly suppresses <lb/>light-parton jets. The (b, c)-jet efficiencies are nearly uniform for jet p  T  &gt; 20 GeV and for <lb/>2.2 &lt; η &lt; 4.2, but are lower for low-p  T  jets and for jets near the edges of the detector. <lb/>The misidentification probability of light-parton jets is less than 0.1% for low-p  T  jets and <lb/>increases to about 1% at 100 GeV. Figure 3 shows the (b, c)-jet efficiencies versus the <lb/>mistag probability of light-parton jets obtained by increasing the BDT(bc|udsg) cut. <lb/>Figure 2 shows the performance of the TOPO algorithm, obtained from simulated <lb/>events. In the trigger, a looser BDT requirement is applied to SVs that contain muons. In <lb/>Ref. [23], this same looser BDT requirement was applied to tag a second jet in the event. <lb/>The nominal trigger BDT requirement strongly suppresses c and light-parton jets, with <lb/>the misidentification probability of light-parton jets being 0.01% for low-p  T  jets. Such a <lb/>strong suppression is required during online running due to output rate limitations. <lb/>The jet-tagging performance is measured in simulated events with one pp collision and <lb/>two or more pp collisions and found to be consistent. The tagging performance is also <lb/>studied in simulation using different event types, e.g. top-quark and QCD di-jet events, <lb/>with only small changes in the tagging efficiencies and BDT templates observed for (b, c) <lb/> jets. The mistag probability of light-parton jets is found to be higher for high-p  T  jets in <lb/>events that also contain (b, c) jets. This is discussed in detail in Sec. 5. <lb/> 4 Efficiency measurements in data <lb/> The tagging efficiencies for b and c jets are measured in data and compared with expecta-<lb/>tions from simulation. To measure the tagging efficiencies in a given data sample, both the <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body> (jet) [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/> efficiency <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>SV-tagger <lb/>TOPO <lb/>TOPO (loose) <lb/> LHCb simulation <lb/>(jet) &lt; 4.2 <lb/> η <lb/> 2.2 &lt; <lb/>-jets <lb/> b <lb/> (jet) <lb/> η <lb/> 2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3 <lb/>3.5 <lb/>4 <lb/>4.5 <lb/> efficiency <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>SV-tagger <lb/>TOPO <lb/>TOPO (loose) <lb/> LHCb simulation <lb/>(jet) &lt; 100 GeV <lb/> T <lb/> 20 &lt; p <lb/>-jets <lb/> b <lb/> (jet) [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/> efficiency <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>SV-tagger <lb/>TOPO <lb/>TOPO (loose) <lb/> LHCb simulation <lb/>(jet) &lt; 4.2 <lb/> η <lb/> 2.2 &lt; <lb/>-jets <lb/> c <lb/> (jet) <lb/> η <lb/> 2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3 <lb/>3.5 <lb/>4 <lb/>4.5 <lb/> efficiency <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>SV-tagger <lb/>TOPO <lb/>TOPO (loose) <lb/> LHCb simulation <lb/>(jet) &lt; 100 GeV <lb/> T <lb/> 20 &lt; p <lb/>-jets <lb/> c <lb/> (jet) [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/> misidentification probability <lb/> -4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/>SV-tagger <lb/>TOPO <lb/>TOPO (loose) <lb/> LHCb simulation <lb/>(jet) &lt; 4.2 <lb/> η <lb/> 2.2 &lt; <lb/>-jets <lb/> udsg <lb/> (jet) <lb/> η <lb/> 2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3 <lb/>3.5 <lb/>4 <lb/>4.5 <lb/> misidentification probability <lb/> -4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/>SV-tagger <lb/>TOPO <lb/>TOPO (loose) <lb/> LHCb simulation <lb/>(jet) &lt; 100 GeV <lb/> T <lb/> 20 &lt; p <lb/>-jets <lb/> udsg <lb/> Figure 2: Efficiencies and mistag probabilities obtained from simulation for the SV-tagger <lb/>and TOPO algorithms for (top) b, (middle) c and (bottom) light-parton jets. The left plots <lb/>show the dependence on p  T  for 2.2 &lt; η &lt; 4.2, while the right plots show the dependence on <lb/> η for p  T  &gt; 20 GeV (see text for details). The &quot; loose &quot; label for the TOPO refers to the BDT <lb/>requirement used in the trigger for SVs that contain muon candidates. <lb/> number of tagged (b, c) jets and the total number of (b, c) jets must be determined. The <lb/>tagged (b, c) yields are obtained by fitting the SV-tagger or TOPO BDT distributions in the <lb/>subsample of jets that are tagged by an SV. The total number of (b, c) jets is determined by <lb/>fitting the χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  distribution of the highest-p  T  track in the jet. The (b, c)-tagging efficiency <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body> light-parton mistag probability <lb/> 0.001 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.003 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.005 <lb/> (b,c)-jet tag efficiency <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> -jet <lb/> b <lb/> -jet <lb/> c <lb/> LHCb simulation <lb/> (jet) &lt; 4.2 <lb/> η <lb/> 2.2 &lt; <lb/>(jet) &lt; 100 GeV <lb/> T <lb/> 20 &lt; p <lb/> Figure 3: Efficiencies for SV-tagging a (b, c)-jet versus mistag probability for a light-parton jet <lb/>from simulation. <lb/> is the ratio of the tagged over total (b, c)-jet yields. <lb/>An alternative approach employed by other experiments (see, e.g. Ref. [24]) is to <lb/>measure the efficiency using the subsample of jets that contain a muon. This approach has <lb/>the advantage that the (b, c)-jet content is enhanced due to the presence of muons from <lb/>the semileptonic decays of (b, c) hadrons; however, the disadvantage is that this method <lb/>assumes that mismodeling of the tagging performance is the same for semileptonic and <lb/>inclusive decays. Both the highest-p  T  track and muon-jet methods are used in this analysis <lb/>to study the jet-tagging performance. <lb/>Combined fits of several data samples enriched in (b, c) jets are performed to obtain <lb/>the tagging efficiencies. It is important to include the systematic uncertainties on both <lb/>the tagged and total (b, c)-jet yields for each data sample in the combined fits. <lb/>This section is arranged as follows: the data samples used are described in Sec. 4.1; the <lb/>BDT fits used to obtain the tagged (b, c)-jet yields are given in Sec. 4.2; the highest-p  T  -track <lb/> χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  fits used to obtain the total (b, c)-jet yields are described in Sec. 4.3; the muon-jet <lb/>subsample method is discussed in Sec. 4.4; the systematic uncertainties on the tagged and <lb/>total (b, c)-jet yields are presented in Sec. 4.5; and the (b, c)-tagging efficiency results are <lb/>given in Sec. 4.6. <lb/> 4.1 Data samples <lb/> Events that contain either a high-p  T  muon or a fully reconstructed (b, c) hadron, referred <lb/>to here as an event-tag, are used to measure the jet-tagging efficiencies in data. The <lb/>highest-p  T  jet in the event that does not have any overlap with the event-tag is chosen as <lb/>the test jet. Each event-tag is required to have satisfied specific trigger requirements and <lb/>to have ∆φ &gt; 2.5 relative to the test-jet axis to reduce the possibility of contamination <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body> of the jet from the event-tag <lb/> 2  . Therefore, all events used to measure the (b, c)-tagging <lb/> efficiency have passed the trigger independently of the presence of the test jet, which <lb/>ensures that the trigger does not bias the efficiency measurement. The following event-tags <lb/>are used (labeled by the data-set identifier): <lb/> • (B+jet) a fully reconstructed b-hadron decay which enriches the b-jet content of the <lb/>test-jet sample; <lb/> • (D+jet) a fully reconstructed c-hadron decay which enriches the c-jet and b-jet <lb/> content of the test-jet sample (due to b → c decays); <lb/> • (µ(b, c)+jet) a displaced high-p  T  muon which enriches the c-jet and b-jet content of <lb/>the test-jet sample; <lb/> • (W+jet) a prompt isolated high-p  T  muon indicative of W+jet events that consists of <lb/>about 95% light-parton jets. <lb/>The first three samples are used to measure the (b, c)-jet identification efficiencies and <lb/>properties. The final sample is used to study misidentification of light-parton jets. In <lb/>all samples the event-tag and test jet are required to originate from the same PV. The <lb/>range 10 &lt; p  T  (jet) &lt; 100 GeV is considered since there are no large enough data samples <lb/>to measure the efficiency for jet p  T  &gt; 100 GeV. <lb/> 4.2 Tagged-jet yields <lb/> The presence of an SV and its kinematic properties are used to discriminate between <lb/> b, c and light-parton jets. As described in Section 3, the SV-tagger algorithm uses two <lb/>BDTs while the TOPO uses one BDT for each SV. The tagged yields for each algorithm <lb/>are obtained by fitting to data BDT templates obtained from simulation for b, c and <lb/>light-parton jets. In all fits the template shapes are fixed and only the yields of each jet <lb/>type are free to vary. <lb/>Figures 4–6 show the results of fits performed to the two-dimensional SV-tagger BDT <lb/>distributions in the B+jet, D+jet and µ(b, c)+jet data samples. The b and c jets are <lb/>clearly distinguishable in the two-dimensional BDT distributions: b jets are mostly found <lb/>in the upper right corner, while c jets are found in the center-right and lower-right regions. <lb/>The light-parton jets cluster near the origin but are difficult to see due to the low SV-tag <lb/>probability of light-parton jets. The BDT templates for b, c and light-parton jets describe <lb/>the data well. A dedicated study of the modeling of the light-parton-jet BDT distributions <lb/>is discussed in Sec. 5. <lb/>A simple cross-check on the b, c and light-parton yields is performed by fitting only <lb/>two of the BDT inputs: the corrected mass defined in Eq. 1 and the number of tracks in <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 2  The event-tag samples are highly pure; however, when the event-tag is not properly reconstructed <lb/>the non-overlap requirements are not guaranteed to hold. Requiring that the event-tag and test jet are <lb/>back-to-back in the transverse plane greatly reduces the probability that a particle originating from the <lb/>event-tag decay but not reconstructed in the event-tag is reconstructed as part of the test jet. <lb/></note>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			<body> 0 <lb/> 100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>700 <lb/>800 <lb/>900 <lb/> ) <lb/> udsg <lb/> | <lb/> bc <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> | <lb/> b <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> LHCb data <lb/>+jet <lb/> B <lb/> 0 <lb/> 100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>700 <lb/>800 <lb/>900 <lb/> ) <lb/> udsg <lb/> | <lb/> bc <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> | <lb/> b <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> LHCb fit <lb/> ) <lb/> udsg <lb/> | <lb/> bc <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>2000 <lb/>4000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/>c <lb/>udsg <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> | <lb/> b <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/>c <lb/>udsg <lb/> Figure 4: SV-tagger BDT fit results for the B+jet data sample with 10 &lt; p  T  (jet) &lt; 100 GeV: <lb/>(top left) distribution in data; (top right) two-dimensional template-fit result; and (bottom) <lb/>projections of the fit result with the b, c, and light-parton contributions shown as stacked <lb/>histograms. <lb/> the SV. The corrected mass provides the best discrimination between c jets and other jet <lb/>types due to the fact that M  cor  peaks near the D meson mass for c jets <lb/> 3  . The number of <lb/>tracks in the SV identifies b jets well since b-hadron decays often produce many displaced <lb/>tracks. Figure 7 shows the results of a two-dimensional fit to these two SV properties. <lb/>The absolute fractions of b, c and light-parton SV tags agree with the BDT fit results <lb/>to within 1–2%. The corrected mass has been previously used in LHCb jet analyses for <lb/>determining the c-jet yield [23] and for extracting the b-jet yield [25]. The clear peaking <lb/>structure for c jets, which relies on the excellent vertex resolution of the LHCb detector, <lb/>makes them easily identifiable. <lb/>Figure 8 shows the results of fitting the TOPO BDT distributions in the various data <lb/>samples using b, c and light-parton jet template shapes obtained from simulation. The <lb/>ratios of SV-tagger to TOPO SV-tagged b, c and light-parton jets are each consistent with <lb/>expectations from simulation. Modeling of both the SV-tagger and TOPO SV properties <lb/>are sufficient to allow the SV-tagged content to be accurately determined. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 3  This is true for all long-lived c hadrons when all tracks are assigned a pion mass. <lb/></note>

			<page> 9 <lb/></page>

			<body> 0 <lb/> 200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/>1000 <lb/> ) <lb/> udsg <lb/> | <lb/> bc <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> | <lb/> b <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> LHCb data <lb/>+jet <lb/> D <lb/> 0 <lb/> 200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/>1000 <lb/> ) <lb/> udsg <lb/> | <lb/> bc <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> | <lb/> b <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> LHCb fit <lb/> ) <lb/> udsg <lb/> | <lb/> bc <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>2000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>6000 <lb/>8000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/>c <lb/>udsg <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> | <lb/> b <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>2000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>6000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/>c <lb/>udsg <lb/> Figure 5: Same as Fig. 4 for the D+jet data sample. <lb/> 0 <lb/> 500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1500 <lb/>2000 <lb/>2500 <lb/>3000 <lb/> ) <lb/> udsg <lb/> | <lb/> bc <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> | <lb/> b <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> LHCb data <lb/>)+jet <lb/> b,c <lb/> ( <lb/> µ <lb/> 0 <lb/> 500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1500 <lb/>2000 <lb/>2500 <lb/>3000 <lb/> ) <lb/> udsg <lb/> | <lb/> bc <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> | <lb/> b <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> LHCb fit <lb/> ) <lb/> udsg <lb/> | <lb/> bc <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>15000 <lb/>20000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/>c <lb/>udsg <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> | <lb/> b <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/>c <lb/>udsg <lb/> Figure 6: Same as Fig. 4 for the µ(b, c)+jet data sample. <lb/></body>

			<page> 10 <lb/></page>

			<body> [GeV] <lb/> cor <lb/> M <lb/> SV <lb/> 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/>c <lb/>udsg <lb/> (tracks) <lb/> N <lb/> SV <lb/> 2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>2000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>6000 <lb/>8000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/>c <lb/>udsg <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> cor <lb/> M <lb/> SV <lb/> 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/>c <lb/>udsg <lb/> (tracks) <lb/> N <lb/> SV <lb/> 2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>15000 <lb/>20000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/>c <lb/>udsg <lb/> [GeV] <lb/> cor <lb/> M <lb/> SV <lb/> 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>15000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/>c <lb/>udsg <lb/> (tracks) <lb/> N <lb/> SV <lb/> 2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/>c <lb/>udsg <lb/> Figure 7: Two-dimensional M  cor  versus SV track multiplicity fit results for (top) B+jet, (middle) <lb/> D+jet and (bottom) µ(b, c)+jet data samples. The left plots show the projection onto the M  cor <lb/> axis, while the right plots show the projection onto the track multiplicity. The highest M  cor  bin <lb/>includes candidates with M  cor  &gt; 10 GeV. <lb/> 4.3 Efficiency measurement using highest-p  T  tracks <lb/> To determine the jet-tagging efficiency, the jet composition prior to applying the SV tag <lb/>must be determined. This is necessarily more difficult than determining the SV-tagged <lb/>composition. The χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  distribution of the highest-p  T  track in the jet is used for this task. <lb/>For light-parton jets the highest-p  T  track will mostly originate from the PV, while for <lb/>(b, c) jets the highest-p  T  track will often originate from the decay of the (b, c) hadron. To <lb/>avoid possible issues with modeling of soft radiation, only the subset of jets for which the <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body> TOPO BDT <lb/> 0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/> c <lb/>udsg <lb/> +jet <lb/> B <lb/> TOPO BDT <lb/> 0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/> c <lb/>udsg <lb/> +jet <lb/> D <lb/> TOPO BDT <lb/> 0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>15000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/> c <lb/>udsg <lb/> )+jet <lb/> b,c <lb/> ( <lb/> µ <lb/> Figure 8: Fits to the TOPO BDT distribution in (left) B+jet, (middle) D+jet and (right) <lb/> µ(b, c)+jet data samples with 10 &lt; p  T  (jet) &lt; 100 GeV. <lb/> highest-p  T  track satisfies p  T  (track)/p  T  (jet) &gt; 10%, which is about 95% of all jets, is used. <lb/>Since the W+jet sample is dominantly composed of light-parton jets, the χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  detector <lb/>response can be obtained in a data-driven way using this data sample. First, the two-<lb/>dimensional SV-tagger BDT response is fitted to determine the SV-tagged b, c and <lb/>light-parton jet yields. The tagging efficiencies obtained in simulation for b and c jets are <lb/>used to estimate the total number of b and c jets in the W+jet data sample. Since the <lb/> b and c jets combined make up only 5% of the total data sample, any mismodeling of <lb/>the SV-tagging efficiency will have negligible impact on this study. The IP resolution is <lb/>studied by comparing the observed χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  distributions in data with templates obtained from <lb/>simulation in bins of jet p  T  . The resolution in data is found to be about 10% worse than <lb/>in the simulation which is consistent with previous LHCb studies of the IP resolution [7]. <lb/>Figure 9 shows that the data-driven templates describe the data well. The difference in the <lb/>detector response between data and simulation is assumed to be universal and is applied <lb/>to correct the χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  templates for b and c jets. <lb/>Figure 10 shows the results of fitting the χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  distributions in the B+jet, D+jet and <lb/> µ(b, c)+jet data samples. Each sample consists of mostly light-parton jets prior to applying <lb/>an SV tag. While these data samples require that an event-tag containing a (b, c) quark is <lb/>reconstructed, the associated (b, c) quarks produced in hard scattering processes are often <lb/>not produced within the LHCb acceptance. Furthermore, for the (B, D)+jet samples, the <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body> ) <lb/> IP <lb/>2 <lb/> χ <lb/> log( <lb/> -5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/> c <lb/>udsg <lb/> +jet <lb/> W <lb/> Figure 9: Results of χ  2 <lb/> IP  calibration using W+jet data for 10 &lt; p  T  (jet) &lt; 100 GeV. The tail out <lb/>to large χ  2 <lb/>IP  values in the light-parton-jet sample is largely due to strange particle decays. <lb/> event-tags often have low p  T  so that the associated (b, c) quarks may be within the LHCb <lb/>acceptance but do not form a high-p  T  jet. The light-parton-jet χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  template has a long <lb/>tail out to large values which arises due to hyperon and kaon decays. In the χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  fits, the <lb/>log χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  &gt; 3 component of the light-parton template is allowed to vary independently to <lb/>allow for different s-quark content from the W+jet calibration sample. Apart from this, <lb/>all χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  templates are fixed in shape. The efficiency for tagging a jet originated by a quark <lb/>of type q is determined as <lb/>  q  = N  q  (SV)/N  q  (χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  ), <lb/>(2) <lb/> i.e. it is the ratio of the yield determined from fits to the SV-tagged BDT distributions, <lb/>either for the SV-tagger or TOPO algorithm, to the yield obtained from fits to the χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP <lb/> distributions. <lb/> 4.4 Efficiency measurement using muon jets <lb/> The approach described in the previous subsection has the advantage that it involves <lb/>measuring the efficiency on almost all of the jets in the data sample; however, its disad-<lb/>vantage is the large light-parton-jet content, which results in 10–20% uncertainties on the <lb/>pre-SV-tag jet content. An approach used by other experiments is to measure the efficiency <lb/>on the subset of jets that contain muons. The tagging efficiencies are also obtained using <lb/>Eq. 2 for the muon-jet subsamples. Figures 11–13 show the SV-tagger BDT and χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  fit <lb/>results for the muon-jet subsample of each data set. In these subsamples the χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  is that <lb/>of the highest-p  T  muon in the jet. The muon is required to satisfy p  T  (µ)/p  T  (jet) &gt; 10%. <lb/>The initial light-parton-jet content is greatly reduced in these data subsamples; however, <lb/>this approach only uses about 10% of the jets and it is possible that mismodeling of the <lb/>jet-tagging performance in semileptonic decays is not the same as for other decays. <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body> ) <lb/> IP <lb/>2 <lb/> χ <lb/> log( <lb/> -5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/> c <lb/>udsg <lb/> +jet <lb/> B <lb/> ) <lb/> IP <lb/>2 <lb/> χ <lb/> log( <lb/> -5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>50000 <lb/>100000 <lb/>150000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/> c <lb/>udsg <lb/> +jet <lb/> D <lb/> ) <lb/> IP <lb/>2 <lb/> χ <lb/> log( <lb/> -5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>50000 <lb/>100000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/> c <lb/>udsg <lb/> )+jet <lb/> b,c <lb/> ( <lb/> µ <lb/> Figure 10: Fits to the χ  2 <lb/> IP  distribution in (top left) B+jet, (top right) D+jet and (bottom) <lb/> µ(b, c)+jet data samples. <lb/> 4.5 Systematic uncertainties <lb/> The systematic uncertainty on N  (b,c)  (SV) is estimated using the difference between the <lb/>(b, c) SV-tagged yields obtained from two different fits: the fit to the BDT distributions <lb/>and the fit to the M  cor  versus track multiplicity distributions. The latter approach removes <lb/>jet quantities such as jet p  T  from the yield determination. While the absolute uncertainty <lb/>on the SV-tagged quark content as determined by the difference in these two methods is <lb/>only a few percent, the relative uncertainty is large for cases where a given jet type makes <lb/>up a small fraction of the SV-tagged data sample. For example, the relative uncertainty on <lb/>the c-jet yield in the B+jet data sample is large. As a further cross-check the (B, D)+jet <lb/> data samples are used to obtain data-driven BDT templates. The difference in (b, c) yields <lb/>obtained by fitting the W+jet data sample using the data-driven and simulation templates <lb/>is found to be negligible. <lb/>The systematic uncertainty on N  (b,c)  (χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  ) has several components. The nominal χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP <lb/> fits allow the large-IP component of the light-parton-jet template to vary. The χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  fits <lb/>are repeated fixing this component to that observed in W+jet data, with the difference in <lb/>(b, c)-jet yields assigned as a systematic uncertainty. This uncertainty is sizable for the case <lb/>of high-p  T  c jets whose χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  template is less distinct from that of light-parton jets which <lb/>has a variable large-IP component in the fit. Possible dependence of the mismodeling of <lb/>the IP resolution on the origin point of the particle is studied and found to be negligible. <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body> ) <lb/> udsg <lb/> | <lb/> bc <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1500 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/>c <lb/>udsg <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> | <lb/> b <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/>c <lb/>udsg <lb/> ) <lb/> IP <lb/>2 <lb/> χ <lb/> muon log( <lb/> -5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/> c <lb/>udsg <lb/> +jet <lb/> B <lb/> Figure 11: <lb/>(top) SV-tagger two dimensional BDT fit results projected onto the (left) <lb/>BDT(bc|udsg) and (right) BDT(b|c) axes and (bottom) χ  2 <lb/> IP  fit results for the B+muon-jet <lb/> subsample with 10 &lt; p  T  (jet) &lt; 100 GeV. <lb/> For the case of muon jets, the misidentification probability of hadrons as muons and <lb/>the jet track multiplicity must be modeled properly to obtain an accurate χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  distribution. <lb/>Mismodeling of these properties does not lead to large uncertainty on N  b  (χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  ), since <lb/>the vast majority of reconstructed muons in b jets are truly muons that arise due to <lb/>semileptonic decays. For c jets, however, mismodeling of these properties can produce <lb/>sizable shifts in N  c  (χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  ) due to the smaller fraction of c jets that contain muons from <lb/>semileptonic decays. A comparison between W+jet data and simulation of the jet fraction <lb/>that satisfies the muon-jet requirements, in bins of jet p  T  , is used to obtain an estimate of <lb/>the probability of misidentifying a jet as a muon jet. Based on this study a 5% relative <lb/>uncertainty is assigned to N  b  (χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  ) and 20% to N  c  (χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  ) for muon jets. Another possible <lb/>way of misidentifying muon jets is if the semileptonic decay of a b hadron outside of the <lb/>jet produces a muon reconstructed as part of the jet <lb/> 4  . The ∆R distribution between the <lb/>SV direction of flight and jet axis for all muons found in an SV is used to conclude that <lb/>this effect is at the per mille level; it is taken to be negligible. <lb/>Jets produced in different types of events can have different properties. The b-tag <lb/> efficiency is found to agree to about 1% in simulated W +b, top and QCD multi-jet events. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 4  This can also happen for semileptonic c-hadron decays; however, such decays rarely produce particles <lb/>with ∆R &gt; 0.5 to the jet axis due to the much lower mass of c hadrons compared to that of b hadrons. <lb/></note>

			<page> 15 <lb/></page>

			<body> ) <lb/> udsg <lb/> | <lb/> bc <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/>c <lb/>udsg <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> | <lb/> b <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/>c <lb/>udsg <lb/> ) <lb/> IP <lb/>2 <lb/> χ <lb/> muon log( <lb/> -5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1500 <lb/>2000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/> c <lb/>udsg <lb/> +jet <lb/> D <lb/> Figure 12: Same as Fig. 11 but for the D+muon-jet data sample. <lb/> ) <lb/> udsg <lb/> | <lb/> bc <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1500 <lb/>2000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/>c <lb/>udsg <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> | <lb/> b <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/>c <lb/>udsg <lb/> ) <lb/> IP <lb/>2 <lb/> χ <lb/> muon log( <lb/> -5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/> c <lb/>udsg <lb/> )+jet <lb/> b,c <lb/> ( <lb/> µ <lb/> Figure 13: Same as Fig. 11 but for the µ(b, c)+muon-jet data sample. <lb/></body>

			<page> 16 <lb/></page>

			<body> Table 1: Summary of relative systematic uncertainties (− denotes negligible). Systematic <lb/>uncertainties that dependent on jet type and p  T  are marked by a  *  (see text for details). <lb/> source <lb/> b jets <lb/> c jets <lb/>BDT templates <lb/>  * <lb/> ≈ 2% <lb/> ≈ 2% <lb/>light-parton-jet large IP component <lb/>  * <lb/> ≈ 5% ≈ 10 − 30% <lb/>IP resolution <lb/> − <lb/>− <lb/> hadron-as-muon probability (muon-jet subsample only) <lb/>5% <lb/>20% <lb/>out-of-jet (b, c)-hadron decay <lb/> − <lb/>− <lb/> gluon splitting <lb/>1% <lb/>1% <lb/>number of pp interactions per event <lb/> − <lb/>− <lb/> The BDT shapes are studied in simulated single-jet b and di-jet b ¯ b events and found to be <lb/>consistent for low-p  T  jets but to show small discrepancies for large jet p  T  . For example, <lb/>the absolute difference in efficiency of requiring BDT(bc|udsg) &gt; 0.2 for b jets is less than <lb/>1% up to a jet p  T  of 50 GeV but reaches about 3% at a jet p  T  of 100 GeV. In the data <lb/>samples considered in this study, such effects are negligible as using BDT templates from <lb/>different event types results in differences in the SV-tagged yields of less than 1%. <lb/>Events where multiple b hadrons are produced could affect the SV BDT shapes. The <lb/>fraction of SVs that contain a track with ∆R &gt; 0.5 relative to the jet axis is studied <lb/>in data with the back-to-back requirement for the event-tag and test jet removed. The <lb/>fraction of SVs that contain such a track is found to vary by at most a few percent as <lb/>a function of ∆R between the event-tag and test jet. This could indicate percent-level <lb/>cross-talk between multiple b jets or could be due to changes in the jet composition. For <lb/>the efficiency measurements presented in this paper the effect of (b, c)-hadron decays <lb/>outside of the jet is negligible; however, such decays could have an important impact on <lb/>the tagging performance in some event types, e.g. in four b-jet events. <lb/>Gluon splitting to b ¯ b or c¯ c can produce jets that contain multiple (b, c) hadrons which <lb/>have a higher tagging efficiency. The requirement that a (b, c)-hadron-decay signature is <lb/>back-to-back with the test jet suppresses gluon-splitting contributions. The fraction of jets <lb/>that contain multiple SVs in data is a few percent, which agrees to about 1% in all bins <lb/>with simulated jets that contain only a single (b, c) hadron. The systematic uncertainty <lb/>due to jets that contain multiple (b, c) hadrons from g → (b ¯ b, c¯ c) is taken to be 1%. Finally, <lb/>there is no evidence in simulation of dependence on the number of pp interactions in the <lb/>event, so the uncertainty due to mismodeling of the number of pp interactions is taken to <lb/>be negligible. The systematic uncertainties are summarized in Table 1. <lb/> 4.6 Results <lb/> A combined fit to the B+jet, D+jet and µ(b, c)+jet data samples, including the systematic <lb/>uncertainties in Table 1, is performed to obtain the (b, c)-jet tagging efficiencies. In these <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body> fits, both N  (b,c)  (SV) and N  (b,c)  (χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  ) are determined simultaneously under the constraint <lb/>that the (b, c)-tagging efficiency in a given jet p  T  and η region must be the same in each <lb/>data sample. The highest-p  T  track and muon-jet subsamples are fitted independently <lb/>since the scale factors between data and simulation could be different for semileptonic <lb/>and inclusive decays. The scale factors for b and c jets are allowed to vary independently <lb/>since these may be different for different jet types. The misidentification probability of <lb/>light-parton jets is allowed to vary freely in each data sample, although the results obtained <lb/>are all consistent and agree with simulation. <lb/>The scale factors for the SV-tagger algorithm are measured versus jet p  T  in the region <lb/>2.2 &lt; η &lt; 4.2, where the efficiencies are expected to be nearly uniform versus η, and in the <lb/>region 2 &lt; η &lt; 2.2 for jet p  T  &gt; 20 GeV, where the efficiencies are nearly uniform versus <lb/>jet p  T  (there are not sufficient statistics to measure the efficiencies in the η &gt; 4.2 region). <lb/>The results versus jet p  T  are shown in Fig. 14 and are summarized as follows: <lb/> • The scale factors obtained from the highest-p  T  track approach are all consistent with <lb/>unity at the ±20% level. They show no trend in p  T  for b or c jets. <lb/> • The scale factors for muon jets are found to be consistent, albeit with large uncer-<lb/>tainties, with those obtained using the highest-p  T  track approach. The results are <lb/>combined assuming that the scale factors are the same for semileptonic and inclusive <lb/>(b, c)-hadron decays (see Fig. 14) and are summarized in Table 2. The scale factors <lb/>are consistent with unity for jet p  T  &gt; 20 GeV, but 10-20% below unity for low-p  T <lb/> jets. <lb/> • The scale-factor results obtained from the global fits are strongly anti-correlated <lb/>between b and c jets. It is likely that the true scale factors are similar between b and <lb/> c jets since many of the contributing factors, e.g. mismodeling of the SV position <lb/>resolution, are expected to affect b and c jets in a similar manner. The highest-p  T <lb/> track fits are repeated assuming that the scale factors are the same for b and c <lb/> jets (see Fig. 14) and summarized in Table 2. The results for jet p  T  &gt; 20 GeV are <lb/>consistent with unity at about the 5% level, while at low jet p  T  the scale factor is <lb/>again less than unity by about 10%. The muon jet results are not combined for b <lb/> and c jets since the b-jet results are much more precise. <lb/>Neither of the assumptions made in the combinations has to be completely valid; however, <lb/>they should each be a good approximation. Overall, the efficiencies measured in data are <lb/>consistent with those in simulation for jet p  T  &gt; 20 GeV with a conservative systematic <lb/>uncertainty estimate of 10%. At low jet p  T  the scale factors are about 0.9 for b jets and <lb/>0.8 for c jets. Using the difference in central values obtained from the highest-p  T  track, <lb/>combined highest-p  T  track and muon jet, and combined b and c jet results, produces a <lb/>conservative systematic uncertainty estimate of 10%. The absolute efficiencies measured <lb/>assuming the scale factors are the same for b and c jets are given in Table 2. For jet <lb/> p  T  &gt; 20 GeV and 2.2 &lt; η &lt; 4.2, the mean SV-tagging efficiency is about 65% for b jets and <lb/>25% for c jets. Finally, the TOPO algorithm efficiencies are measured in data and found <lb/>to be consistent with simulation to about 5% for b jets and 20% for c jets (see Fig. 15). <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body> (jet) [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/> efficiency in data/simulation <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>LHCb <lb/>-jet highest-pt track <lb/> b <lb/> -jet muon <lb/> b <lb/> -jet highest-pt track <lb/> c <lb/> -jet muon <lb/> c <lb/> (jet) [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/> efficiency in data/simulation <lb/> 0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>-jet <lb/> b <lb/> -jet <lb/> c <lb/> (jet) [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/> efficiency in data/simulation <lb/> 0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>)-jet <lb/> b,c <lb/> ( <lb/> (jet) [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/> SV-tag efficiency <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>-jet <lb/> b <lb/> -jet <lb/> c <lb/> Figure 14: Efficiencies of the SV-tagger algorithm measured in data relative to those obtained <lb/>from simulation for 2.2 &lt; η &lt; 4.2: (top left) results from the (closed markers) highest-p  T  track <lb/>and (open markers) muon-jet samples; (top right) the combined results assuming the scale factors <lb/>are the same for semileptonic and inclusive (b, c)-hadron decays; and (bottom left) the combined <lb/>results for (b, c)-jet using the highest-p  T  -track approach assuming the scale factors are the same <lb/>for b and c jets. The absolute efficiencies corresponding to the combined (b, c)-jet results (bottom <lb/>right). <lb/> The absolute efficiencies measured using the TOPO for b jets are: 21 ± 1% for 10–20 GeV; <lb/>44 ± 4% for 20–30 GeV; 60 ± 5% for 30–50 GeV; and 66 ± 6% for 50–100 GeV. <lb/> 5 Light-parton jet misidentification <lb/> Light-parton jets contain SVs due to any of the following: (1) misreconstruction of prompt <lb/>particles as displaced tracks; (2) decays of long-lived strange particles; or (3) interactions <lb/>with material. Type (1) can be studied in data using jets that contain an SV whose <lb/>inverted direction of flight lies in the jet cone (referred to as a backward SV). Types (2) and <lb/>(3) can be studied using SVs for which the ratio of the SV flight distance divided by the SV <lb/>momentum is too large for the decay of a (b, c) hadron (referred to as a too-long-lived SV). <lb/>The mistag probability for simulated light-parton jets using backward and too-long-lived <lb/>SVs is consistent with the nominal mistag probability at the 20% level (the nominal <lb/>mistag probability is shown in Fig. 2). Furthermore, the SV BDT distributions obtained <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body> Table 2: SV-tagger algorithm (b, c)-tagging efficiencies measured in data compared to those <lb/>obtained in simulation. The b and c results are obtained by combining the highest-p  T  track <lb/>and muon-jet results under the assumption that the scale factors are the same for semileptonic <lb/>and inclusive (b, c)-hadron decays. The (b, c) results are obtained by fitting the highest-p  T  -track <lb/>sample under the assumption that the scale factors are the same for b and c jets. The absolute <lb/>efficiencies observed in data are provided using the &quot; (b, c) jets &quot; results. <lb/> (data)//(simulation) <lb/> (data) (%) <lb/> jet p  T  ( GeV) <lb/>jet η <lb/>b jets <lb/> c jets <lb/>(b, c) jets <lb/> b jets c jets <lb/>10–20 <lb/>2.2–4.2 0.89 ± 0.04 0.81 ± 0.09 0.91 ± 0.04 38 ± 2 14 ± 1 <lb/>20–30 <lb/>2.2–4.2 0.92 ± 0.07 0.97 ± 0.09 0.97 ± 0.04 61 ± 3 23 ± 1 <lb/>30–50 <lb/>2.2–4.2 1.06 ± 0.08 1.04 ± 0.09 0.97 ± 0.04 65 ± 3 25 ± 1 <lb/>50–100 <lb/>2.2–4.2 1.10 ± 0.09 0.81 ± 0.15 1.05 ± 0.06 70 ± 4 28 ± 4 <lb/>20–100 <lb/>2–2.2 1.00 ± 0.07 1.12 ± 0.10 1.05 ± 0.03 56 ± 2 20 ± 1 <lb/> (jet) [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/> efficiency data/simulation <lb/> 0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>-jet <lb/> b <lb/> -jet <lb/> c <lb/> Figure 15: TOPO algorithm (b, c)-tagging efficiencies, using the &quot; loose &quot; BDT requirement, in <lb/>data relative to those obtained in simulation. <lb/> using backward and too-long-lived SVs are similar to the nominal light-parton-jet BDT <lb/>distributions. Therefore, the mistag probability of light-parton jets and SV properties can <lb/>be studied in data using backward and too-long-lived SV-tagged jets. <lb/>Such a study is complicated by the fact that prompt tracks in (b, c) jets can also <lb/>be misreconstructed as displaced, and that (b, c) jets also produce strange particles and <lb/>material interactions. Therefore, both backward and too-long-lived SVs are also found in <lb/>(b, c) jets. The W+jet data sample, which is dominantly composed of light-parton jets, is <lb/>used to mitigate effects from mistagged (b, c) jets. Figure 16 shows the BDT distributions <lb/>from backward and too-long-lived SVs observed in data compared to simulation. The <lb/>backward and too-long-lived BDT templates are similar for all jet types. The (b, c) yields <lb/>here are fixed by fitting the nominal SV-tagged data to obtain the total (b, c)-jet content <lb/>then taking the backward and too-long-lived SV-tag probabilities for (b, c) jets from <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body> 0 <lb/> 2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/> ) <lb/> udsg <lb/> | <lb/> bc <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> | <lb/> b <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> LHCb data <lb/>+jet (backward+too-long-lived) <lb/> W <lb/> 0 <lb/> 2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/> ) <lb/> udsg <lb/> | <lb/> bc <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> | <lb/> b <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> LHCb fit <lb/> ) <lb/> udsg <lb/> | <lb/> bc <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/>c <lb/>udsg <lb/> ) <lb/> c <lb/> | <lb/> b <lb/> BDT( <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> candidates <lb/> 0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/> LHCb <lb/>data <lb/> b <lb/>c <lb/>udsg <lb/> Figure 16: SV-tagger algorithm BDT distributions for backward and too-long-lived SVs in the <lb/> W+jet data sample: (top left) distribution in data; (top right) two-dimensional template-fit <lb/>result; and (bottom) projections of the fit result with the b, c, and light-parton contributions <lb/>shown as stacked histograms. <lb/> simulation. The distributions in data and simulation are consistent, which demonstrates <lb/>that the SV properties are well-modeled for light-parton jets. <lb/>The total light-parton-jet composition of this sample, without applying any SV-tagging <lb/>algorithm, is found to be 95%, by fitting the nominal SV-tagged BDT distributions and <lb/>applying the data-driven (b, c)-tagging efficiencies from the previous section. The mistag <lb/>probability of light-parton jets is obtained as the ratio of the number of SV-tags for those <lb/>jets (obtained by fitting the SV BDT distributions) to the total number of light-parton <lb/>jets. The ratio of this probability in data to that in simulation is shown in Fig. 17; data <lb/>and simulation agree at about the ±30% level integrated over jet p  T  . A detailed study <lb/>of W+jet production in LHCb using the SV-tagger algorithm introduced in this paper, <lb/>in which the jets are required to satisfy p  T  &gt; 20 GeV and 2.2 &lt; η &lt; 4.2, finds that the <lb/>nominal light-parton-jet mistag probability is 0.3% which is consistent with simulation [26]. <lb/>The same ratio for the TOPO algorithm is also shown in Fig. 17. <lb/>The performance of any tagging algorithm on light-parton jets can be affected by <lb/>the presence of (b, c) jets in the event. The misidentification probability of light-parton <lb/>jets is studied in simulated di-b-jet events and compared to the performance obtained <lb/>in simulated events that contain no (b, c) jets. The absolute difference in the fraction <lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body> (jet) [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/> mis-ID prob. data/simulation <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/> LHCb <lb/> (jet) [GeV] <lb/> T <lb/> p <lb/> 20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/> mis-ID prob. data/simulation <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/> LHCb <lb/> Figure 17: Ratio of light-parton-jet mistag probabilities observed in data to those in simulation <lb/>for the (left) SV-tagger and (right) TOPO algorithms. <lb/> of light-parton jets that are SV-tagged and have BDT(bc|udsg) &gt; 0.2 is found to be at <lb/>the per mille level for low-p  T  jets, but increases to about 1% for jet p  T  of 50 GeV and <lb/>to about 2–3% at 100 GeV. The BDT shapes are distorted relative to those obtained in <lb/>events that contain no (b, c) jets, but there is still significant discrimination between the <lb/>light-parton and (b, c) distributions. The difference is largely due to particles originating <lb/>from a b-hadron decay and produced with ∆R &lt; 0.5 relative to the light-parton-jet axis. <lb/>These tracks may then form SVs with misreconstructed prompt tracks in the light-parton <lb/>jets. <lb/> 6 Summary <lb/> The LHCb collaboration has developed several algorithms that efficiently identify jets that <lb/>arise from the hadronization of b and c quarks. The performance of these algorithms has <lb/>been studied in data and is found to agree with that in simulation at about the 10% level <lb/>for (b, c) jets, and at the 30% level for light-parton jets. The SV properties of all jet types <lb/>are found to be well modeled by LHCb simulation. The efficiency for identifying a b(c) jet <lb/>is about 65%(25%) with a probability of misidentifying a light-parton jet of 0.3% for jets <lb/>with transverse momentum p  T  &gt; 20 GeV and pseudorapidity 2.2 &lt; η &lt; 4.2. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments <lb/> We express our gratitude to our colleagues in the CERN accelerator departments for <lb/>the excellent performance of the LHC. We thank the technical and administrative staff <lb/>at the LHCb institutes. We acknowledge support from CERN and from the national <lb/>agencies: CAPES, CNPq, FAPERJ and FINEP (Brazil); NSFC (China); CNRS/IN2P3 <lb/>(France); BMBF, DFG, HGF and MPG (Germany); INFN (Italy); FOM and NWO (The <lb/>Netherlands); MNiSW and NCN (Poland); MEN/IFA (Romania); MinES and FANO <lb/>(Russia); MinECo (Spain); SNSF and SER (Switzerland); NASU (Ukraine); STFC (United <lb/></div>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> Kingdom); NSF (USA). The Tier1 computing centres are supported by IN2P3 (France), <lb/>KIT and BMBF (Germany), INFN (Italy), NWO and SURF (The Netherlands), PIC <lb/>(Spain), GridPP (United Kingdom). We are indebted to the communities behind the <lb/>multiple open source software packages on which we depend. We are also thankful for <lb/>the computing resources and the access to software R&amp;D tools provided by Yandex LLC <lb/>(Russia). Individual groups or members have received support from EPLANET, Marie <lb/>Skk lodowska-Curie Actions and ERC (European Union), Conseil général de Haute-Savoie, <lb/>Labex ENIGMASS and OCEVU, Région Auvergne (France), RFBR (Russia), XuntaGal <lb/>and GENCAT (Spain), Royal Society and Royal Commission for the Exhibition of 1851 <lb/>(United Kingdom). <lb/> References <lb/> [1] R. Gauld, Leptonic top-quark asymmetry predictions at LHCb, Phys. Rev. D91 (2015) <lb/>054029, arXiv:1409.8631. <lb/> [2] A. L. Kagan, J. F. Kamenik, G. Perez, and S. Stone, Probing new top physics at the <lb/>LHCb experiment, Phys. Rev. Lett. 107 (2011) 082003, arXiv:1103.3747. <lb/> [3] B. Grinstein and C. W. Murphy, Bottom-quark forward-backward asymmetry in the <lb/>Standard Model and beyond, Phys. Rev. Lett. 111 (2013) 062003, arXiv:1302.6995. <lb/> [4] D. Kahawala, D. Krohn, and M. Strassler, Measuring the bottom-quark forward-central <lb/>asymmetry at the LHC, JHEP 01 (2012) 069, arXiv:1108.3301. <lb/> [5] LHCb collaboration, A. A. Alves Jr. et al., The LHCb detector at the LHC, JINST 3 <lb/> (2008) S08005. <lb/>[6] LHCb, R. Aaij et al., LHCb Detector Performance, Int. J. Mod. Phys. A30 (2015), <lb/>no. 07 1530022, arXiv:1412.6352. <lb/> [7] R. Aaij et al., Performance of the LHCb Vertex Locator, JINST 9 (2014) P09007, <lb/> arXiv:1405.7808. <lb/> [8] R. Arink et al., Performance of the LHCb Outer Tracker, JINST 9 (2014) P01002, <lb/> arXiv:1311.3893. <lb/> [9] A. A. Alves Jr. et al., Performance of the LHCb muon system, JINST 8 (2013) P02022, <lb/> arXiv:1211.1346. <lb/> [10] R. Aaij et al., The LHCb trigger and its performance in 2011, JINST 8 (2013) P04022, <lb/> arXiv:1211.3055. <lb/> [11] L. Breiman, J. H. Friedman, R. A. Olshen, and C. J. Stone, Classification and <lb/>regression trees, Wadsworth international group, Belmont, California, USA, 1984. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [12] V. V. Gligorov and M. Williams, Efficient, reliable and fast high-level triggering using <lb/>a bonsai boosted decision tree, JINST 8 (2013) P02013, arXiv:1210.6861. <lb/> [13] T. Sjöstrand, S. Mrenna, and P. Skands, A brief introduction to PYTHIA 8.1, Comput. <lb/>Phys. Commun. 178 (2008) 852, arXiv:0710.3820. <lb/> [14] I. Belyaev et al., Handling of the generation of primary events in Gauss, the LHCb <lb/>simulation framework, J. Phys. Conf. Ser. 331 (2011) 032047. <lb/>[15] D. J. Lange, The EvtGen particle decay simulation package, Nucl. Instrum. Meth. <lb/> A462 (2001) 152. <lb/>[16] P. Golonka and Z. Was, PHOTOS Monte Carlo: A precision tool for QED corrections <lb/>in Z and W decays, Eur. Phys. J. C45 (2006) 97, arXiv:hep-ph/0506026. <lb/> [17] Geant4 collaboration, J. Allison et al., Geant4 developments and applications, IEEE <lb/>Trans. Nucl. Sci. 53 (2006) 270; Geant4 collaboration, S. Agostinelli et al., Geant4: <lb/>A simulation toolkit, Nucl. Instrum. Meth. A506 (2003) 250. <lb/>[18] M. Clemencic et al., The LHCb simulation application, Gauss: Design, evolution and <lb/>experience, J. Phys. Conf. Ser. 331 (2011) 032023. <lb/>[19] M. Cacciari, G. P. Salam, and G. Soyez, The anti-k  t  jet clustering algorithm, JHEP <lb/> 04 (2008) 063, arXiv:0802.1189. <lb/> [20] M. Cacciari, G. P. Salam, and G. Soyez, FastJet user manual, Eur. Phys. J. C72 <lb/> (2012) 1896, arXiv:1111.6097. <lb/> [21] LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij et al., Study of forward Z+jet production in pp collisions <lb/>at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV , JHEP 01 (2014) 033, arXiv:1310.8197. <lb/> [22] Particle Data Group, K. A. Olive et al., Review of particle physics, Chin. Phys. C38 <lb/> (2014) 090001. <lb/>[23] LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij et al., First measurement of the charge asymmetry in <lb/>beauty-quark pair production, Phys. Rev. Lett. 113 (2014) 082003, arXiv:1406.4789. <lb/> [24] CMS collaboration, S. Chatrchyan et al., Identification of b-quark jets with the CMS <lb/>experiment, JINST 8 (2013) P04013, arXiv:1211.4462. <lb/> [25] LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij et al., Measurement of the Z+b-jet cross-section in pp col-<lb/>lisions at <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV in the forward region, JHEP 01 (2015) 064, arXiv:1411.1264. <lb/> [26] LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij et al., Study of W boson production in association with <lb/>beauty and charm jets in the forward region, LHCb-PAPER-2015-021, in preparation. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<front> LHCb collaboration <lb/> R. Aaij  38  , B. Adeva  37  , M. Adinolfi  46  , A. Affolder  52  , Z. Ajaltouni  5  , S. Akar  6  , J. Albrecht  9  , <lb/>F. Alessio  38  , M. Alexander  51  , S. Ali  41  , G. Alkhazov  30  , P. Alvarez Cartelle  53  , A.A. Alves Jr  57  , <lb/>S. Amato  2  , S. Amerio  22  , Y. Amhis  7  , L. An  3  , L. Anderlini  17,g  , J. Anderson  40  , M. Andreotti  16,f  , <lb/>J.E. Andrews  58  , R.B. Appleby  54  , O. Aquines Gutierrez  10  , F. Archilli  38  , P. d&apos;Argent  11  , <lb/>A. Artamonov  35  , M. Artuso  59  , E. Aslanides  6  , G. Auriemma  25,n  , M. Baalouch  5  , S. Bachmann  11  , <lb/>J.J. Back  48  , A. Badalov  36  , C. Baesso  60  , W. Baldini  16,38  , R.J. Barlow  54  , C. Barschel  38  , <lb/>S. Barsuk  7  , W. Barter  38  , V. Batozskaya  28  , V. Battista  39  , A. Bay  39  , L. Beaucourt  4  , J. Beddow  51  , <lb/>F. Bedeschi  23  , I. Bediaga  1  , L.J. Bel  41  , I. Belyaev  31  , E. Ben-Haim  8  , G. Bencivenni  18  , S. Benson  38  , <lb/>J. Benton  46  , A. Berezhnoy  32  , R. Bernet  40  , A. Bertolin  22  , M.-O. Bettler  38  , M. van Beuzekom  41  , <lb/>A. Bien  11  , S. Bifani  45  , T. Bird  54  , A. Birnkraut  9  , A. Bizzeti  17,i  , T. Blake  48  , F. Blanc  39  , <lb/>J. Blouw  10  , S. Blusk  59  , V. Bocci  25  , A. Bondar  34  , N. Bondar  30,38  , W. Bonivento  15  , S. Borghi  54  , <lb/>M. Borsato  7  , T.J.V. Bowcock  52  , E. Bowen  40  , C. Bozzi  16  , S. Braun  11  , D. Brett  54  , M. Britsch  10  , <lb/>T. Britton  59  , J. Brodzicka  54  , N.H. Brook  46  , A. Bursche  40  , J. Buytaert  38  , S. Cadeddu  15  , <lb/>R. Calabrese  16,f  , M. Calvi  20,k  , M. Calvo Gomez  36,p  , P. Campana  18  , D. Campora Perez  38  , <lb/>L. Capriotti  54  , A. Carbone  14,d  , G. Carboni  24,l  , R. Cardinale  19,j  , A. Cardini  15  , P. Carniti  20  , <lb/>L. Carson  50  , K. Carvalho Akiba  2,38  , R. Casanova Mohr  36  , G. Casse  52  , L. Cassina  20,k  , <lb/>L. Castillo Garcia  38  , M. Cattaneo  38  , Ch. Cauet  9  , G. Cavallero  19  , R. Cenci  23,t  , M. Charles  8  , <lb/>Ph. Charpentier  38  , M. Chefdeville  4  , S. Chen  54  , S.-F. Cheung  55  , N. Chiapolini  40  , M. Chrzaszcz  40  , <lb/>X. Cid Vidal  38  , G. Ciezarek  41  , P.E.L. Clarke  50  , M. Clemencic  38  , H.V. Cliff  47  , J. Closier  38  , <lb/>V. Coco  38  , J. Cogan  6  , E. Cogneras  5  , V. Cogoni  15,e  , L. Cojocariu  29  , G. Collazuol  22  , P. Collins  38  , <lb/>A. Comerma-Montells  11  , A. Contu  15,38  , A. Cook  46  , M. Coombes  46  , S. Coquereau  8  , G. Corti  38  , <lb/>M. Corvo  16,f  , I. Counts  56  , B. Couturier  38  , G.A. Cowan  50  , D.C. Craik  48  , A. Crocombe  48  , <lb/>M. Cruz Torres  60  , S. Cunliffe  53  , R. Currie  53  , C. D&apos;Ambrosio  38  , J. Dalseno  46  , P.N.Y. David  41  , <lb/>A. Davis  57  , K. De Bruyn  41  , S. De Capua  54  , M. De Cian  11  , J.M. De Miranda  1  , L. De Paula  2  , <lb/>W. De Silva  57  , P. De Simone  18  , C.-T. Dean  51  , D. Decamp  4  , M. Deckenhoff  9  , L. Del Buono  8  , <lb/>N. Déléage  4  , D. Derkach  55  , O. Deschamps  5  , F. Dettori  38  , B. Dey  40  , A. Di Canto  38  , <lb/>F. Di Ruscio  24  , H. Dijkstra  38  , S. Donleavy  52  , F. Dordei  11  , M. Dorigo  39  , A. Dosil Suárez  37  , <lb/>D. Dossett  48  , A. Dovbnya  43  , K. Dreimanis  52  , L. Dufour  41  , G. Dujany  54  , F. Dupertuis  39  , <lb/>P. Durante  38  , R. Dzhelyadin  35  , A. Dziurda  26  , A. Dzyuba  30  , S. Easo  49,38  , U. Egede  53  , <lb/>V. Egorychev  31  , S. Eidelman  34  , S. Eisenhardt  50  , U. Eitschberger  9  , R. Ekelhof  9  , L. Eklund  51  , <lb/>I. El Rifai  5  , Ch. Elsasser  40  , S. Ely  59  , S. Esen  11  , H.M. Evans  47  , T. Evans  55  , A. Falabella  14  , <lb/>C. Färber  11  , C. Farinelli  41  , N. Farley  45  , S. Farry  52  , R. Fay  52  , D. Ferguson  50  , <lb/>V. Fernandez Albor  37  , F. Ferrari  14  , F. Ferreira Rodrigues  1  , M. Ferro-Luzzi  38  , S. Filippov  33  , <lb/>M. Fiore  16,38,f  , M. Fiorini  16,f  , M. Firlej  27  , C. Fitzpatrick  39  , T. Fiutowski  27  , K. Fohl  38  , P. Fol  53  , <lb/>M. Fontana  10  , F. Fontanelli  19,j  , R. Forty  38  , O. Francisco  2  , M. Frank  38  , C. Frei  38  , M. Frosini  17  , <lb/>J. Fu  21  , E. Furfaro  24,l  , A. Gallas Torreira  37  , D. Galli  14,d  , S. Gallorini  22,38  , S. Gambetta  19,j  , <lb/>M. Gandelman  2  , P. Gandini  55  , Y. Gao  3  , J. García Pardiñas  37  , J. Garofoli  59  , J. Garra Tico  47  , <lb/>L. Garrido  36  , D. Gascon  36  , C. Gaspar  38  , U. Gastaldi  16  , R. Gauld  55  , L. Gavardi  9  , G. Gazzoni  5  , <lb/>A. Geraci  21,v  , D. Gerick  11  , E. Gersabeck  11  , M. Gersabeck  54  , T. Gershon  48  , Ph. Ghez  4  , <lb/>A. Gianelle  22  , S. Gian  39  , V. Gibson  47  , O. G. Girard  39  , L. Giubega  29  , V.V. Gligorov  38  , <lb/>C. Göbel  60  , D. Golubkov  31  , A. Golutvin  53,31,38  , A. Gomes  1,a  , C. Gotti  20,k  , <lb/>M. Grabalosa Gándara  5  , R. Graciani Diaz  36  , L.A. Granado Cardoso  38  , E. Graugés  36  , <lb/>E. Graverini  40  , G. Graziani  17  , A. Grecu  29  , E. Greening  55  , S. Gregson  47  , P. Griffith  45  , L. Grillo  11  , <lb/>O. Grünberg  63  , B. Gui  59  , E. Gushchin  33  , Yu. Guz  35,38  , T. Gys  38  , C. Hadjivasiliou  59  , <lb/></front>

			<page> 25 <lb/></page>

			<front> G. Haefeli  39  , C. Haen  38  , S.C. Haines  47  , S. Hall  53  , B. Hamilton  58  , T. Hampson  46  , X. Han  11  , <lb/>S. Hansmann-Menzemer  11  , N. Harnew  55  , S.T. Harnew  46  , J. Harrison  54  , J. He  38  , T. Head  39  , <lb/>V. Heijne  41  , K. Hennessy  52  , P. Henrard  5  , L. Henry  8  , J.A. Hernando Morata  37  , <lb/>E. van Herwijnen  38  , M. Heß  63  , A. Hicheur  2  , D. Hill  55  , M. Hoballah  5  , C. Hombach  54  , <lb/>W. Hulsbergen  41  , T. Humair  53  , N. Hussain  55  , D. Hutchcroft  52  , D. Hynds  51  , M. Idzik  27  , <lb/>P. Ilten  56  , R. Jacobsson  38  , A. Jaeger  11  , J. Jalocha  55  , E. Jans  41  , A. Jawahery  58  , F. Jing  3  , <lb/>M. John  55  , D. Johnson  38  , C.R. Jones  47  , C. Joram  38  , B. Jost  38  , N. Jurik  59  , S. Kandybei  43  , <lb/>W. Kanso  6  , M. Karacson  38  , T.M. Karbach  38, †  , S. Karodia  51  , M. Kelsey  59  , I.R. Kenyon  45  , <lb/>M. Kenzie  38  , T. Ketel  42  , B. Khanji  20,38,k  , C. Khurewathanakul  39  , S. Klaver  54  , <lb/>K. Klimaszewski  28  , O. Kochebina  7  , M. Kolpin  11  , I. Komarov  39  , R.F. Koopman  42  , <lb/>P. Koppenburg  41,38  , M. Korolev  32  , L. Kravchuk  33  , K. Kreplin  11  , M. Kreps  48  , G. Krocker  11  , <lb/>P. Krokovny  34  , F. Kruse  9  , W. Kucewicz  26,o  , M. Kucharczyk  26  , V. Kudryavtsev  34  , A. <lb/>K. Kuonen  39  , K. Kurek  28  , T. Kvaratskheliya  31  , V.N. La Thi  39  , D. Lacarrere  38  , G. Lafferty  54  , <lb/>A. Lai  15  , D. Lambert  50  , R.W. Lambert  42  , G. Lanfranchi  18  , C. Langenbruch  48  , B. Langhans  38  , <lb/>T. Latham  48  , C. Lazzeroni  45  , R. Le Gac  6  , J. van Leerdam  41  , J.-P. Lees  4  , R. Leèvre  5  , <lb/>A. Leflat  32,38  , J. Lefrançois  7  , O. Leroy  6  , T. Lesiak  26  , B. Leverington  11  , Y. Li  7  , <lb/>T. Likhomanenko  65,64  , M. Liles  52  , R. Lindner  38  , C. Linn  38  , F. Lionetto  40  , B. Liu  15  , X. Liu  3  , <lb/>S. Lohn  38  , I. Longstaff  51  , J.H. Lopes  2  , P. Lowdon  40  , D. Lucchesi  22,r  , M. Lucio Martinez  37  , <lb/>H. Luo  50  , A. Lupato  22  , E. Luppi  16,f  , O. Lupton  55  , F. Machefert  7  , F. Maciuc  29  , O. Maev  30  , <lb/>K. Maguire  54  , S. Malde  55  , A. Malinin  64  , G. Manca  15,e  , G. Mancinelli  6  , P. Manning  59  , <lb/>A. Mapelli  38  , J. Maratas  5  , J.F. Marchand  4  , U. Marconi  14  , C. Marin Benito  36  , P. Marino  23,38,t  , <lb/>R. Märki  39  , J. Marks  11  , G. Martellotti  25  , M. Martinelli  39  , D. Martinez Santos  42  , <lb/>F. Martinez Vidal  66  , D. Martins Tostes  2  , A. Massafferri  1  , R. Matev  38  , A. Mathad  48  , Z. Mathe  38  , <lb/>C. Matteuzzi  20  , K. Matthieu  11  , A. Mauri  40  , B. Maurin  39  , A. Mazurov  45  , M. McCann  53  , <lb/>J. McCarthy  45  , A. McNab  54  , R. McNulty  12  , B. Meadows  57  , F. Meier  9  , M. Meissner  11  , <lb/>M. Merk  41  , D.A. Milanes  62  , M.-N. Minard  4  , D.S. Mitzel  11  , J. Molina Rodriguez  60  , S. Monteil  5  , <lb/>M. Morandin  22  , P. Morawski  27  , A. Morà  6  , M.J. Morello  23,t  , J. Moron  27  , A.B. Morris  50  , <lb/>R. Mountain  59  , F. Muheim  50  , J. Müller  9  , K. Müller  40  , V. Müller  9  , M. Mussini  14  , B. Muster  39  , <lb/>P. Naik  46  , T. Nakada  39  , R. Nandakumar  49  , I. Nasteva  2  , M. Needham  50  , N. Neri  21  , S. Neubert  11  , <lb/>N. Neufeld  38  , M. Neuner  11  , A.D. Nguyen  39  , T.D. Nguyen  39  , C. Nguyen-Mau  39,q  , V. Niess  5  , <lb/>R. Niet  9  , N. Nikitin  32  , T. Nikodem  11  , D. Ninci  23  , A. Novoselov  35  , D.P. O&apos;Hanlon  48  , <lb/>A. Oblakowska-Mucha  27  , V. Obraztsov  35  , S. Ogilvy  51  , O. Okhrimenko  44  , R. Oldeman  15,e  , <lb/>C.J.G. Onderwater  67  , B. Osorio Rodrigues  1  , J.M. Otalora Goicochea  2  , A. Otto  38  , P. Owen  53  , <lb/>A. Oyanguren  66  , A. Palano  13,c  , F. Palombo  21,u  , M. Palutan  18  , J. Panman  38  , A. Papanestis  49  , <lb/>M. Pappagallo  51  , L.L. Pappalardo  16,f  , C. Parkes  54  , G. Passaleva  17  , G.D. Patel  52  , M. Patel  53  , <lb/>C. Patrignani  19,j  , A. Pearce  54,49  , A. Pellegrino  41  , G. Penso  25,m  , M. Pepe Altarelli  38  , <lb/>S. Perazzini  14,d  , P. Perret  5  , L. Pescatore  45  , K. Petridis  46  , A. Petrolini  19,j  , M. Petruzzo  21  , <lb/>E. Picatoste Olloqui  36  , B. Pietrzyk  4  , T. Pilař  48  , D. Pinci  25  , A. Pistone  19  , A. Piucci  11  , <lb/>S. Playfer  50  , M. Plo Casasus  37  , T. Poikela  38  , F. Polci  8  , A. Poluektov  48,34  , I. Polyakov  31  , <lb/>E. Polycarpo  2  , A. Popov  35  , D. Popov  10,38  , B. Popovici  29  , C. Potterat  2  , E. Price  46  , J.D. Price  52  , <lb/>J. Prisciandaro  39  , A. Pritchard  52  , C. Prouve  46  , V. Pugatch  44  , A. Puig Navarro  39  , G. Punzi  23,s  , <lb/>W. Qian  4  , R. Quagliani  7,46  , B. Rachwal  26  , J.H. Rademacker  46  , B. Rakotomiaramanana  39  , <lb/>M. Rama  23  , M.S. Rangel  2  , I. Raniuk  43  , N. Rauschmayr  38  , G. Raven  42  , F. Redi  53  , S. Reichert  54  , <lb/>M.M. Reid  48  , A.C. dos Reis  1  , S. Ricciardi  49  , S. Richards  46  , M. Rihl  38  , K. Rinnert  52  , <lb/>V. Rives Molina  36  , P. Robbe  7,38  , A.B. Rodrigues  1  , E. Rodrigues  54  , J.A. Rodriguez Lopez  62  , <lb/>P. Rodriguez Perez  54  , S. Roiser  38  , V. Romanovsky  35  , A. Romero Vidal  37  , M. Rotondo  22  , <lb/></front>

			<page> 26 <lb/></page>

			<front> J. Rouvinet  39  , T. Ruf  38  , H. Ruiz  36  , P. Ruiz Valls  66  , J.J. Saborido Silva  37  , N. Sagidova  30  , <lb/>P. Sail  51  , B. Saitta  15,e  , V. Salustino Guimaraes  2  , C. Sanchez Mayordomo  66  , <lb/>B. Sanmartin Sedes  37  , R. Santacesaria  25  , C. Santamarina Rios  37  , M. Santimaria  18  , <lb/>E. Santovetti  24,l  , A. Sarti  18,m  , C. Satriano  25,n  , A. Satta  24  , D.M. Saunders  46  , D. Savrina  31,32  , <lb/>M. Schiller  38  , H. Schindler  38  , M. Schlupp  9  , M. Schmelling  10  , T. Schmelzer  9  , B. Schmidt  38  , <lb/>O. Schneider  39  , A. Schopper  38  , M. Schubiger  39  , M.-H. Schune  7  , R. Schwemmer  38  , B. Sciascia  18  , <lb/>A. Sciubba  25,m  , A. Semennikov  31  , I. Sepp  53  , N. Serra  40  , J. Serrano  6  , L. Sestini  22  , P. Seyfert  11  , <lb/>M. Shapkin  35  , I. Shapoval  16,43,f  , Y. Shcheglov  30  , T. Shears  52  , L. Shekhtman  34  , V. Shevchenko  64  , <lb/>A. Shires  9  , R. Silva Coutinho  48  , G. Simi  22  , M. Sirendi  47  , N. Skidmore  46  , I. Skillicorn  51  , <lb/>T. Skwarnicki  59  , E. Smith  55,49  , E. Smith  53  , J. Smith  47  , M. Smith  54  , H. Snoek  41  , <lb/>M.D. Sokoloff  57,38  , F.J.P. Soler  51  , F. Soomro  39  , D. Souza  46  , B. Souza De Paula  2  , B. Spaan  9  , <lb/>P. Spradlin  51  , S. Sridharan  38  , F. Stagni  38  , M. Stahl  11  , S. Stahl  38  , O. Steinkamp  40  , <lb/>O. Stenyakin  35  , F. Sterpka  59  , S. Stevenson  55  , S. Stoica  29  , S. Stone  59  , B. Storaci  40  , S. Stracka  23,t  , <lb/>M. Straticiuc  29  , U. Straumann  40  , L. Sun  57  , W. Sutcliffe  53  , K. Swientek  27  , S. Swientek  9  , <lb/>V. Syropoulos  42  , M. Szczekowski  28  , P. Szczypka  39,38  , T. Szumlak  27  , S. T&apos;Jampens  4  , <lb/>T. Tekampe  9  , M. Teklishyn  7  , G. Tellarini  16,f  , F. Teubert  38  , C. Thomas  55  , E. Thomas  38  , <lb/>J. van Tilburg  41  , V. Tisserand  4  , M. Tobin  39  , J. Todd  57  , S. Tolk  42  , L. Tomassetti  16,f  , <lb/>D. Tonelli  38  , S. Topp-Joergensen  55  , N. Torr  55  , E. Tournefier  4  , S. Tourneur  39  , K. Trabelsi  39  , <lb/>M.T. Tran  39  , M. Tresch  40  , A. Trisovic  38  , A. Tsaregorodtsev  6  , P. Tsopelas  41  , N. Tuning  41,38  , <lb/>A. Ukleja  28  , A. Ustyuzhanin  65,64  , U. Uwer  11  , C. Vacca  15,e  , V. Vagnoni  14  , G. Valenti  14  , <lb/>A. Vallier  7  , R. Vazquez Gomez  18  , P. Vazquez Regueiro  37  , C. Vázquez Sierra  37  , S. Vecchi  16  , <lb/>J.J. Velthuis  46  , M. Veltri  17,h  , G. Veneziano  39  , M. Vesterinen  11  , B. Viaud  7  , D. Vieira  2  , <lb/>M. Vieites Diaz  37  , X. Vilasis-Cardona  36,p  , A. Vollhardt  40  , D. Volyanskyy  10  , D. Voong  46  , <lb/>A. Vorobyev  30  , V. Vorobyev  34  , C. Voß  63  , J.A. de Vries  41  , R. Waldi  63  , C. Wallace  48  , R. Wallace  12  , <lb/>J. Walsh  23  , S. Wandernoth  11  , J. Wang  59  , D.R. Ward  47  , N.K. Watson  45  , D. Websdale  53  , <lb/>A. Weiden  40  , M. Whitehead  48  , D. Wiedner  11  , G. Wilkinson  55,38  , M. Wilkinson  59  , M. Williams  38  , <lb/>M.P. Williams  45  , M. Williams  56  , F.F. Wilson  49  , J. Wimberley  58  , J. Wishahi  9  , W. Wislicki  28  , <lb/>M. Witek  26  , G. Wormser  7  , S.A. Wotton  47  , S. Wright  47  , K. Wyllie  38  , Y. Xie  61  , Z. Xu  39  , Z. Yang  3  , <lb/>X. Yuan  34  , O. Yushchenko  35  , M. Zangoli  14  , M. Zavertyaev  10,b  , L. Zhang  3  , Y. Zhang  3  , <lb/>A. Zhelezov  11  , A. Zhokhov  31  , L. Zhong  3  . <lb/> 1  Centro Brasileiro de Pesquisas Físicas (CBPF), Rio de Janeiro, Brazil <lb/> 2  Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro (UFRJ), Rio de Janeiro, Brazil <lb/> 3  Center for High Energy Physics, Tsinghua University, Beijing, China <lb/> 4  LAPP, Université Savoie Mont-Blanc, CNRS/IN2P3, Annecy-Le-Vieux, France <lb/> 5  Clermont Université, Université Blaise Pascal, CNRS/IN2P3, LPC, Clermont-Ferrand, France <lb/> 6  CPPM, Aix-Marseille Université, CNRS/IN2P3, Marseille, France <lb/> 7  LAL, Université Paris-Sud, CNRS/IN2P3, Orsay, France <lb/> 8  LPNHE, Université Pierre et Marie Curie, Université Paris Diderot, CNRS/IN2P3, Paris, France <lb/> 9  Fakultät Physik, Technische Universität Dortmund, Dortmund, Germany <lb/> 10  Max-Planck-Institut für Kernphysik (MPIK), Heidelberg, Germany <lb/> 11  Physikalisches Institut, Ruprecht-Karls-Universität Heidelberg, Heidelberg, Germany <lb/> 12  School of Physics, University College Dublin, Dublin, Ireland <lb/> 13  Sezione INFN di Bari, Bari, Italy <lb/> 14  Sezione INFN di Bologna, Bologna, Italy <lb/> 15  Sezione INFN di Cagliari, Cagliari, Italy <lb/> 16  Sezione INFN di Ferrara, Ferrara, Italy <lb/> 17  Sezione INFN di Firenze, Firenze, Italy <lb/></front>

			<page> 27 <lb/></page>

			<front> 18  Laboratori Nazionali dell&apos;INFN di Frascati, Frascati, Italy <lb/> 19  Sezione INFN di Genova, Genova, Italy <lb/> 20  Sezione INFN di Milano Bicocca, Milano, Italy <lb/> 21  Sezione INFN di Milano, Milano, Italy <lb/> 22  Sezione INFN di Padova, Padova, Italy <lb/> 23  Sezione INFN di Pisa, Pisa, Italy <lb/> 24  Sezione INFN di Roma Tor Vergata, Roma, Italy <lb/> 25  Sezione INFN di Roma La Sapienza, Roma, Italy <lb/> 26  Henryk Niewodniczanski Institute of Nuclear Physics Polish Academy of Sciences, Kraków, Poland <lb/> 27  AGH -University of Science and Technology, Faculty of Physics and Applied Computer Science, <lb/>Kraków, Poland <lb/> 28  National Center for Nuclear Research (NCBJ), Warsaw, Poland <lb/> 29  Horia Hulubei National Institute of Physics and Nuclear Engineering, Bucharest-Magurele, Romania <lb/> 30  Petersburg Nuclear Physics Institute (PNPI), Gatchina, Russia <lb/> 31  Institute of Theoretical and Experimental Physics (ITEP), Moscow, Russia <lb/> 32  Institute of Nuclear Physics, Moscow State University (SINP MSU), Moscow, Russia <lb/> 33  Institute for Nuclear Research of the Russian Academy of Sciences (INR RAN), Moscow, Russia <lb/> 34  Budker Institute of Nuclear Physics (SB RAS) and Novosibirsk State University, Novosibirsk, Russia <lb/> 35  Institute for High Energy Physics (IHEP), Protvino, Russia <lb/> 36  Universitat de Barcelona, Barcelona, Spain <lb/> 37  Universidad de Santiago de Compostela, Santiago de Compostela, Spain <lb/> 38  European Organization for Nuclear Research (CERN), Geneva, Switzerland <lb/> 39  Ecole Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL), Lausanne, Switzerland <lb/> 40  Physik-Institut, Universität Zürich, Zürich, Switzerland <lb/> 41  Nikhef National Institute for Subatomic Physics, Amsterdam, The Netherlands <lb/> 42  Nikhef National Institute for Subatomic Physics and VU University Amsterdam, Amsterdam, The <lb/>Netherlands <lb/> 43  NSC Kharkiv Institute of Physics and Technology (NSC KIPT), Kharkiv, Ukraine <lb/> 44  Institute for Nuclear Research of the National Academy of Sciences (KINR), Kyiv, Ukraine <lb/> 45  University of Birmingham, Birmingham, United Kingdom <lb/> 46  H.H. Wills Physics Laboratory, University of Bristol, Bristol, United Kingdom <lb/> 47  Cavendish Laboratory, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, United Kingdom <lb/> 48  Department of Physics, University of Warwick, Coventry, United Kingdom <lb/> 49  STFC Rutherford Appleton Laboratory, Didcot, United Kingdom <lb/> 50  School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, United Kingdom <lb/> 51  School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Glasgow, Glasgow, United Kingdom <lb/> 52  Oliver Lodge Laboratory, University of Liverpool, Liverpool, United Kingdom <lb/> 53  Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom <lb/> 54  School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Manchester, Manchester, United Kingdom <lb/> 55  Department of Physics, University of Oxford, Oxford, United Kingdom <lb/> 56  Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA, United States <lb/> 57  University of Cincinnati, Cincinnati, OH, United States <lb/> 58  University of Maryland, College Park, MD, United States <lb/> 59  Syracuse University, Syracuse, NY, United States <lb/> 60  Pontifícia Universidade Católica do Rio de Janeiro (PUC-Rio), Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, associated to <lb/> 2 <lb/>61  Institute of Particle Physics, Central China Normal University, Wuhan, Hubei, China, associated to <lb/> 3 <lb/>62  Departamento de Fisica , Universidad Nacional de Colombia, Bogota, Colombia, associated to <lb/> 8 <lb/>63  Institut für Physik, Universität Rostock, Rostock, Germany, associated to <lb/> 11 <lb/>64  National Research Centre Kurchatov Institute, Moscow, Russia, associated to <lb/> 31 <lb/>65  Yandex School of Data Analysis, Moscow, Russia, associated to <lb/> 31 <lb/>66  Instituto de Fisica Corpuscular (IFIC), Universitat de Valencia-CSIC, Valencia, Spain, associated to <lb/> 36 <lb/>67  Van Swinderen Institute, University of Groningen, Groningen, The Netherlands, associated to <lb/> 41 <lb/></front>

			<page> 28 <lb/></page>

			<front> a  Universidade Federal do Triângulo Mineiro (UFTM), Uberaba-MG, Brazil <lb/> b  P.N. Lebedev Physical Institute, Russian Academy of Science (LPI RAS), Moscow, Russia <lb/> c  Universià di Bari, Bari, Italy <lb/> d  Universià di Bologna, Bologna, Italy <lb/> e  Universià di Cagliari, Cagliari, Italy <lb/> f  Universià di Ferrara, Ferrara, Italy <lb/> g  Universià di Firenze, Firenze, Italy <lb/> h  Universià di Urbino, Urbino, Italy <lb/> i  Universià di Modena e Reggio Emilia, Modena, Italy <lb/> j  Universià di Genova, Genova, Italy <lb/> k  Universià di Milano Bicocca, Milano, Italy <lb/> l  Universià di Roma Tor Vergata, Roma, Italy <lb/> m  Universià di Roma La Sapienza, Roma, Italy <lb/> n  Universià della Basilicata, Potenza, Italy <lb/> o  AGH -University of Science and Technology, Faculty of Computer Science, Electronics and <lb/>Telecommunications, Kraków, Poland <lb/> p  LIFAELS, La Salle, Universitat Ramon Llull, Barcelona, Spain <lb/> q  Hanoi University of Science, Hanoi, Viet Nam <lb/> r  Universià di Padova, Padova, Italy <lb/> s  Universià di Pisa, Pisa, Italy <lb/> t  Scuola Normale Superiore, Pisa, Italy <lb/> u  Universià degli Studi di Milano, Milano, Italy <lb/> v  Politecnico di Milano, Milano, Italy <lb/>  †  Deceased <lb/></front>

			<page> 29 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
