<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> EUROPEAN ORGANIZATION FOR NUCLEAR RESEARCH (CERN) <lb/> CERN-PH-EP-2015-107 <lb/>LHCb-PAPER-2015-017 <lb/>May 7, 2015 <lb/> Amplitude analysis of <lb/> B  0  → D  0  K  +  π  −  decays <lb/> The LHCb collaboration <lb/>  † <lb/> Abstract <lb/> The Dalitz plot distribution of B  0  → D  0  K  +  π  −  decays is studied using a data sample <lb/>corresponding to 3.0 fb <lb/> −1  of pp collision data recorded by the LHCb experiment <lb/>during 2011 and 2012. The data are described by an amplitude model that contains <lb/>contributions from intermediate K  *  (892)  0  , K  *  (1410)  0  , K  * <lb/> 2  (1430)  0  and D  * <lb/> 2  (2460)  − <lb/> resonances. The model also contains components to describe broad structures, <lb/>including the K  * <lb/> 0  (1430)  0  and D  * <lb/> 0  (2400)  −  resonances, in the Kπ S-wave and the Dπ S-<lb/>and P-waves. The masses and widths of the D  * <lb/> 0  (2400)  −  and D  * <lb/> 2  (2460)  −  resonances <lb/>are measured, as are the complex amplitudes and fit fractions for all components <lb/>included in the amplitude model. The model obtained will be an integral part <lb/>of a future determination of the angle γ of the CKM quark mixing matrix using <lb/> B  0  → DK  +  π  −  decays. <lb/> Submitted to Phys. Rev. D <lb/> c <lb/> CERN on behalf of the LHCb collaboration, licence CC-BY-4.0. <lb/>  †  Authors are listed at the end of this paper. <lb/> arXiv:1505.01505v1  [hep-ex] 6 May 2015 <lb/></front>

			<page> ii <lb/></page>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> Dalitz plot (DP) analysis of B <lb/> 0  → DK <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays has been proposed as a way to measure <lb/>the unitarity triangle angle γ [1, 2]. The sensitivity to γ ≡ arg [−V  ud  V <lb/>  * <lb/> ub  /(V  cd  V <lb/>  * <lb/> cb  )], where <lb/> V  xy  are elements of the Cabibbo-Kobayashi-Maskawa (CKM) quark mixing matrix [3, 4], <lb/>originates from the interference of ¯ b → ¯ <lb/> cu¯ s and ¯ b → ¯ <lb/> uc¯ s amplitudes. Such interference <lb/>occurs when the neutral D meson is reconstructed in a final state that is accessible to both <lb/> D <lb/> 0  and D <lb/> 0  decays and therefore corresponds to an admixture of the two states [5, 6]. One <lb/>of the largest components of the B <lb/> 0  → DK <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  final state is B <lb/> 0  → DK <lb/>  *  (892) <lb/> 0  , for which <lb/>both ¯ b → ¯ <lb/> cu¯ s and ¯ b → ¯ <lb/> uc¯ s amplitudes are colour suppressed, making them comparable <lb/>in magnitude and potentially enhancing CP violation effects [7]. Decay diagrams for the <lb/>quasi-two-body contributions from B <lb/> 0  → DK <lb/>  *  (892) <lb/> 0  and B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> −  K <lb/> +  decays <lb/>are shown in Fig. 1. Observables sensitive to γ have been measured by LHCb with a <lb/>quasi-two-body approach [8], but a DP analysis is expected to be more sensitive because <lb/>interference between resonances provides the possibility to resolve ambiguities in the <lb/>determination of γ. <lb/> In order to determine γ with this method, it is necessary to have an amplitude model <lb/>of the B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decay that proceeds through the favoured ¯ b → ¯ <lb/> cu¯ s transition. This <lb/>can be achieved by reconstructing the D <lb/> 0  meson through the K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decay; in this way <lb/>the contribution from the ¯ b → ¯ <lb/> cu¯ s amplitude is dominant and effects due to ¯ b → ¯ <lb/> uc¯ s <lb/> amplitudes can be neglected. While the analysis of this decay chain is not itself sensitive to <lb/> γ, its outcome will be an integral part of a future analysis using, for example, D → K <lb/> +  K <lb/> − <lb/> decays where CP violation effects are expected as the final state is common to both D <lb/> 0 <lb/> and D <lb/> 0  decays. <lb/>Dalitz plot analyses of B meson decays to final states containing a charmed meson and <lb/>two charged particles (either pions or kaons) also provide opportunities for studies of the <lb/>spectroscopy of charmed mesons. Results in this area have recently been obtained from DP <lb/>analyses of B <lb/> 0 <lb/> s  → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> −  π <lb/> +  [9, 10], B <lb/> +  → D <lb/> −  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> +  [11] and B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  [12] decays, <lb/>all from LHCb. As the branching fraction for B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays is smaller than that <lb/>for B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays, the analysis presented in this paper is not as sensitive to the <lb/>parameters of charm resonances as that of Ref. [12]. However, the much larger sample of B <lb/> 0 <lb/> B <lb/> b <lb/>d <lb/> 0 <lb/> (892) <lb/> K* <lb/>s <lb/>d <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/>c <lb/>u <lb/> + <lb/> W <lb/> (a) <lb/> 0 <lb/> B <lb/> b <lb/>d <lb/> -<lb/> (2460) <lb/> 2 <lb/> D* <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/>s <lb/>u <lb/> + <lb/> W <lb/> (b) <lb/> Figure 1: Decay diagrams for the quasi-two-body contributions to B  0  → DK  +  π  −  from (a) <lb/> B  0  → DK  *  (892)  0  and (b) B  0  → D  * <lb/> 2  (2460)  −  K  +  decays. <lb/></body>

			<page> 1 <lb/></page>

			<body> mesons available at LHCb compared to that used in the only other published DP analysis <lb/>of B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays from the Belle collaboration [13] allows useful results on excited <lb/>charm mesons to be obtained. Moreover, results on charm meson spectroscopy obtained <lb/>from DP analysis of B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays provide important independent cross-checks <lb/>of results from studies of the B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  DP, as possible biases due to other structures <lb/>in the Dalitz plots are different between the two modes. <lb/>In this paper an amplitude analysis of the B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decay is reported. The <lb/>inclusion of charge-conjugate processes is implied throughout the paper. The analysis <lb/>is based on a data sample corresponding to an integrated luminosity of 3.0 fb <lb/> −1  of pp <lb/> collision data collected with the LHCb detector in 2011 and 2012, when the collision <lb/>centre-of-mass energy was <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 7 TeV (1.0 fb <lb/> −1  ) and <lb/> √ <lb/> s = 8 TeV (2.0 fb <lb/> −1  ), respectively. <lb/>Previously, the branching fraction for the three-body decay has been measured [14, 15], <lb/>and the B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/>  *  (892) <lb/> 0  [16, 17] and B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> −  K <lb/> +  [14] contributions have been <lb/>measured using quasi-two-body approaches; however this is the first DP analysis of the <lb/> B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decay. <lb/>The paper is organised as follows. A description of the LHCb detector, reconstruction <lb/>and simulation software is given in Sec. 2. The selection of signal candidates is described <lb/>in Sec. 3, and the determination of signal and background yields is presented in Sec. 4. <lb/>An overview of the Dalitz plot analysis formalism is given in Sec. 5, and details of the <lb/>implementation of the amplitude analysis are presented in Sec. 6. The evaluation of <lb/>systematic uncertainties is described in Sec. 7, with results and a brief summary given in <lb/>Sec. 8. <lb/> 2 LHCb detector and software <lb/> The LHCb detector [18,19] is a single-arm forward spectrometer covering the pseudorapidity <lb/>range 2 &lt; η &lt; 5, designed for the study of particles containing b or c quarks. The detector <lb/>includes a high-precision tracking system consisting of a silicon-strip vertex detector [20] <lb/>surrounding the pp interaction region, a large-area silicon-strip detector located upstream <lb/>of a dipole magnet with a bending power of about 4 Tm, and three stations of silicon-strip <lb/>detectors and straw drift tubes [21] placed downstream of the magnet. The polarity of <lb/>the dipole magnet is reversed periodically throughout data-taking. The tracking system <lb/>provides a measurement of momentum, p, of charged particles with a relative uncertainty <lb/>that varies from 0.5% at low momentum to 1.0% at 200 GeV (natural units with c =  = 1 <lb/>are used). The minimum distance of a track to a primary vertex, the impact parameter <lb/>(IP), is measured with a resolution of (15 + 29/p  T  ) µm, where p  T  is the component of <lb/>the momentum transverse to the beam, in GeV. Different types of charged hadrons <lb/>are distinguished using information from two ring-imaging Cherenkov detectors [22]. <lb/>Photon, electron and hadron candidates are identified by a calorimeter system consisting of <lb/>scintillating-pad and preshower detectors, an electromagnetic calorimeter and a hadronic <lb/>calorimeter. Muons are identified by a system composed of alternating layers of iron and <lb/>multiwire proportional chambers [23]. <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body> The trigger [24] consists of a hardware stage, based on information from the calorimeter <lb/>and muon systems, followed by a software stage, in which all tracks with p  T  &gt; 500 (300) MeV <lb/>are reconstructed for data collected in 2011 (2012). The software trigger used in this <lb/>analysis requires a two-, three-or four-track secondary vertex with significant displacement <lb/>from any primary pp interaction vertex (PV). At least one charged particle must have <lb/> p  T  &gt; 1.7 GeV and be inconsistent with originating from a PV. A multivariate algorithm [25] <lb/>is used for the identification of secondary vertices consistent with the decay of a b hadron. <lb/>In the offline selection, the objects that prompted a positive trigger decision are <lb/>associated with reconstructed particles. Selection requirements can therefore be made not <lb/>only on whether the hardware trigger decision was due to a signature in the calorimeters <lb/>or in the muon system, but on whether the decision was due to the signal candidate, other <lb/>particles produced in the pp collision, or a combination of both. Signal candidates are <lb/>accepted offline if at least one of the final-state particles created a cluster in the hadronic <lb/>calorimeter with sufficient transverse energy to fire the hardware trigger. Events that are <lb/>triggered at the hardware level by another particle in the event are also retained. After <lb/>all selection requirements are imposed, 67 % of events in the sample were triggered by <lb/>the decay products of the signal candidate, while the remainder were triggered only by <lb/>another particle in the event. <lb/>Simulated events are used to characterise the detector response to signal and certain <lb/>types of background events. In the simulation, pp collisions are generated using Pythia [26] <lb/>with a specific LHCb configuration [27]. Decays of hadronic particles are described <lb/>by EvtGen [28], in which final-state radiation is generated using Photos [29]. The <lb/>interaction of the generated particles with the detector, and its response, are implemented <lb/>using the Geant4 toolkit [30] as described in Ref. [31]. <lb/> 3 Selection requirements <lb/> The selection requirements follow closely those used in Ref. [10]. The more copious <lb/> B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decay is topologically and kinematically similar to the B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> − <lb/> channel, allowing it to be used as a control mode to optimise the selection requirements. <lb/>Loose initial requirements are used to obtain a visible signal peak of D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  candidates. <lb/>The tracks are required to be of good quality and must be above thresholds in p, p  T  and <lb/> χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  , where χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  is defined as the difference in χ <lb/> 2  of a given PV reconstructed with and <lb/>without the considered particle. The D <lb/> 0  → K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  candidate must satisfy criteria on its <lb/>vertex quality (χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>vtx  ) and flight distance from any PV and from the B candidate vertex, <lb/>and must have invariant mass m(K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) in the range 1814–1914 MeV. A requirement <lb/>on the output of a boosted decision tree that identifies D <lb/> 0  → K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays originating <lb/>from b hadron decays (D <lb/> 0  BDT) [32, 33] is also applied. Candidate B mesons are selected <lb/>with requirements on invariant mass, χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  and on the cosine of the angle between the B <lb/> momentum vector and the line from the PV under consideration to the B vertex (cos θ  dir  ). <lb/>A requirement is placed on the χ <lb/> 2  of a kinematic fit [34] to the candidate&apos;s decay chain in <lb/>which the D <lb/> 0  mass is constrained to its nominal value. The four final-state tracks must <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body> satisfy pion and kaon particle identification (PID) criteria. <lb/>A neural network [35] is used to discriminate between signal decays and combinatorial <lb/>background. The sPlot technique [36], with the B candidate mass as the discriminating <lb/>variable, is used to separate statistically B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays from background. The <lb/>signal and background weights returned by this method are applied to the candidates, <lb/>which are then used to train the network. The network is trained using 16 variables. They <lb/>include the χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  of the four final-state tracks and the following variables associated to <lb/>the D <lb/> 0  candidate: χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  , χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>vtx  , the square of the flight distance from the PV divided by <lb/>its uncertainty squared (χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>flight  ), cos θ  dir  , and the output of the D <lb/> 0  BDT. In addition, the <lb/>following variables associated to the B candidate are included: p  T  , χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>IP  , χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>vtx  , χ <lb/> 2 <lb/>flight  , and <lb/>cos θ  dir  . The p  T  asymmetry [10] and track multiplicity in a cone with half-angle of 1.5 <lb/>units of the plane of pseudorapidity and azimuthal angle (measured in radians) around <lb/>the B candidate flight direction, which contain information about the isolation of the B <lb/> candidate from the rest of the event, are also used. The input quantities to the neural <lb/>network depend only weakly on the position of the candidate in the B decay Dalitz plot <lb/>and therefore any requirement on the network output cannot appreciably bias the DP <lb/>distribution. A requirement imposed on the network output reduces the combinatorial <lb/>background remaining after the initial selection by a factor of five while retaining more <lb/>than 90 % of the signal. <lb/>The B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  candidates must satisfy the same selection as the B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> − <lb/> decays, except for the PID requirement on the positively charged track from the B decay <lb/>vertex, which is imposed to preferentially select kaons rather than pions. The PID efficiency <lb/>is evaluated from calibration samples of D <lb/> 0  → K <lb/> −  π <lb/> +  decays from the D <lb/>  * +  → D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> +  decay <lb/>chain. The kinematics of this decay chain can be exploited to obtain clean samples without <lb/>using the PID information [22]. The PID efficiency of the requirements on the four tracks <lb/>in the final state is around 50 % and varies depending on the kinematics of the tracks, as <lb/>described in detail in Sec. 6.1. <lb/>Candidates are vetoed when the difference between m(K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  π <lb/> −  ) and m(K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) lies <lb/>within ±2.5 MeV of the known D <lb/>  *  (2010) <lb/> −  –D <lb/> 0  mass difference [37] to remove background <lb/>containing D <lb/>  * −  → D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  decays. Candidates are also rejected if a similar mass difference <lb/>calculated with the pion mass hypothesis applied to the bachelor kaon satisfies the same <lb/>criterion. To reject backgrounds from B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> −  K <lb/> +  , D <lb/> −  → K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  π <lb/> −  decays, it is required <lb/>that the combination of the pion from the D <lb/> 0  candidate together with the two bachelor <lb/>particles does not have an invariant mass in the range 1850–1890 MeV. Additionally, <lb/>candidates are removed if the pion and kaon originating directly from the B <lb/> 0  decay <lb/>combine to give an invariant mass consistent with that of the D <lb/> 0  meson (1835–1880 MeV). <lb/>This removes candidates with the D <lb/> 0  wrongly reconstructed as well as potential background <lb/>from B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  D <lb/> 0  decays. Other incorrectly reconstructed candidates are removed by <lb/>vetoing candidates where the pion from the D <lb/> 0  decay and the kaon originating directly <lb/>from the B <lb/> 0  decay give an invariant mass in the range 1850–1885 MeV. At least one of <lb/>the pion candidates is required to have no associated hits in the muon system to remove <lb/>potential background from B <lb/> 0  → J/ψ K <lb/>  * 0  decays. Charmless decays of b hadrons are <lb/>suppressed by the use of the D <lb/> 0  BDT and further reduced to a negligible level by requiring <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body> that the D <lb/> 0  candidate vertex is separated from the B <lb/> 0  decay vertex by at least 1 mm. <lb/>Signal candidates are retained for further analysis if they have invariant mass in the <lb/>range 5100–5900 MeV. After all selection requirements are applied, fewer than 1 % of <lb/>selected events also contain a second candidate. Such multiple candidates are retained and <lb/>treated in the same manner as other candidates; the associated systematic uncertainty is <lb/>negligible. <lb/> 4 Determination of signal and background yields <lb/> The signal and background yields are determined from an extended maximum likelihood <lb/>fit to the B candidate invariant mass distribution. The fit allows for signal decays, <lb/>combinatorial background and contributions from other b hadron decays. The decay chain <lb/> B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/>  * 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  with D <lb/>  * 0  → D <lb/> 0  γ or D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> 0  forms a partially reconstructed background <lb/>that peaks at low B candidate mass as the neutral particle is not included in the candidate. <lb/>Misidentified B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> ( * )0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  , Λ <lb/> 0 <lb/> b  → D <lb/> ( * )0  K <lb/> +  p and B <lb/> 0 <lb/>(s)  → D <lb/> ( * )0  K <lb/> +  K <lb/> −  decays are found <lb/>to contribute to the background. A possible contribution from the highly suppressed <lb/> B <lb/> 0 <lb/> s  → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decay mode is also included in the fit. <lb/>The signal peak is modelled with the sum of two Crystal Ball [38] functions, which <lb/>have tails on opposite sides and which share a common mean. The tail parameters are <lb/>fixed to the values found in fits to simulated signal decays. The relative normalisation <lb/>and the ratio of widths of the two functions are constrained, within uncertainties, to <lb/>the values determined in a fit to B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  data. The B <lb/> 0 <lb/> s  → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  shape is <lb/>modelled identically to the signal peak, with the difference between the B <lb/> 0  and B <lb/> 0 <lb/> s  mass <lb/>peak positions fixed to its known value [37]. An exponential shape is used to model the <lb/>combinatorial background. <lb/>Misidentified and partially reconstructed backgrounds are modelled with smoothed <lb/>non-parametric functions. Simulated samples are used to obtain the shape for B <lb/> 0  → <lb/> D <lb/>  * 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays, with the D <lb/>  * 0  → D <lb/> 0  γ and D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> 0  contributions generated in the correct <lb/>proportions [37]. To account for differences between simulation and data, for example <lb/>in the polarisation of the D <lb/>  * 0  meson, the B candidate invariant mass distribution for <lb/>partially reconstructed B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/>  * 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays is allowed to be shifted by an offset that <lb/>is a free parameter of the fit. The misidentified background shapes are also obtained <lb/>from simulated samples. For B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> ( * )0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays the D <lb/> 0  and D <lb/>  * 0  contributions are <lb/>combined according to their relative branching fractions [37]. The backgrounds from <lb/> Λ <lb/> 0 <lb/> b  → D <lb/> ( * )0  K <lb/> +  p and B <lb/> 0 <lb/>(s)  → D <lb/> ( * )0  K <lb/> +  K <lb/> −  decays are assumed to have equal branching <lb/>fractions for the decays with D <lb/> 0  and D <lb/>  * 0  mesons in the final state, as the decays involving <lb/> D <lb/>  * 0  mesons have not yet been measured. The simulated samples are reweighted according <lb/>to the relevant particle identification and misidentification probabilities and to match known <lb/>DP distributions [12, 39–41]. The (mis)identification probabilities take account of track <lb/>kinematics and are calculated using calibration samples of D <lb/>  * +  → D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> +  , D <lb/> 0  → K <lb/> −  π <lb/> + <lb/> and Λ → pπ <lb/> −  decays [19, 22]. The yields of the misidentified backgrounds relative to the <lb/>signal are constrained, within uncertainties, to their expected values based on their known <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body> Table 1: Yields from the fit to the D  0  K  +  π  −  data sample. The full mass range is 5100–5900 MeV <lb/>and the signal region is 5248.55–5309.05 MeV. <lb/> Component <lb/> Full mass range Signal region <lb/> B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> − <lb/> 2576 ± 72 <lb/>2344 ± 66 <lb/> B <lb/> 0 <lb/> s  → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> − <lb/> 55 ± 27 <lb/>1 ± 1 <lb/>comb. bkgd. <lb/>5540 ± 187 <lb/>684 ± 23 <lb/> B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/>  * 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> − <lb/> 1750 ± 99 <lb/>6 ± 1 <lb/> B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> ( * )0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> − <lb/> 485 ± 47 <lb/>51 ± 5 <lb/> Λ <lb/> 0 <lb/> b  → D <lb/> ( * )0  K <lb/> +  p <lb/> 95 ± 26 <lb/>18 ± 5 <lb/> B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> ( * )0  K <lb/> +  K <lb/> − <lb/> 127 ± 27 <lb/>10 ± 2 <lb/> B <lb/> 0 <lb/> s  → D <lb/> ( * )0  K <lb/> +  K <lb/> − <lb/> 54 ± 18 <lb/>14 ± 5 <lb/> ) [MeV] <lb/> -<lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 5200 <lb/>5400 <lb/>5600 <lb/>5800 <lb/> Candidates / 8 MeV <lb/> 0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>700 <lb/> LHCb (a) <lb/> Data <lb/> Total fit <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/> → <lb/> (s) <lb/>0 <lb/> B <lb/> Combinatorial bkg. <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> * 0 <lb/> D <lb/> → <lb/> 0 <lb/> B <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> π <lb/> * <lb/> ( )0 <lb/> D <lb/> → <lb/> 0 <lb/> B <lb/>p <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> * <lb/> ( )0 <lb/> D <lb/> → <lb/> 0 <lb/>b <lb/> Λ <lb/> − <lb/> K <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> * <lb/> ( )0 <lb/> D <lb/> → <lb/> (s) <lb/>0 <lb/> B <lb/> ) [MeV] <lb/> -<lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 5200 <lb/>5400 <lb/>5600 <lb/>5800 <lb/> Candidates / 8 MeV <lb/> 1 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> (b) <lb/>LHCb <lb/> Figure 2: Results of the fit to the B candidate invariant mass distribution with (a) linear and <lb/>(b) logarithmic y-axis scales. The components are as described in the legend. <lb/> branching fractions [12, 39, 40] and misidentification probabilities. <lb/>There are 14 free parameters in the fit model: the mean and width of the signal shape, <lb/>the relative normalisation and relative width of the two Crystal Ball functions, the slope <lb/>of the exponential function, the offset of the B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/>  * 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  shape and the yields of the <lb/>eight contributions. The result of the fit is shown in Fig. 2 and the yields are summarised <lb/>in Table 1. The yields are also reported within the signal region used in the Dalitz plot <lb/>fit, corresponding to ±2.5 widths of the B <lb/> 0  signal shape (5248.55–5309.05 MeV). The <lb/>distribution of candidates in the signal region over the Dalitz plot is shown in Fig. 3(a). <lb/>Note that a B <lb/> 0  mass constraint is applied to calculate the variables that are used to <lb/>describe the Dalitz plot [42], improving the resolution of those variables and giving a <lb/>unique kinematic boundary. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body> ] <lb/> 2 <lb/> ) [GeV <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/> ( <lb/> 2 <lb/> m <lb/> 5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/> ] <lb/> 2 <lb/> ) [GeV <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ( <lb/> 2 <lb/> m <lb/> 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/> (a) <lb/>LHCb <lb/> &apos; <lb/> m <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> &apos; <lb/> θ <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1 <lb/> (b) <lb/>LHCb <lb/> Figure 3: Distribution of B  0  → D  0  K  +  π  −  candidates in the signal region over (a) the Dalitz plot <lb/>and (b) the square Dalitz plot. The definition of the square Dalitz plot is given in Sec. 6.1. <lb/> 5 Dalitz plot analysis formalism <lb/> In B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays, resonances are expected in the m <lb/> 2  (D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ) and m <lb/> 2  (K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) <lb/>combinations, so the Dalitz plot shown in Fig. 3(a) is defined in terms of these two <lb/>invariant mass squared terms. For a fixed B <lb/> 0  mass, these two invariant mass squared <lb/>combinations can be used to calculate all other relevant kinematic quantities. <lb/>The isobar model [43–45] is used to describe the complex decay amplitude. The total <lb/>amplitude is given by the coherent sum of amplitudes from resonant and nonresonant <lb/>intermediate contributions and is given by <lb/> A <lb/> m <lb/> 2  (D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ), m <lb/> 2  (K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) <lb/> = <lb/> N <lb/> j=1 <lb/> c  j  F  j <lb/> m <lb/> 2  (D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ), m <lb/> 2  (K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) <lb/> , <lb/> (1) <lb/>where c  j  are complex coefficients describing the relative contribution for each intermediate <lb/>process. The resonant dynamics are contained in the F  j <lb/> m <lb/> 2  (D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ), m <lb/> 2  (K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) <lb/> terms <lb/>that are normalised such that the integral of the squared magnitude over the DP is unity <lb/>for each term. For a D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  resonance F  j <lb/> m <lb/> 2  (D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ), m <lb/> 2  (K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) <lb/> is given by <lb/> F <lb/> m <lb/> 2  (D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ), m <lb/> 2  (K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) <lb/> = R <lb/> m(D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ) <lb/> × X(| p | r  BW  ) × X(| q | r  BW  ) × T ( p, q ) , (2) <lb/>where <lb/>p is the bachelor particle momentum and q is the momentum of one of the resonance <lb/>daughters, both evaluated in the D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  rest frame. The functions R, X and T are described <lb/>below. <lb/>The X(z) terms are Blatt–Weisskopf barrier factors [46], where z = | q | r  BW  or | p | r  BW <lb/> and r  BW  is the barrier radius which is set to 4.0 GeV <lb/> −1  ≈ 0.8 fm [10] for all resonances. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body> The barrier factors are angular momentum dependent and are given by <lb/> L = 0 : X(z) = 1 , <lb/>L = 1 : X(z) = <lb/> 1+z  2 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1+z  2  , <lb/>L = 2 : X(z) = <lb/> z  4 <lb/>0  +3z  2 <lb/>0  +9 <lb/> z  4  +3z  2  +9 <lb/> , <lb/>L = 3 : X(z) = <lb/> z  6 <lb/>0  +6z  4 <lb/>0  +45z  2 <lb/>0  +225 <lb/> z  6  +6z  4  +45z  2  +225 <lb/> , <lb/> (3) <lb/>where z  0  is the value of z at the pole mass of the resonance and L is the orbital angular <lb/>momentum between the resonance and the bachelor particle. Since the parent and daughter <lb/>particles all have zero spin, L is also the spin of the resonance. <lb/>The T ( p, q) terms describe the angular distributions in the Zemach tensor formalism [47, <lb/>48] and are given by <lb/> L = 0 : T ( p, q) = 1 , <lb/>L = 1 : T ( p, q) = − 2 <lb/>p · q , <lb/>L = 2 : T ( p, q) = <lb/> 4 <lb/>3 <lb/> [3( p · q ) <lb/> 2  − (| p || q |) <lb/> 2  ] , <lb/>L = 3 : T ( p, q) = − <lb/> 24 <lb/>15 <lb/> [5( p · q ) <lb/> 3  − 3( p · q )(| p || q |) <lb/> 2  ] . <lb/> (4) <lb/>These expressions are proportional to the Legendre polynomials, P  L  (x), where x is the <lb/>cosine of the angle between <lb/>p and q (referred to as the helicity angle). <lb/>The R <lb/> m(D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ) <lb/> functions are the mass lineshapes. Resonant contributions are <lb/>typically described by the relativistic Breit–Wigner (RBW) function <lb/> R(m) = <lb/>1 <lb/>(m <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  − m  2  ) − i m  0  Γ(m) <lb/> , <lb/> (5) <lb/>where the mass-dependent decay width is <lb/>Γ(m) = Γ  0 <lb/> q <lb/>q  0 <lb/>  2L+1 <lb/>  m  0 <lb/> m <lb/> X <lb/> 2  (q r  BW  ) , <lb/> (6) <lb/>where q  0  is the value of q = | q | when the invariant mass is equal to the pole mass of the <lb/>resonance, m  0  . <lb/>The large phase space available in B decays allows for the presence of nonresonant <lb/>amplitudes (i.e. contributions that do not proceed via a known resonance) that vary across <lb/>the Dalitz plot. An exponential form factor (EFF) has been found to describe nonresonant <lb/>contributions well in several DP analyses of B decays [49], <lb/> R(m) = exp <lb/> −αm <lb/> 2 <lb/> , <lb/> (7) <lb/>where α is a shape parameter that must be determined from the data and m is a two-body <lb/>invariant mass (m(D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ) in this example). <lb/>The RBW function is a good model for narrow resonances that are well separated from <lb/>any other resonant or nonresonant contribution of the same spin. This approach is known <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body> to break down in the Kπ S-wave because the K <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (1430) resonance interferes strongly with <lb/>a slowly varying nonresonant term, as described in Ref. [50]. The LASS lineshape [51] has <lb/>been developed to combine these two contributions, <lb/> R(m) = <lb/> m <lb/>q cot δ  B  − iq <lb/> + exp [2iδ  B  ] <lb/> m  0  Γ  0 <lb/> m  0 <lb/> q  0 <lb/> (m <lb/> 2 <lb/>0  − m  2  ) − im  0  Γ  0 <lb/> q <lb/>m <lb/>m  0 <lb/> q  0 <lb/> , <lb/> (8) <lb/>where cot δ  B  = <lb/>1 <lb/> aq <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> rq , <lb/> (9) <lb/>and where m  0  and Γ  0  are the pole mass and width of the K <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (1430) state, and a and r are <lb/>shape parameters. <lb/>The Dπ S-wave nonresonant contribution can be described by the &quot; dabba &quot; line-<lb/>shape [52], defined as <lb/> R(m) = <lb/> B <lb/>  (m <lb/> 2  )(m <lb/> 2  − s  A  )ρ <lb/>1 − β(m  2  − m <lb/> 2 <lb/>min  ) − iB   (m  2  )(m  2  − s  A  )ρ <lb/> , <lb/> (10) <lb/>where <lb/> B <lb/>  (m <lb/> 2  ) = b exp <lb/> −α(m <lb/> 2  − m <lb/> 2 <lb/>min  ) <lb/> . <lb/> (11) <lb/>Here m  min  is the invariant mass at threshold, s  A  = m <lb/> 2 <lb/> D  − 0.5 m <lb/> 2 <lb/> π  is the Adler zero, ρ is <lb/>a phase-space factor and b, α and β are parameters with values fixed to 24.49 GeV <lb/> −2  , <lb/>0.1 GeV <lb/> −2  and 0.1 GeV <lb/> −2  , respectively, according to Ref. [52]. <lb/>Ignoring reconstruction and selection effects, the DP probability density function would <lb/>be <lb/> P  phys <lb/> m <lb/> 2  (D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ), m <lb/> 2  (K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) <lb/> = <lb/> |A <lb/> m <lb/> 2  (D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ), m <lb/> 2  (K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) <lb/> | <lb/> 2 <lb/> DP <lb/> |A|  2  dm  2  (D  0  π  −  ) dm  2  (K  +  π  −  ) <lb/> , <lb/> (12) <lb/>where the dependence of A on the DP position has been suppressed in the denominator for <lb/>brevity. The primary results of most Dalitz plot analyses are the complex coefficients, as <lb/>defined in Eq. (1). These, however, depend on the choice of phase convention, amplitude <lb/>formalism and normalisation used in each analysis. The convention-independent quantities <lb/>of fit fractions and interference fit fractions provide a way to reliably compare results <lb/>between different analyses. Fit fractions are defined as the integral of the amplitude for <lb/>each intermediate component squared, divided by that of the coherent matrix element <lb/>squared for all intermediate contributions, <lb/> FF  j  = <lb/> DP <lb/> c  j  F  j <lb/> m <lb/> 2  (D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ), m <lb/> 2  (K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) <lb/> 2  dm <lb/> 2  (D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ) dm <lb/> 2  (K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) <lb/> DP <lb/> |A| <lb/> 2  dm  2  (D  0  π  −  ) dm  2  (K  +  π  −  ) <lb/> . <lb/> (13) <lb/>The fit fractions need not sum to unity due to possible net constructive or destructive <lb/>interference, described by interference fit fractions defined (for i &lt; j only) by <lb/> FF  ij  = <lb/> DP <lb/> 2 Re <lb/> c  i  c <lb/>  * <lb/> j  F  i  F <lb/>  * <lb/> j <lb/> dm <lb/> 2  (D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ) dm <lb/> 2  (K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) <lb/> DP <lb/> |A| <lb/> 2  dm  2  (D  0  π  −  ) dm  2  (K  +  π  −  ) <lb/> , <lb/> (14) <lb/>where the dependence of F <lb/> ( * ) <lb/> i <lb/> and A on the DP position has been omitted. <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body> &apos; <lb/> m <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> &apos; <lb/> θ <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1 <lb/>Efficiency (%) <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.25 <lb/> (a) <lb/>LHCb Simulation <lb/> &apos; <lb/> m <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> &apos; <lb/> θ <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1 <lb/>Efficiency (%) <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.25 <lb/> (b) <lb/>LHCb Simulation <lb/> Figure 4: Efficiency variation as a function of SDP position for candidates triggered by (a) signal <lb/>decay products and (b) by the rest of the event. The vertical white stripe is due to the D  *  veto <lb/>and the curved white band is due to the D  0  veto. <lb/> 6 Dalitz plot fit <lb/> 6.1 Signal efficiency <lb/> The variation of the efficiency across the phase space is studied in terms of the square <lb/>Dalitz plot (SDP). The SDP is defined by variables m <lb/>  and θ <lb/>  that range between 0 and 1 <lb/>and are given for the D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  case by <lb/> m <lb/>  ≡ <lb/> 1 <lb/> π <lb/> arccos <lb/> 2 <lb/> m(D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ) − m <lb/> min <lb/> D  0  π  − <lb/> m <lb/> max <lb/> D  0  π  −  − m <lb/> min <lb/> D  0  π  − <lb/> − 1 <lb/> and <lb/> θ <lb/>  ≡ <lb/> 1 <lb/> π <lb/>θ(D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ) , <lb/> (15) <lb/>where m <lb/> max <lb/> D  0  π  −  = m  B  0  − m  K  +  and m <lb/> min <lb/> D  0  π  −  = m  D  0  + m  π  −  are the kinematic boundaries of <lb/> m(D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ) allowed in the B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decay and θ(D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ) is the helicity angle of the <lb/> D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  system (the angle between the K <lb/> +  and the D <lb/> 0  meson in the D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  rest frame). The <lb/>distribution of selected events across the SDP is shown in Fig. 3(b). <lb/>Efficiency variation across the SDP is caused by the detector acceptance and by <lb/>trigger, selection and PID requirements. The efficiency is evaluated with simulated samples <lb/>generated uniformly over the SDP. Data-driven corrections are applied to correct for known <lb/>differences between data and simulation in the tracking, trigger and PID efficiencies, using <lb/>identical methods to those described in Ref. [10]. The efficiency functions are obtained <lb/>by fitting the corrected simulation with two-dimensional cubic splines. Figure 4 shows <lb/>the histograms used to model the variation of the efficiency over the SDP for candidates <lb/>triggered by (a) signal decays and (b) by the rest of the event. <lb/> 6.2 Background studies <lb/> Among the background yields in the signal region, given in Table 1, the only sizeable <lb/>components are due to combinatorial background and B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> ( * )0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays. The SDP <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body> &apos; <lb/> m <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> &apos; <lb/> θ <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.012 <lb/>0.014 <lb/> (a) <lb/>LHCb <lb/> &apos; <lb/> m <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> &apos; <lb/> θ <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.012 <lb/>0.014 <lb/>0.016 <lb/>0.018 <lb/> (b) <lb/>LHCb Simulation <lb/> Figure 5: SDP distributions of the background contributions from (a) combinatorial background <lb/>and (b) B  0  → D  ( * )0  π  +  π  −  decays. <lb/> distributions of these backgrounds are described by the histograms shown in Fig. 5. <lb/>Combinatorial background contributes 22 % of candidates in the signal region. The <lb/>shape of this contribution over the SDP is obtained from the high B mass sideband (5400– <lb/>5900 MeV). As seen in Fig. 2, this sideband is dominated by combinatorial background, <lb/>with a small contribution from B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> ( * )0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays. The SDP distribution of the <lb/> B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> ( * )0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  contribution in the sideband region is modelled as described below <lb/>for the signal region and is subtracted from the sideband sample. To check that the <lb/>SDP shape of the combinatorial background does not vary with the B candidate mass, <lb/>a sample of doubly charged D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> ±  π <lb/> ±  candidates is investigated. This confirms that the <lb/>SDP distribution from the sideband is a reliable model for combinatorial background in <lb/>the signal region. <lb/>The B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> ( * )0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  contribution accounts for 1.6 % of the candidates in the signal <lb/>region. Its SDP distribution is obtained from a simulated sample, with the B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> − <lb/> and B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/>  * 0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  contributions combined and reweighted as described in Sec. 4. The <lb/> B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decay mode is the dominant component of this background in the signal <lb/>region. <lb/>Due to resolution effects, B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/>  *  (2010) <lb/> −  K <lb/> +  , D <lb/>  *  (2010) <lb/> −  → D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  decays are not <lb/>entirely removed by the D <lb/>  *  veto. Although this component corresponds to real B <lb/> 0  → <lb/> D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  K <lb/> +  decays, it is treated as incoherent (i.e. as background) since its interference with <lb/>the remainder of the signal is negligible. Its SDP distribution is modelled as a Gaussian <lb/>peak in m(D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ), with mean fixed to the known D <lb/>  *  (2010) <lb/> −  mass and width and yield <lb/>determined in the fit to data. <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body> Table 2: Signal contributions to the fit model, where parameters and uncertainties are taken <lb/>from Ref. [37]. The models are described in Sec. 5. <lb/> Resonance <lb/> Spin <lb/>DP axis <lb/>Model <lb/>Parameters <lb/> K <lb/>  *  (892) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> m <lb/> 2  (K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) RBW m  0  = 895.81 ± 0.19 MeV, Γ  0  = 47.4 ± 0.6 MeV <lb/> K <lb/>  *  (1410) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> m <lb/> 2  (K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) RBW <lb/> m  0  = 1414 ± 15 MeV, Γ  0  = 232 ± 21 MeV <lb/> K <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (1430) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0 <lb/> m <lb/> 2  (K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) LASS <lb/>Determined from data (see text) <lb/> K <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (1430) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 2 <lb/> m <lb/> 2  (K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) RBW <lb/> m  0  = 1432.4 ± 1.3 MeV, Γ  0  = 109 ± 5 MeV <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (2400) <lb/> − <lb/> 0 <lb/> m <lb/> 2  (D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ) RBW <lb/>Determined from data (see Table 3) <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> − <lb/> 2 <lb/> m <lb/> 2  (D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ) RBW <lb/>Nonresonant <lb/>0 <lb/> m <lb/> 2  (D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ) dabba <lb/>Fixed (see text) <lb/>Nonresonant <lb/>1 <lb/> m <lb/> 2  (D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ) EFF <lb/>Determined from data (see text) <lb/> 6.3 Amplitude model for B <lb/> 0 <lb/> → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays <lb/> The Dalitz plot fit is performed using the Laura++ [53] package. The likelihood function <lb/>is given by <lb/> L = <lb/> Nc <lb/> i <lb/> k <lb/> N  k  P  k <lb/> m <lb/> 2 <lb/> i  (D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ), m <lb/> 2 <lb/> i  (K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) <lb/> , <lb/> (16) <lb/>where the index i runs over N  c  candidates, k runs over the signal and background <lb/>components and N  k  is the yield in each component. The probability density function for <lb/>the signal component, P  sig  , is given by Eq. (12) with the |A <lb/> m <lb/> 2  (D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ), m <lb/> 2  (K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) <lb/> | <lb/> 2 <lb/> terms multiplied by the efficiency function described in Sec. 6.1. As it is possible for the <lb/>minimisation procedure to find a local minimum of the negative log likelihood profile, the <lb/>fit is repeated many times with randomised initial values to ensure the global minimum is <lb/>found. <lb/>The nominal Dalitz plot fit model for B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays is composed of several <lb/>resonant and nonresonant amplitudes. Only those amplitudes that provide significant <lb/>contributions or that aid the fit stability are included. Unnatural spin-parity states are <lb/>not considered as these do not decay to two pseudoscalars. The eight amplitudes included <lb/>in this model are listed in Table 2. The width of the narrowest signal contribution to <lb/>the Dalitz plot (∼ 50 MeV) is far larger than the mass resolution (∼ 2.4 MeV); therefore, <lb/>resolution effects are neglected. <lb/>The real and imaginary parts of the complex coefficients c  j  defined in Eq. (1) are free <lb/>parameters of the fit except for the coefficient of the D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> −  component, which is fixed <lb/>to 1 as a reference. The phases and magnitudes of the complex coefficients, as well as fit <lb/>fractions and interference fit fractions are derived from these free parameters. In addition, <lb/>the masses and widths of the D <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (2400) <lb/> −  and D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> −  resonances are determined <lb/>from the fit to data and are reported in Table 3. The statistical uncertainties on all <lb/>parameters of interest are calculated using large samples of simulated pseudoexperiments. <lb/>The LASS parameters are determined to be m  0  = 1450 ± 80 MeV, Γ  0  = 400 ± 230 MeV, <lb/> a = 3.2 ± 1.8 GeV and r = 0.9 ± 1.1 GeV, while the parameter of the EFF lineshape of the <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body> Table 3: Masses and widths (MeV) determined in the fit to data, with statistical uncertainties <lb/>only. <lb/> Resonance <lb/> Mass <lb/>Width <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (2400) <lb/> − <lb/> 2360 ± 15 <lb/>255 ± 26 <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> − <lb/> 2465.6 ± 1.8 46.0 ± 3.4 <lb/> Table 4: Complex coefficients and fit fractions determined from the Dalitz plot fit. Uncertainties <lb/>are statistical only. Note that the fit fractions, magnitudes and phases are derived quantities. <lb/> Resonance <lb/>Fit fraction <lb/>Isobar model coefficients <lb/>(%) <lb/>Real part <lb/>Imaginary part Magnitude <lb/>Phase <lb/> K <lb/>  *  (892) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 37.4 ± 1.5 −0.00 ± 0.15 −1.27 ± 0.06 1.27 ± 0.06 −1.57 ± 0.11 <lb/> K <lb/>  *  (1410) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.7 ± 0.3 <lb/>0.15 ± 0.06 −0.09 ± 0.09 0.18 ± 0.07 −0.54 ± 0.21 <lb/> K <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (1430) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 5.1 ± 2.0 <lb/>0.14 ± 0.38 <lb/>0.45 ± 0.15 0.47 ± 0.09 <lb/>1.27 ± 0.95 <lb/>LASS nonresonant <lb/>4.8 ± 3.8 −0.10 ± 0.24 <lb/>0.44 ± 0.14 0.46 ± 0.14 <lb/>1.79 ± 0.65 <lb/>LASS total <lb/>6.7 ± 2.7 <lb/> K <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (1430) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 7.4 ± 1.7 −0.32 ± 0.09 −0.47 ± 0.07 0.57 ± 0.05 −2.16 ± 0.19 <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (2400) <lb/> − <lb/> 19.3 ± 2.8 −0.80 ± 0.08 −0.44 ± 0.14 0.91 ± 0.07 −2.64 ± 0.15 <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> − <lb/> 23.1 ± 1.2 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/> Dπ S-wave (dabba) <lb/>6.6 ± 1.4 −0.39 ± 0.09 <lb/>0.36 ± 0.17 0.53 ± 0.07 <lb/>2.40 ± 0.27 <lb/> Dπ P-wave (EFF) <lb/>8.9 ± 1.6 −0.62 ± 0.06 −0.03 ± 0.06 0.62 ± 0.06 −3.09 ± 0.10 <lb/>Total fit fraction <lb/>113.4 <lb/> Dπ P-wave nonresonant amplitude is determined to be α = 0.88 ± 0.10 GeV <lb/> −2  . <lb/>The values of the fit fractions and complex coefficients obtained from the fit are shown <lb/>in Table 4, while the values of the interference fit fractions are given in Appendix A. The <lb/>sum of the fit fractions is seen to exceed unity, mostly due to interference within the Dπ and <lb/> Kπ S-waves. Note that in Table 4, and all results for fit fractions and derived quantities, <lb/>values are reported separately for both the K <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (1430) <lb/> 0  and nonresonant components of the <lb/>LASS lineshape, as well as their coherent sum. <lb/>Projections of the data and the nominal fit model onto m(K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ), m(D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ) and <lb/> m(D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  ) are shown in Fig. 6. Zooms are provided in the regions of the main resonant <lb/>contributions in Fig. 7. Projections onto the cosine of the helicity angle of the D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  and <lb/> K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  systems are shown in Figs. 8 and 9, respectively. These projections all show good <lb/>agreement between data and the fit model. <lb/>Angular moments provide a useful method to investigate the helicity structure of the <lb/>decays. The angular moments in m(D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ) and m(K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ), obtained as in Refs. [10, 11], <lb/>are shown in Figs. 10 and 11, respectively. The contributions due to the K <lb/>  *  (892) <lb/> 0  and <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> −  resonances are seen as peaks in moments up to order 2 and order 4, respectively, <lb/>as expected for spin-1 and spin-2 resonances. Reflections make the interpretation of <lb/>moments at higher masses more difficult. However, the good agreement seen between data <lb/>and the fit model provides further support for the fit model being a good description of <lb/>the data. <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body> ) [GeV] <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/> Candidates / 30 MeV <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/> LHCb <lb/> (a) <lb/> ) [GeV] <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/> Candidates / 30 MeV <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> LHCb <lb/> (b) <lb/> ) [GeV] <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/> Candidates / 30 MeV <lb/> 0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>300 <lb/>350 <lb/> LHCb <lb/> (c) <lb/> ) [GeV] <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/> Candidates / 30 MeV <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> LHCb <lb/> (d) <lb/> ) [GeV] <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/> Candidates / 30 MeV <lb/> 0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>140 <lb/> LHCb <lb/> (e) <lb/> ) [GeV] <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/> Candidates / 30 MeV <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> LHCb <lb/> (f) <lb/> Data <lb/> Total fit <lb/> 0 <lb/> *(892) <lb/> K <lb/> 0 <lb/> *(1410) <lb/> K <lb/> S-wave (LASS) <lb/> π <lb/> K <lb/> 0 <lb/> (1430) <lb/>* <lb/> 2 <lb/> K <lb/> − <lb/> (2400) <lb/>* <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/> − <lb/> (2460) <lb/>* <lb/> 2 <lb/> D <lb/> S-wave (EFF) <lb/> π <lb/> D <lb/>P-wave (EFF) <lb/> π <lb/> D <lb/> − <lb/> * <lb/> D <lb/> Background <lb/> Figure 6: Projections of the data and amplitude fit results onto (a) m(D  0  π  −  ), (c) m(K  +  π  −  ) <lb/>and (e) m(D  0  K  +  ), with the same projections shown in (b), (d) and (f) with a logarithmic y-axis <lb/> scale. Components are described in the legend. <lb/></body>

			<page> 14 <lb/></page>

			<body> ) [GeV] <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 2.35 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>2.45 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>2.55 <lb/> Candidates / 4 MeV <lb/> 0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>35 <lb/>40 <lb/>45 <lb/> LHCb <lb/> (a) <lb/> ) [GeV] <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/> Candidates / 13 MeV <lb/> 0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>140 <lb/>160 <lb/>180 <lb/> LHCb <lb/> (b) <lb/> Figure 7: Projections of the data and amplitude fit results onto (a) m(D  0  π  −  ) in the D  * <lb/> 2  (2460)  − <lb/> region and (b) the low m(K  +  π  −  ) region. Components are as shown in Fig. 6. <lb/> ) <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/> ( <lb/> θ <lb/> cos <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> Candidates / 0.02 <lb/> 0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>) &lt; 2.35 GeV <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 2.04 &lt; <lb/> LHCb <lb/> (a) <lb/> ) <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/> ( <lb/> θ <lb/> cos <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> Candidates / 0.02 <lb/> 0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>35 <lb/>40 <lb/>45 <lb/>) &lt; 2.55 GeV <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 2.35 &lt; <lb/> LHCb <lb/> (b) <lb/> Figure 8: Projections of the data and amplitude fit results onto cos θ(D  0  π  −  ) in the mass ranges <lb/>(a) 2.04 &lt; m(D  0  π  −  ) &lt; 2.35 GeV and (b) 2.35 &lt; m(D  0  π  −  ) &lt; 2.55 GeV. Components are as <lb/>shown in Fig. 6. <lb/> The quality of the fit is evaluated by determining a two-dimensional χ <lb/> 2  value, comparing <lb/>the data and fit model in 144 bins across the SDP that are defined adaptively to ensure <lb/>they are approximately equally populated. The pull in each of these bins, defined as the <lb/>difference between the data and the fit model divided by the uncertainty, is shown in <lb/>Fig. 12. The effective number of degrees of freedom of the χ <lb/> 2  is between N  bins  − N  pars  − 1 <lb/>and N  bins  − 1, where N  pars  is the number of free parameters in the fit, yielding a reduced χ <lb/> 2 <lb/> in the range 0.99 – 1.22. Additional unbinned tests of fit quality [54] also show acceptable <lb/>agreement between the data and the fit model. <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body> ) <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ( <lb/> θ <lb/> cos <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> Candidates / 0.02 <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>) &lt; 0.8 GeV <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 0 &lt; <lb/> LHCb <lb/> (a) <lb/> ) <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ( <lb/> θ <lb/> cos <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> Candidates / 0.02 <lb/> 0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>) &lt; 1.0 GeV <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 0.8 &lt; <lb/> LHCb <lb/> (b) <lb/> ) <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ( <lb/> θ <lb/> cos <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> Candidates / 0.02 <lb/> 0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>) &lt; 1.3 GeV <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 1.0 &lt; <lb/> LHCb <lb/> (c) <lb/> ) <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ( <lb/> θ <lb/> cos <lb/> -1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/> Candidates / 0.02 <lb/> 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/>16 <lb/>) &lt; 1.5 GeV <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 1.4 &lt; <lb/> LHCb <lb/> (d) <lb/> Figure 9: Projections of the data and amplitude fit results onto cos θ(K  +  π  −  ) in the mass ranges <lb/>(a) m(K  +  π  −  ) &lt; 0.8 GeV, (b) 0.8 &lt; m(K  +  π  −  ) &lt; 1.0 GeV, (c) 1.0 &lt; m(K  +  π  −  ) &lt; 1.3 GeV and <lb/>(d) 1.4 &lt; m(K  +  π  −  ) &lt; 1.5 GeV. Components are as shown in Fig. 6. <lb/> 7 Systematic uncertainties <lb/> Systematic uncertainties are considered from sources that can be divided into two categories, <lb/>experimental and model uncertainties. Experimental uncertainties arise due to the signal <lb/>and background yields in the signal region, the distributions of the background components <lb/>across the SDP, the variation of efficiency across the SDP, and possible bias due to the <lb/>fitting procedure. Model uncertainties are considered due to the fixed parameters in the <lb/>signal model, the addition or removal of marginal amplitudes, and the choice of models for <lb/>the Kπ S-wave and the Dπ S-and P-waves. The uncertainties due to all of these sources <lb/>are combined in quadrature. <lb/>The signal and background yields are determined from the fit to the B candidate <lb/>invariant mass distribution. Systematic uncertainties are considered on the total yields <lb/>due to both statistical and systematic variations of these yields, as evaluated in Ref. [15]. <lb/>The yields in the signal region are varied appropriately and the effects of these variations <lb/>on the parameters of interest are assigned as systematic uncertainties. <lb/>The histograms describing the background distributions are each varied within statistical <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body> ) [GeV] <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 2.2 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>2.8 <lb/>3 <lb/> / 0.04 GeV <lb/> 〉 <lb/> 0 <lb/> P <lb/> 〈 <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.18 <lb/>0.2 <lb/> 6 <lb/> 10 <lb/> × <lb/> LHCb (a) <lb/> ) [GeV] <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 2.2 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>2.8 <lb/>3 <lb/> / 0.04 GeV <lb/> 〉 <lb/> 1 <lb/> P <lb/> 〈 <lb/> -30 <lb/>-25 <lb/>-20 <lb/>-15 <lb/>-10 <lb/>-5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> × <lb/> LHCb (b) <lb/> ) [GeV] <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 2.2 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>2.8 <lb/>3 <lb/> / 0.04 GeV <lb/> 〉 <lb/> 2 <lb/> P <lb/> 〈 <lb/> 0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> × <lb/> LHCb (c) <lb/> ) [GeV] <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 2.2 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>2.8 <lb/>3 <lb/> / 0.04 GeV <lb/> 〉 <lb/> 3 <lb/> P <lb/> 〈 <lb/> -15 <lb/>-10 <lb/>-5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> × <lb/> LHCb (d) <lb/> ) [GeV] <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 2.2 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>2.8 <lb/>3 <lb/> / 0.04 GeV <lb/> 〉 <lb/> 4 <lb/> P <lb/> 〈 <lb/> -10 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> × <lb/> LHCb (e) <lb/> ) [GeV] <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 2.2 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>2.8 <lb/>3 <lb/> / 0.04 GeV <lb/> 〉 <lb/> 5 <lb/> P <lb/> 〈 <lb/> -8 <lb/>-6 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> × <lb/> LHCb (f) <lb/> ) [GeV] <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 2.2 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>2.8 <lb/>3 <lb/> / 0.04 GeV <lb/> 〉 <lb/> 6 <lb/> P <lb/> 〈 <lb/> -8 <lb/>-6 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> × <lb/> LHCb (g) <lb/> ) [GeV] <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> 0 <lb/> D <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 2.2 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>2.8 <lb/>3 <lb/> / 0.04 GeV <lb/> 〉 <lb/> 7 <lb/> P <lb/> 〈 <lb/> -6 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> × <lb/> LHCb (h) <lb/> Figure 10: Background-subtracted and efficiency-corrected Legendre moments up to order 7 <lb/>calculated as a function of m(D  0  π  −  ) for data (black data points) and the fit result (solid blue <lb/>curve). <lb/></body>

			<page> 17 <lb/></page>

			<body> ) [GeV] <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/> / 0.04 GeV <lb/> 〉 <lb/> 0 <lb/> P <lb/> 〈 <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.25 <lb/> 6 <lb/> 10 <lb/> × <lb/> LHCb (a) <lb/> ) [GeV] <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/> / 0.04 GeV <lb/> 〉 <lb/> 1 <lb/> P <lb/> 〈 <lb/> -40 <lb/>-20 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> × <lb/> LHCb (b) <lb/> ) [GeV] <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/> / 0.04 GeV <lb/> 〉 <lb/> 2 <lb/> P <lb/> 〈 <lb/> 0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> × <lb/> LHCb (c) <lb/> ) [GeV] <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/> / 0.04 GeV <lb/> 〉 <lb/> 3 <lb/> P <lb/> 〈 <lb/> -30 <lb/>-20 <lb/>-10 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> × <lb/> LHCb (d) <lb/> ) [GeV] <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/> / 0.04 GeV <lb/> 〉 <lb/> 4 <lb/> P <lb/> 〈 <lb/> -10 <lb/>-5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> × <lb/> LHCb (e) <lb/> ) [GeV] <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/> / 0.04 GeV <lb/> 〉 <lb/> 5 <lb/> P <lb/> 〈 <lb/> -30 <lb/>-20 <lb/>-10 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> × <lb/> LHCb (f) <lb/> ) [GeV] <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/> / 0.04 GeV <lb/> 〉 <lb/> 6 <lb/> P <lb/> 〈 <lb/> -15 <lb/>-10 <lb/>-5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> × <lb/> LHCb (g) <lb/> ) [GeV] <lb/> − <lb/> π <lb/> + <lb/> K <lb/> ( <lb/> m <lb/> 0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/> / 0.04 GeV <lb/> 〉 <lb/> 7 <lb/> P <lb/> 〈 <lb/> -20 <lb/>-15 <lb/>-10 <lb/>-5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> × <lb/> LHCb (h) <lb/> Figure 11: Background-subtracted and efficiency-corrected Legendre moments up to order 7 <lb/>calculated as a function of m(K  +  π  −  ) for data (black data points) and the fit result (solid blue <lb/>curve). <lb/></body>

			<page> 18 <lb/></page>

			<body> &apos; <lb/> m <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/> &apos; <lb/> θ <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1 <lb/> Pull <lb/> -2 <lb/>-1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> LHCb <lb/> Figure 12: Differences between the data SDP distribution and the fit model across the SDP, in <lb/>terms of the per-bin pull. <lb/> uncertainties to establish the uncertainty due to the imperfect knowledge of the distribution <lb/>of these backgrounds across the SDP. The histograms describing the efficiency variation <lb/>across the SDP are also varied within their uncertainties prior to the spline fit. The <lb/>efficiency histograms are also varied with local correlations to account for the effects of <lb/>any unknown correlations between neighbouring bins. For each parameter the larger <lb/>uncertainty is considered from the correlated and uncorrelated variations. In addition, the <lb/>binning scheme of the control sample used to evaluate PID performance is varied. <lb/>An ensemble of pseudoexperiments is used to establish systematic uncertainties related <lb/>to any potential fit bias. Pseudoexperiments are generated using the parameters determined <lb/>in the fit to data, and mean fitted values of the parameters are determined from Gaussian <lb/>fits to the distributions of results obtained in the ensemble. The differences between the <lb/>generated and mean fitted values are found to be small. Uncertainties are determined as <lb/>the sum in quadrature of the difference between the generated and mean fitted values, and <lb/>the uncertainty on the mean fitted value from the Gaussian fit. <lb/>Systematic uncertainties due to fixed parameters in the fit model are determined by <lb/>repeating the fit with these parameters varied. The fixed masses and widths are varied <lb/>within their uncertainties as shown in Table 2, while the Blatt–Weisskopf barrier radii, r  BW  , <lb/>are varied independently for D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  and K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  resonances between 3 and 5 GeV <lb/> −1  [10]. <lb/>The K <lb/>  *  (1410) <lb/> 0  amplitude does not contribute significantly to the nominal fit model <lb/>so the fit is repeated with this component removed and the change in results is assigned <lb/>as the associated systematic uncertainty. In addition, uncertainties are assigned from <lb/>the changes in the results when an amplitude due to the K <lb/>  *  (1680) <lb/> 0  resonance or from a <lb/>virtual B <lb/>  *  (5325) <lb/> +  component, as described in Ref. [10], are included in the model. <lb/>A Dalitz plot analysis of B <lb/> 0 <lb/> s  → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> −  π <lb/> +  observed both spin-1 and spin-3 resonances <lb/>at m(D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> −  ) ∼ 2.86 GeV [9, 10]. A spin-3 resonance has also been seen at m(D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ) ∼ <lb/></body>

			<page> 19 <lb/></page>

			<body> Table 5: Experimental systematic uncertainties on the fit fractions (%) and masses and widths <lb/>(MeV). <lb/> Resonance <lb/> Value ± stat. S/B frac. Eff. Bkgd. SDP Fit bias Total syst. <lb/> K <lb/>  *  (892) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 37.4 ± 1.5 <lb/>0.60 <lb/>0.83 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>1.17 <lb/> K <lb/>  *  (1410) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.7 ± 0.3 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.39 <lb/>0.69 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.80 <lb/> K <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (1430) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 5.1 ± 2.0 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>1.48 <lb/>1.85 <lb/>0.33 <lb/>2.41 <lb/>LASS nonresonant <lb/>4.8 ± 3.8 <lb/>0.51 <lb/>2.25 <lb/>2.86 <lb/>0.86 <lb/>3.77 <lb/>LASS total <lb/>6.7 ± 2.7 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>1.86 <lb/>1.60 <lb/>1.02 <lb/>2.67 <lb/> K <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (1430) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 7.4 ± 1.7 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>0.72 <lb/>0.53 <lb/>0.54 <lb/>1.07 <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (2400) <lb/> − <lb/> 19.3 ± 2.8 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>1.39 <lb/>1.43 <lb/>0.40 <lb/>2.04 <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> − <lb/> 23.1 ± 1.2 <lb/>0.70 <lb/>0.70 <lb/>0.49 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>1.11 <lb/> Dπ S-wave (dabba) <lb/>6.6 ± 1.4 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.81 <lb/>0.59 <lb/>0.57 <lb/>1.15 <lb/> Dπ P-wave (EFF) <lb/>8.9 ± 1.6 <lb/>0.86 <lb/>1.91 <lb/>0.52 <lb/>0.38 <lb/>2.19 <lb/> m (D <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (2400) <lb/> −  ) <lb/>2360 ± 15 <lb/>4.6 <lb/>8.1 <lb/>7.0 <lb/>3.7 <lb/>12.2 <lb/> m (D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> −  ) <lb/>2465.6 ± 1.8 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.37 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>0.51 <lb/>Γ (D <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (2400) <lb/> −  ) <lb/>255 ± 26 <lb/>2.8 <lb/>13.1 <lb/>13.9 <lb/>4.8 <lb/>19.9 <lb/>Γ (D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> −  ) <lb/>46.0 ± 3.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.4 <lb/> 2.76 GeV in B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays [12], while an analysis of B <lb/> +  → D <lb/> −  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> +  shows a <lb/>spin-1 resonance at similar m(D <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) values [11]. Uncertainties are assigned corresponding <lb/>to the changes in results when either a spin-1 or spin-3 state at m(D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ) ∼ 2.76 GeV is <lb/>added to the nominal model. <lb/>The LASS model used to describe the Kπ S-wave is replaced with a Flatté shape [55], <lb/>which accounts for the Kη <lb/>  threshold near the K <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (1430) <lb/> 0  mass, and a resonant term <lb/>with a modified mass dependent width [52] for the κ (also known as K <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (800)) state. A <lb/>model-independent description of the Kπ S-wave is also used to fit the data, with the <lb/>uncertainty on each parameter taken as the larger of the two differences. The dabba <lb/>lineshape used to describe the D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  S-wave is replaced with an EFF lineshape, while a <lb/>power-law model is introduced as an alternative to the EFF lineshape that describes the <lb/> D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  P-wave. <lb/>The total systematic uncertainties due to experimental and model effects for fit fractions <lb/>and complex coefficients are given together with the results in Sec. 8. The contributions <lb/>from different sources to the systematic uncertainties on the fit fractions, masses and <lb/>widths are given in Tables 5 and 6. The dominant experimental systematic uncertainty <lb/>on most parameters is due to either the efficiency variation or background distributions <lb/>across the SDP, while the model uncertainties are generally dominated by the effects of <lb/>alternative descriptions of the Kπ S-wave and the Dπ S-and P-waves. For the parameters <lb/>of broad components, the model uncertainties dominate; however for other parameters the <lb/>statistical, experimental and model uncertainties are all of a similar magnitude. <lb/>The stability of the fit results is confirmed by several cross-checks. The data sample is <lb/>divided into subsamples according to the flavour of the B candidate, the trigger decision, <lb/>the polarity of the magnet and the year of data taking. Each subsample is fitted separately <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body> Table 6: Model uncertainties on the fit fractions (%) and masses and widths (MeV). <lb/> Resonance <lb/> Value ± stat. Fixed params Add/rem. Alt. models Total syst. <lb/> K <lb/>  *  (892) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 37.4 ± 1.5 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.14 <lb/>1.09 <lb/>1.74 <lb/> K <lb/>  *  (1410) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.7 ± 0.3 <lb/>0.18 <lb/>0.70 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>0.76 <lb/> K <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (1430) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 5.1 ± 2.0 <lb/>0.79 <lb/>3.30 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>3.40 <lb/>LASS nonresonant <lb/>4.8 ± 3.8 <lb/>1.10 <lb/>3.99 <lb/>5.20 <lb/>6.65 <lb/>LASS total <lb/>6.7 ± 2.7 <lb/>0.53 <lb/>1.42 <lb/>5.21 <lb/>5.43 <lb/> K <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (1430) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 7.4 ± 1.7 <lb/>0.36 <lb/>1.87 <lb/>0.56 <lb/>1.98 <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (2400) <lb/> − <lb/> 19.3 ± 2.8 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>1.95 <lb/>7.11 <lb/>7.40 <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> − <lb/> 23.1 ± 1.2 <lb/>0.18 <lb/>0.73 <lb/>0.99 <lb/>1.24 <lb/> Dπ S-wave (dabba) <lb/>6.6 ± 1.4 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>1.40 <lb/>3.46 <lb/>3.74 <lb/> Dπ P-wave (EFF) <lb/>8.9 ± 1.6 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>1.99 <lb/>2.15 <lb/>2.95 <lb/> m (D <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (2400) <lb/> −  ) <lb/>2360 ± 15 <lb/>6.1 <lb/>9.3 <lb/>25.6 <lb/>27.9 <lb/> m (D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> −  ) <lb/>2465.6 ± 1.8 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>1.05 <lb/>0.48 <lb/>1.15 <lb/>Γ (D <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (2400) <lb/> −  ) <lb/>255 ± 26 <lb/>4.0 <lb/>18.0 <lb/>43.5 <lb/>47.2 <lb/>Γ (D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> −  ) <lb/>46.0 ± 3.4 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>2.9 <lb/> and all are seen to be consistent with the nominal fit results. The fit is also repeated <lb/>with additional resonance components to test the fit model. Resonances up to spin-3 were <lb/>considered for all three pairs of daughters with the mass and width allowed to vary in the <lb/>fit. No additional significant contributions were observed. <lb/> 8 Results and summary <lb/> The results for the complex coefficients are reported in Table 7, with results for the <lb/>fit fractions given in Table 8. The results for the interference fit fractions are given <lb/>in Appendix A. Upper limits are determined on the fit fractions of the K <lb/>  *  (1410) <lb/> 0  and <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> 3  (2760) <lb/> −  components, which do not give significant contributions, using the method <lb/>described in Ref. [10]. <lb/>The fit fractions for resonant contributions are converted into quasi-two-body product <lb/>branching fractions by multiplying by B(B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) = (9.2 ± 0.6 ± 0.7 ± 0.6) × 10 <lb/> −5  , <lb/>which is obtained from the ratio of branching fractions B(B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  )/B(B <lb/> 0  → <lb/> D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) [15] multiplied by the latest result for B(B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  ) [12], accounting for <lb/>the different D <lb/>  *  (2010) <lb/> −  veto windows used in the analyses and for the 3.7 % residual <lb/>background due to B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/>  *  (2010) <lb/> −  K <lb/> +  decays. The statistical correlation between the <lb/>results of Ref. [15] and this analysis is found to be negligible. The results for the product <lb/>branching fractions are shown in Table 9. For the K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  resonances, where the branching <lb/>fractions to Kπ are known, the product branching fractions are converted to the B <lb/> decay branching fractions, shown in Table 10. The results for B(B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/>  *  (892) <lb/> 0  ) and <lb/> B(B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> −  K <lb/> +  ) × B(D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> −  → D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> −  ) are consistent with, and more precise <lb/>than, previous measurements [14, 16, 17]. <lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body> Table 7: Results for the complex amplitudes and their uncertainties presented (top) in terms of <lb/>real and imaginary parts and (bottom) in terms and magnitudes and phases. The three quoted <lb/>errors are statistical, experimental systematic and model uncertainties, respectively. <lb/> Resonance <lb/> Real part <lb/>Imaginary part <lb/> K <lb/>  *  (892) <lb/> 0 <lb/> −0.00 ± 0.15 ± 0.24 ± 0.34 −1.27 ± 0.06 ± 0.03 ± 0.06 <lb/> K <lb/>  *  (1410) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.15 ± 0.06 ± 0.04 ± 0.09 −0.09 ± 0.09 ± 0.18 ± 0.18 <lb/> K <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (1430) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.14 ± 0.38 ± 0.48 ± 0.38 <lb/>0.45 ± 0.15 ± 0.37 ± 0.17 <lb/>LASS nonresonant −0.10 ± 0.24 ± 0.16 ± 0.42 <lb/>0.44 ± 0.14 ± 0.17 ± 0.23 <lb/> K <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (1430) <lb/> 0 <lb/> −0.32 ± 0.09 ± 0.15 ± 0.23 −0.47 ± 0.07 ± 0.14 ± 0.15 <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (2400) <lb/> − <lb/> −0.80 ± 0.08 ± 0.07 ± 0.22 −0.44 ± 0.14 ± 0.12 ± 0.18 <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> − <lb/> 1.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/> Dπ S-wave (dabba) −0.39 ± 0.09 ± 0.09 ± 0.14 <lb/>0.36 ± 0.17 ± 0.14 ± 0.23 <lb/> Dπ P-wave (EFF) <lb/> −0.62 ± 0.06 ± 0.03 ± 0.11 −0.03 ± 0.06 ± 0.05 ± 0.10 <lb/>Resonance <lb/>Magnitude <lb/>Phase <lb/> K <lb/>  *  (892) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1.27 ± 0.06 ± 0.03 ± 0.05 −1.57 ± 0.11 ± 0.16 ± 0.27 <lb/> K <lb/>  *  (1410) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.18 ± 0.07 ± 0.10 ± 0.11 −0.54 ± 0.21 ± 0.55 ± 1.04 <lb/> K <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (1430) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.47 ± 0.09 ± 0.10 ± 0.14 <lb/>1.27 ± 0.95 ± 1.04 ± 0.81 <lb/>LASS nonresonant <lb/>0.46 ± 0.14 ± 0.16 ± 0.29 <lb/>1.79 ± 0.65 ± 0.35 ± 0.69 <lb/> K <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (1430) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.57 ± 0.05 ± 0.04 ± 0.08 −2.16 ± 0.19 ± 0.43 ± 0.43 <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (2400) <lb/> − <lb/> 0.91 ± 0.07 ± 0.06 ± 0.17 −2.64 ± 0.15 ± 0.14 ± 0.23 <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> − <lb/> 1.00 <lb/>0.00 <lb/> Dπ S-wave (dabba) <lb/>0.53 ± 0.07 ± 0.04 ± 0.14 <lb/>2.40 ± 0.27 ± 0.24 ± 0.44 <lb/> Dπ P-wave (EFF) <lb/>0.62 ± 0.06 ± 0.04 ± 0.11 −3.09 ± 0.10 ± 0.07 ± 0.17 <lb/> Table 8: Results for the fit fractions and their uncertainties (%). The three quoted errors are <lb/>statistical, experimental systematic and model uncertainties, respectively. Upper limits are given <lb/>at 90 % (95 %) confidence level. <lb/> Resonance <lb/>Fit fraction <lb/>Upper limit <lb/> K <lb/>  *  (892) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 37.4 ± 1.5 ± 1.2 ± 1.7 <lb/> K <lb/>  *  (1410) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.7 ± 0.3 ± 0.8 ± 0.8 &lt; 3.2 (3.7) <lb/> K <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (1430) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 5.1 ± 2.0 ± 2.4 ± 3.4 <lb/>LASS nonresonant <lb/>4.8 ± 3.8 ± 3.8 ± 6.7 <lb/>LASS total <lb/>6.7 ± 2.7 ± 2.7 ± 5.4 <lb/> K <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (1430) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 7.4 ± 1.7 ± 1.1 ± 2.0 <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (2400) <lb/> − <lb/> 19.3 ± 2.8 ± 2.0 ± 7.4 <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> − <lb/> 23.1 ± 1.2 ± 1.1 ± 1.2 <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> 3  (2760) <lb/> − <lb/> &lt; 1.0 (1.1) <lb/> Dπ S-wave (dabba) 6.6 ± 1.4 ± 1.2 ± 3.7 <lb/> Dπ P-wave (EFF) <lb/>8.9 ± 1.6 ± 2.2 ± 3.0 <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body> Table 9: Results for the product branching fractions. The four quoted errors are statistical, <lb/>experimental systematic, model and PDG uncertainties, respectively. Upper limits are given at <lb/>90 % (95 %) confidence level. <lb/> Resonance <lb/> Product branching fraction (10 <lb/> −5  ) Upper limit (10 <lb/> −5  ) <lb/> K <lb/>  *  (892) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 3.42 ± 0.13 ± 0.10 ± 0.16 ± 0.40 <lb/> K <lb/>  *  (1410) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.07 ± 0.03 ± 0.08 ± 0.07 ± 0.01 <lb/> &lt; 0.29 (0.34) <lb/> K <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (1430) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.47 ± 0.18 ± 0.22 ± 0.31 ± 0.05 <lb/>LASS nonresonant 0.44 ± 0.34 ± 0.34 ± 0.61 ± 0.05 <lb/>LASS total <lb/>0.61 ± 0.25 ± 0.25 ± 0.49 ± 0.07 <lb/> K <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (1430) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.68 ± 0.15 ± 0.10 ± 0.18 ± 0.08 <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (2400) <lb/> − <lb/> 1.77 ± 0.26 ± 0.19 ± 0.67 ± 0.20 <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> − <lb/> 2.12 ± 0.10 ± 0.11 ± 0.11 ± 0.25 <lb/> D <lb/>  * <lb/> 3  (2760) <lb/> − <lb/> &lt; 0.10 (0.11) <lb/> Dπ S-wave (dabba) 0.60 ± 0.13 ± 0.11 ± 0.34 ± 0.07 <lb/> Dπ P-wave (EFF) <lb/>0.81 ± 0.15 ± 0.20 ± 0.27 ± 0.09 <lb/> Table 10: Results for the branching fractions. The four quoted errors are statistical, experimental <lb/>systematic, model and PDG uncertainties, respectively. Upper limits are given at 90 % (95 %) <lb/>confidence level. <lb/> Resonance <lb/>Branching fraction (10 <lb/> −5  ) <lb/>Upper limit (10 <lb/> −5  ) <lb/> K <lb/>  *  (892) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 5.13 ± 0.20 ± 0.15 ± 0.24 ± 0.60 <lb/> K <lb/>  *  (1410) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 1.59 ± 0.68 ± 1.81 ± 1.59 ± 0.36 <lb/> &lt; 6.7 (7.8) <lb/> K <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (1430) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.71 ± 0.27 ± 0.33 ± 0.47 ± 0.08 <lb/>LASS nonresonant 0.66 ± 0.51 ± 0.51 ± 0.92 ± 0.08 <lb/>LASS total <lb/>0.92 ± 0.38 ± 0.38 ± 0.74 ± 0.11 <lb/> K <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (1430) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 2.04 ± 0.45 ± 0.30 ± 0.54 ± 0.25 <lb/>The masses and widths of the D <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (2400) <lb/> −  and D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> −  states are found to be <lb/> m(D <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (2400) <lb/> −  ) = (2360 ± 15 ± 12 ± 28) MeV <lb/>Γ(D <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (2400) <lb/> −  ) = (255 ± 26 ± 20 ± 47) MeV <lb/> m(D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> −  ) = (2465.6 ± 1.8 ± 0.5 ± 1.2) MeV <lb/>Γ(D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> −  ) = (46.0 ± 3.4 ± 1.4 ± 2.9) MeV , <lb/> where the three uncertainties are statistical, experimental systematic and model systematic, <lb/>respectively. These are consistent with, though less precise than, recent results from a DP <lb/>analysis of B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays [12]. They also show good agreement with, and have <lb/>similar precision to, earlier measurements of these quantities [13, 37]. <lb/>In summary, the first amplitude analysis of B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays has been presented, <lb/>using a data sample corresponding to 3.0 fb <lb/> −1  of pp collision data collected by the LHCb <lb/>experiment. A good description of the data is obtained with a model containing contri-<lb/></body>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body> butions from intermediate K <lb/>  *  (892) <lb/> 0  , K <lb/>  *  (1410) <lb/> 0  , K <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (1430) <lb/> 0  and D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> −  resonances, <lb/>with additional components to describe broad structures in the Kπ S-wave and the Dπ S-<lb/>and P-waves. The masses and widths of the D <lb/>  * <lb/> 0  (2400) <lb/> −  and D <lb/>  * <lb/> 2  (2460) <lb/> −  resonances are <lb/>measured, as are the complex amplitudes and fit fractions for all components included <lb/>in the amplitude model. The results can be used in conjunction with an analysis of <lb/> B <lb/> 0  → DK <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays, where the neutral D meson is reconstructed in final states such as <lb/> K <lb/> +  K <lb/> −  , to measure the CKM unitarity triangle parameter γ [1, 2]. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgements <lb/> We express our gratitude to our colleagues in the CERN accelerator departments for <lb/>the excellent performance of the LHC. We thank the technical and administrative staff <lb/>at the LHCb institutes. We acknowledge support from CERN and from the national <lb/>agencies: CAPES, CNPq, FAPERJ and FINEP (Brazil); NSFC (China); CNRS/IN2P3 <lb/>(France); BMBF, DFG, HGF and MPG (Germany); INFN (Italy); FOM and NWO (The <lb/>Netherlands); MNiSW and NCN (Poland); MEN/IFA (Romania); MinES and FANO <lb/>(Russia); MinECo (Spain); SNSF and SER (Switzerland); NASU (Ukraine); STFC (United <lb/>Kingdom); NSF (USA). The Tier1 computing centres are supported by IN2P3 (France), <lb/>KIT and BMBF (Germany), INFN (Italy), NWO and SURF (The Netherlands), PIC <lb/>(Spain), GridPP (United Kingdom). We are indebted to the communities behind the <lb/>multiple open source software packages on which we depend. We are also thankful for <lb/>the computing resources and the access to software R&amp;D tools provided by Yandex LLC <lb/>(Russia). Individual groups or members have received support from EPLANET, Marie <lb/>Skk lodowska-Curie Actions and ERC (European Union), Conseil général de Haute-Savoie, <lb/>Labex ENIGMASS and OCEVU, Région Auvergne (France), RFBR (Russia), XuntaGal <lb/>and GENCAT (Spain), Royal Society and Royal Commission for the Exhibition of 1851 <lb/>(United Kingdom). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] T. Gershon, On the measurement of the unitarity triangle angle γ from B <lb/> 0  → DK <lb/>  * 0 <lb/> decays, Phys. Rev. D79 (2009) 051301(R), arXiv:0810.2706. <lb/> [2] T. Gershon and M. Williams, Prospects for the measurement of the unitarity <lb/>triangle angle γ from B <lb/> 0  → DK <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays, Phys. Rev. D80 (2009) 092002, <lb/> arXiv:0909.1495. <lb/> [3] N. Cabibbo, Unitary symmetry and leptonic decays, Phys. Rev. Lett. 10 (1963) 531. <lb/>[4] M. Kobayashi and T. Maskawa, CP -violation in the renormalizable theory of weak <lb/>interaction, Progress of Theoretical Physics 49 (1973) 652. <lb/>[5] M. Gronau and D. London, How to determine all the angles of the unitarity triangle <lb/>from B <lb/> 0  → DK <lb/> 0 <lb/> S  and B <lb/> 0 <lb/> s  → Dφ , Phys. Lett. B253 (1991) 483. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [6] M. Gronau and D. Wyler, On determining a weak phase from CP asymmetries in <lb/>charged B decays, Phys. Lett. B265 (1991) 172. <lb/>[7] I. Dunietz, CP violation with self-tagging B  d  modes, Phys. Lett. B270 (1991) 75. <lb/>[8] LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij et al., Measurement of CP violation parameters in <lb/> B <lb/> 0  → DK <lb/>  * 0  decays, Phys. Rev. D90 (2014) 112002, arXiv:1407.8136. <lb/> [9] LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij et al., Observation of overlapping spin-1 and spin-<lb/> 3 ¯ <lb/> D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> −  resonances at mass 2.86 GeV/c <lb/> 2  , Phys. Rev. Lett. 113 (2014) 162001, <lb/> arXiv:1407.7574. <lb/> [10] LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij et al., Dalitz plot analysis of B <lb/> 0 <lb/> s  → ¯ <lb/> D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> −  π <lb/> +  decays, <lb/> Phys. Rev. D90 (2014) 072003, arXiv:1407.7712. <lb/> [11] LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij et al., First observation and amplitude analysis of the <lb/> B <lb/> −  → D <lb/> +  K <lb/> −  π <lb/> −  decay, arXiv:1503.0299, to appear in Phys. Rev. D. <lb/>[12] LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij et al., Dalitz plot analysis of B <lb/> 0  → ¯ <lb/> D <lb/> 0  ππ decays, <lb/> LHCb-PAPER-2014-070, in preparation. <lb/>[13] Belle collaboration, A. Kuzmin et al., Study of ¯ <lb/> B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays, Phys. Rev. <lb/> D76 (2007) 012006, arXiv:hep-ex/0611054. <lb/> [14] BaBar collaboration, B. Aubert et al., Measurement of branching fractions and <lb/>resonance contributions for B <lb/> 0  → ¯ <lb/> D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  and search for B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays, <lb/> Phys. Rev. Lett. 96 (2006) 011803, arXiv:hep-ex/0509036. <lb/> [15] LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij et al., Measurements of the branching fractions of <lb/>the decays B <lb/> 0 <lb/> s  → ¯ <lb/> D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> −  π <lb/> +  and B <lb/> 0  → ¯ <lb/> D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  , Phys. Rev. D87 (2013) 112009, <lb/> arXiv:1304.6317. <lb/> [16] Belle collaboration, P. Krokovny et al., Observation of ¯ <lb/> B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  ¯ <lb/> K <lb/> 0  and ¯ <lb/> B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> 0  ¯ <lb/> K <lb/>  * 0 <lb/> decays, Phys. Rev. Lett. 90 (2003) 141802, arXiv:hep-ex/0212066. <lb/> [17] BaBar collaboration, B. Aubert et al., Measurement of ¯ <lb/> B <lb/> 0  → D <lb/> ( * )0  ¯ <lb/> K <lb/> ( * )0  branching <lb/>fractions, Phys. Rev. D74 (2006) 031101, arXiv:hep-ex/0604016. <lb/> [18] LHCb collaboration, A. A. Alves Jr. et al., The LHCb detector at the LHC, JINST 3 <lb/> (2008) S08005. <lb/>[19] LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij et al., LHCb detector performance, Int. J. Mod. Phys. <lb/> A30 (2015) 1530022, arXiv:1412.6352. <lb/> [20] R. Aaij et al., Performance of the LHCb Vertex Locator, JINST 9 (2014) P09007, <lb/> arXiv:1405.7808. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 25 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [21] R. Arink et al., Performance of the LHCb Outer Tracker, JINST 9 (2014) P01002, <lb/> arXiv:1311.3893. <lb/> [22] M. Adinolfi et al., Performance of the LHCb RICH detector at the LHC, Eur. Phys. <lb/>J. C73 (2013) 2431, arXiv:1211.6759. <lb/> [23] A. A. Alves Jr. et al., Performance of the LHCb muon system, JINST 8 (2013) P02022, <lb/> arXiv:1211.1346. <lb/> [24] R. Aaij et al., The LHCb trigger and its performance in 2011, JINST 8 (2013) P04022, <lb/> arXiv:1211.3055. <lb/> [25] V. V. Gligorov and M. Williams, Efficient, reliable and fast high-level triggering using <lb/>a bonsai boosted decision tree, JINST 8 (2013) P02013, arXiv:1210.6861. <lb/> [26] T. Sjöstrand, S. Mrenna, and P. Skands, PYTHIA 6.4 physics and manual, JHEP <lb/> 05 (2006) 026, arXiv:hep-ph/0603175; T. Sjöstrand, S. Mrenna, and P. Skands, <lb/> A brief introduction to PYTHIA 8.1, Comput. Phys. Commun. 178 (2008) 852, <lb/> arXiv:0710.3820. <lb/> [27] I. Belyaev et al., Handling of the generation of primary events in Gauss, the LHCb <lb/>simulation framework, J. Phys. Conf. Ser. 331 (2011) 032047. <lb/>[28] D. J. Lange, The EvtGen particle decay simulation package, Nucl. Instrum. Meth. <lb/> A462 (2001) 152. <lb/>[29] P. Golonka and Z. Was, PHOTOS Monte Carlo: A precision tool for QED corrections <lb/>in Z and W decays, Eur. Phys. J. C45 (2006) 97, arXiv:hep-ph/0506026. <lb/> [30] Geant4 collaboration, J. Allison et al., Geant4 developments and applications, IEEE <lb/>Trans. Nucl. Sci. 53 (2006) 270; Geant4 collaboration, S. Agostinelli et al., Geant4: <lb/>A simulation toolkit, Nucl. Instrum. Meth. A506 (2003) 250. <lb/>[31] M. Clemencic et al., The LHCb simulation application, Gauss: Design, evolution and <lb/>experience, J. Phys. Conf. Ser. 331 (2011) 032023. <lb/>[32] LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij et al., First evidence for the annihilation decay mode <lb/> B <lb/> +  → D <lb/> + <lb/> s  φ, JHEP 02 (2013) 043, arXiv:1210.1089. <lb/> [33] LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij et al., First observations of ¯ <lb/> B <lb/> 0 <lb/> s  → D <lb/> +  D <lb/> −  , D <lb/> + <lb/> s  D <lb/> −  and <lb/> D <lb/> 0  ¯ <lb/> D <lb/> 0  decays, Phys. Rev. D87 (2013) 092007, arXiv:1302.5854. <lb/> [34] W. D. Hulsbergen, Decay chain fitting with a Kalman filter, Nucl. Instrum. Meth. <lb/> A552 (2005) 566, arXiv:physics/0503191. <lb/> [35] M. Feindt and U. Kerzel, The NeuroBayes neural network package, Nucl. Instrum. <lb/>Meth. A 559 (2006) 190. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [36] M. Pivk and F. R. Le Diberder, sPlot: A statistical tool to unfold data distributions, <lb/> Nucl. Instrum. Meth. A555 (2005) 356, arXiv:physics/0402083. <lb/> [37] Particle Data Group, K. A. Olive et al., Review of particle physics, Chin. Phys. C38 <lb/> (2014) 090001. <lb/>[38] T. Skwarnicki, A study of the radiative cascade transitions between the Upsilon-prime <lb/>and Upsilon resonances, PhD thesis, Institute of Nuclear Physics, Krakow, 1986, <lb/>DESY-F31-86-02. <lb/>[39] LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij et al., Observation of B <lb/> 0  → ¯ <lb/> D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  K <lb/> −  and evidence for <lb/> B <lb/> 0 <lb/> s  → ¯ <lb/> D <lb/> 0  K <lb/> +  K <lb/> −  , Phys. Rev. Lett. 109 (2012) 131801, arXiv:1207.5991. <lb/> [40] LHCb collaboration, R. Aaij et al., Study of beauty baryon decays to D <lb/> 0  ph <lb/> −  and Λ <lb/> + <lb/> c  h <lb/> − <lb/> final states, Phys. Rev. D89 (2014) 032001, arXiv:1311.4823. <lb/> [41] Belle collaboration, K. Abe et al., Study of B <lb/> 0 <lb/> → ¯ <lb/> D <lb/> ( * )0  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  decays, <lb/> arXiv:hep-ex/0412072. <lb/> [42] R. H. Dalitz, On the analysis of tau-meson data and the nature of the tau-meson, <lb/> Phil. Mag. 44 (1953) 1068. <lb/>[43] G. N. Fleming, Recoupling effects in the isobar model. 1. General formalism for <lb/>three-pion scattering, Phys. Rev. 135 (1964) B551. <lb/>[44] D. Morgan, Phenomenological analysis of I = <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> single-pion production processes in <lb/>the energy range 500 to 700 MeV, Phys. Rev. 166 (1968) 1731. <lb/>[45] D. Herndon, P. Soding, and R. J. Cashmore, A generalised isobar model formalism, <lb/> Phys. Rev. D11 (1975) 3165. <lb/>[46] J. Blatt and V. E. Weisskopf, Theoretical nuclear physics, J. Wiley (New York), 1952. <lb/>[47] C. Zemach, Three pion decays of unstable particles, Phys. Rev. 133 (1964) B1201. <lb/>[48] C. Zemach, Use of angular-momentum tensors, Phys. Rev. 140 (1965) B97. <lb/>[49] Belle collaboration, A. Garmash et al., Dalitz analysis of the three-body charmless <lb/>decays B <lb/> +  → K <lb/> +  π <lb/> +  π <lb/> −  and B <lb/> +  → K <lb/> +  K <lb/> +  K <lb/> −  , Phys. Rev. D71 (2005) 092003, <lb/> arXiv:hep-ex/0412066. <lb/> [50] B. Meadows, Low mass S-wave Kπ and ππ systems, eConf C070805 (2007) 27, <lb/> arXiv:0712.1605. <lb/> [51] LASS collaboration, D. Aston et al., A study of K <lb/> −  π <lb/> +  scattering in the reaction <lb/> K <lb/> −  p → K <lb/> −  π <lb/> +  n at 11 GeV/c, Nucl. Phys. B296 (1988) 493. <lb/>[52] D. V. Bugg, The Dπ S-wave, J. Phys. G36 (2009) 075003, arXiv:0901.2217. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 27 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [53] Laura++ Dalitz plot fitting package, http://laura.hepforge.net. <lb/> [54] M. Williams, How good are your fits? Unbinned multivariate goodness-of-fit tests in <lb/>high energy physics, JINST 5 (2010) P09004, arXiv:1006.3019. <lb/> [55] S. M. Flatté, Coupled-channel analysis of the πη and KK systems near KK threshold, <lb/> Phys. Lett. B63 (1976) 224. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex"> A Results for interference fit fractions <lb/> The central values of the interference fit fractions are given in Table 11. The statisti-<lb/>cal, experimental systematic and model uncertainties on these quantities are given in <lb/>Tables 12, 13 and 14, respectively. <lb/> Table 11: Interference fit fractions (%) from the nominal DP fit. The amplitudes are all pairwise <lb/>products involving: (A  0  ) K  *  (892)  0  , (A  1  ) K  *  (1410)  0  , (A  2  ) K  * <lb/> 0  (1430)  0  , (A  3  ) LASS nonresonant, <lb/>(A  4  ) K  * <lb/> 2  (1430)  0  , (A  5  ) D  * <lb/> 0  (2400)  −  , (A  6  ) D  * <lb/> 2  (2460)  −  , (A  7  ) Dπ S-wave (dabba), (A  8  ) Dπ P-wave <lb/>(EFF). The diagonal elements are the same as the conventional fit fractions. <lb/> A  0 <lb/> A  1 <lb/> A  2 <lb/> A  3 <lb/> A  4 <lb/> A  5 <lb/> A  6 <lb/> A  7 <lb/> A  8 <lb/> A  0 <lb/> 37.4 <lb/>1.8 −0.0 <lb/> 0.0 <lb/>0.0 −2.4 −0.2 −2.6 −5.0 <lb/> A  1 <lb/> 0.7 −0.0 <lb/> 0.0 <lb/>0.0 −1.1 −0.3 −0.6 −1.1 <lb/> A  2 <lb/> 5.1 −3.2 −0.0 <lb/> 2.9 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.9 <lb/> A  3 <lb/> 4.8 <lb/>0.0 −8.4 <lb/> 0.1 <lb/>2.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/> A  4 <lb/> 7.4 −0.3 −1.0 −1.5 −0.4 <lb/> A  5 <lb/> 19.3 −0.0 <lb/> 2.8 <lb/>0.0 <lb/> A  6 <lb/> 23.1 −0.0 <lb/> 0.0 <lb/> A  7 <lb/> 6.6 −0.0 <lb/> A  8 <lb/> 8.9 <lb/> Table 12: Statistical uncertainties on the interference fit fractions (%). The amplitudes are <lb/>all pairwise products involving: (A  0  ) K  *  (892)  0  , (A  1  ) K  *  (1410)  0  , (A  2  ) K  * <lb/> 0  (1430)  0  , (A  3  ) LASS <lb/>nonresonant, (A  4  ) K  * <lb/> 2  (1430)  0  , (A  5  ) D  * <lb/> 0  (2400)  −  , (A  6  ) D  * <lb/> 2  (2460)  −  , (A  7  ) Dπ S-wave (dabba), (A  8  ) <lb/> Dπ P-wave (EFF). The diagonal elements are the same as the conventional fit fractions. <lb/> A  0  A  1  A  2  A  3  A  4  A  5  A  6  A  7  A  8 <lb/> A  0  1.5 0.7 0.0 0.0 0.0 0.9 0.4 0.4 0.5 <lb/> A  1 <lb/> 0.3 0.0 0.0 0.0 0.7 0.3 0.4 0.5 <lb/> A  2 <lb/> 2.0 2.6 0.0 1.1 0.5 1.5 0.5 <lb/> A  3 <lb/> 3.8 0.0 3.2 0.4 3.4 0.8 <lb/> A  4 <lb/> 1.7 0.6 0.1 0.6 0.5 <lb/> A  5 <lb/> 2.8 0.0 3.1 0.0 <lb/> A  6 <lb/> 1.2 0.0 0.0 <lb/> A  7 <lb/> 1.4 0.0 <lb/> A  8 <lb/> 1.6 <lb/></div>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex"> Table 13: Experimental systematic uncertainties on the interference fit fractions (%). The <lb/>amplitudes are all pairwise products involving: (A  0  ) K  *  (892)  0  , (A  1  ) K  *  (1410)  0  , (A  2  ) K  * <lb/> 0  (1430)  0  , <lb/>(A  3  ) LASS nonresonant, (A  4  ) K  * <lb/> 2  (1430)  0  , (A  5  ) D  * <lb/> 0  (2400)  −  , (A  6  ) D  * <lb/> 2  (2460)  −  , (A  7  ) Dπ S-wave <lb/>(dabba), (A  8  ) Dπ P-wave (EFF). The diagonal elements are the same as the conventional fit <lb/>fractions. <lb/> A  0  A  1  A  2  A  3  A  4  A  5  A  6  A  7  A  8 <lb/> A  0  1.2 0.5 0.0 0.0 0.0 2.3 0.2 0.4 0.5 <lb/> A  1 <lb/> 0.8 0.0 0.0 0.0 0.4 0.8 0.7 0.9 <lb/> A  2 <lb/> 2.4 3.1 0.0 1.4 2.0 2.6 1.1 <lb/> A  3 <lb/> 3.8 0.0 3.6 0.2 2.6 0.3 <lb/> A  4 <lb/> 1.1 2.2 0.2 0.5 1.0 <lb/> A  5 <lb/> 2.0 0.0 4.0 0.0 <lb/> A  6 <lb/> 1.1 0.0 0.0 <lb/> A  7 <lb/> 1.2 0.0 <lb/> A  8 <lb/> 2.2 <lb/> Table 14: Model uncertainties on the interference fit fractions (%). The amplitudes are all pairwise <lb/>products involving: (A  0  ) K  *  (892)  0  , (A  1  ) K  *  (1410)  0  , (A  2  ) K  * <lb/> 0  (1430)  0  , (A  3  ) LASS nonresonant, <lb/>(A  4  ) K  * <lb/> 2  (1430)  0  , (A  5  ) D  * <lb/> 0  (2400)  −  , (A  6  ) D  * <lb/> 2  (2460)  −  , (A  7  ) Dπ S-wave (dabba), (A  8  ) Dπ P-wave <lb/>(EFF). The diagonal elements are the same as the conventional fit fractions. <lb/> A  0  A  1  A  2  A  3  A  4  A  5  A  6  A  7  A  8 <lb/> A  0  1.7 0.8 0.0 0.0 0.0 2.6 0.7 0.8 1.4 <lb/> A  1 <lb/> 0.8 0.0 0.0 0.0 0.8 0.6 0.8 1.1 <lb/> A  2 <lb/> 3.4 2.9 0.0 5.8 1.7 3.6 2.7 <lb/> A  3 <lb/> 6.6 0.0 8.3 0.3 3.5 0.7 <lb/> A  4 <lb/> 2.0 1.7 0.2 1.2 1.0 <lb/> A  5 <lb/> 7.4 0.0 4.5 0.0 <lb/> A  6 <lb/> 1.2 0.0 0.0 <lb/> A  7 <lb/> 3.7 0.0 <lb/> A  8 <lb/> 2.9 <lb/></div>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<front> LHCb collaboration <lb/> R. Aaij  38  , B. Adeva  37  , M. Adinolfi  46  , A. Affolder  52  , Z. Ajaltouni  5  , S. Akar  6  , J. Albrecht  9  , <lb/>F. Alessio  38  , M. Alexander  51  , S. Ali  41  , G. Alkhazov  30  , P. Alvarez Cartelle  53  , A.A. Alves Jr  57  , <lb/>S. Amato  2  , S. Amerio  22  , Y. Amhis  7  , L. An  3  , L. Anderlini  17,g  , J. Anderson  40  , M. Andreotti  16,f  , <lb/>J.E. Andrews  58  , R.B. Appleby  54  , O. Aquines Gutierrez  10  , F. Archilli  38  , P. d&apos;Argent  11  , <lb/>A. Artamonov  35  , M. Artuso  59  , E. Aslanides  6  , G. Auriemma  25,n  , M. Baalouch  5  , S. Bachmann  11  , <lb/>J.J. Back  48  , A. Badalov  36  , C. Baesso  60  , W. Baldini  16,38  , R.J. Barlow  54  , C. Barschel  38  , <lb/>S. Barsuk  7  , W. Barter  38  , V. Batozskaya  28  , V. Battista  39  , A. Bay  39  , L. Beaucourt  4  , J. Beddow  51  , <lb/>F. Bedeschi  23  , I. Bediaga  1  , L.J. Bel  41  , I. Belyaev  31  , E. Ben-Haim  8  , G. Bencivenni  18  , S. Benson  38  , <lb/>J. Benton  46  , A. Berezhnoy  32  , R. Bernet  40  , A. Bertolin  22  , M.-O. Bettler  38  , M. van Beuzekom  41  , <lb/>A. Bien  11  , S. Bifani  45  , T. Bird  54  , A. Birnkraut  9  , A. Bizzeti  17,i  , T. Blake  48  , F. Blanc  39  , <lb/>J. Blouw  10  , S. Blusk  59  , V. Bocci  25  , A. Bondar  34  , N. Bondar  30,38  , W. Bonivento  15  , S. Borghi  54  , <lb/>M. Borsato  7  , T.J.V. Bowcock  52  , E. Bowen  40  , C. Bozzi  16  , S. Braun  11  , D. Brett  54  , M. Britsch  10  , <lb/>T. Britton  59  , J. Brodzicka  54  , N.H. Brook  46  , A. Bursche  40  , J. Buytaert  38  , S. Cadeddu  15  , <lb/>R. Calabrese  16,f  , M. Calvi  20,k  , M. Calvo Gomez  36,p  , P. Campana  18  , D. Campora Perez  38  , <lb/>L. Capriotti  54  , A. Carbone  14,d  , G. Carboni  24,l  , R. Cardinale  19,j  , A. Cardini  15  , P. Carniti  20  , <lb/>L. Carson  50  , K. Carvalho Akiba  2,38  , R. Casanova Mohr  36  , G. Casse  52  , L. Cassina  20,k  , <lb/>L. Castillo Garcia  38  , M. Cattaneo  38  , Ch. Cauet  9  , G. Cavallero  19  , R. Cenci  23,t  , M. Charles  8  , <lb/>Ph. Charpentier  38  , M. Chefdeville  4  , S. Chen  54  , S.-F. Cheung  55  , N. Chiapolini  40  , M. Chrzaszcz  40  , <lb/>X. Cid Vidal  38  , G. Ciezarek  41  , P.E.L. Clarke  50  , M. Clemencic  38  , H.V. Cliff  47  , J. Closier  38  , <lb/>V. Coco  38  , J. Cogan  6  , E. Cogneras  5  , V. Cogoni  15,e  , L. Cojocariu  29  , G. Collazuol  22  , P. Collins  38  , <lb/>A. Comerma-Montells  11  , A. Contu  15,38  , A. Cook  46  , M. Coombes  46  , S. Coquereau  8  , G. Corti  38  , <lb/>M. Corvo  16,f  , B. Couturier  38  , G.A. Cowan  50  , D.C. Craik  48  , A. Crocombe  48  , M. Cruz Torres  60  , <lb/>S. Cunliffe  53  , R. Currie  53  , C. D&apos;Ambrosio  38  , J. Dalseno  46  , P.N.Y. David  41  , A. Davis  57  , <lb/>K. De Bruyn  41  , S. De Capua  54  , M. De Cian  11  , J.M. De Miranda  1  , L. De Paula  2  , W. De Silva  57  , <lb/>P. De Simone  18  , C.-T. Dean  51  , D. Decamp  4  , M. Deckenhoff  9  , L. Del Buono  8  , N. Déléage  4  , <lb/>D. Derkach  55  , O. Deschamps  5  , F. Dettori  38  , B. Dey  40  , A. Di Canto  38  , F. Di Ruscio  24  , <lb/>H. Dijkstra  38  , S. Donleavy  52  , F. Dordei  11  , M. Dorigo  39  , A. Dosil Suárez  37  , D. Dossett  48  , <lb/>A. Dovbnya  43  , K. Dreimanis  52  , L. Dufour  41  , G. Dujany  54  , F. Dupertuis  39  , P. Durante  38  , <lb/>R. Dzhelyadin  35  , A. Dziurda  26  , A. Dzyuba  30  , S. Easo  49,38  , U. Egede  53  , V. Egorychev  31  , <lb/>S. Eidelman  34  , S. Eisenhardt  50  , U. Eitschberger  9  , R. Ekelhof  9  , L. Eklund  51  , I. El Rifai  5  , <lb/>Ch. Elsasser  40  , S. Ely  59  , S. Esen  11  , H.M. Evans  47  , T. Evans  55  , A. Falabella  14  , C. Färber  11  , <lb/>C. Farinelli  41  , N. Farley  45  , S. Farry  52  , R. Fay  52  , D. Ferguson  50  , V. Fernandez Albor  37  , <lb/>F. Ferrari  14  , F. Ferreira Rodrigues  1  , M. Ferro-Luzzi  38  , S. Filippov  33  , M. Fiore  16,38,f  , <lb/>M. Fiorini  16,f  , M. Firlej  27  , C. Fitzpatrick  39  , T. Fiutowski  27  , K. Fohl  38  , P. Fol  53  , M. Fontana  10  , <lb/>F. Fontanelli  19,j  , R. Forty  38  , O. Francisco  2  , M. Frank  38  , C. Frei  38  , M. Frosini  17  , J. Fu  21  , <lb/>E. Furfaro  24,l  , A. Gallas Torreira  37  , D. Galli  14,d  , S. Gallorini  22,38  , S. Gambetta  50  , <lb/>M. Gandelman  2  , P. Gandini  55  , Y. Gao  3  , J. García Pardiñas  37  , J. Garofoli  59  , J. Garra Tico  47  , <lb/>L. Garrido  36  , D. Gascon  36  , C. Gaspar  38  , U. Gastaldi  16  , R. Gauld  55  , L. Gavardi  9  , G. Gazzoni  5  , <lb/>A. Geraci  21,v  , D. Gerick  11  , E. Gersabeck  11  , M. Gersabeck  54  , T. Gershon  48  , Ph. Ghez  4  , <lb/>A. Gianelle  22  , S. Gian  39  , V. Gibson  47  , O. G. Girard  39  , L. Giubega  29  , V.V. Gligorov  38  , <lb/>C. Göbel  60  , D. Golubkov  31  , A. Golutvin  53,31,38  , A. Gomes  1,a  , C. Gotti  20,k  , <lb/>M. Grabalosa Gándara  5  , R. Graciani Diaz  36  , L.A. Granado Cardoso  38  , E. Graugés  36  , <lb/>E. Graverini  40  , G. Graziani  17  , A. Grecu  29  , E. Greening  55  , S. Gregson  47  , P. Griffith  45  , L. Grillo  11  , <lb/>O. Grünberg  63  , B. Gui  59  , E. Gushchin  33  , Yu. Guz  35,38  , T. Gys  38  , C. Hadjivasiliou  59  , <lb/></front>

			<page> 31 <lb/></page>

			<front> G. Haefeli  39  , C. Haen  38  , S.C. Haines  47  , S. Hall  53  , B. Hamilton  58  , T. Hampson  46  , X. Han  11  , <lb/>S. Hansmann-Menzemer  11  , N. Harnew  55  , S.T. Harnew  46  , J. Harrison  54  , J. He  38  , T. Head  39  , <lb/>V. Heijne  41  , K. Hennessy  52  , P. Henrard  5  , L. Henry  8  , J.A. Hernando Morata  37  , <lb/>E. van Herwijnen  38  , M. Heß  63  , A. Hicheur  2  , D. Hill  55  , M. Hoballah  5  , C. Hombach  54  , <lb/>W. Hulsbergen  41  , T. Humair  53  , N. Hussain  55  , D. Hutchcroft  52  , D. Hynds  51  , M. Idzik  27  , <lb/>P. Ilten  56  , R. Jacobsson  38  , A. Jaeger  11  , J. Jalocha  55  , E. Jans  41  , A. Jawahery  58  , F. Jing  3  , <lb/>M. John  55  , D. Johnson  38  , C.R. Jones  47  , C. Joram  38  , B. Jost  38  , N. Jurik  59  , S. Kandybei  43  , <lb/>W. Kanso  6  , M. Karacson  38  , T.M. Karbach  38, †  , S. Karodia  51  , M. Kelsey  59  , I.R. Kenyon  45  , <lb/>M. Kenzie  38  , T. Ketel  42  , B. Khanji  20,38,k  , C. Khurewathanakul  39  , S. Klaver  54  , <lb/>K. Klimaszewski  28  , O. Kochebina  7  , M. Kolpin  11  , I. Komarov  39  , R.F. Koopman  42  , <lb/>P. Koppenburg  41,38  , M. Korolev  32  , L. Kravchuk  33  , K. Kreplin  11  , M. Kreps  48  , G. Krocker  11  , <lb/>P. Krokovny  34  , F. Kruse  9  , W. Kucewicz  26,o  , M. Kucharczyk  26  , V. Kudryavtsev  34  , A. <lb/>K. Kuonen  39  , K. Kurek  28  , T. Kvaratskheliya  31  , V.N. La Thi  39  , D. Lacarrere  38  , G. Lafferty  54  , <lb/>A. Lai  15  , D. Lambert  50  , R.W. Lambert  42  , G. Lanfranchi  18  , C. Langenbruch  48  , B. Langhans  38  , <lb/>T. Latham  48  , C. Lazzeroni  45  , R. Le Gac  6  , J. van Leerdam  41  , J.-P. Lees  4  , R. Leèvre  5  , <lb/>A. Leflat  32,38  , J. Lefrançois  7  , O. Leroy  6  , T. Lesiak  26  , B. Leverington  11  , Y. Li  7  , <lb/>T. Likhomanenko  65,64  , M. Liles  52  , R. Lindner  38  , C. Linn  38  , F. Lionetto  40  , B. Liu  15  , X. Liu  3  , <lb/>S. Lohn  38  , I. Longstaff  51  , J.H. Lopes  2  , D. Lucchesi  22,r  , M. Lucio Martinez  37  , H. Luo  50  , <lb/>A. Lupato  22  , E. Luppi  16,f  , O. Lupton  55  , F. Machefert  7  , F. Maciuc  29  , O. Maev  30  , K. Maguire  54  , <lb/>S. Malde  55  , A. Malinin  64  , G. Manca  7  , G. Mancinelli  6  , P. Manning  59  , A. Mapelli  38  , J. Maratas  5  , <lb/>J.F. Marchand  4  , U. Marconi  14  , C. Marin Benito  36  , P. Marino  23,38,t  , R. Märki  39  , J. Marks  11  , <lb/>G. Martellotti  25  , M. Martinelli  39  , D. Martinez Santos  42  , F. Martinez Vidal  66  , <lb/>D. Martins Tostes  2  , A. Massafferri  1  , R. Matev  38  , A. Mathad  48  , Z. Mathe  38  , C. Matteuzzi  20  , <lb/>K. Matthieu  11  , A. Mauri  40  , B. Maurin  39  , A. Mazurov  45  , M. McCann  53  , J. McCarthy  45  , <lb/>A. McNab  54  , R. McNulty  12  , B. Meadows  57  , F. Meier  9  , M. Meissner  11  , M. Merk  41  , <lb/>D.A. Milanes  62  , M.-N. Minard  4  , D.S. Mitzel  11  , J. Molina Rodriguez  60  , S. Monteil  5  , <lb/>M. Morandin  22  , P. Morawski  27  , A. Morà  6  , M.J. Morello  23,t  , J. Moron  27  , A.B. Morris  50  , <lb/>R. Mountain  59  , F. Muheim  50  , J. Müller  9  , K. Müller  40  , V. Müller  9  , M. Mussini  14  , B. Muster  39  , <lb/>P. Naik  46  , T. Nakada  39  , R. Nandakumar  49  , I. Nasteva  2  , M. Needham  50  , N. Neri  21  , S. Neubert  11  , <lb/>N. Neufeld  38  , M. Neuner  11  , A.D. Nguyen  39  , T.D. Nguyen  39  , C. Nguyen-Mau  39,q  , V. Niess  5  , <lb/>R. Niet  9  , N. Nikitin  32  , T. Nikodem  11  , D. Ninci  23  , A. Novoselov  35  , D.P. O&apos;Hanlon  48  , <lb/>A. Oblakowska-Mucha  27  , V. Obraztsov  35  , S. Ogilvy  51  , O. Okhrimenko  44  , R. Oldeman  15,e  , <lb/>C.J.G. Onderwater  67  , B. Osorio Rodrigues  1  , J.M. Otalora Goicochea  2  , A. Otto  38  , P. Owen  53  , <lb/>A. Oyanguren  66  , A. Palano  13,c  , F. Palombo  21,u  , M. Palutan  18  , J. Panman  38  , A. Papanestis  49  , <lb/>M. Pappagallo  51  , L.L. Pappalardo  16,f  , C. Parkes  54  , G. Passaleva  17  , G.D. Patel  52  , M. Patel  53  , <lb/>C. Patrignani  19,j  , A. Pearce  54,49  , A. Pellegrino  41  , G. Penso  25,m  , M. Pepe Altarelli  38  , <lb/>S. Perazzini  14,d  , P. Perret  5  , L. Pescatore  45  , K. Petridis  46  , A. Petrolini  19,j  , M. Petruzzo  21  , <lb/>E. Picatoste Olloqui  36  , B. Pietrzyk  4  , T. Pilař  48  , D. Pinci  25  , A. Pistone  19  , A. Piucci  11  , <lb/>S. Playfer  50  , M. Plo Casasus  37  , T. Poikela  38  , F. Polci  8  , A. Poluektov  48,34  , I. Polyakov  31  , <lb/>E. Polycarpo  2  , A. Popov  35  , D. Popov  10,38  , B. Popovici  29  , C. Potterat  2  , E. Price  46  , J.D. Price  52  , <lb/>J. Prisciandaro  39  , A. Pritchard  52  , C. Prouve  46  , V. Pugatch  44  , A. Puig Navarro  39  , G. Punzi  23,s  , <lb/>W. Qian  4  , R. Quagliani  7,46  , B. Rachwal  26  , J.H. Rademacker  46  , B. Rakotomiaramanana  39  , <lb/>M. Rama  23  , M.S. Rangel  2  , I. Raniuk  43  , N. Rauschmayr  38  , G. Raven  42  , F. Redi  53  , S. Reichert  54  , <lb/>M.M. Reid  48  , A.C. dos Reis  1  , S. Ricciardi  49  , S. Richards  46  , M. Rihl  38  , K. Rinnert  52  , <lb/>V. Rives Molina  36  , P. Robbe  7,38  , A.B. Rodrigues  1  , E. Rodrigues  54  , J.A. Rodriguez Lopez  62  , <lb/>P. Rodriguez Perez  54  , S. Roiser  38  , V. Romanovsky  35  , A. Romero Vidal  37  , M. Rotondo  22  , <lb/></front>

			<page> 32 <lb/></page>

			<front> J. Rouvinet  39  , T. Ruf  38  , H. Ruiz  36  , P. Ruiz Valls  66  , J.J. Saborido Silva  37  , N. Sagidova  30  , <lb/>P. Sail  51  , B. Saitta  15,e  , V. Salustino Guimaraes  2  , C. Sanchez Mayordomo  66  , <lb/>B. Sanmartin Sedes  37  , R. Santacesaria  25  , C. Santamarina Rios  37  , M. Santimaria  18  , <lb/>E. Santovetti  24,l  , A. Sarti  18,m  , C. Satriano  25,n  , A. Satta  24  , D.M. Saunders  46  , D. Savrina  31,32  , <lb/>M. Schiller  38  , H. Schindler  38  , M. Schlupp  9  , M. Schmelling  10  , T. Schmelzer  9  , B. Schmidt  38  , <lb/>O. Schneider  39  , A. Schopper  38  , M. Schubiger  39  , M.-H. Schune  7  , R. Schwemmer  38  , B. Sciascia  18  , <lb/>A. Sciubba  25,m  , A. Semennikov  31  , I. Sepp  53  , N. Serra  40  , J. Serrano  6  , L. Sestini  22  , P. Seyfert  11  , <lb/>M. Shapkin  35  , I. Shapoval  16,43,f  , Y. Shcheglov  30  , T. Shears  52  , L. Shekhtman  34  , V. Shevchenko  64  , <lb/>A. Shires  9  , R. Silva Coutinho  48  , G. Simi  22  , M. Sirendi  47  , N. Skidmore  46  , I. Skillicorn  51  , <lb/>T. Skwarnicki  59  , E. Smith  55,49  , E. Smith  53  , I. T. Smith  50  , J. Smith  47  , M. Smith  54  , H. Snoek  41  , <lb/>M.D. Sokoloff  57,38  , F.J.P. Soler  51  , F. Soomro  39  , D. Souza  46  , B. Souza De Paula  2  , B. Spaan  9  , <lb/>P. Spradlin  51  , S. Sridharan  38  , F. Stagni  38  , M. Stahl  11  , S. Stahl  38  , O. Steinkamp  40  , <lb/>O. Stenyakin  35  , F. Sterpka  59  , S. Stevenson  55  , S. Stoica  29  , S. Stone  59  , B. Storaci  40  , S. Stracka  23,t  , <lb/>M. Straticiuc  29  , U. Straumann  40  , L. Sun  57  , W. Sutcliffe  53  , K. Swientek  27  , S. Swientek  9  , <lb/>V. Syropoulos  42  , M. Szczekowski  28  , P. Szczypka  39,38  , T. Szumlak  27  , S. T&apos;Jampens  4  , <lb/>T. Tekampe  9  , M. Teklishyn  7  , G. Tellarini  16,f  , F. Teubert  38  , C. Thomas  55  , E. Thomas  38  , <lb/>J. van Tilburg  41  , V. Tisserand  4  , M. Tobin  39  , J. Todd  57  , S. Tolk  42  , L. Tomassetti  16,f  , <lb/>D. Tonelli  38  , S. Topp-Joergensen  55  , N. Torr  55  , E. Tournefier  4  , S. Tourneur  39  , K. Trabelsi  39  , <lb/>M.T. Tran  39  , M. Tresch  40  , A. Trisovic  38  , A. Tsaregorodtsev  6  , P. Tsopelas  41  , N. Tuning  41,38  , <lb/>A. Ukleja  28  , A. Ustyuzhanin  65,64  , U. Uwer  11  , C. Vacca  15,e  , V. Vagnoni  14  , G. Valenti  14  , <lb/>A. Vallier  7  , R. Vazquez Gomez  18  , P. Vazquez Regueiro  37  , C. Vázquez Sierra  37  , S. Vecchi  16  , <lb/>J.J. Velthuis  46  , M. Veltri  17,h  , G. Veneziano  39  , M. Vesterinen  11  , B. Viaud  7  , D. Vieira  2  , <lb/>M. Vieites Diaz  37  , X. Vilasis-Cardona  36,p  , A. Vollhardt  40  , D. Volyanskyy  10  , D. Voong  46  , <lb/>A. Vorobyev  30  , V. Vorobyev  34  , C. Voß  63  , J.A. de Vries  41  , R. Waldi  63  , C. Wallace  48  , R. Wallace  12  , <lb/>J. Walsh  23  , S. Wandernoth  11  , J. Wang  59  , D.R. Ward  47  , N.K. Watson  45  , D. Websdale  53  , <lb/>A. Weiden  40  , M. Whitehead  48  , D. Wiedner  11  , G. Wilkinson  55,38  , M. Wilkinson  59  , M. Williams  38  , <lb/>M.P. Williams  45  , M. Williams  56  , T. Williams  45  , F.F. Wilson  49  , J. Wimberley  58  , J. Wishahi  9  , <lb/>W. Wislicki  28  , M. Witek  26  , G. Wormser  7  , S.A. Wotton  47  , S. Wright  47  , K. Wyllie  38  , Y. Xie  61  , <lb/>Z. Xu  39  , Z. Yang  3  , J. Yu  61  , X. Yuan  34  , O. Yushchenko  35  , M. Zangoli  14  , M. Zavertyaev  10,b  , <lb/>L. Zhang  3  , Y. Zhang  3  , A. Zhelezov  11  , A. Zhokhov  31  , L. Zhong  3  . <lb/> 1  Centro Brasileiro de Pesquisas Físicas (CBPF), Rio de Janeiro, Brazil <lb/> 2  Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro (UFRJ), Rio de Janeiro, Brazil <lb/> 3  Center for High Energy Physics, Tsinghua University, Beijing, China <lb/> 4  LAPP, Université Savoie Mont-Blanc, CNRS/IN2P3, Annecy-Le-Vieux, France <lb/> 5  Clermont Université, Université Blaise Pascal, CNRS/IN2P3, LPC, Clermont-Ferrand, France <lb/> 6  CPPM, Aix-Marseille Université, CNRS/IN2P3, Marseille, France <lb/> 7  LAL, Université Paris-Sud, CNRS/IN2P3, Orsay, France <lb/> 8  LPNHE, Université Pierre et Marie Curie, Université Paris Diderot, CNRS/IN2P3, Paris, France <lb/> 9  Fakultät Physik, Technische Universität Dortmund, Dortmund, Germany <lb/> 10  Max-Planck-Institut für Kernphysik (MPIK), Heidelberg, Germany <lb/> 11  Physikalisches Institut, Ruprecht-Karls-Universität Heidelberg, Heidelberg, Germany <lb/> 12  School of Physics, University College Dublin, Dublin, Ireland <lb/> 13  Sezione INFN di Bari, Bari, Italy <lb/> 14  Sezione INFN di Bologna, Bologna, Italy <lb/> 15  Sezione INFN di Cagliari, Cagliari, Italy <lb/> 16  Sezione INFN di Ferrara, Ferrara, Italy <lb/> 17  Sezione INFN di Firenze, Firenze, Italy <lb/></front>

			<page> 33 <lb/></page>

			<front> 18  Laboratori Nazionali dell&apos;INFN di Frascati, Frascati, Italy <lb/> 19  Sezione INFN di Genova, Genova, Italy <lb/> 20  Sezione INFN di Milano Bicocca, Milano, Italy <lb/> 21  Sezione INFN di Milano, Milano, Italy <lb/> 22  Sezione INFN di Padova, Padova, Italy <lb/> 23  Sezione INFN di Pisa, Pisa, Italy <lb/> 24  Sezione INFN di Roma Tor Vergata, Roma, Italy <lb/> 25  Sezione INFN di Roma La Sapienza, Roma, Italy <lb/> 26  Henryk Niewodniczanski Institute of Nuclear Physics Polish Academy of Sciences, Kraków, Poland <lb/> 27  AGH -University of Science and Technology, Faculty of Physics and Applied Computer Science, <lb/>Kraków, Poland <lb/> 28  National Center for Nuclear Research (NCBJ), Warsaw, Poland <lb/> 29  Horia Hulubei National Institute of Physics and Nuclear Engineering, Bucharest-Magurele, Romania <lb/> 30  Petersburg Nuclear Physics Institute (PNPI), Gatchina, Russia <lb/> 31  Institute of Theoretical and Experimental Physics (ITEP), Moscow, Russia <lb/> 32  Institute of Nuclear Physics, Moscow State University (SINP MSU), Moscow, Russia <lb/> 33  Institute for Nuclear Research of the Russian Academy of Sciences (INR RAN), Moscow, Russia <lb/> 34  Budker Institute of Nuclear Physics (SB RAS) and Novosibirsk State University, Novosibirsk, Russia <lb/> 35  Institute for High Energy Physics (IHEP), Protvino, Russia <lb/> 36  Universitat de Barcelona, Barcelona, Spain <lb/> 37  Universidad de Santiago de Compostela, Santiago de Compostela, Spain <lb/> 38  European Organization for Nuclear Research (CERN), Geneva, Switzerland <lb/> 39  Ecole Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL), Lausanne, Switzerland <lb/> 40  Physik-Institut, Universität Zürich, Zürich, Switzerland <lb/> 41  Nikhef National Institute for Subatomic Physics, Amsterdam, The Netherlands <lb/> 42  Nikhef National Institute for Subatomic Physics and VU University Amsterdam, Amsterdam, The <lb/>Netherlands <lb/> 43  NSC Kharkiv Institute of Physics and Technology (NSC KIPT), Kharkiv, Ukraine <lb/> 44  Institute for Nuclear Research of the National Academy of Sciences (KINR), Kyiv, Ukraine <lb/> 45  University of Birmingham, Birmingham, United Kingdom <lb/> 46  H.H. Wills Physics Laboratory, University of Bristol, Bristol, United Kingdom <lb/> 47  Cavendish Laboratory, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, United Kingdom <lb/> 48  Department of Physics, University of Warwick, Coventry, United Kingdom <lb/> 49  STFC Rutherford Appleton Laboratory, Didcot, United Kingdom <lb/> 50  School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, United Kingdom <lb/> 51  School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Glasgow, Glasgow, United Kingdom <lb/> 52  Oliver Lodge Laboratory, University of Liverpool, Liverpool, United Kingdom <lb/> 53  Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom <lb/> 54  School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Manchester, Manchester, United Kingdom <lb/> 55  Department of Physics, University of Oxford, Oxford, United Kingdom <lb/> 56  Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA, United States <lb/> 57  University of Cincinnati, Cincinnati, OH, United States <lb/> 58  University of Maryland, College Park, MD, United States <lb/> 59  Syracuse University, Syracuse, NY, United States <lb/> 60  Pontifícia Universidade Católica do Rio de Janeiro (PUC-Rio), Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, associated to <lb/> 2 <lb/>61  Institute of Particle Physics, Central China Normal University, Wuhan, Hubei, China, associated to <lb/> 3 <lb/>62  Departamento de Fisica , Universidad Nacional de Colombia, Bogota, Colombia, associated to <lb/> 8 <lb/>63  Institut für Physik, Universität Rostock, Rostock, Germany, associated to <lb/> 11 <lb/>64  National Research Centre Kurchatov Institute, Moscow, Russia, associated to <lb/> 31 <lb/>65  Yandex School of Data Analysis, Moscow, Russia, associated to <lb/> 31 <lb/>66  Instituto de Fisica Corpuscular (IFIC), Universitat de Valencia-CSIC, Valencia, Spain, associated to <lb/> 36 <lb/>67  Van Swinderen Institute, University of Groningen, Groningen, The Netherlands, associated to <lb/> 41 <lb/></front>

			<page> 34 <lb/></page>

			<front> a  Universidade Federal do Triângulo Mineiro (UFTM), Uberaba-MG, Brazil <lb/> b  P.N. Lebedev Physical Institute, Russian Academy of Science (LPI RAS), Moscow, Russia <lb/> c  Universià di Bari, Bari, Italy <lb/> d  Universià di Bologna, Bologna, Italy <lb/> e  Universià di Cagliari, Cagliari, Italy <lb/> f  Universià di Ferrara, Ferrara, Italy <lb/> g  Universià di Firenze, Firenze, Italy <lb/> h  Universià di Urbino, Urbino, Italy <lb/> i  Universià di Modena e Reggio Emilia, Modena, Italy <lb/> j  Universià di Genova, Genova, Italy <lb/> k  Universià di Milano Bicocca, Milano, Italy <lb/> l  Universià di Roma Tor Vergata, Roma, Italy <lb/> m  Universià di Roma La Sapienza, Roma, Italy <lb/> n  Universià della Basilicata, Potenza, Italy <lb/> o  AGH -University of Science and Technology, Faculty of Computer Science, Electronics and <lb/>Telecommunications, Kraków, Poland <lb/> p  LIFAELS, La Salle, Universitat Ramon Llull, Barcelona, Spain <lb/> q  Hanoi University of Science, Hanoi, Viet Nam <lb/> r  Universià di Padova, Padova, Italy <lb/> s  Universià di Pisa, Pisa, Italy <lb/> t  Scuola Normale Superiore, Pisa, Italy <lb/> u  Universià degli Studi di Milano, Milano, Italy <lb/> v  Politecnico di Milano, Milano, Italy <lb/>  †  Deceased <lb/></front>

			<page> 35 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
