<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage>This content has been downloaded from IOPscience. Please scroll down to see the full text. <lb/>Download details: <lb/>IP Address: 131.169.95.182 <lb/>This content was downloaded on 09/01/2017 at 10:16 <lb/>Please note that terms and conditions apply. <lb/>Radio measurements of the energy and the depth of the shower maximum of cosmic-ray air <lb/>showers by Tunka-Rex <lb/>View the table of contents for this issue, or go to the journal homepage for more <lb/>JCAP01(2016)052 <lb/>(http://iopscience.iop.org/1475-7516/2016/01/052) <lb/>Home Search Collections Journals About Contact us My IOPscience <lb/>You may also be interested in: <lb/>The wavefront of the radio signal emitted by cosmic ray air showers <lb/>W.D. Apel, J.C. Arteaga-Velázquez, L. Bähren et al. <lb/>Tunka-Rex: a Radio Extension of the Tunka Experiment <lb/>F G Schröder, D Besson, N M Budnev et al. <lb/>Radio Measurements of Air Showers with LOPES <lb/>F G Schröder, W D Apel, J C Arteaga-Velazquez et al. <lb/>High-energy cosmic rays and the Greisen-Zatsepin-Kuz&apos;min effect <lb/>A A Watson <lb/>Reconstruction of inclined air showers detected with thePierre Auger Observatory <lb/>The Pierre Auger collaboration <lb/>Polarized radio emission from extensive air showers measured with LOFAR <lb/>P. Schellart, S. Buitink, A. Corstanje et al. <lb/>Search for the end of the energy spectrum of primary cosmic rays <lb/>M Nagano <lb/>Cosmic-Ray Energy Spectrum1017-1018.3 eV <lb/>T. Abu-Zayyad, K. Belov, D. J. Bird et al. <lb/></titlePage>

			<front>JCAP01(2016)052 <lb/>ournal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics <lb/>An IOP and SISSA journal <lb/>J <lb/>Radio measurements of the energy <lb/>and the depth of the shower <lb/>maximum of cosmic-ray air showers by <lb/>Tunka-Rex <lb/>The Tunka-Rex collaboration <lb/>P.A. Bezyazeekov, a N.M. Budnev, a O.A. Gress, a A. Haungs, b <lb/>R. Hiller, b T. Huege, b Y. Kazarina, a M. Kleifges, c <lb/>E.N. Konstantinov, a E.E. Korosteleva, d D. Kostunin, b O. Krömer, c <lb/>L.A. Kuzmichev, d N. Lubsandorzhiev, d R.R. Mirgazov, a <lb/>R. Monkhoev, a A. Pakhorukov, a L. Pankov, a V.V. Prosin, d <lb/>G.I. Rubtsov, e F.G. Schröder, b R. Wischnewski f and <lb/>A. Zagorodnikov a <lb/>a Institute of Applied Physics, Irkutsk State University (ISU), <lb/>Blvd Gagarina 20, Irkutsk, Russia <lb/>b Institute for Nuclear Physics (IKP), Karlsruhe Institute of Technology (KIT), <lb/>Hermann-von-Helmholtz-Platz 1, 76344 Eggenstein-Leopoldshafen, Germany <lb/>c Institute for Data Processing and Electronics (IPE), <lb/>Karlsruhe Institute of Technology (KIT), <lb/>Hermann-von-Helmholtz-Platz 1, 76344 Eggenstein-Leopoldshafen, Germany <lb/>d Skobeltsyn Institute of Nuclear Physics, Moscow State University (MSU), <lb/>Leninskie gory, GSP-1, Moscow 119991, Russia <lb/>e Institute for Nuclear Research of the Russian Academy of Sciences, <lb/>60th October Anniversary st. 7a, Moscow, Russia <lb/>f Deutsches Elektronen-Synchrotron (DESY), <lb/>Platanenallee 6, 15738 Zeuthen, Germany <lb/>E-mail: frank.schroeder@kit.edu <lb/>Received September 21, 2015 <lb/>Revised December 22, 2015 <lb/>Accepted January 7, 2016 <lb/>Published January 27, 2016 <lb/>Article funded by SCOAP 3 . Content from this work may be used <lb/>under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License. <lb/>Any further distribution of this work must maintain attribution to the author(s) <lb/>and the title of the work, journal citation and DOI. <lb/>doi:10.1088/1475-7516/2016/01/052 <lb/>JCAP01(2016)052 <lb/>Abstract. We reconstructed the energy and the position of the shower maximum of air <lb/>showers with energies E 100 PeV applying a method using radio measurements performed <lb/>with Tunka-Rex. An event-to-event comparison to air-Cherenkov measurements of the same <lb/>air showers with the Tunka-133 photomultiplier array confirms that the radio reconstruction <lb/>works reliably. The Tunka-Rex reconstruction methods and absolute scales have been tuned <lb/>on CoREAS simulations and yield energy and X max values consistent with the Tunka-133 <lb/>measurements. The results of two independent measurement seasons agree within statistical <lb/>uncertainties, which gives additional confidence in the radio reconstruction. The energy <lb/>precision of Tunka-Rex is comparable to the Tunka-133 precision of 15 %, and exhibits a 20 % <lb/>uncertainty on the absolute scale dominated by the amplitude calibration of the antennas. For <lb/>X max , this is the first direct experimental correlation of radio measurements with a different, <lb/>established method. At the moment, the X max resolution of Tunka-Rex is approximately <lb/>40 g/cm 2 . This resolution can probably be improved by deploying additional antennas and <lb/>by further development of the reconstruction methods, since the present analysis does not <lb/>yet reveal any principle limitations. <lb/>Keywords: ultra high energy cosmic rays, cosmic ray experiments, cosmic rays detectors <lb/>ArXiv ePrint: 1509.05652 <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">JCAP01(2016)052 <lb/></note>

			<div type="toc">Contents <lb/>1 Introduction <lb/>1 <lb/>2 Experimental setup and data selection <lb/>2 <lb/>3 Reconstruction of energy and shower maximum <lb/>6 <lb/>3.1 Asymmetry correction <lb/>7 <lb/>3.2 Lateral distribution function (LDF) <lb/>8 <lb/>3.3 Primary energy E pr , and atmospheric depth of shower maximum X max <lb/>9 <lb/>4 Results <lb/>10 <lb/>5 Discussion <lb/>11 <lb/>5.1 Validity of the results <lb/>11 <lb/>5.2 Precision and accuracy <lb/>12 <lb/>5.3 Comparison with other experiments <lb/>14 <lb/>6 Outlook <lb/>14 <lb/>7 Conclusion <lb/>15 <lb/>A Parametrization of LDF parameter a 2 <lb/>16 <lb/>B Comparison of both seasons <lb/>16 <lb/></div>

			<body>1 Introduction <lb/>After more than 100 years of cosmic-ray measurements, the mass composition and the energy <lb/>spectrum of the primary particles is relatively well-known only in the energy range accessible <lb/>by direct measurements, E 10 15 eV. At higher energies the flux of cosmic-rays is too low <lb/>to perform direct measurements with statistical significance. Consequently, the knowledge <lb/>is poorer and relies on the measurement of secondary-particle cascades called air showers. <lb/>These indirect cosmic-ray measurements use the atmosphere as a calorimeter. The energy of <lb/>the primary particle can be estimated from the energy contained in the shower. The type of <lb/>the primary particle can, for example, be deduced from the longitudinal shower development. <lb/>Heavy primary particles such as iron nuclei on average interact earlier in the atmosphere than <lb/>light particles such as protons. Thus, the mass composition can be statistically estimated <lb/>from measurements of the atmospheric depth of the shower maximum, X max . <lb/>Established air-shower techniques are the measurement of secondary particles on ground, <lb/>the measurement of fluorescence or air-Cherenkov light by dedicated telescopes or non-<lb/>imaging detectors on ground. The latter two methods have a relatively high accuracy for the <lb/>energy and for X max , but are limited to dark and clear nights. Detection of the radio emission <lb/>by air showers is an additional technique, which does not suffer from this intrinsic limitation of <lb/>the exposure. The radio signal is sensitive to the shower energy [1] and X max [2-5], too, but it <lb/>has not yet been demonstrated experimentally that the accuracy for both variables is compet-<lb/>itive with those of the other techniques, as indicated by simulation-based studies, e.g., [6-8]. <lb/></body>

			<page>-1 -<lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">JCAP01(2016)052 <lb/></note>

			<body>The main origin of the radio emission is the geomagnetic deflection of relativistic elec-<lb/>trons and positrons in the shower, which induces a time-variable current [9]. The amplitude <lb/>of this emission is proportional to the shower energy and to sin α, with α the angle between <lb/>the geomagnetic field and the shower direction. On a weaker level the Askaryan effect con-<lb/>tributes, i.e., radio emission due to the time variation of the net charge excess in the shower <lb/>front [10-12]. The interference of both effects leads to an azimuthal asymmetry of the radio <lb/>footprint [5, 13]. Finally, the refractive index of air causes Cherenkov-like effects for both <lb/>emission mechanisms [14-16]. <lb/>Tunka-Rex [17] is the radio extension of the Tunka observatory for cosmic-ray air <lb/>showers. Its main detector, Tunka-133, is an array of non-imaging photomultipliers de-<lb/>tecting the Cherenkov light emitted by air-showers in the atmosphere in the energy range <lb/>of 10 16 -10 18 eV. Tunka-133 is fully efficient for all zenith angles θ ≤ 50 • at energies above <lb/>10 16.2 eV [18], which covers the full energy range of Tunka-Rex. For Tunka-133 measurements, <lb/>the energy of the primary particle E pr is reconstructed from the flux of the Cherenkov light <lb/>at 200 m distance to the shower axis, and X max is reconstructed from the steepness of the <lb/>amplitude-distance function. Using these methods, Tunka-133 features an energy resolution <lb/>of about 15 %, and an X max resolution of about 28 g/cm 2 [19]. For comparison, the average <lb/>difference between the extreme cases of a pure proton and a pure iron composition is in the <lb/>order of 100 g/cm 2 . Since Tunka-133 triggers Tunka-Rex, the same air showers are measured <lb/>simultaneously with the air-Cherenkov and the radio detector. <lb/>These combined measurements are used for a cross-check of both methods. In par-<lb/>ticular the precision of Tunka-Rex is estimated by a comparison of the energy and X max <lb/>reconstructions to Tunka-133. Reconstruction methods for Tunka-Rex have been developed <lb/>with CoREAS simulations [20] (the radio extension of CORSIKA [21]) taking into account <lb/>previous theoretical predictions [6, 7, 22, 23], and experience by other experiments, in par-<lb/>ticular LOPES [3], AERA [11] and LOFAR [24]. <lb/>The parameters in the reconstruction methods have been determined from the simula-<lb/>tions (cf. reference [8] for details), and not tuned against the Tunka-133 measurements. First <lb/>results on energy and X max reconstruction have already been presented in reference [25] using <lb/>the first season of Tunka-Rex measurements from October 2012 to April 2013 (effectively 280 <lb/>hours of measurements). The same reconstruction method is now applied also to the second <lb/>season of data from October 2013 to April 2014 (effectively 260 hours of measurements), <lb/>and the combined results and the cross-check between both measurement seasons are pre-<lb/>sented in this article. In the experimental data we observe a direct correlation between the <lb/>Tunka-Rex and Tunka-133 reconstructions, which is used to estimate precision and accuracy <lb/>of Tunka-Rex for energy and X max . <lb/>2 Experimental setup and data selection <lb/>Tunka-Rex started in autumn 2012 with 19 antenna stations, and in summer 2013, 6 further <lb/>antenna stations went into operation giving a total number of 25 antenna stations used for <lb/>the present analysis. In the central area covering about 1 km 2 the spacing is approximately <lb/>200 m. The outer antennas contribute only to a few events (see figure 1). The air-Cherenkov <lb/>array Tunka-133 covers the inner area with 133 photomultipliers, and features additional <lb/>photomultipliers in the outer area. Upon a coincidence trigger of the photomultipliers, both <lb/>the radio and the air-Cherenkov detector are read out in parallel. The electric field of the <lb/></body>

			<page>-2 -<lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">JCAP01(2016)052 <lb/></note>

			<body>−1000 <lb/>− 500 <lb/>0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>East (m) <lb/>−1000 <lb/>− 500 <lb/>0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>Nort h (m) <lb/>antennas 2012 <lb/>antennas 2013 <lb/>photomultipliers <lb/>events of <lb/>first season <lb/>second season <lb/>Figure 1. Map of the antenna array Tunka-Rex and its host experiment, the photomultiplier array <lb/>Tunka-133. 18 antennas had been available since the start of the first season in October 2012, and 7 <lb/>additional antennas have gone in operation only for the second season starting October 2013. The <lb/>shower cores of the Tunka-Rex events are indicated for both seasons. The dashed circle denotes the <lb/>cut on the central area with 500 m radius used for X max reconstruction. <lb/>radio signal measured by Tunka-Rex is reconstructed in an effective bandwidth of 35-76 MHz. <lb/>Details on the detector setup and its calibration can be read in reference [17]. <lb/>The reconstruction of Tunka-133 is fully efficient and has a reliable reconstruction for <lb/>events with zenith angles θ ≤ 50 • . Therefore, only events with θ ≤ 50 • have been selected <lb/>for the present analysis (see figure 2). For these events the Tunka-133 reconstruction of <lb/>the shower provides: energy of the primary particle E pr , atmospheric depth of the shower <lb/>maximum X max , and axis, i.e., the direction and point of incidence on the ground (= shower <lb/>core). For all Tunka-Rex events we used the shower core of Tunka-133 as input, because of <lb/>the denser spacing of the photomultipliers compared to that of the antennas. The direction <lb/>was only used as cross-check: events are considered false-positive, i.e., contaminated by <lb/>background pulses and excluded from the analysis, if the directions reconstructed from the <lb/>radio and air-Cherenkov arrival times deviate by more than 5 • [17]. <lb/>For the selection of Tunka-Rex events we applied a quality cut based on the signal-to-<lb/>noise ratio in individual antenna stations. The signal has to exceed a signal-to-noise ratio, <lb/>SNR ≡ (S/N ) 2 ≥ 10 in at least three antenna stations, where the signal S is the maximum <lb/>of an envelope on the electric-field strength of the pulse, and the noise N the root-mean <lb/>square of the electric field in a time window before the signal. This cut is set such that <lb/>pure background has a chance of about 5 % to pass in an individual antenna, which balances <lb/>efficiency and purity. Given 25 antenna stations, this leads to a non-negligible probability <lb/></body>
			<page>-3 -<lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">JCAP01(2016)052 <lb/></note>

			<body>E <lb/>N <lb/>W <lb/>S <lb/>20°4 <lb/>0°B <lb/>geo <lb/>θ <lb/>events of <lb/>first season <lb/>second season <lb/>Figure 2. Sky map of the Tunka-Rex events of both seasons. The efficiency rises with zenith angle <lb/>and is smaller for arrival directions close to the geomagnetic field B geo . <lb/>that in a true event antenna stations with false-positive signals are contained. To exclude <lb/>most of these false-positive signals, we sort the antennas by their distance to the shower axis. <lb/>After two antenna stations failing the SNR cut, any further antenna stations are excluded <lb/>from the analysis for the particular event. Thus, the risk that an event is contaminated <lb/>by a station with false-positive signal is reduced to approximately 10 %. If surviving false-<lb/>positive signals significantly impact the event reconstruction, they are removed by the cut <lb/>requiring the 5 • agreement between the direction reconstructed by Tunka-Rex and Tunka-<lb/>133. Thus, the remaining data set is assumed to be practically free of false-positive signals. <lb/>Finally, for the X max reconstruction we apply additional quality cuts: at least one antenna <lb/>above threshold has to be at a distance r axis &gt; 200 m to the shower axis, since X max is <lb/>reconstructed from the slope of the lateral distribution, which requires a sufficient lever arm. <lb/>Moreover, the shower core has to be inside the central area of the array (dashed circle in <lb/>figure 1), and the estimator for the statistical reconstruction uncertainty of Tunka-Rex must <lb/>not exceed a certain value: σ(X radio <lb/>max ) ≤ 50 g/cm 2 . <lb/>Reconstruction of the electric-field strengths (= amplitude) in individual antenna sta-<lb/>tions is performed with a modified version of the &apos;Auger Offline&apos; software developed by the <lb/>Pierre Auger Collaboration [26]. This software applies all known experimental characteristics <lb/>to the recorded signals, in particular the frequency-dependent gain and pulse distortion of <lb/>the various components in the signal chain as determined by calibration measurements [17]. <lb/>For the reconstruction of the electric-field vector the simulated direction dependence of the <lb/>antenna gain is used, which has been validated for a few selected directions by calibration <lb/>measurements. <lb/>For the suppression of narrow-band radio-frequency interferences (RFI) we apply rect-<lb/>angular band-stop filters of ±0.2 MHz width (corresponding to 3 bins) at each integer 5 MHz <lb/></body>

			<page>-4 -<lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">JCAP01(2016)052 <lb/></note>

			<body>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>140 <lb/>ε <lb/>true ε <lb/>meas <lb/>signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) <lb/>proton <lb/>iron <lb/>parametrization <lb/>/ <lb/>Figure 3. Average ratio of the true pulse amplitude of CoREAS simulations E true and the amplitude <lb/>after adding measured noise E meas over the signal-to-noise ratio. <lb/>(35, 40, . . . , 75 MHz), since these frequencies are often contaminated by RFI background. 1 <lb/>Since the radio emission from the air shower is broadband, it is significantly less affected <lb/>by the filter than the narrow-band disturbances. The background remaining after filtering <lb/>still on average increases the measured pulse height E meas compared to the true pulse height <lb/>E true , as already seen at the LOPES experiment [27] and assumed for early experiments [28]. <lb/>We studied this effect by adding measured background to about 300 CoREAS simulations <lb/>(figure 3), and found that the parametrization given in reference [27] has to be slightly mod-<lb/>ified introducing a normalization factor k = 4.1 adapted for Tunka-Rex. This normalization <lb/>factor reflects the different ways how the noise level is measured in LOPES (mean of local <lb/>maxima in the instantaneous amplitude) and Tunka-Rex (root mean square of the electric <lb/>field, which corresponds to the mean power of noise). Thus, we use the following formula to <lb/>correct for the average effect of noise: <lb/>E true = E meas • 1 − <lb/>k <lb/>SNR <lb/>, <lb/>(2.1) <lb/>with the signal-to-noise ratio SNR defined above. <lb/>An overview of the available event statistics is provided in table 1, and figure 4 shows <lb/>the distribution of the selected events over energy and X max . Most of the events used for <lb/>the energy reconstruction are at energies above 10 17 eV. The fraction does not reach 100 % <lb/>because some Tunka-133 events have small geomagnetic angles. Also, there were occasional <lb/>technical issues in single antenna stations. For the high-quality events used for the X max re-<lb/>construction, the threshold is slightly higher: above an energy of about 6 • 10 17 eV, all events <lb/>used for energy reconstruction pass also the high-quality cuts required for X max reconstruc-<lb/>tion (see figure 5). Apart from technical issues (e.g., missing or malfunctioning antennas), the <lb/>fraction shown in figure 5 is the efficiency of Tunka-Rex for zenith angles θ ≤ 50 • , because the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">1 In earlier analyses we used a gliding median filter to suppress narrow-band RFI, but it turned out that this <lb/>filter significantly increases the impact of background on the measured amplitudes, without significantly in-<lb/>creasing the signal-to-noise ratio. Nevertheless, the exact method of RFI suppression has only minor influence <lb/>on the high-quality events used in the present analysis. <lb/></note>

			<page>-5 -<lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">JCAP01(2016)052 <lb/></note>

			<body>Number of events <lb/>first season of <lb/>second season of <lb/>after cut on <lb/>Oct. 2012-Apr. 2013 Oct. 2013-Apr. 2014 <lb/>(280 effective hours) (260 effective hours) <lb/>≥ 3 stations with signal <lb/>244 <lb/>445 <lb/>rejecting outlier stations <lb/>122 <lb/>147 <lb/>(Tunka-Rex, Tunka-133) ≤ 5 • <lb/>91 <lb/>87 <lb/>at least one antenna at r axis &gt; 200 m <lb/>64 <lb/>56 <lb/>σ(X radio <lb/>max ) ≤ 50 g/cm 2 <lb/>25 <lb/>22 <lb/>inner area (r &lt; 500 m) <lb/>23 <lb/>19 <lb/>Table 1. Statistics of Tunka-Rex events triggered at zenith angles θ ≤ 50 • in both seasons after <lb/>certain quality cuts. The cuts are applied consecutively in the given order. The event numbers denote <lb/>the number of surviving events after application of all cuts up to that point. The first three cuts are <lb/>used to reject false-positive events contaminated by background pulses. The remaining 91 + 87 events <lb/>are used for energy reconstruction. For X max reconstruction three additional quality cuts are applied <lb/>leaving 23 + 19 events for the two measurement seasons, respectively. <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>16.6 16.8 17 17.2 17.4 17.6 17.8 18 18.2 18.4 <lb/>number of events N <lb/>reconstructed primary energy lg (E pr / eV) <lb/>Tunka-Rex <lb/>Tunka-133 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>700 <lb/>800 <lb/>900 <lb/>number of events N <lb/>reconstructed atmospheric depth of shower maximum X max (g/cm²) <lb/>Tunka-Rex <lb/>Tunka-133 <lb/>Figure 4. Distributions of energy, E pr , and atmospheric depth of the shower maximum, X max , of the <lb/>Tunka-Rex events used in the present analysis. The figure shows the reconstructed values by both <lb/>Tunka-Rex and Tunka-133. Bars represent the statistical uncertainty calculated as <lb/>√ <lb/>N . <lb/>reference is the fully efficient Tunka-133 trigger. The total number of Tunka-Rex events pass-<lb/>ing the quality cuts is larger [17], since in contrast to the air-Cherenkov detection, radio detec-<lb/>tion is more efficient for inclined air showers. Nevertheless, for the present analysis only events <lb/>with θ ≤ 50 • have been selected, since Tunka-133 is fully efficient for this zenith angle range. <lb/>3 Reconstruction of energy and shower maximum <lb/>In the present analysis, the reconstruction of energy and shower maximum is based on the <lb/>lateral distribution, i.e., the dependence of the radio amplitude on the distance to the shower <lb/>axis. This approach has been used earlier. Different experiments have shown that the <lb/>amplitude at a certain distance is correlated with the primary energy, after correcting for <lb/>the geomagnetic angle [1, 29-31]. Moreover, it has been shown that the shape of the lateral <lb/>distribution depends on the distance to the shower maximum [2, 3, 5]. <lb/></body>

			<page>-6 -<lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">JCAP01(2016)052</note> 

			<body><lb/>0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1 <lb/>16.6 <lb/>16.8 <lb/>17 <lb/>17.2 <lb/>17.4 <lb/>17.6 <lb/>17.8 <lb/>18 <lb/>Fraction of triggered Tunka-Rex events <lb/>Energy lg (Epr / eV) <lb/>Events passing Tunka-Rex quality cuts : <lb/>for energy reconstruction <lb/>subset used for X max reconstruction <lb/>Figure 5. Fraction of events which passes the quality cuts applied for the Tunka-Rex energy and X max <lb/>reconstructions, respectively, in comparison with all events triggered by the fully efficient Tunka-133 <lb/>array in the inner area (r &lt; 500 m). <lb/>Our reconstruction method in brief is: <lb/>1. We correct the lateral distribution for the azimuthal asymmetry caused by the inter-<lb/>ference of the geomagnetic and the Askaryan effects, and for the geomagnetic angle α. <lb/>2. We fit a Gaussian LDF, the shape of which depends on three parameters: one scale <lb/>parameter, E 120 , which is the amplitude at 120 m, and two shape parameters a 1 and a 2 , <lb/>which describe the slope and the width of the Gaussian LDF, respectively. E 120 and a 1 <lb/>are fit to the data points, a 2 is fixed using a parametrization depending on energy and <lb/>zenith angle. <lb/>3. We use the fit result E 120 to reconstruct the primary energy E pr , and the fit result for a 1 <lb/>at 180 m axis distance, representing the slope of the lateral distribution, to reconstruct <lb/>the atmospheric depth of the shower maximum X max . <lb/>3.1 Asymmetry correction <lb/>Because of the different polarizations of the radio emission generated by the Askaryan and <lb/>the geomagnetic effects [11, 12, 32], the radio amplitude on ground depends not only on the <lb/>geomagnetic angle α and distance to the shower axis r, but also on the azimuth angle φ g <lb/>of each antenna relative to the shower axis. Fitting the asymmetry for individual events by <lb/>a two-dimensional lateral distribution function (LDF) introduces additional parameters [5]. <lb/>To maintain events with low station multiplicity, we have developed an alternative approach <lb/>described in reference [8], which is well-suited for sparse arrays like Tunka-Rex. <lb/>Our approach makes use of the fact that the asymmetry to first order only depends <lb/>on the shower geometry, which can be reconstructed independently from the LDF by arrival <lb/>time measurements. Based on CoREAS simulations made for the Tunka-Rex setup, the <lb/>azimuthal asymmetry of the footprint is parametrized as function of the antenna position <lb/></body>

			<page>-7 -<lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">JCAP01(2016)052 <lb/></note>

			<body>using a constant typical value of ε asym = 8.5 % for the relative strength of the Askaryan effect. 2 <lb/>Using this parametrization, we correct all measured amplitudes in individual antennas for <lb/>the azimuthal asymmetry, and obtain a one-dimensional lateral distribution in which the <lb/>amplitude depends only on the distance to the shower axis. Simultaneously, we correct for <lb/>the relative strength of the geomagnetic Lorentz force, since this depends only on the shower <lb/>geometry, too, namely on the geomagnetic angle α. Thus, we use the following equation <lb/>to obtain the corrected amplitude E cor (r), which is later used to fit a radially symmetric <lb/>lateral-distribution function: <lb/>E cor (r) = E(r, φ g )/ ε 2 <lb/>asym + 2ε asym cos φ g sin α + sin 2 α , <lb/>(3.1) <lb/>with E(r, φ g ) the measured amplitude after noise correction (E true of equation (2.1)), r the <lb/>distance to the shower axis, φ g the azimuth angle relative to the shower axis (with φ g = 0, <lb/>when a station is in the direction of the geomagnetic Lorentz force), α the geomagnetic angle, <lb/>ε asym = 0.085 the size of the asymmetry, and E cor (r) the amplitude after correction for the <lb/>asymmetry and the geomagnetic angle. After this correction of the amplitude measured <lb/>at each antenna station, the lateral distribution is approximately azimuthally symmetric <lb/>around the shower axis. Thus, to first order the amplitude depends only on the distance to <lb/>the shower axis r, and the lateral distribution can be fitted with a one-dimensional function <lb/>the parameters of which depend on energy and distance to the shower maximum. <lb/>Figure 6 shows an example event with many stations, where the asymmetry correction <lb/>leaves the energy reconstruction almost unchanged, since the LDF fit averages the asymmetry <lb/>out. However, the X max reconstruction is slightly improved for this event (Tunka-Rex X max is <lb/>613±15 g/cm 2 and 621±15g/cm 2 before and after correction, respectively, and the Tunka-133 <lb/>X max is 657 ± 28 g/cm 2 ). Especially for events with few stations, the asymmetry correction <lb/>is important, and can have an effect on the energy reconstruction in the order of 10 %. <lb/>3.2 Lateral distribution function (LDF) <lb/>The amplitude (= electric field strength) of this one-dimensional lateral distribution is propor-<lb/>tional to the shower energy, because the radio emission in the shower is coherent. Moreover, <lb/>the shape of the lateral distribution depends mainly on the distance to the shower maximum <lb/>and has two main features: first, a bump caused by Cherenkov-like effects [14, 15, 32, 33], <lb/>the existence, size and position of which depend on the distance to the shower maximum; <lb/>second, an exponential tail [1, 34], the slope of which depends on the distance to the shower <lb/>maximum, too. This means that even a one-dimensional LDF should contain at least three <lb/>free parameters: one for the energy scale, and two for the shape, namely the width of the <lb/>bump, and the slope of the exponential fall-off. For this purpose we use the following lateral <lb/>distribution function: <lb/>E cor (r) = E r 0 exp a 1 (r − r 0 ) + a 2 (r − r 0 ) 2 , <lb/>(3.2) <lb/>with the amplitude E cor (r) after correction for the azimuthal asymmetry and for the geomag-<lb/>netic angle as function of axis distance r, and the fitted scale parameter E r 0 , which is the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">2 Although the size of the asymmetry εasym depends on zenith angle and distance to the shower axis [12], <lb/>simulation studies for Tunka-Rex have shown that parameterizing these dependences of εasym instead of <lb/>using a constant value does not describe the lateral distribution better. Probably this is because Tunka-Rex <lb/>measurements mostly fall in a limited zenith range. Moreover, εasym shows little variation in the distance <lb/>range of 100-200 m used for energy and Xmax reconstruction. <lb/></note>

			<page>-8 -<lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">JCAP01(2016)052 <lb/></note>

			<body>LDF fit <lb/>Energy estimator: <lb/>amplitude at 120 m <lb/>X max estimator: <lb/>slope at 180 m <lb/>-1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>150 <lb/>250 <lb/>350 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>x (km) <lb/>distance to shower axis (m) <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>-1 <lb/>y (km) <lb/>1200 <lb/>1000 <lb/>800 <lb/>600 <lb/>400 <lb/>200 <lb/>0 <lb/>corrected amplitude (µV/m) <lb/>Figure 6. Example event. Left: footprint. Large crosses are triggered stations, and blue crosses are <lb/>those stations with signal above the signal-to-noise threshold. The small dark-gray cross is a station <lb/>without measurement for this event. The star and the line indicate the reconstructed shower core <lb/>and direction. Right: lateral distribution before (open circles) and after (filled circles) asymmetry <lb/>correction, but with correction for the geomagnetic angle in both cases. The LDF is fitted to the <lb/>corrected points. The light gray point is a station with signal below the signal-to-noise threshold. <lb/>amplitude at the axis distance r 0 . The shape parameter a 1 determines the slope of the expo-<lb/>nential fall-off, and the shape parameter a 2 is related to the width of the Cherenkov bump. <lb/>The distance parameter r 0 is a purely technical parameter. Using a minimizing chi-square <lb/>fit, the shape of the function does not depend on the choice of r 0 , i.e, for different r 0 the <lb/>resulting function is exactly the same, but just described with a different set of values for the <lb/>parameters E r 0 , a 1 and a 2 . However, the choice of r 0 affects the uncertainties and correlations <lb/>of the fit parameters, which is why a specific choice of r 0 can simplify the reconstruction of <lb/>E pr , X max , and their statistical uncertainties. We set this distance parameter r 0 to 120 m <lb/>for the reconstruction of the primary energy E pr based on E 120 , and to 180 m for the X max <lb/>reconstruction based on a 1 , as these turned out to be the optimum values in the CoREAS <lb/>simulation study. <lb/>In the CoREAS simulations made for Tunka-Rex we observe that the scale parameter <lb/>E 120 is strongly correlated with the primary energy E pr . The shape parameter a 1 , i.e., the <lb/>slope at 180 m axis distance is strongly correlated with the distance to the shower maximum. <lb/>The second shape parameter a 2 is correlated with a 1 , and weakly depends on energy and <lb/>zenith angle. Thus, fitting a 2 as a free parameter would complicate the reconstruction of X max <lb/>significantly. For this reason we decided to perform the fit with only two free parameters, <lb/>and to fix the parameter a 2 using a parametrization depending on zenith angle θ and the <lb/>primary energy E pr (details in appendix A). After fixing a 2 , the LDF is fit to the data <lb/>points. E 120 carries the whole sensitivity to the primary energy E pr , and the remaining free <lb/>shape parameter a 1 carries the whole X max sensitivity of the LDF. Furthermore, reducing <lb/>the number of free parameters in the LDF from three to two brings the additional advantage <lb/>that we can use events with only three antenna stations above threshold (about half of the <lb/>Tunka-Rex events in the present analysis). <lb/>3.3 Primary energy E pr , and atmospheric depth of shower maximum X max <lb/>Energy E pr and X max are determined using the equations presented in reference [8]. While <lb/>for X max we use exactly the same equation as in the reference, i.e., the same values for all <lb/></body>

			<page>-9 -<lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">JCAP01(2016)052 <lb/></note>

			<body>0.1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Tunka-133 <lb/>(air-Cherenkov): energy (EeV) <lb/>Tunka-Rex (radio): energy (EeV) <lb/>Correlation with uncert. <lb/>1:1 correlation (x = y) <lb/>Oct. 2012 -Apr. 2014 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>Number of events <lb/>-1 -0.75 -0.5 -0.25 0 <lb/>0.25 0.5 0.75 1 <lb/>Fitted Gauss: <lb/>µ = -0.03 ± 0.02 <lb/>σ = 0.17 ± 0.02 <lb/>Relative energy deviation: 2 . ETunka-Rex -ETunka-133 <lb/>ETunka-Rex + ETunka-133 <lb/>Oct. 2012 -<lb/>Apr. 2014 <lb/>Figure 7. Correlation and relative deviation (= difference divided by average) of the shower energy <lb/>reconstructed with Tunka-Rex radio and Tunka-133 air-Cherenkov measurements. <lb/>in the equation, for E pr we use a simplification. The simplification is to assume <lb/>that the energy is exactly proportional to the amplitude, as expected for 100 % coherent <lb/>emission. This means that the exponent b = 0.93 of reference [8] is set to 1 instead and, <lb/>thus, is not present in the equation used here. The reason for applying this simplification is <lb/>that with the present statistics and quality of the measured data, we have found no evidence <lb/>for b = 1. Moreover, there is no significant difference in the resulting energy precision <lb/>whether b is set to 0.93 or 1. Consequently, at the moment we lack experimental justification <lb/>for introducing b as an additional parameter and decided for the simpler solution. The <lb/>simplification requires a different proportionality coefficient κ L , which has been determined <lb/>with the same set of CoREAS simulations. Summarizing, we use the following equations for <lb/>the reconstruction of E pr and X max with Tunka-Rex: <lb/>E pr = κ L • E 120 , <lb/>(3.3) <lb/>X max = X det / cos θ − (A + B log(a 1 + b)) , <lb/>(3.4) <lb/>where X det = 955 g/cm 2 is the atmospheric depth of the detector (typical value for the site <lb/>used in the simulations), and the parameters are determined with CoREAS simulations: <lb/>κ L = 884 EeV/(V/m), A = −1864 g/cm 2 , B = −566 g/cm 2 , a 1 given in units of meters, and <lb/>b = 0.005. As explained above, the technical parameter of the LDF, r 0 , is set to 120 m for <lb/>the determination of the amplitude at 120 m, E 120 , and to 180 m for the determination of the <lb/>slope parameter a 1 . <lb/>The energy and X max reconstructions based on simulations were already presented in <lb/>reference [8]. The following section presents the experimental result of Tunka-Rex measure-<lb/>ments and the comparison to the Tunka-133 air-Cherenkov measurements. <lb/>4 Results <lb/>There is a clear correlation between the energy reconstructed from the radio amplitude mea-<lb/>sured by Tunka-Rex and the energy reconstructed from the air-Cherenkov light measured <lb/></body>

			<page>-10 -<lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">JCAP01(2016)052 <lb/></note>

			<body>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/>1000 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/>1000 <lb/>Tunka-133: <lb/>distance to shower maximum (g/cm²) <lb/>Tunka-Rex: distance to shower maximum (g/cm²) <lb/>Correlation with uncert. <lb/>1:1 correlation (x = y) <lb/>Oct. 2012 -Apr. 2014 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/>16 <lb/>Number of events <lb/>-150 -100 <lb/>-50 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>Fitted Gauss: <lb/>µ = -2 ± 7 <lb/>σ = 47 ± 5 <lb/>Difference in Xmax (g/cm²): Tunka-Rex -Tunka-133 <lb/>Oct. 2012 -<lb/>Apr. 2014 <lb/>Figure 8. Correlation and difference of the distance to X max (atmospheric depth between the shower <lb/>maximum and the shower core) as reconstructed with Tunka-Rex radio and Tunka-133 air-Cherenkov <lb/>measurements. <lb/>by Tunka-133 (figure 7). This indicates that the energy reconstruction works reliably with <lb/>the presented method. When combining both seasons, the average deviation between the <lb/>Tunka-Rex and Tunka-133 energy values is (17 ± 2) %, which is only slightly larger than the <lb/>15 % energy resolution reported by Tunka-133 [19]. <lb/>Also for the position of the shower maximum there is a clear correlation between the <lb/>radio and air-Cherenkov reconstructions (figure 8). Due to the stricter quality cuts the event <lb/>statistics is lower than for the energy correlation. Still, the correlation is significant. This <lb/>again indicates that also the reconstruction of X max works reliably for the selected, high-<lb/>quality radio events. Because of the lower statistics, the X max reconstruction precision of <lb/>Tunka-Rex cannot be estimated very accurately. The standard deviation of the X max differ-<lb/>ence between both detectors is (47±5) g/cm 2 , which reflects the combination of the unknown <lb/>Tunka-Rex uncertainty and the Tunka-133 uncertainty of 28 g/cm 2 [19]. This corresponds <lb/>to a radio-only precision of better than 40 g/cm 2 , when assuming that the resolutions of <lb/>Tunka-133 and Tunka-Rex add in squares to the total deviation. <lb/>For both the energy and X max reconstructions the observed correlation is statistically <lb/>compatible with a 1:1 correlation of Tunka-133 and Tunka-Rex: the means of the Gaussians <lb/>fitted in figures 7 and 8 are compatible with 0, where 0 corresponds to no bias (= systematic <lb/>scale offset). This means that the energy and X max scales of both detectors agree on an <lb/>absolute level within the measurement uncertainty. This is remarkable, since the Tunka-<lb/>Rex scale is defined by CoREAS simulations and has not been tuned against Tunka-133. <lb/>With already consistent scales there is no need for a true cross-calibration, i.e., an explicit <lb/>calibration of both detectors against each other. <lb/>5 Discussion <lb/>5.1 Validity of the results <lb/>The present analysis is the first event-by-event comparison of radio and air-Cherenkov mea-<lb/>surements of the same air showers. Since both detection methods are sensitive to the energy <lb/></body>

			<page>-11 -<lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">JCAP01(2016)052 <lb/></note>

			<body>and the position of the maximum of the electromagnetic shower component, a strong correla-<lb/>tion is expected between radio and air-Cherenkov observables. This is especially noteworthy <lb/>since the Tunka-Rex reconstruction is based on simulations and not tuned against the Tunka-<lb/>133 measurements we compared with. Only details of the reconstruction method have been <lb/>decided after looking at the data of the first season, e.g., the filter used to remove narrow-<lb/>band interferences or the exact quality cuts. Neither of these small decisions made the X max <lb/>and energy correlations appear or vanish. <lb/>As additional cross-check of the validity of the results, we decided to blind the energy <lb/>and X max reconstruction of Tunka-133 for the second season. These values were revealed <lb/>to us only after we froze the reconstruction method, including digital filters and quality <lb/>cuts, and after we decided to use the simplified equation (3.4) for energy reconstruction. In <lb/>appendix B the results of both seasons are compared, and found to be compatible within <lb/>statistical uncertainties. Thus, we conclude that our results are not corrupted by any kind <lb/>of implicit tuning on the data set of the first year. Moreover, the quality cuts are general <lb/>enough to cover the slightly different array configurations in both seasons, i.e., the missing <lb/>antennas in the first season do not have significant impact on any of the present results. <lb/>Potential biases not excluded by the cross-check concern possible special events. For <lb/>example, events with their shower maximum very close to the detector will have a very steep <lb/>lateral distribution and a small footprint. Thus, they will likely not be detected or will <lb/>be rejected by the quality cuts. Still, since Tunka-133 is fully efficient and has a reliable <lb/>reconstruction in the full zenith and energy range used in this study, the non-detection <lb/>of certain events is not assumed to cause any significant bias in the observed correlations. <lb/>Furthermore, at high energies less than a third of the events are rejected (cf. figure 5), and <lb/>this due to technical reasons (missing antenna stations) or due to small geomagnetic angles <lb/>leading to small radio amplitudes. Thus, the potential problem of a bias introduced by the <lb/>rejection of any kind of special event can concern only a small fraction of events. Nevertheless, <lb/>this has to be studied in more detail when larger statistics will be available. <lb/>Consequently, the cross-check of both seasons cannot totally exclude all imaginable <lb/>systematic biases implicit in the experimental setup or in the simulations simulations, but it <lb/>definitely confirms that the observed correlations are real. <lb/>5.2 Precision and accuracy <lb/>The spread of the deviation between the Tunka-Rex and Tunka-133 reconstruction values for <lb/>the same events can be used to estimate the reconstruction precision of Tunka-Rex. Assuming <lb/>independent Gaussian uncertainties of both reconstructions, the standard deviation of the <lb/>difference or ratio between Tunka-Rex and Tunka-133 is the quadratic sum of the absolute <lb/>or relative uncertainties, receptively. If Tunka-Rex would feature the same precision as <lb/>Tunka-133, thus, this standard deviation should be a factor of <lb/>√ <lb/>2 larger than the Tunka-133 <lb/>precision alone, i.e.: <lb/>√ <lb/>2•15 % = 21 % for the energy, which is slightly larger than the observed <lb/>standard deviation of (17 ± 2) %. Consequently, the energy precision of Tunka-Rex seems to <lb/>be at least equal to that of Tunka-133. <lb/>For X max , we would expect a standard deviation of the difference of <lb/>√ <lb/>2 • 28 g/cm 2 = <lb/>40 g/cm 2 if Tunka-Rex had the same precision as Tunka-133 (28 g/cm 2 ), but observe a stan-<lb/>dard deviation of the difference of (47±5) g/cm 2 . The derived Tunka-Rex precision is slightly <lb/>better than 40 g/cm 2 , as expected from CoREAS simulations when including realistic back-<lb/>ground [8]. Since the average spacing of the Tunka-133 photomultipliers is half of the average <lb/>antenna spacing, this result does not necessarily imply that the radio X max precision is in-<lb/></body>

			<page>-12 -<lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">JCAP01(2016)052 <lb/></note>

			<body>trinsically worse than the air-Cherenkov precision. Instead, later studies will show how the <lb/>Tunka-133 and Tunka-Rex resolutions compare for equal detector spacing, and by how much <lb/>the Tunka-Rex precision will improve due to additionally deployed antennas. <lb/>Using CoREAS simulations we searched for systematic uncertainties potentially degrad-<lb/>ing the resolution further, in particular biases of the X max reconstruction over energy or zenith <lb/>angle, but we did not find any significant effect. The finally achievable X max uncertainty of <lb/>the radio technique might become equal to the one of the air-Cherenkov technique, when <lb/>events of even higher quality are used. The spread between the Tunka-133 and Tunka-Rex <lb/>X max values approximately corresponds to the cut placed on the estimator σ(X radio <lb/>max ) for the <lb/>statistical uncertainty of Tunka-Rex. This means that this estimator is reliable and can be <lb/>used to set stronger quality cuts when higher statistics are available. <lb/>In addition to the precision also the total accuracy is of importance. This is dominated <lb/>by the 18 % scale uncertainty of the amplitude calibration [17], but at least three further <lb/>systematic scale uncertainties have to be considered: <lb/>First, if the fraction of the total primary energy going in the electromagnetic shower <lb/>component was simulated wrongly in CORSIKA, the energy scale would be wrong by roughly <lb/>the same value. However, the electromagnetic shower component is relatively well under-<lb/>stood, and as estimated by other experiments [35], this uncertainty on the &apos;invisible&apos; energy <lb/>is only a few percent. Moreover, we assume that the CoREAS radio extension of CORSIKA <lb/>simulates the absolute radio amplitude emitted by the electromagnetic shower component <lb/>correctly, i.e., with errors which are small against the calibration scale uncertainty of 18 %, <lb/>which is supported by recent experimental tests [17, 36]. Still, the fraction of energy go-<lb/>ing in the electromagnetic shower component depends on the mass of the primary particle. <lb/>Thus, the parameters in the method slightly depend on the assumed mass composition of <lb/>the primary particles, in particular also the parameter κ L determining the energy scale. For <lb/>the present analysis, we determined κ L as average of proton and iron simulations with the <lb/>hadronic interaction model QGSJET-II.04 [37]. If we had taken a pure proton or a pure <lb/>iron composition to determine κ L of equation (3.4), the reconstructed energy would be 4 % <lb/>smaller or larger, respectively. <lb/>Second, there is some freedom in the equation used for energy reconstruction. For <lb/>example, if we had used exactly the energy equation of reference [8] instead of equation (3.4), <lb/>then the reconstructed primary energy would be about 10 % lower, although both equations <lb/>have been tuned against the same set of CoREAS simulations. This difference is well within <lb/>the 18 % scale uncertainty of the amplitude calibration, but indicates that a more detailed <lb/>study of the reconstruction method will become necessary once a more accurate calibration <lb/>becomes available. <lb/>Third, using CoREAS simulations we found a systematic bias of the energy reconstruc-<lb/>tion depending on the distance to the shower maximum. The mean effect is smaller than the <lb/>difference between proton-and iron-initiated showers, and thus negligible. However, for very <lb/>close or far distances to the shower maximum ( 350 g/cm 2 or 900 g/cm 2 ) the bias becomes <lb/>larger than 10 %, and will have to be corrected for such rare events. Consequently, all known <lb/>systematic uncertainties are small compared to the scale uncertainty of the amplitude calibra-<lb/>tion of 18 %. Thus, the total accuracy of the Tunka-Rex energy scale is approximately 20 %. <lb/>The Tunka-Rex energy scale defined by CoREAS simulations agrees within the un-<lb/>certainties to the Tunka-133 scale. This means that the measurements of Tunka-Rex and <lb/>Tunka-133 are not only correlated, but in addition agree on an absolute level, which is an-<lb/>other confirmation, that CoREAS seems to predict the radio signal correctly. <lb/></body>

			<page>-13 -<lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">JCAP01(2016)052 <lb/></note>

			<body>5.3 Comparison with other experiments <lb/>The 15 % energy precision of Tunka-Rex is at least as good as that of other radio arrays, <lb/>like AERA [38], LOPES [3], and CODALEMA [39], which all reported energy precisions <lb/>around 20 %. The Tunka-Rex scale uncertainty of 20 % roughly corresponds to that of <lb/>AERA [38] and LOPES [36], which compared the radio measurements to air-fluorescence <lb/>and particle measurements on ground. LOFAR as well features an absolute calibration of <lb/>the radio amplitude with similar accuracy [40], but experimental checks of the energy ac-<lb/>curacy are limited by the poor energy resolution of the LORA particle detector array [5]. <lb/>For X max reconstruction, the resolution of LOPES has been significantly worse, using a sim-<lb/>pler method in a more radio-loud environment than Tunka-Rex. The much denser array <lb/>LOFAR is located in more radio-quiet environment similar to the situation of Tunka-Rex. <lb/>Its X max reconstruction is also based on CoREAS simulations using two different methods. <lb/>With an X max reconstruction based on a fitted LDF (like in our approach), the precision <lb/>of X max at LOFAR is only slightly better than our resolution [5]. However, with a more <lb/>computing-intensive method using many simulations for each individual event [4], the pre-<lb/>cision by LOFAR is at least twice as good as ours. This indicates that in addition to the <lb/>planned deployment of additional antennas, also further improvements in the reconstruction <lb/>methods could increase the X max resolution of Tunka-Rex. <lb/>The most important scientific value of the present analysis is the experimental com-<lb/>parision of radio measurements against another, established technique. For the first time, <lb/>energy and X max reconstructions based on absolutely-calibrated radio measurements have <lb/>been compared to air-Cherenkov measurements. While the principle sensitivity of the radio <lb/>signal on the longitudinal shower development was already demonstrated experimentally by <lb/>comparing LOPES lateral distributions to measurements of the KASCADE muon-tracking <lb/>detector [2], KASCADE did not feature direct X max measurements. Thus, with the present <lb/>comparison of Tunka-Rex and Tunka-133, for the first time the radio reconstruction of X max <lb/>is directly cross-checked with an independent X max measurement. This also gives more con-<lb/>fidence in the results of other radio arrays whose reconstruction procedures are developed <lb/>with the same CORSIKA + CoREAS Monte Carlo codes. <lb/>6 Outlook <lb/>The presently achieved accuracy for energy and X max reconstruction by Tunka-Rex is not yet <lb/>at its principle limits. In particular for the X max reconstruction, there is room for improve-<lb/>ment. As shown by LOFAR [4], the precision can be as good as 20 g/cm 2 , when using a denser <lb/>radio array and a simulation-driven method. Thus, we plan to deploy additional antennas <lb/>and to further improve the reconstruction method. With an increased antenna density, the <lb/>average event will contain more antenna stations with signal, which allows fitting of lateral <lb/>distributions with more free parameters. For example, the weak energy and X max sensitivity <lb/>of the LDF parameter a 2 could be exploited when more antenna stations contribute to the fit. <lb/>Compared to this study the antenna density will be tripled. At each of the 19 Tunka clus-<lb/>ters in the inner area, already now a second antenna station is deployed, and a third one will <lb/>be deployed in summer 2016. This enables an experimental test how the antenna density and <lb/>the core resolution affect the X max resolution. Moreover, additional methods for X max recon-<lb/>struction based on other quantities of the radio signal can be used to improve the total accu-<lb/>racy. The shape of the wavefront [41] can be reconstructed by arrival time measurements, and <lb/></body>

			<page>-14 -<lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">JCAP01(2016)052 <lb/></note>

			<body>the slope of the frequency spectrum [42] by sampling the pulse shape. Future studies will show <lb/>by how much these methods can increase the total X max accuracy under practical conditions. <lb/>The statistics of Tunka-Rex will be dramatically increased by joint measurements with <lb/>the newly deployed particle-detector array Tunka-Grande [43], which provides a day-time <lb/>trigger for Tunka-Rex. Tunka-Grande consists of 19 stations, one at each inner cluster, <lb/>where each station features scintillator detectors on ground and under ground, for mea-<lb/>surement of secondary air-shower electrons and muons, respectively. While unimportant <lb/>for the present analysis focused on the feasibility of the reconstruction methods, for recon-<lb/>struction of the cosmic-ray composition possible systematic uncertainties like selection biases <lb/>are relevant. Using the additional statistics and independent measurements provided by <lb/>Tunka-Grande such systematic uncertainties can be checked experimentally. Moreover, the <lb/>additional muon measurements can enhance the total accuracy for the mass composition, <lb/>since the electron-muon ratio provides complementary mass information to X max [44]. In <lb/>addition, the Tunka-Grande measurement accuracy will be enhanced by a cross-calibration <lb/>on hybrid measurements with Tunka-Rex. <lb/>Finally, the absolute energy measurement of air-showers with a radio array opens <lb/>prospects to cross-calibrate the energy scales of different air-shower experiments via radio <lb/>measurements. This aspect is worth to be investigated more deeply, in particular since an-<lb/>tenna arrays can be a very economic add-ons to existing detectors as shown by Tunka-Rex. <lb/>7 Conclusion <lb/>We have compared energy and X max reconstructed from Tunka-Rex and Tunka-133 mea-<lb/>surements of the same air showers in the energy range E pr <lb/>10 17 eV. The reconstruction <lb/>methods have been developed and tuned using simulations with CORSIKA and its radio ex-<lb/>tension CoREAS. For both parameters we find a strong correlation between Tunka-Rex and <lb/>Tunka-133 consistently in two seasons of data taking. This confirms experimentally that the <lb/>radio measurements are indeed sensitive to energy and shower maximum. For X max this is <lb/>the first direct confirmation based on a cross-check with a different, established experimental <lb/>technique, namely air-Cherenkov measurements. <lb/>The Tunka-Rex energy precision seems to be at least as good as the published Tunka-133 <lb/>resolution of 15 %. The total scale uncertainty of Tunka-Rex is dominated by the uncertainty <lb/>of the amplitude calibration, and in total is in the order of 20 %. This is comparable to <lb/>the scale uncertainty of particle detector arrays, like KASCADE-Grande [45]. Since the <lb/>calibration uncertainty dominates the total scale uncertainty of Tunka-Rex, any improvement <lb/>in the calibration accuracy will directly propagate to the energy-scale accuracy. Consequently, <lb/>further efforts on the calibration will be necessary to increase the accuracy to the same level <lb/>as the currently leading fluorescence and air-Cherenkov techniques. At the Pierre Auger <lb/>Observatory, the scale accuracy of fluorescence measurements is 14 % [35]. This now is in <lb/>reasonable reach for future radio measurements, which unlike fluorescence measurements are <lb/>available around-the-clock. Hence, radio measurements can be used to determine the absolute <lb/>energy scale of air-shower measurements. <lb/>The X max precision of Tunka-Rex is roughly 40 g/cm 2 , and can be slightly increased by <lb/>setting stricter quality cuts at the cost of statistics. This resolution is sufficient to statistically <lb/>distinguish light from heavy primary particles. The resolution is worse than the one currently <lb/>achieved by non-imaging air-Cherenkov measurements (28 g/cm 2 for Tunka-133 [19]) and by <lb/>air-fluorescence measurements (20 g/cm 2 for the Pierre Auger Observatory [35]). Neverthe-<lb/></body>

			<page>-15 -<lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">JCAP01(2016)052 <lb/></note>

			<body>less, the resolution of Tunka-Rex is not yet at its limit and can likely be increased by further <lb/>improvements of the reconstruction method, and by deploying additional antennas. <lb/>For astrophysical applications the total accuracy for the reconstruction of the mass <lb/>composition as a function of energy counts, e.g., to better study the transition from Galactic <lb/>to yet-unknown extra-galactic cosmic-ray sources assumed in the energy range of Tunka-<lb/>Rex [46]. Tunka-Rex will provide additional statistics exactly in the energy range where <lb/>current Tunka-133 analyses are limited by statistics. Moreover, hybrid measurements of <lb/>air-showers by Tunka-Rex and Tunka-Grande started in autumn 2015. These hybrid mea-<lb/>surements can be used to enhance the total accuracy for the mass composition by combining <lb/>radio and muon measurements. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>Tunka-Rex has been funded by the German Helmholtz association and the Russian Foun-<lb/>dation for Basic Research (grant HRJRG-303). Moreover, this work was supported by <lb/>the Helmholtz Alliance for Astroparticle Physics (HAP), and by the Russian grant RSF <lb/>15-12-20022. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">A Parametrization of LDF parameter a 2 <lb/>In the Gaussian lateral distribution function (LDF, equation (3.2)), the parameter a 2 defin-<lb/>ing the bump has been set by the following parameterization determined with CoREAS <lb/>simulations made for the situation of Tunka-Rex [8]: <lb/>a 2 (θ, E pr ) = a 21 (E pr ) − a 22 (E pr ) cos θ , <lb/>(A.1) <lb/>a 21 = 0.19 • 10 −5 1 <lb/>m 2 − 1.63 • 10 −5 <lb/>E pr <lb/>m 2 • EeV <lb/>, <lb/>(A.2) <lb/>a 22 = −3.45 • 10 −5 1 <lb/>m 2 + 2.44 • 10 −5 <lb/>E pr <lb/>m 2 • EeV <lb/>. <lb/>Since the a 2 parameter is a function of the primary energy E pr , the shape of the Gaussian <lb/>LDF used to reconstruct the primary energy depends implicitly on the energy itself. This <lb/>reciprocal dependence on E pr can either be solved by an iterative approach, or by using a <lb/>pre-estimate for E pr . We decided for the latter solution, using the energy estimator based <lb/>on a simpler exponential LDF presented in reference [17], since its precision is only slightly <lb/>worse than than in our more advanced approach here. <lb/>B Comparison of both seasons <lb/>The data set of Tunka-Rex is split in two seasons of about equal size. As additional cross-<lb/>check of the validity of our methods, the Tunka-133 reconstruction of energy and X max had <lb/>been blinded for the second season. Only for the first season the Tunka-133 energy and X max <lb/>values had been known, and were used for occasional cross-checks during the development <lb/>of the Tunka-Rex methods. After we frozen the Tunka-Rex reconstruction methods, we <lb/>predicted the energy and X max for the second season based on the radio measurements. <lb/>Only afterwards, Tunka-133 unblinded their reconstruction of the second season to us. <lb/>The plots in this appendix show the comparison of the Tunka-Rex and Tunka-133 energy <lb/>and X max reconstructions (figures 9 and 10) separately for both seasons. The results of both <lb/></div>

			<page>-16 -<lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">JCAP01(2016)052 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">0.1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Tunka-133 <lb/>(air-Cherenkov): energy (EeV) <lb/>Tunka-Rex (radio): energy (EeV) <lb/>first season <lb/>Correlation with uncert. <lb/>1:1 correlation (x = y) <lb/>0.1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Tunka-133 <lb/>(air-Cherenkov): energy (EeV) <lb/>Tunka-Rex (radio): energy (EeV) <lb/>second season <lb/>Correlation with uncert. <lb/>1:1 correlation (x = y) <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>-1 -0.75 -0.5 -0.25 0 <lb/>0.25 0.5 0.75 1 <lb/>Number of events <lb/>Fitted Gauss: <lb/>µ = -0.03 ± 0.03 <lb/>σ = 0.19 ± 0.03 <lb/>first season <lb/>Relative energy deviation: 2 . ETunka-Rex -ETunka-133 <lb/>ETunka-Rex + ETunka-133 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>-1 -0.75 -0.5 -0.25 0 <lb/>0.25 0.5 0.75 1 <lb/>Number of events <lb/>Fitted Gauss: <lb/>µ = -0.02 ± 0.02 <lb/>σ = 0.18 ± 0.03 <lb/>second season <lb/>Relative energy deviation: 2 . ETunka-Rex -ETunka-133 <lb/>ETunka-Rex + ETunka-133 <lb/>Figure 9. Comparison of the first and second season: reconstructed energy (cf. figure 7). <lb/>seasons are consistent within statistical uncertainties. The quality cut on events inside of the <lb/>inner area (r &lt; 500 m, dashed circle in figure 1) was discovered a posteriori by us, i.e., after <lb/>we had frozen the reconstruction methods for the unblinding procedure. Thus, in figure 10 <lb/>five additional events are present (two in the first season, three in the second season), which <lb/>are outside of the inner area and slightly degrade the X max resolution. <lb/>As supplementary material we will upload the list of the events used for the present <lb/>analysis. This list contains the reconstructed energy and X max values of the events. However, <lb/>the values should not be used for reconstruction of the cosmic-ray energy spectrum or the <lb/>mass composition. While unimportant for the present study comparing the Tunka-Rex to the <lb/>Tunka-133 reconstruction, for such analyses selection biases have to be taken into account, <lb/>which cannot be derived from the event list alone. <lb/>The original event lists for the first &apos;tuning&apos; and second &apos;prediction&apos; seasons, as <lb/></div>

			<page>-17 -<lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">JCAP01(2016)052<lb/></note> 

			<div type="annex">200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/>1000 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/>1000 <lb/>Tunka-133: <lb/>distance to shower maximum (g/cm²) <lb/>Tunka-Rex: distance to shower maximum (g/cm²) <lb/>Correlation with uncert. <lb/>1:1 correlation (x = y) <lb/>first season <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/>1000 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/>1000 <lb/>Tunka-133: <lb/>distance to shower maximum (g/cm²) <lb/>Tunka-Rex: distance to shower maximum (g/cm²) <lb/>Correlation with uncert. <lb/>1:1 correlation (x = y) <lb/>second season <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/>-150 -100 <lb/>-50 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>Fitted Gauss: <lb/>µ = 15 ± 10 <lb/>σ = 51 ± 7 <lb/>first season <lb/>Number of events <lb/>Difference in Xmax (g/cm²): Tunka-Rex -Tunka-133 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/>-150 -100 <lb/>-50 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>Number of events <lb/>Difference in Xmax (g/cm²): Tunka-Rex -Tunka-133 <lb/>Fitted Gauss: <lb/>µ = -2 ± 13 <lb/>σ = 59 ± 9 <lb/>second season <lb/>Figure 10. Comparison of the first and second season: distance to shower maximum (cf. figure 8). <lb/>created after freezing the reconstruction methods, but before unblinding, are available at: <lb/>http://www.ikp.kit.edu/tunka-rex/ <lb/>They can be decrypted using the following Linux command: <lb/>openssl aes-256-cbc -d -in encryptedFile -out decryptedFile <lb/>The passwords are &apos;TunkaRex1 H9AoxFywAt&apos; for the tuning season, <lb/>and <lb/>&apos;TunkaRex2 z3DumFNfsq&apos; for the prediction season. All these events are also con-<lb/>tained in the above-mentioned list submitted as supplementary material. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] H.R. Allan, Radio Emission From Extensive Air Showers, Pr. Elem. Part. Cosmic Ray Phys. <lb/>10 (1971) 171. <lb/>[2] LOPES collaboration, W.D. Apel et al., Experimental evidence for the sensitivity of the <lb/>air-shower radio signal to the longitudinal shower development, Phys. Rev. D 85 (2012) 071101 <lb/>[arXiv:1203.3971] [INSPIRE]. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>-18 -<lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">JCAP01(2016)052 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[3] LOPES collaboration, W.D. Apel et al., Reconstruction of the energy and depth of maximum <lb/>of cosmic-ray air-showers from LOPES radio measurements, Phys. Rev. D 90 (2014) 062001 <lb/>[arXiv:1408.2346] [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[4] LOFAR collaboration, S. Buitink et al., Method for high precision reconstruction of air shower <lb/>X max using two-dimensional radio intensity profiles, Phys. Rev. D 90 (2014) 082003 <lb/>[arXiv:1408.7001] [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[5] LOFAR collaboration, A. Nelles et al., The radio emission pattern of air showers as measured <lb/>with LOFAR -a tool for the reconstruction of the energy and the shower maximum, JCAP 05 <lb/>(2015) 018 [arXiv:1411.7868] [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[6] T. Huege, R. Ulrich and R. Engel, Dependence of geosynchrotron radio emission on the energy <lb/>and depth of maximum of cosmic ray showers, Astropart. Phys. 30 (2008) 96 <lb/>[arXiv:0806.1161] [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[7] K.D. de Vries, A.M. van den Berg, O. Scholten and K. Werner, The Lateral Distribution <lb/>Function of Coherent Radio Emission from Extensive Air Showers: Determining the Chemical <lb/>Composition of Cosmic Rays, Astropart. Phys. 34 (2010) 267 [arXiv:1008.3308] [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[8] D. Kostunin, P.A. Bezyazeekov, R. Hiller, F.G. Schröder, V. Lenok and E. Levinson, <lb/>Reconstruction of air-shower parameters for large-scale radio detectors using the lateral <lb/>distribution, Astropart. Phys. 74 (2016) 79 [arXiv:1504.05083] [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[9] F. D. Kahn and I. Lerche, Radiation from cosmic ray air showers, in proceedings of the Royal <lb/>Society of London. Series A, Mathematical and Physical Sciences 289 (1966) 206. <lb/>[10] G.A. Askar&apos;yan, Excess negative charge of an electron-photon shower and its coherent radio <lb/>emission, Sov. Phys. JETP 14 (1962) 441 [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[11] Pierre Auger collaboration, A. Aab et al., Probing the radio emission from air showers with <lb/>polarization measurements, Phys. Rev. D 89 (2014) 052002 [arXiv:1402.3677] [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[12] LOFAR collaboration, P. Schellart et al., Polarized radio emission from extensive air showers <lb/>measured with LOFAR, J. Cosmol. Astropart. Phys. 10 (2014) 014. <lb/>[13] CODALEMA collaboration, A. Bellétoile, R. Dallier, A. Lecacheux, V. Marin, L. Martin, <lb/>B. Revenu et al., Evidence for the charge-excess contribution in air shower radio emission <lb/>observed by the CODALEMA experiment, Astropart. Phys. 69 (2015) 50 [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[14] H.R. Allan, The Lateral Distribution of the Radio Emission and its Dependence on the <lb/>Longitudinal Structure of the Air Shower, in proceedings of the 12th ICRC, Hobart, Tasmania, <lb/>Australia 3 (1971) 1108. <lb/>[15] J.H. Hough, Calculations on the radio emission resulting from geomagnetic charge separation <lb/>in an extensive air shower, J. Phys. A: Math. Nucl. Gen. 6 (1973) 892. <lb/>[16] K.D. de Vries, A.M. van den Berg, O. Scholten and K. Werner, Coherent Cherenkov Radiation <lb/>from Cosmic-Ray-Induced Air Showers, Phys. Rev. Lett. 107 (2011) 061101 [arXiv:1107.0665] <lb/>[INSPIRE]. <lb/>[17] Tunka-Rex collaboration, P.A. Bezyazeekov et al., Measurement of cosmic-ray air showers <lb/>with the Tunka Radio Extension (Tunka-Rex), Nucl. Instrum. Meth. A 802 (2015) 89 <lb/>[INSPIRE]. <lb/>[18] Tunka-133 collaboration, V.V. Prosin et al., Primary CR energy spectrum and mass <lb/>composition by the data of Tunka-133 array, EPJ Web of Conferences 99 (2015) 04002. <lb/>[19] Tunka-133 collaboration, V.V. Prosin et al., Tunka-133: Results of 3 year operation, Nucl. <lb/>Instrum. Meth. A 756 (2014) 94 [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[20] T. Huege, M. Ludwig and C.W. James, Simulating radio emission from air showers with <lb/>CoREAS, AIP Conf. Proc. 1535 (2013) 128 [arXiv:1301.2132] [INSPIRE]. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>-19 -<lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">JCAP01(2016)052 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[21] D. Heck, J. Knapp, J.N. Capdevielle, et al., CORSIKA: A Monte Carlo Code to Simulate <lb/>Extensive Air Showers, FZKA-6019, Forschungszentrum Karlsruhe GmbH, Karlsruhe Germany <lb/>(1998). <lb/>[22] N.N. Kalmykov, A.A. Konstantinov and O.V. Vedeneev, Mass Composition of 10 17 to 10 18 eV <lb/>Primary Cosmic Rays According to Data on the Lateral Distribution of Radio Emission from <lb/>Extensive Air Showers, Phys. Atom. Nucl. 75 (2012) 1513. <lb/>[23] T. Huege, Theory and simulations of air shower radio emission, AIP Conf. Proc. 1535 (2013) <lb/>121 [arXiv:1301.2135] [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[24] LOFAR collaboration, P. Schellart et al., Detecting cosmic rays with the LOFAR radio <lb/>telescope, Astron. Astrophys. 560 (2013) A98 [arXiv:1311.1399] [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[25] Tunka-Rex collaboration, D. Kostunin et al., The Tunka Radio Extension: reconstruction of <lb/>energy and shower maximum of the first year data, PoS(ICRC2015)285. <lb/>[26] Pierre Auger collaboration, P. Abreu et al., Advanced functionality for radio analysis in the <lb/>Offline software framework of the Pierre Auger Observatory, Nucl. Instrum. Meth. A 635 <lb/>(2011) 92 [arXiv:1101.4473] [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[27] LOPES collaboration, F.G. Schröder et al., On noise treatment in radio measurements of <lb/>cosmic ray air showers, Nucl. Instrum. Meth. A 662 (2012) S238 [arXiv:1009.3444] <lb/>[INSPIRE]. <lb/>[28] H.R. Allan, R.W. Clay, and J.K. Jones, Frequency Spectrum of Air Shower Radio Pulses 225 <lb/>(1970) 253. <lb/>[29] LOPES collaboration, H. Falcke et al., Detection and imaging of atmospheric radio flashes <lb/>from cosmic ray air showers, Nature 435 (2005) 313 [astro-ph/0505383] [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[30] CODALEMA collaboration, D. Ardouin et al., Geomagnetic origin of the radio emission from <lb/>cosmic ray induced air showers observed by CODALEMA, Astropart. Phys. 31 (2009) 192 <lb/>[arXiv:0901.4502] [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[31] Pierre Auger collaboration, C. Glaser, Energy Estimation for Cosmic Rays Measured with <lb/>the Auger Engineering Radio Array, AIP Conf. Proc. 1535 (2013) 68. <lb/>[32] K. Werner, K.D. de Vries and O. Scholten, A Realistic Treatment of Geomagnetic Cherenkov <lb/>Radiation from Cosmic Ray Air Showers, Astropart. Phys. 37 (2012) 5 [arXiv:1201.4471] <lb/>[INSPIRE]. <lb/>[33] LOFAR collaboration, A. Nelles et al., Measuring a Cherenkov ring in the radio emission from <lb/>air showers at 110-190 MHz with LOFAR, Astropart. Phys. 65 (2014) 11 [arXiv:1411.6865] <lb/>[INSPIRE]. <lb/>[34] LOPES collaboration, W.D. Apel et al., Lateral Distribution of the Radio Signal in Extensive <lb/>Air Showers Measured with LOPES, Astropart. Phys. 32 (2010) 294 [arXiv:0910.4866] <lb/>[INSPIRE]. <lb/>[35] Pierre Auger collaboration, A. Aab et al., The Pierre Auger Cosmic Ray Observatory, Nucl. <lb/>Instrum. Meth. A 798 (2015) 172 [arXiv:1502.01323] [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[36] LOPES collaboration, W.D. Apel et al., Improved absolute calibration of LOPES <lb/>measurements and its impact on the comparison with REAS 3.11 and CoREAS simulations, <lb/>Astropart. Phys. 75 (2016) 72 [arXiv:1507.07389] [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[37] S. Ostapchenko, QGSJET-II: Results for extensive air showers, Nucl. Phys. Proc. Suppl. 151 <lb/>(2006) 147 [astro-ph/0412591] [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[38] Pierre Auger collaboration, A. Aab et al., Energy Estimation of Cosmic Rays with the <lb/>Engineering Radio Array of the Pierre Auger Observatory, Submitted to: Phys. Rev. D (2015) <lb/>[arXiv:1508.04267] [INSPIRE]. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>-20 -<lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">JCAP01(2016)052 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[39] A. Rebai, P. Lautridou, A. Lecacheux and O. Ravel, Correlations in energy in cosmic ray air <lb/>showers radio-detected by CODALEMA, arXiv:1210.1739 [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[40] LOFAR collaboration, A. Nelles et al., Calibrating the absolute amplitude scale for air showers <lb/>measured at LOFAR, 2015 JINST 10 P11005 [arXiv:1507.08932] [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[41] LOPES collaboration, W.D. Apel et al., The wavefront of the radio signal emitted by cosmic <lb/>ray air showers, JCAP 09 (2014) 025 [arXiv:1404.3283] [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[42] Pierre Auger collaboration, S. Grebe et al., Spectral index analysis of the data from the <lb/>Auger Engineering Radio Array, AIP Conf. Proc. 1535 (2013) 73. <lb/>[43] TAIGA collaboration, N.M. Budnev et al., TAIGA the Tunka Advanced Instrument for cosmic <lb/>ray physics and Gamma Astronomy -present status and perspectives., 2014 JINST 9 C09021 <lb/>[INSPIRE]. <lb/>[44] K.-H. Kampert and M. Unger, Measurements of the Cosmic Ray Composition with Air Shower <lb/>Experiments, Astropart. Phys. 35 (2012) 660 [arXiv:1201.0018] [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[45] KASCADE-Grande collaboration, W.D. Apel et al., The spectrum of high-energy cosmic <lb/>rays measured with KASCADE-Grande, Astropart. Phys. 36 (2012) 183 [INSPIRE]. <lb/>[46] KASCADE-Grande collaboration, W.D. Apel et al., Ankle-like Feature in the Energy <lb/>Spectrum of Light Elements of Cosmic Rays Observed with KASCADE-Grande, Phys. Rev. D <lb/>87 (2013) 081101 [arXiv:1304.7114] [INSPIRE]. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>-21 -</page>


	</text>
</tei>
