<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) <lb/>Preprint 2 December 2015 <lb/>Compiled using MNRAS L A T E X style file v3.0 <lb/> LOFAR MSSS: Detection of a low-frequency radio transient in <lb/>400 hrs of monitoring of the North Celestial Pole <lb/> A. J. Stewart,  1,2  R. P. Fender,  1,2  J. W. Broderick,  1,2,3  T. E. Hassall,  1,2  T. Muñoz-Darias,  4,5,1,2 <lb/> A. Rowlinson,  6,3  J. D. Swinbank,  7,6  T. D. Staley,  1,2  G. J. Molenaar,  6,8  B. Scheers,  9,6 <lb/> T. L. Grobler,  8,10  M. Pietka,  1,2  G. Heald,  3,11  J. P. McKean,  3,11  M. E. Bell,  12,13 <lb/> A. Bonafede,  14  R. P. Breton,  15,2  D. Carbone,  6  Y. Cendes,  6  A. O. Clarke,  15,2  S. Corbel,  16,17 <lb/> F. de Gasperin,  14  J. Eislöffel,  18  H. Falcke,  19,3  C. Ferrari,  20  J.-M. Grießmeier,  21,17 <lb/> M. J. Hardcastle,  22  V. Heesen,  2  J. W. T. Hessels,  3,6  A. Horneffer,  23  M. Iacobelli,  3 <lb/> P. Jonker,  24,19  A. Karastergiou,  1  G. Kokotanekov,  6  V. I. Kondratiev,  3,25  M. Kuniyoshi,  26 <lb/> C. J. Law,  27  J. van Leeuwen,  3,6  S. Markoff,  6  J. C. A. Miller-Jones,  28  D. Mulcahy,  15,2 <lb/> E. Orru,  3  M. Pandey-Pommier,  29  L. Pratley,  30  E. Rol,  31  H. J. A. Röttgering,  32 <lb/> A. M. M. Scaife,  15  A. Shulevski,  11  C. A. Sobey,  3  B. W. Stappers,  15  C. Tasse,  10,33,8 <lb/> A. J. van der Horst,  34  S. van Velzen,  19  R. J. van Weeren,  35  R. A. M. J. Wijers,  6 <lb/> R. Wijnands,  6  M. Wise,  3,6  P. Zarka,  36,17  A. Alexov,  37  J. Anderson,  38  A. Asgekar,  3,39 <lb/> I. M. Avruch,  24,11  M. J. Bentum,  3,40  G. Bernardi,  35  P. Best,  41  F. Breitling,  42 <lb/> M. Brüggen,  14  H. R. Butcher,  43  B. Ciardi,  44  J. E. Conway,  45  A. Corstanje,  19 <lb/> E. de Geus,  3,46  A. Deller,  3  S. Duscha,  3  W. Frieswijk,  3  M. A. Garrett,  3,32 <lb/> A. W. Gunst,  3  M. P. van Haarlem,  3  M. Hoeft,  18  J. Hörandel,  19  E. Juette,  47 <lb/> G. Kuper,  3  M. Loose,  3  P. Maat,  3  R. McFadden,  3  D. McKay-Bukowski,  48,49 <lb/> J. Moldon,  3  H. Munk,  3  M. J. Norden,  3  H. Paas,  50  A. G. Polatidis,  3  D. Schwarz,  51 <lb/> J. Sluman,  3  O. Smirnov,  8,10  M. Steinmetz,  42  S. Thoudam,  19  M. C. Toribio,  3 <lb/> R. Vermeulen,  3  C. Vocks,  42  S. J. Wijnholds,  3  O. Wucknitz  23  and S. Yatawatta  3 <lb/> Affiliations are listed at the end of the paper <lb/> Accepted 2015 November 25. Received 2015 November 24; in original form 2015 July 17 <lb/> ABSTRACT <lb/> We present the results of a four-month campaign searching for low-frequency radio transients <lb/>near the North Celestial Pole with the Low-Frequency Array (LOFAR), as part of the Mul-<lb/>tifrequency Snapshot Sky Survey (MSSS). The data were recorded between 2011 December <lb/>and 2012 April and comprised 2149 11-minute snapshots, each covering 175 deg  2  . We have <lb/>found one convincing candidate astrophysical transient, with a duration of a few minutes and <lb/>a flux density at 60 MHz of 15–25 Jy. The transient does not repeat and has no obvious op-<lb/>tical or high-energy counterpart, as a result of which its nature is unclear. The detection of <lb/>this event implies a transient rate at 60 MHz of 3.9  +14.7 <lb/> −3.7  × 10  −4  day  −1  deg  −2  , and a transient <lb/>surface density of 1.5 × 10  −5  deg  −2  , at a 7.9-Jy limiting flux density and ∼ 10-minute time-<lb/>scale. The campaign data were also searched for transients at a range of other time-scales, <lb/>from 0.5 to 297 min, which allowed us to place a range of limits on transient rates at 60 MHz <lb/>as a function of observation duration. <lb/> Key words: instrumentation: interferometers – techniques: image processing – radio contin-<lb/>uum: general. <lb/> c <lb/> 2015 The Authors <lb/> arXiv:1512.00014v1  [astro-ph.HE] 30 Nov 2015 <lb/></front>

			<page> 2 </page>

			<note place="headnote">Stewart et al. <lb/></note>

			<body> 1 INTRODUCTION <lb/> The variable and transient sky offers a window into the most ex-<lb/>treme events that take place in the Universe. Transient phenomena <lb/>are observed at all wavelengths across a diverse range of objects, <lb/>ranging from optical flashes detected in the atmosphere of Jupiter <lb/>caused by bolides (Hueso et al. 2010), to violent Gamma-Ray <lb/>Bursts (GRBs) at cosmological distances which can outshine their <lb/>host galaxy (Klebesadel et al. 1973; van Paradijs et al. 1997). <lb/>Observations at radio wavelengths provide a robust method to <lb/>probe these events, supplying unique views of kinetic feedback <lb/>and propagation effects in the interstellar medium, which are also <lb/>just as diverse in their associated time-scales. Active Galactic <lb/>Nuclei (AGN; Matthews &amp; Sandage 1963; Smith &amp; Hoffleit 1963) <lb/>are known to vary over time-scales of a month or longer, whereas <lb/>observations of the Crab Pulsar have seen radio bursts with a <lb/>duration of nanoseconds (Hankins et al. 2003). <lb/>Historically, and still to this day, radio observations have been <lb/>used to follow-up transient detections made at other wavelengths. <lb/>Radio facilities generally had a narrow field-of-view (FoV), which <lb/>made them inadequate to perform rapid transient and variability <lb/>studies over a large fraction of the sky. However, blind transient <lb/>surveys have been performed and have produced intriguing results. <lb/>For example, Bower et al. (2007) (also see Frail et al. 2012) <lb/>discovered a single epoch millijansky transient at 4.9 GHz while <lb/>searching 944 epochs of archival Very Large Array (VLA) data <lb/>spanning 22 years, with three other possible marginal events. Sky <lb/>surveys using the Nasu Observatory have also been successful <lb/>in finding a radio transient source, with Niinuma et al. (2007) <lb/>having observed a two epoch event, peaking at 3 Jy at 1.42 GHz. <lb/>Various counterparts were considered at other wavelengths, but <lb/>the origin of the transient remains unknown. Lastly, Bannister <lb/>et al. (2011) surveyed 2775 deg  2  of sky at 843 MHz using the <lb/>Molonglo Observatory Synthesis Telescope (MOST), yielding 15 <lb/>transients at a 5σ level of 14 mJy beam  −1  , 12 of which had not <lb/>been previously identified as transient or variable. <lb/>Surveys at low frequencies ( 330 MHz) have also been <lb/>completed. Lazio et al. (2010) carried out an all-sky transient <lb/>survey using the Long Wavelength Demonstrator Array (LWDA) <lb/>at 73.8 MHz, which detected no transient events to a flux density <lb/>limit of 500 Jy. In addition, Hyman et al. (2002, 2005, 2006, 2009) <lb/>discovered three radio transients during monitoring of the Galactic <lb/>centre at 235 and 330 MHz. These were identified by using archival <lb/>VLA observations along with regular monitoring using the VLA <lb/>and the Giant Metrewave Radio Telescope (GMRT). The transients <lb/>had flux densities in the range of 100 mJy–1 Jy and occurred <lb/>on time-scales ranging from minutes to months. Lastly, Jaeger <lb/>et al. (2012) searched six archival epochs from the VLA at 325 <lb/>MHz centred on the Spitzer-Space-Telescope Wide-Area Infrared <lb/>Extragalactic Survey (SWIRE) Deep Field. In an area of 6.5 deg  2 <lb/> to a 10σ flux limit of 2.1 mJy beam  −1  , one day-scale transient <lb/>event was reported with a peak flux density of 1.7 mJy beam  −1  . <lb/>Radio transient surveys are being revolutionised by the de-<lb/>velopment of the current generation of radio facilities. These in-<lb/>clude new low-frequency instruments such as the International <lb/>Low-Frequency Array (LOFAR; van Haarlem et al. 2013), Long <lb/>Wavelength Array (LWA; Ellingson et al. 2013) and the Murchin-<lb/>son Wide Field Array (MWA; Tingay et al. 2013). The telescopes <lb/>listed offer a large FoV coupled with an enhanced sensitivity, with <lb/>LOFAR having the capability to reach sub-mJy sensitivities and <lb/>arcsecond resolutions (though this full capability is not used in <lb/>this work as such modes were being commissioned at the time). <lb/>These features are achieved by utilising phased-array technology <lb/>with omnidirectional dipoles, and the before mentioned telescopes <lb/>act as pathfinders for the low-frequency component of the Square <lb/>Kilometre Array (SKA; Dewdney et al. 2009). With such greatly <lb/>improved sensitivities at low frequencies, we have a new opportu-<lb/>nity to survey wide areas of the sky for transients and variables, <lb/>with a particular sensitivity to coherent bursts. <lb/>These new facilities have already produced some interesting <lb/>results in this largely unexplored parameter space. Bell et al. (2014) <lb/>searched an area of 1430 deg  2  for transient and variable sources at <lb/>154 MHz using the MWA. No transients were found with flux den-<lb/>sities &gt; 5.5 Jy on time-scales of 26 minutes and one year. However, <lb/>two sources displayed potential intrinsic variability on a one year <lb/>time-scale. Using the LWA, Obenberger et al. (2014a) detected two <lb/>kilojansky transient events while using an all-sky monitor to search <lb/>for prompt low-frequency emission from GRBs. They were found <lb/>at 37.9 and 29.9 MHz, lasting for 75 and 100 seconds respectively, <lb/>and were not associated with any known GRBs. This was followed <lb/>up by Obenberger et al. (2014b) who searched over 11 000 hours of <lb/>all-sky images for similar events, yielding 49 candidates, all with <lb/>a duration of tens of seconds. It was discovered that 10 of these <lb/>events correlated both spatially and temporally with large meteors <lb/>(or fireballs). This low-frequency emission from fireballs was pre-<lb/>viously undetected and identifies a new form of naturally occurring <lb/>radio transient foreground. <lb/>Two transient studies have now also been completed using <lb/>LOFAR. Carbone et al. (2015) searched 2275 deg  2  of sky at 150 <lb/>MHz, at cadences of 15 minutes and several months, with no <lb/>transients reported to a flux limit of 0.5 Jy. Cendes et al. (2015) <lb/>searched through 26, 149-MHz observations centred on the source <lb/>Swift J1644+57, covering 11.35 deg  2  . No transients were found to <lb/>a flux limit of 0.5 Jy on a time-scale of 11 minutes. <lb/>In this paper we use the LOFAR telescope to search 400 hours <lb/>of observations centred at the North Celestial Pole (NCP; δ = 90  •  ), <lb/>covering 175 deg  2  with a bandwidth of 195 kHz at 60 MHz. LO-<lb/>FAR is a low-frequency interferometer operating in the frequency <lb/>ranges of 10–90 MHz and 110–250 MHz. It consists of 46 stations: <lb/>38 in the Netherlands and 8 in other European countries. Full de-<lb/>tails of the instrument can be found in van Haarlem et al. (2013). <lb/>A previous study of variable radio sources located near the <lb/>NCP field (75  •  &lt; δ &lt; 88  •  ) was carried out by Mingaliev et al. <lb/>(2009). This study identified 15 objects displaying variability at <lb/>centimetre wavelengths on time-scales of days or longer. However, <lb/>the variability amplitude was found to be within seven per cent, <lb/>which we would not be able to distinguish with LOFAR due to <lb/>general calibration uncertainties at the time of writing. In addition, <lb/>the lower observing frequency used in this work would mean that <lb/>the expected peak flux densities would be significantly lower, <lb/>assuming a standard synchrotron event (e.g., van der Laan 1966), <lb/>making them challenging to detect. Also, the lower frequency <lb/>means that the variability would occur over even longer time-<lb/>scales, again assuming that the emission arises from a synchrotron <lb/>process. <lb/>The observations and processing techniques are discussed in <lb/>Section 2, with a description of how the transient search was per-<lb/>formed in Section 3. The results can be found in Section 4, which <lb/>is followed by a discussion of a discovered transient event in Sec-<lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A low-frequency transient near the NCP </note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body> Figure 1. Histograms giving a general overview of when the 2609 11-minute snapshots of the NCP were observed. The top panel contains a histogram showing <lb/>how many snapshots were observed on each day over the entire four month period, colour coded by month, which shows the distinct observing blocks in which <lb/>NCP observations were obtained. The bottom panel displays a &apos;zoom-in&apos; of the date range 21:00 2012/02/10–21:00 2012/02/12 UTC, now showing the number <lb/>of snapshots per hour. This emphasises further the sometimes fragmented nature of the observing pattern of the NCP, with which careful consideration had to <lb/>be given on how to combine the observations for the transient search. <lb/> tion 5. The implied transient rates and limits are discussed in Sec-<lb/>tion 6, before we conclude in Section 7. <lb/> 2 LOFAR OBSERVATIONS OF THE NCP <lb/> The monitoring survey of the NCP was performed between 2011 <lb/>December 23–2012 April 16, resulting in a total of 2609 observa-<lb/>tions being recorded. The NCP was chosen because it is constantly <lb/>observable from the Northern Hemisphere, and the centre of the <lb/>field is located towards constant azimuth and elevation (az/el) coor-<lb/>dinates. However, this is not true for sources which lie away from <lb/>the NCP, where these sources rotate within the LOFAR elliptical <lb/>beam. We therefore restrict our transient search to an area around <lb/>the NCP where the LOFAR station beam properties are consistent <lb/>for each epoch observed, avoiding systematic errors in the light <lb/>curves that might be introduced if this was not the case. It is also an <lb/>advantage that the line-of-sight (b=122  •  .93, l=+27  •  .13) is located <lb/>towards a relatively low column density of Galactic free electrons; <lb/>the maximum expected dispersion measure (DM) is 55 pc cm  −3  ac-<lb/>cording to the NE2001 model of the Galactic free electron distribu-<lb/>tion (Cordes &amp; Lazio 2003). <lb/>The NCP measurements were taken using the LOFAR Low-<lb/>Band Antennas (LBA) at a single frequency of 60 MHz; the band-<lb/>width was 195 kHz, consisting of 64 channels. The total integration <lb/>time of each snapshot was 11 min, sampled at 1 s intervals, and data <lb/>were recorded using the &apos;LBA_INNER&apos; setup, where the beam is <lb/>formed using the innermost 46 LBA antennas from each station, <lb/>which gives the largest possible FoV and a full width half maxi-<lb/>mum (FWHM) of 9.77  •  . <lb/> 2.1 Observation epochs <lb/> The programme piggybacked on another commissioning project <lb/>being performed by LOFAR at the time, the Multifrequency Snap-<lb/>shot Sky Survey (MSSS) – the first major LOFAR observing <lb/>project surveying the low-frequency sky (Heald et al. 2015). With <lb/>every single MSSS LBA observation that took place, a beam was <lb/>placed on the NCP using one subband of the full observational <lb/>setup for MSSS. Figure 1 shows a histogram of the number of NCP <lb/>snapshots observed each day over the duration of the programme, <lb/>in addition to a similar histogram showing the number of snapshots <lb/>per hour for a particular set of days. Of the 2609 snapshots, 909 <lb/>were recorded during the day and 1700 were recorded at night. The <lb/>MSSS observational set-up also meant that each 11-minute snap-<lb/>shot in the same observation block was separated by a time gap of <lb/>four minutes. <lb/> 2.2 Calibration and imaging <lb/> Prior to any processing, radio-frequency interference (RFI) was re-<lb/>moved using AOFLAGGER (Offringa et al. 2010, 2012a,b) with a <lb/>default strategy, in addition, the two channels at the highest, and <lb/>lowest, frequency edges of the measurement set were also com-<lb/>pletely flagged, reducing the bandwidth to 183 kHz. When using <lb/>an automatic flagging tool such as AOFLAGGER, it is important <lb/>to be aware of the fact that transient sources could be mistakenly <lb/>identified as RFI by the software. This is a complex issue which <lb/>is beyond the scope of this work. However, an initial investigation <lb/>for the LOFAR case was carried out by Cendes et al. (2015). In <lb/>these tests, simulated transient sources, described by a step func-<lb/>tion, with different flux densities and time durations (from seconds <lb/>to minutes), were injected into an 11 minute dataset. These datasets <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<page> 4 </page>

			<note place="headnote"> Stewart et al. <lb/></note>

			<body> were subsequently passed through AOFLAGGER before calibrating <lb/>and imaging as normal in order to observe how the simulated tran-<lb/>sient was affected by the automatic flagging, if at all. The authors <lb/>concluded that transient signals shorter than a duration of two min-<lb/>utes could be partially, or in the case of ∼Jansky level sources, <lb/>completely flagged. However, there are some caveats to this test-<lb/>ing: short time-scale imaging was not tested for short-duration tran-<lb/>sients, and it remains to be determined how the automatic flagging <lb/>would treat other types of transients (i.e. a non step function event). <lb/>Hence, while these results certainly suggest that transients could be <lb/>affected by AOFLAGGER, further testing is required to completely <lb/>understand how automatic flagging software can affect the detec-<lb/>tion of a transient. <lb/>At this stage we also removed all data from international LO-<lb/>FAR stations, leaving just the Dutch stations. This was due to the <lb/>complex challenges in reducing these corresponding data at the <lb/>time of processing. Following this, the &apos;demixing&apos; technique (de-<lb/>scribed by van der Tol et al. 2007) was used to remove the effects of <lb/>the bright sources Cassiopeia A and Cygnus A from the visibilities. <lb/>Finally, averaging in frequency and time was performed such that <lb/>each observation consisted of 1 channel and an integration time of <lb/>10 seconds per time step. The averaging of the data was necessary <lb/>to reduce the data volume and computing time required to process <lb/>the data. <lb/>This averaging has the potential to introduce effects caused <lb/>by bandwidth and time smearing, which are discussed in more <lb/>detail by Heald et al. (2015) in relation to MSSS data. Following <lb/>Heald et al. (2015), we used the approximations given by Bridle &amp; <lb/>Schwab (1999) to calculate the magnitude of the flux loss (S/S0) <lb/> in each case, assuming a projected baseline length of 10 km. We <lb/>found the bandwidth smearing factor to equal seven per cent (using <lb/>a field radius corresponding to the FWHM) and a time smearing <lb/>factor of 0.4 per cent. Thus, while the effect of time smearing <lb/>was negligible, the impact of bandwidth smearing was potentially <lb/>significant, yet remained within the calibration error margins (10 <lb/>per cent; see Section 4.1). <lb/>A selection of flux calibrators, characterised by Scaife &amp; <lb/>Heald (2012)  1  , were used in the main processing of the data and <lb/>were observed simultaneously utilising LOFAR&apos;s multi-beam <lb/>capability (thus the calibrator scans were also 11 minutes in <lb/>length). The calibrators and their usage can be found in Table 1. <lb/>The standard LOFAR imaging pipeline was then implemented <lb/>which consists of the following steps. Firstly, the amplitude and <lb/>phase gain solutions, using XX and YY correlations, are obtained <lb/>for each calibrator observation using Black Board Selfcal (BBS; <lb/>Pandey et al. 2009). These solutions are direction-independent, and <lb/>are derived for each time step using the full set of visibilities from <lb/>the Dutch stations, as well as a point source model of the calibrator <lb/>itself. Beam calibration was also enabled which accounts, and <lb/>corrects, for elevation and azimuthal effects with the station beam. <lb/>The amplitudes of these gain solutions were then clipped to a 3σ <lb/> level to remove significant outliers, which were not uncommon in <lb/>these early LOFAR data. The gain solutions were then transferred <lb/>directly from the calibrators to the respective NCP observation. <lb/>Secondly, a phase-only calibration step was performed (also <lb/>using BBS) to calibrate the phase in the direction of the target <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 1  Cygnus A is not characterised by Scaife &amp; Heald (2012), but extensive <lb/>commissioning work (summarised by McKean et al. 2011 and McKean et <lb/>al. in prep.) has produced a detailed source model. <lb/></note>

			<body> Table 1. Table listing the calibrators used for the NCP observations. It was <lb/>decided early in the MSSS programme that 3C 48 and 3C 147 might not <lb/>be adequate as calibrators for the LBA portion of the survey, and so these <lb/>were dropped 8 and 22 days after first use, respectively. Observations using <lb/>these calibrators displayed no disadvantages over those observed with other <lb/>calibrators when checked in this project, and hence they were kept as part <lb/>of the sample. <lb/>Calibrator Source % Use First Use Date Last Use Date <lb/>3C 48 <lb/>2% <lb/>2011 Dec 24 <lb/>2012 Jan 01 <lb/>3C 147 <lb/>6% <lb/>2011 Dec 23 <lb/>2012 Jan 14 <lb/>3C 196 <lb/>43% <lb/>2011 Dec 24 <lb/>2012 Apr 14 <lb/>3C 295 <lb/>40% <lb/>2011 Dec 24 <lb/>2012 Apr 01 <lb/>Cygnus A <lb/>9% <lb/>2012 Jan 28 <lb/>2012 Apr 16 <lb/> field. The solutions were derived using data within a maximum <lb/>projected uv distance of 4000λ (20 km; 24 core + 10 remote sta-<lb/>tions). In order to perform this step, a sky model was obtained of <lb/>the NCP field using data from the global sky model (GSM) de-<lb/>veloped by Scheers (2011). This model is constructed by firstly <lb/>gathering sources which are present within a set radius from the <lb/>target pointing in the 74 MHz VLA Low-Frequency Sky Survey <lb/>(VLSS; Cohen et al. 2007). In the NCP case, the radius was set to <lb/>10 deg. From this basis, sources are then cross-correlated, using a <lb/>source association radius of 10 arcsec, with the 325 MHz Wester-<lb/>bork Northern Sky Survey (WENSS; Rengelink et al. 1997) and the <lb/>1400 MHz NRAO VLA Sky Survey (NVSS; Condon et al. 1998) <lb/>to obtain spectral index information. In those cases where no match <lb/>was found, the spectral index, α (using the definition Sν ∝ ν  α  ), <lb/>was set to a canonical value of α = −0.7. No self-calibration was <lb/>performed on the data. The reader is referred to van Haarlem et al. <lb/>(2013) for more LOFAR standard pipeline information. <lb/>The main MSSS project discovered that observations recorded <lb/>during this 2011-2012 period potentially contained one or more bad <lb/>stations, and the data quality would improve if such stations were <lb/>removed. LOFAR was still very much in its infancy at the time, <lb/>and, as a result, was not entirely stable; problems such as network <lb/>connection issues or bad digital beam forming contributed to the <lb/>poor performance of some stations. Hence, an automated tool was <lb/>developed which analysed each station, identifying and flagging <lb/>those that displayed a significant number of baselines with high <lb/>measured noise. This tool was utilised in the NCP processing and <lb/>primarily removed stations with poorly-focussed beam responses <lb/>(Heald et al. 2015). It should be noted that present LOFAR data <lb/>no longer require this tool as the issues outlined above have been <lb/>rectified. <lb/>Finally, a FoV of 175 deg  2  was imaged using the AWIMAGER <lb/> (Tasse et al. 2013), with a robust weighting parameter of 0 (Briggs <lb/>1995), and a primary-beam (PB) correction applied to each image. <lb/>A maximum projected baseline length of 10 km was used in this <lb/>study (2000λ; 24 core + 7 remote stations). This was chosen to <lb/>obtain good uv coverage and a maximum resolution for which we <lb/>were confident with the calibration. The typical resolution for the <lb/>11-minute snapshots was 5.4 × 2.3 arcmin. <lb/> 2.3 Quality control <lb/> A number of bad-quality observations were detected and subse-<lb/>quently flagged using two methods: (i) checking the processed visi-<lb/>bilities and (ii) inspecting the final images for each 11-minute snap-<lb/>shot. When analysing the visibilities, poor snapshots were flagged <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A low-frequency transient near the NCP </note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body> when the calibrated visibilities had a mean value greater than the <lb/>overall mean of the entire four month dataset plus one standard de-<lb/>viation value. A slight, or indeed dramatic rise in the mean of the <lb/>visibilities does not necessarily imply a completely bad dataset: an <lb/>extremely bright transient ( &gt; 100 Jy) could have this effect, for ex-<lb/>ample. Such events may have been previously seen from flare stars <lb/>at low frequencies (Abdul-Aziz et al. 1995), although at shorter <lb/>time-scales than 11 minutes (∼1 s). However, overall, the survey is <lb/>less sensitive to extremely bright events because of this quality con-<lb/>trol step. It was beyond the scope of this project to fully investigate <lb/>this possible effect, and so we decided to only use measurement <lb/>sets that were deemed to be sufficiently well calibrated. <lb/>The results from the automated flagging were also checked <lb/>against a manual analysis of the visibility plots and the snapshot <lb/>images, the latter enabling the detection of more bad observations. <lb/>In total, 460 (out of 2609) snapshots were marked as bad, and were <lb/>discarded from the search. The large size of the full dataset meant <lb/>that there was no single common reason as to why individual snap-<lb/>shots were rejected, but the problems that caused rejection were <lb/>mostly due to RFI or ionospheric issues. After the quality control <lb/>was completed, 2149 observations (394 hr) were considered in the <lb/>analysis. <lb/> 3 TRANSIENT &amp; VARIABILITY SEARCH METHOD <lb/>3.1 Time-scales searched <lb/> As the properties of the target transient population are unknown, <lb/>the complete dataset was split and combined in various ways to <lb/>fully explore the transient parameter space available. Along with <lb/>performing a search on the original snapshots, each with an inte-<lb/>gration time of 11 minutes, searches were also performed on im-<lb/>ages with integration times of 30 seconds, 2 minutes, 55 minutes <lb/>and 297 minutes. For the longer-duration images, only those 11-<lb/>minute snapshots which were four minutes apart were combined <lb/>together and imaged. This was to keep the visibilities as continu-<lb/>ous as possible in the search for transients. After the quality control <lb/>step described in Section 2.3, 297 minutes was the longest contin-<lb/>uous integration time possible. All calibration was performed on <lb/>each individual 11-minute snapshot; for the longer time-scales the <lb/>relevant datasets were combined and then imaged. <lb/> 3.2 The Transients Pipeline <lb/> The analysis of the data and search for radio transients was per-<lb/>formed using software developed by the LOFAR Transients Key <lb/>Science Project, named the Transients Pipeline (TRAP). It is built <lb/>to search for transients in the image plane, whilst also storing light <lb/>curves and variability statistics of all detected sources. Moreover, <lb/>it is designed to cope with large datasets containing thousands of <lb/>sources such as this NCP project. A full and detailed overview of <lb/>the TRAP can be found in Swinbank et al. (2015)  2  . In brief it per-<lb/>forms the following steps: <lb/>(i) Input images are passed through the TRAP quality control <lb/>which examines two features of the images. Firstly, the rms <lb/>of the map is compared against the expected theoretical <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> 2  The work presented in this paper primarily used TRAP release 1.0. How-<lb/>ever, the data were re-processed once TRAP release 2.0 was available, which <lb/>is the version described by Swinbank et al. (2015), to confirm results. <lb/></note>

			<body> rms of the observation, and if the ratio between the ob-<lb/>served and theoretical rms is above a set threshold then the <lb/>image is flagged as bad. In this case, the threshold was set <lb/>to the mean ratio value of each time-scale plus one stan-<lb/>dard deviation. The second test involves checking that the <lb/>beam is not excessively elliptical by comparing the ratio <lb/>of the major and minor axes. If this value is over a set <lb/>threshold then the image is also flagged as bad. All bad <lb/>images are then rejected and are not analysed by the TRAP <lb/> (see Rowlinson et al. in prep. for methods of setting these <lb/>thresholds). The number of images accepted by the TRAP <lb/> compared to the total entered can be seen in Table 2. <lb/>(ii) Sources are extracted using PYSE -a specially developed <lb/>source extractor for use in the TRAP (Spreeuw 2010, Car-<lb/>bone et al. in prep). Importantly, all sources are initially <lb/>extracted as unresolved point sources, which would be ex-<lb/>pected from a transient event. <lb/>(iii) For each image, the source extraction data are analysed <lb/>to associate each source with previous detections of the <lb/>same source, such that a light curve is constructed. In cases <lb/>where no previous source is associated with an extraction, <lb/>the source is flagged as a potential &apos;new source&apos; and is con-<lb/>tinually monitored from the detection epoch onwards. <lb/>For the source extraction, we define an island threshold, which de-<lb/>fines the region in which source fitting is performed, and a detection <lb/>threshold where only islands with peaks above this value are con-<lb/>sidered. These island and detection thresholds were set to 5σ and <lb/>10σ respectively. While the use of a 10σ detection threshold may <lb/>seem very conservative, we agree with the arguments presented by <lb/>Metzger et al. (2015) (hereafter MWB15) who advocate this crite-<lb/>ria when identifying a transient source. In their paper, the authors&apos; <lb/>main motivation for this high threshold is the significant possibility <lb/>of spurious signals such as those seen in previous radio transient <lb/>searches (Gal-Yam et al. 2006; Ofek et al. 2010; Croft et al. 2011; <lb/>Frail et al. 2012; Aoki et al. 2014), arising from calibration arte-<lb/>facts, residual sidelobes and other similar issues. We share these <lb/>concerns, in addition to be being generally cautious as this survey <lb/>is one of the first conducted with the new LOFAR telescope. As <lb/>also stated by MWB15, previous surveys have used 5σ as a detec-<lb/>tion threshold, which will of course increase the number of poten-<lb/>tial transient detections; however, this will also yield a high number <lb/>of false detections, especially with the large number of epochs be-<lb/>ing used in this survey. Thus, minimising false detections and ob-<lb/>taining a manageable number of transient candidates were further <lb/>motivations to use a 10σ detection threshold. We refer the reader to <lb/>MWB15 for further discussion on this topic. <lb/>The transient search was also constrained to within a circular <lb/>area of radius 7.5 deg from the centre of the image. This was to <lb/>avoid the outer part of the image which was much noisier and did <lb/>not have reliable flux calibration. <lb/>For each lightcurve, two values are calculated in order to de-<lb/>fine whether a source is a likely transient or variable: Vν , a co-<lb/>efficient of variation, and ην , the significance of the variability <lb/>(Scheers 2011). Vν is defined as <lb/> Vν = <lb/> sν <lb/>Iν <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/> Iν <lb/> N <lb/>N − 1 <lb/> I  2 <lb/> ν  − Iν <lb/> 2  <lb/> , <lb/>(1) <lb/>where s is the unbiased sample flux standard deviation, I is the <lb/>arithmetic mean flux of the sample, and N is the number of flux <lb/>measurements obtained for a source. The significance value, ην , <lb/>is based on reduced χ  2  statistics and indicates how well a source <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<page> 6 </page>

			<note place="headnote">Stewart et al. <lb/></note>

			<body> 22h <lb/> 23h <lb/>0h <lb/>1h <lb/>2h <lb/>3h <lb/> Right Ascension (J2000) <lb/> +79° <lb/>+79° <lb/>+80° <lb/>+80° <lb/>+81° <lb/>+81° <lb/> Declination (J2000) <lb/> 3C 61.1 <lb/>22h <lb/>23h <lb/>0h <lb/>1h <lb/>2h <lb/>3h <lb/> Right Ascension (J2000) <lb/> +79° <lb/>+79° <lb/>+80° <lb/>+80° <lb/>+81° <lb/>+81° <lb/> Declination (J2000) <lb/> 22h <lb/>23h <lb/>0h <lb/>1h <lb/>2h <lb/>3h <lb/> Right Ascension (J2000) <lb/> +79° <lb/>+79° <lb/>+80° <lb/>+80° <lb/>+81° <lb/>+81° <lb/> Declination (J2000) <lb/> 22h <lb/>23h <lb/>0h <lb/>1h <lb/>2h <lb/>3h <lb/> Right Ascension (J2000) <lb/> +85° <lb/>+85° <lb/> Declination (J2000) <lb/> 2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/>16 <lb/>18 <lb/>20 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>2.8 <lb/>3.2 <lb/>3.6 <lb/>4.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.8 <lb/> Figure 2. Examples of the NCP field maps at different time-scales. Where present, the area within the black circle indicates the portion of the image searched <lb/>for transients. This was the same for each time-scale and had a radius of 7.5  •  . Upper left panel: an image on the 30 s time-scale which was observed on 2012 <lb/>January 9. Using projected baselines of up to 10 km, the map has a resolution of 4.2 × 2.3 arcmin (synthesized beam position angle [BPA] −39  •  ) with a noise <lb/>level of 1.9 Jy beam  −1  . Only the source 3C 61.1 is detected at a 10σ level, and this source is marked on the image. Upper right panel: an 11 minute snapshot <lb/>observed on 2011 December 31. The noise level is 320 mJy beam  −1  and the resolution is 5.6 × 3.6 arcmin (BPA 43  •  ). The number of detected sources at <lb/>a 10σ level is now ∼ 15. Lower left panel: an example of the longest time-scale images available of 297 minutes, constructed by concatenating and imaging <lb/>27, 11-minute sequential snapshots. Observed on 2012 February 4, this image has a resolution of 3.5 × 2.0 arcmin (BPA −6  •  ) and a noise level of 140 mJy <lb/>beam  −1  , with ∼ 50 sources now detected at a 10σ level. Lower right panel: a magnified portion of the lower left panel image. The colour bar units are Jy <lb/>beam  −1  . <lb/> lightcurve is modelled by a constant value. It is given by <lb/> ην = <lb/> N <lb/>N − 1 <lb/> ωI  2 <lb/> ν  − <lb/> ωIν <lb/> 2 <lb/> ω <lb/> , <lb/>(2) <lb/>where ω is a weight which is inversely proportional to the error <lb/>of a given flux measurement (ω = 1/σ  2 <lb/> Iν  ). Throughout this pa-<lb/>per we define these parameters as the &apos;variability parameters&apos;. For <lb/>more detailed discussion on these parameters we refer the reader to <lb/>Scheers (2011) and Swinbank et al. (2015). <lb/>To define a transient or variable source, a histogram of each <lb/>parameter for the sample was created and fitted with a Gaussian <lb/>in logarithmic space. Any source which exceeds a 3σ threshold <lb/>on these plots is flagged as a potential candidate. Rowlinson et al. <lb/>(in prep.) will offer an in-depth discussion on finding transient and <lb/>variable sources using these methods. <lb/> 4 RESULTS <lb/>4.1 Image quality <lb/> Examples of the 30 s, 11 min and 297 min time-scale images can be <lb/>found in Figure 2. Note that imaging the NCP can sometimes cause <lb/>confusion when displaying the right ascension (RA) and declina-<lb/>tion (Dec) on the image axis, as the grid lines become circular. The <lb/>grid lines are shown in all figures to help demonstrate this. The <lb/>obtained uv coverage of the 11 and 297 min observations can be <lb/>viewed in Figure 3. The average sensitivity reached with each time-<lb/>scale is summarised in Table 2, along with the number of epochs <lb/>available after the quality control described in Sections 2 and 3. <lb/>It is important to note that, as a consequence of the primary <lb/>beam correction, search areas centred on the NCP do not have a <lb/>uniform noise level. Larger search areas include noisier regions fur-<lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A low-frequency transient near the NCP </note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body> Figure 3. Left panel: The uv coverage obtained with an 11 min snapshot. Right panel: The improved uv coverage gained when combining 27 snapshots (297 <lb/>min). In each case the uv range is limited to ±2 kλ (10 km). <lb/> 22h <lb/> 23h <lb/>0h <lb/>1h <lb/>2h <lb/>3h <lb/> Right Ascension (J2000) <lb/> +78° <lb/>+78° <lb/>+79° <lb/>+79° <lb/>+80° <lb/>+80° <lb/> Declination (J2000) <lb/> 0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1.0 <lb/> Figure 4. An example of a normalized primary beam map from one of the <lb/>NCP observations, which has been scaled to 1.0. The bold, outer solid-line <lb/>circle represents the full extent of the area for which the transient search <lb/>was performed (radius of 7.5 deg). The inner solid-line circles show how <lb/>the area was divided in order to gain an estimate of the average rms for each <lb/>image accounting for the primary beam. The dashed-line circle indicates <lb/>the position of the primary beam half-power point. <lb/> ther from the phase centre, and hence the flux density threshold at <lb/>which we could detect a transient across the full search area will <lb/>be higher. Figure 4 shows an example of a primary beam map from <lb/>one of the NCP observations. In order to obtain a noise estimate <lb/>accounting for the variation caused by the beam, for each image at <lb/>each time-scale we split the area into four annuli, equally spaced in <lb/>radius. These four regions are also marked on Figure 4. The rms for <lb/>each annulus was then measured, using a clipping technique, with <lb/>the area-weighted average of these four values providing the single <lb/>value rms estimate for the individual image. We then took the av-<lb/>erage of each time-scale, which are used as our sensitivity levels in <lb/>Table 2. Figure 5 shows that these measured rms values of the dif-<lb/>ferent time-scales approximately follow a 1/ <lb/> √ <lb/> t relation, where t <lb/> represents the integration time of the observation. We note that the <lb/>longer time-scale rms values appear to lie above the 1/ <lb/> √ <lb/> t relation. <lb/>We believe this is caused by the clipping technique being less ac-<lb/>curate at measuring the rms of the longer time-scale images annuli. <lb/>This in itself due to the presence of many more sources compared <lb/>to the relatively source free short time-scale images. In addition to <lb/>this, it is possible the CLEAN algorithm was not applied to a deep <lb/>enough level in some cases. Hence, the combination of these two <lb/>methods means that the longer time-scale rms values are likely to <lb/>be slightly overestimated, but not at a concerning level in the con-<lb/>text of this investigation. <lb/>We could have limited the transient search to a smaller region <lb/>with the deepest sensitivity; however, when calculating the figure <lb/>of merit (FoM, ∝ Ωs  −  3 <lb/> 2  where Ω is the FoV and s is the sensi-<lb/>tivity) it can be shown that it is more beneficial to extend the area <lb/>of the search, despite the increase in average rms. This can easily <lb/>be demonstrated as the full area is 16 times larger but the weighted <lb/>sensitivity only drops by a factor of about two; hence the FoM is <lb/>around five times better, illustrating the motivation for searching <lb/>wide area. We refer the reader to Macquart (2014) for an in-depth <lb/>discussion of the FoM in the context of transient surveys. <lb/>The 55 and 297 min time-scale images offered the best flux <lb/>calibration stability from image to image due to the better uv cov-<lb/>erage achieved on these time-scales. An example of the general flux <lb/>calibration quality can be seen in Figure 6, which shows the aver-<lb/>aged measured flux across all the 297 minute snapshots of sources <lb/>detected at 60 MHz, cross-matched with the VLSS catalogue at 74 <lb/>MHz. It shows a general agreement with the fluxes that would be <lb/>expected assuming an average spectral index of α = −0.7. If we <lb/>assume that all sources have this spectral index and calculate the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<page> 8 </page>

			<note place="headnote"> Stewart et al. <lb/></note>

			<body> Table 2. The average image sensitivity and number of epochs for each time-<lb/>scale at which a transient search was performed. The accepted epochs col-<lb/>umn defines how many of the total number of images passed the TRAP im-<lb/>age quality control. <lb/>Time <lb/>Average rms <lb/>Typical Resolution <lb/>Total # <lb/>Accepted # <lb/>(min) (mJy beam  −1  ) <lb/>(arcmin) <lb/>Epochs <lb/>Epochs <lb/>0.5 <lb/>3610 <lb/>4.8 × 2.2 <lb/>47 970 <lb/>41 340 <lb/>2 <lb/>2110 <lb/>4.7 × 2.1 <lb/>10 739 <lb/>9 262 <lb/>11 <lb/>790 <lb/>5.4 × 2.3 <lb/>2 149 <lb/>1 897 <lb/>55 <lb/>550 <lb/>4.9 × 2.1 <lb/>371 <lb/>328 <lb/>297 <lb/>250 <lb/>3.1 × 1.4 <lb/>34 <lb/>32 <lb/> expected VLSS 60 MHz flux for each source, we find that the aver-<lb/>age ratio of this expected VLSS flux against the measured LOFAR <lb/>flux is 1.00 ± 0.17. <lb/> Overall there was a typical scatter of 10 per cent in each <lb/>light-curve of sources detected, which was measured by the TRAP. <lb/> It was common that fainter sources (&lt; 10σ) would appear to <lb/>&apos;blink&apos; in and out of images; this was especially apparent in the 11 <lb/>minute snapshots. This was likely due to a mixture of varying rms <lb/>levels and the ionosphere causing phase calibration issues. Such <lb/>behaviour was a further reason why a 10σ source detection limit <lb/>was used in the transient search. The sensitivities of the shortest <lb/>time-scale maps, 30 s and 2 min, were such that only the brightest <lb/>source in the field, 3C 61.1, was detectable. The LOFAR and VLSS <lb/>source positions were also consistent within 5.1 arcsec on average; <lb/>the typical resolution in the LOFAR band is 3.1 × 1.4 arcmin for <lb/>the 297 min time-scale. <lb/>It was also important to determine whether the images pro-<lb/>duced for the transient search are confusion limited. In order to <lb/>calculate an estimate of the confusion noise for the average res-<lb/>olutions presented in Table 2, we followed the same approach as <lb/>Heald et al. (2015), using VLSS C-configuration estimates (see Co-<lb/>hen 2004) which we extrapolate to 60 MHz using a typical spectral <lb/>index of −0.7. We also alter the formula to account for the non-<lb/>circular beams: <lb/> σconf,VLSS = 29 <lb/> θ1 × θ2 <lb/> 1  <lb/>  0.77  <lb/> 60 MHz <lb/> 74 MHz <lb/>  −0.7 <lb/> µJy beam  −1  , <lb/>(3) <lb/>where θ1 is the synthesized beam size major axis and θ2 is <lb/>the minor axis. For the five time-scales used in the transient <lb/>search shown in Table 2, beginning with 30 sec, we calculate the <lb/>confusion noise estimates to be 113, 107, 128, 111 and 57 mJy <lb/>beam  −1  respectively. Thus, due to our simple reduction strategy, <lb/>our images, at best, are approximately 4× the confusion noise <lb/>level and hence would not affect our transient search. <lb/>Along with these cadences, a deep map was constructed by <lb/>using all the available 297 min images, reaching a sensitivity of 71 <lb/>mJy beam  −1  (this value was measured using the weighted average <lb/>method discussed above in this section). This map can be seen in <lb/>Figure 7. This, however, had to be produced by means of image <lb/>stacking as opposed to direct imaging due to the amount of data in-<lb/>volved. A total of 150 sources were detected at a 10σ level within <lb/>the same 7.5 deg radius circle used for the transient search, with the <lb/>map primarily being used as a deep reference image for the field. <lb/>We can, however, use this deep map to verify our calibration and <lb/>imaging procedures by comparing our detected source counts to the <lb/> 10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 1 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> Integration Time (min) <lb/> 10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> RMS (mJy beam <lb/> ¡1  ) <lb/> Observed average <lb/>Individual images <lb/>1/ <lb/> p <lb/> t <lb/> Figure 5. The average rms obtained from the images produced by combin-<lb/>ing and splitting the dataset. Also plotted in light grey are the range of noise <lb/>values for the individual images at their respective time-scales, in addition <lb/>to the 1/ <lb/> √ <lb/> t relation where t is the integration time of the observation. It can <lb/>be seen that the average rms values approximately follow this relation; the <lb/>longer time-scale values are likely to be slightly overestimated due to the <lb/>methods used to estimate the rms. The errors shown on the average points <lb/>are one standard deviation of the rms measurements from the respective <lb/>time-scale. <lb/> 10 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 1 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> VLSS Sky Model Flux at 74 MHz (Jy) <lb/> 10 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 1 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> Mean LOFAR Flux at 60 MHz (Jy) <lb/> α =0 <lb/> α =−0.7 <lb/> Figure 6. Plot of the mean extracted flux of sources from the 297 minutes <lb/>NCP survey at 60 MHz against the cross-matched VLSS survey at 74 MHz. <lb/>The solid line represents the expected LOFAR flux density assuming a spec-<lb/>tral index of α = −0.7. For illustrative purposes a dashed-line representing <lb/> α = 0 (a 1:1 ratio) is also shown. <lb/> VLSS. Firstly, using a spectral index of −0.7, S60 = 710 mJy cor-<lb/>responds to a flux density at 74 MHz of S74 = 613 mJy. Using this <lb/>flux density limit, there are 263 catalogued VLSS sources within <lb/>7.5 deg of the phase centre. Cross-correlating the VLSS with our <lb/>LOFAR 60 MHz detections, we find that 41 per cent of the VLSS <lb/>sources have a LOFAR match. The factor of ∼ 2 discrepancy can <lb/>be shown to be simply due to the primary beam attenuation in our <lb/>deep map. Hence, we were satisfied that the calibration and imag-<lb/>ing results were valid and consistent with previous studies, and <lb/>therefore would not negatively impact any transient searches. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A low-frequency transient near the NCP </note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body> 22h <lb/> 23h <lb/>0h <lb/>1h <lb/>2h <lb/>3h <lb/> Right Ascension (J2000) <lb/> +76° <lb/>+76° <lb/>+77° <lb/>+77° <lb/>+78° <lb/>+78° <lb/>+79° <lb/>+79° <lb/> Declination (J2000) <lb/> 0.08 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>0.40 <lb/>0.48 <lb/>0.56 <lb/> Figure 7. The deepest map produced of the NCP field from the survey. It <lb/>was constructed by averaging all 31 of the 297-minute-duration images to-<lb/>gether in the image plane, using inverse-variance weighting. It has a noise <lb/>level of 71 mJy beam  −1  and a resolution of 3.1 × 1.4 arcmin (BPA 42  •  ). <lb/>A total of 150 sources are detected at a 10σ level within a radius of 7.5 <lb/>deg from the centre of the map. While none of these sources are previously <lb/>undetected, it provided a detailed reference map to check any transient can-<lb/>didates. The colour bar units are Jy beam  −1  . <lb/> This map was also further analysed for any previously un-<lb/>catalogued radio sources, but none were found. However, the di-<lb/>rect comparison to VLSS revealed that one source, located at <lb/> 02  h  13  m  28  s  +84  •  04   18   , has apparently significantly different 60 <lb/>and 74 MHz flux densities: the VLSS integrated flux density is 1.49 <lb/>Jy (possibly put in the error), whereas in the LOFAR band it is de-<lb/>tected at the 8σ level with a integrated flux density of 236 mJy. <lb/>There are no detections of the source in WENSS or NVSS. How-<lb/>ever, this source is located within a stripe feature in the VLSS im-<lb/>age, and the source is not present in the VLSS Redux catalogue <lb/>(VLSSr; Lane et al. 2014); hence we do not pursue this source fur-<lb/>ther. The full MSSS survey will offer further insight into this po-<lb/>tential source, confirming its flux density and spectral index, if it is <lb/>real. <lb/> 4.2 Variability search results <lb/> The four month dataset provides an opportunity to search for <lb/>variable sources as well as transient sources. We define variables <lb/>as sources which are present throughout the entire dataset, taking <lb/>into consideration varying sensitivity, whose light curve displays <lb/>significant variability over the period. This is opposed to transient <lb/>sources, which we define as sources that appear or disappear <lb/>during the time spanned by the dataset, again taking into account <lb/>the varying sensitivity. Consulting historical catalogues also helps <lb/>with the distinction between variables and transients. Due to the <lb/>higher level of image quality, the variability search was limited to <lb/>the two longest time-scales of 55 and 297 min. For each detected <lb/>source in these two sets of images, variability parameters (Vν and <lb/> ην ) were calculated by the TRAP. Figure 8 shows the respective <lb/>distributions of the variability parameters for each time-scale <lb/>plotted in logarithmic space. In each case, the central panel shows <lb/> Figure 8. This figure shows the distribution of values obtained for the vari-<lb/>ability parameters Vν , a coefficient of variation, and ην , the significance of <lb/>the variability (see text for full definitions) for each light-curve detected. <lb/>The upper panel shows the 55-minute image results and the lower panel <lb/> shows the 297-minute time-scale results. In each case, the central panel <lb/>plots the two values against each other for each source, with the top panel <lb/>and right side panel displaying the histogram showing the distribution of <lb/>the ην and Vν values respectively for all sources. The dotted lines repre-<lb/>sent a 3σ threshold for each parameter. A very-likely variable or transient <lb/>source would appear in the top-right of the plot, exceeding a 3σ level in <lb/>each parameter. At both time-scales, one source (3C 61.1) is found to have <lb/>a significant value in ην . However this is likely to arise from fluctuations <lb/>caused by calibration issues. <lb/> ην plotted against Vν for each detected source. The top panel <lb/>displays a histogram representing the distribution of ην of all <lb/>the sources along with a fitted Gaussian curve. The right panel <lb/>contains the distribution and fitted Gaussian curve for Vν . The <lb/>dashed lines represent a 3σ threshold for each value; any sources <lb/>with variability parameters exceeding one or both of these values <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<page> 10 </page>

			<note place="headnote">Stewart et al. <lb/></note>

			<body> are considered as potentially variable. Candidates also had to show <lb/>a variability of significantly more than ten per cent, which was <lb/>the calibrator error of the measurements. This was set at a level <lb/>of 2σ from this value. An ideal transient would appear in the <lb/>top-right-hand corner of the central panel scatter plot, exceeding <lb/>the threshold in each parameter. <lb/>It can be seen that at both time-scales, no sources exhibit vari-<lb/>able behaviour in Vν above a 3σ level, but one source has a signifi-<lb/>cant ην value. This source is 3C 61.1, which dominates the field. <lb/>While the result points towards low-level variability of 3C 61.1, <lb/>the source is a well resolved radio galaxy (Leahy &amp; Perley 1991) <lb/>whose flux is dominated by 100-kpc-scale lobes, making it very <lb/>unlikely that we would detect any intrinsic variability. It is more <lb/>likely that this is the result of calibration errors and the source <lb/>extraction and subsequent calculation of ην itself. The model for <lb/>3C 61.1 used during this investigation is quite basic for such a com-<lb/>plex source. This, along with ionospheric effects and the general <lb/>calibration accuracy of the instrument at the time, can have quite <lb/>a substantial effect on such a bright source, with such calibration <lb/>errors not included in this analysis. The source is also spatially ex-<lb/>tended, but the extraction treats it as a point source (as mentioned <lb/>in Section 3), and this will therefore also have a significant impact <lb/>on the recorded flux. Removing the point source fitting constraint <lb/>does indeed move the data point closer back towards the 3σ thresh-<lb/>old, but only marginally by 0.1 dex in ην . As for the ην value, <lb/>this parameter is weighted by the flux errors of the source extrac-<lb/>tion. Bright sources, such as 3C 61.1, are well fitted when they are <lb/>extracted, which means they have small associated statistical flux <lb/>errors. This in turn then causes ην to rise. If we discount 3C 61.1, <lb/>no sources displayed any significant variability at the 55 and 297 <lb/>minute time-scales. <lb/> 4.3 Transient search results <lb/> Using the TRAP and a manual analysis of its results, searches <lb/>performed on the time-scales of 0.5, 2, 55 and 297 minutes <lb/>found no transient candidates. However, nine transient candidates <lb/>emerged from the analysis of the 11-minute time-scale. At first <lb/>it appeared strange to achieve nine candidates at one time-scale <lb/>but none at any other. However, the sensitivity of the shorter <lb/>time-scales was such that only bright transients (&gt; 25 Jy) would <lb/>have been confidently detected, and as previously stated no other <lb/>source, or even artefact, was detected at these flux levels other <lb/>than 3C 61.1. At the longer time-scales, the improved uv coverage <lb/>meant that the images improved substantially in quality. This <lb/>reduced the number of imaging artefacts that could spawn false <lb/>detections and sources were consistently detected throughout <lb/>the epochs (as opposed to many sources blinking in and out as <lb/>discussed in Section 4.1). Any sources that were defined as &apos;new&apos; <lb/>by the TRAP (sources which appeared that were not detected in the <lb/>first image) were in fact association errors and not transient sources. <lb/>While the nine candidates could point towards the 11 minute <lb/>images meeting the required sensitivity and time-scale of a tran-<lb/>sient population, these images are also the most likely to exhibit <lb/>misleading artefacts due to the limited uv coverage. Hence, the nine <lb/>reported candidates were subjected to a series of tests to determine <lb/>whether they were spurious sources. The following tests were per-<lb/>formed: <lb/>(i) Subtraction of 3C 61.1 from the visibilities using the clean <lb/>component model from the deconvolution process. The <lb/>visibilities were then re-imaged. <lb/>(ii) Applying an extra round of RFI removal using AOFLAG-<lb/>GER. <lb/> (iii) Re-running the automated tool to remove perceived bad <lb/>LOFAR stations from the observations, followed by a man-<lb/>ual check. <lb/>(iv) Imaging the data using different weighting schemes and <lb/>baseline cutoffs. <lb/>The tests were applied in the above order, meaning that if one <lb/>method definitely succeeded in removing the candidate the latter <lb/>tests were not performed. Only one of the nine candidates com-<lb/>pletely survived all the tests; three were inconclusive but quite <lb/>doubtful, whereas four were definite artefacts. One other source <lb/>was very marginal in passing all the tests; hence this event is not <lb/>presented in this paper, but will be discussed in a future publica-<lb/>tion. The surviving candidate was thus a potential real astrophysical <lb/>event and is the subject of the following Section 5. <lb/> 5 TRANSIENT CANDIDATE ILT J225347+862146 <lb/> The only candidate to have passed all the validity checks, was found <lb/>in a single 11 min snapshot taken on 2011 December 24 at 04:33 <lb/> UTC. The source was extracted by the TRAP with a flux of 7.5 Jy <lb/>(14σ detection in individual image), at coordinates 22  h  53  m  47.1  s <lb/> +86  •  21   46.4   , with a positional error of 11   . It was only seen in <lb/>this one snapshot with no detection of the source in the preceding <lb/>or subsequent snapshots. The observation can be seen in Figure 9. <lb/>Nothing was present at the candidate position in either the rela-<lb/>tively deep image constructed from the longer time-scale images <lb/>(see Section 4.1) or the very deep image of the field from the LO-<lb/>FAR Epoch of Reionisation (EoR) group (Yatawatta et al. 2013). <lb/>Note that the EoR project uses the LOFAR high-band antennas, <lb/>and hence it is at a higher frequency range of 115–163 MHz. <lb/> 5.1 A mirrored ghost source <lb/> On closer inspection, the transient candidate appeared to have a <lb/>secondary associated positive &apos;ghost&apos; source mirrored across the <lb/>brightest source in the field, 3C 61.1 (the transient lies at an angular <lb/>distance of 3.2  •  from 3C 61.1), which can also be seen in Figure 9. <lb/>This ghost was not detected by TRAP due to the higher rms value <lb/>in that region, and like the transient candidate it was a &apos;new&apos; source <lb/>with no previous or subsequent detections. In fact the ghost source <lb/>was actually nominally brighter than the transient source with a flux <lb/>density of 13 Jy. However, in the non-primary-beam-corrected map <lb/>the candidate has a higher peak flux density (9 Jy) than the ghost <lb/>(6 Jy). This was not the first time we had witnessed this type of ef-<lb/>fect in LOFAR observations, with previous commissioning data we <lb/>had obtained in 2010 showing a similar situation. Currently, the ex-<lb/>act explanation of why ghosts of this nature, including specifically <lb/>the ghost presented in this work, are generated in LOFAR data is <lb/>unknown. It should be noted that none of the other eight transient <lb/>candidates detailed previously had an associated ghost source. In <lb/>the following discussions we refer to the original detected transient <lb/>source ILT J225347+862146, to the west of 3C 61.1, as the &apos;tran-<lb/>sient candidate&apos; and the source to the east of 3C 61.1 as the &apos;ghost&apos; <lb/>source (refer to Figure 9). <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A low-frequency transient near the NCP </note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body> 0h <lb/> 1h <lb/>2h <lb/>3h <lb/> Right Ascension (J2000) <lb/> +81° <lb/>+82° <lb/>+83° <lb/>+84° <lb/> Declination (J2000) <lb/> 3C 61.1 <lb/>T <lb/>G <lb/> 0h <lb/>1h <lb/>2h <lb/>3h <lb/> Right Ascension (J2000) <lb/> +81° <lb/>+82° <lb/>+83° <lb/>+84° <lb/> Declination (J2000) <lb/> 3C 61.1 <lb/>T <lb/>G <lb/> 0.8 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>3.2 <lb/>4.0 <lb/>4.8 <lb/>5.6 <lb/>6.4 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>3.2 <lb/>4.0 <lb/>4.8 <lb/>5.6 <lb/>6.4 <lb/> Figure 9. Upper Panel: Illustrates how the transient source (labelled &apos;T&apos;), <lb/>ILT J225347+862146, was originally detected in the image, along with the <lb/>associated ghost source (labelled &apos;G&apos;) across from 3C 61.1. Lower Panel: <lb/> Now the measurement set as been re-calibrated with the transient included <lb/>in the sky model; the ghost source has vanished. Upon closer inspection, <lb/>other faint, source-like features also disappear from the re-calibrated image. <lb/>These are most likely fainter ghost features which are reduced when the data <lb/>were calibrated with a more complete sky model. The colour bar units are <lb/>Jy beam  −1  . <lb/> 5.1.1 Ghost artefacts in radio interferometry <lb/> Calibration artefacts presenting themselves as spurious &apos;ghost&apos; <lb/>sources is not an entirely new topic to radio interferometry. The <lb/>topic of &apos;spurious symmetrisation&apos; is discussed in Cornwell &amp; <lb/>Fomalont (1999); in brief, if a point source model is used for <lb/>a slightly resolved source, a single iteration of self-calibration <lb/>can result in features of the image being reflected relative to the <lb/>point-like object. However, this can be corrected with further <lb/>iterations of self-calibration which would cause the spurious <lb/>features to disappear. As will be discussed in Section 5.1.2, the <lb/>ghost presented in this work can be seen before initiating any kind <lb/>of self-calibration of the target field, i.e. any calibration using a <lb/>target field sky model. Therefore, it is highly unlikely that the <lb/>spurious symmetrisation previously described is the sole cause of <lb/>the ghost. However, this is not to say that the effect plays no role <lb/>in its creation. <lb/>More recently, Grobler et al. (2014) (hereafter &apos;G14&apos;) began a <lb/>series of investigations dedicated to ghost phenomena. This first <lb/>study concentrated on ghosts seen in data from the Westerbork <lb/>Synthesis Radio Telescope (WSRT). In these data, ghost sources <lb/>appeared as strings of (usually) negative point sources passing <lb/>through the dominant source(s) in the field. The arrangement of <lb/>these negative point sources appeared quite regular, along with the <lb/>fact that the positions were not affected by frequency. In their inves-<lb/>tigation, G14 were successful in deriving a theoretical framework <lb/>to predict the appearance of ghosts in WSRT data for a two-source <lb/>scenario, and were able to confirm what previous work had sug-<lb/>gested concerning these ghost sources (see text in G14). <lb/>In brief, the main features about ghosts to note are as follows: <lb/>(i) they are associated with incomplete sky models, for example <lb/>missing or incorrect flux; (ii) in the WSRT case, the ghosts always <lb/>formed in a line passing through the poorly modelled or unmod-<lb/>elled source(s) and the dominant source(s) in the field; (iii) the <lb/>ghosts are mostly negative in flux, while positive ghosts are rare <lb/>and weaker; and (iv) the general ghost mechanism can also explain <lb/>the observed flux suppression of unmodelled sources. <lb/>G14 also concluded that the simple East-West geometry of the <lb/>WSRT array is the reason for ghosts appearing in a regular, straight <lb/>line, pattern. This becomes more complex when a fully 2D/3D ar-<lb/>ray is considered such as LOFAR, where the ghost pattern is ex-<lb/>pected to become a lot more scattered and noise-like. This subject <lb/>will be the focus of Paper II (Wijnholds et al. in prep.) in the se-<lb/>ries on ghost sources. However, G14 did note that regardless of the <lb/>array geometry, ghosts are expected to occur at the nφ0 positions, <lb/>where φ0 represents the angular separation between the respective <lb/>bright source and unmodelled source, and n is an integer number. <lb/>Usually the strongest ghost responses are the n = 0 and n = 1 <lb/> positions, i.e. the suppression ghosts that sit on top of the sources <lb/>in question. However the case discovered in this work, and also two <lb/>independent cases (de Bruyn, priv. comm., Clarke, priv. comm.) in <lb/>LOFAR data suggest that the n = −1 position could also generate <lb/>a strong response. What is significant about the transient presented <lb/>in this work, however, is that the ghost appears as a positive source. <lb/> 5.1.2 Investigating the NCP ghost <lb/> Returning to the situation detailed in this paper, we were presented <lb/>with two sources for which either could be the real (transient) <lb/>source or the ghost. We attempted to simulate the situation within <lb/>real data, in order to investigate how the different stages of calibra-<lb/>tion would react to a bright transient, and if we could also generate <lb/>a positive ghost source. This was done by taking a different NCP <lb/>observation and inserting a simulated transient source into the <lb/>visibilities (the transient was set to be &apos;on&apos; for the entire 11 mins) <lb/>before any calibration had taken place. The snapshot was then <lb/>calibrated as normal, but importantly the inserted source was not <lb/> included in the NCP sky model used for the phase-only calibration <lb/>step (refer to Section 2.2). This test was repeated using various <lb/>different sky positions and flux densities for the inserted source. <lb/>We found that we could produce a significant positive ghost source <lb/>only if the flux of the simulated transient was relatively bright, <lb/> ∼40 Jy. An example can be seen in Figure 10. We observed that it <lb/>was common for the total flux to be shared approximately equally <lb/>between the simulated source and its associated ghost. However, <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<page> 12 </page>

			<note place="headnote">Stewart et al. <lb/></note>

			<body> 0h <lb/> 1h <lb/>2h <lb/>3h <lb/> Right Ascension (J2000) <lb/> +81° <lb/>+82° <lb/>+83° <lb/>+84° <lb/> Declination (J2000) <lb/> 3C 61.1 <lb/>ST <lb/>G <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/> Figure 10. The resultant image after a simulated transient source (labelled <lb/>&apos;ST&apos;) was inserted into the visibilities of a NCP observation and processed <lb/>without the simulated source in the sky model. A ghost source (labelled <lb/>&apos;G&apos;) appears mirrored across 3C 61.1. The effect is not limited to one spe-<lb/>cific insertion point of the simulated transient and is more pronounced the <lb/>brighter the simulated transient. In this example, a source of brightness 80 <lb/>Jy was inserted, which produces a very significant ghost source. The simu-<lb/>lated transient and ghost source each had a measured flux density of ∼25 Jy, <lb/>with the remaining ∼30 Jy being absorbed by 3C 61.1. This transfer of flux <lb/>was common when the simulated transient was brighter than 3C 61.1 (∼80 <lb/>Jy). When lower, the flux is shared equally between the simulated and ghost <lb/>sources, with minimal flux transferred to 3C 61.1. The colour bar units are <lb/>Jy beam  −1  . <lb/> not every position on the sky at which the transient was inserted <lb/>produced a ghost source, a feature that we cannot currently <lb/>explain. Yet, when a transient was inserted at the position of ILT <lb/>J225347+862146, this did produce a ghost source. We were then <lb/>able to test what happened when the simulated source was included <lb/>in the sky model. We observed that when the simulated source <lb/>was accounted for perfectly in the sky model, the ghost source <lb/>disappeared. If the sky model component was instead inserted at <lb/>the location of the ghost source, while the ghost appeared brighter, <lb/>the simulated transient never fully disappeared. <lb/>In light of the results from the simulations, we performed <lb/>the same sky model test with the transient candidate and ghost in <lb/>order to determine which source was the &apos;real&apos; source. Recalling <lb/>that the total flux of the transient candidate and ghost was ∼7 Jy <lb/>+ ∼13 Jy ≈ 20 Jy, we began by inserting a 20 Jy point source <lb/>into the NCP sky model at the position of the transient candidate <lb/>and re-calibrated the dataset. We found that in this case the flux <lb/>of the ghost was significantly reduced, by ∼70 per cent, and the <lb/>candidate brightened by ∼100 per cent. Alternatively, if the model <lb/>component was entered at the ghost location, the candidate source <lb/>and ghost respective fluxes were only ∼10 per cent different from <lb/>their initial fluxes on discovery, i.e. when they were not in the sky <lb/>model at all. In fact increasing the sky model component to 25 <lb/>Jy and placing it back at the position of the transient candidate <lb/>reduced the ghost such that it was no longer distinguishable from <lb/>the noise, as seen in the bottom panel of Figure 9. Hence, the <lb/>&apos;real&apos; source was determined to be at the position TRAP had origi-<lb/>nally reported, 22  h  53  m  47.1  s  +86  •  21   46.4   , to the west of 3C 61.1. <lb/>The above tests have concentrated on the target NCP field sky <lb/>model, but we also have the sky model which was used to cali-<lb/>brate the calibrator observation. For this observation, the calibrator <lb/>source was 3C 295. Considering that ghosts occur because of sky <lb/>model errors, one could envision a scenario in which the error being <lb/>transferred from the calibrator to the target field results in the ghost <lb/>pattern observed. As mentioned in Section 2.2, the calibrator sky <lb/>models only contain the calibrator source itself and not any sur-<lb/>rounding field sources. While this generally allows the derivation <lb/>of sufficiently accurate gain solutions, the missing flux could be at-<lb/>tributed to a ghost pattern, which is then transferred to the target <lb/>field (see also Asad et al. 2015 for a similar discussion regarding <lb/>the 3C 196 field). <lb/>To investigate this, two tests were performed. Firstly, the <lb/>phase-only calibration step was ignored and we imaged the dataset <lb/>using the amplitude and phase gain solutions directly from the <lb/>calibrator. In this case, both the transient and the ghost were <lb/>present, with no major changes from before (a result which makes <lb/>&apos;spurious symmetrisation&apos;, previously discussed in Section 5.1.1, <lb/>unlikely to be the sole cause of the ghost). Secondly, the calibrator <lb/>observation was not used at all and instead the data were calibrated <lb/>in both amplitude and phase using the constructed NCP target sky <lb/>model (described in Section 2.2) which importantly did not contain <lb/>the transient source. For this test, we increased the solution interval <lb/>to one minute (originally 10 s) to gain more signal-to-noise for the <lb/>calculations. We also had to perform post-processing clipping to <lb/>the visibilities to eliminate bad amplitude spikes in the calibrated <lb/>visibilities. In the full 11 min image, while the rms rose to ∼800 <lb/> mJy beam  −1  , a source was detected within one arcmin (the <lb/>resolution of the image was 5.6 × 2.4 arcmin) of the reported <lb/>transient candidate position with a flux density of 13 Jy. The ghost <lb/>source was not detected to a 5σ limit of 10 Jy at its expected <lb/>location, nor was it visible when the map was manually inspected. <lb/>However, due to the increase of the rms in this case, we cannot <lb/>state with complete confidence that the ghost source is not present <lb/>at all. Nonetheless, observing the transient source without placing <lb/>it in the sky model provided additional evidence that we had <lb/>identified the correct source. <lb/>The above result tentatively points to the calibrator having an <lb/>important role in the ghost creation. However, understanding the <lb/>exact ghost mechanism is a complex task in the LOFAR case, and <lb/>each stage of the calibration must be taken into careful consid-<lb/>eration. For example, G14 has exclusively investigated situations <lb/>where full amplitude and phase calibration is used, so the effects of <lb/>a phase-only calibration is generally unknown at this stage. At the <lb/>time of writing, we cannot explain how the ghost is generated; a de-<lb/>tailed investigation is under way (Grobler et al. in prep.) to resolve <lb/>the matter. <lb/> 5.2 Transient flux density <lb/> 5.2.1 Obtaining the correct flux <lb/> The correct flux density of the transient proved difficult to ascer-<lb/>tain. We attempted to obtain an estimate by entering flux values <lb/>of the transient source manually into the calibration sky model, <lb/>over a range of 7.5–45 Jy, in steps of 2.5 Jy, and proceeded to re-<lb/>calibrate the visibilities (as previously described, this calibration <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A low-frequency transient near the NCP </note>

			<page>13 <lb/> </page>

			<body> step is phase only). We then observed the influence this had on <lb/>the measured flux density of the transient itself, as well as the <lb/>measured flux densities of the surrounding sources, including the <lb/>ghost source. We remind the reader that the transient candidate, the <lb/>source deemed &apos;real&apos;, is to the west of 3C 61.1 and the ghost is the <lb/>source to the east of 3C 61.1. The transient was always placed as a <lb/>point source in the sky model. The results of this experiment can <lb/>be seen in Figure 11. We found that the ghost source became in-<lb/>creasingly fainter as the transient flux was increased, right up until <lb/>the transient was entered as 20 Jy and the ghost could no longer <lb/>be distinguished from the background. The transient &apos;light curve&apos; <lb/>itself follows the trend of the increasing sky model flux, but it also <lb/>exhibits a sudden local maximum when the sky model entry level is <lb/>changed from 22.5 to 25 Jy. In this instance the extracted flux rises <lb/>from 16 Jy to 20 Jy. It then proceeds to fall back to an extracted <lb/>flux level of 18 Jy and continues to rise as before. <lb/>As for the other nearby sources, while they are stable prior <lb/>to the sky model transient component reaching 17.5 Jy, beyond <lb/>this level they suffer a very noticeable decline that continues as <lb/>the transient flux is increased. It is also apparent that the other <lb/>sources in the field are affected by the before mentioned sudden <lb/>local maximum of the transient light curve around a sky model <lb/>flux of 25 Jy, with 3C 61.1 also showing a significant flux increase <lb/>(∼ 3σ to the scaled value). However, for VLSS 0110.7+8738 <lb/>and VLSS 2130.1+8357, which are at a similar flux level to ILT <lb/>J225347+862146, there is a hint of a decrease, although within the <lb/>error bars of the flux measurements. In each case, once the sky <lb/>model flux is increased to the next step, the measured fluxes return <lb/>to their previous levels. When comparing the fluxes of the field <lb/>sources with the corresponding averages from the four surround-<lb/>ing snapshots, we see that they mostly agree within all the error <lb/>bars involved. The largest discrepancy comes from 3C 61.1, which <lb/>appears ∼ 10 per cent dimmer in the transient snapshot, which is <lb/>outside the errors of the average measurement. However, the sud-<lb/>den increase around 25 Jy causes 3C 61.1 to match the surrounding <lb/>average. This could be seen as a clue that this area represents the <lb/>real flux of the transient; at this point, with 25 Jy in the sky model, <lb/>the transient appears as 20 Jy in the image. Hence, with this in-<lb/>formation, we associate the true flux of the source with the point at <lb/>which the ghost disappears and the other sources in the field are not <lb/>heavily affected, which constrains our estimate of the flux density <lb/>of ILT J225347+862146 to be in the range 15–25 Jy. <lb/> 5.2.2 Testing known sources <lb/> The test detailed above was performed directly on the two <lb/>field sources that were monitored during the investigation, VLSS <lb/>0110.7+8738 and VLSS 2130.1+8357, with 60-MHz flux densi-<lb/>ties of ∼9 and ∼15 Jy respectively. This also included removing <lb/>the sources from the calibration sky model as well as changing <lb/>the input flux. Each source was treated as a separate case mean-<lb/>ing that both were never subtracted from the sky model, or edited, <lb/>at the same time. As before, these tests were performed at the tran-<lb/>sient epoch, but also in the two neighbouring epochs to ensure that <lb/>any effects were not just local to the transient-containing snapshot. <lb/>Without the source in the model, the measured flux was reduced <lb/>by ∼20 per cent, with the majority of the extra flux in the field be-<lb/>ing absorbed by 3C 61.1, which appeared slightly brighter. Once <lb/>the source was reinserted into the sky model, even at a low flux, <lb/>the source in question returned to the expected level. However, as <lb/>the sky model input flux was increased, so did the extracted flux, <lb/>which is consistent with how the transient acted previously. There <lb/> 10 <lb/> 20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/> Transient Candidate Sky Model Flux (Jy) <lb/> 0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/> PySE Extracted Flux (Jy) <lb/> ILT J225346+862146 <lb/>Ghost Source <lb/>3C 61.1 (40 Jy subtracted) <lb/>3C 220.3 <lb/>VLSS 0110.7+8738 <lb/>VLSS 2130.1+8357 <lb/>5 × RMS at ghost location <lb/> Figure 11. The extracted flux of the transient candidate using the PySE <lb/>source extractor against the manually defined flux entered into the sky <lb/>model at the transient position when processing. Also shown is a measure-<lb/>ment of the ghost source flux obtained by a forced fit at the ghost position. <lb/>The input flux was defined in steps of 2.5 Jy, from 7.5 Jy to 45 Jy. The plot <lb/>also shows the extracted fluxes of four other sources in the field in order to <lb/>monitor any effects to other sources, along with the solid lines which show <lb/>the average flux of these field sources from the four surrounding snapshots. <lb/>The error on these averages is shown by the error bar at the beginning and <lb/>end of the line. Above an input flux value of 20 Jy (extracted transient flux <lb/>value of 17 Jy) it becomes apparent that the other sources are beginning to <lb/>be affected. They drop sharply beyond an entered flux of 30 Jy by which <lb/>point the ghost source is no longer statistically significant. Note that 3C <lb/>61.1 has been scaled by subtracting 40 Jy from its flux measurements. <lb/> was also no distinguishing feature that would enable a confident <lb/>definition of these sources&apos; &apos;correct flux&apos; without prior knowledge. <lb/>Thus, it is not a surprise that the transient flux in Section 5.2.1 is <lb/>hard to identify purely from the behaviour of the source itself dur-<lb/>ing calibration when altering the sky model. Ideally self-calibration <lb/>would be used, but at the time of processing self-calibration with <lb/>LOFAR was still a relatively untested technique. <lb/> 5.2.3 Splitting the dataset in time <lb/> In the test detailed above, where the transient was inserted into the <lb/>sky model with various different flux values, it was noticeable that <lb/>the flux that was inserted was never the flux that was measured. If <lb/>the transient was not &apos;on&apos; for the entire 11 min, this could perhaps <lb/>explain why this was the case. With the transient included in the <lb/>sky model at a flux of 20 Jy, the observation was firstly split in half <lb/>and imaged; however, the flux was consistent within the 1σ error <lb/>bars between each half. To probe deeper, we then referred to the 2-<lb/>minute images produced as part of the transient search, which did <lb/>not have the transient included in the sky model. This particular <lb/>observation, however, was above the average noise level (1.8 Jy <lb/>beam  −1  ) with an rms of ∼2 Jy beam  −1  . Neither the transient nor <lb/>ghost source had significant detections (with the significance level <lb/>now reduced to 5σ in order to try and detect the transient), and <lb/>even surrounding field sources were hard to distinguish because of <lb/>the poorer image quality. <lb/>In an attempt to improve the situation, using our assumption <lb/>that the transient should be included in the sky model for the ob-<lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<page> 14 </page>

			<note place="headnote">Stewart et al. <lb/></note>

			<body> 04:31 <lb/> 04:33 <lb/>04:35 <lb/>04:37 <lb/>04:39 <lb/>04:41 <lb/>04:43 <lb/> UTC <lb/> 0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/> Transient Flux (Jy) <lb/> 10 Jy In Sky Model <lb/>20 Jy In Sky Model <lb/> Figure 12. The extracted flux of the transient candidate in 2-minute inter-<lb/>vals, obtained using the TRAP, for the cases where the transient is included <lb/>in the sky model at 10 and 20 Jy. Data points represented by a square sig-<lb/>nify that the source was extracted from the image with a blind detection. In <lb/>contrast, the triangles represent flux values obtained from a forced fit at the <lb/>source position, where the source was no longer above the source extraction <lb/>threshold (13 Jy, 5σ). The two light curves follow the same trend, suggest-<lb/>ing that the transient is brighter than a 3σ limit of 7.5 Jy in the 4-minute <lb/>period of 04:34 -04:38. The 10-Jy input case, returning a measured flux <lb/>of 16 Jy, also suggests that 16 Jy may be the correct flux during this time <lb/>frame. These light curves were obtained by extending the phase-calibration <lb/>time interval to one min. The date of the observation was 2011 December <lb/>24. <lb/> servation, we phase-calibrated this dataset again using a larger so-<lb/>lution interval of 1-minute (previously 10 s), to allow more signal <lb/>to noise for the calculations. Using a source extraction threshold of <lb/> 5σ,  TRAP was able to find the transient source in the second and <lb/>third of the 5, 2-minute images: the flux densities are 20.9 (8σ) and <lb/>18.7 (7σ) Jy, respectively. The light curve can be seen in Figure 12. <lb/>We were concerned about forcing the flux of the transient to <lb/>a specific value by simply entering that value into the sky model, <lb/>especially as in this case the fluxes returned were approximately <lb/>equal to the flux which was entered (20 Jy). Thus, we repeated this <lb/>test, but this time entering a 10-Jy transient at the position. In the <lb/>10-Jy case the transient was detected in the second image only at <lb/>a lower flux density. The forced fit performed by the TRAP in the <lb/>third image yields a flux measurement of 13 Jy (just below 5σ), <lb/> before dropping off, which mimics the characteristics of the 20 Jy <lb/>sky model case. <lb/>The first 2-minute image from each test was of noticeably <lb/>poorer quality than the other four, 2-minute images of the obser-<lb/>vation. As seen in Figure 12, the forced extraction at the transient <lb/>location in the first image returns the same flux density value (10 <lb/>Jy) in each sky model test case. This value hints at the transient be-<lb/>ing present in this epoch as this flux level is higher than the fourth <lb/>and fifth epochs, where the transient is no longer detected in both <lb/>cases. However, due to the uncertainty in this image and the larger <lb/>error bars associated with this measurement, we cannot state for <lb/>certain that this is the case. <lb/>We attempted to split the dataset which had been calibrated di-<lb/>rectly from the NCP field sky model, as discussed in Section 5.1.2, <lb/>but the calibration was not of sufficient quality to achieve useful <lb/>results. <lb/>The results here therefore suggest that the transient was bright-<lb/>est between the second and sixth minute of the observation, a pe-<lb/>riod of four minutes. However, we are unable to fully characterise <lb/>the decay, or especially the rise time of the event, and hence we <lb/>cannot rule out the transient being active over a longer, 10-minute <lb/>time-scale. <lb/> 5.3 Testing if a source can be created by the sky model <lb/> Because the transient did not correspond to any source contained <lb/>in the sky model, a major concern was the possibility of &apos;creating&apos; <lb/>false sources in the field by purely inserting them into the sky <lb/>model. This could explain the apparent responsiveness of the <lb/>candidate to an entry in the sky model, and perhaps a source placed <lb/>anywhere in the field would have the same effect, both in creating <lb/>a source and causing the ghost source to disappear. We tested this <lb/>in two ways. Firstly, the snapshot containing the candidate was <lb/>reprocessed with the candidate component of the sky model moved <lb/>to an empty, unrelated location on the sky. This resulted in no <lb/>source being &apos;created&apos; at this location and also left the candidate, <lb/>and ghost, unaffected from their original detection states. <lb/>The second test was to process the two preceding and two <lb/>subsequent snapshots with the candidate component inserted into <lb/>the sky model at its correct location. Previously, no detection was <lb/>made of the candidate in any other snapshot, and as the data were <lb/>recorded in sequence, the uv coverage of these observations were <lb/>all very similar. The result was that, once more, no source was <lb/>present at the candidate location, even when placed in the sky <lb/>model; this can be seen in Figure 13, which shows the detection of <lb/>the candidate along with the snapshots before and after in time. <lb/>These two results meant that simply entering sources into the <lb/>sky model at an arbitrary position would not &apos;create&apos; an artificial <lb/>source. In contrast, the responsiveness of the transient candidate <lb/>to such input at the correct position suggested it was a real source <lb/>present in the data. <lb/> 5.4 Further validity testing <lb/> A final set of tests and checks were performed to investigate <lb/>whether ILT J225347+862146 was an unexpected artefact. With <lb/>LOFAR being commissioned at the time, an artefact would not be <lb/>completely surprising. While the telescope was in a good working <lb/>state, a lack of optimisation of aspects such as station calibration <lb/>and beam models could cause issues. A series of tests were devised <lb/>to rule out certain possible artefact causes, all performed with the <lb/>source both in and out of the sky model when processing. These <lb/>tests were: <lb/> • Broadband RFI -Care was taken to manually reduce the <lb/>data, removing anything left over that was suspected of being <lb/>RFI, as well as running another pass of AOFLAGGER on the <lb/>data after calibration. Neither method affected the transient <lb/>source. <lb/> • Narrow-band RFI -To rule out the possibility of narrow-<lb/>band RFI, the already limited bandwidth was split into two <lb/>and processed separately. The transient source remained in <lb/>each half of the bandwidth, with a flux consistent within the <lb/> 1σ error bars between the two halves. <lb/> • Calibrator Issues -The calibrator observation contains <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A low-frequency transient near the NCP </note>

			<page>15 <lb/> </page>

			<body> 0h <lb/> 1h <lb/>2h <lb/> Right Ascension (J2000) <lb/> +84° <lb/>+85° <lb/>+86° <lb/> Declination (J2000) <lb/> 2011-12-24 04:18:05 <lb/> 0h <lb/>1h <lb/>2h <lb/> Right Ascension (J2000) <lb/> +84° <lb/>+85° <lb/>+86° <lb/> Declination (J2000) <lb/> 2011-12-24 04:33:05 <lb/> 0h <lb/>1h <lb/>2h <lb/> Right Ascension (J2000) <lb/> +84° <lb/>+85° <lb/>+86° <lb/> Declination (J2000) <lb/> 2011-12-24 04:48:05 <lb/> 23h <lb/> Right Ascension (J2000) <lb/> +86°10&apos; <lb/>20&apos; <lb/>30&apos; <lb/>40&apos; <lb/>50&apos; <lb/>+87°00&apos; <lb/> Declination (J2000) <lb/> 23h <lb/> Right Ascension (J2000) <lb/> +86°10&apos; <lb/>20&apos; <lb/>30&apos; <lb/>40&apos; <lb/>50&apos; <lb/>+87°00&apos; <lb/> Declination (J2000) <lb/> 23h <lb/> Right Ascension (J2000) <lb/> +86°10&apos; <lb/>20&apos; <lb/>30&apos; <lb/>40&apos; <lb/>50&apos; <lb/>+87°00&apos; <lb/> Declination (J2000) <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/> Figure 13. A sequence of images in time: the transient detection image along with the snapshots before and after the event, together with a zoom-in of the <lb/>transient location. Importantly, each observation has been processed with the transient included in the calibration sky model, showing how even with this taken <lb/>into consideration, there are no significant detections before or after the transient. These images were created using the standard imaging parameters discussed <lb/>throughout the paper, including projected baselines of up to 10 km in length. The synthesized beam can be seen in the bottom-left of each image. The colour <lb/>bar units are Jy beam  −1  . <lb/> nothing peculiar and was of good quality. The calibrator for <lb/>this observation was 3C 295. <lb/> • Calibrator Gains Only -Previously discussed in Sec-<lb/>tion 5.1.2, this test meant the phase-only calibration step <lb/>using the target field sky model was skipped; instead we <lb/>imaged the dataset with the gain amplitude and phase <lb/>solutions obtained directly from the calibrator being applied. <lb/>ILT J225347+862146 was still present in the resulting image <lb/>along with the ghost. <lb/> • Phase Centre Shift -The phase centre of the observation <lb/>was shifted to that of the transient (a shift of ∼4 deg). The <lb/>transient was still clearly visible with the shift, especially <lb/>when the source was included in the sky model. <lb/> • Equal Local Sidereal Time Observations -Sixteen obser-<lb/>vations were found to have very similar local sidereal times <lb/>(LST) to that of the detection measurement, so these were <lb/>used to check whether the candidate was potentially caused <lb/>by that particular projection of the baselines on the sky. There <lb/>was no detection in any of these observations, which covered <lb/>four months of recording. <lb/> • Bad Station Removal -Along with the automatic tool that <lb/>was part of the initial four tests, a manual inspection of the <lb/>data was also carried out, which was in agreement with the <lb/>results from the tool: the same two stations were perceived <lb/>as bad. After these stations were flagged, the image was <lb/>generally cleaner from artefacts with the transient source <lb/>unaffected. <lb/> • Random Subset of Stations -Half of the 33 stations used in <lb/>the observation were randomly removed, after calibration, <lb/>with the remaining data being re-imaged. This was repeated <lb/>three times and the transient source continued to be present <lb/>in each of three resulting maps. <lb/> • Dirty Map Check -The source is present in the dirty map. <lb/> • Field Subtraction -Using a sky model derived from the <lb/>deeper image, the entire field apart from the transient was <lb/>subtracted from the dataset. The transient and ghost were <lb/>clearly visible in this case, with the same flux density. <lb/> • Imaging at a Different Resolution -Reducing the maximum <lb/>baseline length used when imaging from 10 km to various <lb/>lower values had no impact on the transient. An image using <lb/>a maximum projected baseline length of 15 km was also <lb/>produced in which the source was still present. However, <lb/>we did not consider any images produced with projected <lb/>baselines longer than 10 km scientifically useful, due to <lb/>concerns regarding the quality of calibration. <lb/> • Different Imaging Weighting Schemes &amp; Imager -Check-<lb/>ing for further side-lobe related issues, the imaging was re-<lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<page> 16 </page>

			<note place="headnote">Stewart et al. <lb/></note>

			<body> 30&apos;&apos; <lb/> N <lb/>E <lb/> Figure 14. The resultant combined optical image obtained with follow-up <lb/>observations using the Liverpool Telescope. It reaches a depth of r   ∼ 22– <lb/>22.5 mag and is calibrated against the USNO-B1 catalogue (Monet et al. <lb/>2003). The inner circle marked on the image, centred at the reported LO-<lb/>FAR transient position, represents a 1σ positional error of radius 14 arcsec. <lb/>The outer circle shows the 2σ positional error circle of radius 28 arcsec. <lb/>The two stars which have proper motions higher than 100 mas year  −1  , as <lb/>indicated by the USNO-B1 (Monet et al. 2003) catalogue, are indicated by <lb/>arrows. <lb/> done using natural and uniform weighting. The source re-<lb/>mained in the resulting maps. The imager itself was also <lb/>checked by imaging the observation with the &apos;Common As-<lb/>tronomy Software Applications&apos; (CASA; McMullin et al. <lb/>2007) software rather than AWIMAGER (this meant that no <lb/>primary beam correction was made) and the source was still <lb/>present. In this case, the candidate source was marginally <lb/>brighter than the ghost: the flux densities were 5.3 and 4.5 <lb/>Jy respectively. <lb/> 5.5 What is this transient? <lb/> With the candidate successfully passing the numerous exhaustive <lb/>tests detailed previously, we concluded that the candidate was a real <lb/>astrophysical source. Hence we proceeded to investigate its possi-<lb/>ble origin. <lb/> 5.5.1 Catalogue search and multi-wavelength follow-up <lb/> No source was found within a 2-arcmin radius of the transient po-<lb/>sition in historical radio catalogues, including VLSS, WENSS and <lb/>NVSS. Also, no potential counterpart or related object was found <lb/>in high-energy catalogues, and no published gamma-ray burst or <lb/>supernova event is known at the position. <lb/>We carried out optical follow-up of the field by using the Liv-<lb/>erpool Telescope (LT; Steele et al. 2004), though it is worth noting <lb/>that the transient was discovered two years after the event date. <lb/>Therefore, while a direct counterpart would not be observed, an <lb/>object of a certain type may be identified in the vicinity of the tran-<lb/>sient, and could be potentially associated with the radio emission. <lb/> Table 3. Details of the follow-up observations performed with the Liverpool <lb/>Telescope. <lb/>Obs. Date <lb/># Epochs Epoch Exposure Time <lb/>(s) <lb/>2013/11/28 <lb/>3 <lb/>100 <lb/>2013/12/21 <lb/>3 <lb/>100 <lb/>2013/12/30 <lb/>3 <lb/>100 <lb/>2014/01/12 <lb/>2 <lb/>300 <lb/> These observations with the LT used the r   band filter on four dif-<lb/>ferent dates, which are shown in Table 3, totalling 11 epochs and <lb/>1500 seconds of exposure time. <lb/>The combined image, shown in Figure 14, was calibrated <lb/>against USNO-B1 (Monet et al. 2003) and reaches r   ∼ 22– <lb/>22.5 mag. To search for a possible optical counterpart to ILT <lb/>J225347+862146, we established an error on the positional mea-<lb/>surement of the transient from the LOFAR data. This was cal-<lb/>culated by accounting for the following uncertainties which con-<lb/>tribute to the overall error: the error of the source extraction per-<lb/>formed by the TRAP which was reported as 11 arcsec and is mea-<lb/>sured following the error analysis of Condon (1997); the average <lb/>scatter of the extracted positions of bright sources in the dataset <lb/>by TRAP, measured to be 7 arcsec; and finally the reported 5 arcsec <lb/>positional error of the VLSS catalogue, which the phase calibration <lb/>sky model is based upon. Summing these values in quadrature we <lb/>gain the final positional error of 14 arcsec. <lb/>Using this value, we unambiguously detect four sources <lb/>within a 2σ error circle centred at the transient position, one of <lb/>which is fully enclosed by the 1σ uncertainty as shown in Fig-<lb/>ure 14. None of these sources displayed either strong short-term <lb/>(minutes) or long-term (weeks) variability. We used the USNO-B1 <lb/>catalogue to look for high-proper-motion stars in the field, with the <lb/>assumption that these would be nearby objects. Two of the four <lb/>sources mentioned previously within the 2σ radius, had associated <lb/>proper motions of higher than 100 mas year  −1  and are marked in <lb/>Figure 14. However, neither of these sources exhibited a colour <lb/>consistent with being an M-dwarf or any other possible transient <lb/>object (but we note that the error associated to the USNO-B1 cat-<lb/>alogue colours is significant). In addition, both sources were de-<lb/>tected in our LT images and no associated variability was observed. <lb/>We also consulted the Wide-Field Infrared Survey Explorer (WISE; <lb/>Wright et al. 2010) and the Two Micron All Sky Survey (2MASS; <lb/>Skrutskie et al. 2006); a total of three and two sources were located <lb/>within the 2σ error circle in each survey, respectively. In each case, <lb/>two objects were the previously reported high-proper-motion stars; <lb/>however neither of these, or the one other source in WISE, were <lb/>found to be variable. <lb/>Given possible further uncertainties of the accuracy of the <lb/>measured position in the LOFAR band, we extended the error circle <lb/>to a radius of one arcmin from the transient position. A total of 20 <lb/>sources were within this larger error circle in our LT observations; <lb/>however, as previously, there was no strong evidence of a possible <lb/>association with ILT J225347+862146. <lb/>We conclude that there is no obvious counterpart candidate. <lb/>We now consider whether the radio emission could arise from ei-<lb/>ther an incoherent or coherent process. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A low-frequency transient near the NCP </note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body> 5.5.2 Incoherent origin <lb/> If we consider the incoherent emission process, we can place a limit <lb/>on the maximum distance of the source, by using the known char-<lb/>acteristics of the transient along with assuming that its brightness <lb/>temperature (TB) is at the maximum TB = 10  12  K limit, TBmax, for <lb/>(un-beamed) synchrotron radiation (Kellermann &amp; Pauliny-Toth <lb/>1969). To do this we make use of the Rayleigh-Jeans law, that is <lb/> TBmax = <lb/>∆Lν <lb/>8πkν  2  ∆t  2  , <lb/>(4) <lb/>where ∆Lν is the change of the luminosity in time-scale ∆t, k <lb/> is the Boltzmann constant and ν is the observing frequency. The <lb/>luminosity at frequency ν is defined as Lν = 4πd  2  S, where d <lb/> is the distance and S is flux density. Using this and re-arranging <lb/>Equation 4 we obtain an expression for the distance as follows: <lb/> d  2  = <lb/>2kν  2  ∆t  2  TBmax <lb/> ∆S <lb/> . <lb/>(5) <lb/>For the flux density change ∆S = 20 Jy in time ∆t = 10 min, we <lb/>obtain a maximum distance of 13.7 pc. This points to the possibility <lb/>of the transient being a nearby flare star. <lb/>In the case where the source is relativistic, with the <lb/>synchrotron radiation now beamed, the observed brightness <lb/>temperature could exceed 10  12  K. This is seen in populations such <lb/>as AGN (Horiuchi et al. 2004; Kovalev et al. 2005) and GRBs <lb/>(Kulkarni et al. 1999; Anderson et al. 2014). From Equation 5 it <lb/>can be seen that d ∝ T <lb/> 1 <lb/> 2  . For example, if a brightness temperature <lb/>such as 10  16  K was observed, a value at which these sources <lb/>can sometimes appear (Pietka et al. 2015), this would place the <lb/>distance estimate of the transient at 1.4 kpc, an unrealistic distance <lb/>for such classes of objects. <lb/>Various previous studies have investigated the radio transient <lb/>properties of flare stars at both centimetre and decametre wave-<lb/>lenghts (Lovell 1969; Gudel et al. 1989; Bastian 1990; Jackson <lb/>et al. 1990; Abdul-Aziz et al. 1995; Osten et al. 2006). A recent <lb/>study, Boiko et al. (2012), involved monitoring the flare stars AD <lb/>Leonis (d = 4.9 pc) and EV Lacertae (d = 5.1 pc) with the UTR-2 <lb/>telescope, located in Ukraine, during March 2010 and 2011. These <lb/>observations, performed in the frequency range of 16.5–33 MHz, <lb/>yielded a total of 167 and 73 detected radio bursts from the respec-<lb/>tive stars. In the case of AD Leonis, the average flux of the bursts <lb/>was in the range of 10–50 Jy, seemingly consistent with the flux <lb/>measured from ILT J225347+862146 at 60 MHz. However, one <lb/>discrepancy is that the average duration of these bursts seen from <lb/>AD Leonis, which is 2–12 seconds, is considerably shorter than the <lb/>apparent ∼minutes of activity observed for ILT J225347+862146. <lb/>In addition, the sole detection of the transient is possibly suspi-<lb/>cious in this context. One would expect the detection of subse-<lb/>quent transient events from an active flare star over a period of four <lb/>months (the time-scale of this transient search). Recent results such <lb/>as Notsu et al. (2013), which show Kepler solar type stars exhibit-<lb/>ing super-flares, could offer an explanation, with some flare events <lb/>being active for ∼10 min time-scales (Schaefer et al. 2000). The <lb/>flare star hypothesis could be tested further by directing future ob-<lb/>servations towards the Galactic plane rather than the NCP, as the <lb/>density of flare stars should be dramatically increased. <lb/>If a flare star origin is assumed for ILT J225347+862146, <lb/>along with the object not not being detected in our follow-up opti-<lb/>cal image to a depth of r   ∼ 22 mag, we can use this information <lb/>to make a crude estimate of the distance of such an object such that <lb/>it is consistent with a non-detection. For this, we consult a cata-<lb/>logue of 463 UV Cet-type flare stars compiled by Gershberg et al. <lb/>(1999), selecting those which have a measured R band magnitude. <lb/>The stars in the catalogue have a maximum distance of 50 pc, and <lb/>we also only consider M type stars. These selected stars are then <lb/>divided into two sub-type groups: early type stars (M0-4) and late <lb/>type stars (M5-9). In total these groups have 69 and 20 stars re-<lb/>spectively. We then calculated the average absolute magnitudes of <lb/>these two groups, and subsequently at what average distance the <lb/>population would be if the apparent magnitude became 22 mag. <lb/>We found these distances to be ∼ 2 kpc for the early type stars and <lb/> ∼ 0.3 kpc for the late type stars (consistent with estimated Galac-<lb/>tic scale height values defined by Holwerda et al. 2014). Hence, <lb/>the object responsible for ILT J225347+862146 could be further <lb/>than these distances, dependent on spectral sub-type, if it is not de-<lb/>tected in our deep optical image obtained with the LT. However, <lb/>at these distances, this would make the radio event extremely lu-<lb/>minous, which is unlikely. Therefore, it would become likely that <lb/>ILT J225347+862146 is a nearby sub-stellar object. These values <lb/>could be further constrained by a deeper analysis of stellar objects, <lb/>so this conclusion is made tentatively. It is also worth noting that, <lb/>although we were unable to pick out a possible responsible object, <lb/>it is entirely possible that the source is present in the deep optical <lb/>image. <lb/> 5.5.3 Coherent origin <lb/> A new class of radio transient has emerged in recent years, <lb/>known as Fast Radio Bursts (FRBs). These events are single, <lb/>bright (∼ Jy), bursts, which typically last for a few milliseconds <lb/>and have never been seen to repeat. These bursts also exhibit <lb/>high DM indicating that the population is extragalactic in origin. <lb/>The first such event was seen by Lorimer et al. (2007) with the <lb/>Parkes Observatory in Australia. Since this discovery, a further <lb/>eight bursts have been detected using Parkes (Keane et al. 2011; <lb/>Thornton et al. 2013; Burke-Spolaor &amp; Bannister 2014; Ravi et al. <lb/>2015; Petroff et al. 2015) plus one event detected with the Arecibo <lb/>Observatory (Spitler et al. 2014). The implied rate of FRBs based <lb/>on these events has been predicted to be up to possibly thousands <lb/>of FRBs occurring every day over the entire sky (Hassall et al. <lb/>2013; Lorimer et al. 2013). The progenitors of all these events are <lb/>unknown, leading to a wide range of proposed theories regarding <lb/>how FRBs are produced (see Totani 2013; Kashiyama et al. 2013; <lb/>Falcke &amp; Rezzolla 2014; Zhang 2014; Loeb et al. 2014; Kulkarni <lb/>et al. 2014; Mottez &amp; Zarka 2014). Searches at low frequencies <lb/>have, thus far, not detected any FRBs, nor have any FRBs been <lb/>found using interferometric arrays which would enable a better <lb/>localisation of any discovered burst (Coenen et al. 2014; Law et al. <lb/>2015). <lb/>Hassall et al. (2013) showed that when the scattering of a <lb/>highly-dispersed burst is significant, imaging surveys for FRBs can <lb/>be competitive with pulsar-like, high-time-resolution surveys, if not <lb/>more sensitive, in detecting such events. To investigate this possi-<lb/>bility, we consider how the scattering time and fluence of the four <lb/>FRB events reported in Thornton et al. (2013) at 1.3 GHz, compare <lb/>to this event at 60 MHz. Firstly, to achieve estimates for the scat-<lb/>tering time of the Thornton events at 60 MHz, we use the standard <lb/>relation of <lb/> τsc(ν) ∝ ν  γ  , <lb/>(6) <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<page> 18 </page>

			<note place="headnote">Stewart et al. <lb/></note>

			<body> Table 4. The observed width of the four bursts reported in Thornton et al. <lb/>(2013) along with the estimated width of the event at 60 MHz. To calculate <lb/>the estimated width we use the relation τsc(ν) ∝ ν  γ  where γ = −4. <lb/> Dispersion effects are ignored and we assume a scenario of the reported <lb/>widths being dominated by scattering. Of the four reported bursts, FRB <lb/>110220 was the sole event to show any evidence of scattering. <lb/>Event <lb/>Observed width <lb/>Estimated width <lb/>at 1.3 GHz (ms) <lb/>at 60 MHz (s) <lb/>FRB 110220 <lb/>5.6 <lb/>1234 <lb/>FRB 110627 <lb/> &lt; 1.4 <lb/> &lt; 309 <lb/>FRB 110703 <lb/> &lt; 4.3 <lb/> &lt; 948 <lb/>FRB 120127 <lb/> &lt; 1.1 <lb/> &lt; 242 <lb/> where γ = −4. For the purposes of this scenario we ignore any <lb/>dispersion effects and assume that the recorded burst duration is <lb/>dominated by scattering. This assumption is quite reasonable when <lb/>considering the value of any dispersion induced smearing of the <lb/>signal, ∆tD, which can be calculated per MHz of bandwidth by <lb/> ∆tD = 8.3 × 10  3  DM ν  −3 <lb/> MHz , <lb/>(7) <lb/>where DM is the dispersion measure and νMHz is the observing fre-<lb/>quency in MHz. With a bandwidth of 183 kHz and an observing <lb/>frequency of 60 MHz, ∆tD = 7 × 10  −3  DM s. Thus, even with a <lb/>DM value of 1000 pc cm  −3  , ∆tD would only cause 7 s of smearing. <lb/>Table 4 shows that the predicted, scatter-dominated width of the <lb/>events at 60 MHz range from 242–1234 s (taking the upper limit <lb/>values), with the highest value belonging to FRB 110220. We see <lb/>that the maximum duration of our transient, ILT J225347+862146, <lb/>of &lt; 660 s is quite consistent with that expected from an FRB at 60 <lb/>MHz. In reality, only FRB 110220 showed any evidence of scatter-<lb/>ing. <lb/>Next we compare the fluence of the events. Taking a width <lb/>of 11 min for ILT J225347+862146 (6.6 × 10  5  ms), and the <lb/>flux as 20 Jy, the fluence of ILT J225347+862146 can be stated <lb/>as 20 × 6.6 × 10  5  = 1.3 × 10  7  Jy ms at 60 MHz. Taking the <lb/>shorter time-scale of four minutes (as discussed in Section 5.2.3) <lb/>at 20 Jy gives a fluence of 4.8 × 10  6  Jy ms. The event with the <lb/>highest fluence as reported in Thornton et al. (2013) was FRB <lb/>110220 with 8 Jy ms at 1.3 GHz. We can compare these fluence <lb/>values assuming different spectral indices. In the case of α = 0, <lb/> a direct comparison is possible, showing that the LOFAR event <lb/>has a vastly greater fluence than the known FRB. Assuming <lb/> α = −2 and extrapolating the peak flux of the LOFAR event <lb/>to 1.3 GHz, the fluence now becomes 2.81 × 10  4  Jy ms for the <lb/>11 min scenario. This is still much greater than FRB 110220. <lb/>For the LOFAR event to be consistent with this particular burst, <lb/>which is by far the highest fluence of the four reported bursts <lb/>in Thornton et al. (2013), then a spectral index of α ∼ −4.7 <lb/> would be required. This implies that the LOFAR event would <lb/>be an abnormally bright FRB, even more so than the bright <lb/>Lorimer et al. (2007) burst at 30 Jy. The characteristic spectral <lb/>index of FRBs is currently not well defined, but a value of −4.7 <lb/> would be very steep regardless of the population. Although the <lb/>time-scale of ILT J225347+862146 is consistent with a scattered <lb/>FRB at low-frequencies, the required steep spectral index along <lb/>with the inconsistency between the fluence of the known FRB <lb/>events, casts considerable doubt regarding an FRB origin. With <lb/>the exact characteristics of FRBs currently unknown, we can-<lb/>not state that ILT J225347+862146 belongs to the same population. <lb/>It should be noted, as described by Güdel (2002), that coher-<lb/>ent emission from plasma processes can also occur in stellar objects <lb/>such as flare stars. Such emission has also been seen from the Sun <lb/>at low-frequencies; for example in type III solar radio bursts (Bas-<lb/>tian et al. 1998). For this hypothesis, the arguments which were <lb/>presented in Section 5.5.2 concerning a flare star origin also apply <lb/>here. In particular, if this were the origin of ILT J225347+862146, <lb/>it appears unusual to not see the event repeat over a four month <lb/>period, yet we cannot rule out this possibility. <lb/> 5.5.4 Other populations <lb/> Other populations such as AGN and X-ray binary systems were <lb/>considered. However, we have insufficient evidence to confirm or <lb/>rule out such classes as the origin of ILT J225347+862146. <lb/>Over the past decade, a variety of new radio transient sources <lb/>have been attributed to different kinds of neutron stars. These <lb/>include populations such as Rotating Radio Transients (RRATs; <lb/>McLaughlin et al. 2006) and intermittent pulsars (Kramer et al. <lb/>2006), with some intermittent pulsars seen to have periods in the <lb/>off-state of more than a year (Camilo et al. 2012). It is possible <lb/>that the transient reported in this paper could be an atypical iso-<lb/>lated neutron star such as these described populations; however at <lb/>this time it is not possible to present any evidence to support this <lb/>hypothesis. <lb/> 6 TRANSIENT SURFACE DENSITY &amp; RATES <lb/> No transients were found at four of the five time-scales searched, <lb/>with one detection in the other. This allows us to place upper limits <lb/>on the rate of low-frequency transient events on the whole sky at <lb/>these time-scales. To calculate the upper limits of the surface den-<lb/>sity of transients, Poisson statistics are used, specifically: <lb/> P (n) = e  −ρA <lb/> (8) <lb/>where ρ is the surface density of sources per square degree and A <lb/> represents the equivalent solid angle obtained by multiplying the <lb/>area of the sky surveyed, Ω, by the number of epochs N − 1. In <lb/>using this approach we are also assuming isotropic probability of a <lb/>transient detection, i.e. events are likely to be extragalactic in ori-<lb/>gin. We can define P (n) = 0.05 at the Poisson 2σ confidence level, <lb/>and by rearranging Equation 8 we can obtain the respective value <lb/>of ρ for each time-scale, recalling that the area of sky searched in <lb/>each case was 175 deg  2  . For no detections P (0) = 0.05 is used, <lb/>whereas for the 11-minute time-scale this becomes P (1) = 0.05 <lb/> because of our single detection. These values can be found in Ta-<lb/>ble 5. <lb/>ILT J225347+862146 provides us with 1  +3.74 <lb/> −0.95  transient events <lb/>detected in the 11-minute time-scale search, using upper and lower <lb/>limits at 95% confidence as defined by Gehrels (1986). As a 10σ <lb/>limit was used for the source extraction, the flux density limit of <lb/>this search was 7.9 Jy; moreover, 1897 11-minute epochs are equiv-<lb/>alent to 14.5 days of observations. This equates to a transient rate <lb/>of 3.9  +14.7 <lb/> −3.7  × 10  −4  day  −1  deg  −2  . <lb/>However, it should be noted that the flux density limit of this <lb/>rate is defined with the assumption that sources are &apos;non-ghosted&apos;. <lb/>As seen in this work, transients with an associated ghost can be re-<lb/>duced in brightness when not accounted for in processing. While <lb/>we are yet to exactly constrain the magnitude of the effect, we can <lb/>make an estimate by taking ILT J225347+862146 as an example. <lb/>In this case the source was originally detected as 7.5 Jy with an <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A low-frequency transient near the NCP </note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body> Table 5. Summary of the transient surface densities and general information of the results of this work (top section) and other low-frequency ( 330 MHz) <lb/>transient surveys (bottom section). We follow a similar approach to Ofek et al. (2011) where δt is the time-scale of each individual epoch searched in the <lb/>survey, and ∆t is the cadence time-scales(s) of the epochs observed. The value denoted by &apos;-&apos; signifies that we were unsure of the correct value from the <lb/>literature. A time value of &apos;cont.&apos; means the observations were continuous. These values are those which are used in Figures 15 and 16. <lb/>Survey <lb/>Telescope <lb/> ν <lb/> Sensitivity <lb/> ρ <lb/>δt <lb/> ∆t <lb/> # <lb/># Detected <lb/>(MHz) <lb/>(Jy) <lb/>(deg  −2  ) <lb/>Epochs <lb/>Transients <lb/>This work <lb/>LOFAR <lb/>60 <lb/> &gt; 36.1 <lb/>4.1 × 10  −7 <lb/> 30 s <lb/>cont.–4 months <lb/>41 350 <lb/>0 <lb/>This work <lb/>LOFAR <lb/>60 <lb/> &gt; 21.1 <lb/>1.8 × 10  −6 <lb/> 2 min <lb/>cont.–4 months <lb/>9 262 <lb/>0 <lb/>This work <lb/>LOFAR <lb/>60 <lb/> &gt; 7.9 <lb/>1.4 × 10  −5 <lb/> 11 min <lb/>4 min–4 months <lb/>1 897 <lb/>1 <lb/>This work <lb/>LOFAR <lb/>60 <lb/> &gt; 5.5 <lb/>5.2 × 10  −5 <lb/> 55 min <lb/>4 min–4 months <lb/>328 <lb/>0 <lb/>This work <lb/>LOFAR <lb/>60 <lb/> &gt; 2.5 <lb/>5.3 × 10  −4 <lb/> 297 min <lb/>4 min–4 months <lb/>32 <lb/>0 <lb/>Lazio et al. (2010) <lb/>LWDA <lb/>74 <lb/> &gt; 2 500 <lb/>9.5 × 10  −8 <lb/> 5 min <lb/>2 min–4 months <lb/> ∼1 272 <lb/>0 <lb/>Obenberger et al. (2014a) <lb/>LWA1 <lb/>74 <lb/> &gt; 1 440 <lb/>2.2 × 10  −9 a <lb/> 5 s <lb/>cont.–1 year <lb/> ∼43 056 <lb/>2 <lb/>Bell et al. (2014) <lb/>MWA <lb/>154 <lb/> &gt; 5.5 <lb/>7.5 × 10  −5 <lb/> 5 min <lb/>minutes–1 year <lb/>51 <lb/>0 <lb/>Carbone et al. (2015) <lb/>LOFAR <lb/>150 <lb/> &gt; 0.5 <lb/>10  −3 <lb/> 11 min <lb/>minutes–months <lb/>151 <lb/>0 <lb/>Cendes et al. (2015) <lb/>LOFAR <lb/>149 <lb/> &gt; 0.5 <lb/>10  −2 <lb/> 11 min <lb/>minutes–months <lb/>26 <lb/>0 <lb/>Hyman et al. (2009)  b <lb/> VLA,GMRT 235,330 <lb/> &gt; 30 × 10  −3 <lb/> 0.034 <lb/> ∼3 hr <lb/>days–months <lb/>-<lb/>3 <lb/>Jaeger et al. (2012) <lb/>VLA <lb/>325 <lb/> &gt; 2.1 × 10  −3 <lb/> 0.12 <lb/>12 hr <lb/>1 day–1 month <lb/>6 <lb/>1 <lb/> a  Reported as 1.4 × 10  −2  yr  −1  deg  −2  . Using the integration time of 5 s, this converts to 2.2 × 10  −9  deg  −2  . <lb/> b  Values for this survey are obtained from the calculations performed by Williams et al. (2013) which takes into account results from Hyman et al. (2005, <lb/>2006, 2009). <lb/> Obe2014 <lb/> T <lb/> Bell2014 <lb/>Laz2010 <lb/>Jae2012 <lb/> T <lb/> Car2015 <lb/>Hym2009 <lb/> T <lb/>T <lb/> Cen2015 <lb/>10 <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 1 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 4 <lb/> Flux Density (Jy) <lb/> 10 <lb/> -9 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -8 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -7 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -6 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 0 <lb/> Surface Density (deg <lb/> ¡2  ) <lb/> This work <lb/> Figure 15. The logarithm of the surface density (deg  −2  ) against the log-<lb/>arithm of the flux density (Jy) of low-frequency transient surveys. We do <lb/>not consider variable source limits. The surface densities for which tran-<lb/>sients have been detected are marked with a T. The surveys included are as <lb/>follows: Hyman et al. (2005, 2006, 2009) (Hym2009); Lazio et al. (2010) <lb/>(Laz2010); Jaeger et al. (2012) (Jae2012); Bell et al. (2014) (Bel2014); <lb/>Obenberger et al. (2014a) (Obe2014); Carbone et al. (2015) (Car2015) and <lb/>Cendes et al. (2015) (Cen2015). <lb/> accompanying ghost, and when accounted for in processing, the <lb/>minimum flux estimate was 15 Jy in the 11 minute image (see Sec-<lb/>tion 5.2). Therefore a minimum reduction in flux density of 50 per <lb/>cent is possible, meaning that the flux density limit of the quoted <lb/>rate would rise to 8 Jy for ghosted sources. For the purposes of <lb/>comparing rates, in the remainder of the paper we use the ideal, <lb/>non-ghosted flux density limit of 7.9 Jy. <lb/> 6.1 Comparison to other transient surveys <lb/> We primarily consider how our results relate to other low-frequency <lb/>surveys ( 330 MHz). We also only compare against transient sur-<lb/>veys. Figure 15 shows the results in which we have included all the <lb/>surveys that are summarised in Table 5. In general, the results are <lb/>consistent with the previous low-frequency surveys. We are able to <lb/>improve upon the sensitivity of the Lazio et al. (2010) surface den-<lb/>sity by at least two orders of magnitude, with the data points from <lb/>this work providing some of the most extensive searches thus far at <lb/>low frequencies. <lb/>It is also possible to extrapolate our results to gigahertz fre-<lb/>quencies, for which extensive reviews of high-frequency surveys <lb/>have been compiled by Fender &amp; Bell (2011), Ofek et al. (2011) <lb/>and Fender et al. (2015). We find that our limits become competi-<lb/>tive with previous surveys for transient populations with a spectral <lb/>index of −1, and probe deeper than previous surveys if the spectral <lb/>index is steepened to −2. <lb/> 6.2 Comparison of time-dependent surface densities <lb/> It is important to realise that when comparing the transient sur-<lb/>face density and flux densities of different surveys, the time-scale at <lb/>which the survey was performed is just as important. A survey only <lb/>looking at month-scale epochs will not be sensitive to minute or <lb/>sub-minute-scale transients. The converse is also true depending on <lb/>the survey length and sensitivity. Defining the sensitive time-scale <lb/>of a transient survey is a complex task, with the epoch time (i.e. <lb/>the time-scale of an individual epoch) and cadence of the epochs <lb/>usually incorporating a range of values. Generally, we assume that <lb/>the integration time of each observation is the time-scale of a tran-<lb/>sient on which the survey is most sensitive to. If the integration <lb/>time matches the duration of the transient event, then the signal-<lb/>to-noise will, in the majority of cases, be maximised. However as <lb/>surveys are designed differently, the integration time is not always <lb/>the equivalent &apos;epoch time&apos;. Some epochs are created by averaging <lb/>many different observations together for example, or other meth-<lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<page> 20 </page>

			<note place="headnote"> Stewart et al. <lb/></note>

			<body> log Flux Densit y (Jy) <lb/> −3 <lb/>−2 <lb/>−1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/> lo g S u r f a c e D e n s it y ( d e g  − 2 <lb/> ) <lb/> −9 <lb/>−8 <lb/>−7 <lb/>−6 <lb/>−5 <lb/>−4 <lb/>−3 <lb/>−2 <lb/>−1 <lb/>0 <lb/> log <lb/> Time-scale <lb/> Second <lb/> Minute <lb/>Hour <lb/>Day <lb/> Hyman et al. 2009 <lb/>Lazio et al. 2010 <lb/>Jaeger et al. 2012 <lb/>Bell et al. 2014 <lb/>Obenberger et al. 2014a <lb/>Carbone et al. 2015 <lb/>Cendes et al. 2015 <lb/>This Work <lb/> Obe2014 <lb/> T <lb/> Bell2014 <lb/>Laz2010 <lb/>Jae2012 <lb/> T <lb/> Car2015 <lb/>Hym2009 <lb/> T <lb/>T <lb/> Cen2015 <lb/>Second <lb/>Minute <lb/>Hour <lb/>Day <lb/> log Timescale <lb/> 10 <lb/> -9 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -8 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -7 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -6 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> -1 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 0 <lb/> Surface Density (deg <lb/> ¡2  ) <lb/> This work <lb/> Figure 16. Left panel: A 3D plot presenting the 3D low-frequency transient search phase space when considering the time-scale of the search. Here, the <lb/>logarithm of the surface density (deg  −2  ) is plotted against the logarithms of the flux density (Jy) and survey time-scale, with the latter on the z-axis. The <lb/>viewing angle has been selected to primarily show the flux density and time-scale comparison. We do not consider variable source limits in this plot. The <lb/>11-minute limit from this work, as well as the limits of Hyman et al. (2009), Jaeger et al. (2012) and Obenberger et al. (2014a), have been derived from the <lb/>detection of one or more transients. The others are limits placed with no detections. Right panel: The same plot as the left panel, but now the flux density <lb/>axis has been collapsed to clearly show the surface density and time-scale comparison. The surveys included are as follows: Hyman et al. (2005, 2006, 2009) <lb/>(Hym2009); Lazio et al. (2010) (Laz2010); Jaeger et al. (2012) (Jae2012); Bell et al. (2014) (Bel2014); Obenberger et al. (2014a) (Obe2014); Carbone et al. <lb/>(2015) (Car2015) and Cendes et al. (2015) (Cen2015). <lb/> ods such as creating mosaic fields. This can be especially true in <lb/>gigahertz surveys. However, the low-frequency searches presented <lb/>here as a comparison mostly do have an equal integration and epoch <lb/>time. This is likely due to the large FoV of some of the facilities, <lb/>minimising the need to use multiple observations to cover a large <lb/>fraction of the sky. <lb/>The cadence of the observations can also be just as valid <lb/>as a defining characteristic. Taking this work as an example, the <lb/>NCP search is also sensitive to slow transients that could evolve <lb/>on time-scales of days, up to the maximum time between two <lb/>observations of four months. Thus, to avoid the complex visual that <lb/>would be required to represent all this information, we compare <lb/>the surveys based upon their respective epoch times (see Carbone <lb/>et al. 2015 for the alternate cadence comparison). The left panel of <lb/>Figure 16 shows the same plot as in Figure 15; however, a z-axis <lb/>of time-scales has now been included to display which areas of <lb/>the time-scale parameter space have been surveyed. The surveys <lb/>included are the same which have previously been used and are <lb/>summarised in Table 5. The right panel of Figure 16 presents <lb/>the same information but with the flux density axis collapsed, to <lb/>clearly show the surface density against time-scale comparison. <lb/>What we see from this comparison is a clear definition of sur-<lb/>face densities at the time-scales of minutes to hours within a range <lb/>of sensitivities from the millijansky level to tens of jansky, which <lb/>does improve upon the Lazio et al. (2010) surface density. It also <lb/>becomes apparent that there is a region of sensitivities – the jansky– <lb/>millijanksy regime – that is yet to be explored at all time-scales. <lb/>Jaeger et al. (2012) is currently the only survey to have probed to <lb/>a ∼ 1 mJy depth at low frequencies, and with a detected transient, <lb/>this perhaps hints at the potential of further discoveries at these <lb/>depths. Improving the sensitivity at shorter time-scales is also an <lb/>area that could prove fruitful in transient searches. <lb/> 7 CONCLUSIONS <lb/> In this paper, we have presented the results of a search for transient <lb/>or variable sources at 60 MHz using the International LOFAR <lb/>Telescope. The search was centred at the North Celestial Pole, <lb/>covering 175 deg  2  of sky with a bandwidth of 195 kHz and con-<lb/>ducted over the period 2011 December–2012 April. The search for <lb/>transients and variables was performed using the automated, newly <lb/>developed, Transients Pipeline (TRAP). No transient or variable <lb/>sources were discovered at time-scales of 30 seconds, 2 minutes, <lb/>55 minutes and 297 minutes. However, several candidates were <lb/>discovered at the 11-minute time-scale. After extensive testing to <lb/>check if these objects were due to calibration or imaging errors, one <lb/>of these candidates is considered to be a real astrophysical event, <lb/>based on the available data. The transient, ILT J225347+862146, <lb/>was seen only in one 11 minute epoch out of 1897, implying a <lb/>transient rate of 3.9  +14.7 <lb/> −3.7  × 10  −4  day  −1  deg  −2  . While complicated <lb/>by the processing strategy, the flux density of the event is believed <lb/>to be in the range of 15–25 Jy and was most active for an estimated <lb/>time of four minutes. However, the rise or decay time-scale of the <lb/>event is not sufficiently well defined such that the full duration of <lb/>activity could extend to a 10-minute time-scale. <lb/>At present, we are unable to determine the astrophysical origin <lb/>of ILT J225347+862146. There are no recorded objects at the tran-<lb/>sient position in previous radio or high-energy catalogues. Optical <lb/>follow-up observations were performed at the transient position, <lb/>with 20 objects detected within the 1-arcminute-radius error circle. <lb/>None of these optical sources showed any short or long-term vari-<lb/>ability and no immediately obvious counterpart was identified in <lb/>the field. However, the discovery of this transient two years after it <lb/>was active diminishes the effectiveness of follow-up observations, <lb/>highlighting the need for real-time transient searches and follow-<lb/>up. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> A low-frequency transient near the NCP </note>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body> We considered the possibility of the transient being a flare star <lb/>event, due to the likely close proximity of the object. However, <lb/>the time-scale of the burst is an order of magnitude longer than <lb/>what would be expected from previous observations of flare stars <lb/>at low frequencies. We also considered whether the event could be <lb/>an FRB. While the duration of the event is consistent with a scat-<lb/>tered burst at 1.3 GHz extrapolated to 60 MHz, it was considered <lb/>unlikely due to the transient exhibiting a much larger fluence than <lb/>would be expected from previously seen FRBs, which would re-<lb/>quire a very steep spectral index (α &lt; −4.7) to be plausible. <lb/>With LOFAR and other instruments now fully operational, the <lb/>low-frequency transient sky is being probed to depths that have <lb/>never previously been achieved. If the discovered transient pre-<lb/>sented in this paper is a member of a real population, then there <lb/>is no question that more will be found in future and current dedi-<lb/>cated transient surveys. This is especially true with ever improving <lb/>calibration techniques and more accurate sky models at these low <lb/>frequencies, combined with these surveys taking advantage of the <lb/>full capabilities of these new, current generation telescopes. <lb/> </body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/> A.J.S., J.W.B., T.E.H., T.M.-D., T.D.S. and M.P. acknowledge sup-<lb/>port from the European Research Council via Advanced Investiga-<lb/>tor Grant no. 267697 4 π sky: Extreme Astrophysics with Rev-<lb/>olutionary Radio Telescopes (PI: R.P. Fender). T.M.-D. also ac-<lb/>knowledges support by the Spanish Ministerio de Economia y com-<lb/>petitividad (MINECO) under grant AYA2013-42627. A.R., J.D.S., <lb/>G.J.M., D.C., Y.C. and A.J.vdH. acknowledge support from the <lb/>European Research Council via Advanced Investigator Grant no. <lb/>247295 (PI: R.A.M.J. Wijers). B.S. acknowlegdes partial funding <lb/>from the research programme of the Netherlands eScience Cen-<lb/>ter (www.nlesc.nl). T.L.G. acknowledges support from the South <lb/>African Research Chairs Initiative of the Department of Science <lb/>and Technology and National Research Foundation. S.C. acknowl-<lb/>edges financial support from the UnivEarthS Labex program of <lb/>Sorbonne Paris Cité (ANR-10-LABX-0023 and ANR-11-IDEX-<lb/>0005-02). J.W.T.H. acknowledges funding from an NWO Vidi fel-<lb/>lowship and from the European Research Council under the Eu-<lb/>ropean Union&apos;s Seventh Framework Programme (FP/2007-2013) / <lb/>ERC Starting Grant agreement nr. 337062 (&quot;DRAGNET&quot;). <lb/>We would like to warmly thank LOFAR Science Support for <lb/>their efforts during commissioning and the continued support of <lb/>handling and processing LOFAR data. The authors would also like <lb/>to thank Rachel Osten for helpful discussions during the project, <lb/>along with the anonymous referee for their insightful comments <lb/>and suggestions that improved the presentation of this paper. <lb/>LOFAR, the Low Frequency Array designed and constructed <lb/>by ASTRON, has facilities in several countries, that are owned by <lb/>various parties (each with their own funding sources), and that are <lb/>collectively operated by the International LOFAR Telescope (ILT) <lb/>foundation under a joint scientific policy. <lb/>The Liverpool Telescope is operated on the island of La Palma <lb/>by Liverpool John Moores University in the Spanish Observatorio <lb/>del Roque de los Muchachos of the Instituto de Astrofisica de Ca-<lb/>narias with financial support from the UK Science and Technology <lb/>Facilities Council. <lb/>This research has made use of the SIMBAD database and the <lb/>VizieR catalogue access tool, operated at CDS, Strasbourg, France. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> REFERENCES <lb/> Abdul-Aziz H., et al., 1995, A&amp;AS, 114, 509 <lb/>Anderson G. E., et al., 2014, MNRAS, 440, 2059 <lb/>Aoki T., et al., 2014, ApJ, 781, 10 <lb/>Asad K. M. B., et al., 2015, MNRAS, 451, 3709 <lb/>Bannister K. W., Murphy T., Gaensler B. M., Hunstead R. W., Chatterjee <lb/>S., 2011, MNRAS, 412, 634 <lb/>Bastian T. S., 1990, Sol. Phys., 130, 265 <lb/>Bastian T. S., Benz A. O., Gary D. E., 1998, ARA&amp;A, 36, 131 <lb/>Bell M. E., et al., 2014, MNRAS, 438, 352 <lb/>Boiko A. I., Konovalenko A. A., Koliadin V. L., Melnik V. N., 2012, Ad-<lb/>vances in Astronomy and Space Physics, 2, 121 <lb/>Bower G. C., Saul D., Bloom J. S., Bolatto A., Filippenko A. V., Foley R. J., <lb/>Perley D., 2007, ApJ, 666, 346 <lb/>Bridle A. H., Schwab F. R., 1999, in Taylor G. B., Carilli C. L., Perley <lb/>R. A., eds, Astronomical Society of the Pacific Conference Series Vol. <lb/>180, Synthesis Imaging in Radio Astronomy II. p. 371 <lb/>Briggs D. S., 1995, in American Astronomical Society Meeting Abstracts. <lb/>p. 112.02 <lb/>Burke-Spolaor S., Bannister K. W., 2014, ApJ, 792, 19 <lb/>Camilo F., Ransom S. M., Chatterjee S., Johnston S., Demorest P., 2012, <lb/>ApJ, 746, 63 <lb/>Carbone D., et al., 2015, preprint, (arXiv:1411.7928) <lb/>Cendes Y., et al., 2015, preprint, (arXiv:1412.3986) <lb/>Coenen T., et al., 2014, A&amp;A, 570, A60 <lb/>Cohen A., 2004, Long Wavelength Array Memo, 17 <lb/>Cohen A. S., Lane W. M., Cotton W. D., Kassim N. E., Lazio T. J. W., <lb/>Perley R. A., Condon J. J., Erickson W. C., 2007, AJ, 134, 1245 <lb/>Condon J. J., 1997, PASP, 109, 166 <lb/>Condon J. J., Cotton W. D., Greisen E. W., Yin Q. F., Perley R. A., Taylor <lb/>G. B., Broderick J. J., 1998, AJ, 115, 1693 <lb/>Cordes J. M., Lazio T. J. W., 2003, ArXiv Astrophysics e-prints, <lb/>Cornwell T., Fomalont E. B., 1999, in Taylor G. B., Carilli C. L., Perley <lb/>R. A., eds, Astronomical Society of the Pacific Conference Series Vol. <lb/>180, Synthesis Imaging in Radio Astronomy II. p. 187 <lb/>Croft S., Bower G. C., Keating G., Law C., Whysong D., Williams P. K. G., <lb/>Wright M., 2011, ApJ, 731, 34 <lb/>Dewdney P. E., Hall P. J., Schilizzi R. T., Lazio T. J. L. W., 2009, IEEE <lb/>Proceedings, 97, 1482 <lb/>Ellingson S. W., Craig J., Dowell J., Taylor G. B., Helmboldt J. F., 2013, <lb/>preprint, (arXiv:1307.0697) <lb/>Falcke H., Rezzolla L., 2014, A&amp;A, 562, A137 <lb/>Fender R. P., Bell M. E., 2011, Bulletin of the Astronomical Society of <lb/>India, 39, 315 <lb/>Fender R., Stewart A., Macquart J.-P., Donnarumma I., Murphy T., Deller <lb/>A., Paragi Z., Chatterjee S., 2015, preprint, (arXiv:1507.00729) <lb/>Frail D. A., Kulkarni S. R., Ofek E. O., Bower G. C., Nakar E., 2012, ApJ, <lb/>747, 70 <lb/>Gal-Yam A., et al., 2006, ApJ, 639, 331 <lb/>Gehrels N., 1986, ApJ, 303, 336 <lb/>Gershberg R. E., Katsova M. M., Lovkaya M. N., Terebizh A. V., <lb/>Shakhovskaya N. I., 1999, A&amp;AS, 139, 555 <lb/>Grobler T. L., Nunhokee C. D., Smirnov O. M., van Zyl A. J., de Bruyn <lb/>A. G., 2014, MNRAS, 439, 4030 <lb/>Güdel M., 2002, ARA&amp;A, 40, 217 <lb/>Gudel M., Benz A. O., Bastian T. S., Furst E., Simnett G. M., Davis R. J., <lb/>1989, A&amp;A, 220, L5 <lb/>Hankins T. H., Kern J. S., Weatherall J. C., Eilek J. A., 2003, Nature, 422, <lb/>141 <lb/>Hassall T. E., Keane E. F., Fender R. P., 2013, MNRAS, 436, 371 <lb/>Heald G. H., et al., 2015, A&amp;A, 582, A123 <lb/>Holwerda B. W., et al., 2014, ApJ, 788, 77 <lb/>Horiuchi S., et al., 2004, ApJ, 616, 110 <lb/>Hueso R., et al., 2010, ApJ, 721, L129 <lb/>Hyman S. D., Lazio T. J. W., Kassim N. E., Bartleson A. L., 2002, AJ, 123, <lb/>1497 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) <lb/></note>

			<page> 22 </page>

			<note place="headnote">Stewart et al. <lb/></note>

			<listBibl> Hyman S. D., Lazio T. J. W., Kassim N. E., Ray P. S., Markwardt C. B., <lb/>Yusef-Zadeh F., 2005, Nature, 434, 50 <lb/>Hyman S. D., Lazio T. J. W., Roy S., Ray P. S., Kassim N. E., Neureuther <lb/>J. L., 2006, ApJ, 639, 348 <lb/>Hyman S. D., Wijnands R., Lazio T. J. W., Pal S., Starling R., Kassim N. E., <lb/>Ray P. S., 2009, ApJ, 696, 280 <lb/>Jackson P. D., Kundu M. R., Kassim N., 1990, Sol. Phys., 130, 391 <lb/>Jaeger T. R., Hyman S. D., Kassim N. E., Lazio T. J. W., 2012, AJ, 143, 96 <lb/>Kashiyama K., Ioka K., Mészáros P., 2013, ApJ, 776, L39 <lb/>Keane E. F., Kramer M., Lyne A. G., Stappers B. W., McLaughlin M. A., <lb/>2011, MNRAS, 415, 3065 <lb/>Kellermann K. I., Pauliny-Toth I. I. K., 1969, ApJ, 155, L71 <lb/>Klebesadel R. W., Strong I. B., Olson R. A., 1973, ApJ, 182, L85 <lb/>Kovalev Y. Y., et al., 2005, AJ, 130, 2473 <lb/>Kramer M., Lyne A. G., O&apos;Brien J. T., Jordan C. A., Lorimer D. R., 2006, <lb/>Science, 312, 549 <lb/>Kulkarni S. R., et al., 1999, ApJ, 522, L97 <lb/>Kulkarni S. R., Ofek E. O., Neill J. D., Zheng Z., Juric M., 2014, ApJ, 797, <lb/>70 <lb/>Lane W. M., Cotton W. D., van Velzen S., Clarke T. E., Kassim N. E., Helm-<lb/>boldt J. F., Lazio T. J. W., Cohen A. S., 2014, MNRAS, 440, 327 <lb/>Law C. J., et al., 2015, ApJ, 807, 16 <lb/>Lazio T. J. W., et al., 2010, AJ, 140, 1995 <lb/>Leahy J. P., Perley R. A., 1991, AJ, 102, 537 <lb/>Loeb A., Shvartzvald Y., Maoz D., 2014, MNRAS, 439, L46 <lb/>Lorimer D. R., Bailes M., McLaughlin M. A., Narkevic D. J., Crawford F., <lb/>2007, Science, 318, 777 <lb/>Lorimer D. R., Karastergiou A., McLaughlin M. A., Johnston S., 2013, MN-<lb/>RAS, 436, L5 <lb/>Lovell B., 1969, Nature, 222, 1126 <lb/>Macquart J.-P., 2014, Publ. Astron. Soc. Australia, 31, 31 <lb/>Matthews T. A., Sandage A. R., 1963, ApJ, 138, 30 <lb/>McKean J., et al., 2011, preprint, (arXiv:1106.1041) <lb/>McLaughlin M. A., et al., 2006, Nature, 439, 817 <lb/>McMullin J. P., Waters B., Schiebel D., Young W., Golap K., 2007, in Shaw <lb/>R. A., Hill F., Bell D. J., eds, Astronomical Society of the Pacific Con-<lb/>ference Series Vol. 376, Astronomical Data Analysis Software and Sys-<lb/>tems XVI. p. 127 <lb/>Metzger B. D., Williams P. K. G., Berger E., 2015, ApJ, 806, 224 <lb/>Mingaliev M. G., Sotnikova Y. V., Kardashev N. S., Larionov M. G., 2009, <lb/>Astronomy Reports, 53, 487 <lb/>Monet D. G., et al., 2003, AJ, 125, 984 <lb/>Mottez F., Zarka P., 2014, A&amp;A, 569, A86 <lb/>Niinuma K., et al., 2007, ApJ, 657, L37 <lb/>Notsu Y., et al., 2013, ApJ, 771, 127 <lb/>Obenberger K. S., et al., 2014a, ApJ, 785, 27 <lb/>Obenberger K. S., et al., 2014b, ApJ, 788, L26 <lb/>Ofek E. O., Breslauer B., Gal-Yam A., Frail D., Kasliwal M. M., Kulkarni <lb/>S. R., Waxman E., 2010, ApJ, 711, 517 <lb/>Ofek E. O., Frail D. A., Breslauer B., Kulkarni S. R., Chandra P., Gal-Yam <lb/>A., Kasliwal M. M., Gehrels N., 2011, ApJ, 740, 65 <lb/>Offringa A. R., de Bruyn A. G., Biehl M., Zaroubi S., Bernardi G., Pandey <lb/>V. N., 2010, MNRAS, 405, 155 <lb/>Offringa A. R., de Bruyn A. G., Zaroubi S., 2012a, MNRAS, 422, 563 <lb/>Offringa A. R., van de Gronde J. J., Roerdink J. B. T. M., 2012b, A&amp;A, <lb/>539, A95 <lb/>Osten R. A., Hawley S. L., Allred J., Johns-Krull C. M., Brown A., Harper <lb/>G. M., 2006, ApJ, 647, 1349 <lb/>Pandey V. N., van Zwieten J. E., de Bruyn A. G., Nijboer R., 2009, in Saikia <lb/>D. J., Green D. A., Gupta Y., Venturi T., eds, Astronomical Society <lb/>of the Pacific Conference Series Vol. 407, The Low-Frequency Radio <lb/>Universe. p. 384 <lb/>Petroff E., et al., 2015, MNRAS, 447, 246 <lb/>Pietka M., Fender R. P., Keane E. F., 2015, MNRAS, 446, 3687 <lb/>Ravi V., Shannon R. M., Jameson A., 2015, ApJ, 799, L5 <lb/>Rengelink R. B., Tang Y., de Bruyn A. G., Miley G. K., Bremer M. N., <lb/>Roettgering H. J. A., Bremer M. A. R., 1997, A&amp;AS, 124, 259 <lb/>Scaife A. M. M., Heald G. H., 2012, MNRAS, 423, L30 <lb/>Schaefer B. E., King J. R., Deliyannis C. P., 2000, ApJ, 529, 1026 <lb/>Scheers L. H. A., 2011, PhD thesis, University of Amsterdam <lb/>Skrutskie M. F., et al., 2006, AJ, 131, 1163 <lb/>Smith H. J., Hoffleit D., 1963, AJ, 68, 292 <lb/>Spitler L. G., et al., 2014, ApJ, 790, 101 <lb/>Spreeuw J. N., 2010, PhD thesis, University of Amsterdam <lb/>Steele I. A., et al., 2004, in Oschmann Jr. J. M., ed., Society of Photo-<lb/>Optical Instrumentation Engineers (SPIE) Conference Series Vol. 5489, <lb/>Ground-based Telescopes. pp 679–692, doi:10.1117/12.551456 <lb/>Swinbank J. D., et al., 2015, Astronomy and Computing, 11, 25 <lb/>Tasse C., van der Tol S., van Zwieten J., van Diepen G., Bhatnagar S., 2013, <lb/>A&amp;A, 553, A105 <lb/>Thornton D., et al., 2013, Science, 341, 53 <lb/>Tingay S. J., et al., 2013, Publ. Astron. Soc. Australia, 30, 7 <lb/>Totani T., 2013, PASJ, 65, L12 <lb/>Williams P. K. G., Bower G. C., Croft S., Keating G. K., Law C. J., Wright <lb/>M. C. H., 2013, ApJ, 762, 85 <lb/>Wright E. L., et al., 2010, AJ, 140, 1868 <lb/>Yatawatta S., et al., 2013, A&amp;A, 550, A136 <lb/>Zhang B., 2014, ApJ, 780, L21 <lb/>van Haarlem M. P., et al., 2013, A&amp;A, 556, A2 <lb/>van Paradijs J., et al., 1997, Nature, 386, 686 <lb/>van der Laan H., 1966, Nature, 211, 1131 <lb/>van der Tol S. ., Jeffs B. D., van der Veen A.-J. ., 2007, IEEE Transactions <lb/>on Signal Processing, 55, 4497 <lb/></listBibl>

			<front> 1  Astrophysics, Department of Physics, University of Oxford, Keble <lb/>Road, Oxford OX1 3RH, UK <lb/> 2  Physics and Astronomy, University of Southampton, Highfield, <lb/>Southampton, SO17 1BJ, UK <lb/> 3  ASTRON, the Netherlands Institute for Radio Astronomy, Postbus <lb/>2, 7990 AA Dwingeloo, The Netherlands <lb/> 4  Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias, 38200 La Laguna, Tenerife, <lb/>Spain <lb/> 5  Departamento de astrofísica, Univ. de La Laguna, E-38206 La <lb/>Laguna, Tenerife, Spain <lb/> 6  Anton Pannekoek Institute for Astronomy, Science Park 904, 1098 <lb/>XH Amsterdam, The Netherlands <lb/> 7  Department of Astrophysical Sciences, Princeton University, <lb/>Princeton, NJ 08544, USA <lb/> 8  Department of Physics &amp; Electronics, Rhodes University, PO Box <lb/>94, Grahamstown, 6140 South Africa <lb/> 9  Centrum Wiskunde &amp; Informatica, Science Park 123, 1098 XG <lb/>Amsterdam, The Netherlands <lb/> 10  SKA South Africa, 3rd Floor, The Park, Park Road, Pinelands, <lb/>Cape Town 7405, South Africa <lb/> 11  Kapteyn Astronomical Institute, P.O. Box 800, 9700 AV Gronin-<lb/>gen, The Netherlands <lb/> 12  CSIRO Astronomy and Space Science, PO Box 76, Epping, NSW <lb/>1710, Australia <lb/> 13  ARC Centre of Excellence for All-sky Astrophysics (CAASTRO), <lb/>The University of Sydney, NSW 2006, Australia <lb/> 14  Universität Hamburg, Hamburger Sternwarte, Gojenbergsweg <lb/>112, 21029, Hamburg, Germany <lb/> 15  Jodrell Bank Center for Astrophysics, School of Physics and As-<lb/>tronomy, The University of Manchester, Manchester M13 9PL,UK <lb/> 16  Laboratoire AIM (CEA/IRFU -CNRS/INSU -Université Paris <lb/>Diderot), CEA DSM/IRFU/SAp, F-91191 Gif-sur-Yvette, France <lb/> 17  Station de Radioastronomie de Nançay, Observatoire de Paris, <lb/>PSL Research University, CNRS, Univ. Orléans, OSUC, 18330 <lb/>Nançay, France <lb/> 18  Thüringer Landessternwarte, Sternwarte 5, D-07778 Tauten-<lb/>burg, Germany <lb/> 19  Department of Astrophysics/IMAPP, Radboud University Ni-<lb/> </front>

			<note place="headnote">MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) <lb/> A low-frequency transient near the NCP </note>

			<page>23 <lb/> </page>

			<front>jmegen, P.O. Box 9010, 6500 GL Nijmegen, The Netherlands <lb/> 20  Laboratoire Lagrange, UMR 7293, Université de Nice Sophia– <lb/>Antipolis, CNRS, Observatoire de la Côte dâ ˘ <lb/>A ´ <lb/>ZAzur, 06300 Nice, <lb/>France <lb/> 21  LPC2E -Universite d&apos;Orleans/CNRS <lb/> 22  School of Physics, Astronomy and Mathematics, University of <lb/>Hertfordshire, College Lane, Hatfield AL10 9AB, UK <lb/> 23  Max-Planck-Institut für Radioastronomie, Auf dem Hügel 69, <lb/>53121 Bonn, Germany <lb/> 24  SRON Netherlands Insitute for Space Research, PO Box 800, <lb/>9700 AV Groningen, The Netherlands <lb/> 25  Astro Space Center of the Lebedev Physical Institute, Profsoyuz-<lb/>naya str. 84/32, Moscow 117997, Russia <lb/> 26  NAOJ Chile Observatory, National Astronomical Observatory of <lb/>Japan, 2-21-1 Osawa, Mitaka, Tokyo 181-8588, Japan <lb/> 27  Department of Astronomy and Radio Astronomy Lab, University <lb/>of California, Berkeley, CA, USA <lb/> 28  International Centre for Radio Astronomy Research -Curtin <lb/>University, GPO Box U1987, Perth, WA 6845, Australia <lb/> 29  Centre de Recherche Astrophysique de Lyon, Observatoire de <lb/>Lyon, 9 av Charles Andr Ì ˛ <lb/>Ae, 69561 Saint Genis Laval Cedex, <lb/>France <lb/> 30  School of Chemical &amp; Physical Sciences, Victoria University of <lb/>Wellington, PO Box 600, Wellington 6140, New Zealand <lb/> 31  School of Physics and Astronomy, Monash University, PO Box <lb/>27, Clayton, Victoria 3800, Australia <lb/> 32  Leiden Observatory, Leiden University, PO Box 9513, 2300 RA <lb/>Leiden, The Netherlands <lb/> 33  GEPI, Observatoire de Paris, CNRS, Université Paris Diderot, <lb/>5 place Jules Janssen, 92190, Meudon, France <lb/> 34  Department of Physics, The George Washington University, 725 <lb/>21st Street NW, Washington, DC 20052, USA <lb/> 35  Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics, 60 Garden Street, <lb/>Cambridge, MA 02138, USA <lb/> 36  LESIA, Observatoire de Paris, CNRS, UPMC, Université Paris-<lb/>Diderot, 5 place Jules Janssen, 92195 Meudon, France <lb/> 37  Space Telescope Science Institute, 3700 San Martin Drive, Bal-<lb/>timore, MD 21218, USA <lb/> 38  Helmholtz-Zentrum Potsdam, DeutschesGeoForschungsZen-<lb/>trum GFZ, Department 1: Geodesy and Remote Sensing, Tele-<lb/>grafenberg, A17, 14473 Potsdam, Germany <lb/> 39  Shell Technology Center, Bangalore, India <lb/> 40  University of Twente, The Netherlands <lb/> 41  Institute for Astronomy, University of Edinburgh, Royal Obser-<lb/>vatory of Edinburgh, Blackford Hill, Edinburgh EH9 3HJ, UK <lb/> 42  Leibniz-Institut für Astrophysik Potsdam (AIP), An der Stern-<lb/>warte 16, 14482 Potsdam, Germany <lb/> 43  Research School of Astronomy and Astrophysics, Australian Na-<lb/>tional University, Mt Stromlo Obs., via Cotter Road, Weston, A.C.T. <lb/>2611, Australia <lb/> 44  Max Planck Institute for Astrophysics, Karl Schwarzschild Str. <lb/>1, 85741 Garching, Germany <lb/> 45  Onsala Space Observatory, Dept. of Earth and Space Sciences, <lb/>Chalmers University of Technology, SE-43992 Onsala, Sweden <lb/> 46  SmarterVision BV, Oostersingel 5, 9401 JX Assen <lb/> 47  Astronomisches Institut der Ruhr-Universität Bochum, Univer-<lb/>sitaetsstrasse 150, 44780 Bochum, Germany <lb/> 48  Sodankylä Geophysical Observatory, University of Oulu, <lb/>Tähteläntie 62, 99600 Sodankylä, Finland <lb/> 49  STFC Rutherford Appleton Laboratory, Harwell Science and In-<lb/>novation Campus, Didcot OX11 0QX, UK <lb/> 50  Center for Information Technology (CIT), University of Gronin-<lb/>gen, The Netherlands <lb/> 51  Fakultät für Physik, Universität Bielefeld, Postfach 100131, D-<lb/>33501, Bielefeld, Germany <lb/></front>

			<div type="annex"> This paper has been typeset from a T E X/L A T E X file prepared by the author. <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">MNRAS 000, 1–23 (2015) </note>


	</text>
</tei>
