<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Gene family information facilitates variant interpretation and identification of <lb/>disease-associated genes <lb/>Dennis Lal* 1,2,3,4,# , Patrick May* 5 , Kaitlin E. Samocha 1,2 , Jack A. Kosmicki 1,2 , Elise <lb/>B. Robinson 1,2,6 , Rikke S. Møller 7,8 , Roland Krause 5 , Peter Nürnberg 3,9,10 , Sarah <lb/>Weckhuysen 11,12,13 , Peter De Jonghe 11 , Renzo Guerrini 14 , Lisa M. Neupert 3 , <lb/>Juliana Du 3 , Eduardo Perez-Palma 3 , Carla Marini 14 , EuroEpinomics RES-<lb/>consortium, James S. Ware 15 , Mitja Kurki 1,2,4 , Padhraig Gormley 1,2,4 , Sha Tang 16 , <lb/>Sitao Wu 16 , Saskia Biskup 17 , Annapura Poduri 18 , Bernd A. Neubauer 19 , Bobby P. <lb/>C. Koeleman 20 , Katherine L. Helbig 16 , Yvonne G. Weber 21 , Ingo Helbig 22,23 , Amit <lb/>R. Majithia 24 , Aarno Palotie 1,2,4,25 , Mark J. Daly 1,2# <lb/>1 Stanley Center for Psychiatric Research, The Broad Institute of Harvard and M.I.T, Cambridge, <lb/>MA, USA <lb/>2 Analytic and Translational Genetics Unit, Massachusetts General Hospital, Boston, MA, USA <lb/>3 Cologne Center for Genomics, University of Cologne, Cologne, Germany <lb/>4 Psychiatric and Neurodevelopmental Genetics Unit, Department of Psychiatry, Massachusetts <lb/>General Hospital, Boston, USA <lb/>5 Luxembourg Centre for Systems Biomedicine, University of Luxembourg, Esch-sur-Alzette, <lb/>Luxembourg <lb/>6 Department of Epidemiology, Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health, Boston MA <lb/>7 The Danish Epilepsy Centre, Dianalund, Denmark <lb/>8 Institute for Regional Health research, University of Southern Denmark, Odense, Denmark <lb/>9 Center for Molecular Medicine Cologne, University of Cologne, Cologne, Germany <lb/>10 Cologne Excellence Cluster on Cellular Stress Responses in Aging-Associated Diseases, <lb/>University of Cologne, Cologne, Germany <lb/>11 Division of Neurology, Antwerp University Hospital, Antwerp, Belgium <lb/>12 Neurogenetics Group, Center for Molecular Neurology, VIB, Antwerp, Belgium <lb/>13 Laboratory of Neurogenetics, Institute Born-Bunge, University of Antwerp, Antwerp, Belgium <lb/>14 Pediatric Neurology Unit, A. Meyer Pediatric Hospital, Florence, Italy <lb/>15 National Heart &amp; Lung Institute and MRC London Institute of Medical Science, Imperial <lb/>College London, UK <lb/>16 Division of Clinical Genomics, Ambry Genetics, Aliso Viejo, California, USA <lb/>17 Department of Neurology and Epileptology, Hertie Insitute for Clinical Brain Research, <lb/>University of Tübingen, Tübingen, Germany <lb/>18 Epilepsy Genetics Program, Boston Children&apos;s Hospital, Boston, MA, USA <lb/>19 Department of Neuropediatrics UKGM, University of Giessen, Germany <lb/>20 Department of Genetics, University Medical Center Utrecht, Utrecht, The Netherlands <lb/>21 Department of Neurology and Epileptology, Hertie Institute for Clinical Brain Research , <lb/>University of Tübingen , Germany. <lb/>22 Division of Neurology, The Children&apos;s Hospital of Philadelphia, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, <lb/>USA <lb/>23 Department of Neuropediatrics, University Medical Center Schleswig-Holstein, Christian-<lb/>Albrechts University, Kiel, Germany <lb/>24 Diabetes Research Center, Diabetes Unit, Department of Medicine, Massachusetts General <lb/>Hospital, Boston, Massachusetts, USA <lb/>25 Institute for Molecular Medicine Finland, University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland <lb/>* equally contributing first authors <lb/># corresponding author <lb/>Address for Correspondence: <lb/>Mark J. Daly <lb/>Chief, Analytic and Translational Genetics Unit <lb/>Massachusetts General Hospital, Boston, US <lb/>617-643-3290 <lb/>mjdaly@atgu.mgh.harvard.edu <lb/>Dennis Lal <lb/>Stanley Center for Psychiatric Research <lb/>Broad Institute of Harvard and M.I.T, Cambridge, US <lb/>617-714-8527 <lb/>Dlal@Broadinstitute.org <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Differentiating risk-conferring from benign missense variants, and therefore <lb/>optimal calculation of gene-variant burden, represent a major challenge in <lb/>particular for rare and genetic heterogeneous disorders. While orthologous gene <lb/>conservation is commonly employed in variant annotation, approximately 80% of <lb/>known disease-associated genes are paralogs and belong to gene families. It <lb/>has not been thoroughly investigated how gene family information can be utilized <lb/>for disease gene discovery and variant interpretation. We developed a paralog <lb/>conservation score to empirically evaluate whether paralog conserved or non-<lb/>conserved sites of in-human paralogs are important for protein function. Using <lb/>this score, we demonstrate that disease-associated missense variants are <lb/>significantly enriched at paralog conserved sites across all disease groups and <lb/>disease inheritance models tested. Next, we assessed whether gene family <lb/>information could assist in discovering novel disease-associated genes. We <lb/>subsequently developed a gene family de novo enrichment framework that <lb/>identified 43 exome-wide enriched gene families including 98 de novo variant <lb/>carrying genes in more than 10k neurodevelopmental disorder patients. 33 gene <lb/>family enriched genes represent novel candidate genes which are brain <lb/>expressed and variant constrained in neurodevelopmental disorders. <lb/></front>

			<body>Identifying disease-causing mutations from the vast sea of benign rare variants in <lb/>a genome continues to be an important challenge in both clinical and research <lb/>settings despite the availability of large-scale population sequence references 1,2 . <lb/>While functional studies would be the gold standard for determining causality, <lb/>they are expensive, time consuming, and require extensive expert knowledge. <lb/>Even in the case of coding variants, appropriate assays testing the disease-<lb/>relevant impact of a variant on gene function are not readily available for the <lb/>majority of genes and variants. Because of these limitations, in silico prediction <lb/>tools have become the method of choice. These tools predict the deleteriousness <lb/>of variants by assessing sequence conservation between species, structural <lb/>constraints, amino acid physiochemical properties, and/or known annotations 3-5 . <lb/>Sequence conservation, in which mammalian or vertebrate genomes are aligned <lb/>to identify conserved segments among orthologs has been a component of <lb/>nearly every such method, under the sensible premise that since genes often <lb/>retain function through evolution, those genic elements that remain constant <lb/>throughout evolution are more likely essential to gene function. The high average <lb/>sequence similarity of homologs of disease-associated genes often translates <lb/>into high conservation and therefore higher pathogenicity scores for in silico <lb/>prediction tools based on vertical conservation profiles (Fig. 1 left). <lb/>Frequently overlooked, however, is the sequence conservation within species <lb/>available from paralogous genes. Paralogs are defined as genes related via <lb/>ancient duplication events 6-8 . Paralogous sequences are often utilized in <lb/>alignments together with orthologous sequences in several variant prediction <lb/>methods. However, the contribution of human paralogous sequences in variant <lb/>annotation has not been thoroughly explored. Moreover, most of these methods <lb/>rely on trained multi-feature classifier, which do not allow biological interpretation <lb/>of results. Paralogs within gene families show often a relatively high sequence <lb/>divergence. This greater variance among paralogs in comparison to orthologs, <lb/>reflecting deeper evolutionary roots of some duplication events, suggests an <lb/>unexplored opportunity that might aid in classifying residues as more or less <lb/>functionally important (Fig. 1 right) based on their horizontal conservation profiles <lb/>within gene families. The human genome harbors 3,348 protein-coding gene <lb/>families, ranging from 2 to 46 paralog members and accounting for 72% of all <lb/>human protein-coding genes (ENSEMBL v20150512). It has been shown that <lb/>approximately 80% of disease-associated genes have paralogs in human 9 . <lb/>Figure 1: Vertical (ortholog) vs. horizontal (paralog) conservation. Top: Protein sequence <lb/>alignment of voltage-gated sodium channels. Top left: Alignment of Homo sapiens <lb/>(NP_001159435.1), Bos taurus (NP_001180147.1) and Mus musculus (NP_001300926.1) <lb/>SCN1A protein sequences. High sequence similarity is depicted by violet amino acid coloring and <lb/>yellow conservation bars below the alignment using Jalview. Top right: Protein alignment in <lb/>Jalview of all members of the human voltage-gated sodium channel gene family (SCN1A, SCN2A, <lb/>SCN3A, SCN4A, SCN5A, SCN7A, SCN8A, SCN9A, SCN10A, SCN11A). This alignment of <lb/>paralogues shows less conservation compared to the SCN1A vertical cross species alignment on <lb/>the left. Bottom left: GERP score analysis over all genes within gene families (homolog <lb/>conservation is measured by % of all nucleotides per gene with GERP scores &gt;2). Bottom right: <lb/>Distribution % nucleotides per gene within gene families having para_zscores &gt;0. Homolog <lb/>conservation is generally much more uniform and homogeneous than paralog conservation. <lb/>The association of diseases with gene families has been well established in the <lb/>last two decades. For example, protein kinases comprise one of the largest <lb/>families of evolutionarily related proteins and &gt;500 distinct kinases are encoded <lb/>by ~2% of all human genes. Variants in kinase genes have been found to <lb/>underlie many human diseases, particularly developmental and metabolic <lb/>disorders, as well as certain cancers 10 . Another example represents the family of <lb/>keratin genes. Variants in these genes alter the structure of keratins, which <lb/>prevent them from forming an effective network of keratin intermediate filaments. <lb/>Without this network, cells become fragile and are easily damaged, making <lb/>tissues less resistant to friction and minor trauma 11 . More recent large scale <lb/>sequencing studies on neurodevelopmental disorders (NDDs) have <lb/>independently identified multiple paralogous genes associated with the same or <lb/>related NDD (e.g., the family of voltage-gated sodium channel genes: SCN1A, <lb/>SCN2A, SCN8A; the family of chromodomain-helicase-DNA-binding proteins: <lb/>CHD2, CHD4, CHD8 12-15 . This raises the question whether other genes within <lb/>the same gene family are also associated with NDDs. Since in these studies <lb/>truncating variants in paralogs often show consistent associations to NDDs, we <lb/>sought to explore whether paralog information could refine our interpretation of <lb/>missense variation. Paralogs often have similar, but not identical, protein <lb/>sequences (Fig. 1 right) and amino acids conserved across all paralogs might <lb/>well be pointing to essential residues critical for protein function. As such, <lb/>variants changing paralog conserved amino acids may plausibly be more <lb/>deleterious than variants changing amino acids in paralog non-conserved sites <lb/>and therefore be more likely to confer risk to disease. Two previous studies have <lb/>highlighted the utility of systematic functional annotation of disease-causing <lb/>residues across human paralogs for genes associated with Long-QT-syndrome, <lb/>Brugada <lb/>syndrome, <lb/>and <lb/>catecholaminergic <lb/>polymorphic <lb/>ventricular <lb/>tachycardia 16,17 . Both studies showed improved variant interpretation by <lb/>comparing corresponding mutations in paralogs in different patients with the <lb/>same phenotype. To our knowledge, it has not been empirically investigated on <lb/>genome-wide scale whether disease associated missense variants reside in <lb/>paralog conserved or non-conserved sites. <lb/>Statistical power for the discovery of disease associated genes is the greatest in <lb/>genetically homogeneous patient groups. NDDs are phenotypically and <lb/>genetically heterogeneous. Several of the NDD disease-associated genes are <lb/>pleiotropic and appear in clinically distinct NDDs (sub-NDDs) indicating a shared <lb/>molecular pathology. Even in NDD cohorts with &gt;1000 trios, the majority of <lb/>disease-associated genes have fewer than 10 de novo variants 12-15 . To increase <lb/>the statistical power in genetic studies, gene set enrichment analysis is often <lb/>applied to discover pathways associated with diseases of the same or a similar <lb/>phenotype 18,19 . To date, the utility of gene families as gene sets for large-scale <lb/>mutational burden analyses and candidate gene identification has not been <lb/>systematically conducted. <lb/>In this manuscript, we evaluate and develop the use of &apos;paralog conservation&apos; <lb/>and provide evidence that this offers powerful addition to variant annotation over <lb/>and above conventional conservation metrics and other annotations as follows: <lb/>(1) We develop a novel paralog-based conservation score (&quot;para_zscore&quot;, see <lb/>Online Methods and Supplementary Fig. 1) and demonstrate that paralogs <lb/>highlight a smaller, more refined set of conserved residues than conventional <lb/>ortholog conservation. (2) We further empirically demonstrate that disease-<lb/>associated missense variants across all genetic disorders are strongly enriched <lb/>at paralog-conserved sites. (3) We demonstrate that restricting analysis to <lb/>missense variants at only paralog conserved sites increases the power to <lb/>discover novel disease associated genes. (4) Leveraging these observations, we <lb/>create a novel gene-family burden test of association and identify, using a cohort <lb/>of 10,068 NDD trios, gene families with de novo variant burden including novel <lb/>candidate disease genes. <lb/>

			Results <lb/>Allele frequency of paralog conserved and non-conserved sites in the <lb/>general population <lb/>We first sought to test whether paralog conserved amino acids were more likely <lb/>to confer strong disease risk when altered in comparison to sites not conserved <lb/>in paralogs. As an initial test, we correlated the allele frequency of 1.3 million <lb/>missense variants affecting genes with paralogous family members in 60,706 <lb/>reference individuals from the Exome Aggregation Consortium 2 (ExAC) with their <lb/>paralog conservation measured by para_zscore. Testing 1,213,427 amino acids <lb/>across all human gene families, we found that allele frequency decreases with <lb/>increasing paralog conservation, indicating stronger evolutionary selection <lb/>against variation in paralog conserved sites overall (Fig. 2 top left panel). <lb/>To further compare the utility of paralog versus ortholog amino acid conservation, <lb/>we analyzed de novo missense variants identified in 10,068 NDD patients and <lb/>2,078 controls. Using the GERP score we measured the (vertical) divergence <lb/>across 35 mammalian species 20 . Given that only a small fraction of patient <lb/>variants is expected to be associated with disease, we did not expect a major <lb/>shift between the patient and control variant distributions. We did however <lb/>observe a more significant difference between variant scores in patients <lb/>compared to controls using the para_zscore (p&lt;10 -5 ) than we saw for GERP <lb/>(p=.006; Fig. 2 top right panel). <lb/>Paralog conservation of missense de novo mutations in NDD patients and <lb/>controls <lb/>To investigate the degree to which de novo mutations (DNMs) in NDDs are <lb/>enriched in paralog-conserved segments, we compared the variant distribution of <lb/>DNMs in 10,068 NDD patients to 2,078 individuals without NDDs. To increase <lb/>the signal, we excluded those DNMs present in ExAC 2,21 . We compared the <lb/>distributions of para_zscores for synonymous and missense variants (Fig. 2 <lb/>bottom left) expecting only an enrichment for missense variants due to the <lb/>fraction of variants associated with disease. We observe a significant shift <lb/>towards paralog-conserved (P= 2.5 x 10 -6 ) sites for missense DNM variants in <lb/>NDD patients but not in controls (P=0.87). <lb/>Figure 2: Assessment of paralog conservation. Top left: ExAC allele frequency vs. gene <lb/>family (paralog) conservation (given as Z-score). The allele frequency of 1,213,427 missense <lb/>variants decreases with increasing para_zscores for the tested variants. Top right: Ortholog vs. <lb/>paralog conservation of missense variants. Ortholog conservation is measured by GERP scores, <lb/>paralog conservation by para_zscores. Para_zscores better separate patient from control variants <lb/>compared to GERP scores. Higher para_zscores are only slightly enriched in NDD patient <lb/>variants compared to controls, which is in line with the expectation that not all patient de novo <lb/>missense variants contribute to disease. Bottom left: Distribution of NDD patient and control <lb/>missense and synonymous para_zscores depicted by density plots. Patient, but not control, <lb/>missense variants are enriched at paralog conserved sites relative to the synonymous variant <lb/>distribution. P-values were calculated using a Wilcoxon test. Bottom right: Identification of <lb/>missense variant gene family enrichment in NDD patients for paralog conserved missense <lb/>variants but not for the paralog non-conserved variants. NDD associated missense variants are <lb/>enriched in paralog conserved sites. Y-axis: Missense variant enrichment analysis considering <lb/>only paralog non-conserved sites across genes of each gene family (para_zcore ≤0). X-axis: <lb/>Missense variant enrichment analysis considering only paralog conserved sites (para_zcore &gt;0). <lb/>None of the gene families show exome-wide significant enrichment for paralog non-conserved <lb/>sites. 26 gene families (depicted by circles) show exome-wide significant de novo missense <lb/>variant burden at paralog conserved sites. The significance threshold was calculated by <lb/>Bonferroni correction for testing 5 x 2871 gene families (P = 3.48 x 10 <lb/>-6 ) and is depicted by the <lb/>blue dotted line. <lb/>We evaluated the contribution of paralog conserved and non-conserved <lb/>missense variants to NDDs. Considering 2,871 gene families encapsulating <lb/>9,991 genes, we observed 27 significantly enriched (p &lt; 3.48 x 10 -6 ) gene <lb/>families in the patient cohort identified in an analysis of paralog conserved <lb/>missense variants only, but none in the parallel, comparably powered, analysis of <lb/>only non-conserved sites (Fig. 2 bottom right, Supplementary Fig. 1B). <lb/>Although many of these genes also show burden for protein truncating variants <lb/>(PTVs), the paralog enrichment is specific for missense variants since we did not <lb/>identify a shift towards paralog conserved sites for nonsense variants <lb/>(Supplementary Fig. 2). This is in line with expectations because nonsense-<lb/>mediated-decay is the expected disease mechanism. Furthermore, missense <lb/>variant enrichment at paralog conserved sites is not detectable in genes without <lb/>DNM burden in this study (Supplementary Fig. 2). <lb/>Enrichment of missense variants at paralog conserved sites across all <lb/>diseases and associated genes. <lb/>To investigate whether the enrichment for disease variants at paralog conserved <lb/>sites is specific to our NDD cohort or can be generally observed across other <lb/>disease categories, we extracted all missense variants from the ClinVar <lb/>database (accessed June 2016) and classified the disorders into ICD chapters <lb/>and sub-groups. We compared the paralog conservation for all gene families <lb/>harboring disease variants against the missense variants in the same genes from <lb/>ExAC. Overall, we detect a strong enrichment for disease variants at paralog-<lb/>conserved sites compared to ExAC missense variants (P = 2.2 x 10 -287 , shift in <lb/>para_zscore = 0.92, CI=0.87-0.98; Fig. 3). Our analyses indicate that disease-<lb/>associated variants more often affect amino acids that are conserved across all <lb/>members of the gene family. The shift towards paralog conserved sites for <lb/>patient variants in comparison holds true for almost all disease groups tested. <lb/>Figure 3: ClinVar disease vs. ExAC missense variant para_zscore distribution. We scored <lb/>ClinVar variants and variants in a reference population (ExAC) for the same genes in a range of <lb/>disorders and grouped these into ICD10 code defined disorder classes (see Online Methods). <lb/>The distribution of ClinVar variants is shifted towards paralog conserved sites compared to <lb/>missense variants in ExAC as depicted by estimated differences in location plotted in the x-axis <lb/>for the vast majority of disorders tested. The shift to paralog conserved sites is depicted by <lb/>estimates greater zero. P-values were calculated using a Wilcoxon test. <lb/>Gene family enrichment in NDDs and sub-phenotypes <lb/>After establishing that disease-associated missense variants are enriched at <lb/>paralog conserved sites (Fig. 2 bottom right, Fig. 3), we assessed the degree to <lb/>which gene family information could assist in discovering novel disease-<lb/>associated genes. We analyzed again our heterogeneous cohort of 10,068 NDD <lb/>patients with autism spectrum disorder (ASD; N=3982), developmental delay <lb/>(DD; N=5226) and epilepsy (EPI; N=822). We extended the approach of <lb/>Samocha et al., 2014 22 , to gene families to identified gene families with <lb/>significant enrichment of mutations in NDD patients. We included protein <lb/>truncating variants (PTVs) across the whole sequence as well as missense <lb/>variants at paralog conserved protein sites absent from ExAC in the analysis. <lb/>Gene families <lb/>DNMs <lb/>expected <lb/>DNMs <lb/>observed <lb/>P <lb/>5264 DD <lb/>patients <lb/>3982 <lb/>ASD <lb/>patients <lb/>822 EPI <lb/>patients <lb/>2087 <lb/>controls <lb/>ARID1B (40), ARID1A (5) <lb/>0.96 <lb/>45 <lb/>4.28E-58 <lb/>39 <lb/>6 <lb/>0 <lb/>SCN2A (38), SCN1A (18), SCN8A (11), SCN3A (4), <lb/>SCN11A (2), SCN9A (1), SCN5A, SCN7A, SCN4A, <lb/>SCN10A <lb/>6.16 <lb/>74 <lb/>1.77E-52 <lb/>36 <lb/>16 <lb/>22 <lb/>DDX3X (35), DDX3Y <lb/>0.49 <lb/>35 <lb/>8.94E-52 <lb/>34 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>DYRK1A (26), DYRK1B (1) <lb/>0.37 <lb/>27 <lb/>1.89E-40 <lb/>21 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 <lb/>EP300 (20), CREBBP (16) <lb/>1.39 <lb/>36 <lb/>8.81E-38 <lb/>30 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 <lb/>KCNQ2 (23), KCNQ3 (7), KCNQ5 (3) <lb/>1.14 <lb/>33 <lb/>3.09E-36 <lb/>27 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>SYNGAP1 (24), DAB2IP, RASAL2 <lb/>1.33 <lb/>24 <lb/>4.35E-22 <lb/>17 <lb/>6 <lb/>1 <lb/>STXBP1 (20), STXBP3 (1), STXBP2 <lb/>0.88 <lb/>21 <lb/>5.93E-22 <lb/>14 <lb/>2 <lb/>5 <lb/>GRIN2B (16), GRIN2A (6), GRIN2C (1), GRIN2D <lb/>1.89 <lb/>23 <lb/>1.46E-17 <lb/>17 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>CTNNB1 (16), JUP (1) <lb/>0.79 <lb/>17 <lb/>2.27E-17 <lb/>15 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>CHD2 (16), CHD1 (3) <lb/>1.15 <lb/>19 <lb/>4.00E-17 <lb/>10 <lb/>8 <lb/>1 <lb/>PURA (13), PURB <lb/>0.41 <lb/>13 <lb/>1.13E-15 <lb/>12 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>CHD3 (10), CHD4 (6), CHD5 (5) <lb/>1.94 <lb/>21 <lb/>3.45E-15 <lb/>19 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>TCF4 (11), TCF12 (3), TCF3 (2) <lb/>0.93 <lb/>16 <lb/>5.76E-15 <lb/>14 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>CDK13 (14), CDK12 <lb/>0.66 <lb/>14 <lb/>1.71E-14 <lb/>13 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>PPP2R5D (16), PPP2R5A (1), PPP2R5B, <lb/>PPP2R5C, PPP2R5E <lb/>1.25 <lb/>17 <lb/>3.62E-14 <lb/>16 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>WDR45 (11), WDR45B <lb/>0.32 <lb/>11 <lb/>7.60E-14 <lb/>9 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>MEF2C (11), MEF2D (2), MEF2A <lb/>0.58 <lb/>13 <lb/>7.77E-14 <lb/>9 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>EHMT1 (13), EHMT2 <lb/>0.66 <lb/>13 <lb/>3.93E-13 <lb/>13 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>FOXP1 (10), FOXP2 (4), FOXP4 <lb/>0.86 <lb/>14 <lb/>6.02E-13 <lb/>12 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>FOXG1 (11), FOXQ1, FOXN3, FOXN2 <lb/>0.39 <lb/>11 <lb/>6.36E-13 <lb/>7 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>CHD8 (12), CHD7 (7), CHD9 (1) <lb/>2.30 <lb/>20 <lb/>7.73E-13 <lb/>11 <lb/>9 <lb/>0 <lb/>CSNK2A1 (12), CSNK2A3, CSNK2A2 <lb/>0.63 <lb/>12 <lb/>5.00E-12 <lb/>10 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>CACNA1E (10), CACNA1A (9), CACNA1B (1) <lb/>2.72 <lb/>20 <lb/>1.53E-11 <lb/>13 <lb/>1 <lb/>6 <lb/>HDAC8 (9), HDAC3 (2), HDAC1 (1), HDAC2 <lb/>0.83 <lb/>12 <lb/>1.06E-10 <lb/>11 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>GNAO1 (7), GNAI1 (7), GNAZ (1), GNA11 (1), <lb/>GNA14, GNAI3, GNAT2, GNAT3, GNAT1, GNAI2, <lb/>GNA15, GNAQ <lb/>1.82 <lb/>16 <lb/>1.31E-10 <lb/>13 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>CASK (8), DLG4 (6), DLG2 (1), DLG1, DLG3 <lb/>1.58 <lb/>15 <lb/>1.67E-10 <lb/>12 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>GATAD2B (10), GATAD2A <lb/>0.65 <lb/>10 <lb/>2.10E-09 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>MED13L (12), MED13 (2) <lb/>1.68 <lb/>14 <lb/>3.47E-09 <lb/>10 <lb/>4 <lb/>0 <lb/>TBL1XR1 (9), TBL1Y, TBL1X <lb/>0.52 <lb/>9 <lb/>5.01E-09 <lb/>7 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>PHIP (10), BRWD3 (2) <lb/>1.46 <lb/>13 <lb/>5.64E-09 <lb/>10 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>CTCF (9), CTCFL <lb/>0.56 <lb/>9 <lb/>9.00E-09 <lb/>7 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>RAB11A (3), RAB2A (2), RAB11B (2), RAB14 (2), <lb/>RAB19 (1), RAB43 (1), RAB39A, RAB25, RAB4B, <lb/>RAB39B, RAB4A, RAB30, RAB2B <lb/>1.01 <lb/>11 <lb/>1.14E-08 <lb/>9 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>GABRB3 (8), GABRB2 (3), GLRA2 (1), GABRB1 <lb/>(2), GLRB (1), GLRA1, GABRR1, GABRD, <lb/>GABRR3, GABRP, GLRA4, GABRQ, GABRR2, <lb/>GLRA3 <lb/>2.35 <lb/>15 <lb/>3.15E-08 <lb/>7 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>TCF20 (9), RAI1 (3) <lb/>1.40 <lb/>12 <lb/>3.33E-08 <lb/>11 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>NFIX (6), NFIA (2), NFIB (2), NFIC, <lb/>0.90 <lb/>10 <lb/>4.31E-08 <lb/>8 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>USP9X (10), USP24 (1), USP9Y <lb/>1.18 <lb/>11 <lb/>5.29E-08 <lb/>9 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>SATB2 (9), SATB1 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>9 <lb/>1.04E-07 <lb/>9 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>HECW2 (9), HECW1 (1) <lb/>1.04 <lb/>10 <lb/>1.61E-07 <lb/>8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>SOX11 (4), SOX4 (3), SOX9 (1), SOX10 (1), SOX17, <lb/>SOX1, SOX8, SOX7 <lb/>0.82 <lb/>9 <lb/>2.21E-07 <lb/>9 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>ZBTB18 (6), ZBTB3 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>6 <lb/>5.43E-07 <lb/>6 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>TCF7L2 (6), TCF7L1 (1) <lb/>0.53 <lb/>7 <lb/>1.48E-06 <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/>TBR1 (6), EOMES <lb/>0.35 <lb/>6 <lb/>2.01E-06 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>0 <lb/>
			Table 1: 43 significantly enriched gene families in the combined de novo paralog <lb/>conserved missense and PTV analysis for 10,068 NDD trios. Only enriched gene families <lb/>significant after applying the Bonferroni significance threshold for testing 5 x 2,871 gene families <lb/>(3.48 x 10 <lb/>-6 ) are included. Bold-highlighted genes are affected by DNM and the number of DNM <lb/>is indicated inside the soft-brackets. Genes in red have not previously been reported as <lb/>significantly enriched in exome-wide ASD, DD or EPI studies. The full list gene families with <lb/>variants can be found in Supplementary Table 1. <lb/>We identified 43 gene families (1.49% of all gene families) enriched for de novo <lb/>paralog-conserved missense and PTVs (Bonferroni correction significance <lb/>threshold for testing 5 x 2871 gene families = 3.48 x 10 -6 ; Table 1). In all 43 gene <lb/>families, the most frequently mutated gene and often additional genes harboring <lb/>de novo variants are brain-expressed (Supplementary Fig. 3). Within the <lb/>enriched gene families, 94 gene family members (paralogs) carried at least one <lb/>DNM vs. 59 gene family members without DNMs. In total, 7.47% of all NDD <lb/>patients carried a de novo paralog conserved missense or PTV in the 43 <lb/>enriched gene families. In the NDD patients, we found 753 DNMs in 43 gene <lb/>families while only 49.92 DNMs were expected (P &lt;&lt; 1.0 x 10 -100 ). The paralog <lb/>conserved missense variant enrichment signal of these genes was 7.8-fold <lb/>(observed DNMs: 261, expected DNMs: 33.01). There was no signal if we <lb/>examine paralog non-conserved missense variants in this group of genes <lb/>(observed DNMs: 41, expected DNMs: 31.03, Supplementary Table 2). No <lb/>enrichment was observed in the 2,078 individuals without a NDD (observed <lb/>DNMs: 5, expected DNMs: 10.34, P = 1.0). The majority of the frequently <lb/>mutated genes have previously been established as disease-associated genes <lb/>by demonstrating an exome-wide significant DNM burden in disease-specific <lb/>single gene enrichment studies 12-15,23 (Table 1, highlighted in black and bold). <lb/>When removing all the established disease genes (Table 1, bold and black, <lb/>N=42) from the analysis, we still observe a 4.72-fold enrichment (observed: 162 <lb/>DNMs in the 43 enriched genes families, expected 34.27, P = 6.10 x 10 -56 ). This <lb/>enrichment increases to 5.28-fold when we removed all non-brain-expressed <lb/>genes from the 43 enriched genes families (28.71 DNM expected vs. 149 DM <lb/>observed, P = 3.72 x 10 -57 ). <lb/>Several of these genes, previously not associated with any disease, represent <lb/>likely NDD-associated genes. First, in one out of the 43 enriched gene families, <lb/>we observe that the novel gene harbors more DNM variants than the established <lb/>disease-associated gene of the same gene family (CHD3 vs. CHD4; Table 1). <lb/>Second, four families show genome-wide gene family enrichment without prior <lb/>evidence for any gene on the genome-wide level, even though some individual <lb/>genes are known disease genes, such as CACNA1A (Supplementary Table 3). <lb/>These <lb/>gene <lb/>families <lb/>include <lb/>the <lb/>(CACNA1[E/A/B] <lb/>-<lb/>family, <lb/>RAB[2(A/B)/4(A/B)/11(A/B)/14/19/25/30/39(A/B)/43] -family, the HECW[1/2] -<lb/>family, the SOX[1/4/7/8/9/10/11], TCF7L[1/2] -family and the TBR1/EOMES -<lb/>family). To find further evidence of disease association for less frequently <lb/>mutated gene family members, we systematically investigated the evolutionary <lb/>variant intolerance 22 (&quot;constraint&quot;) and brain expression levels for all mutated <lb/>paralog genes within the enriched gene families (Supplementary Fig. 3). We <lb/>observed that 33 paralog genes of the enriched gene families with DNMs are <lb/>under evolutionary constraint and brain expressed (Supplementary Table 3), <lb/>showing the same signature as the known disease genes in the same families <lb/>(Supplementary Fig. 3). Although none of these genes have previously been <lb/>reported to be significant on an exome-wide level, 57.57% (19/33) of the novel <lb/>disease-associated genes have been previously reported in the literature as <lb/>carrying a rare single nucleotide or copy number variant affecting the gene <lb/>(Supplementary Table 3). For 63.63% (21/33) of the genes, available mice <lb/>models show neurological and/or behavioral phenotypes supporting the disease <lb/>association (Supplementary Table 3). Given these multiple lines of evidence, in <lb/>addition to the sequence and expression pattern similarity to the known disease <lb/>genes in the same families, we consider this list of 33 genes as highly promising <lb/>candidate disease genes (Supplementary Table 3). <lb/>Sub-disorder specificity of DNM enriched gene families <lb/>While the initial analysis considered all NDDs as a single group, we next <lb/>explored whether the NDD sub-phenotypes (ASD, DD and EPI) contributed <lb/>equally to the enrichment of the 43 gene families (Table 1) or if a specific sub-<lb/>NDD contributes more to the enrichment and subsequently carries larger <lb/>mutational burden than the other NDDs. Compared to single gene enrichment <lb/>studies, DNM enriched gene families harbor larger numbers of variants due to <lb/>the sum of mutations in several mutated paralogous genes, which increases <lb/>testing power for investigating disease specificity. The increased number of <lb/>variants per family permits frequency comparisons of likely functional related <lb/>proteins across NDDs. We tested the 43 PTV and paralog-conserved missense <lb/>enriched gene families (Table 1) to evaluate gene family specific sub-NDD <lb/>burden. To avoid introducing a bias, we included all mutated genes of each gene <lb/>family in the analysis, regardless of the PTV or missense intolerance and gene <lb/>tissue expression analysis in Supplementary Fig. 3. <lb/>Overall, 31.91% of all de novo variants in patients with DD affected one gene in <lb/>the 43 gene families, compared to 13.53% in the ASD cohort and 26.03% in the <lb/>EPI cohort. Only two out of the 43 enriched gene families (Table 1) showed <lb/>significant sub-disorder enrichment (either ASD, DD or EPI) after multiple testing <lb/>correction. The DDX3[X/Y]-family is 20.55-fold enriched in DD patients in <lb/>comparison with mutation frequencies in ASD and EPI patients combined <lb/>(P=3.17 <lb/>x <lb/>10 -6 ). <lb/>The <lb/>voltage-gated <lb/>sodium <lb/>channels <lb/>(SCN[1/2/3/4/5/7/8/9/10/11]A), have significantly higher mutational burden in the <lb/>EPI cohort compared to variant frequencies in the ASD and DD cohorts <lb/>combined (OR=4.96, P=6.06 x 10 -8 ,) while representing the most frequent gene <lb/>family with de novo mutations in all sub-NDDs (EPI=2.67%, DD=0.68%, <lb/>ASD=0.40% carrier rate). Post-hoc phenotype analysis of the ASD cohort <lb/>revealed that ASD patients with voltage-gated sodium channel mutations have a <lb/>5.08-fold higher frequency of seizures and 8.5-fold higher rate of low IQ <lb/>compared to ASD patients without mutations in this gene family. <lb/>Variant interpretation and correlation of para_zscore with an experimentally <lb/>derived mutation intolerance score <lb/>The vast majority of current variant prediction methods are nucleotide based and <lb/>do not allow visualization of scores across the protein sequence. Paralog <lb/>conservation can identify stretches of conserved amino acids which can overlap <lb/>functional domains; however not all annotated domains are paralog conserved <lb/>and harbor disease variants (Fig. 4). The para_zscore is able to identify paralog <lb/>conserved and non-conserved amino acid residues within known functional <lb/>domains (Fig. 4) and thus is an illustrative tool to visualize the predicted mutation <lb/>tolerance of a protein sequence across the amino acid sequence. As an example, <lb/>we wanted to visualize para_zscore amino acid conservation alongside <lb/>functionally derived data. Variants in PPARG cause Mendelian lipodystrophy and <lb/>increase risk of type 2 diabetes (T2D). Recently, a complete prospective <lb/>functional assessment of all possible 9,595 amino acid exchanges in PPARG <lb/>was conducted 24 . The authors developed a pooled functional assay in human <lb/>macrophages, experimentally evaluated all protein variants, and used the <lb/>experimental data to train a variant classifier by supervised machine learning <lb/>(&quot;mut_tol&quot;, Fig. 5). Comparing the experimental derived data with the PPARG <lb/>para_zscores, we observed high correlation (r 2 =0.71, P = 4.08 x 10 -77 , Pearson&apos;s <lb/>product-moment correlation), supporting the usefulness of the para_zscore as a <lb/>biological interpretable pathogenicity metric. In comparison, averaged mutation <lb/>tolerance scores (see Online Methods) for Polyphen 5 , CADD 4 , SIFT 3 and <lb/>GERP 20 show less correlation (r 2 = 0.28-0.56) with mut_tol (Fig. 5). <lb/>Figure 4: Visualization of para_zscores of proteins encoded by KCNQ2, STXBP1, <lb/>CACNA1A, and GRIN2B. Protein sequence is plotted from left to right. Each bar and dot <lb/>represents one amino acid. Amino acids affected by a missense mutation in the NDD cohort are <lb/>colored blue, patient PTVs are depicted in pink, and synonymous variants in orange. Amino acid <lb/>residues with no mutations are colored grey. Y-axis: Positive values indicate paralog conservation <lb/>and the highest score indicates that these amino acids are identical over all gene family members. <lb/>The red dotted lines indicate the mean paralog conservation of each protein sequence and bars <lb/>below the mean indicate regions of low paralog conservation, thus higher sequence variability <lb/>over all members of the gene family. <lb/>Figure 5: Comparison of experimentally derived mutation tolerance scores and <lb/>para_zscores for PPARG. Raw PPARG function scores for each of the 9,595 amino acid <lb/>exchanges plotted according to the amino acid position along the PPARG sequence. Functional <lb/>scores summed by amino acid position are plotted to the right, showing the level of tolerance for <lb/>any amino acid substitution differing from the human reference genome (derived from Majithia et <lb/>al., 2016 <lb/>24 ). PPARG functionally generated mut_tol scores (blue), para_zscores and averaged <lb/>mutation tolerance scores (amt) for PolyPhen2, CADD, and SIFT. All scores were correlated with <lb/>the experimentally derived mut_tol score and r <lb/>2 and p-values are shown next to the score <lb/>distribution. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Sequence conservation across gene families has been extensively discussed in <lb/>the literature. On the one hand, orthologous domain pairs tend to be significantly <lb/>more structurally similar than paralogous pairs at the same level of sequence <lb/>identity 25 . On the other hand, it has been shown that paralogs are functionally not <lb/>necessarily redundant and the average fitness cost of loss of a paralogous gene <lb/>is at least equal deleting single non-paralogous genes in yeast 26 . In addition, <lb/>protein complexes have been documented to use paralog switching as a <lb/>mechanism for the regulation of complex stoichiometry 27 . For example, many <lb/>receptors in the human brain consist of multiple protein subunits, many of which <lb/>have multiple paralogs and are differentially expressed across brain regions and <lb/>developmental stages. The brain can tune the electrophysiological properties of <lb/>synapses to regulate plasticity and information processing by switching from one <lb/>protein variant to another. Such condition-dependent variant switch during <lb/>development has been demonstrated in several neurotransmitter systems <lb/>including NMDA and GABA 28 . Naturally, the question arises whether paralog <lb/>conserved or non-conserved sites of the protein sequence are essential for <lb/>function. Across multiple analyses in this study, we empirically demonstrate that <lb/>disease-associated missense variants are enriched at paralog conserved sites <lb/>and that this information can offer substantial value in mutation annotation on top <lb/>of widely-used annotation methods. <lb/>We developed a gene family DNM enrichment framework and computed a novel <lb/>amino acid paralog conservation score, the &quot;para_zscore&quot;, applicable to 42% of <lb/>all genes in the human genome. Application of the genome-wide paralog <lb/>conservation score demonstrates that NDD and pathogenic variants in ClinVar <lb/>affect paralog conserved, but not non-conserved, sites when compared to <lb/>mutations in controls and missense variants in ExAC 2 , the vast majority of which <lb/>are presumed benign. It has recently been proposed that conserved residues <lb/>within gene family members (paralogs) are under evolutionary constraint and that <lb/>in silico annotations of known disease associated residues across families of <lb/>related proteins can guide variant interpretation 17 . Our results support the idea <lb/>that paralogs share a similar &quot;core&quot; molecular function of the ancestral gene, <lb/>since variants in these sites are enriched for patient missense variants indicating <lb/>hereby a reduction in evolutionary fitness. Evolutionary younger paralogs show <lb/>higher functional redundancy 29 . To control the functional diversity within gene <lb/>families and to increase within family sequence similarity, we built sub-groups for <lb/>each gene family using pairwise alignment length cut-offs of &gt;80% aligned amino <lb/>acids 30 . <lb/>
			NDDs represent a genetic and phenotypic heterogeneous group of diseases for <lb/>which pathogenic variants in individual disease genes are rare. Using a gene <lb/>family version of a recently established DNM enrichment framework 22 for 10,068 <lb/>NDD patients, we identified 43 PTV and paralog conserved missense DNM <lb/>enriched gene families. Besides highlighting four gene families with genome-wide <lb/>gene family enrichment without carrying any previously exome-wide established <lb/>disease <lb/>gene <lb/>(CACNA1[E/A/B] <lb/>-<lb/>family, <lb/>RAB[2(A/B)/4(A/B)/11(A/B)/14/19/25/30/39(A/B)/43] -family, HECW[1/2] -family, <lb/>SOX[1/4/7/8/9/10/11], TCF7L[1/2] -family, TBR1/EOMES -family), we <lb/>additionally report 33 with first time statistical support as disease genes. <lb/>Pathogenic variants in all of these genes are too rare to reach individual exome-<lb/>wide significant enrichment. However, the individual genes belong to a gene <lb/>family with an exome-wide significant enrichment, are brain expressed, and are <lb/>under evolutionary constraint in the general population 2 . Notably, three of the 43 <lb/>enriched genes belong to chromatin helicase DNA-binding proteins gene families. <lb/>Besides the established genes, we observe also five novel candidate disease <lb/>genes in this group (CHD1, CHD3, CHD5, CHD7, CHD9) with DNM in 20 <lb/>patients in this study. All five genes represent valid candidates for association of <lb/>NDDs based on our detailed analysis (for details see Supplementary Table 3). <lb/>Chromatin remodeling is one of the mechanisms by which gene expression is <lb/>regulated developmentally 31 , perhaps explaining the susceptibility to NDDs when <lb/>mutated. <lb/>Given the larger number of DNMs in gene families compared to single genes, we <lb/>investigated if any of the 43 enriched gene families are specifically enriched in <lb/>patients within the EPI, ASD, or DD sub-cohorts. The vast majority of gene <lb/>families did not show significant sub-NDD specificity. This phenomenon can be <lb/>explained in several ways. Most importantly, there are overlapping phenotypes in <lb/>the different studies. Patients within the developmental delay cohort include <lb/>patients with ASD 15 . For NDD phenotype definitions overlap significantly, <lb/>allowing for including of patients with combined phenotypes into either of the DD, <lb/>ASD, or EPI cohort. However, we showed that paralog conserved missense and <lb/>PTVs affecting the voltage-gated sodium alpha channel family are clearly <lb/>enriched in patient within the EPI cohort, but the same class of variants can also <lb/>be found at lower frequency in DD, and rarely in ASD. Analysis of the ASD <lb/>patients with variants in voltage-gated sodium alpha channels indicated that the <lb/>majority of the ASD patients with such variants had seizures. However, we were <lb/>not able to investigate the DD patients for the seizure phenotype due to the lack <lb/>of available phenotypic data. A higher degree of specificity of pathogenic variants <lb/>in voltage-gated sodium channels in patients with epilepsy is supported <lb/>biologically by the function of the channels. Lack of the sodium channel on <lb/>inhibitory neurons leads to decreased inhibition and net excitation. This <lb/>molecular pathology resembles the long-standing idea that epilepsy is a disorder <lb/>based on imbalances between synaptic excitation and inhibition 32 . <lb/>The para_zscore has single value for each position; it is therefore possible to plot <lb/>the score along the entire protein sequence (see Fig. 4). We propose that <lb/>plotting the para_zscore is a useful tool as it visualizes likely essential protein <lb/>regions of high paralog conservation, and thus intuitively supports decision <lb/>making for variant prioritization (e.g., functional testing or drug target <lb/>development). <lb/>The <lb/>scores <lb/>are <lb/>available <lb/>at <lb/>https://git-<lb/>r3lab.uni.lu/genomeanalysis/paralogs. Supporting this utility, we demonstrated <lb/>that the para_zscore exhibits high correlation (r 2 =0.71) with experimentally <lb/>derived mutation tolerance scores across the entire PPARG protein sequence. <lb/>Other generated averaged mutation tolerance scores for commonly used <lb/>classifiers showed less correlation. Notably, the other prediction tools are not <lb/>made for protein conservation scoring. We suggest that our protein wide paralog <lb/>conservation score could potentially also be used in targeted drug development <lb/>to improve the efficacy of therapy. Paralogs share similar protein sequences or <lb/>structural features, e.g. similar binding pockets, e.g. a given compound may <lb/>show an increased affinity to bind its paralogs, possibly resulting in unexpected <lb/>cross-reactivity and undesired side effects. Using the paralog conservation score <lb/>in drug target design could therefore rule out or reduce such cross-reactivity <lb/>effects. <lb/>Although our results demonstrate the utility of paralog conservation, the ideal <lb/>composition of the gene family and choice of protein isoform may differ <lb/>depending on the individual research question. In addition, while conservation <lb/>across orthologs or paralogs can be indicative of the necessary function of a <lb/>given domain, absence of conservation does not a priori exclude functionally <lb/>important domains within a protein. This consideration may be particularly <lb/>relevant for diseases with a later onset that are less under evolutionary selection. <lb/>
			Overall, we provide extensive empirical evidence using multiple data sets (the <lb/>entire ClinVar resource and published de novo variants from more than 10k NDD <lb/>cases) that disease associated missense variants are enriched at paralog <lb/>conserved sites. We demonstrate that integration of paralog conservation can be <lb/>leveraged as powerful method for variant interpretation and discovery of new <lb/>disease-associated genes. We provide a genome-wide &quot;para_zscore&quot; annotation <lb/>file and pre-computed para_zscores for all human paralogs as individual files. <lb/>This resource should enable data and molecular scientists to score and visualize <lb/>variants/genes/proteins of interest and to integrate paralog conservation with <lb/>existing variant annotation tools. <lb/>Online Methods <lb/>Patient and genetic data. <lb/>We analyzed 10,068 neurodevelopmental disorder (NDD) trios (probands and <lb/>their unaffected parents) including 3,982 autism (ASD), 5,226 developmental <lb/>delay (DD) and 822 severe epilepsy (EPI) patients. The ASD cohort was derived <lb/>from published studies 13,33 . The DD cohort combined published de novo variants <lb/>from previous DD and ID studies due to overlap in cohort <lb/>ascertainment 14,15,23,34,35 . The EPI cohort included published trio data sets <lb/>(356/822 trios; 43%) 12,36 as well as 466 (56% of the 822 trios) unpublished <lb/>exome-wide de novo data. New exome sequencing trio data were collected in <lb/>multiple centers, companies and consortia, including the University Clinic of Kiel, <lb/>Germany, the University Clinic of Tübingen, Germany, the Boston Children&apos;s <lb/>Hospital, USA, the University of Antwerp, the RES consortia, the ESES consortia <lb/>and the DESIRE Consortia, Ambry Genetics and CeGat. <lb/>As control data in several analyses in the study, we used 2,078 trios sequenced <lb/>with the same technology as the ASD patient cohort. These controls are <lb/>unaffected siblings of the ASD patients 13,33 . <lb/>To ensure uniformity in variant representation and annotation across published <lb/>datasets and with respect to the ExAC reference database 2 , we created a <lb/>standardized variant representation using a Python implementation of vt 37 and re-<lb/>annotated all variants from the different datasets with ANNOVAR 38 using the <lb/>RefSeq and Ensembl gene annotations (2016Feb01), ClinVar 39 (v20160302) and <lb/>the dbNSFP v3.0 40 databases for various functional prediction tools and <lb/>conservation scores such as GERP 20 , CADD 4 , Polyphen2 41 , and SIFT 3 . <lb/>Construction of the paralog conservation score. <lb/>We restricted the analysis to within human paralogs to identify gene family <lb/>burden and amino acids in proteins which are essential for function in humans. It <lb/>has previously been shown that the human genome harbors essential genes for <lb/>normal development which are not present in great apes. Such an example <lb/>represents SRGAP2, which is essential for neocortex expansion 42 . Ensembl <lb/>defines gene families based on maximum likelihood phylogenetic gene trees 43 <lb/>based on the longest translation annotated in CCDS 44 for each gene. Paralogs <lb/>are then defined as genes of the same species related by a duplication event (as <lb/>an inner tree node). First, we downloaded the human paralog definitions using <lb/>the Ensembl BioMart system 45 representing each gene with an Ensembl gene <lb/>identifier. The paralogs could be grouped into 3,584 gene families. Ensembl IDs <lb/>were then converted to HGNC gene names (http://www.genenames.org). Non-<lb/>coding genes and genes without a HGNC symbol were excluded and only gene <lb/>families with at least two HGNC genes were used for further analysis. CCDS <lb/>data were downloaded the same day as HGNC and Ensembl data (v20150512). <lb/>In total, 3,348 gene families were defined with 13,570 HGNC genes. 1,815 <lb/>families contained three or more paralogs. Next, we extracted the longest <lb/>transcript from CCDS for each HGNC gene and constructed for each gene family <lb/>a FASTA formatted file for multiple sequence alignment with MUSCLE 46 including <lb/>all paralog protein sequences. Evolutionary younger paralogs show higher <lb/>functional redundancy 29 . To avoid alignments of strongly diverging sequences <lb/>and to increase overall similarity, we built sub-groups for each gene family using <lb/>pairwise alignment length cut-offs of &gt;80% aligned amino acids 30 . The clusters <lb/>(sub-groups) were defined by connected components within an alignment <lb/>similarity graph in which two genes with &gt;80% aligned residues were connected <lb/>through an edge. Clusters were then defined as connected components within <lb/>the graph. Only clusters with at least two proteins were further processed. In total, <lb/>we generated 2,871 (sub) gene families comprising 8,233 genes. Each subgroup <lb/>was re-aligned using MUSCLE. The MUSCLE output was then processed as <lb/>input for Jalview 47 to generate and extract conservation scores for each <lb/>alignment position. The conservation score calculation in Jalview is based on the <lb/>AMAS method of multiple sequence alignment analysis 48 . Conservation is <lb/>measured here as a numerical index reflecting the conservation of physico-<lb/>chemical properties in the alignment. Identities score highest, and the next most <lb/>conserved group contains substitutions to amino acids lying in the same physico-<lb/>chemical class. For each HGNC CCDS gene, the conservation scores at each <lb/>position were extracted from the Jalview. Finally, to identify amino acids of high <lb/>and low paralog conservation and make scores comparable between genes, the <lb/>mean and the standard deviation conservation score over all amino acids per <lb/>gene were calculated to compute a paralog conservation z-score (&quot;para_zscore&quot;) <lb/>per amino acid position by subtracting the mean from the original score dividing <lb/>the difference by the standard deviation. (Supplementary Fig. 4). <lb/>Gene family enrichment analysis. <lb/>To identify gene families with significant mutational burden, we adopted a de <lb/>novo expectation model 22 to assess mutation rates for nonsense, frameshift, or <lb/>canonical splice disruptions (collectively termed protein truncating variants <lb/>&apos;PTVs&apos;) and missense variants for gene families (missense+PTV). We derived <lb/>gene-based rates of de novo mutation from local sequence context and summed <lb/>the expectations and the observed counts for all members within each gene <lb/>family 2 . The expected and observed numbers of de novo mutations in each <lb/>variant class for NDD combined were compared using a Poisson distribution. <lb/>Notably, the discovery of de novo burden in a gene family is more challenging <lb/>compared to the single gene analysis because of larger amount of expected <lb/>mutations due combining the expectations from all gene family members <lb/>(including those which are not expressed in the tissue of interest, e.g., brain). We <lb/>used a Bonferroni corrected significance threshold for the 2,871 gene families <lb/>tested (&lt;0.05). Furthermore, to exclude &quot;passenger&quot; variants and enrich for true <lb/>disease variants we excluded de novo variants also seen in adult individuals <lb/>without early onset NDDs in ExAC 2 (n=60,706 exomes) prior to the enrichment <lb/>analysis. Variants absent from this reference panel, which is a proxy for standing <lb/>variation in the human population, are more likely to be deleterious. This <lb/>conservative filter reduces the power for gene association discovery changes, <lb/>but increases the plausibility for association for the identified variant with severe <lb/>sporadic disorders. <lb/>Sub-NDD enrichment analysis. <lb/>Sub-NDD enrichment was calculated for the significantly enriched gene families <lb/>in the paralog conserved missense and PTV combined analysis. We used <lb/>Fisher&apos;s exact test to compare the sub-NDD of interest (e.g., EPI) with the other <lb/>sub-NDDs (e.g., ASD+DD). <lb/>Paralog conserved site vs. paralog non-conserved sites missense <lb/>enrichment analysis. <lb/>Similar to the missense+PTV enrichment analysis, we adopted the de novo <lb/>expectation model 22 to assess mutation rates for missense variants only. In the <lb/>missense enrichment analysis, we consider only missense variants and <lb/>missense expectations for each gene family. We classified every amino acid <lb/>position within each gene into &apos;conserved sites&apos; with paralog conservation <lb/>(para_zscore &gt; 0, amino acids with higher paralog conservation than gene-<lb/>specific mean) and &apos;non-conserved sites&apos; without paralog conservation <lb/>(para_zscore ≤ 0) and summed the observations for both groups independently <lb/>across the family. The expected missense mutation rates were adjusted for the <lb/>size of the paralog conserved sites and non-conserved sites, respectively. The <lb/>observed variant counts were assigned to either of these two groups depending <lb/>on the paralog conservation state of the mutated amino acid residue for all <lb/>members within each gene family (Supplementary Figure 1). The expected and <lb/>observed numbers of de novo mutations in each variant class for NDD combined <lb/>was compared using a Poisson distribution. To exclude &quot;passenger&quot; variants and <lb/>enrich for disease variants, we excluded de novo variants present as standing <lb/>variation in the 60,706 individuals in ExAC 2 prior to the enrichment analysis. <lb/>Identification of brain expressed genes and evolutionary constraint. <lb/>We extracted brain expression data from the Genotype-Tissue Expression <lb/>consortia 49 (GTEx) data and considered genes with &gt;1 read per kilobase of <lb/>transcript per million mapped reads (RPKM) in brain tissues as &quot; brain-<lb/>expressed&quot;. Gene loss-of-function intolerance (pLI) scores and gene missense <lb/>intolerance scores were derived from ExAC 2 . We considered genes with <lb/>missense Z scores &gt; 3.09 or pLI scores ≥ 0.9 as intolerant of variants. Genes <lb/>were classified as plausible novel disease genes for NDD if they were present in <lb/>an exome-wide enriched gene family, brain expressed, and under constraint <lb/>(either missense or PTV). <lb/>Paralog conservation analysis of ClinVar variants vs. ExAC variants. <lb/>
			The ClinVar database (v20160302) 39 was filtered for missense variants that were <lb/>classified as pathogenic. We excluded variants that were classified as <lb/>pathogenic by one submitter and not pathogenic by another submitter. Next, we <lb/>homogenized disease names by removing ambiguous subtype classifications. <lb/>We removed variants present in ExAC 2 to increase the quality of truly disease <lb/>associated variants. Finally, we counted the number of variants in genes <lb/>associated with a specific disease, and kept only disease-gene association <lb/>supported by at least ten variants. 67 disorders remained in the analysis. For <lb/>each disorder-gene combination, missense variants in the same gene were <lb/>included as comparison in the data set. Next, we classified and grouped all 67 <lb/>disorders by ICD10 codes, scored ClinVar and ExAC variants with the paralog <lb/>score, and compared the paralog variant distribution using the Wilcoxon test <lb/>(wilcox.test implemented in R). Notably, in nearly every ICD-10-CM category <lb/>there <lb/>is <lb/>a <lb/>sub-category <lb/>named <lb/>&quot;other <lb/>specified&quot; <lb/>condition <lb/>(http://www.icd10monitor.com). Codes titled &quot;other&quot; or &quot;other specified&quot; are for <lb/>use when the information in the medical record provides detail for which a <lb/>specific code does not exist (https://www.cdc.gov). Due to the limited definition <lb/>and corresponding limited interpretation of these heterogeneous groups of <lb/>disorders we removed these from the analysis. <lb/>PPARG mutation tolerance scores for para_zscore, GERP, CADD, <lb/>PolyPhen2, and SIFT. <lb/>The mutation tolerance score (see Figure 5) as defined in Majithia et al., 2016 24 , <lb/>is given for every position of the protein sequence. Since the para_zscore is <lb/>defined for every position of the protein, it can directly be used as a mutation <lb/>tolerance score. For PolyPhen2 41 and SIFT 3 we used the matrix of all possible <lb/>amino acid exchanges represented as a nx20 matrix (n=protein length; n=505 for <lb/>PPARG). The exchange matrices for both scores were generated using the <lb/>respective webtools (see URLs) using all amino acid changes as input. Then, for <lb/>every possible amino acid substitution in hg19 the average score of all possible <lb/>amino acid exchanges at a given position was calculated, e.g., if for a given <lb/>codon n missense mutations could cause m different amino acid exchanges, we <lb/>calculated the average score over the m possible amino acid exchanges as the <lb/>mutation tolerance score at a given position. Since CADD 4 and GERP 20 scores <lb/>are defined for every genomic position, we used for every possible amino acid <lb/>exchange the average respective score over all possible nucleotide exchanges <lb/>within a given codon resulting into the same amino acid exchange. <lb/> Correlation between para_zscore and PPARG mut_tolerance score. <lb/>The authors provided us with the experimentally derived and trained mutational <lb/>tolerance score (&quot;mut_tol&quot;) for PPARG. A detailed description of the score can be <lb/>found in Majithia et al., 2016 24 . In short, the authors used highly parallel <lb/>oligonucleotide synthesis to construct a library encoding all 9,595 (505 positions <lb/>x 19 amino acid changes at each position) possible single amino acid <lb/>substitutions to prospectively characterize PPARG variants. They developed a <lb/>pooled functional assay in human macrophages, experimentally evaluated all <lb/>protein variants, and used the experimental data to train a variant classifier by <lb/>supervised machine learning. We used the cor {stats} function in R 50 for the <lb/>correlation analysis of both scores. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Data availability . <lb/>The code for generating the underlying alignments and the para_zscore, <lb/>additional <lb/>code <lb/>and <lb/>examples <lb/>are <lb/>available <lb/>under <lb/>https://git-<lb/>r3lab.uni.lu/genomeanalysis/paralogs. Additional data and annotations for the <lb/>hg19 missense variants are available from: https://zenodo.org/record/817898. All <lb/>de novo variants used in the analysis are listed in Supplementary Table 4. <lb/>URLs. <lb/>PolyPhen2, http:// http://genetics.bwh.harvard.edu/pph2/; SIFT, <lb/>http://sift.jcvi.org/www/SIFT_seq_submit2.html; GTEx portal, <lb/>http://www.gtexportal.org/home/; ExAC, http://exac.broadinstitute.org; ANNOVAR, <lb/>http://annovar.openbioinformatics.org; ClinVar, <lb/>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/clinvar; Ensembl biomart, <lb/>www.ensembl.org/biomart; Ensembl compara, <lb/>www.ensembl.org/info/genome/compara; HGNC, http://www.genenames.org; <lb/>CCDS, https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/CCDS. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We thank Shamil Sunyaev for scientific exchange and comments on the <lb/>evolutionary aspects of our results. Parts of the computational analysis was <lb/>performed on the high-performance computer system of the University of <lb/>Luxembourg. We thank Mungo Carstairs and Jim Procter from the Jalview team <lb/>at the University of Dundee for their help with scripting Jalview. PM was <lb/>supported by the JPND-Courage and FNR NCER-PD grants. RG was supported <lb/>by the EU seventh Framework Programme (FP7) under the project DESIRE <lb/>grant N602531 (to RG). DL received funds from the German Academic <lb/>Exchange Service (DAAD), grant number 57073880.BAN received funding by the <lb/>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (Ne 416/5-1). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions <lb/>DL and PM performed the analyses. DL, PM, AP and MJD designed the <lb/>experiment. DL and PM wrote the code. AP and MJD supervised the research. <lb/>DL, PM, AP and MJD wrote the paper. KES, JAK, EBR, RSM, RK, PN, SW, PDJ, <lb/> RG, LMN, JD, EPP, CM, JSW, MK, PG, ST, SW, SB, AP, BN, BPK, KLH, YGW, <lb/>IH, ARM generated data. DL was responsible for the remainder. All authors <lb/>revised and approved the final manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing Financial Interests <lb/>ST, SW, and KLH are full time employees of Ambry Genetics. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. 1000 Genomes Project Consortium et al. A global reference for human genetic <lb/>variation. Nature 526, 68-74 (2015). <lb/>2. Lek, M. et al. Analysis of protein-coding genetic variation in 60,706 humans. Nature <lb/>536, 285-291 (2016). <lb/>3. Kumar, P., Henikoff, S. &amp; Ng, P. C. Predicting the effects of coding non-synonymous <lb/>variants on protein function using the SIFT algorithm. Nat. Protoc. 4, 1073-1081 <lb/>(2009). <lb/>4. Kircher, M. et al. A general framework for estimating the relative pathogenicity of <lb/>human genetic variants. Nat. Genet. 46, 310-315 (2014). <lb/>5. Adzhubei, I. A. et al. A method and server for predicting damaging missense <lb/>mutations. Nat. Methods 7, 248-249 (2010). <lb/>6. Soukup, S. W. Evolution by gene duplication. S. Ohno. Springer-Verlag, New York. <lb/>1970. 160 pp. Teratology 9, 250-251 (1974). <lb/>7. Koonin, E. V. Orthologs, Paralogs, and Evolutionary Genomics. Annu. Rev. Genet. <lb/>39, 309-338 (2005). <lb/>8. Fitch, W. M. Distinguishing Homologous from Analogous Proteins. Syst. Zool. 19, <lb/>99 (1970). <lb/>9. Dickerson, J. E. &amp; Robertson, D. L. On the Origins of Mendelian Disease Genes in <lb/>Man: The Impact of Gene Duplication. Mol. Biol. Evol. 29, 61-69 (2012). <lb/>10. Lahiry, P., Torkamani, A., Schork, N. J. &amp; Hegele, R. A. Kinase mutations in human <lb/>disease: interpreting genotype-phenotype relationships. Nat. Rev. Genet. 11, 60-74 <lb/>(2010). <lb/>11. Szeverenyi, I. et al. The Human Intermediate Filament Database: comprehensive <lb/>information on a gene family involved in many human diseases. Hum. Mutat. 29, <lb/>351-360 (2008). <lb/>12. Allen, A. S. et al. De novo mutations in epileptic encephalopathies. Nature 501, 217-<lb/>221 (2013). <lb/>13. De Rubeis, S. et al. Synaptic, transcriptional and chromatin genes disrupted in autism. <lb/>Nature 515, 209-215 (2014). <lb/>14. Fitzgerald, T. W. et al. Large-scale discovery of novel genetic causes of <lb/>developmental disorders. Nature 519, 223-228 (2014). <lb/>15. McRae, J. F. et al. Prevalence and architecture of de novo mutations in <lb/>developmental disorders. Nature 542, 433-438 (2017). <lb/>16. Ware, J. S., Walsh, R., Cunningham, F., Birney, E. &amp; Cook, S. A. Paralogous <lb/>annotation of disease-causing variants in long QT syndrome genes. Hum. Mutat. 33, <lb/>1188-1191 (2012). <lb/>17. Walsh, R., Peters, N. S., Cook, S. A. &amp; Ware, J. S. Paralogue annotation identifies <lb/>novel pathogenic variants in patients with Brugada syndrome and catecholaminergic <lb/>polymorphic ventricular tachycardia. J. Med. Genet. 51, 35-44 (2014). <lb/>18. Fromer, M. et al. De novo mutations in schizophrenia implicate synaptic networks. <lb/>Nature 506, 179-184 (2014). <lb/>19. Homsy, J. et al. De novo mutations in congenital heart disease with <lb/>neurodevelopmental and other congenital anomalies. Science 350, 1262-1266 (2015). <lb/>20. Goode, D. L. et al. Evolutionary constraint facilitates interpretation of genetic <lb/>variation in resequenced human genomes. Genome Res. 20, 301-310 (2010). <lb/>21. Kosmicki, J. A. et al. Refining the role of de novo protein-truncating variants in <lb/>neurodevelopmental disorders by using population reference samples. Nat. Genet. 49, <lb/>504-510 (2017). <lb/>22. Samocha, K. E. et al. A framework for the interpretation of de novo mutation in <lb/>human disease. Nat. Genet. 46, 944-950 (2014). <lb/>23. Lelieveld, S. H. et al. Meta-analysis of 2,104 trios provides support for 10 new genes <lb/>for intellectual disability. Nat. Neurosci. 19, 1194-1196 (2016). <lb/>24. Majithia, A. R. et al. Prospective functional classification of all possible missense <lb/>variants in PPARG. Nat. Genet. 48, 1570-1575 (2016). <lb/>25. Peterson, M. E. et al. Evolutionary constraints on structural similarity in orthologs <lb/>and paralogs. Protein Sci. 18, 1306-1315 (2009). <lb/>26. DeLuna, A. et al. Exposing the fitness contribution of duplicated genes. Nat. Genet. <lb/>40, 676-681 (2008). <lb/>27. Ori, A. et al. Spatiotemporal variation of mammalian protein complex stoichiometries. <lb/>Genome Biol. 17, (2016). <lb/>28. Bar-Shira, O., Maor, R. &amp; Chechik, G. Gene Expression Switching of Receptor <lb/>Subunits in Human Brain Development. PLOS Comput. Biol. 11, e1004559 (2015). <lb/>29. Chen, S., Krinsky, B. H. &amp; Long, M. New genes as drivers of phenotypic evolution. <lb/>Nat. Rev. Genet. 14, 645-660 (2013). <lb/>30. Dufayard, J.-F. et al. Tree pattern matching in phylogenetic trees: automatic search <lb/>for orthologs or paralogs in homologous gene sequence databases. Bioinforma. Oxf. <lb/>Engl. 21, 2596-2603 (2005). <lb/>31. Thompson, P. M., Gotoh, T., Kok, M., White, P. S. &amp; Brodeur, G. M. CHD5, a new <lb/>member of the chromodomain gene family, is preferentially expressed in the nervous <lb/>system. Oncogene 22, 1002-1011 (2003). <lb/>32. An Introduction to Epilepsy. (American Epilepsy Society, 2006). <lb/>33. Iossifov, I. et al. The contribution of de novo coding mutations to autism spectrum <lb/>disorder. Nature 515, 216-221 (2014). <lb/>34. de Ligt, J. et al. Diagnostic Exome Sequencing in Persons with Severe Intellectual <lb/>Disability. N. Engl. J. Med. 367, 1921-1929 (2012). <lb/>35. Rauch, A. et al. Range of genetic mutations associated with severe non-syndromic <lb/>sporadic intellectual disability: an exome sequencing study. The Lancet 380, 1674-<lb/>1682 (2012). <lb/>36. Appenzeller, S. et al. De Novo Mutations in Synaptic Transmission Genes Including <lb/>DNM1 Cause Epileptic Encephalopathies. Am. J. Hum. Genet. 95, 360-370 (2014). <lb/>37. Tan, A., Abecasis, G. R. &amp; Kang, H. M. Unified representation of genetic variants. <lb/>Bioinformatics 31, 2202-2204 (2015). <lb/>38. Wang, K., Li, M. &amp; Hakonarson, H. ANNOVAR: Functional annotation of genetic <lb/>variants from high-throughput sequencing data. Nucleic Acids Res. 38, 1-7 (2010). <lb/>39. Landrum, M. J. et al. ClinVar: public archive of interpretations of clinically relevant <lb/>variants. Nucleic Acids Res. 44, D862-868 (2016). <lb/>40. Liu, X., Wu, C., Li, C. &amp; Boerwinkle, E. dbNSFP v3.0: A One-Stop Database of <lb/>Functional Predictions and Annotations for Human Nonsynonymous and Splice-Site <lb/>SNVs. Hum. Mutat. 37, 235-241 (2016). <lb/>41. Adzhubei, I., Jordan, D. M. &amp; Sunyaev, S. R. Predicting Functional Effect of Human <lb/>Missense Mutations Using PolyPhen-2. in Current Protocols in Human Genetics (eds. <lb/>Haines, J. L. et al.) 7.20.1-7.20.41 (John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc., 2013). <lb/>doi:10.1002/0471142905.hg0720s76 <lb/>42. Dennis, M. Y. et al. Evolution of Human-Specific Neural SRGAP2 Genes by <lb/>Incomplete Segmental Duplication. Cell 149, 912-922 (2012). <lb/>43. Vilella, A. J. et al. EnsemblCompara GeneTrees: Complete, duplication-aware <lb/>phylogenetic trees in vertebrates. Genome Res. 19, 327-335 (2008). <lb/>44. Farrell, C. M. et al. Current status and new features of the Consensus Coding <lb/>Sequence database. Nucleic Acids Res. 42, D865-872 (2014). <lb/>45. Kinsella, R. J. et al. Ensembl BioMarts: a hub for data retrieval across taxonomic <lb/>space. Database J. Biol. Databases Curation 2011, bar030 (2011). <lb/>46. Edgar, R. C. MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high <lb/>throughput. Nucleic Acids Res. 32, 1792-1797 (2004). <lb/>47. Waterhouse, A. M., Procter, J. B., Martin, D. M. A., Clamp, M. &amp; Barton, G. J. <lb/>Jalview Version 2--a multiple sequence alignment editor and analysis workbench. <lb/>Bioinformatics 25, 1189-1191 (2009). <lb/>48. Livingstone, C. D. &amp; Barton, G. J. Protein sequence alignments: a strategy for the <lb/>hierarchical analysis of residue conservation. Bioinformatics 9, 745-756 (1993). <lb/>49. Lonsdale, J. et al. The Genotype-Tissue Expression (GTEx) project. Nat. Genet. 45, <lb/>580-585 (2013). <lb/>50. R Core Team. R: A language and environment for statistical computing. Vienna, <lb/>Austria; 2014. URL http://www.R-Proj.org (2015). </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
