<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:1609.04957v2 [cond-mat.supr-con] 4 Oct 2016 <lb/>Experimental evidence of T c enhancement without the influence of spin fluctuations: <lb/>NMR study on LaFeAsO 1−x H x under a pressure of 3.0 GPa <lb/>N. Kawaguchi 1 , N. Fujiwara 1 * , S. Iimura 2,3 , S. Matsuishi 2,3 , and H. Hosono 2,3 <lb/>1 Graduate School of Human and Environmental Studies, Kyoto University, <lb/>Yoshida-Nihonmatsu-cyo, Sakyo-ku, Kyoto 606-8501, Japan and <lb/>2 Material and Structures Laboratory (MSL), Tokyo Institute of Technology, <lb/>4259 Nagatsuda, Midori-ku, Yokohama 226-8503, Japan <lb/>3 Frontier Research Center (FRC), Tokyo Institute of Technology, <lb/>4259 Nagatsuda, Midori-ku, Yokohama 226-8503, Japan <lb/>The electron-doped high-transition-temperature (Tc) iron-based pnictide superconductor <lb/>LaFeAsO1−xHx has a unique phase diagram: Superconducting (SC) double domes are sandwiched <lb/>by antiferromagnetic phases at ambient pressure and they turn into a single dome with a maximum <lb/>Tc that exceeds 45K at a pressure of 3.0 GPa. We studied whether spin fluctuations are involved <lb/>in increasing Tc under a pressure of 3.0 GPa by using the 75 As nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) <lb/>technique. The 75 As-NMR results for the powder samples show that Tc increases up to 48 K with-<lb/>out the influence of spin fluctuations. This fact indicates that spin fluctuations are not involved in <lb/>raising Tc, which implies that other factors, such as orbital degrees of freedom, may be important <lb/>for achieving a high Tc of almost 50 K. <lb/></front>

			<body>The phase diagram of the electron-doped high-<lb/>transition-temperature <lb/>(T c ) <lb/>iron-based <lb/>pnictide <lb/>LaFeAsO 1−x H x (H-doped La1111 series) is unique <lb/>owing to the capability of electron doping: (i) It <lb/>exhibits a superconducting (SC) phase with double <lb/>domes covering a wide H-doping range from x = 0.05 <lb/>to x = 0.44 1 , (ii) the SC phase is sandwiched by <lb/>antiferromagnetic (AF) phases appearing in heavily and <lb/>poorly electron-doped regimes [see Fig. 1(a)] 2 , and (iii) <lb/>the application of pressure transforms the double domes <lb/>into a single dome 1,3 . Intriguingly, upon applying <lb/>pressure, the minimum T c at ambient pressure becomes <lb/>the maximum T c of over 45 K 1 , as shown by the solid <lb/>arrow in Figs. 1(a) and 4 as described in detail below. <lb/>The unique features established in this compound have <lb/>AF <lb/>SC <lb/>AF <lb/>AF <lb/>SC <lb/>(b) <lb/>(a) <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>T <lb/>T <lb/>FIG. 1: (color online) Schematic phase diagrams of (a) H-<lb/>doped La1111 series LaFeAsO1−xHx, and of (b) Ba122 series <lb/>such as Ba(Fe1−xCox)2As2. AF and SC represent antiferro-<lb/>magnetic and superconducting phases, respectively. The ar-<lb/>row in (a) shows the enhancement of Tc that occurs between <lb/>ambient pressure and 3.0 GPa. <lb/></body>

			<front> * Email:naoki@fujiwara.h.kyoto-u.ac.jp <lb/></front>

			<body>not been observed so far in other iron-based pnictides, <lb/>such as the Ba122 and Na111 series, which have been in-<lb/>vestigated intensively from an early stage because they <lb/>are available as large crystals. The electronic phase di-<lb/>agram of the Ba122 series is similar to that of high-T c <lb/>cuprates 4 . The analogy is reminiscent of the impor-<lb/>tance of AF fluctuations in iron-based pnictides. The <lb/>spin-fluctuation-mediated mechanism is a major candi-<lb/>date for the high-T c mechanism. In fact, the SC phase <lb/>of the Ba122 series partially overlaps the AF phase, in <lb/>other words, the SC and AF states are compatible, and <lb/>the maximum T c occurs close to the phase boundary [see <lb/>Fig. 1(b)] 5,6 . Because of this special location, T c is en-<lb/>hanced and low-energy AF fluctuations simultaneously <lb/>become predominant as the doping level approaches the <lb/>AF phase 7,8 . The Na111 series has a phase diagram sim-<lb/>ilar to that of the Ba122 series; however, the SC phase <lb/>overlaps the AF phase over a wide doping range and even <lb/>extends to the undoped material 9 . By tuning pressure, <lb/>T c and AF fluctuations are found to be related in a similar <lb/>manner as in the Ba122 series 10 . A pressure-enhanced <lb/>T c occurs in the 11 series FeSe, which is superconducting <lb/>and has no magnetic orders at ambient pressure. At first <lb/>sight, the series seems to be free from the antiferromag-<lb/>netism; however, at pressures exceeding 1 GPa, the SC <lb/>phase is adjacent to the AF or AF+SC phase 11 . In fact, <lb/>the influence of AF fluctuations is observable in the SC <lb/>phase even at ambient pressure 12 . <lb/>AF fluctuations seem to play a key role in raising T c for <lb/>various iron-based pnictides; however, the scenario does <lb/>not work well for LaFeAsO 1−x F x , because for x = 0.14, <lb/>T c increases up to 40 K at 3.0 GPa with no predom-<lb/>inant AF fluctuations 13,14 . The La1111 series under <lb/>high pressure is the only material available for investi-<lb/>gating the magnetic properties of pnictides with T c in <lb/>the range of 45-50 K. In fact, the Sm1111 series marks <lb/>the highest T c (T c =55 K) in all types of iron-based pnic-<lb/>tides 15 ; however, it includes magnetic Sm ions, which <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>200 <lb/>150 <lb/>100 <lb/>50 <lb/>T (K) <lb/>H44% <lb/>0.1 MPa <lb/>3.0 GPa <lb/>T <lb/>* <lb/>(b) <lb/>200 <lb/>150 <lb/>100 <lb/>50 <lb/>T (K) <lb/>H40% <lb/>0.1 MPa <lb/>3.0 GPa <lb/>T <lb/>* <lb/>(c) <lb/>10 <lb/>-3 <lb/>10 <lb/>-2 <lb/>10 <lb/>-1 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>1/T <lb/>1 T (s <lb/>-1 <lb/>K <lb/>-1 <lb/>) <lb/>200 <lb/>150 <lb/>100 <lb/>50 <lb/>0 <lb/>T (K) <lb/>H20% <lb/>0.1 MPa <lb/>3.0 GPa <lb/>(a) <lb/>FIG. 2: (color online) Nuclear magnetic relaxation rate divided by temperature 1/T1T for 75 As for (a) x = 0.20, (b) x = 0.40, <lb/>and (c) x = 0.44. Arrows represent Tc and solid curves are guides to the eye. Horizontal dotted lines in (a) represent plateaus <lb/>just above Tc. For x =0.40 and 0.44, an anomaly of 1/T1T appears at T * in a paramagnetic phase (see vertical dotted lines). <lb/>15 <lb/>10 <lb/>5 <lb/>0 <lb/>∆ f / f (%) <lb/>60 <lb/>40 <lb/>20 <lb/>T (K) <lb/>(a) H20% <lb/>0.1 MPa <lb/>3.0 GPa <lb/>60 <lb/>40 <lb/>20 <lb/>T (K) <lb/>(b) H40% <lb/>60 <lb/>40 <lb/>20 <lb/>T (K) <lb/>(c) H44% <lb/>FIG. 3: (color online) Detuning of resonance frequency for (a) x = 0.20, (b) x = 0.40, and (c) x = 0.44. Tc&apos;s determined from <lb/>1/T1T [see arrows in Figs. 1(a)-1(c)] are in good agreement with the extrapolations of dashed lines. <lb/>hinders the investigation of the magnetic properties of <lb/>iron-basal planes. The rise of T c without AF fluctuations <lb/>was observed only for x = 0.14 (see the dashed arrow in <lb/>Fig. 4), because AF fluctuations remain in a lower dop-<lb/>ing range than x = 0.14 and unfortunately x = 0.14 is <lb/>nearly the highest level of F doping. So far as nuclear-<lb/>magnetic-resonance (NMR) studies on LaFeAsO 1−x F x <lb/>are concerned, the maximum doping level is less than <lb/>x = 0.14 − 0.15 16,17 . To establish the breakdown of this <lb/>scenario over a wide doping range (0.20 ≤ x ≤ 0.44) that <lb/>covers the second SC dome, we applied 75 As (I=3/2) <lb/>NMR to the powder samples of the H-doped La1111 se-<lb/>ries at 3.0 GPa. <lb/>We applied a pressure of 3.0 GPa to samples with <lb/>x =0.20, 0.40, and 0.44. The pressure was applied by us-<lb/>ing NiCrAl-CuBe hybrid piston-cylinder-type cells. We <lb/>used a mixture of F-70 and F-77 fluorinate as the pres-<lb/>sure mediation liquid. The details of the pressure cells <lb/>are given in Ref. 18. A coil wound around the samples <lb/>inside the pressure cell and capacitors equipped with a <lb/>NMR probe form the tank circuit, which serves to de-<lb/>tect the detuning of the resonance frequency, namely <lb/>the ac susceptibility and to detect the NMR signal as <lb/>well. The NMR measurements were performed using a <lb/>conventional coherent pulsed-NMR spectrometer. The <lb/>75 As-NMR spectra show a broad powder pattern with <lb/>double edges 14 , which originates from the second-order <lb/>quadrupole effect under a magnetic field. The relaxation <lb/>time (T 1 ) for 75 As was measured by using the saturation-<lb/>recovery method at the lower-field edge in the field-swept <lb/>NMR spectra. The low-field edge appears at about 48.2 <lb/>kOe for an NMR frequency of 35.1 MHz. The signals at <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>80 <lb/>60 <lb/>40 <lb/>20 <lb/>0 <lb/>T <lb/>c (K) <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>x <lb/>T 1 (F) 0.1 MPa <lb/>T 1 (H) 0.1 MPa <lb/>R((F) 0.1 MPa <lb/>R(H) 0.1 MPa <lb/>T 1 (F) 3.0 GPa <lb/>T 1 (H) 3.0 GPa <lb/>R(H) 3.0 GPa <lb/>3.0 GPa <lb/>0.1 MPa <lb/>FIG. 4: (color online) Phase diagram of LaFeAsO1−xHx (0.05 <lb/>≤ x ≤ 0.5) and LaFeAsO1−xFx (0.05 ≤ x ≤ 0.14). Solid and <lb/>open triangles represent Tc determined by the resistivity at <lb/>ambient pressure, and open squares represent Tc determined <lb/>by the relaxation time (T1). Downward pointing triangles <lb/>and solid circles represent Tc determined by the resistivity <lb/>and T1 at 3.0 GPa, respectively. The dashed and solid arrows <lb/>indicate the enhancement of Tc that occurs when pressure is <lb/>applied. <lb/>the low-field edge come from the powder samples with <lb/>the iron-basal planes parallel to the applied field. Fig-<lb/>ures 2(a)-2(c) show the evolution of the relaxation rate <lb/>(1/T 1 ) divided by temperature (T ), ( i.e., 1/T 1 T ). Here, <lb/>we chose T c as the onset of 1/T 1 T as plotted as arrows <lb/>in Figs. 2(a)-2(c). For x =0.20, 1/T 1 T just above T c <lb/>exhibited plateaus as shown by dotted lines in Fig. 2(a), <lb/>and T c was remarkably enhanced upon applying pres-<lb/>sure. For x =0.40 and 0.44, an anomaly was observed in <lb/>a paramagnetic state as marked as T * , and both T * and <lb/>T c were unchanged upon applying pressure. For x=0.44, <lb/>Curie-Weiss-like behavior, which implies AF fluctuations, <lb/>appears above T * at 0.1 MPa; however, this behavior has <lb/>no appreciable effect on T c . <lb/>Note that T c was determined under the applied field. <lb/>In general, T c decreases more or less under an applied <lb/>field; however, the decrease is significantly suppressed be-<lb/>cause we measured 1/T 1 T for the powder samples with <lb/>the iron-basal planes parallel to the applied field. In fact, <lb/>the values of T c are in good agreement with those de-<lb/>termined from the detuning of resonance frequency at <lb/>zero field. In this measurement, T c can be determined <lb/>from the extrapolation as shown as dashed lines in Figs. <lb/>3(a)-3(c). Figure 4 shows the doping dependence of T c <lb/>determined from the resistivity 1 and 1/T 1 T . The data <lb/>at 3.0 GPa for the low-doping regime are cited from the <lb/>results of the F-doped La1111 series 14,19 . As highlighted <lb/>by the solid arrow in Fig. 4, T c increases to 48K at 3.0 <lb/>GPa, which is comparable to the highest T c (∼55 K) for <lb/>all types of iron-based superconductors marked in the <lb/>Sm1111 series. <lb/>In general, 1/T 1 T of d-electrons systems is determined <lb/>by spin correlations and is expressed by using the imagi-<lb/>nary part of the dynamical spin susceptibility Imχ(q, ω) <lb/>as 1/T 1 T ∝ Imχ(q, ω N )/ω N , where ω N is the angular fre-<lb/>quency of nuclei. When the interaction between electrons <lb/>is significantly strong, namely spin fluctuations are pre-<lb/>dominant, Curie-Weiss-like behavior is derived, whereas, <lb/>when the interaction is week, 1/T 1 T is determined by <lb/>the density of states (DOS) at Fermi surfaces. Unlike <lb/>other pnictides, Curie-Weiss-like behavior is not observ-<lb/>able for x = 0.20 as seen in Fig. 2(a). Another example is <lb/>K y Fe 2−x Se 2 with T c = 30 K 20 : The compound exhibits <lb/>similar T dependence to the La1111 series. The results <lb/>in Fig. 2(a) demonstrate that T c is enhanced without <lb/>appreciable low-frequency AF fluctuations, which is the <lb/>most important result for this study. The absence of AF <lb/>fluctuations has also been confirmed from the neutron-<lb/>scattering measurements in both LaFeAsO 1−x H x <lb/>21 and <lb/>LaFeAsO 1−x F x <lb/>22 : An inelastic-scattering peak is absent <lb/>for x =0.20, despite the fact that it is unambiguously ob-<lb/>servable near the AF phase. <lb/>Herein, the T dependence of 1/T 1 T is attributable <lb/>to the DOS. The monotonous T dependence at high <lb/>temperatures is attributed to the DOS involved only <lb/>at high temperatures. In fact, the photoemission spec-<lb/>troscopy measurements demonstrate that the DOS for <lb/>LaFeAsO 1−x F x decreases with decreasing temperature <lb/>23 . This scenario is approved by quantitative evaluation <lb/>of 1/T 1 T just at the plateau. We evaluate 1/T 1 T using <lb/>the Korringa relation 24,25 for d-electron alloys 26 : <lb/>1/T 1 T = <lb/>π (2 γ N A hf ) 2 <lb/>i <lb/>n i (ε F ) 2 <lb/>k B <lb/>(1 − α Q ) 2 , <lb/>(1) <lb/>where γ N , A hf and n i (ε F ) represent the gyromagnetic ra-<lb/>tio of 75 As (7.292 MHz/10 kOe), the hyperfine coupling <lb/>constant and DOS at Fermi surfaces for i = d xy , d yz , and <lb/>d zx orbits, respectively. The factor α Q is Iχ(Q) where <lb/>I is the interaction between electrons and χ(Q) is the <lb/>susceptibility without the interaction at dominant wave <lb/>number Q. The value of A hf has been estimated to be <lb/>∼25 kOe/µ B from the K − χ plot 27 . The theoretically <lb/>calculated values of n i (ε F ) for x =0.20 at ambient pres-<lb/>sure are 0.62, 0.92, and 0.92 (eV −1 ), respectively, for <lb/>i = d xy , d yz and d zx orbits 1 . These values result in <lb/>1/T 1 T = 4.96 × 10 −4 <lb/>1 <lb/>(1−αQ) 2 (s −1 K −1 ). The plateau of <lb/>1/T 1 T at 0.1 MPa indicates 0.018 (s −1 K −1 ), and thus <lb/>α Q = 0.83. The value is in good agreement with the the-<lb/>oretically estimated value α Q = 0.94 for x = 0.20 28 . At <lb/>high temperatures, 1/T 1 T at 3.0 GPa is almost the same <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>10 <lb/>-3 <lb/>10 <lb/>-2 <lb/>10 <lb/>-1 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>1/T <lb/>1 T (s <lb/>-1 <lb/>K <lb/>-1 <lb/>) <lb/>200 <lb/>150 <lb/>100 <lb/>50 <lb/>0 <lb/>T (K) <lb/>(a) <lb/>F14% <lb/>0.1 MPa <lb/>3.0 GPa <lb/>10 <lb/>100 <lb/>T <lb/>c (K) <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>1 <lb/>( 1/T 1 T ) c (s <lb/>-1 K <lb/>-1 ) <lb/>(b) <lb/>FIG. 5: (color online) (a) 1/T1T for LaFeAsO1−xFx <lb/>(x =0.14). Arrows represent Tc. (b) Tc vs 1/T1T at Tc for <lb/>LaFeAsO1−xFx and LaFeAsO1−xHx. Circles represent the <lb/>data for x =0.14 (F doping), and squares, regular triangles, <lb/>and downward pointing triangles represent those for x =0.20, <lb/>0.40, and 0.44 (H doping), respectively. Open and solid marks <lb/>represent the measurements at 0.1 MPa and 3.0 GPa, respec-<lb/>tively. The dashed line is a guide to the eye. <lb/>as that at 0.1 MPa, which suggests that α Q is insensi-<lb/>tive to pressure and thus α Q is not a key parameter for <lb/>increasing T c . <lb/>Figure 5(a) shows the plateaus observed for 14% F-<lb/>doped samples 13,14 . The T c enhancement upon applying <lb/>pressure is highlighted by the dashed arrow in Fig. 4. At <lb/>0.1 MPa, the values of 1/T 1 T at T c , (1/T 1 T ) c are 0.023 <lb/>and 0.018 (s −1 K −1 ) for 14% F-and 20% H-doped sam-<lb/>ples, respectively. At 3.0 GPa, these numbers increase to <lb/>0.030 and 0.044, respectively. These data are plotted in <lb/>Figure 5(b). The data for 40% and 44% H-doped sam-<lb/>ples are also plotted for comparison. As seen from the <lb/>figure, T c correlates with (1/T 1 T ) c only for 14% F-and <lb/>20% H-doped samples reflecting n i (ε F ) in Eq. (1). <lb/>Our results for the La1111 series demonstrate that <lb/>T c is not directly affected by AF fluctuations as clearly <lb/>seen from Figs. 2(a) and 2(c). Note that the oppo-<lb/>site conclusion was derived for the Na111 series, such <lb/>as NaFe 1−x Co x As 10 . In the Na111 series, T c follows AF <lb/>fluctuations when pressure is applied. At first sight, the <lb/>results of the Na111 series seem to contradict the results <lb/>reported herein. One may classify the La1111 series as <lb/>an exotic and exceptional compound among iron-based <lb/>pnictides. However, all facts including the La1111 and <lb/>Na111 series are consistent if the superconductivity is <lb/>not directly affected by antiferromagnetism or AF fluc-<lb/>tuations. For all iron-based pnictides without exception, <lb/>1/T 1 T becomes stronger as the doping level approaches <lb/>the AF-phase boundary, but the T c optimal doping level <lb/>is not always located on the AF-phase boundary and de-<lb/>pends on the compounds, which causes an apparent dis-<lb/>crepancy. <lb/>Roughly speaking, T c is proportional to the DOS and <lb/>the paring interaction. The enhancement of the paring <lb/>interaction is hardly expected for the AF-fluctuation-<lb/>mediated scenario. As another candidate, the orbital-<lb/>fluctuation-mediated scenario 28 would be promising. In <lb/>this case, orbital fluctuations are difficult to observe in <lb/>1/T 1 T at a doping level where the structural or nematic <lb/>phase is absent, and thus the increase in T c is observable <lb/>via the DOS alone in 1/T 1 T . To investigate whether the <lb/>paring interaction is enhanced simultaneously as well as <lb/>the DOS, further theoretical investigations are needed; <lb/>however, the results of Fig. 5(b) would give an impor-<lb/>tant clue. <lb/>One may consider another scenario where the pair-<lb/>ing interaction originates from AF fluctuations, but AF <lb/>fluctuations are suppressed at ambient pressure by some <lb/>competing interactions such as orbital and/or charge in-<lb/>teractions. On the basis of this scenario, T c could be <lb/>suppressed and the double-dome structure could be ob-<lb/>served as observed in some high-T c cuprates. Pressure <lb/>could nullify the competition, and T c may increase un-<lb/>der pressure even if AF fluctuations are not enhanced. <lb/>However, the competing orders, which could cause ap-<lb/>preciable suppression of T c , have not been observed so <lb/>far in a wide range around x = 0.14 − 0.20. Furthermore, <lb/>AF fluctuations tend to decrease by applying pressure as <lb/>observed in the poorly F-doped regime 29 or sufficiently <lb/>H-doped regime [See Fig. 1(c)]. At present, there is no <lb/>experimental evidence to support this scenario. <lb/>In conclusion, we have observed in LaFeAsO 1−x H x <lb/>that T c for x = 0.20 marks a high T c of 48 K upon ap-<lb/>plying pressure without the influence of AF fluctuations. <lb/>For x = 0.44 (near the second AF-phase boundary), T c <lb/>remains unchanged without depending on the magnitude <lb/>of AF fluctuations. These results suggest that the super-<lb/>conductivity has no direct connection with AF fluctua-<lb/>tions. So far as the results of 1/T 1 T are concerned, the <lb/>increase in T c up to 48 K originates from an enhancement <lb/>of the DOS just above T c . <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">The authors thank H. Kontani and Y. Yamakawa for <lb/>discussion. <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">1 S. Iimura, S. Matsuishi, H. Sato, T. Hanna, Y. Muraba, <lb/>S. W. Kim, J. E. Kim, M. Takata and H. Hosono, Nature <lb/>communications, 3, 943 (2012). <lb/>2 N. Fujiwara, S. Tsutsumi, S. Iimura, S. Matsuishi, H. <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Hosono, Y. Yamakawa, and H. Kontani Phys. Rev. Lett. <lb/>111, 097002 (2013). <lb/>3 H. Takahashi, H. Soeda, M. Nukii, C. Kawashima, T. <lb/>Nakanishi, S. Iimura, Y. Muraba, S. Matsuishi, and H. <lb/>Hosono, Scientific Reports, 5, 7829 (2014). <lb/>4 I. I. Mazin, Superconductivity gets an iron boost, Nature <lb/>464, 183 (2010). <lb/>5 S. Nandi, M. G. Kim, A. Kreyssig, R. M. Fermandes, D. <lb/>K. Pratt, A. Thaler, N. Ni, S. L. Budko, P. C. Canfield, J. <lb/>Schmalian, R. J. McQueeney, A. I. Goldman, Phys. Rev. <lb/>Lett. 104, 057006 (2010). <lb/>6 H. Chen, Y. Ren, Y. Qiu, Wei Bao, R. H. Liu, G. Wu, T. <lb/>Wu, Y. L. Xie, X. F. Wang, Q. Huang, Europhys. Lett. <lb/>85, 17006 (2009). <lb/>7 F. L. Ning, K. Ahilan, T. Imai, A. S. Sefat, M. A. McGuire, <lb/>B. C. Sales, D. Mandrus, P. Cheng, B. Shen, and H.-H <lb/>Wen, Phys. Rev. Lett. 104, 037001 (2010). <lb/>8 Y. Nakai, T. Iye, S. Kitagawa, K. Ishida, H. Ikeda, S. <lb/>Kasahara, H. Shishido, T. Shibauchi, Y. Matsuda, and T. <lb/>Terashima. Phys. Rev. Lett. 105, 107003 (2010). <lb/>9 A. F. Wang, X. G. Luo, Y. J. Yan, J. J. Ying, Z. J. Xiang, <lb/>G. J. Ye, P. Cheng, Z. Y. Li, W. J. Hu, and X. H. Chen, <lb/>Phys. Rev. B 85, 224521 (2012). <lb/>10 G. F. Ji, J.S. Zhang, L. Ma, P. Fan, P. S. Wang, J. Dai, <lb/>G. T. Tan, Y. Song, C. L. Zhang, P. Dai, B. Normand, <lb/>and W. Yu, Phys. Rev. Lett. 111, 107004 (2013). <lb/>11 M. Bendele, A. Ichsanow, Yu. Pashkevich, L. Keller, Th. <lb/>Strässle, A. Gusev, E. Pomjakushina, K. Conder, R. <lb/>Khasanov, and H. Keller, Phys. Rev. B 85, 064517 (2012). <lb/>12 S.-H. Baek, D. V. Efremov,J. M. Ok, J. S. Kim, J. van den <lb/>Brink, and B. Büchner, Nature Materials, 14, 210 (2015). <lb/>13 K. Tatsumi, N. Fujiwara, H. Okada, H. Takahashi, Y. <lb/>Kamihara, M. Hirano, H. Hosono, J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 78, <lb/>023709 (2009). <lb/>14 T. Nakano, N. Fujiwara, K. Tatsumi, H. Okada, H. Taka-<lb/>hashi, Y. Kamihara, M. Hirano, and H. Hosono, Phys. <lb/>Rev. B 81, 100510(R) (2010). <lb/>15 Z. -A. Ren et. al., Chin. Phys. Lett. 25, 2215 (2008). <lb/>16 F. Hammerath, U. Gräfe, T. Kühne, P. L. Kühne, A. P. <lb/>Reyes, G. Lang, S. Wurmehl, B. Büchner, P. Carretta, H. <lb/>-J. Gräfe, Phys. Rev. B 88, 1004503 (2013). <lb/>17 T. Oka, Z. Li, S. Kawasaki, G. F. Chen, N. L. Wang, and <lb/>Guo-qing Zheng, Phys. Rev. Lett. 108, 047001 (2012). <lb/>18 N. Fujiwara, T. Matsumoto, K. Koyama-Nakazawa, A. <lb/>Hisada, and Y. Uwatoko, Review of Scientific Instruments, <lb/>78, 073905 (2007). <lb/>19 T. Nakano, N. Fujiwara, Y. Kamihara, M. Hirano, H. <lb/>Hosono, H. Okada, and H. Takahashi, Phys. Rev. B 82, <lb/>(2010) 172502 <lb/>20 W. Yu, L. Ma, J. B. He, D. M. Wang, T. -L. Xa, G. F. <lb/>Chen, and W. Bao, Phys. Rev. Lett. 106, 197001 (2011). <lb/>21 S. Iimura, S. Matsuishi, M. Miyakawa, T. Taniguchi, K. <lb/>Suzuki, H. Usui, K. Kuroki, R. Kajimoto, M. Nakamura, <lb/>Y. Inamura, K. Ikeuchi, S. Ji, and H. Hosono, Phys. Rev. <lb/>B 88, 060501(R) (2013). <lb/>22 S. Wakimoto, K. Kodama, M. Ishikado, M. Matsuda, R. <lb/>Kajimoto, M. Arai, K. Kakurai, F. Esaka, A. Iyo, H. Kito, <lb/>H. Eisaki, S. Shyamoto J. Phys. Soc. Japan 79, 074715 <lb/>(2010). <lb/>23 T. Sato, K. Nakayama, Y. Sekiba, T. Arakane, K. Ter-<lb/>ahima, S. Souma, T. Takahashi, Y. Kamihara, M. Hirano, <lb/>and H. Hosono, J. Phys. Soc. Jpn., 77, 65 (2008) <lb/>24 A. Narath and H. T. Weaver, Phys. Rev. B 175, 373 <lb/>(1968). <lb/>25 T. Moriya, J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 18, 516 (1963). <lb/>26 T. Asada, and K. Terakura, J. Phys. F: Met. Phys. 12, <lb/>1387 (1982). <lb/>27 H. -J. Gräfe, G. Lang, F. Hammerath, D. Paar, K. Man-<lb/>they, K. Koch, H. Rosner, N. J. Curro, G. Behr, J. Werner, <lb/>N. Leps, R. Klingeler, H.-H. Klauss, F. J. Litterst, and B. <lb/>Büchner, New Journal of Phys. 11, 35002 1-14 (2009). <lb/>28 S. Onari, Y. Yamakawa, and H. Kontani, Phys. Rev. Lett. <lb/>112, 187001 (2014). <lb/>29 N. Fujiwara, T. Nakano, Y. Kamihara, and H. Hosono, <lb/>Phys. Rev. B 85, 094501 (2012). </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
