<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage>This is the accepted manuscript made available via CHORUS. The article has been <lb/>published as: <lb/>Observation of the doubly radiative decay η^{′}→γγπ^{0} <lb/>M. Ablikim et al. (BESIII Collaboration) <lb/>Phys. Rev. D 96, 012005 -Published 26 July 2017 <lb/>DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.96.012005 <lb/></titlePage>

			<front>Observation of the doubly radiative decay η ′ → γγπ 0 <lb/> M. Ablikim 1 , M. N. Achasov 9,d , S. Ahmed 14 , X. C. Ai 1 , O. Albayrak 5 , M. Albrecht 4 , D. J. Ambrose 45 , A. Amoroso 50A,50C , <lb/>F. F. An 1 , Q. An 47,38 , J. Z. Bai 1 , O. Bakina 23 , R. Baldini Ferroli 20A , Y. Ban 31 , D. W. Bennett 19 , J. V. Bennett 5 , <lb/>N. Berger 22 , M. Bertani 20A , D. Bettoni 21A , J. M. Bian 44 , F. Bianchi 50A,50C , E. Boger 23,b , I. Boyko 23 , R. A. Briere 5 , H. Cai 52 , <lb/>X. Cai 1,38 , O. Cakir 41A , A. Calcaterra 20A , G. F. Cao 1,42 , S. A. Cetin 41B , J. F. Chang 1,38 , G. Chelkov 23,b,c , G. Chen 1 , <lb/>H. S. Chen 1,42 , J. C. Chen 1 , M. L. Chen 1,38 , S. Chen 42 , S. J. Chen 29 , X. Chen 1,38 , X. R. Chen 26 , Y. B. Chen 1,38 , X. K. Chu 31 , <lb/>G. Cibinetto 21A , H. L. Dai 1,38 , J. P. Dai 34,h , A. Dbeyssi 14 , D. Dedovich 23 , Z. Y. Deng 1 , A. Denig 22 , I. Denysenko 23 , <lb/>M. Destefanis 50A,50C , F. De Mori 50A,50C , Y. Ding 27 , C. Dong 30 , J. Dong 1,38 , L. Y. Dong 1,42 , M. Y. Dong 1,38,42 , Z. L. Dou 29 , <lb/>S. X. Du 54 , P. F. Duan 1 , J. Z. Fan 40 , J. Fang 1,38 , S. S. Fang 1,42 , X. Fang 47,38 , Y. Fang 1 , R. Farinelli 21A,21B , L. Fava 50B,50C , <lb/>F. Feldbauer 22 , G. Felici 20A , C. Q. Feng 47,38 , E. Fioravanti 21A , M. Fritsch 22,14 , C. D. Fu 1 , Q. Gao 1 , X. L. Gao 47,38 , Y. Gao 40 , <lb/>Z. Gao 47,38 , I. Garzia 21A , K. Goetzen 10 , L. Gong 30 , W. X. Gong 1,38 , W. Gradl 22 , M. Greco 50A,50C , M. H. Gu 1,38 , Y. T. Gu 12 , <lb/>Y. H. Guan 1 , A. Q. Guo 1 , L. B. Guo 28 , R. P. Guo 1 , Y. Guo 1 , Y. P. Guo 22 , Z. Haddadi 25 , A. Hafner 22 , S. Han 52 , X. Q. Hao 15 , <lb/>F. A. Harris 43 , K. L. He 1,42 , F. H. Heinsius 4 , T. Held 4 , Y. K. Heng 1,38,42 , T. Holtmann 4 , Z. L. Hou 1 , C. Hu 28 , H. M. Hu 1,42 , <lb/>J. F. Hu 50A,50C , T. Hu 1,38,42 , Y. Hu 1 , G. S. Huang 47,38 , J. S. Huang 15 , X. T. Huang 33 , X. Z. Huang 29 , Z. L. Huang 27 , <lb/>T. Hussain 49 , W. Ikegami Andersson 51 , Q. Ji 1 , Q. P. Ji 15 , X. B. Ji 1,42 , X. L. Ji 1,38 , L. W. Jiang 52 , X. S. Jiang 1,38,42 , <lb/>X. Y. Jiang 30 , J. B. Jiao 33 , Z. Jiao 17 , D. P. Jin 1,38,42 , S. Jin 1,42 , T. Johansson 51 , A. Julin 44 , N. Kalantar-Nayestanaki 25 , <lb/>X. L. Kang 1 , X. S. Kang 30 , M. Kavatsyuk 25 , B. C. Ke 5 , P. Kiese 22 , R. Kliemt 10 , B. Kloss 22 , O. B. Kolcu 41B,f , B. Kopf 4 , <lb/>M. Kornicer 43 , A. Kupsc 51 , W. Kühn 24 , J. S. Lange 24 , M. Lara 19 , P. Larin 14 , H. Leithoff 22 , C. Leng 50C , C. Li 51 , <lb/>Cheng Li 47,38 , D. M. Li 54 , F. Li 1,38 , F. Y. Li 31 , G. Li 1 , H. B. Li 1,42 , H. J. Li 1 , J. C. Li 1 , Jin Li 32 , K. Li 33 , K. Li 13 , Lei Li 3 , <lb/>P. R. Li 42,7 , Q. Y. Li 33 , T. Li 33 , W. D. Li 1,42 , W. G. Li 1 , X. L. Li 33 , X. N. Li 1,38 , X. Q. Li 30 , Y. B. Li 2 , Z. B. Li 39 , <lb/>H. Liang 47,38 , Y. F. Liang 36 , Y. T. Liang 24 , G. R. Liao 11 , D. X. Lin 14 , B. Liu 34,h , B. J. Liu 1 , C. X. Liu 1 , D. Liu 47,38 , <lb/>F. H. Liu 35 , Fang Liu 1 , Feng Liu 6 , H. B. Liu 12 , H. H. Liu 16 , H. H. Liu 1 , H. M. Liu 1,42 , J. Liu 1 , J. B. Liu 47,38 , J. P. Liu 52 , <lb/>J. Y. Liu 1 , K. Liu 40 , K. Y. Liu 27 , L. D. Liu 31 , P. L. Liu 1,38 , Q. Liu 42 , S. B. Liu 47,38 , X. Liu 26 , Y. B. Liu 30 , Y. Y. Liu 30 , <lb/>Z. A. Liu 1,38,42 , Zhiqing Liu 22 , H. Loehner 25 , X. C. Lou 1,38,42 , H. J. Lu 17 , J. G. Lu 1,38 , Y. Lu 1 , Y. P. Lu 1,38 , C. L. Luo 28 , <lb/>M. X. Luo 53 , T. Luo 43 , X. L. Luo 1,38 , X. R. Lyu 42 , F. C. Ma 27 , H. L. Ma 1 , L. L. Ma 33 , M. M. Ma 1 , Q. M. Ma 1 , T. Ma 1 , <lb/>X. N. Ma 30 , X. Y. Ma 1,38 , Y. M. Ma 33 , F. E. Maas 14 , M. Maggiora 50A,50C , Q. A. Malik 49 , Y. J. Mao 31 , Z. P. Mao 1 , <lb/>S. Marcello 50A,50C , J. G. Messchendorp 25 , G. Mezzadri 21B , J. Min 1,38 , T. J. Min 1 , R. E. Mitchell 19 , X. H. Mo 1,38,42 , <lb/>Y. J. Mo 6 , C. Morales Morales 14 , N. Yu. Muchnoi 9,d , H. Muramatsu 44 , P. Musiol 4 , Y. Nefedov 23 , F. Nerling 10 , <lb/>I. B. Nikolaev 9,d , Z. Ning 1,38 , S. Nisar 8 , S. L. Niu 1,38 , X. Y. Niu 1 , S. L. Olsen 32 , Q. Ouyang 1,38,42 , S. Pacetti 20B , Y. Pan 47,38 , <lb/>M. Papenbrock 51 , P. Patteri 20A , M. Pelizaeus 4 , H. P. Peng 47,38 , K. Peters 10,g , J. Pettersson 51 , J. L. Ping 28 , R. G. Ping 1,42 , <lb/>R. Poling 44 , V. Prasad 1 , H. R. Qi 2 , M. Qi 29 , S. Qian 1,38 , C. F. Qiao 42 , L. Q. Qin 33 , N. Qin 52 , X. S. Qin 1 , Z. H. Qin 1,38 , <lb/>J. F. Qiu 1 , K. H. Rashid 49,i , C. F. Redmer 22 , M. Ripka 22 , G. Rong 1,42 , Ch. Rosner 14 , X. D. Ruan 12 , A. Sarantsev 23,e , <lb/>M. Savrié 21B , C. Schnier 4 , K. Schoenning 51 , W. Shan 31 , M. Shao 47,38 , C. P. Shen 2 , P. X. Shen 30 , X. Y. Shen 1,42 , <lb/>H. Y. Sheng 1 , W. M. Song 1 , X. Y. Song 1 , S. Sosio 50A,50C , S. Spataro 50A,50C , G. X. Sun 1 , J. F. Sun 15 , S. S. Sun 1,42 , <lb/>X. H. Sun 1 , Y. J. Sun 47,38 , Y. Z. Sun 1 , Z. J. Sun 1,38 , Z. T. Sun 19 , C. J. Tang 36 , X. Tang 1 , I. Tapan 41C , E. H. Thorndike 45 , <lb/>M. Tiemens 25 , I. Uman 41D , G. S. Varner 43 , B. Wang 30 , B. L. Wang 42 , D. Wang 31 , D. Y. Wang 31 , K. Wang 1,38 , L. L. Wang 1 , <lb/>L. S. Wang 1 , M. Wang 33 , P. Wang 1 , P. L. Wang 1 , W. Wang 1,38 , W. P. Wang 47,38 , X. F. Wang 40 , Y. Wang 37 , Y. D. Wang 14 , <lb/>Y. F. Wang 1,38,42 , Y. Q. Wang 22 , Z. Wang 1,38 , Z. G. Wang 1,38 , Z. H. Wang 47,38 , Z. Y. Wang 1 , Z. Y. Wang 1 , T. Weber 22 , <lb/>D. H. Wei 11 , P. Weidenkaff 22 , S. P. Wen 1 , U. Wiedner 4 , M. Wolke 51 , L. H. Wu 1 , L. J. Wu 1 , Z. Wu 1,38 , L. Xia 47,38 , L. G. Xia 40 , <lb/>Y. Xia 18 , D. Xiao 1 , H. Xiao 48 , Z. J. Xiao 28 , Y. G. Xie 1,38 , Y. H. Xie 6 , Q. L. Xiu 1,38 , G. F. Xu 1 , J. J. Xu 1 , L. Xu 1 , Q. J. Xu 13 , <lb/>Q. N. Xu 42 , X. P. Xu 37 , L. Yan 50A,50C , W. B. Yan 47,38 , W. C. Yan 47,38 , Y. H. Yan 18 , H. J. Yang 34,h , H. X. Yang 1 , L. Yang 52 , <lb/>Y. X. Yang 11 , M. Ye 1,38 , M. H. Ye 7 , J. H. Yin 1 , Z. Y. You 39 , B. X. Yu 1,38,42 , C. X. Yu 30 , J. S. Yu 26 , C. Z. Yuan 1,42 , <lb/>Y. Yuan 1 , A. Yuncu 41B,a , A. A. Zafar 49 , Y. Zeng 18 , Z. Zeng 47,38 , B. X. Zhang 1 , B. Y. Zhang 1,38 , C. C. Zhang 1 , <lb/>D. H. Zhang 1 , H. H. Zhang 39 , H. Y. Zhang 1,38 , J. Zhang 1 , J. J. Zhang 1 , J. L. Zhang 1 , J. Q. Zhang 1 , J. W. Zhang 1,38,42 , <lb/>J. Y. Zhang 1 , J. Z. Zhang 1,42 , K. Zhang 1 , L. Zhang 1 , S. Q. Zhang 30 , X. Y. Zhang 33 , Y. Zhang 1 , Y. H. Zhang 1,38 , <lb/>Y. N. Zhang 42 , Y. T. Zhang 47,38 , Yu Zhang 42 , Z. H. Zhang 6 , Z. P. Zhang 47 , Z. Y. Zhang 52 , G. Zhao 1 , J. W. Zhao 1,38 , <lb/>J. Y. Zhao 1 , J. Z. Zhao 1,38 , Lei Zhao 47,38 , Ling Zhao 1 , M. G. Zhao 30 , Q. Zhao 1 , Q. W. Zhao 1 , S. J. Zhao 54 , T. C. Zhao 1 , <lb/>Y. B. Zhao 1,38 , Z. G. Zhao 47,38 , A. Zhemchugov 23,b , B. Zheng 48,14 , J. P. Zheng 1,38 , W. J. Zheng 33 , Y. H. Zheng 42 , <lb/>B. Zhong 28 , L. Zhou 1,38 , X. Zhou 52 , X. K. Zhou 47,38 , X. R. Zhou 47,38 , X. Y. Zhou 1 , K. Zhu 1 , K. J. Zhu 1,38,42 , S. Zhu 1 , <lb/>S. H. Zhu 46 , X. L. Zhu 40 , Y. C. Zhu 47,38 , Y. S. Zhu 1,42 , Z. A. Zhu 1,42 , J. Zhuang 1,38 , L. Zotti 50A,50C , B. S. Zou 1 , J. H. Zou 1 <lb/>(BESIII Collaboration) <lb/>1 Institute of High Energy Physics, Beijing 100049, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>2 Beihang University, Beijing 100191, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>3 Beijing Institute of Petrochemical Technology, Beijing 102617, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>4 Bochum Ruhr-University, D-44780 Bochum, Germany <lb/>5 Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania 15213, USA <lb/>6 Central China Normal University, Wuhan 430079, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>7 China Center of Advanced Science and Technology, Beijing 100190, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>8 COMSATS Institute of Information Technology, Lahore, Defence Road, Off Raiwind Road, 54000 Lahore, Pakistan <lb/>9 G.I. Budker Institute of Nuclear Physics SB RAS (BINP), Novosibirsk 630090, Russia <lb/>10 GSI Helmholtzcentre for Heavy Ion Research GmbH, D-64291 Darmstadt, Germany <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>11 Guangxi Normal University, Guilin 541004, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>12 Guangxi University, Nanning 530004, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>13 Hangzhou Normal University, Hangzhou 310036, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>14 Helmholtz Institute Mainz, Johann-Joachim-Becher-Weg 45, D-55099 Mainz, Germany <lb/>15 Henan Normal University, Xinxiang 453007, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>16 Henan University of Science and Technology, Luoyang 471003, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>17 Huangshan College, Huangshan 245000, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>18 Hunan University, Changsha 410082, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>19 Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana 47405, USA <lb/>20 (A)INFN Laboratori Nazionali di Frascati, I-00044, Frascati, <lb/>Italy; (B)INFN and University of Perugia, I-06100, Perugia, Italy <lb/>21 (A)INFN Sezione di Ferrara, I-44122, Ferrara, Italy; (B)University of Ferrara, I-44122, Ferrara, Italy <lb/>22 Johannes Gutenberg University of Mainz, Johann-Joachim-Becher-Weg 45, D-55099 Mainz, Germany <lb/>23 Joint Institute for Nuclear Research, 141980 Dubna, Moscow region, Russia <lb/>24 Justus-Liebig-Universitaet Giessen, II. Physikalisches Institut, Heinrich-Buff-Ring 16, D-35392 Giessen, Germany <lb/>25 KVI-CART, University of Groningen, NL-9747 AA Groningen, The Netherlands <lb/>26 Lanzhou University, Lanzhou 730000, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>27 Liaoning University, Shenyang 110036, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>28 Nanjing Normal University, Nanjing 210023, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>29 Nanjing University, Nanjing 210093, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>30 Nankai University, Tianjin 300071, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>31 Peking University, Beijing 100871, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>32 Seoul National University, Seoul, 151-747 Korea <lb/>33 Shandong University, Jinan 250100, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>34 Shanghai Jiao Tong University, Shanghai 200240, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>35 Shanxi University, Taiyuan 030006, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>36 Sichuan University, Chengdu 610064, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>37 Soochow University, Suzhou 215006, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>38 State Key Laboratory of Particle Detection and Electronics, Beijing 100049, Hefei 230026, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>39 Sun Yat-Sen University, Guangzhou 510275, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>40 Tsinghua University, Beijing 100084, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>41 (A)Ankara University, 06100 Tandogan, Ankara, Turkey; (B)Istanbul Bilgi University, 34060 Eyup, Istanbul, Turkey; <lb/>(C)Uludag University, 16059 Bursa, Turkey; (D)Near East University, Nicosia, North Cyprus, Mersin 10, Turkey <lb/>42 University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100049, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>43 University of Hawaii, Honolulu, Hawaii 96822, USA <lb/>44 University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, Minnesota 55455, USA <lb/>45 University of Rochester, Rochester, New York 14627, USA <lb/>46 University of Science and Technology Liaoning, Anshan 114051, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>47 University of Science and Technology of China, Hefei 230026, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>48 University of South China, Hengyang 421001, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>49 University of the Punjab, Lahore-54590, Pakistan <lb/>50 (A)University of Turin, I-10125, Turin, Italy; (B)University of Eastern <lb/>Piedmont, I-15121, Alessandria, Italy; (C)INFN, I-10125, Turin, Italy <lb/>51 Uppsala University, Box 516, SE-75120 Uppsala, Sweden <lb/>52 Wuhan University, Wuhan 430072, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>53 Zhejiang University, Hangzhou 310027, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>54 Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou 450001, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/> a Also at Bogazici University, 34342 Istanbul, Turkey <lb/>b Also at the Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology, Moscow 141700, Russia <lb/>c Also at the Functional Electronics Laboratory, Tomsk State University, Tomsk, 634050, Russia <lb/>d Also at the Novosibirsk State University, Novosibirsk, 630090, Russia <lb/>e Also at the NRC &quot;Kurchatov Institute&quot;, PNPI, 188300, Gatchina, Russia <lb/>f Also at Istanbul Arel University, 34295 Istanbul, Turkey <lb/>g Also at Goethe University Frankfurt, 60323 Frankfurt am Main, Germany <lb/>h Also at Key Laboratory for Particle Physics, Astrophysics and Cosmology, Ministry of Education; Shanghai Key Laboratory <lb/>for Particle Physics and Cosmology; Institute of Nuclear and Particle Physics, Shanghai 200240, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>i Government College Women University, Sialkot -51310. Punjab, Pakistan. <lb/></front>

			<front>Based on a sample of 1.31 billion J/ψ events collected with the BESIII detector, we report the <lb/>study of the doubly radiative decay η ′ → γγπ 0 for the first time, where the η ′ meson is produced via <lb/>the J/ψ → γη ′ decay. The branching fraction of η ′ → γγπ 0 inclusive decay is measured to be B(η ′ → <lb/>γγπ 0 ) Incl. = (3.20 ± 0.07(stat) ± 0.23(sys)) × 10 −3 , while the branching fractions of the dominant <lb/>process η ′ → γω and the non-resonant component are determined to be B(η ′ → γω)×B(ω → γπ 0 ) = <lb/></front>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<front>(23.7 ± 1.4(stat) ± 1.8(sys)) × 10 −4 and B(η ′ → γγπ 0 )NR = (6.16 ± 0.64(stat) ± 0.67(sys)) × 10 −4 , <lb/>respectively. In addition, the M 2 <lb/>γγ -dependent partial widths of the inclusive decay are also presented. <lb/>PACS numbers: 13.40.Gp, 13.40.Hq, 13.20.Jf, 14.40.Be <lb/></front>

			<body>I. INTRODUCTION <lb/>The η ′ meson provides a unique stage for understand-<lb/>ing the distinct symmetry-breaking mechanisms present <lb/>in low-energy Quantum Chromodynamics (QCD) [1-5] <lb/>and its decays play an important role in exploring the <lb/>effective theory of QCD at low energy [6]. Recently, the <lb/>doubly radiative decay η ′ → γγπ 0 was studied in the <lb/>frameworks of the Linear σ Model (LσM) and the Vec-<lb/>tor Meson Dominance (VMD) model [7, 8]. It has been <lb/>demonstrated that the contributions from the VMD are <lb/>dominant. Experimentally, only an upper limit of the <lb/>non-resonant branching fraction of B(η ′ → γγπ 0 ) NR &lt; <lb/>8 × 10 −4 at the 90% confidence level has been determined <lb/>by the GAMS-2000 experiment [9]. <lb/>In this article, we report the first measurement of the <lb/>branching fraction of the inclusive η ′ → γγπ 0 decay and <lb/>the determination of the M 2 <lb/>γγ dependent partial widths, <lb/>where M γγ is the invariant mass of the two radiative pho-<lb/>tons. The inclusive decay is defined as the η ′ decay into <lb/>the final state γγπ 0 including all possible intermediate <lb/>contributions from the ρ− and ω−mesons below the η ′ <lb/>mass threshold and the non-resonant contribution from <lb/>the excited vector meson above the η ′ mass threshold. <lb/>Since the contribution from mesons above the η ′ thresh-<lb/>old actually derives from the low-mass tail and looks like <lb/>a contact term, we call this contribution &apos;non-resonant&apos;. <lb/>The branching fraction for the non-resonant η ′ → γγπ 0 <lb/>decay is obtained from a fit to the γπ 0 invariant mass dis-<lb/>tribution by excluding the coherent contributions from <lb/>the ρ and ω intermediate states. The measurement of <lb/>the M 2 <lb/>γγ dependent partial widths will provide direct in-<lb/>puts to the theoretical calculations on the transition form <lb/>factors of η ′ → γγπ 0 and improve the theoretical under-<lb/>standing of the η ′ decay mechanisms. <lb/>II. EXPERIMENTAL DETAILS <lb/>The source of η ′ mesons is the radiative J/ψ → γη ′ <lb/>decay in a sample of 1.31 × 10 9 J/ψ events [10, 11] col-<lb/>lected by the BESIII detector. Details on the features <lb/>and capabilities of the BESIII detector can be found in <lb/>Ref. [12]. <lb/>The response of the BESIII detector is modeled with <lb/>a Monte Carlo (MC) simulation based on geant4 [13]. <lb/>The program evtgen [14] is used to generate a J/ψ → <lb/>γη ′ MC sample with an angular distribution of 1+cos 2 θ γ , <lb/>where θ γ is the angle of the radiative photon relative to <lb/>the positron beam direction in the J/ψ rest frame. The <lb/>decays η ′ → γω(ρ), ω(ρ) → γπ 0 are generated using the <lb/>helicity amplitude formalism. For the non-resonant η ′ → <lb/>γγπ 0 the VMD model [7, 8] is used to generate the <lb/>MC sample with ρ(1450)-or ω(1650)-exchange. Inclusive <lb/>J/ψ decays are generated with kkmc [15] generator; the <lb/>known J/ψ decay modes are generated by evtgen [14] <lb/>with branching fractions setting at Particle Data Group <lb/>(PDG) world average values [16]; the remaining unknown <lb/>decays are generated with lundcharm [17]. <lb/>III. EVENT SELECTION AND BACKGROUND <lb/>ESTIMATION <lb/>Electromagnetic showers are reconstructed from clus-<lb/>ters of energy deposits in the electromagnetic calorime-<lb/>ter (EMC). The energy deposited in nearby time-of-light <lb/>(TOF) counters is included to improve the reconstruction <lb/>efficiency and energy resolution. The photon candidate <lb/>showers must have a minimum energy of 25 MeV in the <lb/>barrel region (| cos θ| &lt; 0.80) or 50 MeV in the end cap <lb/>region (0.86 &lt; | cos θ| &lt; 0.92). Showers in the region <lb/>between the barrel and the end caps are poorly mea-<lb/>sured and excluded from the analysis. In this analysis, <lb/>only the events without charged particles are subjected <lb/>to further analysis. The average event vertex of each run <lb/>is assumed as the origin for the selected candidates. To <lb/>select J/ψ → γη ′ , η ′ → γγπ 0 (π 0 → γγ) signal events, <lb/>only the events with exactly five photon candidates are <lb/>selected. <lb/>To improve resolution and reduce background, a <lb/>five-constraint kinematic (5C) fit imposing energy-<lb/>momentum conservation and a π 0 mass constraint is per-<lb/>formed to the γγγπ 0 hypothesis, where the π 0 candidate <lb/>is reconstructed with a pair of photons. For events with <lb/>more than one π 0 candidate, the combination with the <lb/>smallest χ 2 <lb/>5c is selected. Only events with χ 2 <lb/>5c &lt; 30 are <lb/>retained. The χ 2 <lb/>5C distribution is shown in Fig. 1 with <lb/>events in the η ′ signal region of |M γγπ 0 − M η ′ | &lt; 25 MeV <lb/>(M η ′ is the η ′ nominal mass from PDG [16]). In order to <lb/>suppress the multi-π 0 backgrounds and remove the mis-<lb/>combined π 0 candidates, an event is vetoed if any two of <lb/>five selected photons (except for the combination for the <lb/>π 0 candidate) satisfies |M γγ − M π 0 | &lt; 18 MeV/c 2 , where <lb/>M π 0 is the π 0 nominal mass. After the application of the <lb/>requirements, the most energetic photon is taken <lb/>as the primary photon from the J/ψ decay, and the re-<lb/>maining two photons and the π 0 are used to reconstruct <lb/>the η ′ candidates. Figure 2 shows the γγπ 0 invariant <lb/>mass spectrum. <lb/>Detailed MC studies indicate that no peaking back-<lb/>ground remains after all the selection criteria. The <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>5C <lb/>χ <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>Events/ 2.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>Signal + BG <lb/>0 <lb/>π <lb/>γ <lb/>γ <lb/>→ <lb/>&apos; <lb/>η <lb/>Class I background <lb/>Class II background <lb/>FIG. 1: Distribution of the χ 2 <lb/>5C of the 5C kinematic fit for <lb/>the inclusive η ′ decay. Dots with error bars are data; the <lb/>heavy (black) solid-curve is the sum of signal and expected <lb/>backgrounds from MC simulations; the light (red) solid-curves <lb/>is signal components which are normalized to the fitted yields; <lb/>the (green) dotted-curve is the Class I background; and the <lb/>(pink) dot-dashed-curve is the Class II background. <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>(GeV/c <lb/>0 <lb/>π <lb/>γ <lb/>γ <lb/>M <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>Events/(4.0MeV/c <lb/>0 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>(GeV/c <lb/>0 <lb/>π <lb/>γ <lb/>γ <lb/>M <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>Events/(4.0MeV/c <lb/>0 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/>Global fit <lb/>0 <lb/>π <lb/>γ <lb/>γ <lb/>→ <lb/>&apos; <lb/>η <lb/>Class I background <lb/>Class II background <lb/>FIG. 2: Results of the fit to M γγπ 0 for the selected inclusive <lb/>η ′ → γγπ 0 signal events. The (black) dots with error bars are <lb/>the data. <lb/>sources of backgrounds are divided into two classes. <lb/>Background events of Class I are from J/ψ → γη ′ with <lb/>η ′ decaying into final states other than the signal final <lb/>states. These background events accumulate near the <lb/>lower side of the η ′ signal region and are mainly from <lb/>η ′ → π 0 π 0 η (η → γγ), η ′ → 3π 0 and η ′ → γγ, as <lb/>shown as the (green) dotted curve in Fig. 2. Background <lb/>events in Class II are mainly from J/ψ decays to final <lb/>states without η ′ , such as J/ψ → γπ 0 π 0 and J/ψ → ωη <lb/>(ω → γπ 0 , η → γγ) decays, which contribute a smooth <lb/>distribution under the η ′ signal region as displayed as the <lb/>(pink) dot-dashed curve in Fig. 2. <lb/>IV. SIGNAL YIELDS AND BRANCHING <lb/>FRACTIONS <lb/>A fit to the γγπ 0 invariant mass distribution is per-<lb/>formed to determine the inclusive η ′ → γγπ 0 signal yield. <lb/>The probability density function (PDF) for the signal <lb/>component is represented by the signal MC shape, which <lb/>is obtained from the signal MC sample generated with an <lb/>incoherent mixture of ρ, ω and the non-resonant compo-<lb/>nents according to the fractions obtained in this analysis. <lb/>Both the shape and the yield for the Class I background <lb/>are fixed to the MC simulations and their expected inten-<lb/>sities. The shape for the Class II background is described <lb/>by a third-order Chebychev Polynomial, and the corre-<lb/>sponding yield and PDF parameters are left free in the <lb/>fit to data. The fit range is 0.70 − 1.10 GeV/c 2 . Figure 2 <lb/>shows the results of the fit. The fit quality assessed with <lb/>the binned distribution is χ 2 /n.d.f = 108/95 = 1.14. The <lb/>signal yield and the MC-determined signal efficiency for <lb/>the inclusive η ′ decay are summarized in Table I. <lb/>In this analysis, the partial widths can be obtained <lb/>by studying the efficiency-corrected signal yields for each <lb/>given M 2 <lb/>γγ bin i for the inclusive η ′ → γγπ 0 decay. The <lb/>resolution in M 2 <lb/>γγ is found to be about 5×10 2 (MeV/c 2 ) 2 <lb/>from the MC simulation, which is much smaller than <lb/>1.0 × 10 4 (MeV/c 2 ) 2 , a statistically reasonable bin width, <lb/>and hence no unfolding is necessary. The η ′ signal yield in <lb/>each M 2 <lb/>γγ bin is obtained by performing bin-by-bin fits to <lb/>the γγπ 0 invariant mass distributions using the fit proce-<lb/>dure described above. Thus the background-subtracted, <lb/>efficiency-corrected signal yield can be used to obtain the <lb/>partial width for each given M 2 <lb/>γγ interval, where the PDG <lb/>value is used for the total width of the η ′ meson [16]. The <lb/>results for dΓ(η ′ → γγπ 0 )/dM 2 <lb/>γγ in each M 2 <lb/>γγ interval are <lb/>listed in Table II and depicted in Fig. 3, where the con-<lb/>tributions from each component obtained from the MC <lb/>simulations are normalized with the yields by fitting to <lb/>M γπ 0 as displayed in Fig. 4. <lb/>Assuming that the inclusive decay η ′ → γγπ 0 can <lb/>be attributed to the vector mesons ρ and ω and the <lb/>non-resonant contribution, we apply a fit to the γπ 0 <lb/>invariant mass to determine the branching fraction for <lb/>the non-resonant η ′ → γγπ 0 decay using the η ′ signal <lb/>events with |M γγπ 0 − m η ′ | &lt; 25 MeV/c 2 . In the fit, <lb/>the ρ-ω interference is considered, but possible interfer-<lb/>ence between the ω (ρ) and the non-resonant process is <lb/>neglected. To validate our fit, we also determine the <lb/>product branching fraction for the decay chain η ′ → γω, <lb/>ω → γπ 0 . Figure 4 shows the M γπ 0 distribution. Since <lb/>the doubly radiative photons are indistinguishable, two <lb/>entries are filled into the histogram for each event. For <lb/>the PDF of the coherent ω and ρ produced in η ′ → <lb/>γγπ 0 , we use [ε(M γπ 0 ) × E 3 <lb/>γ η ′ × E 3 <lb/>γ ω(ρ) × |BW ω (M γπ 0 ) + <lb/>αe iθ BW ρ (M γπ 0 )| 2 ×B 2 <lb/>η ′ ×B 2 <lb/>ω(ρ) ]⊗G(0, σ), where ε(M γπ 0 ) <lb/>is the detection efficiency determined by the MC simula-<lb/>tions; E γ η ′ (ω/ρ) is the energy of the transition photon in <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE I: Observed η ′ signal yields (N η ′ ) and detection efficiencies (ǫ) for inclusive η ′ → γγπ 0 , η ′ → γω(ω → γπ 0 ), and the <lb/>non-resonant η ′ → γγπ 0 decays. The measured branching fractions c in this work, comparison of values from the PDG [16] and <lb/>theoretical predictions are listed. The first errors are statistical and the second ones are systematic. <lb/>η ′ → γγπ 0 (Inclusive) η ′ → γω, ω → γπ 0 η ′ → γγπ 0 (Non-resonant) <lb/>N η ′ <lb/>3435 ± 76 ± 244 <lb/>2340 ± 141 ± 180 <lb/>655 ± 68 ± 71 <lb/>ǫ <lb/>16.1% <lb/>14.8% <lb/>15.9% <lb/>B (10 −4 ) <lb/>32.0 ± 0.7 ± 2.3 <lb/>23.7 ± 1.4 ± 1.8 a <lb/>6.16 ± 0.64 ± 0.67 <lb/>BPDG (10 −4 ) <lb/>-<lb/>21.7 ± 1.3 b <lb/>&lt; 8 <lb/>Predictions (10 −4 ) <lb/>57 [7],65 [8] <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>a The product branching fraction B(η ′ → γω) • B(ω → γπ 0 ). b The product branching fraction B(η ′ → γω) • B(ω → γπ 0 ) from PDG [16]. <lb/>c The product branching fraction B(η ′ → γρ 0 ) • B(ρ 0 → γπ 0 ) is determined to be (1.92 ± 0.16(stat)) × 10 −4 using the fitted yield in <lb/>Fig. 4, which is in agreement with the PDG value of (1.75 ± 0.23) × 10 −4 [16]. <lb/>TABLE II: Results for dΓ(η ′ → γγπ 0 )/dM 2 <lb/>γγ (in units of keV/(GeV/c 2 ) 2 ) for thirteen intervals of M 2 <lb/>γγ . The first uncertainties <lb/>are statistical and the second systematic. <lb/>M 2 <lb/>γγ ((GeV/c 2 ) 2 ) <lb/>[0.0, 0.01] <lb/>[0.01, 0.04] <lb/>[0.04, 0.06] <lb/>[0.06, 0.09] <lb/>[0.09, 0.12] <lb/>dΓ(η ′ → γγπ 0 )/M 2 <lb/>γγ 3.17 ± 0.44 ± 0.24 2.57 ± 0.18 ± 0.19 2.60 ± 0.15 ± 0.18 1.87 ± 0.12 ± 0.14 1.76 ± 0.11 ± 0.13 <lb/>M 2 <lb/>γγ ((GeV/c 2 ) 2 ) <lb/>[0.12, 0.16] <lb/>[0.16, 0.20] <lb/>[0.20, 0.25] <lb/>[0.25, 0.28] <lb/>[0.28, 0.31] <lb/>dΓ(η ′ → γγπ 0 )/M 2 <lb/>γγ 1.63 ± 0.10 ± 0.12 1.76 ± 0.09 ± 0.13 1.97 ± 0.10 ± 0.14 2.00 ± 0.17 ± 0.15 1.07 ± 0.20 ± 0.08 <lb/>M 2 <lb/>γγ ((GeV/c 2 ) 2 ) <lb/>[0.31, 0.36] <lb/>[0.36, 0.42] <lb/>[0.42, 0.64] <lb/>dΓ(η ′ → γγπ 0 )/M 2 <lb/>γγ 0.34 ± 0.06 ± 0.03 0.12 ± 0.03 ± 0.01 0.06 ± 0.01 ± 0.01 <lb/>the rest frame of η ′ (ω/ρ); BW ω (M γπ 0 ) is a relativistic <lb/>Breit-Wigner (BW) function, and BW ρ (M γπ 0 ) is a rel-<lb/>ativistic BW function with mass-dependent width [18]. <lb/>The masses and widths of the ρ and ω meson are fixed to <lb/>their PDG values [16]. B 2 <lb/>η ′ (ω/ρ) is the Blatt-Weisskopf <lb/>centrifugal barrier factor for the η ′ (ω/ρ) decay vertex <lb/>with radius R = 0.75 fm [19, 20], and B 2 <lb/>η ′ (ω/ρ) is used <lb/>to damp the divergent tail due to the factor E 3 <lb/>γ η ′ (ω/ρ) . <lb/>The Gaussian function G(0, σ) is used to parameterize <lb/>the detector resolution. The combinatorial background <lb/>is produced by the combination of the π 0 and the pho-<lb/>ton from the η ′ meson, and its PDF is described with <lb/>a fixed shape from the MC simulation. The ratio of <lb/>yields between the combinatorial backgrounds and the <lb/>coherent sum of ρ-ω signals is fixed from the MC simu-<lb/>lations. The shape of the non-resonant signal η ′ → γγπ 0 <lb/>is determined from the MC simulation, and its yield is <lb/>determined in the fit. The background from the Class <lb/>I as discussed above is fixed to the shape and yield of <lb/>the MC simulation. Finally, the shape from the Class <lb/>II background is obtained from the η ′ mass sidebands <lb/>(738 − 788 and 1008 − 1058 MeV/c 2 ), and its normaliza-<lb/>tion is fixed in the fit. The M γπ 0 mass range used in the <lb/>fit is 0.20−0.92 GeV/c 2 . In the fit, the interference phase <lb/>θ between the ρ-and ω-components is allowed. Due to <lb/>the low statistics of the ρ meson contribution, we fix the <lb/>ratio α of ρ and ω intensities to the value for the ratio of <lb/>B(η ′ → γρ) • B(ρ → γπ 0 ) and B(η ′ → γω) • B(ω → γπ 0 ) <lb/>from the PDG [16]. Figure 4 shows the results. The <lb/>yields for the vector mesons ρ, ω and their interfer-<lb/>ence are determined to be (183 ± 15), (2340 ± 141), and <lb/>(174 ± 92), respectively. The signal yields and efficiencies <lb/>as well as the corresponding branching fractions for the <lb/>η ′ → γω(ω → γπ 0 ) and non-resonant decays are summa-<lb/>rized in Table I. <lb/>V. SYSTEMATIC UNCERTAINTIES <lb/>The systematic uncertainties on the branching fraction <lb/>measurements are summarized in Table III. The uncer-<lb/>tainty due to the photon reconstruction is determined to <lb/>be 1% per photon as described in Ref. [21]. The uncer-<lb/>tainties associated with the other selection criteria, kine-<lb/>matic fit with χ 2 <lb/>5C &lt; 30, the number of photons equal to <lb/>5 and π 0 veto (|M γγ − M π 0 | &gt; 18 MeV/c 2 ) are studied <lb/>with the control sample J/ψ → γη ′ , η ′ → γω, ω → γπ 0 <lb/>decay, respectively. The systematic error in each of the <lb/>applied selection criteria is numerically estimated from <lb/>the ratio of the number of events with and without the <lb/>corresponding requirement. The corresponding resulting <lb/>efficiency differences between data and MC (2.7%, 0.5%, <lb/>and 1.9% , respectively) are taken to be representative of <lb/>the corresponding systematic uncertainties. <lb/>In the fit for the inclusive η ′ decay, the signal shape <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>2 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>(GeV/c <lb/>γ <lb/>γ <lb/>2 <lb/>M <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>(keV/(GeV/c <lb/>γ <lb/>γ <lb/>2 <lb/>)/dM <lb/>γ <lb/>γ <lb/>0 <lb/>π <lb/>→ <lb/>&apos; <lb/>η <lb/>( <lb/>Γ <lb/>d <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>Total <lb/>ω <lb/>γ <lb/>→ <lb/>&apos; <lb/>η <lb/>ρ <lb/>γ <lb/>→ <lb/>&apos; <lb/>η <lb/>0 <lb/>π <lb/>γ <lb/>γ <lb/>→ <lb/>&apos; <lb/>η <lb/>Non-resonant <lb/>FIG. 3: Partial width (in keV) versus M 2 <lb/>γγ for the inclusive <lb/>η ′ → γγπ 0 decay. The error includes the statistic and sys-<lb/>tematic uncertainties. The (blue) histogram is the sum of <lb/>an incoherent mixture of ρ-ω and the non-resonant compo-<lb/>nents from MC simulations; the (back) dotted-curves is ω-<lb/>contribution; the (red) dot-dashed-curve is the ρ-contribution; <lb/>and the (green) dashed-curve is the non-resonant contribu-<lb/>tion. All the components are normalized using the yields ob-<lb/>tained in Fig. 4. <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>(GeV/c <lb/>0 <lb/>π <lb/>γ <lb/>M <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>Events/(15MeV/c <lb/>0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1500 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>(GeV/c <lb/>0 <lb/>π <lb/>γ <lb/>M <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>Events/(15MeV/c <lb/>0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1500 <lb/>Global fit <lb/>ω <lb/>γ <lb/>→ <lb/>&apos; <lb/>η <lb/>ρ <lb/>γ <lb/>→ <lb/>&apos; <lb/>η <lb/>interference <lb/>ω <lb/>-<lb/>ρ <lb/>0 <lb/>π <lb/>γ <lb/>γ <lb/>→ <lb/>&apos; <lb/>η <lb/>Non-resonant <lb/>Combinatorial BG <lb/>Class II background <lb/>FIG. 4: Distribution of the invariant mass M γπ 0 and fit re-<lb/>sults in the η ′ mass region. The points with error bars are <lb/>data; the (black) dotted-curve is from the ω-contribution; the <lb/>(red) long dashed-curve is from the ρ-contribution; the (blue) <lb/>short dashed-curve is the contribution of ρ-ω interference; the <lb/>(green) long dashed curve is the non-resonance; the (pink) his-<lb/>togram is from the Class II background; the (black) short dot-<lb/>dashed curve is the combinatorial backgrounds of η ′ → γω, <lb/>γρ. The (blue) solid line shows the total fit function. <lb/>is fixed to the MC simulation. The uncertainty due to <lb/>the signal shape is considered by convolving a Gaussian <lb/>function to account for the difference in the mass resolu-<lb/>tion between data and MC simulation. In the fit to the <lb/>γπ 0 distribution, alternative fits with the mass resolution <lb/>left free in the fit and the radius R in the barrier factor <lb/>changed from 0.75 fm to 0.35 fm are performed, and the <lb/>changes of the signal yields are taken as the uncertainty <lb/>due to the signal shape. <lb/>In the fit to the M γγπ 0 distribution, the signal shape is <lb/>described with an incoherent sum of contributions from <lb/>processes involving ρ and ω and non-resonant processes <lb/>obtained from MC simulation, where the non-resonant <lb/>process is modeled with the VMD model. A fit with an <lb/>alternative signal model for the different components, i.e. <lb/>a coherent sum for the ρ-, ω-components and a uniform <lb/>angular distribution in phase space (PHSP) for the non-<lb/>resonant process, is performed. The resultant changes in <lb/>the branching fractions are taken as the uncertainty re-<lb/>lated to the signal model. An alternate fit to the M γπ 0 <lb/>distribution is performed, where the PDF of the non-<lb/>resonant decay is extracted from the PHSP MC sam-<lb/>ple. The changes in the measured branching fractions <lb/>are considered to be the uncertainty arising from the sig-<lb/>nal model. <lb/>In the fit to the M γπ 0 distribution, the uncertainty due <lb/>to the fixed relative ρ intensity is evaluated by changing <lb/>its expectation by one standard deviation. An alterna-<lb/>tive fit in which the ratio of yields between combinato-<lb/>rial backgrounds and the coherent sum of ρ − ω signals is <lb/>changed by one standard deviation from the MC simula-<lb/>tion is performed, and the change observed in the signal <lb/>yield is assigned as the uncertainty. A series of fits us-<lb/>ing different fit ranges is performed and the maximum <lb/>change of the branching fraction is taken as a systematic <lb/>uncertainty. <lb/>The uncertainty due to the Class I background is es-<lb/>timated by varying the numbers of expected background <lb/>events by one standard deviation according to the errors <lb/>on the branching fraction values in PDG [16]. The un-<lb/>certainty due to the Class II background is evaluated by <lb/>changing the order of the Chebychev polynomial from 3 <lb/>to 4 for the fit to the η ′ inclusive decay, and varying the <lb/>ranges of η ′ sidebands for the fit to the γπ 0 invariant <lb/>mass distribution, respectively. <lb/>The number of J/ψ events is N J/ψ = (1310.6 ± 10.5) × <lb/>10 6 [10, 11], corresponding to an uncertainty of 0.8%. <lb/>The branching fractions for the J/ψ → γη ′ and π 0 → γγ <lb/>decays are taken from the PDG [16], and the correspond-<lb/>ing uncertainties are taken as a systematic uncertainty. <lb/>The total systematic errors are 7.1%, 7.7%, 10.8% for the <lb/>inclusive decay, ω-contribution and non-resonant decay, <lb/>respectively, as summarized in Table III. <lb/>VI. SUMMARY <lb/>In summary, with a sample of 1.31×10 9 J/ψ events col-<lb/>lected with the BESIII detector, the doubly radiative de-<lb/>cay η ′ → γγπ 0 has been studied. The branching fraction <lb/>of the inclusive decay is measured for the first time to be <lb/>B(η ′ → γγπ 0 ) Incl. = (3.20±0.07(stat)±0.23(sys))×10 −3 . <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE III: Summary of relative systematic uncertainties (%) <lb/>for the branching fraction measurements. Here η ′ <lb/>Incl. , η ′ <lb/>ω and <lb/>η ′ <lb/>NR represent the inclusive η ′ → γγπ 0 , η ′ → γω(ω → γπ 0 ) <lb/>and non-resonant decays, respectively. <lb/>η ′ <lb/>Incl. <lb/>η ′ <lb/>ω <lb/>η ′ <lb/>NR <lb/>Photon detection <lb/>5.0 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>5C kinematic fit <lb/>2.7 <lb/>2.7 <lb/>2.7 <lb/>Number of Photons <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>π 0 veto <lb/>1.9 <lb/>1.9 <lb/>1.9 <lb/>Signal shape <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.3 <lb/>Signal Model <lb/>1.7 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>4.3 <lb/>ρ relative intensity <lb/>-<lb/>1.3 <lb/>4.9 <lb/>Combinatorial backgrounds <lb/>-<lb/>1.3 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>Fit range <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>2.1 <lb/>Class I background <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>Class II background <lb/>0.3 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>4.2 <lb/>Cited branching fractions <lb/>3.1 <lb/>3.1 <lb/>3.1 <lb/>Number of J/ψ events <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>Total systematic error <lb/>7.1 <lb/>7.7 <lb/>10.8 <lb/>The M 2 <lb/>γγ dependent partial decay widths are also de-<lb/>termined. In addition, the branching fraction for the <lb/>non-resonant decay is determined to be B(η ′ → γγπ 0 ) NR <lb/>= (6.16 ± 0.64(stat) ± 0.67(sys)) × 10 −4 , which agrees <lb/>with the upper limit measured by the GAMS-2000 ex-<lb/>periment [9]. As a validation of the fit, the product <lb/>branching fraction with the omega intermediate state in-<lb/>volved is obtained to be B(η ′ → γω) • B(ω → γπ 0 ) = <lb/>(2.37 ± 0.14(stat) ± 0.18(sys)) × 10 −3 , which is consistent <lb/>with the PDG value [16]. These results are useful to test <lb/>QCD calculations on the transition form factor, and pro-<lb/>vide valuable inputs to the theoretical understanding of <lb/>the light meson decay mechanisms. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>The BESIII collaboration thanks the staff of BEPCII <lb/>and the IHEP computing center for their strong sup-<lb/>port. This work is supported in part by National <lb/>Key Basic Research Program of China under Contract <lb/>No. 2015CB856700; Joint Funds of the National Nat-<lb/>ural Science Foundation of China under Contracts Nos. <lb/>11079008, 11179007, U1232201, U1332201; National Nat-<lb/>ural Science Foundation of China (NSFC) under Con-<lb/>tracts Nos. 10935007, 11121092, 11125525, 11235011, <lb/>11322544, 11335008, 11335009, 11505111, 11675184; the <lb/>Chinese Academy of Sciences (CAS) Large-Scale Sci-<lb/>entific Facility Program; CAS under Contracts Nos. <lb/>KJCX2-YW-N29, KJCX2-YW-N45; 100 Talents Pro-<lb/>gram of CAS; INPAC and Shanghai Key Laboratory <lb/>for Particle Physics and Cosmology; German Research <lb/>Foundation DFG under Contract No. Collaborative Re-<lb/>search Center CRC-1044; Istituto Nazionale di Fisica <lb/>Nucleare, Italy; Ministry of Development of Turkey un-<lb/>der Contract No. DPT2006K-120470; Russian Foun-<lb/>dation for Basic Research under Contract No. 14-07-<lb/>91152; U. S. Department of Energy under Contracts <lb/>Nos. DE-FG02-04ER41291, DE-FG02-05ER41374, DE-<lb/>FG02-94ER40823, DE-SC-0010118; U.S. National Sci-<lb/>ence Foundation; University of Groningen (RuG) and <lb/>the Helmholtzzentrum fuer Schwerionenforschung GmbH <lb/>(GSI), Darmstadt; WCU Program of National Research <lb/>Foundation of Korea under Contract No. R32-2008-000-<lb/>10155-0. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>[1] J. Steinberger, Phys. Rev. 76, 1180 (1949); S. L. Adler, <lb/>Phys. Rev. 177, 2426 (1969); J. S. Bell and R. Jackiw, <lb/>Nuovo Cim. A 60, 47 (1969); W. A. Bardeen, Phys. Rev. <lb/>184, 1848 (1969). <lb/>[2] J. Wess and B. Zumino, Phys. Lett. B 37, 95 (1971). <lb/>[3] E. Witten, Nucl. Phys. B 223, 422 (1983). <lb/>[4] H. B. Li, J. Phys. G 36, 085009 (2009). <lb/>[5] A. Kupsc, Int. J. Mod. Phys. E 18, 1255 (2009). <lb/>[6] J. Gasser and H. Leutwyler, Nucl. Phys. B 250, 465 <lb/>(1985); H. Neufeld and H. Rupertsberger, Z. Phys. C <lb/>68, 91 (1995). <lb/>[7] R. Jora, Nucl. Phys. Proc. Suppl. 207-208, 224 (2010). <lb/>[8] R. Escribano, PoS QNP 2012, 079 (2012). <lb/>[9] D. Alde et al. (GAMS-2000 Collaboration), Z. Phys. C <lb/>36, 603 (1987). <lb/>[10] M. Ablikim et al. (BESIII Collaboration), Chin. Phys. C <lb/>36, 915 (2012). <lb/>[11] M. Ablikim et al. [BESIII Collaboration], Chin. Phys. C <lb/>41, 013001 (2017). <lb/>[12] M. Ablikim et al. (BES Collaboration), Nucl. Instrum. <lb/>Methods Phys. Res., Sect. A 614, 345 (2010). <lb/>[13] S. Agostinelli et al. (GEANT4 Collaboration), Nucl. In-<lb/>strum. Methods Phys. Res., Sect. A 506, 250 (2003). <lb/>[14] D. J. Lange, Nucl. Instrum. Meth. A 462, 1 (2001); <lb/>R. G. Ping, Chin. Phys. C 32, 599 (2008). <lb/>[15] S. Jadach, B. F. L. Ward and Z. Was, Comput. Phys. <lb/>Commun. 130, 260 (2000); Phys. Rev. D 63, 113009 <lb/>(2001). <lb/>[16] C. Patrignani et al. (Particle Data Group), Chin. Phys. <lb/>C 40, 100001 (2016). <lb/>[17] J. C. Chen, G. S. Huang, X. R. Qi, D. H. Zhang, and Y. <lb/>S. Zhu, Phys. Rev. D 62, 034003 (2000). <lb/>[18] J. P. Lees et al. (BaBar Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D <lb/>88, 032013 (2013). <lb/>[19] S. U. Chung, Phys. Rev. D 48, 1225 (1993). <lb/>[20] F. Hippel, C. Quigg, Phys. Rev. D 5, 624 (1972). <lb/>[21] M. Ablikim et al. (BESIII Collaboration), Phys. Rev. D <lb/>83, 012003 (2011). </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
